<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>The technologies stemming from the Internet promise<lb/> to bring tremendous and fundamental changes to sci-<lb/>entific, technical, and medical (STM) journal publish-<lb/>ing. Yet, contemporaneously, other technologies with<lb/> similar degrees of complexity and widespread imple-<lb/>mentations have emerged in publishers&apos; lives, but<lb/> with much more welcome and well-controlled effects.<lb/> The Internet represents a different type of technology.<lb/> Most technologies are sustaining technologies, largely<lb/> reinforcing the same markets, work flows, and eco-<lb/>nomic assumptions that existed previously. However,<lb/> the Internet is a technology of another sort, a disrup-<lb/>tive technology, one that profoundly alters market as-<lb/>sumptions, economic models, price points, and mar-<lb/>ket participants.<lb/></p> 

			<p>The purpose of this paper is to outline the elements<lb/> of the Internet that make it a disruptive technology<lb/> for STM publishers; analyze the metrics and value<lb/> networks associated with its disruptive influence; pro-<lb/>ject time lines for these disruptions for one journal,<lb/> Pediatrics; analyze the economics of migration from<lb/> print to online publication; and develop a possible set<lb/> of organizational responses for publishers, including<lb/> the publisher of Pediatrics, in response to this disrup-<lb/>tive technology, taking into account the special nature<lb/> of STM journals. It is, simultaneously, an application<lb/> of the conceptual framework developed by <ref type="biblio">Clayton<lb/> Christensen in his 1997 book, The Innovator&apos;s Dilemma, 1<lb/></ref> to test whether STM publishers are facing a disruptive<lb/> technology in the Internet and, if so, whether recom-<lb/>mendations from his research can be extended to STM<lb/> journals.<lb/></p>

			<head>About Pediatrics<lb/></head>

			<p>Pediatrics is the official journal of the American Acad-<lb/>emy of Pediatrics (AAP). Published continuously<lb/> since 1948, it has an ISI impact factor of 3.466 (1998)<lb/> and a monthly print run (including overruns for ar-<lb/>chiving) of approximately 62,500. This large circula-<lb/>tion increases variable costs and makes some com-<lb/>parisons with smaller-circulation journals difficult. In<lb/> January 1997, an online-only section of complete, orig-<lb/>inal, peer-reviewed research articles, Pediatrics elec-<lb/>tronic pages, debuted on the Web, with abstracts of<lb/> these articles printed in the paper edition of the jour-<lb/>nal. Abstracts of the articles published in the paper<lb/> edition were also published on line, alongside the con-<lb/>tents of the electronic pages, creating a complemen-<lb/>tary print-and-online publishing model. On the basis<lb/> of the success of this experiment, 2 the full text of the<lb/> journal was placed on line in July 1998, with the elec-<lb/>tronic pages remaining as an online-only section, its<lb/></p>

			<table>Table 1<lb/> Revenues and Expenditures for Pediatrics, January<lb/> 1996 through July 1999<lb/> Revenue Source<lb/> %<lb/> Expense<lb/> Source<lb/> %<lb/> Member subscriptions<lb/> 27.48 Variable costs:<lb/> 49.39<lb/> Commercial advertising<lb/> 31.33<lb/> Paper<lb/> 37.08<lb/> Nonmember subscrip-<lb/>tions<lb/> 26.25<lb/> Postage<lb/> 24.87<lb/> Article reprints<lb/> 3.47<lb/> Bindery<lb/> 6.15<lb/> Classified advertising<lb/> 9.21<lb/> Redactory<lb/> 9.13<lb/> Royalties and interna-<lb/>tional editions<lb/> 2.26<lb/> Press<lb/> 22.74<lb/> Fixed costs*<lb/> 50.61<lb/> *Include overhead charges (salaries, travel, space charges, tel-<lb/>ephone, distributed costs) for management staff.<lb/></table>

			<table>Table 2<lb/> Changes in Revenue and Expense Levels for<lb/> Pediatrics, 1996 to 1999<lb/> Revenue Source<lb/> %<lb/> Change<lb/> Expense<lb/> Source<lb/> %<lb/> Change<lb/> Member subscrip-<lb/>tions<lb/> 0.76<lb/> Variable costs:<lb/> Paper<lb/> 1.85<lb/> 7.46<lb/> Nonmember sub-<lb/>scriptions*<lb/> 12.46<lb/> Postage<lb/> Bindery<lb/> 11.34<lb/> 37.80<lb/> Article reprints<lb/> 18.05<lb/> Redactory<lb/> 0.30<lb/> Commercial ad-<lb/>vertising<lb/> 36.01<lb/> Press<lb/> Fixed costs †:<lb/> 10.31<lb/> 2.68<lb/> Classified adver-<lb/>tising<lb/> 8.71<lb/> Total change<lb/> 3.12<lb/> NOTE: Figures represent averages of two 12-month periods: Jan-<lb/>uary–December 1996 and July 1998–June 1999. Percentages are<lb/> based on financial data that have been adjusted to 1999 dollars.<lb/> *Because of numerous accounting deferrals and accruals, this<lb/> percentage was derived using composite and averaged data.<lb/> †These include cost-of-living adjustments (required raises in<lb/> staff and consultant pay levels).<lb/></table>

			<p>contents abstracted in the paper version. Since the<lb/> launch of the online-only section of the journal, the<lb/> circulation of Pediatrics has increased from 57,868 to<lb/> 61,110.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Organizationally, Pediatrics is edited by an editor-in-<lb/>chief, an associate editor, two consulting editors, and<lb/> an editorial board of more than 30 members. More<lb/> than 2,500 peer reviewers evaluate the more than<lb/> 1,500 research papers that are submitted each year.<lb/> Only 23 percent of the papers submitted to Pediatrics<lb/> are accepted. At the AAP, management oversight for<lb/> Pediatrics resides in the Department of Education. The<lb/> journal is managed primarily by staff in the Division<lb/> of Medical Journals and Professional Periodicals. A<lb/> managing editor provides the majority of the business<lb/> oversight, with the division&apos;s director, the director of<lb/> the Department of Education, and the Academy&apos;s fi-<lb/>nance staff also contributing. The same staff are re-<lb/>sponsible for the print and online versions of Pediat-<lb/>rics. Advertising, both commercial and classified, is<lb/> sold by an outside firm on a commission basis. The<lb/> online version (www.pediatrics.org) is published with<lb/> the assistance of Stanford University&apos;s HighWire<lb/> Press.<lb/></p>

			<p>An overview of the journal&apos;s average revenues and<lb/> expenses from January 1996 through July 1999 is<lb/> shown in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>. Throughout this analysis, financial<lb/> data are presented as percentages, to effectively dis-<lb/>guise the actual figures while preserving their relative<lb/> values.<lb/></p> 

			<p><ref type="table">Table 2</ref> shows the change in these revenue and ex-<lb/>pense sources between 1996 and 1999.<lb/></p>

			<p>The following points emerge from this revenue and<lb/> expense analysis:<lb/></p> 

			<item>The relatively stable (even deflationary) paper mar-<lb/>ket has played a role in limiting the increase of var-<lb/>iable costs during the period covered.<lb/></item> 

			<item>Nonmember subscriptions have declined, and<lb/> stand out as the only declining revenue source in<lb/> the comparison.<lb/></item> 

			<item>Postal increases have been significant.<lb/> Commercial advertising has become an even more<lb/> important source of revenue for the print version<lb/> of Pediatrics.<lb/></item>

			<head>Disruptive vs. Sustaining Technologies<lb/></head>

			<p>In <ref type="biblio">The Innovator&apos;s Dilemma, 1</ref> his acclaimed analysis of<lb/> technologically driven change, Clayton M. Christen-<lb/>sen articulates the distinction between a sustaining<lb/> technology and a disruptive technology via studies of<lb/> numerous, diverse industries (including computer<lb/> disk drive manufacturers, excavating equipment,<lb/> discount retailing, and motorcycles). His findings<lb/> strongly suggest that the very business practices that<lb/> count as assets under normal circumstances actually<lb/> accelerate the failure of companies in the presence of<lb/> a disruptive technology.<lb/></p>

			<head>Sustaining Technologies<lb/></head>

			<p>Sustaining technologies can themselves be radical, but<lb/> they result in improving established products along<lb/> dimensions of performance demanded by traditional<lb/> markets. For STM publishers, sustaining technologies<lb/> include direct-to-plate printing technologies, high-res-<lb/>olution digital scanning, automated ink coverage on<lb/></p>

			<figure>F i g u r e 1 The inevitability of north-<lb/>east on the profit compass.<lb/> </figure>

			<table>Table 3<lb/> Criteria for a Disruptive Technology<lb/> Markets are not known and are unknowable at beginning.<lb/> Core customers initially reject the new technology.<lb/> Managers hesitate to recommend the technology.<lb/> The technology&apos;s perceived weaknesses are really its strengths.<lb/> Profits and prices are lower for new technology applications.<lb/> The new technology is perceived as underperforming in com-<lb/>parison with existing technologies.<lb/> Markets are viewed as insignificant by entrenched players.<lb/> The new technology heralds a shift in the basis for competition.<lb/> The new technology is simpler, cheaper, and more dependable<lb/> than existing technologies.<lb/> NOTE: The four crucial criteria appear in italics.<lb/> </table>

			<p>press, and improvements in postal coding (bar coding<lb/> and Zip 4). Essentially, improvements emerged, but<lb/> the same value network existed after these changes<lb/> were implemented.<lb/></p>

			<head>Disruptive Technologies<lb/></head>

			<p>Disruptive technologies are qualitatively different<lb/> from sustaining technologies. They are attractive to<lb/> previously unanticipated markets, are often disdained<lb/> by established market forces in their early stages, yet<lb/> are able to survive as smaller entities until the tech-<lb/>nology becomes more mainstream and is proved, at<lb/> which time they may exceed market demands of<lb/> value and overtake existing players, supplanting or<lb/> subsuming them. They fundamentally alter the value<lb/> equations of the market and the measurements of<lb/> value that the market uses to gauge providers.<lb/></p>

			<head>North by Northeast<lb/></head>

			<p>This motivation for established companies to move<lb/> up-market over time (an orientation that tracks north-<lb/>easterly when graphed, as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>) trans-<lb/>forms into inertia over time, as incumbents that sur-<lb/>vive such competition (that is, end up in the high<lb/> northeast corner of the price, value, and size graph)<lb/> are typically large, have high overhead costs (salaries,<lb/> fringe benefits, staff size, and facilities), possess rigid<lb/> manufacturing processes (to reduce product variabil-<lb/>ity), and support significant distribution networks.<lb/> These companies consist of management teams that<lb/> function in a highly structured fashion, and the per-<lb/>sonal ambition of each manager makes recommend-<lb/>ing a new venture with the attributes of a disruptive<lb/> technology (no known market, less revenue, core cus-<lb/>tomer rejection of concept, etc.) highly unlikely. Estab-<lb/>lished firms are effectively forced into a set of pro-<lb/>scribed behaviors by these factors, the primary one<lb/> being the fear of moving southwesterly.<lb/></p>

			<p>Meanwhile, a new entrant, starting at the opposite,<lb/> southwestern corner, is initially geared to survive in<lb/> an environment consisting of low overheads, pos-<lb/>sesses flexible manufacturing processes, and holds<lb/> limited distribution and property, plant, and equip-<lb/>ment commitments. If the new entrant possesses a<lb/> disruptive technology, movement up-market may oc-<lb/>cur very rapidly, and the entrant may be able to de-<lb/>liver more value than its rival in both the newly dis-<lb/>covered markets and traditional markets for the<lb/> displaced technology. By virtue of years of experience<lb/> with the disruptive technology, the new entrant often<lb/> shows more market and technical savvy, may hold<lb/> key patents, has important recognition among the<lb/> newly discovered markets and value network, and<lb/> most often triumphs even when the established firm<lb/> attempts to replicate the new entrant&apos;s technology.<lb/></p>

			<head>The Internet as a Disruptive Technology<lb/></head> 

			<p><ref type="table">Table 3</ref> illustrates the ways in which a disruptive tech-<lb/>nology can be identified, with the most crucial four<lb/> criteria listed first in italics.<lb/></p>

			<p>While the segment of the current core market for Pe-<lb/>diatrics online is relatively small compared with the<lb/> entire subscribership (12 percent of total readership<lb/> actively uses the online version), the rate of growth of<lb/> this market is the more important indicator. (The pos-<lb/>sible significance of this is covered later.) Also, the<lb/> nonsubscriber use of the site is significant (about<lb/> 40,000 unique users per month), as are per-article use<lb/> and occasional use of the site. These are intriguing,<lb/> suggestive tensions—a small but rapidly growing use<lb/> by core customers; a larger, unknown market of oc-<lb/>casional users; and appreciable per-article traffic.<lb/></p>

			<p>We have also found that we can reduce the price of<lb/> an online-only subscription by approximately 40 per-<lb/>cent while maintaining the same margins, assuming<lb/> stable commercial advertising revenues. We have<lb/> offered online-only subscriptions to the segment of<lb/> our market for whom delivery is most problematic—<lb/> international subscribers. So far, more than 125 sub-<lb/>scribers have accepted this option, with many other<lb/> international subscribers expressing gratitude for im-<lb/>mediate access to the online version. We have also<lb/> received a number of requests from domestic sub-<lb/>scribers to stop sending print copies; we have not<lb/> honored these requests yet, since doing so may be<lb/> perceived as placing our advertising rate base at un-<lb/>necessary risk. This is clearly a symptom of manage-<lb/>ment frozen by a business model and revenue expec-<lb/>tations emanating from the print paradigm.<lb/></p>

			<p>We have also noticed a significant increase in the<lb/> amount of direct service we offer for Pediatrics. E-mail<lb/> places us much closer to our customers, and the ex-<lb/>pectation of rapid response is clear. We have aggres-<lb/>sively added services to the online journal (data re-<lb/>trieval, presentation, and communication services),<lb/> which are not possible in print. While the quality of<lb/> information was paramount previously, the basis for<lb/> competition may be shifting to accessibility, search-<lb/>ability, granularity of content, and services around the<lb/> information.<lb/></p>

			<head>Disruption to STM Journal Value Networks<lb/></head>

			<p>For print STM journals, a hypothetic value network is<lb/> shown in <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>. The table is organized roughly in<lb/> reverse sequence (closest to customer vs. furthest from<lb/> customer). This value network clearly shows some of<lb/> the major value elements harnessed by publishers. <ref type="table">Ta-<lb/>ble 5</ref> shows the hypothetic value network for an online<lb/> STM journal. The differences between the two value<lb/> networks include:<lb/></p> 

			<item>The collapse of the printer and distributor catego-<lb/>ries from the print paradigm into online vendors<lb/> for the online paradigm<lb/></item>

			<item>The removal of libraries as key providers of struc-<lb/>tured access and archiving for STM journals<lb/></item> 

			<item>The removal of subscription agencies as providers<lb/> of consolidated subscription purchasing<lb/></item> 

			<item>The diminution of advertisers, at least initially, for<lb/> STM journals<lb/></item>

			<head>Printers and Distributors Become Online<lb/> Vendors<lb/></head>

			<p>The economics of printing, with volatile paper costs<lb/> and, for STM publishers, disadvantageous postal reg-<lb/>ulations, are bound to give way to the lower and less<lb/> variable costs of Internet publishing. With computer<lb/> prices falling and other electronic delivery modalities<lb/> (e.g., palm-top and electronic book technologies) mat-<lb/>ing with Internet technologies, 3 it is only a matter of<lb/> time before market penetration and technologic<lb/> strides make having, carrying, reading, and updating<lb/> Internet publications convenient and inexpensive. For<lb/> Pediatrics, an extensive analysis of 3.5 years of print-<lb/>ing invoices, page counts, and other measurements<lb/> showed that an average of 84.6 percent of our variable<lb/> expense has been consumed solely by the costs of pa-<lb/>per, printing, and postage (see <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>). For Pediatrics,<lb/> moving on line would eliminate 43.82 percent of our<lb/> overall costs (fixed and variable), mainly by eliminat-<lb/>ing 88.73 percent of our variable costs.<lb/></p> 

			<p>A spike in paper prices or continuation of current<lb/> postal trends could precipitate an aggressive move-<lb/>ment by publishers toward online publishing. The<lb/> proliferation of online resources has occurred during<lb/> a period of flat paper prices, probably leading to some<lb/> inertia on the part of publishers. Postal regulations<lb/> continue to favor large-volume, lightweight pub-<lb/>lications and punish small-volume, heavier publi-<lb/>cations. Pricing of raw materials and current delivery<lb/> modalities may drive STM publishers on line, in a<lb/> rearguard action.<lb/></p>

			<head>Removal of Libraries as Key Providers of<lb/> Structured Access and Archiving<lb/></head>

			<p>In recent years, library subscriptions to journals have<lb/> fallen as prices for STM journals have skyrocketed. 4<lb/></p>

			<table>Table 4<lb/> Hypothetic Value Network for a Print STM Journal<lb/> Contributors<lb/> Contributions<lb/> Recipients<lb/> Subscription service/support<lb/> Record maintenance for subscribers, processing<lb/> of payments, feedback to management<lb/> Readers, publishers<lb/> Libraries<lb/> Structured access, archiving<lb/> Readers, researchers<lb/> Subscription agents<lb/> Consolidated ordering, service intermediation,<lb/> claims processing<lb/> Institutional subscribers (libraries, hos-<lb/>pitals, universities)<lb/> Distributors<lb/> Distribution network, border transit, accurate<lb/> delivery, resolution of problems, expertise<lb/> Publishers, readers, printers<lb/> Printers<lb/> Capital equipment; expertise; supply chain; co-<lb/>ordination of delivery; paper, ink, plates, etc.<lb/> Publisher, readers, membership society,<lb/> vendors.<lb/> Managers<lb/> Professional staff, budgeting, coordination of<lb/> activities, innovations, stability<lb/> Editors, membership society, readers<lb/> Advertisers<lb/> Revenues, resources<lb/> Publishers, membership society<lb/> Society affiliation<lb/> Finanacial and management resources, impri-<lb/>matur<lb/> Editors, society members, authors,<lb/> readers<lb/> Redactory<lb/> Uniform style, presentation; standardized or-<lb/>ganization; fact-checking; structural mark-up<lb/> Readers, authors, editors, publishers,<lb/> downstream publishers (document<lb/> delivery services) and researchers<lb/> Reviewers<lb/> Expert critique, selectivity, standards of excel-<lb/>lence, improvement of raw articles<lb/> Authors, editors, publisher, downstream<lb/> editors (for rejected manuscripts)<lb/> Editors<lb/> Organized review, administration, reputation<lb/> for acceptance<lb/> Authors, peer-review network, publisher<lb/> Authors<lb/> Original manuscripts, research, commentary<lb/> Peer-review network, editor, other re-<lb/>searchers, general public, granting<lb/> bodies<lb/> Funding agencies, institutions<lb/> Research funds, resource allocation, support of<lb/> research<lb/> Researchers, authors<lb/> </table>

			<p>Resources from other library activities have been re-<lb/>directed to bolster journal acquisitions in light of these<lb/> rising prices, and this has been a major complaint<lb/> among specialist librarians. 5 With the cumulative ar-<lb/>chive of full-text articles available via the Internet<lb/> growing each month, there will be a time, perhaps in<lb/> 20 years, when the vast majority of historical research<lb/> into relevant prior findings can be accomplished on<lb/> line. Services like PubMed and MEDLINE already make<lb/> this possible to a large extent, and the first peer-re-<lb/>viewed research article relying solely on Internet re-<lb/>sources for bibliographic research has been written,<lb/> reviewed, accepted, and published. In addition, a re-<lb/>cent study comparing hand searching of bibliographic<lb/> citations by a trained librarian and a computer search<lb/> of MEDLINE showed that the computer search yielded<lb/> comparable results and an improvement over similar<lb/> earlier trials (an improvement trajectory). 6 Finally, the<lb/> nature of the Internet makes the collection of infor-<lb/>mation much less rare. It has even been said by some<lb/> that the emergence of the online journal &apos;&apos;is seen as a<lb/> savior for libraries concerned with STM fields,&apos;&apos; in that<lb/> it may solve the pricing dilemmas libraries face. 5 In<lb/> short, libraries may wish to fall out of the print STM<lb/> journal value network. Denmark&apos;s National Technical<lb/> Knowledge Center and Library has already phased<lb/> out journals altogether, delivering journal content to<lb/> patrons solely via the Web. 4<lb/></p>

			<p>Also, completing the move to online-only journals<lb/> may rid libraries of the new problem of having mul-<lb/>tiple online versions of the same journal content in<lb/> place—one version from the publisher, two from dif-<lb/>ferent document delivery companies, and perhaps an<lb/> archival CD-ROM for storage.<lb/></p>

			<p>These redundancies in the current market also may be<lb/></p>

			<table>Table 5<lb/> Hypothetic Value Network for an Online STM Journal<lb/> Contributors<lb/> Contributions<lb/> Recipients<lb/> Subscription service/support<lb/> Record maintenance for subscribers, processing<lb/> of payments, feedback to management<lb/> Readers, publishers<lb/> Online vendors<lb/> Expertise, capital equipment, administration<lb/> Publisher, readers, membership society,<lb/> vendors<lb/> Managers<lb/> Professional staff, budgeting, coordination of<lb/> activities, innovations, stability<lb/> Editors, membership society, readers<lb/> Advertisers (diminshed)<lb/> Revenues, resources<lb/> Publishers, membership society<lb/> Society affiliation<lb/> Finanacial and management resources, impri-<lb/>matur<lb/> Editors, society members, authors,<lb/> readers<lb/> Redactory<lb/> Uniform style, presentation; standardized or-<lb/>ganization; fact-checking; structural mark-up<lb/> Readers, authors, editors, publishers,<lb/> downstream publishers (document<lb/> delivery services)<lb/> Reviewers<lb/> Expert critique, selectivity, standards of excel-<lb/>lence, improvement of raw articles<lb/> Authors, editors, publisher, downstream<lb/> editors (for rejected manuscripts)<lb/> Editors<lb/> Organized review, administration, reputation<lb/> for acceptance<lb/> Authors, peer-review network, publisher<lb/> Authors<lb/> Original manuscripts, research, commentary<lb/> Peer-review network, editor, other re-<lb/>searchers, general public, granting<lb/> bodies<lb/> Funding agencies, institutions<lb/> Research funds, resource allocation, support of<lb/> research<lb/> Researchers, authors<lb/> NOTE: Changes to the value network for a print journal (shown in Table 4) appear in italics. Elements that do not translate from the<lb/> print paradigm are libraries, printers, distributors, and subscription agents. Advertisers may be diminished by the resulting business<lb/> models.<lb/></table> 

			<p>disadvantageous for publishers. The staff of Pediatrics<lb/> recently completed an analysis of 20 representative<lb/> markets served by a major online document delivery<lb/> company (which currently provides a transitional<lb/> model of online publishing). The results showed a<lb/> nonmember subscriber attrition rate more than double<lb/> our average rate (23.65 vs. 11.35 percent), and the de-<lb/>crease in individual nonmember subscription reve-<lb/>nues mentioned earlier (see <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>) was strongly as-<lb/>sociated with the increase in royalties from this<lb/> document delivery service (r 2 = 96.37 percent; F criti-<lb/>cal = 0.1219; F observed = 26.58). Aggressively moving<lb/> online may help publishers remove these aspects of<lb/> interference and redundancy between them and their<lb/> customers.<lb/></p> 

			<head>Removal of Subscription Agencies as Providers<lb/> of Consolidated Subscription Purchasing<lb/></head> 

			<p>The convenience factor of subscription agencies for in-<lb/>stitutions, libraries, and other large organizations has<lb/> to do with the traditionally decentralized nature of<lb/> publishers. With the Internet, online agents have al-<lb/>ready emerged, offering click-through ordering, order<lb/> recall for modification in subsequent years, and other<lb/> services. The linkages that will develop over time be-<lb/>tween publishers and customers via the Internet<lb/> should sufficiently disintermediate subscription agen-<lb/>cies&apos; services. Also, the price premiums agencies de-<lb/>mand from both publishers and customers will prob-<lb/>ably be revealed as unsustainable by this disruptive<lb/> technology. A few entrepreneurial newcomers only need<lb/> apply existing technology to displace the agencies.<lb/></p>

			<head>Diminution of Advertisers<lb/></head>

			<p>Commercial advertisers contribute approximately 31<lb/> percent of the gross revenues generated each year by<lb/> Pediatrics. Primarily, the advertisements are for phar-<lb/>maceutical products, vaccines, or over-the-counter<lb/> preparations. Because of the cost savings generated by<lb/> migration on line, a large portion of these revenues<lb/> can be foregone. Also, because online advertising is<lb/></p>

			<table>Table 6<lb/> Projected Revenues and Expenditures for Pediatrics Online<lb/> Revenue Source<lb/> %<lb/> Expense Source<lb/> %<lb/> Member subscriptions<lb/> Nonmember subscriptions<lb/> Article reprints<lb/> Classified advertising<lb/> Royalties and international editions<lb/> 46.46<lb/> 30.21<lb/> 5.78<lb/> 15.35<lb/> 2.26<lb/> Variable costs:<lb/> Online vendor<lb/> Redactory<lb/> Fixed costs*<lb/> 9.83<lb/> 15.88<lb/> 84.12<lb/> 90.17<lb/> Summary of Changes in Revenues and Expenses:<lb/> Change in gross revenues (overall revenues)<lb/> 31.33<lb/> Change in gross expenses<lb/> Variable costs<lb/> Fixed costs*<lb/> Combined<lb/> 88.73<lb/> No change<lb/> 43.82<lb/> Change in net revenues (revenues minus expenses)<lb/> 16.09<lb/> *Include overhead charges (salaries, travel, space charges, telephone, distributed costs) for management staff.<lb/></table> 

			<p>immature, and because direct-to-consumer advertis-<lb/>ing via the Internet has become more popular with<lb/> many pharmaceutical companies, these revenues are<lb/> not naturally migrating to online journals. With di-<lb/>minished pressure to secure these revenues and a<lb/> nonaggressive approach to Internet advertising by<lb/> pharmaceutical companies and other traditional ad-<lb/>vertisers, online publishers will probably feel less<lb/> pressure to accommodate advertisers or retain adver-<lb/>tising representatives at the level they currently do.<lb/> For example, the cost savings of complete Internet<lb/> publishing combined with the lost revenues from<lb/> commercial advertising would leave Pediatrics at an<lb/> average of 83.9 percent of its current profit levels (Ta-<lb/>ble 6). A 16.1 percent loss in profit is significant, but<lb/> not calamitous. Other opportunities in these unknown<lb/> and unknowable markets could offset this effect.<lb/></p>

			<p>This assumes, of course, that subscription models con-<lb/>tinue to provide current levels of revenues on a sus-<lb/>tainable basis, but the success of e-commerce in many<lb/> applications, and our experience with this for the pur-<lb/>chase of both single articles and online-only subscrip-<lb/>tions, suggest that value translates effectively into<lb/> transactions over the Internet. However, the increased<lb/> granularity of information (article-specific instead of<lb/> issue-specific or title-specific) over the Internet may<lb/> threaten subscription models fundamentally, with<lb/> users finding articles via search engines, purchasing<lb/> just what they need, and moving on. Future purchas-<lb/>ers of journal content may not feel the need to sub-<lb/>scribe. The protection offered by having journal sub-<lb/>scriptions tied to society membership may provide<lb/> some safety in this regard.<lb/></p>

			<head>Publisher vs. Market Value Metrics<lb/></head>

			<p>A list of possible value metrics for print and online<lb/> journals is shown in <ref type="table">Table 7</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Publishers may infer that competitive forces in print<lb/> or online markets will be similar (e.g., better presen-<lb/>tation and strong authors would be equally weighted<lb/> assets in either environment). However, publishers<lb/> also need to consider two special questions raised by<lb/> a disruptive technology:<lb/> </p>

			<item>Whether nontraditional, online sources of pub-<lb/>lished research can exceed market expectations in<lb/> many or all of these value metrics<lb/></item> 

			<item>Whether the revenue levels achieved in this pursuit<lb/> will provide competitors in the disruptive technol-<lb/>ogy environment with the resources they need to<lb/> continue to move northeasterly in the value com-<lb/>pass<lb/></item> 

			<p><ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows a possible level that online STM jour-<lb/>nals may have reached by late 1999 in terms of a sum-<lb/>mary set of STM journal value metrics. It is possible<lb/> that only readability, portability, and archival integrity<lb/> will remain as distinguishing value metrics.<lb/></p>

			<p>It is important to emphasize, as Christensen 1 does,<lb/> that to succeed, new entrants do not need to match<lb/> existing levels of peer review, indexing, or contribu-<lb/>tions to academic credibility. Instead, new entrants<lb/> need to satisfy only the market&apos;s minimum standards<lb/> in these areas. Publishers may have, unwittingly, far<lb/> exceeded the minimum standards in these areas for<lb/></p>

			<table>Table 7<lb/> Value Metrics and Markets for an STM Journal in Print and Online<lb/> Print Journal<lb/> Value Metrics<lb/> Markets<lb/> Online Journal<lb/> Value Metrics<lb/> Markets<lb/> Peer review<lb/> Author/editor reputation<lb/> Contribution to academic credibility<lb/> Uniform presentation<lb/> Readability/legibility<lb/> Reliable delivery/access<lb/> Stability over time<lb/> Widely read and cited<lb/> Good service when needed<lb/> Tie with membership society<lb/> Indexed in MEDLINE<lb/> Readers<lb/> Researchers<lb/> Librarians<lb/> Authors<lb/> Archivists<lb/> Database vendors<lb/> Translators<lb/> General public<lb/> Students<lb/> Author/editor reputation<lb/> Contribution to academic credibility<lb/> Uniform presentation<lb/> Readability/legibility<lb/> Reliable access<lb/> Stability over time<lb/> Widely read and cited<lb/> Tie with membership society<lb/> Readers<lb/> Researchers<lb/> Authors<lb/> Translators<lb/> Geneal public<lb/> Students<lb/> Databases<lb/> </table>

			<figure>F i g u r e 2 Theoretic journey<lb/> of an online journal through<lb/> STM journal market-value met-<lb/>rics.<lb/></figure>

			<p>their readers as they continued to move up-market<lb/> (northeasterly). In fact, they may not know what these<lb/> minimal standards are. The entry of a disruptive tech-<lb/>nology allows markets to realign along true market<lb/> value metrics.<lb/></p>

			<p>Two major value metrics—inclusion in MEDLINE and<lb/> society affiliation—may serve to protect the status<lb/> quo of STM journal publishing and may seem less<lb/> susceptible to technologic disruption. However, with<lb/> the ability of PubMed to accept materials almost im-<lb/>mediately into its very active and accessible index of<lb/> a broader variety of literature sources, the MEDLINE<lb/> value metric may be made less critical because of tech-<lb/>nology (e.g., XML), novel audience expectations, and<lb/> the inability of manual systems to match the speed of<lb/> more automated systems. Also, new metrics of value<lb/> may compete with MEDLINE inclusion, such as infor-<lb/>mation about citation impact factors (i.e., measures of<lb/> utility in the literature), which is becoming more<lb/> timely and accessible than ever. It may someday be<lb/> possible to score the quality of an article&apos;s heritage (as<lb/> well as the lineage of a journal&apos;s contents, and thus<lb/> its relevance to current research) by quantifying in<lb/> some manner the impact factors of an article&apos;s sources,<lb/> the article itself, and the journal in which it appears.<lb/> The effects of networked journals have yet to be felt<lb/> on a broad scale.<lb/></p>

			<head>When Can We Anticipate Disruption?<lb/></head>

			<p>From a study of one year of online subscription use<lb/> and linear extrapolation from these data, it appears<lb/> that more than half the readers of Pediatrics will be<lb/> active users of the online version of the journal within<lb/> 51 months from July 1998, which translates to October<lb/> 2002. Using the same data, but taking out the current<lb/> rate of adoption until 100 percent conversion is<lb/> achieved, we project that the migration from print to<lb/> online publication would take 103 months to com-<lb/>plete, until sometime in the year 2007.<lb/></p>

			<p>The Internet is a disruptive technology, and such tech-<lb/>nologies generally follow a typical product life-cycle<lb/></p>

			<figure>F i g u r e 3 Online subscription<lb/> activations for the online ver-<lb/>sion of Pediatrics.<lb/></figure> 

			<figure>F i g u r e 4 Pearl curve for adop-<lb/>tion of online version of Pedi-<lb/>atrics.<lb/></figure>

			<p>curve, or S curve. 7 The point at which an online jour-<lb/>nal is projected to reach its mature stage (inflection<lb/> point) seems to be the point at which an STM journal<lb/> would finally cross the line from print to online pub-<lb/>lication. It appears that Pediatrics online is just moving<lb/> from the &apos;&apos;early adoption&apos;&apos; phase into the &apos;&apos;rapid<lb/> growth&apos;&apos; phase (<ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>). A Pearl curve shows that<lb/> the current rate of adoption for Pediatrics online is<lb/> more than sufficient to migrate the entire readership<lb/> online. Based on this these calculations, the rate of<lb/> growth observed thus far would support migration of<lb/> 420,000 subscribers before the S-curve inflection point<lb/> would occur (at 95 percent CI; 13.21 percent MAPE).<lb/> This strongly suggests that migration for Pediatrics is a<lb/> plausible outcome of our online publishing initiatives.<lb/></p>

			<p>Extending the S curve yielded by this logistic curve<lb/> analysis and using the resulting formulas to calculate<lb/> the point at which 100 percent of the current subscriber<lb/> base would be active on line, the result is 33 months.<lb/> This assumes that the S-curve model is valid for this<lb/> data set and that the curve of accelerated growth noted<lb/> in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> continues as indicated in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>The capacity of the Internet is increasing at a faster rate<lb/> than is computing power (Moore&apos;s law), with both fi-<lb/>beroptic technologies and router speeds generating in-<lb/>creases of a factor of 1,000 in just 25 years. 7 As of 1997,<lb/> more than 60 percent of surveyed pediatricians stated<lb/> that they had a modem on their computer and access<lb/> to the Internet. 8 Also in 1997, a study by the U.S. Cen-<lb/>sus Bureau showed that more than 80 percent of pri-<lb/>mary school students have access to the Internet in ei-<lb/>ther their schools or homes. 9<lb/></p>

			<p>These two statistical glosses on the available data re-<lb/>veal a possible &apos;&apos;window of disruption,&apos;&apos; shown in <ref type="biblio">Fig-<lb/>ure 5</ref>. While this analysis relies on divergent statistical<lb/> approaches that generate some problematic tensions<lb/> between the conclusions, and therefore must be ac-<lb/>cepted as a current &apos;&apos;best guess&apos;&apos; requiring monitoring<lb/> and recalculations, the following statements may be<lb/> made with some confidence:<lb/></p>

			<figure>F i g u r e 5 Possible &apos;&apos;window<lb/> of disruption&apos;&apos; for Pediatrics.<lb/></figure>

			<item>General adoption of online journals seems to lag<lb/> behind that of the Internet as a technology, as illus-<lb/>trated by the 2002 date for 50 percent adoption by<lb/> Pediatrics subscribers of the online version of the<lb/> journal, and other data. 8,9<lb/></item>

			<item>The S curve for the adoption of this technology for<lb/> Pediatrics indicates the start of an accelerated phase,<lb/> and the rate of adoption of the online version<lb/> clearly supports the migration of the entire sub-<lb/>scription base.<lb/></item>

			<item>Adoption by the complete subscriber base will<lb/> probably occur earlier rather than later, given the<lb/> data points shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>.<lb/></item>

			<head>Caveats for STM Journal Publishers<lb/></head>

			<p>Christensen&apos;s original research is highly suggestive<lb/> but not completely translatable to the STM publishing<lb/> environment. First, his research itself may change the<lb/> environment and the assumptions under which estab-<lb/>lished firms behave regarding disruptive technolo-<lb/>gies, allowing them to identify such technologies by<lb/> logical criteria (see <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>) and anticipate and avoid<lb/> typical problems. Second, many societies tend to<lb/> have very different operating environments from the<lb/> for-profit, commodity-driven businesses Christensen<lb/> studied. Third, the presence of independent and rel-<lb/>atively unassailed value metrics such as peer-review<lb/> and MEDLINE make replicating the &apos;&apos;commodity&apos;&apos; of an<lb/> STM journal more difficult for new entrants. Finally,<lb/> the commodity in question with STM journals is more<lb/> akin to intellectual property than to commodities like<lb/> steel, disk drives, or motorbikes. There is nothing in<lb/> Christensen&apos;s research to suggest how a disruptive<lb/> technology may affect a business based largely on in-<lb/>tellectual property rather than on more traditional<lb/> commodities and raw materials.<lb/></p>

			<p>Intellectual properties may be more malleable, and<lb/> hence less prone to disruption, than hard goods or<lb/> pure commodities. However, this same malleability<lb/> may be used to work against entrenched STM jour-<lb/>nals, either by document delivery companies with<lb/> competitive business models or by new entrants using<lb/> a disruptive technology and gaining access to strong<lb/> intellectual properties.<lb/></p>

			<head>How STM Publishers May Deal with<lb/> Disruption<lb/></head>

			<p>Faced with changing market emphases, a disruptive<lb/> technology, and management practices that are coun-<lb/>terproductive, the options for an STM publisher seem<lb/> few. However, Christensen&apos;s research showed two<lb/> successful management approaches to this dilemma.<lb/> The first is to spin off a separate, majority-owned<lb/> company to develop the new markets and integrate<lb/> the disruptive technology. The second is to acquire<lb/> expertise later by buying a company that has success-<lb/>fully developed new markets, integrated the disrup-<lb/>tive technology, and perhaps even assailed one&apos;s tra-<lb/>ditional markets. 1<lb/></p>

			<p>The latter option, which we consider first, poses two<lb/> difficulties for STM publishers. First, the capital out-<lb/>lay to acquire a growing Internet company would<lb/> probably be beyond the reach of all but the largest<lb/> STM publishers, especially with current valuations of<lb/> these companies in the public sector; second, the man-<lb/>agement decisions that would preclude effectively in-<lb/>tegrating a disruptive technology would probably<lb/> also lead to the rejection of this idea at some point.<lb/> Also, once the acquisition were made, pre-existing<lb/> management expectations and practices might lead to<lb/> an uncomfortable and possibly unproductive match.<lb/> Therefore, this is not a very advisable option.<lb/></p>

			<p>On the other hand, creating a self-sufficient, majority-<lb/>owned spin-off devoted to developing the new tech-<lb/>nology has a number of advantages, including:<lb/></p> 

			<item>Realistic and attainable profit expectations<lb/> </item>

			<item>Freedom to experiment and probe the unknown<lb/> markets<lb/> </item>

			<item>The opportunity to tailor the organizational struc-<lb/>ture, incentives for performance, pricing models,<lb/> and management philosophies to the disruptive<lb/> technology and its true markets<lb/> </item>

			<item>The opportunity to completely explore and exploit<lb/> the disruptive technology, once it is mature, which<lb/> the parent organization can then reintegrate<lb/> </item>

			<item>Creation of an enduring business form that is not<lb/> subject to incompatible management whims and ir-<lb/>relevant financial pressures<lb/> </item>

			<item>Complete reintegration into the parent entity and<lb/> preservation of all derived benefits, once disruptive<lb/> forces have abated.<lb/></item>

			<head>Conclusion<lb/> </head>

			<p>STM publishers facing disruption from the Internet<lb/> can consider the following priorities:<lb/></p> 

			<item>Create an enduring business structure capable of<lb/> exploiting the new cost mix and markets of the In-<lb/>ternet<lb/> </item>

			<item>Build services around the information<lb/> </item>

			<item>Create pathways for more granular, selective access<lb/> to published information<lb/> Experiment with new publishing modalities spring-<lb/>ing from Internet publishing<lb/> </item>

			<item>Begin orienting business models and strategic<lb/> thinking toward this disruptive technology as soon<lb/> as possible<lb/></item>

			<p>Ultimately, this translation of Christensen&apos;s research<lb/> gives rise to three important messages for STM pub-<lb/>lishers. First, the presence of a disruptive technology<lb/> in publishers&apos; lives is virtually unique. Arguably, the<lb/> last legitimate disruption on this scale occurred with<lb/> Johann Gutenberg&apos;s implementation of movable metal<lb/> type for high-quality printing, more than 450 years<lb/> ago, so there are few precedents or guides available<lb/> for publishers today. Second, the market&apos;s value met-<lb/>rics may differ from the value metrics we currently<lb/> use in the print publishing paradigm, and the markets<lb/> will be the primary forces that determine the new hi-<lb/>erarchy of STM journal value relative to the Internet.<lb/> Finally, sound management practices of listening to<lb/> core customers, driving profits northeasterly, and al-<lb/>locating resources to winning programs may acceler-<lb/>ate the disruption of conventional business.<lb/></p>

			<head>Findings Particular to Pediatrics and a Possible<lb/> Strategic Response<lb/></head>

			<p>It is clear from this analysis that Pediatrics is being<lb/> disrupted by the Internet and that the disruption will<lb/> continue throughout the entire subscriber base. The<lb/> implications are as follows:<lb/></p>

			<item>The rate of adoption of the online version of the<lb/> journal appears sufficient to support migration of<lb/> the complete subscriber base to online publication<lb/> early in the 21st century.<lb/></item>

			<item>Variable costs should diminish in this scenario, in-<lb/>creasing net revenues from subscriptions and re-<lb/>ducing the need for ancillary revenue streams (e.g.,<lb/> advertising) while also improving the speed and<lb/> consistency of service.<lb/> </item>

			<item>Pediatrics has already experienced disruption via a<lb/> major online document delivery service.<lb/></item>

			<item>The management and leadership of Pediatrics will<lb/> require an even greater degree of autonomy during<lb/> this transition to propose and act on plans that may<lb/> seem, in the short term and relative to conventional<lb/> management expectations, counter-intuitive if this<lb/> migration is to be as low-risk and productive as<lb/> possible. A possible approach to ensuring this au-<lb/>tonomy would be for the AAP to establish a sepa-<lb/>rate, majority-owned online publishing subsidiary<lb/> with independent fiscal goals, complete access to all<lb/> AAP information resources, autonomous manage-<lb/>ment structures, and a plan for ultimate reintegra-<lb/>tion once the transitions to new markets via this<lb/> disruptive technology are completed.<lb/></item>

			<item>Services ancillary to the content of the journal will<lb/> become increasingly important as a basis for com-<lb/>petition among STM journals in this new publish-<lb/>ing environment and as a basis for competition<lb/> gcwith non-journal suppliers in the health care in-<lb/>formation marketplace.<lb/></item>

			<item>The value network and value metrics associated<lb/> with Pediatrics in a decade are likely to be some-<lb/>what different than they are currently, with libraries<lb/> and subscription agents disintermediated and com-<lb/>mercial advertisers still desirable but less crucial to<lb/> the fiscal health of the journal.<lb/></item>

			<item>Finally, revenues from the journal operations may<lb/> fall during this transition, but most likely as an un-<lb/>avoidable consequence of sustaining this function<lb/> of the AAP&apos;s mission and adapting it to a disruptive<lb/> technology. This phenomenon may actually be a<lb/> sign of health, showing that the journal is adapting<lb/> to the disruptive technology and the new econom-<lb/>ics of publishing that the technology dictates. We<lb/> can also anticipate that revenues will decrease in a<lb/> more controlled fashion if management is allowed the<lb/> freedom and flexibility to adapt rapidly and com-<lb/>pletely to this disruptive technology.</item>

	</text>
</tei>
