<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>1.<lb/> INTRODUCTION<lb/></head>

			<p>Twenty first century saw the emergence of magnetism and magnetic materials as major<lb/> fields of activity which have got profound influence in the industry and day-today life of<lb/> human beings. Magnetic materials play an integral part in applications such as permanent<lb/> magnets, memory devices, transducers etc <ref type="biblio">[1]</ref>. A relatively new entrant to this list is the<lb/> magnetic refrigeration. Magnetic materials are the active materials for a magnetic<lb/> refrigerator <ref type="biblio">[2, 3]</ref>. The use of a magnetic material as a refrigerant in a magnetic<lb/> refrigerator relies on its magnetocaloric behavior. Magnetocaloric effect (MCE) is<lb/> defined as the cooling or heating of a magnetic material when it is subjected to a varying<lb/> magnetic field. This magneto-thermal phenomenon was first discovered by Warburg in<lb/> 1881 <ref type="biblio">[4]</ref>. Warburg found that iron got heated up when placed in a magnetic field and<lb/> when the magnetic field was removed the iron sample cooled down. The origin of MCE<lb/> was explained independently by Debye and Giauque <ref type="biblio">[5, 6]</ref>. They also suggested the first<lb/> practical use of the MCE: the adiabatic demagnetization used to reach temperatures lower<lb/> than that of liquid helium, which had been the lowest achievable experimental<lb/> temperature. Nowadays, there is a great deal of interest in using the magnetic<lb/> refrigeration as an alternative refrigeration technology, from room temperature to the<lb/> cryogenic temperature regime <ref type="biblio">[2, 7]</ref>. The magnetic refrigeration offers the prospect of an<lb/> energy-efficient and environment-friendly alternative to the commonly used vapor-cycle<lb/> refrigeration technology in use today. Furthermore, this technology is purely solid state<lb/> based and has the advantage that the engineering design remains unaltered even when the<lb/> refrigerant is changed to suit different operating temperatures. Efforts are on to fabricate<lb/> magnetic refrigerators for house-hold, industrial and technological applications.<lb/></p>

			<p>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> Schematic S-T plots of a ferromagnetic material illustrating the existence of<lb/> magnetocaloric effect. The solid lines represent the total entropy in two different<lb/> magnetic fields: H 0 and H 1 (H 1 &gt; H 0 ). The horizontal and the vertical arrows show<lb/> adiabatic temperature change (∆T ad ) and the isothermal magnetic entropy change (∆S M ),<lb/> respectively, when the magnetic field is changed from H 0 to H 1 .<lb/></p>

			<head>2.<lb/> MAGNETOCALORIC EFFECT AND MAGNETIC REFRIGERATON<lb/></head>

			<p>The main challenges in the realization of a practical refrigerator are (i) the availability of<lb/> bulk amounts of giant magnetocaloric materials (ii) proper magnetic field design,<lb/> preferably with a permanent magnet array and (iii) ingenious design. Since most of the<lb/> materials developed so far show giant magnetocaloric effect (GMCE) only at fields as<lb/> high as 50 kOe, there is an urgent need to look for more potential materials so that the<lb/> same MCE could be obtained with lower fields. In this context, materials which show<lb/> first order magnetic transitions, metamagnetic transitions or magneto-structural<lb/> transitions are being probed.<lb/></p>

			<p>The MCE is intrinsic to all magnetic materials and is induced via the coupling of<lb/> magnetic sublattice with the applied magnetic field and is measured as adiabatic<lb/> temperature change (∆T ad ) or isothermal entropy change (∆S M ). The isothermal<lb/> magnetization of a paramagnet or a soft ferromagnet reduces the entropy and, in a<lb/> reversible process, demagnetization (which is similar to the expansion of a gas) restores<lb/> the zero-field magnetic entropy of the system. Since in an adiabatic process the total<lb/> entropy of a material remains constant, the adiabatic demagnetization of a ferromagnetic<lb/> material leads to reduction in the temperature.<lb/></p>

			<p>The value of the total entropy (S) of a ferromagnet at constant pressure depends on both<lb/> the magnetic field (H) and temperature (T) and the contribution to it arises from the<lb/> lattice (S lat ), electronic (S el ) and the magnetic (S M ) entropies,<lb/></p>

				<formula>( )<lb/> ( )<lb/> ( )<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> el<lb/> L<lb/> M<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> =<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> ,<lb/> ,<lb/></formula>

				<label>(1)<lb/></label>

			<p>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> schematically shows the S vs T plots of a ferromagnet in two different fields H 0<lb/> and H 1 (H 1 &gt;H 0 ). In order to understand the thermodynamics of MCE, two relevant<lb/> processes are shown in the Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i) When the magnetic field is applied adiabatically in a reversible process, the magnetic<lb/> entropy decreases, but as the total entropy does not change, i.e.,<lb/></p>

				<formula>(<lb/> ) (<lb/> )<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> ,<lb/> ,<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> =<lb/></formula>

		<label>(2)<lb/></label>

			<p>it leads to an increase in the temperature of the material. The adiabatic temperature<lb/> change (∆T ad ), i.e. the difference between the initial temperature T 0 and the final<lb/> temperature T 1 , can be visualized as the isentropic difference between the corresponding<lb/> S(T,H) functions and it is a measure of the MCE of the material.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) When the magnetic field is applied isothermally (i.e. keeping T constant), the total<lb/> entropy decreases due to the increase in the magnetic order. The isothermal magnetic<lb/> entropy change (∆S M ) in the process is defined as<lb/></p>

		<formula>(<lb/> )<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> ,<lb/> )<lb/> ,<lb/> (<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> S M<lb/> −<lb/> =<lb/> ∆<lb/></formula>

		<label>(3)<lb/></label>

			<p>Therefore, it can be seen that ∆T ad and ∆S M represent the two quantities which are<lb/> characteristic of MCE. It is obvious from Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> that both ∆T ad and ∆S M are functions of<lb/> the initial temperature T 0 and the magnetic field change ∆H=H 1 -H 0 . Furthermore, it is<lb/> easy to see from the figure that if raising the magnetic field increases the magnetic order,<lb/> ∆T ad is positive and the magnetic material heats up (∆S M is negative). The signs of ∆T ad<lb/> and ∆S M are correspondingly reversed when the magnetic field is reduced.<lb/></p>

			<p>The MCE parameters viz. ∆T ad and ∆S M are correlated with the magnetization (M), the<lb/> magnetic field strength, the heat capacity (C) and the absolute temperature by one of the<lb/> fundamental Maxwell&apos;s relations <ref type="biblio">[2]</ref>.<lb/></p>

		<formula>( )<lb/> ( )<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> T<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> M<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> ⎟<lb/> ⎠<lb/> ⎞<lb/> ⎜<lb/> ⎝<lb/> ⎛<lb/> ∂<lb/> ∂<lb/> =<lb/> ⎟<lb/> ⎠<lb/> ⎞<lb/> ⎜<lb/> ⎝<lb/> ⎛<lb/> ∂<lb/> ∂<lb/> ,<lb/> ,<lb/></formula>

				<label>(4)<lb/></label>

			<p>For an isothermal-isobaric process the integration of the above equation yields<lb/></p>

				<formula>(<lb/> )<lb/> ( )<lb/> .<lb/> ,<lb/> ,<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> ∫<lb/> ⎟<lb/> ⎠<lb/> ⎞<lb/> ⎜<lb/> ⎝<lb/> ⎛<lb/> ∂<lb/> ∂<lb/> =<lb/> ∆<lb/> ∆<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> M<lb/> dH<lb/> T<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> M<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> (5)<lb/></formula>

			<p>Equation 5 indicates that the magnetic entropy change is proportional to the temperature<lb/> derivative of magnetization at constant field. By combining the equation 4 with the<lb/> corresponding TdS equation, it can be shown that the infinitesimal adiabatic temperature<lb/> rise for the reversible adiabatic-isobaric process is equal to<lb/></p>

				<formula>( )<lb/> ( )<lb/> .<lb/> ,<lb/> ,<lb/> dH<lb/> T<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> M<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> C<lb/> T<lb/> dT<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> ⎟<lb/> ⎠<lb/> ⎞<lb/> ⎜<lb/> ⎝<lb/> ⎛<lb/> ∂<lb/> ∂<lb/> ⎟ ⎟<lb/> ⎠<lb/> ⎞<lb/> ⎜ ⎜<lb/> ⎝<lb/> ⎛<lb/> −<lb/> =<lb/> (6)<lb/></formula>

			<p>Hence, it may be noted from the above equation that the adiabatic temperature rise is<lb/> directly proportional to the absolute temperature, the temperature derivative of<lb/> magnetization and the magnetic field change. However, it is inversely proportional to the<lb/> heat capacity. The integration of equation 6 gives the value of MCE as<lb/></p>

				<formula>(<lb/> )<lb/> ( )<lb/> (<lb/> )<lb/> ∫<lb/> ⎟<lb/> ⎠<lb/> ⎞<lb/> ⎜<lb/> ⎝<lb/> ⎛<lb/> ∂<lb/> ∂<lb/> ⎟ ⎟<lb/> ⎠<lb/> ⎞<lb/> ⎜ ⎜<lb/> ⎝<lb/> ⎛<lb/> −<lb/> =<lb/> ∆<lb/> ∆<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> .<lb/> )<lb/> ,<lb/> ,<lb/> ,<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> ad<lb/> dH<lb/> T<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> M<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> C<lb/> T<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> T<lb/> (7)<lb/></formula>

			<p>A careful examination of the equations 4 to 7 reveals the following points:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i) For a ferromagnet the (<lb/> )</p>

				<formula>H<lb/> T<lb/> M ∂<lb/> ∂ /<lb/> is largest at the ordering temperature (T C ),<lb/> therefore,<lb/> ( ) H<lb/> M T<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> ∆<lb/></formula>

			<p>should peak at T C .<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) Using equations 6 and 7, Tishin et al. have shown that, for a ferromagnet, in the limit<lb/> of ∆H tending to zero, ∆T ad also peaks near the T C <ref type="biblio">[8]</ref>. Furthermore, the behavior of the<lb/> ∆T ad and<lb/></p>

				<formula>( ) H<lb/> M T<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> ∆<lb/></formula>

			<p>should be similar and they will gradually be reduced on both sides<lb/> of the T C .<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) For the same value<lb/></p>

				<formula>( ) H<lb/> M T<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> ∆<lb/></formula>

			<p>, the ∆T ad will be larger at higher absolute<lb/> temperature, and also when the total heat capacity of the solid is lower. Furthermore, at<lb/> elevated temperatures, due to large value of the total heat capacity, considerable ∆T ad can<lb/> be observed only when (<lb/> )</p>

				<formula>H<lb/> T<lb/> M ∂<lb/> ∂ /<lb/> becomes significant.<lb/></formula>

			<p>From the above discussion, it is clear that the MCE is significant only close to a magnetic<lb/> transition temperature. As a consequence, in general ferro-para magnetic transitions will<lb/> show the maximum entropy change. Therefore, the first and foremost attempt in the<lb/> design of a magnetic refrigerator is to identify a suitable magnetic material which shows<lb/> a magnetic transition near the operating temperature of the refrigerator. Since the MCE<lb/> depends on the sharpness of the transition, materials with first order magnetic transitions<lb/> are preferred. Another alternative is to use materials which undergo magnetic field-<lb/>induced structural transitions. The entropy change associated with the structural changes<lb/> would enhance the magnetic entropy change and hence a large MCE is expected.<lb/> Therefore, from the point of view of refrigeration applications, one looks for materials<lb/> which exhibit giant magnetocaloric effect. However, when put into the application, there<lb/> will always be a drift in the operating temperature and therefore, the refrigerant system<lb/> should contribute considerable MCE over a span of temperature around the operating<lb/> temperature. This can be achieved by making a composite magnetic material which<lb/> contains many materials whose magnetic transition temperatures are spread over a span<lb/> around the operating temperature. Other possibility is to have a material which shows<lb/> close-by multiple magnetic transitions. In both these cases, a &apos;table-like&apos; (flat) MCE vs. T<lb/> plot is expected. However, due to the lack of materials with sharp multiple transitions,<lb/> emphasis is given to the first choice, i.e., to tune the magnetic transition of the parent<lb/> system with the help of substitutions so that a graded magnetic material is produced. But,<lb/> substitutions generally reduce the MCE and therefore, a compromise has to be reached so<lb/> as to get a reasonable MCE spread over a range of temperature or a &apos;table-like&apos; MCE.<lb/></p>

			<head>2. 1<lb/> MEASUREMENT OF MCE USING INDIRECT METHODS<lb/></head>

			<p>Unlike direct measurement, which usually yields only the adiabatic temperature change,<lb/> indirect method using the heat capacity data at different applied fields allow the<lb/> calculation of both ∆Tad(T, ∆H) and ∆S M (T, ∆H). On the other hand, the calculation using<lb/> magnetization measurements yields only ∆S M (T, ∆H). In the latter case, magnetization<lb/> must be measured as a function of T and H. This allows to obtain ∆S M (T, ∆H) by<lb/> numerical integration using equation. 5, and it is a very useful tool in the rapid search for<lb/> potential magnetic refrigerant materials <ref type="biblio">[2, 9, 10]</ref>. The accuracy of ∆S M (T,∆H) calculated<lb/> from magnetization data depends on the accuracy of the measurements of the magnetic<lb/> moment, T and H. It is also affected by the fact that the exact differentials in equation 5<lb/> (dM, dH and dT) are replaced by the measured variations (dM, dT and dH). Taking into<lb/> account all these effects, the error in the value of ∆S M (T, ∆H) lies within the range of 3-<lb/>10% <ref type="biblio">[2, 10]</ref>. The measurement of the heat capacity as a function of temperature in<lb/> constant magnetic fields and pressure, C(T)P,H, provides the most complete<lb/> characterization of MCE in magnetic materials. The entropy of a solid can be calculated<lb/> from the heat capacity as:<lb/></p>

		<formula>0<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> S<lb/> dT<lb/> T<lb/> T<lb/> C<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> +<lb/> = ∫<lb/> (8)<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> ,<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> H<lb/> T<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> S<lb/> dT<lb/> T<lb/> T<lb/> C<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> +<lb/> = ∫<lb/></formula>

		<label>(9)<lb/></label>

		<p>where<lb/> 0<lb/> H<lb/> S and<lb/> 1<lb/> H<lb/> S are the zero temperature entropies. In a condensed system<lb/> 0<lb/> H<lb/> S =<lb/> 1<lb/> H<lb/> S<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[11]</ref>. Hence, if S(T)H is known, both ∆Tad(T, ∆H) and ∆S M (T, ∆H) can be obtained <ref type="biblio">[10]<lb/></ref> with he help of the following equations (see Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>):<lb/></p>

				<formula>S<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> ad<lb/> S<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> T<lb/> T<lb/> T<lb/> ]<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> [<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> 0<lb/> 1 −<lb/> ≅<lb/> ∆<lb/> ∆<lb/> (10)<lb/> 0<lb/> 1<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> H<lb/> M<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> T<lb/> S<lb/> −<lb/> =<lb/> ∆<lb/> ∆<lb/> (11)<lb/></formula>

			<p>On the basis of the magnetocaloric properties of a number of compounds, Pecharsky and<lb/> Gschneidner have shown that the determination of MCE using the indirect methods are<lb/> reliable and compares well with those determined from the direct measurement <ref type="biblio">[12]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>2.2<lb/> POTENTIAL MAGNETOCALORIC MATERIALS FOR VARIOUS<lb/> TEMPERATURE REGIMES<lb/></head>

		<p>The magnetocaloric effect can be exploited for cooling applications in various<lb/> temperature regimes, the oldest being the adiabatic demagnetization which was used to<lb/> achieve the temperatures below 1 K with the help of paramagnetic salts such as<lb/> Gd 2 (SO 4 ) 3 .8H 2 O <ref type="biblio">[13]</ref>. Apart from the paramagnetic salts, the paramagnetic alloys like<lb/> PrNi 5 has also been used in the adiabatic demagnetization devices <ref type="biblio">[14]</ref>. Recent studies on<lb/> the paramagnetic garnets and their nanocomposites have shown that these materials are<lb/> also potential refrigerants in the temperatures regime below 10 K <ref type="biblio">[15]</ref>. Due to the low<lb/> value of (<lb/> )H<lb/> T<lb/> M ∂<lb/> ∂ /<lb/>, the paramagnetic salts yield small ∆T ad and hence are not suitable<lb/> refrigerants for the temperatures above 10 K. For this temperature range, magnetically<lb/> ordered materials have to be used. Because of the presence of the magnetic correlations,<lb/> the magnetically ordered materials undergo an order-disorder transition in a narrow<lb/> temperature intervals and therefore yield large value of (<lb/> )H<lb/> T<lb/> M ∂<lb/> ∂ /<lb/> ,which in turn leads<lb/> to considerable MCE. It has been reported that pure rare earth metals such as Pr, Nd, Er<lb/> and Tb exhibit considerable MCE below 60 K <ref type="biblio">[2]</ref>. However, the investigations regarding<lb/> the MCE of various rare earth alloys and intermetallic compounds suggest that they are<lb/> better refrigerants than the pure rare earths. Among them, the best for the range of 10-80<lb/> K are RAl 2 , Dy 0.5 Ho 0.5 , Dy x Er 1-x [0&lt;x&lt;1], RNiAl and RNi 2 compounds <ref type="biblio">[2, 16-18]</ref>. For<lb/> temperatures above 80 K, the promising refrigerants are Dy metal and Gd 5 (Si , Ge) 4 alloys<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[19]</ref>. However, near room temperature, the prototype material is pure Gd <ref type="biblio">[2]</ref>. Most of the<lb/> intermetallic compounds which order near room temperature show significantly lower<lb/> MCE as compared to that of Gd metal <ref type="biblio">[20]</ref>. The only system in which the MCE is equal<lb/> to that of Gd is Gd 5 (Si,Ge) 4 . Apart from the rare earth based intermetallic compounds, a<lb/> few transition metal based compounds are also known to exhibit considerable MCE near<lb/> room temperature. The best among them are MnFeP 1-x As x , Mn(As,Sb) <ref type="biblio">[3, 21, 22]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>3<lb/> MAGNETISM OF RCo 2 COMPOUNDS AND ITS IMPORTANCE IN<lb/> MAGNETOCALORIC EFFECT<lb/></head>

			<p>Rare earth (R) -transition metal (TM) intermetallics formed between different rare earths<lb/> and TM=Fe, Co, Ni crystallize in the cubic structure with MgCu 2 -type structure <ref type="biblio">[23]</ref>.<lb/> They also form with nonmagnetic elements such as Al, Ga, Si, Ge etc. The magnetic<lb/> ordering temperatures of RFe 2 compounds being much above the room temperature, from<lb/> the point of view of magnetic refrigeration application, they are not considered. On the<lb/> other hand the compounds based on Co and Ni have their ordering temperatures below<lb/> room temperature and has attracted several studies. The tunability of the magnetic<lb/> ordering temperature of these compounds over a wide span with the help of substitutions<lb/> at the Co/Ni site, without changes in the crystal structure, has prompted many researchers<lb/> to carry out detailed magnetic and other related investigations <ref type="biblio">[24-30]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 2 Schematic diagram showing the magnetic state of TM sublattices in RTM 2<lb/> compounds.<lb/> RTM 2<lb/> TM= Co<lb/> (On the verge of magnetism)<lb/> TM= Ni<lb/> (Nonmagnetic)<lb/> TM= Fe<lb/> (Magnetic)<lb/></figure>

			<p>Though RTM 2 [TM=Fe, Co and Ni] compounds crystallize in the same structure, there<lb/> are considerable differences in their magnetic properties, especially with regard to the<lb/> TM component <ref type="biblio">[31]</ref>. This is due to the peculiar band structure of these compounds <ref type="biblio">[23]</ref>.<lb/> The hybridization between the transition metal 3d band and the rare earth 5d (4d) band<lb/> gives rise to interesting magnetic properties in R-TM intermetallic compounds. In R-TM<lb/> intermetallics, for a particular R atom, the change in the number of 3d electrons across<lb/> the TM series leads to considerable effect on the density of state s at the Fermi level<lb/> [N(E F )] and plays a decisive role in determining the magnetic properties. Within the<lb/> RTM 2 series, RFe 2 compounds posses magnetic transition metal sublattice with a<lb/> magnetic moment of 1.5µ B <ref type="biblio">[32]</ref>. The complete replacement of Fe by Co gives rise to one<lb/> extra electron per Co atom to the 3d band. In the rigid band picture, the addition of the<lb/> extra electrons leads to the filling of the 3d band, which in turn alters the N(E F ) and gives<lb/> rise to interesting magnetic properties in the RCo 2 compounds. In this series of<lb/> compounds the magnetic state of Co strongly depends on the alloying rare earth and the<lb/> moment varies between 0 and 1 µ B <ref type="biblio">[32]</ref>. The variation within the series indicates the<lb/> inherent instability of the magnetic state of Co sublattice. In the RNi 2 compounds two<lb/> extra 3d electrons, as compared to RFe 2 , per Ni atom are added. This further addition of<lb/> the extra electron, as compared to that of RCo 2 compounds, drives the Fermi level to a<lb/> region of low density of states and therefore leads to a permanently nonmagnetic state of<lb/> the 3d sublattice in the RNi 2 compounds. Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> shows the schematic diagram showing<lb/> the TM magnetic state in RTM 2 compounds.<lb/></p>

			<head>Fig. 3 M vs. H isotherms showing the itinerant electron metamagnetism in ErCo 2<lb/></head>

			<p>In RCo 2 compounds, the T C values vary from ~20 K to ~ 400 K. Unlike the case of the<lb/> YFe 2 , the YCo 2 does not exhibit any magnetic ordering and behaves like an exchange<lb/> enhanced Pauli paramagnet <ref type="biblio">[23]</ref>. The instability of the magnetic state associated with the<lb/> Co sublattice mentioned earlier in some of the RCo 2 compounds leads to metamagnetic<lb/> transition. The creation of the Co moments by the R molecular field as these samples are<lb/> cooled through their ordering temperatures is responsible for the metamagnetic transition,<lb/> which is termed as itinerant electron metamagnetism (IEM). Fig.<ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the M-H<lb/> isotherms illustrating the IEM at temperatures just above T C in ErCo 2 . The IEM in these<lb/> compounds leads to first order transition (FOT) at their ordering temperature and many<lb/> interesting observations regarding their structural, magnetic, thermal and transport<lb/> behavior. Among the RCo 2 compounds, ErCo 2 , HoCo 2 and DyCo 2 are found to show<lb/> FOT while all others show a second order transition (SOT) at their ordering temperature.<lb/> Based on a systematic analysis of the magnetic and electrical resistivity data on<lb/> (Er,Y)Co 2 , Hauser et al. have indeed shown that dilution of Er by Y leads to the<lb/> disappearance of IEM <ref type="biblio">[33]</ref>. The IEM in these compounds may also be induced by an<lb/> external magnetic field in a limited temperature range above T C <ref type="biblio">[23]</ref>. In most of the<lb/> magnetic materials, the transitions are of second order nature and hence IEM systems<lb/> have received a lot of attention for decades owing to their interest in fundamental<lb/> physics. However, of late they have become natural probes in the search for materials<lb/> with large magnetocaloric effect as well as magnetoresistance, by virtue of the first order<lb/> nature of their magnetic transitions. Other IEM systems such as La(Fe,Si) <ref type="biblio">13</ref> -based<lb/> systems have also attracted considerable attention from the point of view of MCE<lb/> recently <ref type="biblio">[34]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.1<lb/> ITINERANT ELECTRON METAMAGNETISM IN RCo 2 COMPOUNDS<lb/></head>

			<p>It has been observed that some RCo 2 compounds [R=Er, Ho and Dy] undergo IEM in<lb/> which the Co sublattice changes from a nonmagnetic state to a magnetic state when the<lb/> field acting on the 3d band is larger than a critical value H C <ref type="biblio">[23, 33, 35]</ref>. This field-<lb/>induced transition in the 3d sublattice is known as itinerant electron metamagnetism and<lb/> was first theoretically predicted by Wohlfarth and Rhodes in 1962 <ref type="biblio">[36]</ref>. Using the Landau<lb/> expansion of the magnetic free energy of the d-electrons as<lb/></p>

		<formula>MH<lb/> M<lb/> C<lb/> M<lb/> B<lb/> M<lb/> A<lb/> F<lb/> −<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> =<lb/> ..........<lb/> 6<lb/> 4<lb/> 2<lb/> 6<lb/> 4<lb/> 2<lb/></formula>

		<label>(12)<lb/></label>

		<p>The theory led to the following expressions for the first lower order coefficients<lb/></p>

				<formula>R<lb/> E<lb/> N<lb/> A<lb/> F )<lb/> (<lb/> 4<lb/> 1<lb/> =<lb/> (13)<lb/> ( )<lb/> ( )<lb/> ( )<lb/> ( ) ⎥<lb/> ⎥<lb/> ⎦<lb/> ⎤<lb/> ⎢<lb/> ⎢<lb/> ⎣<lb/> ⎡<lb/> ⎭<lb/> ⎬<lb/> ⎫<lb/> ⎩<lb/> ⎨<lb/> ⎧<lb/> −<lb/> −<lb/> =<lb/> 2<lb/> &apos;<lb/> &apos;<lb/> &apos;<lb/> 3<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> 3<lb/> 64<lb/> 1<lb/> F<lb/> F<lb/> F<lb/> F<lb/> F<lb/> E<lb/> N<lb/> E<lb/> N<lb/> E<lb/> N<lb/> E<lb/> N<lb/> E<lb/> N<lb/> B<lb/> (</formula>

				<label>14</label>

				<formula>)<lb/></formula>

			<p>where<lb/></p>

				<formula>[<lb/> ] 1<lb/> )<lb/> (<lb/> 1<lb/> −<lb/> −<lb/> =<lb/> F<lb/> E<lb/> IN<lb/> R<lb/></formula>

			<p>is the Stoner enhancement factor. N(E F ), N&apos;(E F ) and N&apos;&apos;(E F ) are<lb/> the density of states and its first and second derivatives at Fermi level. IEM occurs when<lb/> the magnetization dependence of free energy has variation similar to that shown in Fig.<lb/> <ref type="figure">4a</ref> in zero field and it changes to the lower curve of this figure when field is increased to<lb/> higher fields (H 1 &lt;H C &lt;H 2 ) <ref type="biblio">[36]</ref>. The corresponding magnetization curve is shown in Fig.<lb/> <ref type="figure">4b</ref>. It has been reported that such magnetization dependence of free energy and hence the<lb/> metamagnetic transition in the field dependence of magnetization arises when coefficient<lb/> of M 4 is positive and some of higher order terms in the equation 12 give negative<lb/> contribution. Therefore, it may be noticed from equations 13 &amp; 14 that IEM can occur<lb/> when: (1) A is weakly positive. i. e. when the Stoner criterion for the onset of<lb/> ferromagnetism is almost satisfied, and (2) B is negative, which implies another<lb/> minimum for a non-zero value of M. The later condition requires N&apos;&apos;(E F ) to be large<lb/> enough, which in turn means that the density of states at Fermi level should have strong<lb/> positive curvature. On theoretical grounds, Wohlfarth and Rhodes showed that a<lb/> maximum in the temperature dependence of magnetic susceptibility is expected due to<lb/> the large positive curvature of the density of states and is characteristic of an IEM system<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[36]</ref>. Such a temperature dependence of susceptibility has indeed been observed in a<lb/> number of compounds which exhibit IEM <ref type="biblio">[37]</ref>.<lb/></p>

		<figure>Fig. 4. (a) Magnetization dependence of free energy of a metamagnetic system at<lb/> different fields (H 1 &lt;H C &lt;H 2 ); (b) Field dependence of magnetization of a metamagnetic<lb/> system.<lb/> H C<lb/> F<lb/> H=<lb/> H 1<lb/> (a)<lb/> H 2<lb/> M<lb/> Fig. 5 Arrott&apos;s plots of DyCo 2 and TbCo 2 [Fig. <ref type="figure">5a</ref> taken from Ref. <ref type="biblio">35</ref>.]<lb/></figure>

		<p>It was mentioned above that materials with negative M 4 coefficient in equation 12 exhibit<lb/> IEM and FOT. In general, the IEM is accompanied with the hysteresis effect (see Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>).<lb/> However there are reports in literature that, even though some materials posses negative<lb/> M 4 coefficient, they do not distinctly exhibit IEM and hence the hysteretic effect. In such<lb/> cases, the presence of IEM and FOT are diagnosed with the help of Arrott&apos;s plots. It has<lb/> been established that the materials with negative M coefficient in the Landau free energy<lb/> expression posses S-shaped Arrott&apos;s plots <ref type="biblio">[38]</ref>. To emphasize on the above point, the<lb/> Arrott&apos;s plots for DyCo 2 and TbCo 2 are shown in Figs. <ref type="figure">5a &amp;b</ref>, respectively. It can be<lb/> clearly seen from these figures that the near T C Arrott&apos;s plots of DyCo 2 , which exhibits<lb/> FOT, are S-shaped whereas those corresponding to TbCo 2 , which is known to possess<lb/> SOT, are linear.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.2 ROLE OF MAGNETOVOLUME EFFECT IN RCo 2 -BASED COMPOUNDS<lb/></head>

			<p>Considerable effort has been put to understand the mystery behind the changeover of the<lb/> order of magnetic transition from SOT to FOT, as the rare earth is changed in RCo 2<lb/> compounds. The first true attempt towards understanding the nature of transition in these<lb/> compounds was made by Bloch et al. and later by Inoue and Shimizu <ref type="biblio">[39, 40]</ref>. According<lb/> to these authors, the critical parameter that governs the IEM and therefore FOT in these<lb/> compounds is the molecular field or the ordering temperature <ref type="biblio">[39, 40]</ref>. However, these<lb/> theories met with only limited success. Recently, Khmelevskyi and Mohn have modified<lb/> these models by incorporating the contributions from the magnetovolume effect and spin<lb/> fluctuations <ref type="biblio">[41]</ref>. The most important feature in the modified model is the role of lattice<lb/> parameter in determining the magnetic state of Co and thereby the possibility of IEM and<lb/> FOT.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 1 Magnetic ordering temperature, maximum values of isothermal entropy change<lb/> and adiabatic temperature change in substituted RCo 2 compounds [R=Er, Ho and Dy].<lb/> ∆H is the field change for which the MCE is calculated.<lb/> Compound<lb/> T C (K)<lb/> ∆H (kOe)<lb/> (∆S M ) max<lb/> (J Kg -1 K -1 )<lb/> (∆T ad ) max<lb/> (K)<lb/> ErCo 2<lb/> 35 42<lb/> 50<lb/> 33 42 , ~36 24<lb/> ~9.5 24<lb/> Er(Co 0.95 Si 0.05 ) 2<lb/> ~52 43<lb/> 60<lb/> 20 43<lb/> ~7.5 43<lb/> Er(Co 0.925 Al 0.075 ) 2<lb/> 90 44<lb/> Er(Co 0.97 Ga 0.03 ) 2<lb/> 41 26<lb/> Er(Co 0.97 Ge 0.03 ) 2<lb/> 47 26<lb/> Er(Co 0.97 In 0.03 ) 2<lb/> 51 26<lb/> 20<lb/> 1.3 26<lb/> Er(Co 0.9 Ni 0.1 ) 2<lb/> 13 24<lb/> 50<lb/> 29.8 24<lb/> 9.5 24<lb/> HoCo 2<lb/> ~78 28<lb/> 50<lb/> 23 28<lb/> ~7.5 28<lb/> Ho(Co 0.95 Si 0.05 ) 2<lb/> 100 45<lb/> 60<lb/> ~20<lb/> ~6 45<lb/> Ho(Co 0.95 Al 0.05 ) 2<lb/> 110 46<lb/> Ho(Co 0.9 Ga 0.1 ) 2<lb/> 165 47<lb/> Ho(Co 0.9 Ni 0.1 ) 2<lb/> 40 28<lb/> 50<lb/> 22 28<lb/> 8 28<lb/> DyCo 2<lb/> 142 27<lb/> 50<lb/> 11.3 27<lb/> 5.4 27<lb/> Dy(Co 0.925 Si 0.075 ) 2<lb/> 164 27<lb/> 50<lb/> 6.5 27<lb/> 3.6 27<lb/> Dy(Co 1.96 Al 0.04 ) 2<lb/> 171 29<lb/> 10<lb/> 4.3 29<lb/> Dy(Co 1.9 Ge 0.1 ) 2<lb/> 173 29<lb/> 10<lb/> ~1.8 29<lb/> Dy(Co 1.9 Ga 0.1 ) 2<lb/> 195 29<lb/> 10<lb/> ~1.9 29<lb/> Dy(Co 1.94 Fe 0.06 ) 2<lb/> 242 30<lb/> 10<lb/> 1.6 30<lb/></figure>

			<p>The calculations of Khmelevskyi and Mohn suggest that in RCo 2 series, the compounds<lb/> with lattice parameter more than 7.22 Å possess permanently magnetic Co sublattice and<lb/> therefore show SOT at T C . On the other hand, if the lattice parameter is less than 7.05 Å,<lb/> they posses nonmagnetic Co 3d sublattice, which is similar to that in YCo 2 . In the<lb/> compounds with the lattice parameters in the range of 7.05 -7.22 Å, the Co sublattice is<lb/> nonmagnetic, but moment can be induced with the help of the molecular field of the rare<lb/> earth or the applied field. This transition is called IEM, which results in FOT in such<lb/> compounds. Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows the theoretical prediction of Khmelevskyi and Mohn, regarding<lb/> the order of transition for various RCo 2 compounds. It is quite clear from this figure that,<lb/> except TbCo 2 and TmCo 2 , in all other compounds the nature of magnetic transition is<lb/> consistent with the value of the lattice parameter. It is of importance to note that, based<lb/> on the studies of a number of R(Co,Al) 2 compounds, Duc et al. have suggested a critical<lb/> lattice parameter of 7.27 Å for the appearance of Co 3d magnetic moment in RCo 2<lb/> compounds <ref type="biblio">[32]</ref>. In view of these observations, there is a great scope for studying the<lb/> structure-magnetic property correlation in RCo 2 compounds under various substitutions,<lb/> which cause lattice parameter variations. Another point of interest is the study of the<lb/> magnetism and related properties as a function of applied pressure.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 6 The predicted order of transition in various RCo 2 compounds. [Data taken from<lb/> Ref. <ref type="biblio">41</ref>.]<lb/> Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref> Pressure dependence of T C in ErCo 2 and DyCo 2 compounds. [Data taken Ref. <ref type="biblio">42</ref>.]<lb/></figure>

		<p>There are several reports in the literature which show the strong lattice volume<lb/> dependence of the magnetic properties in the RCo 2 compounds <ref type="biblio">[23, 32, 47, 48]</ref>. The role<lb/> of the lattice parameter in RCo 2 compounds has been demonstrated by pressure<lb/> dependent studies as well <ref type="biblio">[48-50]</ref>. Pressure dependence of magnetic properties in RCo 2<lb/> compounds have been reported by many authors, who have shown that the negative<lb/> magnetovolume effect produced by the pressure destabilizes the Co magnetic state,<lb/> thereby reducing the T C values. Fig <ref type="figure">7</ref> shows the pressure dependence of T C in ErCo 2 and<lb/> DyCo 2 compounds.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 8 The concentration dependence of lattice parameter and T C in R(Co 1-x Ga x ) 2<lb/> compounds. [Figure taken from Ref. <ref type="biblio">47</ref>.]<lb/></figure>

			<p>Effect of substitutions of nonmagnetic elements such as Al, Ga, Ge, In and Si for Co in<lb/> RCo 2 compounds with R=Er, Ho and Dy have been reported by many authors. Table <ref type="table">1<lb/></ref> shows the highlights of these studies. As is evident from this table, the ordering<lb/> temperature, in general, increases with substitutions. As expected, substitution of Fe also<lb/> causes an increase in T C . The enhancement of T C due to the substitutions other than Fe<lb/> mainly arises from the positive magnetovolume effect. The increase in lattice parameter<lb/> as a result of substitutions (upto a critical concentration) causes local moment formation<lb/> due to the positive magnetovolume effect. These local moments cause an increase in the<lb/> R-Co and Co-Co exchange interactions, giving rise to an enhancement of T C <ref type="biblio">[35]</ref>.<lb/> However, above the critical concentration, the nonmagnetic substitution causes a nearly<lb/> uniform distribution of Co moments. At this stage, the increasing trend of T C stops and<lb/> for further increase in the concentration of the substituents, T C starts decreasing. Figures<lb/> <ref type="figure">8a &amp; b</ref> show the variation of the lattice parameter and the T C as a function of Ga<lb/> concentration in R(Co 1-x Ga x ) 2 compounds, respectively. It can be seen from these figures<lb/> that the lattice parameters monotonically increase with Ga concentration in all the<lb/> compounds, but the T C variation is different for different rare earths. While the<lb/> compounds based on Dy show an initial increase in T C , the ones with Nd and Gd show a<lb/> decreasing trend of T C even at very small concentrations of Ga. The behavior of Tb-based<lb/> compounds is almost identical to that of Dy compounds. These variations are very much<lb/> consistent with the predictions of Khmelevskyi and Mohn (see Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>). The prediction<lb/> that TbCo 2 is at the boundary between FOT and SOT is reinforced by the variation of T C<lb/> shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">8b</ref>. Therefore, the examples of nonmagnetic substituted compounds<lb/> demonstrate the presence of positive magnetovolume effect, in contrast to the negative<lb/> magnetovolume effect arising from the application of pressure. In the case of Fe<lb/> substitution, the T C shows a monotonic increase with Fe concentration, in all the<lb/> compounds. The increase in T C seen in the case of Fe substitution mainly arises from the<lb/> enhanced TM-TM exchange interaction and not from the magnetovolume effect. Han et<lb/> al have reported that in Dy(Co,Fe) 2 systems, the order of transition changes from first<lb/> order to second order upon Fe substitution. <ref type="biblio">[30]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 9. Variation of T C as a function of pressure in Er(Co 1-x Si x ) 2 compounds. [Data taken<lb/> from Ref. 42]<lb/></figure>

			<p>In view of the opposing effects of nonmagnetic substitutions and applied pressure on the<lb/> magnetovolume effect in RCo 2 compounds, it is of interest to find out the effect of<lb/> pressure on these substituted compounds. Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref> shows the effect of pressure on Si<lb/> substituted ErCo 2 compounds. As is evident from this figure, like the parent compounds,<lb/> the application of pressure causes a reduction in T C in the Si substituted compounds as<lb/> well.<lb/></p>

		<figure>Fig.10 Temperature variation of isothermal magnetic entropy change in Dy(Co 1-x Si x ) 2<lb/> with x= 0, 0.075 and 0.15] compounds obtained for a field change (∆H) of 50 kOe. [Data<lb/> taken from Ref. <ref type="biblio">27</ref>.]<lb/> Fig.11 Temperature variation of the zero-field heat capacity (C) of Dy(Co 1-x Si x ) 2<lb/> compounds [with x=0, 0.75 and 0.15]. The inset shows the C-T data of DyCo 2 obtained<lb/> in zero field and 50 kOe. [Data partly taken from Ref. <ref type="biblio">27</ref>]<lb/></figure>

			<head>4 MAGNETOCALORIC EFFECT IN RCo 2 -BASED COMPOUNDS<lb/></head>

			<p>Magnetocaloric effect in terms of isothermal magnetic entropy change as well as<lb/> adiabatic temperature change on RCo 2 compounds with R=Er, Ho and Dy have been<lb/> measured by many authors and the important results are summarized in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. The<lb/> values obtained in parent RCo 2 compounds with Er, Ho and Dy are quite high as<lb/> compared to many other materials <ref type="biblio">[51]</ref>. It is of interest to note that, though the theoretical<lb/> magnetic entropy i.e. Rln(2J+1) value for all these three compounds are approximately<lb/> equal, the MCE is the highest in ErCo 2 . As the magnetic entropy tends to saturate around<lb/> T C and as the saturation magnetization of these three compounds are very close, the<lb/> smaller the T C the faster the magnetic entropy saturation. Accordingly, the maximum<lb/> entropy change i.e.,<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> is the highest in the compound with the lowest T C . At this<lb/> point it is of importance to mention that the<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> value in TbCo 2 has been found to be<lb/> about 6 J kg -1 K -1 <ref type="biblio">[25, 52]</ref>. Compared to the MCE of the RCo 2 compounds with SOT, the<lb/> MCE seen in TbCo 2 is high, which once again justifies the prediction of Khmelevskyi<lb/> and Mohn (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>In order to find the effect of substitutions on MCE, several studies have been devoted to<lb/> measure the MCE of substituted RCo 2 [R=Er, Ho and Dy] compounds <ref type="biblio">[24-30, 35, 42, 43,<lb/> 45]</ref>. As in the case of other magnetic properties such as ordering temperature, the MCE is<lb/> also found to be very much affected by substitutions. Fig. <ref type="figure">10</ref> shows the MCE variation<lb/> observed in Si substituted DyCo 2 . It has been found that the MCE calculated using the C-<lb/>H-T data as well as the M-H-T data yield almost same results. Fig. <ref type="figure">11</ref> shows the typical<lb/> heat capacity (C) vs. T plot of Dy(Co 1-x Si x ) 2 compounds. It can be seen that the onset of<lb/> magnetic ordering in DyCo 2 is characterized by huge jump in the C-T plot, however, the<lb/> near T C jump seen in the C-T data of the Si substituted compounds decrease with<lb/> increasing Si concentration. This observation indicates the change in the order of<lb/> transition from first order towards second order and corroborates with the magnetization<lb/> studies <ref type="biblio">[35]</ref>. Similar observations have been reported by many other authors on other<lb/> RCo 2 -based systems. The inset of Fig. <ref type="figure">11</ref> shows the C-T plots of DyCo 2 obtained under<lb/> zero field and in a field of 50 kOe. The variation of MCE under various substitutions is<lb/> shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. As is evident, substitutions, in general, tend to increase the T C and<lb/> decrease the MCE values in Er, Ho and Dy compounds. Fig. <ref type="figure">12</ref> shows the effect of<lb/> substitutions on the magnetic entropy change of several RCo 2 compounds.<lb/></p>

		<figure>Fig. 12<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> vs. T C of RCo 2 -based compounds. The filled circles correspond to the<lb/> materials which show FOT whereas the open circles correspond to the materials with<lb/> SOT. [Fig taken from Ref. <ref type="biblio">25</ref>]<lb/></figure>


			<p>Its has been argued by several authors that in RCo 2 compounds the substitution of Co by<lb/> small amounts of magnetic or nonmagnetic elements does not alter the crystalline electric<lb/> field and therefore the R-moments remain unaltered <ref type="biblio">[28]</ref>. Now, since the magnetization<lb/> tends to saturate around the T C , the resulting variations in the MCE are assumed to be<lb/> natural consequence of the T C variation. However, a careful examination of the<lb/> magnetization and MCE data clearly reveals that apart from the T C variations, the nature<lb/> of the transition does play a decisive role in determining the MCE, at least whenever<lb/> there is an increase in T C . At this juncture it is worth mentioning the report on<lb/> Dy(Co 0.925 Si 0.075 ) 2 and Dy(Co 0.85 Si 0.15 ) 2 compounds, which have the T C values of 164 K<lb/> and 154 K, respectively, with maximum ∆S M values of 6.5 and 5.3 Jkg -1 K -1 <ref type="biblio">[27]</ref>. Based<lb/> on the data on Er(Co,Si) 2 compounds, a similar observation has been reported by <ref type="biblio">Duc et<lb/> al.</ref> as well <ref type="biblio">[25]</ref>. Therefore, the reduction in MCE due to substitutions at the Co site could<lb/> be explained as follows. The local magnetic moments arising from the positive<lb/> magnetovolume effect are not fully exchange coupled and therefore enhances the spin<lb/> fluctuations. The presence of spin fluctuations decreases the strength of IEM and<lb/> consequently weakens the first order nature of the transition at T C . Wang et al. have<lb/> studied the effect of nonmagnetic substitutions such as Al, Si, Ga and Ge for Co in<lb/> DyCo 2 and found that the substitutions cause an increase in T C , but the transition changes<lb/> from FOT to SOT <ref type="biblio">[29]</ref>. Depending on the stability of the Co magnetic state, the<lb/> concentration (of the substituent) at which the FOT changes to SOT differs from one<lb/> compound to another. The detrimental role of the spin fluctuations on the strength of IEM<lb/> and MCE has been reported by Han et al. as well <ref type="biblio">[30]</ref>. The presence of increased spin<lb/> fluctuations for small concentrations of nonmagnetic substituents on the properties such<lb/> as electrical resistivity of RCo 2 compounds has also been investigated in the past <ref type="biblio">[53]</ref>. It<lb/> is of interest to note that there exists a correlation between the variations of T C and the<lb/> changes in the properties such as MCE and resistivity, in the substituted compounds.<lb/> Several studies have also revealed that the variation of adiabatic temperature change is<lb/> identical to that of the entropy change. The maximum values of ∆T ad obtained in some of<lb/> the compounds are also listed in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>The effect of substitutions on the magnetic properties and MCE of these compounds<lb/> could be understood by calculating the temperature variation of the Landau coefficients.<lb/> It is well known that the magnetic free energy, F(M,T), in general can be expressed as<lb/> Landau expansion in the magnetization (see equation <ref type="formula">12</ref>) and the temperature and<lb/> magnetic field dependence of F(M,T) determines the nature of magnetic transition. The<lb/> Landau coefficients can be calculated using the equation of state, given by:<lb/></p>

				<formula>5<lb/> 3<lb/> CM<lb/> BM<lb/> AM<lb/> H<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> =<lb/></formula>

				<label>(15)<lb/></label>

			<p>It may be noted from equation 15 that the magnetization isotherms obtained at various<lb/> temperatures may allow one to determine the temperature variation of the Landau<lb/> coefficients. It is well known that the temperature dependence of the Landau coefficients<lb/> may be utilized to distinguish between the first and second order transitions of magnetic<lb/> materials <ref type="biblio">[23, 34, 54]</ref>. It may be noted from equation 15 that the coefficient A<lb/> corresponds to inverse of susceptibility and therefore a minimum in the temperature<lb/> dependence of A is expected at the ordering temperature. The materials with negative A<lb/> are known to exhibit a second order transition whereas those having positive A but<lb/> negative B exhibit first order transition. In the following, the Landau analysis of the<lb/> magnetization data is demonstrated by taking the example of Si substitution for Co in<lb/> ErCo 2 .<lb/></p>

			<p>The temperature variation of Landau coefficient (B) obtained for Er(Co 1-x Si x ) 2<lb/> compounds with x=0 and 0.5 is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">13</ref>. It may be noted from the figure that for<lb/> both the compounds the sign of B near T C is negative and that its magnitude decreases<lb/> with increase in temperature. Therefore the temperature variation of B in both the<lb/> compounds indicates the presence of FOT at T C . It may also be seen that the magnitude<lb/> of B in Er(Co 0.95 Si 0.05 ) 2 at temperatures well below T C is lower than that of ErCo 2 . This<lb/> could be ascribed to the increase in the spin fluctuation contribution on Si substitution.<lb/> The effect of substitutions, as mentioned earlier, is to suppress the IEM and hence the B<lb/> values.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 13 Temperature (T) dependence of the Landau coefficient B in Er(Co 1-x Si x ) 2<lb/> compounds with x=0, 0.05. [B values have been calculated in c.g.s. units]. [Data taken<lb/> from Ref. 42.]<lb/></figure>

			<figure type="table">Table 2 Isothermal entropy change in Er(Co 1-x Si x ) 2 compounds under various pressures.<lb/> ErCo 2<lb/> Er(Co 0.975 Si 0.025 ) 2<lb/> Er(Co 0.95 Si 0.05 ) 2<lb/> P (kbar)<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> (Jkg -1 K -1 )<lb/> P (kbar)<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> (Jkg -1 K -1 )<lb/> P (kbar)<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> (Jkg -<lb/>1 K -1 )<lb/> Ambient*<lb/> 33<lb/> Ambient*<lb/> 27.4<lb/> Ambient*<lb/> 22.7<lb/> 4.7<lb/> 32.8<lb/> 2.7<lb/> 28.8<lb/> 3.3<lb/> 24.8<lb/> 7.4<lb/> 32.5<lb/> 5.8<lb/> 29.9<lb/> 9<lb/> 26.6<lb/> * Ambient pressure = 1 bar.<lb/></figure>

			<head>4.1. Effect of pressure on the magnetocaloric effect<lb/></head>

			<p>As mentioned in the earlier sections, there are several MCE studies in literature regarding<lb/> the substituted RCo 2 compounds. However, the studies of MCE under applied pressure<lb/> are very rare in these compounds. The only work available to this effect is on ErCo 2<lb/> systems. Fig. <ref type="figure">14</ref> shows the MCE variation in ErCo 2 and Er(Co 0.95 Si 0.05 ) 2 compounds<lb/> under various pressures. The pressure dependence of<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> of both these compounds is<lb/> given in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. It can be seen from Fig. <ref type="figure">14</ref> (also from Table <ref type="table">2</ref>) that, with increase in<lb/> pressure, the peak in the ∆S M vs T plot moves towards low temperatures in both the<lb/> compounds. However, in the parent compound, the<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> value of<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> almost remains<lb/> insensitive to pressure while in the substituted compounds,<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> it is found to increase. The<lb/> insensitiveness of MCE on applied pressure in the case of ErCo 2 is due to the fact that the<lb/> strength of IEM has diminished only nominally even at a pressure of about 7.7 kbar.<lb/> Hauser et al. <ref type="biblio">[55]</ref> have indeed reported that the discontinuity (at T C ) in the magnetic<lb/> contribution to the electrical resistivity in ErCo 2 decreases to about 60 % as the pressure<lb/> is increased from 1 bar to ~16 kbar, which is attributed to the reduction in the strength of<lb/> IEM. In view of this, it is reasonable to assume that for a pressure of 7.7 kbar, the<lb/> reduction in the IEM strength is not very much and therefore would contribute only to a<lb/> nominal reduction in<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> . However, the reduction in T C brought about by pressure<lb/> would try to enhance<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> due to the reduction in the thermal spin fluctuations.<lb/> Therefore, it is quite possible that the reduction in MCE caused by the weakening of IEM<lb/> is just compensated by the increase in MCE arising out of the reduction in T C . Therefore,<lb/> the insensitiveness of MCE on pressure seen in the case of ErCo 2 is consistent with the<lb/> observations made by Hauser et al. <ref type="biblio">[55]</ref>.<lb/></p>

		<figure>Fig. 14 Temperature dependence of isothermal entropy change (∆S M ) in Er(Co 1-x Si x ) 2<lb/> compounds obtained for ∆H= 50 kOe, under various applied pressures (P). [Figure taken<lb/> from Ref. <ref type="biblio">42</ref>]<lb/></figure>

		<p>On the other hand, the pressure dependence of<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> in the case of Si substituted<lb/> compounds is quite considerable. The increase seen in<lb/> max<lb/> M<lb/> S<lb/> ∆<lb/> may be attributed to the<lb/> increase in the strength of IEM, which results from the reduction of spin fluctuations<lb/> related to the negative magnetovolume effect. As in the case of substitutions, Landau<lb/> analysis can be used to study the changes in the nature of transitions and MCE, with<lb/> increase in pressure as well. The temperature variation of Landau coefficient (B) obtained<lb/> for Er(Co 1-x Si x ) 2 compounds with x=0 and 0.5 for different pressures is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">15</ref>.<lb/> There is no change in the low temperature value of B in the case of ErCo 2 , while there is<lb/> a considerable increase in Er(Co 0.95 Si 0.05 ) 2 , with increase of pressure. This implies that the<lb/> strength of IEM increases considerably with pressure in the Si substituted compounds<lb/> whereas there is no significant change in ErCo 2 . It may also be noticed from this figure<lb/> that the difference between the low temperature B values of ErCo 2 and the Si-substituted<lb/> compounds almost vanishes with increase in pressure. The effect of applied pressure (in<lb/> the substituted compounds) is to compete with the positive magnetovolume effect caused<lb/> by substitutions and to reduce it. Consequently, the magnetic nature of the Co sublattice<lb/> in the Si-substituted compounds is more or less restored to that of ErCo 2 , by the applied<lb/> pressure. This is exactly seen in Fig.<ref type="figure">15</ref> which shows that at high pressures, the low<lb/> temperature B value of Er(Co 0.95 Si 0.05 ) 2 is almost equal to that of ErCo 2 .<lb/></p>

			<p>At this point, it is of importance to note that the variation of Landau coefficient (B) with<lb/> pressure in the case of parent compounds showed that it is insensitive to pressure whereas<lb/> in the case of Si substituted compounds, it showed an increase in the magnitude.<lb/> Therefore, the variations in the magnitude of B with pressure are consistent with the<lb/> MCE variation, which implies that there is a strong correlation between the B value and<lb/> the MCE in RCo 2 -based IEM systems. In this context, it is of relevance to mention that<lb/> Yamada et al. <ref type="biblio">[56]</ref> have indeed shown that the MCE in IEM systems is primarily<lb/> governed by the magnitude of B. Fujita et al. have also reported a similar dependence of<lb/> MCE on B in La(Fe,Si) 13 compounds which also is a well known IEM system <ref type="biblio">[57]</ref>. Based<lb/> on the magnetization behaviour, it is expected that other nonmagnetic substitutions in<lb/> RCo 2 [R=Er, Ho and Dy] compounds would also result in similar correlation between<lb/> MCE and the Landau coefficient, B.<lb/></p>

		<figure>Fig. 15 Temperature (T) dependence of the Landau coefficient B, obtained under various<lb/> external pressures (P), in Er(Co 1-x Si x ) 2 compounds with x=0, 0.05. [B values have been<lb/> calculated in cgs units]. [Figure taken from Ref.<ref type="biblio">42</ref>]<lb/></figure>

			<head>5.<lb/> SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS<lb/></head>

			<p>In conclusion, the magnetic and magnetocaloric studies on the RCo 2 -based compounds<lb/> show that ErCo 2 , HoCo 2 and DyCo 2 exhibit first order magnetic transition and large<lb/> MCE. The nonmagnetic nature of Co sublattice in these compounds causes IEM at<lb/> temperatures close to the ordering temperature, which leads to first order transition.<lb/></p>

			<p>Positive magnetovolume effect resulting from the substitution of nonmagnetic elements<lb/> for Co is found to suppress IEM and FOT, due to the enhanced spin fluctuations. The<lb/> spin fluctuations arising from the local moment formation are found to be detrimental to<lb/> MCE in the substituted compounds. On the other hand, application of pressure<lb/> destabilizes the Co sublattice magnetization because of the negative magnetovolume<lb/> effect and therefore, the ordering temperature decreases. The effect of pressure on the<lb/> MCE is clearly seen in the substituted compounds in which, the negative magnetovolume<lb/> effect competes with the positive magnetovolume effect resulting from the substitutions.<lb/> The thermodynamic analysis based on the Landau&apos;s theory reveals that the MCE<lb/> variations follow the variations seen in the magnitude of the coefficient B of the Landau<lb/> free energy expression. The variations seen in the order of magnetic transition and the<lb/> MCE values seem to support the recent model proposed by Khmelevskyi and Mohn for<lb/> the occurrence of IEM in RCo 2 compounds.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
