<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Bioactive zinc nanomaterials synthesized from Crotalaria Pallida leaf extract using hydrothermal method</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Ramapriya</forename>
            <surname>Chandramouli</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Thenmozhi</forename>
            <surname>Ramasamy</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-11-12T14:50:07.020553Z">12.11.2025 14:50:07</date>
          <title>grobid.training.fulltext [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1016$1$j.chphi.2024.100701</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.chphi.2024.100701</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Ramapriya Chandramouli, Thenmozhi Ramasamy. (2024). Bioactive zinc nanomaterials synthesized from Crotalaria Pallida leaf extract using hydrothermal method. Chemical Physics Impact, 9(None), 100701. DOI: 10.1016/j.chphi.2024.100701</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T14:50:07.020553Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.fulltext</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-12T14:50:07.020553Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <head>Introduction<lb/></head>

      <p>Since the emergence of the coronavirus disease 2019<lb/> (COVID-19) pandemic, hematological malignancy pa-<lb/>tients have faced substantial risks, being highly vulner-<lb/>able to contracting severe acute respiratory syndrome<lb/> coronavirus type 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and experiencing se-<lb/>vere outcomes, including elevated hospitalization rates<lb/> and increased fatality. <ref type="biblio">1</ref> COVID-19 pandemic reminded<lb/> us the history of other pandemics that happened in the<lb/> last century. In accordance with those, following the<lb/> pandemic phase, we are facing now an epidemic one,<lb/> characterized by less morbidity and severity of the<lb/> virus in the overall population. <ref type="biblio">2,3</ref> However, hematologi-<lb/>cal malignancy patients still remain at risk of severe<lb/> COVID-19. Despite advancements in medical<lb/> interventions, such as the introduction of anti-SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 vaccines, <ref type="biblio">4</ref> targeted antivirals, <ref type="biblio">5</ref> and monoclonal<lb/> antibodies, <ref type="biblio">6</ref> which have shown promising results in<lb/> reducing the impact of COVID-19 on otherwise healthy<lb/> individuals, the same level of effectiveness cannot<lb/> always be guaranteed for patients with hematological<lb/> malignancies.<lb/></p>

        <p>This discrepancy can be attributed to their compro-<lb/>mised immune system, due to both intrinsic disease<lb/> biology and immunosuppressive treatments, rendering<lb/> them less responsive to vaccines and more susceptible<lb/> to severe COVID-19. <ref type="biblio">7-16</ref> As such, understanding the<lb/> factors influencing COVID-19 outcomes in this patient<lb/> population becomes paramount in improving their<lb/> overall management and care. Given the unique chal-<lb/>lenges faced by hematological malignancy patients in<lb/> managing COVID-19, identifying risk factors and pro-<lb/>tective factors can significantly inform clinical decision-<lb/>making and enhance patient outcomes. In response to<lb/> the onset of the pandemic, researchers globally engaged<lb/> in a range of analyses across various research levels.<lb/> These encompassed detailed case reports and case se-<lb/>ries, extensive observational studies to derive broader<lb/> insights, and comprehensive literature reviews and<lb/> meta-analyses to synthesize existing knowledge. These<lb/> combined efforts significantly enriched our under-<lb/>standing of the pandemic&apos;s multifaceted implications. <ref type="biblio">17<lb/></ref> However, within the context of individuals dealing<lb/> with hematological malignancies, several notable gaps<lb/> in understanding remain; while existing research has<lb/> shed light on specific aspects of the interaction between<lb/> COVID-19 and these malignancies, important questions<lb/> still await exploration. <ref type="biblio">14,18</ref> The intricate interplay between<lb/> the infection, its progression, and the management<lb/> strategies employed within this patient population ne-<lb/>cessitates further investigation.<lb/></p>

        <p>The present study was designed to thoroughly<lb/> investigate the outcomes and potential risk factors<lb/> linked to COVID-19 in patients with hematological<lb/> malignancies from 2020 to 2022, describing not only a<lb/> transversal picture, but also the pandemic trajectory over<lb/> those years in this peculiar patient category. Specifically,<lb/> we aimed to assess the influence of diverse de-<lb/>mographic characteristics, comorbidities, underlying<lb/> malignancies, and vaccination status on mortality rates<lb/> and disease severity.<lb/></p>

        <head>Methods<lb/></head>

        <head>Study design, patients and procedures<lb/></head>

        <p>Participating institutions (n = 152) from 41 countries<lb/> (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S1</ref>) documented COVID-19 epi-<lb/>sodes diagnosed between January 1, 2020, and<lb/> December 31, 2022 in patients with hematological ma-<lb/>lignancies in the EPICOVIDEHA registry, accessible at<lb/> www.clinicalsurveys.net (EFS Fall 2022, TIVIAN,<lb/> Cologne,<lb/> Germany),<lb/> including<lb/> both<lb/> already<lb/> described <ref type="biblio">2,7,8,10,11,13,19-33</ref> and undescribed patients. EPI-<lb/>COVIDEHA (National Clinical Trials Identifier,<lb/></p>

        <head>Research in context<lb/></head>

        <head>Evidence before this study<lb/></head>

        <p>Prior to this study, existing research had shed light on the<lb/> risks posed by COVID-19 to hematological malignancy<lb/> patients. Historical data from past pandemics, indicated that<lb/> individuals with hematological malignancies were particularly<lb/> susceptible to severe disease and elevated mortality rates.<lb/> Early in the COVID-19 pandemic, hematological malignancy<lb/> patients faced substantial challenges, with higher<lb/> hospitalization rates and poorer outcomes. Furthermore, the<lb/> emergence of SARS-CoV-2 variants and potential waning<lb/> vaccine efficacy raised concerns about the ongoing<lb/> vulnerability of this population.<lb/></p>

        <head>Added value of this study<lb/></head>

        <p>This study advances our understanding of COVID-19<lb/> outcomes in hematological malignancy patients by analyzing<lb/> data spanning from 2020 to 2022, encompassing the<lb/> transition from pandemic to epidemic phases. Leveraging a<lb/> vast dataset from 152 institutions across 41 countries<lb/> through the EPICOVIDEHA registry, this research provides a<lb/> comprehensive examination of risk factors, disease severity,<lb/> and mortality rates. Notably, it highlights the critical role of<lb/> vaccination and early therapeutic interventions, including<lb/> targeted antivirals and monoclonal antibodies, in improving<lb/> prognosis. The study&apos;s insights into the evolving landscape of<lb/> hematological malignancies and the effectiveness of various<lb/> treatment strategies contribute vital knowledge to guide<lb/> clinical decision-making.<lb/></p>

        <head>Implications of all the available evidence<lb/></head>

        <p>Collectively, the available evidence, including findings from<lb/> this study, underscores the ongoing challenges faced by<lb/> hematological malignancy patients in managing COVID-19.<lb/> Despite the transition from pandemic to epidemic phases, this<lb/> population remains at risk due to their compromised immune<lb/> systems. The implications of this evidence emphasize the<lb/> need for continued vigilance, personalized care, and the<lb/> optimization of vaccination strategies, including booster<lb/> doses. Additionally, the study&apos;s findings underscore the<lb/> significance of early therapeutic interventions and tailored<lb/> treatment approaches based on vaccination status and<lb/> disease severity. As the COVID-19 situation continues to<lb/> evolve, healthcare providers must remain adaptable,<lb/> leveraging the latest evidence to deliver the highest quality<lb/> care to hematological malignancy patients. It is worth noting<lb/> that, even though three years have elapsed since the onset of<lb/> the pandemic, randomized studies in hematology patients<lb/> with COVID-19 are still lacking. Therefore, it is crucial to<lb/> exercise caution with data interpretation as there may be<lb/> aspects where we continue to make errors.<lb/> NCT04733729) is an international open web-based reg-<lb/>istry dedicated to adult hematological malignancy pa-<lb/>tients infected with SARS-CoV-2, set by part of the<lb/> European Hematology Association Specialized Working<lb/> Group (EHA-SWG) Infections in Hematology. <ref type="biblio">30</ref> The<lb/> registry was approved by the local ethics committee of<lb/> the Fondazione Policlinico Universitario Agostino<lb/> Gemelli, IRCCS, Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore of<lb/> Rome, Italy (Study ID: 3226), and was also approved by<lb/> the respective local ethics committees of each partici-<lb/>pating institution if required.<lb/></p>

        <p>To be included in the study, patients had to meet<lb/> certain criteria: they must have had an active hemato-<lb/>logical malignancy within the past 5 years before their<lb/> COVID-19 diagnosis, be aged 18 years or older, have a<lb/> laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection (either by<lb/> polymerase chain reaction [PCR] or rapid antigen test<lb/> kits), and have received a COVID-19 diagnosis between<lb/> January 1, 2020, and December 31, 2022. Patients with<lb/> solid tumors or non-malignant hematological disorders,<lb/> including aplastic anemia, children, patients off-therapy<lb/> or cured for longer than 5 years before COVID-19<lb/> diagnosis or those with only an imaging procedure-<lb/>based COVID-19 diagnosis were excluded from<lb/> analysis. Data collected for each patient encompassed<lb/> baseline conditions before COVID-19, such as age,<lb/> biological sex, hematological malignancy status at<lb/> COVID-19 diagnosis, and COVID-19 predisposing fac-<lb/>tors. Additionally, details regarding hematological ma-<lb/>lignancy clinical management (i.e., malignancy status,<lb/> type of last malignancy treatment immediately before<lb/> COVID-19 diagnosis), and COVID-19 diagnosis, symp-<lb/>tomatology, prophylaxis and treatments (including type<lb/> number of anti-SARS-CoV-2 vaccines at COVID-19<lb/> onset and anti-SARS-CoV-2 treatment strategies), and<lb/> outcomes (including mortality and last follow-up date)<lb/> were recorded. The status of hematological malignancy<lb/> at COVID-19 onset was categorized as active (onset and<lb/> refractory/resistant), stable disease, or controlled (com-<lb/>plete and partial response) based on reports from the<lb/> participating institutions. Additionally, patients were<lb/> graded based on the severity of their COVID-19 epi-<lb/>sodes as asymptomatic, mild, severe and critical as<lb/> previously defined. <ref type="biblio">34<lb/></ref> To ensure data coherence and completeness, all pa-<lb/>tients were included in a validation process conducted<lb/> by experts in hematological malignancy and infectious<lb/> diseases. During this process, efforts were made to<lb/> reduce data missing completely at random by contacting<lb/> contributors to resolve pending queries. This validation<lb/> process was crucial for maintaining the reliability and<lb/> integrity of the data collected from the EPICOVIDEHA<lb/> registry. <ref type="biblio">30</ref> If a certain variable had missing data among<lb/> valid cases and was included in regression analyses,<lb/> those patients were also excluded from the analysis.<lb/> Nevertheless, sensitivity analyses were performed<lb/> applying the following methods: series mean, linear<lb/> interpolation, and linear trend at point.<lb/></p>

        <head>Study objectives<lb/></head>

        <p>The primary objective of the study was to analyze the<lb/> epidemiology and outcomes of hematological malig-<lb/>nancy patients affected by COVID-19 during the period<lb/> 2020-2022. Secondary objectives included estimating<lb/> the relative frequency of disease severity, evaluating the<lb/> relative frequency of intensive care unit (ICU) admis-<lb/>sion among participating patients, assessing the overall<lb/> case-fatality rate, exploring the effect of cancer treatment<lb/> phase on patient outcomes, investigating the impact of<lb/> vaccine doses administered on patient outcomes, and<lb/> studying the effect of COVID-19 treatment on patient<lb/> outcomes.<lb/></p>

        <head>Statistical analysis<lb/></head>

        <p>An a priori sample size calculation was not performed<lb/> as the study was exploratory in nature. Data from<lb/> participating institutions were summarized using fre-<lb/>quencies and percentages for categorical variables, and<lb/> median, interquartile range (IQR), and absolute range<lb/> for continuous variables. A univariable Cox regression<lb/> model was employed to analyze variables suspected to<lb/> influence the mortality of hematological malignancy<lb/> patients with COVID-19. Variables with a p value ≤ 0.1<lb/> were considered for multivariable analysis, after con-<lb/>firming their clinical relevance. The multivariable Cox<lb/> regression model was calculated using the Wald back-<lb/>ward method. The multivariable Cox regression model<lb/> was constructed using backward elimination with the<lb/> Wald test for variable selection. Exclusion criteria were<lb/> established a priori, guided by a predetermined statis-<lb/>tical significance threshold (p value ≤ 0.05). This<lb/> approach retained variables that significantly contrib-<lb/>uted to the model. Mortality was analyzed using Kaplan-<lb/>Meier survival plots, and a log-rank test was used to<lb/> compare the survival probability of patients included in<lb/> different models. The Cox proportional hazards model<lb/> was applied to analyze variables influencing the mor-<lb/>tality of hematological malignancy patients with<lb/> COVID-19. Assumptions of the model were rigorously<lb/> assessed: tests for proportional hazards (Schoenfeld re-<lb/>sidual test) were conducted to verify the assumption of<lb/> hazard functions&apos; proportionality across strata, and<lb/> scatterplots and diagnostic tools were utilized to confirm<lb/> the linearity of the relationship between the log hazard<lb/> and each covariate (Plot martingale residuals). We<lb/> employed Cox regression analysis to assess the associ-<lb/>ation between various covariates and the survival time of<lb/> patients. The following variables were included in the<lb/> multivariable Cox regression model: sex, age, comor-<lb/>bidities, baseline malignancy, malignancy status at<lb/> COVID-19 diagnosis, vaccine doses before COVID-19,<lb/> COVID-19 diagnosis time periods, COVID-19<lb/> symptoms at onset, and stay during COVID-19 episode.<lb/> To account for the potential issue of multiple compari-<lb/>sons, we applied the Bonferroni correction. This<lb/> correction involved adjusting the significance level for<lb/> each individual test to maintain an overall family-wise<lb/> error rate. Specifically, we divided the desired overall<lb/> significance level (p = 0.05) by the number of tests<lb/> conducted. The adjusted significance level was calcu-<lb/>lated as 0.05/9, where 9 represents the number of var-<lb/>iables tested. Therefore, p-values less than 0.0056 were<lb/> considered statistically significant after Bonferroni<lb/> correction. Additionally, we reported Hazard Ratios<lb/> (HR) and 95% Confidence Intervals (CI) to quantify the<lb/> strength and precision of associations. A p value ≤ 0.05<lb/> was considered statistically significant. The statistical<lb/> analyses were conducted using SPSS version 25.0<lb/> (SPSS, IBM Corp, Chicago, IL, United States).<lb/></p>

        <head>Ethics statement<lb/></head>

        <p>The central ethics committee is at Fondazione Policli-<lb/>nico Universitario Agostino Gemelli -IRCCS, Uni-<lb/>versità Cattolica del Sacro Cuore of Rome, Italy (Study<lb/> ID: 3226). Additionally, each participating institution<lb/> may also have a local approval for the research initiative<lb/> as appropriate. The anonymized data that do not contain<lb/> any personally identifiable information from any sour-<lb/>ces implies that the informed consent is not applicable.<lb/></p>

        <head>Role of the funding source<lb/></head>

        <p>This research did not receive any funding. JSG, FM, LP,<lb/> and OAC had access to and verified all raw data sets and<lb/> made the decision to submit the manuscript. The cor-<lb/>responding author can provide the data supporting the<lb/> findings of this study upon a reasonable request.<lb/></p>

        <head>Results<lb/></head>

        <p>Out of the 9416 COVID-19 episodes diagnosed between<lb/> January 1, 2020, and December 31, 2022 and docu-<lb/>mented in the EPICOVIDEHA registry, 8767 were set<lb/> valid and included to analysis. Out of the 649 cases set<lb/> invalid, 179 patients had non-malignant hematological<lb/> disorders or solid tumors, 135 patients were excluded as<lb/> their diagnosis of COVID-19 was based on clinical<lb/> criteria rather than laboratory confirmation, 93 patients<lb/> had hematological malignancies diagnosed longer than<lb/> six months after contracting COVID-19, 87 patients had<lb/> been off therapy for more than 5 years, 86 cases were<lb/> removed due to incomplete information, 55 patients<lb/> were below the age of 18, and 14 cases had double<lb/> entries.<lb/></p>

        <p>The overall sample included 8767 patients, with<lb/> nearly 60% (n = 5119) being male. The median age was<lb/> 65 years (IQR: 54-75); the youngest patient was 18, and<lb/> the oldest was 106, with majority of patients (79.6%,<lb/> n = 6975) older than 50 years. Age groups showed sta-<lb/>tistically significant differences in mortality rates<lb/> (p &lt; 0.0001) (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, Supplementary Tables <ref type="table">S1-S6</ref>).<lb/> Regarding comorbidities, 70.8% (n = 6205) of the pa-<lb/>tients had 0-1 comorbidities, with a significantly lower<lb/> mortality rate as compared to those with 2 or more<lb/> comorbidities (p &lt; 0.0001). The most common comor-<lb/>bidities observed were chronic cardiopathy (35.3%,<lb/> n = 3095), diabetes mellitus (14.5%, n = 1268), and<lb/> chronic pulmonary disease (13.2%, n = 1157)<lb/> (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S2A</ref>). As for the underlying ma-<lb/>lignancies, non-Hodgkin lymphoma (31.2%, n = 2731)<lb/> and plasma cells disorders (17.6%, n = 1546) were the<lb/> most prevalent (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S2B</ref>). However,<lb/> myelodysplastic syndrome (21.2%, n = 121/572), acute<lb/> leukemia (19.0%, n = 280/1475), and chronic lymphoid<lb/> leukemia (18.1%, n = 210/1163) exhibited the highest<lb/> mortality rates, all of which were statistically significant<lb/> (p &lt; 0.0001) (Fig. <ref type="figure">1A</ref>). Almost half of the patients<lb/> (47.1%, n = 4131) had controlled malignancy. Among<lb/> them, patients with controlled malignancy (10.2%,<lb/> n = 420/4131) and stable malignancy (13.6%, n = 230/<lb/> 1688) experienced lower mortality rates compared to<lb/> those with active malignancy (25.5%, n = 676/2646),<lb/> p &lt; 0.0001 (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B</ref>, Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, Supplementary Tables <ref type="table">S1-<lb/>S6</ref>). Regarding the vaccination status against SARS-<lb/>CoV-2, 64.5% (n = 5658) of patients were unvaccinated<lb/> as they were diagnosed with COVID-19 before the<lb/> availability of the first vaccines, and this cohort exhibited<lb/> the highest mortality rate at 20.8%.<lb/></p>

        <p>Mortality rates decreased with an increasing number<lb/> of anti-SARS-CoV-2 vaccine doses administered before<lb/> COVID-19 diagnosis (1 dose: 10.3%, n = 22/214; 5<lb/> doses: 0.0%, n = 0/23), with a statistically significant<lb/> difference (p &lt; 0.001) (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, Supplementary<lb/> Tables <ref type="table">S1-S6</ref>). Six in ten patients (60.0%, n = 5263)<lb/> experienced pulmonary symptoms at the onset of<lb/> COVID-19. Overall, 36.5% (n = 3197) of patients had<lb/> asymptomatic or mild infection (Fig. <ref type="figure">2A</ref>). One third of<lb/> the patients (35.2%, n = 3084) were managed at home,<lb/> while 64.8% (n = 5683) were admitted to the hospital at<lb/> any point during COVID-19. Among the hospitalized<lb/> patients, 16.1% required admission to the ICU (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>,<lb/> Supplementary Tables <ref type="table">S1-S6</ref>). The overall 30-day mor-<lb/>tality rate was 16.1% (n = 1415/8767, Fig. <ref type="figure">2B</ref>), with<lb/> COVID-19 being associated with mortality in 89.8% of<lb/> these cases (Fig. <ref type="figure">2C</ref>, Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, Supplementary<lb/> Tables <ref type="table">S1-S6</ref>). The following factors linked to<lb/> increased mortality: a) older age (aHR 1.037, 95% CI<lb/> 1.032-1.042, p &lt; 0.0001), b) 2 or more comorbidities at<lb/> COVID-19 onset (aHR 1.244, 95% CI 1.117-1.386,<lb/> p &lt; 0.0001), c) active malignancy (aHR 1.832, 95% CI<lb/> 1.617-2.075, p &lt; 0.0001), d) pulmonary symptoms at<lb/> COVID-19 onset, either alone (aHR 1.299, 95% CI<lb/> 1.095-1.541, p = 0.0026) or in combination with<lb/> extrapulmonary symptoms (aHR 1.168, 95% CI<lb/> 0.978-1.396, p = 0.08), and e) hospitalized patients<lb/> without ICU (aHR 12.767, 95% CI 8.723-18.684,<lb/> p &lt; 0.0001) and patients admitted to the ICU (aHR<lb/></p>

        <figure type="table">Total<lb/> Alive<lb/> Dead<lb/> p value<lb/> n<lb/> %<lb/> n<lb/> %<lb/> n<lb/> %<lb/> Sex<lb/> 0.08<lb/> Female<lb/> 3648<lb/> 41.6<lb/> 3089<lb/> 84.7<lb/> 559<lb/> 15.3<lb/> Male<lb/> 5119<lb/> 58.4<lb/> 4263<lb/> 83.3<lb/> 856<lb/> 16.7<lb/> Age<lb/> 65 (54-75)<lb/> [18-106]<lb/> 64 (52-73)<lb/> [18-97]<lb/> 73 (63-80)<lb/> [18-106]<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 18-25 years old<lb/> 268<lb/> 3.1<lb/> 244<lb/> 91.0<lb/> 24<lb/> 9.0<lb/> 26-50 years old<lb/> 1524<lb/> 17.4<lb/> 1411<lb/> 92.6<lb/> 113<lb/> 7.4<lb/> 51-69 years old<lb/> 3517<lb/> 40.1<lb/> 3094<lb/> 88.0<lb/> 423<lb/> 12.0<lb/> &gt;69 years old<lb/> 3458<lb/> 39.4<lb/> 2603<lb/> 75.3<lb/> 855<lb/> 24.7<lb/> Comorbidities at COVID-19 onset<lb/> 0-1 comorbidities<lb/> 6205<lb/> 70.8<lb/> 5401<lb/> 87.0<lb/> 804<lb/> 13.0<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 2+ comorbidities<lb/> 2562<lb/> 29.2<lb/> 1951<lb/> 76.2<lb/> 611<lb/> 23.8<lb/> Chronic cardiopathy<lb/> 3095<lb/> 35.3<lb/> 2422<lb/> 78.3<lb/> 673<lb/> 21.7<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Chronic pulmonary disease<lb/> 1157<lb/> 13.2<lb/> 892<lb/> 77.1<lb/> 265<lb/> 22.9<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Diabetes mellitus<lb/> 1268<lb/> 14.5<lb/> 979<lb/> 77.2<lb/> 289<lb/> 22.8<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Liver disease<lb/> 355<lb/> 4.0<lb/> 267<lb/> 75.2<lb/> 88<lb/> 24.8<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Renal impairment<lb/> 648<lb/> 7.4<lb/> 456<lb/> 70.4<lb/> 192<lb/> 29.6<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Smoking history<lb/> 978<lb/> 11.2<lb/> 781<lb/> 79.9<lb/> 197<lb/> 20.1<lb/> 0.00031<lb/> Baseline hematological malignancy<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Hodgkin lymphoma<lb/> 354<lb/> 4.0<lb/> 328<lb/> 92.7<lb/> 26<lb/> 7.3<lb/> Chronic lymphoid leukemia<lb/> 1163<lb/> 13.3<lb/> 953<lb/> 81.9<lb/> 210<lb/> 18.1<lb/> Acute leukemia<lb/> 1475<lb/> 16.8<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 280<lb/> 19.0<lb/> Acute myeloid leukemia<lb/> 1060<lb/> 12.1<lb/> 824<lb/> 77.7<lb/> 236<lb/> 22.3<lb/> Acute lymphoid leukemia<lb/> 415<lb/> 4.7<lb/> 371<lb/> 89.4<lb/> 44<lb/> 10.6<lb/> Non-Hodgkin lymphoma<lb/> 2731<lb/> 31.2<lb/> 2315<lb/> 84.8<lb/> 416<lb/> 15.2<lb/> Chronic myeloid malignancies<lb/> 867<lb/> 9.9<lb/> 780<lb/> 90.0<lb/> 87<lb/> 10.0<lb/> Chronic myeloid leukemia<lb/> 334<lb/> 3.8<lb/> 313<lb/> 93.7<lb/> 21<lb/> 6.3<lb/> Essential thrombocythemia<lb/> 142<lb/> 1.6<lb/> 131<lb/> 92.3<lb/> 11<lb/> 7.7<lb/> Myelofibrosis<lb/> 233<lb/> 2.7<lb/> 190<lb/> 81.5<lb/> 43<lb/> 18.5<lb/> Polycythemia vera<lb/> 134<lb/> 1.5<lb/> 123<lb/> 91.8<lb/> 11<lb/> 8.2<lb/> Systemic mastocytosis<lb/> 24<lb/> 0.3<lb/> 23<lb/> 95.8<lb/> 1<lb/> 4.2<lb/> Plasma cell disorders<lb/> 1546<lb/> 17.6<lb/> 1281<lb/> 82.9<lb/> 265<lb/> 17.1<lb/> Multiple myeloma<lb/> 1513<lb/> 17.3<lb/> 1249<lb/> 82.6<lb/> 264<lb/> 17.4<lb/> Amyloid light-chain amyloidosis<lb/> 33<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 32<lb/> 97.0<lb/> 1<lb/> 3.0<lb/> Myelodysplastic syndrome<lb/> 572<lb/> 6.5<lb/> 451<lb/> 78.8<lb/> 121<lb/> 21.2<lb/> Hairy cell leukemia<lb/> 59<lb/> 0.7<lb/> 49<lb/> 83.1<lb/> 10<lb/> 16.9<lb/> Baseline hematological malignancy status at COVID-19 onset<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Controlled malignancy<lb/> 4131<lb/> 47.1<lb/> 3711<lb/> 89.8<lb/> 420<lb/> 10.2<lb/> Complete remission<lb/> 2717<lb/> 31.0<lb/> 2502<lb/> 92.1<lb/> 215<lb/> 7.9<lb/> Partial remission<lb/> 1414<lb/> 16.1<lb/> 1209<lb/> 85.5<lb/> 205<lb/> 14.5<lb/> Stable malignancy<lb/> 1688<lb/> 19.3<lb/> 1458<lb/> 86.4<lb/> 230<lb/> 13.6<lb/> Active malignancy<lb/> 2646<lb/> 30.2<lb/> 1970<lb/> 74.5<lb/> 676<lb/> 25.5<lb/> Onset<lb/> 1553<lb/> 17.7<lb/> 1195<lb/> 76.9<lb/> 358<lb/> 23.1<lb/> Refractory/Resistant<lb/> 1093<lb/> 12.5<lb/> 775<lb/> 70.9<lb/> 318<lb/> 29.1<lb/> Unknown<lb/> 302<lb/> 3.4<lb/> 213<lb/> 70.5<lb/> 89<lb/> 29.5<lb/> SARS-CoV-2 vaccination at COVID-19 onset<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0 doses<lb/> 5658<lb/> 64.5<lb/> 4480<lb/> 79.2<lb/> 1178<lb/> 20.8<lb/> 1-2 doses<lb/> 1328<lb/> 15.1<lb/> 1192<lb/> 89.8<lb/> 136<lb/> 10.2<lb/> 1 dose<lb/> 214<lb/> 2.4<lb/> 192<lb/> 89.7<lb/> 22<lb/> 10.3<lb/> 2 doses<lb/> 1114<lb/> 12.7<lb/> 1000<lb/> 89.8<lb/> 114<lb/> 10.2<lb/> (Table 1 continues on next page)<lb/></figure>

        <p>33.684, 95% CI 22.915-49.514, p &lt; 0.0001). On the other<lb/> hand, certain factors were associated with reduced<lb/> mortality, such as: a) vaccination with 1-2 doses (aHR<lb/> 0.681, 95% CI 0.546-0.850, p &lt; 0.00066) or with 3 or<lb/> more (aHR 0.451, 95% CI 0.35-0.582, p &lt; 0.0001), b)<lb/> COVID-19 diagnosis later in the pandemic, specifically<lb/> between July-December 2020 (aHR 0.802, 95% CI<lb/> 0.701-0.917, p &lt; 0.0012), January-June 2021 (aHR<lb/> 0.796, 95% CI 0.662-0.958, p = 0.015) and July-<lb/>December 2022 (aHR 0.427, 95% CI 0.282-0.647,<lb/> p &lt; 0.000059) (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). Sensitivity analyses were con-<lb/>ducted to address the absence of data on observation<lb/> days from certain patients. The outcomes obtained<lb/> showed consistency and endorsed identical variables as<lb/> either risk or protective factors, in alignment with the<lb/> aforementioned paragraph. Comprehensive results can<lb/> be found in Supplementary Tables <ref type="table">S7-S9</ref>.<lb/></p>

        <head>Changes over time<lb/></head>

        <p>During the study period from 2020 to 2022, the patient<lb/> distribution in terms of sex, age group, number of<lb/> comorbidities (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S2A</ref>), and malig-<lb/>nancy status at COVID-19 onset or last malignancy<lb/> treatment remained stable (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S2C</ref>).<lb/> Non-Hodgkin lymphoma exhibited stability, while there<lb/> was an observed rise in the prevalence of plasma cell<lb/> disorders, along with acute leukemia. Conversely, mye-<lb/>lodysplastic syndrome and chronic myeloid malig-<lb/>nancies demonstrated a decline (Supplementary<lb/> Fig. <ref type="figure">S2B</ref>). Moreover, there was an increase in the<lb/> number of vaccinated patients, those not requiring<lb/> hospitalization and managing their condition at home<lb/> during the COVID-19 episode (Supplementary<lb/> Tables <ref type="table">S1-S6</ref>). Alongside this, there was a notable<lb/> reduction in the severity of COVID-19 cases (Fig. <ref type="figure">2A</ref>,<lb/> Supplementary Tables <ref type="table">S1-S6</ref>).<lb/></p>

        <p>A decline in COVID-19-related mortality across all<lb/> severity degrees was observed (Supplementary<lb/> Tables <ref type="table">S1-S6</ref>), as well as in all-cause mortality<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">2B</ref>). Furthermore, this decrease in mortality was<lb/> evident when considering type of baseline malignancy<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">2A</ref>), malignancy treatment (Fig. <ref type="figure">1C</ref>), malignancy<lb/> status at COVID-19 onset (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B</ref>), and the cause of<lb/> death (Fig. <ref type="figure">2C</ref>). Among causes of death there was a<lb/> decrease in the influence of COVID-19-related factors<lb/> and a corresponding increase in the impact of hemato-<lb/>logical malignancy. This reduction in mortality rates was<lb/> evident in the overall analysis but was more limited for<lb/> in-hospital and critical patients.<lb/></p>

        <p>Moreover, the study demonstrated a significant in-<lb/>crease in the likelihood of surviving up to day 30 after<lb/> being diagnosed with COVID-19, especially for patients<lb/></p>

        <figure type="table">Total<lb/> Alive<lb/> Dead<lb/> p value<lb/> n<lb/> %<lb/> n<lb/> %<lb/> n<lb/> %<lb/> (Continued from previous page)<lb/> 3+ doses<lb/> 1781<lb/> 20.3<lb/> 1680<lb/> 94.3<lb/> 101<lb/> 5.7<lb/> 3 doses<lb/> 1484<lb/> 16.9<lb/> 1391<lb/> 93.7<lb/> 93<lb/> 6.3<lb/> 4 doses<lb/> 274<lb/> 3.1<lb/> 266<lb/> 97.1<lb/> 8<lb/> 2.9<lb/> 5 doses<lb/> 23<lb/> 0.3<lb/> 23<lb/> 100.0<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.0<lb/> COVID-19 symptoms at onset<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Screening<lb/> 1787<lb/> 20.4<lb/> 1605<lb/> 89.8<lb/> 182<lb/> 10.2<lb/> Extrapulmonary only<lb/> 1717<lb/> 19.6<lb/> 1554<lb/> 90.5<lb/> 163<lb/> 9.5<lb/> Extrapulmonary + pulmonary<lb/> 2237<lb/> 25.5<lb/> 1781<lb/> 79.6<lb/> 456<lb/> 20.4<lb/> Pulmonary only<lb/> 3026<lb/> 34.5<lb/> 2412<lb/> 79.7<lb/> 614<lb/> 20.3<lb/> COVID-19-episode severity<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Asymptomatic<lb/> 1546<lb/> 17.6<lb/> 1442<lb/> 93.3<lb/> 104<lb/> 6.7<lb/> Mild infection<lb/> 1651<lb/> 18.8<lb/> 1545<lb/> 93.6<lb/> 106<lb/> 6.4<lb/> Severe infection<lb/> 4291<lb/> 48.9<lb/> 3655<lb/> 85.2<lb/> 636<lb/> 14.8<lb/> Critical infection<lb/> 1279<lb/> 14.6<lb/> 710<lb/> 55.5<lb/> 569<lb/> 44.5<lb/> Stay during COVID-19<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> Home<lb/> 3084<lb/> 35.2<lb/> 3056<lb/> 99.1<lb/> 28<lb/> 0.9<lb/> Hospital no ICU<lb/> 4404<lb/> 50.2<lb/> 3586<lb/> 81.4<lb/> 818<lb/> 18.6<lb/> Hospital ICU<lb/> 1279<lb/> 14.6<lb/> 710<lb/> 55.5<lb/> 569<lb/> 44.5<lb/> Mortality, d30<lb/> 1415<lb/> 16.1<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 1415<lb/> 100.0<lb/> Reason for mortality<lb/> COVID-19<lb/> 904<lb/> 10.3<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 904<lb/> 63.9<lb/> COVID-19 + hematological malignancy<lb/> 367<lb/> 4.2<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 367<lb/> 25.9<lb/> Hematological malignancies ± other reasons<lb/> 144<lb/> 1.6<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 144<lb/> 10.2<lb/> COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019; ICU, intensive care unit; SARS-CoV-2, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2.<lb/> Table 1: Characteristics of EPICOVIDEHA 2020-2022 patients.<lb/></figure>

        <figure>Fig. 1: EPICOVIDEHA 2020-2022 patients: mortality per baseline malignancy, malignancy status at COVID-19 onset, and last malignancy<lb/> treatment. A) 2020-2022 mortality per baseline malignancy. B) 2020-2022 mortality per malignancy status at COVID-19 onset. C) 2020-2022<lb/> mortality per last malignancy treatmentAllo, allogeneic; auto, autologous; CAR-T, chimeric antigen T cell receptors; HSCT, hematopoietic stem<lb/> cell transplantation.<lb/></figure>

        <p>who received their diagnosis later in the pandemic<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">3A</ref>). Vaccinated individuals also had considerably<lb/> higher survival rates when compared to the unvacci-<lb/>nated (Fig. <ref type="figure">3B</ref>). This increase in survival probability was<lb/> notable regardless of initial malignancy status<lb/> (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S3A</ref>), or setting during their<lb/> COVID-19 episode at home, in hospital, or ICU<lb/> (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S3B</ref>).<lb/> The impact of COVID-19 treatment on survival was<lb/> substantial. For unvaccinated patients, those with the<lb/> highest likelihood of survival were either those who did<lb/> not require any COVID-19 treatment or those who<lb/> received monoclonal antibodies alone or in combination<lb/> with antiviral medications (Fig. <ref type="figure">3C</ref>). Among patients<lb/> who had received 1-2 vaccine doses, highest survival<lb/> probability was with no treatment required or treatment<lb/> involving monoclonal antibodies and antivirals alone or<lb/> in combination (Fig. <ref type="figure">3D</ref>). Finally, for patients who had<lb/> received 3 or more vaccinations, various treatment op-<lb/>tions showed varying degrees of effectiveness, except for<lb/> corticosteroids alone (Fig. <ref type="figure">3E</ref>).<lb/></p>

        <head>Discussion<lb/></head>

        <p>This manuscript, encompassing data from 2020 to 2022,<lb/> aims to shed light on the significant impact of COVID-<lb/>19 on hematological malignancy patients, with a<lb/> particular emphasis on mortality, which was specifically<lb/> pronounced in the year 2020. The study uncovers<lb/> several critical factors that influence negatively COVID-<lb/>19 outcomes in this patient population, with age,<lb/> comorbidities, and malignancy status emerging as key<lb/> risk factors for mortality. In contrast, the introduction of<lb/> COVID-19 vaccines and the progression of the<lb/> pandemic into later phases, leading to improved pre-<lb/>ventive and targeted treatment options, heightened<lb/> awareness, earlier treatment initiation, and a broader<lb/> knowledge base overall, are associated with reduced<lb/> mortality. Additionally, the study delves into the<lb/> evolving landscape of hematological malignancies most<lb/> closely linked to COVID-19 occurrences, revealing dy-<lb/>namic shifts in prevalence that necessitate adaptable<lb/> treatment strategies to address emerging challenges.<lb/> These findings underscore the significance of tailored<lb/> care, ongoing monitoring, and flexibility in managing<lb/> patients with hematological malignancies in the ever-<lb/>evolving context of COVID-19.<lb/></p>

        <p>The evolving landscape of hematological malig-<lb/>nancies presents a noteworthy development. While the<lb/> number of reported COVID-19 cases in non-Hodgkin<lb/> lymphoma patients remained consistent over time,<lb/> there was an increase in reported cases among in-<lb/>dividuals with plasma cell disorders and acute leukemia.<lb/> Conversely, the number of cases in patients with mye-<lb/>lodysplastic syndrome and chronic myeloid malig-<lb/>nancies decreased. These shifts underscore the<lb/> importance of continuously adapting treatment strate-<lb/>gies to address new challenges and devising personal-<lb/>ized approaches to manage patients with hematological<lb/> malignancies during a pandemic. Taken together, these<lb/> data reveal an overall predominance of COVID-19 di-<lb/>agnoses among patients with lymphoid malignancies<lb/></p>

        <figure>Fig. 1: Continued<lb/></figure>

      <p>throughout the years. This could potentially be attrib-<lb/>uted to the well-documented lower efficacy of anti-<lb/>SARS-CoV-2 vaccines and their reduced development<lb/> of immunity in this patient population. <ref type="biblio">7,9,14</ref><lb/></p>

        <p>The most encouraging findings center around the<lb/> effects of COVID-19 vaccination and treatment strate-<lb/>gies. During the research period, vaccination emerged<lb/> as a significant approach in mitigating the severity of<lb/></p>

        <figure>Fig. 2: EPICOVIDEHA 2020-2022 patients: COVID-19 severity prevalence and mortality rate, overall mortality rate, mortality per malignancy<lb/> status at COVID-19 onset, and mortality per reason for mortality. A) 2020-2022 COVID-19 severity prevalence. B) 2020-2022 mortality rate<lb/> overall. C) 2020-2022 mortality rate per reason for mortality. COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019. *Arrows in this figure indicate the date when<lb/> the respective medical product was made available for the very first time in the world. This is applicable to some of the contributing institutions,<lb/> not to them all.<lb/></figure>

        <p>COVID-19, even in patients with hematological malig-<lb/>nancies. <ref type="biblio">7</ref> Although it was not possible to establish<lb/> complete immunity due to data limitations, the data did<lb/> indicate a dose-response relationship. Patients who had<lb/> received a greater number of vaccine doses before being<lb/> diagnosed with COVID-19 experienced significantly<lb/> lower mortality rates, affirming the findings from our<lb/> initial report. <ref type="biblio">31</ref> This underscores the importance of<lb/> vaccination programs and booster doses in offering the<lb/> utmost protection to this highly vulnerable group.<lb/> Additionally, early therapeutic strategies, particularly the<lb/> use of targeted antivirals and monoclonal antibodies,<lb/> were crucial in enhancing patient outcomes. <ref type="biblio">35-37</ref> These<lb/> early treatments not only reduced the severity of the<lb/> illness but also led to decreased mortality rates. <ref type="biblio">10,11,18<lb/></ref> The study also revealed a notable decline in the<lb/> severity of COVID-19 cases as time progressed. This<lb/> trend aligns with the broader context of the pandemic,<lb/> where advancements in treatment, including the early<lb/> administration of drugs, and the implementation of<lb/> prophylaxis and vaccine programs ultimately led to<lb/> milder cases. <ref type="biblio">38</ref> The reduction in COVID-19 mortality<lb/> across various severity levels, all-cause mortality, and<lb/> factors contributing to mortality is a testament to the<lb/> collaborative efforts of the medical community. Patients<lb/> have reaped the rewards of enhanced treatments and<lb/> more effective supportive care, as healthcare pro-<lb/>fessionals have become increasingly skilled at early<lb/> detection and intervention. These trends underscore the<lb/> adaptability and resilience of the medical community in<lb/> the midst of a rapidly evolving health crisis.<lb/></p>

        <p>Nonetheless, it is important to remain vigilant, as the<lb/> severity levels in hematological malignancy patients are<lb/> still elevated compared to the general population.<lb/></p>

        <p>One of the most striking findings in the dataset is the<lb/> increase in survival probability at day 30 following a<lb/> COVID-19 diagnosis. Patients diagnosed later in the<lb/> pandemic showed notably higher survival rates. Vacci-<lb/>nated individuals also exhibited significantly improved<lb/> survival rates. This proves that not only have medical<lb/> approaches advanced, but patient outcomes have<lb/> benefited from the accumulation of clinical experience<lb/> and learning over time. Moreover, the impact of<lb/> COVID-19-specific treatments on survival should not be<lb/> underestimated. The study revealed that among unvac-<lb/>cinated patients, those who received monoclonal anti-<lb/>bodies alone or in combination with antiviral<lb/> medications had the highest likelihood of survival,<lb/> aligning with findings from studies conducted on the<lb/> general population. <ref type="biblio">39</ref> This underscores the importance<lb/> of tailoring treatment options based on vaccination sta-<lb/>tus and the severity of illness of each patient.<lb/></p>

        <p>Despite positive trends and progress, the challenge of<lb/> COVID-19 persists for hematological malignancy pa-<lb/>tients, particularly those who are in-hospital and critically<lb/> ill. While the World Health Organization (WHO) has<lb/> declared the pandemic phase to be over, concerns still<lb/> loom regarding the virus&apos;s tendency to mutate and the<lb/> potential reduction in the effectiveness of preventive<lb/> measures. The EPICOVIDEHA registry has demon-<lb/>strated its value as a valuable tool for surveillance and<lb/> research in this regard. <ref type="biblio">2,7,8,10,11,13,19-21,24-26,28,29,31,33</ref> As the<lb/></p>

        <figure>Fig. 2: Continued.<lb/></figure>

        <figure type="table">Univariable<lb/> Multivariable<lb/> p value<lb/> HR<lb/> 95% CI<lb/> p value<lb/> HR<lb/> 95% CI<lb/> Lower<lb/> Upper<lb/> Lower<lb/> Upper<lb/> Sex<lb/> Female<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Male<lb/> 0.08<lb/> 1.100<lb/> 0.988<lb/> 1.223<lb/> 0.99<lb/> 1.001<lb/> 0.899<lb/> 1.115<lb/> Age<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 1.037<lb/> 1.033<lb/> 1.041<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 1.037<lb/> 1.032<lb/> 1.042<lb/> Comorbidities<lb/> 0-1 comorbidities<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>2+ comorbidities<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 1.917<lb/> 1.726<lb/> 2.130<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 1.244<lb/> 1.117<lb/> 1.386<lb/> Baseline malignancy<lb/> Hodgkin lymphoma<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Chronic lymphoid leukemia<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 2.638<lb/> 1.755<lb/> 3.965<lb/> 0.52<lb/> 0.874<lb/> 0.578<lb/> 1.32<lb/> Acute leukemia<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 2.818<lb/> 1.885<lb/> 4.211<lb/> 0.08<lb/> 1.431<lb/> 0.956<lb/> 2.141<lb/> Non-Hodgkin lymphoma<lb/> 0.00015<lb/> 2.152<lb/> 1.448<lb/> 3.198<lb/> 0.49<lb/> 0.868<lb/> 0.583<lb/> 1.293<lb/> Chronic myeloid malignancies<lb/> 0.12<lb/> 1.417<lb/> 0.914<lb/> 2.196<lb/> 0.20<lb/> 0.747<lb/> 0.479<lb/> 1.163<lb/> Plasma cell disorders<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 2.503<lb/> 1.673<lb/> 3.744<lb/> 0.71<lb/> 1.08<lb/> 0.72<lb/> 1.621<lb/> Myelodysplastic syndrome<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 3.163<lb/> 2.071<lb/> 4.832<lb/> 0.98<lb/> 0.985<lb/> 0.64<lb/> 1.517<lb/> Hairy cell leukemia<lb/> 0.018<lb/> 2.416<lb/> 1.165<lb/> 5.011<lb/> 0.51<lb/> 0.781<lb/> 0.376<lb/> 1.623<lb/> Malignancy status at COVID-19 diagnosis<lb/> Controlled malignancy<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Stable malignancy<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 1.394<lb/> 1.187<lb/> 1.637<lb/> 0.21<lb/> 1.115<lb/> 0.94<lb/> 1.321<lb/> Active malignancy<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 2.731<lb/> 2.418<lb/> 3.085<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 1.832<lb/> 1.617<lb/> 2.075<lb/> Vaccine doses before COVID-19<lb/> 0 doses<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1-2 doses<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0.503<lb/> 0.421<lb/> 0.601<lb/> 0.00067<lb/> 0.681<lb/> 0.546<lb/> 0.850<lb/> 3+ doses<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0.286<lb/> 0.233<lb/> 0.350<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0.451<lb/> 0.35<lb/> 0.582<lb/> COVID-19 diagnosis<lb/> January-June 2020<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>July-December 2020<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0.577<lb/> 0.506<lb/> 0.657<lb/> 0.0012<lb/> 0.802<lb/> 0.701<lb/> 0.917<lb/> January-June 2021<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0.618<lb/> 0.517<lb/> 0.740<lb/> 0.015<lb/> 0.796<lb/> 0.662<lb/> 0.958<lb/> July-December 2021<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0.470<lb/> 0.388<lb/> 0.567<lb/> 0.59<lb/> 0.938<lb/> 0.745<lb/> 1.18<lb/> January-June 2022<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0.322<lb/> 0.273<lb/> 0.381<lb/> 0.08<lb/> 0.833<lb/> 0.679<lb/> 1.021<lb/> July-December 2022<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0.132<lb/> 0.089<lb/> 0.197<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 0.427<lb/> 0.282<lb/> 0.647<lb/> COVID-19 symptoms at onset<lb/> Screening<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Extrapulmonary only<lb/> 0.49<lb/> 0.928<lb/> 0.751<lb/> 1.146<lb/> 0.13<lb/> 0.848<lb/> 0.685<lb/> 1.049<lb/> Extrapulmonary + pulmonary<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 2.131<lb/> 1.794<lb/> 2.530<lb/> 0.09<lb/> 1.168<lb/> 0.978<lb/> 1.396<lb/> Pulmonary only<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 2.149<lb/> 1.821<lb/> 2.535<lb/> 0.0026<lb/> 1.299<lb/> 1.095<lb/> 1.541<lb/> Stay during COVID-19 episode<lb/> Home<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Hospital, no ICU<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 22.360<lb/> 15.342<lb/> 32.589<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 12.767<lb/> 8.723<lb/> 18.684<lb/> Hospital, ICU<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 57.020<lb/> 39.015<lb/> 83.335<lb/> &lt;0.0001<lb/> 33.684<lb/> 22.915<lb/> 49.514<lb/> COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019; HR, hazard ratio; ICU, intensive care unit. After applying the Bonferroni correction, variables with a p &lt; 0.0056 were considered as<lb/> statistically significant. The variables age, comorbidities, malignancy status at COVID-19 diagnosis, vaccine doses before COVID-19, COVID-19 diagnosis (item July-December<lb/> 2020), COVID-19 symptoms at onset, and stay during COVID-19 episode remain significant. Other variables do not reach the adjusted significance level. To address missing<lb/> data, sensitivity analyses were performed. In Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S7</ref> missing values in Days from COVID-19 diagnosis were input with the series mean method, in<lb/> Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S8</ref> missing values in Days from COVID-19 diagnosis were input with the linear interpolation method, and in Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S9</ref> missing values in<lb/> Days from COVID-19 diagnosis were input with the linear trend at point method. Hazard function proportionality over the time t and lineal relationship between the log<lb/> hazard and each covariate in the model depicted in the table have been analyzed and are presented in Supplementary Figs. <ref type="figure">S4-S7</ref>. Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S4</ref> presents the<lb/> proportional hazard evaluation of the variables presented in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. p values for the Schoenfeld residual test are as follows: age p = 0.09 (proportional), baseline malignancy<lb/> p = 0.0057 (non-proportional), month of COVID-19 diagnosis p &lt; 0.0001 (non-proportional), stay during COVID-19 episodes p &lt; 0.0001 (non-proportional), vaccine doses<lb/> before COVID-19 p = 0.0027 (non-proportional), comorbidities p = 0.88 (proportional), COVID-19 symptoms at onset p = 0.0018 (non-proportional), sex p = 0.68<lb/> (proportional), and malignancy status at COVID-19 diagnosis p = 0.11 (proportional). Plot martingale residuals are presented in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S5</ref>. Sensitivity analyses<lb/> were performed for the proportional hazard evaluation, reducing the answer categories presented in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. These are shown in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S6</ref>. p values for the<lb/> Schoenfeld residual test are as follows: age p = 0.09 (proportional), baseline malignancy p = 0.0054 (non-proportional), month of COVID-19 diagnosis p &lt; 0.0001 (non-<lb/>proportional), stay during COVID-19 episodes p &lt; 0.0001 (non-proportional), vaccine doses before COVID-19 p = 0.00071 (non-proportional), comorbidities p = 0.88<lb/> (proportional), COVID-19 symptoms at onset p = 0.00086 (non-proportional), sex p = 0.69 (proportional), and malignancy status at COVID-19 diagnosis p = 0.11<lb/> (proportional). Plot martingale residuals are presented in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S7</ref>.<lb/>Table 2: Factors associated with mortality in EPICOVIDEHA 2020-2022 patients.<lb/></figure>

        <p>virus continues to evolve, vigilance and adaptability are<lb/> of paramount importance. In the midst of a constantly<lb/> shifting landscape, continuous surveillance, research,<lb/> and adaptation will be crucial to ensure that patients with<lb/> hematological malignancies receive the highest quality<lb/> of care. Ongoing monitoring and adjustment of strate-<lb/>gies are needed to address the potential impact of viral<lb/> mutations and any declines in the effectiveness of<lb/></p>

        <figure>Fig. 3: Continued.<lb/></figure>

        <p>preventive measures. The EPICOVIDEHA registry<lb/> stands as a vital tool in this ongoing battle, offering<lb/> valuable insights into the ever-changing landscape of<lb/> COVID-19 in hematological malignancy patients. <ref type="biblio">32<lb/></ref> However, our study has several limitations. Firstly,<lb/> there is the potential for selection bias due to the use of<lb/> retrospective data from specific institutions. Being an<lb/> observational study, the results may be influenced by<lb/> confounding variables and potential reporting bias<lb/> stemming from self-reported data. Factors that vary with<lb/> time and the validation process could also impact the<lb/> findings, and the study&apos;s design makes it difficult to<lb/> establish causation reliably. Additionally, the absence of<lb/> viral sequencing and serological data for all patients may<lb/> limit a comprehensive understanding of patient risk and<lb/> the natural history of infection. Furthermore, the lack of<lb/> specific denominators due to the scarcity of cases hin-<lb/>ders the ability to provide critical information. Further<lb/> analyses should also provide information with this re-<lb/>gard. Additionally, such analyses would also benefit from<lb/> reporting the days between the different vaccine doses<lb/> and the baseline malignancy diagnosis or the existence<lb/> of previous COVID-19 episodes, as this may impact in<lb/> the evolution of the infectious episode, specially in the<lb/> last semesters. Ultimately, the diverse international and<lb/> multicentric approach adopted in this manuscript may<lb/> have introduced variability in the findings. This variation<lb/> could be attributed to differing timelines in the imple-<lb/>mentation of preventive measures, variations in vaccine<lb/> types, discrepancies in diagnostic test performance, or<lb/> even disparities in the availability of treatments for<lb/> COVID-19. It is inherently challenging to determine the<lb/></p>

        <figure>Fig. 3: Continued.<lb/></figure>

        <figure>Fig. 3: EPICOVIDEHA 2020-2022 patients: survival probability per diagnosis semester, vaccination status, and COVID-19 treatment. A)<lb/> 2020-2022 survival probability per semester. This figure has been replicated with the survival probability ranging from 70% to 100% in<lb/> Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S8</ref>. B) 2020-2022 survival probability per vaccine doses before COVID-19. This figure has been replicated with the survival<lb/> probability ranging from 70% to 100% in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S9</ref>. C) 2020-2022 survival probability per vaccine doses before COVID-19 and<lb/> COVID-19 treatment, 0 vaccines. AVs, antivirals; MoABs, monoclonal antibodies. * No treatment includes patients that did not need to receive<lb/> treatment mainly due to lack of symptoms. This figure has been replicated with the survival probability ranging from 70% to 100% in<lb/> Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S10</ref>. D) 2020-2022 survival probability per vaccine doses before COVID-19 and COVID-19 treatment, 1-2 vaccines. AVs,<lb/> antivirals; MoABs, monoclonal antibodies. *No treatment includes patients that did not need to receive treatment mainly due to lack of<lb/> symptoms. This figure has been replicated with the survival probability ranging from 70% to 100% in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S11</ref>. E) 2020-2022<lb/> survival probability per vaccine doses before COVID-19 and COVID-19 treatment, 3+ vaccines. AVs, antivirals; MoABs, monoclonal antibodies.<lb/> *No treatment includes patients that did not need to receive treatment mainly due to lack of symptoms. This figure has been replicated with<lb/> the survival probability ranging from 70% to 100% in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S12</ref>.<lb/></figure>

        <p>number of SARS-CoV-2-infected patients treated at the<lb/> participating institutions who went undiagnosed during<lb/> this timeframe. However, it is plausible that the figures<lb/> for 2022, particularly in the last six months, are affected<lb/> by individuals with mild infections who may not have<lb/> sought medical attention, and physicians might not have<lb/> actively pursued virologic diagnoses for patients with<lb/> mild symptoms. Consequently, these cases cannot be<lb/> incorporated into the report, and it is imperative to<lb/> recognize this as a limitation. Finally, to enhance the<lb/> accessibility of our findings for our target audience,<lb/> primarily hematologists and infectious diseases medical<lb/> professionals, who may lack advanced statistical profi-<lb/>ciency, we have streamlined our analysis to strike a bal-<lb/>ance between complexity and clarity. As such, we have<lb/> excluded intricate analyses within our multivariable Cox<lb/> regression model, recognizing that not all variables<lb/> maintain proportionality over time or linearity. This<lb/> omission of comprehensive analysis may result in con-<lb/>servative estimations, particularly impacting variables<lb/> such as vaccination status as a protective factor and pa-<lb/>tient stay during the COVID-19 episode as a risk factor.<lb/> In simpler terms, the results from the multivariable Cox<lb/> regression model would require adjustments based on<lb/> the specific duration of exposure. Consequently, the<lb/> hazard ratio for vaccination may decrease over time with<lb/> increased vaccine doses (being the vaccines even more<lb/> protective than what reported here), while it may rise<lb/> with hospital or ICU admission during the COVID-19<lb/> episode (being these admissions even more risky than<lb/> what reported here). Given these considerations, while<lb/> urging caution in interpreting our findings, we recom-<lb/>mend future analyses to address this limitation. Despite<lb/> these limitations, the study offers valuable insights into<lb/> COVID-19 outcomes in patients with hematological<lb/> malignancies, expanding our knowledge in this field.<lb/></p>

        <p>In conclusion, the data from the EPICOVIDEHA<lb/> registry offer a multifaceted view of the COVID-19<lb/> pandemic for patients with hematological malig-<lb/>nancies. While there have been improvements, the road<lb/> ahead remains challenging. The findings from this<lb/> extensive dataset underscore the critical importance of<lb/> vaccination, prophylactic measures, and vigilant moni-<lb/>toring. As the COVID-19 situation continues to evolve,<lb/> we must persist in learning, adapting, and advocating<lb/> for the well-being of patients with hematological ma-<lb/>lignancies. Through ongoing research and collabora-<lb/>tion, we can navigate the ever-changing COVID-19<lb/> landscape and provide the best possible care for this<lb/> vulnerable patient population.</p>

	</text>
</TEI>