<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader/>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>1.<lb/> Introduction<lb/></head>

			<p>The digitalization movement has had a significant impact on<lb/> Moroccan companies, leading to the need for accelerated digital<lb/> transformations. Achieving these transformations requires the mobilization<lb/> of multiple resources and personnel to successfully digitize all business and<lb/> strategic processes. Consequently, professionals and researchers have been<lb/> seeking to identify the variables that contribute to successful digital<lb/> transformations in the Moroccan business environment.<lb/></p>

			<p>Of all the stages involved in the digital transformation of companies,<lb/> IT implementation stands out as a crucial step for success, as highlighted in<lb/> existing literature. According to <ref type="biblio">Randolph et al. (1990)</ref>, IT implementation<lb/> refers to the organizational effort of introducing appropriate information<lb/> technologies to a user community. This exploratory case study aims to<lb/> address the questions and concerns of professionals and management science<lb/> and information systems researchers by identifying the key factors involved<lb/> in the digital transformation process in Moroccan companies. The objectives<lb/> of this study are to identify the challenges faced during the IT<lb/> implementation process in Morocco and to explore the determinants of<lb/> successful IT implementation in the Moroccan context.<lb/></p>

			<p>By addressing these research questions, this study aims to contribute<lb/> to the existing literature by focusing on the specificities of the Moroccan<lb/> context, which has been underrepresented in previous research. Additionally,<lb/> this study aims to shed light on the challenges hindering the digital<lb/> transformation of Moroccan companies and their ability to meet the<lb/> requirements imposed by the digitalization movement in the economic and<lb/> social environment. To achieve these objectives, a qualitative research<lb/> approach using the single case study method <ref type="biblio">(Yin, 2018)</ref> will be adopted,<lb/> with data collected through semi-structured interviews and analyzed using<lb/> NVIVO software.<lb/></p>

			<p>This article begins with a conceptual analysis to define the main<lb/> components of our research question and to identify the key characteristics<lb/> of IT implementation. Subsequently, we will present the theories and<lb/> explanatory models that shed light on the origins of the selected theoretical<lb/> variables. The resource-based view (RBV) <ref type="biblio">(Barney, 2000)</ref> and the theory of<lb/> contingency <ref type="biblio">(Reinking, 2012)</ref> will be utilized to identify the complementary<lb/> organizational and human resources required for the IT implementation<lb/> process and to examine the impact of contingency factors (e.g., structure,<lb/> strategy, size) on IT implementation. Finally, we will present and discuss the<lb/> results achieved in this study.<lb/></p>

			<head>2.<lb/> Conceptual Analysis: Literature Review<lb/></head>

			<p>The debate about IT has been focused, in the literature of management<lb/> sciences and information systems, on numerous dimensions including that of<lb/> their implementation is, often, considered as a major determinant of their<lb/> performance. For that, we will present, in the following, a conceptual<lb/> analysis in order to identify their different associated visions, their<lb/> typologies, the steps of the process of their implementations and their<lb/> different uses.<lb/></p>

			<head>2.1<lb/>The Various Perspectives of IT<lb/></head>

			<p>The literature extensively analyzes five different perspectives on IT.<lb/> These include the tool perspective, the procurement perspective, the holistic<lb/> perspective, the technological perspective, and the nominal perspective. The<lb/> tool perspective, which originated from Kling&apos;s work in 2007, views IT as a<lb/> collection of communication tools with specific characteristics <ref type="biblio">(George et<lb/> al., 1990)</ref>. The procurement perspective, on the other hand, conceptualizes IT<lb/> based on how users perceive it, its level of implementation within the<lb/> organization, and the monetary value attributed to it as an investment in<lb/> companies <ref type="biblio">(Kohli &amp; Grover, 2008)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>The overall vision perceives IT as a comprehensive package that<lb/> includes all necessary components for socio-economic use, such as training,<lb/> qualified personnel, and support services <ref type="biblio">(Kling, 2007)</ref>. However, IT vision<lb/> followers limit their focus to the technical capabilities of IT, such as<lb/> information handling, storage, recovery, and transmission <ref type="biblio">(Melville et al.,<lb/> 2004)</ref>. On the other hand, the nominal vision of IT completely disregards the<lb/> role of technologies, treating it as a mere empty concept mentioned in<lb/> phenomena like IT governance mechanisms and information system strategy<lb/> or planning <ref type="biblio">(Wanda et al., 2001)</ref>. These five conceptions related to IT are<lb/> presented by <ref type="biblio">Orlikowski and Lacono (2001)</ref> in the following manner:<lb/></p>

            <list>
			    <item>-Tool vision: IT is seen as a tool that aims to generate value, whether<lb/> it be through improved productivity, cost reduction, competitive advantage,<lb/> or better relations with suppliers. The intention behind IT use is often<lb/> unclear.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Procuration vision: IT is implemented through various agents,<lb/> similar to actions labeled in dollars. There are numerous potential agents, but<lb/> only a few are actually adopted. The adoption of multiple agents allows for<lb/> triangulation and enhances accumulated knowledge.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Overall vision: This involves evaluating the value generation of IT in<lb/> rich contexts within the field of IT science, often through case studies or<lb/> field studies focused on organizational structure and co-innovation.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Nominal vision: IT is not effectively conceptualized, appearing in<lb/> name only without significant impact. The focus on abstraction leads to<lb/> precise modelling at the expense of generality.<lb/></item>
            </list>

			<p>The computational vision, which pertains to searching for value<lb/> specifically for IT companies, was not considered by <ref type="biblio">Orlikowski and Lacono<lb/> (2001)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>2.2<lb/> Typology of IT<lb/></head>

			<p>IT encompasses a wide range of software platforms and databases<lb/> that provide various information and communication products. Its main<lb/> objective is to ensure coordination between information systems and internal<lb/> and external users <ref type="biblio">(Bhatt &amp; Grover, 2005; Stoel &amp; Muhanna, 2009)</ref>. In new<lb/> organizations, IT plays a significant role and is often considered equivalent<lb/> to the concept of an information system (IS). One popular classification of<lb/> IT, as presented by <ref type="biblio">Brousseau et al. (1997)</ref> is based on organizational<lb/> properties rather than technical criteria. This typology includes the following<lb/> categories:<lb/></p>

            <list>
			    <item>-Telecommunications tools: These tools are used for direct<lb/> interindividual communication. They facilitate communication in a natural<lb/> language such as phone calls, fax, and email.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-IT tools: These tools serve localized functions, such as collecting,<lb/> processing, and storing information. The operations performed with these<lb/> tools remain within the boundaries of the observed organizational<lb/> component, such as a workstation, service, or firm.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Telematic tools: These tools connect IT systems either with each<lb/> other (e.g., exchanging IT documents) or with terminals (e.g., accessing<lb/> databases). Telematic tools are distinct from IT tools as they directly<lb/> contribute to the coordination mechanisms between organizational<lb/> components. They help automate procedures and differ from<lb/> telecommunications tools, as the latter do not involve formalization of<lb/> communication content or coordination procedures.<lb/></item>
            </list>

			<head>2.3<lb/> The implementation process of IT<lb/></head>

			<p>The implementation process of IT, as described by the famous model<lb/> of <ref type="biblio">Kwon and Zmud (1987)</ref>, is based on the Lewin change model (1952) (to<lb/> manage the changes due to readjustments and reorganizations of companies<lb/> often confronted by resistance from employees, the German-American<lb/> psychologist Kurt Lewin developed a model in 1952 for describing the<lb/> change in three steps: Unfreeze-Change-Refreeze). The process consists of<lb/> five stages:<lb/></p>

            <list>
			    <item>-Initiation: This stage starts with the emergence of organizational<lb/> needs for technological innovation. The implementation of IT begins with a<lb/> diagnosis of the potential gains and latent losses that may come with the<lb/> introduction of the technology. The proposed IT solutions should correspond<lb/> with the tasks for which they are being introduced.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Adoption: The adoption stage involves a negotiation process for the<lb/> integration of IT solutions into the organization. It requires an investment<lb/> decision in the IT artefact.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Adaptation: Once IT applications are adopted and installed, the<lb/> organization should aim for harmonization between the new technology and<lb/> existing organizational procedures. This can be achieved through proper<lb/> training and information dissemination to potential users.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Acceptance: The acceptance stage is crucial in the implementation<lb/> process, as it reflects the success of IT introduction through widespread use<lb/> in the organizational working environment.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Routinization: In this final stage, the implementation of IT solutions<lb/> becomes a normal part of users&apos; perception and they become familiar with<lb/> the introduced applications.<lb/></item>

            </list>

			<head>3.<lb/> Nature of Use of IT<lb/></head>

			<p>Information technologies are designed to meet the various needs of<lb/> real and potential users, particularly with the advent of the Internet. In<lb/> addition to the internal and external, as well as operational and strategic uses<lb/> of IT, <ref type="biblio">Aral and Weill (2007)</ref> have identified four specific types of IT use:<lb/></p>

            <list>

			    <item>-Infrastructure use: In this case, IT serves as the foundation for<lb/> shared IT services, providing a flexible base for future commercial<lb/> initiatives.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Transactional use: IT enables process automation and contributes to<lb/> cost reduction.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Information use: IT provides information for management,<lb/> accounting, reporting, decision-making, planning, control, analysis, and data<lb/> collection.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Strategic use: IT facilitates entry into a new market by offering new<lb/> services or activating new products.<lb/></item>

            </list>

			<head>4.<lb/> Theoretical Framework<lb/></head>

			<p>Through an examination of the literature in management sciences,<lb/> various theories and explanatory models have been identified as the<lb/> theoretical framework for different issues related to IT implementation.<lb/> Among these theories, two fundamental ones are the resources-based view<lb/> (RBV) <ref type="biblio">(Barney, 2000)</ref> and the theory of contingency <ref type="biblio">(Reinking, 2012)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>4.1<lb/> Complementarity of Resources and IT Implementation<lb/></head>

			<p>The resource-based view (RBV) is widely used in management<lb/> sciences, as explored by <ref type="biblio">Barney (2000)</ref>, <ref type="biblio">Conner (1991)</ref>, and <ref type="biblio">Schulze (1992)</ref>.<lb/> This theory suggests that companies compete based on unique, valuable,<lb/> rare, difficult to imitate, and non-substitutable resources. IT is considered<lb/> one of the resources that companies seek to acquire and develop in order to<lb/> improve performance in a digitally-driven environment. Various<lb/> classifications of IT resources exist, such as <ref type="biblio">Bharadwaj&apos;s (2000)<lb/></ref> classification of IT infrastructure, human IT resources, and intangible assets<lb/> activated by IT, as well as <ref type="biblio">Ross et al.&apos;s (1998)</ref> classification of human assets,<lb/> technological assets, and relational assets that contribute to value creation<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(Wade &amp; Hulland, 2004)</ref>. Other categories of IT resources identified in the<lb/> literature include:<lb/></p>

            <list>
                <item>-Resources for managing external relationships, such as stakeholder<lb/> management, contract monitoring, and coordination of buyers and suppliers.<lb/></item>

                <item>-IT resources for market reactivity, including agility, fast delivery, and<lb/> organizational flexibility.<lb/></item>

                <item>-IT resources for internal relationships (IS/company partnership), such<lb/> as aligned IT planning, IT/business synergy, and integration of IT into the<lb/> overall strategy.<lb/></item>

                <item>-IT resources for IS planning and change management, encompassing<lb/> problem-solving orientation, IT change management, and architecture<lb/> planning.<lb/></item>

                <item>-IS infrastructure, including physical and flexible infrastructure and<lb/> technological assets.<lb/></item>

                <item>-Technical competencies in IS, such as knowledge and technical assets<lb/> in IT science.<lb/></item>

                <item>-IS development based on technical innovation and experimentation<lb/> with new technologies.<lb/></item>

                <item>-Profitable operations, including support for operations, IT operations,<lb/> and operations focused on improving product quality.<lb/></item>

            </list>

			<p>The concept of IT resources encompasses IT capacities as well.<lb/> <ref type="biblio">Willcocks et al., (2006)</ref> distinguish nine categories, which are business and<lb/> IT vision (integration between IT and other facets of the company), the<lb/> design of IT architectures (competencies in IT development), the provision<lb/> of IT services (implementation, relationships with suppliers and customers),<lb/> and a set of key features including IT leadership and informed procurement.<lb/> <ref type="biblio">Bharadwaj et al., (2013)</ref> have identified six dimensions of companies&apos; IT<lb/> capacity: IT/Enterprise partnership, external IT links, reflection on business<lb/> IT strategies, IT business integration, IT management, and IT infrastructure<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(Wade &amp; Hulland, 2004)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>The idea of complementarity surrounding IT resources has been<lb/> recognized as a mediating variable in various studies and by proponents of<lb/> the resources-based view. <ref type="biblio">Alavi and Leidner (2001)</ref> ; <ref type="biblio">Zhu (2004)</ref> believe that<lb/> complementarity surrounding IT resources is crucial as it implies a more<lb/> intricate role of IT within the company. These resources play an<lb/> interdependent role with other resources of the company in order to develop<lb/> and sustain a competitive advantage <ref type="biblio">(Bhatt &amp; Grover, 2005)</ref>. The conclusion<lb/> is that IT can only create competitive value if they are utilized to leverage<lb/> existing business and human resources <ref type="biblio">(Wasko et al., 2011)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Based on the above, we consider the IT solutions acquired or<lb/> developed by companies as an explanatory variable for the implementation<lb/> of IT. This variable encompasses the IT infrastructure described by <ref type="biblio">Wade and<lb/> Hulland (2004)</ref>. It includes the nature of IT, the brand of the adopted<lb/> solution, and the mode of adoption. Additionally, we include human<lb/> resources as complementary human-informatics resources, which are part of<lb/> the IT resource for IS planning and change management, as proposed by<lb/> <ref type="biblio">Wade and Hulland (2004)</ref>. This competence encompasses both the business<lb/> and IT skills of managers and employees who use IT.<lb/></p>

			<head>4.2<lb/> The Impact of Contextual Factors: Contingency Theory<lb/></head>

			<p>Contingency theory is a theory that seeks to understand the<lb/> relationships within and between organizational subsystems, as well as<lb/> between the organization as a whole and its environments, and how<lb/> organizations function under different conditions. The most commonly<lb/> recognized contingency factors, as described in the literature, include<lb/> strategy, structure, size, environment, and technology <ref type="biblio">(Donaldson, 2006)</ref>.<lb/> The use of contingency theory in the field of information and management<lb/> systems has seen significant development in recent decades. The theory<lb/> posits that contingency factors can influence the performance of information<lb/> systems. <ref type="biblio">Weill and Olson (1989)</ref> suggest a connection between the<lb/> performance of the information system and that of the organization.<lb/></p>

			<p>In the management of information systems, the contingency variables<lb/> typically identified in the literature include strategy, structure, size,<lb/> environment, technology, task, and individual characteristics. In this study,<lb/> three contingency factors -structure, size, and strategy -will be considered<lb/> as they impact the IT implementation process as a dependent variable.<lb/> Structure has been discussed as a contingency variable in the works of <ref type="biblio">Davis<lb/> (1986) ; Ein-Dor (1978); Weill and Olson,(1989)</ref>. Additionally, <ref type="biblio">(Weill &amp;<lb/> Olson, 1989</ref>) analyzed the alignment between organizational structure and<lb/> the structure of the &quot;IT services&quot; function (ISM: Information Systems<lb/> Management). Size has been consistently identified in empirical studies as a<lb/> moderating contingency variable. <ref type="biblio">Klatzky (1970)</ref> argues that size is the<lb/> cause of the decentralized structures that accompany automation. The<lb/> strategy is also considered a contingency variable by <ref type="biblio">Vitale et al., (1986)</ref>,<lb/> who examined the incorporation of information assets and opportunities into<lb/> the company&apos;s strategic planning process.<lb/></p>

			<head>5.<lb/> Methodology And Sample<lb/></head>

			<p>In this qualitative study, we utilized a research methodology based on<lb/> the single case study approach <ref type="biblio">(Yin, 2018)</ref>. Also known as a critical case<lb/> study, this method allows for the examination of one or more analysis unit.<lb/> Researchers often choose this approach when the case represents a critical<lb/> test of existing theory, when it involves a rare or unique event, or when it<lb/> aligns with specific research goals <ref type="biblio">(Verner &amp; Abdullah, 2012)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Among the various data collection techniques offered by the case<lb/> study method, we opted for semi-structured interviews. To facilitate this, we<lb/> developed an interview guide based on the findings from the theoretical<lb/> framework developed earlier. The questions in the interview guide can be<lb/> summarized into three categories:<lb/></p>

			<p>Question 1: What are the factors that influence the pre-<lb/>implementation of IT in Moroccan companies?<lb/></p>

			<p>Question 2: What challenges are encountered throughout the IT<lb/> implementation process?<lb/></p>

			<p>Question 3: What factors contribute to the success of IT<lb/> implementation in Moroccan companies?<lb/></p>

			<p>The data collected will be analyzed and processed using NVIVO<lb/> software, a widely-used tool for qualitative studies. This software provides<lb/> us with multiple tools and functionalities for data presentation, including<lb/> verbatim, correlation matrices, and node clusters. The node clusters will be<lb/> presented along with the Pearson correlation coefficient to indicate the<lb/> degree of correlation between variables that may emerge during the<lb/> empirical investigation.<lb/></p>

			<p>The selected company is internationally renowned and a leader in the<lb/> field of mining extraction. From this company, we selected a sample of 15<lb/> function managers with various roles, including the directorate of<lb/> information systems (DIS) who holds a crucial position. The sample was<lb/> chosen following the methodological recommendations for the case study<lb/> method <ref type="biblio">(Yin, 2018)</ref>, particularly considering the criteria of ease of access<lb/> and availability. The number of individuals in the sample was determined<lb/> based on the recommended saturation point in qualitative research <ref type="biblio">(Patton,<lb/> 2005)</ref>. The table below illustrates the key characteristics of the sample.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 1.Characteristics of the interviewees<lb/> Persons interviewed<lb/> Degree<lb/> Age<lb/> IT Manager<lb/> Engineer<lb/> 29 years<lb/> Head of IS department<lb/> Engineer<lb/> 46 years<lb/> Management Controller<lb/> Master (ISCAE)<lb/> 42 years<lb/> Preparation Manager<lb/> Engineer<lb/> 29 years<lb/> Load and transport manager<lb/> Specialized technician<lb/> 40 years<lb/> Social Affairs Managers<lb/> Master (ISCAE)<lb/> 28 years<lb/> IT Manager<lb/> Engineer<lb/> 29 years<lb/> Technical control manager<lb/> Manager<lb/> 47 years<lb/> Mechanical Installations Manager<lb/> Engineer<lb/> 34 years<lb/> Electrical Maintenance Manager<lb/> Specialized technician<lb/> 52 years<lb/> Maintenance Manager<lb/> Engineer<lb/> 29 years<lb/> Maintenance manager<lb/> Engineer<lb/> 46 years<lb/> Purchasing Manager<lb/> Master<lb/> 43 years<lb/> Sales Manager<lb/> Master<lb/> 55 years<lb/> IT Manager<lb/> Engineer<lb/> 57 years<lb/> Source: Author&apos;s presentation<lb/></figure>

			<p>The company being studied has a modern IT infrastructure that<lb/> incorporates a range of integrated and specialized IT solutions. Additionally,<lb/> the company&apos;s administrative team includes managers from prestigious<lb/> Moroccan and international educational institutions. The table below<lb/> provides an overview of the types of solutions available to the company and<lb/> the corresponding features associated with each type.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 2.Main IT solutions used in the company<lb/> Related features<lb/> Solution type or category<lb/> Industrial management (industrial<lb/> IS)<lb/> These include simple managers, OPM (production<lb/> management), GMAO (IT-aided maintenance<lb/> management), geological databases, modelling and<lb/> data analysis tools, etc. …<lb/> Competencies development<lb/> Training databases and annual assessment and<lb/> appraisal platform).<lb/> Administrative management<lb/> MYOCP, Gestor (day-to-day management of<lb/> absences, authorization...)<lb/> Project management<lb/> E-Supply<lb/> Maintenance<lb/> GMAO sur ORACLE R12<lb/> IT maintenance<lb/> Bureau de service<lb/> Production monitoring<lb/> OPM Extraction<lb/> Administration and secretariat<lb/> MS Office<lb/> Source: Author&apos;s presentation<lb/></figure>

			<head>6.<lb/> Results<lb/></head>

			<p>The results obtained confirmed that there is a complementary<lb/> relationship between IT resources and human resources during the<lb/> implementation process, as well as the impact of contextual factors. In other<lb/> words, there are multiple organizational and managerial challenges that need<lb/> to be explored. This section will first identify the pre-implementation factors<lb/> of IT based on interviews with individuals, specifically the managers of the<lb/> information systems department. Following that, the difficulties observed<lb/> during the IT implementation will be presented, both from the perspective of<lb/> the information systems department and other managers. Lastly, the variables<lb/> that contribute to a successful IT implementation in Moroccan companies<lb/> will be identified.<lb/></p>

			<head>6.1<lb/> Pre-implementation of IT in Moroccan Companies<lb/></head>

			<p>The success of a company&apos;s digital transformation largely depends on<lb/> the pre-implementation phase. This is a phase where all the necessary studies<lb/> are conducted before adopting IT solutions, including studying IT needs,<lb/> assessing the available material and human capacities and competencies,<lb/> evaluating the internal control system, and studying the IT market to select<lb/> the appropriate solutions and developers to contact.<lb/></p>

			<head>6.1.1. IT Needs Study<lb/></head>

			<p>Determining the needs requires the involvement of all staff members,<lb/> particularly the managers. Managers are asked to communicate their needs to<lb/> the department responsible for addressing them, providing details about their<lb/> department or service&apos;s size, stakeholders involved, nature of operations, and<lb/> anticipated changes. In the company being studied, the determination of<lb/> needs is described by IT managers answering the following question:<lb/></p>

			<p>Question: &quot;How do you determine the IT needs and what factors<lb/> determine these needs?&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>Answer: &quot;Our department determines the IT needs based on requests<lb/> from business managers and evaluating the offerings in the IT market to<lb/> update our IT capabilities. Several factors influence this assessment,<lb/> including the budget provided by general management, the size of our<lb/> business, and the expertise of the developer in question.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>As a result, it is evident that this phase holds great significance for all<lb/> stakeholders involved in the IT implementation process. It serves as the<lb/> foundation for the subsequent stages and marks the beginning of the<lb/> deployment of IT strategies in alignment with the overall company strategy.<lb/></p>

			<head>6.1.2. Evaluation of the Internal Control System<lb/></head>

			<p>Another important but often overlooked phase in IT implementation<lb/> is the evaluation of the internal control system. Based on interviews<lb/> conducted, it is apparent that the internal control system requires evaluation<lb/> in order to align with the prevailing quality and management standards<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(Dewett &amp; Jones, 2001)</ref>. This evaluation enables necessary adjustments to be<lb/> made, ensuring a well-founded implementation of IT <ref type="biblio">(Wahyoedi et al. 2023)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>It is worth noting that in our study, we observed the tendency to marginalize<lb/> this evaluation phase of the internal control system. Managers&apos; statements<lb/> revealed the challenges encountered during this stage, such as difficulties<lb/> related to the company&apos;s size and the rigid structure. The company&apos;s size<lb/> poses difficulties in modifying the internal control mechanism, and the rigid<lb/> structure means any modification will affect the established strategies.<lb/> Consequently, we posed the following question to the DIS managers<lb/> regarding this phase:<lb/></p>

			<p>Question: &quot;Do you conduct an evaluation of procedures and<lb/> processes before implementing IT? If so, how do you carry out this<lb/> operation?&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>Answer: &quot;Conducting an evaluation of procedures and processes is a<lb/> crucial step before implementing any IT system. This evaluation is essential<lb/> to establish new information flows using IT. However, this operation requires<lb/> significant resources, both human and material. As a result, the evaluation<lb/> stage is only incorporated when there is a complete replacement of the<lb/> initially adopted information system. In other words, we evaluate internal<lb/> control devices when implementing a new solution that includes the majority<lb/> of business processes. On the other hand, when implementing a solution that<lb/> is limited to a certain number of services or departments, this stage is<lb/> marginalized.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<head>7. Choice of IT to Adopt<lb/></head>

			<p>The choice of IT to be adopted depends on several variables, including<lb/> the type, brand, quality of the developer, and cost. These variables guide the<lb/> decision-making process for implementing IT solutions whether they are<lb/> acquired from the IT market or developed internally. The examination of<lb/> variables that influence the chosen company&apos;s IT solution choices has<lb/> revealed the following correlations:<lb/></p>

			<figure>Cluster no. 1-Correlation of IT choice with type and brand<lb/></figure>

			<head>Source: Author&apos;s presentation<lb/></head>

			<p>Based on the analysis, we have observed a strong correlation<lb/> (0.631234) between the type and brand of IT solutions that the company<lb/> acquires. This is primarily due to the company&apos;s IT strategy, which focuses<lb/> on obtaining integrated ERP solutions. The preferred brand in the IT market,<lb/> according to interviews with managers, is SAP <ref type="biblio">(Monk &amp; Wagner, 2013)</ref>. On<lb/> the other hand, the company only invests in developing specific solutions<lb/> because of its large size and the extensive time required for developing<lb/> integrated ERP solutions.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Cluster no. 2-Correlation of the choice of IT with the quality of the developer<lb/> Source: Author&apos;s presentation<lb/></figure>

			<p>The quality of the developer is a crucial factor that IT managers take<lb/> into consideration. This is evident in the correlation between IT acquisition<lb/> and the search for high-quality developers<lb/> (0.658329). This<lb/> relationship is reinforced by the connection between the brand of IT<lb/> solutions and the quality of the developer.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Cluster no. 3-Correlation of the choice of IT with the cost<lb/> Source: Author&apos;s presentation<lb/></figure>

			<p>The cost variable remains highly correlated with the choice of IT, as<lb/> widely discussed in the literature. In the selected company, there is an<lb/> average correlation (0.390451) between IT choice and cost. This can be<lb/> attributed to strategic guidelines that prioritize the cost/quality ratio when<lb/> making IT decisions.<lb/></p>

			<head>8. Monitoring IT Use<lb/></head>

			<p>After implementing the chosen IT solutions, the process does not end<lb/> there. It extends to the use of the adopted IT solutions. The objective of this<lb/> phase is to evaluate the effectiveness of the IT solutions by ensuring their<lb/> efficiency. In this context, the service will take certain actions during this<lb/> phase to address the following question:<lb/></p>

			<p>Question: &quot;After implementing IT solutions, what actions do you take<lb/> to monitor and control the functionality and efficiency of these solutions?&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>Answer: &quot;The monitoring phase is one of the most critical phases in<lb/> the IT implementation process. During this phase, we engage all service staff<lb/> to intervene and collaborate with all relevant services and units. This<lb/> includes organizing training sessions on the use of new IT solutions, as well<lb/> as addressing any user problems that arise.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>From the above, it is evident that the steps mentioned align closely with<lb/> those presented by <ref type="biblio">Kwon and Zmud (1987)</ref> in their IT implementation<lb/> model. The pre-implementation phase corresponds to the initiation phase,<lb/> and the adoption and adaptation phase of <ref type="biblio">Kwon and Zmud (1987)</ref> align with<lb/> the identification of needs and the selection of IT solutions. Finally, the<lb/> acceptance and routinization phase of the <ref type="biblio">Kwon and Zmud model (1987)<lb/></ref> corresponds to the monitoring of IT use.<lb/></p>

			<head>8.1<lb/> The Challenges of IT Implementation<lb/></head>

			<p>The implementation process of IT in Moroccan companies faces<lb/> various difficulties that often impact the objectives of the IT strategy and the<lb/> digital transformation of these businesses. The obtained results allowed us to<lb/> explore the challenges that arise in terms of the IT strategies adopted by the<lb/> company, as well as the cooperation of users. According to statements made<lb/> by managers, the alignment of IT strategies is often achieved by excluding<lb/> operational managers and relying solely on top-down decisions. This<lb/> situation leads to a lack of alignment between business needs and the<lb/> solutions imposed by top management. The following diagram presents a<lb/> strong correlation (0.718113) between IT implementation and the defects in<lb/> IT strategy alignment:<lb/></p>

			<figure>Cluster no. 4-Correlation between IT implementation and IT strategy alignment<lb/> Source: Author&apos;s presentation<lb/></figure>

			<p>These results highlight the importance of aligning IT strategies for<lb/> the success of the IT implementation process. The main defects reported by<lb/> the interviewed managers are presented in the following correlation matrix:<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table no. 3-IT strategy alignment defects<lb/> Defects<lb/> Number of<lb/> interviewes<lb/> %<lb/> Lack of alignment with business<lb/> needs<lb/> 10<lb/> 67%<lb/> Imposition of certain IT solutions<lb/> (top-down)<lb/> 13<lb/> 87%<lb/> Lack of monitoring of changes in<lb/> requirements over time<lb/> 11<lb/> 73%<lb/> Source: Author&apos;s presentation<lb/></figure>

			<p>In regards to the challenges of IT implementation, we have observed<lb/> a lack of cooperation from IT users, particularly those involved in aligning<lb/> IT strategies. This lack of cooperation hinders the implementation process<lb/> and diminishes the value of IT investments. This situation often results in the<lb/> presence of implemented but unused solutions, as well as partially utilized<lb/> solutions.<lb/></p>

			<p>Our analysis of the relationship between IT user cooperation and IT<lb/> implementation has yielded the following findings:<lb/></p>

			<figure>Cluster no. 5-Correlation between IT strategy alignment and user cooperation<lb/> Source: Author&apos;s presentation<lb/></figure>

			<p>This finding emphasizes the importance of cooperation among all<lb/> participants in the IT implementation process. Cooperation can take various<lb/> forms and greatly contributes to the success of the implementation process.<lb/> This includes providing information services related to IT solution<lb/> implementation, understanding their needs, the IT capabilities of their teams,<lb/> and their feedback on IS service choices.<lb/></p>

			<head>8.2. Determinants of IT Implementation in Moroccan Companies<lb/></head>

			<p>Based on the above findings and the statements of our sample<lb/> managers, we can conclude that IT implementation is dependent on three<lb/> variables: pre-implementation, IT strategy alignment, and user involvement<lb/> (cooperation). In this context, we have identified the determinants of<lb/> successful implementation based on the aforementioned results and manager<lb/> declarations. Please refer to Table <ref type="table">4</ref> for the determinants of IT<lb/> implementation success:<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table no. 4-IT implementation success factors<lb/> Elements of the implementation process<lb/> Determinants<lb/> Pre-implementation<lb/> IT quality;<lb/> Assessment of the internal control<lb/> system.<lb/> IT strategy alignment<lb/> Adequacy with business needs;<lb/> Tracking evolution of the needs during<lb/> the implementation process;<lb/> Translating IT strategies through<lb/> awareness-raising and training.<lb/> Intervener cooperation<lb/> Acceptance of use;<lb/> Participation in the implementation<lb/> process;<lb/> IT competencies.<lb/> Source: Author&apos;s presentation<lb/></figure>

			<p>Based on the results obtained, we can identify the main determinants<lb/> of successful IT implementation. These include pre-implementation<lb/> components, alignment of the IT strategy, and variables explaining<lb/> stakeholder cooperation in the implementation process. These determinants<lb/> are present throughout the implementation process and complement each<lb/> other, ensuring the success of IT solution implementation. Therefore, we can<lb/> consider the complementarity between these determinants as a mediating<lb/> variable between the resources available to Moroccan companies<lb/> (independent variables) and IT implementation (dependent variable).<lb/></p>

			<head>9.<lb/> Discussion<lb/></head>

			<p>The results we obtained revealed the numerous challenges that<lb/> impact the implementation of IT in Moroccan companies, posing obstacles to<lb/> their successful digital transformation. This situation raises concerns about<lb/> the ability of Moroccan companies to derive value from their investments in<lb/> IT and their capacity to adapt to digitalization requirements. According to<lb/> proponents of resource theory, IT can provide a lasting and irreplaceable<lb/> competitive advantage when used in conjunction with other complementary<lb/> organizational and human resources <ref type="biblio">(Barney, 2000)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>The presence of resource complementarity is a crucial factor during<lb/> the IT implementation process, serving as a determinant of success. Without<lb/> it, companies face significant challenges. Complementarity is sought<lb/> throughout all stages of the IT implementation process. Based on the<lb/> aforementioned results and interviews with managers, we will now present<lb/> the characteristics of complementarity between IT and other organizational<lb/> and human resources mobilized during the implementation of IT, as follows:<lb/></p>

            <list>

			    <item>-During the pre-implementation phase of IT, we observed that<lb/> companies primarily mobilize human resources. These include service staff,<lb/> as well as staff from other departments and functions. The complementarity<lb/> between these two categories of stakeholders is evident in the study of needs<lb/> and the evaluation of the internal control system. In this case,<lb/> complementarity is achieved through cooperation and the exchange of<lb/> information between the two categories involved.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-During the phase of selecting IT solutions, we found that companies<lb/> mobilize financial resources, in addition to the human resources from the IT<lb/> department, when acquiring IT solutions. This is done through aligning IT<lb/> choices with contextual factors such as business size, structure, and strategy<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(Reinking, 2012)</ref>. The success of this choice depends on the<lb/> complementarity between these two categories of resources, following a<lb/> rational decision-making process that considers the price/quality ratio. In<lb/> terms of developing IT solutions within the IS service, complementarity is<lb/> achieved through cooperation between IS service personnel and future users,<lb/> as well as through the harmonization of organizational resources with the<lb/> objectives of the solutions being developed.<lb/></item>

			    <item>-Finally, the critical phase in the implementation of IT solutions is the<lb/> beginning of their actual use, which often presents various complaints and<lb/> anomalies. This phase strongly calls for complementarity, particularly<lb/> through cooperation and coordination between users and the IS service.<lb/> Communication and information exchange are essential to align the IT<lb/> strategy with the operational objectives of the company.<lb/></item>

            </list>

			<p>From the above, it is evident that complementarity, both between IT<lb/> resources and between IT human resources and other human resources,<lb/> serves as a mediating variable in the success of IT implementation in<lb/> Moroccan companies. This applies to both acquired IT solutions and<lb/> internally developed ones.<lb/></p>

			<head>Conclusion<lb/></head>

			<p>The digital transformation of Moroccan companies is no longer a<lb/> choice; it is an obligation imposed by the digitalization movements in their<lb/> economic and social environment. In order to support this transition,<lb/> Moroccan companies are seeking IT solutions that can integrate with their<lb/> structures to meet digitalization requirements. The literature in information<lb/> systems management has been providing theoretical guidance for<lb/> professionals to succeed in the digital transformation of their entities.<lb/> However, there is a limited number of works in this area, which motivated<lb/> our study to explore the determinants of successful implementation of IT<lb/> investments for Moroccan companies.<lb/></p>

			<p>To carry out this study, we conducted empirical research at a<lb/> Moroccan company with a highly developed IT structure in the region. The<lb/> main results identified three elements that determine successful<lb/> implementation: pre-implementation factors, alignment of IT strategy, and<lb/> cooperation and coordination among stakeholders. Additionally, we explored<lb/> the mediating variable of complementarity between these determinants,<lb/> which played a role in the IT choices before implementation, alignment of IT<lb/> strategies with the company&apos;s overall strategy, and cooperation and<lb/> coordination among those involved in the implementation process.<lb/></p>

			<p>Despite the limitations of this study, such as difficulties in sample<lb/> access and availability of interviewees, these results provide clarity to<lb/> professionals and managers regarding the factors necessary for successful<lb/> digital transformation, particularly during the implementation phase. This<lb/> study also contributes to the literature on information systems management<lb/> and management science by studying the specificities of the Moroccan<lb/> context. Furthermore, it opens up opportunities for future research, including<lb/> studying other categories of companies like small and medium enterprises<lb/> (SMEs) or conducting multiple case studies instead of a singular one.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
