<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1001._0908.0054"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<head level="1">I. INTRODUCTION<lb/></head>

			<p>It has been argued that a Scalar Field may be a candidate<lb/> to form the main component of the total Dark Matter in the<lb/> universe <ref type="biblio">[1, 2, 3, 4, 5]</ref>, this alternative is called the SFDM<lb/> model. The mass of this Scalar Field is assumed ultra light<lb/> (∼ 10 −22 eV ), and obey an equuation of state p = ωρ, with<lb/> −1 ≤ ω ≤ 1. It is also interesting that this type of matter<lb/> can form astrophysical objects called Boson Stars <ref type="biblio">[6, 7]</ref>. The<lb/> SFDM model has been tested on galactic scales <ref type="biblio">[8, 9, 10]</ref>.<lb/> On the other hand, at cosmological scales, the most powerful<lb/> observable to rule out theoretical models is the Cosmic Mi-<lb/>crowave Background (CMB) spectrum. In <ref type="biblio">[11]</ref> it is studied<lb/> the modification of the spectrum assuming an interaction with<lb/> the baryonic sector.</p>

			<p>In the present treatment we analyze how<lb/> the values of different parameters change the amplitudes of<lb/> the acousitic peaks with no interaction at all.<lb/> There is a fermionic particle which shares some similitudes<lb/> with this hypothetical bosonic species, that is, the neutrino. In<lb/> fact, its study as a candidate for Dark Matter can serve as an<lb/> antecedent for our goal. The neutrino was the first promising<lb/> particle candidate to be the whole Dark Matter of the universe.<lb/> That is because of their low interacting rate with baryons and<lb/> the evidence of the flavour oscillations which strongly sug-<lb/>gest a non-zero neutrino mass. Even though, there are some<lb/> unavoidables problems that indicate that the neutrinos can not<lb/> be the whole Dark Matter of the universe <ref type="biblio">[12]</ref>.<lb/> Very early in the universe, neutrinos were in thermal equi-<lb/>librium with the primeval fireball. Due to its low mass com-<lb/>pared with its temperature in this epoch, they behave exactly<lb/> as radiation. After decoupling, they relax only with the expan-<lb/>sion of the universe as T ν ∝ a −1 , and eventually its tempera-<lb/>ture falls below its mass. It is known as the non-relativistic<lb/> transition (NRT). Besides, once decoupled, its temperature<lb/> remain well determined in terms of the temperature photons<lb/> T ν = (4/11) 1/3 T γ , which fixes the neutrino number density<lb/> today to n<lb/> (0)<lb/> ν ∼ 100cm −3 . An important intrinsic part of its<lb/> nature is that they are fermions and then their density has an<lb/> upper bound. Thus the content of neutrinos Ω ν is entirely<lb/> parameterized by its mass, i.e., m ν ≈ Ω ν 51.013 eV <ref type="biblio">[13]</ref>.</p>

			<p>Between the times of decoupling and the non-relativistic<lb/> transition, neutrinos just free-stream due to the negligible in-<lb/>teraction with the rest of the matter. Thus, the combined effect<lb/> of free-streaming and radiation behavior clears off the fluctu-<lb/>ations of δ ν ≡ δ ρ ν /ρ ν . This means that there is no contribu-<lb/>tion to the acoustic oscillations in the CMB due to massless<lb/> (or relativistic) neutrions.<lb/></p>

			<p>On the other hand, after the non-relativistic transition, the<lb/> neutrinos behave closely as Cold Dark Matter. The fluctua-<lb/>tions begin to grow quickly until they reach the Cold Dark<lb/> Matter rate, that is δ ν ∝ a. Thus, the structure formation has a<lb/> contribution in the neutrino gravitational fluctuations after the<lb/> NRT. However, in most standard models, this transition takes<lb/> place well after the matter dominated epoch and the neutrino<lb/> contribution becomes subdominant. The effect of the neutri-<lb/>nos in the CMB is not negligible, although, it is too low to be<lb/> considered as the whole component of Dark Matter <ref type="biblio">[14]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>In the following, we assume the value of the temperature<lb/> of the CMB photons today T CMB = 2.726 K, the Hubble&apos;s<lb/> constant H 0 = 75.0km s −1 M pc −1 , and a flat geometry with<lb/> a Cosmological Constant Λ, just for simplicity. It is choosed<lb/> units in which c = k B = 1, then, 1 K ∝ 10 −5 eV . This paper is<lb/> organized as follows. Section 2 is concerned to state the key<lb/> equations of this calculation. Section 3 discusses the results,<lb/> and the conclusions are enclosed in section 4.<lb/></p>

			<head level="1">II. ULTRA LIGHT BOSONS AS DARK MATTER<lb/></head>

			<p>We consider a Bosonic Ultra Light species of matter. We<lb/> just know that (i) it is a boson, (ii) with a mass m B ∼ 10 −22 eV .<lb/> (iii) It should be ultra-relativistic when decoupled, behaving<lb/> thus, as radiation. Note that in this approach the Dark Matter<lb/> is not treated as a Scalar Field, but as a bosonic particle. The<lb/> equation of state at the moment of decoupling is assumed to<lb/> be ω = 1/3, corresponding to radiation. We want to inves-<lb/>tigate if the Ultra Light Bosonic Dark Matter (ULBDM) can<lb/> form the main component of Dark Matter and reproduce the<lb/> observed CMB spectrum.<lb/> The geometry of this universe is described by the<lb/> Friedmann-Lemaître (FL) metric, perturbed to first order and<lb/> we take the conformal newtonian gauge<lb/></p>

			<formula>ds 2 = a 2<lb/> −(1 + 2ψ)dτ 2 + (1 − 2φ )dx i dx i<lb/> . <label>(1)</label><lb/></formula>

			<p>Where τ is the proper time. In this gauge the tensor and vector<lb/> degrees of freedom are eliminated from the begining and it<lb/> just appear the scalar modes (ψ and φ ) of the perturbation.<lb/></p>

			<p>Following the same formalism developed for the fermionic<lb/> sector <ref type="biblio">[15]</ref>, it is useful to define the corrected proper mo-<lb/>mentum q i ≡ a p i , q j = q n j , where n j is its direction unit<lb/> vector and a is the scale factor. The proper momentum p i<lb/> was defined in terms of the canonical conjugate momentum<lb/> P i = a(1 − ψ)p i of the the comoving coordinate x i . The co-<lb/>movil proper energy is ε ≡ a(p 2 + m 2 ) 1/2 . We also know that<lb/> the linear metric perturbations induce linear statistical pertur-<lb/>bations in the distribution function.<lb/></p>

			<formula>f (x i , P j , τ) = f 0 (q)<lb/> 1 + Ψ(x i , q,<lb/> j , τ)<lb/> , <label>(2)</label><lb/></formula>

			<p>where f 0 is the phase-space distribution function in an homo-<lb/>geneus background universe<lb/></p>

			<formula>f 0 (q) =<lb/> 1 e q/T B − 1<lb/> <label>(3)</label><lb/></formula>

			<p>and Ψ is related to the perturbation of the bosons temperature<lb/></p>

			<formula>Ψ(x i , q,<lb/> j , τ) = −<lb/> ∂ ln f 0<lb/> ∂ ln q<lb/> (q)<lb/> δ T B<lb/> T B<lb/> (x i , q,<lb/> j , τ).<lb/> <label>(4)</label><lb/></formula>

			<p>The evolution of the ULBDM is described by the collision-<lb/>less Boltzmann (or Vlasov) equation, which in Fourier space<lb/> reads<lb/></p>

			<formula>˙ Ψ − i<lb/> q<lb/> ε Ψ = −<lb/> ( k ·<lb/> ) ˙<lb/> ψ + i<lb/> ε q<lb/> ( k ·<lb/> )φ ∂ ln f 0<lb/> ∂ ln q<lb/> . <label>(5)</label><lb/></formula>

			<p>This equation gives the response of the phase-space distribu-<lb/>tion function to the metric perturbations.<lb/></p>

			<head level="1">III. TESTING WITH THE CMB<lb/></head>

			<p>The first interrogative is whether the CMB is effectively<lb/> sensitive to the nature of the statistics of the SFDM. We denote<lb/> the mass-to-temperature ratio of some species of fermions as<lb/> x F , and a species of bosons as x B , evaluated today. We com-<lb/>pute the CMB spectrums for fermions and bosons separetely.<lb/> It is important to mantain all the parameters fixed in order<lb/> to observe only the effect of the change of the statistics. In<lb/> <ref type="figure">figure 1</ref> one can see that for bosons, the amplitudes of the<lb/> first and second peaks are reduced, albeit the third peak is in-<lb/>creased respect to the corresponding of fermions. This is an<lb/> effect similar to that due to an icrease in the ratio between the<lb/> non-relativistic Matter and the Radiation. Thus, it could be<lb/> interpreted as an additional effective attractive potential.<lb/></p>

			<p>Here, the main problem is that the temperature of the<lb/> ULBDM is entirely unknown. This fact is due to the unknown<lb/> way of colliding with the rest of the matter. Moreover, if the<lb/> interaction rate was always zero, thus there is no reason to<lb/> believe that this species was in thermal equilibrium with the<lb/> primeval fireball. Without any interactions between the parti-<lb/>cles, there is no even a physical meaning for the temperature.<lb/> However, we suppose that there was some primordial decay<lb/> which generated the ULBDM. It also decoupled very early<lb/> (maybe near the Big Bang). Once the species is decoupled<lb/> from the rest of matter, its phase-space distribution function<lb/></p>

			<figure>
				Figure 1: CMB spectrums for Ω F = Ω B = 0.2, x F = x B = 63109,<lb/> τ = 0.13. All the parameters are the same for both curves. The con-<lb/>tinuous line corresponds to bosons and the dashed line to fermions.<lb/>
			</figure>

			<p>is &quot;freezed-out&quot; and its temperature can only relax with the<lb/> expansion of the universe T B ∼ a −1 . Then, after photon de-<lb/>coupling, the temperature of the bosons just can be<lb/></p>

			<formula>T B = αT γ ,<lb/> <label>(6)</label><lb/></formula>

			<p>where α is a constant free parameter to be determined. It is<lb/> crucial to note that if T B ∼ T γ , the quantity<lb/></p>

			<formula>x B ≡<lb/> m B<lb/> T<lb/> (0)<lb/> B<lb/> <label>(7)</label><lb/></formula>

			<p>is effectively zero, which means that the particle is ultra-<lb/>relativistic today (x B = m B /αT CMB ).<lb/> The addition of<lb/> ULBDM to the total matter background with this value of x B<lb/> just moves the entire CMB spectrum to the right and upwards.<lb/> The effect is shown in <ref type="figure">figure 2</ref>. In all the following figures:<lb/> Ω = 1, Ω Λ = 0.74, Ω bar = 0.04, and the crosses form the<lb/> curve of the mean value of the observed CMB spectrum.<lb/></p>

			<p>For all the values α 10 −25 it is noticed that the predicted<lb/> power spectrum is not sensitive to the change of α unless it<lb/> approaches to α = 10 −26 (x B = 10 4 ) or greater. The order<lb/> of magnitude needed to fit the data is α ∝ 10 −27 (x B ∝ 10 5 ).<lb/> The mass of the ULBDM must be five orders of magnitude<lb/> greater than its temperature. In <ref type="figure">figure 3</ref> it is plotted how the<lb/> CMB power spectrum is sensitive to little changes of α. The<lb/> range shown is from α = 0.3x10 −27 to α = 1.1x10 −27 (from<lb/> x B = 73, 367.57 to x B = 40, 759.76). It is noted that, the more<lb/> relativistic the species is, the more enhanced the first and sec-<lb/>ond peaks are.<lb/></p>

			<p>In <ref type="figure">figure 4</ref> it is shown the prediction for α = 10 −28 (second<lb/> curve from bottom to top). In this case, the ULBDM become<lb/> non-relativistic very early, causing a damping in the acoustic<lb/> oscillations because of an increase in the gravitational poten-<lb/>tial wells. On the bottom of the same figure also appears the<lb/> curve for α = 10 −30 , in which the same effect is enhanced.<lb/></p>

			<p>Once the necessary mass-to-temperature ratio is estimated,<lb/> we now investigate the content of bosons against the content<lb/></p>

			<figure>
				Figure 2: CMB spectrum for a Universe with Ω B = 0.2, Ω CDM =<lb/> 0.02, α 10 −26 .<lb/>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>	
				Figure 3: Response of the CMB spectrum to the change in the mass-<lb/>to-temperature ratio of the SFDM. For the three curves Ω B = 0.2,<lb/> Ω CDM = 0.02, α ∝ 10 −27 .<lb/> 
			</figure>
			
			<figure>	
				Figure 4: CMB spectrums for α in the interval (10 −26 , 10 −30 ). With<lb/> Ω B = 0.2, Ω CDM = 0.02, and no reionization.<lb/>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>	
				Figure 5: CMB power spectrums for diferent contents of ULBDM<lb/> and CDM. For the three curves shown α ∝ 10 −27 , no reionization.<lb/>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>	
				Figure 6: CMB power spectrums for diferent optical depths of reion-<lb/>ization. The range shown is from τ = 0.05 to τ = 0.19. Ω Bos = 0.2,<lb/> Ω CDM = 0.02, α ∝ 10 −27 .<lb/>
			</figure>

			<p>of Cold Dark Matter. <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> shows how the increase in Cold<lb/> Dark Matter diminishes the amplitude of the oscillations. This<lb/> is an effect of an enhancement of the gravitational potential<lb/> wells. It also seems to suggest a universe with these two con-<lb/>tents equilibrated. Nevertheless, we must measure the effect<lb/> of the fraction of reionized baryonic matter too. We fix all<lb/> the parameters and now vary the optical depth in <ref type="figure">figure 6</ref>. We<lb/> show that a universe ULBDM-dominated (Ω B = 0.2) could<lb/> be allowed for x B ∝ 10 5 and τ between 0.05 and 0.19.<lb/> Now we just want to say something about the number den-<lb/>sity of the SFDM. Firstly, we must keep in mind that in this<lb/> scheme, there is no condensation explicitly taked into account<lb/> yet. Next, if we must assume that nowadays the ULBDM par-<lb/>ticles behave as non-relativistic, so we can use<lb/></p>

			<formula>m B n B = Ω B ρ c .<lb/> <label>(8)</label><lb/></formula>

			<p>Then if one fixes the mass, the content of bosons in the uni-<lb/></p>

			<p>verse Ω B determines its number density. For m B ≈ 10 −22 and<lb/> Ω B = 0.2 it follows that n B ≈ 10 25 cm −3 . Such a big density<lb/> must be accompanied by a Bose-Einstein condensate treat-<lb/>ment of this matter. That is the aim of one following work<lb/> to be presented.<lb/></p>

			<head level="1">IV. CONCLUSIONS<lb/></head>

			<p>A universe dominated by Ultra Light Bosonic Dark Matter<lb/> in a non-condensate state could be possible only if these par-<lb/>ticles fulfill the condition that its mass-to-temperature ratio<lb/> must be close to ∼ 10 5 . For a mass ∼ 10 −22 eV , this is equiv-<lb/>alent to a temperature of the order of ∼ 10 −27 eV ∼ 10 −22 K.<lb/> Until now, there is no way to falsify such a low temperature<lb/> unless it can be given a mechanism of interaction with the rest<lb/> of the matter or a primeval decay which had could generate<lb/> the ULBDM. The energy of interaction would reveal the tem-<lb/>perature of decoupling. Then the temperature of the ULBDM<lb/> would be determined and it could be predicted a set of allowed<lb/> values of the parameter α. If this interaction can be parameter-<lb/>ized by a constant of interaction, then the CMB data can serve<lb/> to predict an allowed range of values for this constant. This<lb/> range could be used to search this particles by other means.<lb/></p>

			<p>We have shown that the effect of Reionzation is of crucial<lb/> importance to understand the nature of this type of matter in<lb/> the CMB. To get in concordance between the model and the<lb/> observations, it is needed at least a value of τ 0.07.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The most promising and physically interesting feature of<lb/> the ULBDM or SFDM resides on its condensate state <ref type="biblio">[16]</ref>,<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[17]</ref>, <ref type="biblio">[18]</ref>. We have shown that the change in the type of<lb/> statistics in the distribution function has non negligible ef-<lb/>fects in the CMB. It remains to include explicitly the infor-<lb/>mation of a Bose-Einstein condensate in the dynamical equa-<lb/>tions. The number density of the ULBDM (∼ 10 −22 eV ), if<lb/> it dominated the Dark Matter content, should be of the order<lb/> of ∼ 10 25 cm −3 today. It is necessary to investigate whether<lb/> the condition x B ∝ 10 5 should be still satisfied in a condensate<lb/> state, or not.<lb/></p>

	</text>
</tei>
