<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1678-7757-jaos-16-06-0380"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head level="1">INTRODUCTION<lb/></head>

			<p>Hypercementosis is characterized by cementum<lb/> formation beyond the physiologic limits of the tooth. This<lb/> excessive amount of cementum might lead to an abnormal<lb/> thickness of the apex that becomes round-shaped and/or with<lb/> the root appearance altered macroscopically 6 .<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The incidence of hypercementosis by race or population<lb/> group has not yet been established. <ref type="biblio">Grzesik, et al.</ref> 8 studied<lb/> the frequency of this phenomenon in 137 individuals and<lb/> observed an average of 3.8 teeth with hypercementosis per<lb/> individual aged approximately 47 years, and the premolars<lb/> were the most affected teeth 8 . Other studies reported root<lb/> hypercementosis in 84% out of 104 Barbados slave skeletal<lb/> collection from the 17th to 19th centuries 5 . Root<lb/> hypercementosis was also diagnosed in 10 out of 54<lb/> specimens gathered from prehistoric coastal populations of<lb/> Texas, USA 4 .<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The origin of hypercementosis is attributed to conditions<lb/> such as functional stress due to occlusion forces 4,5,7,19 ,<lb/> continuous dental eruption 2,3,9,12 , incorporation of periodontal<lb/> cementicles during physiologic cementum deposition 6 ,<lb/> reactionary deposition in response to periapical<lb/> inflammatory processes 18 , systemic factors such as<lb/> atherosclerosis, acromegaly, deforming arthritis,<lb/> hypertrophic arthritis, thyroid diseases and Paget&apos;s<lb/> disease 1,10,13,17 . <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows the alterations in dental root<lb/> morphology due to hypercementosis.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Radiographically, hypercementosis does not alter the<lb/> biologic width between the root surface, the periodontal<lb/> ligament, and the alveolar bone. Although hypercementosis<lb/> can be identified radiographically, it is not possible to<lb/> estimate the amount of extra cementum present in the<lb/> affected root because dentin and cementum have the same<lb/> radiodensity 7,14 .<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Microscopic studies about hypercementosis have<lb/> reported thick layers of cementum characterized by<lb/> deposition of symmetric, highly basophilic lines parallel to<lb/> dentin surface 6,7 . Occasionally, atypical cementum<lb/> depositions can be identified in focal areas as external<lb/> cementum projections. The presence of blood vessels and<lb/> nervous filaments associated to irregular apical cementum<lb/> deposition could contribute to the formation of multiple<lb/> foramina during cementum deposition, due to<lb/> hypercementosis, originating the apical deltas 19 .<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The lack of recent studies referring to this subject, added<lb/> to the potential clinical implications stimulate the evaluation<lb/> of morphologic characteristics of the apical root third and<lb/> root canal in teeth with hypercementosis. The purpose of<lb/> this study was to examining by scanning electron microscopy<lb/> (SEM) the external anatomy of the apical third of teeth with<lb/> hypercementosis, assessing the existence of any relationship<lb/> between hypercementosis and the diameter of the main<lb/> foramen and the presence of apical foramina. These<lb/> morphological features might implicate specific aspects on<lb/> endodontic therapeutic techniques.<lb/></p>

			<head level="1">MATERIAL AND METHODS<lb/></head>

			<p>Twenty-eight teeth with hypercementosis were selected<lb/> from the archives of the Discipline of Oral Pathology at the<lb/> Bauru School of Dentistry, SP, Brazil. Hypercementosis<lb/> distribution was classified in the present study as: club shape,<lb/> focal or circular cementum hyperplasia (CCH). The<lb/> longitudinal extension of club shape hypercementosis in the<lb/> root thirds was graded as mild, moderate and severe.<lb/> Regarding the tooth type, the sample comprised: 8 maxillary<lb/> molars, 6 mandibular molars, 6 maxillary premolars, 1<lb/> mandibular premolar, 4 canines and 3 residual roots. Sample<lb/> distribution according to hypercementosis type, tooth type<lb/> and number of evaluated roots is displayed in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The teeth had the crown and part of the roots sectioned<lb/> transversally with carborundum disk and discarded, leaving<lb/> 5-mm-long apical root segments. This procedure was<lb/> necessary in order to fit the specimen in a metallic base<lb/> used for SEM analysis. A total of 41 specimens were<lb/> obtained from 46 roots.<lb/> The specimens were dehydrated by immersion in an<lb/> ascending ethanol series (70, 80, 90 and 100%), sputter-<lb/>coated with gold and examined with a scanning electron<lb/> microscope (Zeiss DSM-940A, Oberkochen,</p>

			<p>Germany)<lb/> operating at 15kV. The following aspects were examined in<lb/> the SEM analysis: the contour and regularity of the root<lb/> surface; presence of resorption; presence and the number<lb/> of root foramina, and the diameter of the main foramen.<lb/></p> 
			
			<figure type="table">
				Tooth group<lb/> Hypercementosis type<lb/> Club shape<lb/> Focal<lb/> CCH<lb/> Teeth<lb/> Roots<lb/> Teeth<lb/> Roots<lb/> Teeth<lb/> Roots<lb/> discrete<lb/> moderate<lb/> severe<lb/> Maxillary molars<lb/> 2<lb/> 1<lb/> 2<lb/> 15<lb/> 2<lb/> 2<lb/> 1<lb/> 3<lb/> Mandibular molars<lb/> 2<lb/> 1<lb/> 6<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> 2<lb/> 4<lb/> Maxillary premolars<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> 2<lb/> 5<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> Mandibular premolars<lb/> -<lb/>1<lb/> -<lb/>1<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Maxillary canines<lb/> -<lb/>1<lb/> 1<lb/> 2<lb/> 2<lb/> 2<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>Residual roots<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1<lb/> 1<lb/> 2<lb/> 2<lb/> Total<lb/> 5<lb/> 5<lb/> 5<lb/> 29*<lb/> 7<lb/> 7*<lb/> 6<lb/> 10*<lb/>
			
				TABLE 1- Distribution of the 28 teeth according to the tooth group, type of hypercementosis and number of examined roots<lb/> 
			
				* A total of 41 specimens were obtained from a total of 46 roots.<lb/>
			</figure>

			<figure>
				FIGURE 1- Macroscopic aspects of teeth with different types<lb/> of hypercementosis. (A) Club shape hypercementosis: mild<lb/> (1), moderate (2) and severe (3). (B) Focal hypercementosis.<lb/> (C) Circular cementum hyperplasia hypercementosis<lb/>
			</figure>

			<head level="1">RESULTS<lb/></head> 
			
			<head level="2">Club Shape Hypercementosis<lb/></head>

			<p>Out of 12 specimen with mild club shape<lb/> hypercementosis 7 (58.3%) exhibited the apical foramen, 6<lb/> (50%) foramina and 3 (25%) had the obliteration of the main<lb/> foramen. Four 4 specimens (33.3%) presented more than<lb/> one of the studied aspects. Regarding the main foramen<lb/> diameter, a 150-300 µm range was found. The apical surface<lb/> of the teeth with this type of hypercementosis showed<lb/> sometimes a regular or an irregular aspect.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>It was not possible to observe the apical foramen in only<lb/> 1 specimen of teeth with moderate club shape<lb/> hypercementosis. The foramen diameter varied between 150<lb/> and 450 µm. A larger number of roots presented irregular<lb/> surfaces due to apical resorption as well as the union of the<lb/> roots by the cementum and the presence of an apical main<lb/> foramen and foramina (<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>).<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Seven specimens presented severe club shape<lb/> hypercementosis. Only 3 cases (42.8%) showed apical main<lb/> foramen and apical foramina. The main foramen diameter<lb/> varied between 100 and 300 µm. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> shows the presence<lb/> of tiny foramina at the apex of the mesiobuccal root of a<lb/> maxillary molar. A mineralized structure partially<lb/> obliterating the apical foramina was observed in 1 specimen.<lb/></p>

			<head level="2">CCH Hypercementosis<lb/></head>

			<p>The CCH type hypercementosis presented depressions<lb/> close to the apical foramen and thick cementum grossly<lb/> deposited on the lateral surface of the root. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> presents<lb/> buccal roots of a maxillary molar with depressions close to<lb/> the apical foramen and a thick cementum layer on the lateral<lb/> root surface. The average diameter of the main apical<lb/> foramen was 325 µm, and only 3 specimens (42.85%)<lb/> presented foramina. A mandibular molar and a residual root<lb/> also presented irregularities due to the presence of areas of<lb/> resorption.<lb/></p>

			<head level="2">Focal hypercementosis<lb/></head>

			<p>Regular foramina were observed in the teeth with focal<lb/> hypercementosis. The maxillary canines showed foramina<lb/> in areas of irregular cementum deposition (<ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>). Data<lb/> referring to the main apical foramen and foramina are<lb/> displayed presented in <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<figure>
				FIGURE 2- Moderate club shape hypercementosis. (A) Mesial and distal roots of a mandibular molar. (B) Greater magnification<lb/> of the apical foramen and foramina. Irregular root resorption areas are observed close to the apical foramen and foramina.<lb/> Original magnifications: (A) ×20, (B) ×50<lb/>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				FIGURE 3- Severe club shape hypercementosis. Root apex<lb/> of a maxillary molar, showing the presence of 2 apical<lb/> foramina. Original magnification: ×1,000<lb/>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				FIGURE 4- Circular cementum hyperplasia<lb/> hypercementosis. Original magnification: ×15<lb/> FIGURE 5-Focal hypercementosis. (A) Morphologic aspects of the foramina located in the distobuccal root of a maxillary<lb/> molar. (B) Openings of the foramina at the middle third at the mesiobuccal surface of a maxillary canine. Original magnifications:<lb/> (A) ×100, (B) ×50<lb/>
			</figure>
			
			<figure type="table"> Hypercementosis<lb/> Specimens<lb/> Main foramen<lb/> Foramina<lb/> Obliteration<lb/> n<lb/> %<lb/> n<lb/> %<lb/> n<lb/> %<lb/> mild<lb/> 12<lb/> 7<lb/> 58.3<lb/> 6<lb/> 50.0<lb/> 3<lb/> 25.0<lb/> Club shape<lb/> moderate<lb/> 7<lb/> 6<lb/> 85.7<lb/> 6<lb/> 85.7<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> severe<lb/> 7<lb/> 3<lb/> 42.8<lb/> 3<lb/> 42.8<lb/> 4<lb/> 57.1<lb/> CCH<lb/> 7<lb/> 6<lb/> 85.7<lb/> 3<lb/> 42.8<lb/> 1<lb/> 14.3<lb/> Focal<lb/> 8<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> 6<lb/> 75.0<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> Total<lb/> 41<lb/> 22<lb/> 53.6<lb/> 24<lb/> 58.5<lb/> 8<lb/> 19.5<lb/>
			TABLE 2- Apical main foramen and foramina observed in the 41 examined specimens<lb/>
			</figure>


			<head level="1">DISCUSSION<lb/></head>

			<p>Although there are not many studies regarding this<lb/> subject, hypercementosis can be considered as a common<lb/> finding in endodontic daily practice. The impact of<lb/> hypercementosis on endodontic prognosis and its direct<lb/> influence on therapeutic procedures still unclear 20 . Whether<lb/> to keep instrumentation and root canal filling above or<lb/> beyond the cementum-dentin-canal junction in teeth with<lb/> hypercementosis is a difficult clinical choice. The apical<lb/> limits for root canal preparation depend on different<lb/> reference landmarks 16 , and hypercementosis might impair<lb/> such decisions.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>In the present study, SEM analysis of the root apex of<lb/> permanent teeth with hypercementosis provided a rapid<lb/> evaluation of the structure with identification of the main<lb/> foramen and apical foramina, and determination of their<lb/> dimensions. Moreover how and where the apical foramen<lb/> and accessory foramina are displaced due to<lb/> hypercementosis, and possible variations related to its<lb/> morphotypes were observed. Therefore, knowing the apical<lb/> surface of teeth with hypercementosis is important for<lb/> endodontic treatment planning.<lb/></p>

			<p>The diameter of the main apical foramen ranged in our<lb/> study from 100 to 500 µm. Openings with diameters inferior<lb/> to 100 µm were considered as apical foramina 15 . The<lb/> presence of apical foramina in areas with hypercementosis<lb/> would indicate that cementum deposition occurred<lb/> respecting the neurovascular supply 18 . In the present study,<lb/> the observation of apical foramina in 24 specimens supports<lb/> this idea. The absence of cementum deposition obliterating<lb/> those foramina may be related by cytokines and growth<lb/> factors released by endothelial cells and nervous branches 8 .<lb/> Partial or total obliteration of the apical foramina found in<lb/> the present study could be a reactive response to the cause<lb/> of the tooth extraction 8 .<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Most root apexes of teeth with mild club shape<lb/> hypercementosis did not present surface irregularities and<lb/> cementum resorption, though presenting a large number of<lb/> apical foramina. Moderate club shape hypercementosis<lb/> showed irregular areas and apical foramina. The severe club<lb/> shape hypercementosis presented a decrease in the number<lb/> and sometimes obliteration of the apical foramen.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The present study found that the circular cementum<lb/> hyperplasia type of hypercementosis was not associated with<lb/> apical resorption. Unless proven otherwise, reactive<lb/> mechanisms due to chronic periapical lesions can be<lb/> involved in the process. This type of hypercementosis might<lb/> represent additional anatomic niches to bacterial<lb/> colonization during root canal infection, which contributes<lb/> to the presence of refractory lesions 21 .<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The focal type of hypercementosis presents foramina<lb/> on its surface, even when sidelong located on the roots. This<lb/> observation warns for the development of endo-perio lesions<lb/> if these openings are be reached by bacteria and its toxic<lb/> products 11,21 .<lb/></p>

			<head level="1">CONCLUSIONS<lb/></head>

			<p>The detection of a large number of foramina in the apical<lb/> third of teeth with hypercementosis or even the possible<lb/> existence of apical foramen obliteration contributes to<lb/> understand the difficulties faced during endodontic treatment<lb/> of these cases. Constant research seeking the development<lb/> of techniques and materials that provide a correct<lb/> instrumentation and filling of these teeth should be<lb/> encouraged.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
