<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_6603563a"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>Pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) is the fourth leading<lb/> cause of cancer-related death in Western countries. Although the<lb/> prognosis of patients with many types of cancer has improved<lb/> recently due to advances in diagnostic and therapeutic modalities,<lb/> the outlook for patients with PDAC still remains dismal with a<lb/> median survival of just 6 months from diagnosis and an overall 5-<lb/>year survival rate of less than 5% (<ref type="biblio">Warshaw and Fernandez-del<lb/> Castillo, 1992; Murr et al, 1994; Jemal et al, 2005</ref>). Many previous<lb/> studies have attempted to elucidate the molecular mechanisms<lb/> underlying pancreatic tumorigenesis, but it is still not fully<lb/> understood. Therefore, a better understanding of the genes<lb/> involved in tumour growth and progression is necessary for the<lb/> development of novel diagnostic and therapeutic strategies that<lb/> could improve the outcome of this deadly disease.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Array-based comparative genomic hybridisation (array CGH) is<lb/> a powerful technique that has been used to detect DNA copy<lb/> number alterations across the entire genome of malignant tumours<lb/> (Solinas-<ref type="biblio">Toldo et al, 1997; Pinkel et al, 1998; Pollack et al, 1999;<lb/> Albertson et al, 2000; Snijders et al, 2001; Fiegler et al, 2003</ref>).<lb/> Compared to conventional CGH, the significantly improved<lb/> resolution of array CGH permits highly accurate mapping of<lb/> DNA copy number changes throughout the genome. In cancer,<lb/> genomic alterations contribute to dysregulation of the expression<lb/> levels of oncogenes and tumour suppressor genes, the accumula-<lb/>tion of which is correlated with tumour progression (<ref type="biblio">Ried et al,<lb/> 1999</ref>). Therefore, array CGH provides a promising starting point<lb/> for the identification of novel candidate genes affected by such<lb/> genomic imbalances. Several array CGH investigations of PDAC<lb/> have already been reported, but all these studies were performed<lb/> on cell lines or whole tissue samples (<ref type="biblio">Aguirre et al, 2004;<lb/> Heidenblad et al, 2004; Holzmann et al, 2004; Mahlamaki et al,<lb/> 2004; Bashyam et al, 2005; Gysin et al, 2005; Nowak et al, 2005</ref>). In<lb/> cell lines, culture-induced genetic adaptation may be induced<lb/> during the establishment of cell lines in in vitro conditions. On the<lb/> other hand, PDAC tissues are characterised by a desmoplastic<lb/> reaction, with neoplastic cells constituting only a small proportion<lb/> of the tumour mass. Therefore, cytogenetic analysis using bulk<lb/> tissue samples is invariably hampered by contamination with non-<lb/>neoplastic cells.<lb/></p>

			<p>The aim of this study is to identify novel genetic abnormalities<lb/> that precisely reflect the characteristics of tumour cells in vivo. For<lb/> this purpose, we applied array CGH to 23 microdissected PDAC<lb/> tissue samples that consist of purified populations of cancer cells.<lb/> Then, a subset of identified genetic alterations was evaluated in an<lb/> independent sample set of 19 PDAC cases using fluorescence in<lb/> situ hybridisation (FISH) analysis. Finally, in situ RNA hybridisa-<lb/>tion (ISH) and reverse transcription – PCR (RT – PCR) were<lb/> performed to assess whether the identified genetic alteration could<lb/> lead to significant change in transcript level of the gene in<lb/> question.<lb/></p>

			<head level="1">MATERIALS AND METHODS<lb/></head>

			<head level="2">Tissue samples<lb/></head> 
			
			<p>A total of 23 fresh-frozen PDAC specimens were obtained<lb/> surgically or at autopsy from Yamaguchi University School of<lb/> Medicine, Japan, with appropriate ethical approval (<ref type="table">Table 1</ref>). All<lb/> the tissues were confirmed histologically by a pathologist. Tissue<lb/> microdissection was performed manually to collect more than 90%<lb/> of tumour cells in all the cases as described previously (<ref type="biblio">Harada<lb/> et al, 2002a</ref>). Briefly, only cancerous regions were microdissected<lb/> using a sterile 26-gauge needle from several serial tissue sections<lb/> (20 mm thickness) under visualisation with an inverted microscope<lb/> (Nikon 66906, Tokyo, Japan). DNA was extracted from at least<lb/> 5000 tumour cells according to the standard protocol. Reference<lb/> DNA was obtained from lymphocytes of both healthy male and<lb/> female volunteers. In addition, another series of 19 formalin-fixed,<lb/> paraffin-embedded tumour sections (4 mm thickness) were pro-<lb/>vided from Yamaguchi University (n ¼ 10) and Tohoku University<lb/> School of Medicine, Japan (n ¼ 9), for FISH and ISH analyses<lb/> (<ref type="table">Table 1</ref>). Owing to the limited accessibility of clinical specimens,<lb/> the samples used in array CGH were not available for FISH and<lb/> ISH. For RT – PCR, 16 fresh-frozen PDAC tissues and two normal<lb/> pancreas tissues were obtained from the Human Biomaterials<lb/> Resource Centre, Department of Histopathology, Charing Cross<lb/> </p>

			<figure type="table">
				Table 1 The clinicopathological data of PDAC tissue samples<lb/>
				
				Sample<lb/> Age<lb/> Sex<lb/> Location a<lb/> Histology b<lb/> T<lb/> N<lb/> M<lb/> Stage<lb/> (A) Microdissected fresh-frozen tissue samples used for array CGH (n ¼ 23)<lb/> PC1<lb/> 66<lb/> F<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> II<lb/> PC2<lb/> 66<lb/> F<lb/> P(Pb)<lb/> well<lb/> 3<lb/> 1a<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC3<lb/> 66<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1b<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC4<lb/> 59<lb/> F<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1b<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC5<lb/> 64<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1b<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC6<lb/> 47<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 0<lb/> IVa<lb/> PC7<lb/> 66<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 0<lb/> IVa<lb/> PC8<lb/> 69<lb/> F<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> poor<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 0<lb/> IVa<lb/> PC9<lb/> 73<lb/> F<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 0<lb/> IVa<lb/> PC10<lb/> 56<lb/> M<lb/> P(Pt)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC11<lb/> 76<lb/> F<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC12<lb/> 63<lb/> F<lb/> P(Pb)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC13<lb/> 78<lb/> F<lb/> P(Pt)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC14<lb/> 68<lb/> F<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC15<lb/> 65<lb/> M<lb/> P(Pb)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC16<lb/> 65<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC17<lb/> 60<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC18<lb/> 76<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC19<lb/> 54<lb/> F<lb/> P(Pb)<lb/> poor<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC20<lb/> 72<lb/> F<lb/> P(Pt)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC34<lb/> 60<lb/> M<lb/> LM<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC35<lb/> 75<lb/> M<lb/> LM<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC36<lb/> 67<lb/> F<lb/> LM<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1b<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> (B) Formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tissue sections used for FISH and ISH (n ¼ 19)<lb/> PC37<lb/> 74<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 2<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> I<lb/> PC38<lb/> 72<lb/> M<lb/> P(Pt)<lb/> poor<lb/> 3<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> II<lb/> PC39<lb/> 70<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC40<lb/> 58<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC41<lb/> 69<lb/> F<lb/> P(Pb)<lb/> well<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC42<lb/> 51<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> poor<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC43<lb/> 73<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC44<lb/> 59<lb/> M<lb/> P(Pb)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> III<lb/> PC45<lb/> 53<lb/> F<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> IVa<lb/> PC46<lb/> 53<lb/> M<lb/> P(Pb)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> IVa<lb/> PC47<lb/> 56<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> well<lb/> 4<lb/> 1<lb/> 0<lb/> IVa<lb/> PC48<lb/> 57<lb/> F<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC49<lb/> 65<lb/> F<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC50<lb/> 59<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC51<lb/> 61<lb/> M<lb/> P(Ph)<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC52<lb/> 74<lb/> M<lb/> P(Pb)<lb/> poor<lb/> 4<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC53<lb/> 57<lb/> F<lb/> LM<lb/> mod<lb/> 3<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC54<lb/> 61<lb/> M<lb/> LM<lb/> mod<lb/> 4<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> PC55<lb/> 74<lb/> M<lb/> LM<lb/> poor<lb/> 4<lb/> 1<lb/> 1<lb/> IVb<lb/> a<lb/>
				
				P ¼ primary lesion; Ph ¼ head; Pb ¼ body; Pt ¼ tail of the pancreas; LM ¼ liver metastatic lesion. b mod ¼ moderately; poor ¼ poorly differentiated tubular adenocarcinoma.<lb/> PDAC ¼ pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma; FISH ¼ fluorescence in situ hybridisation; ISH ¼ in situ RNA hybridisation.<lb/>
			</figure>

			<p>Hospital, London, UK, with full ethical approval of the host<lb/> institution. The clinicopathological information was not available<lb/> for these anonymous samples. Haematoxylin – eosin-stained slides<lb/> were examined to ensure a content of 60 – 80% tumour cells before<lb/> use and then, total RNA was extracted directly from homogenised<lb/> tissues using TRIZOL (Invitrogen Ltd, Paisley, UK).<lb/></p>

			<head level="2">CGH arrays and image acquisition<lb/></head>

			<p>The whole-genome CGH arrays were produced at the Wellcome<lb/> Trust Sanger Institute and consist of 3125 BAC/PAC clones that<lb/> cover the entire human genome at 1 Mb resolution (<ref type="biblio">Fiegler et al,<lb/> 2003</ref>). All the clone details are available on the Ensembl genome<lb/> browser (v39, June 2006; http://www.ensembl.org/Homo_sapiens/<lb/> index.html).<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Array CGH was performed as described previously, with minor<lb/> modifications (<ref type="biblio">Fiegler et al, 2003; Hurst et al, 2004</ref>). Briefly,<lb/> tumour and reference DNAs (300 ng) were labelled with Cy5-dCTP<lb/> and Cy3-dCTP, respectively. Hybridisation was carried out at 371C<lb/> for 36 h in a hybridisation chamber (GeneMachines, San Carlos,<lb/> CA, USA). After washing the slides, fluorescence intensities were<lb/> measured on an Axon 4000B scanner (Axon Instruments Inc.,<lb/> Burlingame, CA, USA) and the raw images were analysed using the<lb/> GenePix Pro 4.0 software (Axon). Duplicate hybridisations were<lb/> performed for each sample to verify the reproducibility of the data<lb/> except for one case (PC5). The correlation coefficients were<lb/> calculated on the normalised tumour channel and observed to<lb/> range from 0.63 to 0.90 (data not shown).<lb/></p>

			<head level="2">Statistical and data analysis<lb/></head>

			<p>The CGH arrays were read with the UCSF &apos;SPOT&apos; software to<lb/> produce raw text files (<ref type="biblio">Jain et al, 2002</ref>). These files were read into R<lb/> and normalised (using the loess intensity-dependent method),<lb/> using the &apos;limma&apos; package (<ref type="biblio">Smyth, 2005</ref>; The R Development Core<lb/> <ref type="biblio">Team, 2006</ref>); background correction was omitted in this case, as<lb/> visual inspection showed it increased the scatter in both the MA<lb/> and chromosomal-location plots, and the correlation statistics<lb/> were worse with background subtraction, indicative of low levels of<lb/> background on the slides being misestimated. The log 2 -trans-<lb/>formed normalised data were then pre-processed to average any<lb/> on-slide replicates using the &apos;snapCGH&apos; package from Bioconduc-<lb/>tor and segmented into local regions of constant copy number by<lb/> circular binary segmentation (<ref type="biblio">Gentleman et al, 2004; Olshen et al,<lb/> 2004</ref>). The sample levels (two replicates for each tumour per clone)<lb/> were summarised by means to give tumour-level data (one<lb/> measurement per clone for each tumour). These data were then<lb/> used in a linear model that estimated the fold change across the<lb/> tumours, along with a P-value that the average log 2 -fold change<lb/> between the tumour channel and the normal channel was non-zero<lb/> (for both the normalised data and the locally smoothed data – data<lb/> not shown for the latter). Clones that had an uncorrected P-value<lb/> below 0.001 were considered to be significant candidates.<lb/></p>

			<head level="2">Two-colour FISH<lb/></head> 
			
			<p>Four human BAC clones (RP11-403N12, RP11-232C20, RP11-8H2<lb/> and RP11-350K6) were purchased from BACPAC Resources<lb/> (Oakland, CA, USA) and these DNAs were labelled with Cy3-<lb/>dCTP using BioPrime Array CGH Genomic Labeling System<lb/> (Invitrogen). Centromeric probes for chromosomes 7 and 18<lb/> (CEP7 and 18), labelled with SpectrumGreen, were purchased from<lb/> Vysis (Downers Grove, IL, USA). The specificity of all the probes<lb/> was confirmed by hybridisation onto Normal Male Metaphase<lb/> (Vysis).<lb/> Two-colour FISH was performed as described previously (<ref type="biblio">Lu<lb/> et al, 1999</ref>). DNA copy number was evaluated for each probe by<lb/> counting spots in at least 100 nuclei. A ratio was calculated<lb/> between the average copy number of the BAC probes and of<lb/> corresponding centromeric probes. Based on hybridisation in 10<lb/> normal pancreatic tissues (acinar and ductal cells), the threshold of<lb/> gain and loss was defined as the ratios of 41.16 ( þ 2 standard<lb/> deviation (s.d.)) and o0.87 (À2 s.d.), respectively (data not<lb/> shown). Our approach was to use normal samples to estimate<lb/> overall noise levels: choosing the threshold on the tumour samples<lb/> corresponding to a 72 s.d. of the normal samples indicates a<lb/> roughly 5% false-positive rate if the tumour samples were<lb/> commensurate with diploidy.<lb/></p>

			<p>In situ RNA hybridisation for SEC11L3<lb/></p>

			<p>The SEC11L3 probe was amplified by PCR from OriGene clone<lb/> TC123085 (OriGene Technologies, Inc., Rockville, MD, USA) that<lb/> encodes full-length cDNA of SEC11L3. The primers used to amplify<lb/> a 216-bp SEC11L3 product are as follows: forward 5 0 -TTGGATA<lb/> TCTTCGGGGACCT-3 0 and reverse 5 0 -GTCTTCCCGGAAATTTGT<lb/> GA-3 0 . The PCR product was cloned into the pCR4-TOPO vector<lb/> using the TOPO cloning kit (Invitrogen) to create pCR4-SEC11L3-<lb/>ISH. Positive clones were verified by sequence analysis. The pCR4-<lb/>SEC11L3-ISH plasmid was linearised with PstI for the sense probe<lb/> and NotI for the antisense probe. After removing restriction<lb/> endonucleases, riboprobes were synthesised from 1 mg of template<lb/> DNA and digoxigenin (DIG) were labelled using a DIG RNA<lb/> labeling kit (Roche Diagnostics GmbH, Mannheim, Germany). T3<lb/> and T7 polymerases were used to synthesise antisense probes and<lb/> sense probes, respectively. DIG incorporation of riboprobes was<lb/> verified by DOT blot with anti-digoxigenin-AP Fab fragments<lb/> (Roche). Antisense and sense riboprobes for SEC11L3 were<lb/> hybridised to 19 tissue sections using the Ventana Discovery<lb/> System with Ventana Ribomap and Bluemap kits. Expression of<lb/> SEC11L3 mRNA in cancer cells was compared to that of non-<lb/>neoplastic epithelial cells (ductal, acinar, intestinal and hepatic<lb/> cells) on the identical specimen and judged using a 0 – 2 score<lb/> (0 ¼ no staining, 1 ¼ weak intensity, 2 ¼ intensity comparable to<lb/> non-neoplastic counterparts).<lb/></p>

			<head level="2">Reverse transcription – PCR for SEC11L3<lb/></head> 
			
			<p>cDNAs were synthesised from 1 mg of total RNA using an oligo dT<lb/> primer and the Multiscribe reverse transcription kit (Applied<lb/> Biosystems, Warrington, Cheshire, UK) as instructed by the<lb/> manufacturer. Reverse transcription was followed by 30 PCR<lb/> cycles (1 min of denaturation at 941C, 1 min of annealing at 551C<lb/> and 1 min of extension at 721C). Primers for SEC11L3 are the same<lb/> as those designed in ISH. Primers for 18S ribosomal RNA, which<lb/> was used as an endogenous control for normalisation, are as<lb/> follows: forward 5 0 -CGCCGCTAGAGGTGAAATTC-3 0 and reverse<lb/> 5 0 -CATTCTTGGCAAATGCTTTCG-3 0 . Amplified products were<lb/> separated on 1% agarose gels and visualised with ethidium<lb/> bromide.<lb/></p>

			<head level="1">RESULTS<lb/></head>

			<head level="2">Comparison of array CGH profiles in microdissected<lb/> tissues and cell lines<lb/></head> 
			
			<p>A total of 23 microdissected PDAC tissues were analysed by array<lb/> CGH. Applying highly stringent statistical conditions (Po0.001),<lb/> we could identify the regions of nonrandom genomic changes in<lb/> PDAC. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows overall copy number changes for each<lb/> chromosome and the entire data set of all clones is available in<lb/> Supplementary Table 1 (the raw data set for all the experiments is<lb/> shown in Supplementary Table 2). A total of 1015 clones met the<lb/> statistical criterion; 17% of clones (508 clones including 698<lb/> candidate genes) showed genetic gain and 17% (507 clones<lb/> including 1254 genes) showed loss. The array CGH profiles were<lb/> compared to the previous reports in which PDAC-derived cell lines<lb/> were analysed (<ref type="biblio">Aguirre et al, 2004; Bashyam et al, 2005; Gysin et al,<lb/> 2005; Nowak et al, 2005</ref>). Although they displayed similar<lb/> spectrum patterns of genetic alterations overall, we found that<lb/> there were apparently different breakpoints in our profiles. Our<lb/> data showed several segmented gains on chromosome 2, which<lb/></p>

			<figure>
				Chromosome 1<lb/> Chromosome 2<lb/> Chromosome 3<lb/> Chromosome 4<lb/> Chromosome 5<lb/> Chromosome 6<lb/> Chromosome 8<lb/> Chromosome 9<lb/> Chromosome 10<lb/> Chromosome 11<lb/> Chromosome 12<lb/> Chromosome 13<lb/> Chromosome 14<lb/> Chromosome 15<lb/> Chromosome 16<lb/> Chromosome 17<lb/> Chromosome 19<lb/> Chromosome 7<lb/> Chromosome 18<lb/> Chromosome 20<lb/> Chromosome 21<lb/> Chromosome 22<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> Mean log<lb/> 2 ratio<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> Mean log<lb/> 2 ratio<lb/> Mean log<lb/> 2 ratio<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> Mean log<lb/> 2 ratio<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> Mean log<lb/> 2 ratio<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> Mean log<lb/> 2 ratio<lb/> RUNX3<lb/> MLH1<lb/> MYC<lb/> BRCA2<lb/> KRAS<lb/> CDH1<lb/> TP53<lb/> ERBB2<lb/> MAP2K4<lb/> NCOA3<lb/> SCAP2<lb/> BCMP11<lb/> EGFR<lb/> EGFR<lb/> DCC<lb/> ATP5A1<lb/> SEC11L3<lb/> SMAD4<lb/> MYB<lb/> MLH1<lb/> 0<lb/> 50<lb/> 100 150<lb/> 0<lb/> 50<lb/> 100<lb/> 150<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> 50<lb/> 20 40 60 80<lb/> 100<lb/> 100<lb/> 0 20 40 60 80 100<lb/> 120<lb/> 120<lb/> 0 20 40 60 80 100 120<lb/> 0 20 40 60 80<lb/> 0<lb/> 2 0<lb/> 4 0<lb/> 6 0<lb/> 60<lb/> 80<lb/> 0<lb/> 2 0<lb/> 4 0<lb/> 6 0<lb/> 8 0<lb/> 0<lb/> 2 0<lb/> 4 0<lb/> 6 0<lb/> 0<lb/> 2 0<lb/> 4 0<lb/> 0<lb/> 2 0<lb/> 10<lb/> 40<lb/> 30<lb/> 0<lb/> 2 0<lb/> 10<lb/> 40<lb/> 60<lb/> 30<lb/> 0<lb/> 2 0<lb/> 10<lb/> 50<lb/> 30 40<lb/> 60<lb/> 70<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> 20<lb/> 50<lb/> 100<lb/> 150<lb/> 10<lb/> 50<lb/> 30<lb/> 40<lb/> 0<lb/> 2 0<lb/> 10<lb/> 50<lb/> 30 40<lb/> 60<lb/> 80<lb/> 100<lb/> 100<lb/> 120<lb/> 140<lb/> 0 20 40 60 80<lb/> 0<lb/> 20<lb/> 40<lb/> 60<lb/> 80<lb/> 100<lb/> 100<lb/> 120 140<lb/> 150<lb/> 200<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.2<lb/> –0.2<lb/> –0.4<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 0<lb/> 50<lb/> 100 150 200<lb/> 50<lb/> 100<lb/> 150<lb/> 0<lb/> 50<lb/> 100<lb/> 150<lb/> 0<lb/>

 		   		Figure 1
				
				Summary of overall genome-wide alterations in a total of 23 microdissected PDAC tissues. Genetic gains are shown as green dots and losses as<lb/> red dots (Y axis) at each clone position along the chromosome (X axis). Several representative clones with no genetic changes are depicted as black dots.<lb/> Square-shaped dots indicate the clones validated by FISH, whereas triangle dots indicate previously identified genes in PDAC. Vertical dotted lines represent<lb/> chromosome centromeres.<lb/>
 			</figure>
 
 			<p>have rarely been observed in cell lines. In contrast, losses of 4q and<lb/> 13q and gains of 11q and 20q in cell lines were not as frequent as in<lb/> our microdissected samples. Next, we focused on individual clones<lb/> harbouring the genes that are known to be dysregulated in cell<lb/> lines. Increased copy numbers were detected in the regions<lb/> including MYC (8q24.21) and NCOA3/AIB1 (20q13.12), while<lb/> genetic losses were observed in the regions containing SMAD4<lb/> (18q21.1), TP53 (17p13.1), MAP2K4 (17p11.2) and RUNX3<lb/> (1p36.11). However, using the rigorous statistical conditions<lb/> employed, we identified neither genetic gains of KRAS (12p12.1),<lb/> MYB (6q23.3), EGFR (7p11.2) and ERBB2 (17q12) nor losses of<lb/> MLH1 (3p22.2), BRCA2 (13q13.1) and CDH1 (16q22.1). (All the<lb/> genes cited here are depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> .)<lb/></p>
			
			<head level="2">Contiguous regions of nonrandom copy number changes<lb/></head>

			<p>In addition to numerous localised alterations, we detected a total<lb/> of 41 contiguous regions (43.0 Mb) of nonrandom genomic<lb/> changes (<ref type="table">Table 2</ref>). For instance, increased copy number was<lb/> detected in the 26.0 Mb region of 7p22.2 – p15.1 that contains 48<lb/> known or hypothetical protein-coding genes. We also defined the<lb/> regions of genetic gains on 1q, 3q, 5p, 5q, 8q and 12p, which may<lb/> represent loci for candidate oncogenes in PDAC. The largest region<lb/> of copy number loss was from 17p13.3 to 17p12 (13.6 Mb), which<lb/> covers a total of 53 candidate genes including TP53 (17p13.1) as<lb/> well as MAP2K4 (17p11.2). We delineated three contiguous regions<lb/> of genomic loss on 18q, which is known to be a site of frequent<lb/> deletions in PDAC, 18q21. 2 – q22.1 (12.0 Mb), 18q22.3 – q23<lb/> (7.1 Mb) and 18q12.3 – q21.2 (6.9 Mb). The region of 18q21.2 –<lb/> q22.1 harbours 16 candidate genes in addition to SMAD4 (18q21.1)<lb/> that is one of the most recurrently inactivated tumour suppressor<lb/> genes in PDAC. The region of 18q12.3 – q21.2 contains a total of 23<lb/> putative target genes, whereas seven genes are included in the<lb/> 7.1 Mb region of 18q22.3 – q23. Interestingly, the clone encom-<lb/>passing DCC (18q21.2) has shown an apparent discontinuity<lb/> between two broad regions of genetic loss (18q12.3 – q21.2 and<lb/> 18q21.2 – q22.1) in our 23 microdissected PDAC sample set<lb/> (<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<head level="2">Verification of genetic changes by two-colour FISH<lb/></head>

			<p>To investigate prospectively whether the identified genetic<lb/> abnormalities are prevalent in PDAC, interphase FISH analysis<lb/> was performed using an independent sample set (<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>).<lb/> Previous cytogenetic studies have shown that chromosome arms<lb/> 7p and 18q may include oncogenes and tumour suppressor genes<lb/> that play a critical role in pancreatic carcinogenesis (<ref type="biblio">Griffin et al,<lb/> 1995; Hahn et al, 1995; Fukushige et al, 1997, 1998; Mahlamaki<lb/> et al, 1997; Schleger et al, 2000; Harada et al, 2002a; Iacobuzio-<lb/>Donahue et al, 2004</ref>). Therefore, we prioritised three regions<lb/> (7p22.3 – p15.1, 18q12.3 – q21.2 and 18q21.2 – q22.1) of nonrandom<lb/> copy number changes detected in array CGH and a subset of four<lb/> BAC clones (RP11-403N12 at 7p21.1, RP11-232C20 at 7p15.2,<lb/> RP11-8H2 at 18q21.1 and RP11-350K6 at 18q21.32) were selected<lb/> from those regions (<ref type="table">Table 3</ref>). As shown in <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>, deletion in the<lb/> locus encompassing SEC11L3 (18q21.32) was observed to be the<lb/> most recurrent alteration (13 out of 19 samples; 68%) (<ref type="figure">Figure 2B</ref>).<lb/> The region 18q21.1 defined by RP11-8H2 was deleted in 11 out of<lb/> 19 cases (58%) and contains three known candidate genes:<lb/> ATP5A1, PSTPIP2 and CCDC5. RP11-403N12 including BCMP11<lb/> (7p21.1) showed an increased copy number in 10 out of 19 cases<lb/> (53%) (<ref type="figure">Figure 2C</ref>), whereas gain of the region at RP11-232C20<lb/> containing SCAP2 (7p15.2) was demonstrated in seven out of 19<lb/> cases (37%) (<ref type="figure">Figure 2D</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<head>SEC11L3 mRNA downregulation detected by ISH and<lb/> RT –PCR<lb/></head> 
			
			<p>Subsequently, the SEC11L3 mRNA level was evaluated by ISH<lb/> (<ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>). Firstly, we tested several different types of normal<lb/> epithelial cells from the pancreas, intestine and liver. Normal<lb/> pancreatic tissues showed strong mRNA expression of SEC11L3 in<lb/> both ductal and acinar cells (score 2), whereas there was weak<lb/> expression in islet cells (score 1). Strong expression was also<lb/> observed in normal intestinal and hepatic cells (score 2). Of 19<lb/> PDAC cases, SEC11L3 mRNA was downregulated (score 0 – 1) in 11<lb/> cases (58%), whereas it was unchanged (score 2) in eight cases<lb/></p> 
			
			<figure type="table">
				Table 2 Contiguous regions (43.0 Mb) of chromosomal changes in a total of 23 microdissected PDAC tissues<lb/> 
				
				Locus<lb/> Start (bp)<lb/> End (bp)<lb/> Size (Mb)<lb/> Mean log2<lb/> Locus<lb/> Start (bp)<lb/> End (bp)<lb/> Size (Mb)<lb/> Mean log2<lb/> 1q24.1 – q25.1<lb/> 163 809 021<lb/> 173 127 283<lb/> 9.3<lb/> 0.235<lb/> 1p35.1 – p34.3<lb/> 34 152 076<lb/> 38 379 441<lb/> 4.2<lb/> À0.232<lb/> 1q25.2 – q25.3<lb/> 177 942 453<lb/> 181 046 133<lb/> 3.0<lb/> 0.208<lb/> 4p16.2 – p16.1<lb/> 5 094 062<lb/> 8 313 477<lb/> 3.2<lb/> À0.216<lb/> 1q31.1 – q31.3<lb/> 187 406 225<lb/> 1 957 10 013<lb/> 8.3<lb/> 0.255<lb/> 6p21.32 – p21.31<lb/> 32 031 967<lb/> 34 013 145<lb/> 4.0<lb/> À0.219<lb/> 1q41<lb/> 215 371 867<lb/> 219 919 554<lb/> 4.5<lb/> 0.242<lb/> 6q21<lb/> 108 154 127<lb/> 112 486 834<lb/> 4.3<lb/> À0.181<lb/> 1q42.2 – q43<lb/> 231 700 764<lb/> 241 495 322<lb/> 9.8<lb/> 0.253<lb/> 6q25.2 – q25.3<lb/> 155 289 734<lb/> 158 440 778<lb/> 3.2<lb/> À0.204<lb/> 2p16.1 – p14<lb/> 60 927 185<lb/> 64 676 357<lb/> 4.8<lb/> 0.171<lb/> 8p22 – p21.3<lb/> 17 784 184<lb/> 21 872 595<lb/> 4.1<lb/> À0.264<lb/> 2q22.2 – q22.3<lb/> 143 499 638<lb/> 146 775 971<lb/> 3.3<lb/> 0.168<lb/> 9p24.3 – p24.1<lb/> 190<lb/> 6 659 690<lb/> 6.7<lb/> À0.228<lb/> 2q32.1<lb/> 185 140 061<lb/> 188 357 186<lb/> 3.2<lb/> 0.161<lb/> 9p22.1 – p21.3<lb/> 19 310 506<lb/> 23 557 472<lb/> 4.2<lb/> À0.256<lb/> 2q32.3<lb/> 192 914 919<lb/> 196 752 218<lb/> 3.8<lb/> 0.146<lb/> 9q22.31 – q22.33<lb/> 94 281 893<lb/> 100 889 311<lb/> 6.6<lb/> À0.171<lb/> 3q26.1<lb/> 163 532 324<lb/> 167 501 265<lb/> 4.0<lb/> 0.237<lb/> 9q33.3 – q34.11<lb/> 126 127 921<lb/> 129 390 787<lb/> 3.3<lb/> À0.216<lb/> 5p15.31 – p15.2<lb/> 7 449 057<lb/> 10 495 937<lb/> 3.0<lb/> 0.165<lb/> 9q34.13 – q34.3<lb/> 133 982 008<lb/> 137 333 442<lb/> 3.4<lb/> À0.226<lb/> 5p14.3 – p14.1<lb/> 20 429 524<lb/> 28 918 008<lb/> 8.5<lb/> 0.232<lb/> 17p13.3 – p12<lb/> 800 495<lb/> 14 360 892<lb/> 13.6<lb/> À0.252<lb/> 5q11.1 – q11.2<lb/> 50 061 482<lb/> 54 725 678<lb/> 4.7<lb/> 0.174<lb/> 18q12.3 – q21.2<lb/> 41 216 566<lb/> 48 119 508<lb/> 6.9<lb/> À0.350<lb/> 5q12.2 – q13.1<lb/> 63 325 516<lb/> 66 888 015<lb/> 3.6<lb/> 0.149<lb/> 18q21.2 – q22.1<lb/> 49 795 841<lb/> 61 752 947<lb/> 12.0<lb/> À0.252<lb/> 5q14.1 – q14.3<lb/> 80 075 105<lb/> 86 472 400<lb/> 6.4<lb/> 0.168<lb/> 18q22.3 – q23<lb/> 68 809 458<lb/> 75 940 259<lb/> 7.1<lb/> À0.294<lb/> 5q14.3<lb/> 87 676 680<lb/> 90 964 362<lb/> 3.3<lb/> 0.170<lb/> 21q21.3 – q22.11<lb/> 29 627 040<lb/> 34 602 938<lb/> 5.0<lb/> À0.182<lb/> 7p22.2 – p15.1<lb/> 2 607 390<lb/> 28 603 446<lb/> 26.0<lb/> 0.207<lb/> 22q11.22 – q12.1<lb/> 21 400 636<lb/> 25 896 652<lb/> 4.5<lb/> À0.205<lb/> 7p14.1<lb/> 38 185 228<lb/> 41 345 287<lb/> 3.2<lb/> 0.170<lb/> 22q12.2-q12.3<lb/> 28 379 384<lb/> 31 627 100<lb/> 3.2<lb/> À0.180<lb/> 7q21.11<lb/> 79 539 131<lb/> 83 414 012<lb/> 3.9<lb/> 0.219<lb/> 8q21.11 – q21.13<lb/> 77 234 275<lb/> 81 648 851<lb/> 4.4<lb/> 0.225<lb/> 8q21.13 – q21.3<lb/> 82 640 038<lb/> 89 400 934<lb/> 6.8<lb/> 0.271<lb/> 8q24.11 – q24.13<lb/> 118 297 084<lb/> 123 697 997<lb/> 5.4<lb/> 0.254<lb/> 12p12.3 – p12.1<lb/> 19 403 674<lb/> 23 784 534<lb/> 4.4<lb/> 0.268<lb/>

				PDAC ¼ pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma.<lb/>
			</figure>


			<figure type="table">
				Table 3 Contiguous regions of nonrandom copy number changes on 7p and 18q<lb/>
				
				BAC<lb/> Region<lb/> Genes included a<lb/> Overall results<lb/> Clone ID b<lb/> Cytoband Start (bp) End (bp) Size (bp) Size (Mb) c No Plausible candidates<lb/> Mean log2 Fold changes P-value<lb/> RP11-106E3<lb/> 7p22.2<lb/> 2 607 390<lb/> 2 657 138<lb/> 49 749<lb/> 26.0<lb/> 2 IQCE<lb/> 0.134<lb/> 1.098<lb/> 0.000242<lb/> RP11-172O13 7p22.1<lb/> 5 704 716<lb/> 5 847 079 142 364<lb/> 1 TRIAD3<lb/> 0.182<lb/> 1.135<lb/> 5.25E-06<lb/> RP1-42M2<lb/> 7p22.1<lb/> 59 69 700<lb/> 6 049 710<lb/> 80 011<lb/> 7 PMS2, EIF2AK1<lb/> 0.165<lb/> 1.121<lb/> 0.000272<lb/> RP4-810E6<lb/> 7p22.1<lb/> 6 049 510<lb/> 6 202 437 152 928<lb/> 6 PSCD3, EIF2AK1<lb/> 0.220<lb/> 1.164<lb/> 1.23E-06<lb/> RP11-425P5<lb/> 7p22.1<lb/> 6 233 987<lb/> 6 446 613 212 627<lb/> 4 RAC1, PSCD3<lb/> 0.144<lb/> 1.105<lb/> 0.000254<lb/> RP4-733B9<lb/> 7p22.1-p21.3<lb/> 7 176 436<lb/> 7 292 189 115 754<lb/> 1 C1GALT1<lb/> 0.189<lb/> 1.140<lb/> 4.92E-07<lb/> RP11-505D17 7p21.3<lb/> 7 947 759<lb/> 8 125 919 178 161<lb/> 2 GLCCI1, ICA1<lb/> 0.231<lb/> 1.174<lb/> 1.07E-08<lb/> RP11-304A10 7p21.3<lb/> 8 950 512<lb/> 9 040 173<lb/> 89 662<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.144<lb/> 1.105<lb/> 0.000274<lb/> RP5-959C21<lb/> 7p21.3<lb/> 9 924 891 10 064 840 139 950<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.143<lb/> 1.104<lb/> 6.08E-06<lb/> RP11-352E12<lb/> 7p21.3<lb/> 10 064 640 10 151 963<lb/> 87 324<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.190<lb/> 1.141<lb/> 2.08E-06<lb/> RP11-392P1<lb/> 7p21.3<lb/> 10 372 373 10 429 780<lb/> 57 408<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.207<lb/> 1.155<lb/> 3.66E-08<lb/> RP11-502P9<lb/> 7p21.3<lb/> 11 782 368 11 938 707 156 340<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.254<lb/> 1.192<lb/> 5.32E-09<lb/> RP5-1100A7<lb/> 7p21.3<lb/> 12 725 574 12 827 381 101 808<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.226<lb/> 1.170<lb/> 9.02E-09<lb/> RP11-195L14<lb/> 7p21.3<lb/> 12 951 352 13 077 542 126 191<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.242<lb/> 1.183<lb/> 1.45E-08<lb/> RP4-685A2<lb/> 7p21.2<lb/> 13 887 063 13 996 422 109 360<lb/> 1 ETV1<lb/> 0.278<lb/> 1.213<lb/> 5.64E-10<lb/> RP11-512E16<lb/> 7p21.2<lb/> 14 128 072 14 279 388 151 317<lb/> 1 DGKB<lb/> 0.262<lb/> 1.199<lb/> 1.75E-09<lb/> RP11-196O16 7p21.1<lb/> 16 023 294 16 205 465 182 172<lb/> 2<lb/> 0.182<lb/> 1.135<lb/> 8.23E-07<lb/> RP11-403N12 7p21.1<lb/> 16 865 247 17 055 918 190 672<lb/> 1 BCMP11<lb/> 0.239<lb/> 1.181<lb/> 2.76E-08<lb/> RP11-323K15<lb/> 7p21.1<lb/> 17 781 327 17 929 240 147 914<lb/> 1 SNX13<lb/> 0.109<lb/> 1.079<lb/> 9.16E -05<lb/> RP11-71F18<lb/> 7p21.1-p15.3<lb/> 19 406 242 19 580 569 174 328<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.147<lb/> 1.107<lb/> 8.00E-06<lb/> RP11-486P11<lb/> 7p15.3<lb/> 20 042 179 20 150 597 108 419<lb/> 1 7A5<lb/> 0.317<lb/> 1.246<lb/> 1.30E-11<lb/> RP4-701O19<lb/> 7p15.3<lb/> 20 884 182 20 950 414<lb/> 66 233<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.190<lb/> 1.140<lb/> 4.72E-05<lb/> RP11-211J15<lb/> 7p15.3<lb/> 21 173 901 21 257 598<lb/> 83 698<lb/> 2<lb/> 0.183<lb/> 1.135<lb/> 2.43E-07<lb/> RP11-445O1<lb/> 7p15.3<lb/> 21 588 234 21 669 042<lb/> 80 809<lb/> 1 DNAH11<lb/> 0.210<lb/> 1.157<lb/> 9.97E-08<lb/> RP11-451F11<lb/> 7p15.3<lb/> 23 714 553 23 804 532<lb/> 89 980<lb/> 1 STK31<lb/> 0.346<lb/> 1.271<lb/> 1.43E-11<lb/> RP11-343P21<lb/> 7p15.3<lb/> 24 511 504 24 521 807<lb/> 10 304<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.226<lb/> 1.169<lb/> 3.17E-08<lb/> RP11-99O17<lb/> 7p15.2<lb/> 25 824 267 25 925 677 101 411<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.225<lb/> 1.169<lb/> 2.79E-07<lb/> RP11-232C20 7p15.2<lb/> 26 765 660 26 911 371 145 712<lb/> 1 SCAP2<lb/> 0.275<lb/> 1.210<lb/> 1.80E-10<lb/> RP4-781A18<lb/> 7p15.2-p15.1<lb/> 27 976 171 28 166 812 190 642<lb/> 2 tcag7.981<lb/> 0.181<lb/> 1.133<lb/> 1.83E-06<lb/> RP4-596O9<lb/> 7p15.1<lb/> 28 459 769 28 603 446 143 678<lb/> 1 CREB5<lb/> 0.175<lb/> 1.129<lb/> 8.62E-06<lb/> RP11-463D17 18q12.3<lb/> 41 216 566 41 408 713 192 148<lb/> 6.9<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.439<lb/> À1.356<lb/> 1.00E-11<lb/> RP11-8H2<lb/> 18q21.1<lb/> 41 851 567 41 984 947 133 381<lb/> 5 ATP5A1, CCDC5, PSTPIP2 À0.249<lb/> À1.189<lb/> 1.50E-07<lb/> RP11-313C14 18q21.1<lb/> 423 50 383 42 350 954<lb/> 572<lb/> 1 LOXHD1<lb/> À0.471<lb/> À1.386<lb/> 5.75E-13<lb/> RP11-71F23<lb/> 18q21.1<lb/> 43 069 131 43 274 185 205 055<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.451<lb/> À1.367<lb/> 2.87E-11<lb/> RP11-46D1<lb/> 18q21.1<lb/> 44 393 176 44 552 924 159 749<lb/> 1 KIAA0427<lb/> À0.264<lb/> À1.201<lb/> 1.85E-05<lb/> RP11-141E12<lb/> 18q21.1<lb/> 45 025 819 4 5187 979 162 161<lb/> 1 DYM<lb/> À0.150<lb/> À1.109<lb/> 0.000150<lb/> RP11-419L16<lb/> 18q21.1-q21.2 46 310 160 46 473 840 163 681<lb/> 1 MAPK4<lb/> À0.378<lb/> À1.300<lb/> 1.02E-06<lb/> RP11-76E22<lb/> 18q21.2<lb/> 46 462 730 46 633 371 170 642<lb/> 2 MRO<lb/> À0.393<lb/> À1.313<lb/> 3.94E-10<lb/> RP11-729G3<lb/> 18q21.2<lb/> 46 732 284 46 888 494 156 211<lb/> 4 SMAD4, ELAC1<lb/> À0.389<lb/> À1.309<lb/> 2.67E-08<lb/> RP11-1E21<lb/> 18q21.2<lb/> 47 274 828 47 443 303 168 476<lb/> 2<lb/> À0.322<lb/> À1.250<lb/> 2.22E-08<lb/> RP11-25O3<lb/> 18q21.2<lb/> 47 958 320 48 119 508 161 189<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.346<lb/> À1.271<lb/> 1.64E-06<lb/> RP11-116K4<lb/> 18q21.2<lb/> 49 795 841 49 971 830 175 990<lb/> 12.0<lb/> 1 MBD2<lb/> À0.331<lb/> À1.258<lb/> 6.44E-08<lb/> RP11-99A1<lb/> 18q21.2<lb/> 50 563 151 50 702 093 138 943<lb/> 1 RAB27B<lb/> À0.374<lb/> À1.296<lb/> 4.86E-08<lb/> RP11-397A16 18q21.2<lb/> 51 445 553 51 648 118 202 566<lb/> 1<lb/> À0.263<lb/> À1.200<lb/> 1.58E-07<lb/> RP11-383D22 18q21.31<lb/> 52 656 265 52 867 730 211 466<lb/> 2 WDR7<lb/> À0.179<lb/> À1.132<lb/> 0.000196<lb/> RP11-35G9<lb/> 18q21.31<lb/> 53 447 744 53 561 700 113 957<lb/> 4 ATP8B1<lb/> À0.195<lb/> À1.145<lb/> 1.99E-06<lb/> RP11-61J14<lb/> 18q21.32<lb/> 54 567 090 54 747 580 180 491<lb/> 6 ZNF532, MALT1<lb/> À0.223<lb/> À1.167<lb/> 3.87E-07<lb/> RP11-350K6 18q21.32<lb/> 54 867 252 55 027 999 160 748<lb/> 1 SEC11L3<lb/> À0.289<lb/> À1.222<lb/> 5.58E-09<lb/> RP11-396N11 18q21.32<lb/> 56 063 594 56 151 592<lb/> 87 999<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.233<lb/> À1.176<lb/> 7.74E-08<lb/> RP11-520K18<lb/> 18q21.32<lb/> 56 874 822 57 034w619 159 798<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.230<lb/> À1.173<lb/> 1.22E-06<lb/> RP11-13L22<lb/> 18q21.33<lb/> 58 408 978 58 578 530 169 553<lb/> 3 PHLPP<lb/> À0.320<lb/> À1.248<lb/> 3.63E-11<lb/> RP11-215A20 18q21.33<lb/> 58 572 412 58 756 503 184 092<lb/> 2 PHLPP<lb/> À0.198<lb/> À1.147<lb/> 1.24E-05<lb/> RP11-233O10 18q22.1<lb/> 59 886 252 59 971 318<lb/> 85 067<lb/> 1 C18orf20<lb/> À0.250<lb/> À1.189<lb/> 2.21E-10<lb/> RP11-389J22<lb/> 18q22.1<lb/> 61 594 898 61 752 947 158 050<lb/> 1 CDH7<lb/> À0.189<lb/> À1.140<lb/> 8.76E-07<lb/> RP11-169F17<lb/> 18q22.3<lb/> 68 809 458 69 000 813 191 356<lb/> 7.1<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.329<lb/> À1.256<lb/> 4.02E-10<lb/> RP11-25L3<lb/> 18q22.3<lb/> 69 588 036 69 755 177 167 142<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.236<lb/> À1.177<lb/> 8.63E-08<lb/> RP11-556L15<lb/> 18q22.3<lb/> 70 753 437 70 931 323 177 887<lb/> 1 ZNF407<lb/> À0.348<lb/> À1.272<lb/> 3.55E-09<lb/> RP11-396D4<lb/> 18q22.3 – q23 71 168 342 71 337 306 168 965<lb/> 1<lb/> À0.261<lb/> À1.198<lb/> 1.51E-07<lb/> RP11-234N1<lb/> 18q23<lb/> 72 266 630 72 448 118 181 489<lb/> 2 ZNF516<lb/> À0.373<lb/> À1.295<lb/> 3.41E-11<lb/> RP11-118I2<lb/> 18q23<lb/> 73 613 846 73 764 173 150 328<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.275<lb/> À1.210<lb/> 1.20E-06<lb/> RP11-16L7<lb/> 18q23<lb/> 73 908 671 74 017 409 108 739<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.271<lb/> À1.206<lb/> 2.94E-12<lb/> RP11-563B11<lb/> 18q23<lb/> 74 707 626 74 870 951 163 326<lb/> 1 SALL3<lb/> À0.294<lb/> À1.226<lb/> 3.81E-07<lb/> RP11-154H12 18q23<lb/> 75 586 355 75 701 258 114 904<lb/> 2 CTDP1<lb/> À0.321<lb/> À1.249<lb/> 1.20E-08<lb/> CTC-964M9<lb/> 18q23<lb/> 75 939 424 75 940 259<lb/> 836<lb/> 0<lb/> À0.230<lb/> À1.173<lb/> 9.86E-06<lb/> a<lb/>
				
				The four clones that were used in FISH analysis are outlined in bold. b The size of the contiguous region. c The number of genes included in each clone and examples of candidate<lb/> genes contained within each clone. All the details are shown in Supplementary Table 1.<lb/>
			</figure>	

			<p>(42%) (<ref type="table">Table 4</ref>). All 11 cases with downregulated SEC11L3<lb/> demonstrated genetic losses by FISH. Despite decreased copy<lb/> numbers, SEC11L3 was expressed in two samples (PC46 and<lb/> PC51). A significant correlation between deletion and expression<lb/> levels was found (P ¼ 0.001, Fisher&apos;s exact test), indicating that the<lb/> mRNA level of this gene was highly dependent on its DNA copy<lb/> number.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>RT – PCR was performed further to confirm downregulated<lb/> mRNA of SEC11L3 in PDAC. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> shows SEC11L3 expression<lb/> in normal pancreas and PDAC tissue samples. Compared to two<lb/> normal pancreas tissues, SEC11L3 was found to be downregulated<lb/> in 16 out of 16 PDAC samples (100%). In particular, the SEC11L3<lb/> transcript was virtually almost absent in four PDAC tissues (25%;<lb/> lane 5, 6, 7 and 15).<lb/></p>

			<head level="1">DISCUSSION<lb/></head>

			<p>It is well known that a strong desmoplastic reaction is a typical<lb/> feature of PDAC tissues. A dense stromal component, which<lb/> occupies larger parts of the tumour mass, significantly reduces the<lb/> sensitivity and specificity of cytogenetic analysis. Tissue micro-<lb/>dissection is laborious, but the practical method available to enrich<lb/> the tumour cell population in clinical specimens. In the present<lb/> study, we first identified genomic abnormalities that represent the<lb/> characteristics of tumour cells in vivo by combining CGH arrays<lb/> with tissue microdissection. This approach led to more precise<lb/> definition of chromosomal breakpoints in a panel of 23 PDAC<lb/> tissue samples. To identify nonrandom genomic changes in PDAC,<lb/> we applied a P-value rather than a fixed cutoff value because<lb/> we found that concomitant lack of power in dichotomising the<lb/> data at an early stage in the analysis provided poor resolution<lb/> with which to distinguish between clones. Taking a statistical<lb/> threshold approach allows us to take account of different clones&apos;<lb/> differing variance across samples that a fixed fold-change<lb/> approach does not.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>We compared the CGH profiles to the previously published cell<lb/> line data (<ref type="biblio">Karhu et al, 2006</ref>). Despite overall similar spectrum<lb/> patterns, there were clear differences between both profiles. It is<lb/> important to take into account that the resolution of CGH arrays<lb/> used and the type of statistical analysis employed vary widely<lb/> between the reports. However, our results indicated that some<lb/> recurrent genetic alterations, such as losses of 4q and 13q and<lb/> gains of 11q and 20q, seem to be relatively unique to cell lines,<lb/> implying that these genetic changes may have been artificially<lb/> acquired through the establishment of cell lines or in the course of<lb/> culturing. In addition, our data did not demonstrate significant<lb/> copy number changes of some known genes, such as KRAS,<lb/> ERBB2, MLH1 and CDH1. This is probably due to the fact that<lb/> intragenic mutation or promoter methylation is more likely to<lb/> occur in these genes (<ref type="biblio">Lemoine et al, 1992; Scarpa et al, 1994;<lb/> Rozenblum et al, 1997; Ueki et al, 2000</ref>). Alternatively, this<lb/> discrepancy could be explained by the intratumoral heterogeneity<lb/> that is characteristically observed in PDAC cells in vitro as well as<lb/> in vivo, or may reflect the differences of the geographic origin of<lb/> the tumours used in this study (a total of 42 Japanese samples were<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">
				Table 4 The results of FISH and ISH analyses a<lb/>

				Clone ID/candidate<lb/> RP11-403N12/BCMP11<lb/> RP11-232C20/SCAP2<lb/> RP11-8H2/ATP5A1<lb/> RP11-350K6/SEC11L3<lb/> Analysis<lb/> FISH<lb/> FISH<lb/> FISH<lb/> FISH<lb/> ISH<lb/> PC37<lb/> 1.05<lb/> 0.99<lb/> 0.71<lb/> 0.83<lb/> 1<lb/> PC38<lb/> 1.02<lb/> 1.12<lb/> 0.94<lb/> 0.94<lb/> 2<lb/> PC39<lb/> 0.98<lb/> 1.09<lb/> 1.05<lb/> 0.77<lb/> 0<lb/> PC40<lb/> 1.01<lb/> 1.30<lb/> 0.95<lb/> 0.57<lb/> 1<lb/> PC41<lb/> 1.13<lb/> 0.93<lb/> 0.20<lb/> 0.46<lb/> 0<lb/> PC42<lb/> 1.28<lb/> 1.18<lb/> 0.56<lb/> 0.91<lb/> 2<lb/> PC43<lb/> 1.23<lb/> 0.94<lb/> 0.91<lb/> 0.71<lb/> 1<lb/> PC44<lb/> 1.35<lb/> 1.52<lb/> 0.66<lb/> 0.94<lb/> 2<lb/> PC45<lb/> 1.01<lb/> 1.01<lb/> 0.63<lb/> 0.71<lb/> 1<lb/> PC46<lb/> 1.06<lb/> 1.13<lb/> 0.94<lb/> 0.86<lb/> 2<lb/> PC47<lb/> 0.98<lb/> 1.03<lb/> 0.74<lb/> 0.36<lb/> 0<lb/> PC48<lb/> 1.59<lb/> 0.94<lb/> 0.90<lb/> 0.51<lb/> 0<lb/> PC49<lb/> 1.17<lb/> 1.24<lb/> 0.58<lb/> 1.04<lb/> 2<lb/> PC50<lb/> 1.01<lb/> 1.03<lb/> 0.94<lb/> 0.63<lb/> 0<lb/> PC51<lb/> 1.24<lb/> 1.26<lb/> 0.64<lb/> 0.82<lb/> 2<lb/> PC52<lb/> 1.25<lb/> 0.97<lb/> 0.85<lb/> 1.11<lb/> 2<lb/> PC53<lb/> 1.49<lb/> 1.14<lb/> 0.71<lb/> 0.70<lb/> 1<lb/> PC54<lb/> 1.39<lb/> 1.50<lb/> 0.51<lb/> 0.52<lb/> 0<lb/> PC55<lb/> 1.41<lb/> 1.50<lb/> 0.95<lb/> 1.08<lb/> 2<lb/> Frequency (%)<lb/> 10/19 (53%)<lb/> 7/19 (37%)<lb/> 11/19 (58%)<lb/> 13/19 (68%)<lb/> 11/19 (58%)<lb/> a<lb/>

				Significant differences are outlined in bold. FISH ¼ fluorescence in situ hybridisation; ISH ¼ in situ RNA hybridisation.<lb/>
			</figure>

			<figure>		
				A<lb/> B<lb/> C<lb/> D<lb/>
			
				Figure 2
				
				Four representative images in FISH analysis. Target BAC DNA<lb/> probes were labelled with Cy3-dCTP (red), while centromeric probes<lb/> were labelled with SpectrumGreen. DNA copy number was evaluated for<lb/> each probe by counting spots in at least 100 nuclei. (A) No copy number<lb/> change of BCMP11 in PC40. (B) Genetic loss of SEC11L3 in PC48. (C)<lb/> Genetic gains of BCMP11 in PC44 and (D) of SCAP2 in PC49.<lb/>
			</figure>	

			<p>analysed by array CGH, FISH and ISH) (<ref type="biblio">Scarpa et al, 1994;<lb/> Gorunova et al, 1998; Harada et al, 2002b</ref>). Similarly, deletion<lb/> of the DCC gene was not recurrent in our sample set. However,<lb/> a larger scale of study using much higher-resolution genome-<lb/>wide microarrays (tiling-path CGH arrays or single nucleotide<lb/> polymorphism arrays) is required to conclude whether this<lb/> genetic alteration is critically involved in the pathogenesis of<lb/> PDAC.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>As our array CGH profiles revealed that the regions of 7p22.2 –<lb/> p15.1, 18q12.3 – q21.2 and 18q21.2 – q22.1 are nonrandomly altered,<lb/> four clones from those regions were validated by FISH experi-<lb/>ments. The results showed that genetic alterations for these clones<lb/> were observed in 37 – 68% of tumours in a separate sample set,<lb/> supporting the validity of our CGH results. Moreover, copy<lb/> number changes of those four clones were detected in 18 out of 19<lb/> PDAC cases (95%), implying the potential clinical applicability.<lb/> Among the candidate genes verified by FISH, BCMP11 is newly<lb/> detected in PDAC, although <ref type="biblio">Fletcher et al (2003)</ref> demonstrated<lb/> that mRNA and protein of this gene were overexpressed in<lb/> oestrogen receptor-positive breast cancer. This gene lies adjacent<lb/> to the AGR2 gene (7p21.1) and both genes are classified as<lb/> members of the same family (AGR family) due to highly similar<lb/> (approximately 70%) protein sequences. Interestingly, several gene<lb/> expression analyses have shown that AGR2 is upregulated in the<lb/> majority of PDACs as well as pancreatic intraepithelial neoplasia<lb/> (PanIN) lesions (<ref type="biblio">Crnogorac-Jurcevic et al, 2003; Iacobuzio-<lb/>Donahue et al, 2003a; Iacobuzio-Donahue et al, 2003b; Missiaglia<lb/> et al, 2004; Buchholz et al, 2005</ref>). Taken together, BCMP11 is also<lb/> likely to be involved in the development of PDAC. On the other<lb/> hand, SCAP2 was first described in a recently published report,<lb/></p>


			<figure>
				A<lb/> B<lb/> C<lb/> D<lb/> E<lb/> F<lb/> G<lb/> H<lb/> I<lb/>

 			   Figure 3
			   
			   SEC11L3 mRNA expression in non-neoplastic epithelial cells and PDAC cells, as determined by ISH. (A) Strong expression (score 2) in both<lb/> ductal (white arrows) and acinar cells of non-neoplastic pancreas. (B) ISH conducted with a sense SEC11L3 riboprobe, used as a negative control. (C – E). No<lb/> expression (score 0) in PDAC cells (black arrows), but weak expression (score 1) in non-neoplastic islet cells (black arrow heads) (PC41 and 47) (F). Weak<lb/> expression (score 1) of PDAC cells in PC43 and (G) strong intensity of expression (score 2) of PDAC cells in PC44. (H) Lower level of expression (score 1;<lb/> PC53) and (I) similar intensity of expression (score 2; PC55) in metastatic PDAC cells (black arrows) compared to non-neoplastic hepatic cells (asterisk).<lb/>
		   </figure>

		   <figure>
				SEC11L3<lb/> 18s rRNA<lb/> 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19<lb/>

 			  	Figure 4
			   
			   mRNA expression of SEC11L3 in normal pancreas and PDAC tissues, as determined by RT-PCR. 18S ribosomal RNA was used as an internal<lb/> standard. Samples were run in the following order: lane 1 – 2, normal pancreas; lane 3 – 18, PDACs; lane 19, negative control. SEC11L3 expression was found<lb/> to be present in normal pancreas, while it was decreased in 16 out of 16 PDAC tissues (100%).<lb/>
		   </figure>

			<p>showing that mRNA of this gene is frequently overexpressed in<lb/> PanIN lesions (<ref type="biblio">Buchholz et al, 2005</ref>). The protein encoded by this<lb/> gene belongs to the src family of kinases. <ref type="biblio">Takahashi et al (2003)<lb/></ref> demonstrated that SCAP2 functions as a downstream target of<lb/> c-Src under various stress conditions (UV light, tumour necrosis<lb/> factor-a and osmotic stress). Therefore, SCAP2 also seems to work<lb/> as a cell-signalling molecule in cancer cells. However, the<lb/> biological function and putative role of these two genes have not<lb/> been investigated in cancer.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Remarkably, SEC11L3 was deleted in approximately 70% of<lb/> tumours and its expression level was significantly correlated with<lb/> its DNA copy number. Despite the high frequency of this genetic<lb/> abnormality, this gene has not been described in any type of<lb/> cancer. Previous cytogenetic analyses have revealed a frequent<lb/> deletion of 18q in PDAC, but neither the chromosomal breakpoints<lb/> nor the candidate genes included could be clearly identified due to<lb/> technical limitations of the technology employed (<ref type="biblio">Griffin et al,<lb/> 1995; Hahn et al, 1995; Fukushige et al, 1997, 1998; Mahlamaki<lb/> et al, 1997; Hoglund et al, 1998; Schleger et al, 2000; Harada et al,<lb/> 2002a; Iacobuzio-Donahue et al, 2004</ref>). SMAD4 (18q21.1) has been<lb/> reported to be deleted or inactivated in about 50% of PDACs and,<lb/> therefore, it is considered to be one of the most likely candidate<lb/> tumour suppressor genes at this locus (<ref type="biblio">Hahn et al, 1996;<lb/> Rozenblum et al, 1997</ref>). However, we propose that SEC11L3<lb/> (18q21.32) could be an equally promising candidate gene on 18q<lb/> because the significance of genetic loss of this gene is comparable<lb/> to that of the SMAD4 gene. In addition, both ISH and RT – PCR<lb/> independently confirmed that SEC11L3 mRNA is downregulated<lb/> in PDAC tissues at a high frequency (53% and 100%,<lb/> respectively), suggesting that dysregulation of this gene is<lb/> likely to be associated with the development of PDAC. Little is<lb/> known about the biological role of this gene, although it belongs to<lb/> the peptidase S26B family and functions as part of the signal<lb/> peptidase complex.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>In summary, we could successfully identify genetic alterations<lb/> that reflect the intrinsic characteristics of PDAC cells in vivo by<lb/> combining array CGH with tissue microdissection. These results<lb/> provided a valid data set to search for novel candidate genes<lb/> involved in pancreatic carcinogenesis. The specificity of our array<lb/> CGH results was confirmed by interphase FISH in an independent<lb/> sample set. Among the identified candidates, we are particularly<lb/> interested in the SEC11L3 gene that is located on 18q21.32. FISH<lb/> and ISH analyses for this gene demonstrated a significant<lb/> correlation between genetic deletion and the corresponding mRNA<lb/> downregulation, raising the possibility that the SEC11L3 gene may<lb/> play a putative role as a tumour suppressor. For these reasons, we<lb/> propose that SEC11L3 should be considered as a potential marker<lb/> gene for the molecular diagnosis of PDAC and a possible candidate<lb/> target for therapeutic intervention.</p>

	</text>
</tei>
