<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>1. Introduction<lb/></head>

			<p>Over the last ten years or so, the advent of large for-<lb/>mat near-infrared (NIR) detectors has made images at<lb/> wavelengths longer than 1 µm relatively easy to obtain.<lb/> New infrared cameras based on these detectors make it<lb/> straightforward to study statistically significant samples<lb/> of galaxies in the NIR (see e.g. <ref type="biblio">de Jong &amp; van der Kruit<lb/> 1994</ref>). The NIR wavelengths constitute the spectral re-<lb/>gion best adapted to studies of the quiescent stellar com-<lb/>ponent of galaxies, since they trace mass better than do<lb/> optical bands, being less contaminated by the low M/L<lb/> products of recent episodes of star formation. The NIR<lb/> spectral region is also relatively free of effects of dust, as<lb/> extinction at 1.65 µm is more than seven times lower than<lb/> in the B band (e.g., <ref type="biblio">Landini et al. 1984</ref>). On the negative<lb/> side, the sky brightness can be as much as ten magnitudes<lb/> brighter than in the visible; thus more sophisticated and<lb/> time-consuming observing and data reduction techniques<lb/> are required.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Since 1993 we have used NIR arrays extensively to ob-<lb/>tain images in the H bandpass of galaxies. The observing<lb/> samples were selected by choosing members of the Virgo,<lb/> Coma and A1367 clusters. In addition, we selected a sig-<lb/>nificant population of galaxies in the portion of the &quot; Great<lb/> Wall &quot; which lies in the bridge between Coma and A1367.<lb/> These latter objects can be considered isolated and will<lb/> be used as a control sample for environmental studies.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Our previous papers concentrated on spiral galaxies.<lb/> About 160 such objects observed with the Calar Alto 2.2<lb/> m telescope were reported in <ref type="biblio">Gavazzi et al. (1996c; Paper<lb/> I)</ref>; another 300, observed similarly with the TIRGO 1.5<lb/> m telescope, are given in <ref type="biblio">Gavazzi et al. (1996b; Paper II)</ref>;<lb/> and another 102 Virgo galaxies are reported in <ref type="biblio">Boselli et<lb/> al. (1997; B97)</ref>. More Calar Alto observations of 170 galax-<lb/>ies in the Virgo cluster are given in <ref type="biblio">Boselli et al. (1999,<lb/> Paper IV)</ref>. In this paper, we present 1.65 µm (H-band) sur-<lb/>face brightness measurements, obtained in 1997 at TIRGO<lb/> equipped with the Arcetri NIR camera ARNICA, of 558<lb/> galaxies which are primarily of early-type (E-S0-S0a). We<lb/> also provide several repeated measurements of late-type<lb/> objects with previously unreliable photometry. Section 2<lb/> of the present paper describes the current sample, and<lb/> the observations are outlined in Section 3. Image analysis<lb/> strategies are discussed in Section 4. Preliminary results<lb/> are given in Section 5 and summarized in Section 6. Profile<lb/> decompositions using combinations of exponential profiles<lb/> and de Vaucouleurs laws of the present data and of those<lb/> obtained similarly (Paper I, II, IV and B97) will be given<lb/> in a forthcoming paper (Paper V of this series, <ref type="biblio">Gavazzi et<lb/> al. 1999a</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<head>2. Sample selection<lb/></head>

			<p>We report on the NIR H band observations of 558<lb/> optically-selected galaxies, for the most part (457) of<lb/> early-type morphology, found in the regions of the Coma<lb/> Supercluster and of the Virgo cluster. There are 383 early-<lb/>type galaxies in the CGCG catalogue (m p ≤ 15.7) (<ref type="biblio">Zwicky<lb/> et al. 1961-68</ref>) that are members of the Coma supercluster<lb/> (18 o ≤ δ ≤ 32 o ; 11.5 h ≤ α ≤ 13.5 h ), according to <ref type="biblio">Gavazzi<lb/> et al. (1999)</ref>, i.e. with 5000 &lt; V &lt; 8000 km s −1 . Of these,<lb/> we have observed 372 objects, which constitute 97% of the<lb/> designated sample.<lb/></p>

			<p>We also observed 81 of the 98 early-type galax-<lb/>ies brighter than m p =14.0 listed in the VCC catalogue<lb/> (<ref type="biblio">Binggeli et al. 1985</ref>) which are bona-fide members of the<lb/> Virgo cluster. Thus we have observed 83% of the giant<lb/> early-type galaxies in Virgo.<lb/></p>

			<p>The remaining 101 observations of spiral galaxies given<lb/> here do not form a complete sample in any sense. However,<lb/> they are necessary to define a complete data set. When<lb/> combined with data published in Papers I and II (both of<lb/> which were devoted to observations of spiral galaxies), IV<lb/> of this series and B97 (which contains mainly measure-<lb/>ments of spiral galaxies in Virgo), the NIR survey pre-<lb/>sented in this series of papers represents a complete, op-<lb/>tically selected sample of galaxies, which will be analyzed<lb/> in future papers.<lb/></p>

			<p>The first 9 columns of <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> give the optical param-<lb/>eters of the 558 galaxies studied in the present work as<lb/> follows:<lb/></p>

			<p>Column 1: CGCG (<ref type="biblio">Zwicky et al. 1961-68</ref>) or VCC<lb/> (<ref type="biblio">Binggeli et al. 1985</ref>) denomination.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 2: NGC/IC names.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 3, 4: adopted (1950) celestial coordinates, mea-<lb/>sured by us or taken from NED 2 , with few arcsec uncer-<lb/>tainty.<lb/></p>

			<p>Column 5: &quot; aggregation &quot; parameter. This parameter de-<lb/>fines the membership to a group/cluster/supercluster:<lb/> CSisol, CSpairs, CSgroups indicate members of the Coma<lb/> Supercluster (5000 &lt; V &lt; 8000 km s −1 ); CSforeg means<lb/> objects in the foreground of the Coma Supercluster (V &lt;<lb/> 5000 km s −1 ) and CSbackg means objects in the back-<lb/>ground of the Coma Supercluster (V &gt; 8000 km s −1 ).<lb/> Galaxies in the Virgo region are labelled following the<lb/> membership criteria given by <ref type="biblio">Binggeli et al. (1993)</ref>: VCA,<lb/> VCB, VCM, VCW, VCW&apos;, VCSE, VCmem, are members<lb/> to the cluster A or B, to the M, W, W&apos; or South-East<lb/> clouds or are not better specified members to the Virgo<lb/> cluster respectively. NOVCC are galaxies taken from the<lb/> CGCG in the outskirts of Virgo, but outside the area cov-<lb/>ered by the VCC. VCback are galaxies in the background<lb/> of the Virgo cluster (V&gt;3000 km/sec).<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 6: photographic magnitude as given in the CGCG<lb/> or in the VCC.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 7,8: for CGCG galaxies these are the major and<lb/> minor optical diameters (a 25 , b 25 ) (in arcmin) derived at<lb/> the B band 25 th mag arcsec −2 , as explained in <ref type="biblio">Gavazzi &amp;<lb/> Boselli (1996)</ref>. These diameters are consistent with those<lb/> given in the RC3. For VCC galaxies these are the diam-<lb/>eters measured on the du Pont plates at the faintest de-<lb/>tectable isophote, as listed in the VCC.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 9: morphological type.<lb/></p> 

			<head>3. Observations<lb/></head> 

			<p>The observations reported in this paper were acquired<lb/> with the 1.5 m, f/20 TIRGO telescope from March 13<lb/> to April 13, 1997, when 32 nights were allocated to the<lb/> present project. Only 22/32 nights were useful, 16 of which<lb/> were entirely or partly photometric. The seeing ranged<lb/> from 1.5 to 3.5 arcsec (FWHM) with a mean of 2.4 arc-<lb/>sec, as shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. These seeing conditions are mostly<lb/> due to the large pixels (∼ 1 arcsec) of ARNICA at TIRGO,<lb/> and as such represent a necessary disadvantage, because<lb/> they also provide the large field-of-view (4.1×4.1 arcmin 2 )<lb/> fundamental for our observations.<lb/></p> 

			<figure>Fig. 1. The seeing distribution.<lb/></figure> 

			<p>The folded Cassegrain focus of the telescope is<lb/> equipped with the Arcetri NIR camera, ARNICA, which<lb/> relies on a 256 2 NICMOS3 array detector (<ref type="biblio">Lisi et al. 1993;<lb/> Lisi et al. 1996; Hunt et al. 1996</ref>). With a pixel size of<lb/> 0.97 arcsec, the field-of-view is 4.1×4.1 arcmin 2 . Obtain-<lb/>ing a satisfactory background subtraction is the main dif-<lb/>ficulty of NIR observations. At 1.65 µm, the sky brightness<lb/> at the Gornergrat is ≈ 13.0-13.5 mag arcsec −2 , and varies<lb/> on time scales comparable with the typical duration of an<lb/> observation (e.g., <ref type="biblio">Wainscoat &amp; Cowie 1992</ref>). To achieve<lb/> a brightness limit 8 mag arcsec −2 fainter than the sky re-<lb/>quires an image in which the deviations from flatness do<lb/> not exceed 0.06%. Thus, data acquisition techniques must<lb/> be able to monitor the sky fluctuations and data reduction<lb/> must take these into account.<lb/></p>

			<p>To this end, we used two types of pointing sequences,<lb/> or &quot; mosaics &quot; , according to the size of the galaxy. Galaxies<lb/> with an optical diameter ≥ 1 arcmin were observed using<lb/> a sequence in which half of the time is devoted to the tar-<lb/>get, and half to the surrounding sky (hereafter denoted as<lb/> a type &quot; A &quot; mosaic) 3 . Typically eight on-source pointings<lb/> were alternated with eight on the sky, positioned along<lb/> a circular path around the galaxy and offset by 4 arcmin<lb/> from the source position. The on-source positions were<lb/> &quot; dithered &quot; by 10 arcsec in order to facilitate the elimina-<lb/>tion of bad pixels. To save telescope time, small galaxies<lb/> (with an optical diameter &lt; 1 arcmin were observed with<lb/> a pointing sequence consisting of nine pointings along a<lb/> circular path and displaced from one another by 1 arcmin<lb/> such that the target galaxy is always in the field (hereafter<lb/> denoted as a type &quot; B &quot; mosaic).<lb/></p> 

			<p>On-chip integration times were set to 6 seconds to<lb/> avoid saturation but to ensure background-limited perfor-<lb/>mance. Total integration times on-source were typically<lb/> 400 s and ranged from 150 to 950 s.<lb/></p> 

			<p><ref type="table">Table 1</ref> gives the parameters relevant to the NIR ob-<lb/>servations as follows:<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 10: number of frames N f combined to form the<lb/> final image (depending on the adopted mosaic).<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 11: number of elementary observations (coadds)<lb/> N c . The total integration time (in seconds) is the product<lb/> of the number of coadds N c times the number of combined<lb/> frames N f times the on-chip integration time t int which<lb/> was set to 6 sec.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 12: seeing (in pixels, with 0.97 arcsec per pixel).<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 13: adopted zero point (mag / sec).<lb/> Column 14-17: observing dates (day-month-1997);<lb/></p> 

			<head>3.1. Photometric calibration<lb/></head> 

			<p>Observations of the standard stars HD 84800 (H = 7.53<lb/> mag) and HD 129653 (H = 6.92 mag) from <ref type="biblio">Elias et al.<lb/> (1982)</ref> were taken hourly throughout the nights for cali-<lb/>bration purposes. The calibration stars were observed with<lb/> a third pointing sequence (mosaic type &quot; C &quot; ) which con-<lb/>sisted of five positions, starting with the star near the cen-<lb/>ter of the array, followed by positioning the star in each of<lb/> the four quadrants of the array. The telescope was defo-<lb/>cussed to avoid saturation. During the photometric nights<lb/> (i.e. those of march 20, 21, 25, 27, 29, 31 and of April<lb/> 1, 2, 6, 7 and 13) the typical uncertainty in the nightly<lb/> calibration is 0.05 mag. Those nights were mostly used to<lb/> observe galaxies with unknown H band photometry.<lb/></p> 

			<p>In the remaining non-photometric or marginally pho-<lb/>tometric nights we did not rely on the photometric calibra-<lb/>tion; instead we conservatively observed only those galax-<lb/>ies with aperture photometry available from the literature.<lb/> For these galaxies the calibration was derived from the<lb/> &quot; virtual aperture photometry &quot; (see Section 4.1 below).<lb/> Several (108) galaxies were observed in more than one<lb/> night (see Columns 14-17 in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>). This was done ei-<lb/>ther to check the photometric consistency, because some<lb/> observations were taken in non-photometric conditions,<lb/> or, if the objects were fainter than average, to obtain a<lb/> longer integration. For these objects we obtained an aver-<lb/>age frame by combining the various sets of observations,<lb/> and using the zero point from the frame(s) taken under<lb/> photometric conditions.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.2. Data reduction procedures<lb/></head>

			<p>Since dome exposures cannot be obtained at TIRGO due<lb/> to the vicinity of the telescope secondary ring to the dome,<lb/> the multiplicative correction for the system response, or<lb/> flat-field (FF), was derived daily from the observations.<lb/> Many tens (typically 30 to 40) sky frames taken in sim-<lb/>ilar conditions throughout the night were combined with<lb/> a median filter. The combined frame, normalized to its<lb/> median counts was used as the flat-field frame.<lb/></p> 

			<p>The reduction procedure varied according to the type<lb/> of mosaic. For type &quot; A &quot; mosaics, the (usually eight) sky<lb/> exposures were combined with a median algorithm to form<lb/> a median sky. For type &quot; B &quot; and &quot; C &quot; mosaics, the median<lb/> sky was determined by combining all the frames in the<lb/> pointing sequence. The median algorithm is necessary to<lb/> remove unwanted star and galaxy images in the median<lb/> sky frames. The median sky was first normalized to its<lb/> median, then multiplied by the median counts of the indi-<lb/>vidual target frames. Finally this rescaled frame was sub-<lb/></p>

			<table>1<lb/> Table 1. The program galaxies.This is a one page sample. The entire table con-<lb/>taining 558 entries is only available in electronic format<lb/> Galaxy<lb/> NGC=IC R:A:1950 Dec: Agg mp a<lb/> b<lb/> type Nf Nc Seeing Zp Date1 Date2 Date3 Date4 HB25 H c<lb/> B25 HT rH(20:5) C31<lb/> h m s o 0 &quot;<lb/> mag arcmin arcmin<lb/> pix mag s 1 dd=mm dd=mm dd=mm dd=mm mag mag mag arcsec<lb/> (1)<lb/> (2)<lb/> (3)<lb/> (4)<lb/> (5) (6) (7)<lb/> (8)<lb/> (9) (10) (11) (12) (13)<lb/> (14) (15) (16) (17) (18) (19) (20) (21) (22)<lb/> VC0049<lb/> 4168 120943:50 132905:0 V CM 12:21 1:94 1:54<lb/> E<lb/> 6 8 2:0 19:47 07=04<lb/> 8:84 8:84 8:80 48:88 3:93<lb/> VC0094<lb/> 4191 121116:80 072842:0 V CW 13:57 1:85 1:22<lb/> S0a<lb/> 7 8 1:9 19:47 07=04<lb/> 10:09 10:01 10:16 26:90 5:12<lb/> VC0122<lb/> 4200 121210:80 122730:0 V CM 13:85 2:14 1:07<lb/> S0<lb/> 6 8 2:6 19:25 09=04<lb/> 10:23 10:23 10:30 29:69 5:04<lb/> VC0166<lb/> 4215 121321:20 064045:0 V CW 13:12 2:69 0:72<lb/> S0<lb/> 5 8 3:0 19:38 10=04<lb/> 9:27 9:27 9:10 1:00 6:10<lb/> VC0213<lb/> 3094 121423:40 135413:0 V CA 14:26 1:12 0:86 S BCD 8 8 1:9 19:46 02=04<lb/> 11:54 11:54 11:52 15:42 2:94<lb/> VC0220<lb/> 4233 121433:40 075403:0 V CW 12:97 3:39 1:07<lb/> S0<lb/> 7 8 2:6 19:27 09=04<lb/> 9:06 9:06 8:95 64:16 8:59<lb/> 160250<lb/> 4026 125757:50 281858:0 Coma 15:50 0:82 0:49<lb/> S0<lb/> 7 8 2:2 19:45 31=03<lb/> 11:88 11:88 11:54 13:86 4:92<lb/> 160251<lb/> 125811:00 282455:0 Coma 15:70 0:60 0:20<lb/> S0a<lb/> 9 8 1:7 19:49 02=04<lb/> 12:40 12:19 12:34 16:86 4:06<lb/> 160253<lb/> 4906 125815:10 281134:0 Coma 15:20 0:72 0:57<lb/> E<lb/> 8 8 2:1 19:50 22=03<lb/> 11:54 11:54 11:18 14:90 4:94<lb/> 160254<lb/> 4041 125816:49 281556:6 Coma 15:70 0:70 0:48<lb/> E<lb/> 7 8 2:7 19:47 01=04<lb/> 12:04 12:04 12:08 12:63 3:92<lb/> 160255<lb/> 4042 125818:20 281355:0 Coma 15:50 0:65 0:64<lb/> S0<lb/> 7 8 2:7 19:47 01=04<lb/> 11:42 11:42 11:09 16:68 5:81<lb/> 160256<lb/> 4045 125824:10 282135:0 Coma 15:10 0:84 0:64<lb/> E<lb/> 7 8 2:5 19:50 22=03<lb/> 11:22 11:22 11:24 14:36 3:61<lb/> 160257<lb/> 4907 125824:37 282537:8 Coma 14:60 1:13 1:08<lb/> Sa<lb/> 8 8 1:9 19:45 31=03<lb/> 10:72 10:71 10:68 28:38 3:79<lb/> 160258<lb/> 4908 125827:00 281842:0 Coma 14:90 0:92 0:68<lb/> E<lb/> 30 6 2:5 19:50 15=03 24=03 25=03 31=03 10:93 10:93 10:60 21:36 5:52<lb/> 160259<lb/> 4051 125829:80 281640:0 Coma 14:80 1:49 0:98<lb/> E<lb/> 29 6 2:5 19:52 16=03<lb/> 10:78 10:78 10:64 24:44 4:40<lb/> 160260<lb/> 4911 125831:50 280336:0 Coma 13:70 1:89 1:50<lb/> Sa<lb/> 7 8 1:7 19:48 23=03<lb/> 10:06 10:02 10:28 28:17 2:75<lb/> 161029<lb/> 131912:70 263359:0 CSbac 15:70 0:40 0:30<lb/> E<lb/> 9 8 2:0 19:49 02=04<lb/> 12:37 12:37 12:22 11:36 3:25<lb/> 161030<lb/> 131920:69 313645:1 CSfor 14:80 1:40 0:60<lb/> S0<lb/> 8 8 1:7 19:47 08=04<lb/> 11:57 11:57 11:70 17:82 2:50<lb/> 161034<lb/> 131942:37 313222:9 CSmul 15:70 0:40 0:30<lb/> S0<lb/> 16 8 2:6 19:47 04=04 06=04<lb/> 12:07 12:07 12:06 12:03 2:54<lb/> 161040<lb/> 132102:70 264819:3 CSiso 15:60 0:74 0:40<lb/> Sc<lb/> 9 8 2:1 19:49 02=04<lb/> 12:85 12:74 12:73 11:11 3:13<lb/> 161041<lb/> 132122:30 315421:0 CSfor 15:50 0:80 0:50<lb/> S::<lb/> 8 8 2:0 19:30 11=04<lb/> 12:27 12:27 11:92 16:31 4:18<lb/> 161042<lb/> 5127 132125:80 314934:0 CSfor 13:90 2:30 1:70<lb/> E<lb/> 6 8 1:9 19:43 11=04<lb/> 9:77 9:77 9:84 33:19 4:28<lb/> 161043<lb/> 5131 132137:37 311453:4 CSiso 14:40 2:20 0:44<lb/> Sa<lb/> 16 6 2:9 19:49 17=03 25=03<lb/> 10:32 10:02 10:19 43:41 6:95<lb/> 161044<lb/> 132156:69 313620:0 CSfor 15:30 1:50 0:25<lb/> Sc<lb/> 7 8 2:0 19:45 14=04<lb/> 11:52 11:18 11:34 36:27 3:76<lb/> 161046<lb/> 4241 132224:80 265953:0 CSiso 15:50 0:60 0:60<lb/> E<lb/> 8 8 2:7 19:46 30=03<lb/> 11:83 11:83 11:46 14:83 4:39<lb/> 161047<lb/> 132234:40 264325:0 CSiso 15:60 0:80 0:35<lb/> E<lb/> 9 8 2:6 19:47 01=04<lb/> 11:65 11:65 11:38 16:15 7:54<lb/> 161050<lb/> 132402:10 315731:0 CSbac 15:60 0:50 0:30<lb/> E<lb/> 17 6 3:0 19:49 21=03 01=04<lb/> 12:38 12:38 12:32 9:97 3:30<lb/> 161052<lb/> 132430:00 265101:5 CSiso 15:10 0:30 0:30 I Pec 9 8 3:0 19:46 30=03<lb/> 12:42 12:42 12:24 9:19 3:68<lb/> 161066<lb/> 132714:00 264006:0 CSiso 15:70 1:00 0:20<lb/> S::<lb/> 18 8 2:8 19:48 31=03 06=04<lb/> 12:18 11:87 11:88 19:12 3:43<lb/> 161070<lb/> 132748:19 313845:6 CSiso 15:00 1:00 0:90<lb/> S0<lb/> 15 6 3:0 19:49 20=03 30=03<lb/> 11:33 11:33 10:98 17:24 4:14<lb/> 161071<lb/> 132758:62 313530:3 CSfor 14:90 1:30 0:51 I Pec 8 8 1:7 19:47 08=04<lb/> 12:80 12:80 13:19 12:15 2:67<lb/> 161075<lb/> 132824:50 264643:0 CSiso 15:70 0:70 0:30<lb/> E<lb/> 16 8 2:9 19:48 31=03 06=04<lb/> 13:79 13:79 13:51 9:56 3:54<lb/></table> 

			<p>tracted from each of the target observations. Such a pro-<lb/>cedure accounts for temporal variations in the sky level<lb/> which are on the order of 5% during a pointing sequence,<lb/> but introduces an additive offset which is subsequently re-<lb/>moved (see below). The sky-subtracted target frames are<lb/> then divided by the FF frame. Each of these corrected<lb/> frames was then analyzed for low-spatial-frequency gra-<lb/>dients, and if necessary, fitted with a two-dimensional 3<lb/> degree polynomial which was then subtracted. (We care-<lb/>fully checked that this procedure did not produce artificial<lb/> features which could disturb the photometry of the target<lb/> objects). If this process was not effective in removing the<lb/> spatial gradients, the corresponding frames were rejected<lb/> from further analysis. Finally, the corrected frames were<lb/> registered using field stars and combined with a median fil-<lb/>ter which allows bad pixel removal. Foreground stars were<lb/> eliminated by manual &quot; editing &quot; of the target frames. All<lb/> image reduction and analysis was performed in the IRAF<lb/> environment and relied on the STSDAS package. 4<lb/></p> 

			<p>We have assessed the quality of the final images both<lb/> on small spatial scales, and over the entire array. All of<lb/> the images are truly background limited, as the noise<lb/> we measure is the same as that which we would theo-<lb/>retically expect from the statistical fluctuations in the<lb/> sky background, according to <ref type="biblio">Hunt &amp; Mannucci (1998)</ref><lb/> (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>). The typical pixel to pixel fluctuations are<lb/> ∼ 21mag arcsec −2 , i.e. 0.05-0.06% of the sky.<lb/></p> 

			<figure>Fig. 2. The distribution of the sky rms as a function of integra-<lb/>tion time. The solid line is the prediction by Hunt &amp; Mannucci<lb/> (1998).<lb/></figure> 

			<head>4. Image analysis<lb/></head> 

			<head>4.1. H-band magnitudes from virtual aperture photometry<lb/></head>

			<p>At the position of the galaxies&apos; centers (determined by fit-<lb/>ting a two-dimensional gaussian to the galaxies) a growth<lb/> curve was derived for each object by integrating the<lb/> counts in concentric circular rings of increasing radii. The<lb/> background was determined in a concentric object–free<lb/> corona (where the contribution from contaminating stars<lb/> is rejected by average sigma–clipping). The measurements<lb/> taken through the individual &quot; virtual circular apertures &quot;<lb/> are useful to compare with existing similarly taken mea-<lb/>surements (e.g. <ref type="biblio">Gezari et al. 1993</ref>) and for calibration pur-<lb/>poses of future observations. They are given in <ref type="table">Table 2<lb/></ref> (available only in digital format) as follows:<lb/></p>

			<p>Column 1: Galaxy denomination in the CGCG (Z) or VCC<lb/> catalogues.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 2: aperture diameter in arcsec.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 3: logarithmic ratio of the adopted aperture di-<lb/>ameter to the optical (a 25 ) diameter.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 4: integrated H magnitude within the aperture.<lb/></p> 

			<p>The photometry of 159 galaxies observed under pho-<lb/>tometric conditions has been checked against 187 pub-<lb/>lished aperture photometry measurements (see <ref type="biblio">Gezari et<lb/> al. 1993</ref>). The comparison of our &quot; virtual aperture &quot; mea-<lb/>surements with the reference photometry, taken through<lb/> apertures consistent with ours, is given in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. On the<lb/> average we find:<lb/></p> 

			<formula>H this work − H literature = -0.026 ± 0.095 mag.<lb/></formula> 

			<p>The most discrepant measurements are those taken<lb/> through small apertures (5-15 arcsec), due to a combi-<lb/>nation of seeing effects and unaccurate galaxy center-<lb/>ing. We estimate the overall photometric accuracy of our<lb/> data, including systematic errors in the calibration, to be<lb/> ≤ 0.1 mag.<lb/></p> 

			<table>Table 1. The &quot; virtual aperture photometry &quot; . This is a one<lb/> page sample. The entire table containing 6293 entries is only<lb/> available in electronic format.<lb/> Galaxy<lb/> Ap. logAp/a25 H<lb/> arcsec<lb/> mag<lb/> (1)<lb/> (2)<lb/> (3)<lb/> (4)<lb/> Z 97005<lb/> 3.80<lb/> −1.15<lb/> 15.31<lb/> Z 97005<lb/> 5.80<lb/> −.97<lb/> 14.58<lb/> Z 97005<lb/> 7.70<lb/> −.85<lb/> 14.09<lb/> Z 97005<lb/> 9.60<lb/> −.75<lb/> 13.78<lb/> Z 97005 11.50<lb/> −.67<lb/> 13.52<lb/> Z 97005 15.40<lb/> −.54<lb/> 13.15<lb/> Z 97005 16.70<lb/> −.51<lb/> 13.05<lb/> Z 97005 19.20<lb/> −.45<lb/> 12.92<lb/> Z 97005 22.50<lb/> −.38<lb/> 12.80<lb/> Z 97005 26.90<lb/> −.30<lb/> 12.67<lb/> Z 97005 30.70<lb/> −.25<lb/> 12.61<lb/> Z 97005 34.60<lb/> −.19<lb/> 12.56<lb/> Z 97005 38.40<lb/> −.15<lb/> 12.53<lb/> Z 97011<lb/> 3.80<lb/> −.80<lb/> 14.67<lb/> Z 97011<lb/> 5.80<lb/> −.62<lb/> 14.04<lb/> Z 97011<lb/> 7.70<lb/> −.49<lb/> 13.67<lb/> Z 97011<lb/> 9.60<lb/> −.40<lb/> 13.43<lb/> Z 97011 11.50<lb/> −.32<lb/> 13.26<lb/> Z 97011 15.40<lb/> −.19<lb/> 13.09<lb/> Z 97011 16.70<lb/> −.16<lb/> 13.05<lb/> Z 97011 19.20<lb/> −.10<lb/> 13.01<lb/> Z 97011 22.50<lb/> −.03<lb/> 12.97<lb/> Z 97011 26.90<lb/> .05<lb/> 12.97<lb/> Z 97013<lb/> 3.80<lb/> −1.10<lb/> 16.29<lb/> Z 97013<lb/> 5.80<lb/> −.92<lb/> 15.61<lb/> Z 97013<lb/> 7.70<lb/> −.79<lb/> 15.21<lb/> Z 97013<lb/> 9.60<lb/> −.70<lb/> 14.96<lb/> Z 97013 11.50<lb/> −.62<lb/> 14.76<lb/> Z 97013 15.40<lb/> −.49<lb/> 14.58<lb/> Z 97013 16.70<lb/> −.46<lb/> 14.53<lb/> Z 97013 19.20<lb/> −.40<lb/> 14.53<lb/> Z 97013 22.50<lb/> −.33<lb/> 14.51<lb/> Z 97021<lb/> 3.80<lb/> −.98<lb/> 12.59<lb/> Z 97021<lb/> 5.80<lb/> −.79<lb/> 12.12<lb/> Z 97021<lb/> 7.70<lb/> −.67<lb/> 11.87<lb/> Z 97021<lb/> 9.60<lb/> −.57<lb/> 11.71<lb/> Z 97021 11.50<lb/> −.50<lb/> 11.58<lb/> Z 97021 15.40<lb/> −.37<lb/> 11.41<lb/> Z 97021 16.70<lb/> −.33<lb/> 11.36<lb/> Z 97021 19.20<lb/> −.27<lb/> 11.29<lb/> Z 97021 22.50<lb/> −.20<lb/> 11.21<lb/> Z 97021 27.10<lb/> −.12<lb/> 11.13<lb/> Z 97021 31.50<lb/> −.06<lb/> 11.07<lb/> Z 97021 34.90<lb/> −.01<lb/> 11.02<lb/> Z 97021 38.40<lb/> .03<lb/> 10.98<lb/></table> 

			<figure>Fig. 3. The comparison between the present photometric mea-<lb/>surements and those available from the literature as a function<lb/> of the normalized aperture.<lb/></figure> 

			<head>4.2. Isophotal radii, total magnitudes, and concentration<lb/> indices<lb/></head> 

			<p>Our NIR observations available so far (including those<lb/> given in Papers I, II and IV and in B97) were also analyzed<lb/> using a more sophisticated approach than the one adopted<lb/> here: 1) the surface brightness profiles were derived from<lb/> azimuthally averaged elliptical isophotes with center, ellip-<lb/>ticity and position angle taken as free parameters. 2) the<lb/> surface brightness profiles were decomposed into combina-<lb/>tions of exponential and de Vaucouleurs laws (or double<lb/> exponential profiles) using a fitting algorithm. We pre-<lb/>fer to postpone the discussion of these profile decomposi-<lb/>tions to a forthcoming paper (Paper V of this series; some<lb/> details of the decomposition procedures can be found in<lb/> <ref type="biblio">Scodeggio et al. 1998</ref>). However we wish to anticipate here<lb/> a few results which depend on the fitting algorithms only<lb/> as a tool necessary to extrapolate the measured photome-<lb/>try to infinity: i.e. to obtain total magnitudes, concentra-<lb/>tion indexes and also to derive isophotal radii at a given<lb/> limiting surface brightness (20.5 mag arcsec −2 in this case)<lb/> when the observations do not reach such a limit.<lb/></p> 

			<p><ref type="table">Table 1</ref> gives the H band measured parameters of the ob-<lb/>served galaxies, as follows:<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 18: H B25 magnitude obtained extrapolating the<lb/> present photometric measurements to the optical diame-<lb/>ter along circular apertures as in <ref type="biblio">Gavazzi &amp; Boselli (1996)</ref>.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 19: H c<lb/> B25 magnitude computed at the optical<lb/> diameter (see Column 18) corrected for galactic and<lb/> internal extinction following <ref type="biblio">Gavazzi &amp; Boselli (1996)</ref>.<lb/> The adopted internal extinction correction is ∆m =<lb/> −2.5 D log(b/a) where D=0.17, as determined in <ref type="biblio">Boselli<lb/> &amp; Gavazzi (1994)</ref>.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 20: H T total H magnitude extrapolated to infin-<lb/>ity along either an exponential or a de Vaucouleurs r 1/4<lb/> law fitted to the outer parts of the observed radial surface<lb/> brightness profiles (see Paper V for details).<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 21: galaxy observed major (r H (20.5)) radius (in<lb/> arcsec) determined in the elliptical azimuthally–integrated<lb/> profiles as the radius at which the surface brightness<lb/> reaches 20.5 H–mag arcsec −2 . Galaxies which require a<lb/> surface brightness extrapolation larger than 0.5 mag to<lb/> reach the 20.5 th magnitude isophote are labelled -1.<lb/></p> 

			<p>Column 22: the model–independent concentration index<lb/> C 31 , as defined in <ref type="biblio">de Vaucouleurs (1977)</ref>, is the ratio be-<lb/>tween the radii that enclose 75% and 25% of the total light<lb/> H T .<lb/></p> 

			<head>5. Results<lb/></head> 

			<p>Based on the observations presented in this work, which<lb/> we reiterate does not comprise a complete sample, we de-<lb/>rive the following preliminary results.<lb/></p> 

			<head>5.1. Radii r H (20.5)<lb/></head> 

			<p>The isophotal radii in this work are derived at the 20.5<lb/> mag arcsec −2 H-band isophote, which represents a rather<lb/> bright level, even for H-band measurements. For example<lb/> in Paper I and II we were able to measure similar quanti-<lb/>ties one mag arcsec −2 fainter, i.e. up to 21.5 mag arcsec −2 .<lb/> This is not due to lower signal-to-noise of the present data<lb/> compared with the past data, but rather to the different<lb/> method adopted for deriving the light profiles. In the pre-<lb/>vious papers the radial surface brightness profiles were de-<lb/>rived by azimuthally integrating the counts in concentric<lb/> elliptical coronae of fixed center and ellipticity up to indef-<lb/>inite radii. Here, instead, the center and ellipticity are kept<lb/> as free parameters and the fitting is halted when the mean<lb/> surface brightness within a given elliptical corona equals<lb/> the corresponding rms. fluctuation. The drawback is that<lb/> the new fitting routine halts at higher surface brightnesses<lb/> than before. The lowest surface brightness reached in each<lb/> image is given in <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> as a function of the integration<lb/> time.<lb/></p> 

			<figure>Fig. 4. The distribution of the lowest surface brightness<lb/> reached in the outer light profiles, as a function of the exposure<lb/> time.<lb/></figure> 

			<p>The comparison between the isophotal B band<lb/> r B (25.0) = (a/2) 25 (B) radii (<ref type="biblio">Gavazzi &amp; Boselli 1996</ref>)<lb/> and the infrared r H (20.5) isophotal radii determined in<lb/> this work is shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Apart from the curva-<lb/>ture apparent at small radii, the data are consistent with<lb/> r H (20.5) = 0.7 r B (25.0) between these two arbitrary<lb/> isophotal levels.<lb/></p> 

			<p>This indicates that at the adopted isophotal level, the<lb/> H observations cover a substantial fraction of the light,<lb/> and are not restricted to the bulge. The relationship be-<lb/>tween optical and H-band isophotal radii is consistent with<lb/> that expected from our limiting H surface brightness of<lb/> 20.5 mag arcsec −2 and with the B–H color of the outer<lb/> portion of normal galaxies.<lb/></p> 

			<p>The curvature seen in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref> is only marginally an arte-<lb/>fact of the seeing: the effect is reduced slightly by removing<lb/> the objects observed in the worse seeing conditions. The<lb/> deviation from linearity is not due to an overestimate of<lb/> the H band radii, rather it reflects an underestimate of the<lb/> B band diameter of small (≤ 10 arcsec) early-type galax-<lb/>ies which are intrinsically red (see Paper V for a more<lb/> comprehensive discussion on this issue).<lb/></p> 

			<figure>Fig. 5. The relation between the apparent major isophotal ra-<lb/>dius rH(20.5) as determined in the infrared (this work) and<lb/> in the optical rB(25.0). E+S0 are plotted as open circles,<lb/> S+Irr as filled circles. The solid line represents the relation<lb/> rH(20.5) = 0.7 rB(25.0).<lb/></figure> 

			<head>5.2. Magnitudes (H T , H B25 )<lb/></head> 

			<p>H B25 magnitudes listed in Column 18 of <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> are ob-<lb/>tained by extrapolating the circular aperture measure-<lb/>ments to the optical r B (25.0) radius (as in <ref type="biblio">Gavazzi &amp;<lb/> Boselli 1996</ref>). H T mag instead are obtained by extrapo-<lb/>lating to infinity the magnitude integrated along elliptical<lb/> isophotes using combinations of exponential and de Vau-<lb/>couleurs laws. As expected, H T are brighter than H B25 by<lb/> 0.10 ± 0.2 mag on average.<lb/></p> 

			<head>5.3. Concentration index (C 31 )<lb/></head> 

			<p>The concentration index C 31 is a measure of the shape<lb/> of light profiles in galaxies, independent of a bulge–disk<lb/> decomposition. Values larger than C 31 &gt; 2.8 indicate the<lb/> presence of substantial bulges.<lb/></p> 

			<p>We confirm the presence in our sample of a general<lb/> correlation between C 31 and the H band (H T or H B25 )<lb/> luminosity (computed from the redshift distance). We find<lb/> that C 31 generally increases toward higher absolute mag-<lb/>nitudes (<ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>). High C 31 are found only among high lu-<lb/>minosity systems, but the converse is not true: there are<lb/> several high luminosity systems (namely late–type giant<lb/> spirals) with no or little bulge (C 31 ∼ 3).<lb/></p>

			<head>6. Summary<lb/></head> 

			<p>We have obtained images in the near-infrared H bandpass<lb/> for an optical-magnitude-selected (m p ≤ 15.7) sample of<lb/> 558 nearby (z &lt; 0.02) galaxies primarily of early-type,<lb/> in the regions of Coma and Virgo. We derived H magni-<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 6. The dependence of the near–infrared concentration<lb/> index C31 on H band luminosity.<lb/></figure> 

			<p>tudes at the optical radius, total H magnitudes, isopho-<lb/>tal radii at the 20.5 mag arcsec −2 isophote, and the light<lb/> concentration index C 31 . As mentioned in the Introduc-<lb/>tion, the galaxies presented in this paper do not form by<lb/> themselves a complete sample. Therefore we postpone the<lb/> comprehensive analysis of the NIR properties of galaxies<lb/> to forthcoming papers of this series. Paper V will report<lb/> on the profile decomposition.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
