<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>1. Introduction<lb/></head>

			<p>Materials with large/giant magnetocaloric effect (MCE) have<lb/> gained more and more interest due to their applications for<lb/> magnetic refrigeration. Compared with traditional gas refrig-<lb/>eration, magnetic refrigeration has signicant advantages in<lb/> conversion efficiency, low noise and environmental protec-<lb/>tion. <ref type="biblio">1-5</ref> The MCE manifests as DS M (isothermal magnetic<lb/> entropy change) and DT ad (adiabatic temperature change).<lb/> Finding special materials with a large MCE value is considered<lb/> to be the most important work of magnetic refrigeration, since<lb/> the MCE is an inherent characteristic of magnetic materials. In<lb/> recent years, rare-earth based compounds have been widely<lb/> investigated with respect to their MCE properties. <ref type="biblio">6-19</ref> And some<lb/> of them exhibit large/giant MCE at 10-25 K, which is around the<lb/> boiling point of hydrogen. <ref type="biblio">6-15</ref> Considering the problems in<lb/> application and storage of liquid hydrogen at room tempera-<lb/>ture, these materials are eligible to be applied for magnetic<lb/> refrigeration for hydrogen liquefaction.<lb/></p>

			<p>In the present study, we have investigated the MCE in<lb/> GdCoC 2 which belongs to an existing ternary system RETC 2 (RE<lb/> stands for heavy rare earth element and T stands for transition<lb/> metal Co and Ni). Schafer et al. have reported that all the<lb/> RECoC 2 compounds order ferromagnetically, whereas,<lb/> compounds of RENiC 2 are antiferromagnetic. <ref type="biblio">20-26</ref> Up to the<lb/> present, only the MCE in TbCoC 2 belonging to this series<lb/> compounds has been reported and the maximum magnetic<lb/> entropy change (ÀDS max<lb/> M ) is 15.3 J kg À1 K À1 for the magnetic<lb/> eld change of 0-5 T. <ref type="biblio">15</ref> For the presently studied GdCoC 2 , the<lb/> values of ÀDS max<lb/> M are 16.0 J kg À1 K À1 , 28.4 J kg À1 K À1 , and 32.9 J<lb/> kg À1 K À1 for magnetic eld changes of 0-2 T, 0-5 T and 0-7 T,<lb/> respectively.<lb/></p>

			<head>2. Experimental details<lb/></head>

			<p>The polycrystalline GdCoC 2 sample was synthesized by the<lb/> method of arc-melting. First, stoichiometric amounts of high-<lb/>purity components were weight and 3% extra carbon was<lb/> added to compensate the loss during arc-melting. The sample<lb/> was turned over and melted for four times under an argon<lb/> atmosphere to ensure good homogeneity. Then the sample was<lb/> annealed at 900 C for six days in evacuated quartz tubes and<lb/> rapidly quenched in ice water. The sample was characterized by<lb/> X-ray powder diffraction (XRD) measurement by Rigaku D/MAX<lb/> 2550 using Cu Ka radiation. The magnetization measurements<lb/> were done with a commercial superconducting quantum<lb/> interference device (SQUID) based vibrating sample magne-<lb/>tometer (VSM) (Quantum Design Company, USA).<lb/></p>

			<head>3. Results and discussion<lb/></head>

			<p>The XRD pattern for GdCoC 2 together with the Rietveld rene-<lb/>ment proles which were analyzed by MAUD soware are<lb/> shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. The inset of Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the crystal structure<lb/> diagram obtained by using the CRYSTALMAKER soware<lb/> package. The factors of Rietveld renement which were calcu-<lb/>lated by MAUD soware are R wp (%) ¼ 8.99, R B (%) ¼ 6.69, R exp<lb/> (%) ¼ 12.0. The results reveal that the sample is crystallized in<lb/> single phase with orthorhombic CeNiC 2 -type structure (Amm2<lb/> space group) and no impurity phases can be detected. Accord-<lb/>ing to the Rietveld renement proles, the rened lattice<lb/> parameters a, b, and c are calculated by Bragg equation and<lb/> found to be 3.621, 4.506, and 6.062Å, respectively, which are<lb/> close to the standard values.<lb/></p>

			<p>The zero eld cooling (ZFC) and eld cooling (FC) magnetiza-<lb/>tion (M) at magnetic eld (H) of 0.2 T is shown in the inset of Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>.<lb/> A typical paramagnetic to ferromagnetic (PM-FM) phase transi-<lb/>tion can be observed at the Curie temperature (T C ) $15 K (dened<lb/> as the minimum value of dM/dT curve). No obvious difference can<lb/> be observed between ZFC and FC curves, which is a typical<lb/> behavior for the second order phase transition materials. The<lb/> temperature dependence of magnetization (M) and the inverse<lb/> susceptibility (1/c) under magnetic eld (H) of 1 T are shown in<lb/> Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. At high temperature, the 1/c-T curve shows Curie-Weiss<lb/> behavior. The evaluated value of the effective magnetic moment<lb/> (8.0 m B /f.u.) for GdCoC 2 is close to that of the free ion value of Gd 3+<lb/> (7.94 m B ). A set of magnetization isotherm (M-H) was measured at<lb/> temperatures from 3 K to 45 K under magnetic eld up to 7 T, and<lb/> several M-H curves with increasing eld are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>.<lb/> Among them, the hysteresis cycles at 3 K, 13 K, 15 K, 20 K, and 30 K<lb/> are shown in the gure as well. No obvious hysteresis is observed<lb/> and the magnetization rapidly changes with varying temperature<lb/> around T C , i.e. a large reversible MCE may appear around 15 K.<lb/> The inset of Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the M 2 versus H/M curves (also named as<lb/> Arrot plot) from 3 K to 45 K. Based on the Banerjee criterion, <ref type="biblio">27</ref> the<lb/> present GdCoC 2 undergoes a second-order magnetic phase tran-<lb/>sition since neither negative slope nor inection can be observed<lb/> in the whole temperature range.<lb/></p>

			<p>The isothermal magnetic-entropy change DS M is obtained<lb/> from magnetization isotherms by integrating the Maxwell<lb/> relation<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 1 XRD pattern for GdCoC 2 together with the Rietveld refinement profiles, Bragg peak positions, Rietveld profiles. The inset shows the crystal<lb/> structure diagram.<lb/> Fig. 2 Temperature dependence of magnetization (left scale) and the<lb/> inverse susceptibility (right scale) for GdCoC 2 . The inset shows the<lb/> temperature dependence of zero field cooling (ZFC) and field cooling<lb/> (FC) magnetization (M) under magnetic fields (H) ¼ 0.2 T.<lb/> Fig. 3 Magnetic field (H) dependence of the magnetization (M) for<lb/> GdCoC 2 at different temperatures. The inset shows the Arrot plots<lb/> curves (M 2 versus H/M).<lb/> DS M ðT; DHÞ ¼<lb/> ð Hmax<lb/> 0<lb/> vM<lb/> vT<lb/> H<lb/> dH z<lb/> 1<lb/> DT<lb/> ð Hmax<lb/> 0<lb/> Â<lb/> MðT iþ1 ; HÞ<lb/> À MðT i ; HÞ<lb/> Ã<lb/> dH;<lb/></figure>

			<p>The temperature-dependent ÀDS M under magnetic eld<lb/> changes up to 0-7 T is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. ÀDS M increases with the<lb/> increasing value of DH. The maxima of ÀDS M appears around<lb/> 17 K, which is close to the paramagnetic to ferromagnetic (PM-<lb/>FM) phase transition. The values of ÀDS max<lb/> M<lb/> are equal to 9.3 J<lb/> kg À1 K À1 , 20.9 J kg À1 K À1 , 28.4 J kg À1 K À1 , 32.9 J kg À1 K À1 under<lb/> the eld changes of 0-1 T, 0-3 T, 0-5 T and 0-7 T, respectively.<lb/> These values are around two times of those for TbCoC 2 and<lb/> larger than those of most of recently reported giant MCE<lb/> materials in the same temperature range, indicating that the<lb/> presently studied GdCoC 2 compound belongs to a class of giant<lb/> MCE materials. The origin of giant MCE in GdCoC 2 is probably<lb/> related to the large saturation moment, especially under low<lb/> magnetic eld as well as its eld and temperature sensitive<lb/> magnetic phase transition. Additionally, the large value of<lb/> ÀDS max<lb/> M of 16.0 J kg À1 K À1 is reached under the eld changes of<lb/> 0-2 T with a quite wide temperature range for present GdCoC 2 ,<lb/> which is quite benecial to application.<lb/></p>

			<p>Franco et al. revealed a universal behavior of the eld<lb/> dependence of DS M for the materials with a second-order<lb/> transition, i.e. in ref. <ref type="biblio">28</ref>, the DS M versus T curves under<lb/> different magnetic elds can collapse into a universal curve;<lb/> therefore the inuence of different magnetic elds can be<lb/> ignored. All the curves are normalized to their respective<lb/> maximum value as DS M /DS max<lb/> M<lb/> and the axis of temperature is<lb/> rescaled to q below and above T C ,<lb/></p>

				<formula>q ¼<lb/> &amp;<lb/> ÀðT À T C Þ=ðT r1 À T C Þ ; T # T C<lb/> ðT À T C Þ=ðT r2 À T C Þ ; T . T C<lb/> ;<lb/></formula>

			<p>T r1 and T r2 are the temperatures of the two reference points of<lb/> each curve that corresponds to 0.6 ÀDS max<lb/> M . The curves of<lb/> normalized entropy change DS M /DS max<lb/> M<lb/> versus the rescaled<lb/> temperature q under different magnetic elds are shown in the<lb/> inset of Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. All the curves under different magnetic elds<lb/> collapse onto a single line for GdCoC 2 , which further conrms<lb/> that the present GdCoC 2 undergoes a second order magnetic<lb/> phase transition.<lb/></p>

			<p>The relative cooling power (RCP) and refrigerant capacity<lb/> (RC) are important factors to evaluate refrigeration materials.<lb/> The values of RCP can be calculated as<lb/></p>

				<formula>RCP ¼ ÀS max<lb/> M Â dT FWHM<lb/></formula>

			<p>dT FWHM is the full width at half maximum and ÀDS max<lb/> M<lb/> is the<lb/> maximum of magnetic entropy change, respectively. <ref type="biblio">4</ref> The values<lb/> of RCP for GdCoC 2 are 216, 566, 769 J kg À1 for DH ¼ 0-2, 0-5<lb/> and 0-7 T, respectively. The values of RC can be calculated as<lb/></p>

				<formula>RC ¼<lb/> ð T 2<lb/> T 1<lb/> jDS M jdT;<lb/></formula>

			<p>T 1 and T 2 are the temperatures of half-maximum value of ÀDS M<lb/> peak. <ref type="biblio">4</ref> The value of RC for GdCoC 2 are equal to 160, 369, 514 J<lb/> kg À1 for DH ¼ 0-2, 0-5 and 0-7 T, respectively. For a compar-<lb/>ison, the transition temperature (T M ), together with the values<lb/> of ÀDS max<lb/> M , RCP and RC with the eld change from 0 to 2 T and 5<lb/> T for GdCoC 2 and some recently reported large/giant MCE<lb/> materials with T M around 15 K are shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. These<lb/> values for GdCoC 2 are obviously larger than most of those re-<lb/>ported materials in the similar working temperature range.<lb/></p>

			<head>4. Conclusions<lb/></head>

			<p>In summary, a single phase GdCoC 2 compound is synthesized,<lb/> and its crystal structure, magnetic properties and magneto-<lb/>caloric properties have been investigated. The compound<lb/> undergoes a second-order paramagnetic to ferromagnetic (PM-<lb/>FM) transition at the Curie temperature T C $ 15 K. Accompa-<lb/>nied with the transition, giant reversible MCE is observed. The<lb/> values of ÀDS max<lb/> M<lb/> for GdCoC 2 reach 16.0, 28.4, and 32.9 J kg À1<lb/> K À1 for the eld changes of 0-2 T, 0-5 T and 0-7 T, respectively.<lb/> The corresponding values of RCP (RC) are 216 (160), 566 (369),<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 4 Temperature-dependent magnetic entropy change ÀDS M for<lb/> GdCoC 2 in various magnetic fields changes. The inset shows the<lb/> universal curves.<lb/></figure>

			<figure type="table">Table 1 The transition temperature (T M ), ÀDS max<lb/> M<lb/> and relative cooling<lb/> power (RCP) under 2 T and 5 T for GdCoC 2 and other materials with<lb/> large<lb/> ÀDS max<lb/> M<lb/> (J kg À1 K À1 )<lb/> RCP (J kg À1 )<lb/> Reference<lb/> T M (K)<lb/> 2 T<lb/> 5 T<lb/> 2 T<lb/> 5 T<lb/> GdCoC 2<lb/> 15<lb/> 16.0<lb/> 28.4<lb/> 216<lb/> 566<lb/> Present<lb/> Eu 8 Ga 16 Ge 30<lb/> 11<lb/> 4.5<lb/> 11.5<lb/> 80<lb/> 400<lb/> 7<lb/> GdNiBC<lb/> 15<lb/> 9.3<lb/> 19.8<lb/> 188<lb/> 474<lb/> 8<lb/> HoAgAl<lb/> 18<lb/> 3.8<lb/> 10.3<lb/> 99<lb/> 344<lb/> 10<lb/> ErFeSi<lb/> 22<lb/> 14.2<lb/> 23.1<lb/> $171<lb/> $486<lb/> 29<lb/> GdCo 2 B 2<lb/> 25<lb/> 9.3<lb/> 17.1<lb/> 167<lb/> 462<lb/> 14<lb/> TbCoC 2<lb/> 28<lb/> 7<lb/> 15.3<lb/> $115<lb/> $375<lb/> 15<lb/></figure>

			<p>and 769 (514) J kg À1 . For the reason that the compound has<lb/> large MCE and small hysteresis in a wide temperature range, it<lb/> could be considered as potential refrigerant material for low<lb/> temperature magnetic refrigeration.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
