<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>1 | INTRODUCTION<lb/></head>

			<p>Chagas disease (CD), which is also referred to as American<lb/> trypanosomiasis (AT) is a potentially fatal condition that<lb/> is caused by Trypanosoma cruzi. This parasite is trans-<lb/>mitted through the bite of an infected insect known as<lb/> a &quot;kissing bug&quot; <ref type="biblio">(Rassi &amp; de Rezende, 2012)</ref>. Up to seven<lb/> million people worldwide have a T. cruzi infection, and<lb/> about 75 million people living in endemic regions (Latin<lb/> America) are at risk of contracting the disease <ref type="biblio">(Rodriguez<lb/> &amp; Loaiza, 2017)</ref>. Annually, there are about 12,000 deaths<lb/> attributed to AT. The incidence of AT is rising in both<lb/> endemic and non-endemic regions of the world due to a<lb/> variety of variables, including climate change, and inter-<lb/>national travel <ref type="biblio">(Campos et al., 2017; Velázquez-Ramírez<lb/> et al., 2022)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Nifurtimox and benznidazole are the only two medi-<lb/>cations currently available for the treatment of CD and<lb/> have been in use since the 1970s. These medications<lb/> have side effects and are only useful in the acute or early<lb/> stages of the infection. Some detrimental effects of these<lb/> drugs include anorexia, nausea, vomiting, seizures, ver-<lb/>tigo, headaches, and dermatitis; consequently causing<lb/> 10%-30% of patients to stop taking their medications<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(García-Huertas &amp; Cardona-Castro, 2021)</ref>. According to<lb/> estimates, AT results in an annual global spending of<lb/> USD 627.5 million, mostly in the form of medical ex-<lb/>penses. The cost per AT patient ranges from $200 in the<lb/> early stages of the disease to $6000 in the chronic stage.<lb/> Due to this cost, AT has been identified as a parasitic<lb/> disease with the highest global burden <ref type="biblio">(Gómez-Ochoa<lb/> et al., 2022)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Human African trypanosomiasis (HAT), also referred<lb/> to as sleeping sickness, is a neglected disease solely found<lb/> in Africa, and it is caused by Trypanosoma brucei-a par-<lb/>asitic protozoan transmitted to mammals through the bite<lb/> of an infected tsetse fly <ref type="biblio">(Dunn et al., 2021)</ref>. Two subspecies<lb/> of T. brucei, T. b. gambiense and T. b. rhodesiense, cause<lb/> HAT in humans <ref type="biblio">(Magez et al., 2021)</ref>. If untreated, the ill-<lb/>ness is almost always lethal <ref type="biblio">(Beteck et al., 2019)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Sleeping sickness progresses through two distinct<lb/> stages. In the first or early stage of the disease, trypano-<lb/>somes are limited to the blood and lymphatic systems. In<lb/> the second or late stage of the disease, parasites invade the<lb/> central nervous system <ref type="biblio">(Steverding, 2008)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Depending on whether or not parasites crossed the<lb/> blood-brain barrier (determined by examination of ce-<lb/>rebrospinal fluid obtained by lumbar puncture), the few<lb/> current HAT medications are split into two categories.<lb/> Suramin or pentamidine injections are given intramuscu-<lb/>larly (IM) for Stage 1 HAT. Melarsoprol or eflornithine/ni-<lb/>furtimox combination are used for the treatment of Stage<lb/> 2 HAT. Due to the toxicity of the molecules used to treat<lb/> Stage 2 and/or the challenges associated with administer-<lb/>ing them, patients in Stage 2 are typically treated in hospi-<lb/>tals <ref type="biblio">(Eperon et al., 2014; Venturelli et al., 2022)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Visceral leishmaniasis (VL) is predominantly caused by<lb/> Leishmania donovani and L. infantum parasites-which<lb/> have phlebotomine sand flies as their vector. The risk<lb/> factors for VL include malnutrition, human immunode-<lb/>ficiency virus infection and acquired immunodeficiency<lb/> syndrome (HIV-AIDS), and other immunosuppressive<lb/> diseases/conditions <ref type="biblio">(Adriaensen et al., 2018; Lindoso<lb/> et al., 2016)</ref>. According to World Health Organization<lb/> (WHO) reports, leishmaniasis poses a threat to 350 mil-<lb/>lion people in 98 countries. In 2020, nearly 90% of all new<lb/> VL cases reported to the WHO came from 10 countries:<lb/> Brazil, China, Ethiopia, Eritrea, India, Kenya, Somalia,<lb/> South Sudan, Sudan, and Yemen <ref type="biblio">(Yimer et al., 2022)</ref>. East<lb/> Africa is currently the most affected region in the world,<lb/> accounting for 45% of all cases reported to the WHO in<lb/> 2018. In the Mediterranean region, Central Asia, and<lb/> South America, VL is extensively dispersed <ref type="biblio">(Carvalho<lb/> et al., 2021; Maroli et al., 2013)</ref>. Around 700 cases of au-<lb/>tochthonous VL in Southern Europe have been reported<lb/> annually in nine European Union nations <ref type="biblio">(Dujardin<lb/> et al., 2008)</ref>. Each year, 130 cases on average are reported<lb/> in <ref type="biblio">Morocco (Echchakery et al., 2018)</ref> and almost 90% of<lb/> VL cases can result in mortality if appropriate treatment<lb/> is not started promptly <ref type="biblio">(van Griensven &amp; Diro, 2012)</ref>. Few<lb/> therapeutic options are available, but none of them are<lb/> currently the ideal option because of high toxicity, exorbi-<lb/>tant cost, a lengthy course of therapy, unsuitable mode of<lb/> administration, and patient&apos;s none-compliance which is<lb/> precipitating the emergence of resistance <ref type="biblio">(Freitas-Junior<lb/> et al., 2012)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Quinazolinone is a heterocyclic molecule having<lb/> two isomers: 2-and 4-quinazolinone (see Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>).<lb/> Quinazolinone derivatives have been investigated and<lb/> reported to exhibit a wide spectrum of biological proper-<lb/>ties, including anti-cytotoxin, analgesic, anti-tuberculosis,<lb/> anti-HIV, antibacterial, anti-hypertensive, antifungal,<lb/> anti-inflammatory, anti-diabetic, anti-oxidation, anti-<lb/>malarial, anticonvulsant, anticancer activities <ref type="biblio">(Jafari<lb/> et al., 2016; Liu et al., 2018; Radwan &amp; Alanazi, 2020;<lb/> Rajput &amp; Mishra, 2012; Tiwary et al., 2015)</ref>. There are<lb/> several synthetic procedures that allow for easy access to<lb/> quinazolinone derivatives. Based on this, we are interested<lb/> in identifying cost-effective anti-parasitic quinazolinone-<lb/>based hits/leads.<lb/></p>

			<head>2 | RESULTS AND DISCUSSION<lb/> </head>
				
			<head>2.1 | Chemistry<lb/></head>

			<p>We synthesized 19 new compounds with various substitu-<lb/>ents at position 2 of the quinazoline scaffold (Scheme <ref type="figure">1</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<head>2.2 | In vitro antiprotozoal activities and<lb/> cell toxicity<lb/></head>

			<p>Nineteen compounds were synthesized and tested for<lb/> activity against four parasitic protozoans. Table <ref type="table">1</ref> com-<lb/>piles the IC 50 values of 12 compounds showing activity<lb/> against one or more parasitic protozoans deployed in<lb/> this study.<lb/> </p>
				
			<p>Compounds KJ1 and KJ10 had the best antitrypano-<lb/>somal activity in this study, exhibiting low micromolar<lb/> activity of ~5 μM, and ~1 μM against T. b. rhodesiense. The<lb/> activity data suggest that quinazolinones wherein the<lb/> aroyl moiety at position 2 bears Br, or a NO 2 unit promote<lb/> activity against T. b. rhodesiense. KJ10 also demonstrated<lb/> low micromolar activity against T. b. brucei, exhibiting an<lb/> IC 50 value of ~4 μM. Compounds in this study were gener-<lb/>ally not active against T. cruzi, and L. infantum.<lb/></p>

			<figure>F I G U R E 1 Structures of 2-and 4-quinazolinone.<lb/></figure>

			<p>All 19 compounds were also screened against the<lb/> human fetal lung fibroblast (MRC-5) cell line to investi-<lb/>gate potential toxicity to normal human cells. The min-<lb/>imum concentration required to reduce cell viability by<lb/> 50% (CC 50 ) was determined for all compounds. Only KJ25<lb/> and KJ26 exhibited moderate cell toxicity with CC 50 val-<lb/>ues of 15 μM and 12 μM, respectively. Quinazolinone de-<lb/>rivatives investigated in this study generally showed weak<lb/> to little toxicity against the MRC-5 cell line.<lb/></p>

			<p>As most of the molecules investigated were more ac-<lb/>tive against T. b. rhodesiense, activity data against this<lb/> target was used to generate a selectivity index (SI) in re-<lb/>lation to the MRC-5 cell line. SI is the ratio of cytotoxicity<lb/> against MRC-5 cells and activity against T. b. rhodesiense.<lb/> Compounds with SI values &gt;10 are presumed to have<lb/> intrinsic activity against the target, with minimal risk to<lb/> mammalian or human cells. The calculated SI for T. b. rh-<lb/>odesiense ranged from 0.5 to &gt;55.<lb/></p>

			<head>3 | MATERIALS AND METHODS<lb/> </head>
				
			<head>3.1 | Chemical and instrumentation<lb/></head>

			<p>Reagents and solvents were purchased from Merck (Pty)<lb/> Ltd and were used as supplied. Thin layer chromatogra-<lb/>phy (TLC), making use of Merck 60F 254 silica gel plates<lb/> supported on 0.20 mm thick aluminum sheets, was used<lb/> to monitor reactions. After development, plates were<lb/> visualized under ultraviolet (UV) light at 254 nm and<lb/> 366 nm and/or in an iodine chamber. Where necessary,<lb/> the crude compounds were purified by silica gel col-<lb/>umn chromatography using Merck Kieselgel 60 Å: 70-<lb/>230 (0.068-0.2 mm) silica gel mesh. 1 H and 13 C NMR<lb/> spectra were recorded on a Bruker Biospin 600 MHz<lb/> spectrometer. Chemical shift data are reported relative<lb/> to the residual solvent peaks (DMSO d 6 : 2.5 ppm for 1 H<lb/> and 39.5 ppm for 13 C). MestReNova software was used<lb/> to process the spectra. The J-coupling constants and<lb/> chemical shifts were measured in Hertz (Hz) and parts<lb/> per million (ppm) respectively. Signal multiplicities are<lb/> denoted as follows: s for a singlet, d for a doublet, dd for<lb/> the doublet of doublet, ddd for the doublet of the dou-<lb/>blet of the doublets, t for a triplet and m for a multiplet.<lb/> High-resolution mass spectra (HRMS) were recorded on<lb/> Bruker micrOTOF-Q II mass spectrometer using atmos-<lb/>pheric pressure chemical ionization (APCI) technique<lb/> in positive ion mode. A Büchi® melting point appara-<lb/>tus (Model B-545, AC/DC input 230 V AC) was used to<lb/> determine the melting points of the target compounds.<lb/> A Bruker ALPHA FTIR spectrometer with a Diamond<lb/> Crystal ATR (Attenuated Total Internal Reflectance)<lb/> accessory was used for the Fourier-transform infrared<lb/> spectroscopy (FTIR).<lb/></p>

			<head>3.2 | Procedures for the synthesis of<lb/> target compounds<lb/></head>

			<p>A mixture of acetophenone (441.2 mg, 3.67 mmol), I 2<lb/> (1.1 equiv), 2-aminobenzamide (1.0 equiv), and DMSO<lb/> (15 mL) was stirred at 110°C for 18-48 h. After reaction<lb/> </p>
				
			<figure>S C H E M E 1 Synthetic route for the preparation of 2-aroyl-quinazolin-4(3H)-ones. A variety of spectroscopic techniques, including FTIR,<lb/> 1<lb/> H NMR, 13 C NMR, and high-resolution mass spectrometry, were used to characterize the target compounds. The signal at 12 ppm in the<lb/> 1<lb/> H NMR spectra is assignable to the amide -NH-unit, which confirms the formation of the quinazolinone core. In the 13 C NMR, the amide<lb/> carbonyl carbon appears at ca 152 ppm, while the peak at ca 188 ppm is assignable to the carbonyl carbon at position 2 of the quinazolinone<lb/> core. The molecular ion peak was confirmed for all compounds using APCI/HRMS. The FTIR spectra of all target compounds displayed<lb/> absorbances at 3000 cm -1 (N-H-stretching), 1640 and 1730 cm -1 (C=O-stretching).<lb/> N<lb/> NH<lb/> O<lb/> O<lb/> NH 2<lb/> NH 2<lb/> O<lb/> O<lb/> R 1<lb/> +<lb/> I 2 , DMSO, 110 O C<lb/> 1<lb/> 2<lb/> KJ1-KJ35<lb/> R 1<lb/> 1<lb/> 3<lb/> 4<lb/> 5<lb/> 6<lb/> 7<lb/> 8<lb/> 2<lb/> 2a 2b<lb/> 2c<lb/> 2d<lb/> 2e<lb/> 2f<lb/> KJ1:R 1 = 2 d -Br<lb/> KJ2: R 1 = 2 c -Cl; 2 f -OH<lb/> KJ7: R 1 = 2 d -benzene<lb/> KJ8: R 1 = 2 c -MeO; 2 d -OH<lb/> KJ10: R 1 = 2 d -NO 2<lb/> KJ12: R 1 = 2 c -NO 2<lb/> KJ14: R 1 = 2 d -OH<lb/> KJ16: R 1 = 2 d -Cl<lb/> KJ17: R 1 = 2 b -benzyloxy<lb/> KJ18: R 1 = 2 d -CH 2 CH 3<lb/> KJ21: R 1 = 2 c -MeO; 2 d -benzyloxy<lb/> KJ23: R 1 = 2 d -ethoxy; 2 e -MeO<lb/> KJ25: R 1 = 2 b -p-Cl-benzyloxy<lb/> KJ26: R 1 = 2 b -p-Br-benzyloxy<lb/> KJ31: R 1 = 2 c -MeO; 2 d -p-NO 2 -benzyloxy<lb/> KJ32: R 1 = 2 c -MeO; 2 d -p-Br-benzyloxy<lb/> KJ33: R 1 = 2 c -MeO; 2 d -OCH 2 CH 2 CHCH 3 CH 3<lb/> KJ34: R 1 = 2 b -p-methylbenzyloxy<lb/> KJ35: R 1 = 2 b -p-NO 2 -benzyloxy<lb/></figure>

			<p>completion, 50 mL of water and 50 mL of saturated brine<lb/> solution were added to the mixture and extracted with<lb/> dichloromethane (50 mL ×3). The organic phase was<lb/> washed with a 10% solution of Na 2 S 2 O 3 , dried over an-<lb/>hydrous Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated in vacuo to furnish<lb/> the crude products. Crudes were purified through recrys-<lb/>tallization from ethyl acetate or flushed through a silica<lb/> gel column using DCM as the mobile phase <ref type="biblio">(Fletcher-<lb/>Charles et al., 2022; Kim et al., 2020</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<head>3.2.1 | Williamson Ether synthesis<lb/></head>

			<p>The general procedure of alkylation with alkyl halides<lb/> of 2a-2j<lb/> A round-bottom flask was charged with 2 mL of appro-<lb/>priately substituted acetophenone, aryl/alkyl halide (1.0<lb/> equiv), and K 2 CO 3 (1.2 equiv). Acetonitrile (15 mL) was<lb/> added, and the mixture was stirred under reflux for 16 h.<lb/> Once the reaction was completed, 50 mL of water was<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">T A B L E 1 Results of anti-parasitic activity, cytotoxicity, and selectivity index of selected 2-aroylquinazolin-4(3H)-ones derivatives.<lb/> Compound<lb/> N<lb/> NH<lb/> O<lb/> O<lb/> R 1<lb/> 1<lb/> 3<lb/> 4<lb/> 5<lb/> 6<lb/> 7<lb/> 8<lb/> 2<lb/> 2a 2b<lb/> 2c<lb/> 2d<lb/> 2e<lb/> 2f<lb/> Anti-parasitic activity IC 50 (μM)<lb/> Cytotoxicity<lb/> IC 50 (μM)<lb/> Selectivity<lb/> index (SI)<lb/> Entry<lb/> R 1 -position<lb/> T.b. Cruz<lb/> L. Inf<lb/> T.b. bruc<lb/> T.b. rhod<lb/> MRC-5<lb/> MRC-5/T.b.<lb/> rhod<lb/> KJ1<lb/> 2 d -Br<lb/> &gt;64<lb/> 43.07<lb/> &gt;64<lb/> 4.73<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;13.5<lb/> KJ2<lb/> 2 c -Cl, 2 f -OH<lb/> 41.78<lb/> 43.07<lb/> &gt;64<lb/> 51.18<lb/> 37.20<lb/> 0.7<lb/> KJ7<lb/> 2 d -<lb/>&gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> n.d<lb/> KJ10<lb/> 2 d -NO 2<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> 36.16<lb/> 4.46<lb/> 1.16<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;55.2<lb/> KJ12<lb/> 2 c -NO 2<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> 17.45<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;3.7<lb/> KJ16<lb/> 2 d -Cl<lb/> 32.24<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> 36.52<lb/> 53.20<lb/> 1.5<lb/> KJ17<lb/> 2 b -<lb/>O<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> n.d<lb/> KJ18<lb/> 2 d -<lb/>&gt;64.00<lb/> 24.05<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> 37.91<lb/> 28.32<lb/> 0.7<lb/> KJ23<lb/> 2 d -ethoxy; 2 e -MeO<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> 26.02<lb/> 25.71<lb/> 55.96<lb/> 2.2<lb/> KJ25<lb/> 2 b -<lb/>O<lb/> Cl<lb/> 31.12<lb/> 32.46<lb/> 28.32<lb/> 22.03<lb/> 15.25<lb/> 0.7<lb/> KJ26<lb/> 2 b -<lb/>O<lb/> Br<lb/> 31.01<lb/> 24.05<lb/> 28.85<lb/> 24.76<lb/> 12.49<lb/> 0.5<lb/> KJ31<lb/> 2 c -MeO<lb/> 2 d -<lb/>O<lb/> NO 2<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> &gt;64.00<lb/> 27.18<lb/> 32.68<lb/> 1.2<lb/> Abbreviations: L. inf, Leishmania infatum; n.d, not detected; SI, selectivity index; T.b. bruc, Trypanosoma brucei brucei; T.b. cruz, Trypanosoma cruzi; T.b. rhod,<lb/> Trypanosoma brucei rhodesiense; μM, micromolar concentrations.<lb/></figure>

			<p>added, and the mixture was stirred for an additional 5 min.<lb/> The ensuing precipitate was filtered, dried, and used in<lb/> the next step without further purification.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.3 | 2-(4-bromobenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ1)<lb/></head>

			<p>White powder, yield 3.89%, m.p 240-243°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.74 (s, 1H), 8.48 (d, J = 1.9 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 8.19-8.09 (m, 3H), 7.83-7.79 (m, 2H), 7.75 (dt,<lb/> J = 10.2, 5.1 Hz, 1H), 7.56 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.52 (dd,<lb/> J = 8.1, 3.3 Hz, 1H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ<lb/> 185.9, 148.9, 143.0, 142.8, 134.3, 134.1, 133.0, 132.4, 131.5,<lb/> 129.7, 129.7, 128.5, 124.5. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 665.31<lb/> (C-Br stretching), 1602.40 (C=N stretching), 1660.00<lb/> (C=O stretching), and 2917.62 (N-H stretching). The<lb/> HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 15 H 10 BrN 2 O 2<lb/> 328.9920; found: 328.9900.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.4 | 2-(5-chloro-2-hydroxybenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ2)<lb/></head>

			<p>Mustard powder, yield 17.30% and m.p 300.4-302.2°C. 1 H<lb/> NMR (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 13.80 (s, 1H), 12.51 (s, 1H),<lb/> 8.33 (d, J = 2.6 Hz, 1H), 8.15 (dd, J = 7.9, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.86-<lb/>7.86 (m, 1H), 7.77 (d, J = 7.9 Hz, 1H), 7.56 (d, J = 8.3 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 7.47 (dd, J = 8.8, 2.5 Hz, 1H), 7.02 (dd, J = 8.8, 4.8 Hz,<lb/> 1H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 192.0, 158.6, 152.6,<lb/> 143.2, 135.0, 134.2, 133.3, 133.1, 127.3, 127.2, 127.1, 126.0,<lb/> 122.6, 122.5, 119.6. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 580.24 (C-Cl<lb/> stretching), 1608.59 (C=O stretching), 1673.23 (C=N<lb/> stretching), 2987.78 (N-H stretching), and 3151.01 (O-H<lb/> stretching). The HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated<lb/> for C 15 H 10 ClN 2 O 3 301.0374; found: 301.0375.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.5 | 2-([1,1′-biphenyl]-4-carbonyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ7)<lb/></head>

			<p>White powder, yield 16.28% and m.p 199°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.59 (s, 1H), 8.27 (d, J = 8.4 Hz,<lb/> 2H), 8.23 (dd, J = 7.9, 0.9 Hz, 1H), 7.89 (d, J = 8.4 Hz,<lb/> 3H), 7.80 (t, J = 7.4 Hz, 3H), 7.66 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 1H),<lb/> 7.52 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 7.45 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 1H). 13 C NMR<lb/> (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 186.5, 161.1, 149.1, 147.1, 145.5,<lb/> 138.7, 134.7, 132.9, 131.6, 129.1, 128.6, 128.5, 128.3,<lb/> 127.1, 126.7, 126.0, 122.8. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1665.69<lb/> (C=O stretching), 1694.90 (C=N stretching), 2914.43<lb/> (C-H stretching), and 2960.08 (N-H stretching). The<lb/> HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 21 H 15 N 2 O 2<lb/> 327.1128; found: 327.1138.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.6 | 2-(4-hydroxy-3-methoxybenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ8)<lb/></head>

			<p>Yellow powder, yield 14.71% and m.p 209°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.42 (s, 1H), 10.27 (s, 1H), 8.23 (d,<lb/> J = 1.8 Hz, 1H), 8.12 (d, J = 7.4 Hz, 1H), 7.84 (d, J = 1.6 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 7.82 (d, J = 7.1 Hz, 1H), 7.79 (d, J = 9.7 Hz, 1H), 7.73<lb/> (d, J = 8.1 Hz, 1H), 7.48 (t, J = 7.4 Hz, 1H), 3.94 (s, 3H).<lb/> 13<lb/> C NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 180.6, 162.2, 150.6,<lb/> 149.2, 148.7, 146.6, 134.5, 130.1, 127.3, 126.2, 125.8, 125.0,<lb/> 120.6, 110.9, 84.4, 56.3. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1641.96 (C-H<lb/> stretching), 1675.81 (C=O stretching), 1689.02 (C=N<lb/> stretching), 2970.13 (N-H stretching), and 3178.00 (O-H<lb/> stretching). The HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated<lb/> for C 16 H 13 N 2 O 4 297.0870; found: 297.0851.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.7 | 2-(4-nitrobenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ10)<lb/></head>

			<p>Yellow powder, yield 11.07% and m.p 225°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.54 (s, 1H), 8.42 (d, J = 8.9 Hz,<lb/> 2H), 8.38 (d, J = 8.8 Hz, 2H), 8.24 (d, J = 7.0 Hz, 1H),<lb/> 7.90 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 1H), 7.79 (d, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 7.68 (t,<lb/> J = 7.5 Hz, 1H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 185.6,<lb/> 160.6, 150.0, 147.8, 146.6, 139.2, 134.4, 131.9, 128.7,<lb/> 128.2, 125.8, 122.9, 122.8. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1546.56<lb/> (N-O stretching), 1662.73 (C=N stretching), 1701.00<lb/> (C=O stretching), and 2916.02 (N-H stretching). The<lb/> HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 15 H 10 N 3 O 4<lb/> 296.0666; found: 296.0672.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.8 | 2-(3-nitrobenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ12)<lb/></head>

			<p>Olive green powder, yield 10.88% and m.p 244°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.92 (s, 1H), 9.01 (t, J = 2.0 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 8.61-8.59 (m, 1H), 8.43-8.40 (m, 1H), 8.17-8.10 (m,<lb/> 1H), 7.89-7.76 (m, 3H), 7.56 (dt, J = 3.2, 2.2 Hz, 1H). 13 C<lb/> NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 160.8, 147.9, 143.0, 134.7,<lb/> 134.2, 134.0, 133.9, 130.2, 127.1, 125.9, 125.7, 122.7, 122.6,<lb/> 121.2, 92.2. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1502.97 (N-O stretch-<lb/>ing), 1668.69 (C=O stretching), and 2965.20 (N-H stretch-<lb/>ing). The HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for<lb/> C 15 H 10 N 3 O 4 296.0666; found: 296.0671.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.9 | 2-(4-hydroxybenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ14)<lb/></head>

			<p>Mustard powder, yield 23.63% and m.p 227.3-229.6°C.<lb/> 1 H NMR (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.56 (s, 1H), 11.66 (s,<lb/> 1H), 8.60-8.56 (m, 2H), 8.21 (dd, J = 8.1, 1.1 Hz, 1H),<lb/> 8.12-8.09 (m, 1H), 7.91-7.88 (m, 1H), 7.78 (dd, J = 7.7,<lb/> 4.4 Hz, 1H), 7.65 (ddd, J = 6.8, 6.2, 2.8 Hz, 1H), 7.03 (d,<lb/> J = 8.6 Hz, 1H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 183.8,<lb/> 162.3, 142.2, 138.4, 134.7, 134.7, 133.3, 128.5, 127.0,<lb/> 126.0, 126.0, 114.5, 85.8. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1643.29<lb/> (C=N stretching), 1672.41 (C=O stretching), 2987.46<lb/> (N-H stretching), and 3291.67 (O-H stretching). The<lb/> HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 15 H 11 N 2 O 3<lb/> 267.0745; found: 267.0745.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.10 | 2-(4-chlorobenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ16)<lb/></head>

			<p>White powder, yield 11.67% and m.p 231°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.78 (s, 1H), 8.40 (d, J = 2.1 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 8.21-8.08 (m, 3H), 7.86-7.70 (m, 1H), 7.67-7.64<lb/> (m, 1H), 7.63-7.59 (m, 1H), 7.57-7.50 (m, 1H). 13 C NMR<lb/> (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 185.7, 142.9, 139.2, 134.6, 134.3,<lb/> 134.1, 132.7, 129.6, 129.5, 128.6, 128.6, 126.7, 125.8. IR<lb/> (ATR) V max cm -1 : 586.61 (C-Cl stretching), 1665.04<lb/> (C=O stretching), and 2925.77 (N-H stretching). The<lb/> HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 15 H 10 ClN 2 O 2<lb/> 285.0425; found: 285.0400.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.11 | 2-(2-(benzyloxy)benzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ17)<lb/></head>

			<p>White powder, yield 24.45%, and m.p 168°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.65 (s, 1H), 8.11 (dd, J = 7.9,<lb/> 1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.84-7.81 (m, 1H), 7.73-7.63 (m, 2H), 7.60-<lb/>7.56 (m, 1H), 7.53-7.48 (m, 1H), 7.42-7.39 (m, 1H), 7.30-<lb/>7.25 (m, 1H), 7.17 (s, 1H), 7.11 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 1H), 6.99-6.95<lb/> (m, 2H), 6.93 (d, J = 7.1 Hz, 1H), 5.15-4.93 (m, 2H). 13 C<lb/> NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 189.1, 160.9, 158.1, 150.9,<lb/> 147.5, 135.5, 135.0, 134.5, 130.5, 128.5, 127.9, 127.8, 127.7,<lb/> 127.6, 127.2, 127.0, 126.0, 125.3, 122.7, 121.0, 113.5, 70.0.<lb/> IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1608.62 (C-N stretching), 1660.65<lb/> (C=O stretching), and 2971.62 (N-H stretching). The<lb/> HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 22 H 17 N 2 O 3<lb/> 357.1234; found: 357.1250.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.12 | 2-(4-ethylbenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ18)<lb/></head>

			<p>Yellow powder, yield 12.52% and m.p 168°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.81 (s, 1H), 8.47 (d, J = 2.0 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 8.17 (dd, J = 8.5, 2.0 Hz, 1H), 8.11-8.06 (m, 2H), 7.55<lb/> (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.43 (d, J = 8.2 Hz, 2H), 2.83-2.61 (m,<lb/> 2H), 1.29-1.10 (m, 3H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 )<lb/> δ 186.5, 159.8, 151.1, 149.7, 146.4, 143.0, 134.3, 131.5,<lb/> 131.0, 130.2, 128.0, 124.5, 94.0, 28.3, 15.1. IR (ATR) V max<lb/> cm -1 : 1648.57 (C=N stretching), 1673.88 (C=O stretch-<lb/>ing), 2871.95 (C-H stretching), and 2961.73 (N-H stretch-<lb/>ing). The HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for<lb/> C 17 H 15 N 2 O 2 , 279.1128; found: 279.1116.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.13 | 2-(4-(benzyloxy)-3-methoxybenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ21)<lb/></head>

			<p>Yellow powder, yield 66.95%, and m.p 102°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.79 (s, 1H), 8.47 (d, J = 2.0 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 8.24-8.07 (m, 1H), 7.91-7.71 (m, 3H), 7.58-7.52 (m,<lb/> 1H), 7.50-7.44 (m, 2H), 7.43-7.38 (m, 2H), 7.37-7.32 (m,<lb/> 1H), 7.25-7.19 (m, 1H), 5.36-5.12 (m, 2H), 3.99-3.76 (m,<lb/> 3H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 185.0, 159.8, 153.3,<lb/> 150.0, 148.8, 146.5, 143.0, 136.2, 134.2, 130.2, 128.5,<lb/> 128.4, 128.1, 127.9, 126.7, 126.7, 126.5, 125.9, 112.5,<lb/> 112.4, 112.2, 70.0, 55.6. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1264.80<lb/> (C-O stretching), 1664.82 (C=O stretching), 2871.01<lb/> (C=N stretching), and 2915.34 (N-H stretching). The<lb/> HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 23 H 19 N 2 O 4<lb/> 387.1339; found: 387.1368.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.14 | 2-(4-ethoxy-3-methoxybenzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ23)<lb/></head>

			<p>Yellow powder, yield 15.03% and m.p 221°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.79 (s, 1H), 8.47 (d, J = 2.0 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 8.17 (dd, J = 8.5, 2.1 Hz, 1H), 7.86-7.68 (m, 3H),<lb/> 7.56 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.14-7.08 (m, 1H), 4.17-4.14 (m,<lb/> 2H), 3.88-3.82 (m, 3H), 1.37 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz,<lb/> DMSO-d 6 ) δ 199.8, 161.4, 153.7, 150.9, 148.5, 143.0,<lb/> 134.2, 131.2, 126.9, 126.1, 125.3, 124.3, 113.8, 112.1,<lb/> 111.5, 64.1, 55.5, 14.4. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1125.56<lb/> (C-O stretching), 1638.90 (C=N stretching), 1675.81<lb/> (C=O stretching), and 2973.05 (N-H stretching). The<lb/> HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 18 H 17 N 2 O 4<lb/> 325.1183; found: 325.1178.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.15 | 2-(2-((4-chlorobenzyl)oxy)benzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ25)<lb/></head>

			<p>Light yellow powder, yield 17.9% and m.p 102°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.75 (s, 1H), 8.26 (d, J = 2.0 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 8.06 (dd, J = 8.5, 2.1 Hz, 1H), 7.82-7.53 (m, 3H), 7.34<lb/> (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.28 (t, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.18 (td, J = 7.5,<lb/> 3.0 Hz, 1H), 6.99-6.93 (m, 4H), 5.01-4.95 (m, 2H). 13 C NMR<lb/> (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 188.2, 159.5, 158.4, 151.9, 146.7,<lb/> 142.7, 135.7, 134.3, 134.1, 132.5, 130.5, 129.5, 129.1, 129.0,<lb/> 127.9, 127.8, 124.5, 121.2, 113.6, 92.9, 69.5, 56.0. IR (ATR)<lb/> V max cm -1 : 576.58 (C-Cl stretching), 1286.37 (C-O stretch-<lb/>ing), 1631.16 (C=N stretching), 1664.80 (C=O stretching),<lb/> and 2969.35 (N-H stretching). The HRMS (APCI) m/z<lb/> [M + H] + calculated for C 22 H 16 ClN 2 O 3 391.0844; found:<lb/> 391.0844.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.16 | 2-(2-((4-bromobenzyl)oxy)benzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ26)<lb/></head>

			<p>Yellow powder, yield 27.96% and m.p 113.9-115.5°C.<lb/> 1 H NMR (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.75 (s, 1H), 8.27 (d,<lb/> J = 1.9 Hz, 1H), 8.09-8.04 (m, 1H), 7.83-7.53 (m, 3H),<lb/> 7.34 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.27 (t, J = 8.8 Hz, 1H), 7.18 (td,<lb/> J = 7.5, 3.2 Hz, 1H), 7.11 (dd, J = 8.1, 6.3 Hz, 2H), 6.90<lb/> (dd, J = 8.0, 6.3 Hz, 2H), 4.95 (s, 2H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz,<lb/> DMSO-d 6 ) δ 188.3, 158.4, 158.1, 142.7, 135.7, 135.3,<lb/> 134.6, 134.3, 130.8, 130.8, 129.4, 129.2, 127.6, 125.9,<lb/> 125.0, 124.5, 121.2, 121.1, 121.1, 120.9, 113.6, 69.6. IR<lb/> (ATR) V max cm -1 : 551.66 (C-Br stretching), 1285.85 (C-O<lb/> stretching), 1662.97 (C=N stretching), 1729.77 (C=O<lb/> stretching), and 2924.56 (N-H stretching). The HRMS<lb/> (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 22 H 16 BrN 2 O 3<lb/> 435.0339; found: 435.0317.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.17 | 2-(3-methoxy-4-((4-nitrobenzyl)<lb/> oxy)benzoyl)quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ31)<lb/></head>

			<p>Yellow powder, yield 33.39%, and m.p 224°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.79 (s, 1H), 8.46 (d, J = 2.0 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 8.27 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 2H), 8.16 (dd, J = 8.5, 2.0 Hz, 1H),<lb/> 7.86-7.71 (m, 5H), 7.56 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.20 (dd, J = 8.5,<lb/> 4.7 Hz, 1H), 5.45-5.32 (m, 2H), 3.93-3.83 (m, 3H). 13 C NMR<lb/> (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 185.0, 159.8, 152.8, 149.9, 148.8,<lb/> 147.1, 146.5, 144.1, 143.0, 134.2, 130.2, 128.3, 128.3, 126.9,<lb/> 126.6, 124.4, 123.6, 123.6, 112.6, 112.4, 93.9, 68.7, 56.0.<lb/> IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1279.480 (C-O stretching), 1587.90<lb/> (N-O stretching), 1648.83 (C=N stretching), 1684.06 (C=O<lb/> stretching), and 2911.25 (N-H stretching). The HRMS<lb/> (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated for C 23 H 18 N 3 O 6 432.1190;<lb/> found: 432.1172.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.18 | 2-(4-((4-bromobenzyl)oxy)-3-<lb/>methoxybenzoyl)quinazolin-4(3h)-one<lb/> (KJ32)<lb/></head>

			<p>Yellow powder, yield 40.97%, and m.p 220°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.79 (s, 1H), 8.47 (d, J = 2.0 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 8.17-8.15 (m, 1H), 7.89-7.72 (m, 2H), 7.63-7.54<lb/> (m, 3H), 7.44-7.41 (m, 3H), 7.19 (dt, J = 8.7, 3.3 Hz, 1H),<lb/> 5.23 (s, 2H), 3.84 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ<lb/> 185.0, 173.0, 159.8, 153.1, 149.9, 148.7, 146.5, 143.0, 135.7,<lb/> 134.7, 134.2, 131.4, 131.3, 130.2, 129.9, 126.7, 124.4, 121.2,<lb/> 112.5, 112.2, 93.8, 69.1, 55.7. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 522.26<lb/> (C-Br stretching), 1271.97 (C-O stretching), 1656.78 (C=N<lb/> stretching), 1670.95 (C=O stretching), and 2937.61 (N-H<lb/> stretching). The HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated<lb/> for C 23 H 18 BrN 2 O 4 465.0444; found: 465.0455.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.19 | 2-(4-(isopentyloxy)-3-<lb/>methoxybenzoyl)quinazolin-4(3h)-ONE<lb/> (KJ33)<lb/></head>

			<p>Light yellow powder, yield 26.53% and m.p 182°C. 1 H<lb/> NMR (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.41 (s, 1H), 8.38 (s, 1H),<lb/> 8.15-8.09 (m, 1H), 7.84-7.79 (m, 3H), 7.49 (d, J = 8.5 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 7.12 (d, J = 8.2 Hz, 1H), 4.18-3.71 (m, 5H), 1.65 (d,<lb/> J = 5.8 Hz, 3H), 0.94 (d, J = 5.1 Hz, 6H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz,<lb/> DMSO-d 6 ) δ 183.3, 162.2, 151.0, 148.6, 146.8, 134.6, 134.5,<lb/> 134.1, 127.2, 126.0, 125.7, 124.5, 121.2, 121.1, 112.3, 110.8,<lb/> 66.7, 55.7, 37.3, 24.5, 22.4. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1136.51<lb/> (C-O stretching), 1460.59 (C-H bending), 1640.01 (C=N<lb/> stretching), 1655.36 (C=O stretching), and 2996.35 (N-H<lb/> stretching). The HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calculated<lb/> for C 21 H 23 N 2 O 4 367.1652; found: 367.1657.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.20 | 2-(2-((4-methylbenzyl)oxy)<lb/> benzoyl)quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ34)<lb/></head>

			<p>Light yellow powder, yield 19.33% and m.p 208.4-209.9°C.<lb/> 1 H NMR (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.72 (s, 1H), 8.24 (d,<lb/> J = 2.0 Hz, 1H), 8.06 (dd, J = 8.5, 2.1 Hz, 1H), 7.75 (dd,<lb/> J = 7.7, 1.7 Hz, 1H), 7.71-7.68 (m, 1H), 7.33 (d, J = 8.5 Hz,<lb/> H), 7.29 (d, J = 8.4 Hz, H), 7.17 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 1H), 6.79 (d,<lb/> J = 7.8 Hz, 2H), 6.72 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 3H), 4.90 (s, 2H), 2.22 (s,<lb/> 3H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 188.3, 158.6, 151.9,<lb/> 146.8, 142.6, 136.9, 135.7, 134.2, 132.0, 130.4, 129.5, 128.5,<lb/> 128.4, 127.4, 127.2, 124.4, 124.1, 121.0, 113.5, 92.6, 70.3,<lb/> 56.0, 20.9. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 : 1286.91 (C-O stretching),<lb/> 1667.22 (C=N stretching), 1731.71 (C=O stretching), and<lb/> 2932.93 (N-H stretching). The HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] +<lb/> calculated for C 23 H 19 N 2 O 3 371.1390; found: 371.1363.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.21 | 2-(2-((4-nitrobenzyl)oxy)benzoyl)<lb/> quinazolin-4(3h)-one (KJ35)<lb/></head>

			<p>Yellow powder, yield 81.41% and m.p 228°C. 1 H NMR<lb/> (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.79 (s, 1H), 8.14 (d, J = 2.0 Hz,<lb/> 1H), 7.94 (dd, J = 7.9, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.82-7.74 (m, 3H), 7.71<lb/> (td, J = 9.3, 1.8 Hz, 1H), 7.59 (d, J = 7.9 Hz, 1H), 7.50-7.45 (m,<lb/> 1H), 7.36-7.18 (m, 4H), 5.14 (s, 1H). 13 C NMR (151 MHz,<lb/> DMSO-d 6 ) δ 188.5, 158.2, 157.9, 146.6, 142.8, 135.7, 135.4,<lb/> 134.4, 134.0, 130.6, 130.6, 129.6, 128.2, 128.1, 125.6, 123.0,<lb/> 122.9, 121.5, 121.4, 113.7, 92.9, 69.2. IR (ATR) V max cm -1 :<lb/> 1274.58 (C-O stretching), 1515.26 (N-O stretching), 1682.42<lb/> (C=N stretching), 1701.11 (C=O stretching), and 2913.01<lb/> (N-H stretching). The HRMS (APCI) m/z [M + H] + calcu-<lb/>lated for C 22 H 16 N 3 O 5 402.1082; found: 402.1082.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.22 | In vitro anti-parasitic assay<lb/></head>

			<p>Anti-parasitic assays were performed as described else-<lb/>where <ref type="biblio">(Bouton et al., 2021; Hulpia et al., 2019)</ref>. Briefly, to<lb/> evaluate anti-Leishmania activity, L. infantum [MHOM/<lb/> MA (BE)/67] was used with primary peritoneal mouse<lb/> macrophages as host cells. 3 × 10 4 macrophages were<lb/> infected with 4.5 × 10 5 parasites per well. Compound di-<lb/>lutions were added after 2 h of infection. After 5 days of in-<lb/>cubation, parasite burdens (mean number of amastigotes/<lb/> macrophage) were assessed microscopically after staining<lb/> with a 10% Giemsa solution. For T. cruzi, the Tulahuen<lb/> CL2, β-galactosidase strain (nifurtimox-sensitive) was<lb/> used and maintained on MRC-5SV2 (human lung fibro-<lb/>blast) 4 × 10 3 cells were infected with 4 × 10 4 parasites per<lb/> well. Parasite burdens were assessed after adding the sub-<lb/>strate CPRG (chlorophenol red β-d-galactopyranoside).<lb/> The change in color was measured spectrophotometrically<lb/> at 540 nm after 4 h incubation at 37°C. Drug susceptibility<lb/> tests for T. brucei were performed using a resazurin assay.<lb/> Susceptibility assays were performed with T. brucei Squib<lb/> 42749 or T. b. rhodesiense STIB-90050. T. brucei Squib 427<lb/> was seeded at 1.5 × 10 4 parasites/well and T. b. rhodesiense<lb/> at 4 × 10 3 parasites per well, followed by the addition of<lb/> resazurin after 24 h (T. brucei) or 6 h (T. b. rhodesiense).<lb/> After the addition of resazurin, plates were incubated for<lb/> another 24 h followed by fluorescence detection.<lb/></p>

			<p>In all assays, parasite growth was compared to untreated-<lb/>infected controls (100% growth) and noninfected controls<lb/> (0% growth). Results were expressed as % parasite reduc-<lb/>tion at the different drug concentrations and used to calcu-<lb/>late IC 50 values from the dose-response curves.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.23 | In vitro cytotoxicity assay<lb/></head>

			<p>MRC-5SV2 cell cytotoxicity was evaluated as described<lb/> elsewhere <ref type="biblio">(Bouton et al., 2021)</ref>. Briefly, 1.5 × 105 cells/<lb/> mL cells were cultured with compound dilutions at<lb/> 37°C and with 5% CO 2 . Cell growth was compared to<lb/> untreated-control wells (100% cell growth) and medium-<lb/>control wells (0% cell growth). After 3 days of incuba-<lb/>tion, cell viability was assessed fluorimetrically after the<lb/> addition of 50 μL resazurin per well. After 4 h at 37°C,<lb/> fluorescence was measured (λ ex 550 nm, λ em 590 nm). The<lb/> results were expressed as a % reduction in cell growth/<lb/> viability compared to control wells and an IC 50 value was<lb/> determined.<lb/></p>

			<head>4 | CONCLUSION<lb/></head>

			<p>Nineteen 2-aroylquinazolin-4(3H)-ones derivatives were<lb/> synthesized, characterized, and evaluated in vitro for anti-<lb/>parasitic activities. Two compounds KJ1 and KJ10 are the<lb/> most intriguing anti-parasitic hits, exhibiting low micro-<lb/>molar activity against T. b. rhodesiense, and T. b. brucei.<lb/> These compounds showed no inhibitory effect on human<lb/> cells (MRC-5), with compound KJ10 having a T. b. rho-<lb/>desiense selectivity index of &gt;55. Compounds in this study<lb/> possess a low molecular weight and are easy to synthesize.<lb/> This allows for further analogues, and/or derivatives with<lb/> drug-like properties to be explored in search of more po-<lb/>tent anti-parasitic compounds.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
