<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>1. INTRODUCTION<lb/></head>

			<p>Glucagon-like peptide-1 Receptor (GLP1R) agonists<lb/> have become extensive anti-obesity/diabetes medications in<lb/> the United States. This study aimed to investigate the poten-<lb/>tial mechanisms associated with Ozempic (Semaglutide),<lb/> which is generalized as one of the anti-addiction compounds.<lb/> The impacts of GLP1R agonists on substance use disorder<lb/> (SUD) and alcohol use disorder (AUD) are partially mediat-<lb/>ed by dopamine signaling downregulation. We hypothesize<lb/> that, whereas GLP1R agonism may be beneficial for treating<lb/> hyperdopaminergia, it may be detrimental for treating hypo-<lb/>dopaminergia, perhaps resulting in the long-term induction<lb/> of suicidal ideation (SI). Thus, by examining prior reports and<lb/> our analyses, we will investigate the aforementioned idea.<lb/></p>

			<p>Globally, it is estimated that while 1 in 8 people globally<lb/> are considered obese, close to 300 million individuals suffer<lb/> from AUD, including approximately 150 million individuals<lb/> with alcohol dependence <ref type="biblio">[1, 2]</ref>. Most compelling is that the<lb/> World Health Organization (WHO) estimated that the harm-<lb/>ful qualities of alcohol use and abuse account for approxi-<lb/>mately 5% of premature fatalities. As such, the WHO notes<lb/> that alcohol use and abuse is a leading cause of preventable<lb/> fatalities worldwide. It is considered to be linked to consum-<lb/>ers of alcohol having a lower rate of treatment than other<lb/> psychiatric disorders <ref type="biblio">[3]</ref>. It is also true that AUD is linked to<lb/> a high premature mortality rate, which has been associated<lb/> with dopamine dysregulation, including the DRD2 A1 allele,<lb/> which is over-represented in alcohol-dependent individuals<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[4]</ref>. In one study, this allele has also been associated with a<lb/> highly increased mortality rate in alcohol-dependent individ-<lb/>uals <ref type="biblio">[4]</ref>. Along similar lines, it has been estimated by the<lb/> United Nations 2023 World Drug Report that globally, over<lb/> 354 million humans will use illicit drugs in 2021 <ref type="biblio">[5]</ref>. Out of<lb/> the 354 million, 218 million were attributed to cannabis, 60<lb/> million to opioids, 21 million to cocaine, 20 million to ecsta-<lb/>sy, and 35 million to amphetamine <ref type="biblio">[5]</ref>. These statistics are<lb/> morphed by the unfortunate fact that the prevalence of to-<lb/>bacco use is over 1 billion. Tobacco use is one of the highest<lb/> preventable causes of premature death, while eight million<lb/> humans die due to tobacco-related diseases annually <ref type="biblio">[6-8]</ref>.<lb/> While there are FDA pharmaceuticals approved for alcohol.<lb/> Opioid, and tobacco misuse, albeit these treatments are not<lb/> without adverse effects and even addiction liability (e.g.,<lb/> methadone). There is currently no treatment for cannabis or<lb/> psychostimulant disorders. The search for safe and effective<lb/> modalities to treat all Reward Deficiency Syndrome (RDS)<lb/> behaviors continues to be actively explored. Research has<lb/> shown that people suffering from substance and non-<lb/>substance behavioral addictions (i.e., obesity/food addiction)<lb/> have overlapping brain dysregulation and share genetic and<lb/> epigenetic mechanisms, particularly hypodopaminergia <ref type="biblio">[9,<lb/> 10]</ref>. Therefore, hypodopaminergia could exist in an astonish-<lb/>ing number of people not only in the USA but also globally.<lb/> While Howes &amp; Kapur <ref type="biblio">[10]</ref> correctly point out that dopa-<lb/>mine is currently the only known finite reward molecule, its<lb/> regulation, and neuronal release are a function of many risk<lb/> factors beyond DNA antecedents that are linked to reward<lb/> deficiency <ref type="biblio">[9]</ref>. These include but are not limited to stress,<lb/> trauma, obstetric complications, drug use, genetic and epige-<lb/>netic insults that reduce presynaptic striatal dopaminergic<lb/> function. Our proposal is to balance brain neurotransmitters<lb/> by using positive modulation targeted at both upstream and<lb/> downstream pathways in order to overcome substance and<lb/> non-substance behavioral addictions. Thus providing normal<lb/> or close to normal dopamine release at the various brain re-<lb/>gions, especially the Ventral Tegmental Area (VTA) and<lb/> Nucleus Accumbens (NAc). In terms of the Brain Reward<lb/> Cascade (BRC) that was first published in 1989, it is note-<lb/>worthy to add glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1) receptors to<lb/> the model. One advantage of the GLP-1 receptor agonists in<lb/> relation to obesity is that they play a significant role in in-<lb/>ducing insulin secretion after meals and aid in weight loss by<lb/> encouraging satiety and delaying stomach emptying <ref type="biblio">[11-13]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>In addition, research has shown that GLP-1 receptor agonists<lb/> are very effective at reducing A1c and cardiovascular disease<lb/> in patients with existing Atherosclerotic Cardiovascular Dis-<lb/>ease (ASCVD) <ref type="biblio">[14-21]</ref>. Research has also shown that GLP-1<lb/> receptor agonists have an overall decrease in mortality in<lb/> individuals with cardiovascular disease and type 2 diabetes<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[22, 23]</ref>. Furthermore, many have begun to take a keen inter-<lb/>est in the role of GLP-1 receptors and dopaminergic regula-<lb/>tion in the mesolimbic system of the human brain <ref type="biblio">[24, 25]<lb/></ref> and the potential role of GLP-1 in the attenuation of, for ex-<lb/>ample, alcohol intake from both human genetic association<lb/> studies and mouse models of alcohol dependence. However,<lb/> while there are some reports about the various agonists<lb/> of GLP-1 with some positive effects in curtailing food intake<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[12]</ref> and even AUD <ref type="biblio">[26, 27]</ref>, the agonistic effects of GLP-1<lb/> </p>
				
			<figure> Fig. (1). The mesolimbic brain reward cascade. This figure illustrates the interaction of some well-known brain reward cascade (BRC) neuro-<lb/>transmitter pathways. Environmental stimulation initiates the release of serotonin (5-HT) in the hypothalamus, which in turn, for example, via<lb/> 5 HT-2 A receptors activates (green equal sign) the subsequent release of opioid peptides from opioid peptide neurons. Then, in the Substan-<lb/>tia Nigra (SN), the opioid peptides bind to two distinct opioid receptors with different mechanism of action. One is through the mu-opioid<lb/> receptor that inhibits (red hash sign) GABA-ergic neurons (possibly via an opioid peptide like enkephalins). The second stimulates canna-<lb/>binoid neurons (for example, the Anandamide and 2-arachidonoylglycerol) (green equal sign) through beta-endorphin-linked delta receptors,<lb/> which inhibit GABAA neurons. When activated, cannabinoids, primarily the 2-arachidonoylglycerol neurons, can disinhibit (green hash sign)<lb/> GABA-ergic neurons indirectly by CB1 receptor activation. Glutamatergic neurons in the Dorsal Raphe Nuclei (DRN) disinhibit GABA neu-<lb/>rons in the SN indirectly through GLU M3 receptor activation (green hash sign). When disinhibited, GABAA neurons will powerfully inhibit<lb/> (red hash signs) VTA glutaminergic drive via GABAB 3 receptors. At the Nucleus Accumbens (NAc), Acetylcholine (ACH) neurons may<lb/> inhibit (red hash sign) muscarinic and stimulate Nicotinic (green hash) receptors. Glutamate neurons in the VTA will project to dopamine<lb/> neurons through NMDA receptors (green equal sign) to release dopamine at the NAc. (with permission from Blum et al.). (A higher resolu-<lb/>tion/colour version of this figure is available in the electronic copy of the article).<lb/> </figure>
				
			<p>are very complex (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>). Interestingly, Glucagon-like pep-<lb/>tide 1 (GLP-1) regulates food intake, insulin production, and<lb/> metabolism. Fortunately, a recent study demonstrated that<lb/> pancreatic α-cells-secreted (intraislet) GLP-1 effectively<lb/> promotes maternal insulin secretion and metabolic adapta-<lb/>tion during pregnancy. Specifically, Qiao et al. <ref type="biblio">[28, 29]<lb/></ref> showed a progressive reduction in maternal blood GLP-1<lb/> concentration. GLP-1 receptor agonist injection in late preg-<lb/>nancy significantly reduced fetal body weight, even after<lb/> restoration of maternal blood glucose concentration. GLP-1<lb/> receptor activation significantly reduced the placental laby-<lb/>rinth area, expression of some nutrient transporters, and ca-<lb/>pillary development. Qiao et al. suggested that reducing ma-<lb/>ternal blood GLP-1 levels is a physiological adaptation pro-<lb/>cess that benefits placental development and fetal growth <ref type="biblio">[28]</ref>.<lb/> </p>
				
			<p>Impairment of glucoregulatory function, which is conse-<lb/>quential to the addiction neuropathology, can worsen Sub-<lb/>stance Use Disorder (SUD) and polydrug abuse. Therefore, it<lb/> is reasonable to expect amelioration of addictive behaviors/<lb/> symptoms through the improvement of metabolic function<lb/> (i.e., using GLP-1 receptor agonists). Research has demon-<lb/>strated that the effects of GLP-1 in alcohol use disorder and<lb/> SUD are mediated partly through the downregulation of do-<lb/>pamine signaling and even enhanced catabolism in both the<lb/> synapse and mitochondria due to GLP1 agonistic increase in<lb/> the gene expression such as Catechol-O-methyltransferase<lb/> (COMT) and Monoamine Oxidase A (MAOA) <ref type="biblio">[30, 31]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>While this may have some important relevance in the short<lb/> term, where hyperdopaminergia exists, it is important to cau-<lb/>tion against promoting chronic stimulation via a GLP-1 ago-<lb/>nist. Recent findings have shown a link between GLP-1 re-<lb/>ceptor agonists and several genes within the dopaminergic<lb/> pathway. Therefore, stimulation of GLP-1 receptor agonists,<lb/> especially chronically, can lead to the dysregulation of the<lb/> dopaminergic pathway, which in turn can cause depression,<lb/> suicidality, and other mood disturbances <ref type="biblio">[9, 16, 32-40]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>In sum, while employing GLP-1 agonism may offer ther-<lb/>apeutic benefits in instances of recognized hyperdopaminer-<lb/>gia, it could be determinantal in patients with hypodopamin-<lb/>ergia. Most recently, Klausen et al. <ref type="biblio">[9, 41]</ref> suggested that<lb/> the therapeutic effects of GLP1R agonists on AUD and SUD<lb/> seem to be mediated partly through the downregulation of<lb/> dopaminergic signaling <ref type="biblio">[41]</ref>. While this may have some im-<lb/>portant relevance in the short term, we would like to point<lb/> out a cautionary pitfall in promoting chronic stimulation via<lb/> a GLP1R agonist, like Exenatide, as an anti-craving agent.<lb/></p>

			<p>It behooves the scientific community to understand the<lb/> complexity of GLP1R&apos;s physiology and molecular neurobio-<lb/>logical actions. Importantly, the scientific and clinical com-<lb/>munity are actively exploring both the neurogenetic and epi-<lb/>genetic mechanisms related to, for example, &apos;pre-addiction&quot;<lb/> polymorphic profiles. Understanding the potential of people<lb/> born with DNA-linked GARS genes and, hence, hypodopa-<lb/>minergia is crucial. Having this DNA data may provide im-<lb/>portant genetic information related to both those who require<lb/> and benefit from GLP1R agonistic therapy. It is our hypothe-<lb/>sis that in patients with genotypes displaying low dopamine<lb/> function via reward gene polymorphisms assessed with<lb/> GARS, the long-term administration of GLP1 agonists<lb/> should be cautioned. This notion is based on reported exper-<lb/>iments indicating GLP1 agonists induce dopamine dysregu-<lb/>lation (PUBMED 69 articles listed using word term GLP1<lb/> agonists and dopamine) <ref type="biblio">[42]</ref> that requires possibly modified<lb/> dosage to prevent any further downregulation of dopamine<lb/> release at the nucleus accumbens (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>Accordingly, Klausen et al. <ref type="biblio">[34]</ref> showed that exenatide<lb/> significantly attenuated fMRI alcohol cue reactivity in the<lb/> ventral striatum and septal area, which are critical brain re-<lb/>gions for drug reward and addiction, even though it did not<lb/> significantly reduce the number of heavy drinking days when<lb/> compared with placebo in AUD patients who underwent<lb/> functional MRI (fMRI) and single-photon emission CT<lb/> (SPECT) brain scans. This work further suggested the induc-<lb/>tion of a blunted reward system following the action of<lb/> GLP1agonists. Numerous studies have unfortunately shown<lb/> that blunted brain reward circuitry in the mesolimbic system<lb/> increases a person&apos;s susceptibility to addiction <ref type="biblio">[35-41]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Along these lines, it is indeed noteworthy that in at least<lb/> 1,580 articles listed in PUBMED using the term &quot;Reward<lb/> Deficiency&quot; (by the date: 28 June 2024), the primary culprit is<lb/> a reduced dopaminergic function (hyperdopaminergic), that<lb/> leads to aberrant craving behavior for both substance and non-<lb/>substance behavioral addictions. Studies have shown that the<lb/> exenatide (exendin-4) that passes the blood-brain barrier binds<lb/> to GLP1R expressed on the inhibitory GABAergic medium<lb/> spiny neurons in the NAc shell <ref type="biblio">[11, 43-62]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>It is known that GLP-1 analogs act to attenuate food in-<lb/>take and body weight, including various hypothalamic nuclei<lb/> (arcuate nucleus of the hypothalamus, periventricular hypo-<lb/>thalamus, lateral hypothalamic area), hindbrain nuclei (para-<lb/>brachial nucleus, medial nucleus tractus solitarius), hippo-<lb/>campus (ventral subregion; vHP), and nuclei embedded<lb/> within the mesolimbic reward circuitry (VTA and NAc) <ref type="biblio">[63]</ref>.<lb/> Accordingly, Volkow et al. pointed out that disinhibition/<lb/> stimulation of dopaminergic VTA neurons plays a role in the<lb/> reinforcing effects of alcohol, nicotine, and opioid <ref type="biblio">[12]</ref>. In<lb/> fact, it has been observed that GLP1Rs are localized on mouse<lb/> cortical and hippocampal synaptic boutons, specifically on<lb/> glutamatergic and GABAergic nerve terminals. Activation by<lb/> exendin-4 increased the release of either [ 3 H]d-aspartate or<lb/> [ 3 H]GABA <ref type="biblio">[14]</ref>. It is well-known that in the mesolimbic sys-<lb/>tem, enhancing GABAergic function and neuro-activation<lb/> significantly reduces NAc dopamine release <ref type="biblio">[15]</ref>.<lb/> </p>
				
			<p>Specifically, it was reported that both diazepam and mus-<lb/>cimol attenuate dopamine release and that decreases in do-<lb/>pamine release following GABA A receptor activation is in-<lb/>hibited by co-application of a GABA B receptor antagonist.<lb/> These findings support the notion that activation of GABA A<lb/> receptors in the NAc reduces dopamine release by disinhibi-<lb/>tion of local GABA signaling and subsequent activation of<lb/> GABA B receptors <ref type="biblio">[64]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Research has shown that GLP1R agonists can affect<lb/> binge-like alcohol drinking. Chuong et al. reported that<lb/> semaglutide dose-dependently reduced binge-like alcohol<lb/> drinking in mice <ref type="biblio">[16]</ref>. A similar effect was also observed on<lb/> the intake of other caloric/noncaloric solutions. Semaglutide<lb/> also reduced binge-like and dependence-induced alcohol<lb/> drinking in rats. Additionally, semaglutide increased sIPSC<lb/> frequency in CeA and ILC neurons from alcohol-naive rats,<lb/> suggesting enhanced GABA release. The authors concluded<lb/> that the GLP1R analogue semaglutide decreased alcohol<lb/> intake across different drinking models and species and<lb/> modulated central GABA neurotransmission, which would<lb/> reduce dopaminergic signaling and could then lead to &quot;psy-<lb/>chological extinction&quot; <ref type="biblio">[16]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Finally, as of July 2023, the European Medicines Agency<lb/> (EMA) has begun a genetic analysis through reviewing data<lb/> regarding the risk of suicidal thoughts and thoughts of self-<lb/>harm associated with GLP1R agonists, including Ozempic<lb/> (semaglutide), Saxenda (liraglutide), and Wegovy (semag-<lb/>lutide) <ref type="biblio">[65]</ref>. The Icelandic Medicines Agency prompted this<lb/> genetic analysis in response to reports of suicidal thoughts<lb/> and self-harm among patients taking liraglutide and semag-<lb/>lutide medications. Authorities are currently reviewing ap-<lb/>proximately 150 reports of potential suicide attempts and<lb/> self-harm incidents. Furthermore, from 2010-2023 the FDA<lb/> has received 265 reports of suicidal thoughts in patients tak-<lb/>ing GLP1R agonists, particularly tirzepatide, liraglutide, and<lb/> semaglutide, prompting a review of these medications <ref type="biblio">[66]</ref>.<lb/> Additionally, a recent retrospective pharmacovigilance study<lb/> of the European Pharmacovigilance database was conducted<lb/> for the period from 1 January 2018 to 10 July 2023 <ref type="biblio">[67]</ref>.<lb/> Disproportionality analyses (reporting odds ratio, ROR) were<lb/> performed to assess the reporting probability of suicidal<lb/> events among GLP-1 RAs. A total of 230 reports of suicidal<lb/> events were identified. The most reported GLP-1 RA was<lb/> liraglutide (38.3%), followed by semaglutide (36.5%) and<lb/> dulaglutide (16.1%). The most reported events were suicidal<lb/> ideation (65.3%) and suicide attempt (19.5%). Dispropor-<lb/>tionality analysis found a higher reporting probability of<lb/> suicidal events for semaglutide than dulaglutide (ROR, 2.05;<lb/> 95% CI, 1.40-3.01) and exenatide (ROR, 1.81; 95% CI,<lb/> 1.08-3.05). Suicidal events were mostly reported with<lb/> semaglutide and liraglutide, which were also associated with<lb/> significantly higher reporting probabilities compared to other<lb/> GLP1 RAs. In another study <ref type="biblio">[68]</ref>, during the study period,<lb/> 31,444 adverse event reports were identified: semaglutide<lb/> (n = 13,956; 44.4%), liraglutide (n = 16,748; 53.2%), and<lb/> tirzepatide (n = 740; 2.3%). There were 372 reports with<lb/> psychiatric adverse event reports (n = 372; 1.18%) with<lb/> a total of 481 adverse events. Women accounted for 65%<lb/> (n = 242) of these reports. Depression was the most commonly<lb/> reported adverse event (n = 187; 50.3%), followed by anxie-<lb/>ty (n = 144; 38.7%) and suicidal ideation (n = 73; 19.6%).<lb/> Nine deaths (8 with liraglutide and 1 with semaglutide) and<lb/> 11 life-threatening outcomes (4 associated with liraglutide<lb/> and 7 with semaglutide) were reported. The fatal outcomes<lb/> occurred primarily among men (8 out of 9), resulting from<lb/> completed suicidal attempts and depression. Furthermore,<lb/> various pharmacovigilance analyses and notifications from<lb/> different regulatory agencies have documented the occur-<lb/>rence of suicidal thoughts and self-injurious behavior associ-<lb/>ated with the use of GLP-1 receptor agonists <ref type="biblio">[69]</ref>. Maideen<lb/> and Rashid proposed that healthcare professionals should be<lb/> aware of GLP-1 receptor agonists related to suicidal thoughts<lb/> and self-injurious behavior. Patients should not misuse/abuse<lb/> antidiabetic GLP-1 receptor agonists and should consult their<lb/> physician before using any GLP-1 receptor agonists for<lb/> weight loss <ref type="biblio">[69-76]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>In contrast, others could not find an association between<lb/> GLP1 agonists and SI or suicide attempts <ref type="biblio">[77-80]</ref>. Indeed,<lb/> this is not surprising in terms of our cautionary note concern-<lb/>ing attenuation rather than chronic promotion of enhanced<lb/> dopamine signaling, potentially leading to hypodopaminer-<lb/>gia and potential SI. However, while there is reason for con-<lb/>cern establishing causality requires further investigation,<lb/> which will probably be addressed by the Pharmacovigilance<lb/> Risk Assessment Committee of the European Medicine<lb/> Agency and the FDA in the future, we performed in silico<lb/> pharmacogenomic assessment of GLP1 agonists and GARS<lb/> related pathways to potentially uncover glp1 agonistic in-<lb/>duced suicidality.<lb/></p>

			<head>2. METHODS<lb/></head>

			<p>The current paper employed a filtering strategy by in-<lb/>cluding candidate genes from various sources, including<lb/> DrugBank<lb/> (https://go.drugbank.com/),<lb/> GeneCards<lb/> (https://www.genecards.org/), and our well-described Genetic<lb/> Addiction Risk Score (GARS) test. The rationale behind<lb/> these sources involved the basic interaction of a medication as<lb/> a ligand (e.g., Ozempic) and potential targets (e.g., receptors);<lb/> accordingly. The initial idea of preparing the primary gene list<lb/> was to consider all of the Ligand/Receptor molecular com-<lb/>pounds based on the curated databases and reliable sources.<lb/> DrugBank is a well-known database in pharmacological sci-<lb/>ences that focuses on FDA-approved compounds. This data-<lb/>base has a Ligand/Receptor nature of data availability.<lb/></p>

			<p>GeneCards is a strong, validated, widespread database<lb/> with a genetic focus. Utilizing this databank, we obtained<lb/> highly associated genes with related phenotypes, such as<lb/> Suicide Ideation (SI), based on the relevance score. The the-<lb/>ory behind the relevance score is as follows: Lucene (and<lb/> thus Elasticsearch) employs the Boolean model to identify<lb/> matching documents and a formula called the&quot; practical<lb/> scoring function&quot; to estimate the relevance. This formula<lb/> uses concepts from the term&quot; frequency/inverse document<lb/> frequency and the vector space model. &quot;Still, it adds more<lb/> modern characteristics such as a coordination factor, field<lb/> length normalization, and term or query clause boosting.<lb/></p>

			<p>Finally, the GARS gene panel, directly derived from these<lb/> measurable genes and associated risk polymorphisms, is<lb/> known to help identify many psychological/addictive manifes-<lb/>tations. Moreover, since its inception in 2014, the GARS 10<lb/> gene panel has been shown to predict issues regarding the<lb/> genetic basis of dopamine homeostasis, Substance Use Disor-<lb/>der (SUD), Alcohol Use Disorder (AUD), addiction, and spe-<lb/>cifically, major depression which has been previously docu-<lb/>mented abundant publications (e.g., GWAS) (Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>). An<lb/> initial list containing 35 genes was found:. After duplication<lb/> filtering, 31 genes remained, and by STRING-MODEL<lb/> (https://string-db.org/) refined to <ref type="biblio">29</ref> connected genes. By<lb/> NetworkAnalyst<lb/> (https://www.networkanalyst.ca/Network<lb/> Analyst/), Gene-Regulatory Networks (GRNs) carried out in<lb/> Gene-microRNA (miRNA) Interactions (GMIs) based on<lb/> miRTarBase v.8.0. and TF-miRNA coregulatory based on<lb/> RegNetwork repository as sub-analyses. Deep in sili-<lb/>co/enrichment analyses (https://maayanlab.cloud/Enrichr/)<lb/> were performed in three layers: Pathway analysis, Gene On-<lb/>tology (GO), and Disease/Drug analysis. Pathway analysis<lb/> utilized Reactome (https://reactome.org/), Kyoto Encyclopedia<lb/> of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) (https://www.genome.jp/<lb/> kegg/), and Panther (https://www.pantherdb.org/) databases.<lb/> GO used GO Biological Process, GO Cellular Component,<lb/> and GO Molecular Function; Disease/Drug Analysis em-<lb/>ployed<lb/> DisGENET<lb/> (https://www.disgenet.org/home/),<lb/> GeDiPNet 2023 (http://gedipnet.bicnirrh.res.in/), and Jensen<lb/> DISEASE (https://diseases.jensenlab.org/Search) databases<lb/> (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>Along with Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, we visualized a flowchart represent-<lb/>ing the process of analysis strategy (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). Accordingly, the<lb/> main point in this flowchart is the input data, then refining<lb/> this data by multi-filtration steps, including removing the<lb/> duplicated items and pseudogenes, and reaching multiple<lb/> outputs which are based on the evinced-based clues of<lb/> STRING-MODEL and need future functional validations. Of<lb/> note, further investigations were performed based on the<lb/> connected gene list from PPI, utilizing these refined data<lb/> from the beginning to the end of the analysis.<lb/></p>

			<head>3. RESULTS<lb/> </head>
				
			<head>3.1. Filtration Strategy and Primary Gene List<lb/></head>

			<p>For the filtration process, we employed DrugBank,<lb/> Ozempic (Semaglutide), GLP1R agonist, with four Enzymes<lb/> (DPP4, MME, LPL, and AMY1A) related to GLP1 metabo-<lb/>lism and one carrier in blood plasma albumen (ALB). Based<lb/> on GeneCards score for Suicidal Ideation, the 20 highly<lb/> scored genes were extracted and compared with 10 GARS<lb/> genes (DRD1, DRD2, DRD3, DRD4, MAOA, COMT,<lb/> DAT1 (SLC6A3), SLC6A4, OPRM1, and GABRA3). Re-<lb/>markably, 4 genes of the GARS panel were common in the<lb/> first 20 candidate genes for Suicide Ideation (SI). By com-<lb/>bining the Ozempic target (GLP1R), related enzymes, and<lb/> carrier genes to the 20 best-scored genes and 10 GARS<lb/> genes, 31 genes remained for further analyses.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.2. Primary In silico Analyses<lb/> </head>
				
			<head>3.2.1. Protein-Protein Interactions (PPIs)<lb/></head>

			<p>STRING-MODEL indicated a connected network of 29<lb/> genes out of 31 primary selected genes (PPI enrichment<lb/> p-value &lt; 1.0e-16). Thus, two unlinked proteins (AMY1A<lb/> and XK) were eliminated. The connected genes are as<lb/> follows: GLP1R, SLC6A4, HTR2A, BDNF-AS, TPH2,<lb/> LOC110806262 (SLC6A4 promoter), BDNF, TPH1, COMT,<lb/> FKBP5, HTR1A, NR3C1, HTR1B, CRH, NTRK2, HTR2C,<lb/> DRD2, IL6, MAOA, CREB1, DRD1, DRD3, DRD4, SLC6A3,<lb/> OPRM1, GABRA3, DPP4, MME and LPL. STRING-<lb/>MODEL shows that GLP1R exhibits strong interactions with<lb/> DRD3, BDNF, CREB1, CRH, IL6, and DPP4 genes (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<head>3.2.2. Gene-regulatory Networks (GRNs)<lb/></head>

			<p>Employing NetworkAnalyst (https://www.networkanalyst.<lb/> ca/NetworkAnalyst/), GRNs performed in Gene-miRNA In-<lb/>teractions (GMIs) and TF-miRNA revealed coregulation.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 1. Contents, validations, and references of databases and systems biology approaches applied in this paper.<lb/> Level<lb/> Database<lb/> Site<lb/> Software (Version)<lb/> References<lb/> PPIs<lb/> String-Model<lb/> https://string-db.org/<lb/> STRING (12.0)<lb/> [17]<lb/> GRNs<lb/> GMIs (miRTarBase)<lb/> https://mirtarbase.cuhk.edu.cn<lb/> /~miRTarBase/miRTarBase_2022/php/index.php<lb/> NetworkAnalyst (3.0)<lb/> [18]<lb/> TF-coregulatory Interactions<lb/> http://www.regnetworkweb.org/<lb/> NetworkAnalyst (3.0)<lb/> [19]<lb/> EA<lb/> Pathway Analysis<lb/> https://maayanlab.cloud/Enrichr/<lb/> Enrichr<lb/> [20]<lb/> GO<lb/> https://maayanlab.cloud/Enrichr/<lb/> Enrichr<lb/> [21]<lb/> DDA<lb/> https://maayanlab.cloud/Enrichr/<lb/> Enrichr<lb/> [22]<lb/> Abbreviations: PPIs: Protein-Protein Interactions; GRNs: Gene Regulatory Networks; GMIs: Gene-miRNA Interactions; EA: Enrichment Analysis; GO: Gene Ontology; and DDA:<lb/> Diseases Drugs Assessment.<lb/></figure>

			<figure>Fig. (2). Flowchart of method strategy in a summarized status. Abbreviations: GARS: Genetic Addiction Risk Severity; PPI: Protein-Protein<lb/> Interaction; GNR: Gene Regulatory Networks; and EA: Enrichment Analysis. (A higher resolution/colour version of this figure is available in<lb/> the electronic copy of the article).<lb/></figure>

			<p>We also validated GMIs data obtained from miRTarBase<lb/> v.8.0. In a Force Atlas model, GMIs revealed that the<lb/> CREB1 gene is the most interacted seed (betweenness de-<lb/>gree = 107) and hsa-miR-22-3p has the most interactions<lb/> (betweenness degree = 5) among other miRNAs. Interesting-<lb/>ly, GLP1R interacted with CREB1 by hsa-miR-297 and hsa-<lb/>miR-567. Moreover, hsa-miR-204-5p has links with GLP1R,<lb/> CREB1, BDNF, NTRK2, and NR3C1 (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>For TF-miRNA coregulatory networks, the literature cu-<lb/>rated regulatory interaction information that was collected<lb/> from the RegNetwork repository. In a Linear Bi/Tripartite<lb/> model, the results illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">(5)</ref> show the major im-<lb/>pact of CREB1 (1728 interactions), NR3C1 (612 interac-<lb/>tions), NTRK2 (70 interactions), BDNF (67 interactions),<lb/> IL-6 (59 interactions), and SLC6A4 (47 interactions) as the<lb/> best-scored protein targets. Moreover, SP1 and CTCF, both<lb/> with 9 interactions, and REST, with 8 interactions, are the<lb/> most interacted Transcription Factors (TFs). Additionally,<lb/> the most significant miRNAs in this network are hsa-miR-<lb/>16, hsa-miR-22, and hsa-miR-195, all with 6 interactions.<lb/> Interestingly, SP1 and SP3 are TFs that have relationships<lb/> with GLP1R, and OPRM1 has connections with these two<lb/> TFs.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.3. Deep In silico Identification through Enrichment<lb/> Analysis<lb/></head>

			<p>Enrichment analysis provides deep in silico identifica-<lb/>tion, which was successfully performed on the candidate SI<lb/> gene list suggested in this study. Enrichment analysis was<lb/> categorized into three layers including Pathway Analysis,<lb/> Gene Ontology (GO), and Disease/Drug Analysis. Pathway<lb/> Analysis utilized Reactome, KEGG, and Panther databases.<lb/> GO used GO Biological Process, GO Cellular Component,<lb/> and GO Molecular Function; and Disease/Drug Analysis<lb/> employed DisGENET, GeDiPNet 2023, and JENSEN DIS-<lb/>EASE.<lb/> </p>
				
			<figure>Fig. (3). STRING-MODEL of PPIs for 31 candidate genes relating to Suicidal Ideation with GARS. (A higher resolution/colour version of<lb/> this figure is available in the electronic copy of the article).<lb/></figure>

			<head>3.3.1. Pathway Analysis<lb/></head>

			<p>According to the Reactome 2022, following Amine Lig-<lb/>and-Binding Receptors R-HSA-375280 (p-value = 5.050e-<lb/>16; adjusted p-value = 8.635e-14; OR = 237.37), Dopamine<lb/> Receptors R-HSA-390651 (p-value =1.780e-11; adjusted<lb/> p-value= 1.096e-9; OR = 3195.20) was the most significant<lb/> pathway based on the 29 candidate genes of SI (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).<lb/> Additionally, in KEGG 2021 HUMAN database classifica-<lb/>tion, after Neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction (p-value =<lb/> 4.347e-16; adjusted p-value = 4.869e-14; OR = 48.66)<lb/> and Serotonergic synapse (p-value = 3.139e-12; adjusted<lb/> p-value = 1.758e-10; OR = 72.08), the Dopaminergic syn-<lb/>apse was in third place with a p-value of 1.110e-11, an ad-<lb/>justed p-value of 4.143e-10, and an OR of 60.97; thus, the<lb/> significance of Dopaminergic synapse was not very different<lb/> from the significance of Serotonergic synapses (adjusted<lb/> p-value = 1.758e-10) (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>). Finally, PANTHER listed<lb/> the Dopamine receptor-mediated signaling pathway Homo<lb/> sapiens P05912 as the most significant pathway (p-value =<lb/> 1.040e-10; adjusted p-value = 1.768e-9; and OR = 113) for<lb/> the gene list (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>). Altogether, Pathway Analysis provid-<lb/>ed strong evidence for dopamine signaling in the SI pheno-<lb/>type.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. (4). Force Atlas model of GMIs for 29 candidate genes including GARS genes representing CREB1 and hsa-miR-22-3p as the most in-<lb/>teracting seed and miRNA, respectively. (A higher resolution/colour version of this figure is available in the electronic copy of the article).<lb/></figure>

			<figure type="table">Table 2. Reactome 2022 results for pathway analysis of 21 candidate genes list related to suicide ideation.<lb/> Index<lb/> Name<lb/> P-value<lb/> q-value<lb/> OR<lb/> 1<lb/> Amine Ligand-Binding Receptors R-HSA-375280<lb/> 5.050e-16<lb/> 8.635e-14<lb/> 237.37<lb/> 2<lb/> Dopamine Receptors R-HSA-390651<lb/> 1.780e-11<lb/> 1.096e-9<lb/> 3195.20<lb/> 3<lb/> GPCR Ligand Binding R-HSA-500792<lb/> 1.923e-11<lb/> 1.096e-9<lb/> 26.69<lb/> 4<lb/> Signaling By GPCR R-HSA-372790<lb/> 7.703e-11<lb/> 3.293e-9<lb/> 20.12<lb/> 5<lb/> Class A/1 (Rhodopsin-like Receptors) R-HSA-373076<lb/> 5.619e-10<lb/> 1.922e-8<lb/> 27.81<lb/> 6<lb/> Neurotransmitter Clearance R-HSA-112311<lb/> 7.437e-10<lb/> 2.120e-8<lb/> 532.40<lb/> 7<lb/> Serotonin Receptors R-HSA-390666<lb/> 1.168e-9<lb/> 2.852e-8<lb/> 456.32<lb/> 8<lb/> Signal Transduction R-HSA-162582<lb/> 3.963e-9<lb/> 8.470e-8<lb/> 10.14<lb/> 9<lb/> GPCR Downstream Signaling R-HSA-388396<lb/> 8.833e-9<lb/> 1.678e-7<lb/> 16.73<lb/> 10<lb/> Transcriptional Regulation By MECP2 R-HSA-8986944<lb/> 2.303e-8<lb/> 3.938e-7<lb/> 75.44<lb/> Note: OR refers to Odds ration and q-value is calculated based on adjusted p-value.<lb/></figure>

			<figure>Fig. (5). The Linear Bi/Tripartite model is built on the TF-miRNA coregulatory network of 29 SI candidate genes. According to this figure,<lb/> CREB1, SP1, and miR-16 and -22 are the most important protein targets, TF, and miRNAs, respectively. (A higher resolution/colour version<lb/> of this figure is available in the electronic copy of the article).<lb/></figure>

			<figure type="table">Table 3. KEGG HUMAN 2021 phenotypes resulted from 29 candidate genes.<lb/> Index<lb/> Name<lb/> P-value<lb/> q-value<lb/> OR<lb/> 1<lb/> Neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction<lb/> 4.347e-16<lb/> 4.869e-14<lb/> 48.66<lb/> 2<lb/> Serotonergic synapse<lb/> 3.139e-12<lb/> 1.758e-10<lb/> 72.08<lb/> 3<lb/> Dopaminergic synapse<lb/> 1.110e-11<lb/> 4.143e-10<lb/> 60.97<lb/> 4<lb/> Cocaine addiction<lb/> 7.166e-11<lb/> 2.006e-9<lb/> 120.90<lb/> 5<lb/> Alcoholism<lb/> 1.747e-10<lb/> 3.914e-9<lb/> 42.36<lb/> 6<lb/> cAMP signaling pathway<lb/> 1.983e-8<lb/> 3.702e-7<lb/> 30.09<lb/> 7<lb/> Amphetamine addiction<lb/> 0.000002887<lb/> 0.00004619<lb/> 49.00<lb/> 8<lb/> Gap junction<lb/> 0.000007640<lb/> 0.0001070<lb/> 37.88<lb/> 9<lb/> Tryptophan metabolism<lb/> 0.00003029<lb/> 0.0003769<lb/> 58.97<lb/> 10<lb/> Taste transduction<lb/> 0.0002587<lb/> 0.002897<lb/> 27.65<lb/> Note: OR means Odds Ration and q-value stands for adjusted p-value.<lb/> </figure>
				
			<figure type="table">Table 4. PANTHER pathways for candidate gene list of SI.<lb/> Index<lb/> Name<lb/> P-value<lb/> q-value<lb/> OR<lb/> 1<lb/> Dopamine receptor mediated signaling pathway Homo sapiens P05912<lb/> 1.040e-10<lb/> 1.768e-9<lb/> 113.00<lb/> 2<lb/> Heterotrimeric G-protein signaling pathway-Gi alpha and Gs alpha mediated pathway<lb/> Homo sapiens P00026<lb/> 2.453e-8<lb/> 2.085e-7<lb/> 42.80<lb/> 3<lb/> Adrenaline and noradrenaline biosynthesis Homo sapiens P00001<lb/> 0.000006170<lb/> 0.00003496<lb/> 104.63<lb/> 4<lb/> 5HT1 type receptor mediated signaling pathway Homo sapiens P04373<lb/> 0.000009764<lb/> 0.00004150<lb/> 88.51<lb/> 5<lb/> 5HT2 type receptor mediated signaling pathway Homo sapiens P04374<lb/> 0.00003990<lb/> 0.0001356<lb/> 53.47<lb/> 6<lb/> Enkephalin release Homo sapiens P05913<lb/> 0.0002724<lb/> 0.0007718<lb/> 98.55<lb/> 7<lb/> Heterotrimeric G-protein signaling pathway-Gq alpha and Go alpha mediated path-<lb/>way Homo sapiens P00027<lb/> 0.0004783<lb/> 0.001162<lb/> 22.26<lb/> 8<lb/> Nicotine pharmacodynamics pathway Homo sapiens P06587<lb/> 0.0007496<lb/> 0.001593<lb/> 56.82<lb/> 9<lb/> 5-Hydroxytryptamine degradation Homo sapiens P04372<lb/> 0.007230<lb/> 0.01366<lb/> 178.28<lb/> 10<lb/> 5HT3 type receptor mediated signaling pathway Homo sapiens P04375<lb/> 0.02296<lb/> 0.03548<lb/> 47.51<lb/> Note: q-value is computated based on adjusted p-value and OR refers to Odds Ration.<lb/> </figure>
				
			<figure type="table">Table 5. List of genes associated with suicide ideation (based on GO biological process database, 2023).<lb/> Index<lb/> Name<lb/> P-value<lb/> q-value<lb/> OR<lb/> 1<lb/> Dopamine Metabolic Process (GO:0042417)<lb/> 1.432e-13<lb/> 7.174e-11<lb/> 400.49<lb/> 2<lb/> G Protein-Coupled Receptor (GPCR) Signaling Pathway, (GO:0007187)<lb/> 5.893e-13<lb/> 1.476e-10<lb/> 147.46<lb/> 3<lb/> Catecholamine Metabolic Process (GO:0006584)<lb/> 5.687e-12<lb/> 9.497e-10<lb/> 519.87<lb/> 4<lb/> Adenylate Cyclase-Inhibiting GPCR Signaling Pathway (GO:0007193)<lb/> 1.040e-10<lb/> 1.303e-8<lb/> 113.00<lb/> 5<lb/> GPCR Serotonin Signaling Pathway (GO:0098664)<lb/> 4.467e-10<lb/> 4.476e-8<lb/> 638.91<lb/> 6<lb/> Phospholipase C-mediated Signaling Pathway (GO:0007200)<lb/> 1.870e-9<lb/> 1.562e-7<lb/> 67.40<lb/> 7<lb/> Chemical Synaptic Transmission (GO:0007268)<lb/> 3.642e-9<lb/> 2.607e-7<lb/> 28.33<lb/> 8<lb/> Response To Organonitrogen Compound (GO:0010243)<lb/> 6.552e-9<lb/> 4.103e-7<lb/> 98.85<lb/> 9<lb/> Response to Ethanol (GO:0045471)<lb/> 1.075e-8<lb/> 5.985e-7<lb/> 228.08<lb/> 10<lb/> Behavioral Fear Response (GO:0001662)<lb/> 2.735e-8<lb/> 0.000001246<lb/> 1152.06<lb/> Abbreviations: GO: Gene Ontology; q-value: adjusted p-value; and OR: Odds Ratio.<lb/></figure>

			<head>3.3.2. GO Analyses<lb/></head>

			<p>Deep in silico/enrichment analyses based on GO Biologi-<lb/>cal Process showed Dopaminergic Signaling (GO:0042417,<lb/> p-value of 1.432e-13, adjusted p-value of 7.174e-11, and OR<lb/> of 400.49) as the most associated with the SI phenotype<lb/> (Table <ref type="table">5</ref>). Analysis of GO Cellular Component 2023 indicat-<lb/>ed that Neuron Projection (GO:0043005, p-value of 7.589e-<lb/>15, adjusted p-value of 2.656e-13, and OR of 33.39) is close-<lb/>ly related to the SI phenotype (Table <ref type="table">6</ref>). Moreover, Serotonin<lb/> G Protein-Coupled Receptor Activity (GO:0004993) is the<lb/> top-list of GO Molecular Function 2023 assessment (p-value<lb/> = 8.920e-11; adjusted p-value = 6.779e-9; and OR = 259.83)<lb/> (Table <ref type="table">7</ref>). These findings support the idea that RDS and SI<lb/> may share common mechanisms.<lb/></p>

			<head>3.3.3. Disease Drugs Interaction Analysis (DDA)<lb/></head>

			<p>DDA was conducted by three databases: DisGeNET,<lb/> GeDiPNet 2023, and JENSEN DISEASE, and their results<lb/> are summarized in Table <ref type="table">8</ref>. According to these results, the<lb/> most significant disease phenotype was Major depressive<lb/> disorder defined by Jensen DISEASE (p-value = 4.01E-40;<lb/> adjusted p-value = 6.54e-38; and OR = 630.51) followed by<lb/> Substance abuse (p-value = 2.20E-35; adjusted p-value =<lb/> 1.80e-33; and OR = 681.54) and Alcohol dependence<lb/> (p-value = 4.46E-35; adjusted p-value= 2.42e-33; and OR=<lb/> 382.83). Noteworthy, the best models of DisGeNET and<lb/> GeDiPNet 2023 were Mental depression (p-value = 3.72E-35;<lb/> adjusted p-value = 9.12e-32; and OR = 220.69) and Mood<lb/> disorder (p-value = 1.09E-31; adjusted p-value = 3.69E-29;<lb/> and OR = 163.8), respectively (Table <ref type="table">8</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>To get a better view, Scatter plots, Manhattan plots, and<lb/> Volcano plots for the Jensen DISEASE and DisGeNET are<lb/> illustrated in Figs. <ref type="figure">(6, 7, and 8</ref>). The scatterplot was organized<lb/> so that similar gene sets were clustered together. Larger,<lb/> black-outlined points indicate significantly enriched terms. In<lb/> the Manhattan plot, each line on the x-axis denoted a single<lb/> gene set from the selected library, while the y-axis measured<lb/> the -log 10 (p-value) for each gene set. The volcano plot shows<lb/> the significance of each gene set from the designated library<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 6. Results of GO cellular component 2023 for SI candidate gene list.<lb/> Index<lb/> Name<lb/> P-value<lb/> q-value<lb/> OR<lb/> 1<lb/> Neuron Projection (GO:0043005)<lb/> 7.589e-15<lb/> 2.656e-13<lb/> 33.39<lb/> 2<lb/> Dendrite (GO:0030425)<lb/> 6.176e-14<lb/> 1.081e-12<lb/> 46.51<lb/> 3<lb/> Axon (GO:0030424)<lb/> 4.206e-7<lb/> 0.000004906<lb/> 25.92<lb/> 4<lb/> Non-Motile Cilium (GO:0097730)<lb/> 0.0008611<lb/> 0.007535<lb/> 52.76<lb/> 5<lb/> Ciliary Membrane (GO:0060170)<lb/> 0.001382<lb/> 0.009672<lb/> 41.02<lb/> 6<lb/> Membrane Raft (GO:0045121)<lb/> 0.001843<lb/> 0.01075<lb/> 13.77<lb/> 7<lb/> Flotillin Complex (GO:0016600)<lb/> 0.008670<lb/> 0.04335<lb/> 142.61<lb/> 8<lb/> Cell Projection Membrane (GO:0031253)<lb/> 0.01011<lb/> 0.04421<lb/> 14.29<lb/> 9<lb/> Focal Adhesion (GO:0005925)<lb/> 0.01810<lb/> 0.06685<lb/> 5.89<lb/> 10<lb/> Cell-Substrate Junction (GO:0030055)<lb/> 0.01910<lb/> 0.06685<lb/> 5.76<lb/> Note: GO and OR stand for Gene ontology and Odds Ratio, respectively.<lb/> </figure>
				
			<figure type="table">Table 7. The categorized list of GO Molecular Function 2023 for candidate gene list involving in SI.<lb/> Index<lb/> Name<lb/> P-value<lb/> q-value<lb/> OR<lb/> 1<lb/> GPCR Serotonin Activity (GO:0004993)<lb/> 8.920e-11<lb/> 6.779e-9<lb/> 259.83<lb/> 2<lb/> Serotonin Receptor Activity (GO:0099589)<lb/> 2.869e-10<lb/> 1.084e-8<lb/> 197.92<lb/> 3<lb/> G Protein-Coupled Amine Receptor Activity (GO:0008227)<lb/> 4.278e-10<lb/> 1.084e-8<lb/> 180.69<lb/> 4<lb/> Monoamine Transmembrane Transporter Activity (GO:0008504)<lb/> 0.0001108<lb/> 0.002104<lb/> 164.30<lb/> 5<lb/> Sodium:Chloride Symporter Activity (GO:0015378)<lb/> 0.0001568<lb/> 0.002383<lb/> 134.41<lb/> 6<lb/> Postsynaptic Neurotransmitter Receptor Activity (GO:0098960)<lb/> 0.0003419<lb/> 0.004330<lb/> 86.95<lb/> 7<lb/> GPCR Activity (GO:0004930)<lb/> 0.0004427<lb/> 0.004806<lb/> 12.83<lb/> 8<lb/> Receptor Ligand Activity (GO:0048018)<lb/> 0.001101<lb/> 0.01046<lb/> 9.98<lb/> 9<lb/> Exopeptidase Activity (GO:0008238)<lb/> 0.002574<lb/> 0.02173<lb/> 29.51<lb/> 10<lb/> Growth Factor Activity (GO:0008083)<lb/> 0.006727<lb/> 0.04118<lb/> 17.75<lb/> Abbreviations: GPCR: G-protein Coupled Receptor; GO: Gene Ontology; OR: Odds Ratio.<lb/> </figure>
			
			<figure type="table">Table 8. Candidate genes of SI phenotype (29 genes) extracted from combined results from DisGeNET, GeDiPNET, and JENSEN<lb/> DISEASE databases.<lb/> Index<lb/> Name<lb/> Database<lb/> P-value<lb/> q-value<lb/> OR<lb/> 1<lb/> Major Depressive Disorder<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 4.01E-40<lb/> 6.54E-38<lb/> 630.51<lb/> 2<lb/> Substance Abuse<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 2.20E-35<lb/> 1.80E-33<lb/> 681.54<lb/> 3<lb/> Alcohol Dependence<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 4.46E-35<lb/> 2.42E-33<lb/> 382.83<lb/> 4<lb/> Mental Depression<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 3.72E-35<lb/> 9.12E-32<lb/> 220.69<lb/> 5<lb/> Mental Disorders<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 3.94E-34<lb/> 3.32E-31<lb/> 201.31<lb/> 6<lb/> Major Depressive Disorder<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 4.06E-34<lb/> 3.32E-31<lb/> 191.23<lb/> 7<lb/> Drug Abuse<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 5.88E-33<lb/> 3.61E-30<lb/> 210.12<lb/> 8<lb/> Depressive Disorder<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 2.30E-32<lb/> 1.05E-29<lb/> 168.08<lb/> 9<lb/> Anxiety Disorders<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 2.58E-32<lb/> 1.05E-29<lb/> 164.68<lb/> 10<lb/> Unipolar Depression<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 7.76E-32<lb/> 2.72E-29<lb/> 151.14<lb/> 11<lb/> Mood Disorders<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 1.09E-31<lb/> 3.25E-29<lb/> 163.8<lb/> (Table 8) Contd….<lb/> Index<lb/> Name<lb/> Database<lb/> P-value<lb/> q-value<lb/> OR<lb/> 12<lb/> Alcoholic Intoxication, Chronic<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 1.19E-31<lb/> 3.25E-29<lb/> 152.99<lb/> 13<lb/> Cocaine Dependence<lb/> DisGeNET<lb/> 1.51E-31<lb/> 3.69E-29<lb/> 233.47<lb/> 14<lb/> Mood Disorder<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 1.65E-31<lb/> 6.38E-29<lb/> 176.01<lb/> 15<lb/> Bipolar Disorder<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 7.60E-27<lb/> 1.47E-24<lb/> 89.84<lb/> 16<lb/> Mental Depression<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 4.79E-26<lb/> 6.18E-24<lb/> 83.8<lb/> 17<lb/> Personality Disorder<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 4.82E-20<lb/> 1.97E-18<lb/> 472.55<lb/> 18<lb/> Schizophrenia<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 3.34E-18<lb/> 3.23E-16<lb/> 33.53<lb/> 19<lb/> Obsessive-compulsive Disorder<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 9.18E-17<lb/> 2.99E-15<lb/> 303.94<lb/> 20<lb/> Post-traumatic Stress Disorder<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 3.22E-16<lb/> 8.74E-15<lb/> 253.22<lb/> 21<lb/> Jacksonian Seizure<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 1.37E-14<lb/> 1.06E-12<lb/> 97.23<lb/> 22<lb/> Dementia<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 6.23E-14<lb/> 1.45E-12<lb/> 81.25<lb/> 23<lb/> Clonic Seizures<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 5.33E-14<lb/> 3.44E-12<lb/> 82.76<lb/> 24<lb/> Heroin Dependence<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 2.86E-13<lb/> 5.82E-12<lb/> 347.06<lb/> 25<lb/> Gilles de la Tourette Syndrome<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 4.35E-13<lb/> 7.88E-12<lb/> 154.67<lb/> 26<lb/> Hypotonic Seizures<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 2.42E-13<lb/> 1.34E-11<lb/> 69.22<lb/> 27<lb/> Nicotine Dependence<lb/> JENSEN DISEASE<lb/> 9.07E-13<lb/> 1.48E-11<lb/> 137.82<lb/> 28<lb/> Anhedonia<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 7.07E-13<lb/> 3.42E-11<lb/> 289.17<lb/> 29<lb/> Manic Disorder<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 1.66E-11<lb/> 7.15E-10<lb/> 87.94<lb/> 30<lb/> Melancholia<lb/> GeDiPNet<lb/> 2.32E-11<lb/> 8.99E-10<lb/> 148.59<lb/> Note: q-value and OR refer to adjusted p-value and Odds Ratio, respectively.<lb/></figure>

			<p>versus its odds ratio. Each point displays a single Geneset;<lb/> the x-axis measures the odds ratio (0, inf) calculated for the<lb/> gene set, while the y-axis yields the -log(p-value) of the gene<lb/> set. Larger blue points represent significant terms (p-value &lt;<lb/> 0.05); smaller gray points indicate non-significant terms. Also,<lb/> the darker the blue color of a point, the more important it is.<lb/></p>

			<head>4. DISCUSSION<lb/></head>

			<p>In summary, by employing comprehensive in silico anal-<lb/>ysis, this study revealed genetic associations and close inter-<lb/>action between GLP1 signaling and specifically GLP1 recep-<lb/>tor with 29 refined genes through STRING-MODEL, espe-<lb/>cially with DRD3, BDNF, CREB1, CRH, IL6, and DPP4<lb/> genes. GMIs revealed that the CREB1 gene is the most asso-<lb/>ciated seed, and hsa-miR-22-3p has the most interactions<lb/> among other miRNAs. Interestingly, GLP1R was associated<lb/> with CREB1 through hsa-miR-297 and hsa-miR-567. More-<lb/>over, hsa-miR-204-5p has connections with GLP1R,<lb/> CREB1, BDNF, NTRK2, and NR3C1. TF-miRNA coregula-<lb/>tory networks showed the major impact of CREB1, NR3C1,<lb/> NTRK2, BDNF, IL-6, and SLC6A4 as the best-scored pro-<lb/>tein targets. Furthermore, SP1 and CTCF were the most in-<lb/>terconnected TFs. Additionally, hsa-miR-16, hsa-miR-22,<lb/> and hsa-miR-195 were found to be the most significant asso-<lb/>ciated miRNAs in this network. Curiously, SP1 and SP3<lb/> were linked with GLP1R and OPRM1. According to the<lb/> Pathways analyses, Dopamine Receptors R-HSA-390651,<lb/> Dopaminergic synapse, and Dopamine receptor-mediated<lb/> signaling pathway Homo sapiens P05912 were found as the<lb/> top associate candidates. GO analyses showed Dopamine<lb/> Metabolic Process (GO:0042417), Neuron Projection<lb/> (GO:0043005), and G Protein-Coupled Serotonin Receptor<lb/> Activity (GO:0004993) as the most significant processes.<lb/> The most significant associated disease-causing phenotype<lb/> among all three databases was major depressive disorder.<lb/> Substance abuse and alcohol dependence were the second<lb/> and third. Noteworthy, the best models of DisGeNET and<lb/> GeDiPNet 2023 were both mental depression and mood dis-<lb/>orders.<lb/></p>

			<p>As mentioned earlier, a comprehensive gene list contain-<lb/>ing 29 genes was refined during a strategy of filtering the SI<lb/> construct. These genes are included in the filtration accord-<lb/>ing to the pharmacological and ligand-target interactions of<lb/> Ozempic as the agonist of GLP1R and, three other enzymes<lb/> and one plasma blood carrier. Additionally, we found the top<lb/> 20 best-scored genes in GeneCards for &quot;Suicide Ideation&quot; as<lb/> a keyword, including the 10 genes of GARS. Multiple anal-<lb/>yses of these genes, including PPIs, GMIs, and TF-miR as a<lb/> coregulatory network, revealed interesting results. Specifi-<lb/>cally, a deep in silico study of Enrichment Analysis was suc-<lb/>cessfully carried out for this gene list. Pathway Analysis, GO<lb/> analysis, and Disease Drug Analysis (DDA) all indicated that<lb/> depressive phenotypes and dopamine regulation are the most<lb/> significant associated factors playing remarkable roles in SI.<lb/> Importantly, we caution against GLP1 agonist administra-<lb/>tion, especially in patients with known hypodopaminergia,<lb/> rather than its general approval for long-term addiction<lb/> treatment. However, our results were based on strong evi-<lb/>dence and clinical reports in previous studies. Further clini-<lb/>cal confirmation is required, and we acknowledge that the<lb/> connection between neural transmission changes and SI re-<lb/>mains speculative and multifactorial.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. (6). Scatterplot of all terms in Jensen Disease database (A) and DisGeNET database (B). Each point signifies a term in the library. Term<lb/> frequency-inverse document frequency (TF-IDF) values were computed for the gene set corresponding to each term, and UMAP was utilized<lb/> to display the resulting values. The terms are plotted based on the first two UMAP dimensions. Generally, terms with more similar gene sets<lb/> are positioned closer together. Terms are colored by automatically identified clusters computed with the Leiden algorithm applied to the<lb/> TF-IDF values. The darker and larger the point, the more significantly enriched the term. Hovering over points will display the term, the<lb/> p-value from the enrichment calculation, and the automatically assigned cluster. (A higher resolution/colour version of this figure is available<lb/> in the electronic copy of the article).<lb/> </figure>
				
			<figure>(A)<lb/> (B)<lb/> Fig. (7). Manhattan plot of terms from Jensen Disease database (A) and DisGeNET database (B) for SI candidate gene list indicating Depres-<lb/>sion as the most top hub. Each point represents a single term along the x-axis. The y-values represent the -log10(p-value) corresponding to the<lb/> enrichment of the input gene set for the term gene set. (A higher resolution/colour version of this figure is available in the electronic copy of<lb/> the article).<lb/> </figure>
				
			<figure>(Fig. 8) Contd….<lb/> (A)<lb/> (B)<lb/> (A)<lb/> Fig. (8). Volcano plot of terms from Jensen Disease database (A) and DisGeNET database (B) for SI candidate gene list showing depression<lb/> phenotype in the top. Each point shows a single term, plotted by the corresponding odds ratio (x-position) and -log10(p-value) (y-position)<lb/> from the enrichment results of the input query gene set. The larger and darker-colored the point, the more significantly enriched the input<lb/> gene set is for the term. (A higher resolution/colour version of this figure is available in the electronic copy of the article).<lb/></figure>

			<p>The majority of studies to date have indeed reported the<lb/> benefits of Ozempic consumption. However, our study from<lb/> a genetic standpoint indicated inconsistent findings. It is not<lb/> possible to compare our studies with all of the reports due to<lb/> some glaring reasons; this is not a review article, and we<lb/> introduced a new perspective that requires further validation<lb/> and confirmation. The FDA reported that they did not find an<lb/> association between the use of the GLP-1 variant and suicid-<lb/>al thoughts or actions. However, they could not definitively<lb/> rule out that a small risk may exist.<lb/></p>

			<p>Despite these initial findings, we urge caution concerning<lb/> attenuation rather than the chronic promotion of enhanced<lb/> dopamine signaling, potentially leading to hypodopaminer-<lb/>gic. Most recently, Wang et al., in a real-world cohort rely-<lb/>ing on electronic records, compared GLP1 agonistic therapy<lb/> like semaglutide with other non-GLP1 agonist weight loss<lb/> agents for depression and SI and could not support a rela-<lb/>tionship of induction of depression and SI for semaglutide<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[79]</ref>. While we are not refuting this important work by Wang<lb/> et al. <ref type="biblio">[79]</ref>, albeit the issue whereby electronic records of pa-<lb/>tients may yield omissions related to certain diagnostic crite-<lb/>ria (e.g., SI and even suicide attempts), we cannot ignore<lb/> media reports such as the April 17 th from the NY Post sug-<lb/>gesting that Ozempic appears to be changing a growing<lb/> number of patients claiming that the GLP1 agonistic medica-<lb/>tions have caused anxiety, and SI even as they shed the<lb/> pounds. It is also well-known that obese individuals also<lb/> have a reduced dopaminergic function either genetically <ref type="biblio">[24]<lb/></ref> or epigenetically <ref type="biblio">[25]</ref>, which only further complicates the<lb/> issue at hand. However, it is indeed noteworthy that while<lb/> we are in no position to assess the accuracy of the data col-<lb/>lected from archival EMRs used in the Wang et al. study<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[79]</ref>, there exists a plethora of literature reports (PubMed;<lb/> Assessed 4-20-2024; 51,395 listings using EMR as a word<lb/> search) that argue and or question the validity of utilizing<lb/> EMR for assessing clinical outcomes and important ques-<lb/>tions <ref type="biblio">[26-30]</ref>. Specifically, the secondary use of clinical data<lb/> for research purposes is not without limitations. In accord-<lb/>ance with the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Re-<lb/>views and Meta-Analyses guidelines, Edmondson &amp; Reimer<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[31]</ref> performed a systematic review to identify current issues<lb/> related to the secondary use of electronic medical record data<lb/> via MEDLINE and CINAHL databases. All articles pub-<lb/>lished until June 2018 were included. Sixty articles remained<lb/> after title and abstract review, and four domains of potential<lb/> limitations were identified: (1) data quality issues, present in<lb/> 91.7% of the articles reviewed; (2) data preprocessing chal-<lb/>lenges (53.3%); (3) privacy concerns (18.3%); and (4) poten-<lb/>tial for limited generalizability (21.7%).<lb/> </p>
				
			<p>Diabetes and insulin resistance are associated with al-<lb/>tered brain imaging, depression, and increased rates of age-<lb/>related cognitive impairment. Importantly, it has been<lb/> </p>
				
			<figure>(B)<lb/></figure>

			<p>demonstrated that mice with a brain-specific knockout of the<lb/> insulin receptor (Neuronal Insulin Receptor Knockout<lb/> (NIRKO) mice) exhibit brain mitochondrial dysfunction with<lb/> reduced mitochondrial oxidative activity, increased levels of<lb/> reactive oxygen species, and increased levels of lipid and<lb/> protein oxidation in the striatum and nucleus accumbens <ref type="biblio">[81,<lb/> 82]</ref>; NIRKO mice also exhibit increased levels of monoam-<lb/>ine oxidase A and B (MAO A and B) leading to increased<lb/> dopamine turnover in these areas. This finding may exacer-<lb/>bate people with a genetic predisposition for schizophrenia,<lb/> whereby reduced dopamine availability in the mitochondria<lb/> could affect the clinical presence of schizophrenia and even<lb/> depression <ref type="biblio">[83, 84]</ref>. Studies in cultured neurons and glial<lb/> cells indicate that these changes in MAO A and B are a di-<lb/>rect consequence of loss of insulin signaling <ref type="biblio">[85, 86]</ref>. As a<lb/> result, NIRKO mice develop age-related anxiety and depres-<lb/>sive-like behaviors that can be reversed by treatment with<lb/> MAO inhibitors, as well as the tricyclic antidepressant imi-<lb/>pramine, which inhibits MAO activity and reduces oxidative<lb/> stress <ref type="biblio">[87]</ref>. Also, insulin resistance in the brain induces mito-<lb/>chondrial and dopaminergic dysfunction, leading to anxiety<lb/> and depressive-like behaviors, demonstrating a potential<lb/> molecular link between central insulin resistance and behav-<lb/>ioral disorders <ref type="biblio">[88]</ref>. Another limitation arises from the con-<lb/>troversy of various clinical reports related to this important<lb/> topic. Interestingly, following careful consideration of the<lb/> literature for investigating any match results with ours, we<lb/> found a recent animal study by <ref type="biblio">Sadek et al.</ref> conducted on the<lb/> plausible impact of semaglutide on experimental autoim-<lb/>mune encephalomyelitis (EAE)-induced Multiple sclerosis in<lb/> mice. They found semaglutide triggers the PI3K/Akt axis,<lb/> which, in turn, inhibits the activity of GSK-3β. The inhibited<lb/> GSK3β activity then decreases demyelination and causes<lb/> remyelination via CREB/BDNF; moreover, it increases Nrf2<lb/> and SOD levels leading to protection in mice from EAE-<lb/>induced oxidative stress <ref type="biblio">[89]</ref>. A recently published report by<lb/> Schoretsanitis et al. utilized the WHO database and found an<lb/> association of Ozempic with suicidal ideation, which con-<lb/>firms our results <ref type="biblio">[90]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>5. LIMITATIONS<lb/></head>

			<p>The current study has some limitations. For example,<lb/> there is a lack of functional and molecular validation related<lb/> to the link between pharmacological GLPR1 activation, de-<lb/>pressive behavior, and SI. We utilized well-known sources<lb/> with high reliability in our in silico and systems biology<lb/> analyses, which might be augmented with additional sources<lb/> or new sources in similar future studies. Another limitation<lb/> in silico analysis is considered reporting every detail in fu-<lb/>ture studies and neglecting the priorities (we basically re-<lb/>ported the priorities/top-scored results). Additionally, tran-<lb/>scriptomics and GWAS studies regarding Ozempic or other<lb/> GLP1R agonists are limited; thus, our transcriptomic-<lb/>associated results (potential miRNAs and Transcription Fac-<lb/>tors) remarkably need further validation on clinical samples.<lb/> Our finding in the PPI network for BDNF should be further<lb/> investigated in future genetic studies <ref type="biblio">[91]</ref>, as well as adverse<lb/> effects, especially in terms of depression and RDS behaviors<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[92, 93]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>CONCLUSION<lb/></head>

			<p>Despite the FDA&apos;s recent remarks that SI associated with<lb/> GLP1R agonism is not a concern, these findings obviously<lb/> show the negative impact of Ozempic as an agonist for<lb/> GLP1 and its receptor (GLP1R). When Ozempic reaches the<lb/> blood, it will begin to induce a number of reactions starting<lb/> from GLP1 and its receptor. Based on our silico predictions,<lb/> the binding of Ozempic to GLP1 receptor will activate sev-<lb/>eral pathways, which may lead to the dysregulation of the<lb/> dopaminergic signaling and, as a consequence, exacerbation<lb/> of depressive behaviors, which are one of the main endophe-<lb/>notypes of RDS. Notably, the associations found in the in<lb/> silico analysis require further empirical validation through<lb/> clinical studies.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
