<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>Introduction<lb/></head>

			<p>Enablement is an intervention by which the health care provider<lb/> recognizes, promotes and enhances people&apos;s ability to control their<lb/> health and life <ref type="biblio">[1–4]</ref>. <ref type="biblio">St-Cyr Tribble et al.</ref> propose, in accordance<lb/> with recent reviews on the topic <ref type="biblio">[1–4]</ref>, a model of enablement<lb/> regrouping the following dimensions: contributing to the therapeu-<lb/>tic relationship, building on the person&apos;s point of view, facilitating<lb/> the learning experience, encouraging and supporting the decision-<lb/>making process, building on the person&apos;s strengths and helping to<lb/> broaden the person&apos;s possibilities <ref type="biblio">[3]</ref>.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Enablement is in continuity with the patient-centred model<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[5,6]</ref> because it shares many dimensions with this last model<lb/> (contributing to the therapeutic relationship, building on the per-<lb/>son&apos;s point of view, encouraging and supporting the decision-<lb/>making process and facilitating the learning experience). The term<lb/> &apos;empowerment&apos; is often used to talk about enablement <ref type="biblio">[7–10]</ref>.<lb/> However, this term (empowerment) may be confusing because it<lb/> can also represent the patient&apos;s outcome after the enablement<lb/> intervention <ref type="biblio">[2,4,11]</ref>.<lb/></p>  
			
			<p>Abundant health literature suggests that strategies based on<lb/> enablement are associated with good outcomes <ref type="biblio">[12]</ref>, which<lb/> include a more effective decision-making process, a better man-<lb/>agement of disease complications and adoption of healthier behav-<lb/>iours <ref type="biblio">[13]</ref>. However, despite these potential relevant outcomes,<lb/> the World Health Organization stressed the lack of patients&apos;<lb/> enablement by health care providers in the long-term care of<lb/> chronic diseases <ref type="biblio">[12]</ref>. A primary step in developing and evaluating<lb/> strategies to improve enablement is to have a reliable and valid<lb/> measure of enablement in the health care context. As our capacity<lb/> to measure it grows, we will be in a better position to estimate the<lb/> real effects of enablement on patients&apos; health, and more broadly,<lb/> on the health care system <ref type="biblio">[14]</ref>. We could also be able to design<lb/> effective strategies to improve enablement.<lb/></p>

			<p>In this study, we aimed at identifying and comparing instru-<lb/>ments used to assess enablement in the health care context.<lb/></p>

			<head>Methods<lb/></head> 
			
			<head>Search strategy and articles selection<lb/></head>

			<p>Covering all available years from 1980 to March 2009, we con-<lb/>ducted an electronic literature search of the following databases:<lb/> Medline (1980–), Embase (1980–), Cochrane (1991–), Cinahl<lb/> (1982–) and PsycINFO (1980–), without any language restriction.<lb/> An information specialist was consulted to help develop, update<lb/> and run specific strategies for each databases. The following<lb/> MeSH terms and keywords were used: &apos;Power (psychology)&apos;,<lb/> &apos;Empowerment&apos;, &apos;Empowering&apos;, &apos;Enablement&apos;, &apos;Questionnaires&apos;,<lb/> &apos;Process assessment&apos;, &apos;Quality assessment&apos;, &apos;Psychometrics&apos;,<lb/> &apos;Scale&apos;, &apos;Instrument construction&apos;, &apos;Instrument validation&apos;,<lb/> &apos;Instrument scaling&apos;, &apos;Validation studies&apos;, &apos;Nursing assessment&apos;,<lb/> &apos;Reliability&apos;, &apos;Validity&apos;, &apos;Test validity&apos;, &apos;Test reliability&apos;, &apos;Test<lb/> construction&apos;, &apos;Factor analysis&apos;, &apos;Rating scale&apos;, &apos;Instrument&apos;,<lb/> &apos;Measurement&apos;, &apos;Assessment&apos;, &apos;Tool&apos;, &apos;Health Care Services&apos;,<lb/> &apos;Continuum of Care&apos;, &apos;Long Term Care&apos;, &apos;Mental Health Ser-<lb/>vices&apos;, &apos;Palliative Care&apos;, &apos;Primary Health Care&apos;. We also examined<lb/> additional relevant articles that potentially included an eligible<lb/> instrument from the reference lists of the collected articles (hand<lb/> searching).<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>All searches were transferred to a reference database (Ref-<lb/>works). Refworks gave the opportunity to group similar (not nec-<lb/>essarily identical) citations. Similar citations were then checked to<lb/> remove manually the identical ones (citations indexed on more<lb/> than one database). The titles and abstracts were read one by one<lb/> (CH). We excluded the citation at this stage if it was obvious that<lb/> it did not satisfy our inclusion criteria. We retained other citations<lb/> for complete reading. Two authors (CH and JA) independently<lb/> appraised the full text of identified retained papers to identify<lb/> potentially eligible articles. Discrepancies between the two<lb/> reviewers were resolved by consensus. First authors of included<lb/> studies were contacted to identify uncovered articles.<lb/></p>

			<head>Inclusion and exclusion criteria<lb/></head>

			<p>Citations were retained if they satisfied all of the following criteria:<lb/> (1) development and/or validation of an instrument; (2) evaluation<lb/> of enablement (often called &apos;empowerment&apos;) defined as an inter-<lb/>vention by which the health care provider recognizes, promotes<lb/> and enhances patients&apos; abilities to control their health and lives;<lb/> and (3) quantitative results following administration of the instru-<lb/>ment. We did not search for articles measuring only a sub-concept<lb/> or a dimension of enablement (patient-centred care, shared deci-<lb/>sion making, participation and information, etc.). Articles includ-<lb/>ing only a subscale on enablement were not retained.<lb/></p>

			<head>Assessment of study quality<lb/></head>

			<p>We assessed the quality of the first article published (considered as<lb/> the main article) for each instruments selected, using a modified<lb/> version of the Standards for Reporting of Diagnostic Accuracy<lb/> (STARD) <ref type="biblio">[15–17]</ref>. The STARD is an outgrowth of the Consoli-<lb/>dated Standards of Reporting Trials initiative <ref type="biblio">[18]</ref>, adopted by<lb/> many of the leading biomedical journals and journals in psychol-<lb/>ogy <ref type="biblio">[19]</ref>. The STARD has already been successfully used in a<lb/> similar systematic review by a member of our team (F. L.) <ref type="biblio">[20]</ref>.<lb/> From the initial STARD that contained 25 items <ref type="biblio">[15–17]</ref>, 15 items<lb/> were kept and judged appropriate to evaluate questionnaires.<lb/> Using this modified scale (15 items), two researchers (CH and JA)<lb/> independently determined a global quality score for each article.<lb/> The scores were then compared and a consensus was reached.<lb/></p>

			<head>Data extraction<lb/></head>

			<p>The following data were extracted for each instrument included:<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[21]</ref> name of the instrument as given by the original author, first<lb/> author of the instrument and year of publication, discipline of the<lb/> first author, main purpose (measurement aim, clinical domain and<lb/> context of use envisioned by author, including the person who<lb/> completed the instrument), description of the instrument (number<lb/> of dimensions and items), response scale, development proce-<lb/>dures, conceptual/theoretical foundation and psychometric prop-<lb/>erties. Special attention was given to face and content validity <ref type="biblio">[19]</ref>.<lb/> Face validity indicates whether the instrument appears to be<lb/> assessing the construct of interest. Content validity is the extent to<lb/> which all dimensions of the measured concept are represented<lb/> in the instrument <ref type="biblio">[19]</ref>. Data extraction was completed by two<lb/> members of the team (CH and JA) and disagreements were<lb/> resolved by consensus.<lb/></p>

			<head>Results<lb/></head>
			
			<head>Articles included<lb/></head> 
			 
			<p><ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows the number of citations found at each stage of the<lb/> selection process. The search strategies identified 3800 citations,<lb/> from which 3135 were kept after removing duplicates. Fifty-three<lb/> were read completely and evaluated. Among these articles, eight<lb/> were not about the development or validation of an instrument<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[22–29]</ref>; six were about concepts other than enablement or<lb/> empowerment <ref type="biblio">[30–35]</ref>, 31 did not measure a professional inter-<lb/>vention <ref type="biblio">[36–66]</ref> and five included only a subscale on enablement<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[67–71]</ref>. Hand searching and correspondence with authors added<lb/> another relevant article <ref type="biblio">[72]</ref>.<lb/></p> 
			 
			 <p>Four articles covering two instruments were included in this<lb/> review. The identified instruments were: the Patient Empowerment<lb/> Scale (PES) <ref type="biblio">[72,73]</ref> and the Empowering Speech Practices Scale<lb/> (ESPS) <ref type="biblio">[74,75]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>Quality assessment<lb/></head>

			<p>Overall, the quality of the studies was fair: 8 and 9 out of 15<lb/> (<ref type="table">Table 1</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<head>Characteristics of instruments<lb/></head>

			<p><ref type="table">Tables 2 and 3</ref> summarize both included instruments. Both instru-<lb/>ments (PES and ESPS) were based on conceptual frameworks<lb/> developed from studies conducted by the same authors (as the<lb/> instrument development).<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The PES evaluated patient&apos;s perception, whereas ESPS was<lb/> completed by both patient and nurse with parallel questionnaires,<lb/> thus representing both perceptions of the consultation. Both instru-<lb/>ments targeted inpatients. Both instruments used a 3-point Likert<lb/> response scale. The PES contained 40 items and the ESPS con-<lb/>tained 44 items.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The PES was studied among specific patient populations<lb/> (elderly inpatients), while ESPS was validated among a more<lb/> diverse group of patients. Both studies involved nurses and were<lb/> conducted in Europe.<lb/></p>

			<head>Discussion<lb/></head>

			<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first review to<lb/> identify and compare instruments used to measure enablement<lb/> in a health care context. Two instruments were identified. The<lb/> PES is a 40-item instrument to assess inpatient&apos;s perception<lb/> of enablement. The ESPS, a 44-item instrument, assesses<lb/> enablement in hospital setting, from the patients&apos; and nurses&apos;<lb/> perspectives.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Both instruments were based on conceptual frameworks devel-<lb/>oped from studies conducted by the original authors of the instru-<lb/>ment. Basing instrument development on conceptual framework<lb/> may increase the content validity of the instrument <ref type="biblio">[76–78]</ref>.<lb/> However, it is relevant to start with a critical review of the litera-<lb/>ture to have a more valid conceptual model <ref type="biblio">[79,80]</ref>. As suggested<lb/> by Streiner and Norman <ref type="biblio">[19]</ref>, recent reviews and empirical<lb/> research <ref type="biblio">[1–4]</ref> could be used in further attempts to improve these<lb/> instruments (PES and ESPS) or elaborate new ones.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The enablement model <ref type="biblio">[1,3,4]</ref> and the patient-centred model<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[5,81]</ref> share many common dimensions (contributing to the thera-<lb/>peutic relationship, building on the person&apos;s point of view, encour-<lb/>aging and supporting the decision-making process and facilitating<lb/> the learning experience), raising the question &apos;Is it the same<lb/> concept?&apos; Our view is that the enablement process is necessarily<lb/></p>

			<figure>Total citations identified: 3800<lb/>Citations retrieved for detailed evaluation by two authors: 53<lb/>Duplicate: 665<lb/>Relevant articles: 3 (2 instruments)<lb/>And citations added with hand searching: 1<lb/> Included articles: 4 (2 instruments)<lb/> Citations screened for evaluation: 3135<lb/> Exclusion criteria:<lb/> @BULLET Not about development or validation of an instrument: 8<lb/> @BULLET Concepts other than enablement: 6<lb/> @BULLET Outside the therapeutic relationship: 31<lb/> @BULLET Including only a sub-scale on enablement: 5<lb/> Figure 1 Number of citations identified<lb/> through the stages of the systematic review.<lb/></figure> 
			
			<table>Table 1 Quality assessment of the main studies included, based on the modified version of Standards for Reporting of Diagnostic Accuracy<lb/> Section and topic<lb/> Item<lb/> Patient<lb/> Empowerment<lb/> Scale [72,73]<lb/> Empowering<lb/> Speech Practices<lb/> Scale [74,75]<lb/> Title/abstract<lb/> Identify the article as a study concerning a measuring instrument.<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> Introduction<lb/> State the research question or study aims, like developing or validating a measuring<lb/> instrument.<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> Methods<lb/> Participants<lb/> Describe the study population: The inclusion and exclusion criteria, setting and<lb/> locations where the data were collected.<lb/> +<lb/> 0<lb/> Describe the method of recruitment of the participants.<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> Describe participant sampling: Was the study population a consecutive series of<lb/> participants? If not, specify how participants were further selected.<lb/> 0<lb/> +<lb/> Test methods<lb/> Describe technical specifications of material and methods involved, including how and<lb/> when measurements were taken, and/or cite references for measuring instrument.<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> Describe relevant information for the readers concerning the measuring instrument<lb/> (scale available in the text).<lb/> +<lb/> 0<lb/> Statistical methods Describe methods for calculating or comparing measures of reliability, validity and the<lb/> statistical methods used to quantify uncertainty (e.g. 95% confidence intervals).<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> Results<lb/> Participants<lb/> Report when study was done, including beginning and ending dates of recruitment.<lb/> 0<lb/> +<lb/> Report demographic characteristics of the study population (e.g. age, sex,<lb/> employment, recruitment centres).<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> Report the number of participants satisfying the criteria for inclusion (a flow diagram<lb/> is strongly recommended).<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> Test results<lb/> Report distribution of severity of the situation being assessed.<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> Estimates<lb/> Report estimates of accuracy and measures of statistical uncertainty (e.g. 95%<lb/> confidence intervals).<lb/> 0<lb/> 0<lb/> Report how indeterminate results, missing responses and outliers on the measuring<lb/> instrument were handled.<lb/> 0<lb/> +<lb/> Discussion<lb/> Discuss the clinical applicability of the study findings.<lb/> +<lb/> +<lb/> Total score<lb/> 8/15<lb/> 9/15<lb/></table>
			
			<table>Table 2 Characteristics of the two instruments included<lb/> Name of the<lb/> instrument (First author,<lb/> year of publication)<lb/> Origin of first<lb/> author, country<lb/> Main purpose (Measurement<lb/> aim, clinical domain and context<lb/> of use envisioned by author)<lb/> Description (number<lb/> of dimensions and items)<lb/> Response<lb/> scale<lb/> Patient<lb/> Empowerment<lb/> Scale (Faulkner,<lb/> 2001) [72,73]<lb/> Department of<lb/> Community<lb/> Ageing<lb/> Rehabilitation<lb/> Education and<lb/> Research, UK<lb/> To assess inpatients&apos; enablement<lb/> in hospital environments.<lb/> 3 dimensions in the empowerment<lb/> subscale (20 items): promoting patient<lb/> independence, awareness of patients&apos;<lb/> needs and promoting information<lb/> exchange<lb/> 3-point<lb/> Likert<lb/> Completed by the patient after at<lb/> least 3 days of hospitalization.<lb/> 3 dimensions in the disempowerment<lb/> subscale (20 items): impeding patient<lb/> collaboration in care planning,<lb/> domination and indifference to patients&apos;<lb/> needs.<lb/> Empowering<lb/> Speech<lb/> Practices Scale<lb/> (Kettunen,<lb/> 2006) [74,75]<lb/> Research Center<lb/> for Health<lb/> Promotion,<lb/> Finland<lb/> To assess enablement of dyadic<lb/> counselling in hospital setting.<lb/> 2 dimensions (44 items): professionally<lb/> led conversation and patient&apos;s requests<lb/> for additional clarification.<lb/> 3-point<lb/> Likert<lb/> Completed by the inpatient and the<lb/> nurse (by way of the same<lb/> statements, parallel questionnaires)<lb/> after the counselling encounter.<lb/></table>

			<table>Table 3 Development and psychometric properties of the two instruments included<lb/> Instrument<lb/> Origins and development<lb/> Conceptual framework<lb/> Validity<lb/> Reliability<lb/> Patient<lb/> Empowerment<lb/> Scale [72,73]<lb/> 38 registered nurses were asked to nominate empowering and disempowering acts<lb/> relevant to interactions between staff and elderly patients. Further acts were<lb/> obtained following a literature review.<lb/> Constructed on the basis<lb/> of a conceptual model<lb/> of empowerment and<lb/> disempowerment derived<lb/> from the literature and<lb/> empirical results.<lb/> Face validity: Patients and<lb/> nurses were consulted.<lb/> Internal<lb/> consistency:<lb/> Cronbach alpha<lb/> from 0.75 to<lb/> 0.87 for the<lb/> empowerment<lb/> subscale and<lb/> 0.65 to 0.88<lb/> for the<lb/> disempowerment<lb/> subscale.<lb/> Content validity: The scale is<lb/> coherent with the conceptual<lb/> model developed, but does<lb/> not take into account all the<lb/> literature on empowerment.<lb/> Construct validity: Factor<lb/> analysis (not detailed in the<lb/> article).<lb/> The resulting lists of 98 acts for each disposition were hypothetically judged by older<lb/> hospitalized people as to the extent they would be either &apos;control giving&apos;<lb/> (empowering acts, n<lb/> = 20) or &apos;control taking&apos; (disempowering acts, n<lb/> = 20) if<lb/> personally experienced. The 20 highest scoring acts in each category were<lb/> incorporated into the Patient Empowerment Scale.<lb/> The instrument was tested on 102 elderly (65 years or older) patients from three<lb/> hospitals (inpatients for at least 3 days) in Central England (acute medicine,<lb/> surgery and elderly care rehabilitation).<lb/> Empowering<lb/> Speech<lb/> Practices Scale<lb/> [74,75]<lb/> The first stage was a conversation of counselling encounters.<lb/> Constructed on the basis of<lb/> a conceptual model of<lb/> empowerment derived<lb/> from a case study by the<lb/> authors.<lb/> Face validity: Patients and<lb/> nurses were consulted.<lb/> Internal<lb/> consistency:<lb/> Cronbach alpha<lb/> for global<lb/> score: 0.88 and<lb/> for subscales:<lb/> 0.52 to 0.83.<lb/> Content validity: This scale<lb/> simultaneously includes<lb/> items related to the<lb/> enablement process and<lb/> outcomes<lb/> Construct validity: Factor<lb/> analysis confirms two factors<lb/> accounting for 59% of the<lb/> variance. Average loading<lb/> for professionally led<lb/> conversation: 0.80 and<lb/> patient&apos;s requests for<lb/> additional clarification: 0.84.<lb/> At the second stage, the study was used to design a questionnaire containing 65<lb/> statements.<lb/> At the third stage, interviews were conducted where five patients and five nurses<lb/> assessed their videotaped counselling sessions by means of the instrument. The<lb/> statements were reduced to 58.<lb/> At the fourth stage, the revised instrument was tested by four patients on a hospital<lb/> ward.<lb/> Finally, 127 counselling situations involving adult patients (56 women and 54 men;<lb/> mean age<lb/> = 54.9 years) were evaluated with nurses (mean age<lb/> = 41.7; average<lb/> experience<lb/> = 13.8) on 17 wards and polyclinics providing care to adult patients in<lb/> Finland. This left a total of 44 statements.<lb/></table>

			<p>patient-centred but a patient-centred intervention does not<lb/> always correspond to an enablement intervention. Indeed, build-<lb/>ing on the person&apos;s strengths is central to the enablement model<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[1,82–85]</ref>.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>Another question that could be raised is &apos;How is the enablement<lb/> concept positioned among other concepts such as shared decision<lb/> making, patient participation . . .&apos; As stressed in our enablement<lb/> model (see Introduction), these last concepts could be considered<lb/> as sub-concepts of enablement. Our hypothesis is that improving<lb/> many aspects of the interaction between the patient and the health<lb/> care provider (referring to the dimensions of our enablement<lb/> model) is maybe more effective than improving only one or two<lb/> aspects.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The PES evaluates patient&apos;s perception, while ESPS considers<lb/> patient and professional&apos;s points of view. Some authors argued that<lb/> both points of view have to be taken into account to evaluate<lb/> professional&apos;s practices, because interaction of these points of<lb/> view is determinant in the intervention process <ref type="biblio">[11,86]</ref>. Other<lb/> studies demonstrated stronger relationship between patient&apos;s per-<lb/>ceptions and various outcomes. For example, in one study, per-<lb/>ceived empowering care by patients was the most important<lb/> predictor of their quality of life <ref type="biblio">[87]</ref>. Stewart et al. evaluated<lb/> patient-centredness, a concept regrouping many dimensions of<lb/> enablement. They demonstrated that the patient&apos;s perception was a<lb/> better predictor of certain outcomes at the end of a 2-month period<lb/> than that of a trained person scoring an instrument from the audio-<lb/>tape of the encounter. One of their conclusions was that the patient<lb/> outcomes will be affected only when the doctor&apos;s patient-<lb/>centeredness reaches a level that the patient notices <ref type="biblio">[5]</ref>. This<lb/> conclusion may be true for enablement as well. Further studies are<lb/> needed to evaluate this hypothesis.<lb/></p>
			
			<p>The existing instruments are cross-sectional measures to assess<lb/> enablement (PES and ESPS). It is appropriate when considering<lb/> patients provided with medical care in an inpatient context.<lb/> However, in an ambulatory care setting, because the interaction<lb/> between a patient and a health care provider (his or her family<lb/> doctor for example) may evolve over time, the enablement inter-<lb/>vention may develop on a longitudinal basis <ref type="biblio">[88,89]</ref>. Therefore,<lb/> one has to wonder, before using these instruments in such a<lb/> context, whether they are appropriate to measure an inherently<lb/> longitudinal process. This perspective must be kept in mind while<lb/> developing or improving instruments to assess enablement in an<lb/> ambulatory care context.<lb/></p>

			<head>Limitation of the study<lb/></head>

			<p>One of the main limitations of a review is its inability to include all<lb/> of the relevant literature and unpublished material. We acknowl-<lb/>edge that some eligible articles may have been missed during the<lb/> search stage. However, our search strategy was adapted for differ-<lb/>ent databases, was developed with an information specialist and<lb/> favoured an exhaustive literature review. Our hand search and<lb/> correspondence with experts were other ways to help us identify<lb/> uncovered articles. We did not include articles in which enable-<lb/>ment was part of a larger concept, such as quality of care, because<lb/> of the risk of missing such subscales. Scales measuring sub-<lb/>concepts of enablement (shared decision making for example) or<lb/> measuring enablement as a sub-concept of another construct<lb/> could, however, be used in a pool of items in further instrument<lb/> development.<lb/></p>

			<head>Conclusion<lb/></head>

			<p>Two instruments (PES and ESPS) were identified that measure<lb/> enablement in the health care context. Both instruments assess<lb/> enablement in hospital setting, one from the patient&apos;s perspective<lb/> (PES) and the other from both the patient&apos;s and the nurse&apos;s per-<lb/>spective (ESPS). To date, there is no tool available to the clinicians<lb/> or researchers to assess enablement in an ambulatory care context.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
