<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>Introduction<lb/></head>

			<p>Natural products have played, and will continue to play, a key role in drug discovery. In particu-<lb/>lar, the diversity of plant-based systems has provided an enormous number of lead compounds<lb/> in healthcare <ref type="biblio">[1]</ref>. Indeed, plant products represent, according to an assessment of FDA on the<lb/> source of natural products, over one-quarter of all approved new molecular entities <ref type="biblio">[2,3]</ref>. How-<lb/>ever, despite the intensive investigation of plant kingdom, it is estimated that only 6% of the<lb/> approximately 300,000 species of higher plants have been pharmacologically investigated, and<lb/> only 15% phytochemically <ref type="biblio">[4]</ref>. Therefore, plants should be further investigated because new<lb/> compounds with original structures and novel modes of action are continuously required. Nat-<lb/>urally occurring compounds frequently inspire synthetic medicinal compounds, and they could<lb/> be chemically modified, based upon their structural and biological properties <ref type="biblio">[5-8]</ref>. Their struc-<lb/>tural modification allows increasing their efficacy and selectivity, improving physicochemical,<lb/> biochemical and pharmacokinetic properties, removing or reducing side effects.<lb/></p>

			<p>The therapeutic area of infectious diseases has benefited from abundant scaffold diversity<lb/> in natural products, able to interact with many specific targets <ref type="biblio">[7]</ref>. Significant research and<lb/> development over the last 25 years into antiviral drug discovery has resulted in the identifica-<lb/>tion of important antiviral drugs <ref type="biblio">[7]</ref>. In particular, a number of attempts have been made in<lb/> the fight against HIV-1 infection and several natural compounds able to inhibit the viral<lb/> enzymes have been reported <ref type="biblio">[9-17]</ref>. However, so far all anti HIV-1 approved drugs were<lb/> obtained only by chemical synthesis.<lb/></p>

			<p>HIV-1, the etiological agent of AIDS, still remains a global scourge despite the availability<lb/> of more than 30 approved anti-AIDS drugs <ref type="biblio">[18]</ref>. Although the global scale-up of antiretroviral<lb/> therapy has contributed to reduce the number of new infections and AIDS-related deaths,<lb/> about 37 million people were estimated to be infected with HIV in 2016, with 1.8 million of<lb/> new infections and 1 million of deaths <ref type="biblio">[19]</ref>. To date there is no vaccine or cure for HIV infec-<lb/>tion, and the efficacy of antiretroviral therapy, which combines two or three antiviral agents,<lb/> targeting different steps of the virus replication cycle, can be compromised by the selection of<lb/> strains resistant to one or multiple drug classes <ref type="biblio">[20,21]</ref> and treatment-associated toxicity <ref type="biblio">[22]</ref>,<lb/> requiring the discovery of new antiviral agents with innovative modes of action or targets. In<lb/> this respect, the identification of one molecule able to inhibit more than one viral function<lb/> would provide significant advantages, raising the genetic barrier to resistance and increasing<lb/> the compliance to therapy.<lb/></p>

			<p>Five different classes of anti-AIDS approved molecules are available for therapy <ref type="biblio">[18]</ref> and the<lb/> majority of them is represented by inhibitors of reverse transcriptase (RT), the enzyme respon-<lb/>sible for the conversion of the single-stranded RNA genome into a double-stranded cDNA<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[23,24]</ref>. RT is a multifunctional enzyme with two associated functions <ref type="biblio">[25]</ref>, DNA polymerase<lb/> and RNase H activities <ref type="biblio">[26,27]</ref>, that have been proven to be both essential for viral replication.<lb/> While the first one is currently the main target for AIDS treatment, the latter is the only HIV<lb/> enzymatic function not targeted by approved antiviral drugs <ref type="biblio">[26,28,29]</ref>, although it is a very<lb/> promising target <ref type="biblio">[30]</ref>. Indeed it has been shown that RNase H inactivation lead to non-infec-<lb/>tious virions <ref type="biblio">[31]</ref> and its selective inhibition completely blocks viral replication <ref type="biblio">[32,33]</ref>. RNase<lb/> H catalytic core is highly conserved among viral species and strains <ref type="biblio">[34,35]</ref> and presents high<lb/> structural homologies with HIV-1 integrase (IN) <ref type="biblio">[24]</ref>, the enzyme responsible for the integra-<lb/>tion of the HIV-1 cDNA genome into the host cell chromosome, that takes place through<lb/> DNA-protein and protein-protein interactions <ref type="biblio">[36]</ref>. Among the cellular factors involved in the<lb/> integration process into the host DNA there is the human lens epitelium-derived growth factor<lb/> LEDGF/p75 <ref type="biblio">[37]</ref>, a nuclear protein that promotes IN chromatin tethering by establishing spe-<lb/>cific interactions between its IN-binding domain and the IN dimer. IN has become an explored<lb/> target for development of anti HIV treatments <ref type="biblio">[24,38-40]</ref>, with raltegravir <ref type="biblio">[41,42]</ref>, elvitegravir<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[43]</ref> and dolutegravir <ref type="biblio">[44]</ref> that are IN inhibitors approved for clinical use.<lb/></p>

			<p>For many years, the drug discovery was based on searching for new compounds or new tar-<lb/>gets, recently the development of single molecules targeting both viral HIV-1 RT-associated<lb/> RNase H and RNA-dependent DNA polymerase (RDDP) functions, or RNase H and IN func-<lb/>tions (dual inhibitors) has been proposed as an interesting approach <ref type="biblio">[17,26,45-49]</ref>. This inno-<lb/>vative strategy could offer the possibility to reduce the toxicity associated to the co-<lb/>administration of several classes of drugs <ref type="biblio">[18,40]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>In our ongoing research of new natural compounds as potential scaffolds for developing<lb/> innovative inhibitors of the HIV-1, we focused on Sardinian endemic flora, in which geo-<lb/>graphical isolation has selected original metabolic profiles, as documented by several reports<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[14,50-60]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>In particular, in this study we focus on Hypericum scruglii Bacchetta, Brullo et Salmeri<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[61,62]</ref>, a species exclusive to Sardinia island (Italy). Despite the large number of Hypericum<lb/> species, only H. perforatum L. has been intensively investigated, both chemically and pharma-<lb/>cologically. Commonly known as St. John&apos;s wort, it is widely used in Europe as a drug for the<lb/> treatment of mild to moderate depression <ref type="biblio">[63,64]</ref>. When compared to H. perforatum, few<lb/> studies have been undertaken on the other members of this genus although their recognized<lb/> pharmacological properties range from wound healing and antiseptics to antiviral, anti-<lb/>inflammatory, anticancer, antioxidants, antifungal, antimicrobial, cardioprotective and cyto-<lb/>toxic activities<ref type="biblio">[14,51-53,65-69]</ref>. Some Hypericum species also exhibited anti HIV-1 properties<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[14,70,71]</ref>. This genus is known for the production of a broad spectrum of secondary metabo-<lb/>lites, mainly naphthodianthrones (hypericin and pseudohypericin), phloroglucinols (hyper-<lb/>forin and adhyperforin), phenolic acids, flavonoids (hyperoside, rutin or quercitrin),<lb/> xanthones and essential oils <ref type="biblio">[14,72-75]</ref>. Although H. scruglii was not already characterized in<lb/> terms of phytochemical composition and biological/pharmacological properties, recently<lb/> Mandrone et al. <ref type="biblio">[53]</ref> have identified from this species shikimic and chlorogenic acids, two<lb/> known phlorogucinols derivatives, quercitrin, hyperoside and hypericin, even though in a very<lb/> low content, confirming their chemotaxonomic significance <ref type="biblio">[76]</ref>. They have also described the<lb/> antioxidant and α-glucosidase inhibitory activities.<lb/></p>

			<p>In the present study, we investigated the ability of the main compounds isolated from leaves<lb/> of Hypericum scruglii to inhibit both HIV-1 RDDP and RNase H activities in biochemical<lb/> assays. Active compounds were then assayed for their effects on HIV-1 IN activities and to<lb/> interfere with the HIV-1 life cycle.<lb/></p>

			<head>Material and methods<lb/> </head>
				
			<head>Plant material<lb/></head>

			<p>Aerial parts of H. scruglii were collected at the flowering stage (June 2012) in the site of San-<lb/>t&apos;Antonio (Jerzu, Sardinia, Italy, 39˚45&apos;57.4&quot;N 9˚30&apos;41.8&quot;E). The leaves were randomly har-<lb/>vested from 30 individuals of the same population. No flowers, fruits, seeds and roots were<lb/> collected to avoid damage to the population. The species was botanically identified by C.S. and<lb/> a voucher specimen (CAG 239/c) was deposited at the General Herbarium of the Department<lb/> of Life and Environmental Sciences, University of Cagliari. Although H. scruglii is endemic, it<lb/> is not protected by local or international regulations. Furthermore, the location where the<lb/> plant material was harvested is not included in national or local parks or any other natural pro-<lb/>tected areas. Therefore, no specific permission was required for its collection.<lb/></p>

			<head>Chemicals and instruments<lb/></head>

			<p>Reagents and solvents were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Chemical Company (St. Louis,<lb/> MO, USA). The reagents used for expression, purification and biochemical assays were pur-<lb/>chased from Microbiol (Sardinia, Italy), Sigma-Aldrich (Milano, Italy) and PerkinElmer<lb/> (Milano, Italy). The reference compound raltegravir was purchased from ChemScene<lb/> (Monmouth Junction, United States) while the reference compound RDS1759 was provided<lb/> from a chemist collaborator Prof. Roberto Di Santo (University of Rome La Sapienza). The isola-<lb/>tion of the metabolites was conducted with the aid of distinct chromatographic techniques. The<lb/> thin-layer chromatographies (TLC) were carried out on plates impregnated silica Merck Kiesel-<lb/>gel 60 F 254 thickness 0.20 mm for analytical purposes and on plates impregnated silica Merck<lb/> Kieselgel 60 F 254 thickness 0.5 o 1.0 mm for preparative purposes. The bands were visualized by<lb/> spraying with the solution H 2 SO 4 -AcOH-H 2 O (1:20:4) and subsequent heating in the stove for 5<lb/> min at 120˚C. The column chromatographies (CC) were performed using either silica gel Merck<lb/> Kieselgel 60 (70-240 mesh), Amberlite XAD-4 (20-50 mesh; Fluka) and XAD-7 (20-50 mesh;<lb/> Fluka), Sephadex LH-201 (Pharmacia) or Bakerbond C8 and C18 as stationary phase.<lb/></p>

			<p>NMR spectra were recorded at 25˚C and 300 MHz for 1 H and 75 MHz for 13 C on a Varian<lb/> NMR spectrometer FT-300. Methanol-d 4 was used as internal lock.<lb/></p>

			<p>Correlation spectroscopy (COSY) and double quantum filtered COSY (DQF-COSY) spec-<lb/>tra were recorded with gradient enhanced sequence at spectral widths of 3000 Hz in both f2<lb/> and f1 domains; the relaxation delays were of 1.0 s. The total correlation spectroscopy<lb/> (TOCSY) experiments were performed in the phase-sensitive mode with a mixing time of 90<lb/> ms. The spectral width was 3000 Hz. For all the homonuclear experiments, the initial matrix of<lb/> 512 × 512 data points was zero-filled to give a final matrix of 1 k × 1 k points.<lb/></p>

			<p>Proton-detected heteronuclear correlations were measured. Heteronuclear single-quantum<lb/> coherence (HSQC) experiments (optimized for 1 J (H,C) = 140 Hz) were performed in the phase<lb/> sensitive mode with field gradient; the spectral width was 12000 Hz in f1 ( 13 C) and 3000 Hz in<lb/> f2 ( 1 H) and 1.0 s of relaxation delay; the matrix of 1 k × 1 k data points was zero-filled to give a<lb/> final matrix of 2 k × 2 k points. Heteronuclear 2 bond correlation (H2BC) spectra were<lb/> obtained with T = 30.0 ms, and a relaxation delay of 1.0 s; the third-order low-pass filter was<lb/> set for 130 &lt; 1 J (C,H) &lt; 165 Hz. Heteronuclear multiple bond coherence (HMBC) experiment<lb/> (optimized for n J (H,C) = 8 Hz) was performed in the absolute value mode with field gradient;<lb/> typically, 1 H-13 C gHMBC were acquired with spectral width of 18000 Hz in f1 ( 13 C) and 3000<lb/> Hz in f2 ( 1 H) and 1.0 s of relaxation delay; the matrix of 1 k × 1 k data points was zero-filled to<lb/> give a final matrix of 4 k × 4 k points. Constant time inverse-detection gradient accordion<lb/> rescaled heteronuclear multiple bond correlation spectroscopy (CIGAR-HMBC) spectra (8&gt;<lb/> n<lb/> J (H,C) &gt;5) were acquired with the same spectral width used for HMBC. Heteronuclear single-<lb/>quantum coherence-total correlation spectroscopy (HSQC-TOCSY) experiments were opti-<lb/>mized for n J (H,C) = 8 Hz, with a mixing time of 90 ms.<lb/></p>

			<p>LC-MS analysis was carried out on an Alliance 2695 separation module equipped with a<lb/> column heater and a sample chiller. The liquid chromatography system was coupled to a<lb/> Waters 2487 dual wavelength UV detector and to a Quattro Micro™ triple quadrupole mass<lb/> spectrometer (Waters/Micromass, Manchester, UK).<lb/></p>

			<p>Recombinant proteins were purified using the chromatography system Biological LP<lb/> (Biorad). Biochemical assays were measured using the multiplate reader Victor 3 (Perkin<lb/> Elmer).<lb/></p>

			<head>Extraction and isolation of active compounds<lb/></head>

			<p>Plant material (70.0 g) was extracted by sonication with a solution of H 2 O:MeOH (1:1),<lb/> immersed in an ultrasonic bath (Elma1Transonicdigitals) for 40 min. Subsequently, samples<lb/> were filtered and the obtained crude extract was solubilized in H 2 O and then subjected to liq-<lb/>uid-liquid extraction using ethyl acetate (EtOAc) as extracting solvent. The aqueous fraction<lb/> was chromatographed on Amberlite XAD-4 and XAD-7, eluting first with water and then with<lb/> methanol. The organic fraction (10.0 g) was chromatographed on silica gel (SiO 2 CC) using<lb/> CHCl 3 /MeOH solutions as eluent to afford 13 fractions. Fraction 1, eluted in chloroform, was<lb/> chromatographed through Sephadex LH-20, using n-hexane/CHCl 3 /MeOH (2:1:1) as eluent<lb/> solution; four fractions (A-D) were obtained. Fraction A was chromatographed by semi pre-<lb/>parative TLC (0.5 mm) using CHCl 3 /MeOH (1:19) as eluent. The compounds 3 was obtained.<lb/> From fraction B compounds 1 and 2 were isolated. Fraction 2, eluted with CHCl 3 /MeOH<lb/> (95:5), chromatographed by RP-18 CC using decreasing polarity H 2 O/MeOH solutions, led to<lb/> compounds 4 and 5.<lb/></p>

			<p>Fraction 3 eluted with CHCl 3 /MeOH (9:1), was chromatographed by RP-18 CC using<lb/> decreasing polarity H 2 O/MeOH solutions, obtaining the compound 6.<lb/></p>

			<head>Expression and purification of recombinant HIV-1 RT, IN and LEDGF<lb/></head>

			<p>His-tagged p66/p51 HIV-1 RT was expressed in Escherichia coli strain M15 as previously<lb/> described <ref type="biblio">[77]</ref>. Full-length IN and LEDGF proteins were expressed in E. coli BL21 (DE3)<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[15,78]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>RNase H polymerase-independent cleavage assay<lb/></head>

			<p>The HIV-1 RT-associated RNase H activity was measured in 100 μL reaction volume contain-<lb/>ing 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.8; 6 mM MgCl 2 ; 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT); 80 mM KCl; hybrid<lb/> RNA/DNA (5 0 -GTTTTCTTTTCCCCCCTGAC-3 0 -fluorescein, 5 0 -CAAAAGAAAAGGG<lb/> GGGACUG-3 0 -Dabcyl); and 3.8 nM RT. The reaction mixture was incubated for 1 h at 37˚C,<lb/> the reaction was stopped by the addition of EDTA, and products were measured with a Victor<lb/> 3 (Perkin) at 490/528 nm <ref type="biblio">[35]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>RDDP assay<lb/></head>

			<p>The HIV-1 RT-associated RDDP activity was measured using the Enz-Check Reverse Tran-<lb/>scriptase Assay Kit (Life technologies, Carls-bad, California, USA), as previously described<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[47]</ref>. The Yonetani-Theorell analysis was performed as previously reported <ref type="biblio">[79]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>Homogeneous time resolved fluorescence (HTRF) LEDGF dependent assay<lb/></head>

			<p>The IN LEDGF/p75 dependent assay allowed to measure the inhibition of the 3&apos;processing and<lb/> strand transfer IN reactions in the presence of recombinant LEDGF/p75 protein, as previously<lb/> described <ref type="biblio">[80]</ref>. Briefly, 50 nM IN was preincubated with increasing concentration of com-<lb/>pounds for 1 hour at room temperature in reaction buffer containing 20 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 1<lb/> mM DTT, 1% Glycerol, 20 mM MgCl 2 , 0.05% Brij-35 and 0.1 mg/ml BSA. To this mixture, 9<lb/> nM DNA donor substrate (5&apos;-ACAGGCCTAGCACGCGTCG-Biotin-3&apos; annealed with 5&apos;-<lb/>CGACGCGTGGTAGGCCTGT-Biotin3&apos;) and 50 nM DNA acceptor substrate (5&apos;-Cy5-AT<lb/> GTGGAAAATCTCTAGCAGT-3&apos; annealed with 5&apos;-Cy5-TGAGCTCGAGATTTTCCACAT-<lb/>3&apos;) and 50 nM LEDGF/p75 protein were added and incubated at 37˚C for 90 minutes. After<lb/> the incubation, 4 nM of Europium-Streptavidine were added at the reaction mixture and the<lb/> HTRF signal was recorded using a Perkin Elmer Victor 3 plate reader using a 314 nm for excita-<lb/>tion wavelength and 668 and 620 nm for the wavelength of the acceptor and the donor sub-<lb/>strates emission, respectively.<lb/></p>

			<head>Antiviral activity and cell toxicity. Phenotypic analyses with fully<lb/> replicating recombinant HIV-1 strain<lb/></head>

			<p>The human TZM-bl indicator cell line was obtained from the American Type Culture Collec-<lb/>tion (Manassas, VA) and maintained at 37˚C and 5% CO 2 in Dulbecco&apos;s modified Eagle&apos;s<lb/> medium (DMEM) containing 10% fetal bovine serum, 50 μg/mLpenicillin, and 50 μg/mL<lb/> streptomycin. The HIV-1 virus NL(AD8) was titrated as follows: serial 5-fold dilutions of the<lb/> virus were made in quadruplicate wells in 96-well culture plates, in a total volume of 100 μL of<lb/> growth medium, for a total of 8 dilution steps. Freshly trypsinized cells (20,000 cells in 100 μL<lb/> of growth medium containing 75 μg/mL DEAE-dextran) were added to each well, and the<lb/> plates were incubated at 37˚C in a humidified 5% CO 2 -95% air environment. After 48 h of<lb/> incubation, the medium was removed and viral infection was quantified using a β-galactosi-<lb/>dase (CPRG) assay (Roche). Twenty thousand TZM-bl cells/well were seeded in 96-well plates<lb/> in complete DMEM supplemented with 30 μg/mL DEAE-dextran (Sigma-Aldrich). Three<lb/> hundred times the 50% tissue culture infective dose (TCID50)/mL of HIV AD8 strain and<lb/> seven serial dilutions (range, 40.000 nM to 625 nM) of each compound were added to the cells,<lb/> as previously described <ref type="biblio">[81,82]</ref>. Vehicle (0.1% dimethyl sulfoxide [DMSO])-treated cells<lb/> served as a negative control. A CCR5 inhibitor (maraviroc) and an integrase inhibitor (dolute-<lb/>gravir) were used as positive-control drugs. The TZM-bl indicator cell line has an integrated<lb/> copy of the β-galactosidase gene under control of the HIV-1 promoter. Β-Galactosidase<lb/> expression, measured by use of a chlorophenol red/β-D-galactopyranoside (CPRG) assay<lb/> (Roche) in cell lysates 48 h post-infection was used as a marker of HIV infection. The inhibi-<lb/>tory curves were fitted by nonlinear regression, allowing for the calculation of the 50% effective<lb/> concentration (EC 50 ) using the Prism software. To evaluate the cell toxicity of the compounds,<lb/> the metabolic XTT [2,3-bis-(2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium-5-carboxani-<lb/>lide] test (Sigma-Aldrich) was performed according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions.<lb/></p>

			<head>Time of addition<lb/></head>

			<p>In TOA experiment it is of fundamental importance that only one replication cycle has been<lb/> completed to avoid confounding effects derived from unwashed viruses after 1 hour of infec-<lb/>tion. For this reason, an env-pseudotyped virus (REJO4541 clone 67) was used. Time of addi-<lb/>tion (TOA) experiment was performed as previously described with minor modifications <ref type="biblio">[83]</ref>.<lb/> 40000 TZM-bl cells/well in a 96-multiwell plate were infected with 1500 X the TCID50 per mL<lb/> of the env-pseudotyped HIV-1 virus in complete medium supplemented with DEAE-dextran<lb/> (Sigma-Aldrich, 30 mg/mL). Virus was incubated with cells for 1 h at 4˚C, and unbound virus<lb/> was subsequently removed by extensive and repeated washing with phosphate-buffered saline<lb/> (PBS) to synchronize the replication. For the next 7 h, antiretroviral compounds inhibiting<lb/> distinct viral replication steps (maraviroc, lamivudine, dolutegravir) and compound 3 were<lb/> added at the following time points: at time 0 and after 60, 120, 180, 240, 300, 360 and 420 min.<lb/> To ensure complete inhibition of viral replication we used a 40-fold EC 50 concentration as<lb/> previously evaluated for each compound on TZM-bl cells [maraviroc (0.7 mM), lamivudine<lb/> (5 mM), dolutegravir (1 mM), and compound 3 (10 mM)]. After 2 days, viral infection was<lb/> quantified using a CPRG assay (Roche) and was then normalized to untreated control cells.<lb/></p>

			<head>Results and discussion<lb/> </head>
				
			<head>Phytochemical profile<lb/></head>

			<p>Based on previous observations <ref type="biblio">[53]</ref>, a phytochemical study was undertaken in order to isolate<lb/> the most abundant compounds in the hydroalcoholic extract obtained from leaves of H. scru-<lb/>glii (Fig <ref type="figure">1</ref>). These compounds belong to different classes and, among them, are three phloro-<lb/>glucinol derivatives (compounds 1-3). Three compounds (3-5) were reported and isolated for<lb/> the first time from this species and compound 3 was reported here for the first time.<lb/></p>

			<p>The phytoconstituents isolated were 3-geranyl-1-(2&apos;-methylbutanoyl)phloroglucinol (1),<lb/> 3-geranyl-1-(2&apos;-methylpropanoyl)phloroglucinol (2), 3-(13-hydroxygeranyl)-1-(2&apos;-<lb/>methylbutanoyl)phloroglucinol (3), 1,3,5-benzentriol 2-[(2S,3R)-3-(3,4-dihydroxylphenyl)-<lb/>2,3-dihydroxylpropyl] (4), 3,4-dihydroxybenzoic acid (5 ) and quercitrin (6) (Fig <ref type="figure">2</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>Compounds 1, 2, and 3 belong to the class of phloroglucinols. The NMR data for com-<lb/>pound 1 and 2 were in agreement with 3-geranyl-1-(2&apos;-methylbutanoyl)-phloroglucinol and<lb/> 3-geranyl-1-(2&apos;-methylpropanoyl)-phloroglucinol, respectively, previously reported from<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig 1. 1 H NMR spectra of MeOH/H 2 O extract of H. scruglii. Numbers indicate the diagnostic signals of the isolated secondary metabolites 1-6.<lb/> https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0195168.g001<lb/> </figure>
				
			<figure>Fig 2. Chemical structures of known metabolites isolated from H. scruglii.<lb/> https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0195168.g002<lb/></figure>

			<p>other Hypericum species <ref type="biblio">[71,84]</ref> and also identified in the extract of Hypericum scruglii through<lb/> NMR-based metabolomics<ref type="biblio">[53]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Compound 3 (Fig <ref type="figure">3</ref>) has been identified as a new metabolite on the basis of its spectro-<lb/>scopic features (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). Its 13 C-NMR spectrum shows 21 signals identified through 13 C and<lb/> HSQC experiments as 4 methyls, 5 methylenes, 4 methines and 8 quaternary carbons, one of<lb/> them, at δ 210.1, attributable to a carbonyl group.<lb/></p>

			<p>In the aromatic region of the 1 H-NMR spectrum, a singlet signal at δ 5.88 is observed,<lb/> which correlates, in the HSQC spectrum, with the carbon at δ 93.5 and, in the CIGAR-HMBC<lb/> spectrum, with the C-1, C-2, C-4 and C-5 at δ 161.1, 105.1, 108.0, 163.5, respectively. The<lb/> methine proton at δ 3.87, linked to carbon C-2&apos; at δ 46.7, correlated in the CIGAR-HMBC<lb/> experiment, with the carbonyl carbon and with the C-5&apos; methyls at δ 17.3 and δ 12.4, and with<lb/> the methylene diasterotopic protons at δ 1.34 and δ 1.80 bonded to carbon C-3&apos; δ 28.1. These<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig 3. A: Chemical structure of the novel phloroglucinol 3 from H. scruglii; B: diagnostic 2D NMR correlations.<lb/> https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0195168.g003<lb/></figure>

			<p>correlations were in good agreement with the presence of a 2-methylbutanoyl group on the<lb/> aromatic ring. The C-4 carbon of the aromatic ring at δ 108.0 correlates, in the<lb/> CIGAR-HMBC, with the H-7 methylene doublet at δ 3.19. This proton is directly bonded to a<lb/> carbon at δ 23.7, and it shows long range correlations with the aromatic ring and with the C-8<lb/> and C-9 olefinic carbon at δ 125.5 and 135.1, respectively. Furthermore, the H-8 olefinic pro-<lb/>ton at δ 5.19 correlates with the methyl group linked to the C-9 and the C-10 methylene carbon<lb/> at δ 29.1, bonded to the protons at δ 2.20.<lb/></p>

			<p>The H-12 protons at δ 1.62, directly linked to the methylene carbon at δ 23.7, correlates<lb/> with the C-13 and C-14 carbons at δ 77.0 and 149.1, respectively. This latter presents correla-<lb/>tions with the methyl protons at δ 1.75, bonded to the carbon at δ 17.7, and with the olefinic<lb/> protons at δ 4.83 and 4.95 both correlated in the HSQC experiment to the carbon at δ 111.4.<lb/></p>

			<p>The correlations observed in the CIGAR-HMBC, H2BC and HSQC-TOCSY spectra sug-<lb/>gested the structure of compound 3 (Fig <ref type="figure">3</ref>). These data allowed the identification of compound<lb/> 3 as 3-(13-hydroxygeranyl)-1-(2&apos;-methylbutanoyl)phloroglucinol.<lb/></p>

			<p>Compound 4 was identified as 1,3,5-benzentriol 2-[(2S,3R)-3-(3,4-dihydroxylphenyl)-<lb/>2,3-dihydroxylpropyl], named filiferol, a chalconoid analogue, isolated for the first time from<lb/> leaves of Washingtonia filifera <ref type="biblio">[85]</ref>. It is based on a flavonol structure with the reduction of the<lb/> common flavonoid keto group to give an unprecedented methylene carbon on the three car-<lb/>bon chain. To our knowledge, this is the first report of filiferol from Hypericum genus.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 1. 1D and 2D NMR data of compound 3 in CD 3 OD.<lb/> n o<lb/> δ 1 H<lb/> J (Hz)<lb/> DQ-COSY<lb/> δ 13 C<lb/> HSQC<lb/> CIGAR-HMBC<lb/> HSQC-TOCSY<lb/> H!H<lb/> H!C ( n J)<lb/> H!C<lb/> 1<lb/> 161.1<lb/> C<lb/> 2<lb/> 105.1<lb/> C<lb/> 3<lb/> 165.4<lb/> C<lb/> 4<lb/> 108.0<lb/> C<lb/> 4( 2 J), 5( 3 J), 8( 2 J), 9( 3 J)<lb/> 5<lb/> 163.5<lb/> C<lb/> 6<lb/> 5.88<lb/> s<lb/> 94.8<lb/> CH<lb/> 1( 2 J), 2( 3 J), 4( 3 J), 5( 2 J), 7( 4 J), 1&apos;( 4 J)<lb/> 7<lb/> 3.19<lb/> d (6.9)<lb/> 8<lb/> 21.9<lb/> CH 2<lb/> 2( 3 J), 3( 3 J), 4( 2 J), 5( 3 J), 8( 2 J), 9( 3 J)<lb/> 7, 8, 11(lr)<lb/> 8<lb/> 5.19<lb/> t (6.0)<lb/> 7, 11(lr)<lb/> 125.5<lb/> CH<lb/> 7( 2 J), 10( 3 J)<lb/> 7, 8, 11(lr)<lb/> 9<lb/> 135.1<lb/> C<lb/> 10<lb/> 2.20<lb/> m<lb/> 12<lb/> 29.1<lb/> CH 2<lb/> 8( 3 J), 9( 2 J), 11( 3 J), 12( 2 J), 13( 3 J)<lb/> 10, 12, 13<lb/> 11<lb/> 1.65<lb/> s<lb/> 8(lr)<lb/> 23.7<lb/> CH 3<lb/> 8( 3 J), 9( 2 J), 10( 3 J)<lb/> 12<lb/> 1.62<lb/> m<lb/> 10, 13<lb/> 34.4<lb/> CH 2<lb/> 13( 2 J), 14( 3 J)<lb/> 10, 12, 13<lb/> 13<lb/> 4.03<lb/> t (6.6)<lb/> 12<lb/> 77.0<lb/> CH<lb/> 10( 3 J), 12( 2 J), 14( 2 J), 15( 3 J), 16( 3 J)<lb/> 10, 12, 13<lb/> 14<lb/> 149.1<lb/> C<lb/> 15a<lb/> 4.95<lb/> s<lb/> 15b, 16(lr)<lb/> 111.4<lb/> CH 2<lb/> 13( 3 J), 14( 2 J)<lb/> 14, 16<lb/> 15b<lb/> 4.83<lb/> s<lb/> 15a, 16(lr)<lb/> 111.4<lb/> CH 2<lb/> 13( 3 J), 14( 2 J), 16( 3 J)<lb/> 14, 16<lb/> 16<lb/> 1.75<lb/> s<lb/> 15b(lr), 15a(lr)<lb/> 17.7<lb/> CH 3<lb/> 13( 3 J), 14( 3 J), 15( 2 J)<lb/> 14, 16<lb/> 1&apos;<lb/> 211.7<lb/> C<lb/> 2&apos;<lb/> 3.87<lb/> tq (6.6)<lb/> 3&apos;, 5&apos;<lb/> 46.7<lb/> CH<lb/> 1&apos;( 2 J), 3&apos;( 2 J), 4&apos;( 3 J), 5&apos;( 2 J)<lb/> 2&apos;, 3&apos;, 4&apos;, 5&apos;<lb/> 3&apos;a<lb/> 1.34<lb/> m<lb/> 2&apos;, 4&apos;<lb/> 28.1<lb/> CH 2<lb/> 1&apos;( 3 J), 2&apos;( 3 J), 4&apos;( 2 J), 5&apos;( 3 J)<lb/> 2&apos;, 3&apos;, 4&apos;, 5&apos;<lb/> 3&apos;b<lb/> 1.80<lb/> ov<lb/> 2&apos;, 4&apos;<lb/> 28.1<lb/> CH 2<lb/> 1&apos;( 3 J), 2&apos;( 3 J), 4&apos;( 2 J), 5&apos;( 3 J)<lb/> 2&apos;, 3&apos;, 4&apos;, 5&apos;<lb/> 4&apos;<lb/> 0.89<lb/> t (7.2)<lb/> 3&apos;<lb/> 12.4<lb/> CH 3<lb/> 2&apos;( 3 J), 3&apos;( 2 J)<lb/> 2&apos;, 3&apos;, 4&apos;, 5&apos;<lb/> 5&apos;<lb/> 1.10<lb/> d (6.6)<lb/> 2&apos;<lb/> 17.3<lb/> CH 3<lb/> 2&apos;( 2 J), 3&apos;( 3 J)<lb/> 2&apos;, 3&apos;, 4&apos;, 5&apos;<lb/> d = doublet, m = multiplet, ov = overlapped, s = singlet, t = triplet, tq = triplet of quartet; lr = long range.<lb/> https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0195168.t001<lb/></figure>

			<p>3,4-dihydroxybenzoic acid (<ref type="formula">5</ref> ), is a phenolic acid widely distributed in nature <ref type="biblio">[86]</ref>. This<lb/> compound is one of the biologically active components of some medicinal plants, including<lb/> Hypericum perforatum L. <ref type="biblio">[87]</ref>. It is been defined by the presence of characteristic signals in the<lb/> 1<lb/> H-NMR spectrum.<lb/></p>

			<p>Finally, compound 6, was identified as quercitrin, a quercetin glycoside. It was already<lb/> reported for H. scruglii <ref type="biblio">[53]</ref> and it is commonly present in the genus Hypericum <ref type="biblio">[75,76,88-95]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>Effects of H. scruglii chemical components on both HIV-1 RT-associated<lb/> functions<lb/></head>

			<p>Biological activities of H. scruglii were previously investigated reporting its antioxidant and α-<lb/>glucosidase activity <ref type="biblio">[53]</ref>. However, up to date, no information on its anti HIV-1 properties<lb/> was available. Given the promising results obtained from Hypericum hircinum L. components<lb/> on both HIV-1 RT associated functions <ref type="biblio">[14]</ref>, with the objective to identify new metabolites<lb/> able to inhibit both HIV-1 RT-associated functions from the Hypericum genus, the most abun-<lb/>dant compounds (1-6) isolated from H. scruglii have been tested on both RDDP and RNase H<lb/> activities in biochemical assays, using the RDDP selective non-nucleoside RT inhibitor<lb/> (NNRTI) Efavirenz and the RNase H selective diketo acid (DKA) derivative RDS1759 <ref type="biblio">[33]</ref> as<lb/> controls (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). In accordance to other reports on naturally occurring phloroglucinol com-<lb/>pounds that have shown a broad range of biological activities including anti-HIV activity<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[71,96-99]</ref>, our results showed that 3-geranyl-1-(2&apos;-methylbutanoyl)phloroglucinol (1), 3-ger-<lb/>anyl-1-(2&apos;-methylpropanoyl)phloroglucinol (2), 3-(13-hydroxygeranyl)-1-(2&apos;-methylbutanoyl)<lb/> phloroglucinol (3) inhibited both HIV-1 RT-associated activities with IC 50 values around 4.1-<lb/>25.5 μM range (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). Interestingly, the small differences in the lateral chains of 1, 2 and 3<lb/> do not affect the potency of inhibition towards the two viral functions. Also quercitrin (6)<lb/> showed to be active in the low micromolar range against both RT-associated functions. Quer-<lb/>citrin (6) is indeed a glycoside of quercetin, a flavonoid which is known to be a potent inhibitor<lb/> of both functions of HIV-1 RT <ref type="biblio">[14,100]</ref>. Differently, 1,3,5-benzentriol 2-[(2S,3R)-3-(3,4-dihy-<lb/>droxylphenyl)-2,3-dihydroxylpropyl], known as filiferol (4), exhibited a weak inhibition of<lb/> both HIV-1 RT-associated RNase H and RDDP functions, and 3,4-dihydroxybenzoic acid,<lb/> namely protocatechuic acid (5), was found inactive at the maximum concentration tested<lb/> (100 μM), similarly to what already found for the structurally-related shikimic acid <ref type="biblio">[14]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 2. Effects of compounds isolated from Hypericum scruglii on the HIV-1 RT-associated activities and IN activities in presence of LEDGF/p75.<lb/> Compound<lb/> a HIV-1 RT<lb/> b<lb/> HIV-1 RT<lb/> c HIV-1 IN LEDGF<lb/> RNase H IC 50 (μM)<lb/> RDDP IC 50 (μM)<lb/> dependent IC 50 (μM)<lb/> 1<lb/> 4.3 ± 0.4<lb/> 25.5 ± 8.8<lb/> 7.3 ± 0.3<lb/> 2<lb/> 4.1 ± 0.1<lb/> 12.3 ± 2.5<lb/> 7.4 ± 0.4<lb/> 3<lb/> 9.1 ± 0.5<lb/> 19.7 ± 3.5<lb/> 13.0 ± 1.0<lb/> 4<lb/> 93 ± 7<lb/> 92 ± 10<lb/> 6.4 ± 0.7<lb/> 5<lb/> &gt; 100 (100%) d<lb/> &gt; 100 (85%) d<lb/> &gt;100 (97%) d<lb/> 6<lb/> 6.3 ± 1.0<lb/> 9.7 ± 1.4<lb/> 1.6 ± 0.16<lb/> RDS 1759<lb/> 7.3 ± 0.1<lb/> Efavirenz<lb/> 0.012 ± 0.003<lb/> Raltegravir<lb/> 0.058 ± 0.01<lb/> a<lb/> Compound concentration required to inhibit the HIV-1 RNase H activity by 50%.<lb/> b Compound concentration required to inhibit the HIV-1 RDDP activity by 50%.<lb/> c<lb/> Compound concentration required to inhibit the HIV-1 IN catalytic activities, in the presence of LEDGF, by 50%.<lb/> d<lb/> Percentage of control activity in the presence of 100 μM concentration of compound.<lb/> https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0195168.t002<lb/></figure>

			<head>Evaluation of the effects H. scruglii chemical components on HIV-1 IN<lb/> activity<lb/></head>

			<p>Since HIV-1 RNase H and IN domains have striking similarities, in order to evaluate if the<lb/> compounds able to inhibit HIV-1 RNase H function could act through a multitarget profile,<lb/> we investigated them also on IN catalytic activities. It is well known, in fact, that compounds<lb/> capable to inhibit the HIV-1 RNase H activity may also affect the HIV-1 IN activity<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[15,17,39,45,46,80]</ref>. Hence, we evaluated their ability to inhibit the HIV-1 IN strand transfer<lb/> reaction in the presence of the LEDGF/p75 cellular cofactor, using Raltegravir as positive con-<lb/>trol (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).<lb/> </p>
				
			<p>Results showed that 3-geranyl-1-(2&apos;-methylbutanoyl)phloroglucinol (1), 3-geranyl-1-(2&apos;-<lb/>methylpropanoyl)phloroglucinol (2), 3-(13-hydroxygeranyl)-1-(2&apos;-methylbutanoyl)phloroglu-<lb/>cinol (3) inhibited HIV-1 IN activities in presence of LEDGF/p75 with IC 50 values in the 7.3-<lb/>13μM range. Also in this case, results showed that the small differences in the lateral chains of<lb/> 1, 2 and 3 do not affect the potency of inhibition on these enzymatic functions. It is worth not-<lb/>ing that these compounds were able to inhibit in similar concentration both RT-associated<lb/> RNase H activity and IN strand transfer function, while they were found to be less active on<lb/> RT-associated RDDP activity. Differently, quercitrin (6) inhibited HIV-1 IN in the low micro-<lb/>molar range, resulting 4-fold more active on HIV-1 IN activity with respect to HIV-1 RNase H<lb/> function. The HIV-1 Integrase (IN) inhibition of its aglycon quercetin has been already<lb/> reported in in vitro assay <ref type="biblio">[101]</ref>. Worth to note, the filiferol (4) that weakly inhibited both HIV-<lb/>1 RT-associated RNase H and RDDP functions, were able to inhibit the HIV-1 IN activities in<lb/> presence of LEDGF/p75 with an IC 50 value of 6.4 μM, showing a selectivity for this viral<lb/> enzyme. 3,4-dihydroxybenzoic acid (5), already found inactive on both RT-associated activi-<lb/>ties, was not active also on HIV-1 IN inhibition.<lb/></p>

			<head>Inhibition of HIV-1 in cell culture and characterization of the mechanism<lb/> of action of bioactive compounds in cell-based assays<lb/></head>

			<p>Given that compounds 1, 2, 3, 4 and 6 were able to inhibit both the HIV-1 RT and IN func-<lb/>tions in biochemical assays, we wanted to evaluate their effect on the HIV-1 replication.<lb/></p>

			<p>Results showed that compounds 1, 2 and 3 significantly inhibited HIV-1 replication with<lb/> EC 50 values in the 3.5-8 μM range (Fig <ref type="figure">4</ref>), in accordance with the range of IC 50 values showed<lb/> against the three viral enzymatic functions in biochemical assays, showing no cytotoxic effect<lb/> up to the highest tested concentration in cells (CC 50 &gt; 50 μM) (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>). Quercitrin, even if it<lb/> was able of inhibiting both HIV-1 RT-associated activities and IN functions in biochemical<lb/> assay, did not exert any effect on HIV-1 replication at the highest tested concentration<lb/> (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>), similarly to what reported for its aglycon quercetin <ref type="biblio">[102]</ref>. Since compounds 1, 2 and<lb/> 3 were active on both HIV-1 RT and IN in biochemical assays, we asked which was the viral<lb/> process targeted by bioactive compounds and, hence, a time-of-addition experiment on the<lb/> most promising molecule was carried out. This experiment determines how long the addition<lb/> of an anti-HIV compound can be postponed within the viral replication cycle before losing its<lb/> antiviral activity. Reference compounds with a known mode of action such as Maraviroc,<lb/> Lamivudine and Dolutegravir were included. As shown in Fig <ref type="figure">5</ref>, the compound 3, similarly to<lb/> lamivudine, a RT inhibitor, lost its activity if added after 4-5 hour post-infection. This timing<lb/> is compatible with an anti-RT activity, exerted on both RNase H and RDDP functions, but not<lb/> with IN inhibition <ref type="biblio">[103]</ref>. These data demonstrate that compound 3 exerts its anti-HIV activity<lb/> targeting the RT functions, while the anti-IN activity, exhibited only in enzymatic assays, is<lb/> not significantly involved in the inhibition of viral replication. A number of compounds were<lb/> reported to have dual RNase H/IN inhibitory activity in vitro but were more selective for IN<lb/> and, indeed, they were shown to inhibit the IN in cell-based experiments <ref type="biblio">[104]</ref>. Very few com-<lb/>pounds <ref type="biblio">[32,33]</ref> were reported to be more selective for RNase H versus IN in vitro and were<lb/> shown to inhibit the RT in cell-based experiments. Hence, it is possible that a dual inhibitory<lb/> activity displayed in enzymatic assays, is not supported by cell-based results, but at our knowl-<lb/>edge, no much data are available on such discrepancies on compounds that were shown to<lb/> have equal potency of inhibition in vitro on the two enzymes. Therefore, further studies should<lb/> be performed to elucidate this specific behavior and to obtain derivatives of compound 3 that<lb/> may be active on viral replication targeting both viral enzymes.<lb/></p>

			<head>Conclusions<lb/></head>

			<p>Searching for new potential multitarget anti-HIV active compounds form Sardinian endemic<lb/> flora, we successfully identified in Hypericum scruglii some chemical components able to<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig 4. Antiviral activity of compounds 1, 2 and 3 on HIV AD8 laboratory strain in TZM-bl cells. Cells were infected with<lb/> 300 TCID50/mL and treated with compounds isolated from H. scruglii at seven different concentration. EC 50 values ranged<lb/> from 3.5 to 8 μM. Only active compounds were shown.<lb/> https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0195168.g004<lb/> </figure>
				
			<figure type="table">Table 3. Effects of compounds isolated from Hypericum scruglii on the HIV-1 replication.<lb/> Compounds<lb/> a EC 50 (μM)<lb/> b<lb/> CC 50 (μM)<lb/> 1<lb/> 3.5<lb/> &gt;50<lb/> 2<lb/> 8<lb/> &gt;50<lb/> 3<lb/> 3.5<lb/> &gt;50<lb/> 4<lb/> &gt;40<lb/> 5<lb/> &gt;40<lb/> 6<lb/> &gt;40<lb/> Maraviroc<lb/> 0.07<lb/> &gt;20<lb/> a<lb/> Compound concentration required to inhibit HIV-1 (AD8) replication in TZM-bl cells by 50%.<lb/> b Compound concentration required to inhibit TZM-bl cell viability by 50%.<lb/> https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0195168.t003<lb/></figure>

			<p>inhibit both HIV-1 RT-associated and IN activities in the low micromolar range. Among the<lb/> bioactive compounds, two known phloroglucinol derivatives, compounds 1 and 2, and a<lb/> newly identified acylphloroglucinol, compound 3, were also able to inhibit the virus replication<lb/> in cell-based assays. Mode of action studies demonstrated that these compounds were active<lb/> also in cell cultures and the timing of inhibition was compatible with an action on the HIV RT<lb/> enzyme.<lb/></p>

			<p>Hence, bioactive compounds isolated from H. scruglii, represent new attractive scaffolds for<lb/> the development of new dual inhibitors that deserve further investigations by means of chemi-<lb/>cal modification, in search of new dual derivatives active on both HIV-1 RT and IN.</p>


	</text>
</tei>