<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>Although a large number of experimental and the-<lb/>oretical investigations indicate that strong two dimen-<lb/>sionality of the normal state is one of key factors in<lb/> high-T c superconductivity, <ref type="biblio">1-3</ref> it remains to be criti-<lb/>cally examined whether the cuprates are essentially two-<lb/>dimensional (2D) metals or three-dimensional (3D) met-<lb/>als with strong anisotropy. Strong two-dimensionality in<lb/> the cuprates is after expressed in exotic behavior of the<lb/> out-of-plane resistivity, ρ c , e.g. a low-T upturn in ρ c (T )<lb/> for under-doped high-T c cuprates. <ref type="biblio">4-7</ref> Interlayer coupling,<lb/> as reflected in ρ c , is strongly related to the 2D-electronic<lb/> state.<lb/></p>

			<p>Low dimensionality is generally known as a destruc-<lb/>tive factor for long-range order such as superconductivity.<lb/> Moreover, a theoretical model for high-T c cuprates <ref type="biblio">8</ref> indi-<lb/>cates that T c enhancement is caused not only by strong<lb/> in-plane correlation but also by increase of interlayer cou-<lb/>pling. This suggests that a strongly 2D electronic state,<lb/> i.e. weak interlayer coupling, should weaken high-T c su-<lb/>perconductivity. In this paper, we explore how the two-<lb/>dimensionality in the electronic state is reflected in T c .<lb/></p>

			<p>Pressure, P , experiments on high-T c cuprates have re-<lb/>ceived much attention as a technique which can control<lb/> the two-dimensionality or the lattice parameters which<lb/> govern T c . In many high-T c cuprates, however, it is diffi-<lb/>cult to clarify the effect of the interlayer hopping transfer<lb/> t c on T c , because T c is usually governed by a change of<lb/> carrier concentration caused by applying P . <ref type="biblio">9</ref> In contrast,<lb/> La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 (LSCO) is a suitable system to investi-<lb/>gate this question because the carrier number depends<lb/> only weakly on P . <ref type="biblio">10,11</ref> In LSCO, indeed, the P depen-<lb/>dence of ρ c , which is much stronger than that of the in-<lb/>plane resistivity ρ ab , is interpreted in terms of a change<lb/> of interlayer distance. <ref type="biblio">7</ref> In this work, we have investigated<lb/> the P dependence of ρ c for LSCO in order to understand<lb/> the role of the two dimensionality in the superconductiv-<lb/>ity.<lb/></p>

			<p>The presence of a structural transition from tetrago-<lb/>nal to orthorhombic at T d prevents us from observing the<lb/> generic behavior of ρ c (T ) and T c in LSCO with x &lt; 0.2.<lb/> For instance, a change of slope is clearly observed in the<lb/> ρ c (T ) at T d . <ref type="biblio">12</ref> Moreover, T c in LSCO is suppressed by the<lb/> orthorhombicity. <ref type="biblio">13</ref> It has been reported that T d in LSCO<lb/> can be suppressed by applying high P . <ref type="biblio">14,15</ref> Therefore, we<lb/> have focused on a high-P experiment on LSCO to deter-<lb/>mine the relationship between ρ c (T ) and T c regardless of<lb/> the influence of the structural transition.<lb/></p>

			<p>According to uniaxial P <ref type="biblio">16</ref> and ultrasonic 17 measure-<lb/>ments on high T c cuprates, the P dependence of T c is<lb/> characterized by strong anisotropy. For LSCO, not only<lb/> the absolute value but also the sign of dT c /dP depends<lb/> strongly on the direction of the applied P regardless of<lb/> a change of carrier concentration (dT c /dP ab &gt; 0 and<lb/> dT c /dP c &lt; 0). <ref type="biblio">18</ref> Thus, it is necessary to clarify the uni-<lb/>axial P dependence of T c because the effect of hydrostatic<lb/> P is given by the sum of the uniaxial P coefficients for<lb/> each axis (dT c /dP = 2 × dT c /dP ab + dT c /dP c ).<lb/></p>

			<p>Our P -experiments were performed by using a cubic-<lb/>anvil device <ref type="biblio">19</ref> with a mixture of Fluorinert FC70 and<lb/> FC77 as P -transmitting medium. The samples were put<lb/> into a cylindrical Teflon cell with an inner space of 1.5<lb/> mm diameter and 1.5 mm length, and the current was<lb/> applied parallel to the cylindrical axis of the cell. Vit-<lb/>rification of the fluid medium at low T often causes a<lb/> slight deviation from hydrostaticity, though the applied<lb/> P is completely hydrostatic while the P -medium remains<lb/> fluid. Pressure applied to the anvil unit was held con-<lb/>stant within 3% during T sweeps. In this system, quasi-<lb/>hydrostatic P can be generated by isotropic movement of<lb/> six anvil tops even after the fluid medium vitrifies at low<lb/> T and high P . The key feature of our measurement is<lb/> that, in our cubic anvil device, the hydrostaticity strongly<lb/> depends on the sample shape and size because of a differ-<lb/>ence in the compressibility between the sample and the<lb/> vitrified mixture.<lb/></p>

			<p>Non-hydrostatic P is generally a hindrance in under-<lb/>standing the P dependence of T c . However, if we can<lb/> determine the anisotropy of the applied P , it is possible<lb/> to determine the intrinsic behavior of T c even when P is<lb/> high enough suppress the structural change. In spite of<lb/> the deviation from hydrostaticity, P dependence of T c is<lb/> given by<lb/></p>

				<formula>T c (P ) = T c (0) + 2P ab<lb/> dT c<lb/> dP ab<lb/> + P c<lb/> dT c<lb/> dP c<lb/></formula>

				<label>(1)<lb/></label>

			<p>Moreover, the uniaxial P derivatives have been reported<lb/> for the zero P limit. <ref type="biblio">17</ref> Therefore, we can determine the<lb/> anisotropy in the P acting on the sample by comparing<lb/> the observed T c (P ) with dT c /dP ab and dT c /dP c .<lb/> Single crystals of LSCO were grown by a traveling-<lb/>solvent floating-zone method. The Sr concentrations<lb/> used in this work are x = 0.1 and 0.15, as determined<lb/> by electron-probe micro-analysis. Out-of-plane resistiv-<lb/>ity was measured by a four-probe method under P up to<lb/> 8 GPa for a &quot;stick&quot; shaped sample with dimensions of<lb/> L 110 × L 110 × L 001 = 0.2 × 0.25 × 0.73 mm 3 (x=0.1) and<lb/> &quot;plate&quot; shaped samples with dimensions 0.4 × 0.4 × 0.06<lb/> mm 3 (x=0.1) and 0.45 × 0.45 × 0.06 mm 3 (x=0.15). The<lb/> electrodes were made of gold paste with a post-heat-<lb/>treatment. We verified that the applied P did not dam-<lb/>age the sample by checking that the ρ c (T ) curves un-<lb/>der the ambient P before and after the P measurement<lb/> agreed well with each other.<lb/></p>

			<p>For stick shaped LSCO with x=0.1, we measured the<lb/> P and T dependence of ρ c . Some interesting features<lb/> were found in the P dependence of the ρ c (T ) curve in<lb/> the vicinity of T c as is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>, while ρ c at 300K<lb/> monotonically decreases with P as shown in the inset.<lb/> By applying P ≤ 3 GPa, the maximum value of ρ c (T )<lb/> just above T c is drastically reduced, though T c changes<lb/> weakly. On the other hand, by applying P ≥ 3 GPa<lb/> the maximum value of ρ c (T ) is almost constant though<lb/> T c is strongly suppressed. The feature at around 3GPa<lb/> is probably due to the structural change from the or-<lb/>thorhombic to the tetragonal phase. According to the<lb/> reported P measurements, <ref type="biblio">14,15</ref> the observed T d ∼ 270K<lb/> can be suppressed by P ≥ 3 GPa. Indeed, a change in<lb/> the slope of the ρ c (T ) curve, which is clear at around<lb/> T d ∼ 270K under ambient P , is completely suppressed<lb/> by applying P ≥ 3 GPa. Therefore, we focus on measure-<lb/>ments of ρ c (T ) under P ≥ 3GPa in order to address the<lb/> intrinsic variation of ρ c and T c independent of the struc-<lb/>tural transitions. Incidentally, we note that a deviation<lb/> from hydrostaticity is not so large in this measurement<lb/> judging from the observed P dependence of T d .<lb/></p>

			<p>For the plate shaped LSCO sample with x = 0.1 and<lb/> 0.15, the P and T dependence of ρ c was also measured. P<lb/> dependence of ρ c (T ) for the plate sample with x=0.15 is<lb/> representatively shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The P dependence for<lb/> the plate sample is different from that for the stick sam-<lb/>ple. In particular, increasing ρ c is induced by applying<lb/> P ≥ 0.8 GPa at 297K as shown in the inset. Moreover,<lb/> the P dependence of the interlayer distance is sensitively<lb/> reflected in ρ c in LSCO; <ref type="biblio">7,20</ref> namely, ρ c (P ) can be re-<lb/>garded as a strain gauge along the c axis. Therefore, we<lb/> deduce that the c axis is stretched by applying P in this<lb/> measurement. These results obviously indicate that the<lb/> stress on the plate sample is strongly anisotropic.<lb/></p>

			<p>We can infer the reason why the stress on the plate<lb/> sample is strongly anisotropic even though the sample is<lb/> not in direct contact with the Teflon cell. It is empirically<lb/> known that the Fluorinert mixture is jelled by applying<lb/> P ≥ 1 GPa at around 300K. The jelled mixture, which<lb/> has a much larger compressibility than the sample, acts<lb/> as a cushion. Hence, quasi-hydrostatic conditions would<lb/> be achieved if the sample were embedded in a large vol-<lb/>ume of mixture. However, a deviation from hydrostatic<lb/> P is likely caused by the strongly anisotropic distribu-<lb/>tion of the jelled mixture, though the displacement of six<lb/> anvil-tops was isotropic. In the P cell, the c axis of the<lb/> plate sample was arranged parallel to the cylindrical axis<lb/> of the cell. Comparing the sample size with the inner di-<lb/>ameter of the cell, we can see that the clearance between<lb/> the inner wall of the cell and the sample is much narrower<lb/> than the space along the c-axis direction. Pressure trans-<lb/>mission is strongly anisotropic because the jelled mixture<lb/> shows poor fluidity and the cell geometry is anisotropic.<lb/> In the plate sample measurement, the in-plane compres-<lb/>sion must be much stronger than the interlayer one; thus,<lb/> the c-axis stretch is caused by a large contribution from<lb/> Poisson&apos;s ratio.<lb/></p>

			<p>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> provides a plot of T c determined by zero re-<lb/>sistivity against P for the stick shaped sample (x = 0.1)<lb/> and plate ones (x=0.1 and 0.15). Both the stick and<lb/> plate sample with x = 0.1 show a change of slopes in<lb/> T c (P ) at around P d ∼ 3 GPa. Then, T c changes linearly<lb/> with P in the orthorhombic phase. We found a signifi-<lb/>cant difference between P -dependence of T c for the stick<lb/> and plate samples. For the stick sample, T c decreases at<lb/> a rate of dT c /dP ∼ −0.8K/GPa for P ≤ 3 GPa, and T c<lb/> for P ≥ 3 GPa is more strongly suppressed with a rate<lb/> of dT c /dP ∼ −3K/GPa. By contrast, T c for the plate<lb/> sample increases with a rate of dT c /dP ∼ +3 K/GPa for<lb/> P ≤ 3 GPa and dT c /dP ∼ +0.6 K/GPa under P ≥ 3<lb/> GPa. The plate sample with x = 0.15 shows T c enhance-<lb/>ment from 38 K at ambient P to 51.6 K at 8 GPa with<lb/> a rate of dT c /dP ∼ +5 K/GPa under P ≤ 1.5 GPa and<lb/> dT c /dP ∼ +1.5 K/GPa for P ≥ 1.5 GPa. The maximum<lb/> T c = 51.6K is the highest recorded so far for LSCO.<lb/></p>

			<p>We have attempted to quantify the non-hydrostaticity<lb/> at low T in order to clarify these results. It is reported<lb/> that the uniaxial-P derivatives obtained at around am-<lb/>bient P are dT c /dP ab = +3.2 K/GPa and dT c /dP c =<lb/> −6.6 K/GPa for x = 0.1. <ref type="biblio">17</ref> Comparing these uniaxial-P<lb/> derivatives with the observed dT c /dP in the orthorhom-<lb/>bic phase, we estimated the anisotropy of applied P on<lb/> the stick and plate samples using Eq. <ref type="formula">(1)</ref>. In the mea-<lb/>surement for the stick sample with x=0.1, we obtained<lb/> the anisotropic P ratio to be P c /P ab ∼1.1. By contrast,<lb/> the P c /P ab values for the plate samples with x=0.1<lb/> and 0.15 are about 0.6 and 0.5, respectively. Thus, the<lb/> above-mentioned inference is probably confirmed by this<lb/> estimation. Incidentally, the c-axis stretch for the plate<lb/> samples is also indicated by comparing P c /P ab with<lb/> compressibility <ref type="biblio">21</ref> and Poisson&apos;s ratio, <ref type="biblio">22</ref> as is indicated<lb/> by increasing ρ c .<lb/></p>

			<p>Next, we consider the intrinsic P dependence of T c<lb/> in the tetragonal phase. Assuming that the anisotropic<lb/> P ratio in the orthorhombic phase is retained in the<lb/> P -induced tetragonal one, we estimated the uniaxial-P<lb/> derivatives in the tetragonal phase to be dT c /dP c =<lb/> −8 ± 1 K/GPa and dT c /dP ab = +3 ± 0.5K/GPa from<lb/> Eq.<ref type="formula">(1)</ref>. Equally, we obtained the uniaxial-P derivatives<lb/> for x = 0.15 to be dT c /dP c = −9 ± 1 K/GPa and<lb/> dT c /dP ab = +3.5 ± 0.5K/GPa utilizing the previously<lb/> reported P dependence of T c . <ref type="biblio">7</ref> Though dT c /dP ab re-<lb/>mains nearly constant regardless of the structural change,<lb/> dT c /dP c in the tetragonal phase is much stronger than<lb/> that in the orthorhombic phase. Incidentally, from a<lb/> sum of these uniaxial P derivatives we obtained a hy-<lb/>drostatic P derivative in the P -induced tetragonal phase<lb/> to be dT c /dP ∼ −1K/GPa for optimal doping. This esti-<lb/>mation agrees well with the reported value of dT c /dP =<lb/> −1K/GPa for polycrystalline LSCO with x=0.15 under<lb/> hydrostatic P up to 8GPa. <ref type="biblio">24</ref> Therefore, it is a reasonable<lb/> assumption that the anisotropic P ratio is retained in the<lb/> high-P range.<lb/></p>

			<p>What we are mainly interested in now is why the ab-<lb/>solute value of dT c /dP c is much stronger than that of<lb/> dT c /dP ab . In the tetragonal phase, the enhancement of<lb/> T c due to interlayer expansion is about 2.6 times stronger<lb/> than that due to in-plane compression. Naturally, the<lb/> dT c /dP ab value is too small to account for the observed<lb/> P dependence of T c . As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>, the variations<lb/> of T c obtained for both stick and plate shaped samples<lb/> could be scaled linearly with ρ c at 297K. Additionally,<lb/> the P dependence of ρ c can be expressed as a function of<lb/> the lattice parameter c. <ref type="biblio">7,20</ref> Therefore, T c is much more<lb/> strongly reflected in the interlayer distance than the in-<lb/>plane one. Thus, a change of T c is mainly interpreted in<lb/> terms of the interlayer coupling as monitored in ρ c .<lb/></p>

			<p>Incidentally, ρ c is given by ρ c ∼ [N |t c | 2 τ ] −1 , where N<lb/> is carrier number, and τ is lifetime in the plane. <ref type="biblio">4</ref> In gen-<lb/>eral, P dependence of N and τ is reflected in those of the<lb/> residual resistivity and the slope of ρ ab (T ), respectively. <ref type="biblio">25<lb/></ref> Recently, we have reported that anisotropic pressure does<lb/> not change ρ ab below about 60 K. <ref type="biblio">13,20</ref> Moreover, weak P<lb/> dependence of N has been reported. <ref type="biblio">10,11</ref> Therefore, we<lb/> deduce that τ and N for LSCO are almost independent of<lb/> P at low T ; thus P dependence of ρ c for LSCO is mainly<lb/> governed by that of t c .<lb/></p>

			<p>As a clue to understanding the relation between T c and<lb/> interlayer coupling t c , we focus on the low-T behavior of<lb/> ρ c in the tetragonal phase when the c-axis compression is<lb/> stronger than the in-plane one. Although the P reduces<lb/> ρ c values over the whole T range, the peak value of ρ c (T )<lb/> just above T c is almost independent of P as shown in Fig.<lb/> <ref type="figure">1</ref>. This observation suggests that superconductivity oc-<lb/>curs when t c reaches some critical value. Thus, higher T c<lb/> values can be expected in the system which has strongly<lb/> suppressed t c .<lb/></p>

			<p>We infer why a strongly 2D electronic state is an advan-<lb/>tageous factor for the superconductivity in LSCO against<lb/> the expectations from the theoretical model. <ref type="biblio">8</ref> T depen-<lb/>dence of ρ c and ρ ab indicate that the interlayer coupling<lb/> is suppressed with decreasing T . It seems that the per-<lb/>fectly 2D metal expected from the spin-charge separation<lb/> model is achieved at absolute zero Kelvin when super-<lb/>conductivity is absent. However, it is believed that the<lb/> perfectly 2D metal is unstable at low T . Moreover, it<lb/> has been reported that not only ρ c but also ρ ab shows<lb/> a logarithmic upturn when T c is suppressed by a large<lb/> magnetic field. <ref type="biblio">5</ref> Therefore, superconductivity or a 3D lo-<lb/>calized electronic state is likely required at low T in order<lb/> to depress the instability. Thus, enhancing the instabil-<lb/>ity, which is caused by the c-axis expansion, increases<lb/> T c .<lb/></p>

			<p>In conclusion, we have demonstrated that strong 2D<lb/> structure of the electronic state as is monitored in ρ c is a<lb/> key parameter for high-T c superconductivity, though low<lb/> dimensionality is generally known as a destructive fac-<lb/>tor for conventional superconductivity. The remarkable<lb/> thing is that T c is strongly reflected in interlayer distance<lb/> rather than in-plane one. Indeed, the enhancement of T c<lb/> in LSCO, which reaches 51.6 K at 8 GPa, is mainly inter-<lb/>preted in terms of interlayer expansion, which enhances<lb/> two dimensionality. Therefore, we expect that measure-<lb/>ment under anisotropy controlled pressures causes much<lb/> higher T c than previously reported values for many high-<lb/>T c materials.<lb/></p>

			<figure>0<lb/> 20<lb/> 40<lb/> 0.5<lb/> 1.0<lb/> stick<lb/> 6.5GPa<lb/> 0.1MPa<lb/> 1.5GPa<lb/> 3.0GPa<lb/> 5.0GPa<lb/> 8.0GPa<lb/> ρ<lb/> c (Ω cm)<lb/> Temperature (K)<lb/> 0<lb/> 2<lb/> 4<lb/> 6<lb/> 8<lb/> 0.2<lb/> 0.3<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 300 K<lb/> ρ<lb/> c (Ω cm)<lb/> P (GPa)<lb/> FIG. 1. ρc(T ) curves measured for stick shaped LSCO<lb/> sample with x=0.1 below 55K under P up to 8 GPa. The<lb/> inset shows P dependence of ρc at 300K. The sample shape<lb/> and the configurations of the electrodes are shown.<lb/> 0 2 4 6 8<lb/> 85<lb/> 90<lb/> 95<lb/> T=297K<lb/> ρ<lb/> c<lb/> (mΩcm)<lb/> P (GPa)<lb/> 0<lb/> 20<lb/> 40<lb/> 60<lb/> 80<lb/> 20<lb/> 40<lb/> 60<lb/> 80<lb/> 100<lb/> plate<lb/> x=0.15<lb/> 8.0GPa<lb/> 6.5GPa<lb/> 5.0GPa<lb/> 3.0GPa<lb/> 1.5GPa<lb/> 0.8GPa<lb/> 0.1MPa<lb/> ρ<lb/> c<lb/> (mΩcm)<lb/> Temperature(K)<lb/> FIG. 2. ρc(T ) curves measured for the plate shaped LSCO<lb/> sample with x=0.15 under P up to 8 GPa. The inset shows P<lb/> dependence of ρc at 297K. Also shown is a schematic represen-<lb/>tation of the electrodes attached to the plate shaped crystals.<lb/> 0<lb/> 2<lb/> 4<lb/> 6<lb/> 8<lb/> 10<lb/> 20<lb/> 30<lb/> 40<lb/> 50<lb/> stick<lb/> plate<lb/> plate<lb/> P d<lb/> P d<lb/> La 2-x Sr x CuO 4<lb/> x=0.15<lb/> x=0.1<lb/> T<lb/> c (K)<lb/> Pressure (GPa)<lb/> FIG. 3. Tc for stick and plate shaped samples against P .<lb/> Solid line is a guide to the eye. Meshed marks indicate the<lb/> structural transition pressure P d estimated from the changes<lb/> in ρc(T ) and the reported T d (P ) (Ref. 14,15).<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.6<lb/> 0.8<lb/> 1.0<lb/> 1.2<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.5<lb/> 1.0<lb/> 1.5<lb/> x=0.15<lb/> x=0.1<lb/> La 2-x Sr x CuO 4<lb/> T<lb/> c<lb/> (P)/T<lb/> c<lb/> (0.1MPa)<lb/> ρ c (P)/ρ c (0.1MPa)<lb/> FIG. 4. The variation of Tc(P )/Tc(0.1MPa) in the tetrag-<lb/>onal phase plotted as a function of ρc(P )/ρc(0.1MPa) at<lb/> 297K. Circles and triangles indicate Tc for plate and stick<lb/> shaped samples, respectively. Tc for the stick LSCO with op-<lb/>timal doping (closed triangle) is obtained from Ref. [7,13].</figure>


	</text>
</tei>
