<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>1 Introduction<lb/></head>

			<p>Diabetes mellitus (DM) represents a heterogeneous<lb/> group of metabolic disorders characterized by chronic<lb/> hyperglycemia, clinically categorized as type 1 (T1D) and<lb/> type 2 (T2D), specific types of diabetes and gestational<lb/> diabetes <ref type="biblio">[1]</ref>. Among these, T2D, the most common type,<lb/> is characterized by a progressive loss of insulin secre-<lb/>tion heterogeneity in pancreatic β-cells, typically fol-<lb/>lowing the development of insulin resistance <ref type="biblio">[2]</ref>. There<lb/> is no definitive cure for T2D, but its progression can be<lb/> effectively managed through a combination of lifestyle<lb/> modifications and pharmacological interventions <ref type="biblio">[3]</ref>.<lb/> Current therapeutic strategies primarily involve the use<lb/> of insulin and its analogs, biguanides (e.g., metformin),<lb/> sodium-glucose cotransporter 2 (SGLT2) inhibitors,<lb/> α-glucosidase inhibitors (AGIs), glucagon-like peptide-1<lb/> (GLP-1) receptor agonists, and dipeptidyl peptidase 4<lb/> (DPP-4) inhibitors <ref type="biblio">[2]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>α-Glucosidase is a key enzyme in carbohydrate metab-<lb/>olism responsible for catalyzing the final step of dietary<lb/> carbohydrate digestion <ref type="biblio">[3]</ref>. The therapeutic potential of<lb/> AGIs in diabetes management has been well established,<lb/> particularly for controlling postprandial hyperglycemia<lb/> and preventing associated complications in T2D patients<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[4]</ref>. However, the commonly used AGIs at present are<lb/> frequently associated with gastrointestinal adverse<lb/> effects such as diarrhea, bloating, and nausea, which sig-<lb/>nificantly hinder their clinical utilization and widespread<lb/> adoption <ref type="biblio">[5]</ref>. These limitations underscore the critical<lb/> need for developing novel AGIs with improved safety<lb/> profiles and enhanced therapeutic efficacy.<lb/></p>

			<p>Ottelia acuminata var. acuminata, a perennial herba-<lb/>ceous species of the Ottelia genus in the Hydrocharita-<lb/>ceae family, is predominantly distributed in the provinces<lb/> of Guangdong, Guangxi, Guizhou, and Yunnan <ref type="biblio">[6]</ref>. In<lb/> the traditional Chinese medicine system, this species has<lb/> been widely employed for the treatment of constipation,<lb/> bronchitis, and arteriosclerosis <ref type="biblio">[7]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Previous phytochemical investigations of this plant<lb/> have revealed the presence of diverse chemical constitu-<lb/>ents including diarylheptanoids, lignans, coumarins,<lb/> flavonoids, and sesquiterpenes <ref type="biblio">[8]</ref>. Notably, diarylhep-<lb/>tanoids exhibited significant hypoglycemic potential<lb/> by inhibiting α-glucosidase <ref type="biblio">[8]</ref>. As part of our ongoing<lb/> research to discover hypoglycemic lead compounds,<lb/> five pairs of enantiomeric diarylheptanoids, one unde-<lb/>scribed diarylheptanoid glycoside, and one new lignan<lb/> were isolated from O. acuminata (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>). In this study,<lb/> compounds 1-5 were identified as racemates and the<lb/> absolute configurations of 1-4 were determined by<lb/> combination of NMR, ECD spectroscopy, and X-ray dif-<lb/>fraction analysis. In addition, compounds 1, 2, 4, 6, and<lb/> 7 were evaluated for their inhibitory activities against<lb/> α-glucosidase and protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B<lb/> (PTP1B). Among these, compound 1 exhibited notable<lb/> α-glucosidase inhibitory activity, with an inhibition ratio<lb/> of 38.97% (acarbose as the positive control, inhibition<lb/> ratio = 13.52%).<lb/></p>

			<head>2 Result and discussion<lb/></head>

			<p>Otteacumiene G (1), isolated as colorless crystals, was<lb/> assigned the molecular formula of C 19 H 20 O 4 by the<lb/> HRESIMS at m/z 311.1287 [M -H] -(calculated for<lb/></p>

			<figure>HO<lb/> OH<lb/> OH<lb/> O<lb/> (±)-1<lb/> 1<lb/> 2<lb/> 4<lb/> 7 8<lb/> 9<lb/> 10<lb/> 11<lb/> 12<lb/> 13<lb/> 1&apos;<lb/> 2&apos;<lb/> 3&apos;<lb/> HO<lb/> OH<lb/> OH<lb/> O<lb/> (±)-2<lb/> O<lb/> O<lb/> OH<lb/> O<lb/> OH<lb/> HO<lb/> HO<lb/> OH<lb/> 6<lb/> O<lb/> O<lb/> O<lb/> MeO<lb/> OMe<lb/> OMe<lb/> O<lb/> 1<lb/> 3<lb/> 4<lb/> 7<lb/> 8<lb/> 9<lb/> 9&apos;<lb/> 8&apos;<lb/> 7&apos;<lb/> 1&apos;<lb/> 4&apos;<lb/> 7<lb/> 1&apos;&apos;<lb/> 6&apos;&apos;<lb/> OH<lb/> OH<lb/> O<lb/> (±)-3<lb/> OH<lb/> 8<lb/> 11<lb/> OH<lb/> OH<lb/> O<lb/> (±)-4<lb/> OH<lb/> 8<lb/> 1&apos;<lb/> 2&apos;<lb/> 3&apos;<lb/> OH<lb/> OH<lb/> H<lb/> OH<lb/> (±)-5<lb/> 12<lb/> 9<lb/> 3<lb/> 1 2<lb/> 10<lb/> 11<lb/> 3<lb/> 5<lb/> 6<lb/> 4&apos;<lb/> 5&apos;<lb/> 6&apos;<lb/> 9<lb/> 10<lb/> 11<lb/> 12<lb/> 6&apos;<lb/> 5&apos;<lb/> 4<lb/> 5<lb/> 6<lb/> 7<lb/> 8<lb/> 13<lb/> Fig.1 The chemical structures of compounds 1-7<lb/></figure>

			<p>311.1289), suggesting ten degrees of unsaturation. The<lb/> IR spectrum showed a broad hydroxyl absorption band<lb/> at 3426 cm -1 and aromatic ring absorption band at 1613,<lb/> 1596, 1516, 1502 cm -1 . The 13 C NMR (DEPT) spectra<lb/> (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>) exhibited 19 carbon signals, including two ben-<lb/>zene rings (δ C 146.6, C-1; 151.3, C-2; 118.4, C-3; 134.5,<lb/> C-4; 120.7, C-5; 117.0, C-6 and 158.0, C-1′; 123.7, C-2′;<lb/> 133.5, C-3′; 140.7, C-4′; 131.3, C-5′; 124.8, C-6′) and an<lb/> oxygenated unsaturated heptane (δ C 76.3, C-7; 76.9,<lb/> C-8; 36.3, C-9; 128.9, C-10; 132.0, C-11; 37.1, C-12; 35.9,<lb/> C-13). The key HMBC correlations from H-7 to C-3/C-<lb/>4/C-5 and H 2 -13 to C-3′/C-4′/C-5′ suggested 1 was a<lb/> diarylheptanoid derivative. By combining HRESIMS and<lb/> comparing NMR (Tables <ref type="table">1 and 2</ref>), compound 1 was iden-<lb/>tified to share the same diarylether-type cyclic diarylhep-<lb/>tanoid skeleton as the known otteacumiene C <ref type="biblio">[7]</ref>, with<lb/> only variation occurring in the heptane chain, a hydroxyl<lb/> group at C-7 (δ C 76.3). Furthermore, this deduction was<lb/> confirmed by key 1 H-1 H COSY correlations of H-7 (δ H<lb/> 4.33, d, J = 6.8 Hz)/H-8 (δ H 3.34, m)/H 2 -9/H-10 (δ H 4.84,<lb/> overlapped)/H-11 (δ H 5.15, dt, J = 15.3, 6.1 Hz) /H 2 -12/<lb/> H 2 -13 (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). Besides, the 1 H NMR signals at δ H 4.84<lb/> (H-10) and δ H 5.15 (H-11) also suggested the existence of<lb/> a trans double bond <ref type="biblio">[9]</ref>. Consequently, the planar struc-<lb/>ture of 1 as a diarylether-type cyclic diarylheptanoid was<lb/> unequivocally determined.<lb/> </p>
				
			<p>The cotton effects were not observed in the ECD<lb/> spectrum of 1 and it was separated into two peaks by<lb/> chiral-phase column (Fig. <ref type="figure">S1</ref>). Thus, 1 was a racemic<lb/> mixture <ref type="biblio">[10]</ref>. Fortunately, the crystals of 1 (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>) were<lb/> obtained, which showed the relative configuration of 1.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 1 1 H NMR data of compounds 1-5 in CD 3 OD<lb/> δ in ppm, J in Hz, and obtained at 600 MHz<lb/> No.<lb/> 1<lb/> 2<lb/> 3<lb/> 4<lb/> 5<lb/> 3<lb/> 5.61, d (1.7)<lb/> 5.63, d, (1.4)<lb/> 5.66, d (1.8)<lb/> 5.65, d (2.0)<lb/> 5<lb/> 6.82, dd (8.2, 1.7)<lb/> 6.84, dd (8.2, 1.4)<lb/> 6.55, dd (8.1, 1.8)<lb/> 6.54, dd (8.2, 2.0)<lb/> 7.06, d (8.0)<lb/> 6<lb/> 6.79, d (8.2)<lb/> 6.80, d (8.2)<lb/> 6.69, d (8.1)<lb/> 6.71, d (8.2)<lb/> 6.72, d (8.0)<lb/> 7a<lb/> 4.33, d (6.8)<lb/> 4.49, d (2.5)<lb/> 2.71, dd (13.8, 3.1)<lb/> 2.66, dd (15.2, 8.4)<lb/> 2.86, m<lb/> 7b<lb/> 2.44, dd (13.8, 9.5)<lb/> 2.53, dd (15.2, 2.0)<lb/> 2.72, m<lb/> 8a<lb/> 3.34, m<lb/> 3.64, m<lb/> 3.99, m<lb/> 3.82, td (8.2, 2.1)<lb/> 2.22, m<lb/> 8b<lb/> 1.98, m<lb/> 9a<lb/> 1.98, m<lb/> 1.98, m<lb/> 5.16, dd (15.8, 4.7)<lb/> 5.26, dd (15.4, 8.2)<lb/> 3.35, m<lb/> 9b<lb/> 1.72, d (15.8)<lb/> 1.68, m<lb/> 10<lb/> 4.84, overlapped<lb/> 4.78, dt (15.3, 5.7)<lb/> 5.51, dd (15.8, 7.2)<lb/> 5.32, dd (15.4, 8.2)<lb/> 4.06, dd (17.1, 7.1)<lb/> 11<lb/> 5.15, dt (15.3, 6.1)<lb/> 5.15, dt (15.3, 7.5)<lb/> 4.04, m<lb/> 3.93, td (7.4, 1.7)<lb/> 5.36, dd (17.1, 7.6)<lb/> 12a<lb/> 2.08, m<lb/> 2.41, m<lb/> 2.05, m<lb/> 2.03, m<lb/> 3.81, m<lb/> 12b<lb/> 2.39, m<lb/> 2.06, m<lb/> 1.74, m<lb/> 1.93, m<lb/> 13a<lb/> 2.88, dt (12.6, 5.0)<lb/> 2.90, m<lb/> 2.65, m<lb/> 2.68, m<lb/> 2.49, t (12.4)<lb/> 13b<lb/> 2.66, m<lb/> 2.66, m<lb/> 2.99, dt (13.3, 4.4)<lb/> 3.04, dt (13.6, 4.1)<lb/> 3.10, dd (12.4, 5.0)<lb/> 2′<lb/> 6.83, dd (8.3, 2.3)<lb/> 6.85, dd (8.3, 2.3)<lb/> 6.95, dd (8.3, 2.5)<lb/> 6.94, dd (8.2, 2.5)<lb/> 3′<lb/> 6.98, dd (8.3, 1.9)<lb/> 7.00, dd (8.3, 1.8)<lb/> 7.31, dd (8.3, 1.9)<lb/> 7.25, dd (8.2, 2.0)<lb/> 6.38, d (2.0)<lb/> 5′<lb/> 7.14, dd (8.3, 1.9)<lb/> 7.15, dd (8.3, 1.8)<lb/> 7.32, dd (8.3, 1.9)<lb/> 7.35, dd (8.2, 2.0)<lb/> 7.02, dd (8.0, 2.0)<lb/> 6′<lb/> 7.09, dd (8.3, 2.3)<lb/> 7.09, dd (8.3, 2.3)<lb/> 7.09, dd (8.3, 2.5)<lb/> 7.00, dd (8.2, 2.5)<lb/> 6.78, d (8.0)<lb/> </figure>
				
			<figure type="table">Table 2 13 C NMR and DEPT data of compounds 1-5 in CD 3 OD<lb/> δ in ppm and obtained at 150 MHz<lb/> No.<lb/> 1<lb/> 2<lb/> 3<lb/> 4<lb/> 5<lb/> 1<lb/> 146.6, s<lb/> 146.4, s<lb/> 145.3, s<lb/> 145.2, s<lb/> 153.7, s<lb/> 2<lb/> 151.3, s<lb/> 150.9, s<lb/> 151.0, s<lb/> 151.1, s<lb/> 125.3, s<lb/> 3<lb/> 118.4, d<lb/> 117.8, d<lb/> 118.7, d<lb/> 117.2, d<lb/> 149.9, s<lb/> 4<lb/> 134.5, s<lb/> 133.0, s<lb/> 130.2, s<lb/> 130.7, s<lb/> 137.0, s<lb/> 5<lb/> 120.7, d<lb/> 122.4, d<lb/> 123.8, d<lb/> 123.8, d<lb/> 125.5, d<lb/> 6<lb/> 117.0, d<lb/> 117.0, d<lb/> 116.7, d<lb/> 116.9, d<lb/> 114.3, d<lb/> 7<lb/> 76.3, d<lb/> 76.3, d<lb/> 43.5, t<lb/> 42.7, t<lb/> 31.4, t<lb/> 8<lb/> 76.9, d<lb/> 75.0, d<lb/> 72.3, d<lb/> 74.0, d<lb/> 32.4, t<lb/> 9<lb/> 36.3, t<lb/> 36.1, t<lb/> 134.7, d<lb/> 137.1, d<lb/> 48.7, d<lb/> 10<lb/> 128.9, d<lb/> 129.6, d<lb/> 134.9, d<lb/> 139.4, d<lb/> 137.3, d<lb/> 11<lb/> 132.0, d<lb/> 131.6, d<lb/> 72.4, d<lb/> 73.1, d<lb/> 129.2, d<lb/> 12<lb/> 37.1, t<lb/> 36.8, t<lb/> 41.5, t<lb/> 40.9, t<lb/> 79.9, d<lb/> 13<lb/> 35.9, t<lb/> 35.8, t<lb/> 33.5, t<lb/> 34.0, t<lb/> 47.0, t<lb/> 1′<lb/> 158.0, s<lb/> 157.4, s<lb/> 157.0, s<lb/> 156.7, s<lb/> 154.9, s<lb/> 2′<lb/> 123.7, d<lb/> 123.5, d<lb/> 123.5, d<lb/> 124.4, d<lb/> 120.8, s<lb/> 3′<lb/> 133.5, d<lb/> 133.9, d<lb/> 132.4, d<lb/> 132.3, d<lb/> 145.9, d<lb/> 4′<lb/> 140.7, s<lb/> 140.7, s<lb/> 141.1, s<lb/> 140.2, s<lb/> 129.4, s<lb/> 5′<lb/> 131.3, d<lb/> 131.2, d<lb/> 131.4, d<lb/> 131.5, d<lb/> 129.6, d<lb/> 6′<lb/> 124.8, d<lb/> 124.8, d<lb/> 125.9, d<lb/> 125.1 d<lb/> 115.9, d<lb/></figure>

			<p>Following the chiral resolution of this compound, the<lb/> absolute configurations of the resultant (+)-1 and (-)-1<lb/> enantiomers were unequivocally established via quantum<lb/> chemical calculation. The results demonstrated that the<lb/> calculated ECD spectra of the enantiomeric pair exhib-<lb/>ited excellent agreement with the experimental data,<lb/> allowing unambiguous assignment of the absolute con-<lb/>figurations as 7S,8S for (+)-1 and 7R,8R for (-)-1 (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).<lb/> </p>
				
			<p>Otteacumiene H (2), isolated as colorless crystals, had<lb/> its molecular formula C 19 H 20 O 4 , which was evidenced<lb/> by the HRESIMS at m/z 311.1287 [M -H] -(calculated<lb/> for 311.1289). Compound 2 shared the same planar<lb/> structure as 1, as established by the detailed 1 H-1 H COSY<lb/> and HMBC correlations (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). The trans-configura-<lb/>tion of the double bond was confirmed by the coupling<lb/> constant of the olefinic proton δ H 5.15 (1H, dt, J = 15.3,<lb/> 7.5 Hz, H-11). Comparative analysis of the 1 H and 13 C<lb/> NMR data (Tables <ref type="table">1 and 2</ref>) revealed a key difference at<lb/> the chiral center C-8 (δ H 3.64, m, δ C 75.0 in 2; δ H 3.34,<lb/> m, δ C 76.9 in 1), suggesting that 2 was a stereoisomer of<lb/> 1. As the vicinal dihydroxyl groups in compound 1 adopt<lb/> a trans configuration, the corresponding groups in com-<lb/>pound 2 were cis-configured. With only two chiral cent-<lb/>ers (C-7 and C-8) in this planar structure, there existed<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 2 Key 1 H-1 H COSY and HMBC correlations of 1-7<lb/></figure>
				
			<figure> 1<lb/> 5<lb/> 3<lb/> Fig. 3 X-ray crystallographic structures for 1, 3 and 5<lb/></figure>

			<p>two relative configurations and two possible absolute<lb/> configurations, excluding the already established 7S,8S<lb/> and 7R,8R configurations of (+)-1 and (-)-1, respectively.<lb/> Further analysis of the ECD spectrum and chiral HPLC<lb/> data (Fig. <ref type="figure">S14</ref>) confirmed that compound 2 existed as a<lb/> racemate. Through chiral resolution followed by com-<lb/>parison of experimental and calculated ECD curves, the<lb/> absolute configurations of (+)-2 and (-)-2 were assigned<lb/> as 7S,8R and 7R,8S, respectively (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene I (3) was purified as colorless crystals.<lb/> Its molecular formula was determined as C 19 H 20 O 4 by<lb/> its HRESIMS (m/z 311.1286, [M -H] -, calculated for<lb/> 311.1289). A detailed comparison of the HRESIMS and<lb/> NMR data (Tables <ref type="table">1 and 2</ref>) of 3 with those of 1 revealed<lb/> that they were close structural analogs. The differ-<lb/>ences from 1 were the positional variations of hydroxyl<lb/> groups (δ C 72.4, C-11) and double bond (δ C 134.7, C-9;<lb/> 134.9, C-10) in 3, as confirmed by the key 1 H-1 H COSY<lb/> correlations of H 2 -7 (δ H 2.71, dd, J = 13.8, 3.1 Hz; 2.44,<lb/> dd, J = 13.8, 9.5 Hz)/H-8 (δ H 3.99, m) /H-9 (δ H 5.16, dd,<lb/> J = 15.8, 4.7 Hz)/H-10 (δ H 5.51, dd, J = 15.8, 7.2 Hz)/H-<lb/>11 (δ H 4.04, m)/H 2 -12/H 2 -13 and HMBC correlations<lb/> from H-7 to C-3 (δ C 118.7), C-4 (δ C 130.2), and C-5 (δ C<lb/> 123.8); from H 2 -13 to C-3′ (δ C 132.4), C-4′ (δ C 141.1),<lb/> and C-5′ (δ C 131.4) (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>The appearance of two peaks on chiral-phase column<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">S27</ref>) and the absence of an obvious cotton effect<lb/> in the ECD spectrum indicated that compound 3 was<lb/> a racemate. Furthermore, the relative configurations of<lb/> 3 were proposed by the result of single-crystal X-ray<lb/> diffraction (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>). After chiral separation of (±)-3, the<lb/> absolute configurations of (+)-3 and (-)-3 were deter-<lb/>mined as 8R,11S and 8S,11R by comparing the experi-<lb/>mental and calculated ECD curves (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).<lb/></p>

            <!-- Here there is a missing figure -->
			<p>Otteacumiene J (4), a racemic mixture (Fig. <ref type="figure">S40</ref>), was<lb/> purified as white powder. It had the same molecular<lb/> formula as compound 3, as deduced by HRESIMS (m/z<lb/> 311.1285, [M -H] -, calculated for 311.1289). Compara-<lb/>tive analyses of 1 H and 13 C NMR data (Tables <ref type="table">1 and 2</ref>)<lb/> between 3 and 4 revealed that 4 was an epimer of 3,<lb/> which was supported by the changes in chemical shift<lb/> of C-7 (δ C 42.7), C-8 (δ C 74.0), C-9 (δ C 137.1), C-10 (δ C<lb/> 139.4), and C-11 (δ C 73.1). The relative configurations of<lb/> 3 were proposed by the result of single-crystal X-ray dif-<lb/>fraction (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>), indicating that two hydroxyls (C-8 and<lb/> C-11) were on the opposite side. Therefore, two hydrox-<lb/>yls (C-8 and C-11) of 4 placed the co-facial orientation.<lb/> The ECD spectrum and chiral separation chromatogram<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">S40</ref>) of (±)-4 clearly demonstrated that it was a race-<lb/>mate. Compound (±)-4 was successfully separated into<lb/> (+)-4 and (-)-4 enantiomers whose absolute configura-<lb/>tions were determined as 8R,11R and 8S,11S, respectively<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene K (5), colorless needle crystals, was<lb/> deduced to have a molecular formula of C 19 H 18 O 3<lb/> according to the [M -H] -ion at m/z 293.1178 (calcd. for<lb/> C 19 H 17 O 3 , 293.1178) in negative HRESIMS, suggesting 11<lb/> degrees of unsaturation. By comparing its 1D NMR data<lb/> (Tables <ref type="table">1 and 2</ref>) with strained cyclic diarylheptanoids<lb/> tedarene B <ref type="biblio">[11]</ref>, the differences between 5 and tedarene<lb/> B were that there were hydroxyl groups attached to C-1<lb/> (δ C 153.7) on the benzene ring and to C-12 (δ C 79.9) on<lb/> the heptane chain, as proven by the key 1 H-1 H COSY<lb/> correlations of H 2 -7 (δ H 2.86, m, H-7a; m, H-7b) /<lb/> H 2 -8 (δ H 2.22, m, H-8a; 1.98, m, H-8b) /H-9 (δ H 3.35, m)<lb/> /H-10 (δ H 4.06, dd, J = 17.1, 7.1 Hz) /H-11 (δ H 5.36, dd,<lb/> J = 17.1, 7.6 Hz) /H-12 (δ H 3.81, m) /H 2 -13 (δ H 2.49, t,<lb/> J = 12.4 Hz, H-13a; 3.10, dd, J = 12.4, 5.0 Hz, H-13b) and<lb/> HMBC correlations from H-7 to C-3, C-4, and C-5; from<lb/> H 2 -13 to C-3′, C-4′, and C-5′ (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). The downfield aro-<lb/>matic quaternary carbon signals at C-2 (δ C 125.3) and<lb/> C-2′ (δ C 120.8) suggested that 5 could be a biaryl-type<lb/> cyclic diarylheptanoid derivative (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>), evidenced by<lb/> key HMBC correlations from H-3′ (δ H 6.38, d, J = 2.0 Hz)<lb/> to C-2. Combining degrees of unsaturation and analysis<lb/> of NMR (Tables <ref type="table">1 and 2</ref>), it was inferred that 5 possessed<lb/> one additional cyclic system, proved by key HMBC cor-<lb/>relations (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>) from H-9 to C-3. As a consequence, the<lb/> planar structure of 5 was unambiguously determined.<lb/> The result of single-crystal X-ray diffraction of 5 (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>)<lb/> confirmed the relative configuration and also indicated<lb/> that (±)-5 was a racemate. However, due to the limited<lb/> amount of trace samples obtained, it was unfeasible to<lb/> obtain optically pure enantiomers of (±)-5. Therefore, the<lb/> absolute configurations of (±)-5 could not be determined.<lb/></p>

			<p>Diarylheptanoids featuring a disubstituted heptane<lb/> chain, isolated from O. acuminata, were frequently<lb/> obtained as racemic mixtures. The pronounced confor-<lb/>mational flexibility of these molecules posed challenges<lb/> in definitively assigning their relative configurations<lb/> using NOESY experiments. To address this, these enan-<lb/>tiomers were subjected to chiral separation to obtain<lb/> a pair of optically pure enantiomers. Subsequently, the<lb/> absolute configurations of the enantiomers were deter-<lb/>mined through comparative analysis of experimental<lb/> and calculated ECD spectra. Otteacumienes G-K (1-5)<lb/> were identified as enantiomeric isomers. Based on struc-<lb/>tural analysis, we suppose a potential mechanism for the<lb/> formation of these enantiomers: the double bond ∆(7,8)<lb/> on the heptane chain of 1 and 2 underwent oxidative<lb/> cyclization to form a ternary oxygen ring, followed by a<lb/> ring-opening reaction that results in the generation of<lb/> enantiomers.<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene L (6) was isolated as a white powder<lb/> and its molecular formula was determined as C 25 H 28 O 8<lb/> by the HRESIMS at m/z 479.1682 [M + Na] + (calculated<lb/> for 479.1682), suggesting 12 degrees of unsaturation.<lb/> The 1 H and 13 C NMR (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) showed the presence of a<lb/> β-glucopyranosyl part (δ H 5.02, d, J = 7.9 Hz, H-1″) <ref type="biblio">[12]</ref>.<lb/> Analysis of the HRESIMS and 1D NMR data (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>)<lb/> of compound 6 indicated that the aglycone of 6 shared<lb/> identical planar structure with otteacumiene A, a known<lb/> compound previously characterized by our group <ref type="biblio">[8]</ref>,<lb/> which was confirmed by the key 1 H-1 H COSY correla-<lb/>tions of H 2 -7 (δ H 2.37, m)/H-8 (δ H 4.24, t, J = 9.8 Hz)<lb/> /H-9 (δ H 5.40, t, J = 11.5 Hz) /H-10 (δ H 5.91, t, J = 11.5 Hz)<lb/> /H-11 (δ H 5.32, dd, J = 15.3, 11.5 Hz) /H-12 (δ H 6.07, dt,<lb/> J = 15.3, 4.7 Hz) /H 2 -13 (δ H 3.52, overlapped), accompa-<lb/>nied by HMBC correlations from H-7 to C-3 (δ C 118.7),<lb/> C-4 (δ C 137.7), and C-5 (δ C 122.9); from H-13 to C-3′<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 3 1 H and 13 C NMR data of 6 in CD 3 OD<lb/> δ in ppm, J in Hz, and obtained at 600/150 MHz<lb/> No. δ H<lb/> δ C<lb/> No δ H<lb/> δ C<lb/> 1<lb/> 145.7, s 1′<lb/> 157.6, s<lb/> 2<lb/> 154.2, s 2′<lb/> 7.25, dd (8.3, 2.5)<lb/> 127.1, d<lb/> 3<lb/> 5.44, d (1.9)<lb/> 118.7, d 3′<lb/> 7.30, dd (8.3, 2.5)<lb/> 132.5, d<lb/> 4<lb/> 137.7, s 4′<lb/> 139.2, s<lb/> 5<lb/> 6.68, dd (8.2, 1.9)<lb/> 122.9, d 5′<lb/> 7.35, dd (8.3, 2.5)<lb/> 134.8, d<lb/> 6<lb/> 7.05, d (8.2)<lb/> 118.2, d 6′<lb/> 7.06, dd (8.3, 2.5)<lb/> 124.7, d<lb/> 7<lb/> 2.37, m<lb/> 46.0, t 1′′<lb/> 5.02, d (7.9)<lb/> 103.3, d<lb/> 8<lb/> 4.24, t (9.8)<lb/> 75.0, d 2′′<lb/> 3.59, m<lb/> 75.3, d<lb/> 9<lb/> 5.40, t (11.5)<lb/> 135.6, d 3′′<lb/> 3.52, m<lb/> 78.2, d<lb/> 10<lb/> 5.91, t (11.5)<lb/> 127.1, d 4′′<lb/> 3.45, m<lb/> 71.7, d<lb/> 11<lb/> 5.32, dd (15.3, 11.5) 128.4, d 5′′<lb/> 3.44, m<lb/> 78.5, d<lb/> 12<lb/> 6.07, dt (15.3, 4.7)<lb/> 137.1, d 6′′<lb/> 3.89, d, (12.2)<lb/> 3.74, dd, (12.2, 4.6)<lb/> 62.8, t<lb/> 13<lb/> 3.52, overlapped<lb/> 38.5, t<lb/></figure>

			<p>(δ C 132.5), C-4′ (δ C 139.2), and C-5′ (δ C 134.8) (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).<lb/> Besides, key HMBC correlations from H-1″ to C-1, com-<lb/>bined with the chemical shift changes at C-1 (δ C 145.7),<lb/> C-2 (δ C 154.2), C-4 (δ C 137.7), and C-6 (δ C 118.2) proved<lb/> that the glycosyl group was attached to C-1 <ref type="biblio">[13]</ref>. Conse-<lb/>quently, the planar structure of 6 was determined.<lb/></p>

			<p>In order to determine the absolute configuration of<lb/> 6, it was synthesized by glycosylation. Using Ca(OH) 2<lb/> as a base, otteacumiene A was chosen as a substrate to<lb/> react with α-D-fluoroglucose in aqueous solvent at room<lb/> temperature for 1 h (Scheme <ref type="figure">1</ref>) <ref type="biblio">[14]</ref>. Then, O-β-glc-<lb/>otteacumiene A was purified by semi-preparative HPLC<lb/> (MeOH/H 2 O, 50:50). Comparative analysis of the 1 H/ 13 C<lb/> NMR and HRESIMS data, combined with superimposed<lb/> ECD spectra, revealed that the aglycone of compound 6<lb/> had the same absolute configuration as otteacumiene A<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[8]</ref>. Therefore, this compound was (8S)-otteacumiene A<lb/> 1-O-β-D-glucopyranoside, named otteacumiene L.<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene M (7) was isolated as yellow oil and<lb/> its molecular formula was determined as C 22 H 22 O 7<lb/> by the HRESIMS at m/z 421.1261 [M + Na] + (calc.<lb/> for 421.1263), suggesting 12 degrees of unsaturation.<lb/> Compound 7 was a new natural product. Its 1 H NMR<lb/> spectrum was completely identical to that of synthetic<lb/> (E)-α-(3,4-methylenedioxybenzylidene)-β-(3,4,5-<lb/>trimethoxybenzyl)-γ-butyrolactone <ref type="biblio">[15]</ref>, which was<lb/> confirmed by the key COSY correlations of H 2 -9′/H-8′/<lb/> H 2 -7′, associated with HMBC correlations from H-7 (δ H<lb/> 7.52, s) to C-2 (δ C 108.5), C-6 (δ C 126.8), C-8 (δ C 126.0),<lb/> and C-9 (δ C 172.8); from H 2 -7′ (δ H 3.01, dd, J = 14.9, 4.8<lb/> Hz, H-7′a; 2.63, dd, J = 14.9, 9.9 Hz, H-7′b) to C-8′ (δ C<lb/> 40.3), C-9′ (δ C 70.2), C-8 (δ C 126.0), C-1′ (δ C 133.9), and<lb/> C-2′/C-6′ (δ C 106.1); and from -OCH 2 O-(δ H 6.03, s)<lb/> to C-3 (δ C 149.5) and C-4 (δ C 148.6) (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). However,<lb/> the absolute configuration of the synthetic product<lb/> mentioned above was not determined. Subsequently,<lb/> it was found that the known jatrophan (8′S, + 87) and<lb/> isosuchilactone (8′R, -83.3) were a pair of enantiom-<lb/>ers <ref type="biblio">[16]</ref>. By comparing their NMR data (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>), it was<lb/> found that compound 7 was a methoxylated derivative<lb/> of these two compounds at C-5′ (δ C 153.6). These com-<lb/>pounds had only one chiral center (C-8′). The absolute<lb/> configuration of 7 was speculated to be 8′S by compari-<lb/>son of its rotation ([α] D<lb/> 20 + 27.7 (c 0.141, MeOH) with<lb/> jatrophan (8′S, + 87) and isosuchilactone (8′R, -83.3)<lb/> <ref type="biblio">[16]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>The inhibitory activities of compounds 1, 2, 4, 6, and<lb/> 7 against both α-glucosidase and PTP1B were evalu-<lb/>ated. As summarized in Table <ref type="table">5</ref>, these compounds<lb/></p>

			<figure>Scheme 1 Glycosylation reaction of otteacumiene A<lb/></figure>

			<figure type="table">Table 4 1 H and 13 C NMR data of 7 in CDCl 3<lb/> δ in parts per million, J in Hz, and obtained at 600/150 MHz<lb/> No.<lb/> δ H<lb/> δ C<lb/> 1<lb/> 128.4, s<lb/> 2<lb/> 7.07, d (1.6)<lb/> 108.5, d<lb/> 3<lb/> 149.5, s<lb/> 4<lb/> 148.6, s<lb/> 5<lb/> 6.87, d (8.1)<lb/> 109.0, d<lb/> 6<lb/> 7.05, dd (8.1, 1.6)<lb/> 126.8, d<lb/> 7<lb/> 7.52, s<lb/> 137.6, d<lb/> 8<lb/> 126.0, s<lb/> 9<lb/> 172.8, s<lb/> 1′<lb/> 133.9, s<lb/> 2′<lb/> 6.41, s<lb/> 106.1, d<lb/> 3′<lb/> 153.6, s<lb/> 4′<lb/> 137.2, s<lb/> 5′<lb/> 153.6, s<lb/> 6′<lb/> 6.41, s<lb/> 106.1, d<lb/> 7′a<lb/> 3.01, dd (14.9, 4.8)<lb/> 2.63, dd (14.9, 9.9)<lb/> 38.9, t<lb/> 7&apos;b<lb/> 8′<lb/> 3.79, m<lb/> 40.3, d<lb/> 9′<lb/> 4.31, m<lb/> 70.2, t<lb/> -OCH 2 O-<lb/>6.03, s<lb/> 102.0, t<lb/> 3′-OMe<lb/> 3.86, s<lb/> 56.3, q<lb/> 4′-OMe<lb/> 3.81, s<lb/> 61.1, q<lb/> 5′-OMe<lb/> 3.86, s<lb/> 56.3, q<lb/></figure>

			<p>exhibited varying degrees of inhibitory activity against<lb/> α-glucosidase at a concentration of 50 μM. However,<lb/> none of the tested compounds displayed detectable<lb/> PTP1B inhibitory effects. An analysis of the structures<lb/> and α-glucosidase inhibitory activities was conducted<lb/> by comparing the diarylheptanoids in this study with<lb/> those previously reported by our group <ref type="biblio">[8]</ref>. The results<lb/> of this analysis revealed that the presence and position of<lb/> hydroxyl groups on the heptane chain had an impact on<lb/> their α-glucosidase inhibitory activities. This structural-<lb/>activity relationship warrants further investigation to elu-<lb/>cidate the precise molecular mechanisms underlying the<lb/> observed bioactivity.<lb/></p>

			<head>3 Conclusions<lb/></head>

			<p>Five pairs of enantiomeric diarylheptanoids (1-5), one<lb/> undescribed diarylheptanoid glycoside (6), and one new<lb/> lignan (7) were isolated from O. acuminata var. acumi-<lb/>nata. Among them, compounds 1-4 were individually<lb/> subjected to chiral separation, yielding optically pure<lb/> enantiomers for each. The absolute configurations of<lb/> these enantiomers were determined using X-ray crystal-<lb/>lography and by comparing the calculated and experi-<lb/>mental ECD curves. Notably, compound 6 was the first<lb/> diarylheptanoid glycoside isolated from this plant, and<lb/> its absolute configuration was confirmed by semi-syn-<lb/>thesis. This study enriched the fundamentals of chemical<lb/> substances of the title plant. Furthermore, at a concen-<lb/>tration of 50 μM, all the tested compounds exhibited var-<lb/>ying degrees of inhibitory potency against α-glucosidase,<lb/> which provides a clue for the development of hypoglyce-<lb/>mic drugs.<lb/></p>

			<head>4 Experimental procedures<lb/> </head>
				
			<head>4.1 General experimental procedures<lb/></head>

			<p>Optical rotations were recorded on a JASCO P-1020<lb/> polarimeter. The UV spectra were recorded with a Shi-<lb/>madzu UV-2401PC spectrometer. HRESIMS analysis<lb/> was performed with Agilent G6230 TOF mass spectrom-<lb/>eters. 1D and 2D NMR spectra were obtained with a<lb/> Bruker DRX-600 spectrometer using TMS as an internal<lb/> standard. The chemical shifts (δ) were expressed in ppm<lb/> with reference to the solvent signals. Semi-preparative<lb/> HPLC was performed on a Waters 1525 HPLC with<lb/> a ZORBAX SB-C18 (9.4 × 250 mm) column. Silica gel<lb/> (100-200 and 200-300 mesh, Qingdao Marine Chemi-<lb/>cal Co., Ltd., People&apos;s Republic of China). Fractions were<lb/> monitored by TLC (GF 254, Qingdao Marine Chemical<lb/> Co., Ltd.), and spots were visualized by heating silica gel<lb/> plates immersed in 10% H 2 SO 4 in ethanol. All industrial-<lb/>grade solvents were re-distilled before use. Otteacumiene<lb/> A is an isolate obtained by our group in the early stage.<lb/> α-Glucosidase,<lb/> 4-nitrophenyl-α-D-glucopyranoside<lb/> (PNPG), and acarbose were purchased from Sigma.<lb/> PTP1B was purchased from Sino Biological. Disodium<lb/> 4-nitrophenylphosphate (PNPP) was purchased from<lb/> MeilunBio.<lb/></p>

			<head>4.2 Plant material<lb/></head>

			<p>The plants of O. acuminata var. acuminata were col-<lb/>lected in Dali Prefecture (Yunnan, China) on October<lb/> 2019, it was identified by Prof. Yun-Heng Ji in Kunming<lb/> Institute of Botany, Chinese Academy of Sciences. A<lb/> voucher specimen (KIB L-20191001) was deposited in<lb/> Kunming Institute of Botany.<lb/></p>

			<head>4.3 Extraction and isolation<lb/></head>

			<p>The dried O. acuminata var. acuminata (180.0 kg) were<lb/> soaked and extracted with methanol, and the complete<lb/> evaporation of the solvent gave crude extract (13.5 kg).<lb/> The crude extract was eluted with methanol: water (1:1)<lb/> through macroporous resin to afford a fraction (505.9 g).<lb/> This fraction was suspended in distilled water and par-<lb/>titioned three times with EtOAc to obtain a fraction<lb/> (179.0 g). The EtOAc fraction was subjected to MCI-gel<lb/> column with a gradient system (MeOH-H 2 O from 3:7<lb/> to 10:0) to produce eight fractions (Frs. A-H). Frs. A-H<lb/> were extracted and purified by silica gel, RP-C18, Sepha-<lb/>dex gel, and preparative or semi-preparative HPLC-gel<lb/> chromatographic methods to obtain the nine isolates.<lb/></p>

			<p>Fr. C (10.2 g) was chromatographed on a silica gel<lb/> column with petroleum ether (PE)/acetone (AC)<lb/> (200:1-0:1, v/v), to yield seven fractions (Frs. C1-C7).<lb/> Fr. C3 (436.3 mg) was divided into seven sub-frac-<lb/>tions (Frs. C3-1-C3-7) by Sephadex gel column with<lb/> acetone. Fr. C3-2 (91.1 mg) was further separated by<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Table 5 Inhibitory effects of 1, 2, 4, 6, and 7 against<lb/> α-glucosidase a and PTP1B a<lb/> a Data expressed as means ± SD (n = 3)<lb/> b At a concentration of 50 μM<lb/> c Positive control<lb/> Compounds α-Glucosidase a<lb/> Compounds PTP1B a<lb/> Inhibition ratio<lb/> (%) b<lb/> Inhibition ratio<lb/> (%) b<lb/> 1<lb/> 38.97 ± 2.12<lb/> 1<lb/> 4.30 ± 1.90<lb/> (+)-2<lb/> 25.50 ± 2.34<lb/> (+)-2<lb/> 2.97 ± 1.32<lb/> (-)-2<lb/> 32.32 ± 2.10<lb/> (-)-2<lb/> 3.79 ± 1.18<lb/> 4<lb/> 20.31 ± 2.73<lb/> 4<lb/> 7.60 ± 1.11<lb/> 6<lb/> 4.71 ± 1.12<lb/> 6<lb/> 2.89 ± 1.23<lb/> 7<lb/> 7.79 ± 0.93<lb/> 7<lb/> 8.27 ± 1.82<lb/> Acarbose c<lb/> 13.52 ± 0.46<lb/> Suramin c<lb/> 61.65 ± 1.57<lb/></figure>

			<p>semi-preparative HPLC-gel (CH 3 CN/H 2 O, 70:30, v/v)<lb/> to obtain 7 (4.0 mg).<lb/></p>

			<p>Fr. E (68.4 g) was divided into nine sub-fractions (Frs.<lb/> E1-E9) by a silica gel column with PE/ AC (50:1-0:1,<lb/> v/v). Fr. E8 (10.3 g) was further chromatographed over<lb/> a RP-C18 column, eluted with MeOH/H 2 O (3:7 to<lb/> 100:0), to yield eight fractions (Frs. E8-1-E8-8). Fr. E8-1<lb/> (106.5 mg) was subjected to Sephadex LH-20 (MeOH),<lb/> followed by semi-preparative HPLC (CH 3 CN/H 2 O,<lb/> 38:62) to afford 5 (1.2 mg). Fr. E8-4 (356.6 mg) was puri-<lb/>fied by preparative HPLC (MeOH/H 2 O, 45:55) and<lb/> semi-preparative HPLC (CH 3 CN/H 2 O, 35:65, v/v) to<lb/> get 3 (1.0 mg) and 4 (5.0 mg). Fr. E8-5 (277.6 mg) was<lb/> purified by preparative HPLC (MeOH/H 2 O, 45:55, v/v)<lb/> and semi-preparative HPLC (CH 3 CN/H 2 O, 35:65) to<lb/> obtain 1 (2.4 mg) and 2 (2.1 mg). Fr. E9 (5.5 g) was sub-<lb/>jected on a RP-18 column chromatography (MeOH/<lb/> H 2 O, 3:7 to 10:0) to afford six fractions (Frs. E9-1-E9-6).<lb/> Fr. E9-4 (337.2 mg) was divided into four fractions (Frs.<lb/> E9-4-1-E9-4-4) by Sephadex gel column with methanol.<lb/> Fr. E9-4-4 (63.7 mg) was separated by semi-preparative<lb/> HPLC (MeOH/H 2 O, 50:50) to afford 6 (3.4 mg).<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene G (1): Colorless crystals; IR (v max ) 3426,<lb/> 2926, 1613, 1596, 1516, 1502, 1436, 1210, 1106, 836 cm -1 ;<lb/> UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 278 (2.25) nm; HRESIMS m/z<lb/> 311.1287 [M -H] -(calculated for C 19 H 19 O 4, 311.1289);<lb/> 1 H and 13 C NMR spectroscopic data see Tables <ref type="table">1 and 2</ref>.<lb/> (+)-1: [α] D<lb/> 20 + 40.0 (c 0.037, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max<lb/> (Δε) 285 (-0.94), 269 (1.04), 240 (5.35), 223 (-0.20), 213<lb/> (3.24), 199 (8.30) nm; (-)-1: [α] D<lb/> 20 -35.0 (c 0.040, MeOH);<lb/> ECD (MeOH) λ max (Δε) 284 (1.1), 270 (-0.5), 241 (-4.0),<lb/> 223 (1.2), 214 (-1.5), 199 (-5.9) nm.<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene H (2): Colorless crystals; IR (v max )<lb/> 3414, 2926, 1596, 1503, 1436, 1210, 1108, 848 cm -1 ;<lb/> UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 276 (2.22) nm; HRESIMS m/z<lb/> 311.1287 [M -H] -(calculated for C 19 H 19 O 4, 311.1289);<lb/> 1<lb/> H and 13 C NMR spectroscopic data see Tables <ref type="table">1 and 2</ref>.<lb/> ( +)-2: [α] D<lb/> 25 + 29.2 (c 0.048, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max<lb/> (Δε) 285 (-1.4), 270 (0.8), 242 (5.5), 216 (1.5), 206 (-4.5),<lb/> 197 (9.3) nm; ( -)-2: [α] D<lb/> 25 -37.7 (c 0.052, MeOH); ECD<lb/> (MeOH) λ max (Δε) 284 (1.3), 270 (-4.5), 242 (-4.1), 216<lb/> (-0.8), 206 (4.1), 197 (-6.4) nm.<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene I (3): Colorless crystals; IR (v max )<lb/> 3426, 2922, 1629, 1604, 1412, 1384, 1217, 8337 cm -1 ;<lb/> UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 279 (2.17) nm; HRESIMS m/z<lb/> 311.1286 [M -H] -(calculated for C 19 H 19 O 4, 311.1289);<lb/> 1<lb/> H and 13 C NMR spectroscopic data see Tables <ref type="table">1 and<lb/> 2</ref>. ( +)-3: [α] D<lb/> 20 + 4.59 (c 0.048, MeOH); ECD (MeOH)<lb/> λ max (Δε) 283 (-0.8), 240 (2.3), 221 (-2.7), 198 (2.9) nm;<lb/> ( -)-3: [α] D<lb/> 20 -4.00 (c 0.050, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max<lb/> (Δε) 282 (0.6), 239 (-2.8), 221 (2.4), 199 (-3.3) nm.<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene J (4): White powder; IR (v max ) 3431,<lb/> 2929, 1518,1504, 1273, 1210, 1112, 1029, 837, 574 cm -1 ;<lb/> UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 279 (2.25) nm; HRESIMS m/z<lb/> 311.1285 [M -H] -(calculated for C 19 H 19 O 4, 311.1283);<lb/> 1 H and 13 C NMR spectroscopic data see Tables <ref type="table">1 and<lb/> 2</ref>. ( +)-4: [α] D<lb/> 20 + 4.48 (c 0.067, MeOH); ECD (MeOH)<lb/> λ max (Δε) 285 (0.2), 270 (-0.4), 255 (-0.2), 226 (2.6),<lb/> 201 (-7.8), 195 (-4.2) nm; ( -)-4: [α] D<lb/> 20 -6.08 (c 0.092,<lb/> MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max (Δε) 286 (-0.3), 271 (0.3),<lb/> 255 (0.2), 226 (-2.9), 201 (8.5), 195 (4.9) nm.<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene K (5): Colorless needle crystal;<lb/> [α] D<lb/> 20 -3.17 (c 0.145, MeOH); IR (v max ) 3422, 2925, 1607,<lb/> 1412, 1242, 813, 562 cm -1 ; UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 290<lb/> (2.70) nm; HRESIMS m/z 293.1178 [M -H] -(calculated<lb/> for C 19 H 17 O 3, 293.1178); 1 H and 13 C NMR spectroscopic<lb/> data see Tables <ref type="table">1 and 2</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene L (6): White powder; [α] D<lb/> 25 + 1.1 (c 0.195,<lb/> MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max (Δε) 284 (3.1), 269 (-0.1),<lb/> 242 (10.6), 197 (-27.6) nm; UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 278<lb/> (2.22) nm; IR (v max ) 3413, 2921, 1587, 1510, 1416, 1254,<lb/> 1201, 1073, 868 cm -1 ; HRESIMS m/z 479.1682 [M + Na] +<lb/> (calculated for C 25 H 28 O 8 Na, 479.1682); 1 H and 13 C spec-<lb/>troscopic data see Table <ref type="table">3</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Otteacumiene M (7): Yellow oil; [α] D<lb/> 20 + 27.7 (c 0.141,<lb/> MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max (Δε) 338 (1.0), 287 (-2.3),<lb/> 247 (1.3), 239 (0.8), 231 (1.7), 220 (0.1), 209 (1.5), 197<lb/> (-1.2) nm; UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 205 (3.52), 297<lb/> (2.82), 334 (3.02) nm; IR (v max ) 3435, 2940, 1749, 1640,<lb/> 1591, 1502, 1450, 1342, 1241, 1128 cm -1 ; HRESIMS<lb/> m/z 421.1261 ([M + Na] + (calculated for C 22 H 22 O 7 Na,<lb/> 421.1263); 1 H and 13 C spectroscopic data see Table <ref type="table">4</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Crystal data for 1: C 19 H 20 O 4 , M = 312.35, a = 7.3795(2)<lb/> Å, b = 15.4127(4) Å, c = 14.0622(4) Å, α = 90°,<lb/> β = 104.6890(10)°, γ = 90°, V = 1547.13(7) Å 3 , T = 150.(2)<lb/> K, space group P121/c1, Z = 4, μ(Cu Kα) = 0.759 mm -1 ,<lb/> 13,446 reflections measured, 2809 independent reflec-<lb/>tions (R int = 0.0507). The final R 1 values were 0.0424<lb/> (I &gt; 2σ(I)). The final wR(F 2 ) values were 0.1080 (I &gt; 2σ(I)).<lb/> The final R 1 values were 0.0462 (all data). The final wR(F 2 )<lb/> values were 0.1111 (all data). The goodness of fit on F 2<lb/> was 1.040.<lb/></p>

			<p>Crystal data for 3: C 19 H 20 O 4 , M = 312.35, a = 9.1373(3)<lb/> Å, b = 10.3847(3) Å, c = 16.6741(5) Å, α = 90°,<lb/> β = 102.2910(10)°, γ = 90°, V = 1545.91(8) Å 3 , T = 150.(2)<lb/> K, space group P121/c1, Z = 4, μ(Cu Kα) = 0.760 mm -1 ,<lb/> 26,920 reflections measured, 3031 independent reflec-<lb/>tions (R int = 0.0585). The final R 1 values were 0.0376<lb/> (I &gt; 2σ(I)). The final wR(F 2 ) values were 0.0913 (I &gt; 2σ(I)).<lb/> The final R 1 values were 0.0404 (all data). The final wR(F 2 )<lb/> values were 0.0932 (all data). The goodness of fit on F 2<lb/> was 1.024.<lb/></p>

			<p>Crystal data for 5: Crystal data for rxz160x:<lb/> C 19 H 18 O 3 , M = 294.33, a = 8.9038(4) Å, b = 9.4697(4)<lb/> Å, c = 17.1220(7) Å, α = 90°, β = 90°, γ = 90°,<lb/> V = 1443.66(11) Å 3 , T = 150. (2) K, space group Pna21,<lb/> Z = 4, μ(Cu Kα) = 0.729 mm -1 , 19,243 reflections meas-<lb/>ured, 2586 independent reflections (R int = 0.1368). The<lb/> final R 1 values were 0.0338 (I &gt; 2σ(I)). The final wR(F 2 )<lb/> values were 0.0804 (I &gt; 2σ(I)). The final R 1 values were<lb/> 0.0418 (all data). The final wR(F 2 ) values were 0.0828<lb/> (all data). The goodness of fit on F 2 was 1.043. Flack<lb/> parameter = 0.55(13).<lb/></p>

			<head>4.4 α-Glucosidase and PTB1B inhibitory activities<lb/> detection<lb/></head>

			<p>α-Glucosidase inhibitory assay: enzyme solution (0.025<lb/> U/mL), buffer, and substrate (1 mM) were sequen-<lb/>tially added to the enzyme labeled plates along with<lb/> the samples and three-well replicates were established<lb/> for each sample. A blank control without drug and a<lb/> positive control of acarbose were also set up. The plate<lb/> was incubated at 37 °C for 50 min and the OD value at<lb/> 405 nm was measured by enzyme marker to calculate<lb/> the inhibition rate of α-glucosidase activity.<lb/> </p>
				
			<p>PTB1B inhibitory assay: the procedure was similar<lb/> to α-glucosidase inhibitory assay. Incubate at 37 ℃ for<lb/> 30 min, then add Na 2 CO 3 termination solution. Finally,<lb/> the OD value was determined by an enzyme meter with<lb/> a detection wavelength of 405 nm (positive control was<lb/> suramin).<lb/></p>

			<p>The inhibition percentage: inhibition rate (%) = (1-S/<lb/> E) × 100% (S is the OD of the sample, E is the OD of the<lb/> control).</p>


	</text>
</tei>
