<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>Background &amp; Summary<lb/></head>

			<p>Accurate shoreline monitoring is imperative to understand coastal risks, quantify both long-term and short-term<lb/> change rates, and provide essential information to coastal managers worldwide <ref type="biblio">1-4</ref> . With an estimated 896 mil-<lb/>lion people currently residing in low-lying coastal areas, a figure projected to reach 1 billion by 2050 <ref type="biblio">5</ref> , safeguard-<lb/>ing coastal environments is critical. Sandy beaches and dunes make up about 30% of the global coastline <ref type="biblio">6</ref> and<lb/> are dynamic systems that respond to environmental factors such as waves and sea level changes <ref type="biblio">7</ref> . These sandy<lb/> beaches hold cultural significance for many island and coastal communities and often contribute significantly<lb/> to their economy through coastal tourism <ref type="biblio">8</ref> . Furthermore, they function as critical storm buffers <ref type="biblio">9</ref> and provide<lb/> essential habitats for various species, including monk seals and turtles <ref type="biblio">10</ref> . However, with impacts of rising sea<lb/> levels and intensifying storminess relating to climate change <ref type="biblio">11</ref> , combined with increased coastal development,<lb/> leading to the coastal squeeze of shoreline, many of these sandy environments are suffering from erosion or<lb/> landward shoreline migration <ref type="biblio">6,12,13</ref> . With sea levels expected to rise for centuries to come <ref type="biblio">14</ref> , the threat to coastal<lb/> land loss intensifies. Therefore, acquiring comprehensive data to understand coastal responses is essential for<lb/> effective coastal zone management.<lb/></p>

			<p>Conducting consistent in-situ surveys is challenging because of requirements for time, personnel, and equip-<lb/>ment. Despite their integral role in enhancing the understanding of coastal morphodynamics, only a limited<lb/> number of long-term, consistent coastal study datasets exist <ref type="biblio">15-19</ref> . In recent years, Satellite-Derived Shoreline<lb/> (SDS) data have emerged as a crucial tool for monitoring coastlines <ref type="biblio">20-22</ref> . Here, shorelines are delineated using<lb/> publicly available satellite imagery, creating a time series of shoreline positions from which various metrics,<lb/> such as long-term erosion/accretion rates and seasonal variability <ref type="biblio">23</ref> , and basin-scale patterns <ref type="biblio">24</ref> can be derived.<lb/> Additionally, they can be used for future shoreline projections <ref type="biblio">21,22</ref> . As this method becomes increasingly prev-<lb/>alent in coastal monitoring, it is imperative to benchmark its reliability and accuracy with ground truth survey<lb/> data. Yet, there are only few datasets encompassing long-term consistent in-situ monitoring. Among them are<lb/> datasets from 1) Duck beach, USA <ref type="biblio">15</ref> , 2) Narrabeen, Australia <ref type="biblio">16,17</ref> , 3) Truc Vert, France <ref type="biblio">25</ref> , and 4) and Torrey<lb/> Pines, USA <ref type="biblio">26</ref> . These four datasets are currently used in standardized benchmarking efforts <ref type="biblio">27</ref> and predominantly<lb/> feature large continental, low-sloping silicate beaches. However, previous research has indicated variations<lb/> in the accuracy of satellite benchmarking across different sites <ref type="biblio">23</ref> . Given that no thorough dataset exists to<lb/> inform accuracy on reef-fringed environments to our knowledge, we aim to partially fill this gap by providing<lb/> 3.5 years of benchmarking data for a carbonate reef-fringed beach. This dataset comprises near-weekly surveys<lb/> from 2018 to 2021 of Kahaloa Beach, Hawai&apos;i. For each survey, we employed small Unoccupied Aerial Systems<lb/> (sUAS) to collect aerial imagery, which was processed using photogrammetry software to create digital terrain<lb/> models (DTMs) with 0.5 m resolution and orthorectified image mosaics with 0.03-0.04 m resolution. Ground<lb/> surveys, conducted with a survey-grade total station, were used to establish shoreline position at the mean<lb/> lower low water mark (MLLW), and capture accurate reference points for the photogrammetry processing.<lb/> Additionally, beach volumes were derived from the DTM. Each of these products are described in detail in<lb/> Methods below.<lb/></p>

			<p>This data collection was initially motivated to respond to chronic erosion concerns at the central Kahaloa<lb/> Beach in Waikīkī. Previously, analysis from eight and twenty-two months of data collection have been published<lb/> to understand the drivers of beach change and beach responses to hurricanes <ref type="biblio">28,29</ref> . This accounts for 56% of the<lb/> total data collected (72 surveys), which are accessible in a Mendeley data repository <ref type="biblio">30</ref> . In this report, we present<lb/> an additional 18 months of data (56 surveys), extending the time series to 40 months <ref type="biblio">31</ref> . Additionally, individual<lb/> shoreline vectors at Mean Sea Level (MSL) and Mean Higher High Water (MHHW) contours are provided<lb/> for ease of reuse in satellite shoreline benchmarking efforts. By consolidating these data in one data descrip-<lb/>tor and platform, we provide a valuable asset to enhance the understanding of complex reef-fringed beaches.<lb/> Additionally, these data serve as a critical benchmarking dataset for evaluating satellite derived shorelines in<lb/> reef-fringed beach environments.<lb/></p>

			<head>Site Description<lb/></head>

			<p>Kahaloa Beach, commonly referred to as The Royal Hawaiian Beach, is a popular beach located in the heart<lb/> of Waikīkī (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>). It is a crescent-shaped carbonate beach, fronted by a fringing reef. It extends 520 m and is<lb/> bounded by two terminal shore-normal groins that limit the alongshore sediment exchange into and out of the<lb/> littoral cell <ref type="biblio">32</ref> . Large sediment gains or losses are facilitated primarily through cross-shore transport via a subtle<lb/> sand channel located in the center of the nearshore region <ref type="biblio">29</ref> . Longshore sediment exchange has been shown as a<lb/> mechanism for re-distribution of sediment within the littoral cell <ref type="biblio">28,32</ref> .<lb/></p>

			<p>The beach is characterized by chronic erosion, necessitating intervention to maintain usable beach width.<lb/> Starting in 1890&apos;s, the beach has seen modifications in the form of encroachment of development, beach renour-<lb/>ishment, structural change such as groins and seawalls, which have been constructed and removed through the<lb/> last century, and dredging of the coral reef fronting parts of this beach <ref type="biblio">33</ref> .<lb/></p>

			<p>The chronic erosion is typically punctuated by seasonal morphologic change where summer south swell<lb/> corresponds to accretion and local trade-wind swell (intermittent year-round) promote erosion <ref type="biblio">29,32,34</ref> . The near-<lb/>shore comprises a gently sloping fringing coral reef a few hundred meters wide <ref type="biblio">33</ref> . In the immediate nearshore,<lb/> a sand field with intermittent rocky substrate (fossilized reef) extends seaward from the toe of Kahaloa Beach<lb/> approximately 100-200 m. Foreshore slopes at Kahaloa Beach have been measured to average 0.149 from the<lb/> Low Water Mark (LWM) to the first beach berm (not shown).<lb/></p>

			<p>Sand grain size varies due to numerous engineering and re-nourishment projects. The offshore sand source<lb/> used for two renourishment projects, one in 2012 and another in 2021, had a median diameter of 0.3 mm,<lb/> matching the existing beach sand in distribution, texture, and color. Notably, Kūhiō Beach Park (the eastern-<lb/>most section) exhibited coarser sand (D50 = 0.80 mm) compared to the rest of the beach, where grain sizes<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 1 Kahaloa Beach in Waikīkī. The study site is a narrow reef-fronted beach. Two terminal groins bound the<lb/> beach, and an additional stub groin was placed to retain sand in the easternmost portion of the beach.<lb/></figure>

			<p>ranged from 0.29 mm to 0.40 mm <ref type="biblio">35</ref> . The dredged sand primarily consists of carbonate material, predominantly<lb/> composed of calcareous skeletal fragments from marine organisms such as corals, coralline algae, mollusks,<lb/> echinoids, and foraminifera, with minimal coarse material or fines.<lb/></p>

			<p>The Hawaiian Islands are characterized by a relatively low tidal range, which reaches a maximum of 1 m<lb/> during the summer spring perigee. The prevailing wave conditions in Hawai&apos;i are closely tied to the seasons <ref type="biblio">36,37</ref> .<lb/> Waikīkī experiences two primary wave fields: 1) Summer swells, prominent between April and October, orig-<lb/>inating in the Southern Ocean with periods spanning 14 to 22 s and heights ranging from 1 to 5 m; and 2)<lb/> Locally generated tradewind waves, characterized by shorter periods (6-10 s) and relatively lower heights<lb/> (1-3 m), persisting throughout the year but becoming more frequent in the summer. Winter swells generated by<lb/> North Pacific storms generally have a minimal impact on Waikīkī beaches, as they are sheltered by the island.<lb/> Conversely, swells associated with Kona Storms (typically in winter) or Tropical cyclone swells (typically occur-<lb/>ring from June to November), can introduce substantial wave energy and drive significant coastal change <ref type="biblio">38,39</ref> ,<lb/> including beach accretion <ref type="biblio">29</ref> .<lb/></p>

			<p>During the survey period, three notable changes were made to Kahaloa Beach (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>): (1) In November<lb/> 2019, a small 30 m stub groin constructed from large sandbags was installed to retain sand in the easternmost<lb/> section of the beach. (2) In May 2020, a replacement of the Royal Hawaiian Groin was built at the western-<lb/>most end of the beach, shorter but denser, to replace a failing groin that had been in place since 1930 <ref type="biblio">33</ref> . (3)<lb/> In April through May 2021, a beach renourishment project was undertaken, involving the pumping of sand<lb/> from offshore deposits into a drying basin, after which it was trucked onto Kahaloa Beach over a 2-3-week<lb/> period. This brought in approximately 15,291 m 3 ; widening the beach by 9.1 m on average and increasing<lb/> the dry sandy area by 4,831 m 2 (Figs. <ref type="figure">1 and 4</ref>) <ref type="biblio">40,41</ref> . A prior beach nourishment took place in 2012 <ref type="biblio">32</ref> to retain<lb/> usable beach width and it is projected that sand nourishment will be required every 5-10 years to maintain<lb/> the beach.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> Flowchart of methodology. Following surveys using sUAS and total station, data is processed with<lb/> photogrammetric software, after which the point cloud is processed, and resulting outputs include a surveyed<lb/> shoreline, orthomosaic, Digital Terrain Model and beach volume.<lb/></figure>

			<head>Methods<lb/></head>
			<head>Field work.</head>

			<p>We conducted 128 near-weekly ground and aerial beach surveys at Kahaloa Beach, Waikīkī, from<lb/> April 2018 to July 2021 (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>). These surveys were initially motivated to better understand beach response to<lb/> both seasonal and tropical-storm-generated waves. A consumer-grade sUAS (DJI phantom4 Pro v1 &amp; v2) and the<lb/> flight planning software package DroneDeploy was used to collect overlapping images at 120 m altitude, resulting<lb/> in a ground sampling distance of 3-4 cm. All images were taken at nadir with 80% side-lap/end-lap. The sUAS<lb/> imagery was georeferenced using ground control points (GCPs) described below; RTK or onboard sUAS GPS<lb/> was not used (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>Camera settings varied depending on light conditions, but high shutter speeds (1/1000-1/600) were prior-<lb/>itized to reduce motion blur. Each survey was conducted in the morning around sunrise to capture the beach<lb/> prior to crowds and objects (e.g., beach umbrellas, chairs, tents, etc.), irrespective of tide level and ocean con-<lb/>ditions. Repeat surveys were planned weekly; however, given the weather dependent nature of sUAS flights,<lb/> surveys were conducted around optimal weather (low winds, no rain) for each week resulting in revisit times<lb/> between 5 and 15 days (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>Seven 1 × 1 m vinyl targets functioned as GCPs and were spaced equidistant about 100 m alongshore for<lb/> each survey. The position of GCPs were surveyed using a rod-mounted prism and a Leica TS16 Robotic Total<lb/> Station with millimeter-level accuracy. Additionally, points were collected every 5-15 m along the seaward edge<lb/> of the foreshore, here marked by the position of the top of the beach toe, also approximately equal to the low<lb/> water mark (LWM) <ref type="biblio">39,42</ref> . Existing benchmarks provided a spatial reference using the WGS 1984 UTM Zone 4<lb/> projection. Elevations were measured with respect to local mean sea level (LMSL; Datums -NOAA Tides and<lb/> Currents, present epoch: 1983-2001).<lb/></p>

			<head>Data processing.</head>

			<p>Following standardized USGS protocols <ref type="biblio">43,44</ref> for photogrammetry processing, Agisoft<lb/> Metashape (formerly Photoscan) was used to generate a dense point cloud and orthomosaic (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). An initial<lb/> sparse point cloud was created with GCPs manually identified and subsequently verified for each image con-<lb/>taining a GCP. After importing the surveyed GCP coordinates and re-aligning the sparse cloud, an iterative<lb/> error reduction process was initiated, in which points above a certain threshold were removed and the sparse<lb/> point cloud re-aligned. This iterative process was repeated until uncertainty values were below a specific thresh-<lb/>old. Approximately 10% of the points were removed at each iteration, initially reducing the &quot;Reconstruction<lb/> Uncertainty&quot; to 10, followed by reducing &quot;Projection Accuracy&quot; to 3, and lastly reducing &quot;Reprojection Error&quot; once,<lb/> by eliminating the 10% of the point cloud with highest values. From here, a dense point cloud, DEM, and ortho-<lb/>mosaic was generated from Agisoft Metashape.<lb/></p>

			<p>The dense point cloud was post-processed using rapidlasso LAStools to eliminate data artifacts such as beach<lb/> umbrellas and canoes, identify ground points, and remove outliers. The LAZ point cloud was initially cropped<lb/> to exclude landward and ocean points beyond the study area. It was then tiled, sorted, thinned, and removed of<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 4 Point cloud processing to identify ground points and remove outliers. The dense point cloud exported<lb/> from Agisoft Metashape (A) is clipped (B) and processed to remove all non-ground points, as well as points below<lb/> 0.6 m elevation (C). The ground points are merged with the surveyed LWM (shoreline points in panels B &amp; C),<lb/> and interpolated into a 0.5 m resolution DTM (D).<lb/></figure>

			<figure>Fig. 3 Survey frequency. Surveys were conducted near-weekly, with some gaps due to beach construction<lb/> projects or weather conditions.<lb/></figure>

			<p>erroneous points. In order to minimize the impact of the moving water interface and wave runup, we removed<lb/> all points located in the run-up zone. This involved eliminating all points situated below an elevation threshold<lb/> of 0.6 meters above mean sea level. This threshold was determined empirically, considering high errors and<lb/> sporadic points resulting from saturated sand and wave run-up in the swash zone, which affect the overall qual-<lb/>ity of the DTM. The post-processed point clouds were manually assessed, and any remaining points deemed<lb/> erroneous were removed, if necessary. We then merged the remaining point cloud with the surveyed shoreline<lb/> points of the LWM, approximately -0.251 m relative to MSL. A surface was interpolated across all points at<lb/> 0.5 m resolution using natural neighbor interpolation, then smoothed using mean cell values within a 5 m radius<lb/> circular to eliminate any remaining elevation anomalies caused by beach artifacts. The 5 m radius was selected<lb/> empirically to balance effective smoothing without masking weekly changes or introducing errors compared to<lb/> ground-sampled elevations (see Technical Validation).<lb/></p>

			<p>Beach volume (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>) was calculated in ArcGIS pro using the Surface Volume tool. Here, the floor was<lb/> defined by the MHHW equivalent to 0.329 m above MSL. As a result, the seaward boundary was the intersection<lb/> of the DTM surface with the MHHW contour, while the landward extent was constant and primarily deter-<lb/>mined by walkways and buildings.<lb/></p>

			<p>MSL and MHHW contours were generated using the contour tool in ArcGIS and subsequently reviewed<lb/> for necessary edits. Adjustments were made if a contour was interrupted by the Kūhiō shore normal groin or if<lb/> contours inaccurately extended seaward at the beach ends. In these cases, the contour was completed by digi-<lb/>tizing the shoreline feature in the image mosaic. This would typically occur if the beach was eroded, resulting in<lb/> the DTM encompassing a larger area than the data collection zone, occasionally resulting in sporadic offshore<lb/> discrepancies.<lb/></p>

			<head>Data Records<lb/></head>

			<p>The data are available at figshare <ref type="biblio">31</ref> . This dataset consists of five (5) products derived from each field survey.<lb/> The (1) Digital Terrain Model (DTM) and (2) orthomosaic are provided in LZM compressed tagged image file<lb/> format (TIFF) in WGS 1984 UTM Zone 4 projection (EPSG:32604). The DTMs have a resolution of 0.5 m, and<lb/> a vertical uncertainty quantified as the 95% confidence interval around the mean (±0.0113 m; see Technical<lb/> Validation below). Elevations are measured with respect to local mean sea level (LMSL) (NOAA tides and cur-<lb/>rents; station ID 1612340). The orthomosaics are produced from each survey to create a mosaic without distor-<lb/>tion. The resolution varies slightly between surveys and is 3-4 cm.<lb/></p>

			<p>Surveyed shoreline points (3) marking the seaward edge of the foreshore are provided in a.txt file, with east-<lb/>ing, northing, and elevation values, respectively, as columns and each row representing a surveyed point. These<lb/> are also in WGS 1984 UTM Zone 4 projection and elevations are with respect to LMSL. The Leica TS16 Robotic<lb/> Total Station, which was used to sample these data points, provides sub-centimeter accuracy. The primary<lb/> uncertainty of this measurement is therefore inconsistencies in identifying the beach toe, and wave impacts<lb/> that could potentially shift the position of the rod-mounted prism at the time of measurement (see Technical<lb/> Validation below). For effective comparison with satellite-derived shorelines, shoreline contours (4) are provided<lb/> for MHHW and MSL for each survey. Additionally, a contour produced from the surveyed shorelines points<lb/> representing the LWM is included. These are provided as individual geojson files, named by YYYYMMDD_<lb/> datum.geojson, and each file contains two attributes: the contour elevation relative to MSL (0 m) and the date of<lb/> the survey. Lastly, a text file (5) containing calculated metrics for each survey is included. Each row represents a<lb/> survey labeled with the survey date (YYYYMMDD), and metrics include beach volume, 2D, and 3D area calcu-<lb/>lated from the DTM (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>), as well as volume ± elevation uncertainty times the 3D area.<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 5 Beach volume (orange) and beach area (blue) throughout the survey period. The vertical lines denote<lb/> beach management interventions, the most recent being the beach nourishment that occurred in May 2021.<lb/> Shadings Represent uncertainty bands for volume and area calculations.<lb/></figure>

			<head>technical Validation<lb/></head>
			<head>Uncertainty in sUAS-derived DEM.</head>

			<p>To assess the quality in the elevation values of the sUAS-derived<lb/> DEMs, two separate surveys were conducted in which measured point elevations (collected with the Leica TS16<lb/> Robotic Total Station, n = 228 and n = 198) were compared to modeled point elevations from the corresponding<lb/> sUAS-derived DEM. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows the distribution of these points collected across the beach and their com-<lb/>parison with the measured elevation values for surveys conducted on April 8, 2020 (Fig. <ref type="figure">6A-C</ref>) and August 7,<lb/> 2020 (Fig. <ref type="figure">6A-F</ref>). Panels a and d display a one-to-one comparison between the measured and modeled elevation<lb/> values, while panels b and e present the histogram of residuals. Panels c and f illustrate the distribution of points<lb/> colored by their associated errors. Essential statistical parameters, such as the mean (0.0060 m and 0.0035 m),<lb/> standard deviation (0.0998 m and 0.0680 m), root mean square error (RMSE; 0.0998 m and 0.0680 m), and stand-<lb/>ard error (0.0066 m and 0.0049 m), were computed, assuming a normal distribution.<lb/></p>

			<p>To quantify uncertainties in the elevation values, 95% confidence intervals were calculated as 1.96 times<lb/> the standard error (0.0130 m and 0.0095 m). Subsequently, uncertainties in beach volume calculations were<lb/> estimated by multiplying the 95 percent confidence interval with the 3D beach area. Uncertainties in surveyed<lb/> shoreline positions are attributed to uncertainty or inconsistencies in locating the LWM feature at ±0.3 m in the<lb/> cross-shore direction.<lb/></p>

			<head>Usage Notes<lb/></head>

			<p>The purpose of sharing these data serves a dual role: 1) To encourage research focused on reef-fringed beaches,<lb/> and 2) to offer a dataset for evaluating the accuracy of satellite-derived shoreline (SDS) efforts in the context of<lb/> reef-fringed beaches. It is worth noting that most published coastal survey data are concentrated around expan-<lb/>sive open coastlines or broad embayed beaches. This dataset introduces an additional resource to benchmark<lb/> satellite derived shoreline at reef-fringed beaches.<lb/></p>

			<p>If these data are used for SDS benchmarking efforts, we suggest using one of the produced shoreline contours<lb/> (LWM, MSL, or MHHW). In reference to MSL (0 m) for Honolulu Tide Gauge, MHHW is at an elevation of<lb/> 0.329 m. The LWM represents the top of the toe and can be interpreted as a contour of the Mean Lower Low<lb/> Water (-0.251 m relative to MSL). It is worth noting that the MSL and MHHW contour may contain higher<lb/> uncertainties compared to the manually collected LWM contour due to the interpolation applied across the<lb/> beach foreshore.<lb/></p>

			<p>Other relevant environment data when exploring these data include water level obtained from the Honolulu<lb/> tide gauge <ref type="biblio">45</ref> , accessible through the University of Hawaii Sea Level Center with station ID of UHSLC ID 57<lb/> (https://uhslc.soest.hawaii.edu/stations/?stn=057#levels). You can access a processed dataset of nearshore wave<lb/> information, generated using the Simulated WAves Nearshore (SWAN) model. This dataset provides data at<lb/></p>

			<figure>Fig. 6 Elevation uncertainty of sUAS derived DEM. This figure shows the results of two separate uncertainty<lb/> surveys conducted on April 8, 2020 (panels A-C) and August 7, 2020 (panels D-F). A 1:1 plot of measured<lb/> (x-axis) and modeled (y-axis) elevation values are shown in panels A (n = 228) and D (n = 196). Residuals are<lb/> represented in a histogram in panels B and E. The 95% confidence interval (red vertical bands) was calculated as<lb/> 1.96 times the standard error (SE). Panels C and F show the distribution of points across Kahaloa Beach, colored<lb/> by elevation difference between measured and modeled elevations, with white being lowest (0.001-0.05 m) and<lb/> red being highest (0.20-0.357 m). Yellow points were collected with our total station but did not overlap with<lb/> the derived DEM.<lb/></figure>

			<p>a 500-meter grid resolution covering the period from June 20, 2010, to present from PacIOOS (https://www.<lb/> pacioos.hawaii.edu/metadata/swan_oahu.htm) via THREDDS or OPENDAP. Additionally, data from a wave<lb/> buoy located on the south shore of O&apos;ahu near the entrance to Pearl Harbor is available from PacIOOS (https://<lb/> www.pacioos.hawaii.edu/waves/buoy-pearl/). However, waves originating from the east, which typically wrap<lb/> around the southeastern corner of O&apos;ahu, are not always captured by this buoy. For users interested in elevation<lb/> data beyond the beach, publicly accessible coastal DEMs are available through NOAA Digital Coast (https://<lb/> coast.noaa.gov/digitalcoast/data/coastallidar.html). We recommend using the 2013 Topo-Bathy LiDAR DEM<lb/> as of the date of this publication.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
