<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_submission_103"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			
			<p>Biexciton (bound two-exciton state) and scattering two-exciton states play an essential role in optical<lb/> nonlinearity of semiconducting material. In general, it is difficult to calculate these two-exciton states because of<lb/> a four-body problem consisting of two electrons and two holes. However, two-exciton states consisting of<lb/> Frenkel excitons can be described by a simple tight-binding model with a nearest-neighbor approximation. The<lb/> model Hamiltonian has been extensively studied. Analytical expression of a biexciton for one-dimensional (1D)<lb/> chain <ref type="biblio">[1]</ref> and the third-order nonlinear susceptibility of finite 1D chain <ref type="biblio">[2]</ref> have been obtained from this model<lb/> Hamiltonian. The former is limited to the biexciton, and the latter calculates the susceptibility without obtaining<lb/> wave functions of two-exciton states. For studying nonlinear optical processes in a microcavity, however, the<lb/> wave functions are necessary in order to calculate transition rates from an exciton to two-exciton state via a<lb/> cavity photon <ref type="biblio">[3,4]</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>In this paper, I provide a rapid calculation method for calculating energies and wave functions of the<lb/> two exciton-states in the tight-binding Hamiltonian. The method has been reported in the case of a 1D chain <ref type="biblio">[5]</ref>.<lb/> I extend this method to 2D and 3D systems. Since the two-exciton states are obtained from a bisection method,<lb/> the present method needs much less memory capacity and computation time than the matrix diagonalization.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The two-exciton energies are determined from two kinds of functions U(E) and W(E), each of which<lb/> has singular points. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows U(E) and two-exciton energies for 41x41x41 sites of 3D lattice by applying<lb/> CuCl parameters. A horizontal dotted line represents 1/δ, where δ denotes two-exciton interaction between<lb/> nearest-neighbor sites. The two-exciton energies are obtained as the crossing points between the horizontal<lb/> dotted line and the function U(E) indicated by solid curves. The two-exciton energies can be definitely obtained<lb/> by using a bisection method because all singular points of U(E) can be obtained. Inset shows U(E) around the<lb/> biexciton energy. The two-exciton energies obtained from a function W(E) are marked by closed inverted<lb/> triangles. These two-exciton energies agree with those calculated from diagonalization indicated by open circles.<lb/> <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows wave function in wave-vector space of a biexciton state for CuCl parameters.<lb/> Small lattice size 21x21x21 is chosen because of clearness to see. The size of spheres denotes the amplitude of<lb/> the wave function.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The present method is useful for analysis of experimental data because the parameter δ of the two-<lb/>exciton interaction can be immediately determined from an observed binding energy of biexciton.<lb/></p>

			<figure>
				<head>Figure 1:</head>
				<figDesc>Energies of two-exciton states obtained<lb/> from a bisection method.<lb/></figDesc>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<trash>6.404<lb/> 6.408<lb/> 6.412<lb/> 6.416<lb/> -5<lb/> 0<lb/> 5<lb/> 10<lb/> Energy (eV)<lb/> U(E) (eV -1<lb/> )<lb/> N= 41<lb/> Bisection Method for U<lb/> Bisection Method for W<lb/> Diagonalization<lb/> 6.34<lb/> 6.36<lb/> 6.38<lb/> 6.40<lb/> -4<lb/> 0<lb/> 4<lb/> Energy (eV)<lb/> U(E) (eV -1<lb/> )<lb/> 0 0.1<lb/> 0.2<lb/> 0 0.1<lb/> 0.2<lb/> 0<lb/> 0.1<lb/> 0.2<lb/></trash>
				<head>Figure 2:</head>
				<figDesc>Wave function of biexciton state in wave-<lb/>vector space.</figDesc>
			</figure>

	</text>
</tei>
