<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">From the Field: Law-Related Education as a Branch of Civics Education in the United States</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Latia</forename>
            <surname>Ward</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-07-20T15:25:03.927Z">20.7.2025 17:25:03</date>
          <title>Grobid document segmentation corrected</title>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>		
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Northumbria University Library</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2022</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.19164/ijple.v6i1.1293</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Latia Ward. (2022). From the Field: Law-Related Education as a Branch of Civics Education in the United States. International Journal of Public Legal Education, 6(1). DOI: 10.19164/ijple.v6i1.1293</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="grobid">
          <label>https://grobid.readthedocs.io/</label>
        </application>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor">
          <label>https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor</label>
        </application>
        <application version="1.0" ident="model">
          <label>lfoppiano/grobid:latest-develop</label>
          <desc>https://hub.docker.com/layers/lfoppiano/grobid/latest-develop/images/sha256-735fa2c8facb6f95adef5bf344f7223c2e20aadc9c048f624b83b19d3fbef07b</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-07-12">
        <desc>Extracted 2025-07-12 13:05:47</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<front>From the Field: Law-Related Education as a Branch of Civics Education in the United <lb/>States <lb/>Latia Ward 1 <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Law-related education is &quot;education to equip nonlawyers with knowledge and skills <lb/>pertaining to the law, the legal process and the legal system, and the fundamental <lb/>principles and values on which these are based.&quot; 2 Law-related education is a branch of <lb/>civics education although there is overlap between law-related topics and civics topics <lb/>because both areas include the study of the Bill of Rights, the study of the function of <lb/>government institutions, and the study of one&apos;s rights with respect to voting, jury duty, <lb/>etc. Often, the terms law-related education and civics education are used <lb/>interchangeably. However, there is a trend for law-related education to be associated <lb/>with violence prevention. In this article, I provide an overview of the origin of law-related <lb/>education, a discussion of a law-related education program that I developed for K-12 3 <lb/>students, my reflections on implementing the program, key resources that I found during <lb/></body>

		<front>1 Research Librarian at the Arthur J. Morris Law Library of the University of Virginia School of Law. My <lb/>Twitter handle is @tia_ward17. <lb/></front>

		<listBibl>2 Law-Related Education Act of 1978, Pub. L. No. 95-561, 92 Stat. 2216 (1978) repealed by 20 U.S.C. § <lb/>3863(a)(1) (1982). https://perma.cc/G75R-AFKD and https://perma.cc/8TAQ-M8R6 <lb/></listBibl>
<!-- mixed-reference -->
		<note place="footnote">3 In the United States, K-12 refers to the education of students in grades Kindergarten through twelve <lb/>before these students enter higher education such as college or university. Generally, elementary school <lb/>consists of grades Kindergarten through five, middle school consists of grades six through eight, and high <lb/>school consists of grades nine through twelve. See also Macmillan Dictionary. (n.d.). K-12. <lb/>https://perma.cc/5D7A-SV6S <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

		<body>my planning, an overview of state laws that address K-12 law-related and civics <lb/>education requirements, an analysis of North Carolina&apos;s civics education requirement, <lb/>and an overview of civics education programs outside the K-12 classroom. <lb/>Origin of Law-Related Education <lb/>The late Isidore Starr, social studies teacher and lawyer, is the father of law-related <lb/>education in the United States. 4 In the 1950s and 1960s, he prepared case studies of <lb/>current U.S. Supreme Court cases for use in the classroom. 5 While Starr is one of the more <lb/>well-known people in the field of law-related education, with an American Bar <lb/>Association award being named in his honor, 6 there are others who were instrumental in <lb/>the beginnings of law-related education in the United States. Through the work of Minna <lb/>Post Peyser, the National Assembly on Teaching the Principles of the Bill of Rights <lb/>became affiliated with Columbia University and Teachers College. 7 <lb/>The 1970s were a particularly innovative time for law-related education. 8 In 1972, law <lb/>students founded the Street Law program to teach high school students practical legal <lb/>principles at Georgetown University Law Center in Washington, DC. 9 In 1975, West <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>4 Feinstein, S., &amp; Wood, R. (1995). History of law-related education at 10. (ED401163). ERIC. <lb/>https://perma.cc/KCL2-8VFM <lb/>5 Id. <lb/>6 American Bar Association Division for Public Education. (n.d.). Isidore Starr Award for Excellence in Law-<lb/>Related Education. https://perma.cc/4SZ2-47A9 <lb/>7 Feinstein &amp; Wood, supra note 3 at 12. <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="footnote">8 I have prepared a Timeline of Juvenile Law and Related Topics at https://civicsguide.com/chronology/. <lb/></note>

		<listBibl>9 Arbetman, L. (2018). Street Law, Inc.: context, history and future. International Journal of Public Legal <lb/>Education, 2(1), https://perma.cc/P8RH-2E4D <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

		<body>published the textbook, Street Law: A Course in Practical Law for schools across the nation. 10 <lb/>In 1977, the American Bar Association published the first issue of Update on Law Related <lb/>Education. 11 In 1978, Congress passed the Law-Related Education Act of 1978. 12 <lb/>Practical Life Lessons <lb/>Law-related education programs continue to this day. As a member of the Young <lb/>Lawyers Division of the North Carolina Bar Association, I was invited to speak to a group <lb/>of high school students regarding the North Carolina Bar Association publication entitled <lb/>Life &amp; Laws 101: Citizenship Rights and Responsibilities Over 18. 13 I began thinking about <lb/>how to present rights and responsibilities concepts to high schoolers and my interest in <lb/>law-related education continued well after the presentation had concluded. I began <lb/>saving news articles that dealt with issues of civics education. 14 Later, as part of my course <lb/>work in the Master of Science in Library Science degree program at the University of <lb/>North Carolina at Chapel Hill, I designed and completed a service-learning project called <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>10 National Street Law Institute &amp; District of Columbia Project on Community Legal Assistance. (1975). <lb/>Street law: a course in practical law. West. <lb/>11 The American Bar Association replaced Update on Law Related Education with Insights on Law and Society <lb/>in 2000. <lb/>12 Law-Related Education Act of 1978, Pub. L. No. 95-561, 92 Stat. 2216 (1978) repealed by 20 U.S.C. § <lb/>3863(a)(1) (1982). https://perma.cc/G75R-AFKD and https://perma.cc/8TAQ-M8R6 <lb/>13 North Carolina Bar Association Young Lawyers Division Civic Education Outreach Committee. (2015). <lb/>Life &amp; Laws 101: Citizenship Rights and Responsibilities Over 18. <lb/>http://web.archive.org/web/20150923012636/http://www.ncbar.org/media/95451/Life-and-Laws-101.pdf <lb/></listBibl>
	 <!-- mixed-reference -->
		<note place="footnote">14 Also, during this time, I read a book entitled No One Will Lissen by Lois Forer about Forer&apos;s work as an <lb/>attorney for indigent youth in the late 1960s in Philadelphia. While the book focused on access to justice <lb/>for youth rather than law-related education, it was useful for the insights that Forer provided about <lb/>youth and the legal system. Forer, L.G. (1971). &quot;No one will lissen&quot;: how our legal system brutalizes the <lb/>youthful poor. Grosset &amp; Dunlap. <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Practical Life Lessons 15 at a high school in Durham, North Carolina. My service-learning <lb/>project included teaching ninth and twelfth graders their rights and responsibilities and <lb/>allowing time for questions and discussion. Knowing that not all students would speak <lb/>up during the class discussion, I used exit tickets (end-of-class surveys in which students <lb/>may write responses to questions I have asked them or write down questions to ask me) <lb/>to see how the students were apprehending the information presented. For the session <lb/>entitled &quot;How to Be Safe on Social Media,&quot; I discussed a student who had many Facebook <lb/>friends. The student told her Facebook friends about her father&apos;s confidential settlement <lb/>with his employer. 16 At the end of the lesson, students wrote responses on exit tickets <lb/>such as &quot;Everything you post is linked to some form of personal information,&quot; and &quot;I will <lb/>change my Facebook privacy settings.&quot; For the lesson, &quot;Never Leave Your Luggage <lb/>Alone at the Airport,&quot; I discussed Indonesia&apos;s death penalty for smuggling drugs, the <lb/>Indonesian government&apos;s sentencing to death of people caught drug smuggling, 17 and <lb/>how one should be vigilant regarding one&apos;s luggage at the airport. One student wrote in <lb/>an exit ticket, &quot;I learned how to be more cautious with my luggage.&quot; The students were <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>15 Ward, L. (2015). Practical life lessons [PowerPoint slides]. SlideShare. <lb/>https://www.slideshare.net/practicallifelessons <lb/>16 Green, T. (2014, February 28). Who Is Dana Snay? College Student&apos;s Facebook Bragging Costs Father <lb/>$80,000 Lawsuit Settlement. International Business Times. https://archive.ph/6Q0ga <lb/>17 Phipps, C. (2015, April 28). Who were the eight people executed by Indonesia? The Guardian. <lb/>https://perma.cc/9PPQ-E5M6 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

		<body>interested in the topics presented and they were learning about their rights and <lb/>responsibilities. <lb/>Reflections <lb/>I have had opportunities to reflect on the law-related education program that I designed <lb/>and implemented for high schoolers. The first opportunity came in 2015 when I spoke at <lb/>the North Carolina School Library Media Association (NCSLMA) 2015 Conference and <lb/>discussed the Program&apos;s content. 18 In spring 2016, I reflected on the Program when I <lb/>created a version of the program for middle school students. Another opportunity to <lb/>reflect came when I wrote Five Key Points for Developing an Informative &quot;Know Your Rights&quot; <lb/>Seminar which was published in the fall 2016 issue of the American Bar Association <lb/>Young Lawyers Division Public Education Committee Newsletter. 19 <lb/>These opportunities to reflect have led me to the following conclusions about law-related <lb/>education programs: <lb/>1. Providing attendees with information they can review later, even if the <lb/>information is only a link to a website is key. In 2015, I provided the link to my <lb/>slides for Practical Life Lessons to the students. <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>18 Ward, L. (2015, October 24). A Sea of Information: Navigating the Waters of Digital Citizenship, Rights, and <lb/>Responsibilities [Conference Session]. North Carolina School Library Media Association Conference, <lb/>Winston-Salem, NC, United States. <lb/>19 Ward, L. (2016). Five Key Points for Developing an Informative &quot;Know Your Rights&quot; Seminar. American <lb/>Bar Association Young Lawyers Division Public Education Committee Newsletter, 2(1). https://perma.cc/9STS-<lb/>2VTU <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>2. Providing content that fits the format of the program and the interests of the <lb/>attendees is important. I have led law-related education programs in 20-minute <lb/>and one-hour timeframes. The time-allotted affects the breadth and depth of what <lb/>I am able to cover. In 20 minutes, I am able to introduce a topic and save the <lb/>remaining ten minutes for discussion. In one hour, I am able to provide more <lb/>details about the topic and lead a lengthier group discussion. The topics I selected <lb/>for the initial iteration were based on students&apos; interests and experience. I selected <lb/>&quot;How to be Safe on Social Media&quot; because many students have social media <lb/>accounts. I selected &quot;Never Leave Your Luggage Alone at the Airport&quot; because the <lb/>students attending the program were at a high school that sponsored travel <lb/>programs. <lb/>Key Resources <lb/>In preparing for the law-related education programs that I implemented in spring 2015 <lb/>and 2016, I came across many resources, however six stand out: <lb/>• The original Street Law textbook entitled Street Law: A Course in Practical <lb/>Law, <lb/>• Breaking Rank by Norm Stamper, <lb/>• The Privilege of Silence by Steven M. Salky, <lb/>• Once Upon a Crime by Wanda Cassidy and Ruth Yates, <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>• Law-Related Education as a Delinquency Prevention Strategy: A Three-Year <lb/>Evaluation of the Impact of LRE on Students, by Grant Johnson and Robert <lb/>Hunter, and <lb/>• The Law-Related Education Act of 1978. <lb/>The original Street Law textbook was published by West Publishing Company in 1975 20 <lb/>and is the work of former and current law students of Georgetown University Law Center <lb/>as well as attorneys. It covers practical topics in the field of law such as consumer law, <lb/>housing law, and criminal law. The book has an outline format and hypothetical <lb/>problems for class discussion. While I was lesson planning, the book served as a reminder <lb/>that even from the early days of law-related education programs, law-related education <lb/>was meant to be practical and applied to everyday life. Breaking Rank by Norm Stamper 21 <lb/>and The Privilege of Silence by Steven M. Salky 22 provided useful information such as what <lb/>happens when average citizens encounter the police and the origin of the Miranda <lb/>Warnings as I was planning the Right to Remain Silent activity 23 in 2015. Wanda Cassidy <lb/>and Ruth Yates&apos; book Once Upon a Crime 24 was notable because it supports the notion that <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>20 National Street Law Institute &amp; District of Columbia Project on Community Legal Assistance, supra <lb/>note 9. <lb/>21 Stamper, N. (2006). Breaking rank: a top cop&apos;s exposé of the dark side of American policing. Nation Books. <lb/>22 Salky, S.M., et al. (2014). The privilege of silence: Fifth Amendment protections against self-incrimination. <lb/>American Bar Association. <lb/>23 Ward, L. (2015). Practical life lessons [PowerPoint slides]. SlideShare. <lb/>https://www.slideshare.net/practicallifelessons <lb/>24 Cassidy, W. &amp; Yates, R. (2005). Once upon a crime: using stories, simulations, and mock trials to explore <lb/>justice and citizenship in elementary school. Detselig Enterprises. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

		<body>even younger youth can be introduced to concepts of rights and responsibilities. In Once <lb/>Upon a Crime, Cassidy and Yates provide guidelines and plans for implementing mock <lb/>trials in Kindergarten through fifth grade classrooms. <lb/>Grant Johnson and Robert Hunter&apos;s report entitled Law-Related Education as a Delinquency <lb/>Prevention Strategy: A Three-Year Evaluation of the Impact of LRE on Students prompted me <lb/>to think about the impact of law-related education on students beyond the classroom. <lb/>The report is particularly useful for its enumeration and explanation of features necessary <lb/>for an effective law-related education program. These recommendations include &quot;that <lb/>the system be depicted neither as infallible nor as a nightmare.&quot; 25 The discussion of <lb/>negative realities of the legal system and how people can work within the legal system to <lb/>advocate for their rights needs to be balanced. From the beginning, law-related education <lb/>programs have embraced controversial topics, 26 however, law-related education was not <lb/>intended to be a depressing session where people share grievances or engage in never-<lb/>ending arguments. In the law-related education program that I led in 2015, I spoke of <lb/>practices students could implement in their daily lives such as not putting one&apos;s or one&apos;s <lb/>parents&apos; daily schedule information on social media (and why). <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>25 Johnson, G. &amp; Hunter, R. (1985). Law-Related Education as a Delinquency Prevention Strategy: A Three-Year <lb/>Evaluation of the Impact of LRE on Students (adapted from Law-Related Education Project Final Report, Phase II, <lb/>year 3) (Publication Number 99991). National Criminal Justice Reference Service. https://perma.cc/9ZYA-<lb/>EZQA <lb/>26 Feinstein &amp; Wood, supra note 3. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>The Law-Related Education Act of 1978 was part of a larger Education Amendments Act, <lb/>however, sections 346, 347, and 348 dealt specifically with law-related education. In <lb/>Section 346, Congress stated that it had found that there was a &quot;widespread lack of <lb/>understanding of how our system of law and legal institutions work.&quot; Furthermore, <lb/>&quot;such an understanding is essential&quot; for youth to become knowledgeable and responsible <lb/>citizens and &quot;there is an urgent need for Federal involvement&quot; to develop law-related <lb/>education programs. 27 Section 347 included the definition of law-related education that I <lb/>stated above and empowered a Commissioner to carry out a program of grants so that <lb/>local actors could implement law-related education programs at the local level. These <lb/>programs would be for youth and adults, in community organizations, as well as schools <lb/>and universities. 28 Section 348 authorized $15 million to implement the provisions of the <lb/>Act. 29 Accounting for inflation, the amount would be approximately $62 million in 2021. 30 <lb/>The law was repealed in 1982. 31 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>27 Law-Related Education Act of 1978, Pub. L. No. 95-561, 92 Stat. 2216 (1978) repealed by 20 U.S.C. § <lb/>3863(a)(1) (1982). https://perma.cc/G75R-AFKD and https://perma.cc/8TAQ-M8R6 <lb/>28 Id. <lb/>29 Id. <lb/>30 United States Bureau of Labor Statistics. (n.d.). CPI Inflation Calculator. <lb/>https://www.bls.gov/data/inflation_calculator.htm <lb/>31 Law-Related Education Act of 1978, Pub. L. No. 95-561, 92 Stat. 2216 (1978) repealed by 20 U.S.C. § <lb/>3863(a)(1) (1982). https://perma.cc/G75R-AFKD and https://perma.cc/8TAQ-M8R6 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>State Laws that Address K-12 Law-Related Education Focus on Violence Prevention <lb/>State statutes that address law-related education programs in the K-12 context focus on <lb/>violence prevention as the goal and not necessarily the goal of educating students to learn <lb/>the day-to-day rights and responsibilities of citizens. In Alabama, law-related education <lb/>is &quot;[e]ducation which provides children and youth with the knowledge and skills <lb/>pertaining to the law, the legal process, school safety, and citizenship responsibilities to <lb/>promote law-abiding behavior with the purpose to prevent children and youth from <lb/>engaging in delinquency or violence and enable them to become productive citizens.&quot; 32 <lb/>In Arizona, schools may apply for funding to offset the costs of placing school resource <lb/>officers, juvenile probation officers, school counselors and school social workers at the <lb/>school. 33 Schools that apply for the school safety program must have &quot;[a] plan for <lb/>implementing a law-related education program or a plan that demonstrates the existence <lb/>of a law-related education program as a school safety prevention strategy.&quot; 34 In addition, <lb/>the governing board of schools may &quot;[e] nter into an intergovernmental agreement with <lb/>a presiding judge of the juvenile court to implement a law-related education program as <lb/>defined in section 15-154.&quot; 35 The Colorado Revised Statutes mention &quot;rights and <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>32 ALA. CODE 1975 § 16-1-24.2(a)(2). <lb/>http://alisondb.legislature.state.al.us/alison/CodeOfAlabama/1975/Coatoc.htm <lb/>33 ARIZ. REV. STAT. § 15-154(A) and (B)(2) (2021). https://perma.cc/8JR8-N9Z7 <lb/>34 Id. <lb/>35 ARIZ. REV. STAT. § 15-342(34) (2021). https://perma.cc/FUW8-ALCV <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

		<body>responsibilities of citizenship&quot; as a topic within law-related education programs, 36 <lb/>however, these law-related education programs are not mandated but &quot;strongly <lb/>encourage[d]&quot; 37 and their goal is to promote &quot;behavior which will reduce through <lb/>education the incidence of gang or other antisocial behavior and substance abuse by <lb/>students in the public school system.&quot; 38 In addition, entities such as schools that seek <lb/>funding for comprehensive health education programs must &quot;include provisions for the <lb/>implementation of a law-related education program for the purpose of reducing the <lb/>incidence of gang involvement and substance abuse by students through education&quot; in <lb/>their applications. 39 Iowa requires its department of education to &quot;develop a statewide <lb/>violence prevention program based on law-related education.&quot; 40 Effective July 1, 2022, <lb/>New Mexico will require school resource officers to receive training in &quot;a variety of <lb/>instructional techniques as well as classroom management tools to provide law-related <lb/>education to students.&quot; 41 In Ohio, a certified training program for school resource officers <lb/>must include &quot;Providing assistance on topics such as classroom management tools to <lb/>provide law-related education to students and methods for managing the behaviors <lb/>sometimes associated with educating children with special needs.&quot; 42 New Jersey requires <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>36 COLO. REV. STAT. ANN. § 22-25-104.5(2)(b)(I) (2022). (Lexis Advance). <lb/>37 COLO. REV. STAT. ANN. § 22-25-104.5(1)(b) (2022). (Lexis Advance). <lb/>38 COLO. REV. STAT. ANN. § 22-25-104.5(1)(a) (2022). (Lexis Advance). <lb/>39 COLO. REV. STAT. ANN. § 22-25-105 (2022). (Lexis Advance). <lb/>40 IOWA CODE § 280.9B (2022). https://perma.cc/EY7Z-DUAB <lb/>41 N.M. STAT. ANN. § 29-7-14(B)(4) (2021). https://nmonesource.com/nmos/nmsa/en/nav_date.do <lb/>42 OHIO REV. CODE ANN. § 3313.951(B)(3)(e)(20). https://perma.cc/6E8N-35C7 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>its Police Training Commission to develop a training course for safe school resource <lb/>officers and public school employees who are liaisons to law enforcement. 43 In the <lb/>legislative findings for the law, the New Jersey Session laws note that &quot;most safe schools <lb/>resource officers perform many roles, including law enforcement officer, law-related <lb/>counselor and law-related education teacher.&quot; 44 Throughout the aforementioned statutes, <lb/>law-related education is associated with preventing violence in school and the work of <lb/>school resource officers. <lb/>Colorado, 45 Washington, 46 and Wyoming 47 permit participation in a law-related education <lb/>program as a sentencing option for youth in youth courts. Associating law-related <lb/>education only with policing and violence-prevention is problematic when there is <lb/>controversy over whether police should work in schools at all. Schools in Columbus, Ohio <lb/>removed school resource officers in response to student protests against a police presence <lb/>in the schools. 48 Schools in Madison, Wisconsin removed school resource officers to adopt <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>43 N.J. STAT. § 52:17B-71.8. <lb/>https://lis.njleg.state.nj.us/nxt/gateway.dll?f=templates&amp;fn=default.htm&amp;vid=Publish:10.1048/Enu <lb/>44 2005 N.J. Laws Chapter 276. https://perma.cc/29A8-T5XM <lb/>45 COLO. REV. STAT. ANN. § 19-2.5-1004 (2022) (Lexis Advance). <lb/>46 Participation in law-related education is a youth court disposition. WASH. REV. CODE § 13.40.630(1)(a). <lb/>https://perma.cc/GE95-DH42 Participation in law-related education may be part of a youth court <lb/>agreement. WASH. REV. CODE § 3.72.020(2)(e). https://perma.cc/E75R-8636 <lb/>47 WYO. STAT. ANN. § 7-13-1204(a)(viii)(B) (2021) (Lexis Advance). <lb/>48 Schwartz, S., Sawchuk, S., Pendharker, E. &amp; Najarro, I. (2021, June 4). These districts defunded their school <lb/>police. What happened next? EducationWeek. https://perma.cc/5ZN5-ZGBH <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

		<body>a restorative justice approach and schools in Oakland, California removed school <lb/>resource officers to fulfill a request from the community. 49 <lb/>The origin of law-related education includes instruction on rights, responsibilities, <lb/>government institutions, and current court cases of interest as topics to be taught during <lb/>civics lessons in the classroom, therefore, mentions of law-related education in state law <lb/>should not be confined to the context of violence-prevention and sentences in youth <lb/>court. Those involved with law-related education programs should advise state <lb/>legislatures that law-related education is part of civics education and not primarily a <lb/>sentencing option in youth court or a subject for police officers who work in schools. <lb/>Legislation that Addresses Civics Education in the K-12 Context Throughout the <lb/>United States <lb/>Law-related education is a branch of civics and as such may be taught in schools even <lb/>though the terminology &quot;law-related education&quot; is not used. States that do not mention <lb/>civics education in their laws as well as states that do mention civics education in their <lb/>laws may require civics education through curricula approved by their departments of <lb/>education and therefore, civics may still be taught in their schools. 50 My research has <lb/></body>
<!-- mixed-reference -->
		<listBibl>49 Id. <lb/>50 The report Strengthening Democracy with a Modern Civics Education focuses on civics education <lb/>requirements set by local departments of education and lists all civics education requirements from local <lb/>departments of education for K-12 curricula for all 50 states and the District of Columbia. Jeffrey, A. &amp; <lb/>Sargrad, S. (2019). Strengthening Democracy With a Modern Civics Education. Center for American Progress. <lb/>https://perma.cc/Z7VT-P9FW <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>yielded 28 states that address K-12 civics education in their statutes. Alabama requires <lb/>students to pass a course in government which includes a civics test. 51 Arizona provides <lb/>for the recognition of K-12 students who excel in civics through a state seal of civics <lb/>literacy program. 52 Arkansas&apos; requirements for social studies courses include civics. 53 <lb/>Colorado requires the teaching of history and civil government in schools and requires <lb/>that the civics portion of social studies complies with the subjects outlined in the law. 54 <lb/>In Connecticut, Students are required to take a half-credit course on civics and American <lb/>government to receive a high school diploma and the civics education requirement <lb/>continues for classes graduating in 2023 and later. 55 In Florida, of the three social studies <lb/>credits required to receive a high school diploma, a half-credit must be in government. 56 <lb/>Idaho requires civics education or &quot;instruction in citizenship&quot; in all elementary and <lb/>secondary schools and secondary students must pass a civics test and take a course in <lb/>United States Government. 57 Indiana requires that instruction in the Constitutions of <lb/>Indiana and the United States must be included as part of a civics course. 58 Kansas <lb/>requires instruction in civil government and United States history as well as passing a <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>51 ALA. CODE 1975 § 16-40-10. https://perma.cc/UX52-EJPD <lb/>52 ARIZ. REV. STAT. § 15-259 (2021). https://perma.cc/GCR4-HNZM <lb/>53 ARK. CODE ANN. § 6-16-148 (2022) (Lexis Advance). <lb/>54 COLO. REV. STAT. ANN. § 22-1-104(1)(b) and (c) (Lexis Advance). <lb/>55 CONN. GEN. STAT. § 10-221a(b) and (c). https://perma.cc/7CJ6-J99G <lb/>56 FLA. STAT. § 1003.4282(d) (2021). https://perma.cc/PB4L-9AW5 <lb/>57 IDAHO CODE § 33-1602(6) and (7). https://perma.cc/BB8C-QV76 <lb/>58 IND. CODE § 20-30-5-1(b) (2021). http://iga.in.gov/legislative/laws/2021/ic/titles/001 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>course in United States Government to graduate from high school. 59 Louisiana requires <lb/>all public high schools to provide instruction in civics. 60 Maine requires students to <lb/>receive instruction in civics to receive a high school diploma. 61 Massachusetts requires all <lb/>public schools to teach civics. 62 Michigan requires students to take a civics course to <lb/>receive a high school diploma. 63 The civics course &quot;shall include the form and functions <lb/>of the federal, state, and local governments and shall stress the rights and responsibilities <lb/>of citizens.&quot; 64 Minnesota has set academic standards and civics are part of these <lb/>standards. 65 Missouri requires students to take courses on the constitutions of the United <lb/>States and Missouri, American history, institutions, and civics, and to pass a test on the <lb/>aforementioned subjects to receive a certificate of graduation. 66 Montana aims for <lb/>students to &quot;develop a sense of personal and civic responsibility&quot; and for schools to <lb/>&quot;provide an in-depth understanding of the American political, social, and economic <lb/>systems and the historical context from which they arose&quot; as two of its goals for public <lb/>elementary and secondary schools. 67 Nebraska requires each school board to form a <lb/>committee on American civics which must ensure that the social studies curriculum is <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>59 KAN. STAT. ANN. § 72-3217 (2020). https://perma.cc/NFX9-BEAG <lb/>60 LA. REV. STAT. § 274.1 (2021). https://perma.cc/6XEJ-RKCF <lb/>61 ME. REV. STAT. ANN. tit. 20, § 4722(2)(B) (2021). https://perma.cc/3QDB-NJLE <lb/>62 Massachusetts MASS. GEN. LAWS ch. 71, § 2 (2022). https://perma.cc/LM38-BPRW <lb/>63 MICH. COMP. LAWS § 380.1278a(1)(a)(i) (2021). https://perma.cc/T9BW-B3BW <lb/>64 MICH. COMP. LAWS § 380.1166 (2021). https://perma.cc/M4LQ-ALAG <lb/>65 MINN. STAT. ANN. § 120B.021(4) (2020). https://perma.cc/7L8J-GZKH <lb/>66 MO. REV. STAT. § 170.011(3) (2021). https://perma.cc/3HU2-G67R <lb/>67 MONT. CODE ANN. § 20-1-102(4) and (5) (2021). https://perma.cc/L6XG-U3K9 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>aligned with standards adopted by the State Board of Education and &quot;teaches <lb/>foundational knowledge in civics.&quot; 68 New Hampshire requires students to take a half-<lb/>credit civics course to graduate from high school. 69 New Mexico provides for civic <lb/>engagement experiences for its students. A &quot;civic engagement experience&quot; is one of three <lb/>options that students may select to complete for &quot;college, career and civic readiness.&quot; 70 <lb/>New York requires public day schools to teach civics. 71 North Carolina requires students <lb/>to pass the course &quot;Founding Principles of the United States of America and North <lb/>Carolina: Civic Literacy&quot; to graduate from high school. 72 North Dakota requires students <lb/>to take one unit of social studies which may include civics to graduate from high school. <lb/>73 Oklahoma requires students to take three units of history and citizenship skills to <lb/>graduate from high school. 74 Oregon requires public schools to teach students civics. 75 <lb/>Rhode Island requires middle and high school students to demonstrate proficiency in <lb/>civics education. 76 The Tennessee State Board of Education must include civics in the <lb/>social studies standards and &quot;an understanding of how laws are enacted, and ways <lb/>citizens shape and influence government and governmental actions.&quot; 77 Utah has <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>68 NEB. REV. STAT. ANN. § 79-724(1)(c). https://perma.cc/7JKZ-VX7R <lb/>69 N.H. REV. STAT. ANN. § 189:11. https://perma.cc/963N-97V6 <lb/>70 N.M. STAT. ANN. § 22-2F-2(C) (2022). https://nmonesource.com/nmos/nmsa/en/nav_date.do <lb/>71 N.Y. EDUC. LAW § 3204 (2022). https://perma.cc/TFA6-7YJN <lb/>72 N.C. Gen. Stat. § 115C-81.45(d)(Applicable to students entering the ninth grade in the 2021-2022 <lb/>school year)(1). https://perma.cc/A3XG-EZJM <lb/>73 N.D. CENT. CODE § 15.1-21-02.2(1)(d)(3) (effective through July 31, 2025). https://perma.cc/W9DT-5GPT <lb/>74 OKLA. STAT. TIT. 70 § 11-103.6(B)(4). http://www.oklegislature.gov/osStatuesTitle.aspx <lb/>75 OR. REV. STAT. ANN. § 329.025(8) (2019). https://perma.cc/W4NV-NM5B <lb/>76 R.I. GEN. LAWS ANN. § 16-22-2. https://perma.cc/3ABC-UXG9 <lb/>77 TENN. CODE ANN. § 49-6-1028(b)(1) (2021) (Lexis Advance). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>implemented a pilot program in which the state board will assess whether it will require <lb/>students to complete a civics engagement project to receive a high school diploma. 78 <lb/>Wyoming includes civics in the definition of a &quot;basic academic educational program.&quot; 79 <lb/>Alaska, 80 Illinois, 81 and Vermont 82 are states that have bills addressing civics education <lb/>pending before their legislatures. The Alaska State Legislature&apos;s S.B. 72 requires the board <lb/>&quot;to develop and periodically review a statewide civics education curriculum that is based <lb/>on the civics portion of the naturalization examination used by the United States <lb/>Citizenship and Immigration Services of the Department of Homeland Security and <lb/>primary source documents. The curriculum must also include systems of government <lb/>used by Alaska Natives.&quot; 83 The Illinois General Assembly&apos;s S.B. 1830 requires two years <lb/>of social studies and one of these semesters must be civics. 84 The Vermont General <lb/>Assembly&apos;s S. 17 requires students to take and pass a course in United States civics to <lb/>receive a high school diploma. 85 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>78 UTAH CODE § 53G-10-204(6)(a). https://perma.cc/KQ7J-R984 <lb/>79 WYO. STAT. § 21-4-101(a)(6) (2021) (Lexis Advance). <lb/>80 S.B. 72, 32d Leg., (Alaska 2021). https://perma.cc/C6GB-K4YL and https://perma.cc/KML2-5EYS <lb/>81 S.B. 1830, 102d Gen. Assemb., (Ill. 2021). https://perma.cc/RB7U-B49R <lb/>82 S. 17, 2021 Gen. Assemb., (Vt. 2021). https://perma.cc/R35W-2ZQC and https://perma.cc/6LTJ-UQND <lb/>83 S.B. 72, 32d Leg., (Alaska 2021). https://perma.cc/C6GB-K4YL and https://perma.cc/KML2-5EYS <lb/>84 S.B. 1830, 102d Gen. Assemb., (Ill. 2021). https://perma.cc/RB7U-B49R <lb/>85 S. 17, 2021 Gen. Assemb., (Vt. 2021). https://perma.cc/R35W-2ZQC and https://perma.cc/6LTJ-UQND <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>The United States Citizenship and Immigration Services Civics Test has a role in the <lb/>assessment of student learning. Alabama, 86 Arkansas, 87 Kentucky, 88 Minnesota, 89 <lb/>Montana, 90 Nevada, 91 Tennessee, 92 Texas, 93 and Wisconsin require students to pass an <lb/>examination that contains questions from that test. 94 In addition, the Michigan <lb/>Legislature has required the Michigan State Board of Education to &quot;revise the state <lb/>curriculum content standards for high school social studies to ensure that those content <lb/>standards cover the same content as covered by the 100 questions on the civics portion of <lb/>the naturalization test used by the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services as <lb/>of December 1, 2016.&quot; 95 In, Minnesota, an examination in civics must include questions <lb/>from the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services Civics Test, however a <lb/>school district may not prevent a student from graduating for failing to provide accurate <lb/>answers these questions. 96 Missouri requires that students pass a test that includes <lb/>questions similar to those on the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services <lb/></body>
<!-- mixed-reference -->
			<listBibl>86 Alabama requires students to pass a course in government which includes a test with questions from <lb/>the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services Civics Test. ALA. CODE 1975 § 16-40-10(a). <lb/>https://perma.cc/U3EK-CD9Q <lb/>87 ARK. CODE ANN. § 6-16-149 (2022) (Lexis Advance). <lb/>88 KY. REV. STAT. ANN. § 158.141. https://apps.legislature.ky.gov/lrcsearch <lb/>89 MINN. STAT. § 120B.02 https://perma.cc/KE8L-5M5E <lb/>90 MONT. CODE ANN. § 20-7-119 (2021). https://perma.cc/5PXD-UTRN <lb/>91 NEV. REV. STAT. § 389.009. https://perma.cc/S83S-26X5 <lb/>92 TENN. CODE ANN. § 49-6-408 (2021) (Lexis Advance). <lb/><!-- mixed-reference -->93 Texas requires students to pass a course in United States history which includes questions from the <lb/>United States Citizenship and Immigration Services Civics Test. TEX. EDUC. CODE ANN. § 39.023(C-9). <lb/>https://perma.cc/H8J7-HJPS <lb/>94 WIS. STAT. § 118.33(1m)(a)1 (2021). https://perma.cc/GVW4-DQFQ <lb/>95 MICH. COMP. LAWS § 380.1166 (2021). https://perma.cc/M4LQ-ALAG <lb/>96 MINN. STAT. ANN. § 120B.02, subdivision 3 (2020). https://perma.cc/D6X4-2RDV <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

		<body>Civics Test. 97 South Carolina requires students to take a test with questions from the <lb/>United States Citizenship and Immigration Services Civics Test, however, students are <lb/>not required to pass the test. 98 Utah requires students to pass a &quot;basic civics test&quot; to <lb/>receive a high school diploma. 99 <lb/>Civics Education and &quot;The Founding Principles&quot; -North Carolina and Other States <lb/>North Carolina General Statutes 115C-81.45 addresses civics education. 100 In 2011, the <lb/>North Carolina General Assembly adopted a version of the &quot;Founding Principles Act,&quot; 101 <lb/>a model statute developed by the American Legislative Exchange Council (ALEC). 102 <lb/>ALEC describes itself as &quot;America&apos;s largest nonpartisan, voluntary membership <lb/>organization of state legislators dedicated to the principles of limited government, free <lb/>markets and federalism.&quot; 103 North Carolina&apos;s Founding Principles Act took effect with <lb/>the 2014-2015 school year. 104 The language of the statute may appear neutral, however, <lb/>the Center for Media and Democracy, a self-described &quot;nationally recognized <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>97 MO. REV. STAT. § 170.345(2) and (3) (2021). https://perma.cc/GFV6-2B45 <lb/>98 S.C. CODE ANN. § 59-29-240. https://perma.cc/T9WC-79HT <lb/>99 UTAH CODE ANN. § 53E-4-205 (2021). https://perma.cc/75KW-DMJL <lb/><!-- mixed-reference -->100 N.C. Gen. Stat. § 115C-81.45(d)(Applicable to students entering the ninth grade in the 2021-2022 <lb/>school year)(1). https://perma.cc/A3XG-EZJM <lb/>101 H.R. 588, Sess. 2011 Gen. Assemb., N.C. SESS. LAWS. https://perma.cc/X8MH-QYWS <lb/>102 Ladner, D. &amp; Myslinski, D.J. (2014). Report Card on American Education: Ranking State K-12 Performance, <lb/>Progress and Reform at 113. American Legislative Exchange Council. https://perma.cc/SQ5H-3JW6 and <lb/>American Legislative Exchange Council. (2013). Founding Principles Act. <lb/>https://web.archive.org/web/20130501114024/http://www.alec.org/model-legislation/founding-principles-<lb/>act/ <lb/>103 American Legislative Exchange Council. (n.d.). ABOUT ALEC. https://perma.cc/NT7T-67VD <lb/>104 H.R. 588, Sess. 2011 Gen. Assemb., N.C. SESS. LAWS. https://perma.cc/X8MH-QYWS <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

		<body>watchdog,&quot; 105 noted that the Act could lead to teaching students that the President of the <lb/>United States has &quot;king-like&quot; powers 106 and that the North Carolina Department of Public <lb/>Instruction recommended that the curriculum for the Act come from the Bill of Rights <lb/>Institute, an organization with ties to the politically conservative Koch Brothers. 107 These <lb/>concerns that the Center for Media and Democracy has raised may cause one to question <lb/>whether students will get an unbiased view of civics if they are taught in alignment with <lb/>the &quot;Founding Principles Act.&quot; A recent search within ALEC&apos;s website did not yield the <lb/>model legislation labelled &quot;Founding Principles Act,&quot; 108 however, the website now <lb/>contains a &quot;Civic Literacy Act&quot; which has as its stated purpose &quot;[t]o require during the <lb/>high school years the teaching of the nation&apos;s founding and related documents, which <lb/>shall include the Declaration of Independence, the United States Constitution and the <lb/></body>
<!-- mixed-reference -->
		<listBibl>105 The Center for Media and Democracy&apos;s PRWatch. (n.d.). What we do. https://perma.cc/6ZBL-KQ7N <lb/>106 &quot;This model legislation would require the teaching of a semester-long course on the &quot;philosophical <lb/>understandings&quot; of America&apos;s founders, as incorporated in the Declaration of Independence, the United <lb/>States Constitution, and the Federalist Papers. There are, in fact, many scholarly differences of opinion <lb/>about what weight to accord writings of individuals involved in the drafting and ratification of the <lb/>Constitution. For example, a controversial Bush Administration attorney embraced what he called a <lb/>&quot;Hamiltonian&quot; view of virtually unlimited presidential power as a rationale for presidential violation of <lb/>laws barring torture and warrantless wiretapping. However, Hamilton&apos;s views of king-like presidential <lb/>power were not shared by other leading founding fathers or by the citizens in the states that ratified the <lb/>Constitution and who insisted upon the addition of an explicit Bill of Rights to guard against claims of <lb/>virtually unlimited governmental power to search and seize people and compel them to be witnesses <lb/>against themselves.&quot; The Center for Media and Democracy. ALEC EXPOSED. (2017). Founding Principles <lb/>Act Exposed. https://perma.cc/6ZQD-2PTZ <lb/>107 The Center for Media and Democracy. SOURCEWATCH. (2021). Bill of Rights Institute. <lb/>https://perma.cc/2LZW-V9EE <lb/>108 American Legislative Exchange Council. (2013). Founding Principles Act. <lb/>https://web.archive.org/web/20130501114024/http://www.alec.org/model-legislation/founding-principles-<lb/>act/ <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

		<biblio>Federalist Papers.&quot; 109 It appears that ALEC has replaced the &quot;Founding Principles Act&quot; <lb/>with the &quot;Civic Literacy Act.&quot; <lb/>Other states mention the &quot;founding principles&quot; in their statutes as well. Georgia, 110 <lb/>Louisiana, 111 North Carolina, 112 and South Carolina 113 have statutes which mention the <lb/>&quot;founding philosophy&quot; or &quot;founding principles&quot; of the United States and address <lb/>&quot;federalism&quot; or the &quot;Federalist Papers&quot; in the context of K-12 education. Georgia&apos;s statute <lb/>mentions &quot;limited government&quot; 114 and the Utah Code Annotated mentions &quot;founding <lb/>principles&quot; however, it does not include language regarding federalism and limited <lb/>government. 115 Texas has a founding principles act pending before its legislature. 116 If <lb/>passed, the bill would require &quot;an elective course on the founding principles of the United <lb/>States&quot; in high school curricula. 117 <lb/>Civics Education Programs Outside the K-12 Classroom <lb/>Civics education mandates aside, across the United States, librarians and others offer <lb/>civics education programs to high school students outside the K-12 classroom, yet the <lb/></biblio>

		<listBibl>109 American Legislative Exchange Council. (n.d.). Civic Literacy Act. https://perma.cc/F56U-VESA <lb/>110 GA. CODE ANN. § 20-2-142.1 (2022). (Lexis Advance). <lb/>111 LA. REV. STAT. § 265 (2021). https://perma.cc/7GCT-DL24 <lb/><!-- mixed-reference -->112 N.C. Gen. Stat. § 115C-81.45(d)(Applicable to students entering the ninth grade in the 2021-2022 <lb/>school year)(1). https://perma.cc/A3XG-EZJM <lb/>113 S.C. CODE ANN. § 59-29-155. https://perma.cc/BYT9-B76S <lb/>114 GA. CODE ANN. § 20-2-142.1(c)(1)(B) (2022). (Lexis Advance). <lb/>115 UTAH CODE § 53G-10-204(5)(b). https://perma.cc/H8ZM-U25K <lb/>116 S.B. 1776. 87th Leg., Regul. Sess. (Tex. 2021). https://perma.cc/LS4U-RL2W <lb/>117 S.B. 1776. 87th Leg., Regul. Sess. (Tex. 2021). https://perma.cc/5A6Y-72WP <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

		<body>information shared in these programs is valuable. These programs may focus on knowing <lb/>one&apos;s rights or general information about the legal system in the United States. A Know <lb/>Your Rights Workshop for Teens sponsored by ACLU of Massachusetts and the Boston <lb/>Public Library 118 and the Teen Workshop (Ages 13-17): Know Your Rights sponsored by the <lb/>Glendale Human Coalition and Glendale Police Department of California 119 are <lb/>two examples of such programs. <lb/>The 2018 Cornell Law Institute for High School Students at Cornell Law School had a <lb/>civics or law-related education component through the discussion of the Fourth <lb/>Amendment to the United States Constitution. The 2018 Cornell Law Institute for High <lb/>School Students was an outreach program sponsored by the Cornell Law Library and did <lb/>not provide academic credit for the attendees. The overall goal of the Law Institute was <lb/>to introduce high school students to legal concepts and legal careers. <lb/>During the Law Institute, I led a write-around activity 120 regarding the Fourth <lb/>Amendment. Before the write-around activity, I discussed definitions of legal terms such <lb/>as warrant and probable cause and then gave the students a short news article to read <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>118 Boston Public Library. (2020). Know Your Rights Workshop for Teens. https://perma.cc/ZKR8-4N6N <lb/>119 City of Glendale. (2019). Teen Workshop (Ages 13-17): Know Your Rights. https://perma.cc/P8M2-FRFQ <lb/><!-- mixed-reference -->120 The write-around activity allows students time to think about answers to a question and make <lb/>connections between concepts before engaging in a large group discussion. There are many variations of <lb/>write-arounds (which are discussed in the book entitled The Best-Kept Teaching Secret: How Written <lb/>Conversations Engage Kids, Activate Learning, and Grow Fluent Writers, K-12. Daniels, H. &amp; Daniels, E. <lb/>(2013). The best-kept teaching secret: how written conversations engage kids, activate learning, and grow fluent <lb/>writers, K-12. Corwin. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

		<body>regarding the circuit split 121 and a summary of relevant case law. For the write-around <lb/>activity, students were in small groups of between three and five. I directed them to write <lb/>their answers to the prompts on the same large paper (each group had its own large piece <lb/>of paper). I instructed the students not to speak to one another for the 15 minutes of <lb/>writing. Next, in their small groups, students discussed what they had written. After the <lb/>small-group discussions, I facilitated a large group discussion based on what the students <lb/>had written. The writing prompts consisted of the following questions: <lb/>1. What do you know about probable cause so far?, <lb/>2. What does the article about car searches based on marijuana smoke remind you of <lb/>in things you have seen on social media or TV?, and <lb/>3. What do you think will happen next? Do you think the U.S. Supreme Court will <lb/>resolve the circuit split? Why or why not? 122 <lb/>The writing portion of the activity gave the students time to think before sharing their <lb/>ideas with the class. I ended the lesson with a reflection activity during which we <lb/>discussed the question: &quot;If you were going to explain today&apos;s write-around activity to <lb/>someone who&apos;s not in our class, what would you say?&quot; 123 The main goal of the activity <lb/></body>
<!-- mixed-reference -->
		<listBibl>121 &quot;When two or more circuits in the United States court of appeals reach opposite interpretations of <lb/>federal law. This is sometimes a reason for the Supreme Court to grant certiorari.&quot; Wex. (n.d.). Circuit <lb/>Split. https://perma.cc/693C-WC7Q <lb/>122 Ward, L. (2018, June 28). Where There&apos;s Smoke…A Write-Around Activity Regarding the Circuit Split Over <lb/>Marijuana-Based Car Searches [Conference Session]. 2018 Cornell Law Institute for High School Students, <lb/>Ithaca, NY, United States. <lb/>123 Id. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>was to prompt students to think about why different courts have different rationales <lb/>when making decisions about similar sets of facts. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>From the inception of law-related education, organizers of law-related education <lb/>programs have endeavored to make the programs practical by covering topics that the <lb/>students would need to know in daily life. Although the federal Law-Related Education <lb/>Act was repealed in 1982, states continue to address K-12 civics education in their <lb/>statutes. Recently, state legislatures that have used the term &quot;law-related education&quot; in <lb/>the K-12 context have focused on law-related education for violence prevention and <lb/>within the context of youth courts. Law-related education is about knowing one&apos;s rights <lb/>and responsibilities as a citizen even in situations where one has not been accused of <lb/>breaking the law and there needs to be a concerted effort to bring the essence of law-<lb/>related education within the purview of state legislatures. Additional programs aimed <lb/>toward teenagers that are organized outside the K-12 school context such as &quot;Know Your <lb/>Rights Workshops&quot; and other programs, for example the Cornell Law Institute for High <lb/>School Students, are also valuable in educating youth regarding civics and law-related <lb/>education. Law-related education is more than violence prevention. It is a branch of civics <lb/>that is a necessary part of K-12 education. </body>

  
	</text>
</tei>