<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State in France and Germany</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Roger</forename>
          <surname>Cotterrell</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-09-16T17:28:54.283610Z">16.09.2025 17:28:54</date>
        <title>grobid.training.segmentation [article/dh-law-footnotes]</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.12775$1$clr.2013.002</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Uniwersytet Mikolaja Kopernika/Nicolaus Copernicus University</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2013</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.12775/clr.2013.002</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Roger Cotterrell. (2013). Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State in France and Germany. Comparative Law Review, 15(0), 21. DOI: 10.12775/clr.2013.002</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-09-16T17:28:54.283610Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">0707645</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-09-16T17:28:54.283610Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-10-01T15:22:21.115Z" status="draft" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections2</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-10-01T15:52:25.677Z" status="draft" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Final corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Comparative Law Review <lb/>15 2013 <lb/>Nicolaus Copernicus University <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.12775/CLR.2013.002 <lb/>Roger Cotterrell  <lb/>CLASSICAL SOCIAL THEORY <lb/>AND IDEAS OF RESPONSIBILITY AND THE STATE <lb/>IN FRANCE AND GERMANY <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Social theory can aid comparative legal studies by revealing currents of social ideas in which <lb/>law develops. A comparison of major contributions to French and German social theory between the <lb/>mid-nineteenth and the early twentieth century presents striking contrasts in understandings of the <lb/>nature of legal responsibility and the function of the state. It shows two different movements of <lb/>thought: one elaborating a view of law mainly as a technology of government overseeing and <lb/>co-ordinating individual interests; the other emphasising the law&apos;s importance in nurturing social <lb/>solidarity and facilitating collective responsibility. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>Comte -Von Stein -Tönnies -Weber -Gierke -solidarism -Durkheim -Duguit -individualism -<lb/>collective responsibility -solidarity -functions of law -modern state <lb/> Anniversary Professor of Legal Theory, Queen Mary and Westfield College, University of <lb/>London, and Fellow of the British Academy. This article is adapted, abbreviated and revised <lb/>from a paper published in M. Lobban, J. Moses (eds), The Impact of Ideas on Legal Development, <lb/>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press 2012. <lb/>22 | Roger Cotterrell <lb/></front>

    <body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>Can the study of social theory provide a background for comparative <lb/>inquiries about changing legal ideas? This article explores this issue by <lb/>asking how key contributions to social theory in France and Germany, from <lb/>the mid-nineteenth to the early twentieth century, influenced, supported, <lb/>or reflected changing legal ideas about individual and social responsibility. <lb/>To limit the scope of inquiry here the focus is on ideas about the state&apos;s <lb/>role, especially with regard to public service and social provision, and <lb/>about the importance (reflected in legal debates and law reform) of social, <lb/>collective or state responsibility confronting laissez-faire individualism. <lb/>Social theory can be defined as the systematic, empirically-oriented <lb/>study of the &quot;social&quot; (the recurring forms, or patterned features, of <lb/>interactions and relations between people) in terms of its historical <lb/>variation, and its variation between different societies. Why might this <lb/>theory be significant in considering legal debates around responsibility and <lb/>the role of the state? There is little evidence that social theory has directly <lb/>influenced legal reform, but, in the period addressed by this article, there <lb/>was certainly cross-influence between jurists and social theorists. <lb/>The social theorist Max Weber, for example, interacted extensively <lb/>with leading German jurists of his day 1 . Similarly, Émile Durkheim&apos;s <lb/>sociology, which dominated French social thought in the early decades <lb/>of the twentieth century, powerfully influenced the work of important <lb/>jurists such as Léon Duguit, Emmanuel Lévy and Paul Huvelin -the latter <lb/>two actually being part of Durkheim&apos;s team of collaborators 2 . But <lb/>philosophy was a more important theoretical influence on jurists in this <lb/>period, as for example in the Kantian and Hegelian bases of juristic legal <lb/>theory especially in Germany. Social theorists have often written with the <lb/>aim of promoting change or influencing public debate, but distances <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>1 See S. P. Turner, R. A. Factor, Max Weber: The Lawyer as Social Thinker, London, New York: <lb/>Routledge 1994; P. Honigsheim, On Max Weber, London: Collier-Macmillan Limited 1968, <lb/>pp. 68-75; J. Radkau, Max Weber: A Biography, Cambridge: Polity Press 2009, pp. 258-9, 261-6; <lb/>and, generally, M. Weber, Max Weber: A Biography, New York, London, Sydney, Toronto: John <lb/>Wiley and Sons 1975. <lb/>2 R. Cotterrell, Living Law: Studies in Legal and Social Theory, Aldershot: Ashgate 2008, chs. 6 <lb/>and 7; R. Cotterrell, Émile Durkheim: Law in a Moral Domain, Edinburgh: Edinburgh University <lb/>Press 1999, chap. 3. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>23</page> | 
    
    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>
    
    <body>between social theory and legal practice are considerable. Evidence of <lb/>direct influence is likely to be rare. Far more significant is the point that by <lb/>studying the different standpoints of lawyers, law reformers and social <lb/>theorists it may be possible to integrate perspectives on a shared legal and <lb/>social history. <lb/>Social theory, at least in its most prominent forms, reflects something <lb/>of the generally felt problems, assumptions, aspirations and contradictions <lb/>of its time. Typically, it seeks insight into the nature and sources of <lb/>contemporary social conditions, and their possible future. It aims to <lb/>capture the prevailing sense of movement in social life, and society&apos;s <lb/>self-understandings. Legal thought also, in various ways, reflects these <lb/>matters, but through the prism of professional and political priorities 3 . <lb/>Perhaps, then, social theory can reveal a broad context of social experience <lb/>in which legal issues arise, but its focus will be on the social as a whole, <lb/>and on law and the state only insofar as they are aspects of, or shaping <lb/>influences on, the social. <lb/>The themes focused on in this article are (i) the development <lb/>of conceptions of law as a modern technical instrument of government, <lb/>available to protect or arbitrate between citizens&apos; interests; and <lb/>(ii) the development of ideas of law as existing to nurture and define social <lb/>solidarity and collective responsibility. Both themes characterise main currents <lb/>in social theory from the mid-nineteenth to the early twentieth century. <lb/>A focus on them highlights very different emphases in French and German <lb/>theory in this period. Indeed, the tension between these emphases may be <lb/>especially revealing with respect to changing perceptions of responsibility <lb/>and of the role of the state. <lb/>II. PIONEER SOCIOLOGY: LAW AS OBSTACLE AND SOLUTION <lb/>Sociology (a term coined by the French philosopher Auguste Comte <lb/>in 1839) is said to have been &quot;born in a state of hostility to law&quot; 4 . This <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>3 R. Cotterrell, The Politics of Jurisprudence: A Critical Introduction to Legal Philosophy, 2 nd edn., <lb/>Oxford: Oxford University Press 2003. <lb/>4 N. S. Timasheff, An Introduction to the Sociology of Law, Cambridge: Harvard University <lb/>Committee on Research in the Social Sciences 1939, p. 45. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>24</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>hostility is clearly revealed in Comte&apos;s work which saw the progress <lb/>of human thought as passing through theological and metaphysical stages <lb/>to enter (at different times in the different sciences) a final, modern stage <lb/>in which positivist thought -focusing only on observable facts and <lb/>discarding metaphysics -would triumph in all fields. According to <lb/>Comte&apos;s prediction, all positivist sciences will &quot;converge on sociology, <lb/>because the whole hierarchy of being culminates in the human species&quot; 5 , <lb/>the life of which must be rationally guided by a science of the social. <lb/>So, sociology, not law, is to define the responsibilities of the citizen. <lb/>It will reveal the mechanisms by which the social order sustains itself and <lb/>the part that everyone must play in sustaining these mechanisms. Duty <lb/>flows directly from the social functions that sociology explains. Law retains <lb/>no role in this scientifically regulated world because it purports to address, <lb/>without scientific understanding but through &quot;the vague and turbulent <lb/>discussion of rights&quot; 6 , conflicts that the positivist science of society will <lb/>remove. Law is &quot;a metaphysical vestige (…) absurd as well as immoral&quot; <lb/>and positivism &quot;causes the idea of law to disappear irretrievably&quot; 7 . <lb/>In Comte&apos;s thought both conservatism (resignation to the existing <lb/>order of society) and an idea of progress (the possibility of continuous <lb/>rational reform) loom large, both being removed from the field of human <lb/>will and located now in an impersonal science. So it is easy to see why <lb/>Comte&apos;s sociology treats ideas of will and responsibility in legal thought as <lb/>its enemy: Comtean responsibility does not originate in the individual&apos;s <lb/>acts and motivations, but is fixed by the nature of society. It is established <lb/>not juridically, but by scientific laws that govern social cohesion and set its <lb/>requirements. <lb/>In this context governmental authority must be a unifying force. Comte <lb/>saw that modern, large-scale societies required extensive occupational <lb/>specialisation. But in contrast to the view that Durkheim would later take, <lb/>he thought that the increasing division of labour could undermine social <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>5 R. Aron, Main Currents of Sociological Thought, vol. 1, London: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson 1965, <lb/>pp. 101-2. <lb/>6 A. Comte, Cours de philosophie positive (1830-42), vol. 6, Paris: J. B. Baillière et fils 1869, <lb/>pp. 651-2, [as quoted in:] Timasheff, supra note 6, p. 45. <lb/>7 A. Comte [quoted in:] G. Gurvitch, Sociology of Law, London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, <lb/>Trench, Trubner &amp; Co 1947, p. 12. <lb/></listBibl>

    <page>25</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>
    
<body>cohesion, decomposing society &quot;into a multitude of unconnected <lb/>corporations which scarcely seem to belong to the same species&quot;; <lb/>governmental power must &quot;contain and so far as possible arrest this fatal <lb/>disposition to the fundamental dispersion of ideas, sentiments and <lb/>interests&quot;; it would have to &quot;intervene appropriately in the daily <lb/>performance of all the various functions of the social economy, to sustain <lb/>continuously the idea of the whole and the sentiment of common <lb/>solidarity&quot; 8 . <lb/>Thus, at the beginning of modern sociology, Comte calls for <lb/>government intervention in aid of solidarity -a theme that would resonate <lb/>through much later French thought. But law is not seen as important to this <lb/>intervention; it is merely an arena of irrational conflict where rights are <lb/>fought over without knowledge of their wider social context. A challenge <lb/>is thrown down -if a somewhat unclear one, given Comte&apos;s ultimately <lb/>vague views on the future of the state and on appropriate structures <lb/>of government 9 -to rethink issues of social responsibility outside <lb/>the framework of the rights and duties of private law. <lb/>*** <lb/>At much the same time as Comte wrote, Lorenz von Stein contributed <lb/>foundations for sociological thought in Germany. Von Stein&apos;s work is now <lb/>virtually ignored but in 1850 10 he set out a general theory of social <lb/>development that &apos;laid the cornerstone of what we today call &quot;historical <lb/>sociology&quot; 11 and is &quot;the first German sociology&quot; 12 . Influenced initially by <lb/>Hegel&apos;s philosophy of history, Von Stein replaced such philosophical <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>8 A. Comte, Cours de philosophie positive, vol. 4, Paris: J. B. Baillière et fils 1864, pp. 429, 430-1, <lb/>[as quoted in:] S. Lukes, Émile Durkheim: His Life and Work, Harmondsworth: Penguin 1973, <lb/>pp. 141, 142. <lb/>9 H. E. Barnes, The Social and Political Philosophy of Auguste Comte, [in:] H. E. Barnes, <lb/>An Introduction to the History of Sociology, Chicago: University of Chicago Press 1948, <lb/>pp. 81-109. For the apparent change over time in Comte&apos;s ideas on the organisation and <lb/>radical decentralisation of governmental functions see e.g. R. Vernon, Auguste Comte and the <lb/>Withering-Away of the State, Journal of the History of Ideas 1984, vol. 45, p. 549. <lb/>10 L. v. Stein, The History of the Social Movement in France, 1789-1850, Totowa, New Jersey: <lb/>Bedminster Press 1964. <lb/>11 K. Mengelberg, Lorenz von Stein and his Contribution to Historical Sociology, Journal of the <lb/>History of Ideas 1961, vol. 22, pp. 267, 268. <lb/>12 H. Marcuse, Reason and Revolution: Hegel and the Rise of Social Theory, London: Routledge <lb/>and Kegan Paul 1955, p. 375. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>26</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
      
    <body>speculation with a &quot;science of society&quot;, an empirical inquiry into processes <lb/>by which social life had developed into the form of modern industrial <lb/>organisation. <lb/>The principles of the Declaration des droits de l&apos;homme et du citoyen, <lb/>Von Stein declared, are the &quot;first basic law of the new society&quot; 13 brought <lb/>into being by the French Revolution of 1789. They express fundamental <lb/>laws &quot;structurally separate from state and government&quot; and rooted in <lb/>society itself 14 . These principles are not primarily political but social -&quot;the <lb/>constitution of society&quot; 15 rather than of the state. They do not depend on <lb/>a particular form of state, must be seen as antecedent to state action, and <lb/>can be asserted, if necessary, against it. Thus, natural (scientific) &quot;laws&quot; <lb/>of society&apos;s development are the real motor of modern European history. <lb/>What are these scientific (sociological) &quot;laws&quot;? The Declaration of the <lb/>Rights of Man asserted a principle of equality before the law, which gives <lb/>free rein to the pursuit of self-interest and enables established privileges <lb/>and statuses to be challenged. Thereafter, acquired property becomes <lb/>the foundation of social order and organisation. &quot;For the liberated <lb/>individual (…) property became the natural and indeed primary means of <lb/>shaping his own worth and individuality&quot; 16 and the concrete expression <lb/>of abstract, universal liberty. These conditions support &apos;economic society&apos; <lb/>based on free acquisition. This, in turn, becomes &quot;industrial society&quot;, based <lb/>on capital accumulation which is made possible by the mechanisation <lb/>of production. <lb/>The contradictions of this society are expressed in the contrast between <lb/>universal abstract freedom (in theory) and differential access to property <lb/>(in practice). Hence the conflict of social classes (which are defined by this <lb/>differential access) arises as the proletariat becomes conscious of its <lb/>situation. The result is the threat of violence, civil war and the <lb/>self-destruction of society. And this result is produced by the nature of <lb/>the social -not by the nature of politics, law, or the state. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>13 Von Stein, Geschichte der sozialen Bewegung in Frankreich von 1789 bis auf unserer Tage, vol. 1, <lb/>Munchen: Drei Masken Verlag 1921, p. 209, [as quoted in:] E.-W. Böckenförde, State, Society <lb/>and Liberty: Studies in Political Theory and Constitutional Law, New York: Berg 1991, p. 121. <lb/>14 Böckenförde, supra note 13, p. 121. <lb/>15 Ibid., p. 126. <lb/>16 Ibid., p. 127. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>27</page> | 
    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>
    
    <body>If many of these ideas sound familiar it is, of course, because they are <lb/>so close in outline to Marx&apos;s analysis of the historical trajectory of capitalist <lb/>society. But they were presented by Von Stein before Marx had set out his <lb/>mature theories. There is clear evidence that Marx had read Von Stein&apos;s <lb/>work, perhaps drawing much from it 17 while condemning it for its <lb/>bourgeois defence of the state and the established order. Unlike Marx, <lb/>Von Stein sought to save industrial society from itself, enlisting the state <lb/>as central to this rescue  operation. But his warnings of social unrest were <lb/>largely ignored in the growing optimism in Germany, from the <lb/>mid-nineteenth century, for national unity and a national state 18 . <lb/>Despite the utter disparity in their fame today, Von Stein is more <lb/>significant in the context of this article than Marx because, as <lb/>Ernst-Wolfgang Böckenförde has argued 19 , he can be seen as a proponent in <lb/>1850 of the social or welfare state and of a science of society to serve it. <lb/>He combines a partially Hegelian idealisation of the state with sociological <lb/>realism. The state&apos;s function is to guarantee liberty and property, and in <lb/>principle it is above class antagonisms as &quot;the community acting as <lb/>a personality&quot; 20 . But this is an ethical ideal, &quot;merely an abstraction&quot; 21 . <lb/>The state, in reality, serves the interests of the ruling classes, or becomes <lb/>absolutist and remote, losing support in society. Its only possibility of <lb/>retaining its authority and regulatory power is to enlist the support of wide <lb/>social groupings by guaranteeing the practical (not just formal) liberty <lb/>of all, and facilitating their participation in economic and social life <lb/>especially through the creation of extensive opportunities for property <lb/>acquisition. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>17 J. Singelmann, P. Singelmann, Lorenz von Stein and the Paradigmatic Bifurcation of Social <lb/>Theory in the Nineteenth Century, British Journal of Sociology 1986, vol. 37, pp. 431, 447; <lb/>Marcuse, supra note 12, p. 374. As Werner Cahnman puts it, &quot;Marx&apos;s sociology is therefore as <lb/>Steinian as his economics is Ricardian&quot;. See W. Cahnman, Book review: Lorenz von Stein: <lb/>The History of the Social Movement in France, 1789-1850; Translated by Kaethe Mengelberg, <lb/>American Journal of Sociology 1966, vol. 71, p. 746. <lb/>18 Böckenförde, supra note 13, pp. 117-18. <lb/>19 Ibid. in chap. 6. <lb/>20 Von Stein, supra note 13, p. 16, [as quoted in:] Singelmann, Singelmann, supra note 17, <lb/>p. 436. See also Mengelberg, supra note 11, p. 269; Marcuse, supra note 12, p. 381. <lb/>21 Von Stein, supra note 13, p. 49, [as quoted in:] Mengelberg, supra note 11, p. 269; and see <lb/>Singelmann, Singelmann, supra note 17, pp. 437-8. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>28</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>As Böckenförde remarks, &quot;The logic of this idea, once grasped, took <lb/>Lorenz von Stein beyond liberalism as early as 1850&quot; 22 . Indeed, it led him, <lb/>in his later work on &quot;administrative science&quot; (Verwaltungswissenschaft), <lb/>to develop what now appear as foundations of the modern discipline of <lb/>public administration 23 ; seeking to devise ideas and techniques for use <lb/>in the management of the social by the state 24 . <lb/>Comte and Von Stein presented ideas about law, state and <lb/>responsibility that reappear in new guises in later social theory up to <lb/>the early twentieth century. Among these is the idea in Comte&apos;s work that <lb/>responsibility should be seen as the consequence not of the individual&apos;s <lb/>will and acts, but of social conditions. Von Stein, again like many later <lb/>theorists, sees the state as responsible for creating adequate conditions for <lb/>individual participation in social and economic life. And, for both writers, <lb/>governmental regulatory tasks are not to be set politically or determined by <lb/>the form that the state or governing power takes in a certain time and place. <lb/>They are to be set by what &quot;society&quot; demands of this power -a matter <lb/>which social theory, not juristic analysis, must reveal. The displacement <lb/>of the jurists 25 would allow the emergence of practical administrative <lb/>sciences; sciences of social management, which Comte envisaged in theory <lb/>and Von Stein devoted his career to developing. One way or another, <lb/>the private assertion of rights or of claims of responsibility would <lb/>be subordinated to a scientifically-directed regulation of the social. <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>22 Böckenförde, supra note 13, p. 133. <lb/>23 C. Thornhill, The Domain of Public Administration, Journal of Public Administration 2006, <lb/>vol. 41, pp. 793, 794. <lb/>24 M. R. Rutgers, Can the Study of Public Administration Do Without a Concept of the State? <lb/>Reflections on the Work of Lorenz von Stein, Administration &amp; Society 1994, vol. 26, p. 395. <lb/>25 In this perspective social science overwhelms juristic science. Unsurprisingly, from the <lb/>juristic side, the complaint was made that Von Stein&apos;s &quot;conception of society shows the <lb/>modern tendency unduly to extend its meaning, and to include [in it] the functions <lb/>of government and law and national economics&quot;: F. Berolzheimer, The World&apos;s Legal <lb/>Philosophies, Boston: Boston Book Company 1912, p. 327. Comte&apos;s subsuming of law and <lb/>government in the social attracted the same criticism: ibid., pp. 311-12. Yet some jurists made <lb/>similar claims for the precedence of the social: Otto von Gierke wrote (in his Natural Law and <lb/>the Theory of Society, 1500 to 1800, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press 1950, p. 224) that <lb/>&quot;We shall no longer ask whether the state is prior to law, or law is prior to the state. We shall <lb/>regard them both as inherent functions of the common life which is inseparable from the idea <lb/>of man&quot;. But such general juristic speculations (part of lawyers&apos; &quot;internal&quot; debates) posed <lb/>no threat to lawyers&apos; preserves, unlike the creation of entirely new research fields <lb/>of sociology or social theory to study law and government historically as social phenomena. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>29</page> | 
  
    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>

    
    <body>III. SOCIOLOGICAL PESSIMISM: INDIVIDUALISM AND BUREAUCRACY AS <lb/>INEVITABLE <lb/>Von Stein&apos;s urgent advocacy of state action is strikingly at odds with <lb/>the seemingly resigned, almost fatalistic outlook of some influential later <lb/>German social theory, especially that of Ferdinand Tönnies and Max <lb/>Weber. In their best-known theoretical works neither of these late <lb/>nineteenth and early twentieth century writers sees modern society <lb/>as oriented to developing social or collective responsibility, though both <lb/>recognise some counter-tendencies to the dominant privatised lines <lb/>of development. Tönnies expresses nostalgia for decaying social forms -the <lb/>village and the close-knit kin group -in which common responsibility <lb/>is natural and needs no formal embodiment in law. But he sees the <lb/>dominant kinds of modern social organisation as entirely different. There <lb/>are perhaps, at best, pockets of economic life, such as co-operative <lb/>movements, where something more than the atomistic individual existence <lb/>characteristic of modern society might be created 26 . <lb/>Weber, correspondingly, analyses what he sees as cold, morally empty <lb/>forms of modern routine; the bureaucratised, rule-bound organisation <lb/>of the social. Again, the main focus is on individuals pursuing their own <lb/>projects, fixing their responsibilities primarily in terms of contract and <lb/>private law. When Weber observes new political or legal developments <lb/>that challenge this individualistic universe with its formal, technical law, <lb/>his response is ambivalent. Thus, both theorists, in the main, portray <lb/>a world of individual responsibility and of the legal and social conditions <lb/>that sustain it, and harbour grave doubts as to whether anything different <lb/>can be built. <lb/>*** <lb/>Tönnies&apos; book Gemeinschaft und Gesellschaft, first published in 1887, <lb/>attracted immediate attention, if some initial criticism for its &quot;tone of <lb/>pessimistic resignation&quot; 27 and it has remained influential to the present <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>26 F. Tönnies, Community and Association, London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul 1955, pp. 227-8. <lb/>27 H. Liebersohn, Fate and Utopia in German Sociology 1870-1923, Cambridge, Massachusetts: <lb/>MIT Press 1988, pp. 11-12. It has, however, been argued that, after the publication of his 1887 <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>30</page> | 
    
    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>day. His dichotomy of Gemeinschaft (community) and Gesellschaft <lb/>(association), which he uses to identify the transition to modern society, <lb/>is paralleled by comparable dichotomies in social theory (especially <lb/>Durkheim&apos;s contrasting of mechanical and organic solidarity, discussed <lb/>below). Gemeinschaft is a social bond or community of kinship intimacy <lb/>(&quot;blood&quot;), closeness in a shared environment (&quot;locality&quot;), ideas held <lb/>in common (&quot;mind&quot;) or, often, all of these 28 . In it, the main identity <lb/>of individuals is as part of a communal unity. Built on similarity <lb/>of experience, thought and feeling, Gemeinschaft can flourish only in <lb/>relatively small-scale social networks and so is becoming irrelevant to <lb/>the large-scale networks of modern life; its place being usurped <lb/>by Gesellschaft, the opposing social form. <lb/>Gesellschaft is a social bond based on calculation or rational will, <lb/>in which individuals remain &quot;essentially separated in spite of all uniting <lb/>factors (…) and there exists a tension against all others&quot; 29 . The typical and <lb/>fundamental bond of Gesellschaft is contract, and its perfect legal <lb/>embodiment is the joint stock company 30 . Responsibility arises from <lb/>deliberate undertakings or the need to protect the individual in the life of <lb/>the association. But Gesellschaft requires powerful state support in a way <lb/>that Gemeinschaft does not. While the latter is a natural unity, the former is <lb/>an artificial one: &quot;individuals remain in isolation and veiled hostility <lb/>toward each other so that only fear of clever retaliation restrains them from <lb/>attacking one another&quot; 31 . State power exercised through law is needed <lb/>to sustain Gesellschaft. <lb/>Ultimately, Tönnies, like Von Stein, portrays modern capitalist society <lb/>as unstable, dependent on state law for stability and needing increasingly <lb/>extensive state intervention to achieve this. Yet what the state will enforce <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>book, Tönnies&apos; outlook gradually became more optimistic. This led him to a sustained search <lb/>for opportunities to recover, perhaps in new forms, aspects of Gemeinschaft in modern <lb/>conditions, or to transform Gesellschaft structures productively. See A. Mitzman, Tönnies and <lb/>German Society, 1887-1914: From Cultural Pessimism to Celebration of the Volksgemeinschaft, Journal <lb/>of the History of Ideas 1971, vol. 32, p. 507, and C. Adair-Toteff, Ferdinand Tönnies: Utopian <lb/>Visionary, Sociological Theory 1995, vol. 13, p. 58. <lb/>28 Tönnies, supra note 26, p. 48. <lb/>29 Ibid., p. 74. <lb/>30 Ibid., pp. 225-7, 264. <lb/>31 Ibid., p. 262. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>31</page> | 
    
    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>

    <body>are the calculated, measured, private law responsibilities of isolated <lb/>individuals, not the conditions for mutually-supportive interaction typical <lb/>of integrated communities. <lb/>*** <lb/>If Tönnies&apos; most influential work expresses a longing for <lb/>a pre-capitalist world no longer possible, Max Weber&apos;s rejects all utopias <lb/>and shows a resignation to modern political, economic and social <lb/>conditions that are, in his view, unlikely to change fundamentally. <lb/>The longest section of his magnum opus Economy and Society is titled <lb/>&quot;Economy and Law (Sociology of Law)&quot; 32 . Much of it discusses historical <lb/>processes of rationalisation of law, presenting these partly as a matter <lb/>of comparative doctrinal legal history and partly in relation to political, <lb/>economic and other changes. <lb/>For Weber, rational law is rule-governed law and the bases of law&apos;s <lb/>rational strength and its authority as a rule-system, may be formal <lb/>or substantive. Substantively rational law is determined and legitimated by <lb/>the principles of an ideological system other than law itself -for example, <lb/>ethics, religion or political values. For a time, natural law doctrines in <lb/>the West provided a general input of substantive rationality into law, and <lb/>gave law&apos;s authority a basis in values or beliefs. But one of Weber&apos;s most <lb/>important claims is that, in modern conditions, &quot;the axioms of natural law <lb/>have lost all capacity to provide the fundamental basis of a legal system <lb/>(…). The disappearance of the old natural law conceptions has destroyed <lb/>all possibility of providing the law with a metaphysical dignity by virtue <lb/>of its immanent qualities. In the great majority of its most important <lb/>provisions, it has been unmasked all too visibly, indeed, as the product <lb/>or the technical means of a compromise between conflicting interests&quot; 33 . <lb/>Many factors influence the substantive content of modern law, but, for <lb/>Weber, its integrity and authority as a rule-system have become primarily <lb/>a matter of its technical usefulness in compromising conflicting interests and <lb/>of its formal rationality in which &quot;definitely fixed legal concepts in the form <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>32 M. Weber, Economy and Society: An Outline of Interpretive Sociology, Berkeley, CA: <lb/>University of California Press 1978, pp. 641-900. <lb/>33 Ibid., pp. 874-5. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>32</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>of highly abstract rules are formulated and applied&quot; 34 . Legal thought, <lb/>insofar as it is formally rational, tends to become a logical calculus of rules. <lb/>While formal logical legal rationality never exists in a pure form, it is <lb/>nevertheless a crucial, dominant characteristic of modern law. This <lb/>formality allows the &quot;integration of all analytically derived legal <lb/>propositions&quot; into an &quot;internally consistent, and, at least in theory, gapless <lb/>system of rules&quot; 35 . <lb/>The importance of modern law&apos;s tendency to formal rationality is that <lb/>it removes the need for any consistent reference to &quot;external&quot; moral <lb/>or political sources to validate this law. Modern law, for Weber, is a largely <lb/>self-sustaining normative structure validated by its technical sophistication <lb/>and overall usefulness in regulating the interplay of private interests. <lb/>Beyond that, most importantly, it is the servant and support of the modern <lb/>state. Its formal logic of rules defines authority impersonally and so <lb/>underpins modern bureaucracy and capitalistic business organisation, <lb/>as well as the idea of the rule-governed state (Rechtsstaat), with its everyday <lb/>administrative operations very much like those of a machine largely <lb/>removed from human volition. <lb/>What is portrayed here most significantly is the morally-impregnable, <lb/>fortress-like character of the modern state, seemingly free to do good or <lb/>evil without challenges to its legitimacy from moral or political critics <lb/>or from the social convulsions that Von Stein had feared. Weber was aware, <lb/>like Tönnies, of the dissatisfactions of his time with capitalist society, <lb/>served by seemingly morally cold law and relentless state power. But he <lb/>devotes only a few pages to what he calls &quot;The Anti-Formalistic Tendencies <lb/>of Modern Legal Development&quot; 36 , offering brief comments on juristic and <lb/>political developments at the beginning of the twentieth century that <lb/>challenged legal formalism&apos;s dominance and effects. These included: <lb/>the growth of legal principles of &quot;good faith and fair dealing&quot;; demands <lb/>for &quot;social law&quot; linked to &quot;the emergence of the modern class problem&quot; 37 ; <lb/>and the revival of Catholic natural law doctrines and various critical juristic <lb/>movements in Germany. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>34 Ibid., p. 657. <lb/>35 Ibid., p. 656. <lb/>36 Ibid., pp. 882-9. <lb/>37 Ibid., p. 886. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>33</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>

    <body>Weber sees all of these as fated to be ineffectual when viewed in the <lb/>wider perspective of the processes of rationalisation that have entrenched <lb/>modern economic, legal and political forms. Like Tönnies in Gemeinschaft <lb/>und Gesellschaft, he has little confidence in the possibilities of significant <lb/>change in these forms. &quot;Weber could not conceive of any genuine <lb/>alternative to the capitalist economic system&quot; 38 or of any radical <lb/>reorientation of the private law serving it. Bureaucracy and economic <lb/>routine increasingly made life seem like an &quot;iron cage&quot; 39 , but attempts <lb/>to create a socialist order would merely produce, less efficiently, more <lb/>bureaucracy and formal rules. Again like Tönnies, Weber was far from <lb/>discounting the need for reform, but this would be in the context of <lb/>&quot;an inevitable and prolonged capitalist era&quot; 40 . And what may have <lb/>concerned him far more than legal individualism&apos;s deafness to calls for <lb/>a social law of collective responsibility was the ultimately poor adaptability <lb/>of formal legal reasoning to the means-ends calculations of economic <lb/>entrepreneurs 41 . <lb/>*** <lb/>As social theorists, Tönnies and Weber have powerfully influenced <lb/>general understandings of the legal and social changes that occurred <lb/>in their era. There is, however, little evidence that they themselves <lb/>contributed significantly to those changes. Rather, they wrote in ways that <lb/>enable us now to gain a better perspective on influences that did operate. <lb/>Affinities might easily be found, for example, between Tönnies&apos; evocation <lb/>of pre-modern Gemeinschaft life and the jurist Otto von Gierke&apos;s erudite <lb/>reconstruction of the communal forms of Genossenschaft (association) in old <lb/>Germanic law 42 . Gierke&apos;s scholarly presentation of the legal past reflected <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>38 W. J. Mommsen, Max Weber and German Politics 1890-1920, Chicago: University of Chicago <lb/>Press 1984, p. 104. <lb/>39 M. Weber, The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism, London: G. Allen &amp; Unwin 1930, <lb/>p. 181. <lb/>40 Weber [quoted in:] Mommsen, supra note 38, p. 105. <lb/>41 See Weber, supra note 32, p. 885. <lb/>42 See e.g. O. v. Gierke, Associations and Law: The Classical and Early Christian Stages, Toronto, <lb/>Buffalo: University of Toronto Press 1977; idem, Community in Historical Perspective, <lb/>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press 1990; idem, Natural Law, supra note 25; <lb/>idem, Political Theories of the Middle Age, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press 1900; idem, <lb/>The Development of Political Theory, New York: H. Fertig 1966. <lb/></listBibl>
      
    <page>34</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>an emotional sense of &quot;loss of community&quot; directly comparable with that <lb/>of Tönnies, and Gierke&apos;s rich, romantic evocation of half-forgotten <lb/>characteristics of Germanic law powerfully influenced debates that shaped <lb/>the content of the new German Civil Code of 1900 43 . Ultimately, neither <lb/>Gierke nor Tönnies appear merely as reactionaries seeking to recover <lb/>a golden past. Both of them eventually attacked the individualism of <lb/>modern law for facilitating the exploitation of the socially disadvantaged 44 . <lb/>Gierke&apos;s great influence was mainly due to his juristic skill in <lb/>presenting aspects of the reforms he advocated as being deeply rooted <lb/>in national legal tradition. His efforts may have contributed to an outcome <lb/>in which, while the Civil Code largely expressed Romanist legal <lb/>individualism, it became accepted that legislation reflecting different <lb/>(social) principles was needed to supplement it 45 . Tönnies and Weber, both <lb/>admirers of Gierke&apos;s juristic scholarship, saw his organic imagery of <lb/>socio-legal development as lacking adequate empirical foundation and <lb/>being insufficiently informed about social (especially economic) forces of <lb/>change 46 . Gierke&apos;s ideas were tailored to the political and juristic debates <lb/>of his time and provided rhetorical ammunition for these in a way that <lb/>Weber&apos;s and Tönnies&apos; did not 47 . <lb/>Yet Weber&apos;s and Tönnies&apos; characterisations of legal and social history <lb/>still retain a significant presence in scholarly debate, while Gierke&apos;s have <lb/>ceased to do so. Weber, in particular, was able to see more clearly than <lb/>either Gierke or Tönnies, the capacity of modern law as an instrument of <lb/>government, free of tradition and fixed moral points. Most importantly, <lb/>he recognised the state&apos;s power to direct this instrument in hitherto <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>43 M. John, Politics and the Law in Late Nineteenth-Century Germany: The Origins of the Civil <lb/>Code, Oxford: Clarendon Press 1989, chap. 5. <lb/>44 Ibid., pp. 109-11; Mitzman, supra note 27. <lb/>45 M. F. John, The Politics of Legal Unity in Germany, 1870-1897, Historical Journal 1985, vol. 28, <lb/>pp. 28, 341. <lb/>46 Mommsen, supra note 38, p. 11; W. J. Cahnman, R. Heberle (eds), Ferdinand Toennies on <lb/>Sociology: Pure, Applied and Empirical, Chicago: University of Chicago Press 1971, pp. 22, 32-33; <lb/>A. Brand, Against Romanticism: Max Weber and the Historical School of Law, Australian Journal <lb/>of Law and Society 1982, vol. 1, p. 94. <lb/>47 Cf. A. Black, Editor&apos;s Introduction to Gierke, Community, supra note 42, pp. xiv, xxx: &quot;Gierke <lb/>furnishes a splendid example of the kind of thinking against which (…) Weber (…) reacted <lb/>(…); he was the type case of what Weber called «the professor carrying the marshal&apos;s baton <lb/>of the statesman or reformer in his knapsack»&quot;. <lb/></listBibl>
    

    <page>35</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>

    <body>inconceivable ways, yet to do so in the framework of a capitalist social <lb/>order that legal reform would not significantly disturb. But Weber&apos;s <lb/>message was addressed to &quot;science&quot; and the long term, not to &quot;politics&quot; <lb/>and the legal debates of the moment 48 . <lb/>IV. SOCIOLOGICAL OPTIMISM: SOLIDARITY AND SOCIAL RESPONSIBILITY <lb/>French social theory, developed during the first half century of the <lb/>Third Republic (from 1871 to the early decades of the twentieth century), <lb/>offers a striking contrast to dominant strands of German pessimism <lb/>or ambivalence about possibilities for major social change, and also <lb/>to German portrayals of the state&apos;s central significance, as guarantor of the <lb/>social and as the sovereign source of all law. My concern here is merely <lb/>to illustrate this difference by reference to some leading contributions <lb/>to French theory in this period. <lb/>Informing them are (i) the continuing influence of Comte&apos;s conviction <lb/>that social science could point to ultimate values on which modern society <lb/>should be founded; (ii) echoes of Jean-Jacques Rousseau&apos;s idea of <lb/>sovereignty not as the possession of a state apparatus but as the <lb/>crystallising in legal form of a popular &quot;general will&quot; -&quot;so that the natural <lb/>relations [of social life] are always in agreement with the laws on every <lb/>point, and law only serves (…) to assure, accompany and rectify them&quot; 49 ; <lb/>(iii) the legacy of the Declaration of the Rights of Man; and, finally, <lb/>(iv) a widespread awareness (especially after military defeat in 1871, <lb/>the bitter experience of the Paris Commune in that year, and economic <lb/>unrest from the 1880s) of an urgent need for French national unity and <lb/>a social solidarity capable of bridging class divides. <lb/>*** <lb/>The last of these themes clearly informs the &quot;solidarism&quot; of Charles <lb/>Secrétan, Alfred Fouillée and Léon Bourgeois spanning the period from the <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>48 Cf. M. Weber, Politics as a Vocation and Science as a Vocation, [in:] H. H. Gerth, <lb/>C. W. Mills (eds), From Max Weber: Essays in Sociology, London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul 1948, <lb/>especially, pp. 115-17, 150-3. <lb/>49 J.-J. Rousseau, The Social Contract and Discourses, London: Dent 1973, p. 205. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>36</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>mid-nineteenth century to the early decades of the twentieth. It reflected <lb/>a need to circumvent and defuse the perceived threat of working class <lb/>agitation associated with socialism and radical syndicalism, and to do so <lb/>without recourse to authoritarian solutions. It sought to counter traditional <lb/>conservative Catholic paternalism with a genuine reformism focused, <lb/>inter alia, on changing conceptions of social responsibility and social <lb/>entitlement. Solidarism is less a social theory than a political-moral <lb/>philosophy, significant here not just for its general influence as &quot;a kind <lb/>of official philosophy for the Third Republic&quot; 50 but as an important part <lb/>of the climate of thought in which Durkheim&apos;s social theory developed 51 . <lb/>The solidarists saw justice as governed by the need for social <lb/>solidarity 52 : &quot;The justice of egoism is not justice&quot; 53 and -significantly -the <lb/>state is not the primary agent of solidarity since it can create a kind of unity <lb/>only through constraint. Justice is to be realised in free, egalitarian <lb/>associations with the &quot;associationist principle&quot; penetrating property <lb/>relations. &quot;Participation in profits and in the management of enterprises <lb/>will transform all industries into vast production cooperatives (…). The free <lb/>cooperative association is (…) the future&quot;, wrote Secrétan in 1889 54 ; <lb/>the state is not superior to other associations. Its right to exist comes from <lb/>the fact that it is needed to enforce law, but law (droit) arises outside it, <lb/>and rights express the sharing of liberty. <lb/>Free association is an inalienable right. All voluntary associations are <lb/>founded on contract and contract is the basis of all solidarity. Society, <lb/>for Fouillée, is a &quot;contractual organism (…) freely desired and consented <lb/>to&quot; 55 . Associations can and must flourish independently of the state which, <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>50 C. Bouglé, Le solidarisme, Paris: M. Giard 1924, p. 7. <lb/>51 Cf. Lukes, supra note 8, pp. 350-4. <lb/>52 The following summary draws especially on G. Gurvitch, L&apos;idée du Droit Social: Notion <lb/>et système du droit social. Histoire doctrinale depuis le 17e siècle jusqu&apos;à la fin du 19e siècle, Paris: <lb/>Librairie de Recueil Sirey 1932, pp. 567-89; see also J. E. S. Hayward, Solidarity: The Social <lb/>History of an Idea in Nineteenth-Century France, International Review of Social History 1959, <lb/>vol. 4, p. 261. <lb/>53 C. Secrétan, Philosophie de la liberté, vol. 2, Paris: A. Durand 1865, p. 471, [as quoted in:] <lb/>Gurvitch, supra note 52, p. 572. <lb/>54 C. Secrétan, Études sociales, Paris: F. Alcan 1889, pp. 176, 178, [as quoted in:] Gurvitch, <lb/>supra note 52, p. 574. <lb/>55 A. Fouillée, La science sociale contemporaine, Paris: Hachette et cie 1910, [quoted in:] <lb/>Gurvitch, supra note 52, p. 577. <lb/></listBibl>

    <page>37</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>

    <body>in itself, &quot;is not flexible enough to steer economic life&quot; 56 . Justice, for <lb/>Fouillée, &quot;is the obligation to give each person what is due to him by reason <lb/>of his function in the living totality and his solidarity with the whole <lb/>society&quot; 57 . Léon Bourgeois introduced the idea of a &quot;social debt&quot; owed by <lb/>and to all of society&apos;s interdependent members, reflecting natural <lb/>conditions of solidarity, and of a &quot;social quasi-contract&quot; of membership in <lb/>society -&quot;quasi&quot; because based on what parties would have wanted had <lb/>they been able to consent in advance to the regime of law under which they <lb/>would live 58 . <lb/>In this way solidarism created a rhetoric of social unity across class <lb/>divides -offered to dispel memories of a defeated (in 1871) and <lb/>compromised state that had often appeared to betray revolutionary hopes <lb/>of liberty, equality and fraternity. It sought to replace these memories with <lb/>promises of a new social contract involving a sense of the responsibility of <lb/>social elites to recognise workers&apos; entitlement to decent living conditions <lb/>in return for their productivity. <lb/>Georges Gurvitch, writing in the early 1930s, criticised solidarism&apos;s <lb/>inconsistencies, especially its commitment to legal individualism (signalled <lb/>by the basing of all analysis on contractual relations of individuals) despite <lb/>its concern to transcend individualism as a foundation of social <lb/>organisation 59 . Solidarism proposed that rights and responsibilities should <lb/>be socially determined by the conditions of association. Yet it saw these <lb/>conditions as originating in a real or &quot;quasi&quot; expression of individual wills, <lb/>founding a contract. Solidarism developed no social theory to explain <lb/>the content or significance of solidarity as an idea. Ultimately, Fouillée <lb/>admitted that solidarity was an ideal 60 , not a social fact. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>56 Fouillée [quoted in:] Gurvitch, supra note 52, p. 580. <lb/>57 A. Fouillée, La democratie politique et sociale en France, Paris: F. Alcan 1923, p. 18, [as quoted <lb/>in:] Gurvitch, supra note 52, p. 580. See generally, J. E. S. Hayward, &apos;Solidarity&apos; and the <lb/>Reformist Sociology of Alfred Fouillée, American Journal of Economics and Sociology 1963, <lb/>vol. 22, pp. 205, 303. <lb/>58 See M. Borgetto, La doctrine solidariste de Léon Bourgeois: une nouvelle definition des rapports entre <lb/>le politique, le social et le droit, [in:] C. M. Herrera (ed.), Les juristes face au politique: Le droit, <lb/>la gauche, la doctrine sous la IIIe République, Paris: ime 2003, pp. 35-56; Gurvitch, supra note 52, <lb/>pp. 582-5; and, generally, S. Audier, Léon Bourgeois: fonder la solidarité, Paris: Michalon 2007. <lb/>59 Gurvitch, supra note 52, pp. 575, 589; and see Borgetto, supra note 58, pp. 51-52. <lb/>60 Gurvitch, supra note 52, p. 579. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>38</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>*** <lb/>It was left to Émile Durkheim -sharing the solidarists&apos; desire for <lb/>a society aware of the conditions of its own moral cohesion -to provide <lb/>a social theory to explain the nature and forms of solidarity. In his <lb/>De la division du travail social, published in 1893 but originating in lectures <lb/>in 1887-8, he identified two kinds of social solidarity: mechanical -based <lb/>on shared values, experience and understandings uniting individuals <lb/>or groups; and organic -based on the interdependence of individuals <lb/>or groups having functionally differentiated roles 61 . <lb/>If the solidarists saw solidarity as an ideal, Durkheim argued (against <lb/>Comte) that it could exist as a natural condition of complex societies having <lb/>a highly developed division of labour. In these societies, functional <lb/>differentiation creates conditions of interdependence. But he argued also <lb/>that social cohesion in modern society is not a natural consequence of <lb/>the free play of individual interests. A moral framework enshrined in law <lb/>is needed to guarantee it. The cohesion of society is not based on contracts <lb/>because contracts need non-contractual conditions of existence 62 . The moral <lb/>phenomenon of organic solidarity, arising directly from the social fact <lb/>of interdependence, provides these conditions. <lb/>Tönnies, Durkheim suggested, had rightly characterised Gemeinschaft, <lb/>which is essentially mechanical solidarity, and rightly seen it as declining <lb/>in modern industrial societies. But he was wrong to see these societies as <lb/>inherently unstable and held from self-destructive conflict only by the state. <lb/>What Tönnies ignored, in Durkheim&apos;s view, was the bond of organic <lb/>solidarity that arose from the specialisation of social and economic roles <lb/>and functions in complex modern societies 63 . Organic solidarity based on <lb/>interdependence created cohesion, but needed to be supported by law. <lb/>Contrary to Tönnies&apos; view, law is not required to compensate for <lb/>a pervasive absence of solidarity as if this were an inevitable problem <lb/>of modern society. Instead, law must guard against &quot;abnormal forms&quot; 64 <lb/>of social organisation that may disrupt solidarity, such as the isolation, <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>61 É. Durkheim, The Division of Labour in Society, Basingstoke: Macmillan 1984. <lb/>62 Ibid., p. 162. <lb/>63 É. Durkheim, Communauté et société selon Tönnies, 1889, [reprinted in:] É. Durkheim, Te tes, <lb/>Tome 1: e le ments d&apos;une the orie sociale, Paris: E ditions de Minuit 1975. <lb/>64 Durkheim, supra note 61, bk 3. <lb/></listBibl>
    

    <page>39</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>

    <body>repression or discriminatory treatment of particular social groups <lb/>or classes, which will exclude them from society&apos;s networks of <lb/>interdependence. <lb/>Durkheim&apos;s theory clearly signals a new view of responsibility 65 . <lb/>The meaning of responsibility is fixed by society, not by the expectations <lb/>of individuals. Contracts, for example, are not merely private relations <lb/>between the parties, but depend on regulation that society supplies. <lb/>So their terms should reflect the requirements of solidarity. They should <lb/>be &quot;just contracts&quot; that do not abuse unequal bargaining power 66 . But what <lb/>exactly are solidarity&apos;s requirements? In Durkheim&apos;s early writings <lb/>the morality of modern society is presented as a kind of &quot;governmental <lb/>morality&quot; of good social management. In a society of complex <lb/>specialisation people must fulfil their specialised roles conscientiously. <lb/>Society, through the state and law, imposes the requirement to do <lb/>so -adequately to fulfil one&apos;s function, or that of one&apos;s social group. <lb/>This idea of functionally-determined responsibility is close to Comte&apos;s. <lb/>Later, however, Durkheim&apos;s writings develop a different emphasis 67 : <lb/>the unifying morality of a highly differentiated society can only be one that <lb/>emphasises the equal humanity of all its members, as individuals entitled <lb/>to dignity and respect 68 . Solidarity in modern society cannot be based <lb/>on tradition, blind adherence to authority, or the mere interplay of private <lb/>interests, but only on universal respect for others as individual human <lb/>beings -an ultimate value that must pervade modern law (requiring, <lb/>for example, humane treatment of offenders). This value-system of moral <lb/>individualism (le culte de l&apos;individu) 69 is presented by Durkheim as a direct <lb/>derivation from social theory. He sees it as the only universal, unifying <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>65 See J.-L. Génard, Responsabilité et normativité dans l&apos;école et la pensée de Durkheim, [in:] P. Robert, <lb/>F. Soubiran-Paillet, M. Van Der Kerchove (eds), Normes, normes juridiques, normes pénales: <lb/>Pour une sociologie des frontiers, vol. 2, Paris: L&apos;Harmattan 1997. <lb/>66 É. Durkheim, Professional Ethics and Civic Morals, London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul 1957, <lb/>chap. 18; Durkheim, supra note 61, pp. 316-22; See, generally, C. J. Sirianni, Justice <lb/>and the Division of Labour: A Reconsideration of Durkheim&apos;s Division of Labour in Society, Sociological <lb/>Review 1984, vol. 32, p. 449. <lb/>67 R. Cotterrell, Émile Durkheim: Law in a Moral Domain, Edinburgh: Edinburgh University <lb/>Press 1999, chs. 7-9. <lb/>68 É. Durkheim, L&apos;individualisme et les intellectuels, 1898 [reprinted in:] É. Durkheim, La science <lb/>sociale et l&apos;action, Paris: Presses universitaires de France 1987. <lb/>69 See É. Durkheim, Leçons de sociologie, Paris: Presses universitaires de France 1950, p. 199. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>40</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>morality fully consistent with the nature of solidarity in complex societies. <lb/>Hence, for Durkheim, a sociological understanding of the nature <lb/>of solidarity makes it possible to specify the ultimate parameters of <lb/>individual rights and responsibilities, to be determined not juristically <lb/>or philosophically but by the conditions of complex, modern social life. <lb/>*** <lb/>Durkheim&apos;s ideas were much discussed by jurists in France <lb/>and beyond and are highly relevant in considering how legal responsibility <lb/>might be reformed. Yet they cannot be said to have influenced legal debate <lb/>in the direct way solidarism did. Solidarism postulated solidarity as <lb/>an ideal, not as a sociological concept. As such, like Gierke&apos;s speculative <lb/>appeal to history in Germany, solidarism in France offered an attractive <lb/>rhetoric for political and legal debate (and had a major influence on legal <lb/>reform campaigns in such areas as social welfare, health and safety, and <lb/>industrial conditions.) 70 But it was not rooted in a sociology that, like <lb/>Durkheim&apos;s, sought to explain the historical developments it proclaimed. <lb/>At the same time, Durkheimian social theory lacked wide, direct <lb/>juristic influence partly because it did not provide an unambiguous <lb/>rhetoric for law reform debates. Even among Durkheim&apos;s followers there <lb/>were disagreements about conclusions to be drawn from theory. One <lb/>of them, Paul Fauconnet, argued that modern legal ideas of responsibility, <lb/>emphasising the subjective intentions of the individual wrongdoer, were <lb/>&quot;an immense impoverishment&quot; 71 because attributions of responsibility <lb/>must be made to meet the needs of social solidarity as a whole, and could <lb/>not be restricted by a subjective, &quot;spiritualised&quot; emphasis on any particular <lb/>individual&apos;s state of mind. <lb/>The implication might be that Durkheim&apos;s outlook on the <lb/>&quot;naturalness&quot; of solidarity in modern society (based on universal respect <lb/>for the individual) and the need for legal intervention only to correct <lb/>&quot;abnormal&quot; conditions was too complacent. A revolution in legal <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>70 J. F. Stone, The Search for Social Peace: Reform Legislation in France, 1890-1914, Albany: <lb/>State University of New York Press 1985. <lb/>71 P. Fauconnet, La responsabilité. Étude de sociologie, Paris: F. Alcan 1928, p. 350; cf. Cotterrell, <lb/>supra note 67, pp. 107-8; J. Piaget, The Moral Judgment of the Child, Harmondsworth: <lb/>Penguin 1977, pp. 315-28. <lb/></listBibl>
    

    <page>41</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>

    <body>and social ideas might be needed. This was the conclusion of another <lb/>Durkheimian, the jurist Paul Huvelin. Acknowledging Durkheim&apos;s <lb/>sociological methods as fundamental, he nevertheless argued that organic <lb/>solidarity is not a natural condition of modern societies (although <lb/>interdependence is). So, law&apos;s directive, coercive power is vital to control <lb/>the serious conflicts endemic in modern social life 72 . <lb/>V. CONCLUSION: COMPETING VISIONS OF LAW AND STATE <lb/>Durkheim&apos;s writings on the state 73 emphasise, in the tradition <lb/>of Comte, government&apos;s role as an agent of society. They offer no insights <lb/>such as Weber&apos;s into the state&apos;s bureaucratic structure or the legal <lb/>foundations of its legitimacy. Since Durkheim and Weber never wrote <lb/>about each other&apos;s work, the gulf in perceptions remains unbridged. <lb/>That their social theories follow very different directions is clear, especially <lb/>on matters of legal responsibility. For Durkheim, law and morality <lb/>are always closely interrelated and legal responsibility must be shaped <lb/>by the value system of moral individualism if it is to contribute to social <lb/>solidarity. Even if some of his followers thought this approach might not <lb/>go far enough to emphasise social bases of responsibility, they certainly <lb/>agreed that responsibility is more than a matter between individuals, <lb/>as portrayed in most modern legal conceptions of delict. Dictated <lb/>by society for social ends, it is, by implication, capable of being adjusted <lb/>into forms that best serve the needs of social solidarity. <lb/>Weber is silent on such matters, but one might presume to speak <lb/>for him: Weberian responsibility is surely merely what law and state <lb/>(rather than &quot;society&quot;) decree it to be. In Weber&apos;s view, no consistent <lb/>value-orientations shape modern law; only a mass of disparate policy <lb/>influences give it substance. Legal responsibility is thus the outcome <lb/>of law&apos;s primarily formal-rational and pragmatic prescriptions. Like law <lb/>itself, it is a technical instrument to serve the needs of the state and to <lb/>compromise conflicting private interests. Separated from moral intuitions, <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>72 On Huvelin&apos;s work see R. Cotterrell, Living Law: Studies in Legal and Social Theory, <lb/>Aldershot: Ashgate 2008, chap. 7. <lb/>73 Cotterrell, supra note 67, chs. 10 and 11. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>42</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>legal responsibility is a transaction cost in private dealings or a device <lb/>for governmental coercion. <lb/>The theories of Tönnies and Weber present an image of the largely <lb/>settled law, state, and society of modern capitalism, especially as coloured <lb/>by the experience of a new (German) political unity and centralised <lb/>governmental power. By comparison, the ideas of the solidarists address <lb/>the moral disquiet, increasingly widespread in France, about this modern <lb/>social and politico-legal order in the late nineteenth and early twentieth <lb/>century. Correspondingly, the Durkheimians focused on the need to direct <lb/>law and political power to meet the requirements of solidarity. <lb/>Unsurprisingly, among social theorists it was Durkheim who appealed <lb/>most strongly to reform-minded French jurists in the period. But his ideas <lb/>were useful to them mainly insofar as the sociological idea of solidarity <lb/>could be turned into a philosophical justification for legal reform and <lb/>a rhetorical tool in legal discourse. <lb/>By far the most important and influential appropriation of the concept <lb/>of solidarity in this way was by the public lawyer Léon Duguit. A colleague <lb/>of Durkheim for some years at the University of Bordeaux, <lb/>he enthusiastically adopted the Durkheimian view that law is both <lb/>an instrument and a reflection of social solidarity. Duguit argued, like <lb/>the solidarists, that the source of law, understood in this &quot;objective&quot; way, <lb/>is not the state but the conditions of life of the society in which law exists. <lb/>As such it is &quot;contingent on social fact (…) a spontaneous creation of social <lb/>life&quot; 74 . In his later writings Duguit saw law as based in the consciousness of <lb/>the mass of citizens who view it as necessary to maintain social solidarity. <lb/>Clearly, state law does not always correspond to this &quot;objective&quot; law 75 <lb/>rooted in social fact. But, for Duguit, the authority of the former ultimately <lb/>depends on its congruence with the latter and not on state sovereignty. <lb/>Indeed, he rejected state sovereignty and claimed that the state has <lb/>authority only when it acts to nurture solidarity. The state is subject to law <lb/>-a social law dictated by the needs of solidarity. It must become a public <lb/>service state, its treasury being &quot;so to speak, a friendly society&quot; for the <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>74 C. Eisenmann, Léon Duguit, [in:] D. Sills (ed.), International Encyclopedia of the Social <lb/>Sciences, vol. 4, New York: Macmillan 1968, pp. 305, 306. <lb/>75 L. Duguit, Objective Law, Columbia Law Review 1920, vol. 20, p. 817; ibid. 1921, vol. 21, <lb/>pp. 17, 126 and 242. <lb/></listBibl>
    

    <page>43</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Classical Social Theory and Ideas of Responsibility and the State <lb/></note>

    <body>benefit of its citizens when they suffer harm in the ordinary course of social <lb/>co-operation; in such circumstances &quot;society as a whole should intervene <lb/>to repair the consequences&quot; 76 . <lb/>Duguit assumes Durkheim&apos;s view that law must serve social solidarity, <lb/>but does so without engaging with the sociology that underpins this, and <lb/>his legal politics is close to that of the solidarists. Other jurists, notably <lb/>Maurice Hauriou, strongly criticised Duguit&apos;s rejection, in his legal theory, <lb/>of subjective rights (seen as expressions of individual will) in favour of his <lb/>idea that law expresses objective social functions 77 . But Duguit&apos;s arguments <lb/>had a huge impact on French legal thought 78 . They entrenched in it an <lb/>understanding that responsibility arises in society, out of social associations <lb/>of various kinds, and that the state has a new role as an instrument of <lb/>collective welfare: a role in which -in Durkheim&apos;s conception, influenced <lb/>by Comte and Rousseau -the state &quot;thinks&quot; solutions on behalf of society 79 . <lb/>All this is far removed from Tönnies&apos; and especially Weber&apos;s tendency <lb/>to predict little long-term impact from demands for social law and social <lb/>responsibility. Which of these visions was ultimately the more prescient? <lb/>Perhaps only Von Stein, among the theorists considered here, sensed <lb/>clearly both the unavoidable modern need for some kind of social or <lb/>welfare state and also the sheer difficulty of establishing such a state on <lb/>a stable basis, given the organisational history of Western state forms <lb/>which Weber would explore. Yet in juristic contexts it was not difficult <lb/>in the half-century after 1870 to adopt ideas about law&apos;s foundations <lb/>in society (rather than the state) and to use these to criticise individualistic <lb/>orientations of legal thought and juristic fixations on state sovereignty. <lb/>The story of the main forms of social theory bearing on legal ideas <lb/>of responsibility and the role of the state in this period seems, however, <lb/>to be one of voices talking past each other. On one side was a recurring <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>76 L. Duguit, Souveraineté et liberté, Paris: F. Alcan 1922, p. 168, [as quoted in:] <lb/>J. E. S. Hayward, Solidarist Syndicalism: Durkheim and Duguit, Sociological Review 1960, vol. 8, <lb/>pp. 185, 194. <lb/>77 See e.g. M. Hauriou, The Two Realisms, [in:] A. Broderick (ed.), The French Institutionalists: <lb/>Maurice Hauriou, Georges Renard, Joseph T. Delos, Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University <lb/>Press 1970, pp. 45-51. <lb/>78 E. Pisier-Kouchner, Le service public dans la théorie de l&apos;état de Léon Duguit, Paris: Librairie <lb/>ge ne ral de droit et de jurisprudence 1972. <lb/>79 Cotterrell, supra note 67, chap. 10. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>44</page> | 

    <note place="headnote">Roger Cotterrell <lb/></note>
    
    <body>vision of a state that could -and must -be shaped to fulfil, as a central part <lb/>of its task, an emerging expectation that responsibility would be shared <lb/>socially, or determined by social need. Such a vision implied the necessity, <lb/>if not the inevitability, of social legislation in many fields and a declining <lb/>emphasis on private law solutions to issues of responsibility. On the other <lb/>side were very different ideas that prefigured current neo-liberal <lb/>scepticisms about any such wider responsibility. These ideas portrayed <lb/>the modern state as allied with forms of atomistic individualism reflecting <lb/>increasing social complexity. In such a perspective, the task of managing <lb/>innumerable, endlessly varied conflicts of private interests appeared to be <lb/>at the heart of that complexity. The implication was that an important part <lb/>of the state&apos;s role would continue to be to provide reliable procedures <lb/>and guarantees for private law claims of individual responsibility. </body>


	</text>

</TEI>