<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance in Europe</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Christian</forename>
          <surname>Joerges</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-10-17T09:00:05.061Z">10/17/2025 10:00:05 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.14276$1$2384-8901$1$443</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2015</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.14276/2384-8901/443</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Christian Joerges. (2015). Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance in Europe. Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, (), None. DOI: 10.14276/2384-8901/443</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-04T16:57:30.539041Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">0707645</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-10-04T16:57:30.539041Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>9 <lb/>Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, Special Issue (2015) <lb/>Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance <lb/>in Europe <lb/>Christian Joerges * <lb/></front>
              
      <body>1. Unity in Diversity as Europe's Vocation <lb/>It has become difficult for a German to give a talk in Italy. Even at occasions which do <lb/>not deal with the future of Europe, the crisis is somehow present. And this presence is <lb/>an uncomfortable one. And vice versa, how do Italians feel when they address a German <lb/>audience? Their task is different, but by no means easy. I refrain from reporting my <lb/>experiences and instead try to say what I feel we would need, namely, a type of <lb/>communication and interaction in which we are aware of our differences, try to <lb/>understand the background of the other, and learn to synthesise respect and critique. <lb/>Do we have examples? Jürgen Habermas in his numerous interventions, maybe? 1 <lb/>Ulrich Beck with his reference to Thomas Mann's plea for a "European Germany", <lb/>instead of a "German Europe"? 2 Not only our master thinkers but also many academics <lb/>and publicists, to some degree even my own writings 3 , could be cited here. This is a way <lb/>to make friends abroad, but it is not what I have in mind. Much closer to what I believe <lb/>could be helpful are works such as Angelo Bolaffi's Cuore Tedesco 4 . Bolaffi has a <lb/>profound intellectual background, is intimately informed about Germany's cultural <lb/>heritage, its history, its institutions, the functioning of German politics, and its <lb/>intellectual life. However, he seems to be deeply conservative, and his plea for German <lb/>leadership is "a non-starter" 5 , but he is nonetheless incredibly generous in the way he <lb/>treats my country. And nevertheless, this is a very enlightening and helpful contribution <lb/>both to German-Italian relations and to the miserable state of the European Union. <lb/></body>
    
    <front>* Christian Joerges is Research Professor and Codirector of the Centre of Law and Politcs, Bremen <lb/>University; Senior Professor for Law and Society, Hertie School of Governance, Berlin. <lb/></front>
    
    <listBibl>1 E.g., The interview "Ora in Europa il populismo sta conquistando anche i governi", available at: <lb/>http://www.repubblica.it/esteri/2014/12/02/news/habermas_ora_in_europa_il_populismo_sta_conqui <lb/>stando_anche_i_governi-101916768/Repubblica; "Una partita a poker per i posti di potere ma così <lb/>l'Europa sarà colpita al cuore", La Repubblica, 31 May 2014, available at: <lb/>http://www.repubblica.it/esteri/2014/05/31/news/jrgen_habermas_una_partita_a_poker_per_i_posti_ <lb/>di_potere_ma_cos_l_europa_sar_colpita_al_cuore-87728583/; "Più democrazia, meno mercati <lb/>finanziari", La Repubblica, 19 March 2012, available at: http://temi.repubblica.it/micromega-<lb/>online/europa-habermas-piu-democrazia-meno-mercati-finanziari, etc., etc. <lb/>2 U. BECK, German Europe, Cambridge, Polity Press, 2013, VII. <lb/>3 C. JOERGES and S. GIUBBONI, "Diritto e politica nella crisi europea", (2013) 31 Rivista critica del diritto <lb/>privato, 343-367; a co-authored essay is a nice step, but not yet what I envisage. <lb/>4 A. BOLAFFI, Cuore Tedesco. Il modello Germania, l'Italia e la crisi europea, Roma, Donzelli Editore, 2013 <lb/>[Deutsches Herz. Das Modell Deutschland und die europäische Krise, Stuttgart, Klett-Cotta, 2014]. <lb/>5 See C. OFFE, Europe Entrapped, Cambridge, Polity Press, 2015, 90-108. <lb/></listBibl>
    
  <note place="headnote">Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, Special Issue (2015) <lb/></note>
    
    <page>10 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Reading Bolaffi, you will experience that our countries and "we", their citizens, are <lb/>different. Thinking about these differences, you may prioritise this or that on this or that <lb/>side. But you will also have to consider whether anything can or should be done about <lb/>it. <lb/>At this point, it is about time to go in medias res: "Die Wirtschaft ist das Schicksal" (the <lb/>economy is our destiny) -Walther Rathenau's frightening insight from the early years of <lb/>the Weimar Republic has gained a critical topicality as, by now, we all know so well. His <lb/>economic philosophy was that of a variety of an "organised liberalism" and the motto <lb/>that I have cited concerned the state of Germany's first republic -albeit in its European <lb/>context 6 . What I will complain about in this essay is the disregard of history and <lb/>conceptual history in European law scholarship both in general and in my own <lb/>discipline, namely, European economic law, in particular. This is not the kind of <lb/>discourse which dominates the perception of the economy in European law scholarship. <lb/>To be sure, this scholarship is meticulously documenting, analysing and discussing each <lb/>and every element of the European legal materials pertaining to the economy. It is, <lb/>nonetheless, characterised by a benign neglect of the constitutional importance of the <lb/>economy and not well prepared to comprehend its political dimensions and context. <lb/>The implications of this forgetfulness are dramatic, as I will briefly try to explain <lb/>with the help of three non-legal disciplines: economic sociology, political economy, and <lb/>economic history. On the first: Karl Polanyi, in his legendary Great Transformation 7 , has <lb/>argued that the market and the economy are always "socially embedded". It follows that <lb/>we have to take the institutional, historical and context into account when observing our <lb/>economies and trying to make them "more competitive". It also follows that we have to <lb/>be aware of the "varieties of capitalism" 8 . Torben Iversen and David Soskice, in a paper <lb/>entitled "A Structural-Institutional Explanation of the Eurozone Crisis", have relied on <lb/>the theory and methodology of this approach in a comparison of the German and the <lb/>Italian economy 9 . They refrain from any moralising in their diagnosis of the current <lb/>Italian difficulties and their origins on the one hand, and Germany's present <lb/>performance and its origins, on the other. Werner Abelshauser, Germany's leading <lb/>economic historian, is less cautious and contained. In a recent manifesto, entitled <lb/>"Europa in Vielfalt einigen" (European unitas in pluralitate) 10 , he argues that Europe risks <lb/>the destruction of its competitive advantages through the streamlining of its economies. <lb/>This is precisely the message, to cite another great Italian, in Giandomenico Majone's <lb/>recent monograph 11 . It is also the creed underlying this essay 12 . I cannot explain, let <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>6 See U. MADER, "Die Wirtschaft ist das Schicksal!' Walther Rathenau als Reichsminister 1921 und 1922", <lb/>WRG-Mitteilungen 2002, available at: www.waltherrathenau.de/fileadmin/Material/Mitteilungen/WRG-<lb/>Mitteilungen-2002.pdf. <lb/>7 K. POLANYI, The Great Transformation: The Political and Economic Origins of Our Time [1944], Boston MA, <lb/>Beacon Press, 1957. <lb/>8 P.A. HALL and D. SOSKICE (eds), Varieties of Capitalism: The Institutional Foundations of Comparative <lb/>Advantage, Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2005. <lb/>9 T. IVERSEN and D. SOSKICE, "A Structural-Institutional Explanation of the Eurozone Crisis", <lb/>Cambridge MA, Harvard University, Department of Government. <lb/>10 W. ABELSHAUSER, "Europa in Vielfalt einigen. Eine Denkschrift", available at: http://wwwhomes.uni-<lb/>bielefeld.de/wabelsha/Denkschrift.pdf; see, also, W. ABELSHAUSER, Kulturkampf: Der deutsche Weg in die <lb/>Neue Wirtschaft und die amerikanische Herausforderung, Berlin, Kadmos, 2003; id., D. GILGEN and A. <lb/>LEUTZSCH (eds), Kulturen der Weltwirtschaft, Göttingen, Vandenhoek und Ruprecht, 2013. <lb/>11 G. MAJONE, Rethinking the Union of Europe Post-crisis, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 2014. <lb/>12 C. JOERGES, "Unity in Diversity as Europe's Vocation and Conflicts Law as Europe's Constitutional <lb/>Form", in R. NICKEL and A. GREPPI (eds), The Changing Role of Law in the Age of Supra-and Transnational <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Christian Joerges, Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance in Europe <lb/></note>
    
    <page>11 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>alone defend, all the premises which underlie what I shall be submitting in these few <lb/>pages, and it is equally impossible to summarise the works which lead to this submission <lb/>in the subtlety which such a complex and delicate topic deserves in such difficult times. <lb/>What I will, instead, present are some daring broadsheets which do not elaborate on the <lb/>analyses in economic sociology, political theory and economic history. They focus on <lb/>law. Section II is an assault on the orthodoxy of European legal studies. It submits that <lb/>European economic integration has not only affected the reach of democratic politics <lb/>and the welfare state legacy of post-war Europe negatively, but, by the same token, <lb/>gradually disembedded the formerly national economies. Section III will deal with the <lb/>establishment of the EMU. It will argue that the EMU was neither a re-embedding <lb/>exercise nor a victory of economic constitutionalism. The EMU will, instead, be <lb/>characterised as a "diagonal conflict", creating an irresolvable dilemma. Section IV will <lb/>turn to Europe's crisis management and its new modes of economic governance. It is <lb/>here that the drama transforms into tragedy. The price for the defence of the EMU <lb/>high: economic prospects remain vague and social recovery is out of sight. The <lb/>Epilogue (Section V) is on a theoretically viable, but politically unlikely, alternative. <lb/>2. The Disintegrative Effects of Economic Integration <lb/>The reference to Walter Rathenau alludes to a long-term problématique and a critique of <lb/>European legal scholarship. The problem concerns the relation or tension between <lb/>markets and politics, more specifically between the democratically-legitimated political <lb/>rule in constitutional states and the autonomy of their economies. <lb/>2.1. The Integration Through Law Project and Economic <lb/>Constitutionalism <lb/>What, other than law, was conceivable as the distinctive medium that kept the <lb/>Community, which the Treaty of Rome had established, together? The story of the early <lb/>jurisprudence of the ECJ, which transformed the rule of the Treaty into a Constitutional <lb/>Charter, is well known, and not just to lawyers. So is the characterisation of the <lb/>Community by Walter Hallstein, the first President of the Commission with an explicit <lb/>commitment to ordo-liberalism right after the war 13 , as "Schöpfung des Rechts, Rechtsquelle, <lb/>und Rechtsordnung" 14 . European integration was deliberately launched as an economic <lb/>project. By necessity, provisions concerning the organisation of the economy were to <lb/>become extraordinarily important. Here lies the origin of the powerful alliance between <lb/>the agenda of integration through law and ordo-liberalism. The two allies, however, <lb/>were hardly aware of the fact that they were operating in tandem. Hardly anybody <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>Governance, <lb/>Baden-Baden, <lb/>Nomos <lb/>Verlag, <lb/>2014, <lb/>125-176, <lb/>also <lb/>available <lb/>at: <lb/>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1723249; idem, "Conflicts-Law Constitutionalism: <lb/>Ambitions and Problems", in M. CREMONA, P. HILPOLD, N. LAVRANOS, S.S. SCHNEIDER and A.R. <lb/>ZIEGLER (eds), Reflections on the Constitutionalisation of International Economic Law: Liber Amicorum for Ernst-<lb/>Ulrich Petersmann, Leiden, Brill/Nijhoff, 2014, 111-138, also at: <lb/>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2182092. <lb/>13 See his "Wiederherstellung des Privatrechts", (1946) Süddeutsche Juristenzeitung, 1 et seq. <lb/>14 W. HALLSTEIN, Die Europäische Gemeinschaft, 5th ed., Düsseldorf, Econ, 1979, 33. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, Special Issue (2015) <lb/></note>
    
    <page>12 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>outside Germany knew what ordo-liberalism and its commitment to Ordnungspolitik 15 <lb/>were about. And the same is true vice versa. Germany's European law community did not <lb/>pay much attention to discussions in other countries and foreign??/other languages. <lb/>"Integration through law", which was to become a trademark of the European project, <lb/>was to achieve an umbrella status. Law was famously conceptualised as the "agent and <lb/>the object of integration" 16 . The assignment of both instrumental functions and <lb/>inherently legitimating values was by no means pursuing, indeed, it was not even aware <lb/>of, a notion such as "economic constitutionalism". And yet, what happened through the <lb/>so-called constitutionalisation of European law through the doctrines of "direct effect", <lb/>"supremacy", and "pre-emption", was fully in line with ordo-liberal premises and <lb/>aspirations. In particular the conceptualisation of the economic freedoms as basic rights <lb/>which Europe's market citizens could invoke against their nation states was very much <lb/>to the liking of the one and only school of thought which took the legal dimensions of <lb/>the economy really seriously. It seemed now plausible to assign a constitutional status to <lb/>the core institutions of the Europeanising market economy. <lb/>One aspect and a crucially problematical implication of the ordo-liberal <lb/>conceptualisation of legitimate governance through an economic constitution was to <lb/>constitute a steadily deepening dilemma, namely, the unresolved tensions between the <lb/>juridification of "the economic" according to the "logic of the market", on the one <lb/>hand, and the primacy of democratic legitimacy, on the other. We are currently <lb/>witnessing a dramatic intensification of this tension. This brief re-construction of the <lb/>foundational period reveals that this tension is not new and not a late by-product of the <lb/>financial crisis. It is, instead, a so-to-speak foundational flaw of the integration project. <lb/>As already underlined, the de facto alliance between economic constitutionalism <lb/>and integration through law was hardly noticed in European law scholarship, not even <lb/>in Germany. Economic constitutionalism was a theory residing in the private law <lb/>compartments of our discipline, whereas European law was understood as public law. <lb/>This lack of sensitivity is difficult to explain because the young Federal Republic had <lb/>witnessed an intense debate on the notion of an "economic constitution" in its Basic <lb/>Law. This debate concerned the conceptualisation of the ordering of the economy as a <lb/>self-legitimating ordo which required a legal institutionalisation beyond the reach of <lb/>politics. In this debate, the ordo-liberal school and its allies in the German Staatsrecht <lb/>were confronted with the quest for democratic legitimacy and the primacy of the <lb/>legislative authority in the ordering of "economy and society". The primacy of <lb/>democratic politics was defended at the time by a clear majority of Germany's <lb/>constitutional lawyers even in instances where its policies appeared opportunistic and <lb/>unprincipled 17 . It is worth recalling that ordo-liberalism experienced a first defeat when <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>15 An anecdote may explain my hesitation to search for a translation: "Ordnungspolitik" was the German <lb/>name of Working Group VI in the European Convention in 2003. The English name was "Economic <lb/>Governance". Was this an innovative translation? Not really. It was the Convention Secretariat that was <lb/>responsible for the introduction of the term, in which someone remembered the fierce controversies <lb/>between "Ordnungspolitik" and "industrial policy" in the Maastricht Intergovernmental Conference in <lb/>1991 -a case of "linguistic-discursive path-dependency", according to Andreas Maurer, which confirms <lb/>that the German notion is resistant to translation. <lb/>16 R. DEHOUSSE and J.H.H. WEILER, "The Legal Dimension", in W. WALLACE (ed), The Dynamics of <lb/>European Integration, London, Pinter, 1990, 242-60, at 243. On this legacy, see D. AUGENSTEIN, "Integration <lb/>through Law" Revisited: The Making of the European Polity, Farnham, Ashgate, 2012. <lb/>17 See the re-construction in K.W. NÖRR, Die Republik der Wirtschaft. Teil I. Von der Besatzungszeit bis zur <lb/>Großen Koalition, Tübingen, Mohr Siebeck, 1999, passim. The reference to the legal validity of the <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Christian Joerges, Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance in Europe <lb/></note>
    
    <page>13 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>that debate reached the German Constitutional Court 18 . Ordo-liberalism was again the <lb/>loser in the spectacular debate on the co-determination statute in the seminal judgment <lb/>handed down on 1 March 1979 19 . This is all the more remarkable given that the same <lb/>court arrived at fundamentally different conclusions when it had to evaluate the <lb/>constitutional validity of Monetary Union it its Maastricht judgment 20 , to which Section <lb/>III.1 will return. <lb/>2.2. Foundational Flaws <lb/>The tension between democratic legitimacy as it was institutionalised in the Member <lb/>States of the EC, on the one hand, and the establishment of an economic order of <lb/>supranational validity, on the other, is the most problematical legacy of the foundational <lb/>period of the integration project. But we have to note some more flaws. One is <lb/>methodological. The famous formula characterising law as the "object and the agent of <lb/>integration" was coined at the height of the American law and society movement which <lb/>promoted the sociological study of law and all sorts of interdisciplinary "law and…" <lb/>explorations. This revival of legal realism has attracted much attention, not least in the <lb/>"law-in-context" approach which is very much en vogue at the law department of the <lb/>European University Institute. "Integration through law", however, was an agenda <lb/>which disregarded the embeddedness of law in all sorts of social norms. The <lb/>attractiveness of "integration through law" in European studies is, nevertheless, <lb/>unsurprising. Its methodological solipsism, doctrinal rigidity and its formalism enabled <lb/>transnational interactions and acting, and fostered the emergence of a European <lb/>community of lawyers and legal scholarship long before social scientists started to take <lb/>Europe seriously. <lb/>The primacy of law and its methodological poverty came at a high price, however. <lb/>"Progress" in European integration was equated with the accomplishment of more legal <lb/>uniformity, while legal diversity served to provide conclusive reasons for more legal <lb/>harmonisation. The deficiencies of the integration-through-law fantasy and ideology are <lb/>precisely the two main flaws of which Giandomenico Majone and Fritz Scharpf keep <lb/>reminding us: (1) Integration through law rests upon a "one-size-fits-all" assumption <lb/>and proceeds accordingly; and (2) In integration-through-law, programmatic integration <lb/>as more uniformity figures as a goal itself, as Europe's finalité, which needs no further <lb/>justification 21 . <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>constitutional "Sozialstaatsgebot" usually recalls the seminal Abendroth/Forsthoff debate, re-constructed, <lb/>e.g., in C. JOERGES, "The Rechtsstaat and Social Europe: How a Classical Tension Resurfaces in the <lb/>European Integration Process", (2010) 9 Comparative Sociology, 65-85. <lb/>18 Bundesverfassungsgericht, Judgment of 20 July 1954, Investitionshilfegesetz, BVerfGE 5, 7 ff. <lb/>19 BVerfG 50, 290, unfortunately never translated. <lb/>20 Judgment of 12 October 1993, Brunner v European Union Treaty, (1994) 57 CMLR, 1. <lb/>21 See, e.g., G. MAJONE, Rethinking the Union, n. 11 above (passim); F.W. SCHARPF, Community and Autonomy. <lb/>Institutions, Policies and Legitimacy in Multilevel Europe, Frankfurt/New York: Campus Verlag, 2010. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, Special Issue (2015) <lb/></note>
    
    <page>14 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>3. Economic Constitutionalism: its Pyrrhic Victory and Failure in the <lb/>EMU <lb/>The Treaty of Maastricht, signed in 1992, is an extremely important turning-point in the <lb/>development of the integration project. It was perceived at the time as both a <lb/>continuation and a deepening of what had been accomplished to date at that time, a <lb/>move towards "an ever closer union", marked by an opening of new policy-fields and <lb/>the crowning of the completion of the internal market by monetary union 22 . In <lb/>hindsight, we see a more complex picture, and what we are becoming aware of are both <lb/>its institutional defects and the failures to deal with their tragic consequences. <lb/>3.1. The Judicial Fiction of a "Stability Community" <lb/>The judgment of the German Constitutional Court on the Treaty of Maastricht, which <lb/>was handed down on 12 October 1993, opened the way to the ratification of the Treaty <lb/>in Germany. And it proved to be more controversial than the Treaty itself. Tellingly <lb/>enough, and confirming my introductory remarks on the benign and unfortunate neglect <lb/>of the economy in European constitutional scholarship, critics found that the Court has <lb/>mis-stated the views of Hermann Heller, were irritated by the characterisation of the <lb/>Union as a "Verbund", rather than a "Gemeinschaft", and even found a touch of <lb/>Schmittianism in the judicial reasoning 23 . What the Court had to say about the economy <lb/>seemed less interesting but was, indeed, exciting. The pertinent passages on the <lb/>European Monetary Union, and the economic constitution with its substantive and <lb/>institutional substitution of politics and policies by legal rules, was, so the Court held, <lb/>nothing less than a sine qua non for German participation within the Monetary Union. <lb/>This assertion was the Court's response to the argument that the European Union was <lb/>about to acquire such wide-ranging competences that nation states could no longer act <lb/>as the masters of their "democratic statehood". Economic integration, so the Court replied, <lb/>was an autonomous and apolitical process, which might, and indeed must, take place <lb/>beyond the reach of Member State political influence. By virtue of a constitutional <lb/>commitment to price stability and rules that guarded against inappropriate budgetary <lb/>deficits, the EMU was, in the Court's view, well structured. Accordingly, all doubts <lb/>about the democratic legitimacy of economic integration were diverted. To rephrase the <lb/>argument slightly: yes, the Treaty is compatible with the Basic Law. But this is true only <lb/>because it is inspired by Germany's stability philosophy and only as long as this stability <lb/>pact is actually respected. <lb/>The Court had been warned, for example, by the President of the Bundesbank, <lb/>"that a currency union, especially between States which are oriented towards an active <lb/>economic and social policy, can ultimately only be realized in common with a political <lb/>union (embracing all essential economic functions) and cannot be realized <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>22 See, for an early and still valuable collection of pertinent analyses, R. DEHOUSSSE (ed), Europe after <lb/>Maastricht: An Ever Closer Union?, Munich, C.H. Beck, 1994. <lb/>23 See J.H.H. WEILER, "Does Europe Need a Constitution? Reflections on Demos, Telos and the German <lb/>Maastricht Decision", (1995) 1 European Law Journal, 219-258. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Christian Joerges, Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance in Europe <lb/></note>
    
    <page>15 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>independently thereof or as a mere preliminary stage on the way to it" 24 . It could not be <lb/>so naïve as to believe in the autonomy and sustainability of the "stability community". <lb/>And indeed, Ernst-Wolfgang Böckenförde, one of the renowned judges of the deciding <lb/>2nd Senate, has recently underlined that the judges were, indeed, fully aware of the <lb/>fragility of the Stabilitätsgemeineschaft (stability community) which they defended as a <lb/>constitutional command: <lb/>"The decision to agree on a monetary union and put it into operation without a <lb/>simultaneous or immediately subsequent political union is a political one, for which <lb/>the institutions with competence on the matter must take political responsibility" 25 . <lb/>One remains perplexed. The judges knew very well that it would be simply <lb/>inconceivable to correct politically the deal to which they had given their legal blessing. <lb/>And they decided accordingly when they were confronted with the request to prevent <lb/>the EMU from entering the third stage 26 . The dynamics which had been set in motion <lb/>became irresistible. The common currency had created financial interdependencies in a <lb/>socio-economically ever more heterogeneous Union which had gone out of control. The <lb/>new exclusive European competence for monetary policy was too weak an instrument <lb/>to govern the European economic sphere, but strong enough to deprive the Member <lb/>States of crucially important governmental powers. Europe continued to be a "market <lb/>without a state", while the former masters of the treaties had become "states without <lb/>markets" 27 . <lb/>My queries as a German lawyer are twofold. The first: in the two important <lb/>judgments -Investitionshilfe 28 and Mitbestimmung 29 -the Court had rejected the idea of <lb/>economic constitutionalism. What is the rational of this turn? The query is, rather, an <lb/>objection: the German Court is not entitled to write the constitution for the entire <lb/>Union. To be sure, it based its reasoning upon German principles which affected the <lb/>rest of Europe only indirectly, but it is precisely this kind of external effect of national <lb/>decision-making which has to be avoided in a Union of equals 30 . <lb/>My objection as a German citizen is that the Court is, in the end, not in a position <lb/>to accomplish what it solemnly proclaims. The "stability community" of the EMU <lb/>existed only on paper. It is a fictitious order which cannot be implemented. The Treaty <lb/>of Maastricht simply did not provide for mechanisms to enforce its conceptual basis. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>24 On the intense controversies in Germany over the common currency at the time of its introduction, <lb/>see, recently, F. HEINEMANN, "Zwischen 'Kernschmelze' und 'Fass ohne Boden' -zum Dissens <lb/>deutscher Ökonomen in der Schuldenkrise", (2013) 60 Zeitschrift für Politikwissenschaft, 207-219. <lb/>25 "Not kennt keine Gebot" (necessity knows no rules), Neue Züricher Zeitung, 21 June 2010, available at: <lb/>http://www.nzz.ch/nachrichten/kultur/literatur_und_kunst/kennt_die_europaeische_not_kein_gebot_1 <lb/>.6182412.html. <lb/>26 Decision of 31 March 1998 -2 BvR 1877/97 und 2 BvR 50/98 -available at: <lb/>http://www.bverfg.de/entscheidungen/rs19980331_2bvr187797en.html. <lb/>27 See, in more detail, C. JOERGES, "The Market without a State? States without Markets? Two Essays on <lb/>the Law of the European Economy", EUI Working Paper Law 1/96, San Domenico di Fiesole, 1996, <lb/>available at: http://eiop.or.at/eiop/texte/1997-019 and -020.htm. <lb/>28 Note 18 above. <lb/>29 Note 19 above. <lb/>30 This is the core assumption of "The Idea of a Three-dimensional Conflicts Law as Constitutional <lb/>Form", in: C. JOERGES and E.-U. PETERSMANN (eds.), Constitutionalism, Multilevel Trade Governance and Social <lb/>Regulation, Oxford-Portland OR, Hart Publishing, 2011, 2nd ed., 413-455. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, Special Issue (2015) <lb/></note>
    
    <page>16 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Nor did the successive Stability Pact of 1997 31 complement the Treaty accordingly. The <lb/>operation of the whole new regime was dependent on good economic luck and constant <lb/>political bargaining. <lb/>Against this background, it seems hardly surprising that the Stability Pact was <lb/>disregarded by such central players as Germany, France and the Netherlands when they <lb/>felt they had reasons to do so, or that the Commission's much vaunted efforts to take <lb/>action against deficits dwindled into nothing 32 . It has, nevertheless, become routine to <lb/>assign the failure of the EMU to the non-compliance with its rules, and to conclude that <lb/>such laxity would, in the future, have to be impeded by ever-stricter economic <lb/>governance. An alternative, more honest and more intriguing interpretation would <lb/>attribute non-compliance to the economic, social and political costs of the enforcement <lb/>of a regime which represented an ill-defined political compromise, rather than a <lb/>sustainable accomplishment of constitutional validity and strength. This is the point to <lb/>which I will now turn in a somewhat unusual perspective. <lb/>3.2. The Maastricht Compromise as a Diagonal Conflict <lb/>The oddity of the Maastricht EMU is by now widely recognised. Sergio Fabbrini <lb/>has characterised it as a "compromise" between German Ordnungspolitik and the majority <lb/>preference for national sovereignty in the realms of economic and fiscal policy 33 . Kaarlo <lb/>and Klaus Tuori, in their monograph on the crisis, discern "two layers of the European <lb/>Economic Constitution" 34 . Whether it be compromise or layer, what Maastricht <lb/>established was an incoherent edifice. There is nothing unusual or inherently <lb/>problematical with compromises. What is specific about the Treaty and what <lb/>distinguishes the European order from constitutional democracies is the lack of a <lb/>political infrastructure and institutional framework in which democratic political <lb/>contestation could occur and legitimate a completion or improvement of the unfinished <lb/>edifice. According to a widely shared -and, in the proceedings before the German <lb/>Constitutional Court quite intensively considered view -constitutional coherence would <lb/>have required the move towards political union -a move which Helmut Kohl, then <lb/>Germany's chancellor, was ready to undertake, in contrast to other European leaders 35 . <lb/>Would such a move have saved the EMU? This is what many commentators argue and <lb/>recommend as a response to the present crisis. Section V will return to this problématique. <lb/>With regard to the EMU as it was actually established, speculations about what could <lb/>have been done and what might then have happened do not help us with the <lb/>characterisation of what we actually ended up with. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>31 "Council Regulation (EC) 1467/97: On speeding up and clarifying the implementation of the excessive <lb/>deficit procedure", OJ L 209, 2.8.1997, 1. <lb/>32 For more detail on the following, see C. JOERGES, "What is left of the European Economic <lb/>Constitution? A Melancholic Eulogy", (2005) 30 European Law Review, 461-489, at 476-478. <lb/>33 S. FABBRINI, "The Euro Crisis and its Constitutional Implications", in S. CHAMPEAU, C. CLOSA, D. <lb/>INNERARITY and M. POIARES MADURO (eds), The Future of Europe. Democracy, Legitimacy and Justice After the <lb/>Euro Crisis, London-New York, Rowman and Littlefield, 2015, 19-36. <lb/>34 KAARLO TUORI and KLAUS TUORI, The Eurozone Crisis. A Constitutional Analysis, Cambridge, Cambridge <lb/>University Press, 2014, 13-60. <lb/>35 See K. DYSON, States, Debts and Power. Saints and Sinners in European History and Integration, Oxford, <lb/>Oxford University Press, 2014, 609 ff. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Christian Joerges, Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance in Europe <lb/></note>
    
    <page>17 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>My suggestion is that the Treaty of Maastricht institutionalised was de facto a <lb/>"diagonal" conflict constellation. This notion requires an explanatory remark. <lb/>Monetary policy has become an exclusive competence of the Union (Article 3(1) c <lb/>TFEU). With this provision, the Union claims supremacy in the policy area conferred to <lb/>it, a conferral which did not include economic and fiscal policies. The exercise of these <lb/>policies can have external effects and lead to "horizontal" conflicts. As experienced <lb/>immediately after the establishment of the EMU, monetary policy and the national <lb/>policies could still come into conflict. This, however, is not a vertical conflict for which <lb/>supremacy would provide a response. It is a "diagonal conflict": both the Union and the <lb/>Member States are certainly interested in the functioning of their economies. But the <lb/>powers needed to accomplish this objective are attributed to two distinct levels of <lb/>governance. The type of conflict resolution foreseen in Article 119 TFEU is "the <lb/>adoption of an economic policy which is based on the close coordination of Member <lb/>States' economic policies" as substantiated in Article 121 TFEU 36 . As already <lb/>mentioned, this instrument was legally imperfect. <lb/>At this point, it is illuminating to consider the insights of the non-legal disciplines <lb/>cited in the first section. Not only does the diversity of socio-economic conditions even <lb/>within the Eurozone generate a variety of interests, but the differences in the <lb/>institutional configurations and economic cultures and in the social norms practiced also <lb/>explain why European governance could no longer follow common rules. These <lb/>observations also militate against the complaint about the imperfection of the Stability <lb/>and Growth Pact of 1997. Its enforcement would have done more damage than the <lb/>toleration of extra-legal practices. <lb/>4. Destructing the Alleged Culprit: Emergency Europe <lb/>In a widely noticed lecture on "Macht-Recht-Wirtschaftsverfassung" (Power-Law-Economic <lb/>Constitution), given at the annual conference of the Verein für Socialpolitik in 1972, <lb/>Ernst-Joachim Mestmäcker, the intellectual mastermind of the second generation of the <lb/>Freiburg School, had expressed the expectation that the pressure to harmonise, <lb/>stemming from integration, would become stronger and even irresistible under a <lb/>common currency. A Common Monetary Policy would mean "ultimately giving up" the <lb/>opportunity to maintain far-reaching differences between the economic orders 37 . The <lb/>Community to which Mestmäcker referred looks quite idyllic; it was much smaller and <lb/>more homogeneous than the current Union, and his expectations and claims may have <lb/>had a better fundamentum in re under such conditions. But, by know, we know more and <lb/>can explain a lot. The Union became ever more diverse. The varieties of Europe <lb/>capitalism persisted and conditioned national policy-making 38 . Taking this ever-<lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>36 What kind of power this "co-ordination" mandate confers is thoroughly discussed by B. BRAAMS, <lb/>Koordinierung als Kompetenzkategorie, Tübingen, Mohr Siebeck, 2013. As she underlines, at 228 ff., even the <lb/>soft powers of recommendations and co-ordination are subject to the rule of law and that their exercise <lb/>must be legalised by an amendment of the TFEU. <lb/>37 E.-J. MESTMÄCKER, "Macht-Recht-Wirtschaftsverfassung", (1973) 137 Zeitschrift für das gesamte <lb/>Handelsrecht und Wirtschaftsrecht, 97-118, at 109 ["Power, law and economic constitution", (1973) 11 The <lb/>German Economic Review, 177-192 (1973)]. <lb/>38 P.A. HALL, "The Political Origins of our Economic Discontents. Contemporary Adjustment Problems <lb/>in Historical Perspective", in M. KAHLER and D.A. LAKE (eds), Politics in the New Hard Times, Ithaca NY, <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, Special Issue (2015) <lb/></note>
    
    <page>18 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>increasing diversity into account, it is anything but surprising that the diagonal-conflict <lb/>constellation which Maastricht has established became unmanageable. It is, hélas, equally <lb/>unsurprising that the pressure of the financial crisis generated hectic activities. <lb/>4.1. Conflict "Resolution" through Authoritarian Managerialism <lb/>The fragility of the Maastricht arrangement and the erosion of legal ordering were not <lb/>readily apparent for a long while. This has changed dramatically in the course of the <lb/>crisis 39 . Within a time-span of half a decade, we have been witnessing the establishment <lb/>of new modes of economic governance and regulatory mechanisms such as the "Europe <lb/>2020 Strategy" (March 2010), the "European Semester" (May 2010), the "EFSF <lb/>Framework Agreement" (June 2010), the "Euro Plus Pact" (March 2011), and the "Six <lb/>Pack" (December 2011), the "European Stability Mechanism" (ESM, February 2012), <lb/>the "Treaty on Stability, Coordination and Governance" (TSCG, March 2012), the <lb/>banking union (on the road since September 2012), the "Two Pack" submitted back in <lb/>2011 and adopted with parliamentary blessing in March 2013 40 . With regard to the <lb/>compatibility of these measures with the Treaty, in particular, its bailout ban (Article 125 <lb/>TFEU), an ex-post revision procedure amending Article 136 TFEU has been undertaken <lb/>in order to legalise financial assistance as of 1 January 2013 41 . <lb/>A particular intriguing characteristic of Europe's new modes of economic <lb/>governance is the form of its crisis management. This "managerialism" is delicate for <lb/>three inter-dependent reasons. First, through the supervision and control of macro-<lb/>economic imbalances, it disregards the principle of enumerated powers, and, by the <lb/>same token, cannot respect the democratic legitimacy of national institutions, in <lb/>particular, the budgetary powers of the parliaments of the states receiving assistance. <lb/>Second, in its departure from the one-size-fits-all philosophy that orients European <lb/>integration in general and monetary policy in particular, it nonetheless fails to achieve a <lb/>variation, which might be founded in democratically-legitimated choices; quite to the <lb/>contrary, the individualised scrutiny of all Member States is geared to the objective of <lb/>budgetary balances and seeks to impose the necessary accompanying discipline. Under <lb/>the conditions of monetary unity, the Member States can only respond to pertinent <lb/>requests through austerity measures: reductions of wage levels and of social <lb/>entitlements 42 . Third, the machinery of the new regime with its individualised measures <lb/>which are oriented only by necessarily indeterminate general clauses is regulatory in its <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>Cornell University Press, 2013, 129-149. For a summary of the argument, see P.A. HALL, "Brother, Can <lb/>You Paradigm?", (2013) 26 Governance: An International Journal of Policy, Administration, and Institutions, 189-<lb/>192. <lb/>39 The short story has been retold ad nauseam. For an instructive, if euphemistic, recent summary, see S. <lb/>FERNANDES, "Who Calls the Shots in the Euro Area: 'Brussels' or the Member States?", Notre Europe, <lb/>Policy Paper 111, 15 MAY 2014, available at: http://www.notre-europe.eu/media/emugovernance-<lb/>fernandes-ne-jdi-may14.pdf?pdf=ok. In more detail, see C. JOERGES, "Europe's Economic Constitution <lb/>in Crisis and the Emergence of a New Constitutional Constellation", (2014) 15 German Law Journal, 985-<lb/>1028, available at: http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2179595. <lb/>40 All of these acts can be found at a Commission website which is constantly being updated: <lb/>http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/legal_texts/compendium2014_en.htm. <lb/>41 As is well known, the objections raised by Mr Thomas Pringle, Member of the Irish Parliament, against <lb/>the legality of this amendment were rejected by the CJEU in Case C-370/12 Pringle v Ireland, nyr. <lb/>42 Cf., the listing of pertinent requests in M. DAWSON and F. DE WITTE, "Constitutional Balance in the <lb/>EU after the Euro-Crisis", (2013) 76 Modern Law Review, 817-844, at 825-7, notes 33-37. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Christian Joerges, Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance in Europe <lb/></note>
    
    <page>19 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>&gt;nature, establishing transnational executive machinery outside both the realm of <lb/>democratic politics and the form of accountability which the rule of law used to <lb/>guarantee. Core concepts used by new economic governance cannot be defined with <lb/>any precision, either by lawyers or by economists, and are therefore not justiciable. This <lb/>implies that rule-of-law and legal protection requirements are being suspended 43 . This <lb/>type of de-legalisation is accompanied by assessments of Member State performance, <lb/>which cannot be but highly discretionary 44 . All of this is anathema to legal scholars <lb/>committed to the legacy of the Freiburg School. It is therefore difficult to understand <lb/>why Germany's ordo-liberalism is so widely identified as the ideational background of <lb/>Europe's crisis politics, which the German government is orchestrating 45 . <lb/>All of these measures were taken to compensate for the failure the original EMU <lb/>and the Pact to prevent a downfall of the financial system of the Eurozone and to <lb/>provide for rescue measures. This is why Ernst-Wolfgang Böckenförde, a renowned <lb/>scholar and former judge of the German Constitutional Court, started to talk of a state <lb/>of emergency 46 . We will return to this notion below 47 . For now, it should suffice to list <lb/>the characterisation of the responses to the crisis which seek to capture their <lb/>exceptionalism or specifics: executive federalism (Habermas) 48 , new sovereignty with <lb/>largely unfettered power of rule (Chalmers) 49 , consolidating state (Streeck) 50 , <lb/>authoritarian managerialism (Joerges/Weimer) 51 , legally-and politically-unconstrained <lb/>expertocracy (Scharpf) 52 , executive powers beyond the reach of national and European <lb/>democracies (Curtin) 53 , and, the transformation of the EU's democratic deficit into a <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>43 See the intriguing and concerned analysis by M. EVERSON, "The Fault of (European) Law in (Political <lb/>and Social) Economic Crisis," (2013) 24 Law and Critique, 107-129. <lb/>44 See, e.g., A. WATT, "Commission Makes a Mockery of Imbalance Procedure", Social Europe Journal of 19 <lb/>April 2013, available at: http://www.social-europe.eu/author/andrew-watt. <lb/>45 See, e.g., the much cited essay on "The long shadow of ordo-liberalism" is the title of a much-cited <lb/>paper by U. GUÉROT and S. DULLIEN, available at: http://www.ecfr.eu/page/-<lb/>/ECFR49_GERMANY_BRIEF_AW.pdf, the symposium "Critical Exchange on Neoliberalism and <lb/>Europe. Europe and the political philosophy of neoliberalism", (2013) Contemporary Political Theory <lb/>(advance online publication, 6 August 2013), with contributions by T. BIEBRICHER, J. HIEN, N. JABKO <lb/>and A. CHARI and from Italy S. CESARATTO and A. STIRATI, "Germany and the European and Global <lb/>Crises", 39 (2010) International Journal of Political Economy, 56-86. Unfortunately, all of these contributions <lb/>treat the legal philosophy of ordo-liberalism with benign neglect and fail to mention the harsh critique <lb/>European crisis politics by leading proponants of the ordoliberal legacy; see, in particular, E.-J. <lb/>Mestmäcker's worried interventions "Der Schamfleck ist die Geldverachtung" (the shaming flaw is the <lb/>disdainfulness of money), in: Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, 18 November 2011, 33; and <lb/>"Ordnungspolitische Grundlagen einer politischen Union" (foundational principles for the ordering of a <lb/>political union), in Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, 12 November 2012, 12. <lb/>46 Böckenförde, note 25 above. <lb/>47 Section IV.2. <lb/>48 J. HABERMAS, "A Pact for or against Europe?", in U. GUÉROT and J. HÉNARD (eds), What does Germany <lb/>Think about Europe?, European Council on Foreign Relations, Berlin, 83-89. <lb/>49 D. CHALMERS, "European Restatements of Sovereignty", LSE Working Paper 10/2013. <lb/>50 W. STREECK, Gekaufte Zeit. Die vertagte Krise des demokratischen Kapitalismus, Berlin, Suhrkamp Verlag, <lb/>2013, Chapter III. <lb/>51 C. JOERGES and M. WEIMER, "A Crisis of Executive Managerialism in the EU: No Alternative?", in G. <lb/>DE BÚRCA, C. KILPATRICK and J. SCOTT (eds), Liber Amicorum for David M Trubek, Oxford, Hart <lb/>Publishing, 2014, 295-322, available at http://ssrn.com/abstract=2190362. <lb/>52 F.W. SCHARPF, "Political Legitimacy in a Non-optimal Currency Area", MPIfG Discussion Paper <lb/>12/15, Cologne, 2013. <lb/>53 D.M. CURTIN, "Challenging Executive Dominance in European Democracy", Chorley Lecture, London 2013, <lb/>(2014) 77 Modern Law Review, 1-32. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, Special Issue (2015) <lb/></note>
    
    <page>20 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>democratic default (Majone) 54 . None of these characterisations sounds flattering. <lb/>Concerns as to their compatibility with Europe's commitments to democracy and the <lb/>established understandings of the rule of law are widespread. So are concerns about the <lb/>erosion of the legitimacy of the integration project as such. Equally disquieting is an <lb/>emerging consensus about the features which underline the lack of any <lb/>theoretical/conceptual paradigm. As the most famous (and most thoughtful) proponent <lb/>of the integration-through-law project summarised it recently: while democracy had <lb/>neither been on the foundational agenda or credibly accomplished later, an Ersatz-<lb/>legitimation through the output which the project delivered has become equally <lb/>fictitious at least for the Member States in Europe's new periphery. What is left is <lb/>"messianism", the release of the peoples of Europe from their bellicose past into a <lb/>common future which the former aggressor was invited to share 55 . This grand legacy, <lb/>however, does not render the present economic, social and political hardships <lb/>sustainable. <lb/>4.2. Normalisation v. Political Contestation <lb/>The new modes of economic governance seem, by now, to be firmly established, <lb/>and their legality has been so strongly confirmed that their critique has become <lb/>practically pointless 56 . We will even have to concede that the measures taken cannot <lb/>simply be called a wilful and unwarranted abuse of power. The critical evaluations listed <lb/>do not even insinuate a return to the status quo ante and even uncompromising critics of <lb/>the political choices taken do not suggest that the short decade of Europe's crisis <lb/>management can be undone 57 . Two types of responses prevail at present. One strand in <lb/>the debate pleads for "normalisation". This term has been coined in debates on the state <lb/>of exception 58 . It indicates the readiness to take the transformation which we are <lb/>witnessing as factum (more or less) brutum. The attitude is particularly widespread in legal <lb/>literature. The new framework is meticulously documented, while queries regarding its <lb/>legitimacy are treated with benign neglect. A functional equivalent can be found in the <lb/>re-statement of the position of the Maastricht Court: financial policy is to be treated as a <lb/>non-political matter which can be delegated to experts. At the outer end of this <lb/>spectrum is the position defended by political theorist Kenneth Dyson, who does not <lb/>shy away from flirting with Schmitt -albeit in a rhetorically softened manner and with <lb/>references to John Rawls and H.L.A. Hart. To quote him at some length: <lb/>"…all polities face the basic existential question of whether, in supreme <lb/>emergency, there are limits on what they can do, and how. This question of the <lb/>limits of normal moral reasoning arises when polities are faced by clear and <lb/>imminent danger to their integrity and survival and to the understandings that were <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>54 G. MAJONE, Rethinking the Union of Europe Post-crisis, note 8 above, 179-207. <lb/>55 J.H.H. WEILER, "Europe in Crisis -On 'Political Messianism', 'Legitimacy' and the 'Rule of Law'", <lb/>(2012) Singapore Law Journal, 248-268. <lb/>56 M. RUFFERT, "Annotation to Pringle", (2013) 69 Juiristenzeitung, 257-259. <lb/>57 C. OFFE, Europe Entrapped, Cambridge: Cambridge: Polity Press, 2015. <lb/>58 M.-S. KUO, "The Moment of Schmittian Truth: Conceiving of the State of Exception in the Wake of <lb/>the Financial Crisis", in C. JOERGES and C. GLINSKI (eds), The European Crisis and the Transformation of <lb/>Transnational Governance: Authoritarian Managerialism versus Democratic Governance, Oxford-Portland OR, Hart <lb/>Publishing, 2014, 83-100. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Christian Joerges, Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance in Europe <lb/></note>
    
    <page>21 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>at the heart of their constitution-making process. In the case of the EU and EMU, <lb/>such understandings might relate to treaty provisions on irreversibility and <lb/>solidarity. On this basis, it can be argued that the Euro Area is a matter of <lb/>existential national interest for its member states. They are politically committed to <lb/>'making the euro work' and to ensuring its survival as 'irrevocable', as a <lb/>'community of destiny'. Making credible this commitment means 'doing what has <lb/>to be done' so that intertwined banking collapses and disorderly sovereign defaults <lb/>do not trigger the collapse of the Euro Area and place the survival of the wider <lb/>EU, including the single market, at risk. Politically, this kind of argument involves a <lb/>commitment to 'consequentialism': namely, that the costs of not acting in this way <lb/>would be too awful to contemplate. In legal theory, it finds expression in the <lb/>notion of establishing legal validity by reference to sources of authoritative criteria <lb/>outside specific constitutional or treaty provisions" 59 . <lb/>Are Europe's new modes of economic governance well established? All, by now, <lb/>really firmly established? Assuming that the experts and technocrats in the DG <lb/>Economy and Finance in the European Commission and the European technocratic <lb/>networks will not deliver what their political masters keep promising; will such failures <lb/>generate ever more unrest and protest among disempowered citizens who are exposed <lb/>to austerity measures which are experienced as hopeless, if not unnecessary, suffering? <lb/>What if they recall that the technocrat is an emperor without clothes? 60 Will they <lb/>increasingly provoke the political public, national parliaments and even factions in the <lb/>EP? Will it become ever more apparent that it is simply impossible for the great <lb/>majority of signatories to comply with the requirements imposed upon them? Will <lb/>national constitutional courts provide protection against the erosion of political rights <lb/>and social entitlements? 61 <lb/>If these conjectures prove to be warranted, the room for political manoeuvre will <lb/>widen. The epistemic communities organising Europe's crisis management may be <lb/>forced to re-consider their recipes. Conflicts of interests cannot be camouflaged and the <lb/>European technocracy cannot be shielded either against the European public or against <lb/>politicians who are accountable to their constituencies. Is it conceivable that the new <lb/>policy co-ordination within the annually repeating European Semester, the reporting <lb/>and multilateral surveillance obligations, the macroeconomic imbalance procedures, the <lb/>responses to country-specific recommendations will lead to new assessments of the <lb/>weight of socio-economic diversity, insights into the social embeddedness of markets, <lb/>acknowledgement of the different regulatory, social and economic cultures in the <lb/>Member States, a search for innovative responses to complex conflict constellations, <lb/>and, sooner or later, even to the development of standards and criteria which can <lb/>discipline authoritarian managerialism? <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>59 K. DYSON, "Sworn to Grim Necessity? Imperfections of European Economic Governance, Normative <lb/>Political Theory, and Supreme Emergency", (2013) 35 Journal of European Integration, 207-222, at 211. <lb/>60 See F.A. VON HAYEK, "The Pretence of Knowledge", (1989) 79 The American Economic Review, 3-7. <lb/>61 Acórdão No 187/2013, Processo no 2/2013, 5/2013, 8/2013 e 11/2013, Plenário, English translation <lb/>available at: http://www.tribunalconstitucional.pt/tc/en/acordaos/20130187s.html; A Fischer-Lescano <lb/>has summarised the broad spectre of human rights violations through austerity measures in a pertinent <lb/>study: "Human Rights in Times of Austerity Policy The EU institutions and the conclusion of <lb/>Memoranda of Understanding", available at: http://www.jura.uni-bremen.de/institute/zentrum-fuer-<lb/>europaeische-rechtspolitik/aktuelles. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, Special Issue (2015) <lb/></note>
    
    <page>22 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>All of these considerations and conjectures are far from providing a substantiated <lb/>alternative programmatique. They only assume that Europe's present post-constitutional <lb/>constellation is far from stable, and that its precarious legitimacy will provoke political <lb/>conflict and contestation. To put this slightly differently: legal scholarship is well advised <lb/>to refrain from presumptuous promises; faced with profound uncertainties, it has to <lb/>content itself with tentative deliberation. One not-so-tentative assumption is the <lb/>expectation that the type of normalisation which is currently en vogue will not do away <lb/>with the conflict configurations which it seeks to control. What lawyers can accomplish <lb/>is to re-construct the claims raised in these conflicts and evaluate the arguments <lb/>supporting them. Co-operative problem-solving, rather than authoritarian conditionality, <lb/>is the constitutional assumption and hope implicit in this diagnosis 62 . <lb/>5. "Wo Gefahr ist, wächst das Rettende auch"? 63 An Epilogue <lb/>Contestation is bound to intensify in Europe, both within national societies and <lb/>between them. We can hope for productive innovations which such conflicts and <lb/>debates may generate. But we also have to consider and explore socio-economic <lb/>conditions, chances of deliberative social and legal change. And we should listen to <lb/>outside observers who take an intense and emphatic interest in the future of Europe. <lb/>One particularly stimulating commentator is Dani Rodrik, an economist by education <lb/>and passionate publicist at the Princeton Institute for Advanced Study. In a famous <lb/>book 64 , Rodrik has submitted his "trilemma thesis". He asserts the impossibility of the <lb/>simultaneous pursuit of economic globalisation, democratic politics and national <lb/>determination (autonomy), highlighting that only two goals can be paired: either <lb/>economic globalisation and democratic politics, or democracy and national autonomy. <lb/>Rodrik has recently underlined that the EU furnishes dramatic illustration of this <lb/>trilemma 65 . The EU could transnationalise democracy through federalisation and <lb/>thereby defend the advantages of the common market. Federalisation would imply that <lb/>it would, at the same time, be forced to establish common European politics to <lb/>legitimise the necessary assumption of fiscal and social policy, with negative <lb/>consequences for national sovereignty. In the absence of such a de-nationalising will, he <lb/>asserts, the EU will have to give up the common currency and accept economic <lb/>disintegration. <lb/>Is federalisation the way out of the crisis? Rodrik's diagnosis is de facto deeply <lb/>pessimistic, because, in his view, the federalisation vision is an abstract utopia. Political <lb/>Democratic Union would have to be defined and accomplished in democratic processes. <lb/>The same holds true for the institutional configurations of the economy. All this would <lb/>have to happen very soon, but is inconceivable in the foreseeable future. He concludes: <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>62 Conflicts-Law Constitutionalism's "second dimension" as elaborated, for example, in the contribution <lb/>cited in note 15 above. <lb/>63 (But where danger threatens, that which saves from it also grows) F. HÖLDERLIN, Patmos. Dem <lb/>Landgrafen von Homburg überreichte Handschrift, 1802 (quoted from F. HÖLDERLIN, Werke, Salzburg-Stuttgart, <lb/>Bergland, 1954, 379; English translation by M. HAMBURGER, in F. HÖLDERLIN, Selected Poems and <lb/>Fragments, London, Penguin Books, 1994, 243). <lb/>64 D. RODRIK, The Globalization Paradox: Democracy and the Future of the World Economy, New York-London, <lb/>W.W. Norton, 2011. <lb/>65 The Future of European Democracy, Princeton, available at: <lb/>https://www.sss.ias.edu/files/pdfs/Rodrik/Commentary/Future-of-Democracy-in-Europe.pdf. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Christian Joerges, Flaws, Old and New, of Economic Governance in Europe <lb/></note>
    
    <page>23 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>"Instead of deepening integration, policy makers must look for ways of undoing it <lb/>selectively, opening up policy space for national governments in money, finance, <lb/>and regulation. Under the scenario, the future of monetary union looks particularly <lb/>bleak, as it is hard to see a single currency can be reconciled with multiple <lb/>(democratic) polities" 66 . <lb/>To take outside observers seriously does not mean that we have to subscribe to <lb/>their argument. In defiance of Dani Rodrik's Trilemma thesis, I am not persuaded that <lb/>state-or federation-building is the only conceivable response to the tensions between <lb/>transnational economic integration and democratic legitimacy. As indicated in the first <lb/>section, there is a democratic alternative, namely, the "unity in diversity vision" of the <lb/>2003 draft constitutional Treaty for European Union. Rodrik would agree, but he would <lb/>also argue that then we would forego the economic benefits of the common market. <lb/>But would we really? Werner Abelshauser, in his unitas in pluralitate manifesto, disagrees <lb/>on empirical and normative grounds. His empirical evidence is the resistance of the <lb/>varieties of capitalism against economic integration 67 . This phenomenon is anything but <lb/>deplorable if the institutional diversity is economically beneficial, rather than <lb/>detrimental 68 . <lb/>The lawyer is not in a position to reject or to subscribe to the findings of <lb/>economic historians. What he is competent to explore is the legal framing of the kind of <lb/>variety that the historian has in mind. To my delight, Abelshauser refers, in note 30 of <lb/>his manifesto, to the re-conceptualisation of European law as a new type of conflicts <lb/>law. Conflicts-law constitutionalism is, indeed, a project which conceptualises unity in <lb/>diversity as Europe's constitutional form 69 . What I, sadly, have to add is that the crisis <lb/>has affected this project strongly. It was designed as an exercise in critical theory with <lb/>normative perspectives which would not confront the state of the integration project <lb/>with merely normatively attractive ideas, but which, in the tradition of the Frankfurt <lb/>School, would identify aspects of the integration process which had a potential for <lb/>institutional innovations, and might, thanks to the ingenuity of committed actors, be <lb/>transformed in a constructive way. As it seemed in less troubled times, conflicts-law <lb/>constitutionalism could eventually be elaborated further and proceed as a re-constructive <lb/>project, i.e., a re-conceptualisation of European law, which would, to a considerable <lb/>degree, be compatible with European law as it stood, and be able to orient its further <lb/>development. The re-constructive status was based upon its sociological premises which <lb/>reflect the conflict-laden European constellation more adequately than the orthodoxy of <lb/>European law. All that seemed necessary, and, indeed, overdue, was to re-consider the <lb/>integration project in the light of Europe's ever growing diversity, to take the conflicts <lb/>which this diversity generated into account, and to re-orient Europe's agenda from <lb/>harmonisation and unity to the management of complex conflict constellations. The <lb/>analytics of this approach retain their potential, and the normative commitments have <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>66 D. RODRIK, ibid., 6. <lb/>67 Italy, united for so long, provides a challenging example; see G. MAJONE, "Strength through Union? <lb/>Not Always: The Case of Italian Unification, 1861 to the present. Ms. Florence 2014 (on file with author). <lb/>68 See the works of W. ABELSHAUSER cited in note 10 above, and his The Dynamics of German Industry: The <lb/>German Road toward the New Economy and the American Challenge, Providence-Oxford, Berghahn Books, 2005. <lb/>69 See C. JOERGES, "Unity in Diversity", note 12 above. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Cultura giuridica e diritto vivente, Special Issue (2015) <lb/></note>
    
    <page>24 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>not been invalidated. As outlined in Section IV.2, the crisis requires re-conceptualisation <lb/>under high uncertainties and with uncertain prospects 70 . <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>70 See C. JOERGES and C. GLINSKI (eds), The European Crisis and the Transformation of Transnational <lb/>Governance. Authoritarian Managerialism versus Democratic Governance, Oxford-Portland OR, Hart Publishing, <lb/>2014. </listBibl>


	</text>


  
  </TEI>