<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="https://pdf-tei-editor.panya.de/api/files/872ab" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap: The ‘Anglo-German Antagonism’ as History and International Relations Paradigm</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Matthew P</forename>
            <surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-09-17T17:28:02.729149Z">17.09.2025 17:28:02</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [article/dh-law-footnotes]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1093$1$gerhis$1$ghaf028</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2025</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1093/gerhis/ghaf028</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Matthew P Fitzpatrick. (2025). A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap: The ‘Anglo-German Antagonism’ as History and International Relations Paradigm. German History, 43(2), 161-180. DOI: 10.1093/gerhis/ghaf028</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-09-17T17:28:02.729149Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">0707645</label>
          <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-09-17T17:28:02.729149Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>German History Vol. 43, No. 2, pp. 161-180 <lb/>Advance Access publication 26 June 2025 <lb/>© The Author(s) 2025. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the German History Society. <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (https:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, <lb/>provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact reprints@oup.com for reprints and translation <lb/>rights for reprints. All other permissions can be obtained through our RightsLink service via the Permissions link on the article <lb/>page on our site-for further information please contact journals.permissions@oup.com. https://doi.org/10.1093/gerhis/ghaf028 <lb/>A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap: The &apos;Anglo-<lb/>German Antagonism&apos; as History and International <lb/>Relations Paradigm * <lb/>Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>In 1912, looking back on the Agadir crisis, the American naval officer and noted his-<lb/>torian French Ensor Chadwick summarized the contemporary situation in Europe: <lb/>We see the two foremost nations of Europe, the two most highly civilised nations of the world, spending <lb/>vast sums; the one striving to overtake, the other striving to preserve, supremacy in maritime power. Can <lb/>anyone say that the game of Morocco was worth the candle? […] Is England to be destroyed by Germany, <lb/>or Germany to be destroyed by England, or France to disappear as France because the special trader wants <lb/>an extension of his field? […] It would seem that the words Delenda est Cartago [sic] must be in the hearts of <lb/>many, both German and English. But why this feeling? The Englishman cannot hate the German per se, <lb/>nor the German the Englishman to the extent of desiring one to annihilate the other. There must be some <lb/>deep and powerful reason which does not appear upon the surface […] This reason is in that ever most <lb/>potent cause of international dissension-trade jealousy. 1 <lb/>Chadwick&apos;s assertion-that global trade and the zero-sum competitive nature of pre-<lb/>1914 imperial globalization had led to a poisoning of Anglo-German relations-has <lb/>loomed large in historiography ever since the First World War. Echoing sentiments <lb/>perhaps most famously outlined in the British Foreign Office memorandum penned by <lb/>Eyre Crowe in 1907, some historians have argued that the conduct of the two powers <lb/>during several international crises supports this antagonism paradigm. 2 Whether re-<lb/>counting the two Moroccan crises, the scramble for Africa, the Samoan tangle, differ-<lb/>ences over the Boer War, competition in East Asia or naval rivalry in the North Sea, <lb/>the story is ostensibly always the same: a threatening Germany forcing concession after <lb/>concession from a reluctant Britain. <lb/></body>

            <front>* This research has been enabled by an Australian Research Future Fellowship (FT210100448 -Strategic Friendship: <lb/>Anglo-German Cooperation in the Asia-Pacific Region). Thanks also to Flinders University for assisting me in <lb/>hosting the 2023 conference &apos;Best of Enemies? Anglo-German Relations and Empire&apos;. This article and those in the <lb/>rest of this Special Issue are the product of that conference. They should be read together with a similarly themed <lb/>Special Issue of the journal Australian Historical Studies (forthcoming as 56, 4 [2025]), which looks at similar ques-<lb/>tions of Anglo-German relations through the lens of Australasia and the Pacific. Special thanks to Richard Scully <lb/>for reading and commenting on an earlier draft and to Jan Rüger for his important advice regarding the subject <lb/>matter of this paper. Neither is responsible for the views expressed here. <lb/></front>

            <listBibl>1 F. E. Chadwick, &apos;The Anglo-German Tension and a Solution&apos;, American Journal of International Law, 6, 3 (1912), <lb/>pp. 601-13, here pp. 607-8. <lb/>2 E. Crowe, &apos;Appendix A: Memorandum on the Present State of British Relations with France and Germany&apos; [1 Jan. <lb/>1907], in G. P. Gooch and H. Temperley (eds), British Documents on the Origins of the War, vol. 3: The Testing of <lb/>the Entente, 1904-6 (London, 1928), pp. 397-420, here pp. 402-20. <lb/></listBibl>

            <front>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></front>

			<page>162</page>

            <note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

            <body>This binary picture of great-power antagonism is, as Thomas Sanderson argued in <lb/>his critique of Crowe&apos;s memorandum, only a portion of the picture. 3 While in some im-<lb/>perial sites intense economic (and associated geopolitical) competition seemed to point <lb/>ineluctably towards future conflict, elsewhere commercial and imperial imperatives dic-<lb/>tated that Britain, Germany and their respective subjects work closely together. Under <lb/>the veneer of what some have assumed was enduring great-power rivalry lay a foun-<lb/>dation of common, or at least overlapping, trans-imperial purpose and cooperation. <lb/>Examples of Anglo-German amity abound. As late as the end of 1914, for example, <lb/>with the First World War well underway, the chairman of the Hong Kong and Shanghai <lb/>Banking Corporation (HSBC), Charles Addis, came under enormous pressure from his <lb/>compatriots to disassociate himself from his German colleagues in the Deutsche Bank, <lb/>colleagues with whom he had enjoyed an indispensable and highly profitable decades-<lb/>long partnership in North Asia. Their cooperation had seen the two banks work closely <lb/>with the British and German Foreign Offices to bring the commanding heights of the <lb/>Chinese economy under joint Anglo-German control, a process complicated only by <lb/>the meddling of rivals such as France, Russia, Japan and the United States, who saw <lb/>themselves as being excluded in the &apos;financial battle for Peking&apos; by the lockstep actions <lb/>of the Anglo-German consortium. 4 As late as the first week of January 1915, Addis <lb/>replied to his critics, warning, <lb/>It may be urged that the economic reasons in favour of the retention of German firms must bend to the <lb/>political reasons for wiping them out. Personally, I do not believe it is a good policy to crush Germany […] <lb/>Our quarrel is with the German government, not with the German people. Our aim is to destroy German <lb/>militarism, not to prey on private property. When the war is over, we will shake hands and be friends again. <lb/>Do not let us do anything now to make a rapprochement more difficult hereafter. 5 <lb/>A few months prior, Governor Erich Schultz had made a similarly clear-eyed assessment <lb/>of the still-warm relations between German and British subjects in German Samoa <lb/>after more than a decade of colonial cooperation there. Although the war was already <lb/>in full swing in Europe, Schultz refused to intern, restrict or even disarm British subjects <lb/>living in the colony. When the New Zealanders under Colonel Robert Logan came to <lb/>occupy Samoa, those same British colonists, led by their acting vice consul, Thomas <lb/>Trood, repaid the governor&apos;s wartime solidarity by signing a petition that spelled out <lb/>the extent to which they &apos;fully appreciated the kindness shown&apos; to them &apos;by Dr Schultz <lb/>and the German officials and residents in Samoa since the war was announced&apos;. They <lb/>hoped, the petition continued, &apos;that in the event of a change of flags His Excellency <lb/>Dr Schultz and the German residents will meet with the same consideration that we <lb/>received&apos;. 6 This request from the colony&apos;s British subjects was ignored, however, by the <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>3 T. Sanderson, &apos;Appendix B: Memorandum by Lord Sanderson&apos; [21 Feb. 1907], in Gooch and Temperley, British <lb/>Documents on the Origins of the War, vol. 3, pp. 420-33. <lb/>4 A. Skřivan and A. Skřivan, &apos;The Financial Battle for Beijing: The Great Powers and Loans to China, 1895-1898&apos;, <lb/>Historian, 79, 3 (2017), pp. 476-503; M. P. Fitzpatrick, &apos;Globalisation or Empire? Revolution, the State and the <lb/>Geopolitics of Chinese Debt, 1895-1914&apos;, Enterprise &amp; Society (2024), https://doi.org/10.1017/eso.2024.21; G. <lb/>Moazzin, &apos;Networks of Capital: German Bankers and the Financial Internationalisation of China (1885-1919)&apos;, <lb/>Enterprise &amp; Society, 20, 4 (2019), pp. 796-808. <lb/>5 Addis to Hillier, 4 Jan. 1915, in HSBC Archive HQ HSBCK 0003 Letters (unnumbered). <lb/>6 Petition, 29 Aug. 1914, signed by Thomas Trood and ninety-two others, Bundesarchiv Berlin, R1001/2627, <lb/>&apos;Correspondence Relating to the Occupation of German Samoa by An Expeditionary Force from New Zealand&apos;, p. <lb/>64. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap</note>

            <page>163 <lb/></page>

        <body>commander of New Zealand&apos;s ramshackle occupying force, with a wave of internments <lb/>of prominent German subjects following. <lb/>I. New Approaches <lb/>These anecdotes may well be simply that, exceptions that prove the structural rule of <lb/>wartime hatred built upon long-term prewar enmity. Or they may point to the differ-<lb/>ences between the political friction of European metropoles and the context-bound <lb/>cooperation of the &apos;men on the spot&apos; that Michael Fröhlich investigated thirty-five <lb/>years ago in his study of Anglo-German relations in Africa. 7 Alternatively, these in-<lb/>stances of imperial amity may suggest that there are complexities and contradictions <lb/>in Anglo-German relations prior to 1914 that complicate Paul Kennedy&apos;s now more <lb/>than 40-year-old schema that posited the centrality of &apos;Anglo-German antagonism&apos; to <lb/>the causes of the general European war of 1914 to 1918. 8 Indeed, the examples cited <lb/>above-as well as others like them discussed in the articles in this Special Issue that <lb/>highlight relations far from the heart of Europe-might well offer new answers to old <lb/>but still-pressing questions related to the central place of trans-imperial relations in <lb/>global commerce and imperial diplomacy prior to the First World War. <lb/>The contributions to this Special Issue, focused primarily on Anglo-German rela-<lb/>tions in Africa and Asia, illustrate the extent to which metropolitan officials and British <lb/>and German subjects outside Europe were forced to navigate a complex course be-<lb/>tween cooperation and competition. In the domain of high politics, relations between <lb/>the two powers were characterized, these articles show, by pragmatism, flexibility and <lb/>context-specific considerations of commerce and security. These imperatives are closely <lb/>examined in this issue by Julius Becker, whose article focuses on the North Asian con-<lb/>text, and by Jakob Zollmann, who examines how a long-standing border dispute in <lb/>Southern Africa was negotiated by the two powers. Closer to the lived experience of <lb/>the colonial frontier, both Felicity Jensz and Iris Leung show how relations between <lb/>German missionaries working in British colonial spaces and the British authorities ad-<lb/>ministering these colonies remained amicable and mutually beneficial at the grass-roots <lb/>level, even when their colonizing aims differed, right up until the First World War. 9 <lb/>As Sarah Panzer&apos;s discussion of Japanese leaders such as Katō Takaaki and <lb/>Zollmann&apos;s treatment of Hendrik Witbooi also make clear, these European interactions <lb/>were frequently shaped by the agency of extra-European peoples and nations, including <lb/>the colonized, who expressed and followed their own preferences and priorities in their <lb/>dealings with large foreign imperial powers. So too, in the European metropoles them-<lb/>selves, British and German governments and their respective Foreign Offices could not <lb/>operate without addressing the pressures of public and political opinion. In this regard, <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>7 M. Fröhlich, Von Konfrontation zur Koexistenz: die deutsch-englischen Kolonialbeziehungen in Afrika zwischen <lb/>1884 und 1914 (Bochum, 1990). <lb/>8 P. Kennedy, The Rise of the Anglo-German Antagonism, 1860-1914 (London, 1980). The most detailed and <lb/>wide-ranging historiographical assessment of the fate of this paradigm and its contribution to the broader <lb/>Sonderweg debate remains J. Rüger, &apos;Revisiting the Anglo-German Antagonism&apos;, Journal of Modern History, 83, <lb/>3 (2011), pp. 579-617. <lb/>9 On the relationship between missionary and secular colonizing endeavours, see J. Best, Heavenly Fatherland: <lb/>German Missionary Culture and Globalization in the Age of Empire (Toronto, 2020). <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>164</page>

			<note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

			<body>Andrew Bonnell&apos;s treatment of the German Social Democratic Party demonstrates <lb/>how the party sought to position itself in response to British colonialism. He highlights <lb/>the ambivalences of a party that contained both influential revisionists, who saw colo-<lb/>nialism as serving the imperatives of world historical progress, and a majority who were <lb/>keen to critique the imperial violence of Britain out of a sense of fraternal affiliation <lb/>with the Boer population but did not want to be seen to make common cause with <lb/>German nationalists also opposing Britain&apos;s war. <lb/>Together, these articles underline the extent to which Kennedy&apos;s superseded but <lb/>stubbornly influential antagonism paradigm requires close re-examination and, argu-<lb/>ably, robust negation, as one-sided (in its ascription of colonial crises solely to German <lb/>actions), teleologically flawed (in its orientation towards explaining German guilt for <lb/>the outbreak of the First World War) and misleading in its conclusions-not least be-<lb/>cause of the way in which the antagonism paradigm has influenced political science <lb/>and international relations, crowding out more complex ways of viewing causality and <lb/>the imperial prehistory of the First World War. <lb/>Just as progress has been made by historians such as Christopher Clark and William <lb/>Mulligan in complicating earlier monocausal explanations of the origins of the First <lb/>World War, so too the Anglo-German antagonism should be reappraised for its suit-<lb/>ability as an analytical paradigm, in particular with due consideration given to its global <lb/>dimension. 10 Echoing Dominik Geppert and Robert Gerwarth&apos;s doubts regarding the <lb/>&apos;traditional scholarly focus on the rise of the Anglo-German antagonism&apos; prior to 1914 <lb/>and sharing their scepticism about &apos;a clash of cultures&apos;, the articles in this Special Issue <lb/>offer a sense of the finer grain of the relational ambivalence at the heart of Anglo-<lb/>German history, particularly in the colonial context. 11 The articles here look beyond <lb/>Europe for a history that, as many historians have suggested, vacillated between con-<lb/>flict and cooperation, &apos;appropriation and resistance&apos;, &apos;entanglement and antagonism&apos;. 12 <lb/>Without airbrushing the real points of contention between the two powers, the articles <lb/>in this collection affirm John M. Mackenzie&apos;s insight that &apos;imperialism on the ground <lb/>was often more cooperative than competitive&apos;. 13 They offer further evidence of Ulrike <lb/>Lindner&apos;s view that &apos;global interconnectedness always functioned in parallel to nation-<lb/>alist distinctions&apos; and that by the beginning of the First World War, &apos;a common imperial <lb/>project&apos; was just as evident as antipathy. 14 In the main, the following articles concur <lb/>with Fröhlich&apos;s assessment that &apos;overseas rivalry at no point took on such an intensity as <lb/>to have inflicted irreparable damage to bilateral relations&apos;. 15 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>10 C. Clark, The Sleepwalkers: How Europe Went to War in 1914 (London, 2012); W. Mulligan, The Origins of the <lb/>First World War (Cambridge, 2017). <lb/>11 D. Geppert and R. Gerwarth, &apos;Introduction&apos;, in D. Geppert and R. Gerwarth (eds), Wilhelmine Germany and <lb/>Edwardian Britain: Essays on Cultural Affinity (Oxford, 2008), pp. 1-13, here p. 3. <lb/>12 Ibid., p. 13; R. Muhs, J. Paulmann and W. Steinmetz (eds), Aneignung und Abwehr: interkultureller Transfer <lb/>zwischen Deutschland und Großbritannien im 19. Jahrhundert (Bodenheim, 1998); Rüger, &apos;Revisiting the Anglo-<lb/>German Antagonism&apos;, pp. 581-5. <lb/>13 J. M. Mackenzie, &apos;&quot;Mutual Goodwill and Admiration&quot; or &quot;Jealous Ill-Will&quot;? Empire and Popular Culture&apos;, in <lb/>Geppert and Gerwarth, Wilhelmine Germany and Edwardian Britain, pp. 91-113, here p. 93. <lb/>14 U. Lindner, Koloniale Begegnungen: Deutschland und Großbritannien als Imperialmächte in Afrika 1880-1914 <lb/>(Frankfurt/Main, 2011), pp. 10-11. <lb/>15 Fröhlich, Von Konfrontation zur Koexistenz, p. 311. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap</note>

            <page>165 <lb/></page>

			<body>II. The Antagonism Paradigm <lb/>The intricacies of Kennedy&apos;s thesis, as fleshed out in his still-influential Rise of the Anglo-<lb/>German Antagonism, 1860-1914 (1980), do not require extensive rehearsal here. At heart <lb/>his book argued that the rise of Germany was simply incompatible with the continued <lb/>global hegemony of Britain. Like Chadwick, Kennedy believed that &apos;the most pro-<lb/>found cause&apos; of this great-power estrangement &apos;was economic&apos;. 16 Germany&apos;s &apos;booming <lb/>overseas trade, political influence abroad, colonial acquisitions and an expanding fleet <lb/>[…] necessarily implied a relative diminution in Britain&apos;s own commercial / colonial <lb/>/ maritime position&apos;. 17 Given such zero-sum conditions, Kennedy argued, Germany&apos;s <lb/>expansion was ill-advised, indeed positively dangerous. For Kennedy, that the British <lb/>Empire, as global hegemon, &apos;accounted for something like 44% of foreign investment <lb/>on the eve of the First World War&apos;, was immaterial. 18 It was only German imperialism <lb/>that represented a threat to world peace. Like other historians before him, Kennedy ac-<lb/>cepted Britain&apos;s right to global pre-eminence as a historical given and ignored the fact <lb/>that Britain&apos;s imperial predations were continuing right alongside those of Germany, <lb/>only on a far larger scale. By relegating British imperial expansion to an indistinct <lb/>past and naturalizing Britain&apos;s global empire as a precondition for geopolitical stability, <lb/>Kennedy deflected any attempt to assess the striking commonalities apparent in the <lb/>actions of the two powers, arguing that &apos;the German desire (and attempt) to grow at <lb/>the expense of its neighbours cannot be excused by reference to the earlier misdeeds <lb/>of others&apos;. <lb/>In effect, Kennedy&apos;s tendency to overlook the predatory nature of global British <lb/>imperialism while emphasizing the destabilizing effects of German imperialism repro-<lb/>duced the sense of British exceptionalism rebuked in 1899 by Germany&apos;s foreign min-<lb/>ister, Bernhard von Bülow, in his famous &apos;hammer or anvil&apos; speech: <lb/>The English Prime Minister has long said that the stronger states will get stronger and the weak states <lb/>will get weaker. Everything that has happened since is proof of the correctness of these words. […] We <lb/>cannot allow that some foreign power, that some foreign Jupiter says to us, &apos;What can we do? The world <lb/>has already been divided.&apos; We do not want to encroach on any foreign power, but we don&apos;t want to let a <lb/>foreign power tread on our toes, and we won&apos;t allow ourselves to be pushed aside by any foreign power, not <lb/>in political or commercial matters. 19 <lb/>For Kennedy, any such German presumptions that questioned British imperial he-<lb/>gemony were grossly &apos;imprudent&apos; attempts to enter into the British preserve of global <lb/>power politics. 20 Britain, which Kennedy admitted &apos;had indeed carved out a colossal <lb/>world empire&apos; escaped his opprobrium because he believed that this empire had ex-<lb/>panded while &apos;emphasising the rights of European peoples, converting to free trade <lb/>and allowing open access to its colonies since the mid-nineteenth century&apos;. Ostensibly, <lb/>it had been able to &apos;harmonize its national policy with the general desire and ideals <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>16 Kennedy, Rise of the Anglo-German Antagonism, p. 464. Emphasis in the original. <lb/>17 Ibid., p. 465. <lb/>18 N. Ferguson, The Pity of War (London, 1998), pp. 34-6. <lb/>19 Bernhard von Bülow, 11 Dec. 1899, in Stenographische Bericht über die Verhandlungen des Reichstages, 10. <lb/>Legislaturperiode, 1. Session, 1898/1900, vol. 4 (Berlin, 1900), 119. Sitzung, pp. 3292-5. <lb/>20 Kennedy, Rise of the Anglo-German Antagonism, p. 467; P. Kennedy, The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers: <lb/>Economic Change and Military Conflict from 1500 to 2000 (London, 1988), p. 213. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>166</page>

			<note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

			<body>common to all mankind&apos;. 21 Accordingly, it would have been better if Germany had <lb/>simply not sought to question Britain&apos;s domination of global markets, had not joined <lb/>the other powers in claiming mercantile and settler colonies, and had not presumed to <lb/>have a navy that might compete with (but not remotely eclipse) that of Britain-in sum, <lb/>had not risen (as France, Russia and other powers had) to compete with Britain at all. 22 <lb/>Unwilling to recognize that German imperialism and British imperialism were closely <lb/>bound together, Kennedy pursued a one-sided, determinist line of argument that fore-<lb/>grounded the effects of the &apos;elemental German push to change the existing distribution <lb/>of power&apos; and reduced the agency of the world&apos;s largest and most powerful empire to <lb/>mutely accepting &apos;a substantial diminution in national influence and safety&apos;, a situation <lb/>which he believed &apos;was bound to provoke a reaction on their part&apos;. 23 <lb/>Kennedy was neither the first nor the last to posit that the structural drivers of global <lb/>mercantile and imperial competition had caused a serious deterioration in Anglo-<lb/>German relations or that this deterioration was integral to questions of war and peace <lb/>in 1914. Although also concerned with other factors, in 1927 Friedrich Meinecke had <lb/>pointed to the &apos;growth in global trade and global politics&apos; as partially to blame for <lb/>what he saw as a breakdown in Anglo-German relations. 24 As early as 1933, Ross J. S. <lb/>Hoffman had similarly argued that global economic rivalry was &apos;the soil out of which <lb/>the great questions at issue between the two nations grew&apos; and as such &apos;a basic cause <lb/>for the anti-German orientation of British world policy&apos;. 25 Closer to Kennedy&apos;s time, <lb/>Hugh Neuburger and Houston H. Stokes observed that the growth of the German <lb/>economy had been closely related to military matters, with &apos;predictions of Germany&apos;s <lb/>overtaking of Britain&apos; becoming a &apos;staple of British politics in the two decades before <lb/>World War One&apos;. 26 <lb/>Perhaps most influentially, Fritz Fischer also wrote that in entering the global imperial <lb/>fray, Germany had effectively &apos;entered into single combat with England&apos; in the decade <lb/>before 1914. 27 Crucially, like Kennedy after him, Fischer wanted to critique German <lb/>imperialism as a uniquely destabilizing force jeopardizing the seemingly benevolent <lb/>global Pax Britannica. Like Kennedy, Fischer&apos;s history assumed a static global British <lb/>Empire under attack from a uniquely malign German Empire. He investigated nei-<lb/>ther the devastating global consequences of European imperial competition (including <lb/>that of Britain) more broadly nor the ways in which the powers (including Britain and <lb/>Germany) that were engaged in imperial globalization often bypassed conflict and opted <lb/>instead for trans-imperial cooperation to press their claims onto colonized peoples. For <lb/>Fischer, the colonial inequities and violence emanating from the British Empire prior to <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>21 Kennedy, Rise of the Anglo-German Antagonism, p. 468. <lb/>22 This view, it is worth noting, is at odds with Kennedy&apos;s later axiomatic argument that &apos;the relative strengths of the <lb/>leading nations in world affairs never remain constant&apos;, Kennedy, Rise and Fall of the Great Powers, p. xv. <lb/>23 Kennedy, Rise of the Anglo-German Antagonism, p. 469. <lb/>24 F. Meinecke, Geschichte des deutsch-englischen Bündnisproblems, 1890-1901 (Berlin, 1927), pp. 5-6. <lb/>25 R. J. S. Hoffman, Great Britain and the German Trade Rivalry, 1875-1914 (Philadelphia, 1933), p. 279. <lb/>26 H. Neuburger and H. H. Stokes, &apos;The Anglo-German Trade Rivalry, 1887-1913: A Counterfactual Outcome and Its <lb/>Implications&apos;, Social Science History, 3, 2 (1979), pp. 187-201. <lb/>27 F. Fischer, Weltmacht oder Niedergang: Deutschland im ersten Weltkrieg (Frankfurt/Main, 1965), p. 37. See also <lb/>F. Fischer, Griff nach der Weltmacht: die Kriegszielpolitik des kaiserlichen Deutschland 1914/1918 (Düsseldorf, <lb/>1961), pp. 28-36. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap</note>

            <page>167 <lb/></page>

            <body>1914 remained beyond critique, with the global rights and claims of the British Empire <lb/>an accepted constant. Meanwhile, Germany&apos;s role after entering the global imperial <lb/>arena was evidence of a crippling and uniquely damaging Sonderweg. <lb/>Since Fischer&apos;s powerful intervention, Anglophone and German accounts held in <lb/>common this presumption of the naturalness of Britain&apos;s global empire as a structural <lb/>good guaranteeing the security of an enlightened international system that required <lb/>British hegemony as a benevolent stabilizing force. 28 Decolonizing and recasting this <lb/>starry-eyed British perception of themselves as global civilizers and pacifiers who self-<lb/>lessly worked to ensure the continuation of a peaceful geopolitical status quo remains a <lb/>work in progress. 29 This Anglophilic blind spot was accompanied by a sense that it was <lb/>German expansionism in particular (rather than European imperial competition tout <lb/>court) that had provoked a series of global crises in which Britain remained largely un-<lb/>sullied by ruthless considerations of imperial realpolitik and instead merely responded <lb/>to German provocations. Exemplifying this historiographical tendency, Imanuel Geiss <lb/>(for example) maintained that it was German Weltpolitik alone that &apos;fundamentally al-<lb/>tered the global situation, which led directly to global war&apos;. Meanwhile, the status quo <lb/>hegemon Britain merely reacted by leaving &apos;its splendid isolation&apos; occasionally to &apos;look <lb/>after its allies&apos;. 30 That Geiss saw British claims to the right to rule over the innumerable <lb/>peoples of Africa, Asia, Australasia, the Pacific and the Americas as indicative of a pref-<lb/>erence for the serenity of &apos;splendid isolation&apos;, offers a clear sense of the extent to which <lb/>Britain&apos;s benighted self-understanding had infiltrated postwar German scholarship. <lb/>More than forty years after Kennedy insisted that the notion that war guilt was <lb/>&apos;shared by all&apos; was &apos;flaccid&apos;, historians have moved on from his antagonism paradigm, <lb/>just as they have from Fischer&apos;s sense that Germany&apos;s pre-1914 Weltpolitik rested pre-<lb/>dominately on &apos;the aim of breaking Britain&apos;s domination of the world&apos;. 31 An earlier <lb/>era of historiographical certainty has been replaced by a period of generative historio-<lb/>graphical fragmentation, in which remaining Fischerites contend with the findings <lb/>of historians scrutinizing the role of other powers just as forensically as Fischer had <lb/>Germany&apos;s. 32 Historians now view as questionable Kennedy&apos;s lopsided attribution of <lb/>responsibility to the Germans for a putative Anglo-German estrangement, but occa-<lb/>sionally poisonous responses to attempts to move on from the dichotomous logic of the <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>28 For an overview of the response to Fischer&apos;s work, see A. Mombauer, &apos;The Fischer Controversy, Documents and <lb/>the &quot;Truth&quot; about the Origins of the First World War&apos;, Journal of Contemporary History, 48, 2 (2013), pp. 290-<lb/>314. The apogee of this view came with N. Ferguson, Empire: How Britain Made the Modern World (London, <lb/>2004). <lb/>29 P. Gopal, Insurgent Empire: Anticolonial Resistance and British Dissent (London, 2019); S. Sanghera, Empireland: <lb/>How Imperialism Has Shaped Modern Britain (London, 2021). <lb/>30 I. Geiss, Das Deutsche Reich und die Vorgeschichte des ersten Weltkriegs (Munich, 1978), p. 215. <lb/>31 Kennedy, Rise of the Anglo-German Antagonism, p. 467; F. Fischer, &apos;The Foreign Policy of Imperial Germany <lb/>and the Outbreak of the First World War&apos;, in G. Schöllgen (ed.), Escape into War? The Foreign Policy of Imperial <lb/>Germany (Oxford, 1990), pp. 19-40, here p. 21. <lb/>32 A. Mombauer, &apos;Guilt or Responsibility? The Hundred-Year Debate on the Origins of World War I&apos;, Central European <lb/>History, 48, 4 (2015), pp. 541-64. Rüger baulks at the work required to reconcile these rival historiographies, <lb/>noting that the &apos;challenge of bringing the two together in one narrative is immense&apos; (&apos;Revisiting the Anglo-<lb/>German Antagonism&apos;, p. 617), but arguably a lack of historiographical consensus offers more scope for complex <lb/>historical landscapes. See M. P. Fitzpatrick, &apos;Truth Telling, Historiographical Agonism, and the Colonial Past in <lb/>Germany and Australia&apos;, Australian Historical Studies, 55, 1 (2024), pp. 6-25. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>168</page>

			<note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

			<body>antagonism paradigm and its corollary, sole German war guilt, make it worth briefly <lb/>restating some recently made points of clarification. 33 <lb/>Most obvious among these points is that the war in 1914 was not a product of Anglo-<lb/>German enmity. As Jan Rüger has pointed out, an overwhelming majority of histor-<lb/>ians now understand that the First World War can no longer be assumed to be simply <lb/>&apos;the logical conclusion of a long-term deterioration in Anglo-German relations&apos;. 34 <lb/>Christopher Clark was correct to point out that in entering the war in 1914, Britain was <lb/>just as (if not more) concerned about the global imperial consequences of alienating <lb/>France and Russia (both of whom were well poised to make things difficult for Britain in <lb/>Africa, Asia and the Pacific) as about the need to contain Germany. 35 Similarly, William <lb/>Mulligan was right to argue that despite long-standing claims that a narrowly binary <lb/>Anglo-German antagonism had unalterably set the course for conflict in the decade <lb/>leading up to 1914, &apos;a general war was not an inevitable or even a probable outcome of <lb/>international rivalries before 1914&apos;. Indeed, as Mulligan made clear, stressing the puta-<lb/>tively ineluctable effects of a structuring bilateral rivalry between Britain and Germany <lb/>can only lead historical research &apos;into something of a teleological tunnel&apos;. 36 <lb/>As the following sections make clear, however, the antagonism paradigm has per-<lb/>sisted as received wisdom in fields beyond history, in ways that have real-world con-<lb/>sequences. Most significantly, it has encouraged twenty-first-century international <lb/>relations scholars to deploy the Anglo-German antagonism paradigm as an exemplar <lb/>that underwrites theories of the geopolitical present. In these theories, mid-to late-<lb/>twentieth-century histories (such as those of Fischer and Kennedy) that positioned the <lb/>British Empire as a benevolent guarantor of global stability, unjustly attacked around <lb/>the globe by Germany, function as legitimating narratives for hawkish attempts to nat-<lb/>uralize the global hegemony of the United States and to follow a policy of strict en-<lb/>circlement and containment of China. <lb/>III. The International Relations Trap <lb/>Having examined Anglo-German relations so carefully, it is not surprising that Kennedy <lb/>then turned his structuralist approach towards the construction of a broader theory <lb/>of the &apos;rise and fall&apos; of great powers since the sixteenth century. 37 In this later work, <lb/>Kennedy offered a more pronouncedly realist framework for a long-run geopolitical <lb/>history. As Michael Mann described Kennedy&apos;s case, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>33 Kennedy, Rise of the Anglo-German Antagonism, p. 467; G. Schmidt, &apos;Great Britain and Germany in the Age of <lb/>Imperialism&apos;, War and Society, 4, 1 (1986), pp. 31-51; Clark, Sleepwalkers, p. 560; Rüger, &apos;Revisiting the Anglo-<lb/>German Antagonism&apos;. For incensed reviews of Sleepwalkers from an older generation of Germanists, see, for <lb/>example, J. C. G. Röhl, &apos;Goodbye to All That (Again)? The Fischer Thesis, the New Revisionism and the Meaning <lb/>of the First World War&apos;, International Affairs, 91, 1 (2015), pp. 153-66; R. C. Moore, &apos;Neo-Revisionism and the <lb/>Origins of the First World War&apos;, London Journal of Research in Humanities and Social Sciences, 23, 22 (2023), pp. <lb/>21-51; J. A. Moses, &apos;Christopher Clark, the German Historians and the First World War: Telling It How It Essentially <lb/>Was?&apos;, ISAA Review, 17, 1 (2019), pp. 5-24. <lb/>34 Rüger, &apos;Revisiting the Anglo-German Antagonism&apos;, p. 615; J. Rüger, The Great Naval Game: Britain and Germany <lb/>in the Age of Empire (Cambridge, 2007), p. 248. <lb/>35 Clark, Sleepwalkers, pp. 544-7. <lb/>36 Mulligan, Origins of the First World War, p. 230. <lb/>37 Kennedy, Rise and Fall of the Great Powers. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap</note>

            <page>169 <lb/></page>

			<body>As a Realist he assumes the existence of states and their inherent tendencies to struggle with each other for <lb/>regional and sometimes global domination. It is in the nature of the consequent geopolitical system that <lb/>a few will become Great, and a select few become Hegemonic. But it is also inevitable that they will soon <lb/>decline again, to be replaced by others having their turn. What determines this rise and decline is funda-<lb/>mentally the uneven geographical distribution and economic and technological development. At points of <lb/>change in the geopolitical order, economic and technological dynamism will have passed from the dom-<lb/>inant Powers to some other area of the globe and to the Powers who inhabit it. Provided those newcomers <lb/>can convert that rising resource base into military power, they will become Great Powers. 38 <lb/>This process of rise and fall, driven by emerging powers challenging established ones, <lb/>was best understood, Kennedy asserted, as ancient, dating back to Greece in the fifth <lb/>century BCE. It was Thucydides, he continued, who first observed the iron law of rise <lb/>and fall at work: war between Athens and Sparta had been made inevitable by &apos;the <lb/>growth of Athenian power and the fear that this caused in Sparta&apos;. 39 <lb/>Others in the field of international relations have followed Kennedy in the search <lb/>for a long-range theory for the causes of war. Most recently, in 2017 Graham Allison <lb/>reworked Kennedy&apos;s &apos;Thucydidean&apos; realism into a transtemporal theory of rise and fall <lb/>that used not only Athens and Sparta but also the history of Anglo-German relations <lb/>as a primary case study: <lb/>As Paul Kennedy neatly puts it, the leaders of Britain and Germany considered that their clash in 1914 <lb/>was &apos;but a continuation of what had been going on for at least fifteen or twenty years&apos; and had begun <lb/>&apos;because the former power wished to preserve the existing status quo, whereas the latter, for a mixture of <lb/>offensive and defensive motives, was taking steps to alter it&apos;. 40 <lb/>In his highly mechanistic theory of international relations based on a precariously <lb/>narrow reading of Thucydides&apos;s oeuvre, Allison posited that the friction between rising <lb/>and declining great powers has been (and remains) the central historical dynamic <lb/>governing the propensity for armed conflict. 41 He termed this transtemporal theory of <lb/>imperial antagonism the &apos;Thucydides trap&apos;. Critically, however, Allison took Kennedy&apos;s <lb/>historically framed antagonism paradigm and turned it into a vehicle for geopolitical <lb/>prognostication. According to Allison&apos;s reading of Kennedy, earlier rivalries such as <lb/>that ostensibly structuring Anglo-German relations are best understood as harbingers <lb/>of an all-but-inevitable global future of continuing binary conflict between hegemons <lb/>and aspiring hegemons. In his monograph and several associated articles, Allison has <lb/>argued in no uncertain terms that the global history of great-power competition such <lb/>as that between Britain and Germany points to an apparent historical law that all but <lb/>determines that China and the United States must go to war in the near future. 42 While <lb/>Allison avers that his work was an attempt &apos;not to predict the future but to prevent it&apos;, <lb/>the data he offered suggests that great powers avoid war in only roughly 25 per cent <lb/>38 A. Giddens, M. Mann and I. Wallerstein, &apos;Comments on Paul Kennedy&apos;s The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers&apos;, <lb/>review symposium, British Journal of Sociology, 40, 2 (1989), pp. 328-40, here p. 332. <lb/>39 Thucydides, quoted in Kennedy, Rise and Fall of the Great Powers, p. 198. <lb/>40 G. Allison, Destined for War: Can America and China Escape the Thucydides Trap? (London, 2018), p. 83. <lb/>41 One reviewer summed up Allison&apos;s treatment of Thucydides as &apos;sloppy, superficial, oversimplified, overconfident <lb/>and repetitive&apos;; see J. Kirschner, &apos;Handle Him with Care: The Importance of Getting Thucydides Right&apos;, Security <lb/>Studies, 28, 1 (2018), pp. 1-24, https://doi.org/10.1080/09636412.2018.1508634, here p. 12. <lb/>42 Allison, Destined for War. The book was also the launching pad for an entire research project at Harvard <lb/>University devoted to seeking out further Thucydidean pairings across history. See https://www.belfercenter.org/ <lb/>thucydides-trap/overview-thucydides-trap. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>170</page>

			<note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

			<body>of cases. 43 As Richard Hanania has argued, Allison ended up &apos;all but foreclosing&apos; the <lb/>chances of avoiding war, by presenting the wish for peace as &apos;hopelessly naïve&apos; given the <lb/>overdetermining structures of history. 44 <lb/>Alongside his foundational exemplar of Athens and Sparta, Allison&apos;s most important <lb/>and detailed case study is that of European political relations prior to 1914, painted in <lb/>dichotomous colours strikingly similar to those used by Kennedy. As Allison wrote in <lb/>The Atlantic, it was his view that the tensions between the two powers offered proof posi-<lb/>tive of the axiom that &apos;when a rising power is threatening to displace a ruling power, <lb/>standard crises that would otherwise be contained, like the assassination of an archduke <lb/>in 1914, can initiate a cascade of reactions&apos;. 45 As Allison told a public-policy forum <lb/>in Beijing in March 2019, this example showed how the mutual antagonism between <lb/>China, as a rising power, and the United States, as a dominant power, could see &apos;third <lb/>party actions or accidents&apos; spiral towards war. His evidence lay with the origins of the <lb/>First World War, as he saw them. &apos;Think of 1914&apos;, he argued, <lb/>You had a rivalry between Germany rising and Great Britain. An archduke who was a second level official <lb/>from Austria-Hungary was assassinated in Sarajevo in June 1914. He was not connected to Britain. He <lb/>was not connected to Germany. But that action and the reactions to it within six weeks had the whole of <lb/>Europe at war with each other. And in four years had destroyed all of Europe and Europe&apos;s position as the <lb/>leader of the world at that time. 46 <lb/>As recently as 2020, Allison has reiterated his view that &apos;the risks of war in the decade <lb/>ahead are eerily similar to those faced by Germany and the UK a century ago&apos;. 47 <lb/>In terms of German historiography, Allison&apos;s understanding of the First World War <lb/>is a narrower, more binary, and less empirically grounded version of Geiss&apos;s earlier <lb/>view that &apos;all the other imperialist powers, frightened by the breath-taking dynamism <lb/>of the German upstart, pulled together&apos;. 48 His treatment of Anglo-German relations <lb/>also recalls Michael Howard&apos;s view that war came because Germany threatened the <lb/>&apos;European global order upon which British power and British prosperity rested&apos; and <lb/>John C. G. Röhl&apos;s view (which he held in common with Volker Berghahn and nu-<lb/>merous other historians) that &apos;the deepening antagonism&apos; and, ultimately, war between <lb/>Wilhelmine Germany and Britain was the result of &apos;the Reich&apos;s drive to become a <lb/>Weltmacht&apos; and Britain&apos;s determination &apos;to contain that grand ambition by forming a <lb/>ring of ententes to contain Germany&apos;. 49 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>43 https://www.belfercenter.org/thucydides-trap/case-file. <lb/>44 R. Hanania, &apos;Graham Allison and the Thucydides Trap Myth&apos;, Strategic Studies Quarterly, 15, 4 (2021), pp. 13-24, <lb/>here p. 24. <lb/>45 G. Allison, &apos;The Thucydides Trap: Are the US and China headed for War?&apos;, The Atlantic (24 Sept. 2015). <lb/>46 G. Allison, &apos;How to Escape the Thucydides Trap&apos;, speech given at the 2019 Harvard Alumni China Public Policy <lb/>Forum, Center for China and Globalization, Beijing, 22 Mar. 2019, as quoted in H. H. Wang, Escaping Thucydides&apos;s <lb/>Trap: Dialogue with Graham Allison on China-US Relations (Singapore, 2023), pp. 82-3. <lb/>47 G. Allison, &apos;Beyond Trade: The Confrontation between the U.S. and China&apos;, Security Times (Feb. 2020), web. <lb/>archive.org/20240226201603/https://www.the-security-times.com/beyond-trade-confrontation-us-china/. <lb/>48 I. Geiss, &apos;The German Version of Imperialism, 1898-1914: Weltpolitik&apos;, in Schöllgen, Escape into War?, pp. 105-<lb/>120, here p. 117. <lb/>49 M. Howard, &apos;Die Deutsch-britischen Beziehungen im 20. Jahrhundert: eine Haßliebe&apos;, in W. J. Mommsen (ed.), Die <lb/>ungleichen Partner: deutsche-britische Beziehungen im 19. und 20. Jahrhundert (Stuttgart, 1999), pp. 125-30, <lb/>here p. 130; J. C. G. Röhl, &apos;&quot;The Worst of Enemies&quot;: Kaiser Wilhelm II and his Uncle Edward VII&apos;, in Geppert and <lb/>Gerwarth, Wilhelmine Germany and Edwardian Britain, pp. 41-66, here p. 62. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap</note>

            <page>171 <lb/></page>

            <body>This view been superseded, as Katherine C. Epstein has pointed out, by work that <lb/>has shifted away from the rise-and-fall paradigm, which posits &apos;a narrowing of strategic <lb/>focus to Germany&apos;, towards a broader appreciation of Britain&apos;s &apos;continuing dedication <lb/>to global hegemony&apos;, which was bolstered by its power as &apos;underwriter of the global <lb/>economy&apos;. 50 In problematizing the faulty historical assumptions of the Thucydides <lb/>trap and those who espouse it, Epstein cautions that &apos;consumers&apos; of history-such as <lb/>political scientists like Allison as well as the policy-makers that heed their advice-<lb/>should understand if they &apos;are determined to &quot;use&quot; historians&apos; work&apos;, they must keep in <lb/>mind that deploying &apos;inferior historical scholarship is really no better than speculative <lb/>philosophy&apos;. 51 <lb/>In many respects, Allison&apos;s work demonstrates the salience of Epstein&apos;s warning. His <lb/>purpose in foregrounding Britain and Germany in his theory of history is not to better <lb/>understand the complicated prehistory of the First World War but to instrumentalize <lb/>a prepackaged understanding of this history to support his primary thesis, that the <lb/>war followed the &apos;same bleak pattern-and many of the same dynamics-as other <lb/>Thucydidean conflicts over the centuries&apos;. What matters is not the texture of a compli-<lb/>cated set of events but the overarching impression that Britain was &apos;beset by anxieties <lb/>typical of many ruling powers&apos; and &apos;Germany was driven by the ambition and indig-<lb/>nation characteristic of many up-and-comers&apos;. In the end, Allison argues, &apos;Britain had <lb/>no choice but to fight because it feared that a powerful Germany left unchecked across <lb/>the Continent would threaten its existence.&apos; 52 In a nutshell, Allison draws on Kennedy&apos;s <lb/>rendering of the ostensibly dichotomous dynamics of the antagonism paradigm-char-<lb/>acterized, Stafford wrote, by a &apos;strong whiff of inevitability&apos;-for reasonably straight-<lb/>forward, programmatic theoretical reasons that align with his metahistorical analytical <lb/>project and his grim assessment of the present. 53 <lb/>With Allison&apos;s Thucydides trap thesis, the complex and multidimensional questions <lb/>of cooperation, conflict and war in the final three decades of Europe&apos;s long nineteenth <lb/>century have been reduced to a simple binary conflict that might in turn provide a <lb/>series of maxims that underwrite his deeply pessimistic and arguably simplistic struc-<lb/>turalist interpretation of contemporary geopolitics and the risk of war. Absent is any <lb/>sense of the important recent (and not so recent) historiographical shifts away from <lb/>Kennedy&apos;s antagonism paradigm which might problematize this Manichaean world-<lb/>view. Instead, Allison continues to rely heavily on superannuated iterations of historical <lb/>research that overemphasized the centrality of Anglo-German antagonism. In Allison&apos;s <lb/>Thucydides trap theory, Kennedy&apos;s and Fischer&apos;s increasingly superseded readings of <lb/>the First World War have found new life, influencing political decisions regarding con-<lb/>temporary international security and geopolitical conflict. <lb/>That Allison&apos;s view has become politically influential is no exaggeration. In an era of <lb/>geopolitical nervousness, his book has clearly struck a chord, with former US president <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>50 K. C. Epstein, &apos;Scholarship and the Ship of State: Rethinking the Anglo-American Strategic Decline Analogy&apos;, <lb/>International Affairs, 91, 2 (2015), pp. 319-31, here pp. 320, 326, 330. <lb/>51 Ibid., pp. 327-31. <lb/>52 Allison, Destined for War, pp. 57-8. <lb/>53 D. Stafford, Review Article, &apos;A Moral Tale: Anglo-German Relations, 1860-1914&apos;, International History Review, 4, <lb/>2 (1982), pp. 249-63, here p. 251. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>172</page>

			<note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

			<body>Joe Biden declaring Allison to be &apos;one of the keenest observers of international affairs <lb/>around&apos;. 54 Similarly enthusiastic about the Thucydides trap theory have been the <lb/>late Henry Kissinger, former Australian prime ministers Kevin Rudd and Malcolm <lb/>Turnbull, chairman of the World Economic Forum Klaus Schwab, and former secre-<lb/>tary general of the United Nations Ban Ki-Moon. In China, President Xi Jinping and <lb/>Premier Li Keqiang have also explicitly referred to Allison&apos;s Thucydides trap model to <lb/>warn against further military escalation in the Pacific region. 55 <lb/>To be sure, the instrumentalization of the history of Anglo-German relations as a <lb/>geopolitical morality play, stripped of its complexity and attendant historiographical <lb/>caveats, is not restricted to Allison. During the Cold War the antagonism paradigm <lb/>was drawn upon frequently by political scientists who were similarly seeking to explain <lb/>the inevitability of a march to war between contending great powers. As the United <lb/>States and the Soviet Union stared with both trepidation and perverse thanatopolitical <lb/>longing into the abyss of thermonuclear war, political scientists recast the past roles of <lb/>the freedom-loving British and authoritarian Germans as now inhabited by the United <lb/>States and the Soviet Union respectively. The Anglo-German antagonism became less <lb/>history and more trope, an analytical commonplace frequently deployed to explain how <lb/>and why the US-Soviet Cold War could be expected to turn hot. 56 <lb/>Nor is Allison alone in reading the recent rise of China through the lens of Wilhelmine <lb/>Germany. As early as 1997, the neoconservative foreign-policy hawk and future deputy <lb/>US secretary of defence and president of the World Bank Paul Wolfowitz warned <lb/>that like Wilhelmine Germany, China too might well be &apos;a country that felt it had <lb/>been denied its &quot;place in the sun&quot;&apos;. 57 Alastair Johnston cautioned against embracing <lb/>this misleading transtemporal analogy a few years later. 58 More proximately, in 2014 <lb/>Reinhard Wolf anticipated some of Allison&apos;s arguments regarding the similarities be-<lb/>tween China and Wilhelmine Germany. 59 Perhaps most prominently, in 2011 Henry <lb/>Kissinger also anticipated Allison&apos;s argument. 60 In fact in many respects, Allison&apos;s book <lb/>might be understood as a detailed extrapolation of the concerns and methods used <lb/>by Kissinger in his book On China that seeks to answer its epilogic question, &apos;Does his-<lb/>tory repeat itself ?&apos; 61 In his book (which Allison cites approvingly), Kissinger too had <lb/>pointed to the ostensible &apos;zero-sum game&apos; of Anglo-German relations prior to 1914 as <lb/>a potential harbinger of a twenty-first-century Pacific war. Just as in the case of twenty-<lb/>first-century China, he reasoned, with the emergence of a strong, united and globally <lb/>competent Germany in nineteenth-century Europe, the balance of the international <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>54 Wang, Escaping Thucydides&apos;s Trap, pp. xxvi-xxvii. <lb/>55 Ibid., pp. xxvi-xxvii. <lb/>56 H. Gardner, &apos;Averting World War III: Beyond the World War I, World War II Analogies&apos;, SAIS Review, 8, 2 (1988), <lb/>pp. 121-35; S. M. Lynn-Jones, &apos;Détente and Deterrence: Anglo-German Relations, 1911-1914&apos;, International <lb/>Security, 11, 2 (1986), pp. 121-50; G. Schöllgen, &apos;Introduction: The Theme Reflected in Recent German Research&apos;, <lb/>and W. Gutsche, &apos;The Foreign Policy of Imperial Germany and the Outbreak of the War in the Historiography of <lb/>the GDR&apos;, in Schöllgen, Escape into War?, pp. 1-19 (here p. 1), and pp. 41-62 (here p. 57) respectively. <lb/>57 P. Wolfowitz, &apos;Bridging Centuries: Fin de Siècle All Over Again&apos;, National Interest, 47 (1997), pp. 3-8. <lb/>58 A. I. Johnston, &apos;Is China a Status Quo Power?&apos;, International Security, 27, 4 (2003), pp. 5-56. <lb/>59 R. Wolf, &apos;Rising Powers, Status Ambition, and the Need to Reassure: What China Could Learn from Imperial <lb/>Germany&apos;s Failures&apos;, Chinese Journal of International Politics, 7, 2 (2014), pp. 185-219. <lb/>60 H. Kissinger, On China (New York, 2011). <lb/>61 Ibid., p. 514. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap</note>

            <page>173 <lb/></page>

            <body>state system shifted, challenging British naval hegemony. Resultingly, Kissinger argued, <lb/>a &apos;crisis of the system&apos; took shape, one that saw the emergence of a &apos;bipolar system <lb/>with no diplomatic flexibility&apos;. 62 Unlike Allison, however, Kissinger at least viewed this <lb/>transhistorical parallel as &apos;by nature inexact&apos;, rather than as a firm basis for a unifying <lb/>transtemporal theory of realist international relations. 63 <lb/>IV. The &apos;Crowe Memorandum&apos; and Its Legacies <lb/>What of Allison&apos;s evidentiary basis for an enduring Anglo-German antagonism and <lb/>its adherence to his version of Thucydidean realism? As a political scientist, Allison <lb/>does not work closely with the archival materials required to substantiate the claims he <lb/>makes, which he believes Kennedy has already proven. Nonetheless, following Kissinger, <lb/>Allison leans heavily on the famed 1907 memorandum written by Eyre Crowe, a junior <lb/>assistant clerk whose conclusions briefly piqued the interest of some but were reso-<lb/>lutely disputed at the time by more senior Foreign Office figures. 64 For Allison, as for <lb/>Kissinger, this document is the requisite smoking gun that underpins the thesis that <lb/>Britain had no choice but to engage in a war for global hegemony against Germany. 65 <lb/>Written seven years before the First World War, the Crowe memorandum has inex-<lb/>plicably become a talismanic document said to have deeply and irrevocably coloured <lb/>British attitudes towards Germany thereafter. It is worth making clear, however, as <lb/>Richard A. Cosgrove did more than fifty years ago, that historians have overestimated <lb/>the correlation of the Crowe document with the development of British foreign policy <lb/>after 1907. It was, in fact, far more popular as a post-1918 point of reference for those <lb/>seeking to understand the origins of British participation in the First World War than <lb/>as a policy basis for British political and military planners. 66 It should not, Cosgrove <lb/>emphasized, &apos;be interpreted as a guide to pre-war British diplomacy&apos;. 67 <lb/>According to Crowe, there were only two alternatives for the global politics of his <lb/>time: <lb/>Either Germany is definitely aiming at a general political hegemony and maritime ascendency, threatening <lb/>the independence of her neighbours and ultimately the existence of England; or Germany, free from any <lb/>clear-cut ambition, and thinking for the present merely of using her legitimate position and influence as <lb/>one of the leading powers in the council of nations, is seeking to promote her foreign commerce, spread <lb/>the benefits of German culture, extend the scope of her national energies, and create fresh German inter-<lb/>ests all over the world wherever and whenever a peaceful opportunity offers, leaving it to an uncertain fu-<lb/>ture to decide whether the occurrence of great change in the world may not some day assign to Germany <lb/>a larger share of direct political action over regions not now a part of her dominions. <lb/>In either case, however, Germany was a threat to British global supremacy. For the <lb/>anxious hegemon, the gradual and peaceful enhancement of the position of Germany <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>62 Ibid., p. 516. <lb/>63 Ibid., p. 522. <lb/>64 Z. Steiner, &apos;The Last Years of the Old Foreign Office, 1898-1905&apos;, Historical Journal, 6, 1 (1963), pp. 59-90, here <lb/>pp. 76-7. <lb/>65 Allison, Destined for War, pp. 58-61; Kissinger, On China, pp. 518-20. <lb/>66 R. A. Cosgrove, &apos;The Crowe Memorandum and British Foreign Policy, 1907-1914&apos;, South Atlantic Quarterly, 72, <lb/>4 (1973), pp. 527-39, here pp. 530-1. <lb/>67 Ibid., p. 528. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>174</page>

			<note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

            <body>&apos;would obviously constitute as formidable a menace to the rest of the world as would be <lb/>presented by any deliberate conquest of a similar position by &quot;malice aforethought&quot;&apos;. 68 <lb/>Allison&apos;s smoking gun evidence is hardly decisive. For all their colour and de-<lb/>tail, Crowe&apos;s conclusions were disputed by the senior Foreign Office figure Thomas <lb/>Sanderson, who reminded British officials that &apos;Germany is a helpful, though some-<lb/>what exacting friend&apos;, and that &apos;the history of German policy towards this Country is <lb/>not the unchequered record of black deeds which the [Crowe] Memorandum seems <lb/>to portray&apos;. 69 Instead, he reminded British officials, &apos;there have been many occasions <lb/>on which we have worked comfortably in accord with Germany, and not a few cases in <lb/>which her support has been serviceable to us&apos;. 70 <lb/>Sanderson had long been firmly of the opinion that &apos;the conduct of the German <lb/>government has in some material respects been friendly&apos; towards Britain, and that it re-<lb/>mained important for both countries &apos;that we should work cordially together&apos;. For him, <lb/>those in the British Foreign Office (such as Francis Bertie and Louis Mallet) who were <lb/>quick to denounce Germany were simply &apos;lunatics&apos; driving the Germans further into <lb/>the arms of the Russians. 71 The key difficulty for an ascendant Germany was not that <lb/>it was rising, Sanderson argued, for a &apos;great and growing nation cannot be repressed&apos;, <lb/>but that it would &apos;find the British lion in her path&apos; everywhere around the globe. 72 <lb/>Sanderson made clear that Crowe was wrong to present German colonial expansion <lb/>as an expression of &apos;direct and unmistakable hostility to England&apos;, and that the most <lb/>sensible path for British diplomacy was, in the words of Zara Steiner, to ensure that <lb/>&apos;German sensitivity should be respected and her expansion not checked where it did <lb/>not clash with important British interests&apos;. 73 <lb/>Read now, particularly with Sanderson&apos;s critique in mind, the Crowe memorandum <lb/>might best be interpreted as part full-throated expression of British imperial hubris in <lb/>the wake of its humbling of Germany in partnership with the French at the Algeciras <lb/>Conference in early 1906, and part frank admission of the pathological anxiety of a <lb/>global hegemon that considered it an axiom of geopolitics that &apos;the power of a State <lb/>supreme at sea should inspire universal jealousy and fear&apos;. 74 According to Sanderson, <lb/>Britain&apos;s hubris was such that &apos;to a foreigner reading our press, the British Empire must <lb/>appear in the light of some huge giant sprawling over the globe, with gouty fingers <lb/>and toes stretching in every direction, which cannot be approached without eliciting <lb/>a scream&apos;. 75 Crowe, that is, depicted a characteristically British world-view in which <lb/>all of Britain&apos;s global imperial actions, claims and possessions were manifestations of <lb/>the unfolding of a just and balanced international order. As the Weimar-era German <lb/>historian Friedrich Thimme later pointed out, Crowe expressed perfectly the British <lb/>assumption that there was a &apos;natural harmony between British national and general <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>68 Crowe, &apos;Appendix A: Memorandum&apos;, pp. 397-417. <lb/>69 Sanderson, &apos;Appendix B: Memorandum&apos;, pp. 428-9. <lb/>70 Ibid., p. 428. <lb/>71 Steiner, &apos;Last Years&apos;, pp. 76-8. <lb/>72 Sanderson, &apos;Appendix B: Memorandum&apos;, p. 431. <lb/>73 Ibid., pp. 421-2; Steiner, &apos;Last Years&apos;, p. 79. <lb/>74 Crowe, &apos;Appendix A: Memorandum&apos;, p. 402. <lb/>75 Sanderson, &apos;Appendix B: Memorandum&apos;, p. 430. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap</note>

            <page> 175 <lb/></page>

            <body>global interests&apos;. 76 For Crowe, Wilhelmine Germany&apos;s global expansion indicated the <lb/>unique &apos;extortions&apos; of &apos;a professional blackmailer&apos; menacing Britain and other states &apos;by <lb/>the threat of some vague and dreadful consequences&apos; if their designs were thwarted. 77 <lb/>Sanderson, by contrast, at least understood that &apos;if the mere acquisition of territory <lb/>were in itself immoral, I conceive the sins of Germany since 1871 are light in com-<lb/>parison to ours&apos;. 78 <lb/>In some ways, however, the Crowe memorandum was only incidentally interested <lb/>in German affairs, concerning itself primarily with a stout defence of the new Entente <lb/>Cordiale between Britain and France, which was designed to contain Britain&apos;s hitherto <lb/>largest source of frontier friction in its global empire-France. 79 Replicating almost <lb/>perfectly the well-known views of Bertie in the Foreign Office, one of the chief archi-<lb/>tects of the Entente Cordiale, it makes clear that it was in fact France and not Germany <lb/>that was the greatest material threat to British global designs. It is no surprise to see <lb/>then that Crowe&apos;s study of international affairs gave expression to the palpable relief of <lb/>some in the British Foreign Office that incidents like Fashoda would no longer darken <lb/>the horizon now that the iciness of Anglo-French relations that had followed Britain&apos;s <lb/>unilateral annexation of Egypt had thawed. <lb/>With the geopolitical necessity of the Entente Cordiale for Britain&apos;s global imperial <lb/>fortunes established, Crowe&apos;s reflections on Germany took the form of the elucidation <lb/>of a resulting political corollary. Germany was not so much a threat to Britain as it was <lb/>an opportune third party, instrumental for the process of solidifying Anglo-French ac-<lb/>cord. As Thimme argued in 1929, Crowe&apos;s prioritization of the Entente Cordiale im-<lb/>plied a need for unanimity between Britain and France on all questions relating to third <lb/>parties. This determination was aimed &apos;above all against Germany&apos;. Anglo-French mu-<lb/>tual assistance during the first Moroccan crisis was, he argued, clear evidence of that. 80 <lb/>On this point, Sanderson concurred. For Sanderson, it had been the French who had <lb/>created the crisis in North Africa, through their &apos;exaggerated&apos; demands on the Sultan <lb/>of Morocco. The matter came to a head because, he argued, <lb/>The German government and the German nation are extremely sensitive about being ignored or neg-<lb/>lected in the discussion of important questions, and it is not surprising that on this occasion they should <lb/>have been much exasperated and determined on inflicting on France a severe humiliation. <lb/>In doing so, he continued, it was no surprise that Germany also sought to &apos;separate&apos; Britain <lb/>from France and &apos;prevent the [Entente] Agreement from developing into an alliance&apos;. 81 <lb/>Read through the lens of the Crowe memorandum, the Anglo-German &apos;antagonism&apos; <lb/>was a third-order result of Britain&apos;s decision to secure its global empire by cleaving <lb/>to its alliance with its greatest, and most threatening, global imperial rival, namely <lb/>France. Understood in this broader context, the Crowe memorandum cannot be used <lb/>(as Allison and Kissinger have done) as a statement of government policy, but should be <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>76 F. Thimme, &apos;Das Memorandum E. A. Crowes vom 1. Januar 1907. Seine Bedeutung für die Kriegsschuldfrage&apos;, <lb/>Berliner Monatshefte, 7, 8 (Aug. 1929), pp. 732-68, here pp. 757-8. <lb/>77 Crowe, &apos;Appendix A: Memorandum&apos;, pp. 397-419. <lb/>78 Sanderson, &apos;Appendix B: Memorandum&apos;, p. 430. <lb/>79 Steiner, &apos;Last Years&apos;, pp. 76-7. <lb/>80 Thimme, &apos;Das Memorandum E. A. Crowes vom 1. Januar 1907&apos;, pp. 752-7. See also M. P. Fitzpatrick, The Kaiser <lb/>and the Colonies: Monarchy in the Age of Empire (Oxford, 2022), pp. 161-87. <lb/>81 Sanderson, &apos;Appendix B: Memorandum&apos;, p. 420. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>176</page>

			<note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

            <body>seen instead as one side of an ongoing debate within the British Foreign Office about <lb/>relations with Germany, with the other side of the argument offered by Sanderson, <lb/>who, as Charles Hardinge commented at the time, &apos;took up the cudgels&apos; in defence of <lb/>Germany&apos;s cooperation and competition with Britain. 82 That it was the Entente par-<lb/>dessus tout logic of Crowe and Bertie which proved decisive in July 1914 should not lead <lb/>to the conclusion that the matter was settled after 1907. 83 <lb/>Crowe&apos;s memorandum has a long historiography of its own that extends back almost <lb/>a century before Allison came to use it to &apos;prove&apos; Kennedy&apos;s antagonism paradigm. 84 In <lb/>Weimar Germany, Crowe was a byword for a determined and restrictive British policy <lb/>of containment that had deliberately sought to push Germany to the brink of war, with <lb/>Thimme writing scathingly in 1929 of the influence of Crowe&apos;s &apos;sham document&apos; on <lb/>prewar relations. 85 It was, he argued, the &apos;intellectual forebear of the German war guilt <lb/>thesis&apos;. 86 Unsurprisingly, Thimme was also quick to point to Sanderson as corrobor-<lb/>ating the Germans&apos; own (similarly simplistic) suspicions that it was British rather than <lb/>German intractability that had led to the First World War. 87 For his part, the left-liberal <lb/>Hermann Lutz simply denounced Crowe in 1931 as the &apos;evil spirit&apos; that had haunted <lb/>the British Foreign Office. 88 <lb/>After the Second World War and already convinced of Fischer&apos;s thesis of German <lb/>war guilt, Geiss described the Crowe memorandum as &apos;just and fair&apos; and offering a <lb/>&apos;balanced judgement of German intentions&apos;. It provided, he argued, a &apos;rational ex-<lb/>planation for the apparently irrational and bewildering manifestations of German <lb/>Weltpolitik&apos;. For those seeking an explanation of the trajectory of British policy towards <lb/>Germany between 1907 and 1914, Geiss added, &apos;Crowe&apos;s memorandum can be re-<lb/>garded as the key document.&apos; Crowe had convinced British officials, Geiss believed, <lb/>to remain &apos;against a policy of concessions merely to &quot;conciliate&quot; (we would now say <lb/>&quot;appease&quot;) Germany on her road to more power&apos;. Instead, Geiss believed, Crowe was <lb/>right to advocate checking German power to ensure that its rise &apos;did not violate vital <lb/>British interests either directly or indirectly, nor tried to upset the then existing balance <lb/>of power in Europe and the world&apos;-a remit so broad as to offer an almost limitless <lb/>mandate for action. 89 <lb/>Unlike Allison, however, for Christopher Clark, who has also made the link between <lb/>&apos;the political anxieties of the great-power executives&apos; of Britain pre-1914 and the con-<lb/>cerns of the United States regarding &apos;Chinese economic power&apos; today, the lesson of the <lb/>Crowe memorandum is simply that &apos;there was nothing inevitable about the ascendancy <lb/>of Germanophobe attitudes in British foreign policy&apos; and that (perhaps with Sanderson <lb/>in mind) even when they did emerge, &apos;they were not universal&apos;. The future, as he points <lb/>out, &apos;was not foreordained&apos;. To the extent that it existed, the mutual suspicion between <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>82 Steiner, &apos;Last Years&apos;, p. 79. <lb/>83 Thimme, &apos;Das Memorandum E. A. Crowes vom 1. Januar 1907&apos;, pp. 736-7. <lb/>84 J. S. Dunn, The Crowe Memorandum: Sir Eyre Crowe and Foreign Office Perceptions of Germany, 1918-1925 <lb/>(Newcastle, 2013), pp. 1-46. <lb/>85 F. Thimme, &apos;Das &quot;berühmte Schwindeldokument&quot; E. A. Crowes&apos;, Berliner Monatshefte, 7, 9 (Sept. 1929), pp. <lb/>874-9, here p. 879. <lb/>86 Thimme, &apos;Das Memorandum E. A. Crowes vom 1. Januar 1907&apos;, p. 737. <lb/>87 Ibid., p. 735. <lb/>88 H. Lutz, Eyre Crowe: der böse Geist des Foreign Office (Berlin, 1931). <lb/>89 I. Geiss, July 1914: The Outbreak of the First World War. Selected Documents (London, 1967), pp. 28-33. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap</note>

            <page>177 <lb/></page>

			<body>Germany and Britain was not uniquely binary; it was similar to that which had existed <lb/>between Britain and France, or Britain and Russia, at various times and that which was <lb/>a consequence of &apos;the polycentric world of the &quot;great games&quot; in Africa, China, Persia, <lb/>Tibet and Afghanistan&apos;. The ostensibly structuring Anglo-German antagonism was <lb/>simply a situation in which &apos;the target was new but the mechanisms were familiar&apos;. 90 <lb/>It was, however, Geiss&apos;s view rather than Clark&apos;s that trickled across the disciplinary <lb/>divide to Kissinger and thereafter Allison, who have both expressed their agreement <lb/>with Crowe&apos;s judgement that &apos;regardless of German intentions&apos;, increased German <lb/>naval capacity &apos;would be an objective threat to Britain and &quot;incompatible with the <lb/>existence of the British Empire&quot;&apos;. For Kissinger and Allison, Germany&apos;s &apos;formal as-<lb/>surances were meaningless&apos;, or at least had to be treated as meaningless, because ul-<lb/>timately its rise implied &apos;a conscious scheme for hegemony&apos;. Accordingly, Britain was <lb/>&apos;obliged to assume the worst, and act on the basis of its assumptions&apos;. 91 <lb/>Allison and Kissinger&apos;s championing of Crowe&apos;s 1907 analysis is unsurprising given that <lb/>Crowe&apos;s assumptions are identical to those that undergird the Thucydides trap, namely <lb/>that &apos;history shows&apos; that the primary danger to a hegemon like Britain prior to 1914 or <lb/>the United States presently must inevitably stem from the increasing &apos;predominance of <lb/>a neighbouring State at once militarily powerful, economically efficient and ambitious to <lb/>extend its frontiers or spread its influence&apos;. Accordingly, &apos;by applying this general law&apos;, <lb/>Crowe&apos;s memorandum offers contemporary advocates of Thucydidean realism the pre-<lb/>dictive power required to suggest that it might be necessary for the United States, like <lb/>Britain, to take the measures it deems necessary, including war, to halt any &apos;schemes of <lb/>expansion&apos; that might one day bring into question the current geopolitical status quo. 92 <lb/>Despite its very modest historical role in framing the Anglo-German antagonism prior <lb/>to 1914, the Crowe memorandum has now become a byword for the necessity of reso-<lb/>lute realpolitik in the twenty-first century, with hawkish think tanks such as the London-<lb/>based Council on Geostrategy, encouraged by Britain&apos;s triumph in the First World War, <lb/>forging what they explicitly call &apos;a &quot;Crowe Memorandum&quot; for the twenty-first century&apos;, <lb/>which aims at offering a rationale behind present China-directed policies of contain-<lb/>ment in the Pacific and galvanizing what it presents as &apos;the free and open international <lb/>order&apos; against China&apos;s &apos;malign and revisionist pressure&apos;. In their 2021 report, the Anglo-<lb/>German exemplar and the hawkish views of Crowe are positioned squarely as an argu-<lb/>ment for &apos;a dynamic deterrence posture&apos; rather than &apos;accommodation or acquiescence&apos;. <lb/>In this context, the Crowe memorandum and the Anglo-German antagonism are pre-<lb/>sented as a warning from the past. &apos;Not since Wilhelmine Germany in the early twen-<lb/>tieth century&apos;, the think tank asserts with reference to China, &apos;has a revisionist state held <lb/>such relative material power or potential.&apos; Accordingly, a &apos;New Crowe Memo&apos; should be-<lb/>come the basis for &apos;a new geostrategic approach fit for the twenty-first century&apos;. 93 For its <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>90 Clark, Sleepwalkers, pp. 162-7. <lb/>91 Kissinger, On China, p. 519; Allison, Destined for War, p. 59. <lb/>92 Crowe, &apos;Appendix A: Memorandum&apos;, p. 403. Unlike Allison&apos;s broader (and more pessimistic) reading of Crowe, <lb/>Kissinger posits the lesson of the memorandum is that turning minor events into talismanic struggles for he-<lb/>gemony leads only to disaster; see Kissinger, On China, p. 522. <lb/>93 J. Rogers and A. Lanoszka, &apos;A &quot;Crowe Memorandum&quot; for the Twenty-First Century: Preparing for Intensified <lb/>Geopolitical Competition&apos;, Council on Geostrategy Policy Paper, Mar. 2021, pp. 1-24, https://www.geostrategy. <lb/>org.uk/app/uploads/2021/05/Policy-Paper-GPPP01-02032021.pdf, here pp. 4-5. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>178</page>

			<note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

			<body>hawkish authors, the lessons of the Anglo-German relationship and Crowe&apos;s assessment <lb/>of it are unambiguous: &apos;Just as Sir Eyre knew that Imperial Germany&apos;s autocratic mon-<lb/>archy would exploit British equivocation and indecision, contemporary authoritarian <lb/>regimes are little different.&apos; Accordingly, the United States and its allies should &apos;assert red <lb/>lines unflinchingly&apos; as they &apos;put a bit of stick about&apos; in international relations. 94 <lb/>Chinese scholars too are closely examining the salience of the Crowe memorandum <lb/>to Sino-American relations. For Zhengyu Wu, the Crowe memorandum offers a means <lb/>by which the &apos;parallel strategic interests between Great Britain then and the United <lb/>States now&apos; as well as &apos;the basic parallel between the rise of Germany and the rise of <lb/>China&apos; are being represented. 95 In his analysis, Wu zeroes in on Crowe&apos;s description <lb/>of Britain&apos;s status as the world&apos;s largest thalassocratic empire and its self-perception as <lb/>acting in defence of its &apos;political obligations towards the comity of nations&apos; as the &apos;nat-<lb/>ural protector of smaller nations and […] champion of universal free trade&apos;. Against <lb/>this ostensibly heroic British selflessness, Wu continues, Crowe contrasted supposed <lb/>&apos;German pathologies in its foreign policy&apos;, foremost among these being its &apos;single-<lb/>minded pursuit of global ambition&apos;. 96 Tellingly, however, in the end, Wu argues, Crowe <lb/>was not concerned about any actual direct threat to Britain emanating from Germany, <lb/>but rather feared the potential for disruption to the existing Anglocentric global order, <lb/>and the hypothetical question &apos;whether Germany would pose a threat to the balance <lb/>of power&apos;. 97 In the same way, Wu concluded, US fears of an ascendant China are not <lb/>specific and instead &apos;mainly revolve around the potential disequilibrium that a very <lb/>powerful China would produce&apos; in a geopolitical order that reflected and protected US <lb/>interests. The &apos;strategic adjustments&apos; in Britain heralded by the Crowe memorandum, <lb/>he argues, mirror the US &apos;rebalance to Asia since 2011&apos;. 98 Just as the Tirpitz plan was <lb/>conceived not as a way to rival British sea power, but to rob Britain of its free hand <lb/>to intervene at will in Continental Europe, so too US fears regarding China centre <lb/>on the fact that growing Chinese sea power &apos;could greatly reduce America&apos;s ability to <lb/>meddle in East Asian affairs in the future&apos;. 99 Wu also points out that just as France and <lb/>Russia were integral to British attempts to contain Germany, China&apos;s neighbours are <lb/>also currently playing a key role in assisting the United States in containing China. 100 <lb/>According to this reasoning, the current AUKUS agreement emerges, as some have <lb/>suggested, as a modern-day Triple Entente aimed at containing yet another breakout <lb/>power. 101 Historical inaccuracies baked into this faulty analysis aside, given the disas-<lb/>trous outcome of these pre-1914 treaty arrangements, it is surprising to see Crowe, his <lb/>memorandum and the dynamics of the Anglo-German antagonism, as understood <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>94 Ibid., p. 18. <lb/>95 Zhengyu Wu, &apos;The Crowe Memorandum, the Rebalance to Asia, and Sino-US Relations&apos;, Journal of Strategic <lb/>Studies, 39, 3 (2016), pp. 389-416, here p. 392. <lb/>96 Ibid., pp. 393-4. <lb/>97 Ibid., p. 396. <lb/>98 Ibid., pp. 399-400. <lb/>99 Ibid., pp. 404-5. <lb/>100 Ibid., pp. 407-8. <lb/>101 J. Hemmings, &apos;Should the Quad Become a Formal Alliance?&apos;, Journal of Indo-Pacific Affairs (Mar./Apr. 2022), pp. <lb/>65-77. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A Farewell to the Thucydides Trap</note>

            <page>179 <lb/></page>

			<body>by contemporary political scientists, positioned as an empirical basis for an efficacious <lb/>theory of the present. <lb/>V. Escaping the International Relations Trap <lb/>If the uses and abuses of the historiography of Anglo-German relations by inter-<lb/>national relations and security studies scholars such as Allison remain a source of grave <lb/>concern, perhaps this is not entirely their fault. German historians have been slow to <lb/>communicate outside their discipline that they have moved on from Kennedy&apos;s antag-<lb/>onism paradigm. It is worth considering what kinds of international relations theories <lb/>might be enabled if historians made it clearer to their political scientist colleagues that <lb/>the cause of the First World War was not, as many continue to presume, a decades-long <lb/>struggle to decide the binary question of whether Germany or Britain would emerge as <lb/>the global hegemon of the twentieth century. <lb/>As Reinhard Wolf, like a large number of other historians, has argued, &apos;World War <lb/>I hardly fits the notion of a conflict chiefly motivated by the rising power&apos;s desire to <lb/>defeat the reigning hegemon.&apos; 102 Yet, courtesy of the use of superannuated histories <lb/>of Anglo-German relations by contemporary theorists of international relations, the <lb/>antagonism paradigm continues to cast a shadow over current geopolitical realities. <lb/>The United States and China, Allison believes, are acting as antagonists in the Anglo-<lb/>German model &apos;right on script, almost as if they were competing to see which could <lb/>better exemplify the characteristics of the rising power on the one hand, and the ruling <lb/>power on the other&apos;. 103 World leaders, including US and Chinese presidents, are lis-<lb/>tening carefully to his reading of the past. <lb/>Correctly understanding the past, Allison believes, offers a chance to foretell the <lb/>future. To this end, Allison argues, it is perhaps time for a &apos;White House Council of <lb/>Historical Advisers&apos;, who might help the US president &apos;clarify the geopolitical history <lb/>and the factors that lead to the challenges and choices that the president faces today&apos;. 104 <lb/>What might such an advisory board, the haruspices of global history, tell the presi-<lb/>dent of the United States about the attempts to establish structural, trans-temporal <lb/>links between Anglo-German and Sino-American relations? Perhaps it might begin by <lb/>warning not only against such long-run theories of historical dynamics but also against <lb/>building a simplistic and high stakes theory of the prospects for great-power warfare <lb/>in the present based on a historiography indebted to a reading of German history that <lb/>has been superseded. Hopefully, the research presented in this Special Issue, along with <lb/>other research currently being conducted, will contribute to building a complex and <lb/>complicated history shorn of any teleological foreclosure of the future. <lb/></body>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Prefacing a series of articles in the Special Issue examining the imperial and colonial dimensions of Anglo-<lb/>German relations prior to and during the First World War, this article examines how outdated understandings <lb/></front>

            <listBibl>102 Wolf, &apos;Rising Powers&apos;, p. 193. <lb/>103 J. Mecklin, &apos;Interview with Graham Allison: Are the United States and China Charging into Thucydides&apos;s Trap?&apos;, <lb/>Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 78, 2 (2022), pp. 53-8, here p. 53. <lb/>104 Ibid., pp. 57-8. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>180</page>

			<note place="headnote">Matthew P. Fitzpatrick <lb/></note>

			<front>of Anglo-German relations are currently influencing political scientists who are seeking a historical basis for <lb/>their theoretical models of twenty-first-century geopolitics. It looks at how Paul Kennedy&apos;s understanding <lb/>of an ostensible Anglo-German antagonism has made its way into Graham Allison&apos;s recent theory of the <lb/>&apos;Thucydides trap&apos; and argues that improving the quality of contemporary international relations might well <lb/>rely upon improving our communication of paradigm changes in German historiography. <lb/>Flinders University, Australia <lb/>matthew.fitzpatrick@flinders.edu.au <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/gh/article/43/2/161/8174931 by Max-Planck Society user on 17 September 2025 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>