<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" space="preserve">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Teresa</forename>
          <surname>Weber</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cb">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-07-30T15:50:00.000Z">30.7.2025 17:50:00</date>
        <title>Grobid document segmentation corrected</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Austrian Law Journal</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.25364/01.11:2024.1.5</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Teresa Weber. (2024). KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis. Austrian Law Journal, 11(1), 101-116. DOI: 10.25364/01.11:2024.1.5</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="grobid">
        <label>https://grobid.readthedocs.io/</label>
      </application>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor">
        <label>https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor</label>
      </application>
      <application version="1.0" ident="model">
        <label>lfoppiano/grobid:latest-develop</label>
        <desc>https://hub.docker.com/layers/lfoppiano/grobid/latest-develop/images/sha256-735fa2c8facb6f95adef5bf344f7223c2e20aadc9c048f624b83b19d3fbef07b</desc>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-07-13">
      <desc>Extracted 2025-07-13</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-07-31T12:59:08.998Z" status="draft" who="#cb">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>ISSN: 2409-6911 <lb/>(CC-BY)4.0license <lb/>www.austrian-law-jounal.at <lb/>DOI: 10.25364/01.11:2024.1.5. <lb/>KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of <lb/>the Climate Crisis <lb/>Teresa Weber * , Vienna <lb/>Abstract: The essay discusses the recent KlimaSeniorinnen judgement of the European Court <lb/>of Human Rights. Selected issues such as standing for associations are elaborated on in more <lb/>detail. <lb/>Abstract: Der Beitrag bespricht die KlimaSeniorinnen Entscheidung des EGMR vom April 2024. <lb/>Ausgewählte Fragestellungen dazu, wie etwa rund um die Beschwerdberechtigung von <lb/>Vereinigungen, werden näher diskutiert. <lb/>Keywords: Climate litigation; Strategic Litigation; Access to Justice; Standing for NGOs; locus <lb/>standi; Legal Opportunity Structures. <lb/></front>

        <toc>Inhalt <lb/>I. Introduction and Scope of the Essay ................................................................................ 101 <lb/>II. Summary of Main Points of the Judgement.................................................................... 102 <lb/>III. Some Thoughts on the Judgement ................................................................................. 107 <lb/>A. Strategic Litigation, Strategic Judgement? ................................................................... 107 <lb/>B. Standing for Associations ............................................................................................. 110 <lb/>C. The Literal Costs of KlimaSeniorinnen -Justice is Not Accessible For All ................. 113 <lb/>IV. Changing Legal Opportunity Structures; Opportunities Yet to be Seized ................... 115 <lb/></toc>

        <front>* Teresa Weber is Professor of Public Law at SFU Vienna. Mara Mittelberger, LL.B. offered invaluable <lb/>support in conducting the research for this essay. <lb/></front>

        <page>101</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>I. Introduction and Scope of the Essay <lb/>The KlimaSeniorinnen case 1 has been widely and prominently discussed from the outset <lb/>of the proceedings. 2 Each stage of the litigation efforts brought forward a large number <lb/>of commentators and critics. 3 Unsurprisingly, the long-awaited judgement of the ECtHR, <lb/>delivered on 9 April 2024, has already garnered a lot of attention, be it in the general <lb/>media 4 or through academic outlets. 5 <lb/>In the following essay, I will briefly summarize the judgement and then focus on a few <lb/>issues that seem worth highlighting and to which I feel I can add substantial thoughts. <lb/>These include considerations on aspects of strategic litigation in this case, the much-<lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
        <listBibl>1 ECtHR 09.04.2024, Verein KlimaSeniorinnen Schweiz / Switzerland, application no 53600/20 (references to <lb/>paragraphs without other specifications refer to this decision). The ECtHR issued its decisions on two other <lb/>climate cases on the same day: ECtHR 09.04.2024, Duarte Agostinho and Others / Portugal and 32 others, <lb/>application no 39371/20 ("case of the Portugese children", declared inadmissible due to lack of jurisdiction and <lb/>lack of exhaustion of remedies relating to Portugal) and ECtHR 09.04.2024, Carême / France, application no <lb/>7189/21 ("case of the French Mayor", declared inadmissible due to lack of victim status). These decisions are not <lb/>discussed here. For a comparative discussion see Pedersen, Climate Change and the ECHR: The Results Are In, <lb/>EJIL:Talk!, 11.04.2024, https://www.ejiltalk.org/climate-change-and-the-echr-the-results-are-in/. This and all <lb/>other weblinks were accessed on 31.07.2024. <lb/>2 To name only a few examples: Bähr/Brunner/Casper/Lustig, KlimaSeniorinnen: lessons from the Swiss senior <lb/>women's case for future climate litigation, Journal of Human Rights and the Environment, 9:2 (2018) 194 ff; Niska, <lb/>Climate Change Litigation and the European Court of Human Rights -A Strategic Next Step?, Journal of World <lb/>Energy Law and Business 13 (2020) 331 ff; Keller/Bornemann, New Climate Activism between Politics and Law: <lb/>Analyzing the Strategy of the KlimaSeniorinnen Schweiz, Politics and Governance 9:2 (2021) 124 ff. <lb/>3 Cf Schmid, Victim Status before the ECtHR in Cases of Alleged Omissions: The Swiss Climate Case, EJIL:Talk!, <lb/>30.04.2022, https://www.ejiltalk.org/victim-status-before-the-ecthr-in-cases-of-alleged-omissions-the-swiss-<lb/>climate-case/.; Arling/Taghavi, KlimaSeniorinnen v. Switzerland -A New Era for Climate Change Protection or <lb/>Proceeding with the Status Quo?, EJIL:Talk!, 06.04.2023, https://www.ejiltalk.org/klimaseniorinnen-v-<lb/>switzerland-a-new-era-for-climate-change-protection-or-proceeding-with-the-status-quo/; Grosz, Klimaschutz <lb/>vor Schweizer Gerichten, Swiss Review of International and European Law 33 (2023) 351 ff. <lb/>4 For Austria: Somek, Grundrecht kraft Mitlaufens mit dem Zeitgeist, Die Presse, 15.04.2024; Pflügl, Heimische <lb/>Nachbeben des Klimaurteils, Der Standard 2024, 11.04.2024; Kary, Klimaklagen: Muss jetzt auch Österreich <lb/>zittern?, Die Presse, 06.06.2024; Ennöckl, Ein kleiner Klimaprotest mit großer Wirkung, Die Presse, 27.05.2024. <lb/>5 <lb/>Arntz/Krommendijk, <lb/>Historic <lb/>and <lb/>Unprecedented, <lb/>Verfassungsblog, <lb/>09.04.2024, <lb/>https://verfassungsblog.de/historic-and-unprecedented/ and the other contributions (currently -31.07.2024 -<lb/>17 contributions) under the Verfassungsblog debate "The Transformation of European Climate Litigation", all <lb/>available <lb/>under <lb/>https://verfassungsblog.de/category/debates/the-transformation-of-european-climate-<lb/>litigation/; Auner, Recht auf effektive Maßnahmen zur Eindämmung des Klimawandels <lb/>(Entscheidungsanmerkung), Newsletter Menschenrechte (2024) 123 ff; Bella, Klimaklagen: EGMR stimmt <lb/>Völkerrechtsblog <lb/>zu, <lb/>Völkerrechtsblog, <lb/>06.05.2024, <lb/>https://voelkerrechtsblog.org/klimaklagen/; <lb/>Ennöckl/Handig/Polzer/Rathmayer/Vouk, Klimaseniorinnen erkämpfen Recht auf Klimaschutz vor dem EGMR, <lb/>Österreichische Jurist:innenzeitung 2024, 10 ff; Hollaus, Das Urteil des EGMR im Fall KlimaSeniorinnen und seine <lb/>Implikationen für den europäischen Grundrechtsschutz, Juristische Blätter (2024) 485 ff; Hofer, Klimaschutz als <lb/>Grundrecht: EGMR erkennt positive Klimaschutzpflichten der Vertragsstaaten an, Recht der Umwelt (2024) 136 <lb/>ff; ); Eschenhagen, Anmerkung zum EGMR-Urteil "Verein KlimaSeniorinnen Schweiz and Others v. Switzerland", <lb/>Klimarecht 2024, 147 ff; Fremuth, Klimawandel vor dem EGMR und die Grenzen der Menschenrechtskonvention <lb/>Zugleich Besprechung von EGMR Urt. v. 9.4.2024, Europäische Zeitschrift für Wirtschaftsrecht (2024) 697 ff; <lb/>Payandeh, Völkerrecht: Konventionsrechtliche Implikationen des Klimawandels -Beschwerdebefugnis von <lb/>Umweltverbänden und Umfang und Inhalt der staatlichen Schutzpflicht, Juristische Schulung (2024) 896 ff. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>102</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>discussed issue of standing for associations, and some remarks on the costs of the <lb/>proceedings. This selection is not meant to imply that other parts of the judgement might <lb/>be less important or worthy of discussion. 6 <lb/>II. Summary of Main Points of the Judgement <lb/>The judgement in KlimaSeniorinnen originated in applications of the Verein <lb/>KlimaSeniorinnen Schweiz (the association) and four women born between 1931 and <lb/>1942 (applicants 2 to 5), all of which are members of the association 7 and complained of <lb/>severe health problems during climate-change-induced heat waves. 8 Applications to the <lb/>ECtHR were lodged in November 2020, 9 after requests to the national Swiss authorities to <lb/>take necessary measures to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and comply with the Paris <lb/>agreements' targets and the ensuing proceedings before the Swiss Federal Administrative <lb/>Court and the Swiss Federal Supreme Court were unsuccessful, as the applications were <lb/>considered inadmissible. 10 In April 2022, the case was transferred to the jurisdiction of <lb/>the Grand Chamber, 11 together with two other pending climate cases. 12 A large number <lb/>of written third party comments were received, 13 and a hearing took place on 29 March <lb/>2023. 14 <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
        <listBibl>6 For a broader perspective on human rights and climate litigation cf Varvastian, The Advent of International <lb/>Human Rights Law in Climate Change Litigation, Wisconsin International Law Journal 38:2 (2021) 369 ff; <lb/>Vanhala/Hilson, Climate Change Litigation: Symposium Introduction, Law &amp; Policy 35:3 (2012) 141 ff. For the <lb/>Austrian Perspective Ennöckl, Klimaklagen -Strukturen gerichtler Kontrolle im Klimaschutzrecht (Teil II), Recht <lb/>der Umwelt (2022) 184 ff; Fitz, Klimaklagen in Ennöckl (Hg) Handbuch Klimaschutzrecht (2023) 517 ff (534 ff); <lb/>combining Austrian and Swiss experiences: Prantl, Unsichere Zeiten für Klimaklagen? Perspektiven aus <lb/>Österreich und der Schweiz, Nachhaltigkeitsrecht (2023) 451 ff. <lb/>7 Para 1. <lb/>8 Cf para 12 ff. <lb/>9 Para 1. <lb/>10 Cf para 22 ff. For a summary and analysis cf Niska, Climate Change Litigation and the European Court of Human <lb/>Rights -A Strategic Next Step?, Journal of World Energy Law and Business 13 (2020) 331 (337 f). <lb/>11 Para 4. <lb/>12 Para 5. ECtHR 09.04.2024, Duarte Agostinho and Others / Portugal and 32 others, application no 39371/20; <lb/>ECtHR 09.04.2024, Carême / France, application no 7189/21. <lb/>13 Para 6 ff. This includes eight intervening Governments and more than 15 other third party interveners, such as <lb/>the UN High Commissioner for Human Rights, the International Commission of Jurists, the Sabin Center for <lb/>Climate Change Law, Greenpeace Germany and Oxfam. <lb/>14 Para 8 f. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>103</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>The major part of the judgement deals with the alleged violations of Articles 2 and 8 <lb/>ECHR. 15 In this part of the judgement, the Court frames its legal assessment with <lb/>preliminary remarks and general considerations relating to climate-change cases. 16 Here, <lb/>the court prominently states that "climate change is one of the most pressing issues of <lb/>our time" 17 and goes on to discuss, inter alia, the delicate task of ensuring compliance with <lb/>human rights obligations as an international court that has to be respectful of the <lb/>democratic legitimation of national governments and parliaments. 18 The Court further <lb/>highlights the difficulties of attributing greenhouse gas emissions, the subsequent change <lb/>in climate and its consequences to specific sources 19 and the resulting necessity of <lb/>polycentric measures to combat climate change. 20 Connected to this, the Court also <lb/>elaborates on the importance of intergenerational burden-sharing. 21 All this serves the <lb/>Court to establish the need to depart from its existing environmental case-law, in order <lb/>to take into account the specificities of climate change and climate-change related cases. 22 <lb/>The Court then goes on to describe the effects of climate change on the enjoyment of <lb/>Convention rights broadly, relying heavily on the summaries of scientific evidence <lb/>prepared by the IPCC. 23 It thus comes to the preliminary conclusion that climate change <lb/>"poses a serious current and future threat to the enjoyment of human rights guaranteed <lb/>under the Convention, that States are aware of it and capable of taking measures to <lb/>effectively address it, that the relevant risks are projected to be lower if the rise in <lb/>temperature is limited to 1.5°C above pre-industrial levels and if action is taken urgently, <lb/>and that current global mitigation efforts are not sufficient to meet the latter target" 24 . <lb/>Detailing the legitimate scope of its assessment, the Court then stresses that the ECHR <lb/>does not guarantee a right to a healthy environment, but environmental deterioration <lb/>may have a harmful effect on the enjoyment of the rights guaranteed by the Convention <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>15 Para 296 to 576. <lb/>16 Para 410 ff and para 423 ff respectively. <lb/>17 Para 410. <lb/>18 Para 412; see also para 449 f. <lb/>19 Para 416 ff. See also the considerations on causation and proof at para 424 ff and the discussion of the issue <lb/>of the proportion of State responsibility at para 441 ff. <lb/>20 Para 419. <lb/>21 Para 420. <lb/>22 Para 422. <lb/>23 Para 431 ff. <lb/>24 Para 436. <lb/></listBibl>


        <page>104</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>(first and foremost: Article 8) and thus be relevant from the Convention's point of view. 25 <lb/>As the final general issue, the Court reiterates the principles regarding the interpretation <lb/>of the Convention as an international treaty established in its case-law. 26 Here, the Court <lb/>stresses that the Convention "should be interpreted, as far as possible, in harmony with <lb/>other rules of international law " 27 . <lb/>After these preliminary remarks, the Court assesses the admissibility of the applications <lb/>by connecting elaborations on the victim status of the applicants with the discussion of <lb/>the applicability of Articles 2 and 8 ECHR. 28 At the outset, the Court stresses that the <lb/>concept of victim (Article 34 ECHR) "must also be interpreted in an evolutive manner in <lb/>the light of conditions in contemporary society" 29 and distinguishes categories of direct <lb/>victims, indirect victims and potential victims. 30 The Court also differentiates between <lb/>victim status and locus standi, the latter in principle relating to the question of <lb/>representation of victims before the Court. 31 Faced with the difficult task of delineating <lb/>the circle of victims in a way that makes the impact of climate-change on Convention rights <lb/>actionable but does not open up the Convention for an actio popularis, the Court finds <lb/>that the concept of "potential victims" is too broad and thus not suitable in climate-change <lb/>related cases. 32 Instead, the Court establishes a relatively new test of level and severity of <lb/>the risk of adverse consequences and a pressing need to ensure the applicant's individual <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
        <listBibl>5 Para 445 ff. <lb/>26 Para 452 ff. <lb/>27 Para 455, citing ECtHR 11.05.2021, Caamaño Valle / Spain, application no 43563/17, para 53 f. <lb/>28 Para 458 ff. <lb/>29 Para 461 and 482. Here, the Court cites ECtHR 27.04.2004, Gorraiz Lizarraga / Spain, application no 62543/00, <lb/>para 38: "Admittedly, the applicants were not parties to the impugned proceedings in their own name, but <lb/>through the intermediary of the association which they had set up with a view to defending their interests. <lb/>However, like the other provisions of the Convention, the term "victim" in Article 34 must also be interpreted in <lb/>an evolutive manner in the light of conditions in contemporary society. And indeed, in modern-day societies, <lb/>when citizens are confronted with particularly complex administrative decisions, recourse to collective bodies <lb/>such as associations is one of the accessible means, sometimes the only means, available to them whereby they <lb/>can defend their particular interests effectively. Moreover, the standing of associations to bring legal proceedings <lb/>in defence of their members' interests is recognised by the legislation of most European countries. That is <lb/>precisely the situation that obtained in the present case. The Court cannot disregard that fact when interpreting <lb/>the concept of "victim". Any other, excessively formalistic, interpretation of that concept would make protection <lb/>of the rights guaranteed by the Convention ineffectual and illusory." The Court also references ECtHR 07.12.2021, <lb/>Yusufeli İlçesini Güzelleştirme Yaşatma Kültür Varlıklarını Koruma Derneği / Turkey, application no 37857/14, <lb/>para 39. <lb/>30 Para 463, 465 ff. <lb/>31 Para 464 (citing ECtHR 17.07.2014, Centre for Legal Resources on behalf of Valentin Câmpeanu / Romania, <lb/>application no 47848/08, para 102 f) and para 477. <lb/>32 Para 484 f. 2<lb/></listBibl>

        <page>105</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>protection. 33 The individual applicants in the case at hand, however, failed to meet this <lb/>criteria. 34 <lb/>The Court then goes on to elaborate on assessment criteria for the standing of <lb/>associations, 35 highlighting the important role associations and other interest groups play <lb/>in a complex society faced with issues of intergenerational burden-sharing. 36 The role of <lb/>these associations is also recognized in international instruments, most prominently the <lb/>Aarhus Convention, which the Court discusses in relative detail, also taking into account <lb/>the relevant domestic practice and the practice of the EU. 37 This leads the Court to <lb/>conclude that "the special feature of climate change as a common concern of humankind <lb/>and the necessity of promoting intergenerational burden-sharing in this context […] speak <lb/>in favour of recognising the standing of associations before the Court in climate-change <lb/>cases" 38 . This locus standi is independent of the victim status of an association's <lb/>members. 39 In order to exclude the possibility of actio popularis, the Court then finds it <lb/>necessary to devise a test for standing of associations, which it develops by taking into <lb/>account the principles of the Aarhus Convention. 40 This test of locus standi is met by an <lb/>association that is: "(a) lawfully established in the jurisdiction concerned or have standing <lb/>to act there; (b) able to demonstrate that it pursues a dedicated purpose in accordance <lb/>with its statutory objectives in the defence of the human rights of its members or other <lb/>affected individuals within the jurisdiction concerned, whether limited to or including <lb/>collective action for the protection of those rights against the threats arising from climate <lb/>change; and (c) able to demonstrate that it can be regarded as genuinely qualified and <lb/>representative to act on behalf of members or other affected individuals within the <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
        <listBibl>33 Para 486 ff. As for the relationship of these new criteria to the relatively established criteria to test whether <lb/>Article 8 is applicable in environmental cases (actual interference or serious risk) see para 520. <lb/>34 Para 533, 536. <lb/>35 Para 489 ff. <lb/>36 Confirmed also in para 497 f, with specific focus on climate change litigation. <lb/>37 Para 490 ff. <lb/>38 Para 499. <lb/>39 Para 502, but see 503: "In the event of existing limitations regarding the standing before the domestic courts <lb/>of associations meeting the above Convention requirements, the Court may also, in the interests of the proper <lb/>administration of justice, take into account whether, and to what extent, its individual members or other affected <lb/>individuals may have enjoyed access to a court in the same or related domestic proceedings." <lb/>40 Para 501. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>106</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>jurisdiction who are subject to specific threats or adverse effects of climate change on <lb/>their lives, health or well-being as protected under the Convention" 41 . <lb/>Having laid out these criteria, the Court goes on to assess the applicability of Articles 2 <lb/>and 8 ECHR. Regarding Article 2, the Court reiterates that this provision is applicable only <lb/>in cases of real and imminent risks to life, 42 which according to the Court is not the case <lb/>in view of the individual applicants. 43 Regarding the association, the Court does not make <lb/>a final decision on whether it meets these conditions, but chooses to examine only Article <lb/>8 in detail. 44 Regarding the applicability of Article 8, the Court holds that "Article 8 must be <lb/>seen as encompassing a right for individuals to effective protection by the State <lb/>authorities from serious adverse effects of climate change on their life, health, well-being <lb/>and quality of life." 45 The Court then refers back to the criteria established for locus standi <lb/>of associations, which are met by the applicant association. 46 The individual applicants do <lb/>not fulfil the criteria for victim status with regard to Article 8, according to the Court. 47 <lb/>Having established the admissibility of the association's application (and the <lb/>inadmissibility of the individual applications), the Court goes on to elaborate on the merits <lb/>of the case regarding Article 8. 48 Here, the Court highlights the existing margin of <lb/>appreciation, but also emphasizes the procedural safeguards established in its case-law, <lb/>such as States having to rely on appropriate scientific evidence made available to the <lb/>public. 49 The Court then goes on to find that "climate protection should carry considerable <lb/>weight in the weighing-up of any competing considerations", 50 and becomes even more <lb/>precise by stating that Article 8 in principle demands Contracting States to reach net <lb/>neutrality within the next three decades. 51 This principle is accompanied by specific <lb/>procedural safeguards, such as the duty to adopt general measures specifying a timeline <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>41 Para 502. <lb/>42 Para 513. <lb/>43 Para 533, 536. <lb/>44 Para 536. <lb/>45 Para 519. <lb/>46 Para 521 ff. <lb/>47 Para 527 ff. <lb/>48 Para 538. <lb/>49 Para 539 ff. <lb/>50 Para 542. <lb/>51 Para 548. <lb/></listBibl>


        <page>107</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>to reach this target as well as intermediate reduction targets and pathways. 52 According <lb/>to the Court, Switzerland failed to meet these criteria and thus violated Article 8. 53 <lb/>The judgement then goes on to deal with the alleged violation of Article 6, again first <lb/>reiterating the principles established in previous case-law 54 and then elaborating on <lb/>necessary modifications in the climate change context. 55 These modifications include a <lb/>more distinct approach to the question of whether the object of proceedings can be <lb/>considered directly decisive for the rights relied on, taking into account the specific role <lb/>of associations within climate litigation. 56 <lb/>The Court highlights that in the national proceedings, the applicants relied on the right to <lb/>life (and physical integrity), which is protected under the Swiss Constitution and qualified <lb/>as "civil in nature for the purpose of the first limb of the test for the applicability of Article <lb/>6" 57 . The Court then finds that the parts of the application that relate to the effective <lb/>implementation of mitigation measures provided for in existing Swiss law in principle fall <lb/>under Article 6. 58 Insofar, the Court found the association's application to be admissible <lb/>and rejected the individual applications. 59 After having conducted a proportionality test, <lb/>the Court found there to be a violation of Article 6. 60 <lb/>III. Some Thoughts on the Judgement <lb/>A. Strategic Litigation, Strategic Judgement? <lb/>The KlimaSeniorinnen judgement did not just "happen". To reach the ECtHR was the <lb/>culmination point of litigation efforts that began in 2016 61 and were initiated by <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
		<listBibl>52 Para 550. <lb/>53 Para 572 ff. <lb/>54 Para 594 ff. <lb/>55 Para 608 ff. <lb/>56 Para 613 f, 622. <lb/>57 Para 617. <lb/>58 Para 616. The parts of the application that concern policy decisions subject to the relevant democratic <lb/>processes do not fall under Article 6 ECHR; ibid. <lb/>59 Para 623 ff. <lb/>60 Para 640. <lb/>61 Cf para 22 ff. <lb/></listBibl>


        <page>108</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>Greenpeace Switzerland after the success of Urgenda 62 in the Netherlands. 63 Year-long <lb/>proceedings are not uncommon within the ECHR-system, given that exhaustion of <lb/>remedies is necessary to fulfil the admissibility criteria. Compared to many other <lb/>proceedings in Strasbourg, the judgement was handed down rather speedily in <lb/>KlimaSeniorinnen. 64 What is special about this case is, however, that KlimaSeniorinnen as <lb/>the applicant association has as one of its statutory goals to take legal action in the <lb/>interests of its members with regards to the effect of climate change 65 and was founded <lb/>already with a litigation strategy (focussing on the human rights of senior women) in <lb/>mind. 66 <lb/>Whilst the involvement of the KlimaSeniorinnen association did not seem decisive for the <lb/>outcome of the court proceedings in front of the Swiss Courts, it was the focal point and <lb/>success factor for the application to the ECtHR. This shows how challenging yet important <lb/>the involvement of collective actors in litigation is for legal mobilization. 67 The involvement <lb/>of such collective actors (such as associations and NGOs) is qualified as one of the key <lb/>elements of strategic litigation by some. 68 From this perspective, the KlimaSeniorinnen <lb/>case can be qualified as a prime example of strategic litigation. Whether it is to be qualified <lb/>as successful strategic litigation depends on the observer's point of view: <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
        <listBibl>62 Hoge Raad (Supreme Court of the Netherlands) 20.12.2019, 19/00135, ECLI:NL:HR:2019:2007 (Urgenda). For <lb/>an analysis of the judgement see for instance Pedersen, The networks of human rights and climate change: The <lb/>State of the Netherlands v Stichting Urgenda, Supreme Court of the Netherlands, 20 December 2019 (19/00135), <lb/>Environmental Law Review 22:3 (2020) 227 ff. <lb/>63 Bähr/Brunner/Casper/Lustig, KlimaSeniorinnen: lessons from the Swiss senior women's case for future climate <lb/>litigation, Journal of Human Rights and the Environment, 9:2 (2018) 194 (201). For a comparison of Urgenda and <lb/>KlimaSeniorinnen within the relevant context for instance Schupisser, Judging Climate Change: A Comparative <lb/>Legal and Political Analysis of the KlimaSeniorinnen Schweiz and the Urgenda Cases, Global Europe -Basel Papers <lb/>on Europe in a Global Perspective 124 (2023) 43 ff. <lb/>64 The ECtHR applies a priority policy, cf https://www.echr.coe.int/documents/d/echr/priority_policy_ENG . <lb/>65 Cf para 10. <lb/>66 Bähr/Brunner/Casper/Lustig, KlimaSeniorinnen: lessons from the Swiss senior women's case for future climate <lb/>litigation, Journal of Human Rights and the Environment, 9:2 (2018) 194 (202). <lb/>67 For the concept of legal mobilization: Zeman, Legal mobilization: The neglected role of the law in the political <lb/>system, American Political Science Review 77:3 (1983) 690 ff, esp 700: "(t)he law is mobilized when a desire or a <lb/>want is translated into a demand as an assertion of one's rights". Cf McCann, Litigation and Legal Mobilization, <lb/>in Caldeira et al (eds) The Oxford Handbook of Law and Politics (2008) Oxford: Oxford University Press, 523 ff-<lb/>540 (523 ff). <lb/>68 Hahn, Strategische Prozessführung. Ein Beitrag zur Begriffsklärung, Zeitschrift für Rechtssoziologie 39:1 (2019) <lb/>5 ff; Weber, Zum Begriff der Strategischen Prozessführung, in Weber (Hg) Strategische Prozessführung in <lb/>Österreich (2024) 11 (17 f); cf Guerrero, Strategische Prozessführung -eine Annäherung, Zeitschrift für <lb/>Menschen rechte 2020, 26 (38). <lb/></listBibl>

        <!-- bis hierher bearbeitet -->

		<page>109</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>First, one can look at the judgement itself. On the one hand, looking at the outcome for <lb/>the individual applicants and the way the Court detailed the conditions of victim status, <lb/>not everyone might view this judgement as a success. On the other hand, the novel <lb/>approach to locus standi of associations is definitively a win from the perspective of <lb/>associations active in the field of climate litigation. Given the objective of the applications, <lb/>which aimed at remedying the impact of climate change on the enjoyment of human <lb/>rights through both individual and collective means, the judgement can be qualified as a <lb/>partial "win". <lb/>Second, and much harder, one can try to evaluate the impact the judgement will have for <lb/>advancing climate protection. Here, it is definitively noteworthy that the Court used the <lb/>opportunities it had to highlight the imminent danger climate change holds for the <lb/>enjoyment and protection of human rights. The Court did not shy away from making quite <lb/>general statements with potentially far-reaching consequences, such as regarding the <lb/>weighing of climate protection interests and States' obligation to mitigate greenhouse gas <lb/>emissions and strive for net neutrality. 69 Looking at the case-law of the Court more <lb/>broadly, the elaboration of procedural safeguards based on which the Court will evaluate <lb/>States' compliance with the Convention guarantees was to be expected and is in line with <lb/>the general trend towards procedural control. 70 What is surprising, however, is the detail <lb/>in which the Court lays down these procedural safeguards. Ultimately, however, the <lb/>impact all these requirements will have on climate protection "on the ground" depends <lb/>on the willingness of States 71 to comply with them swiftly. 72 Here, reference to the partly <lb/>concurring, partly dissenting opinion of Judge Eicke is due: He appears to be very sceptic <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
		<listBibl>69 As to the preciseness of this obligation see Hilson/Geden, Climate or carbon neutrality? Which one must states <lb/>aim for under Article 8 ECHR?, EJIL:Talk!, 29.04.2024, https://www.ejiltalk.org/climate-or-carbon-neutrality-<lb/>which-one-must-states-aim-for-under-article-8-echr/. <lb/>70 Cf Brems, The ‚Logics' of Procedural-Type Review by the European Court of Human Right, in: Gerards / Brems <lb/>(editors) Procedural Review in European Fundamental Rights Cases. Cambrigde, Cambridge University Press <lb/>(2017) 17 (17 ff); Pavlidis, Integrierung einer Verhaltenskontrolle gegenüber dem Gesetzgeber in die <lb/>Grundrechtsprüfung? Diskutiert anhand des "Procedural Turn" des EGMR, Zeitschrift für Verwaltung 85:1 <lb/>(2021) 85 (85 ff). <lb/>71 For the discussion of the Judgement in the Swiss Parliament (declaring the judgement to be in violation of <lb/>democratic values): <lb/>https://www.parlament.ch/de/services/news/Seiten/2024/20240612113101111194158159026_bsd076.aspx . <lb/>72 In principle, the requirements the Court established for national legislators are in line with was has been <lb/>established as the "building blocks of effective climate laws": Higham/Keuschnigg/Chan/Setzer, What Does the <lb/>European Court of Human Rights' First Climate Change Decision Mean for Climate Policy?, Verfassungsblog <lb/>15.05.2024, https://verfassungsblog.de/what-does-the-european-court-of-human-rights-first-climate-change-<lb/>decision-mean-for-climate-policy/. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>110</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>as to whether judgements of the ECtHR (and, it seems, courts in general) are a suitable <lb/>means to compel States to the urgent action needed to combat the climate crisis. 73 This <lb/>criticism has some truth to it insofar as it acknowledges that courts alone may not be able <lb/>to exert the pressure that is (obviously) needed to initiate and drive transformative policy. <lb/>What is left out of the picture in this position is, however, that strategic litigation is usually <lb/>part of a bigger strategy to advocate for social change. Court judgements can help to <lb/>legitimize this advocacy efforts, especially when these judgements refer to human rights <lb/>argumentation. 74 As such, these judgements may help to put topics like climate change <lb/>back on the political agenda and shift policy-makers' attention and priorities. <lb/>Lastly, one can ask whether the Court itself acted strategically when devising the <lb/>judgement. Commentators have called the judgement "tainted by [the] objective of <lb/>judicial self-preservation", as the Court did not consider in depth the claims brought <lb/>forward relating to intergenerational equity, 75 which is even more obvious in view of the <lb/>Duarte 76 case. Nevertheless, the Court did introduce standing for NGOs and thus allowed <lb/>for a range of future cases, probably also bringing up (again) intergenerational issues. <lb/>B. Standing for Associations <lb/>One of the major novelties within the KlimaSeniorinnen judgement is the Court's <lb/>approach to associations and their opportunities to access the Court. 77 The Court <lb/>introduced a novel concept of locus standi of associations, independent of the victim <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
		<listBibl>73 Eicke, para 69. <lb/>74 For the strategic orientation of the KlimaSeniorinnen case and the narratives employed cf Keller/Bornemann, <lb/>New Climate Activism between Politics and Law: Analyzing the Strategy of the KlimaSeniorinnen Schweiz, Politics <lb/>and Governance 9:2 (2021) 124 (128 f, 131); highlighting the intersectionality of the approach: Sußner, <lb/>Intersektionalität als Strategie: Der Fall KlimaSeniorinnen v. Switzerland, Zeitschrift des deutschen <lb/>Juristinnenbundes (2023) 74 ff; Jong, Beyond the turn to human rights: a call for an intersectional climate justice <lb/>approach, The International Journal of Human Rights 28:5 (2024), 738 ff; Hefti, Intersectional Victims as Agents <lb/>of Change in International Human Rights-Based Climate Litigation, Transnational Environmental Law (2024) 1 ff. <lb/>75 Brucher/De Spiegeleir, The European Court of Human Rights' April 9 Climate Rulings and the Future (Thereof), <lb/>Verfassungsblog, 29.04.2024, https://verfassungsblog.de/the-european-court-of-human-rights-april-9-climate-<lb/>rulings-and-the-future-thereof/. <lb/>76 ECtHR 09.04.2024, Duarte Agostinho and Others / Portugal and 32 others, application no 39371/20. <lb/>77 Cf also Wende, Das KlimaSeniorinnen-Urteil des EGMR -Was ist neu daran?, EnergieKrise-Aktuell (2024) <lb/>010346. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>111</page>
        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>status of their members. In doing so, the Court went beyond was what initially conceived <lb/>of as possible by the claimants. 78 <lb/>The main justification for this new approach stems from the specificities of the climate <lb/>crisis and the resulting harms. 79 In order to ensure that claims alleging human rights <lb/>violations due to lack of climate change mitigation can reach the Court without allowing <lb/>for actio popularis, the Court found it necessary to develop its case-law in the fashion <lb/>described above in the summary section. <lb/>Given that locus standi is the most obvious novelty, it is unsurprising that this aspect has <lb/>received a major part of scholarly attention and criticism. In Line with Judge Eicke, scholars <lb/>criticise the ECtHR for overstepping the boundaries of the explicit provisions of the <lb/>Convention, 80 namely Article 34 ECHR that reads: "The Court may receive applications <lb/>from any person, non-governmental organisation or group of individuals claiming to be <lb/>the victim of a violation by one of the High Contracting Parties of the rights set forth in the <lb/>Convention or the protocols thereto." Critics argue that Article 34 ECHR demands a direct <lb/>link between the applicant and the alleged violation of human rights. <lb/>However, as the Court has pointed out, the terms of the Convention are usually <lb/>interpreted as being part of a living document that evolves with the changing of <lb/>circumstances. It is not unusual, then, that one and the same word (in this case: victim) <lb/>has more than one meaning and is shaped into different categories of meaning. In the <lb/>specific climate change context, the Court has argued that the "classic" victim concepts <lb/>lead to a lack of enforceability of human rights and thus developed a new approach, <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
		<listBibl>78 Cf Bähr/Brunner/Casper/Lustig, KlimaSeniorinnen: lessons from the Swiss senior women's case for future <lb/>climate litigation, Journal of Human Rights and the Environment, 9:2 (2018) 194 (220), who argue that <lb/>KlimaSeniorinnen could lead to new developments related to standing in climate litigation, but throughout use <lb/>the argument of being specifically affected as individuals or group of individuals, which is more closely related to <lb/>the previously established categories of victim status. <lb/>79 In the same vein: Letwin, Klimaseniorinnen: the Innovative and the Orthodox, EJIL:Talk!, 17.04.2024, <lb/>https://www.ejiltalk.org/klimaseniorinnen-the-innovative-and-the-orthodox/. <lb/> 80 <lb/>For <lb/>instance: <lb/>Wegener, <lb/>"Globuli <lb/>für <lb/>Umweltjuristen", <lb/>Verfassungsblog, <lb/>11.04.2024, <lb/>https://verfassungsblog.de/globuli-fur-umweltjuristen; Auner, Recht auf effektive Maßnahmen zur Eindämmung <lb/>des Klimawandels (Entscheidungsanmerkung), Newsletter Menschenrechte (2024) 123 (124 f); <lb/>Piska/Winkler/Zehetner, Verein Klimaseniorinnen vs Schweiz: Es ist nicht alles Gold, was glänzt, ecolex (2024) <lb/>449 ff; Fremuth, Klimawandel vor dem EGMR und die Grenzen der Menschenrechtskonvention Zugleich <lb/>Besprechung von EGMR Urt. v. 9.4.2024, Europäische Zeitschrift für Wirtschaftsrecht (2024) 697 (702); discussing <lb/>said criticism and highlighting the limitations of the "new" locus standi for NGOs Hollaus, Das Urteil des EGMR <lb/>im Fall KlimaSeniorinnen und seine Implikationen für den europäischen Grundrechtsschutz, Juristische Blätter <lb/>(2024) 485 (491 ff). <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>112</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>consisting in the privileged position of associations meeting certain criteria to bring <lb/>applications. This new approach is in line with the development in international law and <lb/>practice, 81 where associations -mostly: environmental NGOs -are increasingly relied on <lb/>as an important pillar of civil society. 82 The most relevant document in this regard is the <lb/>Aarhus Convention, 83 which qualifies environmental NGOs as important part of civil <lb/>society. 84 <lb/>Here, it is interesting to note that the Court found climate-change litigation not to be <lb/>covered by the Aarhus Convention. This is true only insofar as legislative acts or emissions <lb/>are concerned, as legislators and courts do not fall under the Aarhus Convention's <lb/>definition of "public authority" 85 . Whilst the Court dealt with exactly these legislative <lb/>omissions, legislation and executive measures often mix when it comes to climate <lb/>mitigation, and effective climate mitigation does in many cases depend on implementing <lb/>executive regulations. In these cases, the Aarhus Convention is directly applicable. There, <lb/>it will be interesting to observe if and how the criteria established by the Court for <lb/>associations to have standing will converge with the criteria established under the Aarhus <lb/>Convention and within implementing domestic legislation. <lb/>In addition to this, looking at the quite broad thematic scope of the Aarhus Convention <lb/>highlights another issue of the Court's new approach: Is locus standi of associations limited <lb/>to human rights based climate litigation only? Whilst the climate crisis is definitively one <lb/>of the most pressing global challenges, the climate is only one of the planetary boundaries <lb/>relevant for sustaining a liveable planet. 86 Whilst it might be much less evident or <lb/>imminent that human rights violations could result from a loss of biodiversity or the <lb/>acidification of the oceans, it is not unconceivable to argue that these issues also pose a <lb/>threat to human rights (mainly: Article 2 and 8 ECHR). In addition to that, even if locus <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>81 For the aspects of the judgement relying on international climate law (in particular: the Paris agreement) see <lb/>Jahn, The Paris Effect. Human Rights in Light of International Climate Goals and Commitments, Verfassungsblog, <lb/>25.04.2024, https://verfassungsblog.de/the-paris-effect/. <lb/>82 Cf Hollaus, Das Urteil des EGMR im Fall KlimaSeniorinnen und seine Implikationen für den europäischen <lb/>Grundrechtsschutz, Juristische Blätter (2024) 485 (491 ff). <lb/>83 1998 Aarhus Convention on Access to Information, Public Participation in Decision-Making and Access to <lb/>Justice in Environmental Matters, 2161 UNTS 447. <lb/>84 Cf the Aarhus Convention's definitions of "public" (Article 2 para 4) and "public concerned" (Article 2 para 5). <lb/>85 Article 2 para 2 Aarhus Convention: "This definition does not include bodies or institutions acting in a judicial <lb/>or legislative capacity". <lb/>86 For the planetary boundaries, cf https://www.stockholmresilience.org/research/planetary-boundaries.html. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>113</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>standi of association might be granted for climate litigation cases only, a very broad range <lb/>of legislation is, in fact, relevant for reaching set climate targets. 87 <lb/>C. The Literal Costs of KlimaSeniorinnen -Justice is Not Accessible For All <lb/>Another issue worth highlighting are the literal costs of KlimaSeniorinnen. Altogether, the <lb/>applicant association claimed expenses of roughly EUR 715.000, only CHF 9.000 of which <lb/>were costs imposed by the Swiss Courts at domestic level. 88 The Court deemed only a <lb/>fraction of these costs as necessarily incurred and awarded EUR 80.000 to the applicant <lb/>association. 89 <lb/>Whilst it is speculative to consider whether the case would have been equally successful <lb/>with less or less expensive legal advice, it is nevertheless obvious that the litigation <lb/>strategy employed by KlimaSeniorinnen was costly. It has been pointed out in the <lb/>literature that the efforts were only made possible through Greenpeace's financial <lb/>support. 90 This of course begs the question whether the Court unwillingly opened up the <lb/>door for a very elitist climate litigation scene, allowing only associations with a very stable <lb/>financial background to bring claims of human rights violations resulting from lacking <lb/>climate change mitigation. Whilst this allegation might have some truth to it, one has to <lb/>keep in mind that access to justice in general is usually a privilege of the few, not the reality <lb/>of the many. 91 Taking human rights disputes to the ECtHR is a lengthy process, demanding <lb/>not only from a financial perspective, but also time-wise, psychologically and mentally. <lb/>This is even more so with prominent cases, where applicants are under the critical eye of <lb/>the public (sometimes also: seek media attention to further their case). <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
        <listBibl>87 Cf for the debate on speed limits on Austrian highways: Krempelmeier/Kirchmair, Verfassungswidrigkeit <lb/>klimaschädlicher Verkehrsgesetzgebung. Warum Tempo 130 km/h auf Autobahnen und Tempo 100 km/h auf <lb/>Freilandstraßen (derzeit) verfassungswidrig ist, Recht der Umwelt -Beilage Umwelt und Technik (2023) 39 (43 <lb/>f). <lb/>88 Para 648. <lb/>89 Para 650. <lb/>90 Keller/Bornemann, New Climate Activism between Politics and Law: Analyzing the Strategy of the <lb/>KlimaSeniorinnen Schweiz, Politics and Governance 9:2 (2021) 124 (131). <lb/>91 See recently Hahn, Strategische Prozessführung im Klagekollektiv (2024) BadenBaden Nomos, 187 ff with many <lb/>references. For a critical perspective taking into account the recent climate decisions of the ECtHR cf Raible, <lb/>Priorities for Climate Litigation at the European Court of Human Rights, EJIL:Talk!, 02.05.2024, <lb/>https://www.ejiltalk.org/priorities-for-climate-litigation-at-the-european-court-of-human-rights/; Schayani, No <lb/>Global Climate Justice from this Court, Völkerrechtsblog, 15.04.2024, https://voelkerrechtsblog.org/no-global-<lb/>climate-justice-from-this-court/. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>114</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>Given that the Court found that climate litigation aimed at ensuring the effective <lb/>implementation of existing climate legislation falls under Article 6 ECHR, the case-law on <lb/>legal aid for the civil limb of Article 6 ECHR might become relevant in these cases. 92 In <lb/>climate cases, not only the courts, 93 but first litigants have to deal with complicated legal <lb/>issues as well as with an increasingly complex factual situation. Given the need to provide <lb/>proper evidence and scientific studies to support claims of alleged human rights violations <lb/>through lacking climate protection efforts, 94 the question of costs for acquiring this <lb/>expertise might be even more relevant for climate litigation. Here, next to the principle of <lb/>equality of arms, 95 the Court might want to take a closer look at Article 9 (4) Aarhus <lb/>Convention, demanding that procedures should not be "prohibitively expensive". 96 In <lb/>addition, the procedural safeguards laid down by the Court, including the obligation to <lb/>make scientific evidence and evaluations of policies and legislation available to the public <lb/>could support the realisation of more equitable access to justice. <lb/></body>

        <!-- mixed-reference -->
        <listBibl>92 For a summary see CoE/ECtHR, Guide on Article 6 of the European Convention on Human Rights. Right to a fair <lb/>trial (civil limb). Updated to 31 August 2023 (2023), available at https://ks.echr.coe.int, para 163 ff. For a <lb/>discussion of Article 6 issues in KlimaSeniorinnen cf Hollaus, Das Urteil des EGMR im Fall KlimaSeniorinnen und <lb/>seine Implikationen für den europäischen Grundrechtsschutz, Juristische Blätter (2024) 485 (498 ff). <lb/>93 For a discussion of Judge Eicke's critical perspective on this issue and a rebuttal see Humphreys, A Swiss human <lb/>rights budget?, EJIL:Talk!, 12.04.2024, https://www.ejiltalk.org/a-swiss-human-rights-budget/ . <lb/>94 <lb/>For <lb/>the <lb/>experience <lb/>in <lb/>the <lb/>KlimaSeniorinnen <lb/>case <lb/>cf <lb/>Blattner/Vicedo-<lb/>Cabrera/Frölicher/Ingold/Raible/Wyttenbach, How science bolstered a key European climate-change case, <lb/>Nature 621 (2023) 255 ff. <lb/>95 Cf ECtHR 15.05.2005, Steel and Morris / United Kingdom, application no 68416/01, para 59 ff. In this case, <lb/>the Court found that the refusal to grant legal aid in a complex defamation case, facing a wealthy opponent, <lb/>resulted in a violation of the principle of equality of arms. The Court took into account the legal and factual <lb/>complexity of the case as well as the diverging economic characteristics of the opponents, insofar as they <lb/>resulted in different levels of legal assistance being available. Taking these criteria seriously and applying them <lb/>to climate litigation cases, one could argue that States have a duty to provide legal aid resulting from Art 6 <lb/>ECHR and the principle of equality of arms: Climate litigation usually involves complex legal and factual issues. <lb/>In addition to that, in administrative or constitutional proceedings falling under Art 6 ECHR where litigants face <lb/>"the State" (legislator or executive branch), the State is typically in a privileged position to gain both legal and <lb/>factual expertise. <lb/>96 The Aarhus Convention Compliance Committee (ACCC) has developed a rich case-law on this provision in its <lb/>practice. See recently ACCC, 03.09.2021, Findings and recommendations with regard to communication <lb/>ACCC/C/2015/130 concerning compliance by Italy, ECE/MP.PP/C.1/2021/22. <lb/></listBibl>


        <page>115</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>

        <body>IV. Changing Legal Opportunity Structures; Opportunities Yet to <lb/>be Seized <lb/>The KlimaSeniorinnen judgement can be qualified as revolutionary as it 97 brings about <lb/>major changes for the position of associations and their opportunities to challenge <lb/>human rights violations caused by insufficient climate mitigation measures. Given that <lb/>this is a new development, it is unsurprising and not uncommon for this new doctrine to <lb/>come with some unanswered questions. These questions relate, inter alia, to the <lb/>applicability of the doctrine (whether "only" in climate litigation cases or beyond) and the <lb/>precise criteria associations must fulfil to be granted standing. It remains to be seen how <lb/>this development will impact domestic legal opportunity structures 98 and ensuing climate <lb/>litigation. As of yet, restrictive admissibility criteria often hinder substantive decisions on <lb/>climate issues at the domestic level. 99 <lb/>From a substantive perspective, the Court developed its environmental case-law <lb/>coherently, taking into account the specificities of the climate crisis. A strong focus was <lb/>placed on procedural safeguards, which the Court derived from Article 8 ECHR. According <lb/>to the Court, Article 8 ECHR imposes a general obligation of Contracting States to <lb/>"undertake measures for the substantial and progressive reduction of their respective <lb/>GHG emission levels, with a view to reaching net neutrality within, in principle, the next <lb/>three decades" 100 . <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>97 As the ambiguity of the title of this essay might already suggest to some readers, it is justified to see both the <lb/>ECtHR and the association KlimaSeniorinnen (as well as the many individuals involved in the litigation efforts) <lb/>as drivers of the resulting change in legal opportunity structures. <lb/>98 For the concept of legal opportunity structures see Vanhala, Legal Opportunity Structures and the Paradox of <lb/>Legal Mobilization by the Environmental Movement in the UK, Law &amp; Society Review 46:3 (2012) 523 (526 ff); <lb/>Vanhala, Shaping the Structure of Legal Opportunities: Environmental NGOs Bringing International <lb/>Environmental Procedural Rights Back Home, Law &amp; Policy 40:1 (2018) 110 ff; Andersen, Out of the Closets &amp; <lb/>into the Courts. Legal Opportunity Structure and Gay Rights Litigation (2006) Ann Arbor: University of Michigan <lb/>Press, 204 ff. <lb/>99 For a comparative perspective on admissibility criteria in Austria, Germany and Switzerland see Marhold, <lb/>Klimaklagen. Zulässigkeitsprüfung im Rechtsvergleich (2024) Vienna, Linde Verlag; cf Madner, Climate Change as <lb/>a Challenge for Constitutional Courts: Fundamental Freedoms and Duties of Protection -A Perspective from <lb/>Austria, Human Rights Law Journal (2023) 354 ff. <lb/>100 Para 548. <lb/></listBibl>
  
		<page>116</page>

        <note place="headnote">KlimaSeniorinnen: Changing Legal Opportunity Structures in the Face of the Climate Crisis (Weber) <lb/></note>
  
        <body>While it is true that this judgement is only one piece within the larger puzzle of necessary <lb/>transformative steps, 101 it could become a very important piece. 102 It remains to be seen <lb/>how the new opportunities will be utilized by legislators, governments, courts and civil <lb/>society alike. 103</body> <lb/>
  
        <listBibl>101 Positioning litigation as one of many avenues to strengthen climate protection: Vanhala, Coproducing the <lb/>Endangered Polar Bear: Science, Climate Change, and Legal Mobilization, Law &amp; Policy 42:2 (2020) 105 ff. For a <lb/>fundamental critique of the role of courts for social change cf eg Rosenberg, Tilting at Windmills: Brown II and <lb/>the Hopeless Quest to Resolve Deep-Seated Social Conflict through Litigation, Law &amp; Inequality: A Journal of <lb/>Theory and Practice 24:1 (2006) 31 ff; however, Rosenberg also points to the relevance of legislative action, and <lb/>this is exactly what KlimaSeniorinnen and further climate litigation efforts aim at triggering. <lb/>102 It should also be noted that there are a few climate cases still pending, most notably Müllner / Austria; cf <lb/>Prantl, After Switzerland Comes Austria. Why the ECtHR could soon grant individual standing in a climate <lb/>mitigation case for the first time, Verfassungsblog, 24.05.2024, https://verfassungsblog.de/after-switzerland-<lb/>comes-austria/. <lb/>103 Possible consequences for the EU system of legal protection are discussed by Eeckhout, From Strasbourg to <lb/>Luxembourg? The KlimaSeniorinnen judgment and EU remedies, Verfassungsblog, 05.06.2024, <lb/>https://verfassungsblog.de/from-strasbourg-to-luxembourg/. Observations on the role of collective actors (that <lb/>has been strengthened by the KlimaSeniorinnen judgement) for mobilizing the law with many references: Hahn, <lb/>Strategische Prozessführung im Klagekollektiv (2024) BadenBaden Nomos, 215 ff.</listBibl>

	</text>
</TEI>