<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pdf-tei-editor.panya.de/api/files/872ab" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-09-16T20:34:08.656688Z">16.09.2025 20:34:08</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [article/dh-law-footnotes]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.26321$1$s.marino.01.2025.06</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher/>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication"/>
        <idno type="DOI">10.26321/s.marino.01.2025.06</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>10.26321/s.marino.01.2025.06</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-09-16T20:34:08.656688Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">0707645</label>
          <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-09-16T20:34:08.656688Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <titlePage>Freedom, Security &amp; Justice: <lb/>European Legal Studies <lb/>Rivista giuridica di classe A <lb/>2025, n. 1 <lb/>DIRETTRICE <lb/>Angela Di Stasi <lb/>Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale e di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Salerno <lb/>Titolare della Cattedra Jean Monnet 2017-2020 (Commissione europea) <lb/>&quot;Judicial Protection of Fundamental Rights in the European Area of Freedom, Security and Justice&quot; <lb/>CONSIGLIO SCIENTIFICO <lb/>Giandonato Caggiano, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università Roma Tre <lb/>Sergio Maria Carbone, Professore Emerito, Università di Genova <lb/>Roberta Clerici, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto Internazionale privato, Università di Milano <lb/>Nigel Lowe, Professor Emeritus, University of Cardiff <lb/>Paolo Mengozzi, Professore Emerito, Università &quot;Alma Mater Studiorum&quot; di Bologna -già Avvocato generale presso la Corte di giustizia dell&apos;UE <lb/>Massimo Panebianco, Professore Emerito, Università di Salerno <lb/>Nicoletta Parisi, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Catania -già Componente ANAC <lb/>Guido Raimondi, già Presidente della Corte EDU -già Presidente di Sezione della Corte di Cassazione <lb/>Silvana Sciarra, Professore Emerito, Università di Firenze -Presidente Emerito della Corte Costituzionale <lb/>Giuseppe Tesauro, Professore f.r. di Diritto dell&apos;UE, Università di Napoli &quot;Federico II&quot; -Presidente Emerito della Corte Costituzionale † <lb/>Antonio Tizzano, Professore Emerito, Università di Roma &quot;La Sapienza&quot; -Vice Presidente Emerito della Corte di giustizia dell&apos;UE <lb/>Ennio Triggiani, Professore Emerito, Università di Bari <lb/>Ugo Villani, Professore Emerito, Università di Bari <lb/>COMITATO EDITORIALE <lb/>Maria Caterina Baruffi, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Bergamo <lb/>Alfonso-Luis Calvo Caravaca, Catedrático Jubilado de Derecho Internacional Privado, Universidad Carlos III de Madrid <lb/>Ida Caracciolo, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università della Campania -Giudice dell&apos;ITLOS <lb/>Pablo Antonio Fernández-Sánchez, Catedrático de Derecho Internacional, Universidad de Sevilla <lb/>Inge Govaere, Director of the European Legal Studies Department, College of Europe, Bruges <lb/>Paola Mori, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università &quot;Magna Graecia&quot; di Catanzaro <lb/>Lina Panella, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Messina <lb/>Lucia Serena Rossi, Ordinario di Diritto dell&apos;UE, Università &quot;Alma Mater Studiorum&quot; di Bologna -già Giudice della Corte di giustizia dell&apos;UE <lb/>COMITATO DEI REFEREES <lb/>Bruno Barel, Associato f.r. di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Padova <lb/>Marco Benvenuti, Ordinario di Istituzioni di Diritto pubblico, Università di Roma &quot;La Sapienza&quot; <lb/>Francesco Buonomenna, Associato di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Salerno <lb/>Raffaele Cadin, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Roma &quot;La Sapienza&quot; <lb/>Ruggiero Cafari Panico, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Milano <lb/>Federico Casolari, Ordinario di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università &quot;Alma Mater Studiorum&quot; di Bologna <lb/>Luisa Cassetti, Ordinario di Istituzioni di Diritto Pubblico, Università di Perugia <lb/>Giovanni Cellamare, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Bari <lb/>Giuseppe D&apos;Angelo, Ordinario di Diritto ecclesiastico e canonico, Università di Salerno <lb/>Sara De Vido, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università Ca&apos; Foscari Venezia <lb/>Marcello Di Filippo, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Pisa <lb/>Rosario Espinosa Calabuig, Catedrática de Derecho Internacional Privado, Universitat de València <lb/>Caterina Fratea, Associato di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Verona <lb/>Ana C. Gallego Hernández, Profesora Ayudante de Derecho Internacional Público y Relaciones Internacionales, Universidad de Sevilla <lb/>Pietro Gargiulo, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Teramo <lb/>Francesca Graziani, Associato di Diritto Internazionale, Università della Campania &quot;Luigi Vanvitelli&quot; <lb/>Giancarlo Guarino, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Napoli &quot;Federico II&quot; <lb/>Elspeth Guild, Associate Senior Research Fellow, CEPS <lb/>Victor Luis Gutiérrez Castillo, Profesor de Derecho Internacional Público, Universidad de Jaén <lb/>Ivan Ingravallo, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Bari <lb/>Paola Ivaldi, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Genova <lb/>Luigi Kalb, Ordinario di Procedura Penale, Università di Salerno <lb/>Luisa Marin, Ricercatore di Diritto dell&apos;UE, Università dell&apos;Insubria <lb/>Simone Marinai, Associato di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Pisa <lb/>Fabrizio Marongiu Buonaiuti, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Macerata <lb/>Rostane Medhi, Professeur de Droit Public, Université d&apos;Aix-Marseille <lb/>Michele Messina, Ordinario di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Messina <lb/>Stefano Montaldo, Associato di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Torino <lb/>Violeta Moreno-Lax, Senior Lecturer in Law, Queen Mary University of London <lb/>Claudia Morviducci, Professore Senior di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università Roma Tre <lb/>Michele Nino, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Salerno <lb/>Criseide Novi, Associato di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Foggia <lb/>Anna Oriolo, Associato di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Salerno <lb/>Leonardo Pasquali, Ordinario di Diritto internazionale, Università di Pisa <lb/>Piero Pennetta, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Salerno <lb/>Francesca Perrini, Associato di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Messina <lb/>Gisella Pignataro, Associato di Diritto privato comparato, Università di Salerno <lb/>Emanuela Pistoia, Ordinario di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Teramo <lb/>Anna Pitrone, Associato di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Messina <lb/>Concetta Maria Pontecorvo, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Napoli &quot;Federico II&quot; <lb/>Pietro Pustorino, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università LUISS di Roma <lb/>Santiago Ripol Carulla, Catedrático de Derecho internacional público, Universitat Pompeu Fabra Barcelona <lb/>Angela Maria Romito, Associato di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Bari <lb/>Gianpaolo Maria Ruotolo, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Foggia <lb/>Teresa Russo, Associato di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Salerno <lb/>Alessandra A. Souza Silveira, Diretora do Centro de Estudos em Direito da UE, Universidad do Minho <lb/>Ángel Tinoco Pastrana, Profesor de Derecho Procesal, Universidad de Sevilla <lb/>Sara Tonolo, Ordinario di Diritto Internazionale, Università degli Studi di Padova <lb/>Chiara Enrica Tuo, Ordinario di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Genova <lb/>Talitha Vassalli di Dachenhausen, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Napoli &quot;Federico II&quot; <lb/>Valentina Zambrano, Associato di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Roma &quot;La Sapienza&quot; <lb/>Alessandra Zanobetti, Ordinario f.r. di Diritto Internazionale, Università &quot;Alma Mater Studiorum&quot; di Bologna <lb/>COMITATO DI REDAZIONE <lb/>Angela Festa, Ricercatore di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università della Campania &quot;Luigi Vanvitelli&quot; <lb/>Anna Iermano, Associato di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Salerno <lb/>Daniela Marrani, Associato di Diritto Internazionale, Università di Salerno <lb/>Rossana Palladino (Coordinatore), Associato di Diritto dell&apos;Unione europea, Università di Salerno <lb/>Revisione linguistica degli abstracts a cura di <lb/>Francesco Campofreda, Dottore di ricerca in Diritto Internazionale, Università di Salerno <lb/>Rivista quadrimestrale on line &quot;Freedom, Security &amp; Justice: European Legal Studies&quot; www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/>Editoriale Scientifica, Via San Biagio dei Librai, 39 -Napoli <lb/>CODICE ISSN 2532-2079 -Registrazione presso il Tribunale di Nocera Inferiore n° 3 del 3 marzo 2017 <lb/>Indice-Sommario <lb/>2025, n. 1 <lb/>Editoriale <lb/>Le transizioni dell&apos;Occidente europeo: dalla traslatio imperii alla pace di Westphalia e oltre <lb/>Massimo Panebianco <lb/>p. 1 <lb/>Saggi e Articoli <lb/>Possibili sviluppi in tema di contrasto alle mutilazioni genitali femminili: la recente direttiva UE <lb/>2024/1385 e gli obblighi per il legislatore italiano <lb/>Silvia Angioi, Annachiara Rotondo <lb/>Il nuovo Regolamento (UE) 2024/3015 tra i più recenti strumenti della comunità internazionale <lb/>contro il lavoro forzato: vecchie soluzioni per vecchi schemi <lb/>Silvia Cantoni <lb/>La mano invisibile dell&apos;intelligenza artificiale e il principio di trasparenza nei rapporti B2C: la <lb/>tutela del consumatore nel mercato unico digitale <lb/>Francesco Deana <lb/>Does the EU Corporate Sustainability Due Diligence Directive protect indigenous peoples&apos; <lb/>right to food? Assessment and future prospects <lb/>Anna Facchinetti <lb/>Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law: in quest of localisation <lb/>Silvia Marino <lb/>I valori dell&apos;Unione europea e la loro tutela giurisdizionale <lb/>Criseide Novi <lb/>Alcune considerazioni in merito alla base giuridica della nuova direttiva sui lavori resi tramite <lb/>piattaforme digitali <lb/>Alfredo Rizzo <lb/>Commenti e Note <lb/>Verein Klimaseniorinnen and others v. Switzerland between human rights protection and <lb/>human rights justification <lb/>Nicolò Paolo Alessi <lb/>p. 10 <lb/>p. 45 <lb/>p. 66 <lb/>p. 86 <lb/>p. 111 <lb/>p. 136 <lb/>p. 189 <lb/>p. 210 <lb/>La libertà di stampa e il contenuto dell&apos;ordine pubblico quale limite alla circolazione delle <lb/>sentenze nello spazio giudiziario europeo <lb/>Roberto Dante Cogliandro <lb/>Contrasto alla povertà e cooperazione internazionale nell&apos;area euro-mediterranea <lb/>Giuseppe Emanuele Corsaro <lb/>Illeciti commessi dall&apos;intelligenza artificiale: aspetti di giurisdizione e legge applicabile nel <lb/>quadro normativo dell&apos;Unione europea <lb/>Curzio Fossati <lb/>L&apos;integrazione differenziata nello spazio Schengen: profili &quot;costituzionali&quot; di legittimità <lb/>democratica <lb/>Maria Patrin <lb/>p. 237 <lb/>p. 255 <lb/>p. 281 <lb/>p. 304 <lb/></titlePage>
    
    <front>Freedom, Security &amp; Justice: European Legal Studies <lb/>ISSN 2532-2079 <lb/>2025, n. 1, pp. 111-135 <lb/>DOI:10.26321/S.MARINO.01.2025.06 <lb/>www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/>CROSS BORDER PRIVATE ENFORCEMENT OF EU COMPETITION LAW: <lb/>IN QUEST OF LOCALISATION <lb/>Silvia Marino * <lb/></front>
    
    <div type="toc">SUMMARY: 1. Introduction: the emergence of cross border private litigation in <lb/>competition matters. -2. The determination of jurisdiction: the application of the <lb/>general rules in competition cases. -2.1. The domicile of the defendant. -2.2. <lb/>Availability of the prorogation of jurisdiction. -3. Special grounds of jurisdictions <lb/>relevant for the private enforcement of EU Competition Law. -3.1. The relevance of <lb/>the location of a subsidiary combined with the principle of economic unity. -3.2. <lb/>Jurisdiction in respect of connected claims. -4. The infringement of EU Competition <lb/>Law as a matter (mainly) relating to tort, delict or quasi-delict. -5. The identification <lb/>of the place of the harmful event. -5.1. The place of the causal event. -5.2. The <lb/>place of the damage. -5.3. Assessing collective interests. -6. The law applicable to <lb/>acts restricting free competition. -6.1. The place of the damage: the affected market. <lb/>-6.2. The substantially affected Member State&apos;s market. -7. Some final remarks: the <lb/>localisation of the non-contractual liability arising out of a restriction of competition. <lb/></div>
    
    <body>1. Introduction: the emergence of cross border private litigation in competition <lb/>matters <lb/>In the latest years, private enforcement of EU Competition Law has gained <lb/>momentum 1 . This success can be motivated by several reasons: the harmonisation by the <lb/>EU through Directive 2014/104 2 ; the more widespread information concerning at least <lb/></body>
    
    <front>Double-blind peer reviewed article. <lb/>* Full Professor of European Union Law, University of Insubria. Email: silvia.marino@uninsubria.it. <lb/>Funded by the European Union. This Contribution is published in the framework of the Jean Monnet <lb/>Module: &quot;European Private International Law: Recent Trends and Challenges&quot; (EuPILART), co-funded by <lb/>the EACEA. Views and opinions expressed are however those of the author only and do not necessarily <lb/>reflect those of the European Union or the EACEA. Neither the European Union nor the EACEA as granting <lb/>authority can be held responsible for them. <lb/></front>
    
    <listBibl>1 A. L. CALVO CARAVACA, J. CARRASCOSA GONZÁLEZ, El Derecho internacional privado de la Unión <lb/>Europea frente a las acciones por daños anticompetitivos, in Cuadernos de derecho transnacional, 2018, <lb/>n. 2, pp. 7-178; B. J. RODGER, M. SOUSA FERRO, F. MARCOS (eds.), Research handbook on private <lb/>enforcement of competition law in the EU, Cheltenham, 2023; P. CARO DE SOUSA, The private enforcement <lb/>of competition law, Oxford, 2024. <lb/>2 Directive 2014/104/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council, on certain rules governing actions <lb/>for damages under national law for infringements of the competition law provisions of the Member States <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>112 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>
    
    <body>some infringements among the general public 3 ; not last, the sensitive injury caused by <lb/>some cartels 4 . It being considered as a helpful sword flanking the more classic public <lb/>enforcement system 5 , the development of private enforcement testifies the current <lb/>interests of private parties in the assessment of their own interests, the re-establishment <lb/>of a fair and undistorted competition and the restoration of damages occurred as a <lb/>consequence of EU Competition Law infringements. <lb/>In this framework, also EU civil judicial cooperation has its role to play. Indeed, the <lb/>infringement of EU Competition Law has natural legal consequences in the internal <lb/>market. Article 101 of the TFEU clearly states that the antitrust behaviour shall &quot;affect <lb/>trade between Member States&quot; prevent, restrict or distort &quot;competition within the internal <lb/>market&quot;; abuses of dominant position pursuant to Article 102 of the TFEU &quot;may affect <lb/>trade between Member States&quot;. The infringements must have a wide impact in the internal <lb/>market, or at least in more than one Member State. These multiple effects give rise to <lb/>difficulties in the frame of both public enforcement 6 and private enforcement 7 . In private <lb/>cross border cases, EU Regulations 1215/2012, Brussels Ibis 8 , on jurisdiction and <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>and of the European Union, of 26 November 2014, in OJ L297, 4 November 2011, pp. 1-8; P.L. PARCU, G. <lb/>MONTI, M. BOTTA (eds.), Private enforcement of EU competition law: the impact of the damages directive, <lb/>Cheltenham, 2018; M. STRAND, V. BASTIDAS, M.C. IACOVIDES (eds.), EU Competition Litigation. <lb/>Transposition and First Experiences of the New Regime, London, 2023; F. DÍEZ ESTELLA, Una década de <lb/>la Directiva 2014/104/UE, de acciones de daños antitrust, a través de las sentencias del TJUE, in <lb/>Cuadernos de derecho transnacional, 2024, n. 2, pp. 539-551. <lb/>3 We only need to think of the &quot;trucks case&quot; (Commission decision, Cartel, AT.39824, Trucks, of 27 <lb/>September 2017) that hit the headlines of both specialised and general communication media (see, for <lb/>example, <lb/>in <lb/>Italy, <lb/>the <lb/>ANSA <lb/>news, <lb/>available <lb/>at: <lb/>https://www.ansa.it/pressrelease/economia/2024/03/04/new-class-action-against-the-truck-cartel-another-<lb/>chance-for_d6d3669a-a4ca-4f01-a538-23aebd720ebc.html). <lb/>4 The &quot;trucks cartel&quot; lasted 14 years and had as object the price increase of the goods. It has originated a <lb/>big amount of private enforcement claims, although mostly purely internal: B. BORNEMAN, J. SUDEROW, <lb/>España a la cabeza en la litigación derivada del cartel de los fabricantes de camiones. Primeras sentencias <lb/>del Tribunal Supremo Español y su relevancia en Europa, in Cuadernos de derecho transnacional, 2023, <lb/>n. 2, pp. 1040-1050. <lb/>5 Recital 6 of the Directive 2014/104; Court of Justice, Second Chamber, judgment of 14 March 2019, <lb/>Skanska Industrial Solutions and others, case C-724/17, par. 45. <lb/>6 Neither Council Regulation (EC) 1/2003, on the implementation of the rules on competition laid down in <lb/>Articles 81 and 82 of the Treaty, of 16 December 2002, in OJ L1, 4 January 2003, pp. 1-25 nor Directive <lb/>(EU) 2019/1 of the European Parliament and of the Council, to empower the competition authorities of the <lb/>Member States to be more effective enforcers and to ensure the proper functioning of the internal market, <lb/>of 11 December 2018, in OJ L11, 14 January 2019, pp. 3-33 establish criteria for the determination of the <lb/>proper Competition Authority to investigate the antitrust infringement, thus creating potential problems of <lb/>functional competence and coordination (A.M. ROMITO, Ruolo e funzioni dell&apos;European Competition <lb/>Network, Bari, 2020, pp. 38-49). <lb/>7 P. IANNUCCELLI, La responsabilità delle imprese nel diritto della concorrenza dell&apos;Unione Europea e la <lb/>direttiva 2014/104, Milano, 2015, pp. 157-216; G. BRUZZONE, A. SAIJA, Private e public enforcement dopo <lb/>il recepimento della direttiva. Più di un aggiustamento al margine?, in Mercato, concorrenza, regole, 2017, <lb/>pp. 9-36; O. PALLOTTA, Public e private antitrust enforcement alla luce della direttiva 2014/104/UE: <lb/>l&apos;equilibrio alterato, in Studi sull&apos;integrazione europea, 2017, pp. 621-640; W.P.J. WILS, Private <lb/>Enforcement of EU Antitrust Law and Its Relationship with Public Enforcement: Past, Present, Future, in <lb/>World Competition: Law and Economics Review, 2017, pp. 3-46. <lb/>8 Regulation (EU) 1215/2012 of the European Parliament and of the Council, on jurisdiction and the <lb/>recognition and enforcement of judgments in civil and commercial matters, of 12 December 2012, in OJ <lb/>L351, 20 December 2012, pp. 1-32. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>113 <lb/></page>

<body>864/2007, Rome II 9 , on the applicable law are of assistance. The former provides for a <lb/>general ground of jurisdiction, based on the domicile of the defendant (para. 2.1) and a <lb/>wide possibility of prorogation of jurisdiction (para. 2.2); for the purposes of cross border <lb/>private enforcement of EU Competition Law, alternative grounds of jurisdiction can come <lb/>into play (paras. 3 and 5). Article 6 of the Regulation 864/2007 establishes a special <lb/>connecting factor for claims related to non-contractual obligations arising out of a <lb/>restriction of competition (para. 6). <lb/>Notwithstanding the apparently clear structure of the two Regulations, the <lb/>determination of the jurisdiction and of the applicable law is not always an easy task, due <lb/>to the intricated black letter formulation of Article 6 of the Regulation 864/2007 10 , the <lb/>existing possible alternatives and, very unfortunately, the not always consistent <lb/>interpretation by the Court of Justice of the European Union (hereafter: CJEU). The most <lb/>difficult assignment is indeed that of localisation, the geographical (although theoretical) <lb/>placement of a claim within a (Member) State for the purposes of assessing jurisdiction, <lb/>or determining the applicable law, or both 11 . <lb/>The present paper aims at analysing the possibilities of localisation of the <lb/>infringement of EU Competition Law, for the purposes of its private enforcement, trying <lb/>to offer solutions to the classic private international law issues within the framework of <lb/>the Regulations in force. <lb/>2. The determination of jurisdiction: the application of the general rules in <lb/>competition cases <lb/>The first step consists of an analysis of the general grounds of jurisdiction provided <lb/>for by Regulation Brussels Ibis, having in mind the specific characters of private <lb/>enforcement of EU Competition Law. The continuity of the EU legal instruments enacted <lb/>in the field of civil and judicial cooperation 12 , although recast, offers an important set of <lb/>CJEU&apos;s case law on the interpretation of the rules on jurisdiction, starting from the 1968 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>9 Regulation (EC) 864/2007 of the European Parliament and of the Council, on the law applicable to non-<lb/>contractual obligations (Rome II), of 11 July 2007, in OJ L199, 31 July 2007, pp. 40-49. <lb/>10 C. HONORATI, Regolamento n. 864/2007 sulla legge applicabile alle obbligazioni non contrattuali, in F. <lb/>PREITE, A. GAZZANTI PUGLIESE (a cura di), Atti notarili. Diritto comunitario e internazionale, Torino, 2011, <lb/>p. 536. <lb/>11 A. A. EHRENZWEIG, Specific Principles of Private Transnational Law, in The Hague Academy Collected <lb/>Courses, Volume 124, 1968; G. VAN HECKE, Principes et méthodes de solution des conflits de lois, in The <lb/>Hague Academy Collected Courses, Volume 126, 1969; K. LIPSTEIN, The General Principles of Private <lb/>International Law, in The Hague Academy Collected Courses, Volume 135, 1972; recently: O. BOSKOVIC <lb/>(ed.), Localisation of Damage in Private International Law, Leiden, Boston, 2024. <lb/>12 Recital 34 of the Regulation 1215/2012; Court of Justice, Third Chamber, judgment of 12 September <lb/>2013, Sunico, case C-49/12, par. 32; recently: Court of Justice, Third Chamber, judgment of 20 May 2021, <lb/>CNP spółka z ograniczoną odpowiedzialnością, case C-913/19, par. 49; Court of Justice, Third Chamber, <lb/>judgment of 8 June 2023, BNP Paribas SA, case C-567/21, par. 39; Court of Justice, Seventh Chamber, <lb/>judgment of 14 September 2023, Club La Costa, case C-821/21, par. 41. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>114 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>Brussels Convention 13 . Cross border private enforcement of EU Competition Law is quite <lb/>a new field; nevertheless, the CJEU&apos;s case law can be re-read in the light of its specific <lb/>features. <lb/>2.1. The domicile of the defendant <lb/>The domicile of the defendant in a Member State is at the same time a limit to the <lb/>subjective scope of application 14 and the general rule on jurisdiction in civil and <lb/>commercial matters (Article 4 of the Regulation 1215/2012). The domicile of a legal <lb/>person 15 is defined by Article 63, it being alternatively the place of the statutory seat, or <lb/>of the central administration, or of the principal place of business. Therefore, the claimant <lb/>has a potential choice among three possibly different national courts, since the three <lb/>places can be located in different Member States, as the CJEU&apos;s jurisprudence on the <lb/>right of establishment confirms 16 . In case of multiple defendants, sued for the same <lb/>infringement, as the violation of Article 101 of the TFEU typically is, the possible choice <lb/>amplifies, since at least theoretically each wrongdoer might have three different <lb/>domiciles. This leaves wide room to the claimant for the choice of the best national court, <lb/>according to his/her purposes or needs. At the same time, it could be a proper forum for <lb/>the defendant(s), too, which has strong connections with the Member State of the seat of <lb/>the judge vested with jurisdiction, where the localisation is realised. <lb/>2.2. Availability of prorogation of jurisdiction <lb/>In civil and commercial matters, prorogation of jurisdiction is possible pursuant to <lb/>arts. 25 and 26 of the Regulation 1215/2012 17 . The requirements for a valid express <lb/>agreement are quite soft. Nevertheless, in the scope of EU Competition Law, pursuant to <lb/>the CJEU&apos;s case law, its practical availability must be distinguished depending on <lb/>whether the case refers to the violation of Article 101 or of Article 102 of the TFEU. <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>13 1968 Brussels Convention on jurisdiction and the enforcement of judgments in civil and commercial <lb/>matters, in OJ L299, 31 December 1972, pp. 32-42. <lb/>14 This rule is subject to exceptions, as exclusive grounds of jurisdiction according to Article 24 (for its <lb/>operation, Court of Justice, Grand Chamber, judgment of 25 February 2025, BSH Hausgeräte GmbH, case <lb/>C-339/22); choice of court agreements pursuant to Article 25; some rules devoted to the protection of <lb/>weaker contractual parties. <lb/>15 For the claims in competition matters, the case of the natural person as defendant seems a mere theoretical <lb/>hypothesis. <lb/>16 Court of Justice, judgment of 9 March 1999, Centros, case C-212/97; Court of Justice, Third Chamber, <lb/>judgment of 25 April 2024, Edil Work 2 Srl, case C-276/22. <lb/>17 This possibility is subject to exceptions (exclusive grounds of jurisdiction) and limitations (rules of <lb/>jurisdiction concerning consumer, insurance and employment contracts), that do not pertain to the private <lb/>enforcement of EU Competition Law. Ex multis: F. MARONGIU BUONAIUTI, Le obbligazioni non <lb/>contrattuali nel diritto internazionale privato, Milano, 2013, p. 71; F. GARCIMARTÍN ALFÉREZ, Prorogation <lb/>of Jurisdiction, in A. DICKINSON, E. LEIN (eds.), The Brussels I Regulation Recast, Oxford, 2015, pp. 277-<lb/>312; J. NOWAG, L. TARKKILA, How much effectiveness for the EU Damages Directive? Contractual <lb/>Clauses and Antitrust Damages Actions, in Common Market Law Review, 2020, p. 440. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>115 <lb/></page>

<body>For the former, the CJEU made it clear that a jurisdiction clause can concern only <lb/>disputes which have arisen or which may arise in connection with a particular legal <lb/>relationship. This condition avoids surprises to the detriment of the parties, because they <lb/>can be sued in the chosen court only for those claims that are connected with the contract <lb/>where the jurisdiction clause is included. Therefore, an agreement which refers generally <lb/>to disputes arising from contractual relationships does not extend to a dispute relating to <lb/>the tortious liability resulting from the participation of one contractual party to a cartel. <lb/>Indeed, the contractual party allegedly victim of the infringement could not reasonably <lb/>foresee this kind of litigation at the time of the agreement, since it had no knowledge of <lb/>the cartel involving the other party. Thus, the claim cannot be regarded as stemming from <lb/>a contractual relationship. Eventually, a jurisdiction clause does not bind the parties, if <lb/>the cause of action is the private enforcement of Article 101 of the TFEU, unless the <lb/>clause itself refers to liability for an infringement of EU Competition Law. <lb/>The same interpretation cannot be extended to the infringement of Article 102 of the <lb/>TFEU. Indeed, the abuse of dominant position can materialise in contractual clauses, for <lb/>example impacting on selling prices or conditions. Therefore, the action before the chosen <lb/>court cannot surprise the undertaking in a dominant position and the application of the <lb/>jurisdiction clause is not excluded on the sole ground that it does not expressly refer to <lb/>disputes relating to the infringement of EU Competition Law 18 . <lb/>This seems to be the only meaningful difference between cartels and abuse of <lb/>dominant position in the determination of jurisdiction in cross border private enforcement <lb/>of EU Competition Law. The rationale does not seem really strong 19 : in both situations, <lb/>the contractual party which suffered the loss might not be aware of the anticompetitive <lb/>conduct of the other party at the time of concluding the contract. Then, the infringement <lb/>can have repercussions on the contractual clauses and relationships. Finally, the <lb/>wrongdoer should be self-conscious of its illegal conduct. Furthermore, the need for <lb/>foreseeability seems to be read in different directions in the two cases, in favour of the <lb/>victim within the scope of Article 101 of the TFEU, in favour of the wrongdoer in the <lb/>field of Article 102 of the TFEU, leading to two different solutions, despite the fact that <lb/>foreseeability should be a general feature of the rules of law 20 . <lb/>Tacit prorogation of jurisdiction shall not depend on this distinction. Indeed, the case <lb/>is lodged: the claim, the cause of action and the claimant&apos;s requests are known. Therefore, <lb/>the defendant can simply decide to accept or not to accept the court&apos;s jurisdiction, <lb/>according to any objective or subjective evaluation on convenience. <lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>18 Court of Justice, Third Chamber, judgment of 24 October 2018, Apple, case C-595/17. <lb/>19 L. IDOT, Précisions importantes sur l&apos;application des articles 5, point 3, et point 5, du règlement aux <lb/>actions en réparation du fait de pratiques anticoncurrentielles, in Europe, 2018, p. 102; P. GOFFINET, R. <lb/>SPANGENBERG, Les clauses attributives de jurisdiction à l&apos;épreuve du droit de la concurrence, in Journal <lb/>de droit européen, 2019, pp. 199-201. <lb/>20 N. SAUVAGE, La dangereuse notion de « prévisibilité raisonnable » et l&apos;exigence de sécurité juridique, <lb/>in Revue de l&apos;Union européenne, 2012, p. 518. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>116 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>3. Special grounds of jurisdictions relevant for the private enforcement of EU <lb/>Competition Law <lb/>Arts. 7 and 8 of the Brussels Ibis Regulation provide for special and alternative <lb/>grounds of jurisdiction that widen the possibility to choose the competent court in favour <lb/>of the claimant. Failing any specific rule referring to claims related to the infringement of <lb/>EU Competition Law, Article 7(5) on the operation of a subsidiary, and Article 8(1) on <lb/>consolidation of claims against multiple defendants are likely to come into play. Their <lb/>grounds are examined below. <lb/>3.1. The relevance of the location of a subsidiary combined with the principle of <lb/>economic unity <lb/>According to the current Article 7(5) of the Regulation 1215/2012, a person <lb/>domiciled in a Member State can be sued in another Member State, where a branch, an <lb/>agency or another establishment is situated, as regards a dispute arising out of its <lb/>operations. Despite the necessity of a strict interpretation of the special rules, the <lb/>definition of branch, agency or establishment is quite wide, since it encompasses every <lb/>&quot;centre of operations which has the appearance of permanency, such as the extension of <lb/>a parent body. It must have a management and be materially equipped to negotiate <lb/>business with third parties, so that they do not have to deal directly with the parent <lb/>body&quot; 21 . Therefore, the legal status or personality of the branch is irrelevant, provided <lb/>that it is permanent, it appears connected with the parent company and can deal with third <lb/>parties in its place. <lb/>The only (very reasonable) limit lies in the fact that the claim shall be based on acts <lb/>performed by the branch, or commitments assumed in the name and in the interest of the <lb/>parent company that shall be implemented in the State where the branch is situated 22 . <lb/>Both the black letter formulation of the rule and its teleological interpretation, seeking <lb/>sound administration of justice and procedural economy, come out on the side of this <lb/>necessary connection between the claim and the branch&apos;s activity. <lb/>This connection plays an important role in EU Competition Law thanks to the well-<lb/>established principle of economic unity. As regards private enforcement, in its Sumal <lb/>judgment 23 the CJEU recalled that EU Competition Law targets the activities of <lb/>undertakings, focussing on their conducts on the market. The formal separation between <lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>21 Court of Justice, Third Chamber, CNP spółka z ograniczoną odpowiedzialnością, cit., par. 52. In the <lb/>same sense: Court of Justice, Grand Chamber, judgment of 19 July 2012, Mahamdia, case C-154/11, par. <lb/>48; Court of Justice, Second Chamber, judgment of 5 July 2018, flyLAL, case C-27/17, par. 59; Court of <lb/>Justice, Third Chamber, judgment of 11 April 2019, Ryanair, case C-464/18, par. 33. <lb/>22 It follows that a claim on the ownership of business premises where an undertaking carries out activities <lb/>is excluded from the scope of application of the rule (Court of Justice, Sixth Chamber, order of 19 July <lb/>2019, INA, case C-200/19). Moreover, the mere existence of a subsidiary is irrelevant, if it has not had any <lb/>role in the conclusion and in the implementation of the claimed contract (Court of Justice, Second Chamber, <lb/>Ryanair, cit.). <lb/>23 Court of Justice, Grand Chamber, judgment of 6 October 2021, Sumal, case C-882/19. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>117 <lb/></page>

<body>companies, the legal status and their different legal personalities do not preclude unity <lb/>and unicity of market behaviours 24 as well as pursuing unitary specific economic aims. <lb/>When an economic unit is detected, it is liable for the infringement of EU Competition <lb/>Law, according to the principle of personal responsibility. This principle applies <lb/>regardless to the fact that the infringer was the parent company or the subsidiary: indeed, <lb/>it entails the application of joint and several liability amongst the entities of which the <lb/>economic unit is made up at the time that the infringement was committed 25 . According <lb/>to the recent decision in Athenian Brewery, the presumption is rebuttable, but firm <lb/>evidence must be given. <lb/>Since this unit leads to undistinguishable behaviours on the market, liability can also <lb/>be recognised to the subsidiary due to acts of the parent company. In this case, since the <lb/>organisation of groups of companies can be very different from one group to another, and <lb/>quite complicated, the liability of the subsidiary cannot be invoked automatically: the <lb/>claimant must prove &quot;the existence of a specific link between the economic activity of <lb/>that subsidiary and the subject matter of the infringement for which the parent company <lb/>was held to be responsible&quot; 26 . <lb/>These conditions being satisfied, the claimant can choose between suing the parent <lb/>company or the subsidiary for the infringement of Article 101 of the TFEU, making use, <lb/>whether the case might be, of the alternative ground of jurisdiction provided for by Article <lb/>7(5) of the Regulation 1215/2012. This solution has been expressly confirmed in the case <lb/>flyLAL II, concerning the private enforcement of Article 102 of the TFEU, provided that <lb/>the subsidiary had participated effectively to the antitrust conduct. This condition seems <lb/>perfectly consonant with the case law briefly mentioned, that requires a factual link <lb/>between the activities of the parent company and of the branch even within the economic <lb/>unit. The same solution can be extended, for the same reasoning, to the enforcement of <lb/>Article 101, with regard to all undertakings or groups of companies participating to the <lb/>collusive conduct 27 . <lb/>The combination of the principle of economic unity and the alternative ground of <lb/>jurisdiction in Article 7(5) of the Regulation 1215/2012 has a multiplier effect in terms <lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>24 Court of Justice, judgment of 14 July 1972, Imperial Chemical Industries v. Commission, case 48/69, <lb/>par. 140; Court of Justice, Third Chamber, judgment of 14 December 2006, Confederación Española de <lb/>Empresarios de Estaciones de Servicio, case C-217/05, par. 41; Court of Justice, Third Chamber, judgment <lb/>of 10 September 2009, Akzo Nobel and others v. Commission, case C-97/08 P, parr. 54 and 55; Court of <lb/>Justice, Second Chamber, judgment of 1 July 2010, Knauf Gips v. Commission, case C-407/08 P, parr. 84 <lb/>and 86; Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, judgment of 27 April 2017, Akzo Nobel and others v. Commission, <lb/>case C-516/15 P, parr. 47 and 48. <lb/>25 Court of Justice, First Chamber, judgments of 26 January 2017, Villeroy &amp; Boch v. Commission, case C-<lb/>625/13 P; Court of Justice, Second Chamber, judgments of 25 November 2020, Commission v. GEA Group, <lb/>case C-823/18 P; Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, judgment of 13 February 2025, Athenian Brewery, case <lb/>C-393/23. <lb/>26 Court of Justice, Grand Chamber, Sumal, cit., par. 51. <lb/>27 The principle of economic unity cannot be interpreted so extensively as to allow the service of judicial <lb/>documents to the subsidiary, when the action is started against the parent company (Court of Justice, Fifth <lb/>Chamber, judgment of 11 July 2024, Volvo, case C-632/22). The claimant has the possibility to choose the <lb/>defendant and the competent court and must pursue proceedings accordingly, giving the defendant the <lb/>opportunity to defend through a personal service of documents instituting the claim. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>118 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>of potentially competent national courts, amplifying the choice in favour of the claimant. <lb/>This reduces the foreseeability of the competent court. As a counterpart for the <lb/>defendant(s), jurisdiction is granted to a court closely connected with the defendant, it <lb/>being the Member State where it is situated and where it operates. <lb/>3.2. Jurisdiction in respect of connected claims <lb/>This broad provision for alternative fora seems convenient for the victim also in light <lb/>of the rule on jurisdiction in respect of connected claims envisaged in Article 8(1) of the <lb/>Regulation 1215/2012 as a special ground of jurisdiction. It enables to sue multiple <lb/>defendants, domiciled in different Member States 28 , before the court of the domicile of <lb/>one of them. The claims against the defendants must be closely connected so that it is <lb/>expedient to hear them together in order to avoid future potentially irreconcilable <lb/>judgments. The connection is helpful especially when the causes of action against the co-<lb/>defendants are not the same, but intertwined. A meaningful example could be the <lb/>possibility to sue the parent company as anchor defendant before the court of its domicile, <lb/>when the presumption of economic unity is rebutted; or the action of the indirect victim <lb/>before the same judge against all undertakings located in the value chain 29 , in case of <lb/>partial passing on of the damage 30 . <lb/>The case against the anchor defendant must be real and effective 31 . This does not <lb/>preclude the assessment of jurisdiction if the claimant renounces to the case against it, <lb/>provided that this mechanism is not abusive 32 . This rule has been confirmed in the field <lb/>of competition law 33 , too. <lb/>4. The infringement of EU Competition Law as matters (mainly) relating to tort, <lb/>delict or quasi-delict <lb/>Within the scope of Article 7 of the Brussels Ibis Regulation, a doubt may arise on <lb/>the characterisation of private enforcement of EU Competition Law as a contractual <lb/>matter, thus calling to the application of Article 7(1), or as a tort or delict, according to <lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>28 Some EU Member States&apos; law offer wider connection possibility, that allows to sue co-defendants <lb/>wherever domiciled. This opportunity has proved useful in some climate change cases, such as the Hague <lb/>District Court, judgment of 26 May 2021, Mileudefensie v. Shell. In Competition Law, this rule would be <lb/>useful too. Indeed, EU Competition Law covers all misconduct that produces effects in the internal market <lb/>despite the seat of the tortfeasor (Court of Justice, judgment of 25 November 1971, Béguelin, case 22/71). <lb/>Therefore, it could be convenient to join all claims against all cartels&apos; participants before one national court <lb/>for the same infringement of EU Competition Law. <lb/>29 S. SMITH, The Indirect Purchaser Rule and Private Enforcement of Antitrust Law: A Reassessment, in <lb/>Journal of competition law &amp; economics, 2021, pp. 642-685. <lb/>30 EU Commission, Study on the Passing-on of Overcharges, 2016, final report. <lb/>31 Jurisdiction must be confirmed even if the case against the anchor defendant is inadmissible: Court of <lb/>Justice, Second Chamber, judgment of 13 July 2006, Reisch Montage, case C-103/05. <lb/>32 Court of Justice, Third Chamber, judgment of 11 October 2011, Freeport, case C-98/06. <lb/>33 Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, judgment of 21 May 2015, CDC, case C-352/13. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>119 <lb/></page>

<body>Article 7(2) 34 . Indeed, two sorts of legal relationships are likely to arise in the domain <lb/>concerned: the relationships between the parties to an agreement resulting in a restriction <lb/>of competition, which by their very nature are normally contractual, and the relationships <lb/>between the said parties, or any of them, and third parties. Despite these possible legal <lb/>relationships and consequent claims, many relevant factors lead to the conclusion that all <lb/>these claims are tortious. Firstly, in the flyLAL I case 35 , the CJEU referred directly to <lb/>Article 5(3) of the Regulation 44/2001 36 , the immediate predecessor of Article 7(2) of the <lb/>Regulation 1215/2012, even if the request for a preliminary ruling did not even mention <lb/>this rule or the problem of characterisation of the claim. The Court at para. 28 of its <lb/>judgment clearly stated that damages actions for the infringement of EU Competition <lb/>Law amount to torts or delicts. Secondly, current CJEU&apos;s case law mainly interprets <lb/>Article 7(2) of the Regulation 1215/2012 in damages actions 37 without even mentioning <lb/>Article 7(1). Lastly, the existence of a special rule in the Rome II Regulation 38 seems to <lb/>definitively characterise these claims as non-contractual. However, some other clues <lb/>point to a different conclusion, so that a small set of claims can have contractual nature. <lb/>In order to characterize cross border private enforcement of EU Competition law, it <lb/>is important to recall briefly that, according to the well-established CJEU&apos;s case law on <lb/>the former Article 5(1) and (3) of the Regulation 44/2001, special jurisdictions are an <lb/>exception to the general provision of the domicile of the defendant. Therefore, they must <lb/>be interpreted restrictively 39 . The contractual liability rests on the existence of an <lb/>obligation freely assumed by one party towards another. The non-contractual liability has <lb/>a residual definition and covers those cases where liability is invoked if this freely <lb/>assumed obligation does not exist 40 . <lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>34 G. VAN CALSTER, The EU Rules on Jurisdiction for and the Law Applicable to, Follow-on, and Stand-<lb/>alone Damages Following Competition Infringement, in Journal of European comparative law and <lb/>practice, 2020, p. 153. <lb/>35 Court of Justice, Third Chamber, judgment of 23 October 2014, flyLAL I, case C-302/13. <lb/>36 Council Regulation (EC) 44/2001, on jurisdiction and the recognition and enforcement of judgments in <lb/>civil and commercial matters, of 22 December 2000, in OJ L12, 16 January 2001, pp. 1-23. <lb/>37 Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, CDC, cit.; Court of Justice, Sixth Chamber, judgment of 29 July 2019, <lb/>Tibor Trans, case C-451/18. <lb/>38 The CJEU call for a parallel interpretation of the Regulations on jurisdiction and on applicable law (see, <lb/>for example, Court of Justice, Eight Chamber, judgment of 10 February 2022, UE, case C-595/20), with <lb/>limited exceptions (the most remarkable is Court of Justice, Fourth Chamber, judgment of 16 January 2014, <lb/>Kainz, case C-45/13, where the CJEU did not interpret Article 5(3) of the Regulation 44/2001 according to <lb/>Article 5 of the Regulation 864/2007, since it would have been &quot; unconnected to the scheme and objectives <lb/>pursued by that regulation&quot;, par. 20). Further: E. LEIN, La nouvelle synergie Rome I/ Rome II/ Bruxelles I, <lb/>in Yearbook of Private International Law, 2008, pp. 27-48; E.B. CRAWFORD, J. M. CARRUTHERS, <lb/>Connection and Coherence between and Among European Instruments in the Private International Law of <lb/>Obligations, in The International and Comparative Law Quarterly, 2014, pp. 1-29. <lb/>39 Court of Justice, judgment of 19 September 1995, Marinari, case 364/93; Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, <lb/>judgment of 27 September 1988, Kalfelis, case 189/87; Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, judgment of 15 <lb/>January 2004, Blijdenstein, case C-433/01; Court of Justice, Second Chamber, judgment of 10 June 2004, <lb/>Kronhofer, case C-168/02. <lb/>40 Recently: D. MARTINY, Coordination of contractual and tort claims in the European law of jurisdiction, <lb/>in Cuadernos de derecho transnacional, 2024, n. 2, pp. 1099-1113. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>120 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>In EU Competition Law cases, a contract can indeed exist, among tortfeasors, or <lb/>between a wrongdoer and a supplier or customer, or between parties in the distribution or <lb/>value chain. Still, it needs to be scrutinised whether this fact is meaningful in terms of <lb/>characterisation. The Apple case is relevant because it is the only judgment in which the <lb/>Court had to reason expressly on the relationships between an existing contract and an <lb/>infringement of EU Competition Law. Following the CJUE&apos;s reasoning, the main point <lb/>here is that this violation had no repercussions on the interpretation, the effects, the <lb/>implementation of a contract: allegedly, it only reduced the business of one of the <lb/>parties 41 . Therefore, the contract seems to be irrelevant: the commercial loss was likely <lb/>to be suffered regardless of the contractual relationship due to the allegedly abusive <lb/>distribution chain created and exploited by the tortfeasor. <lb/>The same irrelevance of a contract between the parties appears in Volvo. Here the <lb/>applicant was a customer of one of the companies, that was party to an antitrust <lb/>agreement, suffering the unfair consequences deriving from the original restriction of <lb/>competition. It seized multiple co-defendants for damages resulting from a collusive <lb/>agreement. One of them was its direct seller. Despite the contractual relationship between <lb/>the claimant and one of the defendants, this contract of purchase did not affect the <lb/>applicability of Article 7(2) of the Brussels Ibis Regulation: it was not even mentioned in <lb/>the grounds of the judgment. <lb/>Yet, a distinction has been drawn in Wikingerhof 42 . It lies on the grounds of the claim. <lb/>If it is based on the implementation or on the interpretation of a contract, the claim shall <lb/>be contractual. If it is grounded on the infringement of the (EU Competition) Law, it <lb/>constitutes a delict. Therefore, according to the CJEU, a claim based on Article 102 of <lb/>the TFEU is tortious, because the contract between the parties is the tool for the realisation <lb/>of the anticompetitive infringement 43 : the contract is based on terms imposed by the <lb/>stronger party as a consequence of its decision to exploit its dominant position and <lb/>constitute the performance of the abuse. This conclusion explains better the Apple case, <lb/>too. <lb/>Also in Amazon 44 , although on the use of unfair commercial terms, the CJEU draws <lb/>a very (too?) subtle distinction between the use and the assessment of a particular <lb/>contractual term, the former being tortious, the latter contractual. <lb/>This distinction seems the clarification of the CJEU&apos;s case law on Article 5(1) and <lb/>(3) of the Regulation 44/2001 for the purposes of cross border private enforcement of EU <lb/>Competition Law. It mirrors, too, the black letter formulation of Article 6(3) of the Rome <lb/>II Regulation, that expressly refers to non-contractual obligations, taking from granted <lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>41 The applicant, a distributor who concluded a distribution agreement with Apple, claimed that the <lb/>defendant abused its dominant position while preferring its own chain of distribution, thus jeopardising its <lb/>business. <lb/>42 Court of Justice, Grand Chamber, judgment of 24 November 2020, case C-59/19, Wikingerhof. <lb/>43 W. WURMNEST, Plotting the boundary between contract and tort jurisdiction in private actions against <lb/>abuses of dominance: Wikingerhof v. Booking, in Common Market Law Review, 2021, p. 1581. <lb/>44 Court of Justice, Third Chamber, judgment of 28 July 2016, Amazon, case C-191/15. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>121 <lb/></page>

<body>the existence of contractual obligations arising out of the infringement of EU Competition <lb/>Law. <lb/>Therefore, the main point is to verify when infringements of EU Competition Law <lb/>can have contractual nature. The cause of action must focus on the interpretation or on <lb/>the implementation of the contract as such, regardless the infringement of EU <lb/>Competition Law and its consequences on the sphere of the applicant. This is a contractual <lb/>matter, because the claim is focussed on the contract itself and not on other possible legal <lb/>relationships between the parties or on other infringements. The restriction of competition <lb/>must be caused by an agreement between the parties, which is disputed. Therefore, it <lb/>seems to be exactly the Courage case, the judgment that gave official birth to the private <lb/>enforcement of EU Competition Law 45 : a claim on the full enforcement 46 of the contract <lb/>binding the applicant and the defendant where the contract itself is a collusive agreement. <lb/>Therefore, the contractual nature seems truly residual with respect to the tortious <lb/>characterisation: one of the tortfeasors must challenge the antitrust agreement. <lb/>5. The identification of the place of the harmful event <lb/>This characterisation as tort causes the well-known problem in the application of <lb/>Article 7(2) of the Regulation 1215/2012, that is the localisation of the harmful event. <lb/>Due to the simultaneous relevance of the places of the causal event and of the harm 47 , <lb/>even if located in more than one Member State 48 , this rule can attribute alternative <lb/>jurisdiction to a multiplicity of different national courts. This is a general principle in the <lb/>interpretation of the rule 49 . In EU Competition Law, there is a natural risk of proliferation <lb/>of competent forums. In cartel cases, the conduct requires the action of two or more <lb/>undertakings, that could have their legal seats and centres of interests and of business in <lb/>more than one Member State. Furthermore, according to arts. 101 and 102 of the TFEU, <lb/>the conduct must be detrimental to the internal market and affect trade between Member <lb/>States, so that losses can be suffered in more than one Member State. Although anti-<lb/>competitive conduct can hardly be detrimental in all Member States, it has by nature the <lb/>potential to affect more than just one national market 50 . This first impact harm is followed <lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>45 Court of Justice, judgment of 20 September 2001, Courage, case C-453/99. In the same sense: M. <lb/>HELLNER, Unfair Competition and Acts Restricting Free Competition. A Commentary on Article 6 of the <lb/>Rome II Regulation, in Yearbook of Private International Law, 2007, p. 66. <lb/>46 Or, on the opposite, on nullity: M. FALLON, S. FRANCQ, Private Enforcement of Antitrust Provisions and <lb/>the Rome I Regulation, in J. BASEDOW, S. FRANCQ, L. IDOT (eds.), International Antitrust Litigation, Oxford <lb/>and Portland, 2012, p. 83. <lb/>47 Court of Justice, judgment of 30 November 1976, Bier, case 21/76. <lb/>48 Court of Justice, judgment of 7 March 1995, Shevill, case C-68/93. <lb/>49 P. MANKOWSKI, Art. 7, in U. MAGNUS, P. MANKOWSKI (eds.), European Commentaries on Private <lb/>International Law, Brussels Ibis Regulation, vol. I, Köln, 2023, p. 260. <lb/>50 P. MANKOWSKI, Article 7, in U. MAGNUS, P. MANKOWSKI (eds.), European Commentaries on Private <lb/>International Law, Brussels Ibis Regulation, vol. I, Köln, 2016, p. 333. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>122 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>by individual damage to companies in the relevant market 51 , i.e. specific damage, <lb/>consisting of, for example, economic or commercial loss, loss of customers, orders or <lb/>profits, and, following the causal chain, increasingly more specific injuries suffered by <lb/>the buyers of these companies, by the whole value chain, up to the consumers. Taking <lb/>into account the entire chain of production, distribution and sale, damages and losses are <lb/>to be found everywhere. <lb/>The CJEU&apos;s case law actualised these places for some kinds of torts 52 , granting more <lb/>legal certainty in its application. This pattern is developing in recent years in private <lb/>enforcement of EU Competition Law, too, so that it can be distinguished from other torts, <lb/>although not all main issues have already been dealt with, nor all solutions can be <lb/>considered optimal. <lb/>5.1. The place of the causal event <lb/>The event giving rise to damage is composed by two parts: the decision (to take the <lb/>anticompetitive conduct) and its implementation. According to the flyLAL II judgment, <lb/>both are relevant in the establishment of the jurisdiction to decide on the whole loss <lb/>suffered by the victim 53 . At the same time, both are difficult to localise univocally. Indeed, <lb/>in Tibor Trans the CJEU stated that none of the anticompetitive agreements took place in <lb/>the State of the seized court, this meaning that all agreements -and all decisions, could <lb/>operate as localising elements establishing jurisdiction. If the undertakings met and <lb/>concluded several antitrust agreements in different Member States, the place of the casual <lb/>event is manifold 54 . These places can be easily decided by the undertakings for abusive <lb/>purposes 55 . The globalisation of this place is evident if the contracts among undertakings <lb/>were all or mainly at distance. In the worst cases, there is no agreement 56 . <lb/>A partial limitation to multiplicity is set in the CDC case, since only the final <lb/>agreement, or whether the case may be, the agreement in particular that is identifiable as <lb/>the sole causal event should be considered. This specification does not really help for the <lb/>localisation for distance contacts only. However, it seems to deprive of importance open-<lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>51 Communication from the Commission, Commission Notice on the definition of the relevant market for <lb/>the purposes of Union competition law (C/2024/1645), in OJ 22 February 2024, pp. 1-35. <lb/>52 E. LEIN, Special Jurisdiction, in A. DICKINSON, E. LEIN (eds.), The Brussels I Regulation Recast, Oxford, <lb/>2015, p. 156. <lb/>53 Court of Justice, Grand Chamber, judgment of 25 October 2011, eDate, joined cases C-509/09 and C-<lb/>161/10. <lb/>54 M. BECKER, Kartelldeliktsrecht: § 826 BGB als &quot;Zuständigkeitshebel&quot; im Anwendungsbereich der <lb/>EuGVO?, in Europäisches Wirtschafts-und Steuerrecht, 2008, p. 230; J. BASEDOW, Der Handlungsort im <lb/>internationalen Kartellrecht, in FIW FORSCHUNGSINSTITUT FÜR WIRTSCHAFTSVERFASSUNG (hrsg.), <lb/>Wettbewerbspolitik und Kartellrecht in der Marktwirtschaft, 50 Jahre FIW 1960-2010, Köln, 2010, pp. <lb/>129-142; E. LEIN, Special Jurisdiction, cit., p. 164. Therefore, the place of the conduct should be set aside, <lb/>or considered secondary: S. BARIATTI, Problemi di giurisdizione e di diritto internazionale privato <lb/>nell&apos;azione antitrust, in L.F. PACE (a cura di), Dizionario sistematico del diritto della concorrenza, Napoli, <lb/>2013, p. 269. <lb/>55 P. MANKOWSKI, Article 7, cit., 2016, p. 300. <lb/>56 L. IDOT, Précisions, cit., p. 64. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>123 <lb/></page>

<body>ended meetings, or agreements, or changes to previous agreements, or new agreements, <lb/>concluded by the same parties but that do not affect directly or indirectly the claimant. <lb/>The assessment of jurisdiction shall consider the specific allegations of the victim and the <lb/>claimed anticompetitive behaviour. <lb/>The identification of the conduct giving rise to damage can be easier in order to <lb/>determine the place where the relevant decision was taken in case of infringement of <lb/>Article 102 of the TFEU 57 . Being the tortfeasor one undertaking only, its domicile, in the <lb/>threefold sense of Article 63 of the Regulation 1215/2012, seems the proper place where <lb/>decisions are taken. <lb/>For both infringements, the place of the implementation of the decision tends to <lb/>coincide with the place of damage, due to the relevance of the affected market, that is, at <lb/>the origin, the Member State where the anticompetitive conduct took place, as discussed <lb/>below. <lb/>5.2. The place of the damage <lb/>The mosaic principle 58 has a potential multiplier effect on the number of possible <lb/>courts having jurisdiction due both to the definition of the anticompetitive conducts and <lb/>the EU market&apos;s freedoms. Furthermore, the notion of victim of an infringement of EU <lb/>Competition Law is very broad 59 . In a wide approach, the harm could be the price increase <lb/>of goods, paid by a single consumer domiciled in a Member State, where only one product <lb/>has been sold. <lb/>The CJEU&apos;s case law limits these potentially extreme interpretations for the purposes <lb/>of civil judicial cooperation. <lb/>Firstly, the injury should be a direct consequence of the causal event 60 . Indirect <lb/>damages cannot be held for grounds of jurisdiction 61 . Therefore, the indirect victim <lb/>cannot sue before the court of the place where he/she suffered damage 62 , since the passed-<lb/>on damage is by definition an indirect damage 63 . Neither the parent company can ground <lb/>jurisdiction on its domicile, as the place of damage, when claiming for losses suffered by <lb/>its subsidiaries domiciled elsewhere 64 . <lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>57 L. IDOT, Contentieux international des actions en réparation pour violation du droit de la concurrence: <lb/>l&apos;arrêt CDC revisité, in Revue critique de droit international privé, 2019, p. 804. <lb/>58 The mosaic principle was developed by the CJEU for the purposes of jurisdiction in respect of violations <lb/>of privacy or personality rights (Court of Justice, Shevill, cit.; Court of Justice, Grand Chamber, eDate, cit.; <lb/>Court of Justice, Grand Chamber, judgment of 21 December 2021, Gtflix Tv, case C-251/20). <lb/>59 Court of Justice, Courage, cit.; Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, judgment of 5 June 2014, Kone and <lb/>others, case C-557/12; Court of Justice, Second Chamber, Skanska Industrial Solutions and others, cit.; <lb/>Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, judgment of 12 December 2019, OTIS, case C-435/18. <lb/>60 Court of Justice, First Chamber, judgment of 16 July 2009, Zuid-Chemie, case C-189/08, par. 27. <lb/>61 Court of Justice, Sixth Chamber, judgment of 11 January 1990, Dumez, case C-220/88. <lb/>62 M. REQUEJO ISIDRO, E. WAGNER, M. GARGANTINI, Article 7, in M. REQUEJO ISIDRO (ed.), Brussels Ibis, <lb/>a Commentary on Regulation (EU) No 1215/2012, Cheltenham, 2022, p. 115. <lb/>63 P. MANKOWSKI, Article 7, cit., 2023, p. 292. <lb/>64 Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, judgment of 4 July 2024, MOL, case C-425/22. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>124 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>Secondly, purely financial losses cannot be considered relevant 65 . In general, this <lb/>depends on the first limit, since an economic loss is frequently a secondary consequence, <lb/>a follow up to a first-impact harm. Furthermore, the place of this loss usually coincides <lb/>with the domicile of the victim, and a forum actoris cannot be accepted outside the limited <lb/>hypothesis expressly established by the Regulation, such as the consumers&apos; contracts 66 . <lb/>Indeed, Article 7(2) does not intend to protect the victim as a weak party 67 and an almost <lb/>unconditioned forum actoris would not be desirable 68 . <lb/>Finally, and for the same reason, the rule is not conditional upon the targeting or to <lb/>addressing the companies&apos; activities in one Member State (where the victim&apos;s interests <lb/>were jeopardised) 69 . Indeed, Article 7(2) aims to grant proximity and predictability 70 , thus <lb/>setting aside different purposes that could be realised through a materially-oriented <lb/>private international law 71 . <lb/>These specifications only serve the purpose not to extend indefinitely the places of <lb/>the injuries and thus the courts potentially retaining jurisdiction, but do not help in an <lb/>unequivocal determination of jurisdiction. <lb/>Yet the same principle of specificity, already applied in the determination of the place <lb/>of the causal event, can be adapted to the identification of a unique place of the harm, or <lb/>at least in a reasonable alternative between a reduced number of courts 72 . This pragmatism <lb/>is clear in the flyLAL II case, where the rationale in the interpretation of the place of the <lb/>injury is focussed on the case at stake 73 . More clearly, in Tibor Trans the localisation of <lb/>the harm depends on the combination of the affected market that shall coincide with the <lb/>place where the victim claims to have suffered damage. The direct harm is suffered in the <lb/></body>
        
        <listBibl>65 For example, the Court of Justice, First Chamber, judgment of 9 July 2020, Verein für <lb/>Konsumenteninformation, case C-343/19 did not consider relevant the financial loss of the consumer, buyer <lb/>of a vehicle with defective devices. Indeed, the damage is the purchase of car that does not have the <lb/>advertised environmentally friendly features, and the financial loss (in the bank account of the consumer) <lb/>is derivative only. <lb/>66 H. RÖSLER, Protection of the Weaker Party in European Contract Law: Standardized and Individual <lb/>Inferiority in Multi-level Private Law, in European Review of Private Law, 2010, pp. 729-756; V. VAN DEN <lb/>EECKHOUT, Private International Law in an Era of Globalisation. &apos;Neutral&apos; Private International Law!? <lb/>An Analysis Through the Lens of Protection of Weak c.q. Vulnerable Parties, 2020, available at SSRN: <lb/>https://ssrn.com/abstract=3677937. <lb/>67 L. MARI, Il diritto processuale civile della Convenzione di Bruxelles I, Il sistema della competenza, <lb/>Padova, 1999, p. 389; S.M. CARBONE, C. TUO, Il nuovo spazio giudiziario europeo in materia civile e <lb/>commerciale, Torino, 2016, p. 135; according to M. REQUEJO ISIDRO, E. WAGNER, M. GARGANTINI, Article <lb/>7, cit., p. 111 the decisions on online defamation challenge this assumption. <lb/>68 P. MANKOWSKI, Article 7, cit., 2023, p. 290. <lb/>69 P. MANKOWSKI, Article 7, cit., 2023, p. 260. <lb/>70 This was expressly stated already in the Bier judgment, par. 21. <lb/>71 P. PICONE, Les méthodes de coordination entre ordres juridiques en droit international privé, Cours <lb/>général de droit international privé, in Recueil des cours de l&apos;Académie de La Haye, 1999, Volume 276, <lb/>pp. 9 ff. <lb/>72 J. BASEDOW, International Cartels and the Place of Acting under Article 5(3) of the Brussels Regulation, <lb/>in J. BASEDOW, S. FRANCQ, L. IDOT (eds.), op. cit., p. 33; M. BECKER, Kartelldeliktsrecht, cit., p. 231. <lb/>73 See also Cour de Cassation, Civ. 1 ere , 1 February 2012, in Revue critique de droit international privé, <lb/>2013, p. 464. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>125 <lb/></page>

<body>affected market 74 , where a distortion of competition took place 75 , according to the <lb/>victim&apos;s allegation. It is of no importance if the same conduct caused losses to other <lb/>victims, in other States or affected markets. <lb/>Therefore, the localisation shall not depend on the general impact of the antitrust <lb/>conduct on the internal market, but rather on the specifically affected market where the <lb/>victim complains losses. This is all the truer since the court of the place of the injury has <lb/>jurisdiction to decide on the loss suffered in the Member State where it sits, and other <lb/>prejudices become irrelevant for the purposes of those specific proceedings. <lb/>The place of the injury can be localised where the market conditions were distorted <lb/>and in which the victim claims to have suffered that damage, that is the affected market, <lb/>to the extent that the claimant operated in that market. In an extreme perspective, neither <lb/>the tortfeasors, nor the victim might have the domicile, or a subsidiary, in that State. This <lb/>definition is consistent with the aims of the enforcement of EU Competition Law, as rules <lb/>that are considered EU system&apos;s pillars 76 , while the protection of individual interests plays <lb/>a subordinated role. <lb/>Furthermore, this interpretation would help limiting the fragmentation and the <lb/>potential globalisation of the ground of jurisdiction. <lb/>This approach reduces difficulties and sensitiveness in the localisation, because the <lb/>claimant bears the responsibility to identify the markets where it suffered damage 77 . The <lb/>absolute globalisation exists, in fact, only if tortfeasors and victims are multinational <lb/>corporations organised in groups of companies, forming an economic unit, with a strong <lb/>value chain. In these cases, parcelling out the harm might have a reduced convenience <lb/>and the identification of the proper place of the damage seems almost meaningless. <lb/></body>
          
        <listBibl>74 The German literature has been focussing on the Marktortprinzip as the place of the direct harm, even <lb/>before the outbreak of the CJEU&apos;s case law; see, for example: H. I. MAIER, Marktortanknüpfung im <lb/>internationalen Kartelldeliktsrecht, Frankfurt am Main, 2011; W. WURMNEST, Internationale <lb/>Zuständigkeit und anwendbares Recht bei grenzüberschreitenden Kartelldelickte, in Europäische <lb/>Zeitschrift Für Wirtschaftsrecht, 2012, p. 934. More recently: A. STADLER, Schadensersatzklagen im <lb/>Kartellrecht -Forum shopping welcome! Zugleich Besprechungvon EuGH, Urteil v. 21.5.2015 -C-352/13, <lb/>in JuristenZeitung, 2015, pp. 1138-1149; B. SCRABACK, Marktortanknüpfung bei Kartellen?, in Zeitschrift <lb/>für das Privatrecht der Europäischen Union, 2019, n. 2, p. 69; H. MEYLE, Rethinking &quot;the place of the <lb/>damage rule&quot; in private international law, in Yearbook of Private International Law, 2020/2021, p. 505; <lb/>for further remarks on German literature and reactions to the CJEU&apos;s case law: R. MONICO, La giurisdizione <lb/>in materia extracontrattuale nello spazio giudiziario europeo, Torino, 2022, p. 250. <lb/>75 Therefore, the violation of EU Competition Law does not cause purely economic losses. These torts <lb/>continue challenging the case law (Court of Justice, Marinari, cit.; Court of Justice, Second Chamber, <lb/>judgment of 16 July 2016, Universal Music International Holding, case C-12/15; further: T. HARTLEY, <lb/>Jurisdiction in tort claims for non-physical harm under Brussels 2012, Article 7(2), in International and <lb/>Comparative Law Quarterly, 2018, pp. 987-1003). <lb/>76 Court of Justice, judgment of 1 June 1999, Eco Swiss, case C-126/97. <lb/>77 A mere prima facie evidence is satisfactory, because it is not possible to fully instruct the case for the <lb/>sole purpose of the establishment of jurisdiction (Court of Justice, Fourth Chamber, judgment of 28 January <lb/>2015, Kolassa, case C-375/13, paras. 61-63; Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, Athenian Brewery, cit., par. <lb/>42). The court shall rely on the available uncontested facts (Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, judgment of 7 <lb/>April 2022, VA, case C-645/20, par. 42). Even if the court must consider all the elements at disposal (Court <lb/>of Justice, Second Chamber, Universal Music International Holding, cit., par. 45), the applicant does not <lb/>need to satisfy a disproportionate burden of the proof (Court of Justice, Fourth Chamber, judgment of 6 <lb/>July 2023, BM, case C-462/22, par. 37). <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>126 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>Therefore, from a practical perspective, the jurisdiction shall be better grounded on the <lb/>place of the causal event or on the general rule of the domicile of the defendant, in order <lb/>to avoid the need to split the damage, quantify it in the Member States of the seized courts <lb/>and possibly lodging complaints in more jurisdictions. <lb/>Following this approach, the localisation of the tort does not seem to be a nightmare 78 . <lb/>The problem arises because of three elements. Firstly, the fact that the same conduct can <lb/>generate harms in more Member States means that private enforcement actions can be <lb/>lodged in different courts, at the same time, by different claimants. This consequence <lb/>cannot be properly faced by the law, since risks inherent in the cross-border nature of an <lb/>activity are innate, when an undertaking does business in more States. Whether the case <lb/>might be, rules on lis alibi pendens or, most probably, related actions (arts. 29-34 of the <lb/>Brussels Ibis Regulation) are applicable 79 . <lb/>Secondly, the rule is applicable to actions for negative declarations 80 . In these <lb/>proceedings, the identification of any place related to the harmful event is extremely <lb/>difficult, since the applicant maintains that there is no harmful event. Therefore, the line <lb/>of reasoning risks being quite complicated, since we need to localise the place of the <lb/>direct damage, had any causal event occurred 81 . This place might not immediately <lb/>coincide with the domicile of the defendant, who might suffer only from indirect losses <lb/>in its domicile. However, these difficulties are typical features of all actions for negative <lb/>declarations: private enforcement of EU Competition Law does not seem to make them <lb/>even harder, at least in general. <lb/>Finally, unfortunately the CJEU&apos;s judgments in CDC risks creating confusion 82 . In <lb/>the interpretation of the place of damage, the Court stressed the relevance of the place <lb/>where the harm manifests itself, actualising it in the loss consisting in additional costs <lb/></body>
          
          <listBibl>78 Therefore, Article 7 of the Regulation 1215/2012 does not need a reform that considers expressly antitrust <lb/>claims (B. VILÀ COSTA, How to Apply Articles 5(1) and 5(3) Brussels I Regulation to Private Enforcement <lb/>of Competition Law. A Coherent Approach, in J. BASEDOW, S. FRANCQ, L. IDOT (eds.), op. cit., p. 19. <lb/>79 R. FENTIMAN, Introduction to Articles 29-30, in U. MAGNUS, P. MANKOWSKI (eds.), European <lb/>Commentaries on Private International Law, cit., 2023, p. 728 analyses whether a parent company and a <lb/>subsidiary can be considered the same economic entity for the purposes of lis alibi pendens. Being its <lb/>requirements quite strict, the only possibility would appear to be the exploitation of the principle of <lb/>economic unity. <lb/>80 Court of Justice, First Chamber, judgment of 25 October 2012, Folien Fischer, case C-133/11. <lb/>81 The best solution would be to assume the existence of a causal event and to identify the place where it <lb/>would have caused injuries. According to Bundesgerichtshof, judgment of 29 January 2013, KZR 8/10 <lb/>(BPatG), in Gewerblicher Rechtsschutz und Urheberrecht, Rechtsprechungs-Report, 2013, p. 228, if two <lb/>foreign companies compete in Germany, here can be found a place of the injury even for a negative <lb/>declaration. <lb/>82 O. GEISS, D. HOSRT, Cartel damage Claims (CDC) Hydrogen Peroxide SA v Akzo Nobel NV and Others: <lb/>A summary and critique of the judgment of the European Court of Justice of May 21, 2015, in European <lb/>Competition Law Review, 2015, p. 430; K. HAVU, Private Claims Based on EU Competition Law. <lb/>Jurisdictional Issues and Effective Enforcement Case C-352/13 CDC Hydrogen Peroxide, EU:C:2015:335, <lb/>in Maastricht Journal of European and Comparative Law, 2015, p. 879; A. STADLER, <lb/>Schadensersatzklagen im Kartellrecht -Forum shopping welcome! Zugleich Besprechung von EuGH, <lb/>Urteil v. 21.5.2015 -C-352/13, in JuristenZeitung, 2015, pp. 1138-1149; W. WURMNEST, International <lb/>jurisdiction in competition damages cases under the Brussels I Regulation: CDC Hydrogen Peroxide, in <lb/>Common Market Law Review, 2016, p. 225. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>127 <lb/></page>

<body>occurred due to artificially higher prices. Therefore, the place of the damage is located at <lb/>the victim&apos;s registered office. This conclusion creates a forum actoris, where a financial <lb/>loss is frequently suffered. It contradicts the above-mentioned established case law on <lb/>indirect financial losses, without considering the direct harm 83 . It also allows further <lb/>fragmentation, since even a body consolidating antitrust claims and representing the <lb/>interests of more victims shall file more claims, with the courts of the places of the <lb/>registered offices of each victim. <lb/>The place of the registered office lost momentum in the subsequent case law 84 . As <lb/>already made it clear above, although the CJEU keeps on referring to the place where the <lb/>victim suffered harm, this place is to be connected with an affected market. Therefore, <lb/>the focus is more on the market, and then on the effects of the behaviour on the victim. <lb/>The ground of jurisdiction of the affected market can lead to a forum actoris, as the cases <lb/>flyLAL very clearly demonstrate, but this is not an automatic nor necessary coincidence, <lb/>while the use of the registered office of the victim as ground of jurisdiction cannot but <lb/>lead to the domicile of the victim, by definition. <lb/>Furthermore, the CDC case cannot be considered as a general precedent, since the <lb/>claimant represented the interests of more victims. For this, it is not a standard victim -<lb/>wrongdoer(s) claim, in which the specificity of one single harm, although dispersed in <lb/>more States, must be analysed in quest of localisation. Nevertheless, its peculiarity was <lb/>not stressed in the rationale of the judgment 85 , if not in the limited part referring to the <lb/>different victims&apos; registered offices, in order to state that they all bear the same weight. <lb/>At best, this case shall be evaluated as a specific solution in peculiar actions, those lodged <lb/>by a claimant representing more victims. <lb/>5.3. Assessing collective interests <lb/>These last remarks do not mean that collective or representative actions do not have <lb/>standing in the private enforcement of EU Competition Law, but only that they cannot be <lb/>dealt with as being identical to direct claims between a victim and wrongdoer(s). EU Law <lb/>tries to develop collective actions, although Directive 2020/1828 86 does not apply to <lb/>private enforcement of EU Competition Law within the material scope of Directive <lb/></body>
          
          <listBibl>83 A. PATO, Collective redress for cartel damage claims in the European Union after CDC v Akzo NV and <lb/>others, in Yearbook of Private international Law, 2015/2016, p. 491; L. IDOT, Précisions, cit., p. 64; H. <lb/>MEYLE, Rethinking &quot;the place of the damage rule&quot;, cit., p. 484. <lb/>84 L. IDOT, Contentieux international, cit., p. 805; ID., Contentieux en réparation pour violation du droit de <lb/>la concurrence: de nouvelles précisions sur le lieu de matérialisation du dommage, in Revue critique de <lb/>droit international privé, 2020, p. 135; H. MEYLE, Rethinking &quot;the place of the damage rule&quot;, cit., p. 491; <lb/>L. RADEMACHER, Quieta movere -but please do not do it quietly: the ECJ on international jurisdiction in <lb/>antitrust damages actions (Tibor-Trans, C-451/18), in Cuadernos de derecho transnacional, 2020, n. 1, p. <lb/>677; M. REQUEJO ISIDRO, E. WAGNER, M. GARGANTINI, Article 7, cit., p. 129. <lb/>85 M. WELLER, J. WÄSCHLE, Kommentar, in Recht der Internationalen Wirtschaft, 2015, p. 603. <lb/>86 Directive (EU) 2020/1828 of the European Parliament and of the Council, on representative actions for <lb/>the protection of the collective interests of consumers and repealing Directive 2009/22/EC, of 25 November <lb/>2020, in OJ L409, 4 December 2020, pp. 1-27. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>128 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>2014/104. According to the principle of procedural autonomy 87 , Member States can <lb/>regulate collective or representative actions, outside the boundaries provided for by EU <lb/>Law. Requirements and conditions will therefore depend exclusively on national laws. <lb/>Article 7(2) applies to collective or representative actions. This is very clear already <lb/>from the Henkel case 88 . The CDC judgment is the only decision on these kinds of actions <lb/>in private enforcement of EU Competition Law. According to the CJEU, the transfer of <lb/>the claims by initial creditors cannot have an impact on the determination of the court <lb/>having jurisdiction under Article 7(2), which must be interpreted in the same way <lb/>regardless of the nature of the plaintiff. <lb/>Therefore, the identification of the place of the causal event follows the same path, <lb/>with the clarifications described above. Considering the place of the loss, the collective <lb/>or representative actor does not need to prove its specific or individual harm. <lb/>However, the analogous treatment of individual and collective actions does not <lb/>favour the latter. Indeed, the final outcome of the CDC judgment is that collective actions <lb/>must be considered a bundle of individual claims, for which the places of the injury must <lb/>be determined independently. Consequently, this ground of jurisdiction is de facto useless <lb/>or unusable, because it hinders the consolidation of claims before the court of the place <lb/>of the injury, unless all represented victims claim for a loss suffered in one State only -a <lb/>quite specific hypothesis. <lb/>The real possibilities for a collective or representative body to file a unique claim rest <lb/>therefore on the general jurisdiction according to Article 4 of the Brussels Ibis Regulation, <lb/>in combination with the special forum based on connected claims pursuant to its Article <lb/>8(1); or the place of the causal event, if unequivocally identified. The fact that the <lb/>collective entity represents undertakings&apos; or consumers&apos; interests do not seem to impact <lb/>on these remarks, since, according to the Henkel judgment, the claim is tortious and does <lb/>not involve any contractual relationship or obligation, and least of all a consumer contract. <lb/>6. The law applicable to acts restricting free competition <lb/>The characterisation of private enforcement of EU Competition Law as (mostly) <lb/>tortious is coherent with its purposes, too, which stem clear from art 6(3) of the Rome II <lb/>Regulation 89 . This special rule confirms that it is first and foremost concerned with free <lb/></body>
          
          <listBibl>87 D.-U. GALETTA, Procedural Autonomy of EU Member States: Paradise Lost?: A Study on the <lb/>&quot;Functionalized Procedural Competence&quot; of EU Member States, Berlin, Heidelberg, 2010; B. KRANS, A. <lb/>NYLUND (eds.), Aspects of Procedural Autonomy, Cambridge, 2020. <lb/>88 Court of Justice, Sixth Chamber, judgment of 1 October 2022, Henkel, case C-167/00. <lb/>89 The rule refers to non-contractual obligations arising out of a restriction of competition. This black letter <lb/>formulation leaves open the possibility of contractual claims, to be regulated according to Regulation (EC) <lb/>593/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council, on the law applicable to contractual obligations <lb/>(Rome I), of 17 June 2008, in OJ L177, 4 July 2008, pp. 6-16 (E. RODRIGUEZ PINEAU, Conflict of Laws <lb/>Comes to the Rescue of Competition Law: the New Rome II Regulation, in Journal of Private International <lb/>Law, 2009, p. 320), specially arts. 3, 4 and 6 (M. ILLMER, Article 6, in U. MAGNUS, P. MANKOWSKI (eds.), <lb/>Rome II Regulation -Commentary, Köln, 2019, p. 274). Following the CJEU&apos;s clarifications in <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>129 <lb/></page>

<body>and undistorted competition 90 , while the individual right has a secondary role. Indeed, the <lb/>rule is a specification of the general connecting factor of Article 4, the place of the direct <lb/>damage (recital 21 of the Regulation). It is actualised taking into consideration the <lb/>affected market, although with different shades related to the structures of the claims. The <lb/>prejudice to the market is the direct harm envisaged in Article 4, and all other losses are <lb/>mere consequences thereof, to be considered as indirect damages that are not meaningful <lb/>in order to determine the applicable law. The loss of the victim is not even mentioned in <lb/>Article 6(3) 91 . <lb/>The CJEU mentioned Article 6(3) of the Regulation 864/2007 in the interpretation of <lb/>Article 7(2) of the Regulation 1215/2012 92 , clearly transposing its objectives and values <lb/>into the rule on jurisdiction. <lb/>This approach is consistent with the well-known theory of the effects in EU <lb/>Competition Law 93 , that calls to its application to the extent that the anticompetitive <lb/>conduct produces effects within the internal market 94 , regardless to the seats of the <lb/>companies involved and of the place(s) of the conduct. EU Competition Law would thus <lb/>be applicable to an infringement, whether it was scrutinised under the public and/or the <lb/>private enforcement systems, since the outbreak of effects in the internal market lets it <lb/>fall into EU interests 95 . <lb/></body>
          
          <listBibl>Wikingerhof (see above, para. 4) contractual obligations arise only to the extent that the claimant seeks the <lb/>full and correct implementation of the contract. <lb/>90 C. HONORATI, The Law applicable to Unfair Competition, in A. MALATESTA (ed.), The Unification of <lb/>Choice of Law Rules in Torts and Other Non-Contractual Obligations in Europe, Padova, 2006, p. 151; P. <lb/>FRANZINA, Il regolamento n. 864/2007/CE sulla legge applicabile alle obbligazioni extracontrattuali <lb/>(«Roma II»), in Le nuove leggi civili commentate, 2008, p. 1008; E. RODRIGUEZ PINEAU, Conflict of Laws, <lb/>cit., p. 312; M. ILLMER, Article 6, cit., p. 272. <lb/>91 C. HONORATI, Regolamento n. 864/2007, cit., p. 534. This element must be stressed, because Article 6(1) <lb/>on unfair competition refers to the collective interests of the consumers, making clear the different values <lb/>protected by the rules. <lb/>92 Court of Justice, Second Chamber, flyLAL, cit., par. 41; Court of Justice, Sixth Chamber, Tibor Trans, <lb/>cit., par. 35; Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, Volvo, cit., par. 32; Court of Justice, Fifth Chamber, MOL, <lb/>cit., par. 40. <lb/>93 Notwithstanding some characterisation problems (T. ROSENKRANZ, E. ROHDE, The Law Applicable to <lb/>Non-contractual Obligations Arising out of Acts of Unfair Competition and Acts Restricting Free <lb/>Competition under Article 6 Rome II Regulation, in Nederlands Internationaal Privaatrecht, 2008, p. 436; <lb/>J. FITCHEN, Choice of Law in International Claims Based on Restrictions of Competition: Article 6(3) of <lb/>the Rome II Regulation, in Journal of Private International Law, 2009, p. 347; E. RODRIGUEZ PINEAU, <lb/>Conflict of Laws, cit., p. 319; M. ILLMER, Article 6, cit., p. 260; G. VAN CALSTER, The EU Rules on <lb/>Jurisdiction, cit., p. 154), infringements of Article 101 or 102 of the TFEU are surely included in the scope <lb/>of application of Article 6(3) (recital 23 of the Regulation). <lb/>94 Court of Justice, judgment of 30 June 1966, LTM-MBU, case 56/65; Court of Justice, judgment of 13 <lb/>July 1966, Costen and Grunding, joined cases 56 and 58/64; Court of Justice, judgment of 25 November <lb/>1971, Béguelin, case 22/71; Court of Justice, judgment of 14 July 1972, Imperial Chemical Industries Ltd. <lb/>v. Commission (ICI), case 48/69; Court of Justice, judgment of 21 February 1973, Europemballage <lb/>Corporation and Continetal Can Company Inc. v. Commission (Continental Can), case 6/72; Court of <lb/>Justice, judgment of 6 March 1974, Istituto Chemioterapeutico, joined cases 6 and 7/73. <lb/>95 This remark shall be combined with the partial harmonisation of the private enforcement of EU <lb/>Competition Law realised by the Directive 2014/104 in EU purely internal situations. Indeed, the relevant <lb/>applicable Competition Law is that of the EU Treaties; Member States&apos; national laws on damages actions <lb/>after infringement of Competition Law are consistent and coherent with the set of principles and rules <lb/>established by the Directive. It becomes apparent that conflict of laws issues is becoming less cutting with <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>130 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>The protection of competition is so important, that Article 6(4) excludes the <lb/>possibility of an agreement as to the applicable law: the connection with the law of the <lb/>affected market is mandatory for the (at least tentative) purpose to protect (the whole <lb/>internal) market and overshadows potentially different private interests (in the application <lb/>of another law, for whatever reasons) 96 . <lb/>6.1. The place of the damage: the affected market <lb/>Article 6(3) of the Rome II Regulation distinguishes two hypotheses. The first is the <lb/>general rule, that determines the applicable law as that of the State where the market is, <lb/>or is likely to be, affected (lit. (a)). It is thus confirmed that the provision is a specification <lb/>of Article 4 of the Regulation, because it is focussed on the direct harm. Indirect losses <lb/>are not relevant for the determination of the applicable law 97 . <lb/>Legal scholars discussed the meaning of the concept of affected market for the <lb/>purposes of determining the applicable law, especially in relationship with the notion of <lb/>market used in public enforcement of EU Competition Law 98 . The two meanings cannot <lb/>coincide because the rules containing them serve different purposes: in the former case, <lb/>to localise a tort in order to determine the applicable law; in the latter, to verify an <lb/>anticompetitive conduct. Therefore, in Article 6(3) the notion of affected market has only <lb/>a geographical facet, barely meaning a place where the harm was allegedly suffered. No <lb/>product market nor economic evaluations are necessary at this stage for two reasons. <lb/>Firstly, Article 6(3)(a) does not require a substantial injury, nor establishes any <lb/>quantitative threshold: therefore, the strict analysis of the impact of the conduct, the <lb/>products market and the quantification of the harm are useless at this stage. Secondly, it <lb/>does not require an excessive burden of the proof in order to establish a ground of <lb/>jurisdiction or a connecting factor. An accurate analysis of the elements of the <lb/>anticompetitive conducts, including the quantification of the harm, will take place at a <lb/>second stage 99 , while evaluating the elements of the non-contractual liability. <lb/></body>
          <listBibl>regards to private enforcement in EU cases (T. BALLARINO, L&apos;art. 6 del regolamento Roma II e il diritto <lb/>antitrust comunitario: conflitto di leggi e principio territorialistico, in Rivista di diritto internazionale, <lb/>2008, p. 74; M. ILLMER, Article 6, cit., p. 274). <lb/>96 P. FRANZINA, Il regolamento n. 864/2007/CE, cit., p. 1009; F. MARONGIU BUONAIUTI, Le obbligazioni <lb/>non contrattuali, cit., p. 129; J. FITCHEN, Choice of Law, cit., p. 344. In general: TH. M. DE BOER, Party <lb/>Autonomy and its Limitations in the Rome II Regulation, in Yearbook of Private International Law, 2007, <lb/>pp. 24-25. <lb/>97 Therefore, damages actions of indirect victims are governed by the law of the State of the affected market, <lb/>regardless of the place where they suffered from the loss. This solution is consistent with the determination <lb/>of jurisdiction. <lb/>98 M. HELLNER, Unfair Competition, cit., p. 59; T. ROSENKRANZ, E. ROHDE, The Law Applicable to Non-<lb/>contractual Obligations, cit., p. 437; J. FITCHEN, Choice of Law, cit., p. 360; S. FRANCQ, W. WURMNEST, <lb/>International Antitrust Claims under the Rome II Regulation, in J. BASEDOW, S. FRANCQ, L. IDOT (eds.), <lb/>op. cit., p. 120; M. ILLMER, Article 6, cit., p. 270; P. MANKOWSKI, Article 7, cit., 2023, p. 324. Despite the <lb/>different positions, the CJEU has not yet had the opportunity to interpret this notion. <lb/>99 In this, there might be differences whether the claim is a stand-alone or follow on action, since a decision <lb/>from a Competition Authority might help in the definition of the relevant market. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>131 <lb/></page>

<body>Article 6(3)(a) realises the so called Mosaikbetrachtung in multistate anticompetitive <lb/>conducts 100 , calling for the application of all the national laws of the States whose markets <lb/>are affected. The territorial principle thus embedded requires that each national law shall <lb/>apply to &quot;its&quot; national damages. This solution seems consistent with the CJEU&apos;s case law <lb/>on the jurisdiction of the court sitting in the place of the harm, which is limited to the <lb/>prejudices suffered therein. Consequently, if the case is fragmented in different actions <lb/>lodged with the courts of the places of the injuries, each court could apply its lex fori in <lb/>order to decide on the harms caused there. This coincidence between forum and ius can <lb/>ease the work of the judge. On the opposite, if the seized court has general jurisdiction, it <lb/>must apply different national laws to different parts of the harm. <lb/>The Mosaikbetrachtung bears different effects if applied in the determination of <lb/>jurisdiction or of the applicable law. In the former case, it means that the plaintiff has a <lb/>possibility to choose among different competent (although potentially limited) courts. <lb/>The seized court only needs to verify if it is one of the possibly competent courts 101 . In <lb/>the latter, fragmentation means alternativity or cumulation of the applicable laws, <lb/>according to the competence to decide granted to the seized court, without leaving any <lb/>choice to the claimant, nor to the court itself. <lb/>6.2. The substantially affected Member State&apos;s market <lb/>This fragmentation is partly overcome in multistate cases by Article 6(3)(b), that <lb/>concentrates the applicable law in coordination with the jurisdictional grounds 102 . It is <lb/>applicable if more than one country is affected, thus implicitly confirming that (a) does <lb/>not work perfectly well in multistate losses cases. Therefore, the Mosaikbetrachtung is <lb/>limited in those hypotheses where the risk of fragmentation is very high due to the <lb/>multiplicity of the places of injuries, and/or the number of co-defendants. For this effect, <lb/>(b) seems a useful rule for the concentration of the applicable law in collective actions 103 . <lb/>The rule envisages two cases. In the former, the victim sues in the court of the <lb/>domicile of the defendant. The court shall have general jurisdiction and each national loss <lb/>shall be governed by a different national law (cumulation). Nevertheless, the plaintiff can <lb/>choose to base the claim on the law of the State of the domicile of the defendant, if the <lb/>market of the Member State of the seized court is directly and substantially affected by <lb/>the anticompetitive conduct. This condition confirms that the Member State of the <lb/>domicile of the defendant may not correspond to any of the places of the injury. However, <lb/></body>
          
          <listBibl>100 W. WURMNEST, Internationale Zuständigkeit, cit., p. 938. <lb/>101 In EU civil judicial cooperation there is no margin of appreciation in the assessment of jurisdiction: <lb/>Court of Justice, Grand Chamber, judgment of 1 March 2005, Owusu, case C-281/02. <lb/>102 J. FITCHEN, Choice of Law, cit., p. 357. <lb/>103 In the Report from the Commission to the European Parliament, the Council and the European Economic <lb/>and Social Committee on the application of Regulation (EC) No 864/2007 on the law applicable to <lb/>noncontractual obligations (Rome II Regulation), {SWD(2025) 9 final}, of 31 January 2025, COM(2025) <lb/>20 final, a short statement is devoted to collective redress (p. 10), only to state that further reflections are <lb/>needed on the potential benefits of a future reform of the Regulation on the topic. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>132 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>contrary to (a), it poses a quantitative threshold, a substantial harm 104 . This is not defined. <lb/>Therefore, the court shall be satisfied that at least a meaningful part of the loss occurred <lb/>in that country, although neither a fixed threshold nor a percentage can be established, <lb/>nor suggested 105 . Moreover, the said condition shall be interpreted with caution: strictly, <lb/>it means that the court shall determine the whole loss and that suffered in the State where <lb/>it sits, then deciding if the latter is a substantial part of the former. This would require full <lb/>investigation and ascertainment of the facts for the purposes of the determination of the <lb/>applicable law. This conclusion seems too burdensome. Therefore, a prima facie <lb/>determination seems appropriate in this case, too. In follow on cases, the existence of a <lb/>Competition Authority decision on the effects of the harm can be extremely helpful. <lb/>It is interesting to stress that in this case the claimant can localise the antitrust conduct. <lb/>Indeed, he/she can choose to base the claim on the lex fori, and therefore to decide to <lb/>localise the multistate tort in a place which is highly connected with it, it being both the <lb/>domicile of one of the defendants and one of the places of the injuries. Most probably, <lb/>the choice is determined by the claimant&apos;s convenience; nevertheless, it is fruitful also in <lb/>terms of localisation. <lb/>This possibility of choice of law is partly dissonant with Article 6(4) 106 and seems to <lb/>reduce the relevance of the protection of the free and undistorted competition within the <lb/>internal market. However, setting aside these considerations on the coherence of the <lb/>system, this opportunity generates overwhelming advantages. It avoids cumulation, <lb/>leading to the application of one national law to the whole claim. Furthermore, it eases <lb/>the work of the judge in the ascertainment of the substance of the applicable law. The <lb/>conditions stated in the rule do not diminish the importance of the free and undistorted <lb/>competition in the EU. Indeed, it applies only where there is a strong EU interest, and, in <lb/>particular, if the defendant has its domicile in the EU, pursuant to Article 4 of the <lb/>Regulation 1215/1215. Therefore, the lex fori cannot but be the law of a Member State, <lb/>and EU Competition Law is applicable 107 . Consequently, even if the consolidation option <lb/>is left to the claimant (and to his/her interests), this potential concentration strengthens <lb/>the protection of EU interests and avoids the application of third countries laws that might <lb/>risk undermining EU objectives in the internal market. <lb/>The second hypothesis envisaged in Article 6(3)(b) refers to multistate and multiparty <lb/>claims, clarifying the extent of the first hypothesis. If the claimant sues more than one <lb/></body>
          
          <listBibl>104 The fact that the loss should be direct is already contemplated in Article 6(3)(a), it being a necessary <lb/>quality according to Article 4 of the Regulation 864/2007. <lb/>105 The analysis should be done on a case by case. Elements could be market shares; turnover; absolute <lb/>number of goods or services (M. ILLMER, Article 6, cit., p. 284). <lb/>106 E. RODRIGUEZ PINEAU, Conflict of Laws, cit., p. 327. <lb/>107 The rule protects an EU interest (E. RODRIGUEZ PINEAU, Conflict of Laws, cit., p. 323; P. MANKOWSKI, <lb/>Ausgewählte Einzelfragen zur RomII-VO: Internationales Umwelthaftungsrecht, Internationales <lb/>Kartellrecht, Renvoi, Parteiautonomie, in IPRax, 2010, p. 389; C. HONORATI, Regolamento n. 864/2007 <lb/>cit., p. 538; S. FRANCQ, W. WURMNEST, International Antitrust Claims, cit., p. 100). Without the choice, a <lb/>non-EU national law could be applicable to the part of the harm to the market affected in a third Country, <lb/>as one of the laws cumulatively concurring. The choice, framed and limited under Article 6(3)(b) can only <lb/>lead to a law of a Member State, and does not contradict the universal application of the rules on the <lb/>applicable law according to Article 3 of the Regulation. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>133 <lb/></page>

<body>defendant, the consolidation of the claims (which is a free decision of the plaintiff) cannot <lb/>be abusive against the co-defendants with domiciles in other Member States. Therefore, <lb/>their acts implying restriction of competition must directly and substantially affect the <lb/>market of the State of the seized judge. The rule grants predictability in the consolidation <lb/>of jurisdiction and the concentration of the applicable law with an eye to the co-<lb/>defendants: indeed, they shall know, or reasonably foresee, where their conducts are <lb/>likely to cause direct and substantial losses, and in this case the law of the State of such <lb/>affected market can be applicable, without surprises or frauds. The localisation, that <lb/>seems reasonable if referred to one defendant, must be further conditioned, if referred to <lb/>more than one defendant. This rule seems particularly useful in cases of breaches of <lb/>Article 101 of the TFEU, if the claimant decides to sue all the cartelists, for example <lb/>because he/she is an indirect victim and had no direct relationships with any of the <lb/>wrongdoers. Nevertheless, it might be difficult to prove, even prima facie, that each <lb/>tortfeasor&apos;s conduct caused losses in one State (that of the seized judge), except again in <lb/>follow on cases, where the Competition Authority decision on the effects of the conduct <lb/>might prove very helpful. <lb/>7. Some final remarks: the localisation of the non-contractual liability arising out of <lb/>a restriction of competition <lb/>A positive aspect of Article 6(3) of the Regulation 864/2007 is the tentative <lb/>coordination with jurisdiction in some difficult cases. In civil and commercial matters, <lb/>the adoption of two separate regulations, one on jurisdiction, enforcement and recognition <lb/>of judgments, one on the applicable law 108 , in different moments, risks preventing an <lb/>evaluation of the mutual interactions 109 . Due to the possibly articulated nature of the <lb/>claims considered therein (multistate or multistate and multiparty claims), the solutions <lb/>envisaged try to ease the coordination, favouring the lex fori. This option produces several <lb/>advantages. First and foremost, it is left to the plaintiff&apos;s option, softening the prohibition <lb/>of agreements as to the applicable law. The unilateral choice provokes a positive effect <lb/>towards the victim, that is a possible choice of the law better protecting his/her interests, <lb/>although Article 6(3) is not modelled in order to strengthen the victims&apos; protection 110 . <lb/></body>
          
          <listBibl>108 This is clearly due to the fact that the Brussels regulations replace the Brussels Convention of 1968, <lb/>conceived to deal exclusively with jurisdiction and judgments, in civil and commercial matters, while the <lb/>Rome II Regulation was intended to complete the unification of choice of law rules in matters of obligations <lb/>initiated with the Rome Convention of 1980. At that initial stage, it was not realistically feasible to adopt <lb/>an instrument dealing at the same time with jurisdiction and with applicable law. Therefore, the tentative <lb/>coordination of Article 6(3) shows a very positive attitude. <lb/>109 This procedural safeguard is indeed established in Article 6(3) only, while similar problems can arise in <lb/>the scope of application of other provisions of the Rome II Regulation (C. HONORATI, Regolamento n. <lb/>864/2007, cit., p. 539). <lb/>110 The sole rule protecting victims in the Rome II Regulation is Article 7, on environmental damages: S. <lb/>LAMONT-BLACK, E. GUINCHARD, Environmental Law -the Black Sheep in Rome II&apos;s Drive for Legal <lb/>Certainty: Article 7 of Regulation (EC) No. 864/2007 on the Law Applicable to Non-Contractual <lb/>Obligations in Context, in Environmental Liability: Law, Policy and Practice, 2009, pp. 161-172. <lb/></listBibl>

<note place="headnote">Cross border private enforcement of EU competition law <lb/></note>

<page>134 <lb/></page>

<note place="footnote">www.fsjeurostudies.eu <lb/></note>

<body>This favour does not undermine the EU protection of general interests, such as free and <lb/>undistorted competition in the internal market, since the option left to the applicant is <lb/>conditioned to proximity and localisation, so that the chosen applicable law is surely <lb/>strongly connected with the case and it is a national law of a Member State. <lb/>A unilateral option is however difficult, not only because of the not very well clear-<lb/>cut conditions established therein and of the margin of appreciation left to the judge on <lb/>the evaluation of the substantial harm, but especially because the victim shall still <lb/>compare his/her personal benefits in the application of the lex fori, on one side, and of the <lb/>cumulative application of more concurring national laws (in case, including that of third <lb/>States). In case of mistake in this evaluation, the application of a unique law has <lb/>repercussion on the whole claim. In case of cumulative application of more laws, the fact <lb/>that one of these is not favourable to the victim, for whatever reasons, impacts on a part <lb/>of the loss only, that suffered in the affected market whose law is indeed not favourable, <lb/>without jeopardising the rest of the case, nor the damages to other parts of the harm. The <lb/>concentration can be risky. It is not by chance that the CJEU has not yet had the <lb/>opportunity to interpret this rule: it has been barely invoked. <lb/>Furthermore, the experience so far in the application of the rules of jurisdiction in <lb/>Article 7(2) of the Regulation 1215/2012 demonstrates that the current practice in private <lb/>enforcement of EU Competition law is not that complicated as it could actually be. This <lb/>does not mean that practitioners shall not be ready to face multistate and multiparty <lb/>(claimants and defendants) cases, since infringements of EU Competition Law are indeed <lb/>the proper situations where these hypotheses can occur. The main point is that the victims <lb/>wish to recover damages: therefore, they do not show any interest in complicated cases, <lb/>preferring, very naturally, to find out an alleged wrongdoer and claim directly against it, <lb/>even in the scope of Article 101 of the TFEU. There is this a &quot;one-to-one&quot; case, where <lb/>the elements of the situation are not particularly fragmented and the localisation can take <lb/>place in a few Member States, even only two, not giving rise to serious difficulties. <lb/>Further, there is no need to reason on indirect losses, that might be useful to find indirect <lb/>victims and potential claimants, but not courts with jurisdiction and potentially applicable <lb/>laws. <lb/>Difficulties of localisation are thus tempered, because the claimant can tailor the <lb/>cause of action in order to match its interests at best, without really caring about the fact <lb/>that the anticompetitive conduct had global effects, or that other direct or indirect victims <lb/>suffered loss. This consequence favours the victim, at the end. This pragmatic approach <lb/>is not only typical (and correct) from a claimant&apos;s point of view, but it is justified by the <lb/>same CJEU&apos;s case law, that does not go in depth in the analysis of all the features of the <lb/>infringement, but looks (carefully) at the elements of the concrete cause of action. At the <lb/>end, in the establishment of jurisdiction, the court needs to be satisfied that any of the <lb/>element used as grounds of jurisdiction is located in the State where it sits; then, it is only <lb/>left to establish if it has general or limited jurisdiction. <lb/>In the determination of the applicable law, the court can make use of the general rule <lb/>of Article 6(3)(a) of the Regulation 864/2007, trying to distinguish between a law that <lb/></body>

<note place="headnote">Silvia Marino <lb/></note>

<page>135 <lb/></page>

<body>can govern the whole, or a part of the claim. The fact that the affected market can be both <lb/>a ground of jurisdiction and a connecting factor, it being also frequently the place of the <lb/>domicile of the claimant, or of one of its subsidiaries, helps: the determination of the <lb/>applicable law can follow immediately the establishment of the jurisdiction. This <lb/>produces a convergence of the forum and the applicable law. This market is also most <lb/>probably the place where the claimant suffered the most substantial harm 111 , and <lb/>consequently is not interested in recovering any other damages, wherever caused, erasing <lb/>the problem of multiplicity. <lb/>Furthermore, the fragmentation does not necessarily cause conflicts of judgments, if <lb/>the claimant lodges cases with the courts of the places of the losses. Each court is <lb/>competent for a part of the harm only, and the following decisions might logically differ <lb/>because they pertain to different situations, at least concerning the existence and the <lb/>quantification of the harm. <lb/>These remarks do not aim to oversimplify the challenges of potentially global claims, <lb/>as the consequences of the infringements of EU Competition Law can be, nor <lb/>underestimate the classic issues of evidence of the liability and of costs of the proceedings <lb/>-only partly faced by Directive 2014/104. However, if the interpretation of the rules <lb/>focusses on the specific element of the claim, localisation is indeed possible. It might not <lb/>be unique, it can leave room to choices in favour of the claimant, but these consequences <lb/>are absolutely acceptable in a system, such as that of EU civil judicial cooperation, that <lb/>reduces the cases of exclusive jurisdiction, is based on the freedom of the parties (or of <lb/>one party), and establishes possible alternatives in the determination both of jurisdiction <lb/>and of the applicable law. <lb/></body>
          
          <front>ASTRACT: The article tackles the sensitive issue of localisation of the infringements of <lb/>EU Competition Law for the purposes of the determination of jurisdiction and the <lb/>applicable law in the context of cross-border private enforcement proceedings. The <lb/>analysis considers the relevant EU Regulations and the CJEU&apos;s case law that tries to <lb/>limit multiplicity and fragmentation for these specific cases, notwithstanding the <lb/>availability of alternative grounds of jurisdiction and the application of the <lb/>Mosaikbetrachtung in the determination of the applicable law. The final remarks <lb/>focus on quite well-realised consistency of the solutions in a system that is modelled <lb/>on alternative options and the possibility of a choice by the parties. <lb/>KEYWORDS: private enforcement of EU competition law -multistate torts -affected <lb/>market -alternative grounds of jurisdiction -special rules on applicable law. <lb/></front>
        
        <listBibl>111 C. HONORATI, Regolamento n. 864/2007, cit., p. 536. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>