<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Protection against Indirect Expropriation under National and International Legal Systems</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Max</forename>
          <surname>Gutbrod</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Steffen</forename>
          <surname>Hindelang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Yun-I</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-10-16T13:14:17.789Z">10/16/2025 2:14:17 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.3249$1$1868-1581-1-2-gutbrod</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Institut für Völker- und Europarecht</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2009</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.3249/1868-1581-1-2-gutbrod</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Max Gutbrod, Steffen Hindelang, Yun-I Kim. (2009). Protection against Indirect Expropriation under National and International Legal Systems. Goettingen Journal of International Law, (), None. DOI: 10.3249/1868-1581-1-2-gutbrod</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-04T21:31:00.330507Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">0707645</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-10-04T21:31:00.330507Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Göttingen Journal of International Law 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/>doi: 10.3249/1868-1581-1-2-gutbrod <lb/>Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/>under National and International Legal <lb/>Systems 1 <lb/>Max Gutbrod, Steffen Hindelang &amp; Yun-I Kim  <lb/></front>

			<toc>Table of Contents <lb/>Introduction ................................................................................................ 293 <lb/>A. Identifying a Compensable Taking -A Brief Summary of the <lb/>Present Discussion ................................................................................ 297 <lb/>B. Scenarios of State Measures ................................................................. 305 <lb/>I. State Measures Which Are Lawful by National Standards ............. 305 <lb/>1. First Scenario: A State Measure Which Is Lawful by <lb/>National Standards But Discriminatory ...................................... 305 <lb/>a) Russian Law .......................................................................... 306 <lb/></toc>
    
    <front>1 <lb/>This is an updated version of an article, originally written by Max Gutbrod and Stef-<lb/>fen Hindelang, first published in the Journal of World Investment and Trade, Vo-<lb/>lume 7, No. 1 (February 2006); the publisher's permission is gratefully acknowledged. <lb/> <lb/>Max Gutbrod, Dr. iur. (Munich), Rechtsanwalt (German lawyer); Partner at Baker &amp; <lb/>McKenzie, Moscow. The author has advised on many investments in particular into <lb/>emerging markets as well as some international arbitration proceedings. He may be <lb/>contacted at max.gutbrod@bakernet.com. <lb/>Steffen Hindelang, Dr. iur. (Tübingen), LL.M. (Sheffield); Research Associate and <lb/>Lecturer, Eberhard-Karls-University of Tübingen, School of Law, Germany. His re-<lb/>search mainly focuses on International and European Economic Law, Comparative <lb/>Administrative Law, and the EC Legal Framework on Foreign Investment. He may be <lb/>contacted at st.hi@gmx.de. <lb/>Yun-I Kim, Dipl. iur. (Cologne); Ph.D. Candidate, Faculty of Law, University of <lb/>Potsdam, Germany. Case Assistant to Professor Dr. Karl-Heinz Böckstiegel; Research <lb/>Assistant to Dr. Richard Happ, Luther law firm, Hamburg. Her research concentrates <lb/>on International Investment Protection Law and International Investment Arbitration. <lb/>The views expressed herein are strictly those of the authors. <lb/>GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/>292 <lb/></front>
    
    <toc>b) International Investment Agreements ................................... <lb/>2. Second Scenario: A State Measure Which Is Lawful <lb/>by National Standards But Discriminatory and Ac-<lb/>companied With Mala Fide ........................................................ <lb/>a) Russian Law .......................................................................... <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements ................................... <lb/>3. Third Scenario: Investor Contributing to Bankruptcy ................ <lb/>a) Russian Law .......................................................................... <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements ................................... <lb/>4. Fourth Scenario: Mala Fide, Investor Acting Unlaw-<lb/>fully ............................................................................................. <lb/>a) Russian Law .......................................................................... <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements ................................... <lb/>II. State Action Which Is Unlawful by National Standards ................. <lb/>1. Fifth Scenario: Unlawful State Action Against the <lb/>Management, Management Personally Involved in <lb/>Crimes ......................................................................................... <lb/>a) Russian Law .......................................................................... <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements ................................... <lb/>2. Sixth Scenario: Illegality "All Around" ..................................... <lb/>a) Russian Law .......................................................................... <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements ................................... <lb/>C. Conclusions and Outlook ...................................................................... <lb/></toc>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>293 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Introduction <lb/>In recent years, direct expropriation 2 has rarely been seen. 3 States <lb/>which wish to import capital do not like to be associated with posing a per-<lb/>manent, non-calculable threat to foreign-owned property but prefer to pre-<lb/>sent themselves as jurisdictions with very stable, reliable and orderly regula-<lb/>tory environments. 4 Expropriation, however, has by no means vanished; its <lb/>execution has just become more subtle. 5 Ambiguously or generously <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>2 <lb/>In a nutshell, direct expropriation is the compulsory transfer of legal title or the out-<lb/>right seizure of property by the State. In contrast, indirect expropriation refers to the <lb/>situation in which the investor formally remains legal owner. See, instead of all, <lb/>M. Sornarajah, The International Law on Foreign Investment, 2nd ed. (2004), 344, <lb/>with further references. See generally, C. N. Brower &amp; J. D. Brueschke, The Iran-<lb/>United States Claims Tribunal (1998), 379; G. C. Christie, 'What Constitutes a Taking <lb/>of Property under International Law?', 38 British Yearbook of International Law <lb/>(1962), 309; P. Comeaux &amp; S. Kinsella, Protecting Foreign Investment under Interna-<lb/>tional Law: Legal Aspects of Political Risk (1997), 8; A. Mouri, The International <lb/>Law of Expropriation as Reflected in the Work of the Iran-U.S.Claims Tribunal <lb/>(1994), 70-99; C. Schreuer, 'The Concept of Expropriation under the ECT and other <lb/>Investment Protection Treaties', 2 Transnational Dispute Management, (2005) 3, <lb/>available at www.transnational-dispute-management.com (last visited 9 April 2009); <lb/>B. H. Weston, 'International Law and the Deprivation of Foreign Wealth: A Frame-<lb/>work for Future Inquiry', in R. A. Falk &amp; C. Black (eds), The Future of the Interna-<lb/>tional Legal Order, Vol. 2: Wealth and Resources (1970), 106; M. M. Whiteman, 8 <lb/>Digest of International Law (1976), 1006-1020. <lb/>3 <lb/>For one of the few cases where direct expropriation occurred in recent years, Cf. Mr. <lb/>Franz Sedelmayer v. Russian Federation, Award, 7 July 1998. See also Bolivia's Su-<lb/>preme Decree No. 28701, Nationalization of Hydrocarbon Sector, 1 May 2006, 45 <lb/>ILM 1020 (2006). <lb/>4 <lb/>M. W. Reisman &amp; R. D. Sloane, 'Indirect Expropriation and its Valuation in the BIT <lb/>Generation', 74 British Yearbook of International Law (2003), 118; L. Reed &amp; <lb/>D. Bray, 'Fair and Equitable Treatment: Fairly and Equitably Applied in Lieu of <lb/>Unlawful Indirect Expropriation?', in: A. W. Rovine (ed.), Contemporary Issues in In-<lb/>ternational Arbitration and Mediation, 2008, 13; A. K. Hoffmann, 'Indirect Expro-<lb/>priation', in: A. Reinisch, (ed.), Standards of Investment Protection, 2008, 151; on the <lb/>subject of indirect expropriation in general refer to U. Kriebaum, 'Partial Expropria-<lb/>tion', 8 Journal of World Investment and Trade (2007), 69; U. Kriebaum, 'Regulatory <lb/>Takings: Balancing the Interests of the Investor and the State', Journal of World In-<lb/>vestment and Trade (2007), 717; A. Reinisch, 'Expropriation', in: P. Muchlinski et al. <lb/>(eds), The Oxford Handbook of International Investment Law (2008), 420-451; J. <lb/>Griebel, Internationales Investitionsrecht (2008), 76-79; R. Dolzer &amp; C. Schreuer, <lb/>Principles of International Investment Law (2008), 89-92. <lb/>5 <lb/>Reinisch, supra note 3, 432. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>294 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>worded laws are 'interpreted' in a way that suits certain groups in the gov-<lb/>ernment or are only enforced when it suits a particular interest; administra-<lb/>tive discretion is influenced by factors unrelated to the matter at issue, or <lb/>administrations fail to conduct their processes in a transparent and compre-<lb/>hensible way. All these measures, turned against a foreign investor, can eas-<lb/>ily drive him out of business. Virtually all bilateral investment treaties <lb/>(BITs) and multilateral investment agreements (MITs), therefore, reflect this <lb/>development and also cover acts of State which may expropriate "indirectly <lb/>through measures tantamount to expropriation or nationalisation" 6 (indirect <lb/>expropriation 7 ). Moreover, many international investment agreements (IIAs) <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>6 <lb/>Article III (1) of the Treaty between the United States of America and the Russian <lb/>Federation concerning the Encouragement and Reciprocal Protection of Investment, <lb/>signed 17 June 1992, not yet in force; available at: www.unctad.org/sections/dite/iia/ <lb/>docs/bits/usa_russia.pdf (last visited 9 April 2009). See also Article III of the Abs-<lb/>Shawcross Draft Convention on Investment Abroad of 1959, United Nations Confer-<lb/>ence on Trade and Development (UNCTAD), International Investment Instruments: A <lb/>Compendium, Vol. V, 2000, 396; Article 0(3)(a) of the Harvard Draft Convention of <lb/>1961, in L. B. Sohn &amp; R. R. Baxter, 'Responsibility of States for Injuries to the Eco-<lb/>nomic Interests of Aliens', 55 Amercian Journal of International Law (1961), 553; <lb/>Protocol No. 1 of the European Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and <lb/>Fundamental Freedoms of 1952, available at www.echr.coe.int/NR/rdonlyres/ <lb/>D5CC24A7-DC13-4318-B457-5C9014916D7A/0/EnglishAnglais.pdf (last visited 11 <lb/>August 2005); Article 3 of the Draft Convention of the Organisation for Economic <lb/>Co-operation and Development (OECD) on the Protection of Foreign Property of <lb/>1967, in UNCTAD, International Investment Instruments: A Compendium, Vol. II, <lb/>1996, 114; Article 21 of the American Convention on Human Rights of 1969, avail-<lb/>able at www.oas.org/juridico/english/Treaties/b-32.htm (last visited 1 September <lb/>2005); American Law Institute, Restatement (Third) of the Foreign Relations Law of <lb/>the United States, Vol. 2, 1986, §712(1); OECD Negotiating Group on the Multilateral <lb/>Agreement on Investment (MAI), The Multilateral Agreement on Investment Draft <lb/>Consolidated Text, OECD Doc. DAFFE/MAI(98)7/REV1, 22 April 1998, available at <lb/>www1.oecd.org/daf/mai/pdf/ng/ng987r1e.pdf (last visited 1 September 2005); Article <lb/>13(1) of the Energy Charter Treaty (ECT), available at www.encharter.org (last visited <lb/>9 April 2009); Article 1110 of the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) <lb/>of 1992, available at www.nafta-sec-alena.org/DefaultSite/index_e.aspx?DetailID=78 <lb/>(last visited 9 April 2009); Article 6 of the 2004 US Model BIT; Article 13 of the <lb/>2003 Canadian Model Foreign Investment Protection Agreement; most recently, how-<lb/>ever, solely referring to 'expropriation or nationalisation' without differentiating be-<lb/>tween direct or indirect expropriation, Article 6 of the 2007 Norway Model BIT. <lb/>7 <lb/>From an analytical point of view, one can distinguish between "creeping" and "conse-<lb/>quential expropriation". "'Creeping' expropriation is comprised out of a number of <lb/>elements, none of which can -separately -constitute the international wrong." Reis-<lb/>man &amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 123, 125-127. Intention to harm the investment or the <lb/>investor or an intention to expropriate is not necessary but helps to prove a creeping <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>295 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>not only provide rules on (indirect) expropriation but also establish so-called <lb/>treatment standards "which refer to the legal regime that applies to invest-<lb/>ments once they have been admitted by the host State." 8 Administrative <lb/>malfeasance, misfeasance and nonfeasance may also affect the investment <lb/>adversely without amounting to "indirect expropriation", constituting a less <lb/>intense interference with the property. Indeed, there are arbitral awards <lb/>which, while not accepting a claim based on "indirect expropriation", estab-<lb/>lished a compensable violation of "treatment standards", i.e. in particular the <lb/>"fair and equitable treatment" embodied in BITs or MITs. 9 <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>expropriation; Reisman &amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 124, 128. Cf. also Compañía de <lb/>Aguas del Aconquija S.A. and Vivendi Universal v. Argentina, ICSID Case No. <lb/>ARB/97/3, Award, 20 August 2007, at para. 7.5.20 (hereafter referred to as Compañía <lb/>de Aguas del Aconquija S.A. and Vivendi Universal); Siemens AG v. Argentina, ICSID <lb/>Case No. ARB/02/8, Award, 6 February 2007, at para. 270 (hereafter referred to as <lb/>Siemens AG). See also C. Schachter, The Concept of Expropriation under the ECT and <lb/>other Investment Protection Treaties, in 2 Transnational Dispute Management <lb/>(2005) 3, available at: www.transnational-dispute-management.com (last visited 9 <lb/>April 2009); A. Newcombe &amp; L. Paradell, Law and Practice of Investment Treaties -<lb/>Standards of Treatment (2009), 343-344; Reinisch, supra note 3, 426-431. "Conse-<lb/>quential expropriation" refers to the situation in which the host State fails to properly <lb/>create, maintain and manage "the legal, administrative, and regulatory normative <lb/>framework contemplated by the relevant BIT, an indispensable feature of the 'favour-<lb/>able conditions' for investment." Reisman &amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 129, 130. Here, <lb/>also, an intention on the part of the host State is not required. Reisman &amp; Sloane, su-<lb/>pra note 3, 129. <lb/>8 <lb/>R. Dolzer &amp; M. Stevens, Bilateral Investment Treaties (1995), 58. <lb/>9 <lb/>Cf. CMS Gas Transmission Company v. Argentina, ICSID Case No. ARB/01/8, <lb/>Award, 12 May 2005 (hereafter referred to as CMS); Saluka Investments B.V. (The <lb/>Netherlands) v. Czech Republic, Partial Award, 17 March 2006; Azurix v. Argentina, <lb/>ICSID Case No. ARB/01/12, Award, 14 July 2006; LG&amp;E Energy Corp., LG&amp;E <lb/>Capital Corp. and LG&amp;E International Inc. v. Argentina, ICSID Case No. ARB/02/1, <lb/>Decision on Liability, 3 October 2006 (hereafter referred to as LG&amp;E Energy Corp.); <lb/>PSEG Global, Inc. and Konya Ilgin Elektrik Üretim ve Ticaret Limited Şirketi v. Tur-<lb/>key, ICSID Case No. ARB/02/5, Award, 19 January 2007; Enron Corporation and <lb/>Ponderosa Assets L.P. v. Argentina, ICSID Case No. ARB/01/3, Award, 22 May 2007 <lb/>(hereafter referred to as Enron Corp.); Sempra Energy v. Argentina, ICSID Case No. <lb/>ARB/02/16, Award, 28 September 2007 (hereafter referred to as Sempra Energy); for <lb/>cases where State action amounted to both indirect expropriation as well as to a breach <lb/>of the "fair and equitable treatment" standard, cf. Siemens AG, supra note 6; Com-<lb/>pañía de Aguas del Aconquija S.A. and Vivendi Universal v. Argentina, supra note 6. <lb/>Many BITs provide in rather repetitive wording not only for "fair and equitable treat-<lb/>ment" but also for "full protection and security" and prohibit "unreasonable or dis-<lb/>criminatory measures in the course of management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or <lb/>disposal of investments"; Article 2(2) of the Agreement between The Government of <lb/>the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and The Union of Soviet <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>296 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>This article will look at six typically posed challenges to foreign in-<lb/>vestment posed by administrative acts, focusing on the issues of discrimina-<lb/>tion, mala fide and lack of transparency, and will discuss the response of <lb/>national and international rules applicable to the situation of indirect expro-<lb/>priation. 10 These scenarios are based on Russian legal regulations 11 and are <lb/>inspired by the events in the Commonwealth of Independent States reality <lb/>but by no means intend to be a reflection of facts. <lb/>We will show that the internal legal order cannot respond to any of <lb/>these challenges through striking a just balance between legitimate business <lb/>interests of the foreign investor and the State's sovereign right to regulate. <lb/>Rather, it is the international (contractual) law on foreign investment which <lb/>offers the clearly more sophisticated framework for a balanced settlement of <lb/>a foreign investment dispute. Our prediction is that if economies in transi-<lb/>tion, like Russia, do not start living up to the standards required by interna-<lb/>tional investment agreements quickly, they might face the risk of the mar-<lb/>ginalization of their national legal orders in the settlement of foreign in-<lb/>vestment disputes. Such conflicts, which earlier clearly had an "internal <lb/>component", would increasingly become international only and would, in <lb/>this sense, be externalized. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>Socialist Republics concerning the promotion and reciprocal protection of invest-<lb/>ments, signed 6 April 1989, entered into force 3 July 1991. In academic writing, much <lb/>effort has been spent on the question of whether and how the concepts of "fair and eq-<lb/>uitable treatment", "full protection and security" and "non-discrimination" are to be <lb/>delimited from each other. <lb/>10 <lb/>Occasionally, if it is helpful in making an argument more explicit, we might also make <lb/>reference to the concept of "fair and equitable treatment", part of the treatment stan-<lb/>dards attributable to a foreign investment by virtue of IIAs. <lb/>11 <lb/>Russia, like many countries around the world, has become party to a variety of bilat-<lb/>eral and multilateral international agreements (at least partly) concerned with or re-<lb/>lated to the protection of foreign investment, i.e. numerous bilateral investment trea-<lb/>ties (BITs) with all major capital exporting countries (Russia had signed 56 BITs as of <lb/>1 June 2005, of which 30 had entered into force; for a detailed list, see the UNCTAD <lb/>Website at www.unctad.org/sections/dite_pcbb/docs/bits_russian_federa tion_en.pdf <lb/>(last visited 29 August 2005); the full text can be accessed via www.unctadxi.org/ <lb/>templates/DocSearch____779.aspx (last visited 29 August 2005)); The European <lb/>Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms and its <lb/>First Protocol, available at www.echr.coe.int/NR/rdonlyres/ D5CC24A7-DC13-4318-<lb/>B457-5C9014916D7A/0/EnglishAnglais.pdf (last visited 11 August 2005); and the <lb/>Agreement on Partnership and Cooperation, available at europa.eu.int/comm/external_ <lb/>relations/ceeca/pca/pca_russia.pdf (last visited 11 August 2005) with the European <lb/>Union. Russia is also a signatory to the European Energy Charter Treaty, available at <lb/>www.encharter.org (last visited 28 August 2005) and is provisionally applying it <lb/>while the ratification process is pending before the Duma. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>297 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>This article will start off by providing a brief survey of the present <lb/>discussion in the literature based on the awards rendered on the subject, on <lb/>what constitutes a compensable taking in international law (Section A.). It <lb/>will then turn to certain hypothetical situations (Section B.). These are split <lb/>into two parts: the first four scenarios deal with State measures which are <lb/>lawful by national standards (Section B.I.) and the last two scenarios focus <lb/>on State measures which are unlawful even by national standards (Section <lb/>B.II.). Finally, it summarizes and evaluates our findings. <lb/>A. Identifying a Compensable Taking -A Brief Sum-<lb/>mary of the Present Discussion <lb/>Above, we referred to the 'subtle' governmental interference with for-<lb/>eign property. However, what are those 'subtle' measures 'tantamount to <lb/>expropriation' which will eventually give rise to compensation? <lb/>It has been suggested that the phrase 'tantamount to expropriation' <lb/>does not only refer to intentional or obvious indirect expropriation but that <lb/>"[i]t also captures the multiplicity of inappropriate regulatory acts, omis-<lb/>sions, and other deleterious conduct that undermines the vital normative <lb/>framework created and maintained by BITs". 12 Recalling the objectives pur-<lb/>sued by entering into BITs and similar agreements -the establishment and <lb/>maintenance of a "healthy investment climate" 13 -the concept of 'indirect <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>12 <lb/>Reisman &amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 118-119; differing C. McLachlan et al. (eds), Inter-<lb/>national Investment Arbitration: Substantive Principles (2007), 291, at para. 8.72-<lb/>8.74; cf. also Mr. Eudoro Armando Olguín v. Paraguay, ICSID Case No. ARB/98/5, <lb/>Award, 26 July 2001, at para. 84; Sea-Land Services, Inc. v. Iran, 6 Iran-U.S. C.T.R. <lb/>(1984), 149 (hereafter referred to as Sea-Land Services). <lb/>13 <lb/>Article 31 of the Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties of 1969, available at <lb/>www.un.org/law/ilc/texts/treaties.htm (last visited 11 August 2005), asks to have due <lb/>regard to the object and purpose in the construction of a treaty. Most, if not all, BITs, <lb/>as well as multinational agreements on investment protection such as the European <lb/>Energy Treaty or the NAFTA, intend, as provided for in their preambles, to establish <lb/>favourable conditions for investment by nationals and companies of one State in the <lb/>territory of the other State. For a review of typical preambles, see Dolzer &amp;Stevens, <lb/>supra note 8, 20-21. In short, they envisage a "healthy investment climate" which is <lb/>conditio sine qua non for the attraction of foreign direct investment. Those treaties <lb/>"contemplate […] an effective normative framework: impartial courts, an efficient and <lb/>legally restrained bureaucracy, and the measure of transparency in decision"; Reisman <lb/>&amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 117. If a State signs up to such a treaty, it must be aware that <lb/>it not only opens its doors to foreign investment but also commits itself to establish <lb/>and/or maintain an appropriate legal, administrative, and regulatory framework; <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>298 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>expropriation' is extended to "an egregious failure to create or maintain the <lb/>normative 'favourable conditions' in the host state". 14 <lb/>However, not every governmental adjustment of the normative <lb/>framework or change in the application of this framework, or even mistake <lb/>in application -errare humanum est -that adversely affects the economies <lb/>where a foreign investment is made constitutes an expropriatory act (or a <lb/>violation of treatment standards): 15 <lb/>"[S]tate measures, prima facie a lawful exercise of powers of <lb/>governments, may affect foreign interests considerably without <lb/>amounting to expropriation. Thus, foreign assets and their use <lb/>may be subjected to taxation, trade restrictions involving li-<lb/>censes and quotas, or measures of devaluation. While special <lb/>facts may alter cases, in principle such measures are not unlaw-<lb/>ful and do not constitute expropriation." 16 <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>Reisman &amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 117; undecided, Dolzer, supra note 12, 73-74. See, <lb/>for such an approach, Kuwait v. American Independent Oil Co. (Aminoil), Final <lb/>Award, 24 May 1982 (hereafter referred to as Aminoil), 21 ILM (1982), 976, at para. <lb/>147; Mondev Int'l Ltd v. United States of America, ICSID Case No. ARB(AF)/99/2, <lb/>Award, 11 October 2002, 42 ILM (2003), 110, para. 127. Some may argue now that an <lb/>investment treaty is intended to benefit both investor and host State and that, thus, the <lb/>rights and obligations of both sides need to be recognized; see Dolzer, who stipulates <lb/>this question at Dolzer, supra, 74. As much as this is true, this argument does not <lb/>speak against the aforementioned. It must be stressed again that BITs and MITs are <lb/>not intended to prohibit legitimate regulatory measures by the host State. On the con-<lb/>trary, they encourage the host State to exercise its regulatory powers in a transparent, <lb/>non-discriminating, non-abusive way guided by reason and the rule of law, at least <lb/>towards the foreign investor. In doing so, the host State is maintaining a "healthy in-<lb/>vestment climate" which, as already said, is essential for the attraction of foreign capi-<lb/>tal. The establishment of such a administrative framework will, ultimately, lead to an <lb/>improvement of the overall governance standards in the host State. <lb/>14 <lb/>Reisman &amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 119. <lb/>15 <lb/>Reisman &amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 117. See also Y. L. Fortier &amp; S. L. Drymer, 'Indirect <lb/>Expropriation in the Law of International Investment: I Know it When I See it or Ca-<lb/>veat Investor', 19 ICSID Review (2004), 298. <lb/>16 <lb/>I. Brownlie, Principles of Public International Law, 6th ed. (2003), 509; Sornarajah, <lb/>supra note 1, 357; for tax measures in international investment arbitration also cf. Ar-<lb/>cher Daniels Midland Company and Tate &amp; Lyle Ingredients Americas, Inc. v. United <lb/>Mexican States, ICSID Case No. ARB(AF)/04/05, Award, 21 November 2007, avail-<lb/>able at http://ita.law.uvic.ca/documents/ADMTateRedactedAward.pdf, para. 238; Pan <lb/>American Energy LLC, and BP Argentina Exploration Company v. Argentina, ICSID <lb/>Case No. ARB/03/13, Decision on Preliminary Objections, 27 July 2006, paras 117-<lb/>139; El Paso Energy International Company v. Argentina, ICSID Case No. <lb/>ARB/03/15, Decision on Jurisdiction, 27 April 2006, paras 101-116; EnCana Corpo-<lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>299 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>In other words, doing business means taking advantage of opportuni-<lb/>ties while accepting certain risks. Opportunities, or in other words, "favour-<lb/>able business conditions and goodwill, are transient circumstances, subject <lb/>to inevitable change." 17 Thus, the materialization of a risk ordinarily related <lb/>to a business venture does not amount to an expropriation. 18 It is necessary <lb/>to distinguish between the legitimate interest in adjusting and executing <lb/>national policies and the abuse of sovereign powers through illegitimate <lb/>interferences in foreign investment activities which are tantamount to ex-<lb/>propriation. 19 <lb/>International tribunals, arbitration courts, jurists and scholars "have <lb/>increasingly accepted that expropriation must be analysed in consequential <lb/>rather than formal terms," 20 and no single, clear-cut test has emerged so far <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>ration v. Ecuador, LCIA Case No. UN3481, Award, 3 February 2006, paras 141, 145, <lb/>177; Enron Corporation and Ponderosa Assets, L.P. v. Argentina, Decision on Juris-<lb/>diction, 14 January 2004, paras 25-32; Marvin Roy Feldman Karpa (Cemsa) (USA) v. <lb/>United Mexican States, ICSID (Additional Facility) Case No. ARB(AF)/99/1, Award, <lb/>16 December 2002, 42 I.L.M. 626 (2003) (hereafter referred to as Feldman); United <lb/>Parcel Service of America Inc. v. Canada, UNCITRAL Arbitration, Award on Juris-<lb/>diction, 22 November 2002, paras 116-117; Link-Trading Joint Stock Company v. <lb/>Moldova, UNCITRAL Arbitration, Award, 18 April 2002, paras 63-92. <lb/>17 <lb/>H. Sedigh, 'What Level of Host State Interference Amounts to a Taking under Con-<lb/>temporary International Law?', 2 Journal of World Investment (2001) 4, 646. <lb/>18 <lb/>The Oscar Chinn Case, U.K. v. Belgium, Award, 12 December 1934 (hereafter re-<lb/>ferred to as Oscar Chinn), PCIJ Rep. Series A/B, No. 63, 88: "No enterprise […] can <lb/>escape from the chances and hazards resulting from general economic conditions. <lb/>Some industries may be able to make large profits during a period of general prosper-<lb/>ity, or else by taking advantage of a treaty of commerce or of an alteration in customs <lb/>duties; but they are also exposed to the danger of ruin or extinction if circumstances <lb/>change. Where this is the case, no vested rights are violated by the State."; Starrett <lb/>Housing Corp. v. Iran, 4 Iran-U.S. Claims Tribunal Rep. (1983), 156: (hereafter re-<lb/>ferred to as Starrett Housing) "Investors in Iran, like investors in all other countries, <lb/>have to assume a risk that the country might experience strikes, lock-outs, distur-<lb/>bances, changes of economic and political system and even revolution. That any of <lb/>these risks materialised does not necessarily mean that property rights affected by <lb/>such events can be deemed to have been taken." Feldman, supra note 15, para. 112: <lb/>"Governments, in their exercise of regulatory power, frequently change their laws and <lb/>regulations in response to changing economic circumstances or changing political, <lb/>economic or social considerations. Those changes may well make certain activities <lb/>less profitable or even uneconomic to continue […]". <lb/>19 <lb/>Reisman &amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 17. <lb/>20 <lb/>Revere Copper and Brass, Inc. v. Overseas Private Inv. Corp., OPIC Award, 24 Au-<lb/>gust 1978, 58 ILM (1980), 271-272; lately, T. Wälde &amp; A. Kolo, 'Environmental <lb/>Regulation, Investment Protection and "Regulatory Taking" in International Law', <lb/>50 International and Comparative Law Quarterly (2001), 813; Reisman &amp; Sloane, <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>300 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>to determine whether an indirect expropriation has taken place. 21 Indeed, it <lb/>seems that the organic and slow "common law method of case-by-case de-<lb/>velopment is pre-eminently the best method, in fact probably the only me-<lb/>thod, of legal development" 22 in this field. The discussion surrounding three <lb/>important factors which have emerged from this process deserve to be men-<lb/>tioned here. <lb/>The severity of the impact on the owner's legal status, namely the <lb/>ability to use, enjoy, control and freely dispose of his investment, has been <lb/>accepted as a central factor in drawing the dividing line between expropria-<lb/>tion and legitimate administrative regulation. 23 Importantly, however, it is <lb/>controversial whether this severity is the sole/predominant factor 24 or <lb/>merely one of several important factors. 25 There is case law supporting both <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>supra note 3, 121. A wide range of State measures may be interpreted as expropriatory <lb/>if those measures significantly reduce the value of the property rights of an investor or <lb/>render them useless; see Reisman &amp; Sloane, supra note 3, 123. <lb/>21 <lb/>Sornarajah, supra note 1, 351. <lb/>22 <lb/>Christie, supra note 1, 338; cf. also Reed &amp; Bray, supra note 3, 13; Reinisch, supra <lb/>note 3, 438; Newcombe &amp; Paradell, supra note 6, 344, 366-368. <lb/>23 <lb/>Dolzer, supra note 12, 79; Z. A. AlQurashi, 'Indirect Expropriation in the Field of <lb/>Petroleum', 5 Journal of World Investment and Trade 6 (2004), 911. <lb/>24 <lb/>One strand of case law supports this doctrine: Tippetts, Abbett, McCarthy, Stratton v. <lb/>Tams-Affa Consulting Engineers of Iran (hereafter referred to as Tippetts), 6 Iran-<lb/>U.S. C.T.R. (1984), 225-226; Starrett Housing, supra note 17, 154; Phelps Dodge <lb/>Corp. v. Iran, 10 Iran-U.S. C.T.R. (1986), 130; Metalclad Corp. v. United Mexican <lb/>States, ICSID Case No. ARB(AF)/97/1, Award, 30 August 2000 (hereafter referred to <lb/>as Metalclad), para. 103; Biloune and Marine Drive Complex Ltd. v. Ghana Invest-<lb/>ments Centre and the Government of Ghana (hereafter referred to as Biloune), 95 ILR <lb/>(1989), 183 et seq.; Middle East Cement Shipping and Handling Co. S.A. v. Arab Re-<lb/>public of Egypt, ICSID Case No. ARB/99/6, Award, 12 April 2002, para. 107; Com-<lb/>pañía del Desarrollo de Santa Elena, S.A. v. Costa Rica, ICSID Case No. ARB/96/1, <lb/>Award, 17 February 2000, para. 76. For a more detailed analysis of the presented case <lb/>law, refer to AlQurashi, supra note 22, 907-909 and Dolzer, supra note 12, 86-90. <lb/>25 <lb/>Another strand of case law suggests that there are more factors to be taken into con-<lb/>sideration: Oscar Chinn, supra note 17, 88. See also T. Weiler, 'Saving Oscar Chinn: <lb/>Non-Discrimination in International Investment Law', in N. Horn, (ed.), Arbitrating <lb/>Foreign Investment Disputes (2004), 159-192; Barcelona Traction, Light &amp; Power <lb/>Co., Belgium v. Spain, (hereafter referred to as Barcelona Traction), ICJ Rep. (1970), <lb/>1, see separate opinions of Judge Fitzmaurice, 106, Judge Gros, 273, and Judge Ta-<lb/>naka, 159; Sea-Land Services, supra note 11, 149; S. D. Myers, Inc. v. Canada, First <lb/>Partial Award, 13 November 2000 (hereafter referred to as S. D. Myers); Técnicas <lb/>Medioambientales Tecmed S.A. (Spain) v. The United Mexican States, ICSID Case <lb/>No. ARB(AF)/00/2, Award, 29 May 2003, at para. 116 (hereafter referred to as <lb/>Tecmed); see also the Feldman case, supra note 15. For a more detailed analysis of the <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>301 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>views. 26 In this article, we follow the school of thought that determining <lb/>indirect expropriation only by diminution in property value might reduce <lb/>national policy space to zero as governments would then be confronted with <lb/>claims for compensation any time they change policy; 27 and this would limit <lb/>international law on foreign investment to an insurance policy against bad <lb/>business decisions. 28 We will proceed, therefore, from the assumption that <lb/>the impact of the State measure is a central but not the sole factor. <lb/>The degree of interference with property rights which is necessary in <lb/>order to hold a State liable for indirect expropriation is also controversial. 29 <lb/>Again, two strands of case law have emerged. One line of case law, basi-<lb/>cally as evidenced by decisions of the European Court of Human Rights <lb/>(ECHR), 30 requires that property rights have been rendered totally valueless, <lb/>i.e. the investor has been definitely and fully deprived of the ownership of <lb/>his property, 31 while more moderate authorities demand a significant or sub-<lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>presented case law, refer to AlQurashi, supra note 22, 909-911, Dolzer, supra note <lb/>12, 81-86. <lb/>26 <lb/>Dolzer points at the weakness of the "sole effect doctrine", stating that "the propo-<lb/>nents of the 'sole effect doctrine' would have to explain why international law protect-<lb/>ing aliens should require a higher standard of protection than the major domestic legal <lb/>orders"; Dolzer, supra note 12, 91. <lb/>27 <lb/>Wälde &amp; Kolo, supra note 19, 839; F. O. Vicuña, 'Carlos Calvo, Honorary NAFTA <lb/>Citizen, Keynote Address', 11 New York University Environmental Law Journal <lb/>(2002), 27; J. Paulsson &amp; Z. Douglas, 'Indirect Expropriation in Investment Treaty <lb/>Arbitrations', in N. Horn, (ed.), Arbitrating Foreign Investment Disputes (2004), 145-<lb/>158, at 146; Feldman, supra note 15, para. 112. <lb/>28 <lb/>American Law Institute, Restatement (Third) of the Foreign Relations Law of the <lb/>U.S.A., Vol. 2, 1987, §712, comment g. Cf. also Reinisch, supra note 3, 433. <lb/>29 <lb/>Summarizing Wälde &amp; Kolo, supra note 19, 837 et seq. <lb/>30 <lb/>See, for example, the following cases: Handyside v. United Kingdom, ECHR (1976) <lb/>Series A, No. 24, 29; Poiss v. Austria, ECHR (1987), Series A, No. 117, 108; Spor-<lb/>rong and Lönnroth v. Sweden, ECHR (1982) Series A, No. 52, 1 et seq. (hereafter re-<lb/>ferred to as Sporrong and Lönnroth); Matos e Silva, Lda. and Others v. Portugal, <lb/>ECHR (1996-IV), No. 14, 1092, para. 79; all cases also available at: <lb/>http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/search.asp?skin=hudoc-en (last visited 9 April <lb/>2009). See, for a more detailed discussion, H. R. Fabri, 'The Approach Taken by the <lb/>European Court of Human Rights to the Assessment of Compensation for "Regulatory <lb/>Expropriations of the Property of Foreign Investors"', 11 New York University Envi-<lb/>ronmental Law Journal (2002), 148-173; See also E. M. Freeman, 'Regulatory Ex-<lb/>propriation under NAFTA Chapter 11: Some Lessons from the European Court of <lb/>Human Rights', 42 Columbia Journal of Transnational Law (2003), 184-204. <lb/>31 <lb/>Sporrong and Lönnroth, supra note 29, para. 63; Fredin v. Sweden, ECHR (1991) <lb/>Series A No. 192; Starrett Housing, supra note 17, 154; Tippetts, supra note 23, 225 <lb/>et seq.; Kozacioğlu v. Turkey, judgment of 19 February 2009, para. 70; also refer to <lb/>Lauder v. Czech Republic, UNCITRAL Arbitration, Award, 3 September 2001, para. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>302 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>stantial interference with the property rights. 32 The ECHR leaves the State a <lb/>rather wide "margin of appreciation" in the implementation of their domes-<lb/>tic laws and regulations referring to expropriation. 33 However, this strand of <lb/>case law should not be over-emphasized; nor should it have "authoritative" <lb/>impact on the determination of indirect expropriation outside the European <lb/>Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Free-<lb/>doms, 34 as the Convention and its First Protocol 35 aim to set minimum stan-<lb/>dards for the protection of fundamental rights 36 and are not an investment <lb/>protection agreement and, therefore, do not intend to establish "a healthy <lb/>investment climate" -in other words, an elevated standard for the protection <lb/>of property -as BITs and MITs do. In the context of the latter, there is a <lb/>stronger emphasis on the protection of the legitimate interests of a foreign <lb/>investor. Therefore, this article proceeds from the assumption that a signifi-<lb/>cant or substantial interference with property rights, i.e. a significant reduc-<lb/>tion of value, is sufficient for the establishment of an indirect expropriation <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>198, which stated that a detrimental effect on the economic value of property is not <lb/>sufficient to constitute an expropriation. <lb/>32 <lb/>Pope &amp; Talbot Inc. v. Canada, Interim Award, 26 June 2000, paras 96-98, 102; <lb/>S. D. Myers, supra note 24, para. 283; Feldman, supra note 15, para. 110; Revere, su-<lb/>pra note 19, 258-330; Metalclad, supra note 23, para. 103; CME Czech Republic <lb/>B.V.(The Netherlands) v. Czech Republic, UNCITRAL Arbitration, Partial Award, 13 <lb/>September 2001, para. 604 (hereafter referred to as CME); Tecmed, supra note 24, pa-<lb/>ra. 115; GAMI Investment, Inc. v. Mexico, UNCITRAL Arbitration, Final Award, 15 <lb/>November 2004, para. 126; Telenor Mobile Communications A.S. v. Hungary, ICSID <lb/>Case No. ARB/04/15, Award, 13 September 2006, para. 65; LG&amp;E Energy <lb/>Corp.,supra note 8, paras 188-191; Enron Corp., supra note 8, para. 245; Eastern <lb/>Sugar B.V. v. Czech Republic, SCC Case No. 088/2004, Partial Award, 27 March <lb/>2007; M.C.I. Power Group L.C. and New Turbine, Inc. v. Ecuador, ICSID Case No. <lb/>ARB/03/6, Award, 31 July 2007, para. 300; Parkerings-Compagniet A.S. v. Lithuania, <lb/>ICSID Case No. ARB/05/8, Award, 11 September 2007; Sempra Energy, supra note <lb/>8, para. 284. See, for a brief discussion, OECD, "Indirect Expropriation" and the <lb/>"Right to Regulate" in International Investment Law, Working Papers on Internation-<lb/>al Investment No. 2004/4; available at: www.oecd.org/dataoecd/ 22/54/33776546.pdf <lb/>(last visited 11 August 2005), 10-14. <lb/>33 <lb/>Freeman, supra note 29, 189-191; ECHR, Mellacher and Others v. Austria, judgment <lb/>of December 19, 1989, Series A No. 169, para. 45. <lb/>34 <lb/>Posing the same question, see R, Dolzer, 'Indirect Expropriation: New Develop-<lb/>ments?', 11 New York University Environmental Law Journal (2002), 74. <lb/>35 <lb/>Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms of <lb/>4 November 1950 and its first Protocol; available at: www.echr.coe.int/NR/rdonlyres/ <lb/>D5CC24A7-DC13-4318-B457-5C9014916D7A/0/EnglishAnglais.pdf (last visited <lb/>1 September 2005). <lb/>36 <lb/>Compare Article 53 ECHR; see also C. Grabenwarter, Europäische Menschenrechts-<lb/>konvention, 2nd ed. (2005), §2, mn. 14. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>303 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>if the other criteria are met: first and foremost, the effect of the State meas-<lb/>ure on the legitimate expectations of the investor; and the nature of the gov-<lb/>ernmental action. <lb/>Finally, as just mentioned, an important factor to be taken into consid-<lb/>eration is the nature, i.e. the purpose and context, of the governmental ac-<lb/>tion. This issue directs our attention towards the question of whether the <lb/>State measure affecting the property rights of the foreign investor promotes <lb/>a recognized social purpose or the general welfare, e.g. public health, safety, <lb/>the rule of law, morals or welfare, etc., and whether it is carried out taking <lb/>due account of the legitimate expectations of the investor 37 with a non-<lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>37 <lb/>"Investors are ready, and can be expected to be ready, to accept the regulatory regime <lb/>in situations in which they invest [because they are in the position to make a <lb/>risk/reward assessment of their investment]. Investment protection rather turns around <lb/>the issues of unexpected changes with an excessive detrimental impact on the foreign <lb/>investor's prior calculation." Wälde &amp; Kolo, supra note 19, 819. Courts, tribunals [cf. <lb/>Aminoil, supra note 12, 1034; Phillips Petroleum Co. Iran v. Iran, 21 Iran-U.S. <lb/>C.T.R. (1989), 79 et seq.; Amoco International Finance Corporation v. Iran, 15 Iran-<lb/>U.S. C.T.R. (1987), 189 et seq.; Starrett Housing, supra note 17; Metalclad, supra <lb/>note 23, paras 89, 99; Feldman, supra note 15, paras 145 et seq.; Tecmed, supra note, <lb/>paras 91, 149 et seq., 154; International Thunderbird Gaming Corporation v. Mexico, <lb/>UNCITRAL Arbitration, Arbitral Award, 26 January 2006, para. 147; LG&amp;E Capital <lb/>Corp. and LG&amp;E International Inc. v. Argentina, ICSID Case No. ARB/02/1, Deci-<lb/>sion on Liability, 3 October 2006, para. 195 (hereafter referred to as LG&amp;E Capital). <lb/>Also, the ECHR has relied on this concept; see the ECHR cases quoted by Dolzer, su-<lb/>pra note 33, 78-79, and commentators cf. e.g. AlQurashi, supra note 22, 913; see also <lb/>Wälde &amp; Kolo, supra note 19, 821 et seq., who want to rely heavily on jurisprudence <lb/>of the U.S. Supreme Court] have frequently referred to the interpretative factor of the <lb/>"disappointment of legitimate expectations". In order to distinguish regulation from <lb/>indirect expropriation, one has to ask whether the State has frustrated the legitimate <lb/>expectations of the investor based on representations and actions of the host State. In <lb/>order to do so, one must base one's evaluation on the facts, taking into account all as-<lb/>pects of the specific case at hand. Not only contractual commitments formalize legiti-<lb/>mate expectations but also formal governmental promises in treaties, laws and even <lb/>investment brochures do so. See A. A. Fatouros, Government Guarantees to Foreign <lb/>Investors (1962), 69 et seq.; more critical: Sornarajah, supra note 1, 100 et seq.; just <lb/>recently, M. W. Reisman &amp; M. H. Arsanjani, 'The Question of Unilateral Governmen-<lb/>tal Statements as Applicable Law in Investment Disputes', 19 ICSID Review (2004), <lb/>328-343, which lacks, however, a dogmatic explanation of how a State can bind itself <lb/>by unilateral statement -despite its value as evidence for the creation of legitimate ex-<lb/>pectations within the concept of indirect expropriation or fair and equitable treatment -<lb/>in international law towards an investor which is very often not a subject of interna-<lb/>tional law; see also Southern Pacific Properties (Middle East) Ltd. and Southern Pa-<lb/>cific Properties Ltd (Hong Kong) v. Arab Republic of Egypt, ICSID Case No. <lb/>ARB/84/3, Decision on Jurisdiction and Dissenting Opinion, 14 April 1988 (hereafter <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>304 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>discriminatory, 38 non-protectionist, 39 transparent, bona fide attitude advanc-<lb/>ing legitimate State interests. A State measure advances "the common good" <lb/>if it pursues a legitimate purpose, is necessary and proportionate. 40 How-<lb/>ever, even a legitimate, non-discriminatory regulation might require com-<lb/>pensation if an individual investor is required to make a special sacrifice, i.e. <lb/>giving up legitimate expectations for enjoying his investment-backed prop-<lb/>erty, for the benefit of the society at large. 41 <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>referred to as Southern Pacific Properties), excerpts of the Decision published in <lb/>16 Yearbook Commercial Arbitration (1991), 28, para. 46. This concept allows, <lb/>firstly, to focus on the legal situation in the host State at the time when the investment <lb/>is placed in that country. Secondly, it contains the idea that an expectation deserves <lb/>more protection as it is increasingly backed by investment and, thirdly, it harbours an <lb/>element of flexibility, i.e. legitimate expectations may fade in time and there may be a <lb/>change of priorities in the host society; Dolzer, supra note 33, 78-79. <lb/>38 <lb/>"[A]ny taking that is pursuant to discriminatory or arbitrary action, or any action that <lb/>is without legitimate justification, is considered to be contrary to the non-<lb/>discrimination requirement, even absent any singling-out on the basis of nationality. <lb/>This includes prohibition of discrimination with regard to due process and payment of <lb/>compensation requirements. Moreover, the non-discrimination requirement demands <lb/>that governmental measures, procedures and practices be non-discriminatory even in <lb/>the treatment of members of the same group of aliens." UNCTAD, International In-<lb/>vestment Agreements: Key Issues, Vol. 1, 2004, 239. That also means that in order to <lb/>fall foul of the non-discrimination rule it is not required that the host State discrimi-<lb/>nates explicitly and formally against the foreign investor; it is sufficient that the State <lb/>measure is discriminatory in its effect. For the application of this notion in recent <lb/>NAFTA awards, refer to S. D. Myers, supra note 24, para. 308. See also Wälde &amp; <lb/>Kolo, supra note 19, 835-837. For an older notion of discrimination and the general <lb/>problem of its application, consult W. McKean, Equality and Discrimination under <lb/>International Law (1983); E. W. Vierdag, The Concept of Discrimination in Interna-<lb/>tional Law (1973). <lb/>39 <lb/>It is no easy task to establish the "intention" of a government. However, "formal <lb/>statements of the responsible Minister or a series of circumstances pointing to the pro-<lb/>tectionist intent being the main motivator for a policy can be taken to indicate the 'in-<lb/>tention'"; Wälde &amp; Kolo, supra note 19, 826, footnote 66. See especially the First Par-<lb/>tial Award, paras 171-195 and the separate Concurring Opinion of B. Schwartz, <lb/>paras 62-63, in S. D. Myers. <lb/>40 <lb/>Wälde &amp; Kolo, supra note 19, 827. <lb/>41 <lb/>S. Rose-Ackermann &amp; J. Rossi, 'Disentangling Deregulatory Takings', 86 Virginia <lb/>Law Review (2000), 1441-1496. See also Bundesgerichtshof (German Federal Su-<lb/>preme Court), BGHZ 6, 280; Bundesverwaltungsgericht (German Federal Administra-<lb/>tive Court), BVerwGE 5, 145; BVerwGE 19, 98. The "special sacrifice" (Son-<lb/>deropfer) concept is of primary importance in German constitutional expropriation <lb/>law but is also known to the U.S. legal order; refer to Monogahela Navigation Corp. <lb/>v. U.S., 148 US (1893), 312. Its underlying principle is discrimination, but it goes be-<lb/>yond this concept. It is intended to protect the minority against the majority, prevent-<lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>305 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>&gt;B. Scenarios of State Measures <lb/>I. State Measures Which Are Lawful by National Standards <lb/>1. First Scenario: A State Measure Which Is Lawful by Na-<lb/>tional Standards But Discriminatory <lb/>As mentioned before, as long as a government exercises its adminis-<lb/>trative powers in a transparent, non-discriminatory and lawful way with <lb/>beneficial intentions, negative effects on a foreign investment, legal or ille-<lb/>gal, are unlikely to be remediable. Rather, they are the result of the changing <lb/>business conditions inevitably linked to any business venture. Departing <lb/>from this unlikely ideal world, we turn our attention to the first of our six <lb/>scenarios. <lb/>Under Russian law, raw materials and subsoil resources are the prop-<lb/>erty of the State. 42 However, Russian law provides for the right of a third <lb/>party to acquire such assets. 43 A mining licence is the legal instrument <lb/>which is used to acquire title to a good that is being extracted from under-<lb/>ground. Due to its importance and special nature, a mining licence is typi-<lb/>cally acquired through a tender. One of the major criteria for decision under <lb/>the tender regime is the minimal amount to be extracted ("Minimal <lb/>Amount") for the purpose of ensuring the efficient use of subsoil re-<lb/>sources. 44 However, in many cases, the Minimal Amounts are not matched <lb/>in practice. Also, formal violations of law reportedly take place frequently; <lb/></body>
              
          <listBibl>ing the latter from shifting the costs of regulation to the former; see, Wälde &amp; Kolo, <lb/>supra note 19, 845. The authors of this article are aware of the fact that it is critical to <lb/>derive principles on indirect expropriation from cases decided in national fora, at least <lb/>if one draws heavily only on the case law developed in one single nation (Wälde and <lb/>Kolo indeed do so, arguing that U.S. law, as the law of the last hegemonic power, en-<lb/>joys extra authority; Wälde &amp; Kolo, supra note 19, 821-822, even if it might be the <lb/>most powerful nation at present. One must consider these national principles, but as <lb/>part of a comparative study of the rules developed in other major jurisdictions. This <lb/>approach would be in conformity with the teaching on the sources of international law <lb/>in regard to the "general principles of law" embodied in Article 38 of the Statute of <lb/>the ICJ; Dolzer, supra note 12, 69,76-78. <lb/>42 <lb/>Article 1.2 of the Russian Law "On the Subsoil" -"O nedrakh" No. 2395-I dated 21 <lb/>February 1992. <lb/>43 <lb/>Articles 1.2 and 12 of the Russian Law "On the Subsoil" -"O nedrakh" No. 2395-I <lb/>dated 21 February 1992. <lb/>44 <lb/>Article 13.1 of the Russian Law "On the Subsoil" -"O nedrakh" No. 2395-I dated 21 <lb/>February 1992. <lb/></listBibl>
            
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>306 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>that is, there are minor procedural deviations from the way the licence is to <lb/>be issued, for instance the signatures on the licence are not being made on <lb/>the document as anticipated by legislation. 45 <lb/>In our first scenario, a number of investors receive a mining licence. <lb/>The mining licence of one of these investors is withdrawn because of non-<lb/>compliance with the terms of the licence (Minimum Amounts) and due to <lb/>formal violations of the rules on licence issuance at the time of the granting <lb/>of the licence. As a consequence of the withdrawal, he goes bankrupt. Under <lb/>similar conditions, other investors' licences remain intact. <lb/>a) Russian Law <lb/>Under the Subsoil Law, the licensing authority is entitled to withdraw <lb/>the licence provided that the conditions for doing so are set out in law. 46 <lb/>However, in accordance with Articles 20 and 50 of the Subsoil Law, a licen-<lb/>see has the right to challenge the licence withdrawal in court. A licence is <lb/>seen as an act undertaken by the administration. 47 Thus, the rules established <lb/>by the Arbitration Procedure Code of the Russian Federation for challenging <lb/>administrative acts (including appealing rules) 48 have been applied. Cur-<lb/>rently, there is no body of legislation or theory in Russia which would give <lb/>guidance to public authorities when deciding upon cases dealt with by ad-<lb/>ministrative bodies; 49 in particular, there is no theory of due process. 50 As a <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>45 <lb/>As an example, see M. Pustilnik, Russian authorities show new interest in oil compa-<lb/>nies, Moscow News, 28 July 2005; available at: www.gasandoil.com/goc/news/ <lb/>ntr43548.htm (last visited 29 April 2009. <lb/>46 <lb/>Article 20 of the Russian Law No. 2395-I dated 21 February 1992 "On the Subsoil" -<lb/>"O nedrakh". <lb/>47 <lb/>It should be noted that Russian practice or law does not know of the term "administra-<lb/>tive act" as such (Verwaltungsakt). <lb/>48 <lb/>Chapter 24 of the Arbitration Procedure Code of the Russian Federation of 2002. <lb/>49 <lb/>M. Gutbrod, 'Aktualnye problemy regulirovaniya Rossiskogo bankovskogo sektora i <lb/>finansovykh rynkov', Financial Risks Management, No. 3/2005, 2 et seq. <lb/>50 <lb/>For example, the term is only mentioned in Article 4(11) of Federal Law No. 164 -<lb/>FZ, 8 December 2003 "On the Fundamental Principles of the State Regulation of For-<lb/>eign Trade Activity": "[…] the basic principles of the state regulation of foreign trade <lb/>activity shall be: […] ensuring the right to appeal, either in due process of law or in <lb/>accordance with any other procedure prescribed under the law, against any illegal ac-<lb/>tions (inaction) of governmental agencies and their officials and also the right to chal-<lb/>lenge regulatory legal acts of the Russian Federation, derogating from the right of a <lb/>participant in foreign trade activity to conduct such foreign trade activity." (emphasis <lb/>added). <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>307 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>consequence, from the perspective of the holder of a licence, there is no <lb/>body of doctrine he could rely upon when his licence is revoked. 51 In par-<lb/>ticular, there is no basis in theory to support the argument that purely formal <lb/>violations of the conditions of licensing that have no material consequences <lb/>cannot lead to the withdrawal of a licence, and the general view is that the <lb/>revocation for such formal reasons is lawful. <lb/>The argument that other investors in similar situations would not have <lb/>their licences withdrawn would also not be heard in any of the proceedings. <lb/>Whilst there is a general prohibition of discrimination under the Russian <lb/>Constitution, this has not been implemented in procedural law up to now. <lb/>Turning to the possibility of proceedings before the Constitutional <lb/>Court, due to the very complicated procedures, rules, and reasons for initia-<lb/>tion of proceedings by the Russian Constitutional Court, it is unlikely to <lb/>hear the case, although sometimes decisions of the Russian Constitutional <lb/>Court are unexpected and do not clearly follow established rules. <lb/>Furthermore, a licence is not deemed to be a property right. 52 The fact <lb/>that investors are willing to pay a higher price for a company when it has a <lb/>licence would suggest that, if the licence is looked at from an economic per-<lb/>spective, it has a value and therefore is a property right or at least is to be <lb/>treated as a property right. Nevertheless, in the commentaries 53 to the Rus-<lb/>sian Constitution, licences in general and mining licences in particular are <lb/>not mentioned as potentially being property rights, and in the few deci-<lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>51 <lb/>See, for instance, the Decision of the Federal Russian Arbitrazh Court of the District <lb/>of Moscow, No. KA-A40/4680-05, 2 June 2005. <lb/>52 <lb/>For instance, the relevant statutes in Article 2 of the Law "About licensing of different <lb/>kinds of activity", No. 128-FZ, dated 8 August 2001, give no indications in regard to <lb/>the existence of characteristics resembling property rights: possession, use and dis-<lb/>posal. In addition, the term "property right" itself is not mentioned. <lb/>53 <lb/>O. E. Kutafin, Commentary to the Russian Constitution (2003), Articles 24(1), 36(2), <lb/>55(3), 57, 75(3), and 132(1); L. L. Lasarev, Commentary to the Russian Constitution, <lb/>2003, Articles 14(6), 9(1), 24(4), 34(4), 37(1), 57(1), 58(4), 75(3), and 114(2) and (4); <lb/>W. D. Karpovich, Commentary to the Russian Constitution (2002), Articles 24(1), <lb/>37(1), 43(2), 45(2), 57, 71, 72(1), 74(1), 103(1), and 132(1); L. A. Okunkova, Com-<lb/>mentary to the Russian Constitution (1994), Articles 41, 45, and 114. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>308 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>sions 54 concerning the withdrawals of mining licences, the argument that a <lb/>licence could be a property right has not played any role. 55 <lb/>Moreover, whilst under the Constitution 56 international contracts and <lb/>maybe even custom would have precedence over national law, 57 this has <lb/>never, to the best of our knowledge, led to issues of due process (according <lb/>to international standards) or discrimination being discussed in Russian <lb/>courts. 58 <lb/>In summary, the investor is unlikely to succeed with his claim in Rus-<lb/>sian courts. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>54 <lb/>Reportedly, there have been only a few instances in which mining licences have actu-<lb/>ally been withdrawn. Even in the context of what has often been described in the press <lb/>as a crusade against Yukos, Yukos has not actually lost any of the mining licences <lb/>which reportedly violated mining legislation. <lb/>55 <lb/>Northgas v. Gazprom, Decision of the Federal Arbitrazh Court of the District of Mos-<lb/>cow, No. KA-A40/12425-04, dated 11 January 2005. <lb/>56 <lb/>Virtually all Russian authors dealing with issues of the application of international <lb/>treaties in the Russian Federation ground their positions on Article 15(4) of the Con-<lb/>stitution of the Russian Federation, which states that "[t]he universally-recognized <lb/>norms of international law and international treaties and agreements of the Russian <lb/>Federation shall be a component part of its legal system. If an international treaty or <lb/>agreement of the Russian Federation fixes rules other than those envisaged by law, the <lb/>rules of the international agreement shall be applied." See www.constitution.ru/en/ <lb/>10003000-02.htm (last visited 8 April 2009). <lb/>57 <lb/>See, for instance, T. N. Neshatayeva, International Civil Procedure (2001), 46: "A <lb/>question on the norms of jus cogens character, which mostly exist in the form of cus-<lb/>tom has already been touched upon. Considering these norms as principal ones appar-<lb/>ently witnesses that the widest application of them is possible in the practice of the RF <lb/>Constitutional Court […]. It is possible to assume that the priority of the interpretation <lb/>of jus cogens norms (norms-principles) by the RF Constitutional Court is a feasible <lb/>approach to this question for Russian judicial practice in general […] The issue be-<lb/>comes more complicated when it concerns other international legal norms of custom-<lb/>ary origin. Article 15 of the RF Constitution, and later Article 7 of the RF Civil Code <lb/>included the norms of this type (the universally-recognized norms of international <lb/>law) into the Russian legal system. But their place in the system is less clear in com-<lb/>parison to treaties […]. While hearing economical disputes in Arbitrazh Courts one <lb/>can already meet participants' references to well-known international norms of cus-<lb/>tomary character. First of all, this is true for the substantive norms contained in widely <lb/>known international conventions which are not mandatory for the Russian Federation <lb/>[…]. At this time courts are extremely cautious in appraisal of the procedural norms of <lb/>those conventions that are not in force for Russia yet." <lb/>58 <lb/>Northgas v. Gazprom, supra note, 54; Yukos, Decision of the Constitutional Court, <lb/>No. 36-O, dated 18 January 2005. <lb/></listBibl>
              
        <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>309 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>b) International Investment Agreements <lb/>The foreign investor's licence, 59 but not those of his competitors, irre-<lb/>spective of whether they are nationals of the host country or other foreign <lb/>investors, is revoked (i) due to his non-compliance with the terms of issu-<lb/>ance and (ii) due to formal deficiencies with the licence. This scenario <lb/>clearly raises the issue of discrimination, which we will focus on here. <lb/>As aforementioned, the non-discrimination requirement in the event of <lb/>indirect expropriation "demands that governmental measures, procedures <lb/>and practices be non-discriminatory even in the treatment of members of the <lb/>same group of aliens." 60 It is apparent that this is not the case here. In spite <lb/>of this, one may argue in favour of the State that the government is "merely" <lb/>enforcing the law, in other words serving the rule of law when revoking a <lb/>defective licence whose issuance terms were not followed by the investor. <lb/>Regarding the "non-compliance with the terms of the licence," under <lb/>international law the investor certainly has no legal right to have his licence <lb/>be held valid if he does not act in conformity with its terms. He was aware <lb/>of the terms at the moment of receipt and could not have had any legitimate <lb/>expectations that an illegal situation would be tolerated. A single investor or <lb/>a group of investors within a larger grouping of investors in a similar situa-<lb/>tion may have conducted their business not in compliance with the licence <lb/>conditions and, therefore, also not in compliance with the law; but even if <lb/>this is tolerated by the administration for some time, the investors cannot <lb/>rely on continued toleration of the illegal situation. The same applies to an <lb/>investor whose illegal conduct of business was not tolerated right from the <lb/>beginning. He cannot claim to be discriminated against simply because he <lb/>was being treated in compliance with the law. Any other finding would be <lb/>clearly against the rule of law and the principle of legality (Legalitätsprin-<lb/>zip). Likewise, if the administration changes its internal practice in general <lb/>in regard to the application of administrative discretion after it learns about <lb/>the illegality and begins to apply the law properly, then of course there is no <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>59 <lb/>Licences are now clearly protected by IIAs; see for example Amco Asia Corporation, <lb/>Pan American Development Limited and P.T. Amco Indonesia v. Republic of Indone-<lb/>sia, ICSID Case No. ARB/81/1, Decision Annulling the Award, 16 May 1986 (hereaf-<lb/>ter referred to as Amco (Annulment)), 25 I.L.M. (1986), 1439 et seq.; cf. also for ex-<lb/>ample Metalclad, supra note 23; Tecmed, supra note 24; see also Sornarajah, supra <lb/>note 1, 389 et seq. <lb/>60 <lb/>UNCTAD, International Investment Agreements: Key Issues, Vol. 1 (2004), 239. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>310 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>expectation which deserves to be protected. A government must have the <lb/>right to return to a state of legality. 61 <lb/>This principle was correctly applied in the Estonian Bank Licence case <lb/>(Genin (U.S.A.) v. Estonia) 62 The Central Bank of Estonia cancelled the <lb/>bank licence of the claimant in conformity with the Estonian Banking <lb/>Code 63 due to the Claimant's severe violations. The Tribunal rejected the <lb/>claim for compensation due to the fact that the Central Bank of Estonia had <lb/>carried out its supervision duty in full compliance with the law, non-<lb/>arbitrarily, and without discrimination; and in doing so, the Tribunal bal-<lb/>anced the procedural conduct of the government and the (illegal) conduct of <lb/>the investor. <lb/>However, one must ask whether the same reasoning can be applied if <lb/>the government fails generally to enforce a certain law -which it was <lb/>obliged to do without any discretion and was able to enforce -when it just <lb/>picks one out of a group of investors in a similar (illegal) situation and sud-<lb/>denly enforces the given law only against this one particular investor, while <lb/>claiming to serve the rule of law? We do not think so. 64 If a statute fails to <lb/>create its intended "equal treatment" generally by systematic illegal execu-<lb/>tion 65 of the law, then the proper application in one or a few instances would <lb/>constitute a violation of the non-discrimination requirement. Equality under <lb/>the law means first and foremost equal application of it. 66 Even if the inves-<lb/>tor is not entitled to demand treatment which is against the law, he has the <lb/>right to demand that the State not apply the law in his case differently from <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>61 <lb/>Of the same opinion but not differentiating: AlQurashi, supra note 22, 914. <lb/>62 <lb/>Alex Genin, Eastern Credit Limited, Inc. and A.S. Baltoil v. The Republic of Estonia, <lb/>ICSID Case No. ARB/99/2, Award, 25 June 2001. <lb/>63 <lb/>Even if a revocation of a licence is well justified, the State must act with procedural <lb/>regularity; otherwise, it would be held liable to pay compensation. In Middle Eastern <lb/>Cement Shipping and Metalclad, the host State was not held liable for the cancellation <lb/>of the licence but for a lack of due process, especially for a lack of transparency. <lb/>64 <lb/>For a more detailed and principled account of this issue cf. S. Hindelang, 'No Equals <lb/>in Wrong? The Issue of Equality in a State of Illegality', 7 Journal of World Invest-<lb/>ment and Trade 6 (2006), 883-897. <lb/>65 <lb/>This means that the investor should be able to demonstrate that the State, in respect to <lb/>the other instances, was not acting due to ignorance of these instances or legal obsta-<lb/>cles which would bar it from enforcing the law in question but due to reasons unre-<lb/>lated to the aforementioned. <lb/>66 <lb/>V. Götz, 'Über die "Gleichheit im Unrecht"', in O. Bachof et al. (eds), Verwaltungs-<lb/>recht zwischen Freiheit, Teilhabe und Bindung: Festgabe aus Anlass des 25jährigen <lb/>Bestehens des Bundesverwaltungsgerichts (1978), 254. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>311 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>how it applies it in other cases. 67 Thus, the investor has the right to be pro-<lb/>tected from the burden of an application of a previously unenforced law as <lb/>long as the State does not return to a state of legality in all similar cases. 68 In <lb/>order to avoid abusing the argument regarding intentions to return to a state <lb/>of legality, which is in principle the obligation of the host State, the host <lb/>State must demonstrate that it enforces the given law now in all situations <lb/>similar to that of the investor. If a host State lacks the capabilities to handle <lb/>all cases at once, it must demonstrate that the enforcement of a given law <lb/>against the investor is the first instance in a uniform conceptual approach <lb/>towards the state of legality. 69 <lb/>With regard to our scenario, this would mean that the State should be <lb/>barred from pleading that it serves the principle of legality as long as it fails <lb/>to demonstrate that it is truly returning to a state of legality. 70 Thus, the <lb/>treatment of the investor must be characterized as arbitrary, discriminatory <lb/>and exposing him to sectional prejudice. The investor "expects the State to <lb/>use the legal instruments that govern the actions of the investor or the in-<lb/>vestment in conformity with the function usually assigned to such instru-<lb/>ments." 71 <lb/>The answer to the question of whether a revocation of the licence on <lb/>the grounds of a "formal violation" of the law on licence issuance is subject <lb/>to the provisions of the IIAs on indirect expropriation depends, firstly, on <lb/>whether the investor was able to remedy this revocation immediately at the <lb/>moment of announcement. If he, however, did not do so due to the fact that <lb/>the rules on licence issuance lacked clarity or were contradictory, then those <lb/>formal defects should not destroy the investor's legitimate expectations for <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>67 <lb/>It is important to note that this observation applies only to the situation in which the <lb/>State is obliged by law to interfere with a right of an investor in a certain way without <lb/>any discretion but does so only on a selective basis. This is not to be confused with the <lb/>notion of "no equality in wrong" (keine Gleichheit im Unrecht), in German constitu-<lb/>tional doctrine. For the distinction -a detailed outline would go beyond the scope of <lb/>this article -refer to C. Kölbel, Gleichheit "im Unrecht" (1998). <lb/>68 <lb/>Id., 80, especially p. 141 (English summary); an argument stating that the principle of <lb/>legality demands the immediate proper execution of the law in question against the <lb/>investor implies that the principle of legality takes precedence of the principle of <lb/>equality. This is doubtful. The principle of legality carries inherently the demand of <lb/>due application of the principle of equality; Id., 43, 83. <lb/>69 <lb/>Id., 82, 90. <lb/>70 <lb/>An exception might be necessary in situations in which immediate action is necessary <lb/>in order to avert damage to live and limb. <lb/>71 <lb/>Tecmed, supra note 24, para. 154. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>312 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>the continuing validity of the licence. 72 In the words of one commentator, <lb/>governments "should not be able to rely on legal and formal technicalities if <lb/>they consistently (in particular with respect to nationals) disregard such <lb/>technicalities or if such technicalities were not discernible to the investor <lb/>and its domestic legal advisers for reasons of lack of transparency." 73 This <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>72 <lb/>See, in general, on the issue of transparency in IIAs, UNCTAD, Transparency, UNC-<lb/>TAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreements, 2004, especially 63; <lb/>available at: www.unctad.org/en/docs/iteiit20034_en.pdf (last visited 30 August <lb/>2005). <lb/>73 <lb/>T. Wälde, 'Investment Arbitration under the Energy Charter Treaty: An Overview of <lb/>Key Issues', 1 Transnational Dispute Management (2004) 2; available at: <lb/>www.transnational-dispute-management.com (last visited 11 August 2005). The con-<lb/>cept of transparency arrived late in international investment law. In regard to the stan-<lb/>dard of treatment, two cases deserve to be mentioned. In Metalclad, supra note, 23, <lb/>para. 76, the NAFTA Tribunal defined the concept of transparency (stated in Article <lb/>1802 NAFTA) as requiring the following: "[…] all relevant legal requirements for the <lb/>purpose of initiating, completing and successfully operating investments made, or in-<lb/>tended to be made, under the Agreement should be capable of being readily known to <lb/>all affected investors of another Party." If a State becomes aware of "confusion or <lb/>misunderstanding" among investors concerning the legal requirements to be fulfilled, <lb/>the Party would have "the duty to ensure that the correct position [would be] promptly <lb/>determined and clearly stated so that the investors can proceed with all appropriate <lb/>expedition in the confident belief that they are acting in accordance with all relevant <lb/>laws" (summary taken from OECD, Fair and Equitable Treatment Standard in Inter-<lb/>national Law, Working Papers on International Investment, No. 2004/3, 37). Since <lb/>Mexico had failed to provide such a framework, it was held liable for breach of the <lb/>fair and equitable treatment standard. However, this reading was rejected in a review <lb/>by the Supreme Court of British Columbia on the grounds that the treaty obligation of <lb/>transparency was outside Chapter Eleven and, thus, outside the fair and equitable <lb/>treatment standard. Moreover, the NAFTA Tribunal was charged to have failed to <lb/>have put forward any evidence that the obligation of transparency has become cus-<lb/>tomary international law. Also, in Maffezini, a lack of transparency in administrative <lb/>conduct was established, which led the Tribunal, in connection with other factors, to <lb/>the conclusion that Spain had violated the fair and equitable treatment standard con-<lb/>tained in the Spain-Argentina BIT. No explanation was given on the precise meaning <lb/>of the lack of transparency. See Maffezini (Argentina) v. Kingdom of Spain, ICSID <lb/>Case No. ARB/97/7, Award, 13 November 2000. See also UNCTAD, Transparency, <lb/>UNCTAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreements, 2004, especially <lb/>63, available at www.unctad.org/en/docs/iteiit20034_en.pdf (last visited 9 April <lb/>2009); J. Jr. Hanna, 'Is Transparency of Governmental Administration Customary In-<lb/>ternational Law in Investor-Sovereign Arbitrations? -Courts and Arbitrators May Dif-<lb/>fer', 21 Arbitration International (2005), 187. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>313 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>reasoning is supported by the Decision in the SwemBalt case (Swe-<lb/>den v. Latvia) 74 and the Metalclad case. 75 <lb/>Moreover, even if the investor learns about a violation of national <lb/>laws and the government continues for some time to tolerate this situation, <lb/>the investor must be protected. If the government later suddenly started en-<lb/>forcing the law in a discriminatory fashion, the same reasoning as that ad-<lb/>vanced above would apply. But even if the government acts in a non-<lb/>discriminatory way, it should be liable for compensation if it fails to enforce <lb/>the law non-proportionately, for example without a transitional period for <lb/>the old, by national standards "unlawful", investments. Keeping in mind that <lb/>IIAs, among other functions, intend to promote rules of good governance, <lb/>the requirements for the host State, though depending on the individual cir-<lb/>cumstances, should not be too low. 76 One might therefore conclude that a <lb/>State, by consistently disregarding legal formalities at the time it issues li-<lb/>cences, loses its right to withdraw such licences for those formal violations <lb/>if it does not conduct the withdrawal with procedural regularity and in a <lb/>non-discriminatory manner. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>74 <lb/>Reported by K. Hobér, 'Investment Arbitration in Eastern Europe: Recent Cases on <lb/>Expropriation', 14 American Review of International Arbitration (2003), 407. This <lb/>case was concerned with the removal and subsequent public auctioning of a ship by <lb/>Latvian governmental officials due to an alleged breach of a lease contract on an an-<lb/>chorage. The Tribunal based its finding of indirect expropriation on the failure of the <lb/>government to inform the investor about the (alleged) invalidity (retroactive change of <lb/>laws) of the lease contract in due time (four months inactivity) and cacophonic state-<lb/>ments of a governmental official, the participation of governmental officers in the (al-<lb/>leged) illegal activity of concluding the lease contract and the missing proportionality <lb/>between the (alleged) wrongful act of the investor and State measures; id., 414. <lb/>75 <lb/>The NAFTA Tribunal in Metalclad dealt with a case in which the investor did not <lb/>obey the local building and environmental rules and thus acted unlawfully in regard to <lb/>national rules. However, representations were made by governmental officials who <lb/>were not aware of their own legal order. It was held that the investor's legitimate ex-<lb/>pectations in the lawfulness of his undertaking cannot be destroyed if he learns about <lb/>the illegality of the investment after it was made. Refer also to J. Paulsson &amp; Z. Doug-<lb/>las, 'Indirect Expropriation in Investment Treaty Arbitrations', in N. Horn, (ed.), Arbi-<lb/>trating Foreign Investment Disputes (2004), 154-157. <lb/>76 <lb/>Wälde, supra note 72. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>314 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>2. Second Scenario: A State Measure Which Is Lawful by Na-<lb/>tional Standards But Discriminatory and Accompanied With <lb/>Mala Fide <lb/>In our second scenario, the mining licence is defective as in [scenario <lb/>1. The government does not want to withdraw the mining licence because it <lb/>fears negative consequences for the country's reputation as a location for <lb/>investment. It therefore suddenly, without giving any prior notice, starts <lb/>enforcing a certain tax rule or changes the interpretation of a certain tax rule <lb/>in general, knowing, however, that this change in administrative practice <lb/>hits only a certain investor or even intending to hit a certain investor. As a <lb/>consequence, one foreign company goes bankrupt. <lb/>a) Russian Law <lb/>Russian law does not sanction a State organ changing the interpreta-<lb/>tion of tax legislation. The fact that the intention of the taxation was not to <lb/>obtain money but rather to harm (mala fide) would not change this analysis. <lb/>Also, as already mentioned above, outside the Constitution there is no pro-<lb/>hibition of discrimination under Russian law. Whilst Russian law, in par-<lb/>ticular constitutional law, recognizes the principle of non-discrimination, the <lb/>literature 77 has apparently only dealt with the implications of this principle <lb/>for investors at the beginning of their investment activity, and court practice <lb/>has up to now not taken up these principles. 78 <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements <lb/>Changing and adapting national taxation regimes is in general not <lb/>considered to be an illegitimate regulation but something necessary to main-<lb/>tain and further the overall development and prosperity of a society. 79 As <lb/>already mentioned, in principle a foreign investor cannot have any legiti-<lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>77 <lb/>S. Krupko, 'Investition agreements and disputes between countries and private foreign <lb/>investors', in Business and Law (Attachment No. 5, 5/2001), 6, 14-15, 17-18; <lb/>S. Krupko, 'Investment activity in the constituent entities of the Russian Federation', <lb/>in Business and Law (No. 10/2000), 42. <lb/>78 <lb/>Id. <lb/>79 <lb/>Paulsson &amp; Douglas, supra note 74, 155-156; R. Dolzer, Eigentum, Enteignung und <lb/>Entschädigung im geltenden Völkerrecht (1985), 252; Newcombe &amp; Paradell, supra <lb/>note 6, 358, para. 7.24. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>315 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>mate expectation that a given tax regime is not subject to any alterations. <lb/>This was confirmed, for example, in the awards in Feldman 80 and Goetz. 81 <lb/>In the scenario at hand, however, the situation might be different. If <lb/>the administration suddenly starts enforcing a certain tax rule in general, <lb/>knowing, however, that it hits only a certain investor or even intending this, <lb/>then several conflicting interests need to be balanced. On the one hand, a <lb/>State must have the right to adapt its tax policy to new situations, maybe <lb/>even implementing the recommendations of international expert panels. If <lb/>the tax rules are applied in law and in fact non-discriminatorily, and if this <lb/>change can be seen as proportionate in regard to the ends pursued with the <lb/>change, then it is the ordinary risk of doing business when a certain com-<lb/>pany might not be able to pay its taxes due to its financial situation, i.e. in-<lb/>sufficient profits, and this could happen even if the host State was aware of <lb/>this effect. 82 On the other hand, a discriminating effect, not in law but in <lb/>fact, but originating from sudden and unexpected changes accompanied by <lb/>mala fide intentions should be remedied by IIAs if the damage suffered by a <lb/>foreign investor is "substantial". 83 The investor can reasonably expect that <lb/>tax laws are not used for protective aims or political purposes totally unre-<lb/>lated to taxation but for the functions usually assigned to them. It was also <lb/>sudden, unreasonable and unpredictable changes in the application of law, <lb/>though not a tax law, which led to the finding in favour of the investor in the <lb/>CME case. 84 <lb/>From a host State point of view, one could argue in defence of meas-<lb/>ures taken that the same result (bankruptcy) would have also been inflicted <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>80 <lb/>Feldman, supra note 15, para. 109-111. <lb/>81 <lb/>Goetz and others v. Burundi, ICSID Case No. ARB/95/3, Award, 10 February 1999, <lb/>para. 124. Refer also to Paulsson &amp; Douglas, supra note 74, 155. See, for the taxation <lb/>of windfall profits of the oil industry, the Aminoil case, supra note 12; for the situation <lb/>in the United States, U.S. v. Ptasynki, 462 US (1983), 74 et seq. <lb/>82 <lb/>Kügele v. Polish State, Upper Silesian Arbitral Tribunal Case, 5 February 1932, Amt-<lb/>liche Sammlung von Entscheidungen des Schiedsgerichts für Oberschlesien, Vol. 3 <lb/>(1931), 20. See also H. Lauterpacht, Annual Digest of Public International Law <lb/>Cases, Vol. 6 (1931/32), 69. <lb/>83 <lb/>"Substantial damage" is understood in the sense that a profitable usage of the invest-<lb/>ment is impossible; R. Dolzer, Eigentum, Enteignung und Entschädigung im gelten-<lb/>den Völkerrecht (1985), 252 et seq. Refer also to Dolzer, supra note 12, 78. <lb/>84 <lb/>CME, supra note 31. The actions and non-actions of the Czech Media Council were <lb/>not part of proper administrative process (no justification for the sudden change in the <lb/>interpretation of the legal situation or other regulatory measures and its enforcement <lb/>(1996) and the illegal collusion (1999) with a Czech national with a protectionist in-<lb/>tent). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>316 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>upon the investor by a mining licence withdrawal. Such an argument, how-<lb/>ever, does not seem very convincing. Even if a licence withdrawal could <lb/>have been conducted in a non-discriminatory, transparent manner with a <lb/>bona fide intention, as referred to in the first scenario, the plea of a "hypo-<lb/>thetical alternative lawful conduct" would not rule out the finding of indirect <lb/>expropriation 85 , but might, and this is certainly a very cautious 'might', only <lb/>have an effect on the determination of the damages. 86 Thus, to sum up, the <lb/>conduct of the tax authorities must undoubtedly be attributed to the host <lb/>State. 87 The discriminatory application of tax laws coupled with mala fide in <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>85 <lb/>A first, rather simple argument relates to the rules of causality. An infringement of a <lb/>given right cannot be imputed to someone if it can be demonstrated that the infringe-<lb/>ment would also have been caused if this person had acted correctly. For the example <lb/>here, this would mean that the infringement (indirect expropriation) would also have <lb/>occurred if the host State had lawfully revoked the licence. This apparently is not the <lb/>case. Thus, the host State must have inflicted the infringement. A second argument <lb/>may be drawn from the second Amco v. Indonesia Award on the Merits, Amco Asia <lb/>Corporation and Others v. The Republic of Indonesia, ICSID Case No. ARB/81/1, <lb/>Resubmitted, Award on the Merits, 31 May 1990 (hereafter referred to as Amco II <lb/>(Merits)), in para. 143, the Tribunal states: "[E]ven were a decision on grounds other <lb/>than those stated in the Degree in principle sustainable, they could no more be lawful <lb/>than the decision made on grounds of shortfall of investment, because of the general <lb/>background that pervaded the decision-making." It does not matter that the same re-<lb/>sult could have been reached in another way, i.e. that the foreign investment could <lb/>have also been adversely affected by measures which are in principle sustainable; it is <lb/>only the process of how this result is reached (and that this process was ultimately <lb/>malconducted) which matters. Of the same opinion: Sornarajah, supra note 1, 390. <lb/>86 <lb/>It is open to question whether all of the loss inflicted upon the foreign investor by the <lb/>discriminatory application of certain tax laws can be attributed to the host State due to <lb/>the fact that substantial damages would have occurred also in the case of a lawful (in <lb/>terms of public international law) revocation of the licence. The Amco II (Merits) <lb/>Award casts doubts on this; in para. 174, it reads: "To argue, as did Indonesia, that al-<lb/>though there had been procedural irregularities, a 'fair BKPM' [the governmental <lb/>body acting on behalf of Indonesia] would still have revoked the licence, because of <lb/>Amco's own shortcomings, is to misaddress causality. The Tribunal cannot pronounce <lb/>upon what a 'fair BKPM' would have done. This is both speculative, and not the issue <lb/>before it. Rather, it is required to characterise the acts that BKPM did engage in and to <lb/>see if those acts, if unlawful, caused damage to Amco. It is not required to see if, had <lb/>it acted fairly, harm might then rather have been attributed to Amco's own fault." <lb/>87 <lb/>See the Draft Articles on Responsibility of States for Internationally Wrongful Acts <lb/>adopted by the International Law Commission at its fifty-third session (2001), avail-<lb/>able at http://untreaty.un.org/ilc/texts/instruments/english/draft%20articles/9_6_2001. <lb/>pdf (last visited 22.April.2009) See also Commentaries to the Draft Articles on Re-<lb/>sponsibility of States for Internationally Wrongful Acts adopted by the International <lb/>Law Commission at its fifty-third session (2001), available at: http://untreaty.un.org/ <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>317 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>the way described above that has a severe impact on the foreign investment <lb/>constitutes an indirect expropriation. <lb/>As for the standards of proof it will be no easy task for any investor to <lb/>establish the "intention" of a government. 88 However, the "formal state-<lb/>ments of the responsible Minister or a series of circumstances pointing to <lb/>the protectionist intent being the main motivator for a policy can be taken to <lb/>indicate the 'intention'." 89 Therefore, since the internal governmental papers <lb/>which reveal the true intention of a government are often -understandably -<lb/>not accessible in their entirety to international tribunals, in order to prevent <lb/>cacophonic statements, governments are well advised to keep their high <lb/>ranking officials, to whose statements international tribunals would have to <lb/>turn, under close check until a final position has emerged within the gov-<lb/>ernment; 90 they are best off developing a public communications strategy <lb/>handled by experts. <lb/>3. Third Scenario: Investor Contributing to Bankruptcy <lb/>An investor holds a legally valid mining licence. The government <lb/>starts enforcing a certain tax rule or changes the interpretation of a certain <lb/>tax rule in general, with the stated aim to test the ability of companies to pay <lb/>taxes. As the investor is afraid that his company will not survive, he with-<lb/>draws money from the company. As a consequence, the company goes <lb/>bankrupt. <lb/>a) Russian Law <lb/>When considering a law, a Russian court would typically look at the <lb/>letter of the law and not at the intention of the lawmaker. As a consequence, <lb/>if the pure letter of the law does not violate the Constitution, the intention of <lb/>the lawmaker would not play any role and, to the best of our knowledge, the <lb/>intention of the lawmaker has not played any role in decisions of courts, <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>ilc/texts/instruments/english/commentaries/9_6_2001.pdf (last visited 22.April.2009) <lb/>For academic writing, see, instead of others, Brownlie, supra note 15, 420-456 with <lb/>further references. <lb/>88 <lb/>Newcombe &amp; Paradell, supra note 6, 342. <lb/>89 <lb/>Wälde &amp; Kolo, supra note 19, 826. See especially the First Partial Award, para. 171-<lb/>195 and the Separate Opinion of B. Schwartz, para. 62-64 in S.D.Myers, supra note <lb/>24. <lb/>90 <lb/>Difficulties in finding officials with adequate training should not serve a host State as <lb/>a valid defence, since it signed the IIA fully aware of its duties and the quality of its <lb/>officials. <lb/></listBibl>
        
        <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>318 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>even in cases where laws have been considered illegal. 91 A fortiori, it is not <lb/>likely to be of importance if the implementation of a law is the means by <lb/>which an illegal decision is to be implemented. The action of a government <lb/>would therefore clearly be legal. The same would apply if no new tax provi-<lb/>sion is enacted but an already existing provision is interpreted in a different <lb/>way. 92 In both cases, the outlook for an investor is not promising. <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements <lb/>In this scenario, much depends on the representations the government <lb/>made to the foreign investor in regard to the tax regime. Did the govern-<lb/>ment, for example, include a stabilization clause in the licence agreement, <lb/>ensuring that taxes and other financial liabilities would remain as agreed for <lb/>the duration of the concession? Then, the investor can reasonably expect <lb/>than the tax regime will remain unchanged and raise this in the BIT context. <lb/>If the government changes the law despite these representations and, as a <lb/>result, the company finds it difficult to continue operations and closes op-<lb/>erations, then the government appears to be liable under international law <lb/>irrespective of the company's decision to close down, as the decision in Re-<lb/>vere suggests. 93 Otherwise, the host State's measures are lawful if executed <lb/>without any discrimination. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>91 <lb/>Decision of the Russian Constitutional Court, No. 15, dated 16 July 2005. <lb/>92 <lb/>For example, Article 113 of the Tax Code, No. 146-FZ, dated 31 July 1998 (as effec-<lb/>tive on the date when the Yukos Decision of the Constitutional Court was passed), <lb/>stated that "a person cannot be held liable for a tax offense if three years (the statute of <lb/>limitations) have expired since the day when the offense was committed or since the <lb/>first day after the end of the tax period during which the offense committed." (this Ar-<lb/>ticle of the Tax Code was amended on 27 July 2006). In the Yukos Decision of the <lb/>Constitutional Court, No. 36-O, dated 18 January 2005, the Court re-interpreted this <lb/>provision to apply only for "conscientious" taxpayers. It was deemed not to apply to <lb/>"un-conscientious" taxpayers, which Yukos was found to be. However, the wording of <lb/>the statute does not actually provide a basis for this interpretation. <lb/>93 <lb/>Revere, supra note 19, 291 "In our view, the effects of the Jamaican Government's <lb/>actions in repudiating its long term commitments to RJA (the subsidiary of RC), have <lb/>substantially the same impact on effective control over use and operation as if the <lb/>properties were themselves conceded by a concession contract that was repudiated <lb/>[…]" For a discussion, refer to R. Dolzer, 'Indirect Expropriation of Alien Property', <lb/>1 ICSID Review (1986), 41-65, Sornarajah, supra note 1, 378-380. In contrast, in the <lb/>Elsi case, the foreign company, in the view of the Court, went bankrupt because of its <lb/>own financial situation and not because of the action of the host State; Elettronica Si-<lb/>cula S.p.A. (U.S. v. Italy), Award, ICJ Reports 1989, 15, para 119.. <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>319 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>4. Fourth Scenario: Mala Fide, Investor Acting Unlawfully <lb/>An investor holds a legally valid mining licence. He has used money <lb/>in an unlawful manner, including by bribing officials, to ensure that taxation <lb/>of revenues derived from the mining licence is not fully enforced against his <lb/>business. Nevertheless, certain taxation rules are suddenly generally en-<lb/>forced, leading to the bankruptcy of the investor, which had been the ulti-<lb/>mate intention of the State. <lb/>a) Russian Law <lb/>As discussed above, under Russian law the intention of any State ac-<lb/>tion is not relevant. Accordingly, it cannot possibly be relevant to balance <lb/>various interests against each other. <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements <lb/>Legitimate expectations can only be vested in a legitimate business <lb/>venture. In the given case, the entrepreneur uses illegal means to acquire a <lb/>competitive advantage. If the host State were to enforce its criminal laws to <lb/>prevent the foreign investor from doing so and bring him to justice, this <lb/>would be a legitimate exercise of administrative powers. However, the <lb/>situation at hand poses another question. Is it justifiable that the State inten-<lb/>tionally bankrupts an investor using taxation law as means of punishment, <lb/>thus attributing functions to that law which an investor cannot reasonably <lb/>foresee, in order to prosecute and remedy the criminal offences committed <lb/>by the foreign investor? <lb/>If the bankruptcy is the consequence of an unbiased, non-<lb/>discriminatory and proportionate prosecution carried out in good faith, es-<lb/>pecially if the bankruptcy relates to the payment of taxes owed, penalties <lb/>due and the conviction of the investor in criminal proceedings, a State <lb/>should not be held liable for the bankruptcy. However, a host State should <lb/>by no means be able to plead the tu quoque argument, since it is generally <lb/>bound to the notion of legality, in contrast to a private actor. It should, there-<lb/>fore, not be allowed to (ab)use the violation of the law by the foreign inves-<lb/>tor as a reason to disregard any due process requirements, one of which is to <lb/>apply the laws in conformity with the functions assigned to them. 94 By using <lb/></body>
              
        <listBibl>94 <lb/>Tecmed, supra note 24, para. 154. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>320 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>taxation law, which does not have a function of acting as penalization for <lb/>criminal charges (e.g. bribery), those due process requirements are in-<lb/>fringed, since no investor can reasonably foresee such an application. More-<lb/>over, the host State is also required to conduct the prosecution of allegedly <lb/>criminal behaviour committed by the foreign investor itself using due proc-<lb/>ess. The investment only "loses" protection in so far as it is erected on ille-<lb/>gal groundings. Any deprivation or diminishment of property rights beyond <lb/>this point cannot be justified. The principle that the taking of property "as <lb/>means of the exaction of a criminal penalty is lawful" 95 and that it does not <lb/>need to be compensated has been overridden by the groundbreaking changes <lb/>brought by IIAs. 96 <lb/>II. State Action Which Is Unlawful by National Standards <lb/>1. Fifth Scenario: Unlawful State Action Against the Man-<lb/>agement, Management Personally Involved in Crimes <lb/>In our fifth scenario, a foreign investor runs his business venture in a <lb/>legal manner. However, the management is personally involved in crimes. <lb/>The investor is imprisoned, however not for the personal crime that he has <lb/>allegedly committed, but for a completely unrelated tax matter. The ultimate <lb/>intention of the government is to hit the business. As a consequence of the <lb/>management being imprisoned, banks withdraw their loans and, as a conse-<lb/>quence of that, the business goes bankrupt. <lb/>a) Russian Law <lb/>As frequently reported in the press, Mr Khodorkovsky was imprisoned <lb/>in 2004 for committing violations of tax legislation and subsequently con-<lb/>demned to serve many years for those tax violations. The arguments report-<lb/>edly made by people close to Mr Khodorkovsky and by himself included <lb/>that, in reality, the reason for the imprisonment was not the violation of tax <lb/>legislation but the intention of Mr Khodorkovsky to get involved in politics <lb/>and the desire of the Russian State to acquire his wealth, namely the Yukos <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>95 <lb/>Sornarajah, supra note 1, 390. <lb/>96 <lb/>Id., 390. See, for the old state of the law, A.V. Freeman, The International Responsi-<lb/>bility of States for Denial of Justice (1938), 518, footnote 2. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>321 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Group. However, in the decisions publicly available, 97 this argument has <lb/>never been considered, and there is no evidence that it has been used by <lb/>representatives of Yukos and/or Mr Khodorkovsky as a legal defence. Ig-<lb/>noring the intentions of the State in the results of legal proceedings in this <lb/>manner does coincide with what most Russian lawyers would confirm as <lb/>their view, namely that measures taken by the State against an individual <lb/>would not have any impact when considering the legal merits of an action <lb/>against a group of companies in the context of assessing an action that could <lb/>potentially constitute an indirect expropriation. <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements <lb/>Prosecution of crimes is the duty and prerogative of any State and, <lb/>thus, is viewed as legitimate State action. As already stated, if the bank-<lb/>ruptcy is the consequence of an "orderly" prosecution, then the State is not <lb/>liable for the bankruptcy. However, it is also generally accepted that an un-<lb/>justified "attack" on the management is regarded as an "attack" on the in-<lb/>vestment because the foreign investor is entitled to organize and control his <lb/>business venture as a part of the bunch of property rights protected by an <lb/>IIA. 98 Here again, the intention and the nature of the governmental actions <lb/>would be the decisive criteria. If charges are only brought up "artificially" <lb/>with an intention to bankrupt the investor, the State conduct will come <lb/>within the reach of an IIA. This is necessary in order to protect foreign in-<lb/>vestment comprehensively as envisaged in the IIAs. Thus, indirectly, IIAs <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>97 <lb/>Yukos Decision of the Russian Constitutional Court, No. 36-O, dated 18 January 2005, <lb/>the only decision on the Yukos case available in a public database, as explained above, <lb/>deals with technical issues of the interpretation of tax legislation rather than with the <lb/>overall economical effect of government action. <lb/>98 <lb/>See Tokios Tokelés v. Ukraine, ICSID Case No. ARB/02/18, Decision on Jurisdiction, <lb/>24 April 2004, paras 91-93. In the case at hand: "Tokelés claimed that, following its <lb/>publication of a book favourable to a leading Ukrainian government opposition leader, <lb/>Ukrainian government authorities: (1) conducted numerous invasive investigations <lb/>falsely disguised as tax investigations; (2) initiated frivolous actions in Ukrainian do-<lb/>mestic courts, including actions to invalidate contracts entered into by Tokelés's sub-<lb/>sidiary; (3) placed the subsidiary's assets under administrative arrest; (4) unreasonably <lb/>seized financial and other documents and (5) falsely accused its subsidiary of engag-<lb/>ing in illegal activities." The American Society of International Law, International <lb/>Law in Brief, 25 June 2004; available at: www.asil.org/ilib/ilib0711.htm#j3 (last vis-<lb/>ited 22 April 2009). See also Sedco, Inc. v. National Iranian Oil Company, 9 Iran-<lb/>U.S.C.T.R. (1985), 248 (appointment of directors by the State; not concerned with any <lb/>criminal prosecution); Biloune case, supra note 23. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>322 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>seem to have also a moderating, good governance effect on the prosecution <lb/>of crimes, at least in regard to a foreign investor. However, a criminal inves-<lb/>tigation which raises issues of human rights violations would not be remedi-<lb/>able in international investment law; it would be a case for an international <lb/>human rights convention like the ECHR. 99 <lb/>2. Sixth Scenario: Illegality "All Around" <lb/>The foreign investor uses its company for financing a political cam-<lb/>paign against taxation of oil proceeds in order to create a favourable busi-<lb/>ness environment, including gaining significant influence on the State's <lb/>legislature and administration for its company. The campaign, however, is <lb/>partially illegal under the laws of the host country. Also, the investor is in-<lb/>volved in murder and in bribing officials responsible for the prosecution of <lb/>the murders in order to secure its favourable business environment. As a <lb/>consequence, the foreign investor gains significant influence on the process <lb/>of forming the host State's will. The State takes action illegal under the <lb/>State's law against the company and the investor with a view to stop these <lb/>activities. These activities comprise the engineering of arbitrary and un-<lb/>founded tax claims, the arbitrary and non-proportionate seizure of produc-<lb/>tion facilities, the arbitrary freezing of funds, the harassment of the man-<lb/>agement, non-transparent investigations and a public auction which from the <lb/>beginning is anything but open to bidders other than the pre-chosen winner. <lb/>All these activities are conducted with the view to drive the company out of <lb/>the business (total loss), at which the State ultimately succeeded. <lb/>a) Russian Law <lb/>As discussed above, intentions are not relevant under Russian law. <lb/>This is particularly true for intentions of State action. 100 There nothing in the <lb/>literature, practice or in discussions with Russian lawyers suggesting that <lb/>any interconnection between actions against a shareholder and a company <lb/>from a legal point of view would be accepted as making a difference under <lb/>Russian law. In addition, whilst under Russian law there are rather detailed <lb/>legal provisions about national emergency, no evidence of a theory of extra-<lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>99 <lb/>Biloune, supra note 23, para.1. <lb/>100 <lb/>As above, see as an example the Decision of the Russian Constitutional Court, <lb/>18 January 2005, No. 36-O. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>323 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>legal emergency, for instance during a constitutional breakdown, could be <lb/>found. 101 <lb/>b) International Investment Agreements <lb/>By means of a (partially illegal) political campaign 102 and criminal ac-<lb/>tivities, 103 a foreign investor created a favourable business environment for <lb/>his company. In this process he gained significant influence on all three <lb/>branches of government of the host State and ultimately to a significant ex-<lb/>tent controlled the process of forming the political will in the host State. An <lb/>orderly prosecution became impossible due to the political influence of the <lb/>foreign investor. The corrupting activities of the investor started to threaten <lb/>the very democratic order in the country. In order to stop these activities and <lb/>with a view to return to a state of lawfulness, non-corrupted parts of the <lb/>government take steps to dismantle the influence of the foreign investor by <lb/>bankrupting him. In the course of action as prescribed above, the title of <lb/>property is either transferred by auction to another entity or the investment <lb/>is completely devaluated. This scenario drives the point even further to the <lb/>extremes and poses the question of where the boundaries of the protection <lb/>of a foreign investment by an IIA are to be drawn. <lb/>By taking the measures described above, the host State pursues le-<lb/>gitimate objectives: securing State order, democracy and pluralism and re-<lb/>erecting the rule of law. However, does this give the State the right to take <lb/>recourse to any means at its disposal? We would like to suggest that propor-<lb/>tionality has to be retained also in such cases. Even if the intention of the <lb/>government is to return to a state of lawfulness and to secure the continuing <lb/>operation of such a noble concept as democracy, and even though the for-<lb/></body>
              
        <listBibl>101 <lb/>A search in the most commonly used legal database on "extra-legal emergency" as of <lb/>8 April 2009 gave no results. <lb/>102 <lb/>The interference in domestic politics by foreign investors seen as agents of their home <lb/>State is a well-known instance (as with Allende in Chile) and has been addressed by <lb/>prohibition in many soft-law instruments (voluntary codes of conduct). However, no <lb/>hard-law international obligation has arisen so far. In general, there has been little <lb/>movement in formulating binding obligations of foreign investors (multinational cor-<lb/>porations). Refer to Sornarajah, supra note 1, 171, 174-182. Moreover, in general, <lb/>home States do not carry responsibility for the acts of their nationals not acting on be-<lb/>half of the home State abroad; refer to Article 4-11 of the International Law Com-<lb/>mision's Draft Articles on Responsibility of States for Internationally Wrongful Acts. <lb/>103 <lb/>It seems that criminal activities of a foreign investor do not automatically render an <lb/>investment unprotected by IIAs. See Sornarajah, supra note 1, 390. <lb/></listBibl>
              
        <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>324 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>eign investor could not reasonably expect that his illegal activities would be <lb/>continually tolerated by the host State, a legitimate expectation of due con-<lb/>duct of the prosecution of investment-related crimes should nevertheless not <lb/>easily be compromised. Unfortunately, arguments based on the defence of <lb/>such noble but very broad and vague concepts such as democracy and/or the <lb/>rule of law are also capable of being (ab)used to cover protectionist activi-<lb/>ties in a host State and to quieten criticism from abroad. <lb/>The situation at hand, however, could come close to a state of neces-<lb/>sity 104 within the meaning of Article 25 of the International Law Commis-<lb/>sion's Draft Articles on Responsibility of States for Internationally Wrong-<lb/>ful Acts, which is seen to reflect customary international law. 105 The wrong-<lb/>fulness of an act not in conformity with an international obligation is pre-<lb/>cluded when, inter alia, the act is the only way for the State to safeguard an <lb/>essential interest against a grave and immanent peril (Article 25(1)(a)). If <lb/>one is prepared to accept the perpetuation of democracy as essential inter-<lb/>est 106 and is, moreover, willing to view a single businessman or a small <lb/>group of such as grave and immanent peril to the core of democratic system, <lb/>recourse to the defence of "state of necessity" is still, however, put in doubt <lb/>by the fact that it is confined to situations to which the respondent State has <lb/>not contributed (Article 25(2)(b)), at least not in a manner "sufficiently sub-<lb/>stantial and not merely incidental or peripheral." 107 However, by allowing a <lb/>foreign investor to gain significant influence on essential functions of gov-<lb/>ernment and not fighting corruption effectively, the State contributed to <lb/>such a situation. If one were, nevertheless, to accept such a defence of the <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>104 <lb/>See, on the customary law doctrine of "state of necessity" in general, Brownlie, supra <lb/>note 15, 447-449 with further references. Cf. also S. Schill, 'Auf zu Kalypso? Staats-<lb/>notstand und Internationales Investitionsschutzrecht -Anmerkung zur ICSID-<lb/>Entscheidung LG&amp;E Energy Corp v. Argentina', 5 German Arbitration Journal <lb/>(2007), 178-186. The state of necessity, though in the context of treatment standards <lb/>due under a BIT regime, was also invoked and lengthily discussed in a recent ICSID <lb/>arbitration, CMS, supra note 8, paras 304-394; Enron Corp., supra note 8, para. 93, <lb/>Sempra Energy, supra note 8, paras 333-355; LG&amp;E Capital, supra note 36, para. <lb/>201-266. <lb/>105 <lb/>CMS, supra note 8, para. 315. <lb/>106 <lb/>Very high standards of proof are required, and it is doubtful whether an international <lb/>tribunal would accept a state of necessity in the situation at hand. See CMS, paras <lb/>319-331. <lb/>107 <lb/>Commentaries to the Draft Articles on Responsibility of States for Internationally <lb/>Wrongful Acts, adopted by the International Law Commission at its fifty-third session <lb/>(2001), Article 25, para. 20; available at http://untreaty.un.org/ilc/texts/instruments/ <lb/>english/commentaries/9_6_2001.pdf (last visited 04 April 2009). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>325 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>host State, this would mean compromising one of the main objectives of <lb/>IIAs, i.e. to promote good governance standards. By concluding an IIA, the <lb/>State committed itself to such standards and should have fought corruption <lb/>right from the beginning. It should not be rewarded for failing to do so. 108 <lb/>C. Conclusions and Outlook <lb/>The task of both the national and international rules governing foreign <lb/>investment activities is to balance legitimate business interests and the <lb/>State's sovereign "right to regulate". From a national perspective, our sur-<lb/>vey reveals that the legal order of a country, in transition like Russia, is <lb/>hardly prepared to strike an adequate balance between the aforementioned <lb/>interests. Much more than occasional differences in views of courts, 109 it <lb/>fails in a systematic manner to dispense any protection against the "com-<lb/>mon" threats a foreign investor is exposed to in such a business environ-<lb/>ment. It appears ignorant of notions such as due process, the prohibition of <lb/>discrimination and transparency. Turning to the international perspective, a <lb/>comparison of the outcomes produced by the national and international legal <lb/>orders demonstrates that the former can hardly live up to the standards re-<lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>108 <lb/>For case law on the legality of the investment in general see, Fraport AG Frankfurt <lb/>Airport Services Worldwide v. Philippines, ICSID Case No. ARB/03/25, Award, 17 <lb/>August 2007; see also C. Borris &amp; R. Hennecke, 'Das Kriterium der Einhaltung von <lb/>Vorschriften nationalen Rechts in ICSID-Schiedsverfahren -Anmerkungen zum <lb/>Schiedsspruch in der Sache Fraport v. Philippines', 6 German Arbitration Journal <lb/>(2008) 2, 49-58. <lb/>109 <lb/>As demonstrated, for instance, in the Media Most Gusinsky case, in which the partly <lb/>government-owned Gazprom giant guaranteed two loans to Media Most in 1998 that <lb/>totalled US$ 380 million, secured by a 40 per cent piece of the company. After criti-<lb/>cizing the politics of the Kremlin, with the Kremlin allegedly being instrumental in <lb/>bankrupting Media Most by calling in the loans, the owner of Media Most, Mr Gusin-<lb/>sky, was arrested, allegedly without any charges, and he was allegedly compelled to <lb/>sign an agreement to sell his company. Available at www.mytimes.com/2000/11/15/ <lb/>world/russian-gas-company-pulls-out-of-deal-with-media-tycoon.html (last visited 29 <lb/>April 2009). In response to this, the ECHR ruled that the Russian government had vio-<lb/>lated Articles 5 and 18 of the European Convention on Human Rights in relation to <lb/>Gusinsky, namely his rights to freedom and security. The Court ruled that the viola-<lb/>tion in itself was enough for moral damages to be awarded. As a result, it asked the <lb/>Russian Federation to pay € 88.000 in damages. Available at http://cmiskp.echr.coe. <lb/>int/tkp197/view.asp?item=1&amp;portal=hbkm&amp;action=html&amp;highlight=russia%20%7C% <lb/>2070276/01&amp;sessionid=22944796&amp;skin=hudoc-en (last visited 29 April 2009). No <lb/>arguments as to illegal expropriation or moral damages because of such violations <lb/>seem to have been made before Russian courts. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 1 (2009) 2, 291-327 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>326 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>quired and imposed by international investment instruments, even in "eve-<lb/>ryday situations", as the discussion of our scenarios has revealed. <lb/>Two possible conclusions can be drawn from this observation. Either <lb/>the development of international investment law has gone too far, quasi <lb/>overstraining the capabilities (or the willingness) of the legal order to im-<lb/>bibe the international standards, or Russia, as just an example of many other <lb/>economies in transition, has to start urgently-more than ten years after <lb/>signing its first BIT-living up to the standards of good governance re-<lb/>quired by the IIAs it has signed if it does not want to face significant exter-<lb/>nalization of legal disputes concerned with foreign investment. 110 This is no <lb/>fanciful perspective. <lb/>As regards the first possible conclusion, we do not think that the de-<lb/>velopment of international investment law has gone too far. Most IIAs, on <lb/>the one hand, offer a foreign investor the necessary back-up against sudden <lb/>protective measures of its host State which is needed to conduct business in <lb/>a foreign jurisdiction with a certain degree of predictability. On the other <lb/>hand, IIAs are also capable of accommodating legitimate State interests. <lb/>Moreover, they encourage and promote "good governance" standards. In-<lb/>ternational commitments are at present the best way to protect foreign in-<lb/>vestments against internal attacks and differing interests in the political es-<lb/>tablishment of a State. However, the host State itself will also benefit from <lb/>an internal legal order which acts transparently and produces reliable, pre-<lb/>dictable and just outcomes. Thus, with regard to foreign direct investments, <lb/>the national legal systems of economies in transition should make an effort <lb/>to live up to the standards set under international investment law. By doing <lb/>so, these states can create incentives for foreign investors to perceive their <lb/>domestic legal systems as a genuine alternative to international investment <lb/>law and arbitration. This bears of course the caveat that in view of the <lb/>amounts usually involved in such a dispute, the potential for protective <lb/>measures can be minimised, but never be wholly excluded. Of course, <lb/>sometimes a country subject to international investment arbitration for the <lb/>first time has to learn the hard way about the obligations it has signed up <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>110 <lb/>One way to force an international investor to resort to national jurisdictions is the <lb/>"local remedies requirement". However, the exhaustion of local remedies as a precon-<lb/>dition for commencing an international investment arbitration is nowadays rarely re-<lb/>quired by BITs; C. Schreuer, The ICSID Convention: A Commentary (2001), 391-393. <lb/>For an appraisal of alleged new tendencies in arbitration, see C. Schreuer, 'Calvo's <lb/>Grandchildren: The Return of Local Remedies in Investment Arbitration', 4 The Law <lb/>and Practice of International Courts and Tribunals (2005) 1, 1-3. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Protection against Indirect Expropriation <lb/></note>
    
    <page>327 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>for. But at the end of the day, drawing the right conclusions from the lessons <lb/>learned, it should begin to improve its administrative procedures in particu-<lb/>lar and its legal system in general so that foreign investors do not feel the <lb/>need to resort to international arbitration in the first place. <lb/>This brings us to our second possible conclusion which, in our view, <lb/>appears to be the correct analysis. Countries such as Russia should be aware <lb/>of the costs which they have to bear if they are not capable or willing to of-<lb/>fer the necessary legal tools to respond to the needs and problems of foreign <lb/>investors. They risk that legal issues are litigated far away from the place <lb/>where the conflict originated, adjudicated by rules they were able to shape <lb/>only to a limited extent, and decided by people sometimes not fully aware of <lb/>the local situation. In a nutshell, they risk marginalizing their own legal or-<lb/>der, which, in general, should be able to best accommodate the country's <lb/>specificities. <lb/>Whilst countries may ignore individual cases for some time, in the <lb/>long run there are only two ways out: either to take leave from the IIA re-<lb/>gime, which would completely sideline the country in question, in the view <lb/>of the investors' as well as the state community,; or while globalization is <lb/>deepening to stop hesitating and tackle the issue. </body>


	</text>


  </TEI>