<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court Considered at the first Review Conference on the Court, Kampala, 31 May-11 June 2010</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Roger S.</forename>
          <surname>Clark</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-10-15T14:12:47.521Z">10/15/2025 3:12:47 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.3249$1$1868-1581-2-2-clark</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Institut für Völker- und Europarecht</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2010</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.3249/1868-1581-2-2-clark</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Roger S. Clark. (2010). Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court Considered at the first Review Conference on the Court, Kampala, 31 May-11 June 2010. Goettingen Journal of International Law, (), None. DOI: 10.3249/1868-1581-2-2-clark</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-04T21:18:43.481725Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">0707645</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-10-04T21:18:43.481725Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Goettingen Journal of International Law 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/>doi: 10.3249/1868-1581-2-2-Clark <lb/>Amendments to the Rome Statute of the <lb/>International Criminal Court Considered at the <lb/>first Review Conference on the Court, <lb/>Kampala, 31 May-11 June 2010 <lb/>Roger S. Clark  <lb/></front>
              
              <toc>Table of Contents <lb/>Abstract ...................................................................................................... 690 <lb/>A. <lb/>Introduction ..................................................................................... 690 <lb/>B. <lb/>Non-Deletion of Article 124 of the Statute ..................................... 691 <lb/>C. <lb/>The Crime of Aggression ................................................................ 692 <lb/>I. The Basic Structure of Article 8bis -the Definition ....................... 695 <lb/>II. Structure of Articles 15bis and 15ter -Conditions for <lb/>Exercise of Jurisdiction ....................................................................... 699 <lb/>D. <lb/>Forbidden Weapons in the Statute .................................................. 707 <lb/>E. Conclusion .......................................................................................... 711 <lb/></toc>
    
    <front> <lb/>Board of Governors Professor, Rutgers Law School, Camden, New Jersey, member <lb/>delegation of Samoa in Rome and Kampala. <lb/>GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/>690 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The first Review Conference on the International Criminal Court had three <lb/>items on its agenda proposing amendments to the Rome Statute. The <lb/>proposal to delete Article 124 of the Statute (which permits States to opt out <lb/>of the war crimes provisions of the Statute for seven years) failed. Proposals <lb/>for a comprehensive set of provisions facilitating the Court's exercise of its <lb/>jurisdiction over the crime of aggression were adopted. The existing <lb/>provisions on weapons that are banned in international armed conflict were <lb/>incorporated also into the part of the Statute dealing with non-international <lb/>armed conflicts. <lb/></front>
    
    <body>A. Introduction <lb/>Article 123 of the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court 1 <lb/>provided for a Review Conference on the workings of the Statute, to be <lb/>convened seven years after the Statute's entry into force. Specifically, the <lb/>Article said that the Conference was "to consider any amendments to the <lb/>Statute." While the Conference used a generous interpretation of "review" <lb/>and devoted much of the first week of a two-week conference to a <lb/>"stocktaking", 2 the primary work of the Conference was to examine three <lb/>potential amendments to the Statute that had been forwarded by the <lb/>governing body of the Court, the Assembly of States Parties ("ASP"). These <lb/>were: deletion of Article 124 of the Statute, completion of negotiations to <lb/>activate the Court's jurisdiction over the crime of aggression, and the <lb/>addition of a proscription on the use of certain weapons in the provisions of <lb/>Article 8 dealing with non-international armed conflict. 3 I consider each of <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>1 <lb/>U.N. Doc.A/CONF.183/9, 17 July 1998. <lb/>2 <lb/>The stocktaking entailed a rich review of the topics of complementarity, cooperation, <lb/>the impact of the Rome Statute system on victims and affected communities, and <lb/>peace and justice. There are some very useful papers on these issues on the Court's <lb/>website for the Conference. For the conference website http://www.icc-<lb/>cpi.int/Menus/ASP/ReviewConference/ (last visited 20 August 2010). Perhaps the <lb/>most distressing fact to emerge from the discussions is that fewer than half of the <lb/>parties to the Statute have adopted adequate domestic implementation legislation to <lb/>give effect to the treaty. <lb/>3 <lb/>The Assembly had the power to set the agenda for the Conference. Meeting the <lb/>previous November, it took a cautious view of the amendments that could be <lb/>considered, limiting the agenda to the three just noted. One of the three, possible <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>691 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>these proposals, and the outcomes on them, seriatim. No votes were <lb/>necessary as a consensus was reached on each of the items, albeit in one <lb/>case to do nothing. <lb/>B. Non-deletion of Article 124 of the Statute <lb/>Article 124 of the Statute is the only provision in the Statute that <lb/>specifically required its own inclusion on the agenda of the first Review <lb/>Conference. It provides that, upon becoming a party to the Statute, a State <lb/>may declare that, for a period of seven years, it is not bound by the <lb/>provisions of Article 8 of the Statute (which deals with war crimes) "when a <lb/>crime is alleged to have been committed by its nationals or on its territory". <lb/>The Rome Statute has a general prohibition of reservations; 4 this provision, <lb/>which is headed "Transitional Provision" and often described as an "opt-out <lb/>clause", permits, in this special case, what is functionally a reservation. It <lb/>was negotiated at the very end of the 1998 Diplomatic Conference to enable <lb/>France to accept the Statute. 5 Of the 111 existing parties to the Statute, only <lb/>France and Colombia have availed themselves of it. France, in fact, <lb/>withdrew its declaration after about six years and Colombia's seven years <lb/>have now passed. Article 124 provided, in its own terms, that it "shall be <lb/>reviewed at the [first] Review Conference." "Shall be reviewed" amounts to <lb/>a promise of consideration but not to a promise that a particular -or any -<lb/>result should be reached. <lb/>The procedural stance of the matter going into Kampala was that the <lb/>2009 Assembly of States Parties forwarded a bracketed proposal for the <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>deletion of Art. 124, was required to be on the agenda by the article's own terms; <lb/>aggression had been the subject of extensive preparatory work since 1998 and it was <lb/>inconceivable that it would not be considered, even if it was not strictly required to be <lb/>so; there was wide agreement on the weapons provision by late 2009, but a number of <lb/>other potential additions to Art. 8 did not proceed to Kampala in the absence of a <lb/>fairly clear consensus on them. See infra at notes 71-77. So too, proposals relating to <lb/>addition of crimes of terrorism and serious drug crimes to the subject-matter of the <lb/>Statute were left over to future meetings of the Assembly of States Parties, and indeed, <lb/>potentially, to later Review Conferences. See infra at notes 78-80. (Art. 123 empowers <lb/>the ASP to call future Review Conferences, but does not indicate any particular time <lb/>frame. There seems to be a widespread disposition to have reviews on a regular basis, <lb/>perhaps on a seven-year cycle.). <lb/>4 <lb/>Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 120: "No reservations may be made to this Statute.". <lb/>5 <lb/>Apparently the permanent Five members of the Security Council had agreed a day or <lb/>two earlier that their bottom line was that there should be a ten-year opt-out period in <lb/>respect of both war crimes (Art. 8) and crimes against humanity (Art. 7), but the <lb/>United Kingdom and France opted out of that agreement. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>692 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>deletion of the Article -the brackets indicating that the matter was <lb/>controversial. 6 In the course of the Review Conference, an overwhelming <lb/>majority of those taking the floor spoke in favor of its deletion, although <lb/>France, along with some States that are non-parties to the Rome Statute, <lb/>notably Iran and China, supported its retention. Iran and China suggested <lb/>that it might be helpful in enabling them to come aboard (although it has not <lb/>done the trick in the past eleven years). Many of those opposed to keeping it <lb/>emphasized that it detracted from the general policy of the Statute against <lb/>reservations. Moreover, it did not appear to have played a significant role in <lb/>achieving the goal of universality, that is, of encouraging all hundred and <lb/>ninety-odd States to ratify or accede to the Statute. In the event, the <lb/>Conference adopted a resolution 7 touching on the various points of view by <lb/>referring to "the need to ensure the integrity of the Rome Statute", "the <lb/>importance of the universality of the founding instrument of the <lb/>International Criminal Court", and the "transitional nature of Article 124, as <lb/>decided by the Rome Conference". It then asserted that, having reviewed the <lb/>provisions of Article 124, it "Decides to retain Article 124 in its current <lb/>form" and also decides to "further review the provisions of Article 124 <lb/>during the fourteenth session of the Assembly of States Parties to the Rome <lb/>Statute," that is in 2015. <lb/>There is, of course, no guarantee that the review by the ASP in 2015 <lb/>will result in any other conclusion than to leave "well" alone. This episode <lb/>in Kampala is a good example of what can happen in a consensus <lb/>negotiation -a few adamant states (some of them not even parties to the <lb/>treaty) were able to block what was desired by a very large majority. As will <lb/>be seen, the minority (many of the same states) chose not to stand in the <lb/>way of a consensus on the other two amending items on the Kampala <lb/>agenda. <lb/>C. The Crime of Aggression <lb/>Activating the Court's jurisdiction over the crime of aggression was <lb/>the most important piece of unfinished business from the Rome Diplomatic <lb/>Conference in 1998. The vast majority of the participants in Kampala, <lb/>whether they wished the item to succeed or to fail, regarded it as the most <lb/>significant item at the Review Conference and the one to which they <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>6 <lb/>See Resolution ICC-ASP/8/Res. 6, 26. November 2009, Annex I. <lb/>7 <lb/>Art. 124 ICC Statute, RC/Res.4 (2010). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>693 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>devoted most of their efforts. Those efforts were fulfilled by adoption of a <lb/>comprehensive resolution which aspired to resolve all the outstanding <lb/>issues. 8 <lb/>Article 5 (1) of the Statute lists "the crime of aggression" (along with <lb/>the crime of genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes) as one of <lb/>the four items within the subject-matter jurisdiction of the Court. 9 Paragraph <lb/>2 of Article 5 adds, however, that "[t]he Court shall exercise jurisdiction <lb/>over the crime of aggression once a provision is adopted in accordance with <lb/>Articles 121 and 123 defining the crime and setting out the conditions under <lb/>which the Court shall exercise jurisdiction with respect to this crime. Such a <lb/>provision shall be consistent with the relevant provisions of the Charter of <lb/>the United Nations". 10 Building on Article 5, the Final Act of the Rome <lb/>Conference instructed the Preparatory Commission for the Court to "prepare <lb/>proposals for a provision on aggression, including the definition and <lb/>Elements of Crimes of Aggression and conditions under which the <lb/>International Criminal Court shall exercise its jurisdiction with regard to this <lb/>crime". 11 "Definition" here has been understood to refer to the relevant <lb/>substantive criminal law issues; "conditions" requires consideration of <lb/>whether some organ of the United Nations (in particular the Security <lb/>Council) may be able -or even required -to participate in the process <lb/>alongside the Court. The drafting task not having been completed by the end <lb/>of the life of the Preparatory Commission, 12 the Court's Assembly of States <lb/>Parties created the Special Working Group on the Crime of Aggression <lb/>("SWGCA") to carry forward the task. The SWGCA was open to <lb/>participation by all States, members of the ICC and non-members alike. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>8 <lb/>The Crime of Aggression, RC/Res. 6 (2010). <lb/>9 <lb/>Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 5 (1). <lb/>10 <lb/>Id., Art. 5 (2). <lb/>11 <lb/>Final Act of the United Nations Diplomatic Conference of Plenipotentiaries on the <lb/>Establishment of an International Criminal Court, Annex I, Resolution F, para. 7, U.N. <lb/>Doc. A/CONF.183/10, 17 July 1998, at 8-9 [Resolution F]. <lb/>12 <lb/>The last draft on the table at the Preparatory Commission was a Discussion Paper <lb/>proposed by the Coordinator on the Crime of Aggression, U.N. Doc. <lb/>PCNICC/2002/2/Add.2 [Discussion Paper], discussed in R. S. Clark, 'Rethinking <lb/>Aggression as Crime and Formulating its Elements: The Final Work-Product of the <lb/>Preparatory Commission for the International Criminal Court', 15 Leiden Law Journal <lb/>(2002) 4, 859. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>694 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>The Group's ultimate effort on provisions and conditions was <lb/>contained in its final Report to the Assembly in February 2009, 13 which was <lb/>in front of the Review Conference. It was accompanied by some later <lb/>suggestions which had been generated at a subsequent informal meeting of <lb/>the ASP and by the last Chair of the Working Group. <lb/>The essence of the SWGCA's draft comprised two articles for <lb/>addition to the Statute: "Article 8bis" which contained the definition, and <lb/>"Article 15bis" which dealt with the conditions for exercise. Article 8bis did <lb/>not contain any alternatives, representing a consensus that held in Kampala, <lb/>although not everyone at the Working Group was entirely happy with <lb/>everything. Nonetheless, the SWGCA's work on Article 8bis was adopted <lb/>verbatim in Kampala. Article 15bis, on the other hand, offered many <lb/>alternatives -notably variations on the theme of involvement vel non of the <lb/>Security Council in the process by which a specific case would come before <lb/>the Court. This Article was where most of the debate took place in Kampala. <lb/>That debate resulted in the emergence of two Articles, 15bis and 15ter, <lb/>covering the matters in the SWGCA's draft. The Conference considered that <lb/>Committee's work and a number of new proposals made in Kampala, <lb/>making some hard political decisions between the alternatives. <lb/>Draft Elements of Crimes had also been produced before Kampala, at <lb/>an informal inter-sessional meeting of the Assembly held in June of 2009. 14 <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>13 <lb/>Report of the Special Working Group on the Crime of Aggression, Doc. ICC-<lb/>ASP/7/SWGCA/2 (2009) [2009 Report]. The proposed amendments and the proposed <lb/>"Elements" (see next note) are also contained in Annex II to Resolution ICC-<lb/>ASP/8/Res. 6, supra note 6. Concerning the provisions on aggression in general, see <lb/>N. Weisbord, 'Prosecuting Aggression', 49 Harvard International Law Journal <lb/>(2008) 1, 161; S. Barriga, 'Against the Odds: The Results of the Special Working <lb/>Group on the Crime of Aggression', in G. R. Bellilli ed., International Criminal <lb/>Justice (2010); 'Symposium: The Codification of the Crime of Aggression', 20 <lb/>European Journal of International Law (2009) 4, 1103. Not all the contributors to the <lb/>European Journal symposium are true believers. Another who is skeptical of the <lb/>whole exercise is G. Simpson, '"Stop Calling it Aggression": War as Crime', 61 <lb/>Current Legal Problems (2008), 191. The bulk of the Special Working Group's <lb/>substantive work was done at intercessional meetings held at the Liechtenstein <lb/>Institute on Self-Determination at Princeton University. The SWGCA's materials are <lb/>usefully collected in S. Barriga, W. Danspeckgruber &amp; C. Wenaweser (eds.), The <lb/>Princeton Process on the Crime of Aggression: Materials of the Special Working <lb/>Group on the Crime of Aggression, 2003-2009 (2009). <lb/>14 <lb/>Informal intercessional meeting on the Crime of Aggression, hosted by the <lb/>Liechtenstein Institute on Self-Determination, Woodrow Wilson School, at the <lb/>Princeton Club, New York, from 8 to 10 June 2009, Doc. ICC-ASP/8/INF.2 (2009), <lb/>Appendix I [Draft Elements of Crimes]. There is a useful explanatory note on the <lb/></listBibl>
              
        <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
              
        <page>695 <lb/></page>
              
        <body>While there was some doubt at the time whether these Elements would be <lb/>formally approved in Kampala, that was what in fact occurred. 15 <lb/>In what follows, I discuss what seemed to me to be the most <lb/>significant drafting choices that were made in respect of the definition and <lb/>the conditions for exercise of jurisdiction. <lb/>I. The Basic Structure of Article 8bis -the Definition <lb/>A major intellectual and juridical contribution of the Nuremberg and <lb/>Tokyo trials was to take what in the past had been thought of essentially as a <lb/>question of state responsibility and add to it an enforcement measure based <lb/>on individual criminal responsibility. As the Nuremberg Tribunal said in a <lb/>famous quotation, "Crimes are committed by men, not by abstract entities, <lb/>and only by punishing individuals who commit such crimes can the <lb/>provisions of international law be enforced". 16 As the context of the <lb/>Tribunal's discussion made plain, this is not to deny that there is still state <lb/>responsibility as well. Accordingly, Article 8bis uses a drafting convention <lb/>that builds on this combination of state and individual responsibility. It <lb/>distinguishes between an "act of aggression" (what a State does) and the <lb/>"crime of aggression" (what a leader does). "Act of aggression" is defined <lb/>as "the use of armed force by a State against the sovereignty, territorial <lb/>integrity or political independence of another State or in any other manner <lb/>inconsistent with the Charter of the United Nations". 17 This language, based <lb/>on the United Nations Charter, is followed, in the second paragraph of the <lb/>Article, by a reference to a list of "acts" that "shall, in accordance with <lb/>General Assembly resolution 3314 (XXIX) of 14 December 1974, qualify as <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>elements in Annex II of the Report ("Non-paper by the Chairman on the Elements of <lb/>Crimes"). Art. 9 of the Rome Statute required the production of Elements for <lb/>genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes. Resolution F required them for <lb/>aggression; the SWGCA recommended an amendment to Art. 9 to make clear that <lb/>aggression, too, requires its Elements. Elements emphasize, in more detail than the <lb/>Statute, what the prosecution must prove in order to show that there was a crime; they <lb/>also make some of the connections between the definitions in the "special part" of the <lb/>Statute (Arts 6, 7 and 8, and now 8bis) and the "general principles" contained in Part <lb/>III of the Statute. See generally, discussion of Art. 9 of the Statute ("Elements of <lb/>Crimes") in O. Triffterer (ed.), Commentary on the Rome Statute of the International <lb/>Criminal Court -Observers' Notes, Article by Article, 2 nd ed. (2008), 505. <lb/>15 <lb/>Res. 6, supra note 8, annex II. <lb/>16 <lb/>'International Military Tribunal (Nuremberg), Judgment and Sentences', 41 American <lb/>Journal of International Law (1947) 1, 172, 221. <lb/>17 <lb/>Article 8bis (2), supra note 8, Annex I. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>696 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>an act of aggression." 18 Resolution 3314 19 is the well-known 1974 effort of <lb/>the General Assembly to define aggression so as to assist the Security <lb/>Council in doing its work for the maintenance of peace and security. The <lb/>resolution deals with state responsibility, but there was considerable support <lb/>in the SWGCA for using it as the basis for a definition in the present <lb/>context. Utilizing it was a challenge. The ultimate drafting of 8bis is aimed <lb/>at avoiding the open-ended nature of Resolution 3314 which says, <lb/>essentially, that the Security Council may decide that something that meets <lb/>the definition is nonetheless not aggression and, on the other hand, that acts <lb/>other than those on the list may be regarded by the Security Council as <lb/>aggression. As a political body, the Security Council may act in a <lb/>completely unprincipled and arbitrary manner. A criminal Court constrained <lb/>by the principle of legality 20 must be under more restraint, so the open-<lb/>textured aspects of 3314 needed some pruning and the Security Council's <lb/>determination needed to be removed from the mix. The result is fairly <lb/>precise. The list of "acts" in Article 8bis (2), taken verbatim from <lb/>Resolution 3314, may be open-ended to the extent that it does not say that <lb/>no other acts can amount to aggression. However, any other potential <lb/>candidates must surely be interpreted narrowly and ejusdem generis with the <lb/>existing list. <lb/>"Crime of aggression", for the purpose of the Statute, "means <lb/>the planning, preparation, initiation or execution, by a person <lb/>in a position effectively to exercise control over or to direct the <lb/>political or military action of a State, of an act of aggression <lb/>which, by its character, gravity and scale, constitutes a <lb/>manifest violation of the Charter of the United Nations." 21 <lb/>The crime of aggression is thus a "leadership" crime, a proposition <lb/>captured by the element that the perpetrator has to be in a position <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>18 <lb/>Id. The list of acts that "qualify as an act of aggression" is: invasion, annexation, <lb/>bombardment, blockade, attack on the armed forces of another State, using forces that <lb/>are in a State by consent in contravention of the terms of their presence, allowing a <lb/>State's territory to be used for the purposes of aggression by another, and sending by <lb/>or on behalf of a State of armed bands, groups, irregulars or mercenaries, which carry <lb/>out acts of armed force against another State. <lb/>19 <lb/>G.A. Res. 3314 (XXIX), 14. December 1974, 29 U.N. GAOR, 29 th Sess., Supp. No. <lb/>31, U.N. Doc. A/9631, at 142. <lb/>20 <lb/>Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 22 -"Nullum crimen sine lege". <lb/>21 <lb/>Art. 8bis (1), supra note 8, Annex I. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>697 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>effectively to exercise control over or to direct the political or military <lb/>action of a State. 22 There was considerable discussion in the SWGCA about <lb/>how this applies to someone like an industrialist who is closely involved <lb/>with the organization of the State but not formally part of its structure. 23 <lb/>Some support was shown for clarifying the matter by choosing language <lb/>closer to that used in the United States Military Tribunals at Nuremberg, <lb/>namely "shape and influence" rather than "exercise control over or to <lb/>direct". 24 <lb/>American and French prosecutions at the end the Second World War <lb/>had made it clear that industrial leaders could potentially be responsible for <lb/>the crime of aggression, although none were ultimately convicted. <lb/>Note should also be taken at this point of the "threshold" clause at <lb/>the end of the definition of "crime of aggression", indicating that not every <lb/>act of aggression is the basis for criminal responsibility. It is only those <lb/>which by their character, gravity and scale, constitute a "manifest" violation <lb/>of the Charter. 25 The need for such a limitation was strongly debated 26 but <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>22 <lb/>As well as the leadership language contained in Art. 8bis (5) of the amendments <lb/>adopted in Kampala (in an apparent abundance of caution) adds a para. 3bis to Art. 25 <lb/>(3) of the Statute which deals with individual responsibility: <lb/>In respect of the crime of aggression, the provisions of this article shall apply only to <lb/>persons in a position effectively to exercise control over or to direct the political or <lb/>military action of a State. <lb/>23 <lb/>See K. J. Heller, 'Retreat from Nuremberg: The Leadership Requirement in the Crime <lb/>of Aggression', 18 European Journal of International Law (2007) 3, 477. <lb/>24 <lb/>See Informal intercessional meeting of the Special Working Group on the Crime of <lb/>Aggression, held at the Liechtenstein Institute on Self-Determination, Woodrow <lb/>Wilson School, Princeton University, from 11 to 14 June 2007, Doc. ICC-<lb/>ASP/6/SWGCA/INF.1 (2007) at 3, para. 12. This preparatory work seems to support <lb/>the proposition that industrialists are potentially covered by the amendments, although <lb/>no formal language to that effect was added. <lb/>25 <lb/>Supra note 21. The Introduction to the Draft Elements of Crimes for aggression, supra <lb/>note 14, stated that: "The term 'manifest' is an objective qualification." There is a <lb/>comment in the Report of the 2009 Intercessional meeting on the crime of aggression, <lb/>supra note 14, at 6, para. 25, that "the Court would apply the standard of the <lb/>'reasonable leader', similar to the standard of the 'reasonable soldier' which was <lb/>embedded in the concept of manifestly unlawful orders in article 33 of the Rome <lb/>Statute." The phrase "character, gravity and scale" provides a framework for forging <lb/>such an objective standard. The best analysis of this threshold is J. Potter, The <lb/>Threshold in the Proposed Definition of the Crime of Aggression, 6 N.Z. Y.B. INT'L L. <lb/>(2008), 155. See also understanding adopted in Kampala, infra note 32. <lb/>26 <lb/>See e.g., 2009 SWGCA Report, supra note 13 at 3, para. 13: "It was argued that the <lb/>clause was unnecessary because any act of aggression would constitute a manifest <lb/>violation of the Charter … and that the definition should not exclude any acts of <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>698 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>most participants finally accepted that they could live with it in return for <lb/>removal of any requirement that there be a "war of aggression" 27 or that the <lb/>list of acts in the definition of "act of aggression" be more limited than the <lb/>list in General Assembly Resolution 3314. 28 Some speakers thought it might <lb/>help in analyzing a (rare) case of principled humanitarian intervention or a <lb/>case more generally where the legality of the action was definitely in <lb/>doubt. 29 In a speech to the Conference on 4 June 2010, the Legal Adviser to <lb/>the U.S. Department of State insisted, tendentiously, that: <lb/>"If Article 8bis were to be adopted as a definition, understandings <lb/>would need to make clear that those who undertake efforts to prevent war <lb/>crimes, crimes against humanity or genocide -the very crimes the Rome <lb/>Statute was designed to deter -do not commit "manifest" violations of the <lb/>U.N. Charter within the meaning of Article 8bis. Regardless of how states <lb/>may view the legality of such efforts, those who plan them are not <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>aggression. … Other delegations expressed support for the threshold clause which <lb/>would provide important guidance for the Court, and in particular prevent the Court <lb/>from addressing borderline cases." Some speakers thought it might help in analyzing a <lb/>(rare) case of principled humanitarian intervention or a case more generally where the <lb/>legality of the action was definitely in doubt. <lb/>27 <lb/>The Nuremberg Charter had a puzzling requirement of a "war of aggression" which <lb/>prompted the International Military Tribunal to draw a de facto distinction between <lb/>the conquests of Austria and Czechoslovakia (achieved without actual fighting) on the <lb/>one hand, and the invasions of Poland and others (achieved with considerable <lb/>fighting) on the other. The former were classified as "acts of aggression" (and not yet <lb/>"criminal"), the latter as "wars of aggression" and proscribed under the Charter. <lb/>Control Council Law No. 10, under which subsequent prosecutions were brought, had <lb/>language broad enough to treat Austria and Czechoslovakia as criminal aggressions. <lb/>See generally, R. S. Clark, 'Nuremberg and the Crime against Peace', 6 Washington <lb/>University Global Studies Law Review (2007) 3, 527. <lb/>28 <lb/>Supra note 19. Cf. 2002 Discussion Paper, supra note 12 (containing alternative which <lb/>would modify the Res. 3314 list by requiring that the act of aggression be one that <lb/>"amounts to a war or aggression or constitutes an act which has the object or the result <lb/>of establishing a military occupation of, or annexing, the territory of another State or <lb/>part thereof"). <lb/>29 <lb/>Art. 8bis, following the drafting style of the other substantive articles in the Statute, <lb/>does not address specifically grounds of justification or excuse. Such matters, called <lb/>"grounds for the exclusion of responsibility", fall to be analyzed by the Court under <lb/>the general part of the Statute, and, in particular, under article 31 thereof. The <lb/>requirement that a breach be "manifest" provides an alternative route to analyze some <lb/>of the "defences". Obviously, that state is acting in self-defence as understood under <lb/>the UN Charter, or as authorized by the Security Council, means that there is no act of <lb/>aggression, without getting to the "manifest" issue. Other cases may be more difficult. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>699 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>committing the "crime of aggression" and should not run the risk of <lb/>prosecution." 30 <lb/>Two paragraphs of "understandings" annexed to the Review <lb/>Conference's resolution adopting the amendments on the Crime of <lb/>Aggression 31 address these matters, apparently giving comfort to the United <lb/>States: <lb/>It is understood that aggression is the most serious and dangerous <lb/>form of the illegal use of force; and that a determination whether an act of <lb/>aggression has been committed requires consideration of all the <lb/>circumstances of each particular case, including the gravity of the acts <lb/>concerned and their consequences, in accordance with the Charter of the <lb/>United Nations. <lb/>It is understood that in establishing whether an act of aggression <lb/>constitutes a manifest violation of the Charter of the United Nations, the <lb/>three components of character, gravity and scale must be sufficient to justify <lb/>a "manifest" determination. No one component can be significant enough to <lb/>satisfy the manifest standard by itself. 32 <lb/>II. Structure of Articles 15bis and 15ter -Conditions for <lb/>Exercise of Jurisdiction <lb/>The Special Working Group was less successful in resolving the issue <lb/>of conditions than that of definition. The second sentence of Article 5, <lb/>paragraph 2 of the Statute, added without public debate in the last days of <lb/>the Rome Conference, states that the provision on aggression "shall be <lb/>consistent with the relevant provisions of the Charter of the United <lb/>Nations" 33 . By and large, the Permanent Members of the Security Council <lb/>took the position in the negotiations that Article 39 of the Charter confers on <lb/>them the "exclusive" power to make determinations of the existence of an <lb/>act of aggression, and thus a Security Council pre-determination of <lb/>aggression is an essential precondition to exercise of the ICC's jurisdiction. <lb/>Most other States pointed out that Article 24 of the Charter confers <lb/>"primary" power on the Council in respect of the maintenance of <lb/>international peace and justice and that "primary" does not mean <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>30 <lb/>Statement by Harold Koh to the Conference, 4 June 2010, available at <lb/>http://www.state.gov/s/l/releases/remarks/142665.htm (last visited 19 August 2010). <lb/>31 <lb/>Supra note 8, annex III. <lb/>32 <lb/>Paragraph 7 here underscores the "and" in the phrase "character, gravity and scale". <lb/>33 <lb/>Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 5 (2), second sentence. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>700 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>"exclusive". They added that the General Assembly has made several <lb/>findings of aggression and that the United States, the United Kingdom and <lb/>France were co-sponsors of the 1950 Uniting for Peace resolution which <lb/>recognizes the Assembly's powers 34 and that all five of the Permanent <lb/>Members have voted pursuant to that resolution when it suited them. Non-<lb/>permanent members tend to add that the International Court of Justice has <lb/>addressed issues where aggression is in play. 35 Like the Security Council, <lb/>however, the ICJ has been leery of actually using the word "aggression". <lb/>The draft sent to Kampala included the General Assembly and the <lb/>International Court of Justice as alternative "filters" for the crime of <lb/>aggression in the absence of Security Council action, but these were deleted <lb/>in Kampala. <lb/>The major achievement in this part of the negotiation in the period of <lb/>the Special Working Group was to de-couple the definition from the <lb/>conditions. In the version of the definition and conditions for aggression that <lb/>was on the table at the end of the life of the Preparatory Commission, the <lb/>Security Council (or possibly the General Assembly or the ICJ) would make <lb/>a definitive decision on the existence of the element of "act of aggression" <lb/>which was binding on the ICC. 36 Not only would this subvert the power of <lb/>the Court to decide itself on the existence or otherwise of all the elements of <lb/>the crime, but it would make it extremely difficult to build a criminal <lb/>offence around a structure where one of the key elements was decided <lb/>elsewhere and potentially on the basis of totally political considerations. In <lb/>such circumstances, there would probably be unbearable weight placed on <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>34 <lb/>G.A. Res. 377(V) A, 3. November 1950. The relevant provision reads: <lb/>[The General Assembly] "Resolves that if the Security Council, because of lack of <lb/>unanimity of the permanent members, fails to exercise its primary responsibility for <lb/>the maintenance of international peace and security in any case where there appears to <lb/>be a threat to the peace, breach of the peace, or act of aggression, the General <lb/>Assembly shall consider the matter immediately with a view to making appropriate <lb/>recommendations to Members for collective measures, including in the case of a <lb/>breach of the peace or act of aggression the use of armed force when necessary, to <lb/>maintain or restore international peace and security.". <lb/>35 <lb/>Most recently in Armed Activities on the Territory of the Congo (DR Congo v. <lb/>Uganda), Jurisdiction of the Court, Judgment, ICJ Reports 2005. <lb/>36 <lb/>See the 2002 Coordinator's Paper, supra note 12. This was the effect of the words <lb/>"which has been determined to have been committed by the State concerned" which <lb/>appeared then in paragraph 2 of the definition. The whole context made it clear that <lb/>someone other than the Court would make the determination. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>701 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>the mental element provisions of Article 30 of the Statute, 37 the mistake <lb/>provisions of Article 32 38 or on the "manifest" threshold. 39 This was <lb/>removed in the Special Working Group's draft and in the ultimate language <lb/>adopted in Kampala. Any determination elsewhere is of a preliminary <lb/>nature, although it may have some evidentiary value. 40 This opened the way <lb/>for focusing on the various options put before the Review Conference of <lb/>giving the Security Council (or other United Nations organ) a "filter" role, <lb/>providing either a "green light" (permission to go forward) or a "red light" <lb/>(denial of right to go forward) to the ICC's proceedings. 41 There was, <lb/>however, a solid group of states strongly behind the proposition that the <lb/>Prosecutor should be able to proceed even in the absence of action by <lb/>someone else. 42 <lb/>The resolution of these divergent positions in Kampala was <lb/>facilitated by a move to split the SWGCA's draft Article 15bis into two <lb/>parts, one dealing with state referrals and referrals made by the prosecutor <lb/>proprio motu, and the other dealing with Security Council referrals. These <lb/>became, respectively, Article 15bis and 15ter. Article 15ter referrals are the <lb/>most simple to describe and it will thus be helpful to discuss them first. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>37 <lb/>Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 30, has a general rule that the crimes in the Statute <lb/>must be accompanied by "intent and knowledge". <lb/>38 <lb/>In the structure of the Statute, a mistake is the obverse of knowledge or intent -it <lb/>negatives a mental element of a crime. Rome Statute Art. 32 says that a mistake of <lb/>fact shall be a ground for excluding criminal responsibility only if it negates the <lb/>mental element required by the crime. It continues that a mistake of law as to whether <lb/>a particular type of conduct is a crime within the jurisdiction of the Court shall not be <lb/>a ground for excluding criminal responsibility. Finally, it adds that a mistake of law <lb/>may, however, be a ground for excluding criminal responsibility if it negates the <lb/>mental element required by such a crime, or in certain cases of superior orders. A <lb/>defense that "I made a mistake about the legality of the conduct later held to be <lb/>aggression" might be potentially open to one charged with the crime of aggression. <lb/>The Elements of the crime of aggression work a finesse that is commonly applied to <lb/>Elements of the war crimes under Art. 8 of the Statute by re-directing the enquiry in <lb/>the direction of the facts. The relevant Element is thus: "The perpetrator was aware of <lb/>the factual circumstances that established that such a use of armed force was <lb/>inconsistent with the Charter of the United Nations.". <lb/>39 <lb/>Supra notes 25-32. <lb/>40 <lb/>Draft Art. 15bis (5) of the 2009 Report, supra note 13, provided: "A determination of <lb/>an act of aggression by an organ outside the Court shall be without prejudice to the <lb/>Court's own findings under this Statute.". <lb/>41 <lb/>Id. Draft Art. 15bis, paras 2-4. <lb/>42 <lb/>Id. Draft Art. 15bis,, para. 4, Alternative 2, Option 1. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>702 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Paragraph 1 of Article 15ter is the basic provision authorizing the <lb/>Court to exercise its jurisdiction under the Statute in respect of the crime of <lb/>aggression, when a referral is made by the Security Council: <lb/>The Court may exercise jurisdiction over the crime of aggression in <lb/>accordance with Article 13, paragraph (b), subject to the provisions of this <lb/>Article. 43 <lb/>Then follow two paragraphs of the Article designed to provide a set of <lb/>conditions and a time frame for paragraph 1 to come into play. Paragraph 2 <lb/>says that the Court "may exercise jurisdiction only with respect to crimes of <lb/>aggression committed one year after the ratification or acceptance of <lb/>amendments by thirty States Parties" 44 . Paragraph 3 says that the Court <lb/>"shall exercise jurisdiction over the crime of aggression in accordance with <lb/>this Article, subject to a decision to be taken after 1 January 2017 by the <lb/>same majority of States Parties as is required for the adoption of an <lb/>amendment to the Statute." 45 The required majority at this later date is thus <lb/>two-thirds of all the States Parties at the relevant time. 46 Accordingly, the <lb/>earliest date on which these provisions can become operative is the date on <lb/>which the decision is made by the ASP after 1 January 2017. If the 30 <lb/>ratifications have been received by then (or at least a year before then), all is <lb/>well; otherwise there will be a further delay until one year after the 30 <lb/>ratifications are obtained. 47 <lb/>It should be noted that the requirement of 30 ratifications here is a <lb/>"procedural" hurdle to the entry into force of the amendment. 48 It does not <lb/>mean that the Security Council is limited to making referrals only in respect <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>43 <lb/>Art. 15ter, supra note 8, para. 1, Article 13 (b) of the Rome Statute, supra note 1, <lb/>permits Security Council referrals to the Court. <lb/>44 <lb/>Art. 15ter, supra note 8, para. 2. <lb/>45 <lb/>Id., para. 3. <lb/>46 <lb/>Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 121 (3). <lb/>47 <lb/>And see Understandings, supra note 8, annex III, para. 1. <lb/>It is understood that the Court may exercise jurisdiction on the basis of a Security <lb/>Council referral in accordance with Art. 13 (b) of the Statute only with <lb/>respect to crimes of aggression committed after a decision in accordance with Art. <lb/>15ter (3) is taken, and one year after the ratification or acceptance of the <lb/>amendments by thirty States Parties, whichever is later. <lb/>Note also Resolution 6 itself, supra note 8, in para. 4 of which the Review Conference <lb/>decided "to review the amendments on the crime of aggression seven years after the <lb/>beginning of the Court's exercise of jurisdiction.". <lb/>48 <lb/>The Conference presumably found power to impose conditions such as these under the <lb/>general reference in Art. 5 (2) ICC Statute to "setting out the conditions" for the <lb/>exercise of jurisdiction over aggression. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>703 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>of those states that have ratified the amendment (or the Statute itself, for that <lb/>matter). The nationals of any states may be the subject of a referral once the <lb/>timing and ratification requirements are met. 49 <lb/>Paragraph 4 adds the important principle 50 that "[a] determination of <lb/>an act of aggression by an organ outside the Court shall be without prejudice <lb/>to the Court's own findings under this Statute." Including this language in <lb/>the Article dealing with Security Council referrals underscores the way the <lb/>negotiation has developed towards making the Court master of its own <lb/>decisions in respect of the elements of a particular (alleged) crime of <lb/>aggression. 51 <lb/>So much for Security Council referrals. Article 15bis, as finally <lb/>adopted, deals with the exercise of jurisdiction over the crime of aggression <lb/>in the case of State referrals and referrals by the Prosecutor proprio motu. <lb/>The Court is authorized to exercise jurisdiction over the crime of aggression <lb/>in accordance with Article 13, paragraphs (a) and (c), subject to the other <lb/>provisions of the Article. 52 Once again, there is the requirement of <lb/>ratification or acceptance by 30 States Parties, 53 the passage of a year after <lb/>that, and the further vote after 1 January 2017. 54 Then follows a strange <lb/>"opt-out" provision that reads: <lb/>The Court may, in accordance with Article 12, exercise jurisdiction <lb/>over a crime of aggression, arising from an act of aggression committed by <lb/>a State Party, unless that State Party has previously declared that it does not <lb/>accept such jurisdiction by lodging a declaration with the Registrar. The <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>49 <lb/>This is the general rule on Security Council referrals (as exercised in the case of <lb/>Sudan and Darfur, Sudan not being a party to the Statute). The "preconditions" for a <lb/>Security Council referral in Art. 12 of the ICC Statute do not include the requirement, <lb/>as in the case of state and proprio motu referrals, that either the state of territoriality or <lb/>the state of nationality be party to the Statute. See also Understandings, supra note 8, <lb/>annex III, para. 2: <lb/>It is understood that the Court shall exercise jurisdiction over the crime of aggression <lb/>on the basis of a Security Council referral in accordance with Art. 13 (b) <lb/>of the Statute, irrespective of whether the State concerned has accepted the Court's <lb/>jurisdiction in this regard. <lb/>50 <lb/>Supra note 13 and 40, derived from the SWGCA draft. Note, however, that a referral <lb/>by the Security Council does not necessarily entail a determination that an act of <lb/>aggression has occurred, although it may. The Council may simply conclude that there <lb/>is a prima facie case, but leave the rest to the Court. <lb/>51 <lb/>See references in fn. 36, 37. <lb/>52 <lb/>Res. 6, supra note 8, Art.15bis para. 1. <lb/>53 <lb/>Id., para. 2. <lb/>54 <lb/>Id., para. 3. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>704 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>withdrawal of such a declaration may be effected at any time and shall be <lb/>considered by the State Party within three years. 55 <lb/>The careful reader will have noted the language: "exercise jurisdiction <lb/>over a crime of aggression, arising from an act of aggression committed by <lb/>a State Party." "State Party" must mean State Party to the Rome Statute. <lb/>There is no suggestion here that the Court's jurisdiction is limited to those <lb/>States that have ratified the amendment. A State which has not done so, can, <lb/>on the plain language of the amendment, protect its people from the <lb/>jurisdiction by utilizing the opt-out provision. Indeed, the opt-out language, <lb/>on its face, seems to be coherent only on the possibility that any State Party <lb/>may want to opt out! <lb/>The effect of the language also seems to be that a State Party may <lb/>ratify the amendment and constitute one of the 30 states necessary to bring it <lb/>into force, but block the application of state or proprio motu triggers of the <lb/>jurisdiction with respect to itself. (Like all other States, it apparently cannot <lb/>protect its nationals from being the subject of a Security Council referral.) It <lb/>would take some nerve to help make up the thirty and then opt out, but one <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>55 <lb/>Id., para. 4. Prior to Kampala, there had been some discussion of the appropriate <lb/>modalities for adoption and ratification or acceptance of the provisions making the <lb/>jurisdiction over aggression effective. This took the form of attempts to interpret Art. <lb/>121 (3), (4) and (5) of the Rome Statute, the article on amendment. The correct <lb/>analysis of language that became confusing in the last few days of the Rome <lb/>Conference could perhaps never be ascertained with certainty. I interpret Art. 15bis <lb/>(4) as a finesse of that whole issue, done by consensus of the Parties. Objecting Parties <lb/>have their opt-out rights, something not entirely satisfactory to all, but the trade-off is <lb/>that the provisions can become operative in a reasonable time and with intelligible <lb/>procedural hurdles. There is, perhaps, a (less-than-convincing) counter-argument in <lb/>para. 1 of Resolution 6, supra note 8, in which the Review Conference: <lb/>"1. Decides to adopt, in accordance with Article 5, paragraph 2, of the Rome Statute <lb/>of the International Criminal Court (hereinafter: "the Statute") the amendments to the <lb/>Statute contained in annex I of the present resolution, which are subject to ratification <lb/>or acceptance and shall enter into force in accordance with Art. 121, paragraph 5; and <lb/>notes that any State Party may lodge a declaration referred to in Art.15 bis prior to <lb/>ratification or acceptance." <lb/>I think this must just be referring to the time frame for the ratification to become <lb/>effective, thus setting up the requirement of entry into force a year after the 30 are <lb/>obtained. If all State Parties are not to be bound, the opt-out option makes no sense. <lb/>Compare the resolution on weapons, infra note 70, which makes clear the application <lb/>of the amendments only to those who specifically accept them. Notice that an opt-out <lb/>declaration may be made at any time, even before the necessary passage of seven <lb/>years or the receipt of thirty ratifications. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>705 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>should never underestimate the acrobatic ability of the diplomatic mind in <lb/>construing the national interest! <lb/>Paragraph 5 addresses the non-State party problem. It was of <lb/>particular significance for the three Permanent members of the Security <lb/>Council who have not become party to the Rome Statute -China, the <lb/>Russian Federation and the United States -and for other non-parties who are <lb/>wont to use force outside their own territories. It provides that "[i]n respect <lb/>of a State that is not a party to this Statute, the Court shall not exercise <lb/>jurisdiction over the crime of aggression when committed by that State's <lb/>nationals or on its territory." 56 <lb/>In the negotiations leading up to Kampala, there was widespread <lb/>support for the proposition that where an aggression occurs against a State <lb/>Party to the Statute, the Article 12 precondition of ratification by the state of <lb/>territoriality should be sufficient for the Court's jurisdiction. Article 12 <lb/>requires that either the state of territoriality or the state of nationality be a <lb/>party. An aggression, so the argument goes, can, as a matter of territoriality, <lb/>take place both in the state where the aggression is plotted, and in the place <lb/>where it is executed (the "victim state"). This is in accordance with the <lb/>normal rules on "effects" or "objective territorial" jurisdiction and seems to <lb/>be the case with genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes. Thus, a <lb/>citizen of a non-state party who commits genocide, war crimes or crimes <lb/>against humanity on the territory (or having effect on the territory) of a State <lb/>Party is subject to ICC jurisdiction. <lb/>The present provision is aimed at upsetting this implication, <lb/>specifically in respect of aggression, and preventing jurisdiction over <lb/>aggression in such cases. It is probably another example of a small but <lb/>powerful minority protecting its own position in a consensus negotiation. 57 <lb/>Paragraphs 6, 7 and 8 resolve the various Security Council "red <lb/>light" and "green light" options concerning state and proprio motu referrals <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>56 <lb/>Res. 6, supra note 8, Art. 15bis (5). The argument is that, whatever one might think <lb/>about jurisdiction over genocide and the other crimes so far as non-parties acting on <lb/>the territory of parties, aggression is of a different political and juridical dimension <lb/>and should be treated differently. <lb/>57 <lb/>See also the related point made in Understanding 5, supra note 8, annex III, that "the <lb/>amendments shall not be interpreted as creating the right or obligation to exercise <lb/>domestic jurisdiction with respect to an act of aggression committed by another <lb/>State." Customary law on universal jurisdiction over aggression (and perhaps even <lb/>victim state jurisdiction) may not be as developed as it is in relation to other <lb/>international crimes, and this language is at least neutral, and perhaps discouraging, of <lb/>developments in custom in this area. Is aggression different? <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>706 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>that had been considered intensively but inconclusively before Kampala. <lb/>(Note that this is now in the context of cases where the Security Council has <lb/>not made a referral to the Court and may, or may not, have adopted a <lb/>resolution in respect of actions by a State in respect of a situation coming <lb/>before the Court.) <lb/>Where the Prosecutor concludes that there is a reasonable basis to <lb/>proceed with an investigation in respect of a crime of aggression, proprio <lb/>motu or following a state referral, he is required to first ascertain whether <lb/>the Security Council has made a determination of an act of aggression <lb/>committed by the State concerned. The Prosecutor is to notify the Secretary-<lb/>General of the United Nations of the situation before the Court, including <lb/>any relevant information and documents. 58 If, in fact, the Security Council <lb/>has made a determination of an act of aggression, the Prosecutor may <lb/>proceed with the investigation. 59 Then comes the crunch issue: what if the <lb/>Security Council has not acted, and does not now act? The consensus in <lb/>Kampala represented a strong resolution of an issue that had bedeviled the <lb/>earlier negotiations. The relevant language reads: <lb/>Where no such determination is made within six months after the date <lb/>of notification, the Prosecutor may proceed with the investigation in respect <lb/>of a crime of aggression, provided that the Pre-Trial Division has authorized <lb/>the commencement of the investigation in respect of a crime of aggression <lb/>in accordance with the procedure contained in Article 15, and the Security <lb/>Council has not decided otherwise in accordance with Article 16. 60 <lb/>The "filter" in the ordinary case is not the Security Council, but the <lb/>Pre-Trial Division, that it to say, a majority of all six members of that <lb/>Division sitting together en banc. If the Security Council wishes to enter the <lb/>fray, it must put up its stop-light. But notice that, consistent with the <lb/>existing Rome compromise, contained in Article 16 of the Statute, a <lb/>dissenting member of the Permanent Five members of the Security Council <lb/>cannot stop the process by exercising a veto. It is only where the five are <lb/>agreed (and obtain the other necessary votes) that proceedings may be <lb/>stopped in their tracks. <lb/>Obtaining such a comprehensive consensus was no mean feat! <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>58 <lb/>Res. 6, supra note 8, Art. 15bis (6). <lb/>59 <lb/>Id,. Art. 15bis (7). <lb/>60 <lb/>Id., Art 15bis (8). This is followed by the statement also found in 15ter (4), supra note <lb/>13 and 50, that "[a] determination of an act of aggression by an organ outside the <lb/>Court shall be without prejudice to the Court's own findings under this Statute". <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>707 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>D. Forbidden Weapons in the Statute <lb/>It has long been understood in the laws of armed conflict that some <lb/>weaponry is regarded as so barbaric or so incapable of distinguishing <lb/>between soldiers and civilians that its use is forbidden. 61 These prohibitions <lb/>applied originally to international armed conflict but, during the last <lb/>century, some of the prohibitions were extended, primarily by custom but <lb/>occasionally by treaty, to their use in non-international armed conflict. The <lb/>distinctions between rules of all kinds applicable in international and non-<lb/>international armed conflict are slowly disappearing. 62 Thus, the non-<lb/>international armed conflict parts of the Rome Statute include a number of <lb/>rules taken, for example, from the Hague Convention of 1907 that applied <lb/>originally only to international armed conflict. Nevertheless, the rules on <lb/>forbidden weaponry contained in the Rome Statute apply only in the <lb/>international variety. They are found in Article 8 (2) (b) of the Statute, <lb/>which deals with "[o]ther serious violations of the laws and customs <lb/>applicable in international armed conflict, within the established framework <lb/>of international law" 63 . They provide as follows: <lb/>(xvii) Employing poison or poisoned weapons; <lb/>(xviii) Employing asphyxiating, poisonous or other gases and all <lb/>analogous liquids, materials or devices; <lb/>(xix) Employing bullets which expand or flatten easily in the human <lb/>body, such as bullets with a hard envelope which does not entirely <lb/>cover the core or is pierced with incisions[.] <lb/>Article 8 (2) (e) of the Statute, which deals with "[o]ther serious <lb/>violations of the laws and customs applicable in armed conflicts not of an <lb/>international character, within the established framework of international <lb/>law," contains no such provisions. A draft amendment forwarded to the <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>61 <lb/>See J.-M. Henckaerts, &amp; L. Doswald-Beck, for International Committee of the Red <lb/>Cross, Customary International Humanitarian Law Volume I: Rules, 243 (examples <lb/>of weapons causing unnecessary suffering, beginning with barbed lances and barbed <lb/>spears), 249 (examples of indiscriminate weapons). <lb/>62 <lb/>See J. G. Stewart, 'Towards a single definition of armed conflict in international <lb/>humanitarian law: A critique of internationalized armed conflict,' 85 International <lb/>Review of the Red Cross (2003) 313; L. Moir, 'Grave Breaches and Internal Armed <lb/>Conflicts', 7 Journal of International Criminal Justice (2009) 4, 763. <lb/>63 <lb/>Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 8 (2) (b). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>708 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Review Conference contained a proposal originally put forward informally <lb/>by Belgium early in 2009 and later co-sponsored by nineteen other States <lb/>Parties. It aimed at including the same language in paragraph (2) (e) of <lb/>Article 8 as is contained in paragraph 2 (b). 64 The principle that weapons <lb/>that are not permissible in international conflict are equally not permissible <lb/>in civil wars would be enshrined in the Rome Statute. <lb/>This amendment and the accompanying Elements of Crimes, based <lb/>on the similar crimes in international armed conflict, were duly adopted in <lb/>Kampala. 65 The way the negotiation developed, however, it was thought <lb/>necessary to address a matter in the preamble of the adopting resolution that <lb/>had previously found a solution in the relevant Elements of Crimes adopted <lb/>by the Preparatory Commission for the Court in respect of the original <lb/>weapons prohibitions applicable in international armed conflict. Expanding <lb/>bullets, unlike the other weapons in the Rome Statute, are said not to be <lb/>absolutely banned, even in armed conflict. 66 They may have a legitimate use <lb/>in a narrow range of circumstance, even in the context of an armed conflict. <lb/>This is particularly the case when troops are endeavouring to rescue <lb/>hostages taken in the conflict, without killing the hostages. A regular bullet <lb/>may go through a participant and hit an innocent person. Thus, expanding <lb/>bullets that remain in the person at whom they are aimed, may be used. 67 <lb/>The matter was addressed in Kampala, in part as it had been addressed <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>64 <lb/>This and other proposals for amendment that got as far as the November meeting of <lb/>the Assembly of States Parties are contained in Report of the Bureau on the Review <lb/>Conference, Doc. ICC-ASP/8/43/Add.1, dated 10 November 2009 and in Report of <lb/>the Working Group on the Review Conference, Annex II to Vol. I, Official Records of <lb/>the Eighth Session of the Assembly of States Parties. Doc. ICC-ASP/8/20 (2009). At <lb/>the November meeting, the International Committee of the Red Cross commented in a <lb/>statement that "[t]he prohibitions of poison or poisoned weapons, asphyxiating, <lb/>poisonous or other gases as well as bullets which expand or flatten easily in the body, <lb/>are well-established under customary international law applicable in all armed <lb/>conflicts and are an expression of the prohibition of weapons that are of a nature to <lb/>cause superfluous injury or unnecessary suffering or are by nature indiscriminate. <lb/>Conduct in violation of these prohibitions should therefore be criminalized in all <lb/>armed conflicts." (Statement by ICRC to Assembly of States Parties, on file with <lb/>author.). <lb/>65 <lb/>Amendments to Art. 8 of the Rome Statute, RC/Res. 5 (2010). <lb/>66 <lb/>They also have an arguably legitimate role in domestic police work, where there is a <lb/>danger to such persons as hostages, dignitaries, other police officers or bystanders if <lb/>bullets aimed at criminals go through them and hit someone else. <lb/>67 <lb/>Representatives of several armed forces assured the author in Kampala that their <lb/>troops are armed with a very limited supply of such bullets, carefully kept aside for <lb/>such events and used sparingly. Belgium, it appears, manufactures such ammunition. <lb/></listBibl>
              
        <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>709 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>previously in the Elements for international armed conflict 68 and in part in <lb/>the preamble to the adopting resolution. The latter insists on an <lb/>"understanding that the crime is committed only if the perpetrator employs <lb/>the bullets to uselessly aggravate suffering or the wounding effect upon the <lb/>target of such bullets, as reflected in customary international law" 69 . <lb/>This is an important, 70 if modest, addition to the Statute. It <lb/>establishes the principle that if weapons are prohibited in international <lb/>armed conflict, they are also prohibited in the non-international variety. <lb/>More might perhaps have been achieved if the stars had been <lb/>differently aligned. Belgium, again supported by various groups of co-<lb/>sponsors, had also put before the Assembly several proposals for the <lb/>addition of other weapons to the lists of those prohibited both in <lb/>international and in non-international armed conflict. These included <lb/>chemical weapons, 71 biological weapons, 72 anti-personnel land mines, 73 <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>68 <lb/>The relevant Element of the war crime of employing prohibited bullets adopted in <lb/>Kampala for non-international armed conflict mirrors precisely that for international <lb/>armed conflict: "The perpetrator was aware that the nature of the bullets was such that <lb/>their employment would uselessly aggravate suffering or the wounding effect.". <lb/>69 <lb/>Weapons adopting resolution, supra note 65, preambular paragraph 9, 2. <lb/>70 <lb/>In accordance with Art. 121 (5) of the Rome Statute, supra note 1, this amendment to <lb/>Art. 8 will apply only to those States Parties to the Statute who specifically ratify or <lb/>accept it. This is specifically acknowledged in preambular paragraph 2, 1 of the <lb/>resolution adopting the weapons amendment, supra note 65. Compare the finesse of <lb/>the issue in the aggression amendment, supra note 55. <lb/>71 <lb/>Such weapons are banned by the Convention on the Development, Production, <lb/>Stockpiling and Use of Chemical Weapons and on Their Destruction, 3 September <lb/>1992, 1974 U.N.T.S. 45. Most chemical weapons appear to be banned in warfare <lb/>under the Geneva Protocol for the Prohibition of the Use in War of Asphyxiating, <lb/>Poisonous or Other Gases, and of Bacteriological Methods of Warfare, 17 June 1925, <lb/>94 L.N.T.S. 65 [Geneva Protocol], which is reiterated in Art. 8 (2) (b) (xviii) of the <lb/>Rome Statute, but this is not free from doubt; thus there should probably be express <lb/>references in the Rome Statute to the later treaty. Drafts on the table in Rome until a <lb/>very late stage included chemical weapons but the reference to such weapons was <lb/>deleted in the last few days of the conference. <lb/>72 <lb/>Biological weapons are prohibited under the 1925 Geneva Protocol, supra note 71, <lb/>along with asphyxiating and poisonous gases. There are further regime-articulating <lb/>provisions dealing with them in the Convention on the Prohibition of the <lb/>Development, production and Stockpiling of Bacteriological (Biological) and Toxin <lb/>Weapons and Their Destruction, 10. April 1972, 1015 U.N.T.S. 163. Biological <lb/>weapons were deleted from the draft of the Statute along with chemical weapons; <lb/>there is no reference to them at all in the final Statute. <lb/>73 <lb/>Anti-personnel mines are prohibited under the Convention on the Prohibition of the <lb/>Use, Stockpiling, Production and Transfer of Anti-personnel Mines and on Their <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">GoJIL 2 (2010) 2, 689-711 <lb/></note>
    
    <page>710 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>non-detectable fragments, 74 blinding laser weapons 75 and cluster <lb/>munitions. 76 It was not possible to forge a consensus to send these on to the <lb/>Review Conference. Nor was Mexico able to muster substantial support for <lb/>its proposal to include nuclear weapons amongst those forbidden by the <lb/>Statute. 77 Nonetheless, the Assembly agreed to establish a Working Group <lb/>as from its ninth session late in 2010 for the purpose of considering these <lb/>remaining proposals for amendments. <lb/>The Working Group to be created later in 2010 will also have on its <lb/>agenda two other proposals put forward for additions to the Statute that <lb/>were not sent on to Kampala, terrorism and drug trafficking, the former put <lb/>forward by The Netherlands, 78 the latter by Trinidad and Tobago supported <lb/>by Belize. 79 Earlier versions of both of these proposals had been considered <lb/>and deferred at Rome, largely on the basis of the argument that a new and <lb/>untested organization should not be too ambitious in its early jurisdictional <lb/>net. 80 In fact, most of the larger powers were -and continue to be -happy <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>Destruction, 18 September 1997, 2056 U.N.T.S. 211 [the "Ottawa Convention"]. At <lb/>the time of Rome, the ink was barely dry on this Convention and it had not yet come <lb/>into force. It is now widely ratified, having 156 parties by mind-2010. There are still <lb/>some major powers, like the United States, that have not come aboard. <lb/>74 <lb/>Such weapons are prohibited in Protocol I (Non-Detectable Fragments) to the 1980 <lb/>Convention on Prohibitions or Restrictions on the Use of Certain Conventional <lb/>Weapons which may be deemed to be Excessively Injurious or to have Indiscriminate <lb/>Effects, 10 October 1980, 1342 U.N.T.S. 137. <lb/>75 <lb/>Protocol IV to the 1980 Convention, supra note 74, on Blinding Laser Weapons, 13 <lb/>October 1995, 2024 U.N.T.S. 163, 167 (Doc. No. CCW/CONF.I/16 Part I). <lb/>76 <lb/>See Diplomatic Conference for the Adoption of a Convention on Cluster Munitions, <lb/>Dublin, May 19-30, 2008, Convention on Cluster Munitions, Doc. No. CCM/77 (30 <lb/>May 2008), available at <lb/>http://www.clusterconvention.org/downloadablefiles/ccm77_english.pdf (last visited <lb/>17 August 2010). Arguably, this Convention is not ripe enough for inclusion in the <lb/>Rome Statute since it is not yet overwhelmingly adopted. It came into force on 1 <lb/>August 2010, six months after receipt of 30 ratifications. <lb/>77 <lb/>See Doc. ICC-ASP/8/43/Add. 1, supra note 64 (Annex III), at 9; Doc. ICC-ASP/8/20, <lb/>Vol. I, supra note 64 (Annex II, Appendix II), at 64. <lb/>78 <lb/>Id., 8/43/Add. 1 (Annex IV), at 12; 8/20, Vol. I (Appendix III) at 65. <lb/>79 <lb/>Id., 8/43/Add. 1 (Annex VI) at 16; 8/20, Vol. I (Appendix IV) at 67. <lb/>80 <lb/>The additional argument that terrorism should not be included in the Statute because it <lb/>is not yet defined is something of a red herring. There is a widely agreed list of <lb/>suppression treaties that deal with many of the cases of terrorism. It would be easy <lb/>enough to include such a list as an interim "definition" to be supplemented should the <lb/>General Assembly ever complete its work on a "general" terrorism convention. Which <lb/>are the most serious drug crimes and thus appropriate for international jurisdiction is a <lb/>fair question. The Trinidad and Tobago/Belize draft approached this in a creative <lb/>manner that certainly provides a basis for further discussion. Their draft in the Report <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court</note>
    
    <page>711 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>with the way the current criminalization regime operates in these areas, <lb/>namely with a suppression obligation in the relevant treaties and prosecution <lb/>at the domestic level. Since they have the resources to devote to such <lb/>efforts, the larger powers are comfortable with those modalities. Small <lb/>states, on the other hand, would often be happy to have an international <lb/>instance to which they could refer such cases, thereby avoiding having their <lb/>own resources overwhelmed. The debate will surely continue. <lb/>E. Conclusion <lb/>The Kampala Conference ended in the early hours of the morning in a <lb/>mood of euphoria, nearly as great, in the writer's view, as that in Rome in <lb/>1998. While the effort to remove Article 124 failed, the principle that if a <lb/>weapon is forbidden in international conflict it is equally forbidden in a civil <lb/>war was strongly asserted. The achievement of consensus on the crime of <lb/>aggression, activating the Court's jurisdiction -albeit with some delay -<lb/>constituted a remarkable achievement and a great source of satisfaction to <lb/>those who have laboured for it these many years. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>of the Bureau on the Review Conference, supra note 64, (at 16) would authorize ICC <lb/>jurisdiction over assorted breaches of the 1961 Single Convention on Narcotic Drugs, <lb/>the 1971 Convention on Psychotropic Substances and the 1988 United Nations <lb/>Convention against Illicit Traffic in Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances, "but <lb/>only when they pose a threat to the peace, order and security of a State or region." <lb/>There is thus a strong threshold element that would have to be proved by the <lb/>prosecution. </listBibl>


	</text>


  
  </TEI>