<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">The Polish Financial Supervision Authority in The European Union's Financial Supervision Architecture</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Tomasz</forename>
          <surname>Knepka</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-10-17T14:07:22.497Z">10/17/2025 3:07:22 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.34767$1$dp.2024.02.02</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Dogmatyka Prawa</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2025</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.34767/dp.2024.02.02</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Tomasz Knepka. (2025). The Polish Financial Supervision Authority in The European Union's Financial Supervision Architecture. None, (), None. DOI: 10.34767/dp.2024.02.02</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-04T22:01:54.106014Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">0707645</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-10-04T22:01:54.106014Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Dogmatyka Prawa • 2024, t. 1, nr 2, s. 27-37 <lb/>Legal Dogmatics • 2024, vol. 1, no. 2, pp. 27-37 <lb/>ISSN 2956-9885 <lb/>DOI.10.34767/DP.2024.02.02 <lb/>Tomasz Knepka <lb/>Uniwersytet Kazimierza Wielkiego w Bydgoszczy <lb/>ORCID: 0000-0002-6848-8239 <lb/>Tomasz Knepka | DOI.10.34767/DP.2024.02.02 | The polish financial supervision authority in the european union's financial… <lb/>The polish financial supervision <lb/>authority in the european union's <lb/>financial supervision architecture <lb/>SUMMARY The purpose of the article/hypothesis: The aim of the study is <lb/>to present the relations between the PFSA and the European supervisory au-<lb/>thorities within the European System of Financial Supervision. Using the above <lb/>methods the following research thesis was formulated: The PFSA as a super-<lb/>visor of the Polish financial market functions in a complex regulatory envi-<lb/>ronment in the European Union, which poses a great challenge in achieving <lb/>the objectives for which it was established. <lb/>Methodology: The basic research method used in the paper is the dogmat-<lb/>ic-legal method, the application of which allowed to formulate the research <lb/>thesis. Moreover, the analysis of the preambles to the acts of the European <lb/>Union law and the literature on the subject, especially of the representatives <lb/>of the doctrine of the financial market law, were helpful. <lb/>Results of the research: The shape of financial supervision architecture is <lb/>changing as a result of financial market disturbances. The European Union <lb/>financial market, as a part of the global financial market, is particularly sus-<lb/>ceptible to such changes. The Polish Financial Supervision Authority is a part <lb/>of the integrating financial market within the Economic and Monetary Union <lb/>and has to face modern challenges resulting from globalization. <lb/>KEYWORDS: Polish Financial Supervision Authority, European System <lb/>of Financial Supervision, Financial Architecture <lb/>JEL Class: G15, G32, H12, K23 <lb/></front>
              
         <note place="headnote"> DOGMATYKA PRAWA • LEGAL DOGMATICS <lb/></note>
    
    <page>28 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Introduction <lb/>With Poland's accession to the European Union (EU), the public administration <lb/>started to function on the basis of the EU legal order. The Polish Financial Su-<lb/>pervision Authority (PFSA) as a public administration body is a special entity <lb/>in this area. This uniqueness lies in the specific conditions in which the Polish <lb/>financial market supervisor must operate. <lb/>Supervision over the single EU financial market includes EU regulations <lb/>(treaties, directives and regulations) and normative acts of individual EU mem-<lb/>ber states. In the case of Poland, these are: Constitution, laws, regulations and <lb/>the so-called soft law, which has been gaining importance in recent years 1 . <lb/>In the context of the EU acquis communautaire, each EU country applies EU <lb/>law on the principle of supremacy over domestic law 2 . <lb/>The paper contains two parts. The first presents general issues concern-<lb/>ing the European System of Financial Supervision. The second one presents <lb/>the PFSA in the supervisory system of the European Union financial market. <lb/>The aim of the study is to present the relations between the PFSA and <lb/>the European supervisory authorities within the European System of Financial <lb/>Supervision. <lb/>The basic research method used in the paper is the dogmatic-legal method, <lb/>the application of which allowed to formulate the research thesis. Moreover, <lb/>the analysis of the preambles to the acts of the European Union law and the liter-<lb/>ature on the subject, especially of the representatives of the doctrine of the finan-<lb/>cial market law, were helpful. Using the above methods the following research <lb/>thesis was formulated: The PFSA as a supervisor of the Polish financial market <lb/>functions in a complex regulatory environment in the European Union, which poses <lb/>a great challenge in achieving the objectives for which it was established. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>1 See. A. Nadolska, Soft law w regulacji rynku finansowego w Polsce: rekomendacje, wytyczne i lista <lb/>ostrzeżeń publicznych KNF, Warszawa 2021 and M. Fedorowicz, Nadzór nad rynkiem finansowym <lb/>Unii Europejskiej, Warszawa 2013. <lb/>2 See. E. Całka, Zasada pierwszeństwa w prawie Unii Europejskiej. Wybrane problemy, "Studia <lb/>Iuridica Lublinensia" 2016, Vol. 25, No. 1. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote"> Tomasz Knepka • The polish financial supervision authority in the european union's financial… <lb/></note>
    
    <page>29 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>The Architecture of European Union Financial <lb/>Supervision -General Remarks <lb/>The current shape of supervision of the European Union's financial market is <lb/>the result of legislative actions at the EU level in the wake of the financial crisis <lb/>that started in 2007-2008. This supervision comprises two levels: macropruden-<lb/>tial and microprudential, creating the European System of Financial Supervision <lb/>(ESFS). The main objective of the ESFS is to ensure that the rules applicable <lb/>to the financial sector are adequately implemented to preserve financial stability <lb/>and to ensure confidence in the financial system as a whole and adequate pro-<lb/>tection for the consumers of financial services. <lb/>Macroprudential supervision in the EU is carried out by the European Sys-<lb/>temic Risk Board (ESRB), established in 2011 3 . Under European law, the ESRB <lb/>is responsible for the macroprudential oversight of the financial system within <lb/>the Union in order to contribute to the prevention or mitigation of systemic risks <lb/>to financial stability in the Union that arise from events within the financial sys-<lb/>tem, or mitigation of these risks, taking into account macroeconomic develop-<lb/>ments, so as to prevent periods of widespread financial distress. The ESRB shall <lb/>contribute to the smooth functioning of the internal market and thereby ensure <lb/>a sustainable contribution of the financial sector to economic growth 4 . Central <lb/>to the essence of the objective behind the ESRB's activities is the definition <lb/>of "systemic risk" as amended in 2019. This concept in the revised Union Regu-<lb/>lation means that it is a risk of disruption in the financial system that has the po-<lb/>tential to have serious negative consequences for the real economy of the Union <lb/>or one or more of its Member States, as well as for the functioning of the internal <lb/>market. All types of financial intermediaries, markets and infrastructure can be <lb/>potentially systemically important to some extent. 5 At this point in the study, it <lb/>is worth noting that the ESRB issued a recommendation to the Member States <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>3 Regulation (EU) No 1092/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 Novem-<lb/>ber 2010 on European Union macro-prudential oversight of the financial system and establishing <lb/>a European Systemic Risk Board (15.12.2010), Official Journal of the European Union, L 331/1, <lb/>and Regulation (EU) 2019/2176 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 18 December <lb/>2019 amending Regulation (EU) No 1092/2010 on European Union macro-prudential oversight <lb/>of the financial system and establishing a European Systemic Risk Board (27.12.2019), Official Journal <lb/>of the European Union, L 334/146. <lb/>4 Article 3, Regulation 1092/2010. <lb/>5 Article 1, Regulation 2019/2176. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote"> DOGMATYKA PRAWA • LEGAL DOGMATICS <lb/></note>
    
    <page>30 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>in 2011 relating to the establishment of a similar macroprudential authority <lb/>in each country. 6 <lb/>On the other hand, microprudential supervision is carried out by three su-<lb/>pervisory agencies: the European Insurance and Occupational Pensions Author-<lb/>ity (EIOPA) based in Frankfurt 7 , the European Banking Authority (EBA) based <lb/>in Paris 8 , the European Securities and Markets Authority (ESMA) based in Par-<lb/>is 9 , the Joint Committee of the European Supervisory Authorities and competent <lb/>authorities or supervisory authorities of Member States. The Joint Committee <lb/>shall serve as a forum in which the authorities shall cooperate regularly and <lb/>closely to ensure cross-sectoral consistency -taking into account the specificities <lb/>of the different sectors, in particular, with regard to 10 : <lb/>-financial conglomerates and prudential consolidation, <lb/>-accounting and auditing, microprudential analysis of developments, <lb/>-risks and vulnerabilities related to financial stability, <lb/>-retail investment products, <lb/>-cyber-security, information sharing and best practices with the ESRB, <lb/>-retail financial services and depositor, consumer and investor protection <lb/>issues. <lb/>In the case of Poland, the role of a Member State's supervisory authority under <lb/>the EFSF is played by the Polish Financial Supervision Authority (PFSA), which <lb/>exercises supervision over all market segments. The main objective of the PFSA's <lb/>activity -similarly to the European supervisory agencies -is to ensure the proper <lb/>functioning of the market, its stability, security and transparency, trust in the fi-<lb/>nancial market, as well as to ensure the protection of interests of the market <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>6 Recommendation of the European Systemic Risk Board of 22 December 2011 on the macro-pru-<lb/>dential mandate of national authorities (14.2.2012), Official Journal of the European Union, C 41/1. <lb/>7 Regulation (EU) No 1094/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November <lb/>2010 establishing a European Supervisory Authority (European Insurance and Occupational Pen-<lb/>sions Authority), amending Decision No 716/2009/EC and repealing Commission Decision 2009/79/ <lb/>EC, Official Journal of the European Union (15.12.2010), L 331/48. <lb/>8 Regulation (EU) No 1093/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November <lb/>2010 establishing a European Supervisory Authority (European Banking Authority), amending De-<lb/>cision No 716/2009/EC and repealing Commission Decision 2009/78/EC, Official Journal of the Eu-<lb/>ropean Union, (15.12.2010), L 331/12. <lb/>9 Regulation (EU) No 1095/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November <lb/>2010 establishing a European Supervisory Authority (European Securities and Markets Authority), <lb/>amending Decision No 716/2009/EC and repealing Commission Decision 2009/77/EC, Official <lb/>Journal of the European Union (15.12.2010), L 331/84. <lb/>10 Article 54 point 2. Regulation 1093/2010. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote"> Tomasz Knepka • The polish financial supervision authority in the european union's financial… <lb/></note>
    
    <page>31 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>participants also through reliable information on the functioning of the market. 11 <lb/>The tasks of the PFSC include: exercising supervision over the financial market, <lb/>taking actions aimed at the proper functioning of the financial market, taking <lb/>actions aimed at the development of the financial market and its competitiveness, <lb/>taking actions aimed at supporting the development of innovation in the finan-<lb/>cial market, taking educational and informational actions on the functioning <lb/>of the financial market, its risks and the entities operating in it in order to pro-<lb/>tect the legitimate interests of the financial market participants, in particular, <lb/>by publishing -in a form and time determined by it -free of charge warnings <lb/>and announcements on public radio and television, participation in the prepa-<lb/>ration of draft legislation on financial market supervision, creating opportunities <lb/>for amicable and conciliatory settlement of disputes between financial market <lb/>participants, in particular disputes arising from contractual relations between <lb/>entities subject to the supervision of the PFSA and recipients of services provided <lb/>by these entities. 12 <lb/>Moreover, in the light of Polish regulations, the PFSA cooperates with the Eu-<lb/>ropean Commission, the European Central Bank, the European Banking Au-<lb/>thority, the European Insurance and Occupational Pensions Authority, the Eu-<lb/>ropean Securities and Markets Authority, the European Systemic Risk Board <lb/>and the European System of Central Banks, and provides those bodies with all <lb/>information necessary for the performance of their duties. 13 <lb/>The regulations establishing these autonomous regulatory agencies are based <lb/>on Article 114 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union 14 , which <lb/>allows for the adoption of harmonization measures where these are necessary <lb/>for the establishment and functioning of the internal market. The European fi-<lb/>nancial supervision authorities have been given legal personality and the status <lb/>of EU regulatory agencies as independent entities under European public law. 15 <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>11 Article 2 Act of 21 July 2006 on financial market supervision (consolidated text: Journal of Laws <lb/>2006 No. 157 item 1119, as amended). <lb/>12 Article 4.1 Act of 21 July 2006 on financial market supervision (consolidated text: Journal <lb/>of Laws 2006 No. 157 item 1119, as amended). <lb/>13 Article. 17d. (consolidated text: Journal of Laws 2006, No. 157, item 1119, as amended). <lb/>14 Consolidated version of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, Official Journal <lb/>of the European Union (26.10.2012), C 326/47. <lb/>15 A. Jurkowska-Zeidler, Rynek bankowy Unii Europejskiej, [in:] System prawnofinansowy Unii <lb/>Europejskiej, Eds. A. Drwiłło, A. Jurkowska-Zeidler, Warszawa 2010, p. 235. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">DOGMATYKA PRAWA • LEGAL DOGMATICS <lb/></note>
    
    <page>32 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>The Polish Financial Supervision Authority in the European <lb/>Union's Financial Supervision Architecture <lb/>In order to guarantee financial security in the future, the ESRB issued recom-<lb/>mendations on 22 December 2011 recommending that the EU Member States <lb/>establish similar macroprudential authorities within their jurisdictions and that <lb/>these authorities are equipped with appropriate macroprudential policy instru-<lb/>ments. 16 In the aftermath of the crisis and as a result of the recommendations <lb/>issued, the fundamental regulatory weakness of the financial market became <lb/>clear -systemic supervision was lacking. It turned out that something more than <lb/>just supervision of individual institutions, i.e. microprudential supervision, was <lb/>needed. What is needed is systemic supervision, i.e. macroprudential supervi-<lb/>sion, that not only identifies and analyzes, but also actively mitigates the risks <lb/>that threaten the stability of the financial system as a whole. 17 Macroprudential <lb/>supervision is now an important, if not the most important, component of the fi-<lb/>nancial safety net. 18 <lb/>As indicated earlier, the impetus for the current establishment of a national <lb/>macroprudential authority was the recommendation issued in 2011 by the ESRB <lb/>on the macroprudential mandate of national authorities. 19 In that document, <lb/>the Board identified five groups of recommendations for the establishment <lb/>of a macroprudential authority in European Union Member States, these were 20 : <lb/>-definition of the objective, <lb/>-indication of institutional solutions, <lb/>-defining tasks, competences, instruments <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>16 Recommendation of the European Systemic Risk Board of 22 December 2011 on the macro-<lb/>-prudential mandate of national authorities, (14.2.2012), Official Journal of the European Union, <lb/>C 41/1. Recommendation of the European Systemic Risk Board of 4 April 2013 on intermediate <lb/>objectives and instruments of macro-prudential policy, (15.6.2013), Official Journal of the European <lb/>Union, C 170/1. <lb/>17 P. J. Szpunar, Rola polityki makroostrożnościowej w zapobieganiu kryzysom finansowym, "Mate-<lb/>riały i Studia, Zeszyt" 2012, No. 278, p. 5. <lb/>18 A. Dobrzańska, Polityka makroostrożnościowa -zagadnienia instytucjonalne, Teoria i dotychcza-<lb/>sowe doświadczenia w Unii Europejskiej, "Materiały i Studia" 2014, Vol. 307, p. 9. <lb/>19 The current list of national macroprudential authorities in the European Union is available <lb/>on the ESRB website: https://www.esrb.europa.eu/about/orga/list/html/index.en.html [accessed: <lb/>20.01.25]. <lb/>20 Section 1 Recommendations of the European Systemic Risk Board of 22 December <lb/>2011 on the macro-prudential mandate of national authorities, (14.2.2012), Official Journal of the Eu-<lb/>ropean Union, C 41/1. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Tomasz Knepka • The polish financial supervision authority in the european union's financial… <lb/></note>
    
    <page>33 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>-ensuring transparency and accountability <lb/>-ensuring independence. <lb/>As a result of the emergence of this ESRB document, the Act on macropru-<lb/>dential supervision over the financial system and crisis management was passed <lb/>in Poland and implemented in 2015, under which the currently functioning Fi-<lb/>nancial Stability Committee (FSC), which is also the Polish financial safety net, <lb/>started its activities. 21 Thus, Article 95 of this Act derogates from the previous <lb/>Act on the Financial Stability Committee. 22 <lb/>As the title of the "Macroprudential Act" indicates, its norms regulate <lb/>the functioning of macroprudential supervision and possible crisis management <lb/>in the financial system. 23 Such an approach indicates that the entities compris-<lb/>ing the Financial Stability Committee are active both at the stage of preventing <lb/>the occurrence of financial crises (crisis prevention) and at the stage of manag-<lb/>ing disturbances in the Polish financial system (crisis management). Moreover, <lb/>the above follows directly from Article 3.1 of the "Macroprudential Act", which <lb/>states that the Committee is the competent authority in the area of macropru-<lb/>dential supervision and crisis management. The members of the Committee <lb/>are: Minister of Finance, President of the National Bank of Poland, Chairman <lb/>of the Polish Financial Supervision Authority, President of the Management Board <lb/>of the Bank Guarantee Fund. 24 <lb/>The tasks of the Committee in the area of macroprudential supervision <lb/>include 25 : <lb/>-application of macroprudential instruments, including presentation of po-<lb/>sitions and issuance of recommendations, <lb/>-identifying financial institutions posing a significant risk to the financial <lb/>system, cooperation with the European Systemic Risk Board, other Eu-<lb/>ropean Union authorities, macroprudential supervisory authorities from <lb/>the Member States or third countries, as well as international institutions, <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>21 Act of 5 August 2015 on macroprudential supervision of the financial system and crisis mana-<lb/>gement in the financial system (consolidated text: Journal of Laws of 2015, item 1513, as amended). <lb/>22 Article. 95. The Act of 7 November 2008 on the Financial Stability Committee (consolidated <lb/>text: Journal of Laws, item 1317, and of 2013, item 1012, as amended) shall cease to apply. Art. 95. <lb/>23 The first monographic study that comprehensively addresses the subject of macroprudential <lb/>supervision is the book by Magdalena Fedorowicz entitled "Nadzór makroostrożnościowy w Polsce", <lb/>Poznań 2019. <lb/>24 Article 7 (consolidated text: Journal of Laws of 2015, item 1513, as amended). <lb/>25 Article 5 (consolidated text: Journal of Laws of 2015, item 1513, as amended). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">DOGMATYKA PRAWA • LEGAL DOGMATICS <lb/></note>
    
    <page>34 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>-ensuring the proper flow of information between the Committee members <lb/>in order to accomplish its tasks. <lb/>Whereas the tasks in the area of crisis management include 26 : <lb/>-developing and adopting procedures of cooperation in the event of a direct <lb/>threat to the stability of the financial system; the procedures are passed <lb/>on to the Minister of Finance, the National Bank of Poland, the Polish <lb/>Financial Supervision Authority and the Bank Guarantee Fund, <lb/>-coordination of actions of the Committee members in the event of an <lb/>imminent threat to the stability of the financial system or identification <lb/>of a financial institution whose current or projected financial situation <lb/>may pose a threat to further functioning of this institution, the chairman <lb/>provides the Committee with an opinion on the solvency of the financial <lb/>institution, <lb/>-ensuring proper flow of information between the Committee members <lb/>in order to accomplish its tasks. <lb/>In order to strengthen international cooperation in the area of crisis manage-<lb/>ment tasks, the members of the PFSA may conclude agreements with the institu-<lb/>tions performing tasks in this scope in the Member States, with the central banks <lb/>of the European System of Central Banks, 27 including the European Central <lb/>Bank, as well as with the ministers of finance and the financial market supervi-<lb/>sion authorities in the Member States. 28 <lb/>The functioning of the PFSA in macroprudential supervision is closely relat-<lb/>ed to EU microprudential supervision. As regards microprudential supervision, <lb/>as was mentioned earlier, the PFSA cooperates with the European Commis-<lb/>sion, the European Banking Authority, the European Insurance and Occupa-<lb/>tional Pensions Authority, the European Securities and Markets Authority and <lb/>the European System of Central Banks in the light of Polish regulations and <lb/>provides them with all information necessary for performing their duties. This <lb/>cooperation also results from the acts of European law regulating the function-<lb/>ing of particular supervisory agencies over particular market segments -EBA, <lb/>ESMA and EIOPA. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>26 Article 6 (consolidated text: Journal of Laws of 2015, item 1513, as amended). <lb/>27 The European System of Central Banks is a system consisting of the central banks of the Mem-<lb/>ber States of the European Union, both those that have adopted the single currency and those that <lb/>do not have the euro. According to Article 282 TFEU, the European Central Bank and the national <lb/>central banks of the Member States whose currency is the euro, which form the Eurosystem, conduct <lb/>the monetary policy of the Union. <lb/>28 Article 16 (consolidated text: Journal of Laws of 2015, item 1513, as amended). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Tomasz Knepka • The polish financial supervision authority in the european union's financial… <lb/></note>
    
    <page>35 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Conclusion <lb/>Within the systemic approach to regulation of the European financial market, <lb/>the essence of which is to increase its security, ensure a high level of protection <lb/>for its participants and prevent financial crises, the legal framework for the func-<lb/>tioning of the internal financial market was established. 29 The Polish Financial <lb/>Supervision Authority is an important element of this multi-level supervisory <lb/>structure. The Polish financial market supervisory authority is one of the links <lb/>designed to ensure financial security. Such integrated financial supervision stems <lb/>from the globalization of financial markets, of which the Polish Financial Super-<lb/>vision Authority is an inseparable part, and the current shape of the supervisory <lb/>architecture indicates that the supervisory approach is crucial to ensure financial <lb/>stability. There are also challenges arising from the fact that not all Member States <lb/>have centralised supervision along the lines of the the Polish Financial Super-<lb/>vision Authority. For example -as indicated by Michał Mariański -the separa-<lb/>tion of an auxiliary pillar of financial market supervision in France in the form <lb/>of the Autorité de contrôle prudentiel et de résolution is a solution very similar <lb/>to the model that functioned in Poland in 2006-2008. Like the then Banking <lb/>Supervision Commission, the ACPR is closely linked to the central bank, which <lb/>is intended to contribute to a coordinated yet more specialized supervision <lb/>of the sector. 30 <lb/>The special legal regime of the financial market and its separate nature from <lb/>other market segments means that it is subject to special organization and su-<lb/>pervision by the state. 31 As Anna Jurkowska-Zeidler points out, the systemic <lb/>approach to the European banking market implies that it is impossible to build <lb/>a uniform financial market that would be regulated and supervised by all nation-<lb/>al regulatory and supervisory institutions located in different member states. 32 <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>29 A. Jurkowska-Zeidler, Zmiany w otoczeniu regulacyjnym Unii Europejskiej, [in:] XXV lat prze-<lb/>obrażeń w prawie finansowym i prawie podatkowym -ocena dokonań i wnioski na przyszłość, Ed. <lb/>Z. Ofiarski, Szczecin 2014, pp. 712-713. <lb/>30 M. Mariański, Uprawnienia i kompetencje francuskiego pomocniczego organu nadzoru nad ryn-<lb/>kiem finansowym Autorité de contrôle prudentiel et de résolution, "Przegląd Prawa Handlowego" <lb/>2023, No. 4, pp. 38-44. <lb/>31 A. Jurkowska-Zeidler, Publicznoprawne formy oddziaływania państwa i Unii Europejskiej na in-<lb/>stytucje kredytowe i finansowe [in:] System prawa finansowego, Vol. 4, Ed. J. Głuchowski, Warszawa <lb/>2010, p. 251. <lb/>32 A. Jurkowska-Zeidler, Rynek bankowy…, p. 220. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">DOGMATYKA PRAWA • LEGAL DOGMATICS <lb/></note>
    
    <page>36 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Therefore, the creation of pan-European supervision of the financial market <lb/>with close cooperation of national supervisors -in the case of Poland, the Pol-<lb/>ish Financial Supervision Authority -is an important step in managing future <lb/>financial crises. <lb/>As a collegiate body in the area of banking supervision, the Polish Financial <lb/>Supervision Authority performs typical functions of a modern regulator and <lb/>supervisor, i.e. licensing, supervision and regulation. 33 The above functions are <lb/>conducive to the PFSA's preventive role, i.e. the prevention of the aforementioned <lb/>financial crises. <lb/>The shape of financial supervision architecture is changing as a result of fi-<lb/>nancial market disturbances. The European Union financial market, as a part <lb/>of the global financial market, is particularly susceptible to such changes. <lb/>The Polish Financial Supervision Authority is a part of the integrating financial <lb/>market within the Economic and Monetary Union and has to face modern chal-<lb/>lenges resulting from globalization. <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>Bibliography <lb/>Literature <lb/>Całka E., Zasada pierwszeństwa w prawie Unii Europejskiej. Wybrane problemy, "Studia Iu-<lb/>ridica Lublinensia" 2016, Vol. 25, No. 1. <lb/>Dobrzańska A., Polityka makroostrożnościowa -zagadnienia instytucjonalne, Teoria i do-<lb/>tychczasowe doświadczenia w Unii Europejskiej, "Materiały i Studia" 2014, No. 307. <lb/>Fedorowicz M., Nadzór makroostrożnościowy w Polsce, Poznań 2019. <lb/>Fedorowicz M., Nadzór nad rynkiem finansowym Unii Europejskiej, Warszawa 2013. <lb/>Głuchowski J., Komisja Nadzoru Finansowego oraz Urząd Komisji Nadzoru Finansowego <lb/>[in:] System prawa finansowego, Vol. 4, Ed. J. Głuchowski, Warszawa 2010. <lb/>Jurkowska-Zeidler A., Rynek bankowy Unii Europejskiej [in:] System prawnofinansowy Un-<lb/>ii Europejskiej, Eds. A. Drwiłło, A. Jurkowska-Zeidler. <lb/>Jurkowska-Zeidler A., Publicznoprawne formy oddziaływania państwa i Unii Europejskiej <lb/>na instytucje kredytowe i finansowe [in:] System prawa finansowego, Vol. 4, Ed. J. Głu-<lb/>chowski, Warszawa 2010. <lb/>Jurkowska-Zeidler A., Zmiany w otoczeniu regulacyjnym Unii Europejskiej [in:] XXV lat <lb/>przeobrażeń w prawie finansowym i prawie podatkowym -ocena dokonań i wnioski <lb/>na przyszłość, Ed. Z. Ofiarski, Szczecin 2014. <lb/>Mariański M., Uprawnienia i kompetencje francuskiego pomocniczego organu nadzoru nad <lb/>rynkiem finansowym Autorité de contrôle prudentiel et de résolution, "Przegląd Prawa <lb/>Handlowego" 2023, No. 4. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <listBibl>33 J. Głuchowski, Komisja Nadzoru Finansowego oraz Urząd Komisji Nadzoru Finansowego [in:] <lb/>System prawa finansowego, Vol. 4, Ed. J. Głuchowski, Warszawa 2010, p. 145. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Tomasz Knepka • The polish financial supervision authority in the european union's financial… <lb/></note>
    
    <page>37 <lb/></page>
    
    <listBibl>Nadolska A., Soft law w regulacji rynku finansowego w Polsce: rekomendacje, wytyczne i lis-<lb/>ta ostrzeżeń publicznych KNF, Warszawa 2021. <lb/>Szpunar P.J., Rola polityki makroostrożnościowej w zapobieganiu kryzysom finansowym, <lb/>"Materiały i Studia" 2012, No. 278. <lb/>Acts of Polish law and European Union law <lb/>The Act of 21 July 2006 on financial market supervision (consolidated text: Journal of Laws <lb/>2006 No. 157 item 1119, as amended). <lb/>The Act of 5 August 2015 on macroprudential supervision of the financial system and cri-<lb/>sis management in the financial system (consolidated text: Journal of Laws of 2015, <lb/>item 1513, as amended). <lb/>The Act of 7 November 2008 on the Financial Stability Committee (consolidated text: Jour-<lb/>nal of Laws, item 1317, and of 2013, item 1012, as amended). <lb/>Consolidated version of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, Official <lb/>Journal of the European Union, 26.10.2012, C 326/47. <lb/>Regulation (EU) No 1092/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 No-<lb/>vember 2010 on European Union macro-prudential oversight of the financial sys-<lb/>tem and establishing a European Systemic Risk Board, 15.12.2010, Official Journal <lb/>of the European Union, L 331/1. <lb/>Regulation (EU) 2019/2176 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 18 Decem-<lb/>ber 2019 amending Regulation (EU) No 1092/2010 on European Union macro-pruden-<lb/>tial oversight of the financial system and establishing a European Systemic Risk Board, <lb/>27.12.2019, Official Journal of the European Union, L 334/146. <lb/>Regulation (EU) No 1094/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 No-<lb/>vember 2010 establishing a European Supervisory Authority (European Insurance <lb/>and Occupational Pensions Authority), amending Decision No 716/2009/EC and re-<lb/>pealing Commission Decision 2009/79/EC, Official Journal of the European Union, <lb/>15.12.2010, L 331/48. <lb/>Regulation (EU) No 1093/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 No-<lb/>vember 2010 establishing a European Supervisory Authority (European Banking Au-<lb/>thority), amending Decision No 716/2009/EC and repealing Commission Decision <lb/>2009/78/EC, Official Journal of the European Union, 15.12.2010, L 331/12. <lb/>Regulation (EU) No 1095/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 No-<lb/>vember 2010 establishing a European Supervisory Authority (European Securities and <lb/>Markets Authority), amending Decision No 716/2009/EC and repealing Commission <lb/>Decision 2009/77/EC, Official Journal of the European Union, 15.12.2010, L 331/84. <lb/>Recommendation of the European Systemic Risk Board of 22 December 2011 on the mac-<lb/>ro-prudential mandate of national authorities, 14.2.2012, Official Journal of the Euro-<lb/>pean Union, C 41/1. <lb/>Recommendation of the European Systemic Risk Board of 4 April 2013 on intermedi-<lb/>ate objectives and instruments of macro-prudential policy, 15.6.2013, Official Journal <lb/>of the European Union, C 170/1.</listBibl>


	</text>


  
  </TEI>