<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pdf-tei-editor.panya.de/api/files/872ab" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Legal status of Derived Text Formats – 2nd deliverable of Text+ AG Legal and Ethical Issues –</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Gianna</forename>
            <surname>Iacino</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Paweł</forename>
            <surname>Kamocki</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Keli</forename>
            <surname>Du</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Christof</forename>
            <surname>Schöch</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Andreas</forename>
            <surname>Witt</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Philippe</forename>
            <surname>Genêt</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>José Calvo</forename>
            <surname>Tello</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-09-17T20:01:29.244628Z">17.09.2025 20:01:29</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [article/dh-law-footnotes]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.5771$1$2699-1284-2024-3-149</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Nomos Verlag</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Gianna Iacino, Paweł Kamocki, Keli Du, Christof Schöch, Andreas Witt, Philippe Genêt, José Calvo Tello. (2024). Legal status of Derived Text Formats – 2nd deliverable of Text+ AG Legal and Ethical Issues –. RuZ - Recht und Zugang, 5(3), 149-172. DOI: 10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-09-17T20:01:29.244628Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">0707645</label>
          <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-09-17T20:01:29.244628Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Urheberrecht <lb/>Ass. iur. Gianna Iacino, LL.M., Dr. iur. Paweł Kamocki, Dr. phil. Keli Du, Prof. Dr. <lb/>Christof Schöch, Prof. Dr. Andreas Witt, Philippe Genêt and Dr. José Calvo Tello * <lb/>Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/>-2 nd deliverable of Text+ AG Legal and Ethical Issues -<lb/>This document was created in the context of the work of the association German <lb/>National Research Data Infrastructure (NFDI) e.V. NFDI is financed by the Federal <lb/>Republic of Germany and the 16 federal states, and the consortium Text+ is funded by <lb/>the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG, German Research Foundation) -project <lb/>number 460033370. The authors would like to thank for the funding and support. <lb/>Furthermore, thanks also include all institutions and actors who are committed to the <lb/>association and its goals. <lb/></front>
    
    <body>Introduction <lb/>A key aspect of many Digital Humanities projects is the use of texts as research <lb/>data. Text and Data Mining (TDM) is an umbrella term for a range of methods <lb/>I. <lb/></body>

	<front>* Ass. jur. Gianna Iacino, LL.M., specialised in media law and works at the law department of <lb/>the German National Library. <lb/>Dr. iur. Paweł Kamocki is a Legal Expert at the Leibniz-Institut für Deutsche Sprache, <lb/>Mannheim, co-chair of the Text+ Working Group on Legal and Ethical Issues, and chair of tauthe <lb/>CLARIN Legal and Ethical Issues Committee <lb/>Dr. phil. Keli Du is a PostDoc researcher in Computational Literary Studies at the Trier <lb/>Center for Digital Humanities, Trier University, Germany. <lb/>Prof. Dr. Christof Schöch is Professor of Digital Humanities and Co-Director of the Trier <lb/>Center for Digital Humanities at Trier University, Germany. <lb/>Prof. Dr. Andreas Witt is Professor of Computational Humanities and Text Technology at <lb/>the University of Mannheim, Head of the Department of Digital Linguistics at the Leibniz <lb/>Institute for the German Language in Mannheim, and Spokesperson of the Text+ consortium <lb/>within the German National Research Data Infrastructure (NFDI). <lb/>Philippe Genêt works at the German National Library and coordinates the Task Area <lb/>Collections in the consortium Text+ oft he German National Research Data Infrastructure <lb/>(NFDI). <lb/>Dr. José Calvo Tello works as a researcher and subject librarian at the Göttingen State and <lb/>University Library. <lb/>Recht und Zugang, Heft 3-2024 <lb/>DOI: 10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></front>
    
    <body>used to analyse texts for scientific research. According to the legal definition in the <lb/>Digital Single Market Directive (hereinafter: the DSM Directive), 1 TDM is &quot;any auto <lb/>mated analytical technique aimed at analysing text and data in digital form in order to <lb/>generate information which includes but is not limited to patterns, trends and correla <lb/>tions&quot;. 2 To conduct TDM, it is necessary to reproduce the source material, and in col <lb/>laborative research projects also to communicate it to the public. Such acts are copy <lb/>right-relevant if the source material is protected by copyright. In such cases, perform <lb/>ing TDM requires the authorisation of the rights holders unless a statutory exception <lb/>applies. With the DSM Directive, new copyright exceptions regarding TDM have been <lb/>introduced into the EU legal framework (see art. 3 and 4 DSM Directive). Still, TDM <lb/>encounters limitations concerning the storage, publication, and re-use of datasets <lb/>derived from copyrighted texts: According to the TDM exception for scientific <lb/>research, the source material may only be shared with a limited circle of persons for <lb/>joint scientific research or with third persons for quality evaluation purposes. It can <lb/>only be stored long-term if it was collected for research purposes by cultural heritage <lb/>institutions, research organisations or individual researchers belonging to a research <lb/>organisation. 3 Such limitations, however, run counter to the principles of open science <lb/>in research which, like in many other fields, play an important role in Digital Humani <lb/>ties and make it difficult to replicate or verify the results of existing studies, or to build <lb/>on earlier work when current, in-copyright materials are concerned. <lb/>This paper will focus on Derived Text Formats (DTFs) as a possible way to avoid <lb/>such limitations by using statutory exceptions to transform the source material into <lb/>formats which no longer contain copyrighted content. It will discuss the legal require <lb/>ments to create DTFs from copyright-protected material, as well as the legal criteria to <lb/>determine the applicability (or not) of copyright to DTFs according to German law. <lb/>Copyright law is heavily influenced by EU directives, so these will play a significant <lb/>role throughout this analysis. <lb/>B. What are derived text formats (DTFs) <lb/>DTFs have been described as extracted features for non-consumptive research. 4 They <lb/>are systematically generated representations of a base text, which allow the application <lb/>II. <lb/></body>

    <listBibl>1 Directive (EU) 2019/790 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 17 April 2019 on <lb/>copyright and related rights in the Digital Single Market and amending Directives 96/9/EC <lb/>and 2001/29/EC, DSM Directive, https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/? <lb/>uri=CELEX:32019L0790. <lb/>2 See art. 2.2 DSM Directive. <lb/>3 For a comprehensive analysis of the TDM exceptions in the DSM Directive, their transpo <lb/>sition into German law and the limitations concerning storage, publication and re-use of <lb/>datasets, see: G. Iacino, P. Kamocki, P. Leinen, Assessment of the Impact of the DSM-Direc <lb/>tive on Text+, https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.12759959. <lb/>4 See e.g., Y. Lin, J.-B. Michel, E. Aiden Lieberman, J. Orwant, W. Brockman, S. Petrov, <lb/>Syntactic Annotations for the Google Books NGram Corpus, in: Proceedings of the ACL <lb/>2012 System Demonstrations, Association for Computational Linguistics, Jeju Island, Korea, <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>150 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
    
    <body>of specific TDM methods. They can be produced in such a way that, on the one <lb/>hand, the resulting representation still allows for the application of at least one research <lb/>method, while, on the other hand, the representation is no longer protected by copy <lb/>right. <lb/>The basic idea behind DTFs is to selectively remove specific pieces of informa <lb/>tion, particularly copyright-relevant features, from in-copyright texts to transform <lb/>copyright-protected material into DTFs which no longer contain copyright-relevant <lb/>features and therefore, are no longer affected by copyright restrictions. Additionally, if <lb/>the material cannot be &apos;humanly&apos; read and understood in order to intellectually assimi <lb/>late its content (Baudry, 2023), 5 making it available to the public is less likely to affect <lb/>the interests of copyright holders. At the same time, such materials are still suitable <lb/>for a variety of TDM tasks in the Digital Humanities, such as simple quantification <lb/>of words and other linguistics features, stylometry and authorship attribution, topic <lb/>modelling, or the training of machine learning models. <lb/>There are many ways to create DTFs from source texts, but they can be roughly <lb/>divided into three groups 6 listed below, with examples for reference. <lb/>1) Statistical DTFs: The first method is to extract textual features from texts (e.g. <lb/>tokens, lemmata, n-grams, sentences, lines, paragraphs or pages) and their corre <lb/>sponding statistical information, such as length, absolute/relative frequency or <lb/>sequence. Such extracted, descriptive information can then be published for text <lb/>analysis tasks. Examples of such DTFs are the &quot;Hathi Trust Extracted Features&quot; <lb/>(see e.g., Jett et al. 2020, Organisciak et al. 2017, Parulian et al. 2022) and the <lb/>&quot;Google Books Ngram Datasets&quot; (see e.g., Michel et al. 2011, El-Ebshihy et al. <lb/>2018, Richey &amp; Taylor 2020). <lb/>2) Transformative DTFs: The second method and the idea is to artificially add some <lb/>&quot;noise&quot; to the original text, which reduces its readability (Schöch et al. 2020). <lb/>More precisely, different kinds of transformation are being applied to the source <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>2012, pp. 169-174, https://aclanthology.org/P12-3029; S. Bhattacharyya, P. Organisciak, J. S. <lb/>Downie, A Fragmentizing Interface to a Large Corpus of Digitized Text: (Post)humanism and <lb/>Non-consumptive Reading via Features, Interdisciplinary Science Reviews 40 (2015) 61-77, <lb/>http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/; J. Jett, B. Capitanu, D. Kudeki, T. Cole, Y. Hu, P. Organis <lb/>ciak, T. Underwood, E. Dickson Koehl, R. Dubnicek, J. S. Downie, The HathiTrust Research <lb/>Center Extracted Features Dataset (2.0), 2020, https://wiki.htrc.illinois.edu/pages/viewpage <lb/>.action?pageId= 79069329, doi:10.13012/R2TE-C227; C. Schöch, F. Döhl, A. Rettinger, E. <lb/>Gius, P. Trilcke, P. Leinen, F. Jannidis, M. Hinzmann, J. Röpke, Abgeleitete Textformate: Text <lb/>und Data Mining mit urheberrechtlich geschützten Textbeständen (2020), http://zfdg.de/202 <lb/>0_006. doi:10.17175/2020_006; P. Organisciak, J. S. Downie, Research access to in-copyright <lb/>texts in the humanities, in: Information and Knowledge Organisation in Digital Humanities, <lb/>Routledge, 2021, pp. 157-177. <lb/>5 J. Baudry (2023), Non-consumptive research use, an analysis of the legal situation, on <lb/>Couperin.org, https://www.couperin.org/le-consortium/actus/non-consumptive-research-us <lb/>e/. <lb/>6 Some authors distinguish between &quot;token-based&quot; and &quot;vector-based&quot; DTF, see Schöch et al. <lb/>2020, F. Barth, J. Calvo Tello, K. Du, P. Genêt, L. Keller, J. Knappen, Liste der Abgeleiteten <lb/>Textformate (working title), forthcoming, 2025. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <page>151 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <page>151 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>texts (e.g. removing the sequence information by randomizing the order of the <lb/>words and/or randomly replacing a certain proportion of words in texts with <lb/>their corresponding part-of-speech tags or with a placeholder token) and the trans <lb/>formed texts can then be published in different formats (plain text, JSON, XML, <lb/>tabular formats) as research data. 7 One recent example of this can be found in <lb/>the TextGrid-Repository, with TEI files containing metadata, structure and lexical <lb/>information but with the tokens in randomized order (Calvo Tello et al. 2025). 8 <lb/>3) Language model-based DTFs: The third method is to train a language model using <lb/>the copyrighted texts and publish the model (e.g. topic model, static / contextual <lb/>ized word embedding model, or large language model). In this way, the informa <lb/>tion contained in texts (including for example the frequency and the context of <lb/>words) is mapped to and represented in an algebraic vector space instead of the <lb/>usual symbolic character system. Information in this format could be used for e.g <lb/>context-dependent semantic analysis of individual words or fine-tuning of the large <lb/>language models for specific analysis procedures 9 . <lb/>It should be noted that DTFs are usually published along with information about <lb/>the texts, such as data about the structure of the text (if it contains paratexts, verses, <lb/>images, etc.) and metadata of various kinds, such as details of the composition of the <lb/>files, title and other descriptive information about the work(s) it contains, the author <lb/>and other agents (such as publishers, translators) involved in the process, etc. This is <lb/>the case for Statistical and Transformative DTFs and most of the examples mentioned <lb/>above and in Schöch et al. (2020). Even in cases with poorer metadata, such as Google <lb/>N-grams, some metadata is needed to be able to use them for analysis. As Burnard <lb/>points out, &quot;without metadata, the investigator has nothing but disconnected words of <lb/>unknowable provenance or authenticity&quot; (2004). This is an important feature of textual <lb/>data, and could have important implications for the criteria for copyright status of <lb/>DTFs. <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>7 Note that for a number of kinds of statistical DTFs, a conversion into transformative DTFs <lb/>with identical information content is possible, and vice versa, so that these two types are not <lb/>necessarily fundamentally different. <lb/>8 https://textgridrep.org/search?query=&amp;order=relevance&amp;limit=20&amp;mode=list&amp;filter=format <lb/>:application%2Fxml%3Bderived%3Dtrue&amp;filter=project.id%3ATGPR-8b44ca41-6fa1-9b49-<lb/>67b7-6374d97e29eb. <lb/>9 See e.g. C. Schöch, F. Döhl, A. Rettinger, E. Gius, P. Trilcke, P. Leinen, F. Jannidis, M. <lb/>Hinzmann, J. Röpke, Abgeleitete Textformate: Text und Data Mining mit urheberrechtlich <lb/>geschützten Textbeständen (2020), http://zfdg.de/2020_006,. doi:10.17175/2020_006; Hessel, <lb/>J., &amp; Schofield, A. (2021, August). How effective is BERT without word ordering? implica <lb/>tions for language understanding and data privacy. In Proceedings of the 59th Annual Meeting <lb/>of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the 11th International Joint Conference <lb/>on Natural Language Processing (Volume 2: Short Papers) (pp. 204-211); Keli Du &amp; Christof <lb/>Schöch: &quot;Shifting Sentiments? What happens to BERT-based Sentiment Classification when <lb/>derived text formats are used for fine-tuning&quot; (long presentation). In: Karajgikar, J., Janco, A., <lb/>&amp; Otis, J. (2024). DH2024 Book of Abstracts. Zenodo, https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13761 <lb/>079. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <page>152 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>The way in which DTF&apos;s metadata is published is closely related to the format cho <lb/>sen. For plain text files, metadata is often stored separately in a tabular format or in the <lb/>name file in a precarious way. Other formats, such as JSON or XML-TEI, allow meta <lb/>data to be encoded in a structured way, facilitating better compliance with the FAIR <lb/>principles (Wilkinson et al. 2016). <lb/>Copyright implications of creating DTFs <lb/>This section will discuss in which cases creating DTFs from copyright-protected <lb/>source material qualifies as a copyright-relevant act and therefore can only be carried <lb/>out with authorisation of the rights holders or under a statutory exception. <lb/>Copyright protection of the source material <lb/>This deliverable concerns only the creation of DTFs from copyright-protected source <lb/>material. The reader should be aware, however, that while a great majority of texts <lb/>(novels, poems, song lyrics, news, blog posts, letters, diary entries…) meet the original <lb/>ity threshold required for copyright protection, some texts are copyright-free (i.e., in <lb/>the public domain). This is the case if: <lb/> § Copyright has reached its term, which generally happens 70 years after the death of <lb/>the author 10 OR <lb/> § The text is expressly excluded from copyright by a statutory provision; under <lb/>German law, this is the case of &quot;official works&quot;; 11 <lb/> § The text fails to meet the originality threshold, e.g. because it&apos;s too short for <lb/>the originality (German: persönliche geistige Schöpfung) to manifest itself 12 (some <lb/>tweets, slogans), or because it&apos;s very commonplace (e.g., consists of expressions <lb/>commonly used in the given context 13 , such as &quot;I wish you a merry Christmas <lb/>and a happy new year&quot;), or because the author had to follow some strict formal <lb/>constraints (this could be the case of some product descriptions or user manuals). <lb/>Public domain texts can be freely copied and shared, so there is limited practical <lb/>interest in deriving DTFs from them (at least in the context of copyright concerns); but <lb/>since they can also be freely modified, deriving and sharing DTFs from such texts is <lb/>not in any way restricted by copyright law. <lb/>III. <lb/>1. <lb/></body>

    <listBibl>10 See § 64 Urheberrechtsgesetz (UrhG) for the German legal framework, https://www.gesetze <lb/>-im-internet.de/englisch_urhg/. <lb/>11 See § 5 UrhG. <lb/>12 The Court of Justice of the European Union ruled that texts as short as 11 consecutive words <lb/>can be protected by copyright; however, very short texts (around 4 words and shorter) are <lb/>generally regarded as too short to be protected by copyright, see CJEU, judgement of 16 <lb/>July 2009, Infopaq, Case C-5/08, ECLI:EU:C:2009:465, https://curia.europa.eu/juris/docum <lb/>ent/document.jsf?docid=72482&amp;doclang=EN. <lb/>13 See e.g. LG München I, Urteil vom 12.12.2017, 33 O 15792/16, https://openjur.de/u/970910. <lb/>html. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <page>153 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <page>153 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>Copyright-relevance of creating DTFs <lb/>Two scenarios need to be distinguished. On the one hand, if the outcome of the <lb/>creation process, the DTF itself, still contains copyright protected-source material, <lb/>the creation of the DTF necessarily entailed reproductions of the source material, <lb/>independently from how it was created. On the other hand, if the DTF no longer <lb/>contains copyright-protected source material, the creation process might either not <lb/>have entailed any acts of reproduction or might have required (technically necessary) <lb/>acts of reproduction. Therefore, It is necessary to take a closer look at the creation <lb/>process itself before analysing whether the result of the process, the DTF itself, is still <lb/>protected by copyright. As it will be demonstrated, a distinction can be made between <lb/>manually and automatically creating DTFs. <lb/>Manually deriving DTFs <lb/>Theoretically, one could derive DTFs, especially Statistical DTFs, entirely manually, <lb/>e.g. by manually counting words, characters, etc., and then presenting the results in a <lb/>chart or a diagram. Although certainly time-consuming and inefficient in the digital <lb/>age, manual derivation of Statistical DTFs possibly can be a copyright-irrelevant act, <lb/>if the source text is not reproduced (copied) in the process, and only pure copyright-<lb/>free information is extracted from the text (e.g., there are 3 occurrences of the word <lb/>&quot;kerfuffle&quot; in the text, the text consists of 772 sentences, the most common sentence <lb/>length is 5 words, etc.). However, this is of course a time-consuming and error-prone <lb/>process that does not scale well to larger amounts of text; it is therefore of very limited <lb/>practical relevance. <lb/>Automatically deriving DTFs <lb/>Needless to say, the most convenient and feasible way to derive DTFs is by automated <lb/>means. However, a piece of software used to derive DTFs necessarily copies (large) <lb/>passages of source texts, even if only copyright-free information is extracted from the <lb/>text. It is interesting to realise that an action that would &quot;normally&quot; be free from <lb/>constraints may fall within the ambit of an exclusive right just because it is performed <lb/>with the aid of information technology. <lb/>Copies that are only temporarily stored in the RAM are also copyright-relevant. <lb/>The wording of Article 2 of the InfoSoc Directive 14 and of § 16(1) UrhG, defining <lb/>the exclusive right of reproduction, leaves no doubts as to the fact that all acts of <lb/>reproduction, even technically necessary acts of temporary reproductions, are copy <lb/>right-relevant: <lb/>2. <lb/>a) <lb/>b) <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>14 Directive 2001/29/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 May 2001 on the <lb/>harmonisation of certain aspects of copyright and related rights in the information society, <lb/>InfoSoc Directive, https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/dir/2001/29/oj. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <page>154 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>

      <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>

			<body>Article 2 InfoSoc Directive: <lb/>Member States shall provide for the exclusive right to authorise or prohibit direct or indirect, tempo <lb/>rary or permanent reproduction by any means and in any form, in whole or in part: (a) for authors, of <lb/>their works (...). <lb/> § 16(1) UrhG: <lb/>ʻRight of reproductionʼ means the right to produce copies of the work, whether on a temporary or on <lb/>a permanent basis and regardless of by which means of procedure or in which quantity they are made. <lb/>Creating DTFs under statutory exceptions <lb/>The reproductions necessary to derive a DTF can therefore only be lawfully made <lb/>with the permission from the right holders, unless they are covered by a statutory <lb/>exception. Of course, asking for the rightholder&apos;s permission to derive a DTF is not <lb/>a reasonable option, primarily for pragmatic reasons (e.g., multiple and/or unknown <lb/>copyright holders). The very point of deriving a DTF in the first place is to be able to <lb/>share meaningful information about the text without limitations and without having to <lb/>ask for permission. It is therefore necessary to rely on an existing statutory exception. <lb/>Copyright law knows several statutory exceptions which might be applicable for the <lb/>purpose of creating a DTF, due to the fact that they allow reproductions of entire <lb/>works. In the context of this deliverable, two of these exceptions deserve a closer look: <lb/> § 60d UrhG which allows reproductions necessary for TDM for scientific purposes <lb/>and § 44a UrhG which allows temporary acts of reproduction. Other statutory excep <lb/>tions, such as § 51 UrhG (citation) or § 53 UrhG (private copy) are too narrow in <lb/>scope. Even § 60c UrhG which is the specific statutory exception for scientific <lb/>research, generally only allows reproductions of 15 % of a work, with entire reproduc <lb/>tions being allowed only in very limited cases (for so-called &quot;small-scale works&quot; or <lb/>out-of-commerce works). <lb/>When interpreting statutory exceptions, the so-called three-step test must be con <lb/>sidered, before turning to a more detailed examination of the potentially relevant <lb/>statutory exceptions for creating DTFs. <lb/>Three-step-test <lb/>According to Article 9(2) of the Berne Convention, signatory countries can adopt <lb/>exceptions to the reproduction right in their national laws, provided that these excep <lb/>tions are limited to &quot;certain special cases&quot;, and that the allowed uses &quot;[do] not conflict <lb/>with a normal exploitation of the work and [do] not unreasonably prejudice the legiti <lb/>mate interests of the author[s]&quot;. This provision, called the &quot;three-step test&quot;, was first <lb/>introduced during the 1967 revision of the Convention. Today, it can also be found in <lb/>Article 13 of the TRIPS Agreement, Article 10 of the WIPO Copyright Treaty, and in <lb/>Article 5(5) of the InfoSoc Directive. <lb/>3. <lb/>a) <lb/></body>
      
      
      <page>155 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <page>155 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>The three-step test is the first &quot;bottleneck&quot; that every copyright exception must go <lb/>through before it can be enacted in national law. <lb/>The first step of the test, i.e. limitation &quot;to certain special cases&quot; signifies that <lb/>the exceptions must be clearly defined (&quot;certain&quot;) and limited in scope and reach <lb/>(&quot;special&quot;). For example, an exception allowing for all works to be used without <lb/>permission from the rightholder for &quot;personal development&quot; purposes would fail this <lb/>test, as it is not clearly defined (what exactly is &quot;personal development&quot;? Does it cover <lb/>only spiritual, or also material enrichment? Whose &quot;personal development&quot; -only <lb/>the user&apos;s or also his or her public&apos;s?, etc.) and above all it is too broad in scope <lb/>(not &quot;limited&quot;); in fact, it could strip copyright of any practical significance. This also <lb/>means that exceptions need to be periodically reviewed and adapted to the changing <lb/>reality. <lb/>The second step of the test requires that copyright exceptions &quot;do not conflict with <lb/>a normal exploitation of the work&quot;. This chiefly means that the exceptions should not <lb/>allow users to enter into economic competition with the rightholder. All uses that have <lb/>economic importance, or are likely to acquire such importance, should in principle be <lb/>reserved to the rightholders. <lb/>Thirdly, the exceptions should not &quot;unreasonably prejudice the legitimate interests <lb/>of the right holder&quot;. The ambiguity of the term &quot;legitimate&quot; makes this step particu <lb/>larly hard to evaluate, as it can mean both &quot;lawful&quot; (i.e., grounded in the law), and, <lb/>more broadly, &quot;valid&quot; (as in: justifiable, reasonable). It seems that the narrower view, <lb/>limited to protecting interests enshrined in the law, is more appropriate. Copyright <lb/>exceptions should not &quot;unreasonably prejudice&quot; such legitimate interest. According to <lb/>the WTO Panel, this precludes exceptions that cause or may cause &quot;unreasonable loss <lb/>of income&quot; to the rightholder 15 . However, a contrario, a certain degree of prejudice <lb/>(&quot;reasonable prejudice&quot;, related to a &quot;reasonable loss of income&quot;) remains acceptable. <lb/>This is why some exceptions (such as the private copy exception) are accompanied by <lb/>a compensation scheme (such as a special levy (tax) on purchases of recordable media) <lb/>that is supposed to bring the prejudice suffered by rightholders back to an acceptable <lb/>level. <lb/>As demonstrated, the three-step test offers considerable freedom of interpretation <lb/>and &quot;sufficient breathing space for social, cultural and economic needs&quot; (Senftleben, <lb/>2010) 16 . However, the views on the practical significance of the three-step test differ. <lb/>In particular, the way in which the test is incorporated in the InfoSoc Directive <lb/>indicates that its role, according to the European legislator, is to &quot;narrow down&quot; <lb/>the scope of statutory exceptions: Article 5 in its (1), (2) and (3) offers a list of <lb/>rather narrowly defined uses that should (Article 5(1)) or may (Article 5(2) and (3)) <lb/>be covered by statutory exceptions in national laws of the Member States. This list <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>15 WTO, Report of the Panel, WT/DS160/R, 15 June 2000, para 6.229. <lb/>16 M. Senftleben, The International Three-Step Test: A Model Provision for EC Fair Use <lb/>Legislation, 1 (2010) JIPITEC 67, para. 1, https://www.jipitec.eu/archive/issues/jipitec-1-2-2 <lb/>010/2605/JIPITEC%202%20-%20Senftleben-Three%20Step%20Test.pdf. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <page>156 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>includes, for example, quotations, uses in research and teaching, as well as the private <lb/>copy exception (see below). Then, the same article 5 (in its (5)) provides that all the <lb/>above exceptions (whether affecting only the reproduction right, or also the right of <lb/>communication to the public) should in addition be subject to the three-step test. As <lb/>a result, exceptions stemming from the InfoSoc Directive tend to be defined in a very <lb/>narrow way, which severely limits their practical significance, especially for research <lb/>activities. <lb/>National laws also seem to attribute different roles to the three-step test. The Ger <lb/>man Copyright Act does not mention the three-step test, which indicates that it is a <lb/>&quot;high level&quot; requirement stemming from international law and addressed primarily to <lb/>the national legislator, and not to those who apply the law. Simply put, if an exception <lb/>makes its way into the German Copyright Act, this means that the legislator assumes <lb/>it has passed the three-step test and the role of the test is limited to serving as an aid in <lb/>the interpretation of German copyright regulations (unless, of course, an international <lb/>body such as the WTO Panel decides otherwise and forces the national legislator to <lb/>reform the law). <lb/>Some legal scholars advocate that the three-step test should be elevated to the rank <lb/>of an &quot;open norm&quot; in the EU, similar to the American fair use doctrine 17 . In this <lb/>approach, every use that passes the three-step test should be allowed, and the existing <lb/>exceptions should only serve as examples of &quot;specific cases&quot;. Although this approach <lb/>is tempting and may seem justified, this deliverable is not a place for a debate on law <lb/>reform. <lb/>Exception for TDM for Scientifc research purposes ( § 60 d UrhG) <lb/>Although first introduced into German law in 2018, § 60d UrhG, containing the <lb/>exception for Text and Data Mining (TDM) for scientific research purposes, owes its <lb/>current wording to Article 3 of the 2019 DSM Directive. It can be summarised as fol <lb/>lows: <lb/>b) <lb/></body>

      <listBibl>17 See esp. M. Senftleben, The International Three-Step Test: A Model Provision for EC Fair <lb/>Use Legislation, 1 (2010) Journal of Intellectual Property, Information Technology and <lb/>E-Commerce Law, Vol. 1, No. 2, pp. 67-82; see also Gervais, Daniel J., Towards a New Core <lb/>International Copyright Norm: The Reverse Three-Step Test, SRRN, https://ssrn.com/abstr <lb/>act=499924. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <page>157 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <page>157 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>§ Research organisations, cultural heritage institutions and citizien scientists 18 <lb/>-are allowed to make copies of content <lb/>-that they have lawful access to <lb/>-in order to carry out TDM <lb/>-for scientific research purposes. <lb/>The question of whether the creation of DTFs is covered by the TDM exception will <lb/>be addressed below. An analysis of § 60d beyond this question will not be conducted at <lb/>this point. 19 <lb/>TDM in German copyright law is defined in § 44b UrhG very broadly as an &quot;auto <lb/>mated analysis of individual or several digital or digitised works for the purpose of <lb/>gathering information, in particular regarding patterns, trends and correlations&quot; ( § 44b, <lb/>very close, but not identical to the definition in art. 2 of the DSM Directive). <lb/>The process of creating a DTF entails an automated analysis of the source material <lb/>in order to generate a representation of a base text. This representation contains infor <lb/>mation about the source text. For example, a Statistical DTF can be seen as gathering <lb/>information about patterns of occurrence (e.g., the frequency of use of certain words <lb/>or expressions), and language-model based DTFs can be seen as representing morpho <lb/>logical and semantic information about tokens that are based on patterns of co-occur <lb/>rence and stored as dense numerical vectors. In fact, producing a DTF is very similar in <lb/>nature to applying methods like topic modelling or stylometry, with the exception that <lb/>the process is not continued as it normally would, i.e. by summarizing the transformed <lb/>data, by visualizing a selection of the data, and by drawing conclusions from it. Rather, <lb/>it stops at an earlier phase. This should not be an obstacle to seeing the creation of <lb/>DTFs as compatible with the legal definition of TDM and the DTF itself as a result of <lb/>a TDM process. <lb/>Creating DTFs can be a goal of a TDM process. For example, finding any keyness <lb/>analysis supposes, in a first step, to collect the frequency and/or dispersion informa <lb/>tion about all the different words found in a corpus, which is essentially information <lb/>about how the frequency of a given word evolved over time may require creation <lb/>of Statistical DTFs. Certain research questions may also entail creation of Transforma <lb/>tional DTFs, for example: <lb/>1. In order to compare the semantic similarity of words in texts, a static word embed <lb/>ding model can be trained and then applied for the comparison. <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>18 The beneficiaries mentioned in the DSM directive are limited to research organisations <lb/>(including universities and public research institutes) and cultural heritage institutions <lb/>(libraries, museums, archives…). Going beyond the wording of the DSM Directive, the Ger <lb/>man transposition adds to the list &quot;citizen scientists&quot;, i.e. researchers without academic affili <lb/>ation, as long as they are acting for non-commercial purposes. This addition was possible <lb/>due to a creative fusion of Art. 3 of the DSM Directive with the &quot;general&quot; exception for non-<lb/>commercial scientific research in Art. 5(3)(a) DSM DIrective. <lb/>19 For a more detailed analysis of § 60 d UrhG, G. Iacino, P. Kamocki, P. Leinen, Assessment of <lb/>the Impact of the DSM-Directive on Text+. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <page>158 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>2. In order to explore the hidden thematic structure of a corpus, a topic model can be <lb/>trained and the text data is transformed to two probability distributions: a topics-<lb/>in-documents distribution and a words-in-topics distribution, which can be used to <lb/>analyse the occurrence of semantic/thematic word clusters in text collections. <lb/>But, deriving DTFs can also be a means, rather than a goal, of a TDM process. In <lb/>this scenario, the information incorporated in the derived text format is not the goal <lb/>of the scientific research. Rather, the derived text format serves as a means to an end: <lb/>it shall now be used as a copyright-free corpus for a subsequent TDM analysis. It <lb/>is therefore only an interim step in a larger process. This interim step of the TDM <lb/>process already serves scientific research purposes: Scientific research generally refers <lb/>to the methodical and systematic pursuit of new knowledge. 20 By already deeming <lb/>the &quot;pursuit&quot; of new knowledge sufficient, not only the steps directly related to the <lb/>acquisition of knowledge are included, rather, it is sufficient that the step in question <lb/>is aimed at a (later) gain in knowledge. The creation of a dataset can be considered <lb/>scientific research in this aforementioned sense. While the creation of a dataset itself <lb/>may not yet be associated with knowledge gain, it is a fundamental step aimed at using <lb/>the dataset for future insights. 21 The TDM regulations do not explicitly provide for a <lb/>multi-step TDM process, but it is nevertheless covered by the wording as well as the <lb/>intent and purpose of the regulation. <lb/>Whether a goal in itself or merely a means towards another goal, all reproductions <lb/>necessary to create DTFs are exempted under the TDM exception ( § 60 d UrhG). <lb/>Importantly, German law also expressly allows modifications of the source material <lb/>when it&apos;s technically necessary to carry out TDM. Necessary changes of format or <lb/>encoding of the source material for building DTFs are therefore expressly allowed <lb/>( § 23 (3) UrhG). <lb/>Possible alternative: Temporary acts of reproduction ( § 44 a UrhG) <lb/>Technically necessary acts of reproduction, such as those made in the process of auto <lb/>matically creating DTF, might be covered by § 44a UrhG. 22 <lb/>According to the CJEU 23 , an act of reproduction can be covered by the exception <lb/>for temporary acts of reproduction (Art. 5.1 of the InfoSoc Directive, § 44a UrhG) if it <lb/>meets 5 cumulative conditions: <lb/>c) <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>20 BeckOK UrhR/Grübler, 42. Ed. 1.5.2024, UrhG § 60c Rn. 5; Dreier/Schulze/Dreier, 7. Aufl. <lb/>2022, UrhG § 60c Rn. 1. <lb/>21 LG Hamburg, Urteil vom 27.9.2024, Az.: 310 O 227/23, Rz. 113, https://openjur.de/u/24956 <lb/>51.html. <lb/>22 See Recital 9 DSM Directive. <lb/>23 CJEU, judgement of 26 April 2017, Stichting Brein, Case C-527/15, ECLI:EU:C:2017:300: <lb/>https://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;docid=190142&amp;pageIndex=0&amp; <lb/>doclang=EN&amp;mode=lst&amp;dir=&amp;occ=first&amp;part=1&amp;cid=8019316. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <page>159 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <page>159 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>(1) the copy is temporary (i.e., not intended to last), <lb/>(2) it is transient or incidental (i.e., its lifetime is limited to what is necessary, and the <lb/>copy is then deleted automatically without human intervention 24 ), <lb/>(3) it is an integral and technical part of a technological process (the reproductions <lb/>have to happen within and not outside the process; the process can be manually <lb/>activated 25 ), <lb/>(4) the sole purpose of that process is to enable a transmission in a network between <lb/>third parties by an intermediary or a lawful use of a work or subject matter (i.e., a <lb/>use that was authorised by the rightholder or is not restricted by copyright law 26 ), <lb/>and <lb/>(5) that act does not have any independent economic significance (i.e. the copies do <lb/>not enable the generation of an additional profit going beyond that derived from <lb/>the lawful use of the protected work and do not lead to a modification of that <lb/>work 27 ). <lb/>Classically, this exception is invoked mostly in the context of web browsing (to <lb/>exempt the cache copies made in the process from the obligation to obtain authorisa <lb/>tion). <lb/>The first four requirements are unquestionably met in the creation of derived text <lb/>formats. The necessary acts of reproduction are a technical and integral part of the <lb/>automated process of creating a DTF. They will be automatically deleted at the end of <lb/>the creation process. If the DTF itself no longer contains copyright-protected content, <lb/>then the reproductions made while creating the DTF do not manifest in the DTF and <lb/>these reproductions are therefore, temporary and incidental. <lb/>Since a use should be considered lawful where it is authorised by the rightholder or <lb/>not restricted by law, the key question it boils down to is: is creating DTFs restricted <lb/>by copyright law? As already discussed above, creating a DTF is allowed under the <lb/>TDM exception and therefore, not restricted by copyright law. <lb/>It seems particularly unclear whether copies made in the process of deriving DTFs <lb/>meet the 5th condition, the &quot;lack of independent economic significance&quot; -a DTF <lb/>may indeed have such significance (cf. above about the second step of the three-step <lb/>test). While in the academic context there is no intent to enable additional profit for <lb/>researchers, rightholders might argue that the creation of DTFs disables additional <lb/>profit on their side. <lb/>Some rights holders (in particular in news and scientific domains) are likely to <lb/>argue that DTFs may indeed harm their business models, inasmuch as these involve <lb/>selling data for Large Language Models training (cf. e.g., Le Monde&apos;s partnership with <lb/>Open AI), or providing dedicated TDM platforms (cf. Elsevier&apos;s). Potentially, this <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>24 CJEU, Infopaq, para 64. <lb/>25 CJEU, order of 17 January 2012, Infopaq II, Case C-302/10, ECLI:EU:C:2012,16,para <lb/>39, https://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;docid=118441&amp;pageIndex= <lb/>0&amp;doclang=EN&amp;mode=lst&amp;dir=&amp;occ=first&amp;part=1&amp;cid=8021836. <lb/>26 Recital 33 of the InfoSoc Directive; CJEU, Infopaq II, para 42. <lb/>27 CJEU, Infopaq II, para 54. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <page>160 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>may indeed be an obstacle to making DTFs under the exception for temporary acts <lb/>of reproduction, or even fail to pass the three-step test (which would prevent it also <lb/>under other exceptions). This risk seems much less present in case of literary works <lb/>that are clearly intended for close reading (e.g. novels, short stories etc.) and where <lb/>mining presents limited commercial advantages, compared to scholarly literature (e.g. <lb/>in medicine) where mining may yield commercial benefits. <lb/>It seems that even though the use of § 44a UrhG to enable the creation of DTFs cannot be completely <lb/>excluded, it is not necessary to rely on it. The requirements of § 44a UrhG regarding the creation of a <lb/>DTF are only fulfilled when and if the requirements of a TDM exception ( § 60d UrhG or § 44b <lb/>UrhG) are fulfilled as well. Therefore, relying on § 44a UrhG for creating DTFs is redundant. Indeed, <lb/>the TDM exceptions (see above) provide a much more convenient and secure basis for this activity. <lb/>DTF and the integrity right <lb/>Although rarely discussed in the context of new technologies, moral rights of authors <lb/>should not be absent from the discussion on DTFs. The so-called integrity right is <lb/>recognised by Article 6bis of the Berne Convention. In Germany, it can be found in <lb/> § 14 UrhG. The texts read as follows: <lb/>Article 6bis(1) of the Berne Convention: <lb/>(1) Independently of the author&apos;s economic rights, and even after the transfer of the said rights, the <lb/>author shall have the right to (...) object to any distortion, mutilation or other modification of, or <lb/>other derogatory action in relation to, the said work, which would be prejudicial to his honor or <lb/>reputation. <lb/> § 14 UrhG: <lb/>The author has the right to prohibit the distortion or any other derogatory treatment of his or her <lb/>work which is capable of prejudicing the author&apos;s legitimate intellectual or personal interests in the <lb/>work. <lb/>It seems possible that some DTFs, in particular Transformative DTFs with shuffled <lb/>sentences or added noise, can be perceived by the author (or his or her heirs) as <lb/>prejudicing his or her legitimate interest, or even to his or her honor or reputation. <lb/>This could be the case e.g. when sentences or paragraphs are shuffled, which distorts <lb/>the message of the work, or when added noise deteriorates the artistic quality of the <lb/>work. Theoretically, the recipient of such Transformative DTFs could then have a false <lb/>impression about the opinions of the author or his or her writing skills. <lb/>On the other hand, Transformative DTF are not intended for close reading, and <lb/>therefore are not to be read and understood by humans. It can therefore be argued that <lb/>such DTFs are not meant to give any impression about the opinions or writing skills of <lb/>authors of source texts. <lb/>Nonetheless, transformative DTFs might carry a non-negligeable risk of infringing <lb/>the integrity right. <lb/>4. <lb/></body>
        
      <page>161 <lb/></page>
      
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <page>161 <lb/></page>
        
      <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
      
      <body>Copyright status of DTFs <lb/>The question that arises here is whether a DTF still contains copyright-protected <lb/>content from the source material. In this case, the material continues to be protected in <lb/>favor of the original author and can only be used within the limitations of copyright <lb/>law. However, the goal is to create a DTF which no longer entails copyright protected <lb/>content and can therefore, be used freely without any constraints of copyright law. <lb/>Therefore, this section will address the question of the criteria by which a text can <lb/>be assessed as (still) being protected by copyright. Additionally, this section will deter <lb/>mine whether the DTF itself meets the originality threshold and might therefore be <lb/>protected by copyright in favor of the creator of the DTF. <lb/>DTFs as (partial) reproductions of source texts? <lb/>The very broad definition of the right of reproduction in Article 2 of the InfoSoc <lb/>Directive (see above) can easily be reduced ad absurdum. Interpreted strictly, partial <lb/>reproduction would include a situation in which only the smallest meaningful part of <lb/>a work (in case of literary works: one word of text) is copied. This, however, would <lb/>mean that individual words are protected by copyright, which would not only be <lb/>unworkable in practice, but also devastating for freedom of (artistic) expression. In <lb/>order to avoid this, the CJEU was confronted with the task of defining the limits of <lb/>partial reproduction. <lb/>In the 2009 Infopaq case, the CJEU ruled that parts of works should receive protec <lb/>tion under the reproduction right (Article 2(a) of the InfoSoc Directive) as long as <lb/>they &quot;contain elements which are the expression of the intellectual creation of the <lb/>author of the work&quot;. 28 In other words, under EU law, extraction of a snippet from a <lb/>copyright-protected text is a copyright-relevant act (reproduction in part) only if the <lb/>snippet meets the originality threshold (see section 1) below). <lb/>In the same case, the Court also ruled that in certain contexts, the use of unoriginal <lb/>snippets of a literary work may still amount to an act of reproduction when &quot;the <lb/>cumulative effect of those extracts may lead to the reconstitution of lengthy fragments <lb/>which are liable to reflect the originality of the work in question&quot; 29 . This condition can <lb/>be referred to as &quot;reconstructability&quot; -section 2) below) <lb/>More recently, in the Pelham case, the CJEU ruled that the use of a very short <lb/>sample from a phonogram (in the facts of the case: an approximately 2-second rhythm <lb/>sequence) in another phonogram is an act of reproduction, &quot;unless that sample is <lb/>included in the phonogram in a modified form unrecognizable to the ear&quot; 30 . Although <lb/>it is not clear whether and how this &quot;recognisability&quot; condition applies to literary <lb/>works (texts), it is presented and discussed in section 3) below. <lb/>IV. <lb/>1. <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>28 CJEU, Infopaq, para 39. <lb/>29 CJEU, Infopaq, para 50. <lb/>30 CJEU, Pelham, 29 July 2019, para 39. <lb/></listBibl>
        
        <page>162 <lb/></page>
          
        
        <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
          
      <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
        
      <body>DTFs as potentially containing &quot;partial reproductions&quot; of works <lb/>It is crucial to determine whether in the light of CJEU&apos;s and national case law, the <lb/>snippets of source material that are still present in a DTF meet the originality criterion, <lb/>and therefore can be regarded as &quot;partial reproductions&quot; of the source texts. In such <lb/>cases, their use (further copying and sharing) would either require permission from <lb/>rightholders, or it would need to enter within the scope of an existing statutory <lb/>exception. In both situations, the purpose of a DTF would not be fully achieved. <lb/>The Court also ruled (also in the Infopaq case) that individual words considered <lb/>in isolation are not intellectual creations of their authors, and therefore they are not <lb/>protected by copyright 31 . However, originality of snippets of 11 words (11-grams) <lb/>extracted from newspaper articles cannot, according to the CJEU, &quot;be ruled out&quot; 32 . <lb/>One could expect that in Germany, the country of origin of the kleine Münze <lb/>(small coin) doctrine (under which, briefly put, works that only exhibit a low level <lb/>of originality can still be protected by copyright) 33 , very short texts would enjoy <lb/>copyright protection. Indeed, in 1964 the appellate court of Düsseldorf declared a <lb/>four-word slogan &quot;Ein Himmelbett als Handgepäck&quot; (&apos;A canopy bed as hand luggage&apos;) <lb/>to be original 34 . This decision is, however, both dated and isolated. <lb/>More recently, German courts have systematically refused copyright protection for <lb/>slogans such as: &quot;Für das aufregendste Ereignis des Jahres&quot; (&apos;For the most exciting <lb/>event of the year&apos;) 35 , &quot;Thalia verführt zum Lesen&quot; (&apos;Thalia tempts into reading&apos;) 36 or <lb/>&quot;Wenn das Haus nasse Füße hat&quot; (&apos;When the house has wet feet&apos;) 37 . These decisions <lb/>were mostly motivated by lack of originality (i.e. not meeting the required Schöpfungs <lb/>höhe), which cannot manifest itself in a very short work. Originality of a literary work <lb/>resides in the selection and presentation of its content (&quot;individuelle Auswahl oder <lb/>Darstellung des Inhalts&quot;); a longer text allows for more free and creative choices 38 , <lb/>whereas very short texts (like slogans or catalogue descriptions 39 ) can only exception <lb/>ally meet the required threshold 40 . <lb/>Probably the most representative and relevant for the subject of this deliverable is <lb/>the 2021 ruling of the German Federal Court of Justice (Bundesgerichtshof, BGH) <lb/>in case I ZR12/08. The administrator of the website perlentaucher.de, containing <lb/>(among others) summaries of book reviews from various newspapers (which included <lb/>a) <lb/></body>
          
    <listBibl>31 CJEU, Infopaq, para 45-46. <lb/>32 CJEU, Infopaq, para 47-48. <lb/>33 First formulated in A. Elster, Gewerblicher rechtsschutz, umfassend Urheber-und Verlags <lb/>recht, Patent-und Musterschutzrecht, Warenzeichenrecht und Wettbewerbsrecht, De Gruy <lb/>ter, 1921. <lb/>34 OLG Düsseldorf, 28.2.1964, 2 U 76/63. <lb/>35 OLG Frankfurt, 4.8.1986, 6 W 134/8. <lb/>36 LG Mannheim, 11.12.2009, 7 O 343/08. <lb/>37 OLG Köln, 8.4.2016, 6 U 120/15. <lb/>38 OLG Köln, 30.9.2011, I-6 U 82/11. <lb/>39 LG Frankenthal, 3.11.2020, 6 O 102/20. <lb/>40 OLG Köln, 8.4.2016, 6 U 120/15. <lb/></listBibl>
        
        <page>163 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
        
        <page>163 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
        
        <body>passages from the original reviews), granted two Internet bookstores (amazon.de and <lb/>bucher.de) a license to use these summaries. In the aftermath, perlentaucher was sued <lb/>for copyright infringement (alongside trademark infringement and unfair competition) <lb/>by the publishers of the Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung and the Süddeutsche Zeitung, <lb/>where some of the reviews had originally been published. The Federal Court referred <lb/>the case back to the Frankfurt Court of Appeals, but in doing so clearly confirmed the <lb/>Court of Appeal&apos;s position according to which individual words and short snippets <lb/>(knappe Wortfolgen) are not protected by copyright. <lb/>Furthermore, the Federal Court also criticized the fact that the Court of Appeals did <lb/>not take into account the proportion of &quot;borrowed&quot; text in the summaries and did not <lb/>assess the &quot;distance&quot; between the original reviews and the summaries. <lb/>This requirement of &quot;sufficient distance&quot;, based on the now abandoned doctrine of <lb/>free use (freie Benutzung) of copyright-protected works (former § 24 of the German <lb/>Copyright Act, repealed in June 2021), relates in an interesting way to the criteria of <lb/>reconstructability and recognizability, formulated by the Court of Justice of the Euro <lb/>pean Union (see below). Eventually, only some of perlentaucher&apos;s summaries that were <lb/>not distinct enough from the original reviews were found to be infringing. <lb/>It seems, therefore, that German courts in general refuse copyright protection of <lb/>short texts; their originality was only admitted exceptionally, and in older case law. <lb/>However, the use of multiple short snippets from a copyright protected text, although <lb/>such snippets individually are not protected by copyright, may still amount to copy <lb/>right infringement if the resulting compilation of snippets is not sufficiently different <lb/>(&quot;distant&quot;) from the original work. <lb/>It seems that cases where a snippet as short as 11 consecutive words is original are <lb/>relatively rare. However, this 11-words threshold results exclusively from the facts of <lb/>the Infopaq case, and should not be interpreted as a minimum length for a snippet <lb/>to be found original. Arguably, even shorter snippets can be found original; however, <lb/>such cases are probably so rare that they can generally be ignored in large-scale text <lb/>mining projects. <lb/>Briefly put, the shorter the snippet, the less likely it is to be found original. The <lb/>&quot;risk&quot; of originality of very short snippets (shorter than 11 words) appears so low that <lb/>it&apos;s almost negligible. Longer snippets, however, come with non-negligeable risks. The <lb/>exclusion of very rare snippets from a DTF can significantly reduce this risk. <lb/>The inclusion of a snippet that meets the originality threshold in a DTF constitutes a <lb/>reproduction in part which means that such a DTF can only be shared with permission <lb/>of the rightholder or within the scope of a statutory copyright exception. <lb/>DTFs and the &quot;reconstructability&quot; criterion <lb/>As mentioned above, according to the CJEU snippets are to be regarded as partial <lb/>reproductions if they are original or if their &quot;cumulative effect (...) may lead to the <lb/>b) <lb/></body>
          
      <page>164 <lb/></page>
          
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>

      <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>

      <body>reconstitution of lengthy fragments which are liable to reflect the originality [of the <lb/>source text]&quot; 41 . <lb/>This condition, which can be referred to as &quot;reconstructability&quot;, is instructive, but <lb/>difficult to apply in the realm of language technology. <lb/>If one considers the sentence &quot;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing <lb/>elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua&quot; as an exam <lb/>ple, one can argue that seemingly it can be reconstructed e.g. from the following series <lb/>of 3-grams: &quot;Lorem ipsum dolor&quot;, &quot;dolor sit amet&quot;, &quot;amet, consectetur adipiscing&quot;, <lb/>etc., because of the overlapping words. This is probably true in a small corpus, but not <lb/>necessarily in a larger one, where numerous 3-grams starting with &quot;dolor&quot;, which can <lb/>be a grammatically coherent continuation of &quot;Lorem ipsum dolor&quot;, may occur (such <lb/>as, for example, &quot;dolor in reprehenderit&quot;, which actually does occur in the famous <lb/>&quot;Lorem ipsum&quot; text). On the other hand, if the sentence is divided into non-overlap <lb/>ping 3-grams: &quot;Lorem ipsum dolor&quot;, &quot;sit amer, consectetur&quot;, &quot;adipiscing elit, sed&quot;, etc. <lb/>it does not necessarily mean that the original text is not reconstructible, even though it <lb/>certainly becomes more difficult to do so. <lb/>Reconstruction of source texts from DTFs may in fact be a more complicated task <lb/>than it appears; in one experiment it was not possible to reconstruct even a very short <lb/>source text after scrambling the word order. 42 In another, the successful reconstruction <lb/>of text from a specific kind of language model-based DTF (a BERT-based contextual <lb/>word embedding model) depended on the availability of the encoder used to build the <lb/>DTF. 43 <lb/>Whether it is possible to do so, has to be evaluated separately for each individual <lb/>DTF. The fact that one DTF (e.g. containing only words no. 1, 3, 5, 7…) can be used <lb/>to reconstruct the source text if combined with another DTF (e.g. containing only <lb/>words no. 2, 4, 6, 8 …) developed independently from the same source text, should not <lb/>influence its copyright status. If, however, several DTFs were built in a coordinated <lb/>manner (e.g. by one team, or by members of the same consortium), and jointly they <lb/>can be used to reconstruct the source text, this may have an influence on a judge who <lb/>could find them infringing. <lb/>In any case, due to the constantly evolving technological possibilities, the answer <lb/>to the question of reconstructibility of source texts is susceptible to changing over <lb/>time. It appears that with a very large amount of effort (e.g., ad infinitum repetition <lb/>of simple trial and error), DTFs can often be used to reconstruct source material. <lb/>Therefore, when applying the criterion of reconstructability to DTFs, it appears sen <lb/></body>
          
    <listBibl>41 CJEU, Infopaq, para 50. <lb/>42 K. Du (2024), Rekonstruierbarkeit von abgeleiteten Textformaten, https://events.gwdg.de/ev <lb/>ent/607/contributions/1408/. <lb/>43 K. Kugler, S. Münker, J. Höhmann, A. Rettinger (2023), InvBERT: Reconstructing Text <lb/>from Contextualized Word Embeddings by inverting the BERT pipeline, Journal of Compu <lb/>tational Literary Studies 2(1), 1-18, doi: https://doi.org/10.48694/jcls.3572. <lb/></listBibl>
              
      <page>165 <lb/></page>
              
      <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
        
      <page>165 <lb/></page>
              
      <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
              
    <body>sible to restrict it to reconstructions possible with a &quot;reasonable effort.&quot; 44 However, <lb/>currently copyright law does not contain such a standard, and it appears that every <lb/>reconstructible copy, regardless of the effort invested in the reconstruction, remains an <lb/>act of reproduction. <lb/>DTFs and the &quot;recognisability&quot; criterion <lb/>The third condition that may impact the legal status of short snippets of texts was <lb/>relatively recently formulated by the CJEU. In 2019 Pelham decision 45 the Court <lb/>ruled that the use of a very short sample from a phonogram (in the facts of the <lb/>case: an approximately 2-second rhythm sequence) in another phonogram is an act of <lb/>reproduction, &quot;unless that sample is included in the phonogram in a modified form <lb/>unrecognizable to the ear&quot;. <lb/>Formally, the ruling only addressed the letter (c) of Article 2 of the InfoSoc Direc <lb/>tive (i.e., the part relating only to the right of reproduction of phonogram producers), <lb/>and it is not clear whether this conclusion can (and should) be extrapolated to all rights <lb/>mentioned in Article 2 (i.e., copyright and certain related rights). Martin Senftleben <lb/>(2020) 46 argues that &quot;the CJEU can give the copyright concept of &quot;partial reproduc <lb/>tion&quot; a meaning that corresponds to the approach taken in Pelham&quot;. However, as <lb/>Senftleben 47 also notices, this does not mean that for literary works the recognizability <lb/>criterion (the &quot;Pelham test&quot;) will replace the criteria put forward in Infopaq (i.e., <lb/>originality and reconstructability). <lb/>Furthermore, it is not clear how the recognizability criterion can relate to literary <lb/>works. It is possible to interpret the criterion as referring to the identifiability of the <lb/>work, i.e. the possibility to indicate which literary work the excerpts were taken from. <lb/>Such an interpretation could lead to most undesirable consequences. It would push <lb/>the frontiers of copyright protection beyond reason, as it is easy to imagine that some <lb/>unoriginal elements like statements of (generally unknown) facts, uncommon names or <lb/>simple yet grammatically flawed expressions could indeed pass the recognisability test. <lb/>If this interpretation of the Pelham criterion for partial reproduction were to apply <lb/>to n-grams used in language technologies, it seems that the use of certain anonymiza <lb/>tion techniques taken from the realm of data protection could provide some relief. <lb/>Arguably, the deletion (or other alteration such as obfuscation) of proper names <lb/>(called &quot;named entities&quot; in computer science) could make some excerpts less recogniz <lb/>able to an average reader. For example, a recent study demonstrated that OpenAI <lb/>c) <lb/></body>
              
      <listBibl>44 B. Raue, C. Schöch, Zugang zu großen Textkorpora…; cf. in the context of anonymisation of <lb/>personal data Recital 26 of the GDPR. <lb/>45 CJEU, C-476/17, Pelham, 29 July 2019, para 39. <lb/>46 M. Senftleben, Flexibility Grave -Partial Reproduction Focus and Closed System Fetishism <lb/>in CJEU, Pelham, IIC, 2020, 51, pp.751 -769. See also K. Grisse, Nutzbarmachung urheber <lb/>rechtlich geschützter Textbestände für die Forschung durch Dritte -Rechtliche Bedingungen <lb/>und Möglichkeiten, Recht und Zugang, 2020, 2, pp. 143-159. <lb/>47 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>
              
  <page>166 <lb/></page>
              
    <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
      
      <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
              
    <body>models memorised a large collection of copyrighted material by having models per <lb/>form a task to predict the identity of a single name in a passage of text that contains no <lb/>other named entities. 48 Named entities can be automatically detected in a corpus and <lb/>anonymized or otherwise pre-processed. <lb/>Moreover, understanding the criterion of recognisability as mere identifiability <lb/>would lead to a clash with the need to publish metadata about the text. Not only <lb/>could it be argued that the publication of identifiers about the work or the title could <lb/>be problematic, but also other basic data for analysis, such as the year of publication or <lb/>the author. Applying this criterion in this way would result in the inability to publish <lb/>metadata relating to the DTF, making it unusable for research. In this approach, a <lb/>library catalogue (which essentially is a list of books&apos; metadata) would infringe copy <lb/>right, as it would allow to identify the works it refers to. <lb/>The concept of recognizability in relation to literary works can and should be <lb/>understood differently: It is not about the reader identifying the specific work, but <lb/>rather about recognizing the elements that constitute the creative value of the text, <lb/>or the individual style of the author. According to this interpretation, the criterion <lb/>of recognizability is not fulfilled merely by the use of the name of a famous literary <lb/>character or by the publication of metadata. <lb/>DTFs as adaptations or transformations of source texts? <lb/>The right of adaptation is mentioned in Article 12 of the Berne Convention, according <lb/>to which &quot;Authors of literary or artistic works shall enjoy the exclusive right of autho <lb/>rizing adaptations, arrangements and other alterations of their works&quot;. This right is <lb/>not harmonised at the EU level, unlike the rights of reproduction and communication <lb/>to the public. <lb/>In Germany, the right of adaptation is safeguarded by § 23 UrhG, according to <lb/>which &quot;Adaptations (Bearbeitungen) or other transformations (Umgestaltungen) of a <lb/>work (...) may be published or exploited only with the author&apos;s consent&quot;. The same <lb/>section continues: &quot;If the newly created work maintains sufficient distance to the work <lb/>used, this does not constitute adaptation or transformation (...)&quot;. <lb/>In the creation of a derived text format, the original text undergoes numerous modi <lb/>fications. The legislator took into account the technically necessary changes involved <lb/>in creating a corpus for text and data mining (TDM) when introducing the TDM <lb/>exception. These changes do not constitute adaptations under § 23 of the German <lb/>Copyright Act (UrhG) but are explicitly excluded ( § 23 (3) UrhG). However, whether <lb/>the outcome of the TDM process constitutes an adaptation has not been explicitly <lb/>addressed by the legislator. It can be assumed that the legislator believed that the result <lb/>of a TDM process is no longer protected by copyright, which is why this issue was not <lb/>2. <lb/></body>
              
      <listBibl>48 K. Chang, M. Cramer, S. Soni, D. Bamman, (2023, December). Speak, Memory: An Archae <lb/>ology of Books Known to ChatGPT/GPT-4 (2023), in: Proceedings of the 2023 Conference <lb/>on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (pp. 7312-7327). <lb/></listBibl>

	<page>167 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
    
    <page>167 <lb/></page>
    
    
    <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>

    <body>regulated. However, it appears that in certain cases TDM outputs may still contain <lb/>copyright-protected material. In such situations, the question arises whether these <lb/>constitute adaptations. This article, however, aims to define the conditions under <lb/>which no copyright protection remains, and for this reason, this question will not be <lb/>delved into. <lb/>DTFs as original compilations? <lb/>Prima facie, DTFs could potentially be regarded as compilations, i.e. collections of <lb/>various elements (original or not) that can be protected by copyright by virtue of the <lb/>original &quot;selection or arrangement&quot; of those constitutive parts. <lb/>Typical examples of compilations within the meaning of copyright law include <lb/>dictionaries, encyclopedias, catalogues, collections of poems, &quot;best of&quot; lists, etc. If <lb/>the exercised free and creative choices (e.g. &quot;My favorite quotes from Woody Allen&quot;) <lb/>in the process, the resulting compilation can be original and therefore protected by <lb/>copyright. <lb/>However, creation of scientifically valuable DTFs does not involve free and creative <lb/>choices. The compiler does not eliminate certain elements (e.g., certain n-grams) from <lb/>the DTF on subjective grounds (e.g., just because he or she does not &quot;like&quot; them). On <lb/>the contrary, DTFs are mostly automatically generated according to predefined criteria <lb/>and rules of the art. Any subsequent modifications (e.g., deletion of rare expressions) is <lb/>also based on objective, rather than subjective grounds. <lb/>Therefore, the hypothesis according to which DTFs can be original compilations <lb/>should be excluded. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Technically necessary acts of reproduction are required for the creation of a DTF. If <lb/>the source material is protected by copyright, the creation of the DTF constitutes a <lb/>copyright-relevant act. In the absence of the right holder&apos;s permission, the creation of <lb/>the DTF must fall under a copyright exception in order to be lawful. DTFs can be cre <lb/>ated under the TDM exceptions ( § § 44b, 60d UrhG). The DTFs can then be used as a <lb/>basis for a subsequent analysis. <lb/>Whether the DTFs can also be used freely, made publicly available and stored for an <lb/>unlimited amount of time, depends on the copyright status of these DTFs. The goal of <lb/>creating a DTF which no longer contains copyright-protected content is achieved, if <lb/> § the DTF does not contain elements which are an expression of the creative individ <lb/>uality of the author of the source material, <lb/> § the source material cannot be reconstructed with trivial effort and <lb/> § the author&apos;s creative individuality is not recognizable. <lb/>There are many grey areas in examining the legal status of the many different forms <lb/>of DTFs. In many cases, legal certainty cannot be achieved. Especially Statistical DTFs <lb/>3. <lb/>V. <lb/></body>
              
    <page>168 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
              
    <body>and Transformative DTFs, can contain partial reproductions of source texts; this risk <lb/>can be mitigated by avoiding reproducibility and recognisability of source texts e.g. <lb/>through avoidance of longer n-grams, especially n-grams longer than 10 words and -<lb/>depending on the adopted perspective -by avoiding rare n-grams. <lb/>However, there are many types of DTFs which clearly fulfil the above-mentioned <lb/>criteria and can therefore be used freely and risk-free. <lb/></body>
    
    
    <listBibl>Bibliography <lb/>https://zfdg.de/2020_006 <lb/>https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/10.5771/2699-1284-2020-2-118/zugang-zu-grossen-te <lb/>xtkorpora-des-20-und-21-jahrhunderts-mit-hilfe-abgeleiteter-textformate-versoehnun <lb/>g-von-urheberrecht-und-textbasierter-forschung-jahrgang-1-2020-heft-2?page=1 <lb/>https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/10.5771/2699-1284-2020-2-143.pdf <lb/>https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/10.5771/2699-1284-2020-2-128.pdf <lb/>Keli Du &amp; Christof Schöch: &quot;Shifting Sentiments? What happens to BERT-based <lb/>Sentiment Classification when derived text formats are used for fine-tuning&quot; (long pre <lb/>sentation). In: Karajgikar, J., Janco, A., &amp; Otis, J. (2024). DH2024 Book of Abstracts. <lb/>Zenodo. https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13761079. <lb/>Kent Chang, Mackenzie Cramer, Sandeep Soni, and David Bamman. 2023. Speak, <lb/>Memory: An Archaeology of Books Known to ChatGPT/GPT-4. In Proceedings of <lb/>the 2023 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, pages <lb/>7312-7327, Singapore. Association for Computational Linguistics. https://doi.org/10.1 <lb/>8653/v1/2023.emnlp-main.453. <lb/>Karina Grisse, &quot;Nutzbarmachung urheberrechtlich geschützter Textbestände für die <lb/>Forschung durch Dritte -Rechtliche Bedingungen und Möglichkeiten&quot;, Recht und <lb/>Zugang, 2020, 2, pp. 143-159. <lb/>Kai Kugler, Simon Münker, Johannes Höhmann, &amp; Achim Rettinger (2023), <lb/>&quot;InvBERT: Reconstructing Text from Contextualized Word Embeddings by inverting <lb/>the BERT pipeline&quot;, Journal of Computational Literary Studies 2(1), 1-18. doi: https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.48694/jcls.3572. <lb/>Y. Lin, J.-B. Michel, E. Aiden Lieberman, J. Orwant, W. Brockman, S. Petrov, Syntac <lb/>tic Annotations for the Google Books NGram Corpus, in: Proceedings of the ACL <lb/>2012 System Demonstrations, Association for Computational Linguistics, Jeju Island, <lb/>Korea, 2012, pp. 169-174. URL: https://aclanthology.org/P12-3029. <lb/>S. Bhattacharyya, P. Organisciak, J. S. Downie, A Fragmentizing Interface to a Large <lb/>Corpus of Digitized Text: (Post)humanism and Non-consumptive Reading via Fea <lb/>tures, Interdisciplinary Science Reviews 40 (2015) 61-77. URL: http://www.tandfonli <lb/>VI. <lb/></listBibl>
              
  <page>169 <lb/></page>
    
  <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
    
  <page>169 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
              
    <listBibl>ne.com/doi/full/10.1179/0308018814Z.000000000105. doi:10.1179/0308018814Z.00000 <lb/>0000105. <lb/>J. Jett, B. Capitanu, D. Kudeki, T. Cole, Y. Hu, P. Organisciak, T. Underwood, <lb/>E. Dickson Koehl, R. Dubnicek, J. S. Downie, The HathiTrust Research Center <lb/>Extracted Features Dataset (2.0), 2020. URL: https://wiki.htrc.illinois.edu/pages/viewp <lb/>age.action?pageId=79069329. doi:10.13012/R2TE-C227. <lb/>C. Schöch, F. Döhl, A. Rettinger, E. Gius, P. Trilcke, P. Leinen, F. Jannidis, M. Hinz <lb/>mann, J. Röpke, Abgeleitete Textformate: Text und Data Mining mit urheberrechtlich <lb/>geschützten Textbeständen (2020). URL: http://zfdg.de/2020_006. doi:10.17175/2020_ <lb/>006. <lb/>P. Organisciak, J. S. Downie, Research access to in-copyright texts in the humanities, <lb/>in: Information and Knowledge Organisation in Digital Humanities, Routledge, 2021, <lb/>pp. 157-177. <lb/>P. Organisciak, B. Capitanu, T. Underwood, J. S. Downie, Access to Billions of Pages <lb/>for Large-Scale Text Analysis, iConference 2017 Proceedings Vol. 2 (2017). URL: <lb/>https://hdl.handle.net/2142/98873. <lb/>N. N. Parulian, R. Dubnicek, G. Worthey, D. J. Evans, J. A. Walsh, J. S. Downie, <lb/>Uncovering Black Fantastic: Piloting A Word Feature Analysis and Machine Learning <lb/>Approach for Genre Classification, Proceedings of the Association for Information <lb/>Science and Technology 59 (2022) 242-250. URL: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/ <lb/>10.1002/pra2.620. doi:10.1002/pra2.620. <lb/>Michel, J. B., Shen, Y. K., Aiden, A. P., Veres, A., Gray, M. K., Google Books Team,... <lb/>&amp; Aiden, E. L. (2011). Quantitative analysis of culture using millions of digitized <lb/>books. science, 331(6014), 176-182. <lb/>Richey, S., &amp; Taylor, J. B. (2020). Google Books Ngrams and political science: Two <lb/>validity tests for a novel data source. PS: Political Science &amp; Politics, 53(1), 72-77. <lb/>El-Ebshihy, A., El-Makky, N. M., &amp; Nagi, K. (2018). Using Google Books Ngram in <lb/>Detecting Linguistic Shifts over Time. In KDIR (pp. 330-337). <lb/>Hessel, J., &amp; Schofield, A. (2021, August). How effective is BERT without word <lb/>ordering? implications for language understanding and data privacy. In Proceedings of <lb/>the 59th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the <lb/>11 th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (Volume 2: Short <lb/>Papers) (pp. 204-211). <lb/>G. Iacino, P. Kamocki, P. Leinen, Assessment of the Impact of the DSM-Directive on <lb/>Text+ <lb/>F. Barth, J. Calvo Tello, K. Du, P. Genêt, L. Keller, J. Knappen, Liste der Abgeleiteten <lb/>Textformate (working title), forthcoming, 2025. <lb/></listBibl>
              
    <page>170 <lb/></page>
              
    <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
              
    <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>
              
      <listBibl>J. Baudry (2023). Non-consumptive research use, an analysis of the legal situation, on <lb/>Couperin.org, https://www.couperin.org/le-consortium/actus/non-consumptive-resea <lb/>rch-use/. <lb/>WTO, Report of the Panel, WT/DS160/R, 15 June 2000, para 6.229. <lb/>Martin Senftleben, The International Three-Step Test: A Model Provision for EC Fair <lb/>Use Legislation, 1 (2010) Journal of Intellectual Property, Information Technology and <lb/>E-Commerce Law, Vol. 1, No. 2, pp. 67-82. <lb/>Gervais, Daniel J., Towards a New Core International Copyright Norm: The Reverse <lb/>Three-Step Test. Available at SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=499924. <lb/>BeckOK UrhR/Grübler, 42. Ed. 1.5.2024, UrhG § 60c Rn <lb/>Dreier/Schulze/Dreier, 7. Aufl. 2022, UrhG § 60c Rn. 1 <lb/>First formulated in A. Elster, Gewerblicher rechtsschutz, umfassend Urheber-und <lb/>Verlagsrecht, Patent-und Musterschutztrecht, Warenzeichenrecht und Wettbewerbs <lb/>recht, De Gruyter, 1921. <lb/>N. Carlini et al., &quot;Extracting Training Data from Large Language Models&quot; in: Pro <lb/>ceedings of the 30th USENIX Security Symposium (August 11-13, 2021), USENIX <lb/>Association, 2021, pp. 2633-2650. <lb/>Keli Du (2024), &quot;Rekonstruierbarkeit von abgeleiteten Textformaten&quot;, https://events.g <lb/>wdg.de/event/607/contributions/1408/. <lb/>M. Senftleben, &quot;Flexibility Grave -Partial Reproduction Focus and Closed System <lb/>Fetishism in CJEU, Pelham&quot;, IIC, 2020, 51, pp.751 -769. <lb/>Calvo Tello, José, Mathias Göbel, Ubbo Veentjer, Stefan E. Funk, Nanette Rißler-<lb/>Pipika, and Keli Du. 2025 (accepted). &apos;FAIR Derived Data in TEI and Its Publication <lb/>in the TextGrid Repository&apos;. jTEI. <lb/>Burnard, Lou. 2004. &apos;Metadata for Corpus Work&apos;. In Developing Linguistic Corpora: <lb/>A Guide to Good Practice, edited by Martin Wynne. Oxford: AHDS Literature, Lan <lb/>guages and Linguistics. https://ota.ox.ac.uk/documents/creating/dlc/chapter3.htm. <lb/>Wilkinson, Mark D., Michel Dumontier, IJsbrand Jan Aalbersberg, Gabrielle Apple <lb/>ton, Myles Axton, Arie Baak, Niklas Blomberg, et al. 2016. &apos;The FAIR Guiding <lb/>Principles for Scientific Data Management and Stewardship&apos;. Scientific Data 3 (March). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18. <lb/></listBibl>
              
    <page>171 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
    
    <page>171 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="footnote">RuZ 5. Jg. 3/2024 <lb/>10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -<lb/></note>

    <front>Zusammenfassung: Text-und Data Mining (TDM)-Methoden werden angewandt, um <lb/>große Textmengen für die wissenschaftliche Forschung zu analysieren. Handelt es sich bei <lb/>dem analysierten Text um urheberrechtlich geschütztes Material, hat die Nutzung solcher <lb/>TDM-Methoden urheberrechtliche Implikationen. Die bestehenden Urheberrechtsschran <lb/>ken ermöglichen TDM innerhalb eines engen Rahmens, der die Speicherung, öffentliche <lb/>Zugänglichmachung und Wiederverwendung von Datensätzen einschränkt. Dieser Beitrag <lb/>untersucht den rechtlichen Rahmen für die Umwandlung des Ursprungsmaterials in ein <lb/>abgeleitetes Textformat (ATF), das keinem Urheberrechtsschutz mehr unterliegt, um die <lb/>Nutzung von TDM ohne Einschränkungen zu ermöglichen. Zunächst wird die Erstellung <lb/>des ATF selbst untersucht: Auch sie umfasst urheberrechtlich relevante Handlungen, die <lb/>durch die TDM-Ausnahmen abgedeckt sind. In einem zweiten Schritt muss der urheber <lb/>rechtliche Status des erstellten ATFs anhand von drei Kriterien bewertet werden: Das ATF <lb/>darf keine Elemente enthalten, die die Schöpfungshöhe des Ursprungsmaterials begründet <lb/>haben, das Ursprungsmaterial darf nicht anhand des ATF rekonstruierbar sein und das <lb/>Ursprungsmaterial darf nicht wiedererkennbar sein. <lb/>Summary: Text and Data Mining (TDM) methods are often used in order to analyse large <lb/>amounts of text for scientific research. If the analysed text is protected by copyright, the <lb/>use of such TDM methods has copyright implications. The existing copyright exceptions <lb/>facilitate TDM within a narrow framework which limits the storage, publication and re-use <lb/>of datasets. This paper examines the legal framework of converting the source text into a <lb/>derived text format (DTF) which is no longer protected by copyright in order to allow the <lb/>use of TDM without legal restrictions. First, the creation itself of a DTF is being examined: <lb/>it entails copyright relevant acts which are covered by the TDM exceptions. In a second <lb/>step the copyright status of the created DTF has to be evaluated based on three criteria: the <lb/>DTF may not contain elements which are an expression of the intellectual creation of the <lb/>author of the source material, the source material may not be easily reconstructable based <lb/>on the DTF and the source material may not be recognizable. <lb/>© Gianna Iacino, Paweł Kamocki, Keli Du, Christof Schöch, <lb/>Andreas Witt, Philippe Genêt and José Calvo Tello <lb/></front>
              
    <page>172 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Iacino et al. • Legal status of Derived Text Formats <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">10.5771/2699-1284-2024-3-149 -am 11.08.2025, 18:08:59. https://www.nomos-elibrary.de/de/agb -Open Access -</note>


	</text>

</TEI>