<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a" type="main">A Mistake of Natural Law: Sir William Blackstone and the Anglican Way</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cb">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-08-04T10:47:14.291Z">4.8.2025 12:47:14</date>
        <title>Grobid document segmentation</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Craig A. Stern. (2019). A Mistake of Natural Law: Sir William Blackstone and the Anglican Way. University of Bologna Law Review, (), . DOI: 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-04">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">ed8032b</label>
        <label type="parameters">flavor=article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-08-04T13:06:48.958Z" status="draft" who="#cb">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	<text>
		    <!-- all listBibl are mixed-reference in this file -->
            <front>ARTICLES &amp; ESSAYS <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/>A Mistake of Natural Law: <lb/>Sir William Blackstone and the Anglican Way <lb/>CRAIG A. STERN † <lb/>TABLE OF CONTENTS: 1. Introduction; 2. The Commentaries and the Commentators; 3. Blackstone and <lb/>Justinian; 4.Blackstone and the Church of England; 4.1 Richard Hooker; 4.2 The Latitudinarians; 5. The <lb/>Anglican Blackstone and the Natural Law; 6. Conclusion. <lb/>ABSTRACT: It is said that no book on the common law surpasses the importance of Sir <lb/>William Blackstone's Commentaries on the Laws of England. But it is also said that the <lb/>Commentaries is of questionable merit, with aspects of it downright incoherent. The most <lb/>fundamental element of the Commentaries to attract this disparaging characterization is <lb/>its discussion and use of what it usually calls "the law of nature" -and what we these <lb/>days usually call "natural law." Does the Commentaries perpetrate a mistake -actually <lb/>many mistakes -of natural law? This article answers that it is not the Commentaries, but <lb/>rather its critics that perpetrate mistakes of natural law. The mistakes arise from the <lb/>expectation that Blackstone's natural law would take after Thomas Aquinas's (or even <lb/>Christopher St. German's) natural law. But readers of the Commentaries who allow <lb/>Blackstone his own way with natural law will find it a valuable treatment that animates <lb/>the whole. Blackstone's natural law owes much to two influences, Roman law and the <lb/>Anglican Church. The second influence is the more distinctive and guides Blackstone's <lb/>response to the first. Both led Blackstone to view the natural law as an order immanent in <lb/>human law, an order especially prominent within the common law. Seen in this light, <lb/>natural law provides the foundation for the Commentaries and a foundation for <lb/>understanding law in our own day. <lb/>KEYWORDS: Blackstone; Natural Law; Roman Law; Anglicanism; Law and Religion <lb/>UNIVERSITY OF BOLOGNA LAW REVIEW <lb/>ISSN 2531-6133 <lb/>[VOL.4:2 2019] <lb/>This article is released under the terms of Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC-BY) <lb/>325 <lb/></front>

            <note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

            <body>1. INTRODUCTION <lb/>"[P]erhaps the most important single book . . . in the history of the <lb/>common law" is Sir William Blackstone's Commentaries on the Laws of <lb/>England (hereinafter Commentaries). 1 No other book but the Bible had a <lb/>greater role in generating American institutions 2 and the nineteenth <lb/>century alone saw about one hundred American versions. 3 It is said that <lb/>the Commentaries led early American courts to decide from principles, not <lb/>precedents. 4 But it is said also that the Commentaries is of questionable <lb/>merit, 5 with aspects of it downright incoherent. 6 <lb/>The most fundamental element of the Commentaries to attract this <lb/>disparaging characterization is its discussion and use of what it usually <lb/>calls "the law of nature." 7 "Natural law" is the term more frequently used <lb/>these days for a transcendent legal order to which human law necessarily <lb/>bears some relationship. Because Blackstone's concept of the "law of <lb/>nature" is similar to that of contemporary "natural law," this article <lb/></body>

            <front>† Professor, Regent University School of Law (US). B.A. Yale University, J.D. University of <lb/>Virginia. The author thanks Mark Cartledge, Doug Cook, Alyson Crisbie, Lou Hensler, <lb/>Mike Hernandez, Timothy and Meredith Pettman, Paul Shakeshaft, the good people of <lb/>the Regent University Law Library, and his wife Kelly for their help. <lb/></front>

		    <listBibl>1 DANIEL J. BOORSTIN, THE MYSTERIOUS SCIENCE OF THE LAW, at vii (Peter Smith 1973) (1941); <lb/>see also Albert W. Alschuler, Rediscovering Blackstone, 145 U. PA. L. REV. 1, 2 (1996). The <lb/>Commentaries was hugely popular in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. See WILFRID <lb/>PREST, WILLIAM BLACKSTONE 307 (2008). <lb/>2 See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at iii; see also Alschuler, supra note 1, at 5-9; Joseph W. <lb/>McKnight, Blackstone: Quasi-Jurisprudent, 13 SW L.J. 399, 411 (1959). The present article <lb/>happens to highlight elements of the Commentaries that commended it to Americans <lb/>of the Founding: "Even those who rejected Blackstone's anti-republican emphasis on <lb/>parliamentary omnipotence . . . had no difficulty in accepting the validity of Blackstone's <lb/>exposition of English common law as founded on custom, divine law, and the law of <lb/>nature, hence providing an entirely appropriate legal foundation for the incipient USA." <lb/>Wilfrid Prest, General Editor's Introduction to 1 WILLIAM BLACKSTONE, COMMENTARIES ON THE <lb/>LAWS OF ENGLAND, at vii, xiv (Wilfrid Prest ed., Oxford Univ. Press 2016) (1765) (footnote <lb/>omitted). <lb/>3 See Wilfrid Prest, Blackstone as Architect: Constructing the Commentaries, 15 YALE J.L. &amp; <lb/>HUMAN. 103, 107-08 (2003). <lb/>4 McKnight, supra note 2, at 401. <lb/>5 See Emily Kadens, Justice Blackstone's Common Law Orthodoxy, 103 NW. U. L. REV. 1553, <lb/>1566 (2009). <lb/>6 See infra notes 45-54 and accompanying text. <lb/>7 Sometimes the Commentaries seems to use "natural law" or some similar term for the law <lb/>of nature. See infra text accompanying notes 41-42. This seeming lack of uniformity and <lb/>rigor in terminology certainly does not foster coherence in the Commentaries. On the other <lb/>hand, Aquinas seems to do likewise. See infra note 33. <lb/></listBibl>

            <page>326 <lb/></page>

            <note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>
		
		    <body>often will use the latter term instead. In this parlance, the concern <lb/>becomes the charge of incoherence in Blackstone's discussion and use of <lb/>natural law. Does the Commentaries perpetrate a mistake -actually many <lb/>mistakes -of natural law? <lb/>This article proposes that it is not the Commentaries, but rather its <lb/>critics that perpetrate mistakes of natural law. The mistakes arise from <lb/>the expectation that Blackstone's natural law would take after Thomas <lb/>Aquinas's 8 (or even Christopher St.German's) 9 natural law. As Blackstone <lb/>disappoints these expectations, he has met with criticisms that his <lb/>treatment of natural law is a sloppy pro forma performance that even he <lb/>himself does not take seriously. But readers of the Commentaries who <lb/>allow Blackstone his own way with natural law will find it a valuable <lb/>treatment that animates the whole of the Commentaries. <lb/>Blackstone's natural law owes much to two influences. The first is <lb/>Roman law, especially as captured in the Corpus Juris Civilis. 10 The second <lb/>is the Anglican church, 11 which is the more distinctive and guides <lb/>Blackstone's response to the first. Both led Blackstone to view the natural <lb/>law as an order immanent in human law, an order especially prominent <lb/>within the common law. Seen in this light, natural law provides the <lb/>foundation for the Commentaries. While doing so, it also provides a <lb/>foundation for understanding law even today, a foundation actually in use <lb/>far more than some might think. <lb/></body>
		
		    <listBibl>8 See infra notes 34-44 and accompanying text. <lb/>9 In the early sixteenth century, St. German wrote Doctor and Student, "the first major law <lb/>book published in English," "also the first purely analytical English law book," a work <lb/>of "analytical theology and philosophy." DANIEL R. COQUILLETTE, THE ANGLO-AMERICAN <lb/>LEGAL HERITAGE: INTRODUCTORY MATERIALS 187-88 (2d ed. 2004). He drew in part upon <lb/>Aquinas. CHRISTOPHER SAINT GERMAN, ST. GERMAN'S DOCTOR AND STUDENT, at xxiii-iv, li, <lb/>lvi (T. F. T. Plucknett &amp; J. L. Barton eds., 1975). <lb/>10 See infra notes 55-96 and accompanying text. <lb/>11 See infra notes 97-329 and accompanying text. <lb/></listBibl>

            <page>327 <lb/></page>

            <note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>
		
		    <body>2. THE COMMENTARIES AND THE COMMENTATORS <lb/>After unproductive struggles to develop a successful practice at the bar, <lb/>Blackstone's professional life began to flourish with his Oxford lectures <lb/>on the common law. 12 The Commentaries is not these lectures merely <lb/>recast, delivered as they were to an audience of mere teenagers. 13 <lb/>Nevertheless, the Commentaries is designed to teach and Blackstone <lb/>wanted his readers to learn. 14 The readers for whom he wrote were <lb/>"young nobility and gentry," 15 the leading laymen of the realm. 16 Chief <lb/>among these were those who were or would become legislators, and <lb/>Blackstone was determined to instruct them not to harm by statute the <lb/>liberties of Englishmen. 17 <lb/>Blackstone's aim to instruct lay readers shaped the Commentaries. <lb/>This aim trained the focus of the Commentaries upon substantive rules of <lb/>law, lending the Commentaries both its pathbreaking distinctive and also <lb/>the daunting obstacle to its creation. 18 Blackstone's object was to teach <lb/>laymen the laws of property, crimes, torts, and such -not how to draft <lb/>legal instruments or plead at bar. 19 Beyond teaching the substance of the <lb/>law to laymen, this substantive-law focus gave "lawyers a new vision of <lb/>the law." 20 The Commentaries imposed order and a clarifying system on the <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>See Douglas H. Cook, Sir William Blackstone: A Life and Legacy Set Apart for God's Work, 13 <lb/>REGENT U. L. REV. 169, 172-173 (2000-01). <lb/>See McKnight, supra note 2, at 400. <lb/>See John H. Langbein, Blackstone on Judging, in BLACKSTONE AND HIS COMMENTARIES: <lb/>BIOGRAPHY, LAW, HISTORY 65, 77 (Wilfrid Prest ed., 2009). <lb/>DAVID LIEBERMAN, THE PROVINCE OF LEGISLATION DETERMINED: LEGAL THEORY IN <lb/>EIGHTEENTH-CENTURY BRITAIN 65 (1989). <lb/>See Robert C. Berring, The Ultimate Oldie But Goodie: William Blackstone's Commentaries on <lb/>the Law of England, 4 J.L. 189, 190 (2014). This is not to say that Blackstone disregarded <lb/>the education of lawyers by means of his Commentaries. See David Lemmings, Blackstone <lb/>and Law Reform by Education: Preparation for the Bar and Lawyerly Culture in Eighteenth-<lb/>Century England, 16 LAW HIST. REV. 211, 215, 251-52 (1998); Prest, supra note 2, at ix. <lb/>See LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 56, 66. <lb/>See S. F. C. Milsom, The Nature of Blackstone's Achievement, 1 OXFORD J. LEGAL STUD. 1, 4, 6 <lb/>(1981). <lb/>See id. at 2, 5, 12. <lb/>20 Id. at 10, 12; see also Lemmings, supra note 16, at 243, 252. <lb/></listBibl>

            <page>328 <lb/></page>

            <note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

            <body>jumble that was English law. 21 This arrangement was a key to its success. 22 <lb/>It is Blackstone's use of natural law that undergirds this arrangement. 23 <lb/>Near the beginning of the Commentaries is Blackstone's <lb/>introductory discussion of law. 24 Law is "a rule of action dictated by some <lb/>superior being," and laws considered as rules for human conduct are "the <lb/>precepts by which man, the noblest of all sublunary beings, a creature <lb/>endowed with both reason and freewill, is commanded to make use of <lb/>those faculties in the general regulation of his behavior." 25 The obligation <lb/>to obey law derives from dependence upon the lawgiver, "[a]nd <lb/>consequently as man depends absolutely upon his maker for every thing, <lb/>it is necessary that he should in all points conform to his maker's will. <lb/>THIS will of his maker is called the law of nature." 26 In its scope, <lb/>Blackstone's law of nature reminds one of Aquinas's natural law. 27 <lb/></body>

            <!-- footnote desaparecidos -->
		    <listBibl>See Jessie Allen, Law and Artifice in Blackstone's Commentaries, 4 J.L. 195, 195 (2014). <lb/>See LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 33-36. <lb/>See 1 WILLIAM BLACKSTONE, COMMENTARIES ON THE LAWS OF ENGLAND 37 (The Legal Classics <lb/>Library 1983) (1765-70) (quoting with approval John Fortescue's endorsement that <lb/>lay students "trace[] up the principles and grounds of the law, even to their original <lb/>elements"). Blackstone's use of natural law in the Commentaries may also reflect his <lb/>own introduction to the law. It was St. German's Doctor and Student, a work integrating <lb/>theological and legal thought, that drew Blackstone to the law. Cook, supra note 12, at <lb/>170. Perhaps for similar reasons, the Commentaries turned students from theology to law. <lb/>McKnight, supra note 2, at 401. <lb/>Note that the pagination of the various editions of the Commentaries has become more or <lb/>less standardized. This move is not without its problems, however. See Alschuler, supra <lb/>note 1, at 3 n.4; cf.Carli N. Conklin, The Origins of the Pursuit of Happiness, 7 WASH. U. JURIS. <lb/>REV. 195, 200 (2015)) (selecting for use the first edition, as does the present article); Alan <lb/>Watson, The Structure of Blackstone's Commentaries, 97 YALE L.J. 795, 801 (1988) (same). <lb/>24 See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 38-62. Blackstone's approach reflects Christian and <lb/>classical roots. Conklin, supra note 23, at 246. It owes a debt to Burlamaqui,HENRY SUMNER <lb/>MAINE, ANCIENT LAW 94 (Oxford Univ. Press 1931) (1861).; McKnight, supra note 2, at 406-<lb/>07, but not in its definition of law, J. M. Finnis, Blackstone's Theoretical Intentions, 12 NAT. <lb/>L.F. 163, 171 (1967). Blackstone's definition of municipal law follows his organization of <lb/>the Commentaries. See id. at 167-69. <lb/>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 39. <lb/>26 Id. <lb/>See THOMAS AQUINAS, THE SUMMA THEOLOGICA 209 (Daniel J. Sullivan ed., Fathers of the <lb/>English Dominican Province trans., Encyclopaedia Britannica 1952) (1265-73). (I-II, 91, 2, <lb/>observing, "Now among all others, the rational creature is subject to Divine providence in <lb/>the most excellent way, in so far as it partakes of a share of providence, by being provident <lb/>both for itself and for others. Therefore it has a share of the Eternal Reason, by which it <lb/>has a natural inclination to its due act and end; and this participation of the eternal law in <lb/>the rational creature is called the natural law . . . [T]he natural law is nothing else than <lb/>the rational creature's participation of the eternal law"). <lb/></listBibl>

            <page>329 <lb/></page>

            <note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

            <body>The voluntaristic stamp of Blackstone's law of nature -it is the will of <lb/>God -diminishes somewhat in the next words of the Commentaries. <lb/>God's wisdom leads him to prescribe only what corresponds to the nature <lb/>of things and in this he conforms to "the eternal, immutable laws of good <lb/>and evil." 28 Human reason is able to discover these laws, and God's <lb/>goodness leads him to link our happiness with obedience to the law of <lb/>nature. "For he has so intimately connected, so inseparably interwoven <lb/>the laws of eternal justice with the happiness of each individual, that the <lb/>latter cannot be obtained but by observing the former; and, if the former <lb/>be punctually obeyed, it cannot but induce the latter." 29 This link between <lb/>the law of nature and human happiness "is the foundation of what we call <lb/>ethics, or natural law." 30 Natural law comprises articles that "amount to <lb/>no more than demonstrating, that this or that action tends to man's real <lb/>happiness, and therefore very justly concluding that the performance of it <lb/>is a part of the law of nature." 31 <lb/>Blackstone then renders explicit the supreme authority of the law of <lb/>nature: <lb/>THIS law of nature, being co-eval with mankind and dictated <lb/>by God himself, is of course superior in obligation to any other. <lb/>It is binding over all the globe, in all countries, and at all times: <lb/>no human laws are of any validity, if contrary to this; and such <lb/>of them as are valid derive all their force, and all their authority, <lb/>mediately or immediately, from this original. 32 <lb/>Again, Blackstone's law of nature brings to mind Aquinas's natural law. 33 <lb/>But Blackstone's approach to what he calls natural law differs <lb/>profoundly from that of Aquinas. We already have noted that the <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 40. <lb/>Id. <lb/>Id. at 41. <lb/>31 Id. <lb/>Id. <lb/>See 2 AQUINAS, supra note 27, at 227-28 (I-II, 95, 2, observing, in an article on the relation <lb/>of "human law" to "natural law," that "every human law has just so much of the character <lb/>of law as it is derived from the law of nature. But if in any point it differs from the law of <lb/>nature, it is no longer a law but a corruption of law."). <lb/></listBibl>

            <page>330 <lb/></page>

            <note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

            <body>Commentaries describes natural law as a set of demonstrations that <lb/>certain human conduct leads to human happiness and consequently <lb/>comports with the law of nature. 34 This description is nothing like <lb/>Aquinas's description of natural law as the participation of human beings <lb/>in the eternal law, or perhaps vice versa. 35 This difference between <lb/>Blackstone and Aquinas becomes yet clearer in the former's comparison <lb/>of divine law with natural law. <lb/>Although human reason before the Fall sufficed to discover the <lb/>precepts of the law of nature, human reason after the Fall "is corrupt, and <lb/>[human] understanding full of ignorance and error." 36 Therefore, God of <lb/>his compassion has informed us of the law of nature "by . . . immediate <lb/>and direct revelation." 37 "The doctrines thus delivered we call the <lb/>revealed or divine law, and they are to be found only in the holy <lb/>scriptures." 38 So the natural law and the divine law both bespeak the law <lb/>of nature. <lb/>Yet undoubtedly the revealed law is (humanly speaking) of <lb/>infinite more authority than what we generally call the natural <lb/>law. Because one is the law of nature, expressly declared so to <lb/>be by God himself; the other is only what, by the assistance of <lb/>human reason, we imagine to be that law. If we could be as <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>See supra text accompanying note 31. <lb/>See supra note 27. <lb/>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 41. For discussions of Aquinas's approach to the impact <lb/>of the Fall upon the operation of the natural law, see also CHARLES E. RICE, 50 QUESTIONS <lb/>ON THE NATURAL LAW 159-63 (1993) and Russell Hittinger, Natural Law and Catholic Moral <lb/>Philosophy, in A PRESERVING GRACE 1, 7-8 (Michael Cromartie ed., 1997). Hittinger finds <lb/>that Aquinas, "[i]n his last recorded remarks on the subject of natural law," said: <lb/>Now although God in creating man gave him this law of nature, <lb/>the devil oversowed another law in man, namely, the law of <lb/>concupiscence. . . . Since then the law of nature was destroyed by <lb/>concupiscence, man needed to be brought back to works of virtue, and <lb/>to be drawn away from vice: for which purpose he needed the written <lb/>law. <lb/>Id. at 7 (citing Thomas Aquinas, Collations in Decem Praeceptis (1273)). <lb/>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 42. <lb/>Id. In tension with his formulation here, elsewhere in the Commentaries Blackstone will <lb/>write of "divine law, either natural or revealed," 2 id. at 420, and "divine law both natural <lb/>and revealed," id. at 455. In these two instances, it appears that he uses "divine" to denote <lb/>the divine origin of the law of nature rather than to denote divine law proper. So, in yet <lb/>a third place, he writes of "those laws which the creator has given us; the divine laws, I <lb/>mean, of either nature or revelation." 4 id. at 177. <lb/></listBibl>

            <page>331 <lb/></page>

            <note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

            <body>certain of the latter as we are of the former, both would have an <lb/>equal authority; but, till then, they can never be put in any <lb/>competition together. 39 <lb/>Natural law is "only what . . . we imagine to be" the law of nature. 40 <lb/>The Commentaries continues with further observations on the <lb/>relationship between these laws and human law: <lb/>UPON these two foundations, the law of nature and the law of <lb/>revelation, depend all human laws; that is to say, no human <lb/>laws should be suffered to contradict these. There is, it is true, a <lb/>great number of indifferent points, in which both the divine law <lb/>and the natural leave a man at his own liberty; but which are <lb/>found necessary for the benefit of society to be restrained <lb/>within certain limits. And herein it is that human laws have <lb/>their greatest force and efficacy; for, with regard to such points <lb/>as are not indifferent, human laws are only declaratory of, and <lb/>act in subordination to, the former. 41 <lb/>Two elements of this excerpt warrant special notice. First is Blackstone's <lb/>usage of the "law of nature" and the "natural law." As mentioned <lb/>above, 42 his usage sometimes seems to depart from distinguishing the <lb/>two, with natural law as a merely human construct thought to resemble <lb/>the actual law of nature. On one reading, such a departure appears in this <lb/>passage. <lb/>The second element is the connection between matters <lb/>indifferent -matters for which the law of nature does not prescribe a <lb/>specific rule -and human law. While there is a firm link between the <lb/>laws of nature and human law, it appears that human law largely <lb/></body>

            <listBibl>1 id. at 42. <lb/>Id. <lb/>Id. Examples of Blackstone's references to the divine law include his discussion of the law <lb/>of nuisance as enforcing "that excellent rule of gospel-morality, of 'doing to others as we <lb/>would they should do unto ourselves,'" 3 id. at 218, and of the criminal law, 4 id. at 11, 30, <lb/>42, 43, 60, including laws against homicide, id. at 177, dueling, id. at 199, and sodomy, <lb/>id. at 216. John Finnis has noted that Blackstone's endorsement of the role divine law is <lb/>to play in the formulation of human law does not lead him to confuse crime with sin. See <lb/>Finnis, supra note 24, at 177. <lb/>See supra note 7. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>332 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>concerns itself with matters indifferent. Whereas Aquinas casts human <lb/>law essentially in the position of providing determinations that apply <lb/>rules of the natural law in particular contexts, 43 Blackstone sees human <lb/>law having greatest play where the law of nature appears mute. This <lb/>significant role in his analysis for things indifferent owes a major debt to <lb/>Blackstone's Anglican point of view. 44 <lb/>Blackstone's introductory remarks on law and their relation to the <lb/>rest of the Commentaries (and, for that matter, Blackstone's entire <lb/>project) have drawn sharp criticism. It is reported that no less an <lb/>authority than Dr. Johnson remarked that Blackstone "thought clearly, <lb/>but he thought faintly." 45 The Commentaries "is widely believed to rest on <lb/>silly, ponderous, formal, conceptual, outdated, deductive, mechanistic, <lb/>naive and hopelessly unrealistic jurisprudence," 46 to be lacking in rigor, 47 <lb/>and apparently riven by inconsistencies. 48 Especially for his effort to <lb/>satisfy the customary requirement of supplying his treatise with a general <lb/>introduction on the law, 49 Blackstone has received much criticism. 50 <lb/>Beyond this, Blackstone seems largely to ignore the introductory doctrine <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See 2 AQUINAS, supra note 27, at 209-10 (I-II, 91, 3, observing that, "it is from the precepts <lb/>of the natural law, as from general and indemonstrable principles, that the human reason <lb/>needs to proceed to the more particular determination of certain matters. These particular <lb/>determinations, devised by human reason, are called human laws . . ."). The Commentaries <lb/>is not wholly lacking this approach. For example: "And sometimes, where the thing itself <lb/>has it's [sic] rise from the law of nature, the particular circumstances and mode of doing <lb/>it become right or wrong, as the laws of the land shall direct." 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note <lb/>23, at 55. <lb/>The significant role in the Commentaries for human law to supply rules for matters <lb/>indifferent does not preclude a role for the law of nature (or natural law) in supplying <lb/>specific rules for human law. See, e.g., 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 435-36, 441 <lb/>(discussing parents and children); 2 Id. at 390, 392-93 (discussing property in animals); <lb/>4 Id. at 11 (discussing capital punishment), 29 (discussing wife's defense of duress), <lb/>30 (discussing self-defense), 42 (discussing guilt from crime), 67, 117 (discussing <lb/>international law). <lb/>Richard A. Posner, Blackstone and Bentham, 19 J.L. &amp; ECON. 569, 570 (1976) (quoting C. <lb/>HERBERT STUART FIFOOT, LORD MANSFIELD 26 (1936)). The early classic effort to debunk the <lb/>Commentaries is JEREMY BENTHAM, A FRAGMENT ON GOVERNMENT (London, Thomas Payne <lb/>et al. 1776), but Bentham's target is as much the notion of natural law as the Commentaries <lb/>itself. Posner's article explains that Bentham's is a "fundamentally misconceived attack <lb/>on the Commentaries." Id. at 569. <lb/>Alschuler, supra note 1, at 2. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 189. <lb/>See Posner, supra note 45, at 571. <lb/>See McKnight, supra note 2, at 402. <lb/>See Michael Lobban, Blackstone and the Science of Law, 30 HIST. J. 311, 311 (1987); McKnight, <lb/>supra note 2, at 402, 404. Lobban's criticisms are answered in Harold J. Berman &amp; Charles <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>333 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>he supplies once his introduction is behind him. 51 H.L.A. Hart has argued <lb/>that Blackstone does not use the law of nature to support English law, and <lb/>that his natural law test of the validity of positive law is vacuous in any <lb/>event. 52 Although these arguments have not gone unanswered, 53 they <lb/>actually point not to defects but rather to the very natural law technique <lb/>Blackstone uses in his discussion of English law in the Commentaries, the <lb/>technique based upon his Anglican understanding. 54 <lb/>The Commentaries has suffered at the hands of some commentators. <lb/>The introductory explanation of the law of nature and natural law has been <lb/>a popular target of criticism. So has Blackstone's use -or rather non-use <lb/>-of these elements when he develops his commentaries on the laws of <lb/>England proper. Nevertheless, a more liberal appreciation of his work will <lb/>notice a highly developed and broadly used natural law approach in those <lb/>commentaries. This appreciation, however, must be attuned to discerning <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>J. Reid, Jr., The Transformation of English Legal Science: From Hale to Blackstone, 45 EMORY <lb/>L.J. 437, 490 n.107 (1996). <lb/>See supra notes 41 and 44 for instances where the Commentaries explicitly draws upon <lb/>specific rules of the law of nature, natural law, or divine law. <lb/>H. L. A. Hart, Blackstone's Use of the Law of Nature, 1956 BUTTERWORTHS S. AFR. L. REV. 169, <lb/>169-71. <lb/>See Finnis, supra note 24, at 171-74. <lb/>54 McKnight concurs in Hart's view of Blackstone's treatment of the law of nature and sees <lb/>it as making way for Blackstone's focus on indifferent matters. See McKnight, supra <lb/>note 2, at 405. McKnight's understanding also supports, if ironically, the argument that <lb/>Blackstone thereby paves the way for his own brand of natural law analysis. See infra notes <lb/>309-12 and accompanying text. <lb/>Two other criticisms of the Commentaries deserve scant mention here. First, the radical <lb/>critique of Duncan Kennedy, The Structure of Blackstone's Commentaries, 28 BUFF. L. REV. <lb/>205 (1979), that finds Blackstone "supremely unconvincing." Id. at 211. Kennedy's <lb/>critique itself has been found supremely unconvincing. See, e.g., Alschuler, supra note 1, at <lb/>45-46; Berman &amp; Reid, supra note 50, at 492 n.108; John W. Cairns, Blackstone, an English <lb/>Institutist: Legal Literature and the Rise of the Nation State, 4 OXFORD J. LEGAL STUD. 318, <lb/>350-52 (1984); Watson, supra note 23, at 795, 802. Second, some commentators criticize <lb/>Blackstone on his discussion of absolute rights, as if his use of "absolute" means incapable <lb/>of diminishment or compromise. See, e.g., Lobban, supra note 50, at 329-30; McKnight, <lb/>supra note 2, at 401 n.16. This criticism falls aside upon paying more careful attention to <lb/>Blackstone's usage: <lb/>THE rights of persons considered in their natural capacities are <lb/>also of two sorts, absolute, and relative. Absolute, which are such as <lb/>appertain and belong to particular men, merely as individuals or single <lb/>persons: relative, which are incident to them as members of society, <lb/>and standing in various relations to each other. <lb/>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 119. "Absolute" means apart from social context, not <lb/>sacrosanct. See Watson, supra note 23, at 803. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>334 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>a use of the natural law that Blackstone's own introduction may not have <lb/>foretold for his readers today. <lb/>3. BLACKSTONE AND JUSTINIAN <lb/>Before seeing Blackstone as an Anglican it helps to see him as a civilian -<lb/>a master of the Corpus Juris Civilis, the body of Roman law assembled <lb/>under the Byzantine Emperor Justinian in the early sixth century. 55 <lb/>Blackstone's own studies at Oxford made him well acquainted with <lb/>Roman law. 56 This acquaintance primed him for cultivating his Anglican <lb/>approach to the natural law, an approach that ends up looking very much <lb/>like that of Justinian. <lb/>As noted already, the Commentaries presents the laws of England <lb/>primarily as a body of substantive law. 57 <lb/>This approach enabled <lb/>Blackstone to present the laws as a system, arranging them conceptually <lb/>by categories. 58 In this, the Commentaries resembles the Roman law <lb/>treatises of the ancient jurisconsult Gaius and of Justinian, whose <lb/>Institutes is a component of the Corpus Juris Civilis. 59 The Commentaries has <lb/>been likened to Justinian's work in both content and effect. 60 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>For an introduction to Justinian and his work, see Craig A. Stern, Justinian: Lieutenant of <lb/>Christ, Legislator for Christendom, 11 REGENT U. L. REV. 1 (1998). Helmholz has remarked <lb/>that Blackstone was perhaps one-fifth a civilian, R.H. Helmholz, Natural Law and Human <lb/>Rights in English Law: From Bracton to Blackstone, 3 AVE MARIA L. REV. 1, 5 (2005), not so <lb/>small a fraction considering how imbued Blackstone was with the common law. <lb/>See Cook, supra note 12, at 170-72. <lb/>See supra text accompanying note 18. <lb/>See Berring, supra note 16, at 191; Watson, supra note 23, at 810. It may be that Blackstone <lb/>came to this method owing to his "academic persona." Wilfrid Prest, The Religion of a <lb/>Lawyer?: William Blackstone's Anglicanism, 21 PARERGON 153, 158 (2004). <lb/>See Milsom , supra note 18, at 10-11; Watson, supra note 23, at 810 (finding the <lb/>Commentaries to be a "direct descendant of Justinian's Institutes"); see also Cairns, supra <lb/>note 54, at 320, 340, 350, 359 (finding the Commentaries to be largely an "Institutional" <lb/>work). <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 3. Others have written that Blackstone's work is <lb/>fundamentally unlike Justinian's, Berman &amp; Reid, supra note 50, at 492-96, or failed <lb/>fundamentally by forcing the content of the common law into an unwelcoming structure <lb/>from Roman law. Lobban, supra note 50, at 312, 321-23. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>335 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>Like the Commentaries, the Corpus Juris Civilis presents abstract <lb/>introductory discussions of natural law 61 and manifests its actual use of <lb/>natural law in the body of the work, the treatment of the law of Rome. <lb/>Drawing on the universal and supreme authority of natural law, Justinian <lb/>used it to support and explain Roman law. Intent on promulgating law for <lb/>the entire Roman world, Justinian hoped to justify Roman law as <lb/>universal by demonstrating that it reflected universal principles of law. Of <lb/>course, the Emperor looked to support his own legal regime, not to supply <lb/>arguments to criticize or attack it. The dignity and universal authority of <lb/>the natural law lay ready to lend dignity and universal authority to Roman <lb/>law. 62 <lb/>Beyond lending this support, the natural law helped explain the <lb/>rules of Roman law. Natural and Roman law were viewed as intertwined, <lb/>so much so that natural law was best seen through existing Roman law, <lb/>the celebrated simplicity and harmony of which derived from this <lb/>relationship. 63 As in classical Greek thought on natural law, natural law <lb/>was understood to be from the "aboriginal design of nature," but Roman <lb/>thinking also understood actual, positive Roman law to approximate the <lb/>ideal natural law, gradually conforming to it more fully. 64 Far from a <lb/>revolutionary doctrine, the Roman natural law approach encouraged <lb/>Roman lawyers to find the natural law in positive law. 65 <lb/>In actual operation, Roman natural law concerned itself with <lb/>conforming legal rules to the nature of things. 66 It sought the intrinsic <lb/>character of legal subjects, applying natural reason to the facts of the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See ALEXANDER PASSERIN D'ENTRÈVES, NATURAL LAW 24-25, 27-33 (Transaction Publishers <lb/>1994) (1951). <lb/>See id. at 23-24, 31-32. <lb/>See MAINE, supra note 24, at 60, 63-64. <lb/>64 Id. at 44-45, 60-63. <lb/>See id. at 63, 73. <lb/>66 See BARRY NICHOLAS, AN INTRODUCTION TO ROMAN LAW 57 (1962). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>336 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>matter at hand. 67 A master of both natural law theory and Roman law <lb/>likens this work to developing rules for preparing flaky piecrust. 68 <lb/>The Commentaries makes use of natural law in much the same <lb/>way. 69 Far from using natural law to trump the law of England, 70 and only <lb/>rarely using natural law to criticize English law, 71 Blackstone follows the <lb/>Roman natural law tradition in explaining why English law is as it is. 72 <lb/>This use is in keeping with Blackstone's practical rather than theoretical <lb/>bent. 73 Like the natural law of the Roman lawyer, 74 Blackstone's natural <lb/>law unites is with ought, seeking norms from the nature of things, 75 but <lb/>with more warrant. 76 <lb/>A good example of this technique is offered by Blackstone's <lb/>explanation of the law of property. As Professor Graham has explained, <lb/>the Commentaries does not present irrational support of old ways but <lb/>rather a studied focus on the physical nature of things. 77 From nature and <lb/>the natural order in physical context, for example, Blackstone evolves a <lb/>"natural history" of property to rationalize English property law. 78 . <lb/>Natural law inheres in the nature of things, and the law of England, like <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See id. <lb/>See D'ENTRÈVES, supra note 61, at 148; see also McKnight, supra note 2, at 406 n.67 (agreeing <lb/>with Maine on the somewhat utilitarian cast of Roman natural law). <lb/>Although it may be that Blackstone never explicitly asserted that one could discover the <lb/>law of nature from English law, or vice versa. McKnight, supra note 2, at 403 n.33. At <lb/>least one commentator has written that the common-law tradition reflects the notion that <lb/>innate reason has led the positive law to hold within itself the natural law. Lobban, supra <lb/>note 50, at 314. Similar to this link is the one Blackstone approvingly found to be advanced <lb/>by Aristotle: learning positive law is a good way to learn ethics. See Conklin, supra note 23, <lb/>at 205. <lb/>See LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 49-55. <lb/>71 See id. at 46. <lb/>See Langbein, supra note 14, at 77. <lb/>See PREST, supra note 1, at 310; see also Posner, supra note 45, at 576 (pronouncing <lb/>Blackstone "better at particulars than at generalization"). <lb/>See D'ENTRÈVES, supra note 61, at 151. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 60. One commentator has tagged Blackstone a "natural law <lb/>maverick" for constructing a "pastiche" of natural law and his own views. McKnight, <lb/>supra note 2, at 407. Perhaps the link of is with ought in his romanesque approach invites <lb/>such criticism. <lb/>See infra notes 290-97 and accompanying text. <lb/>Nicole Graham, Restoring the "Real" to Real Property Law: A Return to Blackstone?, in <lb/>BLACKSTONE AND HIS COMMENTARIES, supra note 14, at 151. <lb/>See id. at 154-55, 160. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>337 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/>Roman law, developed in light of this natural law. 79 <lb/></note>

			<body>The Commentaries holds many instances where Blackstone <lb/>explicitly explains that English law is true to the nature of things -<lb/>sometimes presented as fulfilling the obligation of the law to reflect <lb/>"necessity." This, after he notes that the law of nature inheres in the <lb/>nature of things, 80 and that sound Roman laws took "the nature of things <lb/>for their guide." 81 Some examples: Blackstone establishes the obligation <lb/>of allegiance to civil government upon the nature of civil government. 82 <lb/>The legal relationship between husband and wife is founded in nature. 83 <lb/>Necessity has given rise to the law of property, 84 and laws on personal <lb/>property take into account their transitory nature. 85 The laws of civil <lb/>wrongs derive in several respects from the nature of things, often human <lb/>nature, 86 and criminal laws likewise derive from the nature of things or <lb/>reflect the nature of things. 87 In these instances, Blackstone seems to <lb/>hark back to the Roman law, rooted as it was in the nature of things. <lb/>Roman law makes its appearance in the Commentaries in at least <lb/>two other general ways that support Blackstone's Anglican approach to <lb/>the law. First is its concept of the jus gentium, the law of nations. If the <lb/>natural law truly is universal, one would expect it -or projections from it <lb/>-to be found in the laws of all nations. The law of nations, understood as <lb/>the body of laws to be found widespread among the nations of the earth, <lb/>therefore becomes a window on natural law, as the Romans believed. 88 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>The Commentaries suggests that natural law inheres in the nature of things in such <lb/>language as, "when the supreme being formed the universe, and created matter out <lb/>of nothing, he impressed certain principles upon that matter, from which it can never <lb/>depart, and without which it would cease to be." 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 38. If <lb/>Blackstone tags the law of property as governing things indifferent, see infra note 152 and <lb/>accompanying text, he does not thereby hold that property law is wholly without natural <lb/>law principles. See infra notes 309-12 and accompanying text. <lb/>See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 40. <lb/>81 See id. at 58. <lb/>Id. at 354, 358. <lb/>See id. at 410. <lb/>See 2 id. at 4, 7. <lb/>See 3 id. at 146. <lb/>See id. at 4, 22, 116, 379, 434. <lb/>See 4 id. at 20-21, 27, 74, 186, 216. <lb/>See D'ENTRÈVES, supra note 61, at 32-33; MAINE, supra note 24, at 46; NICHOLAS, supra note <lb/>66, at 55. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>338 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>This value of the jus gentium is evident in Blackstone's use of <lb/>comparative law. He looks to law outside England not so much to <lb/>disparage non-English law as to find points of commonality. Those <lb/>points support English law by suggesting that it rests upon natural law <lb/>foundations. 89 A similar cast in Anglican theology could therefore offer a <lb/>link and support to Blackstone's approach to the law. <lb/>Beyond its content, another aspect of Roman law that influenced <lb/>the Commentaries and would harmonize well with an Anglican <lb/>understanding of the law is the process of the development of Roman law. <lb/>Roman law developed over hundreds of years, largely case by case. 90 In <lb/>this respect, its development paralleled that of English common law. <lb/>While Roman law came to repose nearly exclusively in the Corpus Juris <lb/>Civilis, 91 English law rejected such codification in favor of its commitment <lb/>to the method by which Roman law developed. 92 Some have noted that <lb/>Blackstone took the view of a practicing lawyer and judge in the <lb/>Commentaries, 93 and though it was famously said that, "In England less <lb/>attention is paid to natural law than anywhere else in the world," 94 <lb/>Blackstone used natural law arguments successfully at the bar. 95 The <lb/>common law -the law of cases -required barristers and judges to <lb/>consider cases with an eye to their context. This technique largely <lb/>provided the materials Blackstone assembled in the Commentaries. It is a <lb/>technique that befits the Anglican way, a technique that developed law <lb/>that itself befits the Anglican way. It also was the way of Roman lawyers. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See infra notes 279-89 and accompanying text. <lb/>See NICHOLAS, supra note 66, at 28-32. <lb/>91 See 2 EDWARD GIBBON, THE DECLINE AND FALL OF THE ROMAN EMPIRE 80 (Encyclopaedia <lb/>Britannica Inc. 1952) (1788). <lb/>See 2 FREDERICK POLLOCK &amp; FREDERIC WILLIAM MAITLAND, THE HISTORY OF ENGLISH LAW <lb/>BEFORE THE TIME OF EDWARD I 585 (Liberty Fund, Inc. 2010) (1898). So the English were <lb/>"more Roman than the Romanists," those who received as authority the Corpus Juris Civilis <lb/>rather than adhering to the method by which Roman law developed. Id. at 705. <lb/>See Berman &amp; Reid, supra note 50, at 503. But see infra note 235. <lb/>Helmholz , supra note 55, at 20; see also D'ENTRÈVES, supra note 61, at 119 n.1. <lb/>McKnight, supra note 2, at 407-09. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>339 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>If common law judges in deciding cases were making law up, they were <lb/>making it up to fit. 96 <lb/>Blackstone, student of Roman law, reflected a Roman law approach <lb/>to the natural law in the Commentaries. Beginning, like the Digest and <lb/>Institutes of the Corpus Juris Civilis, with an abstract exposition of natural <lb/>law and related formulations, the body of the Commentaries puts natural <lb/>law most to use in explaining and justifying particular rules of law. <lb/>Seeking the dictates of reason and the guide of reasonableness, <lb/>Blackstone rests rules of law upon the nature of the matter at hand -a <lb/>typically Roman technique. In this and other respects, Blackstone's use of <lb/>natural law fits well with the Anglican stance on natural law that he <lb/>adopts in the Commentaries. <lb/>4. BLACKSTONE AND THE CHURCH OF ENGLAND <lb/>No surprise that Sir William Blackstone, Oxford don, justice of both the <lb/>King's Bench and Common Pleas, was an Anglican. What may surprise is <lb/>how serious an Anglican Blackstone was, and how deeply his Anglicanism <lb/>influenced the jurisprudence of his Commentaries. <lb/>Blackstone's deep and pervasive Christian faith was manifest. 97 As <lb/>a young man he took a serious interest in religion, 98 and made a careful <lb/>investigation <lb/>of <lb/>Anglicanism 99 <lb/>before <lb/>committing <lb/>himself <lb/>wholeheartedly to orthodox Anglicanism. 100 <lb/>He celebrated his <lb/>commitment in a poem, a vision of diverse faiths in which he praised the <lb/>Church of England for its moderation, liberty, support of science, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See Milsom, supra note 18, at 11-12. Milsom here speaks of fit according to patterns of legal <lb/>rules, but the notion of judges in a sense creating rules that at the same time are seen as <lb/>compelled by antecedent norms is apropos. <lb/>See Cook, supra note 12, at 169. <lb/>See Prest, supra note 58, at 163. <lb/>See Cook, supra note 12, at 174. <lb/>100 See PREST, supra note 1, at 309; Prest, supra note 3, at 123; Prest, supra note 58, at 161. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>340 <lb/></page>

		    <note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>reforming influence, and virtue. 101 Although a committed Anglican, <lb/>Blackstone was not so committed that he could brook no Dissenters, 102 <lb/>going so far as to alter the Commentaries in light of Dissenter reaction to <lb/>an earlier edition of the work. 103 The general Anglican understanding of <lb/>providential development from primitive sources 104 and the important <lb/>role reason plays in perceiving truth 105 would support Blackstone's <lb/>construction of the Commentaries. <lb/>The substantial alignments between Anglican theology and the <lb/>Commentaries are the focus of the next pages of this article. <lb/>4.1. RICHARD HOOKER <lb/>Key to the Church of England is the work of the Elizabethan divine, <lb/>Richard Hooker. 106 Beyond helping to shape the contours of Anglicanism <lb/>as a whole, Hooker's influence on legal theory was especially <lb/>pronounced. 107 <lb/>Blackstone's Anglican understanding of the law <lb/>necessarily reflects Hooker's understanding. <lb/>Hooker held law in high esteem: <lb/>[O]f Law there can be no less acknowledged, than that her seat is <lb/>the bosom of God, her voice the harmony of the world: all things <lb/>in heaven and in earth do her homage, the very least as feeling <lb/>her care, and the greatest as not exempted from her power: both <lb/>Angels and men and creatures of what condition soever, though <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See WILLIAM BLACKSTONE, THE PANTHEON 27-32 (photo. reprint, Gale ECCO Print Editions <lb/>2010) (1747). Prest has called Blackstone a "comparative theologian." Prest, supra note 3, <lb/>at 110. <lb/>See Prest, supra note 58, at 153, 165-66. <lb/>See id. at 155-56. <lb/>104 See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 74-75. <lb/>See Raymond D. Tumbleson, "Reason and Religion": The Science of Anglicanism, 57 J. HIST. <lb/>IDEAS 131, 133, 151 (1996). <lb/>106 See NIGEL ATKINSON, RICHARD HOOKER AND THE AUTHORITY OF SCRIPTURE, TRADITION AND <lb/>REASON, at ix (1997). Though such, his work earned surprising approval from the leader of <lb/>the Roman Catholic Church. See RUSSELL KIRK, THE ROOTS OF AMERICAN ORDER 246 (1974). <lb/>Harold Berman highlights Hooker's influence as to political authority and consent, <lb/>the importance of history, and the large role played by matters indifferent-those not <lb/>determined by transcendent sources of law. See Harold J. Berman, The Origins of Historical <lb/>Jurisprudence: Coke, Selden, Hale, 103 YALE L.J. 1651, 1665-66 (1994). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>341 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>each in different sort and manner, yet all with uniform consent, <lb/>admiring her as the mother of their peace and joy. 108 <lb/>Law for Hooker is fundamental. 109 Furthermore, his treatment of law is <lb/>no incidental matter but derives from his theology. 110 Law, as one might <lb/>gather from the excerpt just quoted, reigns over politics. In this, Hooker <lb/>departs from an Aristotelian view, 111 and follows, as elsewhere, the <lb/>magisterial reformers rather than Augustine or Aquinas. 112 <lb/>Hooker goes so far as to hold that God himself works according to <lb/>law, 113 and for at least one commentator, Hooker holds that God is law. 114 A <lb/>famous apothegm of Hooker states that "the being of God is a kind of law <lb/>to his working." 115 <lb/>In some respects, Hooker's general discussion of the fundamental <lb/>types of law adumbrates that of Blackstone. Hooker explains that, in his <lb/>usage, both the law of nature and divine law reveal eternal law to <lb/>humankind. 116 At the same time, however, Hooker holds divine law to be <lb/>positive law, a creature of God's reason and will both, whereas for <lb/>Blackstone it is simply a revelation of the law of nature. 117 Likewise, <lb/>Hooker sees some human law as an adaptation of natural law, and other <lb/>human law as an ordinance "merely human," reasonable and convenient <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>108 1 RICHARD HOOKER, OF THE LAWS OF ECCLESIASTICAL POLITY 232 (J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd. 1907) <lb/>(1594, 1597). <lb/>109 See W.J. TORRANCE KIRBY, RICHARD HOOKER, REFORMER AND PLATONIST 48 (2005). "Perhaps <lb/>the most influential Anglican thinker to make explicit use of natural law is the Elizabethan <lb/>divine, Richard Hooker . . . ." Will Adam, Natural Law in the Anglican Tradition, in <lb/>CHRISTIANITY AND NATURAL LAW 58, 63 (Norman Doe ed., 2017). <lb/>See id. at 55. <lb/>111 See ROBERT K. FAULKNER, RICHARD HOOKER AND THE POLITICS OF A CHRISTIAN ENGLAND 114-16 <lb/>(1981). <lb/>See KIRBY, supra note 109, at 52, 58-78. <lb/>See W.J. Torrance Kirby, Reason and Law, in A COMPANION TO RICHARD HOOKER 251, 253, 255 <lb/>(Torrance Kirby ed., 2008). <lb/>See KIRBY, supra note 109, at 51; Kirby, supra note 113, at 251. <lb/>1 HOOKER, supra note 108, at 150. <lb/>See Kirby, supra note 113, at 265. Elsewhere, Kirby notes that the question of Hooker's <lb/>doctrine of natural law is controversial. See KIRBY, supra note 109, at 57. <lb/>See L.S. THORNTON, RICHARD HOOKER 32, 107 (1924). In this context Hooker calls law <lb/>"positive" if express revelation is necessary to know it. 1 HOOKER, supra note 108, at 220 <lb/>n.1. Also, apparently unlike Blackstone, Hooker observes that the evidence of the senses <lb/>is clear and strong while that of revelation is complicated and complex. THORNTON, supra, <lb/>at 16. At the same time, however, the object held out in the Scriptures is more certain than <lb/>that in the senses. Id. at 18. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>342 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>for the time and place. 118 A similar formulation of human law will find its <lb/>way into the Commentaries. 119 <lb/>The line from Hooker to Blackstone is more clearly traced along <lb/>particular elements to be found in the works of both. One is the role of <lb/>human reason in the development of law. 120 Like other Reformation <lb/>theologians, Hooker asserts that Scripture and reason both convey to <lb/>humans the knowledge of God and of his eternal law. 121 "It was part of <lb/>God's nature to work in an orderly and reasonable way . . . ." 122 <lb/>Consequently, "God's own creation also worked in an orderly and <lb/>reasonable way," 123 a way ruled by law. God acts to accomplish his <lb/>"rational purpose." 124 So for Hooker, the appeal to reason becomes <lb/>key. 125 The law of reason is for all humans, 126 endowed as they are with "a <lb/>natural practical wisdom." 127 Humans find themselves ruled by the law of <lb/>reason, divine law, and human law 128 -the last resting upon rational <lb/>human nature 129 and either resolving "probable matters" or "clarify[ing] <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>NIGEL VOAK, RICHARD HOOKER AND REFORMED THEOLOGY 117 (2003); see also FAULKNER, supra <lb/>note 111, at 114 (reading Hooker to state that human law is discovered naturally, but <lb/>that the authority to do so is from God); Rowan Williams, Foreword: Of the Lawes of <lb/>Ecclesiastical Politie Revisited, in A COMPANION TO RICHARD HOOKER, supra note 113, at xv, <lb/>xviii-xix (distinguishing in Hooker laws for humanity from laws for particular societies, <lb/>with both legitimate and binding). <lb/>See infra notes 305-12 and accompanying text. Also finding its way into the Commentaries <lb/>is Hooker's usage of the term lex gentium to mean international law rather than something <lb/>like the Roman usage of jus gentium discussed above at notes 88 to 89. Finnis, supra note <lb/>24, at 177. <lb/>120 Of course, some role for human reason is found in standard views on the making of law, <lb/>with perhaps the classic being that of Aquinas. See, e.g., supra note 43. Nevertheless, the <lb/>uses to which Hooker and Blackstone put reason bear a special affinity, as discussed below. <lb/>See infra notes 305-12 and accompanying text. <lb/>See KIRBY, supra note 109, at 74; see also KIRK, supra note 106, at 243. <lb/>ATKINSON, supra note 106, at 13. <lb/>Id. <lb/>124 KIRBY, supra note 109, at 51. <lb/>See THORNTON, supra note 117, at 13; see also Adam, supra note 109, at 63 (Hooker "often <lb/>uses the term 'law of reason' as synonymous with 'natural law'"), 73 (Hooker took "the <lb/>explicit doctrine of natural law of the Thomistic tradition and repackaged it as the law of <lb/>reason"), 76 ("The concept of natural law, and its derivative-the law of reason, played a <lb/>central role in the thought of Richard Hooker . . . ."). <lb/>126 See FAULKNER, supra note 11, at 63, 72. <lb/>KIRBY, supra note 109, at 55. And reason shows the good, THORNTON, supra note 117, at <lb/>37, presumably the key to the happiness all humans seek. See KIRBY, supra note 109, at <lb/>75; THORNTON, supra note 117, at 38. This idea too finds its way into Blackstone. See supra <lb/>notes 28-31 and accompanying text. <lb/>See ATKINSON, supra note 106, at 14. <lb/>129 See THORNTON, supra note 117, at 36-37. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>343 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>and enforc[ing] the necessary precepts of reason." 130 The authority <lb/>Hooker grants to human reason, a touchstone of Anglicanism, holds sway <lb/>in the Commentaries, as shall appear. 131 <lb/>A second major influence of Hooker upon Blackstone is his <lb/>endorsement of the authority of custom. Against the Puritan threat of <lb/>"singularity," lack of consensus, 132 Hooker counterpoised consent, 133 a <lb/>distant consent presumed to continue. 134 Custom, modified appropriately <lb/>by customarily legitimate written law, is authoritative and likely to induce <lb/>obedience. 135 This appreciation for custom fits well with Hooker's view <lb/>that God teaches through human experience. 136 <lb/>It also supports <lb/>Blackstone's hailing custom as the common law, a move that enabled him <lb/>to capture the advantages of both primitive sources and traditional <lb/>developments. 137 <lb/>Third is the related matter of Hooker's use of history. For Hooker, <lb/>Scripture supports the value of experience. 138 Joined with his notion that <lb/>God delivers law providentially, 139 these views support Hooker's position <lb/>that attaining truth is a gradual affair played out in history. 140 Humans may <lb/>make laws, but in a sense those laws are God's as he works his providential <lb/>will. 141 History as the unfolding of gradual development 142 is normative <lb/>for Hooker. 143 Consequently, Harold Berman has found in Hooker a key to <lb/>English historical jurisprudence and its continuing influence 144 as well as <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>FAULKNER, supra note 111, at 115. <lb/>131 See infra notes 305-12 and accompanying text. <lb/>ATKINSON, supra note 106, at 50. <lb/>See FAULKNER, supra note 111, at 103, 111. <lb/>See id. at 112. <lb/>See 1 HOOKER, supra note 108, at 422; see also ATKINSON, supra note 106, at 55; KIRK, supra <lb/>note 106, at 244. <lb/>See KIRK, supra note 106, at 244-45; Williams, supra note 118, at xix. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 73. <lb/>See THORNTON, supra note 117, at 17. <lb/>See FAULKNER, supra note 111, at 114. <lb/>See THORNTON, supra note 117, at 45-46. <lb/>See id. at 37. Such a commitment to historical development, adapted to local conditions, <lb/>lies at the core of Hooker's chief aim-to explain and defend the ecclesiastical polity of <lb/>the Church of England. See ATKINSON, supra note 106, at 58. <lb/>See ATKINSON, supra note 106, at 47. <lb/>See id. at 54. <lb/>Berman, supra note 107, at 1664-66. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>344 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>an emphasis on historical continuity. 145 For Blackstone, history is the key <lb/>to understanding English law. 146 <lb/>The last marked influence of Hooker on Blackstone is the <lb/>importance of the concept of things indifferent, matters not conclusively <lb/>ordained by transcendent law but rather left more to human <lb/>determination. 147 Positive laws may resolve matters that God leaves to <lb/>human liberty. 148 So, while some human laws are based upon natural <lb/>law, 149 its necessary tenets are few, leaving most matters to public <lb/>authority. 150 Blackstone takes a similar tack 151 : Daniel Boorstin has <lb/>discussed the remarkable degree to which Blackstone holds that private <lb/>property itself is a creature of civil law. 152 Crimes not mala in se but rather <lb/>those "with regard to things in themselves indifferent . . . become either <lb/>right or wrong, just or unjust, duties or misdemeanors, according as the <lb/>municipal legislator sees proper." 153 "Lands are not naturally descendible <lb/>any more than thrones: but the law has thought proper, for the benefit <lb/>and peace of the public, to establish hereditary succession in one as well <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See id. at 1666. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 36; LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 42; Conklin, supra note 23, <lb/>at 218. Lobban finds in Blackstone a commitment to authority and history over deductive <lb/>reasoning, see Lobban, supra note 50, at 328, and views the Commentaries as intertwining <lb/>theory with history. Id. at 330. And Boorstin finds a telling example of Blackstone's <lb/>commitment to history in his treatment of the Revolution of 1688. BOORSTIN, supra note 1, <lb/>at 26. <lb/>See ATKINSON, supra note 106, at 59-60. <lb/>See 2 HOOKER, supra note 108, at 363. <lb/>THORNTON, supra note 117, at 32. <lb/>See FAULKNER, supra note 111, at 113; see also id. at 100 (observing that, after the law <lb/>of reason, human law holds prominence for Hooker), 112 (observing that, once natural <lb/>necessity calls for a rule, nearly any rule will do). <lb/>151 While for Blackstone "indifferent" can mean diverse things, Finnis, supra note 24, <lb/>at 172-73, Blackstone imitates Hooker on biblical law, for example, acceding to its <lb/>authority but finding its still-obligatory moral law pertinent to very few issues. See <lb/>D. SEABORN DAVIES, THE BIBLE IN ENGLISH LAW 20 (1954). As to one such instance, it is <lb/>both intriguing and relevant to note that Blackstone observes that blood guilt-a concept <lb/>harking back to biblical standards-would adhere to Parliament were it to over-extend <lb/>capital punishment. 4 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 11. The Bible also speaks specifically <lb/>of blood guilt for over-extension of capital punishment. See DEUTERONOMY 19:4-10. See <lb/>generally Craig A. Stern, Torah and Murder: The Cities of Refuge and Anglo-American Law, <lb/>35 VAL. U. L. REV. 461 (2001) (demonstrating the influence of the biblical law of homicide <lb/>upon the Anglo-American law of homicide). <lb/>BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 170-74, 179-80. See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 185; 2 Id. at <lb/>2, 210-11, 491 for pertinent passages from the Commentaries. <lb/>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 55. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>345 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>as the other." 154 Regarding the jurisdiction of courts, "[e]very nation <lb/>must and will abide by it's [sic] own municipal laws; which various <lb/>accidents conspire to render different in almost every country in <lb/>Europe." 155 Apart from these specific observations regarding indifferent <lb/>matters, Blackstone's chief use of natural law paradoxically guides the <lb/>resolution of matters that, in a sense, are indifferent. 156 More on this use <lb/>later. 157 <lb/>The teaching of Hooker was not lost on the English legal theorists <lb/>that followed. Edward Coke viewed the law as reason in history -reason <lb/>in the sense of reasonable, not rationalistic -and understood that <lb/>natural law was incorporated into human law. 158 Even more than Coke, <lb/>Matthew Hale especially influenced Blackstone in the Commentaries. 159 <lb/>Like Hooker, Hale saw natural law and divine law as authoritative but also <lb/>as speaking only to a limited set of questions. 160 <lb/>Likewise, Hale <lb/>understood history as providence, 161 with positive law accordingly <lb/>developed through time. 162 This historical focus finds its way from Hale <lb/>into the Commentaries. 163 Also, both Hale's locating reason within a <lb/>particular object (in addition to its being a human faculty) and his debt to <lb/>natural science and empiricism 164 seem reflected in the Commentaries. 165 <lb/>The Anglicanism of Hooker, Coke, and Hale, and their emphasis on <lb/>reason and history alongside the authority of natural law and Holy Writ, <lb/>are to be seen in Blackstone's Commentaries. An even clearer influence on <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Id. at 185. <lb/>3 id. at 87. <lb/>So, as for Hooker, such human law is "grounded upon the Word," 1 HOOKER, supra note <lb/>108, at 309, but not dictated by it. <lb/>See infra notes 305-12 and accompanying text. <lb/>See Berman, supra note 107, at 1690-93. <lb/>See Berman &amp; Reid, supra note 50, at 443, 489-94; Cairns, supra note 54, at 340, 352; <lb/>Finnis, supra note 24, at 164-65; Watson, supra note 23, at 810-12. <lb/>See Berman, supra note 107, at 1709. <lb/>See id. at 1722. <lb/>See id. at 1708, 1711-14. <lb/>See id. at 1733. <lb/>See id. at 1715, 1729. <lb/>See infra notes 241-46, 291-93 and accompanying text. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>346 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>Blackstone, however, is Anglican thought closer to his own time. It is to <lb/>that thought that we now turn. <lb/>4.2. THE LATITUDINARIANS <lb/>The Anglican Church faced the Age of Reason and Deism with <lb/>Latitudinarianism. 166 <lb/>Though standing in opposition to those two <lb/>developments, the Latitudinarians, as their name implies, embraced <lb/>tolerance as their major theme. 167 This theme in no way compromised <lb/>their commitment to God and the Christian faith. The Latitudinarians <lb/>believed that God holds an absolute claim on humanity and that all our <lb/>powers depend upon his will. 168 Christianity is to govern all of life. 169 <lb/>Education for moral and spiritual reformation is especially important. 170 <lb/>With these tenets Latitudinarianism was a major force in seventeenth <lb/>century Anglicanism. <lb/>It also was in important respects a movement in continuity with <lb/>the work of Hooker, a continuity that would support the work of <lb/>Blackstone. The Latitudinarians in their tolerance relied upon Hooker's <lb/>emphasis on things indifferent. 171 <lb/>They also shared Hooker's <lb/>endorsement of strong laws. 172 <lb/>Beyond these particulars, the most important influence of <lb/>Latitudinarianism to be seen in the Commentaries, and well within the <lb/>trajectory Hooker set for the Anglican Church, was its appreciation for <lb/>reason as a guide in human affairs. Latitudinarian thought was well <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See W. M. SPELLMAN, THE LATITUDINARIANS AND THE CHURCH OF ENGLAND 1600-1700 10-83 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>See ERNEST CAMPELL MOSSNER, BISHOP BUTLER AND THE AGE OF REASON: A STUDY IN THE <lb/>HISTORY OF THOUGHT (1936). <lb/>See SPELLMAN, supra note 166, at 120. <lb/>See id. at 7. <lb/>See id. at 4, 61, 128. <lb/>171 See id. at 157. <lb/>See id. at 70. Other Latitudinarian notions to find their way into the Commentaries are the <lb/>endorsement of strong civil government, id. at 122, and self-interest as sound motivation, <lb/>see id. at 118-19, 122. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>347 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>suited to the development of science 173 : it is no accident that Isaac <lb/>Newton was an Anglican. 174 The Latitudinarians understood that human <lb/>reason did not survive the Fall unimpaired. 175 At the same time, however, <lb/>some power of human reason persists. 176 Human reason under God is able <lb/>to understand nature, itself existing under the Sovereign God. 177 This <lb/>human reason is not the reason of rationalism, but instead more like <lb/>common sense. 178 And just as reason is an aid to understanding the <lb/>Bible, 179 so is the Bible a necessary aid to the use of reason. 180 <lb/>Latitudinarians favored reason and the philosophical explanation of <lb/>reality, 181 but more important to Blackstone's jurisprudence was their <lb/>view that reason was useful especially for discerning natural law. 182 <lb/>One who could be viewed as the leading exponent of <lb/>Latitudinarianism in the next century, the century of Blackstone, is <lb/>Bishop Joseph Butler. 183 Butler published his most important work, The <lb/>Analogy of Religion Natural and Revealed, in 1736 and it became hugely <lb/>influential in the middle of the century during the height of Blackstone's <lb/>career and the writing of the Commentaries. 184 Relying on the same <lb/>principles that served Hooker, 185 Butler aimed to refute the deists on the <lb/>grounds of natural theology. 186 <lb/>As Blackstone would argue, 187 the <lb/></body>
		
		<listBibl>See James R. Jacob &amp; Margaret C. Jacob, The Anglican Origins of Modern Science: The <lb/>Metaphysical Foundations of the Whig Constitution, 71 ISIS 251, 258 (1980); SPELLMAN, supra <lb/>note 166, at 6-7. <lb/>See Jacob &amp; Jacob, supra note 173, at 254, 262, 265. The Anglican mix of authority from the <lb/>

			Bible, reason, and the senses-a mix hospitable to science-is one of its distinctives. See <lb/>id. at 256; Tumbleson, supra note 105, at 134-35, 139, 148, 151-53, 156. <lb/>SPELLMAN, supra note 166, at 111. <lb/>See id. at 74-77. <lb/>See id. at 87-88, 160. <lb/>See id. at 4. <lb/>See id. at 156. <lb/>See id. at 83-86. <lb/>See id. at 106-07. <lb/>See id. at 8, 66, 76-77, 81-82. The association of reason with natural law is typically <lb/>English. Helmholz, supra note 55, at 12, 21. <lb/>See Conklin, supra note 23, at 213. <lb/>See MOSSNER, supra note 167, at 178-87. <lb/>See THORNTON, supra note 117, at 103. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 15. The project of natural theology itself received impetus <lb/>from Hooker. See Kirby, supra note 113, at 270-71. Butler also aligned himself with the <lb/>empiricism of Locke and Newton. MOSSNER, supra note 167, at 82. <lb/>See supra notes 24-27 and accompanying text. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>348 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>creature owes a duty to the creator, and design proves a designer. 188 <lb/>Likewise, general laws govern nature, 189 with the nature of things giving <lb/>rise to right and wrong, thus determining God's will. 190 Humans are able <lb/>to discover their duties through reason -more the reasonable dictate of <lb/>God's will than the deliverances of logic. 191 Blackstone would also endorse <lb/>Butler's view of civil government as an agency of God's government <lb/>concerned with social consequences. 192 <lb/>Two major aspects of Butler's theology to lodge in the Commentaries <lb/>command attention here. The first is emphasis on experience. We have <lb/>noted Butler's emphasis on reason, that is on reasonableness more than <lb/>cold logic. 193 Nevertheless, humankind cannot by speculation judge what <lb/>leads to human perfection or happiness. 194 Hooker had held that the degree <lb/>of certainty we attain is relative to the nature of things. 195 Like him, Butler <lb/>held that we should not expect to plumb the depths of all knowledge and <lb/>understanding, but rather follow the light we do have. 196 <lb/>That light largely is the product of experience. The laws by which <lb/>God governs are known to us by reason along with experience. 197 As <lb/>science and medicine developed by progressive advances, 198 so ethics <lb/>depends upon empirical evidence and common sense, and morality itself <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See JOSEPH BUTLER, THE ANALOGY OF RELIGION NATURAL AND REVEALED 245 (J.M. Dent &amp; Co. <lb/>1906) (1736). <lb/>See id. at 105. <lb/>See id. at 243. So, for those designed for society God's laws prescribe justice and charity. <lb/>Id. at 245. <lb/>See MOSSNER, supra note 167, at 14. Butler did not suppose that all elements of moral <lb/>government are clear to humans. Id. at 90. Mossner also discerns some sleight of hand in <lb/>Butler's treatment of the matter of law and will. Id. at 102. <lb/>Compare 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 45, 54, with BUTLER, supra note 188, at 37-38, 41, <lb/>98. <lb/>See supra text accompanying note 191. Again, this emphasis reminds one of Hooker, <lb/>ATKINSON, supra note 106, at 13, as does Butler's division of the precepts of religion into <lb/>moral and positive according as the reasons for the precept are seen or not seen, MOSSNER, <lb/>supra note 167, at 92, and the acknowledgement that reason needs support from God's <lb/>inspiration, id. at 123-24. <lb/>See BUTLER, supra note 188, at xxx. <lb/>See ATKINSON, supra note 106, at 91-92, 98. <lb/>JOSEPH BUTLER, FIFTEEN SERMONS PREACHED AT THE ROLLS CHAPEL AND A DISSERTATION UPON <lb/>THE NATURE OF VIRTUE 237-38 (G. Bell Sons 1914) (1726). <lb/>See BUTLER, supra note 188, at 143. <lb/>See id. at 152-53. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>349 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>is a science of human action with attention paid to the facts of results. 199 <lb/>God uses our experience to teach us duties. 200 As with physics, so with <lb/>human laws, experiment, inductive method, and judgment based upon <lb/>the generality of observations are sound guides. 201 Experience, resting <lb/>upon God's governance by punishment and reward, 202 is a surer guide <lb/>than abstract reason. 203 <lb/>Blackstone suited the Commentaries to his readers, enlightened <lb/>eighteenth-century Anglicans. 204 He himself was committed to English <lb/>enlightenment principles 205 and Butler's welcome to progress, <lb/>knowledge, and experience 206 suited Blackstone well. Like Edmund <lb/>Burke, 207 Blackstone embraced Latitudinarianism and the work of Joseph <lb/>Butler. 208 He subscribed to the test of probability rather than certainty, 209 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See MOSSNER, supra note 167, at 105, 117. <lb/>See id. at 96. <lb/>See BUTLER, supra note 188, at xviii, xxx, 79. <lb/>See id. at 25, 180. <lb/>See id. at 104, 143-44, 148. As Blackstone would remark regarding the changing of human <lb/>laws, see infra notes 272-78 and accompanying text, Butler observed that we hazard <lb/>unknown effects by changing the regime God has instituted for his rule. See BUTLER, supra <lb/>note 188, at 101, 106, 108-09. With the results yet to be experienced, we cannot assess the <lb/>outcome of such a move. <lb/>See Crane Brinton, Book Review, 55 HARV. L. REV. 703, 703 (1942) (reviewing The Mysterious <lb/>Science of the Law: An Essay on Blackstone's Commentaries (1941)). <lb/>See PREST, supra note 1, at 308; Graham, supra note 77, at 152; Tim Stretton, Coverture and <lb/>Unity of Person in Blackstone's Commentaries, in BLACKSTONE AND HIS COMMENTARIES, supra <lb/>note 14, at 111, 125. <lb/>See BUTLER, supra note 188, at 162. <lb/>See MOSSNER, supra note 167, at 189. <lb/>See Conklin, supra note 23, at 213-15. Conklin points out especially the affinity in <lb/>epistemology and the role of happiness. <lb/>See Blackstone's probabilism here, for example: "But this [move of the Restoration <lb/>Parliament] was for the necessity of the thing, which supersedes all law; for if they had <lb/>not so met, it was morally impossible that the kingdom should have been settled in peace." <lb/>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 147 (emphasis added). And here: "So that it is morally <lb/>impossible to trace out, with any degree of accuracy, when the several mutations of the <lb/>common law were made . . . ." 4 id. at 402 (first emphasis added). The probabilism in <lb/>this use of "morally impossible" finds an explanation from Blackstone's contemporary, <lb/>Samuel Johnson: <lb/>He thus defined the difference between physical and moral truth: <lb/>"Physical truth is, when you tell a thing as it actually is. Moral truth <lb/>is, when you tell a thing sincerely and precisely as it appears to you. <lb/>I say such a one walked across the street; if he really did so, I told a <lb/>physical truth. If I thought so, though I should have been mistaken, I <lb/>told a moral truth." <lb/>JAMES BOSWELL, THE LIFE OF SAMUEL JOHNSON 510-11 (C.P. Chadsey ed., Doubleday 1946) <lb/>(1791). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>350 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>reasonableness as a touchstone of truth, 210 and common sense coupled <lb/>with experience. 211 The large role in the Commentaries played by history <lb/>may be ascribed, at least in part, to this regard for experience. 212 <lb/>A second aspect of Butler's theology that helped shape the <lb/>Commentaries is the importance and function of human happiness. 213 God <lb/>governs mankind by reward, by the consequences of human actions. 214 <lb/>Therefore, true happiness directs us towards doing God's will. 215 This <lb/>happiness (supplemented by conscience 216 ) defies certain demonstration, <lb/>but does make itself known with "practical proof." 217 To pursue virtue is <lb/>to pursue happiness, and to pursue happiness is to pursue virtue. 218 <lb/>Again, Blackstone concurs with Butler in his argument that God has <lb/>ordered human affairs so that we need only pursue our own happiness to <lb/>find ourselves pursuing the law of nature that God has established for the <lb/>right ordering of our affairs. 219 For both Butler and Blackstone, reasonable <lb/>self-love motivates us to adhere to God's rule. 220 So here too, Blackstone <lb/>shows himself in the Commentaries aligning with the work of Butler as he <lb/>aligns with other elements of the Anglican tradition. <lb/>Blackstone had every reason to write the Commentaries from an <lb/>Anglican point of view. It was good rhetoric for reaching his intended <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 23. <lb/>211 See id. 55, 117-19. In these last commitments, Blackstone owed a debt also to Locke, id. at <lb/>31, and the Common Sense school of philosophy, Conklin, supra note 23, at 216-17. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 31-40, 55. <lb/>Blackstone's crucial use of happiness has been noted already in these pages. See supra <lb/>notes 29-31 and accompanying text. <lb/>See BUTLER, supra note 188, at 93, 238. <lb/>See id. at 26, 236, 271. <lb/>See BUTLER, supra note 196, at 68. <lb/>MOSSNER, supra note 167, at 100. So probabilism is the method for pursuing happiness. See <lb/>BUTLER, supra note 188, at xxv-xxvii. <lb/>See Butler, supra note 188, at xxx, 36, 56, 61, 72, 93, 112, 268-70; BUTLER, supra note 196, at <lb/>240. At the same time, God has given us some power over the happiness of others. BUTLER, <lb/>supra note 188, at 42. <lb/>See supra notes 29-31 and accompanying text; see also BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 92; <lb/>Alschuler, supra note 1, at 52. <lb/>Compare BUTLER, supra note 196, at 68 (for Butler) with BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 53 (for <lb/>Blackstone). Conklin also finds that the pursuit of happiness is a linchpin for Blackstone, <lb/>Conklin, supra note 23, at 224, 260, but she places his approach also within the Common <lb/>Sense school, id. at 215-17. She attributes the phrase "the pursuit of happiness" in the <lb/>Declaration of Independence to Blackstone. Id. at 200-02. But see Craig A. Stern &amp; Gregory <lb/>M. Jones, The Coherence of Natural Inalienable Rights, 76 UMKC L. REV. 939, 973-74 (2008). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>351 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>audience. It was true to his own convictions. We have seen thus far <lb/>particular elements of the Commentaries signaling Blackstone's Anglican <lb/>approach. The main topic of this article, however, is his use of natural <lb/>law-the concept and body of transcendent law-and the degree to which <lb/>Blackstone's Anglican understanding shapes this use. <lb/>5. THE ANGLICAN BLACKSTONE AND THE NATURAL LAW <lb/>As we have seen, Blackstone's Commentaries bears the impress of its <lb/>author's Anglican faith. This impress shapes the appearance of natural <lb/>law in the Commentaries, but by no means minimizes the role of natural <lb/>law. To be sure, if using natural law means using it as Aquinas used it, <lb/>Blackstone does not use natural law. 221 In fact, Anglican Blackstone <lb/>lodges criticism at the scholastic tradition. 222 But the use of natural law, a <lb/>transcendent norm that guides human law, may transcend Aquinas's use. <lb/>In fact, the Commentaries more than anything takes the common law back <lb/>to natural law, to first principles, 223 portraying the common law as <lb/>blended with the natural law into one body. 224 Its use of natural law is not <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>While Blackstone does subscribe to the notion that natural law bounds the validity of <lb/>human law, see supra text accompanying notes 32, 41; Posner, supra note 45, at 605, his <lb/>use of natural law embraces far more, Finnis, supra note 24, at 183. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 78; see also 2 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 58 (describing <lb/>the "ingenuity" of the middle ages as one "which perplexed all theology with the subtilty <lb/>of scholastic disquisitions, and bewildered philosophy in the mazes of metaphysical <lb/>jargon"); 4 id. at 410-11 (bemoaning the scholastic intricacies of Norman jurisprudence). <lb/>Blackstone's approach avoided the complexities of the scholastics. See Conklin, supra <lb/>note 23, at 224. At the same time, while some note Blackstone's modern emphasis on <lb/>individual rights rather than on the classic common good, Finnis, supra note 24, at 181, <lb/>and on peace as the end of civil society, BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 179, and his "social" <lb/>rather than philosophical consistency, Brinton, supra note 204, at 704, Blackstone does <lb/>hold that society has a "moral purpose," BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 190, and shares also <lb/>with Aquinas, see, e.g., 2 AQUINAS, supra note 27, at 213-14 (I-II, 92, 1), 232-33 (I-II, 96, <lb/>3), the belief that law has moral content, teaches right and wrong, and improves human <lb/>beings. See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 27, 45; 2 id. at 8; 3 id. at 162. <lb/>See Conklin, supra note 23, at 211. <lb/>224 Cf. Helmholz, supra note 55, at 21-22 (noting that English lawyers traditionally assumed <lb/>that the common law and natural law "complemented each other"). But see Allen, supra <lb/>note 21, at 196-98 (questioning the impact of natural law upon the Commentaries). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>352 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>muddled or unnecessary. 225 After its conventional introductory treatment <lb/>of natural law 226 it frequently adverts to natural law principles when <lb/>discussing the common law itself. 227 Blackstone held that the natural law <lb/>was the only sure guide to English law. 228 Desiring not just to understand <lb/>but also to admire, 229 he sought beauty in the law, a beauty lent to English <lb/>law by God's design in natural law. 230 The Commentaries continuously <lb/>pursues this project and shapes its discussion from principles, 231 being <lb/>structured to align positive law with natural law 232 and organized to <lb/>demonstrate order in the English law from divine simplicity. 233 While it <lb/>melded law and equity together into one overall, integral system, 234 it <lb/>treated not the whole of the common law, but rather only what was <lb/>susceptible of rational appreciation. 235 <lb/>The integral connection in the Commentaries between English law <lb/>and natural law constituted English law a handbook on natural law. As the <lb/>spirit of law is a product of natural law, 236 so natural law can be seen from <lb/>the laws of England. 237 At the same time, English common law contained <lb/>a strong cultural component, 238 adapted as it was "to the genius of the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 38-55. <lb/>See Lobban, supra note 50, at 323. <lb/>See LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 37; Finnis, supra note 24, at 175-76 (listing scores of <lb/>references in note 94). <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 142. <lb/>See id. at 30. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 85. In like manner, Maine has remarked the importance of <lb/>simplicity, harmony, and elegance as guides to Roman jurisconsults. MAINE, supra note <lb/>24, at 65. <lb/>231 See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 28. <lb/>See Finnis, supra note 24, at 176. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 92. <lb/>See id. at 98. <lb/>See Lobban, supra note 50, at 332-33. Emily Kadens has emphasized that Blackstone's <lb/>approach to the law differed in its systemization and generalization from that of the <lb/>practitioner. Kadens, supra note 5, at 1559; see also id. 1563 (stating that the Commentaries <lb/>was said to depart from the common law as practiced), 1575 (stating that even in practice <lb/>Blackstone acted as if legal questions held one correct answer without doubt), 1605 <lb/>(stating that Blackstone even as judge knew the law, but not the "legal mind"). <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 58. <lb/>See id. at 53, 60. Following Hale, Blackstone in the Commentaries treats the general <lb/>phenomenon of law under the guise of the law of England as an example historically <lb/>considered. Id. at 35-36. The experience of generations of wise men had rendered the <lb/>common law the nearest human approach to the natural law. KIRK, supra note 106, at 371. <lb/>See Watson, supra note 23, at 795. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>353 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>English nation." 239 Taking liberty as the signal English virtue led, as we <lb/>shall see, only to emphasizing all the more the importance of natural law <lb/>to the laws of England. 240 <lb/>The Anglican context lent Blackstone's natural law an empirical <lb/>cast akin to Sir Isaac Newton's physics. 241 His approach was descriptive, <lb/>not deductive. 242 Blackstone was not unaware of the dangers of arguing <lb/>from particular to general, 243 but he nonetheless endorsed the scientific <lb/>approach. 244 The Commentaries is a quest for reasonableness, for the <lb/>rational principles -the natural law -undergirding the positive <lb/>particulars of English common law. 245 Because law is a rational science, <lb/>natural law suffuses the text. 246 In this commitment to empirical science <lb/>for fleshing out the natural law embedded in English law, Blackstone <lb/>treats law much as Butler treated theology. <lb/>Hooker more than Butler animates Blackstone's emphasis on <lb/>history, but that emphasis likewise demonstrates an Anglican approach to <lb/>natural law. 247 It is in progressive human experience that Providence <lb/>gradually works the natural law into human law. 248 As with Burke's view, <lb/>natural law makes itself known in history. 249 But history is no sure <lb/></body>

		    <listBibl>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 17; cf. 4 Id. at 256 (rooting a legal principle in "the genius <lb/>and spirit of the law of England"). <lb/>See infra notes 306-08 and accompanying text. Blackstone emphasized English civil <lb/>freedom, LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 39-40, and liberty, BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 154, <lb/>giving rights a central position in his analysis, id. at 162; see also Allen, supra note 21, at <lb/>196-97. <lb/>See supra notes 173-74 and accompanying text; Berman &amp; Reid, supra note 50, at 498-500, <lb/>511. <lb/>See Lobban, supra note 50, at 333. <lb/>See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 59. <lb/>See id. at 34; 2 id. at 2. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 11-12, 20-23. <lb/>See LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 37. Blackstone's dedication to the scientific approach <lb/>to the common law did not rule out what Boorstin calls "mystery" when needed to <lb/>supplement science, much as Edmund Burke called upon mystery in aid of his arguments. <lb/>BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 25. Similarly, the Commentaries has been tagged as "formalistic, <lb/>in the sense of describing the nominal power relationships, while failing to acknowledge <lb/>what he and other lawyers of his day knew to be the actual division of power and <lb/>influence." Langbein, supra note 14, at 70. <lb/>Hooker's use of history is treated above at notes 138 to 145. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 62-64, 78. <lb/>See id. at 72-73; RICHARD TUCK, NATURAL RIGHTS THEORIES 84 (1979). One is reminded <lb/>also of Maine's characterization of the Roman law as aspiring to an "indefinite <lb/>approximation" to perfect law. See MAINE, supra note 24, at 63. Here again, Blackstone's <lb/>roots in Roman law complement his Anglicanism. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>354 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>guarantee that the human law has taken on its shape from natural law. <lb/>Blackstone held that awkward complexity too comes from history, 250 and <lb/>history must bow to reason if found to contradict it. 251 Nevertheless, <lb/>Blackstone held history both descriptive of the law and prescriptive, 252 <lb/>obviating the need to distinguish "historical explanation" from "moral <lb/>justification." 253 The providential, historical development of the law <lb/>enabled Blackstone to portray law as possessing both the appropriate <lb/>degree of fixity and the appropriate degree of change. On the one hand, <lb/>common law and justice itself are fixed and uniform. 254 On the other <lb/>hand, natural law leads to growth and change in the law, 255 and it is <lb/>susceptible of diverse interpretations. 256 <lb/>Far from his being an <lb/>uncompromising apologist for the status quo, 257 Blackstone's very <lb/>commitment to history also committed him to progress. 258 Correction <lb/>and improvement -in continuity with historical development -are <lb/>welcome. 259 Accordingly, the Commentaries ends with this charge: <lb/>We have taken occasion to admire at every turn the noble <lb/>monuments of antient simplicity, and the more curious <lb/>refinements of modern art. Nor have it's [sic; i.e., that of the <lb/>body of English law] faults been concealed from view; for faults <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 104. <lb/>251 See LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 45. Boorstin writes that Blackstone employs a fiction that <lb/>English law expresses both "the perfection of reason" and "the fullness of experience," <lb/>BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 135, but Blackstone asserts that legal customs, while often <lb/>rooted in natural law, are not always reasonable and so may stand in need of correction. <lb/>Compare, e.g., 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 251 (suggesting that a custom "seems <lb/>dictated by nature herself") with id. at 280 (observing how an ancient rule of common law <lb/>"was consonant neither to reason nor humanity" and so endorsing its later alteration). <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 63. <lb/>LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 49. This approach was typical of English eighteenth-century <lb/>treatment of the law. Berman &amp; Reid, supra note 50, at 438. <lb/>See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 137 (asserting that the law of England "is permanent, <lb/>fixed, and unchangeable, unless by authority of parliament"); 3 id. at 429 (observing <lb/>that "truth and justice are always uniform"). Langbein suggests that Blackstone himself <lb/>viewed the fixed and settled character of the law as a myth. Langbein, supra note 14, at 68. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 57. <lb/>See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 226 (opining that the terms of the theoretical social <lb/>contract are "only deducible by reason and the rules of natural law; in which deduction <lb/>different understandings might very considerably differ"). <lb/>See PREST, supra note 1, at 307-08. Elsewhere Prest notes Blackstone's Tory opposition to <lb/>the Whig establishment. Prest, supra note 58, at 154. <lb/>See Alschuler, supra note 1, at 37-38. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 81; LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 43-44. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>355 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>it has, lest we should be tempted to think it of more than <lb/>human structure: defects, chiefly arising from the decays of <lb/>time, or the rage of unskilful [sic] improvements in later ages. <lb/>To sustain, to repair, to beautify this noble pile, is a charge <lb/>intrusted principally to the nobility, and such gentlemen of the <lb/>kingdom, as are delegated by their country to parliament. The <lb/>protection of THE LIBERTY OF BRITAIN is a duty which they <lb/>owe to themselves, who enjoy it; to their ancestors, who <lb/>transmitted it down; and to their posterity, who will claim at <lb/>their hands this, the best birthright, and noblest inheritance of <lb/>mankind. 260 <lb/>As the common law embodies and expresses the natural law, it is to be <lb/>reformed when lapses from that transcendent standard appear. <lb/>Blackstone calls English law of "human structure." <lb/>Though <lb/>eighteenth-century English lawyers may have called their law "the <lb/>perfection of reason," 261 Blackstone acknowledges it to be a somewhat <lb/>faulty human application of natural law, 262 sometimes more honored in <lb/>the breach. 263 <lb/>One means of developing the law with both Anglican continuity <lb/>and an eye to the principles of natural law is by legal fiction. 264 <lb/>Blackstone held that legal fictions permit the law to do justice in changed <lb/>circumstances, 265 as in bypassing Norman errors. 266 <lb/>In the <lb/>Commentaries, fictions, along with history, ground the law. 267 Legal <lb/></body>

		    <listBibl>4 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 436. Other passages urging modification of English law <lb/>include id. at 3-5, 88-89, 165-66, 175, 239, 278-79, 349, 353, 381-82, and 409. <lb/>261 MAINE, supra note 24, at 64. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 111, 145. <lb/>See id. at 146-50. <lb/>The classic discussion is to be found in MAINE, supra note 24, at 17-36. <lb/>See LIEBERMAN, supra note 15, at 47. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 69. <lb/>Allen, supra note 21, at 202-05. Allen would have this use of fictions establish that the <lb/>Commentaries sees the law as a fabrication that does not reflect the way things really are. <lb/>Id. at 205. Fabrication the law may be, see supra text accompanying note 260, but the <lb/>point of fictions is to shape this fabric more accurately to reflect the way things really are <lb/>notwithstanding formulations of the positive law that otherwise would depart from the <lb/>way things really are. After all, that is the driving force behind fictions. See MAINE, supra <lb/>note 24, at 17-36. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>356 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>fictions enable the common law to embody the principles of the natural <lb/>law. 268 <lb/>Of course, statutes also might help the law embody the principles <lb/>of natural law. 269 To some degree, the Commentaries portrays statutes as <lb/>declaring the natural law, 270 lending necessary correction to the common <lb/>law while simultaneously rooted in the common law. 271 But statutes <lb/>present a danger: <lb/>THE mischiefs that have arisen to the public from <lb/>inconsiderate alterations in our laws, are too obvious to be <lb/>called in question; and how far they have been owing to the <lb/>defective education of our senators, is a point well worthy of <lb/>the public attention. The common law of England has fared like <lb/>other venerable edifices of antiquity, which rash and <lb/>unexperienced workmen have ventured to new-dress and <lb/>refine, with all the rage of modern improvement. Hence <lb/>frequently it's [sic] symmetry has been destroyed, it's [sic] <lb/>proportions distorted, and it's [sic] majestic simplicity <lb/>exchanged for specious embellishments and fantastic <lb/>novelties. 272 <lb/>Architecture was important to Blackstone. 273 As a "rule-bound art," it <lb/>attracted his keen interest. 274 He used architectural metaphors in the <lb/>Commentaries, 275 and elsewhere portrayed the old common law as a <lb/>well-designed building. 276 <lb/>Damning accusation it was, then, for <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See, e.g., Stretton, supra note 205, at 119-20, 122, 126-27 (casting Blackstone's (?) "one <lb/>person" theory of marriage as a legal fiction to serve his "scientific organizing principle" <lb/>though, according to Stretton, not directly dictated by natural law). <lb/>Again, the classic discussion is to be found in MAINE, supra note 24, at 17-36. <lb/>See Lobban, supra note 50, at 325. <lb/>271 See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 86, 353; 3 Id. at 328, 410; 4 Id. at 431-33. Blackstone <lb/>presupposed and endorsed ameliorative legislation in his charge quoted above at note 260. <lb/>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 10. <lb/>See Conklin, supra note 23, at 220-24. <lb/>Prest, supra note 3, at 115-18. <lb/>See id. at 118-21. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>357 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>Blackstone to picture some statutes as monstrous add-ons. 277 But the <lb/>fault of such statutes is that they are in a sense ahistorical -they reflect <lb/>"visionary schemes" and "have not the foundation of the common law to <lb/>build on." 278 Statutes that bring the law closer to the natural law will find <lb/>their basis not in imagined exploits but rather in the principles already to <lb/>be found in the common law itself, the generally trustworthy, if <lb/>imperfect, presentation of the natural law. <lb/>Blackstone's commitment to the common law as holding within it <lb/>immanent natural law reflects both the Roman law and also the Roman <lb/>notion that the jus gentium, the law of nations, is a sound guide to the <lb/>content of the natural law. 279 While the common law may embody the <lb/>natural law more perfectly than do other systems of human law, those <lb/>other systems may shed light on the natural law to be found within the <lb/>common law. Blackstone subscribed to the uniformity of human nature <lb/>and God's purpose, to the consequent uniformity of natural law, and to <lb/>the expectation that the laws of all nations, past and present, would <lb/>reflect these truths. 280 Comparative law illuminates the universality of <lb/>English legal principles, the deposit of natural law. 281 The Age of Reason <lb/>looked for the natural law in the jus gentium, 282 and the Commentaries <lb/>looks to other legal systems to help find reason in the English law. 283 In <lb/>the spirit of Hooker, Blackstone found natural law principles behind the <lb/>diversity of laws even on aspects indifferent under the natural law. And in <lb/>the spirit of Butler, he found marks of reasonableness in the similarity of <lb/>English law to the law of other nations. <lb/>(The dominant role of <lb/>reasonableness in the Commentaries occupies our attention soon.) <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See id. at 104. <lb/>See Cook, supra note 12, at 175-76 (noting Blackstone's preference for the common law <lb/>over statutes); Kadens, supra note 5, at 1561 (discussing Blackstone's imagery of the law <lb/>as a house deformed by statutes). <lb/>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 353. <lb/>See supra text accompanying notes 63-65; MAINE, supra note 24, at 41-43. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 47. <lb/>281 See generally Alschuler, supra note 1, at 27; McKnight, supra note 2, at 404. <lb/>See MOSSNER, supra note 167, at 26. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 43. Blackstone reflects upon comparative law several times <lb/>in the Commentaries. See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 5, 21, 35-36; 2 id. at 258; 3 id. at <lb/>108; 4 id. at 181, 237, 241. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>358 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>The Bible itself often found its way into the Commentaries under the <lb/>aspect of comparative law -again, this was similar to the approach of <lb/>Hooker. 284 Blackstone kept the Bible close to him while writing the <lb/>Commentaries, 285 and he considered the divine law to be found therein the <lb/>authoritative source on what he called the "law of nature" 286 and on the <lb/>development of legal rules and doctrine. 287 Most typically, however, he <lb/>used the Bible as a source of comparative law, a source presenting a body <lb/>of law perfectly devised to embrace the natural law for a specific people at <lb/>a specific time. 288 Natural law then was to be found within biblical law <lb/>and not to be identified with it in its particulars. 289 <lb/>In these diverse ways -from finding natural law embedded within <lb/>the common law, to the use of science, history, and comparative law -<lb/>the Commentaries takes account of natural law in its treatment of English <lb/>law, all in keeping with an Anglican understanding of natural law and its <lb/>application to human affairs. But the most distinctively Anglican feature <lb/>of how the Commentaries treats the natural law has escaped for the most <lb/>part our attention until now. That feature is the testing and justification <lb/>of the law of England by its reasonableness. Hooker, and especially Butler <lb/>and the Latitudinarians, lent to Anglican theology its distinct emphasis <lb/>on reasonableness. It is in this aspect of his jurisprudence that Blackstone <lb/>most shows himself an Anglican. <lb/>For Blackstone, natural law does not dictate the content of most <lb/>human law. 290 It supplies a few core principles, and those few do not <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See supra notes 116-18 and accompanying text. <lb/>See Cook, supra note 12, at 175. <lb/>See supra text accompanying note 39. Again, this paper uses the term "natural law" for <lb/>what Blackstone usually called "the law of nature." He himself defined "natural law" to <lb/>be human theorizing about the law of nature, see id., though his actual usage seems not to <lb/>be uniform on this point, see supra note 7. <lb/>See Wilfrid Prest, William Blackstone's Anglicanism, in GREAT CHRISTIAN JURISTS IN ENGLISH <lb/>HISTORY 213, 231-32 (Mark Hill &amp; R. H. Helmholz eds., 2017). <lb/>See DAVIES, supra note 151, at 16, 21. <lb/>In keeping with its comparatist approach, the Commentaries with seeming approval notes <lb/>within or alongside the common law itself a diversity of sources and even of rules of law. <lb/>See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 63-64, 74-78; 4 Id. at 403. <lb/></listBibl>
		
			<page>359 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>fundamentally overbear human law. 291 Furthermore, the state of civil <lb/>society itself modifies primordial natural law, introducing a context <lb/>where natural law principles take on a different cast or a subservient <lb/>role. 292 For Blackstone, the application of natural law is not so much a <lb/>matter of tracing specific precepts in human law. Rather, it is more like <lb/>the practice of Roman lawyers, finding reasonable and appropriate legal <lb/>norms suited to the situation at hand -the nature of the thing. The <lb/>Commentaries presents the common law as a "rational, integrated" <lb/>system, but also consistently traces its reasonableness, the reasons <lb/>behind its details. 293 <lb/>The quest for life in accordance with nature, and therefore with <lb/>reason, was a mark of the Age of Reason. 294 But Blackstone sought <lb/>reasons for the law as a mark of God's own perfection, to be discerned <lb/>through human experience. 295 <lb/>Blackstone derived his passion for <lb/>"reasonableness" in the law, and the consequent searching out of reasons <lb/>for the law, from his Anglican theology. 296 <lb/>The very core of the <lb/>Commentaries is this essential use of natural law, this examination of <lb/>reasonableness in light of the way things are. Reasons for the law, reasons <lb/>resting upon on fundamental principles, animate the Commentaries. 297 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See Alschuler, supra note 1, at 2, 24-27. <lb/>291 See id. at 26. <lb/>See 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 410, 423; 2 id. at 8-13, 258, 293; 3 id. at 145, 168, 208, <lb/>327; 4 id. at 3, 9-12, 42, 375. <lb/>Posner, supra note 45, at 579, 590. The Commentaries is so dedicated to this tracing of <lb/>reasons that at least one commentator tags the reasons as "often shallow, formalistic, <lb/>indeed sometimes plain dishonest." Langbein, supra note 14, at 77. <lb/>See MOSSNER, supra note 167, at 25. <lb/>BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 121. <lb/>See Berman &amp; Reid, supra note 50, at 502. Although reasonableness became a hallmark of <lb/>Butler and the Latitudinarians, reasonableness figures in Hooker's work also. See VOAK, <lb/>supra note 118, at 137. Perhaps in some distinction from "reasonableness," "reason" had <lb/>longed served as a touchstone of English law. See NORMAN DOE, FUNDAMENTAL AUTHORITY <lb/>IN LATE MEDIEVAL ENGLISH LAW 83, 106-31, 153, 176-77 (1990). Blackstone no doubt draws <lb/>upon this tradition as well as upon post-Reformation Anglicanism. <lb/>See Lobban, supra note 50, at 334; Posner, supra note 45, at 572. Posner discovers the <lb/>maximization of welfare in Blackstone's approach, Posner 573-74, much as Maine found <lb/>"utilitarianism" in the Roman law, McKnight, supra note 2, at 406 n.67. Finnis notes <lb/>that Blackstone in some respects bases even the human institution of rights upon reason. <lb/>Finnis, supra note 24, at 166. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>360 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>Throughout the Commentaries, Blackstone weighs law against the standard <lb/>of reasonableness. 298 The weighing is not rigorous. Fallen humans cannot <lb/>understand all by reason, and the reason for some law may now evade our <lb/>discovery. 299 It is enough that the law not be contrary to reason: 300 <lb/>[W]hat is not reason is not law. Not that the particular reason <lb/>of every rule in the law can at this distance of time be always <lb/>precisely assigned; but it is sufficient that there be nothing in <lb/>the rule flatly contradictory to reason, and then the law will <lb/>presume it to be well founded. 301 <lb/>Most often, however, the Commentaries highlights the place of reason in <lb/>the formulation of the law and supports the reasonableness of its rules. 302 <lb/>Furthermore, the Commentaries endorses reasonableness in interpreting <lb/>laws according to their equity, reason, and justice. 303 This overall <lb/>emphasis on reasonableness in the law, seeking sound reasons for rules <lb/>and for their proper application, largely shapes the Commentaries. 304 <lb/>Blackstone thought human law most significant on matters <lb/>indifferent, taking full advantage of the Anglican tradition regarding such <lb/>matters, an essential contribution of Hooker. 305 But though "indifferent" <lb/>may describe a matter not dictated by a precept of natural law, it does not <lb/>describe a matter to be determined by human will undirected by reason. <lb/>Support for this proposition derives from Blackstone's theory of natural <lb/>rights. We already have noticed the emphasis Blackstone placed upon <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Lobban describes this as supplying a natural law "external test of reasonableness of the <lb/>law." Lobban, supra note 50, at 333. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 27. <lb/>See id. <lb/>301 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 70 (footnote omitted); see also id. at 77-78, 91. <lb/>See id. at 47, 146, 148, 150, 163, 165, 185-86, 211, 226-27, 238, 246, 280, 287, 411, 443, <lb/>446, 449-50, 464; 2 id. at 4, 8, 10-15, 68, 128, 162, 210-11, 228, 230, 385, 390, 401, 411-<lb/>12, 453-54, 486; 3 id. at 31, 158, 161, 176-77, 188, 219, 226, 241, 244, 271, 379-80, 385, <lb/>430, 434; 4 id. at 14-16, 32, 51, 103, 105, 186, 216, 237, 248, 280, 364, 382-81, 409-12, 416, <lb/>425, 428-29. <lb/>See 1 id. at 61; 3 id. at 192, 207, 226, 392, 429; 4 id. at 423. <lb/>This search for sound reasons is not for Blackstone an individual affair; he distrusted <lb/>individual reason. See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 50, 103, 117; Posner, supra note 45, at <lb/>603. <lb/>See supra notes 147-56 and accompanying text. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>361 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>liberty as a mark of English culture. 306 Liberty -personal freedom -is <lb/>so important that only reasonable constraint upon it is licit. 307 "[L]aws <lb/>themselves, whether made with or without our consent, if they regulate <lb/>and constrain our conduct in matters of mere indifference, without any <lb/>good end in view, are laws destructive of our liberty." 308 Rights therefore <lb/>play a fundamental role in the Commentaries, and help support the natural <lb/>law test of reason even in matters indifferent according to the more <lb/>limited reach of explicit natural law precepts. <lb/>And Blackstone does make much of the notion of matters <lb/>indifferent, a mark of Hooker's theology and the Anglican tradition. 309 <lb/>His frequent use of the test of reasonableness supplies a natural law <lb/>standard in the absence of precise precepts themselves drawn from <lb/>nature. 310 In a sense then, the Commentaries presents most human law as <lb/>prescribing rules for matters indifferent. 311 In another sense, however, <lb/>Blackstone's insistence upon the reasonableness of human law supplies a <lb/>standard and justification much like that of the Roman law, a standard <lb/>and justification from natural law assuring that human law is suited to <lb/>the reality of things. 312 <lb/>The reality of things can become clouded by human artifice, so the <lb/>primitive state -and primitive law -offer a useful corrective. 313 For <lb/>Blackstone, Saxon law stood for law based upon reason, not authority, 314 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>306 See supra note 240 and accompanying text. <lb/>307 Social contract theory plays a role in Blackstone's development of natural law, see Finnis, <lb/>supra note 24, at 178-79, and even property rights are contingent, developed in the context <lb/>of society, see supra note 152 and accompanying text; Allen, supra note 21, at 197. Natural <lb/>liberty yields to social convention, but only for good reasons. <lb/>308 1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 122. <lb/>309 See, e.g., id. at 54-55, 185; 2 id. at 2, 211, 491; 3 id. at 87; 4 id. at 238; see also supra notes <lb/>147-56 and accompanying text. <lb/>See Finnis, supra note 24, at 181; David Lemmings, Editor's Introduction to Book I of 1 <lb/>BLACKSTONE, supra note 2, at xvii, xxxi. H.L.A. Hart has suggested that Blackstone's <lb/>presentation of natural law is expressly to provide gaps to be filled by human law settling <lb/>matters indifferent, Hart, supra note 52, at 174, but Finnis has demonstrated the difficulty <lb/>with Hart's view. See Finnis, supra note 24, at 171-74. <lb/>311 See Lobban, supra note 50, at 324; McKnight, supra note 2, at 404-06. <lb/>Again, it bears repeating that "the reality of things" speaks not only of mere physicality <lb/>but also of the norms appropriate to the situation at hand. The reality of things holds as <lb/>much ought as is. See supra notes 66-76 and accompanying text. <lb/>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 65, 68. <lb/>See Posner, supra note 45, at 604. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>362 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>he himself esteeming primitive law the most rational and therefore most <lb/>true to nature. 315 The corruption of Saxon law by "Norman subtlety" 316 <lb/>left it an ideal to be recovered by progress under the hand of <lb/>Providence. 317 The law is to conform to reason, and Saxon law points the <lb/>way to reasonable law untainted by later human error. <lb/>Likewise, Blackstone's emphasis on the reasonableness of the law <lb/>helps make sense of his theory of judging. A judge is "sworn to determine, <lb/>not according to his own private judgment, but according to the known <lb/>laws and customs of the land; not delegated to pronounce a new law, but <lb/>to maintain and expound the old one." 318 This declaratory theory of <lb/>judging has come under wide-ranging attack, 319 and some doubt has been <lb/>cast on whether Blackstone himself really subscribed to it. 320 Though <lb/>judges even now may pay lip service to the theory, 321 it may seem unlikely <lb/>that the development of the common law and the decision of difficult <lb/>questions proceed simply from the declaration of pre-existing principles <lb/>and rules, and not from judicial invention. 322 But the matter might be less <lb/>puzzling if, rather than thinking that the theory entails some preexistent <lb/>code of natural-law rules ready to fill gaps in the previously declared <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 70. <lb/>Id. at 69. <lb/>See id. at 83-84; McKnight, supra note 2, at 403; Posner, supra note 45, at 583; cf. MAINE, <lb/>supra note 24, at 60 (noting that Roman lawyers respected the natural law within their own <lb/>law for its "descent from the aboriginal reign of nature"). Presumably, Blackstone melds <lb/>his endorsement of both Saxon primitivism and historical development in the notion of <lb/>sound development upon Saxon principle. <lb/>1 BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 69; see also 3 id. at 327 ("For though in many other <lb/>countries every thing is left in the breast of the judge to determine, yet with us he is only <lb/>to declare and pronounce, not to make or new-model, the law"). This understanding of <lb/>the work of the judge is in keeping with Blackstone's view of the use of reason in law to <lb/>discover, not to invent. See BOORSTIN, supra note 1, at 51, 123. So law apparently created by <lb/>human beings has also a divine quality. Id. at 59. <lb/>See, e.g., JOHN CHIPMAN GRAY, THE NATURE AND SOURCES OF THE LAW 59-64 (David Campbell <lb/>&amp; Philip Thomas eds., Dartmouth Publ'g 1997) (1921); William S. Brewbaker III, Found <lb/>Law, Made Law and Creation: Reconsidering Blackstone's Declaratory Theory, 22 J.L. &amp; <lb/>RELIGION 255 (2006). <lb/>320 See Alschuler, supra note 1, at 4, 37, 42. <lb/>See, e.g., Frankland &amp; Moore v. Regina [1987] 1 AC 576, 585, 594 (PC) (appeals taken from <lb/>Isle of Man). <lb/>At the same time, however, Helmholz has noted the traditional role for natural law in <lb/>adjudging cases, Helmholz, supra note 55, at 18, and one may wonder how the rule of law <lb/>could be respected were judges to invent rules to apply to cases before them but arising <lb/>from facts long past. See STEVEN D. SMITH, LAW'S QUANDARY 61-64 (2004). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>363 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>common law, one could see instead that the question in any case is <lb/>governed either by principles marked in precedent or by whichever of the <lb/>rules proposed by the parties is the more reasonable in the light of <lb/>precedent and the facts of the instant case. 323 The judicial resolution of <lb/>otherwise uncertain questions of law demands the application of reason <lb/>and not ex post legislative will. <lb/>As we have seen, Blackstone does take natural law seriously, but in <lb/>an Anglican sense. The common law reflects the natural law, understood <lb/>as the rule of reasonableness, a norm that aligns the law with the realities <lb/>of the situation at hand, much as the Roman law is celebrated for doing so <lb/>well. That is the natural law as the Commentaries most often applies it. <lb/>6. CONCLUSION <lb/>After the spread of the Benthamite positivism, the sense of the <lb/>natural law enterprise was forgotten and (despite the eclipse of <lb/>Bentham's epistemology) it has remained usual to believe that <lb/>the heart of any theory of natural law is, not the problem of the <lb/>varying derivation of positive from natural law, but the thesis <lb/>that positive law is "for all purposes" void if it contradicts <lb/>natural law. Thus Blackstone's introductory discourse and <lb/>definition of municipal law have standardly been interpreted <lb/>on the assumption that any discussion of the relation between <lb/>natural and positive law must be headed for an assertion or <lb/>denial of that crude slogan, lex iniusta non est lex. 324 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>323 Apparently, on the bench Blackstone himself adhered to the declaratory theory and <lb/>faithfully applied precedent. See Kadens, supra note 5, at 1556-58, 1578, 1580, 1583, <lb/>1586, 1590, 1598, 1600-01. That Blackstone does not subscribe to judicial review, see 1 <lb/>BLACKSTONE, supra note 23, at 91; Helmholz, supra note 55, at 14, in no way compromises <lb/>his commitment to natural law. Finnis, supra note 24, at 169-70. <lb/>324 Finnis, supra note 24, at 182-83 (footnote omitted). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>364 <lb/></page>

		    <note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>Readers of the Commentaries committed to a narrow understanding of <lb/>natural law -often so committed only to reject the concept of natural law <lb/>altogether -find Blackstone at best an epigone of natural law thinkers. <lb/>He pays his natural-law lip service and then goes about his merry (and <lb/>disguised) positivist way. 325 Ignoring the relation of law to morals as well <lb/>as historical normativity, 326 we lack eyes to see Blackstone's use of <lb/>natural law in explaining, justifying, and criticizing English law. <lb/>At the same time, how strange to think that human law somehow <lb/>exists apart from reasons for its existence, reasons that connect it to the <lb/>world it is to govern. Holmes supplies such reasons. 327 Posner supplies <lb/>such reasons. 328 Blackstone does too. His reasons, his general recursion <lb/>to reasonableness, is not simply a platitudinous reference. Within his <lb/>Anglican context, reason and reasonableness are notes of God's order and <lb/>providence. They are notes of natural law. <lb/>The concept of law without values is incoherent. The "reason" and <lb/>"reasonableness" peppering the Commentaries are meant to supply the <lb/>link between the laws of England and the values that developed and <lb/>undergird them. Blackstone's Anglican approach to systematizing and <lb/>explaining English law -the systematizing and explaining that made his <lb/>Commentaries such a success -renders this link a natural-law <lb/>enterprise. 329 And this enterprise should strike lawyers, and especially <lb/>law students, as something familiar. They may not share Blackstone's <lb/>theological commitments, but when they strive to make sense of the rules <lb/>of law, to see the rules as reasonable, to find reasons for the rules, they <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>See Alschuler, supra note 1, at 54; cf. Allen, supra note 21, at 198 (stating that "the <lb/>Commentaries is a checkerboard of natural law and positivist perspectives"). <lb/>See Berman &amp; Reid, supra note 50, at 521. <lb/>See OLIVER WENDELL HOLMES, JR., THE COMMON LAW (1881). <lb/>See RICHARD A. POSNER, ECONOMIC ANALYSIS OF LAW (9th ed. 2014). <lb/>This approach bears a resemblance to the natural law of Roman law, "smuggling" into <lb/>the law values under the guise of a merely "technological" approach. See D'ENTRÈVES,supra <lb/>note 61, at 151. Also, Lon Fuller's explanation of the development of the common law case-<lb/>by-case comes to mind: he described each case presenting to the court the opportunity to <lb/>discern the necessary implications of the enterprise the law at issue is to govern. See Lon <lb/>L. Fuller, The Forms and Limits of Adjudication, 92 HARV. L. REV. 353, 357-77 (1978). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>365 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.4:2 2019] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2531-6133/10402 <lb/></note>

			<body>follow a course not unlike the course Blackstone famously set for his <lb/>celebrated Commentaries, a course marked by natural law. <lb/></body>

			<page>366 </page>


	</text>
</TEI>