<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>ARTICLES &amp; ESSAYS <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/>UNIVERSITY OF BOLOGNA LAW REVIEW <lb/>ISSN 2531-6133 <lb/>[VOL.1:2 2016] <lb/>This article is released under the terms of Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License <lb/>166 <lb/>Law, Market and Marketization <lb/>ROBIN PAUL MALLOY † <lb/>TABLE OF CONTENTS: 1. Introduction; 2. Law &amp; Markets; 3. Law &amp; Marketization; 3.1. <lb/>Assetization; 3.2 Transferring Assets; 3.3 Authentication and Valuation of Assets; 4. <lb/>Conclusion. <lb/>ABSTRACT: Marketization is a process occurring in many transitional economies as <lb/>countries seek to adjust their legal systems to facilitate broader market participation <lb/>while expanding global trade. This essay sets out one way of understanding this <lb/>process by focusing on the relationship among, law, markets, and marketization. It <lb/>identifies and explains basic legal requirements for marketization and links these to a <lb/>need to transform legal thinking by integrating a greater understanding of economics <lb/>into both law and public policy. <lb/>KEYWORDS: Law and Economics; Markets; Marketization; Rule of Law; Property. <lb/>University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/>167 <lb/></front>

		<body>1. INTRODUCTION <lb/>In the second decade of the new millennium, as we deal with the post-<lb/>financial market meltdown and the failure of self-correcting market theory <lb/>to prevent a global financial crisis, the legal pragmatists among us realize a <lb/>need to think carefully about the relationship between law, markets and <lb/>marketization. 1 Putting the recent financial collapse into perspective, we <lb/>should note that we have already spent some forty years with law and <lb/>economics as an important influence in jurisprudence, 2 bringing market <lb/>thinking firmly into law, and that we have already been through the <lb/>processes of globalization, harmonization, and the transition to market <lb/>economies in such countries as China, and in some of the countries of <lb/>Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union. Therefore, it is a fitting time to <lb/>reflect on the role of law in facilitating the ongoing process currently <lb/>referred to as marketization. <lb/>The process of marketization can be understood in at least two <lb/>different ways. First, it might simply refer to the process of expanding <lb/>competition and choice. This interpretation is consistent with the <lb/>jurisprudence of people such as Adam Smith. A second way of understanding <lb/>marketization is in terms of legal commodification. This article uses the <lb/>second interpretation. The process of marketization as a form of <lb/>commodification is one in which various social, legal, political, and cultural <lb/></body>

		<front>† E.I. White Chair and Distinguished Professor of Law, and Kauffman Professor of <lb/>Entrepreneurship and Innovation at Syracuse University. He has published sixteen books and <lb/>over 30 articles on subjects including law and market economy, real estate, land use, and Adam <lb/>Smith. This paper is the product of participating as a member in a series of meetings with the <lb/>Working Group on Marketization sponsored by the University of Helsinki, Finland. The working <lb/>group was interdisciplinary and comprised of about two dozen people from several countries <lb/>working in economics, sociology, biology, linguistics, science, and law. <lb/></front>

		<listBibl>1 See THE FUTURE OF FINANCIAL REGULATION (Ian G. MacNeil &amp; Justin O&apos;Brien eds., 2010); LAW AND <lb/>ECONOMICS OF GLOBAL FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS (Peter Nobel, Katrin Krehan, &amp; Anne-Catherine <lb/>Tanner, eds., 3d ed. 2010); MICHAEL MALLOY, ANATOMY MELTDOWN: A DUAL FINANCIAL BIOGRAPHY OF <lb/>THE SUBPRIME MORTGAGE CRISIS (2010); Robin Paul Malloy, Mortgage Market Reform and Fallacy of <lb/>Self-Correcting Markets, 30 PACE L. REV. 79 (2009); David Reiss, Subprime Standardization: How <lb/>Rating Agencies Allow Predatory Lending to Flourish in the Secondary Mortgage Market, 33 FLA. ST. U. L. <lb/>REV. 985 (2006); THOMAS E. WOODS, MELTDOWN: A FREE-MARKET LOOK AT WHY THE STOCK MARKET <lb/>COLLAPSED, THE ECONOMY TANKED, AND GOVERNMENT BAILOUTS WILL MAKE THINGS WORSE (2009). <lb/>2 Ronald H. Coase, The Problem of Social Cost, 56 J.L &amp; ECON 837 (1960); GUIDO CALABRESI, THE COSTS <lb/>OF ACCIDENTS: A LEGAL AND ECONOMIC ANALYSIS (1970); RICHARD A. POSNER, THE ECONOMICS OF JUSTICE <lb/>(1981); RICHARD A. POSNER, ECONOMIC ANALYSIS OF LAW (9th ed. 2014); ROBERT COOTER &amp; THOMAS <lb/>ULEN, LAW &amp; ECONOMICS (2000); ROBIN P. MALLOY, LAW AND MARKET ECONOMY: REINTERPRETING THE <lb/>VALUES OF LAW AND ECONOMICS (2000); NICHOLAS MERCURO &amp; STEVEN G. MEDEMA, ECONOMICS AND THE <lb/>LAW: FROM POSNER TO POST-MODERNISM AND BEYOND (2d ed. 2006). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>168 <lb/></page>

			<body>institutions reform themselves with reference to market mechanisms and <lb/>market values. Thus, lawyers move from discussions of &quot;natural law&quot; and of <lb/>the moral foundations of law, to conversations of &quot;cost and benefit&quot; analysis <lb/>and the economics of justice. 3 Similarly, legal institutions increase their <lb/>focus on matters of &quot;efficiency&quot;, and increasingly speak of &quot;justice&quot; in terms <lb/>of economic opportunities and outcomes. The process of marketization <lb/>involves a reinterpretation of legal and social relationships in terms of the <lb/>needs of commerce, and it increasingly makes reference to economic terms <lb/>such as efficiency and wealth maximization when evaluating such <lb/>relationships. While this process does not equate law to economics, it does <lb/>mean that the legal interpretive frame of reference changes and that more <lb/>and more decision making is based on price calculations and other economic <lb/>considerations. In the process of marketization law serves the purpose of <lb/>commercialization by protecting property, promoting production, and <lb/>facilitating consumption and trade. Freedom, equality, fairness, and progress <lb/>become understood in terms of law&apos;s relationship to market interests; <lb/>including the perceived interests of owners, creditors, investors, <lb/>entrepreneurs, consumers, and workers. <lb/>In this brief essay, I approach the process of marketization as one of <lb/>understanding the market from a legal perspective rather than one of doing <lb/>an economic analysis of law; and, I outline the way in which law functions as <lb/>a form of infrastructure to facilitate trade and exchange. Because the law and <lb/>legal institutions function primarily as infrastructure for trade and exchange, <lb/>they are frequently underappreciated. To many people, trade seems to happen <lb/>by operation of an invisible hand; with law appearing primarily when a <lb/>transaction goes bad and the parties need to resolve a dispute. 4 Dispute <lb/>resolution is, of course, an important function of law, but much of law deals <lb/>with making transactions stable, efficient, and predictable, even as between <lb/>parties who are unknown to each other. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>3 See POSNER [THE ECONOMICS OF JUSTICE], supra note 2; POSNER [ECONOMIC ANALYSIS OF LAW], supra <lb/>note 2; COOTER AND ULEN supra note 2; MALLOY, supra note 2; ROBIN PAUL MALLOY, LAW IN A MARKET <lb/>CONTEXT: AN INTRODUCTION TO MARKET CONCEPTS IN LEGAL REASONING (2004). <lb/>4 See MALLOY, supra note 2; MALLOY, supra note 3; Malloy, supra note 1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>169 <lb/></page>

		<body>The starting point for identifying the connections among law, markets, and <lb/>marketization probably goes back to Adam Smith. 5 In THE WEALTH OF NATIONS, 6 <lb/>published in 1776, Adam Smith observed that legal and economic systems <lb/>developed together and reflected a community&apos;s&apos; economic stage of <lb/>development. Smith identified four stages of development and suggested that <lb/>the age of commerce; based on the specialization of labor, the protection of <lb/>property, the freedom of contract, and the development of good legislation, <lb/>produced more prosperity and greater freedom than observable in any one of <lb/>the earlier three stages of hunting, herding, and farming. 7 Each stage also <lb/>involved a stronger emphasis on property, and on the need for more <lb/>advanced legal arrangements to deal with property. For Smith, the age of <lb/>commerce and the process of marketization facilitated social progress. This <lb/>was because Smith understood that advancing through these stages involved <lb/>expanding opportunities for competition and choice, and this in turn <lb/>facilitated a rising standard of living for everyone. <lb/>Today, political and economic elites in emerging and developing <lb/>countries see the prospects for a more prosperous future arising from <lb/>marketization and the transition to a market economy. In such a market <lb/>economy, relationships are structured in terms of costs and benefits and are <lb/>translated in to value neutral exchanges. Talk of morals and politics are <lb/>implicitly sidestepped as interaction is driven by the desire for making money <lb/>and for turning a profit. This may potentially reduce interpersonal conflict as <lb/>people are motivated by self-interest to work at making money and <lb/>improving their personal fortunes rather than engaging in conflict over <lb/>abstract ethical, moral, and theological matters. In Smithian terms, this may <lb/>also be beneficial because individuals pursuing their own self-interest <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>5 ADAM SMITH, THE THEORY OF MORAL SENTIMENTS (1759); ADAM SMITH, AN INQUIRY INTO THE NATURE <lb/>AND CAUSES OF THE WEALTH OF NATIONS (1776); ADAM SMITH, LECTURES ON JURISPRUDENCE (Glasgow <lb/>ed., Lexicos Publishing 1982) (1896). <lb/>6 See SMITH, supra note 5. <lb/>7 See generally C.A. Cooke, Adam Smith and Jurisprudence, Neil McCormick, Adam Smith on Law, <lb/>Peter Stein, Adam Smith&apos;s Jurisprudence-Between Morality and Economics, David Lieberman, Adam <lb/>Smith on Justice, Rights, and Law, Fabrizio Simon, Adam Smith and the Law, in ADAM SMITH AND LAW <lb/>(Robin Paul Malloy ed., forthcoming Feb. 2017). <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>170 <lb/></page>

			<body>naturally advance the public interest at the same time; even though the <lb/>public interest may be no part of their original intention. 8 <lb/>To be effective, the process of marketization requires embracing a <lb/>need to reform other institutions to reflect the language, values, and <lb/>outcomes that a market economy will hopefully bring. This is because market <lb/>economies not only need the infrastructure of open and unrestricted trade; <lb/>they need the validation of desirability from a variety of other social <lb/>institutions. Marketization, thus, becomes the process of cross validation of <lb/>institutional support for a more open, competitive, and decentralized <lb/>coordination of scarce goods, resources, and services; and, ultimately for <lb/>stronger legal rights. In the process, law not only provides the infrastructure <lb/>for more efficient market activity, it normalizes the power dynamics of <lb/>market relationships and makes them appear &quot;natural.&quot; 9 <lb/>In exploring these ideas, this essay describes some of the key ways <lb/>that law and legal institutions facilitate market exchange. The essay is not <lb/>intended to be all encompassing nor overly detailed. It is meant to offer a <lb/>general and overarching understanding of the various ways in which law <lb/>usefully functions to incentivize and protect market expectations. In <lb/>proceeding, therefore, I should note that many of the ideas expressed herein <lb/>extend on work explored in two of my early books: Law and Market Economy: <lb/>Reinterpreting the Values of Law and Economics; 10 and Law in a Market Context: An <lb/>Introduction to Market Concepts in Legal Reasoning. 11 In each of these books I <lb/>develop the idea of law and market economy. This approach is one based on <lb/>understanding the market as a dynamic process of exchange in which the act <lb/>of exchange itself creates and transforms meanings and values in the <lb/>relationships of participants and the things they trade. 12 For instance, when <lb/>the United States engages in trade with China, both countries have a change <lb/>in values over time. While the United States may believe that trade facilitates <lb/>China becoming more invested in freer markets and in democratic reforms, <lb/>the United States simultaneously experiences pressure to adjust its labor and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>8 See MALLOY, supra note 2; MALLOY, supra note 3; Malloy, supra note 1. <lb/>9 See generally ADAM SMITH AND LAW (Robin Paul Malloy ed., forthcoming Feb. 2017). <lb/>10 MALLOY, supra note 2. <lb/>11 MALLOY, supra note 3 <lb/>12 Id., MALLOY, supra note 2. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>171 <lb/></page>

			<body>production practices in order to be more competitive with China. <lb/>Consequently, as with any exchange relationship, both sides to the exchange <lb/>influence each other because exchange requires the continuous mediation of <lb/>conflicting cultural-interpretive tensions. <lb/>In this approach, the problems of the law are economic because law <lb/>governs the ways that people deal with the competition for limited resources; <lb/>and, the problems of economics are legal because law provides the &quot;tools&quot; <lb/>and infrastructure for trade and exchange. Consequently, this approach <lb/>focuses on the strategic role of law in relation to the stages of social <lb/>development; and, marketization involves the movement of a community <lb/>from the early stages of economic development (the age of hunters, herders, <lb/>and farmers), to the more advanced stages of commerce. In this transition to <lb/>a commercial society, it is also important to understand that the value of any <lb/>given market transaction depends on its position and its relation to all other <lb/>elements of a given system of exchange (a given market context). Thus, <lb/>exchange and the values generated by it are contextually informed by a <lb/>variety of factors such as history, ideology, and culture. In such an <lb/>environment, price functions as a relative interpretation of value; and is not <lb/>value itself. An important implication of this is that cost and benefit analysis <lb/>implicitly incorporates within its calculus a set of historical, ideological, and <lb/>cultural values. For this reason, cost and benefit analysis cannot provide a <lb/>neutral and objective approach to legal decision making. Cost and benefit <lb/>analysis must reflect community values with respect to relative pricing, and it <lb/>favors values that are easily priced over values that are abstract and difficult <lb/>to price, while privileging the preferences of those with many resources over <lb/>the preferences of those with few resources. In this context, law not only <lb/>facilitates these transactions, it normalizes them and makes them appear to <lb/>be natural and desirable. <lb/>In exploring the ways that law functions as an infrastructure for <lb/>markets and marketization, I proceed in two steps. First, I consider the <lb/>relationship between law and markets; where trades are organized, stabilized, <lb/>and pursued in ways that respond to the legal environment in which trade <lb/>takes place. Second, I address the relationship between law and the process of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>172 <lb/></page>

			<body>marketization; where marketization is understood as the process of <lb/>institutionalizing and incentivizing interpersonal relationships in terms that <lb/>facilitate the capture and creation of value through trade. <lb/>2. LAW &amp; MARKETS <lb/>Markets are about the human process of exchange; a giving of a &quot;this&quot; for a <lb/>&quot;that&quot;. In this process, the rules, standards, and norms of law mediate the <lb/>tension between private and public interest so as to peacefully promote the <lb/>common interest. 13 Importantly, law organizes exchange by creating the <lb/>infrastructure to expand beyond local and informal trade networks. 14 It does <lb/>this in several ways. For the purposes of this paper, discussion is focused on <lb/>five key functions of law. These functions include establishing and <lb/>enhancing: 1) acceptable networks and patterns of exchange; 2) <lb/>transparency; 3) predictability; 4) stability; and 5) trust. <lb/>Law is critical to formalizing exchange networks that operate <lb/>effectively across time, and beyond reliance on local and personal <lb/>relationships. 15 Law defines and frames the terms, consequences, and <lb/>acceptable objects of exchange. It also categorizes different types of <lb/>exchanges; such as by consent (contract), gift, and operation of law. Each of <lb/>these categories of exchange has different rules. Likewise, law informs us <lb/>about who may engage in certain types of exchanges. For example, minor <lb/>children (under the age of eighteen years) often have no power or only <lb/>limited power to engage in certain types of trades, and corporations have to <lb/>meet certain tests to qualify as legal persons able to enforce contracts or <lb/>conduct legal trades. In a similar way, law often regulates pricing and the <lb/>content of exchange agreements, while also limiting legally permissible <lb/>objects of exchange. For example, law permits trade in oil, diamonds, and <lb/>automobiles but does not generally permit transactions for the sale of babies, <lb/>body parts, or governmental elections. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>13 MALLOY, supra note 2; MALLOY, supra note 3. <lb/>14 See, e.g., DE SOTO HERNANDO, THE MYSTERY OF CAPITAL: WHY CAPITALISM TRIUMPHS IN THE WEST AND <lb/>FAILS EVERYWHERE ELSE (2000); MALLOY, supra note 2, at 109. <lb/>15 See, e.g., DE SOTO, supra note 14; MALLOY, supra note 14. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>173 <lb/></page>

			<body>Law must also define consequences of trades. Some trades, if permitted and <lb/>properly executed, are upheld by law, other types of trades such as those in <lb/>violation of the appropriate exchange rules (exchanges on the black market, <lb/>for instance), may be disallowed and the parties may be charged with crimes. <lb/>Some exchanges may be legally classified as fraudulent or be unenforceable <lb/>because of the way in which one party obtained the consensual compliance of <lb/>the other party. The nature of what is exchanged, who participates in <lb/>exchange, and the terms and consequences of exchange are all structured in <lb/>reference to law and legal institutions. Even informal and illegal trades make <lb/>reference to formal law by the simple fact that they hold the status of <lb/>informal and illegal exchanges because they are outside of the formal <lb/>framework. <lb/>In addition to identifying the permitted objects of exchange, law <lb/>functions to describe, quantify, and represent the objects of trade. For <lb/>example, the law may provide for private property ownership and for the sale <lb/>and purchase of property within certain approved exchange networks. For <lb/>this to work effectively, law must also describe and define the interest being <lb/>exchanged. Thus, law has to provide a representation of the property that can <lb/>be easily dealt with; this can be accomplished with a deed or other document <lb/>of title. The deed is not the property but a representation of the property that <lb/>is easier to deal with. 16 Extending this example, the deed can be used to <lb/>represent a person&apos;s interest in a particular property and can be used to <lb/>support credit, as in using it to secure a mortgage. 17 The mortgage is thus a <lb/>representation of a right against the property by the creditor in the event of <lb/>nonpayment, and simultaneously a representation of the right to receive a <lb/>stream of cash flow under the terms of the mortgage repayment schedule. As <lb/>a representation of the cash flow under the mortgage, this representation can <lb/>be used to support the issuing of a security based on the expected value of the <lb/>cash stream (e.g. mortgage backed securities). 18 All of this facilitates trade <lb/>and enhances the opportunities for capturing and creating value from <lb/>exchange. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>16 MALLOY, supra note 14; MALLOY, supra note 3. <lb/>17 MALLOY, supra note 3. <lb/>18 Malloy, supra note 1; ROBIN PAUL MALLOY &amp; JAMES CHARLES SMITH, REAL ESTATE TRANSACTIONS: <lb/>PROBLEMS, CASES AND MATERIALS 400 (4th ed. 2013). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>174 <lb/></page>

		<body>Law plays an important role in establishing transparency in the exchange <lb/>network. Transparency is very important for purposes of reducing <lb/>transactions costs, particularly in large and impersonal trading networks. 19 <lb/>Transparency performs at least two very critical functions. It reduces <lb/>information and search costs across the network, and it facilitates the process <lb/>of authentication. The idea of information and search costs is well known. <lb/>Authentication is probably less well understood. 20 Authentication is a key <lb/>factor in exchange. It involves the ability to &quot;prove out&quot; the substance of a <lb/>trade. This includes confirming the identity of the other parties, the validity <lb/>of the documents, the accuracy and availability of credit, and the substance of <lb/>the underlying object of the trade. For example, in a ponzi scheme (such as <lb/>that undertaken by Bernie Madoff) 21 , and as in the recent collapse of <lb/>mortgage markets in the United States, there was little or no reality in the <lb/>underlying economic substance of the trade to support the represented value <lb/>of the exchange. In each case the underlying value was misrepresented such <lb/>that the exchange at the level of a representational interaction (e.g. buying <lb/>securities based on an underlying real estate transaction) was not an <lb/>authentic reflection of the actual economic substance of the underlying <lb/>situation. 22 People were engaging in trades that had no sound basis in <lb/>economics because they either did not or could not properly authenticate the <lb/>underlying arrangements upon which their trades were based. Law can <lb/>provide mechanisms for making it possible to better authenticate the trades <lb/>people are making. Transparency thus reduces risk and lowers the cost of <lb/>exchange. <lb/>Law facilitates predictability in exchange. This also reduces risk and <lb/>cost. By establishing uniform documents, and promoting the standardization <lb/>and harmonization of the terms and conditions of trade, law enhances <lb/>predictability while reducing bargaining costs. Law identifies the background <lb/>legal framework and default rules that apply to certain exchanges and it <lb/>establishes remedies for particular types of failures in performance among <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>19 MALLOY, supra note 2; MALLOY, supra note 3. <lb/>20 Malloy, supra note 1. <lb/>21 See STEPHANIE YANG, 5 Years Ago Bernie Madoff Was Sentenced to 150 Years In Prison -Here&apos;s How His <lb/>Scheme Worked, BUSINESS INSIDER, (Jul. 1, 2014), http://www.businessinsider.com/how-bernie-<lb/>madoffs-ponzi-scheme-worked-2014-7. <lb/>22 Malloy, supra note 1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>175 <lb/></page>

		<body>the parties. With shared knowledge of these criteria, strategic planning and <lb/>structuring of a trade is greatly enhanced because the parties have a more <lb/>predictable basis for assessing and managing risk. <lb/>Law, through legal institutions, must also establish stability. Even <lb/>though markets are dynamic and fluid, the legal system must impose a sense <lb/>of stability on the networks of exchange. Just as it is difficult and costly to <lb/>work in an environment when one never knows if there will be electric power <lb/>available, or if the computer system will be working, or if the banks will be <lb/>open and operating from one day to the next, so too if the stability and <lb/>longevity of the legally supported network is in doubt. Markets can be <lb/>destabilized when governments simply confiscate private property, or <lb/>unexpectedly deflate the currency. Likewise, if the very governance structure <lb/>and functionality of a state and its legal system are in question, exchange will <lb/>be much more difficult and costly. <lb/>Finally, we know from the success of some informal exchange <lb/>networks that trust is an important element of a strong, extensive, and <lb/>efficient trading network. 23 Trust can arise within kinship groups, in local <lb/>communities where everyone knows each other, and in other specified <lb/>circumstances. Trust, however, is really about reputation value. Close friends <lb/>can trade with each other because they probably have good information about <lb/>each other and they have a sense of the reputational value of the likely <lb/>performance of the other party to the exchange (trust). Law can facilitate <lb/>trust by backing up and enhancing that which already exists in the network <lb/>of trades taking place. It can also make many more trades possible by <lb/>providing a substitute reputational reference point. A party can effectively <lb/>trade with another unfamiliar party over a very long distance and across a <lb/>long time horizon if both parties place a high value on the rule of law and <lb/>legal framework applicable to their exchange. In other words, a transparent, <lb/>predictable, stable, and well defined legal system can provide the reputational <lb/>trust value necessary to facilitate trade on a global scale. <lb/>Some aspects of a legal system may even become individually <lb/>&quot;branded&quot;. While there are a number of strong legal systems from which to <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>23 See FRANCIS FUKUYAMA, TRUST: THE SOCIAL VIRTUES AND THE CREATION OF PROSPERITY (1996). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>176 <lb/></page>

			<body>choose when doing trades (choice of law rules), some aspects of a particular <lb/>system may take on the status of a highly sought after brand product. For <lb/>example, many exchanges involving admiralty and maritime law select <lb/>England and English law to govern the trades. 24 Similarly, in the United <lb/>States, many people select the law of the state of Delaware in choosing to <lb/>incorporate their business. 25 Maritime law and England, and corporate law <lb/>and Delaware; these are examples of particular legal institutions that have <lb/>gained &quot;brand status&quot; for facilitating trust among distant and impersonal <lb/>exchange partners trading in these particular legal categories. <lb/>While particular details of law and legal institutions are subject to <lb/>many variables, it seems critical for law to perform the above five functions. <lb/>In facilitating markets by providing a formal infrastructure of exchange, law <lb/>reduces the cost of trading and it makes it possible to extend the networks of <lb/>exchange beyond that of purely local and personal arrangements. This is <lb/>important because value and opportunity are greatly enhanced as the scale of <lb/>trading increases and the flow of information expands. Global market activity <lb/>and economic growth on a large scale are only really manageable under a rule <lb/>of law. Among other things this rule of law must address are: exchange, <lb/>transparency, predictability, stability, and trust. <lb/>3. LAW &amp; MARKETIZATION <lb/>By the term marketization I refer to the process of institutionalizing the <lb/>meanings and values of exchange in networks designed to transform, <lb/>capture, and create value from economically beneficial trades. This process <lb/>is facilitated by law in several ways. Law provides infrastructure for: 1) fixing <lb/>of assets (defining property / the process of assetization); 2) transferring of <lb/>assets (most significantly for markets the voluntary transfer by contract); 3) <lb/>authenticating and valuing assets; and 4) sustaining a dynamic process of <lb/>value formation. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>24 See generally Joseph C. Smith, Comparative Aspects of Commonwealth and U.S. Law Since the <lb/>Collision Convention, 57 TUL. L. REV. 1092 (1983). <lb/>25 See FRANKLIN A. GEVURTZ, CORPORATION LAW 38-40 (2d ed. 2000). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>177 <lb/></page>

		<body>3.1 ASSETIZATION <lb/>Assetization is the process of fixing assets so that they are capable of easy <lb/>exchange. 26 This includes fixing a writing for purposes of copyright, and <lb/>fixing an invention for purposes of patent law, just as much as it includes <lb/>fixing a legal description and an estate interest for the identification of real <lb/>property. 27 Thus, while real property and intellectual property may have <lb/>significantly different qualities, each is able to be properly understood as a <lb/>property asset because each involves the fixing of an interest within the basic <lb/>framework of a property law regime. The idea that certain interests might <lb/>also be describable in non-property terms does little to diminish the reality <lb/>that such an interest can also be a legally fixed property asset. 28 Not all <lb/>property assets need to share exactly the same qualities or characteristics. <lb/>Fixing an asset involves identification, definition, and assignment of <lb/>certain qualities, characteristics, and categories to it. 29 The underlying <lb/>qualities include definitional matters such as fixing a legal description and <lb/>the particular estate interest for real property. In terms of assigning <lb/>characteristics to the asset, the typical characteristics of ownership include <lb/>the right of use and possession, the right to exclude, the right to transfer, and <lb/>the right to the profits attributed to the asset (including equity <lb/>appreciation). 30 Finally, property related assets are categorized in such terms <lb/>as real, personal, intangible, cultural, and intellectual property. This permits <lb/>a more nuanced treatment of the asset. Fixing the asset also involves <lb/>ascribing certain default rules, such as remedies, for example, to transactions <lb/>in that asset. 31 Thus, by simply categorizing something as &quot;real property&quot; one <lb/>can ascribe certain qualities, characteristics, and potential causes of action to <lb/>the asset. This makes dealing with the asset more efficient by reducing <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>26 See, e.g., Robin Paul Malloy, Real Estate Transactions and Entrepreneurship: Transforming Value <lb/>Through Exchange, 43 IND. L. REV. 1150 (2010); DE SOTO, supra note 14. <lb/>27 Malloy, supra note 26. <lb/>28 Malloy, supra note 26. <lb/>29 Malloy, supra note 26. <lb/>30 See JOSEPH WILLIAM SINGER, PROPERTY LAW: RULES, POLICIES AND PRACTICES (4th ed. 2006). <lb/>31 See RICHARD H. THALER AND CASS R. SUNSTEIN, NUDGE: IMPROVING DECISIONS ABOUT HEALTH, WEALTH <lb/>AND HAPPINESS (2008). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>178 <lb/></page>

			<body>various transaction costs associated with learning about its potential value. <lb/>Property law and property lawyers focus primarily on the fixing of assets. 32 <lb/>Assetization is a more flexible term than property because the idea of <lb/>property has different meanings in different communities, and the legal <lb/>mechanisms for dealing with property vary significantly among and between <lb/>common law and civil law jurisdictions. There are some interests such as <lb/>trademark which function in many ways like property but are not categorized <lb/>as property. 33 We can talk about &quot;property-like&quot; assets in a broader context <lb/>of discussing assets that express property-like characteristics in certain <lb/>circumstances and under certain conditions. <lb/>Once fixed, assets become commodified and they are capable of being <lb/>more readily traded and exchanged in the marketplace.Part of assetization, <lb/>therefore, involves the creation of standard and formal representations of the <lb/>assets; such as developing paper representations of assets that are difficult to <lb/>move or are abstract in nature; including deeds for real property that <lb/>&quot;represent&quot; the interest held in an underlying piece of land, and mortgage <lb/>documents that represent the right to cash flow from payments being made <lb/>to purchase land on a credit basis (as well as contingent rights to the land <lb/>itself if the borrower defaults), and a patent or copyright representing rights <lb/>in a given invention or expression. <lb/>3.2 TRANSFERRING ASSETS <lb/>There are generally three methods of transferring property: by gift, operation <lb/>of law, and by exchange for value. A gift is generally not a market event in <lb/>the sense that it need not involve a quid pro quo exchange. A transfer by <lb/>operation of law involves such things as a transfer of ownership under the <lb/>rules applicable at death; the law by its operation transfers the asset from <lb/>one party to another. Exchanges for value can be consensual or forced. <lb/>Consensual exchanges make up the biggest part of market transactions <lb/>between willing buyers and sellers. Forced exchanges might include transfers <lb/>by trespass with a remedy, or a takings with just compensation under the <lb/>United States Constitution, or a taking under the property provisions of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>32 Malloy, supra note 26. <lb/>33 Malloy, supra note 26. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>179 <lb/></page>

		<body>constitutional documents as they exist in many countries. 34 Law must <lb/>provide rules, standards, and institutional infrastructure for each type of <lb/>transfer, with consensual transfers being of most interest to the idea of <lb/>market exchange. Thus, there are rules on contract formation, performance, <lb/>and enforcement, as well as rules dealing with gifts and other types of <lb/>transfers. <lb/>Two important concepts that facilitate incentivizing transfers are <lb/>liquidity and leverage. In turn, both of these are enhanced by the fact that <lb/>assets can be fixed and represented in documentary form. Liquidity involves <lb/>the velocity of value capture, formation, and transformation through market <lb/>exchange. 35 Assetization involves the fixing of assets, and liquidity relates to <lb/>the efficiency of the exchange networks. Liquidity is enhanced by a system of <lb/>uniform and predictable contract rules, standardization of forms and <lb/>documentation, certainty of pricing, ease of spreading risk, and availability of <lb/>good information. Liquidity is also enhanced by expanding the scale of the <lb/>market to include more and more potential traders. <lb/>Related to liquidity is the idea of leverage. Leverage advances the <lb/>quantity and volume of trade value by allowing current access to future value <lb/>by way of debt and equity financing. 36 Leverage can facilitate liquidity by <lb/>making more exchanges possible by expanding the amount of money/credit <lb/>in circulation. Liquidity focuses on the velocity of exchange and leverage <lb/>expands the pool of credit available for exchange. <lb/>Connectivity is also important to transactions and trade. An expanding <lb/>market creates more and more opportunities for interactive exchange <lb/>combinations. 37 As the exchange combinations expand, the system can <lb/>become more diverse and organize more and more information, thereby <lb/>enhancing the potential for value-adding creativity. Connectivity is akin to <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>34 TOM ALLEN, THE RIGHT TO PROPERTY IN COMMONWEALTH CONSTITUTIONS (2000). <lb/>35 See JEFFREY J. HAAS, CORPORATE FINANCE 25 (2014). <lb/>36 Id. at 157. <lb/>37 See generally OZ SHY, THE ECONOMICS OF NETWORK INDUSTRIES (2001); Brett M. Frischmann, An <lb/>Economic Theory of Infrastructure and Commons Management, 89 MINN. L. REV. 917 (2005); BRETT M. <lb/>FRISCHMANN, INFRASTRUCTURE: THE SOCIAL VALUE OF SHARED RESOURCES (2012); YOCHAI BENKLER, THE <lb/>WEALTH OF NETWORKS: HOW SOCIAL PRODUCTION TRANSFORMS MARKETS AND FREEDOM (2006); 1 MANUEL <lb/>CASTELLS, THE RISE OF THE NETWORK SOCIETY: THE INFORMATION AGE -ECONOMY, SOCIETY, AND CULTURE <lb/>(2nd ed. 2010); KECHENG LIU, SEMIOTICS IN INFORMATION SYSTEMS ENGINEERING (2000). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>180 <lb/></page>

			<body>expanding the network architecture of exchange. As with a computer or cell <lb/>phone network, expanding the legal infrastructure of exchange to enhance <lb/>liquidity, leverage, capacity, accessibility, and strategic interaction can <lb/>increase participation value for all users. The more interconnected (in the <lb/>sense of degrees of connectivity) the system and the larger the scaling of <lb/>exchange, the more strategic the network is to the value of market activity. <lb/>Law facilitates connectivity by developing uniform documents, <lb/>standardizing and harmonizing rules and norms, and by establishing a set of <lb/>default rules that lower the cost of bargaining. Law also functions to expand <lb/>the market by creating a partial substitute and an enhancement to &quot;trust&quot;. <lb/>Law can provide a formal, transparent, predictable, and stable substitute for <lb/>local and personal contacts. In this way, the trust functions of personal <lb/>knowledge and experience can be substantially shifted from the individuals to <lb/>the reputational value of the legal system governing exchange, and if the <lb/>system is highly regarded it can function to reduce the risk associated with <lb/>impersonal exchanges across place, space, and time. This reputational value <lb/>may be associated with strong protection of rights to assets, well developed <lb/>contract rights and remedies, objective (apolitical) decision making, and a <lb/>variety of other factors. <lb/>3.3 AUTHENTICATION AND VALUATION OF ASSETS <lb/>In order for the marketization process to work effectively law must provide <lb/>mechanisms to facilitate authentication and valuation. 38 Authenticating a <lb/>transaction is similar to the idea of authenticating a password access to <lb/>certain web pages on the internet, or authenticating a right to be in a given <lb/>place by use of encrypted codes driven by finger prints and other devices. In <lb/>the typical transactional setting it means authenticating the existence of the <lb/>asset, its basic quality and quantity, and such things as the authority of the <lb/>person transferring the goods. It also involves authenticating the <lb/>&quot;originality&quot; and completeness of all documentation. Some ways of dealing <lb/>with these issues require reference to information recorded on the public <lb/>records; review of corporate documents with respect to corporate existence <lb/>and authority of particular individuals to transfer assets; surveying with <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>38 Malloy, supra note 1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>181 <lb/></page>

		<body>respect to land, and other similar action such as credit checks. The basic idea <lb/>is that markets with good tools for authentication have more liquidity, better <lb/>capacity for leverage, and greatly reduced risk. <lb/>As to valuation, law must provide a means for translating value into <lb/>easily measurable units, usually in terms of money for purposes of trade. In <lb/>the marketization process, price, to a large extent, serves as an interpretation <lb/>of value. Through pricing mechanisms, complex systems become easily <lb/>comprehensible in terms of the relative exchange values between different <lb/>positions in the system. Pricing performs the function of translating <lb/>numerous competing preferences and values into a common language. This <lb/>enhances the speed and ease of comparing relative tradeoffs across a large <lb/>scale network. Law and legal institutions need to define the acceptable and <lb/>enforceable methods of translating price into value and the degree to which <lb/>particular translations will be backed up with legal sanctions and remedies. 39 <lb/>More particularly, value is a complex theoretical subject but we can <lb/>begin to understand some basic elements of value by thinking in terms of <lb/>three transactional categories of value: use value, exchange value, and <lb/>network value. Simply and briefly stated: use value is the value derived from <lb/>being able to use an asset (a house provides shelter); exchange value is the <lb/>value, and potential value, that an asset represents as an access point to the <lb/>market (the ability to borrow against one&apos;s home, or its value in resale); and, <lb/>network value is the value of an asset in relationship to an integrated plan of <lb/>asset exchanges (such as the value of housing in terms of being a source of <lb/>employment for construction workers and lumber companies, and as an <lb/>engine for furniture and appliance sales, and in terms of an input item, via <lb/>mortgage activity, to securitized asset markets). <lb/>Value must, of course, also account for different underlying measures <lb/>of fair market, hedonic, and contingent valuation across the above three <lb/>mentioned categories. It also requires knowledge of present discounted value <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>39 See EVE PREMINGER ET AL., TRUSTS AND ESTATES PRACTICE IN N.Y. § 9:249 (Volume D-E New York <lb/>Practice Series)(explaining that the three most common methods used to determine the fair <lb/>market value of real property are cost method, income capitalization and the comparable sales <lb/>method); see also MALLOY, supra note 3 (discussing contingent and hedonic value); see also HAAS, <lb/>supra note 35, at 53-5 (explaining how to calculate discounted present value). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

			<page>182 <lb/></page>

			<body>and the extent to which various legal rules account for different definitions of <lb/>value. <lb/>The process of marketization can be positive when it expands the <lb/>opportunities for trade. For instance, being in a small village with an <lb/>informal market system provides much less value enhancing potential than <lb/>being connected to a larger scale national or global market network. In the <lb/>local market, people may know each other and have relatively good <lb/>information about the people and parties to an exchange. Larger and more <lb/>effective exchange networks bring in more and more people so that discrete <lb/>bits and pieces of knowledge (embedded within individual and personal <lb/>experiences) come into the market. It is the bringing together and mixing of <lb/>fragmented information that allows for opportunities to discover new, better, <lb/>and lower cost avenues of trade. <lb/>Marketization can have negative implications to the extent that it <lb/>involves subordinating a variety of cultural and ethical values to a system in <lb/>which price stands not just for an interpretation of value but is interpreted as <lb/>value itself. Thus, rewriting the grounds upon which human relationships <lb/>take place. It can be a move away from the idea of the sacred, of nature, of <lb/>the spiritual, and the mystical, to the rational reduction of feelings and <lb/>emotion into a cost and benefit calculus; a calculus in which all human values <lb/>are expressed in terms of wealth calculations, whereby everything is given a <lb/>price, and wealth maximization becomes the highest value. Law must <lb/>function to &quot;soften&quot; the marketization process to ensure that it is understood <lb/>as a means to achieving desirable human ends, and that it avoids the <lb/>temptation to become a simplifying end in itself. <lb/>To be positive, marketization has to be based on the advancement of <lb/>human values and the respect for community standards and norms. <lb/>Marketization does not involve merely privileging the individual pursuit of <lb/>self-interest. Market actors are social beings embedded within a culture. In <lb/>order for the pursuit of self-interest to be positive it must be tempered with a <lb/>regard for others, and this tempering and constraint is judged with reference <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

		<page>183 <lb/></page>

		<body>to a third party; a party that Adam Smith identified as the impartial spectator. 40 <lb/>The idea of an impartial spectator might well define the modern day <lb/>understanding of the phrase, &quot;the rule of law&quot;. The impartial spectator is <lb/>symbolically akin to lady justice both representing impartiality and a sense of <lb/>blindness to the qualities of the individuals involved in the exchange. Law <lb/>functions as an impartial spectator to facilitate trades in ways that are <lb/>transparent, predictable, stable, and within the reasonable expectations of <lb/>the original intentions of the parties. At the transactions level, law frequently <lb/>imposes rules on exchange that focus on the protection of third parties. This <lb/>happens, for example, in terms of title registration and recording which <lb/>protects not on the immediate parties to an exchange but third parties who <lb/>might deal in the property at a future date. 41 Likewise, with rules related to <lb/>protecting bona fide purchasers and holders in due course. 42 A third party, <lb/>impartial spectator view is also apparent in such legal standards as those that <lb/>evaluate action with reference to that of a reasonably prudent person, custom <lb/>in trade, and course of dealing. Law functions to promote impartiality so as to <lb/>encourage a perception of fairness in exchange. At the same time, law seeks <lb/>to protect third parties so that future exchanges can be lower risk and thus, <lb/>more highly valued. The value of the property I acquire today includes the <lb/>potential for me to exchange it at a later date with a willing third party buyer. <lb/>Therefore, sustainability of exchange depends on including legal protections <lb/>for potential, yet possibly unidentifiable, future traders. <lb/>4. CONCLUSION <lb/>Law plays an important role in the process of marketization. Through the <lb/>process of marketization law facilitates trades and exchanges in ways that <lb/>validate unequal distributions of resources and that protect the owners of <lb/>many assets from the desires of those who have fewer assets. At the same <lb/>time, law creates a network infrastructure capable of peacefully organizing <lb/>human activity across place, space, and time. This network infrastructure <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>40 See ROBIN PAUL MALLOY, supra note 2; see also MALLOY, supra note 3; see generally ADAM SMITH AND <lb/>LAW (Robin Paul Malloy eds., forthcoming Feb. 2017). <lb/>41 MALLOY &amp; SMITH, supra note 18, at 235 -94. <lb/>42 See, e.g., JAMES J. WHITE &amp; ROBERT S. SUMMERS, UNIFORM COMMERCIAL CODE 151-52 (4th ed. 1995). <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">University of Bologna Law Review <lb/>[Vol.1:2 2016] <lb/>DOI 10.6092/issn.2531-6133/6356 <lb/></note>

		<page>184 <lb/></page>

		<body>facilitates opportunities for all people to improve their well-being. In so <lb/>doing, law provides a foundation upon which a market society may rest, and <lb/>where the language of the market becomes ubiquitous in talking about and <lb/>describing activities and relationships that had not previously been thought <lb/>of in market terms. </body>


	</text>
</tei>
