<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
        <page>83 <lb/></page>
        <front>The Art of Adapting Open Educational Resources for Street Law: Copyright the <lb/>Card Game a Case Study <lb/>Jane Secker 1 , Chris Morrison 2 and Frances Ridout 3 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The Street Law community is well practiced in designing bespoke activities for particular <lb/>community groups. Starting with a blank canvas can often be the easier forma. How often do <lb/>we consider inviting our Street Law students to adapt works, games, and materials designed <lb/>for one purpose or audience (i.e. not Street Law) and transform them into a different format? <lb/>This paper highlights a case study involving undergraduate law students adapting an openly <lb/>licensed card game originally designed for use with academic librarians, and using it as a tool <lb/>to raise awareness with sixth form students about the laws and issues of copyright. <lb/></front>
        
        <body>Open Educational Practices, Information Literacy and Street Law <lb/>This article sits at the intersection of three areas of interest: information literacy, open <lb/>educational practices and Street Law. While the article is largely practical in focus, we <lb/>start by providing a short theoretical framework to our work, which we believe makes <lb/>some new connections between these disciplines. <lb/></body>
        
        <front>1 Dr Jane Secker is Senior Lecturer in Educational Development at City, University of London. <lb/>2 Chris Morrison is Copyright and Licensing Specialist at the Bodleian Libraries, University of Oxford. <lb/>3 Frances Ridout is the Director of the Queen Mary Legal Advice Centre, Queen Mary University of <lb/>London. She is a Barrister and Senior Lecturer. <lb/></front>
        
        <page>84 <lb/></page>

        <body>Firstly, the article is about the adaptation of an information literacy teaching resource, <lb/>developed to educate librarians about copyright. Information literacy is the ability &quot;to <lb/>think critically and make balanced judgements about any information we find and <lb/>use&quot;. 4 The teaching resource in question is available under a Creative Commons <lb/>licence 5 which allows it to be shared and adapted. The resource is also an example of <lb/>the growing global movement towards recognising the benefits of what Cronin calls <lb/>&apos;open educational practices (OEP)&apos; in higher education and more broadly 6 . This <lb/>includes publishing research on open access platforms but also sharing teaching <lb/>materials as open educational resources (OERs) and considering the benefits to <lb/>learners of more open and equitable access to education. Open access as defined by <lb/>the Budapest Open Access Initiative, is scholarly literature that is: <lb/>&quot;.. free(ly) availability on the public internet, permitting any users to read, <lb/>download, copy, distribute, print, search, or link to the full texts of these <lb/>articles.&quot; 7 <lb/>While this movement has gained considerable traction across the world, including <lb/>from research funders, the focus of this article is on raising the profile of OERs, which <lb/>are freely available, openly licensed teaching materials. UNESCO recognise their <lb/>value, saying that OERs &quot;contribute to peace, sustainable social and economic development <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>4 CILIP Definition of Information Literacy (2018) Available at: www.cilip.org.uk/news/421972/What-is-<lb/>information-literacy.htm &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt; <lb/>5 &quot;Creative Commons licenses give everyone from individual creators to large institutions a standardised way to <lb/>grant the public permission to use their creative work under copyright law.&quot; <lb/>www.creativecommons.org/about/cclicences/ &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/>6 Cronin, C., 2017. Openness and praxis: Exploring the use of open educational practices in higher <lb/>education. International Review of Research in Open and Distributed Learning: IRRODL, 18(5), pp.15-34. <lb/>7 See https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Budapest_Open_Access_Initiative <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>85 <lb/></page>

        <body>and intercultural dialogue&quot;. They also believe they improve the quality of education and <lb/>help with capacity building. 8 <lb/>Secondly the article reports on the experiences of law students, working on a Street <lb/>Law programme to adapt the teaching resource to a new audience, in this case sixth <lb/>form students in schools, who need to engage with copyright as it relates to their own <lb/>online behaviour and the social justice issues surrounding it. <lb/>There are several interesting theoretical links between the three areas that we have <lb/>observed. Firstly, the very nature of public legal education is about democratising, <lb/>demystifying and decoding complicated (and often hard to find) legal information for <lb/>the benefit of communities -especially those affected by laws. The law should not be <lb/>secret, it should not be hidden and it should be easily accessible to all who want or <lb/>need to engage with it. 9 The Street Law movement is inextricably linked to both a <lb/>commitment to social justice (it having been described as a type of civic education 10 ) <lb/>and a culture of being free of charge. Secondly, within public legal education and <lb/>Street Law communities we not only recognise and share good practice and resources <lb/>but encourage the adaptation and development of these resources 11 . It is an academic <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>8 See UNESCO page on Open Educational Resources https://www.unesco.org/en/communication-<lb/>information/open-solutions/open-educational-resources &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/>9 Per Lord Bingham &quot;the law must be accessible and so far as possible intelligible, clear and predictable.&quot; <lb/>Bingham, L. (2007) &quot;THE RULE OF LAW,&quot; The Cambridge Law Journal. Cambridge University Press, 66(1), <lb/>pp. 67-85. <lb/>10 Arthurs, S., Cooperman, M., Gallagher, J., Grealy, F., Lunney, J., Marrs, R. and Roe, R.L., 2017. From zero <lb/>to 60: Building belief, capacity and community in Street Law instructors in one weekend. Int&apos;l J. Clinical Legal <lb/>Educ., 24, p.118. <lb/>11 Examples include, but are not limited to, those freely available from Street Law Inc. https://store.streetlaw.org <lb/>&lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;, McQuoid-Mason, D.J., 1994. Democracy for all: education towards a democratic <lb/>culture. Juta and Company Ltd. <lb/>www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Democracy_for_All/Vgnu448i15IC?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1&amp;pg=PP1&amp;printsec=front <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>86 <lb/></page>

        <body>field which is proudly collaborative. Diversity of input to resources improves them <lb/>and ensures they are updated. This spirit aligns closely with the ethos of Creative <lb/>Commons licences which are designed to encourage remixing and building on the <lb/>work of others. Finally, copyright education is one aspect of information literacy <lb/>teaching often undertaken by librarians who seek to empower communities to use <lb/>information to achieve their personal or professional goals. Understanding copyright, <lb/>particularly the application of copyright exceptions, can help ensure it is not seen as a <lb/>barrier to learning. Therefore, what these three disciplines share is a concern about <lb/>equity, social justice and opening up access to knowledge as represented in Figure 1. <lb/>This collaboration potentially led to a more transformational educational experience <lb/>for both the students and the tutors. <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>cover &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;, and content in archive editions of this journal; the International Journal of Public <lb/>Legal Education. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>87 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 1: The relationship between Street Law, information literacy and open <lb/>educational practices <lb/>Copyright might, at first glance, feel like an unusual topic for a Street Law activity, it <lb/>being initially associated with the restriction of individual&apos;s rights, and business law. <lb/>Through the diagram above, we have sought to demonstrate that it is in fact a direct <lb/>fit with the social justice mission of clinical legal education. Perhaps, most <lb/>importantly, clinicians need to provide suitable opportunities for the students <lb/>engaging with Street Law projects in this area to see these connections. Ultimately, <lb/>developing information literacy skills in the area of copyright will serve many <lb/>individuals, protect culture and perhaps ultimately support small businesses in the <lb/>Street Law (part of <lb/>public legal <lb/>education) <lb/>Information literacy / <lb/>copyright education <lb/>Open educational <lb/>practices <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>Social justice <lb/>equity and <lb/>access to <lb/>information <lb/>• Pro-bono / free <lb/>• Empowering <lb/>communities <lb/>• Collaboration <lb/>• Democratising <lb/>• Demystifying <lb/>• Decoding the law <lb/>• Confidence accessing law <lb/>• Learner-centred knowledge <lb/>discovery <lb/>• Open Licensing <lb/>• Open access publishing <lb/>• All rights reserved vs Creative Commons <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>88 <lb/></page>

        <body>future 12 . Businesses need to understand how and where they might have copyright <lb/>protection in part of their business that they have created, but also understand the <lb/>degree to which rules can enable or restrict their output / product. <lb/>Copyright the Card Game <lb/>Copyright the Card Game was created by Chris Morrison and Jane Secker in 2014, <lb/>initially as a training resource for librarians to communicate the changes to UK <lb/>copyright law following the Hargreaves Review of Intellectual Property (Hargreaves, <lb/>2011). 13 It was designed as an accessible and interactive way to introduce the complex <lb/>area of copyright law, and has been effective with a wide variety of audiences <lb/>including educators, researchers, creators and entrepreneurs. 14 The card deck and <lb/>associated PowerPoint slides are available for free download from the website <lb/>www.copyrightliteracy.org. 15 They are available under a Creative Commons licence <lb/>that allows them to be shared and for others to make derivative versions. These digital <lb/>resources can be adapted for use in in-person workshops or digital workshops. As a <lb/>result, a range of international versions have been developed including in the US, <lb/>Canada, New Zealand and Australia. <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>12 Elaine Campbell (2015) A dangerous method? Defending the rise of business law clinics in the UK, The Law <lb/>Teacher, 49:2, 165-175. <lb/>13 Hargreaves, I. (2011). &apos;Digital Opportunity: A Review of Intellectual Property and Growth&apos;. <lb/>14 Secker J and Morrison C. (2016) Copyright and E-learning: a guide for practitioners. Facet Publishing: <lb/>London. Chapter 6: Copyright education and training: <lb/>https://ukcopyrightliteracy.files.wordpress.com/2016/07/chapter-6_secker-m_copyright-e-learning-2nd-edn.pdf <lb/>&lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/>15 https://copyrightliteracy.org/resources/copyright-the-card-game/ &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>89 <lb/></page>

        <body>The game works by covering different aspects of copyright law in a series of rounds <lb/>with an associated suit of cards. Firstly, the &apos;works&apos; round covers the subject matter <lb/>protected by copyright. The second round covers &apos;usages&apos; which are the restricted acts <lb/>in the copyright legislation. Round three provides an overview of different types of <lb/>licences which allow legal use of copyright material with the permission of the <lb/>copyright owner. The fourth round introduces the &apos;exceptions&apos; cards, which list a <lb/>selection of permitted acts -those where activity is legal without the copyright owner&apos;s <lb/>permission. This round also introduces the concept of risk when making decisions <lb/>about using content protected by copyright. <lb/>All rounds involve providing participants with context-specific scenarios related to <lb/>copyright and asking them to select the appropriate cards. Teams then come together <lb/>to share their answers and the facilitators discuss these and award points based on <lb/>well thought through interpretations of the law. <lb/>The game is based on active learning principles and is designed to provide a &apos;safe <lb/>space&apos; where participants are allowed to work through different possibilities without <lb/>fear of &apos;getting it wrong&apos;. In fact, the game is specifically designed to address the fact <lb/>that those who are given responsibility within their organisation often feel the need to <lb/>find the &apos;right&apos; answer to copyright questions. However, copyright law is rarely clear <lb/>cut, particularly when it comes to interpretations of copyright exceptions and risk. <lb/></body>

        <page>90 <lb/></page>

        <body>This has been shown to be particularly helpful for the library and information <lb/>profession where copyright can cause significant anxiety. 16 <lb/>The game incorporates many of the fundamental principles of Street Law; it is <lb/>interactive, fun, and empowering for the participants who have the opportunity to <lb/>develop their knowledge / expertise in an area of law. Areas of law such as copyright <lb/>are too often overlooked as ideal areas of law for Street Law activities; seen in a <lb/>commercial, money driven light rather than as a social justice tool. Society has <lb/>changed in the last decade, even more so since the Covid19 pandemic in 2020. People <lb/>now have greater access to a wide-ranging set of digital tools that allow them to create <lb/>and share their creative work. Most young people have access to a smart phone years <lb/>before they reach adulthood, and social media platforms such as Tiktok and Instagram <lb/>are increasingly focused on visual content rather than words. As such, the need for <lb/>young people (school students and Law students) to be aware of the concept of <lb/>copyright and start the journey of engaging in the various rights and responsibilities <lb/>has never been greater. This is partly reflected in the launch of the Government&apos;s <lb/>Online Media Literacy Strategy in July 2021, which while focusing on countering <lb/>online harms also recognises the need for people to understand how online content is <lb/>generated and be able to critically analyse the content they consume. 17 In addition the <lb/>Intellectual Property Office Strategy 2018-2021 highlights the importance of raising <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>16 Wakaruk, A., Gareau-Brennan, C., Pietrosanu, P. (2021). Introducing the Copyright Anxiety Scale. Journal of <lb/>Copyright in Education and Librarianship, 5(1), 1-38 www.jcel-pub.org/article/view/15212 &lt;accessed <lb/>13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/>17 https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/online-media-literacy-strategy &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>91 <lb/></page>

        <body>awareness of IP law through education and work is underway to develop a new IP <lb/>education framework due for launch in 2022. 18 The need for awareness in this area has <lb/>been amplified by the Covid19 pandemic and advancement of digital communication. <lb/>Put simply, society (and in-particular young people) have access to more digital <lb/>platforms and are creating more digital content with them. <lb/>Adapting for Street Law <lb/>Copyright the Card Game is an ideal tool to be adapted for use in a Street Law activity <lb/>because it is openly licensed. The trial started with a group of 9 undergraduate Law <lb/>students engaging with a 15 credit, level 6, optional module: Street Law. The game <lb/>was first introduced to the students through their participation in a seminar run by <lb/>the game&apos;s creators. The real aim was to get the students (especially those who had <lb/>not studied an intellectual property law or copyright module) comfortable with the <lb/>format and the content. Particularly the idea that intricacies around the law were not <lb/>the priority; engaging in the discussion and issues was. The different rounds were <lb/>used as a way to introduce them to the area of law and effectively help them &apos;research&apos; <lb/>the legal content for their Street Law activity. This came with the caveat that they <lb/>were engaging in more legal content than would be necessary for a teenage audience. <lb/>Their brief was to deliver an engaging Street Law session via Zoom, to approximately <lb/>20 sixth form students who had already self-identified as being interested in Law <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>18 https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/ipo-strategy-2018-to-2021 &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>92 <lb/></page>

        <body>through a school club. For ease and clarity, we will call the Law students, students, <lb/>and the sixth form students, SFS. <lb/>The students were encouraged to work together in a team of 9 and were given all the <lb/>raw resources, logos and content to adapt in any way they saw fit. In reality they <lb/>stripped out approximately 50% of the cards from each round, but did not change the <lb/>written text on any of the cards. They re-named the game Copyright Countdown and <lb/>thought of two current audience appropriate examples per round that the groups <lb/>could fit the cards into. Due to Covid19 restrictions, they could not physically attend, <lb/>so were told that the session would be &apos;beamed&apos; into the classroom with the teacher <lb/>present and all SFS physically present in the same room. This had the advantage that <lb/>the SFS could sit in teams, and the drawback that the students found it challenging to <lb/>see the group via the small laptop camera pointed at the body of the classroom. <lb/>The students designed a scoring system, where the teams could win points. Points <lb/>meant the SFS could open one of a number of envelopes (the more envelopes they <lb/>opened, the more letters they would get in the concluding &apos;hangman&apos; style game). The <lb/>winning team was the team who was able to work out the word from the letters they <lb/>had at the end of the rounds. However, in reality everyone got sweets or a chocolate <lb/>prize! <lb/>Interestingly, the students found it helpful to divide up the different rounds (with two <lb/>students leading on each round) and the ninth member of the team acting as a team <lb/>leader to organise the team and introduce / conclude the session. <lb/></body>

        <page>93 <lb/></page>

        <body>The actual workshop took place during spring 2021 when the SFS were physically in <lb/>the classroom, but the students were stationed around the world and only available <lb/>online. This in itself provided challenges. <lb/>The nine students joined the teaching session on Zoom, being projected onto a main <lb/>screen so they were both visible and audible. The SFS sat around small tables in their <lb/>classroom. The students shared their screen and they were able to see the SFS through <lb/>a webcam in the classroom. The session was facilitated by their class teacher who <lb/>played a pivotal role in supporting the session. <lb/>The students had prepared physical tools for the workshop which had been dropped <lb/>into the school in advance. These were: a brown envelope with a deck of adapted <lb/>cards for each team, a worksheet with scenario questions on (these were also on the <lb/>share screen PowerPoint but in hard copy for ease), and 8 mini envelopes (only to be <lb/>opened if the student won the point). There were also prizes for all teams and SFS at <lb/>the end. <lb/>The session was fully rehearsed with academic support twice before the session was <lb/>facilitated with the SFS. <lb/></body>

        <page>94 <lb/></page>

        <body>Reflections <lb/>Reflecting on the session using Gibbs&apos; model 19 helped us to evaluate the experience <lb/>and to plan for future collaborations. This model involves starting by describing the <lb/>experience, noting our feelings and thoughts, our evaluation of the experience, an <lb/>analysis to make sense of the situation, a conclusion about what we learned and what <lb/>we could have done differently, and then finally creating an action plan for the future. <lb/>The experience <lb/>Much of the work is described above, so rather than repeat this, one thing we reflected <lb/>on was how it was a different task to adapt someone else&apos;s work, rather than letting <lb/>the students start from scratch to facilitate a workshop on copyright. The adaptation <lb/>process allowed the Street Law students to have lived experience of the advantages of <lb/>open educational practice and deep &apos;team work&apos; (meaning with the original creators <lb/>of Copyright the Card Game rather than just each other). One additional important <lb/>stage was ahead of running the session for the SFS, the group did a &apos;dry run&apos; in front <lb/>of the team, who then provided them with additional feedback on how to improve the <lb/>running of the game. <lb/>As with a lot of Street Law projects, the students initially fell into the trap of wanting <lb/>to teach the SFS about the law -and excessive detail on it. It took a number of <lb/>rehearsals (and building of their confidence) for them to realise that the SFS <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>19 Gibbs G (1988). Learning by Doing: A guide to teaching and learning methods. Further Education Unit. <lb/>Oxford Polytechnic: Oxford. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>95 <lb/></page>

        <body>discovering the law through the cards was a much more effective method of learning. <lb/>This also links with the common problem of students viewing themselves as the <lb/>teachers, rather than it being a peer learning exercise. Students took time to <lb/>understand that the discussion and debate on the issue was as important as the <lb/>content. We really encouraged them to think about what they would learn from the <lb/>SFS and how the reaction and answers might be used by them to shape and adapt the <lb/>game further for future workshops. The students essentially needed to understand the <lb/>essence of public engagement as a two-way process. 20 <lb/>Feelings and thoughts <lb/>As creators of the Card Game, Chris and Jane felt invested in helping the Law students <lb/>to understand the design of the original game and its learning outcomes, while trying <lb/>to step back and let them adapt it in the way the group felt was best. For example, one <lb/>experience from using it as a resource is not to present about copyright, but encourage <lb/>the participants to read the cards themselves. When students wanted to &apos;lecture&apos; to <lb/>their students in the initial rehearsal, efforts were made to remind them of this <lb/>essential Street Law pedagogy. While they had the advantages of our experiences as <lb/>creators of the game, and our many hours of using it with different groups, it felt <lb/>unfair to try and unduly influence them by saying &apos;that won&apos;t work&apos;. This resulted in <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>20 The National Co-ordinating Centre for Public Engagement describe the importance of &quot;an open, two-way <lb/>conversation&quot; with communities (https://www.publicengagement.ac.uk/about-engagement/what-public-<lb/>engagement) &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt; <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>96 <lb/></page>

        <body>further discussions with the students about the importance of student-centred <lb/>learning as a fundamental feature of Street Law. <lb/>Evaluation of the experience <lb/>The outcome of the activity was impressive and professional. SFS feedback included: <lb/>• &quot;Copyright Card game was very engaging and provided us with an insight into the <lb/>various different forms of copyright!&quot; and <lb/>• &quot;During the Queen Mary seminar on copyright law, not only did they provide us with <lb/>useful practical gifts but also a great insight to the world of law. We played multiple <lb/>games on different sectors of copyright law. We studied the key aspects of copyright <lb/>found in all parts of our society (music, advertisement, companies) and had to answer <lb/>multiple questions. The session was entertaining, helpful and informative&quot; <lb/>Having the starting base of a professional resource really allowed the students to see <lb/>the standard expected of a &apos;learn by doing&apos; game and concentrate on maintaining and <lb/>building on that standard of work. It is not uncommon to hear Street Law clinicians <lb/>anecdotally describe the difficulties in encouraging students to increase their <lb/>creativity (possibly a hangover from the more formal authoritarian style of <lb/>mainstream legal education). Adapting resources gives students a physical example <lb/>of interactive facilitation, and is a worthwhile activity for students at the start of their <lb/>Street Law course. School teacher Ms Dene, who was based in the classroom with her <lb/>SFS during the session, noted; <lb/></body>

        <page>97 <lb/></page>

        <body>&quot;The Copyright Card game was brilliant fun! We ran it with our Sixth Form Law <lb/>Scholarship Society. The Queen Mary students ran the competitive game online with <lb/>different rounds, which kept it engaging and exciting. The students had a great time <lb/>and also learnt a lot! For students who were already interested in law, I think they were <lb/>surprised at how little they knew about a strand of law that is so important to their <lb/>everyday lives.&quot; <lb/>Despite being actively encouraged to dissect all the original teaching resources, the <lb/>actual cards were not altered. The pack of cards was stripped back to reduce <lb/>complication and sections added in, but the students felt reluctant to change the <lb/>terminology on the cards. In this respect, Street Law students adapting other resources <lb/>need as much encouragement to change them -perhaps something which comes with <lb/>confidence, experience and demonstration. Just as those leading Street Law teaching, <lb/>model student-centred teaching practice within their own classes; we found that <lb/>students benefit when Street Law teachers model the art of adaptation to them. This <lb/>can easily be achieved through adapting the wealth of Street Law resources readily <lb/>available, running a session and then showing the students the original resource 21 . <lb/>One Street Law student provided the following feedback: <lb/>&quot;Working with a copyright card game was very different from the learning resources I <lb/>was used to working with, but it made me be more creative. It gave me a different <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>21 There are some excellent resources available such as &apos;Should it be a Crime?&apos; and &apos;Who gets a Heart&apos; in: <lb/>Arthurs, S., Cooperman, M., Gallagher, J., Grealy, F., Lunney, J., Marrs, R. and Roe, R.L., 2017. From zero to <lb/>60: Building belief, capacity and community in Street Law instructors in one weekend. Int&apos;l J. Clinical Legal <lb/>Educ., 24, p.118. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>98 <lb/></page>

        <body>perspective of copyright. It is a challenge to adapt complex copyright concepts to a six <lb/>form audience but working with a card game as a resource made it interactive and easy <lb/>to understand. [Sixth form] students engaged more and as a result better grasped the <lb/>concepts.&quot; <lb/>Analysis <lb/>The fact that the students were adapting an open educational resource raised <lb/>awareness of this fundamental principle in public legal education and Street Law. It <lb/>enabled discussions on information literacy and perhaps most importantly allowed <lb/>for a demonstration of how both areas link to legal literacy. Law students in the UK <lb/>are often painstakingly aware of rules of plagiarism, citing and linking facts to <lb/>authorities. Perhaps it should come as no surprise that the very concept of adapting <lb/>another work and re-using it felt unnatural to them. <lb/>One thought for why it was so hard for the students to realise that it was a peer to peer <lb/>(two way) learning experience as much as a leader disseminated (one way activity) <lb/>was the nature of the delivery. Were they in the room physically they could have been <lb/>sitting with, walking around, or overhearing the group discussions. Perhaps one <lb/>student would have been integrated into each team of SFS playing the game. This <lb/>could have provided more content to stimulate discussion. Hopefully, in a post <lb/>pandemic world where face-to-face Street Law can resume, this will not be a problem. <lb/>When repeated, we might invite the students to learn more about the two-way process <lb/></body>

        <page>99 <lb/></page>

        <body>of public engagement before delivery, and take time to think about what they are <lb/>seeking to gain from the SFS. <lb/>Wallace and Perdue (2020) 22 published a study reflecting the views of 63 participants <lb/>in Street Law projects from multiple jurisdictions. Their study revealed five key <lb/>themes in student self-identified learning: explaining legal topics to lay audiences, <lb/>public speaking in a non-academic setting, building substantive legal content, <lb/>research and preparation and developing cultural competency and community <lb/>connections. The research highlighted the adaptation of lesson plans in Street Law, <lb/>but there was no further evidence that adapting resources was seen or viewed as a <lb/>skill by the students. Further, in many other research papers on student skills <lb/>development from both clinical legal education and more specifically Street Law; the <lb/>ability to adapt, develop and edit other people&apos;s work is rarely, if not ever, recognised. <lb/>Commercial awareness, adaptability (in terms of their own behaviour), and <lb/>innovation are recognised 23 , but specifically not the ability to adapt tools and <lb/>resources. Grimes et al (2011) 24 acknowledged the need to research materials already <lb/>available, but the skill of adapting open educational resources seems to be an area for <lb/>the Street Law community to explore with Law students both in terms of using, and <lb/>recognising as a valuable employability skill. <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>22 Wallace, A., &amp; Perdue, B. (2020). Preparing Lawyers for Practice: Developing Cultural Competency, <lb/>Communication Skills, and Content Knowledge through Street Law Programs. Journal of Legal Education <lb/>(forthcoming). <lb/>23 Thomas. L., 2018, &apos;It puts the law they&apos;ve learnt in theory into practice&apos;, Reimagining Clinical Legal <lb/>Education. Bloomsbury Publishing, 127-154. <lb/>24 Grimes. R, McQuoid-Mason. D, O&apos;Brien. E, Zimmer.J., (2011) StreetLaw and Social Justice Education The <lb/>Global Clinical Movement, 2011, Edited by Bloch. F., Oxford University Press. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>100 <lb/></page>

        <body>This small-scale case study does not seek to be that research. But given the difficulties <lb/>the team had in encouraging the students to adapt the materials (rather than just <lb/>reduce the number of cards in the game which were available to the SFS), it may <lb/>indicate a reluctance within Street Law students to develop and build on work already <lb/>in existence. We suggest this is an area for discussion and development within the <lb/>Street Law community. <lb/>As with many Street Law activities, really grasping the logistics of running a session <lb/>was one of the factors that needed to be stressed. For example, helping the Street Law <lb/>students to understand the importance of the SFS being comfortable with the cards, <lb/>giving them time to read the cards, and talking slowly and clearly through the rules. <lb/>As with many Street Law sessions, this was achieved with rehearsals and feedback. <lb/>Action Plan <lb/>As a point of principle, this work proved that Copyright the Card Game was a <lb/>resource that could be adapted for quite different audiences to the original intended <lb/>one. It also created an engaging session with SFS. The plan is to share the newly <lb/>created resource so it can be used in other Street Law projects or in schools who wish <lb/>to teach students about copyright and also to share this on the copyrightliteracy.org <lb/>website. The team plan to continue to work together to explore other audiences that <lb/>might benefit from engaging with copyright law using this resource. <lb/>We ran a further adaptation experience of Copyright the Card Game, at the Law <lb/>Society of Ireland orientation weekend in October 2021 (a weekend devoted to <lb/></body>


        <page>101 <lb/></page>

        <body>training trainee solicitors in Ireland to facilitate Street Law sessions in schools). By <lb/>contrast, here it was played with trainee solicitors who were learning about Street <lb/>Law. The game was played to demonstrate to them the art of adaptation and the link <lb/>between copyright and social justice. At the end of playing a significantly paired <lb/>down and compressed version of the game (partly due to time constraints), the <lb/>trainees were asked how copyright links with social justice issues. All the comments <lb/>were related to the right to protect your own work from abuse and exploitation. As a <lb/>twist, trainees were then shown a trailer for Paywall the Movie <lb/>(https://paywallthemovie.com/trailers 25 ) which is an open access documentary <lb/>highlighting the issues of academic writing (especially those coming from publicly <lb/>funded universities) being kept behind expensive paywalls and how this impacts on <lb/>society&apos;s ability to innovate -particularly with medical advances 26 . This additional <lb/>adaptation to the game further emphasised how it is about the discussion of legal <lb/>issues in society rather than participants of the game developing an intricate <lb/>knowledge of copyright law. <lb/>Giving it a Go <lb/>This article aims to inspire you to think about a broad range of topic areas for Street <lb/>Law projects and the social justice benefit in widening awareness about copyright, <lb/>especially in a post Covid19 world. Perhaps most importantly, we hope this article <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>25 &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/>26 The full version of the documentary is available here: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HM_nWsdbNvQ <lb/>&lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>102 <lb/></page>

        <body>will inspire you to think about how you can design Street Law projects which adapt <lb/>and develop already available open educational resources. For those looking for <lb/>existing open educational resources there are numerous collections online, but we <lb/>recommend the University of Edinburgh&apos;s guide to finding suitable resources. 27 When <lb/>re-using or re-purposes educational resources students need to be mindful of any <lb/>financial implications, copyright restrictions on any resources and of course ensuring <lb/>that they are jurisdiction appropriate. The key advantage of open educational <lb/>resources is that they are by definition free and openly licensed so can be freely reused <lb/>and adapted subject to the specific Creative Commons licence. However introducing <lb/>students to these resources can ultimately help them to focus the time they do have <lb/>on producing a better final Street Law session. As clinical legal education academics, <lb/>we must at all times remember the importance of the process on Street Law student <lb/>learning. How can we turn the art of adaption into learning rather than being viewed <lb/>(rightly or wrongly) by Law students as being a short cut to the final product. <lb/>Outside of the UK, Street Law students are perhaps more accustomed to working with <lb/>templates or adapting materials through the work of Street Law, Inc. 28 (providing <lb/>materials for use in the USA) and books like Democracy for all: education towards a <lb/>democratic culture by David McQuoid-Mason. 29 In clinical legal education, we strive <lb/>to develop innovative graduates who think and behave differently; we hope that this <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>27 https://open.ed.ac.uk/how-to-guides-old/where-to-find-oers/ &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/>28 https://www.streetlaw.org/ &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/>29 McQuoid-Mason, D. J. (1994). Democracy for all: education towards a democratic culture. Juta and <lb/>Company Ltd. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>103 <lb/></page>

        <body>article has encouraged you to consider teaching Street Law students about open <lb/>educational practices and Creative Commons materials, as well as the art of adapting. <lb/>We hope it persuades you to approach and encourage your institution to promote <lb/>openness within practice both within and outside of clinical legal education. This final <lb/>quote from one of the Street Law students sums up the benefit he saw: <lb/>&quot;Adapting the game in light of all of these considerations (the knowledge of our <lb/>participants, the length of our session and the impact of COVID-19 on both us and the <lb/>participants) was a challenging but incredibly useful exercise. I enjoyed &apos;thinking <lb/>outside the box&apos; with the added benefit of &apos;standing on the shoulders of giants&apos;. If we <lb/>had started from scratch, I do feel that our session would have been much less successful. <lb/>In fact, I used the skills that I developed in adapting this activity in my final project, <lb/>which was an adaptation of another street law activity. In turn, I managed to go even <lb/>further in my final project.&quot; <lb/>The open access resources for Copyright the Card Game are available for download <lb/>from the www.copyrightliteracy.org website 30 . <lb/>A special thank you goes to Ms Dene at Seven Kings School for facilitating the game. <lb/>Without her enthusiasm present in the classroom, this workshop and trial would not <lb/>have been possible during the pandemic. <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>30 See https://copyrightliteracy.org/resources/copyright-the-card-game/ &lt;accessed 13.06.2022&gt;. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>104 <lb/></page>

        <body>Image of SFSs participating </body>


	</text>
</tei>
