<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Atomic structure of tip apex for spin-polarized scanning tunneling<lb/> microscopy<lb/> G. Rodary, a񮽙 J.-C. Girard, L. Largeau, C. David, O. Mauguin, and Z.-Z. Wang<lb/> Laboratoire de Photonique et de Nanostructures, CNRS, Route de Nozay, 91460 Marcoussis, France<lb/> 񮽙Received 27 December 2010; accepted 3 February 2011; published online 24 February 2011񮽙<lb/></front>

			<p>We present a high resolution transmission electron microscopy study of a Cr-coated W tip apex<lb/> prepared for spin-polarized scanning tunneling microscopy 񮽙SP-STM񮽙. The characterization of the<lb/> tip apex structure has been done with atomic resolution. We show that the Cr film is epitaxially<lb/> grown on W and presents a monocrystalline phase. The surface analysis of the apex reveals<lb/> roughness which gives rise to structures that can be considered as nanotips. In spite of the<lb/> monocrystalline structure of these nanotips, we show that their spin arrangement and resulting<lb/> magnetization direction cannot be controlled.</p>

			<front>SP-STM measurements on a Cr/MgO񮽙001񮽙 sample<lb/> confirm this conclusion. © 2011 American Institute of Physics. 񮽙doi:10.1063/1.3558920񮽙<lb/></front>

			<p>Spin-polarized scanning tunneling microscopy 񮽙SP-<lb/>STM񮽙 is a technique sensitive to the orientation of the local<lb/> magnetization of a sample surface. This sensitivity relies on<lb/> the magnetization direction of the apex of the STM tip. Since<lb/> early SP-STM works, it is well established that proper tip<lb/> preparation and characterization is a important first step to be<lb/> able to measure samples reliably. 1 It has also been proposed<lb/> that the tip magnetic sensitivity, namely sensitivity to the<lb/> in-plane or out-of-plane component of the sample magneti-<lb/>zation, could change depending on the thickness of the mag-<lb/>netic layer that composes the magnetic tip. 1 Recently, it has<lb/> been shown that the magnetic properties of a tip are mainly<lb/> determined by the atomic arrangement of the tip apex, i.e.,<lb/> the very last atoms of the tip which contribute to the tunnel-<lb/>ing current. 2–5 Indeed, the spin orientation at the apex di-<lb/>rectly results from its structural atomic arrangement. While<lb/> SP-STM tip characterization is crucial to analyze spin-<lb/>polarized measurements, only few studies have focused on<lb/> this topic. It is intrinsically difficult to determine the tip apex<lb/> atomic arrangement from STM imaging since images depend<lb/> on the convolution of both the tip and sample configuration,<lb/> and hence an alternative experimental characterization<lb/> method is needed. Recently, field emission microscopy and<lb/> field ion microscopy studies, associated with spin polariza-<lb/>tion measurements, have been made on W tips coated with<lb/> ferromagnetic films. 6,7 Irisawa et al. 6 found that the magnetic<lb/> layer deposited on W is most likely noncrystalline. The ori-<lb/>entation of the spin polarization of the tip apex was found to<lb/> be tilted, neither in-plane nor out-of-plane.<lb/></p>

			<p>In this letter, we present a high resolution transmission<lb/> electron microscopy 񮽙HRTEM񮽙 study of the apex of a Cr-<lb/>coated W tip prepared for SP-STM, combined with SP-STM<lb/> measurements done with another identically prepared tip.<lb/></p>

			<p>For the first time, it has been possible to visualize the atomic<lb/> arrangement of crystalline Cr layers deposited on the apex of<lb/> an W tip. We show that the W tip apex presents a 񮽙110񮽙<lb/> orientation and that the Cr is epitaxially grown on the apex<lb/> following the same orientation. The thickness and roughness<lb/> of the Cr thin film at the end of the tip were also character-<lb/>ized by HRTEM, enabling us to propose a microscopic de-<lb/>scription of the spin polarization of the tip. In order to assure<lb/> the validity of our tip characterization for SP-STM studies,<lb/> we have performed STM measurements on a model Cr񮽙001񮽙<lb/> surface and we show that an expected spin polarized contrast<lb/> is obtained.<lb/></p>

			<p>Our STM tips were prepared from a 0.25 mm W poly-<lb/>crystalline wire. They were electrochemically etched in a<lb/> NaOH solution and then passivated in a HF bath. The quality<lb/> of this etching procedure and the global apex shape was<lb/> checked by scanning electron microscopy. The tips were then<lb/> introduced into an ultrahigh vacuum 񮽙UHV񮽙 preparation<lb/> chamber connected to the STM chamber. There, they were<lb/> flashed by Joule heating to temperature up to white color<lb/> emission. This procedure allows the removal of contaminants<lb/> and oxides from the apex. Bode 1 suggests that such flashing<lb/> induces melting of the apex and that a dense-packed surface<lb/> of W, i.e., W񮽙110񮽙, is probably formed at its end. After this<lb/> treatment, Cr was deposited in situ onto the tips by electron<lb/> beam evaporation at a rate of around one atomic layer per<lb/> minute. One tip was transferred under UHV to the cold STM<lb/> head where experiments were perform at 4 K, while the sec-<lb/>ond was taken out from the UHV chamber, glued on a stan-<lb/>dard TEM copper ring and subsequently analyzed by TEM.<lb/> Electron microscopy was perform on a Jeol 2200 FS<lb/> TEM-STEM microscope equipped with C S -probe aberration<lb/> correction. Figure 1񮽙a񮽙 shows a TEM image of the overview<lb/> a񮽙<lb/> Electronic mail: guillemin.rodary@lpn.cnrs.fr.<lb/> FIG. 1. 񮽙Color online񮽙 񮽙a񮽙 TEM image of a W tip coated by Cr. The dark<lb/> contrast corresponds to the W and the bright one to the Cr coating layers. 񮽙b񮽙<lb/> Electron diffraction pattern of the tip apex. Two lattices corresponding to Cr<lb/> and W are visible and labeled, demonstrating the epitaxial relation Cr񮽙110񮽙/<lb/> W񮽙110񮽙. An additional lattice 񮽙not labeled񮽙 is also visible and is ascribed to<lb/> Cr oxide present at the Cr surface.<lb/> APPLIED PHYSICS LETTERS 98, 082505 񮽙2011񮽙<lb/> 0003-6951/2011/98񮽙8񮽙/082505/3/$30.00<lb/> © 2011 American Institute of Physics<lb/> 98, 082505-1<lb/> Downloaded 20 Sep 2011 to 193.48.163.6. Redistribution subject to AIP license or copyright; see http://apl.aip.org/about/rights_and_permissions<lb/> of the tip end. Due to their large mass difference and relative<lb/> thickness, different electron transmissions result from W and<lb/> Cr. The W tip is thus well identifiable by the black contrast<lb/> and the Cr coating by a brighter layer. This image displays<lb/> the quality of the Cr deposition at the very end of the tip but<lb/> also shows columnar structures on the tip sides due to<lb/> shadow effects during evaporation. The thickness of the Cr<lb/> layer is determined by TEM imaging to be 50񮽙 5 nm, con-<lb/>sistent with our evaporation calibration. In Fig. 2񮽙a񮽙 we<lb/> present a HRTEM image of the tip apex and in Fig. 2񮽙b񮽙 a<lb/> magnification of an apex area where atomic layers are clearly<lb/> observable. Figures 1 and 2񮽙a񮽙 evidence the low roughness of<lb/> the W, while it is obvious from Fig. 2 that the last Cr layers<lb/> present three-dimensional structures of few nanometers. Fig-<lb/>ure 1񮽙b񮽙 presents an electron diffraction pattern of the tip<lb/> apex containing both W and Cr. Two neighboring spot fami-<lb/>lies are clearly observable and are indexed on Fig. 1񮽙b񮽙. The<lb/> first one corresponds to the bulk W lattice parameter and<lb/> the second to bulk Cr, indicating a fully relaxed structure.<lb/> The diffraction pattern shows unambiguously that an epitax-<lb/>ial relationship exists between Cr and W, with both axial<lb/> and radial parallel directions: 񮽙110񮽙Cr 񮽙 񮽙110񮽙W and<lb/> 񮽙100񮽙Cr 񮽙 񮽙100񮽙W. This shows that the treated W tip presents<lb/> a monocrystalline phase at its apex, in spite of the use of an<lb/> usual polycrystalline W wire, as previously suggested, 1,6 and<lb/> that the Cr is epitaxially grown on it. The atomic arrange-<lb/>ment along the 񮽙110񮽙 direction is visible in Fig. 2񮽙b񮽙, which<lb/> confirms that the crystalline order remains until the last Cr<lb/> layers. Chemical analysis have been performed by energy-<lb/>dispersive x-ray spectroscopy at different zones along the tip<lb/> axis. Only W and Cr species were detected by this technique<lb/> 񮽙in exception to oxygen near the surface, originating from<lb/> natural in-air oxidation, in agreement with electron diffrac-<lb/>tion񮽙, confirming the absence of contamination on the tip<lb/> apex.<lb/> The analysis of the HRTEM results implies several con-<lb/>siderations on the apex structure important for SP-STM. We<lb/> can conclude from the observation of the monocrystalline<lb/> phase of the tip apex that the Cr atoms which contribute to<lb/> the spin polarized tunneling current forms a Cr񮽙110񮽙 surface.<lb/> This finding is of major importance as an input for first-<lb/>principle calculations which simulate SP-STM results by tak-<lb/>ing into account tips structure. 3,8 Furthermore, an epitaxial<lb/> surface on the tip apex gives rise to a clearly defined elec-<lb/>tronic structure that contributes to the tunneling effect, while<lb/> a flatter and smoothed density of states arises from polycrys-<lb/>talline apex.<lb/> From this Cr apex atomic arrangement it is naturally<lb/> tempting to deduce also a spin structure of the atoms con-<lb/>tributing to the tunnel current. The 񮽙110񮽙 Cr surface presents<lb/> an antiferromagnetic order with alternative atomic rows of<lb/> opposite spins along the 񮽙001񮽙 direction. 9 If the tip apex<lb/> would present such an ideal surface, no clear magnetic con-<lb/>trast would be observed by SP-STM since the same quanti-<lb/>ties of up and down spins would contribute to the tunneling<lb/> current. However, this ideal surface does not seem to exist in<lb/> our case. Looking at the overall structure of the apex shown<lb/> in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>, the foremost atoms of the apex are not organized as<lb/> a flat surface but rather in three-dimensional clusters. These<lb/> 10 nm clusters probably form the real tip, i.e., the ensemble<lb/> of atoms on which the spin resolved density of states that<lb/> contributes to the tunneling process depends. Even if these<lb/> clusters present a monocrystalline phase, as they appear to in<lb/> Figs. 1񮽙b񮽙 and 2񮽙b񮽙, the absolute orientation of this phase as<lb/> compared to the tip axis cannot be known from one tip to an<lb/> other. Therefore, the foremost spin of the apex which dictates<lb/> the spin orientation of the tip can probably take any direction<lb/> independent of the macroscopic crystalline arrangement of<lb/> the apex. To clean our tip in situ, we pulse the tip-sample<lb/> bias voltage, which frequently can remove material from the<lb/> tip, such as one of these clusters. The spin structure, and<lb/> therefore also the spin sensitivity of the tip, can thus be<lb/> changed by this procedure. An important conclusion is de-<lb/>duced from this result: the spin structure of the apex cannot<lb/> be controlled by the tip preparation. The determination of the<lb/> spin sensitivity of the tip should not rely on the tip prepara-<lb/>tion but rather on in situ characterization of tip magnetization<lb/> by techniques like in field measurement as previously<lb/> proposed. 2<lb/></p>

			<p>These findings concerning control of the tip apex spin<lb/> structure and magnetic sensitivity should have consequences<lb/> on SP-STM measurements. In order to confirm this point, we<lb/> performed STM measurements using a coated Cr tip. As a<lb/> test sample, we chose the Cr񮽙001񮽙 surface whose spin struc-<lb/>ture is suitable for easy magnetic contrast detection. 10,11 But<lb/> instead of using bulk Cr monocrystal, whose surface prepa-<lb/>ration is experimentally very demanding, 12 we rather chose<lb/> an original and new way to prepare Cr񮽙001񮽙 by thin film<lb/> deposition on a MgO񮽙001񮽙 substrate. 13,14 In order to mini-<lb/>mize surface contamination originating from the substrate,<lb/> we cleave a 200 񮽙m thick MgO񮽙001񮽙 substrate in UHV, fol-<lb/>lowing the semiconductor cleavage technique we used for<lb/> cross-sectional STM experiments. 15 We then deposit on the<lb/> cleaved side a 30 nm thick Cr film by thermal evaporation at<lb/> 300 ° C.<lb/> An STM structural study of the Cr sample reveals the<lb/> presence of three-dimensional structures on the surface, such<lb/> as square base pyramids or spirals. 13 These structures are<lb/> formed by stacking of small monoatomic terraces which<lb/> present a statistically predominant 񮽙110񮽙 orientation, as ex-<lb/>pected from the epitaxial relation 񮽙110񮽙񮽙001񮽙bcc-Cr 񮽙 񮽙100񮽙<lb/> 񮽙񮽙001񮽙MgO. 14 STM images are made using a Cr tip at a<lb/> temperature of 4 K. If dI / dV images do not present any spin<lb/> polarized contrast, voltage pulses are performed in order to<lb/> change the atomic scale structure of the tip apex until obtain-<lb/>ing the expected magnetic contrast. The success of this pro-<lb/>cedure confirms the validity of the image described above of<lb/> FIG. 2. 񮽙Color online񮽙 񮽙a񮽙 HRTEM image of the W tip apex where the Cr/W<lb/> interface is clearly visible. The last Cr layers present roughness of few<lb/> nanometers. 񮽙b񮽙 Magnification of the red square depicted in 񮽙a񮽙. Atomic rows<lb/> are observed until the last Cr layers. The arrow indicates the 񮽙110񮽙 crystal-<lb/>line orientation.<lb/> 082505-2<lb/> Rodary et al.<lb/></p>

			<bibl>Appl. Phys. Lett. 98, 082505 񮽙2011񮽙<lb/> Downloaded 20 Sep 2011 to 193.48.163.6. Redistribution</bibl>

			<p>subject to AIP license or copyright; see http://apl.aip.org/about/rights_and_permissions<lb/> a cluster-tip that can change under voltages pulses. <ref type="figure">Figure 3<lb/></ref> shows topographic and differential conductance dI / dV maps<lb/> of the same area presenting a succession of narrow mono-<lb/>atomic terraces. The dI / dV map presents alternative bright<lb/> and dark contrast from one terrace to the adjacent one, which<lb/> is expected for spin resolved mapping. 10,11<lb/></p>

			<p>In conclusion, we show by HRTEM that Cr deposited on<lb/> the apex of a flashed W tip is monocrystalline and presents a<lb/> well defined epitaxial relation with the W apex surface. In<lb/> spite of this well ordered tip, the apex surface presents nano-<lb/>clusters, or nanotips, which determine the properties of the<lb/> tunneling current, such as the spin sensitivity. The foremost<lb/> spins of the apex that contribute to the tunneling current are<lb/> therefore most probably always in a canted direction as com-<lb/>pare to the tip axis, and should thus result in both in-plane<lb/> and out-of-plane sensitivity. SP-STM experiments show that<lb/> such a tip can go through spin sensitive or insensitive states<lb/> under pulse induced atomic rearrangement.<lb/> This project has been partially funded by the Triangle de<lb/> la Physique, project SPECTMAG 2008-048T.<lb/></p>

			<note place="footnote">1</note>

			<bibl>M. Bode, Rep. Prog. Phys. 66, 523 񮽙2003񮽙.<lb/> 2 G. Rodary, S. Wedekind, H. Oka, D. Sander, and J. Kirschner, Appl. Phys.<lb/> Lett. 95, 152513 񮽙2009񮽙.<lb/> 3 M. Czerner, G. Rodary, S. Wedekind, D. V. Fedorov, D. Sander, I. Mertig,<lb/> and J. Kirschner, J. Magn. Magn. Mater. 322, 1416 񮽙2010񮽙.<lb/> 4 M. Ziegler, N. Ruppelt, N. Neel, J. Kroger, and R. Berndt, Appl. Phys.<lb/> Lett. 96, 132505 񮽙2010񮽙.<lb/> 5 A. Schlenhoff, S. Krause, G. Herzog, and R. Wiesendanger, Appl. Phys.<lb/> Lett. 97, 083104 񮽙2010񮽙.<lb/> 6 T. Irisawa, T. K. Yamada, and T. Mizoguchi, New J. Phys. 11, 113031<lb/> 񮽙2009񮽙.<lb/> 7 Y. R. Niu and M. S. Altman, Surf. Sci. 604, 1055 񮽙2010񮽙.<lb/> 8 P. Ferriani, C. Lazo, and S. Heinze, Phys. Rev. B 82, 054411 񮽙2010񮽙.<lb/> 9 B. Santos, J. M. Puerta, J. I. Cerda, R. Stumpf, K. v. Bergmann, R. Wie-<lb/>sendanger, M. Bode, K. F. McCarty, and J. d. l. Figuera, New J. Phys. 10,<lb/> 013005 񮽙2008񮽙.<lb/> 10 M. Kleiber, M. Bode, R. Ravlicacute, and R. Wiesendanger, Phys. Rev.<lb/> Lett. 85, 4606 񮽙2000񮽙.<lb/> 11 A. Li Bassi, C. S. Casari, D. Cattaneo, F. Donati, S. Foglio, M. Passoni, C.<lb/> E. Bottani, P. Biagioni, A. Brambilla, M. Finazzi, F. Ciccacci, and L. Duo,<lb/> Appl. Phys. Lett. 91, 173120 񮽙2007񮽙.<lb/> 12 M. Schmid, M. Pinczolits, W. Hebenstreit, and P. Varga, Surf. Sci. 377–<lb/> 379, 1023 񮽙1997񮽙.<lb/> 13 T. Kawagoe, Y. Iguchi, T. Miyamachi, A. Yamasaki, and S. Suga, Phys.<lb/> Rev. Lett. 95, 207205 񮽙2005񮽙.<lb/> 14 H. Oka and K. Sueoka, J. Appl. Phys. 99, 08D302 񮽙2006񮽙.<lb/> 15 J.-C. Girard, A. Lemaitre, A. Miard, C. David, and Z. Z. Wang, J. Vac. Sci.<lb/> Technol. B 27, 891 񮽙2009񮽙.<lb/> FIG. 3. 񮽙Color online񮽙 Images of successive monoatomic Cr񮽙001񮽙 terraces.<lb/> Left:</bibl>

			<figure>
				<figDesc>topographic image and scan line done on the black line. Right: dI / dV<lb/> mapping of the same area. Images are performed at 4 K and with stabiliza-<lb/>tion parameters of 1 nA and 0.15 V. Bright and dark alternative contrast is<lb/> ascribed to spin polarized sensitivity. Arrows show schematically the alter-<lb/>native spin orientation of each</figDesc>

			</figure>

			<bibl>terrace.<lb/> 082505-3<lb/> Rodary et al.<lb/> Appl. Phys. Lett. 98, 082505 񮽙2011񮽙<lb/> Downloaded 20 Sep 2011 to 193.48.163.6. Redistribution subject to AIP license or copyright; see http://apl.aip.org/about/rights_and_permissions</bibl>


	</text>
</tei>
