<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ZFN-A-054-0304-0272"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">272<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Exact Solitary-wave Solutions for the General<lb/> Fifth-order Shallow Water-wave Models<lb/> Notes<lb/> (tanh^): -2^(0 [-840a/#2« ^(O"<lb/> Woo-Pyo Hong and Young-</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dae Jung''<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Physics, Catholic University of Taegu-Hyosung,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hayang, Kyongsan, Kyungbuk 712-702, South Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>* Department of Physics, Hanyang University, Ansan,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kyunggi-Do 425-791, South Korea<lb/></address>

	<reference>Z. Naturforsch. 54 a, 272-273 (1999);<lb/></reference>

	<note type="submission">received December 15, 1998<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">We perform a computerized symbolic computation to find<lb/> some general solitonic solutions forthe general fifth-order shal-<lb/>low water-wave models. Applying the tanh-typed method, we<lb/> have found certain new exact solitary wave solutions. The pre-<lb/>viously published solutions turn out to be special cases with<lb/> restricted model parameters.<lb/> We investigate the generalized fifth-order shallow<lb/> water-wave model which describes certain physically-<lb/>interesting (1 + l)-dimensional waves but is not integra-<lb/>ble by the conventional methods [1]:<lb/> + 2qvv^ + 3rv^v^ = 0,<lb/> (1)<lb/> where a, fi, y, q, and r are model parameters, i; is a real<lb/> scalar function of the two independent variables, x and t,<lb/> and the subscripts denote partial derivatives.<lb/> We apply the tanh-typed method [2-4] with symbolic<lb/> computation to (1) and assume that the physical field<lb/> V (JC, 0 has the form<lb/> N<lb/> v{x, /) = S<lb/> (0 @BULLET tanh" [^(0X + @BULLET»(/)], (2)<lb/> n=0<lb/> where N is an integer determined via the balance of the<lb/> highest-order contributions from the linear and non-<lb/>linear terms of (1) as N=2, while/^;v(0, ^(0. and<lb/> are the non-trivial differentiable functions to be deter-<lb/>mined.<lb/> With the symbolic computation package Maple we<lb/> introduce Ansatz (2) together with the above conditions<lb/> into (1) and collect the coefficients of like powers of tanh:<lb/> (tanh'): -6^2(0^(0<lb/> @BULLET [r^^itf + 16/^(0^2(0 + nOa(^{tf\ (3)</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
