<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1136451-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1136451" kind="B1" date="20031022"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23237814" ucid="EP-1136451-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1136451</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20031022</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01302596-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01302596</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010321</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-534905" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>534905</doc-number><date>20000323</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-53490500-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>53490500</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000323</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new" /><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B   5/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B   5/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B   5/167       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B   5/225       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B   5/235       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F23L  15/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F23L  15/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F23L  15/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F23L  17/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F23L  17/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C03B5/235</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C03B5/235B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Glasschmelzverfahren und Ofen dafür mit Sauerstoff-Brennstoffverbrennung in der Schmelzzone und Luft-Brennstoffverbrennung in der Lauterzone</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Glass melting process and furnace therefor with oxy-fuel combustion over melting zone and air-fuel combustion over fining zone</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Procédé de fusion de verre et four pour appliquer ledit procédé avec combustion par oxygène-carburant dans la zone de fusion et combustion par air-carburant dans la zone de raffinage</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>AIR PROD &amp; CHEM</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>ENG ROBERT MICHAEL</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HOKE BRYAN CLAIR</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>INSKIP JULIAN LEONARD</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>LIEVRE KEVIN ALAN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>MARCHIANDO ROBERT DEAN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SLAVEJKOV ALEKSANDAR GEORGI</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>ENG, ROBERT MICHAEL</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>HOKE, BRYAN CLAIR</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>INSKIP, JULIAN LEONARD</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>LIEVRE, KEVIN ALAN</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>MARCHIANDO, ROBERT DEAN</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SLAVEJKOV, ALEKSANDAR GEORGI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>ENG, ROBERT MICHAEL</last-name><address><street>17595 Harvard, #C1008</street><city>CA 92614</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>LIEVRE, KEVIN ALAN</last-name><address><street>1115 Greenleaf Circle</street><city>Allentown, PA 18103</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>HOKE, BRYAN CLAIR</last-name><address><street>234 Longwood Drive</street><city>Bethlehem, PA 18020</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>INSKIP, JULIAN LEONARD</last-name><address><street>12 Waterside Cottages, Cholmondeley Road, Wrenbury</street><city>Nantwich, Cheshire CW5 8GZ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>MARCHIANDO, ROBERT DEAN</last-name><address><street>1176 Sharonbrook Drive</street><city>Twinsburg, OH 44087</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>SLAVEJKOV, ALEKSANDAR GEORGI</last-name><address><street>216 Murray Drive</street><city>Allentown, PA 18104</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</last-name><address><street>7201 Hamilton Boulevard</street><city>Allentown, PA 18195-1501</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Burford, Anthony Frederick</last-name><address><street>W.H. Beck, Greener &amp;amp; Co. 7 Stone Buildings Lincoln's Inn</street><city>London WC2A 3SZ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>Glass forming ingredients are melted in a furnace (140; 200) having a melting zone (184; 236) and a fining zone (170; 270) and in which the majority of the combustion energy (172-184; 238-248) over the melting zone (184; 236) is provided by oxy-fuel combustion while a majority of the combustion energy (164-168; 224-234) over the fining zone (170; 270) is provided by air-fuel combustion. Preferably greater than 70% and up to and including 100% of the combustion energy (172-184; 238-248) over the melting zone (184; 236) is provided by oxy-fuel combustion and greater than 70% and up to and including 100% of the combustion energy (164-168; 224-234) over the fining zone (170; 270) is provided by air-fuel combustion. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">Glass forming ingredients are melted in a furnace (140; 200) having a melting
zone (184; 236) and a fining zone (170; 270) and in which the majority of the
combustion energy (172-184; 238-248) over the melting zone (184; 236) is provided by
oxy-fuel combustion while a majority of the combustion energy (164-168; 224-234) over
the fining zone (170; 270) is provided by air-fuel combustion. Preferably greater than
70% and up to and including 100% of the combustion energy (172-184; 238-248) over
the melting zone (184; 236) is provided by oxy-fuel combustion and greater than 70%
and up to and including 100% of the combustion energy (164-168; 224-234) over the
fining zone (170; 270) is provided by air-fuel combustion.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1136555-A1-00000001" he="78" wi="89" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a process and furnace for melting glass forming
ingredients. In the typical glass melting furnace, or glass tank as it is commonly referred
to, the raw glass making materials, termed batch, are charged into the melting zone of
the furnace. Glass tanks are operated continuously and therefore there is an existing
bath of molten glass, termed melt, in the melting zone onto which the raw material is
placed. The molten glass and unmelted batch are collectively referred to as the charge.
The raw batch may be charged into the tank by any of the well-known mechanical
charging devices. In practice, the batch materials float on the surface of the molten bath
forming a semi-submerged layer containing unmelted solids termed a batch blanket.
The blanket sometimes breaks up to form separate batch piles or batch islands (also
called rafts or logs). For the purposes of this disclosure, the section of the furnace
containing significant unmelted batch solids floating on the surface of a molten glass
bath is defined as the melting zone.</p><p num="0002">The glass tank usually consists of the melting zone and the fining zone. For the
purpose of this disclosure, the fining zone is defined as that section of the furnace not
containing significant unmelted batch solids floating on the surface of a molten glass
bath. Foam or scum may be present on the surface of the molten glass bath in the
fining zone or it may be clear, termed &quot;mirror surface&quot; glass. In the fining zone, glass is
homogenized and defects, such as bubbles or &quot;seeds&quot; are driven out. Glass is
continuously withdrawn from the fining zone. The melting zone and the fining zone of a
glass tank may be present in a single chamber or the glass tank may consist of two or
more connected and distinct chambers.</p><p num="0003">Glass has historically been melted in air-fuel furnaces where burners direct
flames across molten glass and the exhaust gas from the flames is removed through
heat recovery devices to improve the overall furnace efficiency, thereby reducing fuel
consumption. Recuperators and regenerators are common heat recovery devices used
in the glass industry. A recuperator is typically a metallic shell-and-tube-style heat
exchanger that indirectly heats the combustion air with the heat removed from exhaust
gases. In the case of regenerators, the exhaust gas passes through the regenerators
transferring its heat to the checker packing or other heat storage media within the 
regenerator. The checker packing is generally constructed from refractory material.
The regenerator may be a common chamber per each side of the furnace, a number of
separate and distinct chambers attached to the furnace or may be incorporated into the
burner supply ducting. The heated packing is used to preheat combustion air which is
combined with fuel used to produce the flames during the firing cycle of the heating
operation. These heat recovery devices are costly and sometimes limit the furnace life
due to design limitations, failure caused by thermal shock to the refractory, corrosion, or
plugging. Occasionally glass is melted in a unit melter which is a furnace without a heat
recovery device to preheat combustion air.</p><p num="0004">In the case of regenerators, the thermal storage medium, i.e. the checkers,
become plugged by condensed volatiles and particulates from the glass melting
process, resulting in insufficient flow of combustion air to the ports. Consequently, glass
manufacturers routinely clean out the checker packs to maintain air flow. The plugging
problem is noticeably worse for the ports connected to the melting zone of the furnace.
The buildup in the regenerator packing which is contacted by gases from the melting
zone of the furnace is often viscous and difficult to remove. Controlling buildup of
material on the checker packing of a regenerator is the subject of <ref type="patent">US-A-5,840,093</ref>. The
buildup in the down tank checkers which is contacted by gases from the fining zone of
the furnace is drier and more powdery resulting in easier removal of the buildup.
Because of the less aggressive attack, down tank checkers have been used for more
than one furnace campaign.</p><p num="0005">Near the end of a furnace campaign, it is sometimes the case that the checkers
become too badly degraded, at times even collapsing, and sufficient air flow is not
possible even after a clean out. The problem usually manifests itself in the regenerator
section receiving gases from the melting zone of the furnace. Oxygen enhanced
combustion technologies have been used in these &quot;crippled&quot; air-fuel furnaces to extend
the furnace life. While the oxygen enhanced combustion technologies do not prevent
the checker plugging problem, they do provide a method to continue furnace operation,
albeit sometimes with a higher operating cost.</p><p num="0006">Industrial oxygen has been used to enhance combustion in the glass industry for
several decades. Oxygen enhanced combustion can be accomplished by (i)
supplemental oxy-fuel burners, (ii) premixed oxygen enrichment of the combustion air, 
or (iii) lancing of oxygen to the port or burner. Supplemental oxy-fuel is the practice of
installing one or more oxy-fuel burners into an air-fuel furnace. Premixed oxygen
enrichment is the practice of introducing oxygen into the combustion air usually to a
level of up to 30% total contained oxygen (i.e., 9% oxygen enrichment). The amount of
oxygen enrichment is limited by materials compatibility issues in highly oxidizing
environments. Lancing is the practice of strategically injecting oxygen through a lance
into the combustion zone. These oxygen enhancing techniques are applied to furnaces
with burners having standard air-fuel designs. The basic air-fuel furnace concept has
not been significantly modified to apply the above mentioned oxygen enrichment
technologies.</p><p num="0007">Supplemental oxy-fuel combustion has been applied to air-fuel glass furnaces
and has shown benefits. One form of supplemental oxy-fuel combustion is commonly
referred to as oxy-fuel boosting. Oxy-fuel boosting is a technology where oxy-fuel
burners are added to an air-fuel furnace. Two locations for the oxy-fuel burners have
been proposed: near the hot spot position and in the zero port position. Typically the
oxy-fuel burners fire constantly, even during the reversal cycle of a regenerative
furnace.</p><p num="0008">The rationale for putting the oxy-fuel burners in the hot spot position is to
reinforce the hot spot with additional heat to positively influence the convective flow
patterns in the glass melt and, as described in several patents, to affect the position of
the batch-line. The overall glass flow pattern is strongly influenced by buoyancy driven
flow and the temperature profile in the furnace is important for the buoyancy driven flow.
Ultimately the glass quality is affected. This is why glass-makers control and monitor
the temperature profile in a furnace.</p><p num="0009">Similar to the hot spot oxy-fuel boost, <ref type="patent">US-A-3,592,623</ref> discloses a process and
furnace where at least part of the furnace heating is provided by an oxy-fuel flame from
a position downstream of the hot spot. The combustion products of the flame impinge
on the unmelted glass making materials (i.e. the batch) causing the unmelted materials
to remain near the feed end of the tank until melted. An objective is to control the
position of the unmelted batch material (batch-line) in the glass tank. The remaining
heating is provided by air-fuel combustion as shown in the figures of <ref type="patent">US-A-3,592,623</ref>. </p><p num="0010"><ref type="patent">US-A-4,473,388</ref> discloses an oxy-fuel boost process where the oxy-fuel flames
cover substantially the whole width of the furnace and are directed at the batch-line.</p><p num="0011"><ref type="patent">US-A-5,139,558</ref> discloses a process where at least part of the furnace heating is
provided by at least one flame from at least one oxy-fuel burner located in the roof of the
furnace, the position of the burner being such that the tip of its flame is directed
approximately at the batch-line. An objective of both of <ref type="patent">US-A-3,592,623</ref> and <ref type="patent">US-A-5,139,558</ref>
processes is to increase the melting rate of the solid glass forming materials
and control the batch-line position.</p><p num="0012">Oxy-fuel firing over the down tank molten glass in a regenerative or recuperative
air-fuel furnace is the subject of <ref type="patent">US-A-5,116,399</ref>. The object of this disclosure is to use
an oxy-fuel flame with velocity greater than 100 m/sec to sweep unmelted glass forming
ingredients floating on the surface of the melt in the vicinity of the glass outlet to prevent
any unmelted glass forming ingredients from entering the glass outlet. Use of
supplemental oxy-fuel burners combined with the oxy-fuel burner for sweeping unmelted
glass forming ingredients within the air-fuel furnace configuration is also disclosed.</p><p num="0013">Supplemental oxy-fuel boost of an air-fuel regenerative furnace is disclosed in
<ref type="patent">US-A-5,147,438</ref> where the oxy-fuel auxiliary burner is bent, angled, or inclined to direct
its flame toward the batch-line or in the vicinity of the batch-line.</p><p num="0014">As an alternative to the hot spot position, oxy-fuel boost can be placed at the
charge end of a furnace. In a side-fired furnace, this is commonly referred to as the
zero port position. It is the space between the charge end-wall and the first air-fuel port,
The rationale for this location is higher heat transfer rates from the hot oxy-fuel flames to
the cold batch. Zero port oxy-fuel boosting is a common method used by industry and is
described in Hope and Schemberg (1997). This reference teaches that as a result of
more intense radiant heat transfer to the cold batch from the oxy-fuel boost flame,
earlier batch fritting and glazing occurs than is possible with just air-fuel melting. The
percentage of oxy-fuel firing for the zero port boosting technology has been
approximately up to 15% of the total firing rate and is often limited by the maximum
allowable temperature of the superstructure refractory. Using zero port oxy-fuel
boosting, production increases on the order of 5 to 10% have been achieved with
simultaneous glass quality improvement. </p><p num="0015"><ref type="patent">US-A-4,531,960</ref> (corresponding to <ref type="patent">EP-A-0127513</ref>) teaches zero port oxy-fuel
boosting where the supplemental (auxiliary) oxy-fuel flames are surrounded with a
current of auxiliary gas where the auxiliary gas is preferably air and directing the
auxiliary gas towards the batch clods (unmelted batch piles or islands). One of the
objectives of the auxiliary gas is to eliminate the use of water cooling of the oxy-fuel
burner which was a common feature of oxy-fuel burners at the time of the patent filing.
Those skilled in the art of NOx technologies will readily appreciate that practice of this
teaching would result in an increased NOx formation since the nitrogen from the air
would mix in the high temperature oxy-fuel flame.</p><p num="0016">Practice of these supplemental oxy-fuel technologies without high NOx formation
rates, requires special methodologies.</p><p num="0017">An extension of the supplemental oxy-fuel technologies would be to combine the
zero port and hot spot oxy-fuel boosting to capture the benefits of improved melting in
the melting zone and batch-line control. This process, however, is likely to particularly
cause concern over an increase in the propensity for NOx formation because there will
be more of the hotter oxy-fuel flames available to form NOx with the migrating nitrogen
from the air-fuel combustion section. Thus, a process utilizing both air-fuel and oxy-fuel
combustion in the same furnace without taking into consideration the problem of NOx
formation would be an incomplete solution.</p><p num="0018">To minimize formation of NOx associated with increasing supplemental oxy-fuel
in air-fuel furnaces, there has been a general trend in the glass industry to convert from
air-fuel firing to full oxy-fuel firing. In this manner, the NOx forming nitrogen is
eliminated as part of the feed to the burners. Because of this NOx issue and other
issues, the move to full oxy-fuel is the obvious choice if increasing use of oxy-fuel is
desired especially at levels suitable for an on-site generated supply of oxygen. In
contrast to oxygen enhanced combustion technologies, significant modifications are
made to a furnace to apply full oxy-fuel combustion in furnaces. In full oxy-fuel
furnaces, air for combustion is replaced by industrial oxygen with purity typically
between 90 and 100%. Heat recovery devices used in air-fuel furnaces such as
regenerators and recuperators are generally not used after the furnace has been
converted to oxy-fuel. Different burners and flow systems are used and the general 
layout of the burners and exhausts is almost always different than previous air-fuel
furnace designs.</p><p num="0019">Full oxy-fuel firing in a glass furnace is a demonstrated and proven technology.
<ref type="npl">Eleazer and Hoke in chapter 7 titled Glass, of the publication <i>Oxygen-Enhanced
Combustion,</i> Charles E. Baukal, Jr., Editor, 1998 pp. 215-236</ref> report 110 full oxy-fuel
conversions in North America. Implementation of full oxy-fuel combustion in glass
furnaces is the topic of <ref type="patent">US-A-5,417,732</ref> and <ref type="patent">US-A-5,655,464</ref>. Some of the benefits
reported for oxy-fuel operation are; fuel savings due to improved furnace efficiency,
production increase resulting from improved heat transfer, reduced electricity costs by
substituting combustion energy for electric boost energy, extended furnace life by
overcoming combustion air throughput limitations caused by plugged checkers or a
failing recuperator, extended furnace life by substituting combustion energy for electric
boost energy, thereby reducing refractory wear caused by electric boost, reduced
pollutant emissions such as NOx, particulates, and carbon dioxide, improved glass
quality resulting from improved furnace temperature profile, lower volatilization, better
batch-line control, and decreased capital cost by reducing or eliminating post-treatment
systems and/or heat recovery systems.</p><p num="0020">However, the use of full oxy-fuel is not without problems or concerns. The
atmosphere generated by oxy-fuel firing over a glass melt has been found to be more
aggressive to superstructure refractory than an air-fuel atmosphere. Several articles in
the 57<sup>th</sup> Conference on Glass Problems in 1996 discussed the increased corrosion of
superstructure refractory resulting from oxy-fuel firing. Consequently, new construction
techniques and new materials of construction which are often more expensive, have
been proposed for oxy-fuel fired furnaces. In addition to the obvious concern for
furnace integrity, refractory corrosion can be detrimental to glass quality if the liquefied
superstructure refractory gets into the glass.</p><p num="0021">Operators of oxy-fuel glass furnaces have reported an increase in foam on the
glass surface as compared to air-fuel operation. Foam is believed to have a negative
impact on heat transfer and on glass quality. Heat transfer is affected because foam
has poor conductive properties. <ref type="patent">US-A-3,350,185</ref> addresses the problem of foam
formation and the elimination thereof. </p><p num="0022">Increased heat transfer using oxy-fuel is the subject of <ref type="patent">WO-A-9931021</ref> which
describes a roof-mounted oxy-fuel burner process and furnace to produce refined glass
without the use of regenerators or recuperators. This application describes high level
usage of oxy-fuel combustion with impingement on the batch surface in the melting
zone of the furnace for increased heat transfer. This application teaches the use of at
least one roof-mounted oxy-fuel burner in the fining zone for combustion proximate top
surface melted raw glass-forming material to reduce the layer of foam from the melted
glass surface to aid in refinement of the melted glass. At least one roof-mounted oxy-fuel
burner in the fining zone is said to have been found to improve the quality of the
glass moving forward into the forming area by removing surface defects such as
incompletely reacted raw glass-forming material or insufficiently mixed surface materials
by substantially raising the surface glass temperature, promoting melting and mixing.
Furthermore, at least one downstream oxy-fuel burner provides a barrier to the forward
flow of material, promotes natural convection currents within the molten glass causing
hotter glass to flow backwards under the raw glass-forming material thereby preventing
a forward surge of the molten glass, increasing the melting effect and increasing the
glass temperatures in the fining zone. As this is a full oxy-fuel furnace technology, this
patent application states that NOx emissions are reduced compared to an all air-fuel
furnace technology.</p><p num="0023">The operation of a full oxy-fuel furnace depends on the constant availability of
oxygen. Many of the larger oxy-fuel glass furnaces are supplied by oxygen generated
on site using well-known cryogenic distillation or vacuum swing adsorption techniques.
It is customary and, to date, the only method for backing up the supply of on-site
generated oxygen by maintaining an inventory of liquid oxygen at the same site. Thus,
when the on-site generation facility is taken off-line either due to a process problem or
for routine maintenance, the inventory of liquid oxygen is utilized to supply the oxygen
for the oxy-fuel combustion. This method of backing up the on-site generated oxygen
requires large insulated tanks for storage of the oxygen in liquid form and vaporizers to
enable the liquid oxygen to be converted into gaseous oxygen for use in the oxy-fuel
process. It is conventional to utilize trucks to haul liquid oxygen to the site from a larger
air separation facility. Utilizing liquid oxygen back-up with an on-site generated oxygen
system permits the user to continue using an oxy-fuel process without interruption. An
alternative technology, where air-fuel combustion, with and without oxygen enrichment, 
is used to back up an oxy-fuel furnace is described in <ref type="patent">EP-A-1094273</ref>, filed 16th January
2000, published 25th April 2001 and claiming priority from <ref type="patent">U.S. Patent Application Serial
No. 09/420,215</ref> filed 14 October 1999 and thus falling within the terms of Article 54(3)
EPC.</p><p num="0024">Since the furnace efficiency changes over the life of the furnace using full oxy-fuel
combustion and the glass production rate may vary over the furnace campaign, the
associated oxygen generator is typically sized for the maximum planned usage rate. This
results in an underutilized oxygen generator for a large percentage of the furnace
campaign.</p><p num="0025">McMahon et al. (hereafter &quot;McMahon&quot;) in an article entitled <ref type="npl">&quot;Can Partial
Conversion to Oxy-fuel Combustion be a Solution to furnace Problems&quot; (Glass Industry,
Dec 1994)</ref> teaches a partial conversion of an air-fuel furnace to an oxy-fuel furnace prior
to and as part of a complete re-build to an oxy-fuel furnace. A key in McMahon is that the
ports in the previous heat recovery system were left open in the converted section of the
furnace's partially converted state, notwithstanding that oxy-fuel combustion does not
require heat recovery. Oxy-fuel combustion, burning hotter than air fuel combustion,
does not require recovering heat from the combustion products exhausted from the
furnace in order to preheat the combustion reactants and boost the combustion
temperatures.</p><p num="0026">Leaving the ports open in McMahon in the converted section was related to the
control of NOx emissions. In particular, this allowed air to enter the converted section,
thereby facilitating the aspiration principle whereby the entering air and furnace gases are
integrated with the oxy-fuel burners such that the oxygen and fuel come into contact only
at low concentrations, thereby yielding peak flame temperatures equal or lower than
those of regenerative air/fuel flames, thereby reducing NOx. The air entering the
converted section brings into question, however, whether oxy-fuel combustion (defined in
the Application as combustion where the oxidant stream is between 50 and 100% oxygen
and preferably between 90 and 100% oxygen) occurred in the converted section or, as is
more likely according to the Inventor's calculations, only &quot;oxygen-enriched&quot; combustion
occurred in the converted section.</p><p num="0027">Leaving the ports open in McMahon in the converted section also mitigated the
migration of combustion products from the converted section to the unconverted section,
thereby impeding the batch volatiles (which are commingled with the oxy-fuel combustion
products from the converted section) from entering the unconverted section and being
exhausted from the unconverted section and subsequently plugging and/or corroding the
heat recovery system needed for the unconverted section. Leaving the ports open in the
converted section, however, also allows combustion products from the unconverted 
section to exhaust from the converted section, thereby allowing the nitrogen contained in
the air used for the air-fuel combustion in the unconverted section to enter the converted
section and mix with oxygen and subsequently form NOx..</p><p num="0028">None of the references discussed above teach a process or furnace with
predominantly oxy-fuel combustion heating in the melting zone and predominantly air-fuel
combustion heating in the fining zone.</p><p num="0029"><ref type="patent">EP-A-1077201</ref>, published 21st February 2001, filed 15th August 2000 and
claiming a priority date of 16th August 1999 and thus falling within the terms of Article
54(3) EPC, discloses a glass furnace containing a recuperator, regenerator, electric boost
or other device for providing heat to glass batch material and having at least one oxy-fuel
burner mounted in the roof of the furnace to provide additional heat to melt the batch
material. The angle of the oxy-fuel combustion flame can deviate from the perpendicular
in the downstream direction by as much as 30 degrees but preferably deviates by less
than 10 degrees.</p><p num="0030">The present invention is a process and furnace for melting glass wherein the
majority of the combustion energy over the melting zone of the furnace is provided by
oxy-fuel combustion, providing an oxy-fuel combustion flame directed toward the glass
forming ingredients at an angle between 0° and 30° to the horizontal, while a majority of
the combustion energy over the fining zone of the furnace is provided by air-fuel
combustion. In many cases, it will be preferable to provide greater than 70% and up to
and including 100% of the combustion energy over the melting zone by oxy-fuel
combustion and greater than 70% and up to and including 100% of the combustion
energy over the fining zone by air-fuel combustion. By proper tailoring of the combustion
space atmosphere through oxy-fuel and air-fuel firing, the present invention can result in
an improvement in glass productivity and quality. The present invention can be applied in
the construction of a new furnace or can be applied to existing air-fuel furnaces.</p><p num="0031">For the purposes of this disclosure, oxy-fuel combustion is defined as combustion
where the oxidant stream is between 50 and 100% oxygen and preferably between 90
and 100% oxygen. Air-fuel combustion is defined as combustion where the oxidant
stream is between 21% and 30% oxygen. Combustion energy is defined as the fuel
heating value, typically expressed in Btu/lb or equivalent converted unit measure,
multiplied by the mass flow rate of the fuel, typically expressed in Ib/h or equivalent
converted unit measure. Volumetric flow rates can be used with appropriate unit
conversion using the density of a fuel gas.</p><p num="0032">The present invention's mixed air-fuel and oxy-fuel approach is contrary to
conventional thinking since increasing oxy-fuel firing in an air-fuel furnace can lead to an 
increase in the propensity for NOx formation and the attendant problems relating
thereto. As discussed in the background section above, there is an increase in the
propensity for NOx formation because there are more of the hotter oxy-fuel flames
available to form NOx with the migrating nitrogen from the air-fuel combustion. Indeed,
the main purpose of <ref type="patent">US-A-5,655,464</ref> cited in the background section is to prevent air
from entering the melting/refining compartment (melting and fining zone) of an oxy-fuel
furnace. The present Inventors have unexpectedly found however that there are
heretofore unrecognized benefits of a mixed air-fuel and oxy-fuel combustion system
and with proper management of the increased propensity for NOx formation, these
benefits can offset the propensity for NOx formation.</p><p num="0033">As compared to full oxy-fuel technologies, the present invention provides for
glass melting with reduced or eliminated full oxy-fuel problems such as refractory wear,
oxygen backup supply, glass foaming, and full utilization of on-site generated oxygen.</p><p num="0034">As compared to air-fuel technologies, the present invention provides for glass
melting with reduced or eliminated air-fuel problems such as heat recovery device life,
batch stability, and pollutant emissions through the well-placed use of oxy-fuel flames
and exhausts.</p><p num="0035">In addition, the Inventors believe that higher productivity and enhanced melting
of the batch is achievable by the present invention in view of limited data by A Dietzel.
Dietzel, in chapter 22 titled Speeding up Glass Melting, of the publication <ref type="npl"><i>The Melting
Process in the Glass Industry</i> (Alexis G. Pincus, Editor, 1980 pp. 138-139)</ref>, has shown
and reported back in 1943 that water vapour reduces the temperature where the batch
begins to melt and therefore speeds the batch melting process. Fluxing agents, in this
case water, are typically added to the batch to reduce the temperature where the first
melt is formed. Enhanced mass transfer and chemical reaction rates result from the
early liquid phase formation. This improves the overall glass melting process and
improves glass quality.</p><p num="0036">Whereas air-fuel combustion will provide more total water molecules in the
combustion space by virtue of a required higher equivalent firing rate for energy
transferred to a charge, oxy-fuel combustion will provide a higher concentration of water
in the combustion space. Although increased water concentration proximate the batch 
can also be accomplished by wetting the incoming batch with water or injecting steam
into the combustion space, these techniques result in decreased fuel efficiency as
compared to the oxy-fuel combustion approach.</p><p num="0037">The following is a description, by way of example only and with reference to the
accompanying drawings, of presently preferred embodiments of the invention. In the
drawings:-
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a schematic top view of a prior art furnace utilizing air-fuel
combustion with oxy-fuel combustion boosting at the hot spot position;</li><li>Figure 2 is a schematic top view of a prior art furnace utilizing air-fuel
combustion with oxy-fuel combustion boosting at the zero port position;</li><li>Figure 3 is a schematic top view of a prior art furnace utilizing only oxy-fuel
combustion;</li><li>Figure 4 is a schematic top plan view of a first embodiment of the furnace of the
present invention;</li><li>Figure 5 is a schematic top plan view of a second embodiment of the furnace of
the present invention;</li><li>Figure 6 is a schematic top plan view of a third embodiment of the furnace of the
present invention;</li><li>Figure 7 is a schematic top plan view of a fourth embodiment of the furnace of
the present invention;</li><li>Figure 8 is a schematic top plan view of a fifth embodiment of the furnace of the
present invention;</li><li>Figure 9 is a cross-sectional view illustrating a technique for protecting the crown
or roof of the furnace of the present invention;</li><li>Figure 10 is a cross-sectional view illustrating the use of oxygen staged
combustion in a furnace of the present invention;</li><li>Figure 11 is a schematic top plan illustrating oxygen enrichment of the
combustion air in the Figure 6 embodiment of the furnace of the present invention; and</li><li>Figure 12 is a schematic top plan illustrating oxygen lancing of the air-fuel flame
in the Figure 6 embodiment of the furnace of the present invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0038">The present invention is best understood in relation to the prior art as
represented by Figures 1-3. Referring to Figure 1, a glass melting furnace 10, includes
a main furnace portion 12 having a first or charging end 14 with a batch charging device 
16 and a second or glass discharge end 18. The overall flow of batch materials and
glass through the furnace is indicated by arrow 20. The furnace has a melting zone
containing the batch 22 and a fining zone containing the molten glass 24. There is a
combustion energy requirement over both the melting zone and the fining zone.</p><p num="0039">Furnace 10 is of the side-port regenerative heating type having regenerators 26
and 28 on either side of the furnace body 12 as is well known in the art. The
regenerators are connected to ports 30, 32, 34, 36, 38, 40, 42, 44, 46, 48, 50 and 52
which contain air-fuel burners or air-fuel combustion devices to produce air-fuel flames
54, 56, 58, 60, 62 and 64 as is well known in the art. In firing of the furnace, the air-fuel
flames 54, 56, 58, 60, 62 and 64 utilize air 66 which is preheated in regenerator 26.
After a period of time, as determined by the furnace heat storage capacity, the flames
54, 56, 58, 60, 62 and 64 are extinguished and like air-fuel flames are produced in ports
42, 44, 46, 48, 50 and 52 utilizing air introduced through regenerator 28. Regenerator
28 has been preheated by gases 68 being exhausted from the furnace. As is well
known in the art, the reversing flow alternately heats the regenerator checkers 26, 28 to
provide preheated air. In the prior art is has been known to introduce oxy-fuel flames
70, 72 in the middle of the furnace to boost or increase the heating capacity of the
furnace and control the batch-line. The oxy-fuel boosting utilizing flames 70, 72 takes
place in what is called the hot spot position of the furnace 10.</p><p num="0040">Referring to Figure 2, Figure 2 is identical to Figure 1 (common features use the
same identification) except the oxy-fuel boosting utilizing flames 74 and 76 is performed
at the zero port position (i.e. the space between the charge end wall and the first air-fuel
port 30) instead of the hot spot position.</p><p num="0041">Referring to Figure 3, Figure 3 shows a glass melting furnace utilizing complete
oxy-fuel combustion in order to provide heating of the furnace from a batch end 110
toward a discharge end 112. As indicated by arrow 121, the overall flow of batch
materials and glass through the furnace begins at charging end 110 and ends at
discharge end 112. Each of the flames represented as 114, 116, 118, 120, 122, 124,
126, 128, 130, 132, is produced using oxy-fuel combustion utilizing known oxy-fuel
burners. The products of the oxy-fuel combustion are vented through exhausts 131 and
133. </p><p num="0042">Referring to the Figure 4 embodiment of the present invention, a furnace 140
includes a furnace body 142 a charging or batch end 144 and a discharge or molten
glass end 146. The overall flow of batch materials and glass through the furnace is
indicated by arrow 151. The furnace can have regenerators 148, 150, which are
associated with ports 152, 154, 156 and 158, 160 and 162. Regenerator 148 receives
air 76 and preheats it for the air-fuel combustion flames 164, 166, 168 respectively.
Regenerator 150 is preheated by gases 77 being exhausted from the furnace. The air-fuel
combustion flames 164, 166 and 168 are positioned over the molten glass in the
fining zone 170 of the furnace 140 and provide all of the combustion energy over the
fining zone. The oxy-fuel flames 172, 174, 176, 178, 180 and 182 are positioned over
the batch materials in the melting zone 184 of the furnace 140 and provide all of the
combustion energy over the melting zone.</p><p num="0043">Referring to the Figure 5 embodiment of the present invention, Figure 5 is similar
to Figure 4 except the furnace 200 does not have regenerative heating capacity. Such
a furnace 200 is adapted to use recuperative heat recovery wherein the exhaust gases
233 from the furnace are removed via an exhaust 220 disposed at the charging end 222
of the furnace 200. The exhaust gases are conducted to a recuperator which is heated
and receives and heats the air used for the air-fuel flames 224, 226, 228, 230, 232 and
234 which are arrayed over the fining zone 270 of the furnace 200 and provide all of the
combustion energy over this zone. Oxy-fuel flames 238, 240, 242, 244, 246 and 248
are utilized over the melting zone 236 of the furnace 200 and provide all of the
combustion energy over this zone. The overall flow of batch materials and glass
through the furnace is indicated by arrow 221.</p><p num="0044">Referring to the Figure 6 embodiment of the present invention, Figure 6 is
identical to Figure 4 (common features use the same identification) except separate
auxiliary exhausts 141 and 143 (i.e. separate from the exhaust in regenerator 150
where gases 78 are discharged) are used for exhausting mainly oxy-fuel combustion
products 145 and 147 from the melting zone. This is done to prevent the batch volatiles
which are commingled with the oxy-fuel combustion products from using, and plugging
or corroding, the heat recovery device. In Figure 6, the auxiliary exhausts are shown as
being located near the middle of the fining zone. Alternatively, the auxiliary exhausts
could be consolidated into a single auxiliary exhaust located at the charging end of the
furnace. </p><p num="0045">Referring to the Figure 7 embodiment of the present invention, Figure 7 is
identical to Figure 6 (common features use the same identification) except the separate
auxiliary exhausts 141 and 143 are located at the end of the melting zone which is
adjacent to the fining zone in order to help impede products of air-fuel combustion from
entering the melting zone.</p><p num="0046">Referring to the Figure 8 embodiment of the present invention, Figure 8 is
identical to Figure 5 (common features use the same identification) except (i) separate
auxiliary exhaust 223, located at the charging end of the furnace, is used to exhaust
oxy-fuel combustion products 231 from the furnace and (ii) there are two exhausts for
the recuperative heat recovery device, namely exhausts 201 and 203, which exhausts
are used to exhaust air-fuel combustion products 241 and 243 from the furnace. In
Figure 8, the auxiliary exhaust is shown as being located at the charging end of the
furnace. Alternatively, this auxiliary exhaust could be divided into two auxiliary exhausts
located on either side of the melting zone. And, analogous to the refractory system of
Figure 7, such auxiliary exhausts in this recuperative system could be located at the end
of the melting zone which is adjacent to the fining zone in order to help impede products
of air-fuel combustion from entering the melting zone.</p><p num="0047">In Figures 6, 7 and 8, the individual exhaust pressures of the multiple exhausts
are controlled to impede the flow of nitrogen contained in the air used for air-fuel
combustion in the fining zone from entering the melting zone. Another option to impede
said flow of said nitrogen would be to place a physical barrier between the melting zone
and fining zone. The auxiliary exhausts 141 and 143 in Figures 6 and 7 and the
auxiliary exhaust 223 in Figure 8 may also be connected to a heat recovery system as
would be known to one skilled in the art.</p><p num="0048">The skilled practitioner will appreciate that a more corrosion resistant refractory
need only be used in the oxy-fuel section of the furnace of the present invention,
thereby reducing the capital costs. Figure 9 illustrates an alternative to using a more
corrosion resistant refractory in the oxy-fuel section of the furnace of the present
invention. Figure 9 is a cross-sectional view illustrating a technique for protecting the
crown, or roof, of either furnace of the present invention 140, 200 whereby a dilution gas
is introduced through an upper conduit 300 just below a crown portion 302 of the 
furnace. This view of furnace 140, 200 also shows a layer of batch material 308 over a
layer of molten glass 309. There is a lower concentration of products of combustion
from the oxy-fuel flame 304 (which is produced by introducing oxygen and fuel through
conduit 306) which reduces the corrosive effects of an oxy-fuel atmosphere proximate
the furnace roof. The dilution gas can consist of air, preheated air, nitrogen, products of
air-fuel combustion or mixtures thereof. Air-fuel combustion products could come from
introduction of exhaust gases from the air-fuel section of the furnace or created in-situ in
the furnace. Like the process disclosed in <ref type="patent">US-A-5,755,818</ref>, a stratified furnace
atmosphere is created.</p><p num="0049">Unlike the <ref type="patent">US-A-5,755,818</ref>, in Figure 9 an atmosphere high in oxy-fuel
combustion products is provided proximate the charge and diluted atmosphere is
provided proximate the crown. The process of the <ref type="patent">US-A-5,755,818</ref> uses a staged
combustion method to form a more oxidizing or a more reducing atmosphere proximate
the charge surface than would be the case with a homogeneous furnace atmosphere.</p><p num="0050">Figure 10 is a cross-sectional view illustrating the use of oxygen staged
combustion with either furnace (140, 200). Oxy-fuel burners with oxygen staging as
described in <ref type="patent">US-A-5,611,682</ref> are preferred for directional heating toward the batch
instead of the crown. Referring to Figure 10, an oxy-fuel flame 304 is produced by
introducing oxygen and fuel through conduit 306 and a lower conduit 310 is used to
introduce oxygen into the furnace 140, 200 with the oxygen being directed underneath
the flame 304. By using oxygen staging with oxygen between the flame and charge as
shown in Figure 10, a region of higher flame temperature 312 on the flame envelope
closest to the batch can be obtained resulting in directional heating toward the batch.
NOx formation rates have been found to be low when the oxy-fuel burner described in
<ref type="patent">US-A-5,611,682</ref> is used, even in furnaces with significant nitrogen concentrations.</p><p num="0051">The air-fuel section of the furnace of the present invention can include oxygen
enhanced combustion technologies familiar to those skilled in the art. The oxygen might
be used to make up any oxidant deficiency in an air-fuel port by adding oxygen, improve
the overall furnace efficiency, or for NOx reduction techniques familiar to those skilled in
the art. General oxygen enrichment of up to 30% or higher, depending on the heat
recovery system, can be directly injected into the combustion air stream or strategically
placed to oxygen enrich a specific port. Oxygen lancing can be used to achieve higher 
levels of oxygen enrichment in the flame if desired. Oxygen could also be used in a
number of new technologies for improved energy efficiency or NOx reduction such as
the disclosed in <ref type="patent">US-A-5,725,366</ref>.</p><p num="0052">Figure 11 is a schematic top plan illustrating oxygen enrichment of the
combustion air in the Figure 6 embodiment of the furnace of the present invention.
Oxygen 320 is introduced into the combustion air 76 prior to introducing the air into
regenerator 148 for oxygen enrichment of the air-fuel flames 164, 166 and 168.
Although shown in connection with the Figure 6 embodiment which uses regenerative
heat recovery, the skilled practitioner will appreciate that oxygen enrichment is equally
applicable to the Figure 5 embodiment which uses recuperative heat recovery.</p><p num="0053">Figure 12 is a schematic top plan illustrating oxygen lancing of the air-fuel flame
in the Figure 6 embodiment of the furnace of the present invention whereby introduction
of oxygen via an oxygen lance 330 is used to enrich the air-fuel flame 164 in furnace
140. Although shown in connection with the Figure 6 embodiment which uses
regenerative heat recovery, the skilled practitioner will appreciate that oxygen lancing is
equally applicable to the Figure 5 embodiment which uses recuperative heat recovery.</p><p num="0054">The oxy-fuel flames are angled toward the batch at between 0° and 30° from
horizontal. This technique is applied also for directional heating toward the batch
instead of the crown and placement of the oxy-fuel combustion atmosphere proximate
the batch especially in the case of diluting the oxy-fuel atmosphere near the crown with
air, preheated air, nitrogen, air-fuel combustion products and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0055">In another embodiment of the present invention, it is contemplated to include an
advanced control system to manage and optimize the oxygen usage in the furnace.
The advanced control system would monitor and control the use of oxygen depending
on, for example, the pollutant emissions requirements, variability in the purity and
production rate of the oxygen generator, and glass production rate.</p><p num="0056">In another embodiment of the present invention, it is contemplated to provide a
process and furnace for melting glass with low NOx emissions by limiting the flow of
nitrogen containing gases from the air-fuel section into the oxy-fuel section. The 
preferred method to reduce flow from the air-fuel section to the oxy-fuel section is by
furnace design where a lower crown height is used in the oxy-fuel section. Other
methods to reduce flow from the air-fuel section to the oxy-fuel section are to provide a
partitioning wall between the air-fuel and oxy-fuel sections, or proper number, size, and
placement and pressure control of the furnace exhausts. Figure 6 illustrates an exhaust
layout where flues for exhausting mainly products of oxy-fuel combustion and volatiles
from the batch are located between the oxy-fuel section and the air-fuel section. Air-fuel
combustion products preferentially exhaust through these exhausts instead of
penetrating into the oxy-fuel section. Alternatively, the configuration shown in Figure 4,
with no separate exhausts for the oxy-fuel combustion products and volatiles from the
batch could be used to create a higher pressure in the oxy-fuel section and force the
flow from the oxy-fuel section into the air-fuel section, thereby minimizing nitrogen
concentrations in the oxy-fuel section.</p><p num="0057">In another embodiment of the present invention, it is contemplated to provide for
low NOx emissions through operational techniques. The preferred method is to operate
the two oxy-fuel burners closest to the air-fuel section with fuel rich combustion (i.e. with
a sub-stoichiometric amount of oxidant), a condition that will be recognized by those
skilled in the art to form less NOx. Other burners operating fuel lean, or the use of
oxygen lances, allow the furnace to operate stoichiometrically overall. Other operational
techniques suitable for NOx reduction are extreme oxygen staging of the oxy-fuel
burners. Extreme staging is the practice whereby greater than 50% of the oxygen for
combustion for a single burner is provided through a staging port.</p><p num="0058">In another embodiment of the present invention, it is contemplated to provide air-fuel
backup capability of the oxy-fuel section of the furnace in case of oxygen supply
disruption. In case of oxygen supply disruption, the oxy-fuel burners can be replaced by
suitable air-fuel burners, available through Air Products and Chemicals Inc., Allentown,
PA. Combustion air can be supplied preferably from the preheated air source used in
the air-fuel section of the furnace or by a separate air supply with or without preheating.</p><p num="0059">In another embodiment of the present invention, it is contemplated to place the
oxy-fuel burners, exhausts, and air-fuel ports and burners to minimize negative
interactions of the flames. Since the oxy-fuel flames in the furnace will typically have
lower momentum than the air-fuel flames, the oxy-fuel flames are at greater risk of being 
disrupted by the air-fuel flames. Disruption of flames can negatively impact flame
characteristics (flame stability, flame geometry, area of glass covered by flame, etc.)
that result in decreased melting efficiency of the furnace as well as potentially causing
physical damage to the furnace. Proper furnace geometry design can be accomplished
by experiments, experience, or preferably through the use of computational fluid
dynamics modelling. For the case of a regenerative furnace, the oxy-fuel burner,
optional oxy-fuel exhaust ports, and air-fuel port configuration must be suitable for the
desired operating conditions where the air-fuel combustion is firing from left to right and
from right to left. Computational fluid dynamics modelling can be used to evaluate
suitable configurations.</p><p num="0060">In another embodiment of the present invention, it is contemplated to operate the
oxy-fuel burners with velocities exiting the burner block of greater than 100 ft/s (30 m/s).
The momentum of the oxy-fuel flames must be sufficient to minimize negative impacts
of the high momentum air-fuel flames.</p><p num="0061">The greater usage of steady, constant oxy-fuel firing according to the invention
provides greater stability of the batch position and shape, especially in regenerative
furnaces, resulting in better glass quality. Because of the reversal cycle in a
regenerative air-fuel furnace, the heat flux from the air-fuel flames varies and can impact
the movement of the batch. The relatively high velocities from the air-fuel flames may
also influence the batch movement. A more stable and controlled batch shape is
important for glass melt convection flow patterns and therefore influences glass quality.
Batch movement is so important that flat glass furnaces often use mechanical means to
control batch movement.</p><p num="0062">For glass furnaces where heat recovery device fouling/plugging is a problem, the
furnace of the present invention can include one or more separate exhausts with limited
or no heat recovery for the oxy-fuel products of combustion and volatiles evolved from
the batch. If the rate of volatilization of the glass being melted is high, one or more flues
not connected with the air-fuel heat recovery device should be installed in the oxy-fuel
section of the furnace to exhaust mainly products of the oxy-fuel combustion and
volatiles from the batch. A benefit of the present invention is the reduction of heat
recovery device fouling and plugging. </p><p num="0063">Oxygen for oxy-fuel boosted furnaces is typically provided by a liquid bulk supply
(LOX) whereas the furnace according to the invention is likely to be supplied by on-site
generated oxygen because of the higher oxygen usage rate. On-site oxygen generators
are typically sized depending on the maximum demand anticipated during the entire
furnace campaign and/or standard engineered equipment designs of the oxygen
supplier. Users of the oxy-fuel boost technology have historically only used oxygen in
the oxy-fuel burners since LOX is more expensive than an on-site generated oxygen
and the greatest benefit is achieved by using the oxygen in this way. Because of the
lower oxygen cost of on-site generated oxygen and expected overproduction of oxygen,
oxygen is used in the air-fuel section of the furnace according to the present invention to
make up any oxidant deficiency for an air-fuel port by adding oxygen. This will improve
the furnace temperature control by allowing greater tailoring of fuel distribution, improve
the furnace efficiency, or provide NOx reduction through techniques familiar to those
skilled in the art. The oxidant supply for the present invention is not limited by the air
flow rates or distribution since the oxygen concentration for each port can be controlled
using oxygen.</p><p num="0064">The present invention uses both oxy-fuel combustion and air-fuel combustion
preferably with conventional heat recovery, whereas full oxy-fuel utilizes only oxy-fuel
combustion. Air-fuel combustion is applied in the section of the furnace where foaming
has been reported as an issue in full oxy-fuel furnaces thereby mitigating the amount of
foam on the glass surface and improving glass quality.</p><p num="0065">Standard refractory materials used in air-fuel furnaces can be used in the air-fuel
section of the furnace of the present invention. A benefit of using standard air-fuel
refractories in the air-fuel section is that they have a proven record for minimizing the
addition of defects to the glass. Because the alternative refractories proposed for oxy-fuel
are more corrosion resistant, they are also harder to melt out in the glass should
pieces of the alternative refractory enter the glass melt either as a liquid or solid. In
liquid form, defects known as cord and viscous knots are apparent in the final product.
The alternative refractories proposed for oxy-fuel combustion can provide defects to the
glass which are more difficult to remove in the overall glass melting process. The air-fuel
section according to the present invention is closer to the glass melt exit of the
furnace and therefore little additional processing time is available to remove any defects
that might be introduced by the down tank (fining zone) refractory. </p><p num="0066">The oxygen supplied to both the furnace according to the invention and a full
oxy-fuel furnace is likely to be from an on-site oxygen generator. On-site oxygen
generators are typically sized depending on the maximum demand anticipated during
the entire furnace campaign and/or standard engineered equipment designs of the
oxygen supplier. For a full oxy-fuel furnace, this often results in incomplete utilization of
oxygen produced during some or all of the furnace campaign. Extra oxygen produced
from an on-site oxygen generator is often unused in the case of a full oxy-fuel furnace
resulting in a cost penalty. Extra oxygen produced on-site can be used in a number of
ways. It could be used in the furnace of the invention to improve the furnace
temperature control since the furnace operator can better tailor the fuel distribution
profile and make up any oxidant deficiency for an air-fuel port by adding oxygen. The
oxidant supply for an air-fuel port is not limited by the air flow rates or distribution since
the oxygen concentration for each port can be controlled using oxygen. In addition,
oxygen can be used to improve the furnace efficiency or for NOx reduction techniques
familiar to those skilled in the art. The benefit is better utilization of on-site generated
oxygen throughout the whole furnace campaign for a furnace as compared to a full oxy-fuel
furnace.</p><p num="0067">As described in the background section, backup of on-site generated oxygen
supply is perceived to be a concern for large full oxy-fuel furnaces and sites with
multiple oxy-fuel furnaces. In case of on-site generated oxygen supply disruption,
continued operation of a full oxy-fuel furnace will depend on stored liquid oxygen which
must be supplied by trucks hauling liquid oxygen from a nearby air separation facility. A
benefit of the furnace technology according to the present invention is a reduced
dependence on an oxygen supply compared to a full oxy-fuel furnace. In case of
oxygen supply disruption, the oxy-fuel burners are replaced by suitable air-fuel burners.
The furnace of the invention has a source of preheated combustion air, whereas a full
oxy-fuel furnace typically does not. Combustion air can be supplied preferably from the
preheated air source used in the air-fuel section of the furnace or by a separate air
supply. Because of the heat recovery system, higher furnace production capability in
the air-fuel backup mode is possible as compared to air-fuel backup operation of a full
oxy-fuel furnace. </p><p num="0068">In another embodiment of the present invention, it is contemplated to provide a
process and furnace for melting glass with low NOx emissions by limiting the flow of
nitrogen containing gases from the air-fuel section into the oxy-fuel section. As
discussed previously, solutions for limiting the migration of nitrogen containing gases
from the fining zone to the melting zone include providing physical barriers between the
melting zone and fining zone such as physical barriers resulting from a furnace design
where (i) a lower roof or crown height is used in the melting zone as compared to the
fining zone and (ii) a partitioning wall is used to separate the two zones. Re (i) above, it
should be noted that the lower crown height solution can be used alone or can
advantageously be used in combination with a solution where a smaller furnace width is
used in the melting zone as compared to the fining zone. Computational fluid dynamics
have shown that the combination of a lower crown or roof in the melting zone with a
small furnace width in the melting zone is especially effective and can almost completely
mitigate the migration of nitrogen from the air fuel combustion in the fining zone to the
oxy-fuel combustion in the melting zone. In this combination solution, the furnace
design is essentially such that the cross section of the furnace in the melting zone is
smaller than the cross section of the furnace in the fining zone. Re (ii) above, it should
be noted that the partitioning wall need only partially separate the melting zone from the
fining zone.</p><p num="0069">The present invention has been described with reference to a number of
embodiments thereof. These embodiments should not be viewed as limitations to the
present invention, the scope of which should be ascertained by the following claims.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Schmelzen von glasbildenden Bestandteilen in einem Ofen (140;
200) mit einem Beschickungsende (144), einem Entnahmeende (142), einer
Schmelzzone (184; 236) in der Nähe des Beschickungsendes (144), die signifikante,
ungeschmolzene Chargenfeststoffe enthält, die auf der Oberfläche des geschmolzenen
Glasbades schwimmen, und mit einer Läuterzone (170; 270) in der
Nähe des Entnahmeendes (142), die keine signifikanten, ungeschmolzenen
Chargenfeststoffe enthält, die auf der Oberfläche des geschmolzenen Glasbades
schwimmen, wobei die glasbildenden Bestandteile in die Schmelzzone (184; 236)
eingeführt werden, sich längs einer Bahn von der Schmelzzone (184; 236) zu der
Läuterzone (170; 270) fortbewegen und als geschmolzenes Glas aus der Läuterzöne
(170; 270) abgezogen werden, und wobei Verbrennungsenergie nach Bedarf
über sowohl der Schmelzzone (184; 236) als auch der Läuterzone (170; 270)
zur Verfügung gestellt wird;dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) der größere Teil der Verbrennungsenergie über der Schmelzzone (184;
236) wird durch Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennung zur Verfügung
gestellt, wobei der Oxidationsmittel-Strom zwischen 50 und 100 % Sauerstoff
liegt, wodurch eine Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennungsflamme
(172-184; 238-248) geliefert wird, die unter einem Winkel zwischen 0° und
30° zur Horizontalen auf die glasbildenden Bestandteile gerichtet wird; und</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) der größere Teil der Verbrennungsenergie (164-168; 224-234) über der
Läuterzone (170; 270) wird durch Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung zur Verfügung
gestellt, wobei der Oxidationsmittel-Strom zwischen 21 % und 30 %
Sauerstoff liegt.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1, wobei mehr als 70 % und bis zu und einschließlich
100 % der Verbrennungsenergie (172-184; 238-248) über der Schmelzzone (184;
236) durch Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennung zur Verfügung gestellt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1 oder Anspruch 2, wobei mehr als 70 % und bis zu
und einschließlich 100 % der Verbrennungsenergie (164-168; 224-234) über der
Läuterzone (170; 270) durch Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung zur Verfügung gestellt
wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, wobei wenigstens ein
Hilfs-Auslass bzw. -Abzug (141; 143; 220; 223; 201; 203) in der Schmelzzone
(184; 236) vorgesehen ist, um in der Hauptsache Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennungsprodukte
(145; 147; 231; 233; 241; 243) aus der Schmelzzone
(184; 236) nach außen abzulassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 4, wobei der wenigstens eine Hilfs-Auslass (141; 143;
201; 203) in der Nähe der Läuterzone (170; 270) angeordnet ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, wobei die Luft für die Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
durch eine Wärmewiedergewinnungsvorrichtung (148;
150) mit einem Auslass bzw. einem Abzug (77; 78) vorgewärmt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 6 in Abhängigkeit von Anspruch 5, wobei die individuellen
Auslassdrücke des Auslasses (77; 78) der Wärmewiedergewinnungsvorrichtung
und des wenigstens einen Hilfs-Auslasses (141; 143; 201; 203) gesteuert
bzw. geregelt werden, um die Strömung des Stickstoffs, der in der für die Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
verwendeten Luft in der Läuterzone (170; 270) enthalten
ist, daran zu hindern, in die Schmelzzone (184; 236) einzudringen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, wobei der Ofen eine physikalische
Sperre zwischen der Schmelzzone (184; 236) und der Läuterzone
(170; 270) hat, um die Strömung des Stickstoffs, der in der für die Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
verwendeten Luft in der Läuterzone (170; 270) enthalten ist, daran
zu hindern, in die Schmelzzone (184; 236) einzudringen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 8, wobei die physikalische Sperre ausgewählt wird aus
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) der Sperre, die sich aus der Verwendung eines niedrigeren Dachs oder einer
niedrigeren Scheitelhöhe in der Schmelzzone (184; 236) im Vergleich
mit der Läuterzone (170; 270) und/oder der Verwendung einer kleineren
Ofenbreite in der Schmelzzone (184; 236) im Vergleich mit der Läuterzone
(170; 272) ergibt; und</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) einer Trennwand, die wenigstens teilweise die Schmelzzone (184; 236)
von der Läuterzone (170; 270) trennt.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, wobei die Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
durch mehrere Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Brenner
zur Verfügung gestellt wird, und wobei eine unterstoichiometrische Menge
an Oxidationsmittel in wenigstens einen der Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Brenner
in der Nähe irgendeiner Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennungsflamme (164-168;
224-243) eingeführt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, wobei ein Hilfsgas zwischen
eine Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Flamme (304) und dem Dach (302) des
Ofens (140; 200) eingeführt wird (300), um die Ofenatmosphäre, die Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennungsprodukte
in der Nähe des Ofensdachs (302)
enthält, zu verdünnen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, wobei die Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
durch wenigstens einen Sauerstoff-Brennstoff-Brenner
mit Sauerstoff-Abstufung (oxygen staging) zur Verfügung gestellt
und wenigstens 50 % des Sauerstoffs für den wenigstens einen Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Brenner
mit Sauerstoff-Stufenbildung durch eine Stufenbildungsöffung
(310) in den Brenner gerichtet wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, wobei die Luft für die
Verbrennungsflamme (164-168; 224-234) mit bis zu 50-Volumen-% Sauerstoff
angereichert wird (320).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, wobei eine Lanze (330)
dazu verwendet wird, Sauerstoff in die Luft-Brennstoff-Flamme (164-168; 224-234)
einzuführen, um die Luft-Brennstoff-Flamme (164-168; 224-234) zu verbessern
bzw. zu verstärken.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen zum Schmelzen von glasbildenden Bestandteilen durch ein Verfahren nach
Anspruch 1 mit:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) einem Beschickungsende (144), einem Entnahmeende (142), einer Schmelzzone
(184; 236) in der Nähe des Beschickungsendes (144) und einer Läuterzone
(170; 270) in der Nähe des Entnahmeendes (142);</claim-text><claim-text>(b) einer Anordnung zur Einführung der glasbildenden Bestandteile in die
Schmelzzone (184; 236);</claim-text><claim-text>(c) einer Anordnung zum Entnehmen der glasbildenden Bestandteile als geschmolzenes
Glas aus der Läuterzone (170; 270);</claim-text><claim-text>(d) einer Anordnung, um Verbrennungsenergie (172-184; 238-248) über der
Schmelzzone (184; 236) zur Verfügung zu stellen;</claim-text><claim-text>(e) eine Anordnung, um Verbrennungsenergie (164-168; 224-234) über der Läuterzone
(170; 270) zur Verfügung zu stellen,
   dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass:</claim-text><claim-text>(i) die Anordnung, um Verbrennungsenergie über der Schmelzzone (184;
236) zur Verfügung zu stellen, den größeren Teil der Verbrennungsenergie
(172-184; 238-248) durch Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
liefert, indem die Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennungsflamme
(172-184; 238-248) unter einem Winkel zwischen
0° und 30° zur Horizontalen auf die glasbildenden Bestandteile gerichtet
wird; und</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) die Anordnung, um Verbrennungsenergie über der Läuterzone (170;
270) zur Verfügung zu stellen, den größeren Teil der Verbrennungsenergie
(164-168; 224-234) durch Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung liefert.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach Anspruch 15, weiterhin mit einer Wärme-Wiedergewinnungsvorrichtung
(148; 150) zur Vorwärmung der Luft für die Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
mit einem Abzug bzw. Auslass (77; 78).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach Anspruch 15 oder 16, weiterhin mit wenigstens einem Hilfs-Auslass
bzw. -Abzug (141; 143; 220; 223; 201; 203) in der Schmelzzone (184; 236), um in
der Hauptsache Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennungsprodukte (145; 147;
231; 233; 241; 243) aus der Schmelzzone (184; 236) abzulassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach Anspruch 17, wobei der wenigstens eine Hilfs-Abzug (141; 143; 201;
203) in der Nähe der Läuterzone (170; 270) angeordnet ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach Anspruch 17 oder Anspruch 18, weiterhin mit einer Wärme-Wiedergewinnungsvorrichtung
(148; 150) zur Vorwärmung der Luft für die Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
mit einem Abzug bzw. Auslass (77; 78) und mit einer
Anordnung zur Steuerung bzw. Regelung der einzelnen Auslassdrücke des
Auslasses (77; 78) der Wärme-Wiedergewinnungsvorrichtung und des wenigstens
einen Hilfs-Auslasses (141; 143; 201; 203), um die Strömung des Stickstoffes,
der in der für die Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung verwendeten Luft in der Läuterzone
(170; 270) enthalten ist, daran zu hindern, in die Schmelzzone (184; 236)
einzudringen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach einem der Ansprüche 15 bis 19, weiterhin mit einer physikalischen
Sperre zwischen der Schmelzzone (184; 236) und der Läuterzone (170; 270), um
die Strömung des Stickstoffs, der in der für die Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennung verwendeten
Luft in der Läuterzone (170; 270) enthalten ist, daran zu hindern, in die
Schmelzzone (184; 236) einzudringen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach Anspruch 20, wobei die physikalische Sperre ausgewählt wird aus
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) der Sperre, die sich aus der Verwendung eines niedrigeren Daches oder
einer niedrigeren Scheitelhöhe in der Schmelzzone (184; 236) im Vergleich
mit der Läuterzone (170; 270) und/oder der Verwendung einer kleineren
Ofenbreite in der Schmelzzone (184; 236) im Vergleich mit der Läuterzone
(170; 270) ergibt, und</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) einer Trennwand, die wenigstens teilweise die Schmelzzone (184; 236)
von der Läuterzone (170; 270) trennt.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach einem der Ansprüche 15 bis 21, wobei die Anordnung, um die Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
zur Verfügung zu stellen, mehrere Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Brenner
aufweist, wobei wenigstens einer der Sauerstoff-Brennstoff-Brenner
in der Nähe irgendeiner Luft-Brennstoff-Verbrennungsflamme
(164-168; 224-234) eine unterstoichiometrische Menge an Oxidationsmittel empfängt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach einem der Ansprüche 15 bis 22, weiterhin mit einer Anordnung (300),
um ein Hilfsgas zwischen der Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Flamme (304) und dem
Dach (302) des Ofens (140; 200) einzuführen, um die Ofenatmosphäre, die in der
Nähe des Ofendachs (302) Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennungsprodukte
enthält, zu verdünnen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach einem der Ansprüche 15 bis 23, wobei das Dach (302) des Ofens
(140; 200) über der Schmelzzone (184; 236) niedriger als das Dach des Ofens
(140; 200) über der Läuterzone (170; 270) ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Ofen nach Anspruch 15, wobei die Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Verbrennung
durch wenigstens einen Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Brenner mit Sauerstoff-Stufenbildung
(oxygen staging) zur Verfügung gestellt wird, wodurch wenigstens
50 % des Sauerstoffs für den wenigstens einen Oxy-(Sauerstoff)-Brennstoff-Brenner
mit Sauerstoff-Stufenbildung durch eine Stufenbildungs-Öffnung (310) in
den Brenner gerichtet werden kann.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process for melting glass forming ingredients in a furnace (140; 200)
having a charging end (144), a discharge end (142), a melting zone (184; 236) adjacent
the charging end (144), containing significant unmelted batch solids floating on the
surface of the molten glass bath, and a fining zone (170; 270) adjacent the discharge
end (142), not containing significant unmelted batch solids floating on the surface of the
molten glass bath, wherein the glass forming ingredients are introduced into the melting
zone (184; 236), travel along a path from the melting zone (184; 236) to the fining zone
(170; 270) and are withdrawn as molten glass from the fining zone (170; 270); and
providing combustion energy as required over both the melting zone (184; 236) and the
fining zone (170; 270);
   characterized in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) the majority of the combustion energy over the melting zone (184; 236) is
provided by oxy-fuel combustion, where the oxidant stream is between 50 and 100%
oxygen, providing an oxy-fuel combustion flame (172-184; 238-248) directed toward the
glass forming ingredients at an angle between 0° and 30° to the horizontal; and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) the majority of the combustion energy (164-168; 224-234) over the fining
zone (170; 270) is provided by air-fuel combustion, where the oxidant stream is between
21% and 30% oxygen.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in Claim 1, wherein greater than 70% and up to
and including 100% of the combustion energy (172-184; 238-248) over the melting zone
(184; 236) is provided by oxy-fuel combustion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in Claim 1 or claim 2, wherein greater than 70%
and up to and including 100% of the combustion energy (164-168; 224-234) over the
fining zone (170; 270) is provided by air-fuel combustion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein there
is at least one auxiliary exhaust (141; 143; 220; 223; 201; 203) in the melting zone (184;
236) for exhausting mainly oxy-fuel combustion products (145; 147; 231; 233; 241; 243)
from the melting zone (184; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in Claim 4, wherein the at least one auxiliary
exhaust (141; 143; 201; 203) is located adjacent to the fining zone (170; 270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein the air
for the air-fuel combustion is preheated by a heat recovery device (148; 150) having an
exhaust (77; 78).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in Claim 6 when dependent on Claim 5, wherein
the individual exhaust pressures of the heat recovery device exhaust (77; 78) and the at
least one auxiliary exhaust (141; 143; 201; 203) are controlled to impede the flow of
nitrogen contained in the air used for the air-fuel combustion in the fining zone (170;
270) from entering the melting zone (184; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein the
furnace has a physical barrier between the melting zone (184; 236) and fining zone
(170; 270) to impede the flow of nitrogen contained in the air used for the air-fuel
combustion in the fining zone (170; 270) from entering the melting zone (184; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in Claim 8, wherein said physical barrier is selected
from (i) the barrier resulting from the use of a lower roof or crown height in the melting
zone (184; 236) as compared to the fining zone (170; 270) and/or use of a smaller
furnace width in the melting zone (184; 236) as compared to the fining zone (170; 270);
and (ii) a partition wall at least partially separating the melting zone (184; 236) from the
fining zone (170; 270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein the
oxy-fuel combustion is provided by a plurality of oxy-fuel burners and wherein a sub-stoichiometric
amount of oxidant is introduced to at least one of the oxy-fuel burners
adjacent to any air-fuel combustion flames (164-168; 224-234).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein an
auxiliary gas is introduced (300) between an oxy-fuel flame (304) and the roof (302) of
the furnace (140; 200) to dilute the furnace atmosphere containing oxy-fuel combustion
products proximate the furnace roof (302).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein the
oxy-fuel combustion is provided by at least one oxy-fuel burner with oxygen staging and
at least 50% of the oxygen for the at least one oxy-fuel burner with oxygen staging is
directed through a staging port (310) in the burner.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein the air
for the combustion flame (164-168; 224-234) is enriched (320) with up to 50% by
volume oxygen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein a
lance (330) is used to introduce oxygen to the air-fuel flame (164-168; 224-234) for
enhancing the air-fuel flame (164-168; 224-234).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace for melting glass forming ingredients by a process of Claim 1
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) a charging end (144), a discharge end (142), a melting zone (184; 236)
adjacent the charging end (144), and a fining zone (170; 270) adjacent the discharge
end (142);</claim-text><claim-text>(b) means for introducing the glass forming ingredients into the melting zone
(184; 236);</claim-text><claim-text>(c) means for withdrawing the glass forming ingredients as molten glass
from the fining zone (170; 270);</claim-text><claim-text>(d) means for providing combustion energy (172-184; 238-248) over the
melting zone (184; 236); and</claim-text><claim-text>(e) means for providing combustion energy (164-168; 224-234) over the
fining zone (170; 270),
   characterized in that:</claim-text><claim-text>(i) said means for providing combustion energy over the melting zone (184;
236) provides a majority of the combustion energy (172-184; 238-248) by oxy-fuel
combustion by directing the oxy-fuel combustion flame (172-184; 238-248) toward the
glass forming ingredients at an angle between 0° and 30° to the horizontal; and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) said means for providing combustion energy over the fining zone (170;
270) provides a majority of the combustion energy (164-168; 224-234) by air-fuel
combustion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in Claim 15, further comprising a heat recovery device
(148; 150) to preheat the air for the air-fuel combustion and having an exhaust (77; 78).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in Claim 15 or Claim 16, further comprising at least
one auxiliary exhaust (141; 143; 220; 223; 201; 203) in the melting zone (184; 236) for
exhausting mainly oxy-fuel combustion products (145; 147; 231; 233; 241; 243) from the
melting zone (184; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in Claim 17, wherein the at least one auxiliary
exhaust (141; 143; 201; 203) is located adjacent to the fining zone (170; 270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in Claim 17 or Claim 18, further comprising a heat
recovery device (148; 150) to preheat the air for the air-fuel combustion and having an
exhaust (77; 78) and a means for controlling the individual exhaust pressures of the
heat recovery device exhaust (77; 78) and the at least one auxiliary exhaust (141; 143;
201; 203) to impede the flow of nitrogen contained in the air used for the air-fuel
combustion in the fining zone (170; 270) from entering the melting zone (184; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in any one of Claims 15 to 19, further comprising a
physical barrier between the melting zone (184; 236) and fining zone (170; 270) to
impede the flow of nitrogen contained in the air used for the air-fuel combustion in the
fining zone (170; 270) from entering the melting zone (184; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in Claim 20, wherein said physical barrier is
selected from (i) the barrier resulting from the use of a lower roof or crown height in the
melting zone (184; 236) as compared to the fining zone (170; 270) and/or use of a
smaller furnace width in the melting zone (184; 236) as compared to the fining zone
(170; 270); and (ii) a partition wall at least partially separating the melting zone (184;
236) from the fining zone (170; 270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in any one of Claims 15 to 21, wherein the means
for providing the oxy-fuel combustion comprises a plurality of oxy-fuel burners with at
least one of the oxy-fuel burners adjacent to any air-fuel combustion flames (164-168;
224-234) receiving a sub-stoichiometric amount of oxidant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in any one of Claims 15 to 22, further comprising a
means (300) for introducing an auxiliary gas between the oxy-fuel flame (304) and the
roof (302) of the furnace (140; 200) to dilute the furnace atmosphere containing oxy-fuel
combustion products proximate the furnace roof (302).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in any one of Claims 15 to 23, wherein the roof
(302) of the furnace (140; 200) over the melting zone (184; 236) is lower than the roof of
the furnace (140; 200) over the fining zone (170; 270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A furnace as claimed in Claim 15 wherein the oxy-fuel combustion is
provided by at least one oxy-fuel burner with oxygen staging whereby at least 50% of
the oxygen for the at least one oxy-fuel burner with oxygen staging can be directed
through a staging port (310) in the burner.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de fusion d'ingrédient de formation de verre
dans un four (140 ; 200) présentant une extrémité de
chargement (144), une extrémité de déchargement (142), une
zone de fusion (184 ; 236) adjacente à l'extrémité de
chargement (144), contenant une charge non fondue
significative de solides flottant à la surface du bain de
verre fondu, et une zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) adjacente à
l'extrémité de déchargement (142), ne contenant pas de
charge non fondue significative de solides flottant à la
surface du bain de verre fondu, dans lequel les ingrédients
de formation de verre sont introduits dans la zone de fusion
(184 ; 236), se déplacent suivant un trajet de la zone de
fusion (184 ; 236) à la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) et sont
enlevés sous forme de verre fondu de la zone d'affinage (170
; 270), et fournissant de l'énergie de combustion comme il
se doit sur à la fois la zone de fusion
(184 ; 236) et la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270),
   caractérisé en ce que :
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) la majorité de l'énergie de combustion sur la zone
d'affinage (184 ; 236) est fournie par une combustion
oxygène-combustible, où le flux d'oxydant contient entre 50
et 100 % d'oxygène, fournissant une flamme de combustion
oxygène-combustible (172 à 184 ; 238 à 248) dirigée vers les
ingrédients de formation de verre à un angle entre 0° et 30°
par rapport à l'horizontale, et</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) la majorité de l'énergie de combustion (164 à 168
; 224 à 234) sur la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) est fournie
par une combustion air-combustible où le flux d'oxydant
contient entre 21 et 30 % d'oxygène.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 1, dans lequel plus
de 70 % et jusqu'à 100 % inclus de l'énergie de combustion(
172 à 184 ; 238 à 248) sur la zone de fusion (184 ; 236) est
fourni par la combustion oxygène-combustible.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 1 ou la revendication
2, dans lequel plus de 70 % et jusqu'à 100 % inclus de
l'énergie de combustion (164 à 168 ; 224 à 234) sur la zone
d'affinage
(170 ; 270) est fourni par la combustion air-combustible.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications
précédentes, dans lequel il y a au moins une évacuation
auxiliaire (141 ; 143 ; 220 ; 223 ; 201 ; 203) dans la zone
de fusion (184 ; 236) destinée à évacuer principalement les
produits de la combustion oxygène-combustible (145 ; 147 ;
231 ; 233 ; 241 ; 243) depuis la zone de fusion (184 ; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 4, dans lequel la au
moins une évacuation auxiliaire (141 ; 143 ; 201 ; 203) est
située de façon adjacente à la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications
précédentes, dans lequel l'air pour la combustion air-combustible
est préchauffé par un dispositif de récupération
de chaleur (148 ; 150) comprenant une évacuation (77 ; 78).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 6 lorsqu'elle dépend
de la revendication 5, dans lequel les pressions
d'évacuation individuelles de l'évacuation du dispositif de
récupération de chaleur (77 ; 78) et de la au moins une
évacuation auxiliaire (141 ; 143 ; 201 ; 203) sont
commandées pour empêcher l'écoulement d'azote contenu dans
l'air utilisé pour la combustion air-combustible dans la
zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) de pénétrer dans la zone de
fusion (184 ; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications
précédentes, dans lequel le four comprend une barrière
physique entre la zone de fusion (184 ; 236) et la zone
d'affinage
(170 ; 270) pour empêcher l'écoulement d'azote contenu dans
l'air utilisé pour la combustion air-combustible dans la
zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) de pénétrer dans la zone de
fusion
(184 ; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 8, dans lequel ladite
barrière physique est choisie parmi (i) la barrière
résultante de l'utilisation d'une hauteur de toit ou de
voûte inférieure dans la zone de fusion (184 ; 236) comparée
à la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) et/ou de l'utilisation
d'une largeur de four plus petite dans la zone de fusion
(184 ; 236) comparée à la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) et
(ii) une paroi de séparation séparant au moins partiellement
la zone de fusion (184 ; 236) de la zone d'affinage (170 ;
270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications
précédentes, dans lequel la combustion oxygène-combustible
est procurée par une pluralité de brûleurs oxygène-combustible
et dans lequel une proportion d'oxydant au-dessous
de la stoechiométrie est introduite dans au moins
l'un des brûleurs oxygène-combustible adjacent à l'une
quelconque des flammes de combustion air-combustible (164 à
168 ; 224 à 234).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications
précédentes, dans lequel un gaz auxiliaire est introduit
(300) entre une flamme oxygène-combustible (304) et le toit
(302) du four (140 ; 200) pour diluer l'atmosphère du four
contenant les produits de la combustion oxygène-combustible
près du toit du four (302).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications
précédentes, dans lequel la combustion oxygène-combustible
est fournie par au moins un brûleur oxygène-combustible
comprenant un étagement de l'oxygène et au moins 50 % de
l'oxygène pour le au moins un brûleur oxygène-combustible
comprenant un étagement de l'oxygène est dirigé par un
orifice d'étagement (310) dans le brûleur.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications
précédentes, dans lequel l'air pour la flamme de combustion
(164 à 168 ; 224 à 234) est enrichi (320) avec jusqu'à 50 %
en volume d'oxygène.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications
précédentes, dans lequel une lance (330) est utilisée pour
introduire de l'oxygène vers la flamme air-combustible (164
à 168 ; 224 à 234) en vue d'enrichir la flamme air-combustible
(164 à 168 ; 224 à 234).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four de fusion d'ingrédients de formation de verre
par un procédé de la revendication 1 comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) une extrémité de chargement (144), une extrémité de
déchargement (142), une zone de fusion (184 ; 236) adjacente
à l'extrémité de chargement (144) et une zone d'affinage
(170 ; 270) adjacente à l'extrémité de déchargement (142),</claim-text><claim-text>(b) un moyen destiné à introduire les ingrédients de
formation de verre dans la zone de fusion (184 ; 236),</claim-text><claim-text>(c) un moyen destiné à retirer les ingrédients de
formation de verre sous forme de verre fondu de la zone
d'affinage
(170 ; 270),</claim-text><claim-text>(d) un moyen destiné à fournir de l'énergie de
combustion (172 à 184 ; 238 à 248) sur la zone de fusion
(184 ; 236), et</claim-text><claim-text>(e) un moyen destiné à fournir de l'énergie de
combustion (164 à 168 ; 224 à 234) sur la zone d'affinage
(170 ; 270),</claim-text></claim-text>
   caractérisé en ce que :
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) ledit moyen destiné à fournir de l'énergie de
combustion sur la zone de fusion (184 ; 236) fournit une
majorité de l'énergie de combustion (174 à 184 ; 238 à 248)
par une combustion oxygène-combustible en dirigeant la
flamme de la combustion oxygène-combustible (172 à 184 ; 238
à 248) vers les ingrédients de formation de verre à un angle
entre 0° et 30° par rapport à l'horizontale, et</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) ledit moyen destiné à fournir de l'énergie de
combustion sur la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) fournit une
majorité de l'énergie de combustion (164 à 168 ; 224 à 234)
par une combustion air-combustible.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon la revendication 15, comprenant en outre
un dispositif de récupération de chaleur (148 ; 150) pour
préchauffer l'air pour la combustion air-combustible et
comportant une évacuation (77 ; 78).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon la revendication 15 ou la revendication
16, comprenant en outre au moins une évacuation auxiliaire
(141 ; 142 ; 220 ; 223 ; 201 ; 203) dans la zone de fusion
(184 ; 236) destinée à évacuer principalement les produits
de la combustion oxygène-combustible (145 ; 147 ; 231 ; 233
; 241 ; 243) de la zone de fusion (184 ; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon la revendication 17, dans lequel la au
moins une évacuation auxiliaire (141 ; 143 ; 201 ; 203) est
située de façon adjacente à la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon la revendication 17 ou la revendication
18, comprenant en outre un dispositif de récupération de
chaleur (148 ; 150) pour préchauffer l'air pour la
combustion air-combustible et comportant une évacuation (77
; 78) et un moyen destiné à commander les pressions
d'évacuation individuelles de l'évacuation du dispositif de
récupération de chaleur (77 ; 78) et de la au moins une
évacuation auxiliaire (141 ; 143 ; 201 ; 203) pour empêcher
l'écoulement d'azote contenu dans l'air utilisé pour la
combustion air-combustible dans la zone d'affinage (170 ;
270) de pénétrer dans la zone de fusion
(184 ; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon l'une quelconque des revendications 15 à
19, comprenant en outre une barrière physique entre la zone
de fusion (184 ; 236) et la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) pour
empêcher l'écoulement d'azote contenu dans l'air utilisé
pour la combustion air-combustible dans la zone d'affinage
(170 ; 270) de pénétrer dans la zone de fusion (184 ; 236).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon la revendication 20, dans lequel ladite
barrière physique est choisie parmi (i) la barrière
résultant de l'utilisation d'une hauteur de toit ou de voûte
inférieure dans la zone de fusion (184 ; 236) comparée à la
zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) et/ou de l'utilisation d'une
largeur de four plus petite dans la zone de fusion (184 ;
236) comparée à la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270) et (ii) une
paroi de séparation séparant au moins partiellement la zone
de fusion (184 ; 236) de la zone d'affinage (170 ; 270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon l'une quelconque des revendications 15 à
21, dans lequel le moyen destiné à fournir la combustion
oxygène-combustible comprend une pluralité de brûleurs
oxygène-combustible, au moins l'un des brûleurs oxygène-combustible
adjacent à l'une quelconque des flammes de
combustion air-combustible (164 à 168 ; 224 à 234) recevant
une proportion d'oxydant au-dessous de la stoechiométrie.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon l'une quelconque des revendications 15 à
22, comprenant en outre un moyen (300) destiné à introduire
un gaz auxiliaire entre la flamme oxygène-combustible (304)
et le toit (302) du four (140 ; 200) pour diluer
l'atmosphère du four contenant les produits de la combustion
oxygène-combustible près du toit du four (302).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon l'une quelconque des revendications 15 à
23, dans lequel le toit (302) du four (140 ; 200) au-dessus
de la zone de fusion (184 ; 236) est plus bas que le toit du
four (140 ; 200) au-dessus de la zone d'affinage (170 ;
270).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Four selon la revendication 15, dans lequel la
combustion oxygène-combustible est fournie par au moins un
brûleur oxygène-combustible comprenant un étagement
d'oxygène, grâce à quoi au moins 50 % de l'oxygène pour le
au moins un brûleur oxygène-combustible comprenant un
étagement d'oxygène peut être dirigé par un orifice
d'étagement (310) dans le brûleur.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20070228"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CY</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DK</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MC</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>TR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031022</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031022</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031022</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031022</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031022</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031022</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040122</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040122</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040331</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="NLR1" date="20041101"><legal-event-body><event-title>NL: OPPOSITION HAS BEEN FILED WITH THE EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>opponent name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>L'AIR LIQUIDE S.A.</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>opponent name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PILKINGTON INSULATION LIMITED</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>opponent name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PILKINGTON PLC</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="R26" date="20040915"><legal-event-body><event-title>OPPOSITION FILED (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>opponent name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>L'AIR LIQUIDE S.A.</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>opponent name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PILKINGTON PLC</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040720</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040720</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26" date="20040908"><legal-event-body><event-title>OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>opponent name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>L'AIR LIQUIDE S.A.</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>opponent name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PILKINGTON INSULATION LIMITED</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040720</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040720</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20040528"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20040501"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ES</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG2A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>2204809</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>T3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20040430"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20031127"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60101011</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031127</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20031126"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20031031"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20031022"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20031022"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIN1" date="20031015"><legal-event-body><event-title>INVENTOR (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ENG, ROBERT MICHAEL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>HOKE, BRYAN CLAIR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>INSKIP, JULIAN LEONARD</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LIEVRE, KEVIN ALAN</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MARCHIANDO, ROBERT DEAN</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SLAVEJKOV, ALEKSANDAR GEORGI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20021009"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AT BE CH CY DE DK ES FI FR GB GR IE IT LI LU MC NL PT SE TR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20020911"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020713</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20020123"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20020123"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIN1" date="20011121"><legal-event-body><event-title>INVENTOR (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ENG, ROBERT MICHAEL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>HOKE, BRYAN CLAIR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>INSKIP, JULIAN LEONARD</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LIEVRE, KEVIN ALAN</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MARCHIANDO, ROBERT DEAN</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SLAVEJKOV, ALEKSANDAR GEORGI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010926"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010926"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>
