<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1125565-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1125565" kind="B1" date="20041222"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23220122" ucid="EP-1125565-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1125565</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20041222</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01100105-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01100105</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010111</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="IT-MI000122" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>IT</country><doc-number>MI000122</doc-number><date>20000128</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="IT-MI20000122-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>IT</country><doc-number>MI20000122</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000128</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20040322</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61B  17/68        20060101C N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61B  17/82        20060101A N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61F   2/00        20060101A N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61F   2/00        20060101C N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61F   2/30        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61F   2/30        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61F   2/40        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61F2/30L2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61F2/40</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61B17:82</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:00A2E</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:00T1C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:00Y2F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:30N2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:30P4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:30S1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:30S20R</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:30S3</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:30S9</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:30W2S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:40C1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:40C6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:40D4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:40D5C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61F2:40D6</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Schulterendoprothese für Brüche des oberen Endes des Oberarmknochens</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Shoulder endoprosthesis for fractures of the upper end of the humerus</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Endoprothèse de l'épaule pour fractures de l'extrémité supérieure de l'humérus</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>CREMASCOLI ORTHO S A</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>CREMASCOLI ORTHO S.A</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>NOGARIN LIVIO</name><address><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>NOGARIN, LIVIO</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>NOGARIN, LIVIO</last-name><address><street>Via Ippogrifo 11</street><city>37100 Verona</city><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Cremascoli Ortho S.A</last-name><address><street>Z.E. La Farlede, Rue Pasteur, BP 222</street><city>83089 Toulon Cedex</city><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Modiano, Guido, Dr.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Modiano &amp;amp; Associati SpA Via Meravigli, 16</street><city>20123 Milano</city><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>A shoulder endoprosthesis for fractures of the upper end of the humerus, comprising a humeral stem (15), adapted to be accommodated in an intramedullary canal of the humerus (11) and provided with multiple longitudinal ribs (18), and a humeral proximal part (16), which is suitable to couple to one end of the stem (15), is provided with a plurality of lateral fins (23) and has, at an upper end, a portion (20) for engagement with a humeral head (17) which is suitable to reconstruct the head of the humerus (11) of the patient. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">A shoulder endoprosthesis for fractures of the upper end of the humerus,
comprising a humeral stem (15), adapted to be accommodated in an
intramedullary canal of the humerus (11) and provided with multiple
longitudinal ribs (18), and a humeral proximal part (16), which is suitable to
couple to one end of the stem (15), is provided with a plurality of lateral fins
(23) and has, at an upper end, a portion (20) for engagement with a humeral
head (17) which is suitable to reconstruct the head of the humerus (11) of
the patient.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1125989-A1-00000001" he="142" wi="70" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a shoulder endoprosthesis for fractures of the
upper end of the humerus.</p><p num="0002">It is known that among the various kinds of fracture of the upper end of the
humerus four-part fractures are the most severe and often require surgical treatment
when the fragments of the fracture are mutually dislocated.</p><p num="0003">In a four-part fracture the muscles play a key role in the pathophysiology of this
type of fracture, since they pull in different directions on each fragment of the fracture.
As shown in Figure 1, the diaphysis 1, the fragments of the inferior tuberosity 2, the
upper tuberosity 3 and the humeral head 4 are separated one another and the fracture is
not simple. Conservative treatment by surgical reduction is not satisfactory and very
often causes pseudarthrosis or necrosis of the humeral head.</p><p num="0004">Accordingly, in these cases the only possible treatment that allows to recover
complete mobility and eliminate pain is joint replacement.</p><p num="0005">Most surgical procedures that use shoulder joint prostheses are the consequence
of fractures.</p><p num="0006">Currently known shoulder prostheses are mainly cemented and have holes in the
proximal-lateral part in order to allow fixation of the tuberosities. However, the
location of said holes makes it difficult to achieve stable fixation of the tuberosities;
accordingly, fragment consolidation is often not achieved and patients complain of
continuous pain and unsatisfactory mobility of the joint.</p><p num="0007">With most of the currently known shoulder prostheses, once the cement has set
it is not possible to correct retroversion and therefore position the prosthesis
appropriately.</p><p num="0008"><ref type="patent">US-A-5728161</ref> and <ref type="patent">EP-A-1043001</ref> (a document in the sense of Article 54(3)
and (4) EPC) disclose shoulder endoprostheses having a combination of features as set
forth in the precharacterizing portion of the appended claim 1. </p><p num="0009">The aim of the present invention is to provide a shoulder endoprosthesis which
can be applied in the case of multiple fractures without requiring bone cement.</p><p num="0010">Within the scope of this aim, an object of the present invention is to provide a
shoulder endoprosthesis which allows to restore humeral length and correct
retroversion.</p><p num="0011">Another object of the present invention is to provide a shoulder endoprosthesis
which allows to fix the tuberosities to the diaphysis as well as to the prosthesis.</p><p num="0012">Another object of the present invention is to provide a shoulder endoprosthesis
which allows to reposition the tuberosities with the correct tension and in the correct
seat.</p><p num="0013">Another object of the present invention is to provide a shoulder endoprosthesis
which is highly reliable, relatively easy to manufacture and at competitive costs.</p><p num="0014">In accordance with the invention, there is provided a shoulder endoprosthesis
for fractures of the upper end of the humerus, as defined in the appended claims.</p><p num="0015">Further characteristics and advantages will become better apparent from the
description of preferred but not exclusive embodiments of the shoulder endoprosthesis
according to the present invention, illustrated only by way of non-limitative example in
the accompanying drawings, wherein:
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a perspective view of a four-part fracture of the upper end of the
humerus; </li><li>Figure 2 is an exploded view of the shoulder endoprosthesis according to
the present invention;</li><li>Figure 3 is a front view of the humeral proximal part that constitutes one
of the components of the endoprosthesis shown in Figure 2;</li><li>Figure 4 is a plan view of the humeral stem, accommodated in the
intramedullary canal of the humerus;</li><li>Figure 5 is a schematic view of the insertion of the endoprosthesis
according to the invention in the humerus; and</li><li>Figure 6 is a view of a second embodiment of the humeral head which
constitutes a component of the endoprosthesis according to the present
invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0016">With reference to the figures, and particularly to Figures 2 to 6, the
endoprosthesis according to the present invention, generally designated by
the reference numeral 10, comprises a humeral stem 15 designed to be
inserted in the intramedullary canal of the humerus, which is designated by
the reference numeral 11 in Figures 4 and 5.</p><p num="0017">The second component of the endoprosthesis according to the invention
is constituted by the humeral proximal part 16, designed to couple to the
humeral stem 15 at one end and to a humeral head 17 at the opposite end.
The humeral head 17 constitutes the third component of the endoprosthesis
10 and is conveniently constituted, for example, by a spherical portion.</p><p num="0018">In detail, the humeral stem 15 is a conical tubular element which has, on
its lateral surface, longitudinal ribs 18 which are suitable to penetrate for a
few tenths of a millimeter in the cortex of the humerus 11, ensuring
excellent primary and secondary stability against rotation.</p><p num="0019">Conveniently, the humeral stem 15 is made for example of titanium alloy
and tapers gently with a total angle of for example 2°.</p><p num="0020">Figure 4 is a plan view of the insertion of the humeral stem 15 in the
intramedullary canal of the humerus 11, with the longitudinal ribs 18 which 
engage the internal surface of the intramedullary canal of the humerus 11,
allowing stable fixation of the humeral stem 15.</p><p num="0021">The second component of the endoprosthesis according to the invention,
i.e., the humeral proximal portion 16, which is also for example made of
titanium alloy, can be provided in different sizes, each having a different
length.</p><p num="0022">The humeral proximal portion 16 is formed by a body which is shaped so
as to engage, at one end, the conical end portion 19 of the humeral stem 15,
and has, at the opposite end, a protruding conical portion 20 which is
suitable to engage an appropriately provided seat 21 formed in the humeral
head 17.</p><p num="0023">Conveniently, the conical portion 20 is angled with respect to the axis of
the proximal part 16 and therefore of the stem 15.</p><p num="0024">Preferably, the angle of the conical portion 20 is approximately 135°.</p><p num="0025">The lateral surface of the proximal part 16 has a plurality of fins 23
which are suitable to allow fixation of the tuberosities in the bone in order
to afford stable anchoring.</p><p num="0026">The fins 23 have holes 24 which allow to fix wires to the tuberosities.</p><p num="0027">Additional holes 25 for anchoring wires to the tuberosities are further
provided in the anterior portion of the proximal part 16.</p><p num="0028">The holes 25 are through holes, as shown in the front view of Figure 3.</p><p num="0029">The seat 21 formed in the humeral head 17 and suitable to allow the
engagement of the conical portion or neck 20 can be conveniently provided
with an axis which is inclined with respect to the axis of symmetry 32 of the
humeral head 17.</p><p num="0030">In this case, the axis of the seat designated by the reference numeral 31 is
substantially inclined with respect to the axis of symmetry 32. This allows
better adaptation of the humeral head 17 to the anatomy of the proximal
epiphysis.</p><p num="0031">Figure 6 illustrates two different inclinations of the axis 31. </p><p num="0032">Essentially, the anchoring of the prosthesis according to the invention to
the humerus is very simple, since it does not require the use of bone cement,
and allows to fix the two tuberosities by using wires.</p><p num="0033">The humeral stem 15 is further inserted in the intramedullary canal of the
humerus 11, also without using bone cement, and the longitudinal ribs 18
allow its stable anchoring.</p><p num="0034">In practice it has been observed that the shoulder endoprosthesis
according to the invention fully achieves the intended aim, since it allows to
reduce the fracture and restore joint function with a fully natural anchoring
to the bone.</p><p num="0035">The endoprosthesis according to the invention is susceptible of numerous
modifications and variations, all of which are within the scope of the
inventive concept. All the details may furthermore be replaced with other
technically equivalent elements.</p><p num="0036">In practice, the materials employed, so long as they are compatible with
the specific use, as well as the dimensions, may be any according to
requirements and to the state of the art.</p><p num="0037">Where technical features mentioned in any claim are followed by
reference signs, those reference signs have been included for the sole
purpose of increasing the intelligibility of the claims and accordingly, such
reference signs do not have any limiting effect on the interpretation of each
element identified by way of example by such reference signs.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Schulterendoprothese (10) für Brüche des oberen Endes des
Oberarmknochens (11), umfassend einen Oberarmknochenschaft
(15), welcher zur Aufnahme in einem intramedullären Kanal des
Oberarmknochens (11) angepaßt und mit mehreren Längsrippen
(18) versehen ist, und ein proximales Oberarmknochenteil (16),
welches zum Verbinden mit einem Ende des Schafts (15) angepaßt
ist, mit einer Mehrzahl von seitlichen Lappen (23) versehen
ist und an einem oberen Ende einen Abschnitt (20) für den Eingriff
mit einem Oberarmknochenkopf (17) besitzt, welcher angepaßt
ist den Kopf des Oberarmknochens (11) des Patienten zu
rekonstruieren, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß die Mehrzahl von
seitlichen Lappen an beiden gegenüberliegenden Seiten des
proximalen Oberarmknochenteils (16) eine Mehrzahl von einzelnen
und unzusammenhängenden seitlichen Lappen (23) entlang von
sich in Längsrichtung der Endoprothese (10) erstreckenden Wegen umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothese nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß
der Oberarmknochenschaft (15) durch ein konisches rohrförmiges
Element gebildet ist, und die Mehrzahl der Längsrippen (18)
auf einer Außenfläche des Schafts (15) gebildet sind.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothese nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß
das proximale Oberarmknochenteil (16) mehrere in einem Vorderbereich
desselben angeordnete Durchgangslöcher (25) besitzt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothese nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß
die Mehrzahl von seitlichen Lappen (23) des proximalen Oberarmknochenteils
(16) jeweils mit einem Loch (24) versehen ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothese nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß
der Abschnitt (20) für den Eingriff des proximalen Oberarmknochenteils
(16) mit dem Oberarmknochenkopf (17) kegelstumpfförmig
und bezüglich der Achse des proximalen Teils (16) und
dadurch des Schafts (15) winklig ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothese nach Anspruch 5, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß
der Oberarmknochenkopf (17) ein kugelförmiger Abschnitt ist,
in dessen Innerem, in einem Zentrum, sich ein Sitz (21) für
den Eingriff mit dem proximalen Oberarmknochenteil (16) befindet.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothese nach Anspruch 6, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß
der Sitz (21) eine Achse (31) besitzt, welche bezüglich der
diametralen Symmetrieachse (32) des kugelförmigen Abschnitts
(17) im wesentlichen geneigt ist.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A shoulder endoprosthesis (10) for fractures of the upper end of the humerus
(11), comprising a humeral stem (15), which is suitable to be accommodated in an
intramedullary canal of the humerus (11) and is provided with multiple longitudinal
ribs (18), and a humeral proximal part (16), which is suitable to couple to one end of
said stem (15), is provided with a plurality of lateral fins (23) and has, at an upper end,
a portion (20) for engagement with a humeral head (17) which is suitable to reconstruct
the head of the humerus (11) of the patient, characterized in that said plurality of lateral
fins comprise on both
opposite sides of said humeral proximal part (16) a plurality of distinct and discontinuous lateral fins (23) arranged along paths extending longitudinally
in the endoprosthesis (10).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The endoprosthesis according to claim 1, characterized in that said humeral
stem (15) is constituted by a conical tubular element, said plurality of longitudinal ribs
(18) being formed on an outer surface of said stem (15).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The endoprosthesis according to claim 1, characterized in that said humeral
proximal part (16) has multiple through holes (25) arranged in an anterior region
thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The endoprosthesis according to claim 1, characterized in that said plurality
of lateral fins (23) of said humeral proximal part (16) are each provided with a hole
(24).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The endoprosthesis according to claim 1, characterized in that said portion
(20) for the engagement of said humeral proximal part (16) with said humeral head (17)
is frustum-shaped and angled with respect to the axis of the proximal part (16) and
therefore of the stem (15).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The endoprosthesis according to claim 5, characterized in that said humeral
head (17) is a spherical portion inside which there is, at a center, a seat (21) for
engagement with said humeral proximal part (16).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The endoprosthesis according to claim 6, characterized in that said seat (21)
has an axis (31) which is substantially inclined with respect to the diametrical axis of
symmetry (32) of said spherical portion (17).</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothèse (10) d'épaule pour fractures de
l'extrémité supérieure de l'humérus (11), comprenant
une tige humérale (15) qui est adaptée pour être logée
dans un canal intramédullaire de l'humérus (11) et est
dotée de multiples nervures longitudinales (18), et une
partie proximale humérale (16) qui est adaptée pour
être couplée à une extrémité de ladite tige (15), est
dotée d'une pluralité d'ailettes latérales (23) et
présente, à une extrémité supérieure, une partie (20)
de mise en prise avec une tête humérale (17) qui est
adaptée pour reconstruire la tête de l'humérus (11) du
patient, caractérisée en ce que ladite pluralité
d'ailettes latérales comprend, sur les deux côtés
opposés de ladite partie proximale humérale (16), une
pluralité d'ailettes latérales (23) distinctes et
discontinues disposées le long de voies s'étendant
longitudinalement dans l'endoprothèse (10).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothèse selon la revendication 1,
caractérisée en ce que ladite tige humérale (15) est
constituée par un élément tubulaire conique, ladite
pluralité de nervures longitudinales (18) étant formée
sur une surface externe de ladite tige (15).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothèse selon la revendication 1,
caractérisée en ce que ladite partie proximale humérale
(16) comporte de multiples orifices traversants (25)
disposés dans une région antérieure de celle-ci.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothèse selon la revendication 1,
caractérisée en ce que ladite pluralité d'ailettes
latérales (23) de ladite partie proximale humérale (16)
est dotée à chaque fois d'un orifice (24).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothèse selon la revendication 1,
caractérisée en ce que ladite partie (20) de mise en
prise de ladite partie proximale humérale (16) avec
ladite tête humérale (17) est de forme tronconique et
forme un angle par rapport à l'axe de la partie
proximale (16) et par conséquent de la tige (15).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothèse selon la revendication 5,
caractérisée en ce que ladite tête humérale (17) est
une partie sphérique à l'intérieur de laquelle se
trouve au centre un logement (21) pour la mise en prise
avec ladite partie proximale humérale (16).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Endoprothèse selon la revendication 6,
caractérisée en ce que ledit logement (21) présente un
axe (31) qui est sensiblement incliné par rapport à
l'axe de symétrie (32) diamétral de ladite partie
sphérique (17).</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20070228"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DK</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LU</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MC</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>TR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041222</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041222</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050111</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050111</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050131</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050322</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050322</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20051214"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050923</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20051102"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MM4A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20051028"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050616"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ES</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG2A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>2233502</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>T3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="NLT2" date="20050401"><legal-event-body><event-title>NL: MODIFICATIONS (OF NAMES), TAKEN FROM THE EUROPEAN PATENT PATENT BULLETIN</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Owner name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>WRIGHT CREMASCOLI ORTHO S.A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050228"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>NV</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>representative=s name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MARK-PAT MODIANO S.A.</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20050127"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60107882</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050127</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RAP2" date="20050126"><legal-event-body><event-title>PATENT OWNER REASSIGNMENT (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Owner name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>WRIGHT CREMASCOLI ORTHO S.A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050126"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20041231"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20041222"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20041222"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20030702"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030516</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20030409"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20030319"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030114</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20020717"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20020717"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010822"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010822"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>