<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1128051-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1128051" kind="B1" date="20040630"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23215417" ucid="EP-1128051-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1128051</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20040630</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01104315-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01104315</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010222</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000045579-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000045579</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000223</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000321699-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000321699</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001020</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000352922-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000352922</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001120</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20040102</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/94        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/94        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/08        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/08        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/24        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/24        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/28        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F01N   3/28        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02B  37/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02B  37/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  21/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  21/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/04        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/14        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/38        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/38        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/40        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  41/40        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  43/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02D  43/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  25/07        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F02M  25/07        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02D21/08B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02D41/00D4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02D41/00F6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02D41/02C4B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02D41/14D3L</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">F02D41/40D4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R01N3:08B6D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">R02M25:07J4H</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage und Verfahren zur Einstellung des Kraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunktes</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Exhaust-gas cleaning devices for an engine and a method of setting its fuel injection timing</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement et procédé de détermination de l'instant d'injection</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>MAZDA MOTOR</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>MAZDA MOTOR CORPORATION</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>WATANABE TOMOMI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SAITO TOMOAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KONDOU TERUNORI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HAYASHIBARA HIROSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KATAOKA MOTOSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>WATANABE, TOMOMI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SAITO, TOMOAKI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>HAYASHIBARA, HIROSHI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KATAOKA, MOTOSHI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KONDOU, TERUNORI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>WATANABE, TOMOMI</last-name><address><street>c/o Mazda Motor Corp., 3-1, Shinchi, Fuchu-cho</street><city>Aki-gun, Hiroshima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KATAOKA, MOTOSHI</last-name><address><street>c/o Mazda Motor Corp., 3-1, Shinchi, Fuchu-cho</street><city>Aki-gun, Hiroshima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>SAITO, TOMOAKI</last-name><address><street>c/o Mazda Motor Corp., 3-1, Shinchi, Fuchu-cho</street><city>Aki-gun, Hiroshima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>HAYASHIBARA, HIROSHI</last-name><address><street>c/o Mazda Motor Corp., 3-1, Shinchi, Fuchu-cho</street><city>Aki-gun, Hiroshima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KONDOU, TERUNORI</last-name><address><street>c/o Mazda Motor Corp., 3-1, Shinchi, Fuchu-cho</street><city>Aki-gun, Hiroshima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>MAZDA MOTOR CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>3-1, Shinchi, Fuchu-cho</street><city>Aki-gun, Hiroshima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Gossel, Hans K., Dipl.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Lorenz-Seidler-Gossel Widenmayerstrasse 23</street><city>80538 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine and a method of setting fuel injection timing employed therein, the exhaust-gas cleaning device comprising a catalytic NOx converter (22) for converting NOx, a reductant adder (38) for increasing the quantity of reductant supplied to the catalytic NOx converter (22) by injecting fuel at a specific time during a period from an expansion stroke through an exhaust stroke, and an activation state detector (37) for judging whether the catalytic NOx converter (22) is in its activated state, wherein when the activation state detector (37) judges that the catalytic NOx converter (22) is in an inactivated state, the fuel injection timing controlled by the reductant adder (38) is advanced compared to a case where the catalytic NOx converter (22) is in the activated state. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine and a
method of setting fuel injection timing employed therein,
the exhaust-gas cleaning device comprising a catalytic
NOx converter (22) for converting NOx, a reductant adder
(38) for increasing the quantity of reductant supplied to
the catalytic NOx converter (22) by injecting fuel at a
specific time during a period from an expansion stroke
through an exhaust stroke, and an activation state
detector (37) for judging whether the catalytic NOx
converter (22) is in its activated state, wherein when
the activation state detector (37) judges that the
catalytic NOx converter (22) is in an inactivated state,
the fuel injection timing controlled by the reductant
adder (38) is advanced compared to a case where the
catalytic NOx converter (22) is in the activated state.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1128415-A2-00000001" he="80" wi="124" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><heading>Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to exhaust-gas cleaning
devices for an engine installed on a motor vehicle or the
like in accordance with the preamble of claim 1 as well
as to a method of setting fuel injection timing in
accordance with the preamble of claim 14.</p><heading>Description of the Prior Art</heading><p num="0002"><ref type="patent">Japanese Unexamined Patent Publication No. 9-317524</ref>
discloses a prior art example of a nitrogen oxide
converter for an internal combustion engine. This
nitrogen oxide converter comprises a catalytic converter
including a first catalytic unit provided upstream in an
exhaust passage and a second catalytic unit provided
downstream of and in series with the first catalytic unit,
and the engine has a first group of cylinders connected
to the exhaust passage upstream of the first catalytic
unit and a second group of cylinders connected to the
exhaust passage between the first catalytic unit and the
second catalytic unit, wherein a primary fuel injection
command for producing engine power and a secondary fuel 
injection command for supplying hydrocarbons (HC) are
transmitted to a fuel injector for each cylinder to
regulate the amount of fuel supplied by secondary fuel
injection in accordance with the temperatures of the
first and second catalytic units determined by a catalyst
temperature detector, and to thereby maximize the
conversion rate of nitrogen oxides (NOx) while preventing
the individual catalytic units from overheating.</p><p num="0003"><ref type="patent">Japanese Unexamined Patent Publication No. 8-261052</ref>
discloses another prior art example of a NOx converter
for an internal combustion engine comprising fuel
injectors provided for individual cylinders, a catalytic
converter provided in an exhaust passage for reducing NOx
and a fuel injection controller for activating the fuel
injectors, wherein the fuel injection controller
transmits primary fuel injection commands to the fuel
injectors for injecting fuel in the vicinity of
compression stroke top dead center for producing engine
power as well as secondary fuel injection commands for
injecting fuel during expansion or exhaust stroke for
supplying HC to the catalytic converter in such a way
that the number of the secondary fuel injection commands
is smaller than the number of the primary fuel injection
commands to thereby obtain a satisfactory NOx conversion 
rate.</p><p num="0004">It is possible to reduce NOx by causing it to react
with reductants including HC in the aforementioned
examples constructed to improve the NOx conversion rate
while preventing overheating of the catalytic units
(catalytic converter) by making the secondary fuel
injection in addition to the primary fuel injection,
which is made in accordance with engine operating
conditions, to thereby increase the amount of HC in
exhaust gas. However, the NOx converters of these prior
art examples have a problem that they can not effectively
reduce NOx or effectively prevent soot formed of an
aggregate of carbon particles produced in combustion
chambers of the engine from being released into the
atmosphere when catalysts are still cold and inactive or
when their temperature is higher than a specified value.</p><p num="0005">While the secondary fuel injection is made besides
the primary fuel injection to accelerate warm-up of the
NOx converters or to make a judgment on the degree of
deterioration of their catalysts based on the rate of
temperature increase of the NOx converters in the prior
art examples, they have a problem that soot produced in
combustion chambers of the engine flows into the exhaust
passage and the quantity of soot released into the 
atmosphere increases if secondary fuel injection timing
is improper.</p><p num="0006">An exhaust-gas cleaning device according to the
preamble of claim 1 is known from document <ref type="patent">EP 0 826 869</ref>.
This prior art reference discloses an exhaust-gas heating
system for an internal combustion engine wherein a
primary fuel injection and a secondary fuel injection is
made. To increase the exhaust-gas temperature for
activation of the NOx purification catalyst, the primary
fuel injection is performed in a time period from an
intake stroke and an expansion stroke and thereafter the
secondary fuel injection is performed at a timing which
is possibly the latest part of a time period during which
a flame due to the primary fuel injection remains.</p><p num="0007">Furthermore, document <ref type="patent">FR 2 782 124</ref> discloses a
direct fuel injection engine with a turbocharger. In
order to improve warm-up characteristic of the catalyst,
a primary fuel injection is performed in a time period
from the intake stroke to an expansion stroke and
thereafter a secondary fuel injection is performed in
such a manner that the timing of secondary fuel injection
is adjusted such that a temperature in a cylinder reaches
a certain level. The fuel injection regimes disclosed by
these documents however may not satisfyingly enough 
purify the exhaust-gas by preventing raw NOx and soot
discharged from the engine from being released into the
atmosphere.</p><p num="0008">It is an objective of the present invention vis-à-vis
this prior art to provide an improved exhaust-gas
cleaning device and an improved method for setting fuel
injection timing which make it possible to more
effectively purify exhaust-gas.</p><p num="0009">This objective is achieved by an exhaust-gas
cleaning device according to claim 1. Furthermore, this
objective is achieved by a method according to claim 14.
Preferred embodiments of the invention are laid down in
the dependent claims.</p><p num="0010">According to the invention, the aforementioned
exhaust-gas cleaning device comprises a turbocharger
driven by exhaust gas for supplying the engine with
precompressed intake air, wherein the secondary fuel
injection time is corrected with reference to the ending
time of diffusion combustion which varies due to a
supercharging effect provided by the turbocharger.</p><p num="0011">In this construction, exhaust gas pressure increases
as the secondary fuel injection is made at a specific
time after the primary fuel injection, and because the
amount of intake air increases due to the supercharging 
effect of the turbocharger, burning of carbon residue
left within the combustion chamber is accelerated and
generation of soot is effectively suppressed.
Furthermore, when the ending time of diffusion combustion
has been advanced as a result of the increase in the
amount of intake air due to the supercharging effect of
the turbocharger, the secondary fuel injection time is
corrected such that the fuel supplied by the secondary
injection would combust approximately at the ending time
of diffusion combustion which tends to vary due to the
supercharging effect of the turbocharger.</p><p num="0012">According to an embodiment of the invention, the
exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine comprises a
fuel injector for injecting fuel into a combustion
chamber, a combustion controller for controlling burning
conditions of the fuel injected by the fuel injector, a
catalytic NOx converter provided in an exhaust passage of
the engine for converting at least NOx, a reductant adder
for increasing the quantity of reductant in exhaust gas
by causing the fuel injector to inject the fuel at a
specified time during a period from an expansion stroke
through an exhaust stroke, and an activation state
detector for judging whether the catalytic NOx converter
is in its activated state, wherein when the activation 
state detector judges that the catalytic NOx converter is
in an inactivated state, fuel injection time controlled
by the reductant adder is advanced compared to a case
where the catalytic NOx converter is in the activated
state.</p><p num="0013">Since the reductant adder performs a control
operation for advancing the fuel injection time compared
to the case where the catalytic NOx converter is in the
activated state when the catalytic NOx converter is
judged to be in its inactivated state in this
construction, the amount of NOx discharged from the
combustion chamber is reduced and, therefore, NOx
emissions into the atmosphere are suppressed.</p><p num="0014">In one embodiment of the invention, the catalytic
NOx converter includes a NOx-reducing catalyst which
purifies the exhaust gas by reducing NOx contained
therein as a result of reaction between NOx and the
reductant occurring under oxygen-rich conditions in which
the concentration of oxygen is high.</p><p num="0015">In this construction, the reductant adder performs
the control operation for advancing the fuel injection
time compared to the case where the catalytic NOx
converter is in the activated state when the NOx-reducing
catalyst which reduces NOx as a result of reaction 
between NOx and the reductant is judged to be in its
inactivated state. Thus, the amount of NOx discharged
from the combustion chamber is reduced and, in particular,
NOx emissions into the atmosphere are suppressed.</p><p num="0016">According to another embodiment of the invention,
the reductant adder includes a secondary injection
controller which controls the fuel injector to make
secondary injection of the fuel at a specific time during
the period from the expansion stroke through the exhaust
stroke after primary injection of the fuel from the fuel
injector in accordance with operating conditions of the
engine, wherein the secondary injection controller
advances the secondary fuel injection time within a
period from the point of the primary fuel injection to a
crank angle of 60° after compression stroke top dead
center when the activation state detector judges that the
NOx-reducing catalyst is in the inactivated state.</p><p num="0017">In this construction, the reductant adder including
the secondary injection controller advances the secondary
fuel injection time within the period from the point of
the primary fuel injection to the crank angle of 60°
after compression stroke top dead center when the NOx-reducing
catalyst is judged to be in the inactivated
state. Accordingly, the amount of NOx discharged from 
the combustion chamber is effectively reduced and NOx
emissions into the atmosphere are suppressed.</p><p num="0018">According to another embodiment of the invention,
the secondary injection controller performs the secondary
fuel injection at longer time intervals than the period
of a single combustion cycle when the activation state
detector judges that the NOx-reducing catalyst is in the
inactivated state.</p><p num="0019">In this construction, the reductant adder including
the secondary injection controller advances the secondary
fuel injection time within the period from the point of
the primary fuel injection to the crank angle of 60°
after compression stroke top dead center, wherein the
number of times of the secondary injection is reduced by
making the secondary fuel injection time longer than the
period of the single combustion cycle, when the NOx-reducing
catalyst is judged to be in the inactivated
state. This approach serves to reduce the amount of NOx
discharged from the combustion chamber even more
effectively.</p><p num="0020">According to another embodiment of the invention,
the activation state detector detects the temperature of
the NOx-reducing catalyst and judges that the NOx-reducing
catalyst is in the inactivated state when the 
detected temperature is equal to or higher than a
specific reference temperature.</p><p num="0021">In this approach, the secondary fuel injection time
is advanced to a specific point and the number of times
of the secondary injection is reduced when the activation
state detector judges that the NOx-reducing catalyst is
in the inactivated state with its temperature becoming
equal to or higher than the reference temperature, so
that the amount of NOx discharged from the combustion
chamber is reduced and NOx emissions into the atmosphere
are suppressed.</p><p num="0022">According to still another embodiment of the
invention, a first NOx-reducing catalyst is provided in
the exhaust passage and a second NOx-reducing catalyst
which becomes activated when the first NOx-reducing
catalyst is in its inactivated state is provided
downstream of the first NOx-reducing catalyst.</p><p num="0023">In this embodiment of the invention, the secondary
fuel injection time is advanced to a specific point and
the number of times of the secondary injection is reduced
when the activation state detector judges that the first
NOx-reducing catalyst is in the inactivated state with
its temperature becoming equal to or higher than the
reference temperature. Accordingly, a sufficient 
quantity of reductant passing through the first NOx-reducing
catalyst and supplied to the second NOx-reducing
catalyst is ensured and the second NOx-reducing catalyst
can effectively reduce NOx using the reductant.</p><p num="0024">In any of the aforementioned embodiments of the
invention, the catalytic NOx converter may be formed by
depositing catalytic metal on zeolite.</p><p num="0025">According to this construction, NOx in the exhaust
gas can be effectively reduced by using the reductant
entrapped in pores within zeolite, which is a porous
material, even when the NOx conversion rate of the
catalytic NOx converter including the NOx-reducing
catalyst is low.</p><p num="0026">According to another embodiment of the invention,
the exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine comprises a
fuel injector for injecting fuel into a combustion
chamber, a primary injection controller for controlling
mode of primary injection of the fuel from the fuel
injector in accordance with engine operating conditions,
a secondary injection controller for controlling the fuel
injector to make secondary fuel injection at a specific
time during a period from the point of the primary fuel
injection through an expansion stroke, and a catalytic
NOx converter provided in an exhaust passage of the 
engine for converting at least NOx, wherein the secondary
fuel injection is performed at a specific time after the
primary fuel injection during a period between crank
angles of 30° and 60° after compression stroke top dead
center when the engine is under operating conditions in
which the amount of NOx delivered to the downstream side
of the catalytic NOx converter is large.</p><p num="0027">In this construction, the secondary fuel injection
is performed during the period between crank angles of
30° and 60° after compression stroke top dead center when
the amount of NOx delivered to the downstream side of the
catalytic NOx converter is large, so that the amount of
raw NOx discharged from the combustion chamber into the
exhaust passage is reduced. As a consequence, NOx
emissions into the atmosphere are suppressed even when
the catalytic NOx converter is in its inactivated state.</p><p num="0028">According to a further embodiment of the invention,
an exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine comprises a
fuel injector for injecting fuel into a combustion
chamber, a primary injection controller for controlling
mode of primary fuel injection performed by the fuel
injector at a specific time during a period from an
intake stroke to an early part of an expansion stroke in
accordance with engine operating conditions, and a 
secondary injection controller for controlling the fuel
injector to make secondary fuel injection at a specific
time during a period from the point of the primary fuel
injection through the expansion stroke, wherein secondary
fuel injection time is set with reference to ending time
of diffusion combustion occurring within the combustion
chamber by the primary fuel injection.</p><p num="0029">Since the secondary fuel injection time is set with
reference to the ending time of diffusion combustion
occurring within the combustion chamber by the primary
fuel injection in this construction, carbon is burnt
together with the fuel injected by the secondary
injection under conditions in which carbon and oxygen
existing within the combustion chamber are premixed.</p><p num="0030">In an embodiment of the invention, the
aforementioned exhaust-gas cleaning device further
comprises a combustion state discriminator for
discriminating the state of diffusion combustion
occurring within the combustion chamber by the primary
fuel injection, wherein the secondary fuel injection time
is set with reference to the ending time of diffusion
combustion determined by the combustion state
discriminator.</p><p num="0031">In this construction, the secondary fuel injection 
time is set with reference to the ending time of
diffusion combustion determined by the combustion state
discriminator based on a sensing signal fed from a
pressure sensor for detecting the pressure within the
combustion chamber, a sensing signal fed from a
temperature sensor for detecting the temperature within
the combustion chamber, a sensing signal fed from a
combustion light sensor for detecting a bright light
produced by diffusion combustion, or a sensing signal fed
from a sensor for detecting the quantity of highly
reactive electrically-charged hydrogen and HC existing
within the combustion chamber. According to this
approach, the secondary fuel injection is made with
optimum timing for current engine operating conditions
and the amount of soot emission is effectively reduced.</p><p num="0032">According to another embodiment of the invention,
the aforementioned exhaust-gas cleaning device further
comprises an exhaust gas recirculator for recirculating
part of the exhaust gas back to an intake passage, and an
exhaust gas recirculation controller for performing a
feedback control operation such that exhaust gas
recirculation ratio determined by the exhaust gas
recirculator becomes equal to a target value.</p><p num="0033">In this construction, when the exhaust gas pressure 
increases due to the secondary fuel injection made at a
specific time after the primary fuel injection and the
amount of intake air increases due to the supercharging
effect of the turbocharger, the exhaust gas recirculation
controller performs the feedback control operation to
correspondingly increase the amount of exhaust gas
recirculated to the intake passage. As a consequence,
the amount of raw NOx discharged from the combustion
chamber is reduced more effectively.</p><p num="0034">According to still another embodiment of the
invention, the aforementioned exhaust-gas cleaning device
further comprises a catalytic NOx converter provided in
an exhaust passage of the engine for converting at least
NOx, wherein the secondary fuel injection time is set
with reference to the ending time of diffusion combustion
occurring within the combustion chamber by the primary
fuel injection when the catalytic NOx converter is in its
inactivated state.</p><p num="0035">In this construction, the secondary fuel injection
time is set with reference to the ending time of
diffusion combustion occurring within the combustion
chamber by the primary fuel injection when the catalytic
NOx converter provided in the exhaust passage of the
engine is in the inactivated state. Therefore, an effect 
of reducing the amount of raw NOx by increasing the
quantity of highly reactive electrically-charged hydrogen
and HC existing within the combustion chamber and an
effect of reducing the quantity of soot by accelerated
burning of carbon residue are obtained simultaneously.</p><p num="0036">According to yet another embodiment of the invention,
when the catalytic NOx converter is in its activated
state, the secondary fuel injection time is set such that
a sufficient quantity of reductant supplied to the
catalytic NOx converter is ensured, and when the
catalytic NOx converter is in its inactivated state, the
secondary fuel injection time is set with reference to
the ending time of diffusion combustion occurring within
the combustion chamber by the primary fuel injection by
advancing the primary fuel injection time.</p><p num="0037">In this construction, a sufficient quantity of
reductant supplied to the catalytic NOx converter is
ensured when the catalytic NOx converter is in its
activated state, so that NOx emissions into the
atmosphere are suppressed by NOx-converting function of
the catalytic NOx converter. Also, the secondary fuel
injection time is set such that the fuel supplied by the
secondary injection would combust approximately at the
ending time of diffusion combustion when the catalytic 
NOx converter is in its inactivated state, so that the
amount of raw NOx discharged from the combustion chamber
into the exhaust passage is reduced effectively.</p><p num="0038">In any of the aforementioned embodiments of the
invention, the amount of fuel supplied by the secondary
injection may preferably be set between 0.2% and 50% of
the total amount of fuel injected.</p><p num="0039">When the secondary injection is set within a range
of 0.2% to 50% of the total amount of fuel injected, it
is possible to effectively reduce the amount of soot
emission without increasing fuel consumption.</p><p num="0040">In a further embodiment of the invention, a method
of setting fuel injection timing in an engine comprising
a fuel injector for injecting fuel into a combustion
chamber, a primary injection controller for controlling
mode of primary fuel injection performed by the fuel
injector at a specific time during a period from an
intake stroke to an early part of an expansion stroke in
accordance with engine operating conditions, and a
secondary injection controller for controlling the fuel
injector to make secondary injection of the fuel at a
specific time during a period from the point of the
primary fuel injection through the expansion stroke,
includes the step of setting secondary fuel injection 
time using a secondary injection controller with
reference to ending time of diffusion combustion
occurring within the combustion chamber by the primary
fuel injection.</p><p num="0041">Since the secondary fuel injection time is set with
reference to the ending time of diffusion combustion
occurring within the combustion chamber by the primary
fuel injection in this method of the invention, the
secondary fuel injection is made under conditions in
which carbon and oxygen existing within the combustion
chamber are premixed and carbon is burnt together with
the fuel. Consequently, generation of soot formed of an
aggregate of carbon particles can be effectively
suppressed.</p><heading><b>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</b></heading><p num="0042"><sl><li>FIG. 1 is a general configuration diagram showing an
exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine according to a
first embodiment of the invention;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a flowchart showing an exhaust gas
recirculation control operation;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a graphical presentation of a map used for
setting a basic exhaust gas recirculation ratio;</li><li>FIG. 4 is a graphical presentation of a map used for 
setting a target fresh air quantity;</li><li>FIG. 5 is a graph showing the relationship between
the quantity of smoke and air-fuel ratio;</li><li>FIG. 6 is a graph showing the relationship between
NOx conversion rate and catalyst temperature;</li><li>FIG. 7 is a flowchart showing a first half of a
control operation performed in the exhaust-gas cleaning
device of the first embodiment;</li><li>FIG. 8 is a flowchart showing a second half of the
control operation performed in the exhaust-gas cleaning
device of the first embodiment;</li><li>FIG. 9 is a graph showing an example of relationship
between secondary injection time and the amount of raw
NOx;</li><li>FIG. 10 is a graph showing variations in the amount
of raw NOx observed when the frequency of secondary
injection was reduced;</li><li>FIG. 11 is a graph showing variations in the amount
of raw NOx observed when the frequency of secondary
injection was further reduced;</li><li>FIG. 12 is a general configuration diagram showing
an exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine according to
a second embodiment of the invention;</li><li>FIG. 13 is a graph showing variations in the 
concentration of HC in exhaust gas which has passed
through a NOx-reducing catalyst;</li><li>FIG. 14 is a graph showing the relationship between
NOx conversion rate and catalyst temperature;</li><li>FIG. 15 is a general configuration diagram showing
an exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine according to
a third embodiment of the invention;</li><li>FIG. 16 is a flowchart showing a control operation
performed in the exhaust-gas cleaning device of the third
embodiment;</li><li>FIGS. 17A-17C are graphs showing variations in heat
release rate in a combustion chamber;</li><li>FIGS. 18A-18C are graphs showing the relationship
between the secondary injection time and the quantity of
soot produced;</li><li>FIGS. 19A-19C are graphs showing the relationship
between the ratio of the amount of fuel injected by the
secondary injection to the total amount of fuel injected
and the quantity of soot produced;</li><li>FIGS. 20A-20C are graphs showing the relationship
between the secondary injection time and the quantity of
HC produced;</li><li>FIGS. 21A-21C are graphs showing the relationship
between the secondary injection time and fuel 
consumption;</li><li>FIGS. 22A-22C are graphs showing the relationship
between the secondary injection time and the amount of
NOx emissions; and</li><li>FIGS. 23A-23C are graphs showing the relationship
between the ratio of the amount of fuel supplied by the
secondary injection to the total amount of fuel injected
and fuel consumption.</li></sl></p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED
EMBODIMENTS OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0043">FIG. 1 shows an exhaust-gas cleaning device for a
diesel engine installed on a motor vehicle according to a
first embodiment of the invention. An engine body 1 has
a plurality of cylinders 2 (of which only one is
illustrated), and a piston 3 is fitted in each cylinder 2,
forming a combustion chamber 4 therein, in a manner that
the piston 3 can reciprocate in the relevant cylinder 2.
A fuel injector 5 is provided approximately at the center
of the top of the combustion chamber 4 of each cylinder 2
to inject fuel directly into the combustion chamber 4
with specific timing. Further, a water temperature
sensor 18 for detecting the temperature of engine cooling
water is provided inside a water jacket (not shown) of 
the engine body 1.</p><p num="0044">The fuel injectors 5 of the individual cylinders 2
are connected to a common rail 6 which retains high-pressure
fuel. The common rail 6 is provided with a
pressure sensor 6a for detecting its internal fuel
pressure (common rail pressure), and a high-pressure
supply pump 8 driven by a crankshaft 7 is connected to
the common rail 6. The high-pressure supply pump 8
maintains the fuel pressure inside the common rail 6
detected by the pressure sensor 6a at 20 MPa or above
when the engine is at idle and at 50 MPa or above under
other engine operating conditions, for example, by
controlling fuel supply pressure.</p><p num="0045">The crankshaft 7 is provided with a crank angle
sensor 9 for detecting the angle of rotation of the
crankshaft 7. The crank angle sensor 9 is formed of a
sensing plate provided at a terminal part of the
crankshaft 7 and an electromagnetic pickup placed
opposite the outer periphery of the sensing plate. The
electromagnetic pickup detects passage of projections
formed on the outer periphery of the sensing plate and
outputs a pulse signal.</p><p num="0046">A downstream end of an intake passage 10 connected
to the engine body 1 branches out toward the individual 
cylinders 2 at an unillustrated surge tank, and branched
channels of the intake passage 10 are connected to the
combustion chambers 4 of the individual cylinders 2
through their intake ports. The surge tank is provided
with an intake air pressure sensor 10a for detecting the
pressure of intake air supplied to the cylinders 2.</p><p num="0047">An airflow sensor 11 for detecting the flow rate of
intake air drawn into the engine body 1, a blower 12
driven by a later-described turbine 21 for compressing
the intake air, an intercooler 13 for cooling the intake
air compressed by the blower 12, and an intake throttle
valve 14 for varying the area of intake air flow are
provided in the intake passage 10 in this order from its
upstream side.</p><p num="0048">The intake throttle valve 14 is formed of a
butterfly valve whose valve element (disc) is partially
cut out to allow intake air passage even in a fully-closed
state. Like a later-described exhaust gas
recirculation valve (hereinafter referred to as the EGR
valve) 24, the opening of the intake throttle valve 14 is
varied as a negative pressure exerted on a diaphragm-type
actuator 15 is regulated by a negative-pressure-controlling
solenoid valve 16. The intake throttle valve
14 is associated with a sensor for detecting its opening. </p><p num="0049">An upstream end of an exhaust passage 20 connected
to the engine body 1 branches out toward the individual
cylinders 2, and branched channels of the exhaust passage
20 are connected to the combustion chambers 4 of the
individual cylinders 2 through their exhaust ports. The
turbine 21 turned by an exhaust gas flow, a catalytic NOx
converter 22 made of a NOx-reducing catalyst for
purifying the exhaust gas by reducing at least NOx
contained therein, and a NOx sensor 19 for detecting the
concentration of NOx in the exhaust gas which has passed
through the catalytic NOx converter 22 are provided in
the exhaust passage 20 in this order from its upstream
side.</p><p num="0050">The catalytic NOx converter 22 made of the NOx-reducing
catalyst includes a cordierite carrier of a
honeycomb structure in which a number of through holes
extending parallel to each other are made in the
direction of the exhaust gas flow, with two catalyst
layers formed surrounding the individual through holes.
More specifically, the catalyst layers are formed by
depositing platinum (Pt) and rhodium (Rh) on MFI zeolite
(ZSM5), for example, which is a porous material serving
as a support.</p><p num="0051">The catalytic NOx converter 22 is so constructed as 
to convert NOx in the exhaust gas by reacting NOx with
reductants when an air-fuel mixture in the combustion
chambers 4 is lean and the concentration of oxygen in the
exhaust gas high, as when the oxygen concentration is 4%
or above, for instance. It is to be noted, however, that
the catalytic NOx converter 22 of this embodiment has a
function as a three-way catalyst even when the oxygen
concentration is low.</p><p num="0052">The airflow sensor 11 provided in the intake passage
10 and the turbine 21 provided in the exhaust passage 20
together constitute a turbocharger 25 made of a variable-geometry
turbocharger (VGT). This turbocharger 25 is so
constructed as to vary the cross-sectional nozzle area of
the exhaust passage 20. The turbocharger 25 is provided
with a diaphragm-type actuator 30 for varying the cross-sectional
nozzle area and a solenoid valve 31 for
controlling a negative pressure exerted on the diaphragm-type
actuator 30.</p><p num="0053">An exhaust gas recirculation passage (hereinafter
referred to as the EGR passage) 23 for recirculating part
of the exhaust gas is connected to the exhaust passage 20
upstream of the turbine 21. A downstream end of the EGR
passage 23 is connected to the intake passage 10
downstream of the intake throttle valve 14. The 
aforementioned negative-pressure-operated EGR valve 24
whose opening is adjustable is provided in the EGR
passage 23 near its downstream end. The EGR valve 24 and
the EGR passage 23 together form an exhaust gas
recirculation system 33.</p><p num="0054">An unillustrated valve element of the EGR valve 24
is biased in a closing direction by a spring and biased
in an opening direction by a diaphragm-type actuator 24a,
whereby the EGR valve 24 linearly adjusts the opening of
the EGR passage 23. More specifically, a negative-pressure
passage 27 is connected to the diaphragm-type
actuator 24a at one end and to a vacuum pump (negative-pressure
source) 29 at the opposite end via a negative-pressure-controlling
solenoid valve 28. A negative
pressure for driving the EGR valve 24 is regulated as the
solenoid valve 28 opens or blocks the negative-pressure
passage 27, whereby the EGR valve 24 is caused to open
and close. The EGR valve 24 is associated with a lift
sensor 26 for detecting the position of its valve element.</p><p num="0055">Operation of the fuel injectors 5, the high-pressure
supply pump 8, the intake throttle valve 14, the EGR
valve 24 and the turbocharger 25 is controlled by control
signals output from a later-described electronic control
unit (hereinafter referred to as the ECU) 35. Output 
signals of the pressure sensor 6a, the crank angle sensor
9, the airflow sensor 11, the water temperature sensor 18
and an acceleration sensor 32, which detects the amount
of operation (depression stroke) of an accelerator pedal
operated by a driver, are entered to the ECU 35.</p><p num="0056">The ECU 35 includes a combustion controller 36 for
controlling burning conditions of the fuel to obtain
required engine output, an activation state detector 37
for determining whether the catalytic NOx converter 22 is
already in an activated state, a reductant adder 38 for
increasing the quantity of such reductants as HC supplied
to the catalytic NOx converter 22, and an exhaust gas
recirculation controller 39 for controlling the amount of
recirculated exhaust gas by driving the EGR valve 24 in
accordance with engine operating conditions.</p><p num="0057">An exhaust gas recirculation control operation
executed by the exhaust gas recirculation controller 39
is now described referring to a flowchart shown in FIG. 2.
Following the start of the control operation of the
flowchart, data detected by the individual sensors are
entered to the ECU 35 (step S1). The exhaust gas
recirculation controller 39 then reads out and sets a
basic exhaust gas recirculation ratio EGRb corresponding
to the engine operating condition from a predefined map 
based on the accelerator pedal depression stroke detected
by the acceleration sensor 32 and engine speed determined
from the output signal of the crank angle sensor 9 (step
S2). Here, the exhaust gas recirculation ratio refers to
the ratio of the quantity of exhaust gas recirculated to
the intake passage 10 through the EGR passage 23 to the
total quantity of intake air.</p><p num="0058">The map used for setting the basic exhaust gas
recirculation ratio EGRb is a mapping of exhaust gas
recirculation ratios experimentally obtained as a
function of the accelerator pedal depression stroke and
engine speed as shown in FIG. 3, in which the basic
exhaust gas recirculation ratio EGRb takes larger values
under low-load conditions where the accelerator pedal
depression stroke is small. The map is made such that
the basic exhaust gas recirculation ratio EGRb takes
smaller values in an engine idling range shown by
hatching in FIG. 3 than under medium-load conditions of
the engine.</p><p num="0059">Succeeding to step S2 above, the exhaust gas
recirculation controller 39 reads out and sets a target
fresh air quantity q from a predefined map based on the
accelerator pedal depression stroke and engine speed
(step S3). The fresh air quantity is a value obtained by 
subtracting the quantities of recirculated exhaust gas
and blowby gas from the total quantity of intake gas
introduced into the combustion chambers 4 and is obtained
based on the output signal of the airflow sensor 11. The
fresh air quantity is closely related to the quantity of
recirculated exhaust gas. As a general tendency, the
larger the quantity of recirculated exhaust gas, the
smaller the fresh air quantity.</p><p num="0060">The map used for setting the target fresh air
quantity q is a mapping of target fresh air quantities
experimentally obtained as a function of the accelerator
pedal depression stroke and engine speed as shown in FIG.
3, in which the larger the accelerator pedal depression
stroke the larger the target fresh air quantity q, and
the higher the engine speed the larger the target fresh
air quantity q. The map is made such that the target
fresh air quantity q takes larger values in the engine
idling range shown by hatching in FIG. 4 than under
medium-load conditions of the engine.</p><p num="0061">In a direct injection diesel engine, it is possible
to suppress NOx generation by increasing the exhaust gas
recirculation ratio. An increase in the exhaust gas
recirculation ratio results in a decrease in average air-fuel
ratio (richer air-fuel mixture) in the combustion 
chambers 4. There is a tendency for the quantity of
smoke (the quantity of soot) to rapidly increase when the
average air-fuel ratio approaches the stoichiometric air-fuel
ratio as depicted in FIG. 5. Therefore, the maps
used for setting the basic exhaust gas recirculation
ratio EGRb and the target fresh air quantity q in the
aforementioned steps S2 and S3 are made such that the
average air-fuel ratio in the combustion chambers 4 is
set to as small a value as possible within a range where
the quantity of smoke does not rapidly increase, as shown
by A/F*1 in FIG. 5, for instance.</p><p num="0062">In the engine idling range, the basic exhaust gas
recirculation ratio EGRb is set to a smaller value and
the target fresh air quantity q is set to a larger value
in the respective maps (FIGS. 2 and 3) such that the
average air-fuel ratio in the combustion chambers 4
becomes much higher than A/F*1 (leaner mixture), as shown
by A/F*2 in FIG. 5. Specifically, when the engine is at
idle, the opening of the EGR valve 24 is made relatively
small, and when the engine transfers from this condition
to a phase of acceleration, the EGR valve 24 is
immediately closed such that the quantity of fresh air
introduced into the combustion chambers 4 can be quickly
increased. This helps improve acceleration performance 
of the engine and prohibit the air-fuel ratio from
becoming momentarily too small (producing a rich mixture)
during transition to the acceleration phase, eventually
preventing an increase in the quantity of smoke during an
early stage of acceleration.</p><p num="0063">Succeeding to step S3 above, the exhaust gas
recirculation controller 39 reads out and sets a feedback
correction value EGRf/b for the exhaust gas recirculation
ratio from a predefined map based on a deviation of the
fresh air quantity obtained by subtracting the target
fresh air quantity q from actual fresh air quantity which
is determined based on the output signal of the airflow
sensor 11 (step S4). The feedback correction value
EGRf/b is set to take a negative value when the target
fresh air quantity q is larger than the actual fresh air
quantity and to a positive value when the target fresh
air quantity q is smaller than the actual fresh air
quantity. In either case, the large the deviation of the
fresh air quantity, the larger the absolute value of the
feedback correction value EGRf/b. In the aforementioned
map, there is provided a dead zone in a region where the
target fresh air quantity q is close to the actual fresh
air quantity.</p><p num="0064">Next, the feedback correction value EGRf/b set in 
step S2 above is added to the basic exhaust gas
recirculation ratio EGRb set in step S3 above to obtain a
target exhaust gas recirculation ratio EGRt (step S5).
Then, the exhaust gas recirculation controller 39 outputs
a control signal corresponding to the target exhaust gas
recirculation ratio EGRt to the solenoid valve 28 to
thereby drive the EGR valve 24 (step S6) and completes
the exhaust gas recirculation control operation of FIG. 2.</p><p num="0065">In low-load ranges of the engine, the exhaust gas
recirculation ratio is basically set to a relatively
large value by executing the exhaust gas recirculation
control operation described above, so that an adequate
amount of recirculated exhaust gas is ensured and the
amount of NOx generated by the engine is reduced. As
engine load increases, on the other hand, the exhaust gas
recirculation ratio is set to progressively smaller
values, so that the fresh air quantity gradually
increases, providing sufficient engine output
corresponding to engine load conditions. Furthermore,
when the engine is at idle, the opening of the EGR valve
24 is made relatively small and, therefore, a momentary
increase in the quantity of smoke during transition to
the acceleration phase is prohibited.</p><p num="0066">The combustion controller 36 provided in the ECU 35 
controls the amount and timing of primary fuel injection
from the fuel injectors 5, the common rail pressure, or
fuel injection pressure, which is regulated by the high-pressure
supply pump 8, as well as the amount of intake
air which is regulated by the intake throttle valve 14 in
accordance with engine operating conditions, to thereby
control fuel-burning conditions to obtain the required
engine output.</p><p num="0067">The activation state detector 37 reads out an
estimated value of the temperature of the catalytic NOx
converter 22 corresponding to the engine operating
condition from a predefined map based on the engine speed
determined from the output signal of the crank angle
sensor 9 and the engine load determined from the output
signal of the acceleration sensor 32, or estimates the
temperature of the catalytic NOx converter 22 based on
the engine operating condition and exhaust gas
temperature detected by an exhaust gas temperature sensor
(not shown), and judges whether the catalytic NOx
converter 22 is already in its activated state.</p><p num="0068">Specifically, the catalytic NOx converter 22 is
judged to be in its activated state when the temperature
of the catalytic NOx converter 22 falls within a
temperature range R shown in FIG. 6 where the NOx 
conversion rate is equal to or larger than a specified
value α, while the catalytic NOx converter 22 is judged
to be in its inactivated state when the catalyst
temperature is higher or lower than the temperature range
R. A resultant judgment signal is output to the
reductant adder 38.</p><p num="0069">The reductant adder 38 is essentially a secondary
injection controller which performs a control operation
for making secondary injection to inject the fuel at a
specific time during a period from and including an
expansion stroke but after the primary fuel injection
executed by the combustion controller 36 through an
exhaust stroke. The reductant adder 38 increases the
quantity of reductants such as HC or carbon monoxide (CO)
and controls the secondary injection time depending on
whether the catalytic NOx converter 22 is already in its
activated state.</p><p num="0070">More specifically, when the catalytic NOx converter
22 is judged to be in its activated state by the
activation state detector 37, the secondary fuel
injection is made at a specific time during a period
between crank angles (CA) of 60° and 180° after the top
dead center (TDC) on a compression stroke, e.g., at 90°
(CA) after the compression stroke TDC. The secondary 
fuel injection is performed in each successive combustion
cycle to increase the quantity of reductants such as HC
or CO discharged from the combustion chambers 4 to the
exhaust passage 20. The amount of fuel supplied by the
secondary injection is set to approximately 0.5% to 4% of
the amount of fuel supplied by the primary injection.</p><p num="0071">On the other hand, when the catalytic NOx converter
22 is judged to be in its inactivated state by the
activation state detector 37, secondary injection timing
is advanced compared to the case where the catalytic NOx
converter 22 is in the activated state such that the
secondary injection of the fuel is made at a specific
time during a period from the point of primary fuel
injection to 60° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC,
e.g., at a specific time during a period of 40° to 50°
(CA) after the compression stroke TDC centering on 45°
(CA) after the compression stroke TDC. In this case, the
secondary fuel injection is not performed in each
successive combustion cycle, but at longer time intervals
than the period of the single combustion cycle.
Specifically, the number of times the secondary fuel
injection is made is reduced to once every 25th
combustion cycle, for example. The amount of fuel
supplied by the secondary injection during a given period 
of time is therefore the total amount of fuel supplied by
the reduced number of times of the secondary injection in
this case.</p><p num="0072">A control operation performed in the exhaust-gas
cleaning device of the present embodiment is described
referring to a flowchart shown in FIGS. 7 and 8.
Following the start of the control operation of the
flowchart, data detected by the individual sensors are
entered to the ECU 35 (step S11). Then, primary fuel
injection quantity Qb and primary fuel injection time Ib
corresponding to the engine operating condition are read
out from a predefined map and set (step S12).</p><p num="0073">Next, a judgment is made to determine whether the
engine is in its steady-state operating condition (step
S13). If the judgment result in step S13 is in the
negative, a combustion cycle count value N is reset to 0
(step S14). If the judgment result in step S13 is in the
positive, verifying that the engine is in its steady-state
operating condition, the combustion cycle count
value N is incremented by 1 (step S15) and a further
judgment is made to determine whether the count value N
is equal to 25 (step S16).</p><p num="0074">If the judgment result in step S16 is in the
positive, verifying that the count value N is equal to 25, 
the count value N is reset to 0 (step S17). In this case,
the activation state detector 37 judges whether the
catalytic NOx converter 22 is at a specific temperature
or above where the catalytic NOx converter 22 is in its
activated state (step S18), and secondary fuel injection
quantity Qp and secondary fuel injection time Ip
corresponding to this judgment result are set (step S19).</p><p num="0075">More specifically, when the catalytic NOx converter
22 is judged to be in its activated state in step S18
above, the secondary fuel injection quantity Qp and the
secondary fuel injection time Ip are set such that the
secondary fuel injection is made at a specific time
during the period between 60° and 180° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, e.g., at 90° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, in each successive combustion
cycle.</p><p num="0076">On the other hand, when the catalytic NOx converter
22 is judged to be in its inactivated state in step S18
above, the secondary fuel injection quantity Qp and the
secondary fuel injection time Ip are set such that the
secondary fuel injection is made at a specific time
during the period from the point of primary fuel
injection to 60° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC,
e.g., at 45° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, at 
longer time intervals than the period of the single
combustion cycle (in every 25th combustion cycle, for
example).</p><p num="0077">Subsequently, a judgment is made to determine
whether the present point in time is the primary fuel
injection time Ib (step S20). If the judgment result in
step S20 is in the positive, the primary fuel injection
is executed (step S21). Further, a judgment is made to
determine whether the secondary fuel injection quantity
Qp is set to 0 (step S22). If the judgment result in
step S22 is in the positive, the control operation of
FIGS. 7 and 8 is terminated without making the secondary
fuel injection.</p><p num="0078">If the judgment result in step S22 is in the
negative, verifying that the secondary fuel injection
quantity Qp is set to a specific value, a judgment is
made to determine whether the present point in time is
the secondary fuel injection time Ip (step S23). If the
judgment result in step S22 is in the positive, the
secondary fuel injection is executed (step S24).</p><p num="0079">As thus far described, the engine exhaust-gas
cleaning device of the present embodiment comprises the
catalytic NOx converter 22 made of the NOx-reducing
catalyst provided in the exhaust passage 20 for 
converting at least NOx by reacting it with reductants
under oxygen-rich conditions in which the oxygen
concentration is high, the reductant adder 38 for
increasing the quantity of reductants supplied to the
catalytic NOx converter 22 by causing the fuel injector 5
to make the secondary injection of the fuel at a specific
time during the period from the expansion stroke through
the exhaust stroke, as well as the activation state
detector 37 for judging whether the catalytic NOx
converter 22 is in its activated state, wherein when the
activation state detector 37 judges that the catalytic
NOx converter 22 is in its inactivated state, the
secondary fuel injection timing controlled by the
solenoid valve 28 is advanced compared to the case where
the catalytic NOx converter 22 is in the activated state.
This construction makes it possible to purify the exhaust
gas by effectively reducing the amount of NOx released
into the atmosphere regardless of whether the temperature
of the catalytic NOx converter 22 is lower or higher than
its activation temperature.</p><p num="0080">It is known that the catalytic NOx converter 22
which converts NOx by reacting it with reductants under
oxygen-rich conditions exhibits a maximum NOx conversion
rate when the catalyst temperature reaches a specific 
value, and becomes inactive with a reduction in NOx
conversion rate as the catalyst temperature drops below
or rises beyond the point of the maximum NOx conversion
rate, as shown in FIG. 6.</p><p num="0081">When the catalytic NOx converter 22 is judged to be
in its inactivated state, the amount of NOx discharged
from the engine can be reduced by advancing the timing of
the secondary fuel injection made after the primary fuel
injection from the fuel injector 5 in accordance with
engine operating conditions compared to the case where
the catalytic NOx converter 22 is in the activated state.
Therefore, it is possible to effectively reduce the
amount of NOx released into the atmosphere even when the
catalytic NOx converter 22 is in the inactivated state.</p><p num="0082">The exhaust-gas cleaning device of the embodiment
was experimented with the engine controlled to run at
approximately 1500 rpm under high-load conditions. In
this experiment, the secondary fuel injection was made in
each successive combustion cycle with the secondary fuel
injection time Ip advanced in incremental steps from 120°
to 30° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, and an
average value of the amount of NOx discharged from the
combustion chambers 4 (hereinafter referred to as the
amount of raw NOx) when 30 seconds have elapsed from the 
start of the secondary fuel injection was taken. FIG. 9
shows data obtained from this experiment. It can be seen
from FIG. 9 that the amount of raw NOx discharged when
the secondary fuel injection is made at 120° (CA) after
the compression stroke TDC is approximately same as the
amount of raw NOx discharged when the secondary fuel
injection is not made that is shown by a line β, whereas
the amount of raw NOx is gradually reduced as the
secondary fuel injection time Ip is progressively
advanced.</p><p num="0083">Likewise, when the secondary fuel injection was made
in every 5th combustion cycle (at intervals of about 0.4
seconds), and in every 25th combustion cycle (at
intervals of about 2.0 seconds), with the secondary fuel
injection time Ip advanced, data as shown in FIGS. 10 and
11 were obtained, respectively. It can also be seen from
FIGS. 10 and 11 that the amount of raw NOx can be reduced
by advancing the secondary fuel injection time Ip even
when the number of times of the secondary fuel injection
is reduced.</p><p num="0084">It has been verified that an effect of reducing the
amount of raw NOx is efficiently obtained by setting the
secondary fuel injection time Ip within the period from
the point of primary fuel injection where the fuel is 
injected near the compression stroke TDC up to 60° (CA)
after the compression stroke TDC and, in particular, the
amount of raw NOx discharged from the combustion chambers
4 can be reduced significantly when the secondary fuel
injection time Ip is set close to 45° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, e.g., within a period of about
40° to 50° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, and the
secondary fuel injection is made in every 25th combustion
cycle (at intervals of about 2.0 seconds), as shown in
FIG. 11.</p><p num="0085">The reason why the amount of raw NOx discharged from
the combustion chambers 4 can be reduced by advancing the
secondary fuel injection time Ip controlled by the
reductant adder 38 formed essentially of the secondary
injection controller into the period from the point of
primary fuel injection up to 60° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, for example, is supposed to be
that the influence of fuel pressure variations within the
common rail 6 caused by making the secondary fuel
injection in an early period after the primary fuel
injection has an effect on the primary fuel injection,
resulting in a reduction in the amount of fuel supplied
by the primary injection. It is also supposed that the
amount of raw NOx is reduced since a large amount of 
inert gases such as carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) produced by
afterburning flows back into the intake passage 10
through the EGR passage 23. The inert gases are
recirculated in large quantities because afterburning of
the fuel supplied by the secondary injection easily
occurs when the secondary fuel injection time Ip is
advanced.</p><p num="0086">If the secondary fuel injection is made at longer
time intervals than the period of the single combustion
cycle, such as in every 5th combustion cycle (at
intervals of about 0.4 seconds) or in every 25th
combustion cycle (at intervals of about 2.0 seconds),
preferably in every 10th combustion cycle (at intervals
of about 0.8 seconds) to 25th combustion cycle (at
intervals of about 2.0 seconds), and the amount of fuel
supplied by one cycle of the secondary injection is set
to 0.2% to 7%, preferably 0.2% to 5%, of the amount of
fuel supplied by the primary injection when the catalytic
NOx converter 22 is in its inactivated state, the amount
of raw NOx discharged from the combustion chambers 4 can
be more effectively reduced as depicted in FIGS. 10 and
11. Thus, the exhaust-gas cleaning device of the
embodiment has such advantage that it can reduce the
amount of NOx released into the atmosphere more 
effectively.</p><p num="0087">FIG. 12 is a general configuration diagram showing
an exhaust-gas cleaning device according to a second
embodiment of the invention comprising a first catalytic
NOx converter 22a provided in the exhaust passage 20 and
a second catalytic NOx converter 22b which is provided
downstream of the first catalytic NOx converter 22a and
becomes active when the first catalytic NOx converter 22a
is in its inactivated state. In FIG. 12, elements
equivalent to those shown in FIG. 1 are designated by the
same reference numerals.</p><p num="0088">In this second embodiment wherein the first
catalytic NOx converter 22a having a relatively low
activation temperature is provided upstream of the second
catalytic NOx converter 22b having a relatively high
activation temperature, it is preferable to advance the
secondary fuel injection timing and execute the secondary
fuel injection at longer time intervals than the period
of the single combustion cycle, e.g., in every 25th
combustion cycle (at intervals of about 2.0 seconds),
when the activation state detector 37 has detected that
the temperature of the first catalytic NOx converter 22a
on the upstream side is higher than a reference
temperature where it is in the activated state. </p><p num="0089">Experiments were conducted with the exhaust-gas
cleaning device of the second embodiment. These included
a first experiment A in which the secondary fuel
injection was made at the point of 90° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC in each successive combustion
cycle, a second experiment B in which the secondary fuel
injection was made at the point of 90° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC in every 25th combustion cycle,
and a third experiment C in which the secondary fuel
injection was made at the point of 45° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC in every 25th combustion cycle.
In these experiments, the amount of HC downstream of the
NOx-reducing catalyst was measured and data as shown in
FIG. 13 was obtained.</p><p num="0090">It has been verified from the data shown in FIG. 13
that the amount of HC downstream of the NOx-reducing
catalyst significantly increased in the third experiment
C, in which the secondary fuel injection was made at the
point of 45° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC in
every 25th combustion cycle, compared to the first and
second experiments A, B. The reason why such an increase
in the amount of HC occurs is supposed to be that when
afterburning of the fuel is accelerated by advancing the
secondary fuel injection timing to a specific time during 
the period from the point of primary fuel injection to
60° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, e.g., to the
point of 45° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, and
the amount of fuel supplied by one cycle of the secondary
injection is increased by making the secondary fuel
injection at longer time intervals than the period of the
single combustion cycle, considerable pressure variations
occur in the exhaust passage 20, causing large quantities
of HC to flow to the downstream side of the NOx-reducing
catalyst at points of high exhaust gas pressure.</p><p num="0091">Therefore, in an engine in which the second
catalytic NOx converter 22b having a high activation
temperature is provided downstream of the first catalytic
NOx converter 22a, when the first catalytic NOx converter
22a is in the inactivated state with its temperature
higher than the activation temperature, it is possible to
flow large quantities of HC and other components to the
downstream side of the first catalytic NOx converter 22a
and supply these components to the second catalytic NOx
converter 22b by advancing the secondary fuel injection
timing to a specific time during the period from the
point of primary fuel injection to 60° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC within a temperature range T3
shown in FIG. 14, for example, and executing the 
secondary fuel injection at longer time intervals than
the period of the single combustion cycle. As the second
catalytic NOx converter 22b reduces NOx using HC and
other components, it is possible to effectively decrease
the amount of NOx released into the atmosphere.</p><p num="0092">In a temperature range T1 in which the first
catalytic NOx converter 22a is in the inactivated state
with its temperature lower than the activation
temperature, on the other hand, the secondary fuel
injection timing is advanced to a specific time and the
secondary fuel injection is made in each successive
combustion cycle or at longer time intervals than the
period of the single combustion cycle. Also, in a
temperature range T2 in which the first catalytic NOx
converter 22a is in the activated state, the secondary
fuel injection is made during a period from the point of
primary fuel injection to 90° (CA) after the compression
stroke TDC in each successive combustion cycle in an
ordinary fashion such that HC and other components which
work as reductants are supplied to the first catalytic
NOx converter 22a. As an alternative, there may be
provided an uncontrolled temperature range in which the
secondary fuel injection is not made between the
temperature range T2 in which the first catalytic NOx 
converter 22a is in its activated state and the
temperature range T3 in which the second catalytic NOx
converter 22b is in its activated state.</p><p num="0093">The aforementioned exhaust-gas cleaning devices of
the first and second embodiments are so constructed as to
increase the quantity of reductants in the exhaust gas by
making the secondary fuel injection at a specific time
during the period from the expansion stroke through the
exhaust stroke. This construction may be modified such
that the quantity of reductants is increased by retarding
the timing of the primary fuel injection which is set in
accordance with the engine load, and when the activation
state detector 37 judges that the catalytic NOx converter
22 is in its inactivated state, the amount of raw NOx is
reduced by reducing the amount of retardation of the
primary fuel injection time to advance the primary fuel
injection time compared to its setting under ordinary
conditions.</p><p num="0094">This means that the quantity of reductants in the
exhaust gas can be increased by retarding the primary
fuel injection time which is set in accordance with the
engine load and thereby increasing the quantity of
unburned fuel components such as HC or CO discharged from
the combustion chambers 4. In this case, it is 
preferable to make pilot injection of a small quantity of
fuel during a first half of intake stroke, for instance,
prior to the primary fuel injection to prevent
deterioration of fuel ignitability.</p><p num="0095">When the activation state detector 37 determines
that the catalytic NOx converter 22 is in its inactivated
state, it is possible to reduce the amount of raw NOx by
advancing the primary fuel injection time compared to its
setting under ordinary conditions, that is, by reducing
the amount of retardation of the primary fuel injection
time, and increasing the quantity of inert gases
recirculated to the intake passage 10 through the EGR
passage 23, for example. Therefore, it is possible to
reduce the amount of NOx released into the atmosphere in
this modified construction as well.</p><p num="0096">Since the catalytic NOx converter 22 (first and
second catalytic NOx converters 22a, 22b) formed by
depositing catalytic metal including platinum on zeolite
like MFI zeolite, which is a porous material, is provided
in the exhaust passage 20 in the aforementioned first and
second embodiments, there is an advantage that NOx in the
exhaust gas can be effectively reduced by using such
reductants as HC entrapped in pores within zeolite even
when the NOx-reducing catalyst is under oxygen-rich 
conditions during ordinary engine operation or when the
NOx-reducing catalyst is in the inactivated state due to
low catalyst temperature.</p><p num="0097">While the foregoing first and second embodiments
have dealt with examples in which the catalytic NOx
converter 22 (first and second catalytic NOx converters
22a, 22b) made of the NOx-reducing catalyst is provided
in the exhaust passage 20, the present invention is also
applicable to an engine provided with a NOx-converting
catalyst made of a NOx-trapping catalyst, for example,
containing alkaline-earth metal like barium (Ba) and
noble metal like platinum (Pt) which purifies the exhaust
gas by absorbing NOx under oxygen-rich conditions and
releasing NOx under reductant-rich conditions. This
alternative is advantageous in that emission of NOx into
the atmosphere can be effectively prevented when the
temperature of the NOx-trapping catalyst is higher than a
specific high temperature or lower than a specific low
temperature resulting in a deterioration of its NOx-trapping
performance.</p><p num="0098">FIG. 15 is a general configuration diagram showing
an exhaust-gas cleaning device according to a third
embodiment of the invention. Provided in a diesel engine
having fuel injectors 5 for injecting fuel into 
individual combustion chambers 4, a primary injection
controller 40 for controlling mode of primary fuel
injection from the fuel injectors 5 in accordance with
engine operating conditions, a secondary injection
controller 41 for controlling the fuel injectors 5 to
make secondary injection of the fuel at a specific time
during a period from the point of the primary fuel
injection through the expansion stroke, and a catalytic
NOx converter 22 made of a NOx-reducing catalyst or a
NOx-trapping catalyst, for instance, provided in an
exhaust passage 20 of the engine for reducing the amount
of NOx released into the atmosphere, the exhaust-gas
cleaning device of the third embodiment is so constructed
as to decrease NOx emissions into the atmosphere by
making the secondary fuel injection at a specific time
after the primary fuel injection during a period of 30°
to 60° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC when the
engine is under such operating conditions that the amount
of raw NOx discharged from the combustion chambers 4 is
large, such as when the engine is under medium or higher
load and speed conditions, or when the catalytic NOx
converter 22 is in its inactivated state.</p><p num="0099">In the diesel engine shown in FIG. 15, it is also
possible to reduce the quantity of soot produced by the 
primary fuel injection by making the secondary fuel
injection at a specific time after the primary fuel
injection. When the engine is under such operating
conditions that the quantity of soot discharged from the
combustion chambers 4 tends to be large, such as when the
engine is under medium or higher load conditions or under
medium or higher speed conditions with an engine speed of
about 2000 rpm or above, or when the engine is provided
with a diesel particulate filter (DPF) installed in the
exhaust passage 20 but its filtering performance is still
low due to low temperature (300°C or less), it is
possible to reduce the quantity of soot by making the
secondary fuel injection at a specific time during a
period set with reference to a point in time when
diffusion combustion of the fuel supplied by the primary
injection finishes (between 30° and 60° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC when the engine speed is 1500 rpm
or above).</p><p num="0100">The aforementioned primary fuel injection refers to
injection of the fuel in which the amount of fuel
corresponding to the required engine output or above is
injected at a specific time from the intake stroke
through an early part of the expansion stroke. The
secondary fuel injection is made to reduce the quantity 
of soot which occurs when the whole or part of the fuel
supplied by the primary fuel injection is burnt by
diffusion combustion. If the primary fuel injection is
made during a period from the proximity of the
compression stroke TDC through the early part of the
expansion stroke, the fuel is burnt mostly by premixed
combustion under low-load conditions, and by both
premixed combustion and diffusion combustion under other
conditions than low-load conditions.</p><p num="0101">If the primary fuel injection is made during a
period from the intake stroke to a point before the
compression stroke TDC, the fuel is burnt mostly by
premixed combustion which does not produce soot. If,
however, the fuel adhering to wall surfaces of the
combustion chambers 4 ignites at the proximity of the
compression stroke TDC, diffusion combustion occurs,
producing soot. Even in such cases, it is possible to
reduce the quantity of soot by making the secondary fuel
injection.</p><p num="0102">While the primary fuel injection has been described
as being made only once in the foregoing discussion, it
may be divided into two or more cycles including a first
cycle of primary fuel injection made at a specific time
during the period from the intake stroke to a point 
before the compression stroke TDC and a second cycle of
primary fuel injection made at a specific time during the
period from the proximity of the compression stroke TDC
through the early part of the expansion stroke.</p><p num="0103">The construction and working of the exhaust-gas
cleaning device of the third embodiment is described more
specifically with reference to FIGS. 16 to 23. Referring
to a flowchart shown in FIG. 16, data detected by the
individual sensors are first entered to the ECU 35 (step
S31). Then, primary fuel injection quantity Qb and
primary fuel injection time Ib corresponding to required
engine torque are read out from a predefined map and set
(step S32) and a judgment is made to determine whether
the engine is in its steady-state operating condition
(step S33).</p><p num="0104">If the judgment result in step S33 is in the
positive, the activation state detector 37 provided in
the ECU 35 judges whether the catalytic NOx converter 22
is at a specific temperature or above where the catalytic
NOx converter 22 is in its activated state (step S34).
If the judgment result in step S34 is in the positive, a
judgment is made to determine whether the engine is under
medium or higher load conditions (step S35). If the
judgment result in step S35 is in the negative, a further 
judgment is made to determine whether the engine rotation
speed (rpm) is under medium or higher speed conditions
(step S36).</p><p num="0105">If the judgment result in step S34 is in the
negative, verifying that the catalytic NOx converter 22
is in its inactivated state, if the judgment result in
step S35 is in the positive, verifying that the engine is
under medium or higher load conditions, or if the
judgment result in step S36 is in the positive, verifying
that the engine is under medium or higher speed
conditions, secondary fuel injection quantity Qp and
secondary fuel injection time Ip corresponding to the
engine operating condition are read out from a predefined
map and set (step S37), whereby the secondary fuel
injection timing is set at a specific time after the
primary fuel injection during the period of 30° to 60°
(CA) after the compression stroke TDC and the operation
flow proceeds to step S38, in which fuel injection is
executed.</p><p num="0106">When the exhaust-gas cleaning device is so
constructed as to make the secondary fuel injection after
the primary fuel injection during the period of 30° to
60° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, for instance,
combustion of the fuel supplied by the secondary 
injection occurs when diffusion combustion occurring
after premixed combustion of the fuel supplied into the
combustion chambers 4 by the primary injection has
finished. Thus, mixing of soot and oxygen existing
within the combustion chambers 4 at the end of diffusion
combustion is accelerated and combustion due to the
secondary fuel injection begins in an easily ignitable
state, so that generation of soot can be suppressed.</p><p num="0107">Now, ending time of diffusion combustion is
described in detail. The ending time of diffusion
combustion is calculated based on heat release rate.
According to &quot;Lectures on Internal-Combustion Engines&quot;
(written by Fujiwo Nagao and published by Yokendo Co.,
Ltd.), the heat release rate is expressed by equation (1)
below:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">dQ/d = A/(K() - 1) x [V()·(dP()/d)<st32:break type="required" />
+ K()·P()·(dV()/d)]</st32:df>
where A is the mechanical equivalent of heat, K() is the
ratio of specific heats, V() is stroke volume, P() is
the pressure in a cylinder, and  is the crank angle.</p><p num="0108">According to a manual of combustion analyzer CB566
manufactured by Ono Sokki Co., Ltd., the ratio of
specific heats K() is given by equations (2)-(5) below:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">K() = Cp/Cv</st32:df><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Cp = ap + b(T()/100) + c(T()/100)<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup> + d(100/T())</st32:df><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Cv = Cp - (A·Ro)/M</st32:df><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">T() = (P()·V())/29.27·G</st32:df>
where Cp is isobaric specific heat, Cv is isochoric
specific heat, Ro is gas constant, M is the molecular
weight of air, T() is gas temperature, G is the weight
of gas, and ap, b, c and d are other constants.</p><p num="0109">From equations (2)-(5) above, the heat release rate
dQ/d of equation (1) is expressed as a function f(P(),
V()) of the cylinder pressure P() and stroke volume
V(). Since the stroke volume V() is expressed by
equation (6) below using bore diameter B and stroke S,
the heat release rate dQ/d can be written as shown in
equation (7):
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">V() = (π·B<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>S/8)·(1 - cos)</st32:df><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">dQ/d = [f(P(+Δ), V(+Δ)) - f(P(), V())]/Δ</st32:df></p><p num="0110">Therefore, if cylinder pressure data for each crank
angle is available, it is possible to calculate the heat
release rate from that data. FIGS. 17A-17C are graphical
representation of the heat release rate obtained in this
fashion. The heat release rate first takes a large
positive value as a result of combustion caused by the
primary fuel injection and drops to zero after completion
of diffusion combustion. Thus, the ending time of 
diffusion combustion can be obtained from time t1 when
the heat release rate becomes approximately zero.</p><p num="0111">Taking into consideration ignition delay time (e.g.,
about 0.4 to 0.7 ms) predefined according to engine
operating conditions, the secondary fuel injection time
is advanced by as much as the ignition delay time from
the time t1 at which the heat release rate becomes
approximately zero such that combustion due to the
secondary fuel injection can be started in the proximity
of the time t1 calculated as described above in the
present embodiment.</p><p num="0112">While the aforementioned ignition delay time varies
with the displacement volume of the engine and fuel
injection pressure, it is approximately 0.4 to 0.7 ms
when the displacement volume is 1000 to 3000 cc and the
fuel injection pressure is 50 to 200 MPa. The
aforementioned ignition delay time is longer than
ignition delay time (0.1 to 0.3 ms) which occurs when the
primary fuel injection is made at the compression stroke
TDC. This is because the secondary fuel injection is
made when the temperature in the cylinders 2 is
relatively low.</p><p num="0113">The ECU 35 stores output timing of an injection
drive signal to each fuel injector 5, wherein the output 
timing is determined in consideration of the
aforementioned ignition delay time as well as dead time
(drive delay time) from the point in time when an
injector open/close signal is output to the point in time
when fuel injection actually begins.</p><p num="0114">Assuming that the engine is under medium-load,
medium-speed conditions with the engine speed controlled
to 2000 rpm and mean effective pressure Pe controlled to
0.57 MPa, for example, the heat release rate within the
combustion chambers 4 obtained when the primary fuel
injection is made at the compression stroke TDC was
thermodynamically calculated and graphed based on
pressure variations within the cylinders 2 and their
volume variations. As can be seen from FIG. 17B, it has
been verified that there occur heat release Y due to
premixed combustion of the fuel supplied by the primary
fuel injection after a delay time Tm of about 0.1 ms from
primary injection time t0 as well as heat release K of
approximately the same level due to diffusion combustion,
and that the diffusion combustion terminates at a point
in time t1 which is delayed by approximately 0.6 ms from
the point of 35° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC.</p><p num="0115">Therefore, if secondary injection of the fuel is
made at time tf which is approximately the point of 35° 
(CA) after the compression stroke TDC, it is possible to
combust the fuel supplied by the secondary injection at
the ending time t1 of diffusion combustion. This, in
turn, means that the fuel injected by the secondary
injection at the time tf begins to burn at the time t1
when an ignition delay time Tf of about 0.6 ms has
elapsed, resulting in an increase in the quantity of heat
release N.</p><p num="0116">In contrast, when the engine is under high-load,
high-speed conditions with the engine speed controlled to
2500 rpm and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled to
0.9 MPa, for example, heat release K due to diffusion
combustion continues for a considerably long time
compared to the aforementioned heat release K due to
premixed combustion, and this diffusion combustion tends
to terminate at a later point in time t1 which is delayed
by approximately 0.7 ms from the point of 47° (CA) after
the compression stroke TDC, as shown in FIG. 17C.
Therefore, if secondary injection of the fuel is made at
time tf which is approximately the point of 47° (CA)
after the compression stroke TDC, it is possible to
combust the fuel supplied by the secondary injection at
the ending time t1 of the diffusion combustion as
depicted by a broken line N in FIG. 17C. </p><p num="0117">Further, when the engine is under low-load, low-speed
conditions with the engine speed controlled to 1500
rpm and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled to 0.3
MPa, for example, it is difficult to discriminate between
premixed combustion and diffusion combustion by the form
of heat release as shown in FIG. 17A. However, the
diffusion combustion terminates and the heat release rate
becomes zero at a relatively early point in time t1 which
is delayed by approximately 0.5 ms from the point of 30°
(CA) after the compression stroke TDC. Therefore, if
secondary injection of the fuel is made at time tf which
is approximately the point of 30° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, it is possible to combust the
fuel supplied by the secondary injection at the ending
time t1 of diffusion combustion as depicted by a broken
line N in FIG. 17A.</p><p num="0118">An effect of reducing the quantity of soot by
setting the secondary fuel injection timing with
reference to the ending time of diffusion combustion is
now described. While running the engine under low-load,
low-speed conditions with the engine speed controlled to
1500 rpm and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled to
0.3 MPa, the secondary fuel injection timing was varied
in various ways and the quantity of soot produced was 
measured at individual settings. It has been verified
from this experiment that the quantity of soot produced
is significantly reduced when the secondary fuel
injection time is set to a point after the primary fuel
injection and later than the point of 30° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC which is supposed to be the point
in time tf advanced by as much as the ignition delay time
from the ending time t1 of diffusion combustion as shown
in FIG. 18A.</p><p num="0119">Next, while running the engine under medium-load,
medium-speed conditions with the engine speed controlled
to 2000 rpm and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled
to 0.57 MPa, the secondary fuel injection timing was
varied in various ways and the quantity of soot produced
was measured at individual settings. It has been
verified from this experiment that the quantity of soot
produced is significantly reduced when the secondary fuel
injection time is set to a point after the primary fuel
injection and later than the point of 35° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC which is supposed to be the point
in time tf advanced by as much as the ignition delay time
from the ending time t1 of diffusion combustion as shown
in FIG. 18B.</p><p num="0120">Further, while running the engine under high-load, 
high-speed conditions with the engine speed controlled to
2500 rpm and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled to
0.9 MPa, the secondary fuel injection timing was varied
in various ways and the quantity of soot produced was
measured at individual settings. It has been verified
from this experiment that the quantity of soot produced
is significantly reduced when the secondary fuel
injection time is set to a point after the primary fuel
injection and later than the point of 47° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC which is supposed to be the point
in time tf advanced by as much as the ignition delay time
from the ending time t1 of diffusion combustion as shown
in FIG. 18C. In the individual experiments mentioned
above, the engine load was kept constant and the ratio of
the amount of fuel supplied by the secondary injection to
the total amount of fuel injected was set to 20%.</p><p num="0121">In these experiments, the secondary fuel injection
was not executed when the secondary fuel injection time
was the point of 0° (CA) and, therefore, FIGS. 18A-18C
show data obtained when only the primary fuel injection
was made in this case.</p><p num="0122">Next, while running the engine under low-load, low-speed
conditions with the engine speed controlled to 1500
rpm and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled to 0.3 
MPa, the secondary fuel injection was made at the point
of 30° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, which is
supposed to be the point in time tf advanced by as much
as the ignition delay time from the ending time t1 of
diffusion combustion, and the quantity of soot produced
was measured, wherein the ratio (P/T) of the amount of
fuel supplied by the secondary injection to the total
amount of fuel injected was varied in various ways within
a range of 10% to 45%. In this experiment, the quantity
of soot produced decreased with an increase in the ratio
(P/T) of the amount of fuel supplied by the secondary
injection as shown by a solid line in FIG. 19A. On the
contrary, when the secondary fuel injection was made at
the point of 8° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC,
which is supposed to be earlier than the time tf, the
quantity of soot produced increased with an increase in
the ratio (P/T) of the amount of fuel supplied by the
secondary injection as shown by a broken line in FIG. 19A.</p><p num="0123">Also, while running the engine under medium-load,
medium-speed conditions with the engine speed controlled
to 2000 rpm and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled
to 0.57 MPa, the secondary fuel injection was made at the
point of 35° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, which
is supposed to be the point in time tf advanced by as 
much as the ignition delay time from the ending time t1
of diffusion combustion caused by the primary fuel
injection, and at the point of 20° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, which is supposed to be earlier
than the time tf. Further, while running the engine
under high-load, high-speed conditions with the engine
speed controlled to 2500 rpm and the mean effective
pressure Pe controlled to 0.9 MPa, the secondary fuel
injection was made at the point of 48° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, which is supposed to be the point
in time tf advanced by as much as the ignition delay time
from the ending time t1 of diffusion combustion caused by
the primary fuel injection, and at the point of 20° (CA)
after the compression stroke TDC, which is supposed to be
earlier than the time tf. The quantity of soot produced
was measured in the respective experiments, in which data
similar to those obtained in the experiment under the
low-load, low-speed conditions were obtained as shown in
FIGS. 19B and 19C.</p><p num="0124">It is understood from the above experimental data
that, according to the above-described engine exhaust-gas
cleaning device and method of setting the fuel injection
timing of the invention, in which the secondary fuel
injection timing is set with reference to the ending time 
of diffusion combustion caused by the primary fuel
injection within the combustion chambers 4 and the fuel
supplied by the secondary injection is ignited at or
slightly before or after the ending time of diffusion
combustion, the quantity of soot discharged from the
combustion chambers 4 into the exhaust passage 20 can be
reduced if carbon residue (soot) is effectively burnt by
executing the secondary fuel injection under conditions
in which carbon and oxygen existing within the combustion
chambers 4 are sufficiently mixed at the end of diffusion
combustion</p><p num="0125">Since the ending time of diffusion combustion varies
depending on the engine speed and load or the like, the
time t1 at which the heat release rate due to diffusion
combustion becomes zero should preferably be mapped based
on experimental data obtained in various engine operating
conditions, as shown in FIGS. 17A-17C, for example, such
that the time t1 to be set can be read out from a map.</p><p num="0126">In one alternative, there may be provided a
combustion state discriminator for discriminating the
state of diffusion combustion based on a sensing signal
fed from a temperature sensor for detecting the
temperature within the combustion chambers 4, a sensing
signal fed from a combustion light sensor, or a sensing 
signal fed from a sensor for detecting the quantity of
highly reactive electrically charged hydrogen or HC
existing within the combustion chambers 4, wherein the
combustion state discriminator determines the ending time
of diffusion combustion by judging whether the
temperature within the combustion chambers 4 after the
primary fuel injection has dropped to or below a specific
temperature, whether fuel-burning light caused by
combustion has disappeared, or whether the quantity of
hydrogen or HC has sharply decreased, and the secondary
fuel injection timing for a succeeding combustion cycle
is set with reference to the ending time of diffusion
combustion thus determined. In another alternative, the
ending time of diffusion combustion may be determined by
calculating a differential of a value obtained by
subtracting a temperature change caused by adiabatic
expansion from the temperature in the cylinders 2
detected by a temperature sensor and determining a point
in time when the differential becomes from a negative
value to zero.</p><p num="0127">As thus far described, if the starting time of
secondary fuel injection is set in accordance with
individual engine operating conditions with reference to
the ending time of diffusion combustion determined based 
on the engine operating conditions such that combustion
caused by the secondary fuel injection would begin in the
proximity (±5° in terms of crank angle) of the ending
time of diffusion combustion, or preferably immediately
after the ending time of diffusion combustion, the
secondary fuel injection is made with optimum timing for
the engine operating conditions, making it possible to
effectively reduce the amount of soot emission.</p><p num="0128">An effect of reducing NOx emissions according to the
third embodiment of the invention is now described.
While running the engine under low-load, low-speed
conditions with the engine speed controlled to 1500 rpm
and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled to 0.3 MPa,
the secondary fuel injection timing was varied in various
ways within a range of 2.5° to 50° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC and the quantity of HC produced
was measured at individual settings. It has been
verified from this experiment that the quantity of HC
produced markedly increases when the secondary fuel
injection time is set to a point after the primary fuel
injection and later than the point of 30° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC.</p><p num="0129">Next, while running the engine under medium-load,
medium-speed conditions with the engine speed controlled 
to 2000 rpm and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled
to 0.57 MPa, the secondary fuel injection timing was
varied in various ways and the quantity of HC produced
was measured at individual settings. It has been
verified from this experiment that the quantity of HC
produced markedly increases when the secondary fuel
injection time is set to a point after the primary fuel
injection and later than the point of 35° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC as shown in FIG. 20B.</p><p num="0130">Further, while running the engine under high-load,
high-speed conditions with the engine speed controlled to
2500 rpm and the mean effective pressure Pe controlled to
0.9 MPa, the secondary fuel injection timing was varied
in various ways and the quantity of HC produced was
measured at individual settings. It has been verified
from this experiment that the quantity of HC produced
markedly increases when the secondary fuel injection time
is set to a point after the primary fuel injection and
later than the point of 45° (CA) after the compression
stroke TDC as shown in FIG. 20C. In the individual
experiments mentioned above, the engine load was kept
.constant and the ratio of the amount of fuel supplied by
the secondary injection to the total amount of fuel
injected was set to 20%. </p><p num="0131">In these experiments, the secondary fuel injection
was not executed when the secondary fuel injection time
was the point of 0° (CA) and, therefore, FIGS. 20A-20C
show data obtained when only the primary fuel injection
was made in this case.</p><p num="0132">It is understood from the above experimental data
that the amount of raw NOx discharged from the combustion
chambers 4 into the exhaust passage 20 can be reduced by
increasing the quantity of HC produced to thereby
increase the quantity of highly reactive hydrogen and HC
carrying concentrated electric charge which act as
reductants when the secondary fuel injection timing is
executed at a point after the primary fuel injection and
later than the point of 30° (CA) after the compression
stroke TDC.</p><p num="0133">Furthermore, with the engine operated under low-load,
low-speed conditions, medium-load, medium-speed
conditions and high-load, high-speed conditions as
described above, fuel consumption was measured when the
secondary fuel injection timing was varied in various
ways within the range of 2.5° to 50° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, and when the secondary fuel
injection was not executed. It has been verified from
these experiments that the more the secondary fuel 
injection timing is delayed, the more the fuel
consumption increases as shown in FIGS. 21A-21C. This is
because the fuel supplied by the secondary injection
becomes less contributory to improvement in engine output
with an increase in delay of the secondary fuel injection
time. To prevent an increase in fuel consumption, it is
preferable to set the secondary fuel injection time to a
point after the primary fuel injection but not later than
the point of 60° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC.</p><p num="0134">Therefore, if the secondary fuel injection time is
set to a specific time after the primary fuel injection
and within the period of 30° to 60° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, there is produced such an
advantageous effect that the exhaust gas can be purified
by effectively preventing NOx emissions into the
atmosphere without increasing fuel consumption.</p><p num="0135">Specifically, with the engine operated under low-load,
low-speed conditions, medium-load, medium-speed
conditions and high-load, high-speed conditions as
described above, the amount of NOx released into the
atmosphere was measured while varying the secondary fuel
injection timing in various ways. It has been verified
from these experiments that the exhaust gas can be
purified by effectively preventing NOx emissions into the 
atmosphere without increasing fuel consumption when the
secondary fuel injection time is set such that the
secondary fuel injection is executed at a specific time
after the primary fuel injection and within the period of
30° to 60° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC as shown
in FIGS. 22A-22C. In these experiments, the exhaust gas
recirculation ratio was kept constant. This is because
if the exhaust gas recirculation controller 39 executes
the exhaust gas recirculation control operation at the
same time with the secondary fuel injection, the amount
of raw NOx varies due to an effect of exhaust gas
recirculation caused by an increase in exhaust gas
pressure and it becomes difficult to accurately ascertain
the raw-NOx-reducing effect provided by the secondary
fuel injection.</p><p num="0136">As an alternative to the above-described third
embodiment of the invention in which the secondary fuel
injection time is set in accordance with the crank angle
(CA), the secondary fuel injection time may be set
according to timing set by a timer. In this alternative,
it is possible to effectively prevent NOx emissions into
the atmosphere without increasing fuel consumption by
executing the secondary fuel injection at a specific time
after the primary fuel injection and within a period of 
1.2 ms to 4 ms (CA) after the compression stroke TDC.</p><p num="0137">As seen in the foregoing discussion, it is possible
to reduce both the amount of soot produced and the amount
of NOx emissions and set the secondary fuel injection
time capable of improving fuel economy with reference to
the ending time of diffusion combustion which occurs
after the primary fuel injection. When the engine speed
is 1500 rpm and the engine load is low, for example, the
ending time of diffusion combustion is a point delayed by
approximately 0.5 ms from the point of 30° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC. To reduce both the amount of
soot produced and the amount of NOx emissions in this
case, the secondary fuel injection time should be set to
the point of about 30° (CA) after the compression stroke
TDC, e.g., between 27° and 35° (CA), wherein the optimum
secondary fuel injection time is the point of 30° (CA).</p><p num="0138">When the engine speed is 2000 rpm and the engine
load is of a medium level, the ending time of diffusion
combustion is a point delayed by approximately 0.6 ms
from the point of 35° (CA) after the compression stroke
TDC. Accordingly, the secondary fuel injection time
should be set to the point of about 35° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, e.g., between 33° and 40° (CA),
wherein the optimum secondary fuel injection time is the 
point of 35° (CA). Also, when the engine speed is 2500
rpm and the engine load is high, the ending time of
diffusion combustion is a point delayed by approximately
0.7 ms from the point of 47° (CA) after the compression
stroke TDC. Similarly, the secondary fuel injection time
should be set to the point of about 47° (CA) after the
compression stroke TDC, e.g., between 45° and 48° (CA),
wherein the optimum secondary fuel injection time is the
point of 47° (CA).</p><p num="0139">In the diesel engine provided with the exhaust-gas-driven
turbocharger 25 for supplying the engine with
precompressed intake air, the exhaust gas pressure rises
and supercharging effect of the turbocharger 25 is
increased if a specific amount of fuel is supplied by the
secondary injection after the primary injection as stated
above. Since the quantity of fresh air introduced into
the combustion chambers 4 increases as a consequence,
there is produced such an advantageous effect that
burning of carbon residue left within the combustion
chambers 4 is accelerated and generation of soot is
effectively suppressed. In addition, since the ending
time of diffusion combustion of the fuel supplied by the
primary injection tends to be advanced when the amount of
intake air increases due to the supercharging effect of 
the turbocharger 25, it is possible to further reduce the
quantity of soot discharged into the exhaust passage 20
by adjusting the secondary fuel injection time in
accordance with the ending time of diffusion combustion
and thereby suppressing soot generation effectively.</p><p num="0140">When the diesel engine having the turbocharger 25 is
provided with the exhaust gas recirculation system 33 for
recirculating part of the exhaust gas to the intake
passage 10 and a feedback control operation is performed
such that the exhaust gas recirculation ratio determined
by the exhaust gas recirculation controller 39 provided
in the ECU 35 becomes equal to a target value, the amount
of exhaust gas recirculated back to the intake passage 10
increases when the amount of intake air increases due to
the supercharging effect of the turbocharger 25. Thus,
there is produced such an advantageous effect that the
amount of raw NOx discharged from the combustion chambers
4 into the exhaust passage 20 is reduced more effectively.</p><p num="0141">Furthermore, when the secondary fuel injection time
is set with reference to the ending time of diffusion
combustion caused by the primary fuel injection within
the combustion chambers 4 in a situation where the
catalytic NOx converter 22 made of the NOx-reducing
catalyst provided in the exhaust passage 20 of the engine 
is in its inactivated state, there is an advantage that
the aforementioned effect of reducing the amount of raw
NOx by increasing the quantity of highly reactive
hydrogen within the combustion chambers 4 and the effect
of reducing the amount of soot emission by accelerated
burning of carbon residue are obtained simultaneously.</p><p num="0142">In particular, when the exhaust-gas cleaning device
is constructed such that the secondary fuel injection
time is set at a point in time where a sufficient
quantity of reductants supplied to the catalytic NOx
converter 22 is ensured, or at a specific time during the
period of 60° to 180° (CA) after the compression stroke
TDC when the catalytic NOx converter 22 is in its
activated state, and the secondary fuel injection time is
set by advancing it with reference to the ending time of
diffusion combustion when the catalytic NOx converter 22
is in its inactivated state, there are produced such
advantageous effects that NOx emissions into the
atmosphere can be suppressed by the NOx-converting
function of the catalytic NOx converter 22 when it is in
the activated state, and the amount of NOx discharged
from the combustion chambers 4 into the exhaust passage
20 can be effectively reduced by increasing the quantity
of highly reactive hydrogen within the combustion 
chambers 4, for instance, when the catalytic NOx
converter 22 is in the inactivated state.</p><p num="0143">The experimental data obtained from the earlier-mentioned
experiments, in which the relationship between
the amount of fuel injected by the secondary injection at
about the ending time of diffusion combustion was
examined, indicate that the more the ratio (P/T) of the
amount of fuel supplied by the secondary injection to the
total amount of fuel injected is increased, the more the
quantity of soot produced is reduced regardless of
whether the engine is under low-load, low-speed
conditions, medium-load, medium-speed conditions, or
high-load, high-speed conditions, as shown by solid lines
in FIGS. 19A-19C.</p><p num="0144">Next, while running the engine under low-load, low-speed
conditions, the ratio (P/T) of the amount of fuel
supplied by the secondary injection to the total amount
of fuel injected was varied in various ways and fuel
consumption was measured at individual settings, wherein
the secondary fuel injection was made at the point of 8°
(CA) after the compression stroke TDC which is supposed
to be earlier than the ending time of diffusion
combustion. In this experiment, an increase in the ratio
(P/T) of the amount of fuel supplied by the secondary 
injection produced almost no variations occurred in fuel
consumption as shown by a broken line in FIG. 23A.
Contrary to this, when the secondary fuel injection was
made at the point of 30° (CA) after the compression
stroke TDC which is in the proximity of the ending time
t1 of diffusion combustion caused by the primary fuel
injection and supposed to be a point in time when
combustion caused by the secondary fuel injection begins,
fuel consumption markedly increased with an increase in
the ratio (P/T) of the amount of fuel supplied by the
secondary injection as shown by a solid line in FIG. 23A.</p><p num="0145">Also, while running the engine under medium-load,
medium-speed conditions, the ratio (P/T) of the amount of
fuel supplied by the secondary injection to the total
amount of fuel injected was varied in various ways and
fuel consumption was measured at individual settings,
wherein the secondary fuel injection was made at the
point of 35° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, which
is in the proximity of the ending time t1 of diffusion
combustion caused by the primary fuel injection and
supposed to be a point in time when combustion caused by
the secondary fuel injection begins, and at the point of
20° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, which is
supposed to be earlier than the ending time of diffusion 
combustion. Further, while running the engine under
high-load, high-speed conditions, the ratio (P/T) of the
amount of fuel supplied by the secondary injection to the
total amount of fuel injected was varied in various ways
and fuel consumption was measured at individual settings,
wherein the secondary fuel injection was made at the
point of 48° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, which
is in the proximity of the ending time t1 of diffusion
combustion caused by the primary fuel injection and
supposed to be a point in time when combustion caused by
the secondary fuel injection begins, and at the point of
20° (CA) after the compression stroke TDC, which is
supposed to be earlier than the ending time of diffusion
combustion. In these experiments, data similar to those
obtained in the experiment under the low-load, low-speed
conditions were obtained as shown in FIGS. 23B and 23C.</p><p num="0146">Therefore, if the amount of fuel supplied by the
secondary injection is set in a range of 0.2% to 50%,
preferably 15% to 35%, in the above-described engine
exhaust-gas cleaning device and method of setting the
fuel injection timing of the invention, in which the
secondary fuel injection timing is set with reference to
the ending time of diffusion combustion caused by the
primary fuel injection within the combustion chambers 4 
and the fuel supplied by the secondary injection is
ignited at or slightly before or after the ending time of
diffusion combustion, it is possible to effectively
reduce the quantity of soot produced without increasing
fuel consumption.</p><p num="0147">Although the foregoing embodiments have thus far
been explained with reference to examples in which the
secondary fuel injection is controlled in accordance with
activation state of the catalytic NOx converter 22,
engine load and engine speed, the invention is not
limited to this form of embodiment. As an example, a
control operation for making secondary injection of the
fuel may be executed under all operating conditions of
the engine.</p><p num="0148">Furthermore, although the foregoing discussion of
the preferred embodiments has dealt with the examples
wherein the invention is applied to the direct injection
diesel engine in which the fuel is injected directly into
the combustion chambers 4, it is also possible to reduce
NOx emissions when the invention is applied to a direct
injection gasoline engine which is operated under lean-burn
conditions in which a mixture whose air-fuel ratio
is higher than the stoichiometric air-fuel ratio is burnt.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindemde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor, wobei
diese emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage umfaßt:
<claim-text><claim-text>ein Einspritzaggregat (5), um Kraftstoff in einen Brennraum (4) einzuspritzen;</claim-text><claim-text>einen Primäreinspritzungsregler (40), um den Modus der Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung
zu steuern, die vom Einspritzaggregat (5) an einem spezifischen
Zeitpunkt während einer Periode von einem Ansaughub bis zu
einem frühen Abschnitt des Expansionshubs den Motorbetriebsbedingungen
entsprechend durchgeführt wird; und</claim-text><claim-text>einen Sekundäreinspritzungsregler (41), um das Einspritzaggregat (5) so
zu steuern, daß es an einem spezifischen Zeitpunkt während einer
Periode vom Punkt der Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung durch den Expansionshub
hindurch eine Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzung durchführt;</claim-text></claim-text>
wobei der Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkt in Bezug auf einen Endzeitpunkt
der Diffusionsverbrennung geregelt wird, der durch die Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung
im Brennraum auftritt, dadurch gekennzeichnet,
daß
ein abgasbetriebener Turbolader (25) vorgesehen ist, um den Motor mit
vorverdichteter Ansaugluft zu versorgen;
wobei der Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkt in Bezug auf einen
Endzeitpunkt der Diffusionsverbrennung korrigiert wird, der aufgrund
einer Vorverdichtungswirkung des Turboladers (25) variiert.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 1, wobei diese emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage
außerdem umfaßt:<claim-text><claim-text>einen Verbrennungszustandsdiskriminator, um den Zustand der
Diffusionsverbrennung zu unterscheiden, der durch die Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung
im Brennraum (4) auftritt;</claim-text></claim-text>
wobei der Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkt in Bezug auf einen
Endzeitpunkt der Diffusionsverbrennung geregelt wird, der vom Verbrennungszustandsdiskriminator
bestimmt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 1 oder 2, wobei diese emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage
außerdem umfaßt:
<claim-text><claim-text>einen Abgasrückführer (23, 24), um einen Teil des Abgases zu einer
Ansaugleitung rückzuführen; und</claim-text><claim-text>einen Abgasrückführungsregler (39), um einen Rückkopplungsregelvorgang
so durchzuführen, daß das Abgasrückführungsverhältnis, das
vom Abgasrückführer bestimmt wird, einem Sollwert entspricht.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 3, außerdem umfassend einen Aktivierungszustandsdetektor
(37), um zu beurteilen, ob der NOx-Katalysator (22) in seinem aktivierten
Zustand ist; und wobei diese emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage
außerdem einen NOx-Katalysator (22) umfaßt, der in einer
Abgasleitung (20) des Motors vorgesehen ist, um mindestens NOx
umzuwandeln;
wobei der Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkt in Bezug auf einen
Endzeitpunkt der Diffusionsverbrennung geregelt wird, die durch die
Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung im Brennraum auftritt, wenn vom Aktivierungszustandsdetektor
(37) beurteilt wird, daß der NOx-Katalysator (22)
in seinem deaktivierten Zustand ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 4, wobei der Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkt so geregelt
wird, daß der NOx-Katalysator (22) mit einer ausreichenden Menge an
Reduktionsmittel versorgt wird, wenn der NOx-Katalysator (22) in seinem
aktivierten Zustand ist, und der Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkt in
Bezug auf den Endzeitpunkt der Diffusionsverbrennung geregelt wird, die
durch Vorschieben des Primärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkts durch die
Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung im Brennraum (4) auftritt, wenn der NOx-Katalysator
(22) in seinem deaktivierten Zustand ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach einem
der Ansprüche 1 bis 5, wobei die Kraftstoffmenge, die durch die Sekundäreinspritzung
zugeführt wird, auf zwischen 0,2 % und 50 % der
Gesamtmenge des eingespritzten Kraftstoffs geregelt ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 1, außerdem umfassend einen NOx-Katalysator (22), der in
einer Abgasleitung (20) des Motors vorgesehen ist, um mindestens NOx
umzuwandeln; und wobei die Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzung an einem
spezifischen Zeitpunkt nach der Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung während
einer Periode zwischen Kurbelwinkeln von 30° und 60° nach dem oberen
Totpunkt im Verdichtungshub durchgeführt wird, wenn der Motor unter
Betriebsbedingungen ist, in welchen die NOx-Menge, die an der Austrittsseite
des NOx-Katalysators (22) abgegeben wird, groß ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 7, wobei der NOx-Katalysator (22) einen NOx-reduzierenden
Katalysator enthält, der das Abgas reinigt, indem er die darin enthaltenen
NOx durch eine Reaktion zwischen NOx und dem Reduktionsmittel reduziert,
die unter sauerstoffreichen Bedingungen auftritt, in denen die
Sauerstoffkonzentration hoch ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 8, außerdem umfassend einen Reduktionsmittelzusetzer, um
die Menge des Reduktionsmittels im Abgas zu erhöhen, indem das Einspritzaggregat
(5) veranlaßt wird, den Kraftstoff an einem spezifischen
Zeitpunkt während einer Periode von einem Expansionshub durch einen
Auspuffhub hindurch einzuspritzen, und dieser Reduktionsmittelzusetzer
einen Sekundäreinspritzungsregler (41) umfaßt, der das Einspritzaggregat
(5) steuert, um die Sekundäreinspritzung an einem spezifischen
Zeitpunkt nach der Primäreinspritzung des Kraftstoffs aus dem Einspritzaggregat
(5) während der Periode vom Expansionshub durch den Auspuffhub
hindurch den Betriebsbedingungen des Motors entsprechend
durchzuführen, und wobei der Sekundäreinspritzungsregler (41) den
Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkt während einer Periode vom Punkt
der Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung bis zu einem Kurbelwinkel von 60° nach
dem oberen Totpunkt (TDC) im Verdichtungshub vorschiebt, wenn der
Aktivierungszustandsdetektor beurteilt, daß der NOx-reduzierende Katalysator
im deaktivierten Zustand ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 9, wobei der Sekundäreinspritzungsregler (41) die Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzung
in einem längeren Zeitintervall durchführt als die
Periode eines einfachen Verbrennungszyklus, wenn der Aktivierungszustandsdetektor
(37) beurteilt, daß der NOx-reduzierende Katalysator
im deaktivierten Zustand ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 10, wobei der Aktivierungszustandsdetektor (37) die Temperatur
des NOx-reduzierenden Katalysators (22a) erkennt und beurteilt,
daß der NOx-reduzierende Katalysator im deaktivierten Zustand ist,
wenn die erkannte Temperatur größer oder gleich einer bestimmten
Bezugstemperatur ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach
Anspruch 11, wobei ein erster NOx-reduzierender Katalysator (22a) in
der Abgasleitung (20) vorgesehen ist und ein zweiter NOx-reduzierender
Katalysator (22b), der aktiviert wird, wenn der erste NOx-reduzierende
Katalysator (22a) in seinem deaktivierten Zustand ist, hinter dem ersten
NOx-reduzierenden Katalysator (22a) vorgesehen ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Emissionsmindernde Abgasreinigungsanlage für einen Motor nach einem
der Ansprüche 8 bis 12, wobei der NOx-Katalysator (22) durch Aufbringen
von katalytischem Metall auf Zeolithe hergestellt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zur Einstellung des Kraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkts in einem
Motor, umfassend ein Einspritzaggregat (5), um Kraftstoff in einen Brennraum
(4) einzuspritzen, einen Primäreinspritzungsregler (40), um den
Modus der Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung zu steuern, die vom Einspritzaggregat
(5) an einem spezifischen Zeitpunkt während einer Periode von
einem Ansaughub bis zu einem frühen Abschnitt des Expansionshubs
den Motorbetriebsbedingungen entsprechend durchgeführt wird, und
einen Sekundäreinspritzungsregler (41), um das Einspritzaggregat (5) so
zu steuern, daß es an einem spezifischen Zeitpunkt während einer
Periode vom Punkt der Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung durch den Expansionshub
hindurch eine Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzung durchführt, wobei
der Sekundäreinspritzungsregler (41) den Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkt
in Bezug auf einen Endzeitpunkt der Diffusionsverbrennung
regelt, der durch die Primärkraftstoffeinspritzung im Brennraum (4) auftritt,
dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß
der Motor mit vorverdichteter Ansaugluft aus einem Turbolader (25) versorgt
wird, wobei der Sekundärkraftstoffeinspritzzeitpunkt in Bezug auf
einen Endzeitpunkt der Diffusionsverbrennung korrigiert wird, der aufgrund
einer Vorverdichtungswirkung des Turboladers (25) variiert.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine,
said exhaust-gas cleaning device comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a fuel injector (5) for injecting fuel into a
combustion chamber (4);</claim-text><claim-text>a primary injection controller (40) for controlling
mode of primary fuel injection performed by the fuel
injector (5) at a specific time during a period from an
intake stroke to an early part of an expansion stroke in
accordance with engine operating conditions; and</claim-text><claim-text>a secondary injection controller (41) for controlling
the fuel injector (5) to make secondary fuel injection at
a specific time during a period from the point of the
primary fuel injection through the expansion stroke;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein secondary fuel injection time is set with
reference to ending time of diffusion combustion
occurring within the combustion chamber by the primary
fuel injection, characterized in that
   a turbocharger (25) driven by exhaust gas is
provided for supplying the engine with precompressed
intake air;
   wherein the secondary fuel injection time is
corrected with reference to the ending time of diffusion
combustion which varies due to a supercharging effect
provided by the turbocharger (25).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 1, said exhaust-gas cleaning device
further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a combustion state discriminator for discriminating
the state of diffusion combustion occurring within the
combustion chamber (4) by the primary fuel injection;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the secondary fuel injection time is set
with reference to the ending time of diffusion combustion
determined by the combustion state discriminator.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 1 or 2, said exhaust-gas cleaning
device further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an exhaust gas recirculator (23, 24) for
recirculating part of the exhaust gas back to an intake
passage; and</claim-text><claim-text>an exhaust gas recirculation controller (39) for
performing a feedback control operation such that exhaust
gas recirculation ratio determined by the exhaust gas
recirculator becomes equal to a target value.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 3, further comprising an activation
state detector (37) for judging whether the catalytic NOx
converter (22) is in its activated state; and wherein
said exhaust-gas cleaning device further including a
catalytic NOx converter (22) provided in an exhaust
passage (20) of the engine for converting at least NOx;
   wherein the secondary fuel injection time is set
with reference to the ending time of diffusion combustion
occurring within the combustion chamber by the primary
fuel injection when the catalytic NOx converter (22) is
judged to be in its inactivated state by the activation
state detector (37).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 4, wherein when the catalytic NOx
converter (22) is in its activated state, the secondary
fuel injection time is set such that a sufficient
quantity of reductant supplied to the catalytic NOx
converter (22) is ensured, and when the catalytic NOx
converter (22) is in its inactivated state, the secondary
fuel injection time is set with reference to the ending
time of diffusion combustion occurring within the
combustion chamber (4) by the primary fuel injection by
advancing the primary fuel injection time.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to one of claims 1 to 5, wherein the amount of
fuel supplied by the secondary injection is set between
0.2% and 50% of the total amount of fuel injected.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 1, further comprising a catalytic NOx
converter (22) provided in an exhaust passage (20) of the
engine for converting at least NOx; and wherein the
secondary fuel injection is performed at a specific time
after the primary fuel injection during a period between
crank angles of 30° and 60° after compression stroke top
dead center when the engine is under operating conditions
in which the amount of NOx delivered to the downstream
side of the catalytic NOx converter (22) is large.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 7, wherein the catalytic NOx converter
(22) includes a NOx-reducing catalyst which purifies the
exhaust gas by reducing NOx contained therein as a result
of reaction between NOx and the reductant occurring under
oxygen-rich conditions in which the concentration of
oxygen is high.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 8, further comprising a reductant
adder for increasing the quantity of reductant in exhaust
gas by causing the fuel injector (5) to inject the fuel
at a specific time during a period from an expansion
stroke through an exhaust stroke, and said reductant
adder includes a secondary injection controller (41)
which controls the fuel injector (5) to make secondary
injection of the fuel at a specific time during the
period from the expansion stroke through the exhaust
stroke after primary injection of the fuel from the fuel
injector (5) in accordance with operating conditions of
the engine, and wherein the secondary injection
controller (41) advances the secondary fuel injection
time within a period from the point of the primary fuel
injection to a crank angle of 60° after compression
stroke top dead center (TDC) when the activation state
detector judges that the NOx-reducing catalyst is in the
inactivated state.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 9, wherein the secondary injection
controller (41) performs the secondary fuel injection at
a longer time interval than the period of a single
combustion cycle when the activation state detector (37)
judges that the NOx-reducing catalyst is in the
inactivated state.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 10, wherein the activation state
detector (37) detects the temperature of the NOx-reducing
catalyst and judges that the NOx-reducing catalyst is in
the inactivated state when the detected temperature is
equal to or higher than a specific reference temperature.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to claim 11, wherein a first NOx-reducing
catalyst (22a) is provided in the exhaust passage (20)
and a second NOx-reducing catalyst (22b), which becomes
activated when the first NOx-reducing catalyst (22a) is
in its inactivated state, is provided downstream of the
first NOx-reducing catalyst (22a).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An exhaust-gas cleaning device for an engine
according to one of claims 8 to 12, wherein the catalytic
NOx converter (22) is formed by depositing catalytic
metal on zeolite.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method of setting fuel injection timing in an
engine comprising a fuel injector (5) for injecting fuel
into a combustion chamber (4), a primary injection
controller (40) for controlling mode of primary fuel
injection performed by the fuel injector (5) at a
specific time during a period from an intake stroke to an
early part of an expansion stroke in accordance with
engine operating conditions, and a secondary injection
controller (41) for controlling the fuel injector (5) to
make secondary injection of the fuel at a specific time
during a period from the point of the primary fuel
injection through the expansion stroke, wherein the
secondary injection controller (41) sets secondary fuel
injection time with reference to ending time of diffusion
combustion occurring within the combustion chamber (4) by
the primary fuel injection, characterized in that
   the engine is supplied with precompressed intake air
from a turbocharger (25), wherein the secondary fuel
injection time is corrected with reference to the ending
time of diffusion combustion which varies due to a
supercharging effect provided by the turbocharger (25).</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur, ledit dispositif
d'épuration de gaz d'échappement comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>un injecteur de carburant (5) pour l'injection du carburant dans une
chambre de combustion (4) ;</claim-text><claim-text>un dispositif primaire de commande d'injection (40) pour commander le
mode d'injection primaire de carburant, exécutée par l'injecteur de
carburant (5) à un instant précis au cours d'une période allant d'un temps
d'admission jusqu'à une première partie d'un temps d'expansion en
accord avec les conditions opératoires du moteur ; et</claim-text><claim-text>un dispositif secondaire de commande d'injection (41) pour commander
l'injecteur de carburant (5) afin de réaliser l'injection secondaire de
carburant à un instant précis au cours d'une période allant du point de
l'injection primaire de carburant jusqu'à la fin du temps d'expansion ;</claim-text><claim-text>selon lequel le temps d'injection secondaire de carburant est programmé
en référence au délai d'achèvement de la combustion par diffusion qui se
produit dans la chambre de combustion par l'injection primaire de
carburant, caractérisé en ce qu'</claim-text><claim-text>un turbocompresseur (25) entraíné par les gaz d'échappement est prévu
pour alimenter le moteur en air d'admission précomprimé ;</claim-text><claim-text>le temps d'injection secondaire de carburant étant corrigé en référence
au délai d'achèvement de la combustion par diffusion qui varie du fait
d'un effet de turbocompression assuré par le turbocompresseur (25).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 1, ledit dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement
comprenant en outre :<claim-text><claim-text>un discriminateur d'état de combustion pour réaliser la discrimination de
l'état de combustion par diffusion qui se produit dans la chambre de
combustion (4) par l'injection primaire de carburant ;</claim-text><claim-text>le temps d'injection secondaire de carburant étant programmé en
référence au délai d'achèvement de la combustion par diffusion,
déterminé par le discriminateur d'état de combustion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 1 ou 2, ledit dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement
comprenant en outre :
<claim-text><claim-text>un équipement de recirculation des gaz d'échappement (23, 24) pour
faire recirculer une partie des gaz d'échappement en retour vers un
conduit d'admission ; et</claim-text><claim-text>un dispositif de commande (39) de recirculation de gaz d'échappement
pour procéder à une opération de commande par feedback, de telle
façon que le rapport de recirculation de gaz d'échappement, déterminé
par l'équipement de recirculation des gaz d'échappement, devienne égal
à une valeur cible.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 3, comprenant en outre un détecteur d'état d'activation (37)
afin d'estimer si le pot catalytique pour NOx (22) est dans son état
activé ; et ledit dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement incluant en
outre un pot catalytique pour NOx (22) prévu dans un conduit
d'échappement (20) du moteur afin de transformer au moins les NOx;
le temps d'injection secondaire de carburant étant programmé en
référence au délai d'achèvement de la combustion par diffusion qui se
produit dans la chambre de combustion par l'injection primaire de
carburant quand on estime que le pot catalytique pour NOx (22) est dans
son état inactivé par le détecteur d'état d'activation (37).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 4, caractérisé en ce que, quand le pot catalytique pour
NOx (22) est dans son état activé, le temps d'injection secondaire de
carburant est programmé de façon telle qu'une quantité suffisante de
réducteur fournie au pot catalytique pour NOx (22) est assurée, et en ce
que, quand le pot catalytique pour NOx (22) est dans son état inactivé, le
temps d'injection secondaire de carburant est programmé en référence
au délai d'achèvement de la combustion par diffusion qui se produit dans
la chambre de combustion (4) par l'injection primaire de carburant, en
avançant l'instant d'injection primaire de carburant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon l'une des
revendications 1 à 5, caractérisé en ce que la quantité de carburant
fournie par l'injection secondaire est programmée entre 0,2 % et 50 % de
la quantité totale de carburant injecté.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 1, caractérisé en ce qu'il comprend en outre un pot
catalytique pour NOx (22) prévu dans un conduit d'échappement (20) du
moteur pour transformer au moins les NOx; et caractérisé en ce que
l'injection secondaire de carburant est exécutée à un instant précis
postérieur à l'injection primaire de carburant, au cours d'une période
correspondant aux valeurs d'angle de maneton comprises entre 30° et
60° après le point mort haut de temps de compression, quand le moteur
est dans des conditions opératoires dans lesquelles la quantité de
NOx délivrée côté aval du pot catalytique pour NOx (22) est grande.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 7, caractérisé en ce que le pot catalytique pour NOx (22)
comprend un catalyseur de réduction des NOx qui purifie les gaz
d'échappement en réduisant les NOx contenus, suite à la réaction entre
les NOx et le réducteur qui se produit dans des conditions riches en
oxygène, dans lesquelles la concentration d'oxygène est élevée.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 8, caractérisé en ce qu'il comprend en outre une unité
d'addition de réducteur pour augmenter la quantité de réducteur dans les
gaz d'échappement en amenant l'injecteur de carburant (5) à injecter le
carburant à un instant précis pendant une période allant d'un temps
d'expansion jusqu'à un temps d'échappement, et en ce que ladite unité
d'addition de réducteur inclut un dispositif secondaire de commande
d'injection (41) qui commande l'injecteur de carburant (5) afin de réaliser
l'injection secondaire de carburant à un instant précis au cours de la
période allant du temps d'expansion jusqu'au temps d'échappement
après l'injection primaire du carburant à partir de l'injecteur de carburant
(5) en accord avec les conditions opératoires du moteur, et en ce que le
dispositif secondaire de commande d'injection (41) fait avancer l'instant
d'injection secondaire de carburant dans l'intervalle d'une période allant
du point de l'injection primaire de carburant jusqu'à un angle de maneton
de 60° après le point mort haut (PMH) de temps de compression quand
le détecteur d'état d'activation estime que le catalyseur de réduction des
NOx est dans l'état inactivé.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 9, caractérisé en ce que le dispositif secondaire de
commande d'injection (41) exécute l'injection secondaire de carburant à
un intervalle de temps plus long que la période d'un cycle unique de
combustion, quand le détecteur d'état d'activation (37) estime que le
catalyseur de réduction des NOx est dans l'état inactivé.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 10, caractérisé en ce que le détecteur d'état
d'activation (37) détecte la température du catalyseur de réduction des
NOx et estime que le catalyseur de réduction des NOx est dans l'état
inactivé quand la température détectée est égale ou supérieure à une
température spécifiée de référence.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon la
revendication 11, caractérisé en ce qu'un premier catalyseur de
réduction des NOx (22a) est prévu dans le conduit d'échappement (20) et
en ce qu'un second catalyseur de réduction des NOx (22b), qui devient
activé quand le premier catalyseur de réduction des NOx (22a) est dans
son état inactivé, est prévu en aval du premier catalyseur de réduction
des NOx (22a).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'épuration de gaz d'échappement pour moteur selon l'une des
revendications 8 à 12, caractérisé en ce que le pot catalytique pour NOx
(22) est formé en déposant du métal catalytique sur de la zéolithe.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de programmation du délai d'injection de carburant dans un
moteur comprenant un injecteur de carburant (5) pour l'injection du
carburant dans une chambre de combustion (4), un dispositif primaire de
commande d'injection (40) pour commander le mode d'injection primaire
de carburant, exécutée par l'injecteur de carburant (5) à un instant précis
au cours d'une période allant d'un temps d'admission jusqu'à une
première partie d'un temps d'expansion en accord avec les conditions
opératoires du moteur, et un dispositif secondaire de commande
d'injection (41) pour commander l'injecteur de carburant (5) afin de
réaliser l'injection secondaire de carburant à un instant précis au cours
d'une période allant du point de l'injection primaire de carburant jusqu'au
temps d'expansion, selon lequel le dispositif secondaire de commande
d'injection (41) programme le temps d'injection secondaire de carburant
en référence au délai d'achèvement de la combustion par diffusion qui se
produit dans la chambre de combustion (4) par l'injection primaire de
carburant, caractérisé en ce que
le moteur est alimenté en air d'admission précomprimé à partir d'un
turbocompressseur (25) , et selon lequel le temps d'injection secondaire
de carburant est corrigé en référence[U1] au délai d'achèvement de la
combustion par diffusion qui varie du fait d'un effet de turbocompression
assuré par le turbocompresseur (25).</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20060809"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ES</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040630</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041011</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050222</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="GBPC" date="20051012"><legal-event-body><event-title>GB: EUROPEAN PATENT CEASED THROUGH NON-PAYMENT OF RENEWAL FEE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050222</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="EN" date="20050624"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION NOT FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20050622"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050331</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20040805"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60104028</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040805</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20040728"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20040630"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEESFRGBIT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20040630"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20030723"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEESFRGBIT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20030625"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030508</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20030122"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20021122</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20021030"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20021030"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010829"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010829"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>
