<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1132442-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1132442" kind="B1" date="20030319"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23245214" ucid="EP-1132442-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1132442</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20030319</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01104755-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01104755</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010226</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000050933-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000050933</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000228</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new" /><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  59/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  59/42        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  73/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  73/02        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 133/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 133/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 163/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 163/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G59/42B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D133/06B6+B4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D163/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L73:02</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Hitzehärtbare Pulverbeschichtungszusammensetzung und Verfahren zum Herstellen einer Deckbeschichtung mit derselben</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Thermosetting powder coating composition and method for forming a topcoat using the same</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Composition de revêtement pulvérulente thermodurcissable et procédé de préparation d'une couche de finition avec celle-ci</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KANSAI PAINT CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KANSAI PAINT CO. LTD.</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HARAKAWA HIROMI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KAWAMOTO YUGEN</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>ADACHI TAKATO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>HARAKAWA, HIROMI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>ADACHI, TAKATO</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KAWAMOTO, YUGEN</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>HARAKAWA, HIROMI</last-name><address><street>242-7, Nagamochi</street><city>Hiratsuka-shi, Kanagawa-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KAWAMOTO, YUGEN</last-name><address><street>Kansai Paint Shataku 2-36, 580, Shindo</street><city>Hiratsuka-shi, Kanagawa-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>ADACHI, TAKATO</last-name><address><street>Kansai Paint Shataku 2-36, 580, Shindo</street><city>Hiratsuka-shi, Kanagawa-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KANSAI PAINT CO. LTD.</last-name><address><street>33-1, Kanzaki-cho</street><city>Amagasaki-shi Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>R.A. KUHNEN &amp;amp; P.A. WACKER</last-name><address><street>Patentanwaltsgesellschaft dbR Postfach 19 64</street><city>85319 Freising</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>The present invention provides a thermosetting powder coating composition comprising:     (A) an epoxy-containing resin; and (B) a curing agent containing, as an essential ingredient, an acid anhydride (a) represented by the formula HOOC- (CH2)m-ÄCOO-CO-(CH2)mÜn-COOR1 wherein R1 represents a C1-10 monovalent saturated hydrocarbon group, m is an integer of 6 to 18, and n is a number of 1 to 20 on average, the molar ratio of carboxyl groups to acid anhydride groups in the curing agent being in the range from 0.15:1 to 2.0:1, the molar ratio of the total of carboxyl groups and acid anhydride groups in the curing agent (B) to epoxy groups in the epoxy-containing resin (A) being in the range from 0.7:1 to 1.2:1. The present invention further provides a method for forming a topcoat according to a 2-coat 1-bake system comprising the steps of applying to a substrate a thermosetting aqueous colored base coating composition, applying to the uncured surface of the base coat a clear coating composition, and curing the two coats by heating, wherein the clear coating composition is the above thermosetting powder coating composition.</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">The present invention provides a thermosetting
powder coating composition comprising:
<sl><li>(A) an epoxy-containing resin; and</li><li>(B) a curing agent containing, as an essential ingredient, an
acid anhydride (a) represented by the formula
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">HOOC- (CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>m</sub>-[COO-CO-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>m</sub>]<sub>n</sub>-COOR<sub>1</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> represents a C<sub>1-10</sub> monovalent saturated hydrocarbon
group, m is an integer of 6 to 18, and n is a number of 1 to
20 on average, the molar ratio of carboxyl groups to acid
anhydride groups in the curing agent being in the range from
0.15:1 to 2.0:1,

the molar ratio of the total of carboxyl groups and acid
anhydride groups in the curing agent (B) to epoxy groups in
the epoxy-containing resin (A) being in the range from 0.7:1
to 1.2:1. The present invention further provides a method for
forming a topcoat according to a 2-coat 1-bake system
comprising the steps of applying to a substrate a
thermosetting aqueous colored base coating composition,
applying to the uncured surface of the base coat a clear
coating composition, and curing the two coats by heating,
wherein the clear coating composition is the above
thermosetting powder coating composition.</li></sl></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a novel
thermosetting powder coating composition and a method for
forming a topcoat using the same.</p><p num="0002">Topcoats for coating substrates such as
automotive exterior panels are required to have excellent
finished appearance such as surface smoothness and
excellent coating properties such as weather resistance,
solvent resistance, acid resistance, etc., in view of uses.
In recent years, the required levels have been getting
even higher.</p><p num="0003">Thermosetting powder coating compositions are
conventionally used as clear coating compositions for
forming topcoats by 2-coat 1-bake systems, etc. From the
viewpoints of environmental protection and energy saving,
it is desired that the thermosetting aqueous coating
compositions be used as base coating compositions.</p><p num="0004">However, the thermosetting powder coating
compositions have the following problems. When surface
smoothness of the coating film is improved, other coating
properties such as weather resistance, solvent resistance
and acid resistance are impaired. On the other hand, when
the other properties are improved, surface smoothness is 
reduced. It has been difficult to achieve a proper
balance therebetween. When conventional thermosetting
powder clear coating compositions are applied to surfaces
of aqueous base coats, such problems develop to a serious
level, and it has been difficult to form a topcoat that
excels in both surface smoothness and the above-mentioned
other coating properties.</p><p num="0005">For example, a 2-coat 1-bake coating method for
forming a topcoat is known from <ref type="patent">U.S. Patent No. 5,565,146</ref>.
This method comprises the steps of applying to a substrate
a thermosetting aqueous base coating composition
comprising a hydroxyl- and carboxyl-containing resin and
an alkyletherified methylol melamine resin, applying to
the uncured surface of the base coat a thermosetting
powder clear coating composition comprising an epoxy-containing
acrylic resin and a dibasic acid such as
dodecanoic diacid or acid anhydride thereof as a curing
agent, followed by curing the two coats by heating.</p><p num="0006">However, in the above 2-coat 1-bake coating
method, when the coat of the aqueous base coating
composition and the coat of the powder clear coating
composition are heated for curing at the same time, a
reaction between the hydroxyl group and the alkylether
group in the aqueous coat produces an alcohol as a
byproduct. When the alcohol evaporates out through the 
thermally fused powder coat, it causes cratering due to
popping on the surface of powder coat, thereby impairing
surface smoothness, distinctness-of-image gloss, and
physical properties of the coating film. When the aqueous
coat comprises a flaky metallic pigment, orientation of
the pigment flakes is altered, thus impairing metallic
effects, etc.</p><p num="0007">In the above method, if curing initiation time
is delayed so as to fully melt and flow the powder coat
particles by heating with the purpose of improving coating
surface smoothness, etc., an insufficiently crosslinked
powder coat will result, thus impairing coating properties
such as weather resistance, solvent resistance and acid
resistance.</p><p num="0008">The document <ref type="patent">EP-A 1 059 343</ref> provides a thermosetting powder coating
composition comprising: an epoxy-containing resin and a curing agent containing an
acid anhydride (a) and at least one species selected from the group consisting of an acid
anhydride (b) and a dibasic acid (c). The material, when applied to a surface, excels in
finished appearance such as surface smoothness and also in other coating properties.
The acid anhydride (a) can be prepared by conventionally known methods, thus
resulting into an acid anhydride having ester groups at both ends.</p><p num="0009">The document <ref type="patent">EP-A 0 696 622</ref> discloses a thermosetting powder paint
comprising, as essential components, (A) a copolymer, and, as curing agents capable of
reacting with the component (A) to crosslink the component (A), (B) an aliphatic
polycarboxylic acid and (C) a linear anhydride of an aliphatic polycarboxylic acid.</p><p num="0010">An object of the present invention is to provide
a novel thermosetting powder coating composition that
excels in finished appearance such as surface smoothness
and also in other coating properties such as weather
resistance, solvent resistance and acid resistance.</p><p num="0011">Another object of the invention is to provide a
method for forming a topcoat using the above-mentioned
thermosetting powder coating composition.</p><p num="0012">Other objects and features of the invention will
become apparent from the following description.</p><p num="0013">The present invention provides the following  
thermosetting powder coating composition and method for
forming a topcoat using the composition:
<sl><li>1. A thermosetting powder coating composition comprising:
<sl><li>(A) an epoxy-containing resin; and</li><li>(B) a curing agent containing, as an essential ingredient,
an acid anhydride (a) represented by the formula
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">HOOC- (CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>m</sub>- [COO-CO- (CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>m</sub>]<sub>n</sub>-COOR<sub>1</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> represents a C<sub>1-10</sub> monovalent saturated
hydrocarbon group, m is an integer of 6 to 18, and n is a
number of 1 to 20 on average, the molar ratio of carboxyl
groups to acid anhydride groups in the curing agent being
in the range from 0.15:1 to 2.0:1,
the molar ratio of COOR<sub>1</sub> groups in the curing agent (B) to the total of carboxyl
groups and acid anhydride groups in the curing agent (B) being in the range from 0.01 :
1 to 0.1 : 1; and

the molar ratio of the total of carboxyl groups and acid
anhydride groups in the curing agent (B) to epoxy groups
in the epoxy-containing resin (A) being in the range from
0.7:1 to 1.2:1.</li></sl></li><li>2. The powder coating composition according to item 1
wherein the epoxy-containing resin (A) is an epoxy-containing
copolymer prepared by copolymerizing an epoxy-containing
vinyl monomer and at least one other
polymerizable vinyl monomer.</li><li>3. The powder coating composition according to item 2
wherein the epoxy-containing resin (A) comprises 20 to 70%
by weight of an epoxy-containing vinyl monomer as a
monomer component of the epoxy-containing copolymer.  </li><li>4. The powder coating composition according to item 1
wherein the epoxy-containing resin (A) has a glass
transition temperature of 40°C to 80°C.</li><li>5. The powder coating composition according to item 1
wherein the epoxy-containing resin (A) has a number
average molecular weight of 1,000 to 10,000.</li><li>6. The powder coating composition according to item 1
wherein the curing agent (B) contains acid anhydride (a)
and at least one species selected from the group
consisting of acid anhydride (b) and dibasic acid (c),
the acid anhydride (b) being represented by the formula
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>2</sub>OOC- (CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>p</sub>- [COO-CO- (CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>p</sub>]<sub>q</sub>-COOR<sub>2</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sub>2</sub> represents a C<sub>1-10</sub> monovalent saturated
hydrocarbon group; p is an integer of 6 to 18; and q is a
number of 1 to 20 on average, and
the dibasic acid (c) being represented by the formula
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">HOOC- (CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>r</sub> - [COO-CO-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>r</sub>]<sub>s</sub>-COOH</st32:che>
wherein r is an integer of 6 to 18; and s is a number of 0
to 20 on average,
the molar ratio of the total of COOR<sub>1</sub> groups and COOR<sub>2</sub> groups in the curing agent
(B) to the total of carboxyl groups and acid anhydride groups in the curing agent (B)
being in the range from 0.01 : 1 to 0.1 : 1.  </li><li>7. The powder coating composition according to item 1
wherein the acid anhydride (a) in the curing agent (B) has
a melting point of 60°C or higher.</li><li>8. The powder coating composition according to item 6
wherein the acid anhydride (b) and dibasic acid (c) in the
curing agent (B) have melting points of 60°C or higher.</li><li>9. The powder coating composition according to item 6
wherein the mixture of acid anhydride (a) with acid
anhydride (b) and/or dibasic acid (c) has a melting point
of 60°C or higher.</li><li>10. A method for forming a topcoat according to a 2-coat
1-bake system comprising the steps of applying to a
substrate a thermosetting aqueous colored base coating
composition, applying to the uncured surface of the base
coat a clear coating composition, and curing the two coats
by heating, wherein the clear coating composition is the
thermosetting powder coating composition according to item
1.</li></sl></p><p num="0014">The present inventors carried out intensive
research to overcome the prior art defects and found that
the above objects can be achieved with a thermosetting
powder coating composition which comprises, as a curing
agent for an epoxy-containing resin, a curing agent
essentially containing the above specified acid anhydride
(a). Stated more specifically, the present inventors 
found that the above powder coating composition is
excellent in curability, and when it is used as a clear
coating composition in a 2-coat 1-bake coating method
using an aqueous base coating composition, a fully
crosslinked powder coat will be formed even with the
curing initiation time being delayed, thus preventing
popping and providing a topcoat with excellent finished
appearance such as smoothness and excellent coating
properties such as weather resistance, solvent resistance
and acid resistance. The present invention has been
accomplished based on this novel finding.</p><p num="0015">The epoxy-containing resin (A) used in the
thermosetting powder coating composition of the invention
may be selected from any known resin that is solid and has
an average of at least one epoxy group, preferably at
least two epoxy groups, per molecule.</p><p num="0016">Examples of resins usable as the epoxy-containing
resin (A) are bisphenol epoxy resins such as
&quot;EPIKOTE 1001&quot; (with an epoxy equivalent of 450 to 500,
product of Shell Chemical Co., Ltd., trade name), &quot;EPIKOTE
1004&quot; (with an epoxy equivalent of 875 to 975, product of
Shell Chemical Co., Ltd., trade name), and &quot;EPIKOTE 1007&quot;
(with an epoxy equivalent of 1,750 to 2,200, Shell Chemical
Co., Ltd., trade name); and epoxy-containing copolymers
each prepared by copolymerizing an epoxy-containing vinyl 
monomer and at least one other polymerizable vinyl monomer.</p><p num="0017">The polymerization method for preparing such
epoxy-containing copolymers is not limited specifically,
but radical polymerization is usually preferred. Examples
of useful epoxy-containing vinyl monomers include glycidyl
(meth)acrylate, allyl glycidyl ether, 3,4-epoxycyclohexyl
(meth)acrylate and β-methylglycidyl (meth)acrylate. The
monomers can be used singly or in combination of two or
more. Particularly preferred are glycidyl (meth)acrylate
and β-methylglycidyl (meth)acrylate.</p><p num="0018">Examples of other polymerizable vinyl monomers
are vinyl aromatic compounds such as styrene, α-methylstyrene,
vinyltoluene and α-chlorostyrene; and
C<sub>1-24</sub> alkyl esters or cycloalkyl esters of acrylic or
methacrylic acids, such as methyl (meth)acrylate, ethyl
(meth)acrylate, n-butyl (meth)acrylate, isobutyl
(meth)acrylate, t-butyl (meth)acrylate, 2-ethylhexyl
(meth)acrylate, n-octyl (meth)acrylate, decyl
(meth)acrylate, lauryl (meth)acrylate, stearyl
(meth)acrylate, cyclohexyl (meth)acrylate, isobornyl
(meth)acrylate and tricyclodecanyl (meth)acrylate.</p><p num="0019">Of the monomers constituting the epoxy-containing
copolymer, the epoxy-containing vinyl monomer
is used preferably in a proportion of 20 to 70% by weight,
more preferably in a proportion of 30 to 60% by weight. 
An epoxy-containing vinyl monomer content of less than 20
wt.% in the copolymer reduces acid resistance, weather
resistance and solvent resistance of the coating film. On
the other hand, an epoxy-containing vinyl monomer content
of more than 70 wt.% impairs storage stability of the
coating composition and finished appearance such as
surface smoothness of the coating film. Therefore, any
epoxy-containing vinyl monomer content outside said range
is undesirable.</p><p num="0020">It is preferable for the epoxy-containing resin
(A) to have a glass transition temperature of 40°C to 80°C,
particularly 50°C to 70°C. A glass transition temperature
of lower than 40°C causes particles in the powder coating
composition to weld together, thereby reducing blocking
resistance. On the other hand, when the glass transition
temperature is higher than 80°C, the viscosity of the
powder coating composition increases at the time of
flowing of the powder coat particles by heating, thus
impairing finished appearance of the coating film.
Therefore, any glass transition temperature outside said
range is undesirable. The glass transition temperature
can be measured by DSC (differential scanning calorimeter).</p><p num="0021">It is preferable for the epoxy-containing resin
(A) to have a number average molecular weight of 1,000 to
10,000, particularly 2,000 to 6,000. A number average 
molecular weight of less than 1,000 reduces blocking
resistance of the powder coating composition and impairs
coating properties such as solvent resistance and acid
resistance. On the other hand, a number average molecular
weight of more than 10,000 impairs finished appearance
such as surface smoothness of the coating film. Therefore,
any number average molecular weight outside said range is
undesirable.</p><p num="0022">The curing agent (B) contains acid anhydride (a)
of the formula (1) as an essential curing ingredient and
optionally contains at least one species selected from the
group consisting of acid anhydride (b) of the formula (2)
and dibasic acid (c) of the formula (3).</p><p num="0023">The molar ratio of carboxyl groups to acid
anhydride groups in the curing agent (B) must be in the
range from 0.15:1 to 2.0:1, preferably from 0.2:1 to 1.8:1.
When the molar ratio of carboxyl group/acid anhydride
group is lower than 0.15, satisfactory curability is not
provided. When the molar ratio of carboxyl group/acid
anhydride group is higher than 2.0, the curing initiation
time occurs earlier, thus causing popping on the coating
film and impairing surface smoothness of the coating film.
Therefore, any molar ratio outside said range is
undesirable.</p><p num="0024">The molar ratio of COOR<sub>1</sub> groups or the total of 
COOR<sub>1</sub> groups and COOR<sub>2</sub> groups in the curing agent (B) to
the total of carboxyl groups and acid anhydride groups in
the curing agent (B) is preferably in the range from
0.01:1 to 0.1:1, more preferably in the range from 0.12:1
to 0.06:1. If the molar ratio is lower than 0.01, the
curing initiation time occurs earlier, giving inferior
finished appearance. On the other hand, if the molar
ratio is higher than 0.1, the cured coat will have low
crosslinking density, thus impairing coating properties
such as acid resistance and solvent resistance. Therefore,
any molar ratio outside said range is undesirable.</p><p num="0025">The acid anhydride (a) of the formula (1) is an
acid anhydride having a carboxyl group at one end and an
ester group at the other end, wherein R<sub>1</sub> included in the
ester group is a C<sub>1-10</sub> monovalent saturated hydrocarbon
group. When the saturated hydrocarbon group has 11 or
more carbon atoms, the resulting coating composition has
inferior coating properties such as acid resistance and
solvent resistance, and hazing occurs on the coating
surface, thus being undesirable.</p><p num="0026">In the formula (1), examples of C<sub>1-10</sub> monovalent
saturated hydrocarbon groups represented by R<sub>1</sub> include
monovalent aliphatic hydrocarbon groups, monovalent
alicyclic hydrocarbon groups and a combination thereof.
Specific examples are methyl, ethyl, n-propyl, iso-propyl, 
n-butyl, iso-butyl, sec-butyl, amyl, n-hexyl, n-octyl, 2-ethylhexyl,
n-decanyl, cyclohexyl, methylcyclohexyl and
the like.</p><p num="0027">In the formula (1), m must be an integer of 6 to
18. If m is 5 or less, the coating composition is cured
too quickly, giving inferior finished appearance. On the
other hand, if m is 19 or more, the cured coat has low
crosslinking density, thus impairing coating properties
such as acid resistance and solvent resistance. Therefore,
any integer outside said range is undesirable.</p><p num="0028">In the formula (1), n represents the degree of
polymerization, which must be in the range of 1 to 20,
preferably 2 to 12, on average. If n is less than 1, the
cured coat has low crosslinking density, thus impairing
coating properties such as acid resistance and solvent
resistance. On the other hand, if n is more than 20, the
viscosity of the powder coating composition increases when
thermally fused, providing a coating film with inferior
finished appearance such as low surface smoothness. Hence
any degree of polymerization outside said range is
undesirable.</p><p num="0029">The acid anhydride (a) of the formula (1) can be
prepared by conventional methods. For example, the
compound can be prepared by heating dibasic acid in the
presence of an acid anhydride, followed by monoesterifying 
part of acid anhydride groups in the resulting product
with an alcohol, thus providing an acid anhydride having
an ester group at one end. A mixture of acid anhydride
(a), acid anhydride (b) and dibasic acid (c) is often
obtained. Such a mixture per se may also be used as a
curing agent (B). Acid anhydrides usually used in the
above reaction are, for example, acetic anhydride and the
like.</p><p num="0030">Examples of alcohols used in the reaction are
methanol, ethanol, iso-propanol, n-butanol, iso-butanol,
sec-butanol, n-pentanol, n-hexanol, n-octanol, 2-ethylhexanol,
cyclohexanol and methylcyclohexanol.</p><p num="0031">Examples of dibasic acids are aliphatic dibasic
acids such as suberic acid, azelaic acid, sebacic acid,
undecanoic diacid, dodecanoic diacid, tridecanoic diacid,
tetradecanoic diacid, pentadecanoic diacid and eicosanoic
diacid.</p><p num="0032">In the curing agent (B) of the invention, the
acid anhydride (b) of the formula (2) is an acid anhydride
having ester groups at both ends. The C<sub>1-10</sub> monovalent
saturated hydrocarbon group represented by R<sub>2</sub> is the same
as R<sub>1</sub> in the formula (1).</p><p num="0033">In the formula (2), p must be an integer of 6 to
18. If p is 5 or less, the coating composition is cured
too quickly, giving inferior finished appearance. On the 
other hand, if p is 19 or more, the cured coat will have
low crosslinking density, thus impairing coating
properties such as acid resistance and solvent resistance.
Therefore, any integer outside said range is undesirable.</p><p num="0034">In the formula (2), q represents the degree of
polymerization, which must be in the range of 1 to 20,
preferably 2 to 12, on average. If q is less than 1, the
cured coat will have low crosslinking density, thus
impairing coating properties such as acid resistance and
solvent resistance. On the other hand, if q is more than
20, the viscosity of the powder coating composition
increases when thermally fused, providing a coating film
with inferior finished appearance such as low surface
smoothness. Hence any degree of polymerization outside
said range is undesirable.</p><p num="0035">The acid anhydride (b) of the formula (2) can be
prepared by conventional methods. For example, the
compound can be prepared by heating dibasic acid in the
presence of an acid anhydride and monoesterifying part of
acid anhydride groups in the intermediate with an alcohol,
followed by further heating the intermediate in the
presence of an acid anhydride, thus giving an acid
anhydride having ester groups at both ends. Acid
anhydrides usually used in the above reaction are, for
example, acetic anhydride and the like. Useful alcohols 
and dibasic acids are the same as used in the preparation
of the acid anhydride (a).</p><p num="0036">The dibasic acid (c) of the formula (3) used in
the curing agent (B) of the invention has carboxyl groups
at both ends.</p><p num="0037">Dibasic acids of the formula (3) wherein s is 1
to 20 have one or more acid anhydride groups. Such
dibasic acids can be prepared, for example, by heating an
aliphatic dibasic acid such as suberic acid, azelaic acid,
sebacic acid, undecanoic diacid, dodecanoic diacid,
tridecanoic diacid, tetradecanoic diacid, pentadecanoic
diacid, eicosanoic diacid and the like in the presence of
an acid anhydride. Usually used as an acid anhydride in
the above reaction is acetic anhydride or the like.
Dibasic acids of the formula (3) wherein s is 0 include,
for example, the above-mentioned aliphatic dibasic acids.</p><p num="0038">In the formula (3), r is an integer of 6 to 18.
If r is 5 or less, the curing initiation time occurs
earlier, thus giving inferior finished appearance. On the
other hand, if r is 19 or more, the cured coat will have
low crosslinking density, thus impairing coating
properties such as acid resistance and solvent resistance.
Therefore, any integer outside said range is undesirable.
In the formula (3), s represents the degree of
polymerization, which must be in the range of 0 to 20, 
preferably 2 to 12, on average. If s is more than 20, the
viscosity of the powder coating composition increases when
thermally fused, providing a coating film with inferior
finished appearance such as low surface smoothness. Hence
any degree of polymerization outside said range is
undesirable.</p><p num="0039">It is preferable for each of the acid anhydride
(a), acid anhydride (b) and dibasic acid (c) in the curing
agent (B) of the invention to have a melting point of 60°C
or higher, more preferably 70°C to 140°C. If the melting
points are lower than 60°C, the powder coating composition
will have poor blocking resistance, thus being undesirable.
Even when the curing agent (B) is a mixture of acid
anhydride (a) with acid anhydride (b) and/or dibasic acid
(c), it is preferable for the mixture to have a melting
point of 60°C or higher.</p><p num="0040">The curing agent (B) of the invention contains
acid anhydride (a) of the formula (1) as an essential
curing ingredient and optionally contains at least one
species selected from the group consisting of acid
anhydride (b) of the formula (2) and dibasic acid (c) of
the formula (3). When the acid anhydride (a) and optional
ingredient(s) are used together, the proportions are not
limited specifically but can be selected from a wide range.
It is usually preferable that acid anhydride (b) and/or 
dibasic acid (c) be used in amount of about 0 to about
3,000 parts by weight per 100 parts by weight of acid
anhydride (a). The acid anhydride (b) and/or dibasic acid
(c) may be prepared separately, or unreacted compounds or
byproducts produced by the process of preparing the acid
anhydride (a) may be used.</p><p num="0041">The thermosetting powder coating composition of
the invention contains an epoxy-containing resin (A) and a
curing agent (B) as essential components. The curing
agent (B) contains acid anhydride (a) as an essential
ingredient and acid anhydride (b) and/or dibasic acid (c)
as optional ingredients.</p><p num="0042">The proportions of the epoxy-containing resin
(A) and curing agent (B) should be selected from the range
that the molar ratio of the total of carboxyl groups and
acid anhydride groups in the curing agent (B) to epoxy
groups in the epoxy-containing resin (A) will be in the
range from 0.7:1 to 1.2:1. If the molar ratio of the
total of carboxyl groups and acid anhydride groups in the
curing agent (B) to epoxy groups in the resin (A) is lower
than 0.7, coating properties such as acid resistance and
solvent resistance will be impaired. On the other hand,
if the molar ratio is higher than 1.2, inferior finished
appearance such as low surface smoothness will result.
Therefore, any molar ratio outside said range is 
undesirable.</p><p num="0043">The thermosetting powder coating composition of
the invention may contain additives, for example,
antipopping agents, surface modifiers, oxidation
inhibitors, UV absorbers, UV stabilizers, antiblocking
agents, fluidity modifiers, antistatic agents, coloring
pigments, metallic pigments, interference pigments,
fillers and curing accelerators.</p><p num="0044">The method for preparing the thermosetting
powder coating composition of the invention is not limited
specifically and the composition can be prepared by
conventional methods. For example, a typical method
comprises dryblending an epoxy-containing resin (A), a
curing agent (B) and optionally other components in a
mixer or the like, and melting and kneading the dryblend
with heating, followed by cooling, coarse grinding, fine
grinding and sieving.</p><p num="0045">The thermosetting powder coating composition of
the invention may be used as a thermosetting clear powder
coating composition or as a thermosetting colored powder
coating composition comprising at least one pigment
selected from coloring pigments, metallic pigments and
interference pigments in the clear powder coating
composition. The thermosetting clear powder coating
composition may contain such pigments in any amount that 
the under coat will be seen through or substantially not
be seen through the coating.</p><p num="0046">The thermosetting powder coating composition of
the invention is applied to a substrate by powder coating
and baked to form a cured coating film. It is preferable
that the baking be performed at a temperature of about
120°C to about 180°C for about 10 to about 50 minutes.</p><p num="0047">The substrate to be coated may be any known
material that is powder coatable. Examples of useful
substrates are metals, surface-treated metals, plastics,
or coated these materials.</p><p num="0048">The powder coating may be performed by
conventional methods, for example, preferably
electrostatic powder coating methods or frictionally
electrified powder coating methods. There is no
limitation on the coating film thickness. However, it is
preferable for the obtained film to have a coating
thickness of about 20 to about 1,000 µm, more preferably
about 20 to about 80 µm.</p><p num="0049">The thermosetting powder coating composition of
the invention can be used for vehicles such as automobiles,
electric appliances, steel furniture, office equipment and
stationery, construction materials and the like where
conventional powder coating compositions are used.
Particularly, the thermosetting powder coating composition 
of the invention is suitable for automotive exterior
panels or interior panels where high surface smoothness of
the coating film is required.</p><p num="0050">Described below is a method for forming a
topcoat on the surface of vehicles or the like, using the
thermosetting powder coating composition of the invention.</p><p num="0051">The method for forming a topcoat using the
present invention may be a 1-coat system or a 2-coat
system. The 1-coat system comprises applying the
thermosetting powder coating composition of the invention
to metallic or plastic substrates for vehicles or the like,
or to the metallic or plastic substrates coated with a
primer such as a cationic electrocoating composition and
optionally coated with an intercoat. The 2-coat system
comprises applying a colored base coating composition to
the substrates and applying the thermosetting powder clear
coating composition of the invention to the coated
substrate.</p><p num="0052">The thermosetting powder coating composition of
the present invention produces particularly remarkable
effects, when used as a clear coating composition in the
method for forming a topcoat according to a 2-coat 1-bake
system, which comprises applying a thermosetting aqueous
colored base coating composition to a substrate, applying
a clear coating composition to the uncured surface of the 
base coat, and curing the two coats by heating.</p><p num="0053">Examples of thermosetting aqueous colored base
coating compositions preferably used are aqueous colored
coating compositions, aqueous metallic coating
compositions, aqueous interference pattern coating
compositions, aqueous colored metallic coating
compositions and aqueous colored interference pattern
coating compositions.</p><p num="0054">According to the 2-coat 1-bake coating method of
the invention, a desirable topcoat can be formed by the
method comprising the following steps:
<sl><li>i) applying an aqueous colored base coating composition
having a solids content of 10 to 60 wt.% (when applied)
to the substrate to a coating thickness of about 10 to
about 60 µm, preferably about 10 to about 40 µm, when
cured, by spray coating such as airless spray coating,
air spray coating or electrostatic coating;</li><li>ii) allowing the coated substrate to stand at room
temperature for about 1 to about 10 minutes or drying the
coated substrate at about 50°C to about 100°C for about 1
to about 10 minutes;</li><li>iii) applying the thermosetting powder clear coating
composition according to the invention to the uncured
surface of the base coat to a coating thickness of about
20 to about 100 µm, more preferably about 20 to about 80 
µm, when cured, by powder coating such as electrostatic
powder coating or frictionally electrified powder coating;
and</li><li>iv) curing the two coats (base coat and clear coat) at
the same time by heating at about 120°C to about 180°C for
about 10 to about 50 minutes.</li></sl></p><p num="0055">The aqueous colored base coating composition may
be selected from the conventional aqueous colored base
coating composition for vehicles, etc. without limitation,
of which melamine-curing aqueous colored base coating
compositions are particularly preferred.</p><p num="0056">Preferably, the melamine-curing aqueous colored
base coating composition comprises (i) a hydroxyl- and
carboxyl-containing resin and (ii) a melamine resin, as
curable resin components.</p><p num="0057">Examples of resins preferably used as the resin
(i) include hydroxyl- and carboxyl-containing acrylic
resins and polyester resins.</p><p num="0058">The hydroxyl- and carboxyl-containing acrylic
resin can be prepared by copolymerizing a hydroxyl-containing
unsaturated monomer, a carboxyl-containing
unsaturated monomer, and optionally one or more other
vinyl unsaturated monomers. Examples of useful hydroxyl-containing
unsaturated monomers are C<sub>2-20</sub> hydroxyalkyl
esters of acrylic or methacrylic acids, such as 
hydroxyethyl (meth)acrylate, hydroxypropyl (meth)acrylate
and hydroxybutyl (meth)acrylate. Example of useful
carboxyl-containing unsaturated monomers are
monocarboxylic acids such as acrylic acid and methacrylic
acid; dicarboxylic acids such as maleic acid, itaconic
acid, fumaric acid and mesaconic acid; and anhydrides of
the dicarboxylic acids or half-esterified or otherwise
modified ones. Examples of vinyl unsaturated monomers
optionally used are C<sub>1-22</sub> alkyl esters of acrylic or
methacrylic acids such as methyl (meth)acrylate, ethyl
(meth)acrylate, propyl (meth)acrylate, butyl
(meth)acrylate and hexyl (meth)acrylate; styrene,
acrylonitrile and the like. It is preferable for the
acrylic resin to have a number average molecular weight of
about 5,000 to about 100,000, particularly about 15,000 to
about 80,000. Preferably, the acrylic resin has a
hydroxyl value of about 20 to about 200 mg KOH/g,
particularly 40 to 150 mg KOH/g. It is preferable for the
acrylic resin to have an acid value of about 10 to about
150 mg KOH/g, particularly 20 to 100 mg KOH/g.</p><p num="0059">The hydroxyl- and carboxyl-containing polyester
resin can be produced by esterification reaction between
polybasic acid and polyhydric alcohol. Examples of useful
polybasic acids are phthalic acid, isophthalic acid,
terephthalic acid, succinic acid, adipic acid, azelaic 
acid, sebacic acid, tetrahydrophthalic acid,
hexahydrophthalic acid, HET acid, maleic acid, fumaric
acid, itaconic acid, trimellitic acid and anhydrides of
these acids. Examples of useful polyhydric alcohols are
ethylene glycol, propylene glycol, butylene glycol,
hexanediol, diethylene glycol, dipropylene glycol,
neopentylglycol, triethyleneglycol, glycerin,
trimethylolethane, trimethylolpropane and pentaerythritol.
It is preferable for the polyester resin to have a number
average molecular weight of about 2,000 to about 100,000,
preferably 3,000 to 80,000. Preferably, the polyester
resin has a hydroxyl value of about 30 to 120 mg KOH/g,
particularly 50 to 80 mg KOH/g. It is preferable for the
polyester resin to have an acid value of about 15 to about
100 mg KOH/g, particularly 30 to 50 mg KOH/g.</p><p num="0060">Resins preferably used as the melamine resin
(ii), which is a curing agent, are partially or fully
etherified methylol melamine resins prepared by the method
described below and having 1 to 5 triazine rings in one
molecule and having a molecular weight of about 300 to
about 3,000, particularly 500 to 2,000. The method for
preparing the partially or fully etherified methylol
melamine resin comprises partially or fully methylolating
a melamine resin and partially or fully etherifying the
methylol groups of the melamine resin using a C<sub>1-8</sub> alcohol, 
such as methanol, ethanol, propanol or butanol. The
melamine resin may be hydrophobic or hydrophilic.</p><p num="0061">The aqueous colored base coating composition may
contain, in addition to the components (i) and (ii), at
least one pigment selected from the group consisting of
coloring pigments, metallic pigments and interference
pigments. The aqueous colored base coating composition
may further contain oxazoline-containing compounds,
extenders, organic solvents, catalysts, sedimentation
inhibitors, UV absorbers, etc.</p><p num="0062">In the case of conventional thermosetting powder
coating compositions, when surface smoothness of the
coating film is improved, other coating properties such as
weather resistance, solvent resistance and acid resistance
are impaired. On the other hand, when these coating
properties are improved, surface smoothness of the coating
film is reduced. It has been difficult to achieve a
proper balance therebetween. When the conventional
thermosetting powder coating compositions are used as
clear coating compositions in 2-coat 1-bake systems using
aqueous base coating compositions, such problems develop
to a serious level. Therefore, it has been difficult to
form a topcoat that excels in both surface smoothness and
the above-mentioned other coating properties.</p><p num="0063">In contrast to the conventional compositions, 
the thermosetting powder coating composition of the
present invention comprises, in addition to an epoxy-containing
resin, a curing agent containing acid anhydride
groups and carboxyl groups in specific proportions. The
powder coating composition comprising such a specific
curing agent is cured after being fully melted and flowed
and therefore excels in both surface smoothness and other
properties of the coating film, even when used as a clear
coating composition in 2-coat 1-bake systems using aqueous
base coating compositions, thus achieving remarkable
effects.</p><p num="0064">The thermosetting powder coating composition of
the present invention comprises, as a curing agent for the
epoxy-containing resin, an acid anhydride (a) having a
carboxyl group at one end and a specific ester group at
the other end and containing a straight chain acid
anhydride group in the main chain, and thereby achieves
the following effects.
<sl><li>(1) The acid anhydride (a) before heating has only one
carboxyl group and therefore, the powder coating
composition does not cure during storage, thus being free
of the problems of decreased fluidity after storage and
impaired surface smoothness of the coating.</li><li>(2) At an early stage in the heating process, the acid
anhydride (a) has only one carboxyl group reactable with 
the epoxy-containing organic resin (A) and therefore, the
powder coating composition does not cure but fully melts
and flows, thus providing a coating film with excellent
surface smoothness.</li><li>(3) After the powder coating composition sufficiently
flows and forms a coating film as described above in (2),
the carboxyl group of acid anhydride (a) reacts with the
epoxy-containing resin (A) and the resulting hydroxyl
group and acid anhydride group react with each other to
generate a carboxyl group which reacts with the epoxy-containing
resin (A) to thereby provide a coating with
high crosslinking density. Therefore, the powder coating
composition provides a coating film with excellent
finished appearance such as surface smoothness and
excellent coating properties such as weather resistance,
solvent resistance, acid resistance, etc.</li></sl></p><p num="0065">The present invention will be described below in
more detail with reference to Preparation Examples,
Examples and Comparative Examples, wherein the parts and
percentages are all by weight unless otherwise specified.</p><heading>Preparation Example 1</heading><heading>Preparation of epoxy-containing resin (A-1) for powder
coating composition</heading><p num="0066">60 parts of toluene was placed in a reactor
equipped with a thermometer, a thermostat, a stirrer, a 
condenser and a dropping device, and heated to 105°C while
blowing nitrogen gas thereinto. A mixture of 15 parts of
styrene, 30 parts of methyl methacrylate, 20 parts of iso-butyl
methacrylate, 35 parts of glycidyl methacrylate and
4 parts of azobisisobutylonitrile was added dropwise over
a period of about 3 hours. After completion of the
addition, the mixture was allowed to stand at 105°C for 1
hour. Further, a mixture of 0.5 part of
azobisisobutylonitrile and 10 parts of toluene was added
dropwise over a period of 1 hour. After completion of the
addition, the mixture was allowed to stand at 105°C for 1
hour, thus completing the copolymerization reaction. The
solvent was then removed from the reaction system under
reduced pressure, thus giving an epoxy-containing resin
(A-1). The resin obtained had a glass transition
temperature of 54°C and a number average molecular weight
of 3,500.</p><heading>Preparation Example 2</heading><heading>Preparation of epoxy-containing resin (A-2) for powder
coating composition</heading><p num="0067">An epoxy-containing resin (A-2) was prepared in
the same manner as in Preparation Example 1 with the
exception of using, as monomers, 15 parts of styrene, 40
parts of methyl methacrylate, 30 parts of iso-butyl
methacrylate and 15 parts of glycidyl methacrylate. The 
resin obtained had a glass transition temperature of 52°C
and a number average molecular weight of 3,600.</p><heading>Preparation Example 3</heading><heading>Preparation of epoxy-containing resin (A-3) for powder
coating composition</heading><p num="0068">An epoxy-containing resin (A-3) was prepared in
the same manner as in Preparation Example 1 with the
exception of using, as monomers, 15 parts of styrene, 5
parts of methyl methacrylate and 80 parts of glycidyl
methacrylate. The resin obtained had a glass transition
temperature of 43°C and a number average molecular weight
of 3,700.</p><heading>Preparation Example 4</heading><heading>Preparation of curing agent (B-1)</heading><p num="0069">230 parts of dodecanoic diacid and 87 parts of
acetic anhydride were placed in a reactor equipped with a
thermometer, a thermostat, a stirrer and a condenser, and
heated to 170°C with stirring while distilling off acetic
acid. After the distillation of acetic acid had ceased,
pressure was reduced to 30 mmHg at 170°C, followed by
cooling the reaction mixture to 100°C. 0.8 part of
methanol was added dropwise over a period of 1 hour and an
esterification reaction was further allowed to proceed for
1 hour, followed by cooling the reaction mixture, thus
giving a curing agent (B-1). </p><p num="0070">The curing agent (B-1) was a solid mixture of
acid anhydride (a), acid anhydride (b) and dibasic acid
(c) and had a melting point of 82°C. The mixture was
composed of the compounds of the formulas (1), (2) and (3)
wherein R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> are methyl, m, p and r are an integer of
10, and n, q and s (polymerization degree) are 2.7 on
average (determined by <sup>1</sup>H-NMR analysis).</p><heading>Preparation Examples 5-17</heading><heading>Preparation of curing agents (B-2) to (B-14)</heading><p num="0071">Curing agents (B-2) to (B-14) were prepared in a
similar manner as in Preparation Example 4, using the
starting materials shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Preparation Example 18</heading><heading>Preparation of curing agent (B-15)</heading><p num="0072">230 parts of dodecanoic diacid and 87 parts of
acetic anhydride were placed in a reactor equipped with a
thermometer, a thermostat, a stirrer and a condenser, and
heated to 170°C with stirring while distilling off acetic
acid. After the distillation of acetic acid had ceased,
pressure was reduced to 30 mmHg at 170°C, followed by
cooling the reaction mixture, thus giving a curing agent
(B-15).</p><p num="0073">The curing agent (B-15) obtained was an acid
anhydride group-containing dibasic acid (c) in the form of
a solid and had a melting point of 87°C. The dibasic acid 
was an acid anhydride of the formula (3) wherein r is 10,
s (polymerization degree) is 4.1 on average (determined by
<sup>1</sup>H-NMR analysis) and had carboxyl groups at both ends.</p><p num="0074">Table 1 shows the starting material compositions,
melting points (°C), contents and structures of the curing
agents (B-1) to (B-15). <img file="00350001.tif" id="img-EP-1134802-A3-00350001" he="214" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00360001.tif" id="img-EP-1134802-A3-00360001" he="189" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><heading>Example 1</heading><heading>Preparation of powder coating composition 1 of the present
invention</heading><p num="0075">100 parts of an epoxy-containing resin (A-1),
38.6 parts of an curing agent (B-1) and 0.5 part of
benzoin (as an antipopping agent) were dry-blended at room
temperature using a Henschel mixer. The blend of the
components was fused and kneaded in an extruder, cooled,
finely ground in a pin disc mill and passed through a 150-mesh
sieve, giving a thermosetting powder coating
composition of the invention. In the curing agent (B-1),
the molar ratio of carboxyl groups to acid anhydride
groups was 0.72, and the molar ratio of ester groups to
the total of carboxyl groups and acid anhydride groups was
0.020.</p><p num="0076">In this composition, the molar ratio of the
total of carboxyl groups and acid anhydride groups in the
curing agent (B-1) to epoxy groups in the epoxy-containing
resin (A-1) was 0.9:1.</p><heading>Examples 2-8 and Comparative Examples 1-12</heading><heading>Preparation of powder coating compositions 2-8 of the
present invention and comparative powder coating
compositions 1-12</heading><p num="0077">Thermosetting powder coating compositions 2-8 of
the present invention and comparative thermosetting powder 
coating compositions 1-12 were prepared in the same manner
as in Example 1, blending components in various
proportions as shown in Table 2. In the compositions, the
molar ratio of the total of carboxyl groups and acid
anhydride groups in the curing agent (B) to epoxy groups
in the epoxy-containing resin (A) was all 0.9:1. In Table
2, the amounts of components are expressed in &quot;parts by
weight&quot;. <img file="00390001.tif" id="img-EP-1134802-A3-00390001" he="247" wi="115" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00400001.tif" id="img-EP-1134802-A3-00400001" he="250" wi="112" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00410001.tif" id="img-EP-1134802-A3-00410001" he="215" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><heading>Preparation Example 19</heading><heading>Preparation of aqueous base coating composition</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of aqueous acrylic resin (C-1)</heading><p num="0078">70 parts of butyl cellosolve was placed in a
reactor equipped with a thermometer, a thermostat, a stirrer,
a condenser and a dropping device, and heated to 115°C while
blowing nitrogen gas thereinto. A mixture of 30 parts of
styrene, 15 parts of methyl methacrylate, 16.7 parts of n-butyl
acrylate, 20 parts of 2-ethylhexyl acrylate, 12 parts of
hydroxyethyl methacrylate, 6.3 parts of acrylic acid and 1
part of azobisisobutylonitrile was added dropwise over a
period of about 3 hours. After completion of the addition,
the mixture was allowed to stand at 115°C for 1 hour. A
mixture of 0.3 part of azobisisobutylonitrile and 10 parts of
butyl cellosolve was further added over a period of 1 hour.
After completion of the addition, the mixture was allowed to
stand at 115°C for 1 hour to complete the copolymerization
reaction, giving a carboxyl- and hydroxyl-containing acrylic
resin solution with a solids content of 65%. The acrylic
resin had an acid value of 50 mg KOH/g, a hydroxyl value of 50
mg KOH/g, a number average molecular weight of 45,000. The
carboxyl group of the acrylic resin was neutralized with an
equivalent amount of dimethylaminoethanol and diluted with
water, thus giving an acrylic resin (C-1) aqueous solution
having a solids content of 55%. </p><heading>(2) Preparation of water-dispersible polyester resin (C-2)</heading><p num="0079">35.95 parts of neopentylglycol, 11.68 parts of
trimethylolpropane, 25.34 parts of phthalic anhydride and
31.24 parts of adipic acid were placed in a reactor equipped
with a thermometer, a thermostat, a stirrer, a Dean-Stark
water separator and a condenser. The mixture was heated to
230°C over a period of 3 hours while distilling off water. A
small amount of xylene was added and a reaction was continued
under reflux for 5 hours while distilling off water using the
water separator. Then 6.57 parts of trimellitic anhydride was
added and a reaction was allowed to proceed at 180°C for 1
hour. Butyl cellosolve was added, giving a carboxyl- and
hydroxyl-containing polyester resin solution having a nonvolatile
content of 70%. The resin obtained had an acid value
of 40 mg KOH/g, a hydroxyl value of 80 mg KOH/g, a number
average molecular weight of 6,000. The polyester resin
solution was neutralized with an equivalent amount of
dimethylaminoethanol, followed by addition of deionized water,
thus giving a polyester resin (C-2) emulsion having a solids
content of 35%.</p><heading>(3) Melamine resin (C-3)</heading><p num="0080">A butyl etherified methylol melamine resin &quot;U-Van
28-60&quot; (product of Mitsui Chemicals, Inc., trade name) was
used as melamine resin (C-3).</p><heading>(4) Metallic pigment</heading><p num="0081">&quot;Alpaste #7680&quot; (product of Toyo Aluminum K.K.,
trade name) was used as a metallic pigment.</p><heading>(5) Blue organic pigment</heading><p num="0082">&quot;Heliogen Blue L6900&quot; (product of BASF, trade name,
Cyanine Blue) was used as a blue organic pigment.</p><heading>(6) Preparation of aqueous base coating composition</heading><p num="0083">A thermosetting aqueous colored base coating
composition was prepared by mixing and dispersing 45 parts
(solids) of the aqueous acrylic resin (C-1), 30 parts (solids)
of the water-dispersible polyester resin (C-2), 25 parts of
the melamine resin (C-3), 10 parts of the metallic pigment and
2 parts of the blue organic pigment.</p><heading>Examples 9-16 and Comparative Examples 13-24</heading><p num="0084">Coated panels I and II were prepared by a method
for forming a topcoat according to a 2-coat 1-bake system
using, as clear coating compositions, thermosetting powder
coating compositions 1-8 of the present invention obtained in
Examples 1-8 and comparative thermosetting powder coating
compositions 1-12 obtained in Comparative Examples 1-12, as
shown below.</p><heading>(1) Preparation of coated panel I (using a solvent-based base
coating composition)</heading><p num="0085">A dull steel panel of 0.8 mm thickness treated by
chemical conversion with zinc phosphate was coated with an
epoxy-based cationic electrodepositable coating composition by 
electrocoating to form a coat of 20 µm thickness (when baked).
The coated panel was baked and further coated by air spray
coating with an alkyd resin/amino resin solvent-based
intercoating surfacer for automobiles to form a coat of 20 µm
thickness (when cured). The coated panel was baked at 140°C
for 20 minutes, wet sanded with #400 sandpaper and dehydrated
for drying, giving a test substrate.</p><p num="0086">&quot;Magicron Basecoat HM-22&quot; (product of Kansai Paint
Co., Ltd., a metallic coating composition, trade name) was
applied to the test substrate to form a coat of about 15 µm
thickness (when cured), and cured by baking at 140°C for 30
minutes in a dryer. Each powder coating composition prepared
above was applied to the base coated substrate by
electrostatic coating to form a coat of about 70 µm thickness
(when cured). The coat was cured by heating in a dryer at
160°C for 30 minutes, thus forming a topcoat according to a 2-coat
2-bake system.</p><heading>(2) Preparation of coated panel II (using an aqueous base
coating composition)</heading><p num="0087">A dull steel panel of 0.8 mm thickness treated by
chemical conversion with zinc phosphate was coated with an
epoxy-based cationic electrodepositable coating composition by
electrocoating to form a coat of 20 µm thickness (when baked).
The coated panel was baked and further coated by air spray
coating with an alkyd resin/amino resin solvent-based 
intercoating surfacer for automobiles to form a coat of 25 µm
thickness (when cured). The coated panel was baked at 140°C
for 30 minutes, wet sanded with #400 sandpaper, dehydrated for
drying, and degreased by wiping with petroleum benzine, giving
a test substrate.</p><p num="0088">The thermosetting aqueous colored base coating
composition obtained in Preparation Example 19 was adjusted to
a viscosity of 45 seconds (Fordcup #4/20°C), and applied to
the test substrate by air spray coating to a thickness of 15±3
µm (when cured), followed by drying at 70°C for 10 minutes.
Each powder coating composition prepared above was applied to
the uncured coated surface by electrostatic coating to form a
coat of about 70 µm thickness (when cured). The coated
substrate was heated at 160°C for 30 minutes to cure the two
coats (base coat and clear coat) at the same time, thus
forming a topcoat according to a 2-coat 1-bake system.</p><p num="0089">The topcoats of the multi-layer coat thus formed
were tested for finished appearance and coating properties.
The finished appearance was observed by the naked eye and
tested for centerline average surface roughness (Ra), popping,
whiteness (IV value) and flip-flop effect. The coating
properties were tested for acid resistance, gasoline
resistance and xylene resistance. The test methods are shown
below.</p><heading>Finished appearance of coat observed by the naked eye:</heading><p num="0090">The appearance of the coat was evaluated for gloss
and surface smoothness according to the following criteria:
<sl><li>A: Good appearance</li><li>B: Slightly poor appearance</li><li>C: Poor appearance.</li></sl></p><heading>Centerline average surface roughness Ra:</heading><p num="0091">The centerline average surface roughness Ra (µm) of
the coat was determined using a surface roughness measuring
device (&quot;Surfcom&quot;, trade name, product of Tokyo Seimitsu Co.,
Ltd.). The smaller the value is, the higher the surface
smoothness is.</p><heading>Popping:</heading><p num="0092">The surface of the coat was observed by the naked
eye and checked for cratering due to foaming, etc. The
degrees of cratering were evaluated according to the following
criteria:
<sl><li>A: No cratering; exhibiting high surface smoothness</li><li>B: Small cratering; exhibiting slightly low surface
smoothness</li><li>C: Large and many cratering; exhibiting significantly low
surface smoothness.</li></sl></p><heading>Whiteness (IV value) and flip-flop effect (FF value):</heading><p num="0093">The IV value and flip-flop effect (FF value) of the
coat were determined using &quot;ALCOPELMR-100&quot; (trade name, a
product of Fuji Kogyo Co., Ltd.). These measurements 
demonstrate finished appearance in the following aspects. IV
value is an index of whiteness achieved by aluminium flakes in
the coating film. The more closely metallic flakes are
oriented to be parallel to the coating surface, the whiter the
flakes look, thereby achieving a higher IV value. Flip-flop
effect (FF value) is a degree of change in brilliancy
depending on the angle of view. The more closely metallic
flakes are oriented to be parallel to the coating surface, the
greater brilliancy varies even with a slight change in the
angle of view, thereby achieving a higher FF value.</p><heading>Acid resistance:</heading><p num="0094">0.4 ml of a 40% sulfuric acid solution was applied
dropwise to the coated panel, followed by heating on a hot
plate at 85°C for 15 minutes. After washing the coated panel
with water, the surface of the coated panel was observed by
the naked eye and evaluated according to the following
criteria:
<sl><li>A: No change; exhibiting high resistance to acid</li><li>B: A difference in film thickness between the solution-applied
portion and the controlled (unapplied)
portion; exhibiting slightly poor resistance to acid</li><li>C: Blushing on the coating surface; exhibiting poor
resistance to acid.</li></sl></p><heading>Gasoline resistance:</heading><p num="0095">The coated panel was immersed in automobile 
gasoline (JIS K 2202) for 2 hours. The surface of the coat
was observed by the naked eye and evaluated according to the
following criteria;
<sl><li>A: Free of blisters and blushing; exhibiting good
resistance to gasoline</li><li>B: Slight blistering or blushing; exhibiting slightly
poor resistance to gasoline</li><li>C: Marked blistering and dulling; exhibiting poor
resistance to gasoline.</li></sl></p><heading>Xylene resistance:</heading><p num="0096">0.5 ml of xylene was dropped onto the coated panel,
and the coated panel was left to stand at room temperature for
30 minutes. After wiping the xylene off with a gauze, the
surface of the coating was observed by the naked eye and
evaluated according to the following criteria;
<dl tsize="2" compact="compact"><dt>A:</dt><dd>No spots; exhibiting good resistance to xylene</dd><dt>B:</dt><dd>The outline of spots visually detected; exhibiting
poor resistance to xylene</dd><dt>C:</dt><dd>Marked swelling on the spots; exhibiting extremely
poor resistance to xylene.</dd></dl></p><p num="0097">Table 3 shows the test results. <img file="00500001.tif" id="img-EP-1134802-A3-00500001" he="230" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00510001.tif" id="img-EP-1134802-A3-00510001" he="224" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Duroplastische Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung, umfassend:
<claim-text><claim-text>(A) ein Epoxidharz und</claim-text><claim-text>(B) ein Härtungsmittel, das als wesentlichen Inhaltsstoff ein Säureanhydrid (a)
enthält, dargestellt durch die Formel
HOOC-(CH2)m-[COO-CO-(CH2)m]n-COOR1
worin R1 eine einwertige, gesättigte C1-10-Kohlenwasserstoff-Gruppe darstellt,
m eine ganze Zahl von 6 bis 18 ist, und n durchschnittlich eine Zahl von 2 bis
12 ist;</claim-text></claim-text>
wobei das Molverhältnis der Carboxylgruppen zu den Säureanhydridgruppen
im Härtungsmittel im Bereich von 0,15 : 1 bis 2,0 : 1 liegt;
   wobei das Molverhältnis der COOR1-Gruppen im Härtungsmittel (B) zur
Gesamtheit der Carboxylgruppen und Säureanhydridgruppen im Härtungsmittel
(B) im Bereich von 0,01 : 1 bis 0,1 : 1 liegt, und
wobei das Molverhältnis der Gesamtheit der Carboxylgruppen und Säureanhydridgruppen
im Härtungsmittel (B) zu den Epoxidgruppen im epoxidhaltigen
Harz (A) im Bereich von 0,7 : 1 bis 1,2 : 1 liegt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung nach Anspruch 1, wobei das epoxidhaltige
Harz (A) ein epoxidhaltiges Copolymer ist, das durch Copolymerisieren
eines epoxidhaltigen Vinylmonomers und mindestens eines weiteren polymerisierbaren
Vinylmonomers hergestellt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung nach Anspruch 2, wobei das epoxidhaltige
Harz (A) zu 20 bis 70 Gew.-% aus einem epoxidhaltigen Vinylmonomer
besteht, das eine Monomerkomponente des epoxidhaltigen Copolymers darstellt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung nach Anspruch 1, wobei das epoxidhaltige
Harz (A) eine Glasübergangstemperatur von 40 °C bis 80 °C aufweist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung nach Anspruch 1, wobei das epoxidhaltige
Harz (A) ein Zahlenmittel des Molekulargewichts von 1000 bis 10 000
aufweist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung nach Anspruch 1, wobei das Härtungsmittel
(B) Säureanhydrid (a) und mindestens eine Spezies enthält, die ausgewähltist
aus der Gruppe bestehend aus Säureanhydrid (b) und zweibasiger Säure (c);
wobei das Säureanhydrid (b) durch die Formel
R2OOC-(CH2)p-[COO-CO-(CH2)p]q-COOR2
dargestellt wird, worin R2 eine einwertige, gesättigte C1-10-Kohlenwasserstoff-Gruppe
darstellt; p eine ganze Zahl von 6 bis 18 ist, und q eine durchschnittliche
Zahl von 1 bis 20 ist; und wobei die zweibasige Säure (c) durch die Formel
HOOC-(CH2)r-[COO-CO-(CH2)r]s-COOH
dargestellt wird, worin r eine ganze Zahl von 6 bis 18 ist, und s eine durchschnittliche
Zahl von 0 bis 20 ist;
wobei das Molverhältnis der Gesamtheit der COOR1-Gruppen und COOR2-Gruppen
im Härtungsmittel (B) zur Gesamtheit der Carboxylgruppen und Säureanhydridgruppen
im Härtungsmittel (B) im Bereich von 0,01 : 1 bis 0,1 : 1 liegt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung nach Anspruch 1, wobei das Säureanhydrid
(a) im Härtungsmittel (B) einen Schmelzpunkt von 60 °C oder höher
aufweist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung nach Anspruch 6, wobei das Säureanhydrid
(b) und die zweibasige Säure (c) im Härtungsmittel (B) Schmelzpunkte
von 60 °C oder höher aufweisen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung nach Anspruch 6, wobei die Mischung
aus Säureanhydrid (a) mit Säureanhydrid (b) und/oder zweibasiger Säure (c) einen
Schmelzpunkt von 60 ° oder höher aufweist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zur Bildung eines Decklacks gemäß einem 2 x Beschichten/1 x Brennen-System,
die Schritte umfassend: Auftragen einer wäßrigen, farbigen Grundbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung
auf ein Substrat, Auftragen einer klaren Beschichtungs-Zusammensetzung
auf die ungehärtete Oberfläche der Grundbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung
und Härten der beiden Überzüge durch Erwärmen,
wobei die klare Beschichtungs-Zusammensetzung die duroplastische
Pulverbeschichtungs-Zusammensetzung nach Anspruch 1 ist.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A thermosetting powder coating composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(A) an epoxy-resin; and</claim-text><claim-text>(B) a curing agent containing, as an essential ingredient, an acid anhydride (a)
represented by the formula
HOOC - (CH2)m - [COO - CO - (CH2)m]n - COOR1
wherein R1 represents a C1-10 monovalent saturated hydrocarbon group, m is an
integer of 6 to 18, and n is a number of 2 to 12 on average;
the molar ratio of carboxyl groups to acid anhydride groups in the curing agent
being in the range from 0.15 : 1 to 2.0 : 1;the molar ratio of COOR1 groups in the curing agent (B) to the total of carboxyl
groups and acid anhydride groups in the curing agent (B) being in the range from
0.01 : 1 to 0.1 : 1; and
the molar ratio of the total of carboxyl groups and acid anhydride groups in the
curing agent (B) to epoxy groups in the epoxy-containing resin (A) being in the
range from 0.7 : 1 to 1.2 : 1.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The powder coating composition according to claim 1 wherein the epoxy-containing
resin (A) is an epoxy-containing copolymer prepared by
copolymerizing an epoxy-containing vinyl monomer and at least one other
polymerizable vinyl monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The powder coating composition according to claim 2 wherein the epoxy-containing
resin (A) comprises 20 to 70 % weight of an epoxy-containing vinyl
monomer as a monomer component of the epoxy-containing copolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The powder coating composition according to claim 1 wherein the epoxy-containing
resin (A) has a glass transition temperature of 40 °C to 80 °C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The powder coating composition according to claim 1 wherein the epoxy-containing
resin (A) has a number average molecular weight of 1,000 to 10,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The powder coating composition according to claim 1 wherein the curing agent
(B) contains acid anhydride (a) and at least one species selected from the group
consisting of acid anhydride (b) and dibasic acid (c), the acid anhydride (b) being
represented by the formula
R2OOC - (CH2)p - [COO - CO - (CH2)p]q - COOR2
wherein R2 represents a C1-10 monovalent saturated hydrocarbon group; p is an
integer of 6 to 18; and q is a number of 1 to 20 on average; and
the dibasic acid (c) being represented by the formula
HOOC - (CH2)r - [COO - CO - (CH2)r]s - COOH
wherein r is an integer of 6 to 18; and s is a number of 0 to 20 on average;
the molar ratio of the total of COOR1 groups and COOR2 groups in the curing
agent (B) to the total of carboxyl groups and acid anhydride groups in the curing
agent (B) being in the range from 0.01 : 1 to 0.1 : 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The powder coating composition according to claim 1 wherein the acid
anhydride (a) in the curing agent (B) has a melting point of 60 °C or higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The powder coating composition according to claim 6 wherein the acid
anhydride (b) and dibasic acid (c) in the curing agent (B) have melting points of
60 °C or higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The powder coating composition according to claim 6 wherein the mixture of
acid anhydride (a) with acid anhydride (b) and/or dibasic acid (c) has a melting
point of 60 °C or higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method for forming a topcoat according to a 2-coat 1-bake system comprising
the steps of applying to a substrate a thermosetting aqueous coloured base coating
composition, applying to the uncured surface of the base coat a clear coating
composition, and curing the two coats by heating, wherein the clear coating
composition is the thermosetting powder coating composition defined in claim 1.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Composition de revêtement pulvérulente
thermodurcissable comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>(A) une résine époxy ; et</claim-text><claim-text>(B) un agent de vulcanisation contenant, comme
ingrédient essentiel, un anhydride d'acide (a) représenté
par la formule
HOOC- (CH2)m- [COO-CO- (CH2)m]n-COOR1
   dans laquelle R1 représente un groupe hydrocarbure
monovalent saturé en C1-10, m est un entier de 6 à 18 et n
est un nombre de 2 à 12 en moyenne ;
   le rapport molaire des groupes carboxyle aux groupes
anhydride d'acide dans l'agent de vulcanisation étant
dans la gamme de 0,15/1 à 2,0/1 ;
   le rapport molaire des groupes COOR1 dans l'agent de
vulcanisation (B) au total des groupes carboxyle et des
groupes anhydride d'acide dans l'agent de vulcanisation
(B) étant dans la gamme de 0,01/1 à 0,1/1 ; et
   le rapport molaire du total des groupes carboxyle et
des groupes anhydride d'acide dans l'agent de
vulcanisation (B) aux groupes époxy dans la résine
contenant un époxy (A) étant dans la gamme de 0,7/1 à
1,2/1.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Composition de revêtement pulvérulente selon la
revendication 1, dans laquelle la résine contenant un
époxy (A) est un copolymère contenant un époxy préparé
par copolymérisation d'un monomère de vinyle contenant un
époxy et au moins un autre monomère de vinyle
polymérisable.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Composition de revêtement pulvérulente selon la
revendication 2, dans laquelle la résine contenant un
époxy (A) comporte 20 à 70 % en poids d'un monomère de
vinyle contenant un époxy en tant que composé monomère du
copolymère contenant un époxy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Composition de revêtement pulvérulente selon la
revendication 1, dans laquelle la résine contenant un
époxy (A) a une température de transition vitreuse de
40° C à 80° C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Composition de revêtement pulvérulente selon la
revendication 1, dans laquelle la résine contenant un
époxy (A) a un poids moléculaire moyen en nombre de 1 000
à 10 000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Composition de revêtement pulvérulente selon la
revendication 1, dans laquelle l'agent de vulcanisation
(B) contient un anhydride d'acide (a) et au moins une
espèce choisie dans le groupe constitué d'anhydride
d'acide (b) et d'acide dibasique (c) ; l'anhydride
d'acide (b) étant représenté par la formule
R2OOC-(CH2)p-[COO-CO(CH2)p]q-COOR2
   dans laquelle R2 représente un groupe hydrocarbure
monovalent saturé en C1-10 ; p est un entier de 6 à 18 ;
et q est un nombre de 1 à 20 en moyenne ; et
   l'acide dibasique (c) étant représenté par la
formule
HOOC-(CH2)r-[COO-CO-(CH2)r]s-COOH
   dans laquelle r est un entier de 6 à 18 ; et s est
un nombre de 0 à 20 en moyenne ;
   le rapport molaire du total des groupes COOR1 et des
groupes COOR2 dans l'agent de vulcanisation (B) au total
des groupes carboxyle et des groupes anhydride d'acide
dans l'agent de vulcanisation (B) étant dans la gamme de
0,01/1 à 0,1/1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Composition de revêtement pulvérulente selon la
revendication 1, dans laquelle l'anhydride d'acide (a)
dans l'agent de vulcanisation (B) a un point de fusion de
60° C ou plus.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Composition de revêtement pulvérulente selon la
revendication 6, dans laquelle l'anhydride d'acide (b) et
l'acide dibasique (c) dans l'agent de vulcanisation (B)
ont des points de fusion de 60° C ou plus.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Composition de revêtement pulvérulente selon la
revendication 6, dans laquelle le mélange d'anhydride
d'acide (a) avec l'anhydride d'acide (b) et/ou l'acide
dibasique (c) a un point de fusion de 60° C ou plus.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de préparation d'une couche de finition
selon un système 2 couches et 1 cuisson comprenant les
étapes consistant à appliquer à un substrat une
composition de revêtement de base colorée, aqueuse et
thermodurcissable, à appliquer à la surface non
vulcanisée de la couche de base une composition de
revêtement transparente, et à vulcaniser les deux couches
par chauffage, la composition de revêtement transparente
étant la composition de revêtement pulvérulente
thermodurcissable définie dans la revendication 1.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20040310"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031222</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20031205"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20030424"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60100123</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030424</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20030319"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20030319"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20020605"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE FR GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20020417"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020301</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20011212"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20011012</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010912"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010912"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>
