<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1127563-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1127563" kind="B1" date="20050427"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23216770" ucid="EP-1127563-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1127563</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20050427</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01104292-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01104292</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010222</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000052587-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000052587</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000228</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000094230-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000094230</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000330</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20041018</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61F  13/15        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61F  13/15        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61F13/15B1D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61F13/15E2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61F13/15J</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Blatt für einen absorbierenden Artikel und absorbierender Artikel mit einem solchen Blatt</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Sheet for absorbent article and absorbent article using the same</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Couvrez pour l'article absorbant et l'article absorbant en utilisant la même chose</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KAO CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KAO CORPORATION</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>TANAKA MASAHITO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KANEDA MANABU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAKANISHI MINORU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KOMORI YASUHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>TANEICHI SHOICHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>FUKUHARA YAYOI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAGAHARA SHINSUKE</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KIGATA TETSUYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>TANAKA, MASAHITO</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KANEDA, MANABU</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAKANISHI, MINORU</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KOMORI, YASUHIRO</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>FUKUHARA, YAYOI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>TANEICHI, SHOICHI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KIGATA, TETSUYUKI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAGAHARA, SHINSUKE</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>TANAKA, MASAHITO</last-name><address><street>c/o Kao Corp., Research Laborat., 2606, Akabane</street><city>Ichikai-machi, Haga-gun, Tochigi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KOMORI, YASUHIRO</last-name><address><street>c/o Kao Corp., Research Laborat., 2606, Akabane</street><city>Ichikai-machi, Haga-gun, Tochigi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KANEDA, MANABU</last-name><address><street>c/o Kao Corp., Research Laborat., 2606, Akabane</street><city>Ichikai-machi, Haga-gun, Tochigi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>NAKANISHI, MINORU</last-name><address><street>c/o Kao Corp., Research Laborat., 2606, Akabane</street><city>Ichikai-machi, Haga-gun, Tochigi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>FUKUHARA, YAYOI</last-name><address><street>c/o Kao Corp., Research Laborat., 2606, Akabane</street><city>Ichikai-machi, Haga-gun, Tochigi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>TANEICHI, SHOICHI</last-name><address><street>c/o Kao Corp., Research Laborat., 2606, Akabane</street><city>Ichikai-machi, Haga-gun, Tochigi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KIGATA, TETSUYUKI</last-name><address><street>c/o Kao Corp., Research Laborat., 2606, Akabane</street><city>Ichikai-machi, Haga-gun, Tochigi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>NAGAHARA, SHINSUKE</last-name><address><street>c/o Kao Corp., Research Laborat., 2606, Akabane</street><city>Ichikai-machi, Haga-gun, Tochigi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KAO CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>14-10, Nihonbashi Kayaba-cho, 1-chome</street><city>Chuo-ku Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Grünecker, Kinkeldey, Stockmair &amp;amp; Schwanhäusser Anwaltssozietät</last-name><address><street>Maximilianstrasse 58</street><city>80538 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>A sheet which gives an absorbent article improved recovery from distortion is disclosed. The sheet has a recovery force of 0.7 cN or more in the cross direction, a compressive strength of 100 cN or less, and a basis weight of 20 g/m&lt;2&gt; or more. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">A sheet which gives an absorbent article improved recovery from distortion is
disclosed. The sheet has a recovery force of 0.7 cN or more in the cross direction, a
compressive strength of 100 cN or less, and a basis weight of 20 g/m<sup>2</sup> or more.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1127391-A1-00000001" he="98" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><heading>Field of the Invention:</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a sheet for absorbent articles. More particularly, it
relates to a sheet which can provide absorbent articles, such as sanitary napkins, panty liners,
and adult incontinence pads, which are prevented from distortion while worn, have an
improved fit to a wearer's body, and hardly cause leakage. The present invention also relates
to an absorbent article using the same.</p><heading>Description of the Related Art:</heading><p num="0002">Various types of sheets for use in absorbent articles have been proposed aiming at
preventing absorbent articles from distortion. For example, <ref type="patent">Japanese Patent Laid-Open No.
24289/96</ref> proposes using nonwoven fabric comprising hollow synthetic fibers having a
specific average diameter as a material making an absorbent member to provide an absorbent
article resistant to distortion. While the proposed nonwoven fabric is capable of producing a
cushioning effect in the thickness direction, it fails to improve resistance to distortion in the
planar direction, still involving reduction in fit to a wearer's body and in leakproofness due to
the distortion. <ref type="patent">EP 0 858 791 A2</ref> discloses an absorbent article comprising thermally
fusible fibers <ref type="patent">US 5,591,150</ref> discloses an absorbent article having a body conforming
portion or component.</p><p num="0003">Various improvements have been added to absorbent articles for improving resistance
to distortion and preventing leakage, such as use of nonwoven fabric comprising fibers having
elasticity recovery properties (<ref type="patent">24289/96 <i>supra</i></ref>) and disposition of a second sheet having a
high rate of absorption between a topsheet and an absorbent member (<ref type="patent">Japanese Patent Laid-Open
No. 192259/99</ref>). However, none of the absorbent articles heretofore proposed is not
sufficient for prevention of distortion while it is worn, which has led to loss of fit to-a wearer's
body and leakproofness.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0004">An object of the present invention is to provide a sheet for an absorbent article which,
when used in an absorbent article, is capable of effectively preventing the absorbent article
from being distorted or twisted in the planar direction as worn thereby securing comfort, a 
good fit to a wearer's body, and leakproofness; a process of producing the sheet; and an
absorbent article using the same.</p><p num="0005">The inventors of the present invention have found that a sheet exhibiting excellent
recovery in a specific direction, when used in an absorbent article, is effective to prevent
distortion of the article.</p><p num="0006">The present invention, completed based on the above finding, includes first to third
aspects. The first aspect of the present invention relates to a sheet that can provide an
absorbent article with improved recovery from distortion, which sheet has a recovery force of
0.7 cN or more in the cross direction (CD), a compressive strength of 100 cN or less, and a
basis weight of 20 g/m<sup>2</sup> or more.</p><p num="0007">The second aspect of the present invention relates to a process of producing a sheet for
an absorbent article, which sheet comprises thermally bonded nonwoven fabric comprising
70% by weight or more of specific core-sheath type thermally bonding conjugate fibers,
which are thermally fused together at their intersections, wherein the process includes a step
of heat treating a fiber web and a step of compressing (a) the fiber web before being heat-treated
or (b) a thermally bonded nonwoven fabric obtained by heating the fiber web to reduce
the thickness of the fiber web (a) or the thermally bonded nonwoven fabric (b) to 20 to 80%
of the original thickness.</p><p num="0008">The third aspect of the present invention relates to an absorbent article comprising a
liquid retentive absorbent layer and a liquid impermeable leakproof layer, wherein the
absorbent layer has the above-described sheet.</p><p num="0009">Another object of the invention is to provide an absorbent article which is not distorted
while worn thereby securing a good fit to a wearer's body, and leakproofness.</p><p num="0010">The above object is accomplished by a fourth aspect of the invention. The fourth
aspect of the invention relates to an absorbent article which has substantially longitudinal
shape and comprises a liquid retentive absorbent layer and a liquid impermeable leakproof
layer, wherein the absorbent layer has a surface layer that is to be brought into contact with a 
wearer's skin and an elastic layer disposed under the surface layer, the elastic layer having an
elastic recovery force of 0.7 cN or more, and the absorbent article has a compressive strain of
less than 5% in the width direction thereof.</p><p num="0011">The sheet according to the first aspect of the invention provides an absorbent article
which is resistant to distortion in the planar direction, feels comfortable to wear, and has
improved leakproofness.</p><p num="0012">The process of producing the sheet of the first aspect, which constitutes the second
aspect of the present invention, makes it possible to prepare an absorbent article which has the
above described excellency easily and simply without causing buckling in roll or stiffness
reduction.</p><p num="0013">The absorbent article according to the third and fourth aspects of the invention is not
liable to distortion while worn, securing a good fit to a wearer's body and leakproofness. According to the above the present invention provides the subject matter as defined in claims 1 to 9.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0014">The present invention will be more particularly described with reference to the
accompanying drawings, in which:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a plan view of an embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a cross section of Fig. 1 along X-X line;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a plan view of another embodiment of the present invention; and</li><li>Fig. 4 is a cross section of Fig. 3 along X-X line.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading><p num="0015">The first to third aspects of the present invention will be described. The sheet for
absorbent articles according to the present invention serves to improve recovery of an
absorbent article from distortion.</p><p num="0016">The term &quot;recovery from distortion&quot; as used herein means a property of an absorbent
article for restoring the initial shape even when it is warped, turned up or twisted by external
force while being worn. </p><p num="0017">The sheet for absorbent articles has a recovery force of 0.7 cN or more, preferably 2.0
to 6.0 cN in the cross direction (CD), a compressive strength of 100 cN or less, preferably 10
to 100 cN, and a basis weight of 20 g/m<sup>2</sup> or more, preferably 20 to 50 g/m<sup>2</sup>, still preferably 30
to 45 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p><p num="0018">If the recovery force in the CD is less than 0.7 cN, the effect on recovery from
distortion is not sufficient. If the compressive strength is more than 100 cN, the comfort and
the fit on wearing reduce.</p><p num="0019">If the basis weight is less than 20 g/m<sup>2</sup>, the effect on recovery from distortion is not
manifested. From the standpoint of productivity and cost, the basis weight is preferably less
than 50 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p><p num="0020">The sheet for absorbent articles preferably has a thickness of 1.0 mm or smaller,
particularly 0.3 to 0.8 mm, for securing the comfort on wearing and the fit to a wearer's body.</p><p num="0021">The recovery force in CD, thickness, and compressive strength of the sheet according
to the present invention are measured as follows. The term &quot;cross direction (CD)&quot; as used
herein means a direction substantially perpendicular to the fiber orientation direction
(machine direction; MD). That is, the sheet of the present invention exhibits a recovery
property from deformation in the CD.</p><heading>Measurement of recovery force in CD:</heading><p num="0022">A 45 mm wide and 145 mm long strip is cut out of a sheet with the width direction of
the strip agreeing with the CD of the sheet. The strip is rolled with its length in the
peripheral direction to make a cylinder of 40 mm in diameter. The lap is fastened with
staples at three positions 10 mm apart from each other.</p><p num="0023">The cylindrical test specimen is set on a compression tester RTM-100, manufactured
by Toyo Baldwin, (initial specimen height: 45 mm) and compressed under a compression
plate at a compressing speed of 50 mm/min in the axial direction of the cylinder
(downstroke). After compressing the specimen by a 15 mm downstroke, the compressing
plate was then moved upward to the initial sample height of 45 mm (upstroke). The load vs.
the stroke distance in the up-and-down double stroke was recorded, and the load at 2 mm 
before the distance of zero load in the upstroke is read, which is taken as a recovery force in
the CD.</p><heading>Measurement of thickness:</heading><p num="0024">The thickness of the sheet was measured with a thickness meter (a constant load
thickness meter PG-11, manufactured by Techloc) under a constant load of 0.36 kPa.</p><heading>Measurement of compressive strength:</heading><p num="0025">A cylindrical test specimen prepared in the same manner as described above is set in a
compression tester (initial sample height: 45 mm). The specimen was compressed with a
compressing plate at a speed of 50 mm/min, and the maximum load applied was measured.</p><p num="0026">The sheet satisfying all the above requirements preferably includes,
nonwoven fabric A or nonwoven fabric B described below.</p><heading>Nonwoven fabric A:</heading><p num="0027">Thermally bonded nonwoven fabric comprising 70% by weight or more of core-sheath
type thermally bonding conjugate fibers which are thermally fused together at their
intersections, wherein the core comprises an olefin polymer, polyester, or polyamide, and the
sheath comprises (1) a copolymer mainly comprising propylene, (2) a copolymer mainly
comprising ethylene, or (3) low-density polyethylene.</p><heading>Nonwoven fabric B:</heading><p num="0028">Thermally bonded nonwoven fabric comprising 70% by weight or more of core-sheath
type thermally bonding conjugate fibers which are thermally fused together at their
intersections, wherein the core comprises polyester or polyamide, the sheath comprises high-density
polyethylene, and the conjugate fibers have an average fineness of 6.6 dtex to 22 dtex.</p><p num="0029">Nonwoven fabrics A and B will be described below. First, nonwoven fabric A will
be described. The olefin polymer which can be used as a core of the core-sheath type
thermally bonding fibers making up nonwoven fabric A includes a propylene homopolymer
and a copolymer mainly comprising propylene and, as a minor component, ethylene or other
α-olefins and having a degree of crystallinity of 40% or more. </p><p num="0030">The polyester which can be used as a core of the thermally bonding fibers making
nonwoven fabric A includes polyethylene terephthalate, polybutylene terephthalate,
polyethylene naphthalate, polyhexamethylene terephthalate, polytetramethylene terephthalate,
poly-1,4-dimethylcyclohexane terephthalate, and polypivalolactone t, and copolyesters
comprising any one or more of the monomers constituting these homopolymers. These
polyester resins can be used either individually or in combination of two or more thereof.</p><p num="0031">The polyamide which can be used as a core of the thermally bonding fibers making up
nonwoven fabric A includes nylon 6, nylon 66, nylon 2, nylon 3, nylon 4, nylon 7, nylon 11,
nylon 12, nylon 610, and copolymers comprising any one or more of the monomers
constituting these homopolymers. These polyamide resins can be used either individually or
as a combination of two or more thereof.</p><p num="0032">The sheath can be made of the polymers (1) to (3) described above either individually
or as a mixture of two or more thereof. Mixtures comprising at least one of these polymers
and at least one of polypropylene, polyethylene, and α-olefin polymers are also useful.</p><p num="0033">The copolymer mainly comprising propylene (1) includes an ethylene-propylene
copolymer, an ethylene-butene-1-propylene terpolymer, and the like, each having a propylene
content of 80 to 98% by weight and an ethylene content of 2 to 20% by weight. These
propylene copolymers can be used either individually or in a combination of two or more
thereof.</p><p num="0034">The copolymer mainly comprising ethylene (2) includes an ethylene-vinyl acetate
copolymer, an ethylene-ethyl acrylate copolymer, and an ethylene-methyl acrylate copolymer,
with an ethylene-ethyl acrylate copolymer having an ethylene content of 70 to 95% by weight
and an ethyl acrylate content of 5 to 30% by weight being preferred. These ethylene
copolymers can be used either individually or as a combination of two or more thereof.</p><p num="0035">The low-density polyethylene (3) includes high pressure processed low-density
polyethylene, a linear low-density polyethylene that is an ethylene-α-olefin copolymer, and
low-density polyethylene or an ethylene-α-olefin copolymer that are produced by use of a
single site catalyst. An ethylene homopolymer and an ethylene-α-olefin copolymer which 
are produced by use of a single site catalyst and have a density of 0.85 to 0.94 g/cm<sup>3</sup>,
particularly 0.86 to 0.88 g/cm<sup>3</sup>, are preferred. They can be used either individually or as a
combination of two or more thereof.</p><p num="0036">The core-sheath type thermally bonding conjugate fibers making nonwoven fabric A
preferably have a core to sheath volume ratio of 1:0.25 to 4, still preferably 1:0.5 to 1.5, and a
fineness of 0.5 to 25 dtex, particularly 2 to 15 dtex.</p><p num="0037">Next, nonwoven fabric B will be described. The polyester which can be used as a
core of the core-sheath type thermally bonding conjugate fibers making up nonwoven fabric
B includes polyethylene terephthalate, polybutylene terephthalate, polyethylene naphthalate,
polyhexamethylene terephthalate, polytetramethylene terephthalate, poly-1,4-dimethylcyclohexane
terephthalate, polypivalolactone t, and copolyesters comprising any one
or more of the monomers constituting these homopolymers. These polyester resins can be
used either individually or in combination of two or more thereof.</p><p num="0038">The polyamide which can be used as a core of the thermally bonding fibers making
nonwoven fabric B includes nylon 6, nylon 66, nylon 2, nylon 3, nylon 4, nylon 7, nylon 11,
nylon 12, nylon 610, and copolymers comprising any one or more of the monomers
constituting these homopolymers. These polyamide resins can be used either individually or
as a combination of two or more thereof.</p><p num="0039">The high-density polyethylene which can be used as a sheath preferably has a melt
flow rate of 20 g/10 min or more, particularly 25 to 50g/10 min, and a density of 0.92 to
0.97 g/cm<sup>3</sup>.</p><p num="0040">The core-sheath type thermally bonding conjugate fibers making nonwoven fabric B
preferably have an average fineness of 6.6 to 25 dtex, particularly 8 to 15 dtex.</p><p num="0041">Nonwoven fabrics A and B are each thermally bonded nonwoven fabric in which the
individual core-sheath type thermally bonding conjugate fibers are heat-bonded at their
intersections. More specifically, the sheaths of the conjugate fibers are heat-fused to each
other at the intersections. </p><p num="0042">The sheet for absorbent articles according to the present invention can be used as a
member of an absorbent layer of an absorbent article, for example.</p><p num="0043">Having the above-described constitution, the sheet of the present invention, when used
in an absorbent article, is capable of effectively preventing the absorbent article from being
distorted or twisted in the planar direction as worn thereby securing a good fit to a wearer's
body and leakproofness.</p><p num="0044">Where used in an absorbent layer of an absorbent article, the sheet may be disposed
with either of its MD (the direction of fiber orientation) or CD being in the longitudinal
direction of the absorbent layer. With productivity taken into consideration, it is preferred
for the sheet to be disposed with its MD in the longitudinal direction of the absorbent layer
(absorbent member).</p><p num="0045">A preferred process for producing the sheet for absorbent articles according to the
present invention will be described with reference to the sheet comprising nonwoven fabric A
or B.</p><p num="0046">The sheet can be produced by a process including a step of heat treating a fiber web
and a step of compressing (a) the fiber web before being heat-treated or (b) a thermally
bonded nonwoven fabric obtained by heating the fiber web to reduce the thickness of the fiber
web (a) or the thermally bonded nonwoven fabric (b) to 20 to 80% of the original thickness.
If the degree of compression is less than 20%, no effect is produced on improvement of
recovery. If it exceeds 80%, the sheet is shaped like film and, when used in an absorbent
article, will give poor fit and discomfort while worn.</p><p num="0047">The step of heat treating is carried out by an air-through method which is usually
practiced in the manufacture of thermally bonded nonwoven fabric.</p><p num="0048">The step of compressing (hereinafter sometimes referred to as a thickness control step)
is applied to either (a) a fiber web before being heat treated or (b) a sheet obtained by
thermally bonding the fiber web by, for example, an air-through method. The thickness
control step is carried out by applying pressure to (a) the fiber web or (b) the thermally 
bonded sheet with an embossing roll and a like means usually employed for pressing
nonwoven fabric with no particular restriction. The configuration of projections (bosses) on
the embossing roll is not particularly limited.</p><p num="0049">Where the fiber web or the thermally bonded sheet is pressed with a flat roll in the
thickness control step, the linear pressure to be given is preferably 5 to 80 cN/cm. Where an
embossing roll is used for pressing, the linear pressure is preferably 100 to 500 N/cm.</p><p num="0050">It is preferred that the embossing roll be heated to a temperature Tr in a range:
(T-80)°C&lt;Tr°C&lt;T°C, wherein T is the melting point of the sheath of the core-sheath type
thermally bonding conjugate fibers.</p><p num="0051">The third aspect of the present invention, i.e., an absorbent article, is described below
with particular reference to a panty liner.</p><p num="0052">The panty liner 1 shown in Figs. 1 and 2 has a substantially rectangular shape and
comprises a liquid retentive absorbent layer 2 and a liquid impermeable leakproof layer 3,
wherein the absorbent layer 2 has a sheet 23 which is the above-described sheet for absorbent
articles according to the present invention.</p><p num="0053">The sheet 23 is disposed under the surface layer forming the wearer's body side 24 of
the panty liner 1. In detail, the absorbing layer 2 comprises a liquid permeable topsheet 21, a
liquid retentive absorbent member 22, and the sheet 23 sandwiched in between the topsheet
21 and the absorbent member 22. The leakproof layer 3 comprises a moisture permeable
and liquid impermeable back sheet 31. The topsheet 21 is fixed to the back sheet 31 at all
the periphery thereof so that the absorbent layer 2 and the leakproof layer 3 are fixed together.
While not shown, a pressure-sensitive adhesive is applied onto the back side of the leakproof
layer 3 to attach the panty liner 1 to underwear on use.</p><p num="0054">The topsheet 21, the back sheet 31, and the absorbent member 22 of the panty liner 1
can be fabricated of the materials commonly employed in general sanitary napkins.</p><p num="0055">The panty liner 1 provided in this embodiment can be used as attached to underwear in 
the same manner as with general panty liners. While worn, the panty liner 1 having the
above-described constitution is prevented from being distorted, ensuring a good fit to a
wearer's body and causing no leakage.</p><p num="0056">The panty liner 1 can be produced by superposing on the back sheet 31, the absorbent
member 22, the sheet 23, and the topsheet 21 in this order in the same manner as with general
panty liners, and adhering the topsheet 21 and the back sheet 31 at the periphery by heat
sealing, etc.</p><p num="0057">Another preferred embodiment of the absorbent article according to the present
invention (fourth aspect) will be described with reference to the panty liner.</p><p num="0058">As shown in Figs. 3 and 4, the panty liner 101 is substantially rectangular and has a
liquid retentive absorbent layer 102 and a liquid impermeable leakproof layer 103, wherein
the absorbent layer 102 comprises an elastic layer 123 which is disposed under the surface
layer forming the wearer's body side 124 of the panty liner 101.</p><p num="0059">The elastic layer 123 has an elastic recovery force of 0.7 cN or more, preferably 0.8 to
4 cN, still preferably 1 to 2 cN, and the panty liner 101 has a compressive strain of less than
5%, preferably 1 to 4%, in the width direction thereof. If the elastic recovery force of the
elastic layer is less than 0.7 cN, the absorbent article has poor conformity to the contour of a
wearer's body, giving poor fit. If the compressive strain of the absorbent article in the width
direction exceeds 5%, it hardly restores from a distorted state, leaving untidy folds.</p><p num="0060">The elastic recovery force and the compressive strain in the width direction can be
measured as follows.</p><heading>Measurement of elastic recovery force:</heading><p num="0061">A 45 mm wide and 140 mm long strip is cut out of an elastic sheet of an absorbent
article with the longitudinal direction of the strip agreeing with the longitudinal direction of
the absorbent article. Because of the limited size of a sample article, the longitudinal edges
of the strip may have a semicircular or trapezoidal shape. The strip is rolled with its length
in the peripheral direction to make a cylinder having a lap of about 5 mm width. The lap is 
fastened with staples (No 10-1M, available from Max Co., Ltd.) at three positions 10 mm
apart from each other, the staples being in parallel with the peripheral direction.</p><p num="0062">The cylindrical specimen (initial height: 45 mm) is set on a Tensilon compression
tester (RTM-25, supplied by Toyo Baldwin) and compressed with a compression plate
initially set a little higher than the specimen (at a height of about 47 mm) at a compressing
speed of 50 mm/min in the axial direction of the cylinder. After compressing the specimen
to a height of 30 mm (downstroke), the compressing plate was then moved upward to the
initial position at the same speed to let the specimen restore the height (upstroke). The up-and-down
double stroke makes one measurement. The measurement was made on at least
two specimens per sample. The stress at a height of 40 mm in the upstroke is recorded, and
an average of the results obtained from two or more specimens is taken as an elastic recovery
force.</p><heading>Measurement of compressive strain in width direction:</heading><p num="0063">A 45 mm width and 140 mm long strip is cut out of an absorbent article with its
longitudinal direction agreeing with the longitudinal direction of the absorbent article and
made into a cylindrical specimen in the same manner as in the measurement of elastic
recovery force. The specimen was given an up-and-down stroke of compression in the same
manner, and the stress of the specimen vs. the position of the plate in the double stroke was
recorded to make a chart. The difference between the height of the compression starting
position in the downstroke (45 mm) and the height at a stress relaxation point (a position
where the stress of the specimen becomes zero) in the upstroke is read from the chart. The
measurement is made on at least two specimens per sample, and an average (mm) of the
measured values is applied to the following equation to obtain a compressive stress in the
width direction.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Compressive stress in the width direction = <st32:frac align="center">average of measured values<st32:over>45 mm</st32:over></st32:frac> × 100</st32:df></p><p num="0064">It is preferred for the panty liner 101 as an absorbent article to have an elastic recovery
force of 4 cN or more, particularly 9 cN or more, especially 12 cN or more, for obtaining
improved fit to a wearer's body. The elastic recovery force of an absorbent article will
hereinafter be referred to as a product elastic recovery force. The product elastic recovery
force is measured as follows. </p><heading>Measurement of product elastic recovery force:</heading><p num="0065">A specimen was prepared in the same manner as in the measurement of compressive
strain in the width direction and given an up-and-down stroke of compression in the same
manner to prepare a chart of the stress of the specimen vs. the position of the plate in the
double stroke. The stress at a height of 40 mm in the upstroke is read. The measurement is
made on at least two specimens per sample, and an average of the measured values is taken as
a product elastic recovery force. In case where an absorbent article has compressed parts as
in the embodiment hereinafter described, the measurements of compressive strain in the width
direction (of the absorbent article) and the product elastic recovery force are made on
specimens-having the compressed parts, while the elastic recovery force of the elastic layer
and the buckling strength (of the elastic layer) hereinafter described are measured on
specimens having no such compressed parts if possible.</p><p num="0066">In the panty liner 101, the absorbent layer 102 comprises a liquid permeable topsheet
121, which forms the surface layer, a liquid retentive absorbent member 122, and the elastic
layer 123 which lies between the topsheet 121 and the absorbent member 122. Interposed
between the topsheet 121 and the absorbent member 122, the elastic layer 123 brings about
improved touch and cushioning properties. The leakproof layer 103 comprises a liquid
impermeable back sheet 131. The topsheet 121 is fixed to the back sheet 131 at all the
periphery thereof so that the absorbent layer 102 and the leakproof layer 103 are fixed
together. The absorbent member 122 is made slightly smaller in size than the topsheet 121
so that the topsheet 121 and the back sheet 131 may be joined directly to form peripheral
portion 105 having no absorbent member 122 around the panty liner 101. While not shown,
a pressure-sensitive adhesive is applied onto the back side of the leakproof layer 103 for
fixing the panty liner 101 to underwear.</p><p num="0067">In order for the elastic layer 123 to have the above-specified elastic recovery force
and/or for the panty liner 101 to have the above-specified compressive strain in the width
direction, it is preferred that the elastic layer 123 be made of a foamed material, a dry
processed pulp sheet, nonwoven fabric, etc. In particular, the nonwoven fabric for use as the
elastic layer is preferably made up of one or more kinds of known resin fibers, such as
polyethylene, polypropylene, polyester, nylon, and polyamide. From the aspect of
production process, thermally bonded nonwoven fabric, spunbonded nonwoven fabric, needle
punched nonwoven fabric and the like can be used. Preferred is thermally bonded 
nonwoven fabric comprising conjugate fibers (e.g., core-sheath type conjugate fiber) having a
fineness of 1 to 10 dtex, preferably 3 to 7 dtex.</p><p num="0068">It is preferred that the nonwoven fabric for use as the elastic layer 123 has increased
elasticity and/or increased stiffness by any one of, preferably two or more, of the methods (i)
to (iv) described below, in which &quot;elasticity/stiffness&quot; means elasticity and/or stiffness.
<sl><li>i) Elasticity/stiffness by fiber
Fiber of resins with high elasticity/stiffness, such as polypropylene, polyester and
polyurethane, are used to obtain improved elasticity/stiffness (effect by fiber).</li><li>ii) Uniformity in fiber orientation
Since the elasticity/stiffness of nonwoven fabric depends on the orientation direction
of constituent fibers, the elasticity/stiffness can be improved by orienting the constituent
fibers in all directions at random (effect by sheet structure).</li><li>iii) Recovery of network structure
The network structure surrounding the bonded intersections of fibers is strengthened
and/or immobilized to enhance the recover properties of the free portions between the bonded
intersections, thereby improving the elasticity/stiffness (effect by sheet structure).</li><li>iv) Densifying of sheet
The sheet is densified by using crimped fibers having a three-dimensional structure,
making the fiber orientation uniform, and increasing the fiber intersections to be bonded,
thereby improving elasticity/stiffness (effect by fiber).</li></sl></p><p num="0069">While any one of the methods (i) to (iv) realizes the above-specified elastic recovery
properties of the elastic layer, it is particularly preferred to use a combination of (i) and (iii), a
combination of (i) and (iv) or a combination of (ii) and (iv), which produces both the effect by
fiber and the effect by sheet structure.</p><p num="0070">It is preferred for the nonwoven fabric for use as the elastic layer 123 be hydrophilic.
Hydrophilic nonwoven fabric can be obtained by a method comprising using fibers 
previously treated with a hydrophilic lubricant, a method comprising incorporating a
hydrophilic lubricant into the fiber-forming resin (the lubricant bleeds out), a method
comprising treating nonwoven fabric with a hydrophilic lubricant, or a like method. The
hydrophilic nonwoven fabric preferably has a contact angle with ion-exchanged water of 70°
or smaller, particularly 50° or smaller. The contact angle is measured as follows.</p><heading>Measurement of contact angle:</heading><p num="0071">Measurement is made with a contact angle meter (CA-S Micron 2, supplied by Kyowa
Kaimen Kagaku K.K.) according to a fiber method (at a magnification of 300). A camera
(Nicon F80) is set on the meter in the prescribed manner and focused on a sample fiber.
Water is sprayed onto the fiber. Five seconds later, a photograph is taken of the fiber on an
ASA 100 film. The contact angle is measured on selected five sites showing a water droplet
clearly (both ends of a droplet are clear) to obtain an average.</p><p num="0072">Where nonwoven fabric having improved elasticity/stiffness by the method (ii) alone
or in combination with other method is used to make the elastic layer 123, it is preferred for
the nonwoven fabric to have a ratio of the buckling strength in the CD (hereinafter &quot;CD
buckling strength&quot;) to that in the MD (hereinafter &quot;MD buckling strength&quot;) of 0.4 to 2.5,
particularly 0.8 to 1.5. While the orientation-state of fibers can be measured with, for
example, an orientation meter, the above-described CD/MD buckling strength ratio is used in
the present invention as an index of the fiber orientation direction because nonwoven fabric
generally shows higher bending resistance in the orientation direction of the constituent
fibers. The buckling strength is to be a quantitative value representing the bending
resistance of the elastic layer. The buckling strength is measured as follows.</p><heading>Measurement of buckling strength:</heading><p num="0073">In the above-described measurement of elastic recovery force of an elastic layer, an
average maximum stress reached in the downstroke is taken as a CD buckling strength. An
MD buckling strength is measured in the same manner as for the CD buckling strength,
except that the 45 mm wide and 140 mm long strip for making the specimen is cut out of the
nonwoven fabric with its width direction being along the longitudinal direction of an
absorbent article. </p><p num="0074">As shown in Fig. 4, the absorbent layer 102 has a plurality of compressed parts 104
formed on the wearer's body side 124 by compressing at least the elastic layer 123 to bring the
topsheet 121, the absorbent member 122, and the elastic layer 123 into one body. The
compressed parts 104 are effective to prevent the elastic layer 123 from causing reduction in
liquid attracting properties. The compressed parts 104 not only bring about improved liquid
attracting properties but facilitate attraction of highly viscous matter into the absorbent
member.</p><p num="0075">In this embodiment, the compressed parts 104, each having a leaf pattern, are formed
by pressing the panty liner 101 from its surface side 124 to press the whole thickness of the
absorbent layer 102, which also produces a decorative effect.</p><p num="0076">In general, an increased density increases the liquid attracting force but, in turn,
decreases liquid permeability for passing the absorbed liquid to the lower layers. Therefore,
it is desirable that the topsheet 121 on at least the compressed parts 104 be perforated to
exhibit excellent absorption performance. In this particular embodiment shown, the topsheet
121 is perforated to have a large number of through-holes 125 over the entire area thereof
except the peripheral portion 105.</p><p num="0077">The compressed parts 104 preferably have a total area of 5 to 50% based on the entire
area of the wearer's skin side 124 except the peripheral portion 105. With this lower limit,
improvement on liquid attracting properties can be secured to prevent any liquid from
remaining on the surface. With the above upper limit, deterioration in liquid permeability
and touch (cushioning) can be minimized.</p><p num="0078">The compressed parts 104 each preferably have a base area (defined below) of 0.5 to
50 mm<sup>2</sup>. With this lower limit, effective manifestation of the effect on liquid attracting
properties is secured. With the above upper limit, hindrance to liquid passage can be
minimized. The term &quot;base area&quot; as used herein denotes the area of the compressed part at
the deepest, i.e., the area of the bottom of the depression.</p><p num="0079">While, in the embodiment shown in Fig. 3, the compressed parts 104 are made on both
lateral side portions of the panty liner 101, they can be provided over the entire surface side, 
for example, in a dot pattern by embossing. To form the compressed parts 104 over the
entire surface is advantageous for liquid attraction, while localizing the compressed parts on
side portions as shown in Fig. 3 is advantageous for obtaining liquid attracting properties on
the side portions and cushioning properties in the middle portion.</p><p num="0080">The effects as expected in the present invention are particularly pronounced in
absorbent articles having a thickness of 4 mm or smaller, particularly 3 mm or smaller,
especially 2 mm or smaller. Conventional absorbent articles with a thickness of 4 mm or
less are very likely to be distorted or twisted while worn. In the present invention, the
above-described construction effectively prevents such distortion from happening even if the
thickness is so reduced. Further, such a thin absorbent article has improved fit, giving
comfort to a wearer.</p><p num="0081">The topsheet 121, the back sheet 131, and the absorbent member 122 of the panty liner
101 can be fabricated of the same materials as commonly employed in general sanitary
napkins.</p><p num="0082">The panty liner 101 provided in the above-described embodiment can be used as
attached to underwear in the same manner as with general panty liners. While worn, the
panty liner 101 having the above-described structure is prevented from being distorted by the
action of the elastic layer, ensuring good fit to a wearer's body and causing no leak during use.</p><p num="0083">The panty liner 101 can be produced by, for example, superposing the topsheet 121 on
the elastic layer 123, partially hot-pressing the laminate from the topsheet 121 side to form
compressed parts 104 of prescribed shape in a prescribed pattern, superposing on the back
sheet 131 the absorbent member 122 and the hot-pressed laminate, and adhering the topsheet
121 and the back sheet 131 at the periphery by, for example, heat sealing.</p><p num="0084">While the present invention has been described with particular embodiments of the
first to fourth aspects, these embodiments should not be deemed as limiting the invention, and
various changes and modifications can be made therein. For example, the present invention
is applicable to sanitary napkins, disposable diapers, and adult incontinence pads as well as
panty liners. The position of the sheet 23 or the elastic layer 123 in the absorbent layer 2 or 
102, respectively, is not particularly limited, provided that it should not form the surface side
24 or 124 which is to be brought into contact with a wearer's skin. That is, the sheet 23 or
the elastic layer 123 can be the undermost layer in the absorbing layer 2 or 102. Further, a
laminate of the absorbent member 22 or 122 and the sheet 23 (which may be backed with
another sheeting) or the elastic layer 123 is bent along the longitudinal direction to make an
inverted &quot;V&quot; shape when seen from the edge side, and the periphery of the inverted V-shaped
laminate is joined with a flat back sheet 31 or 131 to produce a sanitary napkin whose cross
section has an inverted &quot;V&quot; shape. The particulars of the above-described embodiments are
interchangeable among themselves.</p><p num="0085">The present invention will now be illustrated in greater detail by way of Examples.</p><heading>Examples of 1st to third aspect:</heading><heading>EXAMPLES 1 TO 4 AND COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0086">A fiber web having the fiber composition shown in Table 1 below was thermally fused
by an air-through method at the heating temperature shown in Table 1 to prepare nonwoven
fabric.</p><p num="0087">An absorbent article shown in Fig. 1 was prepared by using the resulting nonwoven
fabric as a sheet 23 and tested organoleptically. As a result, the absorbent articles of
Examples 1 to 4 did not undergo distortion nor twist while worn, retaining good fit or comfort
and excellent leakproofness. To the contrary, the product of Comparative Example 1 was
distorted while being worn, giving discomfort to a wearer.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 5</heading><p num="0088">A fiber web having the fiber composition shown in Table 1 was thermally fused by an
air-through method at the heating temperature shown in Table 1. The resulting sheet was
50% compressed with a flat roll under a linear pressure of 40 g/cm to prepare nonwoven
fabric as a sheet for absorbent articles.</p><p num="0089">An absorbent article shown in Fig. 1 was prepared by using the resulting sheet and 
tested organoleptically. As a result, the absorbent article did not undergo distortion nor twist
while worn, retaining good fit or comfort and excellent leakproofness.</p><p num="0090">Abbreviations used in Table 1 have the following meanings.
<sl><li>PET: polyethylene terephthalate</li><li>E-P: ethylene-propylene copolymer having a propylene content of 95.5 wt% and an
ethylene content of 4.5 wt%</li><li>EEA: ethylene-ethyl acrylate copolymer having an ethylene content of 80 wt% and
an ethyl acrylate content of 20 wt%</li><li>PP: polypropylene</li><li>VLDPE: mixture of an ethylene-α-olefin copolymer obtained by using a single site
catalyst and polyethylene</li><li>PE20: polyethylene having an MFR of 20 g/10 min.</li><li>PE12: polyethylene having an MFR of 12 g/10 min.</li></sl><img file="00190001.tif" id="img-EP-1128367-A3-00190001" he="212" wi="108" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><heading>Examples and Comparative Examples of the 4th aspect:</heading><heading>EXAMPLES 6 TO 11 AND COMPARATIVE EXAMPLES 2 TO 4</heading><p num="0091">The members described below and shown in Table 2 below were superposed in the top-to-bottom
order of a topsheet, an elastic layer, and an absorbent member (Examples 6 to 11
and Comparative Examples 2 and 4) or a topsheet and an absorbent member (Comparative
Example 3). A breathable and leakproof sheet (KTF-37, available from Mitsubishi
Chemical Corp.) was disposed under the absorbent member. Every adjacent members were
adhered by applying 5 g/m<sup>2</sup> of a hot-melt adhesive in a spiral pattern (a hot-melt adhesive
applied to a strippable substrate in a spiral pattern could be transferred) to make a 57 mm
wide and 140 mm long absorbent article having the shape shown in Fig. 3. The absorbent
articles of Examples 8 to 11 had compressed parts 104 as shown in Fig. 3, except that the
individual compressed parts of Examples 8, 9 and 11 had a circular shape (the individual
compressed parts of Example 10 had a leaf shape). The ratio of the total area of the
compressed parts to the entire area of the wearer's skin side was obtained. The results are
shown in Table 2.

Members used in the absorbent articles:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Topsheet 1</entry><entry align="left">Nonwoven fabric comprising PET/PE fibers having a basis weight of 25 g/m<sup>2</sup>, the same member as used as a topsheet of a commercially available panty liner (Lone Panty Liner (non-fragrant type), available from Kao Corp.)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Topsheet 2</entry><entry align="left">Commercially available nonwoven fabric (CotAce C03OS/A25, available from Unitika, Ltd.)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elastic layer 1</entry><entry align="left">Nonwoven fabric prepared by thermally fusing a web of fibers NBF(SH), available from Daiwabo Co., Ltd (fineness: 4.4 dtex; average length: 51 mm), having a basis weight of 40 g/m<sup>2</sup> by an air-through method at a temperature of 148°C and treating the nonwoven fabric with a hydrophilic lubricant according to <ref type="patent">Japanese Patent Laid-Open No. 309111/93</ref>. The resulting nonwoven fabric (elastic layer 1) had a thickness of 0.57 mm, an elastic recovery force of 0.78 cN, and a CD/MD buckling strength ratio of 0.29. The nonwoven fabric had improved elasticity/stiffness according to the above-described method (i). </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elastic layer 2</entry><entry align="left">Nonwoven fabric prepared in the same manner as for elastic layer 1, except for using a web of fibers NBF(SP) (available from Daiwabo Co., Ltd.; fineness: 4.4 dtex; average length: 51 mm) having a basics weight of 40 g/m<sup>2</sup>. The nonwoven fabric (elastic layer 2) had a thickness of 0.55 mm, an elastic recovery force of 1.18 cN, and a CD/MD buckling strength ratio of 0.30. Elastic layer 2 had improved elasticity/stiffness according to the above-described methods (i) and (iii).</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elastic layer 3</entry><entry align="left">Nonwoven fabric prepared as follows. A web of fibers NBF(SH) (available from Daiwabo Co., Ltd., fineness: 2.2 dtex; average length. 51 mm) having a basis weight of 10 g/m<sup>2</sup> and a web of fibers NBF(SP) (available from Daiwabo Co., Ltd.; fineness: 4.4 dtex; average length: 51 mm) having a basis weight of 20 g/m<sup>2</sup> were superposed on each other to prepare a laminate web having a total basis weight of 30 g/m<sup>2</sup>. The laminate web was thermally fused by an air-through method at a heating temperature of 148°C to prepare nonwoven fabric, which was then treated with a hydrophilic lubricant in the same manner as for elastic layer 1. Elastic layer 3 had a thickness of 0.48 mm, an elastic recovery force of 0.88 cN, and a CD/MD buckling strength ratio of 0.34. Elastic layer 3 had improved elasticity/stiffness by the above-described methods (i) and (iii).</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elastic layer 4</entry><entry align="left">Nonwoven fabric prepared as follows. A web of fibers NBF(SH) (available from Daiwabo Co., Ltd.; fineness: 2.2 dtex; average length: 51 mm) having a basis weight of 10 g/m<sup>2</sup> and a web of 1:1 mixed fibers of NBF(SH) (available from Daiwabo Co., Ltd.; fineness: 2.2 dtex; average length: 51 mm; three-dimensional crimped fibers) and PET fibers Tetoron (available from Teijin Ltd.; fineness: 8.8 dtex; average length: 51 mm) and having a basis weight of 30 g/m<sup>2</sup> were superposed on each other to prepare a laminate web having a total basis weight of 40 g/m<sup>2</sup>. The laminate web was thermally fused by an air-through method at a heating temperature of 148°C to prepare nonwoven fabric, which was then treated with a hydrophilic lubricant in the same manner as for elastic layer 1. Elastic layer 4 thus prepared had a thickness of 0.65 mm, an elastic recovery force </entry></row><row><entry align="left" /><entry align="left">of 1.76 cN, and a CD/MD buckling strength ratio of 1.06. Elastic layer 4 had improved elasticity/stiffness by the above-described methods (i) to (iv).</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elastic layer 5</entry><entry align="left">Nonwoven fabric prepared by thermally fusing a web of fibers NBF(SH) (available from Daiwabo Co., Ltd.; fineness: 2.2 dtex; average length: 51 mm) having a basis weight of 25 g/m<sup>2</sup> by an air-through method at a temperature of 148°C to prepare nonwoven fabric and treating the resulting nonwoven fabric with a hydrophilic lubricant in the same manner as for elastic layer 1. Elastic layer 5 thus prepared had a thickness of 0.26 mm, an elastic recovery force of 0.2 cN, and a CD/MD buckling strength ratio of 0.29.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Absorbent member 1</entry><entry align="left">Paper having a basis weight of 16 g/m<sup>2</sup> and a craping ratio of 10%.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Absorbent member 2</entry><entry align="left">Dry-processed pulp sheet having a basis weight of 45 g/m<sup>2</sup> (JS45HDW, available from J Soft K.K.)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Absorbent member 3</entry><entry align="left">Two-ply paper (30 mm x 120 mm) having a basis weight of 35 g/m<sup>2</sup>, each ply having a craping ratio of 20%.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Absorbent member 4</entry><entry align="left">A laminate sheet having a basis weight of 50 g/m<sup>2</sup>, made of a pair of pulp webs (30 mm x 60 mm) having 10 g/m<sup>2</sup> of superabsorbent polymer particles (Aquaric CAW-4, available from Nippon Shokubai Co., Ltd.) scattered therebetween.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0092">Each of elastic layers 1 to 4 had a contact angle between 50° and 60°. The thickness
of elastic layers I to 5 and the final products (absorbent articles) was measured with a
thickness gauge ID-C112CB (supplied by Mitsutoyo K.K.) to which a measuring part of
30 mm in diameter was attached to give a load of about 10 cN.</p><p num="0093">The compressive strain in the width direction and the product elastic recovery force of
the absorbent articles obtained in Examples 6 to 11 and Comparative Examples 2 to 4 were
measured according to the methods previously described. Further, the absorbent articles
were evaluated for non-liability to distortion and absorption performance in accordance with
the following test methods. The results of the measurement and evaluation are shown in 
Table 2.</p><heading>Evaluation of non-liability to distortion:</heading><p num="0094">A ten member panel were asked to use the absorbent articles of Examples 6 to 11 and
Comparative Examples 2 to 4 (test sample) and, for reference, Lorie Panty Liner (non-fragrant
type, &quot;non-distortion stitches&quot;, available from Kao Corp. July, 1999), to make a judgement
which of the test sample and the reference sample is less liable to distortion and to grade on
the following A-to-E scale. Two articles per sample were used by each panel member.
<sl><li>A: The test sample is less liable to distortion.</li><li>B: The test sample is somewhat less liable to distortion.</li><li>C: The test sample and the reference sample are equal in liability to distortion.</li><li>D: The reference sample is somewhat less liable to distortion.</li><li>E: The reference sample is less liable to distortion.</li></sl></p><p num="0095">The difference between the number of panel members who graded A or B (the number
of panel members who approved of the test sample) and the number of panel members who
graded D or E (the number of panel members who approved of the reference sample) (the
former - the latter) was taken-as an index for judging non-liability to distortion. The index of
5 or greater was rated &quot;excellent&quot;, 3 to 4 &quot;good&quot;, 1 to 2 &quot;medium&quot;, and 0 or smaller &quot;bad&quot;</p><heading>Evaluation of absorption performance:</heading><p num="0096">The absorbent articles prepared in Examples 6 to 11 and Comparative Examples 2 to 4,
which had the laminate structure of topsheet/(elastic layer)/absorbent member/back sheet
(hereinafter referred to type A), and those having the same structure as type A but the
absorbent member removed therefrom (hereinafter referred to type B) were tested as follows.</p><p num="0097">Five drops of a 65 wt% glycerol solution to which 0.5 wt% of food colorant Blue 1
(available from Aizen K.K.) had been added were dropped on the same point of the topsheet
of the test sample from a height of 10 mm. After 5 minutes from the completion of
dropping, the contour of the spread blue solution was marked and scanned with a scanning
system comprising a light source (Sunlight SL-230K2, available from LPL), a stand (Copy
Stand CS-5, available from LPL), a lens (24 mm/F2.8 Nikkor Lens), a CCD camera (HV-D37, 
available from Hitachi Electronics, Ltd.; the lens connected with an F-mount connector),
and a video board (Spectra 3200, available from Canopus Co., Ltd.). The digital image
information obtained were processed on image analyzing software supplied by NEXUS (ver
3.08) to obtain the area of the spread.</p><p num="0098">The ratio of the spread area on an A type sample to that on a corresponding B type
sample was obtained. The ratio of 0.8 or less was graded &quot;good&quot;, more than 0.8 and less
than 0.9 &quot;medium&quot;, and 0.91 or more &quot;bad&quot;. <img file="00250001.tif" id="img-EP-1128367-A3-00250001" he="247" wi="83" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><p num="0099">In Examples 6 to 11, the elastic recovery force of the elastic layer and the width
direction compressive strain of the panty liner are within the respective ranges specified in the
present invention so that the absorbent articles exhibit satisfactory resistance against
distortion while worn. In particular, the absorbent articles of Examples 8 to 10 have a width
direction compressive strain of 3% or less by virtue of the effects of the compressed parts and
the topsheet and were highly approved of by the panel members. Further, the absorbent
articles of Examples 8 to 11 which have compressed parts exhibited satisfactory absorption
performance.</p><p num="0100">On the other hand, Comparative Example 2 in which the elastic layer has a low elastic
recovery force and Comparative Example 3 having no elastic layer were not exactly approved
of by users with regard to liability to distortion. The absorbent article of Comparative
Example 4 which has a large compressive strain in the width direction did not find much
approval, either.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lage bzw. Schicht (23, 123), die einem absorptionsfähigen Artikel bzw. Gegenstand
(1, 101) eine verbesserte Erholung von einer Verformung verleiht und eine
Erholungskraft von 0,7 cN oder mehr in der Querrichtung, eine Druckfestigkeit von
100 cN oder weniger und ein Flächengewicht von 20 g/m2 oder mehr aufweist, die
umfasst einen thermisch gebundenen Vliesstoff, der 70 Gew.-% oder mehr thermisch
bindungsfähige Konjugatfasern vom Kern-Hüllen-Typ enthält, die an ihren
Überkreuzungsstellen thermisch miteinander fusioniert sind, wobei der Kern ein Olefinpolymer,
einen Polyester oder ein Polyamid umfasst und die Hülle ein Copolymer,
das hauptsächlich Propylen umfasst, ein Copolymer, das hauptsächlich Ethylen
umfasst, oder Polyethylen mit niedriger Dichte umfasst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lage bzw. Schicht (23, 123), die einem absorptionsfähigen Artikel bzw. Gegenstand
(1, 101) eine verbesserte Erholung von einer Verformung verleiht und eine
Erholungskraft von 0,7 cN oder mehr in der Quer-Richtung, eine Druckfestigkeit von
100 cN oder weniger und ein Flächengewicht von 20 g/m2 oder mehr aufweist, die
umfasst einen thermisch gebundenen Vliesstoff, der 70 Gew.-% oder mehr thermisch
bindungsfähige Konjugatfasern vom Kern-Hüllen-Typ enthält, die an ihren
Überkreuzungsstellen thermisch miteinander fusioniert sind, wobei der Kern einen
Polyester oder ein Polyamid umfasst, die Hülle ein Polyethylen mit hoher Dichte
umfasst und die Konjugatfasern eine durchschnittliche Feinheit von 6,6 bis 22 dtex
aufweisen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zur Herstellung einer Lage bzw. Schicht (23, 123) für einen absorptionsfähigen
Artikel bzw. Gegenstand (1, 101), wie sie in Anspruch 1 beschrieben ist,
das umfasst eine Stufe der Wärmebehandlung einer Faserbahn und eine Stufe der
Komprimierung (a) der Faserbahn vor der Wärmebehandlung oder (b) eines thermisch
gebundenen Vliesstoffes, der durch Erhitzen der Faserbahn hergestellt worden
ist, um die Dicke der Faserbahn (a) zu verringern oder um die Dicke des thermisch
gebundenen Vliesstoffes (b) auf 20 bis 80 % der ursprünglichen Dicke zu verringern.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Absorptionsfähiger Artikel bzw. Gegenstand (1, 101), der umfasst eine Flüssigkeit
zurückhaltende absorptionsfähige Schicht (2, 102) und eine für Flüssigkeit
undurchlässige auslaufdichte Schicht (3, 103), worin die absorptionsfähige Schicht
(2, 102) die Lage bzw. Schicht (23, 123) für einen absorptionsfähigen Artikel bzw.
Gegenstand, wie sie in Anspruch 1 beschrieben ist, aufweist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Absorptionsfähiger Artikel bzw. Gegenstand (1, 101), der eine Flüssigkeit zurückhaltende
absorptionsfähige Schicht (2, 102) und eine für Flüssigkeit undurchlässige
auslaufdichte Schicht (3, 103) umfasst, worin die absorptionsfähige Schicht die
Lage bzw. Schicht (23, 123) für einen absorptionsfähigen Artikel bzw. Gegenstand,
wie sie in Anspruch 2 beschrieben ist, aufweist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Absorptionsfähiger Artikel bzw. Gegenstand, der eine im Wesentlichen longitudinale
Gestalt hat und umfasst eine Flüssigkeit zurückhaltende absorptionsfähige
Schicht (2, 102) und eine für Flüssigkeit undurchlässige auslaufdichte Schicht (3,
103), worin die absorptionsfähige Schicht (2, 102) eine Oberflächenschicht (21, 121),
die mit der Haut eines Trägers in Kontakt gebracht werden soll, und eine elastische
Schicht (23, 123) aufweist, die unterhalb der Oberflächenschicht angeordnet ist, wobei
die elastische Schicht (23, 123) eine elastische Erholungskraft von 0,7 cN oder
mehr aufweist und der absorptionsfähige Artikel bzw. Gegenstand (1, 101) eine
Druckverformung von weniger als 5 % in der Breiten-Richtung aufweist, wobei die
elastische Schicht ein thermisch gebundener Vliesstoff ist, der 70 Gew.-% oder mehr
thermisch bindungsfähige Konjugatfasern vom Kern-Hüllen-Typ enthält, die an ihren
Überkreuzungsstellen thermisch miteinander fusioniert sind, wobei der Kern ein Olefinpolymer,
einen Polyester oder ein Polyamid umfasst und die Hülle ein Copolymer,
das hauptsächlich Propylen umfasst, ein Copolymer, das hauptsächlich Ethylen
umfasst, oder ein Polyethylen mit niedriger Dichte umfasst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Absorptionsfähiger Artikel bzw. Gegenstand nach Anspruch 6, worin die absorptionsfähige
Schicht (2, 102) umfasst eine für Flüssigkeit durchlässige Decklage
(21, 121), welche die Oberflächenschicht bildet, ein Flüssigkeit zurückhaltendes absorptionsfähiges
Element (22, 122) und die elastische Schicht (23, 123), die zwischen
der Decklage (21, 121) und dem absorptionsfähigen Element (22, 122) angeordnet
ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Absorptionsfähiger Artikel bzw. Gegenstand nach Anspruch 7, worin die absorptionsfähige
Schicht (102) eine Vielzahl von komprimierten Teilen (104) auf der
Seite der Oberflächenschicht (121) aufweist, wobei die komprimierten Teile (104)
durch Komprimieren mindestens der elastischen Schicht (123) gebildet worden sind,
um die Decklage (121), das absorptionsfähige Element (122) und die elastische
Schicht (123) in den Teilen zu einem Körper zu vereinigen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Absorptionsfähiger Artikel bzw. Gegenstand nach Anspruch 6, der eine Dicke
von 4 mm oder weniger aufweist.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A sheet (23, 123) which gives an absorbent article (1, 101) improved recovery from distortion, which
sheet (23, 123) has a recovery force of 0.7 cN or more in the cross direction, a compressive
strength of 100 cN or less, and a basis weight of 20 g/m2 or more, comprising thermally
bonded nonwoven fabric containing 70% by weight or more of core-sheath type thermally
bonding conjugate fibers which are thermally fused together at their intersections, wherein
the core comprises an olefin polymer, polyester, or polyamide, and the sheath comprises
a copolymer mainly comprising propylene, a copolymer mainly comprising ethylene, or
low-density polyethylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A sheet (23, 123) which gives an absorbent article (1, 101) improved recovery from distortion, which
sheet (23, 123) has a recovery force of 0.7 cN or more in the cross direction, a compressive
strength of 100 cN or less and a basis weight of 20 g/m2 or more, comprising thermally
bonded nonwoven fabric containing 70% by weight or more of core-sheath type thermally
bonding conjugate fibers which are thermally fused together at their intersections, wherein
the core comprises polyester or polyamide, the sheath comprises high-density
polyethylene, and the conjugate fibers have an average fineness of 6.6 dtex to 22 dtex.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process of producing the sheet (23, 123) for an absorbent article (1, 101) described in claim 1,
which includes a step of heat treating a fiber web and a step of compressing (a) said fiber
web before being heat-treated or (b) a thermally bonded nonwoven fabric obtained by
heating said fiber web to reduce the thickness of said fiber web (a) or said thermally
bonded nonwoven fabric (b) to 20 to 80% of the original thickness.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An absorbent article (1, 101) comprising a liquid retentive absorbent layer (2, 102) and a liquid
impermeable leakproof layer (3, 103), wherein said absorbent layer (2, 102) has the sheet (23, 123) for an
absorbent article described in claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An absorbent article (1, 101) comprising a liquid retentive absorbent layer (2, 102) and a liquid
impermeable leakproof layer (3, 103), wherein said absorbent layer has the sheet (23, 123) for an
absorbent article described in claim 2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An absorbent article which has substantially longitudinal shape and comprises a
liquid retentive absorbent layer (2, 102) and a liquid impermeable leakproof layer (3, 103), wherein said
absorbent layer (2, 102) has a surface layer (21, 121) that is to be brought into contact with a wearer's skin
and an elastic layer (23, 123) disposed under said surface layer, said elastic layer (23, 123) having an elastic
recovery force of 0.7 cN or more, and said absorbent article (1,101) has a compressive strain of
less than 5% in the width direction, said elastic layer being a thermally bonded nonwoven
fabric containing 70% by weight or more of core-sheath type thermally bonding conjugate
fibers which are thermally fused together at their intersections, wherein the core
comprises an olefin polymer, polyester, or polyamide, and the sheath comprises a
copolymer mainly comprising propylene, a copolymer mainly comprising ethylene, or low-density
polyethylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The absorbent article according to claim 6, wherein said absorbent layer (2, 102)
comprises a liquid permeable topsheet (21, 121) which forms said surface layer, a liquid retentive
absorbent member (22, 122), and said elastic layer (23, 123) lying between said topsheet (21, 121) and said absorbent
member (22, 122).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The absorbent article according to claim 7, wherein said absorbent layer (102) has a
plurality of compressed parts (104) on the side of said surface layer (121), said compressed parts (104)
being formed by compressing at least said elastic layer (123) to unite said topsheet (121), said
absorbent member (122) and said elastic layer (123) into one body in said parts.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The absorbent article according to claim 6, which has a thickness of 4 mm or
smaller.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Feuille (23, 123) qui donne une recouvrance
élastique améliorée après déformation à un article
absorbant (1, 101), laquelle feuille (23, 123) a une
force de recouvrance élastique de 0,7 cN ou plus dans
le sens travers, une résistance à la compression de
100 cN ou moins et une masse surfacique de 20 g/m2 ou
plus, comprenant un tissu non tissé lié thermiquement
contenant 70% en poids ou plus de fibres conjuguées à
liaison thermique de type coeur/enveloppe qui sont
fusionnées ensemble thermiquement au niveau de leurs
intersections, dans lequel le coeur comprend un polymère
oléfine, un polyester ou un polyamide, et l'enveloppe
comprend un copolymère comprenant principalement du
propylène, un copolymère comprenant principalement de
l'éthylène, ou du polyéthylène basse densité.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Feuille (23, 123) qui donne une recouvrance
élastique améliorée après déformation à un article
absorbant (1, 101), laquelle feuille (23, 123) a une
force de recouvrance élastique de 0,7 cN ou plus dans
le sens travers, une résistance à la compression de
100 cN ou moins et une masse surfacique de 20 g/m2 ou
plus, comprenant un tissu non tissé lié thermiquement
contenant 70% en poids ou plus de fibres conjuguées à
liaison thermique de type coeur/enveloppe qui sont
fusionnées ensemble thermiquement au niveau de leurs
intersections, dans lequel le coeur comprend du
polyester ou du polyamide, l'enveloppe comprend du
polyéthylène haute densité et les fibres conjuguées ont
une finesse moyenne de 6,6 dtex à 22 dtex.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de production de la feuille (23, 123)
pour un article absorbant (1, 101) décrite dans la
revendication 1, qui inclut une étape de traitement par
la chaleur d'une toile de fibres et une étape de
compression (a) de ladite toile de fibres avant qu'elle
ne soit traitée par la chaleur ou (b) d'un tissu non
tissé lié thermiquement obtenu en chauffant ladite
toile de fibres pour réduire l'épaisseur de ladite
toile de fibres (a) ou dudit tissu non tissé lié
thermiquement (b) à une épaisseur de 20% à 80% de
celle d'origine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Article absorbant (1, 101) comprenant une
couche absorbante retenant les liquides (2, 102) et une
couche étanche imperméable aux liquides (3, 103), dans
lequel ladite couche absorbante (2, 102) a la feuille
(23, 123) pour un article absorbant décrite dans la
revendication 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Article absorbant (1, 101) comprenant une
couche absorbante retenant les liquides (2, 102) et une
couche étanche imperméable aux liquides (3, 103), dans
lequel ladite couche absorbante a la feuille (23, 123)
pour un article absorbant décrite dans la revendication
2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Article absorbant qui a une forme
essentiellement allongée et qui comprend une couche
absorbante retenant les liquides (2, 102) et une couche
étanche imperméable aux liquides (3, 103), dans lequel
ladite couche absorbante (2, 102) a une couche de
surface (21, 121) qui est destinée à venir en contact
avec la peau d'un porteur et une couche élastique (23,
123) disposée sous ladite couche de surface, ladite
couche élastique (23, 123) ayant une force de
recouvrance élastique de 0,7 cN ou plus, et ledit
article absorbant (1, 101) a une déformation de
compression inférieure à 5% dans le sens de la largeur,
ladite couche élastique étant un tissu non tissé lié
thermiquement contenant 70% en poids ou plus de fibres
conjuguées à liaison thermique de type coeur/enveloppe
qui sont fusionnées ensemble thermiquement au niveau de
leurs intersections, dans lequel le coeur comprend un
polymère oléfine, un polyester ou un polyamide et
l'enveloppe comprend un copolymère comprenant
principalement du propylène, un copolymère comprenant
principalement de l'éthylène, ou du polyéthylène basse
densité.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Article absorbant selon la revendication 6,
dans lequel ladite couche absorbante (2, 102) comprend
une feuille supérieure perméable aux liquides (21, 121)
qui forme ladite couche de surface, un élément
absorbant retenant les liquides (22, 122), et ladite
couche élastique (23, 123) disposée entre ladite
feuille supérieure (21, 121) et ledit élément absorbant
(22, 122).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Article absorbant selon la revendication 7,
dans lequel ladite couche absorbante (102) a une
pluralité de parties comprimées (104) sur la face de
ladite couche de surface (121), lesdites parties
comprimées (104) étant formées en comprimant au moins
ladite couche élastique (123) pour unir ladite feuille
supérieure (121), ledit élément absorbant (122) et
ladite couche élastique (123) en un corps dans lesdites
parties.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Article absorbant selon la revendication 6,
qui a une épaisseur de 4 mm ou moins.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="EN" date="20060623"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION NOT FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20060419"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060130</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20050602"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60110290</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050602</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050427"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGBSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050427"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040225"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031218</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20020807"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE FR GB SE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20020227"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20011221</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20011121"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20011121"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010829"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGBSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010829"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>
