<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1129932-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1129932" kind="B1" date="20050518"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23212240" ucid="EP-1129932-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1129932</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20050518</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01103471-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01103471</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010214</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000055085-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000055085</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000301</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20041201</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B62M   9/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B62M   9/12        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B62M  23/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B62M  23/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B62M  25/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B62M  25/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H02K   7/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H02K   7/10        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62M23/02H10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62M23/02H2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B62M25/08</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Antriebseinheit für Fahrräder</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Motor-driven bicycle</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Bicyclette à moteur</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HONDA MOTOR CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>HONDA GIKEN KOGYO KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SAKAGAMI KOJI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SAKAGAMI, KOJI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Sakagami, Koji,c/o K.K. Honda Gijutsu Kenkyusho</last-name><address><street>4-1, Chuo 1-chome</street><city>Wako-shi, Saitama</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>HONDA GIKEN KOGYO KABUSHIKI KAISHA</last-name><address><street>1-1, Minami-Aoyama 2-chome</street><city>Minato-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Liska, Horst, Dr.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Weickmann &amp;amp; Weickmann Patentanwälte Postfach 86 08 20</street><city>81635 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>The invention provides a motor-driven bicycle including an automatic gear shifter, which is capable of improving a shift feeling upon gear-shift and controlling a self-running power of a drive motor determined on the basis of an amount of a self-running operation by a driver as a function of a braking state and a vehicle speed. To achieve this, a motor-driven bicycle includes a drive motor M for generating a self-running power in response to a self-running operation by a driver, a gear shifter connected between the drive motor M and a drive wheel, and means for detecting a vehicle speed. This motor-driven bicycle further includes a self-running reference duty ratio map 201 for determining a self-running power to be generated by the drive motor M, that is, a duty ratio of an AC exciting current to be supplied to the drive motor M on the basis of an operated amount of a self-running operation by a driver, a gear step of the gear shifter, and a vehicle speed. In the self-running reference duty ratio map 201, a reference duty ratio Drefl of a drive current to be supplied to the drive motor M at the time of self-running is previously registered as a function of a throttle angle θ th detected by a throttle opening sensor 15. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">The invention provides a motor-driven bicycle including an
automatic gear shifter, which is capable of improving a
shift feeling upon gear-shift and controlling a self-running
power of a drive motor determined on the basis of
an amount of a self-running operation by a driver as a
function of a braking state and a vehicle speed.
To achieve this, a motor-driven bicycle includes a drive
motor M for generating a self-running power in response
to a self-running operation by a driver, a gear shifter
connected between the drive motor M and a drive wheel,
and means for detecting a vehicle speed. This motor-driven
bicycle further includes a self-running reference
duty ratio map 201 for determining a self-running power
to be generated by the drive motor M, that is, a duty
ratio of an AC exciting current to be supplied to the
drive motor M on the basis of an operated amount of a
self-running operation by a driver, a gear step of the
gear shifter, and a vehicle speed. In the self-running
reference duty ratio map 201, a reference duty ratio
Drefl of a drive current to be supplied to the drive
motor M at the time of self-running is previously
registered as a function of a throttle angle <i></i> th detected
by a throttle opening sensor 15.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1129667-A1-00000001" he="84" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a motor-driven bicycle according to the preamble
part of claim 1.</p><p num="0002">Such a bicycle is known from <ref type="patent">EP-A-0 222 179</ref>. This document discloses a motor-driven
bicycle including a drive motor for generating a self-running power in
response to an activation of a twist grip by a driver. The bicycle further includes a
gear shifter connecting between that drive motor and a drive wheel, and means for
detecting a vehicle speed. The known motor-driven bicycle finally comprises
means for determining a self-running power to be generated by the drive motor on
the basis of an amount by which the twist grip has been twisted by the driver. </p><p num="0003">Unlike a motor-assisted bicycle, called an assist bicycle, including an electric
motor for generating an assisting power in response to a leg-power inputted to a
crank shaft, wherein a synthetic power of the leg-power and assisting power is
transmitted to a drive wheel, a motor-driven bicycle including a drive motor for
generating a self-running power in response to, typically, an opening degree of a
throttle lever has been proposed, for example, in <ref type="patent">Japanese Patent Laid-open No.
Hei 9-263289</ref>.</p><p num="0004">A motor-driven bicycle, including a stepping gear shifter different from a
continuous variable transmission mounted on a conventional motor-driven scooter
or the like and an actuator of the stepping gear shifter, has a technical problem
that if a difference occurs between output torques at adjacent two of gear steps
before and after gear-shift, a desirable gear-shift feeling cannot be obtained.</p><p num="0005">The object of the present invention is to solve the above-described problem of the
prior art motor-driven bicycle, and to provide a motor-driven bicycle capable of
obtaining a desirable gear-shift feeling upon automatic gear-shift. </p><p num="0006">To achieve the above object, according to the present invention, there is provided
a motor-driven bicycle according to claim 1, i.e. a bicycle including a drive motor
for generating a self-running power in response to a throttle lever operation by a
driver, a gear shifter connected between the drive motor and a drive wheel, and
means for detecting a vehicle speed, wherein the motor-driven bicycle further
includes self-running power determining means for determining a self-running
power to be generated by the drive motor on the basis of an operated amount of
the throttle lever operation, a gear step of the gear-shifter, and a vehicle speed.</p><p num="0007">The throttle lever operation in the following is also referred to as &quot;self-running
operation&quot;.</p><p num="0008">With the above-described feature, since a self-running power to be generated by
the drive motor can be finely set to an optimum value on the basis of the operated
amount of a self-running operation, a gear-step of the gear shifter, and a vehicle
speed, it is possible to make output torques at adjacent two of gear steps before
and after gear-shift correspond to each other upon gear-shift, and hence to obtain
a desirable shift feeling. </p><p num="0009">In the above prior art motor-driven bicycle, since it is not required to generate a
self-running power in a state in which a brake lever is being operated during
running of the vehicle, the self-running power is limited during operation of the
brake lever for keeping the stored energy; however, since the motor-driven bicycle
is heavier than a conventional bicycle, at the time of start-up of the vehicle on a
slope for example, a self-running power is generated by operating a throttle lever
from the state in which the brake lever is being operated for smoothening the
start-up of the vehicle.</p><p num="0010">In the prior art motor-driven bicycle, however, since the drive motor is not
controlled on the basis of a braking operation and a vehicle speed, there may
occur inconvenience that the drive motor may generate a self-running power
although brake operation is being performed during running of the vehicle or the
drive motor may be difficult to generate, at the time of start-up of the vehicle, a
self-running power from the braking state so as to smoothen the start-up of the
vehicle.</p><p num="0011">To solve the above problem, according to a preferred embodiment of the present
invention, there is provided a motor-driven bicycle exhibiting all features of
dependent claim 8. </p><p num="0012">With the above-described feature, since a self-running power determined on the
basis of an amount of a self-running operating by a driver can be controlled by a
braking operation and a vehicle speed, the self-running power at the time of
braking operation can be optimized.</p><p num="0013">Embodiments of the present invention as defined in the main claim and in the
dependent subclaims may exhibit the following effects:
<sl><li>(1) Since a self-running power to be generated by the drive motor can be set to an
optimum value with the operated amount of a self-running operation, a gear step
of the gear shifter, and a vehicle speed taken as parameters, it is possible to
make output torques at adjacent two of gear steps before and after gear-shift 
correspond to each other upon gear-shift, and hence to
obtain a desirable shift feeling.</li><li>(2) Since a vehicle speed is detected on the basis
of a detection signal of the sensor provided for
detecting a rotational speed of the crank pedals, it is
possible to eliminate the need of provision of a vehicle
speed sensor.</li><li>(3) Since a vehicle speed is detected on the basis
of a rotational speed of the drive motor and a gear step
of the gear shifter, it is possible to eliminate the need
of provision of a vehicle speed sensor.</li><li>(4) Since a gear step of the gear shifter is
detected on the basis of a rotational speed of the drive
motor and a vehicle speed, it is possible to eliminate
the need of provision of a vehicle speed sensor.</li><li>(5) Since a target value of self-running output of
the drive motor determined in response to the operated
amount of a self-running operation is obtained from the
mapping table, it is possible to easily perform the
setting of the target value, the change thereof, and the 
like.</li><li>(6) Since a self-running power determined on the
basis of an amount of a self-running operation by a
driver can be controlled on the basis of the presence or
absence of braking operation and a vehicle speed, the
self-running power at the time of braking operation can
be optimized.</li><li>(7) Since the drive motor is allowed to generate,
when a braking operation is detected during running of
the vehicle, a drive force being small enough to bring
about a state in which no load is apparently applied to
the drive motor, it is possible to prevent useless power
consumption due to operation of the drive motor during
braking operation. Further, since the drive motor does
not cause any rotational load even during braking
operation, it is possible to obtain a natural brake
feeling corresponding to an operated amount of the brake.</li><li>(8) Since the drive motor is allowed to generate,
when a self-running operation is performed in a vehicle
stoppage state in which braking operation is being
performed, a drive force corresponding to an amount of 
the self-running operation, it is possible to prevent
&quot;slip-down&quot; of the vehicle upon start-up of the vehicle
on a slope.</li><li>(9) Since a self-running power generated by the
drive motor is, when a self-running operation is
performed in a vehicle stoppage state in which braking
operation is being performed, gradually increased up to a
value corresponding to an amount of the self-running
operation, it is possible to obtain smooth acceleration
feeling.</li></sl></p><p num="0014">Hereinafter, the present invention will be
described in detail with reference to the accompanying
drawings.
<dl tsize="7"><dt>Fig. 1</dt><dd>is a view showing a configuration of a motor-driven
bicycle to which the present invention is applied.</dd><dt>Fig. 2</dt><dd>is a block diagram of a controller shown in FIG. 1.</dd><dt>Fig. 3</dt><dd>is a flow chart showing an operation of the controller.</dd><dt>Fig. 4</dt><dd>is a flow chart showing a rapid acceleration
suppressing control. </dd><dt>Fig. 5</dt><dd>is a flow chart showing a gear-shift control.</dd><dt>Fig. 6</dt><dd>is a flow chart showing a motor output limiting
control.</dd><dt>Fig. 7</dt><dd>is a view showing a gear-shift control method upon
shift-up from the &quot;second speed&quot; to the &quot;third speed&quot;.</dd><dt>Fig. 8</dt><dd>is a view showing a gear-shift control method upon
shift-down from the &quot;second speed&quot; to the &quot;first speed&quot;.</dd><dt>Fig. 9</dt><dd>is a view showing a gear-shift control method upon
shift-up from the &quot;first speed&quot; to the &quot;second speed&quot;.</dd><dt>Fig. 10</dt><dd>is aview showing a method of setting a gear-shift
vehicle speed Vch23 between the &quot;second speed&quot; and the
&quot;third speed&quot;.</dd><dt>Fig. 11</dt><dd>is a view showing a method of setting a gear-shift
vehicle speed Vch12 between the &quot;first speed&quot; and the
&quot;second speed&quot;.</dd><dt>Fig. 12</dt><dd>is a block diagram of another embodiment of the
controller shown in FIG. 1.</dd></dl></p><p num="0015">FIG. 1 is a view showing a configuration of a
motor-driven bicycle to which the present invention is 
applied. In this figure, parts not necessary for
description of the present invention are omitted.</p><p num="0016">Like a conventional bicycle, a handlebar 10
includes at its left end portion a brake lever 11 for a
rear wheel and at its right end portion a brake lever 13
for a front wheel. The handlebar 10 also includes in the
vicinities of fulcrums of the brake levers 11 and 13
brake switches 12 and 14 for detecting operational states
of the brake levers 11 and 13 and outputting during-braking
signals SB. The handlebar 10 further includes at
its right end portion a throttle lever 16 as self-running
input means for indicating generation of a self-running
power to a drive motor M (which will be described later),
and a throttle opening sensor 15 for detecting an
operated angle th as an operated amount.</p><p num="0017">A body frame has at its central portion a power
unit 2 for selectively carrying out &quot;self-running&quot; by the
drive motor M and &quot;assist-running&quot; for assisting a leg
power by a drive force of the drive motor M. A leg-power
inputted to a crank shaft 30 from left and right crank
pedals 38L and 38R is transmitted via a one-way clutch 26
to a large-diameter gear 36 coaxially connected to the
crank shaft 30, and is further transmitted via a first
idle shaft 35 to an output shaft 34. The one-way clutch
26 allows transmission of a rotational force from the
crank shaft 30 to the large-diameter gear 36, and 
prohibits transmission of a rotational force from the
large-diameter gear 36 to the crank shaft 30.</p><p num="0018">A drive force generated by the drive motor M is
transmitted via a second idle shaft 36 to an idle gear 37.
The idle gear 37 is connected via a one-way clutch 29 to
the first idle shaft 35. The drive force having been
transmitted to the idle gear 37 is transmitted via the
first idle shaft 35 to the output shaft 34. One end of
the output shaft 34 is exposed to the outside of the
power unit 2, and a drive sprocket 32 is connected to the
exposed end of the output shaft 34.</p><p num="0019">A motor rotation sensor 25 detects a rotational
speed NM of the drive motor M. A temperature sensor 24
detects a temperature TM of the drive motor M. A leg-power
sensor 23 detects a leg-power inputted to the crank
shaft 30. A crank pedal rotation sensor 22 detects a
rotational speed of the crank pedals 38 (38L, 38R) on the
basis of the rotational speed of the large-diameter gear
36. A current sensor 27 detects a drive current IM of the
drive motor M. Output signals of the above-described
sensors are inputted to a controller 20. </p><p num="0020">A driven sprocket 33 and a four-step gear shifter
19 are provided on an axle of a rear wheel 31 as a drive
wheel. The drive sprocket 32 of the output shaft 34 is
connected to the driven sprocket 33 via a chain 39. An
automatic gear-shift actuator 17 outputs a gear-shift
step signal DG representative of a gear-shift step in
response to a gear-shift command SG outputted from the
controller 20. The gear shifter 19 is driven on the basis
of the gear-shift step signal DG. A rotational speed V of
the rear wheel 31 is detected by a vehicle speed sensor
18, and a signal of the vehicle speed sensor 18 is
inputted to the controller 20.</p><p num="0021">FIG. 2 is a block diagram showing a configuration
of a main portion of the controller 20. In this figure,
the same characters as those shown in FIG. 1 designate
the same or similar parts.</p><p num="0022">In a self-running reference duty ratio map 201, a
reference duty ratio Dref1 of a drive current IM to be
supplied to the drive motor M upon self-running is
previously registered in the form of a mapping table with
the throttle opening angle th detected by the throttle
opening sensor 15, the vehicle speed V, and a gear step G 
taken as parameters.</p><p num="0023">In an assist-running reference duty ratio map 202,
a reference duty ratio Dref2 of the drive current IM to
be supplied to the drive motor M upon assist-running is
previously registered in the form of a mapping table with
the leg-power F detected by the leg-power sensor 23 and
the vehicle speed V detected by the vehicle speed sensor
18 taken as parameters.</p><p num="0024">It should be noted that in place of detection of
the vehicle speed V by the vehicle speed sensor 18, the
vehicle speed V may be detected, by a vehicle speed
detecting portion 213 additionally provided, on the basis
of the gear-shift step signal DG, which is representative
of the gear-shift step G and which is outputted from the
automatic gear-shift actuator 17, and the motor
rotational speed.</p><p num="0025">An acceleration detecting portion 203 detects an
acceleration ΔV on the basis of a rate of change in
vehicle speed V with elapsed time. A gear step deciding
portion 204 decides the present gear step G on the basis
of the detected vehicle speed V and motor rotational 
speed NM. A rapid acceleration suppressing control
portion 205 compares the detected acceleration ΔV with a
reference acceleration ΔVref, and instructs, if the
detected acceleration ΔV is more than the reference
acceleration ΔVref, a duty ratio correcting portion 208
(which will be described later) to correct a duty ratio
so as to suppress rapid acceleration.</p><p num="0026">Referring to a gear shifting vehicle speed (Vch)
data table 206a, a gear-shift control portion 206 decides,
on the basis of the detected acceleration ΔV and vehicle
speed V and the present gear step G decided by the gear
step deciding portion 204, whether or not the present
running state is a gear-shift timing state. The decided
result is supplied to the duty ratio correcting portion
208 and is also outputted to the gear-shift actuator 17.</p><p num="0027">A non-riding self-running deciding portion 207
decides, on the basis of the present gear step G and
motor rotational speed NM, whether or not the present
self-running operation is performed in the driver's non-riding
state. If it is decided that the self-running
operation is performed in the driver's non-riding state,
a hand-pushing drive control portion 211 instructs the 
duty ratio correcting portion 208 to correct a duty ratio
so as to generate a self-running power corresponding to a
walking speed.</p><p num="0028">A during-braking control portion 210 instructs the
duty ratio correcting portion 208 to correct a duty ratio
so as to control a self-running power on the basis of the
presence or absence of a braking operation and the
vehicle speed V. To be more specific, if the on-states of
the brake switches 12 and 14 are detected during running
of the vehicle, the during-braking control portion 210
instructs the duty ratio correcting portion 208 to
correct a duty ratio so as to allow the drive motor M to
generate a drive force being small enough to bring about
a state in which no load is apparently applied to the
drive motor M. Meanwhile, if a self-running operation is
performed in a vehicle stoppage state in which the brake
switches 12 and 14 are in the on-states, the during-braking
control portion 210 instructs the duty ratio
correcting portion 208 to correct a duty ratio so as to
allow the drive motor M to generate a drive force
corresponding to an operated amount of the self-running
operation. </p><p num="0029">A motor output limiting portion 209 monitors an
operational state of the drive motor M on the basis of
the drive current IM of the drive motor M detected by the
current sensor 27 and the temperature TM of the drive
motor M detected by the temperature sensor 24, and
instructs, if the drive motor M is in a severe
operational state, the duty ratio correcting portion 208
to correct a duty ratio so as to limit the self-running
power.</p><p num="0030">The duty ratio correcting portion 208 corrects, as
will be described in detail later, the reference duty
ratio Dref1 or Dref2 obtained from the duty ratio map 201
or 202 on the basis of the instructions supplied from the
rapid acceleration suppressing control portion 205, the
gear-shift control portion 206, the hand-pushing control
portion 211, the during-braking control portion 210, and
the motor output limiting portion 209, and outputs the
corrected result as a target duty ratio DM.</p><p num="0031">A method of controlling the drive motor M upon
self-running by the controller 20 will be described with
reference to a flow chart shown in FIG. 3. </p><p num="0032">In step S11, an opening angle th of the throttle
lever 16 is detected as an operated amount of the self-running
operation by the throttle opening sensor 15; a
vehicle speed V is detected by a vehicle speed sensor 18;
and a rotational speed NM of the drive motor M is
detected by the motor rotation sensor 25. In step S12, an
acceleration ΔV is calculated on the basis of the vehicle
speed V detected in step S11 by the acceleration
detecting portion 203. In step S13, the present gear step
G is decided on the basis of a correlation between the
vehicle speed V and the motor rotational speed NM by the
gear step deciding portion 204. It should be noted that
the present gear step G may be decided on the basis of
the gear-shift step signal DG outputted from the
automatic gear-shift actuator 17.</p><p num="0033">In step S14, a drive current IM of the drive motor
M is detected by the current sensor 27, and a temperature
TM of the drive motor M is detected by the temperature
sensor 24. In step S15, a reference duty ratio Dref1 upon
self-running is retrieved from the duty ratio map 201 for
self-running on the basis of the throttle opening angle 
th and vehicle speed V detected in step S11 and the
present gear step G decided in step S13. </p><p num="0034">In step S16, on the basis of the states of the
brake switches 12 and 14, it is decided by the during-braking
control portion 210 whether or not a braking
operation has been performed. If it is decided that the
braking operation has not been performed, the process
goes on to step S17. In step S17, on the basis of an
increase ratio ΔNM of the motor rotational speed NM, it
is decided by the non-riding self-running deciding
portion 207 whether or not the driver has operated the
throttle lever 16 in the driver's non-riding state. If
the increase ratio ΔNM of the motor rotational speed NM
is a reference increase ratio ΔNref or more, it is
decided that the driver has operated the throttle lever
16 in the driver's non-riding state, and the process goes
on to step S24. If the increase ratio ΔNM is less than
the reference increase ratio ΔNref, it is decided that
the driver has operated the throttle lever 16 in the
driver's riding state, and the process goes on to step
S18.</p><p num="0035">The parameter for deciding whether or not the
driver has operated the throttle lever 16 in the driver's
non-riding state is not limited to the above-described 
increase ratio ΔNM of the motor rotational speed NM. For
example, the acceleration ΔV may be used as the decision
parameter. In this case, if the acceleration ΔV is
larger than a reference acceleration, it may be decided
that the driver has operated the throttle lever 16 in the
driver's non-riding state. Alternatively, a change ratio
of the drive current of the drive motor M may be used as
the decision parameter. In this case, if the change ratio
of current is larger than a reference change ratio of
current, it may be decided that the driver has operated
the throttle lever 16 in the driver's non-riding state.</p><p num="0036">In this way, according to this embodiment, it is
decided, on the basis of the increase ratio of the motor
rotational speed, acceleration of the vehicle, or the
change ratio of a drive current of the drive motor,
whether or not the self-running operation is performed in
the driver's non-riding state, and accordingly, it is
possible to eliminate the need of providing a sensor or a
switch for detecting the driver's non-riding state.</p><p num="0037">In step S18, a routine of &quot;rapid acceleration
suppressing control&quot; for ensuring a sufficient
acceleration performance while suppressing rapid 
acceleration is executed.</p><p num="0038">FIG. 4 is a flow chart indicating a control content
of the &quot;rapid acceleration suppressing control&quot;. The
control content is determined such that an acceleration
corresponding to an operated amount of the throttle lever
16 can be obtained irrespective of a road surface state,
a deadweight, and the like by controlling a self-running
power of the drive motor M on the basis of a correlation
between an operated amount of the throttle lever 16 and
an acceleration.</p><p num="0039">In step S181, the present acceleration ΔV is
compared with a reference acceleration ΔVref by the rapid
acceleration suppressing control portion 205. If the
acceleration ΔV is more than the reference acceleration
ΔVref, it is decided that the vehicle is in the rapid
acceleration state, and the process goes on to step S182.
In step S182, the reference duty ratio Dref1 retrieved
from the duty ratio map 201 upon self-running is
multiplied by a correction coefficient smaller than &quot;1&quot;
by the duty ratio correcting portion 208, and the
calculated result is taken as a target duty ratio DM. </p><p num="0040">In this embodiment, the correction coefficient is
defined as &quot;0.9<sup>k1</sup>&quot;, and the initial value of the exponent
k1 is set to &quot;1&quot;. Accordingly, in the initial state, a
value being 0.9 times the reference duty ratio Dref1
decided by the map 201 is registered as the target duty
ratio DM. In step S183, the value of the exponent k1 is
incremented by &quot;1&quot;. In step S184, a rapid acceleration
suppressing flag F1 is set to &quot;1&quot;.</p><p num="0041">After that, since the above steps are repeated to
increase the value of the exponent k1 until it is decided
in step S181 that the acceleration ΔV is less than the
reference acceleration ΔVref, the target duty ratio DM is
gradually reduced depending on the value of the exponent
k1.</p><p num="0042">If it is decided in step S181, as a result of
gradually reducing the target duty ratio DM, that the
acceleration ΔV is less than the reference acceleration
ΔVref, the process goes on to step S185 in which it is
decided that the rapid acceleration suppressing flag F1
is &quot;1&quot;. If it is decided that the flag F1 is set to &quot;1&quot;,
the process goes on to step S186 in which the duty ratio
having been gradually reduced in step S182 is gradually 
increased.</p><p num="0043">In step S186, the present target duty ratio DM is
multiplied by a correction coefficient smaller than &quot;1&quot;,
and the calculated result is taken as a new target duty
ratio DM. In this embodiment, the correction coefficient
is defined as a value of &quot;0.9<sup>k2</sup>&quot;, and the initial value of
the exponent k2 is set to &quot;5&quot;. In the initial state, a
value being 0.59 (= 0.95) times the target duty ratio DM
is taken as a target duty ratio DM.</p><p num="0044">In step S187, it is decided whether or not the
exponent k2 is reduced to &quot;0&quot;. Since the exponent k2 is
&quot;5&quot; in the initial state, the process goes on to step
S188. In step S188, the value of the exponent k2 is
decremented by &quot;1&quot;. If it is decided in step S187 that
the exponent k2 is &quot;0&quot;, the process goes on to step S189
in which the rapid acceleration suppressing flag F1 is
reset, thereby ending the routine of &quot;rapid acceleration
suppressing control&quot; shown in FIG. 4.</p><p num="0045">In this way, according to this embodiment, if the
acceleration ΔV is more than the reference acceleration
ΔVref, the correction coefficient is, in step S182, 
gradually reduced for gradually reducing the target duty
ratio DM, and thereafter, if the acceleration ΔV is less
than the reference acceleration ΔVref, the correction
coefficient is, in step S186, gradually increased for
gradually increasing the target duty ratio DM, thereby
compensating for the above-described gradually reduced
amount of the target duty ratio DM. Accordingly, it is
possible to obtain a sufficient acceleration performance
while suppressing rapid acceleration.</p><p num="0046">Referring again to FIG. 3, in step S19, it is
decided by the gear-shift control portion 206 whether or
not automatic gear-shift should be performed. If an
absolute value of a difference between the present
vehicle speed V and a gear-shift vehicle speed Vch stored
in the gear-shift vehicle speed data table 206a for each
gear step is less than a reference speed VA, the process
goes on to step S20 in which a &quot;gear-shift control&quot; is
executed for automatic gear-shift. As the gear-shift
vehicle speed Vch, a gear-shift vehicle speed Vch12
indicating a gear-shift timing between &quot;first speed&quot;/&quot;second
speed&quot;, a gear-shift vehicle speed Vch23
indicating a gear-shift timing between &quot;second speed&quot;/&quot;third
speed&quot;, and a gear-shift vehicle speed Vch34 
indicating a gear-shift timing between &quot;third
speed&quot;/&quot;fourth speed&quot; are registered. Either of the gear-shift
vehicle speeds Vch12, Vch23, and Vch34 is selected
on the basis of the present gear step G.</p><p num="0047">FIG. 5 is a flow chart indicating the routine of
the &quot;gear-shift control&quot;, which mainly shows the
operation of the gear-shift control portion 206.</p><p num="0048">In step S201, it is decided whether or not a
variation in torque caused by gear-shift is increased or
decreased. For example, upon shift-up from the &quot;second
speed&quot; to the &quot;third speed&quot;, as shown in FIG. 7, a torque
at the &quot;third speed&quot; is larger than that of the &quot;second
speed&quot; at the gear-shift vehicle speed Vch23, and
accordingly, it is decided in step S201 that the torque
is increased after gear-shift, and the process goes on to
step S202. Similarly, upon shift-down from the &quot;second
speed&quot; to the &quot;first speed&quot;, as shown in FIG. 8, a torque
at the &quot;first speed&quot; is larger than that of the &quot;second
speed&quot; at the gear-shift vehicle speed Vch12, and
accordingly, it is decided in step S201 that the torque
is increased after gear-shift, and the process goes on to
step S202. </p><p num="0049">In step S202, referring to the gear-shift vehicle
speed data table 206a, the gear-shift control portion 206
decides whether or not the present vehicle speed V
reaches a predetermined gear-shift vehicle speed Vch
corresponding to the present gear step. Here, if it is
decided that, as shown in FIG. 7, the vehicle speed V
reaches the gear-shift vehicle speed Vch23 during running
at the &quot;second speed&quot; and thereby the timing of shift-up
to the &quot;third speed&quot; comes, the process goes on to step
S203 in which the gear-shift actuator 17 is driven for
gear-shift (shift-up). In step S204, the present target
duty ratio DM is multiplied by a correction coefficient
smaller than &quot;1&quot;, and the calculated result is taken as a
new target duty ratio DM.</p><p num="0050">According to this embodiment, the correction
coefficient is defined as &quot;0.9<sup>k3</sup>&quot;, and the initial value
of the exponent k3 is set to &quot;5&quot;. Accordingly, in the
initial state, a value being 0.59 times (= 0.95) the
present target duty ratio DM is taken as a target duty
ratio DM. As a result, as shown in FIG. 7, a torque
immediately after shift-up to the &quot;third speed&quot; is
lowered to the same level as that of a torque at the 
&quot;second speed&quot;, with a result that it is possible to
obtain a desirable shift feeling.</p><p num="0051">In step S205, it is decided whether or not the
exponent k3 is &quot;0&quot;. Since the exponent k3 is &quot;5&quot; in the
initial state, the process goes on to step S207 in which
the exponent k3 is decremented by &quot;1&quot;.</p><p num="0052">After that, the above-described steps are repeated,
to gradually reduce the value of exponent k3, thereby
gradually reducing the target duty ratio DM. Accordingly,
as shown in FIG. 7, a self-running power of the drive
motor M is rapidly reduced at the gear-shift vehicle
speed Vch23, and then gradually increased to be returned
to the original target duty ratio DM, thereby obtaining a
proper torque corresponding to the gear step.</p><p num="0053">Similarly, as shown in FIG. 8, even in the case
where the vehicle speed V is lowered to the gear-shift
vehicle speed Vch12 during running at the &quot;second speed&quot;
to be thus shifted down to the &quot;first speed&quot;, the target
duty ratio DM is reduced such that a torque immediately
after shift-down to the &quot;first speed&quot; is reduced to the
same level as that of a torque at the &quot;second speed&quot;, and 
then the target duty ratio DM is gradually increased to
be returned to the original target duty ratio DM, thereby
obtaining a desirable shift feeling.</p><p num="0054">On the other hand, upon shift-up from the &quot;first
speed&quot; to the &quot;second speed&quot;, as shown in FIG. 9, since a
torque at the &quot;second speed&quot; is smaller than a torque at
the &quot;first speed&quot; at the gear-shift vehicle speed Vch12,
it is decided in step S201 that the torque is reduced
after gear-shift, and the process goes on to step S208 in
which it is decided whether or not the present vehicle
speed V reaches a predetermined gear-shift vehicle speed
Vch12. If it is decided that the vehicle speed does not
reach the gear-shift vehicle speed Vch12, the process
goes on to step S209 in which the present target duty
ratio DM is multiplied by a correction coefficient
smaller than &quot;1&quot; and the calculated result is taken as a
new target duty ratio DM.</p><p num="0055">In this embodiment, the correction coefficient is
defined as &quot;0.9<sup>k4</sup>&quot;, and the initial value of the exponent
k4 is set to &quot;1&quot;. Accordingly, in the initial state, a
value being 0.9 times the present target duty ratio DM is
taken as a target duty ratio. In step S210, the exponent 
k4 is incremented by &quot;1&quot;.</p><p num="0056">After that, the above-described steps are repeated
until it is decided in step S208 that the vehicle speed V
reaches the gear-shift vehicle speed Vch12, whereby the
target duty ratio DM is gradually reduced according to
the value of the exponent k4. Accordingly, as shown in
FIG. 9, the torque is gradually reduced.</p><p num="0057">If it is decided in step S208 that the vehicle
speed V reaches the gear-shift vehicle speed Vch12, the
process goes on to step S211 in which the gear-shift
actuator is driven for gear-shift. At this time,
according to this embodiment, since a torque at the
&quot;first speed&quot; is reduced to the same level as that of a
torque at the &quot;second speed&quot; as shown in FIG. 9, that is,
no difference in output torque lies between before and
after gear-shift, it is possible to obtain a desirable
shift feeling. In step S212, the exponent k4 is set to
&quot;1&quot;, thereby completing the routine of the &quot;gear-shift
control&quot; shown in FIG. 5.</p><p num="0058">In the above description, to improve the shift
feeling upon gear-shift, the duty ratio of a current 
supplied to the drive motor M is corrected such that
torques of adjacent two of gear steps before and after
gear-shift are made to substantially correspond to each
other, the present invention is not limited thereto. For
example, as shown in FIGS. 10 and 11, the gear-shift
vehicle speed Vch, typically, Vch12 or Vch23 may be set
to a speed at which torque curves of adjacent two of gear
steps before and after gear-shift intersect each other,
or a neighborhood of the speed. With this configuration,
it is also possible to improve the shift feeling upon
gear-shift.</p><p num="0059">Referring again to FIG. 3, in step S23, a routine
of &quot;motor output limiting control&quot; for preventing a
severe operation of the drive motor is executed. The
&quot;motor output limiting control&quot; will be described below
with reference to a flow chart shown in FIG. 6.</p><p num="0060">In step S231, on the basis of a motor drive current
IM detected by the current sensor 27 and the present
target duty ratio DM, the present output Pout of the
drive motor M is calculated. In step S232, the present
output Pout of the drive motor M is compared with a
specific maximum output Pmax. The maximum output Pmax is 
preferably set to a value being about two times the
maximum rating of the drive motor M and is, in this
embodiment, set to a value being 1.5 times the maximum
rating.</p><p num="0061">Here, if it is decided in step S232 that the
present output Pout is equal to or more than the maximum
output Pmax, the process goes on to step S233 in which
the target duty ratio DM is set to a specific maximum
value Dmax. In step S234, a temperature TM of the drive
motor M detected by the temperature sensor 24 is compared
with a reference temperature Tref. In this embodiment,
the reference temperature Tref is set to 90°C.</p><p num="0062">Here, if the temperature TM is the reference
temperature Tref or more, the process goes on to step
S235 in which the present target duty ratio DM is
multiplied by a correction coefficient smaller than &quot;1&quot;
and the calculated result is taken as a new target duty
ratio DM. In this embodiment, the correction coefficient
is defined as &quot;0.5<sup>k5</sup>&quot;, and the initial value of the
exponent k5 is set to &quot;1&quot;. Accordingly, a value being 0.5
times the present target duty ratio DM is taken as a
target duty ratio DM. In step S236, the exponent k5 is 
incremented by &quot;1&quot;.</p><p num="0063">On the other hand, if it is decided in step S234
that the temperature TM is less than the reference
temperature Tref, the process goes on to step S236 in
which the exponent k5 is set to the initial value &quot;1&quot;.</p><p num="0064">In this way, according to this embodiment, since
the output of the drive motor M is limited and also if
the temperature of the drive motor M is increased, the
target duty ratio DM is gradually reduced, it is possible
to prevent a severe operation of the drive motor M. Also,
since the upper limit of the output of the drive motor M
lies within a range being two times the rating of the
drive motor M, it is possible to obtain a self-running
power from the drive motor M without a severe operation
of the drive motor M.</p><p num="0065">Referring again to FIG. 3, in step S25, a control
of a current of the drive motor M based on the target
duty ratio thus determined is executed.</p><p num="0066">Additionally, if it is decided in step S16 whether
or not either of the brake switches 12 and 14 is in the 
on-state, that is, the vehicle is on braking, the process
goes on to step S21. In step S21, it is decided, on the
basis of the vehicle speed V, whether or not the vehicle
is on running.</p><p num="0067">Here, if the vehicle speed V is larger than &quot;0&quot;, it
is decided in step S21 that the vehicle is on running,
and the process goes on to step S22. In step S22, a value
being 20% (or which may be 0%) of the present target duty
ratio DM, or a value being 20% (or which may be 0%) of
the maximum value Dmax of the target duty ratio is set as
a target duty ratio DM for allowing the drive motor M to
generate a drive force being small enough to bring about
a state in which no load is apparently applied to the
drive motor M.</p><p num="0068">If it is decided in step S21 that the vehicle is on
stoppage, the process goes on to step S186 of the above-described
routine of &quot;rapid acceleration suppressing
control&quot; shown in FIG. 4. As a result, the target duty
ratio DM is rapidly reduced, and then gradually increased.</p><p num="0069">In this way, according to this embodiment, if a
self-running operation is performed in a stoppage state 
of the vehicle with braking actuated, a self-running
power to be generated by the drive motor is gradually
increased to a value corresponding to an operated amount
of self-running, it is possible to prevent &quot;slip-down&quot; of
the vehicle upon start-up of the vehicle on a slope.</p><p num="0070">It is decided in step S17 that the vehicle is in
the driver's non-riding state, the process goes on to
step S24. In step S24, to allow the drive motor M to
generate a self-running power optimum for hand-pushing
drive of the vehicle, a value being 20% of the present
target duty ratio DM, or a value being 20% of the maximum
value Dmax of the target duty ratio is set as a new
target duty ratio DM.</p><p num="0071">In this way, according to this embodiment, since a
self-running power matched to a walking speed can be
generated by using the self-running operation input means
(throttle lever 16) for generating a usual self-running
power, the motor-drive bicycle in this embodiment is
allowed to achieve a self-running function matched to a
walking speed without provision of a plurality of self-running
operation input means. </p><p num="0072">Further, according to this embodiment, it is
decided whether or not a self-running operation is
performed in the driver's non-riding state, and a self-running
power matched to a walking speed is generated
only when it is decided that the self-running operation
is performed in the driver's non-riding state, and
accordingly, it is possible to eliminate an inconvenience
that a self-running power matched to a walking speed is
outputted in the driver's riding state.</p><p num="0073">In the above-described embodiment, the rotational
speed of the drive wheel 31 is directly detected by the
vehicle speed sensor 18 and the vehicle speed V is
detected on the basis of the rotational speed of the
drive wheel 31; however, the present invention is not
limited thereto. For example, the vehicle speed V may be
calculated on the basis of the rotational speed NM of the
drive motor M detected by the motor rotation sensor 25
and the gear step G. Alternatively, the vehicle speed V
may be calculated on the basis of the rotational speed of
the crank pedals 38 detected by the crank pedal rotation
sensor 22 and the gear step G.</p><p num="0074">In the above-described embodiment, the reference 
duty ratio Dref1 of the drive current IM to be supplied
to the drive motor M during self-running is registered,
in the self-running reference duty ratio map 201, as the
function of the throttle opening angle th, the vehicle
speed V, and the gear step G; however, the present
invention is not limited thereto. For example, as shown
in FIG. 12, only a relationship between the reference
duty ratio Dref1 and the throttle opening angle th may
be registered, as a map, in the self-running reference
duty ratio map 201, and the reference duty ratio Dref1
retrieved on the basis of the throttle opening angle th
may be suitably corrected on the basis of the vehicle
speed V and the gear step G by the correcting portion 213. </p><p num="0075">The invention provides a motor-driven bicycle including an
automatic gear shifter, which is capable of improving a
shift feeling upon gear-shift and controlling a self-running
power of a drive motor determined on the basis of
an amount of a self-running operation by a driver as a
function of a braking state and a vehicle speed.
To achieve this, a motor-driven bicycle includes a drive
motor M for generating a self-running power in response
to a self-running operation by a driver, a gear shifter
connected between the drive motor M and a drive wheel,
and means for detecting a vehicle speed. This motor-driven
bicycle further includes a self-running reference
duty ratio map 201 for determining a self-running power
to be generated by the drive motor M, that is, a duty
ratio of an AC exciting current to be supplied to the
drive motor M on the basis of an operated amount of a
self-running operation by a driver, a gear step of the
gear shifter, and a vehicle speed. In the self-running
reference duty ratio map 201, a reference duty ratio
Dref1 of a drive current to be supplied to the drive
motor M at the time of self-running is previously
registered as a function of a throttle angle th detected 
by a throttle opening sensor 15. A during-braking control
portion 210 decides whether or not braking operation is
performed on the basis of the states of brake switches 12
and 14, and receives a vehicle speed V detected by a
vehicle speed sensor 18. A duty ratio correcting portion
208 corrects the reference duty ratio Dref1 obtained from
the duty ratio map 201 on the basis of a control signal
from the during-braking control portion 210.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad, das einen Antriebsmotor (M) enthält, der
dafür ausgelegt ist, eine Selbstfahrleistung in Reaktion auf eine Fahrhebelbetätigung
von einem Fahrer zu erzeugen, eine Gangwechselvorrichtung (19),
die zwischen dem Antriebsmotor (M) und einem Antriebsrad (31) angeordnet
und verbunden ist, Mittel zum Erfassen einer Fahrzeuggeschwindigkeit, und
ein Selbstfahrleistungsbestimmungsmittel (20), das dafür ausgelegt ist, eine
Selbstfahrleistung, die vom Antriebsmotor zu erzeugen ist, auf der Grundlage
eines Betätigungsmaßes des Fahrhebels (16) zu bestimmen, dadurch
gekennzeichnet, dass
   das Selbstfahrleistungsbestimmungsmittel (20) ferner dafür ausgelegt
ist, die Selbstfahrleistung auf der Grundlage einer Getriebestufe der
Gangwechselvorrichtung und einer Fahrzeuggeschwindigkeit (V) zusätzlich
zum Betätigungsmaß des Fahrhebels (16) zu bestimmen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrzeug nach Anspruch 1, das ferner enthält:
<claim-text><claim-text>Kurbelpedale (38L, R);</claim-text><claim-text>eine Abtriebswelle (34), auf die die vom Antriebsmotor (M) erzeugte
Antriebskraft übertragen wird;</claim-text><claim-text>einen Rotor (36), der zwischen den Kurbelpedalen und der Abtriebswelle
angeordnet und verbunden ist, wobei dem Rotor erlaubt wird, eine von
den Kurbelpedalen eingegebene Beinkraft und eine in die Abtriebswelle
eingegebene Antriebskraft aufzunehmen und mittels der Beinkraft und der
Antriebskraft zu rotieren, und nicht erlaubt wird, die Kurbelpedale einhergehend
mit seiner Rotation zu drehen; und</claim-text><claim-text>einen Kurbelsensor (22) zum Erfassen einer Drehzahl des Rotors;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wobei die Fahrzeuggeschwindigkeit (V) auf der Grundlage der vom
Kurbelsensor erfassten Drehzahl des Rotors erfasst wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach Anspruch 1,
   das ferner einen Rotationssensor (25) zum Erfassen einer Drehzahl
des Antriebsmotors (M) enthält, wobei die Fahrzeuggeschwindigkeit (V) auf
der Grundlage der Drehzahl des Antriebsmotors und einer Getriebestufe der
Gangwechselvorrichtung (19) erfasst wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach Anspruch 1,
   das ferner einen Rotationssensor (25) zum Erfassen einer Drehzahl
des Antriebsmotors (M) enthält, wobei die Getriebestufe der Gangwechselvorrichtung
(19) auf der Grundlage der Drehzahl des Antriebsmotors (M) und
der Fahrzeuggeschwindigkeit (V) festgelegt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach Anspruch 1,
   wobei das Selbstfahrbestimmungsmittel (20) eine Kennfeldtabelle
(201) aufweist, um eine vom Antriebsmotor (M) zu erzeugende Selbstfahrleistung
vorzugeben, wobei die Leistung der jeweiligen Getriebestufe der
Gangwechselvorrichtung entspricht, wobei das Betätigungsmaß der Fahrhebelbetätigung
und die Fahrzeuggeschwindigkeit (V) als Parameter genommen
werden.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach irgendeinem der vorangehenden
Ansprüche,
   bei dem das Selbstfahrleistungsbestimmungsmittel (20) enthält:
<claim-text><claim-text>eine Kennfeldtabelle (201) zum Vorgeben einer Selbstfahrleistung,
die vom Antriebsmotor (M) zu erzeugen ist, wobei das Betätigungsmaß der
Fahrhebelbetätigung als Parameter genommen wird; und</claim-text><claim-text>ein Korrekturmittel (208) zum Korrigieren der von der Kennfeldtabelle
(201) vorgegebenen Selbstfahrleistung auf der Grundlage der Fahrzeuggeschwindigkeit
(V) und einer Getriebestufe der Gangwechselvorrichtung.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach Anspruch 5 oder 6, bei dem die vom
Antriebsmotor (M) erzeugte Selbstfahrleistung gesteuert wird, indem ein
Tastverhältnis (Dref1) eines Erregerwechselstroms, der dem Antriebsmotor
(M) zuzuführen ist, variiert wird, wobei ein Tastverhältnis (Dref2) des Erregerwechselstroms,
das einer spezifischen Selbstfahrleistung entspricht, in
der Kennfeldtabelle registriert ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach irgendeinem der vorangehenden
Ansprüche,
   dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
das Fahrrad Mittel (12, 14) enthält zum Erfassen einer Bremsbetätigung und
von Ausgangssignalen, die eine Bremsbetätigung anzeigen, sowie ein
Steuermittel (210), das dafür ausgelegt ist, die Selbstfahrleistung auf der
Grundlage der Signale, die eine Bremsoperation anzeigen, bzw. einer
Fahrzeuggeschwindigkeit (V) zu steuern.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach Anspruch 8,
   bei dem dann, wenn eine Bremsbetätigung während des Fahrens
des Fahrzeugs erfasst wird, das Steuermittel (210) dem Antriebsmotor (M)
erlaubt, eine Antriebskraft zu erzeugen, die klein genug ist, um einen Zustand
herbeizuführen, in welchem scheinbar keine Last auf den Antriebsmotor
(M) ausgeübt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach Anspruch 8 oder 9,
   bei dem dann, wenn die Fahrhebeloperation in einem Fahrzeugstoppzustand
durchgeführt wird, in welchem die Bremsbetätigung
durchgeführt wird, das Steuermittel (210) dem Antriebsmotor (M) erlaubt,
eine Antriebskraft entsprechend einem Maß der Fahrhebelbetätigung zu
erzeugen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach Anspruch 9,
   bei dem eine Antriebskraft, die klein genug ist, um einen Zustand
herbeizuführen, in welchem scheinbar keine Last auf den Antriebsmotor (M)
ausgeübt wird, ein Wert ist, der ein Selbstfahren bei einer Gehgeschwindigkeit
oder &quot;0&quot; erlaubt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motorgetriebenes Fahrrad nach Anspruch 10,
   bei dem dann, wenn die Fahrhebelbetätigung ausgehend vom
Fahrzeugstoppzustand durchgeführt wird, in welchem die Bremsbetätigung
durchgeführt wird, das Steuermittel (210) die vom Antriebsmotor erzeugte
Selbstfahrleistung allmählich bis zu einem Wert erhöht, der dem Maß der
Fahrhebelbetätigung entspricht.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle including a drive motor (M) adapted to generate a
self-running power in response to a throttle lever operation by a driver, a
gear shifter (19) connected between said driven motor (M) and a drive
wheel (31), means for detecting a vehicle speed, and
self-running power determining means (20) adapted to determine a self-running
power to be generated by said drive motor, on the basis of an
operated amount of the throttle lever (16), characterized in that
said self-running power determining means (20) is further adapted to
determine said self-running power, in addition to the operated amount of
said throttle lever (16), on the basis of a gear step of said gear-shifter, and
a vehicle speed (V).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to claim 1,
further including:
<claim-text><claim-text>crank pedals (38L; R);</claim-text><claim-text>an output shaft (34) to which a drive force generated by said drive motor
(M) is transmitted;</claim-text><claim-text>a rotator (36) connected between said crank pedals and said output shaft,
said rotator being allowed to receive a leg-power inputted from said crank
pedals and the drive force inputted to said output shaft and to rotate by the
leg-power and the drive force and not allowed to rotate said crank pedals
accompanied by its rotation; and</claim-text><claim-text>a crank sensor (22) for detecting a rotational speed of said rotator;</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the vehicle speed (V) is detected on the basis of the rotational
speed of said rotator detected by said crank sensor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to claim 1,
further including a rotation sensor (25) for detecting a rotational speed of
said drive motor (M), wherein the vehicle speed (V) is detected on the basis
of the rotational speed of said drive motor and a gear step of said gear
shifter (19).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to claim 1,
further including a rotation sensor (25) for detecting a rotational speed of
said drive motor (M), wherein the gear step of said gear shifter (19) is
decided on the basis of the rotational speed of said drive motor (M) and the
vehide speed (V).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to claim 1,
wherein said self-running determining means (20) has a mapping table
(201) for giving a self-running power to be generated by said drive motor
(M), which power corresponds to each gear step of said gear shifter, with
the operated amount of the throttle lever operation and the vehicle speed
(V) taken as parameters.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to one of the preceding claims,
wherein said self-running power determining means (20) includes:
<claim-text><claim-text>a mapping table (201) for giving a self-running power to be generated by
said drive motor (M) with the operated amount of the throttle lever operation
taken as parameters; and</claim-text><claim-text>correcting means (208) for correcting the self-running power given by said
mapping table (201) on the basis of the vehicle speed (V) and a gear step
of said gear shifter.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to claim 5 or 6,
wherein the self-running power generated by said drive motor (M) is
controlled by varying a duty ratio (Dref1) of an AC exciting current to be
supplied to said drive motor (M), and a duty ratio (Dref2) of the AC exciting
current corresponding to a specific self-running power is registered in said
mapping table.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to one of the preceding claims,
characterized in that
said bicycle includes means (12, 14) for detecting a braking operation and
outputting signals indicating a braking operation and a control means (210)
adapted to control said self-running power on the basis of said signals
indicating a braking operation and a vehicle speed (V), respectively.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to claim 8,
wherein when the braking operation is detected during running of the
vehicle, said control means (210) allows said drive motor (M) to generate a
drive force being small enough to bring about a state in which no load is
apparently applied to said drive motor (M).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to claim 8 or 9,
wherein when the throttle lever operation is performed in a vehicle
stoppage state in which the braking operation is performed, said control
means (210) allows said drive motor (M) to generate a drive force
corresponding to an amount of the throttle lever operation.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to claim 9,
wherein the drive force being small enough to bring about a state in which
no load is apparently applied to said drive motor (M) is a value allowing self-running
at a walking speed or &quot;0&quot;.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor-driven bicycle according to claim 10,
wherein when the throttle lever operation is performed from the vehicle
stoppage state in which the braking operation is performed, said control
means (210) gradually increases the self-running power generated by said
drive motor up to a value corresponding to the amount of the throttle lever
operation.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur
comprenant un moteur d'entraínement (M) adapté pour
générer une puissance de roulement automatique en
réponse à l'actionnement d'un levier d'étranglement
par un conducteur, un dispositif de changement de
vitesse (19) raccordé entre ledit moteur
d'entraínement (M) et une roue motrice (31), des
moyens pour détecter une vitesse de véhicule, et
   des moyens de détermination d'une puissance
de roulement automatique (20) adaptés pour déterminer
une puissance de roulement automatique devant être
générée par ledit moteur d'entraínement, sur la base
d'une valeur appliquée du levier d'étranglement (16)
caractérisée en ce que
   lesdits moyens de détermination de la
puissance de roulement automatique (20) sont adaptés
en outre pour déterminer ladite puissance de roulement
automatique, en plus de la valeur appliquée dudit
levier d'étranglement (16) sur la base d'un rapport de
boíte dudit dispositif de changement de vitesse, et
une vitesse de véhicule (V).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon la
revendication 1, comprenant en outre :
<claim-text><claim-text>des pédales à manivelle (38L ; R) ;</claim-text><claim-text>un arbre de sortie (34) auquel est transmise
une force motrice générée par ledit moteur
d'entraínement (M) ;</claim-text><claim-text>un rotateur (36) raccordé entre lesdites
pédales à manivelle et ledit arbre de sortie, ledit
rotateur pouvant recevoir une puissance appliquée par
la jambe, sur lesdites pédales à manivelle et la force
motrice appliquée audit arbre de sortie et entraínée
en rotation par la puissance de jambe et la force
motrice et ne pouvant pas faire tourner lesdites
pédales à manivelle accompagnées par sa rotation ; et</claim-text><claim-text>un capteur (22) destiné à détecter une
vitesse de rotation dudit rotateur ; dans lequel la
vitesse de véhicule (V) est détectée sur la base de la
vitesse de rotation dudit rotateur détectée par ledit
capteur.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon la
revendication 1, comprenant en outre un détecteur de
rotation (25) pour détecter une vitesse de rotation
dudit moteur d'entraínement (M), dans laquelle la
vitesse de véhicule (V) est détectée sur la base de la
vitesse de rotation dudit moteur d'entraínement et un
rapport de boite dudit dispositif de changement de
vitesse (19).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon la
revendication 1, comprenant en outre un détecteur de
rotation (25) pour détecter une vitesse de rotation
dudit moteur d'entraínement (M), dans laquelle le
rapport de boíte dudit dispositif de changement de
vitesse (19) est fixé sur la base de la vitesse de
rotation dudit moteur d'entraínement (M) et de la
vitesse de véhicule (V).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon la
revendication 1, dans laquelle lesdits moyens de
détermination du roulement automatique (20) ont un
index (201) pour donner une puissance de roulement
automatique devant être générée par ledit moteur
d'entraínement (M) dont la puissance correspond à
chaque rapport de boíte dudit dispositif de changement
de vitesse, la valeur appliquée par l'actionnement du
levier d'étranglement et la vitesse de véhicule (V)
étant prises comme paramètres.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon
l'une des revendications précédentes, dans laquelle
lesdits moyens de détermination (20) de la puissance
de roulement automatique comprennent :
<claim-text><claim-text>un index (201) pour donner une puissance de
roulement automatique devant être générée par ledit
moteur d'entraínement (M) la valeur appliquée par
l'actionnement du levier d'étranglement étant prise
comme paramètres ; et</claim-text><claim-text>des moyens de correction (208) destinés à
corriger la puissance de roulement automatique donnée
par ledit index (201) sur la base de la vitesse du
véhicule (V) et d'un rapport de boíte dudit dispositif
de changement de vitesse.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon la
revendication 5 ou 6, dans laquelle la puissance de
roulement automatique générée par ledit moteur
d'entraínement (M) est commandée en variant un facteur
de marche (Dref1) d'un courant d'excitation alternatif
devant être fourni audit moteur d'entraínement (M), et
un facteur de marche (Dref2) du courant d'excitation
alternatif correspondant à une puissance spécifique de
roulement automatique est enregistré dans ledit index.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon
l'une des revendications précédentes, caractérisée en
ce que ladite bicyclette comprend des moyens (12, 14)
destinés à détecter une opération de freinage et des
signaux de sortie indiquant une opération de freinage
et des moyens de commande (210) adaptés pour commander
ladite puissance de roulement automatique sur la base
desdits signaux indiquant une opération de freinage et
une vitesse de véhicule (V), respectivement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon la
revendication 8, dans laquelle lorsque l'opération de
freinage est détectée pendant le fonctionnement du
véhicule, lesdits moyens de commande (210) permettent
audit moteur d'entraínement (M) de générer une force
motrice suffisamment petite pour provoquer un état
dans lequel aucune charge n'est apparemment appliquée
audit moteur d'entraínement (M).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon
les revendications 8 ou 9, dans laquelle le
fonctionnement du levier d'étranglement est réalisé
dans un état d'arrêt du véhicule dans lequel
l'opération de freinage est réalisée, lesdits moyens
de commande (210) permettent audit moteur
d'entraínement (M) de générer une force motrice
correspondant à une valeur du fonctionnement du levier
d'étranglement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon la
revendication 9, dans laquelle la force motrice
suffisamment petite pour provoquer un état dans lequel
aucune charge n'est apparemment appliquée audit moteur
d'entraínement (M), est une valeur permettant le
roulement automatique à une vitesse de marche ou
« 0 ».</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bicyclette entraínée par moteur selon la
revendication 10, dans laquelle lorsque le
fonctionnement du levier d'étranglement est effectué à
partir de l'état d'arrêt du véhicule dans lequel
l'opération de freinage est réalisée, lesdits moyens
de commande (210) augmentent progressivement la
puissance de roulement automatique générée par ledit
moteur d'entraínement jusqu'à une valeur correspondant
à la valeur d'actionnement du levier d'étranglement.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20070321"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>BE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DK</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050518</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050518</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050518</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050818</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050818</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050818</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20051024</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060214</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20070105"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ST</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20061031</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20061115"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MM4A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="GBPC" date="20061025"><legal-event-body><event-title>GB: EUROPEAN PATENT CEASED THROUGH NON-PAYMENT OF RENEWAL FEE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060214</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20061013"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20060510"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060221</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20060407"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20051101"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ES</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG2A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>2241698</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>T3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050630"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>NV</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>representative=s name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A. BRAUN, BRAUN, HERITIER, ESCHMANN AG PATENTANWAE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20050623"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60110853</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050623</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050615"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050531"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050518"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050518"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20050209"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040804"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040621</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20040728"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040525</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20040519"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20040519"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Countries concerned </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ALLTLVMKROSI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>