<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1120196-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1120196" kind="B1" date="20050601"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23192349" ucid="EP-1120196-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1120196</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20050601</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01100166-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01100166</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010116</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000010844-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000010844</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000119</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20041209</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B24D   3/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B24D   3/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B24D   7/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B24D   7/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B24D  18/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B24D  18/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B24D18/00C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B24D3/06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B24D7/14</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Galvanisch hergestellte Schleifscheibe und dessen Herstellungsvorrichtung</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Electroplated grinding wheel and its production equipment</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Meule abrasive galvanisée et son dispositif de fabrication</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI MATERIALS CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI MATERIALS CORPORATION</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>TAKAHASHI TSUTOMU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HATA HANAKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SHIMOMAE NAOKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>TAKAHASHI, TSUTOMU</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>HATA, HANAKO</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SHIMOMAE, NAOKI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Shimomae, Naoki, c/o Iwaki Plant</last-name><address><street>Mitsubishi Materials Corp., 246-1,Egoshi, Kurosuno</street><city>Izumi-cho, Iwaki-shi, Fukushima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Hata, Hanako, c/o Iwaki Plant</last-name><address><street>Mitsubishi Materials Corp., 246-1,Egoshi, Kurosuno</street><city>Izumi-cho, Iwaki-shi, Fukushima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Takahashi, Tsutomu, c/o Iwaki Plant</last-name><address><street>Mitsubishi Materials Corp., 246-1,Egoshi, Kurosuno</street><city>Izumi-cho, Iwaki-shi, Fukushima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Mitsubishi Materials Corporation</last-name><address><street>1-5-1, Ohtemachi,</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name><address><street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street><city>81925 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>The invention relates to an electroplated grinding wheel having abrasive grain layer parts in which plural abrasive grains are fixed with the metal bonding phase. The abrasive grain layer part has a high abrasive grains concentration at a center part of said abrasive grain layer part and a low abrasive grain concentration at a surrounding area of said abrasive grain layer part. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">The invention relates to an electroplated grinding wheel having abrasive grain
layer parts in which plural abrasive grains are fixed with the metal bonding phase.
The abrasive grain layer part has a high abrasive grains concentration at a center part
of said abrasive grain layer part and a low abrasive grain concentration at a
surrounding area of said abrasive grain layer part.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1120642-A3-00000001" he="69" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><heading>[Technical field of the Invention]</heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to an electroplated grinding wheel, its production
method and equipment.</p><heading>[Description of the Background]</heading><p num="0002">Conventionally, when a requested formed abrasive grain layer is formed by
electroplating on a grinding wheel substrate (base metal) with use of a masking
component, an electroplating method is mainly used as the production method of the
electroplated grinding wheel. For example, the said method is done as follows.</p><p num="0003">First, as shown in Fig. 13, the surface 1a of the grinding-wheel substrate
(base metal) 1, is masked by the masking component 2, excepting the area which
should form the desired abrasive grain layer, and said grinding-wheel substrate 1 is
dipped in the electroplating liquid with arranging the surface 1a upward.</p><p num="0004">Next, the super abrasive grains 3 are sprinkled on the non masking area 1b of
the surface 1a. In addition, the super abrasive grains 3 are fixed by depositing the
metal plating layer 4 by passing current between the surface 1a and the anodes
arranged at opposite to the surface 1a, while the grinding stone substrate 1 is
connected to a power cathode. Moreover, the masking component 2 is removed, and
as shown in Fig. 14, the electroplated grinding wheel 6, in which a mono layer 5 of
abrasive grains is formed on the grinding stone substrate 1, is obtained. </p><p num="0005">European patent application publication no. <ref typ="patent">EP 0393540</ref> discloses a process
for electroplating surface segments situated on the surface of an object first provided,
by mechanical means, with corrugation or knurling which is coated with an insulating
material. Exposed surface segments are then produced by stripping the surface and
these are electroplated. The insulating material in between is then removed. This
makes it possible, for example, in the case of grinding tools on which an electroplated
layer containing abrasive particles is to be deposited, to keep the segments small and
to create gaps for receiving cuttings which are recessed with respect to the surface
segments.</p><p num="0006">European patent application publication no. <ref typ="patent">EP 0950470</ref> discloses an abrasive
tool including an electroformed layer having superabrasive grains electroplated on an
outer surface of the electroformed layer and a plurality of dimples arranged thereon,
as well as a method of producing said tool by using a mold with projections made of
gel adhesive. The concentration of the abrasive grains is regulated by changing the
concentration of the dimples. The gel adhesive preferably has a viscosity of 500,000
cP or smaller. The ratio of area with dimples to area without dimples is preferably
from 7 to 70%. </p><heading>[Object of this Invention]</heading><p num="0007">However, the following phenomena happen in the electroplated grinding
wheel 6 made by the production method mentioned above. The edge part 5a, which is
a boundary between the masking component 2 and the abrasive grain layer 5, rises up
rather than a central area to become thick in the metal plating phase 4. As a result,
burrs are occurred on the edge part 5a, or the super abrasive grains 3 are projected
out rather than said central area by being fixed at the edge part. Therefore, there is a
fault that scratches are occurred on a work material, or the grinding precision is fallen
at the grinding time. Moreover, there also is a fault that the life of said grinding stone
is shortened, since the edge part 5a is easily broken at the grinding time.</p><p num="0008">In addition, the masking component 2 is like a sheet or a film, and must be
made by using the photoengraving process, etc., according to the configuration of the
abrasive grain layer 5 which should be formed. Moreover, there is a problem that the
production cost becomes high, since it is necessary that the masking component 2 is
precisely positioned at the time of setting of said masking component.</p><p num="0009">The object of this invention is to offer the electroplated grinding wheel,
which has sharp grinding performance and a prolonged tool life, in view of the above
mentioned conditions.</p><p num="0010">Moreover, the other purpose of this invention is also to offer the production
method and its equipment, which are enable to produce easily the electroplated
grinding wheel having sharp grinding performance and the prolonged tool life, in low
cost. </p><heading>[Summary of the Invention]</heading><p num="0011">In the electroplated grinding wheel having the abrasive grain layer part, in
which the multiple abrasive grains are stuck in the metal bonding phase, the
electroplated grinding wheel of this invention is characterized that the abrasive grain
layer part has the high concentration of the abrasive grain at the center part, and said
concentration is relatively low at the surrounding part.</p><p num="0012">The life of the abrasive grains can be prolonged by arranging the abrasive
grains densely in the abrasive grain layer part at the center part. Moreover, sharpness
of the abrasive grains can be kept good to prevent the blinding with ground dust by
arranging the abrasive grains coarsely at the surrounding part.</p><p num="0013">In addition, the electroplated grinding wheel of this invention is characterized
that the thickness of the metal bonding phase, is thick at the center part, and is
gradually decreased towards the surrounding part, in the electroplated grinding wheel
which has the abrasive grain layer parts, in which the multiple abrasive grains are
fixed in the metal bonding phase.</p><p num="0014">Since the thickness of the abrasive grain layer part is gradually decreased
towards the surrounding part from the center part, the burr, etc., is not occurred at
the edge part of said abrasive grain layer part at the grinding time, so that the work
material is not damaged and good grinding performance can be done.</p><p num="0015">Moreover, it may be acceptable that the abrasive grain layer parts are made
plural numbers by being separated each other.</p><p num="0016">Since the non abrasive grain parts, where the abrasive grain layer part is not 
made, are connected with the separation part among the each abrasive grain layer
parts, the ground dust can be exhausted smoothly through these non abrasive grain
parts mentioned above, which are used as the exhaust passages. Therefore, the
blinding is prevented much more and the sharpness can be improved.</p><p num="0017">Moreover, it may be acceptable that the plural abrasive grain layer parts are
made by being separated each other, above mentioned abrasive grain layer parts are
connected with each other, and the abrasive grains are distributed and fixed at the
connecting part.</p><p num="0018">By this way, the blinding at the connecting part is prevented and the
sharpness in each abrasive grain layer part can be kept good.</p><p num="0019">Moreover, the production equipment of the electroplated grinding wheel of
this invention is characterized by the following processes.

That is, the processes which make to mask the masking component on the grinding
stone substrate, excepting for the area which should form abrasive grain layer part, to
dip said substrate into the electroplating liquid, to connect said substrate with the
cathode, to make the anode at the opposite to said substrate, and to fix the abrasive
grains at the non masking area on said substrate with the metal plating. Furthermore,
the equipment is also characterized that the masking component comprising the
multiple masking parts, and said masking parts are formed like inclined planes, in
which the said masking parts are stretched into the space on the non masking area, as
departing from its contacting part on the grinding stone substrate.</p><p num="0020">At the time of fixing of the abrasive grains by metal plating, the
concentration of the abrasive grains is high at the center part of the non-masking area, 
but the abrasive grains are distributed in low concentration at the surrounding part of
non masking area, since the abrasive grains cannot enter into the near area of the
boundary between the grinding stone substrate and the masking part by existing of the
inclined plane of the masking part. Moreover the current density of the plating
becomes comparatively dense at the center part, but becomes coarse at the
surrounding part, according to approach to the grinding stone substrate, since the
current is surrounded by the inclined plane of the multiple masking parts. Therefore,
the metal bonding phase is deposited to form that its thickness is decreased towards
the surrounding part from the center part. As a result, the burr etc. is not formed at
the edge part of the metal bonding phase, or the abrasive grain is not fixed in the
projection state.</p><p num="0021">The production method of the electroplated grinding wheel by this invention
is the way, which masks said grinding wheel excepting the area where should form
the abrasive grain layer part on the grinding stone substrate, and forms the masking
parts, which is in the masking component, like the inclined plane, which is stretched
out on the non masking area as departing from the grinding stone substrate. Then,
said grinding wheel substrate is dipped in the electroplating liquid, and is passed the
current by connecting with the cathode to fix the abrasive grains on the non masking
area of the grinding stone substrate with the metal plating. </p><heading>[Brief Description of the Drawings]</heading><p num="0022"><sl><li>Figure 1 is the partial drawing of vertical section of the electroplated grinding
wheel by the 1st Example of this invention.</li><li>Fig. 2 is the partial floor plane of the abrasive grain layer part of the
electroplated grinding wheel shown in Fig. 1.</li><li>Fig. 3 is the partial floor plane showing the state that the masking
components were laid on the surface of the grinding stone substrate.</li><li>Fig. 4 is the A-A line vertical section of the masking component and the
grinding-stone substrate shown in Fig. 3.</li><li>Fig. 5 is the drawing of vertical section showing the state that the super
abrasive grains were sprinkled on the non masking area shown in Fig. 4.</li><li>Fig. 6 is the drawing of vertical section showing the state that the super
abrasive grains laid on the non masking area were fixed with the metal plating.</li><li>Fig. 7 (a) shows the current distribution of the non masking area where was
faced by the masking component.</li><li>Fig.7 (b) shows the thickness distribution of the deposition metal by the metal
plating corresponding to the current distribution shown in Fig. (a).</li><li>Figure 8 is the drawing of vertical section showing the state that the masking
part and super abrasive grains fixed with the metal plating in the 2nd Example as same
as Fig.4</li><li>Figure 9 is the drawing of vertical section showing the state that the masking
part and super abrasive grains in the 3rd Example fixed with the metal plating as same
as Fig.4.</li><li>Fig. 10 is the floor plane of the abrasive grain layer part obtained using the 
masking component shown in Fig. 9.</li><li>Fig. 11 is the drawing of the vertical section showing the modification of the
masking part the 3rd Example as same as Fig. 4.</li><li>Fig. 12 is the drawing of the vertical section showing the masking part in the
3rd Example.</li><li>Fig. 13 is the drawing of the vertical section of the principal part showing the
state that the super abrasive grains were laid on the grinding stone substrate having the
masking part by the conventional production method of the electroplated grinding
wheel.</li><li>Fig. 14 is the partial drawing of vertical section of the electroplated grinding
wheel produced by using the masking part in Fig 13.</li></sl></p><heading>[Brief Description of the Preferred Embodiments]</heading><p num="0023">Hereafter, the example of this invention is explained with the appending
drawings. Fig. 1 to 7 is related with the 1st Example. Fig. 1 is the partial longitudinal
sectional plane of the electroplated grinding wheel, and Fig. 2 is the floor plane of the
electroplated grinding wheel in Fig. 1, and Fig. 3 to 7 are the production method of
the electroplated grinding wheel. Fig. 3 is the partial floor plane in the state that the
masking component was set on the grinding stone substrate. Fig. 4 is the A-A line
sectional plane of Fig. 3. Fig. 5 is the drawing showing the state that the super
abrasive grains were dropped on the non masking area. Fig. 6 is the vertical section
showing the state that the super abrasive grains were fixed with the metal plating. Fig.
7 (a) is the figure showing the current distribution of the non masking area. Fig. 7 (b)
is the drawing showing the thickness distribution of the deposited metal with the metal 
plating, according to the current distribution.</p><p num="0024">In the electroplated grinding wheel 10 in the example of Fig. 1 and 2, the
plural grinding stone layer parts 12 existed like dots being separated each other on the
surface 11a of the grinding stone substrate (base metal) 11, which comprises, for
example, stainless steel etc., or said plural abrasive grain layer parts 12 are formed
like a net by connecting with each other through the bridge part. The electroplated
grinding wheel 10 in this example, has the abrasive grain layer 13, in which the plural
abrasive grain layer parts 12 are connected with each other like the net through the
bridge part 9.</p><p num="0025">In each abrasive grain layer part 12 included in the abrasive grain layer 13 of
the electroplated grinding wheel 10 shown in Fig. 1 and 2, the multiple super
abrasive grains 14 which comprise diamonds or CBN, etc., (it is considered as
diamonds in this figure), are arranged on the grinding stone substrate 11, and are
fixed in the first metal plating phase 15, which comprises, for example, nickel. This
first metal plating phase 15 is formed in the area of the abrasive grain layer parts 12.
In addition, on the first metal plating phase 15, the second-metal metal plating phase
16 which comprises, for example, nickel, is formed overall the abrasive grain layer 13.
Therefore, the super abrasive grains 14 are fixed by the metal bonding phase 17 which
comprises the binary layers of the first metal plating phase 15 and the second metal
plating phase 16, and the upside of the super abrasive grains 14 are projected out the
outside from the second metal plating phase 16.</p><p num="0026">Moreover, in each abrasive grain layer part 12, the arrangement density of
the multiple super abrasive grains 14 is high at the center part 12a, and the 
arrangement density of the multiple super abrasive grains 14 is low at the surrounding
part 12b which is the outside of the diameter direction. The number of the super
abrasive grains 14 in one abrasive grain layer part 12 is arbitrary, that is, for example,
100 pieces. In this example, although the super abrasive grains 14 are set as a single
layer at the abrasive grain part 12, it may be acceptable for said grains 14 that is
consisted of two or more layers.</p><p num="0027">Moreover, the first metal plating phase 15 is formed like a mountain in the
vertical section, where the thickness of center part 12a is large, and the thickness of
the surrounding part 12b becomes gradually small, as shown in Fig. 1.</p><p num="0028">In addition, as shown in Fig. 2, for example, if the abrasive grain layer part
12 is considered to be formed like an almost triangle, two adjacent abrasive grain
layer parts 12 and 12 are connected each other, through the bridge part 9, in which
the surrounding parts 12b and 12b are extended from the top of the almost triangle. In
the bridge part 9, the super abrasive grains 14 are set in more coarse interval than the
surrounding part 12b, and are fixed by the metal bounding phase 17 which comprises
the first metal plating phase 15 and the second metal plating phase 16. Therefore, the
abrasive grain layer 13 is presenting like the net form, with which the multiple
abrasive grain layers 12 are connected at the bridge part 9 through each top part.</p><p num="0029">The electroplated grinding wheel 10 in this example has the above mentioned
structure, and next, the production method of this electroplated grinding wheel 10 is
explained with Fig. 3 to Fig.7.</p><p num="0030">First, the masking component 18 is set on the surface 11a of the grinding
stone substrate 11, where the abrasive grain layer should be formed. As shown in Fig. 
3 and Fig 4., this masking component 18 comprises the multiple masking parts 19,
which have a half sphere form, made with the non conductivity components, such as
plastics, and have a large specific gravity preferably in order to make to dip into the
metal plating liquid. The masking component 18 are closed packed in order to contact
each other at the almost circular flat surface 19a of the each mask part 19 arranged in
the flat surface, and are set in the state that the top of the half ball 19a was contacted
with the surface 11a of the grinding-stone substrate 11. In addition, it may be also
acceptable that each masking components 18 are connected each other to arrange
closely at each contact of the almost circular flat face 19a of each mask part 19
arranged flatly.</p><p num="0031">Moreover, the grinding stone substrate 11 is dipped into the electrolytic metal
plating liquid with the masking component 18, and the surface 11a is arranged upward
horizontally.</p><p num="0032">By this state, the almost triangle clearance 20 is formed among three masking
parts 19, 19, and 19, in the plane view shown in Fig. 3, and the super abrasive
grains 14 are dropped from these clearances 20 to the non-masking area 11b of
surface 11a of the grinding stone substrate 11, as shown in Fig.5. In the case of the
feed of the super abrasive grains 14, if the grinding stone substrate 11 is vibrated with
the masking component 18, the super abrasive grains 14 can be fallen efficiently.</p><p num="0033">The non-masking area 11b of the grinding stone substrate 11 corresponding
to the clearance 20, becomes broader to an overall than the clearance 20, for the half
sphere face 19a of the masking part 19, and is in the state that the non masking areas
11b and 11b, corresponding to the adjacent clearances 20 and 20 which are separated 
each other, are passed seriously each other. Since the super abrasive grains 14 are laid
on the non masking area 11b excepting the area of the half sphere face 19a of the
masking part 19, the arrangement density of the super abrasive grains 14 is high at the
center part which counters the clearance 20 of the non masking area 11b. On the other
hand, on the surrounding part, since the inclined plane on the convex surface of half
sphere face 19a is stretched on the non masking area 11b, the super abrasive grains
are regulated to be few, and so that the arrangement density becomes coarse.</p><p num="0034">Next, while the grinding stone substrate 11 is connected to the power cathode,
the current is passed between the surface 11a and the anode arranged at the opposite
of the surface 11a (not shown), and the first metal plating phase 15, which comprises
nickel, etc., is deposited to fix the super abrasive grains14. At this time, the thickness
of the first metal plating phase 15 is controlled by each half sphere face 19b of the
multiple masking parts 19 which form the clearance 20.</p><p num="0035">Thus, as shown in Fig. 7 (a), the current, which flows from the anode to the
cathode (grinding stone substrate 11) between the anode and cathodes in electric metal
plating liquid, is diffused to spread out like an unfolded fan, along with the half
sphere part 19b of the masking part 19 towards the non masking area 11b from the
inlet of the clearance 20. Therefore, the current density becomes high at the center
part of the non masking area 11b, and low at the surrounding part, so tat the
first-metal plating phase 15 is formed like an almost mountain, where the thickness of
the metal plating is thick at center part 12a and is decreased gradually at the
surrounding part 12b along with the current density. The thickness of the metal plating
is restricted by the half sphere face 19b of the masking part 19, at the surrounding
part 12b of the first metal plating phase 15. </p><p num="0036">Moreover, the super abrasive grains 14 sprinkled from the clearance 20, are
arranged with coarse density between the adjacent non masking areas 11b and 11b,
and are fixed with the thin first metal plating phase 15, at the time of the metal plating,
to form the bridge part 9 connecting the abrasive grain layer part 12 with the abrasive
grain layer part 12.</p><p num="0037">Next, the excessive super abrasive grains 14, which are not fixed, are
removed, while the masking component 18 is removed, and the current is passed
again between the anode and the cathode (grinding stone substrate 11), to form the
metal bonding phase 17 by depositing the second metal plating phase 16 overall.</p><p num="0038">In the electroplated grinding wheel 10 obtained by this way, as shown in
Fig.1 and Fig.2, the near area, where the top of the half sphere face 19b of the
masking part 19 is contacted with the surface 11a of the grinding stone substrate 11,
becomes to the non abrasive grain part 22 in which the abrasive grain layer part 12 is
not formed. As the result, the abrasive grain layer part 13 is obtained, where the
abrasive grain layers 12 are formed respectively to connect with the bridge parts 9 at
the non masking area 11b corresponding to the clearances 20 formed in three masking
parts 19, 19, and 19. Therefore, at the abrasive grain layer 13, the non abrasive grain
part 22 and the abrasive-grain layer part 12 are arranged alternately.</p><p num="0039">When the grinding is done by using the produced electroplated grinding
wheel 10 made by this way, the grinding of the work material is done with each
abrasive grain layer part 12. At this time, at the surrounding part 12b of the abrasive
grain layer part 12, since the abrasive grain density is small to be difficult to be
blinded, the sharpness is kept good. In addition, at the center part 12a, the abrasive 
grain density is high and so, its durability becomes high.</p><p num="0040">Moreover, the ground dust can be stored, at the non abrasive grain part 22
between the abrasive grain layer parts 12 and 12.</p><p num="0041">According to this example as mentioned above, each abrasive grain layer part
12 of the electroplated grinding wheel 10, has the high abrasive grain density to have
good durability at the center part 12a, and has the small abrasive grain density to be
difficult to be blinded at the surrounding part 12b. So its sharpness is good. Moreover,
the first metal plating phase 15 and the second metal plating phase 16, are formed like
the mountain in which the thickness of the metal plating becomes thin gradually from
the center part 12a to the surrounding part 12b of abrasive grain layer part 12.
Therefore, as compared with the electroplated grinding wheel produced by the
conventional masking, the burr is not made to the edge part, or the super abrasive
grains 14 are not fixed to be upheaved, so that there is not scratches, etc., on the work
material at the grinding.</p><p num="0042">Moreover, as the masking component 18, since the almost half sphere
masking parts 19 are closed packed to arrange in X-Y direction in Fig. 11a on the
surface 11a of the grinding stone substrate 1, it does not necessary to make by the
photoengraving process like the conventional masking component and the complicated
positioning. Therefore, it can be produced in the low cost and easily. In addition, it
is easy to adjust the size of the abrasive grain layer part 12, the arrangement distance,
and the concentration of the super abrasive grains 14, by increasing or decreasing the
radius of the masking parts 19. When the radius of the masking parts 19 becomes
large, the clearance 20 increases and the concentration also increases. When the 
radius of the masking parts 19 becomes small, the clearance 20 reduces, and the
concentration also becomes small.</p><p num="0043">Next, the other example of this invention is explained by using the same code,
which is used for the same segment and component as the above mentioned example.</p><p num="0044">Fig. 8 shows the masking component used for the production of the
electroplated grinding wheel by the second example, and is the vertical section same
as Fig. 4.</p><p num="0045">The masking component 25 used in the production method of the
electroplated grinding wheel in the 2nd Example, has the multiple mask parts 26,
which like cone configuration respectively, and are closed packed and arranged while
their apexes P of said cones contact with the surface 11a of the grinding stone
substrate 11. In the case of this mask parts 26, the configuration of the clearance 20 is
the same as the 1st Example, but the area of the non masking area 11b on the surface
11a of the grinding-stone substrate 11, increases substantially. Moreover, when the
super abrasive grains 14 are sprinkled through the clearance 20, the abrasive grain
density of the surrounding part 12b at the non masking area 11b, becomes high, as
compared with the abrasive grain layer part 12 of the first example, because of the
cone circumference side 26b of the mask part 26.</p><p num="0046">Next, the third example of this invention is explained with Fig. 9 and Fig. 10.
Fig. 9 is the drawing of vertical section which showing the masking component used
for the production of the electroplated grinding wheel by the 3rd Example, and Fig.
10 is the partial floor plane of the electroplated grinding wheel 30, which is produced 
by using the masking component shown in Fig. 9.</p><p num="0047">The masking component 32 used in the production method in the 3rd
Example, comprises the multiple masking parts 33 being closed packed and arranged
in the X-Y direction. Each masking part 33 is the almost truncated-cone form, and the
upper face 33a and the under face 33b, which are like a circle, are countered each
other. The under face 33b has the smaller diameter than that of the upper face 33a,
and is contacted to the surface 11a of the grinding stone substrate 11. Moreover, the
side face 33c is the convex face and becomes the inclined face as reducing the
diameter gradually from upper face 33a to under face 33b.</p><p num="0048">By constituting the masking component 32 in this way, when the super
abrasive grains 14 are sprinkled through the clearance 20 to the non-masking range
11b of the grinding stone substrate 11, each abrasive grain layer 12 is formed in the
separated state each other like islands without bridge parts 9 where the super abrasive
grain 14 are arranged linearly to connect the abrasive grain layer part 12 with the
adjacent abrasive grain part 12, since the under face 33b of the masking part 33 is
broad and is contacted with the face.</p><p num="0049">Therefore, in each abrasive-grain layer part 12, as shown in Fig. 10, the first
metal plating phase 15 which fixes the super abrasive grains 14, has the constitution in
which said first metal plating phases 15 are separated each other through the
separation part 35. Therefore, the non abrasive grain part 22 prepared between the
abrasive grain layer parts 12 and 12, are passed each other through the separation part
35, so that the ground dust can be exhausted smoothly.</p><p num="0050">Next, Fig. 11 shows the other masking component, and this masking 
component 37 is the modification example of the masking component 32 shown in Fig.
9. In the multiple masking parts 38 comprising said masking component 37, the side
face 38 connects upper face 38a with the under face 38b, which are almost circular
form, and decreases its radius gradually, after expanding the radius gradually towards
under face 38b from top face 38a. As the result, said side face 38 has the almost
circular convex face in the cross section.</p><p num="0051">When the mask part 38 is comprised in this way, the clearance 20 among the
mask parts 38 each other is expanded at the upper side, and the introduction of the
super abrasive grains 14 to the non masking range 11b by sprinkling, becomes easy.</p><p num="0052">In addition, the configuration of the mask part can be take arbitrary without
being limited to the each above mentioned example. For example, as the masking
component 40 shown in Fig. 12, it may be acceptable that each multiple mask parts 42
are formed like a sphere which has a suitable radius, and these spheres are closed
packed and arranged to contact each other. In this case, when the frame mold of the
suitable configuration, such as a ring, is made at the periphery of the abrasive grain
layer 13, to close pack said masking parts 42 inside of said ring, the positioning can
be done easily.</p><p num="0053">Moreover, in the each above mentioned example, the electrolytic metal
plating was done to fix the super abrasive grains 14, after the super abrasive grains 14
were sprinkled on the grinding stone substrate 11, but this invention is not limited to
such production methods. For example, it may be also acceptable that the current can
be passed, while metal plating liquid is stirring, where the super abrasive grains 14
are mixed into the electrolytic metal plating liquid, and said super abrasive grains 14 
can be deposited to be fixed with the metal on the grinding-stone substrate 11 which is
the cathode.</p><p num="0054">Moreover, blocky super abrasive grains are sufficient as the super abrasive
grains 14, or general abrasive grains can also be used instead of the super abrasive
grains.</p><p num="0055">In the each above mentioned example, the super abrasive grains 14 are fixed
in the metal bonding phase 17 which comprises the first metal plating phase 15 and
second metal plating phase 16. However, it may be acceptable that the super abrasive
grains 14 can also be fixed with only the first metal plating phase 15 as the metal
bonding phase 17, without being limited to said method.</p><p num="0056">In addition, it is also acceptable that the quality of the material of each
masking part, which comprises the masking components 18, 25, 32, 37, and 40, is
other suitable non-conductivity components, for example, glasses or rubbers, etc.,
without being limited to plastics.</p><p num="0057">As explained above, about the electroplated grinding wheel of this invention,
the abrasive grain layer part has the high concentration of the abrasive grains at the
center part, and has the comparatively low concentration at the surrounding part.
Therefore, the life of the abrasive grain layer part can be prolonged at the center part,
and the blinding of the ground dust can be prevented at the surrounding part, so that
the sharpness of the abrasive grains can be kept good.</p><p num="0058">Moreover, about the electroplated grinding wheel of this invention, the
thickness of the metal bonding phase is thick at the center part, and is decreased
gradually towards the surrounding part, so that the thickness of the abrasive grain 
layer part is decreased gradually towards the surrounding part from the center part.
Therefore, since the burr, etc., is not occurred in the edge part at the grinding time,
the good grinding performance can be obtained without damaging the work material.</p><p num="0059">Moreover, since the abrasive grain layer parts are separated each other and
made plural numbers, the exhaust passages of ground dust can be made among the
abrasive grain layer parts to exhaust the ground dust smoothly with preventing the
blinding much more. In this way, the sharpness can be improved..</p><p num="0060">In addition, the abrasive grain layer parts are separated each other, made
plural numbers, and are connected each other through the bridge parts. These abrasive
grains are distributed and fixed at this bridge part, so that the sharpness of each
abrasive grain layer part is good, and the blinding at the bridge part can be prevented.</p><p num="0061">In addition, about the production equipment of the electroplated grinding
wheel of this invention, the masking component comprises the multiple masking parts,
and said masking parts are formed like the inclined plane, which is stretched in the
space on the non masking area as departing from the segment of contact with the
grinding stone substrate. Therefore, at the time of the fixing of the abrasive grains by
the metal plating, the concentration of the abrasive grain is high at the center part of
the non-masking range, and the abrasive grains are distributed at the surrounding part
with the low concentration, since said abrasive grains cannot enter into the boundary
area between the grinding stone substrate and the masking part by the mask part. In
addition, the current density of the plating current, which is surrounded with the
inclined plane of the multiple mask parts, is comparatively dense at the center part, 
and becomes coarse at the surrounding part, as approaching to the grinding stone
substrate. Therefore, the deposited metal bonding phase is formed with the
configuration that its thickness is decreased towards the surrounding part from the
center part, the burr, etc., is not formed, and the abrasive grains are not fixed in the
projection state, at the edge part of the metal bonding phase.</p><p num="0062">The production method of the electroplated grinding wheel by this invention
comprising,
<sl><li>masking on the grinding stone substrate except for the area, which should form the
abrasive grain layer part, with the masking component which comprises the masking
parts,</li><li>forming the masking parts like the inclined plane which is stretched on the non
masking area as departing from the grinding stone substrate,</li><li>dipping into the metal plating liquid,</li><li>connecting the grinding stone substrate to the cathode, and</li><li>passing the current to fix the abrasive grains on the non masking area on the grinding
stone substrate with the metal plating.</li></sl>
Therefore, at the time of the fixing of the abrasive grains with the metal plating, the
concentration of the abrasive grains is high at the center part of the non masking area,
and the abrasive grains are distributed in the low concentration at the surrounding part.
Moreover, according to the variation of the current density of the metal plating, the
deposited metal bonding phase is formed with the configuration that its thickness is
decreased towards the surrounding part from the center part, the burr etc. is not
formed, and the abrasive grains are not fixed in the projection state, at the edge part
of the metal bonding phase.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Galvanisch belegte Schleifscheibe (10), aufweisend
auf einer Oberfläche (11a) des Schleifscheiben-Trägers
(11) einen Abschnitt (22) ohne abrasive Körner sowie einen
Abschnitt mit abrasiven Körnern (14), wobei der Abschnitt
mit abrasiven Körnern einen abrasiven Kornschicht-Teil
(12) zum Schleifen beinhaltet, in dem eine Vielzahl
abrasiver Körner mit einer metallischen Binderphase (15,
16) fixiert sind, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
   dieser abrasive Kornschicht-Teil eine hohe
Konzentration abrasiver Körner in einem zentralen Teil
(12a) des abrasiven Kornschicht-Teils sowie eine niedrige
Konzentration an abrasiven Körnern in einem Bereich (12b)
aufweist, der den zentralen Teil des abrasiven
Kornschicht-Teils umgibt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Galvanisch belegte Schleifscheibe (10), aufweisend an
einer Oberfläche (11a) des Schleifscheiben-Trägers (11)
einen Abschnitt (22) ohne abrasive Körner sowie einen
Abschnitt mit abrasiven Körnern (14), wobei der Abschnitt
mit abrasiven Körnern einen abrasiven Kornschicht-Teil
(12) zum Schleifen beinhaltet, bei dem eine Vielzahl
abrasiver Körner mit einer metallischen Binderphase (15,
16) fixiert sind, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
   ein Abschnitt der metallischen Binderphase, die die
Vielzahl abrasiver Körner beinhaltet, eine Dicke aufweist,
die schrittweise von einem zentralen Teil (12a) der
metallischen Binderphase auf einen umgebenden Bereich
(12b) verringert ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Galvanisch belegte Schleifscheibe gemäß Anspruch 1
oder Anspruch 2, wobei
   die abrasiven Kornschicht-Teile in einer Vielzahl
durch Trennung voneinander erzeugt werden.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Galvanisch belegte Schleifscheibe gemäß Anspruch 1
oder Anspruch 2, wobei
   die abrasiven Kornschicht-Teile in einer Vielzahl
durch Trennung voneinander erzeugt und miteinander über
Brückenteile (9) verbunden sind, und wobei
   diese abrasiven Körner getrennt und an den BrückenTeilen
fixiert werden.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Produktionsanlage für eine galvanisch belegte
Schleifscheibe (10) mit
   einem Abschnitt, der so angebracht ist, dass er mit
Abdeck-Komponenten (18) die Schleifscheibe bis auf einen
nicht abgedeckten Bereich (11b) abdeckt, wo abrasive
Kornschicht-Teile (12) ausgeformt werden sollen, und so
angeordnet, dass die Schleifscheibe in eine metallische
Plattierungsflüssigkeit getaucht wird,
   einen Bereich, der so angebracht ist, dass er die
Schleifscheibe mit einer Kathode verbindet und um eine
Anode derart anzuordnen, dass sie der Schleifscheibe
gegenübersteht,
   wobei die Abdeck-Komponenten aus einer Vielzahl von
Abdeckteilen (19) bestehen, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
   die Abdeckteile mit geneigten Oberflächen (19b)
ausgeformt sind, die in den Raum in dem nicht abgedeckten
Bereich ausgedehnt sind und sich von ihrem
Kontaktabschnitt (33b, P) an dem Schleifscheiben-Träger
entfernen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Produktionsprozess für eine galvanisch belegte
Schleifscheibe (10), umfassend
   das Abdecken mit Abdeck-Komponenten (18), die aus
Abdeck-Teilen (19) bestehen, auf dem Schleifscheiben-Träger,
ausgenommen ein nicht abgedeckter Bereich (11b),
wo abrasive Kornschicht-Teile ausgeformt werden sollen,
   Ausbilden der Abdeck-Teile mit geneigten Oberflächen
(19b)
   Eintauchen des Schleifscheiben-Trägers in eine
metallische Plattierungsflüssigkeit,
   in Berührung bringen des Schleifscheiben-Trägers mit
einer Kathode, um einen Strom hindurchzuführen, sowie
   Fixieren der abrasiven Körner (14) auf dem nicht
abgedeckten Bereich an dem Schleifscheiben-Träger mit der
metallischen Plattierung, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
   die Abdeck-Teile (19) mit geneigten Oberflächen (19b)
in den Raum an dem nicht abgedeckten Bereich ausgestreckt
sind und sich von deren Kontaktbereich (33, P) an dem
Schleifscheiben-Träger entfernen.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An electroplated grinding wheel (10) having
on a surface (11a) of the grinding
wheel substrate (11)
a portion (22) without abrasive
grains and a portion with abrasive grains (14), the portion with abrasive grains
including an abrasive grain layer part (12) for grinding in which plural abrasive
grains are fixed with a metal bonding phase (15, 16), characterised in that
   said abrasive grain layer part has a high abrasive grain concentration at a center
part (12a) of said abrasive grain layer part and a low abrasive grain concentration at
an area (12b) surrounding the center part of said abrasive grain layer part.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An electroplated grinding wheel (10) having
on a surface (11a) of the grinding
wheel substrate (11)
a portion (22) without abrasive
grains and a portion with abrasive grains (14), the portion with abrasive grains
including an abrasive grain layer part (12) for grinding in which plural abrasive
grains are fixed with a metal bonding phase (15, 16), characterised in that
   a portion of said metal bonding phase, that includes the plural abrasive grains,
has a thickness which is decreased gradually from a center part (12a) of the metal
bonding phase toward a surrounding area (12b).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An electroplated grinding wheel according to claim 1 or claim 2
wherein
   said abrasive grain layer parts are made in plural numbers by separating each
other.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An electroplated grinding wheel according to claim 1 or claim 2
wherein
   said abrasive grain layer parts are made in plural numbers by separating each
other and are connected to each other through bridge parts (9), and
   these abrasive grains are separated and fixed at said bridge parts.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A production equipment of an electroplated grinding wheel (10) with
   a portion which is arranged to mask, with masking components (18), said
grinding wheel excepting a non masking area (11b) where abrasive grain layer parts
(12) should be formed, and arranged to dip said grinding wheel into a metal plating
liquid,
   a portion which is arranged to connect said grinding wheel to a cathode and to
arrange an anode so as to oppose said grinding wheel,
   said masking components consist of plural masking parts (19), characterized
in that said masking parts are formed with inclined faces (19b) which are stretched
into the space on the non masking area as departing from its contact portion (33b, P)
on the grinding wheel substrate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A production process of electroplated grinding wheel (10) comprising
   masking with masking components (18), which consists of masking parts (19),
on said grinding wheel substrate excepting a non masking area (11b) where abrasive
grain layer parts should be formed,
   forming said masking parts with inclined faces (19b)
   dipping said grinding wheel substrate into metal plating liquid,
   contacting said grinding wheel substrate to a cathode to pass current, and
   fixing abrasive grains (14) on the non masking area on said grinding wheel
substrate with the metal plating characterized in that
said masking parts (19) with inclined faces
(19b)
are stretched into
the space on the non masking area as departing from its contact portion (33b, P) on
the grinding wheel substrate.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Meule abrasive galvanisée (10) possédant sur une surface (11a)
du substrat de meule abrasive (11) une partie (22) sans grain abrasif et
une partie dotée de grains abrasifs (14), la partie dotée de grains abrasifs
comprenant une partie de couche de grains abrasifs (12) destinée au
meulage dans laquelle la pluralité de grains abrasifs sont fixés à une
phase de liaison métallique (15, 16), caractérisée en ce que ladite partie
de couche de grains abrasifs présente une concentration de grains
abrasifs élevés au niveau d'une partie centrale (12a) de ladite partie de
couche de grains abrasifs et une concentration de grains abrasifs faible au
niveau d'une zone (12b) entourant la partie centrale de ladite partie de
couche de grains abrasifs.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Meule abrasive galvanisée (10) possédant sur une surface (11a)
du substrat de meule abrasive (11) une partie (22) sans grain abrasif et
une partie dotée de grains abrasifs (14), la partie dotée de grains abrasifs
comprenant une partie de couche de grains abrasifs (12) destinée au
meulage dans laquelle la pluralité de grains abrasifs sont fixés à une
phase de liaison métallique (15, 16), caractérisée en ce que une partie de
ladite phase de liaison métallique, qui comprend la pluralité de grains
abrasifs, a une épaisseur qui diminue progressivement d'une partie
centrale (12a) de la phase de liaison métallique vers une zone
environnante (12b).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Meule abrasive galvanisée selon la revendication 1 ou la
revendication 2, dans laquelle lesdites parties de couche de grains abrasifs
sont faites en une pluralité de nombres en se séparant les unes des
autres.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Meule abrasive galvanisée selon la revendication 1 ou la
revendication 2, dans laquelle lesdites parties de couche de grains abrasifs
sont faites en une pluralité de nombres en les séparant les unes des
autres et sont reliées les unes aux autres par des parties de pont (9), et
ces grains abrasifs sont séparés et fixés auxdites parties de pont.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif de production d'une meule abrasive galvanisée (10)
avec une partie qui est agencée pour masquer, à l'aide de composants de
masquage (18), ladite meule abrasive à l'exception d'une zone de non-masquage
(11b) où des parties de couche de grains abrasifs (12) doivent
être formées, et agencée pour tremper ladite meule abrasive dans un
liquide de métallisation, une parité qui est agencée pour relier ladite meule
abrasive à une cathode et pour agencer une anode de façon à s'opposer à
ladite meule abrasive, lesdits composants de masquage sont constitués
d'une pluralité de parties de masquage (19), caractérisé en ce que lesdites
parties de masquage sont formées de faces inclinées (19b) qui s'étalent
dans l'espace sur la zone de non-masquage en partant de sa partie de
contact (33b, P) sur le substrat de meule abrasive.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de production de meule abrasive galvanisée (10)
comprenant
le masquage à l'aide de composants de masquage (18), qui sont
constitués de parties de masquage (19), sur ledit substrat de meule
abrasive à l'exception d'une zone de non-masquage (11b) où des parties
de couche de grains abrasifs doivent être formées,
la formation desdites parties de masquage de faces inclinées (19b),
le trempage dudit substrat de meule abrasive dans un liquide de
métallisation,
la mise en contact dudit substrat de meule abrasive avec une cathode
pour faire passer du courant,
la fixation des grains abrasifs (14) sur la zone de non-masquage sur ledit
substrat de meule abrasive par la métallisation, caractérisé en ce que
lesdites parties de masquage (19) présentant des faces inclinées (19b)
s'étalent dans l'espace sur la zone de non-masquage en partant de sa
partie de contact (33b, P) sur le substrat de meule abrasive.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20070314"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>BE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DK</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LU</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MC</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>NL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050601</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050601</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050601</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050601</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050601</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050601</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050901</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050901</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050901</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20051103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060116</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060116</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060131</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060131</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20061018"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MM4A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="GBPC" date="20060927"><legal-event-body><event-title>GB: EUROPEAN PATENT CEASED THROUGH NON-PAYMENT OF RENEWAL FEE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060116</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20060524"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060302</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20060414"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20051215"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="NLV1" date="20051201"><legal-event-body><event-title>NL: LAPSED OR ANNULED DUE TO FAILURE TO FULFILL THE REQUIREMENTS OF ART. 29P AND 29M OF THE PATENTS ACT; NO LEGAL EFFECT FROM</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20050707"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60111090</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050707</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050629"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050615"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050601"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050601"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIN1" date="20050126"><legal-event-body><event-title>INVENTOR (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>HATA, HANAKO,C/O IWAKI PLANT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SHIMOMAE, NAOKI,C/O IWAKI PLANT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>TAKAHASHI, TSUTOMU,C/O IWAKI PLANT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040929"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040817</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20040721"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20040512"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040317</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20031029"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20031029"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Countries concerned </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ALLTLVMKROSI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIC1" date="20031029"><legal-event-body><event-title>CLASSIFICATION (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 24D 18/00 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 24D 3/06 A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 24D 7/14 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010801"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010801"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>