<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document country="US" doc-number="20070000901" kind="A1" ucid="US-20070000901-A1" lang="EN" date="20070104" family-id="34550959" date-produced="20090604" status="new"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="76990762" ucid="US-20070000901-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>US</country><doc-number>20070000901</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20070104</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-53112006-A" us-series-code="11" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>53112006</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20060912</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-53112006-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>53112006</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20060912</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-69942203-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>69942203</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031031</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  65/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  65/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  65/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  65/18        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H05B   1/00        20060101ALI20070104BHUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H05B   1/00        20060101CLI20070104BHUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H05B   3/42        20060101AFI20070104BHUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H05B   3/42        20060101CFI20070104BHUS        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-national country="US" status="new"><main-classification>219237</main-classification></classification-national><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29C  65/00P4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29C  65/18+F4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29C  65/18+F4B4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C65:00P4</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new">System And Method For Monitoring Heat Seal Devices</invention-title></technical-data><related-documents status="new"><relation type="division"><child-doc ucid="US-53112006"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>US</country><doc-number>53112006</doc-number><date>20060912</date></document-id></child-doc><parent-doc ucid="US-69942203" psta="unknown"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>US</country><doc-number>69942203</doc-number><date>20031031</date></document-id></parent-doc></relation></related-documents><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>NORDSON CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>NORDSON CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>MISTER EDGAR J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo"  status="new"><addressbook><name>VANTASSEL DOUGLAS R</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>MISTER EDGAR J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>VANTASSEL DOUGLAS R.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Mister</last-name><first-name>Edgar</first-name><address><address-1>19344 Rosewood Drive</address-1><city>Stewartstown</city><state>PA</state><postcode>17363</postcode><country>US</country></address></addressbook> </inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>VanTassel</last-name><first-name>Douglas</first-name><address><address-1>5534 Grace Avenue</address-1><city>Bethlehem</city> <state>PA</state> <postcode>18017</postcode><country>US</country> </address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><correspondence-address sequence="1"  format="original"  status="new"><addressbook><last-name>WOOD, HERRON &amp; EVANS, LLP (NORDSON)</last-name><address><address-1>2700 CAREW TOWER</address-1><address-2>441 VINE STREET</address-2><city>Cincinnati</city><state>OH</state><postcode>45202</postcode><country>US</country></address></addressbook></correspondence-address></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" load-source="us"  status="new"><p num="p-0001">An apparatus for monitoring the operation of a heating element moving periodically along a predefined path includes first and second sensors positioned adjacent the path of the heating element. The first sensor is configured to sense the presence of the heating element proximate to the second sensor, and the second sensor is configured to sense a temperature associated with the heating element as is passes by the second sensor. A controller receives signals from the first and second sensors and performs a control function such as indicating when the temperature sensed by the second sensor fall outside a predetermined range. </p></abstract><description lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new"><?cross-reference-to-related-applications description="Cross Reference To Related Applications" end="lead"?><p num="p-0002"> This application is a divisional of <ref type="patent">U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/699,422</ref>, filed Oct. 31, 2003 (now pending), the disclosure of which is incorporated by reference herein in its entirety</p><?cross-reference-to-related-applications description="Cross Reference To Related Applications" end="tail"?><?summary-of-invention description="Summary of Invention" end="lead"?><heading>TECHNICAL FIELD </heading><p num="p-0003"> The present invention relates generally to heat sealing devices, and more particularly to an apparatus for monitoring the operation of a heat sealing device. </p><heading>BACKGROUND </heading><p num="p-0004"> Many consumer goods are provided in sealed packages such as heat-sealed polymeric bags. When the packaged goods are perishable goods such as cereal, crackers, or other foodstuffs, it is important that the package be properly sealed to keep the goods fresh and to avoid spillage and contamination of the goods. One type of sealing device used to seal polymeric bags utilizes one or more heater blocks provided on a rotating belt. The blocks cooperate with an adjustable press plate whereby the open end of a polymeric bag positioned between the press plate and rotating belt is sealed as a heater block passes the plate. Advantageously, the speed of the belt and the spacing of the blocks on the belt can be set to correspond to the timing of filled bags provided to a sealing station including the press plate and heater blocks such that continuous sealing of bags in a production line may be accomplished. </p><p num="p-0005"> One drawback of this type of bag sealing system is that many improperly sealed bags may pass through the sealing station without detection when one or more of the heater blocks fail. The improperly sealed bags must either be reworked or the product in the improperly sealed bags disposed of. In either case, the inability to detect failed heater blocks results in waste and increased manufacturing costs. In the worst case, the improperly sealed bags may pass through the manufacturing system undetected, ultimately resulting in unsatisfied customers. </p><p num="p-0006"> There is thus a need for an apparatus and method for monitoring the operation of a heat sealing device so that failure of one or more of the heating elements may be detected. </p><heading>SUMMARY </heading><p num="p-0007"> The present invention provides an apparatus for monitoring the operation of a heating device, such as a device for heat sealing polymeric bags, having one or more heating elements moving with periodic motion along a predefined path. The apparatus includes first and second sensors located adjacent to the path of the heating elements. The first sensor is configured to detect the presence of a heating element as it passes, and the second sensor is configured to sense a temperature associated with the passing heating element. This may, for example, involve sensing and communicating the actual temperature of the heating element or elements to a controller for various monitoring purposes and/or purposes related to taking corrective actions. It may alternatively or additionally involve detecting when the temperature is below a lower limit or above an upper limit for the particular heating element. Other implementations of the inventive principles can involve monitoring the temperature of the heating element(s) over time to detect rising or falling temperatures of the element(s) prior to actually reaching the upper or lower temperature limits established for that type of element. This would allow maintenance or replacement of the element(s) prior to actual failure. Temperatures of different elements in the same apparatus also could be monitored and compared to indicate a potential problem with one or more of the elements. </p><p num="p-0008"> The apparatus further includes a controller in communication with the sensors. The controller monitors the sensors and provides an indication when the temperature sensed by the second sensor falls outside of a predetermined range. The controller can perform other functions, such as those mentioned above, as well. The monitoring apparatus alerts operators to faulty operation of the heating elements so that the heating elements can be inspected and problems can be corrected in a timely fashion. </p><p num="p-0009"> In another aspect of the invention, an apparatus for sealing bags includes a sealing station having a press plate and a heating element configured to move past the press plate in a periodic fashion to seal bags passing between the press plate and heating element. A sealing station monitor has first and second sensor positioned adjacent to the path of the heating element to detect the passage of the heating element and a temperature associated with the heating element. A controller monitors the sensors and performs a control function such as, for example, providing an indication if the temperature of the heating element falls outside a predetermined range, whereafter the sealing process can be stopped and any problems with the heating element corrected. The process may be stopped by an operator alerted by the indication from the controller, or the controller may be configured to automatically stop the process. </p><p num="p-0010"> In another aspect of the invention, a method of monitoring the operation of a heating element moving along a predefined path includes sensing the presence of the heating element with a first sensor, sensing the temperature associated with the heating element with a second sensor performs a control function for determining whether a faulty heating element exists. This may be, for example, indicating when the temperature sensed by the second sensor falls outside a predetermined range or other desirable functions. The method is particularly applicable to the bag sealing apparatus discussed above, but can have other applications as well. </p><p num="p-0011"> These and other features, objects and advantages of the invention will become more readily apparent to those of ordinary skill in the art upon review of the following detailed description, taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p><?summary-of-invention description="Summary of Invention" end="tail"?><?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS </heading><p num="p-0012"> The accompanying drawings, which are incorporated in and constitute a part of this specification, illustrate embodiments of the invention and, together with a general description of the invention given above, and the detailed description given below, serve to explain the invention. </p><p num="p-0013"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic illustration depicting a bag seal system including an exemplary heating device monitor of the present invention; and </p><p num="p-0014"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic illustration depicting an alternate embodiment of the bag seal system.</p><?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?><?detailed-description description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION </heading><p num="p-0015"> Referring to <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, there is shown a bag fill and seal system <b>10</b> including an exemplary sealing station monitor <b>12</b> according to the present invention. The fill and seal system <b>10</b> includes a bag fill machine (not shown) and a sealing station <b>16</b> downstream from the bag fill machine. After bags <b>18</b> are filled with one or more articles, such as foodstuffs or other products, whereafter individual bags <b>18</b> are transported along a conveyer <b>20</b> to the sealing station <b>16</b> to seal the open end of the bags <b>18</b>. Sealing station <b>16</b> includes a press plate <b>22</b> mounted, for example, to vertical supports <b>24</b> such that the position of the press plate on the supports <b>24</b> may be adjusted as desired. Sealing station <b>1</b> <b>6</b> further includes one or more heater blocks <b>26</b> provided on a rotating belt <b>28</b>. The belt <b>28</b> is carried by rollers <b>30</b><i>a</i>, <b>30</b><i>b </i>such that heater blocks <b>26</b> are caused to pass in close proximity to press plate <b>22</b> as belt <b>28</b> rotates. As the open end of a bag <b>18</b> passes beneath press plate <b>22</b>, the pressure between heater blocks <b>26</b> passing by press plate <b>22</b>, in conjunction with the heat from the heater blocks <b>26</b>, seals the open end of the bag <b>18</b>. </p><p num="p-0016"> Sealing station monitor <b>12</b> includes first and second sensors <b>32</b>, <b>34</b> located adjacent the path of heater blocks <b>26</b> on belt <b>28</b>. The first sensor <b>32</b> is configured to detect the presence of a heater block <b>26</b> as it passes the first sensor <b>32</b>. In an exemplary embodiment, the first sensor is an optical sensor. However, it will be recognized that the first sensor may alternatively be selected from various other types of sensors, such as eddy current sensors, or any other proximity sensor capable of detecting the presence of a heater block <b>26</b> as it passes the first sensor <b>32</b>. Second sensor <b>34</b> is configured to sense the temperature of a heater block <b>26</b> as it passes second sensor <b>34</b>. </p><p num="p-0017"> First and second sensors <b>32</b>, <b>34</b> communicate with a controller <b>36</b> and transmit signals to the controller <b>36</b> related to the detection of a heater block passing by the first sensor <b>32</b> and the temperature detected by the second sensor <b>34</b>. Controller <b>36</b> monitors the signals from the first and second sensors <b>32</b>, <b>34</b> and checks to see whether the temperature sensed by second sensor <b>34</b> falls outside a predetermined range. When the temperature sensed by second sensor <b>34</b> exceeds or falls below the predetermined range, controller <b>36</b> indicates a failure of the sealing station <b>1</b> <b>6</b> so that operators can stop the fill and seal system <b>10</b> and correct problems with the heater blocks <b>26</b>, as may be required. Alternatively, controller <b>36</b> may be configured to automatically stop the fill and seal system <b>1</b> <b>0</b> when a problem with the heater blocks <b>26</b> is detected. Controller <b>36</b> may perform various other control functions using information obtained from temperature sensor <b>34</b>. As examples, controller <b>36</b> may monitor rising or falling temperatures of each heater block <b>26</b> during operation which, even if within the specified temperature range, could indicate a failing heater block <b>26</b>. Also, by comparing temperatures of different heater blocks <b>26</b> in a group and performing statistical analysis, a heater block <b>26</b> having a temperature statistically outside of the others could be checked and appropriately serviced prior to actual failure. In one embodiment, the controller <b>36</b> comprises a Seal Sentry™ Bead Detection System available from Nordson Corporation of Westlake, Ohio. </p><p num="p-0018"> Referring now to <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, there is shown an alternative bag seal arrangement, similar to that shown in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> wherein the sealing station <b>16</b><i>a </i>is configured to seal articles within packaging material provided to the sealing station <b>16</b><i>a </i>as a continuous tube or web <b>40</b>. In this embodiment, individual heater blocks <b>26</b><i>a </i>are spaced at predetermined intervals around the belt <b>28</b><i>a </i>to correspond to desired locations on the tube or web <b>40</b> where a seal <b>42</b> is to be formed. The sealed area of the tube or web <b>40</b> may be subsequently cut, or otherwise separated, to form individual sealed packages <b>44</b>. As a heater block <b>26</b><i>a </i>is carried past the first and second sensors <b>32</b>, <b>34</b> by rotating belt <b>28</b><i>a</i>, the first sensor <b>32</b> senses the presence of the heater block <b>26</b><i>a </i>and the second sensor <b>34</b> senses the temperature of the heater block <b>26</b><i>a</i>. Controller <b>36</b> monitors signals from the first and second sensors <b>32</b>, <b>34</b> and checks to determine whether the temperature sensed by second sensor <b>34</b> falls outside a predetermined range. When the temperature sensed by second sensor <b>34</b> exceeds or falls below the predetermined range, controller <b>36</b> indicates a failure of the sealing station <b>16</b><i>a </i>so that the sealing process can be stopped and problems with the heater block <b>26</b><i>a </i>addressed, as described above. </p><p num="p-0019"> While the present invention has been illustrated by the description of an embodiment thereof, and while the embodiment has been described in considerable detail, it is not intended to restrict or in any way limit the scope of the appended claims to such detail. Additional advantages and modifications will readily appear to those skilled in the art. The invention in its broader aspects is therefore not limited to the specific details, representative apparatus and method and illustrative examples shown and described. Accordingly, departures may be made from such details without departing from the scope or spirit of the general inventive concept.</p><?detailed-description description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?></description><claims lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new"><claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001"><claim-text><b>1</b>. A method of monitoring the operation of a heating device having at least one heating element moving periodically along a predefined path, the method comprising: 
<claim-text>sensing the presence of the heating element with a first sensor; </claim-text><claim-text>sensing a temperature associated with the heating element with a second sensor when the first sensor senses the presence of the heating element; and </claim-text><claim-text>sending a control signal in response to the temperature sensed by the second sensor. </claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002"><claim-text><b>2</b>. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein sending the control signal further comprises: 
<claim-text>sending the control signal when the temperature sensed by the second sensor deviates from a predetermined range. </claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003"><claim-text><b>3</b>. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising: 
<claim-text>sensing temperatures associated with a plurality of heating elements; </claim-text><claim-text>comparing the sensed temperatures associated with the plurality of heating elements; and </claim-text><claim-text>sending a control signal in response to the comparison made between the sensed temperatures associated with the plurality of heating elements. </claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004"><claim-text><b>4</b>. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising: 
<claim-text>sensing temperatures associated with the heating element over time; </claim-text><claim-text>comparing the sensed temperatures associated with the heating element over time; and </claim-text><claim-text>sending a control signal in response to the comparison made between the sensed temperatures associated with the heating element over time. </claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005"><claim-text><b>5</b>. A method of monitoring a bag sealer having one or more heater blocks moving periodically along a predefined path in proximity to a press plate, the method comprising: 
<claim-text>moving the heater block along the path and past the press plate; </claim-text><claim-text>feeding a bag having an open end to the bag sealer; </claim-text><claim-text>sealing the open end of the bag; </claim-text><claim-text>sensing the presence of the heater block with a first sensor; </claim-text><claim-text>sensing a temperature associated with the heater block with a second sensor when the first sensor senses the presence of the heater block; and </claim-text><claim-text>sending a control signal in response to the temperature sensed by the second sensor. </claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006"><claim-text><b>6</b>. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising stopping the movement of the heater block when the temperature sensed by the second sensor deviates from the predetermined temperature range.</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure id="figure-D00000" num="00000"><img id="EMI-D00000" he="53.72mm" wi="151.45mm" file="US20070000901A1-20070104-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00001" num="00001"><img id="EMI-D00001" he="261.20mm" wi="175.94mm" orientation="landscape" file="US20070000901A1-20070104-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></figure></drawings><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>
