<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><patent-document country="US" doc-number="20030004620" kind="A1" ucid="US-20030004620-A1" lang="EN" family-id="19038135" status="new" date-produced="20090605" date="20030102"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="US-20030004620-A1" status="new" fvid="75910750"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>US</country><doc-number>20030004620</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030102</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-18990602-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>18990602</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020702</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001201123-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001201123</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010702</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>G06F  17/00</main-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B64G   1/24        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B64G   1/28        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B64G   1/36        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B64G   1/36        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B64G   3/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B64G   3/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01C   1/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01C   1/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01C  19/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01C  19/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01P   9/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01P   9/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01P  21/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01P  21/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G05D   1/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G05D   1/08        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-national status="new" country="US"><main-classification>701013</main-classification><further-classification>701004</further-classification></classification-national><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B64G   1/36</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">G05D   1/08D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L64G1:28E</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L64G1:36A</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="us" status="new" lang="EN">Attitude detection system for artificial satellite</invention-title></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NIPPON ELECTRIC CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NEC CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YAMASHITA TOSHIAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YAMASHITA TOSHIAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Yamashita</last-name><first-name>Toshiaki</first-name><address><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee status="new" format="original"><addressbook><name>NEC CORPORATION</name></addressbook></assignee></assignees><correspondence-address status="new" sequence="1" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ostrolenk Faber Gerb &amp; Soffen</last-name></addressbook> </correspondence-address></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="us" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An attitude detection system for an artificial satellite includes an interpolator for interpolating an angular-velocity signal to generate an interpolated angular-velocity signal, a sequential Kalman filter for generating a low-frequency attitude-angle signal, and an adder for adding the low-frequency attitude-angle signal and a high-frequency attitude-angle signal generated by a high-frequency angular sensor to generate a broad-band attitude-angle signal. </p></abstract> <description load-source="us" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION </heading> <p>[0001] (a) Field of the Invention </p><p>[0002] The present invention relates to an attitude detection system for an artificial satellite and, more particularly, to an attitude detection system for detecting the attitude angle of an artificial satellite in a ground station, which is capable of accurately detecting fluctuation of the attitude angle of the artificial satellite over a broad frequency band. The present invention also relates to a method for detecting the attitude angle of the artificial satellite. </p> <p>[0003] (b) Description of the Related Art </p><p>[0004] The attitude of an artificial satellite residing in the space is generally observed from a ground station. FIG. 1 shows an example of the conventional attitude detection system, which includes an attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>11</b> for sampling the attitude angle of the artificial satellite at a low frequency to generate an attitude-angle calibration signal <b>14</b>, an angular-velocity sensor <b>12</b> for detecting the angular velocity of the artificial satellite to generate an angular-velocity signal <b>15</b> and a sequential Kalman filter <b>13</b> for estimating the attitude, i.e., the attitude angle of the artificial satellite by integrating the angular-velocity signal <b>15</b> with respect to time while calibrating the integrated data based on the attitude-angle calibration signal <b>14</b> at a specified time interval. </p><p>[0005] Examples of the angular-velocity sensor <b>12</b> include a gyroscope, and examples of the attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>11</b> include a start tracker. In the sequential Kalman filter <b>13</b>, the noise characteristics of the attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>11</b> and the angular-velocity sensor <b>12</b>, which are mounted on the artificial satellite, are modeled by using a probability model technique, thereby estimating and removing the noise included in the angular-velocity signal <b>15</b> and the attitude-angle calibration signal <b>14</b>. </p><p>[0006] The attitude detection system shown in FIG. 1 has a relatively simple structure, and is originally developed as an on-board processing system, i.e., a real-time processing system on the artificial satellite. However, since the ground station can also extract time-series data of the angular-velocity signal <b>15</b> and the attitude-angle calibration signal <b>14</b> from the telemetry data received by the ground station, the attitude detection system of FIG. 1 is generally and widely used as an on-board processing system as well as a ground processing system. </p><p>[0007] In the conventional attitude detection system of FIG. 1, although the attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>11</b> generally has a higher accuracy compared to the angular-velocity sensor <b>12</b>, the attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>11</b> has a longer measurement cycle which is, for example, more than <b>10</b> times longer compared to the measurement cycle of the angular-velocity sensor <b>12</b>. Accordingly, even if the measurement cycle of the angular-velocity sensor <b>12</b> may be significantly improved, the frequency band of the final attitude-angle signal <b>16</b> obtained thereby is relatively limited due to the waste time caused by the characteristics of the attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>11</b>. </p><p>[0008] It may be considered that the angular-velocity sensor <b>12</b> alone is used for obtaining the attitude-angle signal <b>16</b> to improve the measurement cycle. However, in this case, there arises a problem that the noise involved in the angular-velocity signal <b>15</b> largely affects and degrades the accuracy of the calculated attitude-angle signal <b>16</b>, although it is possible to detect the fluctuation of the attitude angle of the artificial satellite itself in a higher frequency range. </p><p>[0009] <ref type="patent">JP Application 2000-265553</ref> proposes an attitude detection system for an artificial satellite which can solve the above problem in the conventional technique. The proposed system includes an on-board high-frequency attitude-angle sensor, in addition to the attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>11</b> and the angular-velocity sensor <b>12</b> shown in FIG. 1, thereby generating a broad-band attitude-angle signal. </p><p>[0010]FIG. 2 shows the proposed system, which includes a telemetry data memory <b>220</b> for storing the telemetry data received from the artificial satellite, a first data extractor <b>201</b> for extracting attitude-angle calibration data <b>209</b> as time-series data from the telemetry data memory <b>220</b>, a second data extractor <b>202</b> for extracting angular-velocity data <b>210</b> as time-series data from the telemetry data memory <b>220</b>, and a third data extractor <b>205</b> for extracting high-frequency attitude-angle data as time series data from the telemetry data memory <b>220</b>. </p><p>[0011] An angular displacement sensor using a liquid is used as the on-board high-frequency attitude-angle sensor <b>205</b>, whereby the attitude angle of the artificial satellite can be detected at a higher frequency compared to the angular-velocity data <b>210</b>. The high-frequency attitude-angle signal, stored in the telemetry data memory <b>220</b>, is extracted by the third data extractor <b>205</b> as a high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>213</b>. </p><p>[0012] The sequential Kalman filter <b>203</b> generates an attitude-angle signal <b>211</b> based on the attitude-angle calibration signal <b>209</b> and the angular-velocity signal <b>210</b> extracted by the first data extractor <b>201</b> and the second data extractor <b>202</b>, respectively, from the telemetry data memory <b>220</b>. The attitude-angle signal <b>211</b> generated by the sequential Kalman filter <b>203</b> is passed by a low-pass filter <b>204</b>, interpolated in an interpolator <b>207</b>, and then delivered to an attitude data adder <b>208</b> as a low-frequency interpolated signal <b>215</b>. </p><p>[0013] The high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>213</b> extracted by the third data extractor <b>205</b> is passed by a band-pass-filter <b>206</b> and then delivered to the attitude data adder <b>208</b> as a high-frequency attitude signal <b>214</b>. The attitude data adder <b>208</b> adds both the low-frequency interpolated signal <b>215</b> and the high-frequency attitude signal <b>214</b> together to generate a high-accuracy broad-band attitude-angle signal <b>216</b>. </p><p>[0014] In the proposed system of FIG. 2, as described above, the low-frequency attitude signal <b>212</b> obtained by the sequential Kalman filter <b>203</b> and the low-pass filter <b>204</b> is interpolated in the interpolator <b>207</b>, and then added to the high-frequency attitude signal <b>214</b> in the attitude data adder <b>208</b> to obtain the high-accuracy attitude signal <b>216</b>. </p><p>[0015] In the above operation of the sequential Kalman filter <b>203</b>, the angular-velocity signal <b>210</b> is sampled at a specified time interval corresponding to the measurement interval of the angular-velocity sensor, and integrated with respect to time while being calibrated based on the attitude-angle calibration signal <b>209</b>. In general, a shorter step interval for the integration provides a higher accuracy. However, in the proposed system, the step interval in the integration is determined by the frequency, or the measurement cycle, of the angular-velocity sensor which has a relatively limited performance as to the measurement cycle, and thus an accurate broad-band attitude-angle signal by the system is difficult to expect. </p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION </heading><p>[0016] In view of the above problems in the conventional attitude detection system and the proposed attitude detection system proposed in <ref type="patent">JP Application 2000-265553</ref>, it is an object of the present invention to provide an attitude detection system for an artificial satellite, which is capable of detecting a broad-band attitude-angle signal for the artificial satellite with improved accuracy. </p><p>[0017] It is another object of the present invention to provide a method for detecting a broad-band attitude-angle signal for the artificial satellite with improved accuracy. </p><p>[0018] The present invention provides an attitude detection system for an artificial satellite including a telemetry data memory for storing telemetry data received from the artificial satellite, a first data extractor for extracting attitude-angle calibration data from the telemetry data memory as time-series data, a second data extractor for extracting angular-velocity data from the telemetry data memory as time-series data, an interpolator for interpolating the angular-velocity data to generate interpolated angular-velocity data, a sequential Kalman filter to generate a low-frequency attitude-angle signal from the interpolated angular-velocity data and the attitude-angle calibration data, a third extractor for extracting high-frequency attitude-angle data as time series data from the telemetry data memory to generate a high-frequency attitude-angle signal, and an adder for adding the low-frequency attitude-angle signal and the high-frequency attitude-angle signal together to generate a broad-band attitude-angle signal. </p><p>[0019] The present invention also provides a method for detecting attitude of an artificial satellite, including the steps of: storing telemetry data received from the artificial satellite, extracting attitude-angle calibration data from the telemetry data memory as time-series data, extracting angular-velocity data from the telemetry data memory as time-series data, interpolating the angular-velocity data to generate interpolated angular-velocity data, generating a low-frequency attitude-angle signal from the interpolated angular-velocity data and the attitude-angle calibration data, extracting high-frequency attitude-angle data as time series data from the telemetry data memory to generate a high-frequency attitude-angle signal, and adding the low-frequency attitude-angle signal and the high-frequency attitude-angle signal together to generate a broad-band attitude-angle is signal. </p><p>[0020] In the attitude detection system of the present invention, the sequential Kalman filter has a shorter step interval in the integration, which corresponds to the data interval of the interpolated angular-velocity data in the interpolated angular-velocity signal and is thus shorter than the sampling interval of the original angular-velocity signal. Thus, the integrated data obtained by the sequential Kalman filter has a higher accuracy compared to that obtained in the proposed system. That is, this configuration provides a higher accuracy in the low-frequency attitude-angle signal. Although high-frequency noise is increased by the shorter step interval in the integration and errors of the interpolated attitude-angle signal are caused by the interpolation in the low-frequency attitude-angle signal are, these noise and the errors are cancelled by addition of the high-frequency attitude-angle signal to the low-frequency attitude-angle signal. The method of the present invention also achieves a similar advantage. </p><p>[0021] The above and other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will be more apparent from the following description, referring to the accompanying drawings.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS </heading><p>[0022]FIG. 1 is a block diagram of a conventional attitude detection system for an artificial satellite. </p><p>[0023]FIG. 2 is a block diagram of the attitude detection system proposed in the JP patent application. </p><p>[0024]FIG. 3 is a block diagram of an attitude detection system according to an embodiment of the present invention. </p><p>[0025]FIG. 4 is a graph showing simulation data in a simulation, representing the attitude angle of an artificial satellite, which was used for evaluation of the first embodiment. </p><p>[0026]FIG. 5 is a graph showing the attitude angle of the artificial satellite obtained in the simulation by the conventional attitude detection system of FIG. 1 in the case of the fluctuation of the satellite shown in FIG. 4. </p><p>[0027]FIG. 6 is a graph showing the attitude angle of the artificial satellite obtained in the simulation by the attitude detection system of the embodiment in the case of the fluctuation of the satellite shown in FIG. 4.</p><heading>PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS OF THE INVENTION </heading><p>[0028] Now, the present invention is more specifically described with reference to the accompanying drawing. </p><p>[0029] Referring to FIG. 3, an attitude detection system according to an embodiment of the present invention is provided in a ground station and operates in association with on-board sensors <b>117</b> to <b>119</b> mounted on an artificial satellite. The on-board sensors include an attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>117</b> for detecting the attitude angle of the artificial satellite to generate an attitude-angle calibration signal, an angular-velocity sensor <b>118</b> for detecting the angular velocity of the artificial satellite to generate an angular-velocity signal, and a high-frequency attitude-angle sensor <b>119</b> for detecting the attitude angle of the artificial satellite to generate a high-frequency attitude-angle signal. The term “high frequency” as used herein means a relative expression, wherein the attitude-angle sensor <b>119</b> has a higher operational speed and generates a higher-frequency signal compared to the operational speed and the signal frequency of the angular-velocity sensor <b>118</b>. </p><p>[0030] The attitude detection system of FIG. 3 includes a telemetry data memory <b>120</b> for storing the telemetry data received from the artificial satellite, a first data extractor <b>101</b> for extracting attitude-angle calibration data from the telemetry data memory <b>120</b>, a second data extractor <b>102</b> for extracting angular-velocity data from the telemetry data memo <b>120</b>, a third data extractor <b>105</b> for extracting high-frequency attitude-angle data from the telemetry data memory <b>120</b>, a sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b> having a shorter step interval in the integration of the angular velocity signal compared to the sampling interval of the angular-velocity sensor <b>118</b>, an angular-velocity data aliasing filter <b>104</b> for receiving an angular-velocity signal <b>110</b> extracted by the second data extractor <b>102</b>, a high-frequency attitude-angle data aliasing filter <b>106</b> for receiving a high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>113</b> extracted by the third data extractor <b>105</b>, an interpolator <b>107</b> for interpolating the corrected angular-velocity signal <b>111</b> received from the angular-velocity data aliasing filter <b>104</b>, and an attitude-angle data adder <b>108</b> for receiving a high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>114</b> from the high-frequency data aliasing filter <b>106</b> and a low-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>115</b> from the sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b>. </p><p>[0031] The sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b> receives the interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>112</b> from the interpolator <b>107</b> and the attitude-angle calibration signal <b>109</b> extracted by the first data extractor <b>101</b>, to generate the low-frequency attitude signal <b>115</b> by integrating the interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>112</b> while calibrating the same based on the attitude-angle calibration signal <b>109</b>. The attitude data adder <b>108</b> adds the low-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>115</b> to the high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>114</b> received from the high-frequency attitude data aliasing filter <b>106</b>, thereby generating a broad-band attitude-angle signal <b>116</b>. </p><p>[0032] The artificial satellite periodically forwards a variety of telemetry data detected on the orbit of the artificial satellite. The telemetry data memory <b>120</b> successively stores the telemetry data as time-series data. The first through third data extractors <b>101</b>, <b>102</b> and <b>105</b> operate at different cycles and extract at least the telemetry data which are detected at a time, to deliver the attitude-angle calibration signals <b>109</b>, the angular-velocity signal <b>110</b> and the high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>113</b>, respectively. </p><p>[0033] The angular-velocity data aliasing filter <b>104</b> is implemented by a low-pass filter of a first power or more sequential number of power, which has a cut-off frequency equal to half the sampling frequency of the angular-velocity sensor <b>118</b>. The angular-velocity data aliasing filter <b>104</b> passes the low-frequency components of the angular-velocity signal <b>110</b> to output the corrected angular-velocity signal <b>111</b>. </p><p>[0034] The interpolator <b>107</b> receives the corrected angular-velocity signal <b>111</b> to deliver the interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>112</b>. </p><p>[0035] The interpolator <b>107</b> interpolates data in the corrected angular-velocity signal <b>110</b> to increase the number of data in the corrected angular-velocity signal <b>111</b> so that the interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>111</b> has a number of data each corresponding to one of the data in the high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>113</b>. In other words, the interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>112</b> is obtained as time-series data sampled at a pseudo sampling cycle equal to the sampling cycle of the high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>113</b>. </p><p>[0036] The sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b> integrates the interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>112</b> at a step interval equal to the sampling cycle of the high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>113</b> while using the attitude-angle calibration signal <b>109</b> as calibration data, thereby generating a low-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>115</b>. </p><p>[0037] It is to be noted that the interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>112</b> has a probability of a lower accuracy compared to the corrected angular-velocity signal <b>111</b>. </p><p>[0038] The sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b> changes the relative relationship between the noise model value of the attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>117</b> and the noise model value of the angular-velocity sensor <b>118</b> in a considerably amount from the design value which is provided as a hardware characteristic, the relative relationship being the design parameter of the sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b>. </p><p>[0039] More specifically, the sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b> changes the predetermined value of the noise model of the angular-velocity sensor <b>118</b> provided as the specification value to a higher value, in order to suppress degradation of the accuracy caused by the interpolation in the interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>112</b> and maintain the accuracy of the low-frequency attitude signal <b>115</b> generated in the sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b>. It is to be noted that a strict setting is required of the attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>17</b> in this case. In view of this, it is preferable to use an attitude-angle calibration sensor <b>117</b> having an excellent noise characteristic to obtain an accurate low-frequency attitude signal <b>115</b>. </p><p>[0040] The high-frequency attitude-angle data aliasing filter <b>106</b> is implemented by a low-pass filter of a first-power function or a higher-power function having a cut-off frequency equal to half the sampling frequency of the high-frequency attitude-angle sensor <b>119</b>. The high-frequency attitude-angle data aliasing filter <b>106</b> receives the high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>113</b> to deliver the high-frequency attitude signal <b>114</b>. </p><p>[0041] The attitude data adder <b>108</b> receives the low-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>115</b> and the high-frequency attitude-angle signal <b>114</b>, add together the corresponding data, which correspond to each other in the detected time, in both the signals <b>114</b> and <b>115</b>, and delivers a broad-band attitude-angle signal <b>116</b> representing the attitude angle of the artificial satellite at a higher accuracy. </p><p>[0042] The above embodiment is directed to a broad-band attitude detection system provided in the ground station which receives the telemetry data from the artificial satellite. </p><p>[0043] In the above embodiment, interpolation of the corrected angular-velocity signal <b>111</b> assists the sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b> to integrate the angular-velocity signal by using a short step interval corresponding to the sampling cycle of the high-frequency attitude-angle sensor <b>119</b>. The interpolation in the interpolator <b>107</b> uses a linear interpolation in this embodiment, wherein the interpolation is conducted by using a straight line passing two adjacent data actually obtained by the angular velocity sensor <b>118</b>, to generate interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>112</b> corresponding to a higher sampling frequency. Addition of the low-frequency attitude signal <b>115</b> obtained from the angular-velocity sensor <b>118</b> which samples the angular velocity at a lower frequency and the high-frequency attitude signal <b>114</b> obtained from the high-frequency attitude-angle sensor <b>119</b> which samples the attitude-angle at a higher frequency achieves an accurate broad-band attitude signal. </p><p>[0044] A simulation is conducted using simulation data representing fluctuation of the artificial satellite for evaluating the above embodiment. The simulation data, depicted in FIG. 4, includes a large number of frequency components, residing between 0.05 Hz and 50 Hz especially in the time range between five seconds and ten seconds elapsed since the start of the simulation. </p><p>[0045] Referring to FIG. 5, the attitude angle detected by the conventional attitude detection system of FIG. 1 in the simulation includes only limited frequency components having lower frequencies. That is, the conventional attitude detection system could not detect the high-frequency components of the fluctuation of the attitude angle of the artificial satellite shown in FIG. 4, because the sampling frequency of the angular-velocity sensor <b>118</b> limits the frequency range of the attitude-angle signal <b>116</b> in the conventional system of FIG. 1. It is to be noted that the sampling cycle of the angular-velocity sensor <b>118</b> is set at 0.1 second in the simulation, which resulted in degraded detection accuracy of the fluctuation. That is, the high-frequency components of the fluctuation residing in the time range between the five seconds and the ten seconds could not be detected by the conventional system. </p><p>[0046] Referring to FIG. 6, the attitude angle in the broad-band attitude-angle signal <b>116</b> detected by the attitude detection system of FIG. 3 in the simulation includes high-frequency components well following the fluctuated angle of FIG. 4 especially in the time range between five seconds and ten seconds. The interpolator <b>107</b> used a linear interpolation, whereas the sequential Kalman filter <b>103</b> used the interpolated angular-velocity signal <b>112</b> and the attitude-angle calibration signal <b>109</b> after changing the noise parameters thereof. </p><p>[0047] In a modification of the above embodiment, the interpolator <b>107</b> uses a spline interpolation, wherein the angular velocities residing between adjacent two detected data of the angular velocity are approximated by a function having suitable power terms. The function may have a plurality of terms having respective powers of time for approximation. </p><p>[0048] The spline interpolation approximates undetected data residing between adjacent two of the actually detected data by using a function having a third or more power term as a maximum power term, thereby more accurately approximating the undetected data compared to the linear interpolation. The suitable maximum power of the terms in the function may be between around third power to around sixth power to obtain optimum results. </p><p>[0049] Since the above embodiments are described only for examples, the present invention is not limited to the above embodiments and various modifications or alterations can be easily made therefrom by those skilled in the art without departing from the scope of the present invention. </p></description><claims load-source="us" status="new" lang="EN"><claim-statement>What is claimed is: </claim-statement><claim id="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00001" num="1"><claim-text><b>1</b>. An attitude detection system for an artificial satellite comprising a telemetry data memory for storing telemetry data received from the artificial satellite, a first data extractor for extracting attitude-angle calibration data from said telemetry data memory as time-series data, a second data extractor for extracting angular-velocity data from said telemetry data memory as time-series data, an interpolator for interpolating said angular-velocity data to generate interpolated angular-velocity data, a sequential Kalman filter for generating a low-frequency attitude-angle signal from said interpolated angular-velocity data and said attitude-angle calibration data, a third extractor for extracting high-frequency attitude-angle data as time-series data from said telemetry data memory to generate a high-frequency attitude-angle signal, and an adder for adding said low-frequency attitude-angle signal and said high-frequency attitude-angle signal to generate a broad-band attitude-angle signal. </claim-text></claim><claim id="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00002" num="2"><claim-text><b>2</b>. The attitude detection system as defined in <claim-ref idref="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said interpolator uses a liner interpolation. </claim-text></claim><claim id="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00003" num="3"><claim-text><b>3</b>. The attitude detection system as defined in <claim-ref idref="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said interpolator uses a spline interpolation. </claim-text></claim><claim id="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00004" num="4"><claim-text><b>4</b>. The attitude detection system as defined in <claim-ref idref="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a low-pass filter is interposed between said second data extractor and said interpolator. </claim-text></claim><claim id="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00005" num="5"><claim-text><b>5</b>. A method for detecting attitude of an artificial satellite, comprising the steps of: storing telemetry data received from the artificial satellite, extracting attitude-angle calibration data from said telemetry data memory as time-series data, extracting angular-velocity data from said telemetry data memory as time-series data, interpolating said angular-velocity data to generate interpolated angular-velocity data, generating a low-frequency attitude-angle signal from said interpolated angular-velocity data and said attitude-angle calibration data, extracting high-frequency attitude-angle data as time series data from said telemetry data memory to generate a high-frequency attitude-angle signal, and adding said low-frequency attitude-angle signal and said high-frequency attitude-angle signal together to generate a broad-band attitude-angle signal. </claim-text></claim><claim id="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00006" num="6"><claim-text><b>6</b>. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said interpolating step uses a liner interpolation. </claim-text></claim><claim id="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00007" num="7"><claim-text><b>7</b>. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said interpolating step uses a spline interpolation. </claim-text></claim><claim id="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00008" num="8"><claim-text><b>8</b>. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="US-20030004620-A1-CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said interpolating step interpolates said angular-velocity data after passing the same through a low-pass filter.</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure id="figure-D00000" num="figure-D00000"><img id="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00000.TIF" orientation="unknown" wi=""  img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00000.TIF" inline="no" he=""/></figure><figure id="figure-D00001"  num="figure-D00001"><img id="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00001.TIF"  orientation="unknown" wi=""  img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00001.TIF" inline="no" he=""/></figure><figure id="figure-D00002" num="figure-D00002"><img id="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00002.TIF" orientation="unknown" wi="" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00002.TIF" inline="no" he=""/></figure><figure id="figure-D00003" num="figure-D00003"><img id="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00003.TIF" orientation="unknown" wi="" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00003.TIF" inline="no" he=""/></figure><figure id="figure-D00004" num="figure-D00004"><img id="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00004.TIF" orientation="unknown" wi="" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00004.TIF" inline="no" he=""/></figure><figure id="figure-D00005" num="figure-D00005"><img id="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00005.TIF" orientation="unknown" wi="" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00005.TIF" inline="no" he=""/></figure><figure id="figure-D00006" num="figure-D00006"><img id="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00006.TIF" orientation="unknown" wi="" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="US20030004620A1-20030102-D00006.TIF" inline="no" he=""/></figure></drawings><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>