<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0070234"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>

	<note type="doctype">Analysis of a Case</note>
	
	Ⅲ<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>From Paper to Electron:<lb/> How an STM Journal Can Survive the<lb/> Disruptive Technology of the Internet<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>KENT R. ANDERSON<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	A b s t r a c t 
	<div type="abstract">The Internet represents a different type of technology for publishers of<lb/> scientific, technical, and medical journals. It is not a technology that sustains current markets and<lb/> creates new efficiencies but is, rather, a disruptive technology that could radically alter market<lb/> forces, profit expectations, and business models. This paper is a translation and amplification of<lb/> the research done in this area, applied to a large-circulation new science journal, Pediatrics. The<lb/> findings suggest that the journal of the future will be electronic, have a less volatile cost<lb/> structure, be supported more by services than by content, be less able to rely on subscription<lb/> revenues, and abandon certain elements of current value networks. It also provides a possible<lb/> framework for other publishers to use to evaluate their own journals relative to this disruptive<lb/> technology.<lb/></div>

	Ⅲ
	<reference>J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2000;7:234–245. .<lb/></reference>

	Affiliation of the author: 
	<byline>
	<affiliation>American Academy of Pediatrics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Elk<lb/> Grove Village, Illinois.<lb/></address>

	Correspondence and reprints: 
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Kent R. Anderson, Director,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Di-<lb/>vision of Medical Journals and Professional Periodicals, Amer-<lb/>ican Academy of Pediatrics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>141 Northwest Point Boulevard,<lb/> Elk Grove Village, IL 60007;</address>

	e-mail: 
	<email>͗kanderson@aap.org͘.<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received for publication: 9/24/99; accepted for publication:<lb/> 1/4/00..<lb/></note>

	<reference>Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association Volume 7 Number 3 May / Jun 2000</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
