<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="007336v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Non--respiratory functions of Saccharomyces cerevisiae<lb/> mitochondria are required for optimal attractiveness to<lb/> Drosophila melanogaster<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Kelly M. Schiabor 1 , Allison S. Quan 1 and Michael B. Eisen 1,2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Molecular and Cell Biology, and 2 Howard Hughes Medical Institute,<lb/> University of California,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Berkeley, CA.</address>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">While screening a large collection of wild and laboratory yeast isolates for their<lb/> ability to attract Drosophila melanogaster adults, we noticed a large difference in fly<lb/> preference for two nearly isogenic strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae, BY4741 and<lb/> BY4742. Using standard genetic analyses, we tracked the preference difference to<lb/> the lack of functional mitochondria the stock of BY4742 used in the initial<lb/> experiment. We used gas chromatography coupled with mass spectroscopy to<lb/> examine the volatile compounds produced by BY4741 and the mitochondria--<lb/>deficient BY4742, and found they differed significantly. We found that several ethyl<lb/> esters are present at much higher levels in strains with functional mitochondria,<lb/> even in fermentative conditions. We confirmed the role of these ethyl esters in<lb/> attraction by examining an EEB1Δ strain which reduces ethyl ester production. We<lb/> found that nitrogen levels in the substrate affect the production of these<lb/> compounds, and that they are produced at high levels by strains with functional<lb/> mitochondria in the fermentation of natural substrates. Collectively these<lb/> observations demonstrate the effect core metabolic processes have in mediating the<lb/> interaction between yeasts and insect vectors, and highlight the importance of non--<lb/>respirative mitochondrial functions in yeast ecology.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
