<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="007567v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">© Oxford University Press 2005</note>

	1<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">Sequence Analysis<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>poRe: an R package for the visualization and analysis of na-<lb/>nopore sequencing data<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mick Watson 1* , Marian Thomson 2 , Judith Risse 2 , Richard Talbot 1 , Javier Santoyo-Lopez 2 , Ka-<lb/>rim Gharbi 2 and Mark Blaxter 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Edinburgh Genomics, The Roslin Institute and R(D)SVS, University of Edinburgh,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Easter Bush, EH25 9RG<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Edinburgh Genomics, Ashworth Laboratories, University of Edinburgh, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>W Mains Rd, Edinburgh, EH9 3JT<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received on XXXXX; revised on XXXXX; accepted on XXXXX<lb/></note>

	Associate Editor: XXXXXXX<lb/> ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Motivation: The Oxford Nanopore MinION device represents a<lb/> unique sequencing technology. As a mobile sequencing device<lb/> powered by the USB port of a laptop, the MinION has huge potential<lb/> applications. To enable these applications, the bioinformatics com-<lb/>munity will need to design and build a suite of tools specifically for<lb/> MinION data.<lb/> Results: Here we present poRe, a package for the statistical soft-<lb/>ware R that enables users to manipulate, organize, summarise and<lb/> visualize MinION nanopore sequencing data. As a packge for R,<lb/> poRe has been tested on both Windows and Linux. Crucially, the<lb/> Windows version allows users to analyse MinION data on the Win-<lb/>dows laptop attached to the device<lb/></div>

	Availability: 
    <note type="availability">Pre-built R packages for Windows and Linux are avail-<lb/>able under a BSD license at http://sourceforge.net/projects/rpore/<lb/></note>

	Contact:
	<email>mick.watson@roslin.ed.ac.uk</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
