<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="007583v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>BIOINFORMATICS APPLICATIONS NOTE<lb/> Vol. 00 no. 00 2014<lb/> Pages 1-2<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>UniqTag: Content-derived unique and stable identifiers<lb/> for gene annotation<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Shaun Jackman 1,2, * , Joerg Bohlmann 3,4 and İnanc ¸Birol 1,5 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Genome Sciences Centre, British Columbia Cancer Agency,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Vancouver, BC, Canada<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Graduate Program in Bioinformatics, University of British Columbia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Vancouver, BC, Canada<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Michael Smith Laboratories, University of British Columbia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Vancouver, BC, Canada<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Forest Science, University of British Columbia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Vancouver, BC, Canada<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Department of Medical Genetics, University of British Columbia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Vancouver, BC, Canada<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received on XXXXX; revised on XXXXX; accepted on XXXXX<lb/></note>

	Associate Editor: XXXXXXX<lb/> ABSTRACT<lb/> Summary<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">When working on an ongoing genome sequencing and assembly<lb/> project, it is rather inconvenient when gene identifiers change from<lb/> one build of the assembly to the next. The gene labelling system<lb/> described here, UniqTag, addresses this common challenge. UniqTag<lb/> assigns a unique identifier to each gene that is a representative k-<lb/>mer, a string of length k, selected from the sequence of that gene.<lb/> Unlike serial numbers, these identifiers are stable between different<lb/> assemblies and annotations of the same data without requiring that<lb/> previous annotations be lifted over by sequence alignment. We assign<lb/> UniqTag identifiers to nine builds of the Ensembl human genome<lb/> spanning seven years to demonstrate this stability.<lb/></div>

	Availability and implementation<lb/> 
	<note type="availability">The implementation of UniqTag is available at<lb/> https://github.com/sjackman/uniqtag<lb/> Supplementary data and code to reproduce it is available at<lb/> https://github.com/sjackman/uniqtag-paper<lb/> </note>

	Contact<lb/>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Shaun Jackman</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	&lt;<email>sjackman@bcgsc.ca</email>&gt;<lb/>

	Inanc Birol
	&lt;<email>ibirol@bcgsc.ca</email>&gt;

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
