<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="008052v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	Title: 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Transposable elements contribute to activation of maize genes in response to<lb/> abiotic stress<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle> 

	Running title: TEs contribute to stress-responsive gene expression !<lb/> 

	Authors:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Irina Makarevitch 1,2 , Amanda J. Waters 2 , Patrick T. West 2 , Michelle C. Stitzer 3 ,<lb/> Jeffrey Ross-Ibarra 3 , Nathan M. Springer 2 * !<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Affiliations:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Biology, Hamline University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Saint Paul, MN USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Plant Biology, University of Minnesota,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Saint Paul, MN USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Plant Sciences, University of California-Davis,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Davis, CA USA.<lb/></address>

	*Correspondence to:
	<email>springer@umn.edu<lb/></email>

	! ! ! 1<lb/> ! ! ! 

	Abstract: 
	<div type="abstract">Transposable elements (TEs) account for a large portion of the genome in many<lb/> eukaryotic species. Despite their reputation as &quot;junk&quot; DNA or genomic parasites<lb/> deleterious for the host, TEs have complex interactions with host genes and the potential<lb/> to contribute to regulatory variation in gene expression. It has been hypothesized that<lb/> TEs and genes they insert near may be transcriptionally activated in response to stress<lb/> conditions. The maize genome, with many different types of TEs interspersed with<lb/> genes, provides an ideal system to study the genome-wide influence of TEs on gene<lb/> regulation. To analyze the magnitude of the TE effect on gene expression response to<lb/> environmental changes, we profiled gene and TE transcript levels in maize seedlings<lb/> exposed to a number of abiotic stresses. Many genes exhibit up-or down-regulation in<lb/> response to these stress conditions. The analysis of TE families inserted within upstream<lb/> regions of up-regulated genes revealed that between four and nine different TE families<lb/> are associated with up-regulated gene expression in each of these stress conditions,<lb/> affecting up to 20% of the genes up-regulated in response to abiotic stress and as many as<lb/> 33% of genes that are only expressed in response to stress. Expression of many of these<lb/> same TE families also responds to the same stress conditions. The analysis of the stress-<lb/> induced transcripts and proximity of the transposon to the gene suggests that these TEs<lb/> may provide local enhancer activities that stimulate stress-responsive gene expression.<lb/> Our data on allelic variation for insertions of several of these TEs show strong correlation<lb/> between the presence of TE insertions and stress-responsive up-regulation of gene<lb/> expression. Our findings suggest that TEs provide an important source of allelic<lb/> regulatory variation in gene response to abiotic stress in maize.<lb/></div>  

	! 2<lb/> 

	Author summary: <lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Transposable elements are mobile DNA elements that are a prevalent component of many <lb/>eukaryotic genomes. While transposable elements can often have deleterious effects <lb/>through insertions into protein-coding genes they may also contribute to regulatory <lb/>variation of gene expression. There are a handful of examples in which specific <lb/>transposon insertions contribute to regulatory variation of nearby genes, particularly in <lb/>response to environmental stress. We sought to understand the genome-wide influence of <lb/>transposable elements on gene expression responses to abiotic stress in maize, a plant <lb/>with many families of transposable elements located in between genes. Our analysis <lb/>suggests that a small number of maize transposable element families may contribute to <lb/>the response of nearby genes to abiotic stress by providing stress-responsive enhancer-<lb/>like functions. The specific insertions of transposable elements are often polymorphic <lb/>within a species. Our data demonstrate that allelic variation for insertions of the <lb/>transposable elements associated with stress-responsive expression can contribute to <lb/>variation in the regulation of nearby genes. Thus novel insertions of transposable <lb/>elements provide a potential mechanism for genes to acquire cis-regulatory influences <lb/>that could contribute to heritable variation for stress response. <lb/></div>

	! <lb/>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
