<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="015370v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	Collado-Torres et al.<lb/> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>derfinder: Software for annotation-agnostic RNA-seq differential expression analysis<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	Authors:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Leonardo Collado-Torres 1,2 , Alyssa C. Frazee 1 , Michael I. Love 3 ,<lb/> Rafael A. Irizarry 3 , Andrew E. Jaffe 1,2,4* , Jeffrey T. Leek 1,4*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1. Department of Biostatistics, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Baltimore,<lb/> MD 21205 USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2. Lieber Institute for Brain Development, Johns Hopkins Medical Campus,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Baltimore, MD<lb/> 21205, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3. Department of Biostatistics, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute and Harvard School of Public<lb/> Health,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, MA 02115 USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4. Center for Computational Biology, McKusick-Nathans Institute of Genetic Medicine, Johns<lb/> Hopkins University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Baltimore, MD 21025, USA<lb/></address>

	* Corresponding authors: AEJ:
	<email>andrew.jaffe@libd.org</email>

	; JTL:
	<email>jtleek@gmail.com</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background Differential expression analysis of RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) data typically relies on<lb/> reconstructing transcripts or counting reads that overlap known gene structures. Previously we<lb/> introduced an intermediate approach called differentially expressed region (DER) finder that seeks<lb/> to identify contiguous regions of the genome showing differential expression signal at single base<lb/> resolution that does not rely on existing annotation or potentially inaccurate transcript discovery.<lb/> However, there were computational challenges involved with performing base-resolution analyses<lb/> in large numbers of samples at genome scale.<lb/> Results Here we describe a new version of the derfinder software that allows for: (1) genome-<lb/>scale analyses in a large number of samples, (2) flexible statistical modeling, including multi-group<lb/> and time course analyses, and (3) a new, computationally efficient approach to re-analysis at base<lb/> resolution called expressed-region analysis. We also introduce functionality for annotating and<lb/> plotting base-resolution data to identify artifacts and confirm results. We apply this approach<lb/></div> 

	<page>1<lb/></page>

	<date>2015/02/17<lb/></date> 

	Collado-Torres et al.<lb/> 

	<div type="abstract">to public RNA-seq data from the developing human brain to illustrate the types of analyses and<lb/> results possible using derfinder.<lb/> Conclusions Single-base and expressed-region RNA-sequencing analysis provides compromise be-<lb/>tween full transcript reconstruction and gene-level analysis. derfinder is software designed to<lb/> identify, visualize, and interpret differentially expressed regions. The package is available from<lb/> Bioconductor at www.bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/derfinder.html.<lb/></div>

	Key words:
	<keyword>RNA sequencing, differential expression analysis, coverage, gene annotation, gene expression</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
