<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="018861v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	Running head: Species interactions in Markov networks<lb/>

	Title:
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Estimating species interactions from observational data with Markov networks<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	Author:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>David J. Harris</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	: 
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Population Biology;</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1 Shields Avenue, Davis CA, 95616</address>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Inferring species interactions from observational data is one of the most controversial tasks in<lb/> community ecology. One difficulty is that a single pairwise interaction can ripple through an<lb/> ecological network and produce surprising indirect consequences. For example, two<lb/> competing species would ordinarily correlate negatively in space, but this effect can be<lb/> reversed in the presence of a third species that is capable of outcompeting both of them<lb/> when it is present. Here, I apply models from statistical physics, called Markov networks or<lb/> Markov random fields, that can predict the direct and indirect consequences of any possible<lb/> species interaction matrix. Interactions in these models can be estimated from observational<lb/> data via maximum likelihood. Using simulated landscapes with known pairwise interaction<lb/> strengths, I evaluated Markov networks and several existing approaches. The Markov<lb/> networks consistently outperformed other methods, correctly isolating direct interactions<lb/> between species pairs even when indirect interactions or abiotic environmental effects largely<lb/> overpowered them. A linear approximation, based on partial covariances, also performed well<lb/> as long as the number of sampled locations exceeded the number of species in the data.<lb/> Indirect effects reliably caused a common null modeling approach to produce incorrect<lb/> inferences, however.<lb/></div>

	Key words:
	<keyword>Ecological interactions; Occurrence data; Species associations; Markov network;<lb/> Markov random field; Ising model; Biogeography; Presence-absence matrix; Null model</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
