<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="023093v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The Nicrophorus vespilloides genome and methylome, a beetle with complex social behavior 1 2<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Christopher B. Cunningham 1,* , Lexiang Ji 2 , R. Axel W. Wiberg 3 , Jennifer Shelton 4 , Elizabeth C. McKinney 1 , 3<lb/> Darren J. Parker 3 , Richard B. Meagher 1 , Kyle M. Benowitz 1 , Eileen M. Roy-Zokan 1 , Michael G. Ritchie 3 , 4<lb/> Susan J. Brown 4 , Robert J. Schmitz 1 , Allen J. Moore 1,* 5 6<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Affiliations: 7 8<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Genetics, University of Georgia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Athens, Georgia, USA 9 10<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Institute of Bioinformatics, University of Georgia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Athens, Georgia, USA 11</address>

	12<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Centre for Biological Diversity, School of Biology, University of St.</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Andrews, Fife, KY16 9TH, UK.</address>

	13 14<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Division of Biology &amp; Bioinformatics Center &amp; Arthropod Genomics Center, Kansas State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	15<lb/> 
	<address>Manhattan, Kansas, USA</address>

	16 17<lb/> *Corresponding Authors: CB Cunningham (
	<email>cbc83@uga.edu</email>

	) and AJ Moore (
	<email>ajmoore@uga.edu</email>

	) 18 19<lb/> Running Title: Burying Beetle Genome 20 2 21 Abstract 22<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Testing for conserved and novel mechanisms underlying phenotypic evolution requires a diversity of 23<lb/> genomes available for comparison spanning multiple independent lineages. For example, complex social 24<lb/> behavior in insects has been investigated primarily with eusocial lineages, nearly all of which are 25<lb/> Hymenoptera. If conserved genomic influences on sociality do exist, we need data from a wider range of taxa 26<lb/> that also vary in their levels of sociality. Here we present information on the genome of the subsocial beetle 27<lb/> Nicrophorus vespilloides, a species long used to investigate evolutionary questions of complex social 28<lb/> behavior. We used this genome to address two questions. First, does life history predict overlap in gene 29<lb/> models more strongly than phylogenetic groupings? Second, like other insects with highly developed social 30<lb/> behavior but unlike other beetles, does N. vespilloides have DNA methylation? We found the overlap in gene 31<lb/> models was similar between N. vespilloides and all other insect groups regardless of life history. Unlike 32<lb/> previous studies of beetles, we found strong evidence of DNA methylation, which allows this species to be 33<lb/> used to address questions about the potential role of methylation in social behavior. The addition of this 34<lb/> genome adds a coleopteran resource to answer questions about the evolution and mechanistic basis of 35<lb/> sociality.</div>

	36 37<lb/> 

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
