<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="030544v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	Title<lb/> 
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Sub-tomogram averaging in RELION Authors<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Tanmay A.M. Bharat* &amp; Sjors H.W. Scheres*</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Affiliations<lb/> Structural Studies Division, MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cambridge CB2 0QH,<lb/> United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	* Correspondence to:
	<email>tbharat@mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk</email>

	or
	<email>scheres@mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Electron cryo-tomography (cryo-ET) and sub-tomogram averaging allow structure determination<lb/> of macromolecules in situ, and are gaining in popularity for initial model generation for single-<lb/>particle analysis. We describe herein, a protocol for sub-tomogram averaging from cryo-ET data<lb/> using the RELION software. We describe how to calculate newly developed three-dimensional<lb/> models for the contrast transfer function and the missing wedge of each sub-tomogram, and how<lb/> to use these models for regularized-likelihood refinement. This approach has been implemented<lb/> in the existing workflow for single-particle analysis, so that users may conveniently tap into<lb/> existing capabilities of the RELION software. As example applications, we present analyses of<lb/> purified hepatitis B capsid particles and S. cerevisiae 80S ribosomes. In both cases, we show that<lb/> following initial classification, sub-tomogram averaging in RELION allows de novo generation<lb/> of initial models, and provides high-resolution maps where secondary structure elements are<lb/> resolved.<lb/> Recently, we introduced a new image processing approach to sub-tomogram averaging (Bharat<lb/> et al., 2015) that is based on regularized likelihood optimization in the RELION program</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
