<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="05367858"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Measuring the Generality of Nanotechnologies and<lb/> its Potential Economic Implications<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Fernando Gómez-Baquero<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>College of Nanoscale Science and Engineering, University at Albany<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Albany, NY 12203 USA<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract-Technologies that have applications in a large<lb/> number of sectors (general) have a more significant<lb/> positive impact on economic activity in comparison to<lb/> technologies that have applications in a few sectors<lb/> (focused). The former are referred to in the economic<lb/> literature as General Purpose Technologies (GPTs). Using<lb/> patent data I conclude that nanotechnologies show one of<lb/> the main characteristics of a GPT, high Generality, and I<lb/> show the progression of their generality over the time<lb/> period 1980-2008. A metric for generality is applied to<lb/> compare nanotechnologies with other technologies<lb/> previously identified as GPTs. The measurements show<lb/> that &apos;Nanotechnologies&apos; have a higher average Generality<lb/> than semiconductors, and that the level of Generality of<lb/> nanotechnologies has remained fairly constant for more<lb/> than two decades. Technologies such as &apos;Carbon<lb/> Nanotubes&apos;, and &apos;Nanoparticles&apos; have a higher Generality<lb/> than &apos;Quantum Dots&apos;. &apos;Self-assembly&apos; appears to have<lb/> transformed from a focused technology to a general<lb/> purpose one. The choice of classification system used to<lb/> calculate the Generality is relevant for the analysis of time<lb/> trends. A high level of Generality in nanotechnologies is<lb/> important to nanotech-intensive firms because it translates<lb/> into a larger potential range of applications of their<lb/> innovations. On the other hand, it also increases the<lb/> possibility of competition from rivals that were previously<lb/> developing focused technologies.<lb/></div>

	<div type="introduction">I. INTRODUCTION<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
