<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="054FDC7D60FFBA48D836D0EEFABFE07D14AFF13B"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Baseline Serum Cholesterol Is Selectively Associated<lb/> With Motor Speed and Not Rates of Cognitive Decline:<lb/> The Women&apos;s Health and Aging Study II<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Michelle M. Mielke, 1,2 Qian-Li Xue, 2,3 Jing Zhou, 2 Paulo H. M. Chaves, 2,3<lb/> Linda P. Fried, 2,3 and Michelle C. Carlson 2,4 </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of Psychiatry, Division of Geriatric Psychiatry and Neuropsychiatry,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Center on Aging and Health, </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	and 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/>Division of Geriatric Medicine and Gerontology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Baltimore, Maryland.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4<lb/> Department of Mental Health, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Baltimore, Maryland.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Background. Although several studies have investigated the association between cholesterol and dementia, few have<lb/> examined cholesterol and decline across cognitive domains. We examined serum total and high-density lipoprotein (HDL)<lb/> cholesterol, total-to-HDL ratio, and trajectories across cognitive domains.<lb/> Methods. Participants were 436 community-residing women (70-79 years old) in the Women&apos;s Health and Aging<lb/> Study II; they were screened to be physically high-functioning and cognitively intact at baseline. Cognition and other<lb/> health-related variables were assessed at five intervals spanning 9 years. Cognitive assessments included Trail Making<lb/> Test Parts A (TMT-A) and B (TMT-B), Hopkins Verbal Learning Test-Revised, Purdue Pegboard, and Mini-Mental State<lb/> Examination (MMSE). The association between baseline levels of serum lipids and cognitive trajectories were evaluated<lb/> using Generalized Estimating Equations (GEE). Covariates included age, education, race, vascular disease, serum<lb/> creatinine, depression, and lipid-lowering medications.<lb/> Results. In multivariate analyses, baseline higher total (p ¼ .02) and HDL (p ¼ .03) cholesterol were associated with<lb/> better performance on the Purdue Pegboard. Using clinical cholesterol cutoffs, baseline serum total cholesterol levels<lb/> .240 mg/dL were associated with the best performance (p ¼ .02). Baseline lipids were not associated with any other<lb/> cognitive tests; there were no Lipid 3 Time interactions.<lb/> Conclusion. Higher baseline serum lipid levels predicted better performance over time on a measure of motor speed,<lb/> but not memory or psychomotor or executive functioning in this population of elderly women. This association suggests<lb/> that peripheral cholesterol levels, measured in late-life, may not be a good predictor of subsequent cognitive decline.<lb/> Future research examining peripheral cholesterol over the life span and its relationship with cognition is needed.<lb/></div>

	Key Words: 
	<keywords>Cholesterol-Cognition-Motor speed-Biological aging.</keywords> 

	<page>619<lb/></page> 

	<title level="j">Journal of Gerontology: MEDICAL SCIENCES<lb/> </title>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright 2008 by The Gerontological Society of America<lb/> </note>

	<reference>2008, Vol. 63A, No. 6, 619-624 </reference>

	CORRESPONDENCE<lb/>

	Address correspondence to

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Michelle M. Mielke, PhD,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Johns Hopkins<lb/> University School of Medicine, Center on Aging and Health and<lb/> Department of Psychiatry, Division of Geriatric Psychiatry and Behavioral<lb/>Sciences, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>550 N. Broadway, Suite 308, Baltimore, MD 21205. </address>

	E-mail:<lb/>
	<email>mmielke1@jhmi.edu<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received January 17, 2007<lb/> Accepted August 26, 2007<lb/></note> 

	Decision Editor: 
	<editor>Luigi Ferrucci, MD, PhD</editor>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
