<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="05_-_PMID_17035732"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">©<lb/> 2 0 0 6 L A N D E S B I O S C I E N C E . D O N O T D I S T R I B U T E .<lb/></note>
	
	www.landesbioscience.com 

	<title level="j">Autophagy<lb/></title>

	[<reference>Autophagy 3:1, 45-47, January/February 2007</reference>]; 

	<note type="copyright">©2007 Landes Bioscience<lb/></note> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Gregory Lavieu 1, *<lb/> Francesca Scarlatti 2<lb/> Giusy Sala 2<lb/> Thierry Levade 3<lb/> Riccardo Ghidoni 2<lb/> Joëlle Botti 1,4<lb/> Patrice Codogno 1,4<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 INSERM U504; Institut Andre Lwoff; </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Villejuif, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Laboratory of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology; San Paolo Medical School;<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Milan, Italy<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 INSERM U466; Institut Louis Bugnard; Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de<lb/> Rangueil; </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Toulouse, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 INSERM U576; Faculte de Pharmacie; Universite Paris Sud;</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Chatenay-Malabry, France<lb/></address>

	*Correspondence to: 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Gregory Lavieu</docAuthor>
	</byline>; 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Columbia University; Department of<lb/> Physiology and Cellular Biophysics;</affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>Russ Berrie Pav Rm519; 1150 St. Nicholas Ave.;<lb/> New York, New York 10032 USA</address>; 

	Tel.: <phone>212.851.5560</phone>; 
	Fax: 212.851.5562; 

	Email:<lb/> 
	<email>gl2204@columbia.edu<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received 09/18/06; Accepted 09/18/06<lb/></note>

	Previously published online a an Autophagy E-publication:<lb/>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.landesbioscience.com/journals/autophagy/abstract.php?id=3416<lb/></ptr>

	KEY WORDS<lb/> 
	<keyword>cell death, sphingosine 1-phosphate, sphingosine<lb/> kinase, ceramide, cancer, sphingolipids<lb/></keyword>

	Addendum to:<lb/>

	<reference>Regulation of Autophagy by Sphingosine Kinase 1 and Its<lb/> Role in Cell Survival during Nutrient Starvation<lb/> G. Lavieu, F. Scarlatti, G. Sala, S. Carpentier, T. Levade,<lb/> R. Ghidoni, J. Botti and P. Codogno<lb/>J Biol Chem 2006; 281:8518-27</reference>

	Addenda<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Is Autophagy the Key Mechanism by Which the Sphingolipid Rheostat<lb/> Controls the Cell Fate Decision?</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Sphingolipids are major constituents of biological membrane and some of them<lb/> behave as second messengers involved in the cell fate decision. Ceramide and sphingosine<lb/> 1-phosphate (S1P) constitute a rheostat system in which ceramide promotes cell death and<lb/> S1P increases cell survival. We have shown that both sphingolipids are able to trigger<lb/> autophagy with opposing outcomes on cell survival. Here we discuss and speculate on<lb/> the diverging functions of the autophagic pathways induced by ceramide and S1P,<lb/> respectively.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
