<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="05EBA9BEE848BB25DAE58C4C09CFF03A20A0AB32"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	Vascular: AVM<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The Significance of Retrograde<lb/> Thrombosis Following Removal of<lb/> Arteriovenous Malformations in<lb/> Elderly Patients<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Yoshio Miyasaka, M.D., Akira Kurata, M.D., Ryusui Tanaka, M.D., Katsumi Irikura, M.D.,<lb/> Masaru Yamada, M.D., and Kiyotaka Fujii, M.D.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Kitasato University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sagamihara,<lb/> Kanagawa, Japan<lb/></address>

	<reference>Miyasaka Y, Kurata A, Tanaka R, Irikura K, Yamada M, Fujii K. The<lb/> significance of retrograde thrombosis following removal of arte-<lb/>riovenous malformations in elderly patients. Surg Neurol<lb/> 1998;49:399 -405. </reference>

	<div type="abstract">BACKGROUND<lb/> Retrograde thrombosis of former feeding arteries should<lb/> be considered as a distinct postoperative complication<lb/> following surgery for arteriovenous malformation (AVM).<lb/> Regardless of the presence of AVMs, the cerebral arteries<lb/> undergo atherosclerotic changes with advancing age. In<lb/> the present study, three cases in elderly patients who<lb/> developed retrograde thrombosis are reported, and the<lb/> effect of the patient&apos;s age on this complication is<lb/> discussed.<lb/> CLINICAL MATERIALS AND METHODS<lb/> The present study group consisted of 158 patients who<lb/> underwent AVM resection and postoperative angio-<lb/>graphic studies. Five patients were 65 years of age or<lb/> older (elderly group) at the time of operation, 108 were<lb/> between 20 and 64 years of age (adult group), and 45 were<lb/> less than 20 years of age (young group). The incidence of<lb/> retrograde thrombosis in the elderly group was com-<lb/>pared with that of the other two groups. RESULTS<lb/> We found that surgery in the elderly group was accom-<lb/>panied by a significantly higher incidence of retrograde<lb/> thrombosis (60%) than in the adult group (4%), or the<lb/> young group (0%). CONCLUSIONS<lb/> The present study suggests that this complication should<lb/> be considered as a serious possibility following removal<lb/> of an AVM, especially in elderly patients.</div>

	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by<lb/> Elsevier Science Inc.<lb/> </note>

	KEY WORDS<lb/>
	<keyword>Arteriovenous malformation, elderly patient, surgery, com-<lb/>plication, retrograde thrombosis.<lb/> </keyword>

	Address reprint requests to: 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Yoshio Miyasaka, M.D., </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of<lb/> Neurosurgery, Kitasato University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1-15-1 Kitasato,<lb/> Sagamihara, Kanagawa 228, Japan.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received March 27, 1996; accepted February 5, 1997.<lb/></note> 

	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by Elsevier Science Inc.<lb/></note>

	0090-3019/98/$19.00<lb/> 655 Avenue of the Americas, New York, NY 10010<lb/> 

	<idno>PII S0090-3019(97)00159-6</idno> 


		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
