<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0741-3335_53_8_085003"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<note type="other">Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience<lb/></note> 
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Resistive wall mode stabilization by differential rotation in an analytic
					tokamak<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<note type="other">This article has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the
				full text article.<lb/></note>

			<reference>2011 Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion 53 085003<lb/></reference>

			<ptr type="web">(http://iopscience.iop.org/0741-3335/53/8/085003)<lb/></ptr>

			<note>View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for
				more<lb/></note> 
			<note>Download details:<lb/></note>

			<note type="other">IP Address: 145.64.134.241<lb/></note>

			<note>The article was downloaded on 27/05/2011 at 09:32<lb/> Please note that terms and
				conditions apply.<lb/></note>
		
			<pb/>
			<note type="other">IOP PUBLISHING</note>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<reference>PLASMA PHYSICS AND CONTROLLED FUSION<lb/></reference>
	
			<reference>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion 53 (2011) 085003 (12pp)<lb/></reference>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<idno>doi:10.1088/0741-3335/53/8/085003<lb/></idno>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Resistive wall mode stabilization by differential<lb/> rotation in an
					analytic tokamak<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>C J Ham, C G Gimblett and S E Penington<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>EURATOM/CCFE Fusion Association, Culham Science Centre,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Abingdon, Oxon,<lb/> OX14 3DB, UK<lb/></address>

			<email>E-mail: christopher.ham@ccfe.ac.uk<lb/></email>

			<note type="submission">Received 18 February 2011, in final form 8 April 2011<lb/></note>
				<date>Published 12 May 2011<lb/></date>

			<ptr type="web">Online at stacks.iop.org/PPCF/53/085003<lb/></ptr>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract It is well known that stabilization of the resistive wall
				mode (RWM) may allow<lb/> fusion power to be significantly increased for a given
				magnetic field in advanced<lb/> tokamak operation. The principle of stabilization of
				the RWM by rotation has<lb/> been established both experimentally and theoretically.
				Recent experimental<lb/> results have indicated stabilization of the RWM has been
				achieved with very<lb/> small levels of rotation using balanced neutral beam
				injection. The framework<lb/> of Connor et al (Connor et al 1988 Phys. Fluids 31
				577) is used to develop<lb/> two ideal plasma analytic toroidal models where stepped
				pressure profiles and<lb/> careful ordering of terms are used to simplify the
				analysis. The first model has<lb/> one resonant layer in the plasma and two
				resistive walls and the second has<lb/> two resonant layers and one resistive wall.
				The RWM can be stabilized with<lb/> slow rotation (∼0.5%&#x6ef59; A , where &#x6ef59; A is
				the Alfvénic rotation frequency) of a<lb/> secondary resistive wall. A secordary
				rotating resistive wall can only stabilize<lb/> the plasma if a perfectly conducting
				wall at that location would stabilize the<lb/> plasma. Differential rotation in the
				plasma is investigated by rotating two<lb/> resonant layers in the plasma at
				different rates. It is found in this model that<lb/> differential rotation of the
				outer resonant surface can stabilize the RWM, with no<lb/> rotation required at the
				inner surface. However, stabilization is not possible with<lb/> the outer surface
				static and the inner surface rotating. Experimental rotation<lb/> profiles for
				balanced neutral beam shots have higher levels of rotation near the<lb/> plasma edge
				showing differential rotation between the outer surface and the<lb/> wall may be
				part of the RWM stabilization mechanism.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
