<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0803686a"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			
			<reference>International Journal of Obesity (2008) 32, 144–151 <lb/> </reference>
			<note type="copyright">c 2008 Nature Publishing Group	All rights reserved	0307-0565/08	$30.00<lb/></note>
			<ptr type="web">www.nature.com/ijo<lb/></ptr>
			
			<note type="articleType">ORIGINAL ARTICLE<lb/></note>
	
	<docTitle>
		<titlePart>Body mass index and weight change since 20 years of<lb/> age and risk of coronary heart disease among<lb/> Japanese: the Japan Public Health Center-Based Study<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
		<docAuthor>CL Chei 1 , H Iso 2 , K Yamagishi 1 , M Inoue 3 and S Tsugane 3 , for the JPHC Study Group</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Public Health Medicine, Doctoral Program in Medical Sciences, Graduate School of Comprehensive Human<lb/> Sciences, University of Tsukuba,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tsukuba, Ibaraki-ken, Japan;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Public Health, Department of Social and Environmental<lb/> Medicine, Graduate School of Medicine, Osaka University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Suita, Osaka, Japan and</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Epidemiology and Prevention Division,<lb/> Research Center for Cancer Prevention and Screening, National Cancer Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Chuo-ku, Tokyo, Japan<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Background: Obesity and weight gain are associated with increased risk of coronary heart disease in Western countries.<lb/> However, their impact is not well elucidated in Asia, where body mass index (BMI) levels are generally lower than in Western<lb/> countries. We examined associations of BMI (kg/m 2 ) and weight change with risk of coronary heart disease in Japanese people.<lb/> Methods and results: A total of 43 235 men and 47 444 women aged 40–69 years living in communities were followed up from<lb/> 1990 to 2001 in the Japan Public Health Center-based (JPHC) prospective study . During 879 619 person-years of follow-up, we<lb/> documented 399 cases of coronary heart disease (334 myocardial infarction and 65 sudden cardiac death) for men and 119 (95<lb/> myocardial infarction and 24 sudden cardiac death) for women. Compared with persons with BMI 23.0–24.9, men, but not<lb/> women, with BMI X30.0 had higher risk of coronary heart disease and myocardial infarction; the multivariable relative risks for<lb/> men were 1.8 (1.1–3.0) and 1.9 (1.1–3.2), respectively. When weight change was examined according to BMI at age 20 years,<lb/> men with initial BMI o21.7 who gained more than 10 kg compared with men of no weight change had a twofold higher risk of<lb/> coronary heart disease. Both men and women with initial BMI X21.7 showed no association between weight loss and the risk.<lb/> Conclusions: High BMI was associated with increased risk of coronary heart disease among men. Also, weight gain was<lb/> associated with increased risk among lean men.<lb/> </div>
	
	<reference>International Journal of Obesity (2008) 32, 144–151; </reference>
	<idno>doi:10.1038/sj.ijo.0803686; published online 17 July 2007<lb/></idno>

	<keyword>Keywords: body mass index; weight change; coronary heart disease; follow-up study; Japanese<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="introduction">Introduction<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
