<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0807_5021"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<idno>arXiv:0807.5021v2 [hep-ex]</idno>

	<date>1 Aug 2008<lb/></date>

	August 14, 2019 8:41<lb/> 

	<meeting>WSPC -Proceedings</meeting>

	Trim Size: 9in x 6in schill˙procs 

	<page>1<lb/></page>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Exclusively produced ρ 0 asymmetries on the deuteron and<lb/> future GPD measurements at COMPASS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>C. Schill</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	on behalf of 

	<note type="group">the COMPASS collaboration<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Physikalisches Institut der Albert-Ludwigs-Universität Freiburg,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hermann-Herder Str.3, D-79104 Freiburg, Germany.<lb/></address>

	E-mail:
	<email>Christian.Schill@cern.ch<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Generalized parton distributions (GPDs) provide a new and powerful frame-<lb/>work for a complete description of the nucleon structure. They can provide a<lb/> three-dimensional picture of how the quarks and gluons form a nucleon. GPDs<lb/> can be probed experimentally in hard exclusive meson production or deeply<lb/> virtual Compton scattering (DVCS). The COMPASS experiment at CERN is<lb/> a unique place to study these reactions. At COMPASS, a high energy polarized<lb/> positive or negative muon beam is scattered off a polarized or unpolarized fixed<lb/> target. First results for exclusive ρ 0 meson production are shown. The trans-<lb/>verse target spin asymmetry for exclusively produced ρ 0 on a transversely po-<lb/>larized deuteron target has been measured. Prospects for future measurements<lb/> of DVCS and exclusive meson production at COMPASS will be shown. The<lb/> experiment will use the existing COMPASS spectrometer with a new target, a<lb/> new recoil detector and extended calorimetry. Simulations for different models<lb/> and a test of the recoil detector have been performed.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>nucleon structure, Generalized Parton Distributions, COMPASS,<lb/> recoil detector</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
