<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="084541v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	TITLE<lb/> 
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Power calculator for instrumental variable analysis in pharmacoepidemiology<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	CO-AUTHORS<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Venexia M Walker 1,2 , Neil M Davies 1,2 , Frank Windmeijer 3,2 , Stephen Burgess 4,2 , Richard M Martin 1,2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 School of Social and Community Medicine, University of Bristol,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 MRC University of Bristol Integrative Epidemiology Unit,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Economics, University of Bristol,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Public Health and Primary Care, University of Cambridge,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	FUNDING STATEMENT<lb/>
	<note type="funding"> This work was supported by the Perros Trust and the Integrative Epidemiology Unit. The Integrative<lb/> Epidemiology Unit is supported by the Medical Research Council and the University of Bristol [grant number<lb/> MC_UU_12013/9]. Stephen Burgess is supported by a post-doctoral fellowship from the Wellcome Trust<lb/> [100114].</note>

	2 ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: Instrumental variable analysis, for example with physicians&apos; prescribing preferences as an<lb/> instrument for medications issued in primary care, is an increasingly popular method in the field of<lb/> pharmacoepidemiology. Existing power calculators for studies using instrumental variable analysis, such as<lb/> Mendelian randomisation power calculators, do not allow for the structure of research questions in this<lb/> field. This is because the analysis in pharmacoepidemiology will typically have stronger instruments and<lb/> detect larger causal effects than in other fields. Consequently, there is a need for dedicated power<lb/> calculators for pharmacoepidemiological research.<lb/> Methods and results: The formula for calculating the power of a study using instrumental variable analysis<lb/> in the context of pharmacoepidemiology is derived before being validated by a simulation study. The<lb/> formula is applicable for studies using a single binary instrument to analyse the causal effect of a binary<lb/> exposure on a continuous outcome. A web application is provided for the implementation of the formula<lb/> by others.<lb/> Conclusions: The statistical power of instrumental variable analysis in pharmacoepidemiological studies to<lb/> detect a clinically meaningful treatment effect is an important consideration. Research questions in this<lb/> field have distinct structures that must be accounted for when calculating power.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>pharmacoepidemiology, instrumental variable, power, binary exposure, continuous outcome,<lb/> prescribing preference<lb/></keyword>

	KEY MESSAGES
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
