<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="095430v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Distributed alpha networks underlie individual differences in<lb/> memory performance<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Roy Cox, Anna C Schapiro, Robert Stickgold<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Psychiatry<lb/> Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center and Harvard Medical School<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>330 Brookline Avenue<lb/> Boston, MA 02215, USA<lb/></address>

	corresponding author:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Roy Cox<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	330
	<address>Brookline Avenue<lb/> Boston, MA 02215, USA<lb/></address>

	phone: 617-667-8422<lb/> email:
	<email>roycox.roycox@gmail.com<lb/></email>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>episodic memory, alpha oscillations, networks, EEG, individual differences</keyword>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Episodic memory, our ability to remember specific events, varies considerably across<lb/> individuals. However, little is known about the neural basis of this variability. To address<lb/> this issue, we investigated the role of distributed networks of oscillatory activity, as<lb/> measured through electroencephalography (EEG). We observed that individual<lb/> differences in alpha network structure reliably predict individual memory capacity.<lb/> Specifically, individuals whose network profiles during encoding were most different<lb/> from their resting state networks exhibited greatest subsequent memory performance,<lb/> suggesting that optimal information processing requires substantial shifts in large-scale<lb/> oscillatory organization. Furthermore, these results were not observed in circumscribed<lb/> topographical regions or individual connections, indicating that distributed network<lb/> approaches were more sensitive to functional processes than more conventional<lb/> methods. These findings uncover a physiological correlate of individual differences in<lb/> episodic memory and demonstrate the utility of multivariate EEG techniques to uncover<lb/> brain-behavior correlates.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
