<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0963-0252_20_4_045003"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<note type="other">Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience<lb/></note>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Internal current measurements in high power impulse magnetron
					sputtering<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<note type="other">This article has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the
				full text article.<lb/></note>

			<reference>2011 Plasma Sources Sci. Technol. 20 045003<lb/></reference>

			<ptr type="web">(http://iopscience.iop.org/0963-0252/20/4/045003)<lb/></ptr>
			
			<note type="other">View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for
				more<lb/></note>

			<note type="other">Download details:<lb/></note>

			<note type="other">IP Address: 145.64.134.241<lb/></note>

			<note type="other">The article was downloaded on 27/05/2011 at 09:38<lb/> Please note that terms and
				conditions apply.<lb/></note>
			<pb/>
			<note type="other">IOP PUBLISHING</note> 
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<reference>PLASMA SOURCES SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY<lb/></reference>
			<reference>Plasma Sources Sci. Technol. 20 (2011) 045003 (9pp)</reference>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<idno>doi:10.1088/0963-0252/20/4/045003<lb/></idno>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Internal current measurements in high<lb/> power impulse magnetron
					sputtering<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Daniel Lundin 1 , Seham Al Sahab 1 , Nils Brenning 2 , Chunqing Huo 2
					and<lb/> Ulf Helmersson 1<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 Plasma and Coatings Physics Division, IFM-Materials Physics,
					Linköping University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>SE-581 83<lb/> Linköping, Sweden<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 Division of Space and Plasma Physics, School of Electrical
					Engineering, Royal Institute of Technology,<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>SE-100 44 Stockholm, Sweden<lb/></address>

			<email>E-mail: daniel.lundin@liu.se<lb/></email>

			<note type="submission">Received 30 November 2010, in final form 4 April 2011<lb/></note>
			<date>Published 25 May 2011<lb/></date>

			<ptr type="web">Online at stacks.iop.org/PSST/20/045003<lb/></ptr>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract The transport of charged particles in a high power impulse
				magnetron sputtering (HiPIMS)<lb/> discharge is of considerable interest when
				optimizing this promising deposition technique with<lb/> respect to deposition rate
				and control of the ion acceleration. In this study the internal current<lb/>
				densities J ϕ (azimuthal direction) and J z (axial direction) have therefore been
				spatially and<lb/> temporally resolved in the bulk plasma region above a cylindrical
				magnetron using Rogowski<lb/> coils. From the measurements a phenomenological model
				has been constructed describing the<lb/> evolution of the current density in this
				pulsed plasma. The core of the model is based on three<lb/> different types of
				current systems, which characterize the operating transport mechanisms,<lb/> such as
				current transport along and across magnetic field lines. There is a gradual
				change<lb/> between these current systems during the initiation, build-up and steady
				state of a HiPIMS<lb/> plasma. Furthermore, the data also show that there are
				spatial and temporal variations of the<lb/> key transport parameter J ϕ /J z ,
				governing the cross-B resistivity and also the energy of the<lb/> charged particles.
				The previously reported faster-than-Bohm cross-B electron transport is<lb/> verified
				here, but not for all locations. These results on the plasma dynamics are essential
				input<lb/> when modeling the axial electric field, governing the back-attraction of
				ionized sputtered<lb/> material, and might furthermore provide a link between the
				different resistivities reported in<lb/> HiPIMS, pulsed-DC, and DC magnetron
				discharges.<lb/></div>

			<note type="other">(Some figures in this article are in colour only in the electronic
				version)<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
