<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10.1371_journal.pone.0210387"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Comparison of predicted and measured axial<lb/> length for ophthalmic lens design<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hyeong-Su Kim 1,2 , Dong-Sik YuID 1 *, Hyun Gug Cho 1 , Byeong-Yeon Moon 1 , Sang-<lb/>Yeob KimID 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Optometry, Kangwon National University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Samcheok, Korea,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Optometry<lb/> and Vision Science, Kyungwoon University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gumi, Korea<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>yds@kangwon.ac.kr</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Ocular parameters have been applied to ophthalmic lens designs in order to satisfy individ-<lb/>ual wearers. An axial length (AL) of them can be used in individual ophthalmic lens designs.<lb/> Our aim was to propose a reliable formula that predicts an individual&apos;s AL using the corneal<lb/> radius and refractive error, and to demonstrate the applicability of this formula. A total of 348<lb/> subjects underwent keratometry, objective and subjective refraction, and AL measurement.<lb/> The formula of calculated AL for prediction obtained from the original Gullstrand simplified<lb/> schematic eye: calculated AL = (24.00 × aveK/7.80)-(SE × 0.40), where aveK and SE<lb/> denote average corneal radius and spherical equivalent, respectively. Calculated AL was<lb/> 24.50 ± 1.83 mm, which was 0.18 ± 0.47 mm longer than the measured value of 24.32 ±<lb/> 1.73 mm (p &lt; 0.001). The proportion showing the differences between the calculated and<lb/> measured ALs were 284 eyes (40.8%) for 0.00-0.25 mm, 525 eyes (75.4%) for less than<lb/> 0.50 mm, 665 eyes (95.5%) for less than 1.00 mm, and 31 eyes (4.5%) for more than 1.01<lb/> mm. Correlation coefficient showed a very high correlation between calculated and mea-<lb/>sured ALs (r = 0.967, p &lt; 0.001), and higher in the myopic than in the hyperopic group. The<lb/> mean difference was 0.18 mm; the 95% limit of agreement was +1.10--0.75 mm in all<lb/> groups. Agreement was better in hyperopic eyes than myopic eyes. Prediction from calcula-<lb/>tion of AL with a formula using the corneal radius and SE provides an alternative method to<lb/> direct measurements of AL, especially in the restricted environment, which can&apos;t use biomet-<lb/>ric equipment for personalized ophthalmic lens design.<lb/></div>

	<reference>PLOS ONE | <idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210387</idno> January 7, 2019<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 12<lb/></page> 

	a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Kim H-S, Yu D-S, Cho HG, Moon B-Y,<lb/> Kim S-Y (2019) Comparison of predicted and<lb/> measured axial length for ophthalmic lens design.<lb/> PLoS ONE 14(1): e0210387.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/<lb/> 10.1371/journal.pone.0210387<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Andrew D. Pucker,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Alabama at<lb/> Birmingham,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>UNITED STATES<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: July 3, 2018<lb/> Accepted: December 21, 2018<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>January 7, 2019<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2019 Kim et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/> </note>
	
	Data Availability Statement: 
	<note type="availability">All relevant data are<lb/> within the manuscript and its Supporting<lb/> Information files.<lb/></note>

	Funding: 
	<note type="funding">The authors received no specific funding<lb/> for this work.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests: The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
