<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10.1371_journal.pone.0210122"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Mapping the global potential distributions of<lb/> two arboviral vectors Aedes aegypti and Ae.<lb/> albopictus under changing climate<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mahmoud Kamal ID 1<lb/> *, Mohamed A. Kenawy 1 , Magda Hassan Rady 1 , Amany<lb/> Soliman Khaled 1,2 , Abdallah M. Samy 1 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Entomology Department, Faculty of Science, Ain Shams University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Abbassia, Cairo, Egypt,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Research<lb/> and Training Center on Vectors of Diseases, Faculty of Science, Ain Shams University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Abbassia, Cairo, Egypt<lb/></address>

	*
	<email>mkasu@sci.asu.edu.eg</email>

	,
	<email>mkasu2020@gmail.com</email>

	(MK);
	<email>samy@sci.asu.edu.eg</email>

	(AMS) Abstract
	<div type="abstract">Background<lb/> Aedes aegypti and Ae. albopictus are the primary vectors that transmit several arboviral dis-<lb/>eases, including dengue, chikungunya, and Zika. The world is presently experiencing a<lb/> series of outbreaks of these diseases, so, we still require to better understand the current<lb/> distributions and possible future shifts of their vectors for successful surveillance and control<lb/> programs. Few studies assessed the influences of climate change on the spatial distribu-<lb/>tional patterns and abundance of these important vectors, particularly using the most recent<lb/> climatic scenarios. Here, we updated the current potential distributions of both vectors and<lb/> assessed their distributional changes under future climate conditions. Methods<lb/> We used ecological niche modeling approach to estimate the potential distributions of Ae.<lb/> aegypti and Ae. albopictus under present-day and future climate conditions. This approach<lb/> fits ecological niche model from occurrence records of each species and environmental vari-<lb/>ables. For each species, future projections were based on climatic data from 9 general circu-<lb/>lation models (GCMs) for each representative concentration pathway (RCP) in each time<lb/> period, with a total of 72 combinations in four RCPs in 2050 and 2070. All ENMs were tested<lb/> using the partial receiver operating characteristic (pROC) and a set of 2,048 and 2,003 addi-<lb/>tional independent records for Ae. aegypti and Ae. albopictus, respectively. Finally, we used<lb/> background similarity test to assess the similarity between the ENMs of Ae. aegypti and Ae.<lb/> albopictus. Results<lb/> The predicted potential distribution of Ae. aegypti and Ae. albopictus coincided with the cur-<lb/>rent and historical known distributions of both species. Aedes aegypti showed a markedly<lb/> broader distributional potential across tropical and subtropical regions than Ae. albopictus.<lb/> Interestingly, Ae. albopictus was markedly broader in distributional potential across<lb/></div>

	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210122 December 31, 2018<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 21<lb/></page>

	a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>

	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Kamal M, Kenawy MA, Rady MH, Khaled<lb/> AS, Samy AM (2018) Mapping the global potential<lb/> distributions of two arboviral vectors Aedes aegypti<lb/> and Ae. albopictus under changing climate. PLoS<lb/> ONE 13(12): e0210122.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/<lb/> journal.pone.0210122<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Nagila Francinete Costa Secundino,<lb/></editor>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Instituto de Pesquisas de Rene Rachou,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>BRAZIL<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: September 21, 2018<lb/> Accepted: December 17, 2018<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>December 31, 2018<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2018 Kamal et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement:
	<note type="availability">All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>Information files. GeoTIFF dataset for different <lb/>general circulation models are openly available via <lb/>Figshare repository, https://figshare.com/s/ <lb/>6b18c6ce273a3ecaaddc. <lb/></note>

	Funding:
	<note type="funding">The authors received no specific funding<lb/> for this work.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests: The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.<lb/>

	<div type="abstract">temperate Europe and the United States. All ecological niche models (ENMs) were statisti-<lb/>cally robust (P &lt; 0.001). ENMs successfully anticipated 98% (1,999/2,048) and 99% (1,985/<lb/> 2,003) of additional independent records for both Ae. aegypti and Ae. albopictus, respec-<lb/>tively (P &lt; 0.001). ENMs based on future conditions showed similarity between the overall<lb/> distributional patterns of future-day and present-day conditions; however, there was a north-<lb/>ern range expansion in the continental USA to include parts of Southern Canada in case of<lb/> Ae. albopictus in both 2050 and 2070. Future models also anticipated further expansion of<lb/> Ae. albopictus to the East to include most of Europe in both time periods. Aedes aegypti<lb/> was anticipated to expand to the South in East Australia in 2050 and 2070. The predictions<lb/> showed differences in distributional potential of both species between diverse RCPs in 2050<lb/> and 2070. Finally, the background similarity test comparing the ENMs of Ae. aegypti and<lb/> Ae. albopictus was unable to reject the null hypothesis of niche similarity between both spe-<lb/>cies (P &gt; 0.05). Conclusion<lb/> These updated maps provided details to better guide surveillance and control programs of<lb/> Ae. aegypti and Ae. albopictus. They have also significant public health importance as a<lb/> baseline for predicting the emergence of arboviral diseases transmitted by both vectors in<lb/> new areas across the world.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
