<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin11171109090500491505"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
            <reference>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448<lb/></reference>

            Available online
            <date>1 March 2024<lb/></date>

            <idno>2405-8440</idno>/

            <note type="copyright">© 2024 The Authors.<lb/> Published by Elsevier Ltd.<lb/> This is an open access article under the CC BY license<lb/> (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).<lb/></note>

            <note type="doctype">Research article<lb/></note>

            <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Propionyl-L-carnitine mitigates ischemia-reperfusion injury in rat<lb/> epigastric island flaps<lb/></titlePart>
            </docTitle>

            <byline>
            <docAuthor>Atilla Adnan Eyuboglu a , Ovunc Akdemir b, * , Oytun Erbas c , Mustafa Tonguc Isken d ,<lb/> Feng Zhang e , William C. Lineaweaver f<lb/></docAuthor>
            </byline>

            <byline>
            <affiliation>a Arel University, Department of Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery,</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>Istanbul, Turkey<lb/></address>

            <byline>
            <affiliation>b Aydin University, Department of Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery,</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>Istanbul, Turkey<lb/></address>

            <byline>
            <affiliation>c Bilim University, Department of Physiopathology,</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>Istanbul, Turkey<lb/></address>

            <byline>
            <affiliation>d Bahcesehir Medical University, Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery,</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>Istanbul, Turkey<lb/></address>

            <byline>
            <affiliation>e PhD University of Mississippi Medical Center, Division of Plastic Surgery, Microsurgery,</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>2500 North State Street, Jackson, MS 39216, USA<lb/></address>

            <byline>
            <affiliation>f Vanderbilt Bill Wilkerson Center for Otolaryngology and Communication Sciences, Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery,</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>Nashville, TN, USA<lb/></address>

            A R T I C L E I N F O<lb/> Keywords:<lb/>
            <keyword>Carnitine<lb/> Flap survival<lb/> Inflammation<lb/> Ischemia-reperfusion injury<lb/> Necrosis<lb/> Oxidative stress<lb/></keyword>

            A B S T R A C T<lb/>
            <div type="abstract">Background: Ischemia-reperfusion injury presents a substantial concern in various medical sce-<lb/>narios, notably in reconstructive surgery involving tissue flaps. Despite reports on the protective<lb/> benefits of Propionyl-L-carnitine against ischemia-reperfusion injury, a thorough assessment of its<lb/> efficacy in epigastric island flap models is currently lacking.<lb/> Methods: Sixteen male Sprague-Dawley rats underwent epigastric island flap surgery and were<lb/> divided into two groups: a Propionyl-L-carnitine group that received intraperitoneal Propionyl-L-<lb/>carnitine prior to ischemia induction and a sham group that received saline treatment. A<lb/> comprehensive evaluation was performed including macroscopic, biochemical and histological<lb/> assessments encompassing measurements of flap survival areas, lipid peroxidation (malondial-<lb/>dehyde), glutathione, myeloperoxidase, nitric oxide and peripheral neutrophil counts.<lb/> Results: The Propionyl-L-carnitine group demonstrated significantly increased flap survival areas<lb/> when compared to the sham group. Administration of Propionyl-L-carnitine led to reduced<lb/> malondialdehyde levels and elevated glutathione levels indicating a reduction in oxidative stress.<lb/> Furthermore, the Propionyl-L-carnitine group exhibited lower myeloperoxidase levels, higher<lb/> nitric oxide levels and reduced peripheral neutrophil counts, suggesting a decrease in the in-<lb/>flammatory response. Histopathological analysis revealed decreased levels of inflammation, ne-<lb/>crosis, polymorphonuclear leukocyte infiltration and edema in the Propionyl-L-carnitine group.<lb/> Additionally, vascularity was enhanced in the Propionyl-L-carnitine group.<lb/> Conclusion: This study provides compelling evidence that Propionyl-L-carnitine administration<lb/> effectively mitigates the deleterious effects of ischemia-reperfusion injury in epigastric island<lb/> flaps. This is substantiated by the improved flap survival, diminished oxidative stress and<lb/> inflammation, as well as the enhanced vascularity observed. Propionyl-L-carnitine emerges as a<lb/> promising therapeutic intervention to enhance tissue flap survival in reconstructive surgery,<lb/> warranting further exploration through larger-scale investigations.<lb/></div>

            * Corresponding author.
            <byline>
                <affiliation>Aydin University, Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery,<lb/></affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>Istanbul, Turkey.</address>

            E-mail addresses:
            <email>atillaeyuboglu@yahoo.com</email>

            (A.A. Eyuboglu),
            <email>ovuncakdemir@gmail.com</email>

            (O. Akdemir),
            <email>oytunerbas2012@gmail.com<lb/></email>

            (O. Erbas),
            <email>tongucisken@yahoo.com</email>

            (M.T. Isken),
            <email>feng.zhang@jmsburncenters.com</email>

            (F. Zhang),
            <email>william.c.lineaweaver@vumc.org<lb/></email>

            (W.C. Lineaweaver).<lb/> Contents lists available at ScienceDirect Heliyon<lb/> journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon<lb/>

            <idno>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e27448<lb/></idno>

            <note type="submission">Received 8 November 2023; Received in revised form 30 January 2024; Accepted 28 February 2024</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
