<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10.1186_s13064-019-0127-z"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E<lb/></note>

	<note type="doctype">Open Access<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>TrkB expression and dependence divides<lb/> gustatory neurons into three subpopulations<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jennifer Rios-Pilier and Robin F. Krimm *</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: During development, gustatory (taste) neurons likely undergo numerous changes in morphology and<lb/> expression prior to differentiation into maturity, but little is known this process or the factors that regulate it. Neuron<lb/> differentiation is likely regulated by a combination of transcription and growth factors. Embryonically, most geniculate<lb/> neuron development is regulated by the growth factor brain derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF). Postnatally, however,<lb/> BDNF expression becomes restricted to subpopulations of taste receptor cells with specific functions. We hypothesized<lb/> that during development, the receptor for BDNF, tropomyosin kinase B receptor (TrkB), may also become developmentally<lb/> restricted to a subset of taste neurons and could be one factor that is differentially expressed across taste neuron subsets.<lb/> Methods: We used transgenic mouse models to label both geniculate neurons innervating the oral cavity (Phox2b+),<lb/> which are primarily taste, from those projecting to the outer ear (auricular neurons) to label TrkB expressing neurons<lb/> (TrkB GFP ). We also compared neuron number, taste bud number, and taste receptor cell types in wild-type animals and<lb/> conditional TrkB knockouts.<lb/> Results: Between E15.5-E17.5, TrkB receptor expression becomes restricted to half of the Phox2b + neurons. This TrkB<lb/> downregulation was specific to oral cavity projecting neurons, since TrkB expression remained constant throughout<lb/> development in the auricular geniculate neurons (Phox2b-). Conditional TrkB removal from oral sensory neurons (Phox2b+)<lb/> reduced this population to 92% of control levels, indicating that only 8% of these neurons do not depend on TrkB for<lb/> survival during development. The remaining neurons failed to innervate any remaining taste buds, 14% of which remained<lb/> despite the complete loss of innervation. Finally, some types of taste receptor cells (Car4+) were more dependent on<lb/> innervation than others (PLCβ2+).<lb/> Conclusions: Together, these findings indicate that TrkB expression and dependence divides gustatory neurons into three<lb/> subpopulations: 1) neurons that always express TrkB and are TrkB-dependent during development (50%), 2) neurons<lb/> dependent on TrkB during development but that downregulate TrkB expression between E15.5 and E17.5 (41%), and 3)<lb/> neurons that never express or depend on TrkB (9%). These TrkB-independent neurons are likely non-gustatory, as they do<lb/> not innervate taste buds.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>BDNF, TrkB, Neurotrophin, Taste, Geniculate ganglion, Taste buds, Innervation, Neuron development, Gustatory<lb/></keyword>

	* Correspondence:
	<email>rfkrim01@louisville.edu<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Anatomical Sciences and Neurobiology, University of<lb/> Louisville School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>511 S. Floyd St., MDR Building Room 111,<lb/> Louisville, KY 40202, USA<lb/></address>

	<note type="copyright">© The Author(s). 2019 Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0<lb/> International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to<lb/> the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver<lb/> (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development<lb/> (2019) 14:3<lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13064-019-0127-z<lb/></reference>

	<note type="submission">Received: 17 October 2018 Accepted: 7 January 2019<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
