<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10.1038_s41597-022-01497-x"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page>

	<reference>Scientific Data |<lb/> (2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x<lb/> 
	www.nature.com/scientificdata<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Datasets of fingertip forces while<lb/> grasping a handle with unsteady<lb/> thumb platform<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Banuvathy Rajakumar &amp; Varadhan SKM ✉<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">This article presents the fingertip forces and moments data of the individual fingers and thumb when<lb/> the thumb was placed on an unsteady platform, when the mass of the handle was systematically<lb/> increased and when the thumb normal force was restricted while grasping a handle. Further, this<lb/> article also includes a dataset while the thumb makes vertical movements such as extension (or<lb/> upward motion) and flexion movement (or downward motion) during the static holding of a handle.<lb/> An instrumented five-finger prehension handle was designed with a vertical railing on the thumb<lb/> side. A slider platform was placed over the railing to mount the thumb force sensor. Further, a<lb/> laser displacement sensor was mounted on top of the handle towards the thumb side to record the<lb/> displacement of the thumb platform. The dataset includes fingertip forces, orientation of the handle,<lb/> and the displacement data of thumb platform. This data helps therapists assess the degree of thumb<lb/> disability, the contribution of ulnar fingers in establishing static equilibrium of a handheld object.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Applied Mechanics, indian institute of technology Madras,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>chennai, india.</address>

	✉ e-mail:
	<email>skm@iitm.ac.in<lb/></email>

	<note type="doctype">DATA DeScRipToR</note>
	<note type="doctype">opeN<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Received: 7 March 2022; Accepted: 28 June 2022;<lb/></note>

	Published: xx xx xxxx<lb/>
	Additional information<lb/>

	Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to V.S.<lb/>
	Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints.<lb/> Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and<lb/> institutional affiliations.<lb/>

	<note type="copyright">Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International<lb/> License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or<lb/> format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this<lb/> article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the<lb/> material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the<lb/> copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.<lb/> © The Author(s) 2022</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
