<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10.1186_s13287-018-0774-8"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">R E S E A R C H<lb/></note>

	<note type="doctype">Open Access<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Mesenchymal stem cell-derived<lb/> extracellular vesicles attenuate influenza<lb/> virus-induced acute lung injury in a pig model<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mahesh Khatri 1* , Levi Arthur Richardson 1 and Tea Meulia 2</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: Mesenchymal stem (stromal) cells (MSCs) mediate their immunoregulatory and tissue repair functions<lb/> by secreting paracrine factors, including extracellular vesicles (EVs). In several animal models of human diseases,<lb/> MSC-EVs mimic the beneficial effects of MSCs. Influenza viruses cause annual outbreaks of acute respiratory illness<lb/> resulting in significant mortality and morbidity. Influenza viruses constantly evolve, thus generating drug-resistant<lb/> strains and rendering current vaccines less effective against the newly generated strains. Therefore, new therapies<lb/> that can control virus replication and the inflammatory response of the host are needed. The objective of this study<lb/> was to examine if MSC-EV treatment can attenuate influenza virus-induced acute lung injury in a preclinical model.<lb/> Methods: We isolated EVs from swine bone marrow-derived MSCs. Morphology of MSC-EVs was determined by<lb/> electron microscopy and expression of mesenchymal markers was examined by flow cytometry. Next, we examined<lb/> the anti-influenza activity of MSC-EVs in vitro in lung epithelial cells and anti-viral and immunomodulatory<lb/> properties in vivo in a pig model of influenza virus.<lb/> Results: MSC-EVs were isolated from MSC-conditioned medium by ultracentrifugation. MSC-EVs were round-shaped<lb/> and, similarly to MSCs, expressed mesenchymal markers and lacked the expression of swine leukocyte antigens I and II.<lb/> Incubation of PKH-26-labeled EVs with lung epithelial cells revealed that MSC-EVs incorporated into the epithelial cells.<lb/> Next, we examined the anti-influenza and anti-inflammatory properties of MSC-EVs. MSC-EVs inhibited the<lb/> hemagglutination activity of avian, swine, and human influenza viruses at concentrations of 1.25-5 μg/ml.<lb/> MSC-EVs inhibited influenza virus replication and virus-induced apoptosis in lung epithelial cells. The anti-<lb/>influenza activity of MSC-EVs was due to transfer of RNAs from EVs to epithelial cells since pre-incubation of<lb/> MSC-EVs with RNase enzyme abrogated the anti-influenza activity of MSC-EVs. In a pig model of influenza virus,<lb/> intratracheal administration of MSC-EVs 12 h after influenza virus infection significantly reduced virus shedding in the<lb/> nasal swabs, influenza virus replication in the lungs, and virus-induced production of proinflammatory cytokines in the<lb/> lungs of influenza-infected pigs. The histopathological findings revealed that MSC-EVs alleviated influenza virus-induced<lb/> lung lesions in pigs.<lb/></div>

	(Continued on next page)<lb/> * Correspondence:
	<email>khatri.14@osu.edu</email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Food Animal Health Research Program, Ohio Agricultural Research and<lb/> Development Center, The Ohio State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1680 Madison Avenue,<lb/> Wooster, OH 44691, USA<lb/></address>

	Full list of author information is available at the end of the article<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">© The Author(s). 2018 Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0<lb/> International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to<lb/> the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver<lb/> (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17<lb/> DOI 10.1186/s13287-018-0774-8<lb/></reference>

	(Continued from previous page)<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Conclusions: Our data demonstrated in a relevant preclinical large animal model of influenza virus that MSC-EVs<lb/> possessed anti-influenza and anti-inflammatory properties and that EVs may be used as cell-free therapy for influenza<lb/> in humans.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>Mesenchymal stem cells, Extracellular vesicles, Influenza, Acute lung injury, Stem cell therapy, Large animal model<lb/></keyword>

	Publisher&apos;s Note<lb/> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published<lb/> maps and institutional affiliations.<lb/>

	Author details
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Food Animal Health Research Program, Ohio Agricultural Research and<lb/> Development Center, The Ohio State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1680 Madison Avenue,<lb/> Wooster, OH 44691, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Molecular and Cellular Imaging Center, Ohio<lb/> Agricultural Research and Development Center, The Ohio State University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wooster, OH, USA.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: 27 July 2017 Revised: 19 December 2017<lb/> Accepted: 15 January 2018</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
