<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin8094746469636947761"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
            <reference>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580<lb/></reference>

            Available online
            <date>4 March 2024<lb/></date>

            <idno>2405-8440</idno>/

            <note type="copyright">© 2024 The Authors.<lb/> Published by Elsevier Ltd.<lb/> This is an open access article under the CC BY license<lb/> (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).<lb/></note>

            <note type="doctype">Research article<lb/></note>

            <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Preparation and performance of alumina/epoxy-siloxane<lb/> composites: A comparative study on thermal-and<lb/> photo-curing process<lb/></titlePart>
            </docTitle>

            <byline>
            <docAuthor>Chan Soo Kim a,b,1 , Junho Jang a, 1 , Hyeon-Gyun Im a , Seogyoung Yoon b,** , Dong<lb/> Jun Kang a, *<lb/></docAuthor>
            </byline>

            <byline>
            <affiliation>a Insulation Materials Research Center, Electrical Materials Research Division, Korea Electrotechnology Research Institute (KERI),</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>Changwon-si,<lb/> 51543, Republic of Korea<lb/></address>

            <byline>
            <affiliation>b School of Materials Science and Engineering, Pusan National University,</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>Busan, 46241, Republic of Korea<lb/></address>

            A R T I C L E I N F O<lb/>

            Keywords:<lb/>
            <keyword>Epoxy-siloxane composites<lb/> Alumina particle<lb/> Thermal conductivity<lb/> Electronic packaging<lb/></keyword>

            A B S T R A C T<lb/>
            <div type="abstract">Although epoxy-based composites that consist of inorganic fillers and matrixes are widely used in<lb/> &quot;conventional&quot; electronic packaging applications due to their excellent insulation and robust<lb/> properties, they limit their uses in &quot;advanced electronic packaging&quot; which requires enhanced<lb/> thermal conductivity. However, conventional thermal curing methods for fabrication of epoxy-<lb/>based composites do not fulfill sufficient thermal conductivity. Herein, we apply photo-induced<lb/> curing strategy for fabricating alumina-incorporated epoxy-siloxane composites that consist of<lb/> sol-gel derived siloxane matrix and bimodal sized alumina particles as a thermally conductive<lb/> filler. We investigate how curing mechanism (thermal-or UV-curing) and varying the ratios of the<lb/> alumina particles of two different sizes affect the various physical properties. It is found that<lb/> photo-curing process makes greatly enhanced thermal conductivity, low thermal expansion, and<lb/> high mechanical robustness compared to thermally-cured composites. As the results, we can<lb/> achieve significantly enhanced thermal conductivity (&gt;11 W/m K) with high thermal stability<lb/> and mechanical robustness.<lb/></div>

            * Corresponding author.<lb/> ** Corresponding author.<lb/> E-mail addresses:
            <email>syy3@pusan.ac.kr</email>

            (S. Yoon),
            <email>kangdj@keri.re.kr</email>

            (D.J. Kang).<lb/>
            1 These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/> Contents lists available at ScienceDirect Heliyon<lb/> journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon<lb/>

            <idno>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e27580<lb/></idno>

            <note type="submission">Received 25 February 2024; Accepted 1 March 2024</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
