<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10.1038_s41597-022-01570-5"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page>
	<reference>Scientific Data |<lb/> (2022) 9:448 |</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5<lb/></idno>

	<ptr type="web">www.nature.com/scientificdata<lb/></ptr>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>a high spatial resolution land<lb/> surface phenology dataset for<lb/> ameriFlux and NEON sites<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Minkyu Moon 1 ✉ , andrew D. Richardson 2,3 , thomas Milliman 4 &amp; Mark a. Friedl 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Vegetation phenology is a key control on water, energy, and carbon fluxes in terrestrial ecosystems.<lb/> Because vegetation canopies are heterogeneous, spatially explicit information related to seasonality in<lb/> vegetation activity provides valuable information for studies that use eddy covariance measurements<lb/> to study ecosystem function and land-atmosphere interactions. Here we present a land surface<lb/> phenology (LSP) dataset derived at 3 m spatial resolution from PlanetScope imagery across a range of<lb/> plant functional types and climates in North america. the dataset provides spatially explicit information<lb/> related to the timing of phenophase changes such as the start, peak, and end of vegetation activity,<lb/> along with vegetation index metrics and associated quality assurance flags for the growing seasons of<lb/> 2017-2021 for 10 × 10 km windows centred over 104 eddy covariance towers at AmeriFlux and National<lb/> Ecological Observatory Network (NEON) sites. these LSP data can be used to analyse processes<lb/> controlling the seasonality of ecosystem-scale carbon, water, and energy fluxes, to evaluate predictions<lb/> from land surface models, and to assess satellite-based LSP products.</div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of earth and environment, Boston University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 School of informatics, computing &amp; cyber<lb/> Systems, Northern Arizona University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Flagstaff, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 center for ecosystem Science and Society, northern Arizona<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Flagstaff, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 earth Systems Research center, University of new Hampshire,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Durham, USA.</address>

	✉ e-mail:<lb/>
	<email>moon.minkyu@gmail.com<lb/></email>

	<note type="doctype">Data DEScRiPtOR</note>

	<note type="doctype">OPEN<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Received: 17 March 2022; Accepted: 19 July 2022;<lb/></note>

	Published: xx xx xxxx<lb/> additional information<lb/>

			<!-- is this the availability? -->
	Supplementary information The online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi.<lb/> org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5.<lb/>

	Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to M.M.<lb/>

	<note type="copyright">Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints.<lb/> Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and<lb/> institutional affiliations.<lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International<lb/> License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or<lb/> format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this<lb/> article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the<lb/> material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the<lb/> copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.<lb/> © The Author(s) 2022</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
