<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10.1038_s41746-018-0018-4"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">BRIEF COMMUNICATION OPEN<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Digital biomarkers of cognitive function<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Paul Dagum 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">To identify digital biomarkers associated with cognitive function, we analyzed human-computer interaction from 7 days of<lb/> smartphone use in 27 subjects (ages 18-34) who received a gold standard neuropsychological assessment. For several<lb/> neuropsychological constructs (working memory, memory, executive function, language, and intelligence), we found a family of<lb/> digital biomarkers that predicted test scores with high correlations (p &lt; 10 −4 ). These preliminary results suggest that passive<lb/> measures from smartphone use could be a continuous ecological surrogate for laboratory-based neuropsychological assessment.<lb/></div>

	<reference>npj Digital Medicine (2018) 1:10 ;</reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1038/s41746-018-0018-4<lb/></idno>

	<note type="submission">Received: 5 October 2017 Revised: 3 February 2018 Accepted: 7 February 2018</note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Mindstrong Health,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>248 Homer Street, Palo Alto, CA 94301, USA<lb/></address>

	Correspondence:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Paul Dagum</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(
	<email>paul@mindstronghealth.com</email>

	)<lb/> www.nature.com/npjdigitalmed<lb/> Published in partnership with the Scripps Translational Science Institute<lb/>

	<note type="copyright">Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons<lb/> Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing,<lb/> adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give<lb/> appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative<lb/> Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party<lb/> material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless<lb/> indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the<lb/> article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory<lb/> regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly<lb/> from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.<lb/> org/licenses/by/4.0/.<lb/> © The Author(s) 2018<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Digital biomarkers of cognitive function<lb/> P Dagum</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
