<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">The Cerebellum Is Sensitive to the Lexical Properties of Words During Spoken Language Comprehension</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hannah</forename>
          <surname>Mechtenberg</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Christopher C.</forename>
          <surname>Heffner</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Emily B.</forename>
          <surname>Myers</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sara</forename>
          <surname>Guediche</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T16:31:11.037745Z">12.11.2025 16:31:11</date>
        <title>grobid.training.header [default]</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.1162$1$nol_a_00126</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1162/nol_a_00126</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Hannah Mechtenberg, Christopher C. Heffner, Emily B. Myers, Sara Guediche. (2024). The Cerebellum Is Sensitive to the Lexical Properties of Words During Spoken Language Comprehension. Neurobiology of Language, 5(3), 757-773. DOI: 10.1162/nol_a_00126</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T16:31:11.037745Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T16:31:11.037745Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-11-12T16:32:57.783Z" status="draft" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
    <note type="doctype">SPECIAL ISSUE</note>
          
      :<lb/> 
          
    <title level="j">The Role of the Cerebellum in Language Comprehension and Production<lb/></title>
	
    <docTitle>
	<titlePart>The Cerebellum Is Sensitive to the Lexical<lb/> Properties of Words During Spoken<lb/> Language Comprehension<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hannah Mechtenberg 1 , Christopher C. Heffner 2 , Emily B. Myers 1,3 , and Sara Guediche 4<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Psychological Sciences, University of Connecticut,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Storrs, CT, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Communicative Sciences and Disorders, University at Buffalo,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Buffalo, NY, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Speech, Language and Hearing Sciences, University of Connecticut,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Storrs, CT, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 College of Science and Mathematics, Augusta University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Augusta, GA, USA<lb/></address>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>cerebellum, continuous listening, fMRI, lexical processing, prediction, speech perception</keyword>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Over the past few decades, research into the function of the cerebellum has expanded far<lb/> beyond the motor domain. A growing number of studies are probing the role of specific<lb/> cerebellar subregions, such as Crus I and Crus II, in higher-order cognitive functions including<lb/> receptive language processing. In the current fMRI study, we show evidence for the<lb/> cerebellum&apos;s sensitivity to variation in two well-studied psycholinguistic properties of<lb/> words-lexical frequency and phonological neighborhood density-during passive,<lb/> continuous listening of a podcast. To determine whether, and how, activity in the cerebellum<lb/> correlates with these lexical properties, we modeled each word separately using an<lb/> amplitude-modulated regressor, time-locked to the onset of each word. At the group level,<lb/> significant effects of both lexical properties landed in expected cerebellar subregions: Crus I<lb/> and Crus II. The BOLD signal correlated with variation in each lexical property, consistent<lb/> with both language-specific and domain-general mechanisms. Activation patterns at the<lb/> individual level also showed that effects of phonological neighborhood and lexical frequency<lb/> landed in Crus I and Crus II as the most probable sites, though there was activation seen in<lb/> other lobules (especially for frequency). Although the exact cerebellar mechanisms used<lb/> during speech and language processing are not yet evident, these findings highlight the<lb/> cerebellum&apos;s role in word-level processing during continuous listening.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">a n o p e n a c c e s s<lb/> j o u r n a l<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Mechtenberg, H., Heffner,<lb/> C. C., Myers, E. B., &amp; Guediche, S.<lb/> (2024). The cerebellum is sensitive to<lb/> the lexical properties of words during<lb/> spoken language comprehension.<lb/> Neurobiology of Language, 5(3),<lb/> 757-773.</reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1162<lb/> /nol_a_00126<lb/></idno>


	<idno>DOI:<lb/> https://doi.org/10.1162/nol_a_00126<lb/></idno>

	<note type="submission">Received: 1 February 2023<lb/> Accepted: 30 October 2023<lb/></note>

	Competing Interests:
	<note type="conflict">The authors have<lb/> declared that no competing interests<lb/> exist.<lb/></note>

	Corresponding Author:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hannah Mechtenberg<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<email>hannah.mechtenberg@uconn.edu<lb/></email>

	Handling Editor:<lb/>
	<editor>Julie Fiez<lb/></editor>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2024<lb/> Massachusetts Institute of Technology<lb/> Published under a Creative Commons<lb/> Attribution 4.0 International<lb/> (CC BY 4.0) license<lb/> The MIT Press<lb/></note>

	Downloaded from
	<ptr type="web">http://direct.mit.edu/nol/article-pdf/5/3/757/2465633/nol_a_00126.pdf</ptr>

	by guest on
	<date>10 September 2025</date>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>