<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10.1038_s41597-022-01566-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page>

	<reference>Scientific Data |<lb/> (2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1<lb/> www.nature.com/scientificdata<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Mapping hydrologic alteration and<lb/> ecological consequences in stream<lb/> reaches of the conterminous United States<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ryan a. McManamay 1 ✉ , Rob George 2 , Ryan R. Morrison 3 &amp; Benjamin L. Ruddell 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Environmental flows are critical for balancing societal water needs with that of riverine ecosystems;<lb/> however, data limitations often hinder the development of predictive relationships between<lb/> anthropogenic modifications to streamflow regimes and ecological responses -these relationships<lb/> are the basis for setting regional water policy standards for rivers. Herein, we present and describe a<lb/> comprehensive dataset of modeled hydrologic alteration and consequences for native fish biodiversity,<lb/> both mapped at the stream-reach resolution for the conterminous U.S. Using empirical observations<lb/> of reference conditions and anthropogenically altered streamflow at over 7000 stream gauges, we<lb/> developed a predictive model of hydrologic alteration, which was extended to &gt;2.6 million stream<lb/> reaches. We then used a previous nationwide assessment of ecological responses to hydrologic<lb/> alteration to predict fish biodiversity loss in stream reaches resulting from streamflow modification.<lb/> Validation efforts suggested hydrologic alteration models had satisfactory performance, whereas<lb/> modeled ecological responses were susceptible to compounded errors. The dataset could ameliorate<lb/> regional data deficits for setting environmental flow standards while providing tools for prioritizing<lb/> streamflow protection or restoration.</div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of Environmental Science, Baylor University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Waco, TX, 76798, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 School of informatics, computing<lb/> and Cyber Systems, Northern Arizona University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Flagstaff, AZ, 86011, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of civil and environmental<lb/> Engineering, Colorado State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Fort Collins, CO, 80523, USA.</address>

	✉ e-mail:
	<email>Ryan_McManamay@baylor.edu<lb/></email>

	<note type="docType">Data DeScRiptoR</note>

	<note type="docType">opeN<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Received: 8 February 2022; Accepted: 13 July 2022;<lb/></note>

	Published: xx xx xxxx<lb/> additional information<lb/> 

	Supplementary information The online version contains supplementary material available at 

	<idno>https://doi.<lb/> org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1.<lb/></idno>

	Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to R.A.M.<lb/>
	Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints.<lb/> Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and<lb/> institutional affiliations.<lb/>

	<note type="copyright">Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International<lb/> License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or<lb/> format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this<lb/> article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the<lb/> material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the<lb/> copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.<lb/> © The Author(s) 2022</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
