<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10.1371_journal.pone.0210059"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Topical essential fatty acid oil on wounds:<lb/> Local and systemic effects<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Bruno Grosselli LaniaID 1☯ *, Joseane Morari 2☯ , Amanda Roberta de Almeida 1☯ , Marilene<lb/> Neves da Silva 1 ‡ , Gislaine Vieira-Damiani 1 ‡ , Karina de Almeida Lins 1 ‡ , Carlos<lb/> Lenz Ce ´sar 3 ‡ , Lı ´cio Augusto Velloso 2,4 ‡ , Nilson Borlina Maia 5 ‡ , Maria Letı ´cia Cintra 6☯ ,<lb/> Paulo Eduardo Neves Ferreira Velho 1,4☯<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Laboratory of Applied Research in Dermatology and Bartonella Infection, School of Medical Sciences,<lb/> University of Campinas,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Campinas, Sao Paulo, Brazil,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Cell Signaling Laboratory and Obesity and<lb/> Comorbidities Research Center, School of Medical Sciences, University of Campinas,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Campinas, Sao Paulo,<lb/> Brazil,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 National Institute of Photonics Applied to Cell Biology (INFABIC), Gleb Wataghin Institute of Physics,<lb/> University of Campinas,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Campinas, Sao Paulo, Brazil,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Clinical Medicine Department, School of Medical<lb/> Sciences, University of Campinas,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Campinas, Sao Paulo, Brazil,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Aromatic Plants Division, Agronomic<lb/> Institute of Campinas,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Campinas, Sao Paulo, Brazil,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 Pathological Anatomy Department, School of Medical<lb/> Sciences, University of Campinas,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Campinas, Sao Paulo, Brazil<lb/></address>

	☯ These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/> ‡ These authors also contributed equally to this work.<lb/> 

	*
	<email>bruglania@gmail.com</email>

	Abstract
	<div type="abstract">Background<lb/> The use of medicinal plants and their derivatives is increasing, and approximately one-third<lb/> of all traditional herbal medicines are intended for wound treatment. Natural products used<lb/> in these treatments include vegetable oils, which are rich in essential fatty acids. Once in<lb/> contact with an ulcerative surface, the oil reaches the blood and lymphatic vessels, thus elic-<lb/>iting systemic effects. Objective<lb/> This study evaluated the local and possible systemic effects of essential fatty acids (sun-<lb/>flower oil) applied topically to rat wounds. Methods<lb/> Cutaneous punch wounds (6 mm) were produced on the dorsa of 30 rats. Saline (SS), min-<lb/>eral oil (MO) or essential fatty acid (EFA) solutions were applied topically. Healing was eval-<lb/>uated after 2, 4 and 10 days (n = 5 per group) by visual and histological/morphometric<lb/> examination, second harmonic generation (SHG) microscopy, and cytokine and growth fac-<lb/>tor quantification in the scar tissue (real-time PCR) and in serum (ELISA). Results<lb/> MO/EFA-treated animals had higher IGF-1, leptin, IL-6 and IFN-γ mRNA expression and<lb/> lower serum IL-6 levels than the control (SS/MO) animals. SHG analysis showed no differ-<lb/>ence in collagen density between the animals treated with MO and EFA.<lb/></div>

	<reference>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210059 January 4, 2019<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 / 15<lb/></page> 

	a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111<lb/> a1111111111 a1111111111<lb/>
	
	<note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

	Citation:
	<reference>Lania BG, Morari J, Almeida ARd, Silva<lb/> MNd, Vieira-Damiani G, Lins KdA, et al. (2019)<lb/> Topical essential fatty acid oil on wounds: Local<lb/> and systemic effects. PLoS ONE 14(1): e0210059.<lb/></reference>

	<idno>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210059<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>David M. Burmeister,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>US Army Institute of<lb/> Surgical Research,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>UNITED STATES<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: December 20, 2017<lb/> Accepted: December 17, 2018<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>January 4, 2019<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">© 2019 Lania et al. This is an open<lb/> access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License, which<lb/> permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original<lb/> author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Data Availability Statement: 
	<note type="availability">Data are available<lb/> from Figshare at https://figshare.com/s/<lb/> 6c396e16f3991d7eaa00 and under the DOI: 10.<lb/> 6084/m9.figshare.5917225.<lb/></note>

	Funding: 
	<note type="funding">This work was supported by grant # 07/<lb/> 59319-5 Sao Paulo Research Foundation -Fapesp<lb/> -http://www.fapesp.br/en/ -NBM; grant # 015/<lb/> 2014-Fundo de Apoio à Dermatologia do Estado<lb/> de São Paulo &quot;Sebastião Sampaio&quot; -Funadersp -<lb/>http://www.sbd-sp.org.br/funadersp.php -PENFV;<lb/> grant # 043/2016 -Fundo de Apoio à Dermatologia<lb/> do Estado de São Paulo &quot;Sebastião Sampaio&quot; -Conclusion<lb/> EFA treatment induces topical (observed by local IGF-1, leptin, IL-6 and IFN-γ production)<lb/> and systemic effects, lowering IL-6 levels in the serum. As the oil is widely used to shorten<lb/> ulcer healing time, studies are needed to evaluate the treatment safety and possible unde-<lb/>sired effects.<lb/> Funadersp -http://www.sbd-sp.org.br/funadersp.<lb/> php -PENFV; grant # 01P-04520-2013 -<lb/>Coordenac ¸ão de Aperfeic ¸oamento de Pessoal de<lb/> Nı ´vel Superior -Capes -http://www.capes.gov.br/ -<lb/>BGL; Fundo de Apoio ao Ensino, à Pesquisa e<lb/> Extensão, Universidade Estadual de Campinas<lb/> (0044/17). The funders had no role in study<lb/> design, data collection and analysis, decision to<lb/> publish, or preparation of the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing interests: The authors have declared<lb/> that no competing interests exist.
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
