<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin10514392054570657484"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
            <!-- how should I annotate this? I would capture the docType, more useful-->
            ESI
            <docType>Preprints<lb/></docType>

            <docType>Not Peer-reviewed<lb/></docType>

            <!-- how should I annotate this? no annotation... -->
            www.esipreprints.org

            <page>199<lb/></page>

            <docTitle>
            <titlePart>The Determinants of Success in the Implementation of<lb/> Information Technology in Moroccan Companies:<lb/> Exploratory Case Study<lb/></titlePart>
            </docTitle>

            <byline>
            <docAuthor>Mohamed Alami<lb/></docAuthor>
            </byline>

            <byline>
            <affiliation>Faculty of Legal, Economic and Social Sciences,<lb/> Sidi Mohamed Ben Abdellah University,</affiliation>
            </byline>

            <address>Fes, Morocco<lb/></address>

            <idno>Doi: 10.19044/esipreprint.3.2024.p199<lb/></idno>

            <note type="submission">Approved: 06 March 2024<lb/>
            Posted: 07 March 2024<lb/></note>

            <note type="copyright">Copyright 2024 Author(s)<lb/> Under Creative Commons CC-BY 4.0<lb/></note>

            <note type="doctype">OPEN ACCESS<lb/></note>

            Cite As:<lb/>
            <reference>Alami M. (2024). The Determinants of Success in the Implementation of Information<lb/> Technology in Moroccan Companies: Exploratory Case Study. ESI Preprints.<lb/></reference>

            <idno>https://doi.org/10.19044/esipreprint.3.2024.p199<lb/></idno>

            Abstract<lb/>
            <div type="abstract">The study, which is being conducted in the context of the widespread<lb/> use of information technology in Moroccan companies, focuses on<lb/> examining the success factors of IT implementation. This is a crucial step in<lb/> maximizing the value of information technology investments. The goal is to<lb/> address concerns regarding the delay in digital transformation and the role of<lb/> information technology in establishing a sustainable and irreplaceable<lb/> competitive advantage. The research methodology utilizes a qualitative<lb/> approach, specifically a single case study with semi-structured interviews for<lb/> data collection. The theoretical framework incorporates the resource-based<lb/> view (RBV) and contingency theories. The key findings of the study<lb/> emphasize the challenges encountered during information technology<lb/> implementation, especially concerning the complementarity of<lb/> organizational and human resources with information technology resources.<lb/> Based on these challenges, the factors contributing to successful information<lb/> technology implementation are categorized into three groups: pre-<lb/>implementation phase, alignment of information technology strategy, and<lb/> collaboration and coordination among all stakeholders involved in the<lb/> implementation process.<lb/></div>

            <!-- Same as above, how should I annotate this? no annotation... -->
            ESI Preprints<lb/> March 2024<lb/> www.esipreprints.org

            <page>200<lb/></page>

            Keywords:<lb/>
            <keyword>Implementation<lb/> process;<lb/> information<lb/> technology;<lb/> complementarity of resources; IT strategy; cooperation and coordination</keyword>

        </front>
	</text>
</tei>
