<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-11-13T12:01:53.299595Z">13.11.2025 12:01:53</date>
          <title>grobid.training.header [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.5187_jast.2024.e50</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher/>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication"/>
        <idno type="DOI"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: None</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-13T12:01:53.299595Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-13T12:01:53.299595Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<title level="j">JAST (Journal of Animal Science and Technology)</title>
			
	TITLE PAGE<lb/>
	Upload this completed form to website with submission<lb/> ARTICLE INFORMATION<lb/> Fill in information in each box below<lb/>

	Article Type<lb/> 
			<note type="doctype">Research article<lb/></note>

	Article Title (within 20 words without<lb/> abbreviations)<lb/> 
			<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Dietary coated copper and zinc improve growth performance by modulating immune<lb/> responses and fecal microbiota of weaned pigs<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
			
			Running Title (within 10 words)<lb/> Effects of dietary coated copper and zinc in weaned pigs<lb/> Author<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jinuk Nam1#, Hyunjin Kyoung1#, Yonghee Kim# Jinho Cho2#, Jinmu Ahn1, Kimoon<lb/> Kim1, Ikcheol Shin1, Sheena Kim 3, Jin Tae Kim 4, Sung Woo Jung 5, Hyeun Bum<lb/> Kim 3*, and Minho Song 1*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>
Affiliation<lb/> 
			
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Division of Animal and Dairy Science, Chungnam National University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Daejeon<lb/> 34134, Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Animal Science, Chungbuk National University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cheongju 28644,<lb/> Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Animal Resources Science, Dankook University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cheonan 31116,<lb/> Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
		<affiliation>4 AGRANCO Corp.,</affiliation>
	</byline>
			<address>Florida 33134, United States of America<lb/></address>
			
	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 ACC Inc.,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seongnam 13647, Republic of Korea<lb/></address>

	ORCID (for more information, please<lb/> visit https://orcid.org)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jinuk Nam</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0009-0003-8696-5697</idno>
			)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hyunjin Kyoung</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5742-5374</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Yonghee Kim</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		(
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0009-0009-8334-3706</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jinho Cho</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7151-0778</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jinmu Ahn</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0009-0005-1490-2974</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Kimoon Kim</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0009-0008-2988-5179</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ikcheol Shin</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0009-0003-0072-5626</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sheena Kim</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5410-1347</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jin Tae Kim</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0009-0007-4964-2994</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sung Woo Jung</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0009-0007-5587-8864</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hyeun Bum Kim</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1366-6090</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			<byline>
	<docAuthor>Minho Song</docAuthor>
			</byline>
		 (
			<idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4515-5212</idno>
		)<lb/> 
			
			Competing interests<lb/> 
			
			<div type="conflict">No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.<lb/></div>
			
			Funding sources<lb/> State funding sources (grants, funding<lb/> sources, equipment, and supplies).<lb/> Include name and number of grant if<lb/> available.<lb/> 
			
			<div type="funding">This work was carried out with the support of &quot;Cooperative Research Program for<lb/> Agriculture Science and Technology Development (RS-2023-00230754), Rural<lb/> Development Administration, Republic of Korea.<lb/></div>
			
			Acknowledgements<lb/> Not applicable.<lb/>

	Availability of data and material<lb/> 
			
			<div type="availability">Upon reasonable request, the datasets of this study can be available from the<lb/> corresponding author.<lb/></div> 
			
			Authors&apos; contributions<lb/> Please specify the authors&apos; role using<lb/> this form.<lb/> 
			
			<div type="contribution">Conceptualization: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J, Kim HB, Song M<lb/> Data curation: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J, Kim HB, Song M<lb/> Formal analysis: Nam J, Ahn J, Kim K, Shin I, Kim S, Kim JT, Jung SW<lb/> Methodology: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J<lb/> Software: Nam J, Kyoun H, Kim Y, Cho J<lb/> Validation: Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J, Kim HB, Song M<lb/> Investigation: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J<lb/> Writing -original draft: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J<lb/> Writing -review &amp; editing: Nam J, Kyoung H, Cho J, Kim Y, Ahn J, Kim K, Shin I,<lb/> Kim S, Kim JT, Jung SW, Kim HB, Song M<lb/></div>

	Ethics approval and consent to participate<lb/> The experimental protocol for this study was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Chungnam National University, Daejeon, Republic of Korea. (approval# 202103A-CNU-080)<lb/>
			
			A C<lb/> C<lb/> E P T E D<lb/>
	
			CORRESPONDING AUTHOR CONTACT INFORMATION<lb/> For the corresponding author (responsible for<lb/> correspondence, proofreading, and reprints)<lb/> Fill in information in each box below<lb/> First name, middle initial, last name<lb/>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hyeun Bum Kim<lb/> Minho Song<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Email address -this is where your proofs will be sent<lb/>
	<email>hbkim@dankook.ac.kr<lb/> mhsong@cnu.ac.kr<lb/></email>

	Secondary Email address<lb/> Address<lb/> Department of
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Animal Resources Science, Dankook University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cheonan 31116, Korea.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Division of Animal and Dairy Science, Chungnam National<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Daejeon 34134, Korea.<lb/></address>

	Cell phone number<lb/> Office phone number<lb/> 
			
			<phone>+82-41-550-3653<lb/> +82-42-821-5776<lb/></phone>
			
			Fax number<lb/> A C<lb/> C<lb/> E P T E D<lb/> Abstract (up to 350 words)<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">In the swine industry, supplementation with high levels of zinc oxide and copper sulfate in the weaner diet could<lb/> be excreted through feces without being normally absorbed in the intestine, resulting in environmental pollution.<lb/> Therefore, the various methods have been proposed to address this issue. The objective of this study was to<lb/> investigate effects of a low dietary dose of coated copper sulfate (CuSO 4 ) and zinc oxide (ZnO) on growth<lb/> performance, frequency of diarrhea, nutrient digestibility, and immune responses of weaned pigs. The four dietary<lb/> treatments were (1) a basal weaner diet based on corn and soybean meal (CON), (2) CON supplemented with<lb/> 2,500 ppm standard ZnO (T1), (3) CON supplemented with 100 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO 4 and 100 mg/kg<lb/> dietary coated ZnO (T2), and (4) CON supplemented with 200 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO 4 and 200 mg/kg dietary<lb/> coated ZnO (T3). Dietary T2 and T3 increased (p &lt; 0.05) the average daily gain for the first two weeks and the<lb/> overall experimental period compared to that with CON. In addition, the groups supplemented with Cu and Zn<lb/> tended to have a decreased (p &lt; 0.10) frequency of diarrhea. Pigs fed dietary T2 and/or T3 had lower (p &lt; 0.10)<lb/> number of white blood cells on day 7 and hematocrit on day 14 compared to those fed CON. However, no<lb/> difference was observed in the number of red blood cells among the dietary treatments. Regarding immune<lb/> responses, dietary T2 decreased (p &lt; 0.10) serum tumor necrosis factor-α on day 7 and increased (p &lt; 0.10)<lb/> immunoglobulin G on day 14 compared with CON. Moreover, pigs fed dietary T2 tended to have increased<lb/> Limosilacatobacilus (p &lt; 0.10). Dietary T3 had higher (p &lt; 0.05) relative abundance of the genus Agathobacter<lb/> compared to those fed CON and dietary T1 and decreased (p &lt; 0.05) genus Terrisporobacter compared to those<lb/> fed dietary T1. These results suggested the supplementation of dietary coated ZnO and CuSO 4 enhanced growth<lb/> performance and modulated immune responses associated with changes in the fecal microbiota composition.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>Copper; Growth performance; Immune response; Microbiota; Weaned pig; Zinc<lb/></keyword>

	A C<lb/> C<lb/> E P T E D
		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>