<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Potential use of dried persimmon (Diospyros kaki)
                    byproducts as feed sources for ruminants</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sang Moo</forename>
          <surname>Lee</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Tabita Dameria</forename>
          <surname>Marbun</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Eun Joong</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-12T17:12:13.819222Z">12.11.2025 17:12:13</date>
        <title>grobid.training.header [default]</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.5187$1$jast.2023.e83</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Korean Society of Animal Science and Technology</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5187/jast.2023.e83</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Sang Moo Lee, Tabita Dameria Marbun, Eun Joong Kim. (2024). Potential use of dried persimmon (Diospyros kaki)
                    byproducts as feed sources for ruminants. Journal of Animal Science and Technology, 66(4), 749-792. DOI: 10.5187/jast.2023.e83</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-12T17:12:13.819222Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">4ae14a7</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.header</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-12T17:12:13.819222Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-11-12T17:21:57.150Z" status="draft" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page>
          
    <title level="j">JAST (Journal of Animal Science and Technology)</title>
          
    TITLE PAGE<lb/>
	
	Upload this completed form to website with submission<lb/> ARTICLE INFORMATION<lb/> Fill in information in each box below<lb/>

	Article Type<lb/>
          
    <note type="doctype">Research Article<lb/></note>

	Article Title (within 20 words without abbreviations) 
	<docTitle>
        <titlePart>Evaluation of the Quality Characteristics of Nitrogen Gas-Stunned<lb/> Chicken Meat and Small Intestine<lb/></titlePart>
    </docTitle>

	Running Title (within 10 words)<lb/> Quality of chicken meat and small intestine by stunning method<lb/> Author<lb/>
	
  <byline>
	<docAuthor>Muhammad Shahbubul Alam [first_author] 1,2, Dong-Heon Song<lb/> [first_author] 1, Sun-Moon kang1, Inho Hwang2, Kuk-Hwan Seol1,<lb/> Soo-Hyun Cho1, Jung-Hwan Jeon3, Hyoun Wook Kim1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

    Affiliation<lb/> 
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Animal Products Utilization Division, National Institute of Animal<lb/> Science, Rural Development Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wanju-gun 55365,<lb/> Korea, Republic of<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Animal Science, Jeonbuk National University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Jeonju 561756, Korea, Republic of<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Animal Welfare Research Team, National Institute of Animal<lb/> Science, Rural Development Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

    <address>Wanju-gun 55365,<lb/> Korea, Republic of<lb/></address>

	  ORCID (for more information, please visit<lb/> https://orcid.org)<lb/> 
          
    <byline>
	<docAuthor>Muhammad Shahbubul Alam</docAuthor>
    </byline>
          
    (
    <idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2697-<lb/>1492</idno>
          
    )<lb/> 
          
    <byline>
	<docAuthor>Dong-Heon Song</docAuthor>
    </byline>
           (
      
      <idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4670-3321</idno>
      
      )<lb/>
      
      <byline>
	<docAuthor>Sun-Moon kang</docAuthor>
    </byline>
           (
      
      <idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3947-4337</idno>
      
      )<lb/> 
      
      <byline>
	<docAuthor>Inho Hwang</docAuthor>
    </byline>
           (
      
      <idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2474-2733</idno>
      
      )<lb/>
      
      <byline>
	<docAuthor>Kuk-Hwan Seol</docAuthor>
    </byline>
           (
      
      <idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0907-882X</idno>
      
      )<lb/>
      <byline>
	<docAuthor>Soo-Hyun Cho</docAuthor>
    </byline>
           (
      
      <idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8073-8771</idno>
      
      )<lb/>
      
      <byline>
	<docAuthor>Jung-Hwan Jeon</docAuthor>
    </byline>
           (
      
      <idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9725-547X</idno>
      
      )<lb/>
      
      <byline>
	<docAuthor>Hyoun Wook Kim</docAuthor>
    </byline>
           (
      
      <idno>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3947-4337</idno>
      
      )<lb/>
      
      Competing interests<lb/> 
          
      <note type="conflict">No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.<lb/></note> 
          
      Funding sources<lb/> State funding sources (grants, funding sources,<lb/> equipment, and supplies).
          
      Include name and number of<lb/> grant if available.<lb/> 
          
      <note type="funding">The study was funded by the &quot;RDA Fellowship program&quot; and<lb/> &quot;Cooperative Research Program for Agriculture Science and<lb/> Technology Development (Project No. PJ01621403 and PJ<lb/> 01490102)&quot;, NIAS, RDA, Republic of Korea.</note>

	Acknowledgements<lb/> Availability of data and material<lb/> Authors&apos; contributions<lb/> Please specify the authors&apos; role using this form.<lb/> 
    <note type="contribution">Conceptualization: kang SM, Seol KH, Kim HW<lb/> Data curation: Alam MS, Song DH<lb/> Formal analysis: Alam MS, Song DH<lb/> Methodology: Alam MS, Song DH, Hwang I, Jeon JH<lb/> Software: Alam MS, Song DH<lb/> Validation: Cho SH<lb/> Investigation: Alam MS, Song DH<lb/> Writing -original draft: Alam MS, Song DH<lb/> Writing -review &amp; editing: Alam MS, Song DH, kang SM, Hwang I,<lb/> Seol KH, Cho SH, Jeon JH, Kim HW<lb/></note>

	Ethics approval and consent to participate<lb/> The experiment was performed at the research of the National<lb/> Institute of Animal Science of Korea (NIAS). The animal care and<lb/> use committee of NIAS reviewed and approved the protocol for this<lb/> study (Approval Number: NIAS20191536).<lb/>

	CORRESPONDING AUTHOR CONTACT INFORMATION<lb/> For the corresponding author<lb/> (responsible for correspondence,<lb/> proofreading, and reprints)<lb/> Fill in information in each box below<lb/>
	<keyword>First name, middle initial, last name<lb/></keyword>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hyoun Wook Kim<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Email address -this is where your proofs will be sent<lb/>
	<email>woogi78@korea.kr<lb/></email>

	Secondary Email address Address<lb/> Cell phone number<lb/> Office phone number<lb/> Fax number<lb/> 
          
    <docTitle>
        <titlePart>Evaluation of the Quality Characteristics of Nitrogen Gas-Stunned<lb/> Chicken Breast Meat and Small Intestine</titlePart>
    </docTitle>
          
    Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">This study aimed to confirm the applicability of the new nitrogen (N2) gas stunning method in the broiler slaughtering<lb/> process by comparing the meat and small intestine quality following different stunning methods (electrical, carbon<lb/> dioxide (CO2), N2, and halal). Four treatments were compared: (i) electrical stunning (Elec), (ii) 80% CO2 gas stunning<lb/> (CO2-gas), (iii) 98% N2 gas stunning (N2-gas), and (iv) the non-stunning method (Halal). N2 gas stunning (98%) and<lb/> the halal method were conducted at the pilot plant abattoir of the national institute of animal science, Korea, and<lb/> electrical and 80% CO2 stunning were performed on the nearest commercial slaughter house. Meat pH24h, color<lb/> (lightness, redness and yellowness), proximate composition, water holding capacity (WHC), cooking loss, and<lb/> Warner-Bratzler shear force (WBSF) were measured, and in the small intestine, pH24h, color, thickness, and WBSF<lb/> were measured. The Elec treatment showed high lightness, yellowness, and low redness in both meat and the small<lb/> intestine, indicated by a pale color; the CO2-gas treatment showed high redness, low lightness, and low yellowness,<lb/> and the coloration of meat from the N2-gas treatment was intermediate between Elec and CO2-gas. For other quality<lb/> traits, the N2-gas showed good results and was between Elec and CO2-gas. Additionally, severe stress (low pH in both<lb/> meats), low WHC in meat, and cracked small intestine with numerous apertures were observed in the CO2-gas, and<lb/> pale colored hemorrhagic breast meat was found in the Elec. Therefore, in view of animal welfare and quality traits<lb/> of meat and the small intestine, 98% N2 gas can be considered in broiler stunning.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>slaughtering process; gas stun; nitrogen-stunning; chicken breast meat; small intestine</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>

</TEI>