<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="100._tr684.Tally_NP_sets_and_easy_census_functions"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Tally NP Sets and Easy Census Functions<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Judy Goldsmith 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Computer Science<lb/> University of Kentucky<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Lexington, KY 40506, USA<lb/></address>

	<email>goldsmit@cs.engr.uky.edu<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mitsunori Ogihara 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Computer Science<lb/> University of Rochester<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rochester, NY 14627, USA<lb/></address>

	<email>ogihara@cs.rochester.edu<lb/></email>

	<reference>J org Rothe 3<lb/></reference>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institut f ur Informatik<lb/> Friedrich-Schiller-Universit at Jena<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>07740 Jena, Germany<lb/></address>

	<email>rothe@informatik.uni-jena.de<lb/></email>

	<date>March 19, 1998<lb/></date>

	<note type="funding">1 Supported in part by NSF grant CCR-9315354.<lb/> 2 Supported in part by NSF CAREER Award CCR-9701911.<lb/> 3 Supported in part by grants NSF-INT-9513368/DAAD-315-PRO-fo-ab and NSF-CCR-9322513<lb/> and by a NATO Postdoctoral Science Fellowship from the Deutscher Akademischer Austausch-<lb/>dienst (\Gemeinsames Hochschulsonderprogramm III von Bund und L andern&quot;).</note> 

	Current address:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Computer Science, University of Rochester,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rochester, NY 14627, USA.</address>

	Work done<lb/> in part while visiting the University of Kentucky and the University of Rochester. 

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">We study the question of whether every P set has an easy (i.e., polynomial-<lb/>time computable) census function. We characterize this question in terms of<lb/> unlikely collapses of language and function classes such as #P 1 FP, where<lb/> #P 1 is the class of functions that count the witnesses for tally NP sets. We<lb/> prove that every #P PH 1 function can be computed in FP #P #P 1<lb/> 1 . Consequently,<lb/> every P set has an easy census function if and only if every set in the polynomial<lb/> hierarchy does. We show that the assumption #P 1 FP implies P = BPP and<lb/> PH MOD k P for each k 2, which provides further evidence that not all sets<lb/> in P have an easy census function. We also relate a set&apos;s property of having an<lb/> easy census function to other well-studied properties of sets, such as rankability<lb/> and scalability (the closure of the rankable sets under P-isomorphisms). Finally,<lb/> we prove that it is no more likely that the census function of any set in P can<lb/> be approximated (more precisely, can be n -enumerated in time n for xed<lb/> and ) than that it can be precisely computed in polynomial time.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
