<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1023._IntJModPhy17-519"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>International Journal of Modern Physics D<lb/> Vol. 17, Nos. 3 &amp; 4 (2008) 519-523<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">c World Scientific Publishing Company<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THE INEQUALITY BETWEEN MASS AND<lb/> ANGULAR MOMENTUM FOR AXIALLY<lb/> SYMMETRIC BLACK HOLES *<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SERGIO DAIN<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Facultad de Matemática, Astronomía y Física,<lb/> Universidad Nacional de Córdoba,<lb/> Ciudad Universitaria,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>(5000) Córdoba, Argentina<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Max Planck Institute for Gravitational Physics,<lb/> (Albert Einstein Institute),</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Am Mühlenberg 1,<lb/> D-14476 Potsdam, Germany<lb/></address>

	<email>dain@famaf.unc.edu.ar<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received 01 December 2007<lb/> Communicated by D. V. Ahluwalia-Khalilova<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">In this essay I first discuss the physical relevance of the inequality m ≥<lb/> p<lb/> |J| for axially<lb/> symmetric (nonstationary) black holes, where m is the mass and J the angular momen-<lb/>tum of the space-time. Then, I present a proof of this inequality for the case of one<lb/> spinning black hole. The proof involves a remarkable characterization of the extreme<lb/> Kerr black hole as an absolute minimum of the total mass. Finally, I conjecture about<lb/> the physical implications of this characterization for the nonlinear stability problem for<lb/> black holes.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>Black holes; axial symmetry; angular momentum; mass; extreme Kerr.<lb/></keyword>

	* This essay received an &quot;honorable mention&quot; in the 2007 Essay Competition of the Gravity<lb/> Research Foundation.
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
