<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1030._taste_variety_wp"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Taste for Variety and Endogenous Fluctuations in a<lb/> Monopolistic Competition Model<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Thomas Seegmuller<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>CNRS and Centre d&apos;Economie de la Sorbonne,<lb/> Paris School of Economics, Université Paris 1,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>106-112 Boulevard de l&apos;Hôpital 75647 Paris Cedex 13, France.<lb/></address>

	Tel: <phone>(33) 1 44 07 81 99</phone><lb/> Fax: (33) 1 44 07 82 31<lb/> E-mail:
	<email>seegmu@univ-paris1.fr</email>

	<page>1<lb/></page> 
	halshs-00266722, version 1 -
	
	<date>25 Mar 2008<lb/></date>

	<note type="doctype">Author manuscript</note>

	, published in &quot;Macroeconomic Dynamics (2008) xx-xx&quot; 

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">In past years, imperfect competition has been introduced in several dy-<lb/>namic models to show how mark-up variability, increasing returns (decreas-<lb/>ing marginal cost), and monopoly prots aect the occurrence of endogenous<lb/> uctuations. In this paper, we focus on another possible feature of imper-<lb/>fectly competitive economies: consumers&apos; taste for variety due to endoge-<lb/>nous product diversity. Introducing monopolistic competition (Dixit and<lb/> Stiglitz (1977), Benassy (1996)) in an overlapping generations model where<lb/> consumers have taste for variety, we show that local indeterminacy can occur<lb/> under the three following conditions: a high substitution between capital and<lb/> labor, increasing returns arbitrarily small and a not too elastic labor supply.<lb/> The key mechanism for this result is based on the fact that, due to taste for<lb/> variety, the aggregate price decreases with the pro-cyclical product diversity,<lb/> which has a direct inuence on the real wage and the real interest rate.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>Endogenous uctuations, taste for variety, imperfect competition. Résumé<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">Dans les années passées, la concurrence imparfaite a été introduite dans<lb/> des modèles dynamiques pour montrer comment la variabilité du taux de<lb/> marge, les rendements croissants (coût marginal décroissant), et les prof-<lb/>its de monopole aectent l&apos;apparition de uctuations endogènes. Dans ce<lb/> papier, nous nous intéressons à une autre caractéristique des économies im-<lb/>parfaitement concurrentielles : le goût pour la variété dû à la diversité en-<lb/>dogène des produits. Introduisant de la concurrence monopolistique (Dixit<lb/> et Stiglitz (1977), Benassy (1996)) dans un modèle à générations imbriquées<lb/> dans lequel les consommateurs ont du goût pour la variété, nous montrons<lb/> que de l&apos;indétermination locale peut apparaître sous les trois conditions suiv-<lb/>antes : une substitution entre le capital et le travail élevée, des rendements<lb/> croissants arbitrairement faibles et une ore de travail pas trop fortement<lb/> élastique. Le mécanisme clé pour ce résultat repose sur le fait que, dû au<lb/> goût pour la variété, le prix agrégé décroît avec la diversité pro-cyclique des<lb/> produits, ce qui inuence directement le salaire et le taux d&apos;intérêt réels.<lb/></div>

	Mots-clés: 
	<keyword>Fluctuations endogènes, goût pour la variété, concurrence impar-<lb/>faite.<lb/></keyword>

	<keyword>JEL classication: C62, D43, E32.<lb/></keyword>

	halshs-00266722, version 1 -

	<date>25 Mar 2008<lb/> </date>

	halshs-00266722, version 1 -Mar 2008

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
