<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10461_2010_Article_9674"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">ORIGINAL PAPER<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Barriers to Pharmacy-Based Syringe Purchase Among Injection<lb/> Drug Users in Tijuana, Mexico: A Mixed Methods Study<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Robin A. Pollini • Remedios Lozada • Manuel Gallardo •<lb/> Perth Rosen • Alicia Vera • Armando Macias •<lb/> Lawrence A. Palinkas • Steffanie A. Strathdee<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Published online:
	<date>19 March 2010<lb/></date>

	<note type="copyright">Ó The Author(s) 2010. This article is published with open access at Springerlink.com<lb/></note>

	Abstract
	<div type="abstract">Injection drug users (IDUs) may be denied<lb/> purchase of sterile syringes even where purchase without a<lb/> prescription is legal. This study examined barriers to over-<lb/>the-counter (OTC) syringe purchase among IDUs in<lb/> Tijuana, Mexico. A quantitative survey and subsequent<lb/> focus groups were used to quantify barriers to purchase,<lb/> identify their correlates and provide in-depth exploration of<lb/> syringe purchase experiences. Of 627 IDUs, 81% pur-<lb/>chased a syringe in the past 6 months and 16% were<lb/> refused or overcharged. Factors independently associated<lb/> with refusal/overcharging were homelessness, receptive<lb/> syringe sharing, [5 uses per syringe, and number of life-<lb/>time abscesses. Few pharmacies sold syringes to IDUs,<lb/> who adapted by limiting purchase attempts to pharmacies<lb/> known to sell syringes consistently. Failed purchases<lb/> occurred when drug withdrawal required purchase at unu-<lb/>sual times or locations, often following release from jail.<lb/> IDUs reported syringe sharing, syringe reuse, and search-<lb/>ing through unsecured medical waste for syringes in<lb/> response to failed purchase attempts. Interventions to<lb/> expand OTC syringe sales to IDUs, particularly near<lb/> detention facilities, will facilitate safer injection practices.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords Injection drug use Á Pharmacies Á<lb/> Syringe access Á Syringe sharing Á Mexico<lb/></keyword>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>R. A. Pollini (&amp;) Á P. Rosen Á A. Vera Á<lb/> L. A. Palinkas Á S. A. Strathdee<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Division of Global Public Health, Department of Medicine,<lb/> School of Medicine, University of California San Diego,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>9500 Gilman Drive, Mailcode 0507, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA<lb/></address>

	e-mail:
	<email>rpollini@ucsd.edu<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>R. Lozada Á M. Gallardo Á A. Macias<lb/> Patronado Pro-COMUSIDA, Tijuana, Mexico<lb/> L. A. Palinkas<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Social Policy and Health, School of Social Work,<lb/> University of Southern California,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Los Angeles, CA, USA</address>

	123<lb/>
	<reference>AIDS Behav (2010) 14:679-687<lb/></reference>

	<idno>DOI 10.1007/s10461-010-9674-3</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
