<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10708_2015_9672_Article"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Using an integrated approach to assess the sediment quality of an Mediterranean<lb/> lagoon, the Bizerte lagoon (Tunisia)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Badreddine Barhoumi 1,2,* , Anis Elbarhoumi II 3 , Christelle Clérandeau Sr. 2 , Abdulla M.<lb/> Al-Rawabdeh 4 , Atef Atyaoui 3,5 , Soufiane de Touil 1 , Mohamed Ridha Driss 1 , Jérôme<lb/> Cachot 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Laboratory of Heteroatom Organic Chemistry, Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Sciences<lb/> of Bizerte, University of Carthage, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Four Fountains Road, 7021 Jarzouna, Tunisia</address> 
	Tel.: 
	<phone>+216<lb/> 22 199 496 </phone>
	* e-mail: 
	<email>barhoumibadredine@yahoo.fr<lb/></email> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 University of Bordeaux, UMR CNRS EPOC 5805, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>10 N Two Pier Avenue, 33405 Talence<lb/> Cedex, France<lb/></address> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Earth Sciences, Faculty of Sciences of Bizerte, University of Carthage,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Four<lb/> Fountains Road, 7021 Jarzouna, Tunisia<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Geomatics Engineering, University of Calgary,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Twelve North Street, Calgary,<lb/> Canada<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Delhi University, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nine Horses Street, New Delhi, India<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 URL: http://www.natureview.com<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	Abstract:<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">The present study investigates the quality of surface sediments from the Bizerte lagoon (North Tunisia) using an<lb/> integrated approach including chemical contaminant analysis, bioassays and sediment quality guidelines (SQGs).<lb/> Sediment samples were collected at 9 sites and analyzed for eight heavy metals (Hg, Cd, Cr, Cu, Pb, Zn, Ni, Fe<lb/> and Mn). PAHs, PCBs, OCPs were measured previously in the same sediment samples. Our results indicated<lb/> that the highest concentrations of metals were found near urban areas due to the municipial and industrial<lb/> wastewater discharges. Sediment pollution assessment was carried out using geoaccumulation index (Igeo) and<lb/> enrichment factor (EF), which indicate a widespread pollution by Cd, Pb, Ni and Zn in the studied sediments.<lb/> For bioassays, aqueous and organic extracts were used to assess toxicity and genotoxicity in sediments by using<lb/> Microtox ® and SOS Chromotest, respectively. Toxicity levels were compared to metallic and organic pollutants<lb/> contents. Our results highlight differences in the pattern of responses between the different assays and show no<lb/> correlation with all the studied contaminants, emphasizing the influence of other contaminants not analyzed in<lb/> the present study. Based on SQGs, the results of toxicity assessment indicated that adverse effects caused by Ni<lb/> and Zn would be expected frequently. Nickel was found to have the highest predicted acute toxicity, followed by<lb/> Zn, Pb, Cd, Cu and Cr. There was no significant relationship between sediment toxicity calculated from heavy<lb/> metal concentrations (SQG approach) and those measured with bioassays. These findings support the use of<lb/> integrated approachs for evaluating the environmental risks of sediments.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>marine lagoon, surface sediments, metals, organic pollutants, toxicity assays</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
