<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1105"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Selene: Voting with Transparent Verifiability <lb/>and Coercion-Mitigation <lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Peter Y A Ryan, Peter B Rønne, Vincenzo Iovino<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract. End-to-end verifiable voting schemes typically involves vot-<lb/>ers handling an encrypted ballot in order to confirm that their vote is<lb/> accurately included in the tally. While this may be technically valid,<lb/> from a public acceptance standpoint is may be problematic: many voters<lb/> may not really understand the purpose of the encrypted ballot and the<lb/> various checks that they can perform. In this paper we take a different<lb/> approach and revisit an old idea: to provide each voter with a private<lb/> tracking number. Votes are posted on a bulletin board in the clear along<lb/> with their associated tracking number. This is appealing in that it pro-<lb/>vides voters with a very simple, intuitive way to verify their vote, in the<lb/> clear. However, there are obvious drawbacks: we must ensure that no two<lb/> voters are assigned the same tracker and we need to keep the trackers<lb/> private.<lb/> In this paper, we propose a scheme that addresses both of these problems:<lb/> we ensure that voters get unique trackers and we close off the coercer&apos;s<lb/> window of opportunity by ensuring that the voters only learn their track-<lb/>ing numbers after votes have been posted. The resulting scheme provides<lb/> receipt-freeness, and indeed a good level of coercion-resistance while also<lb/> providesinga more immediately understandable form of verifiability. The<lb/> cryptographyis under the bonnet as far as the voter is concerned.<lb/> The basic scheme still has a problem in some contexts: if the coercer is<lb/> himself a voter there is a chance that the coerced voter might light on the<lb/> coercer&apos;s tracker, or the coercer simply claims that it is his. We argue that<lb/> in many contexts this may be an acceptable threat when weighed against<lb/> the more transparent verification provided by the scheme. Nonetheless,<lb/> we describe some elaborations of the basic scheme to mitigate such<lb/> threats.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
