<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1151.full"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>American Journal of Epidemiology</reference>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<reference>Vol. 161, No. 12<lb/></reference>
			<note type="copyright">Copyright a 2005 by the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public
				Health</note>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<note type="other">Printed in U.S.A.<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">All rights reserved</note>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<idno>DOI: 10.1093/aje/kwi149</idno>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Analysis of Worldwide Earthquake Mortality using Multivariate Demographic
					and<lb/> Seismic Data<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>E. Gutie rez 1 , F. Taucer 1 , T. De Groeve 2 , D. H. A. Al-Khudhairy 2 ,
					and J. M. Zaldivar 3<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 European Laboratory for Structural Assessment Unit, Joint Research
					Centre–Institute for the Protection and Security of the<lb/>
					Citizen,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Ispra, Italy.<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 External Security Unit, Joint Research Centre–Institute for the
					Protection and Security of the Citizen,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Ispra, Italy.<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>3 Inland Marine Waters Unit, Joint Research Centre–Institute for
					Environment and Sustainability, Commission of the<lb/> European
					Communities,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Ispra, Italy.<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received for publication July 8, 2004; accepted for publication
				February 16, 2005.<lb/></note>

			<div type="abstract">In this paper, mortality in the immediate aftermath of an
				earthquake is studied on a worldwide scale using<lb/> multivariate analysis. A
				statistical method is presented that analyzes reported earthquake fatalities as a
				function<lb/> of a heterogeneous set of parameters selected on the basis of their
				presumed influence on earthquake mortality.<lb/> The ensemble was compiled from
				demographic, seismic, and reported fatality data culled from available records
				of<lb/> past earthquakes organized in a geographic information system. The authors
				consider the statistical relation<lb/> between earthquake mortality and the
				available data ensemble, analyze the validity of the results in view of the<lb/>
				parametric uncertainties, and propose a multivariate mortality analysis prediction
				method. The analysis reveals<lb/> that, although the highest mortality rates are
				expected in poorly developed rural areas, high fatality counts can<lb/> result from
				a wide range of mortality ratios that depend on the effective population
				size.<lb/></div>

			<keywords>demography; mortality; multivariate analysis; natural disasters</keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
