<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="11606_2011_Article_1801"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Use of Prescription Drug Samples and Patient Assistance<lb/> Programs, and the Role of Doctor-Patient Communication<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Walid F. Gellad, MD, MPH 1,2,3 , Haiden A. Huskamp, PhD 4 , Angela Li, MPH 5,6 , Yuting Zhang, PhD 7 ,<lb/> Dana Gelb Safran, ScD 5,6 , and Julie M. Donohue, PhD 7</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Pittsburgh Veterans Affairs Medical Center and the Center for Health Equity Research and Promotion,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pittsburgh, PA, USA;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 University of<lb/> Pittsburgh School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pittsburgh, PA, USA;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 RAND Corporation,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pittsburgh, PA, USA;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Health Care Policy, Harvard<lb/> Medical School, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, MA, USA;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 The Health Institute, Tufts Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, MA, USA;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 Blue Cross Blue Shield of Massachusetts,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, MA, USA;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>7 University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public Health,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pittsburgh, PA, USA.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">BACKGROUND: Cost-related underuse of medications<lb/> is common among older adults, who seldom discuss<lb/> medication costs with their physicians. Some older<lb/> adults may use free drug samples or industry-spon-<lb/>sored patient assistance programs (PAP) in hopes of<lb/> lowering out-of-pocket costs, although the long-term<lb/> effect of these programs on drug spending is unclear.<lb/> OBJECTIVE: To examine older adults&apos; use of industry-<lb/>sponsored strategies to reduce out-of-pocket drug<lb/> costs and the association between doctor-patient<lb/> communication and use of these programs.<lb/> DESIGN: Cross-sectional analysis of a 2006 nationally<lb/> representative survey of Medicare beneficiaries.<lb/> PARTICIPANTS: 14,322 community-dwelling Medi-<lb/>care beneficiaries age ≥65.<lb/> MAIN MEASURES: We conducted bivariate and multi-<lb/>variate analyses of the association between receipt of<lb/> free samples and participation in PAPs with socio-<lb/>demographic characteristics, health status, access to<lb/> care, drug coverage, medication cost burden, and<lb/> doctor-patient communication.<lb/> KEY RESULTS: 51.4% of seniors reported receiving at<lb/> least one free sample over the last 12 months and<lb/> 29.2% reported receiving free samples more than once.<lb/> In contrast, only 1.3% of seniors reported participating<lb/> in an industry-sponsored PAP. Higher income respon-<lb/>dents were more likely to report free sample receipt<lb/> than low-income respondents (50.8% vs. 43.8%, p&lt;<lb/> 0.001) and less likely to report participating in a PAP<lb/> (0.42% vs. 2.2%, p&lt;0.001). In multivariate analyses,<lb/> those who reported talking to their doctor about the<lb/> cost of their medications had more than twice the odds<lb/> of receiving samples as those who did not (OR 2.17,<lb/> 95% CI 1.95-2.42).<lb/> CONCLUSIONS: In 2006, over half of seniors in<lb/> Medicare received free samples, but only 1.3%<lb/> reported receiving any medications from a patient<lb/> assistance program. Doctor-patient communication is<lb/> strongly associated with use of these programs, which<lb/> has important implications for clinical care regardless<lb/> of whether these programs are viewed as drivers of<lb/> prescription costs or a remedy for them.<lb/></div>

	KEY WORDS:
	<keyword>free drug samples; prescription assistance programs;<lb/> Medicare; physician-patient communication.<lb/></keyword>

	<reference>J Gen Intern Med 26(12):1458-64<lb/></reference>

	<idno>DOI: 10.1007/s11606-011-1801-y<lb/></idno>

	<note type="copyright">© Society of General Internal Medicine 2011<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Received February 21, 2011<lb/> Revised June 6, 2011<lb/> Accepted June 24, 2011<lb/></note> 

	Published online 
	<date>July 13, 2011</date>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
