<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="125._CS-TR-3632"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Exploiting the Temporal Structure of MPEG Video<lb/> for the Reduction of Bandwidth Requirements<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Marwan Krunz and Satish Tripathi<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institute for Advanced Computer Studies<lb/> Department of Computer Science<lb/> University of Maryland<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>College Park, MD 20742<lb/></address>

	Email:
	<email>krunz@cs.umd.edu</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">We propose a new bandwidth allocation scheme for VBR video tra c in ATM networks.<lb/> The scheme is tailored to MPEG-coded video sources that require stringent and deterministic<lb/> quality-of-service guarantees. By exploiting the temporal structure of MPEG sources, we show<lb/> that our scheme results in an e ective bandwidth which, in most cases, is less than the source<lb/> peak rate. The reduction in the bandwidth requirement is achieved without sacri cing any<lb/> perceived QoS. E cient procedures are provided for the computation of the e ective bandwidth<lb/> under heterogeneous MPEG sources. The e ective bandwidth strongly depends on the arrange-<lb/>ment of the multiplexed streams which is a measure of the degree of synchronization between the<lb/> GOP patterns of di erent streams. Assuming that all possible arrangements are equi-probable,<lb/> we derive an expression for the asymptotic tail distribution of the e ective bandwidth. From<lb/> the tail distribution, we compute several performance measures for the call blocking probability<lb/> when the allocation is made based on the e ective bandwidth. In the case of homogeneous<lb/> sources, we give a closed-form expression for the`best&apos; arrangement that results in the`optimal&apos;<lb/> e ective bandwidth. Numerical examples based on real MPEG traces are used to demonstrate<lb/> the advantages of our scheme.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>bandwidth allocation, MPEG, statistical multiplexing, CAC.<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="funding">This research was partially supported by the NSF grant # CCR 9318933.</note>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
