<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12862_2014_Article_245"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E<lb/></note> 

	<note type="doctype">Open Access<lb/></note> 
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Hybridisation and diversification in the adaptive<lb/> radiation of clownfishes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Glenn Litsios 1,2 and Nicolas Salamin 1,2*</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: The importance of hybridisation during species diversification has long been debated among<lb/> evolutionary biologists. It is increasingly recognised that hybridisation events occurred during the evolutionary<lb/> history of numerous species, especially during the early stages of adaptive radiation. We study the effect of<lb/> hybridisation on diversification in the clownfishes, a clade of coral reef fish that diversified through an adaptive<lb/> radiation process. While two species of clownfish are likely to have been described from hybrid specimens, the<lb/> occurrence and effect of hybridisation on the clade diversification is yet unknown.<lb/> Results: We generate sequences of three mitochondrial genes to complete an existing dataset of nuclear<lb/> sequences and document cytonuclear discordance at a node, which shows a drastic increase of diversification rate.<lb/> Then, using a tree-based jack-knife method, we identify clownfish species likely stemming from hybridisation events.<lb/> Finally, we use molecular cloning and identify the putative parental species of four clownfish specimens that display<lb/> the morphological characteristics of hybrids.<lb/> Conclusions: Our results show that consistently with the syngameon hypothesis, hybridisation events are linked<lb/> with a burst of diversification in the clownfishes. Moreover, several recently diverged clownfish lineages likely<lb/> originated through hybridisation, which indicates that diversification, catalysed by hybridisation events, may still be<lb/> happening.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>Syngameon, Speciation, Diversification, Cytonuclear discordance, Anemonefish<lb/></keyword>

	* Correspondence:
	<email>nicolas.salamin@unil.ch</email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of Ecology and Evolution, Biophore, University of Lausanne,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1015 Lausanne, Switzerland</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, Génopode, Quartier Sorge,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1015 Lausanne, Switzerland<lb/></address>

	<note type="copyright">© 2014 Litsios and Salamin; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the<lb/> Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0), which permits unrestricted use,<lb/> distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public<lb/> Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this<lb/> article, unless otherwise stated.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Litsios and Salamin BMC Evolutionary Biology 2014, 14:245<lb/></reference> 

	<ptr type="web">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/14/245</ptr>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
