<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12916_2014_Article_197"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197<lb/></reference>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="other">C O R R E S P O N D E N C E<lb/> </note>
	
	<note type="copyright">Open Access<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Five-step authorship framework to improve<lb/> transparency in disclosing contributors to<lb/> industry-sponsored clinical trial publications<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ana Marušić<lb/> 1*<lb/> , Darko Hren<lb/> 2<lb/> , Bernadette Mansi<lb/> 3,4 , Neil Lineberry<lb/> 4,5<lb/> , Ananya Bhattacharya<lb/> 4,6 , Maureen Garrity<lb/> 4,7 ,<lb/> Juli Clark<lb/> 4,8<lb/> , Thomas Gesell<lb/> 4,9 , Susan Glasser<lb/> 4,10 , John Gonzalez<lb/> 4,11 , Carolyn Hustad<lb/> 4,12 , Mary-Margaret Lannon<lb/> 4,13 ,<lb/> LaVerne A Mooney<lb/> 4,14 and Teresa Peña<lb/> 4,15<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Authorship guidelines have established criteria to guide author selection based on significance of contribution and helped<lb/> to define associated responsibilities and accountabilities for the published findings. However, low awareness, variable<lb/> interpretation, and inconsistent application of these guidelines can lead to confusion and a lack of transparency when<lb/> recognizing those who merit authorship. This article describes a research project led by the Medical Publishing Insights and<lb/> Practices (MPIP) Initiative to identify current challenges when determining authorship for industry-sponsored clinical trials<lb/> and develop an improved approach to facilitate decision-making when recognizing authors from related publications. A<lb/> total of 498 clinical investigators, journal editors, publication professionals and medical writers were surveyed to understand<lb/> better how they would adjudicate challenging, real-world authorship case scenarios, determine the perceived frequency of<lb/> each scenario and rate their confidence in the responses provided. Multiple rounds of discussions about these results with<lb/> journal editors, clinical investigators and industry representatives led to the development of key recommendations intended<lb/> to enhance transparency when determining authorship. These included forming a representative group to establish<lb/> authorship criteria early in a trial, having all trial contributors agree to these criteria and documenting trial contributions to<lb/> objectively determine who warrants an invitation to participate in the manuscript development process. The resulting<lb/> Five-step Authorship Framework is designed to create a more standardized approach when determining authorship for<lb/> clinical trial publications. Overall, these recommendations aim to facilitate more transparent authorship decisions and help<lb/> readers better assess the credibility of results and perspectives of the authors for medical research more broadly.<lb/> Please see related article: http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/214.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: Authorship, Transparency, Clinical trial, MPIP Initiative, Journal editors, Medical writers, Clinical investigators,<lb/> Publication professionals<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="other">* Correspondence:</note>

	<email>ana.marusic@mefst.hr<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of Research in Biomedicine and Health, University of Split<lb/> School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Šoltanska 2, 21000 Split, Croatia<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">Full list of author information is available at the end of the article<lb/></note>

	<note type="copyright">© 2014 Marusic et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative<lb/> Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public</note>

	<note type="copyright">Domain<lb/> Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article,<lb/> unless otherwise stated.<lb/></note> 
	
	<note type="other">Author details<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of Research in Biomedicine and Health, University of Split<lb/> School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Šoltanska 2, 21000 Split, Croatia.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> University of Split<lb/> School of Humanities and Social Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Split, Croatia.<lb/> 3 GlaxoSmithKline,<lb/> King of Prussia, PA, USA.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Member of MPIP Initiative Steering Committee,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, MA, USA.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5<lb/> Navigant Consulting,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, MA, USA.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6<lb/> Bristol-Myers<lb/> Squibb, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Princeton, NJ, USA.<lb/> </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>7<lb/> Astellas, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Northbrook, IL, USA.<lb/> </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>8<lb/> Amgen, </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>Thousand<lb/> Oaks, CA, USA.<lb/> </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>9<lb/> On behalf of the International Society for Medical Publication<lb/> Professionals,</affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>Briarcliff Manor, NY, USA.<lb/> </address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>10<lb/> Janssen Research &amp;Development,<lb/> LLC, </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address> Raritan, NJ, USA.<lb/> </address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>11<lb/> AstraZeneca,</affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>Alderley Park, UK.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>12<lb/> Merck &amp; Co, Inc,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Whitehouse Station, NJ, USA.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>13<lb/> Takeda, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Deerfield, IL, USA.<lb/> </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>14<lb/> Pfizer,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New York,<lb/> NY, USA.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>15<lb/> AstraZeneca,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wilmington, DE, USA.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: 16 July 2014 Accepted: 1 October 2014</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
