<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12970_2015_Article_108"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E<lb/></note> 

	<note type="doctype">Open Access<lb/></note> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Nutritional behaviour and beliefs of<lb/> ski-mountaineers: a semi-quantitative and<lb/> qualitative study<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Caroline Praz 1 , Mélanie Granges 2 , Céline Burtin 2 and Bengt Kayser 3*</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: Endurance athletes are advised to optimize nutrition prior to races. Little is known about actual<lb/> athletes&apos; beliefs, knowledge and nutritional behaviour. We monitored nutritional behaviour of amateur<lb/> ski-mountaineering athletes during 4 days prior to a major competition to compare it with official recommendations<lb/> and with the athletes&apos; beliefs.<lb/> Methods: Participants to the two routes of the &apos;Patrouille des Glaciers&apos; were recruited (A, 26 km, ascent 1881 m,<lb/> descent 2341 m, max altitude 3160 m; Z, 53 km, ascent 3994 m, descent 4090 m, max altitude 3650 m). Dietary intake<lb/> diaries of 40 athletes (21 A, 19 Z) were analysed for energy, carbohydrate, fat, protein and liquid; ten were interviewed<lb/> about their pre-race nutritional beliefs and behaviour.<lb/> Results: Despite belief that pre-race carbohydrate, energy and fluid intake should be increased, energy consumption<lb/> was 2416 ± 696 (mean ± SD) kcal • day −1 , 83 ± 17 % of recommended intake, carbohydrate intake was only 46 ± 13 % of<lb/> minimal recommended (10 g • kg −1 • day −1 ) and fluid intake only 2.7 ± 1.0 l • day −1 .<lb/> Conclusions: Our sample of endurance athletes did not comply with pre-race nutritional recommendations despite<lb/> elementary knowledge and belief to be compliant. In these athletes a clear and reflective nutritional strategy was<lb/> lacking. This suggests a potential for improving knowledge and compliance with recommendations. Alternatively,<lb/> some recommendations may be unrealistic.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>Endurance activity, Food behaviour, Food beliefs, Pre-race nutrition, Energy intake, Ski-mountaineering<lb/></keyword>

	* Correspondence:
	<email>bengt.kayser@unil.ch</email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> Institute of Sports Sciences and Department of Physiology, University of<lb/> Lausanne,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Géopolis, Campus Dorigny, 1015 Lausanne, Switzerland<lb/></address>

	Full list of author information is available at the end of the article<lb/> 

	<note type="copyright">© 2015 Praz et al. Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0<lb/> International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to<lb/> the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver<lb/> (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Praz et al. Journal of the International Society of Sports Nutrition (2015) 12:46<lb/></reference>

	<idno>DOI 10.1186/s12970-015-0108-5<lb/></idno>

	<reference>Praz et al. Journal of the International Society of Sports Nutrition (2015) 12:46<lb/></reference>

	Author details
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Institute of Sports Sciences and Department of Physiology, University of<lb/> Lausanne and Institute for Research in Rehabilitation, SuvaCare Rehabilitation<lb/> Clinic,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sion, Switzerland.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Nutrition and Dietetics Department, School of<lb/> Health, University of Applied Sciences and Arts of Western Switzerland,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Geneva, Switzerland.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Institute of Sports Sciences and Department of<lb/> Physiology, University of Lausanne,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Géopolis, Campus Dorigny, 1015<lb/> Lausanne, Switzerland.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: 22 June 2015 Accepted: 4 December 2015</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
