<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1309.7222"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Continuous compliance: a proxy-based<lb/> monitoring framework<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Julien VEDANI * † ‡<lb/> Fabien RAMAHAROBANDRO * §<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<date>September 26, 2013</date>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Within the Own Risk and Solvency Assessment framework, the Solvency II<lb/> directive introduces the need for insurance undertakings to have efficient tools en-<lb/>abling the companies to assess the continuous compliance with regulatory solvency<lb/> requirements. Because of the great operational complexity resulting from each<lb/> complete evaluation of the Solvency Ratio, this monitoring is often complicated to<lb/> implement in practice. This issue is particularly important for life insurance com-<lb/>panies due to the high complexity to project life insurance liabilities. It appears<lb/> relevant in such a context to use parametric tools, such as Curve Fitting and Least<lb/> Squares Monte Carlo in order to estimate, on a regular basis, the impact on the<lb/> economic own funds and on the regulatory capital of the company of any change<lb/> over time of its underlying risk factors.<lb/> In this article, we first outline the principles of the continuous compliance re-<lb/>quirement then we propose and implement a possible monitoring tool enabling to<lb/> approximate the eligible elements and the regulatory capital over time. In a final<lb/> section we compare the use of the Curve Fitting and the Least Squares Monte Carlo<lb/> methodologies in a standard empirical finite sample framework, and stress adapted<lb/> advices for future proxies users.<lb/></div>

	Key words 
	<keyword>Solvency II, ORSA, continuous compliance, parametric proxy, Least<lb/> Squares Monte Carlo, Curve Fitting.<lb/></keyword>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>* Milliman Paris,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>14 rue Pergolèse, 75116 Paris, France<lb/></address> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>† Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1, ISFA,</affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>50 Avenue Tony Garnier, F-69007 Lyon, France<lb/></address>

	‡ Email:
	<email>julien.vedani@etu.univ-lyon1.fr<lb/></email>

	§ Email:
	<email>fabien.ramaharobandro@milliman.com<lb/></email>

	<idno>arXiv:1309.7222v1 [q-fin.RM]</idno> 
	<date>27 Sep 2013</date>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
