<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1334015"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Lie superalgebras of Krichever–Novikov type<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Martin Schlichenmaier<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract. Classically, starting from the Witt and Virasoro algebra im-<lb/>portant examples of Lie superalgebras were constructed. In this write-up<lb/> of a talk presented at the Biaa lowie˙ za meetings we report on results on<lb/> Lie superalgebras of Krichever-Novikov type. These algebras are multi-<lb/>point and higher genus equivalents of the classical algebras. The grading<lb/> in the classical case is replaced by an almost-grading. It is induced by<lb/> a splitting of the set of points, were poles are allowed, into two disjoint<lb/> subsets. With respect to a fixed splitting, or equivalently with respect<lb/> to a fixed almost-grading, it is shown that there is up to rescaling and<lb/> equivalence a unique non-trivial central extension of the Lie superalge-<lb/>bra of Krichever–Novikov type. It is given explicitly.<lb/></div>

	<keywords type="other">Mathematics Subject Classification (2010). Primary: 17B56; Secondary:<lb/> 17B68, 17B65, 17B66, 14H99, 81R10, 81T40.<lb/></keywords>

	<keywords>Keywords. Superalgebra; Krichever–Novikov type algebra; central ex-<lb/>tensions; Witt algebra; Virasoro algebra; Lie algebra cohomology; con-<lb/>formal field theory.<lb/></keywords>

	<note type="grant">Partial support by the Internal Research Project GEOMQ11, University of Luxembourg, <lb/>and by the OPEN scheme of the Fonds National de la Recherche (FNR) with the project <lb/>QUANTMOD O13/5707106 is acknowledged. <lb/></note>

	<byline><docAuthor>Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/></docAuthor></byline>

	<byline><affiliation>University of Luxembourg <lb/>Mathematics Research Unit, FSTC <lb/></affiliation></byline>

	<address>Campus Kirchberg, 6, rue Coudenhove-Kalergi <lb/>L-1359 Luxembourg-Kirchberg, Luxembourg <lb/></address>

	<email>e-mail: martin.schlichenmaier@uni.lu</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
