<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1335582"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>20th IMEKO TC4 International Symposium and<lb/> 18th International Workshop on ADC Modelling and Testing<lb/> Research on Electric and Electronic Measurement for the Economic Upturn<lb/> Benevento, Italy, September 15-17, 2014<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Beam Diagnostics by Infrared Time Resolved<lb/> Detectors<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Alessandro Drago<lb/> 1<lb/> ,Mariangela Cestelli Guidi<lb/> 1<lb/> ,Antonio De Sio<lb/> 2<lb/> ,Augusto Marcelli<lb/> 1<lb/> ,Emanuele Pace<lb/> 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare, Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Via E. Fermi 40, Frascati,<lb/></address>

	<email>alessandro.drago@lnf.infn.it, mariangela.cestelliguidi@lnf.infn.it, augusto.marcelli@lnf.infn.it<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> INAF, Osservatorio Astrofisico di Arcetri,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Largo E. Fermi 5, 50125 Firenze</address>

	<email>, desio@arcetri.astro.it<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> Universita&apos; di Firenze,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Largo E. Fermi 5, 50125 Firenze</address>

	<email>, pace@arcetri.astro.it<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract – Last generation storage rings, both light<lb/> sources and colliders, needs many different diagnostic<lb/> systems to achieve specification goals. Many<lb/> commercially available diagnostics are used to<lb/> measure<lb/> real-time<lb/> accelerators<lb/> performance.<lb/> Nevertheless going towards higher luminosities or<lb/> lower emittance, diagnostics need to be always more<lb/> sophisticated. At DAFNE, the LNF e+/e-F-factory,<lb/> colliding at 1.02 GeV energy in c.m., efforts are<lb/> carrying on to achieve higher luminosities for the<lb/> KLOE detector. Given that a ~20-25% discrepancy<lb/> has been measured between the extrapolated 10<lb/> bunches peak luminosity and the standard fill pattern<lb/> (~100 bunches) one, it is necessary to investigate what<lb/> really happens and why. Letting apart the trivial case<lb/> of measurement non-linearity or saturation in KLOE,<lb/> used as precision luminosity monitor, new diagnostic<lb/> techniques are needed. A new diagnostics tools, based<lb/> on infrared time resolved multi-pixels detector and<lb/> funded by CSNV of INFN is under test at LNF to help<lb/> this analysis.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
