<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1336700"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<idno>arXiv:1410.1182v1 [math.AG]</idno>

	<date>5 Oct 2014<lb/></date>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A GENERALIZED QUOT SCHEME AND MEROMORPHIC VORTICES<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>INDRANIL BISWAS, AJNEET DHILLON, JACQUES HURTUBISE,<lb/> AND RICHARD A. WENTWORTH<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract. Let X be a compact connected Riemann surface. Fix a positive integer r<lb/> and two nonnegative integers d p and d z . Consider all pairs of the form (F , f ), where F<lb/> is a holomorphic vector bundle on X of rank r and degree d z − d p , and<lb/> f : O<lb/> ⊕r<lb/> X −→ F<lb/> is a meromorphic homomorphism which an isomorphism outside a finite subset of X<lb/> and has pole (respectively, zero) of total degree d p (respectively, d z ). Two such pairs<lb/> (F 1 , f 1 ) and (F 2 , f 2 ) are called isomorphic if there is a holomorphic isomorphism of F 1<lb/> with F 2 over X that takes f 1 to f 2 . We construct a natural compactification of the<lb/> moduli space equivalence classes pairs of the above type. The Poincaré polynomial of<lb/> this compactification is computed.<lb/></div>

	<keywords type="classes"> 2000 Mathematics Subject Classification. 14H60, 14D21, 14D23. <lb/></keywords>

	<keywords> Key words and phrases. Generalized Quot scheme, meromorphic vortices, moduli space, Poincaré <lb/>polynomial. <lb/></keywords>

	<byline><affiliation> School of Mathematics, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, <lb/></affiliation></byline>

	<address>Bombay 400005, India <lb/></address>

	<email> E-mail address: indranil@math.tifr.res.in <lb/></email>

	<byline><affiliation> Department of Mathematics, Middlesex College, University of Western Ontario, Lon-<lb/>don,</affiliation></byline>

	<address> ON N6A 5B7, Canada <lb/></address>

	<email> E-mail address: adhill3@uwo.ca <lb/></email>

	<byline><affiliation> Department of Mathematics, McGill University,</affiliation></byline>

	<address> Burnside Hall, 805 Sherbrooke St. <lb/>W., Montreal, Que. H3A 0B9, Canada <lb/></address>

	<email> E-mail address: jacques.hurtubise@mcgill.ca <lb/></email>

	<byline><affiliation> Department of Mathematics, University of Maryland,</affiliation></byline>

	<address> College Park, MD 20742, USA <lb/></address>

	<email> E-mail address: raw@umd.edu </email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
