<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1342197"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Topological invariants in interacting Quantum Spin Hall: a Cluster Perturbation<lb/> Theory approach.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>F. Grandi,<lb/> 1 F. Manghi,<lb/> 1, 2 O. Corradini,<lb/> 3, 1 C.M. Bertoni,<lb/> 1, 2 and A. Bonini<lb/> 4<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Dipartimento di Scienze Fisiche, Informatiche e Matematiche,<lb/> Università di Modena e Reggio Emilia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Via Campi 213/A, I-41125 Modena, Italy<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 CNR -Institute of NanoSciences</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>-S3<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Facultad de Ciencias en Física y Matemáticas, Universidad Autónoma de Chiapas, Ciudad Universitaria, <lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tuxtla Gutiérrez 29050, México<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Università di Bologna,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Via Irnerio 46, I-40126 Bologna, Italy<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">(Dated: February 3, 2015)<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Using Cluster Perturbation Theory we calculate Green&apos;s functions, quasi-particle energies and<lb/> topological invariants for interacting electrons on a 2-D honeycomb lattice, with intrinsic spin-orbit<lb/> coupling and on-site e-e interaction. This allows to define the parameter range (Hubbard U vs<lb/> spin-orbit coupling) where the 2D system behaves as a trivial insulator or Quantum Spin Hall<lb/> insulator. This behavior is confirmed by the existence of gapless quasi-particle states in honeycomb<lb/> ribbons. We have discussed the importance of the cluster symmetry and the effects of the lack of<lb/> full translation symmetry typical of CPT and of most Quantum Cluster approaches. Comments on<lb/> the limits of applicability of the method are also provided.<lb/> PACS numbers: 71.10.Fd, 71.27.+a,73.43-f,73.22-f<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
