<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1343221"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<idno>arXiv:math-ph/0208002v1</idno>

	<date>1 Aug 2002<lb/></date>

	<note type="other">LPTENS-02/39<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>An extension of the HarishChandra-Itzykson-Zuber integral<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>E. Brézin<lb/> a) and S. Hikami<lb/> b)<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a) Laboratoire de Physique Théorique, Ecole Normale Supérieure<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>24 rue Lhomond 75231, Paris Cedex 05, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> b) Department of Basic Sciences,<lb/> University of Tokyo,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Meguro-ku, Komaba, Tokyo 153, Japan<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> The HarishChandra-Itzykson-Zuber integral over the unitary group U(k)<lb/> (β = 2) is present in numerous problems involving Hermitian random ma-<lb/>trices. It is well known that the result is semi-classically exact. This simple<lb/> result does not extend to other symmetry groups, such as the symplectic or<lb/> orthogonal groups. In this article the analysis of this integral is extended<lb/> first to the symplectic group Sp(k) (β=4). There the semi-classical approx-<lb/>imation has to be corrected by a WKB expansion. It turns out that this<lb/> expansion stops after a finite number of terms ; in other words the WKB ap-<lb/>proximation is corrected by a polynomial in the appropriate variables. The<lb/> analysis is based upon new solutions to the heat kernel differential equation.<lb/> We have also investigated arbitrary values of the parameter β, which char-<lb/>acterizes the symmetry group. Closed formulae are derived for arbitrary β<lb/> and k = 3, and also for large β and arbitrary k.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Unité Mixte de Recherche 8549 du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique et<lb/> de l&apos; ´<lb/> Ecole Normale Supérieure.<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
