<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1471-2458-10-696"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

			<reference>Kim et al. BMC Public Health 2010, 10:696 <lb/></reference>
			<ptr type="web">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2458/10/696<lb/></ptr>

			<note type="articleType">RE S E A R C H A R T I C L E<lb/></note>

			<note type="copyright">Open Access<lb/></note>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Geographical variation in cardiovascular<lb/> incidence: results from the British Women's Heart<lb/> and Health Study<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Lois G Kim 1* , Claire Carson 2 , Debbie A Lawlor 3 , Shah Ebrahim 4<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Background: Prevalence of cardiovascular disease (CVD) in women shows regional variations not explained by<lb/> common risk factors. Analysis of CVD incidence will provide insight into whether there is further divergence<lb/> between regions with increasing age.<lb/>
	Methods: Seven-year follow-up data on 2685 women aged 59-80 (mean 69) at baseline from 23 towns in the UK <lb/>
	were available from the British Women’s Heart and Health Study. Time to fatal or non-fatal CVD was analyzed using <lb/>
	Cox regression with adjustment for risk factors, using multiple imputation for missing values.<lb/>
	Results: Compared to South England, CVD incidence is similar in North England (HR 1.05 (95% CI 0.84, 1.31)) and <lb/>
	Scotland (0.93 (0.68, 1.27)), but lower in Midlands/Wales (0.85 (0.64, 1.12)). Event severity influenced regional <lb/>
	variation, with South England showing lower fatal incident CVD than other regions, but higher non-fatal incident <lb/>
	CVD. Kaplan-Meier plots suggested that regional divergence in CVD occurred before baseline (before mean <lb/>
	baseline age of 69).<lb/>
	Conclusions: In women, regional differences in CVD early in adult life do not further diverge in later life. This may <lb/>
	be due to regional differences in early detection, survivorship of women entering the study, or event severity. <lb/>
	Targeting health care resources for CVD by geographic variation may not be appropriate for older age-groups.<lb/></div>

	<div type="introduction">Background<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
