<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1471-2296-11-40"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>

	<reference>Byrne et al. BMC Family Practice 2010, 11:40<lb/></reference>
	<ptr type="web">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2296/11/40<lb/></ptr>

	

	
			<note type="copyright">Open Access<lb/></note>
			<note type="articleType">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>
	

	
			<note type="other">BioMed Central<lb/></note>
	

			<note type="copyright">© 2010 Byrne et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons<lb/> Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in<lb/> any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<lb/> </note> 
			<note type="articleType">Research article<lb/></note>
		<docTitle>	
			<titlePart>General practitioner views about discussing sexual<lb/> issues with patients with coronary heart disease: a<lb/> national survey in Ireland<lb/></titlePart>	
		</docTitle>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Molly Byrne* 1 , Sally Doherty 1 , Hannah M McGee 2 and Andrew W Murphy 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract Background: Sexual problems are common among people with coronary heart disease and can adversely affect<lb/> patients' quality of life. GPs are ideally placed to deal with these problems. Research suggests that GPs are reluctant to<lb/> address sexual problems but little is known about what currently takes place in practice. The aim of this study was to<lb/> examine GPs' self-reported behaviour and attitudes to discussing sexual problems with people with coronary heart<lb/> disease.<lb/> Method: Design: A cross-sectional survey which administered 230 postal questionnaires to a nationally representative,<lb/> stratified random sample of GPs in the Republic of Ireland. GPs were asked about current practice, knowledge,<lb/> awareness and confidence in dealing with sexual problems, barriers to addressing sexual problems, and about<lb/> improving services in this area.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
