<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1471-2296-11-40"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Byrne et al. BMC Family Practice 2010, 11:40<lb/></reference>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2296/11/40<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="doctype">Open Access<lb/></note>

	<note type="doctype">RESEARCH ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<publisher>BioMed Central<lb/></publisher>

	<note type="copyright">© 2010 Byrne et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons<lb/> Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in<lb/> any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<lb/></note>

	<note type="doctype">Research article<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>General practitioner views about discussing sexual<lb/> issues with patients with coronary heart disease: a<lb/> national survey in Ireland<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Molly Byrne* 1 , Sally Doherty 1 , Hannah M McGee 2 and Andrew W Murphy 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: Sexual problems are common among people with coronary heart disease and can adversely affect<lb/> patients&apos; quality of life. GPs are ideally placed to deal with these problems. Research suggests that GPs are reluctant to<lb/> address sexual problems but little is known about what currently takes place in practice. The aim of this study was to<lb/> examine GPs&apos; self-reported behaviour and attitudes to discussing sexual problems with people with coronary heart<lb/> disease.<lb/> Method: Design: A cross-sectional survey which administered 230 postal questionnaires to a nationally representative,<lb/> stratified random sample of GPs in the Republic of Ireland. GPs were asked about current practice, knowledge,<lb/> awareness and confidence in dealing with sexual problems, barriers to addressing sexual problems, and about<lb/> improving services in this area.<lb/> Results: Responses were available for 61 GPs (27% response rate). Seventy percent of GPs reported that they rarely or<lb/> never discussed sexual problems with coronary patients. While all GPs believed addressing sexual problems was<lb/> important, many GPs reported lacking awareness, knowledge and confidence in addressing sexual problems. The main<lb/> barriers were lack of time, feeling the patient wasn&apos;t ready and lack of training in the area. GPs wanted more training<lb/> and guidelines for practice.<lb/> Conclusions: There is currently no standardised protocol for GPs for dealing with sexual problems among coronary<lb/> patients. Awareness of these issues appears to be low among GPs. Services could be improved by developing practice<lb/> guidelines for brief, effective actions or assessments, providing training in the area and improving information<lb/> resources and support services for referral.<lb/></div>

	* Correspondence:
	<email>molly.byrne@nuigalway.ie<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received: 10 September 2009 Accepted: 25 May 2010<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>25 May 2010<lb/></date>

	This article is available from: 
	<ptr type="web">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2296/11/40<lb/> </ptr>

	<note type="copyright">© 2010 Byrne et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.<lb/> This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<lb/></note>

	<reference>BMC Family Practice 2010, 11:40</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
