<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="origin15283803433844136683"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Gior Neuropsich Età Evol 2006;26:315-321<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>La spasticità: il trattamento<lb/> farmacologico. L&apos;uso della tossina<lb/> botulinica e trattamento riabilitativo<lb/> specifico *<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The spasticity: farmacological treatment. The use of the botulin<lb/> toxin and specific rehabilitative treatment<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>L. TORNETTA, M. MARTIELLI, R. CARTELLO, M. MELILLO, L. OBINO,<lb/> L. CLARICI, T. BORRO, B. BASSI, R. RIGARDETTO<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Dipartimento a Direzione Universitaria di NPI, A.S.O. O.I.R.M.-S. ANNA,<lb/> Università di Torino<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

    PAROLE CHIAVE.
	<keywords>-Spasticità -Tossina botulinica -Trattamento riabilitativo -Paralisi<lb/> cerebrale infantile (PCI)<lb/></keywords>

	KEY WORDS.
    <keywords>-Spasticity -Botulin toxin -Rehabilitative treatment -Cerebral palsy</keywords>

    Summary<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Introduction. The spasticity is a complex movement disorder in which several neuro-<lb/>physiological circuits are involved. This complexity added to the rheological muscle&apos;s modi-<lb/>fications make it difficult to understand the functional meaning of the symptom. In cerebral<lb/> palsy, in fact, spasticity can also be seen as positive factor and used in a functional manner.<lb/> Before choosing a therapeutic strategy it is important to understand the functional meaning<lb/> of spasticity for that child. Nowadays pharmacological treatments include systemic, intrate-<lb/>cal and local approaches.<lb/> Methods and Materials. Our experience is focused on the use of the botulin toxin. We<lb/> explain clinical assessment and protocol for post-inoculation on rehabilitative treatment.<lb/> Results. Results vary depending on the severity of the disability and on the age of pa-<lb/>tients, on a correct identification of muscles to inoculate, on an adequate dose of toxin and<lb/> most of all on post-inoculation rehabilitative treatment.<lb/> Conclusions. In our experience post-inoculation rehabilitative treatment can influence<lb/> the outcome especially from a functional point of view. Nevertheless, there aren&apos;t enough sta-<lb/>tistical evidence yet either to confirm or to refute advantages of using BT-A in cerebral palsy.<lb/></div>

	Le richieste di estratti vanno inviate:

    <byline>
    <docAuthor>dott.ssa Lorella Tornetta</docAuthor>
    </byline>

    <byline>
	<affiliation>-Dipartimento di NPI, A.S.O. O.I.R.M.-S.<lb/> ANNA.</affiliation>
	</byline>

    <address>P.za Polonia 94 -10136 Torino</address>

    -E-mail:
	<email>lorella.tornetta@torton.net<lb/></email>

	* Comunicazione svolta al <meeting>Corso Satellite su &quot;Riabilitazione e Trattamento Farmacologico nei disturbi<lb/> neuropsichici del bambino&quot;, a cura della Sezione di Riabilitazione della SINPIA. Napoli, 7-10 Dicembre<lb/> 2005.</meeting>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
