<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="154._10.1.1.55.9160"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Emerging Opportunities for Theoretical Computer Science<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Alfred V. Aho<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Columbia University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>David S. Johnson<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>AT &amp; T Research<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Richard M. Karp (Chair)<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Washington<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>S. Rao Kosaraju<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Johns Hopkins University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Catherine C. McGeoch<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Amherst College<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Christos H. Papadimitriou<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of California at Berkeley<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Pavel Pevzner<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Southern California<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<date>October 15, 1996</date>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">The principles underlying this report can be summarized as follows:<lb/> 1. A strong theoretical foundation is vital to computer science.<lb/> 2. Theory can be enriched by practice.<lb/> 3. Practice can be enriched by theory.<lb/> 4. If we consider (2) and (3), the value, impact, and funding of theory will be enhanced.<lb/> In order to achieve a greater synergy between theory and application, and to sustain and expand on<lb/> the remarkable successes of Theory of Computing (TOC), we consider it essential to increase the impact<lb/> of theory on key application areas. This requires additional nancial resources in support of theory, and<lb/> closer interaction between theoreticians and researchers in other areas of computer science and in other<lb/> disciplines.<lb/> The report does not make a detailed assessment of the overall state of theoretical computer science<lb/> or fully chronicle the achievements of this eld. Instead, it has the speci c objective of recommending<lb/> ways to harness these remarkable achievements for the solution of challenging problems emerging from<lb/> new developments such as the information superhighway.<lb/> Section 1 describes the events leading up to this report and delineates the report&apos;s objectives. Section<lb/> 2 establishes the context for the report. It traces the history of TOC, describes the impact that TOC has<lb/> achieved in the areas of core theory and fundamental algorithms, points out the di erences between these<lb/> areas and application-oriented theory, and calls for an intensi ed e ort to bring the methods of TOC<lb/> to bear on applications. It then goes on to de ne the four main categories into which our recommen-<lb/>dations fall: building bridges between theory and applications, algorithm engineering, communication,<lb/> and education. Section 3 discusses some speci c opportunities for stimulating interactions between TOC<lb/> and applied areas. Section 4 proposes an applied research initiative, Information Access in a Globally<lb/> Distributed Environment, which identi es an exciting current technological area that we believe presents<lb/> challenging opportunities for excellent theoretical work. Section 5 proposes a second applied research<lb/> initiative, The Algorithmic Stockroom, that would exploit and extend the body of theoretical knowledge<lb/> in the eld of algorithms. Section 6 proposes a broadening in graduate education with two purposes<lb/> in mind: to better prepare theoreticians to interact creatively with practitioners, and to provide future<lb/> practitioners with the background they will need to bene t from this exchange.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
