<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1557.full"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Annals of Botany 103: 1557– 1566, 2009<lb/></reference>
			<idno>doi:10.1093/aob/mcp032,</idno> <ptr type="web">available online at www.aob.oxfordjournals.org</ptr>
			
			<note type="articleType">VIEWPOINT<lb/></note>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Using phenotypic manipulations to study multivariate selection<lb/> of
					floral trait associations<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Diane R. Campbell*<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Department of Ecology &amp; Evolutionary Biology, University of
					California,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Irvine, CA 92697, USA<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received: 27 October 2008 Returned for revision: 3 December 2008
				Accepted: 8 January 2009</note> <date>Published electronically: 14 February 2009<lb/></date>

			<div type="abstract">Background A basic theme in the study of plant –pollinator
				interactions is that pollinators select not just for<lb/> single floral traits, but
				for associations of traits. Responses of pollinators to sets of traits are inherent
				in the<lb/> idea of pollinator syndromes. In its most extreme form, selection on a
				suite of traits can take the form of correla-<lb/>tional selection, in which a
				response to one trait depends on the value of another, thereby favouring floral
				inte-<lb/>gration. Despite the importance of selection for combinations of traits in
				the evolution of flowers, evidence is<lb/> relatively sparse and relies mostly on
				observational approaches.<lb/> Scope Here, methods for measuring selection on
				multivariate suites of floral traits are presented, and the studies<lb/> to date are
				reviewed. It is argued that phenotypic manipulations present a powerful, but rarely
				used, approach to<lb/> teasing apart the separate and combined effects of particular
				traits. The approach is illustrated with data from<lb/> studies of alpine plants in
				Colorado and New Zealand, and recommendations are made about several features<lb/>
				of the design of such experiments.<lb/> Conclusions Phenotypic manipulations of two
				or more traits in combination provide a direct way of testing for<lb/> selection of
				floral trait associations. Such experiments will be particularly valuable if rooted
				in hypotheses about<lb/> differences between types of pollinators and tied to a
				proposed evolutionary history.<lb/></div>

			<keywords>Key words: Colour, correlational selection, experiment, floral integration,
				multivariate selection, phenotypic<lb/> manipulation, pollination syndrome,
				pollinator visitation.<lb/></keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
