<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1678-7757-jaos-16-06-0380"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	T ABSTRACT<lb/> 

	www.fob.usp.br/jaos or www.scielo.br/jaos<lb/> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPIC STUDY OF HYPERCEMENTOSIS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Bethânia Camargo PINHEIRO 1 , Tiago Novaes PINHEIRO 1 , Ana Lúcia Alvarez CAPELOZZA 2 , Alberto CONSOLARO 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1-DDS, Master&apos;s degree in Oral Pathology, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bauru, SP, Brazil.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2-DDS, MSc, PhD, Associate Professor, Discipline of Radiology, Department of Stomatology, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bauru, SP, Brazil.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3-DDS, MSc, PhD, Full Professor, Discipline of Oral Pathology, Department of Stomatology, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bauru, SP, Brazil.<lb/></address>

	Corresponding address:

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dra. Bethânia Camargo Pinheiro</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	-
	<address>Rua Garcia Braga, 126, Centro, 18940-000, São Pedro do Turvo, SP, Brasil.<lb/> </address>

	Phone:
	<phone>+55-14-3377-1190</phone> -e-mail:
	<email>bethaniacp@hotmail.com<lb/></email>

	Received:
	<reference>February 22, 2008 -Modification: April 18, 2008 -Accepted: May 08, 2008<lb/></reference>

	<div type="abstract">he purpose of this study was to evaluate morphological characteristics of teeth with hypercementosis that are relevant to endodontic<lb/> practice. Twenty-eight extracted teeth with hypercementosis had their root apexes analyzed by scanning electron microscopy (SEM).<lb/> The teeth were divided according to tooth groups and type of hypercementosis. The following aspects were examined under SEM:<lb/> the contour and regularity of the root surface; presence of resorption; presence and number of apical foramina, and the diameter of<lb/> the main foramen. The progression of club shape hypercementosis was directly associated with the presence of foramina and apical<lb/> foramen obstruction. Cases of focal hypercementosis presented foramina on the surface, even when sidelong located in the root.<lb/> Circular cementum hyperplasia form was present in 2 out of 3 residual roots, which was the highest proportion among the tooth<lb/> types. The detection of a large number of foramina in the apical third of teeth with hypercementosis or even the possible existence<lb/> of apical foramen obliteration contributes to understand the difficulties faced during endodontic treatment of these cases.<lb/></div>

	Key Words: 
	<keywords>Hypercementosis. Root canal. Morphology. Endodontics.<lb/></keywords>
	
	<reference>J Appl Oral Sci. 2008;16(6):380-4</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
