<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="171._download"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">c IASTED/ACTA Press (Anaheim/Calgary/Zürich),</note>

	<reference>pp. 144-148, Oct. 1996.</reference>

	<idno>[ISBN: 0-88986-213-3]<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>HPF and MPI Implementation of the NAS Parallel Benchmarks<lb/> Supported by Integrated Program Engineering Tools<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Christian Clémençon<lb/> Karsten M. Decker<lb/> Vaibhav R. Deshpande<lb/> Akiyoshi Endo<lb/> Josef Fritscher<lb/> Paulo A. R. Lorenzo<lb/> Norio Masuda<lb/> Andreas Müller<lb/> Roland Rühl<lb/> William Sawyer<lb/> Brian J. N. Wylie<lb/> Frank Zimmermann<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Centro Svizzero di Calcolo Scientifico (CSCS/SCSC) and<lb/> NEC European Supercomputer Systems,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Swiss Branch<lb/> CH-6928 Manno, Switzerland<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>http://www.cscs.ch/Official/Project CSCS-NEC.html<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	Abstract:
	<div type="abstract">High Performance Fortran (HPF) compilers<lb/> and communication libraries with the standardized Mes-<lb/>sage Passing Interface (MPI) are becoming widely avail-<lb/>able, easing the development of portable parallel appli-<lb/>cations on distributed-memory parallel processor systems.<lb/> The recently developed Annai tool environment supports<lb/> programming, debugging and tuning of both HPF-and<lb/> MPI-based applications. Considering code development<lb/> and subsequent maintenance time to be as important as ul-<lb/>timate performance, we address how sequential Fortran-77<lb/> versions of the familiar NAS Parallel Benchmark kernels<lb/> can be expediently parallelized with appropriate tool sup-<lb/>port. While automatic parallelization of scientific applica-<lb/>tions written in traditional sequential languages remains<lb/> largely impractical, Annai provides users with high-level<lb/> language extensions and integrated program engineering<lb/> support tools. In this paper, Annai support is demon-<lb/>strated primarily focusing on the MG (multigrid) kernel,<lb/> with complementary examples selected from the other four<lb/> kernels. Respectable performance and good scalability<lb/> in most cases are obtained with this straightforward par-<lb/>allelization strategy, even without recourse to platform-<lb/>specific optimizations or major program transformations.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>HPF &amp; MPI parallelization; parallel program<lb/> engineering tools.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
