<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1755-8166-2-3"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<publisher>BioMed Central<lb/> </publisher>

	<page>Page 1 of 11<lb/></page> 

	(page number not for citation purposes)<lb/> 

	<title level="j">Molecular Cytogenetics<lb/> </title>

	<note type="doctype">Open Access<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="doctype">Case report<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Meiotic and mitotic behaviour of a ring/deleted chromosome 22 in<lb/> human embryos determined by preimplantation genetic diagnosis<lb/> for a maternal carrier<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Anna Mantzouratou* 1,2 , Anastasia Mania 1 , Marianna Apergi 1 , Sarah Laver 2 ,<lb/> Paul Serhal 2 and JDA Delhanty 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Address:
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 UCL Centre for PGD, Institute for Women&apos;s Health, University College London,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>86-96 Chenies Mews, London, WC1E-6HX, UK,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 The<lb/> Assisted Conception Unit, University College Hospital, Eastman Dental Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gray&apos;s Inn Road, London, WC1X 8LD, UK and<lb/></address>

	Email: Anna Mantzouratou* -
	<email>a.mantzouratou@ucl.ac.uk</email>

	; Anastasia Mania -
	<email>anastasia.mania@ucl.ac.uk</email>

	;<lb/> Marianna Apergi -
	<email>m_apergi@yahoo.co.uk</email>

	; Sarah Laver -
	<email>Sarah.Laver@uclh.nhs.uk</email>

	; Paul Serhal -
	<email>paul.serhal@uclh.nhs.uk</email>

	;<lb/> JDA Delhanty -
	<email>j.delhanty@ucl.ac.uk<lb/></email>

	* Corresponding author 
	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: Ring chromosomes are normally associated with developmental anomalies and are<lb/> rarely inherited. An exception to this rule is provided by deletion/ring cases. We were provided<lb/> with a unique opportunity to investigate the meiotic segregation at oogenesis in a woman who is a<lb/> carrier of a deleted/ring 22 chromosome. The couple requested preimplantation genetic diagnosis<lb/> (PGD) following the birth of a son with a mosaic karyotype.<lb/> The couple underwent two cycles of PGD. Studies were performed on lymphocytes, single<lb/> embryonic cells removed from 3 day-old embryos and un-transferred embryos. Analysis was<lb/> carried out using fluorescence in situ hybridisation (FISH) with specific probe sets in two rounds<lb/> of hybridization.<lb/> Results: In total, 12 embryos were biopsied, and follow up information was obtained for 10<lb/> embryos. No embryos were completely normal or balanced for chromosome 22 by day 5. There<lb/> was only one embryo diagnosed as balanced of 12 biopsied but that accumulated postzygotic errors<lb/> by day 5. Three oocytes apparently had a balanced chromosome 22 complement but all had the<lb/> deleted and the ring 22 and not the intact chromosome 22. After fertilisation all the embryos<lb/> accumulated postzygotic errors for chromosome 22.<lb/> Conclusion: The study of the preimplantation embryos in this case provided a rare and significant<lb/> chance to study and understand the phenomena associated with this unusual type of anomaly during<lb/> meiosis and in the earliest stages of development. It is the first reported PGD attempt for a ring<lb/> chromosome abnormality.<lb/></div>

	Published:
	<date>23 January 2009<lb/></date>

	<reference>Molecular Cytogenetics 2009, 2:3</reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1186/1755-8166-2-3<lb/></idno>

	<note type="submission">Received: 3 December 2008<lb/> Accepted: 23 January 2009<lb/></note>

	This article is available from:
	<ptr type="web">http://www.molecularcytogenetics.org/content/2/1/3<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="copyright">© 2009 Mantzouratou et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.<lb/> This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0),<lb/> which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Molecular Cytogenetics 2009, 2:3<lb/></reference>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.molecularcytogenetics.org/content/2/1/3</ptr>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
