<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="18._10.1.1.76.8297"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Extraction of Keyphrases from Text:<lb/> Evaluation of Four Algorithms<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>P. Turney<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<date>October 23, 1997<lb/></date>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>National Research<lb/> Council Canada<lb/> Institute for<lb/> Information Technology<lb/> Conseil national<lb/> de recherches Canada<lb/> Institut de technologie<lb/> de l&apos;information<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	ERB-1051<lb/>

	<note type="copyright">© Copyright 1997 by<lb/> National Research Council of Canada<lb/> Permission is granted to quote short excerpts and to reproduce figures and tables from this report,<lb/> provided that the source of such material is fully acknowledged.<lb/></note>

	Extraction of Keyphrases from Text: Evaluation of Four Algorithms<lb/> 
	ERB-1051<lb/>
	
	<date>October 23, 1997</date>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">This report presents an empirical evaluation of four algorithms for automatically extracting<lb/> keywords and keyphrases from documents. The four algorithms are compared using five dif-<lb/>ferent collections of documents. For each document, we have a target set of keyphrases, which<lb/> were generated by hand. The target keyphrases were generated for human readers; they were<lb/> not tailored for any of the four keyphrase extraction algorithms. Each of the algorithms was<lb/> evaluated by the degree to which the algorithm&apos;s keyphrases matched the manually generated<lb/> keyphrases. The four algorithms were (1) the AutoSummarize feature in Microsoft&apos;s Word 97,<lb/> (2) an algorithm based on Eric Brill&apos;s part-of-speech tagger, (3) the Summarize feature in Ver-<lb/>ity&apos;s Search 97, and (4) NRC&apos;s Extractor algorithm. For all five document collections, NRC&apos;s<lb/> Extractor yields the best match with the manually generated keyphrases. 1<lb/> </div>

	1. Introduction<lb/> 

	Turney 

	<page>1</page>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
