<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="184._10.1.1.16.8869"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Observational Uncertainty in Plan Recognition Among Interacting Robots<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Marcus J. Huber<lb/> Edmund H. Durfee<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Distributed Intelligent Agents Group (DIAG)<lb/> Arti cial Intelligence Laboratory<lb/> The University of Michigan<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109-2110<lb/></address>

	<email>marcush@engin.umich.edu</email>

	,
	<email>durfee@engin.umich.edu<lb/></email>

	<date>May 16, 1994</date>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Plan recognition is the process of observing another agent&apos;s behavior(s) and inferring what, and<lb/> possibly why, the agent is acting as it is. Plan recognition becomes a very important means of acquiring<lb/> such information about other agents in situations and domains where explicit communication is either<lb/> very costly, dangerous, or impossible. Performing plan recognition in a physical domain (i.e. the real<lb/> world) forces the world&apos;s ubiquitous uncertainty upon the observing agent because of the necessity to<lb/> use real sensors to make the observations. We have developed a multiple resolution, hierarchical plan<lb/> recognition system to coordinate the motion of two interacting mobile robots. Uncertainty arises in the<lb/> system from dead reckoning errors that accumulate while the robots are moving, as well as by errors<lb/> in the computer vision system that is used to detect the other agent&apos;s behaviors. Based upon belief<lb/> networks, the plan recognition system gracefully degrades in performance as the level of uncertainty<lb/> about observations increase.<lb/></div>

	<note type="funding">This research was sponsored in part by the NSF under grants IRI-9015423, IRI-9010645, and IRI-9158473, and by DARPA<lb/> under contract DAAE-07-92-C-R012.</note>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
