<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="19008482v1.full"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Inconsistent Addiction Treatment for Patients Undergoing Cardiac Surgery for Injection<lb/> Drug Use-Associated Infective endocarditis<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Max Jordan Nguemeni Tiako, MS; 1 Seong Hong; BS 1 Syed Usman Bin Mahmood MBBS; 1<lb/> Makoto Mori, MD, 1 Abeel Mangi, MD, 1 James Yun, MD, PhD, 2 Manisha Juthani-Mehta, MD,<lb/> 3,4 Arnar Geirsson, MD 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Section of Cardiac Surgery, Department of Surgery, Yale University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New<lb/> Haven, CT<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery, Cleveland clinic,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cleveland, OH<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Section of Infectious Diseases, Department of Internal Medicine, Yale University School of<lb/> Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New Haven, CT<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Epidemiology of Microbial Diseases, Yale School of Public Health,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New Haven, CT<lb/></address>

	Authors report no conflict of interests. 
	<note type="funding">This study was funded by the Horace Stansel Jr<lb/> Research Fund.<lb/> IRB protocol ID: 2000020356, approval date: 3/2/2017<lb/> </note>

	Word count: 3085<lb/> 

	Key words: 
	<keywords>Cardiac surgery, endocarditis, opioid epidemic, addiction<lb/></keywords> 

	Corresponding author:<lb/>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Arnar Geirsson, MD<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Associate Professor of Surgery<lb/> Section of Cardiac Surgery<lb/> Yale School of Medicine<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>BB204, 330 Cedar Street<lb/> P.O. Box 208039<lb/> New Haven, CT<lb/></address>

	Business phone: 
	<phone>203-785-6214<lb/></phone> 

	Fax: 203-785-3346<lb/>

	Email:
	<email>arnar.geirsson@yale.edu<lb/></email>

	Abstract:<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Introduction:<lb/>Cases of injection drug use-related infective endocarditis (IDU-IE) requiring surgery are<lb/> rising in the setting of the current U.S. opioid epidemic. We thus aimed to determine the nature<lb/> of addiction interventions in the perioperative period.<lb/> Methods:<lb/> This is a retrospective review of surgical IDU-IE from 2011 to 2016 at a tertiary care<lb/> center in New Haven, Connecticut. The data collected included substances consumed<lb/> recreationally, consultations by social work (SW), psychiatry, pharmacotherapy for addiction,<lb/> and evidence of enrollment in a drug rehabilitation program upon discharge.<lb/> Among patients with active drug use (ADU), we compared the 24-month survival of<lb/> those who received at least one form of addiction intervention to that of those who did not.<lb/> Results:<lb/> Forty-two patients (75%) had active drug use. Among them, 22 used heroin. Forty-one<lb/> patients (73.2%) saw SW, 17 (30.4%) saw psychiatry; 14 (25%) saw neither SW nor psychiatry.<lb/> Twenty-one patients (37.5%) received methadone, 6 (10.7%) received buprenorphine, 1<lb/> (0.02%) received naltrexone; 26 (46.4%) did not receive any pharmacotherapy. Fifteen patients<lb/> (26.8%) attended a drug rehabilitation program, 13 (86.7%) of whom had seen SW and 8 (53%)<lb/> psychiatry. Among patients with ADU, there was no statistically significant difference in<lb/> survival between those who received at least one intervention and those who did not (p=0.1 by<lb/> log rank).<lb/> Conclusion:<lb/> Addiction interventions are deployed inconsistently for patients with surgical IDU-IE.<lb/> Untreated substance use disorder and recurrent endocarditis are the leading cause of death in this<lb/> population. Studying best-practices for perioperative interventions in IDU-IE and establishing<lb/> protocols are of the upmost importance.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
