<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="192377v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	(1) Overview<lb/> Title<lb/> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A random dot kinematogram for online visual psychophysics<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	Paper Authors<lb/>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1. Rajananda, Sivananda;<lb/> 2. Lau, Hakwan;<lb/> 3. Odegaard, Brian<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Paper Author Roles and Affiliations<lb/> 1. Designed software; coded software; tested software; uploaded software to<lb/> GitHub &amp; CodePen; 
	Affiliation: 
	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of California--Los Angeles<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	2. Designed software<lb/> 
	Affiliations:
	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of California--Los Angeles<lb/> Brain Research Institute (UCLA)<lb/> Hong Kong University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	3. Designed software; proofread code; tested software<lb/> 
	Affiliations:
	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of California--Los Angeles</affiliation>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Online experiments using visual stimuli have become increasingly common in recent<lb/> years, but many frequently-used stimuli in visual psychophysical experiments have<lb/> yet to be developed for web-based platforms. Here, we introduce the first open-<lb/>access random-dot kinematogram (RDK) for use in web browsers. This fully-<lb/>customizable RDK offers options to implement several different types of noise<lb/> (random position, random walk, random direction) and parameters to control aperture<lb/> shape, coherence level, the number of dots, and many other features. We include<lb/> links to commented JavaScript code for easy implementation in online experiments,<lb/> as well as an example of how this stimulus can be integrated as a plugin with an<lb/> online experimental library (jsPsych).</div>

	Keywords<lb/>
	<keyword>Random dot kinematogram, random dot motion, moving dot stimulus, online<lb/> experiments, visual psychophysics, visual stimuli, JavaScript, jsPsych</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
