<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="19657CE640C02491B875DC0F1515201284CFFEF5"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The role of hyaluronic acid in protecting<lb/> surface-active phospholipids from lysis by<lb/> exogenous phospholipase A 2<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>D. W. Nitzan, U. Nitzan 1 , P. Dan 1 and S. Yedgar 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, The Hebrew<lb/> University±Hadassah School of Dental Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Jerusalem</address>

	and

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of Biochemistry, Hadassah University Hospital,<lb/> The Hebrew University±Hadassah Medical School,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Jerusalem, Israel</address>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background. This in vitro study aimed to elucidate the extent and kind of involvement<lb/> of hyaluronic acid (HA) in the currently accepted view of synovial joint lubrication, in which<lb/> surface-active phospholipids (SAPL) constitute the main boundary lubricant. The integrity<lb/> of SAPL is apparently threatened by the lysing activity of phospholipase A 2 (PLA 2 ).<lb/> Methods. The effects of increasing concentrations of HA degraded by free radicals and<lb/> non-degraded HA on the lysing activity of PLA 2 were examined in vitro. Liposomes (lipid model<lb/> membrane) containing phosphatidylcholine (PC) were used as the substrate, on the assumption<lb/> that they are appropriate representatives of SAPL.<lb/> Results. HA adhered to the phospholipid membrane (liposomes), inhibiting their lysis by<lb/> PLA 2 . However, in its degraded form, HA not only failed to inhibit PLA 2 -lysing activity, but<lb/> accelerated it.<lb/> Conclusions. It is reasonable to assume that HA plays an important indirect role in the steady<lb/> state of the boundary lubrication process of joints by protecting SAPL from being lysed by<lb/> PLA 2 . However, as excessive loading generates free radicals within the joint (among other<lb/> effects), the HA that is degraded in this way is incapable of protecting SAPL from lysis by PLA 2 .<lb/> When the rate of degradation exceeds that of synthesis, there will be insuf®cient replacement<lb/> of HA anduor SAPL, resulting in denudation of the articular surfaces. These are then exposed<lb/> to increasing friction, and hence increased danger of degenerative joint changes.<lb/></div>

	KEY WORDS:
	<keyword>Hyaluronic acid, Lubrication, Phospholipase A 2 , Surface-active phospholipids,<lb/> Synovial joint, Degenerative joint changes.<lb/></keyword>

	Correspondence to:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>D. W. Nitzan,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Oral and<lb/> Maxillofacial Surgery, Faculty of Dental Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P.O.B. 12272,<lb/> Jerusalem 91120, Israel.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Submitted 14 January 2000; revised version accepted 9 October<lb/> 2000.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Rheumatology 2001;40:336±340<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">ß 2001 British Society for Rheumatology</note>

	<page>336</page>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
