<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="1A276C42D47BD849B5786969218F5211C2C65A02"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	Infancy<lb/> The first year of life.<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The impact of differential antiviral<lb/> immunity in children and adults<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Andrew J. Prendergast 1 , Paul Klenerman 2 and Philip J. R. Goulder 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract |
	<div type="abstract">The course of immune maturation has evolved to favour survival at each<lb/> stage of development in early life. Fetal and neonatal immune adaptations facilitate<lb/> intrauterine survival and provide early postnatal protection against extracellular<lb/> pathogens, but they leave infants susceptible to intracellular pathogens such as viruses<lb/> that are acquired perinatally. This Review focuses on three such pathogens -HIV,<lb/> hepatitis B virus and cytomegalovirus -and relates the differential impact of these<lb/> infections in infants and adults to the antiviral immunity that is generated at different<lb/> ages. A better understanding of age-specific antiviral immunity may inform the<lb/> development of integrated prevention, treatment and vaccine strategies to minimize<lb/> the global disease burden resulting from these infections.</div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Centre for Paediatrics,<lb/> Blizard Institute, Queen Mary<lb/> University of London,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Newark<lb/> Street, London E1 2AT, UK.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> NIHR Biomedical Research<lb/> Centre and Nuffield<lb/> Department of Medicine,<lb/> University of Oxford,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Peter Medawar Building,<lb/> South Parks Road,<lb/> Oxford OX1 3SY, UK.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> Department of Paediatrics,<lb/> University of Oxford,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Peter Medawar Building,<lb/> South Parks Road,<lb/> Oxford OX1 3SY, UK.<lb/></address>

	Correspondence to P.J.R.G.<lb/> 
	e-mail: 
	<email>philip.goulder@<lb/> paediatrics.ox.ac.uk<lb/></email>

	<idno>doi:10.1038/nri3277<lb/></idno>

	<note type="doctype">R E V I E W S<lb/></note>
	
	<page>636</page> 

	<reference>| SEPTEMBER 2012 | VOLUME 12<lb/></reference>
	www.nature.com/reviews/immunol<lb/>

	<note type="copyright">© 2012 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
