<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="2001_02928"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	P JINST<lb/> CHEF<lb/> -C<lb/> H<lb/> E<lb/> F<lb/> -N<lb/> F<lb/> , J<lb/>
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Performance of the ALICE electromagnetic calorimeters in<lb/> LHC Runs 1 and 2 and upgrade projects<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>D. Blau</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	on behalf of 

	<note type="group">ALICE collaboration<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>NRC &quot;Kurchatov institute&quot;,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>123182 Kurchatov sq. 1, Moscow, Russia<lb/></address>

	E-mail:
	<email>dmitry.blau@cern.ch<lb/></email>

	A<lb/> : 
	<div type="abstract">ALICE (A Large Ion Collider Experiment) at the LHC is designed for studies of nuclear<lb/> matter at extreme temperatures and energy densities, so called Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP). Two<lb/> detectors for measurements of electromagnetic signals, high-granularity photon spectrometer PHOS<lb/> and large acceptance electromagnetic calorimeter EMCal/DCal, are incorporated into the ALICE<lb/> apparatus. In order to enhance the data sample of the high-energy part of the spectra, a dedicated<lb/> triggers on high energetic photons or jets are used. High precision measurements of neutral mesons<lb/> require fine energy and timing calibrations. Photon signal purity is improved using dedicated<lb/> photon PID criteria based on cluster shape and anti-track matching with the ALICE central tracking<lb/> system, as well as a special detector located in front of PHOS called CPV.<lb/> PHOS and EMCal participated in LHC Run 1 (2009-2013) and Run 2 (2015-2018) during data<lb/> taking periods of pp, p-Pb and Pb-Pb collisions. We give an overview of their performance in Runs<lb/> 1 and 2 in low and high multiplicity environments as well as the upgrade plans for future LHC runs.<lb/></div>

	K<lb/> : 
	<keyword>Performance of High Energy Physics Detectors, Calorimeters, Heavy-ion detectors<lb/></keyword>

	<idno>arXiv:2001.02928v1 [hep-ex]</idno>

	<date>9 Jan 2020</date>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
