<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="2019.12.17.880526v1.full"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A novel totivirus alters gene expression and vacuolar morphology in Malassezia cells<lb/> and induces a TLR3-mediated inflammatory immune response<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Minji Park a , Yong-Joon Cho b , Donggyu Kim c , Chul-Su Yang c,d , Shi Mun Lee e , Thomas L.<lb/> Dawson Jr. e,f , Satoshi Nakamizo e , Kenji Kabashima e,g , Yang Won Lee h,i , Won Hee Jung a,#</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a<lb/> Department of Systems Biotechnology, Chung-Ang University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Anseong, 17546, Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b The Research Institute of Basic Sciences, Seoul National University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seoul, 08826, Korea</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c<lb/> Department of Molecular and Life Science, Hanyang University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Ansan 15588, Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>d Department of Bionano Technology, Hanyang University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seoul, 04673, Korea</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>e<lb/> Singapore Immunology Network (SIgN) and Skin Research Institute of Singapore (SRIS),<lb/> Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR), </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>8A Biomedical Grove,<lb/> IMMUNOS Building, Biopolis, 138648 Singapore<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>f Center for Cell Death, Injury &amp; Regeneration, Departments of Drug Discovery &amp;<lb/> Biomedical Sciences and Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Biology, Medical University of South<lb/> Carolina,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Charleston, SC, 29425, United States<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>g Department of Dermatology Kyoto University Graduate School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kyoto, 606-<lb/>8507, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>h Department of Dermatology, School of Medicine, Konkuk University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seoul, 05029, Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>i Research Institute of Medicine, Konkuk University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seoul, 05029, Korea .<lb/></address>

	Running Head: A novel totivirus in Malassezia<lb/> #Address correspondence to Won Hee Jung,
	<email>whjung@cau.ac.kr<lb/></email>

	Word counts<lb/> Abstract: 206 words; Text: 4,730 words .Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Most fungal viruses have been identified in plant pathogens, whereas the presence of viral<lb/> particles in human pathogenic fungi is less well studied. In the present study, we observed<lb/> extrachromosomal double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) segments in various clinical isolates of<lb/> Malassezia species. Malassezia is the most dominant fungal genus on the human skin surface,<lb/> and species in this group are considered to be etiological factors in various skin diseases<lb/> including dandruff, seborrheic dermatitis, and atopic dermatitis. We identified novel dsRNA<lb/> segments and our sequencing results revealed that the virus, named MrV40, belongs to the<lb/> Totiviridae family and contains an additional satellite dsRNA segment encoding a novel<lb/> protein. The transcriptome of virus-infected M. restricta cells was compared to that of virus-<lb/>free cells, and the results showed that transcripts involved in ribosomal biosynthesis were<lb/> down regulated and those involved in energy production and programmed cell death were<lb/> increased in abundance. Moreover, transmission electron microscopy revealed significantly<lb/> larger vacuoles for virus-infected M. restricta cells, indicating that MrV40 infection<lb/> dramatically altered M. restricta physiology. Our analysis also revealed that a viral nucleic<lb/> acid from MrV40 induces a TLR3-mediated inflammatory immune response in bone marrow-<lb/>derived dendritic cells (BMDCs) and this result suggests that a viral element contributes to<lb/> the pathogenesis of Malassezia.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
