<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="205._10.1.1.38.1704"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>INTERNATIONAL COMPUTER SCIENCE INSTITUTE I<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>1947 Center St. Suite 600 Berkeley, California 94704-1198</address>
	<phone>(510) 643-9153</phone>
	FAX (510) 643-7684<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Managing ABR Capacity in<lb/> Reservation-based Slotted Networks<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Roya Ulrich and Pieter Kritzinger<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<email>fulrich@icsi.berkeley.edu</email>
	,
	<email>psk@cs.uct.ac.zag<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>The Networks Group<lb/> International Computer Science Institute, and<lb/> The Computer Science Depatrment<lb/> University of Cape Town<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	TR-96-006<lb/>

	<date>January 1996</date>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">For slotted networks carrying full multi-media tra c to work successfully, it is es-<lb/>sential that connection setup and management is done well under all tra c conditions.<lb/> Major challenges remain with the current state of the technology, however, particu-<lb/>larly on how one copes with tra c bursts. Existing reservation-based networks do not<lb/> allow the user to dynamically adjust his bandwidth requirements on demand. In this<lb/> paper we propose a new scheme, called the reservoir scheme, which allows dynamic<lb/> and distributed resource allocation. The basic idea behind the scheme is to reserve<lb/> bandwidth with a guaranteed bit rate for each virtual circuit. The user is allowed to<lb/> decentrally allocate additional bandwidth from an Available Bit Rate (ABR) reser-<lb/>voir to satisfy dynamic changes of Variable Bit Rate (VBR) tra c. The duration and<lb/> bandwidth of this dynamic access are negotiated in the call setup phase and do not<lb/> require any renegotiation with the service provider so that this solution overcomes the<lb/> rigidity of current static bandwidth reservation schemes. The additional management<lb/> requirements are low compared to other dynamic bandwidth reservation schemes. We<lb/> also describe an analytic model and simulation which we used to determine whether<lb/> it would be practical to apply the proposed scheme in a slotted network.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Pieter Kritzinger</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	is in the 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Computer Science Depatrment, University of Cape Town,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>private<lb/> Bag, Rondbosch 7700</address> 

	<page>ii</page>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
