<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="2104.06550v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>

	Title: 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>PMIPv6 Integrated with MIH for Flow Mobility Management: a Real Testbed with<lb/> Simultaneous Multi-Access in Heterogeneous Mobile Networks<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	Affiliation:<lb/>

	• 
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hugo Alves</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	,

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Instituto Universitário de Lisboa (ISCTE-IUL), Instituto de<lb/> Telecomunicações,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Av. Forças Armadas, 1649-026 Lisboa, Portugal;<lb/></address>

	• 
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Luis Silva</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	, 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Instituto Universitário de Lisboa (ISCTE-IUL), Instituto de<lb/> Telecomunicações,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Av. Forças Armadas, 1649-026 Lisboa, Portugal;<lb/></address>

	• 
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rui Neto Marinheiro</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	,

	<email>rui.marinheiro@iscte.pt</email>, 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Instituto Universitário de Lisboa (ISCTE-<lb/>IUL), Instituto de Telecomunicações,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Av. Forças Armadas, 1649-026 Lisboa, Portugal;<lb/></address>

	• 
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jose Moura</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	,

	<email>jose.moura@iscte.pt</email>, 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Instituto Universitário de Lisboa (ISCTE-IUL),<lb/> Instituto de Telecomunicações,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Av. Forças Armadas, 1649-026 Lisboa, Portugal.<lb/></address>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">The exponential growth of the number of multihomed mobile devices is changing the way<lb/> how we can connect to the Internet. Our mobile devices are demanding for more network<lb/> resources, in terms of traffic volume and QoS requirements. Unfortunately, it is very hard to<lb/> a multihomed device to be simultaneously connected to the network through multiple links.<lb/> The current work enhances the network access of multihomed devices agnostically to the<lb/> deployed access technologies. This enhancement is achieved by using simultaneously all of<lb/> the mobile devices interfaces, and by routing each individual data flow through the most<lb/> convenient access technology. The proposed solution is only deployed at the network side<lb/> and it extends Proxy Mobile IPv6 with flow mobility in a completely transparent way to<lb/> mobile nodes. In fact, it gives particular attention to the handover mechanisms, by improving<lb/> the detection and attachment of nodes in the network, with the inclusion of the IEEE 802.21<lb/> standard in the solution. This provides the necessary implementation and integration details<lb/> to extend a network topology with femtocell devices. Each femtocell is equipped with<lb/> various network interfaces supporting a diverse set of access technologies. There is also a<lb/> decision entity that manages individually each data flow according to its QoS / QoE<lb/> requisites.<lb/> The proposed solution has been developed and extensively tested with a real prototype.<lb/> Evaluation results evidence that the overhead for using the solution is negligible as compared<lb/> to the offered advantages such as: the support of flow mobility, the fulfil of VoIP functional<lb/> requisites, the session continuity in spite of flows mobility, its low overhead, its high<lb/> scalability, and the complete transparency of the proposed solution to the user terminals.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>PMIPv6, IEEE 802.21, Flow Mobility, Multi-Access, Heterogeneous Networks,<lb/> Real Testbed<lb/> </keyword>

	I.

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
