<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="2104.06608v2"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Search to aggregate neighborhood<lb/> for graph neural network<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Huan ZHAO 1 , Quanming YAO 1,2 and Weiwei TU 1<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 4Paradigm Inc.</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Electronic Engineering, Tsinghua University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>{zhaohuan,yaoquanming,tuweiwei}@4paradigm.com<lb/></email>

	Abstract-
	<div type="abstract">Recent years have witnessed the popularity and<lb/> success of graph neural networks (GNN) in various scenarios.<lb/> To obtain data-specific GNN architectures, researchers turn to<lb/> neural architecture search (NAS), which have made impressive<lb/> success in discovering effective architectures in convolutional<lb/> neural networks. However, it is non-trivial to apply NAS ap-<lb/>proaches to GNN due to challenges in search space design and<lb/> expensive searching cost of existing NAS methods. In this work,<lb/> to obtain the data-specific GNN architectures and address the<lb/> computational challenges facing by NAS approaches, we propose<lb/> a framework, which tries to Search to Aggregate NEighborhood<lb/> (SANE), to automatically design data-specific GNN architectures.<lb/> By designing a novel and expressive search space, we propose<lb/> a differentiable search algorithm, which is more efficient than<lb/> previous reinforcement learning based methods. Experimental<lb/> results on four tasks and seven real-world datasets demonstrate<lb/> the superiority of SANE compared to existing GNN models and<lb/> NAS approaches in terms of effectiveness and efficiency. 1<lb/></div>
	
	Index Terms-
	<keyword>graph neural network, neural architecture<lb/> search, message passing<lb/></keyword>

	<idno>arXiv:2104.06608v2 [cs.LG]</idno>

	<date>20 Apr 2021</date>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
