<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="2104.08739v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>CONTINUITY-DISCRIMINATION CONVOLUTIONAL NEURAL NETWORK<lb/> FOR VISUAL OBJECT TRACKING<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Shen Li †,<lb/> Bingpeng Ma<lb/> Hong Chang † Shiguang Shan †,<lb/> Xilin Chen †<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>† Key Lab of Intelligent Information Processing of Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS),<lb/> Institute of Computing Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>CAS, Bejing, 100190, China.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>School of Computer and Control Engineering,<lb/> University of Chinese Academy of Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Beijing 100049, China.<lb/></address>

	<email>{shen.li, bingpeng.ma, hong.chang, shiguang.shan, xilin.chen}@vipl.ict.ac.cn</email>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">This paper proposes a novel model, named Continuity-<lb/>Discrimination Convolutional Neural Network (CD-CNN),<lb/> for visual object tracking. Existing state-of-the-art tracking<lb/> methods do not deal with temporal relationship in video se-<lb/>quences, which leads to imperfect feature representations. To<lb/> address this problem, CD-CNN models temporal appearance<lb/> continuity based on the idea of temporal slowness. Mathe-<lb/>matically, we prove that, by introducing temporal appearance<lb/> continuity into tracking, the upper bound of target appearance<lb/> representation error can be sufficiently small with high proba-<lb/>bility. Further, in order to alleviate inaccurate target localiza-<lb/>tion and drifting, we propose a novel notion, object-centroid,<lb/> to characterize not only objectness but also the relative posi-<lb/>tion of the target within a given patch. Both temporal appear-<lb/>ance continuity and object-centroid are jointly learned during<lb/> offline training and then transferred for online tracking. We<lb/> evaluate our tracker through extensive experiments on two<lb/> challenging benchmarks and show its competitive tracking<lb/> performance compared with state-of-the-art trackers.<lb/></div>

	Index Terms-
	<keyword>Visual object tracking, temporal appear-<lb/>ance continuity, object-centroid discrimination<lb/></keyword>

	978-1-5386-1737-3/18/$31.00 

	<note type="copyright">©2018 IEEE<lb/></note>
	
	<idno>arXiv:2104.08739v1 [cs.CV]</idno>

	<date>18 Apr 2021</date>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
