<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="222554v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
	<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Identification of key pathways and metabolic fingerprints<lb/> of longevity in C. elegans<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Arwen W. Gao*, Reuben L. Smith*, Michel van Weeghel, Rashmi Kamble, Riekelt H. Houtkooper<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Laboratory Genetic Metabolic Diseases, Academic Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1105 AZ Amsterdam,<lb/> The Netherlands.<lb/></address>

	#Correspondence:
	<email>r.h.houtkooper@amc.nl<lb/></email>

	*Equal contribution<lb/> Manuscript statistics: 4713 words (excluding Abstract, Methods, References and Figure<lb/> Legends) Abstract<lb/>
	
	<div type="abstract">Impaired insulin/IGF-1 signaling (IIS) pathway and caloric restriction (CR) are two well-<lb/>established interventions to prolong lifespan in worm C. elegans. However, a cross<lb/> comparison of these longevity pathways using a multi-omics integration approach is lacking.<lb/> In this study, we aimed to identify key pathways and metabolite fingerprints of longevity that<lb/> are shared between IIS and CR worm models using a multi-omics integration approach. We<lb/> generated transcriptomics and metabolomics data from two long-lived mutant worm strains,<lb/> i.e. daf-2 (impaired IIS pathway) and eat-2 (CR model) and compared them with the N2<lb/> strain. Transcriptional profiling identified shared longevity signatures between the two strains,<lb/> such as an upregulation of lipid storage and defense responses and downregulation of<lb/> macromolecule synthesis and developmental processes. The shared longevity signatures<lb/> revealed by metabolomics profiling included an increase in the levels of glycerol-3P,<lb/> ademine, xanthine, and AMP, and a decrease in the levels of the amino acid pool, the C18:0<lb/> and C17:1 fatty acids. After we integrated transcriptomics and metabolomics data based on<lb/> the annotations in KEGG, our results highlighted a downregulation of pyrimidine metabolism<lb/> and upregulation of purine metabolism as a commonality between the two longevity<lb/> mechanisms. Overall, our findings point towards the existence of shared metabolic pathways<lb/> that are likely important for lifespan extension and provide novel insights into potential<lb/> regulators and metabolic fingerprints for longevity.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
