<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="22900_ftp"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Movement Disorders<lb/></reference>
			<reference>Vol. 25, No. 3, 2010, pp. 309–314<lb/></reference>
			<note type="copyright">Ó 2010 Movement Disorder Society<lb/></note>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Health-Related Quality of Life in Patients<lb/> with Gilles de la
					Tourette's Syndrome<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Kirsten Müller-Vahl, MD, 1 Ines Dodel, MD, 2 Norbert Müller, MD, 3<lb/>
					Alexander Münchau, MD, 4 Jens Peter Reese, PhD, MPH, 2 Monika Balzer-Geldsetzer,
					PhD, 2<lb/> Richard Dodel, MD, MPH, 2 * and Wolfgang H. Oertel, MD
					2<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 Department of Psychiatry, Socialpsychiatry and Psychotherapy,
					Hannover Medical School,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Germany<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 Department of Neurology, Philipps-University Marburg,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Germany<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>3<lb/> Department of Psychiatry, Ludwig-Maximilians-University
					Munich,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Germany<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>4<lb/> Department of Neurology, University Hamburg
					Eppendorf,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Germany<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract: To investigate the health-related quality of life<lb/>
				(HrQoL) of adult patients with Gilles de la Tourette's syn-<lb/>drome (GTS) in
				Germany. HrQoL was evaluated in 200 adult<lb/> patients with GTS (Mean age: 34.9 6
				11.8 years). Patients<lb/> were recruited from three outpatient departments in
				Germany<lb/> and completed a semi-structured, self-rating interview.<lb/> HrQoL was
				measured using the EQ-5D. Depression was<lb/> assessed using the Beck's depression
				inventory (BDI) and<lb/> clinical symptoms using the Yale Tourette syndrome
				symp-<lb/>tom list (TSSL) and the Shapiro Tourette-syndrome severity<lb/> scale
				(STSSS). Multivariate regression analyses were per-<lb/>formed to identify
				independent predictors of HrQoL. Patients<lb/> with GTS proved to have a worse HrQoL
				than a sample<lb/> from the general German population. The domains most<lb/>
				affected were anxiety/depression (57.1%), followed by pain/<lb/> discomfort (47.5%),
				usual activities (38.4%), mobility (14%),<lb/> and self-care (6.6%). The mean EQ-5D
				visual analog scale<lb/> (EQ-VAS) was 65.4 6 21.9. The patients had a mean BDI<lb/>
				score of 12.3 6 9.9, which was considerably worse compared<lb/> to a healthy group
				who had a score of 6.45 6 5.2. The mean<lb/> STSSS value was 3.2 6 1.1. In
				multivariate analyses,<lb/> depressive symptoms contributed considerably, whereas
				the<lb/> severity of symptoms as well as age only contributed<lb/> minimally to
				HrQoL in the model (R 2 5 0.54). HrQoL is<lb/> considerably reduced in adult
				patients with GTS. The main<lb/> independent factors for determining HrQoL were
				depression,<lb/> severity of symptoms, and age. Although, treatment of tics is<lb/>
				important, co-morbidities such as depression should be diag-<lb/>nosed and treated
				vigorously.</div>
			<note type="copyright">Ó 2010 Movement Disorder<lb/> Society</note>
			<keywords>Key words: movement disorders; outcome research; qual-<lb/>ity of life; Gilles
				de la Tourette's syndrome; Euroqol</keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
