<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="243.full"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Multivariate-activity mining for molecular quasi-species<lb/> in a glutathione transferase mutant library<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sanela Kurtovic 1 , Arna Runarsdottir 1 , Lars O. Emrén 2 ,<lb/> Anna-Karin Larsson and Bengt Mannervik 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Organic Chemistry, Uppsala University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>BMC, Box 576, SE-75123 Uppsala, Sweden<lb/></address>

	1 Authors contributed equally to the work.<lb/>
	
	2 Previously Lars O. Hansson.<lb/>

	3 To whom correspondence should be addressed.<lb/> E-mail:
	<email>Bengt.Mannervik@biorg.uu.se<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">A library of recombinant glutathione transferases (GSTs)<lb/> generated by shuffling of DNA encoding human GST<lb/> M1-1 and GST M2-2 was screened with eight alternative<lb/> substrates, and the activities were subjected to multi-<lb/>variate analysis. Assays were made in lysates of bacteria<lb/> in which the GST variants had been expressed. The<lb/> primary data showed clustering of the activities in eight-<lb/>dimensional substrate-activity space. For an incisive<lb/> analysis, the rows of the data matrix, corresponding to<lb/> the different enzyme variants, were individually scaled to<lb/> unit length, thus accounting for different expression levels<lb/> of the enzymes. The columns representing the activities<lb/> with alternative substrates were subsequently individually<lb/> normalized to unit variance and a zero mean. By this<lb/> standardization, the data were adjusted to comparable<lb/> orders of magnitude. Three molecular quasi-species were<lb/> recognized by multivariate K-means and principal com-<lb/>ponent analyses. Two of them encompassed the parental<lb/> GST M1-1 and GST M2-2. A third one diverged func-<lb/>tionally by displaying enhanced activities with some sub-<lb/>strates and suppressed activities with signature substrates<lb/> for GST M1-1 and GST M2-2. A fourth cluster contained<lb/> mutants with impaired functions and was not regarded as<lb/> a quasi-species. Sequence analysis of representatives of<lb/> the mutant clusters demonstrated that the majority of the<lb/> variants in the diverging novel quasi-species were structu-<lb/>rally similar to the M1-like GSTs, but distinguished<lb/> themselves from GST M1-1 by a Ser to Thr substitution<lb/> in the active site. The data show that multivariate analysis<lb/> of functional profiles can identify small structural<lb/> changes influencing the evolution of enzymes with novel<lb/> substrate-activity profiles.<lb/></div>

	Keywords: 
	<keywords>directed evolution/DNA shuffling/glutathione<lb/> transferase/library/multivariate analysis<lb/></keywords> 

	<note type="copyright"># The Author 2007. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved.<lb/> For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org<lb/></note>

	<reference>Protein Engineering, Design &amp; Selection vol. 20 no. 5 pp. 243-256, 2007<lb/></reference>

	Published online 
	<date>April 27, 2007</date> 

	<idno>doi:10.1093/protein/gzm017<lb/></idno>

	<note type="submission">Received March 12, 2007; revised March 12, 2007;<lb/> accepted March 14, 2007<lb/></note>

	Edited by 
	<editor>Frances Arnold<lb/> S.Kurtovic et al.</editor>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
