<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="257._56961"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Parallelization of Linearized<lb/> Applications in Fortran D<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Lorie M. Liebrock<lb/> Ken Kennedy<lb/> CRPC TR93342-S<lb/> November, 1993<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Center for Research on Parallel Computation<lb/> Rice University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P.O. Box 1892<lb/> Houston, TX 77251-1892<lb/></address>

	<note type="funding">This research was supported by: Center for Research on<lb/> Parallel Computation, a National Science Foundation Sci-<lb/>ence and Technology Center, through Cooperative Agree-<lb/>ment No. CCR-9120008, NSF/NASA Agreement No.<lb/> ASC-9213821, and ONR Agreement No. N00014-93-1-<lb/>0158. Use of the Intel i860 was provided under a Texas<lb/> CER Grant No. CISE 8619893.</note> 

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">The Fortran D language extends Fortran by permitting the user to specify the distribution of array variables<lb/> across the processors of a parallel computer system. This information can then be used by the compiler<lb/> to derive a multidimensional parallelization. For programs in which multidimensional arrays have been lin-<lb/>earized for optimal performance on vector processors, this strategy will not produce the best results because<lb/> in those programs Fortran D is limited to a one-dimensional parallelization, which yields less e cient com-<lb/>munication than multidimensional parallelization because of surface-to-volume e ects. This paper proposes<lb/> Fortran D extensions and associated compiler technology to support natural topology parallelization of ap-<lb/>plications&apos; codes with linearized arrays. Experimental results are presented to illustrate the improvement in<lb/> performance of this new approach over the performance of currently available methods such as Fortran D<lb/> and the PARTI inspector/executor strategy.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
