<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="2BECAAF106E6F3607275FB57D73C0D16C39CE741"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A Reading-Level Design Study of Phonological<lb/> Skills Underlying Fourth-Grade Children&apos;s<lb/> Word Reading Difficulties<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Judith A. Bowey, Mary T. Cain, and Sharon M. Ryan<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Queensland<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<reference>BowEY, JUDITH A.; CAIN, MAHY T.; and RYAN, SHARON M. A Reading-Level Design Study of Phono-<lb/> logical Skills Underlying Fourth-Grade Children&apos;s Word Reading Difficulties. CHILD DEVELOP-<lb/>MENT, 1992, 63, 999-1011.</reference>

	<div type="abstract">A 3-group reading-level design was used to investigate phonological<lb/> analysis, verbal working memory, and pseudoword reading performance in less skilled fourth-<lb/>grade readers. Children were given phonological oddity tasks assessing their sensitivity to sub-<lb/>syllabic and phonemic units, together with standardized tests of verbal working memory and<lb/> pseudoword reading. Less skilled fourth-grade readers performed lower than both chronological<lb/> age and reading-level controls on the phonological oddity and pseudoword reading tests. Less<lb/> skilled fourth-grade readers performed at the same level as skilled second-grade readers on a<lb/> test of verbal working memory. Skilled fourth-grade readers scored higher than both other groups<lb/> on this test. Correlational analyses were consistent with the view that phonological analysis skills<lb/> contribute more strongly than verbal working memory skills to children&apos;s decoding abilities.<lb/></div>

	[
	<reference>ChUd Development, 1992, 63, 999-lOH.</reference>

	<note type="copyright">© 1992 by the Society for Research in Child Development, Inc.<lb/> All rights reserved. </note>

	0009-3920/92/6304-0003$01.00]
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
