<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="308.full"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Annals of Oncology 13: 308–317, 2002<lb/></reference>

			<note type="articleType">Original article<lb/></note>

			<idno>DOI: 10.1093/annonc/mdf034<lb/></idno>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Clinical determinants of survival in patients with
					5-fluorouracil-<lb/>based treatment for metastatic colorectal cancer: results of
					a<lb/> multivariate analysis of 3825 patients<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>C.-H. Köhne 1 *, D. Cunningham 2 , F. Di Costanzo 3 , B. Glimelius 4 , G.
					Blijham 5 , E. Aranda 6 ,<lb/> W. Scheithauer 7 , P. Rougier 8 , M. Palmer 9 ,
					J. Wils 10 , B. Baron 11 , F. Pignatti 11 , P. Schöffski 12 ,<lb/> S. Micheel 13
					&amp; H. Hecker 12<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>


			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 Medizinische Klinik und Poliklinik I, Universitätsklinikum Carl
					Gustav Carus der TU-Dresden,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Dresden, Germany;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 The Cancer Research Company Section of<lb/> Medicine and the GI Unit,
					The Royal Marsden Hospital,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Sutton, UK;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>3 Department of Internal Medicine and Oncology, Azienda Ospedaliera S.
					Maria,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Terni,<lb/> Italy;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>4 University Hospital, Department of Oncology,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Uppsala, Sweden;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>5 Academisch Ziekenhuis Utrecht, Department of Internal Medicine,
					Utrecht,<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>The Netherlands;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>6 Hospital Universitario 'Reina Sofia',</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Cordoba, Spain;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>7 University Hospital, Department of Internal Medicine,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Vienna, Austria;<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>8 Hôpital Ambroise Paré, Service de Hepato-Gastroent. Concologie
					Digestive,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Boulogne Cedex, France;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>9 ASTRA-ZENECA Pharmaceuticals,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Macclesfield, UK;<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>10 Laurentius Hospital,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Roermond, The Netherlands;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>11 EORTC Data Center,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Brussels, Belgium;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>12 Medical School Hannover, Department of Internal
					Medicine,<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Hannover;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>13 Robert-Rössle-Clinic Charité, Campus Berlin-Buch,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Berlin, Germany<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received 6 July 2001; accepted 27 August 2001<lb/></note>

			<div type="abstract">Background: Patients with metastatic colorectal cancer are usually
				offered systemic chemotherapy as<lb/> palliative treatment. A multivariate analysis
				was performed in order to identify predictors and their con-<lb/> stellation that
				allow a valid prediction of the outcome in patients treated with 5-fluorouracil
				(5-FU)-<lb/> based therapy.<lb/> Patients and methods: A total of 3825 patients
				treated with 5-FU within 19 prospective randomised<lb/> and three phase II trials
				were separated into learning (n = 2549) and validation (n = 1276) samples. Data<lb/>
				were analysed by tree analysis using the recursive partition and amalgamation method
				(RECPAM). A<lb/> predictor could only enter the RECPAM analysis if the number of
				patients with missing values was<lb/> &lt;33.3% within a node, and the minimal node
				size was set to 50 patients. Twenty-three potential pre-<lb/> dictors were grouped
				into subsets of laboratory variables (11 parameters), tumour-related variables<lb/>
				(seven parameters) and clinical variables (five parameters). In the first step, tree
				analysis was performed<lb/> separately for each predictor subset. The selected
				prognostic parameters of the resulting partial models<lb/> (the ‘winners’) were
				entered into the general model. The classification rule from the data of the
				learning<lb/> set was applied to the independent validation set.<lb/> Results:
				Winners of the subgroup analysis for laboratory variables were: platelets ≥400 ×
				109/l, alka-<lb/> line phosphatase ≥300 U/l, white blood cell (WBC) count ≥10 ×
				109/l and haemoglobin &lt;11 × 109/l, and<lb/> all predicted a worse outcome.
				Negative predictors within the subgroup of tumour parameters were:<lb/> number of
				tumour sites more than one or more than two, presence of liver metastases or
				peritoneal<lb/> carcinomatosis, which predicted a worse outcome. Furthermore,
				presence of lung metastases, a primary<lb/> rectal cancer and presence of lymph node
				metastases all predicted a better outcome in the multivariate<lb/> setting. Among
				the clinical parameters only performance status of ECOG 0 or 1 predicted better
				out-<lb/> come. In the final regression tree, three risk groups could be identified:
				low risk group (n = 1111) with a<lb/> median survival of 15 months for patients with
				ECOG 0/1 and only one tumour site; intermediate risk<lb/> group (n = 904) with a
				median survival of 10.7 months for patients with ECOG 0/1 and more than one<lb/>
				tumour site and alkaline phosphatase &lt;300 U/l or patients with ECOG >1, WBC count
				&lt;10 × 109/l and<lb/> only one tumour site; high risk group (n = 534) with a
				median survival of 6.1 months for patients with<lb/> ECOG 0/1 and more than one
				tumour site and alkaline phosphatase of ≥300 U/l or patients with ECOG<lb/> >1 and
				more than one tumour site or WBC count >10 × 109/l. The median survival times for
				the good,<lb/> intermediate and high risk groups in the validation sample were 14.7,
				10.5 and 6.4 months, respectively.<lb/> Conclusions: Patients can be divided into at
				least three risk groups depending on the four baseline<lb/> clinical parameters:
				performance status, WBC count, alkaline phosphatase and number of metastatic<lb/>
				sites. Any molecular or biological marker should be validated against these clinical
				parameters and<lb/> decisions for more or less intensive treatments may be studied
				separately in these three risk groups.<lb/> Also, clinical trials should be
				stratified according to the three risk groups.<lb/></div>
			<keywords>Key words: colorectal neoplasm, metastatic disease, multivariate analysis,
				prognosis<lb/></keywords>



			<note type="other">*Correspondence to: Medizinische Klinik und Poliklinik I,
				Universitätsklinikum Carl Gustav Carus der TU-Dresden, Fetscher Strasse 74,<lb/>
				01307 Dresden, Germany.</note>
			<phone>Tel: +49-351-458-4780; Fax: +49-351-458-5859;</phone>
			<email>E-mail: koehne@mk1.med.tu-dresden.de<lb/></email>


			<note type="copyright">© 2002 European Society for Medical Oncology<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
