<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="314898v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
	<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Prevalence of subclinical ketosis and production diseases in dairy cows in<lb/> Central and South America, Africa, Asia, Australia and New Zealand, and<lb/> Eastern Europe<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Nikolaus Brunner 1 , Stephan Groeger 1 , Jose Raposo 1 , Rupert M. Bruckmaier 2 , Josef J. Gross 2*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Bayer Animal Health GmbH,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Leverkusen, Germany<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Veterinary Physiology, Vetsuisse Faculty, University of Bern,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bern, Switzerland<lb/></address>

	* Corresponding author<lb/> Email:
	<email>josef.gross@vetsuisse.unibe.ch</email>

	(JJG) Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Subclinical ketosis (SCK) and periparturient diseases considerably account for<lb/> economic and welfare losses in dairy cows. The majority of scientific reports investigating the<lb/> prevalence of SCK and production diseases are based on empirical studies conducted in<lb/> Western Europe and North America. The present study surveyed the prevalence of SCK and<lb/> production-related clinical diseases in early lactating cows in various countries across the<lb/> world other than those in North America and Western Europe. Twelve countries of South and<lb/> Central America (Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Mexico), Africa (South Africa), Asia<lb/> (Thailand, China), Eastern Europe (Russia, Ukraine), Australia and New Zealand were<lb/> assessed, and data from a total of 8,902 cows kept at 541 commercial dairy farms were<lb/> obtained. A minimum of 5 cows per farm were blood sampled and examined once after<lb/> parturition up to day 21 of lactation. Blood concentration of β-hydroxybutyrate (BHBA) was<lb/> measured (threshold for SCK: 1.2 mmol/l) and the presence of production-related diseases<lb/> such as milk fever, retained placenta, mastitis, metritis, displaced abomasum, claw disease<lb/> and clinical ketosis was recorded. More than 95% of all cows were examined in their second<lb/> week of lactation. Across all investigated countries, the SCK prevalence was 24.1%, ranging<lb/> from 8.3% up to 40.1%. The prevalence of production-related diseases detected during the<lb/> first 21 days of lactation was relatively low (&lt; 5%). Calculated odds ratios did not indicate an<lb/> elevated risk for production diseases in cows with SCK. Despite differences in production<lb/> systems across countries and variation between individual farms within a region, the present<lb/> study data on SCK prevalence align with observations in Western European and North<lb/> American dairy herds. At the very early stage of sampling and clinical examination for<lb/> detection of SCK, it cannot be excluded that certain production diseases such as DA,<lb/> lameness and mastitis have developed later.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
