<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="351841v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Attenuation of obesity and related metabolic disorders by the<lb/> individual or combination treatment with IL-2/anti-IL-2 complex<lb/> and hyperbaric oxygen<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Eun-Jeong Choi 1 ¶ , Hyung-Ran Kim 1 ¶ , Jeong-Hae Kie 2 , Byung-In Moon 3* ,<lb/> and Ju-Young Seoh 1*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Microbiology and 3 Surgery, Ewha Womans University<lb/> Graduate School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seoul, Korea;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Pathology, National Health<lb/> Insurance Cooperation Ilsan Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Koyang, Korea<lb/></address>

	¶ These authors contributed equally to this work<lb/> *Shared Correspondence to<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Professor Ju-Young Seoh, MD, PhD<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Microbiology,<lb/> Ewha Womans University Graduate School of Medicine,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Anyangcheon-Ro 1071, Yangchon-Gu,<lb/> Seoul 07985, South Korea<lb/></address>

	Tel: <phone>+ 82 2 2650 5738</phone> (Office), <phone>+ 82 10 7222 5738</phone> (Cell)<lb/> Fax: + 82 2 2650 5591<lb/> E-mail:
	<email>jyseoh@ewha.ac.kr<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Professor Byung-In Moon, MD, PhD<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Surgery,<lb/> Ewha Womans University Graduate School of Medicine,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Anyangcheon-Ro 1071, Yangchon-Gu,<lb/> Seoul 07985, South Korea<lb/></address>

	Tel: <phone>+ 82 2 2650 5102</phone> (Office), <phone>+ 82 10 8724 0687</phone> (Cell)<lb/> Fax: + 82 2 2650 5591<lb/> E-mail:
	<email>mbit@ewha.ac.kr</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Obesity is the disease accumulating excessive fat in the body. The<lb/> prevalence of obesity and related metabolic disorders is increasing every<lb/> year worldwide. Immunologically, obesity is a chronic low-grade<lb/> inflammatory state with the increase of M1 macrophages and decrease of<lb/> regulatory T cells (Tregs). IL-2/anti-IL-2 complex (IL-2C) and hyperbaric<lb/> oxygen (HBO) are known to expand Tregs in vivo and suppress<lb/> inflammation. Therefore, in this study, IL-2C and HBO were investigated<lb/> for the preventive effect of obesity and related metabolic disorders. Male<lb/> C57BL/6 mice were fed with a high-fat diet (HFD) for 16 weeks, and<lb/> counterparts were fed with a low-fat diet (LFD). At the end of the<lb/> experiment, the body weight gain and impaired glucose metabolism,<lb/> elevated levels of insulin and total cholesterol induced by HFD were<lb/> improved by the individual or combination treatment with Il-2C and HBO.<lb/> Histological examination of the epididymal white adipose tissue showed<lb/> adipocyte hypertrophy and many crown-like structures in the HFD control<lb/> groups. In addition, the liver showed the progression of non-alcoholic fatty<lb/> liver disease (NAFLD) in the HFD control groups, but it was significantly<lb/> improved by the individual or combination treatment with IL-2C and HBO.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
