<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="375._getPDF"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<meeting>Proceedings of the 35th<lb/> Conference on Decision and Control<lb/> WA05 10:20<lb/> Kobe, Japan</meeting>
	0 
	<date>December 1996<lb/></date>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Construction of Fuzzy Linguistic Model<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Tak-Kuen John Koo<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Robotics and Intelligent Machines Laboratory<lb/> 211-85 Cory Hall, Department of EECS<lb/> University of California at Berkeley<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Berkeley, CA94720<lb/></address>

	<email>koo@robotics.eecs. berkeley.edu</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Using linguistic variables to describe the behavior of a<lb/> hybrid system, which consists of a discrete event sys-<lb/>tem and a continuous system, could make the design<lb/> of the controller and verification of the system perform<lb/> on an unified framework. In this paper, we show the<lb/> construction of a fuzzy linguistic model from a given<lb/> mathematical model of a physical system. By consider-<lb/>ing the state-space realization of the model, the system<lb/> construction problem can be transformed into a func-<lb/>tion approximation problem. We propose to use pro-<lb/>jection theorem in obtaining an optimal fuzzy system<lb/> which is the best approximation of a given nonlinear<lb/> function in L z ( U ) space. We show that the existence<lb/> and uniqueness of the optimal solution is assured when<lb/> the Fuzzy Basis Functions(FBFs) are linearly indepen-<lb/>dent. We demonstrate that the dependence of the basis<lb/> functions can be examined by checking the condition of<lb/> the Gram determinant associated to the FBFs. Finally,<lb/> a method is proposed in converting the optimal coeffi-<lb/>cients into fuzzy sets to obtain a fuzzy linguistic model.<lb/> Continuous time<lb/> Discrete time<lb/> 4 t ) = f(+))<lb/> 4 k + 1) = f ( 4 k ) )<lb/> where z E U c !Rn and f : !Rn x !Rn.</div>

	The vector<lb/> 0-7803-3590-2/96 $5.00 

	<note type="copyright">0 1996 IEEE 98<lb/> </note>

	Authorized licensed use limited to: European Patent Office. Downloaded on September 18, 2009 at 04:52 from IEEE Xplore. Restrictions apply.
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
