<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="386813v1.full"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Fndc3a (Fibronectin Domain Containing Protein 3A) influences median fin fold<lb/> development and caudal fin regeneration in zebrafish by ECM alteration.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Daniel Liedtke 1,* , Melanie Orth 1 , Michelle Meissler 1 , Sinje Geuer 2 , Sabine Knaup 1 , Isabell<lb/> Köblitz 1,3 , Eva Klopocki 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Institute of Human Genetics, Biocenter, University of Würzburg,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>97074 Würzburg, Germany<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Human Genetics, Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour,<lb/> Radboud University Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>6500 HB Nijmegen, The Netherlands<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, Biocenter, University of Würzburg,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>97074<lb/> Würzburg, Germany<lb/></address>

	* Corresponding author: 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Daniel Liedtke<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institut für Humangenetik,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Biozentrum, Am Hubland<lb/> Julius-Maximilians Universität Würzburg<lb/> D-97074 Würzburg<lb/></address>

	Tel.: 
	<phone>+49-931-31-81350<lb/></phone> 
	Fax.: +49-931-31-81350-0<lb/> E-mail address:
	<email>liedtke@biozentrum.uni-wuerzburg.de<lb/></email>

	Keywords (max. 6)<lb/>
	<keyword>median fin fold, caudal fin regeneration, epidermal cells, zebrafish, CRISPR/Cas9, ECM<lb/> </keyword>

	Summary statement<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">We investigated potential functions of Fndc3a during caudal fin development and<lb/> regeneration in zebrafish. Reduced function interferes with correct epidermal cells structure<lb/> and implies a role during vertebrate extremity development.</div>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Inherited genetic alterations are often found to be disease-causing factors of patient<lb/> phenotypes. To unravel the molecular consequences of newly identified factors functional<lb/> investigations in vivo are eminent. We investigated molecular functions of FNDC3A<lb/> (Fibronectin Domain Containing Protein 3A; HUGO), a novel candidate gene for split-<lb/>hand/foot malformations (SHFM) in humans, by utilizing zebrafish (Danio rerio) as a<lb/> vertebrate model. Patients with congenital SHFM display prominent limb malformations,<lb/> which are caused by disturbance of limb development due to defects in apical ectodermal<lb/> ridge (AER) establishment and maintenance. Initial gene expression and protein localization<lb/> studies clarified the presence of fndc3a in developing and regenerating fins of zebrafish. For<lb/> functional studies we established a hypomorphic fndc3a mutant line (fndc3a wue1/wue1 ) via<lb/> CRISPR/Cas9, exhibiting phenotypic malformations and changed gene expression patterns<lb/> during early stages of median fin fold development. Furthermore, fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants<lb/> display abnormal collagen localization, actinotrichia breakup and cellular defects in epidermal<lb/> cells during caudal fin development. The observed effects are only temporary and later result<lb/> in rather normal fin development in adults. In accordance with early fin development, proper<lb/> caudal fin regeneration in adult fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants is hampered by interference with<lb/> actinotrichia formation and epidermal cell abnormalities. Investigation of cellular matrix<lb/> formation implied that loss of ECM structure is a common cause for both phenotypes. Our<lb/> results thereby provide a molecular link between Fndc3a function during both developmental<lb/> processes in zebrafish and foreshadow Fndc3a as a novel temporal regulator of epidermal<lb/> cell properties during extremity development in vertebrates.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
