<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="388793v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Monocyte depletion attenuates the development of posttraumatic hydrocephalus and<lb/> preserves white matter integrity after traumatic brain injury.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hadijat M. Makinde 1&amp; , Talia B. Just 1&amp; , Carla M. Cuda 2 , Nicola Bertolino 3 , Daniele<lb/> Procissi 3,4 ¶ , Steven J. Schwulst 1* ¶<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Surgery, Division of Trauma and Critical Care, Northwestern University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Chicago, Illinois, United States of America<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Medicine, Division of Rheumatology, Northwestern University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Chicago,<lb/> Illinois, United States of America<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Radiology, Northwestern University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Chicago, Illinois, United States of<lb/> America<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Biomedical Engineering, Northwestern University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Chicago, Illinois,<lb/> United States of America<lb/></address>

	* Corresponding author<lb/> E-Mail:
	<email>s-schwulst@northwestern.edu<lb/></email>

	¶ SJS and DP are Joint Senior Authors<lb/> &amp; HMM and TBJ are Joint First Authors Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Monocytes are amongst the first cells recruited into the brain after traumatic brain<lb/> injury (TBI). We have shown monocyte depletion 24 hours prior to TBI reduces brain<lb/> edema, decreases neutrophil infiltration and improves behavioral outcomes. Additionally,<lb/> both lesion and ventricle size correlate with poor neurologic outcome after TBI. Therefore,<lb/> we aimed to determine the association between monocyte infiltration, lesion size, and<lb/> ventricle volume. We hypothesized that monocyte depletion would attenuate lesion size,<lb/> decrease ventricle enlargement, and preserve white matter in mice after TBI. C57BL/6<lb/> mice underwent pan monocyte depletion via intravenous injection of liposome-<lb/>encapsulated clodronate. Control mice were injected with liposome-encapsulated PBS.<lb/> TBI was induced via an open-head, controlled cortical impact. Mice were imaged using<lb/> magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) at 1, 7, and 14 days post-injury to evaluate<lb/> progression of lesion and to detect morphological changes associated with injury (3D T1-<lb/>weighted MRI) including regional alterations in white matter patterns (multi-direction<lb/> diffusion MRI). Lesion size and ventricle volume were measured using semi-automatic<lb/> segmentation and active contour methods with the software program ITK-SNAP. Data<lb/> was analyzed with the statistical software program PRISM. No significant effect of<lb/> monocyte depletion on lesion size was detected using MRI following TBI (p=0.4).<lb/> However, progressive ventricle enlargement following TBI was observed to be attenuated<lb/> in the monocyte-depleted cohort (5.3 ± 0.9mm 3 ) as compared to the sham-depleted<lb/> cohort (13.2 ± 3.1mm 3 ; p=0.02). Global white matter integrity and regional patterns were<lb/> evaluated and quantified for each mouse after extracting fractional anisotropy maps from<lb/> the multi-direction diffusion-MRI data using Siemens Syngo DTI analysis package. 3<lb/> Fractional anisotropy values were preserved in the monocyte-depleted cohort (123.0 ±<lb/> 4.4mm 3 ) as compared to sham-depleted mice (94.9 ± 4.6mm 3 ; p=0.025) by 14 days post-<lb/>TBI. The MRI derived data suggests that monocyte depletion at the time of injury may be<lb/> a novel therapeutic strategy in the treatment of TBI. Furthermore, non-invasive<lb/> longitudinal imaging allows for the evaluation of both TBI progression as well as<lb/> therapeutic response over the course of injury.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
