<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="39B858D1EC346AFC9C2F80908ADC7F5B4D0BC719"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Community Mental Health Journal, Vol. 29, No. 5, October 1993<lb/></reference>

	<note type="doctype">BRIEF REPORT<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Counseling Army Reservists<lb/> and Their Families During<lb/> Operation Desert Shield/Storm<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>David D. Rabb, MA, LICSW, A CSW<lb/> Robert J. Baumer, M.D.<lb/> Norman A. Wieseler, Ph.D.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	ABSTRACT:
	<div type="abstract">The hardships of war affect all members of society. Those most acutely<lb/> affected are service members and their families. Civilian service personnel mobilized<lb/> within an active reserve component experience a disruption of life style which can<lb/> cause stress. Service members are trained to be effective soldiers, but very little<lb/> training is provided to service members or their families on the wartime stresses they<lb/> face. The psychiatric army reserve unit based in Minneapolis developed a family<lb/> support program for three phases of wartime stress: (1) pre-deployment, (2) deployment,<lb/> and (3) reunification and sustainment. Recommendations are provided for family sup-<lb/>port in future wartime situations.<lb/> </div>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>David D. Rabb</docAuthor>
	</byline> 
	
	is affiliated with the 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Veterans Affairs Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>Min-<lb/>neapolis, Minnesota.</address> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Robert J. Baumer</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	is affiliated with the 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Anoka-Metro Regional Treatment<lb/> Center, </affiliation> 
	</byline> 

	<address>Anoka, Minnesota. </address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Norman A. Wieseler</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	is affiliated with the

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Faribault Regional Center,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Faribault, Minnesota.<lb/></address>

	Reprints may be obtained from the first author at the Department of Veterans Affairs Medical<lb/> Center, One Veteran Drive, Minneapolis, MN 55417. The opinions or assertions in this manuscript<lb/> are the views of the authors and do not reflect an endorsement of the Department of Defense or the<lb/> authors&apos; civilian employment agencies. 

	<page>441<lb/></page>

	<note type="copyright">9 1993 Human Sciences Press, Inc.</note>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
