<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="3E47BB5CC6E10BA32D627966335902C60E7FA45E"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Children&apos;s Appraisals of ]\Iarital<lb/> Conflict: Initial Investigations of<lb/> the Cognitive-Contextual Framework<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>John H. Grych and Frank D. Fincham<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Illinois<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<reference>GRYCH, JOHN H., and FINCHAM, FRANK D. Children&apos;s Appraisals of Marital Conflict: Initial<lb/> Investigations of the Cognitive-Contextual Framework. CHILD DEVELOPMENT, 1993, 64, 215-230. <lb/></reference>

	<div type="abstract">2 studies examined children&apos;s appraisals of marital conflict. In Study 1, 45 11-and 12-year-<lb/>olds reported cognitive, affective, and coping responses to conflicts varying in content and inten-<lb/>sity. When conflict concerned the child, children reported more shame and fear of being drawn<lb/> into the conflict and tended to endorse coping responses that involved direct intervention in it.<lb/> More intense conflicts led to greater negative affect and perceived threat. In Study 2,112 12-year-<lb/>olds responded to conflicts that included a parent-blaming or child-blaming explanation or gave<lb/> no explanation for the conflict. Explanations that absolved the children of blame for the conflict<lb/> decreased their fear of becoming involved in the conflict and their desire to intervene in it.<lb/> These findings show that appraisals of marital conflict are influenced by its content, intensity,<lb/> and cause and suggest that the meaning of conflict to children is an important determinant of its<lb/> impact.<lb/></div>

	<note type="funding">John Grych was supported in this research by a National Research Service Award from the<lb/> National Institute of Mental Health. Frank Fincham was supported by grants from the Harry<lb/> Frank Guggenheim Foundation, National Institute of Mental Health (MH 44078) and by a Fac-<lb/>ulty Scholar Award from the W.T. Grant Foundation. We thank Susan Englund and Reliford<lb/> Sanders for their help in creating the vignettes used in this project and Michael Seid for his<lb/> assistance in collecting the data. </note>

	Address correspondence to 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Frank Fincham, </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of<lb/> Psychology, University of Illinois,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Champaign, IL 61820.<lb/></address>

	[<reference>Child Development, 1993, 64, 215-230. </reference>

	<note type="copyright">© 1993 by the Society for Research in Child Development, Inc.<lb/> AU rights reserved. </note>

	0009-3920/93/6401-OOllSOl.OO]

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
