<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="3f9e0973-a71c-42d3-9d37-8e01a10d78d4_PMC5022041"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">Scientific RepoRts</note>

	| 6:33321 |

	<idno>DOI: 10.1038/srep33321<lb/></idno>

	www.nature.com/scientificreports<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Emergence of event cascades in<lb/> inhomogeneous networks<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Tomokatsu Onaga &amp; Shigeru Shinomoto<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">There is a commonality among contagious diseases, tweets, and neuronal firings that past events<lb/> facilitate the future occurrence of events. The spread of events has been extensively studied such<lb/> that the systems exhibit catastrophic chain reactions if the interaction represented by the ratio of<lb/> reproduction exceeds unity; however, their subthreshold states are not fully understood. Here, we<lb/> report that these systems are possessed by nonstationary cascades of event-occurrences already in the<lb/> subthreshold regime. Event cascades can be harmful in some contexts, when the peak-demand causes<lb/> vaccine shortages, heavy traffic on communication lines, but may be beneficial in other contexts, such<lb/> that spontaneous activity in neural networks may be used to generate motion or store memory. Thus<lb/> it is important to comprehend the mechanism by which such cascades appear, and consider controlling<lb/> a system to tame or facilitate fluctuations in the event-occurrences. The critical interaction for the<lb/> emergence of cascades depends greatly on the network structure in which individuals are connected.<lb/> We demonstrate that we can predict whether cascades may emerge, given information about the<lb/> interactions between individuals. Furthermore, we develop a method of reallocating connections<lb/> among individuals so that event cascades may be either impeded or impelled in a network.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Physics, Kyoto University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kyoto 606-8502, Japan.</address>

	Correspondence and requests for materials should<lb/> be addressed to S.S. (email:
	<email>shinomoto@scphys.kyoto-u.ac.jp</email>

	)<lb/>
	<note type="submission">received: 05 April 2016<lb/> Accepted: 24 August 2016<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>14 September 2016</date>

	<note type="doctype">OPEN<lb/></note>

	How to cite this article:
	<reference>Onaga, T. and Shinomoto, S. Emergence of event cascades in inhomogeneous<lb/> networks. Sci. Rep. 6, 33321;</reference>

	<idno>doi: 10.1038/srep33321</idno>

	<note type="copyright">(2016).<lb/> This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images<lb/> or other third party material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license,<lb/> unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license,<lb/> users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this<lb/> license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/<lb/> © The Author(s) 2016</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
