<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="4073d504-1720-44a6-993b-3351b4192e8d_PMC5744005"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>December 2017 | Volume 8 | Article 694 </reference>

	<page>1<lb/> </page>

	<note type="doctype">Original research<lb/></note>

	published:
	<date>22 December 2017<lb/></date>

	<idno>doi: 10.3389/fneur.2017.00694<lb/></idno>

	<title level="j">Frontiers in Neurology</title> 

	| www.frontiersin.org<lb/> Edited by:<lb/>
	
	<editor>J. Marc Simard,<lb/></editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Maryland,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Baltimore, United States<lb/></address>

	Reviewed by:<lb/>
	<editor>Minjee Kim,<lb/></editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Northwestern University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>United States<lb/></address>

	<editor>Robert F. James,<lb/></editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Louisville,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>United States<lb/></address>

	*Correspondence:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Anke Höllig<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<email>ahoellig@ukaachen.de<lb/></email>

	Specialty section:<lb/>
	<note type="submission">This article was submitted<lb/> to Neurocritical and<lb/> Neurohospitalist Care,<lb/> a section of the journal<lb/> Frontiers in Neurology<lb/></note>
	<note type="submission">Received: 20 July 2017<lb/> Accepted: 04 December 2017<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>22 December 2017<lb/></date>

	Citation:<lb/>
	<reference>Höllig A, Stoffel-Wagner B,<lb/> Clusmann H, Veldeman M,<lb/> Schubert GA and Coburn M (2017)<lb/> Time Courses of Inflammatory<lb/> Markers after Aneurysmal<lb/> Subarachnoid Hemorrhage and Their<lb/> Possible Relevance for Future<lb/> Studies.<lb/> Front. Neurol. 8:694.<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi: 10.3389/fneur.2017.00694<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Time courses of inflammatory<lb/> Markers after aneurysmal<lb/> subarachnoid hemorrhage and<lb/> Their Possible relevance for<lb/> Future studies<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Anke Höllig 1 *, Birgit Stoffel-Wagner 2 , Hans Clusmann 1 , Michael Veldeman 1 ,<lb/> Gerrit A. Schubert 1 and Mark Coburn 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Neurosurgery, University Hospital RWTH Aachen,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Aachen, Germany,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Clinical Chemistry and<lb/> Clinical Pharmacology, University Hospital Bonn,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bonn, Germany,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Anesthesiology, University Hospital RWTH<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Aachen, Aachen, Germany<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Object: Aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage triggers an intense inflammatory<lb/> response, which is suspected to increase the risk for secondary complications such as<lb/> delayed cerebral ischemia (DCI). However, to date, the monitoring of the inflammatory<lb/> response to detect secondary complications such as DCI has not become part of the<lb/> clinical routine diagnostic. Here, we aim to illustrate the time courses of inflammatory<lb/> parameters after aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage (aSAH) and discuss the prob-<lb/>lems of inflammatory parameters as biomarkers but also their possible relevance for<lb/> deeper understanding of the pathophysiology after aSAH and sophisticated planning of<lb/> future studies.<lb/> Materials and methods: In this prospective cohort study, 109 patients with aSAH were<lb/> initially included, n = 28 patients had to be excluded. Serum and-if possible-cerebral<lb/> spinal fluid samples (n = 48) were retrieved at days 1, 4, 7, 10, and 14 after aSAH.<lb/> Samples were analyzed for leukocyte count and C-reactive protein (CRP) (serum sam-<lb/>ples only) as well as matrix metallopeptidase 9 (MMP9), intercellular adhesion molecule<lb/> 1 (ICAM1), and leukemia inhibitory factor (LIF) [both serum and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)<lb/> samples]. Time courses of the inflammatory parameters were displayed and related to<lb/> the occurrence of DCI.<lb/> results: We illustrate the time courses of leukocyte count, CRP, MMP9, ICAM1, and LIF<lb/> in patients&apos; serum samples from the first until the 14th day after aSAH. Time courses of<lb/> MMP9, ICAM1, and LIF in CSF samples are demonstrated. Furthermore, no significant<lb/> difference was shown relating the time courses to the occurrence of DCI.<lb/> conclusion: We estimate that the wide range of the measured values hampers their<lb/> interpretation and usage as a biomarker. However, understanding the inflammatory<lb/> response after aSAH and generating a multicenter database may facilitate further stud-<lb/>ies: realistic sample size calculations on the basis of a multicenter database will increase<lb/> the quality and clinical relevance of the acquired results.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>inflammatory response, subarachnoid hemorrhage, early brain injury, delayed cerebral ischemia,<lb/> observational research 2<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2017 Höllig, Stoffel-Wagner, Clusmann, Veldeman, Schubert and<lb/> Coburn. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative<lb/> Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in<lb/> other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited<lb/> and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted<lb/> academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not<lb/> comply with these terms.</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
