<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="419.full"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Biostatistics (2008), 9, 3, pp. 419–431<lb/></reference>

			<idno>doi:10.1093/biostatistics/kxm041<lb/></idno>

			<date>Advance Access publication on December 3, 2007<lb/></date>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Predicting renal graft failure using multivariate<lb/> longitudinal
					profiles<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>STEFFEN FIEUWS * , GEERT VERBEKE<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Biostatistical Centre, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Leuven, Belgium<lb/></address>

			<email>steffen.fieuws@med.kuleuven.be<lb/></email>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>BART MAES<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Department of Nephrology, H.-Hartziekenhuis,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Roeselare-Menen, Belgium<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>YVES VANRENTERGHEM<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Department of Nephrology, University Hospital
					Gasthuisberg,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Leuven, Belgium<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">SUMMARY Patients who have undergone renal transplantation are
				monitored longitudinally at irregular time intervals<lb/> over 10 years or more.
				This yields a set of biochemical and physiological markers containing valuable<lb/>
				information to anticipate a failure of the graft. A general linear, generalized
				linear, or nonlinear mixed<lb/> model is used to describe the longitudinal profile
				of each marker. To account for the correlation between<lb/> markers, the univariate
				mixed models are combined into a multivariate mixed model (MMM) by specify-<lb/>ing
				a joint distribution for the random effects. Due to the high number of markers, a
				pairwise modeling<lb/> strategy, where all possible pairs of bivariate mixed models
				are fitted, is used to obtain parameter estimates<lb/> for the MMM. These estimates
				are used in a Bayes rule to obtain, at each point in time, the prognosis for<lb/>
				long-term success of the transplant. It is shown that allowing the markers to be
				correlated can improve<lb/> this prognosis.<lb/></div>

			<keyword>Keywords: Discriminant analysis; High dimensional; Joint modeling; Longitudinal
				profiles; Multivariate mixed<lb/> models.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
