<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="436519v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page> 

	Title: &quot;
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Mitochondrial GWAS and Association of Nuclear -Mitochondrial Epistasis with<lb/> BMI in T1DM Patients</titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	&quot;<lb/> 

	Short title: &quot;Mitochondrial epistasis and Body Mass Index&quot;<lb/>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Agnieszka H. Ludwig-Słomczyńska 1 , Michał T. Seweryn 1,2 , Przemysław Kapusta 1 , Ewelina<lb/> Pitera 1 , Urszula Mantaj 3 , Katarzyna Cyganek 4 , Paweł Gutaj 3 , Łucja Dobrucka 4 , Ewa Wender-<lb/>Ożegowska 3 , Maciej T. Małecki 4,5 , Paweł P. Wołkow 1*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Center for Medical Genomics OMICRON, Jagiellonian University Medical College ,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kraków,<lb/> Poland;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 The Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center, Department of Cancer Biology and<lb/> Genetics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Columbus, Ohio, United States of America;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Poznan University of Medical Sciences, Division of Reproduction,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Poznań, Poland;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 University Hospital Kraków, Department of Metabolic Diseases,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kraków, Poland;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Department of Metabolic Diseases, Jagiellonian University Medical College,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kraków, Poland.<lb/></address>

	*Corresponding author:<lb/> e-mail:
	<email>pawel.wolkow@uj.edu.pl</email>

	(PPW)<lb/> Author contributions:<lb/> UM, KC, PG and ŁD gathered study cohort and phenotypic data; EWO and MTM supervised<lb/> cohort construction; AHLS and EP performed genotyping; AHLS, MTS and PK analyzed and<lb/> interpreted data; AHLS, MTS, PK and PPW wrote the paper; AHLS and PPW and guarantors<lb/> of this work. All authors contributed to critical revision of the manuscript and approved its<lb/> publication. Abstract<lb/>
	
	<div type="abstract">Mitochondria are organelles whose main role is energy production and might influence obesity.<lb/> They are the only organelles with their own genome. Here we have genotyped 435 patients with<lb/> type 1 diabetes using Illumina Infinium Omni Express Exome-8 v1.4 arrays and performed<lb/> mitoGWAS on BMI. We have analyzed additive interactions between mitochondrial and<lb/> nuclear variants in genes known to be associated with mitochondrial functioning<lb/> (MitoCarta2.0) and confirmed and refined the results on external cohorts -Framingham Heart<lb/> Study (FHS) and GTEx data. The linear mixed model analysis was performed using the<lb/> GENESIS package in R/Bioconductor We have found a nominal association between<lb/> rs28357980 localized to MT-ND2 and BMI (β=-0.69, p=0.056). This was confirmed on 1889<lb/> patients from FHS cohort (β =-0.312, p=0.047). Next, we have searched for additive<lb/> interactions between mitochondrial and nuclear variants. MT-ND2 variants interacted with<lb/> variants in SIRT3, ATP5B, CYCS, TFB2M and POLRMT genes. TFB2M is a mitochondrial<lb/> transcription factor and together with TFAM creates transcription promoter complex for<lb/> mitochondrial polymerase POLRMT. We have found that the interaction between rs3021088<lb/> of MT-ND2 gene and rs6701836 in TFB2M has led to BMI decrease (inter_pval=0.0241), while<lb/> interaction of rs3021088in MT-ND2 and rs41542013 in POLRMT gene led to BMI increase<lb/> (inter_pval=0.0004). The influence of these interactions on BMI was confirmed on external<lb/> cohorts. Here, we have shown that variants in mitochondrial genome as well as additive<lb/> interactions between mitochondrial and nuclear SNPs influence BMI in T1DM and general<lb/> cohorts.<lb/> production. They are the only organelles that contain their own genome. Thus, we have<lb/> genotyped 435 patients with type 1 diabetes and looked on single mitochondrial variant<lb/> influence as well as on additive interactions between mitochondrial and nuclear variants which<lb/> might affect BMI. Our analysis has shown, that rs28357980 localized to MT-ND2 is associated<lb/> with BMI. Next, we looked whether variants in this gene, which builds complex I of the electron<lb/> transport chain, might interact with nuclear variants and together they modify obesity risk. We<lb/> focused mainly on mitochondrial biogenesis and found that interactions between variants in<lb/> TFB2M (rs6701836) or POLRMT (rs41542013) and MT-ND2 (rs3021088) affect patients<lb/> BMI. TFB2M is a mitochondrial transcription factor which, together with TFAM, creates<lb/> transcription promoter complex and enables transcription by mitochondrial polymerase<lb/> POLRMT. The obtained results were also confirmed and refined on external cohorts -<lb/>Framingham Heart Study (FHS) and GTEx data. Thus, we have shown that variations in<lb/> mitochondrial genome and its interactions with nuclear variants might have an influence on<lb/> BMI.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
