<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="43A267909531F6861327189829BD021DF4300E11"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>ECOLOGICAL MANAGEMENT &amp; RESTORATION VOL 6 NO 1 APRIL 2005 43<lb/> </reference>

	<note type="doctype">R E S E A R C H<lb/> R E P O R T<lb/> </note>

	<publisher>Blackwell Publishing, Ltd.<lb/></publisher>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Grassland structure in native pastures: links to soil<lb/> surface condition<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	By 
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sue McIntyre and David Tongway<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sue McIntyre</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(<address>GPO Box 284, Canberra, ACT<lb/> 2601, Australia.</address> 

	Tel. <phone>61-2 6242 1604</phone>. 
	Fax. 61-2<lb/> 6242 1565. Email:
	<email>Sue.Mcintyre@csiro.au</email>
	) and <lb/>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>David Tongway</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(<address>GPO Box 284, Canberra, ACT<lb/> 2601, Australia</address>. 
	Tel. 
	<phone>61-2 6242 1641</phone>. 
	Fax. 61-2<lb/> 6242 1565) 

	are from 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>CSIRO Sustainable Ecosys-<lb/>tems. </affiliation>
	</byline>

	This work was part of a longer-term study<lb/> identifying the practices associated with ecological<lb/> sustainability of grazing enterprises. Detailed<lb/> research has focused on how management affects<lb/> patterns of plant diversity in the subtropical<lb/> grassy woodlands of southern Queensland. Here,<lb/> they examine how well the appearance of a patch<lb/> of grassland can predict its ecological health.<lb/> 

	Summary 
	<div type="abstract">When grassland is grazed by livestock, the structure of the sward changes in<lb/> a patchy manner. With continuous selective grazing there is a mosaic of short and tall patches<lb/> but as grazing intensifies the area of short-grazed patch increases until the paddock has a<lb/> lawn-like appearance. This mosaic of patch structures can be stable, as short patches tend<lb/> to attract repeated grazing and tall patches tend to be avoided. Because heavy grazing can<lb/> detrimentally affect soil and water functions in grassland (ultimately resulting in erosion), we<lb/> aimed to assess how well the physical structure of the sward reflects soil surface condition.<lb/> We described four grassland patch structures that were assumed to reflect different levels of<lb/> present grazing, and to some extent, past grazing pressure. We assessed patch structure and<lb/> two other grass-related variables (basal area of a &apos;large tussock&apos; functional group and basal<lb/> area of all perennial grass) as possible indicators of soil surface condition. Three indices of<lb/> condition were measured in the field. The infiltration and nutrient cycling index declined<lb/> progressively across patch structures, consistent with increasing grazing pressure. The<lb/> stability index was found to be reduced only for the most heavily grazed grass structure (short<lb/> patches). We found the &apos;large tussock&apos; grass functional group to be a more sensitive indicator<lb/> of soil surface condition than the group consisting of all perennial grasses. We found no<lb/> evidence of sudden soil surface condition decline beyond a certain level of grass basal area,<lb/> that is, there was no evidence of thresholds, rather, incremental loss of condition accompanied<lb/> grass decline. We are thus not able to further refine an earlier proposed management rec-<lb/>ommendation &apos;Graze conservatively to maintain dominance of large and medium tussock<lb/> grasses over 60 -70% of the native pastures&apos;, except to suggest the use of short patches as<lb/> a more practical indicator, rephrasing the recommendation as &apos;Graze conservatively to allow<lb/> a maximum of 30% short-grazed patches in native pastures&apos;.<lb/></div>

	Key words
	<keyword>ecological thresholds, grassland, grazing, Landscape Function Analysis, sustainability.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
