<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="450056v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Oral microbial dysbiosis linked to worsened periodontal condition in rheumatoid<lb/> arthritis patients<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle> 

	Short title: Oral microbial dysbiosis and arthritis<lb/>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jôice Dias CORRÊA 1 , Gabriel R. FERNANDES 2 , Débora Cerqueira CALDERARO 3 , Santuza<lb/> Maria Souza MENDONÇA 1 , Janine Mayra Silva 1 , Mayra Laino ALBIERO 4 , Fernando Q<lb/> CUNHA 5 , E XIAO 6 , Gilda Aparecida FERREIRA 3 , Antônio Lúcio TEIXEIRA 3 , Chiranjit<lb/> MUKHERJEE 7 , Eugene J. LEYS 7 , Tarcília Aparecida SILVA 1 ¶ , Dana T. GRAVES 6 ¶*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1. Faculty of Dentistry, Federal University of Minas Gerais,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Belo Horizonte -MG, Brazil.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2. Oswaldo Cruz Fundation, René Rachou Research Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Belo Horizonte -MG, Brazil.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3. University Hospital, Federal University of Minas Gerais,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Belo Horizonte -MG, Brazil.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4. Faculty of Dentistry, University of Campinas,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Piracicaba -SP, Brazil.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5. Faculty of medicine of Ribeirão Preto, University of São Paulo</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>-SP, Brazil.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6. Penn Dental School, University of Pennsylvania,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Philadelphia -PA, USA.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>7. The Ohio State University, College of Dentistry,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Columbus -OH, USA.<lb/></address>

	¶ The two senior authors contributed equally to this publication<lb/> *Corresponding author:<lb/> E-mail:
	<email>dtgraves@upenn.edu</email>

	(DG) Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is an autoimmune disorder associated with increased<lb/> periodontal destruction. It is thought that RA increases the risk of periodontal disease; it is not<lb/> known how it influences the oral microbiota. Our aim was to analyze the impact of RA on<lb/> subgingival microbiota and its association with periodontal inflammation and RA activity.<lb/> Forty-two patients with RA were compared to 47 control subjects without RA. Patients were<lb/> screened for probing depth, clinical attachment level, bleeding on probing and classified as with<lb/> or without periodontitis. Subgingival plaque was examined by Illumina MiSeq Sequencing of<lb/> 16S rRNA gene V4 region and inflammatory cytokines were measured in saliva. RA was<lb/> associated to severe periodontal disease. In addition, the severity of RA, reflected by the number<lb/> of tender and swollen joints, was significantly correlated with the presence of pathogenic oral<lb/> bacteria (i.e. Fusobacterium nucleatum and Treponema socransky). Non-periodontitis RA<lb/> patients compared to healthy controls had increased microbial diversity and bacterial load,<lb/> higher levels of pathogenic species (Prevotella, Selenomonas, Anaeroglobus geminatus,<lb/> Parvimonas micra, Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans) and reduction of health-related<lb/> species (Streptococcus, Rothia aeria, Kingela oralis). Genes involved with bacterial virulence<lb/> (i.e. lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis, peptidases) were more prevalent in the subgingival<lb/> metagenome of subjects with RA. In addition, the degree of oral inflammation reflected by<lb/> IL-2, IL-6, TNF-, IFN- salivary levels was increased in non-periodontitis RA patients in<lb/> comparison with controls. Our findings support the hypothesis that RA triggers dysbiosis of<lb/> subgingival microbiota, which may contribute to worsening periodontal status.<lb/></div>

	Author Summary<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is an autoimmune disease characterized by joints inflammation,<lb/> swelling, pain and stiffness. Exactly what starts this disease is still unclear. Some recent studies<lb/> have suggested mucosal surfaces in the body, like those in the gums, could affect the disease<lb/> process. It has been observed that people with RA have higher risk of periodontitis (a bacterial<lb/> inflammatory disease of the gums), compared with the general population, and this may be the<lb/> start of the autoimmune process. Also, periodontitis increases the severity of RA while<lb/> interventions by treating periodontitis can improve the symptoms of RA. One of the possible<lb/> mechanisms that link the higher prevalence of periodontitis in RA patients is the dysbiosis of<lb/> the oral microbiota triggered by the chronic inflammation in RA. Increased levels of molecules<lb/> of inflammation may affect the oral environment and change the type of bacteria that live there.<lb/> Here, we examined RA patients and healthy subjects, screening their oral health and<lb/> inflammatory markers. We collected their saliva and the dental plaque from the space between<lb/> the teeth and the gum. We found that RA patients exhibited severe periodontitis, increased<lb/> levels of inflammatory mediators on their saliva and distinct bacterial communities, with higher<lb/> proportions of bacteria species linked to periodontal disease, even in patients without<lb/> periodontitis. We also found that the presence of these bacteria species was linked to worse RA<lb/> conditions. Our study provides new insights to understand the bi-directional mechanisms<lb/> linking periodontal disease to the development of RA, showing that we need to pay attention to<lb/> the oral cavity in patients with RA and refer people for dental evaluation. This practice might<lb/> have a positive impact in the course of RA.<lb/></div>

	KEYWORDS:
	<keyword>Oral Microbiota; Arthritis; Subgingival dental plaque, Dysbiosis.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
