<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="47._sdarticle"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of Visual Languages and Computing<lb/> (1992) 3, 221-236<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Hypertextual Concurrent Control of a Lisp Kernel<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>I&apos;. DAVID STO-ITS*$ AND RICHARD FURUTA-@<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>&apos;*Department of Computer and Information<lb/> Sciences, University of Florida,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gainesville, Florida<lb/> 32611, U.S.A. </address>

	and 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>fDepartment<lb/> of Computer Science and Institute for Advanced Computer<lb/> Studies, University of Maryland,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>College Park, Maryland 20742, U.S.A.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 16 December 1991 and accepted 14 February 1992<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Using the Trellis human/computer<lb/> interaction<lb/> model as an implementation<lb/> vehicle,<lb/> we demonstrate<lb/> how to use concurrency-supporting<lb/> hypertext to provide visual<lb/> displays of the execution flows through<lb/> a parallel Lisp program.<lb/> In addition to<lb/> displays, the hypertext interface allows injection of control flow into an otherwise<lb/> functional<lb/> computation,<lb/> and therefore provides reader control over the order and<lb/> speed of evaluation of expressions. The resulting system, termed ATrellis, can be<lb/> thought of as a concurrent control flow browser for composing functional computa-<lb/>tions, providing<lb/> a visual implementation<lb/> of kernel-control<lb/> decomposition.<lb/> The<lb/> advantages of ATrellis are ease of exploring program side-effects; ease of debugging<lb/> parallel code; aid in teaching functional<lb/> languages; and the ability to construct<lb/> hypertext documents that have parallel execution semantics and flexible browsing<lb/> behaviors.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
