<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005013"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>

			<reference>Information and Software Technology 53 (2011) 230–244<lb/></reference>

			<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">Information and Software Technology<lb/></note>
			<ptr type="web">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/infsof<lb/></ptr>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>A two-stage framework for UML specification matching<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Wei-Jin Park ⇑ , Doo-Hwan Bae<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Dept. of Computer Science, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and
					Technology,<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Republic of Korea</address>

			<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/></note>
			<note type="submission">Article history:<lb/>Received 9 January 2009<lb/> Received in
				revised form 28 October 2010<lb/> Accepted 2 November 2010<lb/></note> 
			<date>Available online 17
				November 2010<lb/></date>
			<keywords>Keywords:<lb/> Specification matching<lb/> UML Structure mapping<lb/> Graph
				similarity scoring<lb/></keywords>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<div type="abstract">a b s t r a c t<lb/> Context: Specification matching techniques are
				crucial for effective retrieval processes. Despite the prev-<lb/> alence for
				object-oriented methodologies, little attention has been given to Unified Modeling
				Language<lb/> (UML) for matching.<lb/> Objective: This paper presents a two-stage
				framework for matching two UML specifications and quanti-<lb/> fying the results
				based on the systematic integration of their structural and behavioral similarities
				in<lb/> order to identify the candidate component set for reuse.<lb/> Method: The
				first stage in the framework is an evaluation of the similarities between UML class
				diagrams<lb/> using the Structure-Mapping Engine (SME), a simulation of the
				analogical reasoning approach known as<lb/> the structure-mapping theory. The second
				stage, performed on the components identified in the first<lb/> stage, is based on a
				graph-similarity scoring algorithm in which UML class diagrams and sequence
				dia-<lb/> grams are transformed into an SME representation and a
				Message-Object-Order Graph (MOOG). The<lb/> effectiveness of the proposed framework
				was evaluated using a case study.<lb/> Results: The experimental results showed a
				reduction in potential mismatches and an overall high pre-<lb/> cision and
				recall.<lb/> Conclusion: It is concluded that the two-stage framework is capable of
				performing more precise matching<lb/> compared to those of other single-stage
				matching frameworks. Moreover, the two-stage framework could<lb/> be utilized within
				a reuse process, bypassing the need for extra information for retrieval of the
				compo-<lb/> nents described by UML.</div>
			<lb/>
			<note type="copyright">&#169; 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
