<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55008520"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>British journal o/Huernatology. 1992, 81, 614-621<lb/></reference>

	<note>Case Reports<lb/> </note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>PYRIDOXAL 5-PHOSPHATE THERAPY IN A PATIENT WITH MYELODYSPLASTIC SYNDROME AND ADULT<lb/> ONSET CONGENITAL ERYTHROPOIETIC PORPHYRIA<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="introduction">We report herein a patient who suffered from refractory<lb/> anaemia (RA), a subtype of the myelodysplastic syndrome<lb/> (MDS). with an acquired defect in porphyrin metabolism<lb/> consistent with congenital erythropoietic prophyria (CEP).<lb/> Marrow aspiration revealed a low percentage of ringed<lb/> sideroblasts which did not fulfil the FAb criteria of refractory<lb/> anaemia with ringed sideroblasts. However, we administered<lb/> pyridoxal 5-phosphate (PLP). the active cofactor of pyri-<lb/>doxine (vitamin Bb). which is the established treatment for<lb/> sideroblastic anaemia, to assess the effect on the haem<lb/> biosynthetic pathway. The abnormality in the porphyrin<lb/> metabolism associated with CEP improved with this treat-<lb/>ment. This approach may be helpful as an alternative<lb/> treatment to blood transfusion, charcoal or /I-carotene for<lb/> CEP.<lb/> In August 1989 a 63-year-old Japanese male noticed<lb/> reddish brown urine and tingling pain, redness, swelling and<lb/> thickening of sun-exposed skin. In September 1990 labora-<lb/>tory evaluations revealed normal serum aspartate amino-<lb/>transferase, alanine aminotransferase and y-glutamyl trans-<lb/>peptidase, but elevated alkaline phosphatase concentrations.<lb/> Neither the liver nor the spleen were palpable. His urine<lb/> contained elevated concentrations of coproporphyrin (COP)<lb/> (6735 pg/24 h) and uroporphyrin (3555 pg/24 h), but<lb/> normal concentrations of 6-aminolevulinic acid and porpho-<lb/>bilinogen. High-performance liquid chromatography<lb/> revealed 96.3% of the urinary.UP0 to be the I isomer.<lb/> Increased concentrations of porphyrins were also found in<lb/> the erythrocytes. Fecal COP was markedly increased to 40.7<lb/> mg/d. Although the patient exhibited none of the usual signs<lb/> of CEP in infancy and had no family history suggesting<lb/> porphyria, these biochemical findings supported the diagno-<lb/>sis of CEP rather than porphyria cutanea tarda. Haematologi-<lb/>cal data revealed pancytopenia with a haemoglobin concen-<lb/>tration of 7.1 g/dl, a platelet count of 10 x 10y/l, a leucocyte<lb/> count of 2.4 x 10y/l with 1% blasts, and 7 normoblasts per<lb/> 100 leucocytes. Bone marrow analysis revealed hypercellu-<lb/>larity with an increase in the erythroid series (76.6%). ringed<lb/> sideroblasts (4% of the total erythroblast count), megaloblas-<lb/>toid features, but no maturation arrest in the myeloid series,<lb/> Pelger-Huet-like anomalies in the neutrophils and haemosi-<lb/>derin-laden macrophages. Haemolysis was evident with<lb/> a shortened erythrocyte life span (13.8 d; normal range<lb/> 2 5-30 d), an elevated serum indirect bilirubin (1.0 mg/dl)<lb/> and positive urinary haemoglobin. but no reactive reticulocy-<lb/>tosis (2.45 x 10y/l). Plasma iron disappearance time was<lb/> shortened to 3 7 min (normal half-life range 60-120 min).<lb/> The percentage utilization of 59Fe for haemoglobin synthesis<lb/> was only 18%. indicating ineffective erythropoiesis. Finally, a<lb/> diagnosis of RA with adult onset CEP was made. Prednisolone<lb/> therapy was initiated at a dose of 1 5 mg daily, but this did not<lb/> reduce the excess excretion of urinary porphyrin and did not<lb/> improve the progressive pancytopenia. Photosensitivity<lb/> eruptions were totally unresponsive to oral pyridoxine.<lb/> Instead, subcutaneous injection of pyridoxal 5-phosphate<lb/> (PLP) was given at a dose of 30 mg/d. The urinary porphyrin<lb/> concentration decreased to the normal values during the<lb/> ensuing 5 months (Fig 1). The elevated serum indirect<lb/> bilirubin concentration decreased to values within the<lb/> normal range, and the urinary haemoglobin became nega-<lb/>tive within 2 months, however, the anaemia gradually<lb/> progressed. The cutaneous lesions disappeared gradually<lb/> over a period of 1 year. In March 1991 haematological<lb/> findings showed a haemoglobin concentration of 3.9 g/dl, a<lb/> leucocyte count of 6.9x1OY/1 and a platelet count of<lb/> 0.2 x 10y/l. The reticulocyte count had decreased to<lb/> 1.29 x 10y/l, and the erythroblasts had disappeared from the<lb/> blood. Blasts began to circulate at less than 5% of the total</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
