<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006880"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">Copyright 1999, Society of Petroleum Engineers Inc.<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">This paper was prepared for presentation at</note>

	<reference>the1999 SPE Annual Technical Conference and<lb/> Exhibition held in Houston, Texas, 3–6 October 1999.<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">This paper was selected for presentation by an SPE Program Committee following review of<lb/> information contained in an abstract submitted by the author(s). Contents of the paper, as<lb/> presented, have not been reviewed by the Society of Petroleum Engineers and are subject to<lb/> correction by the author(s). The material, as presented, does not necessarily reflect any<lb/> position of the Society of Petroleum Engineers, its officers, or members. Papers presented at<lb/> SPE meetings are subject to publication review by Editorial Committees of the Society of<lb/> Petroleum Engineers. Electronic reproduction, distribution, or storage of any part of this paper<lb/> for commercial purposes without the written consent of the Society of Petroleum Engineers is<lb/> prohibited. Permission to reproduce in print is restricted to an abstract of not more than 300<lb/> words; illustrations may not be copied. The abstract must contain conspicuous<lb/> acknowledgment of where and by whom the paper was presented. Write Librarian, SPE,</note>

	<address>P.O.<lb/> Box 833836, Richardson, </address>
	
	<phone>TX 75083-3836, U.S.A., fax 01-972-952-9435.<lb/></phone>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract Over the past few years, several &quot;premium&quot; sand control<lb/> screens have been introduced into the market. The<lb/> proliferation of new screens has raised questions about how to<lb/> choose the proper sand control screen for a particular<lb/> formation. In order to address this concern, a project was<lb/> initiated at Chevron to devise a method to evaluate sand<lb/> control screens.<lb/> As a result of this program, a method has been<lb/> standardized for the evaluation of sand control screens. The<lb/> method known as the Screen Efficiency Test shows the<lb/> relationship between the normalized sand control<lb/> characteristics (i.e., Sand Control Factor) of the screens and<lb/> the normalized length of time it takes a screen to plug under a<lb/> certain set of conditions (i.e., the Performance Factor). The<lb/> results of Screen Efficiency tests to evaluate several sand<lb/> control screens for a North Sea and West Africa field are<lb/> discussed in the paper.<lb/> The data in this paper also documents that the numerical<lb/> rating given the screens by the manufacturers are generally not<lb/> very useful in understanding the sand control rating of the<lb/> particular screen, or comparing screens from different<lb/> manufacturers.<lb/> In addition, the effect of particle size<lb/> distribution and sand concentration on the relative<lb/> performance of sand control screens was demonstrated.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
