<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007619"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Amnion-derived Cellular Cytokine Solution<lb/> A Physiological Combination of Cytokines for Wound Healing<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>David L. Steed, MD,<lb/> a,b Cathy Trumpower, BS,<lb/> b Danelle Duffy, MS,<lb/> b Charlotte Smith,<lb/> MS,<lb/> b Vivienne Marshall, PhD,<lb/> b Randall Rupp, PhD,<lb/> b Martin Robson, MD<lb/> b,d<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a University of Pittsburgh/UPMC,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pittsburgh, PA;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Stemnion, Inc, Pittsburgh, PA; University of South<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Florida, Tampa, FL; and<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>d Institute for Tissue Regeneration, Repair, Rehabilitation, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bay Pines VA<lb/>Medical Center, Bay Pines, FL<lb/></address>

	<email>Correspondence: steeddl@upmc.edu<lb/></email>

	<date type="publication">Published April 14, 2008<lb/></date>

	<div type="abstract">Objective: Wound repair is a complex integration of dynamic processes mediated by<lb/> humeral messages controlling the levels of cytokines, growth factors, and matrix met-<lb/>alloproteinases in the wound space. Isolated growth factors and growth factor combi-<lb/>nations have been used to accelerate wound healing with limited success. A cellular<lb/> cytokine solution can be collected by harvesting the proteins released from amnion-<lb/>derived multipotent progenitor cells. The purpose of this study was to compare levels<lb/> of cytokines/growth factors in amnion-derived cellular cytokine solution with physio-<lb/>logical levels reported in the medical literature. Methods: Amnion-derived multipotent<lb/> progenitor cells were grown to confluency, and the proteins secreted were characterized<lb/> by qualitative and quantitative analysis. These results were compared with physiologic<lb/> levels reported in the medical literature. Results: The results demonstrated that amnion-<lb/>derived cellular cytokine solution contained physiologic levels of cytokines relevant to<lb/> wound healing, including platelet-derived growth factor, vascular endothelial growth<lb/> factor, angiogenin, transforming growth factor β2, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-<lb/>1, and tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-2. The ranges (mean ± standard deviation)<lb/> were as follows: platelet-derived growth factor, 86 ± 33 pg/mL; vascular endothelial<lb/> growth factor, 5.7 ± 1.5 ng/mL; angiogenin, 1.0 ± 0.33 ng/mL; transforming growth<lb/> factor β2, 500 ± 330 pg/mL; tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-1, 530 ± 140 ng/mL;<lb/> and tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-2230 ± 40 ng/mL. These levels are compara-<lb/>ble with the physiologic levels reported in the literature. Conclusions: The physiologic<lb/> levels of cytokines important to healing found in amnion-derived cellular cytokine solu-<lb/>tion suggest that amnion-derived cellular cytokine solution may be of benefit in healing<lb/> certain acute and chronic wounds.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
