<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004869"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">45<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>IMMUNO-MAGNETIC SEPARATION FOLLOWED BY SOLID-PHASE<lb/> CYTOMETRY FOR THE RAPID DETECTION AND ENUMERATION OF<lb/> PATHOGENS IN SURFACE WATER<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>B. Pourima<lb/> 1<lb/> , C. Pougnard<lb/> 2<lb/> , C. Josson<lb/> 1<lb/> , P. Le Baron<lb/> 3<lb/> , E. Pringuez<lb/> 2<lb/> , J.L. Drocourt<lb/> 4<lb/> , P.A. Cabanes<lb/> 2<lb/> , &amp; S. Legastelois<lb/> 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Indicia Biotechnology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>33 avenue de la Californie, 69600 Oullins, France,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Electricité de France,<lb/> Division Recherche et Développement,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>6 quai Watier, 78401 Chatou Cedex, France,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Observatoire<lb/> Océanologique, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique CNRS-UMR7621, Université Paris<lb/> VI,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>66651 Banyuls-sur-Mer, France,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Chemunex, </affiliation>

	<address>3 allée de la Seine,</address>
	</byline>

	<address>94854 Ivry-sur-Seine Cedex,<lb/> France<lb/></address>

	<div type="introduction">INTRODUCTION: Contamination of surface<lb/> waters with pathogens such Naegleria fowleri,<lb/> Cryptosporidium parvum, Legionella pneumophila<lb/> is a major public health concern worldwide.<lb/> Detection and enumeration methods for these<lb/> pathogens in water are based on culture enrichment<lb/> to increase the concentration of viable organisms,<lb/> followed by immunofluorescence assay, enzyme-<lb/>immunoassay, polymerase-chain reaction, latex<lb/> agglutination test, flow cytometry, or enzyme<lb/> electrophoresis for identification and, to some<lb/> extent, enumeration.<lb/> There are two major drawbacks for simple and<lb/> rapid detection of pathogens in water. First, most<lb/> of the current methods are not sensitive enough to<lb/> detect small numbers of pathogens in their original<lb/> environment. Second, technologies that could<lb/> reach the required level of sensitivity are limited<lb/> by the fact that large volumes of water (1 to 100<lb/> liters) must be processed for one single analysis.<lb/> Membrane filtration often used is laborious, time-<lb/>consuming and non-selective, leading to the<lb/> presence in the filtrated samples of undesired<lb/> contaminants such PCR inhibitors, auto-<lb/>fluorescent events or cross-reactive unrelated<lb/> organisms.<lb/> The ChemScan<lb/> TM</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
