<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007212"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">This Article<lb/> Services<lb/> Email this article to a friend<lb/> Similar articles in this journal<lb/> Alert me to new issues of the journal<lb/> Download to citation manager<lb/> Citing Articles<lb/> Citing Articles via Google Scholar<lb/> Google Scholar<lb/> Articles by Strissel, K.<lb/> Articles by Arshavsky, V.<lb/> Search for Related Content<lb/> PubMed<lb/> Articles by Strissel, K.<lb/> Articles by Arshavsky, V.<lb/> HOME HELP<lb/> FEEDBACK SUBSCRIPTIONS<lb/> ARCHIVE SEARCH<lb/> QUICK SEARCH:<lb/> [advanced]<lb/> Go<lb/> Author:<lb/> Keyword(s):<lb/> Year:<lb/> Vol:<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="other">Page:<lb/></note>

	<reference>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 2002;43: E-Abstract 1387.<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">© 2002 ARVO<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>An In Situ Model for Investigating Mechanisms of Light-<lb/>Dependent Transducin Movement in Rod Photoreceptors of<lb/> the Rodent Retina<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>KJ Strissel, M Sokolov, IB Leskov, VI Govardovskii and VY Arshavsky<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Ophthalmology Harvard Medical School Boston MA<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<note type="other">Commercial Relationships: K.J. Strissel, None; M. Sokolov, None; I.B. Leskov, None; V.I.<lb/> Govardovskii, None; V.Y. Arshavsky, None.<lb/> Grant Identification: Knights Templar Pediatric Ophthalmology Award (KJS) NIH Grant<lb/> EY10336 (VYA) RPB (VYA)<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Purpose: Light stimulates both the alpha and beta/gamma subunits of the photoreceptor-specific G protein, transducin, to redistribute<lb/> from the rod outer segment (ROS) to other parts of the photoreceptor cell in living rats, leading to a reduction in photoresponse<lb/> sensitivity and contributing to light adaptation. As a first step towards determining the cellular mechanisms that control this light-<lb/>stimulated redistribution, we needed to develop a model that would allow us to uniformly and reliably deliver agents to the living retina<lb/> to test their potential effects upon light-stimulated transducin movement. Two models, an eyecup and isolated retina, were considered.<lb/> Methods: Rats were dark-adapted 15 hours prior to all experiments. The animals were euthanized and the eyes extracted under dim<lb/> red light. For eyecups, the extra ocular tissue, central cornea and the lens were carefully removed. For isolated retina, the entire<lb/> anterior portion of the eye was cut away and the retina dissected intact. Dissections were performed in supplemented Ringer&apos;s<lb/> maintained at 37 C with constant aeration (5% CO 2 /95% O 2 ). Retinas and eyecups were also maintained under these conditions for the<lb/> in situ cultures. For experiments, retinas and eyecups were then subjected to various time periods of illumination using a light source<lb/> measured by a calibrated light meter at a light intensity level known to stimulate maximal transducin movement in vivo. At the end of<lb/> the illumination period the isolated retinas or retinas freshly dissected from the illuminated eyecups were flat-mounted and immediately<lb/> frozen for serial tangential frozen sectioning and Western blot analysis for protein content determination.<lb/> Results: Retinas maintained in either the eyecup or isolated retina using these culture conditions exhibited light-stimulated transducin<lb/> redistribution when compared to cultured retinas left in the dark. The greatest extent of light-stimulated movement observed under the<lb/> in situ conditions for the transducin alpha subunit was 60% of the total alpha subunit pool, somewhat less than the maximum of 90%<lb/> observed in vivo. For the transducin beta subunit, 80% of the total pool redistributed from ROS upon illumination in situ, identical to<lb/> the maximum observed in vivo.<lb/> Conclusion: We succeeded in developing an in situ retina model in which light-stimulated transducin movement takes place very close<lb/> to the extent observed in the rodent retina in vivo. We may now use a pharmacological approach to begin testing specific hypotheses<lb/> about essential requirements and mechanisms of this phenomenon.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: 517 photoreceptors @BULLET 555 retina: distal(photoreceptors, horizontal cells, bipolar cells) @BULLET 560 retinal culture<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="copyright">© 2002, The Association for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology, Inc., all rights reserved. For permission to<lb/> reproduce any part of</note>

	<note type="other">this abstract, contact the ARVO Office at arvo@arvo.org.<lb/> HOME HELP<lb/> FEEDBACK SUBSCRIPTIONS<lb/> ARCHIVE SEARCH<lb/></note>

	<note>An In Situ Model for Investigating Mechanisms of Light-Dependent Tra ...<lb/> </note>

	<ptr type="web">http://abstracts.iovs.org/cgi/content/abstract/43/12/1387<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="page">1 of 1<lb/></note>

	<date>15-09-2011</date>

	<note type="other">10:41</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
