<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006057"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Rhodia presents its cost-effective and eco-friendly<lb/> surfactant technologies at Cesio 2008<lb/>Rhodia presents its cost-effective and<lb/> eco-friendly surfactant technologies at<lb/> Cesio 2008<lb/> News release<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	<div type="abstract">Paris (France) andBristol(PA,USA) -June 23, 2008-Improved cost-effectiveness and eco-friendly properties are the key factors strengthening<lb/> Rhodia&apos;s position as a global leader in the specialty surfactant market.<lb/> Rhodia provides innovative surfactant systems -structured surfactant liquids, polymeric and eco-friendly surfactants -for use in home and personal care,<lb/> agrochemicals and other industrial applications.<lb/> Rhodia uses sustainable chemistry to develop surfactant-based systems in partnership with customers delivering the following benefits:<lb/>  Cost-effective performance: increased process efficiency, energy and raw materials savings, highly-concentrated products;<lb/>  Sustainability: renewable resources utilization, eco-friendly product profile.<lb/> For the Personal Care market, Rhodia has designed Miracare® Plaisant, a new plant-based surfactant system that offers an eco-friendly solution for mild<lb/> and refreshing cleansing. Miracare® Plaisant is based on biodegradable and renewable ingredients, while providing flexibility and cost efficiency to<lb/> formulators.<lb/> In the Agrochemicals market, Geronol® CF/AR, a surfactant based-system, is a bio-activator for water soluble actives. It has an excellent tox and eco-<lb/>tox profile and is extremely compatible with concentrated glyphosate formulations and co-herbicides.<lb/> In Industrial applications, Rhodibloc® RS, a surfactant booster for emulsion stabilization, uses innovative chemistry for the industrial production of block<lb/> copolymers. It provides a cost-effective process solution for stabilization of water-in-oil emulsions, preventing coalescence and flocculation.<lb/> Rhodia&apos;s Novecare Enterprise supplies a large range of surfactants — cationic, anionic, non-ionic and amphoteric — delivering multi-functions adapted<lb/> to specific applications, including foaming effect, surface modification, cleansing, emulsion, rheology, environmental and health protection.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
