<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001536"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<date>05/18/2005 10:05 AM<lb/> </date>
	
	<reference>SVG Tiny 1.2<lb/></reference>
	
	<note type="page">Page 1 of 133<lb/></note>

	<ptr type="web">http://shadok.enst.fr:8080/svgAggregate/svgmobile12.main<lb/></ptr>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) Tiny 1.2 Specification<lb/> W3C Working Draft 13 April 2005<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<ptr type="web">This version:<lb/>

	http://www.w3.org/TR/ 2005/WD-SVGMobile12-20050413/<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="other">Previous version:<lb/>

	http://www.w3.org/TR/

	2004/WD-SVGMobile12-20040813/<lb/>

	Latest SVG Mobile 1.2 version:<lb/>

	http://www.w3.org/TR/SVGMobile12/<lb/>

	Latest SVG Mobile Recommendation:<lb/>

	http://www.w3.org/TR/SVGMobile /<lb/> Editors:<lb/> </note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ola Andersson</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>(Ikivo)</affiliation>
	</byline> 
	
	<email>&lt;ola.andersson@ikivo.com&gt;<lb/></email>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jon Ferraiolo</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>(Adobe Systems)</affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<email>&lt;jon.ferraiolo@adobe.com&gt;<lb/> </email>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Vincent Hardy</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>(Sun Microsystems, Inc.)</affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<email>&lt;vincent.hardy@sun.com&gt;<lb/> </email>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dean Jackson</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>(W3C)</affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<email>&lt;dean@w3.org&gt;<lb/> </email>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Antoine Quint</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>(Invited Expert)</affiliation>
	</byline>
	 	
	<email>&lt;aq@fuchsia-design.com&gt;<lb/> </email>
	
	<note type="other">Authors:<lb/> See author list<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="copyright">Copyright &amp;#xa9;2005 W3C<lb/> &amp;#xae; ( MIT , ERCIM , Keio), All Rights Reserved. W3C liability, trademark and document use rules apply.<lb/></note>
	
	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> This specification defines the features and syntax for Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) Tiny, Version 1.2, a modularized language for describing two-dimensional<lb/> vector and mixed vector/raster graphics in XML. SVG Tiny 1.2 is the baseline profile of SVG, implementable on a range of devices from cellphones and PDAs to<lb/> desktop and laptop computers, and is the core of SVG 1.2. Other SVG 1.2 specifications will extend this functionality to form supersets (for example, SVG 1.2 Full).
</div>

	<div type="introduction"><lb/> Status of this document<lb/> This section describes the status of this document at the time of its publication. Other documents may supersede this document. A list of current W3C publications<lb/> and the latest revision of this technical report can be found in the W3C technical reports index at http://www.w3.org/TR/.<lb/> This is a W3C Last Call Working Draft. If the feedback is positive, the SVG Working Group plans to submit this specification for consideration as a W3C Candidate<lb/> Recommendation. Comments for this specification should have a subject starting with the prefix &apos;[SVGMobile12]&apos;. Please send them to www-svg@w3.org, the public<lb/> email list for issues related to SVG. This list is archived and acceptance of this archiving policy is requested automatically upon first post. To subscribe to this list<lb/> send an email to www-svg-request@w3.org with the word subscribe in the subject line. Comments are accepted until 20 May 2005.<lb/> Previous versions of this specification expressed the SVG Tiny 1.2 language as a profile; a set of pointers to portions of the SVG 1.1 and SVG 1.2 specifications<lb/> plus a list of restrictions. Feedback from implementors and reviewers indicated that this was hard to follow and may have lacked precision. In this version, SVG Tiny<lb/> 1.2 is described as a complete language specification, with no dependencies on other SVG specifications. This makes it a first class citizen, and is easier to read<lb/> and to implement.<lb/> This document has been produced by the SVG Working Group as part of the W3C Graphics Activity, following the procedures set out for the W3C Process. The<lb/> authors of this document are listed at the end in the Author List section.<lb/> The patent policy for this document is the 5 February 2004 W3C Patent Policy. Patent disclosures relevant to this specification may be found on the SVG Working<lb/> Group&apos;s patent disclosure page. An individual who has actual knowledge of a patent which the individual believes contains Essential Claim(s) with respect to this<lb/> specification should disclose the information in accordance with section 6 of the W3C Patent Policy.<lb/> Publication as a Working Draft does not imply endorsement by the W3C Membership. This is a draft document and may be updated, replaced or obsoleted by other<lb/> documents at any time. It is inappropriate to cite this document as other than work in progress.<lb/> Available languages<lb/> The English version of this specification is the only normative version. However, for translations in other languages see

	http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/svg-<lb/>updates/translations.html.<lb/>

	Table of Contents<lb/> 1 Introduction<lb/> 2 Concepts<lb/> 3 Rendering Model<lb/> 4 Basic Data Types and Color Keywords<lb/> 5 Document Structure<lb/> 6 Styling<lb/> 7 Coordinate Systems, Transformations and Units<lb/> 8 Paths<lb/> 9 Basic Shapes<lb/> 10 Text<lb/> 11 Painting: Filling, Stroking, Colors and Paint Servers<lb/> 12 Multimedia<lb/> 13 Interactivity<lb/> 14 Linking<lb/> 15 Scripting<lb/> 16 Animation<lb/> 17 Fonts<lb/> 18 Metadata<lb/> 19 Extensibility
	</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
