<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002063"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A SIP-based Web Session Migration Service<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Michael Adeyeye, Neco Ventura and *David Humphrey<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Electrical Engineering, University of Cape Town,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Private Bag X3, Rondebosch 7701, South Africa<lb/></address>

	<email>{micadeyeye; neco}@crg.ee.uct.ac.za<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>*School of Computer Studies, Seneca College,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Toronto, Canada<lb/></address>

	<email>david.humphrey@senecac.on.ca<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract-Web session handoff is one of the ways of improving<lb/> the web browsing experience; other ways include the use of<lb/> bookmarks and web history synchronization between two PCs.<lb/> This paper discusses the implementation and evaluation of a SIP-<lb/>based web session migration service. A graphical tool, which is<lb/> called Data Flow Diagram, is used to describe how the session<lb/> migration service works. This work is compared with other<lb/> existing web session migration approaches. In addition, the large<lb/> scale deployment and limitations of the service are also discussed.<lb/> Although all web sessions could not be migrated, the session<lb/> mobility service worked in a Peer-to-Peer environment and<lb/> offered SIP functionalities within web browsers. That is, a web<lb/> browser can now act as an adaptive User Agent Client to surf the<lb/> Internet and set-up multimedia sessions like a SIP client. In<lb/> summary, it is a novel approach to web session migration in<lb/> which SIP is used to transfer session data. It also borrowed SIP<lb/> Mobility mechanisms to introduce new service, namely content<lb/> sharing and session handoff, to the web browsing experience.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: Web Session Migration, SIP, HTTP, Web Browser<lb/> Extension<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
