<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000009-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<note type="other">Methane Activation<lb/></note>

			<idno>DOI: 10.1002/anie.201100606<lb/></idno>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Diatomic [CuO] + and Its Role in the Spin-Selective Hydrogen-and<lb/>
					Oxygen-Atom Transfers in the Thermal Activation of Methane**<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Nicolas Dietl, Christian van der Linde, Maria Schlangen, Martin K. Beyer,
					and Helmut Schwarz*<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<note type="dedication">Dedicated to Professor Hans-Joachim Freund on the occasion of his 60th
				birthday<lb/></note>

			<div type="abstract">The activation of methane and its subsequent conversion into<lb/>
				more valuable feedstocks at ambient conditions is regarded as<lb/> one of the major
				challenges in contemporary catalysis. [1] In<lb/> this context, two different
				transformations are of particular<lb/> interest. The first one concerns the
				oxidative coupling of<lb/> methane (OCM) to the C 2 hydrocarbons ethane and
				ethylene<lb/> using metal oxide based catalysts in heterogeneous cataly-<lb/>sis;
				[1c,d, 2] the second process is the selective oxidation of<lb/> methane to methanol,
				which is performed in nature by the<lb/> methane monoxygenase (MMO) metalloenzymes.
				[3] Soluble<lb/> MMO (sMMO) contains a well-characterized doubly oxygen-<lb/>bridged
				di-iron cluster; in contrast, the reactivity of partic-<lb/>ulate MMO (pMMO), after
				a long controversy about the<lb/> nature of its active site, has been shown to
				depend on<lb/> copper. [4]<lb/> A useful approach to investigate model systems
				for<lb/> oxygen-containing catalysts takes advantage of state-of-the-<lb/>art
				gas-phase experiments conducted in a mass spectrometer,<lb/> in conjunction with
				computational studies; this combined<lb/> experimental and theoretical approach
				provides insight into<lb/> the elementary steps of these reactions at a molecular
				level<lb/> and, thus, permits us to unravel detailed mechanistic aspects. [5]<lb/>
				For example, the efficient gas-phase activation of methane at<lb/> room temperature
				has been demonstrated to be brought<lb/> about by a variety of systems, including
				transition-and main-<lb/>group-metal oxides [6] as well as some selected
				nonmetal<lb/> oxides [7] and mixed metal/nonmetal oxides; [8] based on these<lb/>
				studies, a rather detailed understanding of the intriguing<lb/> mechanistic aspects
				has been arrived at.<lb/> With respect to biological relevance, it was
				demonstrated<lb/> twenty years ago that bare [FeO] + is capable of activating<lb/>
				methane at room temperature. [9] The now well-established<lb/> concept of two-state
				reactivity (TSR), [10] which also proved<lb/> important in describing the mechanisms
				of metalloenzyme-<lb/>mediated reactions, is in fact based on a detailed analysis
				of<lb/> the gas-phase reactions of this simple, diatomic reagent<lb/> [FeO] + . Yet,
				only recently has a complete description of the<lb/> gas-phase conversion of methane
				to methanol by [FeO] + been<lb/> achieved; this elucidation was based on advanced
				gas-phase<lb/> spectroscopy combined with rather high-level calculations. [11]<lb/>
				Further, while the detailed nature of the active copper<lb/> oxide species in pMMO
				had been under debate for quite<lb/> some time, [3, 4, 12] bare [CuO] + was
				predicted a decade ago to<lb/> be a suitable, if not extremely powerful, candidate
				to mediate<lb/> the methane to methanol conversion. [13, 14] However, no
				gas-<lb/>phase experiments with bare [CuO] + have been reported to<lb/> date. The
				ligated cation [Cu(O)(phen)] + (phen = 1,10-phe-<lb/>nanthroline) brings about
				activation of small hydrocarbons,<lb/> that is, propane or butane, but it is not
				powerful enough to<lb/> attack the thermodynamically strong and kinetically inert C
				À<lb/> H bond of methane. [15] Owing to the relatively low dissoci-<lb/>ation energy
				D 0 (Cu + ÀO) = 130 kJ mol À1 , [5a, 16] it proved rather<lb/> difficult to produce
				sufficient amounts of [CuO] + to probe its<lb/> reactivity in bond-activation
				processes, and various attempts<lb/> to generate this cationic metal oxide by, for
				example, electro-<lb/>spray ionization mass spectrometry failed. [5j, 15] Thus,
				[CuO] +<lb/> is to date the only bare transition-metal oxide cation of the<lb/>
				first row whose reactivity towards methane has not been<lb/> experimentally
				investigated.<lb/> Herein we present our results on 1) the successful<lb/> formation
				of gaseous [CuO] + and 2) its reactivity towards<lb/> methane at thermal conditions.
				Briefly, [CuO] + is generated<lb/> by laser desorption/ionization from isotopically
				pure copper<lb/> 63 Cu targets, suitable for the laser-vaporization/ionization<lb/>
				source of an FT-ICR mass spectrometer in the presence of a<lb/> He/N 2 O plasma (for
				details about the instrumental setup, see<lb/> the Experimental Section). As shown
				in Figure 1, [CuO] +<lb/> brings about efficient activation of methane at room
				temper-<lb/>ature both by hydrogen abstraction [Eq. (1)] and by oxygen-<lb/>atom
				transfer [Eq. (2)]. Furthermore, the open-shell product<lb/> cation [CuOH]C + itself
				also homolytically cleaves the CÀH<lb/> bond of a second methane molecule, thus
				giving rise to the<lb/> formation of a closed-shell water complex [Eq. (3)].
				[17]<lb/> ½CuOHC þ þ CH 4 ! ½CuðOH 2 Þ þ þ CH 3 C<lb/> ð3Þ</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
