<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006572"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The effects of Self Assembled Monolayer(SAM) on the back<lb/> back interface of a-IGZO TFT.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1<lb/> Seung-Hwan Cho,<lb/> 1 Yong-Uk Lee,<lb/> 1 Jeong-Soo Lee,<lb/> 2 Kang-<lb/>Moon Jo,<lb/> 2 Do-Hwan Kim,<lb/> 1 Bo-Sung Kim, and<lb/> 1<lb/> Min-Koo Han<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science<lb/> Seoul National University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gwanak-ro 599, Gwanak-gu, Seoul, Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Samsung Electronics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Mt. 14-1, Giheung-Gu,<lb/> Yongin-Si, Gyeonggi-Do 446-712, Korea<lb/></address>

	<phone>Tel.: +82-2-880-7992, Fax: +82-2-871-7992,<lb/> </phone>
	
	<email>E-mail: mkh@snu.ac.kr<lb/></email>

	<div type="introduction">The a-GIZO TFTs have attracted considerable attention for a<lb/> next generation display due to its high mobility and good<lb/> uniformity[1,2]. The passivation on the back surface of the<lb/> active layer is a important issue to protect back interface from<lb/> moisture or plasma damage because the back channel may<lb/> control the reliability of the device.[3]<lb/> It has been reported that the moisture and oxygen are strongly<lb/> associated with caracteristics of oxide transistors. Since H 2 O and<lb/> O 2 molecules are adsorbed or desorbed on the oxide<lb/> semiconductor, they can easily capture electrons or release<lb/> electrons.[4] During the adsorption or desorption process,<lb/> electrical properties of oxide semiconductor are changed<lb/> considerably.<lb/> The purpose of the paper is to report for the first time that<lb/> SAM(self-assembled monolayer), which consists of a functional<lb/> group at the terminal and the head group at the other end,<lb/> improve the back interface properties of a-IGZO TFT. The<lb/> ordered SAMs with molecular dipole moment generate the local<lb/> electric field and have a influence on the Vth of the oxide<lb/> semiconductor. Also a hydrophobic SAM can be used in<lb/> blocking moisture efficiently. In addition, SAM can suppress<lb/> various plasma damages considerably as a very thin organic<lb/> layer.<lb/> We fabricated bottom gate a-GIZO TFTs. 200nm Mo metal is<lb/> deposited on a glass substrate as a gate electrode with a 300nm<lb/> SiOx insulator on top of it. A 40nm ITO metal is used as a drain<lb/> and source electrodes. The a-IGZO active layer was formed by<lb/> sputtering method. Each layers are patterned by<lb/> photolithography and etching. Finally we deposited 3 different<lb/> SAMs(3-chloropropyltriethoxysilane, Triethoxy(octyl)silane and<lb/> (3-Aminopropyl)triethoxysilane) on the oxide TFT by solution<lb/> method.[5]<lb/> After SAM treatment, we observed the different Vth shift of<lb/> oxide TFTs with 3 different SAMs treatment as shown in Table<lb/> 1. In the case of Cl-SAM(3-chloropropyltriethoxysilane) and<lb/> NH 2 -SAM((3-Aminopropyl)triethoxysilane), the Vth is shifted<lb/> to a negative direction while that for CH 3 -SAM is shifted to a<lb/> positive direction. This phenomenon can be explained from the<lb/> fact that SAM has a dipole moment according to a functional<lb/> group. The dipole moment is positive in Cl-, F-, and NH 2 -<lb/>functional group, while it is negative in CH 3 -functional group.<lb/> So each SAMs can generate the built-in local electric field that<lb/> accumulates or release electrons on the oxide semiconductor.[6]<lb/> Cl-SAM with negative dipole moment create local electric field<lb/> normal to semiconductor and this electric field provides<lb/> electrons to the active layer similar to a negative back gate.<lb/> Therefore Cl-SAM with a negative dipole mement forms a high<lb/> conductive back channel which requires more negative gate bias<lb/> in order to deplete the active channel layer. This agrees fairly<lb/> well that we observed smaller negative Vth shift in NH 2 -SAM<lb/> with less dipole moment and positive Vth shift in CH 3 -SAM<lb/> with opposite dipole direction.<lb/> Also, in order to investigate SAM as a blocking layer from<lb/> moisture and oxygen, we measured the bias stability of a-IGZO<lb/> TFTs. We observed similar positive Vth shift in both deviece(A)<lb/> with Cl-SAM and device(B) without SAM under positive gate<lb/> bias stress.(Vg=+20V, Vds=0.1V, from 0s to 1000s). In contrast,<lb/> device A shows very small negative Vth shift while the<lb/> Von(turn on voltage) is shifted to a positive direction including a<lb/> change of swing value in device B under negative gate bias<lb/> stress(Vg=-20V, Vds=10V, from 0s to 1000s) as shown in fig. 2.<lb/> It was reported previously that H 2 O molecules can act as<lb/> acceptorlike deep trap as well as electron donors on the a-IGZO<lb/> surface[3]. In case of accompanying a change of swing value,<lb/> H 2 O molecules are closely involved in it. So it can be inferred<lb/> that SAM blocked moisture effectively in device A without any<lb/> significant change in Vth, swing.<lb/> We also investigated SAM as a plasma protecting layer at the<lb/> back side of oxide TFT. After SAM deposition, the device was<lb/> treated with CF 4 plasma. While the device without SAM was<lb/> degraded severely, there was no degradation in the device with<lb/> SAM as shown in Fig 3. The proposed SAM suppressed CF 4<lb/> plasma damage successfully.<lb/> Our experimental result shows that by employing SAM on the<lb/> back interface of the active layer, the back channel was<lb/> protected from moisture for better stability and SAM suppressed<lb/> various troublesome plasma damage without any additional<lb/> photolithography process. We also observed different Vth shifts<lb/> of a-IGZO TFT according to the dipole moment of each SAMs.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
