<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000741"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">http://www.gnpd.com<lb/> This information is supplied in accordance with Mintel&apos;s Terms &amp; Conditions. 1<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Vegetable Bread Spread<lb/> with Mild Olive Oil<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="introduction">Record
	

	ID:<lb/> 1334818 Company:<lb/> Unilever Brand:<lb/> Bertolli Category:<lb/> Dairy Sub-Category:<lb/> Margarine &amp; Other<lb/> Blends Country:<lb/> Netherlands Date Published:<lb/> May 2010<lb/> Product source:<lb/> Shopper Launch Type:<lb/> New Formulation<lb/>

	Price in local currency: 0.99<lb/> Price in US Dollars:<lb/> 1.28<lb/> Bar Code:<lb/> 5410003104783<lb/>

	Product Description<lb/>

	Bertolli Vegetable Voor OpBrood Met Milde Olijfolie (Bread Spread with Mild Olive Oil) now features a new formula. It is<lb/> rich in monounsaturated fatty acids and is suitable for cooking and baking. The product is suitable for vegetarians and<lb/> retails in a 250g tub with a new look.<lb/>

	Product Analysis<lb/> Package Type:<lb/> Tub Package Material:<lb/> Plastic PP<lb/> Pack Size:<lb/> 250.00<lb/> Storage:<lb/> Shelf stable<lb/> Alcohol By Volume (%):<lb/> Private Label:<lb/> Branded<lb/>

	Product Variants<lb/> Product Variant<lb/> Flavours Format Type<lb/> Claims Still Selling<lb/> Vegetable Bread<lb/> Spread with Mild Olive<lb/> Oil<lb/> Unflavoured/Plain<lb/> — Vegetarian<lb/> —<lb/>
	

	Ingredients:<lb/> Waters, Vegetable Fats and Oils (Vegetable Based) (Olive Oil (Refined)), Modified Starches<lb/> (Modified), Salt, emulsifiers (Mono-and Di-glycerides of Fatty Acids, Lecithin), Whey, Potassium<lb/> Sorbate (Preservatives), Citric Acid (Food Acids), Flavouring Substances, Beta-carotene (Food<lb/> Colours), Vitamins (Vitamin A, Vitamin D, Vitamin E)<lb/> Nutrition:<lb/> Per 10g serving: Energy 150kJ/35kcal, Protein &lt;0.1g, Carbohydrate &lt;0.5g (of which Sugars &lt;0.1g),<lb/> Fat 3.8g (of which Saturated Fat 0.9g, Monounsaturated fat 2.1g, Polyunsaturated fat 1g, Trans Fat<lb/> &lt;0.01g), Fibres &lt;0.1g, Sodium 0.1g, Vitamin A 80µg (10% ADH), Vitamin D 0.8µg (15% ADH),<lb/> Vitamin E 1.8mg (18% ADH)<lb/>

	Annotations<lb/> Additional Product Images</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
