<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005171"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<note type="other">1962</note>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<reference>IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 8, NO. 4, APRIL
				2009<lb/></reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Fast Multiple Access Selection through<lb/> Variable Power
					Transmissions<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Raymond Yim, Member, IEEE, Neelesh B. Mehta, Senior Member, IEEE,<lb/>
					and Andreas F. Molisch, Fellow, IEEE<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract—Many wireless applications demand a fast mech-<lb/> anism
				to detect the packet from a node with the highest<lb/> priority ("best node") only,
				while packets from nodes with lower<lb/> priority are irrelevant. In this paper, we
				introduce an extremely<lb/> fast contention-based multiple access algorithm that
				selects the<lb/> best node and requires only local information of the
				priorities<lb/> of the nodes. The algorithm, which we call Variable Power<lb/>
				Multiple Access Selection (VP-MAS), uses the local channel state<lb/> information
				from the accessing nodes to the receiver, and maps<lb/> the priorities onto the
				receive power. It is based on a key result<lb/> that shows that mapping onto a set
				of discrete receive power levels<lb/> is optimal, when the power levels are chosen
				to exploit packet<lb/> capture that inherently occurs in a wireless physical layer.
				The<lb/> VP-MAS algorithm adjusts the expected number of users that<lb/> contend in
				each step and their respective transmission powers,<lb/> depending on whether
				previous transmission attempts resulted<lb/> in capture, idle channel, or collision.
				We also show how reliable<lb/> information regarding the total received power at the
				receiver<lb/> can be used to improve the algorithm by enhancing the feedback<lb/>
				mechanism. The algorithm detects the packet from the best node<lb/> in 1.5 to 2.1
				slots, which is considerably lower than the 2.43 slot<lb/> average achieved by the
				best algorithm known to date.<lb/>
			</div>
			<keywords> Index Terms—Multiuser diversity, splitting algorithms, multi-<lb/> ple
				access, capture, collision, relay selection, power control.<lb/>
			</keywords>
			<div type="introduction">I. INTRODUCTION<lb/> 
			</div>
			
			<note type="submission"> Manuscript received February 28, 2008; revised July 14, 2008
				and October<lb/> 17, 2008; accepted December 17, 2008. The associate editor
				coordinating the<lb/> review of this paper and approving it for publication was V.
				K. N. Lau.<lb/>
			</note>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>R. Yim is with Mitsubishi Electric Research Labs
					(MERL),</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Cambridge,<lb/> MA, USA</address>
			<email>(e-mail: yim@merl.com).<lb/></email>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>N. B. Mehta is with the Indian Institute of Science
					(IISc),<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Bangalore, India.<lb/></address>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>A. F. Molisch is with the University of Southern
					California,</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Los Angeles,<lb/> USA.</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>At the time of this work he was with MERL,<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Cambridge, MA, USA.<lb/></address>

			<note type="other">A part of this work was presented at ICC 2008.<lb/></note>
			<idno>Digital Object Identifier 10.1109/TWC.2009.080260</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
