<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003983"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Metals Technologies<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SIMETAL LiquiRob for EAF<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">The main demands to be met by modern steel<lb/> production are high productivity, high production<lb/> flexibility and a high product quality level.<lb/> Robots are common in operation in high<lb/> productivity, reproducible and flexible industries,<lb/> for example, in car assembling manufacture.<lb/> Now, Siemens VAI, as a pioneer in innovating<lb/> processes, technologies and automation at steel<lb/> plants, introduces a robot suitable for the harsh<lb/> operation conditions and rough environment<lb/> at casters, secondary metallurgical plants,<lb/> converters and also EAFs.<lb/> Our answer to these demands is an extremely fast<lb/> Siemens VAI robot performing fully automatic<lb/> temperature and sample measurements cycles<lb/> including cartridge replacement, so that manual<lb/> and even manipulator measurement are obsolete.<lb/> Your challenge:<lb/> Personnel health and safety when working in the<lb/> vicinity of steel, slag and extremly hot environment<lb/> is our main concern. The steelplant managers take<lb/> full responsibilty regarding health and safety of their<lb/> employees as well as strict compliance with the<lb/> associated legislation.<lb/> A further issue is accuracy and reliability in<lb/> performing measurement and taking samples during<lb/> production, having direct influence on the quality<lb/> of the produced steel and on productivity thanks to<lb/> faster cycle times and less measurement errors.<lb/> Our solution:<lb/> With the SIMETAL LiquiRob, Siemens VAI provides a<lb/> highly flexible robot-aided measuring and sampling<lb/> solution that gives you the flexibility and reliability<lb/> needed to ensure uninterrupted, fail-safe and<lb/> controlled EAF steel production.<lb/> The SIMETAL LiquiRob will replace mechanical<lb/> manipulators benefiting from higher availibility and<lb/> easy upgrading and learning of new operations. In<lb/> many cases it will prevent operators from making<lb/> temperature or celox measurements or taking<lb/> samples. Thanks to the SIMETAL LiquiRob, work in<lb/> hazardous areas is largely eliminated.<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">SIMETAL LiquiRob at RIVA Neuves-Maisons, France<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Robot-aided measuring and sampling at EAF.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
