<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55008020"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>JOURNAL OF CLINICAL MICROBIOLOGY,<lb/></reference>

	<idno>0095-1137/99/$04.00ϩ0<lb/></idno>

	<reference>Dec. 1999, p. 3990–3996<lb/> Vol. 37, No. 12<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 1999, American Society for Microbiology. All Rights Reserved.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Sensitive and Specific Serodiagnosis of Lyme Disease by<lb/> Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay with a Peptide<lb/> Based on an Immunodominant Conserved<lb/> Region of Borrelia burgdorferi VlsE<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<docAuthor>FANG TING LIANG,<lb/> 1 ALLEN C. STEERE,<lb/> 2 ADRIANA R. MARQUES,<lb/> 3<lb/> BARBARA J. B. JOHNSON,<lb/> 4 JAMES N. MILLER,<lb/> 5 AND MARIO T. PHILIPP<lb/> 1 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Parasitology, Tulane Regional Primate Research Center, Tulane University Medical Center, Covington,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Louisiana 70433;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Division of Rheumatology, New England Medical Center, Tufts University School of Medicine,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, Massachusetts 02111<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 ; National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bethesda, Maryland 20892<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 ; Division of Vector-Borne Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control<lb/> and Prevention,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Fort Collins, Colorado 80522<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 ; and Department of Microbiology and Immunology,<lb/> University of California at Los Angeles,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Los Angeles, California 90095<lb/> 5<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 30 June 1999/Returned for modification 12 August 1999/Accepted 19 August 1999<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">VlsE, the variable surface antigen of Borrelia burgdorferi, contains an immunodominant conserved region<lb/> named IR 6 . In the present study, the diagnostic performance of a peptide enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay<lb/> (ELISA) based on a 26-mer synthetic peptide (C 6 ) with the IR 6 sequence was explored. Sensitivity was assessed<lb/> with serum samples (n ‫؍‬ 210) collected from patients with clinically defined Lyme disease at the acute (early<lb/> localized or early disseminated disease), convalescent, or late disease phase. The sensitivities for acute-,<lb/> convalescent-, and late-phase specimens were 74% (29 of 39), 85 to 90% (34 of 40 to 35 of 39), and 100% (59<lb/> of 59), respectively. Serum specimens from early neuroborreliosis patients were 95% positive (19 of 20), and<lb/> those from an additional group of patients with posttreatment Lyme disease syndrome yielded a sensitivity of<lb/> 62% (8 of 13). To assess the specificity of the peptide ELISA, 77 serum samples from patients with other<lb/> spirochetal or chronic infections, autoimmune diseases, or neurologic diseases and 99 serum specimens from<lb/> hospitalized patients in an area where Lyme disease is not endemic were examined. Only two potential false<lb/> positives from the hospitalized patients were found, and the overall specificity was 99% (174 of 176). Precision,<lb/> which was assessed with a panel of positive and negative serum specimens arranged in blinded duplicates, was<lb/> 100%. Four serum samples with very high anti-OspA antibody titers obtained from four monkeys given the<lb/> OspA vaccine did not react with the C 6 peptide. This simple, sensitive, specific, and precise ELISA may<lb/> contribute to alleviate some of the remaining problems in Lyme disease serodiagnosis. Because of its synthetic<lb/> peptide base, it will be inexpensive to manufacture. It also will be applicable to serum specimens from<lb/> OspA-vaccinated subjects.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
