<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004285"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of Ethnopharmacology 133 (2011) 364–370<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/> Journal of Ethnopharmacology<lb/> j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : </note>
	<ptr>w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / j e t h p h a r m<lb/></ptr>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A biochemical comparison of the in vivo effects of Bulbine frutescens and Bulbine<lb/> natalensis on cutaneous wound healing<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Nalini Pather<lb/> a,* , Alvaro M. Viljoen<lb/> b , Beverley Kramer<lb/> a<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Embryonic Differentiation and Development Research Programme, School of Anatomical Sciences, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of the Witwatersrand,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Johannesburg,<lb/> South Africa<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences Programme, Tshwane University of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pretoria, South Africa<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Article history:<lb/> Received 28 May 2010<lb/> Received in revised form 1 October 2010<lb/> Accepted 4 October 2010<lb/></note>

	<date>Available online 19 October 2010<lb/></date>

	<keyword>Keywords:<lb/> Wound healing<lb/> Bulbine Biochemical<lb/> Collagen Hexoamine<lb/> Protein DNA<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">a b s t r a c t<lb/> Aim of the study: In South Africa the local population relies extensively on indigenous plants in the for-<lb/>mulation of traditional medicines to treat skin ailments. The scientific merits of many of these plants<lb/> used to treat wounds and burns are yet to be validated. Bulbine natalensis and Bulbine frutescens of the<lb/> Asphodelaceae family are indigenous to only southern Africa and are widely used as a skin remedy. This<lb/> study aimed to explore the scientific value of these plants through investigating the in vivo biochemical<lb/> effects of Bulbine natalensis and Bulbine frutescens on cutaneous wounds.<lb/> Material and methods: Excisional and incisional wounds treated with either B. natalensis or B. frutescens<lb/> and mirrored control wounds were created on the back of 12 domestic pigs. Wound contraction was<lb/> recorded daily. The excisional wounds, biopsied at days 2, 4, 7, 10 and 16, were used to analyse the<lb/> biochemical composition of the wounds by estimating the total amount of protein, DNA, collagen and<lb/> hexosamine present. The incisional wounds, biopsied at day 16, were used to test the tensile strength of<lb/> the healed wounds using a tensiometer.<lb/> Results: Wound contraction following treatment with Bulbine natalensis on days 2, 4 and 10 (p = .004, 0.007<lb/> and 0.03, respectively), and Bulbine frutescens on day 4 (p = 0.004) increased significantly when compared<lb/> to the corresponding untreated wounds. The tensile strength of the wounds treated with the leaf gels<lb/> was significantly stronger than that of the untreated wounds. There was also a significant increase in the<lb/> collagen, protein and DNA content of the Bulbine natalensis-and Bulbine frutescens-treated wounds com-<lb/>pared with that of the untreated wounds (collagen content: p = 0.014 and 0.018; protein content: p = 0.03<lb/> and 0.04; DNA content p = 0.04 and 0.04; respectively) over the 16-day experimental period. Treatment<lb/> with both leaf gels followed the same pattern in hexosamine content with a maximum hexosamine con-<lb/>tent on day 4 followed by a steady decrease to day 16. No significant difference between the hexosamine<lb/> content of the wounds of animals treated with either Bulbine frutescens or Bulbine natalensis was found.<lb/> Conclusions: These findings validate the traditional use of the leaf gel extracts of B. frutescens and B.<lb/> natalensis in the treatment of wounds and may warrant further investigation towards producing a low-<lb/>cost effective topical treatment for wounds.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2010 Elsevier Ireland Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
