<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000029-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Macromolecules 2009, 42, 6671–6681<lb/></reference>
			<note type="other">6671<lb/></note>
			<idno>DOI: 10.1021/ma901169r<lb/></idno>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Effect of Sequence Distribution on the Morphology, Crystallization,<lb/>
					Melting, and Biodegradation of Poly(ε-caprolactone-co-ε-caprolactam)<lb/>
					Copolymers<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Rose Mary Michell,† Alejandro J. M€ller,*,† Valeria Castelletto,‡ Ian Hamley,‡<lb/>
					Gaelle Deshayes,§ and Philippe Dubois§<lb/>
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>†Grupo de Polıeros USB, Departamento de Ciencia de los Materiales,
					Universidad Sim on Bolıar,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Apartado<lb/> 89000, Caracas 1080-A, Venezuela,</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>‡Department of Chemistry, University of Reading,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Reading RG6 6AD, United Kingdom,<lb/></address>

			<note type="other">and</note>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>§Laboratory of Polymeric and Composite Materials,
					Center of Innovation and Research<lb/> in Materials &amp; Polymers (CIRMAP),
					University of Mons-Hainaut,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Place du Parc 20, Mons B-7000, Belgium<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received May 31, 2009; Revised Manuscript Received July 28,
				2009<lb/></note>

			<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT: Two types of poly(ε-caprolactone
				(CLo))-co-poly(ε-caprolactam (CLa)) copolymers were<lb/> prepared by catalyzed
				hydrolytic ring-opening polymerization. Both cyclic comonomers were added<lb/>
				simultaneously in the reaction medium for the first type of materials where
				copolymers have a random<lb/> distribution of counits, as evidenced by 1 H and 13 C
				NMR. For the second type of copolymers, the cyclic<lb/> comonomers were added
				sequentially, yielding diblock poly(ester-amides). The materials were
				characterized<lb/> by differential scanning calorimetry (DSC), wide-and small-angle
				X-ray scattering (WAXS and SAXS), and<lb/> transmission and scanning electron
				microscopies (TEM and SEM). Their biodegradation in compost was<lb/> also studied.
				All copolymers were found to be miscible by the absence of structure in the melt.
				TEM revealed<lb/> that all samples exhibited a crystalline lamellar morphology. DSC
				and WAXS showed that in a wide<lb/> composition range (CLo contents from 6 to 55%)
				only the CLa units were capable of crystallization in the<lb/> random copolymers.
				The block copolymer samples only experience a small reduction of crystallization
				and<lb/> melting temperature with composition, and this was attributed to a dilution
				effect caused by the miscible<lb/> noncrystalline CLo units. The comparison between
				block and random copolymers provided a unique<lb/> opportunity to distinguish the
				dilution effect of the CLo units on the crystallization and melting of the<lb/>
				polyamide phase from the chemical composition effect in the random copolymers case,
				where the CLa<lb/> sequences are interrupted statistically by the CLo units, making
				the crystallization of the polyamide strongly<lb/> composition dependent. Finally,
				the enzymatic degradation of the copolymers in composted soil indicate a<lb/>
				synergistic behavior where much faster degradation was obtained for random
				copolymers with a CLo content<lb/> larger than 30% than for neat PCL.<lb/></div>

			<ptr type="web">pubs.acs.org/Macromolecules</ptr> 
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<date>Published on Web 08/10/2009<lb/></date>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<note type="copyright">r 2009 American Chemical Society<lb/></note>
			
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
