<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55009947"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>

	<note>MOBILEMAN<lb/> IST-2001-38113<lb/> Mobile Metropolitan Ad hoc Networks<lb/> </note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>MOBILEMAN<lb/> Architecture, protocols and services<lb/> Deliverable D5<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="submission">Contractual Report Preparation Date: September 2003<lb/> Actual Date of Delivery: 7 October 2004<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Estimated Person Months: 46<lb/> Number of pages: 165<lb/> Contributing Partners:</note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>(Italy),</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Cambridge<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>(UK), </address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institut Eurecom</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>(France),</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Helsinki University</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>(Finland),</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>NETikos</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>(Italy),</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Scuola<lb/> Universitaria Professionale della Svizzera Italiana</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>(Switzerland)<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Authors: Marco Conti, Giovanni Turi, Gaia Maselli (CNR), Jon Crowcroft, Sven Ostring<lb/> (Cambridge), Pietro Michiardi, Refik Molva (Eurecom), Jose Costa Requena (HUT),<lb/> Piergiorgio Cremonese, Veronica Vanni (Netikos), Ivan Defilippis, Silvia Giordano,<lb/> Alessandro Puiatti (SUPSI)<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract: The aim of this deliverable is to provide the overview of the architecture, protocols and<lb/> services designed for the MobileMAN paradigm as emerging at the end of the first year of the<lb/> project. First, we present the complete architecture with the communication flows among different<lb/> functions, and then we discuss protocols belonging to the MobileMAN protocols&apos; stack. Protocols<lb/> are presented by following a bottom up approach from wireless technologies up to the application<lb/> and economic issues.<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">Project funded by the European<lb/> Community under the &quot;Information<lb/> Society Technologies&quot; Programme (1998-<lb/>2002)</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
