<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007037"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">LABELLING METHODS AND RADIOSYNTHESIS – ORGANIC POSITRON EMITTERS </note>

	<note type="page">S111<lb/> </note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>P023 SYNTHESIS OF CARBON-11 LABELED N-METHYL-LAUDANOSINE AND ITS DERIVATIVES AS NOVEL PET<lb/> AGENTS FOR SK CHANNELS IN THE HEART<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>M. GAO, M. WANG and Q.-H. ZHENG<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Radiology, Indiana University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Indianapolis, IN, USA<lb/></address>

	<div type="introduction">Introduction: Three types of calcium-activated potassium channels, including large (BK), intermediate (IK) and<lb/> small (SK) conductance, have been identified. SK channels are widely expressed in different tissues such as the<lb/> brain, peripheral nervous system, skeletal muscle, smooth muscle and heart, and regulate cognitive dysfunction,<lb/> neuronal hyperexcitability, dopamine-related disorders, depression, hormone secretion from endocrine cells, and<lb/> repolarization of cardiac action potentials. We are interested in the development of PET heart imaging agents.<lb/> N-methyl-laudanosine (NML) is a potent SK channel blocker. Carbon-11 labeled NML and structurally close to<lb/> NML derivatives, substituted 1-(3,4-dimethoxybenzyl)-2,2-dimethyl-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroisoquinoliniums may serve<lb/> as novel radiotracers for PET to image SK channels in the heart. Here we present the synthesis of carbon-11 labeled<lb/> NML and its derivatives.<lb/> Experimental: Precursor (2a) is commercially available, and precursors (2b-d) and their corresponding standards<lb/> (1a-d) were synthesized in multiple steps starting from the substituted benzaldehydes and aminoacetaldehyde<lb/> dimethyl acetal in moderate to excellent chemical yields using a modification of the literature procedure (Graulich A,<lb/> et al. J Med Chem, 2005, 48, 4972-82).<lb/> Results and Discussion: Carbon-11 labeled quaternary ammonium target tracers, 6,7-dimethoxy-1-(3,4-<lb/>dimethoxybenzyl)-2-[<lb/> 11 C]methyl-2-methyl-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroisoquinolium triflate ([<lb/> 11 C]NML, [<lb/> 11 C]1a) and its deriva-<lb/>tives, 1-(3,4-dimethoxybenzyl)-8-ethyl-2-[<lb/> 11 C]methyl-2-methyl-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroisoquinolium triflate ([<lb/> 11 C]1b), 1-<lb/>(3,4-dimethoxybenzyl)-8-isopropyl-2-[<lb/> 11 C]methyl-2-methyl-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroisoquinolium triflate ([<lb/> 11 C]1c) and 1-<lb/>(3,4-dimethoxybenzyl)-6-isopropyl-2-[<lb/> 11 C]methyl-2-methyl-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroisoquinolium triflate ([<lb/> 11 C]1d), were<lb/> prepared by the N-[<lb/> 11 C]methylation of their corresponding precursors 2a-d using [<lb/> 11 C]CH 3 OTf and purified by<lb/> a simplified SPE method using a cation-exchange CM Sep-Pak cartridge in 40-65% radiochemical yield based on<lb/> [ 11 C]CO 2 , 15 min overall synthesis time from EOB, &gt;95% radiochemical purity and 1.0-2.0 Ci/μmol specific activity<lb/> at EOS (Scheme 1).<lb/> Scheme 1. Synthesis of carbon-11 labeled N-methyl-laudanosine and its derivatives.<lb/> Conclusion: An efficient and convenient synthesis of the tetrahydroisoquinoline precursors, tetrahy-<lb/>droisoquinolium standards and carbon-11 labeled substituted 1-(3,4-dimethoxybenzyl)-2,2-dimethyl-1,2,3,4-<lb/>tetrahydroisoquinoliniums has been well developed.<lb/> Acknowledgement: Supported in part by INGEN of Indiana University.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: Carbon-11 Labeled N-Methyl-Laudanosine, SK Channels, PET, Heart Imaging</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
