<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001832"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>HIGHLIGHTS OF PRESCRIBING INFORMATION<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">These highlights do not include all the information needed to use TISSEEL safely and effectively.<lb/> See full prescribing information for TISSEEL.<lb/></div>

	<div type="introduction"> TISSEEL [Fibrin Sealant]<lb/> For Topical Use Only<lb/> Frozen solution and lyophilized powder for solution for topical application<lb/> Initial U.

	S. Approval: 1998<lb/> ––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––– RECENT MAJOR CHANGES ––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––<lb/> Adverse Reactions; Post Marketing (6.3)<lb/> 11/2009<lb/> ––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––– INDICATIONS AND USAGE –––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––<lb/>

	>@BULLET Hemostasis: TISSEEL is a fibrin sealant indicated for use as an adjunct to hemostasis in surgeries involving<lb/> cardiopulmonary bypass and treatment of blunt or penetrating splenic injuries when control of bleeding by<lb/> conventional surgical techniques, including suture, ligature, and cautery, is ineffective or impractical. TISSEEL is a<lb/> hemostatic agent that may be used in fully heparinized patients undergoing cardiopulmonary bypass (1.1)<lb/> @BULLET Sealing: TISSEEL is a fibrin sealant indicated as an adjunct to standard surgical techniques (such as suture and<lb/> ligature) to prevent leakage from colonic anastomoses following the reversal of temporary colostomies

	(1.2)<lb/> –––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––– DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION ––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––––<lb/> For Topical Use Only. Do Not Inject (2)<lb/>

	TISSEEL Kit (Freeze-Dried) requires reconstitution prior to use (2.1)<lb/> TISSEEL Pre-filled Syringe (Frozen) requires thawing prior to use (2.2)<lb/> Apply TISSEEL as a thin layer (2.3, 5.2)<lb/> Vials and pre-filled syringes are for single use only. Discard unused contents (2.3)<lb/> To ensure adequate mixing, expel and discard the first several drops from the cannula in cases where very small<lb/> volumes (1 – 2 drops) are applied (2.3)</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
