<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006092"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">FULL PAPER<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Synthesis of Modified Ingenol Esters<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Giovanni Appendino,*<lb/> [a] Gian Cesare Tron,<lb/> [a] Giancarlo Cravotto,<lb/> [a] Giovanni Palmisano,<lb/> [b]<lb/> Rita Annunziata,<lb/> [c] Germano Baj,<lb/> [d,e] and Nicola Surico<lb/> [d]<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<keyword>Keywords: Natural products / Diterpenes / Ingenol / Antitumor agents / Isosters<lb/></keyword>
	
	<div type="abstract">Synthetic protocols for the manipulation of the<lb/> modifications. These data suggest that chemical<lb/> manipulation can effectively dissect cytotoxicity and tumour-<lb/>polyhydroxylated southern region of ingenol (1a) were<lb/> developed, and a series of isosteres of the anticancer<lb/> promoting activity (or potential) of ingenoids, affording more<lb/> optimal candidates for development, like 20-deoxy-20-<lb/>compound ingenol 3,20-dibenzoate (1b) was prepared. The<lb/> biological evaluation of these compounds showed that fluoroingenol 3,20-dibenzoate (5b). In mild acidic medium,<lb/> an unexpected vinylogous retro-pinacol rearrangement of<lb/> cytotoxicity was relatively tolerant to changes at C-20, while<lb/> PKC activation was markedly affected by these<lb/> ingenol to a tigliane derivative was observed.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">Ingenol (1a) is a diterpenoid polyol first characterised in evaluation of the antitumour activity. The potential of in-<lb/>genol as a scaffold for bioactivity was further fuelled by the<lb/> the course of studies aimed at the identification of the irri-<lb/>tant and co-cancerogenic constituents of plants from the discovery of the outstanding anti-HIV activity of some of<lb/> its derivatives, which are able to downregulate CD4 ex-<lb/>spurge family (Euphorbiaceae).<lb/> [1] Paradoxically, following a<lb/> seminal report by Kupchan on the anticancer activity of pression in host cells.<lb/> [11] As with cytotoxicity, the anti-HIV<lb/> activity was not seemingly directly correlated to PKC acti-<lb/>ingenol-3,20-dibenzoate (1b),<lb/> [2] various derivatives of in-<lb/>genol were also identified as the active constituents of anti-vation.<lb/> [11]</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
