<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004230"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>JOURNAL OF CELLULAR PHYSIOLOGY 206:807–813 (2006)<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>MyoD Recruits the cdk9/Cyclin T2 Complex<lb/> on Myogenic-Genes Regulatory Regions<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>CRISTINA GIACINTI,<lb/> 1 LUIGI BAGELLA,<lb/> 1 PIER LORENZO PURI,<lb/> 3<lb/> ANTONIO GIORDANO,<lb/> 1<lb/> * AND CRISTIANO SIMONE<lb/> 1,2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of Biology, Sbarro Institute for Cancer Research and Molecular Medicine,<lb/> College of Science and Technology Temple University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> Department of Biomedicine in Childhood, Division of Medical Genetics,<lb/> University of Bari,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bari, Italy<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> DTI at Fondazione A. Cisalpino, ICBTE, San Raffaele Biomedical Science Park of Rome,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rome, Italy;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>The Burnham Institute,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>La Jolla, San Diego, California<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">During skeletal myogenesis, muscle-regulatory factors bHLH and MEF2 promote the expression of muscle-specific genes by<lb/> recruiting several chromatin-modifying complexes on specific DNA regulatory sequences. A number of MyoD-interacting proteins<lb/> have been reported, but whether they are recruited to the chromatin of myogenic loci, and the relationship with other chromatin<lb/> bound proteins is unknown. We show that MyoD recruits cdk9/cyclin T2, together with the histone acetyltransferases p300 and<lb/> PCAF, and the chromatin remodeling complex SWI/SNF, on promoters and enhancers of muscle-specific genes, and that this event<lb/> correlates with the acetylation of histone tails, remodeling of chromatin, and phosphorylation of the C-terminal domain (CTD) of the<lb/> RNA polymerase II at these elements.</div>

	<reference>J. Cell. Physiol. 206: 807–813, 2006.</reference>

	<note type="copyright">&#169; 2005 Wiley-Liss, Inc.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
