<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001022"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Ze n t r S t e r i l 2 0 0 8 ; 1 6 ( 6 ) : 4 2 4 – 4 3 5<lb/> 430<lb/> CENTRAL SERVICE<lb/> Volume 16 2008<lb/></reference>>

	<note type="other">Z ZE EN NT TR RA AL L<lb/> STERILISATION 6<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Multicentre Trial on Standardisation of a Test Soil<lb/> of Practical Relevance for Comparative and Quantitative<lb/> Evaluation of Cleaning Pursuant to EN ISO 15883<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>J. Köhnlein<lb/> 1<lb/> , R. Glasmacher<lb/> 2<lb/> , V. Heide<lb/> 2<lb/> , D. Kunde<lb/> 3<lb/> , M. Mohr<lb/> 3<lb/> , D. Otto<lb/> 4<lb/> , K. Roth<lb/> 5<lb/> , J. Staffeldt<lb/> 4<lb/> , P. Tiarks<lb/> 4<lb/> , S. Wagenknecht<lb/> 5<lb/> , H.-P. Werner<lb/> 1<lb/> , W. Michels*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="other">04-09 in order to standardise the methods<lb/> used for verification of the cleaning per-<lb/>formance. The Ad Hoc Group decided to<lb/> have experienced laboratories carry out<lb/> comparative tests. The participating labo-<lb/>ratories are as follows<lb/> 1<lb/> :<lb/> – Chemische Fabrik Dr.

	Weigert GmbH &amp;<lb/> Co. KG<lb/> – Ecolab GmbH &amp; Co. OHG<lb/> – HygCen GmbH<lb/> – Miele &amp; Cie. KG<lb/>
	

	– Schülke &amp; Mayr GmbH<lb/> – SMP GmbH<lb/>

	1 The order in which the laboratories are list-<lb/>ed here differs from that given in the figures<lb/> The main focus here must be on practical<lb/> relevance. For example, indicators fea-<lb/>turing a test soil composed primarily of<lb/> starch must not be used when checking<lb/> the cleaning performance of a WD used<lb/> to decontaminate medical devices, since<lb/> these harbour mainly blood or organic con-<lb/>tamination. Ultimately, these manifold in-<lb/>dicator systems gave rise to a situation<lb/> whereby at the time of commissioning<lb/> WDs, the processes were often brought<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Keywords @BULLET test soil<lb/> @BULLET standardisation<lb/> @BULLET EN ISO 15883<lb/> @BULLET cleaning<lb/></keyword>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>* Dr. Winfried Michels,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Miele &amp; Cie. KG,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Carl-Miele-<lb/>Str. 29, 33332 Gütersloh, Germany<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Hyg Cen GmbH,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bornhövedstr. 78, 19055 Schwerin,<lb/> Germany</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Ecolab GmbH &amp; Co. OHG,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Reisholzer Werftstr. 38-42,<lb/> 40589 Düsseldorf, Germany<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Schülke &amp; Mayr GmbH.</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Robert-Koch-Str. 2, 22851<lb/> Norderstedt, Germany<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Chemische Fabrik Dr. Weigert GmbH &amp; Co. KG, Müh-<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>lenhagen 85, 20539 Hamburg, Germany<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 SMP GmbH,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hechinger Str. 262, 72072 Tübingen,<lb/> Germany<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">T<lb/> he cleaning performance of washer-dis-<lb/>infectors can be verified pursuant to ISO<lb/> 15883-1and ISO/TS 15883-5 using various coun-<lb/>try-specific test soils. Hence comparability<lb/> of the results achieved is questionable. The Ad<lb/> Hoc Group &quot;Test Soil and Methods&quot; was<lb/> founded by the DIN standardisation commit-<lb/>tee NA Med 063-04-09 in order to standardise<lb/> the test soils. To that effect, the Ad Hoc Group<lb/> aimed to develop an in vitro reference sys-<lb/>tem with a test soil suited to everyday prac-<lb/>tice, which could then be used to study dif-<lb/>ferent variables, such as detergents or the be-<lb/>haviour exhibited by other test soils compared<lb/> to the reference soil.<lb/> Comparative testing was conducted by<lb/> six experienced laboratories. In several ex-<lb/>perimental series it was possible to gradual-<lb/>ly optimise, first, standardisation of soiling<lb/> the test objects for process challenge devices,<lb/> second, the test procedure and, third, analy-<lb/>sis of residual soils.<lb/> On the basis of the series of tests carried<lb/> out, a system was devised and defined for<lb/> characterisation of the detachment kinetics,<lb/> providing for quantification of the cleaning<lb/> performance relevant to the practical situation.<lb/> This meant that there was now a refer-<lb/>ence standard that also permitted quantifi-<lb/>able comparison of the various test systems<lb/> available, including those cleaning indica-<lb/>tors already commercially available.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
