<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006879"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">Copyright 2001, Society of Petroleum Engineers Inc.<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">This paper was prepared for presentation at </note> 
	
	<reference>the SPE European Formation Damage<lb/> Conference held in The Hague, The Netherlands, 21–22 May 2001.<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">This paper was selected for presentation by an SPE Program Committee following review of<lb/> information contained in an abstract submitted by the author(s). Contents of the paper, as<lb/> presented, have not been reviewed by the Society of Petroleum Engineers and are subject to<lb/> correction by the author(s). The material, as presented, does not necessarily reflect any<lb/> position of the Society of Petroleum Engineers, its officers, or members. Papers presented at<lb/> SPE meetings are subject to publication review by Editorial Committees of the Society of<lb/> Petroleum Engineers. Electronic reproduction, distribution, or storage of any part of this paper<lb/> for commercial purposes without the written consent of the Society of Petroleum Engineers is<lb/> prohibited. Permission to reproduce in print is restricted to an abstract of not more than 300<lb/> words; illustrations may not be copied. The abstract must contain conspicuous<lb/> acknowledgment of where and by whom the paper was presented. Write Librarian, SPE,</note>

	<address>P.O.<lb/> Box 833836, Richardson, TX 75083-3836, U.S.A., </address>
	
	<phone>fax 01-972-952-9435.<lb/></phone>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract Open hole gravel packing for sand control can offer<lb/> productivity and cost reduction advantages over cased-hole<lb/> completions, particularly in thick, high permeability sands.<lb/> The filter cake formed by the reservoir drilling fluid can be<lb/> trapped by the gravel, resulting in high drawdown<lb/> requirements, non-uniform inflow profiles and/or low<lb/> productivity. Effective clean-up and flow-back of this filter<lb/> cake is necessary to fully realize productivity advantages of<lb/> open-hole completions.<lb/> A comprehensive series of over 20 laboratory experiments<lb/> were carried out to better understand filter cake flow-back in<lb/> sand control completions. Variables investigated included<lb/> mud weight and type, gravel size, additives like enzymes and<lb/> acids, gravel size, and screen type. Results from 12 of these<lb/> experiments are summarized in this paper.<lb/> Key findings include:<lb/>  Tested synthetic oil base muds resulted in filter<lb/> cakes which were much easier to remove than<lb/> those formed from tested water-based muds.<lb/>  40/60 mesh gravel can severely inhibit filter cake<lb/> removal compared to larger gravel sizes, which<lb/> still maintain sand control.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
