<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007004"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">3<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Care &amp; Maintenance<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="other">For trouble free operation, follow the instructions shown below.<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Handling Cautions<lb/> Formation of Condensation<lb/></note>
	
	<div type="abstract">Due to sharp changes in temperature and humidity, condensation may form if warm air comes in contact with any cold parts inside the player.<lb/> @BULLET When condensation forms inside the player, the player may not operate correctly. If this occurs, leave the player at room temperature until the<lb/> inside of the player becomes dry and operational.<lb/> @BULLET If condensation forms on a disc, wipe the disc with a soft and dry cloth by moving the cloth from the center hole toward the outer edge.<lb/> @BULLET Before connecting other components to this player, be sure to turn them all off.<lb/> @BULLET Do not move the player while a disc is being played, or the disc may be scratched or<lb/> broken, and the player&apos;s internal parts may be damaged.<lb/> @BULLET Do not put a flower vase filled with water or any small metal objects on the player.<lb/> @BULLET Be careful not to put your hand into the disc tray.<lb/> @BULLET Do not place anything other than the disc in the disc tray.<lb/> @BULLET Exterior interference such as lightning and static electricity can affect normal opera-<lb/>tion of this player. If this occurs, turn the player off and on again with the POWER but-<lb/>ton, or disconnect and then reconnect the AC power cord to the AC power outlet. The<lb/> player will operate normally.<lb/> @BULLET Be sure to remove the disc and turn off the player after use.<lb/> @BULLET Disconnect the AC power cord from the AC outlet when you don&apos;t intend to use the<lb/> player for long periods of time.<lb/> @BULLET Clean the disc by wiping in a straight line from the inside to the outside of the disc.<lb/> @BULLET Do not pull or push the disc tray forcibly. Doing so may cause malfunction of the play-<lb/>er. When you move the player, first remove all discs in the tray. When &quot;NO DISC&quot; is<lb/> displayed on the front display, turn the power off.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
