<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004854"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A Congestion Control Model for Multicast Overlay<lb/> Networks and its Performance<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Guillaume Urvoy-Keller<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institut Eurecom<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2229, route des C<lb/> etes 06904 Sophia-Antipolis, France<lb/></address>

	<email>urvoy@eurecom.fr<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ernst W. Biersack<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institut Eurecom<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2229, route des C<lb/> etes 06904 Sophia-Antipolis, France<lb/></address>

	<email>erbi@eurecom.fr<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> We propose a new TCP-friendly Multicast Congestion Con-<lb/>trol (MCC) model for overlay networks and study its perfor-<lb/>mance in terms of throughput. We assume that the multi-<lb/>cast distribution tree is built at the application level and<lb/> that each overlay network node has a limited buffer for<lb/> packet storage. The overlay MCC decomposes the feedback<lb/> loop between receivers and sender into a chain of control<lb/> loops, one for each branch of the multicast distribution tree.<lb/> To calculate the throughput of a multicast session, we<lb/> use a linear recurrence method based on the max-plus alge-<lb/>bra. Preliminary numerical results demonstrate that the<lb/> throughput performance of overlay MCC is almost inde-<lb/>pendent of the number of receivers, while for the end-to-<lb/>end MCC, the throughput decreases logarithmically with<lb/> the number of receivers. This result is a clear indication<lb/> that overlay networks for multicast distribution offer a ma-<lb/>jor performance advantage over native end-to-end multicast<lb/> distribution.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords<lb/> Congestion Control, Multicast, Overlay Network, TCP<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
