<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005187"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Unconventional Fabrics, Architectures, and Models<lb/> for Future
					Multi-core Systems<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Radu Marculescu<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Carnegie Mellon University<lb/> Department of Electrical and<lb/>
					Computer Engineering<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Pittsburgh, PA 15213-3890<lb/></address>

			<email>radum@ece.cmu.edu<lb/></email>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Christof Teuscher<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Portland State University<lb/> Department of Electrical and<lb/>
					Computer Engineering<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Portland, OR 97201<lb/></address>

			<email>teuscher@pdx.edu<lb/></email>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Partha Pratim Pande<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Washington State University<lb/> School of Electrical Engineering
					and<lb/> Computer Science<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Pullman, WA 99164<lb/></address>

			<email>pande@eecs.wsu.edu<lb/></email>

			<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Massive level of integration is making modern
				multi-core chips<lb/> all-pervasive in several domains. Hence, high
				performance,<lb/> robustness, and low power are crucial for the widespread
				adoption<lb/> of such platforms. However, achieving all these goals forces us
				to<lb/> re-think the basis of designing multi-core systems at nanoscale,<lb/>
				starting with the very substrate we need to use to implement such<lb/> systems in
				the future, particularly for nanowire (or carbon<lb/> nanotube) based on-chip
				interconnect obtained through self-<lb/> assembly techniques. Due to the lack of
				control over these<lb/> processes, such interconnects are expected to be
				largely<lb/> unstructured [1][2][3]. While large unstructured networks are easy<lb/>
				to fabricate, they require unconventional architectures and<lb/> communication
				paradigms. For instance, by getting inspiration<lb/> from many natural systems with
				network-based architectures [1],<lb/> the future multi-core systems at nanoscale are
				expected to be<lb/> hierarchical and heterogeneous in nature, as many powerful<lb/>
				features such as increased performance, better resource<lb/> utilization, and an
				increased robustness against failures  of many<lb/> natural networks come precisely
				from their heterogeneity,<lb/> unstructuredness, and hierarchical nature. As such,
				an important<lb/> performance limitation of multi-core chips designed with
				regular<lb/> network architectures arises from planar metal interconnect-based<lb/>
				multi-hop links, where the data transfer between two distant<lb/> blocks can cause
				high latency and power consumption.<lb/> Different revolutionary approaches for
				creating low latency, long-<lb/> range communication channels like optical
				interconnects, on-chip<lb/> transmission lines and wireless interconnects have been
				explored,<lb/> particularly in the context of network-on-chip (NoC) based<lb/>
				communication. These emerging interconnect technologies can<lb/> enable the design
				of hierarchical on-chip network architectures,<lb/> where closely spaced cores
				communicate through traditional<lb/> metal wires, but long distance communications
				is predominantly<lb/> achieved through high performance specialized links. It
				is<lb/> possible to find optimal interconnection architectures for massive<lb/>
				multi-core chips by drawing inspiration from natural (complex)</div>
			
			<note type="copyright">Copyright is held by the author/owner(s).<lb/></note>
			<reference>CODES/ISSS’10, October 24–29, 2010, Scottsdale, Arizona, USA.<lb/>
				ACM 978-1-60558-905-3/10/10.<lb/></reference>
			

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
