<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006763"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Immunoreactivity with the Anti-MAGE Antibody 57B in<lb/> Malignant Melanoma: Frequency of Expression and<lb/> Correlation with Prognostic Parameters<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Klaus J. Busam, M.D., Kristin Iversen, B.S., Marianne Berwick, Ph.D, Guilio C. Spagnoli, Ph.D.,<lb/> Lloyd J. Old, M.D., Achim A. Jungbluth, M.D.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Pathology (KJB), Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research, New York Branch (KI, LJO, AAJ),<lb/> and Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics (MB), Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New<lb/> York, New York;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>and Department of Surgery, University Hospital (GCS),</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Basel, Switzerland<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">The melanoma-associated antigen (MAGE) family<lb/> consists of a number of antigens initially recognized<lb/> by cytotoxic T lymphocytes, which are currently be-<lb/>ing investigated for immunotherapy of patients<lb/> with metastatic melanoma and other tumor types.<lb/> Expression of MAGE mRNA in melanocytic tumors<lb/> is said to be restricted to invasive malignant tumors<lb/> and absent in nevi. Recently, a monoclonal anti-<lb/>body (57B) has become available to examine MAGE<lb/> protein expression in archival material. In this<lb/> study, we performed immunohistochemical analy-<lb/>sis on 132 melanocytic nevi and 205 melanomas (85<lb/> primary cutaneous melanomas and 120 metastatic<lb/> tumors) to determine the frequency of MAGE ex-<lb/>pression and to explore a potential correlation with<lb/> various prognostic parameters. None of the mela-<lb/>nocytic nevi and none of the 20 in situ melanomas<lb/> was immunopositive with the antibody 57B. Immu-<lb/>noreactivity was present in 17 of 65 (26%) primary<lb/> invasive melanomas of the skin and in 30 of 120<lb/> (25%) metastatic tumors. Positive immunostaining<lb/> did not correlate with tumor stage (P ‫؍‬ .66),<lb/> Breslow thickness (P ‫؍‬ .39), Clark level (P ‫؍‬ .5), or<lb/> the histologic type of melanoma (P ‫؍‬ .23) but was<lb/> associated with a brisk infiltrate of lymphocytes in-<lb/>volving the vertical growth phase of melanomas<lb/> (P ‫؍‬ .01). Because tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes<lb/> in melanoma are associated with longer survival,<lb/> our findings suggest a potential prognostic role for<lb/> MAGE. Furthermore, the seeming restriction of im-<lb/>munopositivity to invasive malignant tumors sug-<lb/>gests a potential diagnostic role for the antibody<lb/> 57B in confirming the malignant potential of a<lb/> melanocytic tumor.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
