<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005281"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">&#169; 1994 by The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Inc<lb/></note>

	<reference>THE JOURNAL OF BIOL~CICAL CHEMISTRY<lb/> Vol. 269, No. 19, Issue of May 13, pp. 13893-13898, 1994<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">Printed in U.S.A.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Expression of Multiple Chemokine Genes by a Human Mast Cell<lb/> Leukemia*<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="submission">(Received for publication, January 31, 1994, and in revised form, March 15, 1994)<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rathinam S. Selvan, Joseph H. Butterfield$, and Michael S. KrangelO<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>From the Department of Immunology, Duke University Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Durham, North Carolina 27710</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>and the<lb/> $Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Allergic Diseases, Mayo Clinic,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rochester, Minnesota 55905<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">The chemokines are a large group of cytokines that<lb/> are recognized to be important mediators of inflamma-<lb/>tion. In this study we show that the human mast<lb/> cell leukemia line HMC-1 is a source of multiple chemokines,<lb/> including 1-309, monocyte chemoattractant protein 1,<lb/> macrophage inflammatory protein-la, macrophage in-<lb/>flammatory protein-lp, RANTES, and interleukin-8.<lb/> 1-309 and MCP-1 transcripts are expressed at low levels<lb/> in unstimulated HMC-1. However, phorbol ester treat-<lb/>ment up-regulates these and other chemokine tran-<lb/>script levels and also up-regulates chemokine protein<lb/> synthesis and secretion. Induction of chemokine tran-<lb/>scripts in HMC-1 requires de nouo protein synthesis. W e<lb/> compared the effects of anti-inflammatory glucocorti-<lb/>coids on the expression of chemokine genes in HMC-1 to<lb/> their effects in activated T-cells. W e find that methyl-<lb/>prednisolone reduces MCP-1 but not other chemokine<lb/> transcripts in HMC-1, even though there are distinct<lb/> and more general effects on chemokine transcripts in<lb/> activated T-cells. These effects are attributed to inhibi-<lb/>tion of transcription rather than transcript stability.<lb/> Our results suggest that human mast cells may be a<lb/> source of multiple chemokines, that glucocorticoids may<lb/> inhibit the expression of only a subset of these chemo-<lb/>kines, and that mast cells and T-cell chemokine expres-<lb/>sion may occur via distinct regulatory pathways.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">Chemokines are small secreted proteins that play essential<lb/> roles in the recruitment and activation of leukocytes and other<lb/> cells at sites of inflammation (1). The members of this family<lb/> are all structurally related and display four highly conserved<lb/> cysteine residues, yet can be segregated into either of two sub-<lb/>families (C-C or C-X-C) depending upon the presence or ab-<lb/>sence of an intervening amino acid between the first two con-<lb/>served cysteine residues.<lb/> The human<lb/> C-C subfamily is<lb/> comprised of at least six distinct molecules: 1-309, MCP-1,l<lb/> MIP-la, MIP-lP, RANTES, and HC14. The human C-X-C sub-<lb/>family includes IL-8, PF4, platelet basic protein and its deriva-<lb/>tives (connective tissue-activating peptide (CTAP), P-thrombo-<lb/>globulin, neutrophil activating peptide-2 (NAP-Z), YIP-10, and<lb/> the GRO family of molecules (a, P, and y). Examination of the</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
