<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004212"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>JOURNAL OF CELLULAR PHYSIOLOGY 203:251–260 (2005)<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Differential Localization and Expression of the<lb/> Cdk9 42k and 55k Isoforms<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>HONGBING LIU AND CHRISTINE H. HERRMANN*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Molecular Virology and Microbiology,<lb/> Baylor College of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Houston, Texas<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Cdk9, a member of the cyclin-dependent kinase family, is the catalytic subunit of P-TEFb, a protein kinase complex that stimulates<lb/> transcriptional elongation. Cdk9, complexed with its regulatory partner cyclin T1, serves as the cellular mediator of the<lb/> transactivation function of the HIV Tat protein. There are two known isoforms of Cdk9: a 42 kDa protein (42k, originally identified as<lb/> PITALRE) and a more recently identified 55 kDa form (55k). To investigate possible functional differences between the two isoforms,<lb/> we examined their kinase activities, their subcellular distributions, and their expression levels in primary cells relevant to HIV<lb/> infection. Both isoforms were found to hyper-phosphorylate the carboxyl-terminal domain of the largest subunit of RNA polymerase<lb/> II and displayed identical phosphorylation patterns with 144 peptide substrates. Epitope-tagged transiently-expressed Cdk9 42k<lb/> localized diffusely in the nucleoplasm, while Cdk9 55k accumulated in the nucleolus. In primary undifferentiated monocytes,<lb/> Cdk9 55k expression was not detected although 42k was present at high levels; however, 55k expression was induced upon<lb/> macrophage differentiation. In primary lymphocytes, the levels of 55k decreased or remained steady following activation, while the<lb/> levels of 42k increased. The promoter for 42k was significantly stronger than that of 55k in HeLa cells, and only the 42k promoter was<lb/> responsive to activation signals in primary lymphocytes. These results indicate that expression of the 42k and 55k isoforms is<lb/> differentially regulated and suggest that functional differences between the 42k and 55k isoforms of Cdk9 are likely to depend on<lb/> access to substrates based on their differential subcellular localization and expression patterns.</div>

	<reference>J. Cell. Physiol. 203: 251–260,<lb/> 2005. </reference>
	
	<note type="copyright">&#169; 2004 Wiley-Liss, Inc.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
