<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005202"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>The Journal of China<lb/>
				Universities of Posts and<lb/>
			Telecommunications<lb/> Avril 2010, 17(2): 85–91<lb/></reference>
			
			<ptr type="web">www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/10058885</ptr>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<ptr type="web">www.buptjournal.cn/xben<lb/></ptr>
			
		

		

			<docTitle><titlePart>Relaying strategy for peer-to-peer content<lb/> distribution based on genetic
				algorithm<lb/></titlePart></docTitle>
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>HE Qian (&#x6ef59;), MENG Xiang-wu, SHANG Yan-lei, CHEN
					Jun-liang<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Networking and Switching Technology, Beijing
					University of Posts and Telecommunications,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Beijing 100876, China<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> This article proposes a cooperative relaying strategy
				to efficiently utilize the relaying resources of Internet service providers<lb/>
				(ISPs), speedup distribution and save server bandwidth costs. ISPs cooperatively
				relay for each other, and peers assist in<lb/> distributing and fetching the content
				as near as possible. Base on the fluid model, a constrained model is derived to get
				optimized<lb/> global distribution performance in the channel-based system with
				limited relaying resources. The multi-objectives of the model<lb/> are minimizing
				the average distribution time and the distribution time of the slowest channel.
				Genetic algorithm (GA) is designed<lb/> to solve the optimization problem. The
				relaying strategy based on GA can be run periodically to update the allocation
				policy of<lb/> ISPs. The distribution performance of the relaying strategy is
				analyzed in the experiments and results show that GA can provide<lb/> proper
				solutions for various network topologies.<lb/></div>

			<keywords>Keywords content distribution, peer-to-peer, genetic algorithm, cooperative
				relaying, resource allocation<lb/></keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
