<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003031"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">952<lb/> </note>
	<reference>Karnataka J. Agric. Sci.,19(4): (<lb/> ) 2006<lb/></reference>

	<div type="introduction">Susceptibility of Helicoverpa armigera (Hubner) to Beauveria bassiana<lb/> (BALSAMO) Vuill<lb/> Helicoverpa armigera (Hub) a most<lb/> devastating pest, being polyphagous, it can invade<lb/> more than 200 host plants. Recently, the<lb/> management of the pest becomes most difficult<lb/> as it has developed the resistance towards most<lb/> of chemical insecticides. Therefore, exclusive<lb/> dependence of chemical pesticides is not likely<lb/> to provide sustained solutions against pest. To<lb/> overcome or minimise such problems, the study<lb/> on B. bassiana a fungal pathogen was carried<lb/> out under laboratory conditions, to know its<lb/> effectiveness against different stages of the pest<lb/> as a safe, effective and economical alternative<lb/> for chemical control.<lb/> The culture of Beauveria bassiana was<lb/> isolated from a commercial product, Dispel ®-L,<lb/> (2.3x10<lb/> 7 spores/ml) formulated by the Pesticides<lb/> India, Udaipur.<lb/> Potato dextrose agar (PDA) was used for<lb/> production of the fungus under laboratory. Culture<lb/> of the H. armigera was maintained under<lb/> laboratory conditions. First to fifth larval instars<lb/> of H. armigera were evaluated for their sensitivity<lb/> to the action of B. bassiana. The microbes were<lb/> tried at a spore load of 10<lb/> 2<lb/> , 10<lb/> 3<lb/> , 10<lb/> 5 , 10<lb/> 7 and 10<lb/> 8<lb/> conidia per ml. The first and second instars were<lb/> sprayed in groups with one milliliter of suspension<lb/> with varying spore concentrations with the help<lb/> of chromatographic sprayer. The treated larvae<lb/> were allowed to feed on chickpea seedlings. The<lb/> third, fourth and fifth instar larvae were treated<lb/> individually with known quantity of fungal spore<lb/> suspension (50 l/larvae) containing differential<lb/> spore load. Infected larvae were reared individually<lb/> on artificial diet in glass vials. Similarly, treated<lb/> larvae of same age with 0.02 per cent tween 80<lb/> served as control for all the treatments. Bioassay<lb/> was carried out in four replications with 10 larvae<lb/> each. Mortality of the larvae due to fungal infection<lb/> was recorded as per symptoms described by Kish<lb/> (1975).</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
