<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007359"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<ptr type="web">www.wjgnet.com<lb/></ptr>
	
	<note type="other">ORIGINAL ARTICLES<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Bile-acid-activated farnesoid X receptor regulates hydrogen<lb/> sulfide production and hepatic microcirculation<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Barbara Renga, Andrea Mencarelli, Marco Migliorati, Eleonora Distrutti, Stefano Fiorucci<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<ptr>Online Submissions: wjg.wjgnet.com<lb/></ptr>

	<reference>World J Gastroenterol 2009 May 7; 15(17): 2097-2108<lb/> wjg@wjgnet.com<lb/> World Journal of Gastroenterology ISSN 1007-9327<lb/></reference>

	<idno type="DOI">doi:10.3748/wjg.15.2097<lb/></idno>

	<note type="copyright">© 2009 The WJG Press and Baishideng. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Barbara Renga, Andrea Mencarelli, Marco Migliorati,<lb/> Stefano Fiorucci,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Clinical and Experimental<lb/> Medicine, University of Perugia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Via E dal Pozzo, 06122<lb/> Perugia, Italy<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Eleonora Distrutti, Azienda Ospedaliera di Perugia, Ospedale<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Santa Maria della Misericordia, 06122 Perugia, Italy<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">Author contributions: Renga B designed the study, carried<lb/> out in vitro experiments and wrote the manuscript; Migliorati<lb/> M performed in vitro experiments (Western blotting and PCR);<lb/> Mencarelli A performed in vivo experiments; Distrutti E was<lb/> involved in designing and writing the manuscript; Fiorucci S<lb/> designed the study and wrote the manuscript.<lb/> Correspondence to: </note>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Barbara Renga,</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Clinical<lb/> and Experimental Medicine University of Perugia,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Via E dal<lb/> Pozzo, 06122 Perugia, Italy.</address>

	<email>barbara.renga@unipg.it<lb/></email>

	<phone>Telephone: +39-075-5855819 Fax: +39-075-5855819<lb/></phone>

	<note type="submission">Received: December 19, 2008 Revised: March 20, 2009<lb/> Accepted: March 27, 2009<lb/></note>

	<date type="publication">Published online: May 7, 2009<lb/></date>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> AIM: To investigate whether the farnesoid X receptor<lb/> (FXR) regulates expression of liver cystathionase (CSE),<lb/> a gene involved in hydrogen sulfide (H2S) generation.<lb/> METHODS: The regulation of CSE expression in<lb/> response to FXR ligands was evaluated in HepG2<lb/> cells and in wild-type and FXR null mice treated<lb/> with 6-ethyl chenodeoxycholic acid (6E-CDCA), a<lb/> synthetic FXR ligand. The analysis demonstrated an<lb/> FXR responsive element in the 5&apos;-flanking region of<lb/> the human CSE gene. The function of this site was<lb/> investigated by luciferase reporter assays, chromatin<lb/> immunoprecipitation and electrophoretic mobility shift<lb/> assays. Livers obtained from rats treated with carbon<lb/> tetrachloride alone, or in combination with 6-ethyl<lb/> chenodeoxycholic acid, were studied for hydrogen<lb/> sulphide generation and portal pressure measurement.<lb/> RESULTS: Liver expression of CSE is regulated by<lb/> bile acids by means of an FXR-mediated mechanism.<lb/> Western blotting, qualitative and quantitative polymerase<lb/> chain reaction, as well as immunohistochemical analysis,<lb/> showed that expression of CSE in HepG2 cells and<lb/> in mice is induced by treatment with an FXR ligand.<lb/> Administration of 6E-CDCA to carbon tetrachloride<lb/> treated rats protected against the down-regulation of<lb/> CSE expression, increased H2S generation, reduced<lb/> portal pressure and attenuated the endothelial<lb/> dysfunction of isolated and perfused cirrhotic rat livers.<lb/> CONCLUSION: These results demonstrate that<lb/> CSE is an FXR-regulated gene and provide a new<lb/> molecular explanation for the pathophysiology of portal<lb/> hypertension.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2009 The WJG Press and Baishideng. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Key words: Nuclear receptor; Farnesoid X receptor;<lb/> Cystathionase; Hydrogen sulfide; Portal hypertension<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="other">Peer reviewer: Sharon DeMorrow, Assistant Professor,<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Division of Research and Education, Scott and White Hospital<lb/> and The Texas A&amp;M University System, Health Science Center<lb/> College of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Temple, Texas 76504, United States<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Renga B, Mencarelli A, Migliorati M, Distrutti E, Fiorucci S.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
