<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005139"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<note type="other">1394</note>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<reference>IEEE JOURNAL ON SELECTED AREAS IN COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 18, NO. 8,
				AUGUST 2000<lb/></reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Adaptive Nonuniform Phase-Shift-Key Modulation<lb/> for Multimedia
					Traffic in Wireless Networks<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Michael B. Pursley, Fellow, IEEE, and John M. Shea, Member, IEEE<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract—The characteristics of mobile wireless communica-<lb/>
				tion channels fluctuate for many reasons, including movement of<lb/> the radios,
				changes in path attenuation, and variations in interfer-<lb/> ence. Several adaptive
				signaling techniques have been proposed for<lb/> use in wideband code-division
				multiple-access (CDMA) systems in-<lb/> cluding adaptive data rates, adaptive
				spreading code rates, discon-<lb/> tinuous transmission, and multicode CDMA. In this
				paper we in-<lb/> troduce adaptive signaling techniques that use nonuniform
				phase-<lb/> shift-key (PSK) modulation. These techniques have several advan-<lb/>
				tages for use in CDMA communications, and they support mul-<lb/> timedia
				transmission by simultaneously delivering different types<lb/> of traffic, each with
				its own required quality of service. The sig-<lb/> naling methods that we propose
				deliver a basic message at a spec-<lb/> ified error rate and simultaneously deliver
				an additional message<lb/> by exploiting any extra capability that is available. We
				show that<lb/> by adapting the location of the points in a PSK constellation,
				the<lb/> throughput can be maximized for the additional message while<lb/>
				maintaining an acceptable error rate for the basic message. Re-<lb/> sponses to
				larger changes in channel quality are accomplished by<lb/> adapting the PSK
				constellation size, signaling rate, and error-cor-<lb/> recting code. Examples of
				adaptive signaling schemes that employ<lb/> nonuniform PSK constellations are
				presented, including an appli-<lb/> cation to a cellular CDMA system.<lb/> Index
				Terms—Adaptive error-correction coding, adaptive mod-<lb/> ulation, code division
				multiple access (CDMA), multimedia trans-<lb/> mission, phase-shift-keying.<lb/>
			</div>
			
			<div type="introduction">
				I. INTRODUCTION<lb/> 
			</div>
			
			<note type="submission">Manuscript received August 1999; revised February 28, 2000.</note>

			<grant>This work was<lb/> supported by the U.S. Army Research Office under Grants
				DAAH04-95-1-0247<lb/> and DAAG55-98-1-0013.<lb/></grant>
			
			<note type="other">M. B. Pursley is with the</note>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer<lb/> Engineering, Clemson
					University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Clemson, SC 29634 USA</address>

			<email>(e-mail:<lb/> pursley@eng.clemson.edu).<lb/></email>

			<note type="other">J. M. Shea is with the </note>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering,<lb/>
					University of Florida,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Gainesville, FL 32611 USA</address>

			<email>(e-mail: jshea@ece.ufl.edu).<lb/></email>

			<idno>Publisher Item Identifier S 0733-8716(00)06108-4.</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
