<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55008075"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Improved Serologic Testing for Lyme Disease @BULLET JID 2003:187 (15 April) @BULLET </reference>
	
	<note type="page">1187<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">M A J O R A R T I C L E<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Serodiagnosis of Lyme Disease by Kinetic<lb/> Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay Using<lb/> Recombinant VlsE1 or Peptide Antigens<lb/> of Borrelia burgdorferi Compared with 2-Tiered<lb/> Testing Using Whole-Cell Lysates<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rendi Murphree Bacon,<lb/> 1 Brad J. Biggerstaff,<lb/> 1 Martin E. Schriefer,<lb/> 1 Robert D. Gilmore, Jr.,<lb/> 1 Mario T. Philipp,<lb/> 2<lb/> Allen C. Steere,<lb/> 3,a Gary P. Wormser,<lb/> 4 Adriana R. Marques,<lb/> 5 and Barbara J. B. Johnson<lb/> 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Division of Vector-Borne Infectious Diseases, National Center for Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Fort Collins,<lb/> Colorado;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Tulane National Primate Research Center, Tulane University Health Sciences Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Covington, Louisiana;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> Tufts University School<lb/> of Medicine, New England Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, Massachusetts;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases, New York Medical<lb/> College,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Valhalla;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Laboratory of Clinical Investigation, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bethesda, Maryland<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">In a study of US patients with Lyme disease, immunoglobulin (Ig) G and IgM antibody responses to recombinant<lb/> Borrelia burgdorferi antigen VlsE1 (rVlsE1), IgG responses to a synthetic peptide homologous to a conserved<lb/> internal sequence of VlsE (C6), and IgM responses to a synthetic peptide comprising the C-terminal 10 amino<lb/> acid residues of a B. burgdorferi outer-surface protein C (pepC10) were evaluated by kinetic enzyme-linked<lb/> immunoassay. At 99% specificity, the overall sensitivities for detecting IgG antibody to rVlsE1 or C6 in samples<lb/> from patients with diverse manifestations of Lyme disease were equivalent to that of 2-tiered testing. When data<lb/> were considered in parallel, 2 combinations (IgG responses to either rVlsE1 or C6 in parallel with IgM responses<lb/> to pepC10) maintained high specificity (98%) and were significantly more sensitive than 2-tiered analysis in<lb/> detecting antibodies to B. burgdorferi in patients with acute erythema migrans. In later stages of Lyme disease,<lb/> the sensitivities of the in parallel tests and 2-tiered testing were high and statistically equivalent.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">Lyme disease is a tick-transmitted illness that occurs in<lb/> the temperate zone of the northern hemisphere. This<lb/> study concerns the serodiagnosis of Lyme disease in the<lb/> United States, where the occurrence of Lyme disease is<lb/> geographically focal and results from infection by Bor-<lb/></div>

	<note type="submission">Received 15 July 2002; accepted 3 December 2002; </note>

	<date type="publication">electronically published 2<lb/> April 2003.<lb/></date>

	<note type="other">Presented in part: 100th annual meeting of the American Society for Micro-<lb/>biology,Los Angeles, 21–25 May 2000 (abstract V-10); IX International Conference<lb/> on Lyme Borreliosis and Other Tick-Borne Diseases, New York, 18–20 August 2002<lb/> (abstract 171).<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Reprints or correspondence: Dr. Barbara J. B. Johnson, Div. of Vector-Borne<lb/> Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, PO Box 2087,<lb/> Fort Collins, CO 80522 (BJohnson@cdc.gov).<lb/></note>

	<reference>The Journal of Infectious Diseases 2003; 187:1187–99<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">&#169; 2003 by the Infectious Diseases Society of America. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">0022-1899/2003/18708-0003$15.00<lb/></note>

	<div type="introduction">relia burgdorferi sensu stricto. Several other B. burg-<lb/>dorferi sensu lato species have been isolated from ticks<lb/> and animals in the United States, but they are not<lb/> Written informed consent was obtained from patients with Lyme disease and<lb/> multiple sclerosis who donated serum samples. Other classes of serum samples<lb/> were exempt from National Institutes of Health (NIH) and Centers for Disease<lb/> Control and Prevention (CDC) institutional review board approval. The human<lb/> experimentation guidelines of the US Department of Health and Human Services<lb/> and the authors&apos; institutions were followed in conducting the clinical research.<lb/> Financial support: National Center for Research Resources, NIH (grant RR00164<lb/> to M.T.P.); CDC (Cooperative Agreement CCU 110291).</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
