<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003278"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of Optoelectronics and Advanced Materials Vol. 7, No. 6, December 2005, p. 3197 -3208<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>COMPACT SCANNING LIDAR FLUOROSENSOR FOR INVESTIGATIONS OF<lb/> BIODEGRADATION ON ANCIENT PAINTED SURFACES<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>F. Colao, R. Fantoni, L. Fiorani<lb/> *<lb/> , A. Palucci, I. Gomoiu<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a<lb/> ENEA, Applied Physics Technologies Dep. (FIS), Laser Application Section (LAS)<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Via Enrico Fermi 45, 00044 Frascati (Rome), Italy<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a<lb/> Romanian Academy, Institute of Biology, Microbiology Centre 296, Splaiul Independentei,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>79651 Bucharest, Romania<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">A compact scanning lidar fluorosensor apparatus has been completed and employed in the<lb/> diagnosis of wall frescos relevant to the preservation and valorization of European cultural<lb/> heritage. Preliminary laboratory investigations on natural stones and a painted wood icon<lb/> were performed before the participation to the Advanced On-Site Laboratory for European<lb/> Antique Heritage Restoration, held in Constanta (Romania), April 15-30, 2004. The<lb/> scanning LIF (Laser Induced Fluorescence) prototype was utilized during the campaign to<lb/> investigate painted walls of a Byzantine crypt. Scanned images at different spectral channels<lb/> and their suitable combination, showing the effectiveness of the technique to reveal the<lb/> occurrence of biodegradation produced by different microorganisms, are presented.<lb/></div>

	<note type="submission">(Received November 9, 2005; accepted November 24, 2005)<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Keywords: Laser induced fluorescence (LIF), Laser scanning systems, Frescos, Biodeterioration<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
