<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006785"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>BIOLOGY OF REPRODUCTION 53, 276-284 (1995)<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Viability Assessment of Mammalian Sperm Using SYBR-14 and Propidium Iodide&apos;<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Duane L. Garner<lb/> 2 &apos;<lb/> 3 and Lawrence A. Johnson<lb/>4<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>School of Veterinary Medicine,<lb/> 3 University of Nevada,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Reno, Nevada<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Germplasm &amp; Gamete Physiology Laboratory,<lb/> 4 Agricultural Research Service<lb/> U.S. Department of Agriculture,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Beltsville, Maryland<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> The proportion of living sperm in semen from six representative mammals was assessed by means of a dual staining technique using<lb/> the stains SYBR-14 and propidium iodide (PI). SYBR-14, a newly developed fluorescent nucleic acid stain, maximally absorbs at 488 nm<lb/> and emits at 518 nm when bound to DNA. Microscopic examination revealed that SYBR-14 stained the nuclei of living sperm bright green<lb/> as determined by simultaneous examination of fluorescence and motility. Conversely, PI stained only nonmotile sperm that had lost their<lb/> membrane integrity. Sperm from bulls, boars, rams, rabbits, mice, and men were stained and examined through use of fluorescence<lb/> microscopy. The proportions of living and dead sperm were determined by first staining with SYBR-14 and PI and then assessing stain<lb/> uptake by flow cytometry. Similar staining patterns were observed in all six mammalian species tested. Three populations of sperm were<lb/> identified: living-SYBR-14 stained, dead-PI stained, and moribund-doubly stained. The SYBR-14 staining was replaced by PI staining<lb/> as sperm progressed from living to moribund. The transition from green (SYBR-14) to red (PI) fluorescence started at the posterior region<lb/> of the sperm head and proceeded anteriorly. The proportions of living and dead sperm in mammalian semen were readily identified<lb/> through use of dual staining with SYBR-14 and PI and quantified through use of flow cytometry.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
