<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007269"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Categories<lb/> FAQ<lb/> Diet &amp; Health<lb/> Diseases and Other<lb/> Conditions<lb/> Food Safety and<lb/> Preparation<lb/> Naturopathic Herbal<lb/> Remedies<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="other">A B C D E F G H<lb/> I J L<lb/> M N O P S<lb/> T U W<lb/> Nutrition<lb/> Recipes<lb/> Supplements<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The Medical Benefits of Ceratonia Siliqua<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<note type="other">Other</note>
	</byline>

	<keyword>Common Names: Algaroba, Algarrobo, Carob, Carob-Tree, Caroube, John&apos;s Bread,<lb/> Keciboynuzu Agaci, St John&apos;s Bread, St John&apos;s-bread, Ceratonia siliqua<lb/> Range: S. Europe; Egypt; Spain; Turkey<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">Habitat: Rocky places near the sea shore<lb/> Carob Tree or Ceratonia siliqua, is a small tree of the Mediterranean coasts. It furnishes the St.<lb/> John&apos;s Bread which probably corresponds to the husks of the Prodigal Son parable, and the seed<lb/> which is said to have been the original jewellers&apos; carat weight. The Spaniards call it Algaroba, and<lb/> the Arabs Kharoub, hence Carob or Caroub Pods, Beans, or Sugar-pods. It is also called Locust<lb/> Pods. These pods are much used in the south of Europe for feeding domestic animals and, in times<lb/> of scarcity, as human food. Being saccharine, they are more heatgiving than nourishing. The seeds<lb/> or beans were used as fodder for British cavalry horses during the Spanish campaign of 1811-12.<lb/> The pulp in the seedpods of carob is very nutritious and, due to its high sugar content, sweet-<lb/>tasting and mildly laxative. However, the pulp in the pods is also astringent and, used in a<lb/> decoction, will treat diarrhoea and gently help to cleanse and also relieve irritation within the gut.<lb/> Whilst these appear to be contradictory effects, carob is an example of how the body responds to<lb/> herbal medicines in different ways, according to how the herb is prepared and according to the<lb/> specific medical problem. The seedpods are also used in the treatment of coughs. A flour made from<lb/> the ripe seedpods is demulcent and emollient. It is used in the treatment of diarrhea.<lb/> The seed husks are astringent and purgative. The bark is strongly astringent. A decoction is used in<lb/> the treatment of diarrhea.<lb/> Seedpods -raw or ground into a powder. The seedpods are filled with a saccharine pulp and can be<lb/> eaten both green or dried. They are very sweet but fibrous, the pulp can be used as a chocolate<lb/> substitute in cakes, drinks etc. It is rich in sugars and protein. The pods contain about 55% sugars,<lb/> 10% protein and 6% fat.<lb/> Seed -rich in protein. A flour is made from them which is 60% protein, it is free from sugar and<lb/> starch and is suitable for baking. It can be used as a chocolate substitute. An edible gum is<lb/> extracted from the seed, a substitute for Gum Tragacanth (Astragalus species). A stabilizer and<lb/> thickening agent, it is also used as an egg substitute. The roasted seed is a coffee substitute.<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">Home Contact Us<lb/> Links Glossary<lb/> Bibliography<lb/></note>

	<note>Useful Information on Carob -Diet-and-Health<lb/></note>

	<ptr type="web">http://web.archive.org/web/20080924231653/http://www.diet-and-heal...<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="page">1 of 1<lb/></note>

	<date>15-09-2011</date>

	<note type="other">15:44</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
