<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003902"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">1<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>PATTERN RECOGNITION METHODS FOR THE CLASSIFICATION OF TRACE<lb/> EVIDENCE TEXTILE FIBERS FROM UV/VISIBLE AND FLUORESCENCE SPECTRA<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Stephen L. Morgan,<lb/> 1 Suzanna H. Hall,<lb/> 1 James E. Hendrix,<lb/> 1 and Edward G. Bartick<lb/> 2<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, University of South Carolina,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Columbia, South<lb/> Carolina 29208.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> Present address: Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Suffolk University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>41 Temple<lb/> Street, Boston, MA 02114-4280.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Identification of patterns in analytical chemical data and interpretation of observed differences is<lb/> a frequent task for forensic chemists. A fiber examiner might perform UV/visible<lb/> microspectrophotometry on known and questioned fibers to evaluate possible associations<lb/> between source and location. Multivariate statistics enable confirmation of statistical validity of<lb/> discrimination between different polymer classes and dyed textile fibers, visualization of<lb/> significant differences between groups of spectra discrimination, and tracking of spectral<lb/> changes with environmental changes. The fibers and associated spectra in the database, in<lb/> combination with validated computer programs, represent an extensible tool for fiber<lb/> comparisons in casework and should also be of value in quality control and training of analysts.<lb/> In this paper, the application of linear discriminant analysis to a data base of over 5,000<lb/> UV/visible absorbance and fluorescence spectra is described.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
