<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007580"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Solaris 10 Installation Guide:<lb/> Solaris Flash Archives (Creation<lb/> and Installation)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Sun Microsystems, Inc.<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>4150 Network Circle<lb/> Santa Clara, CA 95054<lb/> U.S.A.<lb/></address>

	<idno>Part No: 817–5668–10<lb/></idno>

	<date>January 2005<lb/></date>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright 2005 Sun Microsystems, Inc.<lb/> 4150 Network Circle, Santa Clara, CA 95054 U.S.A. All rights reserved.<lb/> </note>
	
	<note type="other">This product or document is protected by copyright and distributed under licenses restricting its use, copying, distribution, and decompilation. No<lb/> part of this product or document may be reproduced in any form by any means without prior written authorization of Sun and its licensors, if any.<lb/>Third-party software, including font technology, is copyrighted and licensed from Sun suppliers.<lb/> Parts of the product may be derived from Berkeley BSD systems, licensed from the University of California. UNIX is a registered trademark in the U.S.<lb/> and other countries, exclusively licensed through X/Open Company, Ltd.<lb/> Sun, Sun Microsystems, the Sun logo, docs.sun.com, AnswerBook, AnswerBook2, JumpStart, Solaris Flash, and Solaris are trademarks, registered<lb/> trademarks, or service marks of Sun Microsystems, Inc. in the U.S. and other countries. All SPARC trademarks are used under license and are<lb/> trademarks or registered trademarks of SPARC International, Inc. in the U.S. and other countries. Products bearing SPARC trademarks are based upon<lb/> an architecture developed by Sun Microsystems, Inc.<lb/> The OPEN LOOK and Sun™ Graphical User Interface was developed by Sun Microsystems, Inc. for its users and licensees. Sun acknowledges the<lb/> pioneering efforts of Xerox in researching and developing the concept of visual or graphical user interfaces for the computer industry. Sun holds a<lb/> non-exclusive license from Xerox to the Xerox Graphical User Interface, which license also covers Sun&apos;s licensees who implement OPEN LOOK GUIs<lb/> and otherwise comply with Sun&apos;s written license agreements.</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
