<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004113"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">18<lb/> </note>
	
	<reference>CAN Newsletter Automotive Networks 2006<lb/></reference>
	
	<note type="other">Specification<lb/> </note>
	
	<div type="introduction">T<lb/> he immense innovative<lb/> potential of electronics<lb/> -and its associated abilities<lb/> to make car driving safer,<lb/> more comfortable, econom-<lb/>ical and environmentally<lb/> friendly – has caused the<lb/> automobile to undergone<lb/> a genuine electronification<lb/> that started in the 1970s and<lb/> gained momentum in the<lb/> 1980s. Above all, this is due<lb/> to the networking of elec-<lb/>tronic components, which<lb/> is a prerequisite to great-<lb/>er functionality and conse-<lb/>quently a greater range of<lb/> performance. In order to re-<lb/>duce the cabling effort and<lb/> also the costs, the weight<lb/> and the need for space that<lb/> come with increasing net-<lb/>working, the vehicle man-<lb/>ufacturers have long since<lb/> decided upon serial data<lb/> transmission. In addition to<lb/> the serial bus system CAN,<lb/> LIN and Most (Media Ori-<lb/>ented System Transport)<lb/> have been established in<lb/> vehicles within a very short<lb/> time. In Fall 2006, BMW will<lb/> introduce its new X5 as the<lb/> first production vehicle with<lb/> FlexRay, a bus system spe-<lb/>cially designed for use in<lb/> time-critical and safety-criti-<lb/>cal applications.<lb/> The Controller Area<lb/> Network (CAN), which was<lb/> standardized internationally<lb/> in 1992, is without a doubt<lb/> the most-used serial bus<lb/> system, which can be used<lb/> several times even within a<lb/> single vehicle: a slow CAN<lb/> bus system for the network-<lb/>ing of comfort ECUs with a<lb/> maximum transmission rate<lb/> of 125 Kbit/s (CAN fault-tol-<lb/>erant) and a fast CAN bus<lb/> system for networking ECUs<lb/> for the drive and chassis<lb/> The role of CAN in ECU<lb/> communication<lb/> By Holger Heit (Vector Informatik)<lb/> with a maximum transmis-<lb/>sion rate of 1 Mbit/s (CAN<lb/> high-speed). CAN offers<lb/> extraordinarily high trans-<lb/>mission security. An impor-<lb/>tant contribution is made by<lb/> the differential signal trans-<lb/>mission and the coopera-<lb/>tion of five error detection<lb/> mechanisms (among others<lb/> bit monitoring, form check,<lb/> cyclic redundancy check),<lb/> which are handled by the<lb/> CAN controllers.<lb/> LIN (Local Intercon-<lb/>nected Network) is used<lb/> for cost-effective and easy<lb/> data transmission in the<lb/> sensor/actuator area. The<lb/> data rate is limited to just 20<lb/> Kbit/s, but this is completely<lb/> sufficient for transmission of<lb/> non-critical sensor and ac-<lb/>tuator signals.<lb/> For real time-criti-<lb/>cal applications, there is a<lb/> need for a bus system that<lb/> is independent of the bus<lb/> load, guarantees hard real<lb/> time. Real time-critical sys-<lb/>tems are often also safety-<lb/>critical systems. FlexRay<lb/> is the solution here: with a<lb/> maximum data rate of 20<lb/> Mbit/s and based on a guar-<lb/>anteed equidistant data<lb/> transmission, FlexRay en-<lb/>sures deterministic time</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
