<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004929"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">426<lb/></note>
	
	<reference> A. J. Melvin, M. E. McGurn, S. J. Bort et al.<lb/>  Eur. J. Immunol. 1995. 25: 426-430<lb/></reference>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ann J. Melvin,<lb/> Mary E. McGurn,<lb/> Susan J. Bort,<lb/> Christine Gibson and<lb/> David B. Lewis<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Departments of Pediatrics and<lb/> Immunology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of<lb/> Washington, </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>Seattle<lb/></address>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Hypomethylation of the interferon-y gene<lb/> correlates with its expression by primary T-lineage<lb/> cells *<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<div type="abstract">To determine the potential role of methylation in the regulation of interferon-y<lb/> (IFN-y) gene transcription by T cells, primary T-lineage cell populations were<lb/> analyzed for the extent of methylation of three CpG sites within or near<lb/> transcriptional activator elements in the 5&apos; flank and first intron of the human<lb/> IFN-y gene. A striking correlation was observed between the capacity of the<lb/> IFN-y gene to be expressed and the degree of hypomethylation. The IFN-y gene<lb/> was virtually completely methylated at all sites in thymocytes, neonatal T cells,<lb/> and adult CD45RAhiCD45R010 (antigenically naive) CD4 T cells, cell types that<lb/> all have a low or undetectable capacity to express the IFN-y gene. In contrast,<lb/> there was substantial hypomethylation in T-lineage cell types with relatively high<lb/> capacities to express the IFN-y gene, including adult CD8 Tcells and adult<lb/> CD45RA10CD45ROhi (memory/effector) CD4 T cells. These results suggest that<lb/> hypomethylation of the IFN-y genetic locus may be an important determinant of<lb/> IFN-y gene expression in vivo by T-lineage cells.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
