<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005460"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">1<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">SM/EN-07<lb/> </note>
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Acquisition of neutron-induced gamma signatures of chemical agents<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>B. Perot<lb/> 1<lb/> , C. Carasco<lb/> 1<lb/> , R. Vogler<lb/> 2<lb/> , E. Cusset<lb/> 2<lb/> , J.-L. Ma<lb/> 1<lb/> , P. Pras<lb/> 2<lb/> , M. Gmar<lb/> 3<lb/> , G. Sannie<lb/> 3<lb/> , S. Normand<lb/> 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> CEA, DEN,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cadarache, F-13108 St Paul-lez-Durance, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> CEA, DAM,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<affiliation>DIF, </affiliation>
	<address>F-91297 Arpajon, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> CEA, DRT, LIST,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>F-91191 Gif-sur-Yvette, France<lb/></address>

	<email>Email contact of main author: f.muelhauser@iaea.org<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract. The detection of special chemical elements that could be used by terrorist in improvised explosive<lb/> devices (IED) can be performed by the spectroscopic analysis of neutron-induced gamma rays. Capture gamma-<lb/>ray detection is optimally performed by thermal neutron analysis (TNA) between the pulses delivered by a fast<lb/> neutron generator, when the ratio between thermal and fast neutrons reaches a maximum. On the other hand,<lb/> gamma rays induced by fast neutrons, mainly during inelastic scattering reactions, can be optimally detected<lb/> with the associated particle technique (APT). The signal associated to an inspected object is enhanced with<lb/> respect to the noise coming from its environment through the selection of the gamma rays produced in the<lb/> corresponding volume. In the frame of the French CBNR R&amp;D program, which aims at developing new<lb/> detection technologies to improve the fight against chemical, biological, nuclear, radiological and explosive<lb/> threats, the combination of TNA and APT in a portable inspection system is being studied to identify the largest<lb/> panel of chemical elements of interest, such as fluorine, sodium, phosphorus, sulphur, chlorine, arsenic,<lb/> bromine, iodine, mercury and thallium. TNA and APT signatures of these elements are being acquired with low<lb/> background measurement systems and long acquisition times, to constitute a reference database that will be used<lb/> to process the data in a future mock-up of the portable inspection system. The status of the experimental<lb/> database is presented and the measured gamma-ray spectra are compared with numerical simulations performed<lb/> with the MCNPX particle transport code and the ENDF/B-VII nuclear data library.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
