<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007513"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">34 </note>
	
	<reference>January 2009 Physics Today<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">© 2009 American Institute of Physics, S</note>

	<idno>-0031-9228-0901-020-5<lb/></idno>

	<div type="introduction">Since the demonstration of the first transistors in 1947,<lb/> computing electronics has been based mostly on one mate-<lb/>rial, silicon. The emergence of MOSFETs in the 1960s and the<lb/> development of microlithography and other fabrication<lb/> techniques have allowed the continuous miniaturization of<lb/> silicon devices. The resulting increases in density and<lb/> switching speed and the reduced cost have made today&apos;s in-<lb/>formation age possible. Unfortunately, for various techno-<lb/>logical and even fundamental physical reasons, that scaling<lb/> process is reaching its useful limits. In response, researchers<lb/> are exploring ideas for logic devices based on either differ-<lb/>ent operating principles or different materials whose prop-<lb/>erties can sustain the scaling to yet smaller size and greater<lb/> performance.<lb/> Among the alternative technologies, carbon-based elec-<lb/>tronics is particularly significant. It is based on the 1991 dis-<lb/>covery of carbon nanotubes<lb/> 1 and the more recent studies of<lb/> individual graphite layers, so-called graphenes.<lb/> 2 A single-<lb/>walled CNT can be thought of as a ribbon of graphene rolled<lb/> into a seamless, one-atom-thick cylinder. The ribbon&apos;s width<lb/> determines the CNT&apos;s diameter (typically 1–2 nm), and the<lb/> direction in which the graphene is rolled defines the CNT<lb/> chirality. Moreover, most of the CNT&apos;s electrical properties<lb/> can be deduced from those of graphene after additional<lb/> boundary conditions are introduced.<lb/> 3 Both materials display<lb/> outstanding electrical properties such as either ballistic<lb/> transport or diffusive transport with long mean free paths.<lb/> And both are mechanically strong, flexible, and thermally<lb/> conductive. But unlike graphene, semiconducting nan-<lb/>otubes have fairly large bandgaps that allow them to pro-<lb/>duce large on/off current ratios when fashioned into logic<lb/> devices such as an FET.<lb/> The structure of traditional MOSFETs is described in the<lb/> box on page 35. In a CNT FET, the silicon channel is replaced<lb/> by an individual single-walled CNT (see figure 1); the<lb/> first such transistors were independently reported in 1998<lb/> from groups at Delft University of Technology and IBM&apos;s<lb/> Thomas J. Watson Research Center (see the article by Cees<lb/> Dekker in PHYSICS TODAY, May 1999, page 22).<lb/> 4<lb/> For the last several decades optoelectronics has been dom-<lb/>inated by III–V semiconductors, particularly gallium arsenide<lb/> and its alloys. In 2002, Rice University researchers observed<lb/> photoluminescence from CNTs,<lb/> 5 and the following year, IBM<lb/> researchers reported electroluminescence.<lb/> 6 Those later devel-<lb/>opments opened the possibility of basing both computing elec-<lb/>tronics and optoelectronics on the same material; for recent<lb/> reviews, see reference 3.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
