<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005065"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			
			<ptr type="web">Available online at www.sciencedirect.com<lb/></ptr>
			
			<reference>Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Reviews 19 (2008) 263–276<lb/></reference>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>TACI, an enigmatic BAFF/APRIL receptor, with new unappreciated<lb/>
					biochemical and biological properties<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Fabienne Mackay a, * , Pascal Schneider b<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>a Autoimmunity Research Unit, The Garvan Institute of Medical
					Research,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>384, Victoria Street, Darlinghurst, NSW 2010, Australia<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>b Department of Biochemistry, University of Lausanne,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>CH-1066, Epalinges, Switzerland<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> BAFF is a B cell survival factor that binds to three
				receptors BAFF-R, TACI and BCMA. BAFF-R is the receptor triggering naïve B cell<lb/>
				survival and maturation while BCMA supports the survival of plasma cells in the bone
				marrow. Excessive BAFF production leads to<lb/> autoimmunity, presumably as the
				consequence of inappropriate survival of self-reactive B cells. The function of TACI
				has been more elusive<lb/> with TACI À/À mice revealing two sides of this receptor,
				a positive one driving T cell-independent immune responses and a negative one
				down-<lb/> regulating B cell activation and expansion. Recent work has revealed that
				the regulation of TACI expression is intimately linked to the<lb/> activation of
				innate receptors on B cells and that TACI signalling in response to multimeric BAFF
				and APRIL provides positive signals to<lb/> plasmablasts. How TACI negatively
				regulates B cells remains elusive but may involve an indirect control of BAFF
				levels. The discovery of<lb/> TACI mutations associated with common variable
				immunodeficiency (CVID) in humans not only reinforces its important role for
				humoral<lb/> responses but also suggests a more complex role than first anticipated
				from knockout animals. TACI is emerging as an unusual TNF receptor-<lb/> like
				molecule with a sophisticated mode of action.<lb/>
			</div>
			
			<note type="copyright"># 2008 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

			<keywords>Keywords: BAFF; APRIL; TACI; BAFF-R; BCMA; CVID; TLR; Autoimmunity; Signalling;
				B cell activation; Plasmablast</keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
