<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006131"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Additional positive results from global Phase III program with lixisenatide for Type 2<lb/> Diabetes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="other">Copenhagen, 2011-04-12 07:02 CEST (GLOBE NEWSWIRE) --Company Announcement<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">No. </note>
	
	<date>05/2011<lb/></date>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Additional positive results from global Phase III program with lixisenatide for Type 2 Diabetes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">Lixisenatide achieves reduced HbA1c with a significant decrease in body weight, as an add-on therapy to<lb/> sulfonylureas<lb/> q In the 859-patient GetGoal-S Phase III study, lixisenatide achieved the primary efficacy endpoint of reduced<lb/> HbA1c with a significant decrease in body weight and no increase in hypoglycemia as an add-on therapy for<lb/> patients with Type 2 diabetes insufficiently controlled by sulfonylureas<lb/> q Results show potential for an improved blood glucose level during the day, further supporting the promising<lb/> therapeutic profile of lixisenatide<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">Copenhagen, 12 April 2011 — Zealand Pharma (NASDAQ OMX: ZEAL), a biopharmaceutical company based in Scandinavia,<lb/> today announced the release by its partner, sanofi-aventis, of positive top-line results from the GetGoal-S Phase III study of<lb/> lixisenatide, a once-daily GLP-1 agonist in development for patients with Type 2 diabetes. In the study, lixisenatide achieved the<lb/> primary efficacy endpoint of significant HbA1c reduction, improved glycemic control from baseline versus placebo and led to a<lb/> significant decrease in body weight.<lb/> GetGoal-S, the largest of nine studies in the GetGoal Phase III clinical program, investigated the efficacy and safety of<lb/> lixisenatide as an add-on therapy for patients with Type 2 diabetes whose condition was inadequately controlled by<lb/> sulfonylureas, with or without metformin. GetGoal-S was a randomized, double-blind and placebo-controlled study with a 24-<lb/>week treatment period. In the study, a total of 859 patients were randomized to receive either lixisenatide or placebo in step-<lb/>wise increasing doses, up to a maintenance dose of 20µg daily.<lb/> Patients in the lixisenatide group experienced a significant reduction in their HbA1c levels, with a -0.74% difference versus<lb/> placebo (p&lt;0.0001) at week 24. Lixisenatide also significantly improved patients&apos; 2-hour post-prandial (after meal) glucose<lb/> (p&lt;0.0001) and fasting plasma glucose (p&lt;0.0001) levels. In addition, patients treated with lixisenatide had a significant<lb/> decrease in body weight (p&lt;0.0001), versus those receiving placebo.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
