<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002963"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The Caffeoylics as a New Family<lb/> of Natural Antiviral Compounds<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>B. K6nig and J.H. Dustmann<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Nieders~chsisches Landesinstitut ffir Bienenforschung,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>D-3100 Celle<lb/></address>

	<div type="introduction">Considering some of the best-known<lb/> reviews on antiviral chemotherapy<lb/> [i-3], there has been on the one hand<lb/> an obvious increase in knowledge both<lb/> of antivirotically active compounds<lb/> and of modes of action, but on the<lb/> other hand, this increase in knowledge<lb/> is relatively sparse compared to the de-<lb/>velopment of antimicrobial chemother-<lb/>apy. In fact, in broad areas of viral dis-<lb/>eases there is currently no effective che-<lb/>motherapy at hand, and in many cases<lb/> no kind of therapy at all, as is reported<lb/> in many diseases caused by viruses of<lb/> the Herpes group, for example, in der-<lb/>matology [4, 5]. We were therefore in-<lb/>terested on reading of the possible anti-<lb/>Herpes activity firstly of propolis (bee<lb/> glue), a complex mixture of natural<lb/> compounds obtained by honey bees<lb/> from poplar and other plant resins, and<lb/> secondly flavonoids, which have been<lb/> reported to be its main constituents [6,<lb/> 7]. In this context it should be remem-<lb/>bered that propolis has a long history<lb/> in European ethnomedicine, that it is<lb/> currently used to a great extent in east<lb/> European medicine, that it possesses<lb/> proven antimicrobial activity [8] and<lb/> that it is attracting steadily increasing<lb/> interest in pharmacological research in<lb/> western Europe. However, the antiviral<lb/> activity tests so far reported, applying<lb/> complete propolis samples, are some-<lb/>what arbitrary in their methodology<lb/> and as most results reported are insig-<lb/>nificant, we decided to enter this field<lb/> of research ourselves.<lb/> Some analytical work was done on pro-<lb/>polis of different geographic origin<lb/> with the support of colleagues from<lb/> Chemical Institute, Veterinary School<lb/> of Hannover (Schweer, Heidmann,<lb/> Bfithe) and from the Institute of Food<lb/> Chemistry, University of Hannover<lb/> (Siewek), but we focused our efforts on<lb/> virus inhibition tests of our samples<lb/> against avian Herpes viruses. This was<lb/> made possible by the colleagues of the<lb/> Klinik ffir Geflfigel (bird clinical), Vet-<lb/>erinary School of Hannover, where the<lb/> greater part of the work reported has<lb/> been carried out. In addition to tests<lb/> of our propolis samples, the results of<lb/> which will be published elsewhere [9,<lb/> 10], we tested several cinnamic acid de-<lb/>rivatives and flavonoids, which either<lb/> have been found in our own propolis<lb/> samples or are reported in the literature<lb/> to occur in propolis. We discovered a<lb/> family of antiviral active compounds<lb/> which have the caffeoylic molecular<lb/> moiety of caffeic acid (3,4-dihydroxy-<lb/>cinnamic acid) in common.<lb/> In our assays 8 mg of the commercially<lb/> available test compounds (Roth, Sigma<lb/> or Aldrich) for the full size, or alterna-<lb/>tively 2 mg for the quarter size tests,<lb/> are dissolved in 1 ml of 95% analysis-<lb/>grade ethanol (Merck), to which 3 ml<lb/> of Dulbeccos phosphate-buffered solu-<lb/>tion are added. This results in clear yel-<lb/>low or colorless solutions with cin-<lb/>namic acid derivatives, but in milky<lb/> white or pale yellow emulsions with fla-<lb/>vonoids, similar to those of complete<lb/> propolis samples.<lb/> Chicken embryo fibroblast (CEF) cul-<lb/>tures in Petri dishes are used after 1 day<lb/> of outgrowth; the medium is poured<lb/> off and 0.1 ml of a test virus suspension<lb/> is pipetted into each Petri dish. After<lb/> 1 h of incubation, the cells are supplied<lb/> with fresh medium (BME, 2% FCS,<lb/> phenol red as indicator), between 3.6<lb/> to 3.9 ml for each Petri dish (and 4.0 ml<lb/> for the controls), to which between 0.4<lb/> and 0.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
