<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005096"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<idno>B978-0-12-374892-8.00004-1, 00004<lb/></idno>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					Chapter 4<lb/>
					Piloting and Launching<lb/>
					the Study<lb/>
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			<note type="other">93<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">
				After designing the study, it’s time to build, pilot, and launch it. We discuss<lb/>
				more about your options for building the study in Chapter 7, which gives an<lb/>
				overview of various commercial services, as well as in Chapter 8, which explains<lb/>
				how to put together a discount online study. Regardless of which implementa-<lb/>
				tion method you’ve chosen, this chapter focuses on how to prepare the study<lb/>
				to be piloted and launched. We first discuss the various aspects of the study to<lb/>
				validate through piloting, including technical checks, usability checks, and data<lb/>
				checks. We then discuss factors around timing and phasing the study launch and<lb/>
				monitoring the results.<lb/>
				4.1  Pilot Data<lb/>
				Regardless of how small or large the study, we think it’s important to do a small<lb/>
				pilot test first. Believe us when we say that no matter how confident you are that<lb/>
				the study is perfect, there will likely be some issue—whether it’s people misinter-<lb/>
				preting a task or question, a drop-down list not working properly on a particular<lb/>
				browser or platform, or data being returned to the database in some unexpected<lb/>
				format. These kinds of issues are bound to come up, and it’s ­ mportant to catch<lb/>
				them before launching the full study. Just as having an unusable Web site can<lb/>
				affect the perception of a company or institution negatively, so can administer-<lb/>
				ing a faulty online study. A study that is broken or confusing may also under-<lb/>
				mine users’ trust in a Web site or a company’s brand.<lb/>
				Piloting is especially important for online studies. Because there’s no one mod-<lb/>
				erating the study in person, it’s possible to wind up with poor quality results if<lb/>
				the study is not pretested. But this doesn’t mean the whole test will take lon-<lb/>
				ger than if you conducted it in a lab. From our experience, the end-to-end time<lb/>
				spent is about equal or less for online studies.<lb/>
				So how long are we talking? It varies. We’ve done pilot tests for online studies<lb/>
				by sending out a link to a few people and were done running and analyzing<lb/>
				it an hour, whereas for other tests we’ve done iterative piloting with different<lb/>
				groups over a few days. It also depends on how quickly the pilot participants<lb/>
			</note>
			<note type="copyright">&#169; 2010 Elsevier Inc.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
