<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005087"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Fuzzy-control for improved nitrogen removal and energy<lb/> saving in WWT-plants with pre-denitrification<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>U. Meyer* and H. J. Pöpel**<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>* Vivendi Water Germany, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Walter-Köhn-Str. 1a, 04356 Leipzig, Germany<lb/></address>

	<email>(E-mail: umeyer@vivendi-water.de)<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<address>** Carl-Ulrich Str. 39a, 64297 Darmstadt, Germany<lb/></address>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract In the last few years, numerous studies were carried out, dealing with the application of fuzzy-logic<lb/> to improve the control of the activated sludge process. In this paper, fuzzy-logic based control strategies for<lb/> wastewater treatment plants with pre-denitrification are presented that should lead to better effluent quality<lb/> and, in parallel, to a reduction of energy consumption. Extensive experimental investigations on a large scale<lb/> pilot plant as well as simulation studies (ASM1 with SIMBA ® ) were carried out in order to design, evaluate<lb/> and compare different fuzzy-controllers with each other and with comparable conventional control systems.<lb/> The fuzzy-controllers were designed as high-level controllers that determine the DO-setpoints in the aerated<lb/> zones and the ratio between aerated and non-aerated zones. Conventional PI-controllers were used to<lb/> maintain the DO-concentration at the set-point levels. The ammonia and nitrate concentration in the effluent<lb/> and the ammonia load in the influent were considered as input variables for the different fuzzy-controllers.<lb/> Compared to the operation with fixed nitrification/denitrification zones and constant DO concentrations, the<lb/> required air-flow could be reduced up to 24% by using fuzzy-logic based control strategies. In comparison<lb/> with a more advanced conventional control strategy (relay controller with two thresholds and the NH 4 -N<lb/> concentration in the effluent as single control variable) a reduction of air-flow-rate up to 14% could be<lb/> achieved. At the same time, NH 4 -N peaks in the effluent that are normally caused by peak flow conditions<lb/> could be reduced significantly. The large scale experiments show that the fuzzy-controllers can be easily<lb/> implemented in modern control and supervision systems and that the control characteristics can be followed<lb/> and modified during operation. It therefore can be expected that the developed fuzzy-control systems will be<lb/> accepted by the operating personnel in wastewater treatment plants.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords Energy saving; fuzzy-control; nitrogen removal; process optimisation<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
