<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007038"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of<lb/> Pharmacy and Pharmacology<lb/> JPP 2001, 53: 481–486<lb/> </reference>
	
	<note type="copyright">&#169; 2001 The Authors<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Received July 24, 2000<lb/> Accepted November 28, 2000<lb/></note>

	<idno type="ISSN">ISSN 0022-3573<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Characterization and purification of the vitamin K 1 2,3<lb/> epoxide reductase system from rat liver<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Louise A. Begent, Anthony P. Hill, Glyn B. Steventon, Andrew J. Hutt,<lb/> Christopher J. Pallister and David C. Cowell<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> The enzyme vitamin K 1 2,3 epoxide reductase is responsible for converting vitamin K 1 2,3<lb/> epoxide to vitamin K 1 quinone thus completing the vitamin K cycle. The enzyme is also the<lb/> target of inhibition by the oral anticoagulant, R,S-warfarin. Purification of this protein would<lb/> enable the interaction of the inhibitor with its target to be elucidated. To date a single protein<lb/> possessing vitamin K 1 2,3 epoxide reductase activity and binding R,S-warfarin has yet to be<lb/> purified to homogeneity, but recent studies have indicated that the enzyme is in fact at least<lb/> two interacting proteins. We report on the attempted purification of the vitamin K 1 2,3 epoxide<lb/> reductase complex from rat liver microsomes by ion exchange and size exclusion chromato-<lb/>graphy techniques. The intact system consisted of a warfarin-binding factor, which possessed<lb/> no vitamin K 1 2,3 epoxide reductase activity and a catalytic protein. This catalytic protein was<lb/> purified 327-fold and was insensitive to R,S-warfarin inhibition at concentrations up to 5 mM.<lb/> The addition of the S-200 size exclusion chromatography fraction containing the inhibitor-<lb/>binding factor resulted in the return of R,S-warfarin inhibition. Thus, to function normally, the<lb/> rat liver endoplasmic reticulum vitamin K 1 2,3 epoxide reductase system requires the association<lb/> of two components, one with catalytic activity for the conversion of the epoxide to the quinone<lb/> and the second, the inhibitor binding factor. This latter enzyme forms the thiol-disulphide<lb/> redox centre that in the oxidized form binds R,S-warfarin.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
