<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006522"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>

	<reference>ELSEVIER<lb/> Surface Science 370 (1996) 32-46<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">surface science<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Bromine adsorption, reaction, and etching of Cu(100)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>C.Y. Nakakura a, E.I. Altman b,,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Department of Applied Physics, Yale University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New Haven, CT 06520, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Department of Chemical Engineering, Yale University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New Haven, CT 06520, USA<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 28 March 1996; accepted for publication 9 July 1996<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> The interaction of Br 2 with Cu(100) was characterized using temperature-programmed desorption (TPD) and low-energy electron<lb/> diffraction (LEED). Initial exposure to Br2 resulted in the formation of a c(2 × 2) LEED pattern and CuBr desorption peaks at 870<lb/> and 1000 K. These desorption peaks saturated at a dose of approximately 5 L and were attributed to Br chemisorption. Continued<lb/> exposure to Br2 resulted in the growth of Cu3Br3 desorption peaks associated with the formation of bulk CuBr. The Cu3Br3<lb/> desorption peaks exhibited a strong coverage dependence. At low CuBr coverages, desorption peaks at 450 and 485 K were observed,<lb/> while at intermediate coverages a third peak at 540 K was observed, and at high coverages a single broad peak at 500 K was<lb/> observed. Similar results were obtained whether the CuBr layer was formed by exposure to Br2 or by deposition of Cu3Br3 onto a<lb/> c(2 × 2) layer. The two higher-temperature peaks were shown to be consistent with sublimation of ~ and fl CuBr, while the lowest-<lb/>temperature peak could not be associated with sublimation of any bulk phase of CuBr. The lowest-temperature peak was attributed<lb/> to either a grain-size effect or to the interaction of CuBr with chemisorbed Br. At 325 K, growth of CuBr resulted in a hexagonal<lb/> LEED pattern that disappeared upon annealing to 400 K. Again, the same results were obtained for CuBr formed by reaction with<lb/> Br 2 and by vapor deposition of Cu3Br 3, suggesting that the reaction produces near-equilibrium structures. The hexagonal LEED<lb/> pattern was attributed to compressed epitaxial CuBr(111). The reaction of Br2 with Cu(100) was characterized by a constant sticking<lb/> coefficient, indicating that the reaction is adsorption-rate limited over the range studied. The sticking coefficient was found to depend<lb/> on temperature in two distinct ways: (i) annealing the c(2 x 2) layer irreversibly increases the sticking coefficient, and (ii) the sticking<lb/> coefficient reversibly decreases with increasing reaction temperature. The first effect was attributed to structural changes in the<lb/> chemisorbed layer.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: Adsorption kinetics; Bromine; Chemisorption; Compound formation; Copper; Corrosion; Etching; Evaporation and<lb/> sublimation; Halides; Halogens; Low energy electron diffraction (LEED); Low index single crystal surfaces; Molecule-solid reactions;<lb/> Oxidation; Thermal desorption spectroscopy<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
