<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000850"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Assay for Measurement of Intact B-Type<lb/> Natriuretic Peptide Prohormone in Blood<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	
	<docAuthor>Isabelle Giuliani,<lb/> 1 Franç ois Rieunier,<lb/> 1 Catherine Larue,<lb/> 1 Jean-Franç ois Delagneau,<lb/> 1<lb/> Claude Granier,<lb/> 2 Bernard Pau,<lb/> 3 Marc Ferrière,<lb/> 4 Max Saussine,<lb/> 4 Jean-Paul Cristol,<lb/> 5<lb/> Anne-Marie Dupuy,<lb/> 5 Emmanuel Merigeon,<lb/> 2 Delphine Merle,<lb/> 2 and Sylvie Villard<lb/>2*</docAuthor>
	

	<div type="abstract">Background: B-Type natriuretic peptide (BNP 1–32 ) as<lb/> well as the N-terminal fragment of the prohormone<lb/> containing residues 1–76 (NT-proBNP 1–76 ), both cleav-<lb/>age products of the precursor proBNP 1–108 , are reported<lb/> to be powerful markers for prognosis and risk stratifi-<lb/>cation of heart failure. However, the intact precursor<lb/> also circulates in the bloodstream. Assays for the detec-<lb/>tion of these cleavage products have been developed,<lb/> but most of these assays may overestimate the concen-<lb/>trations of the cleavage products because they also<lb/> measure the precursor form. It is therefore important to<lb/> develop an immunoassay that specifically measures<lb/> solely proBNP 1–108 in plasma.<lb/> Methods: After carefully designing the peptide used to<lb/> immunize mice, we selected a specific monoclonal anti-<lb/>body (mAb Hinge76) that recognizes the cleavage site of<lb/> proBNP 1–108 , an epitope present only in the precursor<lb/> form. mAb Hinge76 recognizes recombinant proBNP 1–108<lb/> in a dose-dependent manner, without any significant<lb/> cross-reactivity with either recombinant NT-proBNP 1–76 or<lb/> synthetic BNP 1–32 . By combining mAb Hinge76 with a<lb/> polyclonal antibody directed against BNP 1–32 , we were<lb/> able to set up a proBNP 1–108 -specific sandwich immuno-<lb/>assay able to confirm the presence of proBNP 1–108 in blood<lb/> samples.<lb/> Results: From a cohort of 50 healthy persons and 170<lb/> patients with congestive heart failure (CHF), our assay<lb/> was able to differentiate healthy individuals from CHF<lb/> patients (P &lt;0.005). Interestingly, plasma proBNP 1–108<lb/> concentrations were correlated with New York Heart<lb/> Association classification. Moreover, a close relationship<lb/> between proBNP 1–108 and BNP 1–32 concentrations may<lb/> exist, as a good correlation (r<lb/> 2<lb/> ‫؍‬ 0.89) was obtained<lb/> when their respective concentrations were compared.<lb/> Conclusion: mAb Hinge76 is the first proBNP 1–108 -<lb/>specific mAb produced that allows accurate estimation<lb/> of proBNP 1–108 concentrations in plasma.</div>
	
	<note type="copyright"><lb/> © 2006 American Association for Clinical Chemistry</note>

	<div type="introduction"><lb/> In 1981, de Bold et al. (1 ) provided the definitive demon-<lb/>stration of the endocrine function of the heart. This was<lb/> followed by the identification of the &quot;brain natriuretic<lb/> peptide&quot;, or B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP),<lb/> 6 in 1988<lb/> (2, 3 ). This natriuretic peptide was originally discovered<lb/> in the porcine brain, but its name is a misnomer as the<lb/> protein is synthesized, stored, and released mainly in the<lb/> ventricular myocardium (4 ). This hormone promotes na-<lb/>triuresis and diuresis, acts as a vasodilator, and antago-<lb/>nizes the vasoconstrictor effects of the renin-angiotensin-<lb/>aldosterone system (5 ).<lb/> The human gene for BNP codes a 134 –amino acid<lb/> preproBNP precursor, which after removal of a 26-amino<lb/> acid signal peptide gives rise to a 108-amino acid proBNP<lb/> polypeptide (proBNP 1–108 ) (6 ). Further processing re-<lb/>leases a mature 32-amino acid BNP molecule (BNP 1–32 ),<lb/> which corresponds to the C-terminal sequence of the<lb/> human proBNP and a 76 –amino acid N-terminal frag-<lb/>ment (NT-proBNP 1–76 ). The former exhibits the biological<lb/> activity, whereas no defined biological function has been<lb/> found to be associated with the latter. The processing site<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Bio-Rad Laboratories,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Marnes-La-Coquette, France.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 CNRS UMR 5160,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Montpellier, France.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 I2T,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Montpellier, France.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Hô pital Arnaud de Villeneuve,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Montpellier, France.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Hô pital Lapeyronie, Département de Biochimie,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Montpellier, France.<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">* Address correspondence to this author at:</note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>CNRS UMR 5160, Faculté de<lb/> Pharmacie,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>15 avenue Charles Flahault, 34093 Montpellier Cedex 5, France.</address>

	<phone>Fax<lb/> 33-467-548-610;</phone>

	<email>e-mail sylvie.villard@cpbs.univ-montp1.fr.<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received October 7, 2005; accepted March 13, 2006.<lb/></note>

	<idno type="DOI">Previously published online at DOI: 10.1373/clinchem.2005.061770</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
