<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005239"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA<lb/> Vol. 90, pp. 7538-7542, August 1993<lb/> Immunology<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A recombinant immunotoxin containing a disulfide-stabilized<lb/> Fv fragment<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>ULRICH BRINKMANN, YORAM REITER, SUN-HEE JUNG, BYUNGKOOK LEE, AND IRA PASTAN<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Division of Cancer Biology, Diagnosis, and Centers, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bethesda, MD 20892<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">Contributed by </note>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ira Pastan,</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<date>May 10, 1993<lb/></date>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT B3(dsFv)-PE38KDEL is a recombinant im-<lb/>munotoxin composed of the Fv region of monoclonal antibody<lb/> B3 connected to a truncated form of Pseudomonas exotoxin<lb/> (PE38KDEL), in which the unstabl Fv heterodimer (composed<lb/> of heavy-and ight-chain variable regions) is held together and<lb/> stabilized by a dbsulfde bond [termed disulfide-stabilized Fv<lb/> (dsFv)]. A computer modeled structure of the B3(Fv), made by<lb/> mutating and energy miniming the amino acid sequence and<lb/> structure of McPC603, enabled us to identify positions in<lb/> conserved framework regions that &quot;hypothetically&quot; could be<lb/> used for disulflde stabilization without changing the structure<lb/> or affing antigen biding. This predon was evaluated<lb/> experimentally by constucting a disulfidelinked two-chain<lb/> dsFv-immunotoxin that was produced in Eschenchia col. The<lb/> activity and specificity of this immunotoxin was indistinguish-<lb/>able from its single-chain Fv (scFv) counterpart, indicating<lb/> that, as in B3(scFv), the structure of the binding reion is<lb/> retained in B3(dsFv). Because we introduced the stabilizing<lb/> disulfide bond in between two framework residues in a position<lb/> that is conserved in most Fv molecules, this method of lnkage<lb/> between the heavy-and light-chain variable regions should be<lb/> generaiy applicable to construct immunotoxins and dsFv mol-<lb/>ecules using other antibodies. Furthermore, the finding that<lb/> B3(dsFv) was much more stable at 370C in human plasma than<lb/> B3(scFv) indicates that dsFvs are possibly more versatile for<lb/> therapeutic application than scFvs.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
