<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004449"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SenseLess: A Database Driven White Spaces Network<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rohan Murty<lb/> , Ranveer Chandra, Thomas Moscibroda, Paramvir Bahl<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Microsoft Research,<lb/> Harvard University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<idno>Microsoft Research Technical Report MSR-TR-2010-127<lb/></idno>

	<date>September 20th, 2010<lb/></date>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> The FCC ruling on Nov 4th, 2008 on white spaces has<lb/> opened up the possibility of wireless network deploy-<lb/>ments over white spaces, i.e., vacant UHF TV channels.<lb/> A key requirement for any white space device (WSD) is<lb/> that it must ensure that none of of its transmissions inter-<lb/>fere with incumbents, namely TV transmitters and wire-<lb/>less microphones. The FCC ruling proposes two tech-<lb/>niques for WSDs to meet these requirements: spectrum<lb/> sensing and the use of a geo-location database. A host<lb/> of prior work has focussed on building better spectrum<lb/> sensing techniques for WSDs to determine those parts<lb/> of teh spectrum that are currently occupied by primaries.<lb/> While potentially feasible, this approach is technically<lb/> challenging. Hence, in this paper we propose Sense-<lb/>Less, an alternate design and approach towards building<lb/> a white spaces network. As suggested by the very name,<lb/> in SenseLess, WSDs rely less on spectrum sensing to<lb/> determine white spaces availability. Instead, they pri-<lb/>marily rely on a combination of an up-to-date database<lb/> of incumbents, sophisticated signal propagation model-<lb/>ing, and an efficient content dissemination mechanism to<lb/> ensure efficient, scalable, and safe white space network<lb/> operation. We build, deploy, and evaluate this infras-<lb/>tructure service and compare our results to ground truth<lb/> spectrum measurements. We present the unique system<lb/> design considerations in the design and implementation<lb/> of SenseLess that arise due to operating over the white<lb/> spaces. We also evaluate the efficiency and scalability of<lb/> SenseLess.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
