<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005615"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">ORIGINAL ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Peripheral Refraction in Orthokeratology<lb/> Patients<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>W. NEIL CHARMAN, DSc, JOHN MOUNTFORD, DipAppSc, FAAO,<lb/> DAVID A. ATCHISON, DSc, FAAO, and EMMA L. MARKWELL, BAppSc(Optom)<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Faculty of Health Science, University of Manchester,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Manchester, United Kingdom (WNC),</address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Private Practice, </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>Brisbane, Australia</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>(JM),<lb/> Visual and Ophthalmic Optics Group, and School of Optometry and Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation, Queensland University<lb/> of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Brisbane, Australia (DAA, EM)<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT Purpose. The purpose of this study is to measure refraction across the horizontal central visual field in orthokeratology<lb/> patients before and during treatment.<lb/> Methods. Refractions were measured out to 34° eccentricity in both temporal and nasal visual fields using a free-space<lb/> autorefractor (Shin-Nippon SRW5000) for the right eyes of four consecutively presenting myopic adult patients. Mea-<lb/>surements were made before orthokeratology treatment and during the course of treatment (usually 1 week and 2 weeks<lb/> into treatment). Refractions were converted into mean sphere (M), 90° to 180° astigmatism (J 180 ), and 45° to 135°<lb/> astigmatism (J 45 ) components.<lb/> Results. Before treatment, subjects had either a relatively constant mean sphere refraction across the field or a relative<lb/> hypermetropia in the periphery as compared with the central refraction. As a result of treatment, myopia decreased but<lb/> at reduced rate out into the periphery. Most patients had little change in mean sphere at 30° to 34°. In all patients, the<lb/> refraction pattern altered little after the first week.<lb/> Conclusion. Orthokeratology can correct myopia over the central Ϯ 10° of the visual field but produces only minor<lb/> changes at field angles larger than 30°. If converting relative peripheral hypermetropia to relative peripheral myopia is a<lb/> good way of limiting the axial elongation that leads to myopia, orthokeratology is an excellent option for achieving this.<lb/> (Optom Vis Sci 2006;83:641–648)<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key Words: astigmatic decomposition, myopia, myopia progression, orthokeratology, peripheral refraction, RGP,<lb/> visual field<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="introduction">R<lb/> efractive error has traditionally been corrected by spectacles<lb/> or contact lenses that, when worn, add appropriate com-<lb/>pensating optical power to the eye. More recently, refrac-<lb/>tive surgery has been used to permanently alter the power and<lb/> correct the refraction of the eye. Surgical techniques include re-<lb/>shaping the cornea, like in excimer laser methods such as photore-<lb/>fractive keratectomy or laser-assisted keratomileusis (LASIK), sur-<lb/>gical implantation of additional lens power, and removal of the<lb/> crystalline lens and its replacement with an appropriately powered<lb/> implant. The disadvantages of these methods are that patients<lb/> must either always wear lenses to see clearly or must undergo in-<lb/>terventionist procedures that, if unsuccessful, cannot easily be re-<lb/>versed.<lb/> Orthokeratology (ortho-K), as currently practiced, represents an<lb/> intermediate approach in which a patient&apos;s myopia and with-the-<lb/>rule astigmatism are temporarily corrected by flattening the central<lb/> cornea by programmed application of high-Dk, gas-permeable<lb/> rigid contact lenses.<lb/> 1– 4 The corneal molding effect is maintained<lb/> by the use of the lenses on a wearing schedule appropriate to the<lb/> patient&apos;s needs. This normally involves overnight lens wear with<lb/> daytime removal. The attractive feature of ortho-K is that for pa-<lb/>tients needing modest levels of myopic and with-the-rule astig-<lb/>matic correction (up to around – 4.00 DS and 1.50 DC, respec-<lb/>tively), it allows freedom from lens wear with good vision for at<lb/> least 1 day and often 2. The integrity of the cornea is not normally<lb/> affected in any permanent way, although some uncertainty exists<lb/> over possible levels of risk from infectious keratitis in comparison<lb/> with those from other types of contact lens wear, particularly for<lb/> children.<lb/> 5–10 Cessation of lens wear leads to a gradual return to the<lb/> baseline condition.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
