<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55008414"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Alternative Methods to Chemical Control<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="page">855<lb/></note>

	<idno>PS7-26 – 6247<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Factors affecting storage insect susceptibility to the<lb/> entomopathogenic fungus Beauveria bassiana<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>M.E. Wakefield<lb/> 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Central Science Laboratory,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sand Hutton, York, YO41 1LZ, UK.</address>

	<email>E-mail: m.wakefield@csl.gov.uk<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> There is an increasing need to examine<lb/> alternatives to the use of traditional pesticides in<lb/> grain storage and biological control methods<lb/> have received renewed interest over the past<lb/> decade. The various biological control agents that<lb/> could be used include macroorganisms such as<lb/> parasitoids and predators and microorganisms<lb/> such as bacteria, viruses and fungi. There is<lb/> increasing evidence that entomopathogenic fungi<lb/> have potential for control of arthropod pest<lb/> species in the storage environment. It has been<lb/> demonstrated in previous studies, and further<lb/> evidence obtained in this study, that storage beetle<lb/> species have different susceptibilities to the<lb/> entomopathogenic fungus Beauveria bassiana.<lb/> For example, the saw-toothed grain beetle,<lb/> Oryzaephilus surinamensis is more susceptible<lb/> to B. bassiana than the confused flour beetle,<lb/> Tribolium confusum at the same conidial<lb/> concentration. This could be a result of a number<lb/> of factors. Fungal infection of an insect occurs<lb/> by a series of events. Adherence of the fungal<lb/> conidia to the insect cuticle followed by<lb/> germination and penetration through the cuticle<lb/> are key events in the initial stages of infection.<lb/> In this study O. surinamensis and T. confusum<lb/> have been used as representative species to<lb/> examine adherence and germination of B.<lb/> bassiana conidia using scanning electron<lb/> microscopy (SEM). It was found that there were<lb/> differences between the two species in terms of<lb/> both the amount of conidia found on the insect<lb/> and the germination of the conidia. Fewer conidia<lb/> were found on T. confusum compared to O.<lb/> surinamensis. There was also little evidence of<lb/> germination of the conidia on T. confusum. This<lb/> study has provided information on the relative<lb/> importance of the initial stages of infection in<lb/> overall virulence and has highlighted<lb/> requirements when considering formulation of<lb/> conidia.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key words: Stored product insects; Beauveria<lb/> bassiana; Entomopathogenic fungi; Electron<lb/> microscopy; Biological control.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
