<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000330"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Research article<lb/></note>

	<reference>The Journal of Clinical Investigation<lb/></reference>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.jci.org<lb/></ptr>

	<reference>Volume 115<lb/> Number 1<lb/> January 2005<lb/></reference>
	
	<note type="page">155<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Can antibodies with specificity for soluble<lb/> antigens mimic the therapeutic effects<lb/> of intravenous IgG in the treatment<lb/> of autoimmune disease?<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Vinayakumar Siragam, 1,2 Davor Brinc, 1,2 Andrew R. Crow, 1,2 Seng Song, 1<lb/> John Freedman, 1,2,3 and Alan H. Lazarus 1,2,3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Transfusion Medicine Research and the Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathobiology,St. Michael&apos;s Hospital, 2 The Canadian Blood Services, and <lb/> 3 Department of Medicine, University of Toronto and the Toronto Platelet Immunobiology Group,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Toronto, Ontario, Canada.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Intravenous Ig (IVIg) mediates protection from the effects of immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP) as<lb/> well as numerous other autoimmune states; however, the active antibodies within IVIg are unknown. There is<lb/> some evidence that antibodies specific for a cell-associated antigen on erythrocytes are responsible, at least in<lb/> part, for the therapeutic effect of IVIg in ITP. Yet whether an IVIg directed to a soluble antigen can likewise be<lb/> beneficial in ITP or other autoimmune diseases is also unknown. A murine model of ITP was used to deter-<lb/>mine the effectiveness of IgG specific to soluble antigens in treating immune thrombocytopenic purpura. Mice<lb/> experimentally treated with soluble OVA + anti-OVA versus mice treated with OVA conjugated to rbcs (OVA-<lb/>rbcs) + anti-OVA were compared. In both situations, mice were protected from ITP. Both these experimental<lb/> therapeutic regimes acted in a complement-independent fashion and both also blocked reticuloendothelial<lb/> function. In contrast to OVA-rbcs + anti-OVA, soluble OVA + anti-OVA (as well as IVIg) did not have any effect<lb/> on thrombocytopenia in mice lacking the inhibitory receptor FcγRIIB (FcγRIIB –/– mice). Similarly, antibodies<lb/> reactive with the endogenous soluble antigens albumin and transferrin also ameliorated ITP in an FcγRIIB-<lb/>dependent manner. Finally, broadening the significance of these experiments was the finding that anti-albu-<lb/>min was protective in a K/BxN serum–induced arthritis model. We conclude that IgG antibodies directed to<lb/> soluble antigens ameliorated 2 disparate IVIg-treatable autoimmune diseases.<lb/></div>
	
	<div type="introduction">Introduction Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP) is an autoimmune<lb/> disease characterized by platelet clearance mediated by patho-<lb/>genic antiplatelet antibodies (1–3). It is thought that this plate-<lb/>let clearance is mediated by Fcγ receptor–bearing (FcγR-bearing)<lb/> macrophages in the reticuloendothelial system (RES) (4). While<lb/> intravenous Ig (IVIg) is widely used in the treatment of ITP and<lb/> other autoimmune/inflammatory diseases, its mechanism of<lb/> action has not been fully elucidated. In murine models of ITP,<lb/> it has been demonstrated that IVIg ameliorates ITP by a mech-<lb/>anism dependent upon the expression of the inhibitory FcγR<lb/> FcγRIIB (5, 6). In addition, IVIg induces RES blockade (4, 7, 8);<lb/> this &quot;competitive&quot; RES blockade has long been considered to be<lb/> the primary mechanism whereby IVIg increases platelet counts<lb/> in patients with ITP (4, 9, 10). We have previously found that<lb/> IVIg (11) and some monoclonal mimetics of IVIg (12) can block<lb/> murine RES function.<lb/> IVIg can potentially bind to a number of different cell surface<lb/> or soluble antigens (13–21), and antibody specificities within IVIg<lb/> may be responsible for different therapeutic effects through a vari-<lb/>ety of mechanisms (22–29). We undertook the present study to<lb/> establish whether antibodies to soluble antigens could ameliorate<lb/> ITP. In particular, IgGs targeted to either a soluble or a cell-bound<lb/> antigen were compared in murine ITP. OVA was selected as the<lb/> primary target antigen because it can be used in its soluble form<lb/> or can be coupled to syngeneic rbcs (OVA-rbcs), and the same anti-<lb/>OVA antibody can be used with both OVA and OVA-rbcs.<lb/> We demonstrate that, like IVIg, antibodies to soluble antigens<lb/> can ameliorate ITP in an FcγRIIB-dependent manner. In addi-<lb/>tion, anti-albumin was protective for K/BxN serum–induced<lb/> inflammatory arthritis (30, 31). Taken together, these new data<lb/> demonstrate that IgG reactive with soluble antigens can mimic<lb/> the therapeutic effects of IVIg in treating these 2 different auto-<lb/>immune diseases.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
