<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000002-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Journal of Cellular Biochemistry 90:339–346 (2003)<lb/></reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Human Cardiomyocytes Express High Level<lb/> of Na þ /Glucose
					Cotransporter 1 (SGLT1)<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Lubing Zhou, 1 * Ellen V. Cryan, 1 Michael R. D'Andrea, 2 Stanley
					Belkowski, 2<lb/> Bruce R. Conway, 1 and Keith T. Demarest 1<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 Endocrine Therapeutics and Metabolic Disorders Team, Drug
					Discovery,<lb/> Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research and Development,
					LLC.,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Raritan, New Jersey 08869<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 MorphoMetrics Team, Drug Discovery, Johnson &amp; Johnson
					Pharmaceutical Research and Development,<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>LLC., Spring House, PA 19477<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract We have quantitatively measured gene expression for the
				sodium-dependent glucose cotransporters 1<lb/> and 2 (SGLT1 and SGLT2) in 23 human
				tissues using the method of real time PCR. As predicted, our results revealed that
				the<lb/> expression of SGLT1 was very high in the small intestine (1.2E þ 6
				molecules/mg total RNA) relative to that in the kidney<lb/> (3E þ 4 molecules/mg
				total RNA). Surprisingly, we observed that the expression of SGLT1 in human heart
				was<lb/> unexpectedly high (3.4E þ 5 molecules/mg total RNA), approximately 10-fold
				higher than that observed in kidney tissue.<lb/> DNA sequencing confirmed that the
				PCR amplified fragment was indeed the human SGLT1 gene. Moreover, in situ<lb/>
				hybridization studies using a digoxigenin (DIG)-labeled antisense cRNA probe
				corresponding to human SGLT1 cDNA<lb/> confirm that human cardiomyocytes express
				SGLT1 mRNA. In contrast, the expression of SGLT2 in human tissues appears<lb/> to be
				ubiquitous, with levels ranging from 6.7E þ 4 molecules/mg total RNA (in skeletal
				muscle) to 3.2E þ 6 molecules/mg<lb/> total RNA (in kidney), levels 10–100-fold
				higher than the expression of SGLT1 in the same tissues. Our finding that human<lb/>
				cardiomyocytes express high levels of SGLT1 RNA suggests that SGLT1 may have a
				functional role in cardiac glucose<lb/> transport. Since several SGLT inhibitors are
				currently in development as potential anti-diabetic agents, it may be important<lb/>
				to assess the functional consequences of inhibition of SGLT1 in the heart.</div>
			<reference>J. Cell. Biochem. 90: 339–346, 2003.<lb/></reference>
			<note type="copyright">ß 2003 Wiley-Liss, Inc.</note>
			<keywords>Key words: human Naþ/glucose cotransporter 1 and 2 (SGLT1 and SGLT2); gene
				quantification; in situ hybridization</keywords>


		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
