<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005199"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Pervasive and Mobile Computing 7 (2011) 98–113<lb/></reference>

			<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">Pervasive and Mobile Computing<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/pmc<lb/></note>
			<note type="articleType">Fast track article<lb/></note>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>An efficient routing protocol for connecting vehicular networks to the<lb/> Internet<lb/>
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Abderrahim Benslimane a,∗ , Saman Barghi b , Chadi Assi c<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>a Université d’Avignon,</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>339 chemin des Meinajaries, Avignon, France<lb/></address>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>b School of Computer Science, University of Waterloo,</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Waterloo, Ontario, Canada<lb/></address>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>c Concordia University,</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Montreal, Quebec, Canada H3G 1M8<lb/></address>
			<note type="other">article<space dim="horizontal"/>info<lb/></note>
			<note type="submission">Article history:<lb/> Received 14 May 2010<lb/> Received in
				revised form 31 August 2010<lb/> Accepted 16 September 2010<lb/> 
			</note>	
				
			<date>Available online 23 October 2010<lb/></date>
			
			<keywords> Keywords:<lb/> VANET<lb/> Vehicular networks<lb/> Routing<lb/> Location estimation<lb/> Inter-vehicle communication<lb/></keywords>
			
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<div type="abstract"> abstract<lb/> Vehicular ad hoc networks (VANETs) enable vehicles
				to communicate with each other<lb/> (V2V) as well as with roadside infrastructure
				units (V2I). These units provide different<lb/> services such as driver information
				systems and Internet access. The high speed and high<lb/> mobility of vehicles make
				it very challenging to establish and maintain a connection<lb/> to these units. We
				introduce a new protocol which uses the characteristics of vehicle<lb/> movements to
				predict the future behavior of vehicles, and to select a route with the longest<lb/>
				lifetime to connect to the wired network. The proposed protocol aims at spreading
				the<lb/> advertisement messages through multi-hops without flooding the network and
				performing<lb/> seamless handovers. The proposed protocol is simulated by
				considering mobility scenarios,<lb/> generated by the MOVE tool, in the ns-2
				simulator tool. The simulation results show that<lb/> the proposed scheme increases
				the packet delivery ratio and decreases the packet delay<lb/> and overhead.<lb/>
			</div>
			<note type="copyright">© 2010 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
