<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003029"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>APPLIED AND ENVIRONMENTAL MICROBIOLOGY,<lb/> 0099-2240/00/$04.00ϩ0<lb/> Aug. 2000, p. 3468–3473<lb/> Vol. 66, No. 8<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2000, American Society for Microbiology. All Rights Reserved.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Colonization of Corn, Zea mays, by the Entomopathogenic<lb/> Fungus Beauveria bassiana<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>BRUCE L. WAGNER AND LESLIE C. LEWIS*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Entomology, Iowa State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Ames, Iowa<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 7 February 2000/Accepted 4 June 2000<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Light and electron microscopy were used to describe the mode of penetration by the entomopathogenic<lb/> fungus Beauveria bassiana (Balsamo) Vuillemin into corn, Zea mays L. After inoculation with a foliar spray of<lb/> conidia, germinating hyphae grew randomly across the leaf surface. Often a germ tube formed from a conidium<lb/> and elongated only a short distance before terminating its growth. Not all developing hyphae on the leaf surface<lb/> penetrated the cuticle. However, when penetration did occur, the penetration site(s) was randomly located,<lb/> indicating that B. bassiana does not require specific topographic signals at an appropriate entry site as do some<lb/> phytopathogenic fungi. Long hyphal structures were observed to follow the leaf apoplast in any direction from<lb/> the point of penetration. A few hyphae were observed within xylem elements. Because vascular bundles are<lb/> interconnected throughout the corn plant, this may explain how B. bassiana travels within the plant and<lb/> ultimately provides overall insecticidal protection. Virulency bioassays demonstrate that B. bassiana does not<lb/> lose virulence toward the European corn borer, Ostrinia nubilalis (Hübner), once it colonizes corn. This<lb/> endophytic relationship between an entomopathogenic fungus and a plant suggests possibilities for biological<lb/> control, including the use of indigenous fungal inocula as insecticides.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">The fungus Beauveria bassiana (Balsamo) Vuillemin (Deu-<lb/>teromycotina: Hyphomycetes) has been reported as a suppres-<lb/>sive agent for several insect species worldwide (1, 15). The use<lb/> of biological control with microorganisms, including fungi,<lb/> against plant pests and diseases has been the major content of<lb/> several reviews (9, 15, 40). In North America, B. bassiana is a<lb/> natural agent of control for the European corn borer, Ostrinia<lb/> nubilalis (Hübner) (1, 10), a serious pest of corn, Zea mays L.<lb/> The potential for suppression of O. nubilalis larvae by B. bas-<lb/>siana persisting on the phylloplane or within the corn plant has<lb/> been proposed (24). Bing and Lewis (4–6, 23) showed that B.<lb/> bassiana, applied to whorl-stage corn by foliar application or<lb/> injection, colonized, translocated, and persisted in corn plants<lb/> to provide season-long suppression of O. nubilalis (26). Field<lb/> studies have demonstrated that B. bassiana forms an endo-<lb/>phyte with corn, but the potential insecticidal application of<lb/> this relationship and the method of colonization of corn by B.<lb/> bassiana have not been investigated. Thus, in the present study,<lb/> we used light microscopic (LM) and electron microscopic tech-<lb/>niques to elucidate penetration and colonization of corn by B.<lb/> bassiana.<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">MATERIALS AND METHODS</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
