<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005209"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>J. Med. Microbiol. -Voi. 38 (1993), 384-387<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">&#169; 1993 The Pathological Society of Great Britain and Ireland<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Detection of C/mtridium difficile enterotoxin gene in<lb/> clinical specimens by the polymerase chain reaction<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>HELEN S. BOONDEEKHUN, V. GURTLER&quot;, MARYANN L. ODD, VICKI A. WILSON and<lb/> B. C. MAYALL<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Heidelberg West 308 I , Victoria, Australia<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Summary. A rapid assay was developed for detection of the Clostridium dzficile enterotoxin<lb/> gene in stool specimens by means of the polymerase chain reaction (PCR). The PCR primers<lb/> amplified a 63-bp repetitive sequence of the enterotoxin gene, thereby generating a distinctive<lb/> ladder pattern of DNA bands following electrophoresis. Crude DNA extracts from stools<lb/> containing C. dzficile produced one (63-bp) or more bands of the characteristic ladder. Of 172<lb/> stool specimens from 58 patients, 37 gave positive results by culture (15 specimens) or<lb/> cytotoxin assay (36 specimens). When 36 available &quot; positive&quot; specimens were tested by the<lb/> PCR assay, 34 (94%) gave positive results-24 by direct testing, and 10 after extraction of<lb/> DNA by the Qiagen procedure. Insufficient material of the remaining two specimens was<lb/> available for DNA extraction. Of 2 1 stools &quot; negative &quot; for C. dzficile by culture or cytotoxin<lb/> assay, one gave a positive result by PCR and seven produced atypical bands. The rapid PCR<lb/> detection technique for C. dzficile was more sensitive than standard culture, and of a<lb/> sensitivity similar to cytotoxin testing. The method has the potential for adoption in routine<lb/> laboratory practice.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
