<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005135"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<ptr type="web">Available online at www.sciencedirect.com<lb/></ptr>
			<reference>Bioresource Technology 99 (2008) 4919–4928<lb/></reference>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Effects of mixing on methane production during thermophilic<lb/>
					anaerobic digestion of manure: Lab-scale and pilot-scale
					studies<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Prasad Kaparaju a , Inmaculada Buendia a,1 , Lars Ellegaard b , Irini
					Angelidakia a, *<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>a Institute of Environment and Resources, Technical University of
					Denmark,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Building 115, DK-2800, Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark<lb/></address>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>b Burmeister and Wain Scandinavian Contractor A/S, </affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Gydevang 35, DK-3450 Allerød, Denmark<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received 22 June 2007; received in revised form 5 September 2007; accepted 10 September
				2007<lb/> 
			</note>
			<date>	
				Available online 26 October 2007<lb/>
			</date>
			<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> The effect of mixing on anaerobic digestion of manure
				was evaluated in lab-scale and pilot-scale experiments at 55 °C. The effect of<lb/>
				continuous (control), minimal (mixing for 10 min prior to extraction/feeding) and
				intermittent mixing (withholding mixing for 2 h prior<lb/> to extraction/feeding) on
				methane production was investigated in three lab-scale continuously stirred tank
				reactors. On comparison to<lb/> continuous mixing, intermittent and minimal mixing
				strategies improved methane productions by 1.3% and 12.5%, respectively. Pilot-<lb/>
				scale studies also supported the lab-scale results with an average 7% increase in
				biogas yields during intermittent mixing compared to<lb/> continuous mixing. The
				effect of mixing intensities (minimal, gentle or vigorous) in batch assays at 55 °C
				showed that when the process<lb/> was overloaded by high substrate to inoculum ratio
				(40/60), gentle (35 times per minute) or minimal mixing (10 min mixing before
				feed-<lb/> ing) was advantageous compared to vigorous mixing (110 times per minute).
				On the other hand, under low substrate to inoculum ratio<lb/> (10/90), gentle mixing
				was the best. The study thus indicated that mixing schemes and intensities have some
				effect on anaerobic digestion<lb/> of manures.<lb/> 
			</div>
			<note type="coypright">© 2007 Elsevier Ltd. All rights
				reserved.<lb/></note>

			<keywords>Keywords: Anaerobic digestion; Intensity; Mixing; Methanogens;
				Stratification</keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
