<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007941"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Life Sciences<lb/> </note>
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Antibody Screening Sandwich Assay<lb/> by Label-free Epic® Technology<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jeffery J. Scibek*, Arron S. Xu*, Klaus Kaluza#, and Anthony G.<lb/> Frutos*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>*Corning Life Sciences, Corning Inc,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Corning, NY 14831, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation># Screening Technologies, Pharma Research Penzberg, Roche<lb/> Diagnostics GmbH,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nonnenwald 2, 82377 Penzberg, Germany<lb/></address>

	<note>2 Corning Restricted<lb/> Life Sciences<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Antibody therapeutics represent the single fastest growing area of drug discovery and<lb/> development. There are now more than 20 approved antibody therapeutics on the market with<lb/> hundreds more in clinical trials and preclinical development. As a result of the increased<lb/> interest in antibody therapeutics, there is currently a need for new tools to identify candidate<lb/> antibodies as early in the drug discovery process as possible. These new tools must be i)<lb/> sensitive enough to detect antibody-antigen interactions in complex biological samples; ii)<lb/> flexible and easy to use and iii) high throughput for biopharmaceutical discovery needs.<lb/> A label-free antibody competition assay was developed on the Corning® Epic® System<lb/> to demonstrate the detection of the competitive binding to an immobilized receptor, and the<lb/> ability to distinguish antibodies of distinct vs overlapping binding epitopes in complex samples.<lb/> In these studies, the binding of three monoclonal antibodies against macrophage-colony<lb/> stimulating factor receptor (M-CSF R) was investigated. The M-CSF receptor contained an Fc<lb/> tag and was captured non-covalently via an anti-Fc antibody immobilized in the wells of a 384-<lb/>well Epic® microplate. Binding of three different antibodies to the immobilized receptor was<lb/> studied in the absence and presence of serum. When added individually, each antibody<lb/> exhibited dose-dependent binding to the receptor. The assay exhibited a large signal window<lb/> and a dynamic range from 0.1mg/mL to &gt;10mg/mL in both assay buffer and culture medium<lb/> containing 10% bovine serum. To test for competition, antibodies were added either<lb/> sequentially or in batches to M-CSF R. Two of the antibodies were shown to compete for the<lb/> same epitope on M-CSF R, consistent with the overlap in binding epitopes. The third antibody<lb/> showed binding to a different epitope on the receptor and was non-competitive. The observed<lb/> sensitivity of the assay suggests that the Epic® System can be used to screen hybridoma<lb/> samples without the need for labeled secondary antibodies in a simple, high-throughput<lb/> format.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
