<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005791"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Pose-Consistent 3D Shape Segmentation Based<lb/> on a Quantum Mechanical Feature Descriptor<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mathieu Aubry<lb/> 1,2 , Ulrich Schlickewei<lb/> 1 and Daniel Cremers<lb/> 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Computer Science,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>TU München<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Adobe Systems Inc.</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cambridge, MA<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract. We propose a novel method for pose-consistent segmenta-<lb/>tion of non-rigid 3D shapes into visually meaningful parts. The key idea<lb/> is to study the shape in the framework of quantum mechanics and to<lb/> group points on the surface which have similar probability of presence<lb/> for quantum mechanical particles. For each point on an object&apos;s sur-<lb/>face these probabilities are encoded by a feature vector, the Wave Ker-<lb/>nel Signature (WKS). Mathematically, the WKS is an expression in the<lb/> eigenfunctions of the Laplace–Beltrami operator of the surface. It char-<lb/>acterizes the relation of surface points to the remaining surface at various<lb/> spatial scales. Gaussian mixture clustering in the feature space spanned<lb/> by the WKS signature for shapes in several poses leads to a grouping<lb/> of surface points into different and meaningful segments. This enables<lb/> us to perform consistent and robust segmentation of new versions of the<lb/> shape.<lb/> Experimental results demonstrate that the detected subdivision agrees<lb/> with the human notion of shape decomposition (separating hands, arms,<lb/> legs and head from the torso for example). We show that the method is<lb/> robust to data perturbed by various kinds of noise. Finally we illustrate<lb/> the usefulness of a pose-consistent segmentation for the purpose of shape<lb/> retrieval.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
