<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005174"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Applied Energy 88 (2011) 1681–1689<lb/></reference>
			<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">Applied Energy<lb/></note>
			<ptr type="web">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/apenergy<lb/></ptr>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Passive direct methanol fuel cells for portable electronic
					devices<lb/>
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>F. Achmad a , S.K. Kamarudin a,b,⇑ , W.R.W. Daud a , E.H. Majlan
					a<lb/>
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>a Fuel Cell Institute, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address> 43600 UKM Bangi, Selangor, Malaysia<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>b Department of Chemical and Process Engineering, Universiti Kebangsaan
					Malaysia,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>43600 UKM Bangi, Selangor, Malaysia<lb/></address>

			<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/></note> 
			<note type="submission">>Article history:<lb/> Received 19 July
				2010<lb/> Received in revised form 3 November 2010<lb/> Accepted 7 November
				2010<lb/>
			</note>	 
				
			<date>Available online 18 December 2010<lb/></date>
			
			<keywords>Keywords:<lb/> Direct methanol fuel
				cell<lb/> Electronic devices<lb/> Renewable energy<lb/>
			</keywords>
			
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<div type="abstract">
				a b s t r a c t<lb/> Due to
				the increasing demand for electricity, clean, renewable energy resources must be
				developed. Thus,<lb/> the objective of the present study was to develop a passive
				direct methanol fuel cell (DMFC) for portable<lb/> electronic devices. The power
				output of six dual DMFCs connected in series with an active area of 4 cm 2<lb/> was
				approximately 600 mW, and the power density of the DMFCs was 25 mW cm À2 . The DMFCs
				were<lb/> evaluated as a power source for mobile phone chargers and media players.
				The results indicated that<lb/> the open circuit voltage of the DMFC was between 6.0
				V and 6.5 V, and the voltage under operating con-<lb/> ditions was 4.0 V. The fuel
				cell was tested on a variety of cell phone chargers, media players and PDAs.<lb/>
				The cost of energy consumption by the proposed DMFC was estimated to be USD 20 W À1
				, and the cost<lb/> of methanol is USD 4 kW h. Alternatively, the local conventional
				electricity tariff is USD 2 kW h. However,<lb/> for the large-scale production of
				electronic devices, the cost of methanol will be significantly lower.<lb/> Moreover,
				the electricity tariff is expected to increase due to the constraints of fossil fuel
				resources<lb/> and pollution. As a result, DMFCs will become competitive with
				conventional power sources.<lb/>
			</div>
			<note type="copyright">&#169; 2010 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
