<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005010"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>

			<reference>Expert Systems with Applications 38 (2011) 2536–2549<lb/></reference>
			
			<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">Expert Systems with Applications<lb/></note>
			<ptr type="web">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/eswa<lb/></ptr>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Representing and reasoning on fuzzy UML models: A description logic
					approach<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Z.M. Ma a,⇑ , Fu Zhang a , Li Yan b , Jingwei Cheng a<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>a College of Information Science and Engineering, Northeastern
					University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Shenyang, 110819, China<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>b School of Software, Northeastern University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Shenyang, 110819, China<lb/></address>

			<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/></note>
			<keywords>Keywords:<lb/> Knowledge representation<lb/> Reasoning Fuzzy UML model<lb/>
				Fuzzy description logic<lb/></keywords>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<div type="abstract">a b s t r a c t<lb/> UML is the most widely accepted formalism for
				the analysis and design of software. Recent proposals to<lb/> improve the ability of
				reasoning automatically on UML models. However, information imprecision and<lb/>
				uncertainty exist in many real-world applications and hence fuzzy UML models have
				been extensively<lb/> investigated. In this paper, we propose a description logic
				approach to represent and reason on fuzzy<lb/> UML models. Firstly, for the specific
				purposes of representing and reasoning on fuzzy UML models, a<lb/> fuzzy description
				logic called FDLR (fuzzy DLR) is introduced. Moreover, we further investigate the
				rea-<lb/> soning problems and reasoning algorithms for FDLR. Then, the fuzzy UML
				model is investigated, and a<lb/> kind of formal definition of fuzzy UML models is
				proposed. Furthermore, representation and reasoning<lb/> of fuzzy UML models with
				FDLR is investigated, i.e., we first consider the fuzzy UML model and the cor-<lb/>
				responding fuzzy UML instantiations (i.e., object diagrams) simultaneously, and
				translate them into FDLR<lb/> knowledge bases at both terminological (TBox) and
				assertional (ABox) levels, respectively; then how the<lb/> reasoning problems of
				fuzzy UML models (e.g., consistency, subsumption, logical consequence, and so
				on)<lb/> may be reasoned through reasoning mechanism of FDLR is investigated. The
				formalization in FDLR of<lb/> fuzzy UML models makes a significant improvement and
				it is the first step towards developing intelligent<lb/> systems that provide
				computer aided support during the application design phase in order to automat-<lb/>
				ically detect relevant properties of fuzzy UML models.<lb/></div>
			<note type="copyright">&#169; 2010 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
