<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005121"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Defect-Oriented Dynamic Fault Models for Embedded-SRAMs
					*<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Simone Borri 1 Magali Hage-Hassan 1,2 Patrick Girard 3 Serge
					Pravossoudovitch 3 Arnaud Virazel 3<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 Infineon Technologies France<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>2600, Route des Crêtes<lb/>F-06560 Sophia-Antipolis<lb/></address>
			<email>simone.borri@infineon.com</email>
			
			<space dim="horizontal"/>


			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 Institut des Sciences de l'Ingénieur<lb/> de Montpellier (ISIM)</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Place E. Bataillon<lb/>F-34095 Montpellier<lb/></address>
			<email>hage@isim.univ-montp2.fr</email>
			
			<space dim="horizontal"/>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>3 Laboratoire d’Informatique, Robotique<lb/>et Microélectronique (LIRMM)
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>161, Rue Ada<lb/>F-34392 Montpellier</address>
			<email>{lastname}@lirmm.fr<lb/></email>


			<div type="abstract">Abstract *<lb/> This paper presents the results of resistive
				fault<lb/> insertion in the core-cell array and in the address<lb/> GHFRGHUU RII
				WKHH ,QILQHRQQ PP HPEHGGHG-SRAM family.<lb/> Resistive opens defects were the
				primary target of this<lb/> study because of their growing importance in VDSM<lb/>
				technologies. Electrical simulations have been performed<lb/> to evaluate the
				effects of resistive opens in terms of<lb/> functional faults detected and verify
				the presence of<lb/> timing-dependent faults. Read disturb, deceptive read<lb/>
				disturb and dynamic read disturb faults have been<lb/> reproduced and accurately
				characterized. The<lb/> dependence of the fault detection on memory operating<lb/>
				conditions, injected resistance value and clock speed have<lb/> been investigated
				and the importance of speed testing for<lb/> dynamic fault models is emphasized.
				Finally resistive<lb/> Address Decoder Open Faults (ADOF) have been<lb/> simulated
				and the conditions for maximum fault detection<lb/> are discussed as well as the
				resulting implications for<lb/> memory test.<lb/>
			</div>
			
			<grant>* This work has been partially funded by the French government under the framework of the MEDEA+ A503 “Associate” European program.<lb/></grant>
			
			<reference>Proceedings of the Eighth IEEE European Test Workshop (ETW’03)<lb/></reference>
			<note type="other">1530-1877/03 $17.00</note> 
			<note type="copyright">© 2003 IEEE<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
