<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002088"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<address>21, rue d&apos;Artois, F-75008 PARIS<lb/></address>

	<reference>B4-109<lb/> 
	CIGRE 2010<lb/></reference>

	<ptr type="web">http : //www.cigre.org<lb/></ptr>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Continental Overlay HVDC-Grid<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>G. ASPLUND<lb/> B. JACOBSON<lb/> B. BERGGREN<lb/> K. LINDÉN*<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>ABB Sweden<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">SUMMARY<lb/> The growth in renewable power generation, increases in power trade across national borders,<lb/> deregulation and global climate discussions are posing new challenges to power generation and high<lb/> voltage transmission systems.<lb/> The need for new power transfer corridors, especially in mature networks such as in Europe and North<lb/> America, is impeded by the permitting process to build new overhead lines, which is very slow or<lb/> even impossible. An HVDC-grid, using converted ac-overhead lines or dc-underground cables could<lb/> offer an alternative.<lb/> In a two terminal HVDC-transmission the load flow is fully controlled, whereas in a meshed dc-grid it<lb/> might not be possible to directly control currents in all lines. Buses connected to large production<lb/> areas will have higher voltages than buses connected to major load centres. To make sure that no<lb/> branch is overloaded, no bus has too high voltage and to minimise losses, load flow calculations need<lb/> to be done both during the designing stage and during the operation of the dc-grid together with the ac-<lb/>system.<lb/> This paper shows how power flow calculations can be done by a simple routine which has been<lb/> implemented in the well-known program MATLAB. The paper also shows how dc-voltage and power<lb/> are controlled in smaller dc-systems and shows the analogy with power-frequency control in an ac-<lb/>system. The need for a new power flow control strategy for large HVDC-systems such as in an<lb/> Overlay HVDC-Grid is discussed.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
