<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002545"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Slit Diaphragms Contain Tight Junction Proteins<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hirotaka Fukasawa, Scott Bornheimer, Krystyna Kudlicka, and Marilyn G. Farquhar<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine, University of California San Diego,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>La Jolla, California.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Slit diaphragms are essential components of the glomerular filtration apparatus, as changes in these<lb/> junctions are the hallmark of proteinuric diseases. Slit diaphragms, considered specialized adherens<lb/> junctions, contain both unique membrane proteins (e.g., nephrin, podocin, and Neph1) and typical<lb/> adherens junction proteins (e.g., P-cadherin, FAT, and catenins). Whether slit diaphragms also contain<lb/> tight junction proteins is unknown. Here, immunofluorescence, immunogold labeling, and cell fraction-<lb/>ation demonstrated that rat slit diaphragms contain the tight junction proteins JAM-A (junctional<lb/> adhesion molecule A), occludin, and cingulin. We found these proteins in the same protein complexes as<lb/> nephrin, podocin, CD2AP, ZO-1, and Neph1 by cosedimentation, coimmunoprecipitation, and pull-down<lb/> assays. PAN nephrosis increased the protein levels of JAM-A, occludin, cingulin, and ZO-1 several-fold<lb/> in glomeruli and loosened their attachment to the actin cytoskeleton. These data extend current<lb/> information about the molecular composition of slit diaphragms by demonstrating the presence of tight<lb/> junction proteins, although slit diaphragms lack the characteristic morphologic features of tight junc-<lb/>tions. The contribution of these proteins to the assembly of slit diaphragms and potential signaling<lb/> cascades requires further investigation.<lb/></div>

	<reference>J Am Soc Nephrol 20: 1491–1503, 2009.</reference>

	<idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1681/ASN.2008101117</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
