<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000022-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Vol. 264, No. 7, Issue of March 5,pp. 3869-3876, 1989<lb/></reference>
			<note type="other">Printed in U.S.A.</note>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<reference>THE
			JOURNAL BIOLOGICAL
			OF
			CHEMISTRY<lb/></reference>
			<note type="copyright">0 1989 by The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Inc.<lb/></note>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Purification and Characterization of an a-1,Z-Mannosidase Involved
					in<lb/> Processing Asparagine-linked Oligosaccharides*<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<note type="submission">(Received for publication, July 6, 1988)<lb/></note>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>W. Thomas Forsee, Christopher F. Palmer, and John S.
					Schutzbach<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>From the Department of Microbiology, University of
					Alabama,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Birmingham, Alabama 35294<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">A calcium-dependent a-1,Z-mannosidase involved in<lb/> the
				processing of asparagine-linked oligosaccharides<lb/> was purified to homogeneity
				from rabbit liver micro-<lb/>somes. N-terminal amino acid analysis was
				consistent<lb/> with the presence of a homogeneous protein. Sodium<lb/> dodecyl
				sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis,<lb/> under both reducing and nonreducing
				conditions, re-<lb/>vealed a single protein band with an apparent molec-<lb/>ular
				weight of 52,000. Gel filtration and sedimentation<lb/> analysis under
				nondenaturing<lb/> conditions suggested<lb/> that the purified enzyme is a monomeric
				protein. The<lb/> mannosidase is a glycoprotein based on the presence of<lb/>
				protein-linked sugar and specific binding of the en-<lb/>zyme to concanavalin
				A-Sepharose. Purified mannos-<lb/>idase was optimally active between pH 6.0 and
				6.0.<lb/> The enzyme was inactive withp-nitrophenyl-a-D-man-<lb/>nopyranoside and
				was inhibited by deoxymannojiri-<lb/>mycin but not by swainsonine. The enzyme was
				specif-<lb/>ically activated by Ca", with half-maximal activation<lb/> occurring at
				concentrations of 10 pM or less and was<lb/> inhibited by Mn2+, Co2+, Ba2+, and
				Zn2+. Calcium ions<lb/> protected the enzyme against inactivation by
				p-chlo-<lb/>romercuribenzoate. Rabbit liver mannosidase hydro-<lb/>lyzed
				a-1,Z-mannosyl-mannose linkages in a variety<lb/> of substrates including
				methyl-2-O-a-D-mannopy-<lb/>ranosyl-a-D-mannopyranoside (Schutzbach, J. S.<lb/>
				(1987) Anal. Biochem. 167,279-283), ovalbumin gly-<lb/>copeptide IV, and the high
				mannose chains of thyro-<lb/>globulin and phytohemagglutinin-P. Approximately<lb/>
				70% of the a-l,Z-linked mannosyl units in the oligo-<lb/>saccharides of
				thyroglobulin were accessible to rabbit<lb/> liver a-mannosidase, whereas most of
				the a-1,Z-man-<lb/>nosy1 units in phytohemagglutinin were resistant to<lb/>
				digestion prior to heat denaturation of the plant lectin.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
