<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007531"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>JOURNAL OF VIROLOGY, JUly 1994, p. 4636-4642<lb/> Vol. 68, No. 7<lb/></reference>

	<idno>00 &apos;-538X/94/$04.00+0<lb/></idno>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 1994, American Society for Microbiology<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>NOTES<lb/> A Novel, Glycan-Dependent Epitope in the V2 Domain of Human<lb/> Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1 gpl20 Is Recognized by a Highly<lb/> Potent, Neutralizing Chimpanzee Monoclonal Antibody<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SUJATA V. WARRIER,1 ABRAHAM PINTER,&apos; WILLIAM J. HONNEN,1 MARC GIRARD,2<lb/> ELIZABETH MUCHMORE,3 AND SHERMAINE A. TILLEY&apos;*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Public Health Research Institute,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New York, New York 10016,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Institut Pasteur,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>75015 Paris, France,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 and Laboratory<lb/> for Experimental Medicine and Surgery in Primates, New York University Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tuxedo, New York 109871<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 9 November 1993/Accepted 21 March 1994<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">An anti-gpl20 monoclonal antibody (MAb), C108G (-yl, K), was isolated from a chimpanzee that had been<lb/> infected with strain IIIB of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-l111B) and subsequently immunized<lb/> with the recombinant glycoprotein rgpl60MN. This MAb is specific for the IIIB strain of HIV-1 and related<lb/> clones and exhibits very potent neutralization of these viruses; e.g., 100% neutralization of approximately 8 x<lb/> 103 infectious units of HXB2 was achieved with 125 ng of C108G per ml. Commensurate with this potent<lb/> neutralizing activity, the apparent affinity of C108G for rgpl60AI was very high, i.e., approximately 3 x 1010<lb/> liters/mol. The C108G epitope was not destroyed by reduction of gpl20 disulfide bonds but was profoundly<lb/> disrupted by removal of N-linked sugars from gpl20. Despite the importance of a glycan(s) in forming the<lb/> C108G epitope, specific binding of C108G to synthetic peptides overlapping in amino acids 162 to 169 of the<lb/> V2 region was detected, albeit with an affinity approximately 2,000-fold lower than that of C108G&apos;s binding to<lb/> glycosylated envelope protein. This epitope mapping correlated with results of competition assays using MAbs<lb/> of known epitope specificities. To our knowledge, this is the first description of an anti-V2 MAb raised in<lb/> response to HIV-1 infection. Its potent neutralizing activity and epitope specificity indicate that the V2 domain<lb/> of gpl20 may be an effective target of the protective immune response and, therefore, potentially an important<lb/> component of HIV vaccines.<lb/> Two major neutralization epitope clusters in gpl2O have<lb/> been identified as targets in human immunodeficiency virus<lb/> type 1 (HIV-1)-infected individuals: the V3 loop (reviewed in<lb/> references 27 and 44) and the CD4-binding site (44). Antibod-<lb/>ies against the V3 loop inhibit HIV-induced syncytium forma-<lb/>tion and infectivity, and mutations within this region inhibit the<lb/> fusogenicity of HIV-1 Env (7, 12, 16, 17, 31, 45) and affect<lb/> tropism of the virus (3, 16, 37, 49, 50). It has been suggested<lb/> that at least some antibodies against epitopes overlapping the<lb/> CD4-binding site may act as competitive inhibitors to block<lb/> viral attachment to the CD4 receptor (29); however, the<lb/> neutralization potency of such monoclonal antibodies (MAbs)<lb/> does not correlate with their ability to be blocked by soluble<lb/> CD4 (sCD4) in binding to gpl2O or to block gpl2O-CD4<lb/> binding (la, 25), and their mechanism of action has yet to be<lb/> elucidated.<lb/> The V2 region is clearly important in HIV-1 gpl2O function,<lb/> in that the amino acid sequence in this region influences the<lb/> replication competence of the virus (38) as well as its tropism<lb/> (21, 50). In addition, single amino acid changes in the V2<lb/> domain decrease the association between gpl2O and gp4l (38),<lb/> and the configuration of a hypervariable locus in the V2<lb/> domain has recently been correlated with non-syncytium-<lb/>inducing (SI)-to-SI phenotype conversion (13). Recently, a</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
