<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000122-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Comparison of Metal Ion Dissolutions from Lithium Ion<lb/> Battery Cathodes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>W. Choi * and A. Manthiram ** ,z<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Materials Science and Engineering Program, The University of Texas at Austin,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Austin, Texas 78712, USA<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">With an aim to develop a better understanding of the capacity fade mechanisms of manganese spinel oxide cathodes, the amount<lb/> of metal ion dissolution from various lithium ion battery cathodes ͑layered, orthorhombic LiMnO 2 , 4 V spinel, 5 V spinel, and<lb/> olivine͒ is compared. >Orthorhombic LiMnO 2 , layered LiMn 0.8 Cr 0.2 O 2 , and spinel LiMn 2 O 4 containing Mn 3+ exhibit much higher<lb/> amounts of manganese dissolution irrespective of the structure compared to the total transition metal ion dissolution found from<lb/> cathodes containing Mn 4+ , such as layered LiNi 1/3 Mn 1/3 Co 1/3 O 2 and 5 V spinel LiMn 1.5 Ni 0.5 O 4 or from layered LiCoO 2 and<lb/> olivine LiFePO 4 . However, the manganese dissolution from the Mn 3+ -containing spinel oxides could be lowered significantly to<lb/> the levels found from LiCoO 2 , LiFePO 4 , and LiMn 1.5 Ni 0.5 O 4 by appropriate cationic and anionic ͑fluorine͒ substitutions,<lb/> which leads to excellent capacity retention at elevated temperatures. For example, LiMn 1.85 Li 0.075 Ni 0.075 O 4 and<lb/> LiMn 1.85 Li 0.075 Ni 0.075 O 3.94 F 0.06 exhibit manganese dissolutions of 1.5 and 1.1%, respectively, compared to 3.2% for LiMn 2 O 4 .<lb/> Furthermore, manganese dissolution is found to bear a clear relationship to the lattice parameter difference ⌬a between the two<lb/> cubic phases formed during the charge-discharge process; Mn dissolution decreases with decreasing ⌬a.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2006 The Electrochemical Society. ͓</note>

	<idno>DOI: 10.1149/1.2219710͔</idno> 

	<note type="copyright">All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Manuscript submitted February 24, 2006; revised manuscript received May 16, 2006.</note> 

	Available electronically 

	<date>July 20, 2006</date>.<lb/> 

	* Electrochemical Society Student Member.<lb/> 

	** Electrochemical Society Active Member.<lb/>

	z E-mail:
	<email>rmanth@mail.utexas.edu<lb/></email>

	<reference>Journal of The Electrochemical Society, 153 ͑9͒ A1760-A1764 ͑2006͒<lb/></reference>

	0013-4651/2006/153͑9͒/A1760/5/$20.00
	
	<note type="copyright">© The Electrochemical Society </note>

	<page>A1760<lb/></page>

	Downloaded 26 May 2011 to 145.64.134.242. 

	<note type="copyright">Redistribution subject to ECS license or copyright; see http://www.ecsdl.org/terms_use.jsp</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
