<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000006-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<note type="other">G Model<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">PRONEU 1104 1–13<lb/></note>
			<reference>Progress in Neurobiology xxx (2011) xxx–xxx<lb/></reference>
			<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
			<reference>Progress in Neurobiology<lb/></reference>
			<ptr type="web">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/pneurobio</ptr>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>The emergence of designed multiple ligands for neurodegenerative
					disorders<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Werner J. Geldenhuys a , Moussa B.H. Youdim b,c,1 , Richard T. Carroll a
					, Cornelis J. Van der Schyf a, *<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>a Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Northeastern Ohio Universities
					Colleges of Medicine and Pharmacy,</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>4209 State Route 44, Rootstown, OH 44272, USA<lb/></address>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>b Technion-Rappaport Family-Faculty of Medicine, Eve Topf and US
					National Parkinson Foundation Centers of Excellence for Neurodegenerative
					Diseases,</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Haifa, Israel<lb/></address>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>c Department of Biology, Yonsei World Central University,</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Seoul, South Korea<lb/></address>
			<note>A R T I C L E I N F O<lb/></note>
			<note type="submission">Article history:<lb/> Received 3 September 2010<lb/> Received in
				revised form 13 April 2011<lb/> Accepted 15 April 2011<lb/> Available online
				xxx<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">7</note>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<div type="abstract">The incidence of neurodegenerative diseases has seen a constant
				increase in the global population, and is<lb/> likely to be the result of extended
				life expectancy brought about by better health care. Despite this<lb/> increase in
				the incidence of neurodegenerative diseases, there has been a dearth in the
				introduction of<lb/> new disease-modifying therapies that are approved to prevent or
				delay the onset of these diseases, or<lb/> reverse the degenerative processes in
				brain. Mounting evidence in the peer-reviewed literature shows<lb/> that the
				etiopathology of these diseases is extremely complex and heterogeneous, resulting in
				significant<lb/> comorbidity and therefore unlikely to be mitigated by any drug
				acting on a single pathway or target. A<lb/> recent trend in drug design and
				discovery is the rational design or serendipitous discovery of novel drug<lb/>
				entities with the ability to address multiple drug targets that form part of the
				complex pathophysiology<lb/> of a particular disease state. In this review we
				discuss the rationale for developing such multifunctional<lb/> drugs (also called
				designed multiple ligands or DMLs), and why these drug candidates seem to offer<lb/>
				better outcomes in many cases compared to single-targeted drugs in pre-clinical
				studies for<lb/> neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s
				disease. Examples are drawn from<lb/> the literature of drug candidates that have
				already reached the market, some unsuccessful attempts, and<lb/> others that are
				still in the drug development pipeline.<lb/>
			</div>
			<note type="copyright">ß 2011 Published by Elsevier Ltd.<lb/></note>
			<keywords>Keywords:<lb/> HLA20/HLA20A<lb/> Homobivalent b-carbolines<lb/>
				Istradefylline/KW6002<lb/> L-3-n-butylphthalide<lb/> Ladostigil<lb/> Memoquin<lb/>
				mitoNEET<lb/> NGP1-01<lb/> Pioglitazone<lb/> Rasagiline<lb/> Resveratrol<lb/>
			</keywords>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
