<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003316"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Mini-Symposium<lb/> </note>
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Understanding the Role of DISC1 in Psychiatric Disease and<lb/> during Normal Development<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Nicholas J. Brandon, 1 J. Kirsty Millar, 2 Carsten Korth, 3 Hazel Sive, 4,5,6 Karun K. Singh, 7 and Akira Sawa 8,9,10<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Discovery Neuroscience, Wyeth Research CN 8000,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Princeton, New Jersey 08543,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Medical Genetics Section, University of Edinburgh Centre for Molecular<lb/> Medicine and The Institute of Genetics &amp; Molecular Medicine, University of Edinburgh,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Western General Hospital, Edinburgh EH4 2XU, United Kingdom,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Neuropathology, University of Duesseldorf Medical School,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>40225 Duesseldorf, Germany,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Whitehead Institute for Biomedical Research,<lb/> 5 Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and 6 Stanley Center for Psychiatric Research, Broad Institute,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02142,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>7 Picower Institute<lb/> of Learning and Memory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139,and </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Departments of 8 Psychiatry and Behavioral<lb/> Sciences and 9 Neuroscience and 10 Program in Cellular and Molecular Medicine, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Baltimore, Maryland 21205<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">The biology of schizophrenia is complex with multiple hypotheses (dopamine, glutamate, neurodevelopmental) well supported to underlie the<lb/> disease.Pathwayscenteredontheriskfactor&quot;disruptedinschizophrenia1&quot;(DISC1)maybeabletoexplainandunitethesedisparatehypotheses<lb/> and will be the topic of this mini-symposium preview. Nearly a decade after its original identification at the center of a translocation breakpoint<lb/> in a large Scottish family that was associated with major psychiatric disease, we are starting to obtain credible insights into its function and role<lb/> in disease etiology. This preview will highlight a number of exciting areas of current DISC1 research that are revealing roles for DISC1 during<lb/> normal brain development and also in the disease state. Together these different threads will provide a timely and exciting overview of the DISC1<lb/> field and its potential in furthering our understanding of psychiatric diseases and in developing new therapies.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
