<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55008095"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	
	<note type="other">Audio Engineering Society<lb/> Convention Paper<lb/> Presented at the 116th Convention<lb/> 2004 May 8–11<lb/> Berlin, Germany<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">This convention paper has been reproduced from the author&apos;s advance manuscript, without editing, corrections, or<lb/> consideration by the Review Board. The AES takes no responsibility for the contents. Additional papers may be<lb/> obtained by sending request and remittance to Audio Engineering Society, 60 East 42<lb/>nd Street, New York, New York<lb/> 10165-2520, USA; also see www.aes.org. All rights reserved. Reproduction of this paper, or any portion thereof, is<lb/> not permitted without direct permission from the Journal of the Audio Engineering Society.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Synthetic Ambience in Parametric Stereo Coding<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jonas Engdegård 1 , Heiko Purnhagen 1 , Jonas Rödén 1 , Lars Liljeryd 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Coding Technologies,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Döbelnsgatan 64, 11352 Stockholm, Sweden<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">Correspondence should be addressed to Jonas Engdegård </note>
	
	<email>(je@codingtechnologies.com)<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Parametric stereo coding in combination with an efficient coder for the underlying monaural audio signal results in<lb/> the most efficient coding scheme for stereo signals at very low bit rates available today. While techniques for lateral<lb/> localization have been studied since early intensity stereo coding tools, synthesis of stereophonic ambience was only<lb/> recently applied in parametric stereo coding systems. This paper studies different techniques for synthetic ambience<lb/> generation in the context of parametric stereo coding systems and discusses their mono-compatibility. Implementations<lb/> of these techniques in combination with mp3PRO and aacPlus are presented together with experimental results.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
