<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000013-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<note type="other">0022-3565/03/3042-781–791$7.00<lb/></note>
			<reference>THE JOURNAL OF PHARMACOLOGY AND EXPERIMENTAL THERAPEUTICS</reference>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2003 by The American Society for Pharmacology and
				Experimental Therapeutics<lb/></note>
			<reference>JPET 304:781–791, 2003</reference>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<reference>Vol. 304, No. 2<lb/></reference>
			<note type="other">44313/1038742<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">Printed in U.S.A.</note>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Interactions of the Dipeptide Ester Prodrugs of Acyclovir with<lb/> the
					Intestinal Oligopeptide Transporter: Competitive Inhibition<lb/> of
					Glycylsarcosine Transport in Human Intestinal Cell<lb/>
					Line-Caco-2<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>BANMEET S. ANAND, JIGNESH PATEL, and ASHIM K. MITRA<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Division of Pharmaceutical Sciences, School of Pharmacy, University of
					Missouri-Kansas City,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Kansas City, Missouri<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received September 13, 2002; accepted October 25,
				2002<lb/></note>

			<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT The oligopeptide transporter may be exploited to enhance
				the<lb/> absorption of drugs by synthesizing their dipeptide ester pro-<lb/>drugs,
				which may be recognized as its substrates. Various<lb/> dipeptide esters of
				acyclovir (ACV), an antiviral nucleoside an-<lb/>alog, were synthesized. Enzymatic
				hydrolysis and affinity of the<lb/> prodrugs toward the human intestinal peptide
				transporter<lb/> hPEPT1 were studied using the human intestinal Caco-2 cell<lb/>
				line. Affinity studies were performed by inhibiting the uptake of<lb/> [ 3
				H]glycylsarcosine by the prodrugs. The uptake of glycylsar-<lb/>cosine was found to
				be saturable at higher concentrations and<lb/> was competitively inhibited by the
				prodrugs of ACV. All pro-<lb/>drugs except Tyr-Gly-ACV demonstrated a higher
				affinity (1.41–<lb/> 4.96 mM) toward hPEPT1 than cephalexin (8.19 &#x6ef59; 2.12
				mM),<lb/> which was used as a positive control. Two prodrugs, Gly-Val-<lb/>ACV and
				Val-Val-ACV, showed comparable affinity to Val-ACV,<lb/> an amino acid prodrug of
				ACV recognized by PEPT1/PEPT2.<lb/> The permeability of Gly-Val-ACV (2.99 &#x6ef59;
				0.59 &#x6ef59; 10 &#x6ef59;6 cm/s)<lb/> across Caco-2 was comparable with that of
				Val-ACV (3.01 &#x6ef59;<lb/> 0.21 &#x6ef59; 10 &#x6ef59;6 cm/s) and was
				significantly inhibited (63%) in<lb/> presence of glycylsarcosine. The transport of
				GVACV across<lb/> Caco-2 was saturable at higher concentrations, and the
				param-<lb/>eters were calculated as K m 3.16 &#x6ef59; 0.31 mM and V max 0.014
				&#x6ef59;<lb/> 0.00058 nmol cm &#x6ef59;2 min &#x6ef59;1 . Overall, the results
				suggest that the<lb/> dipeptide prodrugs of ACV have a high affinity toward the<lb/>
				intestinal oligopeptide transporter hPEPT1 and therefore seem<lb/> to be promising
				candidates in the treatment of ocular and oral<lb/> herpesvirus infections, because
				cornea and intestinal epithelia<lb/> seem to express the oligopeptide
				transporters.<lb/></div>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
