<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006259"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Advanced system for calibration and characterization of solar cells<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>F. GRANEK and T. ¯DANOWICZ *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Faculty of Microelectronic Systems and Photonics, SolarLab, Wroc³aw University of Technology<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>11/17 Janiszewskiego Str., 50-372 Wroc³aw, Poland<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">This paper presents high performance setup developed at the SolarLab to measure current-voltage (I–V) curves of solar cells.<lb/> The core of a setup is a steady light solar simulator of class A, according to specifications of IEC 60904-9 and ASTM E927<lb/> standards. Available range of measurements enables us to characterise not only all kinds of silicon wafer-based solar cells<lb/> but also thin film cells and minimodules. A lot of effort has been done to make a setup as a powerful tool for advanced re-<lb/>search work. For that purpose, such options have been implemented as various algorithms for I–V curve translation to exter-<lb/>nal conditions other than those recorded during measurement or several techniques to determine lumped series resistance of<lb/> solar cells (in both cases procedures recommended by IEC 60891 standard have been included). Advanced numerical fitting<lb/> algorithms allow to extract from I–V curves the parameters corresponding to either of three commonly used equivalent diode<lb/> models of a solar cell.<lb/> Using an independent microprocessor unit, the temperature of the measuring table may be controlled in the range 0–60°C<lb/> due to a system of four Peltier cells attached to its rear side. This allows for routine determination of thermal coefficients of<lb/> basic cell parameters.<lb/> The paper discusses also some of elemental random and nonrandom error sources that can be encountered during the<lb/> standard I–V measurements of a solar cell. The test results of repeatability of measurements, problems related to probe con-<lb/>figuration, and heating up of the cells during &quot;light&quot; measurements are presented showing that the developed system can be<lb/> successfully used both for laboratory work and as a tester on a production line. The system meets all requirements of the IEC<lb/> 60904-1, IEC 60904-3, and IEC 60904-9 standards.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: I–V curve, solar cell calibration, solar cell characterisation.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
