<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006922"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>MIPS64™ 5Kc™ Processor Core Datasheet<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<date>November 19, 2001<lb/></date>

	<note type="other">MIPS64™ 5Kc™ Processor Core Datasheet, Revision 02.23<lb/></note>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 1999-2001 MIPS Technologies Inc. All right reserved.<lb/></note>

	<div type="introduction">The MIPS64™ 5Kc™ processor core from MIPS Technologies is a synthesizable, highly-integrated 64-bit MIPS® RISC<lb/> microprocessor core designed for high-performance, low-power, low-cost embedded applications. To semiconductor<lb/> manufacturing companies and system OEMs who are building complex System-On-Chip ASIC devices, the 5Kc core<lb/> offers the long-awaited benefits of an easy-to-integrate, synthesizable core that provides 64-bit address and data paths along<lb/> with the 64-bit computing power of an R5000®-class processor. The 5Kc core is portable across processes, is highly<lb/> configurable, and is easily integrated into standard design flows, thereby reducing time to market and allowing designers<lb/> to focus their attention on end-user products. The 5Kc core is ideally positioned to support new products for emerging<lb/> segments of the digital consumer, network, and office automation markets. The power-management features of the 5Kc core<lb/> make it ideally suited for use in battery-powered applications.<lb/> The 5Kc core implements the MIPS64 Architecture. It contains special multiply-accumulate, conditional move, prefetch,<lb/> wait, leading zero/one detect instructions, and the 64-bit privileged resource architecture. A coprocessor interface is also<lb/> provided, which allows designers a way to easily extend their architectures by addition of custom functionality, such as<lb/> floating-point, network, or graphics coprocessors.<lb/> The memory management unit contains a configurable 16, 32, or 48 dual-entry Joint TLB (JTLB) with variable page sizes,<lb/> a 4-entry Instruction micro TLB (ITLB), and a 4-entry Data micro TLB (DTLB). Using a TLB with the 5Kc core is<lb/> optional. The alternative is to use a far simpler Fixed Mapping Translation (FMT) scheme.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
