<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004191"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The Branched-Chain Amino Acid Transaminase Gene<lb/> Family in Arabidopsis Encodes Plastid and<lb/> Mitochondrial Proteins<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1<lb/> Ruth Diebold<lb/> 2 , Joachim Schuster<lb/> 2 , Klaus Däschner, and Stefan Binder*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Molekulare Botanik, Universität Ulm,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Albert-Einstein-Allee 11, 89069 Ulm, Germany<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Branched-chain amino acid transaminases (BCATs) play a crucial role in the metabolism of leucine, isoleucine, and valine.<lb/> They catalyze the last step of the synthesis and/or the initial step of the degradation of this class of amino acids. In<lb/> Arabidopsis, seven putative BCAT genes are identified by their similarity to their counterparts from other organisms. We<lb/> have now cloned the respective cDNA sequences of six of these genes. The deduced amino acid sequences show between<lb/> 47.5% and 84.1% identity to each other and about 30% to the homologous enzymes from yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae) and<lb/> mammals. In addition, many amino acids in crucial positions as determined by crystallographic analyses of BCATs from<lb/> Escherichia coli and human (Homo sapiens) are conserved in the AtBCATs. Complementation of a yeast ⌬bat1/⌬bat2 double<lb/> knockout strain revealed that five AtBCATs can function as BCATs in vivo. Transient expression of BCAT:green fluorescent<lb/> protein fusion proteins in tobacco (Nicotiana tabacum) protoplasts shows that three isoenzymes are imported into chloroplasts<lb/> (AtBCAT-2, -3, and -5), whereas a single enzyme is directed into mitochondria (AtBCAT-1).<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">In plants, branched-chain amino acids are impor-<lb/>tant compounds in many respects. Besides their func-<lb/>tion as building blocks of proteins, they play a piv-<lb/>otal role in the synthesis of a number of secondary<lb/> products in plants (Lea and Ireland, 1999). In addi-<lb/>tion, the intermediates of branched-chain amino acid<lb/> biosynthesis are also substrates for the synthesis of<lb/> pantothenate and propionyl-CoA (Singh, 1999).<lb/> The pathways of branched-chain amino acid bio-<lb/>synthesis are well investigated in plants because sev-<lb/>eral commercially important herbicides interfere<lb/> with selected enzymes of these cascades (Wittenbach<lb/> and Abell, 1999). In the branched-chain amino acid<lb/> biosynthesis pathways, almost all enzymatic activi-<lb/>ties have been described and many genes and cDNAs<lb/> have been characterized (for review, see Singh, 1999).<lb/> The single exception is the final synthesis step, the<lb/> conversion of respective 2-oxo acids to the branched-<lb/>chain amino acids, which is catalyzed by branched-<lb/>chain amino acid transaminases (BCATs). Very little<lb/> is known about this final step besides a biochemical<lb/> study, in which a respective activity from spinach<lb/> (Spinacia oleracea) chloroplasts was enriched and en-<lb/>zyme activities for the synthesis of Val and for Leu<lb/> and iso-Leu, respectively, could be differentiated<lb/> (Hagelstein et al., 1997).<lb/> However, BCAT activity is not only involved in the<lb/> biosynthesis, but also in the degradation of these<lb/> three amino acids. First indications for the presence<lb/> of branched-chain amino acid degradative pathways<lb/> in plants have been reported in castor bean (Ricinus<lb/> communis), where gluconeogenesis from Leu was re-<lb/>ported (Stewart and Beevers, 1967) and in maize (Zea<lb/> mays), where the respiration of Leu and its conver-<lb/>sion to starch, sugars, or organic acids has been ob-<lb/>served (Sodek and Wilson, 1973). The detection of<lb/> branched-chain 2-oxo acids in peroxisomes of mung<lb/> bean (Vigna radiata) further indicated the presence of<lb/> branched-chain catabolic processes (Gerbling and<lb/> Gerhardt, 1988, 1989).<lb/> The biochemical evidence for the involvement of the<lb/> biotin-containing subunit of the 3-methylcrotonyl-<lb/>CoA carboxylase in Leu degradation and the charac-<lb/>terization of the respective cDNA provided evidence<lb/> for the conversion of at least Leu in several plant<lb/> species (Alban et al., 1993; Song et al., 1994; Wang et<lb/> al., 1994; Weaver et al., 1995; Aubert et al., 1996). This<lb/> enzyme is located in mitochondria, where the oper-<lb/>ation of Leu degradation is further confirmed by the<lb/> detection of several other enzyme activities associ-<lb/>ated with Leu catabolism (Anderson et al., 1998). The<lb/> unambiguous location of the isovaleryl-CoA dehy-<lb/>drogenase in mitochondria of Arabidopsis further<lb/> substantiated the presence of a Leu degradation<lb/> pathway in these organelles. Substrate specificity<lb/> tests of this latter enzyme and the respective enzyme<lb/> activity enriched from potato (Solanum tuberosum) also<lb/> indicated activity in the conversion of isobutyryl-CoA,<lb/> an intermediate of Val degradation in mammalian<lb/> mitochondria (Faivre-Nitschke et al., 2001; Däschner<lb/> et al., 2001). This prompted the speculation of whether</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
