<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004491"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">©2005 Integrated DNA Technologies. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<note type="page">1<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Fluorescence Quenching by Proximal G-bases<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mark A. Behlke<lb/> 1,2 , Lingyan Huang<lb/> 2 , Lisa Bogh<lb/> 3<lb/> , Scott Rose<lb/> 2 , and Eric J. Devor<lb/> 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Molecular Genetics and Bioinformatics<lb/> 2 Molecular Genetics and Biophysics<lb/> 3 Analytical Services<lb/> Integrated DNA Technologies<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Detection of dye-labeled nucleic acids via fluorescence reporting has become a routine<lb/> technique in molecular biology laboratories. Given this, it is important to note that the<lb/> quantum yield of fluorophores attached to nucleic acids is dependent upon a number of<lb/> factors. One of these is the choice of the base that lies adjacent to the fluorescent<lb/> molecule. Fluorescence quenching by an adjacent guanosine nucleotide is an<lb/> under-appreciated phenomenon that can significantly effect quantum yield. Depending<lb/> upon the fluorophore, this effect can be as much as 40%.<lb/> The mechanism of fluorophore quenching has been explained by electron<lb/> sharing/donor properties of the adjacent base (Nazarenko et al., 2002). Quenching of 2-<lb/>aminopurine fluorescence in DNA is dominated by distance-dependent electron transfer<lb/> from 2-aminopurine to guanosine (Kelly and Barton, 1999). Seidel et al. (1996) found<lb/> that photo-induced electron transfer plays an important role in this type of quenching.<lb/> The order of quenching efficiency is G&lt;A&lt;C&lt;T if the nucleobase is reduced but it is the<lb/> reverse, G&gt;A&gt;C&gt;T, if the nucleobase is oxidized (Seidel et al., 1996). Nazarenko et al.<lb/> (2002) also report that quenching by adjacent nucleobases is dependent upon the location<lb/> of the fluorophore within the oligonucleotide.<lb/> We have investigated some of the practical aspects of fluorescence quenching by an<lb/> adjacent guanosine nucleotide. A series of fluorescence-labeled oligonucleotides sharing<lb/> the same core sequence was synthesized such that one of three commonly used<lb/> fluorophores and each of the four possible adjacent nucleotides was present in each<lb/> construct (Table 1).</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
