<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002902"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>CXXXIV. THE CONSTITUENTS OF FABIANA<lb/> IMBRICA TA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>BY GLYN REES EDWARDS AND HAROLD ROGERSON.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>From the Chemical Department, Liverpool University.<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<note type="submission">(Received June 20th, 1927.)<lb/></note>

	<div type="introduction">THE plant Fabiana imbricata (Ruiz and Pavon) or pichi-pichi is a well-known<lb/> shrub growing in South America and belongs to the Solanaceae.<lb/> It has been used medicinally for centuries by the Incas, and about 50 years<lb/> ago attracted some attention in Europe as a specific for urinary and liver<lb/> complaints.<lb/> The first chemical examination appears to have been carried out by<lb/> Niviere and Lotard [1887], who state definitely that the drug is free from<lb/> alkaloid. They ascertained the presence of a fluorescent principle, a yellow<lb/> precipitate with lead acetate analogous to &quot;l&apos;esculo-tannate de plomb,&quot;<lb/> gummy matter, glucose and calcium tartrate.<lb/> A more detailed examination was carried out, however, by Kunz-Krause<lb/> [1899], who found the leaves to contain choline, chrysotropic acid (now known<lb/> as scopoletin) and a substance which he called &quot;fabioglucotannoid&quot; and for<lb/> which he suggested the formula:<lb/> C6H1105. 0. C6H2(OH)(OMe)CH: CH. C02H<lb/> or its internal anhydride. The compound was described as a yellow, very<lb/> hygroscopic substance softening at 800 and beginning to swell up at 1050.<lb/> Kunz-Krause further isolated from the wood a volatile oil which he called<lb/> fabianol (no formula given) together with a non-volatile white crystalline<lb/> solid melting at about 2800 and capable of being sublimed. This was called<lb/> fabianaresen and the formula was C0mH9006 although cryoscopic determinations</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
