<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005008"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>

			<reference>Methods 53 (2011) 347–355<lb/></reference>

			<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">Methods<lb/></note>
			
			<ptr type="web">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/ymeth<lb/></ptr>
			
			<note type="articleType">Review Article<lb/></note>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>High throughput gene trapping and postinsertional modifications of
					gene<lb/> trap alleles<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Frank Schnütgen a , Franziska Ehrmann a , Patricia Ruiz-Noppinger b ,
					Harald von Melchner a,⇑<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>a Department for Molecular Hematology, University of Frankfurt Medical
					School,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Theodor-Stern-Kai 7, Frankfurt am Main, Germany<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>b Center for Cardiovascular Research, Charité, University of Berlin
					Medical School,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Berlin, Germany<lb/></address>

			<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/></note> 
			
			<note type="other">Article history:<lb/> </note> 
			<date>Available online 19 February 2011<lb/></date>
				
			<keywords>Keywords:<lb/> Conditional mutagenesis<lb/>Gene trapping<lb/> Embryonic stem
				cells<lb/> Recombinase-mediated cassette exchange<lb/> (RMCE)<lb/> Proteomics
				Insertional mutagenesis<lb/> Site specific recombination<lb/>
				Retrovirus<lb/></keywords>
				
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			
			<div type="abstract">a b s t r a c t<lb/> Gene trapping is a high-throughput insertional
				mutagenesis approach that has been primarily used in<lb/> mouse embryonic stem cells
				(ESCs). As a high throughput technology, gene trapping helped to generate<lb/> tenth
				of thousands of ESC lines harboring mutations in single genes that can be used for
				making knock-<lb/> out mice. Ongoing international efforts operating under the
				umbrella of the International Knockout<lb/> Mouse Consortium (IKMC;
				www.knockoutmouse.org) aim to generate conditional alleles for every pro-<lb/> tein
				coding gene in the mouse genome by high throughput conditional gene targeting and
				trapping. Here,<lb/> we provide protocols for gene trapping in ESCs that can be
				easily adapted to any other mammalian cell.<lb/> We further provide protocols for
				handling and verifying conditional gene trap alleles in ESC lines<lb/> obtained from
				the IKMC repositories and describe a highly efficient method for the postinsertional
				mod-<lb/> ification of gene trap alleles. More specifically, we describe a protein
				tagging strategy based on recombi-<lb/> nase mediated cassette exchange (RMCE) that
				enables protein localization and protein–protein<lb/> interaction studies under
				physiological conditions.<lb/></div>
				
			<note type="copyright">&#169; 2011 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
