<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001463"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>How Light Emitting Plasma™ Works<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">Introduction<lb/> LUXIM&apos;s LiFi ® brand of Light Emitting Plasma™ is a new class of solid state high inten-<lb/>sity light sources bringing clean lighting solutions to general and specialty lighting.<lb/> With energy efficiency, long useful lifetime, full spectrum color, and dimming, LiFi<lb/> lighting applications work better compared to conventional approaches such as HID<lb/> or even newer sources such as LED in many applications. This technology brief de-<lb/>scribes the general construction of LiFi lighting systems and the basic technology<lb/> building blocks behind their function.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">LiFi construction<lb/> The LiFi product consists of three primary sub-assemblies:<lb/> @BULLET Emitter (including bulb)<lb/> @BULLET RF Driver<lb/> @BULLET Power supply<lb/> An RF (radio-frequency) signal is generated by the solid-state RF<lb/> Driver and is guided into an electric field about the bulb. The<lb/> high concentration of energy in the electric field vaporizes the<lb/> contents of the bulb to a plasma state at the bulb&apos;s center; this<lb/> controlled plasma generates an intense source of light.<lb/> Function of the Bulb Assembly<lb/> At the heart of LIFI™ is the bulb sub-assembly where a sealed bulb is embedded in a<lb/> dielectric material. This design is more reliable than conventional light sources that<lb/> insert degradable electrodes into the bulb. The dielectric material serves two pur-<lb/>poses; first as a waveguide for the RF energy transmit-<lb/>ted by the PA and second as an electric field con-<lb/>centrator that focuses energy in the bulb. The energy<lb/> from the electric field rapidly heats the material in the<lb/> bulb to a plasma state that emits light of high intensity<lb/> and full spectrum.<lb/> Summary<lb/> The design and construction of the LIFI™ light source enable efficiency, long stable<lb/> life, full spectrum intensity that is digitally controlled and easy to use.<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">Technology Brief</note>
	
	<div type="introduction"><lb/> Bulb<lb/> RF Driver<lb/> Power Supply<lb/> Puck<lb/> Emitter<lb/> Bulb<lb/> Dialectric Material<lb/></div>
	
	<note type="page">1/10<lb/></note>

	<div type="introduction">How Light Emitting Plasma™ Works<lb/> Introduction</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
