<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001029"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<idno>ID<lb/> AWH69796 standard; RNA; 22 BP.<lb/> XX AC<lb/> AWH69796;<lb/>XX DT<lb/> </idno>
	
	<date> 09-JUL-2009 (first entry)<lb/> </date>
	
	<note type="other">XX DE<lb/> </note>
	
	<docTitle>
		<titlePart>Human herpesvirus 1 miRNA oligo, SEQ ID 8800.<lb/> XX KW<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<keyword>Virucide; Respiratory-Gen.; Anti-HIV; Antiinflammatory; Hepatotropic;<lb/> KW Cytostatic; Immunosuppressive; Neuroprotective; Vaccine; viral infection;<lb/> KW cancer; hepatitis; mononucleosis; bronchiolitis; ss; miRNA; microRNA.<lb/> XX OS<lb/> Human herpesvirus 1.<lb/> XX PN<lb/></keyword>

	<idno type="patent">WO2009024834-A2.<lb/> XX PD<lb/> 26-FEB-2009.<lb/> XX PF<lb/> 05-DEC-2007; 2007WO-IB004718.<lb/> XX PR<lb/> 05-DEC-2006; 2006US-0868666P.<lb/> PR 11-SEP-2007; 2007US-0971265P</idno>

	<div type="introduction">.<lb/> XX PA<lb/> (ROSE-) ROSETTA GENOMICS LTD.<lb/> XX DR<lb/> WPI; 2009-F32128/17.<lb/> XX PT<lb/> New isolated nucleic acid that is involved in viral infection, useful for<lb/> PT manufacturing medicament for treating or preventing viral infection or<lb/> PT viral mediated disease condition, e.g. cervical cancer, hepatitis, and<lb/> PT influenza, in a subject.<lb/> XX PS<lb/> Claim 1; SEQ ID NO 8800; 0pp; English.<lb/> XX CC<lb/> The present invention relates to novel nucleic acid sequences which are<lb/> CC involved in viral infection. Also claimed are: a method of preventing or<lb/> CC treating viral infection or a condition associated with a viral infection<lb/> CC in a subject comprising administering to the subject a composition<lb/> CC comprising a nucleic acid sequence selected from AWH60997 -AWH70217,<lb/> CC AWH76362 -AWH76388 or AWH76512 -AWH76523; a method of inhibiting<lb/> CC expression of a target gene in a cell comprising introducing a nucleic<lb/> CC acid into a cell to inhibit expression of the target gene, where the<lb/> CC target gene comprises a binding site comprising a sequence selected from<lb/> CC AWH70218 -AWH76361 or AWH76389 -AWH76512 and where the nucleic acid is<lb/> CC a nucleic acid selected from AWH60997 -AWH70217, AWH76362 -AWH76388 or<lb/> CC AWH76512 -AWH76523; a method of detecting viral infection of a cell<lb/> CC comprising determining the expression level of at least one nucleic acid<lb/> CC sequence selected from AWH60997 -AWH70217, AWH76362 -AWH76388 or<lb/> CC AWH76512 -AWH76523; and a method of reducing the amount of virus<lb/> CC replication in a target cell, comprising introducing into a target cell<lb/> CC infected with the virus an amount of a composition comprising the nucleic<lb/> CC acid sequence selected from AWH60997 -AWH70217, AWH76362 -AWH76388 or<lb/> CC AWH76512 -AWH76523. The nucleic acid sequences are useful for treating<lb/> CC or preventing a viral infection or viral mediated disease condition,<lb/> CC where the viral infection is caused by a virus selected from herpes<lb/> CC simplex virus (HSV)-1, HSV2, human respiratory syncytial virus (RSV),<lb/> CC Epstein Barr-Virus (EBV), Influenza A, hog cholera virus (HCV), human<lb/> CC papillomavirus (HPV), HIV, hepatitis B virus (HBV) and Vaccinia virus;<lb/> CC inhibiting expression of a target gene in a cell; detecting viral<lb/> CC infection of a cell; reducing the amount of virus replication in a target<lb/> CC cell; and for treating a viral mediated disease condition in a subject,<lb/> CC where the disease condition is selected from Burkitt&apos;s lymphoma,<lb/> CC nasopharyngeal carcinoma, ovarian carcinoma, cervical cancer, hepatitis,<lb/> CC mononucleosis, influenza, genital herpes, encephalitis, and<lb/> CC bronchiolitis. Additionally, the nucleic acid is useful for manufacturing<lb/> CC a medicament for treating or preventing viral infection.<lb/> XX SQ<lb/> Sequence 22 BP; 5 A; 4 C; 11 G; 0 T; 2 U; 0 Other;<lb/> ggacgaatcg gaggcctggg ag<lb/> 22 //<lb/> GENESEQN:AWH69796<lb/>

	http://ibis.internal.epo.org/IBIS/exam/dbfetch.

	jsp?id=GENESEQN:A

	...<lb/></div>

	<note type="page">1 of 1<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="other">21-06-2011 09:08</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
