<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005054"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>

			<reference>Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews 14 (2010) 1722–1743<lb/></reference>
			
			<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews<lb/></note>
			<ptr type="web">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/rser<lb/></ptr>
			

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Feasibility study of offshore wind turbine installation in Iran
					compared<lb/> with the world<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Ali Mostafaeipour *<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Industrial Engineering Department, Yazd University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Yazd, Iran<lb/></address>

			<note type="other">A R T I C L E I N F O<lb/></note>

			<note type="submission"> Article history:<lb/>Received 30 November 2009<lb/>Accepted 18
				March 2010<lb/></note>

			<keywords>Keywords:<lb/>Offshore wind<lb/>Turbine<lb/>Iran<lb/>Persian Gulf<lb/>Caspian
				Sea<lb/>Urmia Lake<lb/>Feasibility study<lb/></keywords>
			
			<space dim="horizontal"/>

			<div type="abstract"> A B S T R A C T<lb/> Renewable energies have potential for
				supplying of relatively clean and mostly local energy. Wind<lb/> energy generation
				is expected to increase in the near future and has experienced dramatic growth
				over<lb/> the past decade in many countries. Offshore winds are generally stronger
				and more constant than<lb/> onshore winds in many areas. The economic feasibility
				for utilization of offshore wind energy depends<lb/> on the favorable wind
				conditions in the area. The present paper analyses offshore wind speed in
				global<lb/> scale and also studies feasibility of introducing this technology for
				harnessing wind in Persian Gulf,<lb/> Caspian Sea, Urmia Lake and Gulf of Oman. Wind
				speed data were collected from different sources. The<lb/> ocean surface winds at a
				10 m height from satellite passes as processed by NOAA/NESDIS, from near real-<lb/>
				time data collected by NASA/JPL’s Sea Winds Scatterometer aboard the QuikSCAT.
				Development of<lb/> renewable energy is one of priority research goals in Iran.
				There are many installed wind turbines in<lb/> suitable regions like Manjil and
				Binalood, but there has not been any offshore wind installation yet in<lb/> Iran. It
				is suggested that policy makers to invest and pay more attentions toward harnessing
				renewable<lb/> energy sources like offshore wind in Persian Gulf and Gulf of Oman in
				southern parts of Iran.<lb/>
			</div>
			<note type="copyright">&#169; 2010 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</note>


		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
