<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002938"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Kidney International, Vol. 49 (1996), pp. 1642—1648<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>cAMP-regulated trafficking of epitope-tagged CFTR<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>MARYBETH HOWARD, TAMAS JILLING, MIcI-iL DUVALL, and RAYMOND A. FRIZZELL<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Physiology and Biophysics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, and Department of Cell Biology and<lb/> Physiology, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA<lb/></address>

	<div type="introduction">cAMP-regulated trafficking of epitope-tagged CFFR. The cystic fibrosis<lb/> transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) is a phosphorylation-<lb/>activated chloride channel responsible for cAMP-induced Cl secretion<lb/> across the apical membranes of epithelial cells. To optimize its detection<lb/> in membrane localization studies, we tagged CFTR with epitope se-<lb/>quences at the carboxy terminus or in the fourth external loop. The<lb/> function of six different tagged-CFTRs was tested in two different<lb/> physiological assays. CFTRs containing the M2 epitope responded to<lb/> cAMP, whereas cells expressing CFTR with the hemagglutinin I-LA tag<lb/> showed little or no cAMP response. Using CFTR tagged in the fourth<lb/> external ioop, we demonstrate that cAMP activation using forskolin<lb/> results in an increase in CFTR in the plasma membrane of HeLa cells.<lb/> Forskolin inhibited CFTR endocytosis, and this contributes to the increase<lb/> in cell surface CFTR expression. Our results indicate that regulation of<lb/> cell surface CVFR contributes to the increase in plasma membrane Cl<lb/> conductance evoked by cAMP stimulation.<lb/> Cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR)<lb/> is involved in the cAMP-dependent regulation of membrane<lb/> trafficking. Epithelia that express wild-type (wt) CFI&apos;R show<lb/> cAMP-induced activation of exocytosis and inhibition of endocy-<lb/>tosis [1]. These cAMP-induced changes in membrane recycling<lb/> cause a proliferation of membrane surface area detected as an<lb/> increase in membrane capacitance measurements [2]. Cystic<lb/> fibrosis (CF) cells lack the cAMP-dependent regulation of these<lb/> membrane trafficking events, which can be restored by expression<lb/> of wt CFTR in CF cells [1]. Prince and Marchase [3] used a<lb/> surface labeling strategy to measure directly the effect of cAMP-<lb/>activation on CFTR endocytosis. Forskolin inhibited endocytosis<lb/> of 50% of plasma membrane CFTR in T84 cells, detected from<lb/> immunoprecipitation of the surface-labeled protein.<lb/> cAMP-regulation of membrane trafficking events could contrib-<lb/>ute to the expression of active CFTR Cl channels in the apical<lb/> membranes of secretory epithelial cells, providing an ancillary<lb/> means of increasing apical Cl conductance, in addition to the<lb/> direct activation of membrane-resident CFTR. Of critical impor-<lb/>tance is the question of whether CFTR itself is a passenger in this<lb/> cAMP-regulated apical membrane traffic or whether it regulates<lb/> these events from another location. If it is the former, then it<lb/> becomes important to define the membrane turnover properties<lb/> of various CFTR mutants. Their residency in the plasma mem-<lb/>brane may correlate with impairments described for regulation of<lb/> their Cl conductance, and this would support the idea that<lb/> conduction and trafficking are causally related. Moreover, en-<lb/>© 1996 by the International Society of Nephrology<lb/> hancing the plasma membrane residence time of mutant CFTRs<lb/> may provide a means of enhancing apical Cl conductance.<lb/> Our understanding of wild-type (wt) and mutant CFTR local-<lb/>ization, trafficking and membrane insertion is incomplete. These<lb/> issues could be addressed at greater resolution with more sensitive<lb/> CFTR detection assays. We chose to epitope-tag the CFTR<lb/> protein on one of the external loops and at the C-terminus as a<lb/> means to detect the protein when it is expressed in various cell<lb/> lines and tissues. The advantage of this approach is the use of a<lb/> small highly hydrophillic epitope, engineered into the protein at a<lb/> specific site, and the availability of a specific monoclonal antibody<lb/> that can be used to detect the epitope. This results in increased<lb/> sensitivity and specificity of protein detection. Epitope-tagging has<lb/> been used successfully with a variety of proteins to determine their<lb/> cellular locations [4], subcellular targeting [5] and protein-protein<lb/> interactions [6].<lb/> In this paper, we briefly review the procedures used for tagging<lb/> and functional analysis of six CFTR constructs, tagged with two<lb/> different epitopes [7]. Using one of these constructs, we demon-<lb/>strate that cAMP-activation results in (1) an increase in the<lb/> number of CFTR molecules in the plasma membrane under</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
