<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000010-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Relation of Tumor Size, Lymph Node Status, and Survival in<lb/> 24,740
					Breast Cancer Cases<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>CHRISTINE L. CARTER, PHD, MPH,* CAROL ALLEN, PHD,t AND DONALD E. HENSON,
					MD*<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<div type="abstract">Two of the most important prognostic indicators for breast cancer
				are tumor size and extent of axillary<lb/> lymph node involvement. Data on 24,740
				cases recorded in the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End<lb/> Results (SEER)
				Program of the National Cancer Institute were used to evaluate the breast cancer
				survival<lb/> experience in a representative sample of women from the United States.
				Actuarial (life table) methods<lb/> were used to investigate the 5-year relative
				survival rates in cases with known operative/pathologic axillary<lb/> lymph node
				status and primary tumor diameter. Survival rates varied from 45.5% for tumor
				diameters<lb/> equal to or greater than 5 cm with positive axillary nodes to 96.3%
				for tumors less than 2 cm and with<lb/> no involved nodes. The relation between
				tumor size and lymph node status was investigated in detail.<lb/> Tumor diameter and
				lymph node status were found to act as independent but additive prognostic
				indicators.<lb/> As tumor size increased, survival decreased regardless of lymph
				node status; and as lymph node involvement<lb/> increased, survival status also
				decreased regardless of tumor size. A linear relation was found between<lb/> tumor
				diameter and the percent of cases with positive lymph node involvement. The results
				of our analyses<lb/> suggest that disease progression to distant sites does not
				occur exclusively via the axillary lymph nodes,<lb/> but rather that lymph node
				status serves as an indicator of the tumor's ability to spread.<lb/></div> 
				<reference>Cancer 63:181-187, 1989.<lb/></reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
