<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007716"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>CMLS, Cell. Mol. Life Sci. 57 (2000) 311–322<lb/></reference>

	<idno>1420-682X/00/020311-12 $ 1.50 +0.20/0<lb/></idno>

	<note type="copyright">© Birkhäuser Verlag, Basel, 2000<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Review<lb/> P58<lb/> IPK<lb/> , a novel cochaperone containing tetratricopeptide<lb/> repeats and a J-domain with oncogenic potential<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>M. W. Melville<lb/> a, , M. G. Katze<lb/> b,<lb/> * and S.-L. Tan<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Department of Microbiology, School of Medicine, University of Washington,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seattle (Washington 98195,<lb/> USA)<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Department of Microbiology, School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Box 357242,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Washington,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1705 Pacific St. NE,<lb/> Seattle (Washington 98195, USA),</address>

	<phone>Fax + 1 206 685 0305; </phone>

	<email>e-mail: honey@u.washington.edu<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received 5 July 1999; received after revision 18 October 1999; accepted 26 October 1999<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">vated cellular inhibitor of the PKR protein kinase,<lb/> Abstract. Tetratricopeptide repeats (TPRs) are loosely<lb/> conserved 34-amino acid sequence motifs that have whose different TPR motifs mediate interactions with<lb/> distinct proteins. P58<lb/> IPK , which possesses cochaperone<lb/> been shown to function as scaffolding structures to<lb/> mediate protein-protein interactions. TPRs have been and oncogenic properties, represents a unique class of<lb/> identified in a number of proteins with diverse functions TPR proteins containing a J-domain. Here we review<lb/> recent progress on the structural and functional charac-<lb/>and cellular locations. Recent studies suggest that indi-<lb/>vidual TPR motifs can confer specificity in promoting terization of P58<lb/> IPK , and discuss the possible mecha-<lb/>nisms by which P58<lb/> IPK modulates PKR and induces<lb/> homotypic and/or heterotypic interactions, often in a<lb/> tumorigenesis in view of present knowledge of TPR<lb/> mutually exclusive manner. These features are best ex-<lb/>emplified by the P58<lb/> IPK protein, an influenza virus-acti-proteins and molecular chaperones.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key words. Tetratricopeptide repeat; J-domain; P58<lb/> IPK ; PKR; protein-protein interactions; cochaperone; protein<lb/> folding; tumorigenesis.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
