<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003729"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Lasers in Surgery and Medicine 40:371–378 (2008)<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Irradiation With 780 nm Diode Laser Attenuates<lb/> Inflammatory Cytokines but Upregulates Nitric Oxide in<lb/> Lipopolysaccharide-Stimulated Macrophages: Implications<lb/> for the Prevention of Aneurysm Progression<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Lilach Gavish, MSc,* Louise S. Perez, BSc, Petachia Reissman, MD, and S. David Gertz, MD, PhD<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology, The Hebrew University, Hadassah Medical School,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Jerusalem 91120, Israel<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Background and Objectives: Low level laser irradiation<lb/> (LLLI) has been shown to reduce inflammation in a variety<lb/> of clinical situations. We have shown that LLLI (780 nm)<lb/> increases aortic smooth muscle cell proliferation and<lb/> matrix protein secretion and modulates activity and<lb/> expression of matrix metalloproteinases. Inflammation is<lb/> a major component of arteriosclerotic diseases including<lb/> aneurysm. Macrophage recruitment and secretion of pro-<lb/>inflammatory cytokines and the vasodilator, nitric oxide<lb/> (NO), are central to most immune responses in the arterial<lb/> wall. The present study was designed to determine the<lb/> effect of LLLI on cytokine gene expression and secretion as<lb/> well as gene expression of inducible nitric oxide synthase<lb/> (iNOS) and NO production in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-<lb/>stimulated macrophages.<lb/> Study Design/Materials and Methods: Murine mono-<lb/>cyte/macrophages (RAW 264.7) were irradiated with a<lb/> 780 nm diode laser (2 mW/cm<lb/> 2<lb/> , 2.2 J/cm<lb/> 2 ) during stim-<lb/>ulation with LPS (0, 0.1, and 1 mg/ml). Gene expression of<lb/> chemokines, cytokines, and iNOS were assessed by RT-<lb/>PCR. Secretion of interleukin (IL)-1b and monocyte chemo-<lb/>tactic protein (MCP)-1 and NO were assessed by ELISA and<lb/> the Griess reaction, respectively.<lb/> Results: LLLI reduced gene expression of MCP-1, IL-1a,<lb/> IL-10 (P&lt;0.01), IL-1b, and IL-6 (P&lt;0.05) when cells were<lb/> stimulated by 1 mg/ml LPS. LLLI reduced LPS-induced<lb/> secretion of MCP-1 over non-irradiated cells by 17 AE 5%<lb/> and 13 AE 5% at 12 hours (0.1 and 1 mg/ml LPS; P&lt;0.01 and<lb/> P ¼ 0.05, respectively), and reduced IL-1b by 22 AE 5%<lb/> and 25 AE 9% at 24 hours (0.1 and 1 mg/ml LPS, P ¼ 0.01<lb/> and P ¼ 0.06, respectively). However, LLLI increased<lb/> NO secretion after 12 hours (LLLI vs. Control: without<lb/> LPS, 1.72 AE 0.37 vs. 0.95 AE 0.4 mM, P&lt;0.05; 0.1 mg/ml LPS,<lb/> 7.46 AE 1.62 vs. 4.44 AE 1.73 mM, P ¼ 0.06; 1 mg/ml LPS,<lb/> 10.91 AE 3.53 vs. 6.88 AE 1.52 mM, P&lt;0.05).<lb/> Conclusions: These properties of LLLI, with its effects<lb/> on smooth muscle cells reported previously, may be of<lb/> profound therapeutic relevance for arterial diseases such<lb/> as aneurysm where inflammatory processes and weaken-<lb/>ing of the matrix structure of the arterial wall are<lb/> major pathologic components. </div>
	
	<reference>Lasers Surg. Med. 40:371–<lb/> 378, 2008. </reference>
	
	<note type="copyright">&#169;ß 2008 Wiley-Liss, Inc.<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Key words: photobiostimulation; chemokines; inflamma-<lb/>tion; low level laser irradiation; macrophage; phototherapy<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
