<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007621"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The Use of Amnion-Derived Cellular Cytokine<lb/> Solution to Improve Healing in Acute<lb/> and Chronic Wound Models<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Michael G. Franz, MD,<lb/> a Wyatt G. Payne, MD,<lb/> b Liyu Xing, PhD,<lb/> a D. K. Naidu, MD,<lb/> b<lb/> R. E. Salas, MD,<lb/> b Vivienne S. Marshall, PhD,<lb/> c C. J. Trumpower, BS,<lb/> c<lb/> Charlotte A. Smith, MS,<lb/> c David L. Steed, MD,<lb/> d and M. C. Robson, MD<lb/> b<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a University of Michigan,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Ann Arbor, MI;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Institute for Tissue Regeneration, Repair, Rehabilitation,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Veterans Affairs Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bay Pines, FL;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c Stemnion, Inc. and<lb/> d University of<lb/> Pittsburgh,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pittsburgh, PA<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">Correspondence: </note>
	
	<email>mfranz@med.umich.edu<lb/> </email>
	
	<note type="other">Presented in part at the Wound Healing Society meeting, San Diego,Calif.  on April 27, 2008.<lb/></note>

	<date>Published April 11, 2008<lb/></date>

	<div type="abstract">Objective: Growth factors demonstrate mixed results improving wound healing.<lb/> Amnion-derived multipotent cells release physiologic levels of growth factors and tis-<lb/>sue inhibitors of metalloproteinases. This solution was tested in models of acute and<lb/> chronic wound healing. Methods: Acute model: Sprague-Dawley rats underwent la-<lb/>parotomy incisions. The midline fascia was primed with phosphate-buffered saline,<lb/> unconditioned media, or amnion-derived cellular cytokine suspension prior to incision.<lb/> Breaking strength of laparotomy wounds was tested with an Instron tensiometer. Inci-<lb/>sional hernia formation was measured after 28 days. Chronic model: Chronic, infected<lb/> granulating wounds were produced in rats by excising full thickness burn eschars inoc-<lb/>ulated with Escherica coli. Granulating wounds were treated with unconditioned media<lb/> or amnion-derived cellular cytokine suspension. Treatments were applied either on day 0<lb/> and day 7 or day 0 and then every other day. Wounds were traced every 72 hours and biop-<lb/>sied for quantitative bacteriology. Results: Acute model: Priming with amnion-derived<lb/> cellular cytokine suspension increased the breaking strength of laparotomy incisions in<lb/> comparison with phosphate-buffered saline or unconditioned media (P &lt; .05). Acute<lb/> wound failure and incisional hernia formation was 100% in the phosphate-buffered<lb/> saline and unconditioned media groups and 18% in the amnion-derived cellular cy-<lb/>tokine suspension–treated group (P &lt; .05). Chronic model: The rate of wound closure<lb/> was accelerated in amnion-derived cellular cytokine suspension–treated chronic wounds<lb/> (P &lt; .05). Multidosing improved the effect. Conclusions: A physiologic solution of cy-<lb/>tokines and tissue inhibitors of metalloproteinases improves healing in models of acute<lb/> and chronic wounds. Such a cocktail can be produced from amnion-derived multipotent<lb/> progenitor cells.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
