<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004121"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>2009 AACR Annual Meeting<lb/> April 18-22, 2009<lb/> Denver, CO<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">Print this Page for Your Records Close Window<lb/> Abstract Number:<lb/> 724<lb/> Session Title:<lb/> Cancer Vaccines: Human Studies<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Presentation Title:<lb/> A phase 1 clinical trial of immune response and safety of an active immunotherapy regimen co-targeting PRAME and PSMA antigens in<lb/> subjects with advanced solid malignancies<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="other">Presentation Start/End Time:<lb/> Sunday, Apr 19, 2009, 8:00 AM -12:00 PM<lb/> Location:<lb/> Hall B-F, Poster Section 31<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="other">Poster Section:<lb/> 31, 31<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="other">Poster Board<lb/> Number:<lb/> 13<lb/> Author Block:<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mihail Obrocea, Nicholas Vogelzang, Lee Cranmer, Marc S. Ernstoff, Jeffrey Weber, John Marshall, Zhiong Qiu, Darlene Rosario, Adrian Bot.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>MannKind Corp, Inc.,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Valencia, CA, </address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Nevada Cancer Institute, </affiliation>
	</byline>
		
	<address>Las Vegas, NV, </address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Arizona Cancer Center, </affiliation>
	</byline>
		
	<address>Tucson, AZ, </address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical<lb/> Center, </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>Lebanon, NH, </address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Moffitt Cancer Center, </affiliation>
	</byline>
		
	<address>Tampa, FL,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Georgetown, DC<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Background: This clinical trial is testing an investigational immunotherapeutic 3-component regimen encompassing a recombinant plasmid (pPRA-PSM) dose followed by 2<lb/> peptide (E-PSM and E-PRA) doses (low and high) delivered by intra lymph node injection in a prime-boost sequence aimed to elicit an immune response against PRAME and<lb/> PSMA antigens. Methods: The trial design used a prime-boost strategy with all patients receiving a fixed priming dose (2,400 µg/dose) of the plasmid-antigen vector via<lb/> ultrasound guided intranodal injection into inguinal or axillary lymph nodes on days 1, 4, 15 and 18 of each treatment cycle followed by peptide administrations on days 29 and<lb/> 32. The peptide doses used are as follows: low dose cohort: E-PSM: 30 mg/dose, E-PRA: 22.5mg/dose; high dose cohort: E-PSM: 300mg/dose, E-PRA: 150mg/dose. All<lb/> patients enrolled have advanced and/or refractory carcinomas, are HLA*0201+ and tumor samples obtained from prior biopsies show presence of both PRAME and PSMA</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
