<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006852"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>ORGANIC CHEMISTRY<lb/> STUDY OF THE REACTIVITY OF AMMONIUM CARBOXYLATES IN THE SYNTHESIS<lb/> OF AMIDES UNDER HIGH-PRESSURE DEFORMATION CONDITIONS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>N. P. Chistotina and A. A. Zharov<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<idno>UDC 541.12.034.2:539.37:547.29-38<lb/></idno>

	<div type="abstract">On deformation under pressures up to I0 GPa the ammonium salts of aliphatic and aro-<lb/>matic acids~ as well as mixtures of a free carboxylic acid with the ~mmonium salts of<lb/> strong mineral acids, are converted into the corresponding amides.<lb/> The amide yields<lb/> increase with pressure, the magnitude of shearing deformation, and temperature.<lb/> The temperature and pressure coefficients for amide formation are low and have values of<lb/> 2.5-4 kJ/mole and --i to --2 cm3/mole, respectively.<lb/> The reactivity of ammonium salts<lb/> in the synthesis of amides alternates in the homologous series of aliphatic acids in<lb/> a similar way to the shear stress of these salts. The reactivity of the ammonium salts<lb/> of aliphatic acids increases when the reaction is conducted in a matrix of an ammonium<lb/> salt which possesses plasticity and a high shear stress.<lb/> At present it has been established that under shearing deformation conditions under high<lb/> pressure (DC + HP) chemical reactions take place in solid substances at great velocities, the<lb/> degree of conversion of the substances being a function of the shearing deformation [i]. There<lb/> are numerous demonstrations that the physical properties of the substances, such as plastic-<lb/>ity and shear stress, have an effect on a chemical process under DC + HP [2].<lb/> With the purpose of studying therelationships in the chemical reactions of organic com-<lb/>pounds under DS + HP we have undertaken an investigation into the formation of amides from am-<lb/>monium carboxylates.<lb/> A high temperature is usually required for the conversion of ammonium<lb/> salts into acid amides but under DS + HP conditions amides may be formed at room temperature</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
