<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004006"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Human trophoblast noncoding RNA suppresses CIITA promoter<lb/> III activity in murine B-lymphocytes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>q<lb/> Arnar Geirsson,<lb/> a Raymond J. Lynch,<lb/> a Indu Paliwal,<lb/> a Alfred L.M. Bothwell,<lb/> b<lb/> and Graeme L. Hammond<lb/> a, *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Department of Surgery, Yale University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>333 Cedar Street, FMB 121, New Haven, CT 06510, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Section of Immunobiology, Yale University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New Haven, CT 06510, USA<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 8 January 2003<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Trophoblasts lack expression of all classical MHC antigens. Determination of the mechanism involved could provide insight into<lb/> selective gene suppression and allograft tolerance. Suppression of class II expression in trophoblasts is secondary to dominant<lb/> negative trans-acting factors that suppress class II transactivator (CIITA) transcription. We recently described a trophoblast-derived<lb/> noncoding RNA (TncRNA) that suppresses class II expression. Murine B-cells CH27 were stably transfected with TncRNA and<lb/> analyzed for MHC class II and CIITA expression by FACS and Northern blots. Functional assessment of CIITA promoter III<lb/> (pIII) was performed by transient transfection of promoter–reporter constructs. Methylation of pIII was assessed by Southern blots<lb/> and FACS. TncRNA suppressed constitutive I-Ak and CIITA expression in murine B-cells CH27. The mechanism involves inhi-<lb/>bition of CIITA pIII activity. The mechanism does not involve methylation of the promoter.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">&#169; 2003 Elsevier Science (USA). All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Keywords: MHC class II; CIITA; Gene regulation; Xenograft; Noncoding RNA; Repressor</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
