<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000018-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			
			<lb/>
			<reference>Cytokine and Growth Factor Reviews 12 (2001) 361– 373<lb/></reference>
			<ptr type="web">www.elsevier.com/locate/cytogfr<lb/></ptr>
			
			<note type="articleType">Survey<lb/></note>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>The GDNF/RET signaling pathway and human diseases<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Masahide Takahashi *<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Department of Pathology, Nagoya Uni6ersity Graduate School of
					Medicine,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>65 Tsurumai-cho, Showa-ku, Nagoya 466-8550, Japan<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor (GDNF)
				and related molecules, neurturin, artemin and persephin, signal through a<lb/>
				unique multicomponent receptor system consisting of RET tyrosine kinase and
				glycosyl-phosphatidylinositol-anchored coreceptor<lb/> (GFRa1–4). These neurotrophic
				factors promote the survival of various neurons including peripheral autonomic and
				sensory<lb/> neurons as well as central motor and dopamine neurons, and have been
				expected as therapeutic agents for neurodegenerative<lb/> diseases. In addition, it
				turned out that the GDNF/RET signaling plays a crucial role in renal development and
				regulation of<lb/> spermatogonia differentiation. RET mutations cause several human
				diseases such as papillary thyroid carcinoma, multiple<lb/> endocrine neoplasia
				types 2A and 2B, and Hirschsprung's disease. The mutations resulted in RET
				activation or inactivation by<lb/> various mechanisms and the biological properties
				of mutant proteins appeared to be correlated with disease phenotypes. The<lb/>
				signaling pathways activated by GDNF or mutant RET are being extensively
				investigated to understand the molecular<lb/> mechanisms of disease development and
				the physiological roles of the GDNF family ligands.</div>

			<note type="copyright">© 2001 Elsevier Science Ltd. All<lb/> rights reserved.<lb/></note>

			<keywords>Keywords: RET proto-oncogene; Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor;
				Papillary thyroid carcinoma; Multiple endocrine neoplasia 2;<lb/> Hirschsprung's
				disease<lb/></keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
