<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002209"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Numerical study of single mode Er-doped<lb/> microstructured fibers: influence of geometrical<lb/> parameters on amplifier performances<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Stéphane Hilaire, Dominique Pagnoux, Philippe Roy, and Sébastien Février<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<affiliation>Xlim -</affiliation>
	<address>123 avenue Albert Thomas, 87060 Limoges, France<lb/></address>

	<email>stephane.hilaire@xlim.fr<lb/></email>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.xlim.fr<lb/></ptr>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract: A theoretical study of optimized single mode Er-doped MOFs<lb/> designed for high efficiency amplification at 1550nm is carried out,<lb/> deriving benefit from the demonstrated very low decrease of the overlap<lb/> factor versus wavelength. In spite of this potential advantage, classical<lb/> single mode MOFs are first shown to be less efficient than usual Er-doped<lb/> step index fibers (SIF). However, novel single mode large core MOFs<lb/> (LCMOFs) are designed, providing overlap factors higher than 0.9 at both<lb/> the pump and the signal wavelengths. To obtain the same gain, the<lb/> necessary length of LCMOF is reduced by up to 40% compared to that of<lb/> Er-doped SIF. Such a highly efficient amplifying fiber is attractive for short<lb/> pulse and soliton amplification.<lb/> </div>
	
	<note type="copyright">©2006 Optical Society of America<lb/> </note>

	<keyword>OCIS codes: (060.2320) Fiber optics amplifiers and oscillators; (060.2410) Fibers, erbium;<lb/> (060.2430) Fibers, single-mode; (230.3990) Microstructure devices.<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="other">References and Links<lb/> 1.<lb/> E. Desurvire, Erbium-Doped Fibre Amplifiers-Principles and Applications (Wiley-Interscience, New<lb/> York, 1994).<lb/> 2.<lb/> G. P. Agrawal, Nonlinear Fibre Optics 3<lb/> rd edition (Academic Press, San Diego, 2003) 3.<lb/> G. Kulcsar, Y. Jaouen, G. Canat, E. Olmedo, and G. Debarge</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
