<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000016-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>International Journal of Cosmetic Science, 2011, 33, 210–221</reference>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<idno>doi: 10.1111/j.1468-2494.2010.00616.x</idno>
			
			<note type="articleType">Review Article<lb/></note>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>The melanogenesis and mechanisms of skin-lightening<lb/> agents –
					existing and new approaches<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>J. M. Gillbro and M. J. Olsson<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Oriflame Cosmetics Skin Research Institute,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>SE-101 39 Stockholm, Sweden<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received 7 May 2010, Accepted 10 July 2010<lb/></note>

			<keywords>Keywords: adrenergic, melanogenesis, skin lightening, tyrosinase,
				vitiligo<lb/></keywords>

			<div type="abstract">Synopsis<lb/> Skin-lightening products are commercially available
				for cosmetic<lb/> purposes to obtain lighter skin complexion. Clinically, they are
				also<lb/> used for treatment of hyperpigmentary disorders such as melasma,<lb/> cafe
				áu lait spot and solar lentigo. All of these target naturally mel-<lb/>anin
				production, and many of the commonly used agents are<lb/> known as competitive
				inhibitors of tyrosinase, one of the key<lb/> enzymes in melanogenesis. In this
				review, we present an overview<lb/> of commonly used skin-whitening ingredients that
				are commercia-<lb/>lized, but we also hypothesize on other mechanisms that could
				be<lb/> important targets to control skin pigmentation such as for example<lb/>
				regulation of the adrenergic and glutaminergic signalling and also<lb/> control of
				tetrahydrobiopterins in the human skin.<lb/></div> 
			<div type="abstract" xml:lang="fr">Re ume ´<lb/> Les produits e
				´claircissants sont disponibles dans le commerce pour<lb/> des buts cosme ´tiques
				afin d'obtenir un tient plus clair. Ils sont e ´gale-<lb/>ment utilise ´s en
				clinique, pour le traitement de troubles hyper pig-<lb/>mentaires comme le melasma,
				les taches cafe áu lait et le lentigo<lb/> solaire. Tous ces produits ont pour cible
				la production naturelle de<lb/> me ´lanine et beaucoup de ceux ge ´ne ´ralement
				utilise ´s sont reconnus<lb/> comme des inhibiteurs compe ´titifs de la tyrosinase,
				une des enzymes<lb/> cle ´s de la me ´lanoge ´ne `se. Dans cette revue, nous pre
				´sentons une vue<lb/> d'ensemble des ingre ´dients ge ´ne ´ralement utilise ´s et
				commercialise ´s<lb/> comme blanchissant cutane ´s mais nous formulons aussi
				l'hypothe `se<lb/> que d'autres me ´canismes pourraient e ˆtre des cibles
				importantes pour<lb/> contro ˆler la pigmentation de la peau comme par exemple la re
				´gula-<lb/>tion du signal adre ´nergique et glutaminergique ou le contro ˆle des
				tet-<lb/>rahydrobiopterines dans la peau humaine.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
