<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003737"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Cell Host &amp; Microbe<lb/> Article<lb/> </note>
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Phagocytosis by Human Neutrophils<lb/> Is Stimulated by a Unique<lb/> Fungal Cell Wall Component<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ifat Rubin-Bejerano,<lb/> 1 Claudia Abeijon,<lb/> 2,3 Paula Magnelli,<lb/> 2 Paula Grisafi,<lb/> 1 and Gerald R. Fink<lb/> 1,<lb/> *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Whitehead Institute for Biomedical Research, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Nine Cambridge Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cambridge,<lb/> MA 02142, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Molecular and Cell Biology, Goldman School of Dental Medicine, Boston University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, MA 02118, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Present address: Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine, Tufts University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>200 Westboro Road, North Grafton, MA 01536, USA.<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">*Correspondence: </note>
	
	<email>gfink@wi.mit.edu<lb/></email>

	<idno type="DOI">DOI 10.1016/j.chom.2007.06.002<lb/></idno>

	<div type="abstract">SUMMARY<lb/> Innate immunity depends upon recognition of<lb/> surface features common to broad groups of<lb/> pathogens. The glucose polymer b-glucan has<lb/> been implicated in fungal immune recognition.<lb/> Fungal walls have two kinds of b-glucan:<lb/> b-1,3-glucan and b-1,6-glucan. Predominance<lb/> of b-1,3-glucan has led to the presumption that<lb/> it is the key immunological determinant for neu-<lb/>trophils. Examining various b-glucans for their<lb/> ability to stimulate human neutrophils, we find<lb/> that the minor cell wall component b-1,6-glucan<lb/> mediates neutrophil activity more efficiently<lb/> than b-1,3-glucan, as measured by engulfment,<lb/> production of reactive oxygen species, and ex-<lb/>pression of heat shock proteins. Neutrophils<lb/> rapidly ingest beads coated with b-1,6-glucan<lb/> while ignoring those coated with b-1,3-glucan.<lb/> Complement factors C3b/C3d are deposited<lb/> on b-1,6-glucan more readily than on b-1,<lb/> 3-glucan. b-1,6-glucan is also important for<lb/> efficient engulfment of the human pathogen<lb/> Candida albicans. These unique stimulatory<lb/> effects offer potential for directed stimulation<lb/> of neutrophils in a therapeutic context.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
