<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004799"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Control of Sucrose Loss in Sugarbeet During Storage<lb/> by Chemicals<lb/> 1 and Modified Atmosphere and<lb/> Certain Associated Physiological Changes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>M. T. Wu ,z B. SINGH,2 J. C. THEURER ,&quot; L. E. OLSO N,&quot; AND<lb/> D. K. SALL&quot;IKHE2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="submission">Received for publication January 15. [970<lb/></note>

	<div type="introduction">Introduction The loss of sucrose during the storage of sugarbeet is a prob­<lb/> lem of major concern in the sugar industry. In the year 1966­<lb/> 1967 alone, the loss of sucrose in stored sugarbeets in North<lb/> America was over ~30 million.4 The loss has been attributed<lb/> principally to the respiration of sugarbeet roots (15)5.<lb/> In 1950, Stout suggested ventilating storage piles of sugarbeet<lb/> roots to lo&quot;ver the high rate of respiration associated with high<lb/> temperature build-up inside the pile. Other workers have used<lb/> metabolic inhibitors and growth regulators as preharvest foliar<lb/> sprays or post-harvest treatments of the sugarbeet roots with vary­<lb/> ing results. The chemicals tested include amino triawle, 2,4-dini­<lb/> trophenol , sodium arsenate, sodium azide, iodoacetamide, hy­<lb/> droxylamine, sodium fluoride, maleic hydrazide, etc. (5,6,9,14,17).<lb/> vVe have applied preharvest foliar sprays of several pesticides<lb/> and plant growth regulators, postharvest dips of the sugarbeet<lb/> roots in solutions of pesticides and growth regulators, and modi­<lb/> fied atmosphere to control sucrose losses during the storage of<lb/> the roots. The effects of these treatments on the chemical com­<lb/> position and the rate of respiration of the roots during storage are<lb/> reported here.<lb/> Material and Methods<lb/> Pre harvest foliar application of the chemicals<lb/> Test plots of sugarbeet (cultivar: Utah-Idaho No.7) planted<lb/> in 22-inch rows at Utah State University&apos;s experimental farm,<lb/> Logan, Utah, were sprayed 10 days before harvest with on&quot;e of the<lb/> following test chemicals: Randox (a-Chloro-N, N-Diallylace ta­<lb/> mide) 200 ppm ; maleic hydrazide (1,2-Dihydro-3 , 6-pyridaz i­<lb/> nedione) 10, 100, and 1000 ppm; simazine [2-Chloro-4 ,6­<lb/> bis(ethylamino)-s-triazine ], 5, 50, 500 ppm ; N 6-benzyladen i ne,<lb/> 10, 100, and 1000 ppm; mixture of l\( 6-benzyladenine, 1000 ppm,<lb/> and indoleacetic acid (3-indoleacetic acid) 1000 ppm ; mixture of<lb/> </div>
	
	<note type="other">1 Mention of a specific commercial product does not constitute endorsement by the<lb/> </note>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>U. S. Department of Agriculture or by the Ltah State University.<lb/> 2 Deparuuent of Food Science and Industries. U tah Sta te Uni versity. </affiliation>
	</byline>
		
	<address>Logan, l:tah.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Crops R esearch Division. Agricultural Resea rch Service, Department of Agriculture,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Logan, Utah.<lb/></address>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
