<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003618"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>ieee transactions on ultrasonics, ferroelectrics, and frequency control, vol. 51, no. 1, january 2004<lb/></reference>

	<note type="page">71<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Bidirectional Axial Transmission Can Improve<lb/> Accuracy and Precision of Ultrasonic Velocity<lb/> Measurement in Cortical Bone: A Validation<lb/> on Test Materials<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Emmanuel Bossy, Maryline Talmant, Marielle Defontaine, Frédéric Patat, and Pascal Laugier<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract—The axial transmission technique uses a linear<lb/> arrangement of ultrasonic emitters and receivers placed on<lb/> a same side of a cortical bone site in contact with the skin,<lb/> involving ultrasonic propagation along the axis of bone. The<lb/> velocity of the waves radiated from bone has been shown to<lb/> reflect bone status. The thickness and composition of soft<lb/> tissue may vary along the length of the bone, between dif-<lb/>ferent skeletal sites, or between subjects. Hence, accurate<lb/> estimates of velocity require first to eliminate the effect of<lb/> the overlying soft tissue that is traversed by the ultrasound<lb/> wave. To correct for such bias without measuring soft tis-<lb/>sue properties, we designed new ultrasonic probes in the<lb/> 1–2 MHz frequency range. It is based on propagation along<lb/> the bone surface in two opposite directions from two sources<lb/> placed on both sides of a unique group of receivers. The aim<lb/> is to obtain an unbiased estimate of the velocity without<lb/> any intermediate calculation of soft tissue properties, such<lb/> as thickness variation or velocity. Validation tests were per-<lb/>formed on academic material such as Perspex or aluminum.<lb/> We found that head wave velocity values could be biased<lb/> by more than 10% for inclination of a few degrees between<lb/> the test specimen surface and the probe. On test materials,<lb/> the compensation procedure implemented in our probe led<lb/> to a relative precision error on velocity measurement lower<lb/> than 0.2 to 0.3%. These results suggest that the correction<lb/> procedure allows measuring in vivo velocities independently<lb/> of soft tissue properties.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
