<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002078"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Mesenchymal Stem Cells: Mechanisms of Immunomodulation and<lb/> Homing<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hiroshi Yagi 1,3,* , Alejandro Soto-Gutierrez 1,* , Biju Parekkadan 1 , Yuko Kitagawa 3 , Ronald<lb/> G. Tompkins 1 , Naoya Kobayashi 2 , and Martin L. Yarmush 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Center for Engineering in Medicine and Surgical Services, Massachusetts General Hospital,<lb/> Shriners Hospitals for Children and Harvard Medical School,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>51 Blossom Street, Boston,<lb/> Massachusetts 02114, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Surgery, Okayama University Graduate School of Medicine and Dentistry,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2-5-1<lb/> Shikata-cho, Okayama, 700-8558, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Surgery, Keio University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>35 Shinanomachi, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo<lb/> 160-8582, Japan<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Mesenchymal stem cell (MSC) transplantation has been explored as a new clinical approach to repair<lb/> injured tissue. A growing corpus of studies have highlighted two important aspects of MSC therapy:<lb/> (1) MSCs can modulate T-cell mediated immunological responses, and (2) systemically administered<lb/> MSCs home to sites of ischemia or injury. In this review, we describe the known mechanisms of<lb/> immunomodulation and homing of MSCs. First, we examine the low immunogenicity of MSCs and<lb/> their antigen presentation capabilities. Next, we discuss the paracrine interactions between MSCs<lb/> and innate (dendritic cells (DC)) and adaptive immune cells (T lymphocytes) with a focus on<lb/> prostaglandin E2 (PGE2), indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase (IDO) and toll-like receptor (TLR) signaling<lb/> pathways. We transition to outline the steps of activation, rolling/adhesion, and transmigration of<lb/> MSCs into target tissues during inflammatory or ischemic conditions. These aspects of MSC grafts<lb/> -immunomodulation and homing -are contextualized to understand a reported side-effect of MSC<lb/> therapy, cancer development.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords<lb/> Immunosuppression; T-cell proliferation; Stem cell migration; IFN-γ; NFκB<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
