<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006371"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>APPLIED AND ENVIRONMENTAL MICROBIOLOGY,<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">0099-2240/01/$04.00ϩ0</note>

	<idno type="DOI">DOI: 10.1128/AEM.67.1.217–224.2001<lb/> </idno>
	
	<reference>Jan. 2001, p. 217–224<lb/> Vol. 67, No. 1<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2001, American Society for Microbiology. All Rights Reserved.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Development and Optimization of a Novel Immunomagnetic Separation-<lb/>Bacteriophage Assay for Detection of Salmonella enterica<lb/> Serovar Enteritidis in Broth<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>STACY J. FAVRIN,<lb/> 1 SABAH A. JASSIM,<lb/> 1 AND MANSEL W. GRIFFITHS<lb/> 1,2 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Food Science<lb/> 1 and Canadian Research Institute for Food Safety,<lb/> 2<lb/> University of Guelph,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Guelph, Ontario, Canada N1G 2W1<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 14 June 2000/Accepted 13 October 2000<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Salmonella is the second-leading cause of food-borne illness in most developed countries, causing diarrhea,<lb/> cramps, vomiting, and often fever. Many rapid methods are available for detection of Salmonella in foods, but<lb/> these methods are often insensitive or expensive or require a high degree of technical ability to perform. In this<lb/> paper we describe development and characterization of a novel assay that utilizes the normal infection cycle<lb/> of bacteriophage SJ2 for detection of Salmonella enterica serovar Enteritidis in broth. The assay consists of four<lb/> main stages: (i) capture and concentration of target cells by using immunomagnetic separation (IMS); (ii)<lb/> infection of the target bacterium with phage; (iii) amplification and recovery of progeny phage; and (iv) assay<lb/> of progeny phage on the basis of their effect on a healthy population of host cells (signal-amplifying cells). The<lb/> end point of the assay can be determined by using either fluorescence or optical density measurements. The<lb/> detection limit of the assay in broth is less than 10<lb/> 4 CFU/ml, and the assay can be performed in 4 to 5 h. The<lb/> results of this study demonstrate that the IMS-bacteriophage assay is a rapid, simple, and sensitive technique<lb/> for detection of Salmonella serovar Enteritidis in broth cultures which can be applied to preenriched food samples.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">Salmonellae remain a major cause of food-borne illness in<lb/> the developed world, causing gastroenteritis characterized by<lb/> diarrhea, cramps, vomiting, and often fever. Salmonellae are<lb/> ubiquitous in the environment and primarily reside in the in-<lb/>testinal tracts of birds, reptiles, farm animals, and humans.<lb/> Transmission to humans is usually food borne and results from<lb/> eating undercooked meat, milk, or eggs or from cross-contam-<lb/>ination of other foods which are eaten without cooking.<lb/> Conventional methods for detection of Salmonella in foods<lb/> are based on nonselective and selective enrichment, followed<lb/> by biochemical and serological identification. These methods<lb/> can take from 4 to 6 days to perform and thus lack the speed<lb/> required for analysis of food products. Numerous rapid meth-<lb/>ods have been developed for Salmonella detection, but these<lb/> methods often suffer from a lack of sensitivity or specificity or<lb/> require expensive equipment or considerable technical exper-<lb/>tise to perform (3, 22, 30).<lb/> The specificities of bacteriophages for their host bacteria<lb/> make them ideal agents for bacterial identification and strain<lb/> typing (7). Bacteriophages (phages) have been investigated for<lb/> use in detecting food-borne pathogens. Bacterial luciferase has<lb/> been used as a reporter for bacterial detection and enumera-<lb/>tion (28). To do this, lux genes are introduced into the genome<lb/> of a bacteriophage. The bacteriophage lacks the intracellular ma-<lb/>chinery necessary for light production and thus remains dark.<lb/> Upon infection of a host, the phage genes, including the addi-<lb/>tional lux genes, are expressed within 1 h of infection and the host<lb/> cells become bioluminescent (28). Kodikara et al. (14) have used<lb/> lux ϩ recombinant phage for nearly on-line detection of enteric<lb/> indicator organisms. If a target is present at levels greater than 10</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
