<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004843"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Simulation of Enzyme Mechanisms, and Protein Dynamics,<lb/> Structures and Properties; Definition of the Chemical Mechanism<lb/> of the Photosynthetic Enzyme Rubisco; Simulation of Protein<lb/> Properties; Conformations of Disordered Peptides<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">Simulation of biochemical mechanisms can provide information not possible, or readily available, from<lb/> experimental methods, and, hence, can contribute to the elucidation of processes such as enzyme<lb/> catalysis, drug binding and conformations and dynamics of proteins and complex sugars, which<lb/> underpin applications in biotechnology and biopharmaceuticals. Fortunately, highly developed quantum<lb/> mechanical (QM) and force field [molecular mechanical/ dynamical (MM/MD)] methods and<lb/> combinations of these (e.g. QM/MM and QM/MM within MD), originated from computational chemistry,<lb/> are now available to tackle problems of the required molecular complexity and scale of computing. The<lb/> provision of the National Facility computing resources now allows internationally competitive<lb/> calculations of sufficient reliability to be performed in practical real-time scales of days to weeks, not<lb/> months to years. All four applications projects under study in this project have direct links to ongoing<lb/> experiments, thus allowing simulation to be used most effectively in hypothesis generation and<lb/> predictions for new experiments, interpretation and analysis of experimental data, and design for<lb/> protein engineering.<lb/> The photosynthetic enzyme, Rubisco (D-ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase-oxygenase), fixes carbon<lb/> dioxide into organic compounds and is arguably the most important enzyme on earth, but it is also a<lb/> very inefficient enzyme. Our studies aim to find out why, and suggest ways to redesign and re-engineer<lb/> Rubisco. Prion protein (PrP) is a very unusual protein involved in diseases such as mad-cow disease<lb/> (BSE) and CJD in humans. We are investigating the conformational distributions of the N-terminal<lb/> repeat region of PrP, which high-resolution NMR structural solution shows is mostly disordered but<lb/> shows regions of transient order, with a view to exploring the function of this region of the protein.<lb/> Methyltetrahydrofolate (Me-THF), corrinoid iron-sulfur protein (CFeSP) methyltransferase (MeTr) is a<lb/> newly found enzyme which catalyzes a key step in CO2 fixation in acetogenic bacteria. Although this<lb/> reaction is completely different from that for dihydrofolate reductase (DHFR), an enzyme we have<lb/> studied extensively, there are some intriguing similarities in structural and apparent mechanistic<lb/> properties of the two enzymes; these provide us with the opportunity to make rapid progress in<lb/> elucidating the mechanism of MeTr, together with our experimental collaborators. R67 DHFR is an<lb/> enzyme with no homology to normal chromosomal DHFR which is encoded by bacterial plasmids; it has<lb/> allowed the development of antifolate-drug (trimethoprim) resistant bacterial pathogens because it is<lb/> not inhibited by the drug. Also for comparison with binding and reaction mechanisms we have studied<lb/> extensively for DHFR, we are studying the substrate-binding and reaction mechanisms of R67 DHFR in<lb/> order to see how a protein with a quite different active-site organization can effectively catalyze the<lb/> same reaction, albeit less efficiently.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
