<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004974"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">ELSEVIER<lb/> </note>
	
	<reference>Inf. Dairy Journal 7 (1997) 435443<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">&#169; 1997 Elsevier Science Ltd<lb/> All rights reserved. Printed in Great Britain<lb/></note>

	<note>PII:<lb/> SO958-6946(97)00026-5<lb/> 0958-6946/97/$17.00+0.00<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Effectiveness of Ascorbic Acid as an Oxygen<lb/> Scavenger in Improving Viability of Probiotic<lb/> Bacteria in Yoghurts Made with Commercial<lb/> Starter Cultures<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rajiv 1. Dave u and Nagendra P. Shahb*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Yentre for Bioprocessing and Food Technology, Victoria University of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>PO Box 144228, MCMC, Melbourne, Victoria<lb/> 8001, Australia<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>&apos;Department of Food Technology, Victoria University of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>PO Box 144228, MCMC, Melbourne, Victoria 8001, Australia<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">(Received 19 October 1996; accepted 26 April 1997)<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> The viability of yoghurt and probiotic bacteria was assessed during manufacture and 35 days storage of yoghurt supplemented<lb/> with four levels of ascorbic acid using four commercial starter cultures. There were no marked differences in titratable acidity and<lb/> pH of the yoghurt, whereas oxygen content and redox potential varied in yoghurts with various levels of ascorbic acid. Hydrogen<lb/> peroxide content was initially higher in the products prepared with starter cultures that contained Lactobacillus delbrueckii ssp.<lb/> bulgaricus. During storage of yoghurt, increase in oxygen content and redox potential and percentage retention of ascorbic acid<lb/> were identical for all four starter cultures, but different at various levels of ascorbic acid. The oxygen content and redox potential<lb/> gradually increased during storage in plastic cups and remained lower with higher levels of ascorbic acid. Loss of ascorbic acid<lb/> occurred during manufacture and storage, with an average retention of only 1520% after about 35 days storage of yoghurt at 4°C.<lb/> The viable counts of Streptococcus thermophilus were lower, whereas those of L. delbrueckii ssp. bulgaricus were higher, with<lb/> increasing concentration of ascorbic acid. The counts of Lactobacillus acidophilus during storage decreased less rapidly with<lb/> increasing concentration of acsorbic acid for all four starter cultures, whereas the counts of bifidobacteria remained unchanged. 0<lb/> 1997 Elsevier Science Ltd. All rights reserved<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: viability; yoghurt bacteria; probiotic bacteria; oxygen content; redox potential; ascorbic acid; pH; hydrogen peroxide<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
