<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000024-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications 269, 415– 421
				(2000)<lb/></reference>
			<idno>doi:10.1006/bbrc.2000.2303,</idno>
			<ptr type="web">available online at http://www.idealibrary.com</ptr>
			<note type="other">on</note>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Selective Inhibition of Cyclooxygenase-2 with Antisense<lb/>
					Oligodeoxynucleotide Restricts Induction<lb/> of Rat Adjuvant-Induced
					Arthritis<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Ryoji Yamada,* Hajime Sano,* ,1 Timothy Hla,† Akira Hashiramoto,* Yutaka
					Kawahito,*<lb/> Shigehiko Mukai,* Masataka Kohno,* Yasunori Tsubouchi,* Miki
					Inoue,*<lb/> Akiko Komatsu,* Ken-ichiro Inoue,* and Motoharu
					Kondo*<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>*First Department of Internal Medicine, Kyoto Prefectural University of
					Medicine, </affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Kamigyo-ku,<lb/> Kyoto, 602-8566, Japan;</address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>and †Center for Vascular Biology, Department of Physiology,<lb/>
					University of Connecticut School of Medicine,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Farmington, Connecticut 06030<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received January 17, 2000<lb/></note>

			<div type="abstract">The effects of cyclooxygenase (COX)-2 antisense
				oli-<lb/>godeoxynucleotide (ODN) in induction of adjuvant-<lb/>induced arthritis
				were investigated. Female Lewis<lb/> rats were injected with Mycobacterium butyricum
				in-<lb/>tradermally at the base of tails to induce arthritis.<lb/> Synthetic 18 mer
				phosphorothioate ODNs correspond-<lb/>ing to the translation initiation site of rat
				COX-2<lb/> mRNA were prepared. The antisense (AS), sense (S),<lb/> and "scrambled"
				(Sc) ODNs were intraperitoneally ad-<lb/>ministered. Arthropathy was evaluated with
				arthritis<lb/> score, paw edema, and histological examination. Ex-<lb/>pression of
				COX-1 and -2 protein and mRNA were<lb/> examined with immunostaining and
				reverse-tran-<lb/>scription polymerase chain reaction, respectively.<lb/> COX-2 AS
				ODN significantly suppressed induction of<lb/> arthritis in a dose-dependent manner
				without severe<lb/> adverse effects, whereas S and Sc ODNs did not show<lb/>
				significant inhibitory effects. COX-2 mRNA and pro-<lb/>tein expression were also
				suppressed only by COX-2<lb/> AS ODN without any alteration of COX-1
				expression.<lb/> These data suggest that selective inhibition of COX-2<lb/> with AS
				ODN may have a therapeutic potency in the<lb/> treatment of rheumatoid
				arthritis.</div>
			<note type="other">© 2000 Academic Press<lb/></note>
			<keywords>Key Words: cyclooxygenase-2; antisense oligode-<lb/>oxynucleotide;
				adjuvant-induced arthritis; rheuma-<lb/>toid arthritis.<lb/></keywords>


		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
