<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006350"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Adsorption Kinetics and Ligand-Binding Properties of<lb/> Thiol-Modified Double-Stranded DNA on a Gold Surface<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mengsu Yang,* Hellas C. M. Yau, and Hing Leung Chan<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Biology and Chemistry, City University of Hong Kong,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>83 Tat Chee Avenue,<lb/> Kowloon, Hong Kong, China<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received May 14, 1998. In Final Form: July 20, 1998<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">The development of DNA-based biosensors requires efficient immobilization of DNA probes on the sensor<lb/> surfaces with optimum coverage and orientation. In this study, we have prepared thin films of a 718 base<lb/> pair 5′-thiol-labeled double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) on a gold surface by chemisorption and determined<lb/> the quantity, surface coverage, and adsorption kinetics of dsDNA using cyclic voltammetry (CV), quartz<lb/> crystal resonator (QCR), and radioactive labeling techniques. The adsorption and desorption rate constants<lb/> of the 5′-thiol-labeled dsDNA on a gold surface are estimated to be (1.9 ( 0.2) × 10 3 M -1 s -1 and (1.3 (<lb/> 1.1) × 10 -3 s -1 , respectively. The equilibrium constant is (1.5 ( 1.3) × 10 6 M -1 and the fractional coverage<lb/> is &gt;75% for the DNA concentration range of 2-10 µM. The ligand-binding properties of the immobilized<lb/> dsDNA were investigated using doxorubicin, a DNA-intercalating anthracyclic antibiotic, as the probing<lb/> molecule. The binding of doxorubicin to the immobilized dsDNA was examined by CV to verify the ligand-<lb/>binding capacity and specificity of the immobilized dsDNA. The kinetics of the interaction between<lb/> doxorubicin conjugated with a 200-kDa dextran polymer and the immobilized dsDNA was determined by<lb/> QCR, which gives the association and dissociation rate constants of (1.8 ( 0.5) × 10 3 M -1 s -1 and (3.5 (<lb/> 1.5) × 10 -3 s -1 , respectively, and an equilibrium binding constant of (5.1 ( 2.6) × 10 5 M -1 . The binding<lb/> parameters for the conjugate-DNA interaction were also determined by using a surface plasmon resonance<lb/> (SPR)-based biosensor, in which dsDNA was immobilized on the hydrogel matrix of the sensor chip through<lb/> a biotin-streptavidin linkage. While the kinetic constants from SPR measurements, ka ) (5.7 ( 0.2) ×<lb/> 10 3 M -1 s -1 and kd ) (1.2 ( 0.2) × 10 -2 s -1 , are different from those determined by QCR, the thermodynamic<lb/> constant KA obtained by SPR, (4.8 ( 0.8) × 10 5 M -1 , is similar to that by QCR.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
