<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000339"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">© 2002, Open Mobile Alliance, Ltd. All Rights Reserved. Terms and conditions of use are available from the Open<lb/> Mobile Alliance<lb/> TM Web site (

	http://www.openmobilealliance.org/documents/copyright.htm).<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
		<titlePart>DRM Content Format Version 1.0</titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<date><lb/>Proposed Version 08-July-2002<lb/></date>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Open Mobile Alliance<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<idno>OMA-Download-DRMCF-v1_0-20020708-p<lb/></idno>

	<div type="introduction">This document is a work in process and is not an approved Open Mobile Alliance™ specification. This document is<lb/> subject to revision or removal without notice. No part of this document may be used to claim conformance or<lb/> interoperability with the Open Mobile Alliance specifications.<lb/>

	OMA-Download-DRMCF-v1_0-20020708-p, Proposed Version 08-July-2002<lb/>

	Page 2 (14)<lb/>

	© © 2002, Open Mobile Alliance, Ltd.<lb/> All rights reserved<lb/> © 2002, Open Mobile Alliance, Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/>

	Terms and conditions of use are available from the Open Mobile Alliance™ Web site at<lb/>

	http://www.openmobilealliance.org/documents/copyright.htm).<lb/>

	You may use this document or any part of the document for internal or educational purposes only, provided you do not<lb/> modify, edit or take out of context the information in this document in any manner. You may not use this document in any<lb/> other manner without the prior written permission of the Open Mobile Alliance™. The Open Mobile Alliance authorises<lb/> you to copy this document, provided that you retain all copyright and other proprietary notices contained in the original<lb/> materials on any copies of the materials and that you comply strictly with these terms. This copyright permission does not<lb/> constitute an endorsement of the products or services offered by you.<lb/> The Open Mobile Alliance™ assumes no responsibility for errors or omissions in this document. In no event shall the Open<lb/> Mobile Alliance be liable for any special, indirect or consequential damages or any damages whatsoever arising out of or in<lb/> connection with the use of this information.<lb/> This document is not a Open Mobile Alliance™ specification, is not endorsed by the Open Mobile Alliance and is<lb/> informative only. This document is subject to revision or removal without notice. No part of this document may be used to<lb/> claim conformance or interoperability with the Open Mobile Alliance specifications.<lb/> Open Mobile Alliance™ members have agreed to use reasonable endeavors to disclose in a timely manner to the Open<lb/> Mobile Alliance the existence of all intellectual property rights (IPR&apos;s) essential to the present document. However, the<lb/> members do not have an obligation to conduct IPR searches. The information received by the members is publicly available<lb/> to members and non-members of the Open Mobile Alliance and may be found on the &quot;WAP IPR Declarations&quot; list at<lb/>

	http://www.wapforum.org/what/ipr.htm

	. Essential IPR is available for license on the basis set out in the schedule to the<lb/> Open Mobile Alliance Application Form.<lb/> No representations or warranties (whether express or implied) are made by the Open Mobile Alliance™ or any Open<lb/> Mobile Alliance member or its affiliates regarding any of the IPR&apos;s represented on this &quot;WAP IPR Declarations&quot; list,<lb/> including, but not limited to the accuracy, completeness, validity or relevance of the information or whether or not such<lb/> rights are essential or non-essential.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
