<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000873"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">VCL/Reconfigurable. Data Centers &amp; Clouds/NCSU/V19-Draft<lb/></note>

	<date>Feb-2009<lb/></date>
	
	<note type="page"> 1/27<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Using VCL Technology to Implement Distributed<lb/> Reconfigurable Data Centers and Computational Services for<lb/> Educational Institutions<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<docAuthor>Mladen Vouk, Andy Rindos*, Sam Averitt, John Bass, Michael Bugaev, Aaron Peeler, Henry Schaffer,<lb/> Eric Sills, Sarah Stein, Josh Thompson, Matthew P. Valenzisi**<lb/></docAuthor>
	
	<affiliation>North Carolina State University,</affiliation>
	
	<address>Raleigh, NC 27695<lb/></address>

	<email>{vouk, sfa, john_bass, mabugaev, fapeeler, hes, edsills, sstein, jfthomps}@ncsu.edu<lb/> *{rindos}@us.ibm.com, **{matt}@ncsu.net<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">1. Abstract<lb/> In the context of educational institutions, small distributed data centers and labs are<lb/> becoming increasingly expensive to provision, support and maintain on their own. This<lb/> leads to preferences towards centralized and integrated data center resource management<lb/> and network access to the resources. In turn, the data centers are undergoing a<lb/> transformation driven by the nature of the equipment in them, and by the way they are<lb/> used. As the computational and storage equipment becomes more powerful and more<lb/> densly packed, the power and cooling needs are growing as well. One of the challenges is<lb/> how to provision, manage and deliver such a large amount of physical and virtual<lb/> resources in an efficient way.<lb/> In this paper we discuss how

	NC State University Virtual Computing Laboratory (VCL,<lb/>
	

	http://vcl.

	ncsu.edu)

	technology can be used to implement distributed reconfigurable data<lb/> centers and IT services in educational institutions. We use the NC State VCL<lb/> implementation as a case study. It extends over four physical data centers and<lb/> encompasses over 2000 computational platforms – most of them are IBM BladeCenter<lb/> TM<lb/> resources, some are HP, SUN and Dell platforms. VCL is an award-winning open source<lb/> implementation of a secure production-level on-demand utility computing and services<lb/> oriented technology for wide-area access to solutions based on real and virtualized<lb/> resources, including computational, storage, network and software resources. NC State<lb/> has been researching this technology and operating it in production settings since 2004.<lb/> Currently, NC State VCL is serving a student and faculty population of more than<lb/> 30,000. There also are VCL pilots with several UNC campuses, North Carolina<lb/> Community College System, and several of out-of-state universities.<lb/> VCL technology can host practically any other environment, overlay and virtualization<lb/> solution, from single-seat desktops in an operating system of choice, to high-performance<lb/> computing (HPC) clusters. It is a technology well suited for hosting &quot;cloud&quot; solutions of<lb/> almost any type. We discuss how this technology scales and what its return on investment<lb/> is, and how it can deliver clouds that offer a mix of resource architectures and ensembles,<lb/> including those that may integrate traditional main-frames (e.g., IBM System z and<lb/> System p platforms).</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
