<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003631"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Open Access<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Two-color STED microscopy reveals different<lb/> degrees of colocalization between hexokinase-I<lb/> and the three human VDAC isoforms<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Daniel Neumann, Johanna Bückers, Lars Kastrup<lb/> * , Stefan W Hell, Stefan Jakobs<lb/> *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="other">* Correspondence: </note>
	
	<email>lkastru@gwdg.<lb/> de; sjakobs@gwdg.de<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Max Planck Institute for Biophysical<lb/> Chemistry, Department of<lb/> NanoBiophotonics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Am Fassberg<lb/> 11, 37077 Göttingen, Germany<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract The voltage-dependent anion channel (VDAC, also known as mitochondrial porin) is<lb/> the major transport channel mediating the transport of metabolites, including ATP,<lb/> across the mitochondrial outer membrane. Biochemical data demonstrate the bind-<lb/>ing of the cytosolic protein hexokinase-I to VDAC, facilitating the direct access of<lb/> hexokinase-I to the transported ATP. In human cells, three hVDAC isoforms have<lb/> been identified. However, little is known on the distribution of these isoforms within<lb/> the outer membrane of mitochondria and to what extent they colocalize with hexo-<lb/>kinase-I. In this study we show that whereas hVDAC1 and hVDAC2 are localized pre-<lb/>dominantly within the same distinct domains in the outer membrane, hVDAC3 is<lb/> mostly uniformly distributed over the surface of the mitochondrion. We used two-<lb/>color stimulated emission depletion (STED) microscopy enabling a lateral resolution<lb/> of ~40 nm to determine the detailed sub-mitochondrial distribution of the three<lb/> hVDAC isoforms and hexokinase-I. Individual hVDAC and hexokinase-I clusters could<lb/> thus be resolved which were concealed in the confocal images. Quantitative colocali-<lb/>zation analysis of two-color STED images demonstrates that within the attained reso-<lb/>lution, hexokinase-I and hVDAC3 exhibit a higher degree of colocalization than<lb/> hexokinase-I with either hVDAC1 or hVDAC2. Furthermore, a substantial fraction of<lb/> the mitochondria-bound hexokinase-I pool does not colocalize with any of the three<lb/> hVDAC isoforms, suggesting a more complex interplay of these proteins than pre-<lb/>viously anticipated. This study demonstrates that two-color STED microscopy in con-<lb/>junction with quantitative colocalization analysis is a powerful tool to study the<lb/> complex distribution of membrane proteins in organelles such as mitochondria.<lb/> </div>
	
	<idno>PACS: 87.16.Tb, 87.85.Rs<lb/></idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
