<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006382"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">1<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A Quantum Leap Forward for Li-Ion Battery Cathodes<lb/> GCEP Final	Technical Report:	</titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<date>August 2007 – July 2010<lb/></date>

	<note type="other">Investigators Josh Thomas (PI), Professor; Torbjörn Gustafsson, Lennart Häggström; Assistant Professors;<lb/> Anti Liivat, Mohammed Dahbi, Kinson Kam, David Ensling: Postdoctoral Researchers; Meifang<lb/> Lo: MSc student. Ångström</note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Advanced Battery Centre, Department of Materials Chemistry,<lb/> Uppsala University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Uppsala, Sweden.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract Our project focus has been to develop a new silicate-based cathode material for large-scale,<lb/> environmentally friendly, low-cost, high energy-and power-density Li-ion batteries giving long<lb/> cycle-life over a wide-range of temperatures. The parent material in this context is Li 2 FeSiO 4<lb/> (&quot;LFS&quot; -hereafter). A central goal has been to extract &gt;1 electron per 3d-metal, and thereby<lb/> achieve a cathode material with capacity well in excess 200 mAh/g – a critical EV-related<lb/> breakthrough. We have throughout exploited a DFT-modeling based screening procedure –<lb/> followed by synthesis of the most promising candidate materials which emerge. Earlier<lb/> screening of this type had suggested three general strategies which could prove fruitful:<lb/> A: Non-stoichiometry -for capacity enhancement.<lb/> B: TM-ion substitution -for capacity and rate enhancement, and structural stabilization.<lb/> C: Polyanion substitution -for capacity and rate enhancement.<lb/> A fourth somewhat related approach has latter b.egun to show promise: the use of standby-ions<lb/> which do not themselves participate actively in the redox reaction, but perturb the structural<lb/> situation of the redox active ions themselves.<lb/> New theoretical results include Li-ion diffusion data for &quot;un-mixed&quot; and &quot;mixed&quot; Li/Fe-ion<lb/> systems showing Li<lb/> +<lb/> diffusion to be two-dimensional in the LFS structure. This suggests that Li-<lb/>insertion/de-insertion kinetics (and hence cathode rate-performance) can be improved if the<lb/> growth of rod-like particles can be promoted with their diffusion plane perpendicular to the rod<lb/> axis. It is also found that TM-ions can be incorporated into the non-stoichiometric structure,<lb/> formulation Li 2-2x Fe 1+x SiO 4, to give shorter TM-TM ion distances, higher electron-transport rates<lb/> -and hence higher electronic conductivities. This will most certainly prove to be a key result.<lb/> Surprisingly, even 50% substitution of the Mn-site in Li 2 MnSiO 4 by different inert &quot;bystander&quot;<lb/> ions (Mg, Ni, Zn, Cu, Ca, …) was found to be unable to suppress the problematical distortion<lb/> found earlier in the Mn-coordination. The notion thus emerges that such distortion can, in fact,<lb/> be an essential structural condition for future success. This idea has been fueled by recent<lb/> interesting results on the LiFePO 4 system. Finally; 12.5% substitution of VO 4<lb/> 3-</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
