<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006712"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Pharmacological Classification of Benzamides<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>A J PUECH,&apos; Y LECRUBIER2 and P SIMON&apos;<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>From the Department of Pharmacology, Facult6 de Me&apos;decine Pitie-Salpe^triere,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>91, Bld de<lb/> I&apos;Hhpital, F-75634 PARIS CEDEX 13, France,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>&apos; and Service de Psychiatrie, Hhpital de la<lb/> Salpe^tri2re, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>47, Bld de I&apos;Hhpital, F-75013 PARIS, Franck<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract: The problem of classifying benzamides is, in general, the same as classifying<lb/> neuroleptics. A pharmacological classification of neuroleptics can be established on the<lb/> basis of the following criteria<lb/> -specificity of action on dopaminergic receptors<lb/> -penetration into the CNS<lb/> -dopaminergic profile in the CNS<lb/> 0 relative binding with respect to subclasses of DA<lb/> preferential antagonism of certain effects of apomorphine<lb/> 0 preferential affinity for dopaminergic structures<lb/> 0 activating effects on DA systems at low doses<lb/> neurologic.<lb/> -different clinical effects: antiemetic, psychiatric (antihallucinatory and disinhibitory),<lb/> A relationship between biochemical, behavioural and clinical effects is proposed<lb/> -antihallucinatory effect: decrease of dopaminergic function<lb/> -disinhibitory effect: increase of dopaminergic function.<lb/> We emphasize the problem of doses used because the different effects occurred for a<lb/> given drug at different doses.<lb/> This hypothesis suggests that positive symptomatology of schizophrenia is related to<lb/> hyperdopaminergic activity, negative symptomatology is related to hypodopaminergic<lb/> activity.<lb/> Classification of benzamides<lb/> -metocloprumide: peripheral dopaminolytic activity antiemesis without psychiatric or<lb/> -sulpiride, tiapride, DAN 2163: peripheral effects + preferential blockade of D3 and<lb/> neuroleptic effects with low doses.<lb/> 0 4 receptors, central DA activation with low doses, disinhibitory effects.<lb/> With high doses, decrease of specificity for subclasses of DA receptors, central DA<lb/> inhibition, antihallucinatory effects but little extrapyramidal symptomatology and seda-<lb/>tion.<lb/> -sultopride: central DA inhibition, antihallucinatory effects, sedative and neurological<lb/> effects.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key-words: Benzamides -classification -sulpiride -metoclopramide -sultopride -<lb/>tiapride.<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="introduction">The problem of classifying benzamides is, in general, the same as classifying<lb/> neuroleptics.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
