<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002321"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Occurrence and persistence of perfluorooctanesulfonate and other<lb/> perfluorinated surfactants in groundwater at a fire-training area<lb/> at Wurtsmith Air Force Base, Michigan, USA{<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Cheryl A. Moody,<lb/> a<lb/> { Gretchen N. Hebert,<lb/> b Steven H. Strauss*<lb/> b and Jennifer A. Field*<lb/> c<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Department of Chemistry, Oregon State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Corvallis, Oregon 97331, USA.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Department of Chemistry, Colorado State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Fort Collins, Colorado 80523, USA.<lb/></address>

	<email>E-mail: strauss@lamar.colostate.edu;</email>

	<phone>Tel: (970)491-5104<lb/></phone>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c Department of Environmental and Molecular Toxicology, Oregon State University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Corvallis, Oregon 97331, USA.</address>

	<email>E-mail: jennifer.field@orst.edu;</email>

	<phone>Tel: (541)737-2265<lb/></phone>

	<note type="submission">Received 24th December 2002, Accepted 26th February 2003<lb/> First published as an Advance Article on the web 10th March 2003<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Various formulations of fire-extinguishing materials, including aqueous film-forming foams (AFFFs), were used<lb/> as part of fire-training exercises conducted at Wurtsmith Air Force Base (WAFB) in northeastern Michigan<lb/> from the 1950s until the base was decommissioned in 1993. As a result of past fire-training exercises, AFFF-<lb/>laden wastewater containing fuels, solvents, and other materials directly entered groundwater without prior<lb/> treatment. Perfluorinated surfactants are key components in some AFFF formulations. In this study,<lb/> groundwater was analyzed for perfluoroalkanesulfonates and perfluorocarboxylates. Perfluoroalkanesulfonates<lb/> were directly detected using negative-ion electrospray ionization mass spectrometry. Derivatized<lb/> perfluorocarboxylates were detected using electron impact gas chromatography-mass spectrometry.<lb/> Groundwater from wells around fire-training area FTA-02 at WAFB contained four perfluorinated surfactants<lb/> ranging in concentration from 3 to 120 mg L<lb/> 21 : perfluorooctanesulfonate (PFOS); perfluorohexanesulfonate;<lb/> perfluorooctanoate; and perfluorohexanoate. This is the first report demonstrating that PFOS, recently shown<lb/> to be toxic to organisms ranging from zooplankton to primates, is still present in groundwater in measurable<lb/> quantities five or more years after its last known use.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
