<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005198"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Journal of Parallel and Distributed Computing 60, 374 406
				(2000)<lb/></reference>


			<idno>doi:10.1006/jpdc.1999.1613,</idno>
			<ptr type="web">available online at http:wwww.idealibrary.com on<lb/></ptr>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>INSIGNIA: An IP-Based Quality of Service<lb/> Framework for Mobile ad Hoc
					Networks<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Seoung-Bum Lee, Gahng-Seop Ahn, Xiaowei Zhang, and Andrew T.
					Campbell<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Center for Telecommunication Research, Columbia
					University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>New York, New York 10027<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received January 15, 1999; revised August 15, 1999; accepted
				December 15, 1999<lb/></note>

			<div type="abstract">We present the design, implementation, and evaluation of INSIGNIA,
				an<lb/> IP-based quality of service framework that supports adaptive services in
				mobile<lb/> ad hoc networks. The framework is based on an in-band signaling and
				soft-state<lb/> resource management approach that is well suited to supporting
				mobility and<lb/> end-to-end quality of service in highly dynamic environments where
				the network<lb/> topology, node connectivity, and end-to-end quality of service are
				time varying.<lb/> Architecturally INSIGNIA is designed to support fast reservation,
				restoration,<lb/> and end-to-end adaptation based on the inherent flexibility and
				robustness<lb/> and scalability found in IP networks. We evaluate the framework,
				paying<lb/> particular attention to the performance of the in-band signaling
				system,<lb/> which helps counter time-varying network dynamics in support of the
				delivery<lb/> of adaptive services. Our results show the benefit of our framework
				under diverse<lb/> mobility, traffic, and channel conditions. </div>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<note type="copyright">&#x6ef59; 2000 Academic Press<lb/></note>
			<keywords>Key Words: quality of service; mobile ad hoc networks; adaptive services;<lb/>
				in-band signaling; soft-state resource management.<lb/></keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
