<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004416"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Inhibition of Viral Replication by Nitric Oxide<lb/> and Its Reversal by Ferrous Sulfate<lb/> and Tricarboxylic Acid Cycle Metabolites<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>By Gunasegaran Karupiah and Nicholas Harris<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>From the Laboratory of Viral Diseases, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases,<lb/> National Institutes of Health,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bethesda, Maryland 20892<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Slllmmal&apos;y<lb/> IFN-&apos;y-induced nitric oxide (NO) in the murine macrophage-derived cell line RAW 264.7 was<lb/> previously shown to inhibit replication of the poxviruses ectromelia and vaccinia (VV) and HSV-1.<lb/> In the current study we demonstrate that murine macrophages activated as a consequence of<lb/> VV infection express inducible nitric oxide synthase. These activated macrophages were resistant<lb/> to infection with VV and efficiently blocked the replication of VV and HSV-1 in infected by-<lb/>stander cells of epithelial and fibroblast origin. This inhibition was arginine dependent, cor-<lb/>related with nitrite production in cultures, and reversible by the NOS inhibitor N&apos;~-monomethyl -<lb/>r-arginine. NO-mediated inhibition of VV replication was studied by treatment of virus-infected<lb/> human 293 cells with the NO donor S-nitroso-N-acetyl-penicillamine. Using a VV-specific DNA<lb/> probe, antibodies specific for temporally expressed viral proteins, and transmission electron mi-<lb/>croscopy, we have shown that NO inhibited viral late gene protein synthesis, DNA replication,<lb/> and virus particle formation, but not expression of the early proteins that were analyzed. Putative<lb/> enzymatic targets of NO were identified by reversing the NO-mediated inhibition of VV replica-<lb/>tion in the 293 cells with exogenous ferrous sulfate and t-cysteine. Reversal of inhibition may<lb/> derive from the capacity of these reagents to protect or regenerate nonheme iron or thiol groups,<lb/> respectively, which are essential for the catalytic activities of enzymes susceptible to inactivation<lb/> by NO.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">T<lb/> he successful elimination of viral infection is dependent<lb/> on both innate and acquired immunity. Macrophages,<lb/> strategically placed in various body compartments, play a key<lb/> role in the orchestration of both innate and antigen-specific<lb/> immune responses. Apart from their role as phagocytic<lb/> scavengers of infectious agents, macrophages can stimulate<lb/> the antiviral activities of NK and T cells. Together, these<lb/> effector cells and the cytokines they produce act to limit virus<lb/> multiplication before the induction of antigen-specific T cell-<lb/>mediated immunity and antibody responses. By their capacity<lb/> to produce IFNs and other cytokines, NK and T cells are<lb/> responsible for a reciprocal activation of macrophages. Of the<lb/> IFNs, IFN-y is the most potent macrophage-activating factor<lb/> and the only known cytokine with the capacity to induce<lb/> nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) 1 in macrophages by itself (1).<lb/> 1 Abbreviations used in thispaper: D-A and L-A, D-and L-arginine, respec-</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
