<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005151"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>MOLECULAR AND CELLULAR BIOLOGY, May 2009, p. 2609–2621<lb/>Vol. 29, No. 10<lb/></reference>
			<note type="other">0270-7306/09/$08.000</note> 
			<idno>doi:10.1128/MCB.01277-08<lb/></idno> 
			<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2009,
				American Society for Microbiology. All Rights Reserved.<lb/></note>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Polo-Like Kinase 1 Depletion Induces DNA Damage in Early S Prior<lb/> to
					Caspase Activation &#x6ef59;<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Hyungshin Yim* and Raymond L. Erikson<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology, Harvard
					University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received 12 August 2008/Returned for modification 22 September
				2008/Accepted 4 March 2009<lb/></note>
			<div type="abstract">
				Polo-like kinase 1 (Plk1) plays several roles in
				mitosis, and it has been suggested to have a role in tumorigenesis.<lb/> We have
				previously reported that Plk1 depletion results in cell death in cancer cells,
				whereas normal cells survive<lb/> similar depletion. However, Plk1 depletion
				together with p53 depletion induces cell death in normal cells as well.<lb/> This
				communication presents evidence on the sequence of events that leads to cell death
				in cancer cells. DNA<lb/> damage is detected at the first S phase following Plk1
				depletion and is more severe in Plk1-depleted p53-null cancer<lb/> cells. As a
				consequence of Plk1 depletion using lentivirus-based small interfering RNA
				techniques, prereplicative<lb/> complex (pre-RC) formation is disrupted at the G 1
				/S transition, and DNA synthesis is reduced during S phase of<lb/> the first cycle
				after depletion. The levels of geminin, an inhibitor of DNA pre-RC, and Emi1, an
				inhibitor of<lb/> anaphase-promoting complex/cyclosome, are elevated in
				Plk1-depleted cells. The rate of cell cycling is slower in<lb/> Plk1-depleted cells
				than in control cells when synchronized by serum starvation. Plk1 depletion results
				in disrupted<lb/> DNA pre-RC formation, reduced DNA synthesis, and DNA damage before
				cells display severe mitotic catastrophe<lb/> or apoptosis. Our data suggest that
				Plk1 is required for cell cycle progression not only in mitosis but also for
				DNA<lb/> synthesis, maintenance of DNA integrity, and prevention of cell death.<lb/>
			</div>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
