<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005922"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">578<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Diversity does make a difference: fibroblast growth<lb/> factor-heparin interactions<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Salem Faham*, Robert J Linhardtt and Douglas C Rees<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Fibroblast growth factors (FGFs) are members of a protein<lb/> family with a broad range of biological activities. The best<lb/> characterized FGFs interact with two distinct extracellular<lb/> receptors -a transmembrane tyrosine kinase FGF receptor<lb/> (FGFR) and a heparan sulfate-related proteoglycan of the<lb/> extracellular matrix. These components form a<lb/> FGF-FGFR-proteoglycan complex that activates the<lb/> FGF-mediated signal transduction process through FGFR<lb/> dimerization. Recent crystal structure determinations of<lb/> FGF-heparin complexes have provided insights into both the<lb/> interactions between these components and the role of<lb/> heparin-like proteoglycans in FG F function. Future advances in<lb/> this field will benefit enormously from an ability to specifically<lb/> prepare homogenous heparin-based oligosaccharides of<lb/> defined sequence for use in biochemical and structural studies<lb/> of FGF and many other systems.<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">Addresses<lb/></note>

	<affiliation>*Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry and Laboratory of<lb/> Structural Biology and Molecular Medicine, University of California Los<lb/>	Angeles, </affiliation>
	
	<address>405 Hilgard Avenue, Los Angeles, CA 90095-1570, USA;<lb/></address>

	<email>e-mail: salem@ewald.mbi.ucla.edu<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>tDivision of Medicinal and Natural Products Chemistry and Department<lb/> of Chemical and Biochemical Engineering, University of Iowa,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Phar S-<lb/>328, Iowa City, IA 52242, USA;</address>

	<email>e-mail: robert-linhardt@uiowa.edu<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>SHoward Hughes Medical Institute, Division of Chemistry and<lb/> Chemical Engineering,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>147-75CH,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>California Institute of Technology,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pasadena, CA 91125, USA;</address>

	<email>e-mail: dcrees@cco.caltech.edu<lb/></email>

	<note type="other">Correspondence: Douglas C Rees<lb/></note>

	<reference>Current Opinion in Structural Biology 1998, 8:578-586<lb/></reference>

	<ptr type="web">http://biomednet.com/elecref/0959440X00800578<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="copyright">© Current Biology Ltd</note>

	<idno>ISSN 0959-440X<lb/></idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
