<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006305"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>3rd World Conference on Photovoltaic Energy Conversion May 11-18, 2003 Osaka, Japan<lb/></reference>

	<idno>4P-A8-68<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>COMPARATIVE STUDY ON EMITTER SHEET RESISTIVITY<lb/> MEASUREMENTS FOR INLINE QUALITY CONTROL<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>E. Riiland&apos;, P. Fath&apos;, T. Pavelka2, A. Pap2, K. Peter&apos;, J. Mizsei3,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>&apos; University of Konstanz, Department of Physics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>78457 Konstanz, Germany,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>SEMILAB Rt.,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Prielle KomClia U. 2, H-1117 Budapest, Hungary,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Budapest University of Technology and Economics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Goldmann Gy. TCr 3., H-1521 Budapest, Hungary<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">normally measured based on<lb/> manually drawn samples. In<lb/> contrast, our aim was to<lb/> develop and test measurement<lb/> methods which can be directly<lb/> incorporated in high volume<lb/> diffusion equipment.<lb/> Two contactless approaches<lb/> have been studied, the Eddy<lb/> Current technique and a newly<lb/> SPV (Surface-Photo-Voltage)<lb/> probing.<lb/> As<lb/> reference<lb/> developed system based on<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">( C o n d u e l i v c R i n g )<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Probe H e a d Q,.<lb/> L.ser<lb/> In the underlying study two contactless<lb/> measurement techniques were applied to study the emitter<lb/> sheet resistance ps after the phosphorus emitter diffusion:<lb/> the Eddy current method and a novel SPV technique. As a<lb/> reference four point probe (FPP) measurements were<lb/> undertaken which request a direct contact between probe<lb/> head and silicon wafer sample. There are several reasons to<lb/> rely on contactless approaches within an inline quality<lb/> control system:<lb/> o lower probability of contaminating the silicon wafer<lb/> by metal probes<lb/> Stress free measurements reduce the chance of wafer<lb/> breakage (especially appropriate for thin substrates)<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
