<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005100"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">490 </note>
	<reference>@BULLET Hepatobiliary Pancreat Dis Int，Vol 5，No 4 @BULLET </reference>
	
	<date type="publication">November 15，2006 @BULLET</date> 
	
	<ptr>www.hbpdint.com<lb/></ptr>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Author Affiliations: Department of Hepatobiliary Surgery, First<lb/> Affiliated Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hangzhou<lb/> 310003, China</address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>(Feng XN, Xu X and Zheng SS)<lb/> Corresponding Author: Shu-Sen Zheng, MD, PhD, FACS</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>, Department<lb/> of Hepatobiliary Surgery, First Affiliated Hospital, Zhejiang University<lb/> School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hangzhou 310003, China (</address>

	<phone>Tel: 86-571-87236570;<lb/></phone>

	<email>Email: zyzss@zju.edu)<lb/></email>

	<note type="copyright">© 2006, Hepatobiliary Pancreat Dis Int. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">BACKGROUND: A safe and effective preservation solution<lb/> is a precondition for liver transplantation, which is<lb/> accepted as the radical treatment for patients with end-<lb/>stage liver disease. The increasing use of marginal donors<lb/> and non-heart beating donors as well as the establishment<lb/> of a national organ allocation network call for better<lb/> preservation. New preservation solutions like histidine-<lb/>tryptophan-ketoglutarate (HTK) solution and Celsior<lb/> solution have been introduced to liver preservation, and<lb/> protective gene intervention and other modifications have<lb/> also been investigated. In this article, we review recent<lb/> advances in liver preservation solutions.<lb/> DATA SOURCES: An English-language literature search<lb/> was conducted using MEDLINE (1990-2005) on liver<lb/> preservation solution, biliary complication, protective<lb/> gene and other related subjects.<lb/> RESULTS: Although the high viscosity of the University of<lb/> Wisconsin (UW) solution proved harmful to the hepatic<lb/> microcirculation, three solutions showed equivalent<lb/> preservation effects. When the cold ischemia time was<lb/> short, there were no significant differences among the<lb/> three solutions in the incidence of biliary complications.<lb/> So far, modifications of preservation solutions have<lb/> achieved great success. Several types of protective genes<lb/> like A20, Bcl-2, Bcl-X L and HO-1 were reported to have<lb/> definite liver protective effects. The addition of other<lb/> substrates like TNF-α antibody, tacrolimus (FK506) and<lb/> fructose-1, 6-bisphosphate (FBP) can also improve the<lb/> preservation effect. However, addition of insulin to UW<lb/> solution is harmful to the graft.<lb/> CONCLUSIONS: In centers with highly-developed<lb/> transplantation techniques, HTK and Celsior solutions<lb/> are acceptable in liver preservation. Protective gene<lb/> modification and addition of substrates like TNF-α<lb/> antibody, FK506 and FBP are prominent approaches to<lb/> improve liver preservation.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
