<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005035"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			
			<reference>Building and Environment 45 (2010) 1153–1160<lb/></reference>
			
			<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">Building and Environment<lb/></note>
			<ptr type="web">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/buildenv<lb/></ptr>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Estimation of mould growth levels on rendered façades based on surface
					relative<lb/> humidity and surface temperature measurements<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Sanne Johansson * , Lars Wadsö , Kenneth Sandin<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>Building Materials, Lund University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Box 118, 221 00 Lund, Sweden<lb/></address>

			<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o</note>
			<lb/> 
			<note type="submission">
				Article history:<lb/> Received 23 April 2009<lb/> Received in revised form<lb/>27 October 2009<lb/> Accepted 29 October 2009
			</note>
			<lb/>
			<keywords>Keywords:<lb/>Rendering Mould growth<lb/> Temperature Moisture<lb/> ETICS
				Façade<lb/>
			</keywords>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<div type="abstract">	
				a b s t r a c t<lb/> Many façades made with thin rendering on thermal
				insulation have problems with biological growth. In<lb/> this study, surface
				temperature and surface relative humidity were monitored over a 20-month period
				on<lb/> test house façades with different constructions (thermal inertia), surface
				colour and compass directions.<lb/> This data were used to test three theoretical
				indices of biological growth with the aim of indicating the<lb/> potential of mould
				growth on different types of rendered façades. The results show that thin
				renderings<lb/> on thermal insulation have significantly higher surface humidities
				compared to façade constructions<lb/> with higher thermal inertia, and therefore
				have a higher potential for mould growth. The colour is the<lb/> most important
				factor for the surface humidity levels on south-facing façades (in the northern
				hemi-<lb/> sphere) as darker surfaces absorb more solar radiation and therefore have
				a higher average temperature.<lb/> On a north-facing façade the heat storage
				capability of the façade and its effect on the surface temper-<lb/> ature is most
				important.
			</div>
			<lb/>
			<note type="copyright">&#169; 2009 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</note>
			<lb/>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
