<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005109"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">ORIGINAL ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Oxidative Stress in Chronic Renal Allograft Nephropathy<lb/> in Rats: Effects of Long-term Treatment with Carvedilol,<lb/> BM 91.0228, or Alpha-tocopherol<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>*Uwe Göttmann, MD, *Jens Oltersdorf, *Meike Schaub, MD, Thomas Knoll, MD,<lb/> Walter E. Back, MD, *Fokko J. van der Woude, MD, PhD, and *Claude Braun, MD<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract: Oxidative stress is markedly increased after kidney<lb/> transplantation and may participate in the development and/or pro-<lb/>gression of chronic renal allograft nephropathy. In the present study<lb/> we sought to assess the nephroprotective potential of antioxidative<lb/> treatment in renal allograft recipients. Experiments were performed in<lb/> the Fisher-Lewis rat model of chronic renal allograft nephropathy,<lb/> with isografted Lewis rats serving as controls. Allografted rats were<lb/> orally treated with carvedilol, an antihypertensive drug with antioxi-<lb/>dative properties (25 mg/kg/d), its purely antioxidative derivative<lb/> BM 91.0228 (5 mg/kg/d), alpha-tocopherol (100 mg/kg/d), a combi-<lb/>nation of propranolol/doxazosine (10/5 mg/kg/d), or vehicle for 24<lb/> weeks. At the end of the study, oxidative status and influence of an-<lb/>tioxidative treatment were assessed in transplanted animals. Chronic<lb/> allograft nephropathy was characterized by a marked increase of<lb/> markers for oxidative stress (increased plasma and kidney levels of<lb/> malondialdehyde, reduced glutathione, and tocopherol levels in renal<lb/> allografts). Treatment with carvedilol, BM 91.0228, and tocopherol<lb/> significantly improved antioxidative status of allograft kidney recipi-<lb/>ents. In addition, carvedilol reduced elevated blood pressure in allo-<lb/>grafted rats. However none of the drugs had a beneficial influence on<lb/> functional and morphologic renal changes. Our data thus demonstrate<lb/> that long-term treatment with the antioxidants carvedilol, BM<lb/> 91.0228, or alpha-tocopherol does not prevent development of<lb/> chronic transplant nephropathy, despite an improvement of antioxi-<lb/>dative status.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key Words: BM 91.0228, carvedilol, chronic rejection, kidney,<lb/> oxidative stress, rats, tocopherol, transplantation</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
