<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005035"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Illuminating the Structure of Code and Decoder of Parallel Concatenated<lb/> Recursive Systematic (Turbo) Codes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Patrick Robertson *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institute for Communications Technology<lb/> German Aerospace Research Establishment (DLR)<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P.O. Box 1116, D-82230 Wessling, Germany.<lb/></address>

	<phone>Tel.: ++49 8153 282808; FAX: ++49 8153 281442<lb/></phone>

	<email>e-mail: pat rick0 holmes. nt .op .dlr . de<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Recently, a coding scheme (turbo-codes) was proposed, that<lb/> achieves almost reliable data communication at signal-to-noise ra-<lb/>tios very close to the Shannon-limit. In this paper we show that<lb/> the associated iterative decoder can be formulated in a simpler<lb/> fashion by passing information from one decoder to the next us-<lb/>ing log-likelihood ratios as opposed to channel values that need to<lb/> be normalized. Also no heuristically determined correction pa-<lb/>rameters are necessary for stable decoding. In addition, we can<lb/> reduce the average number of iterations needed for the same BER<lb/> performance by determining when further iterations achieve no<lb/> more benefit. Furthermore, it seems that the trellis-termination<lb/> problem appears non-trivial and we give a pragmatic suboptimal<lb/> solution. We investigate different block sizes and also a hybrid<lb/> scheme that performs extremely well with less computations. A<lb/> drawback of the codes has been discovered: the BER curves show<lb/> a flattening at higher signal-to-noise ratios, this is due to the small<lb/> minimum distance of the whole code. By analyzing the interleaver<lb/> used in the encoder we can calculate approximations to the BER<lb/> at high SNRs. Finally, by careful interleaver manipulation the<lb/> minimum distance of the code can be increased and the error-<lb/>coefficient for the remaining small distance events can be further<lb/> reduced. Furthermore, we have investigated the influence of the<lb/> interleaver length on the SNR needed to achieve a certain BER.<lb/> Simulations confirm both the analytical approximation to the BER<lb/> as well as the method for interleaver design which yields a marked<lb/> improvement at higher SNR.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
