<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007391"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Spring constants of composite ceramic/gold cantilevers for scanning probe<lb/> microscopy<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>John L. Hazel, Vladimir V. Tsukruk *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>College of Engineering and Applied Sciences, Western Michigan University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kalamazoo, MI 49008, USA<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 19 November 1997; accepted 5 June 1998<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> A combination of ®nite element analysis (FEA) calculations and resonant frequency measurements are applied for determining the normal<lb/> and lateral spring constants of microfabricated ceramic/gold cantilevers for friction force mode of scanning probe microscopy (SPM). The<lb/> cantilever Si 3 N 4 and Au layers are combined analytically into an equivalent single composite layer. Bending and torsion behavior of the<lb/> cantilever are determined through FEA. Effective Young&apos;s modulus for the composite Si 3 N 4 -Au beam is determined through assimilation of<lb/> FEA and fundamental resonant frequency measurements. Several current analytical solutions are compared with the full FEA evaluation. A<lb/> new analytical expression is derived for obtaining the ratio of lateral to normal spring constants and thereby the evaluation of absolute values<lb/> of friction coef®cients. Calibration plots are presented for the assessment of both vertical and torsion spring constants of bi-component<lb/> cantilevers by measuring their resonant frequencies and thickness of gold overlay. The complex relationship between resonant frequency, f o ,<lb/> and spring constants, k, can be presented in scaling form k , f<lb/> a<lb/> o with a &lt; 2:60 for a wide range of compositions of cantilever beams.<lb/> Deviations from the simple cubic relationship k , f<lb/> 3<lb/> o known for a homogeneous beam are related to the bi-component nature of cantilevers<lb/> with ceramic layer and gold overlay. The calibration plots are proposed and analytical expression is derived to make more accurate<lb/> assessment of spring constants for composite SPM cantilevers. q 1999 Elsevier Science S.A. All rights reserved.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: Atomic force; Elastic properties; Surface energy; Tribology<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
