<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005587"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>SURFACE AND INTERFACE ANALYSIS, VOL. 15, 26S272 (1990)<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>X-ray ]Photoelectron Spectroscopic Studies of Thin<lb/> Film Oxides of Cobalt and Molybdenum<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>N. S. McIntyre, D. D. Johnston, L. L. Coatsworth and R. D. Davidson<lb/> J. R. Brown<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Surface Science Western, Faculty of Science, The University of Western Ontario. London, Ontario, Canada<lb/> Energy Research Laboratory, Energy, Mines and Resources,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Canada, 555 Booth Street, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Surface oxidation reactions of cobalt, molybdenum and mixed cobalt-molybdenum metals have been investigated<lb/> using x-ray pbchelectron spectroscopy (XPS). Tbe oxide stoicbiometries have been determined from XPS intensity<lb/> measurements Sucb quantification has been important in identifying oxide compositions with cbaracteristic XPS<lb/> spectra. A number of discrete binary molybdenum oxides have been characterized after reactions at 2OOOC and<lb/> pressures ranging from 1 atm to<lb/> Pa. At the lowest pressure, the Mo 3d spectra and O/Mo ratias suggest the<lb/> formation of a molybdenum-oxygen structure with a stoicbiometry oear unity. By contrast, at bigber presa~ures,<lb/> oxides that are predominantly MOO, and MOO, appear, but other intermediate oxide structures are also identi-<lb/>fied. Wellde6ned binary oxides of cobalt can be prepared from cobalt metal after beating in oxygen at merent<lb/> pressures. New binary oxides of cobalt and molybdenum have been generated by the reaction on MOO, or c0#4<lb/> substrates. Oxidation of a tbin film of molybdenum on a Co,O, substrate bas been shown to produce a nearly<lb/> stoichiometric rrurface layer of CoMd), . The procedure could be wieful for the production of other ternary oxides<lb/> of possible interest for use as XPS reference materials.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
