<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004969"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Geologic Storage of CO 2<lb/> Subsurface Monitoring of CO 2 Sequestration in Coal<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="other">GCEP Annual Report<lb/></note>

	<date>May, 2008<lb/></date>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Investigators Jerry M. Harris, Professor, Geophysics<lb/> Youli Quan, Research Associate, Geophysics<lb/> Eduardo Santos, Postdoc, Geophysics<lb/> Tope Akinbehinje, Adeyemi Arogunmati, Jolene Robin-McCaskill, and Evan S. Um,<lb/> Graduate Research Assistants, Geophysics<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Dynamic imaging provides an effective way to integrate previous time-lapse data<lb/> with current data in order to estimate a current model. We present two methods useful for<lb/> continuous dynamic reservoir and subsurface monitoring. The first method is a stochastic<lb/> method for the inversion of geophysical data. It uses the ensemble Kalman filter (EnKF)<lb/> that we demonstrate using time-lapse surface seismic data. We use reflection waveform<lb/> and traveltime data plus sonic log information as input to the EnKF inversion. Unlike<lb/> conventional seismic methods that give relative impedance, the EnKF inversion yields<lb/> absolute seismic velocity. The second method is a specific dynamic imaging algorithm<lb/> we call DynaSIRT. DynaSIRT integrates data from previous surveys in an efficient way,<lb/> without the reprocessing older data. It preserves state variables that store the temporally<lb/> damped effective illumination of previous surveys and timestamps to track parameter<lb/> updates. We show results of DynaSIRT applied to synthetic time-lapse diffraction<lb/> tomography data, where it provides a clear detection of a CO 2 leak even for sparse survey<lb/> geometry. Lastly, we introduce the method of data evolution to supplement sparse data<lb/> surveys for continuous monitoring. Data evolution may be used with any dynamic<lb/> imaging stream to supplement sparse data recordings with predicted data based on spatio-<lb/>temporal interpolation. And finally, we report herein a feasibility study for the use<lb/> controlled-source electromagnetics (CSEM) for monitoring geological CO 2 storage in<lb/> coal. We conducted the CSEM study in both the frequency domain and time domain. In<lb/> order to test various monitoring methods and strategies, we used relatively realistic time-<lb/>lapse seismic and electrical models that were constructed from flow simulation and rock<lb/> physics.<lb/> -2-<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
