<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005189"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Advances in Water Resources 34 (2011) 395–406<lb/></reference>
			<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
			<note type="other">Advances in Water Resources<lb/></note>
			<ptr type="web">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/advwatres<lb/></ptr>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Dual state-parameter estimation of root zone soil moisture by
					optimal<lb/> parameter estimation and extended Kalman filter data
					assimilation<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Haishen Lü a,b,⇑ , Zhongbo Yu a,c , Yonghua Zhu a , Sam Drake d ,
					Zhenchun Hao a , Edward A. Sudicky b<lb/>
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>a State Key Laboratory of Hydrology-Water Resources and Hydraulic
					Engineering, College of Hydrology and Water Resources, Hohai
					University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Nanjing 210098, China<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>b Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of Waterloo,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Waterloo, Ontario, Canada N2L 3G1<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>c Department of Geoscience, University of Nevada,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Las Vegas, NV 89154, USA<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>d Office of Arid Lands Studies, University of Arizona,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>1955 E. 6th Street, Tucson, AZ 85719, USA<lb/></address>

			<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/></note> 
			<note type="submission">
				Article history:<lb/> Received 13
				November 2009<lb/> Received in revised form 10 December 2010<lb/> Accepted 10 December 2010<lb/> 
			</note>
			<date>Available online 21 December 2010<lb/></date>
			
			<keywords>
				Keywords:<lb/> Soil moisture content<lb/> Root zone<lb/> Richards' equation<lb/> Optimal parameters and
				extended Kalman<lb/> filter data assimilation method<lb/> Particle swarm
				optimization algorithm<lb/>
			</keywords> 
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<div type="abstract">
				a b s t r a c t<lb/> With well-determined hydraulic
				parameters in a hydrologic model, a traditional data assimilation<lb/> method (such
				as the Kalman filter and its extensions) can be used to retrieve root zone soil
				moisture<lb/> under uncertain initial state variables (e.g., initial soil moisture
				content) and good simulated results<lb/> can be achieved. However, when the key soil
				hydraulic parameters are incorrect, the error is non-Gauss-<lb/> ian, as the Kalman
				filter will produce a persistent bias in its predictions. In this paper, we propose
				a<lb/> method coupling optimal parameters and extended Kalman filter data
				assimilation (OP-EKF) by combin-<lb/> ing optimal parameter estimation, the extended
				Kalman filter (EKF) assimilation method, a particle<lb/> swarm optimization (PSO)
				algorithm, and Richards' equation. We examine the accuracy of estimating<lb/> root
				zone soil moisture through the optimal parameters and extended Kalman filter data
				assimilation<lb/> method by using observed in situ data at the Meiling experimental
				station, China. Results indicate that<lb/> merely using EKF for assimilating surface
				soil moisture content to obtain soil moisture content in the root<lb/> zone will
				produce a persistent bias between simulated and observed values. Using the OP-EKF
				assimila-<lb/> tion method, estimates were clearly improved. If the soil profile is
				heterogeneous, soil moisture retrieval<lb/> is accurate in the 0–50 cm soil profile
				and is inaccurate at 100 cm depth. Results indicate that the method<lb/> is useful
				for retrieving root zone soil moisture over large areas and long timescales even
				when available<lb/> soil moisture data are limited to the surface layer, and soil
				moisture content are uncertain and soil<lb/> hydraulic parameters are
				incorrect.<lb/>
			</div>
			<note type="copyright">&#169; 2010 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
