<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000341"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>HISTOACRYL® and HISTOACRYL® BLUE TOPICAL SKIN ADHESIVE<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<note type="other">Package Insert<lb/>Before using product, read the following information thoroughly.</note>

	<div type="introduction"><lb/> CAUTION: Federal (USA) law restricts this device to sale and use by, or on the order of, a physician.<lb/> IMPORTANT! This insert is designed to assist in using the Histoacryl® tissue adhesive. It is not a reference to<lb/> surgical techniques.<lb/> DESCRIPTION Histoacryl® and Histoacryl® Blue are sterile liquid topical skin adhesives composed of n-Butyl-2-Cyanoacrylate<lb/> monomer. The two products are different in only one respect: Histoacryl® is provided as a colorless liquid, and<lb/> Histoacryl® Blue is colored with the dye D&amp;C Violet #2 in order to make it easier to see the thickness of the layer of<lb/> Histoacryl Blue that has been applied. Histoacryl® and Histoacryl® Blue topical skin adhesives are supplied in a 0.5<lb/> ml single patient use plastic ampoules. Each ampoule is sealed within a plastic vial so the exterior of the ampoule<lb/> can remain sterile. Histoacryl® remains liquid until exposed to acid, base, alcohol, water or water-containing<lb/> substances, including tissues; upon contact with water or water-containing substances such as tissues. Histoacryl<lb/> cures (polymerizes exothermically) and forms a film that bonds to the underlying surface. All references to<lb/> Histoacryl® below refer to both Histoacryl® (without dye) and Histoacryl® Blue (with dye) unless stated otherwise<lb/> INDICATIONS Histoacryl and Histoacryl Blue topical skin adhesives are intended for topical application to hold closed easily<lb/> approximated skin edges of minimum-tension wounds from clean surgical incisions and simple, thoroughly<lb/> cleansed, trauma-induced lacerations. Histoacryl and Histoacryl Blue may be used in conjunction with, but not in<lb/> place of, dermal sutures.<lb/> CONTRAINDICATIONS:<lb/> , Histoacryl® topical skin adhesive is not to be applied to below the surface of the skin, epidermis. The liquid<lb/> adhesive will react exothermically with tissue; the polymerized adhesive is not absorbed by any tissues and<lb/> may elicit a foreign body reaction.<lb/> * The topical skin adhesive is not to be applied to any internal organs, blood vessels, nerve tissue, mucosal<lb/> surfaces or mucocutaneous junctions, areas with dense natural hair, or within the conjunctival sac of the<lb/> eye.<lb/> * The topical skin adhesive is not to be applied to the surface of the eye. If the eyelids are accidentally<lb/> bonded closed, release eyelashes with warm water by covering with a wet pad. The adhesive will bond to<lb/> eye protein and will cause periods of weeping which will help to debond the adhesive. Keep the eye<lb/> covered until debonding is complete -usually within 1 to 3 days. Do not force the eye open.<lb/> * The topical skin adhesive is not to be applied to wounds subject to high skin tension, or on areas of<lb/> increased skin tension such as the elbows, knees, or knuckles. The topical skin adhesive is not to be used<lb/> in areas of skin excision.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
