<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55009627"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">1<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Designing Digital Tables for Highly Integrated Collaboration<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>David Pinelle, Carl Gutwin, Sriram Subramanian<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<email>david.pinelle@usask.ca, gutwin@cs.usask.ca, sriram@cs.usask.ca<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Computer Science<lb/> University of Saskatchewan<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>176 Thorvaldson Building<lb/> 110 Science Place<lb/> Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, S7N 5C9 CANADA<lb/></address>

	<phone>Tel: +1 306 966 2327 Fax: +1 306 966-4884<lb/> </phone>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract Digital tabletop systems are currently receiving considerable attention, but present systems do<lb/> not allow the fluid and natural work that is evident when people work around a traditional table.<lb/> This fluidity is particularly obvious in highly-integrated collaboration, where people work<lb/> together in a closely coordinated fashion. Highly-integrated collaboration is common on regular<lb/> tables, but is not well supported in digital tabletop systems. As a first step in determining how<lb/> this support can be added to digital tables, we carried out an observational study of groups doing<lb/> highly integrated tasks on regular tables. We saw that people perform several kinds of actions<lb/> around tables that have not been considered before in digital table design, and we also found that<lb/> digital tables impose several physical constraints on highly integrated collaboration. These<lb/> findings suggest possible design opportunities that can help digital tables improve support for<lb/> highly integrated collaboration, and can help make digital tabletop systems a compelling<lb/> alternative to the traditional table.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: digital tables, tabletop displays, human-computer interaction, computer-supported<lb/> cooperative work, highly integrated collaboration<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
