<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001060"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Phyrochemisrry, Vol. 24, No. 4, pp. 815-811, 1985.<lb/> </reference>
	
	<note type="other">0031~9422/85 53.00 + 0.00<lb/> F&apos;rinted in Great Britain.<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="copyright"> &#169; 1985 Pergamon F&apos;ress Ltd.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>PIGMENTS FROM SAL VIA MZLTIORRHlZA<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>HOU-WEI Luo, BAO-JING Wu, MEI-YU Wu,* ZHONG-GEN YONG,* MASATAKE NIWA~$ and YOSHIMASA HIRATA~<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Nanjing College of Pharmacy,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nanjing, China;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>*Institute of Jingsu Industrial Chemical Research,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nanjing, China;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>t Faculty of<lb/> Pharmacy, Meijo University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tempaku, Nagoya 468, Japan<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">(Revised received 25 July 1984)<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Key Word Index-Salvia<lb/> miltiorrhiza; Labiatae; pigment; diterpene; o-naphthaquinone; tanshindiol A; tanshindiol<lb/> B; tanshindiol C, nortanshinone; 3a-hydroxytanshinone<lb/> IIA.<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract-Five<lb/> new o-naphthaquinone diterpenes, tanshindiol A, tanshindiol B, tanshindiol C, nortanshinone and<lb/> 3a-hydroxytanshinone HA, have been isolated from the roots of Saluia miltiorrhiza as minor components. Their relative<lb/> stereochemistries have been established on the basis of spectral and chemical evidence.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">INTRODUCIION<lb/> &apos;Dan-Shen&apos;, the dried roots of Salvia miltiorrhiza Bunge, is<lb/> a clinically important Chinese drug in the treatment of<lb/> heart disease. Many chemists have studied the physiologi-<lb/>cally active constituents of this drug and have isolated<lb/> more than 16 orange-red crystalline pigments, abietanoids<lb/> [l, 2 and refs. therein]. Most abietanoids have either a<lb/> furano-ortho-naphthaquinone<lb/> or a furano-para-naphtha-<lb/>quinone skeleton and are classified biogenetically<lb/> as diterpenes. In the course of our search for physiologi-<lb/>cally active substances in Chinese drugs [3 and refs.<lb/> therein], we have isolated five new pigments, tanshindiol<lb/> A (l), tanshindiol B (2), tanshindiol C (3), nortanshinone<lb/> (4) and 3cr-hydroxytanshinone IIA (5), from Dan-Shen as<lb/> minor components. This paper describes the isolation and<lb/> characterization of these pigments.<lb/> Tanshindiols B (2) and C (3) had the same molecular<lb/> formula, ClsH160s (m/z 312 [Ml&apos;), and their spectral<lb/> data were quite similar to each other, indicating that they<lb/> must be stereoisomers. Thus, in addition to each tertiary<lb/> hydroxyl group, 2 had a secondary axial hydroxyl group<lb/> cS3.98 (lH, dd, J = 4.8, 2.9 Hz)] and 3 had a secondary<lb/> equatorial one cS3.96 (lH, dd, J = 4.0, 12 Hz)]. In fact,<lb/> oxidation of either 2 or 3 with sodium periodate gave the<lb/> same product (8). 8 had an acetophenone-type methyl<lb/> ketone moiety c62.61 (3H, s)] and a phenylpropion-<lb/>aldehyde moiety. The presence of the latter moiety<lb/> (Ar-CH&amp;H&amp;HO)<lb/> in 8 was established by the<lb/> &apos;H NMR spectrum with the aid of double resonance</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
