<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000738"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">FULL PAPER</note>	
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart><lb/> Novel Fluorescent Dyes by the Extension of the Core of<lb/> Perylenetetracarboxylic Bisimides<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Heinz Langhals*<lb/> [a] and Susanne Kirner<lb/>[a]<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="dedication">Dedicated to Prof. Dr. C. Rüchardt on the occasion of his 70th birthday<lb/></note>
	
	<keyword>Keywords: Fluorescent dyes / Perylenes / Heterocycles / NIR dyes<lb/></keyword>
	
	<div type="abstract"> Core-extended perylenetetracarboxylic bisimides were<lb/> were obtained with absorption regions from the visible to the<lb/> NIR. Applications for solar energy harvesting, and quantum<lb/> prepared by Diels–Alder reaction followed by reduction, or<lb/> by nitration followed by cyclisation. Highly fluorescent dyes<lb/> counters were suggested.</div>
	
	<div type="introduction"><lb/> Perylene dyes such as perylene-3,4:9,10-tetracarboxylic<lb/> bisimides 1, exhibit unusually good properties such as high<lb/> photostabilities and high fluorescence quantum yields.<lb/> [1]<lb/> The introduction of solubilizing groups such as tert-bu-<lb/>tylaryl [2] groups or long-chain sec-alkyl groups (&quot;swallow-<lb/>tail&quot; substituents<lb/> [3] ) render the dyes soluble in organic sol-<lb/>vents. The extension of the aromatic core of perylene is a<lb/> modern topic in chemistry; see for example ref.<lb/> [4] The reac-<lb/>tion of perylene itself to form benzperylenedicarbox-<lb/>imides [5] as well as the anellation of perylene-3,4-dicarbox-<lb/>imide with heterocycles has been studied in preceding pap-<lb/>ers.<lb/> [6] However, such extensions of 1 are unknown.<lb/> The DielsϪAlder reaction of perylene with maleic anhy-<lb/>dride proceeds easily<lb/> [1,7,8] so that a complete conversion is<lb/> obtained within 10 min at 190Ϫ200°C. The bisimide 1 is<lb/> less electron-rich than perylene and therefore less reactive<lb/> and gives insignificant yields in this reaction. However, a<lb/> [a]</div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institut für Organische Chemie der Universität München,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<div type="introduction">prolongation of the reaction time to 4 d, and a simul-<lb/></div>
	
	<address>Butenandtstraße 5-13 (Haus F), D-81377 München, Germany</address>
	
	<div type="introduction"><lb/> taneous aromatization with chloranil led to a yield of some<lb/></div>
	
	<phone>Fax: (internat. ) ϩ 49-(0)89/2180-7640<lb/></phone>

	<email>E-mail: Langhals@lrz.uni-muenchen.de<lb/></email>

	<div type="introduction">70% of the benzperylenebisimide anhydrides 2. This reac-<lb/></div>

	<reference>Eur. J. Org. Chem. 2000, 365Ϫ380<lb/></reference>
	
	<note type="copyright">© WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH, D-69451 Weinheim, 2000 w <lb/> 1434Ϫ193X/00/0102Ϫ365 $ 17.50ϩ.50/0<lb/> </note>
	
	<note type="page">365</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
