<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005386"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>JOURNAL OF VIROLOGY,<lb/></reference>

	<note>0022-538X/01/$04.00ϩ0 </note>
	
	<idno type="DOI">DOI: 10.1128/JVI.75.23.11534–11543.2001<lb/> </idno>
	
	<reference>Dec. 2001, p. 11534–11543<lb/> Vol. 75, No. 23<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2001, American Society for Microbiology. All Rights Reserved.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Unique Monoclonal Antibody Recognizing the Third Extracellular<lb/> Loop of CXCR4 Induces Lymphocyte Agglutination and<lb/> Enhances Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1-Mediated<lb/> Syncytium Formation and Productive Infection<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>REIKO TANAKA,<lb/> 1 ATSUSHI YOSHIDA,<lb/> 1 TSUTOMU MURAKAMI,<lb/> 1 EISHI BABA,<lb/> 1 JULLIANE LICHTENFELD,<lb/> 1<lb/> TAKERU OMORI,<lb/> 1 TOHRU KIMURA,<lb/> 2 NAOMI TSURUTANI,<lb/> 3 NOBUTAKA FUJII,<lb/> 4 ZI-XUAN WANG,<lb/> 5<lb/> STEPHEN C. PEIPER,<lb/> 5 NAOKI YAMAMOTO,<lb/> 3 AND YUETSU TANAKA<lb/> 1 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease and Immunology, Okinawa-Asia Research Center of Medical Science, Faculty of Medicine,<lb/> University of the Ryukyus,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Okinawa,<lb/> 1</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Molecular Cell Biology, Research Institute for Microbial Diseases,<lb/> Osaka University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Osaka,<lb/>2 </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Molecular Virology, Bio-Response, Graduate School, Tokyo Medical<lb/> and Dental University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tokyo,<lb/>3 and </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Graduate School of Pharmaceutical Science, Kyoto University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kyoto,<lb/>4<lb/> </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Japan, and Henry Vogt Cancer Research Institute, University of Louisville,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Louisville, Kentucky<lb/>5<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 8 May 2001/Accepted 28 August 2001<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">To increase insight into the structural basis of CXCR4 utilization in human immunodeficiency virus type 1<lb/> (HIV-1) infection, a new generation of three monoclonal antibodies (MAbs) was developed in WKA rats. The<lb/> A80 MAb, which binds an epitope in the third extracellular loop (ECL3) of CXCR4, has unique biologic<lb/> properties that provide novel insights into CXCR4 function. This agent enhanced syncytium formation in<lb/> activated human peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) infected with X4 or R5 and CEM cells infected<lb/> with X4 HIV-1 strains. Exposure to A80 increased the productive infection of activated CD4<lb/> ؉ T cells and CEM<lb/> cells with R5 and X4 viruses, respectively. This antibody uniquely induced agglutination of PBMC and CEM<lb/> cells but did not activate calcium mobilization. Agglutination induced by A80 was inhibited by stromal<lb/> cell-derived factor 1, T22, and phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate but was not significantly altered by pretreat-<lb/>ment of cells with pertussis toxin, wortmannin, or MAbs to LFA-1, ICAM-1, ICAM-2, and ICAM-3. The binding<lb/> of the A145 and A120 MAbs was mapped to the N-terminal extracellular domain and a conformational epitope<lb/> involving ECL1 and ECL2, respectively. Both of these MAbs inhibited HIV-1 infection and lacked the novel<lb/> properties of A80. These results suggest a new role for CXCR4 in homologous lymphocyte adhesion that is<lb/> ligand independent and in HIV-1 infection.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">Human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) infects tar-<lb/>get cells through sequential binding of the gp120 subunit of<lb/> envelope glycoprotein with cellular receptors. Binding to the<lb/> primary receptor, CD4 (26, 47, 50, 51), induces a gp120 con-<lb/>formation that is permissive for interaction with a coreceptor,<lb/> which is required for envelope-mediated fusion (3, 7, 21, 28,<lb/> 30, 32, 35). CCR5 is the front line coreceptor for commonly<lb/> transmitted forms of HIV-1 and CXCR4 serves this role for<lb/> T-cell-tropic (T-tropic) strains that evolve late in the course of<lb/> infection (22, 24, 28, 29, 60, 70). CCR5 and CXCR4 belong to<lb/> the chemokine receptor family, which transmit signals through<lb/> heterotrimeric G proteins (3, 8, 7, 35). T-tropic HIV-1, desig-<lb/>nated X4 strains based on the functional relationship with<lb/> CXCR4, has been suggested to be more virulent than R5 or<lb/> macrophage-tropic strains (7, 9, 23), possibly due to the wider<lb/> spectrum of target cells that express CXCR4 (13).<lb/> The exclusive ligand of CXCR4 is stromal cell-derived factor<lb/> 1 (SDF-1), a member of the family of chemo-attractant cyto-<lb/>kines (54, 56). This chemokine has been demonstrated to play<lb/> a critical role during embryologic development in the homing</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
