<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005061"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Seminars in Immunology 18 (2006) 261–262<lb/></reference>

			<note type="other">Editorial<lb/></note>
			<docTitle><titlePart>Travelling with the BAFF/BLyS family: Are we there yet?<lb/></titlePart></docTitle>
			<note type="other">
				The development, maturation and activation of B-<lb/> lymphocytes is a
				perilous odyssey, starting in the bone marrow<lb/> and finishing in the peripheral
				lymphoid organs. This journey is<lb/> characterised by a constant struggle for
				survival and a need to<lb/> "clear" multiple checkpoints that neutralise potentially
				harmful<lb/> self-reactive B cells and selectively favour useful clonotypes.<lb/>
				Until recently, B cell receptor (BCR) specificity was considered<lb/> the prime, if
				not sole, determinant of survival among developing<lb/> and primary B cells.
				However, characterisation of the TNF-<lb/> like ligand BAFF/BLyS has fundamentally
				changed this notion.<lb/> BAFF is now appreciated as central to the survival of
				peripheral<lb/> B cells, since without it neither the maturation nor survival of
				pri-<lb/> mary B cells is possible. Moreover, BAFF over-expression leads<lb/> to the
				development of autoimmune disorders, and elevated BAFF<lb/> levels are associated
				with autoimmune diseases such as Systemic<lb/> Lupus Erythematosus, rheumatoid
				arthritis and Sjögren's syn-<lb/> drome. As a result, BAFF and its corresponding
				receptors have<lb/> become major targets in the development of therapeutics for<lb/>
				these diseases, and several promising reagents are presently in<lb/> clinical
				trials.<lb/> Despite the broad conceptual and clinical importance already<lb/>
				evident, readers of this Seminars in Immunology volume will<lb/> learn that the BAFF
				saga is still far from complete. Numer-<lb/> ous exciting new concepts and functions
				are emerging, and<lb/> intriguing mysteries remain to be solved. This assembly of
				con-<lb/> tributions provides the latest views and ideas of many experts,<lb/> and
				will hopefully serve as the basis for future work on BAFF<lb/> and related
				molecules.<lb/> BAFF mediates survival signals via its receptor (BAFF-R,<lb/> BR3)
				but also binds to two other receptors, TACI and BCMA,<lb/> which are shared with
				another TNF-related ligand, APRIL.<lb/> Bossen and Schneider refine this picture
				with the characteri-<lb/> sation of a splice variant of BAFF that, when combined
				with<lb/> full-length BAFF subunits, can create inactive heterotrimeric<lb/>
				ligands, perhaps serving as negative regulators. They also<lb/> find that APRIL can
				be expressed as a shorter variant that<lb/> weakly binds BAFF-R. Finally, APRIL
				interacts with proteo-<lb/> glycan structures expressed on T cells and non-lymphoid
				cells.<lb/> Clearly, our knowledge of the ligand/receptor relationships in<lb/> this
				system is far from complete and future additional find-<lb/> ings are likely to
				color interpretations of observed biological<lb/> effects.<lb/> Since BAFF
				over-expression is linked to B cell-mediated<lb/> autoimmunity, considerable effort
				has focused on how BAFF<lb/> corrupts B cell tolerance. Robert Brink provides his
				views on<lb/> this important question, based on data obtained using the pow-<lb/>
				erful anti-hen egg lysozyme (HEL) BCR transgenic systems.<lb/> This work showed that
				excessive BAFF production would not<lb/> prevent elimination of high-affinity
				self-reactive B cells, pre-<lb/> sumably because they are deleted prior to
				expression of suf-<lb/> ficient BAFF-R. In contrast, low-affinity self-reactive B
				cells<lb/> that fail transitional differentiation at normal physiologic BAFF<lb/>
				levels, benefit from excessive BAFF and accumulate. Thus,<lb/> whether the rescue of
				weakly self-reactive B cells via such<lb/> mechanisms drives autoimmune etiology is
				a key remaining<lb/> question.<lb/> BAFF and APRIL may also influence T cell
				functions. In<lb/> their contribution, Mackay and Leung combine their findings<lb/>
				with those of others, showing direct and indirect effects of BAFF<lb/> on the makeup
				of the T cell compartment and T cell functions.<lb/> Excess BAFF induces changes of
				the B cell compartment, which<lb/> in turn increase the number of effector T cells,
				possibly via the<lb/> antigen-presenting cell (APC) function of B cells,
				particularly<lb/> marginal zone (MZ) B cells. Thus, BAFF-mediated autoimmune<lb/>
				disorders may reflect combined pathogenic effects involving<lb/> both B and T cells.
				This section also highlights a possible role for<lb/> BAFF as a negative regulator
				of T cell activation in some inflam-<lb/> matory settings and the expression of
				BAFF-R on regulatory T<lb/> cells.<lb/> While the function of BAFF-R as a survival
				receptor is now<lb/> well characterised, functions through TACI and BCMA are
				not<lb/> fully understood, an aspect complicated by the fact that both<lb/> BAFF and
				APRIL can activate these receptors. In her contribu-<lb/> tion, Susan Kalled
				describes BAFF/APRIL-mediated functions<lb/> which are BAFF-R-independent, such as
				BAFF-mediated up-<lb/> regulation of CD23 and CD21 on B cells, maturation of
				follicular<lb/> dendritic cells in germinal centers (GCs), isotype switching
				and<lb/> plasma cell survival, the latter possibly relying on APRIL bind-<lb/> ing
				to BCMA.<lb/> In a similar vein, the Cancro laboratory (Treml/Crowley)<lb/> presents
				data suggesting that the spectrum of BLyS receptors<lb/> expressed among antigen
				activated B cells is characteristic of<lb/> their likely differentiative fate. In
				general, AFC differentia-<lb/> tion is associated with marked TACI up-regulation,
				whereas<lb/>
			</note>
			<note type="other">1044-5323/$ – see front matter </note> 
			<note type="copyright">© 2006 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>
			<idno>doi:10.1016/j.smim.2006.07.003</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
