<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004246"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Use of Wireless Data Loggers for Temperature Uniformity Studies<lb/> in an ISO 17025 Accreditation Program<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>John J. Sullivan<lb/> 1 ; Mohammad H. Samimi<lb/> 2 ; Thanh-Thu Huynh<lb/> 2, Cathy Burns<lb/> 3 ; Mike Hough<lb/> 3<lb/> ; Kevin Kallander<lb/> 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Validation of controlled temperature equipment (incubators,<lb/> autoclaves, water baths, ovens, refrigerators, and freezers) is an<lb/> important part of an ISO 17025 accreditation program, involving<lb/> temperature and/or humidity testing for uniformity and stability. For<lb/> temperature, many validation studies are performed using wired,<lb/> thermocouple-based systems. Setting up a wired system is time-<lb/>consuming and tedious, and thermocouples are prone to failure,<lb/> causing difficulty in interpreting results. An alternative to wired<lb/> systems are wireless data loggers which are small, self-contained,<lb/> measurement and recording devices that eliminate the disadvantages<lb/> of the wired systems.<lb/> The objectives of this study were to demonstrate the utility of wireless<lb/> data loggers in temperature uniformity studies of incubators and<lb/> autoclaves and to develop guidelines in terms of logger placement,<lb/> testing variables (such as chamber loading), and acceptance criteria.<lb/> Data loggers were placed throughout the chamber to be measured,<lb/> either by themselves for empty chamber validation, or with other<lb/> materials for loaded chamber validation. Generally, ten or more<lb/> loggers were placed in pre-determined patterns in the chamber and<lb/> data taken for 16-48 hours. After the end of the measurement period,<lb/> the data were transferred to a PC for analysis.<lb/> As a result of the studies, it was determined that certain equipment<lb/> had to be taken out of service because it did not meet the +/-2<lb/> o C<lb/> uniformity criteria (e.g., 2 of the 17 incubators in one lab). Certain<lb/> equipment was determined to be malfunctioning, since room<lb/> temperature variations dramatically affected their interior<lb/> temperatures. Additionally, guidelines were developed on loading of<lb/> incubators and autoclaves, based on temperature measurements in<lb/> loaded chambers.<lb/> From this work, it is clear that wireless data loggers can be used to<lb/> easily and rapidly perform temperature studies on a variety of<lb/> laboratory equipment as an integral part of a lab&apos;s ISO 17025<lb/> accreditation program.<lb/> Affiliations:<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Mesa Laboratories,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Lakewood, CO;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 U.S. Food and<lb/> Drug Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Alameda, CA;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> U.S. Food and Drug<lb/> Administration,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Denver, CO;<lb/></address>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
