<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005194"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>The Journal of China<lb/>
			Universities of Posts and<lb/>
			Telecommunications<lb/> August 2010, 17(4): 94–99<lb/></reference>
			<ptr type="web">www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/10058885</ptr>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<ptr type="web">http://www.jcupt.com<lb/></ptr>
			

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Energy-balanced unequal clustering protocol for<lb/>
					wireless sensor networks<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>JIANG Chang-jiang 1 (&#x6ef59;), SHI Wei-ren 1 , XIANG min 2 , TANG Xian-lun
					2<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1. College of Automation, Chongqing University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Chongqing 400044, China<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2. College of Automation, Chongqing University of Posts and
					Telecommunications,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Chongqing 400065, China<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Clustering provides an effective way to prolong the
				lifetime of wireless sensor networks. One of the major issues of a clustering<lb/>
				protocol is selecting an optimal group of sensor nodes as the cluster heads to
				divide the network. Another is the mode of<lb/> inter-cluster communication. In this
				paper, an energy-balanced unequal clustering (EBUC) protocol is proposed and
				evaluated. By<lb/> using the particle swarm optimization (PSO) algorithm, EBUC
				partitions all nodes into clusters of unequal size, in which the<lb/> clusters
				closer to the base station have smaller size. The cluster heads of these clusters
				can preserve some more energy for the<lb/> inter-cluster relay traffic and the
				'hot-spots' problem can be avoided. For inter-cluster communication, EBUC adopts
				an<lb/> energy-aware multihop routing to reduce the energy consumption of the
				cluster heads. Simulation results demonstrate that the<lb/> protocol can efficiently
				decrease the dead speed of the nodes and prolong the network lifetime.<lb/></div>

			<keywords>Keywords wireless sensor networks, clustering protocol, PSO algorithm, multihop
				routing<lb/></keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
