<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007171"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>URI research on self-healing concrete yields cost-effective<lb/> system to extend life of structures<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="other">Media Contact: Todd McLeish, 401-874-7892<lb/> KINGSTON, R.I. – </note>
	
	<date>May 25, 2010 –</date>

	<div type="abstract">Efforts to extend the<lb/> life of structures and reduce repair costs have led<lb/> engineers to develop &quot;smart materials&quot; that have<lb/> self-healing properties, but many of these new materials<lb/> are difficult to commercialize. A new self-healing<lb/> concrete developed and tested by a graduate student at<lb/> the University of Rhode Island, however, may prove to<lb/> be cost-effective.<lb/> Michelle Pelletier, a URI master&apos;s degree candidate,<lb/> embedded a microencapsulated sodium silicate healing<lb/> agent directly into a concrete matrix. When tiny stress<lb/> cracks begin to form in the concrete, the capsules<lb/> rupture and release the healing agent into the adjacent areas.<lb/> The sodium silicate reacts with the calcium hydroxide naturally present in the concrete to form a<lb/> calcium-silica-hydrate product to heal the cracks and block the pores in the concrete. The chemical<lb/> reaction creates a gel-like material that hardens in about one week. &quot;Smart materials usually have an environmental trigger that causes the healing to occur,&quot; explained<lb/> Pelletier, who is collaborating on the project with URI Chemical Engineering Professor Arijit Bose.<lb/> &quot;What&apos;s special about our material is that it can have a localized and targeted release of the<lb/> healing agent only in the areas that really need it.&quot;<lb/> In tests comparing a standard concrete mix to concrete containing two percent sodium silicate<lb/> healing agent, Pelletier&apos;s healing mix recovered 26 percent of its original strength (after being<lb/> stressed to near breaking) versus just 10 percent recovery by the standard mix. The URI student<lb/> said that an increase in the quantity of healing agent would likely further improve the recovered<lb/> strength of the concrete.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
