<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007799"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Two-dimensional correlation analysis<lb/></note>

	<note type="page">1<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Two-dimensional correlation analysis<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">Two dimensional correlation analysis is a mathematical technique that is used to study changes in measured<lb/> signals. As mostly spectroscopic signals are discussed, sometime also two dimensional correlation spectroscopy is<lb/> used and refers to the same technique.<lb/> In 2D correlation analysis, a sample is subjected to an external perturbation while all other parameters of the system<lb/> are kept at the same value. This perturbation can be a systematic and controlled change in temperature, pressure, pH,<lb/> chemical composition of the system, or even time after a catalyst was added to a chemical mixture. As a result of the<lb/> controlled change (the perturbation), the system will undergo variations which are measured by an chemical or<lb/> physical detection method. The measured signals or spectra will shown systematic variations that are processed with<lb/> 2D correlation analysis for interpretation.<lb/> When one considers spectra that consist of few bands, it is quite obvious to determine which bands are subject to a<lb/> changing intensity. Such a changing intensity can be caused for example by chemical reactions. However, the<lb/> interpretation of the measured signal becomes more tricky when spectra are complex and bands are heavily<lb/> overlapping. Two dimensional correlation analysis allows one to determine at which positions in such a measured<lb/> signal there is a systematic change in a peak, either continuous rising or drop in intensity. 2D correlation analysis<lb/> results in two complementary signals, which referred to as the 2D synchronous and 2D asynchronous spectrum.<lb/> These signals allow amongst others<lb/> [1] [2] [3]<lb/> 1. to determine the events that are occurring at the same time (in phase) and those events that are occurring at<lb/> different times (out of phase)<lb/> 2. to determine the sequence of spectral changes<lb/> 3. to identify various inter-and intramolecular interactions<lb/> 4. band assignments of reacting groups<lb/> 5. to detect correlations between spectra of different techniques, for example near infrared spectroscopy (NIR) and<lb/> Raman spectroscopy<lb/> History<lb/> 2D correlation analysis originated from 2D NMR spectroscopy. Isao Noda developed perturbation based 2D<lb/> spectroscopy in the 1980&apos;s.<lb/> [4] This technique required sinusoidal perturbations to the chemical system under<lb/> investigation. This specific type of the applied perturbation severely limited its possible applications. Following<lb/> research done by several groups of scientists, perturbation based 2D spectroscopy could be developed to a more<lb/> extended and generalized broader base. Since the development of generalized 2D correlation analysis in 1993 based<lb/> on Fourier transformation of the data, 2D correlation analysis gained widespread use. Alternative techniques that<lb/> were simpler to calculate, for example the disrelation spectrum, were also developed simultaneously. Because of its<lb/> computational efficiency and simplicity, the Hilbert transform is nowadays used for the calculation of the 2D<lb/> spectra. To date, 2D correlation analysis is not only used for the interpretation of many types of spectroscopic data<lb/> (including XRF, UV/VIS spectroscopy, fluorescence, infrared, and Raman spectra), although its application is not<lb/> limited to spectroscopy.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
