<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007305"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">SimBuild 2010<lb/> Fourth National Conference of IBPSA-USA<lb/> New York City, New York<lb/></note>

	<date>August 11 – 13, 2010<lb/></date>

	<note type="page">474<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>MODEL-BASED THERMAL LOAD ESTIMATION IN BUILDINGS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Zheng O&apos;Neill, Satish Narayanan, and Rohini Brahme<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>United Technologies Research Center<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>East Hartford, CT 06108, USA<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT Understanding and optimizing the energy performance<lb/> of a building requires insights into the dynamics of<lb/> thermal loads at a variety of spatial scales within the<lb/> building. When available, sensors within the terminal<lb/> units and indoor environment can provide useful<lb/> information, but they can be grossly inaccurate when<lb/> estimating loads over extended periods of time.<lb/> Increasing the number of sensors or including more<lb/> accurate sensors will help, but would increase the<lb/> system complexity and lifecycle cost. The use of<lb/> physics-based thermal balance models with measured<lb/> data can provide more robust and accurate estimates of<lb/> the loads. In this paper, a model-based approach is<lb/> used to estimate zonal loads in a medium-sized<lb/> commercial building and verified with measurements.<lb/> INTRODUCTION Model-based estimation approaches (Goodwin and Sin<lb/> 1984, Dougherty and Astola 1999, Tanizaki 1996)<lb/> have been widely applied in a variety of complex<lb/> dynamical systems encountered in aerospace and<lb/> process control applications. Model-based estimation is<lb/> used here to provide real-time information about<lb/> internal loads within a building that affects energy<lb/> performance. The proposed estimation technique is<lb/> built upon a reduced-order thermal network model and<lb/> real-time data including temperatures and airflow rates<lb/> from the Building Management System (BMS),<lb/> considering uncertainties from sensor data and the<lb/> model. A subset of real-time weather data is also<lb/> incorporated into the estimation procedure. An<lb/> Extended Kalman Filter (EKF) is used to estimate<lb/> unmeasured states<lb/> including room<lb/> surface temperatures. The real-time load estimation will<lb/> facilitate the understanding of building usage (i.e.,<lb/> occupancy, plug loads, lighting loads and process<lb/> loads), and provide real-time load information where<lb/> measurements are not available or are highly uncertain.<lb/> The estimated load can also be used as inputs to<lb/> diagnostic tools and to whole building simulation<lb/> programs such as EnergyPlus (DOE 2010) and eQuest<lb/> (eQuest 2010) as refinements to the input load profile.<lb/> This work focuses on the Classroom and Office<lb/> Building (COB) at University of California at Merced<lb/> Campus (UC Merced). Figure 1 shows the second<lb/> floor plan in COB. This floor contains both offices and<lb/> classrooms.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
