<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005132"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>On a IEEE 802.15.4/ZigBee to IEEE 802.11 Gateway for the ART-WiSe<lb/>
					Architecture<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>João LEAL 1 , André CUNHA 2 , Mário ALVES 2 , Anis KOUBÂA
					2,3<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 <note type="other">Undergraduate Student,</note> Polytechnic Institute of Porto, School of
					Engineering (ISEP/IPP), </affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Porto, Portugal<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 IPP-HURRAY! Research Group, Polytechnic Institute of Porto, School of
					Engineering (ISEP/IPP),</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Porto, Portugal<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>3 Al-Imam Muhammad Ibn Saud University, Computer Science
					Dept.,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>11681 Riyadh, Saudi Arabia<lb/></address>

			<email>{1010609, arec, mjf}@isep.ipp.pt, akoubaa@dei.isep.ipp.pt<lb/></email>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract. Wireless Sensor Networks (WSN) have been<lb/> attracting
				growing interests for developing a new generation of<lb/> large-scale embedded
				computing systems, with a great potential<lb/> for a wide range of applications such
				as surveillance,<lb/> environmental monitoring, emergency medical response or<lb/>
				building automation. However, the communication paradigms in<lb/> wireless sensor
				networks differ from the ones associated to<lb/> traditional wireless networks,
				triggering the need for new<lb/> communication protocols and architectures. The
				ART-WiSe<lb/> (Architecture for Real-Time communications in Wireless Sensor<lb/>
				Networks) framework aims at the design of a scalable multiple-<lb/> tiered WSN
				architecture for supporting large-scale embedded<lb/> computing applications with
				critical requirements. An overlay<lb/> Wireless Local Area Network (Tier-2) serves
				as a backbone for<lb/> a WSN (Tier 1), relying on existing standard
				communication<lb/> protocols and commercial-off-the-shell (COTS) technologies –<lb/>
				IEEE 802.15.4/ZigBee for Tier 1 and IEEE 802.11 for Tier-2.<lb/> This paper outlines
				ongoing work on the design of the<lb/> architectural requirements and features for a
				QoS-aware<lb/> gateway between both networks.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
