<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001306"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A Markovian Signature-Based Approach<lb/> to IP Traffic Classification<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hamza Dahmouni<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>ENST Bretagne<lb/> Department of computer Science<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Brest, France<lb/></address>

	<email>hamza.dahmouni@enst-<lb/>bretagne.fr<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sandrine Vaton<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>ENST Bretagne<lb/> Department of computer Science<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Brest, France<lb/></address>

	<email>sandrine.vaton@enst-<lb/>bretagne.fr<lb/></email>


	<docAuthor>David Rossé<lb/></docAuthor>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>France Telecom<lb/>Research and Development<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Belfort, France<lb/></address>

	<email>david.rosse@orange-<lb/>ftgroup.com<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> In this paper we present a real-time automatic process to traffic<lb/> classification and to the detection of abnormal behaviors in IP<lb/> traffic. The proposed method aims to detect anomalies in the traffic<lb/> associated to a particular service, or to automatically recognize the<lb/> service associated to a given sequence of packets at the transport<lb/> layer. Service classification is becoming a central issue because of<lb/> the emergence of new services (P2P, VoIP, Streaming video, etc…)<lb/> which raises new challenges in resource reservation, pricing,<lb/> network monitoring, etc… In order to identify a specific signature to<lb/> an application, we first of all model the sequence of its packets at<lb/> the transport layer by means of a first order Markov chain. Then, we<lb/> decide which service should be associated to any new sequence by<lb/> means of standard decision techniques (Maximum Likelihood<lb/> criterion, Neyman-Pearson test). The evaluation of our automatic<lb/> recognition procedure using live GPRS Orange France traffic traces<lb/> demonstrates the feasibility and the excellent performance of this<lb/> approach.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Categories and Subject Descriptors<lb/> C.2.3 [Computer Communications Networks]: Network<lb/> Operations --Network Management, Network Monitoring.<lb/> General Terms<lb/> Reliability, Security, Management.<lb/> Keywords<lb/> Traffic Classification, Service Recognition, Network Monitoring,<lb/> Markov Chain, Neyman-Pearson, Maximum Likelihood.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
