<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55008620"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of Food and Drug Analysis, Vol. 15, No. 3, 2007, Pages 325-331<lb/></reference>

	<note type="page">325<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="other">藥物食品分析　第十五卷　第三期<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A Study on the Analytical Methods for Total Dietary<lb/> Fiber in Fructan-Containing Foods<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SHU-CHI TSAI, SHU-FANG LU, WEN-WEN YU, HSIAO-CHEN LIN AND WEIGUANG FU*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Analysis Research and Service Center, Food Industry Research &amp; Development Institute,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hsinchu, Taiwan, R.O.C.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">(Received: January 18, 2007, Accepted: July 24, 2007)<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> The fructans, inulin and oligofructose, were known to possess many of the physiologic properties of dietary fiber (DF).<lb/> However, they were not listed as DF on labels of foods that contained them, because they cannot be completely recovered by the<lb/> precipitate of AOAC enzymatic-gravimetric method. The main goal of this study was therefore to develop a quantitative method<lb/> for total DF in fructan-containing foods. Evaluation was carefully done by combining AOAC 985.29 DF method and AOAC<lb/> 999.03 fructans method. In addition to three commercial fructan products, asparagus and tea drink samples were selected and<lb/> spiked with fructans to carry out the method validation. The results were all in excellent agreement with the expected values.<lb/> Also, associated precision and measurement uncertainties were evaluated as well. Recoveries by the proposed method ranged<lb/> from 97.02% to 101.35%, with coefficients of variation (CVs) of 0.63~1.17%. Total DF content was more accurate for combined<lb/> method than either from AOAC 985.29 only or the sum of determining values from AOAC 985.29 plus AOAC 999.03.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key words: fructans, inulin, fructo-oligosaccharides, dietary fiber, analytical method<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
