<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000031-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Protein Engineering, Design &amp; Selection vol. 23 no. 4 pp. 229– 241,
				2010<lb/></reference>
			<date>Published online November 27, 2009</date>
			<idno>doi:10.1093/protein/gzp074<lb/></idno>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Knowledge-based design of reagentless fluorescent<lb/> biosensors from a
					designed ankyrin repeat protein<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Elodie Brient-Litzler 1 , Andreas Plü ckthun 2<lb/> and Hugues Bedouelle
					1,3<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 Unit of Molecular Prevention and Therapy of Human Diseases (CNRS<lb/>
					URA3012), Institut Pasteur,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>25 rue Docteur Roux, 75724 Paris Cedex 15,<lb/> France </address>

			<note type="other">and</note>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 Biochemisches Institut, Universität Zürich,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Winterthurerstr. 190,<lb/> 8057 Zürich, Switzerland<lb/></address>


			<note type="other">3 To whom correspondence should be addressed.<lb/></note>

			<email>E-mail: hugues.bedouelle@pasteur.fr<lb/></email>

			<note type="submission">Received October 21, 2009; revised October 21, 2009;<lb/>
				accepted October 27, 2009<lb/></note>

			<reference>Edited by Andrew Bradbury<lb/></reference>

			<div type="abstract">Designed ankyrin repeat proteins (DARPins) can be<lb/> selected
				from combinatorial libraries to bind any target<lb/> antigen. They show high levels
				of recombinant expression,<lb/> solubility and stability, and contain no cysteine
				residue.<lb/> The possibility of obtaining, from any DARPin and at<lb/> high yields,
				fluorescent conjugates which respond to the<lb/> binding of the antigen by a
				variation of fluorescence,<lb/> would have numerous applications in micro-and
				nano-<lb/>analytical sciences. This possibility was explored with<lb/> Off7, a
				DARPin directed against the maltose binding<lb/> protein (MalE) from Escherichia
				coli, with known crystal<lb/> structure of the complex. Eight residues of Off7,
				whose<lb/> solvent accessible surface area varies on association with<lb/> the
				antigen but which are not in direct contact with the<lb/> antigen, were individually
				mutated into cysteine and then<lb/> chemically coupled with a fluorophore. The
				conjugates<lb/> were ranked according to their relative sensitivities. All of<lb/>
				them showed an increase in their fluorescence intensity<lb/> on antigen binding by
				>1.7-fold. The best conjugate<lb/> retained the same affinity as the parental
				DARPin. Its<lb/> signal increased linearly and specifically with the
				concen-<lb/>tration of antigen, up to 15-fold in buffer and 3-fold in<lb/> serum
				when fully saturated, the difference being mainly<lb/> due to the absorption of
				light by serum. Its lower limit of<lb/> detection was equal to 0.3 nM with a
				standard spectro-<lb/>fluorometer. Titrations with potassium iodide indicated<lb/>
				that the fluorescence variation was due to a shielding of<lb/> the fluorescent group
				from the solvent by the antigen.<lb/> These results suggest rules for the design of
				reagentless<lb/> fluorescent biosensors from any DARPin.<lb/></div>
			<keywords>Keywords: ankyrin repeat protein (DARPin)/antibody/<lb/>
				biosensor/fluorescence/protein design<lb/></keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
