<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006979"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">1<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="other">LTC1775<lb/> DESCRIPTIO U<lb/> FEATURES<lb/> APPLICATIO S<lb/> U<lb/> TYPICAL APPLICATION<lb/> U<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>High Power<lb/> No R SENSE<lb/> TM<lb/> Current Mode<lb/> Synchronous Step-Down<lb/> Switching Regulator<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<div type="abstract">s Highest Efficiency Current Mode Controller<lb/> s No Sense Resistor Required<lb/> s 300mV Maximum Current Sense Voltage<lb/> s Stable High Current Operation<lb/> s Dual N-Channel MOSFET Synchronous Drive<lb/> s Wide V IN Range: 4V to 36V<lb/> s Wide V OUT Range: 1.19V to V IN<lb/> s ±1% 1.19V Reference<lb/> s Programmable Fixed Frequency with Injection Lock<lb/> s Very Low Drop Out Operation: 99% Duty Cycle<lb/> s Forced Continuous Mode Control Pin<lb/> s Optional Programmable Soft Start<lb/> s Pin Selectable Output Voltage<lb/> s Foldback Current Limit<lb/> s Output Overvoltage Protection<lb/> s Logic Controlled Micropower Shutdown: I Q &lt; 30µA<lb/> s Available in 16-Lead Narrow SSOP and SO Packages<lb/>	The LTC<lb/> ® 1775 is a synchronous step-down switching<lb/> regulator controller that drives external N-channel power<lb/> MOSFETs using few external components. Current mode<lb/> control with MOSFET V DS sensing eliminates the need for<lb/> a sense resistor and improves efficiency. Largely similar<lb/> to the LTC1625, the LTC1775 has twice the maximum<lb/> sense voltage for high current applications. The frequency<lb/> of a nominal 150kHz internal oscillator can be synchro-<lb/>nized to an external clock over a 1.5:1 frequency range.<lb/> Burst Mode<lb/> TM operation at low load currents reduces<lb/> switching losses and low dropout operation extends oper-<lb/>ating time in battery-powered systems. A forced continu-<lb/>ous mode control pin can assist secondary winding<lb/> regulation by disabling Burst Mode operation when the<lb/> main output is lightly loaded.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
