<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001478"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Home -Learn -Shop -Bands -Forums -Search -Contact Us<lb/>Login:<lb/> +<lb/> Username:<lb/> Password:<lb/> Remember Login<lb/> Login<lb/> New user? Register<lb/> (it&apos;s free!)<lb/> Forgot password?<lb/>Home:<lb/> +<lb/> Thereminworld News<lb/> Message Forums<lb/> Member Map<lb/> Privacy Policy<lb/> About ThereminWorld<lb/> Link to us<lb/> Contact Us<lb/>Getting Started:<lb/> +<lb/> What&apos;s a Theremin?<lb/> FA Q Page<lb/> Guide to Buying a Theremin<lb/> Theremin Gallery<lb/> Learn To Play<lb/>Shop:<lb/> +<lb/> Theremins &amp; Kits<lb/> Theremin Coupons<lb/> Accessories Auctions<lb/> Books CDs &amp; Recordings<lb/> Effects Logo Gear<lb/> Movies<lb/>Learn:<lb/> +<lb/> What&apos;s a theremin?<lb/> Theremin FA Q<lb/> Articles Audio Samples<lb/> Bands with theremins<lb/> Events and Concerts<lb/> History Learn to play<lb/> Monthly Contest<lb/> Notable Thereminists<lb/> Photo Gallery<lb/> Publications RCA Theremins<lb/> Repertoire Schematics<lb/> Software Theremin Gallery<lb/> Theremin in Film<lb/> Theremin Videos<lb/>More:<lb/> +<lb/> Other Theremin Resources<lb/> Spellbound Radio<lb/> ThereminWorld Search<lb/>Home -Forums -Theremin Construction<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Topic: ther-force one...NEW DUAL THEREMIN</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="introduction"><lb/> Showing Posts 1 -10 of 14<lb/> Go to page: 1, 2, Next<lb/> Author Message<lb/> BlackEdition<lb/> Joined: Oct 2008<lb/> 12/3/2008 4:27:58 PM<lb/> i am a drummer and got a crazy idea to incorporate two<lb/> theremins into my drumset. i have put two art harrison<lb/> theremins in a small enclosure.<lb/> i would like to get some advice on antennas, however. i am<lb/> running a two to three foot wire from the antenna solder hole<lb/> on the circuit board. the wire is insulated but not shielded. i<lb/> can&apos;t get an antenna working. the wire does act as an<lb/> antenna, but, i would like to have a metal disc or plate<lb/> antenna like suggested by art harrison.<lb/> any ideas as to how i can get this working? i think that i<lb/> would like to use pie plates as the antenna...<lb/> BlackEdition<lb/> Joined: Oct 2008<lb/> 12/3/2008 5:41:56 PM<lb/> just another quick question.<lb/> i have read on art harrison&apos;s website that the antenna lead<lb/> should be 8 inches or shorter. do you think that there is<lb/> anyway to increase the distance between the antenna and<lb/> the antenna lead without losing sensitivity?<lb/> thanks!<lb/> GordonC<lb/> From: Croxley<lb/> Green,<lb/> Hertfordshire, UK<lb/> Joined: Oct 2005<lb/> 12/3/2008 6:49:50 PM<lb/> i have put two art harrison theremins in a small enclosure.<lb/> I can&apos;t help you with the antennas, but I can mention that<lb/> putting two theremins operating on the same frequencies<lb/> close to one another will change their behaviour. Whether it<lb/> will cause them stop working entirely or become erratic and<lb/> unpredictable, as it does with etherwaves, I cannot predict.<lb/> I think better to have two separate instruments with integral<lb/> antennas than a conjoined pair with remote antennas.<lb/> Mmm. Pie.<lb/> djpb_designs<lb/> From: Escondido,<lb/> CA Joined: Feb 2008<lb/> 12/4/2008 3:53:34 PM<lb/> Ok, I am at a loss as to what you want to do with those 2<lb/> theremins. Playing theremin requires a steady hand and very<lb/> slight finger movements ... a far cry from the motion of drum<lb/> rolls and high-hat hits!<lb/> If you want to use hits on the toms to trigger sounds, you<lb/> would have more luck adapting triggers from electronic drum<lb/> kits. They are ready-made for this purpose.<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">Theremin World<lb/></note>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.thereminworld.com /forum.asp?cmd=p&amp;T=3671&amp;F=3<lb/> </ptr>

	<note type="other">1 of 3<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">28-06-2011 09:53</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
