<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005186"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<docTitle>
				<lb/>
				<titlePart> An Energy-efficient Load-balanceable Multipath Routing Algorithm Based
					on AHP<lb/> for Wireless Sensor Networks<lb/>
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Wang Min, Li Shining<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>Department of Computer Science<lb/> Northwestern Polytechnical
					University<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Xi 'an, China<lb/></address>
			<email>wangmin_nwpu@163.com<lb/></email>

			<div type="abstract"> Abstract-As a key design criterion for the routing protocols
				in<lb/> wireless sensor network, energy consumption is an important<lb/> factor
				which affects network lifetime. Some of the conventional<lb/> routing schemes may
				not be optimal to maximize the network<lb/> lifetime. In this paper, we propose a
				multipath routing<lb/> algorithm (MRA-AHP) with flexible application relativity
				on<lb/> the basis of Directed Diffusion. The algorithm establishes<lb/> multiple
				paths from the source node to the destination node.<lb/> According to the residual
				energy of the neighbor node, the<lb/> transmission delay and bandwidth of the link
				to that neighbor,<lb/> each neighbor node can be given a selection weight for the
				next<lb/> relay node selection, which makes multiple paths of better<lb/>
				performance. We also propose a load balancing scheme to<lb/> distribute the traffic
				over the multiple paths discovered. Both<lb/> the next hop selection algorithm and
				load balancing scheme<lb/> apply Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP).At last, we
				simulate<lb/> our multipath routing scheme on the NS2, and compare it with<lb/> DD
				and HREEMR routing algorithms. The simulation results<lb/> indicate that our
				proposed routing algorithm effectively<lb/> extends network lifetime and has a good
				performance on node<lb/> average energy consumption and average transmission
				delay.<lb/>
			</div>
			<keywords> Keywords- Sensor network; multipath routing; lifetime; AHP;<lb/> load
				balancing<lb/>
			</keywords>
			<note type="other">978-1-4244-6585-9/10/$26.00</note>
			<note type="copyright">©2010 IEEE<lb/></note>


		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
