<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004335"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Soluble fms-like tyrosine kinase 1 and Human placental growth factor: New &quot;troponins&quot; for cardiac-surgery-associated acute kidney injury?<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jan Runte<lb/> 1<lb/> ; Nicola Gatz<lb/> 1<lb/> , Anna Beilharz<lb/> 1<lb/> , Daniel Holz<lb/> 1<lb/> , Hermann Heinze<lb/> 1<lb/> , Klaus-Ulrich<lb/> Berger<lb/> 1<lb/> , Thorsten Hanke<lb/> 2<lb/> , Hauke Paarmann<lb/> 1<lb/> , Julika Schön<lb/> 1<lb/> , Matthias Heringlake<lb/> 1<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Departments of Anesthesiology (1) and Thoracic Vascular and Cardiac Surgery (2),<lb/> University of Luebeck,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Luebeck, Germany.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Objective: Early diagnosis of cardiac-surgery-associated acute kidney injury (CSA-AKI) is a<lb/> prerequisite for investigating potential treatments aimed at modulating or reversing the renal<lb/> insult occurring in this setting. The clinical usefulness and reliability of available markers for<lb/> this indication is controversial. Placental growth factor (PIGF) and Soluble – fms-like tyrosine<lb/> kinase (sFLT-1) are established plasmatic markers for preeclampsia – a clinical syndrome<lb/> often associated with renal dysfunction -and have not been tested as markers for CSA-AKI.<lb/> Methods: 102 consecutive patients scheduled for on-pump cardiac surgery were studied<lb/> during a prospective observational pilot study. The ratio between sFLT-1 and PlGF<lb/> (electrochemiluminescence immunoassays &quot;ECLIA&quot; on Elecsys 2010 (Roche Diagnostics,<lb/> Germany)) was determined immediately before induction of anesthesia, at the end of<lb/> surgery, and on the morning of the first to third postoperative day. Patients were grouped<lb/> according to creatinine AKI – criteria.<lb/> Results: In patients fulfilling any AKI – criterium the sFLT-1 / PlGF ratio increased<lb/> immediately and was significantly higher than in control patients already at the end of surgery<lb/> (Figure 1a). This effect was especially pronounced in patients postoperatively treated with<lb/> renal replacement therapy (RRT; figure 1b). The AUC for detecting the need for new RRT<lb/> was 0.72 ((0.63 to 0.8), p = 0.012) immediately after surgery and 0.8 ((0.71 to 0.87), p &lt;<lb/> 0.001) on the morning of the first postoperative day.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
