<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000681"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>IEEE COMMUNICATIONS SURVEYS &amp; TUTORIALS, VOL. 11, NO. 3, THIRD QUARTER 2009<lb/></reference>
	<note type="page"> 37<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A Survey on Internet Traffic Identification<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Arthur Callado, Carlos Kamienski Member, IEEE, Géza Szabó, Balázs Péter Ger˝ o, Judith Kelner,<lb/> Stênio Fernandes Member, IEEE, and Djamel Sadok, Senior Member, IEEE<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract—The area of Internet traffic measurement has ad-<lb/>vanced enormously over the last couple of years. This was<lb/> mostly due to the increase in network access speeds, due to<lb/> the appearance of bandwidth-hungry applications, due to the<lb/> ISPs&apos; increased interest in precise user traffic profile information<lb/> and also a response to the enormous growth in the number<lb/> of connected users. These changes greatly affected the work of<lb/> Internet Service Providers and network administrators, which<lb/> have to deal with increasing resource demands and abrupt traffic<lb/> changes brought by new applications. This survey explains the<lb/> main techniques and problems known in the field of IP traffic<lb/> analysis and focuses on application detection. First, it separates<lb/> traffic analysis into packet-based and flow-based categories and<lb/> details the advantages and problems for each approach. Second,<lb/> this work cites the techniques for traffic analysis accessible in<lb/> the literature, along with the analysis performed by the authors.<lb/> Relevant techniques include signature-matching, sampling and<lb/> inference. Third, this work shows the trends in application clas-<lb/>sification analysis and presents important and recent references<lb/> in the subject. Lastly, this survey draws the readers&apos; interest to<lb/> open research topics in the area of traffic analysis and application<lb/> detection and makes some final remarks.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Index Terms—Measurement, Application Identification, Traffic<lb/> Analysis, Classification.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
