<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55008383"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Architecting a Mashable<lb/> Open World Wide Web of Things<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dominique Guinard, Vlad Trifa<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institute for Pervasive Computing, ETH Zurich<lb/> and SAP Research CEC Zurich<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>8092 Zurich, Switzerland<lb/></address>

	<email>Email: {dguinard,trifam}@ethz.ch<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Erik Wilde<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>School of Information, UC Berkeley<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Berkeley CA 94720, USA<lb/></address>

	<email>Email: dret@berkeley.edu<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract—Many efforts are currently going towards network-<lb/>ing smart things from the physical world (e.g. RFID, wireless<lb/> sensor and actuator networks, embedded devices) on a larger<lb/> scale. Rather than exposing real-world data and functionality<lb/> through proprietary and tightly-coupled systems we propose to<lb/> make them an integral part of the Web. As a result, smart things<lb/> become easier to build upon. Popular Web languages (e.g. HTML,<lb/> URI, JavaScript, PHP) can be used to build applications involving<lb/> smart things and users can leverage well-known Web mechanisms<lb/> (e.g. browsing, searching, bookmarking, caching, linking) to<lb/> interact and share things. In this paper, we begin by describing<lb/> a Web of Things architecture and best-practices rooted on the<lb/> RESTful principles that contributed to the popular success,<lb/> scalability, and evolvability of the traditional Web. We then<lb/> discuss several prototypes implemented using these principles to<lb/> connect environmental sensor nodes, energy monitoring systems<lb/> and RFID tagged objects to the World Wide Web. We finally<lb/> show how Web-enabled things can be used in lightweight ad-hoc<lb/> applications called &quot;physical mashups&quot;.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
