<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006510"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Publications Internes de l&apos;IRISA<lb/> ISSN : en cours<lb/> </note>

	<idno>PI 1927 – </idno>

	<date>Avril 2009<lb/></date>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A review of weighting schemes for bag of visual words image retrieval<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Pierre Tirilly * , Vincent Claveau ** , Patrick Gros ***<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<email>pierre.tirilly@irisa.fr, vincent.claveau@irisa.fr, patrick.gros@inria.fr<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract: Current studies on content-based image retrieval mainly rely on bags of visual words. This model of image<lb/> description allows to perform image retieval in the same way as text retrieval: documents are described as vectors of (visual)<lb/> word frequencies, and documents are match by computing a distance or similarity measure between the vectors. But instead<lb/> of raw frequencies, documents can also be described as vectors of word weights, each weight corresponding to the importance<lb/> of the word in the document. Although the problem of determining automatically such weights, and therefore which words<lb/> describe well documents, has been widely studied in the case of text retrieval, there is very little litterature applying this idea<lb/> to the case of image retrieval. In this report, we explore how the use of standard weighting schemes and distance from text<lb/> retrieval can help to improve the performance of image retrieval systems. We show that there is no distance or weighting<lb/> scheme that can improve performance on any dataset, but choosing weights or a distance consistent with some properties of<lb/> a given dataset can improve the performance up to 10%. However, we also show that in the case of very varied and general<lb/> datasets, the performance gain is not significant.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key-words: Weighting schemes, content-based image retrieval, bag of visual words, information retrieval, vector space<lb/> model, probabilistic model, Minkowski distance, divergence from randomness, BM25, TF*IDF<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="introduction">Un aperçu des schémas de pondération pour la recherche d&apos;images par sac de mots visuels<lb/> Résumé :<lb/> Les travaux actuels en recherche d&apos;image par le contenu se basent sur unmo ele en sac de mots visuels.<lb/> Cemo ele permet de rechercher des images d&apos;une façont es similairè<lb/> a celle de la recherche textuelle : les documents sont<lb/> représentés par des vecteurs de fréquences de mots (visuels), et sont appariés en calculant une distance entre ces vecteurs. Au<lb/> lieu de comparer des fréquences brutes, il est possible d&apos;utiliser des vecteurs de poids, chaque poids représentant l&apos;importance<lb/> d&apos;un terme dans un document. Bien que de nombreuses méthodes pour déterminer automatiquement ces poids, et donc<lb/> l&apos;importance des termes, on eté développées pour les documents textuels, il existe peu de travau equivalents dans le domaine<lb/> de la recherche d&apos;image. Dans ce rapport, nou etudions l&apos;influence que peuvent avoir les schémas de pondération et les<lb/> distances classiques de la recherche d&apos;information textuelle sur les performances dessys emes de recherche d&apos;images. Nous<lb/> montrons qu&apos;il n&apos;existe pas de pondération ni de distance qui soit optimale sur n&apos;importe quelles données, mais aussi que le<lb/> choix d&apos;une distance ou d&apos;une pondération en adéquation avec les propriétés des donnée etudiées permet d&apos;augmenter les<lb/> résultats jusquaenviron10%.Cependant,nousmontronsaussiquedanslecasdegrandescollectionsd&apos;imagesvariées,les<lb/>améliorationsobtenuesnesontpassignificatives.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
