<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005067"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			
			<reference>Fuzzy Sets and Systems 172 (2011) 1 – 12<lb/></reference>

			<space dim="horizontal"/>

			<ptr type="web">www.elsevier.com</ptr>
			<note>/locate/fss<lb/></note>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>On the failure of the finite model property in some Fuzzy<lb/>
					Description Logics<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Fernando Bobillo a,* , Félix Bou b , Umberto Straccia c<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>a Department of Computer Science and Systems Engineering, University of
					Zaragoza,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Spain<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>b Department of Probability, Logic and Statistics, University of
					Barcelona,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Spain<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>c Istituto di Scienza e Tecnologie dell'Informazione, Consiglio
					Nazionale delle Ricerche (ISTI - CNR),</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Pisa, Italy<lb/></address>

			<note type="submission">Received 8 September 2009; received in revised form 3 February 2011; accepted 4 February
				2011<lb/></note> 
				
			<date>Available online 23 February 2011<lb/></date>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Fuzzy Description Logics (DLs) are a family of logics
				which allow the representation of (and the reasoning with) structured<lb/> knowledge
				affected by vagueness. Although most of the not very expressive crisp DLs, such as
				ALC, enjoy the Finite Model<lb/> Property (FMP), this is not the case once we move
				into the fuzzy case. In this paper we show that if we allow arbitrary knowledge<lb/>
				bases, then the fuzzy DLs ALC under Łukasiewicz and Product fuzzy logics do not
				verify the FMP even if we restrict to witnessed<lb/> models; in other words, finite
				satisfiability and witnessed satisfiability are different for arbitrary knowledge
				bases. The aim of<lb/> this paper is to point out the failure of FMP because it
				affects several algorithms published in the literature for reasoning under<lb/>
				fuzzy DLs.<lb/></div>
				
			<note type="copyright">© 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>	

			<keywords>Keywords: Fuzzy Description Logics; Fuzzy ontologies; Fuzzy logic; Logic for
				the semantic web</keywords>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
