<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55006220"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<ptr type="web">www.elsevier.nl/locate/farmac<lb/></ptr>

	<reference>Il Farmaco 56 (2001) 159– 167<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Synthesis, in vitro antiproliferative activity and DNA-interaction<lb/> of benzimidazoquinazoline derivatives as potential anti-tumor<lb/> agents<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Lisa Dalla Via<lb/> a , Ornella Gia<lb/> a , Sebastiano Marciani Magno<lb/> a , Antonio Da Settimo<lb/> b,<lb/> *,<lb/> Anna Maria Marini<lb/> b<lb/> , Giampaolo Primofiore<lb/> b , Federico Da Settimo<lb/> b<lb/> , Silvia Salerno<lb/> b<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Uni6ersity of Padua,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Via Marzolo 5, 35131 Padua, Italy<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Uni6ersity of Pisa,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Via Bonanno 6, 56126 Pisa, Italy<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 10 November 2000; accepted 8 January 2001<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> The synthesis of benzimidazoquinazoline derivatives bearing different alkylamino side chains is reported. All new compounds<lb/> tested by means of an in vitro assay exhibit antiproliferative activity toward human tumor cell lines. The cytotoxic effect depends<lb/> on the type of side chain inserted in the planar nucleus and in some cases it is comparable to that of the well-known drug<lb/> ellipticine. In order to understand the mechanism of action of these compounds, the interaction with DNA has been investigated.<lb/> Linear flow dichroism measurements allowed us to verify the formation of a molecular complex with DNA and the corresponding<lb/> geometry of interaction. Intrinsic binding constants have also been evaluated by performing fluorimetric titrations. </div>
	<note type="copyright">© 2001<lb/> Elsevier Science S.A. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Keywords: Benzimidazoquinazoline; Antiproliferative activity; DNA binding<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
