<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007178"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>High-efficiency red electroluminescence from a narrow recombination zone<lb/> confined by an organic double heterostructure<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Z. Y. Xie, L. S. Hung, and S. T. Lee<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a)<lb/> Center of Super-Diamond and Advanced Films (COSDF) and Department of Physics and Materials<lb/> Sciences, City University of Hong Kong,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hong Kong SAR, People&apos;s Republic of China<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">͑Received 30 March 2001; accepted for publication 6 June 2001͒<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Red light-emitting diodes ͑LEDs͒ with both a conventional bilayer structure and a double<lb/> heterostructure ͑DH͒ have been investigated. In these LEDs, N,NЈ-bis-͑1-naphthl͒-diphenyl-1,<lb/> 1Ј-biphenyl-4,4Ј-diamine ͑NPB͒, 2,9-dimethyl-4,7-diphenyl-1,10-phenanthroline ͑BCP͒, and<lb/> tris͑8-quinolinolato͒ aluminum (Alq 3 ) were used as hole-transporting, hole-blocking, and<lb/> electron-transporting layers, respectively. The bilayer and DH LEDs had a configuration of ITO/<lb/> NPB/Alq 3 :red dopant/Alq 3 /MgAg and ITO/NPB/Alq 3 :red dopant/BCP/Alq 3 /MgAg, respectively.<lb/> Three kinds of red fluorescent dyes—nile red, DCJTB, and DCM—were used as dopants. Compared<lb/> with the bilayer structures, the luminance efficiencies of the DH LEDs were found to increase as<lb/> much as 100%. We attribute the efficiency enhancement to the formation of a narrow recombination<lb/> zone, in which both charge carriers and excitons were confined. High charge concentrations in the<lb/> emissive layer resulted in efficient collision capture in the electron–hole recombination process.<lb/> Exciton confinement led to improved energy transfer. The two factors were simultaneously<lb/> operating and consequently benefitted from efficiency enhancement.</div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2001 American Institute of<lb/> Physics.</note>

	<idno type="DOI">͓DOI: 10.1063/1.1390479͔<lb/></idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
