<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001777"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Fiberoptic 6-DOF Force-Torque-Sensing for Haptic Feedback in Minimally Invasive<lb/> Robotic Surgery<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Robert Haslinger, Georg Passig, Ulrich Seibold, Ulrich Hagn, Gerd Hirzinger<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> In minimally invasive robotic surgery long and slender instruments are introduced into<lb/> the body of the patient through small incisions or natural orifices. Robotics technology<lb/> is applied in order to comply with the kinematic constraints of the fulcrum point, to<lb/> increase the immersion for the surgeon by sensors and to increase dexterity by<lb/> supplemental motion capabilities.<lb/> Haptic feedback for the surgeon can be realized in such a robotic system (MIRS,<lb/> minimally invasive robotic surgery) through measurement of interaction forces at the<lb/> instruments tip and a high bandwidth haptic user interface for the surgeon. Contact<lb/> forces should be measured as close as possible to the distal tip of the instrument (i.e.<lb/> tips of forceps, scalpel) to reduce impact of parasitic forces like friction and moments<lb/> in the fulcrum point or actuation forces of distal joints.<lb/> Forces are commonly measured by applying strain gauge sensors to a suitable<lb/> sensor structure allowing a decoupled measurement of forces and torques in several<lb/> degrees of freedom. She response is very small and has to be amplified and<lb/> processed in close proximity to the sensors, thus inside the patient.<lb/> A six degrees of freedom sensor based on a Stewart platform and strain gauge<lb/> sensors integrated into a MIRS system (see figure 1 left) was presented in [1].<lb/> However, the constraints shown above lead to suboptimal designs. This is reflected<lb/> by multiple approaches to this problem in research [1-5].</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
