<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002075"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Maximizing dye fluorescence via incorporation<lb/> of metallic nanoparticles in solution<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Yang Xu<lb/> a , Guangyin Lei<lb/> b<lb/> , Annette C. Booker<lb/> a<lb/> , Katherine A. Linares<lb/> c<lb/> , Dara Fleming<lb/> b<lb/> , Kathleen<lb/> Meehan<lb/> a*<lb/> , Guo-Quan Lu<lb/> b<lb/> , Nancy G. Love<lb/> c<lb/> , and Brian J. Love<lb/> b<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a The Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering<lb/> b<lb/> Materials Science and Engineering Department<lb/> c<lb/> The Via Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering<lb/> Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Blacksburg, VA 24060<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Gram-negative bacteria initiate a stress response in which the cells efflux potassium when electrophilic toxins are<lb/> introduced into their environment. Hence, measurement of K<lb/> + concentration in the surrounding water using a<lb/> fluorescence-based potassium-selective optode has been proposed for environmental and homeland security<lb/> applications. Unfortunately, the fluorophore commonly used in such an optode is inefficient. Surface enhanced<lb/> fluorescence (SEF) can be used to increase its fluorescence efficiency, which will improve the sensor&apos;s performance.<lb/> To understand this phenomenon before applying it to the optode system, Rose Bengal (RB), an inexpensive and well<lb/> characterized dye, in solution with gold and silver nanoparticles was studied. As expected, fluorescence from RB-<lb/>gold solutions was low since alignment of gold&apos;s surface plasmon resonance (SPR) peak and absorption and<lb/> fluorescence energies in RB favored energy transfer from RB to the gold nanoparticles. The alignment of the silver&apos;s<lb/> SPR peak and the RB transitions favored transfer from silver to RB. SEF was observed in solutions with large dye-to-<lb/>silver separation. However, little fluorescence was observed when the solution was pumped at the silver&apos;s SPR peak.<lb/> Fluorescence from the dye decreased as dye-to-silver separation decreased. An explanation for these observations is<lb/> presented; additional research is needed to develop a complete understanding.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: Surface enhanced fluorescence, surface plasmon, nanoparticles, colloids, gold, silver, Rose Bengal<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
