<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004288"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of Ethnopharmacology 86 (2003) 235–241<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Screening of traditionally used South African plants<lb/> for antifungal activity against Candida albicans<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>M.L. Motsei, K.L. Lindsey, J. van Staden * , A.K. Jäger<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Research Centre for Plant Growth and Development, School of Botany and Zoology, University of Natal Pietermaritzburg,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Private Bag X01, Scottsville 3209, South Africa<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 3 September 2002; received in revised form 20 February 2003; accepted 20 February 2003<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Twenty-four South African medicinal plants were screened against Candida albicans standard strain ATCC 10231 and two clinical isolates<lb/> from a 5-month-old baby and an adult, in an attempt to find a traditional remedy to treat oral candidiasis, which is prevalent in HIV-patients.<lb/> Allium sativum L. and Tulbaghia violacea L. aqueous bulb extracts had MIC values of 0.56 and 3.25 mg/ml respectively, whilst Polygala<lb/> myrtifolia L. leaves and Glycyrrhiza glabra L. rhizome extracts had MIC values of 1.56 mg/ml when tested against the 5-month-old isolate.<lb/> Fresh water extracts stored at 4, 23 and 33<lb/> @BULLET C over a period of a week, were used to determine the stability of these extracts. Allium sativum<lb/> and Tulbaghia violacea maintained activity at 4<lb/> @BULLET C, but not at higher temperatures, whereas Polygala myrtifolia and Glycyrrhiza glabra lost<lb/> activity within a day even at 4<lb/> @BULLET C. The unpleasant taste of the two species with a garlic smell, could however not be masked, and as the<lb/> smell following the eating of the two species would lead to HIV-patients being recognised, these two plants where not considered for further<lb/> investigation. Therefore, Polygala myrtifolia and Glycyrrhiza glabra are being further investigated for use as an oral mouthwash in clinics<lb/> and homes.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2003 Elsevier Science Ireland Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Keywords: Antifungal; Candida albicans; HIV/AIDS; Traditional medicine<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
