<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005196"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Applied Mathematics and Computation 192 (2007) 487–495<lb/></reference>
			<ptr type="web">www.elsevier.com/locate/amc<lb/></ptr>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>A simple mobile communication billing system<lb/> among charged
					parties<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Hsia-Hung Ou a , Min-Shiang Hwang b, * , Jinn-Ke Jan a<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>a Department of Computer Science, National Chung Hsing
					University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Taichung 402, Taiwan, ROC<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>b Department of Management Information Systems, National Chung Hsing
					University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>250, Kuo Kuong Road, Taichung 402, Taiwan, ROC<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Mobile communication is a milestone technology that
				has brought people a kind of universal convenience otherwise<lb/> unattainable. From
				GSM to UMTS, the mobile communication technologies, like all the other great
				inventions in human<lb/> history, have gone through such fast-paced advancements
				since the very first day it came to existence that each day we<lb/> seem to be using
				a newer, more powerful device than before to talk to people close by or far away. We
				are so used to this<lb/> convenience that it is hard to imagine how life could carry
				on without cell phones. However, when cell phone users roam<lb/> from city to city
				crossing different system facilitators' domains of services, besides the conveyance
				of the signals, some<lb/> charging problems may also arise between or among the
				service providers. In this paper, we shall present a simple mobile<lb/>
				communication billing system that can help solve roaming-related charging problems.
				Our new system can be used in a<lb/> wide variety of applications without having to
				modify the standard UMTS protocol, and it only causes slight, readily<lb/> ignorable
				traffic increase. As we can expect, the new mobile communication billing system will
				be a friendly design that<lb/> comes in handy for both service providers and
				users.<lb/>
			</div>
			
			<keywords>Keywords: Mobile communication; Billing; Charging; UMTS<lb/></keywords>
			
			<note type="other">0096-3003/$ - see front matter</note> 
			<note type="copyright">&#169; 2007 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>
			
			<idno>doi:10.1016/j.amc.2007.03.034</idno>
			

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
