<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005981"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Real-time FPGA-based Coherent Optical Receiver for<lb/> 1 Gsymbol/s, 64 QAM Transmission<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Masato Yoshida, Tatsunori Omiya, Keisuke Kasai, and Masataka Nakazawa<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Research Institute of Electrical Communication, Tohoku University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2-1-1 Katahira, Aoba-ku, Sendai-shi, Miyagi-ken, 980-8577 Japan.<lb/></address>

	<email>E-mail: masato@riec.tohoku.ac.jp<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract: We demonstrated the first time real-time FPGA-based coherent optical receiver for a 64<lb/> QAM transmission. Error free performance (BER &lt; 1x10<lb/> -12 ) was achieved under a back-to-back<lb/> condition and the BER after transmission was measured on-line.<lb/> </div>
	
	<reference>OCIS codes: (060.1660) Coherent communications; (060.2330) Fiber optics communications<lb/> </reference>
	
	<div type="introduction">1. Introduction<lb/> Coherent multilevel optical transmission has been receiving a lot of attention with respect to expanding the<lb/> transmission capacity in a finite optical amplification bandwidth. In particular, quadrature amplitude modulation<lb/> (QAM) has an advantage as regards increasing the spectral efficiency (SE). Recently, total WDM transmission<lb/> capacities of 69.1 and 64 Tbit/s transmission have been reported using 16 and 36 QAM formats with SEs as high as<lb/> 6.4 and 8 bit/s/Hz, respectively [1,2]. We have also demonstrated 256 and 512 QAM transmissions that achieved<lb/> SEs exceeding 10 bit/s/Hz [3,4]. However, previous QAM transmission experiments were based on off-line<lb/> processing. The development of a real-time coherent optical receiver for multi-level QAM signals is an important<lb/> issue if we are to realize highly spectral efficient optical transmission systems.<lb/> Recently, a real-time coherent optical receiver for QPSK signals beyond 40 Gbit/s [5-7] and a 6.67 Gbit/s OFDM<lb/> signal with a 16 QAM modulation format [8] have been demonstrated. Since it is difficult to completely compensate<lb/> for phase error in homodyne or heterodyne detection with a real-time digital signal processor (DSP), a real-time<lb/> receiver for a coherent optical signal with a multiplicity of more than 32 has not yet been reported. In this paper, we<lb/> demonstrate the first real-time FPGA-based coherent optical receiver for a 64 QAM transmission with an optical<lb/> phase-locked loop (OPLL) technique. Error free performance (bit error rate (BER) &lt; 1 x 10<lb/> -12 ) is achieved under a<lb/> back-to-back condition. In this experiment, 6 Gbit/s data can be demodulated with four 1 GS/s analog to digital<lb/> converters (ADCs), and a data bit rate to ADC sampling rate ratio of 6 bit/sample can be achieved.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
