<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004846"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Print this Page<lb/> Presentation Abstract<lb/> Program#/Poster#:<lb/> 4850/A94<lb/> Abstract Title:<lb/> Reversal of Reactive Gliosis Promote De Novo Vascular<lb/> Remodeling and Prevent Retinal Vasculopathies<lb/> Presentation Start/End<lb/> Time:<lb/> Wednesday, May 04, 2011, 3:45 PM -5:30 PM<lb/> Session Number:<lb/> 472<lb/> Session Title:<lb/> Angiogenesis II<lb/> /<lb/> Location:<lb/> Hall B/C<lb/> Reviewing Code:<lb/> 123 angiogenesis: retinal disease processes -RE<lb/> Author Block:<lb/> Michael DeNiro<lb/> 1,2A<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>, Falah H. Al-Mohanna<lb/> 2A<lb/> , Futwan A.<lb/> Al-Mohanna<lb/> 2B<lb/> .<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation> 1<lb/> Research Department, King Khaled Eye Specialist<lb/> Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Riyadh, Saudi Arabia;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>A<lb/> Comparative Medicine,<lb/> B<lb/> Department of Biological and Medical Research,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<affiliation>2<lb/></affiliation>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>King Faisal Specialist Hospital<lb/> and Research Centre,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.<lb/></address>

	<keyword>Keywords:<lb/> 697 retinal neovascularization; 571 ischemia; 602 Muller cells<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract Body:<lb/> Purpose: Retinal neovascularization [NV] is a major cause of blindness<lb/> in ischemic retinopathies. Previous investigations have indicated that<lb/> ischemia upregulates GFAP, PDGF-B, and iNOS expression. GFAP<lb/> overexpression is a hallmark of reactive gliosis [RG], which is a major<lb/> pathophysiological feature of retinal damage. In addition, PDGF -B has<lb/> been implicated in proliferative retinopathies; while data have indicated<lb/> that iNOS upregulation plays a pathological role by which it inhibits<lb/> angiogenesis in the ischemic retina. It was the aim of this study to<lb/> evaluate the efficacy of YC-1, a HIF-1 inhibitor, in modulating<lb/> PDGF-B and iNOS expression and reversing RG and NV.<lb/> Methods: An array of assays to evaluate the effects of YC-1 on RG<lb/> and NV; in vitro and in vivo.<lb/> Results: Dual-intravitreal injections of YC-1; [1] reduced the<lb/> hypoxia/ischemia-induced expression of GFAP, PDGF-B, and iNOS<lb/> message and protein levels, in vivo and in vitro, respectively; [2]<lb/> reduced the filopodial length and number in endothelial tip cells; [3]<lb/> inhibited ischemic pathologic neovascular response; [4] promoted<lb/> retinal microvascular repair and intra-retinal revascularization.<lb/> Abstract Print View<lb/></div>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.abstractsonline.com/plan/AbstractPrintView.aspx?mID=2...<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="page">1 of 2<lb/> </note>
	
	<date>16-08-2011 </date>
	
	<note type="other">09:30</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
