<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55000020-orginal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>THE JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY<lb/></reference>
			<note type="copyright">© 2000 by The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Inc.</note>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<reference>Vol. 275, No. 17, Issue of April 28, pp. 12572–12580, 2000<lb/></reference>
			<note type="other">Printed in U.S.A.<lb/></note>
			
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Simultaneous Suppression of cdc2 and cdk2 Activities Induces<lb/>
					Neuronal Differentiation of PC12 Cells*<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<note type="submission">(Received for publication, December 3, 1999, and in revised form, February 1,
				2000)<lb/></note>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Yoh Dobashi‡§, Mitsuhiko Shoji‡, Masatoshi Kitagawa¶ʈ, Takashi Noguchi‡, and Toru Kameya‡
					<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>From the ‡Department of Pathology, Kitasato University School of
					Medicine,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>1-15-1, Kitasato, Sagamihara,<lb/> Kanagawa 228-8555, Japan, </address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>the ¶Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology, Medical Institute for
					Bioregulation,<lb/> Kyushu University,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Fukuoka 812-8582, Japan, </address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>and the ʈCREST, Japan Science and Technology Corporation (JST),<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Kawaguchi, Saitama 332-0012, Japan<lb/></address>

			<div type="abstract">The involvement of cdc2 and cdk2 during neuronal<lb/>
				differentiation in rat pheochromocytoma PC12 cells was<lb/> examined. When PC12
				cells were cultured with nerve<lb/> growth factor (NGF), expression of cdc2
				decreased sig-<lb/>nificantly after day 5, while expression of cdk2 de-<lb/>creased
				gradually after day 7. Cells overexpressing cdc2<lb/> or cdk2 were resistant to
				NGF-induced differentiation<lb/> and growth suppression, and maintained high cdc2
				or<lb/> cdk2 kinase activity, respectively, during NGF treat-<lb/>ment. In contrast,
				the NGF-treated parental cells<lb/> showed a marked decline in these kinase
				activities after<lb/> day 3. When PC12 cells were treated with specific
				inhib-<lb/>itors of cdc2/cdk2 (butyrolactone-I, olomoucin), they<lb/> showed marked
				neurite extension and up-regulation of<lb/> microtubule-associated protein 2
				expression. In addi-<lb/>tion, treatment with mixtures of antisense
				oligonucleo-<lb/>tides for cdc2 and cdk2 resulted in down-regulation of<lb/> both
				cdc2 and cdk2 kinase activities as well as signifi-<lb/>cant neurite outgrowth and
				up-regulation of microtu-<lb/>bule-associated protein 2 expression. However,
				neurite<lb/> outgrowth was not observed in cells treated with either<lb/> single
				antisense oligonucleotide, or antisense cdc2 &#x6ef59;<lb/> cdk4 or cdk2 &#x6ef59; cdk4
				oligonucleotide mixtures. These<lb/> results suggest that simultaneous
				down-regulation of<lb/> cdc2 and cdk2 activity is sufficient and necessary for<lb/>
				neuronal differentiation in PC12 cells.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
