<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005116"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>A New Aspect of Dual Basis for Efficient Field<lb/>
					Arithmetic<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Chang-Hyi Lee 1 and Jong-In Lim 2<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 Samsung Advanced Institute of Technology<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<email>chang@saitgw.sait.samsung.co.kr<lb/></email>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 Korea University<lb/></affiliation>
			</byline>

			<email>jilim@tiger.korea.ac.kr<lb/></email>

			<div type="abstract">Abstract. In this paper we consider a special type of dual basis
				for finite<lb/> fields, GF (2 m ), where the variants of m are presented in section
				2. We<lb/> introduce our field representing method for efficient field
				arithmetic(such<lb/> as field multiplication and field inversion). It reveals a very
				effective role<lb/> for both software and hardware(VLSI) implementations, but the
				aspect<lb/> of hardware design of its structure is out of this manuscript and so,
				here,<lb/> we deal only the case of its software implementation(the efficiency
				of<lb/> hardware implementation is appeared in another article submitted to<lb/>
				IEEE Transactions on Computers). A brief description of several advan-<lb/> tageous
				characteristics of our method is that (1) the field multiplication<lb/> in GF (2 m )
				can be constructed only by m + 1 vector rotations and the<lb/> same amount of vector
				XOR operations, (2) there is required no addi-<lb/> tional work load such as basis
				changing(from standard to dual basis or<lb/> from dual basis to standard basis as
				the conventional dual based arith-<lb/> metic does), (3) the field squaring is only
				bit-by-bit permutation and it<lb/> has a good regularity for its implementation, and
				(4) the field inversion<lb/> process is available to both cases of its
				implementation using Fermat's<lb/> Theorem and using almost inverse algorithm[14],
				especially the case of<lb/> using the almost inverse algorithm has an additional
				advantage in find-<lb/> ing(computing) its complete inverse element(i.e., there is
				required no<lb/> pre-computed table of the values, x −k , k = 1, 2, . .
				.).<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
