<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002820"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Supplementary Materials and Methods<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="introduction">Vectors construction. The sequence for the poliovirus internal ribosomal entry site (pIRES) was<lb/> obtained from plasmid pS1179D8 following PCR amplification using primers IRES1For, with<lb/> sequence 5&apos;-CATGTCGACATCGATTTAAAACAGCTCTG, introducing a SalI restriction site at<lb/> the 5&apos; of the sequence (underlined), and IRES2Rev, with sequence 5&apos;-<lb/>CATCCATGGTGGTGGAGGGTACCTAGG-3&apos;, introducing a NcoI restriction site (underlined)<lb/> with ATG start codon (bold, in reverse orientation) at the 3&apos; of the sequence. The coding sequence<lb/> for the mouse granulocyte monocyte-colony stimulatory factor (mGM-CSF) was obtained from<lb/> plasmid pxLNC-mGM-CSF following PCR amplification using primers mGMS1, with sequence 5&apos;-<lb/>CATCCATGGGGCTGCAGAATTTACTTTTCCT-3&apos;, introducing a NcoI restriction site<lb/> (underlined) with ATG start codon (bold) at the 5&apos; of the sequence, and mGMAS2, with sequence<lb/> 5&apos;-CATGGTACCTCATTTTTGGCTTGGTTTTTTGCA-3&apos;, introducing a KpnI restriction site<lb/> (underlined) with TGA stop codon (bold, in reverse orientation) at the 3&apos; of the sequence. The<lb/> sequence for the woodchuck hepatitis post-transcriptional regulatory element (WPRE) was obtained<lb/> from plasmid R5SA-EFS-GFP-W following PCR amplification using primers WPREfor, with<lb/> sequence 5&apos;-CATGGTACCTGATAATCAACCTCTGGATTACA-3&apos;, introducing a KpnI<lb/> restriction site (underlined) at the 5&apos; of the sequence, and WPRErev, with sequence 5&apos;-<lb/>CATGCGGCCGCCCGATGCGGGGAGGCGGCCCAAA-3&apos;, introducing a NotI restriction site<lb/> (underlined) at the 3&apos; of the sequence. All fragments were separately cloned into pCR2.1 plasmid<lb/> (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) and sequenced to confirm their identity and the absence of PCR-<lb/>introduced base pair errors. Subsequently, plasmid pCR2.1mZ was produced by introducing the<lb/> pIRES (restricted with SalI/NcoI), mGM-CSF (restricted with NcoI/KpnI) and WPRE (restricted<lb/> with KpnI/NotI) sequences into the SalI/NotI restricted pCR2.1 plasmid. Finally, the lentiviral<lb/> transfer vector plasmid pTY2-JRmZ was produced by insertion of the pIRES-mGM-CSF-WPRE<lb/> (mZ) sequence, after restriction of pCR2.1mZ with SalI/NotI, into the SalI/NotI restricted parental</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
