<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55004850"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>BIOVAL Association of Bioenterprises of<lb/> Valencian Community Region<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="other">Bioval<lb/> Home Interviews<lb/> News Products<lb/> Business Opportunities<lb/> Invest in Science<lb/> About<lb/> « Scientists at the CIPF-CSIC collaborate in an advance in the development of anti cancer<lb/> drugs Nutracitrus, Malta Polyphenols 2009 award »<lb/> Products -</note>
	<date>Wednesday,April 14, 2010<lb/></date>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Kit Bioalarm Legionella receives validation<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">New Bioalarm kit allows for Legionella testing in less than 1 hour without specialized<lb/> training or instrumentation.<lb/> The Kit Bioalarm Legionella developed by Biótica, Bioquímica<lb/> Analítica, S.L., has been validated for the detection of Legionella<lb/> pneumophila in waters through the two expert laboratories,<lb/> Laboratorios Labaqua, S.A. and Iproma, S.A. Validation of the<lb/> Biótica´s kit is part of an effort to effectively respond to the<lb/> prevention of Legionellosis, which represents a considerable challenge for public health.<lb/> The Bioalarm Legionella Kit is a immunomagnetic beads-based tool for monitoring the level of<lb/> Legionella pneumophila both natural and man-made aquatic environments. It could help<lb/> avoid costly impacts of prevention strategies for Legionella pneumophila, which is responsible<lb/> of 90-98 % of the cases.<lb/> The Bioalarm Legionella Kit is intended to enhance the ability of government and industry to<lb/> test Legionella pneumophila, which has been implicated in several recent outbreaks, including<lb/> cooling waters, hospitals and hotels. These bacteria represent a fatality rate of 12-15 % that<lb/> can easily extend up to 50% in cases of immunocompromised patients. This kit helps the<lb/> companies to improve their measures to prevent infective levels in risk environments.<lb/> Kit Bioalarm Legionella receives validation « BIOVAL Association of ...<lb/></div>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.valencianbiotechnology.com/?p=421</ptr>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
