<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003550"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Dielectric and structural properties of thin SrHfO 3 layers on TiN<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>G. Lupina,<lb/> a͒ G. Kozłowski, J. Dabrowski, P. Dudek, G. Lippert, and H.-J. Müssig<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>IHP,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Im Technologiepark 25, 15236 Frankfurt (Oder), Germany<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">͑Received 1 October 2008; accepted 22 November 2008; published online 24 December 2008͒<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">We studied several properties of thin amorphous and polycrystalline SrHfO 3 layers on TiN in the<lb/> context of memory capacitor applications. Amorphous SrHfO 3 has the dielectric constant ␬ = 21 and<lb/> is transformed upon rapid thermal annealing into polycrystalline SrHfO 3 with ␬ = 35. We discuss the<lb/> influence of the annealing treatment on leakage currents, and briefly discuss, on the basis of ab initio<lb/> calculations, the possible role of vacancylike defects and Ti contamination.</div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2008 American<lb/> Institute of Physics.</note>

	<idno>͓DOI: 10.1063/1.3049611͔<lb/></idno>

	<div type="introduction">Innovations in architecture and materials are expected to<lb/> drive future scaling and performance increase of memory<lb/> devices.<lb/> 1,2 To satisfy requirements of high capacitance den-<lb/>sity and low leakage current in advanced high-␬ capacitors,<lb/> various dielectric materials are investigated. Despite the con-<lb/>troversial issue of grain boundaries which may act as leakage<lb/> sites,<lb/> 3,4 the interest of researchers is now focused rather on<lb/> polycrystalline than amorphous insulators.<lb/> 5 This trend is<lb/> mainly due to the fact that polycrystalline materials generally<lb/> offer higher dielectric constants ␬ than their amorphous<lb/> analog. For this reason, crystalline phases of well known<lb/> high-␬ dielectrics such as HfO 2 and ZrO 2 as well as struc-<lb/>tural phase transformations in these systems attracted much<lb/> attention.<lb/> 6–10 Another interesting group of materials are poly-<lb/>crystalline complex metal oxides, which crystallize in the<lb/> perovskite structure.<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">11–13</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
