<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005197"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>JOURNAL OF PARALLEL AND DISTRIBUTED COMPUTING 48, 71–95
				(1998)<lb/></reference>
			<idno>ARTICLE NO. PC971403<lb/></idno>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>A Parallel Algorithm for Multilevel Graph<lb/> Partitioning and Sparse
					Matrix Ordering 1<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>George Karypis 2 and Vipin Kumar 3<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>Department of Computer Science/Army HPC Research Center,
					University<lb/> of Minnesota,</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<address>Minneapolis, Minnesota 55455<lb/></address>
			<div type="abstract">In this paper we present a parallel formulation of the multilevel
				graph<lb/> partitioning and sparse matrix ordering algorithm. A key feature of our
				parallel<lb/> formulation (that distinguishes it from other proposed parallel
				formulations of<lb/> multilevel algorithms) is that it partitions the vertices of
				the graph into<lb/> √ p parts<lb/> while distributing the overall adjacency matrix
				of the graph among all p processors.<lb/> This mapping results in substantially
				smaller communication than one-dimensional<lb/> distribution for graphs with
				relatively high degree, especially if the graph is<lb/> randomly distributed among
				the processors. We also present a parallel algorithm<lb/> for computing a minimal
				cover of a bipartite graph which is a key operation for<lb/> obtaining a small
				vertex separator that is useful for computing the fill reducing<lb/> ordering of
				sparse matrices. Our parallel algorithm achieves a speedup of up to<lb/> 56 on 128
				processors for moderate size problems, further reducing the already<lb/> moderate
				serial run time of multilevel schemes. Furthermore, the quality of the<lb/> produced
				partitions and orderings are comparable to those produced by the serial<lb/>
				multilevel algorithm that has been shown to outperform both spectral
				partitioning<lb/> and multiple minimum degree. </div>
			<space dim="horizontal"/>
			<note type="copyright">© 1998 Academic Press<lb/></note>
			<keywords>Key Words: parallel graph partitioning; multilevel partitioning methods;
				fill<lb/> reducing ordering; numerical linear algebra.<lb/>
			</keywords>
			<note type="grant">1<lb/> This work was supported by NSF CCR-9423082, by the Army
				Research Office Contract DA/DAAH04-95-<lb/> 1-0538, by the IBM Partnership Award,
				and by Army High Performance Computing Research Center under the<lb/> auspices of
				the Department of the Army, Army Research Laboratory Cooperative Agreement Number
				DAAH04-<lb/> 95-2-0003/Contract DAAH04-95-C-0008, the content of which does not
				necessarily reflect the position or the<lb/> policy of the government, and no
				official endorsement should be inferred. Access to computing facilities<lb/> was
				provided by AHPCRC. Minnesota Supercomputer Institute, Cray Research Inc., and by
				the Pittsburgh<lb/> Supercomputing Center.</note>
			<note type="other">Related papers are available via WWW at</note>
			
			<ptr type="web">URL: http://www.cs.umn.edu/ ∼ karypis.<lb/></ptr>> 
			
			<email> 2<lb/> E-mail:
				karypis@cs.umn.edu.<lb/>
			</email>
			
			<email> 3<lb/> E-mail: kumar@cs.umn.edu.<lb/>
			</email>
			
			<note type="other">71<lb/></note>
			
			<note type="other">0743-7315/98$25.00<lb/></note>
			
			<note type="copyright">Copyright © 1998 by Academic Press<lb/> All rights of
				reproduction in any form reserved.<lb/></note>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
