<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55007708"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Extraordinary optical reflection from<lb/> sub-wavelength cylinder arrays<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Raquel Gómez-Medina<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Donostia International Physics Center (DIPC), </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Paseo Manuel de Lardizábal 4,<lb/>20018 San Sebastian, Spain<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Nanophotonics and Metrology Laboratory, Swiss Federal Institute of Technology,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1015 Lausanne, Switzerland<lb/></address>

	<email>raquel.gomezmedina@epfl.ch<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Marine Laroche and Juan José Sáenz<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Departamento de Física de la Materia Condensada and Instituto &quot;Nicolás Cabrera&quot;,<lb/> Universidad Autónoma de Madrid,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>E-28049 Madrid, Spain.<lb/></address>

	<email>marine.laroche@uam.es<lb/> juanjo.saenz@uam.es<lb/></email>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.uam.es/mole<lb/></ptr>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract: A multiple scattering analysis of the reflectance of a periodic<lb/> array of sub-wavelength cylinders is presented. The optical properties<lb/> and their dependence on wavelength, geometrical parameters and cylinder<lb/> dielectric constant are analytically derived for both s-and p-polarized<lb/> waves. In absence of Mie resonances and surface (plasmon) modes, and for<lb/> positive cylinder polarizabilities, the reflectance presents sharp peaks close<lb/> to the onset of new diffraction modes (Rayleigh frequencies). At the lowest<lb/> resonance frequency, and in the absence of absorption, the wave is perfectly<lb/> reflected even for vanishingly small cylinder radii.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2006 Optical Society of America<lb/></note>

	<keyword>OCIS codes: (050.1960) Diffraction theory ; (290.4210) Multiple scattering<lb/> </keyword>
	
	<note type="other">References and links<lb/> 1. R.W. Wood, &quot;On the remarkable case of uneven distribution of light in a diffraction grating spectrum,&quot; Proc. R.<lb/>Soc. London A 18, 269 (1902).<lb/> 2. R.W. Wood, &quot;Anomalous Diffraction Gratings,&quot; Phys. Rev. 15, 928 (1935).<lb/> 3. U. Fano, &quot;The Theory of Anomalous Diffraction Gratings and of Quasi-Stationary Waves on Metallic Surfaces<lb/> (Sommerfeld&apos;s Waves),&quot; J. Opt. Soc. Am. 31, 213 (1941).<lb/> 4. Lord Rayleigh, &quot;On the dynamical theory of gratings,&quot; Proc. Roy. Soc. (London) A79, 399 (1907).<lb/> 5. A. Hessel and A.A. Oliner, &quot;A new theory of Wood&apos;s anomalies on optical gratings,&quot; Appl. Opt. 4, 1275 (1965)<lb/> 6. M.Nevì ere, D. Maystre, P. Vincent,&quot;Application du calcul des modes de propagation a letude theorique des<lb/> anomalies des reseaux recouverts de dielectrique,&quot; J. Opt. (Paris) 8, 231 (1977).<lb/> 7. T.</note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>W. Ebbesen, H.J. Lezec, H.F. Ghaemi, T. Thio and P.A.</docAuthor>
	</byline>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
