<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003654"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Endovascular aneurysm repair reverses the<lb/> increased titer and the inflammatory activity of<lb/> interleukin-1␣ in the serum of patients with<lb/> abdominal aortic aneurysm<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Clara M. Yates, PhD,<lb/> a Mohamed Abdelhamid, MSc, MRCSEd,<lb/> b Donald J. Adam, MD, FRCSEd,<lb/> b<lb/> Gerard B. Nash, PhD,<lb/> a Andrew W. Bradbury, BSc, MBA, MD, FRCSEd,<lb/> b and<lb/> G. Ed Rainger, PhD,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Birmingham and Solihull,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>West Midlands, United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Objective: To examine serum cytokine/chemokine profiles before and 6 months after endovascular repair (EVAR) of<lb/> abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA) and to determine whether they correlate with serum inflammatory activity using an in<lb/> vitro model of leukocyte recruitment.<lb/> Methods: Serum IL-1-␣, IL-1␤, IL-4, IL-6, IL-8, IL-10, IFN-␥, IP-10, MCP-1, TNF-␣, and TNF-␤ were measured using<lb/> a cytometry-based immunoassay. To test patient serum for direct inflammatory activity, human endothelial cells (EC)<lb/> were stimulated with 30% patient serum for 24 hours. To test patient serum for the ability to prime EC for inflammatory<lb/> responses, EC were incubated with 30% patient serum for 24 hours, followed by stimulation with low-dose (5 U/mL)<lb/> TNF for 4 hours. Under both regimens of stimulation, the degree of EC activation was assessed by assaying neutrophil<lb/> recruitment in a flow-based model.<lb/> Results: Only IL-1␣ (67.9 ؎ 10.4 pg/mL vs 41.9 ؎ 7.4 pg/mL) and IL-8 (51.5 ؎ 5.1 vs 32.6 ؎ 4.7 pg/mL) changed<lb/> significantly after surgery. Patient serum alone was unable to activate EC. However, serum from both time points could<lb/> prime EC responses to low-dose TNF. Thus, after priming with preoperative serum, EC stimulated with TNF could<lb/> recruit 76.7 ؎ 12.0 neutrophils/mm<lb/> 2 into the subendothelial cell space. Post-EVAR serum was significantly less effective<lb/> (44.4 ؎ 10.2 neutrophils/mm<lb/> 2 ). This reduction in neutrophil recruitment correlated with reduced IL-1␣ in post-EVAR<lb/> serum. The addition of a neutralizing antibody against IL-1␣ to pre-EVAR serum inhibited EC priming and neutrophil<lb/> recruitment, strongly implying that this cytokine was the priming agent.<lb/> Conclusion: EVAR reduces serum IL-1␣ and its inflammatory activity in patient serum. IL-1␣ is, therefore, implicated in<lb/> the molecular pathology of AAAs and may have potential as a clinically useful biomarker. ( J Vasc Surg 2011;ⅢⅢ:ⅢⅢⅢ.)<lb/> Clinical Relevance: Continuing uncertainty exists over which patients will benefit from abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA)<lb/> repair in addition to medical therapy as well as which repair method, open or endovascular, is the most clinically and<lb/> cost-effective. Greater understanding of AAA development and progression, and the subsequent identification of<lb/> biomarkers for rupture risk, are likely to result in better selection of patients for intervention and provide better measures<lb/> of successful repair. These novel data implicate interleukin (IL)-1␣ in the molecular pathology of AAA. Further, they<lb/> suggest that IL-1␣ may be a predictive biomarker for AAA size as well as outcome after endovascular aneurysm repair.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">With respect to the management of abdominal aortic<lb/> aneurysms (AAAs), it is widely believed that the risks of<lb/> repair generally outweigh the risks of continued surveil-<lb/>lance until the AAA reaches 5.5 cm in maximum anterior-</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
