<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55009664"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Molecular Microbiology (1995) 18(1), 77-87<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>NPI1, an essential yeast gene involved in induced<lb/> degradation of Gap1 and Fur4 permeases, encodes the<lb/> Rsp5 ubiquitin-protein ligase<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Claudine Hein, it Jean-Yves Springael, it Christiane<lb/> Volland, 2 Rosine Haguenauer-Tsapis 2 and Bruno<lb/> Andrd 1.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>~ Laboratoire de Physiologie Cellulaire et de G~n~tique<lb/> des Levures, Universit~ Libre de Bruxelles,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Campus<lb/> Plaine CP 244, Bid du Triomphe, B-1050 Bruxelles,<lb/> Belgium.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>21nstitut Jacques Monod, Universit~ Paris VII,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2 place<lb/> Jussieu 75251, Paris Cedex 05, France.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Summary<lb/> When yeast cells growing on a poor nitrogen source<lb/> are supplied with NH~ ions, several nitrogen per-<lb/>meases including the general amino acid permease<lb/> (Gaplp) are rapidly and completely inactivated. This<lb/> report shows that inactivation by NH + of the Gap1 per-<lb/>mease is accompanied by its degradation. A functional<lb/> NPI1 gene product is required for both inactivation and<lb/> degradation of Gaplp. Molecular analysis of the NPI1<lb/> gene showed that it is identical to RSP5. The RSP5pro-<lb/>duct is a ubiquitin-protein ligase (E3 enzyme) whose<lb/> physiological function was, however, unknown. Its C-<lb/>terminal region is very similar to that of other mem-<lb/>bers of the E6-AP-like family of ubiquitin-protein<lb/> ligases. Its N-terminal region contains a single C2<lb/> domain that may be a Ca2+-dependent phospholipid<lb/> interaction motif, followed by several copies of a<lb/> recently identified domain called WW(P). The Npil/<lb/> Rsp5 protein has a homologue both in humans and<lb/> in mice, the latter being involved in brain development.<lb/> Stress-induced degradation of the uracil permease<lb/> (Fur4p), a process in which ubiquitin is probably<lb/> involved, was also found to require a functional NPI1/<lb/> RSP5 product. Chromosomal deletion of NPI1/RSP5<lb/> showed that this gene is essential for cell viability. In<lb/> the viable npil/rsp5 strain, expression of NPI1/RSP5<lb/> is reduced as a result of insertion of a Tyl element in<lb/> its 5&apos; region. Our results show that the Npil/Rsp5<lb/></div>

	<note type="submission">Received 17 May, 1995; revised 31 May, 1995; accepted 6 June,<lb/> 1995.</note>

	<note type="other">-J&apos;These authors contributed equally to this work. *For<lb/> correspondence.</note>

	<email>E-maU bran@ulb.ac.be;</email>

	<phone>Tel. (2) 6505411; Fax (2)<lb/> 6505421.<lb/> </phone>

	<note type="copyright">© 1995 Blackwell Science Ltd<lb/> </note>
	
	<div type="abstract">ubiquitin-protein ligase participates in induced degra-<lb/>dation of at least two permeases, Gaplp and Fur4p,<lb/> and probably also other proteins.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
