<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005071"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb/>
			<reference>Hindawi Publishing Corporation<lb/> EURASIP Journal on Advances in Signal
				Processing<lb/> Volume 2009, Article ID 783194, 14 pages<lb/>
			</reference>
			<idno>doi:10.1155/2009/783194<lb/></idno>

			<note type="other">Research Article<lb/></note>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>Kernel Principal Component Analysis for the
					Classification of<lb/> Hyperspectral Remote Sensing Data over Urban
					Areas<lb/></titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>Mathieu Fauvel, 1, 2 Jocelyn Chanussot, 1 and Jon Atli Benediktsson2<lb/></docAuthor>
			</byline>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>1 GIPSA-lab,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Grenoble INP, BP 46, 38402 Saint Martin d'Hères, France<lb/></address>

			<byline>
				<affiliation>2 Faculty of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of
					Iceland,</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<address>Hjardarhagi 2-6, 107 Reykjavik, Iceland<lb/></address>

			<note type="other">Correspondence should be addressed to Mathieu Fauvel</note>

			<email>, mathieu.fauvel@inrialpes.fr<lb/></email>

			<note type="submission">Received 2 September 2008; Revised 19 December 2008; Accepted 4 February 2009<lb/>
				Recommended by Mark Liao<lb/></note>

			<div type="abstract">Kernel principal component analysis (KPCA) is investigated for
				feature extraction from hyperspectral remote sensing data.<lb/> Features extracted
				using KPCA are classified using linear support vector machines. In one experiment,
				it is shown that kernel<lb/> principal component features are more linearly
				separable than features extracted with conventional principal component<lb/>
				analysis. In a second experiment, kernel principal components are used to construct
				the extended morphological profile (EMP).<lb/> Classification results, in terms of
				accuracy, are improved in comparison to original approach which used conventional
				principal<lb/> component analysis for constructing the EMP. Experimental results
				presented in this paper confirm the usefulness of the KPCA<lb/> for the analysis of
				hyperspectral data. For the one data set, the overall classification accuracy
				increases from 79% to 96% with the<lb/> proposed approach.<lb/>
			</div>
			<note type="copyright">
				Copyright © 2009 Mathieu Fauvel et al. This is an open access article distributed under the Creative
				Commons Attribution<lb/> License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
				reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly<lb/>
				cited.<lb/>
			</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
