<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55005742"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">297<lb/> </note>
	
	<note>1064-7562/02/1100-0297/0</note>

	<note type="copyright">© 2003 Plenum Publishing Corporation<lb/></note>

	<reference>Journal of Materials Synthesis and Processing, Vol. 10, No. 6, November 2002</reference>
	
	<note type="copyright"> (© 2003)<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Synthesis and Characterization of Mesoporous<lb/> Manganese Oxides<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Xinlin Hong,<lb/> 1 Gaoyong Zhang,<lb/> 1,2,3 Hengquan Yang,<lb/> 1 and Yinyan Zhu<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">1<lb/> Mesoporous manganese oxide (MPMO) K 0.216 MnO 2 и 1.26H 2 O was synthesized by reduction of<lb/> KMnO 4 with maleic acid. Its composition and structure were analyzed and characterized by induc-<lb/>tive coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometry (ICP-AES), titration, X-ray powder diffractom-<lb/>etry (XRD), thermogravimetry (TG)-differential thermoanalysis (DTA). The morphology and pore<lb/> structure of the MPMO material were accomplished by means of high-resolution transmission elec-<lb/>tron microscopy (HRTEM) and N 2 sorptometry and transmission electron microscopy (TEM). The<lb/> results show that MPMO is a pseudocrystalline material with complex network pore structure; its<lb/> BET surface area is 261.6 m<lb/> 2 /g and pore diameter distribution is approximately in the range of<lb/> 2–10 nm. The MPMO material turns into a-MnO 2 when the calcinating temperature rises to 400°C.<lb/> KEY WORDS: Mesoporous manganese oxide (MPMO); pseudocrystalline; complex network pore structure.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 School of Chemistry and Molecular Science, Wuhan University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wuhan 430072, P. R. China.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 China Research Institute of Daily Chemical Industry,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Taiyuan<lb/> 030001, P. R. China.<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">3 To whom all correspondence should be addressed.</note>

	<email>e-mail:<lb/> RIDCI@public.ty.sx.cn<lb/></email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
