<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55008084"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">You are here: Tobacco Asia<lb/> Features Hauni Highlights 2010<lb/> Search...<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Hauni Highlights 2010<lb/> Staff Report<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="introduction">Japan expects perfection<lb/> The double-track rod charcoal filter line consisting of KDF-M teamed with AC-M<lb/> is undergoing tests to determine how well it can process the materials needed to<lb/> make specially demanding products.<lb/> As tests in various standard areas of production have already shown, the new<lb/> KDF-M double-track filter line puts 100% shift efficiency within reach. In 2009<lb/> Japan Tobacco International (JTI) carried out a series of extensive tests at its<lb/> German location in Trier which confirmed the line&apos;s high productivity figure.<lb/> The charcoal filter line – KDF-M teamed up with an AC-M charcoal feeder – is<lb/> now in Tokyo where it is undergoing further tests at Japan Filter Technology<lb/> (JFT) to assess how well it can cope with more extreme demands. These tests<lb/> include processing highly porous papers and making filters that contain more<lb/> than the standard amount of active charcoal.<lb/> &quot;The first tests were the compulsory exercises, and this is what you might call the freestyle part,&quot; comments Gunnar Tons, head of Product<lb/> Management Filter at Hauni. &quot;Japan is a key market for charcoal filters,&quot; says Hauni Project manager Ralf Meyer, explaining why JFT<lb/> expects such high standards in the production of high-granule-density active charcoal filters. &quot;It was a conscious decision on our part to<lb/> tackle this difficult area with the KDF-M/AC-M line. Showing we are able to master the challenge will send out a clear message to the<lb/> marketplace.&quot;<lb/> From the outset, Hauni and JFT decided to approach the job of developing the charcoal filter line&apos;s full potential in the form of a joint project.<lb/> As it approaches completion, Hauni already recognises the tremendous value of working with JFT. &quot;The past few weeks have turned up a<lb/> number of key points that will make our line even better. Wherever feasible we intend to implement these straight away at the facility,&quot; says<lb/> Ralf Meyer on behalf of his team in Tokyo.<lb/> The joint project has led to the double-track filter line being fitted with valuable features like a suction unit in the tow processing area and<lb/> modifica-tions to optimise glue application. And it now features an entirely new accessory: an integrated dust removal system to keep the<lb/> machine clean.<lb/> Masaru Atsumi, Sub Project leader at JFT, also takes a positive view of the progress made so far.<lb/> &quot;KDF-M is a good machine. Filters have small variations of pressure drop and circumference as well as good appearances,&quot; he said. &quot;I<lb/> appreciate cooperation with Hauni, working together for a high target.&quot;<lb/> High moisture, white portions<lb/> As one of the world&apos;s first commercially available machines, HAUNI&apos;S<lb/> SEALUTION TS 1000 can process snus tobacco with up to 55% initial moisture<lb/> to form non-remoisturised &quot;white portions&quot;, the snus market&apos;s premium product.<lb/> And that&apos;s not all: Hauni now offers equipment covering all steps in the snus<lb/> process chain from pouch making to packing in shipping boxes.<lb/> There has been a long wait for anything innovative to happen in the process of<lb/> manufacturing snus portions (pouches), a product sold in small portion-sized<lb/> bags designed to be tucked under the user&apos;s upper lip. Extra-moist snus is a<lb/> variant which is gaining more and more popularity. The snus tobacco, often blended with aromas enhancing the natural tobacco taste, is so<lb/> moist that it helps to release the flavourings in the pouch as soon as it is in place, affording an immediately pleasurable experience. Yet<lb/> moist tobacco has a drawback: when remoisturized and squeezed into conventional snus tins, the pouches end up with an unsightly,<lb/> brownish appearance.<lb/> Now, a technical innovation evolved by Hauni in conjunction with MediSeal, another company of the Körber Group, makes it possible to<lb/> combine high moisture content with attractive appearance. SEALUTION TS 1000 processes tobacco containing up to 55% moisture into<lb/> evenly filled &quot;white portions&quot;, a name earned by this top-of-the-range product on account of its immaculate appearance. And it achieves all<lb/> that at speeds up to 1,000 portion bags per minute. The first moist snus machine of this type, completed just a few weeks ago, has<lb/> meanwhile been delivered to the Danish firm Assens Tobaksfabrik. The tobacco company, established in 1864, has just started a state-<lb/>of-the-art Swedish snus factory in Assens. As owners Georg and Alex Gundersen always said: If there&apos;s a way to do it, Hauni will find it!<lb/> The &quot;TS&quot; in SEALUTION TS 1000 stands for tobacco stick pack while the figure denotes its speed – the machine will make up to 1,000<lb/> portion bags per minute on a maximum of 16 parallel tracks designed to ensure that the pouches are evenly filled with tobacco. &quot;Our secret is the new dosing method. Metering moist tobacco is particularly difficult as it quickly gets sticky,&quot; explains Thomas Gruss,<lb/> Business Development manager Hauni. Gruss has spent the last two years working on the job of implementing a &quot;1000&quot; model for moist<lb/> snus. The new metering unit was developed on SEALUTION TS 80 and TS 1000, both already established on the market. The result, a<lb/> sliding gate feeder, presents an alternative to the micro-piston metering system which will continue to be used for dry snus (? 20%<lb/> moisture). The sliding gate method involves compressing the loose tobacco into stick form for easier handling, and then applying a brief<lb/> burst of air to loosen it again before feeding it into bags. Being a modular system, SEALUTION TS 1000 can be configured with 2 to 16<lb/> tracks, depending on the pouch format. &quot;SEALUTION&apos;s modular principle appeals to customers. As all components are indexed, extensions or conversions are quick and<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">QUART ER 3, 2011<lb/> To View E-magazine manu<lb/> Log in or Register (free)<lb/> HOT T O PICS<lb/> PROTOBEX ASIA: FINALLY<lb/> THERE IS A CHOICE<lb/> HOME LATEST ISSUE<lb/> PREVIOUS ISSUES<lb/> E-MAGAZINE<lb/> 中文版。 ADVERTISING<lb/> SUBSCRIBE LOGIN<lb/> EVENTS CONTACT US<lb/> Hauni Highlights 2010<lb/></note>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.tobaccoasia.com/features/324-hauni-highlights-2010.html<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="page">1 of 2<lb/></note>

	<date>26-09-2011</date>

	<note type="other">16:25</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
