<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55001189"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>AIDS PATIENT CARE and STDs<lb/> Volume 21, Number 11, 2007<lb/></reference>
	
	<note type="copyright"> © Mary Ann Liebert, Inc.<lb/></note>

	<idno type ="DOI">DOI: 10.1089/apc.2006.0210<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Review<lb/>Kidney Disease in the HIV-Infected Patient<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>DEREK M. FINE, M.D. and MOHAMED G. ATTA, M.D., M.P.H.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> As survival has improved in the highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) era, the preva-<lb/>lence of kidney disease is increasing in the aging HIV-infected population. Since HIV-spe-<lb/>cific kidney disease, particularly human immunodeficiency virus-associated nephropathy<lb/> (HIVAN), incidence has remained stable if not declining in the HAART era, the rising rates<lb/> reflect to a great extent increases in kidney disease seen in the general population due to hy-<lb/>pertension and diabetes. In addition, HIV-infected patients are exposed to toxicities of anti-<lb/>retrovirals and other drugs. There is also a disproportionate prevalence of HIV in black Amer-<lb/>icans, who have a higher risk of kidney disease and the associated risk factors. Because of<lb/> the high rates of kidney disease, screening for kidney dysfunction is recommended at the<lb/> time of HIV diagnosis. Because kidney disease is usually asymptomatic, effective screening<lb/> will include assessment of risk factors and markers of kidney disease, specifically estima-<lb/>tions of glomerular filtration rate using serum creatinine and quantification of urine protein.<lb/> Upon identification of renal dysfunction, the differential diagnosis may be broad, including<lb/> etiologies common in the general population as well as HIV-specific causes. Although clini-<lb/>cal diagnoses can be made, a kidney biopsy is often necessary. Regardless of the cause of kid-<lb/>ney disease, early identification, accurate diagnosis and consequent appropriate management<lb/> are likely to result in improved outcomes. Success in confronting this growing problem can<lb/> only be achieved with better understanding of kidney diseases affecting the HIV population.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
