<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55013019"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">287<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Detection of Proarrhythmia in the Female Rabbit Heart:<lb/> Blinded Validation<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>LUC M. HONDEGHEM, M.D., PH.D., HUA RONG LU, M.D., PH.D.,*<lb/> KOEN VAN ROSSEM, M.D., PH.D.,* and FRED DE CLERCK, M.SC., PH.D.*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>From the Department of Pharmacology, K.U. Leuven, Leuven, Belgium; and *Center of Excellence<lb/> for Cardiovascular Safety Research, Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development,<lb/>a Division of Janssen Pharmaceutica,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Beerse, Belgium<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Validation of Proarrhythmia Detection. Introduction: Reliable detection of drug-induced proar-<lb/>rhythmia, especially the potential for polymorphic ventricular tachycardia, is of great importance in the<lb/> development of new compounds that are safe for the heart and was evaluated in a blinded study.<lb/> Methods and Results: In 142 female rabbits, the monophasic action potential was used to determine<lb/> intraventricular conduction, action potential duration (APD), triangulation (APD 30 to APD 90 ), reverse use-<lb/>dependence, instability and presence of chaotic behavior, early afterdepolarizations, torsades de pointes<lb/> (TdP), and ventricular fibrillation. In addition, 31 coded drugs were tested in a blinded fashion in another<lb/> 150 hearts. Prototype cardiovascular agents [quinidine (IA), lidocaine (IB), flecainide (IC), propranolol<lb/> (II), sotalol (IIIB), amiodarone (IIIAB) and verapamil (IV)] were correctly characterized in terms of their<lb/> effects upon conduction and APD. Agents documented in clinical practice to have proarrhythmic potential<lb/> (droperidol, sotalol, mibefradil, bepridil, lidoflazine, ketanserin, sertindole, terfenadine, haloperidol, astem-<lb/>izole, cisapride, ziprasidone, lubeluzole, dofetilide, quinidine, ibutilide) were identified as such. Pimozide<lb/> is reported to rarely produce TdP and was also found to elicit Class III action with few adverse effects.<lb/> Equally important, agents believed not to be proarrhythmic (two solvents, atenolol, propranolol, fenox-<lb/>imone, cetirizine, verapamil, sildenafil, lidocaine, diltiazem) were identified as having no proarrhythmic<lb/> activity.<lb/> Conclusion: The SCREENIT method properly characterized and quantified prototype cardiovascular<lb/> drugs and correctly identified proarrhythmic noncardiovascular agents of various mechanisms, but it did<lb/> not produce false-positive results.</div>

	<reference>(J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol, Vol. 14, pp. 287-294, March 2003)<lb/></reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
