<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55010012"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Automatically Translated by the Intellectual Property Publishing House of SIPO<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="introduction">Embodiment of this invention has disclosed a kind of wireless data card, comprisings:<lb/> Strengthen the power interface module, is used for offering and strengthening the<lb/> interface that the power couples, obtain the power from strengthening the power; The<lb/> power interface module of common serial interface, are used for connecting with<lb/> common serial interface, obtain the power from the common serial interface; Host<lb/> processor, are used for measuring and inserting and strengthening the power interface<lb/> module and power signal of the common serial interface power interface module,<lb/> according to the detected power signal, emerging controls the power signal; Power<lb/> amplifier, are used in according to controlling the power signal, regulate the<lb/> transmitted power of the wireless data card. Embodiment of this invention also<lb/> disclosed a method for regulating the transmitted power of the wireless data card at<lb/> the same time. Employ this invention, can supply power according to the power the<lb/> state controls the wireless radio transmitted power, improve the wireless radio<lb/> transmitted power, ensure the wireless transmissive characteristic.<lb/> A method for regulating the transmitted power of the wireless data card and wireless<lb/> data card<lb/> Technical field<lb/> This invention involves the technology of power regulation, especially involve a<lb/> method for regulating the transmitted power of the wireless data card and wireless<lb/> data card.<lb/> Background technology<lb/> With the development of wireless network, a large number of portable machines<lb/> enter the Internet through the wireless data card. Because of the common serial<lb/> interface (USB, Universal Serial Bus) mass use, the wireless data card is often made<lb/> the wireless data card (USB Dongle) of common serial interface, namely cross USB<lb/> mouth and obtain the power, pass USB mouth and the personal computer (PC at the<lb/> same time in wireless data cartoon, PersonalComputer) carries on data<lb/> communication.<lb/> The wireless data card of the prior art, in order to achieve the goal of obtaining the<lb/> best communication result and controlling the power consumption, control the radio<lb/> transmitted power by software, that is to act as the wireless data card relatively far<lb/> from the base station, when the wireless signal is greater in transmission attenuation,<lb/> increase the radio transmitted power of the wireless data card through software<lb/> control, the power consumption increases correspondingly too at this moment; It is<lb/> relatively near to act as wireless data card and distance of base station, the<lb/> transmission attenuation of the wireless signal is smaller, when quality is better, can<lb/> reduce the transmitted power through software control, thus can reduce the power<lb/> consumption.<lb/> USB Dongle in the prior art, through obtaining the power from USB mouth of PC,<lb/> carries on data transmission with PC through USB mouth at the same time. And the<lb/> general USB host computer (HOST) maximum ability of supplying power to the<lb/> outside is 5V 0.5A, namely the maximum power of supplying power to the outside is<lb/> 2.5W, so, it must be smaller than 2.5W to require the maximum power consumption<lb/> of USB Dongle, therefore make the transmitted power of USB Dongle limited, it can&apos;t<lb/> be too big.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
