<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55012218"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">1<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Foam Enhancement<lb/>Gelling<lb/> Thickening<lb/> Film Formation<lb/> Stabilization METHOCEL cellulose ethers<lb/> 
	</note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Multifunctional water-soluble<lb/> polymers that enhance foams,<lb/> form fi lms, thicken, and stabilize<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="page">2<lb/> </note>

	<div type="abstract">METHOCEL * cellulose ethers are an extensive family of methylcellulose<lb/> (MC) and hydroxypropyl methylcellulose (HPMC) polymers that are used<lb/> globally in many personal care products. They are primarily used as<lb/> polymeric surfactants, thickeners in liquid formulations, and as binders in<lb/> solid and semi-solid products. However, the ability of METHOCEL products<lb/> to perform these primary functions with reliability and effi ciency is only<lb/> part of the reason for their increasing popularity with formu lators…even 70<lb/> years after the intro duction of the METHOCEL family.<lb/> </div>

	<div type="introduction">The reason is the host of important performance properties that these<lb/> multi-functional ingredients deliver. In many cases a METHOCEL product can<lb/> replace two, three, or more ingredients, even though it is added in extremely<lb/> low concentrations.<lb/> Beyond offering thickening, binding and surface active properties,<lb/> METHOCEL products act as fi lm formers, suspension aids, lubricants, lather<lb/> enhancers/stabilizers, emulsion stabilizers and gelling agents. It is this<lb/> unique combination of properties that sets METHOCEL cellulose ethers<lb/> apart from other water soluble polymers. The result is an ability to improve<lb/> personal care product formulations. It also allows the creation of entirely<lb/> new hair care, skin care, bath and cosmetic products because product<lb/> performance can often be achieved with fewer ingredients, greater control,<lb/> and greater economy.<lb/> This guide has been prepared to further introduce you to the family<lb/> of METHOCEL MC and HPMC products and serve as an idea-starter. Its<lb/> goal is to provide you with the information to begin formulating with these<lb/> polymers (as well as the many reasons for doing so). We realize, however,<lb/> that not all of your questions may be answered. Please call us at the<lb/> numbers listed on the back cover for further technical assistance.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
