<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55012278"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>African Journal of Biotechnology Vol. 8 (19), pp. 4996-5004, 5 October, 2009<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">Available online at</note>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.academicjournals.org/AJB<lb/></ptr>

	<idno>ISSN 1684–5315</idno>

	<note type="copyright">© 2009 Academic Journals<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Full Length Research Paper<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Production of freeze-dried lactic acid bacteria starter<lb/> culture for cassava fermentation into gari<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Amenan A. Yao<lb/> 1<lb/> *, Carine Dortu<lb/> 2<lb/> , Moutairou Egounlety<lb/> 3<lb/> , Cristina Pinto<lb/> 4<lb/> , Vinodh A. Edward<lb/> 4<lb/> , Melanie Huch (née Kostinek)<lb/> 5<lb/> , Charles M. A. P. Franz<lb/> 5<lb/> , Willhelm Holzapfel<lb/> 5<lb/> , Samuel Mbugua<lb/> 6<lb/> , Moses Mengu<lb/> 7<lb/> and Philippe Thonart<lb/> 1,2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Wallon Center for Industrial Biology, University of Liège,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Belgium.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> Bio-Industry Unit, Gembloux Agricultural University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Belgium.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> University of Bénin,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Abomey-Calavi, Bénin.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4<lb/> Council for Scientific and Industrial Research, CSIR Biosciences, </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>South Africa.<lb/> </address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>5<lb/> Max Rubner Institute for Nutrition,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Germany.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6<lb/> University of Nairobi,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>University Way, Kenya.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>7<lb/> Botswana Technology Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Botswana.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Accepted 1 June, 2009<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Sixteen lactic acid bacteria, eight Lactobacillus plantarum, three L. pentosus, 2 Weissella<lb/> paramesenteroides, two L. fermemtum and one Leuconostoc mesenteroides ssp. mesenteroides were<lb/> previously isolated from cassava fermentation and selected on the basis of their biochemical properties<lb/> with a view to selecting appropriate starter cultures during cassava fermentation for gari production. In<lb/> this study, the potential of these pre-selected strains as suitable freeze-dried cultures was evaluated.<lb/> Their ability to tolerate the freeze-drying process was assessed by dehydration in a glycerol solution of<lb/> increasing concentration, followed by staining with two fluorescent markers: rhodamine 123 and<lb/> propydium iodide. Twelve strains that recovered more than 50% of their population value after<lb/> visualisation on an epi-fluorescent microscope were produced in a bioreactor and freeze-dried. The<lb/> technological characteristics identified after the freeze-drying process, were a high cell concentration<lb/> or high survival rate. The ability of the freeze-dried strains to recover their acidification activity was<lb/> evaluated through the determination of the pH, titratable acidity (% lactic acid/g Dry Weight) and cell<lb/> count over 24 h on MRS broth. Ultimately, the strains L. plantarum VE36, G2/25, L. fermentum G2/10 and<lb/> W. paramesenteroides LC11 were selected to be developed as freeze-dried starter cultures for gari<lb/> production.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key words: Freeze-drying, gari, lactic acid bacteria, fermentation, starter culture, cassava, developing<lb/> countries, fermented food.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
