<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55010770"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Proceedings of the NAACL HLT Student Research Workshop and Doctoral Consortium, pages 61–65,<lb/> Boulder, Colorado, June 2009. </reference>

	<note type="copyright">&#169;<lb/>2009 Association for Computational Linguistics<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Loss-Sensitive Discriminative Training of Machine Transliteration Models<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Kedar Bellare<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Computer Science<lb/> University of Massachusetts Amherst<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Amherst, MA 01003, USA<lb/></address>

	<email>kedarb@cs.umass.edu<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Koby Crammer<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Computer Science<lb/> University of Pennsylvania<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA<lb/></address>

	<email>crammer@cis.upenn.edu<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dayne Freitag<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>SRI International<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>San Diego, CA 92130, USA<lb/></address>

	<email>dayne.freitag@sri.com<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> In machine transliteration we transcribe a<lb/> name across languages while maintaining its<lb/> phonetic information. In this paper, we<lb/> present a novel sequence transduction algo-<lb/>rithm for the problem of machine transliter-<lb/>ation. Our model is discriminatively trained<lb/> by the MIRA algorithm, which improves the<lb/> traditional Perceptron training in three ways:<lb/> (1) It allows us to consider k-best translitera-<lb/>tions instead of the best one. (2) It is trained<lb/> based on the ranking of these transliterations<lb/> according to user-specified loss function (Lev-<lb/>enshtein edit distance). (3) It enables the user<lb/> to tune a built-in parameter to cope with noisy<lb/> non-separable data during training. On an<lb/> Arabic-English name transliteration task, our<lb/> model achieves a relative error reduction of<lb/> 2.2% over a perceptron-based model with sim-<lb/>ilar features, and an error reduction of 7.2%<lb/> over a statistical machine translation model<lb/> with more complex features.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
