<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55013721"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>The 10th International Conference on Miniaturized Systems for Chemistry and Life Sciences (μTAS2006)<lb/> November 5-9, 2006, Tokyo, Japan<lb/></reference>

	<note>4-9903269-0-3-C3043</note>

	<note type="copyright">© 2006 Society for Chemistry and Micro-Nano Systems<lb/></note>

	<note type="page">642<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A NOVEL INTEGRATED MICROFLUIDIC SERS-CD WITH<lb/> HIGH-THROUGHPUT CENTRIFUGAL CELL TRAPPING<lb/> ARRAY FOR QUANTITATIVE BIOMEDICINE<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hansang Cho and Luke P. Lee<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Biomolecular Nanotechnology Center, Berkeley Sensor and Actuator Center<lb/> Department of Bioengineering, University of California,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Berkeley, CA 94720 USA<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract Integrated microfluidic surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy on a compact disk<lb/> (SERS-CD) platform has been developed for high-throughput quantitative biomedicine.<lb/> A smart design of a SERS-CD platform including efficient cell-trapping microfluidics, a<lb/> locally integrated SERS probe, and a sample-accumulating concentrator is a solution for<lb/> label-free high-throughput screening and detection. A SERS probe combined with a<lb/> protein concentrator allows monitoring the dynamics of secreted proteins as a function<lb/> of trapped cell density, accumulation time, and the induced centrifugal force. The<lb/> design of centrifugal cell trapping microfluidics was characterized by using polystyrene<lb/> beads and HeLa cells and the preliminary evaluation of a centrifugal sample<lb/> concentrator on a SERS probe was accomplished by observing the increased Raman<lb/> spectrum of Rhodamin 6G (R6G) as the molecule accumulated on the probe.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keyword: quantitative cell analysis, centrifugal concentrator, centrifugal<lb/> separation, cell trapping, SERS, SERS-CD<lb/>
	</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
