<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55010458"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Tetrahedron Letters No.16, pp. 1091-1099, 1965. Pergamon Press Ltd<lb/> Printed in Great Britain.<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>LAURENCIN, A CONSTITUENT FROM LAURENCIA SPECIES&apos;<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Toshi Irie, Minoru Suzuki and Tadashi Masamune<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, Hokkaido University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sapporo, Japan<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">(Received 27 January 1965; in revised form 1 hfarch 1965)<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">An investigation of constituents from Laurencia glandulifera,<lb/> Kiit.zing,* led to the isolation of a compound containing bromine, which<lb/> was designated laurencin. In the present paper we wish to report that<lb/> formula (I) is the most favorable structure for the compound.<lb/> Laurencin (I), m.p. 73-74&apos; (methanol) and [d]i3 +70:2&apos; (in chloroform),<lb/> was obtained in 0.035% yield by chromatographic purificatior of the neutral<lb/> fraction from methanol extracts, and was analyzed for C H 0 Br (Found:<lb/> 17 23 3<lb/> C, 57.42, 57.31; H, 6.54, 6.40; Br, 22.15; mol. wt. 354 and 356, from the<lb/> mass spectrum). The infrared spectrum suggested the presence of a termina<lb/> methine ( 3zio1<lb/> 3285 and 2100 Cm-l), an acetoxyl (1735 and 1230 cm-&apos;)<lb/> and an ether group (1168 and 1080 cm-l), and trans and &amp;<lb/> double bonds<lb/> (3040, 950 and 750 cm<lb/> -1<lb/> ); and the ultraviolet spectrum (in ethanol),<lb/> a max<lb/> 224 mi_&apos; (E 16,400) ar.d hinfl<lb/> 232 mp (E ll,OOO), showed the<lb/> presence of a conjugated diene or enyne. The N.M.R. spectrum3 (FIG. 1)<lb/> indicated the presence of four olefinic protons (the absorptions A, B and<lb/> C; abbr. H-A, H-B and H-C) and an acetoxyl group (K), and also suggested<lb/> the existence of an ethyl group (N, triplet). The latter was confirmed<lb/> by isolation of propionaldehyde on ozonization4 of I. However, only one<lb/> proton is involved in the absorption M and, therefore, two protons of the<lb/> methylene adjacent to the methyl group are not magnetically equivalent. 5<lb/> Another proton<lb/> was<lb/> found as a multiplet (L&apos;) in L, which was confirmed by<lb/> 1091</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
