<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55011443"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Typical pulse as measured with<lb/> THz-TDS.<lb/> Fourier transform of the above<lb/> pulse.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Terahertz time-domain spectroscopy<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="other">From Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia<lb/>This is an old revision of this page, as edited by Lightbot (talk | contribs) at<lb/> 07:06, 22 November 2008. It may differ significantly from the current<lb/> revision (//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terahertz_time-domain_spectroscopy) .<lb/> (diff) ← Previous revision | Latest revision (diff) | Newer revision → (diff)<lb/>
	</note>

	<div type="abstract">In physics, terahertz time-domain spectroscopy<lb/> (THz-TDS) is a spectroscopic technique where a<lb/> special generation and detection scheme is used to<lb/> probe material properties with short pulses of<lb/> terahertz radiation. The generation and detection<lb/> scheme is sensitive to the sample material&apos;s effect<lb/> on both the amplitude and the phase of the terahertz<lb/> radiation. In this respect, the technique can provide<lb/> more information than conventional Fourier-<lb/>transform spectroscopy that is only sensitive to the<lb/> amplitude.<lb/> The radiation has several distinct advantages over<lb/> other forms of spectroscopy: many materials are<lb/> transparent to THz, THz radiation is safe for<lb/> biological tissues because it is non-ionizing (unlike<lb/> for example X-rays), and images formed with<lb/> terahertz radiation can have relatively good<lb/> resolution (less than 1 mm). Also, many interesting<lb/> materials have unique spectral fingerprints in the<lb/> terahertz range, which means that terahertz radiation<lb/> can be used to identify them. Examples which have<lb/> been demonstrated include several different types of explosives, polymorphic forms of<lb/> many compounds used as Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients (API) in commercial<lb/> medications as well as several illegal narcotic substances. Again, as many materials<lb/> are quite transparent to THz radiation, these items of interest can be observed through<lb/> normally opaque intervening layers (packaging, clothing). Additionally, though not<lb/> strictly a spectroscopic technique, the ultrashort width of the THz radiation pulses<lb/> allows for measurements (e.g., thickness, density, defect location) on difficult to probe<lb/> materials (e.g., foam). The measurement capability shares many similarities to that<lb/> observed with pulsed ultrasonic systems. Reflections off buried interfaces and defects<lb/> can be found and precisely imaged. THz measurements are non-contact however.<lb/> Typically, the terahertz pulses are generated by an ultrashort pulsed laser and last only<lb/> a few picoseconds. A single pulse can contain frequency components covering the<lb/> whole terahertz range from 0.05 to 4 THz. For detection, the electrical field of the<lb/> terahertz pulse is sampled and digitized, conceptually similar to the way an audio card<lb/> transforms electrical voltage levels in an audio signal into numbers that describe the<lb/> audio waveform. In THz-TDS, the electrical field of the THz pulse interacts in the<lb/></div>

	<note type="page">Page 1 of 5<lb/> </note>

	<note type="other">Terahertz time-domain spectroscopy -Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia<lb/></note>

	<date>07-11-2011<lb/></date>

	<ptr type="web">http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Terahertz_time-domain_spectroscopy&amp;oldid=253350085<lb/></ptr>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
