<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55010049"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">1<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>E-LEARNING IN THE SEMANTIC AGE<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Matthias Palmér<lb/> Ambjörn Naeve<lb/> Mikael Nilsson<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>The KMR (Knowledge Management Research) group<lb/> CID (Centre for user oriented IT Design)<lb/> NADA (Numerical Analysis and Computing Science)<lb/> KTH (Royal Institute of Technology)<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>100 44 Stockholm, Sweden<lb/></address>

	<email>[amb|mini|matthias@nada.kth.se]<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Today educational technologies are reaching a state that allows interoperability and<lb/> reuse of learning resources. The underlying techniques rely heavily on the standards<lb/> movement for metadata representation. On top of this, monolithic reference<lb/> platforms are being developed with the aim to ease application development.<lb/> However, we do not think this approach is flexible enough to embrace future<lb/> learning techniques. In contrast, we suggest a learning framework where services can<lb/> be developed and exchanged between as well as within systems. A fundamental part<lb/> of this framework is the semantic layer, which builds on the structure of the Semantic<lb/> Web. Hence we do not regard metadata as something &apos;objective&apos; that you have to<lb/> download from some central server. On the contrary, metadata should be allowed to<lb/> consist of subjective views of resources that are distributed and shared in contexts<lb/> that can evolve dynamically. In support of such requirements, our learning<lb/> framework consists of a combination of semantic web techniques and peer-to-peer<lb/> services for search, retrieval, publication, replication and mapping of metadata.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>KEYWORDS</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
