<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55011573"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Sixth International Workshop Advances in Signal Processing for Non Destructive Evaluation of Materials (2009)<lb/>
	</note>

	<note type="other">*)</note>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Salzgitter Mannesmann Forschung GmbH,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Ehinger Str. 200, 47259 Duisburg, Germany,</address>

	<email>t.orth@du.szmf.de<lb/></email>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Wavelet Signal Processing of Magnetic Flux<lb/> Leakage Signals -Implementation of a<lb/> Multichannel Wavelet-Filter for<lb/> Nondestructive Testing Systems in Steel<lb/> Tube Mills<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Thomas ORTH*, Till SCHMITTE </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Salzgitter Mannesmann Forschung, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Duisburg, Germany<lb/> </address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Robert PETERS, Klaus-Dieter MÜLLER, Ashraf KOKA, Stefan NITSCHE,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<address>V&amp;M Deutschland, Düsseldorf, Germany<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract. Magnetic flux leakage testing is one of the most important NDT methods<lb/> for seamless steel tubes. In order to increase the sensitivity of the inspection, diverse<lb/> signal processing techniques are already applied. As an alternative to conventional<lb/> filter techniques, wavelet filtering reveals a higher separation of the signal to the<lb/> noise level together with an improved adaptation to the signal structure. For the im-<lb/>plementation of wavelet filtering into existing third party systems, a multichannel<lb/> DSP-hardware has been developed, which is capable to filter 32 sensor signals si-<lb/>multaneously. The results show a significant improvement of the signal to noise ra-<lb/>tio. Furthermore, it is possible to dispend with the commonly applied differential<lb/> sensor technique so that a wider range of defect types can be detected.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
