<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55013276"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Midwest Biological Control News Online<lb/> July 1995, Vol. II No. 7<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Field Crops News<lb/> 1. Natural Enemies of Spider Mites on Field Corn<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="introduction">Spider mites are very small arthropods, usually less than 1 mm in length, that<lb/> can be severe pests of field corn. The Banks grass mite (Oligonychus pratensis)<lb/> and the twospotted spider mite (Tetranychus urticae) are the two most common<lb/> mite pest species on field corn grown in the Midwest. The Banks grass mite<lb/> feeds specifically on grass plants, whereas the twospotted spider mite will feed<lb/> on a wide variety of plants including soybeans, alfalfa and apple trees. On many<lb/> crops, including field corn, spider mite problems may be increased when natural<lb/> enemies are destroyed by applications of broad-spectrum insecticides applied<lb/> against other pests. Several species of naturally occurring insects and mites<lb/> prey on spider mites. The most important of these include a predatory mite the<lb/> fallacis mite, Neoseiulus fallacis; a lady beetle the spider mite destroyer,<lb/> Stethorus punctum; a predaceous thrips the six-spotted thrips, Scolothrips<lb/> sexmaculatus; and minute pirate bugs, Orius spp. In addition to these<lb/> arthropods, the fungal pathogens, Neozygites spp., are also important in<lb/> reducing spider mite populations.<lb/> The fallacis mite is the most important spider mite predator found in corn fields. These<lb/> mites are slightly larger than the pest mites, pear-shaped, and uniformly pale brown or<lb/> straw-colored. In addition, they do not have the dark pigmentation characteristic of the<lb/> pest mite species. Fallacis mite eggs are laid in pest mite colonies and under summer<lb/> conditions hatch in 1.5 days. After hatching, the juveniles feed on 4 pest mite eggs per<lb/> day for the 8 days which it takes them to reach the adult stage. Female mites will mate<lb/> and begin to lay about 3 eggs per day for about 13 days. Adult mites eat about 15 mites<lb/> per day for the 70 days that they survive. This consumption rate varys depending on the<lb/> density of pest mites, but when they are present, the fallacis mite can quickly build its<lb/> population and significantly reduce pest mite numbers.<lb/> The spider mite destroyer is a small (about 2 mm long) black lady beetle which can eat<lb/> up to 40 mites or mite eggs each day it lives. The adult beetles lay eggs in active mite<lb/> colonies. After 5 days, eggs hatch and larvae begin to feed on mite eggs. The larvae are<lb/> gray and cylindrical, growing in about 17 days to 2 mm long at maturity. The adult<lb/> beetles are relatively long-lived with a life span of over 1 year. Adults hibernate during<lb/> the winter months in leaf litter and other organic debris. Females lay eggs for about 67<lb/> days and are capable of producing 750 offspring. These predators are usually most<lb/> numerous when the pest mite population is also high.<lb/> The six-spotted thrips is a small (2 mm long), tan, cigar-shaped insect, with long narrow<lb/> wings fringed with hairs. Thrips eggs are laid in the leaf where they hatch in 7 days.<lb/> There are 4 larval stages, of which 2 are active. During the active stages the larvae eat 10<lb/> mite eggs per day over a period of 10 days. When adult thrips emerge, they feed on<lb/> about 60 mite eggs per day over a 30 day life span.<lb/> Minute pirate bugs are small insects (2 mm long) but can be important predators of<lb/> insect eggs and spider mites in both the immature and adult stages. The immature bugs<lb/> (nymphs) are orange and wingless, whereas the adults are black, with white triangles at<lb/> the tips of the wings. These bugs are usually found in protected places on the plant, such<lb/> as the whorl, tassels, leaf axils, corn husks or corn silks. Eggs are laid in the leaf collar<lb/> tissue and hatch in about 4 days. Nymphs go through 5 stages in 9 days. The adults live<lb/> an additional 26 days and the females lay an average of 45 eggs. Each Orius adult or<lb/> nymph can eat 30 or more spider mites per day. Orius are generalist predators which<lb/> makes their presence highly desirable since they can survive on other prey (insect eggs,<lb/> small caterpillars) or pollen if pest mite populations are low.<lb/> In addition to predatory arthropods, naturally occurring fungal pathogens can, under the<lb/> proper conditions, easily provide complete control of a spider mite infestation.<lb/> Neozygites floridana has been identified from spider mites in the southeastern portion of<lb/> the country, whereas the predominant fungal species attacking Banks grass mite in<lb/> western Kansas has been identified as N. adjarica. If several cooler (&lt;80-85F), damp<lb/> days occur together, these pathogens have an excellent opportunity to infect and kill<lb/> spider mites. Infected mites become shriveled and brown, and die quickly. If weather<lb/> conditions favoring fungal propagation occur, a re-evaluation of the pest mite population<lb/> should be undertaken before making any pest control decisions.<lb/> At this time the full impact of these natural enemies on pest mite infestations it is not<lb/> known, but during many years they are important in keeping spider mite populations<lb/> below economic levels. They are particularly effective during cooler, moist periods in<lb/> early and mid-summer when pest mite reproduction is slowed. Although high<lb/> temperatures do not reduce the development rate of the fallacis mite, low relative<lb/> humidity may be the cause of low adult survival and high egg mortality. Researchers<lb/> have shown (using a simulation model) that under conditions of higher humidity, such as<lb/> those found in well watered, non-stressed field corn, the fallacis mite can completely<lb/> control Banks grass mite. Less is known about the effect of climatic conditions on the<lb/> other natural enemies, but they also seem to be more efficient in cooler conditions with<lb/> higher relative humidity. For these reasons, the presence and abundance of natural<lb/> enemies, as well as long range weather forecasts, should be noted and considered when<lb/> evaluating spider mite populations and making pest management decisions.<lb/> In addition to identifying and monitoring naturally occurring beneficial species, there<lb/> have been some attempts to document the effectiveness of inoculative releases of<lb/> insectary-reared predators. When released in cage studies, the predatory mites<lb/> Phytoseiulus persimilis and Amblyseius californicus reduced spider mite infestations on<lb/> corn by 60% and 28%, respectively. Predator releases in field plots by hand at a rate of 5<lb/> per plant became established well enough to provided adequate control of Banks grass<lb/> mite. Finally, P. persimilis was released from an airplane to pre-tassel stage field corn, at<lb/> a rate of 15,000 per hectare in corn cob grit. While this application did not successfully<lb/> suppress the pest mite infestation, the predators did become established and were<lb/> beginning to impact the pests. Additional research needs to be conducted on the delivery</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
