<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55014886"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>African Journal of Biotechnology Vol. 7 (16), pp. 2739-2767, 18 August, 2008<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">Available online at</note>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.academicjournals.org/AJB<lb/></ptr>

	<idno>ISSN 1684–5315</idno>

	<note type="copyright">© 2008 Academic Journals<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Review<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The principles of ultra high pressure technology and its<lb/> application in food processing/preservation: A review<lb/> of microbiological and quality aspects<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Maryam Yaldagard<lb/> 1<lb/> *, Seyed Ali Mortazavi<lb/> 2<lb/> and Farideh Tabatabaie<lb/> 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Department of Chemical Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, Ferdowsi University of Mashad.</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P. O. BOX 91775-1111,<lb/> Iran.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> Department of Food Science and Technology, Ferdowsi University of Mashad,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Iran.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Accepted 4 July, 2008<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Consumers have a growing preference for convenient, fresh-like, healthy, palatable, additive-free, high-<lb/>quality and microbiologically safe food products. However, as food deterioration is constant threat<lb/> along the entire food chain, food preservation remains as necessary today as in the past. The food<lb/> industry has responded by applying a number of new technologies including high hydrostatic pressure<lb/> for food processing and preservation. In addition, food scientists have demonstrated the feasibility of<lb/> industrial-scale high pressure processing. High pressure processing is one of the emerging<lb/> technologies to be studied as an alternative to classical thermal processing of food. This &apos;clean&apos;<lb/> technology offers an effective and safe method of modifying protein structure, enzyme inactivation, and<lb/> formation of chemical compounds. In addition the study of the effects of high pressure on biological<lb/> materials has received a great deal of attention in recent years. During the last decade, numerous<lb/> publications that describe the influence of pressure on various constituents and contaminants of foods<lb/> such as spoilage microorganisms, food pathogens, enzymes and food proteins have appeared in the<lb/> literature. This paper reviews the literature on high pressure application in food industry most notably it<lb/> covers various facets of high pressure technology, which is, history, concepts and principles underlying<lb/> the application of this technology, physicochemical, chemical, microbiological aspects of high pressure<lb/> in the viewpoint of food technology.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key words: Ultra-high pressure (UHP), food processing/preservation and new food-processing technologies.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
