<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55012935"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Conquer Cancer Foundation @BULLET Cancer.Net @BULLET Journal of Clinical Oncology @BULLET Journal of Oncology Practice<lb/> ASCO University @BULLET Quality Oncology Practice Initiative (QOPI) @BULLET ASCO Connection<lb/>View Sitemap<lb/> A-Z Indexed Sitemap<lb/> Advanced Search<lb/> ASCO SIGN IN<lb/> Username:<lb/> Create an account<lb/> Why Be A Member?<lb/> Password:<lb/> Remember me Forgot your username or password?<lb/> ASCO Membership Directory<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">The Remember Me feature is an automatic login process which creates a cookie on the hard drive of your<lb/> computer containing a unique identifier which ASCO.org will utilize to remember you by, thereby<lb/> avoiding the need to enter username and password upon subsequent visits to ASCO.org. DO NOT select<lb/> this option if you share this computer with others since transactional, personal, or member only<lb/> information will be accessible by other users.<lb/> To activate the Remember Me option, click the empty check box when signing in to the site. The<lb/> Remember Me functionality is deactivated at the logout.<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">For additional information please review our Privacy Policy.<lb/> Practice &amp;<lb/> Guidelines Research<lb/> Resources Education &amp;<lb/> Training Public Policy<lb/> International Affairs<lb/> Grants &amp;<lb/> Awards MultiMedia<lb/> Press Center<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Novel organic arsenic molecule<lb/> darinaparsin: Development of IV<lb/> and oral forms.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="other">Print this page<lb/> Sub-category:<lb/> Lymphoma<lb/> Category:<lb/> Lymphoma and Plasma Cell Disorders<lb/> Meeting:<lb/> 2009 ASCO Annual Meeting<lb/> Home About ASCO<lb/> MyASCO Cancer Portals<lb/> Products Meetings<lb/> Donate Join ASCO<lb/> Novel organic arsenic molecule darinaparsin: Development of IV and or...</note>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.asco.org/ascov2/Meetings/Abstracts?&amp;vmview=abst_detai...<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="page">1 of 5<lb/></note>

	<date>23-11-2011</date>

	<note type="other">16:10<lb/> Session Type and Session Title:<lb/> Clinical Science Symposium, New Agents for Lymphoma<lb/> Abstract No:<lb/> 8501<lb/> Citation:<lb/></note>

	<reference>J Clin Oncol 27:15s, 2009 (suppl; abstr 8501)</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
