<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55010378"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Clinical Perspectives CME/CE<lb/> Medical Economics<lb/> Careers Community<lb/> Clinical Tools<lb/> Products<lb/> ModernMedicine Recommended Medical Sites<lb/> Register | More Info<lb/> (it&apos;s free)<lb/> Email | Print |<lb/> | Save | License | Discuss On Sermo<lb/> ADVERTISEMENT<lb/> TREATMENT AREAS | SUBSCRIBE | ADVERTISE | CONTACT US<lb/> Resources: Oral Anticoagulation in Atrial Fibrillation [SPONSORED]<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Lorcaserin: A novel, selective 5-HT2C-<lb/>receptor agonist for the treatment of<lb/> obesity<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<date>Jun 1, 2010<lb/></date>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>By: Maribeth Pauli, PharmD, BCPS, Sam Abdelghany, PharmD, BCOP<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="other">Formulary<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Obesity is a prevalent disease that has reached epidemic proportions<lb/> in both the developed and developing world. In the United States, it is<lb/> estimated that 66% of the adult population is overweight or obese.<lb/> There are several available pharmacologic treatments for obesity used<lb/> as an adjunct to diet, exercise, and behavioral therapy. However,<lb/> weight loss with these agents is modest and usually reversible when<lb/> the drug is discontinued, and novel, more-effective anti-obesity agents<lb/> are desperately needed. Lorcaserin is a selective 5-HT2C-receptor<lb/> agonist under development for weight management. This receptor is<lb/> expressed in the brain, including the hypothalamus, an area involved<lb/> in the control of appetite and metabolism. Lorcaserin has<lb/> demonstrated efficacy in 2 pivotal phase 3 clinical trials. Mean weight<lb/> loss at 1 year was approximately 6 kg in both trials. These trials have<lb/> also demonstrated that lorcaserin is devoid of the serious adverse<lb/> reactions that have plagued other weight-loss medications. A new<lb/> drug application for lorcaserin was submitted in December 2009, and a<lb/> response from FDA is expected in the fourth quarter of this year.<lb/> (Formulary. 2010;45;180–186.)<lb/> Obesity is a leading cause of morbidity worldwide. World Health<lb/> Organization projections indicate that at least 400 million adults were obese</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
