<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55012341"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Simultaneous estimation of soil hydraulic and solute transport<lb/> parameters from transient in®ltration experiments<lb/>
	</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>M. Inoue<lb/> a<lb/> , J. Sim# unek<lb/> b, * , S. Shiozawa<lb/> c<lb/> , J.W. Hopmans<lb/> d<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Arid Land Research Center, Tottori University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hamasaka 1390, Tottori 680, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b US Salinity Laboratory,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>USDA-ARS, 450 W. Big Springs Dr., Riverside, CA 92507, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c Institute of Agricultural and Forest Engineering, University of Tsukuba,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tsukuba, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>d Hydrology Program, Department LAWR,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>123 Veihmeyer Hall,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of California,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Davis, CA 95616, USA<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 6 October 1999; received in revised form 10 February 2000; accepted 11 February 2000<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Estimation of soil hydraulic and solute transport parameters is important to provide input parameters for numerical models<lb/> simulating transient water ¯ow and solute transport in the vadose zone. The Levenberg±Marquardt optimization algorithm in<lb/> combination with the HYDRUS-1D numerical code was used to inversely estimate unsaturated soil-hydraulic and solute transport<lb/> parameters from transient matric pressure head, apparent electrical conductivity, and euent ¯ux measurements. A 30 cm long soil<lb/> column with an internal diameter of 5 cm was used for in®ltration experiments in a coarse-textured soil. In®ltration experiments<lb/> were carried out with both increasing and decreasing solute concentrations following a sudden increase in the in®ltration rate.<lb/> Matric pressure heads and solute concentrations were measured using automated mini-tensiometers and four-electrode sensors,<lb/> respectively. The simultaneous estimation results were compared with independently measured soil water retention, unsaturated<lb/> hydraulic conductivity, and solute dispersion data obtained from steady-state water ¯ow experiments. The optimized values cor-<lb/>responded well with those measured independently within the range of experimental data. The information contained in the ap-<lb/>parent electrical conductivity (which integrates information about both water ¯ow and solute transport) proved to be very useful for<lb/> the simultaneous estimation of soil hydraulic and solute transport parameters.</div>

	<note type="copyright">&#169; 2000 Elsevier Science Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Keywords: Four-electrode sensor; Bulk soil electrical conductivity; Hydraulic conductivity; Soil water retention curve; Dispersivity<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
