<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55011389"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Towards effective SIP load Balancing<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Georgios Kambourakis<lb/> Dimitris Geneiatakis<lb/> Tasos Dagiuklas<lb/> Costas Lambrinoudakis<lb/> Stefanos Gritzalis<lb/>
	</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Laboratory of Information and Communication Systems Security<lb/> Department of Information and Communication Systems Engineering<lb/> University of the Aegean<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Karlovassi, GR-83200 Samos, Greece<lb/></address>

	<phone>Tel: +30-22730-82247<lb/> </phone>

	<email>Email:{gkamb, dgen, ntan, clam, sgritz}@aegean.gr<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) high availability, reliability and<lb/> redundancy are determined by the ability of the core SIP network<lb/> components to offer high quality SIP services in the event(s) of<lb/> high call transactions, link outages, device failures,<lb/> misconfigurations and security attacks. In this context, load<lb/> balancers can be used to achieve redundancy and active load<lb/> balancing of SIP transactions. In load balancing schemes, new<lb/> requests are allocated across available servers using a selection<lb/> algorithm. Although considerable work has been already done for<lb/> Web traffic balancing, little research effort is primarily aiming to<lb/> SIP load balancing. This paper proposes a SIP dedicated load<lb/> balancing solution, which is currently under development within<lb/> the EC funded project SNOCER. We describe in detail our<lb/> balancing scheme, its associated architecture elements and<lb/> provide implementation details showing that it is simple to<lb/> realize, effective, flexible, robust and secure.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Categories and Subject Descriptors<lb/> C2.1 [Computer Communication Networks]: Network<lb/> Architecture and Design, C.2.2 Network Protocols.<lb/> General Terms<lb/> Design, Reliability, Security.<lb/> Keywords<lb/> Session Initiation Protocol; Load balancing; SIP architectures;<lb/> Redundancy.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
