<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55011769"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Africa Asia Pacific<lb/> Europe Latin America<lb/> Middle East<lb/> North America<lb/> Resources<lb/> Products / Milk Proteins<lb/> Products<lb/> Amino Acids, Vitamins, Minerals &amp; Speciality Ingredients<lb/> 1.<lb/> Dairy Minerals<lb/> 2.<lb/> Flaxseed 3.<lb/> Functional Ingredient Systems<lb/> 4.<lb/> Micronutrient Premixes<lb/> 5.<lb/> Milk Proteins<lb/> 6.<lb/> Whey Proteins<lb/> 7.<lb/> Whey Peptide &amp; Hydrolysate Technologies<lb/> 8.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Milk proteins made to outperform.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="introduction">We&apos;re a leading supplier of milk proteins for use in food and beverage applications. Our milk protein<lb/> ingredients offer excellent nutritional value while providing value-adding functional properties like<lb/> improved flavor, solubility and heat stability.<lb/> Whatever your application need, we have the processing expertise and advanced dairy resources to help<lb/> you achieve your project goals.<lb/> Click to CloseSolmiko Milk Protein Isolate &amp; Milk Protein Concentrate<lb/> Solmiko milk protein concentrate (MPC) and milk protein isolate (MPI) are excellent sources of native<lb/> casein and whey proteins that offer excellent flavor, solubility and heat stability. Solmiko milk proteins are<lb/> ideally suited for applications where low micro counts, functionality and flavor are critical, including<lb/> ready-to-drink and instant protein beverages, sports nutrition bars and beverages, and fresh dairy products.<lb/>Applications Benefits<lb/> Beverages Foods<lb/> Supplements<lb/> Age-Related Muscle Maintenance<lb/> Food &amp; Beverage Fortification<lb/> Sports Performance<lb/> Request Product Details &gt;<lb/>Solmiko MPC 80 is a spray-dried milk protein concentrate powder with 85% protein, manufactured from<lb/> fresh, ultrafiltered skim milk. Solmiko MPC 80 is a good source of native micellar casein and whey<lb/> proteins in the same ratio as found naturally in milk. The product is characterized by low bacterial counts.<lb/> It has excellent flavor, solubility and heat stability, and is suitable for use in a range of applications, both<lb/> functional and nutritional.<lb/> Solmiko MPI is a spray-dried milk protein isolate powder with 90% protein, manufactured from fresh,<lb/> ultrafiltered skim milk. Solmiko MPI is a good source of native micellar casein and whey proteins in the<lb/> same ratio as found naturally in milk. The product is characterized by low bacterial counts, high protein<lb/> and low lactose. It has excellent flavor, solubility and heat stability, and is suitable for use in a range of<lb/> applications, both functional and nutritional.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
