<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55011668"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">practice<lb/> </note>

	<reference>J O U R N A L O F WO U N D C A R E VO L 1 8 , N O 3 , M A R C H 2 0 0 9<lb/> </reference>

	<note type="page">1 1 4<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Clinical experience with a glucose<lb/> oxidase-containing dressing on<lb/> recalcitrant wounds<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">This large open study investigated the clinical benefi ts of a new hydrogel dressing<lb/> when used on chronic wounds of different aetiologies in real-life clinical settings.<lb/> Nearly three-quarters of the patients assessed either healed or improved<lb/> </div>

	<note type="other">healing outcomes; wound bed characteristics; pain; patient and clinician satisfaction<lb/> </note>

	<div type="introduction">O<lb/> xyzyme (Archimed Division) is a new<lb/> type of hydrogel dressing containing a<lb/> natural enzyme that is designed to pro-<lb/>mote a healing environment in superfi -<lb/>cial wounds. For its registration, two<lb/> open, non-comparative, clinical trials were undertaken<lb/> to gather evidence on its safety and effi cacy.<lb/> 1,2 The<lb/> Canadian four-week study involved 20 patients with<lb/> 22 hard-to-heal wounds (venous leg ulcers, post-surgi-<lb/>cal and radiation wounds, diabetic foot ulcers and pres-<lb/>sure ulcers).<lb/> 1 Four wounds healed (18%), 15 improved<lb/> (68%), one remained static (5%) and two deteriorated<lb/> (9%) in the four-week study period. The UK study<lb/> involved 31 patients with chronic venous leg ulcers<lb/> (median duration 39 months), of whom 21 completed<lb/> the six-week trial. Of these, 10 patients healed fully<lb/> (32%), eight improved (26%) and three (10%) derived<lb/> little or no benefi t. While these results are encouraging,<lb/> the small sample sizes and open nature of the trials<lb/> meant that further evidence was required.<lb/> To gain fi eld experience of the dressing with a large<lb/> number of patients with a variety of hard-to-heal,<lb/> chronic wounds, an open, non-comparative, multi-<lb/>national case-series study was conducted. A ran-<lb/>domised controlled trial (RCT) or cohort study<lb/> approach was considered but not pursued as it was<lb/> judged that, under these circumstances, it was likely<lb/> to be more time-consuming and bureaucratic to con-<lb/>duct, and more diffi cult to oversee effectively. The<lb/> case-series study design also offered the opportunity<lb/> for rapid recruitment at a wide range of expert cen-<lb/>tres, as well as enabling structured feedback from<lb/> their experienced staff. In addition, this approach<lb/> gives a direct insight into the effectiveness of the new<lb/> dressing when applied by nurses in real-life settings.<lb/> The study aims were therefore to:<lb/> ● Gain evidence of the performance of Oxyzyme<lb/> with a variety of hard-to-heal chronic wounds of<lb/> various aetiologies in clinical settings<lb/> ● Evaluate its ability to promote a healing environ-<lb/>ment in chronic wounds<lb/> ● Examine its effect on the wound bed, exudate lev-<lb/>els, the surrounding skin and pain levels<lb/> ● Obtain patient and carer feedback on its use and<lb/> performance.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
