<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55013644"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note>Audio Engineering Society<lb/> </note>
 
	<note>Convention Paper 8517<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Presented at the 131st Convention<lb/> </note>

	<date>2011 October 20–23<lb/> </date>

	<address>New York, NY, USA<lb/></address>
	
	<note type="other">This Convention paper was selected based on a submitted abstract and 750-word precis that have been peer reviewed by at least<lb/> two qualified anonymous reviewers. The complete manuscript was not peer reviewed. This convention paper has been<lb/> reproduced from the author&apos;s advance manuscript without editing, corrections, or consideration by the Review Board. The AES<lb/> takes no responsibility for the contents. Additional papers may be obtained by sending request and remittance to Audio<lb/> Engineering Society, 60 East 42nd Street, New York, New York 10165-2520, USA; also see www.aes.org. All rights reserved.<lb/> Reproduction of this paper, or any portion thereof, is not permitted without direct permission from the Journal of the Audio<lb/> Engineering Society.<lb/>
	</note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>QMF Based Harmonic Spectral Band<lb/> Replication<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Zhong Haishan<lb/> 1 , Lars Villemoes<lb/> 2 , Per Ekstrand<lb/> 2 , Sascha Disch<lb/> 3 , Frederik Nagel<lb/> 3 , Stephan Wilde<lb/> 3 , Chong<lb/> Kok Seng<lb/> 1 , Takeshi Norimatsu<lb/> 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Panasonic Corporation<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<affiliation>2 Dolby Sweden AB<lb/></affiliation>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Fraunhofer Institute for Integrated Circuits IIS<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Unified speech and audio coding (USAC) is the next step in the evolution of audio codecs that are standardized by<lb/> the Moving Picture Experts Group (MPEG). USAC provides consistent quality for music, speech and mixed<lb/> material, by extending the strength of an audio codec by speech codec functions. Two novel flavors of Spectral<lb/> Band Replication (SBR) were introduced to enhance the perceptual quality of SBR: the Discrete Fourier Transform<lb/> (DFT) based and the Quadrature Mirror Filter (QMF) bank harmonic SBR. The DFT-based SBR has higher<lb/> frequency resolution for the harmonic transposition process, resulting in good sound quality. The QMF-based SBR<lb/> has significantly lower computational complexity. This paper describes the detailed technical aspects of the low<lb/> complexity QMF-based harmonic SBR tool within USAC. A complexity comparison and the listening test results<lb/> are also presented in the paper.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
