<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55013512"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">150<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Synthesis of 6-Substituted Nicotinic Acid Uerivatives<lb/> as Analogs of Ergot Alkaloicls;&quot;&quot;~&quot;<lb/>
	</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="introduction">Structural resemblaiices ot deri\.ati\es of ti-plicii-<lb/>cthylnicotinic acid, ti,nns-(j-st&apos;yryliiicotiiiic. acid. ris-<lb/>(i-styrylnicotiiiic acid. aiid Ci-plieiietliyiiyliiicotiiii(~ acid<lb/> to the iiaturally occurring ei,got alkaloids pixmipted<lb/> their synthesis aiid biological civaluat,ioii. Tliesc.<lb/> derivatives, coiitaiiiiiig rings ,2 and I ) of t hr: lyset~gic<lb/> acid molecule (I), a portion of riiig (&quot;, a i d a caihosainidtb<lb/> gi.oup, iiiiglit be considered to hcl aiialogs of ctgoiioviiie.<lb/> l&apos;hey differ from each ot,lier not, oiily iii thr: degree of<lb/> unsaturation in t&apos;he aliphatic carbon to carlion bond but,<lb/> in tlie spatial relationship of the phenyl group to the<lb/> heterocyclic ring. It would lie expected t&apos;liat com-<lb/>pouiids of the cis s t p y l series (11) wmld most&apos; closely<lb/> approximate the spatial configuratioii fouiid in lysergic<lb/> acid, while the phenyl group in the t,,ans-Ci-styryliiico-<lb/>tiiiic acid and 6-phenethynylnicotiiiic acid deixivatives<lb/> would possess markedly different spatial relationships<lb/> t&apos;o t&apos;he het&apos;erocyclic ring. In the phenet&apos;hyl series it<lb/> niiglit he assumed that because of free rotation of thc<lb/> carbon to carbon bond of the ethyleiie giuup, the t\\-o<lb/> aromatic rings Cali assuine the same spatial confid (J u1.a-<lb/>t i o i l fouiid in t&gt;he lyseigic acid niolecule : howevw,<lb/> st&apos;rric interactioii tietn-een the tn.o riigs ivould probably<lb/> pimwit this from kieconiiiig their preferred configura-<lb/>tiot 1 .<lb/> Lthyl tr.Qns-(j-st,yryliiicotiiiate \vas prepared by tjlw<lb/> condensation of benzaldehyde with ethyl 6-methyl-<lb/>nicotinate and on hydrolysis yielded the previously<lb/> reported bt&apos;yrylnicotinic acid.3 Attempts t&apos;o prepare<lb/> t,.ans-O-styrylnicotinic acid l y tlie corideiisation of<lb/> heiizaldehyde and 6-methylnicotinic acid following thf&gt;<lb/> diiwtioiis of l&apos;lieniger3 failed to yield t,liis compound.<lb/> I&apos;thyl i~~nris-ti-styryliiicotiriat~~~ \vheii t&apos;reated with<lb/> aninioiiia, tnethylaiiiiiie. and pyrrolidine, yielded t&apos;lw<lb/> expected amides (Table I ) . Tliesr aniiiies, ho\vevci..<lb/> failed to add to the double h i i d . &apos;Treatment of ethyl<lb/> f/,ari.s-(j-styryliiicotiiiate with hydiazine hydrate gave<lb/> t&apos;lir hydrazide. Wheii the ester was boiled with an</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
