<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55014045"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">124<lb/></note>

	<reference>PTEP 13(2009) 2<lb/> Biblid: 1450-5029 (2009) 13; 2; p.124-127<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">Original scientific paper<lb/> </note>

	<idno>UDK: 664.653.4<lb/> </idno>

	<note type="other">Originalni naučni rad<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>HIGH QUALITY NOODLE PRODUCTS AND THEIR TRADITIONAL AND<lb/> NON-TRADITIONAL PROCESSING<lb/> VISOKOKVALITETNI TESTIČARSKI PROIZVODI I NJIHOVA<lb/> TRADICIONALNA I NETRADICIONALNA PROIZVODNJA<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dr. Elisabeth T. KOVACS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Szeged, Faculty of Engineering, Institute of Food Engineer<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>H-6724 Szeged, Mars tér 7, Hungary,</address>

	<email>e-mail: elisabet@mk.u-szeged.<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">SUMMARY<lb/> Traditional pasta is produced only from different qualities of wheat flour (T. durum, T. aestivum) and water, but the use of legu-<lb/>minous flour (like yellow pea flour), pseodecereals (like amaranth ) or maize starch as well etc. for producing noodle products is un-<lb/>conventional. There are several possibilities for improving the quality of the products: to change the technology (drying on low or<lb/> high temperature) or to use additives such as emulsifiers and/or enzymes. For developing an improved pasta structure the enzyme<lb/> transglutaminase can be used as well.<lb/> In the presence of emulsifier an emulsifier-carbohydrate-protein-lipid complex can be expected. The rate of the individual interac-<lb/>tions depends on the components of the sample and on the type of applied emulsifiers. Transglutaminase enzyme, a protein-glutamine<lb/> γ-glutamyl-transferase (EC.2.3.2.13), catalysis acyl-transfer reactions, and introduces covalent cross-links between proteins. The<lb/> application of transglutaminase has great importance for the development of pasta products: from pseudocereals, or wheat flours (T.<lb/> durum, T. aestivum). Pasta products with good quality like T. durum-based pastas can be produced from T. aestivum flour. By using<lb/> transglutaminase the quality of T. durum flour can also be improved, so the pastas will show higher cooking quality. The enzyme in-<lb/>sures cholesterol free products. Pasta and noodle products were produced according a modelling system. The effect of the enzyme<lb/> treatment on cooking properties, sensory assessment and protein distribution was analyzed. The change of the protein structure de-<lb/>pends on the type of systems, the amount and the type of additives.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key words: emulsifiers, transglutaminase enzyme, pasta properties, SDS-PAGE.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
