<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55011039"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Cellulosic Ethanol Produced by Recombinant Yeast<lb/> </note>

	<note type="page">403<lb/></note>
	
	<reference>Applied Biochemistry and Biotechnology<lb/> Vol. 113–116, 2004<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2004 by Humana Press Inc.<lb/> All rights of any nature whatsoever reserved.<lb/></note>

	<note>0273-2289/04/114/0403–0416/$25.00<lb/></note>

	<note type="page">403<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">*Author to whom all correspondence and reprint requests should be addressed.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Production of Ethanol from Cellulosic<lb/> Biomass Hydrolysates Using Genetically<lb/> Engineered Saccharomyces Yeast Capable<lb/> of Cofermenting Glucose and Xylose<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>MIROSLAV SEDLAK AND NANCY W. Y. HO<lb/>*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Laboratory of Renewable Resources Engineering (LORRE),<lb/> Purdue University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>500 Central Drive, West Lafayette, IN 47907,<lb/></address>

	<email>E-mail: nwyho@ecn.purdue.edu<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Recent studies have proven ethanol to be the ideal liquid fuel for transpor-<lb/>tation, and renewable lignocellulosic materials to be the attractive feedstocks<lb/> for ethanol fuel production by fermentation. The major fermentable sugars<lb/> from hydrolysis of most cellulosic biomass are D-glucose and D-xylose. The<lb/> naturally occurring Saccharomyces yeasts that are used by industry to pro-<lb/>duce ethanol from starches and cane sugar cannot metabolize xylose. Our<lb/> group at Purdue University succeeded in developing genetically engineered<lb/> Saccharomyces yeasts capable of effectively cofermenting glucose and xylose<lb/> to ethanol, which was accomplished by cloning three xylose-metabolizing<lb/> genes into the yeast. In this study, we demonstrated that our stable recom-<lb/>binant Saccharomyces yeast, 424A(LNH-ST), which contains the cloned<lb/> xylose-metabolizing genes stably integrated into the yeast chromosome in<lb/> high copy numbers, can efficiently ferment glucose and xylose present in<lb/> hydrolysates from different cellulosic biomass to ethanol.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Index Entries: Ethanol; Saccharomyces yeasts; hydrolysate; corn stover;<lb/> corn fiber; xylose; glucose; glycerol; xylitol.
	<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
