<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55012147"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Presented at the 67<lb/> th Annual International Water Conference, Engineers Society of Western Pennsylviania, Pittsburgh, Oct 2006<lb/> </note>

	<note type="page">-1 -<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A Comprehensive Look at Conductivity Measurement<lb/> in Steam and Power Generation Waters<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>DAVID M. GRAY – </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Mettler-Toledo</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Thornton, Inc.,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bedford, MA<lb/></address>

	<idno>IWC-06-29<lb/></idno>

	<keyword>KEYWORDS: conductivity, cation conductivity, degassed cation conductivity, cycle chemistry, TOC,<lb/> total organic carbon<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT: Conductivity has been the simplest, oldest, most common, most reliable and lowest cost<lb/> measurement used for determining water purity. Nevertheless, this lowly measurement has provided the<lb/> means for protecting and assuring efficient operation of billions of dollars worth of power and steam<lb/> generation equipment throughout the world for over three-quarters of a century. Recent innovations in<lb/> measurement accuracy, temperature compensation, and sample conditioning have enabled this basic<lb/> detection method to provide more information and to expand its use even further. From the simplest TDS<lb/> meter to the most sophisticated ion chromatograph, conductivity measurement is the core technology.<lb/> The widespread use of this measurement often outpaces the understanding of it. Provided here<lb/> are the fundamentals and application of conductivity measurement as used in power and steam<lb/> generation, including ionic conductance, cell constant, measuring techniques and temperature effects. In<lb/> addition, various means of sample conditioning are discussed, covering the measurements of cation<lb/> conductivity, degassed cation conductivity, pH and CO 2 calculations and even TOC (total organic carbon)<lb/> measurements. It is hoped this discussion will assist those applying conductivity measurement in any of<lb/> its incarnations to have a greater understanding and to obtain better results.
	<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
