<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="abstract">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55114105"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">This Article<lb/> Services<lb/> Similar articles in this journal<lb/> Download to citation manager<lb/> Google Scholar<lb/> Articles by Zhang, C.<lb/> Articles by Anderes, K.<lb/> PubMed<lb/> Articles by Zhang, C.<lb/> Articles by Anderes, K.<lb/> HOME HELP FEEDBACK HOW TO CITE ABSTRACTS ARCHIVE CME INFORMATION SEARCH<lb/> Cancer Research<lb/> Clinical Cancer Research<lb/> Cancer Epidemiology Biomarkers &amp; Prevention Molecular Cancer Therapeutics<lb/> Molecular Cancer Research<lb/> Cancer Prevention Research<lb/> Cancer Prevention Journals Portal<lb/> Cancer Reviews Online<lb/> Annual Meeting Education Book<lb/> Meeting Abstracts Online<lb/> QUICK SEARCH:<lb/> [advanced]<lb/> Go<lb/> Author:<lb/> zhang<lb/> Keyword(s):<lb/> pf-03732010<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Institution: European Patent Office | Sign In via User Name/Password<lb/> </note>
	
	<reference>99th AACR Annual Meeting-- Apr 12-16, 2008;  San Diego, CA<lb/> </reference>

	<note>New Targets for the Therapy of Metastasis: Oral Presentations -<lb/>Proffered Abstracts<lb/> Abstract #2575<lb/> </note>	

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Preclinical characterization of PF-03732010: A<lb/> human IgG1 mAb against P-cadherin, reveals antitumor and<lb/> antimetastatic activity in xenografts<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Cathy Zhang, Zhengming Yan, Maria Arango, Ming Qiu, Pramod Mehta, Casperson Jerry, Todd VanArsdale,<lb/> Gerrit Los and Kenna Anderes<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Pfizer Inc,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>San Diego, CA<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">P-cadherin is one member of the classical cadherin family and plays a critical role in tumor cell-cell and cell-stroma<lb/> adhesions. Up-regulation of P-cadherin has been frequently reported in major tumors such as colon, lung, breast,<lb/> pancreatic and bladder cancers. Here we report the in vivo antitumor activity of PF-03732010, a human IgG1 mAb that<lb/> binds to both human and mouse P-cadherin with high affinity and selectivity. Antitumor acitivity of PF-03732010 was<lb/> assessed in orthotopic or ectopic xenografts models including 1) PC-3M-luc-P-Cad 2) MDA-MB-435-luc-P-Cad<lb/> subrenal capsule model (SRC) and 3) MDA-MB-435-luc-P-Cad experimental metastasis model. Surgically implanted<lb/> tumor models are inaccessible to traditional caliper measurements; therefore, bioluminescence imaging (BLI) was<lb/> applied to evaluate the antitumor activity of PF-03732010. PC3M-luc-PCad and MDA-MB-435-HAL-luc-PCad cells<lb/> were stably transfected to constitutively express luciferase and overexpress P-Cadherin. PF-03732010 (5 and 20<lb/> mg/kg) displayed significant tumor growth inhibition (TGI) of 57% and 73% respectively in the PC3M-luc-PCad<lb/> model. In addition, BLI revealed PF-03732010 at 5 and 20 mg/kg inhibited lymph node metastases. In MDA-MB-<lb/>435-HAL-luc-PCad SRC model, distant metastasis in the lungs can be visualized the 4<lb/> th week after the tumor implant.<lb/> PF-03732010 (10, 20 &amp; 40 mg/kg) showed significant antitumor activity in MDA-MB-435-HAL-luc-PCad SRC<lb/> model with TGI of 51.8%, 66.5% and 68.0% respectively against the primary tumor; and antimetastatic activity of<lb/> 54.2%, 72.8% and 82.2% respectively against the tumor burden in the lungs. Kaplan-Meier survival plot showed that<lb/> PF-03732010 significantly improved mouse medium survival time compared to the vehicle treated group. IHC<lb/> examination of MDA-MB-435-HAL-luc-PCad SRC tumors showed a dose-dependent decrease in β-actin and Ki67,<lb/> suggesting antitumor activity is a result of cytoskeletal disruption and reduced proliferation due to PF-03732010<lb/> blockade of P-cadherin signaling. We further evaluated the antimetastatic activity of PF-03732010 in an experimental<lb/> model of metastasis, IV delivery of MDA-MB-435-HAL-luc-PCad cells to mice. When mice were treated with<lb/> PF-03732010 either twenty-four hours before or 14 days after injection of tumor cells, PF-03732010 (20 mg/kg)<lb/> significantly inhibited metastases and tumor burden increase in lungs (TGI 93% and 87% respectively) with a<lb/> concomitant increase in median survival of 39 and 19 days respectively. Overall, PF-03732010 consistently<lb/> demonstrated significant antitumor activity, reduction in metastatic burden and improvement in survival. PF-03732010<lb/> Preclinical characterization of PF-03732010: A human IgG1 mAb a...<lb/></div>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.aacrmeetingabstracts.org/cgi/content/meeting_abstract/...<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="page">1 of 2<lb/></note>

	<date>15-04-2014</date>

	<note type="other">08:59</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
