<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="conference-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55113813"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>lAPR Workshop on CV -Special Hardware and Industrial Applications OCT.12-14, 1988, Tokyo<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A NEW SCHEME FOR PRACTICAL FLEXIBLE AND INTELLIGENT<lb/> VISION SYSTEMS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Nobuyuki OTSU and Takio KURITA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Electrotechnical Laboratory<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1-1-4 Umezono, Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki-ken, Japan 305<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> We propose a new scheme for practical vision systems which<lb/> are simple in structure, directly and adaptively trainable for<lb/> various purposes. The feature extraction consists of two stages:<lb/> At first, general and primitive features which are shift-invariant<lb/> and additive are extracted over the retinal image plane. Then<lb/> those features are linearly combined on the bases of multivari-<lb/>ate analysis methods so as to provide new effective features for<lb/> each task. Such a system can adaptively and automatically<lb/> learn the task from the given supervised training examples and<lb/> show an intelligent performance. Some examples of practical<lb/> applications to object recognition and measurements are exper-<lb/>imentally shown.<lb/> which is simple in structure and directly and a d a p<lb/> tively trainable for various purposes. The basic idea<lb/> is similar to Perceptron [I] or neural networks (for<lb/> example, see 12)) but more practical being based on<lb/> closed-form solutions for statistical performance cri-<lb/>teria without employing such slow iterative learning<lb/> processes.<lb/> The basic idea of the system has already been pre-<lb/>sented in [3] and registered as patents (for example,<lb/> [4]). A hardware implementation (named AISS) has<lb/> been developed in cooperation with OKK Inc. and<lb/> the detail will be presented in a different paper [5] to-<lb/>gether with actual demonstration at this conference.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
