<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="web">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55114674"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Breaking New s on Cosmetics Formulation &amp; Packaging in Europe<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Silab develops anti-ageing active from<lb/> peach tree leaves<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>By M ic helle Yeomans , </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<date>1 5 -Feb-2 0 1 2<lb/></date>

	<note type="other">Related topic s : Skin C are, Formulation &amp; Sc ienc e<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Silab has launched Vitagenyl, an active ingredient rich in purified α-glucans (Prunus persica) derived<lb/> from peach tree leaves with properties said to improve vitality and regeneration potential in ageing skin.<lb/> According to the manufacturer, the active is an adaptative ingredient for a new anti-ageing strategy as it contributes to<lb/> the skin&apos;s capacity to regenerate and accelerates its renewal. &quot;It is now known that micro stress can be beneficial to skin as it stimulates skin cells to develop natural repair and<lb/> defense mechanisms, thereby slowing down the ageing process, known as the hormesis principal,&quot; says Silab.<lb/> Vitagenyl features this hormetic action, meaning that the cells are therefore better prepared and armed to fight<lb/> subsequent stress. As a result of this, skin is regenerated and revitalised and the signs of ageing are less pronounced.<lb/> Trials<lb/> According to Silab, the effect of Vitagenyl on cell growth tested at 1 per cent significantly stimulated the viability of<lb/> fibroblasts in a depleted medium by 22 per cent.<lb/> The active, again tested at 1 per cent &quot;significantly increased Ki67 synthesis by 39 per cent. In a dose-dependent and<lb/> hormetic manner, it also stimulated the capacity of human fibroblasts to flourish.&quot;<lb/> Vitagenyl also significantly increases the expression of chaperone proteins and reduces the roughness parameters Sa in<lb/> 61 per cent of volunteers and attenuates wrinkles by a significant reduction of volume in 56 per cent.<lb/> Overall, the anti-wrinkle regenerating effect &quot;formulated at 3 per cent smoothed the skin surface on crow&apos;s feet, as a<lb/> result over 70 per cent of the volunteers noted a decrease in crow&apos;s feet wrinkles&quot;, Silab concluded.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright -Unless otherwise stated all contents of this web site are © 2014 -William Reed Business Media SAS -All Rights Reserved -For<lb/> permission to reproduce any contents of this web site, please email our Syndication department copyright@wrbm.com</note>

	<note type="other">-Full details for the use of<lb/> materials on this site can be found in the Terms &amp; Conditions<lb/></note>

	<note type="copyright">© 2014 -William Reed Business Media SAS -All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<note>Silab develops anti-ageing active from peach tree leaves<lb/></note>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.cosmeticsdesign-europe.com/content/view/print/612491<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="page">1 of 1<lb/></note>

	<date>22-04-2014</date>

	<note type="other">11:01</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
