<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="journal-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55114802"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Informatica 34 (2010) 477–490<lb/></reference>

	<note type="page">477<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Dynamic Process Integration Framework: Toward Efficient Information<lb/> Processing in Complex Distributed Systems<lb/>
	</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Gregor Pavlin and Michiel Kamermans </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Thales </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nederland B.V.,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>D-CIS Lab Delft,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nederland<lb/></address>

	<email>E-mail: gregor.pavlin@d-cis.nl, michiel.kamermans@d-cis.nl<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mihnea Scafe<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Craiova,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Romania<lb/></address>

	<email>scafes_mihnea@software.ucv.ro<lb/></email>

	<keyword>Keywords: service oriented architectures, distributed reasoning, negotiation, multi agent systems<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="submission">Received: February 22, 2010<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">The Dynamic Process Integration Framework (DPIF) is a service oriented approach which supports effi-<lb/>cient creation of distributed systems for collaborative reasoning. The DPIF is relevant for an important<lb/> class of contemporary applications requiring efficient and reliable processing of large quantities of het-<lb/>erogeneous information. An example of such an application is situation assessment in complex decision<lb/> making processes in dynamic environments. The DPIF supports (i) a systematic encapsulation of hetero-<lb/>geneous processes and (ii) negotiation-based self configuration mechanisms which automate creation of<lb/> meaningful workflows implementing complex collaborative reasoning processes. The resulting systems<lb/> support processing based on rich domain knowledge while, at the same time, the collaboration between<lb/> heterogeneous services requires minimal ontological commitments.<lb/> Povzetek: Opisan je nov pristop v procesiranju informacij v kompleksnih porazdeljenih sistemih.
	<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
