<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="journal-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55115158"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>

	<reference>Arham Shabbir<lb/> J. Anim. Plant Sci. 22(2):2012<lb/></reference>

	<note type="page">505<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>RHUS CORIARIA LINN, A PLANT OF MEDICINAL, NUTRITIONAL AND INDUSTRIAL<lb/> IMPORTANCE: A REVIEW<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Arham Shabbir<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, COMSATS Institute of Information Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Abbottabad-22060, Pakistan<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">Corresponding author;</note>

	<email>email: charham007@hotmail.com<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Rhus coriaria Linn. (Anacardiacea), commonly known as sumac, has been used as a spice, condiment, appetizer, and as<lb/> a souring agent for centuries. A broad range of nutritionally and medicinally significant phytochemical components have<lb/> been identified from various parts of sumac such as tannins, flavonoids, anthocyanins, organic acids, flavones, proteins,<lb/> fiber, volatile oils, nitrates, and nitrites. The plant also possesses minerals which are beneficial in the treatment of<lb/> different disorders and contribute to various biological processes. In traditional system of medicine, this plant has been<lb/> used in the treatment of diarrhea, dysentery, ulcer, hemorrhoids, hemorrhage, wound healing, hematemesis, hemoptysis,<lb/> leucorrhea, sore throat, ophthalmia, conjunctivitis, diuresis, animal bites, poison, pain, and liver disease. Traditional<lb/> practitioners have also prescribed this plant as antimicrobial, abortifacient, and stomach tonic. Rhus coriaria is known to<lb/> possess DNA protective, non-mutagenic, chondroprotective, antifungal, antibacterial, antioxidant, anti-ischemic,<lb/> vasorelaxant, hypoglycemic, xanthine oxidase inhibition, vascular smooth muscle cell migration inhibition, and<lb/> hepatoprotective properties, supporting its traditional uses. The role of plant in leather and textile industry as tanning<lb/> agent and as a coloring agent is significant. It also prevents wood decay and has considerable potential for future<lb/> research.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key Words: Rhus coriaria; phytochemistry; antioxidant; antibacterial; sumac.<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
