<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55114668"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">151<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Context-Based Retrieval in Digital Libraries: Approach and<lb/> Technological Framework<lb/>♣<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<note type="copyright">© </note>

	<docAuthor>Kurt Sandkuhl<lb/> 1<lb/> , Alexander Smirnov<lb/> 2<lb/> , Vladimir Mazalov<lb/> 3<lb/> , Vladimir Vdovitsyn<lb/> 3<lb/> ,<lb/> Vladimir Tarasov<lb/> 1<lb/> , Andrew Krizhanovsky<lb/> 2<lb/> , Feiyu Lin<lb/> 1<lb/> , Evgeny Ivashko<lb/> 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> School of Engineering at Jönköping University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>{kurt.sandkuhl, vladimir.tarasov, feiyu.lin}@ jth.hj.se<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> St.Petersburg Institute for Informatics and Automation of the RAS (SPIIRAS)<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>{smir, aka}@iias.spb.su<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> Institute of Applied Mathematical Research of the KarRC RAS (IAMR)<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>{vmazalov, vdov, ivashko}@krc.karelia.ru<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Digital libraries face similar challenges as<lb/> enterprise information sources and the Internet:<lb/> a fast growing amount of digital content<lb/> requires enhanced ways of supporting<lb/> information seeking. This paper presents an<lb/> approach to context-based retrieval in Digital<lb/> Libraries (DLs). The proposed approach<lb/> includes creation of a profile representing<lb/> general information demand of a user (abstract<lb/> context), and use of ontology matching to<lb/> identify the documents relevant to the<lb/> operational context representing the current<lb/> information demand of the user. A profile<lb/> represents the user&apos;s interests as a DL reader<lb/> and after creation is dynamically updated<lb/> based on the changes in the user&apos;s interests.<lb/> The identification of documents relevanсе is<lb/> carried out by matching the user profile<lb/> ontology against the digital library ontology.<lb/> Semantic distance calculation is based on the<lb/> use of a thesaurus.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
