<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="journal-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55113607"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">[CONTRIBUTION FROM THE NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF ARTHRITIS AND METABOLIC DISEASES,<lb/> NATIONAL INSTITUTES OF HEALTH, PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE, U. S.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>STEVIOSIDE. 11. THE STRUCTURE OF THE AGLUCON<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>ERICH MOSETTIG AND WILLIAM R. NES<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="submission">Received March 7, 1966<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH, EDUCATION, AND WELFARE]<lb/> Bride1 and Lavieille (1) have shown in a series of excellent investigations that<lb/> stevioside (1):.<lb/> the principal constituent of Skvia Rebaudiana Bertoni (the<lb/> Paraguayan kaA-hM), is hydrolyzed by enzymatic material prepared from<lb/> Helix pomatia to &quot;steviol&quot; (IV) and with dilute sulfuric acid to an isomeric<lb/> aglucon, &quot;isosteviol&quot; (11). &quot;Isosteviol&quot; was also obtained by boiling &quot;steviol&quot;<lb/> in dilute ethanolic sulfuric acid. By careful analysis of the glucoside and the<lb/> aglucon the French invmtigators were able to formulate the hydrolysis as:<lb/> CssHsoOls + 3H20 + Cno&amp;oO8 + 3CsHiiOs<lb/> The sugar moiety was recognized as consisting of three D-glucose units, while<lb/> &quot;steviol&quot; and &quot;isosteviol&quot; were found to be weakly acidic compounds forming<lb/> well-defined salts. From the aqueous, alkaline solutions they could be pre-<lb/>cipitated whh carbon dioxide which led the French authors to assume that they<lb/> are either phenols or compounds containing an acidic hydroxyl group. Since, in<lb/> contrast to the aglucon and its isomer, the glucoside contained no titratable<lb/> group, it was concluded that it is the acidic group of &quot;steviol&quot; to which the sugar<lb/> moiety is attached. The authors did not venture to comment on the nature of<lb/> the acid-catalyzed isomerization, but they did show that the ultraviolet spectrum<lb/> of &quot;isosteviol&quot; has a maximum at about 305 mp3, while the curve of &quot;steviol&quot;<lb/> is lacking in a maximum.<lb/> The major part of our investigations concern &quot;isosteviol&quot; (11). This proved<lb/> to be exceedingly stable; it sublimed readily in vacuo and could be distilled under<lb/> atmospheric pressure without decomposition. It readily formed a semicarbazone<lb/> indicating the presence of a carbonyl group. That a carboxyl group is responsi-<lb/>ble for the acidity of the molecule has been shown with diazomethane by the<lb/> formation of an ester which could be reduced with lithium aluminum hydride<lb/> 1 For a short historical review of this glucoside, see the foregoing paper by Wood, Aller-<lb/>ton, Diehl, and Fletcher (2).<lb/> 2 Very recently Bell (3) has drawn attention to &quot;Stevioside, a unique sweetening agent&quot;<lb/> and suggested further investigation. He proposes (entirely speculatively) for the aglucon<lb/> a formula of the type:</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
