<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="journal-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55114340"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Nebraska -</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Lincoln<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>DigitalCommons@University of Nebraska -</affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>Lincoln<lb/></address>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Faculty Publications in Food Science and<lb/> Technology Food Science and Technology Department<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<date>1-1-1975<lb/></date>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Reuse Limits and Regeneration of Solutions for<lb/> Cleaning Dairy Equipment<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>S. M. Kulkarni<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Nebraska -Lincoln<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>R. G. Arnold<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Nebraska -Lincoln<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>R. B. Maxcy<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Nebraska -Lincoln<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<note type="other">Follow this and additional works at:</note>

	<ptr type="web">http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/foodsciefacpub<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="other">Part of the Food Science Commons<lb/> This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Food Science and Technology Department at DigitalCommons@University of Nebraska -<lb/>Lincoln. It has been accepted for inclusion in Faculty Publications in Food Science and Technology by an authorized administrator of<lb/> DigitalCommons@University of Nebraska -Lincoln.<lb/> Kulkarni, S. M.; Arnold, R. G.; and Maxcy, R. B., &quot;Reuse Limits and Regeneration of Solutions for Cleaning Dairy Equipment&quot; (1975).<lb/> Faculty Publications in Food Science and Technology. Paper 60.<lb/></note>

	<ptr type="web">http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/foodsciefacpub/60<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="other">RESEARCH PAPERS<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Reuse Limits and Regeneration of Solutions<lb/> for Cleaning Dairy Equipment I<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>S. M. KULKARNI, R. G. ARNOLD, and R. B. MAXCY<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology<lb/> University of Nebraska<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Lincoln 68503<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Usable life of cleaning solutions in a<lb/> model heat processing unit was studied<lb/> by evaluation of the nature and quantity<lb/> of residue remaining on the surface of the<lb/> equipment after cleaning. Lipoidal resi-<lb/>due was recovered from equipment sur-<lb/>faces by ether rinsing. A surface displace-<lb/>ment technique was used to quantify the<lb/> lipoidal material, which was characterized<lb/> by gas-liquid chromatographic analyses of<lb/> triglycerides and fatty acid methyl esters.<lb/> Effects of factors, such as water hardness,<lb/> rinse water temperature, cleaning solution<lb/> additives and acid versus alkaline cleaners<lb/> also were investigated in relation to over-<lb/>all cleaning efficiency. After evaluating<lb/> limits of reuse of cleaning solutions, used<lb/> solutions were regenerated by sorption of<lb/> lipoidal residue on Celite, resulting in<lb/> restored cleaning effectiveness. When<lb/> spent-cleaning solutions were circulated<lb/> in previously cleaned equipment, there<lb/> was redeposition of lipoidal material onto<lb/> the equipment surfaces.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
