<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="journal-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55115208"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Ž<lb/> .</note>

	<reference>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta 1324 1997 27–36<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The reduction of the positive charges of polylysine by partial<lb/> gluconoylation increases the transfection efficiency of polylysinerDNA<lb/> complexes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Patrick Erbacher, Annie Claude Roche, Michel Monsigny, Patrick Midoux<lb/> )<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Glycobiologie, Centre de Biophysique Moleculaire, CNRS et UniÕersite d&apos;Orleans,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1 rue Charles-Sadron, F-45071 Orleans Cedex 02 rance<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 16 July 1996; revised 13 September 1996; accepted 24 September 1996<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/>A polylysine partially substituted with polyhydroxyalkanoyl residues and specially with gluconoyl residues was<lb/> developed in order to increase the transfection efficiency by decreasing the strength of the electrostatic interactions between<lb/> the DNA and the cationic polymer. Partially gluconoylated polylysine r DNA complexes were more easily dissociated in<lb/> solution and their transfection efficiency in the presence of chloroquine, evaluated with HepG2 cells, a human hepatocarci-<lb/> nomaline, was higher when 43 &quot; 4% of the e-amino groups of polylysine were blocked with gluconoyl residues. Partially<lb/> gluconoylated polylysine r plasmid complexes were efficient intransfecting different adherent as well as non-adherent cell<lb/>Ž.<lb/> lines. Partially gluconoylated polylysine formed highly soluble above 100mg rmlin DNA complexes with DNA<lb/> plasmids. In addition, partially gluconoylated polylysine bearing few lactosyl residues increased the transfection efficiency<lb/> of HepG2 cells which express a galactose-specific membrane lectin.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: Gene therapy; Gene transfer; Polylysine; Chloroquine<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
