<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="journal-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55113548"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of Energy Chemistry 22(2013)136–144<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Remarkable carbon dioxide catalytic capture (CDCC) leading to<lb/> solid-form carbon material via a new CVD integrated process<lb/> (CVD-IP): An alternative route for CO 2 sequestration<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Wei Chu a,c* , Maofei Ran a , Xu Zhang a , Ning Wang a , Yufei Wang b , Heping Xie b , Xiusong Zhao d,e*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a. Key Laboratory Green Chemistry &amp; Technology of Ministry of Education (MOE), College of Chemical Engineering, Sichuan University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Chengdu 610065,<lb/> Sichuan, China;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b. State Key Laboratory of Hydraulics and Mountain River Engineering, Sichuan University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Chengdu 610065, Sichuan, China;<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c. SABIC Technology Center Riyadh,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P. O. Box 42503, Riyadh, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>d. Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering,<lb/> National University of Singapore,
	</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Engineering Drive 4, 117576, Singapore;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>e. University Queensland, School Chemical Engineering,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Brisbane 4072, Australia<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">[ Manuscript received December 10, 2012; revised December 20, 2012 ]<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract Through our newly-developed &quot;chemical vapor deposition integrated process (CVD-IP)&quot; using carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) as the raw material<lb/> and only carbon source introduced, CO 2 could be catalytically activated and converted to a new solid-form product, i.e., carbon nanotubes<lb/> (CO 2 -derived) at a quite high yield (the single-pass carbon yield in the solid-form carbon-product produced from CO 2 catalytic capture and<lb/> conversion was more than 30% at a single-pass carbon-base). For comparison, when only pure carbon dioxide was introduced using the<lb/> conventional CVD method without integrated process, no solid-form carbon-material product could be formed. In the addition of saturated<lb/> steam at room temperature in the feed for CVD, there were much more end-opening carbon nano-tubes produced, at a slightly higher carbon<lb/> yield. These inspiring works opened a remarkable and alternative new approach for carbon dioxide catalytic capture to solid-form product,<lb/> comparing with that of CO 2 sequestration (CCS) or CO 2 mineralization (solidification), etc. As a result, there was much less body volume and<lb/> almost no greenhouse effect for this solid-form carbon-material than those of primitive carbon dioxide.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key words<lb/> carbon dioxide catalytic capture (CDCC); carbon nanotubes (CNTs); chemical vapor deposition integrated process (CVD-IP); solid-form<lb/> carbon material; debating greenhouse gases (GHG) effects<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
