<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="serie-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55114520"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Adaptive thresholding of digital subtraction angiography images<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Nong Sang<lb/> a<lb/> , Heng Li<lb/> b<lb/> , Weixue Peng<lb/> a<lb/> , Tianxu Zhang<lb/> b<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a<lb/> Institute for Pattern Recognition and Artificial Intelligence<lb/> Huazhong University of Science and Technology,
	</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wuhan 430074, P.R. China<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b<lb/> Key Laboratory of Ministry of Education for Image Processing and Intelligent Control<lb/> Huazhong University of Science and Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wuhan 430074, P.R. China<lb/></address>

	<email>Email: joelhqlj@hotmail.com<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> In clinical practice, digital subtraction angiography (DSA) is a powerful technique for the visualization of blood vessels in<lb/> the human body. Blood vessel segmentation is a main problem for 3D vascular reconstruction. In this paper, we propose a<lb/> new adaptive thresholding method for the segmentation of DSA images. Each pixel of the DSA images is declared to be a<lb/> vessel/background point with regard to a threshold and a few local characteristic limits depending on some information<lb/> contained in the pixel neighborhood window. The size of the neighborhood window is set according to a priori knowledge of<lb/> the diameter of vessels to make sure that each window contains the background definitely. Some experiments on cerebral<lb/> DSA images are given, which show that our proposed method yields better results than global thresholding methods and<lb/> some other local thresholding methods do.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords: digital subtraction angiography, vessel segmentation, adaptive thresholding, local characteristic limits<lb/>
	</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
