<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="product-sheet">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55113611"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Opadry®<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<note type="other">Product Information<lb/> </note>

	<note>One Step Film Coating System<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Opadry<lb/> ® </div>

	<note type="page">-1 -<lb/></note>

	<div type="introduction">Reconstitution<lb/> Opadry ® , one step film coating system, is quick and easy to prepare. Simply add the pre-formulated powder<lb/> to the relevant solvents and mix for 45 minutes with a propeller stirrer.* The coating suspension can be made<lb/> with 5 -15% w/w solids in water or up to 5 -8% w/w solids in organic solvent or hydro-alcoholic solvent<lb/> solutions. The recommended solvent solutions are as follows: Alcohol/methylene chloride (dichloromethane):<lb/> 50/50 or Alcohol /purified water: 80/20. The recommended type of alcohol, in order of preference is methanol,<lb/> ethanol, or isopropyl alcohol. Your Area Technical Manager can recommend the ideal solids and solvents for<lb/> your specific Opadry system and equipment.<lb/> 
	
	MATERIALS<lb/> F i g u r e 1<lb/> @BULLET Opadry film coating system.<lb/> @BULLET Water, deionized or distilled preferred ambient temperature<lb/> (maximum 30° C).<lb/> @BULLET Alcohol (see above for suggested alcohol type).<lb/> @BULLET Methylene Chloride (dichloromethane).<lb/> EQUIPMENT<lb/> @BULLET Variable-speed mixer capable of producing and maintaining a vortex.<lb/> @BULLET Propeller stirrer. For optimum mixing, utilize a propeller with a<lb/> diameter equivalent to 1/4 -1/3 of the diameter of the mixing vessel.<lb/> (Figure 1.)<lb/> @BULLET Mixing vessel large enough to contain a liquid volume 15% to 25%<lb/> greater than the total suspension being prepared. The liquid height and vessel diameter should be equal.<lb/> *MIXING PROCEDURE<lb/> 1. Weigh necessary quantity of Opadry film coating system.<lb/> 2. Weigh necessary quantity of solvent into the mixing vessel.<lb/> 3. With the propeller in the centre and as close to the bottom of the vessel as possible, stir the solvent to<lb/> form a vortex without drawing air into the liquid.<lb/> 4. Steadily add the Opadry system powder to the vortex, avoiding powder flotation on the liquid surface. If<lb/> required, increase the stirrer speed in order to maintain the vortex.<lb/> 5. After all the Opadry system has been added, reduce the mixer speed to nearly eliminate the vortex. Mix<lb/> for 45 minutes.<lb/> SUSPENSION HANDLING<lb/> @BULLET The prepared Opadry dispersion can be pumped directly from the preparation vessel if desired.<lb/> @BULLET We recommend that the Opadry dispersion be gently agitated during the coating process.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
