<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="journal-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55115386"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of Asian Ceramic Societies 1 (2013) 17–25<lb/> </reference>

	<note type="other">Journal of Asian Ceramic Societies<lb/> Journal of Asian Ceramic Societies<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : </note>

	<ptr>w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / j a s c e r<lb/></ptr>
	
	<note type="other">Review article<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Recent development of sulfide solid electrolytes and interfacial modification for<lb/> all-solid-state rechargeable lithium batteries<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Masahiro Tatsumisago<lb/> * , Motohiro Nagao, Akitoshi Hayashi<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Applied Chemistry, Graduate School of Engineering, Osaka Prefecture University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1-1 Gakuen-cho, Naka-ku, Sakai, Osaka 599-8531, Japan<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Article history:<lb/> Received 17 February 2013<lb/> Accepted 18 March 2013<lb/></note>

	<date>Available online 9 April 2013<lb/></date>

	<keyword>Keywords:<lb/> Sulfide solid electrolyte<lb/> Interfacial modification<lb/> All-solid-state battery<lb/> Rechargeable lithium battery<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">a b s t r a c t<lb/> Recent development of inorganic sulfide solid electrolytes and all-solid-state rechargeable lithium bat-<lb/>teries with them is reviewed. Electrical conductivity, electrochemical stability and chemical stability<lb/> of these sulfide electrolytes are reported. Formation of favorable solid–solid contacts between elec-<lb/>trode and electrolyte is important in all-solid-state batteries. Useful techniques to achieving intimate<lb/> electrode–electrolyte interfaces are proposed. Application of sulfur positive electrode and lithium metal<lb/> negative electrode with large theoretical capacity to all-solid-state lithium batteries is demonstrated.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2013 The Ceramic Society of Japan and the Korean Ceramic Society. Production and hosting by<lb/> Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
