<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="journal-article">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55113733"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Effects of Laminaria japonica on the physico-chemical and sensory characteristics of<lb/> reduced-fat pork patties<lb/>
	</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Yun-Sang Choi<lb/> a<lb/> , Ji-Hun Choi<lb/> b , Doo-Jeong Han<lb/> b , Hack-Youn Kim<lb/> b , Hyun-Wook Kim<lb/> b , Mi-Ai Lee<lb/> c<lb/> , Hai-Jung Chung<lb/> d , Cheon-Jei Kim<lb/> b,<lb/> ⁎<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Food and Biological Resources Examination Division, Korean Intellectual Property Office,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Dunsan-dong, Seo-gu, Daejeon 302-701, Republic of Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Department of Food Science and Biotechnology of Animal Resources, Konkuk University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1 Hwayang-dong, Gwangjin-gu, Seoul 143-701, Republic of Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c World Institute of Kimchi, An Annex of Korea Food Research Institute,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Baekhyun-dong, Bundang-ku, Sungnam-si, Gyeonggido, 463-746, Republic of Korea<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>d Department of Food Science and Nutrition, Daejin University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sundan-ri, Phochon-si, Gyeonggido 487-711, Republic of Korea<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">a b s t r a c t<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Article history:<lb/> Received 30 December 2010<lb/> Received in revised form 14 February 2011<lb/> Accepted 2 November 2011<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Keywords:<lb/> Laminaria japonica<lb/> Reduced-fat<lb/> Pork patties<lb/> Dietary fiber<lb/> Quality properties<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">Reduced-fat pork patties produced with the addition of Laminaria japonica powder were evaluated for the<lb/> chemical composition, cooking characteristics and sensory properties. Reduced-fat pork patties containing<lb/> L. japonica powder had significantly higher moisture, ash, carbohydrate content, yellowness, and springiness<lb/> than the control sample (P b 0.05). Protein and fat contents, energy value, lightness, redness, cooking loss, re-<lb/>duction in diameter, reduction in thickness, hardness, gumminess, and chewiness of the regular-fat (20%)<lb/> control samples were significantly higher than reduced-fat pork patties containing L. japonica (P b 0.05).<lb/> The sensory evaluations indicated that the greatest overall acceptability in reduced-fat pork patties was<lb/> attained at a L. japonica concentration of 1 or 3%. Pork patties with fat contents reduced from 20% to 10%<lb/> and supplemented with 1 or 3% L. japonica had improved quality characteristics that were similar to the con-<lb/>trol patties containing a fat content of 20%.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2011 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
