<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei type="web">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55115488"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Black cBNMesh<lb/> Light Amber cBNMesh<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Cubic Boron Nitride Products<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">Cubic Boron Nitride Products – cBNMesh and cBNMic<lb/> Cubic Boron nitride, cBN, is the second hardest material after diamond but it has one key<lb/> advantage over diamond: it does not chemically wear in the presence of graphite and/or carbide<lb/> forming elements like iron, nickel or cobalt, for example, during abrasive processing. It is therefore<lb/> the preferred product for machining of ferrous materials. Unlike diamond, cBN is only available as<lb/> a synthesized material, it does not occur naturally. But this means that, like synthetic diamond, it<lb/> can be tailored to provide exactly the required characteristics for the application and key to this is<lb/> the ability to synthesize tetrahedral morphology in addition to the cubic / octahedral morphology<lb/> that also occurs in diamond. It is available from coarse grit down to micron powder and as<lb/> sintered polycrystalline products.<lb/> cBN varies in colour from a light amber colour to a boron rich black colour and this difference<lb/> does manifest itself in a difference in performance depending on the tool type and application.<lb/> For instance, the boron-rich material is often considered more difficult to use in electroplated<lb/> tools since it can lead to overplating.<lb/> NDP markets its range of cBN under the trade names cBNMesh and cBNMic. cBNMesh is available<lb/> from 50/60 to 325/400 mesh and cBNMic is available from 0-0.5 micron up to 40-60 micron. There is<lb/> a variant suitable for all of the bond types commonly used: metal, electroplated, resin and<lb/> vitreous.<lb/> It is available with a 60% nickel cladding for resin bonds or titanium for metal bonds. As a grit<lb/> product, cBNMesh it is used in grinding wheels for a myriad of applications: high stock removal<lb/> OD and surface grinding, profile grinding, surface finishing and sharpening of steel cutters. As a<lb/> micron product, cBNMic is used for lapping, honing and polishing of many components in fields<lb/> of automotive, aerospace and scientific instruments.<lb/></div>

	<note type="other">NANODIAMOND PRODUCTS<lb/> Diamond<lb/> Polycrystalline<lb/> cBN<lb/> cBNMesh<lb/> cBNMic<lb/> Tel: +353 61 360333<lb/> Home About Us<lb/> Applications Products<lb/> Technology Contact Us<lb/> Home / Cubic Boron Nitride Products<lb/> Cubic Boron Nitride Products | Nano Diamond Products<lb/></note>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.nanodiaproducts.com/cbn/<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="page">1 of 2<lb/></note>

	<date>28-04-2014</date>

	<note type="other">10:09</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
