<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="67FA6A2CCF3B44A06E0C65E8B827B3F8DF9D1C6F"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Community Mental Health Journal, Vol. 29, No. 2, April 1993<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Assessing Levels of<lb/> Adaptive Functioning:<lb/> The Role Functioning Scale<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sherryl H. Goodman, Ph.D.<lb/> Daniel R. Sewell, Ph.D.<lb/> Eileen L. Cooley, Ph.D.<lb/> Naomi Leavitt, Ph.D.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	ABSTRACT:
	<div type="abstract">This paper reports data on reliability and validity of the Role Function-<lb/>ing Scale (RFS) a measure of level of functioning of adults in four domains. Psycho-<lb/>metric properties were tested on an inner city sample of 112 psychiatrically disturbed<lb/> and well, predominantly African-American, low-income mothers of young children. The<lb/> RFS has good interitem, test-retest, and interrater reliability. The four scales and<lb/> global RFS Index discriminated accurately between well and disturbed subjects. The<lb/> Global RFS Index was significantly correlated with self-esteem and degree of distur-<lb/>bance. Individual scales demonstrated predicted relationships with quality of child-<lb/>rearing and other independent behavioral indices. Results are discussed in terms of the<lb/> unique information provided by the RFS and its potential contribution to treatment<lb/> planning.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sherryl H. Goodman</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	is affiliated with 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Emory University. </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Daniel R. Sewell</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	is affiliated with<lb/> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Freedom Recovery Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Metairie, LA.</address> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Eileen L. Cooley</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	is affiliated with 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Agnes Scott College,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>Decatur, GA.</address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Naomi Leavitt</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	is affiliated with 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Bridgewater State Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bridgewater, MA.<lb/></address>

	Requests for reprints should be sent to
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sherryl Goodman,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Psychology, Emory<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Atlanta, Georgia 30322.<lb/></address>

	<note type="funding">Preparation of this article was supported in part by National Institute of Mental Health Grant<lb/> #MH35042-02 to Sherryl Goodman.<lb/> We gratefully acknowledge the assistance of the Project PACT staff in the data collection and of<lb/> the families for their participation in the research. Nangel Lindberg and Mary Goedde assisted in<lb/> the final preparation of the manuscript.</note>

	<page>119<lb/></page>
	
	<note type="copyright">9 1993 Human Sciences Press, Inc.</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
