<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="6CDD1BB7BE4988F7EBB93484C0ED304C17EFB0E5"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">L E T T E R S<lb/></note>

	<reference>NATURE CELL BIOLOGY VOLUME 8 | NUMBER 6 | JUNE 2006<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The NuMA-related Mud protein binds Pins and<lb/> regulates spindle orientation in Drosophila neuroblasts<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Karsten H. Siller 1 , Clemens Cabernard 1 and Chris Q. Doe 1,2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Asymmetric cell division generates cell diversity during<lb/> development 1,2 and regulates stem-cell self-renewal in<lb/> Drosophila and mammals 3,4 . In Drosophila, neuroblasts align<lb/> their spindle with a cortical Partner of Inscuteable (Pins)−Gαi<lb/> crescent to divide asymmetrically, but the link between cortical<lb/> polarity and the mitotic spindle is poorly understood. Here, we<lb/> show that Pins directly binds, and coimmunoprecipitates with,<lb/> the NuMA-related Mushroom body defect (Mud) protein. Pins<lb/> recruits Mud to the neuroblast apical cortex, and Mud is also<lb/> strongly localized to centrosome/spindle poles, in a similar way<lb/> to NuMA. In mud mutants, cortical polarity is normal, but the<lb/> metaphase spindle frequently fails to align with the cortical<lb/> polarity axis. When spindle orientation is orthogonal to cell<lb/> polarity, symmetric division occurs. We propose that Mud is a<lb/> functional orthologue of mammalian NuMA and Caenorhabditis<lb/> elegans Lin-5, and that Mud coordinates spindle orientation<lb/> with cortical polarity to promote asymmetric cell division.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Institute of Molecular Biology, Institute of Neuroscience, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, University of Oregon,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Eugene, OR 97403, USA.<lb/></address>

	2 Correspondence should be addressed to C.Q.D. (e-mail:
	<email>cdoe@uoregon.edu</email>

	)<lb/>
	<note type="submission">Received 20 March 2006; accepted 10 April 2006;</note>

	published online
	<date>30 April 2006</date>

	;
	<idno>DOI: 10.1038/ncb1412<lb/></idno>

	<note type="copyright">Nature Publishing Group ©2006</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
