<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="719708v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page> 

	Face-hand interactions revealed by afferent inhibition<lb/> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Electrocutaneous stimulation to the face inhibits motor evoked<lb/> potentials in the hand: face-hand interactions revealed by afferent inhibition<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Bia L. Ramalho 1,2,#,* , Julien Moly 1,2 , Estelle Raffin 3 , Sylvain Harquel 3 ,<lb/> Alessandro Farnè 1,2,4 , Karen T. Reilly 1,2,*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1. ImpAct team, Lyon Neuroscience Research Center, INSERM U1028, CRNS-<lb/>UMR5292,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bron, France.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2. Lyon 1 University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Lyon, France.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3. University Grenoble Alpes, Grenoble Institute of Neuroscience, INSERM<lb/> U1216,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Grenoble, France.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4. Hospices Civils de Lyon, Neuro-immersion,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bron, France.<lb/></address>

	# Current Address: 
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Laboratory of Neurobiology II, Institute of Biophysics Carlos<lb/> Chagas Filho, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.<lb/></address>

	*Corresponding authors<lb/> E-mail :
	<email>ramalhobsl@biof.ufrj.br</email>

	(BR) and
	<email>karen.reilly@inserm.fr</email>

	(KR) 2 Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Reorganization of the sensorimotor cortex following amputation and other<lb/> interventions has revealed large-scale plastic changes between the hand and<lb/> face representations. To investigate whether hand-face interactions are also<lb/> present in the normal state of the system we measured sensorimotor interactions<lb/> between these two areas using an afferent inhibition transcranial magnetic<lb/> stimulation (TMS) protocol in which the TMS motor evoked potential (MEP) is<lb/> inhibited when it is preceded by an afferent stimulus. We hypothesized that if<lb/> hand-face interactions exist in the normal state of the system then stimulation of<lb/> the face would inhibit hand MEPs. In two separate experiments we delivered an<lb/> electrocutaneous stimulus to either the right upper lip (Experiment 1) or right<lb/> cheek (Experiment 2) and recorded muscular activity from the right first dorsal<lb/> interosseous (FDI). Both lip and cheek stimulation inhibited FDI MEPs. To<lb/> investigate the specificity of this effect we conducted two additional experiments<lb/> in which cutaneous stimulation was applied to either the right forearm<lb/> (Experiment 3) or right arm (Experiment 4). Neither forearm nor arm stimulation<lb/> inhibited FDI MEPs. These data provide the first evidence for face-to-hand<lb/> afferent inhibition and we suggest that the mechanisms underlying these<lb/> sensorimotor interactions could contribute to face/hand interactions observed<lb/> following sensorimotor reorganisation.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
