<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="732859v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page> 
	Title page<lb/> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Pseudolesion in the right parafissural liver parenchyma on CT: the base is<lb/> found in embryology and collagen content.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle> 

	Short title: The liver pseudolesion is a normal developmental phenomenon<lb/> 

	Author list<lb/>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Willemijn M Klein 1 , Lianne JP Sonnemans 1 , Sabine Franckenberg 2,3 , Barbara<lb/> Fliss 3 , Dominic Gascho 3 , Mathias Prokop 1 , Wouter H Lamers 4 , Jill PJM Hikspoors 4 ,<lb/> Michael J Thali 3 , Patricia M Flach 3,5<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Radiology and Nuclear Medicine, Radboud university medical<lb/> center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nijmegen, the Netherlands<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Institute for Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital Zurich,<lb/> University of Zurich,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Zürich, Switzerland</address>

	(current working address)<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Forensic Medicine and Imaging, Institute of Forensic Medicine,<lb/> University of Zürich,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Zürich, Switzerland<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Anatomy and Embryology, Maastricht University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Maastricht, the Netherlands<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Clinic for Radiology and Nuclear Medicine, Cantonal Hospital St.</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gallen, St. Gallen,<lb/> Switzerland</address>

	(current working address) 2<lb/> Corresponding author<lb/> e-mail:
	<email>Willemijn.Klein@radboudumc.nl</email>

	(WK)<lb/> Additional Information<lb/> The authors declare no competing interests.<lb/> Pseudolesion in the right parafissural liver parenchyma on CT: the base is<lb/> found in embryology and collagen content.<lb/> Short title: The liver pseudolesion is a normal developmental phenomenon Abstract<lb/>
	
	<div type="abstract">Background: Computed tomography (CT) images of livers may show a hypo-<lb/>attenuated structure alongside the falciform ligament, which can be a focal fatty<lb/> pseudolesion and can mimic a malignancy. The preferred location is on the right<lb/> parafissural site, ventral in segment IVa/b. The etiology is not clear, nor is it known<lb/> how the histology of this location develops. These are evaluated in this study.<lb/> Methods: 40 adult cadavers with autopsy and / or postmortem CT in a university<lb/> hospital and a forensic center were included. Liver biopsies were taken at the left<lb/> side of the falciform ligament as control, and at the right side as the possible<lb/> precursor of a pseudolesion; these were examined for collagen and fat content. 3<lb/> Cadavers with steatotic (&gt;5% fat) or fibrotic (&gt;2% collagen) control samples were<lb/> excluded.<lb/> Results: Significantly more collagen was present in the right parafissural liver<lb/> parenchyma: median 0.68% (IQR: 0.32 -1.17%), compared to the left side 0.48%<lb/> (IQR: 0.21 -0.75%) (p 0.008), with equal fat content and CT attenuation values. The<lb/> etiophysiology goes back to the demise of the umbilical venes in the early embryonic<lb/> and neonatal period.<lb/> Conclusions: The right parafissural area contains more collagen and an equal<lb/> amount of fat compared to the control left side. This supports the hypothesis of<lb/> delayed, &apos;third&apos; inflow: the postnatal change in blood supply from umbilical to portal<lb/> leaves the downstream parafissural area hypoperfused leading to hypoxia which in<lb/> turn results in collagen accumulation and the persistence of paraumbilical veins of<lb/> Sappey.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>liver, pseudolesion, histology, etiology<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">Key points<lb/> 1. The typical location for a parafissural hepatic pseudolesion contains increased<lb/> collagen.<lb/> 2. A change in histology is caused by physiological demise of the umbilical<lb/> venes. 4<lb/> 3. The suboptimal blood supply of the right parafissural side leads to hypoxia<lb/> and collagen deposition.<lb/> 4. Embryologic knowledge and postmortem histology can help resolve issues in<lb/> radiology.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
