<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="75E64DC1152F1C53894B27B14C76E9F0BAFAD509"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<note type="doctype">Papers<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Acute treatment of moderate to severe depression with hypericum<lb/> extract WS 5570 (St John&apos;s wort): randomised controlled double<lb/> blind non-inferiority trial versus paroxetine<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>A Szegedi, R Kohnen, A Dienel, M Kieser</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Objective To investigate the efficacy of hypericum extract WS<lb/> 5570 (St John&apos;s wort) compared with paroxetine in patients with<lb/> moderate to severe major depression.<lb/> Design Randomised double blind, double dummy, reference<lb/> controlled, multicentre non-inferiority trial.<lb/> Setting 21 psychiatric primary care practices in Germany.<lb/> Participants 251 adult outpatients with acute major depression<lb/> with total score ≥ 22 on the 17 item Hamilton depression scale.<lb/> Interventions 900 mg/day hypericum extract WS 5570 three<lb/> times a day or 20 mg paroxetine once a day for six weeks. In<lb/> initial non-responders doses were increased to 1800 mg/day<lb/> hypericum or 40 mg/day paroxetine after two weeks.<lb/> Main outcome measures Change in score on Hamilton<lb/> depression scale from baseline to day 42 (primary outcome).<lb/> Secondary measures were change in scores on<lb/> Montgomery-Åsberg depression rating scale, clinical global<lb/> impressions, and Beck depression inventory.<lb/> Results The Hamilton depression total score decreased by<lb/> mean 14.4 (SD 8.8) points, corresponding to 56.6% (SD 34.3%)<lb/> of the baseline value, in the hypericum group and by 11.4 (SD<lb/> 8.6) points (44.8% (SD 33.5%) of baseline value) in the<lb/> paroxetine group (intention to treat analysis; similar results<lb/> were observed in the per protocol analysis). The intention to<lb/> treat analysis (lower one sided 97.5% confidence limit 1.5 points<lb/> for the difference hypericum minus paroxetine) and the per<lb/> protocol analysis (lower confidence limit 0.7 points) showed<lb/> non-inferiority of hypericum and statistical superiority over<lb/> paroxetine. The lower limits in both cases exceeded the<lb/> pre-specified non-inferiority margin of − 2.5 points and the<lb/> superiority margin of 0. The incidence of adverse events was<lb/> 0.035 and 0.060 events per day of exposure for hypericum and<lb/> paroxetine, respectively.<lb/> Conclusions In the treatment of moderate to severe major<lb/> depression, hypericum extract WS 5570 is at least as effective as<lb/> paroxetine and is better tolerated.<lb/></div>

	Cite this article as: 
	<title level="j">BMJ</title>, 

	<idno>doi:10.1136/bmj.38356.655266.82</idno>

	(published
	<date>11 February 2005</date>
	)<lb/> 
	BMJ Online First bmj.com<lb/> 

	<page>page 1 of 5<lb/></page> 

	<note type="submission">(Accepted 17 December 2004)<lb/></note>

	<idno>doi 10.1136/bmj.38356.655266.82<lb/></idno>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Campus Benjamin Franklin, Department of<lb/> Psychiatry and Psychotherapy,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Eschenallee 3, 14050 Berlin, Germany<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>A Szegedi</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	managing senior physician<lb/> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institute for Medical Research Management and Biometrics GmbH,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Scheurlstraße<lb/> 21, 90478 Nürnberg, Germany<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>R Kohnen</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	head of scientific affairs<lb/> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Dr Willmar Schwabe Pharmaceuticals,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>PO Box 410925, 76209 Karlsruhe,<lb/> Germany<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>A Dienel</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	head of clinical trials department<lb/> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>M Kieser</docAuthor>
	</byline>
	 
	head of biometry department<lb/> 

	Correspondence to: M Kieser
	<email>meinhard.kieser@schwabe.de</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
