<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="7B500C33DCC28A2530BB5A6E4083F9AFDE902102"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">A R T I C L E S<lb/></note>

	<page>308<lb/></page>

	<reference>NATURE CELL BIOLOGY VOLUME 6 | NUMBER 4 | APRIL 2004<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A signalling pathway controlling c-Myc<lb/> degradation that impacts oncogenic transformation<lb/> of human cells<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Elizabeth Yeh 1 , Melissa Cunningham 2 , Hugh Arnold 2 , Dawn Chasse 3 , Teresa Monteith 3 , Giovanni Ivaldi 1 ,<lb/> William C. Hahn 4 , P. Todd Stukenberg 5 , Shirish Shenolikar 1 , Takafumi Uchida 6 , Christopher M. Counter 1 ,<lb/> Joseph R. Nevins 3 , Anthony R. Means 1 and Rosalie Sears 2,7<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">The stability of c-Myc is regulated by multiple Ras effector pathways. Phosphorylation at Ser 62 stabilizes c-Myc, whereas<lb/> subsequent phosphorylation at Thr 58 is required for its degradation. Here we show that Ser 62 is dephosphorylated by protein<lb/> phosphatase 2A (PP2A) before ubiquitination of c-Myc, and that PP2A activity is regulated by the Pin1 prolyl isomerase.<lb/> Furthermore, the absence of Pin1 or inhibition of PP2A stabilizes c-Myc. A stable c-Myc T58A mutant that cannot bind Pin1 or be<lb/> dephosphorylated by PP2A replaces SV40 small T antigen in human cell transformation and tumorigenesis assays. Therefore,<lb/> small T antigen, which inactivates PP2A, exerts its oncogenic potential by preventing dephosphorylation of c-Myc, resulting in<lb/> c-Myc stabilization. Thus, Ras-dependent signalling cascades ensure transient and self-limiting accumulation of c-Myc,<lb/> disruption of which contributes to human cell oncogenesis.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Pharmacology and Cancer Biology, Duke University Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Durham, NC 27710, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Molecular and Medical Genetics,<lb/> Oregon Health and Sciences University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Portland, OR 97239, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Duke<lb/> University Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Durham, NC 27710, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Medical Oncology and Medicine, Dana Farber Cancer Institute, Brigham and Women&apos;s Hospital,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA 02115, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Genetics, University of Virginia Medical School,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Charlottesville, VA<lb/> 22908, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 Institute of Development, Aging, and Cancer, Tohuku University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>4-1 Seiryo, Aoba, Sendai 980-8575, Japan.<lb/></address>

	7 Correspondence should be addressed to R.S. (e-mail:
	<email>searsr@ohsu.edu</email>).<lb/>

	Published online:
	<date>14 March 2004</date>

	;
	<idno>DOI: 10.1038/ncb1110<lb/></idno>

	<note type="submission">Received 17 November 2003; accepted 25 MARCH 2004<lb/></note>

	Published online at http://www.nature.com/naturecellbiology.

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
