<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="853911v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<page>1 of 27<lb/></page>

	Willis, Kamphausen, et al. 2019<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Restoration, dispersal and settlement of native European oyster (Ostrea<lb/> edulis) in energetic tidal areas.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	Running head: Oyster settlement models<lb/> 

	<date>23 rd November 2019<lb/></date>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jay Willis 1* , Lisa Kamphausen 2 , Anthony Jensen 3 , Roger J.H. Herbert 4 , Elfed Jones 5<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1. Corresponding author. Turnpenny Horsfield Associates</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>UK</address>. 
	(
	<email>jkwillis@gmail.com</email>
	)<lb/>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2. Scottish Natural Heritage,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Inverness, IV3 8NW UK.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3. University of Southampton,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>SO17 1BJ UK.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4. University of Bournemouth,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>BH1 3LT UK.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5. HR Wallingford Ltd.</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>OX10 8BA UK.<lb/></address>

	Word count 4984<lb/>

	Willis, Kamphausen, et al. 2019

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">We modelled the pelagic larval phase of native European oyster (Ostrea edulis) in the Solent.<lb/> The Solent is a complex and tidally energetic environment on the south coast of the UK. Until<lb/> recently it was the largest self-sustaining fishery of the native oyster in Europe. We developed a<lb/> new larval settlement behavioural model that is the simplest plausible model which remains<lb/> consistent with all available data and evidence on larval behaviour. We used a hydrodynamic<lb/> sub-model, a Lagrangian advection sub-model, and an individual agent based model. The results<lb/> demonstrate how isolated oyster assemblages can re-populate larger areas of historical<lb/> inhabitance. We predict the most likely patterns of redistribution from refugia or from fisheries<lb/> seeding. We show that settlement swimming behaviour is as equally important as passive<lb/> hydrodynamic transport for larval survival and adult distribution and that settlement swimming<lb/> behaviour has a profound impact on settlement patterns. The models show that managed<lb/> broodstock refugia have the potential to seed much larger oyster beds in contrast to broad-scale<lb/> seeding. Such refugia have the advantage of maintaining a locally high and mature population<lb/> with potential for reef features and their associated biodiversity. We show that such refugia may<lb/> be best placed in the tidally dynamic and exposed areas rather than on sheltered coastal sites as<lb/> they have been in the past. Our model is insensitive to parameter variation and could be an<lb/> effective and practical management tool in the face of a paucity of field data on larval distribution<lb/> and behaviour.</div>

	Keywords<lb/>
	<keyword>Benign invasion Connectivity<lb/> ELAM Eulerian Lagrangian Agent Based Model<lb/> Habitat restoration<lb/> PLD Pelagic larval duration<lb/> Range collapse<lb/> Spat fall</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
