<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="902718v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>NRF1 and NRF3 complementarily maintain a basal proteasome activity in cancer cells<lb/> through CPEB3-mediated translational repression<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	Running title: NRF3-CPEB3-NRF1 axis for proteasome regulation<lb/>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Tsuyoshi Waku 1 † , Hiroyuki Katayama 2 † , Miyako Hiraoka 2 , Atsushi Hatanaka 2, 3 , Nanami<lb/> Nakamura 2 , Yuya Tanaka 1 , Natsuko Tamura 2 , Akira Watanabe 4 , Akira Kobayashi 1,2 *<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	†Equal contribution<lb/>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Laboratory for Genetic Code, Department of Medical Life Systems, Faculty of Life and Medical<lb/> Sciences, Doshisha University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kyotanabe, Kyoto, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Laboratory for Genetic Code, Graduate School of Life and Medical Sciences, Doshisha<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kyotanabe, Kyoto, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Research Fellow of Japan Society for the Promotion of Science,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tokyo, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Department of Life Science Frontiers, Center for iPS Cell Research and Application, Kyoto<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kyoto, Japan<lb/></address>

	*To whom correspondence should be addressed:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Akira Kobayashi<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1-3 Tatara Miyakodani, Kyotanabe 610-0394, Japan<lb/></address>

	Phone: 
	<phone>+81-774-65-6273<lb/></phone> 
	Fax: +81-774-65-6274<lb/> 
	E-mail:
	<email>akobayas@mail.doshisha.ac.jp</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Proteasomes are protease complexes essential for cellular homeostasis, and their activity is crucial<lb/> for cancer cell growth. However, the mechanism of how proteasome activity is maintained in<lb/> cancer cells has remained unclear. The CNC family transcription factor NRF1 induces the<lb/> expression of almost all proteasome-related genes under proteasome inhibition. NRF1 and its<lb/> phylogenetically closest homolog NRF3 are both highly expressed in several types of cancers,<lb/> such as colorectal cancer. Herein, we demonstrate that NRF1 and NRF3 complementarily<lb/> maintain basal proteasome activity in cancer cells. A double knockdown of NRF1 and NRF3<lb/> impaired the basal proteasome activity in cancer cells and the cancer cell resistance to a<lb/> proteasome inhibitor anticancer drug bortezomib by significantly reducing basal expression of<lb/> seven proteasome-related genes, including PSMB3, PSMB7, PSMC2, PSMD3, PSMG2, PSMG3,<lb/> and POMP. Interestingly, the molecular basis behind these cellular consequences was that NRF3<lb/> repressed NRF1 translation by the gene induction of translational regulator CPEB3, which binds<lb/> to NRF1-3′UTR and decreases polysome formation on NRF1 mRNA. Consistent results were<lb/> obtained from clinical analysis, wherein patients with cancer having higher CPEB3/NRF3-<lb/>expressing tumors exhibit poor prognosis. These results provide the novel regulatory mechanism<lb/> of basal proteasome activity in cancer cells through an NRF3-CPEB3-NRF1 translational<lb/> repression axis.<lb/></div>

	* *<lb/> Emp<lb/> Flag-CPEB3<lb/> siCont siNRF3
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
