<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="904052v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Function and evolution of B-Raf loop dynamics relevant to<lb/> cancer recurrence under drug inhibition<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Gregory A. Babbitt 1 *, Miranda L. Lynch 2 , Matthew McCoy 3 , Ernest P. Fokoue 4 , and André O.<lb/> Hudson 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Thomas H. Gosnell School of Life Sciences, Rochester Institute of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rochester NY, USA<lb/> 14623<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Hauptmann-Woodward Medical Research Institute,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Buffalo NY, USA 14203<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Innovation Center for Biomedical Informatics, Georgetown University Medical Center,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Washington DC, USA 20007<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 School of Mathematical Sciences, Rochester Institute of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rochester NY, USA 14623<lb/></address>

	Contact Information -Gregory A. Babbitt (
	<email>gabsbi@rit.edu</email>

	)<lb/>
	Short title -cancer recurrence and protein dynamics<lb/> 

	Authors&apos; contributions -GAB and EPF designed the statistical method and software. GAB, MLL, MM,<lb/> designed the study and all author&apos;s interpreted the data and wrote the manuscript.

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Oncogenic mutations in the kinase domain of the B-Raf protein have long been associated with cancers<lb/> involving the RAF-MEK-ERK pathway. One constitutive ERK activating mutation in B-Raf, the V600E<lb/> (valine to glutamate) replacement occurring adjacent to a site of threonine phosphorylation (T599)<lb/> occurs in many types of cancer, and in a large percentage of certain cancers, such as melanoma.<lb/> Because natural ATP binding activity and the V600E mutation are both known to alter the physical<lb/> behavior of the activation loop in the ATP binding domain, this system is especially amenable to<lb/> comparative functional analyses using molecular dynamics of drug classes and genetic variants at all-<lb/>atom resolution. Here, we employ machine learning enabled identification of functionally conserved<lb/> protein dynamics to compare how disease pertinent molecular variations impact conserved loop<lb/> dynamics during the binding of four ATP competitive B-Raf inhibitors (sorafenib, vemurafenib,<lb/> dabrafenib, and PLX7904) that differ in their effectiveness in preventing cancer recurrence. We<lb/> demonstrate that drug development targeting B-Raf has progressively moved towards ATP competitive<lb/> inhibitors that demonstrate less tendency to mimic the functional dynamic shifts associated with ATP<lb/> binding in this domain. We argue this functional dynamic mimicry in first generation B-Raf inhibitors<lb/> increases the side effect of hyperactivation (i.e. inducing MAPK activation in non-tumorous cells in the<lb/> absence of secondary mutation). Within the context of the binding interaction of each inhibitor, we<lb/> compare the functional dynamic impacts of V600E and other sensitizing and drug resistance causing<lb/> mutations in the activation and P-loops, confirming sites of low mutational tolerance in these two<lb/> functional regions. Lastly, we investigate V600E sensitivity of B-Raf loop dynamics in an evolutionary<lb/> context, demonstrating that while it probably shares partial origin with its early evolution in primitive<lb/> eukaryotes, the functional sensitivity to V600E was secondarily increased during early jawed vertebrate<lb/> evolution.<lb/></div>

	Author Summary<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Our lab has recently developed a combined simulation-based and machine learning method and user-<lb/>friendly software for identifying dynamic motions in proteins that are preserved over evolutionary time<lb/> scales (i.e. are functionally conserved). Our method also can assess how genetic or chemical variation<lb/> affects these functionally conserved motions. Here, we utilize this approach to computationally<lb/> demonstrate how one of the most common mutations that arise in tumors, the V600E B-Raf protein<lb/> mutation, disrupts the functioning of protein loop dynamics responsible for normal regulation of the<lb/> oncogenic B-Raf protein and its growth signaling pathway. We demonstrate that cancer recurrence in<lb/> the absence of new mutations may be caused by drug interactions impacting these dynamics. We<lb/> propose that mimicry of the functional dynamics of natural chemical activators (i.e. agonists) by many<lb/> cancer targeting drugs may be a potent causal factor in recurrence of cancer in the absence of<lb/> secondary mutation. By combining comparative modeling of molecular dynamics and analyses of<lb/> molecular evolution, we also demonstrate that the unusual sensitivity of B-Raf protein regulatory loop<lb/> dynamics to this mutation has an ancient evolutionary origin.<lb/></div>

	Keywords -
	<keyword>oncogene, mutation, B-Raf, inhibitor, molecular dynamics, molecular evolution,<lb/> machine learning, dynamic mimicry</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
