<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="904136v1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Comparison of de-duplication methods used by WHO Global<lb/> Antimicrobial Resistance Surveillance System (GLASS) and<lb/> Japan Nosocomial Infections Surveillance (JANIS) in the<lb/> surveillance of antimicrobial resistance<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Toshiki Kajihara 1*# , Koji Yahara 1*# , John Stelling 2 , Sergey Romualdovich Eremin 3 ,<lb/> Barbara Tornimbene 3 , Visanu Thamlikitkul 4 , Aki Hirabayashi 1 , Eiko Anzai 1 , Satoyo<lb/> Wakai 1 , Nobuaki Matsunaga 5 , Kayoko Hayakawa 6 , Norio Ohmagari 5 , Motoyuki Sugai 1 ,<lb/> and Keigo Shibayama 1,7<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Antimicrobial Resistance Research Center, National Institute of Infectious Diseases,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Higashimurayama, Tokyo 189-0002, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Brigham and Women&apos;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boston, MA, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 WHO Headquarters,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Geneva<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Division of Infectious Diseases and Tropical Medicine, Department of Medicine,<lb/> Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bangkok, Thailand<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 AMR Clinical Reference Center, National Center for Global Health and Medicine<lb/> Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Toyama, Tokyo 162-8655, Japan 2<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 Disease Control and Prevention Center, National Center for Global Health and<lb/> Medicine Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Toyama, Tokyo 162-8655, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>7 Department of Bacteriology II, National Institute of Infectious Diseases,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Musashimurayama, Tokyo 280-0011, Japan<lb/></address>

	* contributed equally to this article<lb/> #Corresponding authors<lb/> 
	Short title: Comparison of de-duplication methods in the surveillance of AMR<lb/> 

	Abstract <lb/>
	<div type="abstract">A major issue in the surveillance of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is &quot;de-<lb/>duplication&quot; or removal of repeated isolates, for which there exist multiple methods. <lb/>The World Health Organization (WHO) Global Antimicrobial Resistance Surveillance <lb/>System (GLASS) requires de-duplication by selecting only the first isolate of a given <lb/>bacterial species per patient per surveillance period per specimen type per age group, <lb/>gender, and infection origin stratification. However, no study on the comparative <lb/>application of this method has been reported. The objective of this study was to evaluate <lb/>differences in data tabulation between the WHO GLASS and the Japan Nosocomial <lb/>Infections Surveillance (JANIS) system, which counts both patients and isolates after <lb/>removing repeated isolates of the same bacterial species per multiresistance phenotype <lb/>isolated from a patient within 30 days, regardless of specimen type. All bacterial data, <lb/>consisting of approximately 8 million samples from 1795 Japanese hospitals in 2017 <lb/>were exported from the JANIS database, and were tabulated using either the de-<lb/>duplication algorithm of GLASS, or JANIS. We compared the tabulated results of the <lb/>total number of patients whose blood and urine cultures were taken and of the <lb/>percentage of resistant isolates of Escherichia coli for each priority antibiotic. The <lb/>number of patients per specimen type tabulated by the JANIS method was always<lb/> smaller than that of GLASS. There was a small (&lt; 3%) difference in the percentage of<lb/> resistance of E. coli for any antibiotic between the two methods in both out-and<lb/> inpatient settings and blood and urine isolates. The two tabulation methods did not show<lb/> considerable differences in terms of the tabulated percentages of resistance for E. coli.<lb/> We further discuss how the use of GLASS tabulations to create a public software and<lb/> website that could help to facilitate the understanding of and treatment against AMR.<lb/></div>

	(294/300 words)
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
