<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="91DEFC68B3FE7BE75AC647268D8D756CD415870E"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>ECOLOGICAL MANAGEMENT &amp; RESTORATION VOL 5 NO 2 AUGUST 2004 125<lb/></reference>

	<note type="doctype">R E S E A R C H<lb/> R E P O R T<lb/></note>

	<publisher>Blackwell Publishing, Ltd.<lb/></publisher>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Estimating population abundance in plant species<lb/> with dormant life-stages: Fire and the endangered<lb/> plant Grevillea caleyi R. Br.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	By 
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Tony D. Auld and Judith Scott<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Tony Auld and Judith Scott </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	are with the<lb/> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Biodiversity Research Group of the Depart-<lb/>ment of Environment and Conservation<lb/> (NSW),</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>(PO Box 1967, Hurstville, NSW 2220,<lb/> Australia.</address>

	Email:
	<email>tony.auld@npws.nsw.gov.au</email>,<lb/> 
	<email>judy.scott@npws.nsw.gov.au</email>

	). The project is part<lb/> of the research and management arising from<lb/> the implementation of the recovery plan for the<lb/> endangered shrub, Grevillea caleyi.<lb/> 

	Summary
	<div type="abstract">Assessment of the conservation significance of a species at a particular site<lb/> involves estimating the population size. Generally this is based on a single survey. However,<lb/> where plant species vary greatly in abundance in response to disturbance regimes, there will<lb/> be uncertainty associated with the use of single estimates of abundance. The interpretation<lb/> of such estimates is dependent on an understanding of the ecology of the species and the dis-<lb/>turbance regimes that impact on it. We examined the usefulness of abundance estimates in<lb/> the endangered shrub Grevillea caleyi (a fire-sensitive shrub with a persistent soil seed bank )<lb/> from south-eastern Australia, where fire is a major landscape disturbance. Comparisons of<lb/> estimates of abundance before and after fire showed very large changes in the number of<lb/> plants of G. caleyi above ground. Changes in abundance of over two orders of magnitude<lb/> were observed. The longer the site was left unburnt, the greater the magnitude of change in<lb/> abundance after the next fire. Above-ground plants may be rare or absent at sites unburnt for<lb/> over 15 -20 years, but were abundant after fire, due to re-establishment from the soil seed bank.<lb/> Sites burnt by two fires in quick succession showed declines in population abundance, most<lb/> likely due to the soil seed bank not being replenished between such short interval fires.<lb/> Assessments of the conservation significance of remnant sites of G. caleyi and similar species<lb/> based on a single sample of above-ground plant abundance at one time are considered inappro-<lb/>priate. The amount of available habitat for G. caleyi , either as area of occupancy or preferably extent<lb/> of available habitat, was a moderate predictor of the likely magnitude of abundance in the species<lb/> after fire. However, the usefulness of these measures for species whose biology is comparable<lb/> to Grevillea caleyi , will be limited due to factors relating to the degree of species-specific hab-<lb/>itat requirements, local site fire history and the impact of any one fire on resultant post-fire<lb/> germination levels. Any assessment of conservation significance will require the interpreta-<lb/>tion of available information in relation to the ecology of a species.<lb/></div>

	Key words
	<keyword>monitoring, plant ecology, population structure, sampling, soil seed bank, threatened<lb/> species.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
