<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="933DFD2BEDDD1A7B937C0E3A5A696EF3D45FBC93"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>An exact solution for ideal dam-break floods on steep slopes<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>C. Ancey, 1 R. M. Iverson, 2 M. Rentschler, 1 and R. P. Denlinger 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="submission">Received 17 July 2007; revised 23 September 2007; accepted 17 October 2007;</note>

	published
	<date>25 January 2008.<lb/></date>

	[1]
	<div type="abstract">The shallow-water equations are used to model the flow resulting from the sudden<lb/> release of a finite volume of frictionless, incompressible fluid down a uniform slope of<lb/> arbitrary inclination. The hodograph transformation and Riemann&apos;s method make it<lb/> possible to transform the governing equations into a linear system and then deduce an<lb/> exact analytical solution expressed in terms of readily evaluated integrals. Although the<lb/> solution treats an idealized case never strictly realized in nature, it is uniquely well-suited<lb/> for testing the robustness and accuracy of numerical models used to model shallow-water<lb/> flows on steep slopes.<lb/></div>

	Citation:
	<reference>Ancey, C., R. M. Iverson, M. Rentschler, and R. P. Denlinger (2008), An exact solution for ideal dam-break floods on steep<lb/> slopes, Water Resour. Res., 44, W01430, </reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1029/2007WR006353</idno>.<lb/>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 School of Architecture, Civil and Environmental Engineering,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>É cole<lb/> Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Lausanne, Switzerland.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 U.S. Geological Survey, Cascades Volcano Observatory,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Vancouver,<lb/> Washington, USA.<lb/></address>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright 2008 by the American Geophysical Union.<lb/></note>

	0043-1397/08/2007WR006353 W01430<lb/>
	<reference>WATER RESOURCES RESEARCH, VOL. 44, W01430, doi:10.1029/2007WR006353, 2008<lb/></reference>

	<page>1 of 10<lb/></page>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>C. Ancey and M. Rentschler,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>School of Architecture, Civil and<lb/> Environmental Engineering, É cole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1015 Lausanne, Switzerland.</address>

	(
	<email>christophe.ancey@epfl.ch</email>
	)<lb/> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>R. P. Denlinger and R. M. Iverson,</docAuthor>
	</byline> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>U.S. Geological Survey, Cascades<lb/> Volcano Observatory,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Vancouver, WA, USA.</address>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
