<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="9D152B16CF6F54563293A82F27F6E6AC582D45F2"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>NORDINFO (Nordic<lb/> Council for Scientific<lb/> Information): financing<lb/> international<lb/> development without bureaucracy<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sigru Â n Klara Hannesdo Âttir<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	The author<lb/> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sigru Â n Klara Hannesdo Â ttir</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	is Director of 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>NORDINFO, The<lb/> Nordic Council of Scientific Information.</affiliation>
	</byline>

	She is Professor of<lb/> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Library and Information Studies at the University of Iceland<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	and on leave to hold this director&apos;s position. 

	Keywords<lb/>
	<keyword>Libraries, Research organizations, Co-operation,<lb/> Co-operative organization, Financing</keyword>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">NORDINFO (The Nordic Council for Scientific Information) was<lb/> founded in 1977 after a long tradition of Nordic cooperation<lb/> within the research library field. The Council is responsible for<lb/> coordinating Nordic cooperative initiatives that can facilitate<lb/> access to scientific information. Prior to that, Nordic countries<lb/> developed a variety of cooperative forms: political, economic,<lb/> cultural and scientific. During its 20 years of operation,<lb/> NORDINFO has financed many experimental projects and<lb/> financially supported many conferences, seminars and smaller<lb/> projects with the general aim that these projects should have<lb/> benefit beyond each individual country. Projects included an<lb/> interface, which was to serve as a tool to search databases in<lb/> different countries and structured in different languages.<lb/> NORDINFO also financed Centres of Excellence where Nordic<lb/> expertise could be developed. NORDINFO operates on a<lb/> budget provided by the Nordic Council of Ministers and is<lb/> given a three-year contract based on strategy which must be<lb/> accepted by the board, consisting of one member from each<lb/> of the five countries that finance Nordic cooperation.<lb/></div>

	Electronic access<lb/> The current issue and full text archive of this journal is<lb/> available at
	http://www.emerald-library.com

	<page>134<lb/></page>

	<reference>The Bottom Line: Managing Library Finances<lb/> Volume 13 . Number 3 . 2000 . pp. 134±141<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright"># MCB University Press</note> . 

	<idno>ISSN 0888-045X</idno>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
