<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="A574898911CD66D29295BB04E3C5DD25B6B4F6F8"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Selective Thrombolysis of Central<lb/> Retinal Artery Occlusion Without<lb/> Long-term Systemic Heparinization<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>William J. Wirostko, M.D.,* Jose S. Pulido, M.D.,* and Lloyd E. Hendrix, M.D. †<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>*The Eye Institute, Medical College of Wisconsin,</affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>Milwaukee, Wisconsin </address>

	and 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>†Department<lb/> of Radiology, Medical College of Wisconsin,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Milwaukee, Wisconsin<lb/></address>

	<reference>Wirostko WJ, Pulido JS, Hendrix LE. Selective thrombolysis of<lb/> central retinal artery occlusion without long-term systemic he-<lb/>parinization. Surg Neurol 1998;50:408 -10.</reference>

	<div type="abstract">BACKGROUND<lb/> A central retinal artery occlusion is a potentially blinding<lb/> retinal vascular event with no effective treatment regimen<lb/> available. Recently, a few reports have described im-<lb/>proved vision in eyes with central retinal artery occlu-<lb/>sions after selective fibrinolytic therapy followed by long-<lb/>term systemic anticoagulation. Acceptance of this<lb/> treatment, however, has been hampered by a paucity of<lb/> confirmatory reports and its potential for producing se-<lb/>rious hemorrhagic complications. Our report indepen-<lb/>dently confirms the beneficial effects of selective throm-<lb/>bolysis, even with the use of only short-term, post-<lb/>procedure systemic heparinization. METHODS<lb/> A case report of selective fibrinolysis of an occluded<lb/> central retinal artery using urokinase infusion into the<lb/> ophthalmic artery followed with only 12 h of systemic<lb/> heparinization is described. RESULTS<lb/> A 65-year-old man presenting with a central retinal artery<lb/> occlusion of less than 4-h duration enjoyed an improve-<lb/>ment of vision from counting-fingers acuity to 20/20 after<lb/> selective fibrinolysis with urokinase and only 12 h of<lb/> systemic heparinization. No hemorrhagic or thrombotic<lb/> complications occurred. CONCLUSIONS<lb/> Selective thrombolysis with urokinase followed by short-<lb/>term systemic heparinization can effectively treat a cen-<lb/>tral retinal artery occlusion. Whereas the authors ac-<lb/>knowledge that a single case does not prove that short-<lb/>term heparinization is better than long-term<lb/> heparinization, it does show that the latter is not always<lb/> required.</div>

	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by Elsevier Science Inc.<lb/></note>

	KEY WORDS<lb/>
	<keyword>Central retinal artery occlusion, selective fibrinolysis,<lb/> urokinase.<lb/></keyword>

	Address reprint requests to:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dr. William J. Wirostko,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>The Eye Institute,<lb/> Medical College of Wisconsin,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>925 N. 87th St., Milwaukee, WI 53226-4812.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received January 27, 1997; accepted May 5, 1997.<lb/></note>

	0090-3019/98/$19.00<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by Elsevier Science Inc.<lb/></note>

	<idno>PII S0090-3019(97)00338-8<lb/></idno>

	655 Avenue of the Americas, New York, NY 10010
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
