<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="A9A14530D8197E92365AEE517F1DC210E68F9007"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	Information in practice<lb/> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Effect of electronic health records in ambulatory care: retrospective,<lb/> serial, cross sectional study<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Terhilda Garrido, Laura Jamieson, Yvonne Zhou, Andrew Wiesenthal, Louise Liang</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Objective To evaluate the effect of implementing<lb/> comprehensive, integrated electronic health record systems on<lb/> use and quality of ambulatory care<lb/> Design Retrospective, serial, cross sectional study.<lb/> Setting Colorado and Northwest regions of Kaiser Permanente,<lb/> a US integrated healthcare delivery system.<lb/> Population 367 795 members in the Colorado region and<lb/> 449 728 members in the Northwest region.<lb/> Intervention Implementation of electronic health record<lb/> systems.<lb/> Main outcome measures Total number of office visits and use<lb/> of primary care, specialty care, clinical laboratory, radiology<lb/> services, and telephone contact. Health Plan Employer Data<lb/> and Information Set to assess quality.<lb/> Results Two years after electronic health records were fully<lb/> implemented, age adjusted rates of office visits fell by 9% in<lb/> both regions. Age adjusted primary care visits decreased by<lb/> 11% in both regions and specialty care visits decreased by 5% in<lb/> Colorado and 6% in the Northwest. All these decreases were<lb/> significant (P &lt; 0.0001). The percentage of members making<lb/> ≥ 3 visits a year decreased by 10% in Colorado and 11% in the<lb/> Northwest, and the percentage of members with ≤ 2 visits a<lb/> year increased. In the Northwest, scheduled telephone contact<lb/> increased from a baseline of 1.26 per member per year to 2.09<lb/> after two years. Use of clinical laboratory and radiology services<lb/> did not change conclusively. Intermediate measures of quality<lb/> of health care remained unchanged or improved slightly.<lb/> Conclusions Readily available, comprehensive, integrated<lb/> clinical information reduced use of ambulatory care while<lb/> maintaining quality and allowed doctors to replace some office<lb/> visits with telephone contacts. Shifting patterns of use suggest<lb/> reduced numbers of ambulatory care visits that are<lb/> inappropriate or marginally productive.<lb/></div>

	<page>page 1 of 5<lb/></page>

	<reference>BMJ VOLUME 330 5 MARCH 2005 bmj.com<lb/></reference>

	(<note type="submission">Accepted 31 January 2005</note>)<lb/>

	<reference>bmj.com 2005;330:581<lb/> </reference>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Clinical Systems Planning and Consulting, Kaiser Permanente, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2101 Webster<lb/> Street, Oakland, CA 94612, USA<lb/> </address>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Terhilda Garrido</docAuthor>
	</byline> 
	senior director<lb/> 
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Laura Jamieson</docAuthor>
	</byline> 
	senior business consultant<lb/> 
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Yvonne Zhou</docAuthor>
	</byline> 
	project manager<lb/> 
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Andrew Wiesenthal</docAuthor>
	</byline> 
	associate executive director, Permanente Federation<lb/> 
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Louise Liang</docAuthor>
	</byline> 
	senior vice president for quality and clinical systems support, 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Kaiser<lb/> Foundation Health Plan<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	Correspondence to: T Garrido
	<email>terhilda.garrido@kp.org</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
