<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="AB6AECD1EEF07CBB1D50E2C1011FB2E248E62362"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	Medicolegal Issues<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Vascular and Visceral Injuries<lb/> Associated with Lumbar Disc<lb/> Surgery: Medicolegal Implications<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Robert Goodkin, M.D., and Lewis L. Laska, Ph.D., J.D.*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Neurological Surgery, University of Washington School of Medicine and<lb/> VA Puget Sound Health Care System, </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>Seattle, Washington</address> 

	and 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>*College of Business,<lb/> Tennessee State University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nashville, Tennessee<lb/></address>

	<reference>Goodkin R, Laska LL. Vascular and visceral injuries associated<lb/> with lumbar disc surgery: medicolegal implications. Surg Neurol<lb/> 1998;49:358 -72.<lb/></reference>

	<div type="abstract">Symptomatic perforation of the anterior annulus fibro-<lb/>sus/anterior longitudinal ligament during surgery for her-<lb/>niated lumbar disc disease is one of the more solemn and<lb/> sobering complications experienced by neurosurgeons<lb/> or orthopedic surgeons. This complication frequently re-<lb/>sults in the death of the patient. Its occurrence is prob-<lb/>ably more common than the medical community would<lb/> expect. The authors report 21 cases since 1985 in which<lb/> an injury to an intra-abdominal vessel or viscera oc-<lb/>curred. In all cases litigation resulted and a settlement or<lb/> verdict was rendered. A review of the literature is pre-<lb/>sented and the medicolegal implications of symptomatic<lb/> ventral perforations of the annulus fibrosus/anterior lon-<lb/>gitudinal ligament are discussed.</div>

	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by Elsevier<lb/> Science Inc.<lb/></note>

	KEY WORDS<lb/>
	<keyword>Lumbar disc surgery, ventral perforation, vascular/visceral<lb/> injury, medicolegal implications.<lb/></keyword>

	Address reprint requests to:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Robert Goodkin, M.D.,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Neu-<lb/>rological Surgery, University of Washington School of Medicine and VA<lb/> Puget Sound Health Care System,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Box 356470, Seattle, WA 98195.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received December 24, 1996; accepted June 25, 1997.<lb/></note>

	0090-3019/98/$19.00<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by Elsevier Science Inc.<lb/></note>

	<idno>PII S0090-3019(97)00372-8<lb/></idno>

	655 Avenue of the Americas, New York, NY 10010<lb/> Summary of Medicolegal Cases (continued)<lb/> NO. SEX AGE DIAGNOSIS<lb/> OPERATION<lb/> COMPLICATION<lb/> RECOGNIZED<lb/> REPAIR<lb/> OUTCOME<lb/> COMPLAINT<lb/> VERDICT SPECIALTY<lb/> ?<lb/> 54 ?<lb/> Hemilaminectomy<lb/> &amp; discectomy<lb/> L3/4<lb/> Goodkin and Laska<lb/> 1998;49:358 -72
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
