<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="AF734F166732AF7BAB20C0DCF450A81D1F8F2A04"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Age-Related Correlation Between Antioxidant<lb/> Enzymes and DNA Damage With Smoking and<lb/> Body Mass Index<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Parvathi Kumara Reddy Thavanati, 1 Kodanda Reddy Kanala, 2 Aurora Escoto de Dios, 3<lb/> and Jose Maria Cantu Garza 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Instituto de Genética, Departamento de Biología Molecular y Genomica,<lb/> Centro Universitario de Ciencias de la Salud, Universidad de Guadalajara,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Guadalajara, México.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Anthropology, School of Biological &amp; Earth Sciences, Sri Venkateswara University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tirupati, India.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> Instituto de Biología Molecular en Medicina, Departamento de Biología Molecular y Genomica,<lb/> Centro Universitario de Ciencias de la Salud, Universidad de Guadalajara,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Guadalajara, México.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">To understand whether oxidants contribute to the initiation and/or promulgation toward aging,<lb/> the present study has been undertaken on 220 healthy male volunteers aged 20-80 years selected<lb/> from the defined electoral area (suburbs of Tirupati, Andhra Pradesh, India) to evaluate the<lb/> concentrations of free radicals (superoxide anion, hydrogen peroxide), lymphocyte antioxidant<lb/> enzymes (glutathione S-transferase, superoxide dismutase, catalase), and DNA damage in relation<lb/> to obesity and smoking (lifestyles). A two fold increase of lymphocyte free radical generation<lb/> (DNA damage) was observed in older age groups with a reduced antioxidant potential, forming<lb/> a link between cigarette smoking and oxidative stress represented by an antioxidant imbalance.<lb/> Body mass index had a positive relationship with oxidative stress, but antioxidant levels did not<lb/> vary with body mass index. The findings conclude that free radical-mediated oxidative stress<lb/> and DNA damage accelerate with lifestyle variations under reduced antioxidant potential.<lb/></div>

	Key Words:
	<keyword>Aging-Antioxidants-DNA damage-Smoking-Obesity.</keyword>

	<page>360<lb/></page>

	<title level="j">Journal of Gerontology: BIOLOGICAL SCIENCES<lb/></title>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright 2008 by The Gerontological Society of America<lb/> </note>

	<reference>2008, Vol. 63A, No. 4, 360-364</reference>

	CORRESPONDENCE<lb/> Address correspondence to
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Parvathi Kumara Reddy Thavanati, PhD,<lb/>DSc, </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Instituto de Genética, Departamento de Biología Molecular y<lb/> Genomica, Centro Universitario de Ciencias de la Salud, Universidad<lb/> de Guadalajara,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sierra Mojada 950, Puerta 7, Edificio P, Nivel II, Col.<lb/> Independencia, Guadalajara. Jalisco. Código Postal: 44340. México.<lb/></address>

	E-mail:
	<email>tpkreddy@yahoo.com</email>; <email>reddy.parvathi@mail.cucs.udg.mx</email><lb/>

	<note type="submission">Received July 11, 2007<lb/> Accepted October 24, 2007<lb/></note>

	Decision Editor:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Huber R. Warner, PhD</docAuthor>
	</byline>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
