<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="Amilhat_Parinas"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Anne-Laure AMILHAT SZARY<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institut de Géographie Alpine / Laboratoire PACTE-TERRITOIRES UMR5194<lb/> Université Joseph Fourier<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>14 bis avenue Marie Reynoard, 38100 Grenoble, France<lb/></address>

	<email>anne-laure.amilhat@ujf-grenoble.fr<lb/></email>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The impact of growing trans-mountain mobilities : first conclusions of a<lb/> comparative Alpine / Andean research</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Traffic flows have little in common in the Western Alps and the tropical Central Andes,<lb/> However the rhythm of circulation increase, the stress produced by the recent construction of<lb/> new infrastructures (accelerated in the Andes since the 1990&apos;s), the growing concentration of<lb/> traffic justify bringing together such different worlds in a parallel analysis. Mobilities are here<lb/> considered as much more than a moving capacity. They are defined as a social relation to<lb/> movement: transportation therefore appears as only one aspect of mobility analysis. A special<lb/> emphasis is put on the link between mobilities and mountains because of a complex relation<lb/> between the existence of an old interaction (mountains are mobile worlds) and new mobility<lb/> patterns derived from the growing importance of transit traffic. Through this interaction, we<lb/> question societies&apos; adaptations to the globalised world and the sustainibility of their choices.<lb/> The paper first settles on the recent changes of mobility patterns in mountain areas, insisting<lb/> on the context of these evolutions (i.e. the opening of borders in an exchange economy<lb/> favourable to the growth of international freight traffic). After reviewing the adaptation of the<lb/> transport infrastructures offer in terms, it considers the traffic regulation frame in both the<lb/> Andean and the Alpine contexts. This crossed analysis allows us to offer an interpretation of<lb/> the mountain populations&apos; self-consciousness as perceived through the adaptation of their<lb/> mobility patterns. By evidencing their vulnerability, we also illustrate the difficulties in the<lb/> implementation of sustainable principles in contexts where they have not been re-<lb/>appropriated.<lb/></div>

	KEY WORDS : 
	<keywords>transportation / connection / regulation / identity / sustainability</keywords>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
