<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ana0064-0199"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199–211<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1111/j.1365-2044.2008.05733.x<lb/></idno>

	<note type="other">.....................................................................................................................................................................................................................<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">G U I D E L I N E S<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Suspected Anaphylactic Reactions Associated with<lb/> Anaesthesia<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<note type="other">Membership of the Working Party:</note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>N J N Harper, Chairman; T Dixon; P Dugué; D M Edgar;<lb/>A Fay; H C Gooi; R Herriot; P Hopkins; J M Hunter; R Mirakian; R S H Pumphrey;<lb/> S L Seneviratne; A F Walls; P Williams; J A Wildsmith; P Wood. Ex Officio: A S Nasser<lb/> 1<lb/> ,<lb/> R K Powell<lb/> 1 , R Mirakhur<lb/> 2 , J Soar<lb/> 3 , Executive Officers, AAGBI<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 British Society for Allergy and Clinical Immunology<lb/> 2 Royal College of Anaesthetists<lb/> 3 Resuscitation Council UK<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">This is a consensus document produced by expert members of a Working Party established by the Association of<lb/> Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland (AAGBI). It updates and replaces previous guidance published in<lb/> 2003.<lb/> Summary<lb/> (1) The AAGBI has published guidance on manage-<lb/>ment of anaphylaxis during anaesthesia in 1990,<lb/> 1995 and 2003. This 2008 update was necessary to<lb/> disseminate new information.<lb/> (2) Death or permanent disability from anaphylaxis in<lb/> anaesthesia may be avoidable if the reaction is<lb/> recognised early and managed optimally.<lb/> (3) Recognition of anaphylaxis during anaesthesia is<lb/> usually delayed because key features such as hypo-<lb/>tension and bronchospasm more commonly have a<lb/> different cause.<lb/> (4) Initial management of anaphylaxis should follow the<lb/> ABC approach. Adrenaline (epinephrine) is the<lb/> most effective drug in anaphylaxis and should be<lb/> given as early as possible.<lb/> (5) If anaphylaxis is suspected during anaesthesia, it is<lb/> the anaesthetist&apos;s responsibility to ensure the patient<lb/> is referred for investigation.<lb/> (6) Serum mast cell tryptase levels may help the<lb/> retrospective diagnosis of anaphylaxis: appropriate<lb/> blood samples should be sent for analysis.<lb/> (7) Specialist (allergist) knowledge is needed to inter-<lb/>pret investigations for anaesthetic anaphylaxis,<lb/> including sensitivity and specificity of each test<lb/> used. Specialist (anaesthetist) knowledge is needed<lb/> to recognise possible non-allergic causes for the<lb/> &apos;reaction&apos;. Optimal investigation of suspected reac-<lb/>tions is therefore more likely with the collaboration<lb/> of both specialties.<lb/> (8) Details of specialist centres for the investigation of<lb/> suspected anaphylaxis during anaesthesia may be<lb/> found on the AAGBI website http://www.aagbi.<lb/> org.<lb/> (9) Cases of anaphylaxis occurring during anaesthesia<lb/> should be reported to the Medicines Control<lb/> Agency and the AAGBI National Anaesthetic<lb/> Anaphylaxis Database. Reports are more valuable<lb/> if the diagnosis is recorded following specialist<lb/> investigation of the reaction.<lb/> (10) This guidance recommends that all Departments<lb/> of Anaesthesia should identify a Consultant Anaes-<lb/>thetist who is Clinical Lead for anaesthetic<lb/> anaphylaxis.<lb/></div> 
	
	<note type="copyright">Re-use of this article is permitted in accordance with the Creative<lb/> Commons Deed, Attribution 2.5, which does not permit commercial<lb/> exploitation.<lb/> Ó 2008 The Authors<lb/> Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland<lb/> </note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
