<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="APL0774202-CC"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<idno>arXiv:cond-mat/0007013v1 [cond-mat.supr-con]</idno>

	<date>2 Jul 2000<lb/></date>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Measurements of the absolute value of the penetration depth in high-T c<lb/> superconductors using a tunnel diode resonator<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>R. Prozorov, 1 R. W. Giannetta, 1 A. Carrington, 2 P. Fournier, 3<lb/> R. L. Greene, 3 P. Guptasarma, 4 D.G. Hinks, 4 and A. R. Banks 5<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Loomis Laboratory of Physics, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1110 West Green St., Urbana, 61801 Illinois.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Leeds,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Leeds LS2 9JT, United Kingdom<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Center for Superconductivity Research, Department of Physics,<lb/> University of Maryland,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>College Park, Maryland 20742<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Chemistry and Materials Science Division, Argonne National Laboratory,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Argonne, Illinois 60439<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Materials Research Laboratory, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>104 South Goodwin Ave, Urbana, 61801 Illinois.<lb/></address>

	(Dated:
	<note type="submission">Submitted to Applied. Phys. Lett. June 30, 2000</note>

	)<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">A method is presented to measure the absolute value of the London penetration depth, λ, from<lb/> the frequency shift of a resonator. The technique involves coating a high-Tc superconductor (HTSC)<lb/> with film of low -Tc material of known thickness and penetration depth. The method is applied<lb/> to measure London penetration depth in YBa2Cu3O 7−δ (YBCO) Bi2Sr2CaCu2O 8+δ (BSCCO) and<lb/> Pr1.85Ce0.15CuO 4−δ (PCCO). For YBCO and BSCCO, the values of λ(0) are in agreement with the<lb/> literature values. For PCCO λ ≈ 2790Å, reported for the first time.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
