<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="B4F5BC21A707678D9118EBF6C669B5B0EC312706"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Does Neurotensin Mediate the Effects<lb/> of Antipsychotic Drugs?<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Becky Kinkead, Elisabeth B. Binder, and Charles B. Nemeroff<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">The possibility that the neuropeptide neurotensin (NT)<lb/> may function as an endogenous antipsychotic compound<lb/> was first hypothesized almost two decades ago. Since that<lb/> time, considerable effort has been directed towards deter-<lb/>mining whether NT neurons mediate the effects of antipsy-<lb/>chotic drugs (APDs). The anatomic, biochemical, behav-<lb/>ioral, and clinical relevance of this hypothesis is reviewed.<lb/> Although the majority of the available evidence is indirect,<lb/> the availability of several NT receptor (NTR) antagonists<lb/> have now made possible the direct examination of the<lb/> involvement of the NT system in the mechanism of action<lb/> of APDs. Preliminary studies in our laboratory demon-<lb/>strate the ability of a selective NTR antagonist to block the<lb/> effects of APDs in two models of sensory motor gating<lb/> deficits characteristic of schizophrenia. These data, taken<lb/> together with a compelling series of studies demonstrating<lb/> that increases of NT/neuromedin N mRNA expression and<lb/> NT content in the nucleus accumbens and striatum after<lb/> chronic administration of APDs are predictive of clinical<lb/> efficacy and extrapyramidal side effects, respectively,<lb/> provide direct preclinical evidence for a role of the NT<lb/> system in the clinical efficacy of APDs. Although effects of<lb/> selective NTR antagonists in normal volunteers or schizo-<lb/>phrenic patients have not been studied, and nonpeptider-<lb/>gic NTR agonists have not yet been identified, these<lb/> cumulative results provide the groundwork for the use of<lb/> NT-ergic compounds in the treatment of schizophrenia.<lb/></div>

	<reference>Biol Psychiatry 1999;46:340 -351 © 1999 Society of Bi-<lb/>ological Psychiatry<lb/></reference>

	Key Words:
	<keyword>Schizophrenia, clinical efficacy, extrapyra-<lb/>midal side effect<lb/></keyword>

	From the
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Laboratory of Neuropsychopharmacology, Department of Psychiatry and<lb/> Behavioral Sciences, Emory University School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Atlanta, GA.<lb/></address>

	Address reprint requests to
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Charles B. Nemeroff, MD, Ph.D.,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of<lb/> Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Emory University School of Medicine,<lb/> Woodruff Memorial Research Building,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1639 Pierce Drive, Suite 4000,<lb/> Atlanta, GA 30322.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received December 7, 1998; revised March 9, 1999; accepted March 10, 1999.<lb/></note>

	<note type="copyright">© 1999 Society of Biological Psychiatry<lb/></note>

	0006-3223/99/$20.00<lb/>
	<idno>PII S0006-3223(99)00070-0</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
