<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="BC186CCD726BBB050988EB5659EBD9D117A53FF4"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Cavernous Angiomas of the<lb/> Cauda Equina: Case Report and<lb/> Review of the Literature<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Bryan J. Duke, M.D., A. Stewart Levy, M.D., and Kevin O. Lillehei, M.D.<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Division of Neurosurgery, University of Colorado Health Sciences Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Denver, Colorado<lb/></address>

	<reference>Duke BJ, Levy AS, Lillehei KO. Cavernous angiomas of the cauda<lb/> equina: case report and review of the literature. Surg Neurol<lb/> 1998;50:442-5.</reference>

	<div type="abstract">BACKGROUND<lb/> Cavernous hemangiomas of the spine and spinal cord are<lb/> relatively uncommon lesions that are being discovered<lb/> more frequently because of the increased use of magnetic<lb/> resonance imaging (MRI). We present a rare case of a<lb/> symptomatic cavernous hemangioma of the cauda equina.<lb/> CASE DESCRIPTION<lb/> A 49-year-old woman presented to our institution with the<lb/> chief complaint of low back pain of acute onset. On phys-<lb/>ical examination the patient was found to be tender to<lb/> percussion over the lumbar spine, had tenderness over<lb/> the sciatic nerve, loss of pinprick sensation over the right<lb/> lateral foot and loss of the Achilles&apos; reflex on the right. In<lb/> addition, she was found to have a large postvoid urinary<lb/> bladder residual volume. MRI revealed a 20 mm ϫ 11 mm<lb/> nonenhancing, heterogenous mass obliterating the spinal<lb/> canal at the L4 level. At operation, this lesion was found<lb/> to be adherent to the nerve roots and was completely<lb/> resected. Pathology revealed this lesion to be a cavern-<lb/>ous angioma of the cauda equina. A review of the perti-<lb/>nent literature is presented. CONCLUSIONS<lb/> Cavernous hemangiomas of the cauda equina are ex-<lb/>tremely rare lesions that may present as low back pain,<lb/> neurologic deficit, or as subarachnoid hemorrhage. They<lb/> can be successfully treated with surgical excision.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by Elsevier Science Inc.<lb/></note>

	KEY WORDS<lb/>
	<keyword>Cavernous angioma, cauda equina, cavernoma.<lb/></keyword>

	Address reprint requests to:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dr. Kevin O. Lillehei,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Colo-<lb/>rado Health Sciences Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>4200 E. Ninth Avenue, Box C307, Denver, CO<lb/> 80262.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received December 13, 1996; accepted June 4, 1997.<lb/></note>

	0090-3019/98/$19.00<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by Elsevier Science Inc.<lb/></note>

	<idno>PII S0090-3019(97)00354-6<lb/></idno>

	655 Avenue of the Americas, New York, NY 10010
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
