<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="Biometrics_2006_62_3_PCouteron"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<title level="j">Biometrics<lb/></title>
	<idno>DOI: 10.1111/j.1541-0420.2005.00497.x<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Orthonormal Transform to Decompose the Variance<lb/> of a Life-History Trait Across a Phylogenetic Tree<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>S. Ollier, 1, * P. Couteron, 2 and D. Chessel 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 UMR CNRS 5558, Laboratoire de Biométrie et Biologie Evolutive,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1,<lb/> 69 622 Villeurbanne Cedex, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 ENGREF/UMR AMAP,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Boulevard de la Lironde, TA40/PS2, 34 398 Montpellier Cedex 05, France<lb/></address>

	* email:
	<email>ollier@biomserv.univ-lyon1.fr<lb/></email>

	Summary.
	<div type="abstract">In recent years, there has been an increased interest in studying the variability of a quantitative<lb/> life history trait across a set of species sharing a common phylogeny. However, such studies have suffered<lb/> from an insufficient development of statistical methods aimed at decomposing the trait variance with respect<lb/> to the topological structure of the tree. Here we propose, a new and generic approach that expresses the<lb/> topological properties of the phylogenetic tree via an orthonormal basis, which is further used to decompose<lb/> the trait variance. Such a decomposition provides a structure function, referred to as &quot;orthogram,&quot; which<lb/> is relevant to characterize in both graphical and statistical aspects the dependence of trait values on the<lb/> topology of the tree (&quot;phylogenetic dependence&quot;). We also propose four complementary test statistics to be<lb/> computed from orthogram values that help to diagnose both the intensity and the nature of phylogenetic<lb/> dependence. The relevance of the method is illustrated by the analysis of three phylogenetic data sets, drawn<lb/> from the literature and typifying contrasted levels and aspects of phylogenetic dependence. Freely available<lb/> routines which have been programmed in the R framework are also proposed.<lb/></div>

	Key words:
	<keyword>Life history trait; Orthogram; Orthonormal transform; Phylogenetic tree; Variance decompo-<lb/>sition.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
