<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="Bouvet_12129"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Influence of internally dropped-off plies on the impact damage<lb/> of asymmetrically tapered laminated CFRP<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Hakim Abdulhamid a,b,⇑ , Christophe Bouvet a , Laurent Michel a , Jacky Aboissière b , Clément Minot b<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Université de Toulouse; INSA, UPS, Mines ALBI, ISAE; ICA (Institut Clément Ader), ISAE (Institut Supérieur de l&apos;Aéronautique et de l&apos;Espace),</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>10, avenue Edouard Belin,<lb/> BP 54032-31055 Toulouse Cedex 4, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Sogeti High Tech, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Avenue Escadrille Normandie Niemen, Parc du Millénaire, 31703 Blagnac, France<lb/></address>

	a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/> 

	Keywords:<lb/> 
	<keywords>A. Carbon fibre<lb/> B. Impact behaviour<lb/> C. Damage mechanics<lb/> Ply drop-off<lb/> </keywords>

	a b s t r a c t<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">This paper presents an experimental study of low velocity impact response of carbon/epoxy asymmetri-<lb/>cally tapered laminates. The tests are realised at energy between 10 and 30 J on two types of layup with<lb/> multiple terminated plies. The type and localisation of damage are analysed using C-scan and<lb/> micrographs. Then, the data is compared with the response of corresponding respective plain laminate.<lb/> The effects of some tapering parameters (taper angle, drop-off disposition and configuration) on the<lb/> impact damage mechanisms are also investigated. Very similar impact damage phenomena are found<lb/> between tapered and plain laminates. The presence of material discontinuity due to the resin pocket<lb/> affects less the damage mechanism than the structural difference between the thick and the thin sections.<lb/></div>

	⇑ Corresponding author at:
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Université de Toulouse; INSA, UPS, Mines ALBI, ISAE;<lb/> ICA (Institut Clément Ader), ISAE (Institut Supérieur de l&apos;Aéronautique et de<lb/> l&apos;Espace),</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>10, Avenue Edouard Belin, BP 54032-31055 Toulouse Cedex 4, France.<lb/></address>

	E-mail address:
	<email>hakim.abdulhamid@isae.fr</email>

	(H. Abdulhamid).
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
