<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="C02-1051"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Automatic Linguistic Analysis for Language Teachers:<lb/> The Case of Zeros<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>MITSUKO YAMURA-TAKEI<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Graduate School of Information Sciences<lb/> Hiroshima City University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>3-4-1 Ozuka-higashi, Asaminami-ku,<lb/> Hiroshima, JAPAN 731-3194<lb/></address>

	<email>yamuram@nlp.its.hiroshima-cu.ac.jp<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>MIHO FUJIWARA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Japanese and Chinese<lb/> Willamette University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>900 State Street, Salem,<lb/> OR. USA 97301<lb/></address>

	<email>mfujiwar@willamette.edu<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>MAKOTO YOSHIE<lb/> Graduate School of Information Sciences<lb/> Hiroshima City University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>yoshie@nlp.its.hiroshima-cu.ac.jp<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>TERUAKI AIZAWA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Faculty of Information Sciences<lb/> Hiroshima City University<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>aizawa@its.hiroshima-cu.ac.jp</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">This paper presents the Natural Language<lb/> Processing-based linguistic analysis tool that<lb/> we have developed for Japanese as a Second<lb/> Language teachers. This program, Zero De-<lb/>tector (ZD), aims to promote effective instruc-<lb/>tion of zero anaphora, on the basis of a hy-<lb/>pothesis about ideal conditions for second<lb/> language acquisition, by making invisible<lb/> zeros visible. ZD takes Japanese written<lb/> narrative discourse as input and provides the<lb/> zero-specified texts and their underlying<lb/> structures as output. We evaluated ZD&apos;s<lb/> performance in terms of its zero detecting<lb/> accuracy. We also present an experimental<lb/> report of its validity for practical use. As a<lb/> result, ZD has proven to be pedagogically<lb/> feasible in terms of its accuracy and its impact<lb/> on effective instruction.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
