<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="C12-1005"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Proceedings of COLING 2012: Technical Papers, pages 67-82,<lb/> COLING 2012, Mumbai, December 2012.<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Experiments with Term Translation<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>M ihael ARCAN 1 Chr ist ian F E DERM AN N 2 Paul BU I T E LAAR 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>(1) Unit for Natural Language Processing, Digital Enterprise Research Institute<lb/> National University of Ireland Galway<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Galway, Ireland<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>(2) Language Technology Lab, German Research Center for AI<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Saarbrücken, Germany<lb/></address>

	<email>mihael.arcan@deri.org</email>, <email>paul.buitelaer@deri.org</email>,<lb/> <email>cfedermann@dfki.de</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">In this article we investigate the translation of financial terms from English into German in the<lb/> isolation of an ontology vocabulary. For this study we automatically built new domain-specific<lb/> resources from the translation search engine Linguee and from the online encyclopaedia Wikipedia.<lb/> Due to the fact that we performed the translation approach on a monolingual ontology, we ran<lb/> several sub-experiments to find the most appropriate model to translate the financial vocabulary.<lb/> The findings from these experiments lead to the conclusion that a hybrid translation system, a<lb/> combination of bilingual terminological resources and statistical machine translation, can help<lb/> to improve translation of domain-specific terms. Finally we undertook a manual cross-lingual<lb/> evaluation on the monolingual ontology to get a better understanding on this specific short text<lb/> translation task.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>Ontologies and terminology, Empirical machine translation.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
