<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="c6ra16486b"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Magnetic properties and giant reversible<lb/> magnetocaloric effect in GdCoC 2<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Lingjian Meng, ab Chi Xu, c Ye Yuan, c Yang Qi, b Shengqiang Zhou c and Lingwei Li * ab<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">The crystal structure, magnetic properties and magnetocaloric effect (MCE) of GdCoC 2 have been studied.<lb/> The compound crystallizes in an orthorhombic CeNiC 2 -type structure which belongs to the Amm2 space<lb/> group. A giant reversible MCE is observed in GdCoC 2 accompanied by a second-order paramagnetic to<lb/> ferromagnetic (PM-FM) phase transition around the Curie temperature $15 K. For the magnetic field<lb/> change of 0-5 T, the maximum values of the magnetic entropy change (ÀDS max<lb/> M ), relative cooling power<lb/> (RCP), and refrigerant capacity (RC) are 28.4 J kg À1 K À1 , 566 J kg À1 and 369 J kg À1 , respectively. The<lb/> present results indicate that GdCoC 2 is a promising candidate for low temperature magnetic refrigeration.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Key Laboratory of Electromagnetic Processing of Materials (Ministry of Education),<lb/> Northeastern University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Shenyang 110819, China.</address>

	E-mail:
	<email>lingwei@epm.neu.edu.cn<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Institute of Materials Physics and Chemistry, School of Materials Science and<lb/> Engineering, Northeastern University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Shenyang 110819, China<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c Helmholtz-Zentrum Dresden-Rossendorf, Institute of Ion Beam Physics and Materials<lb/> Research,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bautzner Landstrasse 400, 01328 Dresden, Germany<lb/></address>

	Cite this:
	<reference>RSC Adv., 2016, 6, 74765<lb/></reference>

	<note type="submission">Received 26th June 2016<lb/> Accepted 3rd August 2016<lb/></note>

	<idno>DOI: 10.1039/c6ra16486b<lb/></idno>

	www.rsc.org/advances<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">This journal is © The Royal Society of Chemistry 2016<lb/></note>

	<reference>RSC Adv., 2016, 6, 74765-74768</reference>
	| 
	<page>74765<lb/></page>

	<note type="doctype">RSC Advances PAPER<lb/> Open Access Article.</note>

	Published on
	<date>03 August 2016</date>

	Downloaded on 10/15/2020 4:13:18 AM.<lb/>

	<note type="copyright">This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported Licence.<lb/></note>

	View Article Online<lb/> View Journal | View Issue
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
