<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="Chirouze_HESS2014gilles"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165-1188, 2014<lb/> www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi:10.5194/hess-18-1165-2014<lb/></idno>

	<note type="copyright">© Author(s) 2014. CC Attribution 3.0 License.<lb/> Hydrology and<lb/> Earth System Sciences<lb/></note>

	<note type="doctype">Open Access<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance<lb/> methods to retrieve surface evapotranspiration and water stress<lb/> of irrigated fields in semi-arid climate<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>J. Chirouze 1 , G. Boulet 1 , L. Jarlan 1 , R. Fieuzal 1 , J. C. Rodriguez 2 , J. Ezzahar 3 , S. Er-Raki 4 , G. Bigeard 1 , O. Merlin 1 ,<lb/> J. Garatuza-Payan 5 , C. Watts 2 , and G. Chehbouni 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Centre d&apos;Etudes Spatiales de la Biosphère, UPS, CNRS, CNES, IRD -UMR5126,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Toulouse, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Universidad de Sonora,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hermosillo, Sonora, México<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Centre National de l&apos;Energie, des Sciences et des Techniques Nucléaires,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kénitra, Morocco<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 LP2M2E, Département de physique, Faculté des Sciences et Techniques, Université Cadi Ayyad,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Marrakech, Morocco<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Instituto Tecnológico de Sonora,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Ciudad Obregón, Sonora, México<lb/></address>

	Correspondence to:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>G. Boulet</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(
	<email>gilles.boulet@cesbio.cnes.fr</email>
	)<lb/>

	<note type="submission">Received: 18 December 2012 -</note>

	<reference>Published in Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci. Discuss.: 21 January 2013<lb/></reference>

	<note type="submission">Revised: 11 February 2014 -Accepted: 15 February 2014</note>

	 -Published:
	<date>27 March 2014<lb/></date>

	Abstract.
	<div type="abstract">Instantaneous evapotranspiration rates and surface<lb/> water stress levels can be deduced from remotely sensed<lb/> surface temperature data through the surface energy bud-<lb/>get. Two families of methods can be defined: the contex-<lb/>tual methods, where stress levels are scaled on a given im-<lb/>age between hot/dry and cool/wet pixels for a particular veg-<lb/>etation cover, and single-pixel methods, which evaluate la-<lb/>tent heat as the residual of the surface energy balance for<lb/> one pixel independently from the others. Four models, two<lb/> contextual (S-SEBI and a modified triangle method, named<lb/> VIT) and two single-pixel (TSEB, SEBS) are applied over<lb/> one growing season (December-May) for a 4 km × 4 km ir-<lb/>rigated agricultural area in the semi-arid northern Mexico.<lb/> Their performance, both at local and spatial standpoints, are<lb/> compared relatively to energy balance data acquired at seven<lb/> locations within the area, as well as an uncalibrated soil-<lb/>vegetation-atmosphere transfer (SVAT) model forced with<lb/> local in situ data including observed irrigation and rainfall<lb/> amounts. Stress levels are not always well retrieved by most<lb/> models, but S-SEBI as well as TSEB, although slightly bi-<lb/>ased, show good performance. The drop in model perfor-<lb/>mance is observed for all models when vegetation is senes-<lb/>cent, mostly due to a poor partitioning both between tur-<lb/>bulent fluxes and between the soil/plant components of the<lb/> latent heat flux and the available energy. As expected, con-<lb/>textual methods perform well when contrasted soil moisture<lb/> and vegetation conditions are encountered in the same im-<lb/>age (therefore, especially in spring and early summer) while<lb/> they tend to exaggerate the spread in water status in more ho-<lb/>mogeneous conditions (especially in winter). Surface energy<lb/> balance models run with available remotely sensed prod-<lb/>ucts prove to be nearly as accurate as the uncalibrated SVAT<lb/> model forced with in situ data.<lb/></div>

	Published by <publisher>Copernicus Publications on behalf of the European Geosciences Union.</publisher>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
