<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="DAA1982EE2D6F693C20D84789446E98B5FF028C2"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Executive compensation<lb/> in libraries: an<lb/> oxymoron?<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jeanne Goodrich and<lb/> Paula M. Singer<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	The authors<lb/>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jeanne Goodrich </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	is an independent library consultant<lb/> specializing in strategic planning, work flow and work analysis,<lb/>
	and organizational design, 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Jeanne Goodrich Consulting,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Portland, Oregon, USA.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Paula M. Singer</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	is Principal Consultant, specializing in<lb/> compensation consulting, strategic planning, organization<lb/> design and development, and performance management, The<lb/> 

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Singer Group, Inc.,</affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>Reisterstown, Maryland, USA.</address>

	Keywords<lb/> 
	<keywords>Compensation, Chief executives, Libraries, Pay,<lb/> Senior management</keywords>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Pay, benefits, perquisites, the work environment and the intrinsic<lb/> rewards that it offers, all need to be used to attract the executive<lb/> a library needs and wants. To that end, this article provides an<lb/> overview of current practices in library executive compensation,<lb/> with an explanation of various approaches and the provision of<lb/> ideas for compensation components. This is especially pertinent,<lb/> as nearly 60 percent of professional librarians will retire,<lb/> including a large number of library executives, during the next<lb/> ten to 15 years. Other fields and professions face similarly large<lb/> numbers of retirements. The competition for top-quality library<lb/> executives will be fierce. Both library executives and libraries<lb/> hiring new executives need to be aware of the variety of<lb/> compensation approaches available to them.<lb/></div>

	Electronic access<lb/> The Emerald Research Register for this journal is<lb/> available at<lb/> www.emeraldinsight.com/researchregister<lb/> The current issue and full text archive of this journal is<lb/> available at<lb/> www.emeraldinsight.com/0888-045X.htm<lb/>
	
	<reference>The Bottom Line: Managing Library Finances<lb/> Volume 17 • Number 4 • 2004 • pp. 132-136<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">q Emerald Group Publishing Limited • </note>

	<idno>ISSN 0888-045X<lb/></idno>

	<idno>DOI 10.1108/08880450410567419</idno>

	<page>132</page>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
