<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ddn286"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Putative direct and indirect Wnt targets identified<lb/> through consistent gene expression changes<lb/> in APC-mutant intestinal adenomas<lb/> from humans and mice<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Stefania Segditsas 1,Ã, { , Oliver Sieber 1, { , Maesha Deheragoda 2 , Phil East 3 , Andrew Rowan 1 ,<lb/> Rosemary Jeffery 4 , Emma Nye 5 , Susan Clark 6 , Bradley Spencer-Dene 5 , Gordon Stamp 5 ,<lb/> Richard Poulsom 4 , Nirosha Suraweera 7 , Andrew Silver 7 , Mohammad Ilyas 8 and Ian Tomlinson 1</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Molecular and Population Genetics Laboratory,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Histopathology Laboratory, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Bioinformatics and Biostatistics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4<lb/> In Situ Hybridisation Service and 5 Experimental Pathology Laboratory, London Research Institute, Cancer Research<lb/> UK,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>44, Lincoln&apos;s Inn Fields, London WC2A 3PX, UK,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 Polyposis Registry, St Mark&apos;s Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Watford Road, Harrow<lb/> HA1 3UJ, UK,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>7 Colon Cancer Genetics, Institute of Cell and Molecular Science, Bart&apos;s and the London Medical School,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Whitechapel, London, UK and</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>8 Department of Histopathology, University of Nottingham, Queen&apos;s Medical Centre,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nottingham, UK<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received August 13, 2008; Revised and Accepted September 6, 2008<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">In order to identify new genes with differential expression in early intestinal tumours, we performed mRNA<lb/> (messenger ribonucleic acid) expression profiling of 16 human and 63 mouse adenomas. All individuals<lb/> had germline APC mutations to ensure that tumorigenesis was driven by &apos;second hits&apos; at APC. Using strin-<lb/>gent filtering to identify changes consistent between humans and mice, we identified 60 genes up-regulated<lb/> and 151 down-regulated in tumours. For 22 selected genes-including known Wnt targets-expression differ-<lb/>ences were confirmed by qRT -PCR (quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction). Most, but<lb/> not all, differences were also present in colorectal carcinomas. In situ analysis showed a complex picture.<lb/> Expression of up-regulated genes in adenomas was usually uniform/diffuse (e.g. ITGA6) or prominent in<lb/> the tumour core (e.g. LGR5); in normal tissue, these genes were expressed at crypt bases or the transit ampli-<lb/>fying zone. Down-regulated genes were often undetectable in adenomas, but in normal tissue were expressed<lb/> in mesenchyme (e.g. GREM1/2) or differentiated cells towards crypt tops (e.g. SGK1). In silico analysis of<lb/> TCF4-binding motifs showed that some of our genes were probably direct Wnt targets. Previous studies,<lb/> mostly focused on human tumours, showed partial overlap with our &apos;expression signature&apos;, but 37 genes<lb/> were unique to our study, including TACSTD2, SEMA3F, HOXA9 and IER3 (up-regulated), and TAGLN,<lb/> GREM1, GREM2, MAB21L2 and RARRES2 (down-regulated). Combined analysis of our and published<lb/> human data identified additional genes differentially expressed in adenomas, including decreased BMPs<lb/> (bone morphogenetic proteins) and increased BUB1/BUB1B. Several of the newly identified, differentially<lb/> expressed genes represent potential diagnostic or therapeutic targets for intestinal tumours.</div>

	Ã<lb/> To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: þ
	<phone>44 2072692884</phone>; 
	Fax: þ44 2072693093; Email:
	<email>stefania.segditsas@cancer.org.uk<lb/></email>

	† The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors.<lb/>
	
	<note type="copyright"># 2008 The Author(s)<lb/> This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/<lb/> licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is<lb/> properly cited.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24<lb/> 3864-3875<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1093/hmg/ddn286<lb/></idno>

	Advance Access published
	<date>on September 9, 2008</date>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
