<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="E5862773C3F2C8DAD61415066F38792411118030"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>ROLE OF ELECTRON MICROSCOPY OF SPERM IN THE<lb/> EVALUATION OF MALE INFERTILITY DURING THE ERA OF<lb/> ASSISTED REPRODUCTION<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>DOMINICK J. CARBONE, JR, JAMES T. MCMAHON, HOWARD S. LEVIN, ANTHONY J. THOMAS, JR,<lb/> AND ASHOK AGARWAL<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Objectives. To determine whether there are indications for and benefits from electron microscopy (EM) of<lb/> sperm during the era of assisted reproductive technology.<lb/> Methods. The medical history, semen analyses, and EM findings of 55 patients with pure male-factor<lb/> infertility were reviewed to determine: (1) which semen characteristics (seminal volume, sperm concentra-<lb/>tion, percent motility, and percent normal morphology) were associated with normal or abnormal ultrastruc-<lb/>ture as determined by EM, (2) whether EM findings correlated with success or failure of in vitro fertilization<lb/> (IVF), and (3) whether EM could screen for potentially inheritable genetic disorders.<lb/> Results. Principal EM diagnoses were normal sperm ultrastructure (11 of 55; 20%), tail abnormalities (21<lb/> of 55; 38%), necrospermia (12 of 55; 22%), acrosomal defects (9 of 55; 16%), neck abnormalities (1 of 55;<lb/> 2%), and incomplete maturation (1 of 55; 2%). Every patient with an abnormal EM study had impaired<lb/> motility (33% or below) and abnormal morphology (13% or lower normal forms by World Health Organiza-<lb/>tion criteria). The percentage of normal sperm morphology differed significantly across EM diagnoses (P Ͻ<lb/> 0.0001). Differences in motility across the groups could not be detected because EM was only performed on<lb/> patients with impaired motility. Although the partner of 1 patient with a normal EM study who underwent IVF<lb/> achieved pregnancy, 11 with abnormal EM studies failed to establish a pregnancy by IVF. Finally, 5 (11%) of<lb/> 44 patients with abnormal EM findings were diagnosed with primary ciliary dyskinesia directly as a result of<lb/> EM. In addition, 3 (6.8%) of the 44 patients with abnormal EM findings were diagnosed with complete<lb/> acrosomal loss.<lb/> Conclusions. Patients with severely abnormal motility and morphology on routine semen analysis may<lb/> benefit from EM study of sperm. Our data indicate that EM findings correlate with success or failure of IVF,<lb/> and that EM can screen for potentially inheritable genetic disorders.</div>

	<reference>UROLOGY 52: 301-305, 1998.<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">© 1998, Elsevier Science Inc. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	Presented at the
	<meeting>Annual Meeting of the American Society of An-<lb/>drology, Baltimore, Maryland, February 1997.<lb/></meeting>

	From the 
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Andrology Research and Clinical Laboratories, De-<lb/>partment of Urology, and Department of Anatomic Pathology,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cleveland Clinic Foundation, Cleveland, Ohio<lb/></address>

	Reprint requests:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ashok Agarwal, Ph.D.,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Andrology Research<lb/> and Clinical Laboratories, Department of Urology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>A19, Cleve-<lb/>land Clinic Foundation, Cleveland, OH 44195<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Submitted: June 26, 1997, accepted (with revisions): March 11, 1998<lb/></note>

	ADULT UROLOGY<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">© 1998, ELSEVIER SCIENCE INC.<lb/></note>

	0090-4295/98/$19.00<lb/> ALL RIGHTS RESERVED<lb/>
	<idno>PII S0090-4295(98)00155-1 301</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
