<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ele0017-1464"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">R E V I E W A N D<lb/> S Y N T H E S I S<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Hybridisation is associated with increased fecundity and size in<lb/> invasive taxa: meta-analytic support for the hybridisation-<lb/>invasion hypothesis<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Stephen M. Hovick 1 * and Kenneth<lb/> D. Whitney 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Evolution, Ecology,<lb/> and Organismal Biology The Ohio<lb/> State University Columbus,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>OH,43210, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Biology University<lb/> of New Mexico Albuquerque,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>NM,87131, USA<lb/></address>

	*Correspondence:<lb/> E-mail:
	<email>hovick.2@osu.edu<lb/></email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">The hypothesis that interspecific hybridisation promotes invasiveness has received much recent<lb/> attention, but tests of the hypothesis can suffer from important limitations. Here, we provide the<lb/> first systematic review of studies experimentally testing the hybridisation-invasion (H-I) hypothesis<lb/> in plants, animals and fungi. We identified 72 hybrid systems for which hybridisation has been<lb/> putatively associated with invasiveness, weediness or range expansion. Within this group, 15 sys-<lb/>tems (comprising 34 studies) experimentally tested performance of hybrids vs. their parental spe-<lb/>cies and met our other criteria. Both phylogenetic and non-phylogenetic meta-analyses<lb/> demonstrated that wild hybrids were significantly more fecund and larger than their parental taxa,<lb/> but did not differ in survival. Resynthesised hybrids (which typically represent earlier generations<lb/> than do wild hybrids) did not consistently differ from parental species in fecundity, survival or<lb/> size. Using meta-regression, we found that fecundity increased (but survival decreased) with gener-<lb/>ation in resynthesised hybrids, suggesting that natural selection can play an important role in<lb/> shaping hybrid performance -and thus invasiveness -over time. We conclude that the available<lb/> evidence supports the H-I hypothesis, with the caveat that our results are clearly driven by tests in<lb/> plants, which are more numerous than tests in animals and fungi.<lb/></div>

	Keywords<lb/>
	<keyword>Adaptive evolution, colonisation, hybridisation, introgression, invasion genetics, phylogenetic<lb/> meta-analysis, polyploidy, range expansion, weeds.<lb/></keyword>

	<reference>Ecology Letters (2014) 17: 1464-1477<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">© 2014 The Authors. Ecology Letters published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and CNRS.<lb/> This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and<lb/> distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Ecology Letters, (2014) 17: 1464-1477<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi: 10.1111/ele.12355</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
