<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="EPJ0290369-CC"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>High field magnetoresistivity of epitaxial La 2-x Sr x CuO 4 thin films<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>J. Vanacken 1,2 , L. Weckhuysen 1 , T. Wambecq 1 , P. Wagner 3 , and V.V. Moshchalkov 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Laboratorium voor Vaste-Stoffysica en Magnetisme, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Celestijnenlaan 200 D, B-3001 Leuven, Belgium<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Laboratoire National de Champs Magnétiques Pulsés,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>143, Avenue de Rangueil BP 4245, F31432 Toulouse, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Instituut voor Materiaalonderzoek, Limburgs Universitair Centrum,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wetenschapspark 1, B-3590 Diepenbeek, Belgium</address>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">A large positive magnetoresistivity (up to tens of percents) is observed in both underdoped and<lb/> overdoped superconducting La 2-x Sr x CuO 4 epitaxial thin films at temperatures far above the<lb/> superconducting critical temperature T c . For the underdoped samples, this magnetoresistance far<lb/> above T c cannot be described by the Kohler rule and we believe it is to be attributed to the influence of<lb/> superconducting fluctuations. In the underdoped regime, the large magnetoresistance is only present<lb/> when at low temperatures superconductivity occurs. T he strong magnetoresistivity, which persists<lb/> even at temperatures far above T c , can be related to the pairs forming eventually the superconducting<lb/> state below T c . Our observations support the idea of a close relation between the pseudogap and the<lb/> superconducting gap and provide new indications for the presence of pairs above T c .<lb/></div>

	<keyword>PACS numbers: 74.25.-q, 74.25.Dw, 74.25.Fy, 74.40.+k</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
