<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="F6B5A5277176483B3D56DC05887FE4A43965359F"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	Featured Subject: Radiosurgery<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Radiation-Related Adverse Effects<lb/> Observed on Neuro-Imaging<lb/> Several Years After Radiosurgery<lb/> for Cerebral Arteriovenous Malformations<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Masaaki Yamamoto, M.D.,* Mitsuhiro Hara, M.D., † Mitsunobu Ide, M.D.,*<lb/> Yuko Ono, M.D., § Minoru Jimbo, M.D.,* and Isamu Saito, M.D. †<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Departments of *Neurosurgery and §Radiology, Tokyo Women&apos;s Medical College Dai-ni<lb/> Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tokyo, Japan,</address>

	and
	<byline>
	<affiliation>†Department of Neurosurgery, Kyorin University School of<lb/> Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tokyo, Japan<lb/></address>

	<reference>Yamamoto M, Hara M, Ide M, Ono Y, Jimbo M, Saito I. Radiation-<lb/>related adverse effects observed on neuro-imaging several years<lb/> after radiosurgery for cerebral arteriovenous malformations.<lb/> Surg Neurol 1998;49:385-98.</reference>

	<div type="abstract">BACKGROUND<lb/> To our knowledge, there are no reported arteriovenous<lb/> malformation (AVM) series in which detailed long-term<lb/> follow-up results after radiosurgery were described<lb/> based on the whole patient group. METHOD<lb/> We performed a detailed long-term follow-up study of 53<lb/> patients with cerebral AVMs treated with gamma knife<lb/> (GK) radiosurgery, with emphasis on radiation-related<lb/> adverse effects detected on neuro-imaging after a long<lb/> post-irradiation latency period (3-10 years). The post-GK<lb/> follow-up period was 40 -232 months excluding two mor-<lb/>talities, the mean being 112 and the median being 111<lb/> months. RESULTS<lb/> Three patients (5.6%) have, as yet, refused all neuro-<lb/>imaging follow-up studies. Complete nidus obliteration<lb/> was confirmed angiographically in 32 patients (60.4%)<lb/> between 1 and 5 post-GK years. In the other 18 patients<lb/> (34%), despite significant nidus shrinkage being angio-<lb/>graphically demonstrated, complete obliteration was not<lb/> achieved during a 2-7 year follow-up period. There were<lb/> two mortalities, one AVM-related (massive re-bleeding<lb/> during the latency period) and the other angiography-<lb/>related. There were five radiation-related morbidities<lb/> (9.4%), three of which-hemi-Parkinson syndrome, hemi-<lb/>paresis, and visual field disturbances attributable to de-<lb/>layed cyst formation-manifested at 5.5, 7 and 7 post-GK<lb/> years, respectively. We also experienced five patients<lb/> (9.4%) in whom, despite remaining asymptomatic to date,<lb/> radiation-related adverse effects were seen on neuro-<lb/>imaging: middle cerebral artery stenosis at 3 post-GK<lb/> years in one patient; dural arteriovenous fistula at 7 post<lb/> GK-years in one; delayed cyst formation in two, at 5 and<lb/> 10 post-GK years; and a small cavitation at 9 post-GK<lb/> years. CONCLUSION<lb/> Long-term follow-up, particularly with neuro-imaging mo-<lb/>dalities, is essential even after the &quot;treatment goal&quot; has<lb/> been attained.</div>

	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by Elsevier Science Inc.<lb/></note>

	KEY WORDS<lb/>
	<keyword>Arteriovenous malformation, radiosurgery, gamma knife,<lb/> complication, radiation necrosis, cyst formation, dural arte-<lb/>riovenous fistula, rebleeding.<lb/></keyword>

	Address correspondence and reprint requests to:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dr. Masaaki<lb/> Yamamoto,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Tokyo Women&apos;s Medical Col-<lb/>lege Dai-ni Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2-1-10 Nishiogu, Arakawa-ku, Tokyo, 116 Japan.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received December 24, 1996; accepted December 4, 1997.<lb/></note>

	<note type="copyright">© 1998 by Elsevier Science Inc.<lb/></note>

	0090-3019/98/$19.00<lb/> 655 Avenue of the Americas, New York, NY 10010<lb/>
	<idno>PII S0090-3019(97)00531-4<lb/></idno>

	<reference>Complications after AVM Radiosurgery<lb/> Surg Neurol<lb/> 1998;49:385-98</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
