<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="F72502D82B96C863B0EF1C51BAE784C4F523F888"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>They Really Are That Old: A Validation Study of<lb/> Centenarian Prevalence in Okinawa<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>D. Craig Willcox, 1,2,4 Bradley J. Willcox, 2,3,4 Qimei He, 2<lb/> Nien-chiang Wang, 5 and Makoto Suzuki 4,6<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Okinawa International University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Japan.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2<lb/> Pacific Health Research Institute,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Honolulu, Hawaii.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Departments of Geriatric Medicine and Medicine, John A. Burns School of Medicine, University of Hawaii,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Honolulu.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4<lb/> Okinawa Research Center for Longevity Science,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Japan.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5<lb/> National Taiwan University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Taiwan.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6<lb/> Faculty of Medicine, University of the Ryukyus,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Okinawa, Japan.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Long-lived individuals, such as centenarians, may harbor genetic or environmental advantages<lb/> important for healthy aging. Populations with high prevalence of such individuals offer fertile<lb/> ground for such research. However, precise phenotypes are required, particularly accurate age.<lb/> Okinawa has among the world&apos;s highest reported prevalence of centenarians but, despite ex-<lb/>tensive study, no systematic validation of centenarian prevalence has been published. Therefore,<lb/> we performed comprehensive age validation of a subset (8%) of the total centenarian population<lb/> and assessed the reliability of the age registration system. Self-reported age was validated with<lb/> several common methods and found to correlate well with documented age. Demographic<lb/> methods, including assessment of age heaping, maximum age at death, centenarian proportions,<lb/> and male to female ratios of centenarians indicate that the age registration system is reliable. We<lb/> conclude that the high reported centenarian prevalence in Okinawa is valid and warrants further<lb/> study for its genetic and environmental correlates.<lb/></div>

	Key Words:
	<keyword>Longevity-Centenarian-Age Validation-Okinawa.</keyword>

	<page>338<lb/></page>

	<title level="j">Journal of Gerontology: BIOLOGICAL SCIENCES<lb/> </title>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright 2008 by The Gerontological Society of America<lb/> </note>

	<reference>2008, Vol. 63A, No. 4, 338-349<lb/></reference>

	CORRESPONDENCE<lb/> Address correspondence to
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>D. Craig Willcox, PhD,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of<lb/> Human Welfare, Okinawa International University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2-6-1 Ginowan,<lb/> Ginowan City, Okinawa, Japan.</address>

	E-mail:
	<email>d.willcox@okiu.ac.jp<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received August 21, 2007<lb/> Accepted December 18, 2007<lb/></note>

	Decision Editor:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Huber R. Warner, PhD</docAuthor>
	</byline>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
