<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="Faraday-discuss-post-ref"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>On the accuracy of intermolecular interactions<lb/> and charge transfer: the case of TTF-CA<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Pilar García a , Slimane Dahaoui a , Claudine Katan b , Mohamed<lb/> Souhassou a and Claude Lecomte a †<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">High-resolution X-ray diffraction experiments and state of the art density<lb/> functional theory calculations have been performed. The validity of the<lb/> atoms in molecules approach is tested for the neutral-ionic transition of<lb/> TTF-CA which involves a transfer of less than one electron between the<lb/> donor and acceptor molecules. Foremost, crystallographical data have been<lb/> reassessed along the temperature-induced neutral-ionic phase transition<lb/> undergone by this charge transfer complex. Based on accurate X-ray<lb/> structures at 105 and 15 K, topological analysis of both DFT and the<lb/> experimental multipolar electron densities allowed detailed characterization<lb/> of intra-and interstack intermolecular interactions. Direct quantification of<lb/> the intermolecular charge transfer and the dipole moment are discussed.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Laboratoire de Cristallographie et Modélisation des Matériaux Minéraux et Biologiques LCM 3 B<lb/> CNRS UMR 7036.Université Henri Poincaré, Nancy 1, Faculté des Sciences, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>BP 239, 54506<lb/> Vandoeuvre-lès-Nancy Cedex (France). </address>

	Fax: +33-(0)383 406492; 
	Tel: 
	<phone>+33-(0383 684863</phone>; 
	E-mail:<lb/>
	<email>Claude.Lecomte@lcm3b.uhp-nancy.fr<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Synthèse et ElectroSynthèse Organiques, CNRS UMR6510, Université de Rennes 1, Campus de<lb/> Beaulieu, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Bât. 10A,Case 1003, 35402 Rennes Cedex, France. </address>

	Fax : +33-(0)223 236955
	; Tel: 
	<phone>+33-<lb/>(0)223 235682</phone>.<lb/> 

	† Author to whom correspondece should be adressed. E-mail:
	<email>Claude.Lecomte@lcm3b.uhp-nancy.fr</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
