<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="FB5D4C15DEAB23FC35E2BE7045788E925EC896C1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Measuring Bilingual Children&apos;s Receptive Vocabularies<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Vivian M. Umbel, Barbara Z. Pearson,<lb/> Maria C. Fernandez, and D, K. Oiler<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Miami<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<reference>UMBEL, VIVIAN M.; PEARSON, BARBABA Z.; FEBNANDEZ, MARIA C; and OLLER, D. K. Measuring<lb/> Bilingual Children&apos;s Receptive Vocabularies. CHILD DEVELOPMENT, 1992, 63, 1012-1020.</reference>

	<div type="abstract">Re-<lb/>ceptive vocabulary of Hispanic children in Miami was tested in both English and Spanish with<lb/> complementary standardized tests, the Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test (PPVT-H) and the Test<lb/> de Vocabulario en Imagenes Peabody (TVIP-H), 105 bilingual flrst graders, of middle to high<lb/> socioeconomic status relative to national norms, were divided according to the language(s) spo-<lb/>ken in their homes. Both groups, whether they spoke only Spanish in the home (OSH) or both<lb/> English and Spanish in the home (ESH), performed near the mean of 100 in Spanish receptive<lb/> vocabulary (TVIP-H means 97,0 and 96.5); in contrast, ESH group children scored more than 1<lb/> SD higher in EngUsh than OSH group children (PPVT-R means 88.0 and 69,7, respectively). It<lb/> appears, therefore, that learning 2 languages at once does not harm receptive language develop-<lb/>ment in the language of origin, while it does lay the groundwork for superior performance in the<lb/> majority language. Furthermore, an analysis of translation equivalents, items shared by both<lb/> tests, shows that a statistically signiflcant portion of bilingual children&apos;s lexical knowledge does<lb/> not overlap in their 2 languages and is therefore not reflected in single-language scores.<lb/></div>

	[<reference>Child Development, 1992, 63, 1012-1020.</reference>
	<note type="copyright">© 1992 by the Society for Research in Child Development, Inc.<lb/> All rights reserved,</note>

	0009-3920/92/6304-0018$01.00]
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
