<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="687"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">The Relative Complexity of NP Search Problems <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Paul Beame <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Computer Science and Engineering <lb/>University of Washington <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<email>beame@cs.washington.edu <lb/></email>
		<byline><docAuthor>Stephen Cook <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Computer Science Dept. <lb/>University of Toronto <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<email>sacook@cs.toronto.edu <lb/></email>
		<byline><docAuthor>Jeff Edmonds <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>I.C.S.I. <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>Berkeley, CA 94704-1198 <lb/></address>
		<email>edmonds@icsi.berkeley.edu <lb/></email>
		<byline><docAuthor>Russell Impagliazzo x <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Computer Science and Engineering <lb/>UC, San Diego <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>9500 Gilman Drive <lb/>La Jolla, CA 92093-0114 <lb/></address>
		<email>russell@cs.ucsd.edu <lb/></email>
		<byline><docAuthor>Toniann Pitassi - <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Mathematics and Computer Science <lb/>University of Pittsburgh <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<email>toni@cs.pitt.edu <lb/></email>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/>Papadimitriou introduced several classes of NP search problems based on combinatorial principles which guarantee the <lb/>existence of solutions to the problems. Many interesting <lb/>search problems not known to be solvable in polynomial <lb/>time are contained in these classes, and a number of them <lb/>are complete problems. We consider the question of the relative complexity of these search problem classes. We prove <lb/>several separations which show that in a generic relativized <lb/>world, the search classes are distinct and there is a standard <lb/>search problem in each of them that is not computation-ally equivalent to any decision problem. (Naturally, absolute separations would imply that P 6= NP.) Our separation <lb/>proofs have interesting combinatorial content and go to the <lb/>heart of the combinatorial principles on which the classes are <lb/>based. We derive one result via new lower bounds on the <lb/>degrees of polynomials asserted to exist by Hilbert&apos;s Null-stellensatz over finite fields. <lb/></div>
		<note type="grant">Research supported by NSF grants CCR-8858799 and CCR-9303017 <lb/>Research supported by an NSERC operating grant and the Information Technology Research Centre <lb/>Supported by an NSF postdoctoral fellowship and by a Canadian <lb/>NSERC postdoctoral fellowship <lb/>x Research Supported by NSF YI Award CCR-92-570979, Sloan <lb/>Research Fellowship BR-3311, grant #93025 of the joint US-Czechoslovak Science and Technology Program, and USA-Israel BSF <lb/>Grant 92-00043 <lb/>Research supported by an NSF postdoctoral fellowship and by <lb/>NSF Grant CCR-9457782 <lb/></note>
		<div type="intro">1 Introduction</div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>