<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1035"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<note type="other">1 <lb/></note>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">On the relationship between interdisciplinarity and scientific impact <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Vincent Larivière and Yves Gingras <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Observatoire des sciences et des technologies (OST) <lb/> Centre interuniversitaire de recherche sur la science et la technologie (CIRST) <lb/> Université du Québec à Montréal <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>CP 8888, Succursale Centre-ville <lb/> Montréal, Québec, H3C 3P8 <lb/></address>
		<email>[lariviere.vincent; gingras.yves]@uqam.ca <lb/></email>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/> This paper analyzes the effect of interdisciplinarity on the scientific impact of individual papers. Using all the <lb/> papers published in Web of Science in 2000, we define the degree of interdisciplinarity of a given paper as <lb/> the percentage of its cited references made to journals of other disciplines. We show that, although for all <lb/> disciplines combined there is no clear correlation between the level of interdisciplinarity of papers and their <lb/> citation rates, there are nonetheless some disciplines in which a higher level of interdisciplinarity is related <lb/> to a higher citation rates. For other disciplines, citations decline as interdisciplinarity grows. One <lb/> characteristic is visible in all disciplines: highly disciplinary and highly interdisciplinary papers have a low <lb/> scientific impact. This suggests that there might be an optimum of interdisciplinarity beyond which the <lb/> research is too dispersed to find its niche and under which it is too mainstream to have high impact. Finally, <lb/> the relationship between interdisciplinarity and scientific impact is highly determined by the citation <lb/> characteristics of the disciplines involved: papers citing citation intensive disciplines are more likely to be <lb/> cited by those disciplines and, hence, obtain higher citation scores than papers citing non citation intensive <lb/> disciplines. <lb/></div>
		<div type="intro">Introduction <lb/></div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>