<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="247"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<note type="reference">To Appear in the ACM Multimedia Journal <lb/></note>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Dynamic Management of Guaranteed Performance Multimedia Connections <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Colin Parris, Hui Zhang , and Domenico Ferrari <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<email>parris, hzhang, ferrari@tenet.Berkeley.EDU <lb/></email>
		<byline><affiliation>Computer Science Division <lb/>University of California at Berkeley <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>Berkeley, CA 94720 <lb/></address>
		<keywords>Keywords: Multimedia, Network Management, Quality of Service, High Speed Networks. <lb/></keywords>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/>Most of the solutions proposed to support real-time (i.e. guaranteed performance) communication services in packet-switching networks adopt a connection-oriented and reservation-oriented approach. In such an approach, resource allocation <lb/>and route selection decisions are made before the start of the communication on the basis of resource availability and real-time network load at that time, and are usually kept for the duration of the communication. This rather static resource <lb/>management approach has certain limitations: it does not take into account (a) the dynamics of the communicating clients; <lb/>(b) the dynamics of the network state; and (c) the tradeoff between quality of service and network availability, thus affecting <lb/>the availability and flexibility of the real-time network services. Availability is the ability of the network to accommodate <lb/>as many real-time clients as possible, while flexibility is the ability to adapt the real-time services to changing network state <lb/>and client demands. In this paper, we present the Dynamic Connection Management (DCM) scheme, which addresses these <lb/>issues by providing the network with the capability to dynamically modify the performance parameters and the routes of <lb/>any existing real-time connection. With these capabilities, DCM can be used to increase the availability and flexibility of <lb/>the guaranteed performance service offered to the clients. <lb/></div>
		<div type="intro">1 Introduction</div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>