<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1099"/> 
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en"> 
	<front> 
		<note type="submission">Confidential:  not for distribution. Submitted to IOP Publishing for peer review </note>
        <date type="submission">11 January 2010<lb/></date>

		<note type="title">Determination  and simulation of the angular distribution of the metal flux<lb/></note>
	
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Experimental determination and simulation of the angular<lb/> distribution of the metal flux during magnetron sputter<lb/> deposition<lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle> 
		 
		<byline><docAuthor>M Horkel  1  , K Van Aeken  2  , C Eisenmenger-Sittner  1  , D Depla  2  , S Mahieu  2  and W P Leroy  2<lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		
		<byline><affiliation> 1  Institute of Solid State Physics, E-138, Vienna University of Technology, </affiliation></byline> 
		<address>Wiedner<lb/>Hauptstrasse 8-10, Vienna A-1040, Austria<lb/></address>
				
		<byline><affiliation>2  Department for Solid State Sciences, Ghent University, </affiliation></byline> 
		<address>Krijgslaan 281 (S1) 9000, Ghent<lb/>9000, Belgium<lb/></address>
		
		<email>e-mail: m.horkel@gmx.at<lb/></email>
		
		<div type="abstract">To understand the film growth during magnetron sputter deposition a detailed knowledge of<lb/> the flux of sputtered species from the target towards the substrate is vital. One important<lb/> parameter is the angular distribution of the impinging neutral target atoms on the substrate,<lb/> since it is responsible for e.g. self shadowing effects. The determination of the angular<lb/> distribution of the metal flux at an arbitrary point in the deposition chamber is achieved by a<lb/> pinhole-camera, where the information of the angular distribution is converted into a thickness<lb/> profile. This paper describes the construction of such a pinhole-camera which is capable of<lb/> differential pumping, the determination of the angular distribution for a wide variety of target<lb/>  materials, and which can easily be inserted into a deposition chamber. The angular<lb/>  distributions of different materials (Cu; W; Al; Ti; Mg) at different parameters (pressure,<lb/> lateral position, and vertical position) are experimentally determined and compared to<lb/>  simulations obtained from a newly developed Monte Carlo code. It was also investigated, if <lb/>parameters derived from the angular distribution are related to the degree of thermalization of<lb/> the impinging particles.<lb/></div> 
		
		<keywords type="pacs">PACS: 81.15.Cd Deposition by sputtering<lb/></keywords>
		
		<keywords>Keywords: angular distribution, sputter deposition, magnetron deposition, pinhole camera,<lb/> thermalization<lb/></keywords>
		
		<note type="submission">Submitted to: Journal of Physics D: Applied Physics<lb/></note>
		
   		<introduction>1. Introduction:<lb/></introduction>
		
    </front>
</text>
</tei>                              