<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="190"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Hierarchical Optimization of Optimal Path Finding for <lb/>Transportation Applications <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Ning Jing <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Changsha Institute of Technology <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<email>jning@eecs.umich.edu <lb/></email>
		<byline><docAuthor>Yun-Wu Huang <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>University of Michigan <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<email>ywh@eecs.umich.edu <lb/></email>
		<byline><docAuthor>Elke A. Rundensteiner <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>University of Michigan <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<email>rundenst@eecs.umich.edu <lb/></email>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/>Efficient path query processing is a key requirement for advanced <lb/>database applications including GIS (Geographic Information Systems) and ITS (Intelligent Transportation Systems). We study the <lb/>problem in the context of automobile navigation systems where a <lb/>large number of path requests can be submitted over the transportation network within a short period of time. To guarantee efficient re-sponsefor path queries, we employ a path view materialization strategy for precomputing the best paths. We tackle the following three <lb/>issues: (1) memory-resident solutions quickly exceed current computer storage capacity for networks of thousands of nodes, (2) disk-based solutions have been found inefficient to meet the stringent <lb/>performance requirements, and (3) path views become too costly <lb/>to update for large graphs. We propose the HEP V (Hierarchical <lb/>Encoded Path View) approach that addresses these problems while <lb/>guaranteeing the optimality of path retrieval. Our experimental results reveal that HEP V is more efficient than previously known <lb/>path finding approaches. <lb/></div>
		<div type="intro">1 Introduction</div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>