<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1071"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Study  of strange particle production in pp collisions<lb/> with the ALICE detector<lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Hélène Ricaud   1   , Alexander Kalweit   1   and Antonin Maire   2<lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<note type="other">(for<lb/> the ALICE Collaboration)<lb/></note>
		<byline><affiliation>1   Technical  University of Darmstadt, Institut fuer Kernphysik,</affiliation></byline>
		<address>Schlossgartenstrasse 9,<lb/> D-64289 Darmstadt, Germany<lb/></address>    
		<byline><affiliation>2   Institut Pluridisciplinaire Hubert Curien, </affiliation></byline>
		<address>23 rue du Loess, F-67037 Strasbourg,<lb/>France<lb/></address>
		<email>E-mail:  H.Ricaud@gsi.de<lb/></email>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract.  ALICE is well suited for strange particles production studies since it has<lb/> very good reconstruction capabilities in the low transverse momentum (p   t   ) region and<lb/> it also allows to extend the identification up to quite high  p   t   . Charged strange mesons<lb/> (K   +   , K   −   ,) are reconstructed via energy loss measurements whereas neutral strange<lb/> mesons (K   0<lb/> s   ) and strange hyperons (Λ, Ξ, Ω) are identified via vertex reconstruction.<lb/> All these particles carry important information: first, the measurement of production<lb/> yields and the particle ratio within the statistical models can help to understand the<lb/> medium created and secondly the dynamics at intermediate  p   t   investigated via the<lb/> baryon over meson ratio (Λ/K   0<lb/> s   ) allows a better understanding of the hadronization<lb/> mechanisms and of the underlying event processes. We present these two aspects of<lb/> the strange particles analysis in pp collisions using simulated data.<lb/></div>
		<note type="title">Study  of strange particle production in pp collisions with the ALICE detector<lb/>2<lb/></note>
		<introduction>1. Introduction<lb/></introduction>
        </front>
</text>
</tei>