<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="602"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Coordination and Control Structures and Processes: <lb/>Possibilities for Connectionist Networks (CN) <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Vasant Honavar &amp; Leonard Uhr <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Computer Sciences Department <lb/>University of Wisconsin-Madison <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/>The absence of powerful control structures and processes that synchronize, coordinate, switch between, choose among, regulate, direct, modulate interactions between, and <lb/>combine distinct yet interdependent modules of large connectionist networks (CN) is <lb/>probably one of the most important reasons why such networks have not yet succeeded at <lb/>handling difficult tasks (e.g. complex object recognition and description, complex <lb/>problem-solving, planning). <lb/>In this paper we examine how CN built from large numbers of relatively simple <lb/>neuron-like units can be given the ability to handle problems that in typical multi-computer networks and artificial intelligence programs along with all other types of <lb/>programs are always handled using extremely elaborate and precisely worked out central control (coordination, synchronization, switching, etc.). We point out the several <lb/>mechanisms for central control of this un-brain-like sort that CN already have built into <lb/>them albeit in hidden, often overlooked, ways. <lb/>We examine the kinds of control mechanisms found in computers, programs, fetal <lb/>development, cellular function and the immune system, evolution, social organizations, <lb/>and especially brains, that might be of use in CN. Particularly intriguing suggestions are <lb/>found in the pacemakers, oscillators, and other local sources of the brain&apos;s complex partial synchronies; the diffuse, global effects of slow electrical waves and neurohormones; <lb/>the developmental program that guides fetal development; communication and coordination within and among living cells; the working of the immune system; the evolutionary <lb/>processes that operate on large populations of organisms; and the great variety of partially competing partially cooperating controls found in small groups, organizations, and <lb/>larger societies. All these systems are rich in control but typically control that emerges <lb/>from complex interactions of many local and diffuse sources. We explore how several <lb/>different kinds of plausible control mechanisms might be incorporated into CN, and <lb/>assess their potential benefits with respect to their cost. <lb/></div>
		<div type="intro">Introduction</div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>