<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="541"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Mixed-Initiative Management of Integrated Process-Planning and <lb/>Production-Scheduling Solutions <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>David W. Hildum, Norman M. Sadeh, Thomas J. Laliberty, <lb/>Stephen F. Smith, John McA&apos;Nulty and Dag Kjenstad <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Intelligent Coordination and Logistics Laboratory <lb/>Center for Integrated Manufacturing Decision Systems <lb/>The Robotics Institute <lb/>Carnegie Mellon University <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>Pittsburgh PA 15213-3890 <lb/></address>
		<note type="phone">412.268.7598 fax: 412.268.5569 <lb/></note>
		<email>{HILDUM,SADEH,SFS,DAG}@ISL1.RI.CMU.EDU <lb/></email>
		<byline><affiliation>Software Engineering Laboratory <lb/>Raytheon Electronic Systems <lb/>Raytheon Company <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>Tewksbury MA 01876-0901 <lb/></address>
		<note type="phone">508.858.5756 fax: 508.858.5976 <lb/></note>
		<email>LALIBERTY_THOMAS@CAEMAC.MSD.RAY.COM <lb/></email> 
		<email>MCANULTY@CAESUN.MSD.RAY.COM <lb/></email>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/>Increased reliance on agile manufacturing techniques has created a demand for systems to solve integrated process-planning <lb/>and production-scheduling problems in large-scale dynamic environments. To be effective, these systems should provide user-oriented interactive functionality for managing the various user <lb/>tasks and objectives and reacting to unexpected events. This paper describes the mixed-initiative problem-solving features of <lb/>IP3S, an Integrated Process-Planning/Production-Scheduling <lb/>shell for agile manufacturing. IP3S is a blackboard -based system <lb/>that supports the concurrent development and dynamic revision <lb/>of integrated process-planning and production-scheduling solutions and the maintenance of multiple problem instances and <lb/>solutions, as well as other flexible user-oriented decision-making <lb/>capabilities, allowing the user to control the scope of the problem and explore alternate tradeoffs (what-if scenarios) interactively. The system is scheduled for initial deployment <lb/>and evaluation in a large and highly dynamic machine shop at <lb/>Raytheon&apos;s Andover manufacturing facility. <lb/></div>
		<div type="intro">Introduction</div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>