<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1114"/>  
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en"> 
	<front>    
		<note type="submission">Confidential:  not for distribution. Submitted to IOP Publishing for peer review </note>
        <date type="submission">30 April 2010<lb/></date>
    
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Reflection  Anisotropy Spectra of Polydimethylsiloxane under<lb/> a range of mechanically applied stress<lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle> 
		
		<byline><docAuthor> T Farrell  1  , C I Smith  1  , A L Schofield  1  , R L Williams  2  and P Weightman  1*<lb/> </docAuthor></byline>
		
		<byline><affiliation> 1  Department of Physics, University of Liverpool, </affiliation></byline> 
		<address>Liverpool, L69 7ZE, UK<lb/></address>  
		
		<byline><affiliation> 2  School of Clinical Sciences, University of Liverpool, </affiliation></byline> 
		<address>L69 3GA, UK<lb/></address> 
				
		<note> *Corresponding Author<lb/></note>
		
		<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Reflection anisotropy spectra (RAS) of transparent elastomeric polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) have<lb/> been determined over the spectral range 1.5 eV to 5.0 eV for a range of tensile loads. Using a slight<lb/> wedge shaped sample the spectra from the incident air/PDMS surface are shown to be weak and<lb/> largely featureless at all loads. By contrast the spectra from the light transmitted through the sample<lb/> and reflected at the other interface are large in magnitude and exhibit features which arise from the<lb/> small stress birefringence of PDMS.<lb/> The birefringent dominated spectra can readily be simulated using expressions derived from a<lb/> Stokes-Mueller treatment of the optical system and this enabled the stress-optical coefficient to be<lb/> determined at any energy within the spectral range covered. It is shown that there is a small angle<lb/> between the optical axes and the mechanical axes in the sample and that this is consistent with the<lb/> model of an elastomer which comprises a network of soft linear chains cross linked with stiff bridges.<lb/></div>  	
		
		<keywords type="pacs"> PACS<lb/></keywords>
		
		<introduction>1.  Introduction<lb/></introduction>
		
    </front>
</text>
</tei>                              