<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="638"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Investigating <lb/>Genetic Algorithms <lb/>for Scheduling <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Hsiao-Lan Fang <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<note type="degree">MSc Dissertation <lb/></note>
		<byline><affiliation>Department of Artificial Intelligence <lb/>University of Edinburgh <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<date>1992 <lb/></date>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/> This project investigates the use of Genetic Algorithms on the problem of <lb/> scheduling exam timetables for the AI/CS MSc exams at the University of Edin- <lb/> burg, with the constraints that the timetables should be as fair as possible on <lb/> students (avoiding clashes, three exams in a day, and consecutive exams). This <lb/> problem is very hard to solve because of the extremely large number of possible <lb/> timetables, and the difficulty of simultaneously satisfying a large number of stu- <lb/> dents. Human experts take many iterations at this task, until over several days <lb/> of trial and error and consultation with students a timetable is arranged. This <lb/> project shows that a Genetic Algorithm system can perform this job quickly (in <lb/> about 5 minutes) and satisfactorily (producing timetables which are measurably <lb/> better than those produced by the human schedulers). The project describes Ge- <lb/> netic Algorithms, the representation used for exam timetables, and also discusses <lb/> experiments in which ways are studied to improve performance. We find that an <lb/> elitist strategy using inverse square pressure, variation of operator rates (crossover <lb/> and mutation) and fixed-point uniform crossover is a measurably better strategy <lb/> than traditional Genetic Algorithms on this problem. The system described can <lb/> be easily adapted for use in similar timetabling problems. <lb/></div>
		<note type="other">Table of Contents <lb/></note>
		<div type="intro">1. Introduction <lb/></div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>