<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="unknown"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Automatically Selecting and Using Primary Effects <lb/>in Planning: Theory and Experiments <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Eugene Fink <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>School of Computer Science <lb/>Carnegie Mellon University <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>Pittsburgh, PA 15213, USA <lb/></address>
		<email>eugene@cs.cmu.edu <lb/></email>
		<ptr type="web">http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~eugene <lb/></ptr>
		<byline><docAuthor>Qiang Yang <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>School of Computing Science <lb/>Simon Fraser University <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>Burnaby, BC V5A1S6, Canada <lb/></address>
		<email>qyang@cs.sfu.ca <lb/></email>
		<ptr type="web">http://fas.sfu.ca/cs/people/Faculty/Yang <lb/></ptr>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/>The use of primary effects of operators is an effective approach to improving the <lb/>efficiency of planning. The characterization of &quot;good&quot; primary effects, however, has <lb/>remained at an informal level and there have been no algorithms for selecting primary <lb/>effects of operators. <lb/>We formalize the use of primary effects in planning and present a criterion for <lb/>selecting useful primary effects, which guarantees efficiency and completeness. We <lb/>analyze the efficiency of planning with primary effects and the quality of the resulting <lb/>plans. <lb/>We then describe a learning algorithm that automatically selects primary effects <lb/>and demonstrate, both analytically and empirically, that the use of this algorithm <lb/>significantly reduces planning time and does not compromise completeness. <lb/></div>
		<note type="grant">Eugene Fink is supported by Wright Laboratory, Aeronautical Systems Center, Air Force Materiel <lb/>Command, USAF, and the Advanced Research Projects Agency (ARPA) under grant number F33615-93-1-1330. Qiang Yang is supported by Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) <lb/>under grant number OGP0184883. <lb/></note>
		<pb/>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>