<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1123"/>  
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en"> 
	<front>    
    	<idno>DOI:  10.1002/zaac.200700516 <lb/></idno>
    			
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Synthesis and Characterization of a Purely Inorganic Open-framework<lb/> Bimetallic Phosphite with Intersecting 12- and 16-membered Ring Channels<lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle> 
		
		<byline><docAuthor>Gaijuan Li  a  , Yan Xing  a,  *, Yunling Liu  b  , Xianchun Liu  a  , Ning Xu  a  , and Shuyan Song  a<lb/> </docAuthor></byline>
		
		<address>Changchun  / P R China,   </address>  
		<byline><affiliation> a  College of Chemistry, Northeast Normal University and  b  State Key Laboratory of Inorganic Synthesis and<lb/> Preparative Chemistry, College of Chemistry, Jilin University <lb/></affiliation></byline> 
		
		<note type="submission">Received October 14  th  , 2007; accepted November 14  th  , 2007.<lb/></note>
		
		<div type="abstract">Abstract. A new three-dimensional open-framework cobalt-zinc<lb/> phosphite [Co(H  2  O)  4  Zn(HPO  3  )  2  ] · H  2  O (1), has been prepared un-<lb/> der hydrothermal conditions and characterized by single-crystal X-<lb/> ray diffraction, XRD, IR and SQUID magnetometer. The com-<lb/> pound crystallizes in the triclinic space group  P1  ¯ with a  񮽙  7.552(5),<lb/> b  񮽙  7.671(5), c  񮽙  9.443(5) A   񮽙  񮽙  88.538(5)°,  β  񮽙  89.109(5)°,  γ  񮽙<lb/>  87.056(5)°, V  񮽙  546.1(6) A ˚  , Z  񮽙  2. The structure of 1 consists of<lb/> corner-shared (cs) four-membered-ring chains formed by alter-<lb/> nating ZnO  4  tetrahedra and HPO  3  pseudopyramids, which are<lb/> further linked through CoO  2  (H  2  O)  4  octahedra giving rise to a<lb/> three-dimensional (3-D) neutral open-framework with intersecting<lb/> 12- and 16-MR channels. The synthesis of system required the pres-<lb/> ence of L-histidine which is not incorporated into the structure of<lb/> the product. It is noteworthy that compound 1 represents the only<lb/> known example of purely inorganic open-framework cobalt-zinc<lb/> phosphite.<lb/> </div>  

		<keywords>Keywords: Hydrothermal synthesis; Open-framework; Cobalt-zinc<lb/> phosphite; Magnetic properties<lb/></keywords>
		
		<introduction>Introduction <lb/></introduction>
		
    </front>
</text>
</tei>                              