<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1101"/> 
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en"> 
	<front>
		<note type="submission">Confidential:  not for distribution. Submitted to IOP Publishing for peer review </note>
        <date type="submission">12 November 2010<lb/></date>
	
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Contrasting  characteristics of sub-microsecond pulsed<lb/> atmospheric air and atmospheric pressure helium-<lb/> oxygen glow discharges<lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle> 
		 
		<byline><docAuthor>J. L. Walsh  1  , D. X. Liu  1,2  , F. Iza  1  , M. Z. Rong  2  , and M. G. Kong  1 *<lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		
		<byline><affiliation>1 <lb/>  Dept  of Electronic and Electrical Engineering, Loughborough University,   </affiliation></byline> 
		<address>Leics LE11 3TU, UK<lb/></address> 
				
		<byline><affiliation>2 <lb/> State Key Lab of Electrical Insulation and Power Equipments, Xi'an Jiaotong University,  </affiliation></byline> 
		<address>710049, P. <lb/> R. China<lb/></address>
				
		<div type="abstract">Abstract:  Glow discharges in air are often considered to be the ultimate low-temperature<lb/> atmospheric pressure plasmas for numerous chamber-free applications. This is due to the<lb/> ubiquitous presence of air and the perceived abundance of reactive oxygen and nitrogen<lb/> species in air plasmas. In this paper, sub-microsecond pulsed atmospheric air plasmas are<lb/>  shown to produce a low concentration of excited oxygen atoms but an abundance of excited<lb/> nitrogen species, UV photons and ozone molecules. This contrasts sharply with efficient<lb/> production of excited oxygen atoms in comparable helium-oxygen discharges. Relevant<lb/> reaction chemistry analyzed with a global model suggests that collisional excitation of O  2  by<lb/> helium metastables is significantly more efficient than electron dissociative excitation of O  2  ,<lb/> electron excitation of O, and ion-ion recombination. These results suggest different practical<lb/> uses of the two oxygen-containing atmospheric discharges, with air plasmas being well<lb/> suited for nitrogen and UV based chemistry and He-O  2  plasmas for excited atomic oxygen<lb/> based chemistry.<lb/></div> 
		
		<note>* <lb/>   Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; </note>
 		<email>e-mail: m.g.kong@lboro.ac.uk<lb/></email>
		
    </front>
</text>
</tei>                              