<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1093"/> 
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en"> 
	<front> 
		<note type="submission">Confidential:  not for distribution. Submitted to IOP Publishing for peer review </note>
        <date type="submission">21 October 2009<lb/></date>

		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">On  the electronic origin of the inverse magnetocaloric effect in Ni-Co-Mn-In Heusler alloys<lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle> 
		 
		<byline><docAuthor>A.N. Vasiliev  1  , O. Heczko  2,3,♣  , O.S. Volkova  1  , T.N. Vasilchikova  1  , T.N. Voloshok  1  , K.V.<lb/> Klimov  1  , W. Ito  4  , R. Kainuma  4  , K. Ishida  5  , K. Oikawa  5  , and S. Fähler  2<lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		
		<byline><affiliation>1  Low Temperature Physics and Superconductivity Department, Moscow State University, <lb/></affiliation></byline>	
		<address>Moscow, 119991, Russia <lb/></address>
		
		<byline><affiliation>2  IFW Dresden, Institute for Metallic Materials, </affiliation></byline>	
		<address>P.O. Box 27 01 16, 01171 Dresden, Germany<lb/></address>

		<byline><affiliation>3  Institute of Physics, Academy of Sciences of Czech Republic,  </affiliation></byline>	
		<address>Na Slovance 2, Prague, Czech<lb/>Republic<lb/></address>
		
		<byline><affiliation>4  IMRAM, Tohoku University, </affiliation></byline>
		<address>6-6-02 Aoba-yama, Sendai 980-8579, Japan<lb/></address>
		
		<byline><affiliation>5  Department of Materials Science, Graduate School of Engineering, </affiliation></byline>	
		<address>Tohoku University, 6-6-02<lb/> Aoba-yama, Sendai 980-8579, Japan<lb/></address>
		
		<note type="other">♣   corresponding author</note>
		
		<div type="abstract">In order to understand the electronic origin of the inverse magnetocaloric effect<lb/> observed in the Ni-Co-Mn-In system we used the combination of indirect<lb/> experimental probes as magnetization, resistivity and specific heat. Findings are<lb/> compared with the band structure of isostructural Heusler alloys like Ni-Mn-Ga.<lb/> We suggest that the inverse magnetocaloric effect in Ni-Co-Mn-In originates from<lb/> the high density of states close to Fermi energy. Within the austenite state this<lb/> causes ferromagnetic band splitting. The structural change to the martensite<lb/> allows an alternative way to reduce the high density of states at lower<lb/> temperature, which does not require the band splitting and thus it does not support<lb/> ferromagnetic order.<lb/></div>
		
		<keywords type="pacs">PACS: 71.20.Eh, 75.30.Sg, 75.30.Kz<lb/></keywords>
    </front>
</text>
</tei>                              