<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1024"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Reducing labeling effort for structured prediction tasks <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Aron Culotta and Andrew McCallum <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Department of Computer Science <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>140 Governor&apos;s Drive <lb/></address>
		<byline><affiliation>University of Massachusetts <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>Amherst, MA 01003?4601 <lb/></address>
		<email>{culotta, mccallum}@cs.umass.edu <lb/></email>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/> A common obstacle preventing the rapid deployment of <lb/> supervised machine learning algorithms is the lack of <lb/> labeled training data. This is particularly expensive to <lb/> obtain for structured prediction tasks, where each train- <lb/> ing instance may have multiple, interacting labels, all <lb/> of which must be correctly annotated for the instance to <lb/> be of use to the learner. Traditional active learning ad- <lb/> dresses this problem by optimizing the order in which <lb/> the examples are labeled to increase learning efficiency. <lb/> However, this approach does not consider the difficulty <lb/>  of labeling each example, which can vary widely in <lb/> structured prediction tasks. For example, the labeling <lb/> predicted by a partially trained system may be easier <lb/> to correct for some instances than for others. <lb/> We propose a new active learning paradigm which re- <lb/> duces not only how many instances the annotator must <lb/> label, but also how difficult each instance is to annotate. <lb/> The system leverages information from partially cor- <lb/> rect predictions to efficiently solicit annotations from <lb/> the user. We validate this active learning framework in <lb/> an interactive information extraction system, reducing <lb/> the total number of annotation actions by 22%. <lb/></div>
		<div type="intro">Introduction <lb/></div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>