<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1094"/> 
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en"> 
	<front> 
		<note type="submission">Confidential:  not for distribution. Submitted to IOP Publishing for peer review </note>
        <date type="submission">17 December 2009<lb/></date>

		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Thin-film Magneto-Inductive Cables<lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle> 
		 
		<byline><docAuthor>by<lb/> R.R.A.Syms  *  , L.Solymar, I.R.Young and T.Floume<lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		 
		<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Magneto-inductive cables for low (ca 100 MHz) radio frequencies are demonstrated in<lb/> thin-film form. 20 cm long resonant elements are formed using double-sided patterning of<lb/>  copper-clad polyimide, based on single-turn inductors and parallel plate capacitors that<lb/> use the substrate as an interlayer dielectric. Continuous cables are formed by overlaying<lb/> elements, in an arrangement that allows a high, positive coupling coefficient (κ > 0.6) to<lb/> be achieved despite the use of a planar geometry. Equivalent circuit parameters are<lb/> extracted from experiments on integrated coupling transducers, and propagation<lb/> characteristics are compared with simple theory. Low propagation loss (4 dB/m at 55<lb/> MHz, falling to 2.3 dB/m at 130 MHz) is demonstrated near the operating frequencies of<lb/> magnetic resonance imaging, for a potential application as patient-safe cable in internal<lb/> imaging.<lb/></div>
		
		<keywords>KEYWORDS<lb/> Metamaterial, periodic structure, magneto-inductive wave<lb/></keywords>
		
		<keywords type="pacs">PACS numbers<lb/> 41.20.-q<lb/> Applied classical electromagnetism<lb/> 81.05.Zx<lb/> New materials: theory, design and fabrication<lb/> 84.30.Bv<lb/> Circuit theory<lb/></keywords>
		
		<byline><affiliation>Optical and Semiconductor Devices Group, EEE Dept., Imperial College London,<lb/></affiliation></byline>
        <address>Exhibition Road, London SW7 2AZ, UK<lb/></address>
		
		<note type="other">Corresponding Author: </note> <phone>TEL +44-207-594-6203 FAX +44-207-594-6308</phone> <email>Email<lb/> r.syms@imperial.ac.uk<lb/></email>
 
		<introduction>1.<lb/> Introduction<lb/></introduction>
		
    </front>
</text>
</tei>                              