<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="603"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">1 FEATURE SUBSET SELECTION USING A <lb/>GENETIC ALGORITHM <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Jihoon Yang and Vasant Honavar <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<byline><affiliation>Artificial Intelligence Research Group <lb/>Department of Computer Science <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>226 Atanasoff Hall <lb/></address>
		<byline><affiliation>Iowa State University <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>Ames, IA 50011 <lb/>U.S.A. <lb/></address>
		<email>{yang|honavar}@cs.iastate.edu <lb/></email>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract: Practical pattern classification and knowledge discovery problems require selection of a <lb/>subset of attributes or features (from a much larger set) to represent the patterns to be classified. <lb/>This is due to the fact that the performance of the classifier (usually induced by some learning <lb/>algorithm) and the cost of classification are sensitive to the choice of the features used to construct <lb/>the classifier. Exhaustive evaluation of possible feature subsets is usually infeasible in practice because <lb/>of the large amount of computational effort required. Genetic algorithms, which belong to a class of <lb/>randomized heuristic search techniques, offer an attractive approach to find near-optimal solutions <lb/>to such optimization problems. This paper presents an approach to feature subset selection using a <lb/>genetic algorithm. Some advantages of this approach include the ability to accommodate multiple <lb/>criteria such as accuracy and cost of classification into the feature selection process and to find feature <lb/>subsets that perform well for particular choices of the inductive learning algorithm used to construct <lb/>the pattern classifier. Our experiments with several benchmark real-world pattern classification <lb/>problems demonstrate the feasibility of this approach to feature subset selection in the automated <lb/>design of neural networks for pattern classification and knowledge discovery. <lb/></div>
		<div type="intro">1.1 INTRODUCTION</div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>