<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="13"/>
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">A Neural Network Pole Balancer <lb/>that Learns and Operates on a Real Robot in Real Time <lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<byline><docAuthor>Dean Hougen John Fischer Deva Johnam <lb/></docAuthor></byline>
		<email>hougen@cs.umn.edu</email> <email>jfischer@cs.umn.edu</email> <email> johnam@cs.umn.edu <lb/></email>
		<byline><affiliation>Artificial Intelligence, Robotics, and Vision Laboratory <lb/> Department of Computer and Information Sciences <lb/> University of Minnesota <lb/></affiliation></byline>
		<address>4-192 Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Building <lb/>200 Union St. SE, Minneapolis, MN 55455 <lb/></address>
		<div type="abstract">Abstract <lb/>A neural network approach to the classic <lb/>inverted pendulum task is presented. This task is the <lb/>task of keeping a rigid pole, hinged to a cart and free <lb/>to fall in a plane, in a roughly vertical orientation by <lb/>moving the cart horizontally in the plane while keeping the cart within some maximum distance of its <lb/>starting position. This task constitutes a difficult control problem if the parameters of the cart-pole system <lb/>are not known precisely or are variable. It also forms <lb/>the basis of an even more complex control-learning <lb/>problem if the controller must learn the proper actions <lb/>for successfully balancing the pole given only the current state of the system and a failure signal when the <lb/>pole angle from the vertical becomes too great or the <lb/>cart exceeds one of the boundaries placed on its position. <lb/>The approach presented is demonstrated to <lb/>be effective for the real-time control of a small, self-contained mini-robot, specially outfitted for the task. <lb/>Origins and details of the learning scheme, specifics <lb/>of the mini-robot hardware, and results of actual <lb/>learning trials are presented. <lb/></div>
		<div type="intro">1 Introduction</div>
		</front>
</text>
</tei>