<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1115"/>  
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en"> 
	<front>    
		<note type="submission">Confidential:  not for distribution. Submitted to IOP Publishing for peer review </note>
        <date type="submission">28 April 2010<lb/></date>
    
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Optically  stimulated phosphorescence in quartz over the<lb/> millisecond to second time scale: insights into the role of<lb/> shallow traps in delaying luminescent recombination<lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle> 
		
		<byline><docAuthor>C. Ankjaergaard  *  , M. Jain<lb/> </docAuthor></byline>
		
		<byline><affiliation>Radiation Research Division, Risø National Laboratory for Sustainable Energy <lb/>Technical University of Denmark,</affiliation></byline> 
		<address>DK-4000 Roskilde, Denmark.<lb/></address>  
				
		<note>*Corresponding author; </note>
		
		<email>email: christina.ankjaergaard@gmail.com; </email>
		<phone>Telephone: +45<lb/>  4677 4920<lb/></phone>
		
		<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Time-resolved OSL curves from quartz are usually measured over a few hundred ¬µs<lb/> because this time range best illustrates the main component in quartz which lies in the<lb/> range of 30-45 ¬µs. In this study we present the decay form of quartz time-resolved<lb/> optically stimulated luminescence (TR-OSL) and optically stimulated<lb/> phosphorescence (OSP) covering over 8 orders of magnitude from 50 ns to ~8 s. A<lb/> detailed characterisation of the previously unstudied slowly decaying signals (ms-s<lb/> time scales) is undertaken to understand the origin of these components and the role<lb/> of re-trapping following optical stimulation. We present preheat and stimulation<lb/> temperature dependence for both the TR-OSL and OSP curves in these time ranges<lb/> and use the latter data to determine the E and s values for the participating shallow<lb/> traps. We observe an abnormal decay behaviour seen as a sudden increase in the<lb/> decay rate (a 'kink') conspicuous at about 2 – 3 s in the OSP curves measured at 75<lb/> and 100°C. We satisfactorily reproduce this behaviour with a numerically solved<lb/> kinetic model consisting of 4 energy levels. The physical interpretation of the kinetic<lb/> rate equations is discussed in terms a three trap – one centre model or a one trap – two<lb/> centres model involving localised charge transfer.<lb/></div>  	
		
		<keywords>  KEYWORDS<lb/>Quartz,  Optically Stimulated Luminescence (OSL), Time-Resolved OSL (TR-OSL),<lb/> Optically Stimulated Phosphorescence (OSP), Delayed OSL (DOSL), Photo-<lb/> Transferred Thermoluminescence (PTTL), 110  o  C TL trap, kinetic model<lb/></keywords>
		
		<introduction>1.  INTRODUCTION<lb/></introduction>
		
    </front>
</text>
</tei>                              