<tei>
	<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc xml:id="1112"/>  
	</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en"> 
	<front>        
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart type="main">Numerical  simulation and PIV experimental analysis of<lb/>
 electrohydrodynamic plumes induced by a blade electrode.<lb/></titlePart>
		</docTitle> 
		
		<byline><docAuthor>Ph Traoré<lb/> </docAuthor></byline>
		
		<byline><affiliation>Laboratoire d'Etudes Aérodynamiques<lb/> </affiliation></byline> 
		<address>Boulevard Pierre et Marie Curie, BP 30179, <lb/> 86962 Futuroscope-Chasseneuil, France<lb/></address>  
		
		<email>philippe.traore@univ-poitiers.fr</email>
		
		<byline><docAuthor>M Daaboul<lb/> </docAuthor></byline>
		
		<byline><affiliation>Laboratoire d'Etudes Aérodynamiques<lb/> </affiliation></byline> 
		<address>Boulevard Pierre et Marie Curie, BP 30179, <lb/> 86962 Futuroscope-Chasseneuil, France<lb/></address>  
		
		<byline><docAuthor>Ch Louste<lb/> </docAuthor></byline>
		
		<byline><affiliation>Laboratoire d'Etudes Aérodynamiques<lb/> </affiliation></byline> 
		<address>Boulevard Pierre et Marie Curie, BP 30179, <lb/> 86962 Futuroscope-Chasseneuil, France<lb/></address>  
		
		<note type="submission">Received </note><date type="submission">2 December 2003 ;</date> <note type="submission">received in revised form 9 July 2004; accepted 9 September 2004<lb/></note>

		<keywords>KEYWORDS<lb/> Multivariate;<lb/> Mean equality;<lb/> Two-group design;<lb/>  Robust estimation;<lb/> Covariance<lb/> heterogeneity<lb/></keywords>
		
		<div type="abstract">Abstract. In this paper, a comparative study between numerical and experimental results from<lb/> PIV measurements is presented in the case of two-dimensional electrohydrodynamic plumes that<lb/> arise when a sharp metallic blade, submerged in non conducting liquids, supports high electric<lb/> potential. Experiments and numerical simulations have been conducted in order to confront the<lb/> both approaches. A very good agreement has been found through velocity profiles and velocity<lb/> fields which testifies the relevance of our numerical model. For high potentials the jet flow<lb/> issued<lb/> forth from the blade becomes unsteady and starts to flap on the vertical wall. Some captions of the<lb/> temporal evolution of the isocontours of charge density which is not accessible from experiment are presented thanks to the numerical simulation.<lb/></div>  	
				
		<introduction>1. Introduction<lb/></introduction>
		
    </front>
</text>
</tei>                              