<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ims"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Intrinsic Motivation Systems for Autonomous<lb/> Mental Development<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Pierre-Yves Oudeyer, Frédéric Kaplan, Verena V. Hafner<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Sony Computer Science Lab,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Paris<lb/> 6 rue Amyot 75005 Paris<lb/></address>

	<email>{oudeyer, kaplan, hafner}@csl.sony.fr<lb/></email>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.csl.sony.fr</ptr>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Exploratory activities seem to be intrinsically rewarding for children<lb/> and crucial for their cognitive development. Can a machine be endowed<lb/> with such an intrinsic motivation system? This is the question we study<lb/> in this paper, presenting a number of computational systems that try to<lb/> capture this drive towards novel or curious situations. After discussing<lb/> related research coming from developmental psychology, neuroscience, de-<lb/>velopmental robotics and active learning, this article presents the mech-<lb/>anism of Intelligent Adaptive Curiosity, an intrinsic motivation system<lb/> which pushes a robot towards situations in which it maximizes its learning<lb/> progress. This drive makes the robot focus on situations which are neither 1<lb/> too predictable nor too unpredictable thus permitting autonomous mental<lb/> development. The complexity of the robot&apos;s activities autonomously in-<lb/>creases and complex developmental sequences self-organize without being<lb/> constructed in a supervised manner. Two experiments are presented illus-<lb/>trating the stage-like organization emerging with this mechanism. In one<lb/> of them, a physical robot is placed on a baby play mat with objects that<lb/> it can learn to manipulate. Experimental results show that the robot first<lb/> spends time in situations which are easy to learn, then shifts its attention<lb/> progressively to situations of increasing di±culty, avoiding situations in<lb/> which nothing can be learnt. Finally, these various results are discussed<lb/> in relation to more complex forms of behavioural organization and data<lb/> coming from developmental psychology.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>intrinsic motivation, curiosity, values, development, learn-<lb/>ing, autonomy, epigenetic robotics, behaviour, developmental trajectory,<lb/> complexity, active learning.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
