<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j.1365-2648.2007.04529.x"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<note type="other">JAN ORIGINAL RESEARCH<lb/></note>
			
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Chinese couples' experiences during convalescence from a first heart<lb/> attack: a focus group study<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Wenru Wang, David R. Thompson, Sek Y. Chair &amp; Sheila F. Twinn<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="accepted">Accepted for publication 12 October 2007<lb/></note> 
	
	<note type="other">Correspondence to W. Wang:<lb/></note>

	<email>e-mail: sxxawwr@cuhk.edu.hk<lb/></email>

	<byline>
		<docAuthor>Wenru Wang PhD RN<lb/> Assistant Professor<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>School of Medicine, Xi'an Jiaotong<lb/> University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Xi'an, Shannxi, China<lb/></address>

	<byline>
		<affiliation>The Nethersole School of Nursing, The<lb/> Chinese University of Hong Kong,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address> Hong<lb/> Kong, China<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>David R. Thompson PhD RN FRCN<lb/>Professor<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Health Sciences, University of<lb/> Leicester,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Leicester, UK<lb/></address>

	<byline>
		<docAuthor>Sek Y. Chair PhD RN<lb/> Associate Professor<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
		<affiliation>The Nethersole School of Nursing, The<lb/> Chinese University of Hong Kong</affiliation>,
	</byline>

	<address>Hong<lb/> Kong, China<lb/></address>

	<byline>
		<docAuthor>Sheila F. Twinn PhD RN RSCN<lb/> Professor</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
		<affiliation>The Nethersole School of Nursing, The<lb/> Chinese University of Hong Kong,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Hong<lb/> Kong, China<lb/></address>

	<reference>WANG W. , THOMPSON D. R., CHAIR S. Y. &amp; TWINN S. F. (2008)<lb/> Chinese<lb/> couples' experiences during convalescence from a first heart attack: a focus group<lb/> study. Journal of Advanced Nursing 61(3), 307–315<lb/></reference> 
	
	
	<idno>doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2648.2007.04529.x<lb/></idno> 
	
	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Title. Chinese couples' experiences during convalescence from a first heart attack: a<lb/> focus group study<lb/> Aim. This paper is a report of a study to explore Chinese patients' and partners'<lb/> experiences during early convalescence from a first heart attack.<lb/> Background. There are important socio-cultural differences between Chinese and<lb/> western populations and comparatively little is known about the experiences of<lb/> Chinese patients and partners living with a first heart attack.<lb/> Method. A qualitative study using focus groups was conducted in 2005 with 17<lb/> Chinese patients and their partners during convalescence from a first heart attack.<lb/> The interviews were tape-recorded and transcribed. Analysis was used to identify<lb/> categories using established qualitative phenomenological techniques.<lb/> Findings. Content analysis of the data revealed five major categories: enduring<lb/> uncertainty; coping with changes; experiencing emotional reactions; living with<lb/> medications and needing professional help.<lb/> Conclusion. The experiences of Chinese patients and partners during early conva-<lb/> lescence from a first heart attack are different from their western counterparts and<lb/> are affected by cultural traditions. Findings from this study may provide useful<lb/> pointers for health professionals to deliver culturally sensitive and appropriate<lb/> support and education during early convalescence.<lb/></div>

			<keyword>Keywords: Chinese, convalescence, couples' experiences, focus groups, heart<lb/> attack, nursing, patient education<lb/></keyword>

			<div type="introduction">Introduction<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
