<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="JAP0805169-CC"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Thermoelectric power studies on Nd 1.82؊x Sr x Ce 0.18 CuO y :xр0.18 superconductors<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Okram G. Singh a) and B. D. Padalia<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Powai, Bombay 400 076, India<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Om Prakash<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Metallurgical Engineering and Materials Science, Indian Institute of Technology, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Powai,<lb/> Bombay 400 076, India<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>S. K. Agarwal and A. V. Narlikar b)<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Superconductivity Group, National Physical Laboratory,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New Delhi 110012, India<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">͑Received 21 March 1996; accepted for publication 15 July 1996͒<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Thermoelectric power (S) studies on a Nd 1.82Ϫx Sr x Ce 0.18 CuO y :xр0.18 superconducting system in<lb/> the temperature range 35-250 K are reported here. In the xϭ0.09 sample, synthesized in the<lb/> reduced environment, the small magnitude of S is highly metalliclike and its sign is negative, a<lb/> characteristic of electron conduction. The sign of S for the xϭ0.18 sample shows a crossover below<lb/> 75 K from negative to positive, in apparent conflict with electronic conduction. Interestingly, after<lb/> oxygenation this sample exhibits a broadened but positive phonon draglike peak. This oxygenated<lb/> sample shows overcompensation of the carrier ͑electron͒ concentration. Critical analysis of the data<lb/> suggests that Sr doping seemingly causes a competition between electron-and holelike conduction.<lb/> The slope dS/dT is, in general, negative suggesting that the main contribution is coming from the<lb/> diffusive part. The observed thermopower features seem to fall in line with the theoretical curves of<lb/> Durczewski and Ausloos ͓Z. Phys. B 85, 59 ͑1991͒; Phys. Rev. B 53, 1762 ͑1996͔͒ based on the<lb/> inelastic scattering of quasifree electrons by phonons.</div>

	<note type="copyright">© 1996 American Institute of Physics.<lb/></note>

	͓S0021-8979͑96͒06820-X͔
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
