<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="jcp062760"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Out of the darkness and into the light: bright field in<lb/> situ hybridisation for delineation of ERBB2 (HER2)<lb/> status in breast carcinoma<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Aaron M Gruver, Ziad Peerwani, Raymond R Tubbs<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Assessment of ERBB2 (HER2) status in breast<lb/> carcinomas has become critical in determining response<lb/> to the humanised monoclonal antibody trastuzumab. The<lb/> current joint College of American Pathologists and the<lb/> American Society of Clinical Oncology guidelines for the<lb/> evaluation of HER2 status in breast carcinoma involve<lb/> testing by immunohistochemistry and fluorescence in situ<lb/> hybridisation (FISH). However, neither of these modalities<lb/> is without limitations. Novel bright field in situ<lb/> hybridisation techniques continue to provide viable<lb/> alternatives to FISH testing. While these techniques are<lb/> not limited to evaluation of the HER2 gene, the extensive<lb/> number of studies comparing bright field in situ<lb/> techniques with other methods of assessing HER2 status<lb/> allow a robust evaluation of this approach. Analysis of the<lb/> literature demonstrates that, when used to assess HER2<lb/> gene status, bright field in situ hybridisation demonstrates<lb/> excellent concordance with FISH results. The average<lb/> percentage agreement in an informal analysis of studies<lb/> comparing HER2 amplification by chromogenic in situ<lb/> hybridisation with FISH was 96% (SD 4%); k coefficients<lb/> ranged from 0.76 to 1.0. Although a much smaller<lb/> number of studies are available for review, similar levels<lb/> of concordance have been reported in studies comparing<lb/> HER2 amplification by methods employing metallography<lb/> (silver in situ hybridisation) with FISH. A summary of the<lb/> advancements in bright field in situ hybridisation, with<lb/> focus on those techniques with clinical applications of<lb/> interest to the practicing pathologist, is presented.<lb/></div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Molecular<lb/> Pathology, Pathology and<lb/> Laboratory Medicine Institute,<lb/> Cleveland Clinic, Lerner College<lb/> of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cleveland, Ohio, USA<lb/></address>

	Correspondence to<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Raymond R Tubbs,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department<lb/> of Molecular Pathology,<lb/> Pathology and Laboratory<lb/> Medicine Institute, Cleveland<lb/> Clinic, Lerner College of<lb/> Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cleveland, OH 44195,<lb/> USA;</address>

	<email>tubbsr@ccf.org<lb/></email>

	Accepted
	<date>23 November 2009<lb/></date>

	<note type="copyright">This paper is freely available<lb/> online under the BMJ Journals<lb/> unlocked scheme, see http://jcp.<lb/> bmj.com/site/about/unlocked. xhtml<lb/></note>
	
	<reference>J Clin Pathol 2010;63:210e219.</reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1136/jcp.2009.062760</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
