<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="JPS0723041-CC"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<idno>arXiv:cond-mat/0308506v1 [cond-mat.supr-con]</idno>

	<date>25 Aug 2003<lb/></date>

	Typeset with jpsj2.cls &lt;ver.1.2&gt; Letter<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Unconventional Superconductivity and Nearly Ferromagnetic Spin Fluctuations in<lb/> Na x CoO 2 • yH 2 O<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>K. Ishida 1 * , Y. Ihara 1 Y. Maeno 1 C. Michioka 2 M. Kato 2 K. Yoshimura 2 K. Takada 3 T. Sasaki 3 H.<lb/> Sakurai 4 and E. Takayama-Muromachi 5<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Physics, Graduate School of Science, Kyoto University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kyoto 606-8502, Japan,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Chemistry, Graduate School of Science, Kyoto University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kyoto 606-8502, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Advanced Materials Laboratory, National Institute for Materials Science,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1-1 Namiki, Tsukuba, Ibaraki, 305-0044, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Superconducting Materials Center, National Institute for Materials Science,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1-1 Namiki, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-0044, Japan.<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Co NQR studies were performed in recently discovered superconductor NaxCoO2•yH2O to<lb/> investigate physical properties in the superconducting (SC) and normal states. Two samples<lb/> from the same NaxCoO2 were examined, SC bilayer-hydrate sample with Tc ∼ 4.7 K and<lb/> non-SC monolayer-hydrate sample. From the measurement of nuclear-spin lattice relaxation<lb/> rate 1/T1 in the SC sample, it was found that the coherence peak is absent just below Tc and<lb/> that 1/T1 is proportional to temperature far below Tc. These results, which are in qualitatively<lb/> agreement with the previous result by Fujimoto et al., suggest strongly that unconventional<lb/> superconductivity is realized in this compound. In the normal state, 1/T1T of the SC sample<lb/> shows gradual increase below 100K down to Tc, whereas 1/T1T of the non-SC sample shows the<lb/> Korringa behavior in this temperature range. From the comparison between 1/T1T and χ bulk in<lb/> the SC sample, the increase of 1/T1T is attributed to nearly ferromagnetic fluctuations. These<lb/> remarkable findings suggest that the SC sample possesses nearly ferromagnetic fluctuations,<lb/> which are possibly related with the unconventional superconductivity in this compound. The<lb/> implication of this finding is discussed.<lb/></div>

	KEYWORDS:
	<keyword>superconductivity, hydrous sodium cobalt oxide, NQR, spin fluctuations<lb/></keyword>

	* E-mail address:
	<email>kishida@scphys.kyoto-u.ac.jp</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
