<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="L092157004-CC"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<idno>arXiv:cond-mat/0306659v2 [cond-mat.str-el]</idno>

	<date>17 Oct 2003<lb/></date>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Thermodynamic and Transport Measurements on Superconducting Na x CoO 2 • yH 2 O<lb/> Single Crystals Prepared by Electrochemical De-intercalation<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>F.C. Chou, 1 J.H. Cho, 2 † P.A. Lee, 1,2 E.T. Abel, 1,2 , K. Matan, 1,2 and Y.S. Lee 1,2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Center for Materials Science and Engineering, Massachusetts Institute of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Physics, Massachusetts Institute of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139<lb/></address>

	(Dated:
	<date>November 3, 2018</date>
	)<lb/>

	<div type="abstract">Superconducting single crystal samples of NaxCoO2 • yH2O have been produced using an elec-<lb/>trochemical technique which dispenses with the usual bromine chemical de-intercalation step and<lb/> permits much more precise control of the Na content. After careful hydration, nearly single-phase<lb/> crystals have been obtained in which over 90% of the sample&apos;s volume corresponds to the supercon-<lb/>ducting Na0.3CoO2 • 1.3H2O structure. Susceptibility and specific heat measurements confirm that<lb/> bulk superconductivity has been achieved. The extracted normal state density of states indicates<lb/> Fermi-liquid behavior with strong mass enhancement and a modest Wilson ratio. Measurements of<lb/> Hc2 for H c and H ab reveal significant anisotropy. The estimated value of Hc2 for H c yields<lb/> a coherence length of ∼ 100Å, consistent with an extremely narrow bandwidth.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>PACS numbers: PACS numbers: 74.70.-b, 74.62.Bf, 74.25.Bt, 74.25.Fy<lb/></keyword>

	† Permanent address:
	<byline>
	<affiliation>RCDAMP and Department of<lb/> Physics, Pusan National University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Pusan 609-735, Ko-rea</address>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
