<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="Mori_et_al_Bone"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>DU145 human prostate cancer cells express functional Receptor Activator of NF-κ κ κ<lb/> κB:<lb/> New insights in the prostate cancer bone metastasis process.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mori K. 1, 2, * , Le Goff B. 1, 2 , Charrier C. 1, 2 , Battaglia S. 1, 2 , Heymann D. 1, 2,* , Rédini F. 1, 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1. INSERM, ERI 7, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nantes, F-44035 France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2. Université de Nantes, Nantes atlantique universités, Laboratoire de Physiopathologie de la<lb/> Résorption Osseuse et Thérapie des Tumeurs Osseuses Primitives, EA3822, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Nantes, F-44035 France<lb/></address>

	Correspondence and reprint request to:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dr. D. HEYMANN or Dr K. MORI</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Université de Nantes EA 3822 ; INSERM ERI 7,<lb/> Physiopathologie de la Résorption Osseuse et Thérapie des Tumeurs Osseuses Primitives.<lb/> Faculté de Médecine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1 rue Gaston Veil, 44035, Nantes cedex 1, France<lb/></address>

	Tel: <phone>+33 2 40 41 28 45</phone><lb/> 
	Fax: +33 2 40 41 28 60<lb/> 
	e-mail:
	<email>dominique.heymann@univ-nantes.fr</email> or <email>kanchi@belle.shiga-med.ac.jp</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Prostate cancer metastases to bone are observed in around 80% of prostate cancer patients and<lb/> represent the most critical complication of advanced prostate cancer, frequently resulting in<lb/> significant morbidity and mortality. As the underlying mechanisms are not fully characterized,<lb/> understanding the biological mechanisms that govern prostate cancer metastases to bone at the<lb/> molecular level should lead to the determination of new potential therapeutic targets. Receptor<lb/> Activator of NF-κB ligand (RANKL)/RANK/Osteoprotegerin (OPG) are the key regulators of<lb/> bone metabolism both in normal and pathological condition, including prostate cancer bone<lb/> metastases. In the present study, we demonstrated that human prostate cancer cell lines, DU145<lb/> and PC3 express biologically functional RANK. Indeed, soluble human RANKL (shRANKL,<lb/> 100ng/ml) treatment induced ERK 1/2, p38 and IκB phosphorylations in these cells. shRANKL<lb/> administration also promoted DU145 and PC3 prostate cancer cell invasion in vitro. Whereas<lb/> human OPG (hOPG) administration alone (100ng/ml) had no marked effect, combined<lb/> association of both agents abolished the RANKL-induced DU145 cell invasion. As RANKL<lb/> had no direct effect on DU145 cell proliferation, the observed effects were indeed related to<lb/> RANKL-induced cell migration. DU145 human prostate cancer cells promoted<lb/> osteoclastogenesis of osteoclast precursors generated from mouse bone marrow. Moreover,<lb/> DU145 cells produced soluble factor(s) that up-regulate the proliferation of MC3T3-E1<lb/> pre-osteoblasts through the activation of the ERK 1/2 and STAT3 signal transduction pathways.<lb/> This stimulation of pre-osteoblast proliferation resulted in an increased local RANKL<lb/> expression that can activate both osteoclast/osteoclast precursors and prostate cancer cells, thus<lb/> facilitating prostate cancer metastasis development in bone. We confirm that RANKL is a<lb/> factor that facilitates metastasis to bone by acting as an activator of both osteoclasts and<lb/> RANK-positive prostate cancer cells in our model. Furthermore, the present study provides the<lb/> evidence that blocking RANKL-RANK interaction offer new therapeutic approach not only at<lb/> the level of bone resorbing cells, but also by interfering with RANK-positive prostate cancer<lb/> cells in the prostate cancer bone metastasis development.<lb/></div>

	Key words:
	<keyword>RANK, RANKL, prostate cancer, migration, bone metastasis</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
