<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="nihms326588"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">NIH Public Access<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Author Manuscript<lb/> Forum Health Econ Policy. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2012 January 4.<lb/> Published in final edited form as:<lb/> </note>

	<reference>Forum Health Econ Policy. 2010 ; 13(2): .</reference>

	<idno>doi:10.2202/1558-9544.1204.<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The Effect of Massachusetts&apos; Health Reform on Employer-<lb/>Sponsored Insurance Premiums *<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>John F. Cogan * , R. Glenn Hubbard † , and Daniel Kessler ‡<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>* Stanford University, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>cogan@stanford.edu</email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>† Graduate School of Business of Columbia University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>rgh1@columbia.edu<lb/></email>

	<note type="other">NIH-PA Author Manuscript</note> 
		
	<byline>
	<affiliation>‡ Stanford University, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>fkessler@stanford.edu<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> In this paper, we use publicly available data from the Medical Expenditure Panel Survey -<lb/>Insurance Component (MEPS-IC) to investigate the effect of Massachusetts&apos; health reform plan on<lb/> employer-sponsored insurance premiums. We tabulate premium growth for private-sector<lb/> employers in Massachusetts and the United States as a whole for 2004 – 2008. We estimate the<lb/> effect of the plan as the difference in premium growth between Massachusetts and the United<lb/> States between 2006 and 2008—that is, before versus after the plan—over and above the<lb/> difference in premium growth for 2004 to 2006. We find that health reform in Massachusetts<lb/> increased single-coverage employer-sponsored insurance premiums by about 6 percent, or $262.<lb/> Although our research design has important limitations, it does suggest that policy makers should<lb/> be concerned about the consequences of health reform for the cost of private insurance.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Keywords<lb/> health reform<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="other">NIH-PA Author Manuscript<lb/> * John F. Cogan is the Leonard and Shirley Ely Senior Fellow at the Hoover Institution at Stanford University; R. Glenn Hubbard is<lb/> Dean and Russell L. Carson Professor of Finance and Economics (Graduate School of Business) and Professor of Economics at<lb/> Columbia University and Research Associate at the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER); and Daniel Kessler is Professor<lb/> (Graduate School of Business and Law School) and Senior Fellow (Hoover Institution) at Stanford University and Research Associate<lb/> at NBER. Kessler gratefully acknowledges funding from the National Institutes on Aging through the NBER. All errors or<lb/> misstatements are our own.<lb/></note>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2010 The Berkeley Electronic Press. All rights reserved.</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
