<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="onc1292"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Outcomes of Research Biopsies in Phase I Clinical Trials:<lb/> The MD Anderson Cancer Center Experience<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>HAZEM EL-OSTA, a DAVID HONG, a JENNIFER WHELER, a SIQING FU, a AUNG NAING, a GERALD FALCHOOK, a<lb/> MARSHALL HICKS, b SIJIN WEN, c APOSTOLIA M. TSIMBERIDOU, a RAZELLE KURZROCK a<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Departments of a Investigational Cancer Therapeutics (Phase I Clinical Trials Program), b Diagnostic Imaging,<lb/> and c Biostatistics, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Houston, Texas, USA<lb/></address>

	Key Words. 
	<keyword>Drug development • Mandatory biopsy • Optional biopsy • Phase I clinical trial • Research biopsy<lb/></keyword>

	Disclosures: Hazem El-Osta: None; David Hong: None; Jennifer Wheler: None; Siqing Fu: None; Aung Naing: Research<lb/> 

	<note type="funding">funding/contracted research: National Institutes of Health; Gerald Falchook: None; Marshall Hicks: None; Sijin Wen: None;<lb/> Apostolia M. Tsimberidou: None; Razelle Kurzrock: None.<lb/></note>

	The content of this article has been reviewed by independent peer reviewers to ensure that it is balanced, objective, and free from<lb/> commercial bias. No financial relationships relevant to the content of this article have been disclosed by the independent peer<lb/> reviewers. 

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background. Research biopsies are crucial for exploring<lb/> the impact of novel agents on putative targets. The cur-<lb/>rent study assesses the safety and success rate associated<lb/> with performing such biopsies.<lb/> Methods. We reviewed the medical records of 155 con-<lb/>secutive patients who had one or more research biopsies as<lb/> part of a phase I trial from September 2004 to October 2009.<lb/> Results. Of 281 research biopsies performed, 118 were<lb/> paired before and after treatment biopsies (total ‫؍‬ 236 bi-<lb/>opsies). The most common sites of biopsy were superficial<lb/> lymph node (19.9%), followed by liver (16.4%), and then<lb/> soft tissue (15.7%). Ultrasound-guided biopsies were the<lb/> most frequent type (53.7%). Among 142 patients who con-<lb/>sented for mandatory biopsy, 86.6% had the biopsy per-<lb/>formed, compared with 4.4% of 911 patients offered a<lb/> biopsy on an optional basis (p &lt; .0001). Biopsy was ob-<lb/>tained most frequently on industry-sponsored trials; lack<lb/> of funding on nonindustry trials was the most common<lb/> reason that biopsies were not obtained. Of 281 single biop-<lb/>sies, only 4 (1.4%) had complications: pneumothorax re-<lb/>quiring chest tube placement (n ‫؍‬ 2), infection requiring<lb/> admission (n ‫؍‬ 1), and arrhythmia with hypotension (n ‫؍‬<lb/> 1). All but one biopsy was successful in obtaining tissue.<lb/> No deaths were attributable to biopsy.<lb/> Conclusions. Our experience demonstrates that re-<lb/>search biopsies in early phase clinical trials are safe<lb/> (1.4% risk of serious complications), and a higher per-<lb/>centage of patients underwent mandatory biopsies<lb/> (86.6%) compared with that of the patients with op-<lb/>tional biopsies (4.4%).</div>

	<reference>The Oncologist 2011;16:1292-1298</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
