<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="p020-dutot"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Bi-criteria Algorithm for Scheduling Jobs on Cluster<lb/> Platforms<lb/> *<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Pierre-François Dutot<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>ID-IMAG<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>51 avenue Jean Kuntzmann<lb/> 38330 Montbonnot Saint-Martin, France<lb/></address>

	<email>pfdutot@imag.fr<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Lionel Eyraud<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>ID-IMAG<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>51 avenue Jean Kuntzmann<lb/> 38330 Montbonnot Saint-Martin, France<lb/></address>
	
	<email>Lionel.Eyraud@imag.fr<lb/></email> 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Grégory Mounié<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>ID-IMAG<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>51 avenue Jean Kuntzmann<lb/> 38330 Montbonnot Saint-Martin, France<lb/></address>
	
	<email>Gregory.Mounie@imag.fr<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Denis Trystram<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>ID-IMAG<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>51 avenue Jean Kuntzmann<lb/> 38330 Montbonnot Saint-Martin, France<lb/></address>

	<email>Denis.Trystram@imag.fr<lb/></email>

	ABSTRACT<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">We describe in this paper a new method for building an<lb/> efficient algorithm for scheduling jobs in a cluster. Jobs are<lb/> considered as parallel tasks (PT) which can be scheduled on<lb/> any number of processors. The main feature is to consider<lb/> two criteria that are optimized together. These criteria are<lb/> the makespan and the weighted minimal average completion<lb/> time (minsum). They are chosen for their complementarity,<lb/> to be able to represent both user-oriented objectives and<lb/> system administrator objectives.<lb/> We propose an algorithm based on a batch policy with<lb/> increasing batch sizes, with a smart selection of jobs in each<lb/> batch. This algorithm is assessed by intensive simulation<lb/> results, compared to a new lower bound (obtained by a re-<lb/>laxation of ILP) of the optimal schedules for both criteria<lb/> separately. It is currently implemented in an actual real-size<lb/> cluster platform.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Categories and Subject Descriptors<lb/> F.2.2 [Analysis of Algorithms and Problem Complex-<lb/>ity]: Nonnumerical Algorithms and Problems-Sequencing<lb/> and scheduling; D.4.1 [Operating Systems]: Process man-<lb/>agement-Scheduling, Concurrency<lb/> General Terms<lb/> Algorithms, Management<lb/></keyword>

	* Authors are members of the <note type="group">APACHE project</note> 
	<note type="funding">supported<lb/> by CNRS, INPG, INRIA, UJF<lb/></note>

	Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for<lb/> personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are<lb/> not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies<lb/> bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to<lb/> republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific<lb/> permission and/or a fee.<lb/>

	<meeting>SPAA&apos;04, June 27-30, 2004, Barcelona, Spain.<lb/></meeting>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright 2004 ACM</note> 

	1-58113-840-7/04/0006 ...$5.00.<lb/>

	Keywords<lb/> 
	<keyword>Parallel Computing, Algorithms, Scheduling, Parallel Tasks,<lb/> Moldable Tasks, Bi-criteria</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
