<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="paph-29-826"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Language and iconic gesture use in procedural discourse by speakers<lb/> with aphasia<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Madeleine Pritchard a *, Lucy Dipper a , Gary Morgan a and Naomi Cocks b<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Division of Language and Communication Science, City University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>London, UK;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b School of<lb/> Psychology and Speech Pathology, Curtin University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Perth, Australia<lb/></address>

	(
	<note type="submission">Received 16 April 2014; accepted 28 November 2014</note>
	)<lb/>

	<div type="abstract">Background: Conveying instructions is an everyday use of language, and gestures are<lb/> likely to be a key feature of this. Although co-speech iconic gestures are tightly<lb/> integrated with language, and people with aphasia (PWA) produce procedural dis-<lb/>courses impaired at a linguistic level, no previous studies have investigated how PWA<lb/> use co-speech iconic gestures in these contexts.<lb/> Aims: This study investigated how PWA communicated meaning using gesture and<lb/> language in procedural discourses, compared with neurologically healthy people<lb/> (NHP). We aimed to identify the relative relationship of gesture and speech, in the<lb/> context of impaired language, both overall and in individual events.<lb/> Methods &amp; Procedures: Twenty-nine PWA and 29 NHP produced two procedural<lb/> discourses. The structure and semantic content of language of the whole discourses were<lb/> analysed through predicate argument structure and spatial motor terms, and gestures were<lb/> analysed for frequency and semantic form. Gesture and language were analysed in two key<lb/> events, to determine the relative information presented in each modality.<lb/> Outcomes &amp; Results: PWA and NHP used similar frequencies and forms of gestures,<lb/> although PWA used syntactically simpler language and fewer spatial words. This<lb/> meant, overall, relatively more information was present in PWA gesture. This finding<lb/> was also reflected in the key events, where PWA used gestures conveying rich<lb/> semantic information alongside semantically impoverished language more often than<lb/> NHP.<lb/> Conclusions: PWA gestures, containing semantic information omitted from the con-<lb/>current speech, may help listeners with meaning when language is impaired. This<lb/> finding indicates gesture should be included in clinical assessments of meaning-<lb/>making.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>aphasia; iconic gesture; procedural discourse; discourse; semantic weight<lb/></keyword>

	*Corresponding author. Email:
	<email>madeleine.pritchard.1@city.ac.uk<lb/></email>

	<reference>Aphasiology, 2015<lb/> Vol. 29, No. 7, 826-844, </reference>

	<idno>http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/02687038.2014.993912</idno><lb/>

	<note type="copyright">© 2014 The Author(s). Published by Taylor &amp; Francis.<lb/> This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives<lb/> License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduc-<lb/>tion in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, and is not altered, transformed, or built upon in any way.</note>
	
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
