<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PatternV12014"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Accurate 3D Action Recognition using Learning on the<lb/> Grassmann Manifold<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Rim Slama a,b , Hazem Wannous a,b , Mohamed Daoudi b,c , Anuj Srivastava d</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a<lb/> University Lille</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1, Villeneuve d&apos;Ascq, France</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b<lb/> LIFL Laboratory / UMR CNRS 8022,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Villeneuve d&apos;Ascq, France</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c<lb/> Institut Mines-Telecom / Telecom Lille,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Villeneuve d&apos;Ascq, France</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>d<lb/> Florida State University, Departement of Statistics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Tallahassee, USA</address>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">In this paper we address the problem of modelling and analyzing hu-<lb/>man motion by focusing on 3D body skeletons. Particularly, our intent is<lb/> to represent skeletal motion in a geometric and e cient way, leading to an<lb/> accurate action-recognition system. Here an action is represented by a dy-<lb/>namical system whose observability matrix is characterized as an element<lb/> of a Grassmann manifold. To formulate our learning algorithm, we pro-<lb/>pose two distinct ideas: (1) In the first one we perform classification using<lb/> a Truncated Wrapped Gaussian model, one for each class in its own tangent<lb/> space. (2) In the second one we propose a novel learning algorithm that<lb/> uses a vector representation formed by concatenating local coordinates in<lb/> tangent spaces associated with di↵erent classes and training a linear SVM.<lb/> We evaluate our approaches on three public 3D action datasets: MSR-action<lb/> 3D, UT-kinect and UCF-kinect datasets; these datasets represent di↵erent<lb/></div>

	Email addresses:

	<email>rim.slama@telecom-lille.fr</email>
	(Rim Slama),<lb/>

	<email>hazem.wannous@telecom-lille.fr</email>
	(Hazem Wannous),<lb/>

	<email>mohamed.daoudi@telecom-lille.fr</email>
	(Mohamed Daoudi),

	<email>anuj@stat.fsu.edu</email>
	(Anuj<lb/> Srivastava)<lb/>

	<note type="submission">Preprint submitted to Pattern Recognition<lb/> </note>

	<date>August 14, 2014<lb/></date>

	<div type="abstract">kinds of challenges and together help provide an exhaustive evaluation. The<lb/> results show that our approaches either match or exceed state-of-the-art per-<lb/>formance reaching 91.21% on MSR-action 3D, 97.91% on UCF-kinect, and<lb/> 88.5% on UT-kinect. Finally, we evaluate the latency, i.e. the ability to<lb/> recognize an action before its termination, of our approach and demonstrate<lb/> improvements relative to other published approaches.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>Human action recognition, Grassmann manifold, observational<lb/> latency, depth images, skeleton, classification.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
