<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="pgen.1002065"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Nuclear cGMP-Dependent Kinase Regulates Gene<lb/> Expression via Activity-Dependent Recruitment of a<lb/> Conserved Histone Deacetylase Complex<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Yan Hao 1 , Ningyi Xu 1 , Andrew C. Box 1 , Laura Schaefer 1 , Kasthuri Kannan 1 , Ying Zhang 1 , Laurence<lb/> Florens 1 , Christopher Seidel 1 , Michael P. Washburn 1,2 , Winfried Wiegraebe 1 , Ho Yi Mak 1,3 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Stowers Institute for Medical Research, Kansas City, Missouri, United States of America, 2 Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, University of Kansas<lb/> Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kansas City, Kansas, United States of America, 3</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Molecular and Integrative Physiology, University of Kansas Medical Center, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kansas City,<lb/> Kansas, United States of America<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> Elevation of the second messenger cGMP by nitric oxide (NO) activates the cGMP-dependent protein kinase PKG, which is<lb/> key in regulating cardiovascular, intestinal, and neuronal functions in mammals. The NO-cGMP-PKG signaling pathway is<lb/> also a major therapeutic target for cardiovascular and male reproductive diseases. Despite widespread effects of PKG<lb/> activation, few molecular targets of PKG are known. We study how EGL-4, the Caenorhabditis elegans PKG ortholog,<lb/> modulates foraging behavior and egg-laying and seeks the downstream effectors of EGL-4 activity. Using a combination of<lb/> unbiased forward genetic screen and proteomic analysis, we have identified a conserved SAEG-1/SAEG-2/HDA-2 histone<lb/> deacetylase complex that is specifically recruited by activated nuclear EGL-4. Gene expression profiling by microarrays<lb/> revealed .40 genes that are sensitive to EGL-4 activity in a SAEG-1–dependent manner. We present evidence that EGL-4<lb/> controls egg laying via one of these genes, Y45F10C.2, which encodes a novel protein that is expressed exclusively in the<lb/> uterine epithelium. Our results indicate that, in addition to cytoplasmic functions, active EGL-4/PKG acts in the nucleus via a<lb/> conserved Class I histone deacetylase complex to regulate gene expression pertinent to behavioral and physiological<lb/> responses to cGMP. We also identify transcriptional targets of EGL-4 that carry out discrete components of the physiological<lb/> response.<lb/></div>

	<reference>Citation: Hao Y, Xu N, Box AC, Schaefer L, Kannan K, et al. (2011) Nuclear cGMP-Dependent Kinase Regulates Gene Expression via Activity-Dependent<lb/> Recruitment of a Conserved Histone Deacetylase Complex. PLoS Genet 7(5): e1002065.</reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002065<lb/></idno>

	<note type="other">Editor: Andrew D. Chisholm, University of California San Diego, United States of America<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Received December 8, 2010; Accepted March 21, 2011;</note>

	<date>Published May 5, 2011<lb/></date>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright: ß 2011 Hao et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted<lb/> use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Funding: This work was supported by the Stowers Institute for Medical Research. The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to<lb/> publish, or preparation of the manuscript.<lb/> Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.<lb/> *</note>

	<email>E-mail: hym@stowers.org<lb/></email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
