<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC3905510"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Addict &amp; Health, Summer &amp; Autumn 2010; Vol 2, No 3-4. 89<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) and<lb/> Conduct Disorder in Children of Drug Dependent Parents<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Nooshin Parvaresh MD*, Hassan Ziaaddini MD**,<lb/> Ali Kheradmand MD***, Hamidreza Bayati MD****<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>* Assistant Professor, Department of Psychiatry, Kerman Neuroscience Research Center and School of<lb/> Medicine, Kerman University of Medical Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kerman, Iran.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>** Associate Professor, Department of Psychiatry, Kerman Neuroscience Research Center, School of<lb/> Medicine, Kerman University of Medical Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kerman, Iran.<lb/></address>

	 <byline>
	<affiliation>*** Psychiatrist, Kerman Neuroscience Research Center, School of Medicine, Kerman University of<lb/> Medical Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kerman, Iran.<lb/> </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>****Psychiatrist, School of Medicine, Birjand University of Medical Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Khorasan Shomali, Iran.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: 3.4.2010<lb/> Accepted: 31.8.2010</note>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and conduct disorder are among<lb/> relatively prevalent disorders during childhood and adolescence.<lb/> Considering the negative impact of the parents&apos; drug dependency and<lb/> bipolar disorder, the present study aimed to determine the prevalence of<lb/> ADHD and conduct disorder in children of drug-dependent and bipolar<lb/> parents.<lb/> Background:<lb/> In this case-control study, the case group included two groups of<lb/> patients with drug dependency and bipolar disorder hospitalized in<lb/> Shahid Beheshti hospital in Kerman who had 7 to 11-year-old children.<lb/> The control group included healthy individuals without any drug<lb/> dependency or other psychiatric disorders. Data were collected using<lb/> Rutter scale Form A (parents&apos; form) and a demographic questionnaire.<lb/> Data were analyzed with ANOVA, Chi-square and Tamhane&apos;s post-hoc<lb/> test.<lb/> Methods:<lb/> Rutter&apos;s abnormal scores were generally 7.11% in children of drug<lb/> dependent parents, 14% in children of bipolar parents and 1.6% in children<lb/> of healthy parents demonstrating no significant difference. The frequency<lb/> of conduct disorder in the bipolar and drug dependent group was higher<lb/> than the healthy group, but the difference was not significant. The<lb/> frequency of ADHD was 8.9% in the drug dependency group and 1% in<lb/> the control group which shows a significant difference.<lb/> Findings:<lb/> Drug dependency in parents may be a leading factor to mental<lb/> disorders such as ADHD and conduct disorder in children.<lb/> Conclusion:<lb/></div>

	<keyword>ADHD, Conduct disorder, Drug dependency .<lb/></keyword>

	Key words:<lb/>
	6<lb/> 2<lb/> 0 14<lb/>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ali Kheradmand MD, Psychiatrist,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Kerman Neuroscience Research Center, School of<lb/> Medicine, Kerman University of Medical Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kerman, Iran.<lb/></address>

	Email:
	<email>dr.alikheradmand@yahoo.com<lb/></email>

	Page count:<lb/> Tables:<lb/> Figures:<lb/> References:<lb/> Address of<lb/> Correspondence:<lb/>
	
	<note type="doctype">Original Article<lb/></note>

	<reference>Journal of Addiction and Health<lb/> Vol 2, No. 3-4, Summer &amp; Autumn 2010</reference>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
