<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC3878353"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E<lb/></note>

	<note type="doctype">Open Access<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Pregnancy planning, smoking behaviour during<lb/> pregnancy, and neonatal outcome: UK<lb/> millennium cohort study<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Anika Flower 1 , Jill Shawe 2 , Judith Stephenson 2 and Pat Doyle 3*</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: Pre-pregnancy health and care are important for the health of the future generations. Smoking<lb/> during pregnancy has been well-researched and there is clear evidence of harm. But there has been little research<lb/> on the health impact of planning for pregnancy. This study aims to investigate the independent effects of<lb/> pregnancy planning and smoking during pregnancy on neonatal outcome.<lb/> Methods: This analysis made use of data from the UK Millennium Cohort Study. The study sample consisted of<lb/> 18,178 singleton babies born in UK between 2000 and 2001. The neonatal outcomes of interest were low<lb/> birthweight (&lt;2.5 Kg) and pre-term birth (&lt;37 completed weeks gestation). Logistic regression was used to estimate<lb/> the association between pregnancy planning and/or smoking and neonatal outcome. Adjusted odds ratios were<lb/> used to calculate population attributable risk fractions (PAFs).<lb/> Results: 43% of mothers did not plan their pregnancy and 34% were smoking just before and/or during<lb/> pregnancy. Planners were half as likely to be smokers just before pregnancy, and more likely to give up or reduce<lb/> the amount smoked if smokers. Unplanned pregnancies had 24% increased odds of low birth weight and<lb/> prematurity compared to planned pregnancies (AOR LBW 1.24, 95% CI 1.04-1.48; AOR PREM 1.24, 95% CI 1.05-1.45),<lb/> independent of smoking status. The odds of low birth weight for babies of mothers who were smoking just before<lb/> pregnancy was 91% higher than that of mothers who were not (AOR LBW 1.91, 95% CI 1.56-2.34). Women who quit<lb/> or reduced the amount smoked during pregnancy lowered the risk of a low birth weight baby by one third<lb/> (AOR LBW 0.66, 95% CI 0.51-0.85) compared with women whose smoking level did not change. Smaller effects were<lb/> found for prematurity. If all women planned their pregnancy and did not smoke before or during pregnancy, 30%<lb/> of low birthweight and 14% of prematurity could, in theory, be avoided.<lb/> Conclusions: Planning a pregnancy and avoiding smoking during pregnancy has clear, independent, health benefits<lb/> for babies. Quitting or reducing the amount smoked during pregnancy can reduce the risk of low birthweight.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>Pregnancy planning, Smoking, Low birthweight, Prematurity<lb/></keyword>

	* Correspondence:
	<email>Pat.doyle@lshtm.ac.uk</email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3<lb/> London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>London, England<lb/></address>

	Full list of author information is available at the end of the article<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">© 2013 Flower et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative<lb/> Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and<lb/> reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<lb/></note>

	Author details
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> King&apos;s College London, School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>London, England.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Institute for<lb/> Women&apos;s Health, University College London,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>London, England.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 London<lb/> School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>London, England.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received: 28 August 2013 Accepted: 5 November 2013<lb/></note>

	Published:
	<date>19 December 2013</date>

	0 5
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
