<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC3858645"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="doctype">HYPOTHESIS AND THEORY ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	published:
	<date>11 December 2013<lb/></date>

	<idno>doi: 10.3389/fnint.2013.00092<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Vestibular activity and cognitive development in children: perspectives<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sylvette R. Wiener-Vacher 1 , Derek A. Hamilton 2 and Sidney I. Wiener 3,4 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Vestibular and Oculomotor Evaluation Unit, Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Robert Debré Pediatric Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Paris, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Psychology, University of New Mexico,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Albuquerque, NM, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Laboratoire de Physiologie de la Perception et de l&apos; Action, UMR-7152, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique -Collège de France,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Paris, France<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Memolife Laboratory of Excellence, Paris Science and Letters University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Paris, France<lb/></address>

	Edited by:<lb/>
	<editor>Paul Smith</editor>,

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Otago<lb/> Medical School,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New Zealand<lb/></address>

	Reviewed by:<lb/>
	<editor>Cynthia Darlington</editor>,

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of<lb/> Otago, New Zealand<lb/> Paul Smith, University of Otago<lb/> Medical School,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>New Zealand<lb/></address>

	*Correspondence:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sidney I. Wiener, </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Laboratoire de<lb/> Physiologie de la Perception et de<lb/> l&apos; Action, UMR-7152, Centre National<lb/> de la Recherche Scientifique -Collège<lb/> de France,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>11 Place Marcelin<lb/> Berthelot, 75231 Paris Cedex 05,<lb/> France<lb/></address>

	e-mail:
	<email>sidney.wiener@<lb/> college-de-france.fr</email><lb/>

	<div type="abstract">Vestibular signals play an essential role in oculomotor and static and dynamic posturomotor<lb/> functions. Increasing attention is now focusing on their impact on spatial and non-spatial<lb/> cognitive functions. Movements of the head in space evoke vestibular signals that make<lb/> important contributions during the development of brain representations of body parts<lb/> relative to one another as well as representations of body orientation and position within<lb/> the environment. A central nervous system pathway relays signals from the vestibular<lb/> nuclei to the hippocampal system where this input is indispensable for neuronal responses<lb/> selective for the position and orientation of the head in space. One aspect of the<lb/> hippocampal systems&apos; processing to create episodic and contextual memories is its role in<lb/> spatial orientation and navigation behaviors that require processing of relations between<lb/> background cues.These are also impaired in adult patients with vestibular deficits. However<lb/> little is known about the impact of vestibular loss on cognitive development in children.<lb/> This is investigated here with a particular emphasis upon the hypothetical mechanisms and<lb/> potential impact of vestibular loss at critical ages on the development of respective spatial<lb/> and non-spatial cognitive processes and their brain substrates.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>ontogeny, development, vestibular, otolith, cognitive, navigation, human<lb/></keyword>

	<reference>Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience<lb/> www.frontiersin.org<lb/> December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | 1<lb/> Wiener-Vacher et al.<lb/> Vestibular activity and cognitive development<lb/></reference>
	
	<note type="submission">Received: 31 July 2013; paper pending published: 09 November 2013; accepted: 21<lb/> November 2013;</note>

	published online:
	<date>11 December 2013.<lb/></date> 

	Citation: 
	<reference>Wiener-Vacher SR, Hamilton DA and Wiener SI (2013) Vestibular activity<lb/> and cognitive development in children: perspectives. Front. Integr. Neurosci. 7:92.</reference>

	<idno>doi:<lb/> 10.3389/fnint.2013.00092<lb/></idno>

	This article was submitted to the journal Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience.<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2013 Wiener-Vacher, Hamilton and Wiener. This is an open-access<lb/> article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License<lb/> (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted,<lb/> provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original pub-<lb/>lication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No<lb/> use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these<lb/> terms.</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
