<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC3441574"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>FSH Modulates PKAI and GPR3 Activities in Mouse<lb/> Oocyte of COC in a Gap Junctional Communication (GJC)-<lb/>Dependent Manner to Initiate Meiotic Resumption<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Junxia Li . , Guankun Mao . , Guoliang Xia*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Agro-Biotechnology, College of Biological Science, China Agricultural University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Beijing, China</address>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Many studies have shown that cyclic adenosine-59-monophosphate (cAMP)-dependent protein kinase A (PKA) and G-<lb/>protein-coupled receptor 3 (GPR3) are crucial for controlling meiotic arrest in oocytes. However, it is unclear how<lb/> gonadotropins modulate these factors to regulate oocyte maturation, especially by gap junctional communication (GJC).<lb/> Using an in vitro meiosis-arrested mouse cumulus-oocyte complex (COC) culture model, we showed that there is a close<lb/> relationship between follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and the PKA type I (PKAI) and GPR3. The effect of FSH on oocyte<lb/> maturation was biphasic, initially inhibitory and then stimulatory. During FSH-induced maturation, rapid cAMP surges were<lb/> observed in both cumulus cells and oocyte. Most GJC between cumulus cells and oocyte ceased immediately after FSH<lb/> stimulation and recommenced after the cAMP surge. FSH-induced maturation was blocked by PKAI activator 8-AHA-cAMP.<lb/> Levels of PKAI regulatory subunits and GPR3 decreased and increased, respectively, after FSH stimulation. In the presence of<lb/> the GJC inhibitor carbenoxolone (CBX), FSH failed to induce the meiotic resumption and the changes in PKAI, GPR3 and<lb/> cAMP surge in oocyte were no longer detected. Furthermore, GPR3 was upregulated by high cAMP levels, but not by PKAI<lb/> activation. When applied after FSH stimulation, the specific phosphodiesterase 3A (PDE3A) inhibitor cilostamide<lb/> immediately blocked meiotic induction, regardless of when it was administered. PKAI activation inhibited mitogen-<lb/>activated protein kinase (MAPK) phosphorylation in the oocytes of COCs, which participated in the initiation of FSH-induced<lb/> meiotic maturation in vitro. Just before FSH-induced meiotic maturation, cAMP, PKAI, and GPR3 returned to basal levels, and<lb/> PDE3A activity and MAPK phosphorylation increased markedly. These experiments show that FSH induces a transient<lb/> increase in cAMP levels and regulates GJC to control PKAI and GPR3 activities, thereby creating an inhibitory phase. After<lb/> PDE3A and MAPK activities increase, meiosis resumes.<lb/></div>

	Citation:
	<reference>Li J, Mao G, Xia G (2012) FSH Modulates PKAI and GPR3 Activities in Mouse Oocyte of COC in a Gap Junctional Communication (GJC)-Dependent<lb/> Manner to Initiate Meiotic Resumption. PLoS ONE 7(9): e37835.</reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0037835<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Hongmei Wang,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>China<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received December 28, 2011; Accepted April 24, 2012;</note>

	Published
	<date>September 13, 2012<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">ß 2012 Li et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted<lb/> use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Funding: 
	<note type="funding">This work was supported by National Basic Research Program of China (No. 2012CB944401 and No. 2012CB944701). The funders had no role in study<lb/> design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.<lb/> * E-mail:
	<email>glxiachina@sohu.com<lb/></email>

	. These authors contributed equally to this work.<lb/>
	<reference>September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
