<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC4719240"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<note type="doctype">Editorial<lb/></note> 
	<note type="doctype">Case Report<lb/></note>

	<reference>Journal of Orthopaedic Case Reports 2013 April-June;3(2):32-34<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>The Incomplete Superficial Palmar Arch<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 2<lb/> Anneh Mohammad Gharravi*<lb/> Mohammad Reza<lb/> 3 2<lb/> Gholami ,Daryoush Bijan Nejad<lb/> , Saeed Azandeh ,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/> Introduction:<lb/>
	Case Report:<lb/> Conclusion:<lb/> Keywords: S<lb/>

	<div type="abstract">Superficial palmar arch (SPA) is dominant vascular structure in palm of hand. In<lb/> present study we described a case of Ulnar / Radiopalmar pattern of incomplete SPA in an Iranian<lb/> cadaver. When the SPA is complete, the superficial palmer branches of the radial artery contribute<lb/> to the ulnar artery. In incomplete type of SPA, there was no anastomosis between the ulnar and<lb/> radial arteries (UA, RA).<lb/> In the present case, the brachial artery divided into RA and UA at the cubital fossa.<lb/> There was no anastomosis between radial and ulnar arteries (RA, UA) in the palm of the hand. UA<lb/> gave three palmar digital arteries; proper palmar digital artery and two common palmar digital<lb/> arteries. RA gave proper palmar digital artery and arteria princeps pollicis.<lb/> Knowledge of anatomical variation of SPA is important for the hand surgical<lb/> interventions and this is a very rare variation which can be easily tested clinically by Allen&apos;s test<lb/> uperficial palmar arch, Ulnar artery, Radial artery<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2013 by Journal of Orthpaedic Case Reports<lb/></note> 

	<title level="j">Journal of Orthopaedic Case Reports</title> 
	|
	<idno>pISSN 2250-0685</idno> 
	
	| eISSN<lb/> | Available on www.jocr.co.in | doi:<lb/> 

	<note type="copyright">This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits<lb/> unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<lb/></note>

	2321-3817<lb/>

	<idno>10.13107/jocr.2250-0685.099<lb/></idno>

	What to Learn from this Article?<lb/>
	A rare variation of Incomplete Palmar arch?<lb/> Anatomical and Clinical review of such presentation?<lb/>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dr. Anne Mohammad Gharravi<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Author&apos;s Photo Gallery
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Shahroud, Iran.<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of anatomy, Faculty of Medicine, Ahvaz<lb/> Jundishapour University of Medical Sciences (AJUMS),<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Ahvaz, Iran<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Department of anatomy, Faculty of Medicine, Lorestan<lb/> University of Medical Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Khorram Abad, Iran<lb/></address>

	Address of Correspondence<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dr. Anneh Mohammad Gharravi<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>School of Medicine, Shahroud University of Medical<lb/> Sciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Shahroud, Iran.<lb/></address>

	E-mail:
	<email>annehgh@yahoo.com<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>School of Medicine, Shahroud University of Medical<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Dr. Saeed Azandeh<lb/> Dr. Mohammad R Gholami Dr. Darioush B Nejad<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Case Report Conclusion<lb/> Discussion References
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
