<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC4843051"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of Investigative Medicine High<lb/> Impact Case Reports<lb/> April-June 2016: 1 -6<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">© 2016 American Federation for<lb/> Medical Research<lb/></note>

	<idno>DOI: 10.1177/2324709616643990<lb/></idno>

	hic.sagepub.com<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">Creative Commons CC-BY: This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License<lb/> (http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/) which permits any use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further<lb/> permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage).<lb/></note>

	<note type="doctype">Case Report<lb/></note>

	643990H ICXXX10.1177/2324709616643990Journal of Investigative Medicine High Impact Case ReportsNguyen et al<lb/> case-report2016<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 University of California,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Davis, CA, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 VA Northern California Health Care System,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Mather, CA, USA<lb/></address>

	Corresponding Author:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Lam-Phuong Nguyen,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>DO, Department of Internal Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>4150 V<lb/> Street, Suite 3100, Sacramento, CA 95817, USA.<lb/></address>

	Email:
	<email>lptnguyen@ucdavis.edu<lb/></email>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Acute Fibrinous and Organizing<lb/> Pneumonia Associated With Allogenic<lb/> Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant<lb/> Successfully Treated With Corticosteroids:<lb/> A Two-Patient Case Series<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Lam-Phuong Nguyen, DO 1,2 , Stella Ahdoot, MD 1,2 ,<lb/> Narin Sriratanaviriyakul, MD 1,2 , Yanhong Zhang, MD 1 ,<lb/> Nicholas Stollenwerk, MD 1,2 , Michael Schivo, MD 1,2 ,<lb/> and Richart Harper, MD 1,2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Acute fibrinous and organizing pneumonia (AFOP) is an extremely rare, relatively new, and distinct histological pattern of<lb/> acute lung injury characterized predominately by the presence of intra-alveolar fibrin and associated organizing pneumonia.<lb/> AFOP may be idiopathic or associated with a wide spectrum of clinical conditions. It has a variable clinical presentation from<lb/> mild respiratory symptoms to that similar to the acute respiratory distress syndrome. Currently there is no consensus on<lb/> treatment, and corticosteroids previously were of unclear benefit. To date, there are less than 40 cases of AFOP reported in<lb/> the literature and only one has been linked to hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Here we report the first case series<lb/> of 2 patients who developed AFOP following allogenic stem cell transplant that were successfully treated with high-dose<lb/> corticosteroids.<lb/></div>

	Keywords<lb/>
	<keyword>AFOP, ARDS, allogenic stem cell transplant, BOOP, diffuse alveolar damage<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="submission">Received February 23, 2016. Received revised March 15, 2016. Accepted for publication March 16, 2016.</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
