<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC5561184"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>1<lb/></page>

	<reference>SCieNtifiC RepoRts | 7: 8622 |</reference>

	<idno>DOI:10.1038/s41598-017-09468-8<lb/></idno>

	www.nature.com/scientificreports<lb/>
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Generation and intracellular<lb/> trafficking of a polysialic acid-<lb/>carrying fragment of the neural cell<lb/> adhesion molecule NCAM to the<lb/> cell nucleus<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Nina Westphal 1 , Gabriele Loers 1 , David Lutz 1,2 , Thomas Theis 1 , Ralf Kleene 1 &amp; Melitta<lb/> Schachner 3,4<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Polysialic acid (PSA) and its major protein carrier, the neural cell adhesion molecule NCAM, play<lb/> important roles in many nervous system functions during development and in adulthood. Here, we show<lb/> that a PSA-carrying NCAM fragment is generated at the plasma membrane by matrix metalloproteases<lb/> and transferred to the cell nucleus via endosomes and the cytoplasm. Generation and nuclear import of<lb/> this fragment in cultured cerebellar neurons is induced by a function-triggering NCAM antibody and a<lb/> peptide comprising the effector domain (ED) of myristoylated alanine-rich C kinase substrate (MARCKS)<lb/> which interacts with PSA within the plane of the plasma membrane. These treatments lead to activation<lb/> of the fibroblast growth factor (FGF) receptor, phospholipase C (PLC), protein kinase C (PKC) and<lb/> phosphoinositide-3-kinase (PI3K), and subsequently to phosphorylation of MARCKS. Moreover, the<lb/> NCAM antibody triggers calmodulin-dependent activation of nitric oxide synthase, nitric oxide (NO)<lb/> production, NO-dependent S-nitrosylation of matrix metalloprotease 9 (MMP9) as well as activation<lb/> of matrix metalloprotease 2 (MMP2) and MMP9, whereas the ED peptide activates phospholipase D<lb/> (PLD) and MMP2, but not MMP9. These results indicate that the nuclear PSA-carrying NCAM fragment is<lb/> generated by distinct and functionally defined signal transducing mechanisms.</div>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1<lb/> Zentrum für Molekulare Neurobiologie, Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Falkenried 94, 20251, Hamburg,<lb/> Germany.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Institut für Strukturelle Neurobiologie, Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Falkenried 94, 20251,<lb/> Hamburg, Germany.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Center for Neuroscience, Shantou University Medical College,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>22 Xin Ling Road, Shantou,<lb/> Guangdong, 515041, China.</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>4 Keck Center for Collaborative Neuroscience and Department of Cell Biology and<lb/> Neuroscience, Rutgers University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>604 Allison Road, Piscataway, NJ, 08854, USA.</address>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ralf Kleene and Melitta Schachner<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	contributed equally to this work. Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to M.S. (email:<lb/>
	<email>schachner@stu.edu.cn</email>

	)<lb/>
	<note type="submission">Received: 25 May 2017<lb/> Accepted: 25 July 2017<lb/></note>

	Published: xx xx xxxx
	<note type="doctype">OPEN<lb/></note>

	<note type="copyright">Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International<lb/> License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or<lb/> format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this<lb/> article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the<lb/> material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the<lb/> copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.<lb/> © The Author(s) 2017</note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
