<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC5442078"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Recent advances in the management of pruritus in chronic<lb/> liver diseases<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Kazuto Tajiri, Yukihiro Shimizu<lb/> Kazuto Tajiri,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology, Toyama<lb/> University Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Toyama 939-1724, Japan<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Yukihiro Shimizu, Gastroenterology Center, Nanto Municipal<lb/> Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Toyama 939-1724, Japan<lb/></address>

	Author contributions: Tajiri K and Shimizu Y wrote this paper,<lb/> Tajiri K conducted this work.<lb/>

	Conflict-of-interest statement: Tajiri K and Shimizu Y declare<lb/> no conflict of interests for this publication.<lb/> 

	<note type="copyright">Open-Access: This article is an open-access article which was<lb/> selected by an in-house editor and fully peer-reviewed by external<lb/> reviewers. It is distributed in accordance with the Creative<lb/> Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license,<lb/> which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this<lb/> work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on<lb/> different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and<lb/> the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/<lb/> licenses/by-nc/4.0/<lb/></note> 

	Manuscript source:
	<note type="doctype">Invited manuscript<lb/></note>

	Correspondence to:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Kazuto Tajiri, MD, PhD,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of<lb/> Gastroenterology, Toyama University Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2630 Sugitani,<lb/> Toyama 939-1724, Japan.</address>

	<email>tajikazu@med.u-toyama.ac.jp<lb/></email>

	Telephone:
	<phone>+81-76-4347301</phone><lb/> 
	Fax: +81-76-4345027<lb/>

	<note type="submission">Received: January 23, 2017<lb/> Peer-review started: January 28, 2017<lb/> First decision: March 3, 2017<lb/> Revised: March 13, 2017<lb/> Accepted: May 4, 2017<lb/> Article in press: May 4, 2017<lb/></note>

	Published online:
	<date>May 21, 2017</date>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Pruritus is a symptom found in patients with chronic<lb/> liver diseases, especially cholestatic liver diseases such<lb/> as primary biliary cholangitis. This symptom impairs<lb/> patient quality of life by disturbing sleep and may lead<lb/> to consideration of liver transplantation. Mechanisms<lb/> implicated in pruritus have been associated with the<lb/> peripheral and central nervous systems, leading to<lb/> the development of various therapeutic options. Little<lb/> evidence for the efficacy of most of these treatments<lb/> is currently available, indicating a need for further<lb/> investigations.<lb/></div>

	Key words:
	<keyword>Pruritus; Cholestasis; Autotaxin; Opioid<lb/> receptor antagonist<lb/></keyword>

	<note type="copyright">© The Author(s) 2017. Published by Baishideng Publishing<lb/> Group Inc. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	Core tip:
	<div type="abstract">Pruritus is a symptom influencing the quality<lb/> of life in patients with chronic liver diseases especially<lb/> with cholestatic liver diseases. Complex underlying<lb/> mechanisms have been identified and various<lb/> therapeutic options developed. More evidence is<lb/> needed for these treatments, as well as improvements<lb/> in their tolerability.<lb/> Tajiri K, Shimizu Y. Recent advances in the management of<lb/> pruritus in chronic liver diseases.</div>

	<reference>World J Gastroenterol 2017;<lb/> 23(19): 3418-3426</reference>

	Available from: URL:
	<ptr type="web">http://www.wjgnet.<lb/> com/1007-9327/full/v23/i19/3418.htm</ptr> 

	<idno>DOI: http://dx.doi.<lb/> org/10.3748/wjg.v23.i19.3418</idno>

	<note type="doctype">REVIEW<lb/></note>

	<page>3418<lb/></page> 

	<reference>May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19|<lb/> WJG|www.wjgnet.com<lb/></reference> 

	Submit a Manuscript: http://www.f6publishing.com<lb/>
	
	<idno>DOI: 10.3748/wjg.v23.i19.3418<lb/></idno>

	<reference>World J Gastroenterol 2017 May 21; 23(19): 3418-3426<lb/></reference>

	<idno>ISSN 1007-9327 (print)</idno> 

	<idno>ISSN 2219-2840 (online)</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
