<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC5238813"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">© 2017 Khalid et al. This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php<lb/> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/). By accessing the work you<lb/> hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission<lb/> for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php).<lb/></note>

	<reference>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2017:11 193-202<lb/></reference>

	<title level="j">Drug Design, Development and Therapy</title>

	<publisher>Dovepress<lb/></publisher>

	submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com Dovepress 193<lb/> O r i g i n a l r e s e a r c h<lb/> open access to scientific and medical research<lb/> 

	<note type="doctype">Open access</note>

	<note type="doctype">Full Text article<lb/></note>

	<idno>http://dx.doi.org/10.2147/DDDT.S119432<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>computational intelligence models to predict<lb/> porosity of tablets using minimum features<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mohammad hassan Khalid 1<lb/> Pezhman Kazemi 1<lb/> lucia Perez-gandarillas 2<lb/> abderrahim Michrafy 2<lb/> Jakub Szlęk 1<lb/> renata Jachowicz 1<lb/> aleksander Mendyk 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Department of Pharmaceutical<lb/> Technology and Biopharmaceutics,<lb/> Faculty of Pharmacy, Jagiellonian<lb/> University Medical college,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Krakow,<lb/> Poland;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 centre national de la<lb/> recherche scientifique, centre<lb/> raPsODee, Mines albi, Université<lb/> de Toulouse,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>albi, France<lb/></address>

	Abstract:
	<div type="abstract">The effects of different formulations and manufacturing process conditions on the<lb/> physical properties of a solid dosage form are of importance to the pharmaceutical industry. It is<lb/> vital to have in-depth understanding of the material properties and governing parameters of its<lb/> processes in response to different formulations. Understanding the mentioned aspects will allow<lb/> tighter control of the process, leading to implementation of quality-by-design (QbD) practices.<lb/> Computational intelligence (CI) offers an opportunity to create empirical models that can be<lb/> used to describe the system and predict future outcomes in silico. CI models can help explore<lb/> the behavior of input parameters, unlocking deeper understanding of the system. This research<lb/> endeavor presents CI models to predict the porosity of tablets created by roll-compacted binary<lb/> mixtures, which were milled and compacted under systematically varying conditions. CI models<lb/> were created using tree-based methods, artificial neural networks (ANNs), and symbolic regres-<lb/>sion trained on an experimental data set and screened using root-mean-square error (RMSE)<lb/> scores. The experimental data were composed of proportion of microcrystalline cellulose (MCC)<lb/> (in percentage), granule size fraction (in micrometers), and die compaction force (in kilonewtons)<lb/> as inputs and porosity as an output. The resulting models show impressive generalization abil-<lb/>ity, with ANNs (normalized root-mean-square error [NRMSE] =1%) and symbolic regression<lb/> (NRMSE =4%) as the best-performing methods, also exhibiting reliable predictive behavior when<lb/> presented with a challenging external validation data set (best achieved symbolic regression:<lb/> NRMSE =3%). Symbolic regression demonstrates the transition from the black box modeling<lb/> paradigm to more transparent predictive models. Predictive performance and feature selection<lb/> behavior of CI models hints at the most important variables within this factor space.<lb/></div>

	Keywords:
	<keyword>computational intelligence, artificial neural network, symbolic regression, feature<lb/> selection, die compaction, porosity<lb/></keyword>

	correspondence:
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Mohammad<lb/> hassan Khalid<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical<lb/> Technology and Biopharmaceutics,<lb/> Faculty of Pharmacy, Jagiellonian<lb/> University-Medical college,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Medyczna 9, Krakow 30-688, Poland<lb/></address>

	Tel <phone>+48 73 306 5594</phone><lb/> email
	<email>hassankhalid101@gmail.com<lb/></email>

	This article was published in the following Dove Press journal:<lb/> 
	<title level="j">Drug Design, Development and Therapy<lb/></title>
	<date>12 January 2017<lb/></date>

	Number of times this article has been viewed
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
