<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC5332171"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	<page>284<lb/></page>

	<reference>volume 125 | number 3 | March 2017 • Environmental Health Perspectives</reference>

	<note type="doctype">Commentary<lb/></note>

	A Section 508-conformant HTML version of this article<lb/> is available at
	<idno>http://dx.doi.org/10.1289/EHP108</idno>

	.<lb/> Address correspondence to 

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>S. Satarug, </docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Centre for<lb/> Kidney Disease Research, Translational Research<lb/> Institute, University of Queensland School of<lb/> Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kent St., Woolloongabba, Brisbane,<lb/> Australia 4102.</address>

	Telephone: <phone>61-7-344-38011</phone>. E-mail:<lb/>
	<email>sj.satarug@yahoo.com.au<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">S.S. (L-14568) received Research Professorship from<lb/> the Japan Society for Promotion of Science (JSPS).<lb/> </note>

	The authors declare they have no actual or potential<lb/> competing financial interests.<lb/>
	
	<note type="submission">Received: 14 March 2016; Revised: 23 August<lb/> 2016; Accepted: 12 September 2016;</note>

	Published:<lb/>
	<date>1 March 2017</date>

	.<lb/>
	Note to readers with disabilities: EHP strives<lb/> to ensure that all journal content is accessible to all<lb/> readers. However, some figures and Supplemental<lb/> Material published in EHP articles may not conform to<lb/> 508 standards due to the complexity of the information<lb/> being presented. If you need assistance accessing journal<lb/> content, please contact ehponline@niehs.nih.gov.<lb/> Our staff will work with you to assess and meet your<lb/> accessibility needs within 3 working days.<lb/>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Health Risk Assessment of Dietary Cadmium Intake: Do Current Guidelines<lb/> Indicate How Much is Safe?<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Soisungwan Satarug, 1,2 David A.Vesey, 1 and Glenda C. Gobe 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Centre for Kidney Disease Research, Translational Research Institute, University of Queensland School of Medicine, Woolloongabba,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Brisbane, Queensland, Australia;</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Molecular Biology and Applied Physiology, Tohoku University School of Medicine,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sendai, Japan<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Background: Cadmium (Cd), a food-chain contaminant, is a significant health hazard. The<lb/> kidney is one of the primary sites of injury after chronic Cd exposure. Kidney-based risk assessment<lb/> establishes the urinary Cd threshold at 5.24 μg/g creatinine, and tolerable dietary intake of Cd at<lb/> 62 μg/day per 70-kg person. However, cohort studies show that dietary Cd intake below a threshold<lb/> limit and that tolerable levels may increase the risk of death from cancer, cardiovascular disease, and<lb/> Alzheimer&apos;s disease.<lb/> oBjective: We evaluated if the current tolerable dietary Cd intake guideline and urinary Cd<lb/> threshold limit provide sufficient health protection.<lb/> discussion: Staple foods constitute 40-60% of total dietary Cd intake by average consumers. Diets<lb/> high in shellfish, crustaceans, mollusks, spinach, and offal add to dietary Cd sources. Modeling<lb/> studies predict the current tolerable dietary intake corresponding to urinary Cd of 0.70-1.85 μg/g<lb/> creatinine in men and 0.95-3.07 μg/g creatinine in women. Urinary Cd levels of &lt; 1 μg/g creatinine<lb/> were associated with progressive kidney dysfunction and peripheral vascular disease. A urinary Cd<lb/> of 0.37 μg/g creatinine was associated with breast cancer, whereas dietary Cd of 16-31.5 μg/day<lb/> was associated with 25-94% increase in risk of estrogen receptor-positive breast cancer.<lb/> conclusion: Modeling shows that dietary intake levels for Cd exceed the levels associated with<lb/> kidney damage and many other adverse outcomes. Thus, the threshold level of urinary Cd should<lb/> be re-evaluated. A more restrictive dietary intake guideline would afford enhanced health protection<lb/> from this pervasive toxic metal.<lb/></div>

	citation:
	<reference>Satarug S, Vesey DA, Gobe GC. 2017. Health risk assessment of dietary cadmium<lb/> intake: do current guidelines indicate how much is safe? Environ Health Perspect 125:284-288;<lb/></reference>

	<idno>http://dx.doi.org/10.1289/EHP108</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
