<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="PMC5426865"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	www.PRSGlobalOpen.com 1 VIDEO<lb/>
	Operative Technique 

	<div type="abstract">I<lb/> n Asian rhinoplasty, for patients who mostly have low<lb/> and small noses compared to Caucasians, the most fre-<lb/>quently performed procedures are nasal tip projection,<lb/> lengthening and augmentation.<lb/> Various alloplastic materials such as silicone, polytet-<lb/>rafluoroethylene, high-density polyethylene (Medpor,<lb/> Stryker), etc., have been applied for such operations even<lb/> until recently. 1,2 However, when these implants are used<lb/> improperly or cause infection, it may result in severe con-<lb/>tracture that is very hard to correct.<lb/></div>

	From the
	<byline>
	<affiliation>April 31 Plastic Surgery Clinic,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Seoul, Korea.<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received for publication October 21, 2016; accepted January 27,<lb/> 2017.<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Contracted Nose Correction with Dermofat and<lb/> Conchal Cartilage<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jae Hoon Kim, MD, PhD; Jin Woo Song, MD; Sung Wan Park, MD<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	Disclosure: The authors have no financial interest to declare<lb/> in relation to the content of this article. The Article Processing<lb/> Charge was paid for by the authors.<lb/>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2017 The Authors. Published by Wolters Kluwer Health,<lb/> Inc. on behalf of The American Society of Plastic Surgeons. This is<lb/> an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative<lb/> Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0<lb/> (CCBY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the<lb/> work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in<lb/> any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.<lb/></note>

	<reference>Plast Reconstr Surg Glob Open 2017;5:e1272;</reference>

	<idno>doi: 10.1097/<lb/> GOX.0000000000001272</idno>

	; Published online
	<date>25 April 2017</date>

	.<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jae Hoon Kim, MD, PhD<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>April 31 Plastic Surgery Clinic<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>6th floor, Geonwoo B/D, Gangnam-daero 548<lb/> Kangnam-gu, Seoul 135-010<lb/> Korea<lb/></address>

	E-mail:
	<email>april31kjh@naver.com</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
