<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="pone.0028201"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Value of Laboratory Tests in Employer-Sponsored Health<lb/> Risk Assessments for Newly Identifying Health<lb/> Conditions: Analysis of 52,270 Participants<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Harvey W. Kaufman*, Fred R. Williams, Mouneer A. Odeh<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Quest Diagnostics,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Madison, New Jersey, United States of America</address>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: Employer-sponsored health risk assessments (HRA) may include laboratory tests to provide evidence of<lb/> disease and disease risks for common medical conditions. We evaluated the ability of HRA-laboratory testing to provide new<lb/> disease-risk information to participants.<lb/> Methodology/Principal Findings: We performed a cross-sectional analysis of HRA-laboratory results for participating adult<lb/> employees and their eligible spouses or their domestic partners, focusing on three common health conditions:<lb/> hyperlipidemia, diabetes mellitus, and chronic kidney disease. HRA with laboratory results of 52,270 first-time participants<lb/> were analyzed. Nearly all participants had access to health insurance coverage. Twenty-four percent (12,392) self-reported<lb/> one or more of these medical conditions: 21.1% (11,017) self-identified as having hyperlipidemia, 4.7% (2,479) self-identified<lb/> as having diabetes, and 0.7% (352) self-identified as having chronic kidney disease. Overall, 36% (n = 18,540) of participants<lb/> had laboratory evidence of at least one medical condition newly identified: 30.7% (16,032) had laboratory evidence of<lb/> hyperlipidemia identified, 1.9% (984) had laboratory evidence of diabetes identified, and 5.5% (2,866) had laboratory<lb/> evidence of chronic kidney disease identified. Of all participants with evidence of hyperlipidemia 59% (16,030 of 27,047),<lb/> were newly identified through the HRA. Among those with evidence of diabetes 28% (984 of 3,463) were newly identified.<lb/> The highest rate of newly identified disease risk was for chronic kidney disease: 89% (2,866 of 3,218) of participants with<lb/> evidence of this condition had not self-reported it. Men (39%) were more likely than women (33%) to have at least one<lb/> newly identified condition (p,0.0001). Among men, lower levels of educational achievement were associated with<lb/> modestly higher rates of newly identified disease risk (p,0.0001); the association with educational achievement among<lb/> women was unclear. Even among the youngest age range (20 to 29 year olds), nearly 1 in 4 participants (24%) had a newly<lb/> identified risk for disease.<lb/> Conclusions/Significance: These results support the important role of employer-sponsored laboratory testing as an integral<lb/> element of HRA for identifying evidence of previously undiagnosed common medical conditions in individuals of all<lb/> working age ranges, regardless of educational level and gender.<lb/></div>

	Citation:
	<reference>Kaufman HW, Williams FR, Odeh MA (2011) Value of Laboratory Tests in Employer-Sponsored Health Risk Assessments for Newly Identifying Health<lb/> Conditions: Analysis of 52,270 Participants. PLoS ONE 6(12): e28201.</reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0028201<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>>Joseph S. Ross,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Yale University School of Medicine, United States of America<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<note type="submission">Received June 13, 2011; Accepted November 3, 2011;</note>

	Published
	<date>December 7, 2011<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">ß 2011 Kaufman et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits<lb/> unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Funding: 
	<note type="submission">The authors have no support or funding to report.<lb/> </note>
	
	Competing Interests: The authors have the following competing interest: All the authors are employees of Quest Diagnostics. There are no patents, products in<lb/> development or marketed products to declare. This does not alter the authors&apos; adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.<lb/> 

	* E-mail:
	<email>Harvey.W.Kaufman@QuestDiagnostics.com<lb/></email>

	<reference>PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org<lb/> 1<lb/> December 2011 | Volume 6 | Issue 12 | e28201</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
