<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="pone.0003353"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Rapid Chromosome Evolution in Recently Formed<lb/> Polyploids in Tragopogon (Asteraceae)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>K. Yoong Lim 1 , Douglas E. Soltis 2 , Pamela S. Soltis 3 , Jennifer Tate 4 , Roman Matyasek 5 , Hana Srubarova 5 ,<lb/> Ales Kovarik 5 , J. Chris Pires 6 , Zhiyong Xiong 6 , Andrew R. Leitch 1 *<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 School of Biological and Chemical Sciences, Queen Mary College, University of London,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>London, United Kingdom, </address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Department of Botany and the Genetics Institute,<lb/> University of Florida,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gainesville, Florida, United States of America,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Florida Museum of Natural History and the Genetics Institute, University of Florida,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gainesville, Florida,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>United States of America, 4 Massey University, Institute of Molecular Biosciences,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Palmerston North, New Zealand,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>5 Institute of Biophysics, Academy of Sciences of the<lb/> Czech Republic,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Brno, Czech Republic,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>6 Division of Biological Sciences, Life Sciences Center, University of Missouri,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Columbia, Missouri, United States of America</address>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">Background: Polyploidy, frequently termed &apos;&apos;whole genome duplication&apos;&apos;, is a major force in the evolution of many<lb/> eukaryotes. Indeed, most angiosperm species have undergone at least one round of polyploidy in their evolutionary history.<lb/> Despite enormous progress in our understanding of many aspects of polyploidy, we essentially have no information about<lb/> the role of chromosome divergence in the establishment of young polyploid populations. Here we investigate synthetic<lb/> lines and natural populations of two recently and recurrently formed allotetraploids Tragopogon mirus and T. miscellus<lb/> (formed within the past 80 years) to assess the role of aberrant meiosis in generating chromosomal/genomic diversity. That<lb/> diversity is likely important in the formation, establishment and survival of polyploid populations and species.<lb/> Methodology/Principal Findings: Applications of fluorescence in situ hybridisation (FISH) to natural populations of T. mirus<lb/> and T. miscellus suggest that chromosomal rearrangements and other chromosomal changes are common in both<lb/> allotetraploids. We detected extensive chromosomal polymorphism between individuals and populations, including (i)<lb/> plants monosomic and trisomic for particular chromosomes (perhaps indicating compensatory trisomy), (ii) intergenomic<lb/> translocations and (iii) variable sizes and expression patterns of individual ribosomal DNA (rDNA) loci. We even observed<lb/> karyotypic variation among sibling plants. Significantly, translocations, chromosome loss, and meiotic irregularities,<lb/> including quadrivalent formation, were observed in synthetic (S 0 and S 1 generations) polyploid lines. Our results not only<lb/> provide a mechanism for chromosomal variation in natural populations, but also indicate that chromosomal changes occur<lb/> rapidly following polyploidisation.<lb/> Conclusions/Significance: These data shed new light on previous analyses of genome and transcriptome structures in de<lb/> novo and establishing polyploid species. Crucially our results highlight the necessity of studying karyotypes in young<lb/> (,150 years old) polyploid species and synthetic polyploids that resemble natural species. The data also provide insight<lb/> into the mechanisms that perturb inheritance patterns of genetic markers in synthetic polyploids and populations of young<lb/> natural polyploid species.<lb/></div>

	Citation:
	<reference>Lim KY, Soltis DE, Soltis PS, Tate J, Matyasek R et al. (2008) Rapid Chromosome Evolution in Recently Formed Polyploids in Tragopogon<lb/> (Asteraceae). PLoS ONE 3(10): e3353.</reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353<lb/></idno>

	Editor:
	<editor>Samuel P. Hazen,</editor>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>University of Massachusetts Amherst, United States of America<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<note type="submission">Received July 3, 2008; Accepted September 8, 2008;</note>

	Published
	<date>October 9, 2008<lb/></date>

	Copyright:
	<note type="copyright">ß 2008 Lim et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted<lb/> use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.<lb/></note>

	Funding: 
	<note type="funding">The authors thank NERC, Grant Agency of the Czech Republic (521/07/0116), and the USA National Science Foundation (grants MCB-0346437, DEB-<lb/>0608268, DBI 0638536 and DBI 0501712) for support. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of<lb/> the manuscript.<lb/></note>

	Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.<lb/>

	* E-mail:
	<email>a.r.leitch@qmul.ac.uk<lb/></email>

	<reference>PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org<lb/> 1<lb/> October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353</reference>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
