<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="regensburg2_25"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>On the Diastereoisomerism of Natural and Synthetic a-Bisabolols</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Elmar Flaskamp*, Gerhard Nonnenmacher und Otto Isaac<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Aus der Anwendungstechnik Naturstoffe des Chemiewerks Homburg,<lb/> Zweigniederlassung der Degussa AG, Frankfurt am Main und der<lb/> Physikahsch-Chemischen Forschung der Degussa AG,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Wolfgang<lb/></address>

	<reference>Z. Naturforsch. 86b, 114-118 (1981);</reference>

	<note type="submission">eingegangen am 17. Juli 1980<lb/></note>

	<keyword>a-Bisabolol, Vanillosmopsis erythropappa Matricaria chamomilla, Myoporum crassifolium,<lb/> Populus balsamifera<lb/> </keyword>

	<div type="abstract">The stereochemistry of a-bisabolol is discussed. The chirahties of the different a-bisabolols<lb/> from Myoporum crassifolium, Populus balsamifera and Vanillosmopsis erythropappa are<lb/> deduced from the absolute configuration of natural bisabolol from chamomile, which has<lb/> to be considered as being (l'S,2S)-configurated according to most recent investigations.<lb/> Based on this assumption, (l'S, 2Reconfiguration has to be ascribed to (—)-a-bisabolol<lb/> from Myoporum crassifolium, whereas (l'R,2R)-resp. (l'S,2S)-structure is present in<lb/> (4-)-a-bisabolol from Populus balsamifera and (—)-a-bisabolol from<lb/> Vanillosmopsis erythropappa being therefore enantiomeric to the latter. Consequently, the (—)-a-bisabolols<lb/> from Matricaria chamomilla and Vanillosmopsis erythropappa turn out to be identical in<lb/> all respects.<lb/> Synthetic a-bisabolols, however, featuring approximately equal amounts of all the four<lb/> possible stereoisomers, differ not only optically but also in their stereochemical uniformity<lb/> from natural a-bisabolols.<lb/> By means of NMR spectrometric methods the identity of the native active agent can be<lb/> established in chamomile specialities; as a consequence possible admixtures of synthetic<lb/> racemates of a-bisabolol thus can be identified and quantified.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
