<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="regensburg2_7"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>IR, 31 P-, 55 Mn-und 185 187 Re-NMR spektroskopische Untersuchungen<lb/> an einigen Carbonylmangan-und -rhenium-Komplexen<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="english-title">IR, 31 P, 55 Mn and i85,i87Re ^MR Spectroscopic Investigations<lb/> of Some Carbonylmanganese and -rhenium Complexes<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ahmet Kececi und Dieter Rehder*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institut für Anorganische und Angewandte Chemie der Universität Hamburg,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Martin-Luther-King-Platz 6, D-2000 Hamburg 13<lb/></address>

	<reference>Z. Naturforsch. 36b, 20-26 (1981);</reference>

	<note type="submission">eingegangen am 6. Oktober 1980<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Carbonylphosphinemanganese, Carbonylphosphinerhenium, IR Spectra, Manganese NMR Spectra,<lb/> Rhenium NMR Spectra<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">The IR and NMR spectra of the complexes [M(C0)6]C1 @BULLET HCl (M = Mn: 1, M = Re: 2),<lb/> M(CO)5C02Et (M = Mn: 3, M = Re: 4), [Mn(CO)5PR3][PF6] (5; PR3 = PPh(OPh)2: a,<lb/> P(n-Pr)3: b, PHPh2: c, PPh(NEt2)2: d, P(p-C6H4F)3: e), [Re(CO)5PHPh2][PF6] (6 c),<lb/> Mn2(CO)8(PR3)2 (7) and Re2(CO)s(PHPh2)2 (8c) are discussed in the context of a-and<lb/> jr-interactions in the metal-ligand system and compared with 51 V NMR data of the<lb/> analogous isoelectronic and isostructural carbonyl vanadates (—I). On the basis of these<lb/> results, the phosphines are arranged in the order of decreasing integral ligand strength<lb/> according to a>b>c>d. The 55 Mn shielding of 5 is greater than that of 1, which is<lb/> explained by strong ^-interactions and correspondingly large e-ai* splitting dominating<lb/> the paramagnetic deshielding term in the pseudooctahedral complexes of type 5. The<lb/> only rhenium compound accessible to NMR is 2, for which the 185 Re and 187 Re resonances<lb/> were obtained. 31 P coordination shifts are positive for all complexes. Spectroscopic data<lb/> for 7 c show that this complex presumably has the structure (CO)sMn-Mn(CO)3(PHPh2)2,<lb/> contrasting 7 a, 7 b, 7d and 7e (local D4d symmetry).<lb/></div>

	<intro>Einleitung<lb/></intro>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
