<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="sdarticle01"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>A hierarchical model for the relationships between general and specific<lb/> vulnerability factors and symptom levels of generalized anxiety disorder<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Colin van der Heiden a,b, *, Kim Melchior a,b , Peter Muris b , S. Bouwmeester b , Arjan E.R. Bos c ,<lb/> Henk T. van der Molen b<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Outpatient Treatment Center PsyQ,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rotterdam, The Netherlands<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Institute of Psychology, Erasmus University Rotterdam,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>The Netherlands<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c Faculty of Psychology and Neuroscience, Maastricht University,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>The Netherlands<lb/></address>

	<reference>Journal of Anxiety Disorders 24 (2010) 284-289<lb/></reference>

	A R T I C L E I N F O<lb/>

	Article history:<lb/>
	<note type="submission">Received 10 July 2009<lb/> Received in revised form 11 December 2009<lb/> Accepted 11 December 2009<lb/></note>

	Keywords:<lb/>
	<keyword>Generalized anxiety disorder<lb/> Hierarchical model<lb/> Neuroticism<lb/> Metacognitions<lb/> Intolerance of uncertainty Worry<lb/></keyword>

	A B S T R A C T<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">The present study examined a hierarchical model for the relationships between general and specific<lb/> vulnerability factors and symptom manifestations of generalized anxiety disorder (GAD). A clinical<lb/> sample of patients with GAD (N = 137) completed a set of self-report questionnaires for measuring<lb/> neuroticism, extraversion, intolerance of uncertainty, metacognitive beliefs, and symptoms of<lb/> generalized anxiety (i.e., worry) and depression. A bootstrapping analysis yielded support for a model<lb/> in which the relation between the general vulnerability factor of neuroticism and symptoms of GAD<lb/> were mediated by the specific vulnerability factors of intolerance of uncertainty and negative<lb/> metacognitions. Implications for the classification and treatment of GAD are discussed.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">ß 2009 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	* Corresponding author at:
	<byline>
	<affiliation>PsyQ,</affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>Van Vollenhovenstraat 3 (2nd floor), 3016 BE<lb/> Rotterdam, The Netherlands.</address>

	Tel.: <phone>+31 88 0013991</phone>; fax: +31 88 0013999.<lb/> E-mail address:
	<email>c.vanderheiden@psyq.nl</email>
	(C. van der Heiden).<lb/> 

	Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/>
	
	<title level="j">Journal of Anxiety Disorders<lb/></title>

	0887-6185/$ -see front matter
	<note type="copyright">ß 2009 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

	<idno>doi:10.1016/j.janxdis.2009.12.005</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
