<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="tc031963"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Research paper<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Tobacco marketing in California and implications for<lb/> the future<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>April Roeseler,<lb/> 1 Ellen C Feighery,<lb/> 2 Tess Boley Cruz<lb/> 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">ABSTRACT<lb/> Background Tobacco marketing influences tobacco use<lb/> initiation, maintenance of use, and it undermines<lb/> comprehensive tobacco control programmes. Policies to<lb/> ban the impact of tobacco marketing are most likely to<lb/> be more effective if they are comprehensive, as partial<lb/> bans shift marketing to non-banned forms of media. A<lb/> comprehensive approach to reducing tobacco marketing<lb/> includes documentation through monitoring, media and<lb/> policy interventions and aggressive enforcement of<lb/> existing laws.<lb/> Methods This paper summarises California tobacco<lb/> industry monitoring of events and retail outlets, and<lb/> findings about exposure to and beliefs about tobacco<lb/> industry marketing among youths and adults conducted<lb/> during the period 2000 through 2008.<lb/> Results There was no overall change in the average<lb/> number of cigarette materials per store, and an increase<lb/> in the percentage of stores with advertisements<lb/> promoting price discounts for cigarettes. Stores with<lb/> cigarette advertisements near candy displays declined<lb/> from 12.5% (95% CI 9.8% to 15.2%) to 1% (95% CI 0.2%<lb/> to 1.9%) of stores, and advertisements at or below the<lb/> eye-level of children declined from 78.6% (95% CI 75.2%<lb/> to 82.0%) to 31% (95% CI 27.1% to 34.9%) of stores.<lb/> Overall, the number of public events with tobacco<lb/> sponsorship declined from 77.3% to 48.1%. This trend<lb/> was consistent with a significant decline noted among<lb/> high school students and adults who reported seeing<lb/> tobacco advertisements at events or attending a tobacco<lb/> company-sponsored event.<lb/> Conclusions Tobacco industry monitoring, media, policy<lb/> and enforcement interventions may have contributed to<lb/> observed changes in tobacco marketing and to declines<lb/> in reported exposure to tobacco marketing.<lb/></div> 
	
	<p type="introduction">contributions, sponsorship, philanthropy and<lb/> corporate responsibility efforts subtly influence<lb/> tobacco-related policy decisions made by elected<lb/> officials, community leaders, constituency groups<lb/> and even juries.<lb/> 10e16<lb/> The California Department of Public Health<lb/> (CDPH), California Tobacco Control Program<lb/> (CTCP) has continuously monitored exposure to<lb/> and beliefs about tobacco industry marketing<lb/> among adults and youths through telephone and<lb/> in-school surveys. These population-based surveys<lb/> are supplemented with observational surveys of<lb/> tobacco marketing focused on sponsored events and<lb/> the retail environment. This paper describes Cali-<lb/>fornia&apos;s media and programme interventions to<lb/> stimulate tobacco marketing restrictions; enforce-<lb/>ment of the Master Settlement Agreement<lb/> i (MSA),<lb/> Smokeless Tobacco Settlement Agreement and<lb/> existing laws; and reports on changes in marketing,<lb/> and adult and youth attitudes about and exposure<lb/> to tobacco industry marketing in California.<lb/></p>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 California Department of Public<lb/> Health, California Tobacco<lb/> Control Program, Sacramento,<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>California, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 International Research,<lb/> Campaign for Tobacco Free<lb/> Kids,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address> Washington, DC, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 Preventive Medicine, University<lb/> of Southern California, Keck<lb/> School of Medicine,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Los<lb/> Angeles, California, USA<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">Correspondence to<lb/> </note>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>April Roeseler, </docAuthor>
	</byline>
	
	<byline>
	<affiliation>Programs and<lb/> Media Operations Section,<lb/> California Department of Public<lb/> Health, CDIC/California Tobacco<lb/> Control Program,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>MS 7206, PO<lb/> Box 997377, Sacramento, CA<lb/> 95899-7377, USA;<lb/></address>

	<email>April.Roeseler@cdph.ca.gov<lb/></email>

	<note type="submission">Received 3 June 2009<lb/> Accepted 8 January 2010<lb/></note>

	<note type="copyright">Sponsorship<lb/> This paper is freely available<lb/> online under the BMJ Journals<lb/> unlocked scheme, see http://<lb/> tobaccocontrol.bmj.com/site/<lb/> about/unlocked.xhtml<lb/></note>

	<reference>Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29.</reference>

	<idno>doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963</idno>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
