<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="two_pages"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>

	GE98<lb/> 

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Ability of different obturation techniques to fill canal irregularities using gutta-percha and<lb/> RealSeal<lb/> </titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
		<docAuthor>Alabsi S1, *Alhadainy HA 2, Darrag AM 2, Mohammed AA 3<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
		<affiliation>Department of Endodontics, 1Ministry of Health, </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Sanaa, Yemen, 2Tanta University, Tanta,<lb/> Egypt,</address> 

	<byline>
		<affiliation>3Endodontics, Islamic University,</affiliation>
	</byline> 

	<address>Medina, Saudi Arabia<lb/></address> 

	<div type="abstract">Aim To test the ability of gutta-percha and RealSeal to fill canal irregularities using different<lb/> obturation techniques.<lb/> Methodology A split-tooth model with four artificially created defects on canal wall was used to<lb/> compare three techniques, cold lateral (CLC), warm lateral (WLC), and warm vertical (WVC)<lb/> used with gutta-percha and RealSeal obturating materials. The technique evaluation was based<lb/> on defect replication quality as a function of defect location and size. Obturation mass was<lb/> removed for visual evaluation on an ordinal scale, 0 to 4, based on how much each defect was<lb/> replicated. Statistical analysis was performed using Kruskal-Wallis test and Mann Whitney test<lb/> (p = 0.05).<lb/> Results Both warm techniques were significantly better than CLC. Based on defect sites, WVC<lb/> was better than WLC in replicating the apical defect. There was no significant difference<lb/> between replicating small and large middle defect for the two warm techniques. For filling<lb/> materials, no significant difference was found between gutta-percha and RealSeal in all defect<lb/> sites using WLC and WVC.<lb/> Conclusions Both gutta percha and RealSeal can similarly replicate canal irregularities with<lb/> worm obturation technique. Worm condensation (either vertical or lateral) is proved to be better<lb/> than the cold lateral condensation in replicating the apical defect.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
