<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="W09-1206"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Proceedings of the Thirteenth Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL): Shared Task, pages 43-48,<lb/> Boulder, Colorado, June 2009.</reference>

	<note type="copyright">c 2009 Association for Computational Linguistics<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Multilingual Semantic Role Labeling<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Anders Björkelund<lb/> Love Hafdell<lb/> Pierre Nugues<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Computer Science, Lund University<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>S-221 00 Lund, Sweden<lb/></address>

	<email>fte04abj@student.lth.se<lb/></email>

	<email>love hafdell@hotmail.com</email><lb/> 
	<email>Pierre.Nugues@cs.lth.se</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">This paper describes our contribution to the<lb/> semantic role labeling task (SRL-only) of the<lb/> CoNLL-2009 shared task in the closed chal-<lb/>lenge (Hajič et al., 2009). Our system con-<lb/>sists of a pipeline of independent, local clas-<lb/>sifiers that identify the predicate sense, the ar-<lb/>guments of the predicates, and the argument<lb/> labels. Using these local models, we carried<lb/> out a beam search to generate a pool of candi-<lb/>dates. We then reranked the candidates using<lb/> a joint learning approach that combines the lo-<lb/>cal models and proposition features.<lb/> To address the multilingual nature of the data,<lb/> we implemented a feature selection procedure<lb/> that systematically explored the feature space,<lb/> yielding significant gains over a standard set<lb/> of features. Our system achieved the second<lb/> best semantic score overall with an average la-<lb/>beled semantic F1 of 80.31. It obtained the<lb/> best F1 score on the Chinese and German data<lb/> and the second best one on English.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
