<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="W09-1417"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Proceedings of the Workshop on BioNLP: Shared Task, pages 115-118,<lb/> Boulder, Colorado, June 2009.</reference>

	<note type="copyright">c 2009 Association for Computational Linguistics<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Biomedical Event Detection using Rules,<lb/> Conditional Random Fields and Parse Tree Distances<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Farzaneh Sarafraz*, James Eales*, Reza Mohammadi ♦<lb/> ♦ ♦<lb/> ♦ , Jonathan Dickerson ♣<lb/> ♣ ♣<lb/> ♣ ,<lb/> David Robertson ♣<lb/> ♣ ♣<lb/> ♣ , Goran Nenadic*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>* School of Computer Science, University of Manchester<lb/> ♣ Faulty of Life Sciences, University of Manchester<lb/> ♦ Dept. of Mathematics and Computer Science, Sharif University of Technology<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<email>sarafraf@cs.man.ac.uk</email>, <email>g.nenadic@manchester.ac.uk</email>

	Abstract<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">This paper reports on a system developed for<lb/> the BioNLP&apos;09 shared task on detection and<lb/> characterisation of biomedical events. Event<lb/> triggers and types were recognised using a<lb/> conditional random field classifier and a set of<lb/> rules, while event participants were identified<lb/> using a rule-based system that relied on rela-<lb/>tive distances between candidate entities and<lb/> the trigger in the associated parse tree. The re-<lb/>sults on previously unseen test data were en-<lb/>couraging: for non-regulatory events, the F-<lb/>score was almost 50% (with precision above<lb/> 60%), with the overall F-score of around 30%<lb/> (49% precision). The performance on more<lb/> complex regulatory events was poor<lb/> (F-measure of 7%). Among the 24 teams<lb/> submitting the test results, our results were<lb/> ranked 12 th for the overall F-score and 8 th for<lb/> the F-score of non-regulation events.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
