<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ZFN-A-036-02-0165"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<titlePage>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="main">X-Ray and Neutron Diffraction Studies on Amorphous <lb/>
Transitionmetal — Boron Alloys (Fe-B, Co-B, Ni-B) <lb/></titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline><docAuthor>P. Lamparter, E. Nold, G. Rainer-Harbach, E. Grallath, and S. Steeb</docAuthor><lb/></byline>
				<byline><affiliation>Max-Planck-Institut für Metallforschung , Institut für Werkstoffwissenschaften</affiliation>, <address>Stuttgart Germany</address> <lb/></byline>
				<reference>Z. Naturforsch. 86a, 165—172 (1981); </reference>
				<note type="submission">received December 11  1980 <lb/></note>
			</titlePage>
			<div type="abstract">The atomic-scale structure of the amorphous metallic alloys FesoBjjo, Cogi-yBig.ö, and <lb/>Nisi. Bis.s was investigated by X-ray- and neutron-diffraction covering a wide range of the ratio <lb/>( /metai/ftxmm ) of the scattering factors of both components. The structure factors S(q ) show a <lb/>pronounced dependence on the ratio /meUi//boron* In the cases of a small ratio an additional <lb/>peak near ? —21.5 nm -1 appears in the structure factors from which a definite distance between <lb/>B-B atoms, which are separated by metal atoms, is deduced. The corresponding structure factors <lb/>show only weak oscillations in the range of the second and third maxima, which are followed by <lb/>increased amplitudes at larger g's. <lb/>By Fourier-transformation radial distribution curves were evaluated, from which the distances <lb/>between the metal-metal-, the metal-boron-, and the boron-boron-atoms and the coordination <lb/>numbers are extracted. From the splitted first maximum of the radial distribution function in <lb/>the cases of small ratio /met*i//boron a * so partial coordination numbers could be obtained. The <lb/>results suggest some kind of short range order between the metal and the boron atoms.<lb/></div>
			<div type="intro">Introduction <lb/></div>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
