<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ZNA-1972-27a-0373"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Low-Energy Electron Diffraction Amplitudes for a "Bare-Substrate" Model<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>E. G. MCRAE<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Bell Laboratories,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Murray Hill, New Jersey<lb/></address>

	<reference>(Z. Naturforsch. 27 a, 373—382 [1972] ;</reference>

	<note type="submission">received 16 November 1971)<lb/></note>

	<note type="dedication">Dedicated to Prof. Dr. K. MOLIERE on his 60-th<lb/> birthday<lb/> </note>

	<div type="abstract">A theory of low-energy electron diffraction (LEED) amplitudes is developed for a model in<lb/> which the crystal surface is represented by a step-function termination of the bulk crystal potential<lb/> ("bare-substrate" model). The crystal is considered to be centro-symmetric and it is assumed that<lb/> either the crystal has a two-fold axis of rotation normal to the surface or the primay beam is<lb/> normally incident on the surface. The origin of coordinates is taken to lie at a center of symmetry<lb/> of the substrate crystal. The diffraction amplitude is considered as a function of complex electron<lb/> energy. For a real potential it is shown to have the following properties:<lb/> 1. The imaginary part of the amplitude vanishes at each branch point of the amplitude function;<lb/> 2. There are certain segments of the real-energy axis, called "inactive" segments, throughout<lb/> which the imaginary part of the amplitude vanishes approximately.<lb/> The theoretical results are illustrated by a numerical example. It is suggested that the diffrac-<lb/>tion amplitude can be represented by a simple expression that has the correct functional form<lb/> and that satisfies the appropriate dispersion relation. One such expression is proposed and discussed<lb/> in comparison with exact computational results.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
