<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ZNA-1972-27a-0236"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Über di e Ursache der Supral ei tung. III.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>H. KREBS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Institut für Anoorganische Chemie der Universität Stuttgart<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<reference>(Z. Naturforsch. 27 a, 236—249 [1972] ;</reference>

	<note type="submission">eingegangen am 5. November 1971)<lb/></note>

	<note type="english-title">ON THE CAUSE OF SUPERCONDUCTIVITY. 111.<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">By consideration of superconducting compounds, whose chemical bond nature is known or can<lb/> be derived with some certainty, it is shown that superconductivity only occurs, if valency electrons<lb/> of a band can move in at least one space direction without intersecting any nodal surfaces. This<lb/> applies both for metallic substances and for semiconductors. The following examples are discussed:<lb/> 1. Metallic and semiconducting compounds composed of elements of the main groups and having<lb/> a lattice similar to that of NaCl.<lb/> 2. Nb-and Ta-chalcogenides with MoS2-structure.<lb/> 3. The clathrate-compound [Ag708] + X~.<lb/> 4. LaC2 with CaC2-structure.<lb/> 5. Metallic and semiconducting perovskites.<lb/> 6. Spinels and interstitial compounds with NaCl-structure.<lb/> 7. Pyrites.<lb/> 8. Some metals and their alloys.<lb/> In the case of s-electrons, this condition is fulfilled for all space directions, in the case of 5-bonds<lb/> only along the intersecting line of the two nodal planes. A "(5"-bond is often — especially in an<lb/> NaCl-type lattice — associated with a translation perpendicular to this intersecting line (in the<lb/> NaCl-type lattice a translation by a/2) and a rotation by 90°. In such a V'-bond system the four<lb/> segments of a dt2g-electron belong to four adjacent canals of quadratic cross-section (in the NaCl-<lb/>type lattice the side length is a/2) which are not intersected by nodal surfaces. Only electrons ful-<lb/>filling the condition indicated above can be considered as "free electrons".<lb/> </div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
