<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ZNC-1988-43c-0199"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Dynamics of the Tissue-Specific Metabolism of Luteolin Glucuronides<lb/> in the Mesophyll of Rye Primary Leaves (Secale cereale)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Margot Schulz* and Gottfried Weissenböck<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Botanisches Institut der Universität zu Köln,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Gyrhofstraße 15, 5000 Köln 41,<lb/> Bundesrepublik Deutschland<lb/></address>

	<reference>Z. Naturforsch. 43c, 187-193 (1988);</reference>

	<note type="submission">received November 19/December 30, 1987<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Secale cereale L., UDP-glucuronate: flavone-glucuronosyltransferases, ß-Glucuronidase,<lb/> Luteolin 7-0-Diglucuronosyl-4'-0-Glucuronide<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">Developing primary leaves of Secale cereale L. exhibit a dynamic metabolism of the major<lb/> flavonoid luteolin 7-Ö-[ß-D-glucuronosyl(l—>2)ß-D-glucuronide]-4'-0-ß-D-glucuronide (R,). Fi-<lb/>nal steps of R] biosynthesis are sequential glucuronidations of luteolin, which are catalyzed by<lb/> three specific UDP-glucuronate: flavone glucuronosyltransferases. These enzymes reach highest<lb/> activities at the fourth and fifth day of leaf development, coinciding with maximal R, accumula-<lb/>tion. The activities decrease with advancing age of the leaves. In contrast, a R,-specific ß-<lb/>glucuronidase, responsible for the hydrolysis of glucuronic acid in position 4', shows increasing<lb/> activity up to the 5 th or 6 th day; but this activity, leading to luteolin 7-O-diglucuronide (R 2 ), is not<lb/> reduced in later developmental stages. In this phase of leaf development, the amount of R]<lb/> drastically drops, whereas R 2 accumulates only slightly. From in vitro results and from feeding<lb/> experiments using [ 14 C]cinnamic acid, a precursor of R, biosynthesis, we conclude that the<lb/> anabolic sequential glucuronidation takes place in young and expanding leaf tissue, whereas<lb/> deglucuronidation occurs in nearly mature and mature tissue. The three glucuronosyltransferases<lb/> as well as the ß-glucuronidase, and the flavonoids R, and R 2 are localized in the mesophyll.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
