<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
	
		References<lb/> 
	
        <listBibl>
            <bibl>Borges, A.S., Divers, T.J., Stokol, T., Mohammed, O.H., 2007. Serum iron and plasma ﬁbrinogen concentrations as indicators of systemic inﬂamma- tory diseases in horses. J. Vet. Intern. Med. 21, 489–494.</bibl>
            <bibl>Chapman, M., French, D., Taylor, H., Klei, T., 2002. One season of pasture exposure fails to induce a protective resistance to cyathostomes but increases numbers of hypobiotic third-stage larvae. J. Parasitol. 88, 678–683.</bibl>
            <bibl>Christoffersen, M., Woodward, E., Bojesen, A.M., Jacobsen, S., Petersen, M.R., Troedsson, M.H.T., Lehn-Jensen, H., 2012. Inﬂammatory responses to induced infectious endometritis in mares resistant or susceptible to persistent endometritis. BMC Vet. Res. 8, 41.</bibl>
            <bibl>Crisman, M.V., Scarratt, W.K., Zimmerman, K.L., 2008. Blood proteins and inﬂammation in the horse. Vet. Clin. North Am. Equine Pract. 24, 285–297.</bibl>
            <bibl>Davidson, A.J., Hodgkinson, J.E., Proudman, C.J., Matthews, J.B., 2005. Cytokine responses to cyathostominae larvae in the equine large intestinal wall. Res. Vet. Sci. 78, 169–176.</bibl>
            <bibl>Dennis, V.A., Klei, T.R., Miller, M.A., Chapman, M.R., McClure, J.R., 1992. Immune responses of pony foals during repeated infections of Strongy- lus vulgaris and regular ivermectin treatments. Vet. Parasitol. 42, 83–99.</bibl>
            <bibl>Drudge, J.H., Lyons, E.T., Szanto, J., 1966. Pathogenesis of Migrating Stages of Helminths, with Special Reference to Strongylus vulgaris. World Association for the Advancement of Veterinary Parasitology, New York/London, pp. 199–214.</bibl>
            <bibl>du Toit, N., McGorum, B.C., Pemberton, A.D., Brown, J., Dacre, K.J., 2007. The involvement of mast cells and mast cell proteinases in the intestinal response to equine cyathostomin infection. Vet. Immunol. Immunopathol. 115, 35–42.</bibl>
            <bibl>Enigk, K., 1970. The development of the three species of Strongylus of the horse during the prepatent period. In: Bryans, J.T., Gerber, H. (Eds.), Equine Infectious Diseases. S. Karger, Basel, pp. 259–268.</bibl>
            <bibl>Eysker, M., Jansen, J., Mirck, M., 1984. Inhibited development of cyathos- tominae in the horse in the early third stage. Res. Vet. Sci. 37, 355.</bibl>
            <bibl>Faul, F., Erdfelder, E., Buchner, A., Lang, A.-G., 2009. Statistical power anal- yses using G*Power 3.1: tests for correlation and regression analyses. Behav. Res. Methods 41, 1149–1160.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gibson, T.E., 1953. The effect of repeated anthelmintic treatment with phenothiazine on the faecal egg counts of housed horses, with some observations on the life cycle of Trichonema spp. in the horse. J. Helminthol. 27, 29–40.</bibl>
            <bibl>Giraudoux, P., 2011. pgirmess: Data Analysis in Ecology.</bibl>
            <bibl>Herd, R., Queen, W., Majewski, G., 1992. Sex-related susceptibility of bulls to gastrointestinal parasites. Vet. Parasitol. 44, 119–125.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hultén, C., Tulamo, R.M., Suominen, M.M., Burvall, K., Marhaug, G., Forsberg, M., 1999. A non-competitive chemiluminescence enzyme immunoassay for the equine acute phase protein serum amyloid A (SAA) – a clinically useful inﬂammatory marker in the horse. Vet. Immunol. Immunopathol. 68, 267–281.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hutchings, M.R., Milner, J.M., Gordon, I.J., Kyriazakis, I., Jackson, F., 2002. Grazing decisions of Soay sheep, Ois aries, on St Kilda: a consequence of parasite distribution? OIKOS 96, 235–244.</bibl>
            <bibl>Jacobsen, S.,2007. Review of equine acute-phase proteins. In: 53rd Annual Convention of the American Association of Equine Practition- ers. American Association of Equine Practitioners (AAEP), Orlando, Florida.</bibl>
            <bibl>Jacobsen, S., Kjelgaard-Hansen, M., Hagbard Petersen, H., Jensen, A.L., 2006a. Evaluation of a commercially available human serum amyloid A (SAA) turbidometric immunoassay for determination of equine SAA concentrations. Vet. J. 172, 315–319.</bibl>
            <bibl>Jacobsen, S., Niewold, T.A., Halling-Thomsen, M., Nanni, S., Olsen, E., Linde- gaard, C., Andersen, P.H., 2006b. Serum amyloid A isoforms in serum and synovial ﬂuid in horses with lipopolysaccharide-induced arthritis. Vet. Immun. Immunopathol. 110, 325–330.</bibl>
            <bibl>Jacobsen, S., Thomsen, M.H., Nanni, S., 2006c. Concentrations of serum amyloid A in serum and synovial ﬂuid from healthy horses and horses with joint disease. Am. J. Vet. Res. 67, 1738–1742.</bibl>
            <bibl>Kent, J.E., 1987. Speciﬁc serum protein changes associated with primary and secondary Strongylus vulgaris infections in pony yearlings. Equine Vet. J. 19, 133–137.</bibl>
            <bibl>Klei, T.R., Chapman, M.R., Torbert, B.J., McClure, J.R., 1983. Antibody responses of ponies to initial and challenge infections of Strongylus vulgaris. Vet. Parasitol. 12, 187–198.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>
