<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">

        References<lb/> 

		<listBibl>
        <bibl>Arber, S., Barbayannis, F.A., Hanser, H., Schneider, C., Stanyon, C.A., Bernard, O. and<lb/> Caroni, P. (1998) Regulation of actin dynamics through phosphorylation of cofilin by LIM-<lb/>kinase. Nature 393: 805-809.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Arber, S. and Caroni, P. (1996) Specificity of single LIM motifs in targeting and LIM/LIM<lb/> interactions in situ. Genes Dev. 10: 289-300.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Arber, S., Halder, G. and Caroni, P. (1994) Muscle LIM protein, a novel essential regulator of<lb/> myogenesis, promotes myogenic differentiation. Cell 79: 221-231.<lb/> Bach, I. (2000) The LIM domain: regulation by association. Mech. Dev. 91: 5-17.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Baltz, R., Domon, C., Pillay, D.T.N. and Steinmetz, A. (1992) Characterization of a pollen-<lb/>specific cDNA from sunflower encoding a zinc finger protein. Plant J. 2: 713-721.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Baltz, R., Schmit, A.C., Kohnen, M., Hentges, F. and Steinmetz, A. (1999) Differential<lb/> localization of the LIM domain protein PLIM-1 in microspores and mature pollen grains from<lb/> sunflower. Sex. Plant Reprod. 12: 60-65.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Caumont, C., Petitprez, M., Woynaroski, S., Barthou, H., Brière, C., Kallerhoff, J., Borin, C.,<lb/> Souvré, A. and Alibert, G. (1997) Agarose embedding affects cell wall regeneration and<lb/> microtubule organization in sunflower hypocotyl protoplasts. Physiol. Plant. 99: 129-134.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Chanabé, C., Burrus, M. and Alibert, G. (1989) Factors affecting the improvement of colony<lb/> formation from sunflower protoplasts. Plant Science 64: 125-132.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Chanabé, C., Burrus, M., Bidney, D. and Alibert, G. (1991) Studies on plant regeneration<lb/> from protoplasts in the genes Helianthus. Plant Cell Rep. 9: 635-638.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Dawid, I.B., Breen, J.J. and Toyama, R. (1998) LIM domains: multiple roles as adapters and<lb/> functional modifiers in protein interactions. Trends Genet. 14: 156-162.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Eliasson, A., Gass, N., Mundel, C., Baltz, R., Kräuter, R., Evrard, J.L. and Steinmetz, A.<lb/> (2000) Molecular and expression analysis of a LIM protein gene family from flowering<lb/> plants. Mol. Gen. Genet. 264: 257-267.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Freydt, G., Kim, S.K. and Horvitz, H.R. (1990) Novel cysteine-rich motif and homeodomain<lb/> in the product of the Caenorhabditis elegans cell lineage gene lin-11. Nature 344: 876-879.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Galway, M.E. and Hardham, A.R. (1989) Oryzalin-induced microtubule disassembly and<lb/> recovery in regenerating protoplasts of the alga Mougeotia. J. Plant Physiol. 135: 337-345.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Gibbon, B.C., Kovar, D.R. and Staiger, C.J. (1999) Latrunculin B has different effects on<lb/> pollen germination and tube growth. Plant Cell 11: 2349-2363.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>Herreros, L., Rodriguez-Fernandez, J. L., Brown, M. C., Alonso-Lebrero, J. L., Cabanas, C.,<lb/> Sanchez-Madrid, F., Longo, N., Turner, C. E. and Sanchez-Mateos, P. (2000) Paxillin<lb/> localizes to the lymphocyte microtubule organizing center and associates with the microtubule<lb/> cytoskeleton. J. Biol. Chem. 275: 26436-26440.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>Karlsson, O., Thor, S., Norberg, T., Ohlsson, H. and Edlund, T. (1990) Insulin gene enhancer<lb/> binding protein Isl-1 is a member of a novel class of proteins containing both a homeo-and a<lb/> Cys-His domain. Nature 344: 879-882.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kawaoka, A., Kaothien, P., Yoshida, K., Endo, S., Yamada, K. and Ebinuma, H. (2000)<lb/> Functional analysis of tobacco LIM protein NtLim involved in lignin biosynthesis. Plant J.<lb/> 22: 289-301.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kong, Y., Flick, M.J., Kudla, A.J., and Konieczny, S.F. (1997) Muscle LIM protein promotes<lb/> myogenesis by enhancing the activity of MyoD. Mol Cell Biol 17: 4750-4760.<lb/>  </bibl>
		<bibl>Laemmli, U. K. (1970) Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of<lb/> bacteriophage T4. Nature 227: 680-685.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Liu, B., Marc, J., Joshi, H.C. and Palevitz, B.A. (1993) A γ-tubulin-related protein associated<lb/> with the microtubule arrays of higher plants in a cell cycle-dependent manner. J. Cell Sci.<lb/> 104: 1217-1228.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>Liu, B., Marc, J., Joshi, H.C. and Palevitz, B.A. (1995) Experimental manipulation of γ-<lb/>tubulin distribution in Arabidopsis using anti-microtubule drugs. Cell Mot. Cytoskel. 31: 113-129.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Liu, L., White, M.J., and MacRae, T.H. (1999) Transcription factors and their genes in higher<lb/> plants. Functional domains, evolution and regulation. Eur. J. Biochem. 262: 247-257.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Louis, H.A., Pino, J.D., Schmeichel, K.L., Pomiès, P. and Beckerle, M.C. (1997) Comparison<lb/> of three members of the cysteine-rich protein family reveals functional conservation and<lb/> divergent patterns of gene expression. J. Biol. Chem. 272: 27484-27491.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>Manders, E.M.M., Verbeek, F.J. and Aten, J.A. (1993) Measurement of co-localization of<lb/> objects in dual-colour confocal images. J. Microscopy 169: 375-382.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Mils, V., Yuen Lee, S.M., Joly, W., Hang, E.W., Baldin, V.V., Waye, M.M., Ducommun, B.,<lb/> and Tsui, S.K. (2003) LIM-only protein FHL3 interacts with CDC25B2 phosphatase. Exp<lb/> Cell Res 285: 99-106.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Mundel, C., Baltz, R., Eliasson, A., Bronner, R., Gass, N., Kräuter, R., Evrard, J.L. and<lb/> Steinmetz, A. (2000) A LIM-domain protein from sunflower is localized to the cytoplasm<lb/> and/or nucleus in a wide variety of tissues and is associated with the phragmoplast in dividing<lb/> cells. Plant Mol. Biol. 42: 291-302.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Murashige, K. and Skoog, F. (1962) A revised medium for rapid growth and bioassays with<lb/> tobacco tissue cultures. Physiol. Plant. 15: 473-497.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Nix, D.A. and Beckerle, M.C. (1997) Nuclear-cytoplasmic shuttling of the focal contact<lb/> protein, zyxin: A potential mechanism for communication between sites of cell adhesion and<lb/> the nucleus. J. Cell Biol. 138: 1139-1147.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Pahl, H.L. and Baeuerle, P.A. (1996) Control of gene expression by proteolysis. Curr. Op.<lb/> Cell Biol. 8: 340-347.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Petit, M.M.R., Fradelizi, J., Golsteyn, R.M., Ayoubi, T.A.Y., Menichi, B., Louvard, D., Van<lb/> de Ven, W.J.M. and Friederich, E. (2000) LPP, an actin cytoskeleton protein related to zyxin,<lb/> harbors a nuclear export signal and transcriptional activation capacity. Mol. Biol. Cell 11:<lb/> 117-129.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Petitprez, M., Brière, C., Borin, C., Kallerhoff, J., Souvré, A. and Alibert, G. (1995)<lb/> Characterisation of protoplasts from hypocotyls of Helianthus annuus in relation to their<lb/> tissue origin. Plant Cell Tiss. Org. Cult. 41: 33-40.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Petitprez, M., Caumont, C., Barthou, H., Wright, M. and Alibert, G. (2000) Two γ-tubulin<lb/> isoforms are differentially expressed during development in Helianthus annuus. Physiol.<lb/> Plant. 111: 102-107.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Pomiès, P., Louis, H.A. and Beckerle, M.C. (1997) CRP1, a LIM domain protein implicated<lb/> in muscle differentiation, interacts with alpha-actinin. J. Cell Biol. 139: 157-168.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sadler, L., Crawford, A.W., Michelsen, J.W. and Beckerle, M.C. (1992) Zyxin and cCRP:<lb/> two interactive LIM domain proteins associated with the cytoskeleton. J. Cell Biol. 119:<lb/> 1573-1587.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Schmeichel, K.L. and Beckerle, M.C. (1994) The LIM domain is a modular protein-binding<lb/> interface. Cell 79: 211-219.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Shepherd, H.S., Ledoigt, G. and Howell, S.H. (1983) Regulation of light-harvesting<lb/> chlorophyll-binding protein (LHCP) mRNA accumulation during the cell cycle in<lb/> Chlamydomonas reinhardi. Cell 32: 99-107.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Stronach, B.E., Renfranz, P.J., Lilly, B. and Beckerle, M.C. (1999) Muscle LIM proteins are<lb/> associated with muscle sarcomeres and require dMEF2 for their expression during Drosophila<lb/> myogenesis. Mol. Biol. Cell 10: 2329-2342.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>Traas, J.A., Burgain, S. and Dumas de Vaulx, R. (1989) The organization of the cytoskeleton<lb/> during meiosis in eggplant (Solanum melongena L.): microtubules and F-actin are both<lb/> necessary for coordinated meiotic division. J. Cell Sci. 92: 541-550.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Vandromme, M., Gauthier-Rouviere, C., Lamb, N., and Fernandez, A. (1996) Regulation of<lb/> transcription factor localization: fine-tuning of gene expression. Trends Biochem Sci 21: 59-<lb/>64.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wadmann, I.A., Osada, H., Grutz, G.G., Agulnick, H., Westphal, A., Forster, T.H. and<lb/> Rabbitts, T.H. (1997) The LIM-only-protein Lmo2 is a bridging molecule assembling an<lb/> erythroid, DNA-binding complex wich includes the TAL1, E47, GATA-1, and Ldb1/NLI<lb/> proteins. EMBO J. 16: 3145-3157.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>Way, J.C. and Chalfie, M. (1988) mec-3, a homeobox-containing gene that specifies<lb/> differentiation of the touch receptor neurons in C. elegans. Cell 54: 5-16.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Whitmarsh, A.J. and Davis, R.J. (2000) Regulation of transcription factor function by<lb/> phosphorylation. Cell Mol Life Sci 57: 1172-1183.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>Yang, N., Higuchi, O., Ohashi, K., Nagata, K., Wada, A., Kangawa, K., Nishida, E. and<lb/> Mizuno, K. (1998) Cofilin phosphorylation by LIM-kinase 1 and its role in Rac-mediated<lb/> actin reorganization. Nature 393: 809-812.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

