<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>
        <bibl>Alexander, R. D. &amp; G. Borgia. 1978. Group selection, altruism, and the levels of organization of life.<lb/> Ann. Rev. Ecol. Syst. 9: 449-474.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Allard, R. W. 1975. The mating system and microevolution. Genetics 79:115-126.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; L W. Kannenberg. 1968. Population studies in predominantly self-pollinated species, XI. Ge-<lb/>netic divergence among the members of the Festuca microstachys complex. Evolution 22:517-528.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>-, S. K. Jain &amp; P. L. Workman. 1968. The genetics of inbreeding populations. Adv, Genetics 14:<lb/> 55-131.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Allem, A. C. 1991. Estudo da biologia reprodutiva de duas esp~cies florestais Aroeira e Gongalo-Alves da<lb/> Regiao do Cerrado. Pesquisa em Andamento, Cenargen 2: 1-5.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Anderson, C. 1982. A monograph of the genus Peixotoa (Malpighiaceae): Taxonomic history, anatomy<lb/> and morphology, chromosomes, distribution, apomixis, new taxa. Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb. 15:<lb/> 1-92.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Anderson, W. R. 1980. Cryptic self-fertilization in the Malpighiaceae. Science 207: 892-893.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Antonovlcs, J. &amp; D. A. Levin. 1980. The ecological and genetic consequences of density-dependent<lb/> regulation in plants. Ann. Rev. Ecol. Syst. 11:411-452.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Appanah, S. &amp; H. T. Chart. 1981. Thrips: The pollinators of some Dipterocarps. Malaysian Forester 44:<lb/> 234-252.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Aron, R. 1967. Main currents in sociological thought, 2. Pareto, Weber, Durkheim. Penguin, New York.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Arroyo, M. T. K. 1976. Geitonogamy in animal pollinated tropical angiosperms: A stimulus for the<lb/> evolution of self-incompatibility. Taxon 25: 543-548.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1979. Comments on breeding systems in neotropical forests. Pp. 371-380 in K. Larsen &amp; L. B.<lb/> Holm-Nielsen (eds.), Tropical botany. Academic Press, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ashton, P. S. 1976. An approach to the study of breeding systems, population structure and taxonomy of<lb/> tropical trees. Pp. 35-42 in J. Burley &amp; B. T. Styles (eds.), Tropical trees: Variation, breeding and<lb/> conservation. Linnaean Society Symposium Series, 2. Academic Press, London.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1977. A contribution of rain forest research to evolutionary theory. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 64:<lb/> 694-705.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1979. Some geographic trends in morphological variation in the Asian Tropics and their possible<lb/> significance. Pp. 35-48 in K. Larsen &amp; L. B. Holm-Nielsen (eds.), Tropical botany. Academic Press,<lb/> London.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1988a. Systematics and ecology of rain forest trees. Taxon 37: 622~529.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1988b. Dipterocarp biology as a window to the understanding of tropical forest structure. Ann.<lb/> Rev. Ecol. Syst. 19: 347-370.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Asker, S. 1980. Gametophytic apomixis: Elements and genetic regulation. Hereditas 93: 277-293.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Asker, S. E. &amp; L. derling. 1992. Apomixis in plants. CRC Press, Boca Raton, FL.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ayala, F. J. 1974. Biological evolution: Natural selection or random walk? Am. Sci. 62: 692-701.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--~<lb/> 1975. Genetic differentiation during the speciation process. Evolut. Biol. 8: 1-78.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ayensu, E. S. 1974. Plant and bat interactions in West Africa. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 61: 702-727.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Badillo, V. M. 1971. Monografia de la familia Caricaceae. Asociaci6n de Profesores, Universidad Central<lb/> de Venezuela, Maracay.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>BaiHon, H. 1865. Sur la parthenogenese et la suppression du genre Caelebogyne. Adansonia 6: 368-379.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Baker, H. G. 1959. Reproductive methods as factors in speciation in flowering plants. Cold Spring Har-<lb/>bor Symposium on Quantitative Biology 24: 177-191.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--..<lb/> 1960. Apomixis and polyembryony in Pachira oleaginea (Bombacaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 47:<lb/> 296-302.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1970. Evolution in the Tropics. Biotropica 2:101-111.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1976. &quot;Mistake&quot; pollination as a reproductive system with special reference to the Caricaceae.<lb/> Pp. 161-169 in J. Burley &amp; B. T. Styles (eds.), Tropical trees: Variation, breeding and conservation.<lb/> Linnaean Society Symposium Series, 2. Academic Press, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--..<lb/> 1979. Anthecology: Old testament, new testament, apocrypha. New Zeal. J. Bot. 17: 431-440.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1983. An outline of the history of anthecology, or pollination biology. Pp. 7-28 in L. Real (ed.),<lb/> Pollination biology. Academic Press, Orlando, FL.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; P. A. Cox. 1984. Further thoughts on islands and dioecism. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 71: 230-239.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>, K. S. Bawa, G. W. Frankie &amp; P. A. Opler. 1983. Reproductive biology of plants in tropical<lb/> forests. Pp. 183-215 in F. B. Golley (ed.), Tropical rain forest ecosystems: Structure and function.<lb/> Elsevier, Amsterdam.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bancilhon, L. 1971. Contribution ~t l&apos;6tude taxonomique du genre Phyllanthus (Euphorbiaceae). Boissiera<lb/> 18: 1-81, pls. 1-22.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Barlow, B. A., D. Wiens, C. Wiens, W. H. Busby &amp; C. Brighton. 1978. Permanent translocation het-<lb/>erozygosity in ~scum album and V. cruciatum, sex association, balanced lethals, sex ratios. Hered-<lb/>ity 40: 33-38.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bateman, A. J. 1952. Self-incompatibility systems in angiosperms. Heredity 6:285-310.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bawa, K. S. 1974. Breeding systems of tree species of a lowland tropical community. Evolution 28: 85-92.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>9 1979. Breeding systems of trees in a tropical wet forest. New Zeal. J. Bot. 17: 521-524.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--..<lb/> 1980. Evolution ofdioecy in flowering plants. Ann. Rev. Ecol. Syst. 11: 15-39.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--..<lb/> 1982. Outcrossing and the incidence of dioecism in island floras. Am. Nat. 119:866-871.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; P. A. Opler. 1975. Dioecism in tropical forest trees. Evolution 29: 167-179.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--.,<lb/> D. 1L Perry &amp; J. H. Beach. 1985a. Reproductive biology of tropical lowland rain forest trees,<lb/> I. Sexual systems and incompatibility mechanisms. Amer. J. Bot. 72:331-345.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>-, S. H. Bullock, D. R. Perry, R. E. Coville &amp; M. H. Grayum. 1985b. Reproductive biology of<lb/> tropical lowland rain forest trees, II. Pollination systems. Amer. J. Bot. 72: 346-356.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>---,<lb/> P. S. Ashton, R. B. Primack, d. Terborgh, S. M. Nor, F. S. P. Ng &amp; M. Hadley. 1989. Repro-<lb/>ductive ecology of tropical forest plants: Research insights and management implications. Biology<lb/> International, Special Issue, 21: 1-56.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>-,<lb/> &amp; S. M. Nor. 1990. Reproductive ecology of tropical forest plants: Management issues.<lb/> Pp. 3-13 in K. S. Bawa &amp; M. Hadley (eds.), Reproductive ecology of tropical forest plants. UNESCO<lb/> and the Parthenon Publishing Group, Paris and Camforth.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Beach, J. H. &amp; K. S. Bawa. 1980. Role of pollinators in the evolution of dioecy from distyly. Evolution<lb/> 34: 1138-1142.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bernardo, F. A., C. C. Jesena &amp; C. C. l~mirez. 1961. Parthenocarpy and apomixis in Lansium<lb/> domesticum Corr. Philippines Agricultural Review 44: 415--421.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Berry, P. E.,H. Tobe &amp; J. A. Gomez. 1991. Agamospermy and loss of distyly in Erythroxylum undulatum<lb/> from northem Venezuela. Amer. J. Bot. 78: 595-600.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Black, G. A., 2&quot;. Dobzhansky &amp; C. Pavan. 1950. Some attempts to estimate species diversity and popu-<lb/>lation density of trees in Amazonian forests. Bot. Gaz. 111: 413-425.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>B~cher, T. W. 1977. Convergence as an evolutionary process. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 75: 1-19.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bradshaw, A. D. &amp; K. Hardwick. 1989. Evolution and stress-genotypic and phenotypic components.<lb/> Biol. J. Linn. Soc. 37: 137-155.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; T. MeNeilly. 1991. Evolutionary response to global climatic change. Ann. Bot. 67 (Suppl. 1):<lb/> 5-14.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Brandon, R. N. &amp; R. M. Burlan (eds.). 1984. Genes, organisms, populations: controversies over the<lb/> units of selection. MIT Press, Cambridge.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Brown, W. L. 1983. Genetic diversity and genetic vulnerability--An appraisal. Econ. Bot. 37: 4-12.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Carman, J. G. 1997. Asynchronous expression of duplicate genes in angiosperms may cause apomixis,<lb/> bispory, tetraspory, and polyembryony. Biol. J. Linn. Soc. 61: 51-94.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Carpenter, F. L. 1976. Plant-pollinator interactions in Hawaii: Pollination energetics of Metrosideros<lb/> collina (Myrtaceae). Ecology 57:1125-1144.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Carson, H. L. 1985. Unification of speciation theory in plants and animals. Syst. Bot. 10: 380-390.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--..<lb/> 1987a. The genetic system, the deme, and the origin of species. Ann. Rev. Genet. 21:405-423<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1987b. The process whereby species originate. Bioscience 37: 715-720.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Casper, B. B. &amp; E. L. Charnov. 1982. Sex allocation in heterostylous plants. J. Theor. Biol. 96: 143-149.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Chan, H. T. 1981. Reproductive biology of some Malaysian dipterocarps, III. Breeding systems. Malay-<lb/>sian Forester 44: 28-36.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Chantaranothai, P. &amp; J. A. N. Parnell 9 1994. The breeding biology of some Thai Syzygium species.<lb/> Trop. Ecol. 35: 199-208.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Chapman, G. P. &amp; C. D. Darlington. 1992. Apomixis and evolution. Pp. 138-155 in G. P. Chapman<lb/> (ed.), Grass evolution and domestication. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Clausen, J. 1951. Stages in the evolution of plant species. Comell University Press, Ithaca.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1954. Partial apomixis as an equilibrium system in evolution. Caryologia (Vol. Suppl.): 469-479.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; W. M. Hiesey. 1958. Experimental studies on the nature of species, IV. Genetic structure of<lb/> ecological races. Carnegie Institute of Washington Publications 615: 1-312.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>---,<lb/> D. D. Keck &amp; W. M. Hiesey. 1940. Experimental studies on the nature of species, I. Effect of<lb/> varied environments on western North American plants. Carnegie Institute of Washington Publica-<lb/>tions 520: 1-452.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>-,<lb/> &amp;<lb/> .1945. Experimental studies on the nature of species, II. Plant evolution through<lb/> amphiploidy and autoploidy, with examples from the Madiinae. Carnegie Institute of Washington<lb/> Publications 564: 1-174.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>&amp; --.<lb/> 1947. Heredity of geographically and ecologically isolated races. Am. Nat.<lb/> 81: 114-133.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>, --<lb/>&amp;<lb/> . 1948. Experimental studies on the nature of species, III. Environmental re-<lb/>sponses of climatic races of Achillea. Carnegie Institute of Washington Publications 581: 1-129.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Connor, H. E. 1979. Breeding systems in the grasses: A survey. New Zeal. J. Bot. 17: 547-574.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Costa, R. B., P. Y. Kageyama &amp; G. Mariano. 1992. Estudo do sistema de cruzamento de Anadenanthera<lb/> falcata Benth. Vochysia tucanorum Mart. e Xylopia aromatica Baill. e ~rea de Cerrado. Rev. Brasil.<lb/> Sementes 14: 93-96.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Cox, P. A. 1989. Baker&apos;s Law: Plant breeding systems and island colonization. Pp. 209-224 in J. H. Bock<lb/> &amp; Y. B. Linhart (eds.), The evolutionary ecology of plants. Westview Press: Boulder, CO.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1990. Pollination and the evolution of breeding systems in Pandanaceae. Ann. Missouri Bot.<lb/> Gard. 77: 816-840.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Crestana, C. M. S. 1995. Ecologia da poliniza~;~o de Genipa americana L. (Rubiaceae) na Esta~o<lb/> Ecolrgica de Moji-Gua~u, estado de S~o Paulo. Revista do Instituto Florestal, S~lo Paulo, 7: 169-<lb/>195.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Crisp, P. 1976. Trends in the breeding and cultivation of cruciferous crops. Pp. 69-118 in J. G. Vaughan,<lb/> A. J. Macleod &amp; B. M. Ct Jones (eds.), The biology and chemistry of the Cruciferae. Academic<lb/> Press, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Cronquist, A. 1987. A botanical critique of cladism. Bot. Rev. 53:1-52<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Cuatreeasas, J. 1964. Cacao and its allies: A taxonomic revision of the genus Theobroma. Contr. U.S.<lb/> Natl. Herb. 35: 379-614.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Darlington, C. D. 1939. The evolution of genetic systems. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1958. Evolution of genetic systems. Ed. 2. Oliver and Boyd, Edinburgh.<lb/> 9 1963. Chromosome botany and the origins of cultivated plants, Ed. 2. Allen and Unwin, London.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; K. Mather. 1949. The elements of genetics. Allen and Unwin, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Darwin, C. 1981 [1859]. The origin of species. Harmondsworth, England, Penguin.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1878. The effects of cross and self fertilization in the vegetable kingdom. Ed. 2. John Murray,<lb/> London.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1882. The various contrivances by which orchids are fertilised by insects. Ed. 2. John Murray,<lb/> London.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Davis, J. I. &amp; A. J. Gilmartin. 1985. Morphological variation and speciation. Syst. Bot. 10: 417--425.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Dawldns, R. 1989. The selfish gene. Ed. 2. Oxford University Press, Oxford.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Dobzhansky, T. 1937. Genetic nature of species differences. Am. Nat. 71: 404-420.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1940. Speciation as a stage in evolutionary divergence. Am. Nat. 74: 312-321.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1950. Mendelian populations and their evolution. Am. Nat. 84: 401-418.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1956. What is an adaptive trait? Am. Nat. 90: 337-347.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1959. Variation and evolution. Proc. Amer. Phil. Soc. 103: 252-263.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1966. Are naturalists old-fashioned? Am. Nat. 100: 541-550.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1968. Adaptedness and fitness. Pp. 109-121 in R. C. Lewontin (ed.), Population biology and<lb/> evolution. Syracuse University Press, Syracuse, NY.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>, F. J. Ayala, G. L. Stebbins &amp; J. W. Valentine 9 1977. Evolution. W. H. Freeman, San Francisco.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ehrendorfer, 17. 1968. Geographical and ecological aspects of infraspecific differentiation. Pp. 261-296<lb/> in V. H. Heywood (ed.), Modem methods in plant taxonomy. Academic Press, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ehrlich, P. R. &amp; E H. Raven. 1969. Differentiation of populations. Science 165: 1228-1232.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Eldredge, N. 1985. Time frames: The rethinking of Darwinian evolution and the theory of punctuated<lb/> equilibria. Simon &amp; Schuster, New York.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ellstrand, N. C. &amp; D. A. Levin. 1980. Recombination system and population structure in Oenotheru.<lb/> Evolution 34: 923-933.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Elumeev, E.A. 1976. Peculiarities of flower structure, flowering and fruiting in Eleutherococcus senticosus.<lb/> Pp. 248-252 in S. S. Khokhlov (ed.), Apomixis and breeding. B. R. Sharma, transl. Amerind, New<lb/> Delhi.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Faegri, K. &amp; L. van der Pijl. 1979. The principles of pollination ecology. Ed. 3. Oxford University Press,<lb/> Oxford.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Fedorov, A. A. 1966. The structure of the tropical rain forest and speciation in the Humid Tropics. J. Ecol.<lb/> 54:1-11.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Fleming, T. H. &amp; E. R. Heithaus. 1981. Frugivorous bats, seed shadows, and the structure of tropical<lb/> forests. Biotropica 13: 45-53.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Frankie, G. W. 1975. Tropical forest phenology and pollinator plant coevolution. Pp. 192-209 in L. E.<lb/> Gilbert &amp; P. H. Raven (eds.), Coevolution of animals and plants. University of Texas, Austin.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1976. Pollination of widely dispersed trees by animals in Central America, with an emphasis on<lb/> bee pollination systems. Pp. 151-159 in J. Burley &amp; B. T. Styles (eds.), Tropical trees: Variation,<lb/> breeding and conservation. Linnaean Society Symposium Series, 2. Academic Press, London.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>9 , P. A. Opler &amp; K. S. Bawa. 1976. Foraging behaviour of solitary bees: Implications for outcross-<lb/>ing ofa neotropical forest tree species. J. Ecol. 64: 1049-1057.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Frost, H. B. 1926. Polyembryony, heterozygosis and vhimeras in Citrus. Hilgardia 1: 365-402.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Fryxell, P. A. 1957. Mode of reproduction of higher plants. Bot. Rev. 23: 135-233.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Givnish, T. J. 1982. Outcrossing Versus ecological constraints in the evolution of dioecy. Am. Nat. 119:<lb/> 849-865.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Goldenberg, R. &amp; G. J. Shepherd 9 1998. Studies on the reproductive biology of Melastomataceae in<lb/> &quot;Cerrado&quot; vegetation. P1. Syst. Evol. 211: 13-29.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Gould, S. J. &amp; R. C. Lewontin. 1979. The spandrels of San Marco and the Panglossian paradigm: A<lb/> critique of the adaptationist programme. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, Series B. 205:<lb/> 581-598.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Grant, V. 1958. The regulation of recombination in plants. Cold Spring Harbor Symposium on Quantita-<lb/>tive Biology 23: 337-363.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1963. The origin of adaptations. Columbia University Press, New York.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1964. The architecture of the germplasm. John Wiley and Sons, New York.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1975. Genetics of flowering plants. Columbia University Press, New York.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1977. Organismic evolution. W. H. Freeman, San Francisco.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1980. Gene flow and the homogeneity of species populations. Biologisches Zentralblatt 99:<lb/> 157-169.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1981. Plant speciation. Ed. 2. Columbia University Press, New York.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Gupta, P., K. R. Shivanna, H. Y. M. Ram &amp; P. Gupta. 1996. Apomixis and polyembryony in the guggul<lb/> plant, Commiphora wightii. Ann. Bot. 78: 67-72.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Gustafsson, A. 1947. Apomixis in higher plants, 1I. The causal aspect of apomixis. Lunds Universitat<lb/> Arsskriet 43: 69-178, 181-370.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ha, C. O., V. E. Sands, E. Soepadmo &amp; K. Jong. 1988. Reproductive patterns of selected understorey<lb/> trees in the Malaysian rain forest: The apomictic species. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 97: 317-331.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Hamriek, J. L. 1979. Genetic variation and longevity. Pp. 84-113 In O. T. Solbrig, S. Jain, G. B. Johnson<lb/> &amp; P. H. Raven (eds.), Topics in plant population biology. Columbia University Press, New York.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; M. D. Loveless. 1989. The genetic structure of tropical tree populations: Associations with<lb/> reproductive biology. Pp. t29-146 in J. H. Bock&amp; Y. B. Linhart (eds.), The evolutionary ecology of<lb/> plants. Westview Press, Boulder, CO.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Hanna, W. W. &amp; E. C. Bashaw. 1987. Apomixis: Its identification and use in plant breeding. Crop<lb/> Science 27: 1136-1139.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Heithans, E. R., E A. Opler &amp; H. G. Baker. 1974. Bat activity and pollination of Bauhinia pauletia:<lb/> Plant-pollinator coevolution. Ecology 55: 412-419.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Heslop-Harrison, J. 1966. Reflections on the role of environmentally-governed reproductive versatility<lb/> in the adaptation of plant populations. Transactions Proceedings of the Botanical Society of Edinburgh<lb/> 40: 159-168.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Hiekman, J. C. 1979. The basic biology of plant numbers. Pp. 232-263 in O. T. Solbrig, S. Jain, (3. B.<lb/> Johnson &amp; P. H. Raven (eds.), Topics in plant population biology. Columbia University Press, New<lb/> York.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Howe, H. E 1977. Bird activity and seed dispersal of a tropical wet forest tree. Ecology 58: 539-550.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; G. E Estabrook. 1977. On intraspecific competition for avian dispersers in tropical trees. Am.<lb/> Nat. lll: 817-832.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; J. Smallwood. 1982. Ecology of seed dispersal. Ann. Rev. Ecol. Syst. 13: 201-228.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Huxley, J. 1942. Evolution: The modem synthesis. Allen and Unwin, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Imam, A. G. &amp; R. W. Allard. 1965. Population studies in predominantly self-pollinated species, VI.<lb/> Genetic variability between and within natural populations of wild oats from differing habitats in<lb/> California. Genetics 51:49--62.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Join, S. K. 1975. Population structure and the effects of breeding system. Pp. 15-36 in O. H. Frankel &amp;<lb/> J. G. Hawkes (eds.), Crop genetic resources for today and tomorrow. Cambridge University Press,<lb/> Cambridge.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1976. The evolution of inbreeding in plants. Ann. Rev. Ecol. Syst. 7: 469-495.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; R. W. Allard. 1966. The effects of linkage, epistasis and inbreeding on population changes<lb/> under selection. Genetics 53: 633~i59.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Janzen, D. H. 1971. Euglossine bees as long-distance pollinators of tropical plants. Science 171: 203-<lb/>205.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kaur, A., C. O. Ha, K. Jong, V. E. Sands, H. T. Chart, E. Soepadmo &amp; P. S. Ashton. 1978. Apomixis<lb/> may be widespread among trees of the climax rain forest. Nature 271: 440-442.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>, K. dong, V. E. Sands &amp; E. Soepadmo. 1986. Cytoembryology of some Malaysian dipterocarps,<lb/> with some evidence of apomixis. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 92: 75-88.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Khokhlov, S. S. 1976. Evolutionary-genetic problems of apomixis in angiosperms. Pp. 3-17 in S. S.<lb/> Khokhlov (ed.), Apomixis and breeding. B. R. Sharma, transl. Amerind, New Delhi.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Knox, P. B. 1967. Apomixis: Seasonal and population differences in a grass. Science 157: 325-326.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Koltunow, A. M. 1993. Apomixis: Embryo sacs and embryos formed without meiosis or fertilization in<lb/> ovules. Plant Cell 5: 1425-1437.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kroodsma, D. E. 1975. Flight distances of male euglosssine bees in orchid pollination. Biotropica 7:<lb/> 71-72.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kruekeberg, A. R. 1986. An essay: The stimulus of unusual geologies for plant speciation. Syst. Bot. 11:<lb/> 455-463.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kupriyanov, P. G. 1986. The role of apomictic genetic complexes in the flora and the evolutionary sig-<lb/>nificance of apomixis in flowering plants, lstochniki lnformatsii V Filogeneticheskoi Sistematike<lb/> Rastenie. V. N. Tikhomirov, ed. Vllth Moscow Conference on Plant Phylogeny, 23-25 December,<lb/> 1986. Vol. 2. Moscow: Nauka, 38-40 (in Russian).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Levin, D. A. 1972. Competition for pollinator service: A stimulus for the evolution of autogamy. Evolu-<lb/>tion 26: 668-669.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1975. Pest pressure and recombination systems in plants. Am. Nat. 109: 437-451.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>-<lb/>-<lb/>&amp; H. W. Kerster. 1974. Gene flow in seed plants. Evolut. Biol. 7: 139-220.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lewis, D. 1942. The evolution of sex in flowering plants. Biol. Rev. 17: 46-67.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lewis, H. 1963. The taxonomic problems of inbreeders or how to solve any taxonomic problem. Regnum<lb/> Vegetabile 27: 37-44.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lewontin, R. C. 1957. The adaptations of populations to varying environments. Cold Spring Harbor<lb/> Symposium on Quantitative Biology 22: 395-408.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1970. The units of selection. Ann. Rev. Ecol. Syst.l: 1-18.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1974. The genetic basis of evolutionary change. Columbia University Press, New York.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1985. Population genetics. Ann. Rev. Genet. 19: 81-102.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lloyd, D. G. 1979a. Evolution towards dioecy in heterostylous populations. PI. Syst. Evol. 131:71-80.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1979b. Parental strategies of angiosperms. New Zeal. J. Bot. 17: 595-606.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>9 1979e. Some reproductive factors affecting the selection of self-fertilization in plants. Am. Nat.<lb/> 113: 67-79.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lord, E. M. 1981. Cleistogamy: A tool for the study of floral morphogenesis, function and evolution. Bot.<lb/> Rev. 47: 421--449.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Love, A. 1960. Biosystematics and classification of apomicts. Feddes Repertorium 63: 136-148.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lugada, E. N. &amp; C. Proenea. 1996. A survey of the reproductive biology of the Myrtoideae (Myrtaceae).<lb/> Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 83(4): 480-503.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Maguire, B. 1976. Apomixis in the genus Clusia (Clusiaceae): A preliminary report. Taxon 25: 241-244.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Maseie-Taylor, C. G. N., J. B. Gibson &amp; J. M. Thoday. 1986. Effects of disruptive selection, XI. Gene<lb/> flow and divergence. Heredity 57: 407-413.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Mather, K. 1943. Polygenic inheritance and natural selection. Biol. Rev. 18: 32-64.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1955. Polymorphism as an outcome of disruptive selection. Evolution 9: 52-61.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>9 1966. Breeding systems and response to selection. Pp. 13-19 in J. G. Hawkes (ed.), Reproductive<lb/> biology and taxonomy of vascular plants. Pergamon Press, Oxford.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Maynard Smith, J. 1962. Disruptive selection, polymorphism and sympatric speciation. Nature 195:<lb/> 60-62.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1964. Group selection and kin selection. Nature 201:1145-1147.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1966. Sympatric speciation. Am. Nat. 100: 637-650.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1976. Group selection. Quart. Rev. Biol. 51: 277-283.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1978. Optimization theory in evolution. Ann. Rev. Ecol. Syst. 9: 31-56.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Mayr, E. 1940. Speciating phenomena in birds. Am. Nat. 74: 249-278.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1947. Ecological factors in speciation. Evolution 1: 263-288.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--..<lb/> 1955. Integration of genotypes: Synthesis. Cold Spring Harbor Symposium on Quantitative Biol-<lb/>ogy 20: 327-333.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1963. Animal species and evolution. Oxford University Press, London.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--..<lb/> 1969. The biological meaning of species. Biol. J. Linn. Soc. 1:311-320.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--~<lb/> 1970. Populations, species and evolution. Belknap Press, Cambridge.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>9 1982. The growth of biological thought: Diversity, evolution, and inheritance. Belknap Press of<lb/> Harvard University Press, Cambridge.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--..<lb/> 1983. How to carry out the adaptationist program? Am. Nat. 121: 324-334.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Meln, G. F. A. 1995. Biologia floral e sistema reprodutivo de cinco esp6cies de Melastomataceae na mata de<lb/> Dois Irmiios, Recife, Pernambuco. M.S. thesis, Universidade Federal de Pernambuco, Recife, Brazil.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>-<lb/>-<lb/>&amp; I. C. Machado. 1996. Biologia da reprodu95o de Henriettea succosa DC. (Melastomataceae).<lb/> Rev. Brasil. Biol. 56: 383-389.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Mogie, M. 1986. On the relationship between asexual reproduction and polyploidy. J. Theor. Biol. 122:<lb/> 493-498.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>---.<lb/> 1992. The evolution of asexual reproduction in plants. Chapman and Hall, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Murawski, D. A. &amp; K. S. Bawa. 1994. Genetic structure and mating system of Stemonoporus oblongifolius<lb/> (Dipterocarpaceae) in Sri Lanka. Amer. J. Bot. 81: 155-160.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Naumova, T. N. 1993. Apomixis in angiosperms: Nucellar and integumentary embryony. CRC Press,<lb/> Boca Raton, FL.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Nygren, A. 1954. Apomixis in the angiosperms, II. Bot. Rev. 20: 577~49.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Obeso, J. R. 1996. Producci6n de frutos y semillas en Ilex aquifolium L. (Aquifoliaceae). Anales del<lb/> Jardin Bot~inico de Madrid 54: 533-539.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Oliveira, P. E., P. E. Gibbs, A. A. Barhosa &amp; S. Talavera. 1992. Contrasting breeding systems in two<lb/> Eriotheca (Bombacaceae) species of the Brazilian Cerrados. P1. Syst. Evol. 179: 207-219.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ornduff, R. 1970. Pathways and patterns of evolution: A discussion. Taxon 19: 202-204.<lb/> Percival, M. S. 1965. Floral biology. Pergamon Press, Oxford.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Piedade, L. H. &amp; N. T. Ranga. 1993. Ecologia da polinizagAo de Galipeajasminiflora Engler (Rutaceae).<lb/> Rev. Brasil. Bot. 16: 151-158.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Popper, K. 1982. Unended quest: An intellectual autobiography. FontanaJCollins, Glasgow.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Proctor, M. &amp; P. Yeo. 1973. The pollination of flowers. Collins, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Quarin, C. L. 1986. Seasonal changes in the incidence of apomixis of diploid, triploid, and tetraploid<lb/> plants of Paspalum cromyorrhizon. Euphytica 35: 515-522.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Randell, B. R. 1970. Adaptations in the genetic system of Australian arid zone Cassia species (Leguminosae,<lb/> Caesalpinioideae). Austral. Bot. 18: 77-97.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Raven, P. H. 1976. Systematics and plant population biology. Syst. But. l: 284-316.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1977. The systematics and evolution of higher plants. Pp. 59-83 in C. E. Goulden (ed.), Chang-<lb/>ing scenes in natural sciences, 1776-1976. Special Publication 12. Academy of Natural Sciences,<lb/> Philadelphia.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Riehards, A. J. 1986. Plant breeding systems. Allen and Unwin, London.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 . 1990a. Studies in Garcinia, dioecious tropical forest trees: Agamospermy. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 103:<lb/> 233-250.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1990b. Studies in Garcinia, dioecious tropical fruit trees: The origin of the mangosteen<lb/> (G mangostana L.). Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 103: 301-308.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1990c. Studies in Garcinia, dioecious tropical forest trees: The phenology, pollination biology<lb/> and fertilization of G. hombroniana Pierre. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 103: 251-261.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1996. Breeding systems in flowering plants and the control of variability. Folia Geobotanica et<lb/> Phytotaxonomica, Praha, 31: 283-293.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Runemark, H. 1970. The role of small populations for the differentiation in plants. Taxon 19: 196-201.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Salomio, A. N. &amp; A. C. Allem. 2001. Polyembryony in angiospermous trees of the Brazilian Cerrado and<lb/> Caatinga vegetation. Acta Bot. Bras. 15: 369-378.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Saraiva, L. C., O. C6sar &amp; R. Monteiro. 1996. Breeding systems of shrubs and trees of a Brazilian<lb/> savanna. Arquivos de Biologia e Tecnologia, S~o Paulo, 39: 751-763.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Seharloo, W. 1989. Developmental and physiological aspects of reaction norms. Bioscience 39: 464-<lb/>471.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sehemske, D. W. 1980. Floral ecology and hummingbird pollination of Combretum farinosum in Costa<lb/> Rica. Biotropica 12: 169-181.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Schliehting, C. D. 1989. Phenotypic integration and environmental change. Bioscience 39: 460-464.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Simpson, G. G. 1953. The major features of evolution. Columbia University Press, New York.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Smith, J. 1841. Notice of a plant which produces perfect seeds without any apparent action of pollen.<lb/> Transactions of the Linnaean Society of London 18: 509-512, table 36.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Snaydon, R. W. &amp; T. M. Davies. 1982. Rapid divergence of plant populations in response to recent<lb/> changes in soil conditions. Evolution 36: 289-297.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Solbrig, O. T. 1976a. On the relative advantages of cross and self-fertilization. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard.<lb/> 63: 262-276.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1976b. Plant population biology: An overview. Syst. Bot. l: 202-208.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1979. A cost-benefit analysis of recombination in plants. Pp. 114-130 in O. T. Solbrig, S. Jain,<lb/> G. B. Johnson &amp; P. H. Raven (eds.), Topics in plant population biology. Columbia University Press,<lb/> New York.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Staee, C. A. 1980. Plant taxonomy and biosystematics. Edward Arnold, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Stearns, S. C. 1989. The evolutionary significance of phenotypic plasticity. Bioscience 39: 436-445.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Stebbins, G. L. 1941. Apomixis in the angiosperms. Bot. Rev. 7: 507-542.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1957. Self-fertilisation and population variability in the higher plants. Am. Nat. 91: 337-354.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1958. Longevity, habitat, and release of genetic variability in the higher plants. Cold Spring<lb/> Harbor Symposium on Quantitative Biology 23: 365-378.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1968. Integration of development and evolutionary progress. Pp. 17-36 in R. C. Lewontin (ed.),<lb/> Population biology and evolution. Syracuse University Press, Syracuse.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1970. Variation and evolution in plants: Progress during the past twenty years. Pp. 173-208 in<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>M. K. Hecht &amp; W. C. Steere (eds.), Essays in evolution and genetics in honor of Theodosius<lb/> Dobzhansky: A supplement to evolutionary biology. Appleton-Century-Crofts, New York.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1972. Ecological distribution of centers of major adaptive radiation in angiosperms. Pp. 7-34 in<lb/> D. H. Valentine (ed.), Taxonomy, phytogeography and evolution. Academic Press, New York.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1974. Flowering plants: Evolution above the species level. Edward Arnold, London.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1981. Why are there so many species of flowering plants? Bioscience 31: 573-577.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1985. Polyploidy, hybridization, and the invasion of new habitats. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 72:<lb/> 824-832.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Stiles, E G. 1978. Temporal organization of flowering among the hummingbird food-plants of a tropi-<lb/>cal wet forest. Biotropica 10: 194-210.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Stout, A. B. 1938. The genetics of incompatibilities in homomorphic flowering plants. Bot. Rev. 4:<lb/> 275-369.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Thoday, J. M. 1972. Review lecture: Disruptive selection. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London,<lb/> Series B, 182: 109-143.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>--<lb/>&amp; J. B. Gibson 9 1962. Isolation by disruptive selection. Nature 193:1164-1166.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Thomas, S. C. 1997. Geographic parthenogenesis in a tropical forest tree. Amer. J. Bot. 84: 1012-1015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Tisserat, B., E. B. Esan &amp; T. Murashige. 1979. Somatic embryogenesis in angiosperms. Horticultural<lb/> Review l: 1-78.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Tiiresson, G. 1922a. The species and the variety as ecological units. Hereditas 3: 100-113.<lb/> 9 1922b. The genotypical response of the plant species to the habitat. Hereditas 3:211-350.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1925. The plant species in relation to habitat and climate. Hereditas 6: 147-236.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1930. The selective effect of climate upon the plant species. Hereditas 14: 99-152.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Turrill, W. B. 1964. Plant taxonomy, phytogeography, and plant ecology. Pp. 187-224 in J. Ct W. B.<lb/> TurriU (ed.), Vistas in botany. Macmillan, New York.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Uphof, J. C. T. 1938. Cleistogamic flowers. But. Rev. 4: 21--49.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Urbanska-Worytkiewiez, K. 1974. L&apos;Agamospermie, systrme de reproduction important dans la sprciation<lb/> des angiospermes. Bulletin de la Societ6 Botanique de France 121: 329-346.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Van tier Pijl, L. 1960. Ecological aspects of flower evolution, I. Phyletic evolution. Evolution 14:<lb/> 403-416.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--..<lb/> 1969. Evolutionary action of tropical animals on the reproduction of plants. Biol. J. Linn. Soc. 1:<lb/> 85-96.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>---.<lb/> 1978. Reproductive integration and sexual disharmony in floral functions. Pp. 79-88 in A. J.<lb/> Richards (ed.), The pollination of flowers by insects. Linnaean Society Symposium Series, 6. Aca-<lb/>demic Press, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Van Steenis, C.G.G.J. 1969. Plant speciation in Malesia, with special reference to the theory of non-<lb/>adaptive saltatory evolution. Biol. J. Linn. Soc. 1: 97-133.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Waddington, C. H. 1959. Canalization of development and genetic assimilation of acquired characters.<lb/> Nature 183: 1654-1655.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Webb, C. J. &amp; K. S. Bawa. 1983. Pollen dispersal by hummingbirds and butterflies: A comparative study<lb/> of two lowland tropical plants. Evolution 37: 1258-1270.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Webster, G. L. 1967. The genera of Euphorbiaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arb. 48:<lb/> 303-361, 363-430.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Whitmore, I&quot;. C. 1975. Tropical rain forests of the Far East. Clarendon Press, Oxford.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Wilkins, D. A. 1968. The scale of genecological differentiation. Pp. 227-239 in V. H. Heywood (ed.),<lb/> Modern methods in plant taxonomy. Academic Press, London.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Williams, G. C. 1966. Adaptation and natural selection: A critique of some current evolutionary thought.<lb/> Princeton University Press, Princeton, NJ.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>. 1975. Sex and evolution. Princeton University Press, Princeton, NJ.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>9 1979. The question of adaptive sex ration in outcrnssed vertebrates. Proceedings of the Royal<lb/> Society of London, Series B, 205: 567-580.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wilison, M. E 1979. Sexual selection in plants. Am. Nat. 113: 777-790.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1982. Sexual selection and dicliny in angiosperms. Am. Nat. 119: 579-583.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wright, S. 1940. Breeding structure of populations in relation to speciation. Am. Nat. 74: 232-248.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>--.<lb/> 1978, Evolution and the genetics of populations, 1. Variability within and among natural popula-<lb/>tions. University of Chicago Press, Chicago.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wyatt, R. 1983. Pollinator-plant interactions and the evolution of breeding systems. Pp. 51-95 in L. Real<lb/> (ed.), Pollination biology. Academic Press, Orlando, FL.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Zang, G, G. &amp; T. N. Zhao. 1996. Preliminary report of agamic complex in Boehmeria. China&apos;s Fibre<lb/> Crops 1:19 (in Chinese).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Zapata, T. R. &amp; M. T. K. Arroyo. 1978. Plant reproductive ecology of a secondary deciduous tropical<lb/> forest in Venezuela. Biotropica 10: 221-230.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

