<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Arnon, J., Meirow, D., Lewis-Roness, H., &amp; Ornoy, A. (2001). Genetic and teratogenic effects of<lb/> cancer treatments on gametes and embryos. Human Reproduction Update, 7(4), 394-403.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1093/HUMUPD/7.4.394<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Braun, R. E., Behringer, R. R., Peschon, J. J., Brinster, R. L., &amp; Palmiter, R. D. (1989).<lb/>  Genetically haploid spermatids are phenotypically diploid. Nature, 337(6205), 373-6.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1038/337373a0<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Brodsky, M. H., Weinert, B. T., Tsang, G., Rong, Y. S., McGinnis, N. M., Golic, K. G., …<lb/> Rubin, G. M. (2004). Drosophila melanogaster MNK/Chk2 and p53 regulate multiple DNA<lb/> repair and apoptotic pathways following DNA damage. Molecular and Cellular Biology,<lb/> 24(3), 1219-31. Retrieved from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14729967<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Cheng, J., Türkel, N., Hemati, N., Fuller, M. T., Hunt, A. J., &amp; Yamashita, Y. M. (2008).<lb/>  Centrosome misorientation reduces stem cell division during ageing. Nature, 456(7222),<lb/> 599-604. http://doi.org/10.1038/nature07386<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Chiang, A. C.-Y., Yang, H., &amp; Yamashita, Y. M. (2017). spict, a cyst cell-specific gene,<lb/> regulates starvation-induced spermatogonial cell death in the Drosophila testis. Scientific<lb/> Reports, 7, 40245. http://doi.org/10.1038/srep40245<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ciccia, A., &amp; Elledge, S. J. (2010). The DNA Damage Response: Making It Safe to Play with<lb/> Knives. Molecular Cell, 40(2), 179-204. http://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2010.09.019<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Cox, R. T. (2003). A Balbiani body and the fusome mediate mitochondrial inheritance during<lb/> Drosophila oogenesis. Development, 130(8), 1579-1590. http://doi.org/10.1242/dev.00365<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>de Cuevas, M., Lee, J. K., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (1996). alpha-spectrin is required for germline cell<lb/> division and differentiation in the Drosophila ovary. Development, 122(12).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>de Cuevas, M., Lilly, M., &amp; Spradling, A. (1997). GERMLINE CYST FORMATION IN<lb/> DROSOPHILA. Annual Review of Genetics, 31(1), 405-428.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.genet.31.1.405<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Decotto, E., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (2005). The Drosophila Ovarian and Testis Stem Cell Niches:<lb/> Similar Somatic Stem Cells and Signals. Developmental Cell, 9(4), 501-510.<lb/>  http://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2005.08.012<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Fairchild, M. J., Smendziuk, C. M., &amp; Tanentzapf, G. (2015). A somatic permeability barrier<lb/> around the germline is essential for Drosophila spermatogenesis. Development, 142(2),<lb/> 268-281. http://doi.org/10.1242/dev.114967<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Fu, K. K., Phillips, T. L., Heilbron, D. C., Ross, G., &amp; Kane, L. J. (1979). Relative Biological<lb/> Effectiveness of Low-and High-LET Radiotherapy Beams for Jejunal Crypt Cell Survival<lb/> at Low Doses Per Fraction. Radiology, 132(1), 205-209. http://doi.org/10.1148/132.1.205<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Fuller, M. T. (1993). Spermatogenesis. In The Development of Drosophila melanogaster. In The<lb/> Development of Drosophila melanogaster (Vol. 1, pp. 71-147). New York: Cold Spring<lb/> Harbor Laboratory Press.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Greenbaum, M. P., Iwamori, T., Buchold, G. M., &amp; Matzuk, M. M. (2011). Germ cell<lb/> intercellular bridges. Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology, 3(8), a005850.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1101/cshperspect.a005850<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Gunes, S., Al-Sadaan, M., &amp; Agarwal, A. (2015). Spermatogenesis, DNA damage and DNA<lb/> repair mechanisms in male infertility. Reproductive BioMedicine Online, 31(3), 309-319.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1016/j.rbmo.2015.06.010<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Haglund, K., Nezis, I. P., &amp; Stenmark, H. (2011). Structure and functions of stable intercellular<lb/> bridges formed by incomplete cytokinesis during development. Communicative &amp;<lb/> Integrative Biology, 4(1), 1-9. http://doi.org/10.4161/cib.4.1.13550<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Huynh, J.-R., &amp; St Johnston, D. (2004). The Origin of Asymmetry: Early Polarisation of the<lb/> Drosophila Germline Cyst and Oocyte. Current Biology, 14(11), R438-R449.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2004.05.040<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Igaki, T., Suzuki, Y., Tokushige, N., Aonuma, H., Takahashi, R., &amp; Miura, M. (2007). Evolution<lb/> of mitochondrial cell death pathway: Proapoptotic role of HtrA2/Omi in Drosophila.<lb/> Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications, 356(4), 993-997.<lb/>  http://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2007.03.079<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Khan, F. S., Fujioka, M., Datta, P., Fernandes-Alnemri, T., Jaynes, J. B., &amp; Alnemri, E. S.<lb/> (2008). The interaction of DIAP1 with dOmi/HtrA2 regulates cell death in Drosophila. Cell<lb/> Death and Differentiation, 15(6), 1073-83. http://doi.org/10.1038/cdd.2008.19<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lei, L., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (2016). Mouse oocytes differentiate through organelle enrichment<lb/> from sister cyst germ cells. Science, 352(6281), 95-99.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1126/science.aad2156<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lilly, M. A., de Cuevas, M., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (2000). Cyclin A Associates with the Fusome<lb/> during Germline Cyst Formation in the Drosophila Ovary. Developmental Biology, 218(1),<lb/> 53-63. http://doi.org/10.1006/dbio.1999.9570<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lim, J. G. Y., &amp; Fuller, M. T. (2012). Somatic cell lineage is required for differentiation and not<lb/> maintenance of germline stem cells in Drosophila testes. Proceedings of the National<lb/> Academy of Sciences, 109(45), 18477-18481. http://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1215516109<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lin, H., Yue, L., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (1994). The Drosophila fusome, a germline-specific<lb/> organelle, contains membrane skeletal proteins and functions in cyst formation.<lb/>  Development (Cambridge, England), 120(4), 947-56. Retrieved from<lb/> http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7600970<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Madigan, J. P., Chotkowski, H. L., &amp; Glaser, R. L. (2002). DNA double-strand break-induced<lb/> phosphorylation of Drosophila histone variant H2Av helps prevent radiation-induced<lb/> apoptosis. Nucleic Acids Research, 30(17), 3698-705. Retrieved from<lb/> http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12202754<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Meistrich, M. L. (2013). Effects of chemotherapy and radiotherapy on spermatogenesis in<lb/> humans. Fertility and Sterility, 100(5), 1180-1186.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1016/j.fertnstert.2013.08.010<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Oakberg, E. F. (1955). Sensitivity and Time of Degeneration of Spermatogenic Cells Irradiated<lb/> in Various Stages of Maturation in the Mouse Sensitivity and Time of Degeneration of<lb/> Spermatogenic Cells Irradiated in Various Stages of Maturation in the Mouse&amp;quot;&apos;2.<lb/> Source: Radiation Research, 2(4), 369-391. Retrieved from<lb/> http://www.jstor.org/stable/3570245<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Pepling, M. E., de Cuevas, M., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (1999). Germline cysts: a conserved phase of<lb/> germ cell development? Trends in Cell Biology, 9(7), 257-62.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1016/S0962-8924(99)01594-9<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Peters, M., DeLuca, C., Hirao, A., Stambolic, V., Potter, J., Zhou, L., … Mak, T. W. (2002).<lb/>  Chk2 regulates irradiation-induced, p53-mediated apoptosis in Drosophila. Proceedings of<lb/> the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 99(17), 11305-10.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.172382899<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Song, Y.-H. (2005). Drosophila melanogaster: a model for the study of DNA damage checkpoint<lb/> response. Molecules and Cells, 19(2), 167-79. Retrieved from<lb/> http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15879698<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Tain, L. S., Chowdhury, R. B., Tao, R. N., Plun-Favreau, H., Moisoi, N., Martins, L. M., …<lb/> Tapon, N. (2009). Drosophila HtrA2 is dispensable for apoptosis but acts downstream of<lb/> PINK1 independently from Parkin. Cell Death and Differentiation, 16(8), 1118-1125.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1038/cdd.2009.23<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Takada, S., Collins, E. R., &amp; Kurahashi, K. (2015). The FHA domain determines Drosophila<lb/> Chk2/Mnk localization to key mitotic structures and is essential for early embryonic DNA<lb/> damage responses. Molecular Biology of the Cell, 26(10), 1811-28.<lb/>  http://doi.org/10.1091/mbc.E14-07-1238<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Takada, S., Kelkar, A., &amp; Theurkauf, W. E. (2003). Drosophila Checkpoint Kinase 2 Couples<lb/> Centrosome Function and Spindle Assembly to Genomic Integrity. Cell, 113(1), 87-99.<lb/>  http://doi.org/10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00202-2<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ulsh, B. A. (2010). CHECKING THE FOUNDATION: RECENT RADIOBIOLOGY AND<lb/> THE LINEAR NO-THRESHOLD THEORY. Health Physics, 99(6), 747-758.<lb/>  http://doi.org/10.1097/HP.0b013e3181e32477<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Van Doren, M., Williamson, A. L., &amp; Lehmann, R. (1998). Regulation of zygotic gene<lb/> expression in Drosophila primordial germ cells. Current Biology (Vol. 8). Retrieved from<lb/> http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0960982298700910<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Vande Walle, L., Lamkanfi, M., &amp; Vandenabeele, P. (2008). The mitochondrial serine protease<lb/> HtrA2/Omi: an overview. Cell Death and Differentiation, 15(3), 453-460.<lb/>  http://doi.org/10.1038/sj.cdd.4402291<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wichmann, A., Jaklevic, B., &amp; Su, T. T. (2006). Ionizing radiation induces caspase-dependent<lb/> but Chk2-and p53-independent cell death in Drosophila melanogaster. Proceedings of the<lb/> National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 103(26), 9952-7.<lb/>  http://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0510528103<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wylie, A., Lu, W.-J., D&apos;Brot, A., Buszczak, M., Abrams, J. M., Abdu, U., … Xu, Y. (2014). p53<lb/> activity is selectively licensed in the Drosophila stem cell compartment. eLife, 3, e01530.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.01530<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Xie, H. B., &amp; Golic, K. G. (2004). Gene deletions by ends-in targeting in Drosophila<lb/> melanogaster. Genetics, 168(3), 1477-89. http://doi.org/10.1534/genetics.104.030882<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Yacobi-Sharon, K., Namdar, Y., &amp; Arama, E. (2013). Alternative germ cell death pathway in<lb/> Drosophila involves HtrA2/Omi, lysosomes, and a caspase-9 counterpart. Developmental<lb/> Cell, 25(1), 29-42. http://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2013.02.002<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Yang, H., &amp; Yamashita, Y. M. (2015). The regulated elimination of transit-amplifying cells<lb/> preserves tissue homeostasis during protein starvation in Drosophila testis. Development<lb/> (Cambridge, England), 142(10), 1756-66. http://doi.org/10.1242/dev.122663<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Yoshida, S. (2016). From cyst to tubule: innovations in vertebrate spermatogenesis. Wiley<lb/> Interdisciplinary Reviews: Developmental Biology, 5(1), 119-131.<lb/> http://doi.org/10.1002/wdev.204<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Yuan, H., Chiang, C.-Y. A., Cheng, J., Salzmann, V., &amp; Yamashita, Y. M. (2012). Regulation of<lb/> cyclin A localization downstream of Par-1 function is critical for the centrosome orientation<lb/> checkpoint in Drosophila male germline stem cells. Developmental Biology, 361(1), 57-67.<lb/>  http://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2011.10.010</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

