<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>1</label>. <lb/> Campos GS, Bandeira AC, Sardi SI. Zika virus outbreak, Bahia, Brazil. Emerging Infectious Diseases.<lb/> 2015;21(10):1885-6.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>2</label>. <lb/> Pan American Health Organization / World Health Organization. Zika Epidemiological Update, 29<lb/>  December 2016 Washington, D.C. Available from:<lb/> http://www2.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_view&amp;Itemid=270&amp;gid=37579&amp;lang=en.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>3</label>. <lb/> Duffy MR, Chen T-H, Hancock WT, Powers AM, Kool JL, Lanciotti RS, et al. Zika virus outbreak on Yap<lb/> Island, federated states of Micronesia. New England Journal of Medicine. 2009;360(24):2536-43.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>4</label>. <lb/> Cao-Lormeau V-M, Blake A, Mons S, Lastère S, Roche C, Vanhomwegen J, et al. Guillain-Barré Syndrome<lb/> outbreak associated with Zika virus infection in French Polynesia: a case-control study. The Lancet.<lb/> 2016;387(10027):1531-9.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>5</label>. <lb/> Dos Santos T, Rodriguez A, Almiron M, Sanhueza A, Ramon P, de Oliveira WK, et al. Zika virus and the<lb/> Guillain-Barré syndrome-case series from seven countries. New England Journal of Medicine.<lb/> 2016;375(16):1598-601.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>6</label>. <lb/> Krauer F, Riesen M, Reveiz L, Oladapo OT, Martínez-Vega R, Porgo TV, et al. Zika virus infection as a<lb/> cause of congenital brain abnormalities and Guillain-Barré syndrome: systematic review: DATASET. 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>7</label>. <lb/> Rasmussen SA, Jamieson DJ, Honein MA, Petersen LR. Zika virus and birth defects-reviewing the<lb/> evidence for causality. New England Journal of Medicine. 2016;374(20):1981-7.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>8</label>. <lb/> Musso D, Gubler DJ. Zika virus: following the path of dengue and chikungunya? The Lancet.<lb/> 2015;386(9990):243-4.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>9</label>. <lb/> Adalja AA, Sell TK, Bouri N, Franco C. Lessons learned during dengue outbreaks in the United States,<lb/> 2001-2011. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2012;18(4):608-14.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>10</label>. <lb/> Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Locally acquired Dengue--Key West, Florida, 2009-2010.<lb/> MMWR Morbidity and mortality weekly report. 2010;59(19):577.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>11</label>. <lb/> Kendrick K, Stanek D, Blackmore C. Notes from the field: transmission of chikungunya virus in the<lb/> continental United States-Florida, 2014. MMWR Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. 2014;63(48):1137.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>12</label>. <lb/> Likos A, Griffin I, Bingham A, et al. Local Mosquito-Borne Transmission of Zika Virus -Miami-Dade and<lb/> Broward Counties, Florida, June-August 2016. MMWR Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. 2016;65(38);<lb/> 1032-1038.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>13</label>. <lb/> Texas Department of State Health Services. Texas Announces Local Zika Virus Case in Rio Grande Valley<lb/> 2016 [updated November 28, 2016]. Available from:<lb/> http://www.dshs.texas.gov/news/releases/2016/20161128.aspx.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>14</label>. <lb/> Reiter P, Lathrop S, Bunning M, Biggerstaff B, Singer D, Tiwari T, et al. Texas lifestyle limits transmission<lb/> of dengue virus. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2003;9(1):86-9.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>15</label>. <lb/> Food and Drug Administration. FDA News Release: FDA advises testing for Zika virus in all donated blood<lb/> and blood components in the US 2016. Available from:<lb/> http://www.fda.gov/NewsEvents/Newsroom/PressAnnouncements/ucm518218.htm.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>16</label>. <lb/> Kuehnert MJ. Screening of blood donations for Zika virus infection-Puerto Rico, April 3-June 11, 2016.<lb/> MMWR Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. 2016;65.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>17</label>. <lb/> Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Zika CDC Interim Response Plan: May 2017. Available from:<lb/> https://www.cdc.gov/zika/pdfs/zika-draft-interim-conus-plan.pdf.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>18</label>. <lb/> Oduyebo T. Update: interim guidelines for health care providers caring for pregnant women and women<lb/> of reproductive age with possible Zika virus exposure-United States, 2016. MMWR Morbidity and Mortality<lb/> Weekly Report. 2016;65.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>19</label>. <lb/> Chung KW, Basavaraju SV, Mu Y, van Santen KL, Haass KA, Henry R, et al. Declining blood collection and<lb/> utilization in the United States. Transfusion. 2016.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>20</label>. <lb/> United States Census Bureau. Annual Estimates of Resident Population for Selected Age Groups by Sex<lb/> for the United States, States, Counties, and Puerto Rico Commonwealth and Municipios: April 1, 2010 to July 1,<lb/> 2013. Available from: https://factfinder.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?src=bkmk.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>21</label>. <lb/> Aubry M, Teissier A, Huart M, Merceron S, Vanhomwegen J, Roche C, et al. Zika Virus Seroprevalence,<lb/> French Polynesia, 2014-2015. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2017;23:669-72.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>22</label>. <lb/> Gallian P, Cabié A, Richard P, Paturel L, Charrel RN, Pastorino B, et al. Zika virus in asymptomatic blood<lb/> donors in Martinique. Blood. 2017;129(2):263-6.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>23</label>. <lb/> Hunsperger EA, Yoksan S, Buchy P, Nguyen VC, Sekaran SD, Enria DA, et al. Evaluation of commercially<lb/> available anti-dengue virus immunoglobulin M tests. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2009;15(3):436-40.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>24</label>. <lb/> Groen J, Koraka P, Velzing J, Copra C, Osterhaus AD. Evaluation of six immunoassays for detection of<lb/> dengue virus-specific immunoglobulin M and G antibodies. Clinical and diagnostic laboratory immunology.<lb/> 2000;7(6):867-71.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>25</label>. <lb/> Guzman MG, Jaenisch T, Gaczkowski R, Hang VTT, Sekaran SD, Kroeger A, et al. Multi-country evaluation<lb/> of the sensitivity and specificity of two commercially-available NS1 ELISA assays for dengue diagnosis. PLOS<lb/> Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2010;4(8):e811.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>26</label>. <lb/> Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Zika MAC-ELISA: Instructions for Use 2016. Available from:<lb/> https://www.fda.gov/downloads/MedicalDevices/Safety/EmergencySituations/UCM488044.pdf.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>27</label>. <lb/> Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Fact Sheet for Health Care Providers: Interpreting Zika MAC-<lb/>ELISA Results 2016. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/zika/pdfs/zika-mac-elisa-fact-sheet-for-hcp.pdf.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>28</label>. <lb/> Paz-Bailey G, Rosenberg ES, Doyle K, Munoz-Jordan J, Santiago GA, Klein L, et al. Persistence of Zika Virus<lb/> in Body Fluids-Preliminary Report. New England Journal of Medicine. 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>29</label>. <lb/> Rabe IB. Interim guidance for interpretation of Zika virus antibody test results. MMWR Morbidity and<lb/> Mortality Weekly Report. 2016;65.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>30</label>. <lb/> Hamilton B, Martin J, Osterman M, Curtin S, Matthews TJ. Births: Final Data for 2014. National Vital<lb/> Statistics Reports: 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>31</label>. <lb/> Galel SA, Williamson PC, Busch MP, Stanek D, Bakkour S, Stone M, et al. First Zika-positive donations in<lb/> the continental United States. Transfusion. 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>32</label>. <lb/> Williamson PC, Linnen JM, Kessler DA, Shaz BH, Kamel H, Vassallo RR, et al. First cases of Zika virus-<lb/>infected US blood donors outside states with areas of active transmission. Transfusion. 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>33</label>. <lb/> Stone M, Lanteri MC, Bakkour S, Deng X, Galel SA, Linnen JM, et al. Relative analytical sensitivity of<lb/> donor nucleic acid amplification technology screening and diagnostic real-time polymerase chain reaction assays<lb/> for detection of Zika virus RNA. Transfusion. 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>34</label>. <lb/> Pai A, Kleinman S, Malhotra K, Lee-Haynes L, Pietrelli L, Saldanha J. Performance characteristics of the<lb/> Food and Drug Administration-licensed Roche Cobas TaqScreen West Nile virus assay. Transfusion.<lb/> 2008;48(10):2184-9.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>35</label>. <lb/> Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Trioplex Real-time RT-PCR Assay 2017 [updated March 1,<lb/> 2017]. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/zika/pdfs/trioplex-real-time-rt-pcr-assay-instructions-for-use.pdf.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>36</label>. <lb/> Dirlikov E. Update: Ongoing Zika Virus Transmission-Puerto Rico, November 1, 2015-April 14, 2016.<lb/> MMWR Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. 2016;65.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>37</label>. <lb/> National Center for Health Statistics. National Hospital Ambulatory Medical Care Survey: 2011<lb/> Emergency Department Summary Tables 2011. Available from:<lb/> https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/ahcd/nhamcs_emergency/2011_ed_web_tables.pdf.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>38</label>. <lb/> National Syndromic Surveillance Program (NSSP). BioSense Platform 2016. Available from:<lb/> https://www.cdc.gov/nssp/biosense/.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>39</label>. <lb/> Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Combined NAMCS and NHAMCS: Annual number and<lb/> percent distribution of ambulatory care visits by setting type according to diagnosis group: United States, 2009-<lb/>2010. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/ahcd/namcs_summary/2010_namcs_web_tables.pdf.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>40</label>. <lb/> Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Guidance for U.S. Laboratories Testing for Zika Virus<lb/> Infection 2016. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/zika/pdfs/laboratory-guidance-zika.pdf.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>41</label>. <lb/> Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Prolonged IgM Antibody Response in People Infected with<lb/> Zika Virus: Implications for Interpreting Serologic Testing Results for Pregnant Women [updated May 5, 2017].<lb/>  Available from: https://emergency.cdc.gov/han/han00402.asp.</bibl>

        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

