<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> M. E. Peskin, D. V. Schroeder, An Introduction to Quantum Field Theory; 1995 ed., Westview, Boulder, CO,<lb/> 1995.<lb/> URL https://cds.cern.ch/record/257493<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> E. Fradkin, Field Theories of Condensed Matter Physics, 2nd Edition, Cambridge University Press, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> K. G. Wilson,<lb/> Confinement of Quarks,<lb/> Phys. Rev. D10 (1974) 2445-2459,<lb/> [,45(1974)].<lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.10.2445.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> M. Troyer, U.-J. Wiese, Computational complexity and fundamental limitations to fermionic quan-<lb/>tum Monte Carlo simulations, Phys. Rev. Lett. 94 (2005) 170201.<lb/> arXiv:cond-mat/0408370,<lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.170201.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> J. Kogut, L. Susskind, Hamiltonian formulation of wilson&apos;s lattice gauge theories, Phys. Rev. D 11 (1975) 395-<lb/>408. doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.11.395.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevD.11.395<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> E. Zohar, J. I. Cirac, B. Reznik, Quantum Simulations of Lattice Gauge Theories using Ultracold Atoms in Opti-<lb/>cal Lattices, Rept. Prog. Phys. 79 (1) (2016) 014401. arXiv:1503.02312, doi:10.1088/0034-4885/79/1/014401.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label> U.-J. Wiese, Ultracold Quantum Gases and Lattice Systems: Quantum Simulation of Lattice Gauge Theories,<lb/> Annalen Phys. 525 (2013) 777-796. arXiv:1305.1602, doi:10.1002/andp.201300104.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> S. R. White, Density matrix formulation for quantum renormalization groups, Physical Review Letters 69 (19)<lb/> (1992) 2863-2866. doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.69.2863.<lb/> URL http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.69.2863<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> F. Verstraete, V. Murg, J. I. Cirac, Matrix product states, projected entangled pair states, and variational renormalization group m<lb/> 57 (2) 143-224. arXiv:0907.2796, doi:10.1080/14789940801912366.<lb/> URL http://arxiv.org/abs/0907.2796<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> D.<lb/> Pérez-García,<lb/> M.<lb/> Sanz,<lb/> C.<lb/> E.<lb/> Gonzalez-Guillen,<lb/> M.<lb/> M.<lb/> Wolf,<lb/> J.<lb/> I.<lb/> Cirac,<lb/> A canonical form for Projected Entangled Pair States and applications<lb/> 12<lb/> 025010.<lb/> doi:10.1088/1367-2630/12/2/025010.<lb/> URL http://arxiv.org/abs/0908.1674v1;http://arxiv.org/pdf/0908.1674v1<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> M. Bañuls, K. Cichy, J. Cirac, K. Jansen, The mass spectrum of the schwinger model with matrix product states,<lb/> Journal of High Energy Physics 2013 (11) (2013) 158. doi:10.1007/JHEP11(2013)158.<lb/> URL https://doi.org/10.1007/JHEP11(2013)158<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> Y. Shimizu, Y. Kuramashi, Grassmann tensor renormalization group approach to one-flavor lattice schwinger model,<lb/> Phys. Rev. D 90 (2014) 014508. doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.90.014508.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevD.90.014508<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> B.<lb/> Buyens,<lb/> J.<lb/> Haegeman,<lb/> K.<lb/> Van<lb/> Acoleyen,<lb/> H.<lb/> Verschelde,<lb/> F.<lb/> Verstraete,<lb/> Matrix product states for gauge field theories,<lb/> Phys.<lb/> Rev.<lb/> Lett.<lb/> 113<lb/> (2014)<lb/> 091601.<lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.113.091601.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.113.091601<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> P. Silvi, E. Rico, T. Calarco, S. Montangero, Lattice gauge tensor networks, New Journal of Physics 16 (10)<lb/> (2014) 103015.<lb/> URL http://stacks.iop.org/1367-2630/16/i=10/a=103015<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> B. Buyens, K. Van Acoleyen, J. Haegeman, F. Verstraete, Matrix product states for Hamiltonian lattice gauge<lb/> theories, ArXiv e-printsarXiv:1411.0020.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> E. Rico, T. Pichler, M. Dalmonte, P. Zoller, S. Montangero, Tensor networks for lattice gauge theories and atomic quantum simulat<lb/> Phys. Rev. Lett. 112 (2014) 201601. doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.112.201601.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.112.201601<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> H. Saito, M. C. Bañuls, K. Cichy, J. I. Cirac, K. Jansen, The temperature dependence of the chiral condensate<lb/> in the Schwinger model with Matrix Product States, PoS LATTICE2014 (2014) 302. arXiv:1412.0596.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> S. Kühn, E. Zohar, J. I. Cirac, M. C. Bañuls, Non-abelian string breaking phenomena with matrix product states,<lb/> Journal of High Energy Physics 2015 (7) (2015) 130. doi:10.1007/JHEP07(2015)130.<lb/> URL https://doi.org/10.1007/JHEP07(2015)130<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> M. C. Bañuls, K. Cichy, J. I. Cirac, K. Jansen, H. Saito, Thermal evolution of the schwinger model with matrix product operators,<lb/> Phys. Rev. D 92 (2015) 034519. doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.92.034519.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevD.92.034519<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> M. C. Bañuls, K. Cichy, K. Jansen, H. Saito, Chiral condensate in the schwinger model with matrix product operators,<lb/> Phys. Rev. D 93 (2016) 094512. doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.93.094512.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevD.93.094512<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> T. Pichler, M. Dalmonte, E. Rico, P. Zoller, S. Montangero, Real-time dynamics in u(1) lattice gauge theories with tensor networks<lb/> Phys. Rev. X 6 (2016) 011023. doi:10.1103/PhysRevX.6.011023.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevX.6.011023<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> B. Buyens, J. Haegeman, F. Hebenstreit, F. Verstraete, K. Van Acoleyen, Real-time simulation of the Schwinger<lb/> effect with Matrix Product StatesarXiv:1612.00739.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> P. Silvi, E. Rico, M. Dalmonte, F. Tschirsich, S. Montangero, Finite-density phase diagram of a (1+1)-d non-<lb/>abelian lattice gauge theory with tensor networksarXiv:1606.05510, doi:10.22331/q-2017-04-25-9.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> A. Milsted, Matrix product states and the non-abelian rotor model, Phys. Rev. D 93 (2016) 085012.<lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.93.085012.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevD.93.085012<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> M. C. Bañuls, K. Cichy, J. I. Cirac, K. Jansen, S. Kühn, H. Saito, The multi-flavor Schwinger model with<lb/> chemical potential -Overcoming the sign problem with Matrix Product States, PoS LATTICE2016 (2016) 316.<lb/> arXiv:1611.01458.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> B. Buyens, F. Verstraete, K. Van Acoleyen, Hamiltonian simulation of the schwinger model at finite temperature,<lb/> Phys. Rev. D 94 (2016) 085018. doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.94.085018.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevD.94.085018<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[27]</label> H. Saito, M. C. Bañuls, K. Cichy, J. I. Cirac, K. Jansen, Thermal evolution of the one-flavour Schwinger model<lb/> with using Matrix Product States, PoS LATTICE2015 (2016) 283. arXiv:1511.00794.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[28]</label> M. C. Bañuls, K. Cichy, J. I. Cirac, K. Jansen, S. Kühn, Density induced phase transitions in the schwinger model: A study with m<lb/> Phys. Rev. Lett. 118 (2017) 071601. doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.118.071601.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.118.071601<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[29]</label> M. C. Bañuls, K. Cichy, J. Ignacio Cirac, K. Jansen, S. Kühn, H. Saito, Towards overcoming the Monte Carlo<lb/> sign problem with tensor networks, in: European Physical Journal Web of Conferences, Vol. 137 of European<lb/> Physical Journal Web of Conferences, 2017, p. 04001. arXiv:1611.04791, doi:10.1051/epjconf/201713704001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[30]</label> M. C. Bañuls, K. Cichy, J. I. Cirac, K. Jansen, S. Kühn, Efficient basis formulation for 1+1 dimensional SU(2)<lb/> lattice gauge theory: Spectral calculations with matrix product statesarXiv:1707.06434.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[31]</label> L. Tagliacozzo, A. Celi, M. Lewenstein, Tensor networks for lattice gauge theories with continuous groups, Phys.<lb/> Rev. X 4 (2014) 041024. doi:10.1103/PhysRevX.4.041024.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevX.4.041024<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[32]</label> J. Haegeman, K. Van Acoleyen, N. Schuch, J. I. Cirac, F. Verstraete, Gauging quantum states: from<lb/> global to local symmetries in many-body systems, Phys. Rev. X5 (1) (2015) 011024. arXiv:1407.1025,<lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevX.5.011024.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[33]</label> E. Zohar, M. Burrello, T. Wahl, J. I. Cirac, Fermionic Projected Entangled Pair States and Local U(1) Gauge<lb/> Theories, Annals Phys. 363 (2015) 385-439. arXiv:1507.08837, doi:10.1016/j.aop.2015.10.009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[34]</label> E. Zohar, M. Burrello, Building Projected Entangled Pair States with a Local Gauge Symmetry, New J. Phys.<lb/> 18 (4) (2016) 043008. arXiv:1511.08426, doi:10.1088/1367-2630/18/4/043008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[35]</label> E. Zohar, T. B. Wahl, M. Burrello, J. I. Cirac, Projected Entangled Pair States with non-Abelian gauge symme-<lb/>tries: an SU(2) study, Annals Phys. 374 (2016) 84-137. arXiv:1607.08115, doi:10.1016/j.aop.2016.08.008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[36]</label> E. Zohar, M. Burrello, Formulation of lattice gauge theories for quantum simulations, Phys. Rev. D91 (5) (2015)<lb/> 054506. arXiv:1409.3085, doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.91.054506.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[37]</label> D. Pérez-García, F. Verstraete, M. M. Wolf, J. I. Cirac, Matrix Product State Representations 7 401.<lb/> URL http://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0608197v2;http://arxiv.org/pdf/quant-ph/0608197v2<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[38]</label> J. I. Cirac, D. Perez-Garcia, N. Schuch, F. Verstraete, Matrix product density operators: Renormalization fixed points and boundar<lb/> 378 100-149. arXiv:1606.00608, doi:10.1016/j.aop.2016.12.030.<lb/> URL http://arxiv.org/abs/1606.00608<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[39]</label> M.<lb/> Wolf,<lb/> Quantum<lb/> channels<lb/> and<lb/> operations<lb/> guided<lb/> tour,<lb/> https://www-<lb/>m5.ma.tum.de/foswiki/pub/M5/Allgemeines/MichaelWolf/QChannelLecture.pdf.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[40]</label> M. Sanz, D. Perez-Garcia, M. M. Wolf, J. I. Cirac, A quantum version of wielandt&apos;s inequality 56 (9) 4668-4673.<lb/> arXiv:0909.5347, doi:10.1109/TIT.2010.2054552.<lb/> URL http://arxiv.org/abs/0909.5347<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[41]</label> B. C. Hall, Quantum Theory for Mathematicians., Vol. 267 of Graduate Texts in Mathematics, Springer New<lb/> York, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[42]</label> C. CHENG, A character theory for projective representations of finite group.<lb/> URL http://maths.nju.edu.cn/ ~ ccheng/Writings/preps-notes.pdf<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[43]</label> N. Vilenkin, A. Klimyk, Representation of Lie Groups and Special Functions: Recent Advances, Springer, 1995,<lb/> section 4.3.3.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[44]</label> M. Sanz, M. M. Wolf, D. Pérez-García, J. I. Cirac, Matrix product states: Symmetries and two-body hamiltonians,<lb/> Phys. Rev. A 79 (2009) 042308. doi:10.1103/PhysRevA.79.042308.<lb/> URL https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevA.79.042308<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[45]</label> F. Pollmann, A. M. Turner, E. Berg, M. Oshikawa, Entanglement spectrum of a topological phase in one<lb/> dimension, prb 81 (6) (2010) 064439. arXiv:0910.1811, doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.81.064439.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[46]</label> V. K. Agrawala, Wigner-Eckart theorem for an arbitrary group or lie algebra, Journal of Mathematical Physics<lb/> 21 (7) (1980) 1562-1565. arXiv:http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.524639, doi:10.1063/1.524639.<lb/> URL http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.524639<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[47]</label> D. Pérez-García, M. M. Wolf, M. Sanz, F. Verstraete, J. I. Cirac, String Order and Symme-<lb/>tries in Quantum Spin Lattices, Physical Review Letters 100 (16) (2008) 167202.<lb/> arXiv:0802.0447,<lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.100.167202.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[48]</label> B. C. Hall, Lie groups, Lie algebras and representations , an elementary introduction, 2nd Edition, Springer,<lb/> 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[49]</label> G. B. Folland, A Course in Abstract Harmonic Analysis, CRC Press, 1994, theorem 7.25.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[50]</label> N. Bultinck, D. J. Williamson, J. Haegeman, F. Verstraete, Fermionic projected entangled-pair states and topo-<lb/>logical phases, ArXiv e-printsarXiv:1707.00470.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[51]</label> N. Bultinck, D. J. Williamson, J. Haegeman, F. Verstraete, Fermionic matrix product states and one-dimensional<lb/> topological phases, Phys. Rev. B95 (7) (2017) 075108. arXiv:1610.07849, doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.95.075108.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

