<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        REFERENCES<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> F. Sauli, &quot;GEM: A new concept for electron amplification in gas<lb/> detectors,&quot; Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. A, Accel. Spectrom.<lb/> Detect. Assoc. Equip., vol. 386, nos. 2-3, pp. 531-534, Feb. 1997.<lb/> [Online]. Available: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/<lb/> S0168900296011722<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> Y. Giomataris, P. Rebourgeard, J. Robert, and G. Charpak,<lb/> &quot;MICROMEGAS: A high-granularity position-sensitive gaseous detec-<lb/>tor for high particle-flux environments,&quot; Nucl. Instrum. Methods<lb/> Phys. Res. Section A, Accel., Spectrometers, Detectors Assoc. Equip.,<lb/> vol. 376, no. 1, pp. 29-35, Jun. 1996. [Online]. Available: http://<lb/> www.sciencedirect.com/science/articlepii/0168900296001751<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> T. Francke, Innovative Applications and Developments of Micro-Pattern<lb/> Gaseous Detectors. Delhi, India, IGI Global, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> X. Llopart, R. Ballabriga, M. Campbell, L. Tlustos, and W. Wong<lb/> &quot;Timepix, a 65k programmable pixel readout chip for arrival time,<lb/> energy and/or photon counting measurements,&quot; Nucl. Instrum. Methods<lb/> Phys. Res. A, Accel. Spectrom. Detect. Assoc. Equip., vol. 581, no. 1,<lb/> pp. 485-494, Oct. 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> M. Chefdeville et al., &quot;An electron-multiplying &apos;Micromegas&apos; grid made<lb/> in silicon wafer post-processing technology,&quot; Nucl. Instrum. Methods<lb/> Phys. Res. A, Accel. Spectrom. Detect. Assoc. Equip., vol. 556, no. 2,<lb/> pp. 490-494, Jan. 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> M. Lupberger. (2010). Avalanche Statistics and Single Electron<lb/> Counting with a Timepix-InGrid Detector. [Online]. Available:<lb/> http://terascale.physik.uni-freiburg.de/Publikationen/abschlussarbeiten/<lb/> diplom-masterarbeiten/diplomarbeit_lupberger.pdf<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label> D. S. S. Bello, M. van Beuzekom, P. Jansweijer, H. Verkooijen, and<lb/> J. Visschers, &quot;An interface board for the control and data acquisition<lb/> of the Medipix2 chip,&quot; Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. A, Accel.<lb/> Spectrom. Detect. Assoc. Equip., vol. 509, nos. 1-3, pp. 164-170,<lb/> Aug. 2003. [Online]. Available: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/<lb/> article/pii/S0168900203015663<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> A. Bamberger et al., &quot;Resolution studies on 5 GeV electron tracks<lb/> observed with triple-GEM and MediPix2/TimePix-readout,&quot; Nucl.<lb/> Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. A, Accel. Spectrom. Detect. Assoc. Equip.,<lb/> vol. 581, nos. 1-2, pp. 274-278, Oct. 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> R. Menzen, &quot;InGrid based TPC readout,&quot; M.S. thesis, Math.-<lb/>Naturwissenschaftliche Fakultät, Univ. Bonn, Bonn Germany, 2013.<lb/> [Online]. Available: https://www.lhc-ilc.physik.uni-bonn.de/ergebnisse/<lb/> dateien/t00000042.pdf<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> M. Lupberger, &quot;The pixel-TPC: First results from an 8-InGrid module,&quot;<lb/> J. Instrum., vol. 9, no. 1, p. C01033, Jan. 2014. [Online]. Available:<lb/> http://arxiv.org/pdf/1311.3125.pdf<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> T. Behnke et al. (2013). &quot;The international linear collider technical<lb/> design report-Volume 1: Executive summary.&quot; [Online]. Available:<lb/> https://arxiv.org/abs/1306.6327<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> T. Behnke et al.. (2013). &quot;The international linear collider tech-<lb/>nical design report-Volume 4: detectors.&quot; [Online]. Available:<lb/> https://arxiv.org/abs/1306.6329<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> P. Schade and J. Kaminski, &quot;A large TPC prototype for a linear<lb/> collider detector,&quot; Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. A, Accel. Spec-<lb/>trom. Detect. Assoc. Equip., vol. 628, no. 1, pp. 128-132, Feb. 2011.<lb/> [Online]. Available: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/<lb/> S0168900210014907<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> J. Tomtschak, &quot;CAD Design eines 96 Chip Modultragers fur den<lb/> Large Prototype,&quot; Bachelor, Math.-Naturwissenschaftliche Fakultät,<lb/> Univ. Bonn, Bonn Germany, 2014. [Online]. Available: https://www.<lb/> lhc-ilc.physik.uni-bonn.de/ergebnisse/dateien/t00000055.pdf<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> W. J. C. Koppert et al., &quot;GridPix detectors: Production and beam test<lb/> results,&quot; Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. A, Accel. Spectrom. Detect.<lb/> Assoc. Equip., vol. 732, pp. 245-249, Dec. 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> K. Kohl, &quot;Untersuchung der Feldverzerrungen bei InGrid-basierten<lb/> Pixelchips,&quot;<lb/> Bachelor,<lb/> Math.-Naturwissenschaftliche<lb/> Fakultät,<lb/> Univ. Bonn, Bonn Germany, 2014. [Online]. Available: https://www.lhc-<lb/>ilc.physik.uni-bonn.de/ergebnisse/dateien/t00000056.pdf<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> M. Lupberger, K. Desch, and J. Kaminski, &quot;Implementation of the<lb/> timepix ASIC in the scalable readout system,&quot; Nucl. Instrum. Meth-<lb/>ods Phys. Res. A, Accel. Spectrom. Detect. Assoc. Equip., vol. 830,<lb/> pp. 75-81, Sep. 2016. [Online]. Available: http://www.sciencedirect.<lb/> com/science/article/pii/S0168900216304235<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> A. Hamann, &quot;Stromversorgung, Temperaturüberwachung und Vermes-<lb/>sung einer TPC-Ausleseeinheit mit 160 GridPix,&quot; M.S. thesis, Math.-<lb/>Naturwissenschaftliche Fakultät, Univ. Bonn, Bonn Germany, 2015.<lb/> ttps://www.lhc-ilc.physik.uni-bonn.de/ergebnisse/dateien/t00000071.pdf<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> D. Danilov, &quot;Readout system for a large pixel-TPC-module and test-<lb/>beam analysis,&quot; M.S. thesis, Math.-Naturwissenschaftliche Fakultät,<lb/> Univ. Bonn, Bonn Germany, 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> J. Abernathy et al., &quot;MarlinTPC: A common software framework<lb/> for TPC development,&quot; in Proc. IEEE Nucl. Sci. Symp. Conf. Rec.,<lb/> Oct. 2008, pp. 1704-1708.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> M. Lupberger, &quot;The Pixel-TPC: A feasibility study,&quot; Ph.D. dissertation,<lb/> Math.-Naturwissenschaftliche Fakultät, Univ. Bonn, Bonn Germany,<lb/> 2015. [Online]. Available: http://hss.ulb.uni-bonn.de/2016/4348/4348.<lb/> htm<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> J. Ottnad, &quot;Studies on field distortions and quenching gas prop-<lb/>erties of an ingrid based X-ray detector,&quot; M.S. thesis, Math.-<lb/>Naturwissenschaftliche Fakultät, Univ. Bonn, Bonn Germany, 2014.<lb/> [Online]. Available: https://www.lhc-ilc.physik.uni-bonn.de/ergebnisse/<lb/> dateien/t00000048.pdf</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

