<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> W. Gai, P. Schoessow, B. Cole, R. Konecny, J. Norem,<lb/> J. Rosenzweig, and J. Simpson, &quot;Experimental demon-<lb/>stration of wake-field effects in dielectric structures,&quot;<lb/> Physical Review Letters 61, 2756-2758 (1988).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> M. Rosing and W. Gai, &quot;Longitudinal-and transverse-<lb/>wake-field effects in dielectric structures,&quot; Physical Re-<lb/>view D 42, 1829-1834 (1990); </bibl>
        <bibl>King-Yuen Ng, &quot;Wake<lb/> fields in a dielectric-lined waveguide,&quot; Physical Review<lb/> D 42, 1819-1828 (1990).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> S. Y. Park and J. L. Hirshfield, &quot;Theory of wakefields<lb/> in a dielectric-lined waveguide,&quot; Physical Review E 62,<lb/> 1266-1283 (2000).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> J. G. Power, M. E. Conde, W. Gai, R. Conecny,<lb/> P. Schoessow, and A. D. Kanareykin, &quot;Measurements<lb/> of the longitudinal wakefields in a multimode, dielec-<lb/>tric wakefield accelerator driven by a train of electron<lb/> bunches,&quot; Phys. Rev. ST Accel. Beams 3, 101302 (2000).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> S.S. Baturin and A. Zholents, &quot;Upper limit for the accel-<lb/>erating gradient in the collinear wakefield,&quot; Phys. Rev.<lb/> ST Accel. Beams 20, 061302 (2017).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> T-B. Zhang, J. L. Hirshfield, T. C. Marshall, and<lb/> B. Hafizi, &quot;Stimulated dielectric wake-field accelerator,&quot;<lb/> Physical Review E 56, 4647-4655 (1997).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label> Liling Xiao, Wei Gai, and Xiang Sun, &quot;Field analysis<lb/> of a dielectric-loaded rectangular waveguide accelerating<lb/> structure,&quot; Physical Review E 65, 016505 (2001).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> T. C. Marshall, Changbiao Wang, and J. L. Hirshfield,<lb/> &quot;Femtosecond planar electron beam source for micron-<lb/>scale dielectric wake field accelerator,&quot; Phys. Rev. ST<lb/> Accel. Beams 4, 121301 (2001).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> T. C. Marshall, J-.M. Fang, and J. L. Hirshfield, &quot;The-<lb/>ory for wake fields and bunch stability in planar dielectric<lb/> structures,&quot; in Advanced Accelerator Concepts: Tenth<lb/> Workshop. AIP Conf. Proc., Vol. 647, edited by C. E.<lb/> Clayton and P. Muggly (AIP, New York, 2002) pp. 527-<lb/>541.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> Changbiao Wang, J. L. Hirshfield, J.-M. Fang, and<lb/> Thomas C. Marshall, &quot;Strong wakefields generated by<lb/> a train of femtosecond bunches in a planar dielectric mi-<lb/>crostructure,&quot; Phys. Rev. ST Accel. Beams 7, 051301<lb/> (2004).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> R. B. Yoder and J. B. Rosenzweig, &quot;Side-coupled slab-<lb/>symmetric structure for high-gradient acceleration using<lb/> terahertz power,&quot; Phys. Rev. ST Accel. Beams 8, 111301<lb/> (2005).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> S.V. Shchelkunov, T.C. Marshall, G. Sotnikov, J.L. Hir-<lb/>shfield, , Wei Gai, M. Conde, J. Power, D. Mihalcea, and<lb/> Z. Yusof, &quot;Comparison of experimental tests and theory<lb/> for a rectangular two-channel dielectric wakefield acceler-<lb/>ator structure,&quot; Phys. Rev. ST Accel. Beams 15, 031301<lb/> (2012).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> Changbiao Wang and J. L. Hirshfield, &quot;Theory for wake-<lb/>fields in a multizone dielectric lined waveguide,&quot; Phys.<lb/> Rev. ST Accel. Beams 9, 031301 (2006).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> L. Pincherle, &quot;Electromagnetic waves in metal tubes<lb/> filled longitudinally with two dielectrics,&quot; Physical Re-<lb/>view 66, 118-130 (1944).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> G. V. Sotnikov, I. N. Onishchenko, and T. C. Mar-<lb/>shall, &quot;3D analysis of wake field excitation in a dielectric<lb/> loaded rectangular resonator,&quot; in Advanced Accelerator<lb/> Concepts: 12 th Workshop. AIP Conf. Proc., Vol. 877,<lb/> edited by Manoel Conde and Catherine Eyberger (Amer-<lb/>ican Institute of Physics, New York, 2006) pp. 888-894.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> V. Shiltsev, &quot;On the future high energy colliders,&quot; ArXiv<lb/> e-prints (2015), presentation at the DPF 2015 Meet-<lb/>ing of the American Physical Society Division of Parti-<lb/>cles and Fields, Ann Arbor, Michigan, August 4-8, 2015,<lb/> arXiv:1509.08369v1 [physics.acc-p].<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> Sergey Shchelkunov, &quot;High transformer ratio of multi-<lb/>channel dielectric wakefield structures and real-time di-<lb/>agnostic for charging and damage of dielectrics,&quot; (2015),<lb/> presentation at the the 2nd European Advanced Acceler-<lb/>ator Concepts Workshop, La Biodola, Isola d&apos;Elba, Italy,<lb/> 13-19 September 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> C. Li, W. Gai, C. Jing, J.G. Power, C.X. Tang, and<lb/> A. Zholents, &quot;High gradient limits due to single bunch<lb/> beam breakup in a collinear dielectric wakefield acceler-<lb/>ator,&quot; Phys. Rev. ST Accel. Beams 17, 091302 (2014).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> A. Tremaine, J. Rosenzweig, and P. Schoessow, &quot;Elec-<lb/>tromagnetic wake fields and beam stability in slab-<lb/>symmetric dielectric structures,&quot; Physical Review E 56,<lb/> 7204-7216 (1997).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> T. C. Marshall, J. M. Fang, J. L. Hirshfield, and S. Y.<lb/> Park, &quot;Multi-mode, multi-bunch dielectric wake field res-<lb/>onator accelerator,&quot; in Advanced Accelerator Concepts:<lb/> Ninth Workshop. AIP Conf. Proc., Vol. 569, edited by<lb/> P. Colestock and S. Kelley (AIP, New York, 2001) pp.<lb/> 316-325.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> V. A. Kiselev, A. F. Linnik, T. C. Marshall, I. N. On-<lb/>ishchenko, N. I. Onishchenko, G. V. Sotnikov, and V. V.<lb/> Uskov, &quot;Wakefield excitation by a sequence of electron<lb/> bunches in a rectangular waveguide lined with dielectric<lb/> slabs,&quot; in Advanced Accelerator Concepts: 12 th Work-<lb/>shop. AIP Conf. Proc., Vol. 877, edited by Manoel Conde<lb/> and Catherine Eyberger (AIP, New York, 2006) pp. 851-<lb/>858.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> G.V. Sotnikov, I.N. Onishchenko, J.L. Hirshfield, and<lb/> T.C. Marshall, &quot;A five-zone two-channel dielectric wake-<lb/>field structure for two beam acceleration experiments at<lb/> Argonne National Laboratory,&quot; Problems of Atomic Sci-<lb/>ence and Technology. Series: Nuclear Physics Investiga-<lb/>tions, 49, 148-152 (2008).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> Nikolay I. Onishchenko, Gennadij V. Sotnikov, and<lb/> Thomas C. Marshall, &quot;Amplitudes and spectra of wake<lb/> fields in a planar dielectric resonator with finite q-factor,&quot;<lb/> in Advanced Accelerator Concepts: 12 th Workshop. AIP<lb/> Conf. Proc., Vol. 877, edited by Manoel Conde and<lb/> Catherine Eyberger (AIP, New York, 2006) pp. 866-872.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> I. N. Onishchenko, D. Yu. Sidorenko, and G. V. Sot-<lb/>nikov, &quot;Structure of electromagnetic field excited by an<lb/> electron bunch in a semi-infinite dielectric-filled waveg-<lb/>uide,&quot; Phys. Rev. E 65, 066501 (2002).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> T. C. Marshall, G. V.Sotnikov, S. V. Shchelkunov, and<lb/> J. L. Hirshfieldd, &quot;Analysis of a symmetric terahertz<lb/> dielectric-lined rectangular structure for high gradient<lb/> acceleration,&quot; in Advanced Accelerator Concepts: 13 th<lb/> Workshop. AIP Conf. Proc., Vol. 1086, edited by C. B.<lb/> Schroeder, W. Leemans, and E. Esarey (AIP, New York,<lb/> 2009) pp. 421-426.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> S. V. Shchelkunov, T.C. Marshall, and Hirshfield, &quot;Real-<lb/>time diagnostic for charging and damage of dielectrics<lb/> in accelerators,&quot; Nuclear Instruments and Methods in<lb/> Physics Research Section A: Accelerators, Spectrome-<lb/>ters, Detectors and Associated Equipment 829, 194-198<lb/> (2016).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

