<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Firoj Alam, Fahim Dalvi, Shaden Shaar, Nadir Durrani,<lb/> Hamdy Mubarak, Alex Nikolov, Giovanni Da San<lb/> Martino, Ahmed Abdelali, Hassan Sajjad, Kareem<lb/> Darwish, et al. 2020. Fighting the COVID-19 info-<lb/>demic in social media: A holistic perspective and a<lb/> call to arms. arXiv preprint arXiv:2007.07996.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Rich Caruana. 1997. Multitask learning. Machine<lb/> learning, 28(1):41-75.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Giovanni Luca Ciampaglia, Prashant Shiralkar, Luis M<lb/> Rocha, Johan Bollen, Filippo Menczer, and<lb/> Alessandro Flammini. 2015. Computational fact<lb/> checking from knowledge networks. PloS one,<lb/> 10(6):e0128193.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Giovanni Da San Martino, Seunghak Yu, Alberto<lb/> Barrón-Cedeno, Rostislav Petrov, and Preslav<lb/> Nakov. 2019. Fine-grained analysis of propaganda<lb/> in news article. In Proceedings of the 2019 Con-<lb/>ference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language<lb/> Processing and the 9th International Joint Confer-<lb/>ence on Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-<lb/>IJCNLP), pages 5640-5650.<lb/> </bibl>        
        <bibl>Leon Derczynski, Kalina Bontcheva, Maria Liakata,<lb/> Rob Procter, Geraldine Wong Sak Hoi, and Arkaitz<lb/> Zubiaga. 2017. Semeval-2017 task 8: Rumoureval:<lb/> Determining rumour veracity and support for ru-<lb/>mours. In Proceedings of the 11th International<lb/> Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval-2017),<lb/> pages 69-76.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Oren Etzioni, Michele Banko, Stephen Soderland, and<lb/> Daniel S. Weld. 2008. Open information extraction<lb/> from the Web. Commun. ACM, 51(12):68-74.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lisa Fan, Marshall White, Eva Sharma, Ruisi Su,<lb/> Prafulla Kumar Choubey, Ruihong Huang, and<lb/> Lu Wang. 2019. In plain sight: Media bias through<lb/> the lens of factual reporting. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 2019 Conference on Empirical Methods in Nat-<lb/>ural Language Processing and the 9th International<lb/> Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing<lb/> (EMNLP-IJCNLP), pages 6344-6350.<lb/> </bibl>        
        <bibl>Laura Joszt. 2020. Combatting covid-19 misinforma-<lb/>tion.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Diederik P Kingma and Jimmy Ba. 2014. Adam: A<lb/> method for stochastic optimization. arXiv preprint<lb/> arXiv:1412.6980.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Angelika Kirilin and Micheal Strube. 2018. Exploit-<lb/>ing a speaker&apos;s credibility to detect fake news. In<lb/> Proceedings of Data Science, Journalism &amp; Media<lb/> workshop at KDD (DSJM&apos;18).<lb/> </bibl>        
        <bibl>Elena Kochkina, Maria Liakata, and Arkaitz Zubi-<lb/>aga. 2018. All-in-one: Multi-task learning for ru-<lb/>mour verification. In Proceedings of the 27th Inter-<lb/>national Conference on Computational Linguistics,<lb/> pages 3402-3413.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ramez Kouzy, Joseph Abi Jaoude, Afif Kraitem,<lb/> Molly B El Alam, Basil Karam, Elio Adib, Jabra<lb/> Zarka, Cindy Traboulsi, Elie W Akl, and Khalil<lb/> Baddour. 2020. Coronavirus goes viral: quantify-<lb/>ing the covid-19 misinformation epidemic on twitter.<lb/> Cureus, 12(3).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sejeong Kwon, Meeyoung Cha, Kyomin Jung, Wei<lb/> Chen, and Yajun Wang. 2013. Prominent features of<lb/> rumor propagation in online social media. In 2013<lb/> IEEE 13th International Conference on Data Min-<lb/>ing, pages 1103-1108. IEEE.<lb/> </bibl>        
        <bibl>Quanzhi Li, Qiong Zhang, and Luo Si. 2019. Rumor<lb/> detection by exploiting user credibility information,<lb/> attention and multi-task learning. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 57th Annual Meeting of the Association for Com-<lb/>putational Linguistics, pages 1173-1179.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Xiaodong Liu, Pengcheng He, Weizhu Chen, and Jian-<lb/>feng Gao. 2019a. Multi-task deep neural networks<lb/> for natural language understanding. In Proceedings<lb/> of the 57th Annual Meeting of the Association for<lb/> Computational Linguistics, pages 4487-4496, Flo-<lb/>rence, Italy. Association for Computational Linguis-<lb/>tics.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Yinhan Liu, Myle Ott, Naman Goyal, Jingfei Du, Man-<lb/>dar Joshi, Danqi Chen, Omer Levy, Mike Lewis,<lb/> Luke Zettlemoyer, and Veselin Stoyanov. 2019b.<lb/> Roberta: A robustly optimized bert pretraining ap-<lb/>proach. arXiv preprint arXiv:1907.11692.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Yunfei Long, Qin Lu, Rong Xiang, Minglei Li,<lb/> and Chu-Ren Huang. 2017. Fake news detection<lb/> through multi-perspective speaker profiles. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the Eighth International Joint Confer-<lb/>ence on Natural Language Processing (Volume 2:<lb/> Short Papers), pages 252-256.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Jing Ma, Wei Gao, and Kam-Fai Wong. 2018. Ru-<lb/>mor detection on twitter with tree-structured recur-<lb/>sive neural networks. In Proceedings of the 56th An-<lb/>nual Meeting of the Association for Computational<lb/> Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers), pages 1980-<lb/>1989.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bernard Marr. 2018. How much data do we create ev-<lb/>ery day? the mind-blowing stats everyone should<lb/> read. Forbes.<lb/> </bibl>        
        <bibl>Andreas Maurer, Massimiliano Pontil, and Bernardino<lb/> Romera-Paredes. 2016. The benefit of multitask rep-<lb/>resentation learning. The Journal of Machine Learn-<lb/>ing Research, 17(1):2853-2884.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Yixin Nie, Haonan Chen, and Mohit Bansal. 2019.<lb/> Combining fact extraction and verification with neu-<lb/>ral semantic matching networks. In Proceedings of<lb/> the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, vol-<lb/>ume 33, pages 6859-6866.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Amin Omidvar, Hui Jiang, and Aijun An. 2018. Using<lb/> neural network for identifying clickbaits in online<lb/> news media. In Annual International Symposium on<lb/> Information Management and Big Data, pages 220-<lb/>232. Springer.<lb/> </bibl>        
        <bibl>Kashyap Popat, Subhabrata Mukherjee, Andrew Yates,<lb/> and Gerhard Weikum. 2018. Declare: Debunking<lb/> fake news and false claims using evidence-aware<lb/> deep learning. In Proceedings of the 2018 Confer-<lb/>ence on Empirical Methods in Natural Language<lb/> Processing, pages 22-32.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Martin Potthast, Johannes Kiesel, Kevin Reinartz,<lb/> Janek Bevendorff, and Benno Stein. 2018. A stylo-<lb/>metric inquiry into hyperpartisan and fake news. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 56th Annual Meeting of the As-<lb/>sociation for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1:<lb/> Long Papers), pages 231-240, Melbourne, Australia.<lb/> Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>        
        <bibl>Hannah Rashkin, Eunsol Choi, Jin Yea Jang, Svitlana<lb/> Volkova, and Yejin Choi. 2017. Truth of varying<lb/> shades: Analyzing language in fake news and polit-<lb/>ical fact-checking. In Proceedings of the 2017 Con-<lb/>ference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language<lb/> Processing, pages 2931-2937.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Victoria Rubin, Niall Conroy, Yimin Chen, and Sarah<lb/> Cornwell. 2016. Fake news or truth? using satiri-<lb/>cal cues to detect potentially misleading news. In<lb/> Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Computa-<lb/>tional Approaches to Deception Detection, pages 7-<lb/>17, San Diego, California. Association for Computa-<lb/>tional Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sebastian Ruder. 2017. An overview of multi-task<lb/> learning in deep neural networks. arXiv preprint<lb/> arXiv:1706.05098.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kai Shu, Suhang Wang, and Huan Liu. 2019. Beyond<lb/> news contents: The role of social context for fake<lb/> news detection. In Proceedings of the Twelfth ACM<lb/> International Conference on Web Search and Data<lb/> Mining, pages 312-320.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>James Thorne,<lb/> Andreas Vlachos,<lb/> Christos<lb/> Christodoulopoulos, and Arpit Mittal. 2018.<lb/> Fever: a large-scale dataset for fact extraction and<lb/> verification. In Proceedings of the 2018 Conference<lb/> of the North American Chapter of the Association<lb/> for Computational Linguistics: Human Language<lb/> Technologies, Volume 1 (Long Papers), pages<lb/> 809-819.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Svitlana Volkova, Kyle Shaffer, Jin Yea Jang, and<lb/> Nathan Hodas. 2017. Separating facts from fiction:<lb/> Linguistic models to classify suspicious and trusted<lb/> news posts on twitter. In Proceedings of the 55th An-<lb/>nual Meeting of the Association for Computational<lb/> Linguistics (Volume 2: Short Papers), pages 647-<lb/>653.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Soroush Vosoughi, Deb Roy, and Sinan Aral. 2018.<lb/> The spread of true and false news online. Science,<lb/> 359(6380):1146-1151.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>William Yang Wang. 2017. &quot;Liar, Liar Pants on Fire&quot;:<lb/> A new benchmark dataset for fake news detection.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 55th Annual Meeting of the As-<lb/>sociation for Computational Linguistics (Volume 2:<lb/> Short Papers), pages 422-426, Vancouver, Canada.<lb/> Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>        
        <bibl>Lianwei Wu, Yuan Rao, Haolin Jin, Ambreen Nazir,<lb/> and Ling Sun. 2019. Different absorption from the<lb/> same sharing: Sifted multi-task learning for fake<lb/> news detection. In Proceedings of the 2019 Con-<lb/>ference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language<lb/> Processing and the 9th International Joint Confer-<lb/>ence on Natural Language Processing (EMNLP-<lb/>IJCNLP), pages 4636-4645.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>You Wu, Pankaj K Agarwal, Chengkai Li, Jun Yang,<lb/> and Cong Yu. 2014. Toward computational fact-<lb/>checking. Proceedings of the VLDB Endowment,<lb/> 7(7):589-600.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Jianfei Yu, Jing Jiang, Ling Min Serena Khoo,<lb/> Hai Leong Chieu, and Rui Xia. 2020. Coupled hi-<lb/>erarchical transformer for stance-aware rumor veri-<lb/>fication in social media conversations. In Proceed-<lb/>ings of the 2020 Conference on Empirical Methods<lb/> in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP), pages<lb/> 1392-1401, Online. Association for Computational<lb/> Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Yu Zhang and Qiang Yang. 2017. A survey on multi-<lb/>task learning. arXiv preprint arXiv:1707.08114.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Arkaitz Zubiaga, Maria Liakata, Rob Procter, Geral-<lb/>dine Wong Sak Hoi, and Peter Tolmie. 2016.<lb/> Analysing how people orient to and spread rumours<lb/> in social media by looking at conversational threads.<lb/> PloS one, 11(3):e0150989.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

