<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> Robert Roskoski Jr. USFDA Approved Protein Kinase Inhibitors. . 2017; http://www.brimr.org/PKI/PKIs.htm, updated<lb/> 3 May 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> Santos R, Ursu O, Gaulton A, Bento AP, Donadi RS, Bologa CG, Karlsson A, Al-Lazikani B, Hersey A, Oprea TI,<lb/> Overington JP. A Comprehensive Map of Molecular Drug Targets. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2016 Dec; 16(1):19-34. doi:<lb/> 10.1038/nrd.2016.230.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> Shah NP, Nicoll JM, Nagar B, Gorre ME, Paquette RL, Kuriyan J, Sawyers CL. Multiple BCR-ABL Kinase Domain<lb/> Mutations Confer Polyclonal Resistance to the Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor Imatinib (STI571) in Chronic Phase and Blast<lb/> Crisis Chronic Myeloid Leukemia. Cancer Cell. 2002 Aug; 2(2):117-125.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> Buczek M, Escudier B, Bartnik E, Szczylik C, Czarnecka A. Resistance to tyrosine kinase inhibitors in clear cell<lb/> renal cell carcinoma: From the patient&apos;s bed to molecular mechanisms. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) -<lb/>Reviews on Cancer. 2014; 1845(1):31 -41. http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0304419X13000437, doi:<lb/> https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbcan.2013.10.001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> Huang L, Fu L. Mechanisms of Resistance to EGFR Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors. Acta Pharm Sin B. 2015; 5(5):390-401.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> Meyer SC, Levine RL. Molecular Pathways: Molecular Basis for Sensitivity and Resistance to JAK Kinase Inhibitors.<lb/> Clin Cancer Res. 2014; 20(8):2051-2059. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-13-0279.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label> Davare MA, Vellore NA, Wagner JP, Eide CA, Goodman JR, Drilon A, Deininger MW, O?Hare T, Druker BJ. Struc-<lb/>tural Insight into Selectivity and Resistance Profiles of ROS1 Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2015;<lb/>  112(39):E5381-E5390. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1515281112.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> Van Allen EM, Wagle N, Sucker A, Treacy DJ, Johannessen CM, Goetz EM, Place CS, Taylor-Weiner A, Whittaker S,<lb/> Kryukov GV, Hodis E, Rosenberg M, McKenna A, Cibulskis K, Farlow D, Zimmer L, Hillen U, Gutzmer R, Goldinger SM,<lb/>  Ugurel S, et al. The Genetic Landscape of Clinical Resistance to RAF Inhibition in Metastatic Melanoma. Cancer Discov.<lb/> 2014; 4(1):94-109. doi: 10.1158/2159-8290.CD-13-0617.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> Rani S, Corcoran C, Shiels L, Germano S, Breslin S, Madden S, McDermott MS, Browne BC, OtextquoterightDonovan<lb/> N, Crown J, Gogarty M, Byrne AT, OtextquoterightDriscoll L. Neuromedin U: A Candidate Biomarker and Therapeutic<lb/> Target to Predict and Overcome Resistance to HER-Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors. Cancer Res. 2014; 74(14):3821-3833.<lb/> doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-13-2053.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> Holohan C, Van Schaeybroeck S, Longley DB, Johnston PG. Cancer Drug Resistance: An Evolving Paradigm. Nat Rev<lb/> Cancer. 2013 Sep; 13(10):714-726. doi: 10.1038/nrc3599.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> Weisberg E, Manley PW, Cowan-Jacob SW, Hochhaus A, Griffin JD. Second Generation Inhibitors of BCR-ABL for<lb/> the Treatment of Imatinib-Resistant Chronic Myeloid Leukaemia. Nat Rev Cancer. 2007 May; 7(5):345-356. doi:<lb/> 10.1038/nrc2126.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> Y Lu X, Cai Q, Ding K. Recent Developments in the Third Generation Inhibitors of Bcr-Abl for Overriding T315I<lb/> Mutation. Curr Med Chem. 2011 May; 18(14):2146-2157. doi: 10.2174/092986711795656135.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> Juchum M, Günther M, Laufer SA. Fighting Cancer Drug Resistance: Opportunities and Challenges for Mutation-<lb/>Specific EGFR Inhibitors. Drug Resist Updat. 2015 May; 20:12-28. doi: 10.1016/j.drup.2015.05.002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> Song Z, Wang M, Zhang A. Alectinib: A Novel Second Generation Anaplastic Lymphoma Kinase (ALK) Inhibitor for<lb/> Overcoming Clinically-Acquired Resistance. Acta Pharm Sin B. 2015 Jan; 5(1):34-37. doi: 10.1016/j.apsb.2014.12.007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> Neel DS, Bivona TG. Resistance Is Futile: Overcoming Resistance to Targeted Therapies in Lung Adenocarcinoma.<lb/> Npj Precis Oncol. 2017 Dec; 1(1). doi: 10.1038/s41698-017-0007-0.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> Gruber F, Hjorth-Hansen H, Mikkola I, Stenke L, TA J. A Novel BCR-ABL Splice Isoform Is Associated with the L248V<lb/> Mutation in CML Patients with Acquired Resistance to Imatinib. Leuk Off J Leuk Soc Am Leuk Res Fund UK. 2006 Dec;<lb/> 20:2057-60.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> Chandarlapaty S, Sawai A, Scaltriti M, Rodrik-Outmezguine V, Grbovic-Huezo O, Serra V, Majumder PK, Baselga J,<lb/> Rosen N. AKT Inhibition Relieves Feedback Suppression of Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Expression and Activity. Cancer<lb/> Cell. 2011 Jan; 19(1):58-71. doi: 10.1016/j.ccr.2010.10.031.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> Knight ZA, Lin H, Shokat KM. Targeting the Cancer Kinome through Polypharmacology. Nat Rev Cancer. 2010;<lb/> 10(2):130.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> Housman G, Byler S, Heerboth S, Lapinska K, Longacre M, Snyder N, Sarkar S. Drug Resistance in Cancer: An<lb/> Overview. Cancers. 2014 Sep; 6(3):1769-1792. doi: 10.3390/cancers6031769.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> Zehir A, Benayed R, Shah RH, Syed A, Middha S, Kim HR, Srinivasan P, Gao J, Chakravarty D, Devlin SM, Hellmann MD,<lb/> Barron DA, Schram AM, Hameed M, Dogan S, Ross DS, Hechtman JF, DeLair DF, Yao J, Mandelker DL, et al. Mutational<lb/> Landscape of Metastatic Cancer Revealed from Prospective Clinical Sequencing of 10,000 Patients. Nat Med. 2017<lb/>  May; 23(6):703-713. doi: 10.1038/nm.4333.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> Redig A J, Jänne PA. Basket Trials and the Evolution of Clinical Trial Design in an Era of Genomic Medicine. American<lb/> Society of Clinical Oncology; 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> Hyman DM, Taylor BS, Baselga J. Implementing Genome-Driven Oncology. Cell. 2017 Feb; 168(4):584-599. doi:<lb/> 10.1016/j.cell.2016.12.015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> Pesesky MW, Hussain T, Wallace M, Patel S, Andleeb S, Burnham CAD, Dantas G. Evaluation of Machine Learning<lb/> and Rules-Based Approaches for Predicting Antimicrobial Resistance Profiles in Gram-Negative Bacilli from Whole<lb/> Genome Sequence Data. Front Microbiol. 2016 Nov; 7. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2016.01887.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> Melnikov A, Rogov P, Wang L, Gnirke A, Mikkelsen TS. Comprehensive Mutational Scanning of a Kinase in Vivo Reveals<lb/> Substrate-Dependent Fitness Landscapes. Nucleic Acids Res. 2014 Aug; 42(14):e112-e112. doi: 10.1093/nar/gku511.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> Harder E, Damm W, Maple J, Wu C, Reboul M, Xiang JY, Wang L, Lupyan D, Dahlgren MK, Knight JL, Kaus JW, Cerutti<lb/> DS, Krilov G, Jorgensen WL, Abel R, Friesner RA. OPLS3: A Force Field Providing Broad Coverage of Drug-like Small<lb/> Molecules and Proteins. J Chem Theory Comput. 2016 Jan; 12(1):281-296. doi: 10.1021/acs.jctc.5b00864.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> Huang J, MacKerell AD. CHARMM36 All-Atom Additive Protein Force Field: Validation Based on Comparison to NMR<lb/> Data. J Comput Chem. 2013 Sep; 34(25):2135-2145. doi: 10.1002/jcc.23354.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[27]</label> Maier JA, Martinez C, Kasavajhala K, Wickstrom L, Hauser KE, Simmerling C. ff14SB: Improving the Accuracy of<lb/> Protein Side Chain and Backbone Parameters from ff99SB. J Chem Theory Comput. 2015 Aug; 11(8):3696-3713. doi:<lb/> 10.1021/acs.jctc.5b00255.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[28]</label> Chodera JD, Mobley DL, Shirts MR, Dixon RW, Branson K, Pande VS. Alchemical Free Energy Methods for Drug<lb/> Discovery: Progress and Challenges. Curr Opin Struct Biol. 2011 Apr; 21(2):150-160. doi: 10.1016/j.sbi.2011.01.011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[29]</label> Wang L, Wu Y, Deng Y, Kim B, Pierce L, Krilov G, Lupyan D, Robinson S, Dahlgren MK, Greenwood J, Romero DL, Masse<lb/> C, Knight JL, Steinbrecher T, Beuming T, Damm W, Harder E, Sherman W, Brewer M, Wester R, et al. Accurate and<lb/> Reliable Prediction of Relative Ligand Binding Potency in Prospective Drug Discovery by Way of a Modern Free-Energy<lb/> Calculation Protocol and Force Field. J Am Chem Soc. 2015 Feb; 137(7):2695-2703. doi: 10.1021/ja512751q.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[30]</label> Abel R, Mondal S, Masse C, Greenwood J, Harriman G, Ashwell MA, Bhat S, Wester R, Frye L, Kapeller R, et al.<lb/> Accelerating drug discovery through tight integration of expert molecular design and predictive scoring. Current<lb/> opinion in structural biology. 2017; 43:38-44.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[31]</label> Aldeghi M, Heifetz A, Bodkin MJ, Knapp S, Biggin PC. Accurate Calculation of the Absolute Free Energy of Binding for<lb/> Drug Molecules. Chem Sci. 2016; 7(1):207-218. doi: 10.1039/C5SC02678D.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[32]</label> Cappel D, Hall ML, Lenselink EB, Beuming T, Qi J, Bradner J, Sherman W. Relative Binding Free Energy Calculations<lb/> Applied to Protein Homology Models. J Chem Inf Model. 2016; 56(12):2388-2400. doi: 10.1021/acs.jcim.6b00362.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[33]</label> Clark A J, Gindin T, Zhang B, Wang L, Abel R, Murret CS, Xu F, Bao A, Lu NJ, Zhou T, et al. Free Energy Perturbation<lb/> Calculation of Relative Binding Free Energy between Broadly Neutralizing Antibodies and the gp120 Glycoprotein of<lb/> HIV-1. Journal of molecular biology. 2017; 429(7):930-947.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[34]</label> Steinbrecher T, Zhu C, Wang L, Abel R, Negron C, Pearlman D, Feyfant E, Duan J, Sherman W. Predicting the Effect of<lb/> Amino Acid Single-Point Mutations on Protein Stability-Large-Scale Validation of MD-Based Relative Free Energy<lb/> Calculations. Journal of molecular biology. 2017; 429(7):948-963.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[35]</label> Ford MC, Babaoglu K. Examining the Feasibility of Using Free Energy Perturbation (FEP+) in Predicting Protein<lb/> Stability. J Chem Inf Model. 2017 Jun; 57(6):1276-1285. doi: 10.1021/acs.jcim.7b00002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[36]</label> Zou J, Song B, Simmerling C, Raleigh D. Experimental and Computational Analysis of Protein Stabilization by Gly-<lb/>to-D -Ala Substitution: A Convolution of Native State and Unfolded State Effects. J Am Chem Soc. 2016 Dec;<lb/>  138(48):15682-15689. doi: 10.1021/jacs.6b09511.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[37]</label> Mondal J, Tiwary P, Berne BJ. How a Kinase Inhibitor Withstands Gatekeeper Residue Mutations. J Am Chem Soc.<lb/> 2016; 138(13):4608-4615. doi: 10.1021/jacs.6b01232.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[38]</label> Lovering F, Aevazelis C, Chang J, Dehnhardt C, Fitz L, Han S, Janz K, Lee J, Kaila N, McDonald J, Moore W, Moretto<lb/> A, Papaioannou N, Richard D, Ryan MS, Wan ZK, Thorarensen A. Imidazotriazines: Spleen Tyrosine Kinase<lb/> (Syk) Inhibitors Identified by Free-Energy Perturbation (FEP). ChemMedChem. 2016 Jan; 11(2):217-233. doi:<lb/> 10.1002/cmdc.201500333.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[39]</label> Rapp C, Kalyanaraman C, Schiffmiller A, Schoenbrun EL, Jacobson MP. A Molecular Mechanics Approach to Modeling<lb/> Protein-Ligand Interactions: Relative Binding Affinities in Congeneric Series. J Chem Inf Model. 2011 Sep; 51(9):2082-<lb/>2089. doi: 10.1021/ci200033n.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[40]</label> Shirts MR, Mobley DL, Chodera JD. Chapter 4 Alchemical Free Energy Calculations: Ready for Prime Time? In: Annual<lb/> Reports in Computational Chemistry, vol. 3 Elsevier; 2007.p. 41-59.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[41]</label> Mobley DL, Klimovich PV. Perspective: Alchemical Free Energy Calculations for Drug Discovery. J Chem Phys. 2012<lb/> Dec; 137(23):230901. doi: 10.1063/1.4769292.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[42]</label> Abel R, Mondal S, Masse C, Greenwood J, Harriman G, Ashwell MA, Bhat S, Wester R, Frye L, Kapeller R, Friesner RA.<lb/> Accelerating Drug Discovery through Tight Integration of Expert Molecular Design and Predictive Scoring. Curr Opin<lb/> Struct Biol. 2017 Apr; 43:38-44. doi: 10.1016/j.sbi.2016.10.007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[43]</label> Kuhn B, Tichý M, Wang L, Robinson S, Martin RE, Kuglstatter A, Benz J, Giroud M, Schirmeister T, Abel R, Diederich F,<lb/> Hert J. Prospective Evaluation of Free Energy Calculations for the Prioritization of Cathepsin L Inhibitors. J Med Chem.<lb/> 2017 Mar; 60(6):2485-2497. doi: 10.1021/acs.jmedchem.6b01881.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[44]</label> Pemovska T, Johnson E, Kontro M, Repasky GA, Chen J, Wells P, Cronin CN, McTigue M, Kallioniemi O, Porkka K,<lb/> Murray BW, Wennerberg K. Axitinib Effectively Inhibits BCR-ABL1(T315I) with a Distinct Binding Conformation. Nature.<lb/> 2015 Feb; 519(7541):102-105. doi: 10.1038/nature14119.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[45]</label> Schrock A, Chen TH, Clackson T, Rivera VM. Comprehensive Analysis Of The In Vitro Potency Of Ponatinib, and<lb/> All Other Approved BCR-ABL Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors (TKIs), Against a Panel Of Single and Compound BCR-ABL<lb/> Mutants. Blood. 2013; 122(21):3992-3992.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[46]</label> Davis MI, Hunt JP, Herrgard S, Ciceri P, Wodicka LM, Pallares G, Hocker M, Treiber DK, Zarrinkar PP. Comprehensive<lb/> Analysis of Kinase Inhibitor Selectivity. Nat Biotechnol. 2011 Oct; 29(11):1046-1051. doi: 10.1038/nbt.1990.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[47]</label> Soverini S, Colarossi S, Gnani A, Rosti G, Castagnetti F, Poerio A, Iacobucci I, Amabile M, Abruzzese E, Orlandi<lb/> E, Radaelli F, Ciccone F, Tiribelli M, di Lorenzo R, Caracciolo C, Izzo B, Pane F, Saglio G, Baccarani M, Martinelli G.<lb/> Contribution of ABL Kinase Domain Mutations to Imatinib Resistance in Different Subsets of Philadelphia-Positive<lb/> Patients: By the GIMEMA Working Party on Chronic Myeloid Leukemia. Clinical Cancer Research. 2006; 12(24):7374-<lb/>7379. http://clincancerres.aacrjournals.org/content/12/24/7374, doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-06-1516.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[48]</label> O&apos;Hare T, Eide CA, Deininger MW. Bcr-Abl kinase domain mutations, drug resistance, and the road to a cure for<lb/> chronic myeloid leukemia. Blood. 2007; 110(7):2242-2249.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[49]</label> O&apos;Hare T. Combined Abl Inhibitor Therapy for Minimizing Drug Resistance in Chronic Myeloid Leukemia: Src/Abl<lb/> Inhibitors Are Compatible with Imatinib. Clin Cancer Res. 2005 Oct; 11(19):6987-6993. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-<lb/>05-0622.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[50]</label> Shan Y, Seeliger MA, Eastwood MP, Frank F, Xu H, Jensen MØ, Dror RO, Kuriyan J, Shaw DE. A Conserved Protonation-<lb/>Dependent Switch Controls Drug Binding in the Abl Kinase. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2009; 106(1):139-144.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[51]</label> Demerdash O, Yap EH, Head-Gordon T. Advanced Potential Energy Surfaces for Condensed Phase Simulation. Annu<lb/> Rev Phys Chem. 2014 Apr; 65(1):149-174. doi: 10.1146/annurev-physchem-040412-110040.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[52]</label> Jiao D, Golubkov PA, Darden TA, Ren P. Calculation of Protein-ligand Binding Free Energy by Using a Polarizable<lb/> Potential. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2008; 105(17):6290-6295.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[53]</label> Shirts MR, Mobley DL, Chodera JD, Pande VS. Accurate and Efficient Corrections for Missing Dispersion Interactions<lb/> in Molecular Simulations. J Phys Chem B. 2007 Nov; 111(45):13052-13063. doi: 10.1021/jp0735987.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[54]</label> Essmann U, Perera L, Berkowitz ML, Darden T, Lee H, Pedersen LG. A Smooth Particle Mesh Ewald Method. J Chem<lb/> Phys. 1995 Nov; 103(19):8577-8593. doi: 10.1063/1.470117.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[55]</label> Wennberg CL, Murtola T, Hess B, Lindahl E. Lennard-Jones Lattice Summation in Bilayer Simulations Has Crit-<lb/>ical Effects on Surface Tension and Lipid Properties. J Chem Theory Comput. 2013 Aug; 9(8):3527-3537. doi:<lb/> 10.1021/ct400140n.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[56]</label> Onufriev AV, Alexov E. Protonation and pK Changes in Protein-ligand Binding. Q Rev Biophys. 2013 May; 46(02):181-<lb/>209. doi: 10.1017/S0033583513000024.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[57]</label> Martin YC. Let&apos;s Not Forget Tautomers. J Comput Aided Mol Des. 2009 Oct; 23(10):693-704. doi: 10.1007/s10822-<lb/>009-9303-2.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[58]</label> Jensen J. Calculating pH and Salt Dependence of Protein-Protein Binding. Curr Pharm Biotechnol. 2008 Apr;<lb/> 9(2):96-102. doi: 10.2174/138920108783955146.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[59]</label> Nagar B, Hantschel O, Young MA, Scheffzek K, Veach D, Bornmann W, Clarkson B, Superti-Furga G, Kuriyan J. Structural<lb/> Basis for the Autoinhibition of C-Abl Tyrosine Kinase. Cell. 2003; 112(6):859-871.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[60]</label> Lorenz S, Deng P, Hantschel O, Superti-Furga G, Kuriyan J. Crystal Structure of an SH2-kinase Construct of C-Abl and<lb/> Effect of the SH2 Domain on Kinase Activity. Biochem J. 2015 Jun; 468(2):283-291. doi: 10.1042/BJ20141492.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[61]</label> O&apos;Hare T, Shakespeare WC, Zhu X, Eide CA, Rivera VM, Wang F, Adrian LT, Zhou T, Huang WS, Xu Q, Metcalf CA, Tyner<lb/> JW, Loriaux MM, Corbin AS, Wardwell S, Ning Y, Keats JA, Wang Y, Sundaramoorthi R, Thomas M, et al. AP24534, a Pan-<lb/>BCR-ABL Inhibitor for Chronic Myeloid Leukemia, Potently Inhibits the T315I Mutant and Overcomes Mutation-Based<lb/> Resistance. Cancer Cell. 2009 Nov; 16(5):401-412. doi: 10.1016/j.ccr.2009.09.028.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[62]</label> Levinson NM, Boxer SG. Structural and Spectroscopic Analysis of the Kinase Inhibitor Bosutinib and an Isomer<lb/> of Bosutinib Binding to the Abl Tyrosine Kinase Domain. PLoS ONE. 2012 Apr; 7(4):e29828. doi: 10.1371/jour-<lb/>nal.pone.0029828.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[63]</label> Weisberg E, Manley PW, Breitenstein W, Brüggen J, Cowan-Jacob SW, Ray A, Huntly B, Fabbro D, Fendrich G, Hall-<lb/>Meyers E, Kung AL, Mestan J, Daley GQ, Callahan L, Catley L, Cavazza C, Mohammed A, Neuberg D, Wright RD, Gilliland<lb/> DG, et al. Characterization of AMN107, a Selective Inhibitor of Native and Mutant Bcr-Abl. Cancer Cell. 2005 Feb;<lb/> 7(2):129-141. doi: 10.1016/j.ccr.2005.01.007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[64]</label> Zhou T, Commodore L, Huang WS, Wang Y, Thomas M, Keats J, Xu Q, Rivera VM, Shakespeare WC, Clackson T, Dalgarno<lb/> DC, Zhu X. Structural Mechanism of the Pan-BCR-ABL Inhibitor Ponatinib (AP24534): Lessons for Overcoming<lb/> Kinase Inhibitor Resistance: Structural Mechanism of Ponatinib. Chem Biol Drug Des. 2011 Jan; 77(1):1-11. doi:<lb/> 10.1111/j.1747-0285.2010.01054.x.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[65]</label> Li H, Robertson AD, Jensen JH. Very Fast Empirical Prediction and Rationalization of Protein pKa Values. Proteins<lb/> Struct Funct Bioinforma. 2005 Oct; 61(4):704-721. doi: 10.1002/prot.20660.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[66]</label> Friesner RA, Banks JL, Murphy RB, Halgren TA, Klicic JJ, Mainz DT, Repasky MP, Knoll EH, Shelley M, Perry JK, Shaw DE,<lb/> Francis P, Shenkin PS. Glide: A New Approach for Rapid, Accurate Docking and Scoring. 1. Method and Assessment of<lb/> Docking Accuracy. J Med Chem. 2004 Mar; 47(7):1739-1749. doi: 10.1021/jm0306430.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[67]</label> Park JH, Liu Y, Lemmon MA, Radhakrishnan R. Erlotinib Binds Both Inactive and Active Conformations of the EGFR<lb/> Tyrosine Kinase Domain. Biochem J. 2012 Dec; 448(3):417-423. doi: 10.1042/BJ20121513.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[68]</label> Yosaatmadja Y, Squire CJ. 1.85 Angstrom Structure of EGFR Kinase Domain with Gefitinib. . 2014 Nov; doi:<lb/> 10.2210/pdb4wkq/pdb.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[69]</label> Shelley JC, Cholleti A, Frye LL, Greenwood JR, Timlin MR, Uchimaya M. Epik: A Software Program for pK a Prediction<lb/> and Protonation State Generation for Drug-like Molecules. J Comput Aided Mol Des. 2007 Dec; 21(12):681-691. doi:<lb/> 10.1007/s10822-007-9133-z.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[70]</label> Berendsen HJC, Postma JPM, van Gunsteren WF, Hermans J. Interaction Models for Water in Relation to Protein<lb/> Hydration. In: Pullman B, editor. Intermolecular Forces, vol. 14 Dordrecht: Springer Netherlands; 1981.p. 331-342. doi:<lb/> 10.1007/978-94-015-7658-1_21.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[71]</label> Shivakumar D, Williams J, Wu Y, Damm W, Shelley J, Sherman W. Prediction of Absolute Solvation Free Energies<lb/> Using Molecular Dynamics Free Energy Perturbation and the OPLS Force Field. J Chem Theory Comput. 2010 May;<lb/>  6(5):1509-1519. doi: 10.1021/ct900587b.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[72]</label> Pearlman DA. A Comparison of Alternative Approaches to Free Energy Calculations. J Phys Chem. 1994 Feb;<lb/>  98(5):1487-1493. doi: 10.1021/j100056a020.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[73]</label> Rocklin GJ, Mobley DL, Dill KA, Hünenberger PH. Calculating the Binding Free Energies of Charged Species Based<lb/> on Explicit-Solvent Simulations Employing Lattice-Sum Methods: An Accurate Correction Scheme for Electrostatic<lb/> Finite-Size Effects. J Chem Phys. 2013 Nov; 139(18):184103. doi: 10.1063/1.4826261.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[74]</label> Feller SE, Zhang Y, Pastor RW, Brooks BR. Constant pressure molecular dynamics simulation: The Langevin pis-<lb/>ton method. The Journal of Chemical Physics. 1995; 103(11):4613-4621. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.470648, doi:<lb/> 10.1063/1.470648.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[75]</label> Essmann U, Perera L, Berkowitz ML, Darden T, Lee H, Pedersen LG. A smooth particle mesh Ewald method. The<lb/> Journal of Chemical Physics. 1995; 103(19):8577-8593. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.470117, doi: 10.1063/1.470117.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[76]</label> Martyna GJ, Tobias DJ, Klein ML. Constant pressure molecular dynamics algorithms. The Journal of Chemical Physics.<lb/> 1994; 101(5):4177-4189. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.467468, doi: 10.1063/1.467468.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[77]</label> Tuckerman M, Berne BJ, Martyna GJ. Reversible multiple time scale molecular dynamics. The Journal of Chemical<lb/> Physics. 1992; 97(3):1990-2001. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.463137, doi: 10.1063/1.463137.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[78]</label> Hopkins CW, Le Grand S, Walker RC, Roitberg AE. Long-Time-Step Molecular Dynamics through Hydrogen Mass<lb/> Repartitioning. Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation. 2015; 11(4):1864-1874. http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/<lb/> ct5010406, doi: 10.1021/ct5010406, pMID: 26574392.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[79]</label> Wang L, Berne BJ, Friesner RA. On Achieving High Accuracy and Reliability in the Calculation of Relative Protein-Ligand<lb/> Binding Affinities. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2012 Feb; 109(6):1937-1942. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1114017109.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[80]</label> Bennett CH. Efficient Estimation of Free Energy Differences from Monte Carlo Data. J Comput Phys. 1976; 22:245-<lb/>268.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[81]</label> Shirts MR, Bair E, Hooker G, Pande VS. Equilibrium Free Energies from Nonequilibrium Measurements Using<lb/> Maximum-Likelihood Methods. Phys Rev Lett. 2003 Oct; 91(14). doi: 10.1103/PhysRevLett.91.140601.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[82]</label> Price DJ, Jorgensen WL. Computational Binding Studies of Human Pp60c-Src SH2 Domain with a Series of Nonpeptide,<lb/> Phosphophenyl-Containing Ligands. Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2000 Sep; 10(18):2067-2070. doi: 10.1016/S0960-<lb/>894X(00)00401-7.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[83]</label> Luccarelli J, Michel J, Tirado-Rives J, Jorgensen WL. Effects of Water Placement on Predictions of Binding Affinities for<lb/> P38 MAP Kinase Inhibitors. J Chem Theory Comput. 2010 Dec; 6(12):3850-3856. doi: 10.1021/ct100504h.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[84]</label> Michel J, Verdonk ML, Essex JW. Protein-Ligand Binding Affinity Predictions by Implicit Solvent Simulations: A Tool for<lb/> Lead Optimization? J Med Chem. 2006 Dec; 49(25):7427-7439. doi: 10.1021/jm061021s.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[85]</label> Salvatier J, Wiecki TV, Fonnesbeck C. Probabilistic programming in Python using PyMC3. PeerJ Computer Science.<lb/> 2016 Apr; 2:e55. https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj-cs.55, doi: 10.7717/peerj-cs.55.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[86]</label> Gruber FX, Lundán T, Goll R, Silye A, Mikkola I, Rekvig OP, Knuutila S, Remes K, Gedde-Dahl T, Porkka K, Hjorth-Hansen<lb/> H. BCR-ABL Isoforms Associated with Intrinsic or Acquired Resistance to Imatinib: More Heterogeneous than Just<lb/> ABL Kinase Domain Point Mutations? Med Oncol. 2012 Mar; 29(1):219-226. doi: 10.1007/s12032-010-9781-z.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[87]</label> Branford S. High Frequency of Point Mutations Clustered within the Adenosine Triphosphate-Binding Region of<lb/> BCR/ABL in Patients with Chronic Myeloid Leukemia or Ph-Positive Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Who Develop<lb/> Imatinib (STI571) Resistance. Blood. 2002 May; 99(9):3472-3475. doi: 10.1182/blood.V99.9.3472.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

