<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        * To whom correspondence should be addressed at hugh-<lb/>est@illinois.edu<lb/> † on sabbatical<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>1</label> W. A. Benalcazar, B. A. Bernevig, and T. L.<lb/> Hughes, &quot;Quantized electric multipole insulators,&quot; Sci-<lb/>ence, vol. 357, no. 6346, pp. 61-66, 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>2</label> R. Resta, &quot;Theory of the electric polarization in crystals,&quot;<lb/> Ferroelectrics, vol. 136, no. 1, pp. 51-55, 1992.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>3</label> R. D. King-Smith and D. Vanderbilt, &quot;Theory of polariza-<lb/>tion of crystalline solids,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 47, pp. 1651-<lb/>1654, Jan 1993.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>4</label> D. Vanderbilt and R. King-Smith, &quot;Electric polarization as<lb/> a bulk quantity and its relation to surface charge,&quot; Phys.<lb/> Rev. B, vol. 48, no. 7, p. 4442, 1993.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>5</label> R. Resta, M. Posternak, and A. Baldereschi, &quot;Towards a<lb/> quantum theory of polarization in ferroelectrics: The case<lb/> of knbo3,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 70, pp. 1010-1013, Feb<lb/> 1993.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>6</label> R. Resta, &quot;Macroscopic polarization in crystalline di-<lb/>electrics: the geometric phase approach,&quot; Rev. Mod. Phys.,<lb/> vol. 66, pp. 899-915, Jul 1994.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>7</label> R. Resta and D. Vanderbilt, Theory of Polarization: A<lb/> Modern Approach, pp. 31-68. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer<lb/> Berlin Heidelberg, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>8</label> M. V. Berry, &quot;Quantal phase factors accompanying adia-<lb/>batic changes,&quot; Proceedings of the Royal Society of Lon-<lb/>don A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences,<lb/> vol. 392, no. 1802, pp. 45-57, 1984.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>9</label> J. Zak, &quot;Berry&apos;s phase for energy bands in solids,&quot; Phys.<lb/> Rev. Lett., vol. 62, pp. 2747-2750, Jun 1989.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>10</label> W. P. Su, J. R. Schrieffer, and A. J. Heeger, &quot;Solitons in<lb/> polyacetylene,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 42, pp. 1698-1701,<lb/> Jun 1979.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>11</label> S. Kivelson, &quot;Wannier functions in one-dimensional dis-<lb/>ordered systems: Application to fractionally charged soli-<lb/>tons,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 26, no. 8, p. 4269, 1982.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>12</label> D. J. Thouless, &quot;Quantization of particle transport,&quot; Phys.<lb/> Rev. B, vol. 27, pp. 6083-6087, May 1983.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>13</label> D. Thouless, M. Kohmoto, M. Nightingale, and<lb/> M. Den Nijs, &quot;Quantized hall conductance in a two-<lb/>dimensional periodic potential,&quot; Physs Rev. Lett., vol. 49,<lb/> no. 6, p. 405, 1982.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>14</label> K. v. Klitzing, G. Dorda, and M. Pepper, &quot;New method<lb/> for high-accuracy determination of the fine-structure con-<lb/>stant based on quantized hall resistance,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett.,<lb/> vol. 45, no. 6, p. 494, 1980.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>15</label> F. Haldane, &quot;Model for a quantum hall effect without<lb/> landau levels: Condensed-matter realization of the&quot;parity<lb/> anomaly&quot;,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 61, no. 18, pp. 2015-2018,<lb/> 1988.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>16</label> X.-L. Qi, T. L. Hughes, and S.-C. Zhang, &quot;Topological field<lb/> theory of time-reversal invariant insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev. B,<lb/> vol. 78, no. 19, p. 195424, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>17</label> A. M. Essin, J. E. Moore, and D. Vanderbilt, &quot;Mag-<lb/>netoelectric polarizability and axion electrodynamics in<lb/> crystalline insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 102, no. 14,<lb/> p. 146805, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>18</label> T. L. Hughes, E. Prodan, and B. A. Bernevig, &quot;Inversion-<lb/>symmetric topological insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 83,<lb/> no. 24, p. 245132, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>19</label> A. M. Turner, Y. Zhang, R. S. Mong, and A. Vishwanath,<lb/> &quot;Quantized response and topology of magnetic insulators<lb/> with inversion symmetry,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 85, no. 16,<lb/> p. 165120, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>20</label> A. Altland and M. R. Zirnbauer, &quot;Nonstandard symme-<lb/>try classes in mesoscopic normal-superconducting hybrid<lb/> structures,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 55, p. 1142, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>21</label> A. P. Schnyder, S. Ryu, A. Furusaki, and A. W. W. Lud-<lb/>wig, &quot;Classification of topological insulators and supercon-<lb/>ductors in three spatial dimensions,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 78,<lb/> p. 195125, Nov 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>22</label> A. Kitaev, &quot;Periodic table for topological insulators and<lb/> superconductors,&quot; AIP Conference Proceedings, vol. 1134,<lb/> no. 22, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>23</label> J. C. Y. Teo, L. Fu, and C. L. Kane, &quot;Surface states and<lb/> topological invariants in three-dimensional topological in-<lb/>sulators: Application to bi1−xsbx,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 78,<lb/> p. 045426, Jul 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>24</label> C.-K. Chiu, H. Yao, and S. Ryu, &quot;Classification of topo-<lb/>logical insulators and superconductors in the presence of<lb/> reflection symmetry,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 88, p. 075142, Aug<lb/> 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>25</label> C.-K. Chiu, H. Yao, and S. Ryu, &quot;Classification of topo-<lb/>logical insulators and superconductors in the presence of<lb/> reflection symmetry,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 88, p. 075142, Aug<lb/> 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>26</label> Y. Ueno, A. Yamakage, Y. Tanaka, and M. Sato,<lb/> &quot;Symmetry-protected majorana fermions in topological<lb/> crystalline superconductors: Theory and application to<lb/> sr2ruo4,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 111, p. 087002, Aug 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>27</label> F. Zhang, C. L. Kane, and E. J. Mele, &quot;Topological mirror<lb/> superconductivity,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 111, p. 056403,<lb/> Aug 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>28</label> A. Lau, J. van den Brink, and C. Ortix, &quot;Topological mir-<lb/>ror insulators in one dimension,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 94,<lb/> p. 165164, Oct 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>29</label> L. Fu and C. L. Kane, &quot;Topological insulators with inver-<lb/>sion symmetry,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 76, p. 045302, Jul 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>30</label> A. M. Turner, Y. Zhang, and A. Vishwanath, &quot;Entangle-<lb/>ment and inversion symmetry in topological insulators,&quot;<lb/> Phys. Rev. B, vol. 82, p. 241102, Dec 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>31</label> L. Fu, &quot;Topological crystalline insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev.<lb/> Lett., vol. 106, p. 106802, Mar 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>32</label> C. Fang, M. J. Gilbert, and B. A. Bernevig, &quot;Bulk topo-<lb/>logical invariants in noninteracting point group symmetric<lb/> insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 86, p. 115112, Sep 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>33</label> C. Fang, M. J. Gilbert, and B. A. Bernevig, &quot;Entangle-<lb/>ment spectrum classification of Cn-invariant noninteract-<lb/>ing topological insulators in two dimensions,&quot; Phys. Rev.<lb/> B, vol. 87, p. 035119, Jan 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>34</label> J. C. Y. Teo and T. L. Hughes, &quot;Existence of majorana-<lb/>fermion bound states on disclinations and the classification<lb/> of topological crystalline superconductors in two dimen-<lb/>sions,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 111, p. 047006, Jul 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>35</label> W. A. Benalcazar, J. C. Y. Teo, and T. L. Hughes, &quot;Clas-<lb/>sification of two-dimensional topological crystalline super-<lb/>conductors and majorana bound states at disclinations,&quot;<lb/> Phys. Rev. B, vol. 89, p. 224503, Jun 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>36</label> C.-X. Liu, R.-X. Zhang, and B. K. VanLeeuwen, &quot;Topo-<lb/>logical nonsymmorphic crystalline insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev.<lb/> B, vol. 90, p. 085304, Aug 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>37</label> S. Kobayashi, Y. Yanase, and M. Sato, &quot;Topologically sta-<lb/>ble gapless phases in nonsymmorphic superconductors,&quot;<lb/> Phys. Rev. B, vol. 94, p. 134512, Oct 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>38</label> A. Alexandradinata, Z. Wang, and B. A. Bernevig, &quot;Topo-<lb/>logical insulators from group cohomology,&quot; Phys. Rev. X,<lb/> vol. 6, p. 021008, Apr 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>39</label> R. S. K. Mong, A. M. Essin, and J. E. Moore, &quot;Antifer-<lb/>romagnetic topological insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 81,<lb/> p. 245209, Jun 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>40</label> P. Jadaun, D. Xiao, Q. Niu, and S. K. Banerjee, &quot;Topolog-<lb/>ical classification of crystalline insulators with space group<lb/> symmetry,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 88, p. 085110, Aug 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>41</label> R.-J. Slager, A. Mesaros, V. Juricic, and J. Zaanen, &quot;The<lb/> space group classification of topological band-insulators,&quot;<lb/> Nat Phys, vol. 9, pp. 98-102, 02 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>42</label> T. Morimoto and A. Furusaki, &quot;Topological classification<lb/> with additional symmetries from clifford algebras,&quot; Phys.<lb/> Rev. B, vol. 88, p. 125129, Sep 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>43</label> K. Shiozaki and M. Sato, &quot;Topology of crystalline in-<lb/>sulators and superconductors,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 90,<lb/> p. 165114, Oct 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>44</label> X.-Y. Dong and C.-X. Liu, &quot;Classification of topologi-<lb/>cal crystalline insulators based on representation theory,&quot;<lb/> Phys. Rev. B, vol. 93, p. 045429, Jan 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>45</label> C.-K. Chiu, J. C. Y. Teo, A. P. Schnyder, and S. Ryu,<lb/> &quot;Classification of topological quantum matter with sym-<lb/>metries,&quot; Rev. Mod. Phys., vol. 88, p. 035005, Aug 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>46</label> X.-Y. Dong and C.-X. Liu, &quot;Classification of topologi-<lb/>cal crystalline insulators based on representation theory,&quot;<lb/> Phys. Rev. B, vol. 93, p. 045429, Jan 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>47</label> H. Watanabe and L. Fu, &quot;Topological crystalline mag-<lb/>nets: Symmetry-protected topological phases of fermions,&quot;<lb/> Phys. Rev. B, vol. 95, p. 081107, Feb 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>48</label> B. Bradlyn, L. Elcoro, J. Cano, M. G. Vergniory, Z. Wang,<lb/> C. Felser, M. I. Aroyo, and B. A. Bernevig, &quot;Topological<lb/> quantum chemistry,&quot; arXiv:1703.02050, 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>49</label> K. Shiozaki, M. Sato, and K. Gomi, &quot;Topological crys-<lb/>talline materials: General formulation, module structure,<lb/> and wallpaper groups,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 95, p. 235425,<lb/> Jun 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>50</label> R. Yu, X. L. Qi, A. Bernevig, Z. Fang, and X. Dai, &quot;Equiv-<lb/>alent expression of z 2 topological invariant for band insu-<lb/>lators using the non-abelian berry connection,&quot; Phys. Rev.<lb/> B, vol. 84, no. 7, p. 075119, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>51</label> L. Fidkowski, T. S. Jackson, and I. Klich, &quot;Model charac-<lb/>terization of gapless edge modes of topological insulators<lb/> using intermediate brillouin-zone functions,&quot; Phys. Rev.<lb/> Lett., vol. 107, p. 036601, Jul 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>52</label> A. Alexandradinata, X. Dai, and B. A. Bernevig, &quot;Wilson-<lb/>loop characterization of inversion-symmetric topological<lb/> insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 89, p. 155114, Apr 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>53</label> M. Taherinejad and D. Vanderbilt, &quot;Adiabatic pumping of<lb/> chern-simons axion coupling,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 114,<lb/> p. 096401, Mar 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>54</label> T. Olsen, M. Taherinejad, D. Vanderbilt, and I. Souza,<lb/> &quot;Surface theorem for the chern-simons axion coupling,&quot;<lb/> Phys. Rev. B, vol. 95, p. 075137, Feb 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>55</label> Y. Zhou, K. M. Rabe, and D. Vanderbilt, &quot;Surface polar-<lb/>ization and edge charges,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 92, p. 041102,<lb/> Jul 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>56</label> R. Resta, &quot;Quantum-mechanical position operator in ex-<lb/>tended systems,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 80, pp. 1800-1803,<lb/> Mar 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>57</label> G. H. Wannier, &quot;Dynamics of band electrons in electric<lb/> and magnetic fields,&quot; Rev. Mod. Phys., vol. 34, pp. 645-<lb/>655, Oct 1962.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>58</label> N. Marzari and D. Vanderbilt, &quot;Maximally localized gen-<lb/>eralized wannier functions for composite energy bands,&quot;<lb/> Phys. Rev. B, vol. 56, no. 20, p. 12847, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>59</label> I. Souza, N. Marzari, and D. Vanderbilt, &quot;Maximally local-<lb/>ized wannier functions for entangled energy bands,&quot; Phys.<lb/> Rev. B, vol. 65, p. 035109, Dec 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>60</label> M. J. Rice and E. J. Mele, &quot;Elementary excitations of a<lb/> linearly conjugated diatomic polymer,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett.,<lb/> vol. 49, pp. 1455-1459, Nov 1982.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>61</label> M. Atala, M. Aidelsburger, J. T. Barreiro, D. Abanin,<lb/> T. Kitagawa, E. Demler, and I. Bloch, &quot;Direct measure-<lb/>ment of the zak phase in topological bloch bands,&quot; Nat<lb/> Phys, vol. 9, pp. 795-800, 12 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>62</label> L. Wang, M. Troyer, and X. Dai, &quot;Topological charge<lb/> pumping in a one-dimensional optical lattice,&quot; Phys. Rev.<lb/> Lett., vol. 111, p. 026802, Jul 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>63</label> H.-I. Lu, M. Schemmer, L. M. Aycock, D. Genkina, S. Sug-<lb/>awa, and I. B. Spielman, &quot;Geometrical pumping with<lb/> a bose-einstein condensate,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 116,<lb/> p. 200402, May 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>64</label> S. Coh and D. Vanderbilt, &quot;Electric polarization in a chern<lb/> insulator,&quot; Phys. Rev. Lett., vol. 102, p. 107603, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>65</label> D. Asahi and N. Nagaosa, &quot;Topological indices, defects,<lb/> and majorana fermions in chiral superconductors,&quot; Phys.<lb/> Rev. B, vol. 86, p. 100504, Sep 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>66</label> T. L. Hughes, H. Yao, and X.-L. Qi, &quot;Majorana zero modes<lb/> in dislocations of sr2ruo4,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 90, p. 235123,<lb/> Dec 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>67</label> C. Sgiarovello, M. Peressi, and R. Resta, &quot;Electron local-<lb/>ization in the insulating state: Application to crystalline<lb/> semiconductors,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 64, p. 115202, Aug<lb/> 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>68</label> M. Taherinejad, K. F. Garrity, and D. Vanderbilt, &quot;Wan-<lb/>nier center sheets in topological insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev. B,<lb/> vol. 89, p. 115102, Mar 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>69</label> G. W. Winkler, A. A. Soluyanov, and M. Troyer, &quot;Smooth<lb/> gauge and wannier functions for topological band struc-<lb/>tures in arbitrary dimensions,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 93,<lb/> p. 035453, Jan 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>70</label> E. Prodan, &quot;Manifestly gauge-independent formulations of<lb/> the 2 invariants,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 83, p. 235115, Jun<lb/> 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>71</label> A. A. Soluyanov and D. Vanderbilt, &quot;Smooth gauge for<lb/> topological insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 85, p. 115415,<lb/> Mar 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>72</label> A. Vishwanath and T. Senthil, &quot;Physics of three-<lb/>dimensional bosonic topological insulators:<lb/> Surface-<lb/>deconfined criticality and quantized magnetoelectric ef-<lb/>fect,&quot; Phys. Rev. X, vol. 3, no. 1, p. 011016, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>73</label> P. Bonderson, C. Nayak, and X.-L. Qi, &quot;A time-reversal<lb/> invariant topological phase at the surface of a 3d topolog-<lb/>ical insulator,&quot; Journal of Statistical Mechanics: Theory<lb/> and Experiment, vol. 2013, no. 09, p. P09016, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>74</label> C. Wang, A. C. Potter, and T. Senthil, &quot;Gapped symmetry<lb/> preserving surface state for the electron topological insu-<lb/>lator,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 88, no. 11, p. 115137, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>75</label> X. Chen, L. Fidkowski, and A. Vishwanath, &quot;Symmetry<lb/> enforced non-abelian topological order at the surface of<lb/> a topological insulator,&quot; Phys. Rev. B, vol. 89, no. 16,<lb/> p. 165132, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>76</label> M. A. Metlitski, C. Kane, and M. P. Fisher, &quot;Symmetry-<lb/>respecting topologically ordered surface phase of three-<lb/>dimensional electron topological insulators,&quot; Phys. Rev. B,<lb/> vol. 92, no. 12, p. 125111, 2015.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>77</label> Although a bulk transition implies closing the edge energy<lb/> gap, the contrary is not true, i.e., a closing of the edge<lb/> energy gap as a result of a phase transition of the edge<lb/> does not imply a transition in the bulk; in this later case,<lb/> the edge transition just causes the non-trivial edge at the<lb/> boundary of the quadrupole to recede in order to exclude<lb/> the outermost trivial edge that underwent the transition.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>78</label> Z. Song, Z. Fang, and C. Fang, &quot;(d2)-dimensional edge<lb/> states of rotation symmetry protected topological states,&quot;<lb/> arXiv preprint: 1708.02952, 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>79</label> F. Schindler, A. M. Cook, M. G. Vergniory, Z. Wang,<lb/> S. S. P. Parkin, B. A. Bernevig, and T. Neupert, &quot;Higher-<lb/>order topological insulators,&quot; arXiv preprint, 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>80</label> J. Langbehn, Y. Peng, L. Trifunovic, F. von Oppen, and<lb/> P. W. Brouwer, &quot;Reflection symmetric second-order topo-<lb/>logical insulators and superconductors,&quot; arXiv preprint,<lb/> 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>81</label> Y. Peng, Y. Bao, and F. von Oppen, &quot;Boundary green<lb/> functions of topological insulators and superconductors,&quot;<lb/> Phys. Rev. B, vol. 95, p. 235143, Jun 2017.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

