<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>[1]</label><lb/> A. Poiani, Complexity of seminal fluid: A review, Behav. Ecol. Sociobiol. 60 (2006)<lb/> 289-310. doi:10.1007/s00265-006-0178-0.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label><lb/> L.A. Mcgraw, S.S. Suarez, M.F. Wolfner, On a matter of seminal importance,<lb/> BioEssays. 37 (2015) 142-147. doi:10.1002/bies.201400117.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label><lb/> J.C. Perry, L. Sirot, S. Wigby, The seminal symphony: How to compose an ejaculate,<lb/> Trends Ecol. Evol. 28 (2013) 414-422. doi:10.1016/j.tree.2013.03.005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label><lb/> B.R. Hopkins, I. Sepil, S. Wigby, Seminal fluid, Curr. Biol. 27 (2017) R404-R405.<lb/> doi:10.1016/j.cub.2017.03.063.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label><lb/> L.K. Sirot, A. Wong, T. Chapman, M.F. Wolfner, Sexual conflict and seminal fluid<lb/> proteins: A dynamic landscape of sexual interactions, Cold Spring Harb. Perspect.<lb/> Biol. 7 (2015). doi:101101/cshperspect.a017533.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label><lb/> H. Rodríguez-Martínez, U. Kvist, J. Ernerudh, L. Sanz, J.J. Calvete, Seminal plasma<lb/> proteins: What role do they play?, Am. J. Reprod. Immunol. 66 (2011) 11-22.<lb/> doi:10.1111/j.1600-0897.2011.01033.x.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label><lb/> F.W. Avila, L.K. Sirot, B.A. Laflamme, C.D. Rubinstein, M.F. Wolfner, Insect seminal<lb/> fluid proteins: identification and function, Annu. Rev. Entomol. 56 (2011) 21-40.<lb/> doi:10.1146/annurev-ento-120709-144823.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label><lb/> L.K. Sirot, M.F. Wolfner, Who&apos;s Zooming Who? Seminal Fluids and Cryptic Female<lb/> Choice in Diptera, in: A. V Peretti, A. Aisenberg (Eds.), Cryptic Female Choice<lb/> Arthropods Patterns, Mech. Prospect., Springer International Publishing, Cham, 2015:<lb/> pp. 351-384. doi:10.1007/978-3-319-17894-3_13.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label><lb/> K. Gilany, A. Minai-Tehrani, E. Savadi-Shiraz, H. Rezadoost, N. Lakpour, Exploring<lb/> the human seminal plasma proteome: An unexplored gold mine of biomarker for male<lb/> Infertility and male reproduction disorder, J. Reprod. Infertil. 16 (2015) 61-71.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> H. Levine, N. Jørgensen, A. Martino-Andrade, J. Mendiola, D. Weksler-Derri, I.<lb/> Mindlis, R. Pinotti, S.H. Swan, Temporal trends in sperm count: A systematic review<lb/> and meta-regression analysis, Hum. Reprod. Update. 23 (2017) 646-659.<lb/> doi:10.1093/humupd/dmx022.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> S.L. Johnson, J. Dunleavy, N.J. Gemmell, S. Nakagawa, Consistent age-dependent<lb/> declines in human semen quality: A systematic review and meta-analysis, Ageing<lb/> Res. Rev. 19 (2015) 22-33. doi:10.1016/j.arr.2014.10.007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> M. Jodar, A. Soler-Ventura, R. Oliva, Semen proteomics and male infertility, J.<lb/> Proteomics. 162 (2017) 125-134. doi:10.1016/j.jprot.2016.08.018.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> T. Chapman, The soup in my fly: Evolution, form and function of seminal fluid<lb/> proteins, PLoS Biol. 6 (2008) 1379-1382. doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.0060179.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> S.A. Ramm, L. McDonald, J.L. Hurst, R.J. Beynon, P. Stockley, Comparative<lb/> proteomics reveals evidence for evolutionary diversification of rodent seminal fluid<lb/> and its functional significance in sperm competition, Mol. Biol. Evol. 26 (2009) 189-<lb/>198. doi:10.1093/molbev/msn237.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> M.D. Dean, N.L. Clark, G.D. Findlay, R.C. Karn, X. Yi, W.J. Swanson, M.J. MacCoss,<lb/> M.W. Nachman, Proteomics and comparative genomic investigations reveal<lb/> heterogeneity in evolutionary rate of male reproductive proteins in mice (Mus<lb/> domesticus), Mol. Biol. Evol. 26 (2009) 1733-1743. doi:10.1093/molbev/msp094.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> L. Alphey, M. Benedict, R. Bellini, G.G. Clark, D.A. Dame, M.W. Service, S.L. Dobson,<lb/> Sterile-insect methods for control of mosquito-borne diseases: an analysis., Vector<lb/> Borne Zoonotic Dis. 10 (2010) 295-311. doi:10.1089/vbz.2009.0014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> J.J. Bromfield, J.E. Schjenken, P.Y. Chin, A.S. Care, M.J. Jasper, S.A. Robertson,<lb/> Maternal tract factors contribute to paternal seminal fluid impact on metabolic<lb/> phenotype in offspring, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 111 (2014) 2200-2205.<lb/> doi:10.1073/pnas.1305609111.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> B. Baer, J.L. Heazlewood, N.L. Taylor, H. Eubel, A.H. Millar, The seminal fluid<lb/> proteome of the honeybee Apis mellifera, Proteomics. 9 (2009) 2085-2097.<lb/> doi:10.1002/pmic.200800708.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> K. Borziak, A. Álvarez-Fernández, T. L. Karr, T. Pizzari, S. Dorus, The Seminal fluid<lb/> proteome of the polyandrous Red junglefowl offers insights into the molecular basis of<lb/> fertility, reproductive ageing and domestication, Sci. Rep. 6 (2016) 35864.<lb/> doi:10.1038/srep35864.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> X. Druart, J.P. Rickard, S. Mactier, P.L. Kohnke, C.M. Kershaw-Young, R. Bathgate,<lb/> Z. Gibb, B. Crossett, G. Tsikis, V. Labas, G. Harichaux, C.G. Grupen, S.P. de Graaf,<lb/> Proteomic characterization and cross species comparison of mammalian seminal<lb/> plasma, J. Proteomics. 91 (2013) 13-22. doi:10.1016/j.jprot.2013.05.029.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> R. Tecirlioglu, E. Hayes, A. Trounson, Semen collection from mice: electroejaculation,<lb/> Reprod. Fertil. Dev. 14 (2002) 363-371.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> M.D. Dean, G.D. Findlay, M.R. Hoopmann, C.C. Wu, M.J. Maccoss, W.J. Swanson,<lb/> M.W. Nachman, Identification of ejaculated proteins in the house mouse ( Mus<lb/> domesticus ) via isotopic labeling, BMC Genomics. 12 (2011) 306. doi:10.1186/1471-<lb/>2164-12-306.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> G. Findlay, X. Yi, M. MacCoss, W. Swanson, Proteomics Reveals Novel Drosophila<lb/> Seminal Fluid Proteins Transferred at Mating, PLoS Biol. 6 (2008) e178.<lb/> doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> L.K. Sirot, M.C. Hardstone, M.E. Helinski, J.M. Ribeiro, M. Kimura, P.<lb/> Deewatthanawong, M.F. Wolfner, L.C. Harrington, Towards a semen proteome of the<lb/> dengue vector mosquito: protein identification and potential functions, PLoS Negl Trop<lb/> Dis. 5 (2011) e989. doi:10.1371/journal.pntd.0000989.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> Y. Heifetz, L.N. Vandenberg, H.I. Cohn, M.F. Wolfner, Two cleavage products of the<lb/> Drosophila accessory gland protein ovulin can independently induce ovulation, Proc.<lb/> Natl. Acad. Sci. 102 (2005) 743-748. doi:10.1073/pnas.0407692102.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> L.K. Sirot, N.A. Buehner, A.C. Fiumera, M.F. Wolfner, Seminal fluid protein depletion<lb/> and replenishment in the fruit fly, Drosophila melanogaster: An ELISA-based method<lb/> for tracking individual ejaculates, Behav. Ecol. Sociobiol. 63 (2009) 1505-1513.<lb/> doi:10.1007/s00265-009-0806-6.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[27]</label> L.K. Sirot, G.D. Findlay, J.L. Sitnik, D. Frasheri, F.W. Avila, M.F. Wolfner, Molecular<lb/> Characterization and Evolution of a Gene Family Encoding Both Female-and Male-<lb/>Specific Reproductive Proteins in Drosophila, Mol. Biol. Evol. 31 (2014) 1554-1567.<lb/> doi:10.1093/molbev/msu114.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[28]</label> A. Bateman, Intra-sexual sexual selection in Drosophila, Heredity (Edinb). (1948)<lb/> 349-368.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[29]</label> T. Chapman, G. Arnqvist, J. Bangham, L. Rowe, Sexual conflict, Trends Ecol. Evol.<lb/> 18 (2003) 41-47. doi:10.1016/S0169-5347(02)00004-6.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[30]</label> K.R. Ram, M.F. Wolfner, Seminal influences: Drosophila Acps and the molecular<lb/> interplay between males and females during reproduction, Integr. Comp. Biol. 47<lb/> (2007) 427-445. doi:10.1093/icb/icm046.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[31]</label> K. Ravi Ram, S. Ji, M.F. Wolfner, Fates and targets of male accessory gland proteins<lb/> in mated female Drosophila melanogaster, Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol. 35 (2005)<lb/> 1059-1071. doi:10.1016/j.ibmb.2005.05.001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[32]</label> J.L. Mueller, J.L. Page, M.F. Wolfner, An ectopic expression screen reveals the<lb/> protective and toxic effects of Drosophila seminal fluid proteins, Genetics. 175 (2007)<lb/> 777-783. doi:10.1534/genetics.106.065318.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[33]</label> E. Lewis, A new standard food medium, Drosoph. Inf. Serv. 34 (1960) 117-118.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[34]</label> D.J. Clancy, Kennington W J, A simple method to achieve consistent larval density in<lb/> bottle cultures, Drosoph. Inf. Serv. 84 (2001) 168-169.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[35]</label> A. Bateman, M.J. Martin, C. O&apos;Donovan, M. Magrane, E. Alpi, R. Antunes, B. Bely, M.<lb/> Bingley, C. Bonilla, R. Britto, B. Bursteinas, H. Bye-AJee, A. Cowley, A. Da Silva, M.<lb/> De Giorgi, T. Dogan, F. Fazzini, L.G. Castro, L. Figueira, P. Garmiri, G. Georghiou, D.<lb/> Gonzalez, E. Hatton-Ellis, W. Li, W. Liu, R. Lopez, J. Luo, Y. Lussi, A. MacDougall, A.<lb/> Nightingale, B. Palka, K. Pichler, D. Poggioli, S. Pundir, L. Pureza, G. Qi, S. Rosanoff,<lb/> R. Saidi, T. Sawford, A. Shypitsyna, E. Speretta, E. Turner, N. Tyagi, V. Volynkin, T.<lb/> Wardell, K. Warner, X. Watkins, R. Zaru, H. Zellner, I. Xenarios, L. Bougueleret, A.<lb/> Bridge, S. Poux, N. Redaschi, L. Aimo, G. ArgoudPuy, A. Auchincloss, K. Axelsen, P.<lb/> Bansal, D. Baratin, M.C. Blatter, B. Boeckmann, J. Bolleman, E. Boutet, L. Breuza, C.<lb/> Casal-Casas, E. De Castro, E. Coudert, B. Cuche, M. Doche, D. Dornevil, S. Duvaud,<lb/> A. Estreicher, L. Famiglietti, M. Feuermann, E. Gasteiger, S. Gehant, V. Gerritsen, A.<lb/> Gos, N. Gruaz-Gumowski, U. Hinz, C. Hulo, F. Jungo, G. Keller, V. Lara, P.<lb/> Lemercier, D. Lieberherr, T. Lombardot, X. Martin, P. Masson, A. Morgat, T. Neto, N.<lb/> Nouspikel, S. Paesano, I. Pedruzzi, S. Pilbout, M. Pozzato, M. Pruess, C. Rivoire, B.<lb/> Roechert, M. Schneider, C. Sigrist, K. Sonesson, S. Staehli, A. Stutz, S. Sundaram,<lb/> M. Tognolli, L. Verbregue, A.L. Veuthey, C.H. Wu, C.N. Arighi, L. Arminski, C. Chen,<lb/> Y. Chen, J.S. Garavelli, H. Huang, K. Laiho, P. McGarvey, D.A. Natale, K. Ross, C.R.<lb/> Vinayaka, Q. Wang, Y. Wang, L.S. Yeh, J. Zhang, UniProt: The universal protein<lb/> knowledgebase, Nucleic Acids Res. 45 (2017) D158-D169. doi:10.1093/nar/gkw1099.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[36]</label> T.N. Petersen, S. Brunak, G. von Heijne, H. Nielsen, SignalP 4.0: discriminating<lb/> signal peptides from transmembrane regions, Nat. Methods. 8 (2011) 785-786.<lb/> doi:10.1038/nmeth.1701.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[37]</label> V.R. Chintapalli, J. Wang, J.A.T. Dow, Using FlyAtlas to identify better Drosophila<lb/> melanogaster models of human disease, Nat. Genet. 39 (2007) 715-720.<lb/> doi:10.1038/ng2049.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[38]</label> R. Fischer, B.M. Kessler, Gel-aided sample preparation (GASP)-A simplified method<lb/> for gel-assisted proteomic sample generation from protein extracts and intact cells,<lb/> Proteomics. 15 (2015) 1224-1229. doi:10.1002/pmic.201400436.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[39]</label> D.W. Huang, B.T. Sherman, R.A. Lempicki, Systematic and integrative analysis of<lb/> large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources, Nat. Protoc. 4 (2009) 44-57.<lb/> doi:10.1038/nprot.2008.211.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[40]</label> D.W. Huang, B.T. Sherman, R.A. Lempicki, Bioinformatics enrichment tools: Paths<lb/> toward the comprehensive functional analysis of large gene lists, Nucleic Acids Res.<lb/> 37 (2009) 1-13. doi:10.1093/nar/gkn923.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[41]</label> R.D.C. Team, R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing, R Found.<lb/> Stat. Comput. Vienna, Austria. (2012) {ISBN} 3-900051-07-0, http://www.R-<lb/>project.org.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[42]</label> E.C. Keilhauer, M.Y. Hein, M. Mann, Accurate Protein Complex Retrieval by Affinity<lb/> Enrichment Mass Spectrometry (AE-MS) Rather than Affinity Purification Mass<lb/> Spectrometry (AP-MS), Mol. Cell. Proteomics. 14 (2015) 120-135.<lb/> doi:10.1074/mcp.M114.041012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[43]</label> E.R. Wasbrough, S. Dorus, S. Hester, J. Howard-Murkin, K. Lilley, E. Wilkin, A.<lb/> Polpitiya, K. Petritis, T.L. Karr, The Drosophila melanogaster sperm proteome-II<lb/> (DmSP-II), J. Proteomics. 73 (2010) 2171-2185. doi:10.1016/j.jprot.2010.09.002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[44]</label> P. Saudan, K. Hauck, M. Soller, Y. Choffat, M. Ottiger, M. Spörri, Z. Ding, D. Hess,<lb/> P.M. Gehrig, S. Klauser, P. Hunziker, E. Kubli, Ductus ejaculatorius peptide 99B<lb/> (DUP99B), a novel Drosophila melanogaster sex-peptide pheromone, Eur. J.<lb/> Biochem. 269 (2002) 989-997. doi:10.1046/j.0014-2956.2001.02733.x.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[45]</label> N. Takemori, M.T. Yamamoto, Proteome mapping of the Drosophila melanogaster<lb/> male reproductive system, Proteomics. 9 (2009) 2484-2493.<lb/> doi:10.1002/pmic.200800795.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[46]</label> L.K. Sirot, R.L. Poulson, M.C. Mckenna, H. Girnary, M.F. Wolfner, L.C. Harrington,<lb/> Identity and transfer of male reproductive gland proteins of the dengue vector<lb/> mosquito, Aedes aegypti: potential tools for control of female feeding and<lb/> reproduction, Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol. 38 (2009) 176-189.<lb/> doi:10.1016/j.ibmb.2007.10.007.Identity.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[47]</label> B.A. LaFlamme, K. Ravi Ram, M.F. Wolfner, The Drosophila melanogaster seminal<lb/> fluid protease &quot;Seminase&quot; regulates proteolytic and post-mating reproductive<lb/> processes, PLoS Genet. 8 (2012) 30-32. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1002435.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[48]</label> K. Sheehan, R.C. Richmond, B.J. Cochrane, Studies of esterase 6 in Drosophila<lb/> melanogaster. III. The developmental pattern and tissue distribution, Insect Biochem.<lb/> 9 (1979) 443-450. doi:10.1016/0020-1790(79)90062-3.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[49]</label> L.K. Sirot, M.F. Wolfner, S. Wigby, Protein-specific manipulation of ejaculate<lb/> composition in response to female mating status in Drosophila melanogaster, Proc.<lb/> Natl. Acad. Sci. 108 (2011) 9922-9926. doi:10.1073/pnas.1100905108.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[50]</label> C. Meslin, T.S. Cherwin, M.S. Plakke, B.S. Small, B.J. Goetz, N.I. Morehouse, N.L.<lb/> Clark, Structural complexity and molecular heterogeneity of a butterfly ejaculate<lb/> reflect a complex history of selection, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 114 (2017) E5406-<lb/>E5413. doi:10.1073/pnas.1707680114.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[51]</label> S. La Vignera, E. Vicari, R.A. Condorelli, R. D&apos;Agata, A.E. Calogero, Male accessory<lb/> gland infection and sperm parameters (review), Int. J. Androl. 34 (2011).<lb/> doi:10.1111/j.1365-2605.2011.01200.x.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[52]</label> L.A. Herndon, T. Chapman, J.M. Kalb, S. Lewin, L. Partridge, M.F. Wolfner, Mating<lb/> and hormonal triggers regulate accessory gland gene expression in male Drosophila,<lb/> J. Insect Physiol. 43 (1997) 1117-1123. doi:10.1016/S0022-1910(97)00062-0.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[53]</label> M. Koppik, C. Fricke, Gene expression changes in male accessory glands during<lb/> ageing are accompanied by reproductive decline in Drosophila melanogaster, Mol.<lb/> Ecol. (2017) 6704-6716. doi:10.1111/mec.14384.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[54]</label> S.A. Teichmann, C. Chothia, Immunoglobulin superfamily proteins in Caenorhabditis<lb/> elegans, J. Mol. Biol. 296 (2000) 1367-1383. doi:10.1006/jmbi.1999.3497.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

