<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Anderson, A. M. (1977). Influence of Pointed Regions on Shape Preference of<lb/> Honey Bees. Animal Behaviour 25, 88-94.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Avarguès-Weber, A., Dyer, A. G., Combe, M. and Giurfa, M. (2012).<lb/> Simultaneous mastering of two abstract concepts by the miniature brain of bees. Proceedings<lb/> of the National Academy of Sciences 109, 7481-7486.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Baird, E., Boeddeker, N., Ibbotson, M. R. and Srinivasan, M. V. (2013). A<lb/> universal strategy for visually guided landing. Proceedings of the National Academy of<lb/> Sciences 110, 18686-91.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Boeddeker, N., Dittmar, L., Sturzl, W. and Egelhaaf, M. (2010). The fine structure<lb/> of honeybee head and body yaw movements in a homing task. Proceedings of the Royal<lb/> Society B 277, 1899-906.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Boeddeker, N. and Hemmi, J. M. (2010). Visual gaze control during peering flight<lb/> manoeuvres in honeybees. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 277, 1209-17.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Boeddeker, N., Mertes, M., Dittmar, L. and Egelhaaf, M. (2015). Bumblebee<lb/> Homing: The Fine Structure of Head Turning Movements. PLoS One 10, e0135020.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Collett, M. (2010). How desert ants use a visual landmark for guidance along a<lb/> habitual route. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 107, 11638-43.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Collett, T. S., Dillmann, E., Giger, A. and Wehner, R. (1992). Visual Landmarks<lb/> and Route Following in Desert Ants. Journal of Comparative Physiology A 170, 435-442.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Collett, T. S., Graham, P., Harris, R. A. and Hempel de Ibarra, N. (2006).<lb/> Navigational memories in ants and bees: Memory retrieval when selecting and following<lb/> routes. Advances in the Study of Behavior, Vol 36 36, 123-172.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Collett, T. S. and Zeil, J. (1998). Places and landmarks: an arthropod perspective. In<lb/> Spatial representation in animals, (ed. S. Healy), pp. 18-53. New York: Oxford University<lb/> Press.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Dafni, A. and Giurfa, M. (1999). The functional ecology of floral guides in relation<lb/> to insect behaviour and vision. In Evolutionary Theory and Processes -Modern Perspectives,<lb/> eds. S. Wasser and R. May), pp. 363-383. Berlin: Springer.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Daumer, K. (1958). Blumenfarben, Wie Sie Die Bienen Sehen. Zeitschrift Fur<lb/> Vergleichende Physiologie 41, 49-110.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Delius, J. D. (1992). Categorical Discrimination of Objects and Pictures by Pigeons.<lb/> Animal Learning &amp; Behavior 20, 301-311.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Dickinson, M. H., Farley, C. T., Full, R. J., Koehl, M. A. R., Kram, R. and<lb/> Lehman, S. (2000). How animals move: An integrative view. Science 288, 100-106.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Dyer, A. G., Neumeyer, C. and Chittka, L. (2005). Honeybee (Apis mellifera)<lb/> vision can discriminate between and recognise images of human faces. Journal of<lb/> Experimental Biology 208, 4709-4714.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Dyer, A. G., Rosa, M. G. P. and Reser, D. H. (2008). Honeybees can recognise<lb/> images of complex natural scenes for use as potential landmarks. Journal of Experimental<lb/> Biology 211, 1180-1186.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Egelhaaf, M., Boeddeker, N., Kern, R., Kurtz, R. and Lindemann, J. P. (2012).<lb/> Spatial vision in insects is facilitated by shaping the dynamics of visual input through<lb/> behavioral action. Frontiers in Neural Circuits 6.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Evangelista, C., Kraft, P., Dacke, M., Reinhard, J. and Srinivasan, M. V. (2010).<lb/> The moment before touchdown: landing manoeuvres of the honeybee Apis mellifera. Journal<lb/> of Experimental Biology 213, 262-270.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Free, J. B. (1970). Effect of flower shapes and nectar guides on the behaviour of<lb/> foraging honeybees. Behaviour 37, 269-285.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Fry, S. N., Sayaman, R. and Dickinson, M. H. (2005). The aerodynamics of<lb/> hovering flight in Drosophila. Journal of Experimental Biology 208, 2303-2318.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Fuller, J. (1992). Comparison of head movement strategies among mammals. In The<lb/> headneck sensory motor system., eds. A. Berthoz W. Graf and P. Vidal), pp. 101-112. New<lb/> York: Oxford University Press.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Furtak, S. C., Cho, C. E., Kerr, K. M., Barredo, J. L., Alleyne, J. E., Patterson,<lb/> Y. R. and Burwell, R. D. (2009). The Floor Projection Maze: A novel behavioral apparatus<lb/> for presenting visual stimuli to rats. Journal of Neuroscience Methods 181, 82-88.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Galen, C. and Plowright, R. C. (1985). Contrasting Movement Patterns of Nectar-<lb/>Collecting and Pollen-Collecting Bumble Bees (Bombus-Terricola) on Fireweed<lb/> (Chamaenerion-Angustifolium) Inflorescences. Ecological Entomology 10, 9-17.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Giger, A. D. (1996). Honeybee vision : analysis of pattern orientation, pp. xi, 155<lb/> leaves.: Australian National University.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Giger, A. D. and Srinivasan, M. V. (1997). Honeybee vision: Analysis of orientation<lb/> and colour in the lateral, dorsal and ventral fields of view. Journal of Experimental Biology<lb/> 200, 1271-1280.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl> Giurfa, M., Hammer, M., Stach, S., Stollhoff, N., Muller-Deisig, N. and<lb/> Mizyrycki, C. (1999a). Pattern learning by honeybees: conditioning procedure and<lb/> recognition strategy. Animal Behaviour 57, 315-324.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Giurfa, M., Zaccardi, G. and Vorobyev, M. (1999b). How bees detect coloured<lb/> targets using different regions of their compound eyes. Journal of Comparative Physiology A<lb/> 185, 591-600.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Graham, P. and Collett, T. S. (2002). View-based navigation in insects: how wood<lb/> ants (Formica rufa L.) look at and are guided by extended landmarks. Journal of<lb/> Experimental Biology 205, 2499-2509.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Harris, R. A., Hempel de Ibarra, N., Graham, P. and Collett, T. S. (2005). Ant<lb/> navigation -Priming of visual route memories. Nature 438, 302-302.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Hateren, J. H. and Schilstra, C. (1999). Blowfly flight and optic flow. II. Head<lb/> movements during flight. Journal of Experimental Biology 202, 1491-500.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Haynes, J. and Mesler, M. (1984). Pollen Foraging by Bumblebees -Foraging<lb/> Patterns and Efficiency on Lupinus-Polyphyllus. Oecologia 61, 249-253.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Hempel de Ibarra, N., Philippides, A., Riabinina, O. and Collett, T. S. (2009).<lb/> Preferred viewing directions of bumblebees (Bombus terrestris L.) when learning and<lb/> approaching their nest site. Journal of Experimental Biology 212, 3193-3204.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Hempel de Ibarra, N., Vorobyev, M. and Menzel, R. (2014). Mechanisms,<lb/> functions and ecology of colour vision in the honeybee. Journal of Comparative Physiology<lb/> A 200, 411-33.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Hertz, M. (1935). Die Untersuchungen über den Formensinn der Honigbiene.<lb/> Naturwissenschaften 23, 618-624.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ibbotson, M. R., Hung, Y. S., Meffin, H., Boeddeker, N. and Srinivasan, M. V.<lb/> (2017). Neural basis of forward flight control and landing in honeybees. Scientific Reports 7,<lb/> 14591.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Land, M. F. (1997). Visual acuity in insects. Annual Review of Entomology 42, 147-<lb/>177.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Land, M. F. (1999). Motion and vision: why animals move their eyes. Journal of<lb/> Comparative Physiology A 185, 341-352.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Land, M. F. and Collett, T. S. (1997). A survey of active vision in invertebrates. In<lb/> Living eyes to seeing machines, eds. M. V. Srinivasan and S. Venkatesh), pp. 16-36. Oxford:<lb/> Oxford University Press.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Lashley, K. S. (1938). The mechanism of vision: XV. Preliminary studies of the rat&apos;s<lb/> capacity for detail vision. Journal of General Psychology 18, 123-193.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Lehrer, M. (1996). Small-scale navigation in the honeybee: Active acquisition of<lb/> visual information about the goal. Journal of Experimental Biology 199, 253-261.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Lehrer, M. (1998). Looking all around: Honeybees use different cues in different eye<lb/> regions. Journal of Experimental Biology 201, 3275-3292.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Lehrer, M. (1999). Dorsoventral asymmetry of colour discrimination in bees. Journal<lb/> of Comparative Physiology A 184, 195-206.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lehrer, M. and Srinivasan, M. V. (1994). Active vision in honeybees -task-oriented<lb/> suppression of an innate behavior. Vision Research 34, 511-516.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Lehrer, M., Srinivasan, M. V. and Zhang, S. W. (1990). Visual edge-detection in<lb/> the honeybee and its chromatic properties. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 238, 321-330.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Lehrer, M., Wehner, R. and Srinivasan, M. (1985). Visual scanning behavior in<lb/> honeybees. Journal of Comparative Physiology A 157,    405-415.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Luu, T., Cheung, A., Ball, D. and Srinivasan, M. V. (2011). Honeybee flight: a<lb/> novel &apos;streamlining&apos; response. Journal of Experimental Biology 214, 2215-2225.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Manning, A. (1956). The effect of honey-guides. Behaviour 9, 114-139.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Martin, G. R. (2007). Visual fields and their functions in birds. Journal of<lb/> Ornithology 148, S547-S562.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Martin, G. R. and Shaw, J. M. (2010). Bird collisions with power lines: Failing to<lb/> see the way ahead? Biological Conservation 143, 2695-2702.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>McCluskey, M. K. and Cullen, K. E. (2007). Eye, head, and body coordination<lb/> during large gaze shifts in rhesus monkeys: movement kinematics and the influence of<lb/> posture. Journal of Neurophysiology 97, 2976-2991.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Menzel, R. and Lieke, E. (1983). Antagonistic Color Effects in Spatial Vision of<lb/> Honeybees. Journal of Comparative Physiology 151, 441-448.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Meyer-Rochow, V. B. (1981). Electrophysiology and histology of the eye of the<lb/> bumblebee Bombus hortorum (L.)(Hymenoptera: Apidae). Journal of the Royal Society of<lb/> New Zealand 11, 123-153.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Minini, L. and Jeffery, K. J. (2006). Do rats use shape to solve &quot;shape<lb/> discriminations&quot;? Learning &amp; Memory 13, 287-297.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Morawetz, L. and Spaethe, J. (2012). Visual attention in a complex search task<lb/> differs between honeybees and bumblebees. Journal of Experimental Biology 215, 2515-<lb/>2523.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Oommen, B., Smith, R. and Stahl, J. (2004). The influence of future gaze<lb/> orientation upon eye-head coupling during saccades. Experimental Brain Research 155, 9-18.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Pyke, G. H. (1978). Optimal Foraging in Bumblebees and Coevolution with Their<lb/> Plants. Oecologia 36, 281-293.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Reber, T., Baird, E. and Dacke, M. (2016). The final moments of landing in<lb/> bumblebees, Bombus terrestris. Journal of Comparative Physiology A 202, 277-85.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Riabinina, O., Hempel de Ibarra, N., Philippides, A. and Collett, T. S. (2014).<lb/> Head movements and the optic flow generated during the learning flights of bumblebees.<lb/> Journal of Experimental Biology 217, 2633-2642.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Robert, T., Frasnelli, E., Hempel de Ibarra, N. and Collett, T. S. (2018).<lb/> Variations on a theme: bumblebee learning flights from the nest and from flowers. Journal of<lb/> Experimental Biology 221.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Schilstra, C. and van Hateren, J. H. (1998). Stabilizing gaze in flying blowflies.<lb/> Nature 395, 654.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Seidl, R. and Kaiser, W. (1981). Visual-Field Size, Binocular Domain and the<lb/> Ommatidial Array of the Compound Eyes in Worker Honey Bees. Journal of Comparative<lb/> Physiology 143, 17-26.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Srinivasan, M. V. (2011). Honeybees as a Model for the Study of Visually Guided<lb/> Flight, Navigation, and Biologically Inspired Robotics. Physiological Reviews 91, 413-460.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Srinivasan, M. V. and Zhang, S. (2004). Visual motor computations in insects.<lb/> Annual Review of Neuroscience 27, 679-96.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Srinivasan, M. V., Zhang, S. W., Chahl, J. S., Barth, E. and Venkatesh, S. (2000).<lb/> How honeybees make grazing landings on flat surfaces. Biological Cybernetics 83, 171-183.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Stamp Dawkins, M. (2002). What are birds looking at? Head movements and eye use<lb/> in chickens. Animal Behaviour 63, 991-998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Taylor, G. J., Luu, T., Ball, D. and Srinivasan, M. V. (2013). Vision and air flow<lb/> combine to streamline flying honeybees. Scientific Reports 3, 2614.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Thivierge, J. P., Plowright, C. M. S. and Chan, T. (2002). Recognition of<lb/> incomplete patterns by bumble bees. Behavioural Processes 59, 185-191.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Ushimaru, A., Dohzono, I., Takami, Y. and Hyodo, F. (2009). Flower orientation<lb/> enhances pollen transfer in bilaterally symmetrical flowers. Oecologia 160, 667-674.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Ushimaru, A. and Hyodo, F. (2005). Why do bilaterally symmetrical flowers orient<lb/> vertically? Flower orientation influences pollinator landing behaviour. Evolutionary Ecology<lb/> Research 7, 151-160.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ushimaru, A., Kawase, D. and Imamura, A. (2006). Flowers adaptively face down-<lb/>slope in 10 forest-floor herbs. Functional Ecology 20, 585-591.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Ushimaru, A., Watanabe, T. and Nakata, K. (2007). Colored floral organs<lb/> influence pollinator behavior and pollen transfer in Commelina communis (Commelinaceae).<lb/> American Journal of Botany 94, 249-258.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Vance, J. T., Altshuler, D. L., Dickson, W. B., Dickinson, M. H. and Roberts, S.<lb/> P. (2014). Hovering Flight in the Honeybee Apis mellifera: Kinematic Mechanisms for<lb/> Varying Aerodynamic Forces. Physiological and Biochemical Zoology 87, 870-881.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Waddington, K. D. and Heinrich, B. (1979). Foraging Movements of Bumblebees<lb/> on Vertical Inflorescences -Experimental-Analysis. Journal of Comparative Physiology 134,<lb/> 113-117.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wehner, R. (1972). Dorsoventral Asymmetry in Visual-Field of Bee, Apis-Mellifica.<lb/> Journal of Comparative and Physiological Psychology 77, 256-&amp;.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wehner, R. and Flatt, I. (1977). Visual fixation in freely flying bees. Zeitschrift für<lb/> Naturforschung 32, 469-472.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wu, W., Moreno, A. M., Tangen, J. M. and Reinhard, J. (2013). Honeybees can<lb/> discriminate between Monet and Picasso paintings. Journal of Comparative Physiology A<lb/> 199, 45-55.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Wystrach, A. and Graham, P. (2012). What can we learn from studies of insect<lb/> navigation? Animal Behaviour 84, 13-20.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Zhang, S., Srinivasan, M. V., Zhu, H. and Wong, J. (2004). Grouping of visual<lb/> objects by honeybees. Journal of Experimental Biology 207, 3289-3298.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

