<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Adams, P.D., Grosse-Kunstleve, R.W., Hung, L.W., Ioerger, T.R., McCoy, A.J., Moriarty,<lb/> N.W., Read, R.J., Sacchettini, J.C., Sauter, N.K., and Terwilliger, T.C. (2002). PHENIX:<lb/> building new software for automated crystallographic structure determination. Acta<lb/> Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr 58, 1948-1954.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Agirre, J., Iglesias-Fernandez, J., Rovira, C., Davies, G.J., Wilson, K.S., and Cowtan, K.D.<lb/> (2015). Privateer: software for the conformational validation of carbohydrate<lb/> structures. Nature structural &amp; molecular biology 22, 833-834.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Andrabi, R., Bhiman, J.N., and Burton, D.R. (2018). Strategies for a multi-stage<lb/> neutralizing antibody-based HIV vaccine. Curr Opin Immunol 53, 143-151.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Andrabi, R., Su, C.Y., Liang, C.H., Shivatare, S.S., Briney, B., Voss, J.E., Nawazi, S.K., Wu,<lb/> C.Y., Wong, C.H., and Burton, D.R. (2017). Glycans Function as Anchors for Antibodies<lb/> and Help Drive HIV Broadly Neutralizing Antibody Development. Immunity 47, 524-<lb/>537 e523.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Andrabi, R., Voss, J.E., Liang, C.H., Briney, B., McCoy, L.E., Wu, C.Y., Wong, C.H.,<lb/> Poignard, P., and Burton, D.R. (2015). Identification of Common Features in Prototype<lb/> Broadly Neutralizing Antibodies to HIV Envelope V2 Apex to Facilitate Vaccine<lb/> Design. Immunity 43, 959-973.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Barad, B.A., Echols, N., Wang, R.Y., Cheng, Y., DiMaio, F., Adams, P.D., and Fraser, J.S.<lb/> (2015). EMRinger: side chain-directed model and map validation for 3D cryo-electron<lb/> microscopy. Nature methods 12, 943-946.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Barbian, H.J., Decker, J.M., Bibollet-Ruche, F., Galimidi, R.P., West, A.P., Jr., Learn, G.H.,<lb/> Parrish, N.F., Iyer, S.S., Li, Y., Pace, C.S., et al. (2015). Neutralization properties of<lb/> simian immunodeficiency viruses infecting chimpanzees and gorillas. mBio 6.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Behrens, A.J., Harvey, D.J., Milne, E., Cupo, A., Kumar, A., Zitzmann, N., Struwe, W.B.,<lb/> Moore, J.P., and Crispin, M. (2017). Molecular Architecture of the Cleavage-Dependent<lb/> Mannose Patch on a Soluble HIV-1 Envelope Glycoprotein Trimer. Journal of virology<lb/> 91.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Behrens, A.J., Vasiljevic, S., Pritchard, L.K., Harvey, D.J., Andev, R.S., Krumm, S.A.,<lb/> Struwe, W.B., Cupo, A., Kumar, A., Zitzmann, N., et al. (2016). Composition and<lb/> Antigenic Effects of Individual Glycan Sites of a Trimeric HIV-1 Envelope<lb/> Glycoprotein. Cell reports 14, 2695-2706.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bhiman, J.N., Anthony, C., Doria-Rose, N.A., Karimanzira, O., Schramm, C.A., Khoza, T.,<lb/> Kitchin, D., Botha, G., Gorman, J., Garrett, N.J., et al. (2015). Viral variants that initiate<lb/> and drive maturation of V1V2-directed HIV-1 broadly neutralizing antibodies. Nature<lb/> medicine 21, 1332-1336.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Blattner, C., Lee, J.H., Sliepen, K., Derking, R., Falkowska, E., de la Pena, A.T., Cupo, A.,<lb/> Julien, J.P., van Gils, M., Lee, P.S., et al. (2014). Structural delineation of a quaternary,<lb/> cleavage-dependent epitope at the gp41-gp120 interface on intact HIV-1 Env trimers.<lb/> Immunity 40, 669-680.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bonomelli, C., Doores, K.J., Dunlop, D.C., Thaney, V., Dwek, R.A., Burton, D.R., Crispin,<lb/> M., and Scanlan, C.N. (2011). The glycan shield of HIV is predominantly oligomannose<lb/> independently of production system or viral clade. PloS one 6, e23521.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bonsignori, M., Hwang, K.K., Chen, X., Tsao, C.Y., Morris, L., Gray, E., Marshall, D.J.,<lb/> Crump, J.A., Kapiga, S.H., Sam, N.E., et al. (2011). Analysis of a clonal lineage of HIV-1<lb/> envelope V2/V3 conformational epitope-specific broadly neutralizing antibodies and<lb/> their inferred unmutated common ancestors. Journal of virology 85, 9998-10009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Braibant, M., Gong, E.Y., Plantier, J.C., Moreau, T., Alessandri, E., Simon, F., and Barin,<lb/> F. (2013). Cross-group neutralization of HIV-1 and evidence for conservation of the<lb/> PG9/PG16 epitopes within divergent groups. Aids 27, 1239-1244.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Briney, B., Sok, D., Jardine, J.G., Kulp, D.W., Skog, P., Menis, S., Jacak, R., Kalyuzhniy, O.,<lb/> de Val, N., Sesterhenn, F., et al. (2016). Tailored Immunogens Direct Affinity<lb/> Maturation toward HIV Neutralizing Antibodies. Cell 166, 1459-1470 e1411.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Briney, B.S., Willis, J.R., and Crowe, J.E., Jr. (2012). Human peripheral blood antibodies<lb/> with long HCDR3s are established primarily at original recombination using a limited<lb/> subset of germline genes. PloS one 7, e36750.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Brochet, X., Lefranc, M.P., and Giudicelli, V. (2008). IMGT/V-QUEST: the highly<lb/> customized and integrated system for IG and TR standardized V-J and V-D-J sequence<lb/> analysis. Nucleic acids research 36, W503-508.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Chen, V.B., Arendall, W.B., 3rd, Headd, J.J., Keedy, D.A., Immormino, R.M., Kapral, G.J.,<lb/> Murray, L.W., Richardson, J.S., and Richardson, D.C. (2010). MolProbity: all-atom<lb/> structure validation for macromolecular crystallography. Acta Crystallogr D Biol<lb/> Crystallogr 66, 12-21.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>DiMaio, F., Song, Y., Li, X., Brunner, M.J., Xu, C., Conticello, V., Egelman, E., Marlovits, T.,<lb/> Cheng, Y., and Baker, D. (2015). Atomic-accuracy models from 4.5-A cryo-electron<lb/> microscopy data with density-guided iterative local refinement. Nature methods 12,<lb/> 361-365.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Doria-Rose, N.A., Schramm, C.A., Gorman, J., Moore, P.L., Bhiman, J.N., DeKosky, B.J.,<lb/> Ernandes, M.J., Georgiev, I.S., Kim, H.J., Pancera, M., et al. (2014). Developmental<lb/> pathway for potent V1V2-directed HIV-neutralizing antibodies. Nature 509, 55-62.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Dosenovic, P., von Boehmer, L., Escolano, A., Jardine, J., Freund, N.T., Gitlin, A.D.,<lb/> McGuire, A.T., Kulp, D.W., Oliveira, T., Scharf, L., et al. (2015). Immunization for HIV-1<lb/> Broadly Neutralizing Antibodies in Human Ig Knockin Mice. Cell 161, 1505-1515.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Emsley, P., and Cowtan, K. (2004). Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics.<lb/> Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr 60, 2126-2132.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Escolano, A., Dosenovic, P., and Nussenzweig, M.C. (2017). Progress toward active or<lb/> passive HIV-1 vaccination. The Journal of experimental medicine 214, 3-16.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Escolano, A., Steichen, J.M., Dosenovic, P., Kulp, D.W., Golijanin, J., Sok, D., Freund, N.T.,<lb/> Gitlin, A.D., Oliveira, T., Araki, T., et al. (2016). Sequential Immunization Elicits<lb/> Broadly Neutralizing Anti-HIV-1 Antibodies in Ig Knockin Mice. Cell 166, 1445-1458<lb/> e1412.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Falkowska, E., Le, K.M., Ramos, A., Doores, K.J., Lee, J.H., Blattner, C., Ramirez, A.,<lb/> Derking, R., van Gils, M.J., Liang, C.H., et al. (2014). Broadly neutralizing HIV antibodies<lb/> define a glycan-dependent epitope on the prefusion conformation of gp41 on cleaved<lb/> envelope trimers. Immunity 40, 657-668.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Gao, F., Bailes, E., Robertson, D.L., Chen, Y., Rodenburg, C.M., Michael, S.F., Cummins,<lb/> L.B., Arthur, L.O., Peeters, M., Shaw, G.M., et al. (1999). Origin of HIV-1 in the<lb/> chimpanzee Pan troglodytes troglodytes. Nature 397, 436-441.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Garces, F., Lee, J.H., de Val, N., de la Pena, A.T., Kong, L., Puchades, C., Hua, Y., Stanfield,<lb/> R.L., Burton, D.R., Moore, J.P., et al. (2015). Affinity Maturation of a Potent Family of<lb/> HIV Antibodies Is Primarily Focused on Accommodating or Avoiding Glycans.<lb/> Immunity 43, 1053-1063.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Garces, F., Sok, D., Kong, L., McBride, R., Kim, H.J., Saye-Francisco, K.F., Julien, J.P., Hua,<lb/> Y., Cupo, A., Moore, J.P., et al. (2014). Structural evolution of glycan recognition by a<lb/> family of potent HIV antibodies. Cell 159, 69-79.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Georgiev, I.S., Doria-Rose, N.A., Zhou, T., Kwon, Y.D., Staupe, R.P., Moquin, S., Chuang,<lb/> G.Y., Louder, M.K., Schmidt, S.D., Altae-Tran, H.R., et al. (2013). Delineating antibody<lb/> recognition in polyclonal sera from patterns of HIV-1 isolate neutralization. Science<lb/> 340, 751-756.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Gorman, J., Soto, C., Yang, M.M., Davenport, T.M., Guttman, M., Bailer, R.T., Chambers,<lb/> M., Chuang, G.Y., DeKosky, B.J., Doria-Rose, N.A., et al. (2016). Structures of HIV-1 Env<lb/> V1V2 with broadly neutralizing antibodies reveal commonalities that enable vaccine<lb/> design. Nat Struct Mol Biol 23, 81-90.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Harvey, D.J., Baruah, K., and Scanlan, C.N. (2009). Application of negative ion MS/MS<lb/> to the identification of N-glycans released from carcinoembryonic antigen cell<lb/> adhesion molecule 1 (CEACAM1). J Mass Spectrom 44, 50-60.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Havenar-Daughton, C., Lee, J.H., and Crotty, S. (2017). Tfh cells and HIV bnAbs, an<lb/> immunodominance model of the HIV neutralizing antibody generation problem.<lb/> Immunological reviews 275, 49-61.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Haynes, B.F., Kelsoe, G., Harrison, S.C., and Kepler, T.B. (2012). B-cell-lineage<lb/> immunogen design in vaccine development with HIV-1 as a case study. Nature<lb/> biotechnology 30, 423-433.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Haynes, B.F., and Mascola, J.R. (2017). The quest for an antibody-based HIV vaccine.<lb/> Immunological reviews 275, 5-10.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Jardine, J., Julien, J.P., Menis, S., Ota, T., Kalyuzhniy, O., McGuire, A., Sok, D., Huang, P.S.,<lb/> MacPherson, S., Jones, M., et al. (2013). Rational HIV immunogen design to target<lb/> specific germline B cell receptors. Science 340, 711-716.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Jardine, J.G., Ota, T., Sok, D., Pauthner, M., Kulp, D.W., Kalyuzhniy, O., Skog, P.D.,<lb/> Thinnes, T.C., Bhullar, D., Briney, B., et al. (2015). HIV-1 VACCINES. Priming a broadly<lb/> neutralizing antibody response to HIV-1 using a germline-targeting immunogen.<lb/> Science 349, 156-161.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Julien, J.P., Cupo, A., Sok, D., Stanfield, R.L., Lyumkis, D., Deller, M.C., Klasse, P.J., Burton,<lb/> D.R., Sanders, R.W., Moore, J.P., et al. (2013a). Crystal structure of a soluble cleaved<lb/> HIV-1 envelope trimer. Science 342, 1477-1483.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Julien, J.P., Lee, J.H., Cupo, A., Murin, C.D., Derking, R., Hoffenberg, S., Caulfield, M.J.,<lb/> King, C.R., Marozsan, A.J., Klasse, P.J., et al. (2013b). Asymmetric recognition of the<lb/> HIV-1 trimer by broadly neutralizing antibody PG9. Proceedings of the National<lb/> Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 110, 4351-4356.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kepler, T.B., Liao, H.X., Alam, S.M., Bhaskarabhatla, R., Zhang, R., Yandava, C., Stewart,<lb/> S., Anasti, K., Kelsoe, G., Parks, R., et al. (2014). Immunoglobulin gene insertions and<lb/> deletions in the affinity maturation of HIV-1 broadly reactive neutralizing antibodies.<lb/> Cell Host Microbe 16, 304-313.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Klein, F., Diskin, R., Scheid, J.F., Gaebler, C., Mouquet, H., Georgiev, I.S., Pancera, M.,<lb/> Zhou, T., Incesu, R.B., Fu, B.Z., et al. (2013). Somatic mutations of the immunoglobulin<lb/> framework are generally required for broad and potent HIV-1 neutralization. Cell<lb/> 153, 126-138.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Korber, B., Muldoon, M., Theiler, J., Gao, F., Gupta, R., Lapedes, A., Hahn, B.H., Wolinsky,<lb/> S., and Bhattacharya, T. (2000). Timing the ancestor of the HIV-1 pandemic strains.<lb/> Science 288, 1789-1796.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kwon, Y.D., Pancera, M., Acharya, P., Georgiev, I.S., Crooks, E.T., Gorman, J., Joyce, M.G.,<lb/> Guttman, M., Ma, X., Narpala, S., et al. (2015). Crystal structure, conformational<lb/> fixation and entry-related interactions of mature ligand-free HIV-1 Env. Nature<lb/> structural &amp; molecular biology 22, 522-531.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Landais, E., Huang, X., Havenar-Daughton, C., Murrell, B., Price, M.A., Wickramasinghe,<lb/> L., Ramos, A., Bian, C.B., Simek, M., Allen, S., et al. (2016). Broadly Neutralizing<lb/> Antibody Responses in a Large Longitudinal Sub-Saharan HIV Primary Infection<lb/> Cohort. PLoS pathogens 12, e1005369.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Landais, E., Murrell, B., Briney, B., Murrell, S., Rantalainen, K., Berndsen, Z.T., Ramos,<lb/> A., Wickramasinghe, L., Smith, M.L., Eren, K., et al. (2017). HIV Envelope Glycoform<lb/> Heterogeneity and Localized Diversity Govern the Initiation and Maturation of a V2<lb/> Apex Broadly Neutralizing Antibody Lineage. Immunity 47, 990-1003 e1009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lee, J.H., Andrabi, R., Su, C.Y., Yasmeen, A., Julien, J.P., Kong, L., Wu, N.C., McBride, R.,<lb/> Sok, D., Pauthner, M., et al. (2017). A Broadly Neutralizing Antibody Targets the<lb/> Dynamic HIV Envelope Trimer Apex via a Long, Rigidified, and Anionic beta-Hairpin<lb/> Structure. Immunity 46, 690-702.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lee, J.H., de Val, N., Lyumkis, D., and Ward, A.B. (2015). Model Building and<lb/> Refinement of a Natively Glycosylated HIV-1 Env Protein by High-Resolution<lb/> Cryoelectron Microscopy. Structure 23, 1943-1951.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lee, J.H., Ozorowski, G., and Ward, A.B. (2016). Cryo-EM structure of a native, fully<lb/> glycosylated, cleaved HIV-1 envelope trimer. Science 351, 1043-1048.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Lyumkis, D., Julien, J.P., de Val, N., Cupo, A., Potter, C.S., Klasse, P.J., Burton, D.R.,<lb/> Sanders, R.W., Moore, J.P., Carragher, B., et al. (2013). Cryo-EM structure of a fully<lb/> glycosylated soluble cleaved HIV-1 envelope trimer. Science 342, 1484-1490.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>McCoy, L.E., and Burton, D.R. (2017). Identification and specificity of broadly<lb/> neutralizing antibodies against HIV. Immunological reviews 275, 11-20.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>McGuire, A.T., Gray, M.D., Dosenovic, P., Gitlin, A.D., Freund, N.T., Petersen, J., Correnti,<lb/> C., Johnsen, W., Kegel, R., Stuart, A.B., et al. (2016). Specifically modified Env<lb/> immunogens activate B-cell precursors of broadly neutralizing HIV-1 antibodies in<lb/> transgenic mice. Nature communications 7, 10618.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>McGuire, A.T., Hoot, S., Dreyer, A.M., Lippy, A., Stuart, A., Cohen, K.W., Jardine, J., Menis,<lb/> S., Scheid, J.F., West, A.P., et al. (2013). Engineering HIV envelope protein to activate<lb/> germline B cell receptors of broadly neutralizing anti-CD4 binding site antibodies.<lb/> The Journal of experimental medicine 210, 655-663.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>McLellan, J.S., Pancera, M., Carrico, C., Gorman, J., Julien, J.P., Khayat, R., Louder, R.,<lb/> Pejchal, R., Sastry, M., Dai, K., et al. (2011). Structure of HIV-1 gp120 V1/V2 domain<lb/> with broadly neutralizing antibody PG9. Nature 480, 336-343.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Montefiori, D.C. (2005). Evaluating neutralizing antibodies against HIV, SIV, and SHIV<lb/> in luciferase reporter gene assays. Current protocols in immunology / edited by John<lb/> E Coligan [et al] Chapter 12, Unit 12.11.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Moore, P.L., Gray, E.S., Sheward, D., Madiga, M., Ranchobe, N., Lai, Z., Honnen, W.J.,<lb/> Nonyane, M., Tumba, N., Hermanus, T., et al. (2011). Potent and broad neutralization<lb/> of HIV-1 subtype C by plasma antibodies targeting a quaternary epitope including<lb/> residues in the V2 loop. Journal of virology 85, 3128-3141.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Morgand, M., Bouvin-Pley, M., Plantier, J.C., Moreau, A., Alessandri, E., Simon, F., Pace,<lb/> C.S., Pancera, M., Ho, D.D., Poignard, P., et al. (2016). V1/V2 Neutralizing Epitope is<lb/> Conserved in Divergent Non-M Groups of HIV-1. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr 71, 237-<lb/>245.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ogura, T., Iwasaki, K., and Sato, C. (2003). Topology representing network enables<lb/> highly accurate classification of protein images taken by cryo electron-microscope<lb/> without masking. J Struct Biol 143, 185-200.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ozorowski, G., Pallesen, J., de Val, N., Lyumkis, D., Cottrell, C.A., Torres, J.L., Copps, J.,<lb/> Stanfield, R.L., Cupo, A., Pugach, P., et al. (2017). Open and closed structures reveal<lb/> allostery and pliability in the HIV-1 envelope spike. Nature 547, 360-363.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Pancera, M., Shahzad-Ul-Hussan, S., Doria-Rose, N.A., McLellan, J.S., Bailer, R.T., Dai, K.,<lb/> Loesgen, S., Louder, M.K., Staupe, R.P., Yang, Y., et al. (2013). Structural basis for<lb/> diverse N-glycan recognition by HIV-1-neutralizing V1-V2-directed antibody PG16.<lb/> Nature structural &amp; molecular biology 20, 804-813.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Pancera, M., Zhou, T., Druz, A., Georgiev, I.S., Soto, C., Gorman, J., Huang, J., Acharya, P.,<lb/> Chuang, G.Y., Ofek, G., et al. (2014). Structure and immune recognition of trimeric pre-<lb/>fusion HIV-1 Env. Nature 514, 455-461.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Panico, M., Bouche, L., Binet, D., O&apos;Connor, M.J., Rahman, D., Pang, P.C., Canis, K., North,<lb/> S.J., Desrosiers, R.C., Chertova, E., et al. (2016). Mapping the complete glycoproteome<lb/> of virion-derived HIV-1 gp120 provides insights into broadly neutralizing antibody<lb/> binding. Sci Rep 6, 32956.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Pejchal, R., Doores, K.J., Walker, L.M., Khayat, R., Huang, P.S., Wang, S.K., Stanfield, R.L.,<lb/> Julien, J.P., Ramos, A., Crispin, M., et al. (2011). A potent and broad neutralizing<lb/> antibody recognizes and penetrates the HIV glycan shield. Science 334, 1097-1103.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Pritchard, L.K., Harvey, D.J., Bonomelli, C., Crispin, M., and Doores, K.J. (2015). Cell-<lb/>and Protein-Directed Glycosylation of Native Cleaved HIV-1 Envelope. Journal of<lb/> virology 89, 8932-8944.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Pugach, P., Ozorowski, G., Cupo, A., Ringe, R., Yasmeen, A., de Val, N., Derking, R., Kim,<lb/> H.J., Korzun, J., Golabek, M., et al. (2015). A native-like SOSIP.664 trimer based on a<lb/> HIV-1 subtype B env gene. Journal of virology.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Riedel, S. (2005). Edward Jenner and the history of smallpox and vaccination. Proc<lb/> (Bayl Univ Med Cent) 18, 21-25.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sanders, R.W., Derking, R., Cupo, A., Julien, J.P., Yasmeen, A., de Val, N., Kim, H.J.,<lb/> Blattner, C., de la Pena, A.T., Korzun, J., et al. (2013). A next-generation cleaved, soluble<lb/> HIV-1 Env trimer, BG505 SOSIP.664 gp140, expresses multiple epitopes for broadly<lb/> neutralizing but not non-neutralizing antibodies. PLoS pathogens 9, e1003618.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sanders, R.W., van Gils, M.J., Derking, R., Sok, D., Ketas, T.J., Burger, J.A., Ozorowski, G.,<lb/> Cupo, A., Simonich, C., Goo, L., et al. (2015). HIV-1 VACCINES. HIV-1 neutralizing<lb/> antibodies induced by native-like envelope trimers. Science 349, aac4223.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Saunders, K.O., Verkoczy, L.K., Jiang, C., Zhang, J., Parks, R., Chen, H., Housman, M.,<lb/> Bouton-Verville, H., Shen, X., Trama, A.M., et al. (2017). Vaccine Induction of<lb/> Heterologous Tier 2 HIV-1 Neutralizing Antibodies in Animal Models. Cell reports 21,<lb/> 3681-3690.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Scheres, S.H. (2012). RELION: implementation of a Bayesian approach to cryo-EM<lb/> structure determination. J Struct Biol 180, 519-530.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Seaman, M.S., Janes, H., Hawkins, N., Grandpre, L.E., Devoy, C., Giri, A., Coffey, R.T.,<lb/> Harris, L., Wood, B., Daniels, M.G., et al. (2010). Tiered categorization of a diverse<lb/> panel of HIV-1 Env pseudoviruses for assessment of neutralizing antibodies. Journal<lb/> of virology 84, 1439-1452.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sharma, S.K., de Val, N., Bale, S., Guenaga, J., Tran, K., Feng, Y., Dubrovskaya, V., Ward,<lb/> A.B., and Wyatt, R.T. (2015). Cleavage-independent HIV-1 Env trimers engineered as<lb/> soluble native spike mimetics for vaccine design. Cell reports 11, 539-550.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sharp, P.M., and Hahn, B.H. (2011). Origins of HIV and the AIDS pandemic. Cold Spring<lb/> Harbor perspectives in medicine 1, a006841.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sok, D., Briney, B., Jardine, J.G., Kulp, D.W., Menis, S., Pauthner, M., Wood, A., Lee, E.C.,<lb/> Le, K.M., Jones, M., et al. (2016a). Priming HIV-1 broadly neutralizing antibody<lb/> precursors in human Ig loci transgenic mice. Science.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sok, D., Doores, K.J., Briney, B., Le, K.M., Saye-Francisco, K.L., Ramos, A., Kulp, D.W.,<lb/> Julien, J.P., Menis, S., Wickramasinghe, L., et al. (2014a). Promiscuous glycan site<lb/> recognition by antibodies to the high-mannose patch of gp120 broadens<lb/> neutralization of HIV. Science translational medicine 6, 236ra263.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sok, D., Pauthner, M., Briney, B., Lee, J.H., Saye-Francisco, K.L., Hsueh, J., Ramos, A., Le,<lb/> K.M., Jones, M., Jardine, J.G., et al. (2016b). A Prominent Site of Antibody Vulnerability<lb/> on HIV Envelope Incorporates a Motif Associated with CCR5 Binding and Its<lb/> Camouflaging Glycans. Immunity 45, 31-45.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sok, D., van Gils, M.J., Pauthner, M., Julien, J.P., Saye-Francisco, K.L., Hsueh, J., Briney,<lb/> B., Lee, J.H., Le, K.M., Lee, P.S., et al. (2014b). Recombinant HIV envelope trimer selects<lb/> for quaternary-dependent antibodies targeting the trimer apex. Proceedings of the<lb/> National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 111, 17624-17629.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Steichen, J.M., Kulp, D.W., Tokatlian, T., Escolano, A., Dosenovic, P., Stanfield, R.L.,<lb/> McCoy, L.E., Ozorowski, G., Hu, X., Kalyuzhniy, O., et al. (2016a). HIV Vaccine Design to<lb/> Target Germline Precursors of Glycan-Dependent Broadly Neutralizing Antibodies.<lb/> Immunity 45, 483-496.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Steichen, J.M., Kulp, D.W., Tokatlian, T., Escolano, A., Dosenovic, P., Stanfield, R.L.,<lb/> McCoy, L.E., Ozorowski, G., Hu, X., Kalyuzhniy, O., et al. (2016b). HIV Vaccine Design to<lb/> Target Germline Precursors of Glycan-Dependent Broadly Neutralizing Antibodies.<lb/> Immunity 45, 483-496.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Tas, J.M., Mesin, L., Pasqual, G., Targ, S., Jacobsen, J.T., Mano, Y.M., Chen, C.S., Weill, J.C.,<lb/> Reynaud, C.A., Browne, E.P., et al. (2016). Visualizing antibody affinity maturation in<lb/> germinal centers. Science 351, 1048-1054.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Tian, M., Cheng, C., Chen, X., Duan, H., Cheng, H.L., Dao, M., Sheng, Z., Kimble, M., Wang,<lb/> L., Lin, S., et al. (2016). Induction of HIV Neutralizing Antibody Lineages in Mice with<lb/> Diverse Precursor Repertoires. Cell 166, 1471-1484 e1418.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Tiller, T., Meffre, E., Yurasov, S., Tsuiji, M., Nussenzweig, M.C., and Wardemann, H.<lb/> (2008). Efficient generation of monoclonal antibodies from single human B cells by<lb/> single cell RT-PCR and expression vector cloning. Journal of immunological methods<lb/> 329, 112-124.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Verkoczy, L., Diaz, M., Holl, T.M., Ouyang, Y.B., Bouton-Verville, H., Alam, S.M., Liao,<lb/> H.X., Kelsoe, G., and Haynes, B.F. (2010). Autoreactivity in an HIV-1 broadly reactive<lb/> neutralizing antibody variable region heavy chain induces immunologic tolerance.<lb/> Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 107,<lb/> 181-186.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Voss, J.E., Andrabi, R., McCoy, L.E., de Val, N., Fuller, R.P., Messmer, T., Su, C.Y., Sok, D.,<lb/> Khan, S.N., Garces, F., et al. (2017). Elicitation of Neutralizing Antibodies Targeting the<lb/> V2 Apex of the HIV Envelope Trimer in a Wild-Type Animal Model. Cell reports 21,<lb/> 222-235.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Voss, N.R., Yoshioka, C.K., Radermacher, M., Potter, C.S., and Carragher, B. (2009). DoG<lb/> Picker and TiltPicker: software tools to facilitate particle selection in single particle<lb/> electron microscopy. J Struct Biol 166, 205-213.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Walker, L.M., Huber, M., Doores, K.J., Falkowska, E., Pejchal, R., Julien, J.P., Wang, S.K.,<lb/> Ramos, A., Chan-Hui, P.Y., Moyle, M., et al. (2011). Broad neutralization coverage of<lb/> HIV by multiple highly potent antibodies. Nature 477, 466-470.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Walker, L.M., Phogat, S.K., Chan-Hui, P.Y., Wagner, D., Phung, P., Goss, J.L., Wrin, T.,<lb/> Simek, M.D., Fling, S., Mitcham, J.L., et al. (2009). Broad and potent neutralizing<lb/> antibodies from an African donor reveal a new HIV-1 vaccine target. Science 326, 285-<lb/>289.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wang, S., Mata-Fink, J., Kriegsman, B., Hanson, M., Irvine, D.J., Eisen, H.N., Burton, D.R.,<lb/> Wittrup, K.D., Kardar, M., and Chakraborty, A.K. (2015). Manipulating the Selection<lb/> Forces during Affinity Maturation to Generate Cross-Reactive HIV Antibodies. Cell<lb/> 160, 785-797.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Ward, A.B., and Wilson, I.A. (2017). The HIV-1 envelope glycoprotein structure:<lb/> nailing down a moving target. Immunological reviews 275, 21-32.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Webb, B., and Sali, A. (2016). Comparative Protein Structure Modeling Using<lb/> MODELLER. Curr Protoc Bioinformatics 54, 5 6 1-5 6 37.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wibmer, C.K., Bhiman, J.N., Gray, E.S., Tumba, N., Abdool Karim, S.S., Williamson, C.,<lb/> Morris, L., and Moore, P.L. (2013). Viral escape from HIV-1 neutralizing antibodies<lb/> drives increased plasma neutralization breadth through sequential recognition of<lb/> multiple epitopes and immunotypes. PLoS pathogens 9, e1003738.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Williams, W.B., Zhang, J., Jiang, C., Nicely, N.I., Fera, D., Luo, K., Moody, M.A., Liao, H.X.,<lb/> Alam, S.M., Kepler, T.B., et al. (2017). Initiation of HIV neutralizing B cell lineages with<lb/> sequential envelope immunizations. Nature communications 8, 1732.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Worobey, M., Gemmel, M., Teuwen, D.E., Haselkorn, T., Kunstman, K., Bunce, M.,<lb/> Muyembe, J.J., Kabongo, J.M., Kalengayi, R.M., Van Marck, E., et al. (2008). Direct<lb/> evidence of extensive diversity of HIV-1 in Kinshasa by 1960. Nature 455, 661-664.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Wu, X., Yang, Z.Y., Li, Y., Hogerkorp, C.M., Schief, W.R., Seaman, M.S., Zhou, T., Schmidt,<lb/> S.D., Wu, L., Xu, L., et al. (2010). Rational design of envelope identifies broadly<lb/> neutralizing human monoclonal antibodies to HIV-1. Science 329, 856-861.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Xiao, X., Chen, W., Feng, Y., Zhu, Z., Prabakaran, P., Wang, Y., Zhang, M.Y., Longo, N.S.,<lb/> and Dimitrov, D.S. (2009). Germline-like predecessors of broadly neutralizing<lb/> antibodies lack measurable binding to HIV-1 envelope glycoproteins: implications for<lb/> evasion of immune responses and design of vaccine immunogens. Biochemical and<lb/> biophysical research communications 390, 404-409.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Zhang, K. (2016). Gctf: Real-time CTF determination and correction. J Struct Biol 193,<lb/> 1-12.<lb/> Zhang, M., Gaschen, B., Blay, W., Foley, B., Haigwood, N., Kuiken, C., and Korber, B.<lb/> (2004). Tracking global patterns of N-linked glycosylation site variation in highly<lb/> variable viral glycoproteins: HIV, SIV, and HCV envelopes and influenza<lb/> hemagglutinin. Glycobiology 14, 1229-1246.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Zheng, S.Q., Palovcak, E., Armache, J.P., Verba, K.A., Cheng, Y., and Agard, D.A. (2017).<lb/> MotionCor2: anisotropic correction of beam-induced motion for improved cryo-<lb/>electron microscopy. Nature methods 14, 331-332.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Zhou, T., Georgiev, I., Wu, X., Yang, Z.Y., Dai, K., Finzi, A., Kwon, Y.D., Scheid, J.F., Shi, W.,<lb/> Xu, L., et al. (2010). Structural basis for broad and potent neutralization of HIV-1 by<lb/> antibody VRC01. Science 329, 811-817.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

