<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>1</label>.<lb/> Shen J, Obin MS, Zhao L. The gut microbiota, obesity and insulin resistance. Mol<lb/> Aspects Med. Elsevier Ltd; 2013;34: 39-58. doi:10.1016/j.mam.2012.11.001<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>2</label>.<lb/> Heymsfield SB, Wadden TA. Mechanisms, Pathophysiology, and Management of<lb/> Obesity. N Engl J Med. 2017;376: 254-266. doi:10.1056/NEJMra1514009<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>3</label>.<lb/> Grasa L, Abecia L, Forcén R, Castro M, de Jalón JAG, Latorre E, et al. Antibiotic-<lb/>Induced Depletion of Murine Microbiota Induces Mild Inflammation and Changes in<lb/> Toll-Like Receptor Patterns and Intestinal Motility. Microb Ecol. 2015;70: 835-848.<lb/> doi:10.1007/s00248-015-0613-8<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>4</label>.<lb/> Cani PD, Delzenne NM. The gut microbiome as therapeutic target. Pharmacol Ther.<lb/> Elsevier Inc.; 2011;130: 202-212. doi:10.1016/j.pharmthera.2011.01.012<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>5</label>.<lb/> Ottman N, Smidt H, de Vos WM, Belzer C. The function of our microbiota: who is out<lb/> there and what do they do? Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2012;2: 104.<lb/> doi:10.3389/fcimb.2012.00104<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>6</label>.<lb/> Buettner R, Schölmerich J, Bollheimer LC. High-fat diets: Modeling the metabolic<lb/> disorders of human obesity in rodents. Obesity. 2007. pp. 798-808.<lb/> doi:10.1038/oby.2007.608<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>7</label>.<lb/> Nilsson C, Raun K, Yan F, Larsen MO, Tang-Christensen M. Laboratory animals as<lb/> surrogate models of human obesity. Acta Pharmacol Sin. 2012;33: 173-181.<lb/> doi:10.1038/aps.2011.203<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>8</label>.<lb/> Zhao L, Zhang Q, Ma W, Tian F, Shen H, Zhou M. A combination of quercetin and<lb/> resveratrol reduces obesity in high-fat diet-fed rats by modulation of gut microbiota.<lb/> Food Funct. England; 2017;8: 4644-4656. doi:10.1039/c7fo01383c<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>9</label>.<lb/> Boi SK, Buchta CM, Pearson NA, Francis MB, Meyerholz DK, Grobe JL, et al. Obesity<lb/> alters immune and metabolic profiles: New insight from obese-resistant mice on high-fat<lb/> diet.<lb/> Obesity<lb/> (Silver<lb/> Spring).<lb/> United<lb/> States;<lb/> 2016;24:<lb/> 2140-2149.<lb/> doi:10.1002/oby.21620<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>10</label>.<lb/> Ha M, Sabherwal M, Duncan E, Stevens S, Stockwell P, McConnell M, et al. In-Depth<lb/> Characterization of Sheep (Ovis aries) Milk Whey Proteome and Comparison with Cow<lb/> (Bos<lb/> taurus).<lb/> PLoS<lb/> One.<lb/> United<lb/> States;<lb/> 2015;10:<lb/> e0139774.<lb/> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0139774<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>11</label>.<lb/> Janssen AWF, Kersten S. The role of the gut microbiota in metabolic health. FASEB J.<lb/> 2015;9: 577-589. doi:10.1096/fj.14-269514<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>12</label>.<lb/> Lee P, Yacyshyn BR, Yacyshyn MB. Gut microbiota and obesity: An opportunity to<lb/> alter obesity through faecal microbiota transplant (FMT). Diabetes, Obes Metab. 2018;<lb/> doi:10.1111/dom.13561<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl><label>13</label>.<lb/> Lai ZL, Tseng CH, Ho HJ, Cheung CKY, Lin JY, Chen YJ, et al. Fecal microbiota<lb/> transplantation confers beneficial metabolic effects of diet and exercise on diet-induced<lb/> obese mice. Sci Rep. 2018;8: 1-11. doi:10.1038/s41598-018-33893-y<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>14</label>.<lb/> Sun W, Guo Y, Zhang S, Chen Z, Wu K, Liu Q, et al. Fecal Microbiota Transplantation<lb/> Can Alleviate Gastrointestinal Transit in Rats with High-Fat Diet-Induced Obesity via<lb/> Regulation of Serotonin Biosynthesis. Biomed Res Int. Hindawi; 2018;2018.<lb/> doi:10.1155/2018/8308671<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>15</label>.<lb/> Schuijt TJ, Lankelma JM, Scicluna BP, De Sousa E Melo F, Roelofs JJTH, De Boer JD,<lb/> et al. The gut microbiota plays a protective role in the host defence against<lb/> pneumococcal pneumonia. Gut. 2016;65: 575-583. doi:10.1136/gutjnl-2015-309728<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>16</label>.<lb/> Le Bastard Q, Ward T, Sidiropoulos D, Hillmann BM, Chun CL, Sadowsky MJ, et al.<lb/> Fecal microbiota transplantation reverses antibiotic and chemotherapy-induced gut<lb/> dysbiosis in mice. Sci Rep. Springer US; 2018;8: 1-11. doi:10.1038/s41598-018-24342-<lb/>x<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>17</label>.<lb/> Wang S, Huang M, You X, Zhao J, Chen L, Wang L, et al. Gut microbiota mediates the<lb/> anti-obesity effect of calorie restriction in mice. Sci Rep. Springer US; 2018;8: 2-15.<lb/> doi:10.1038/s41598-018-31353-1<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>18</label>.<lb/> Zhou D, Pan Q, Shen F, Cao HX, Ding WJ, Chen YW, et al. Total fecal microbiota<lb/> transplantation alleviates high-fat diet-induced steatohepatitis in mice via beneficial<lb/> regulation of gut microbiota. Sci Rep. Springer US; 2017;7: 1-11. doi:10.1038/s41598-<lb/>017-01751-y<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl><label>19</label>.<lb/> Daniel H, Gholami AM, Berry D, Desmarchelier C, Hahne H, Loh G, et al. High-fat diet<lb/> alters gut microbiota physiology in mice. ISME J. 2014;8: 295-308.<lb/> doi:10.1038/ismej.2013.155<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl><label>20</label>.<lb/> del Bas JM, Guirro M, Boqué N, Cereto A, Ras R, Crescenti A, et al. Alterations in gut<lb/> microbiota associated with a cafeteria diet and the physiological consequences in the<lb/> host. Int J Obes. Macmillan Publishers Limited, part of Springer Nature; 2017;<lb/> Available: http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ijo.2017.284<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>21</label>.<lb/> Guirro M, Costa A, Gual-Grau A, Mayneris-Perxachs J, Torrell H, Herrero P, et al.<lb/> Multi-omics approach to elucidate the gut microbiota activity: Metaproteomics and<lb/> metagenomics<lb/> connection.<lb/> Electrophoresis.<lb/> 2018;39:<lb/> 1692-1701.<lb/> doi:10.1002/elps.201700476<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>22</label>.<lb/> Tanca A, Manghina V, Fraumene C, Palomba A, Abbondio M, Deligios M, et al.<lb/> Metaproteogenomics reveals taxonomic and functional changes between cecal and fecal<lb/> microbiota in mouse. Front Microbiol. 2017;8: 391. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2017.00391<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl><label>23</label>.<lb/> Bäckhed F, Ding H, Wang T, Hooper L V, Koh GY, Nagy A, et al. The gut microbiota<lb/> as an environmental factor that regulates fat storage. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.<lb/> 2004;101: 15718-23. doi:10.1073/pnas.0407076101<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>24</label>.<lb/> Reikvam DH, Erofeev A, Sandvik A, Grcic V, Jahnsen FL, Gaustad P, et al. Depletion<lb/> of murine intestinal microbiota: Effects on gut mucosa and epithelial gene expression.<lb/> PLoS One. 2011;6: 1-13. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0017996<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>25</label>.<lb/> Hernández-Jarguín A, Díaz-Sánchez S, Villar M, de la Fuente J. Integrated<lb/> metatranscriptomics and metaproteomics for the characterization of bacterial microbiota<lb/> in unfed Ixodes ricinus. Ticks Tick Borne Dis. Elsevier; 2018;9: 1241-1251.<lb/> doi:10.1016/j.ttbdis.2018.04.020<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>26</label>.<lb/> Xiao M, Yang J, Feng Y, Zhu Y, Chai X, Wang Y. Metaproteomic strategies and<lb/> applications for gut microbial research. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. Applied<lb/> Microbiology and Biotechnology; 2017;101: 3077-3088. doi:10.1007/s00253-017-8215-<lb/>7<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>27</label>.<lb/> Wei F, Wu Q, Hu Y, Huang G, Nie Y, Yan L. Conservation metagenomics: a new<lb/> branch of conservation biology. Sci China Life Sci. China; 2018; doi:10.1007/s11427-<lb/>018-9423-3<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>28</label>.<lb/> Caporaso JG, Kuczynski J, Stombaugh J, Bittinger K, Bushman FD, Costello EK, et al.<lb/> QIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing data. Nat Methods.<lb/> 2011;7: 335-336. doi:10.1038/nmeth.f.303.QIIME<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>29</label>.<lb/> Guirro M, Herrero P, Costa A, Gual-Grau A, Ceretó-Massagué A, Hernández A, et al.<lb/> Deciphering the functions of gut microbiota in an animal model of obesity using an<lb/> optimized metaproteomics workflow . J Proteome Res. 2019;Submitted.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>30</label>.<lb/> Lee S, Keirsey KI, Kirkland R, Grunewald ZI, Fischer JG, de La Serre CB. Blueberry<lb/> Supplementation Influences the Gut Microbiota, Inflammation, and Insulin Resistance in<lb/> High-Fat-Diet-Fed<lb/> Rats.<lb/> J<lb/> Nutr.<lb/> United<lb/> States;<lb/> 2018;148:<lb/> 209-219.<lb/> doi:10.1093/jn/nxx027<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>31</label>.<lb/> Behr C, Kamp H, Fabian E, Krennrich G, Mellert W, Peter E, et al. Gut microbiome-<lb/>related metabolic changes in plasma of antibiotic-treated rats. Arch Toxicol. Springer<lb/> Berlin Heidelberg; 2017;91: 3439-3454. doi:10.1007/s00204-017-1949-2<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>32</label>.<lb/> Tulstrup MVL, Christensen EG, Carvalho V, Linninge C, Ahrné S, Højberg O, et al.<lb/> Antibiotic Treatment Affects Intestinal Permeability and Gut Microbial Composition in<lb/> Wistar Rats Dependent on Antibiotic Class. PLoS One. 2015;10: 1-17.<lb/> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0144854<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>33</label>.<lb/> Hoban AE, Moloney RD, Golubeva A V., McVey Neufeld KA, O&apos;Sullivan O, Patterson<lb/> E, et al. Behavioural and neurochemical consequences of chronic gut microbiota<lb/> depletion during adulthood in the rat. Neuroscience. IBRO; 2016;339: 463-477.<lb/> doi:10.1016/j.neuroscience.2016.10.003<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>34</label>.<lb/> Lamendella R, Santo Domingo JW, Ghosh S, Martinson J, Oerther DB. Comparative<lb/> fecal metagenomics unveils unique functional capacity of the swine gut. BMC<lb/> Microbiol. BioMed Central Ltd; 2011;11: 103. doi:10.1186/1471-2180-11-103<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>35</label>.<lb/> Villamil SI, Huerlimann R, Morianos C, Sarnyai Z, Maes GE. Adverse effect of early-<lb/>life high-fat/high-carbohydrate (&quot;Western&quot;) diet on bacterial community in the distal<lb/> bowel<lb/> of<lb/> mice.<lb/> Nutr<lb/> Res.<lb/> Elsevier<lb/> Inc.;<lb/> 2018;50:<lb/> 25-36.<lb/> doi:10.1016/j.nutres.2017.11.008<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>36</label>.<lb/> Zhang Y, Limaye PB, Renaud HJ, Klaassen CD. Effect of various antibiotics on<lb/> modulation of intestinal microbiota and bile acid profile in mice. Toxicol Appl<lb/> Pharmacol. Elsevier Inc.; 2014;277: 138-145. doi:10.1016/j.taap.2014.03.009<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>37</label>.<lb/> Verdú EF, Bercik P, Verma-Gandhu M, Huang XX, Blennerhassett P, Jackson W, et al.<lb/> Specific probiotic therapy attenuates antibiotic induced visceral hypersensitivity in mice.<lb/> Gut. 2006;55: 182-190. doi:10.1136/gut.2005.066100<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>38</label>.<lb/> Fröhlich EE, Farzi A, Mayerhofer R, Reichmann F, Jačan A, Wagner B, et al. Cognitive<lb/> impairment by antibiotic-induced gut dysbiosis: Analysis of gut microbiota-brain<lb/> communication. Brain Behav Immun. 2016;56: 140-155. doi:10.1016/j.bbi.2016.02.020<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>39</label>.<lb/> Matsunaga N, Shimizu H, Fujimoto K, Watanabe K, Yamasaki T, Hatano N, et al.<lb/> Expression of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase on the surface of Clostridium<lb/> perfringens<lb/> cells.<lb/> Anaerobe.<lb/> England;<lb/> 2018;51:<lb/> 124-130.<lb/> doi:10.1016/j.anaerobe.2018.05.001<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>40</label>.<lb/> Schreiber W, Durre P. The glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase of Clostridium<lb/> acetobutylicum: isolation and purification of the enzyme, and sequencing and<lb/> localization of the gap gene within a cluster of other glycolytic genes. Microbiology.<lb/> England; 1999;145 ( Pt 8: 1839-1847. doi:10.1099/13500872-145-8-1839<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>41</label>.<lb/> Oberbach A, Haange SB, Schlichting N, Heinrich M, Lehmann S, Till H, et al.<lb/> Metabolic in Vivo Labeling Highlights Differences of Metabolically Active Microbes<lb/> from the Mucosal Gastrointestinal Microbiome between High-Fat and Normal Chow<lb/> Diet. J Proteome Res. 2017;16: 1593-1604. doi:10.1021/acs.jproteome.6b00973<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>42</label>.<lb/> Heinritz SN, Weiss E, Eklund M, Aumiller T, Louis S, Rings A, et al. Intestinal<lb/> microbiota and microbial metabolites are changed in a pig model fed a high-fat/low-fiber<lb/> or<lb/> a<lb/> low-fat/high-fiber<lb/> diet.<lb/> PLoS<lb/> One.<lb/> 2016;11:<lb/> 1-21.<lb/> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0154329</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

