<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>
        <bibl>I. ELLIOTT. Dibenzopyrrocoline alkaloids. Dans The^ alkaloids.<lb/> Vol. 31. Éditeur : A. Brossi. Academic Press, New York. 1987.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>J. EWING, G. K. HUGUES, E. RITCHIE et W. C. TAYLOR. Nature<lb/> (London), 169, 618 (1952).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>J. EWING, G. K. HUGUES, E. RITCHIE et W. C. TAYLOR. Aust. J.<lb/> Chem. 6, 78 (1953).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>T. KAMETANI et K. OGASAWARA. Chem. Pharm. Bull. 16, 1498<lb/> (1968).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>M. SHAMMA et D. M. HINDENLANG. Carbon-13 NMR shift<lb/> assignments of amines and alkaloids. Plenum Press, New York.<lb/> 1979.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>A. J. MARSAIOLI, E. A. RUVÉDA et F. DE A. M. REIS. Phyto-<lb/>chemistry, 17, 1655 (1978).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>C. P. MAKet A. BROSSI. Heterocycles, 12, 1413 (1979).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>S. TAKANO, S. SATOH, Y. OSHIMA etK. OGASAWARA. Heterocy-<lb/>cles, 26,1487 (1987).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>E. SANCHEZ et J. COMIN. Tetrahedron Lett. 1139(1967).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>T. KAMETANI et K. OGASAWARA. J. Chem. Soc. (C), 2208<lb/> (1967).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>F. BENINGTON etR. D. MORIN. J. Org. Chem. 32, 1050 (1967).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>R. ROBINSON et S. SUGASAWA. J. Chem. Soc. 3163 (1931).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>FOU-TIAN et DOU-BIAN. J. Pharm. Soc. Jpn. 58,783 (1938).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>H. WEIL. Beilstein, 43, 2605 (1910).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>R. G. NAIK et T. S. WHEELER. J. Chem. Soc. 1780 (1938).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>A. BROSSI, A. RAMEL, J. O'BRIEN et S. TEITEL. Chem. Pharm.<lb/> Bull. 21, 1839(1973).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>I. R. C. BICK, W. SINCHAI, T. SÉVENET, A. RANAIVO, M. NIETO<lb/> et A. CAVÉ. Planta Med. 39, 205 (1980).<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>A. CAVÉ, M. LEBOEUF, H. MOSKOWITZ, A. RANAIVO, I. R. C.<lb/> BICK, W. SINCHAI, M. NIETO, T. SÉVENET et P. CABALION.<lb/> Aust. J. Chem. Soumis.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl>T. KAMETANI, A. UJIIE, K. TAKAHASHI, T. NAKANO, T. SUZUKI<lb/> etK. FUKUMOTO. Chem. Pharm. Bull. 21, 766 (1973).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

