<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Andalman AS, Fee MS. A basal ganglia-forebrain circuit in the songbird biases motor output to<lb/> avoid vocal errors. Proc Natl Acad Sci 106: 12518-12523, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Baker SN, Perez MA. Reticulospinal Contributions to Gross Hand Function after Human Spinal<lb/> Cord Injury. J Neurosci 37: 3368-16, 2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Bottjer S, Miesner E, Arnold A. Forebrain lesions disrupt development but not maintenance of<lb/> song in passerine birds. Science (80-) 224: 901-903, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Cannonieri GC, Bonilha L, Fernandes PT, Cendes F, Li LM. Practice and perfect: Length of<lb/> training and structural brain changes in experienced typists. Neuroreport 18: 1063-1066, 2007.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Carlsen AN, Chua R, Inglis JT, Sanderson DJ, Franks IM. Can prepared responses be stored<lb/> subcortically? Exp Brain Res 159: 301-9, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Carlsen AN, Chua R, Inglis JT, Sanderson DJ, Franks IM. Differential effects of startle on<lb/> reaction time for finger and arm movements. J Neurophysiol 101: 306-314, 2009.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Carlsen AN, Dakin CJ, Chua R, Franks IM. Startle produces early response latencies that are<lb/> distinct from stimulus intensity effects. Exp Brain Res 176: 199-205, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Carlsen AN, Maslovat D, Lam MY, Chua R, Franks IM. Considerations for the use of a<lb/> startling acoustic stimulus in studies of motor preparation in humans. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 35:<lb/> 366-76, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Chapman JC. The learning curve in typewriting. J Appl Psychol 3: 252-268, 1919.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Churchland MM, Cunningham JP, Kaufman MT, Foster JD, Nuyujukian P, Ryu SI,<lb/> Shenoy K V., Shenoy K V. Neural population dynamics during reaching. Nature 487: 51-56,<lb/> 2012.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Cohen J. Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences. 1988.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Coppens MJM, Roelofs JMB, Donkers NAJ, Nonnekes J, Geurts ACH, Weerdesteyn V. A<lb/> startling acoustic stimulus facilitates voluntary lower extremity movements and automatic<lb/> postural responses in people with chronic stroke. J Neurol , 2018. doi:10.1007/s00415-018-8889-<lb/>5.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Darling WG, Ge J, Stilwell-Morecraft KS, Rotella DL, Pizzimenti MA, Morecraft RJ. Hand<lb/> motor recovery following extensive frontoparietal cortical injury is accompanied by upregulated<lb/> corticoreticular projections in monkey. J Neurosci 38: 6323-6339, 2018.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Davis M, Gendelman DS, Tischler MD, Gendelman PM. A primary acoustic startle circuit:<lb/> lesion and stimulation studies. J Neurosci 2: 791-805, 1982.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Davis M, Gendelman PM. Plasticity of the acoustic startle response in the acutely decerebrate<lb/> rat. J Comp Physiol Psychol 91: 549-563, 1977.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Fee MS, Goldberg JH. REVIEW A HYPOTHESIS FOR BASAL GANGLIA-DEPENDENT<lb/> REINFORCEMENT LEARNING IN THE SONGBIRD. NSC 198: 152-170, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Fish J, Soechting J. Synergistic finger movements in a skilled motor task. Exp Brain Res 91:<lb/> 327-334, 1992.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Fletcher C, Jon E. Clinical Neurophysiology Deficits in startle-evoked arm movements increase<lb/> with impairment following stroke. Clin Neurophysiol 125: 1682-1688, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Groves PM, Wilson CJ, Boyle RD. Brain stem pathways, cortical modulation, and habituation<lb/> of the acoustic startle response. Behav Biol 10: 391-418, 1974.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Hager-Ross C, Schieber MH. Quantifying the Independence of Human Finger Movements:<lb/> Comparisons of Digits, Hands, and Movement Frequencies. J Neurosci 20: 8542-8550, 2000.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Hammond GR. Lesions of pontine and medullary reticular formation and prestimulus inhibition<lb/> of the acoustic startle reaction in rats. [Online]. Physiol Behav 10: 239-43,<lb/> 1973http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4575307.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Hill LB. A Quarter Century of Delayed Recall. J Genet Psychol 44: 231-238, 1934.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Hill LB, Rejall AE, Thorndike E. Practice in the case of typewriting. J Genet Psychol 20: 516-<lb/>529, 1913.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Honeycutt CF, Kharouta M, Perreault EJ. Evidence for reticulospinal contributions to<lb/> coordinated finger movements in humans. J Neurophysiol 1404, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Honeycutt CF, Perreault EJ. Planning of Ballistic Movement following Stroke: Insights from<lb/> the Startle Reflex. PLoS One 7, 2012a.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Honeycutt CF, Perreault EJ. Planning of Ballistic Movement following Stroke: Insights from<lb/> the Startle Reflex. PLoS One 7: e43097, 2012b.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Honeycutt CF, Tresch UA, Perreault EJ. Startling acoustic stimuli can evoke fast hand<lb/> extension movements in stroke survivors. Clin Neurophysiol , 2014.<lb/> doi:10.1016/j.clinph.2014.05.025.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Honeycutt CF, Tresch UA, Perreault EJ. Startling acoustic stimuli can evoke fast hand<lb/> extension movements in stroke survivors. Clin Neurophysiol 126: 160-164, 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kao JC, Nuyujukian P, Ryu SI, Churchland MM, Cunningham JP, Shenoy K V. Single-<lb/>trial dynamics of motor cortex and their applications to brain-machine interfaces. Nat Commun<lb/> 6, 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kawai R, Markman T, Poddar R, Ko R, Fantana AL, Dhawale AK, Kampff AR, Ölveczky<lb/> BP. Motor Cortex Is Required for Learning but Not for Executing a Motor Skill. Neuron 86:<lb/> 800-812, 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Kirkpatrick N, Ravichandran V, Perreault E, Schaefer S, Honeycutt C. Evidence for startle<lb/> as a measurable behavioral indicator of motor learning. PLoS One 9: e0195689, 2018.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Leijnse JNAL, Campbell-Kyureghyan NH, Spektor D, Quesada PM. Assessment of<lb/> Individual Finger Muscle Activity in the Extensor Digitorum Communis by Surface EMG. J<lb/> Neurophysiol 100: 3225-3235, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Leow LA, Uchida A, Egberts JL, Riek S, Lipp O V., Tresilian J, Marinovic W. Triggering<lb/> Mechanisms for Motor Actions: The Effects of Expectation on Reaction Times to Intense<lb/> Acoustic Stimuli. Neuroscience 393: 226-235, 2018.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Limentani GB, Ringo MC, Ye F, Bergquist ML, McSorley EO. Beyond the t-Test: statistical<lb/> equivalence testing. Anal Chem 77: 221A-226A, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Marinovic W, Brauer SG, Hayward KS, Carroll TJ, Riek S. Electric and acoustic stimulation<lb/> during movement preparation can facilitate movement execution in healthy participants and<lb/> stroke survivors. Neurosci Lett 618: 134-138, 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Marinovic W, Tresilian JR. Triggering prepared actions by sudden sounds: Reassessing the<lb/> evidence for a single mechanism. Acta Physiol 217: 13-32, 2016.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Maslovat D, Carlsen AN, Chua R, Franks IM. Response preparation changes during practice<lb/> of an asynchronous bimanual movement. Exp Brain Res 195: 383-92, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Maslovat D, Carlsen AN, Franks IM. Subcortical motor circuit excitability during simple and<lb/> choice reaction time. Behav Neurosci 126: 499-503, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Maslovat D, Carlsen AN, Ishimoto R, Chua R, Franks IM. Response preparation changes<lb/> following practice of an asymmetrical bimanual movement. Exp Brain Res 190: 239-249, 2008.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Maslovat D, Hodges NJ, Chua R, Franks IM. Motor preparation and the effects of practice:<lb/> evidence from startle. Behav Neurosci 125: 226-40, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Neuringer A, Deiss C, Olson G. Reinforced variability and operant learning. J Exp Psychol<lb/> Anim Behav Process 26: 98-111, 2000.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Nonnekes J, Geurts ACH, Oude LB. Reduced StartReact effect and freezing of gait in<lb/> Parkinson&apos;s disease : two of a kind ? J Neurol 943-950, 2014a.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Nonnekes J, Kam D De, Nijhuis LBO, Geel K Van. StartReact Effects Support Different<lb/> Pathophysiological Mechanisms Underlying Freezing of Gait and Postural Instability in<lb/> Parkinson &apos; s Disease. PLoS One 1-17, 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Nonnekes J, Oude Nijhuis LB, de Niet M, de Bot ST, Pasman JW, van de Warrenburg<lb/> BPC, Bloem BR, Weerdesteyn V, Geurts AC. StartReact restores reaction time in HSP:<lb/> evidence for subcortical release of a motor program. J Neurosci 34: 275-81, 2014b.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Rahimi M, Honeycutt CF. Does startle enhance unrestricted, 2D reaching movement in stroke<lb/> survivors? Society for Neuroscience Abstract2017.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sadtler PT, Quick KM, Golub MD, Chase SM, Ryu SI, Tyler-Kabara EC, Yu BM, Batista<lb/> AP. Neural constraints on learning. Nature 512: 423-426, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Santello M, Baud-Bovy G, Jörntell H. Neural bases of hand synergies. Front Comput Neurosci<lb/> 7: 1-15, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Schieber MH, Santello M. Neural Control of Movement Hand function : peripheral and central<lb/> constraints on performance. 2293-2300, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Serranová T, Jech R, Martí MJ, Modreanu R, Valldeoriola F, Sieger T, Růžička E, Valls-<lb/>Solé J. A Loud Auditory Stimulus Overcomes Voluntary Movement Limitation in Cervical<lb/> Dystonia. PLoS One 7: 1-9, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Sternberg S, Monsell S, Knoll RL, Wright CE. The latency and duration of rapid movement<lb/> sequences: Comparisons of speech and typewriting. ACADEMIC PRESS, INC., 1978.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Turner RS, Desmurget M. Basal ganglia contributions to motor control: a vigorous tutor. Curr<lb/> Opin Neurobiol 20: 704:716, 2010.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Valls-Solé J, Rothwell JC, Goulart F, Cossu G, Muñoz E. Patterned ballistic movements<lb/> triggered by a startle in healthy humans. J Physiol 516 ( Pt 3: 931-8, 1999.<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Valls-Solé J, Solé a, Valldeoriola F, Muñoz E, Gonzalez LE, Tolosa ES. Reaction time and<lb/> acoustic startle in normal human subjects. Neurosci Lett 195: 97-100, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>You A, JM C. Flexible modulation of neural variance facilitates neuroprosthetic skill learning.<lb/> BioRxiv 817346, 2019.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

