<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> A. G. Riess, A. V. Filippenko, P. Challis et al., &quot; Observational<lb/> evidence from supernovae for an accelerating universe and a<lb/> cosmological constant, &quot; The Astronomical Journal, vol. 116, no.<lb/> 3, p. 1009, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> S. Perlmutter, G. Aldering, G. Goldhaber et al., &quot; Measurements<lb/> of Ω and Λ from 42 high-redshift supernovae, &quot; The Astrophysical<lb/> Journal, vol. 517, no. 2, p. 565, 1999.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> R. Amanullah, C. Lidman, D. Rubin et al., &quot; Spectra and hubble<lb/> space telescope light curves of six type ia supernovae at 0.511 &lt;<lb/> í µí± § &lt; 1.12 and the union2 compilation, &quot; The Astrophysical<lb/> Journal, vol. 716, p. 712, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> A. C. Pope, T. Matsubara, A. S. Szalay et al., &quot; Cosmological<lb/> parameters from eigenmode analysis of sloan digital sky survey<lb/> galaxy redshifts, &quot; The Astrophysical Journal, vol. 607, no. 2, p.<lb/> 655, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> D. N. Spergel, L. Verde, H. V. Peiris et al., &quot; First-year Wilkin-<lb/>son Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP)<lb/> * observations:<lb/> determination of cosmological parameters, &quot; The Astrophysical<lb/> Journal Supplement Series, vol. 148, no. 1, p. 175, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> G. C. Samanta, &quot; Bianchi type-III cosmological models with<lb/> anisotropic dark energy (DE) in lyra geometry, &quot; International<lb/> Journal of Theoretical Physics, vol. 52, no. 10, pp. 3442–3456,<lb/> 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label> S. Weinberg, &quot; The cosmological constant problems (Talk given<lb/> at Dark Matter 2000, February, 2000), &quot; http://arxiv.org/abs/<lb/> astro-ph/0005265.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> J.Soì a and H. ˇ<lb/> Stefanči´Stefanči´c, &quot; Effective equation of state for dark<lb/> energy: Mimicking quintessence and phantom energy through<lb/> a variable Λ, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 624, no. 3-4, pp. 147–157,<lb/> 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> I. L. Shapiro and J.Soì a, &quot; On the possible running of the<lb/> cosmological &apos;constant&apos; , &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 682, no. 1, pp.<lb/> 105–113, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> C. Armendariz-Picon, V. Mukhanov, and P. J. Steinhardt,<lb/> &quot; Dynamical solution to the problem of a small cosmological<lb/> constant and late-time cosmic acceleration, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 85, no. 21, pp. 4438–4441, 2000.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> C. Armendariz-Picon and V. Mukhanov, &quot; Essentials of k-<lb/>essence, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 63, no. 10, Article ID 103510,<lb/> 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> M. Khurshudyan, J. Sadeghi, M. Hakobyan, H. Farahani, and<lb/> R. Myrzakulov, &quot; Interaction between modified Chaplygin gas<lb/> and ghost dark energy in the presence of extra dimensions, &quot; The<lb/> European Physical Journal Plus, vol. 129, article 119, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> Y.-B. Wu, Y.-Y. Su, J.-B. Lu et al., &quot; Effects of modified Chaplygin<lb/> gas on structure formation in the universe, &quot; General Relativity<lb/> and Gravitation, vol. 45, no. 7, pp. 1387–1402, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> E. O. Kahya, M. Khurshudyan, B. Pourhassan, R. Myrzakulov,<lb/> and A. Pasqua, &quot; Higher order corrections of the extended Chap-<lb/>lygin gas cosmology with varying í µí°º and Λ, &quot; http://arxiv.org/<lb/> abs/1402.2592.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> J. Sadeghi, M. Khurshudyan, M. Hakobyan, and H. Fara-<lb/>hani, &quot; Hubble parameter corrected interactions in cosmology, &quot;<lb/> Advances in High Energy Physics, vol. 2014, Article ID 129085, 16<lb/> pages, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> J. Sadeghi, M. Khurshudyan, and H. Farahani, &quot; Phenomenolog-<lb/>ical varying modified chaplygin gas with variable G and Λ: toy<lb/> models for our universe, &quot; http://arxiv.org/abs/1308.1819.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> M. Khurshudyan, &quot; Interaction between generalized varying<lb/> Chaplygin gas and Tachyonic fluid, &quot; http://arxiv.org/abs/1301<lb/> .1021.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> J. Sadeghi, B. Pourhassan, and Z. Abbaspour Moghaddam,<lb/> &quot; Interacting entropy-corrected holographic dark energy and IR<lb/> cut-off length, &quot; International Journal of Theoretical Physics, vol.<lb/> 53, no. 1, pp. 125–135, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> U. Debnath, &quot; Constraining the parameters of modified chap-<lb/>lygin gas in Einstein-Aether gravity, &quot; Advances in High Energy<lb/> Physics, vol. 2014, Article ID 653630, 8 pages, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> H. Saadat and B. Pourhassan, &quot; Viscous varying generalized<lb/> Chaplygin gas with cosmological constant and space curvature, &quot;<lb/> International Journal of Theoretical Physics, vol. 52, no. 10, pp.<lb/> 3712–3720, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> M. Sharif and M. Azam, &quot; Spherical thin-shell wormholes and<lb/> modified chaplygin gas, &quot; Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle<lb/> Physics, vol. 2013, no. 5, article 25, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> B. Pourhassan, &quot; Viscous modified cosmic chaplygin gas cos-<lb/>mology, &quot; International Journal of Modern Physics D, vol. 22, no.<lb/> 9, Article ID 1350061, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> C. Uggla, &quot; Global cosmological dynamics for the scalar field<lb/> representation of the modified Chaplygin gas, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> D, vol. 88, Article ID 064040, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> H. Saadat and B. Pourhassan, &quot; FRW bulk viscous cosmology<lb/> with modified cosmic Chaplygin gas, &quot; Astrophysics and Space<lb/> Science, vol. 344, no. 1, pp. 237–241, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> R. Herrera, M. Olivares, and N. Videla, &quot; Intermediate-<lb/>generalized Chaplygin gas inflationary universe model, &quot; The<lb/> European Physical Journal C, vol. 73, no. 1, p. 2295, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> H. Saadat and B. Pourhassan, &quot; Effect of varying bulk viscosity<lb/> on generalized chaplygin gas, &quot; International Journal of Theoret-<lb/>ical Physics, vol. 53, no. 4, pp. 1168–1173, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[27]</label> J. Wang, Y.-B. Wu, D. Wang, and W.-Q. Yang, &quot; Extended analysis<lb/> on new generalized Chaplygin gas, &quot; Chinese Physics Letters, vol.<lb/> 26, no. 8, Article ID 089801, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[28]</label> H. Saadat and B. Pourhassan, &quot; FRW bulk viscous cosmology<lb/> with modified Chaplygin gas in flat space, &quot; Astrophysics and<lb/> Space Science, vol. 343, no. 2, pp. 783–786, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[29]</label> T. P. Sotiriou and V. Faraoni, &quot; f(R) theories of gravity, &quot; Reviews<lb/> of Modern Physics, vol. 82, no. 1, pp. 451–497, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[30]</label> Y.-F. Cai, S.-H. Chen, J. B. Dent, S. Dutta, and E. N. Saridakis,<lb/> &quot; Matter bounce cosmology with the f (T) gravity, &quot; Classical and<lb/> Quantum Gravity, vol. 28, no. 21, Article ID 215011, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[31]</label> J. Wang, Y.-B. Wu, Y.-X. Guo, W.-Q. Yang, and L. Wang,<lb/> &quot; Energy conditions and stability in generalized f(R) gravity<lb/> with arbitrary coupling between matter and geometry, &quot; Physics<lb/> Letters B, vol. 689, no. 4-5, pp. 133–138, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[32]</label> Y.-B. Wu, Y.-Y. Zhao, R.-G. Cai, J.-B. Lu, J.-W. Lu, and X.-J.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gao, &quot; Thermodynamic laws for generalized f(R) gravity with<lb/> curvature-matter coupling, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 717, no. 4-5,<lb/> pp. 323–329, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[33]</label> S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Introduction to modified gravity<lb/> and gravitational alternative for dark energy, &quot; International<lb/> Journal of Geometric Methods in Modern Physics, vol. 4, no. 1,<lb/> pp. 115–145, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[34]</label> S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Unified cosmic history in<lb/> modified gravity: from F(R) theory to Lorentz non-invariant<lb/> models, &quot; Physics Reports, vol. 505, no. 2–4, pp. 59–144, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[35]</label> G. Cognola, E. Elizalde, S. Nojiri, S. D. Odintsov, L. Sebastiani,<lb/> and S. Zerbini, &quot; Class of viable modified f(R) gravities describ-<lb/>ing inflation and the onset of accelerated expansion, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D, vol. 77, no. 4, Article ID 046009, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[36]</label> A. V. Astashenok, S. Capozziello, and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Further<lb/> stable neutron star models from í µí±(í µí±) gravity, &quot; Journal of<lb/> Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, vol. 12, article 040, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[37]</label> H. Farajollahi, J. Sadeghi, and M. Pourali, &quot; Stability analysis<lb/> of holographic dark energy in Brans-Dicke cosmology, &quot; Astro-<lb/>physics and Space Science, vol. 341, no. 2, pp. 695–700, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[38]</label> M. Khurshudyan, B. Pourhassan, and A. Pasqua, &quot; Higher<lb/> derivative corrections of f (R) gravity with varying equation of<lb/> state in the case of variable G and Λ, &quot; http://arxiv.org/abs/1401<lb/> .6630.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[39]</label> B. Ratra and P. J. E. Peebles, &quot; Cosmological consequences of a<lb/> rolling homogeneous scalar field, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 37, no.<lb/> 12, pp. 3406–3427, 1988.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[40]</label> C. Wetterich, &quot; Cosmology and the fate of dilatation symmetry, &quot;<lb/> Nuclear Physics, Section B, vol. 302, no. 4, pp. 668–696, 1988.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[41]</label> A. R. Liddle and R. J. Scherrer, &quot; Classification of scalar field<lb/> potentials with cosmological scaling solutions, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> D, vol. 59, Article ID 023509, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[42]</label> I. Zlatev, L. Wang, and P. J. Steinhardt, &quot; Quintessence, cosmic<lb/> coincidence, and the cosmological constant, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 82, no. 5, pp. 896–899, 1999.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[43]</label> K. Guo, N. Ohta, and Y. Z. Zhang, &quot; Parametrizations of the dark<lb/> energy density and scalar potentials, &quot; Modern Physics Letters A,<lb/> vol. 22, no. 12, pp. 883–890, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[44]</label> S. Dutta, E. N. Saridakis, and R. J. Scherrer, &quot; Dark energy from a<lb/> quintessence (phantom) field rolling near a potential minimum<lb/> (maximum), &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 79, Article ID 103005,<lb/> 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[45]</label> E. N. Saridakis and S. V. Sushkov, &quot; Quintessence and phantom<lb/> cosmology with nonminimal derivative coupling, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D, vol. 81, Article ID 083510, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[46]</label> M. Khurshudyan, E. Chubaryan, and B. Pourhassan, &quot; Interact-<lb/>ing quintessence models of dark energy, &quot; International Journal<lb/> of Theoretical Physics, vol. 53, no. 7, pp. 2370–2378, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[47]</label> M. Khurshudyan, A. Pasqua, J. Sadeghi, and H. Farahani,<lb/> &quot; Quintessence cosmology with an effective Λ-term in Lyra<lb/> manifold, &quot; http://arxiv.org/abs/1402.0118.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[48]</label> W. Hao, &quot; Cosmological constraints on the sign-changeable<lb/> interactions, &quot; Communications in Theoretical Physics, vol. 56, no.<lb/> 5, p. 972, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[49]</label> P. G. Ferreira and M. Joyce, &quot; Structure formation with a self-<lb/>tuning scalar field, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 79, no. 24, pp.<lb/> 4740–4743, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[50]</label> E. J. Copeland, A. R. Liddle, and D. Wands, &quot; Exponential<lb/> potentials and cosmological scaling solutions, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> D, vol. 57, no. 8, pp. 4686–4690, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[51]</label> M. Khurshudyan, &quot; Phenomenological models of universe with<lb/> varying G and Λ, &quot; Central European Journal of Physics, vol. 12,<lb/> no. 5, pp. 348–366, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[52]</label> G. Lyra, &quot; ¨<lb/> Uber eine modifikation der riemannschen geometrie, &quot;<lb/> Mathematische Zeitschrift, vol. 54, pp. 52–64, 1951.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[53]</label> D. K. Sen, &quot; A static cosmological model, &quot; Zeitschrift für Physik,<lb/> vol. 149, no. 3, pp. 311–323, 1957.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[54]</label> K. A. Dunn, &quot; A scalar-tensor theory of gravitation in a modified<lb/> Riemannian manifold, &quot; Journal of Mathematical Physics, vol. 12,<lb/> p. 578, 1971.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[55]</label> W. D. Halford, &quot; Cosmological theory based on Lyra&apos;s geometry, &quot;<lb/> Australian Journal of Physics, vol. 23, no. 5, pp. 863–870, 1970.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[56]</label> V. K. Shchigolev, &quot; Cosmology with an effective Λ-term in Lyra<lb/> manifold, &quot; Chinese Physics Letters, vol. 30, Article ID 119801,<lb/> 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[57]</label> X.-m. Chen, Y. Gong, and E. N. Saridakis, &quot; Phase-space analysis<lb/> of interacting phantom cosmology, &quot; Journal of Cosmology and<lb/> Astroparticle Physics, vol. 2009, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[58]</label> J. K. Erickson, R. R. Caldwell, P. J. Steinhardt, C. Armendariz-<lb/>Picon, and V. Mukhanov, &quot; Measuring the speed of sound of<lb/> quintessence, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 88, no. 12, Article ID<lb/> 121301, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[59]</label> T. Koivisto and D. F. Mota, &quot; Dark energy anisotropic stress and<lb/> large scale structure formation, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 73, no.<lb/> 8, Article ID 083502, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[60]</label> S. Kumar, &quot; Observational constraints on Hubble constant and<lb/> deceleration parameter in power-law cosmology, &quot; Monthly<lb/> Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, vol. 422, no. 3, pp.<lb/> 2532–2538, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[61]</label> A. G. Riess, L. Macri, S. Casertano et al., &quot; A 3% solution:<lb/> determination of the Hubble constant with the Hubble space<lb/> telescope and wide field camera 3, &quot; The Astrophysical Journal,<lb/> vol. 730, no. 2, p. 119, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[62]</label> F. Beutler, C. Blake, M. Colless et al., &quot; The 6dF Galaxy Survey:<lb/> baryon acoustic oscillations and the local Hubble constant, &quot;<lb/> Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, vol. 416, no.<lb/> 4, pp. 3017–3032, 2011.<lb/></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

