<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>1 </label>D. N. Spergel, L. Verde, H. V. Peiris et al., &quot; First year Wilkinson Microwave AnisotropyProbe<lb/> WMAP observations: determination of cosmological parameters, &quot; The Astrophysical Journal<lb/> Supplement, vol. 148, no. 1, pp. 175–194, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>2 </label>D. N. Spergel, R. Bean, O. Doré et al., &quot; Three-year Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe WMAP<lb/> observations: implications for cosmology, &quot; The Astrophysical Journal Supplement, vol. 170, no. 2, p. 377,<lb/> 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>3 </label>E. Komatsu, J. Dunkley, M. R. Nolta et al., &quot; Five-year Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe<lb/> observations: cosmological interpretation, &quot; The Astrophysical Journal Supplement, vol. 180, no. 2, p.<lb/> 330, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>4 </label>E. Komatsu, K. M. Smith, J. Dunkley et al., &quot; Seven-year Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe<lb/> Wmap observations: cosmological interpretation, &quot; The Astrophysical Journal Supplement, vol. 192,<lb/> no. 2, p. 18, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>5 </label>S. Perlmutter, G. Aldering, G. Goldhaber et al., &quot; Measurements of Ω and Λ from 42 high-redshift<lb/> supernovae, &quot; The Astrophysical Journal, vol. 517, no. 2, p. 565, 1999.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>6 </label>A. G. Riess, A. V. Filippenko, P. Challis et al., &quot; Observational evidence from supernovae for an<lb/> accelerating universe and a cosmological constant, &quot; The Astronomical Journal, vol. 116, no. 3, p. 1009,<lb/> 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>7 </label>M. Tegmark, M. Strauss, M. Blanton et al., &quot; Cosmological parameters from SDSS and WMAP, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review D, vol. 69, no. 10, Article ID 103501, 26 pages, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>8 </label>U. Seljak, A. Makarov, P. McDonald et al., &quot; Cosmological parameter analysis including SDSS Lyα<lb/> forest and galaxy bias: constraints on the primordial spectrum of fluctuations, neutrino mass, and<lb/> dark energy, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 71, no. 10, Article ID 103515, 20 pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>9 </label>D. J. Eisenstein, I. Zehavi, D. W. Hogg et al., &quot; Detection of the baryon acoustic peak in the large-scale<lb/> correlation function of SDSS luminous red galaxies, &quot; The Astrophysical Journal, vol. 633, no. 2, p. 560,<lb/> 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>10 </label>B. Jain and A. Taylor, &quot; Cross-correlation tomography: measuring dark energy evolution with weak<lb/> lensing, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 91, no. 14, Article ID 141302, 4 pages, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>11 </label>E. J. Copeland, M. Sami, and S. Tsujikawa, &quot; Dynamics of dark energy, &quot; International Journal of Modern<lb/> Physics D, vol. 15, no. 11, pp. 1753–1935, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>12 </label>R. Durrer and R. Maartens, &quot; Dark energy and dark gravity: theory overview, &quot; General Relativity and<lb/> Gravitation, vol. 40, no. 2-3, pp. 301–328, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>13 </label>Y. F. Cai, E. N. Saridakis, M. R. Setare, and J. Q. Xia, &quot; Quintom cosmology: theoretical implications<lb/> and observations, &quot; Physics Reports, vol. 493, no. 1, pp. 1–60, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>14 </label>S. Tsujikawa, &quot; Dark energy: investigation and modeling, &quot; submitted to Cosmology and Extragalactic<lb/> Astrophysics.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>15 </label>L. Amendola and S. Tsujikawa, Dark Energy, Cambridge University press, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>16 </label>M. Li, X. D. Li, S. Wang, and Y. Wang, &quot; Dark energy, &quot; Communications in Theoretical Physics, vol. 56,<lb/> no. 3, p. 525, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>17 </label>S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Unified cosmic history in modified gravity: from FR theory to Lorentz<lb/> non-invariant models, &quot; Physics Reports, vol. 505, no. 2–4, pp. 59–144, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>18 </label>S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Introduction to modified gravity and gravitational alternative for dark<lb/> energy, &quot; International Journal of Geometric Methods in Modern Physics, vol. 4, pp. 115–146, 2007, eConf<lb/> C0602061, 06, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>19 </label>T. P. Sotiriou and V. Faraoni, &quot; fR theories of gravity, &quot; Reviews of Modern Physics, vol. 82, no. 1, pp.<lb/> 451–497, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>20 </label>S. Capozziello and V. Faraoni, Beyond Einstein Gravity, Springer, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>21 </label>S. Capozziello and M. De Laurentis, &quot; Extended theories of gravity, &quot; Physics Reports, vol. 509, no. 4-5,<lb/> pp. 167–321, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>22 </label>A. De Felice and and S. Tsujikawa, &quot; fR theories, &quot; Living Reviews in Relativity, vol. 13, p. 3, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>23 </label>T. Clifton, P. G. Ferreira, A. Padilla, and C. Skordis, &quot; Modified gravity and cosmology, &quot; Physics<lb/> Reports, vol. 513, no. 1–3, pp. 1–189, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>24 </label>R. R. Caldwell, M. Kamionkowski, and N. N. Weinberg, &quot; Phantom energy: dark energy with w &lt; −1<lb/> causes a cosmic doomsday, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 91, no. 7, Article ID 071301, 4 pages, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>25 </label>B. McInnes, &quot; The dS/CFT correspondence and the big smash, &quot; Journal of High Energy Physics, vol.<lb/> 208, p. 29, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>26 </label>S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Quantum de Sitter cosmology and phantom matter, &quot; Physics Letters B,<lb/> vol. 562, no. 3-4, pp. 147–152, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>27 </label>S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Effective equation of state and energy conditions in phantom/tachyon<lb/> inflationary cosmology perturbed by quantum effects, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 571, no. 1-2, pp. 1–10,<lb/> 2003.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>28 </label>V. Faraoni, &quot; Superquintessence, &quot; International Journal of Modern Physics D, vol. 11, pp. 471–482, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>29 </label>P. F. Gonzalez-Diaz, &quot; k-essential phantom energy: doomsday around the corner? &quot; Physics Letters B,<lb/> vol. 586, no. 1-2, pp. 1–4, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>30 </label>E. Elizalde, S. Nojiri, and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Late-time cosmology in a phantom scalar-tensor theory:<lb/> dark energy and the cosmic speed-up, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 70, no. 4, Article ID 043539, 20 pages,<lb/> 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>31 </label>P. Singh, M. Sami, and N. Dadhich, &quot; Cosmological dynamics of a phantom field, &quot; Physical Review D,<lb/> vol. 68, no. 2, Article ID 023522, 7 pages, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>32 </label>C. Csáki, N. Kaloper, and J. Terning, &quot; Exorcising w &lt; −1, &quot; Annals of Physics, vol. 317, no. 2, pp.<lb/> 410–422, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>33 </label>P. X. Wu and and H. W. Yu, &quot; Avoidance of big rip in phantom cosmology by gravitational back<lb/> reaction, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol. 727, no. 1-2, pp. 355–367, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>34 </label>S. Nesseris and L. Perivolaropoulos, &quot; The fate of bound systems in phantom and quintessence<lb/> cosmologies, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 70, Article ID 123529, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>35 </label>M. Sami and A. Toporensky, &quot; Phantom field and the fate of the universe, &quot; Modern Physics Letters A,<lb/> vol. 19, no. 20, p. 1509, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>36 </label>L. P. Chimento and R. Lazkoz, &quot; Constructing phantom cosmologies from standard scalar field<lb/> universes, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 91, no. 21, Article ID 211301, 3 pages, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>37 </label>J. G. Hao and X. Z. Li, &quot; Phantom-like GCG and the constraints of its parameters via cosmological<lb/> dynamics, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 606, no. 1-2, pp. 7–11, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>38 </label>E. Elizalde, S. Nojiri, S. D. Odintsov, and P. Wang, &quot; Dark energy: vacuum fluctuations, the effective<lb/> phantom phase, and holography, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 71, no. 10, Article ID 103504, 8 pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>39 </label>M. P. Dabrowski and T. Stachowiak, &quot; Phantom Friedmann cosmologies and higher-order<lb/> characteristics of expansion, &quot; Annals of Physics, vol. 321, no. 4, pp. 771–812, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>40 </label>F. S. N. Lobo, &quot; Phantom energy traversable wormholes, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 71, no. 8, Article ID<lb/> 084011, 8 pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>41 </label>R. G. Cai, H. S. Zhang, and A. Wang, &quot; Crossing w −1 in gauss–bonnet brane world with induced<lb/> gravity, &quot; Communications in Theoretical Physics, vol. 44, no. 5, p. 948, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>42 </label>I. Y. Aref&apos;eva, A. S. Koshelev, and S. Y. Vernov, &quot; Crossing the w −1 barrier in the D3-brane dark<lb/> energy model, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 72, no. 6, Article ID 064017, 11 pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>43 </label>H. Q. Lu, Z. G. Huang, and W. Fang, &quot; Quantum cosmology and dark energy model of born-infeld<lb/> type scalar field, &quot; submitted to High Energy Physics—Theory.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>44 </label>W. Godlowski and M. Szydlowski, &quot; How many parameters in the cosmological models with dark<lb/> energy? &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 623, no. 1-2, pp. 10–16, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>45 </label>J. Sola and H. Stefancic, &quot; Effective equation of state for dark energy: mimicking quintessence and<lb/> phantom energy through a variable Λ, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 624, no. 3-4, pp. 147–157, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>46 </label>Y. Shtanov and V. Sahni, &quot; New cosmological singularities in braneworld models, &quot; Classical and<lb/> Quantum Gravity, vol. 19, no. 11, pp. L101–L107, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>47 </label>J. D. Barrow, &quot; Sudden future singularities, &quot; Classical and Quantum Gravity, vol. 21, no. 11, pp. L79–<lb/> L82, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>48 </label>S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Quantum escape of sudden future singularity, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol.<lb/> 595, no. 1–4, pp. 1–8, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>49 </label>S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Final state and thermodynamics of a dark energy universe, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D, vol. 70, no. 10, Article ID 103522, 15 pages, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>50 </label>S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Inhomogeneous equation of state of the universe: phantom era, future<lb/> singularity, and crossing the phantom barrier, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 72, no. 2, Article ID 023003, 12<lb/> pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>51 </label>S. Cotsakis and I. Klaoudatou, &quot; Future singularities of isotropic cosmologies, &quot; Journal of Geometry<lb/> and Physics, vol. 55, no. 3, pp. 306–315, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>52 </label>M. P. Dabrowski, &quot; Inhomogenized sudden future singularities, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 71, no. 10,<lb/> Article ID 103505, 6 pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>53 </label>L. Fernández-Jambrina and R. Lazkoz, &quot; Geodesic behavior of sudden future singularities, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D, vol. 70, no. 12, Article ID 121503, 3 pages, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>54 </label>L. Fernández-Jambrina and R. Lazkoz, &quot; Singular fate of the universe in modified theories of gravity, &quot;<lb/> Physics Letters B, vol. 670, no. 4-5, pp. 254–258, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>55 </label>J. D. Barrow and C. G. Tsagas, &quot; New isotropic and anisotropic sudden singularities, &quot; Classical and<lb/> Quantum Gravity, vol. 22, no. 9, pp. 1563–1571, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>56 </label>H. Stefancic, &quot; Expansion around the vacuum equation of state: sudden future singularities and<lb/> asymptotic behavior, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 71, no. 8, Article ID 084024, 9 pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>57 </label>C. Cattoën and M. Visser, &quot; Necessary and sufficient conditions for big bangs, bounces, crunches,<lb/> rips, sudden singularities and extremality events, &quot; Classical and Quantum Gravity, vol. 22, no. 23, pp.<lb/> 4913–4930, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>58 </label>P. Tretyakov, A. Toporensky, Y. Shtanov, and V. Sahni, &quot; Quantum effects, soft singularities and the<lb/> fate of the universe in a braneworld cosmology, &quot; Classical and Quantum Gravity, vol. 23, no. 10, pp.<lb/> 3259–3274, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>59 </label>A. Balcerzak and M. P. Dabrowski, &quot; Strings at future singularities, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 73, no. 10,<lb/> Article ID 101301, 5 pages, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>60 </label>M. Sami, P. Singh, and S. Tsujikawa, &quot; Avoidance of future singularities in loop quantum cosmology, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review D, vol. 74, no. 4, Article ID 043514, 6 pages, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>61 </label>M. Bouhmadi-Lopez, P. F. Gonzalez-Diaz, and P. Martin-Moruno, &quot; Worse than a big rip? &quot; Physics<lb/> Letters B, vol. 659, no. 1-2, pp. 1–5, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>62 </label>A. V. Yurov, A. V. Astashenok, and P. F. Gonzalez-Diaz, &quot; Astronomical bounds on a future big freeze<lb/> singularity, &quot; Gravitation and Cosmology, vol. 14, no. 3, pp. 205–212, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>63 </label>T. Koivisto, &quot; Dynamics of nonlocal cosmology, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 77, no. 12, Article ID 123513,<lb/> 12 pages, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>64 </label>J. D. Barrow and S. Z. W. Lip, &quot; Classical stability of sudden and big rip singularities, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> D, vol. 80, no. 4, Article ID 043518, 8 pages, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>65 </label>M. Bouhmadi-Lopez, Y. Tavakoli, and P. V. Moniz, &quot; Appeasing the phantom menace? &quot; Journal of<lb/> Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, vol. 2010, no. 4, p. 16, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>66 </label>S. Nojiri, S. D. Odintsov, and S. Tsujikawa, &quot; Properties of singularities in the phantom dark energy<lb/> universe, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 71, no. 6, Article ID 063004, 16 pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>67 </label>S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Future evolution and finite-time singularities in FR gravity unifying<lb/> inflation and cosmic acceleration, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 78, no. 4, Article ID 046006, 12 pages, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>68 </label>K. Bamba, S. Nojiri, and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; The future of the universe in modified gravitational<lb/> theories: approaching a finite-time future singularity, &quot; Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics,<lb/> vol. 2008, no. 10, p. 45, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>69 </label>K. Bamba, S. D. Odintsov, L. Sebastiani, and S. Zerbini, &quot; Finite-time future singularities in modified<lb/> Gauss–Bonnet and FR,G gravity and singularity avoidance, &quot; The European Physical Journal C, vol.<lb/> 67, no. 1-2, pp. 295–310, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>70 </label>H. Stefancic, &quot; Generalized phantom energy, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 586, pp. 5–10, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>71 </label>P. J. Steinhardt and N. Turok, &quot; Cosmic evolution in a cyclic universe, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 65, no.<lb/> 12, Article ID 126003, 20 pages, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>72 </label>J. Khoury, B. A. Ovrut, P. J. Steinhardt, and N. Turok, &quot; Density perturbations in the ekpyrotic<lb/> scenario, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 66, no. 4, Article ID 046005, 14 pages, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>73 </label>P. J. Steinhardt and N. Turok, &quot; The cyclic universe: an informal introduction, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol.<lb/> 124, pp. 38–49, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>74 </label>P. J. Steinhardt and N. Turok, &quot; A cyclic model of the universe, &quot; Science, vol. 296, no. 5572, pp. 1436–<lb/> 1439, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>75 </label>J. Khoury, P. J. Steinhardt, and N. Turok, &quot; Designing cyclic universe models, &quot; Physical Review Letters,<lb/> vol. 92, no. 3, Article ID 031302, 4 pages, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>76 </label>P. J. Steinhardt and N. Turok, &quot; Why the cosmological constant is small and positive, &quot; Science, vol.<lb/> 312, no. 5777, pp. 1180–1183, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>77 </label>K. Saaidi, H. Sheikhahmadi, and A. H. Mohammadi, &quot; Interacting new agegraphic dark energy in a<lb/> cyclic universe, &quot; Astrophysics and Space Science, vol. 338, no. 2, pp. 355–361, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>78 </label>S. Nojiri, S. D. Odintsov, and D. Saez-Gomez, &quot; Cyclic, ekpyrotic and little rip universe in modified<lb/> gravity, &quot; submitted to High Energy Physics—Theory, http://arxiv.org/abs/1108.0767.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>79 </label>Y. F. Cai and E. N. Saridakis, &quot; Non-singular cyclic cosmology without phantom menace, &quot; Journal of<lb/> Cosmology, vol. 17, pp. 7238–7254, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>80 </label>V. Sahni and A. Toporensky, &quot; Cosmological hysteresis and the cyclic universe, &quot; Physical Review D,<lb/> vol. 85, Article ID 123542, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>81 </label>D. Y. Chung, &quot; The cyclic universe, &quot; submitted to General Physics, http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/<lb/> physics/0105064v1.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>82 </label>J. Khoury, B. A. Ovrut, P. J. Steinhardt, and N. Turok, &quot; Ekpyrotic universe: colliding branes and the<lb/> origin of the hot big bang, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 64, no. 12, Article ID 123522, 24 pages, 2001.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>83</label> M. Nowakowski, J. C. Sanabria, and A. Garcia, &quot; Gravitational equilibrium in the presence of a<lb/> positive cosmological constant, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 66, Article ID 023003, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>84 </label>R. Y. Donagi, J. Khoury, B. A. Ovrut, P. J. Steinhardt, and N. Turok, &quot; Visible branes with negative<lb/> tension in heterotic m-theory, &quot; Journal of High Energy Physics, vol. 2001, no. 11, p. 41, 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>85 </label>J. Khoury, B. A. Ovrut, P. J. Steinhardt, and N. Turok, &quot; Density perturbations in the ekpyrotic<lb/> scenario, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 66, no. 4, Article ID 046005, 14 pages, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>86 </label>D. N. Page, &quot; A fractal set of perpetually bouncing universe? &quot; Classical and Quantum Gravity, vol. 1,<lb/> no. 4, p. 417, 1984.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>87 </label>P. Peter and N. Pinto-Neto, &quot; Has the universe always expanded? &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 65, Article<lb/> ID 023513, 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>88 </label>P. Peter and and N. Pinto-Neto, &quot; Primordial perturbations in a nonsingular bouncing universe<lb/> model, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 66, no. 6, Article ID 063509, 12 pages, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>89 </label>Y. Shtanov and V. Sahni, &quot; Bouncing braneworlds, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 557, no. 1-2, pp. 1–6, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>90 </label>T. Biswas, A. Mazumdar, and W. Siegel, &quot; Bouncing universes in string-inspired gravity, &quot; Journal of<lb/> Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, vol. 2006, no. 3, p. 9, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>91 </label>Y. F. Cai, T. Qiu, Y. S. Piao, M. Li, and X. Zhang, &quot; Bouncing universe with quintom matter, &quot; Journal<lb/> of High Energy Physics, vol. 2007, no. 710, p. 71, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>92 </label>P. Creminelli and L. Senatore, &quot; A smooth bouncing cosmology with scale invariant spectrum, &quot;<lb/> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, vol. 2007, no. 711, p. 10, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>93 </label>M. Novello and S. E. P. Bergliaffa, &quot; Bouncing cosmologies, &quot; Physics Reports, vol. 463, no. 4, pp. 127–<lb/> 213, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>94 </label>Y. S. Piao, &quot; Proliferation in cycle, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 677, no. 1-2, pp. 1–5, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>95 </label>J. Zhang, Z. G. Liu, and Y. S. Piao, &quot; Amplification of curvature perturbations in cyclic cosmology, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review D, vol. 82, no. 12, Article ID 123505, 6 pages, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>96 </label>Y. S. Piao, &quot; Design of a cyclic multiverse, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 691, no. 5, pp. 225–229, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>97 </label>Z. G. Liu and Y. S. Piao, &quot; Scalar perturbations through cycles, &quot; submitted to General Relativity and<lb/> Quantum Cosmology, http://arxiv.org/abs/1201.1371.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>98 </label>R. Myrzakulov, &quot; FT gravity and k-essence, &quot; submitted to General Physics, http://arxiv.org/abs/<lb/> 1008.4486.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>99 </label>R. Myrzakulov, &quot; Dark energy in FR,T gravity, &quot; submitted to General Physics, http://arxiv<lb/> .org/abs/1205.5266.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>100 </label>R. Myrzakulov, &quot; FRW cosmology in FR,T gravity, &quot; submitted to General Relativity and Quantum<lb/> Cosmology, http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.1039.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>101</label> K. Esmakhanova, Y. Myrzakulov, G. Nugmanova, and R. Myrzakulov, &quot; A note on the relationship<lb/> between solutions of einstein, ramanujan and chazy equations, &quot; International Journal of Theoretical<lb/> Physics, vol. 51, no. 4, pp. 1204–1210, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>102</label> R. Myrzakulov, K. R. Yesmakhanova, N. A. Myrzakulov, K. K. Yerzhanov, G. N. Nugmanova,<lb/> and N. S. Serikbayaev, &quot; Some models of cyclic and knot universes, &quot; submitted to General Physics,<lb/> http://arxiv.org/abs/1201.4360.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>103 </label>R. Myrzakulov, &quot; Knot universes in bianchi type I cosmology, &quot; submitted to General Physics,<lb/> http://arxiv.org/abs/1204.1093.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>104 </label>G. W. Gibbons and M. Vyska, &quot; The application of Weierstrass elliptic functions to Schwarzschild null<lb/> geodesics, &quot; Classical and Quantum Gravity, vol. 29, no. 6, Article ID 065016, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>105 </label>I. Bochicchio, S. Capozziello, and E. Laserra, &quot; The Weierstrass criterion and the LemaˆLemaˆıtre-Tolman-<lb/>Bondi models with cosmological constant Λ, &quot; International Journal of Geometric Methods in Modern<lb/> Physics, vol. 8, no. 7, pp. 1653–1666, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>106 </label>B. G. Dimitrov, &quot; Cubic algebraic equations in gravity theory, parametrization with the Weierstrass<lb/> function and nonarithmetic theory of algebraic equations, &quot; Journal of Mathematical Physics, vol. 44,<lb/> no. 6, pp. 2542–2578, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>107 </label>S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, &quot; Inhomogeneous equation of state of the universe: phantom era, future<lb/> singularity, and crossing the phantom barrier, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 72, no. 2, Article ID 023003, 12<lb/> pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>108 </label>H. Stefancic, &quot; Expansion around the vacuum equation of state: sudden future singularities and<lb/> asymptotic behavior, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 71, no. 8, Article ID 084024, 9 pages, 2005.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label> 109</label> K. Bamba, K. Yesmakhanova, K. Yerzhanov, and R. Myrzakulov, &quot; Reconstruction of the equation<lb/> of state for the cyclic universes in homogeneous and isotropic cosmology, &quot; submitted to General<lb/> Relativity and Quantum Cosmology, http://arxiv.org/abs/1203.3401.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>110 </label>A. Y. Kamenshchik, U. Moschella, and V. Pasquier, &quot; An alternative to quintessence, &quot; Physics Letters<lb/> B, vol. 511, no. 2–4, pp. 265–268, 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>111 </label>M. C. Bento, O. Bertolami, and A. A. Sen, &quot; Generalized chaplygin gas, accelerated expansion, and<lb/> dark-energy-matter unification, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 66, no. 4, Article ID 043507, 5 pages, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>112 </label>H. B. Benaoum, &quot; Accelerated universe from modified chaplygin gas and tachyonic fluid, &quot; submitted<lb/> to High Energy Physics—Theory, http://arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/0205140.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>113 </label>K. Bamba, U. Debnath, K. Yesmakhanova, P. Tsyba, G. Nugmanova, and R. Myrzakulov, &quot; Periodic<lb/> generalizations of chaplygin gas type models for darkenergy, &quot; submitted to General Relativity and<lb/> Quantum Cosmology, http://arxiv.org/abs/1203.4226.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>114 </label>S. Kanno, M. Kimura, J. Soda, and S. Yokoyama, &quot; Anisotropic inflation from vector impurity, &quot; Journal<lb/> of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, vol. 2008, p. 34, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>115 </label>M. A. Watanabe, S. Kanno, and J. Soda, &quot; Inflationary universe with anisotropic hair, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 102, no. 19, Article ID 191302, 4 pages, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>116 </label>J. D&apos;Ambroise, &quot; Applications of elliptic and theta functions to Friedmann-Robertson-Lemaitre-<lb/>Walker cosmology with cosmological constant, &quot; submitted to General Relativity and Quantum<lb/> Cosmology, http://arxiv.org/abs/0908.2481.<lb/></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

