<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>References<lb/>
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> J. Beringer, J. F. Arguin, R. M. Barnett et al., &quot; Review of particle<lb/> physics, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 86, Article ID 010001, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> G. Bellini, L. Ludhova, G. Ranucci, and F. L. Villante, &quot; Neutrino<lb/> oscillations, &quot; Advances in High Energy Physics, vol. 2014, Article<lb/> ID 191960, 28 pages, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> E. Majorana, &quot; Teoria simmetrica dell&apos; elettrone e del positrone, &quot;<lb/> Il Nuovo Cimento, vol. 14, no. 4, pp. 171–184, 1937.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> F. T. Avignone, S. R. Elliott, and J. Engel, &quot; Double beta decay,<lb/> Majorana neutrinos, and neutrino mass, &quot; Reviews of Modern<lb/> Physics, vol. 80, p. 481, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> S. M. Bilenky and C. Giunti, &quot; Neutrinoless double-beta decay.<lb/> A brief review, &quot; Modern Physics Letters A, vol. 27, Article ID<lb/> 1230015, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> H. V. Klapdor-Kleingrothaus, I. V. Krivosheina, A. Dietz, and<lb/> O. Chkvorets, &quot; Search for neutrinoless double beta decay with<lb/> enriched<lb/> 76 Ge in Gran Sasso 1990–2003, &quot; Physics Letters B:<lb/> Nuclear, Elementary Particle and High-Energy Physics, vol. 586,<lb/> no. 3-4, pp. 198–212, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label> H. V. Klapdor-Kleingrothaus and I. V. Krivosheina, &quot; The evi-<lb/>dence for the observation of 0]í µí»½í µí»½ decay: the identification of<lb/> 0]í µí»½í µí»½ events from the full spectra, &quot; Modern Physics Letters A,<lb/> vol. 21, no. 20, pp. 1547–1566, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> M. Auger, D. J. Auty, P. S. Barbeau et al., &quot; Search for neutrinoless<lb/> double-beta decay in<lb/> 136 Xe with EXO-200, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 109, Article ID 032505, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> A. Gando, Y. Gando, and H. Hanakago, &quot; Limit on Neutrinoless<lb/> í µí»½í µí»½ decay of<lb/> 136 Xe from the first phase of KamLAND-Zen and<lb/> comparison with the positive claim in<lb/> 76 Ge, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 110, Article ID 062502, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> M. Agostini, M. Allardt, E. Andreotti et al., &quot; Results on<lb/> neutrinoless double-í µí»½<lb/> 76 Ge decay of from phase I of the GERDA<lb/> experiment, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 111, Article ID 122503,<lb/> 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> C. Arnaboldi, F. T. Avignone III, and J. Beeman, &quot; CUORE: a<lb/> cryogenic underground observatory for rare events, &quot; Nuclear<lb/> Instruments and Methods in Physics Research A: Accelerators,<lb/> Spectrometers, Detectors and Associated Equipment, vol. 518, no.<lb/> 3, pp. 775–798, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> R. Ardito, C. Arnaboldi, D. R. Artusa, and CUORE Collabora-<lb/>tion, &quot; CUORE: a cryogenic underground observatory for rare<lb/> events, &quot; http://arxiv.org/abs/hepex/0501010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> E. Andreotti, C. Arnaboldi, F. T. Avignone et al., &quot;<lb/> 130 Te neu-<lb/>trinoless double-beta decay with CUORICINO, &quot; Astroparticle<lb/> Physics, vol. 34, no. 11, pp. 822–831, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> M. Redshaw, B. J. Mount, E. G. Myers, and F. T. Avignone III,<lb/> &quot; Masses of<lb/> 130 Te,<lb/> 130 Xe and double-beta-decay Q-value of<lb/> 130 Te, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review Letters, vol. 102, no. 21, Article ID 212502, 2009.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> N. D. Scielzo, S. Caldwell, and G. Savard, &quot; Double-í µí»½ decay Q<lb/> values of<lb/> 130 Te,<lb/> 128 Te, and<lb/> 120 Te, &quot; Physical Review C, vol. 80,<lb/> Article ID 025501, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> S. Rahaman, V.-V. Elomaa, T. Eronen et al., &quot; Double-beta decay<lb/> Q values of<lb/> 116 Cd and<lb/> 130 Te, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 703, no. 4,<lb/> pp. 412–416, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> M. A. Fehr, M. Rehkamper, and A. N. Halliday, &quot; Application of<lb/> MC-ICPMS to the precise determination of tellurium isotope<lb/> compositions in chondrites, iron meteorites and sulfides, &quot; Inter-<lb/>national Journal of Mass Spectrometry, vol. 232, no. 1, pp. 83–94,<lb/> 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> C. Arnaboldi, &quot; Production of high purity TeO 2 single crystals<lb/> for the study of neutrinoless double beta decay, &quot; Journal of<lb/> Crystal Growth, vol. 312, p. 2999, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> E. E. Haller, &quot; Advanced far-infrared detectors, &quot; Infrared Physics<lb/> &amp; Technology, vol. 35, pp. 127–146, 1994.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> D. McCammon, &quot; Semiconductor thermistors, &quot; Applied Physics,<lb/> vol. 99, pp. 35–61, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> E. Andreotti, C. Brofferio, L. Foggetta et al., &quot; Production,<lb/> characterization, and selection of the heating elements for<lb/> the response stabilization of the CUORE bolometers, &quot; Nuclear<lb/> Instruments and Methods in Physics Research A, vol. 664, pp.<lb/> 161–170, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> A. Alessandrello, C. Brofferio, C. Bucci et al., &quot; Methods for<lb/> response stabilization in bolome-ters for rare decays, &quot; Nuclear<lb/> Instruments and Methods in Physics Research A: Accelerators,<lb/> Spectrometers, Detectors and Associated Equipment, vol. 412, pp.<lb/> 454–464, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> F. Alessandria, R. Ardito, D. R. Artusa (CUORE Collaboration),<lb/> and CUORE Collaboration &quot; Sensitivity and discovery potential<lb/> of CUORE to neutrinoless double-beta decay, &quot; Submitted,<lb/> http://arxiv.org/abs/1109.0494.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> D. R. Artusa, F. T. Avignone III, O. Azzolini et al., &quot; Initial<lb/> performance of the CUORE-0 experiment, &quot; The European<lb/> Physical Journal C, vol. 74, article 2956, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> F. Alessandria, E. Andreotti, and R. Ardito, &quot; CUORE crys-<lb/>tal validation runs: results on radioactive contamination and<lb/> extrapolation to CUORE background, &quot; Astroparticle Physics,<lb/> vol. 35, pp. 839–849, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> M. Ambrosio, R. Antolini, G. Auriemma et al., &quot; Vertical muon<lb/> intensity measured with MACRO at the Gran Sasso laboratory, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review D, vol. 52, no. 7, pp. 3793–3802, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[27]</label> D. Mei and A. Hime, &quot; Muon-induced background study for<lb/> underground laboratories, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 73, no. 5,<lb/> Article ID 053004, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[28]</label> M. Selvi, &quot; Analysis of the seasonal modulation of the cosmic<lb/> muon flux in the LVD detector during 2001–2008, &quot; in Proceed-<lb/>ings of the 31st International Cosmic Ray Conference (ICRC &apos;09),<lb/> 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[29]</label> G. Bellini, J. Benziger, D. Bick et al., &quot; Cosmic-muon flux and<lb/> annual modulation in Borexino at 3800 m water-equivalent<lb/> depth, &quot; Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, vol. 2012,<lb/> article 015, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[30]</label> D. R. Artusa et al., &quot; Projected background budget of the CUORE<lb/> experiment, &quot; to be submitted.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[31]</label> F. Alessandria, R. Ardito, D. R. Artusa et al., &quot; Validation<lb/> of techniques to mitigate copper surface contamination in<lb/> CUORE, &quot; Astroparticle Physics, vol. 45, pp. 13–22, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[32]</label> A. Alessandrello, C. Arpesella, C. Brofferio et al., &quot; Measure-<lb/>ments of internal radioactive contamination in samples of<lb/> Roman lead to be used in experiments on rare events, &quot; Nuclear<lb/> Instruments and Methods in Physics Research B: Beam Interac-<lb/>tions with Materials and Atoms, vol. 142, no. 1-2, pp. 163–172,<lb/> 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[33]</label> E. Andreotti, C. Arnaboldi, F. T. Avignone III et al., &quot; Muon-<lb/>induced backgrounds in the CUORICINO experiment, &quot;<lb/> Astroparticle Physics, vol. 34, no. 1, pp. 18–24, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[34]</label> F. Bellini, C. Bucci, S. Capelli et al., &quot; Monte Carlo evaluation of<lb/> the external gamma, neutron and muon induced background<lb/> sources in the CUORE experiment, &quot; Astroparticle Physics, vol.<lb/> 33, no. 3, pp. 169–174, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[35]</label> D. R. Artusa et al., &quot; Validation of parylene coating technique<lb/> to suppress copper surface contamination in CUORE, &quot; to be<lb/> submitted.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[36]</label> C. Arnaboldi, D. R. Artusa, and F. T. Avignone III, &quot; Results from<lb/> a search for the 0]í µí»½í µí»½-decay of<lb/> 130 Te, &quot; Physical Review C, vol. 78,<lb/> Article ID 035502, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[37]</label> C. Arnaboldi, C. Bucci, S. Capelli et al., &quot; The front-end readout<lb/> for CUORICINO, an array of macro-bolometers and MIBETA,<lb/> an array of í µí¼-bolometers, &quot; Nuclear Instruments and Methods in<lb/> Physics Research A, vol. 520, no. 1–3, pp. 578–580, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[38]</label> C. Arnaboldi, M. Cariello, S. Di Domizio, A. Giachero, and G.<lb/> Pessina, &quot; A programmable multichannel antialiasing filter for<lb/> the CUORE experiment, &quot; Nuclear Instruments and Methods in<lb/> Physics Research A, vol. 617, pp. 327–328, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[39]</label> E. Gatti and P. F. Manfredi, &quot; Processing the signals from solid-<lb/>state detectors in elementary-particle physics, &quot; La Rivista del<lb/> Nuovo Cimento, vol. 9, no. 1, pp. 1–146, 1986.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[40]</label> M. Clemenza, C. Maiano, L. Pattavina, and E. Previtali, &quot; Radon-<lb/>induced surface contaminations in low background experi-<lb/>ments, &quot; The European Physical Journal C, vol. 71, article 1805,<lb/> 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[41]</label> A. Nucciotti, F. Alessandria, M. Ameri et al., &quot; Status of the<lb/> cryogen-free cryogenic system for the CUORE experiment, &quot;<lb/> Journal of Low Temperature Physics, vol. 167, no. 3-4, pp. 528–<lb/> 534, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[42]</label> E. Ferri, D. Bagliani, M. Biassotti et al., &quot; Preliminary results of<lb/> the MARE experiment, &quot; Journal of Low Temperature Physics,<lb/> vol. 176, no. 5-6, pp. 885–890, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[43]</label> K. Chodorow and M. Dirolf, MongoDB—The Definitive Guide:<lb/> Powerful and Scalable Data Storage, O&apos; Reilly, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[44]</label> R. Brun and F. Rademakers, &quot; ROOT: an object oriented<lb/> data analysis framework, &quot; Nuclear Instruments and Methods in<lb/> Physics Research A, vol. 389, no. 1-2, pp. 81–86, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[45]</label> C. Mancini-Terracciano and M. Vignati, &quot; Noise correlation<lb/> and decorrelation in arrays of bolometric detectors, &quot; Journal of<lb/> Instrumentation, vol. 7, Article ID P06013, 2012.<lb/></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

