<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> R. Aaij, C. A. Beteta, A. Adametz et al., &quot; First evidence for the<lb/> decay í µí°µ<lb/> 0<lb/> í µí± → í µí¼<lb/> + í µí¼<lb/> − , &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 110, no. 2,<lb/> Article ID 021801, 9 pages, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> B. B. Sirvanli, &quot; Lepton asymmetries for the í µí°µ í µí± → í µí»¾í µí±<lb/> + í µí±<lb/> − decay<lb/> in a family nonuniversal Z<lb/> í® í° model, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 89,<lb/> Article ID 095016, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> C. D. Lü and D. X. Zhang, &quot; í µí°µ í µí± (í µí°µ í µí± ) → í µí»¾VV, &quot; Physics Letters B,<lb/> vol. 381, no. 1–3, pp. 348–352, 1996.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> T. M. Aliev, A. ¨<lb/> Ozpineci, and M. Savc, &quot; Rare í µí°µ → VVí µí»¾ decay<lb/> in light cone QCD sum rule, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 393, no. 1-2,<lb/> pp. 143–148, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> Y. Fukuda, T. Hayakawa, E. Ichihara et al., &quot; Evidence for<lb/> oscillation of atmospheric neutrinos, &quot; Physical Review Letters,<lb/> vol. 81, no. 8, pp. 1562–1567, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> M. S. Alam, J. Kim, Z. Ling et al., &quot; First measurement of the<lb/> rate for the inclusive radiative penguin decay í µí± → í µí± í µí»¾, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 74, p. 2885, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label> D. Melikhov and N. Nikitin, &quot; Rare radiative leptonic decays<lb/> í µí°µ í µí±,í µí± → í µí±<lb/> + í µí±<lb/> − í µí»¾, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 70, Article ID 114028,<lb/> 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> Y. G. Aditya, K. J. Healey, and A. A. Petrov, &quot; Faking í µí°µ í µí± →<lb/> í µí¼<lb/> + í µí¼<lb/> − , &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 87, Article ID 074028, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> O. Cakir and B. Sirvanl, &quot; Rare í µí°µ í µí± → ] overline ] í µí»¾ decay<lb/> beyond the standard model, &quot; Acta Physica Polonica B, vol. 34,<lb/> pp. 2643–2650, 2003, http://arxiv.org/abs/hep-ph/0210019.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> B. Sirvanl and G. Turan, &quot; Rare í µí°µ í µí± → í µí»¾VV decay with polarized<lb/> photon and new physics effects, &quot; Modern Physics Letters A, vol.<lb/> 18, pp. 47–56, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> S. Rai Choudhury and N. Gaur, &quot; Supersymmetric effects in<lb/> í µí°µ í µí± → ℓ<lb/> + ℓ<lb/> − í µí»¾ decays, &quot; http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/hep-ph/0205076.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> G. Buchalla, A. J. Buras, and M. E. Lautenbacher, &quot; Weak decays<lb/> beyond leading logarithms, &quot; Reviews of Modern Physics, vol. 68,<lb/> no. 4, pp. 1125–1244, 1996.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> M. Misiak, &quot; The b → se<lb/> + e<lb/> − and b → sí µí»¾ decays with next-to-<lb/>leading logarithmic QCD-corrections, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol.<lb/> 393, no. 1-2, pp. 23–45, 1993.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> M. Misiak, &quot; Erratum, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol. 439, no. 1-2, pp.<lb/> 461–465, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> G. Buchalla and A. J. Buras, &quot; QCD corrections to rare K-and<lb/> B-decays for arbitrary top quark mass, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol.<lb/> 400, no. 1–3, pp. 225–239, 1993.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> C. H. Chen and H. Hatanaka, &quot; Nonuniversal Z<lb/> í® í° couplings in B<lb/> decays, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 73, Article ID 075003, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> V. Barger, L. Everett, J. Jiang, P. Langacker, T. Liu, and C. E.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>M. Wagner, &quot; Family nonuniversal í µí±(1)<lb/> í® í° gauge symmetries and<lb/> í µí± → í µí± transitions, &quot; Physics Letters D, vol. 80, Article ID 055008,<lb/> 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> T. M. Aliev and M. Savci, &quot; Lepton polarization effects in Λ í µí± →<lb/> Λℓ<lb/> + ℓ<lb/> − decay in family non-universal í µí±<lb/> í® í°<lb/> model, &quot; Physics Letters<lb/> B, vol. 718, no. 2, pp. 566–572, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> G. L. Lin and Y. P. Yao, &quot; Top quark mass dependence of the decay<lb/> í µí°µ í µí± → í µí»¾í µí»¾ in the standard electroweak model, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> D, vol. 42, pp. 2319–2323, 1990.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> G. Eilam, I. Halperin, and R. R. Mendel, &quot; Radiative decay í µí°µ →<lb/> í µí±]í µí»¾ in the light cone QCD approach, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 361,<lb/> no. 1–4, pp. 137–145, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> T. M. Aliev, A. ¨<lb/> Ozpineci, and M. Savc, &quot; Rare í µí°µ → ℓ<lb/> + ℓ<lb/> − í µí»¾ decay<lb/> and new physics effects, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 520, pp. 69–77,<lb/> 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> A. Buras and M. Münz, &quot; Effective Hamiltonian for í µí°µ →<lb/> í µí± í µí± í µí±<lb/> + í µí±<lb/> − beyond leading logarithms in the naive dimensional<lb/> regularization and &apos;t Hooft–Veltman schemes, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> D, vol. 52, article 186, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> C. H. Chen and C. Q. Geng, &quot; Study of Λ í µí± → ΛVV with<lb/> polarized baryons, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 63, Article ID<lb/> 054005, 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> G. Eilam, I. Halperin, and R. R. Mendel, &quot; Radiative decay í µí°µ →<lb/> í µí±Ví µí»¾ in the light cone QCD approach, &quot; Physics Letters, Section B:<lb/> Nuclear, Elementary Particle and High-Energy Physics, vol. 361,<lb/> no. 1–4, pp. 137–145, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> T. M. Aliev, A. Ozpineci, and M. Savci, &quot; í µí°µ í µí± → í µí±<lb/> + í µí±<lb/> − í µí»¾ decays in<lb/> light cone QCD, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 55, p. 7059, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> Q. Chang, X. Q. Li, and Y. D. Yang, &quot; A comprehensive analysis<lb/> of hadronic í µí± → í µí± transitions in a family non-universal í µí±<lb/> í® í°<lb/> model, &quot; Journal of Physics G, vol. 41, no. 10, Article ID 105002,<lb/> 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[27]</label> A. J. Buras and J. Girrbach, &quot; Left-handed Z<lb/> í® í° and Z FCNC quark<lb/> couplings facing new í µí± → í µí± í µí¼<lb/> + í µí¼<lb/> − data, &quot; Journal of High Energy<lb/> Physics, vol. 121, article 009, 2013.<lb/></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

