<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> L. Meitner and O. Hahn, &quot; ¨<lb/> Uber die Verteilung der Beta-<lb/>Strahlen auf die einzelnen Produkte des aktiven Niederschlags<lb/> des Thoriums, &quot; Physikalische Zeitschrift, vol. 13, p. 390, 1912.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> J. Chadwick, &quot; Distribution in intensity in the magnetic spec-<lb/>trum of the í µí»½-rays of radium, &quot; Verhandlungen der Deutschen<lb/> Physikalischen Gesellschaft, vol. 16, pp. 383–391, 1914.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> W. Pauli, &quot; Dear radioactive ladies and gentlemen, &quot; in Proceed-<lb/>ings of the Tubingen conference, December 1930.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> S. F. King, A. Merle, S. Morisi, Y. Shimizu, and M. Tanimoto,<lb/> &quot; Neutrino mass and mixing: from theory to experiment, &quot; New<lb/> Journal of Physics, vol. 16, Article ID 045018, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> S. M. Bilenky, &quot; Neutrino in standard model and beyond, &quot;<lb/> http://arxiv.org/abs/1501.00232.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> S. M. Bilenky and B. Pontecorvo, &quot; Lepton mixing and neutrino<lb/> oscillations, &quot; Physics Reports, vol. 41, no. 4, pp. 225–261, 1978.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7] S.</label> M. Bilenky and S. T. Petcov, &quot; Massive neutrinos and neutrino<lb/> oscillations, &quot; Reviews of Modern Physics, vol. 59, no. 3, pp. 671–<lb/> 754, 1987.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> S. M. Bilenky, C. Giunti, and W. Grimus, &quot; Phenomenology of<lb/> neutrino oscillations, &quot; Progress in Particle and Nuclear Physics,<lb/> vol. 43, no. 1, pp. 1–86, 1999.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> S. M. Bilenky, C. Giunti, J. A. Grifols, and E. Massó, &quot; Abso-<lb/>lute values of neutrino masses: status and prospects, &quot; Physics<lb/> Reports, vol. 379, no. 2, pp. 69–148, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> M. Gonzalez-Garcia and Y. Nir, &quot; Neutrino masses and mixing:<lb/> evidence and implications, &quot; Reviews of Modern Physics, vol. 75,<lb/> no. 2, pp. 345–402, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> M. Maltoni, T. Schwetz, M. Tórtola, and J. W. F. Valle, &quot; Status of<lb/> global fits to neutrino oscillations, &quot; New Journal of Physics, vol.<lb/> 6, p. 122, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> G. L. Fogli, E. Lisi, A. Marrone, and A. Palazzo, &quot; Global<lb/> analysis of three-flavor neutrino masses and mixings, &quot; Progress<lb/> in Particle and Nuclear Physics, vol. 57, no. 2, pp. 742–795, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> T. Yanagida, in Proceedings of the Workshop on the Baryon<lb/> Number of the Universe and Unified Theories, Tsukuba, Japan,<lb/> February 1979.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> P. Minkowski, &quot; í µí¼ → í µí±í µí»¾ at a rate of one out of 109 muon<lb/> decays? &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 67, no. 4, pp. 421–428, 1977.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> M. Gell-Mann, P. Ramond, and R. Slansky, Supergravity, North-<lb/>Holland, Amsterdam, The Netherlands, 1979.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> R. N. Mohapatra and G. Senjanovi´Senjanovi´c, &quot; Neutrino mass and<lb/> spontaneous parity nonconservation, &quot; Physical Review Letters,<lb/> vol. 44, no. 14, pp. 912–915, 1980.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> M. Kobayashi and T. Maskawa, &quot; CP-violation in the renormaliz-<lb/>able theory of weak interaction, &quot; Progress of Theoretical Physics,<lb/> vol. 49, no. 2, pp. 652–657, 1973.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> R. Davis, D. S. Harmer, and K. C. Hoffman, &quot; Search for<lb/> neutrinos from the sun, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 20, no. 21,<lb/> pp. 1205–1209, 1968.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> S. P. Mikheyev and A. Y. Smirnov, &quot; Resonant amplification<lb/> of ] oscillations in matter and solar-neutrino spectroscopy, &quot; Il<lb/> Nuovo Cimento C, vol. 9, no. 1, pp. 17–26, 1986.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> L. Wolfenstein, &quot; Neutrino oscillations in matter, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D, vol. 17, no. 9, pp. 2369–2374, 1978.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> V. Gribov and B. Pontecorvo, &quot; Neutrino astronomy and lepton<lb/> charge, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 28, no. 7, pp. 493–496, 1969.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> Y. Fukuda, T. Hayakawaa, E. Ichiharaa et al., &quot; Evidence for<lb/> oscillation of atmospheric neutrinos, &quot; Physical Review Letters,<lb/> vol. 81, no. 8, pp. 1562–1567, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> Y. Fukuda, T. Hayakawa, E. Ichihara et al., &quot; Study of the<lb/> atmospheric neutrino ux in the multi-GeV energy range, &quot;<lb/> Physics Letters B, vol. 436, pp. 33–41, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> Q. R. Ahmad, R. C. Allen, T. C. Andersen et al., &quot; Measurement<lb/> of the rate of ] í µí± + í µí± → í µí± + í µí± + í µí±<lb/> − interactions produced by<lb/> 8 B<lb/> solar neutrinos at the sudbury neutrino observatory, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 87, no. 7, Article ID 071301, 6 pages, 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> Q. R. Ahmad, R. C. Allen, T. C. Andersen et al., &quot; Direct evidence<lb/> for neutrino flavor transformation from neutral-current inter-<lb/>actions in the sudbury neutrino observatory, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 89, Article ID 011301, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> K. Eguchi, S. Enomoto, K. Furuno et al., &quot; First results from<lb/> KamLAND: evidence for reactor antineutrino disappearance, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review Letters, vol. 90, Article ID 021802, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[27]</label> S. J. Parke, &quot; Nonadiabatic level crossing in resonant neutrino<lb/> oscillations, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 57, no. 10, pp. 1275–<lb/> 1278, 1986.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[28]</label> B. T. Cleveland, T. Daily, R. Davis Jr. et al., &quot; Measurement of<lb/> the solar electron neutrino flux with the homestake chlorine<lb/> detector, &quot; The Astrophysical Journal, vol. 496, p. 505, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[29]</label> J. N. Abdurashitov, E. P. Veretenkin, V. M. Vermul et al., &quot; Solar<lb/> neutrino flux measurements by the Soviet-American gallium<lb/> experiment (SAGE) for half the 22-year solar cycle, &quot; Journal of<lb/> Experimental and Theoretical Physics, vol. 95, no. 2, pp. 181–193,<lb/> 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[30]</label> J. N. Abdurashitov, &quot; Solar neutrino flux measurements by the<lb/> Soviet-American gallium experiment (SAGE) for half the 22-<lb/>year solar cycle, &quot; Zhurnal Eksperimental&apos;noi i Teoreticheskoi<lb/> Fiziki, vol. 122, pp. 211–226, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[31]</label> W. Hampel, J. Handt, G. Heusser et al., &quot; GALLEX solar neutrino<lb/> observations: results for GALLEX IV, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 447,<lb/> no. 1-2, pp. 127–133, 1999.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[32]</label> S. Fukuda, Y. Fukudaa, M. Ishitsuka et al., &quot; Determination of<lb/> solar neutrino oscillation parameters using 1496 days of Super-<lb/>Kamiokande-I data, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 539, no. 3-4, pp. 179–<lb/> 187, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[33]</label> C. Arpesella, G. Bellini, J. Benziger et al., &quot; First real time<lb/> detection of<lb/> 7 Be solar neutrinos by Borexino, &quot; Physics Letters B,<lb/> vol. 658, no. 4, pp. 101–108, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[34]</label> T. Araki, K. Eguchi, S. Enomoto et al., &quot; Measurement of<lb/> neutrino oscillation with KamLAND: evidence of spectral<lb/> distortion, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 94, no. 8, Article ID<lb/> 081801, 5 pages, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[35]</label> S. Abe, T. Ebihara, S. Enomoto et al., &quot; Precision measurement<lb/> of neutrino oscillation parameters with KamLAND, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 100, no. 22, Article ID 221803, 5 pages, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[36]</label> I. Shimizu, in Proceedings of the International Conference on<lb/> Topics in Astroparticle and Underground Physics (TAUP&apos;07),<lb/> 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[37]</label> M. C. Gonzalez-Garcia and M. Maltoni, &quot; Phenomenology with<lb/> massive neutrinos, &quot; Physics Reports, vol. 460, no. 1–3, pp. 1–129,<lb/> 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[38]</label> M. Maltoni, T. Schwetz, M. A. Tortola, and J. W. F. Valle, &quot; Status<lb/> of global fits to neutrino oscillations, &quot; New Journal of Physics,<lb/> vol. 6, no. 1, article 122, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[39]</label> S. Goswami, &quot; Neutrino oscillations and masses, &quot; International<lb/> Journal of Modern Physics A, vol. 21, pp. 1901–1913, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[40]</label> A. Bandyopadhyay, S. Choubey, S. Goswami, S. T. Petcov, and<lb/> D. P. Roy, &quot; Update of the solar neutrino oscillation analysis with<lb/> the 766 Ty KamLAND spectrum, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 608, no.<lb/> 1-2, pp. 115–129, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[41]</label> G. L. Fogli, E. Lisi, A. Marrone et al., &quot; Observables sensitive<lb/> to absolute neutrino masses: a reappraisal after WMAP 3-year<lb/> and first MINOS results, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 75, Article ID<lb/> 053001, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[42]</label> Y. Ashie, J. Hosaka, K. Ishihara et al., &quot; Measurement of atmo-<lb/>spheric neutrino oscillation parameters by Super-Kamiokande<lb/> I, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 71, Article ID 112005, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[43]</label> M. H. Ahn, S. Aoki, H. Bhang et al., &quot; Indications of neutrino<lb/> oscillation in a 250 km long-baseline experiment, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 90, no. 4, Article ID 041801, 5 pages, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[44]</label> E. Aliu, S. Andringa, S. Aoki et al., &quot; Evidence for muon neutrino<lb/> oscillation in an accelerator-based experiment, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 94, no. 8, Article ID 081802, p. 5, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[45]</label> D. G. Michael, P. Adamson, T. Alexopoulos et al., &quot; Observation<lb/> of muon neutrino disappearance with the MINOS detectors<lb/> in the NuMI neutrino beam, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 97,<lb/> Article ID 191801, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[46]</label> J. I. Crespo-Anadon, &quot; Double Chooz: latest results, &quot; http://arxiv.<lb/> org/abs/1412.3698.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[47]</label> Y. Abe, C. Aberle, J. C. dos Anjos et al., &quot; Reactor ^ e disappear-<lb/>ance in the double chooz experiment, &quot; Physical Review D, vol.<lb/> 86, no. 5, Article ID 052008, 21 pages, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[48]</label> Y. Abe, C. Aberle, J. C. dos Anjos et al., &quot; First measurement of<lb/> í µí¼13 from delayed neutron capture on hydrogen in the Double<lb/> Chooz experiment, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 723, no. 1–3, pp. 66–<lb/> 70, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[49]</label> Y. Abe, J. C. dos Anjose, J. C. Barriere et al., &quot; Background-<lb/>independent measurement of í µí¼ 13 in Double Chooz, &quot; Physical<lb/> Letters B, vol. 735, pp. 51–56, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[50]</label> Y. Abe, J. C. dos Anjos, J. C. Barriere et al., &quot; Ortho-positronium<lb/> observation in the Double Chooz Experiment, &quot; Journal of High<lb/> Energy Physics, vol. 2014, article 32, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[51]</label> F. P. An, A. B. Balantekin, H. R. Band et al., &quot; Spectral mea-<lb/>surement of electron antineutrino oscillation amplitude and<lb/> frequency at Daya Bay, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 112, Article<lb/> ID 061801, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[52]</label> P. Adamson, I. Anghel, C. Backhouse et al., &quot; Electron neutrino<lb/> and antineutrino appearance in the full MINOS data sample, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review Letters, vol. 110, no. 17, Article ID 171801, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[53]</label> K. Abe, J. Adam, H. Aihara et al., &quot; Observation of electron<lb/> neutrino appearance in a muon neutrino beam, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 112, Article ID 061802, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[54]</label> M. C. Gonzalez-Garcia, M. Maltoni, and T. Schwetz, &quot; Updated<lb/> fit to three neutrino mixing: status of leptonic CP violation, &quot;<lb/> Journal of High Energy Physics, vol. 2014, article 52, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[55]</label> N. Cabibbo, &quot; Unitary symmetry and leptonic decays, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 10, pp. 531–533, 1963.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[56]</label> A. H. Guth and P. J. Steinhardt, &quot; The inflationary universe, &quot;<lb/> Scientific American, vol. 250, no. 5, pp. 90–102, 1984.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[57]</label> L. Fromme, S. J. Huber, and M. Seniuch, &quot; Baryogenesis in the<lb/> two-Higgs doublet model, &quot; Journal of High Energy Physics, vol.<lb/> 2006, no. 11, p. 038, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[58]</label> K. Kajantie, M. Laine, K. Rummukainen, and M. E. Shaposh-<lb/>nikov, &quot; The electroweak phase transition: a non-perturbative<lb/> analysis, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol. 466, no. 1-2, pp. 189–258, 1996.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[59]</label> C. Jarlskog, &quot; Commutator of the quark mass matrices in the<lb/> standard electroweak model and a measure of maximal CP<lb/> nonconservation, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 55, no. 10, pp.<lb/> 1039–1042, 1985.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[60]</label> C. Amsler, M. Doser, M. Antonelli et al., &quot; Review of particle<lb/> physics, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 667, no. 1–5, pp. 1–6, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[61]</label> G. C. Branco, L. Lavoura, and M. N. Rebelo, &quot; Majorana neutri-<lb/>nos and CP violation in the leptonic sector, &quot; Physics Letters B,<lb/> vol. 180, no. 3, pp. 264–268, 1986.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[62]</label> G. C. Branco and L. Lavoura, &quot; On the addition of vector-like<lb/> quarks to the standard model, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol. 278, pp.<lb/> 738–754, 1986.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[63]</label> H. K. Dreiner, J. S. Kim, O. Lebedev, and M. Thormeier, &quot; Super-<lb/>symmetric Jarlskog invariants: the neutrino sector, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D: Particles, Fields, Gravitation and Cosmology, vol. 76,<lb/> no. 1, Article ID 015006, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[64]</label> A. D. Sakharov, &quot; Violation of CP invariance, C asymmetry, and<lb/> baryon asymmetry of the universe, &quot; ZhETF Pis ma Redaktsiiu,<lb/> vol. 5, p. 32, 1967.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[65]</label> C. D. Froggat and H. B. Nielsen, &quot; Hierarchy of quark masses,<lb/> cabibbo angles and CP violation, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol. 147, no.<lb/> 3-4, pp. 277–298, 1979.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[66]</label> C. D. Froggatt and H. B. Nielsen, &quot; Statistical analysis of quark<lb/> and lepton masses, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol. 164, pp. 114–140, 1980.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[67]</label> A. Antaramian, L. J. Hall, and A. Rašin, &quot; Flavor-changing<lb/> interactions mediated by scalars at the weak scale, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 69, no. 13, pp. 1871–1873, 1992.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[68]</label> S. F. King and C. Luhn, &quot; Neutrino mass and mixing with discrete<lb/> symmetry, &quot; Reports on Progress in Physics, vol. 76, no. 5, Article<lb/> ID 056201, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[69]</label> H. Fritzsch, &quot; Weak-interaction mixing in the six-quark theory, &quot;<lb/> Physics Letters B, vol. 73, no. 3, pp. 317–322, 1978.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[70]</label> H. Fritzsch, &quot; Quark masses and flavor mixing, &quot; Nuclear Physics<lb/> B, vol. 155, pp. 189–207, 1979.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[71]</label> S. Dimopoulos, &quot; Natural generation of fermion masses, &quot; Physics<lb/> Letters B, vol. 129, no. 6, pp. 417–428, 1983.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[72]</label> T. P. Chang and M. Sher, &quot; Mass-matrix ansatz and flavor<lb/> nonconservation in models with multiple Higgs doublets, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review D, vol. 35, no. 11, pp. 3484–3491, 1987.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[73]</label> H. Georgi and C. Jarlskog, &quot; A new lepton-quark mass relation in<lb/> a unified theory, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 86, no. 3-4, pp. 297–300,<lb/> 1979.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[74]</label> S. Dimopoulos, L. J. Hall, and S. Raby, &quot; Predictive framework for<lb/> fermion masses in supersymmetric theories, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 68, no. 13, pp. 1984–1987, 1992.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[75]</label> H. Harari, H. Haut, and J. Weyers, &quot; Quark masses and cabibbo<lb/> angles, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 78, no. 4, pp. 459–461, 1978.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[76]</label> H. Fritzsch and J. Plankl, &quot; Flavour democracy and the lepton-<lb/>quark hierarchy, &quot; Physics Letters, Section B: Nuclear, Elementary<lb/> Particle and High-Energy Physics, vol. 237, no. 3-4, pp. 451–456,<lb/> 1990.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[77]</label> P. H. Frampton, S. L. Glashow, and D. Marfatia, &quot; Zeroes of<lb/> the neutrino mass matrix, &quot; Physics Letters, Section B: Nuclear,<lb/> Elementary Particle and High-Energy Physics, vol. 536, no. 1-2,<lb/> pp. 79–82, 2002.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[78]</label> B. R. Desai, D. P. Roy, and A. R. Vaucher, &quot; Three-neutrino mass<lb/> matrices with two texture zeros, &quot; Modern Physics Letters A, vol.<lb/> 18, no. 20, pp. 1355–1365, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[79]</label> Z.-Z. Xing, &quot; Texture zeros and majorana phases of the neutrino<lb/> mass matrix, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 530, no. 1–4, pp. 159–166,<lb/> 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[80]</label> W. Guo and Z.-Z. Xing, &quot; Implications of the KamLAND<lb/> measurement on the lepton flavor mixing matrix and the<lb/> neutrino mass matrix, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 67, Article ID<lb/> 053002, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[81]</label> A. Merle and W. Rodejohann, &quot; Elements of the neutrino mass<lb/> matrix: allowed ranges and implications of texture zeros, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review D, vol. 73, no. 7, Article ID 073012, 11 pages,<lb/> 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[82]</label> S. Dev and S. Kumar, &quot; Neutrino parameter space for a vanishing<lb/> ee element in the neutrino mass matrix, &quot; Modern Physics Letters<lb/> A, vol. 22, p. 1401, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[83]</label> M. Honda, S. Kaneko, and M. Tanimoto, &quot; Prediction of U e3 in<lb/> neutrino mass matrix with two zeros, &quot; Journal of High Energy<lb/> Physics, vol. 2003, no. 9, article 28, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[84]</label> S. Kaneko, H. Sawanaka, and M. Tanimoto, &quot; Hybrid textures<lb/> of neutrinos, &quot; Journal of High Energy Physics, vol. 2005, no. 8,<lb/> article 73, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[85]</label> M. Frigerio, S. Kaneko, E. Ma, and M. Tanimoto, &quot; Quaternion<lb/> family symmetry of quarks and leptons, &quot; Physical Review D, vol.<lb/> 71, Article ID 011901, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[86]</label> M. Frigerio and A. Y. Smirnov, &quot; Neutrino mass matrix: inverted<lb/> hierarchy and CP violation, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 67, Article<lb/> ID 013007, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[87]</label> G. C. Branco, R. González Felipe, F. R. Joaquim, and T.<lb/> Yanagida, &quot; Removing ambiguities in the neutrino mass matrix, &quot;<lb/> Physics Letters B, vol. 562, no. 3-4, pp. 265–272, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[88]</label> B. C. Chauhan, J. Pulido, and M. Picariello, &quot; Neutrino mass<lb/> matrices with vanishing determinant, &quot; Physical Review D—<lb/> Particles, Fields, Gravitation and Cosmology, vol. 73, no. 5,<lb/> Article ID 053003, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[89]</label> X.-G. He and A. Zee, &quot; Neutrino masses with a &apos;zero sum&apos;<lb/> condition: í µí± ] 1 + í µí± ] 2 + í µí± ] 3 = 0, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 68, no.<lb/> 3, Article ID 037302, p. 4, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[90]</label> S. N. Gupta and S. Rajpoot, Quark Mass Matrices and the Top<lb/> Quark Model, Wayne State University, September 1990.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[91]</label> S. N. Gupta and J. M. Johnson, &quot; Quark mixing and CP<lb/> violation, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 44, no. 7, pp. 2110–2113, 1991.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[92]</label> S. Rajpoot, &quot; Evading the top mass bound in the fritzsch scheme, &quot;<lb/> Modern Physics Letters A, vol. 7, no. 4, pp. 309–313, 1992.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[93]</label> H. Fritzsch and Z.-Z. Xing, &quot; A symmetry pattern of maximal CP<lb/> violation and a determination of the unitarity triangle, &quot; Physics<lb/> Letters B, vol. 353, pp. 114–118, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[94]</label> G. Ahuja, S. Kumar, M. Randhawa, M. Gupta, and S. Dev,<lb/> &quot; Texture 4 zero Fritzsch-like lepton mass matrices, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D: Particles, Fields, Gravitation and Cosmology, vol. 76,<lb/> no. 1, Article ID 013006, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[95]</label> P. H. Frampton, M. C. Oh, and T. Yoshikawa, &quot; Majorana mass<lb/> zeros from Higgs triplet vacuum expectation values without<lb/> a Majoron problem, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 66, Article ID<lb/> 033007, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[96]</label> W. Grimus and L. Lavoura, &quot; On a model with two zeros in the<lb/> neutrino mass matrix, &quot; Journal of Physics G: Nuclear and Particle<lb/> Physics, vol. 31, no. 7, pp. 693–702, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[97]</label> H. S. Goh, R. N. Mohapatra, and S.-P. Ng, &quot; Minimal supersym-<lb/>metric SO(10) model and predictions for neutrino mixings and<lb/> leptonic CP violation, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 68, no. 11, Article<lb/> ID 115008, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[98]</label> S. Kaneko, M. Katsumata, and M. Tanimoto, &quot; Leptogenesis<lb/> in neutrino textures with two zeros, &quot; Journal of High Energy<lb/> Physics, vol. 2003, article 025, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[99]</label> M. Hirsch, A. S. Joshipura, S. Kaneko, and J. W. F. Valle,<lb/> &quot; Predictive flavor symmetries of the neutrino mass matrix, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review Letters, vol. 99, no. 15, Article ID 151802, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[100]</label> S. Dev, S. Kumar, S. Verma, and S. Gupta, &quot; Phenomenological<lb/> implications of a class of neutrino mass matrices, &quot; Nuclear<lb/> Physics B, vol. 784, no. 1-2, pp. 103–117, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[101]</label> S. Dev, S. Kumar, S. Verma, and S. Gupta, &quot; Phenomenology of<lb/> two-texture zero neutrino mass matrices, &quot; Physical Review D,<lb/> vol. 76, no. 1, Article ID 013002, 15 pages, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[102]</label> I. de Medeiros, S. F. Varzielas, and G. G. Ross, &quot; Tri-bimaximal<lb/> neutrino mixing from discrete subgroups of SU(3) and SO(3)<lb/> family symmetry, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 644, no. 2-3, pp. 153–<lb/> 157, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[103]</label> A. A. Aguilar-Arevalo, C. E. Anderson, S. J. Brice et al., &quot; Event<lb/> excess in the MiniBooNE search for ] í µí¼ → ] í µí± Oscillations, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review Letters, vol. 105, Article ID 181801, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[104]</label> A. Aguilar, L. B. Auerbach, R. L. Burman et al., &quot; Evidence for<lb/> neutrino oscillations from the observation of ] í µí± appearance in<lb/> a ] í µí¼ beam, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 64, Article ID 112007, 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[105]</label> Z. Hou, R. Keisler, L. Knox, M. Millea, and C. Reichardt, &quot; How<lb/> massless neutrinos affect the cosmic microwave background<lb/> damping tail, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 87, no. 8, Article ID<lb/> 083008, 11 pages, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[106]</label> M. Lavedor and C. Guinti, &quot; Phenomenology of neutrino oscil-<lb/>lations and mixing, &quot; Acta Physica Polonica B, vol. 44, no. 11, pp.<lb/> 2323–2330, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[107]</label> S. M. Bilenky, S. Pascoli, and S. Petcov, &quot; Majorana neutrinos,<lb/> neutrino mass spectrum, CP violation, and neutrinoless double<lb/> í µí»½ decay. II. Mixing of four neutrinos, &quot; Physical Review D, vol.<lb/> 64, Article ID 113003, 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[108]</label> A. S. Riis and S. Hannestad, &quot; Detecting sterile neutrinos<lb/> with KATRIN like experiments, &quot; Journal of Cosmology and<lb/> Astroparticle Physics, vol. 2011, article 011, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[109]</label> J. A. Barrett and J. Formaggio, &quot; Resolving the reactor neutrino<lb/> anomaly with the KATRIN neutrino experiment, &quot; Physics Let-<lb/>ters B, vol. 706, no. 1, pp. 68–71, 2011.<lb/></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

