<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> The ALPHA Collaboration and A. E. Charman, &quot; Description<lb/> and first application of a new technique to measure the grav-<lb/>itational mass of antihydrogen, &quot; Nature Communications, vol.<lb/> 4, article 1785, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> AEGIS Collaboration and M. G. Giammarchi, &quot; AEGIS at CERN:<lb/> measuring antihydrogen fall, &quot; Few-Body Systems, vol. 54, no. 5-<lb/>6, pp. 779–782, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> P. Pérez and Y. Sacquin, &quot; The GBAR experiment: gravitational<lb/> behaviour of antihydrogen at rest, &quot; Classical and Quantum<lb/> Gravity, vol. 29, no. 18, Article ID 184008, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> K. Kirch and K. S. Khaw, &quot; Testing antimatter gravity with<lb/> muonium, &quot; International Journal of Modern Physics: Conference<lb/> Series, vol. 30, Article ID 1460258, 8 pages, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> D. B. Cassidy and S. D. Hogan, &quot; Atom control and gravity mea-<lb/>surements using Rydberg positronium, &quot; International Journal of<lb/> Modern Physics: Conference Series, vol. 30, Article ID 1460259,<lb/> 9 pages, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> M. M. Nieto and T. Goldman, &quot; The arguments against &quot; anti-<lb/>gravity &quot; and the gravitational acceleration of antimatter, &quot; Physics<lb/> Report, vol. 205, no. 5, pp. 221–281, 1991.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label> J. Scherk, &quot; Antigravity: a crazy idea? &quot; Physics Letters: B, vol. 88,<lb/> no. 3-4, pp. 265–267, 1979.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> G. Chardin and J.-M. Rax, &quot; CP violation. A matter of (anti)<lb/> gravity? &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 282, no. 1-2, pp. 256–262, 1992.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> G. Chardin, &quot; CP violation and antigravity (revisited), &quot; Nuclear<lb/> Physics, Section A, vol. 558, pp. 477–495, 1993.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> G. Chardin, &quot; Motivations for antigravity in general relativity, &quot;<lb/> Hyperfine Interactions, vol. 109, no. 1–4, pp. 83–94, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> V. A. Kostelecky and J. D. Tasson, &quot; Matter-gravity couplings and<lb/> Lorentz violation, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 83, no. 1, Article ID<lb/> 016013, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> M. L. Good, &quot; í µí°¾ 2 0 and the equivalence principle, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review, vol. 121, pp. 311–313, 1961.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> S. Pakvasa, W. A. Simmons, and T. J. Weiler, &quot; Test of equivalence<lb/> principle for neutrinos and antineutrinos, &quot; Physical Review D,<lb/> vol. 39, no. 6, pp. 1761–1763, 1989.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> A. Apostolakis, E. Aslanides, G. Backenstoss et al., &quot; Tests of<lb/> the equivalence principle with neutral kaons, &quot; Physics Letters B:<lb/> Nuclear, Elementary Particle and High-Energy Physics, vol. 452,<lb/> no. 3-4, pp. 425–433, 1999.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> G. Gabrielse, A. Khabbaz, D. S. Hall, C. Heimann, H. Kali-<lb/>nowsky, and W. Jhe, &quot; Precision mass spectroscopy of the<lb/> antiproton and proton using simultaneously trapped particles, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review Letters, vol. 82, no. 16, pp. 3198–3201, 1999.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> F. C. Witteborn and W. M. Fairbank, &quot; Experimental comparison<lb/> of the gravitational force on freely falling electrons and metallic<lb/> electrons, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 19, no. 18, pp. 1049–1052,<lb/> 1967.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> M. H. Holzscheiter, &quot; Constraints on gravitational properties<lb/> of antimatter from cyclotron-frequency measurements, &quot; Inter-<lb/>national Journal of Modern Physics: Conference Series, vol. 30,<lb/> Article ID 1460260, 9 pages, 2014.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> Antimatter and Gravity, International Journal of Modern<lb/> Physics: Conference Series, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> M. Abramowitz and I. A. Stegun, Handbook of Mathematical<lb/> Functions with Formulas, Graphs, and Mathematical Tables,<lb/> Wiley, New York, ny, usa, 1972.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> L. D. Landau, E. M. Lifshitz, J. B. Sykes, and J. S. Bell, Quantum<lb/> Mechanics: Non-Relativistic Theory, Royaume-Uni, Oxford, UK,<lb/> 1965.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> V. V. Nesvizhevsky, H. G. Börner, A. K. Petukhov et al.,<lb/> &quot; Quantum states of neutrons in the Earth&apos;s gravitational field, &quot;<lb/> Nature, vol. 415, no. 6869, pp. 297–299, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> G. Chardin, P. Grandemange, D. Lunney et al., &quot; Proposal to<lb/> measure the gravitational behaviour of antihydrogen at rest, &quot;<lb/> Tech. Rep. CERN-SPSC-2011-029. SPSC-P-342, CERN, Geneva,<lb/> Switzerland, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> J. Walz and T. W. Hänsch, &quot; A proposal to measure antimatter<lb/> gravity using ultracold antihydrogen atoms, &quot; General Relativity<lb/> and Gravitation, vol. 36, no. 3, pp. 561–570, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> J. P. Merrison, H. Bluhme, J. Chevallier et al., &quot; Hydrogen<lb/> formation by proton impact on positronium, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 78, no. 14, pp. 2728–2731, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> H. R. J. Walters and C. Starrett, &quot; Positron and positronium<lb/> scattering, &quot; Physica Status Solidi (C), vol. 4, no. 10, pp. 3429–<lb/> 3436, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> P. Comini and P.-A. Hervieux, &quot; í µí°»<lb/> + ion production from<lb/> collisions between antiprotons and excited positronium: cross<lb/> sections calculations in the framework of the GBAR experi-<lb/>ment, &quot; New Journal of Physics, vol. 15, no. 9, Article ID 095022,<lb/> 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[27]</label> L. Liszkay, C. Corbel, P. Pérez et al., &quot; Positronium reemission<lb/> yield from mesostructured silica films, &quot; Applied Physics Letters,<lb/> vol. 92, no. 6, Article ID 063114, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[28]</label> D. B. Cassidy, T. H. Hisakado, H. W. K. Tom, and A. P.<lb/> Mills, &quot; Photoemission of positronium from Si, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 107, no. 3, Article ID 033401, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[29]</label> N. Oshima, T. M. Kojima, M. Niigaki, A. Mohri, K. Komaki, and<lb/> Y. Yamazaki, &quot; New scheme for positron accumulation in ultra-<lb/>high vacuum, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 93, no. 19, Article<lb/> ID 195001, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[30]</label> P. Grandemange, Piegeage et accumulation de positons issus<lb/> d&apos;un faisceau pulse produit par un accelerateur pour I&apos; etude de<lb/> I&apos;interaction gravitationnelle de I&apos; antimatiere [Ph.D. thesis], Uni-<lb/>versite Paris Sud, Paris, France, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[31]</label> L. Hilico, J.-P. Karr, A. Douillet, P. Indelicato, S. Wolf, and F.<lb/> S. Kaler, &quot; Preparing single ultra-cold antihydrogen atoms for<lb/> free-fall in GBAR, &quot; International Journal of Modern Physics:<lb/> Conference Series, vol. 30, Article ID 1460269, 11 pages, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[32]</label> H. B. G. Casimir and D. Polder, &quot; Influence of retardation on the<lb/> London-van der Waals forces, &quot; Nature, vol. 158, no. 4022, pp.<lb/> 787–788, 1946.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[33]</label> H. B. G. Casimir, &quot; On the attraction between two perfectly<lb/> conducting plates, &quot; Proceedings of the Koninklijke Nederlandse<lb/> Akademie van Wetenschappen, vol. 51, p. 793, 1948.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[34]</label> H. Friedrich, G. Jacoby, and C. G. Meister, &quot; Quantum reflection<lb/> by Casimir-van der Waals potentials tails, &quot; Physical Review A,<lb/> vol. 65, no. 3 B, Article ID 032902, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[35]</label> A. Lambrecht, P. A. Maia Neto, and S. Reynaud, &quot; The Casimir<lb/> effect within scattering theory, &quot; New Journal of Physics, vol. 8,<lb/> article no. 243, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[36]</label> R. Messina, D. A. R. Dalvit, P. A. M. Neto, A. Lambrecht,<lb/> and S. Reynaud, &quot; Dispersive interactions between atoms and<lb/> nonplanar surfaces, &quot; Physical Review A, vol. 80, no. 2, Article<lb/> ID 022119, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[37]</label> G. Dufour, A. Gerardin, R. Guérout et al., &quot; Quantum reflection<lb/> of antihydrogen from the Casimir potential above matter slabs, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review A, vol. 87, no. 1, Article ID 012901, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[38]</label> M. V. Berry and K. E. Mount, &quot; Semiclassical approximations in<lb/> wave mechanics, &quot; Reports on Progress in Physics, vol. 35, no. 1,<lb/> article no. 306, pp. 315–397, 1972.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[39]</label> A. Y. Voronin, P. Froelich, and B. Zygelman, &quot; Interaction of<lb/> ultracold antihydrogen with a conducting wall, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> A, vol. 72, no. 6, Article ID 062903, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[40]</label> G. Dufour, R. Guerout, A. Lambrecht, V. V. Nesvizhevsky, S.<lb/> Reynaud, and A. Y. Voronin, &quot; Quantum reflection of antihydro-<lb/>gen from nanoporous media, &quot; Physical Review A, vol. 87, no. 2,<lb/> Article ID 022506, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[41]</label> G. Dufour, P. Debu, A. Lambrecht, V. V. Nesvizhevsky, S. Rey-<lb/>naud, and A. Y. Voronin, &quot; Shaping the distribution of vertical<lb/> velocities of antihydrogen in GBAR, &quot; European Physical Jour-<lb/>nal C, vol. 74, no. 1, article 2731, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[42]</label> V. V. Nesvizhevsky, H. Börner, A. M. Gagarski et al., &quot; Search<lb/> for quantum states of the neutron in a gravitational field:<lb/> gravitational levels, &quot; Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics<lb/> Research, Section A: Accelerators, Spectrometers, Detectors and<lb/> Associated Equipment, vol. 440, no. 3, pp. 754–759, 2000.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[43]</label> V. V. Nesvizhevsky, H. G. Börner, A. M. Gagarski et al.,<lb/> &quot; Measurement of quantum states of neutrons in the Earth&apos;s<lb/> gravitational field, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 68, no. 10, Article ID<lb/> 102002, 2003.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[44]</label> V. V. Nesvizhevsky, A. K. Petukhov, H. G. Börner et al., &quot; Study<lb/> of the neutron quantum states in the gravity field, &quot; European<lb/> Physical Journal C, vol. 40, no. 4, pp. 479–491, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[45]</label> A. Y. Voronin, H. Abele, S. Baeßler et al., &quot; Quantum motion<lb/> of a neutron in a waveguide in the gravitational field, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D, vol. 73, no. 4, Article ID 044029, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[46]</label> A. Y. Voronin, P. Froelich, and V. V. Nesvizhevsky, &quot; Gravita-<lb/>tional quantum states of Antihydrogen, &quot; Physical Review A:<lb/> Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Physics, vol. 83, no. 3, Article ID<lb/> 032903, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[47]</label> W. E. Lamb, &quot; Fine structure of the hydrogen atom. III, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review, vol. 85, no. 2, pp. 259–276, 1952.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[48]</label> L. P. Gor&apos;kov and I. E. Dzyaloshinskii, &quot; Contribution to the<lb/> theory of the Mott exciton in a strong magnetic field, &quot; Soviet<lb/> Physics—JETP, vol. 26, pp. 449–453, 1968.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[49]</label> Y. E. Lozovik and S. Y. Volkov, &quot; Hydrogen atom moving across<lb/> a magnetic field, &quot; Physical Review A: Atomic, Molecular, and<lb/> Optical Physics, vol. 70, no. 2, Article ID 023410, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[50]</label> A. Y. Voronin and P. Froelich, &quot; Quantum reflection of ultracold<lb/> antihydrogen from a solid surface, &quot; Journal of Physics B: Atomic,<lb/> Molecular and Optical Physics, vol. 38, no. 18, pp. L301–L308,<lb/> 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[51]</label> M. Kreuz, V. V. Nesvizhevsky, P. Schmidt-Wellenburg et al.,<lb/> &quot; A method to measure the resonance transitions between<lb/> the gravitationally bound quantum states of neutrons in the<lb/> GRANIT spectrometer, &quot; Nuclear Instruments and Methods in<lb/> Physics Research A: Accelerators, Spectrometers, Detectors and<lb/> Associated Equipment, vol. 611, no. 2-3, pp. 326–330, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[52]</label> A. P. Mills Jr., &quot; Positron moderation and remoderation tech-<lb/>niques for producing cold positron and positronium sources, &quot;<lb/> Hyperfine Interactions, vol. 44, no. 1–4, pp. 105–123, 1989.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[53]</label> H. A. Bethe and E. E. Salpeter, Quantum. Mechanics of One-And<lb/> Two-Electron Atoms, Dover, New York, NY, USA, 1957.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[54]</label> T. F. Gallagher, Rydberg Atoms, Cambridge University Press,<lb/> Cambridge, UK, 1994.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[55]</label> A. P. Mills Jr. and M. Leventhal, &quot; Can we measure the gravi-<lb/>tational free fall of cold Rydberg state positronium? &quot; Nuclear<lb/> Instruments and Methods in Physics Research, Section B: Beam<lb/> Interactions with Materials and Atoms, vol. 192, no. 1-2, pp. 102–<lb/> 106, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[56]</label> C. Seiler, S. D. Hogan, H. Schmutz, J. A. Agner, and F. Merkt,<lb/> &quot; Collisional and radiative processes in adiabatic deceleration,<lb/> deflection, and off-axis trapping of a Rydberg atom beam, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review Letters, vol. 106, no. 7, Article ID 073003, 2011.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[57]</label> A. C. L. Jones, T. H. Hisakado, H. J. Goldman, H. W. K. Tom,<lb/> A. P. Mills Jr., and D. B. Cassidy, &quot; Doppler-corrected Balmer<lb/> spectroscopy of Rydberg positronium, &quot; Physical Review A, vol.<lb/> 90, no. 1, Article ID 012503, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[58]</label> T. E. Wall, D. B. Cassidy, and S. D. Hogan, This has not yet<lb/> been demonstrated for positronium; the feasibility of doing so<lb/> is considered, to be published.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[59]</label> T. F. Gallagher, &quot; Rydberg atoms, &quot; Reports on Progress in Physics,<lb/> vol. 51, no. 2, pp. 143–188, 1988.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[60]</label> E. Vliegen and F. Merkt, &quot; Normal-incidence electrostatic ryd-<lb/>berg atom mirror, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 97, no. 3, Article<lb/> ID 033002, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[61]</label> S. D. Hogan and F. Merkt, &quot; Demonstration of three-dimensional<lb/> electrostatic trapping of state-selected rydberg atoms, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 100, no. 4, Article ID 043001, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[62]</label> T. J. Phillips, &quot; Antimatter gravity studies with interferometry, &quot;<lb/> Hyperfine Interactions, vol. 109, no. 1–4, pp. 357–365, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[63]</label> M. K. Oberthaler, &quot; Anti-matter wave interferometry with<lb/> positronium, &quot; Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics<lb/> Research, Section B: Beam Interactions with Materials and<lb/> Atoms, vol. 192, no. 1-2, pp. 129–134, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[64]</label> P. Crivelli, V. V. Nesvizhevsky, and A. Y. Voronin, &quot; Can we<lb/> observe the gravitational quantum states of Positronium?, &quot;<lb/> Advances in High Energy Physics. In press.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[65]</label> S. D. Hogan, C. Seiler, and F. Merkt, &quot; Rydberg-state-enabled<lb/> deceleration and trapping of cold molecules, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> Letters, vol. 103, no. 12, Article ID 123001, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[66]</label> D. B. Cassidy, P. Crivelli, T. H. Hisakado et al., &quot; Positronium<lb/> cooling in porous silica measured via Doppler spectroscopy, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review A: Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Physics, vol.<lb/> 81, no. 1, Article ID 012715, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[67]</label> P. Crivelli, U. Gendotti, A. Rubbia, L. Liszkay, P. Pérez, and C.<lb/> Corbel, &quot; Measurement of the orthopositronium confinement<lb/> energy in mesoporous thin films, &quot; Physical Review A—Atomic,<lb/> Molecular, and Optical Physics, vol. 81, no. 5, Article ID 052703,<lb/> 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[68]</label> C. Hugenschmidt, B. Löwe, J. Mayer et al., &quot; Unprecedented<lb/> intensity of a low-energy positron beam, &quot; Nuclear Instruments<lb/> and Methods in Physics Research A: Accelerators, Spectrometers,<lb/> Detectors and Associated Equipment, vol. 593, no. 3, pp. 616–618,<lb/> 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[69]</label> A. Kellerbauer, M. Amoretti, A. S. Belov et al., &quot; Proposed<lb/> antimatter gravity measurement with an antihydrogen beam, &quot;<lb/> Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research B: Beam<lb/> Interactions with Materials and Atoms, vol. 266, no. 3, pp. 351–<lb/> 356, 2008.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[70]</label> D. P. van der Werf, &quot; The GBAR experiment, &quot; International<lb/> Journal of Modern Physics: Conference Series, vol. 30, Article ID<lb/> 1460263, 2014.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[71]</label> A. I. Zhmoginov, A. E. Charman, R. Shalloo, J. Fajans, and<lb/> J. S. Wurtele, &quot; Nonlinear dynamics of anti-hydrogen in mag-<lb/>netostatic traps: implications for gravitational measurements, &quot;<lb/> Classical and Quantum Gravity, vol. 30, no. 20, Article ID<lb/> 205014, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[72]</label> I. Antoniadis, S. Baessler, M. Büchner et al., &quot; Short-range<lb/> fundamental forces, &quot; Comptes Rendus Physique, vol. 12, no. 8,<lb/> pp. 755–778, 2011.<lb/></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

