<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>[1]</label> G. B. Whitham, Linear and Non-Linear Waves, John Wiley &amp;<lb/> Sons, New York, NY, USA, 1974.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[2]</label> A. C. Scott, F. Y. F. Chu, and D. W. McLaughlin, &quot; The soliton: a<lb/> new concept in applied science, &quot; Proceedings of the IEEE, vol. 61,<lb/> no. 10, pp. 1443–1482, 1973.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[3]</label> R. Rajaraman and E. J. Weinberg, &quot; Internal symmetry and the<lb/> semiclassical method in quantum field theory, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> D, vol. 11, no. 10, pp. 2950–2966, 1975.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[4]</label> T. Vachaspati, Kinks and Domain Walls: An Introduction to<lb/> Classical and Quantum Solitons, Cambridge University Press,<lb/> Cambridge, UK, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[5]</label> M. K. Prasad and C. M. Sommerfield, &quot; Exact classical solution<lb/> for the &apos;t Hooft monopole and the Julia-Zee Dyon, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 35, no. 12, pp. 760–762, 1975.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[6]</label> E. B. Bolgomol&apos;nyi, &quot; The stability of classical solutions, &quot; Soviet<lb/> Journal of Nuclear Physics, vol. 24, pp. 449–454, 1976.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[7]</label> R. Rajaraman, Solitons and Instantons, North-Holland, Amster-<lb/>dam, The Netherlands, 1982.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[8]</label> A. Vilenkin and E. P. Shellard, Cosmic Strings and Other Top-<lb/>ological Defects, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK,<lb/> 1994.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[9]</label> S. Coleman, &quot; í µí±-balls, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol. 262, no. 2, pp. 263–<lb/> 283, 1985.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[10]</label> T. D. Lee and Y. Pang, &quot; Nontopological solitons, &quot; Physics Reports<lb/> A: Review Section of Physics Letters, vol. 221, no. 5-6, pp. 251–350,<lb/> 1992.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[11]</label> H. Arod´Arod´z, &quot; On expansion in the width for domain walls, &quot;<lb/> Nuclear Physics B, vol. 450, no. 1-2, pp. 174–188, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[12]</label> A. Strumia and N. Tetradis, &quot; A consistent calculation of bubble-<lb/>nucleation rates, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol. 542, no. 3, pp. 719–741,<lb/> 1999.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[13]</label> C. Csáki, J. Erlich, C. Grojean, and T. J. Hollowood, &quot; General<lb/> properties of the self-tuning domain wall approach to the<lb/> cosmological constant problem, &quot; Nuclear Physics B, vol. 584, no.<lb/> 1-2, pp. 359–386, 2000.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[14]</label> M. Gremm, &quot; Four-dimensional gravity on a thick domain wall, &quot;<lb/> Physics Letters B, vol. 478, no. 4, pp. 434–438, 2000.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[15]</label> A. de Souza Dutra and J. Amaro de Faria, &quot; Expanding the class<lb/> of general exact solutions for interacting two field kinks, &quot; Physics<lb/> Letters B, vol. 642, no. 3, pp. 274–278, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[16]</label> D. Bazeia, W. Freire, L. Losano, and R. F. Ribeiro, &quot; Topological<lb/> defects and the trial orbit method, &quot; Modern Physics Letters A,<lb/> vol. 17, no. 29, pp. 1945–1953, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[17]</label> A. Campos, &quot; Critical phenomena of thick branes in warped<lb/> spacetimes, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 88, no. 14, 4 pages,<lb/> 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[18]</label> A. de Souza Dutra, &quot; General solutions for some classes of<lb/> interacting two field kinks, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 626, no. 1–4,<lb/> pp. 249–255, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[19]</label> V. I. Afonso, D. Bazeia, and L. Losano, &quot; First-order formalism<lb/> for bent brane, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 634, no. 5-6, pp. 526–530,<lb/> 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[20]</label> M. Cvetič and H. H. Soleng, &quot; Supergravity domain walls, &quot;<lb/> Physics Reports A, vol. 282, no. 4, pp. 159–223, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[21]</label> L. J. Boya and J. Casahorran, &quot; Normal-mode diagonalization for<lb/> two-component topological kinks, &quot; Physical Review A, vol. 39,<lb/> no. 8, pp. 4298–4300, 1989.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[22]</label> D. Bazeia, M. J. dos Santos, and R. F. Ribeiro, &quot; Solitons in<lb/> systems of coupled scalar fields, &quot; Physics Letters A, vol. 208, no.<lb/> 1-2, pp. 84–88, 1995.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[23]</label> A. de Souza Dutra and R. A. C. Correa, &quot; Fluctuating solutions<lb/> for the evolution of domain walls, &quot; Physics Letters, Section B:<lb/> Nuclear, Elementary Particle and High-Energy Physics, vol. 679,<lb/> no. 2, pp. 138–143, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[24]</label> A. de Souza Dutra and R. A. C. Correa, &quot; Fermions bounded by<lb/> kinks of false vacuum models, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 693, no. 2,<lb/> pp. 188–197, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[25]</label> C. Adam, L. A. Ferreira, E. da Hora, A. Wereszczynski, and W. J.<lb/> Zakrzewski, &quot; Some aspects of self-duality and generalised BPS<lb/> theories, &quot; Journal of High Energy Physics, vol. 1308, article 62,<lb/> 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[26]</label> L. A. Ferreira and W. J. Zakrzewski, &quot; A Skyrme-like model with<lb/> an exact BPS bound, &quot; Journal of High Energy Physics, vol. 2013,<lb/> no. 9, article 97, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[27]</label> G. P. de Brito, R. A. C. Correa, and A. de Souza Dutra,<lb/> &quot; Analytical multikinks in smooth potentials, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> D: Particles, Fields, Gravitation and Cosmology, vol. 89, no. 6,<lb/> Article ID 065039, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[28]</label> A. A. Izquierdo, J. M. Guilarte, and N. G. de Almeida, &quot; Solitons<lb/> and entanglement in the double sine-Gordon model, &quot; Journal of<lb/> Physics B: Atomic, Molecular and Optical Physics, vol. 48, no. 1,<lb/> Article ID 015501, 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[29]</label> I. L. Bogolyubsky and V. G. Makhankov, &quot; Lifetime of pul-<lb/>sating solitons in certain classical models, &quot; Pis&apos;ma v ZhurnalZhurnaì<lb/> Eksperimental&apos;noi i Teoreticheskoi Fiziki, vol. 24, pp. 15–18, 1976.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[30]</label> M. Gleiser, &quot; Pseudostable bubbles, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 49,<lb/> no. 6, pp. 2978–2981, 1994.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[31]</label> M. Gleiser and J. Thorarinson, &quot; Class of nonperturbative config-<lb/>urations in Abelian-Higgs models: complexity from dynamical<lb/> symmetry breaking, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 79, no. 2, Article<lb/> ID 025016, 2009.<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>[32]</label> N. Graham, &quot; An electroweak oscillon, &quot; Physical Review Letters,<lb/> vol. 98, Article ID 101801, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[33]</label> E. W. Kolb and I. I. Tkachev, &quot; Nonlinear axion dynamics and<lb/> the formation of cosmological pseudosolitons, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> D, vol. 49, no. 10, pp. 5040–5051, 1994.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[34]</label> N. Graham and N. Stamatopoulos, &quot; Unnatural oscillon lifetimes<lb/> in an expanding background, &quot; Physics Letters, Section B: Nuclear,<lb/> Elementary Particle and High-Energy Physics, vol. 639, no. 5, pp.<lb/> 541–545, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[35]</label> E. J. Copeland, M. Gleiser, and H.-R. Müller, &quot; Oscillons: reso-<lb/>nant configurations during bubble collapse, &quot; Physical Review D,<lb/> vol. 52, no. 4, pp. 1920–1933, 1920.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[36]</label> M. A. Amin and D. Shirokoff, &quot; Flat-top oscillons in an expand-<lb/>ing universe, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 81, Article ID 085045, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[37]</label> H. Segur and M. D. Kruskal, &quot; Nonexistence of small-amplitude<lb/> breather solutions in í µí¼<lb/> 4 theory, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 58,<lb/> no. 8, pp. 747–750, 1987.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[38]</label> G. Fodor, P. Forgács, Z. Horváth, and M. Mezei, &quot; Radiation of<lb/> scalar oscillons in 2 and 3 dimensions, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol.<lb/> 674, no. 4-5, pp. 319–324, 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[39]</label> M. P. Hertzberg, &quot; Quantum radiation of oscillons, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D, vol. 82, no. 4, Article ID 045022, 15 pages, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[40]</label> M. Gleiser and R. C. Howell, &quot; Resonant nucleation, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 94, no. 15, Article ID 151601, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[41]</label> P. M. Saffin and A. Tranberg, &quot; Particle transfer in braneworld<lb/> collisions, &quot; Journal of High Energy Physics, vol. 2007, no. 8, article<lb/> 072, 2007.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[42]</label> T. Romanczukiewicz and Y. Shnir, &quot; Oscillon resonances and<lb/> creation of kinks in particle collisions, &quot; Physical Review Letters,<lb/> vol. 105, no. 8, Article ID 081601, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[43]</label> R. A. C. Correa and A. de Souza Dutra, &quot; Phantom oscillons, &quot;<lb/> http://arxiv.org/abs/1411.1795.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[44]</label> K. McQuighan and B. Sandstede, &quot; Oscillons in the planar<lb/> Ginzburg-Landau equation with 2:1 forcing, &quot; Nonlinearity, vol.<lb/> 27, no. 12, article 3073, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[45]</label> S.-Y. Zhou, E. J. Copeland, R. Easther, H. Finke, Z.-G. Mou,<lb/> and P. M. Saffin, &quot; Gravitational waves from oscillon preheating, &quot;<lb/> Journal of High Energy Physics, vol. 2013, article 26, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[46]</label> V. Achilleos, F. K. Diakonos, D. J. Frantzeskakis et al., &quot; Oscillons<lb/> and oscillating kinks in the Abelian-Higgs model, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D: Particles, Fields, Gravitation and Cosmology, vol. 88,<lb/> no. 4, Article ID 045015, 2013.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[47]</label> P. M. Saffin, P. Tognarell, and A. Tranberg, &quot; Oscillon lifetime in<lb/> the presence of quantum fluctuations, &quot; Journal of High Energy<lb/> Physics, vol. 2014, article 125, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[48]</label> F. K. Diakonos, G. C. Katsimiga, X. N. Maintas, and C. E.<lb/> Tsagkarakis, &quot; Symmetric solitonic excitations of the (1 + 1)-<lb/>dimensional Abelian-Higgs classical vacuum, &quot; Physical Review<lb/> E, vol. 91, no. 2, Article ID 023202, 7 pages, 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[49]</label> V. Kosteleck´Kosteleck´y and S. Samuel, &quot; Spontaneous breaking of Lorentz<lb/> symmetry in string theory, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 39, no. 2, pp.<lb/> 683–685, 1989.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[50]</label> D. Colladay and V. A. Kosteleck´Kosteleck´y, &quot; CPT violation and the<lb/> standard model, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 55, no. 11, pp. 6760–<lb/> 6774, 1997.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[51]</label> L. Maccione, S. Liberati, and G. Sigl, &quot; Ultrahigh-energy photons<lb/> as probes of lorentz symmetry violations in stringy space-time<lb/> foam models, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 105, no. 2, Article ID<lb/> 021101, 4 pages, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[52]</label> H. Belich, E. O. Silva, M. M. Ferreira Jr., and M. T. D.<lb/> Orlando, &quot; Aharonov-Bohm-Casher problem with a nonmini-<lb/>mal Lorentz-violating coupling, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 83, no.<lb/> 12, Article ID 125025, 8 pages, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[53]</label> H. Belich, M. M. Ferreira Jr., and J. A. Helayël-Neto, &quot; Dimen-<lb/>sional reduction of the Abelian Higgs Carroll-Field-Jackiw<lb/> model, &quot; The European Physical Journal C—Particles and Fields,<lb/> vol. 38, no. 4, pp. 511–519, 2005.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[54]</label> J. L. Boldo, J. A. Helayël-Neto, L. M. de Moraes, C. A. Sasaki,<lb/> and V. J. Vásquez Otoya, &quot; Graviton excitations and Lorentz-<lb/>violating gravity with cosmological constant, &quot; Physics Letters B,<lb/> vol. 689, no. 2-3, pp. 112–115, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[55]</label> V. A. Kosteleck´Kosteleck´y and M. Mewes, &quot; Neutrinos with Lorentz-<lb/>violating operators of arbitrary dimension, &quot; Physical Review D,<lb/> vol. 85, Article ID 096005, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[56]</label> A. de Souza Dutra, M. Hott, and F. A. Barone, &quot; Two field BPS<lb/> solutions for generalized Lorentz breaking models, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D, vol. 74, no. 8, Article ID 085030, 6 pages, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[57]</label> A. de Souza Dutra and R. A. C. Correa, &quot; Traveling solitons in<lb/> Lorentz and CPT breaking systems, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 83,<lb/> no. 10, Article ID 105007, 6 pages, 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[58]</label> R. A. C. Correa, R. da Rocha, and A. de Souza Dutra,<lb/> &quot; Information-entropic for travelling solitons in Lorentz and<lb/> CPT breaking systems, &quot; http://arxiv.org/abs/1501.02000.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[59]</label> R. Casana, M. M. Ferreira Jr., E. da Hora, and C. Miller,<lb/> &quot; Magnetic flux inversion in charged BPS vortices in a Lorentz-<lb/>violating Maxwell-Higgs framework, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 718,<lb/> no. 2, pp. 620–624, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[60]</label> F. Allmendinger, W. Heil, S. Karpuk et al., &quot; New limit on<lb/> Lorentz-invariance-and CPT-violating neutron spin interac-<lb/>tions using a free-spin-precession He3-Xe129 comagnetometer, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review Letters, vol. 112, no. 11, Article ID 110801, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[61]</label> L. Zhou and B.-Q. Ma, &quot; Lorentz violation of the photon sector<lb/> in field theory models, &quot; Advances in High Energy Physics, vol.<lb/> 2014, Article ID 374572, 8 pages, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[62]</label> R. Casana, M. M. Ferreira Jr., E. da Hora, and A. B. F. Neves,<lb/> &quot; Maxwell-Chern-Simons vortices in a CPT-odd Lorentz-<lb/>violating Higgs electrodynamics, &quot; The European Physical Jour-<lb/>nal C, vol. 74, no. 9, p. 3064, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[63]</label> J. I. Aranda, F. Ramírez-Zavaleta, D. A. Rosete, F. J. Tlachino, J. J.<lb/> Toscano, and E. S. Tututi, &quot; Effects of Lorentz violation through<lb/> the í µí»¾í µí± → í µí±] í µí± process in the standard model extension, &quot;<lb/> Journal of Physics G: Nuclear and Particle Physics, vol. 41, no.<lb/> 5, Article ID 055003, 2014.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[64]</label> F. Tamburini and M. Laveder, &quot; Apparent Lorentz violation<lb/> with superluminal Majorana-tachyonic neutrinos at OPERA? &quot;<lb/> Physica Scripta, vol. 85, no. 3, Article ID 035101, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[65]</label> J. Polchinski, &quot; Comment on &apos;Small Lorentz violations in quan-<lb/>tum gravity: do they lead to unacceptably large effects?&apos; , &quot; Clas-<lb/>sical and Quantum Gravity, vol. 29, Article ID 088001, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[66]</label> K. Bakke and H. Belich, &quot; On the influence of a Rashba-type<lb/> coupling induced by Lorentz-violating effects on a Landau<lb/> system for a neutral particle, &quot; Annals of Physics, vol. 354, pp. 1–9,<lb/> 2015.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[67]</label> A. Connes, M. R. Douglas, and A. Schwarz, &quot; Noncommutative<lb/> geometry and matrix theory, &quot; Journal of High Energy Physics,<lb/> vol. 1998, article 003, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[68] S.</label> M. Carroll, J. A. Harvey, V. A. Kosteleck´Kosteleck´y, C. D. Lane,<lb/> and T. Okamoto, &quot; Noncommutative field theory and Lorentz<lb/> violation, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 87, no. 14, 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[69]</label> G. T. Zatsepin and V. A. Kuzmin, &quot; Upper limit of the spectrum<lb/> of cosmic rays, &quot; Pis&apos;ma v Zhurnaì<lb/> Eksperimental&apos;noi i Teoretich-<lb/>eskoi Fiziki, vol. 4, p. 114, 1966.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[70]</label> M. Takeda, N. Hayashida, K. Honda et al., &quot; Extension of the<lb/> cosmic-ray energy spectrum beyond the predicted Greisen-<lb/>Zatsepin-Kuz&apos;min Cutoff, &quot; Physical Review Letters, vol. 81, no.<lb/> 6, pp. 1163–1166, 1998.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[71]</label> S. R. Coleman and S. L. Glashow, &quot; High-energy tests of Lorentz<lb/> invariance, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 59, no. 11, Article ID 116008,<lb/> 14 pages, 1999.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[72]</label> J. D. Bekenstein, &quot; Relativistic gravitation theory for the mod-<lb/>ified Newtonian dynamics paradigm, &quot; Physical Review D, vol.<lb/> 70, no. 8, Article ID 083509, 28 pages, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[73]</label> O. Bertolani, R. Lehnert, R. Potting, and A. Ribeiro, &quot; Cosmo-<lb/>logical acceleration, varying couplings, and Lorentz breaking, &quot;<lb/> Physical Review D, vol. 69, Article ID 083513, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[74]</label> O. Bertolami, &quot; Letter: ultra-high energy cosmic rays and sym-<lb/>metries of spacetime, &quot; General Relativity and Gravitation, vol.<lb/> 34, no. 5, pp. 707–713, 2002.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[75]</label> S. Kanno and J. Soda, &quot; Lorentz violating inflation, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review D, vol. 74, Article ID 063505, 2006.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[76]</label> M. A. Amin, R. Easther, and H. Finkel, &quot; Inflaton fragmentation<lb/> and oscillon formation in three dimensions, &quot; Journal of Cosmol-<lb/>ogy and Astroparticle Physics, vol. 2010, no. 12, article 001, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[77]</label> M. A. Amin, R. Easther, H. Finkel, R. Flauger, and M. P.<lb/> Hertzberg, &quot; Oscillons after inflation, &quot; Physical Review Letters,<lb/> vol. 108, no. 24, Article ID 241302, 4 pages, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[78]</label> V. A. Kosteleck´Kosteleck´y and R. Lehnert, &quot; Stability, causality, and Lor-<lb/>entz and CPT violation, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 63, no. 6, Article<lb/> ID 065008, 19 pages, 2001.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[79]</label> R. Potting, &quot; Källén-Lehmann representation for Lorentz-<lb/>violating field theory, &quot; Physical Review D, vol. 85, Article ID<lb/> 045033, 2012.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[80]</label> M. A. Anacleto, F. A. Brito, and E. Passos, &quot; Acoustic black holes<lb/> from abelian Higgs model with Lorentz symmetry breaking, &quot;<lb/> Physics Letters B, vol. 694, no. 2, pp. 149–157, 2010.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[81]</label> C. S. Gardner, J. M. Greene, M. D. Kruskal, and R. M. Miura,<lb/> &quot; Method for solving the Korteweg-deVries equation, &quot; Physical<lb/> Review Letters, vol. 19, no. 19, pp. 1095–1097, 1967.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[82]</label> M. Gleiser, &quot; í µí±-dimensional oscillating scalar field lumps and the<lb/> dimensionality of space, &quot; Physics Letters B, vol. 600, no. 1-2, pp.<lb/> 126–132, 2004.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>[83]</label> M. Gleiser, N. Graham, and N. Stamatopoulos, &quot; Generation of<lb/> coherent structures after cosmic inflation, &quot; Physical Review D,<lb/> vol. 83, Article ID 096010, 2011.<lb/></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

