<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Binggeli B., Sandage A., Tammann G., 1985, AJ, 90, 1681<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Binggeli B., Popescu C., Tammann G., 1993, A&amp;AS, 98, 275<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Boselli A., Gavazzi G., 1994, A&amp;A, 283, 12<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Boselli A., Tuffs R., Gavazzi G., Hippelein H., Pierini D., 1997,<lb/> A&amp;AS, 121, 507 (B97)<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Boselli A., Gavazzi G., Franzetti P., Pierini D., Scodeggio M.,<lb/> 1999, A&amp;AS (this issue) (Paper IV)<lb/></bibl> 
<bibl>de Jong R., van der Kruit P., 1994, A&amp;AS, 106, 451<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>de Vaucouleurs G., 1977, in &quot; Evolution of Galaxies and Stellar<lb/> Populations &quot; , eds. R. Larson &amp; B. Tinsley (New Haven:<lb/> Yale University Observatory), 43<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Elias J., Frogel J., Matthews K., Neugebauer G., 1982, AJ, 87,<lb/> 1029<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gavazzi G., Boselli A., 1996, Ap.Lett.&amp; Comm, 35, 1<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gavazzi G., Pierini D., Boselli A., Tuffs R., 1996c, A&amp;AS, 120,<lb/> 489 (Paper I)<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gavazzi G., Pierini D., Baffa C., Lisi F., Hunt L., Boselli, A.,<lb/> 1996b, A&amp;AS, 120, 521 (Paper II)<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gavazzi G., Pierini D., Boselli A., 1996a, A&amp;A, 312, 397<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gavazzi G., Carrasco L., Galli R., 1999, A&amp;AS, 136, 227<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gavazzi G., Franzetti P., Scodeggio M., Boselli A., Pierini D.,<lb/> 1999a, A&amp;AS (submitted) (Paper V)<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gezari D., Schmitz M., Pitts P., Mead J., 1993, Nasa Reference<lb/> Publication, 1294<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Hunt L., Lisi F., Testi L., Baffa C., Borelli S., Maiolino R.,<lb/> Moriondo G., Stanga R., 1996, A&amp;AS, 115, 181<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Hunt L. &amp; Mannucci F., 1998, Arcetri Technical Report N.<lb/> 2/98<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Landini M., Natta A., Salinari P., Oliva E., Moorwood A.,<lb/> 1984, A&amp;A, 134, 284<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Lisi F., Baffa C., Hunt L. 1993, SPIE, 1495, 594<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Lisi F., Baffa C., Bilotti V., et al., 1996, PASP, 108, 364<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Scodeggio M., Giovanelli R., Haynes M., 1998, AJ, 116, 2728<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Wainscoat R., Cowie L., 1992, AJ, 103, 332<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Zwicky F., Herzog E., Karpowicz M., Kowal C., Wild P., 1961-<lb/>1968, &quot; Catalogue of Galaxies and Clusters of Galaxies &quot; , 6<lb/> vol., Pasadena, C.I.T.<lb/> </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

