<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>S. P. Abney, D. A. McAllester, and F. Pereira. 1999. Re-<lb/>lating probabilistic grammars and automata. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of ACL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>A. Blum and T. Mitchell. 1998. Combining labeled<lb/> and unlabeled data with co-training. In Proceedings<lb/> of COLT.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>L. Breiman. 1996. Stacked regressions. Machine Learn-<lb/>ing, 24:49.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>E. Brill. 1993. A Corpus-Based Approach to Language<lb/> Learning. Ph.D. thesis, University of Pennsylvania.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>S. Buchholz and E. Marsi. 2006. CoNLL-X shared task<lb/> on multilingual dependency parsing. In Proceedings<lb/> of CoNLL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Y. J. Chu and T. H. Liu. 1965. On the shortest arbores-<lb/>cence of a directed graph. Science Sinica, 14:1396–<lb/> 1400.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>W. W. Cohen and V. Rocha de Carvalho. 2005. Stacked<lb/> sequential learning. In Proceedings of IJCAI.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>A. Culotta and J. Sorensen. 2004. Dependency tree ker-<lb/>nels for relation extraction. In Proceedings of ACL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Y. Ding and M. Palmer. 2005. Machine translation using<lb/> probabilistic synchronous dependency insertion gram-<lb/>mar. In Proceedings of ACL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>J. Edmonds. 1967. Optimum branchings. Journal of Re-<lb/>search of the National Bureau of Standards, 71B:233–<lb/> 240.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>J. Eisner and G. Satta. 1999. Efficient parsing for bilex-<lb/>ical context-free grammars and head automaton gram-<lb/>mars. In Proceedings of ACL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>J. Eisner. 1996. Three new probabilistic models for de-<lb/>pendency parsing: An exploration. In Proceedings of<lb/> COLING.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>J. Hall, J. Nivre, and J. Nilsson. 2006. Discriminative<lb/> classifiers for deterministic dependency parsing. In<lb/> Proceedings of ACL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Z. Kou and W. W. Cohen. 2007. Stacked graphical mod-<lb/>els for efficient inference in Markov random fields. In<lb/> Proceedings of SDM.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>J. Lafferty, A. McCallum, and F. Pereira. 2001. Con-<lb/>ditional random fields: Probabilistic models for seg-<lb/>menting and labeling sequence data. In Proceedings<lb/> of ICML.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>P. Liang, H. Daumé, and D. Klein. 2008. Structure com-<lb/>pilation: trading structure for features. In Proceedings<lb/> of ICML.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>R. McDonald and J. Nivre. 2007. Characterizing the<lb/> errors of data-driven dependency parsing models. In<lb/> Proceedings of EMNLP-CoNLL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>R. T. McDonald and F. C. N. Pereira. 2006. Online learn-<lb/>ing of approximate dependency parsing algorithms. In<lb/> Proceedings of EACL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>R. McDonald and G. Satta. 2007. On the complexity<lb/> of non-projective data-driven dependency parsing. In<lb/> Proceedings of IWPT.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>R. McDonald, K. Crammer, and F. Pereira. 2005a. On-<lb/>line large-margin training of dependency parsers. In<lb/> Proceedings of ACL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>R. T. McDonald, F. Pereira, K. Ribarov, and J. Ha-<lb/>jic. 2005b. Non-projective dependency parsing us-<lb/>ing spanning tree algorithms. In Proceedings of HLT-<lb/>EMNLP.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>R. McDonald, K. Lerman, and F. Pereira. 2006. Multi-<lb/>lingual dependency analysis with a two-stage discrim-<lb/>inative parser. In Proceedings CoNLL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>J. Nivre and R. McDonald. 2008. Integrating graph-<lb/>based and transition-based dependency parsers. In<lb/> Proceedings of ACL-HLT.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>J. Nivre, J. Hall, and J. Nilsson. 2004. Memory-based<lb/> dependency parsing. In Proceedings of CoNLL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>J. Nivre, J. Hall, J. Nilsson, G. EryiˇEryiˇgit, and S. Marinov.<lb/> 2006. Labeled pseudo-projective dependency pars-<lb/>ing with support vector machines. In Proceedings of<lb/> CoNLL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>A. Ratnaparkhi, S. Roukos, and R. T. Ward. 1994. A<lb/> maximum entropy model for parsing. In Proceedings<lb/> of ICSLP.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>S. Riedel and J. Clarke. 2006. Incremental integer linear<lb/> programming for non-projective dependency parsing.<lb/> In Proceedings of EMNLP.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>K. Sagae and A. Lavie. 2005. A classifier-based parser<lb/> with linear run-time complexity. In Proceedings of<lb/> IWPT.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>D. A. Smith and J. Eisner. 2008. Dependency parsing by<lb/> belief propagation. In Proceedings of EMNLP.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>I. Titov and J. Henderson. 2007. A latent variable model<lb/> for generative dependency parsing. In Proceedings of<lb/> IWPT.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>M. Wang, N. A. Smith, and T. Mitamura. 2007. What is<lb/> the Jeopardy model? A quasi-synchronous grammar<lb/> for QA. In Proceedings of EMNLP-CoNLL.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>D. Wolpert. 1992. Stacked generalization. Neural Net-<lb/>works, 5(2):241–260.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>H. Yamada and Y. Matsumoto. 2003. Statistical depen-<lb/>dency analysis with support vector machines. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of IWPT.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

