<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>James F. Allen. 1983. Maintaining knowledge about<lb/> temporal intervals. Communications of the ACM,<lb/> 26(11):832–843.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Javier Artiles, Qi Li, Taylor Cassidy, Suzanne Tamang,<lb/> and Heng Ji. 2011. CUNY BLENDER TAC-<lb/>KBP2011 Temporal Slot Filling System Description.<lb/> In Proceedings of Text Analysis Conference (TAC),<lb/> November.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Jonathan Berant, Ido Dagan, and Jacob Goldberger.<lb/> 2011. Global learning of typed entailment rules. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 49th Annual Meeting of the Asso-<lb/>ciation for Computational Linguistics: Human Lan-<lb/>guage Technologies, pages 610–619, Portland, Ore-<lb/>gon, USA, June. Association for Computational Lin-<lb/>guistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Amev Burman, Arun Jayapal, Sathish Kannan, Madhu<lb/> Kavilikatta, Ayman Alhelbawy, Leon Derczynski, and<lb/> Robert Gaizauskas. 2011. USFD at KBP 2011: Entity<lb/> Linking, Slot Filling and Temporal Bounding. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of Text Analysis Conference (TAC), Novem-<lb/>ber.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Lorna Byrne and John Dunnion. 2011. UCD IIRG at<lb/> TAC 2011. In Proceedings of Text Analysis Confer-<lb/>ence (TAC), November.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Nathanael Chambers and Dan Jurafsky. 2008. Jointly<lb/> combining implicit constraints improves temporal or-<lb/>dering. In Proceedings of the Conference on Empir-<lb/>ical Methods in Natural Language Processing, pages<lb/> 698–706. Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Angel X. Chang and Christopher D. Manning. 2012.<lb/> SUTIME: A library for recognizing and normalizing<lb/> time expressions. In 8th International Conference on<lb/> Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2012),<lb/> May.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Ming-Wei Chang, Dan Goldwasser, Dan Roth, and Vivek<lb/> Srikumar. 2010. Discriminative learning over con-<lb/>strained latent representations. In Human Language<lb/> Technologies: The 2010 Annual Conference of the<lb/> North American Chapter of the Association for Com-<lb/>putational Linguistics, pages 429–437. Association for<lb/> Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mark Craven and Johan Kumlien. 1999. Constructing<lb/> biological knowledge bases by extracting information<lb/> from text sources. In Proceedings of the Seventh Inter-<lb/>national Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molec-<lb/>ular Biology, pages 77–86. Heidelberg, Germany.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Marie-Catherine de Marneffe and Christopher D. Man-<lb/>ning. 2008. The Stanford typed dependencies repre-<lb/>sentation. In Proceedings of the COLING Workshop<lb/> on Cross-framework and Cross-domain Parser Evalu-<lb/>ation.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Jenny R. Finkel, Teg Grenager, and Christopher D. Man-<lb/>ning. 2005. Incorporating non-local information into<lb/> information extraction systems by Gibbs sampling. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 43rd Annual Meeting on Associ-<lb/>ation for Computational Linguistics, pages 363–370.<lb/> Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Guillermo Garrido, Bernardo Cabaleiro, Anselmo Pe nas,<lb/> Alvaro Rodrigo, and Damiano Spina. 2011. A distant<lb/> supervised learning system for the TAC-KBP Slot Fill-<lb/>ing and Temporal Slot Filling Tasks. In Proceedings of<lb/> Text Analysis Conference (TAC), November.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Heng Ji, Ralph Grishman, and Hoa Trang Dang. 2011.<lb/> Overview of the TAC 2011 Knowledge Base Popula-<lb/>tion track. In Proceedings of Text Analysis Conference<lb/> (TAC), November.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Dan Klein and Christopher D. Manning. 2003. Accurate<lb/> unlexicalized parsing. In Proceedings of the 41st An-<lb/>nual Meeting on Association for Computational Lin-<lb/>guistics, pages 423–430. Association for Computa-<lb/>tional Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Terry Koo, Alexander M. Rush, Michael Collins, Tommi<lb/> Jaakkola, and David Sontag. 2010. Dual decompo-<lb/>sition for parsing with non-projective head automata.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 2010 Conference on Empiri-<lb/>cal Methods in Natural Language Processing, pages<lb/> 1288–1298. Association for Computational Linguis-<lb/>tics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Heeyoung Lee, Yves Peirsman, Angel X. Chang,<lb/> Nathanael Chambers, Mihai Surdeanu, and Dan Juraf-<lb/>sky. 2011. Stanford&apos;s Multi-Pass Sieve Coreference<lb/> Resolution System at the CoNLL-2011 Shared Task.<lb/> In CoNLL 2011, page 28.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Xiao Ling and Daniel S. Weld. 2010. Temporal infor-<lb/>mation extraction. In Proceedings of the Twenty Fifth<lb/> National Conference on Artificial Intelligence.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Inderjeet Mani, Marc Verhagen, Ben Wellner, Chong Min<lb/> Lee, and James Pustejovsky. 2006. Machine learning<lb/> of temporal relations. In Proceedings of the 21st In-<lb/>ternational Conference on Computational Linguistics<lb/> and the 44th Annual Meeting of the Association for<lb/> Computational Linguistics, pages 753–760. Associa-<lb/>tion for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>André F. T. Martins, Noah A. Smith, and Eric P. Xing.<lb/> 2009. Concise integer linear programming formula-<lb/>tions for dependency parsing. In Proceedings of the<lb/> Joint Conference of the 47th Annual Meeting of the<lb/> ACL and the 4th International Joint Conference on<lb/> Natural Language Processing of the AFNLP, pages<lb/> 342–350. Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mike Mintz, Steven Bills, Rion Snow, and Dan Jurafsky.<lb/> 2009. Distant supervision for relation extraction with-<lb/>out labeled data. In Proceedings of the Joint Confer-<lb/>ence of the 47th Annual Meeting of the ACL and the 4th<lb/> International Joint Conference on Natural Language<lb/> Processing of the AFNLP, pages 1003–1011. Associa-<lb/>tion for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Sebastian Riedel and Andrew McCallum. 2011. Fast and<lb/> robust joint models for biomedical event extraction. In<lb/> Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods<lb/> in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP &apos;11), July.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Dan Roth and Wen-tau Yih. 2004. A linear program-<lb/>ming formulation for global inference in natural lan-<lb/>guage tasks. In Hwee Tou Ng and Ellen Riloff, editors,<lb/> HLT-NAACL 2004 Workshop: Eighth Conference on<lb/> Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL-<lb/>2004), pages 1–8, Boston, Massachusetts, USA, May<lb/> 6 -May 7. Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mihai Surdeanu, Sonal Gupta, John Bauer, David Mc-<lb/>Closky, Angel X. Chang, Valentin I. Spitkovsky, and<lb/> Christopher D. Manning. 2011. Stanford&apos;s Distantly-<lb/>Supervised Slot-Filling System. In Proceedings of<lb/> Text Analysis Conference (TAC), November.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Partha Pratim Talukdar, Derry Wijaya, and Tom Mitchell.<lb/> 2012. Coupled temporal scoping of relational facts. In<lb/> Proceedings of the Fifth ACM International Confer-<lb/>ence on Web Search and Data Mining, pages 73–82.<lb/> ACM.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Kristina Toutanova, Dan Klein, Christopher D. Manning,<lb/> and Yoram Singer. 2003. Feature-rich part-of-speech<lb/> tagging with a cyclic dependency network. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the 2003 Conference of the North Ameri-<lb/>can Chapter of the Association for Computational Lin-<lb/>guistics on Human Language Technology, pages 173–<lb/> 180. Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Kristina Toutanova, Aria Haghighi, and Christopher D.<lb/> Manning. 2008. A global joint model for semantic<lb/> role labeling. Computational Linguistics, 34(2):161–<lb/> 191.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Yafang Wang, Bing Yang, Lizhen Qu, Marc Spaniol, and<lb/> Gerhard Weikum. 2011. Harvesting facts from textual<lb/> web sources by constrained label propagation. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the 20th ACM International Conference on<lb/> Information and Knowledge Management, pages 837–<lb/> 846. ACM.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Katsumasa Yoshikawa, Sebastian Riedel, Yuji Mat-<lb/>sumoto, and Masayuki Asahara. 2009. Jointly iden-<lb/>tifying temporal relations with Markov Logic. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the Joint Conference of the 47th Annual<lb/> Meeting of the ACL and the 4th International Joint<lb/> Conference on Natural Language Processing of the<lb/> AFNLP, pages 405–413. Association for Computa-<lb/>tional Linguistics.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

