<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Barry J. Blake. 2001. Case. Cambridge University<lb/> Press, Cambridge, New York, 2nd edition.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Bernd Bohnet and Joakim Nivre. 2012. A Transition-<lb/>Based System for Joint Part-of-Speech Tagging and<lb/> Labeled Non-Projective Dependency Parsing. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the 2012 Joint Conference on Empirical<lb/> Methods in Natural Language Processing and Com-<lb/>putational Natural Language Learning, pages 1455–<lb/> 1465, Jeju, South Korea. Association for Computa-<lb/>tional Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Bernd Bohnet. 2010. Very high accuracy and fast depen-<lb/>dency parsing is not a contradiction. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 23rd International Conference on Computational<lb/> Linguistics, pages 89–97, Beijing, China. International<lb/> Committee on Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Sabine Brants, Stefanie Dipper, Silvia Hansen-Shirra,<lb/> Wolfgang Lezius, and George Smith. 2002. The<lb/> TIGER treebank. In Proceedings of the 1st Workshop<lb/> on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories, pages 24–41,<lb/> Sozopol, Bulgaria.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Joan Bresnan. 2001. Lexical-Functional Syntax. Black-<lb/>well Publishers.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Xavier Carreras, Isaac Chao, Llus Padr, and Muntsa Padr.<lb/> 2004. Freeling: An open-source suite of language<lb/> analyzers. In Proceedings of the 4th International<lb/> Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation<lb/> (LREC&apos;04), pages 239–242. European Language Re-<lb/>sources Association (ELRA).<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Grzegorz Chrupała, Georgiana Dinu, and Josef van<lb/> Genabith. 2008. Learning morphology with mor-<lb/>fette.<lb/> In Proceedings of the Sixth International<lb/> Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation<lb/> (LREC&apos;08), pages 2362–2367, Marrakech, Morocco.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>European Language Resources Association (ELRA).<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2008/.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Shay B. Cohen and Noah A. Smith. 2007. Joint morpho-<lb/>logical and syntactic disambiguation. In Proceedings<lb/> of the 2007 Joint Conference on Empirical Methods<lb/> in Natural Language Processing and Computational<lb/> Natural Language Learning, pages 208–217, Prague,<lb/> Czech Republic. Association for Computational Lin-<lb/>guistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Michael Collins. 2002. Discriminative training meth-<lb/>ods for hidden markov models: Theory and experi-<lb/>ments with perceptron algorithms. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 2002 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natu-<lb/>ral Language Processing, pages 1–8. Association for<lb/> Computational Linguistics, July.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Greville G. Corbett. 1991. Gender. Cambridge Text-<lb/>books in Linguistics. Cambridge University Press.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Greville G. Corbett. 2006. Agreement. Cambridge Text-<lb/>books in Linguistics. Cambridge University Press.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Michael A. Covington. 2001. A fundamental algorithm<lb/> for dependency parsing (with corrections). In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the 39th Annual ACM Southeast Confer-<lb/>ence, Athens, Gorgia. ACM.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Koby Crammer, Ofer Dekel, Shai Shalev-Shwartz, and<lb/> Yoram Singer. 2003. Online passive-aggressive algo-<lb/>rithms. In Proceedings of the 16th Annual Conference<lb/> on Neural Information Processing Systems, volume 7,<lb/> pages 1217–1224, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA.<lb/> MIT Press.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Richárd Farkas, Veronika Vincze, and Helmut Schmid.<lb/> 2012. Dependency parsing of hungarian: Baseline re-<lb/>sults and challenges. In Proceedings of the 13th Con-<lb/>ference of the European Chapter of the Association<lb/> for Computational Linguistics, pages 55–65, Avignon,<lb/> France. Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Yoav Goldberg and Michael Elhadad. 2010. Easy first<lb/> dependency parsing of modern Hebrew. In Proceed-<lb/>ings of the NAACL HLT 2010 First Workshop on Sta-<lb/>tistical Parsing of Morphologically-Rich Languages,<lb/> pages 103–107, Los Angeles, California, USA. Asso-<lb/>ciation for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Yoav Goldberg and Michael Elhadad. 2013. Word seg-<lb/>mentation, unknown-word resolution, and morpholog-<lb/>ical agreement in a hebrew parsing system. Computa-<lb/>tional Linguistics, 39(1):121–160.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Yoav Goldberg and Reut Tsarfaty. 2008. A single gener-<lb/>ative model for joint morphological segmentation and<lb/> syntactic parsing. In Proceedings of the 46th Annual<lb/> Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguis-<lb/>tics, pages 371–379, Columbus, Ohio. Association for<lb/> Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Jan Hajič. 2000. Morphological Tagging: Data vs. Dic-<lb/>tionaries. In Proceedings of the 6th ANLP Conference<lb/> / 1st NAACL Meeting, pages 94—101, Seattle, Wash-<lb/>ington. Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Jan Hajič. 2004. Disambiguation of Rich Inflection<lb/> (Computational Morphology of Czech). Nakladatel-<lb/>ství Karolinum, Prague, Czech Republic.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Jan Hajič, Jarmila Panevová, Eva Hajičová, Petr Sgall,<lb/> Petr Pajas, Jaň<lb/> Stěpánek, Jií Havelka, and Marie<lb/> Mikulová. 2006. Prague Dependency Treebank 2.0.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Jan Hajič, Massimiliano Ciaramita, Richard Johans-<lb/>son, Daisuke Kawahara, Maria Antònia Martí, Lluís<lb/> M` arquez, Adam Meyers, Joakim Nivre, Sebastian<lb/> Padó, Jan Stepánek, Pavel Stranák, Mihai Surdeanu,<lb/> Nianwen Xue, and Yi Zhang. 2009. The CoNLL-<lb/>2009 shared task: Syntactic and Semantic dependen-<lb/>cies in multiple languages. In Proceedings of the<lb/> 13th Conference on Computational Natural Language<lb/> Learning: Shared Task, pages 1–18, Boulder, Col-<lb/>orado, USA. Association for Computational Linguis-<lb/>tics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Dilek Z. Hakkani-Tür, Kemal Oflazer, and Gökhan Tür.<lb/> 2002. Statistical morphological disambiguation for<lb/> agglutinative languages. Computers and the Humani-<lb/>ties, 36(4):381–410.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Matt Hohensee and Emily M. Bender. 2012. Getting<lb/> more from morphology in multilingual dependency<lb/> parsing. In Proceedings of the 2012 Conference of the<lb/> North American Chapter of the Association for Com-<lb/>putational Linguistics: Human Language Technolo-<lb/>gies, pages 315–326, Montréal, Canada. Association<lb/> for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>John Lee, Jason Naradowsky, and David A. Smith. 2011.<lb/> A discriminative model for joint morphological disam-<lb/>biguation and dependency parsing. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 49th annual meeting of the Association for Compu-<lb/>tational Linguistics, pages 885–894, Portland, USA.<lb/> Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Yuval Marton, Nizar Habash, and Owen Rambow. 2013.<lb/> Dependency parsing of modern standard arabic with<lb/> lexical and inflectional features. Computational Lin-<lb/>guistics, 39(1):161–194.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Igor Melčuk. 2009. Dependency in linguistic descrip-<lb/>tion.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Robbert Prins. 2004. Beyond N in N-gram tagging. In<lb/> Leonoor Van Der Beek, Dmitriy Genzel, and Daniel<lb/> Midgley, editors, Proceedings of the ACL 2004 Student<lb/> Research Workshop, pages 61–66, Barcelona, Spain.<lb/> Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Anne Schiller. 1994. Dmor -user&apos;s guide. Technical<lb/> report, University of Stuttgart.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Helmut Schmid and Florian Laws. 2008. Estimation<lb/> of conditional probabilities with decision trees and an<lb/> application to fine-grained POS tagging. In Proceed-<lb/>ings of the 22nd International Conference on Compu-<lb/>tational Linguistics, pages 777–784, Morristown, NJ,<lb/> USA. Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Wolfgang Seeker and Jonas Kuhn. 2012. Making El-<lb/>lipses Explicit in Dependency Conversion for a Ger-<lb/>man Treebank. In Proceedings of the 8th Interna-<lb/>tional Conference on Language Resources and Eval-<lb/>uation, pages 3132–3139, Istanbul, Turkey. European<lb/> Language Resources Association (ELRA).<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Wolfgang Seeker and Jonas Kuhn. 2013. Morphologi-<lb/>cal and syntactic case in statistical dependency pars-<lb/>ing. Computational Linguistics, 39(1):23–55.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Noah A. Smith, David A. Smith, and Roy W. Tromble.<lb/> 2005. Context-based morphological disambiguation<lb/> with random fields. In Proceedings of Human Lan-<lb/>guage Technology Conference and Conference on<lb/> Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing,<lb/> pages 475–482, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada,<lb/> October. Association for Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Drahomíra &quot; Johanka &quot; Spoustová, Jan Hajič, Jan Raab,<lb/> and Miroslav Spousta. 2009. Semi-supervised train-<lb/>ing for the averaged perceptron POS tagger. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the 12th Conference of the European<lb/> Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguis-<lb/>tics, pages 763–771, Athens, Greece. Association for<lb/> Computational Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Viktor Trón, Péter Halácsy, Péter Rebrus, András Rung,<lb/> Péter Vajda, and Eszter Simon. 2006. Morphdb.hu:<lb/> Hungarian lexical database and morphological gram-<lb/>mar. In Proceedings of the 5th International Confer-<lb/>ence on Language Resources and Evaluation, pages<lb/> 1670–1673, Genoa, Italy.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Reut Tsarfaty and Khalil Sima&apos;an. 2010. Modeling mor-<lb/>phosyntactic agreement in constituency-based parsing<lb/> of Modern Hebrew. In Proceedings of the NAACL<lb/> HLT 2010 First Workshop on Statistical Parsing of<lb/> Morphologically-Rich Languages, pages 40–48, Los<lb/> Angeles, California, USA. Association for Computa-<lb/>tional Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Reut Tsarfaty, Djamé Seddah, Yoav Goldberg, Sandra<lb/> Kübler, Marie Candito, Jennifer Foster, Yannick Vers-<lb/>ley, Ines Rehbein, and Lamia Tounsi. 2010. Statistical<lb/> parsing of morphologically rich languages (SPMRL):<lb/> what, how and whither. In Proceedings of the NAACL<lb/> HLT 2010 First Workshop on Statistical Parsing of<lb/> Morphologically-Rich Languages, pages 1–12, Los<lb/> Angeles, California, USA. Association for Computa-<lb/>tional Linguistics.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Yannick Versley, Kathrin Beck, Erhard Hinrichs, and<lb/> Heike Telljohann. 2010. A syntax-first approach to<lb/> high-quality morphological analysis and lemma dis-<lb/>ambiguation for the tba-d/z treebank. In 9th Confer-<lb/>ence on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories (TLT9),<lb/> pages 233–244.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Veronika Vincze, Dóra Szauter, Attila Almási, György<lb/> Móra, Zoltán Alexin, and János Csirik. 2010. Hungar-<lb/>ian Dependency Treebank. In Proceedings of the 7th<lb/> Conference on International Language Resources and<lb/> Evaluation, pages 1855–1862, Valletta, Malta. Euro-<lb/>pean Language Resources Association (ELRA).<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Jan Votrubec. 2006. Morphological tagging based on<lb/> averaged perceptron. In WDS&apos;06 Proceedings of Con-<lb/>tributed Papers, pages 191–195, Praha, Czechia. Mat-<lb/>fyzpress, Charles University.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>János Zsibrita, Veronika Vincze, and Richárd Farkas.<lb/> 2013. magyarlanc 2.0: szintaktikai elemzéselemzés´elemzésés felgy-<lb/>orsított szófaji egyértelmsítés. In Attila Tanács and<lb/> Veronika Vincze, editors, IX. Magyar Számítógépes<lb/> Nyelvészeti Konferencia, pages 368–374, Szeged,<lb/> Hungary.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

