<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Jordi Atserias, Luís Villarejo, German Rigau, Eneko<lb/> Agirre, John Carroll, Bernardo Magnini, and Piek<lb/> 15 Only GermaNet is subject to a restricted license and can-<lb/>not be redistributed in UBY format.<lb/> 16 http://www.ukp.tu-darmstadt.de/data/uby<lb/> Vossen. 2004. The Meaning Multilingual Central<lb/> Repository. In Proceedings of the second interna-<lb/>tional WordNet Conference (GWC 2004), pages 23–<lb/> 30, Brno, Czech Republic.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Collin F. Baker and Christiane Fellbaum. 2009. Word-<lb/>Net and FrameNet as complementary resources for<lb/> annotation. In Proceedings of the Third Linguis-<lb/>tic Annotation Workshop, ACL-IJCNLP &apos;09, pages<lb/> 125–129, Suntec, Singapore.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Collin F. Baker, Charles J. Fillmore, and John B.<lb/> Lowe. 1998. The Berkeley FrameNet project. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 36th Annual Meeting of the As-<lb/>sociation for Computational Linguistics and 17th<lb/> International Conference on Computational Lin-<lb/>guistics (COLING-ACL&apos;98, pages 86–90, Montreal,<lb/> Canada.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Christian Bizer, Jens Lehmann, Georgi Kobilarov,<lb/> Sören Auer, Christian Becker, Richard Cyganiak,<lb/> and Sebastian Hellmann. 2009. DBpedia A Crys-<lb/>tallization Point for the Web of Data. Journal of<lb/> Web Semantics: Science, Services and Agents on the<lb/> World Wide Web, (7):154–165.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Daan Broeder, Marc Kemps-Snijders, Dieter Van Uyt-<lb/>vanck, Menzo Windhouwer, Peter Withers, Peter<lb/> Wittenburg, and Claus Zinn. 2010. A Data Cat-<lb/>egory Registry-and Component-based Metadata<lb/> Framework. In Proceedings of the 7th International<lb/> Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation<lb/> (LREC), pages 43–47, Valletta, Malta.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Paul Buitelaar, Philipp Cimiano, Peter Haase, and<lb/> Michael Sintek. 2009. Towards Linguistically<lb/> Grounded Ontologies.<lb/> In Lora Aroyo, Paolo<lb/> Traverso, Fabio Ciravegna, Philipp Cimiano, Tom<lb/> Heath, Eero Hyvönen, Riichiro Mizoguchi, Eyal<lb/> Oren, Marta Sabou, and Elena Simperl, editors, The<lb/> Semantic Web: Research and Applications, pages<lb/> 111–125, Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany. Springer.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gerard de Melo and Gerhard Weikum. 2009. Towards<lb/> a universal wordnet by learning from combined ev-<lb/>idence. In Proceedings of the 18th ACM conference<lb/> on Information and knowledge management (CIKM<lb/> &apos;09), CIKM &apos;09, pages 513–522, New York, NY,<lb/> USA. ACM.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Christiane Fellbaum. 1998. WordNet: An Electronic<lb/> Lexical Database. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA,<lb/> USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Charles J. Fillmore. 1982. Frame Semantics. In The<lb/> Linguistic Society of Korea, editor, Linguistics in<lb/> the Morning Calm, pages 111–137. Hanshin Pub-<lb/>lishing Company, Seoul, Korea.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gil Francopoulo, Nuria Bel, Monte George, Nico-<lb/>letta Calzolari, Monica Monachini, Mandy Pet, and<lb/> Claudia Soria. 2006. Lexical Markup Framework<lb/> (LMF). In Proceedings of the 5th International<lb/> Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation<lb/> (LREC), pages 233–236, Genoa, Italy.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mark Hall, Eibe Frank, Geoffrey Holmes, Bernhard<lb/> Pfahringer, Peter Reutemann, and Ian H. Witten.<lb/> 2009. The WEKA Data Mining Software: An<lb/> Update. ACM SIGKDD Explorations Newsletter,<lb/> 11(1):10–18.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Verena Henrich and Erhard Hinrichs. 2010. Standard-<lb/>izing wordnets in the ISO standard LMF: Wordnet-<lb/>LMF for GermaNet. In Proceedings of the 23rd In-<lb/>ternational Conference on Computational Linguis-<lb/>tics (COLING), pages 456–464, Beijing, China.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Richard Johansson and Pierre Nugues. 2007. Us-<lb/>ing WordNet to extend FrameNet coverage. In<lb/> Proceedings of the Workshop on Building Frame-<lb/>semantic Resources for Scandinavian and Baltic<lb/> Languages, at NODALIDA, pages 27–30, Tartu, Es-<lb/>tonia.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Karin Kipper, Anna Korhonen, Neville Ryant, and<lb/> Martha Palmer. 2008. A Large-scale Classification<lb/> of English Verbs. Language Resources and Evalu-<lb/>ation, 42:21–40.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Claudia Kunze and Lothar Lemnitzer. 2002. Ger-<lb/>maNet – representation, visualization, application.<lb/> In Proceedings of the Third International Con-<lb/>ference on Language Resources and Evaluation<lb/> (LREC), pages 1485–1491, Las Palmas, Canary Is-<lb/>lands, Spain.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Beth Levin. 1993. English Verb Classes and Alterna-<lb/>tions. The University of Chicago Press, Chicago,<lb/> IL, USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Michael Matuschek and Iryna Gurevych.<lb/> 2011.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Where the journey is headed: Collaboratively con-<lb/>structed multilingual Wiki-based resources. In<lb/> SFB 538: Mehrsprachigkeit, editor, Hamburger Ar-<lb/>beiten zur Mehrsprachigkeit, Hamburg, Germany.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>John McCrae, Dennis Spohr, and Philipp Cimiano.<lb/> 2011. Linking Lexical Resources and Ontologies<lb/> on the Semantic Web with Lemon. In The Seman-<lb/>tic Web: Research and Applications, volume 6643<lb/> of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pages 245–<lb/> 259. Springer, Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Clifton J. McFate and Kenneth D. Forbus. 2011.<lb/> NULEX: an open-license broad coverage lexicon.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 49th Annual Meeting of the<lb/> Association for Computational Linguistics: Human<lb/> Language Technologies: short papers -Volume 2,<lb/> HLT &apos;11, pages 363–367, Portland, OR, USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Christian M. Meyer and Iryna Gurevych. 2010. Worth<lb/> its Weight in Gold or Yet Another Resource —<lb/> A Comparative Study of Wiktionary, OpenThe-<lb/>saurus and GermaNet. In Alexander Gelbukh, ed-<lb/>itor, Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text<lb/> Processing: 11th International Conference, volume<lb/> 6008 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pages<lb/> 38–49. Berlin/Heidelberg: Springer, IasIas¸i, Romania.<lb/> Christian M. Meyer and Iryna Gurevych. 2011. What<lb/> Psycholinguists Know About Chemistry: Align-<lb/>ing Wiktionary and WordNet for Increased Domain<lb/> Coverage. In Proceedings of the 5th International<lb/> Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing<lb/> (IJCNLP), pages 883–892, Chiang Mai, Thailand.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Roberto Navigli and Simone Paolo Ponzetto. 2010a.<lb/> BabelNet: Building a Very Large Multilingual Se-<lb/>mantic Network. In Proceedings of the 48th Annual<lb/> Meeting of the Association for Computational Lin-<lb/>guistics, pages 216–225, Uppsala, Sweden, July.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Roberto Navigli and Simone Paolo Ponzetto. 2010b.<lb/> Knowledge-rich Word Sense Disambiguation Ri-<lb/>valing Supervised Systems. In Proceedings of the<lb/> 48th Annual Meeting of the Association for Com-<lb/>putational Linguistics, pages 1522–1531, Uppsala,<lb/> Sweden.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Roberto Navigli. 2006. Meaningful Clustering of<lb/> Senses Helps Boost Word Sense Disambiguation<lb/> Performance. In Proceedings of the 21st Inter-<lb/>national Conference on Computational Linguistics<lb/> and the 44th Annual Meeting of the Association for<lb/> Computational Linguistics (COLING-ACL), pages<lb/> 105–112, Sydney, Australia.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Elisabeth Niemann and Iryna Gurevych. 2011. The<lb/> People&apos;s Web meets Linguistic Knowledge: Auto-<lb/>matic Sense Alignment of Wikipedia and WordNet.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 9th International Conference<lb/> on Computational Semantics (IWCS), pages 205–<lb/> 214, Oxford, UK.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Muntsa Padró, Núria Bel, and Silvia Necsulescu.<lb/> 2011. Towards the Automatic Merging of Lexical<lb/> Resources: Automatic Mapping. In Proceedings of<lb/> the International Conference on Recent Advances<lb/> in Natural Language Processing (RANLP), pages<lb/> 296–301, Hissar, Bulgaria.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Martha Palmer. 2009. Semlink: Linking PropBank,<lb/> VerbNet and FrameNet. In Proceedings of the Gen-<lb/>erative Lexicon Conference (GenLex-09), pages 9–<lb/> 15, Pisa, Italy.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Sameer S. Pradhan, Eduard Hovy, Mitch Mar-<lb/>cus, Martha Palmer, Lance Ramshaw, and Ralph<lb/> Weischedel. 2007. OntoNotes: A Unified Rela-<lb/>tional Semantic Representation. In Proceedings of<lb/> the International Conference on Semantic Comput-<lb/>ing, pages 517–526, Washington, DC, USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Lei Shi and Rada Mihalcea. 2005. Putting Pieces To-<lb/>gether: Combining FrameNet, VerbNet and Word-<lb/>Net for Robust Semantic Parsing. In Proceedings<lb/> of the Sixth International Conference on Intelligent<lb/> Text Processing and Computational Linguistics (CI-<lb/>CLing), pages 100–111, Mexico City, Mexico.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Claudia Soria, Monica Monachini, and Piek Vossen.<lb/> 2009. Wordnet-LMF: fleshing out a standardized<lb/> format for Wordnet interoperability. In Proceed-<lb/>ings of the 2009 International Workshop on Inter-<lb/>cultural Collaboration, pages 139–146, Palo Alto,<lb/> CA, USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Fabian M. Suchanek, Gjergji Kasneci, and Gerhard<lb/> Weikum. 2007. Yago: A Core of Semantic Knowl-<lb/>edge. In Proceedings of the 16th International Con-<lb/>ference on World Wide Web, pages 697–706, Banff,<lb/> Canada.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Antonio Toral, Stefania Bracale, Monica Monachini,<lb/> and Claudia Soria. 2010. Rejuvenating the Italian<lb/> WordNet: Upgrading, Standarising, Extending. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 5th Global WordNet Conference<lb/> (GWC), Bombay, India.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Piek Vossen, editor. 1998. EuroWordNet: A Multi-<lb/>lingual Database with Lexical Semantic Networks.<lb/> Kluwer Academic Publishers, Dordrecht, Nether-<lb/>lands.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

