<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Albers HE (2012) The regulation of social recognition, social com-<lb/>munication and aggression: vasopressin in the social behavior<lb/> neural network. Horm Behav 61:283-292. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Arakawa H, Arakawa K, Blanchard DC, Blanchard RJ (2008a) A new<lb/> test paradigm for social recognition evidenced by urinary scent<lb/> marking behavior in C57BL/6J mice. Behav Brain Res 190:97-104.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Arakawa H, Blanchard DC, Arakawa K, Dunlap C, Blanchard RJ<lb/> (2008b) Scent marking behavior as an odorant communication in<lb/> mice. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 32:1236 -1248. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Bakker J, Honda S-I, Harada N, Balthazart J (2002) The aromatase<lb/> knock-out mouse provides new evidence that estradiol is required<lb/> during development in the female for the expression of sociosex-<lb/>ual behaviors in adulthood. J Neurosci 22:9104 -9112. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Barkley MS, Goldman BD (1977) The effects of castration and Silas-<lb/>tic implants of testosterone on intermale aggression in the mouse.<lb/> Horm Behav 9:32-48. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Baum MJ, Keverne EB (2002) Sex difference in attraction thresholds<lb/> for volatile odors from male and estrous female mouse urine. Horm<lb/> Behav 41:213-219. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Beeman EA (1947) The relation of the interval between castration and<lb/> first encounter to the aggressive behavior of mice. Anat Rec<lb/> 99:570. Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Beiderbeck DI, Neumann ID, Veenema AH (2007) Differences in<lb/> intermale aggression are accompanied by opposite vasopressin<lb/> release patterns within the septum in rats bred for low and high<lb/> anxiety. Eur J Neurosci 26:3597-3605. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Bielsky IF, Hu SB, Szegda KL, Westphal H, Young LJ (2004) Pro-<lb/>found impairment in social recognition and reduction in anxiety-<lb/>like behavior in vasopressin V1a receptor knockout mice.<lb/> Neuropsychopharmacology 29:483-493. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Bielsky IF, Hu SB, Young LJ (2005) Sexual dimorphism in the vaso-<lb/>pressin system: lack of an altered behavioral phenotype in female<lb/> V1a receptor knockout mice. Behav Brain Res 164:132-136.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Bishop MJ, Chevins PF (1987) Urine odours and marking patterns in<lb/> territorial laboratory mice (Mus musculus). Behav Processes 15:<lb/> 233-248. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Bleickardt CJ, Mullins DE, Macsweeney CP, Werner BJ, Pond AJ,<lb/> Guzzi MF, Martin FDC, Varty GB, Hodgson RA (2009) Character-<lb/>ization of the V1a antagonist, JNJ-17308616, in rodent models of<lb/> anxiety-like behavior. Psychopharmacology 202:711-718. Cross-<lb/>Ref Medline<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Bradbury JW, Vehrencamp SL (1998) Principles of animal commu-<lb/>nication, Ed 2. Sunderland, MA: Sinauer Associates, Oxford Uni-<lb/>versity Press.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Caligioni CS (2009) Assessing reproductive status/stages in mice.<lb/> Curr Protoc Neurosci Appendix 4:Appendix 4I. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Chabout J, Sarkar A, Dunson DB, Jarvis ED (2015) Male mice song<lb/> syntax depends on social contexts and influences female prefer-<lb/>ences. Front Behav Neurosci 9:76. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Cole JC, Rodgers RJ (1993) An ethological analysis of the effects of<lb/> chlordiazepoxide and bretazenil (Ro 16-6028) in the murine ele-<lb/>vated plus-maze. Behav Pharmacol 4:573-580. Medline<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Compaan JC, Buijs RM, Pool CW, De Ruiter AJ, Koolhaas JM (1993)<lb/> Differential lateral septal vasopressin innervation in aggressive and<lb/> nonaggressive male mice. Brain Res Bull 30:1-6. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Connor JL, Winston H (1972) Genetic analysis of conditioned emo-<lb/>tional responses in the mouse (Mus musculus L.). J Comp Physiol<lb/> Psychol 81:37-44. Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Coquelin A (1992) Urine-marking by female mice throughout their<lb/> reproductive cycle. Horm Behav 26:255-271. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Crawley JN (2007) Mouse behavioral assays relevant to the symp-<lb/>toms of autism. Brain Pathol 17:448 -459. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Crawley JN (2012) Translational animal models of autism and neu-<lb/>rodevelopmental disorders. Dialogues Clin Neurosci 14:293-305.<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Dantzer R, Koob GF, Bluthé RM, Le Moal M (1988) Septal vasopres-<lb/>sin modulates social memory in male rats. Brain Res 457:143-147.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Darwin C (1871) The descent of man, and selection in relation to sex.<lb/> Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Desjardins C, Maruniak JA, Bronson FH (1973) Social rank in house<lb/> mice: differentiation revealed by ultraviolet visualization of urinary<lb/> marking patterns. Science 182:939 -941. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>De Vries GJ (2008) Sex differences in vasopressin and oxytocin<lb/> innervation of the brain. Prog Brain Res 170:17-27. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>De Vries GJ, Buijs RM (1983) The origin of the vasopressinergic and<lb/> oxytocinergic innervation of the rat brain with special reference to<lb/> the lateral septum. Brain Res 273:307-317. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>De Vries GJ, Boyle PA (1998) Double duty for sex differences in the<lb/> brain. Behav Brain Res 92:205-213. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>De Vries GJ, Panzica GC (2006) Sexual differentiation of central<lb/> vasopressin and vasotocin systems in vertebrates: different mech-<lb/>anisms, similar endpoints. Neuroscience 138:947-955. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Dumais KM, Veenema AH (2016) Vasopressin and oxytocin receptor<lb/> systems in the brain: sex differences and sex-specific regulation of<lb/> social behavior. Front Neuroendocrinol 40:1-23. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Ebner K, Wotjak CT, Landgraf R, Engelmann M (2000) A single social<lb/> defeat experience selectively stimulates the release of oxytocin,<lb/> but not vasopressin, within the septal brain area of male rats. Brain<lb/> Res 872:87-92. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Ebner K, Wotjak CT, Landgraf R, Engelmann M (2002) Forced swim-<lb/>ming triggers vasopressin release within the amygdala to modulate<lb/> stress-coping strategies in rats. Eur J Neurosci 15:384 -388.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Everts HG, Koolhaas JM (1999) Differential modulation of lateral<lb/> septal vasopressin receptor blockade in spatial learning, social<lb/> recognition, and anxiety-related behaviors in rats. Behav Brain Res<lb/> 99:7-16. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Everts HG, De Ruiter AJ, Koolhaas JM (1997) Differential lateral<lb/> septal vasopressin in wild-type rats: correlation with aggression.<lb/> Horm Behav 31:136 -144. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Freeman AR, Hare JF, Anderson WG, Caldwell HK (2018) Effects of<lb/> arginine vasopressin on Richardson&apos;s ground squirrel social and<lb/> vocal behavior. Behav Neurosci 132:34 -50. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Gheusi G, Bluth R-M, Goodall G, Dantzer R (1994) Social and indi-<lb/>vidual recognition in rodents: methodological aspects and neuro-<lb/>biological bases. Behav Processes 33:59 -87. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Goodson JL, Adkins-Regan E (1999) Effect of intraseptal vasotocin<lb/> and vasoactive intestinal polypeptide infusions on courtship song<lb/> and aggression in the male zebra finch (Taeniopygia guttata). J<lb/> Neuroendocrinol 11:19 -25. Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Goodson JL, Bass AH (2001) Social behavior functions and related<lb/> anatomical characteristics of vasotocin/vasopressin systems in<lb/> vertebrates. Brain Res Brain Res Rev 35:246 -265. Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Goodson JL, Evans AK (2004) Neural responses to territorial chal-<lb/>lenge and nonsocial stress in male song sparrows: segregation,<lb/> integration, and modulation by a vasopressin V1 antagonist. Horm<lb/> Behav 46:371-381. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Goodson JL, Kabelik D, Schrock SE (2009) Dynamic neuromodula-<lb/>tion of aggression by vasotocin: influence of social context and<lb/> social phenotype in territorial songbirds. Biol Lett 5:554 -556.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Gosling LM, Roberts SC, Thornton EA, Andrew MJ (2000) Life history<lb/> costs of olfactory status signalling in mice. Behav Ecol Sociobiol<lb/> 48:328 -332. CrossRef<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Halladay AK, Bishop S, Constantino JN, Daniels AM, Koenig K,<lb/> Palmer K, Messinger D, Pelphrey K, Sanders SJ, Singer AT, Taylor<lb/> JL, Szatmari P (2015) Sex and gender differences in autism spec-<lb/>trum disorder: summarizing evidence gaps and identifying emerg-<lb/>ing areas of priority. Mol Autism 6:36. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Hanson JL, Hurley LM (2012) Female presence and estrous state<lb/> influence mouse ultrasonic courtship vocalizations. PLoS One<lb/> 7:e40782. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Hogg S (1996) A review of the validity and variability of the elevated<lb/> plus-maze as an animal model of anxiety. Pharmacol Biochem<lb/> Behav 54:21-30. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Ho JM, Murray JH, Demas GE, Goodson JL (2010) Vasopressin cell<lb/> groups exhibit strongly divergent responses to copulation and<lb/> male-male interactions in mice. Horm Behav 58:368 -377. Cross-<lb/>Ref Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Iijima M, Yoshimizu T, Shimazaki T, Tokugawa K, Fukumoto K,<lb/> Kurosu S, Kuwada T, Sekiguchi Y, Chaki S (2014) Antidepressant<lb/> and anxiolytic profiles of newly synthesized arginine vasopressin<lb/> V1B receptor antagonists: TASP0233278 and TASP0390325. Br J<lb/> Pharmacol 171:3511-3525. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Insel TR (2010) The challenge of translation in social neuroscience: a<lb/> review of oxytocin, vasopressin, and affiliative behavior. Neuron<lb/> 65:768 -779. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Kelly AM, Goodson JL (2013a) Functional significance of a phyloge-<lb/>netically widespread sexual dimorphism in vasotocin/vasopressin<lb/> production. Horm Behav 64:840 -846. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl>Kelly AM, Goodson JL (2013b) Behavioral relevance of species-<lb/>specific vasotocin anatomy in gregarious finches. Front Neurosci<lb/> 7:242. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Kelly AM, Kingsbury MA, Hoffbuhr K, Schrock SE, Waxman B,<lb/> Kabelik D, Thompson RR, Goodson JL (2011) Vasotocin neurons<lb/> and septal V1a-like receptors potently modulate songbird flocking<lb/> and responses to novelty. Horm Behav 60:12-21. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Koolhaas JM, Moor E, Hiemstra Y, Bohus B (1991) The testosterone-<lb/>dependent vasopressinergic neurons in the medial amygdala and<lb/> lateral septum: Involvement in social behaviour of male rats. In<lb/> Vasopressin, (Jard S, Jamison R, eds), pp 213-219. Paris/London:<lb/> INSERM/John Libbey Eurotext Ltd.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Koolhaas JM, Coppens CM, de Boer SF, Buwalda B, Meerlo P,<lb/> Timmermans PJ (2013) The resident-intruder paradigm: a stan-<lb/>dardized test for aggression, violence and social stress. J Vis Exp<lb/> (77):e4367. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Labov JB, Wysocki CJ (1989) Vomeronasal organ and social factors<lb/> affect urine marking by male mice. Physiol Behav 45:443-447.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Landgraf R, Gerstberger R, Montkowski A, Probst JC, Wotjak CT,<lb/> Holsboer F, Engelmann M (1995) V1 vasopressin receptor anti-<lb/>sense oligodeoxynucleotide into septum reduces vasopressin<lb/> binding, social discrimination abilities, and anxiety-related behav-<lb/>ior in rats. J Neurosci 15:4250 -4258. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Landgraf R, Frank E, Aldag JM, Neumann ID, Sharer CA, Ren X,<lb/> Terwilliger EF, Niwa M, Wigger A, Young LJ (2003) Viral vector-<lb/>mediated gene transfer of the vole V1a vasopressin receptor in the<lb/> rat septum: improved social discrimination and active social be-<lb/>haviour. Eur J Neurosci 18:403-411. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Lehmann ML, Geddes CE, Lee JL, Herkenham M (2013) Urine scent<lb/> marking (USM): a novel test for depressive-like behavior and a<lb/> predictor of stress resiliency in mice. PLoS One 8:e69822. Cross-<lb/>Ref Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Liebsch G, Wotjak CT, Landgraf R, Engelmann M (1996) Septal<lb/> vasopressin modulates anxiety-related behaviour in rats. Neurosci<lb/> Lett 217:101-104. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Lim MM, Young LJ (2004) Vasopressin-dependent neural circuits<lb/> underlying pair bond formation in the monogamous prairie vole.<lb/> Neuroscience 125:35-45. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Lim MM, Hammock EAD, Young LJ (2004) The role of vasopressin in<lb/> the genetic and neural regulation of monogamy. J Neuroendocri-<lb/>nol 16:325-332. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Lister RG (1987) The use of a plus-maze to measure anxiety in the<lb/> mouse. Psychopharmacology 92:180 -185. Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Liu Y, Curtis JT, Wang Z (2001) Vasopressin in the lateral septum<lb/> regulates pair bond formation in male prairie voles (Microtus<lb/> ochrogaster). Behav Neurosci 115:910 -919. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Ludwig M, Stern J (2015) Multiple signaling modalities mediated by<lb/> dendritic exocytosis of oxytocin and vasopressin. Philos Trans R<lb/> Soc Lond B Biol Sci 370:20140182. CrossRef Medline<lb/> Lukas M, Wöhr M (2015) Endogenous vasopressin, innate anxiety,<lb/> and the emission of pro-social 50-kHz ultrasonic vocalizations<lb/> during social play behavior in juvenile rats. Psychoneuroendocri-<lb/>nology 56:35-44. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Lumley LA, Sipos ML, Charles RC, Charles RF, Meyerhoff JL (1999)<lb/> Social stress effects on territorial marking and ultrasonic vocaliza-<lb/>tions in mice. Physiol Behav 67:769 -775. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Maggio JC, Whitney G (1985) Ultrasonic vocalizing by adult female<lb/> mice (Mus musculus). J Comp Psychol 99:420 -436. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Maruniak JA, Wysocki CJ, Taylor JA (1986) Mediation of male mouse<lb/> urine marking and aggression by the vomeronasal organ. Physiol<lb/> Behav 37:655-657. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Matochik JA, Sipos ML, Nyby JG, Barfield RJ (1994) Intracranial<lb/> androgenic activation of male-typical behaviors in house mice:<lb/> motivation versus performance. Behav Brain Res 60:141-149.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Meyer H (1957) The ninhydrin reaction and its analytical applications.<lb/> Biochem J 67:333-340. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Mieda M, Ono D, Hasegawa E, Okamoto H, Honma K-I, Honma S,<lb/> Sakurai T (2015) Cellular clocks in AVP neurons of the SCN are<lb/> critical for interneuronal coupling regulating circadian behavior<lb/> rhythm. Neuron 85:1103-1116. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Miller MA, Kolb PE, Raskind MA (1993) Extra-hypothalamic vaso-<lb/>pressin neurons coexpress galanin messenger RNA as shown by<lb/> double in situ hybridization histochemistry. J Comp Neurol 329:<lb/> 378 -384. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Moncho-Bogani J, Lanuza E, Lorente MJ, Martinez-Garcia F (2004)<lb/> Attraction to male pheromones and sexual behaviour show differ-<lb/>ent regulatory mechanisms in female mice. Physiol Behav 81:427-<lb/>434. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Morgan CW, Julien O, Unger EK, Shah NM, Wells JA (2014) Turning<lb/> on caspases with genetics and small molecules. Methods Enzymol<lb/> 544:179 -213. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Moy SS, Nadler JJ, Young NB, Nonneman RJ, Grossman AW,<lb/> Murphy DL, D&apos;Ercole AJ, Crawley JN, Magnuson TR, Lauder JM<lb/> (2009) Social approach in genetically engineered mouse lines<lb/> relevant to autism. Genes Brain Behav 8:129 -142. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Oldfield RG, Harris RM, Hofmann HA (2015) Integrating resource<lb/> defence theory with a neural nonapeptide pathway to explain<lb/> territory-based mating systems. Front Zool 12:S16. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Otero-Garcia M, Martin-Sanchez A, Fortes-Marco L, Martínez-Ricós<lb/> J, Agustin-Pavón C, Lanuza E, Martínez-García F (2014) Extending<lb/> the socio-sexual brain: arginine-vasopressin immunoreactive cir-<lb/>cuits in the telencephalon of mice. Brain Struct Funct 219:1055-<lb/>1081. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Paul MJ, Peters NV, Holder MK, Kim AM, Whylings J, Terranova JI,<lb/> de Vries GJ (2016) Atypical social development in vasopressin-<lb/>deficient brattleboro rats. eNeuro 3:ENEURO.0150-15.2016.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Paxinos G, Franklin K (2012) The mouse brain in stereotaxic coordi-<lb/>nates, Ed 4. San Diego, CA: Academic Press.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Pedersen CA, Boccia ML (2006) Vasopressin interactions with oxy-<lb/>tocin in the control of female sexual behavior. Neuroscience 139:<lb/> 843-851. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Pitkow LJ, Sharer CA, Ren X, Insel TR, Terwilliger EF, Young LJ<lb/> (2001) Facilitation of affiliation and pair-bond formation by vaso-<lb/>pressin receptor gene transfer into the ventral forebrain of a mo-<lb/>nogamous vole. J Neurosci 21:7392-7396. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>R Core Team (2013). R: A language and environment for statistical<lb/> computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Aus-<lb/>tria.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Raggenbass M (2008) Overview of cellular electrophysiological ac-<lb/>tions of vasopressin. Eur J Pharmacol 583:243-254. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Rilling JK, Demarco AC, Hackett PD, Chen X, Gautam P, Stair S,<lb/> Haroon E, Thompson R, Ditzen B, Patel R, Pagnoni G (2014) Sex<lb/> differences in the neural and behavioral response to intranasal<lb/> oxytocin and vasopressin during human social interaction. Psy-<lb/>choneuroendocrinology 39:237-248. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Roberts SC, Gosling LM, Thornton EA, McClung J (2001) Scent-<lb/>marking by male mice under the risk of predation. Behav Ecol<lb/> 12:698 -705. CrossRef<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Rood BD, De Vries GJ (2011) Vasopressin innervation of the mouse<lb/> (Mus musculus) brain and spinal cord. J Comp Neurol 519:2434 -<lb/>2474. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Rood BD, Stott RT, You S, Smith CJW, Woodbury ME, De Vries GJ<lb/> (2013) Site of origin of and sex differences in the vasopressin<lb/> innervation of the mouse (Mus musculus) brain. J Comp Neurol<lb/> 521:2321-2358. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Roullet FI, Wöhr M, Crawley JN (2011) Female urine-induced male<lb/> mice ultrasonic vocalizations, but not scent-marking, is modulated<lb/> by social experience. Behav Brain Res 216:19 -28. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Schultz RT (2005) Developmental deficits in social perception in<lb/> autism: the role of the amygdala and fusiform face area. Int J Dev<lb/> Neurosci 23:125-141. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Scott N, Prigge M, Yizhar O, Kimchi T (2015) A sexually dimorphic<lb/> hypothalamic circuit controls maternal care and oxytocin secre-<lb/>tion. Nature 525:519 -522. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Shimshek DR, Kim J, Hübner MR, Spergel DJ, Buchholz F, Casanova<lb/> E, Stewart AF, Seeburg PH, Sprengel R (2002) Codon-improved<lb/> Cre recombinase (iCre) expression in the mouse. Genesis 32:19 -<lb/>26. CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Södersten P, Henning M, Melin P, Ludin S (1983) Vasopressin alters<lb/> female sexual behaviour by acting on the brain independently of<lb/> alterations in blood pressure. Nature 301:608 -610. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Ström JO, Theodorsson A, Ingberg E, Isaksson IM, Theodorsson E<lb/> (2012) Ovariectomy and 17␤-estradiol replacement in rats and<lb/> mice: a visual demonstration. J Vis Exp. Advance online publica-<lb/>tion. Retrieved June 12, 2012. doi:10.3791/4013<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl>Terranova JI, Song Z, Larkin TE 2nd, Hardcastle N, Norvelle A, Riaz<lb/> A, Albers HE (2016) Serotonin and arginine-vasopressin mediate<lb/> sex differences in the regulation of dominance and aggression by<lb/> the social brain. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 113:13233-13238.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Treit D, Aujla H, Menard J (1998) Does the bed nucleus of the stria<lb/> terminalis mediate fear behaviors? Behav Neurosci 112:379 -386.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Unger EK, Burke KJ Jr, Yang CF, Bender KJ, Fuller PM, Shah NM<lb/> (2015) Medial amygdalar aromatase neurons regulate aggression<lb/> in both sexes. Cell Rep 10:453-462. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>van Leeuwen FW, Caffe AR, De Vries GJ (1985) Vasopressin cells in<lb/> the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis of the rat: sex differences<lb/> and the influence of androgens. Brain Res 325:391-394. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Van Loo PL, Mol JA, Koolhaas JM, Van Zutphen BF, Baumans V<lb/> (2001) Modulation of aggression in male mice: influence of group<lb/> size and cage size. Physiol Behav 72:675-683. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Van Segbroeck M, Knoll AT, Levitt P, Narayanan S (2017) MUPET-<lb/>Mouse Ultrasonic Profile ExTraction: A Signal Processing Tool for<lb/> Rapid and Unsupervised Analysis of Ultrasonic Vocalizations.<lb/> Neuron 94:465-485.e5. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Veenema AH, Beiderbeck DI, Lukas M, Neumann ID (2010) Distinct<lb/> correlations of vasopressin release within the lateral septum and<lb/> the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis with the display of intermale<lb/> aggression. Horm Behav 58:273-281. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Veenema AH, Bredewold R, De Vries GJ (2012) Vasopressin regu-<lb/>lates social recognition in juvenile and adult rats of both sexes, but<lb/> in sex-and age-specific ways. Horm Behav 61:50 -56. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Veenema AH, Bredewold R, De Vries GJ (2013) Sex-specific modu-<lb/>lation of juvenile social play by vasopressin. Psychoneuroendocri-<lb/>nology 38:2554 -2561. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Veyrac A, Wang G, Baum MJ, Bakker J (2011) The main and acces-<lb/>sory olfactory systems of female mice are activated differentially<lb/> by dominant versus subordinate male urinary odors. Brain Res<lb/> 1402:20 -29. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Wang Z, Smith W, Major DE, De Vries GJ (1994) Sex and species<lb/> differences in the effects of cohabitation on vasopressin messen-<lb/>ger RNA expression in the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis in<lb/> prairie voles (Microtus ochrogaster) and meadow voles (Microtus<lb/> pennsylvanicus). Brain Res 650:212-218. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Wei YC, Wang SR, Jiao ZL, Zhang W, Lin JK, Li XY, Li SS, Zhang X,<lb/> Xu XH (2018) Medial preoptic area in mice is capable of mediating<lb/> sexually dimorphic behaviors regardless of gender. Nat Commun<lb/> 9:279. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Wersinger SR, Kelliher KR, Zufall F, Lolait SJ, O&apos;Carroll A-M, Young<lb/> W 3rd (2004) Social motivation is reduced in vasopressin 1b<lb/> receptor null mice despite normal performance in an olfactory<lb/> discrimination task. Horm Behav 46:638 -645. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Wersinger SR, Caldwell HK, Martinez L, Gold P, Hu S-B, Young WS<lb/> 3rd (2007) Vasopressin 1a receptor knockout mice have a subtle<lb/> olfactory deficit but normal aggression. Genes Brain Behav 6:540 -<lb/>551. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Wilczynski W, Quispe M, Muñoz MI, Penna M (2017) Arginine vaso-<lb/>tocin, the social neuropeptide of amphibians and reptiles. Front<lb/> Endocrinol 8:186. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Winslow JT, Insel TR (1993) Effects of central vasopressin adminis-<lb/>tration to infant rats. Eur J Pharmacol 233:101-107. CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Wöhr M (2014) Ultrasonic vocalizations in Shank mouse models for<lb/> autism spectrum disorders: detailed spectrographic analyses and<lb/> developmental profiles. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 43:199 -212.<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Wu Z, Autry AE, Bergan JF, Watabe-Uchida M, Dulac CG (2014)<lb/> Galanin neurons in the medial preoptic area govern parental be-<lb/>haviour. Nature 509:325-330. CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl>Yang CF, Chiang MC, Gray DC, Prabhakaran M, Alvarado M, Juntti<lb/> SA, Unger EK, Wells JA, Shah NM (2013) Sexually dimorphic<lb/> neurons in the ventromedial hypothalamus govern mating in both<lb/> sexes and aggression in males. Cell 153:896 -909. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

