<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_D_-1"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>
<bibl> <label>1.</label> R. Guha, Contexts: a formalization and some applications, PhD thesis, Stanford university (CA US), 1991 (Technical Report STAN-CS-91-1399-Thesis et MCC ACT-CYC-423-91).</bibl>
<bibl> <label>2.</label> O. Khriyenko, V. Terziyan, Context description framework for the semantic web, Proceedings Context 2005 Context representation and reasoning workshop, Paris (FR), 2005</bibl>
<bibl> <label>3.</label> A. Dey, D. Salber, G. Abowd, A conceptual framework and a toolkit for supporting the rapid prototyping of context-aware applications, Human-Computer Interaction 16:97-166., 2001</bibl>
<bibl> <label>4.</label> P. Dourish, Seeking a foundation for context-aware computing, Human-Computer Interaction, 16(2-3), 2001.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>5.</label> M. Chalmers, A Historical View of Context, Computer supported cooperative work 13(3), 223-247, 2004.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>6.</label> A. Dey, Understanding and using context, Personal and ubiquitous computing 5(1):4-7, 2001.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>7.</label> J. Coutaz, J. Crowley, S. Dobson, D. Garlan, Context is key, Communications of the ACM 48(3):49-53, 2005.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>8.</label> G. Klyne, J. Carroll, Eds., Resource Description Framework (RDF): Concepts and Abstract Syntax, W3C Recommendation, 2004 http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-concepts/</bibl>
<bibl> <label>9.</label> M. Dean, G. Schreiber Eds, OWL Web Ontology Language: Reference, W3C Recommendation, 2004. http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-ref/</bibl> 
<bibl> <label>10.</label> A. Seaborne, RDQL — A Query Language for RDF, W3C Member submission, 2004. http://www.w3.org/Submission/2004/SUBM-RDQL-20040109/</bibl>
<bibl> <label>11.</label> J. Crowley, J. Coutaz, G. Rey, P. Reignier, Perceptual components for context aware computing, Proceedings International Conference on Ubiquitous Computing, Göteborg (SW), pp. 117-134, 2002.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>12.</label> X. H. Wang, D. Q. Zhang, T. Gu, H. Keng Pung, Ontology based context modeling and reasoning in OWL, Proceedings 2 nd International conference on pervasive computing and communication Workshop on Context Modeling and Reasoning (CoMoRea), Orlando (FL US), 2000.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>13.</label> J. Euzenat, Alignment infrastructure for ontology mediation and other applications, Proceedings ICSOC 1 st international workshop on Mediation in semantic web services, pp.81-95, Amsterdam (NL), 2005.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

