<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        Web1T<lb/> 
        Curvature<lb/> 46.0 33.8 30.7 25.2 21.9<lb/> 
SquaT++ V<lb/> 45.9 34.5 28.3 24.0 21.0<lb/> 
SquaT++ E<lb/> 42.8 35.3 29.1 23.6 20.4<lb/> 
B-MST<lb/> 43.6 35.3 29.3 25.7 21.6<lb/> 
HyperLex<lb/> 46.5 38.0 31.3 26.5 22.5<lb/> 
Chinese Whispers 49.4 35.2 28.9 24.2 21.9<lb/> ukWaC<lb/> Curvature<lb/> 37.9 33.2 27.4 24.3 20.4<lb/> 
SquaT++ V<lb/> 45.0 34.4 28.8 25.5 22.2<lb/> 
SquaT++ E<lb/> 42.0 34.0 29.3 25.2 20.5<lb/> 
B-MST<lb/> 49.3 36.7 33.5 26.3 22.5<lb/> 
HyperLex<lb/> 51.4 40.0 32.4 27.6 22.6<lb/> 
Chinese Whispers 45.1 36.6 30.1 24.5 20.5<lb/> 
KeySRC<lb/> 29.3 22.3 17.7 15.4 12.0<lb/> 
EP<lb/> 33.6 24.9 18.9 16.1 13.2<lb/> 
Yahoo!<lb/> 36.1 25.7 18.7 15.5 12.6<lb/> 
References<lb/> 
<bibl>Agirre, Eneko, David Martínez, Oier L ´<lb/> opez<lb/> de Lacalle, and Aitor Soroa. 2006a.<lb/> Evaluating and optimizing the parameters<lb/> of an unsupervised graph-based WSD<lb/> algorithm. In Proceedings of the 1st<lb/> Workshop on Graph-Based Algorithms for<lb/> Natural Language Processing, pages 89–96,<lb/> New York.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Agirre, Eneko, David Martínez, Oier<lb/> L ´<lb/> opez de Lacalle, and Aitor Soroa.<lb/> 2006b. Two graph-based algorithms<lb/> for state-of-the-art WSD. In Proceedings<lb/> of the 2006 Conference on Empirical<lb/> Methods in Natural Language Processing,<lb/> pages 585–593, Sydney.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Agirre, Eneko and Aitor Soroa. 2007.<lb/> 
UBC-AS: A graph based unsupervised<lb/> system for induction and classification.<lb/> 
In Proceedings of the 4 th International<lb/> Workshop on Semantic Evaluations,<lb/> pages 346–349, Prague.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Agrawal, Rakesh, Sreenivas Gollapudi,<lb/> Alan Halverson, and Samuel Ieong. 2009.<lb/> Diversifying search results. In Proceedings<lb/> of the 2nd International Conference on Web<lb/> tree methods. In Technical Report CS276A<lb/> Final Project, Stanford University.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Brants, Thorsten and Alex Franz. 2006. Web<lb/> 1T 5-gram, ver. 1, ldc2006t13. In Linguistic<lb/> Data Consortium, Philadelphia, PA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Brody, Samuel and Mirella Lapata. 2009.<lb/> Bayesian Word Sense Induction. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 12th Conference of the<lb/> European Chapter of the Association for<lb/> Computational Linguistics, pages 103–111,<lb/> Athens.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Bruza, Peter, Robert McArthur, and Simon<lb/> Dennis. 2000. Interactive Internet<lb/> search: Keyword, directory and query<lb/> reformulation mechanisms compared. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 23rd Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> pages 280–287, Athens.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Bunescu, Razvan C. and Marius Pasca. 2006.<lb/> Using encyclopedic knowledge for named<lb/> entity disambiguation. In Proceedings of<lb/> 11th Conference of the European Chapter of the<lb/> Association for Computational Linguistics,<lb/> pages 9–16, Trento.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Carbonell, Jaime and Jade Goldstein.<lb/> 1998. The use of MMR, diversity-based<lb/> reranking for reordering documents and<lb/> producing summaries. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 21st Annual International ACM SIGIR<lb/> Conference on Research and Development in<lb/> Information Retrieval, pages 335–336,<lb/> Melbourne.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Carmel, David, Haggai Roitman, and<lb/> Naama Zwerdling. 2009. Enhancing<lb/> cluster labeling using Wikipedia. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 32nd Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> pages 139–146, Boston, MA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Carpineto, Claudio, Massimiliano D&apos;Amico,<lb/> and Andrea Bernardini. 2011. Full<lb/> discrimination of subtopics in search<lb/> results with keyphrase-based clustering.<lb/> Web Intelligence and Agent Systems,<lb/> 9(4):337–349.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Carpineto, Claudio, Stanislaw Osí<lb/> nski,<lb/> Giovanni Romano, and Dawid Weiss.<lb/> 
<label>2009.</label> A survey of Web clustering engines.<lb/> 
ACM Computing Surveys, 41(3):1–38.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Carpineto, Claudio and Giovanni Romano.<lb/> 2004. Exploiting the potential of concept<lb/> lattices for Information Retrieval with<lb/> CREDO. Journal of Universal Computer<lb/> Science, 10(8):985–1013.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Chandar, Praveen and Ben Carterette. 2010.<lb/> Diversification of search results using<lb/> webgraphs. In Proceedings of the 33rd<lb/> International ACM SIGIR Conference on<lb/> Research and Development in Information<lb/> Retrieval, pages 869–870, Geneva.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Chapelle, Olivier, Yi Chang, and Tie-Yan Liu.<lb/> 2011. Future directions in learning<lb/> to rank. Journal of Machine Learning<lb/> Research—Proceedings Track, 14:91–100.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Chen, Harr and David R. Karger. 2006. Less<lb/> is more: Probabilistic models for retrieving<lb/> fewer relevant documents. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 29th Annual International ACM SIGIR<lb/> Conference on Research and Development in<lb/> Information Retrieval, pages 429–436,<lb/> Seattle, WA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Chen, Jiyang, Osmar R. Za¨Za¨ıane, and Randy<lb/> Goebel. 2008. An unsupervised approach<lb/> to cluster web search results based on<lb/> word sense communities. In Proceedings<lb/> of 2008 IEEE/WIC/ACM International<lb/> Conference on Web Intelligence,<lb/> pages 725–729, Sydney.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Cheng, David, Santosh Vempala, Ravi<lb/> Kannan, and Grant Wang. 2005. A<lb/> divide-and-merge methodology for<lb/> clustering. In Proceedings of the 24th<lb/> ACM SIGACT-SIGMOD-SIGART<lb/> Symposium on Principles of Database<lb/> Systems, pages 196–205, Baltimore, MD.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Clarke, Daoud. 2012. A context-theoretic<lb/> framework for compositionality in<lb/> distributional semantics. Computational<lb/> Linguistics, 38(1):41–71.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Clough, Paul, Mark Sanderson, Murad<lb/> Abouammoh, Sergio Navarro, and<lb/> Monica Lestari Paramita. 2009. Multiple<lb/> approaches to analysing query diversity. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 32nd Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> pages 734–735, Boston, MA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Crabtree, Daniel, Xiaoying Gao, and Peter<lb/> Andreae. 2005. Improving Web clustering<lb/> by cluster selection. In Proceedings of 2005<lb/> IEEE/WIC/ACM International Conference on<lb/> Web Intelligence, pages 172–178,<lb/> Compiegne.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Cutting, Douglass R., David R. Karger,<lb/> Jan O. Pedersen, and John W. Tukey. 1992.<lb/> Scatter/Gather: A cluster-based approach<lb/> to browsing large document collections. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 15th Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> pages 318–329, Copenhagen.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Di Giacomo, Emilio, Walter Didimo,<lb/> Luca Grilli, and Giuseppe Liotta. 2007.<lb/> Graph visualization techniques for Web<lb/> clustering engines. IEEE Transactions on<lb/> Visualization and Computer Graphics,<lb/> 13(2):294–304.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Di Marco and Navigli<lb/> Clustering and Diversifying Search Results with Graph-Based WSI<lb/> Di Marco, Antonio and Roberto Navigli.<lb/> 2011. Clustering Web search results with<lb/> maximum spanning trees. In Proceedings of<lb/> the XIIth International Conference of the<lb/> Italian Association for Artificial Intelligence,<lb/> pages 201–212, Palermo.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Dorow, Beate, Dominic Widdows, Katarina<lb/> Ling, Jean-Pierre Eckmann, Danilo Sergi,<lb/> and Elisha Moses. 2005. Using curvature<lb/> and Markov clustering in graphs for<lb/> lexical acquisition and word sense<lb/> discrimination. In Proceedings of the<lb/> Meaning-2005 Workshop, Trento.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Erk, Katrin, Sebastian PadPad´Padó, and Ulrike PadPad´Padó.<lb/> 2010. A flexible, corpus-driven model of<lb/> regular and inverse selectional preferences.<lb/> Computational Linguistics, 36(4):723–763.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Fellbaum, Christiane, editor. 1998. WordNet:<lb/> An Electronic Database. MIT Press,<lb/> Cambridge, MA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Ferraresi, Adriano, Eros Zanchetta, Marco<lb/> Baroni, and Silvia Bernardini. 2008.<lb/> Introducing and evaluating ukWaC,<lb/> a very large Web-derived corpus of<lb/> English. In Proceedings of the 4th Web as<lb/> Corpus Workshop (WAC-4), pages 47–54,<lb/> Marrakech.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Furnas, G. W., T. K. Landauer, L. M.<lb/> Gomez, and S. T. Dumais. 1987. The<lb/> vocabulary problem in human-system<lb/> communication. Commununications of<lb/> ACM, 30(11):964–971.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gabrilovich, Evgeniy and Shaul Markovitch.<lb/> 2009. Wikipedia-based semantic<lb/> interpretation for natural language<lb/> processing. Journal of Artificial Intelligence<lb/> Research (JAIR), 34:443–498.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Geiss, Johanna. 2009. Creating a gold<lb/> standard for sentence clustering in<lb/> multi-document summarization. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 47th Annual Meeting<lb/> of the Association for Computational<lb/> Linguistics and the 4th International Joint<lb/> Conference on Natural Language Processing<lb/> of the AFNLP, pages 96–104, Singapore.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gelgi, Fatih, Hasan Davulcu, and Srinivas<lb/> Vadrevu. 2007. Term ranking for clustering<lb/> Web search results. In Proceedings of<lb/> 10th International Workshop on the Web<lb/> and Databases, Beijing, China.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Gonzalo, Julio, Anselmo Penas, and Felisa<lb/> Verdejo. 1999. Lexical ambiguity and<lb/> Information Retrieval revisited. In<lb/> Proceedings of the Joint SIGDAT Conference<lb/> on Empirical Methods in Natural Language<lb/> Processing and Very Large Corpora,<lb/> pages 195–202, College Park, MD.<lb/> Harris, Zellig. 1954. Distributional structure.<lb/> Word, 10:146–162.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Hubert, L. and P. Arabie. 1985. Comparing<lb/> partitions. Journal of Classification,<lb/> 2(1):193–218.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Kamvar, Maryam and Shumeet Baluja.<lb/> 2006. A large scale study of wireless<lb/> search behavior: Google mobile search.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 2006 Conference on<lb/> Human Factors in Computing Systems,<lb/> pages 701–709, Montréal.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Ke, Weimao, Cassidy R. Sugimoto, and<lb/> Javed Mostafa. 2009. Dynamicity vs.<lb/> effectiveness: Studying online clustering<lb/> for Scatter/Gather. In Proceedings of the<lb/> 32nd Annual International ACM SIGIR<lb/> Conference on Research and Development<lb/> in Information Retrieval, pages 19–26,<lb/> Boston, MA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Kim, Sang-Bum, Hee-Cheol Seo, and<lb/> Hae-Chang Rim. 2004. Information<lb/> Retrieval using word senses: Root sense<lb/> tagging approach. In Proceedings of the<lb/> 27th Annual International ACM SIGIR<lb/> Conference on Research and Development<lb/> in Information Retrieval, pages 258–265,<lb/> Sheffield.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Korkontzelos, Ioannis and Suresh<lb/> Manandhar. 2010. UoY: Graphs of<lb/> unambiguous vertices for word sense<lb/> induction and disambiguation.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 5th International<lb/> Workshop on Semantic Evaluation,<lb/> pages 355–358, Uppsala.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Krovetz, Robert and William B. Croft.<lb/> 1992. Lexical ambiguity and Information<lb/> Retrieval. ACM Transactions on Information<lb/> Systems, 10(2):115–141.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Kurland, Oren. 2008. The opposite of<lb/> smoothing: A language model approach<lb/> to ranking query-specific document<lb/> clusters. In Proceedings of the 31st Annual<lb/> International ACM SIGIR Conference on<lb/> Research and Development in Information<lb/> Retrieval, pages 171–178, Singapore.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Kurland, Oren and Carmel Domshlak. 2008.<lb/> A rank-aggregation approach to searching<lb/> for optimal query-specific clusters. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 31st Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> pages 547–554, Singapore.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Lee, Kyung Soon, W. Bruce Croft, and James<lb/> Allan. 2008. A cluster-based resampling<lb/> method for pseudo-relevance feedback. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 31st Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> pages 235–242, Singapore.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Lin, Dekang. 1998. Automatic retrieval and<lb/> clustering of similar words. In Proceedings<lb/> of the 17 th International Conference on<lb/> Computational Linguistics, pages 768–774,<lb/> Montreal.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Lin, Dekang and Patrick Pantel. 2002.<lb/> Discovering word senses from text.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 8 th ACM SIGKDD<lb/> International Conference on Knowledge<lb/> Discovery and Data Mining, pages 613–619,<lb/> Edmonton.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Liu, Shuang, Clement Yu, and Weiyi Meng.<lb/> 2005. Word Sense Disambiguation<lb/> in queries. In Proceedings of the 2005<lb/> ACM CIKM International Conference on<lb/> Information and Knowledge Management,<lb/> pages 525–532, Bremen.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Liu, Tie-Yan, Yiming Yang, Hao Wan,<lb/> Hua-Jun Zeng, Zheng Chen, and<lb/> Wei-Ying Ma. 2005. Support vector<lb/> machines classification with a very<lb/> large-scale taxonomy. SIGKDD<lb/> Explorations, 7(1):36–43.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Liu, Ying, Wenyuan Li, Yongjing Lin, and<lb/> Liping Jing. 2008. Spectral geometry for<lb/> simultaneously clustering and ranking<lb/> query search results. In Proceedings of the<lb/> 31st Annual International ACM SIGIR<lb/> Conference on Research and Development<lb/> in Information Retrieval, pages 539–546,<lb/> Singapore.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Ma, Hao, Michael R. Lyu, and Irwin King.<lb/> 2010. Diversifying query suggestion<lb/> results. In Proceedings of the 24th AAAI<lb/> Conference on Artificial Intelligence, AAAI<lb/> 2010, pages 1,399–1,404, Atlanta, GA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Maarek, Yoelle, Ron Fagin, Israel Ben-Shaul,<lb/> and Dan Pelleg. 2000. Ephemeral<lb/> document clustering for Web applications.<lb/> IBM Research Report RJ 10186. Haifa.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Manandhar, Suresh, Ioannis P. Klapaftis,<lb/> Dmitriy Dligach, and Sameer S. Pradhan.<lb/> 2010. SemEval-2010 task 14: Word sense<lb/> induction &amp; disambiguation. In Proceedings<lb/> of the 5th International Workshop on Semantic<lb/> Evaluation, pages 63–68, Uppsala.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mandala, Rila, Takenobu Tokunaga, and<lb/> Hozumi Tanaka. 1998. The use of WordNet<lb/> in Information Retrieval. In Proceedings of<lb/> the COLING-ACL workshop on Usage of<lb/> Wordnet in Natural Language Processing,<lb/> pages 31–37, Montréal.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Matsuo, Yutaka, Takeshi Sakaki, K ˆ<lb/> oki<lb/> Uchiyama, and Mitsuru Ishizuka. 2006.<lb/> Graph-based word clustering using a Web<lb/> search engine. In Proceedings of the 2006<lb/> Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural<lb/> Language Processing, pages 542–550,<lb/> Sydney.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mihalcea, Rada. 2007. Using Wikipedia for<lb/> automatic Word Sense Disambiguation.<lb/> In Human Language Technology Conference of<lb/> the North American Chapter of the Association<lb/> of Computational Linguistics, pages 196–203,<lb/> Rochester, NY.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mihalkova, L. and R. Mooney. 2009. Learning<lb/> to disambiguate search queries from short<lb/> sessions. In Proceedings of Machine Learning<lb/> and Knowledge Discovery in Databases (2),<lb/> pages 111–127, Bled.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Miller, George A., R. T. Beckwith,<lb/> Christiane D. Fellbaum, D. Gross, and<lb/> K. Miller. 1990. WordNet: an online<lb/> lexical database. International Journal of<lb/> Lexicography, 3(4):235–244.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mitchell, Jeff and Mirella Lapata. 2010.<lb/> Composition in distributional models<lb/> of semantics. Cognitive Science,<lb/> 34(8):1388–1429.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Navigli, Roberto. 2009. Word Sense<lb/> Disambiguation: A survey. ACM<lb/> Computing Surveys, 41(2):1–69.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Navigli, Roberto. 2012. A quick tour of Word<lb/> Sense Disambiguation, induction and<lb/> related approaches. In Proceedings of the<lb/> 38th Conference on Current Trends in<lb/> Theory and Practice of Computer Science,<lb/> pages 115–129, Spindleruv Mí<lb/> yn.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Navigli, Roberto and Giuseppe Crisafulli.<lb/> 2010. Inducing word senses to improve<lb/> Web search result clustering. In Proceedings<lb/> of the 2010 Conference on Empirical<lb/> Methods in Natural Language Processing,<lb/> pages 116–126, Boston, MA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Navigli, Roberto and Simone Paolo Ponzetto.<lb/> 2012. The automatic construction,<lb/> evaluation and application of a<lb/> wide-coverage multilingual semantic<lb/> network. Artificial Intelligence,<lb/> 193:217–250.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Ngo, Chi Lang and Hung Son Nguyen.<lb/> 2005. A method of Web search result<lb/> clustering based on rough sets. In<lb/> Proceedings of 2005 IEEE/WIC/ACM<lb/> International Conference on Web Intelligence,<lb/> pages 673–679, Compiegne.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Nguyen, Cam-Tu, Xuan-Hieu Phan,<lb/> Susumu Horiguchi, Thu-Trang Nguyen,<lb/> and Quang-Thuy Ha. 2009. Web search<lb/> clustering and labeling with hidden topics.<lb/> ACM Transactions on Asian Language<lb/> Information Processing, 8(3):1–40.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Osinski, Stanislaw and Dawid Weiss. 2005.<lb/> A concept-driven algorithm for clustering<lb/> search results. IEEE Intelligent Systems,<lb/> 20(3):48–54.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Rand, W. M. 1971. Objective criteria for the<lb/> evaluation of clustering methods. Journal<lb/> of the American Statistical Association,<lb/> 66(336):846–850.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Di Marco and Navigli<lb/> Clustering and Diversifying Search Results with Graph-Based WSI<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Reisinger, Joseph and Marius Pasca. 2011.<lb/> Fine-grained class label markup of search<lb/> queries. In Proceedings of the 49th Annual<lb/> Meeting of the Association for Computational<lb/> Linguistics: Human Language Technologies,<lb/> pages 1,200–1,209, Portland, OR.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Rosenberg, Andrew and Julia Hirschberg.<lb/> 2007. V-measure: A conditional<lb/> entropy-based external cluster evaluation<lb/> measure. In Proceedings of the 2007 Joint<lb/> Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural<lb/> Language Processing and Computational<lb/> Natural Language Learning, pages 410–420,<lb/> Prague.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Sanderson, Mark. 1994. Word Sense<lb/> Disambiguation and Information<lb/> Retrieval. In Proceedings of the 17th Annual<lb/> International ACM-SIGIR Conference on<lb/> Research and Development in Information<lb/> Retrieval, pages 142–151, Dublin.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Sanderson, Mark. 2000. Retrieving with good<lb/> sense. Information Retrieval, 2(1):49–69.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Sanderson, Mark. 2008. Ambiguous queries:<lb/> Test collections need more sense. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 31st Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> pages 499–506, Singapore.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Santamaría, Celina, Julio Gonzalo, and<lb/> Javier Artiles. 2010. Wikipedia as sense<lb/> inventory to improve diversity in Web<lb/> search results. In Proceedings of the 48th<lb/> Annual Meeting of the Association for<lb/> Computational Linguistics, ACL 2010,<lb/> pages 1,357–1,366, Uppsala.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>SchSch¨Schütze, Hinrich. 1992. Dimensions of<lb/> meaning. In Proceedings of the 1992<lb/> ACM/IEEE Conference on Supercomputing,<lb/> pages 787–796, Los Alamitos, CA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>SchSch¨Schütze, Hinrich. 1998. Automatic word<lb/> sense discrimination. Computational<lb/> Linguistics, 24(1):97–124.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>SchSch¨Schütze, Hinrich and Jan Pedersen. 1995.<lb/> Information Retrieval based on word<lb/> senses. In Proceedings of SDAIR&apos;95,<lb/> pages 161–175, Las Vegas, NV.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Silberer, Carina and Mirella Lapata.<lb/> 2012. Grounded models of semantic<lb/> representation. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 2012 Joint Conference on Empirical<lb/> Methods in Natural Language<lb/> Processing and Computational Natural<lb/> Language Learning, pages 1,423–1,433,<lb/> Jeju Island.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Smadja, Frank, Kathleen R. McKeown,<lb/> and Vasileios Hatzivassiloglou. 1996.<lb/> Translating collocations for bilingual<lb/> lexicons: A statistical approach.<lb/> Computational Linguistics, 22(1):1–38.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Song, Ruihua, Zhenxiao Luo, Jian-Yun Nie,<lb/> Yong Yu, and Hsiao-Wuen Hon. 2009.<lb/> Identification of ambiguous queries in<lb/> Web search. Information Processing and<lb/> Management, 45:216–229.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Steinley, Doug. 2004. Properties of the<lb/> Hubert-Arabie adjusted Rand index.<lb/> Psychological Methods, 9(3):386–396.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Stokoe, Christopher, Michael J. Oakes,<lb/> and John I. Tait. 2003. Word Sense<lb/> Disambiguation in Information Retrieval<lb/> revisited. In Proceedings of the 26th Annual<lb/> International ACM SIGIR Conference on<lb/> Research and Development in Information<lb/> Retrieval, pages 159–166, Toronto.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Swaminathan, Ashwin, Cherian V. Mathew,<lb/> and Darko Kirovski. 2009. Essential pages.<lb/> In Proceedings of 2009 IEEE/WIC/ACM<lb/> International Conference on Web Intelligence,<lb/> pages 173–182, Milan.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Udani, Goldee, Shachi Dave, Anthony<lb/> Davis, and Tim Sibley. 2005. Noun sense<lb/> induction using Web search results. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 28th Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> pages 657–658, Salvador.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Van de Cruys, Tim and Marianna<lb/> Apidianaki. 2011. Latent semantic word<lb/> sense induction and disambiguation.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 49th Annual Meeting<lb/> of the Association for Computational<lb/> Linguistics: Human Language Technologies,<lb/> pages 1,476–1,485, Portland, OR.<lb/> van Rijsbergen, C. J. 1979. Information<lb/> Retrieval, second edition. Butterworths,<lb/> London.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Véronis, Jean. 2004. HyperLex: Lexical<lb/> cartography for information retrieval.<lb/> Computer, Speech and Language,<lb/> 18(3):223–252.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>von Luxburg, Ulrike, Robert C. Williamson,<lb/> and Isabelle Guyon. 2012. Clustering:<lb/> Science or art? Journal of Machine<lb/> Learning Research—Proceedings Track,<lb/> 27:65–80.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Voorhees, Ellen M. 1993. Using WordNet<lb/> to disambiguate word senses for text<lb/> retrieval. In Proceedings of the 16th Annual<lb/> International ACM-SIGIR Conference on<lb/> Research and Development in Information<lb/> Retrieval, pages 171–180, Pittsburgh, PA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Wang, Xuanhui, Deepayan Chakrabarti,<lb/> and Kunal Punera. 2009. Mining broad<lb/> latent query aspects from search sessions.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 15th ACM SIGKDD<lb/> International Conference on Knowledge<lb/> Discovery and Data Mining, pages 867–876,<lb/> Paris.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Wang, Xuanhui and ChengXiang Zhai.<lb/> 2007. Learn from Web search logs to<lb/> organize search results. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 30th Annual International ACM SIGIR<lb/> Conference on Research and Development<lb/> in Information Retrieval, pages 87–94,<lb/> Amsterdam.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Widdows, Dominic and Beate Dorow. 2002.<lb/> A graph model for unsupervised lexical<lb/> acquisition. In Proceedings of the 19th<lb/> International Conference on Computational<lb/> Linguistics, pages 1–7, Taipei.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Wu, Fei, Jayant Madhavan, and Alon Y.<lb/> Halevy. 2011. Identifying aspects for<lb/> Web-search queries. Journal of Artificial<lb/> Intelligence Research (JAIR), 40:677–700.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Xue, Gui-Rong, Dikan Xing, Qiang Yang,<lb/> and Yong Yu. 2008. Deep classification in<lb/> large-scale text hierarchies. In Proceedings<lb/> of the 31st Annual International ACM SIGIR<lb/> Conference on Research and Development in<lb/> Information Retrieval, pages 619–626,<lb/> Singapore.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Xue, Xiaobing and Xiaoxin Yin. 2011. Topic<lb/> modeling for named entity queries. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 20th ACM International<lb/> Conference on Information and Knowledge<lb/> Management, pages 2009–2012, New York.<lb/> Yarowsky, David. 1993. One sense per<lb/> collocation. In Proceedings of the ARPA<lb/> Workshop on Human Language Technology,<lb/> pages 266–271, Princeton, NJ.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Zamir, Oren and Oren Etzioni. 1998. Web<lb/> document clustering: A feasibility<lb/> demonstration. In Proceedings of the 21st<lb/> Annual International ACM SIGIR Conference<lb/> on Research and Development in Information<lb/> Retrieval, pages 46–54, Melbourne.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Zamir, Oren, Oren Etzioni, Omid Madani,<lb/> and Richard M. Karp. 1997. Fast and<lb/> intuitive clustering of Web documents.<lb/> In Proceedings of the Third International<lb/> Conference on Knowledge Discovery and<lb/> Data Mining, pages 287–290, Newport<lb/> Beach, CA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Zeng, Hua-Jun, Qi-Cai He, Zheng Chen,<lb/> Wei-Ying Ma, and Jinwen Ma. 2004.<lb/> Learning to cluster Web search results. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 27th Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> pages 210–217, Sheffield.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Zhai, ChengXiang, William W. Cohen,<lb/> and John Lafferty. 2003. Beyond<lb/> independent relevance: Methods and<lb/> evaluation metrics for subtopic retrieval.<lb/> In Proceedings of the 26th Annual<lb/> International ACM SIGIR Conference on<lb/> Research and Development in Information<lb/> Retrieval, pages 10–17, Toronto.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Zhang, Benyu, Hua Li, Yi Liu, Lei Ji,<lb/> Wensi Xi, Weiguo Fan, Zheng Chen,<lb/> and Wei-Ying Ma. 2005. Improving Web<lb/> search results using affinity graph. In<lb/> Proceedings of the 28th Annual International<lb/> ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and<lb/> Development in Information Retrieval,<lb/> SIGIR 2005, pages 504–511, Salvador.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Zhang, Xiaodan, Xiaohua Hu, and Xiaohua<lb/> Zhou. 2008. A comparative evaluation<lb/> of different link types on enhancing<lb/> document clustering. In Proceedings of the<lb/> 31st Annual International ACM SIGIR<lb/> Conference on Research and Development<lb/> in Information Retrieval, pages 555–562,<lb/> Singapore.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Zhao, Ying and George Karypis. 2004.<lb/> Empirical and theoretical comparisons of<lb/> selected criterion functions for document<lb/> clustering. Machine Learning, 55(3):311–331.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

