<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>1.</label> Virtanen, H., Leino-Kilpi, H. &amp; Salantera, S. (2007) Empowering<lb/> discourse in patient education. Patient Education and Counseling, 66,<lb/> 140–146.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>2.</label> Ouschan, R., Sweeney, J. C. &amp; Johnson, L. W. (2000) Dimensions of<lb/> patient empowerment: implications for professional services market-<lb/>ing. Health Marketing Quarterly, 18 (1–2), 99–114.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>3.</label> St-Cyr Tribble, D., Gallagher, F., Bell, L., et al. (2008) Empowerment<lb/> interventions, knowledge translation and exchange: perspectives of<lb/> home care professionals, clients and caregivers. BMC Health Services<lb/> Research, 8, 177.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>4.</label> Aujoulat, I., D&apos;Hoore, W. &amp; Deccache, A. (2007) Patient empower-<lb/>ment in theory and practice: polysemy or cacophony? Patient Educa-<lb/>tion and Counseling, 66, 13–20.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>5.</label> Stewart, M. A., Belle Brown, J. B., Weston, W. W., McWhinney, I. R.,<lb/> McWilliam, C. L. &amp; Freeman, T. R. (2003) In Patient-Centered Medi-<lb/>cine: Transforming the Clinical Method, 2nd edn. Cornwall: Radcliffe<lb/> Medical Press Ltd.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>6.</label> Mead, N. &amp; Bower, P. (2000) Patient-centredness: a conceptual frame-<lb/>work and review of the empirical literature. Social Science &amp; Medi-<lb/>cine, 51, 1087–1110.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>7.</label> Clay, T. (1992) Education and empowerment: securing nursing&apos;s<lb/> future. International Nursing Review, 39, 15–19.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>8.</label> Hawks, J. H. (1992) Empowerment in nursing education: concept<lb/> analysis and application to philosophy, learning and instruction.<lb/> Journal of Advanced Nursing, 17, 609–618.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>9.</label> Rodwell, C. M. (1996) An analysis of the concept of empowerment.<lb/> Journal of Advanced Nursing, 23, 305–313.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>10.</label> Ellis-Stoll, C. (1998) A concept analysis on the process of empower-<lb/>ment. ANS. Advances in Nursing Science, 21, 62–68.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>11.</label> St-Cyr Tribble, D., Gallagher, F., Paul, D. &amp; Archambault, J. (2003)<lb/> Les Pratiques D&apos;empowerment En Première Ligne. Compréhension Et<lb/> Évaluation De L&apos;efficacité Des Interventions Infirmières Et Psychoso-<lb/>ciales Conduites Auprès De Parents: Rapport De Recherche. Sher-<lb/>brooke: CSSS-IUGS.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>12.</label> World Health Organization (2002) Innovative care for chronic condi-<lb/>tions. Building blocks for action. Available at: http://www.who.int/<lb/> diabetesactiononline/about/icccglobalreport.pdf (last accessed 24 July<lb/> 2009).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>13.</label> World Health Organization (2006) What is the evidence on effective-<lb/>ness of empowerment to improve health? The Regional Office for<lb/> Europe of the World Health Organization. Available at: http://<lb/> www.euro.who.int/Document/E88086.pdf (last accessed 24 July<lb/> 2009).<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>14.</label> Loukanova, S., Molnar, R. &amp; Bridges, J. F. P. (2007) Promoting patient<lb/> empowerment in the healthcare system: highlighting the need for<lb/> patient-centered drug policy. Expert Review of Pharmacoeconomics &amp;<lb/> Outcomes Research, 7, 281–289.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>15.</label> Bossuyt, P. M. &amp; Reitsma, J. B. (2003) The STARD initiative. Lancet,<lb/> 361, 7.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>16.</label> Bossuyt, P. M., Reitsma, J. B., Bruns, D. E., et al. (2003) The STARD<lb/> statement for reporting studies of diagnostic accuracy: explanation and<lb/> elaboration. Annals of Internal Medicine, 138, w1–w12.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>17.</label> Meyer, G. J. (2003) Guidelines for reporting information in studies of<lb/> diagnostic test accuracy: the STARD initiative. Journal of Personality<lb/> Assessment, 81, 191–193.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>18.</label> Altman, D. G., Schilz, K. F., Moher, D., et al. (2001) The revised<lb/> CONSORT statement for reporting randomized trials : explanation and<lb/> elaboration. Annals of Internal Medicine, 134, 663–694.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>19.</label> Streiner, D. L. &amp; Norman, G. R. (2008) In Health Measurement<lb/> Scales: A Practical Guide to Their Development and Use, 4th edn.<lb/> Oxford: Oxford University Press.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>20.</label> Légaré, F., Moher, D., Elwyn, G., LeBlanc, A. &amp; Gravel, K. (2007)<lb/> Instruments to assess the perception of physicians in the decision-<lb/>making process of specific clinical encounters: a systematic review.<lb/> BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making, 7, 30.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>21.</label> McDowell, I. (2006) In Measuring Health. A Guide to Rating Scales<lb/> and Questionnaires, 3rd edn. New York: Oxford University Press.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>22.</label> Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. J. &amp; Maxwell, M. (1995) Care of patients<lb/> with selected health problems in fundholding practices in Scotland in<lb/> 1990 and 1992: needs, process and outcome. The British Journal of<lb/> General Practice, 45, 121–126.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>23.</label> Pawlikowska, T. R., Nowak, P. R., Szumilo-Grzesik, W. &amp; Walker, J.<lb/> J. (2002) Primary care reform: a pilot study to test the evaluative<lb/> potential of the Patient Enablement Instrument in Poland. Family<lb/> Practice, 19, 197–201.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>24.</label> Kilian, R., Lindenbach, I., Löbig, U., Uhle, M., Petscheleit, A. &amp;<lb/> Angermeyer, M. C. (2003) Indicators of empowerment and disempow-<lb/>erment in the subjective evaluation of the psychiatric treatment process<lb/> by persons with severe and persistent mental illness: a qualitative and<lb/> quantitative analysis. Social Science &amp; Medicine, 57, 1127–1142.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>25.</label> Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. &amp; Maxwell, M. (2004) Quality, core values<lb/> and the general practice consultation: issues of definition, measure-<lb/>ment and delivery. Family Practice, 21, 458–468.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>26.</label> Cottrell, R. P. F. &amp; Langzettel, M. (2005) Identifying dimensions of<lb/> empowerment in consumers of psychiatric services. Occupational<lb/> Therapy in Mental Health, 21, 13–38.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>27.</label> Gagnon, J. &amp; Grenier, R. (2004) Élaboration et validation<lb/> d&apos;indicateurs de la qualité des soins relatifs à l&apos;empowerment dans un<lb/> contexte de maladie complexe à caractère chronique. Recherche En<lb/> Soins Infirmiers, 76, 50–67.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>28.</label> van Uden-Kraan, C. F., Drossaert, C. H., Taal, E., Seydel, E. R. &amp; van<lb/> de Laar, M. A. (2009) Participation in online patient support groups<lb/> endorses patients&apos; empowerment. Patient Education and Counseling,<lb/> 74, 61–69.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>29.</label> Williamson, K. M. (2007) Home health care nurses&apos; perceptions of<lb/> empowerment. Journal of Community Health Nursing, 24, 133–153.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>30.</label> Johnson, P. T. &amp; Johnson, C. W. (1991) Power assessment inventory:<lb/> tool development. Applied Nursing Research: ANR, 4, 141–146.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>31.</label> Leddy, S. K. (1996) Development and psychometric testing of the<lb/> Leddy Healthiness Scale. Research in Nursing &amp; Health, 19, 431–440.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>32.</label> Maly, R. C., Frank, J. C., Marshall, G. N., DiMatteo, M. R. &amp; Reuben,<lb/> D. B. (1998) Perceived efficacy in patient-physician interactions<lb/> (PEPPI): validation of an instrument in older persons. Journal of the<lb/> American Geriatrics Society, 46, 889–894.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>33.</label> Coyle, J. &amp; Williams, B. (2001) Valuing people as individuals: devel-<lb/>opment of an instrument through a survey of person-centerdness in<lb/> secondary care. Journal of Advanced Nursing, 36, 450–459.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>34.</label> McDowell, J., Courtney, M., Edwards, H. &amp; Shortridge-Baggett, L.<lb/> (2005) Validation of the Australian/English version of the Diabetes<lb/> Management Self-Efficacy Scale. International Journal of Nursing<lb/> Practice, 11, 177–184.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>35.</label> Wensing, M., Vingerhoets, E. &amp; Grol, R. (2001) Functional status,<lb/> health problems, age and comorbidity in primary care patients. Quality<lb/> of Life Research, 10, 141–148.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>36.</label> Gagnon, M., Hébert, R., Dubé, M. &amp; Dubois, M. F. (2006) Develop-<lb/>ment and validation of an instrument measuring individual empower-<lb/>ment in relation to personal health care: the Health Care<lb/> Empowerment Questionnaire (HCEQ). American Journal of Health<lb/> Promotion, 20, 429–435.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>37.</label> Haughney, J., Cotton, P., Rosen, J. P., Rosen, J. P., Morrison, K. &amp;<lb/> Price, D. (2007) The use of a modification of the Patient Enablement<lb/> Instrument in asthma. Primary Care Respiratory Journal, 16, 89–92.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>38.</label> Dempsey, I. (1995) The enabling practices scale: the development of<lb/> an assessment instrument for disability services. Australia and New<lb/> Zealand Journal of Developmental Disabilities, 20, 67–73.<lb/> </bibl>
		<bibl><label>39.</label> Klakovich, M. (1995) Development and psychometric evaluation of<lb/> the reciprocal empowerment scale. Journal of Nursing Measurement,<lb/> 3, 127–143.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>40.</label> Rissel, C., Perry, C. &amp; Finnegan, J. (1996) Toward the assessment of<lb/> psychological empowerment in health promotion: initial tests of valid-<lb/>ity and reliability. Journal of the Royal Society of Health, 116, 211–<lb/> 218.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>41.</label> Rogers, E. S., Chamberlin, J., Ellison, M. L. &amp; Crean, T. (1997) A<lb/> consumer-constructed scale to measure empowerment among users of<lb/> mental health services. Psychiatric Services (Washington, DC), 48,<lb/> 1042–1047.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>42.</label> Bolton, B. &amp; Brookings, J. (1998) Development of a measure of<lb/> intrapersonal empowerment. Rehabilitation Psychology, 43, 131–142.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>43.</label> Brookings, J. B. &amp; Bolton, B. (2000) Confirmatory factor analysis of<lb/> a measure of intrapersonal empowerment. Rehabilitation Psychology,<lb/> 45 (3), 292–298.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>44.</label> Corrigan, P. W., Faber, D., Rashid, F. &amp; Leary, M. (1999) The con-<lb/>struct validity of empowerment among consumers of mental health<lb/> services. Schizophrenia Research, 38, 77–84.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>45.</label> Wowra, S. A. &amp; McCarter, R. (1999) Validation of the empowerment<lb/> scale with an outpatient mental health population. Psychiatric Services<lb/> (Washington, DC), 50, 959–961.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>46.</label> Anderson, R. M., Funnell, M. M., Fitzgerald, J. T. &amp; Marrero, D. G.<lb/> (2000) The Diabetes Empowerment Scale: a measure of psychosocial<lb/> self efficacy. Diabetes Care, 23, 739–743.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>47.</label> Speer, P. W. &amp; Peterson, N. A. (2000) Instrument development. Psy-<lb/>chometric properties of an empowerment scale: testing cognitive,<lb/> emotional, and behavioral domains. Social Work Research, 24, 109–<lb/> 118.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>48.</label> Anderson, R. M., Fitzgerald, J. T., Gruppen, L. D., Funnell, M. M. &amp;<lb/> Oh, M. S. (2003) The Diabetes Empowerment Scale-Short Form<lb/> (DES-SF). Diabetes Care, 26, 1641–1642.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>49.</label> Shiu, A. T., Wong, R. Y. &amp; Thompson, D. R. (2003) Development of<lb/> a reliable and valid Chinese version of the diabetes empowerment<lb/> scale. Diabetes Care, 26, 2817–2821.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>50.</label> Le Bossé, Y., Dufort, F. &amp; Vandette, L. (2004) L&apos;évaluation de<lb/> l&apos;empowerment des personnes: développement d&apos;une mesure<lb/> d&apos;indices psychosociologiques du pouvoir d&apos;agir (MIPPA). Canadian<lb/> Journal of Community Mental Health, 23, 91–114.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>51.</label> Hancer, M. (2005) Dimensions of the Turkish version of the<lb/> Psychological Empowerment Scale. Psychological Reports, 97, 645–<lb/> 650.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>52.</label> Hansson, L. &amp; Björkman, T. (2005) Empowerment in people with a<lb/> mental illness: reliability and validity of the Swedish version of an<lb/> empowerment scale. Scandinavian Journal of Caring Sciences, 19,<lb/> 32–38.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>53.</label> Hochwälder, J. &amp; Bergsten Brucefors, A. (2005) A psychometric<lb/> assessment of a Swedish translation of Spreitzer&apos;s empowerment<lb/> scale. Scandinavian Journal of Psychology, 46, 521–529.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>54.</label> Johnson, D. M., Worell, J. &amp; Chandler, R. K. (2005) Assessing psy-<lb/>chological health and empowerment in women: the personal progress<lb/> scale revised. Women Health, 41, 109–129.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>55.</label> Shiu, A. T., Li, S. M. &amp; Thompson, D. R. (2005) The concurrent<lb/> validity of the Chinese version of the Diabetes Empowerment Scale.<lb/> Diabetes Care, 28, 498–499.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>56.</label> Bulsara, C., Styles, I., Ward, A. M. &amp; Bulsara, M. (2006) The psy-<lb/>chometrics of developing the patient empowerment scale. Journal of<lb/> Psychosocial Oncology, 24, 1–16.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>57.</label> Mikky, I. F. (2006) Development of the Client Empowerment Scale<lb/> (CES). PhD Dissertation. University of Connecticut.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>58.</label> Peterson, N. A., Lowe, J. B., Hughey, J., Reid, R. J., Zimmerman, M.<lb/> A. &amp; Speer, P. W. (2006) Measuring the intrapersonal component of<lb/> psychological empowerment: confirmatory factor analysis of the<lb/> sociopolitical control scale. American Journal of Community Psychol-<lb/>ogy, 38, 287–297.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>59.</label> Shiu, A. T., Martin, C. R., Thompson, D. R. &amp; Wong, R. Y. (2006)<lb/> Psychometric properties of the Chinese version of the diabetes<lb/> empowerment scale. Psychology, Health &amp; Medicine, 11, 198–208.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>60.</label> Leksell, J., Funnell, M., Sandberg, G., Smide, B., Wiklund, G. &amp;<lb/> Wikblad, K. (2007) Psychometric properties of the Swedish Diabetes<lb/> Empowerment Scale. Scandinavian Journal of Caring Sciences, 21,<lb/> 247–252.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>61.</label> Stratic, E., Mirabella, F., Degli Espositi, M. &amp; Morosini, P. (2007)<lb/> Psychometric properties of the SESM, Italian version of the &apos;Con-<lb/>sumer constructed scale to measure empowerment among users of<lb/> mental health services&apos; (Rodgers et al. 1997). Epidemiologia E Psi-<lb/>chiatria Sociale, 16, 256–264.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>62.</label> Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. J. &amp; Maxwell, M. (1997) Measuring quality<lb/> in general practice. Pilot study of needs, process and outcome<lb/> measure. The Journal of the Royal College of General Practitioners.<lb/> Occasional Paper, 75, i–xii, 1–32.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>63.</label> Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. J., Maxwell, M. &amp; Walker, J. J. (1998) A<lb/> comparison of a Patient Enablement Instrument (PEI) against two<lb/> established satisfaction scales as an outcome measure of primary care<lb/> consultations. Fam Practice, 15, 165–171.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>64.</label> Price, D., Haughney, J., Rosen, J. P., Morrison, K. &amp; Howie, J. (2003)<lb/> Validation of a modified patient enablement instrument in asthma<lb/> [abstract]. The European Respiratory Journal, 22 (suppl 45),<lb/> P1701.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>65.</label> Castelein, S., van der Gaag, M., Bruggeman, R., van Busschbach, J. T.<lb/> &amp; Wiersma, D. (2008) Measuring empowerment among people with<lb/> psychotic disorders: a comparison of three instruments. Psychiatric<lb/> Services, 59, 1338–1342.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>66.</label> Klima, C., Vonderheid, S. &amp; Norr, K. (2007) Measuring empowerment<lb/> in pregnancy: the pregnancy-related empowerment scale [Abstract].<lb/> Journal of Midwifery &amp; Women&apos;s Health, 52, 531.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>67.</label> Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. J., Maxwell, M., Walker, J. J. &amp; Freeman, G.<lb/> K. (2000) Developing a &apos;consultation quality index&apos; (CQI) for use in<lb/> general practice. Family Practice, 17, 455–461.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>68.</label> Kim, S. C., Boren, D. &amp; Solem, S. L. (2001) The Kim Alliance Scale:<lb/> development and preliminary testing. Clinical Nursing Research, 10,<lb/> 314–331.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>69.</label> Chanter, C., Ashmore, S. &amp; Mandair, S. (2005) Improving the patient<lb/> experience in general practice with the General Practice Assessment<lb/> Questionnaire (GPAQ). Quality in Primary Care, 13, 225–232.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>70.</label> Mercer, S. W. &amp; Howie, J. G. (2006) CQI-2 – a new measure of<lb/> holistic interpersonal care in primary care consultations. The British<lb/> Journal of General Practice, 56, 262–268.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>71.</label> Jaturapatporn, D., Hathirat, S., Manataweewat, B., et al. (2006) Reli-<lb/>ability and validity of a Thai version of the General Practice Assess-<lb/>ment Questionnaire (GPAQ). Journal of the Medical Association of<lb/> Thailand, 89, 1491–1496.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>72.</label> Faulkner, M. (2001) A measure of patient empowerment in hospital<lb/> environments catering for older people. Journal of Advanced Nursing,<lb/> 34, 676–686.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>73.</label> Faulkner, M. (2001) Empowerment and disempowerment: models of<lb/> staff/patient interaction. NT Research, 6, 936–950.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>74.</label> Kettunen, T., Liimatainen, L., Villberg, J. &amp; Perko, U. (2006) Devel-<lb/>oping empowering health counselling measurement preliminary<lb/> results. Patient Education and Counseling, 64, 159–166.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>75.</label> Kettunen, T., Poskiparta, M. &amp; Liimatainen, L. (2001) Empowering<lb/> counselling – a case study: nurse–patient encounter in a hospital.<lb/> Health Education Research, 16, 227–238.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>76.</label> Clark, L. A. &amp; Watson, D. (1995) Constructing validity: basic issues in<lb/> objective scale development. Psychological Assessment, 7, 309–319.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>77.</label> Strickland, O. L. (2003) Using factor analysis for validity assessment:<lb/> practical considerations. Journal of Nursing Measurement, 11, 203–<lb/> 205.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>78.</label> Griffin, S. J., Kinmonth, A. L., Veltman, M. W. M., Gillard, S., Grant,<lb/> J. &amp; Stewart, M. (2004) Effect on health-related outcomes of inter-<lb/>ventions to alter the interaction between patients and practitioners : a<lb/> systematic review of trials. Annals of Family Medicine, 2, 595–608.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>79.</label> Rodgers, B. L. (2000) Concept analysis: an evolutionary view. In<lb/> Concept Development in Nursing: Foundations, Techniques and<lb/> Applications, 2nd edn (eds B. L. Rodgers &amp; K. A. Knafl), pp. 77–102.<lb/> Philadelphia, PA: Saunders.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>80.</label> Walker, L. O. &amp; Avant, K. C. (1995) Strategies for Theory Construc-<lb/>tion in Nursing East Norwalk, CT: Appleton &amp; Lange.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>81.</label> Mead, N. &amp; Bower, P. (2002) Patient-centred consultations and out-<lb/>comes in primary care : a review of the literature. Patient Education<lb/> and Counseling, 48, 51–61.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>82.</label> Gibson, C. H. (1991) A concept analysis of empowerment. Journal of<lb/> Advanced Nursing, 16, 354–361.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>83.</label> Cowger, C. D. (1994) Assessing client strengths : clinical assessment<lb/> for client empowerment. Social Work, 39, 262–268.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>84.</label> Illmann, J. (2000) Patient power. Nursing Times, 96, 28–30.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>85.</label> Poskiparta, M., Liimatainen, L., Kettunen, T. &amp; Karhila, P. (2001)<lb/> From nurse-cenered health counseling to empowermental health coun-<lb/>selling. Patient Education and Counseling, 45, 69–79.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>86.</label> Guba, E. &amp; Lincoln, Y. (1989) Fourth Generation Evaluation.<lb/> Newbury Park, CA: Sage.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>87.</label> Tu, Y. C., Wang, R. H. &amp; Yeh, S. H. (2006) Relationship between<lb/> perceived empowerment care and quality of life among elderly resi-<lb/>dents within nursing homes in Taiwan: a questionnaire survey. Inter-<lb/>national Journal of Nursing Studies, 43, 673–680.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>88.</label> McKay, B., Forbes, J. A. &amp; Bourner, K. (1990) Empowerment in<lb/> general practice: the trilogies of caring. Australian Family Physician,<lb/> 19, 513–520.<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>89.</label> Toofany, S. (2007) Empowering older people. Nursing Older People,<lb/> 19, 12–14.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

