<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl>Yaser Al-Onaizan and Kishore Papineni. 2006. Distor-<lb/>tion models for statistical machine translation. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the 21st International Conference on Com-<lb/>putational Linguistics and 44th Annual Meeting of<lb/> the Association for Computational Linguistics, pages<lb/> 529–536, Sydney, Australia, July.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Jacob Andreas, Nizar Habash, and Owen Rambow. 2011.<lb/> Fuzzy syntactic reordering for phrase-based statistical<lb/> machine translation. In Proceedings of the Sixth Work-<lb/>shop on Statistical Machine Translation, pages 227–<lb/> 236, Edinburgh, Scotland, July.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Satanjeev Banerjee and Alon Lavie. 2005. METEOR:<lb/> An automatic metric for MT evaluation with improved<lb/> correlation with human judgments. In Proceedings of<lb/> the ACL Workshop on Intrinsic and Extrinsic Evalu-<lb/>ation Measures for Machine Translation and/or Sum-<lb/>marization, pages 65–72, Ann Arbor, Michigan, June.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>A. L. Berger, P. F. Brown, S. A. Della Pietra, V. J. Della<lb/> Pietra, J. R. Gillett, A. S. Kehler, and R. L. Mercer.<lb/> 1996. Language translation apparatus and method of<lb/> using context-based translation models. United States<lb/> Patent, No. 5510981, Apr.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Alexandra Birch, Phil Blunsom, and Miles Osborne.<lb/> 2009. A quantitative analysis of reordering phenom-<lb/>ena. In StatMT &apos;09: Proceedings of the Fourth Work-<lb/>shop on Statistical Machine Translation, pages 197–<lb/> 205, Morristown, NJ, USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Alexandra Birch, Miles Osborne, and Phil Blunsom.<lb/> 2010. Metrics for MT evaluation: evaluating reorder-<lb/>ing. Machine Translation, 24(1):15–26.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Arianna Bisazza and Marcello Federico. 2012. Modi-<lb/>fied distortion matrices for phrase-based statistical ma-<lb/>chine translation. In Proceedings of the 50th Annual<lb/> Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguis-<lb/>tics (Volume 1: Long Papers), pages 478–487, Jeju Is-<lb/>land, Korea, July.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Arianna Bisazza, Daniele Pighin, and Marcello Fed-<lb/>erico. 2012. Chunk-lattices for verb reordering in<lb/> Arabic-English statistical machine translation. Ma-<lb/>chine Translation, Special Issue on MT for Arabic,<lb/> 26(1-2):85–103.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Arianna Bisazza. 2013. Linguistically Motivated Re-<lb/>ordering Modeling for Phrase-Based Statistical Ma-<lb/>chine Translation. Ph.D. thesis, University of Trento.<lb/> http://eprints-phd.biblio.unitn.it/1019/.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Marine Carpuat, Yuval Marton, and Nizar Habash. 2012.<lb/> Improved Arabic-to-English statistical machine trans-<lb/>lation by reordering post-verbal subjects for word<lb/> alignment. Machine Translation, Special Issue on MT<lb/> for Arabic, 26(1-2):105–120.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mauro Cettolo, Nicola Bertoldi, and Marcello Federico.<lb/> 2011. Methods for smoothing the optimizer instability<lb/> in SMT. In MT Summit XIII: the Thirteenth Machine<lb/> Translation Summit, pages 32–39, Xiamen, China.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Stanley F. Chen and Joshua Goodman. 1999. An empiri-<lb/>cal study of smoothing techniques for language model-<lb/>ing. Computer Speech and Language, 4(13):359–393.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Marta R. Costa-jussà and José A. R. Fonollosa. 2009.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>State-of-the-art word reordering approaches in statisti-<lb/>cal machine translation: A survey. IEICE TRANSAC-<lb/>TIONS on Information and Systems, E92-D(11):2179–<lb/> 2185.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Koby Crammer and Yoram Singer. 2003. Ultraconser-<lb/>vative online algorithms for multiclass problems. J.<lb/> Mach. Learn. Res., 3:951–991, March.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Hal Daumé III. 2004. Notes on CG and LM-BFGS op-<lb/>timization of logistic regression. Paper available at<lb/> http://pub.hal3.name, implementation avail-<lb/>able at http://hal3.name/megam.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Mona Diab, Kadri Hacioglu, and Daniel Jurafsky. 2004.<lb/> Automatic Tagging of Arabic Text: From Raw Text to<lb/> Base Phrase Chunks. In Daniel Marcu Susan Dumais<lb/> and Salim Roukos, editors, HLT-NAACL 2004: Short<lb/> Papers, pages 149–152, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Marcello Federico, Nicola Bertoldi, and Mauro Cettolo.<lb/> 2008. IRSTLM: an Open Source Toolkit for Handling<lb/> Large Scale Language Models. In Proceedings of In-<lb/>terspeech, pages 1618–1621, Melbourne, Australia.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Minwei Feng, Arne Mauser, and Hermann Ney. 2010.<lb/> A source-side decoding sequence model for statisti-<lb/>cal machine translation. In Conference of the Associa-<lb/>tion for Machine Translation in the Americas (AMTA),<lb/> Denver, Colorado, USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Michel Galley and Christopher D. Manning. 2008. A<lb/> simple and effective hierarchical phrase reordering<lb/> model. In EMNLP &apos;08: Proceedings of the Confer-<lb/>ence on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Pro-<lb/>cessing, pages 848–856, Morristown, NJ, USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Spence Green, Conal Sathi, and Christopher D. Man-<lb/>ning. 2009. NP subject detection in verb-initial Ara-<lb/>bic clauses. In Proceedings of the Third Workshop<lb/> on Computational Approaches to Arabic Script-based<lb/> Languages (CAASL3), Ottawa, Canada.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Spence Green, Michel Galley, and Christopher D. Man-<lb/>ning. 2010. Improved models of distortion cost for<lb/> statistical machine translation. In Human Language<lb/> Technologies: The 2010 Annual Conference of the<lb/> North American Chapter of the Association for Com-<lb/>putational Linguistics (NAACL), pages 867–875, Los<lb/> Angeles, California.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Magnus R. Hestenes and Eduard Stiefel. 1952. Meth-<lb/>ods of conjugate gradients for solving linear systems.<lb/> Journal of Research of the National Bureau of Stan-<lb/>dards, 49(6):409–436.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>H. Johnson, J. Martin, G. Foster, and R. Kuhn. 2007. Im-<lb/>proving translation quality by discarding most of the<lb/> phrasetable. In In Proceedings of EMNLP-CoNLL 07,<lb/> pages 967–975.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Philipp Koehn, Franz Josef Och, and Daniel Marcu.<lb/> 2003. Statistical phrase-based translation. In Proceed-<lb/>ings of HLT-NAACL 2003, pages 127–133, Edmonton,<lb/> Canada.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Philipp Koehn, Amittai Axelrod, Alexandra Birch<lb/> Mayne, Chris Callison-Burch, Miles Osborne, and<lb/> David Talbot. 2005. Edinburgh system description<lb/> for the 2005 IWSLT speech translation evaluation. In<lb/> Proc. of the International Workshop on Spoken Lan-<lb/>guage Translation, October.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>P. Koehn, H. Hoang, A. Birch, C. Callison-Burch,<lb/> M. Federico, N. Bertoldi, B. Cowan, W. Shen,<lb/> C. Moran, R. Zens, C. Dyer, O. Bojar, A. Constantin,<lb/> and E. Herbst. 2007. Moses: Open Source Toolkit<lb/> for Statistical Machine Translation. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 45th Annual Meeting of the Association for Com-<lb/>putational Linguistics Companion Volume Proceed-<lb/>ings of the Demo and Poster Sessions, pages 177–180,<lb/> Prague, Czech Republic.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Ravi Kumar and Sergei Vassilvitskii. 2010. General-<lb/>ized distances between rankings. In Proceedings of<lb/> the 19th international conference on World Wide Web,<lb/> pages 571–580, New York, NY, USA. ACM.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Percy Liang, Ben Taskar, and Dan Klein. 2006. Align-<lb/>ment by agreement. In Proceedings of the Human<lb/> Language Technology Conference of the NAACL, Main<lb/> Conference, pages 104–111, New York City, USA,<lb/> June.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Ryan McDonald, Fernando Pereira, Kiril Ribarov, and<lb/> Jan Hajič. 2005. Non-projective dependency parsing<lb/> using spanning tree algorithms. In Proceedings of the<lb/> conference on Human Language Technology and Em-<lb/>pirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, HLT<lb/> &apos;05, pages 523–530, Stroudsburg, PA, USA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Robert C. Moore and Chris Quirk. 2007. Faster beam-<lb/>search decoding for phrasal statistical machine transla-<lb/>tion. In In Proceedings of MT Summit XI, pages 321–<lb/> 327, Copenhagen, Denmark.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>F. Och and H. Ney. 2002. Discriminative training<lb/> and maximum entropy models for statistical machine<lb/> translation. In Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meet-<lb/>ing of the Association for Computational Linguistics<lb/> (ACL), pages 295–302, Philadelhpia, PA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Franz Josef Och. 2003. Minimum Error Rate Training<lb/> in Statistical Machine Translation. In Erhard Hinrichs<lb/> and Dan Roth, editors, Proceedings of the 41st Annual<lb/> Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguis-<lb/>tics, pages 160–167.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Kishore Papineni, Salim Roukos, Todd Ward, and Wei-<lb/>Jing Zhu. 2002. BLEU: a method for automatic eval-<lb/>uation of machine translation. In Proceedings of the<lb/> 40th Annual Meeting of the Association of Compu-<lb/>tational Linguistics (ACL), pages 311–318, Philadel-<lb/>phia, PA.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Stefan Riezler and John T. Maxwell. 2005. On some<lb/> pitfalls in automatic evaluation and significance test-<lb/>ing for MT. In Proceedings of the ACL Workshop on<lb/> Intrinsic and Extrinsic Evaluation Measures for Ma-<lb/>chine Translation and/or Summarization, pages 57–<lb/> 64, Ann Arbor, Michigan, June.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Christoph Tillmann. 2004. A Unigram Orientation<lb/> Model for Statistical Machine Translation. In Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the Joint Conference on Human Language<lb/> Technologies and the Annual Meeting of the North<lb/> American Chapter of the Association of Computa-<lb/>tional Linguistics (HLT-NAACL).<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Karthik Visweswariah, Rajakrishnan Rajkumar, Ankur<lb/> Gandhe, Ananthakrishnan Ramanathan, and Jiri<lb/> Navratil. 2011. A word reordering model for im-<lb/>proved machine translation. In Proceedings of the<lb/> 2011 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natu-<lb/>ral Language Processing, pages 486–496, Edinburgh,<lb/> Scotland, UK., July.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Dekai Wu. 1997. Stochastic inversion transduction<lb/> grammars and bilingual parsing of parallel corpora.<lb/> Computational Linguistics, 23(3):377–403.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Sirvan Yahyaei and Christof Monz. 2010. Dynamic dis-<lb/>tortion in a discriminative reordering model for sta-<lb/>tistical machine translation. In International Work-<lb/>shop on Spoken Language Translation (IWSLT), Paris,<lb/> France.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>Richard Zens and Hermann Ney. 2006. Discriminative<lb/> reordering models for statistical machine translation.<lb/> In Proceedings on the Workshop on Statistical Ma-<lb/>chine Translation, pages 55–63, New York City, June.<lb/> </bibl>
<bibl>R. Zens, F. J. Och, and H. Ney. 2002. Phrase-based sta-<lb/>tistical machine translation. In 25th German Confer-<lb/>ence on Artificial Intelligence (KI2002), pages 18–32,<lb/> Aachen, Germany. Springer Verlag.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

