<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_D_-1"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>
			References
<bibl> <label>[1]</label> F. Dubois, M. Salaü, and S. Salmon, Vorticity-velocity-pressure and stream function- vorticity formulations for the Stokes problem, J Math Pures Appl 82 (2003), 1395–1451.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[2]</label> C. B` egue, C. Conca, F. Murat, and O. Pironneau, " Les equations de Stokes et de Navier- Stokes avec des conditions aux limites sur la pression, " In Nonlinear Partial Differential Equations and their Applications,Colì ege de France Seminar Vol. IX, 1988, p. 179–264.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[3]</label> V. Girault, Incompressible Finite Element Methods for Navier-Stokes Equations with Non- standard Boundary Conditions in R 3 , Math Comput 183 (1988), 55–74.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[4]</label> M. Amara, D. Capatina-Papaghiuc, E. Chacó-Vera, and D. Trujillo, Vorticity-velocity- pressure formulation for Navier-Stokes equations, Comput Vis Sci 6 (2004), 47–52.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[5]</label> M. Amara, E. Chacó-Vera, and D. Trujillo, Vorticity-velocity-pressure formulation for the Stokes equations, Math Comput 73 (2004), 1673–1697.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[6]</label> M. Aza¨ , C. Bernardi, and N. Chorfi, Spectral discretization of the vorticity, velocity and pressure formulation of the Navier-Stokes equations, Numer Math 104 (2006), 1–26.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[7]</label> F. Dubois, Vorticity-velocity-pressure formulation for the Stokes problem, Math Meth Appl Sci 25 (2002), 1091–1191.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[8]</label> F. Dubois, M. Salaü, and S. Salmon, First vorticity-velocity-pressure numerical scheme for the Stokes problem, Comput Meth Appl Mech Eng 192 (2003), 4877–4907.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[9]</label> H. Abboud, F. El Chami, and T. Sayah, A priori and a posteriori estimates for three- dimensional Stokes equations with nonstandard boundary conditions, Numer Methods Par- tial Differ Equations 28 (2012), 1178–1193.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[10]</label> C. Bernardi and N. Chorfi, Spectral discretization of the vorticity, velocity and pressure formulation of the Stokes equations, SIAM J Numer Anal 44 (2006), 826–850.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[11]</label> M.M.J. Proot and M.I. Gerrtisma, Least-Squares spectral elements applied to the Stokes problem, J Comput Phys 181 (2002), 454–477.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[12]</label> F.H. Harlow and F.E. Welch, Numerical calculations of time dependent viscous incompress- ible flow of fluids with a free surface, Phys Fluids 8 (1965), 2182–2189.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[13]</label> R.A. Nicolaides, T.A. Porshing, and C.A. Hall, " Covolume methods, " In computational fluid dynamics review, M. Hafez and K. Oshma (Editors), John Wiley and sons, 1995, p. 279–299.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[14] S.</label> Delcourte, K. Domelevo, and P. Omnes, " Discrete duality finite volume method for sec- ond order elliptic problems, " In Finite Volumes for Complex Applications IV, F. Benkhal- doun, D. Ouazar and S. Raghay (Editors), Hermes Science publishing, 2005, p. 447–458.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[15]</label> K. Domelevo and P. Omnes, A finite volume method for the Laplace equation on almost arbitrary two-dimensional grids, Math Model Numer Anal 39 (2005), 1203–1249.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[16]</label> F. Hermeline, A finite volume method for the approximation of diffusion operators on distorted meshes, J Comput Phys 160 (2000), 481–499.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[17] F.</label> Hermeline, Approximation of diffusion operators with discontinuous tensor coefficients on distorted meshes, Comput Methods Appl Mech Eng 192 (2003), 1939–1959.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[18]</label> B. Andreianov, F. Boyer, and F. Hubert, Discrete duality finite volume schemes for Leray- Lions-type elliptic problems on general 2D meshes, Numer Methods Partial Differ Equations 23 (2007), 145–195.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[19]</label> F. Boyer and F. Hubert, Finite volume method for 2D linear and nonlinear elliptic problems with discontinuities, SIAM J Numer Anal 46 (2008), 3032–3070.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[20] Y.</label> Coudì ere and F. Hubert, A 3D discrete duality finite volume method for nonlinear elliptic equations, SIAM J Sci Comput 33 (2011), 1739–1764.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[21]</label> Y.Coudì ere and G. Manzini, The discrete duality finite volume method for convection- diffusion problems, SIAM J Numer Anal 47 (2010), 4163–4192.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[22]</label> B. Andreianov, M. Bendahmane, K. H. Karlsen, and C. Pierre, Convergence of discrete duality finite volume schemes for the cardiac bidomain model, Networks and Heterogeneous Media 6 (2011), 195–240.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[23]</label> Y.Coudì ere, C. Pierre, O. Rousseau, and R. Turpault, A 2D/3D Discrete Duality Finite Volume Scheme. Application to ECG simulation, Int J Finite Volumes 6 (2009), electronic only.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[24]</label> C. Chainais-Hillairet, Discrete duality finite volume schemes for two-dimensional drift- diffusion and energy-transport models, Internat J Numer Methods Fluids 59 (2009), 239– 257.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[25]</label> S. Delcourte, K. Domelevo, and P. Omnes, A discrete duality finite volume approach to Hodge decomposition and div-curl problems on almost arbitrary two-dimensional meshes, SIAM J Numer Anal 45 (2007), 1142–1174.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[26]</label> F. Hermeline, S. Layouni, and P. Omnes, A finite volume method for the approximation of Maxwell's equations in two space dimensions on arbitrary meshes, J Comput Phys 227 (2008), 9365–9388.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[27]</label> S. Delcourte, Dé de mé de volumes finis pour la mé des flu- ides, Ph.D. Thesis (in French), University of Toulouse III, France, 2007. Available at http://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-00200833/fr/</bibl> 
<bibl>[28] S. Krell, Stabilized DDFV Schemes for Stokes Problem with Variable Viscosity on General 2D Meshes, Numer Methods Partial Differential Eq (2011), 1666–1706.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[29] S.</label> Krell, Finite volume method for general multifluid flows governed by the interface Stokes problem, Math Models Methods Appl Sci 22 (2012), 1150025, 35 p.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[30]</label> S. Krell and G. Manzini, The discrete duality finite volume method for Stokes equations on three-dimensional polyhedral meshes, SIAM J Numer Anal 50 (2012), 808–837.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[31]</label> P. Blanc, R. Eymard, and R. Herbin, A staggered finite volume scheme on general meshes for the generalized Stokes problem in two space dimensions, Int J Finite Volumes 2 (2005), electronic only.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[32]</label> R. Eymard and R. Herbin, A staggered finite volume scheme on general meshes for the Navier-Stokes equations in two space dimensions, Int J Finite Volumes 2 (2005), electronic only.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[33]</label> R. Eymard, J.C. Latché, and R. Herbin, On a stabilized collocated finite volume scheme for the Stokes problem. Math Model Numer Anal 40 (2006), 501–527.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[34]</label> R. Eymard, J.C. Latché, and R. Herbin, Convergence analysis of a colocated finite volume scheme for the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations on general 2 or 3D meshes, SIAM J Numer Anal 45 (2007), 1–36.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[35]</label> A.H. Le and P. Omnes, Discrete Poincaré inequalities for arbitrary meshes in the discrete duality finite volume context, ETNA, Electronic Transactions on Numerical Analysis 40 (2013), 94–119.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[36]</label> S. Heib, Nouvelles discré non structuré pour des ecoulements de fluides a incom- pressibilité renforcé (in French), Ph.D. Thesis, Université Pierre et Marie Curie, Paris, France, 2002.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[37]</label> C. Bernardi and F. Hecht, More pressure in the finite element discretization of the Stokes Problem, Math Model Numer Anal 34 (2000), 953–980.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[38]</label> M. Crouzeix and P.-A. Raviart, Conforming and nonconforming finite element methods for solving the stationary Stokes equations, RAIRO Anal Numer 7 (1973), 33–76.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[39]</label> V. Girault and P.-A. Raviart, Finite Element Methods for Navier-Stokes Equations, Springer-Verlag, Berlin, 1986.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[40]</label> P.G. Ciarlet, The finite element method for elliptic problems, North Holland publishing company, 1978.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[41]</label> L.E. Payne, and H.F. Weinberger, An optimal Poincaré inequality for convex domain. Arch Rational Mech Anal 5 (1960), 286–292.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[42]</label> C. Carstensen and S. Funken, Constants in Clé-interpolation error and residual based a posteriori estimates in finite element methods, East-West J Numer Math 8 (2000), 153–175.</bibl> 
<bibl>[43] R. Verfü, Error estimates for some quasi-interpolation operators, Math Model Numer Anal 33 (1999), 695–713.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[44]</label> M. Bercovier and M. Engelman, A finite element for the numerical solution of viscous incompressible flows, J Comput Phys 30 (1979), 181–201.</bibl>
<bibl> <label>[45]</label> V. Ruas, Mé vitesse-tourbillon pour les equations de Navier-Stokes, in: Actes du 29 eme congr es d'Analyse Numé, Canum'97 (1997), 329–330.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

