<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_D_-1"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>
References
<bibl>Albert TJ, Molla MN, Muzny DM, Nazareth L, Wheeler D, et al: Direct selection of human genomic loci by microarray hybridization. Nat Methods 4: 903–905 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Aleck KA, Argueso L, Stone J, Hackel JG, Erick- son RP: True hermaphroditism with partial duplication of chromosome 22 and without SRY . Am J Med Genet 85: 2–4 (1999).</bibl>
<bibl>Andrieux J, Dubourg C, Rio M, Attie-Bitach T, Delaby E, et al: Genotype-phenotype corre- lation in four 15q24 deleted patients identi- fied by array-CGH. Am J Med Genet A 149A:2813–2819 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Ansorge WJ: Next-generation DNA sequencing techniques. N Biotechnol 25: 195–203 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Audi L, Fernández-Cancio M, Carrascosa A, Andaluz P, Torán N, et al: Novel (60%) and recurrent (40%) androgen receptor gene mu- tations in a series of 59 patients with a 46,XY disorder of sex development. J Clin Endocri- nol Metab 95: 1876–1888 (2010).</bibl>
<bibl>Barbaro M, Oscarson M, Schoumans J, Staaf J, Ivarsson SA, Wedell A: Isolated 46,XY go- nadal dysgenesis in two sisters caused by a Xp21.2 interstitial duplication containing the DAX1 gene. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 92: 3305–3313 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Barbaro M, Balsamo A, Anderlid BM, Myhre AG, Gennari M, et al: Characterization of deletions at 9p affecting the candidate re- gions for sex reversal and deletion 9p syn- drome by MLPA. Eur J Hum Genet 17: 1439– 1447 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Bardoni B, Zanaria E, Guioli S, Floridia G, Wor- ley KC, et al: A dosage sensitive locus at chro- mosome Xp21 is involved in male to female sex reversal. Nat Genet 7: 497–501 (1994).</bibl>
<bibl>Bentley DR, Balasubramanian S, Swerdlow HP, Smith GP, Milton J, et al: Accurate whole hu- man genome sequencing using reversible terminator chemistry. Nature 456: 53–59 (2008).</bibl> 
<bibl>Beroukhim R, Mermel CH, Porter D, Wei G, Raychaudhuri S, et el: The landscape of so- matic copy-number alteration across human cancers. Nature 463: 899–905 (2010).</bibl>
<bibl>Bignell GR, Huang J, Greshock J, Watt S, Butler A, et al: High-resolution analysis of DNA copy number using oligonucleotide microar- rays. Genome Res 14: 287–295 (2004).</bibl>
<bibl>Bogani D, Siggers P, Brixey R, Warr N, Beddow S, et al: Loss of mitogen-activated protein ki- nase kinase kinase 4 (MAP3K4) reveals a re- quirement for MAPK signalling in mouse sex determination. PLoS Biol 7:e1000196 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Branton D, Deamer DW, Marziali A, Bayley H, Benner SA, et al: The potential and challeng- es of nanopore sequencing. Nat Biotechnol 26: 1146–1153 (2008).</bibl>
<bibl>Brouzes E, Medkova M, Savenelli N, Marran D, Twardowski M, et al: Droplet microfluidic technology for single-cell high-throughput screening. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 106: 14195–14200 (2009).</bibl> 
<bibl>de Kovel CG, Trucks H, Helbig I, Mefford HC, Baker C, et al: Recurrent microdeletions at 15q11.2 and 16p13.11 predispose to idiopath- ic generalized epilepsies. Brain 133: 23–32 (2010).</bibl>
<bibl>Erickson RP, Skinner S, Jacquet H, Campion D, Buckley PG, et al: Does chromosome 22 have anything to do with sex determination: fur- ther studies on a 46,XX,22q11.2 del male.</bibl>
<bibl>Am J Med Genet A 123A:64–67 (2003) Fedurco M, Romieu A, Williams S, Lawrence I, Turcatti G: BTA, a novel reagent for DNA at- tachment on glass and efficient generation of solid-phase amplified glass and efficient generation of solid-phase amplified DNA colonies. Nucleic Acids Res 34:e22 (2006).</bibl>
<bibl>Fukami M, Wada Y, Miyabayashi K, Nishino I, Hasegawa T, et al: CXorf6 is a causative gene for hypospadias. Nat Genet 38: 1369–1371 (2006).</bibl>
<bibl>Girirajan S, Rosenfeld JA, Cooper GM, Antonac- ci F, Siswara P, et al: A recurrent 16p12.1 mi- crodeletion supports a two-hit model for se- vere developmental delay. Nat Genet 42: 203–209 (2010).</bibl>
<bibl>Glessner JT, Hakonarson H: Common variants in polygenic schizophrenia. Genome Biol 10: 236 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Gnirke A, Melnikov A, Maguire J, Rogov P, LeP- roust EM, et al: Solution hybrid selection with ultralong oligonucleotides for massive- ly parallel targeted sequencing. Nature Bio- tech 27: 182–189 (2009).</bibl> 
<bibl>Harris TD, Buzby PR, Babcock H, Beer E, Bowers J, et al: Single-molecule DNA sequencing of a viral genome. Science 320: 106–109 (2008).</bibl>
<bibl>Hartmann A, Thieme M, Nanduri LK, Stempfl T, Moehle C, et al: Validation of microarray- based resequencing of 93 worldwide mito- chondrial genomes. Hum Mutat 30: 115–122 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Hodges E, Xuan Z, Balija V, Kramer M, Molla MN, et al: Genome-wide in situ exon capture for selective resequencing. Nature Genet 39: 1522–1527 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Huang B, Wang S, Ning Y, Lamb AN, Bartley J: Autosomal XX sex reversal caused by dupli- cation of SOX9 . Am J Med Genet 87: 349–353 (1999).</bibl>
<bibl>Hughes IA, Houk C, Ahmed SF, Lee PA; LWPES Consensus Group; ESPE Consensus Group: Consensus statement on management of in- tersex disorders. Arch Dis Child 91: 554–563 (2006).</bibl>
<bibl>Kallioniemi A, Kallioniemi OP, Sudar D, Ruto- vitz D, Gray JW, et al: Comparative genomic hybridization for molecular cytogenetic analysis of solid tumors. Science 258: 818– 821 (1992).</bibl>
<bibl>Köhler B, Lin L, Mazen I, Cetindag C, Bieber- mann H, et al: The spectrum of phenotypes associated with mutations in steroidogenic factor 1 (SF-1, NR5A1, Ad4BP) includes severe penoscrotal hypospadias in 46,XY males without adrenal insufficiency. Eur J Endocrinol 161: 237–242 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Leamon JH: A massively parallel PicoTiterPlate based platform for discrete picoliter-scale polymerase chain reactions. Electrophoresis 24: 3769–3777 (2003).</bibl> 
<bibl>Le Caignec C, Delnatte C, Vermeesch JR, Boceno M, Joubert M, et al: Complete sex reversal in a WAGR syndrome patient. Am J Med Genet A 143A:2692–2695 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Lecointre C, Pichon O, Hamel A, Heloury Y, Mi- chel-Calemard L, et al: Familial acampo- melic form of campomelic dysplasia caused by a 960 kb deletion upstream of SOX9 . Am J Med Genet A 149A:1183–1189 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Lipshutz RJ, Fodor SP, Gingeras TR, Lockhart DJ: High density synthetic oligonucleotide arrays. Nat Genet 21 Suppl 1: 20–24 (1999).</bibl>
<bibl>Lourenço D, Brauner R, Lin L, De Perdigo A, Weryha G, et al: Mutations in NR5A1 associ- ated with ovarian insufficiency. N Engl J Med 360: 1200–1210 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Lucito R, Healy J, Alexander J, Reiner A, Esposi- to D, et al: Representational oligonucleotide microarray analysis: a high-resolution meth- od to detect genome copy number variation.</bibl>
<bibl>Genome Res 13: 2291–2305 (2003).</bibl>
<bibl>Mandal MN, Heckenlively JR, Burch T, Chen L, Vasireddy V, et al: Sequencing arrays for screening multiple genes associated with early-onset human retinal degenerations on a high-throughput platform. Invest Oph- thalmol Vis Sci 46: 3355–3362 (2005).</bibl>
<bibl>Margulies M, Egholm M, Altman WE, Attiya S, Bader JS, et al: Genome sequencing in micro- fabricated high-density picolitre reactors. Nature 437: 376–380 (2005).</bibl>
<bibl>McElreavey K, Rappaport R, Vilain E, Abbas N, Richaud F, et al: A minority of 46,XX true hermaphrodites are positive for the Y-DNA sequence including SRY . Hum Genet 90: 121– 125 (1992a).</bibl>
<bibl>McElreavey K, Vilain E, Abbas N, Costa JM, Souleyreau N, et al: XY sex reversal associ- ated with a deletion 5 񮽙 to the SRY 'HMG box' in the testis-determining region. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 89: 11016–11020 (1992b).</bibl>
<bibl>McElreavey K, Fellous M. Sex determination and the Y chromosome. Am J Med Genet 89: 176– 185 (1999).</bibl>
<bibl>McKernan KJ, Peckham HE, Costa GL, McLaughlin SF, Fu Y, et al: Sequence and structural variation in a human genome un- covered by short-read, massively parallel li- gation sequencing using two-base encoding.</bibl>
<bibl>Genome Res 19: 1527–1541 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>McPherson JD: Next-generation gap. Nat Meth- ods 6(suppl 11):S2–S5 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Medvedev P, Stanciu M, Brudno M: Computa- tional methods for discovering structural variation with next-generation sequencing. Nat Methods 6(suppl 11):S13–S20 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Metzker ML: Sequencing technologies – the next generation. Nat Rev Genet 11: 31–46 (2010).</bibl>
<bibl>Ng SB, Turner EH, Robertson PD, Flygare SD, Bigham AW, et al: Targeted capture and mas- sively parallel sequencing of 12 human exomes. Nature 461: 272–276 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Ng SB, Buckingham KJ, Lee C, Bigham AW, Ta- bor HK, et al: Exome sequencing identifies the cause of a mendelian disorder. Nat Genet 42: 30–35 (2010).</bibl>
<bibl>Ogata T, Muroya K, Sasagawa I, Kosho T, Wakui K, et al: Genetic evidence for a novel gene(s) involved in urogenital development on 10q26. Kidney Int 58: 2281–2290 (2000).</bibl>
<bibl>Pinkel D, Segraves R, Sudar D, Clark S, Poole I, et al: High resolution analysis of DNA copy number variation using comparative ge- nomic hybridization to microarrays. Nat Genet 20: 207–211 (1998).</bibl>
<bibl>Pitteloud N, Quinton R, Pearce S, Raivio T, Aci- erno J, et al: Digenic mutations account for variable phenotypes in idiopathic hypogo- nadotropic hypogonadism. J Clin Invest 117: 457–463 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Porreca GJ, Zhang K, Li JB, Xie B, Austin D, et al: Multiplex amplification of large sets of human exons. Nature Methods 4: 931–936 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Porter FD: Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome: pathogenesis, diagnosis and management.</bibl>
<bibl>Eur J Hum Genet 16: 535–541 (2008).</bibl>
<bibl>Refai O, Friedman A, Terry L, Jewett T, Pearlman A, et al: De novo 12; 17 translocation up- stream of SOX9 resulting in 46,XX testicular disorder of sex development. Am J Med Gen- et A 152A:422–426 (2010).</bibl>
<bibl>Ronaghi M, Karamohamed S, Pettersson B, Uhlé n M, Nyré n P: Real-time DNA sequenc- ing using detection of pyrophosphate re- lease. Anal Biochem 242: 84–89 (1996).</bibl>
<bibl>Schlaubitz S, Yatsenko SA, Smith LD, Keller KL, Vissers LE, et al: Ovotestes and XY sex rever- sal in a female with an interstitial 9q33.3– q34.1 deletion encompassing NR5A1 and LMX1B causing features of Genitopatellar syndrome. Am J Med Genet A 143A:1071– 1081 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Schlessinger D, Garcia-Ortiz JE, Forabosco A, Uda M, Crisponi L, Pelosi E: Determination and stability of gonadal sex. J Androl 31: 16– 25 (2010).</bibl>
<bibl>Schnack TH, Zdravkovic S, Myrup C, Wester- gaard T, Christensen K, et al: Familial aggre- gation of hypospadias: a cohort study. Am J Epidemiol 167: 251–256 (2008).</bibl>
<bibl>Seeherunvong T, Perera EM, Bao Y, Benke PJ, Be- nigno A, et al: 46,XX sex reversal with partial duplication of chromosome arm 22q. Am J Med Genet A 127A:149–151 (2004).</bibl>
<bibl>Sekido R, Lovell-Badge R: Sex determination in- volves synergistic action of SRY and SF1 on a specific Sox9 enhancer. Nature 453: 930–934 (2008).</bibl>
<bibl>Sekido R, Lovell-Badge R: Sex determination and SRY : down to a wink and a nudge? Trends Genet 25: 19–29 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Sharp AJ, Selzer RR, Veltman JA, Gimelli S, Gi- melli G, et al: Characterization of a recurrent 15q24 microdeletion syndrome. Hum Mol Genet 16: 567–752 (2007).</bibl> 
<bibl>Smith CA, Roeszler KN, Ohnesorg T, Cummins DM, Farlie PG, et al: The avian Z-linked gene DMRT1 is required for male sex determina- tion in the chicken. Nature 461: 267–271 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Smyk M, Berg JS, Pursley A, Curtis FK, Fernan- dez BA, et al: Male-to-female sex reversal associated with an approximately 250 kb deletion upstream of NR0B1 (DAX1). Hum Genet 122: 63–70 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Solinas-Toldo S, Lampel S, Stilgenbauer S, Nick- olenko J, Benner A, et al: Matrix-based com- parative genomic hybridization: biochips to screen for genomic imbalances. Genes Chro- mosomes Cancer 20: 399–407 (1997).</bibl>
<bibl>Sultan C, Biason-Lauber A, Philibert P: Mayer- Rokitansky-Kuster-Hauser syndrome: re- cent clinical and genetic findings. Gynecol Endocrinol 25: 8–11 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Szoke D, Molnar B, Solymosi N, Racz K, Gergics P, et al: Polymorphisms of the ApoE , HS- D3B1 , IL-1beta and p53 genes are associated with the development of early uremic com- plications in diabetic patients: results of a DNA resequencing array study. Int J Mol Med 23: 217–227 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Temel SG, Gulten T, Yakut T, Saglam H, Kilic N, et al: Extended pedigree with multiple cases of XX sex reversal in the absence of SRY and of a mutation at the SOX9 locus. Sex Dev 1: 24–34 (2007).</bibl> 
<bibl>Bashamboo /Ledig /Wieacker / Tewhey R, Warner JB, Nakano M, Libby B, Med- kova M, et al: Microdroplet-based PCR en- richment for large-scale targeted sequenc- ing. Nat Biotechnol 27: 1025–1031 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Turner EH, Lee C, Ng SB, Nickerson DA, Shen- dure J: Massively parallel exon capture and library-free resequencing across 16 genomes. Nature Methods 6: 315–316 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Uhlenhaut NH, Jakob S, Anlag K, Eisenberger T, Sekido R, et al: Somatic sex reprogramming of adult ovaries to testes by FOXL2 ablation. Cell 139: 1130–1142 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Valouev A, Ichikawa J, Tonthat T, Stuart J, Ranade S, et al: A high-resolution, nucleo- some position map of C. elegans reveals a lack of universal sequence-dictated position- ing. Genome Res 18: 1051–1063 (2008).</bibl> 
<bibl>van Silfhout A, Boot AM, Dijkhuizen T, Hoek A, Nijman R, et al: A unique 970 kb microdele- tion in 9q33.3, including the NR5A1 gene in a 46,XY female. Eur J Med Genet 52: 157–160 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Vinci G, Chantot-Bastaraud S, El Houate B, Lor- tat-Jacob S, Brauner R, et al: Association of deletion of 9p, 46,XY gonadal dysgenesis and autistic spectrum disorder. Mol Hum Re- prod 13: 685–689 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Voelkerding KV, Dames SA, Durtschi JD: Next- generation sequencing: from basic research to diagnostics. Clin Chem 55: 641–658 (2009).</bibl>
<bibl>Vogelstein B: Transforming single DNA mole- cules into fluorescent magnetic particles for detection and enumeration of genetic varia- tions. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 100: 8817– 8822 (2003).</bibl>
<bibl>Wieacker P, Volleth M: WNT4 and RSPO1 are not involved in a case of male-to-female sex reversal with partial duplication of 1p. Sex Dev 1: 111–113 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Wilhelm D, Palmer S, Koopman P: Sex determi- nation and gonadal development in mam- mals. Physiol Rev 87: 1–28 (2007).</bibl>
<bibl>Zhang F, Gu W, Hurles ME, Lupski JR: Copy number variation in human health, disease, and evolution. Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet 10: 451–481 (2009).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

