<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>1</label>. Hershko, A., and Ciechanover, A. (1998) The ubiquitin system. Annu. Rev.<lb/> Biochem. 67, 425-479 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>2</label>. Pickart, C. M., and Eddins, M. J. (2004) Ubiquitin: structures, functions,<lb/> mechanisms. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1695, 55-72 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>3</label>. Buetow, L., and Huang, D. T. (2016) Structural insights into the catalysis<lb/> and regulation of E3 ubiquitin ligases. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 17,<lb/> 626 -642 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>4</label>. Dye, B. T., and Schulman, B. A. (2007) Structural mechanisms underlying<lb/> posttranslational modification by ubiquitin-like proteins. Annu. Rev. Bio-<lb/>phys. Biomol. Struct. 36, 131-150 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>5</label>. Dynek, J. N., and Vucic, D. (2013) Antagonists of IAP proteins as cancer<lb/> therapeutics. Cancer Lett 332, 206 -214 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>6</label>. Hu, S., and Yang, X. (2003) Cellular inhibitor of apoptosis 1 and 2 are<lb/> ubiquitin ligases for the apoptosis inducer Smac/DIABLO. J. Biol. Chem.<lb/> 278, 10055-10060 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>7</label>. Eckelman, B. P., and Salvesen, G. S. (2006) The human anti-apoptotic<lb/> proteins cIAP1 and cIAP2 bind but do not inhibit caspases. J. Biol. Chem.<lb/> 281, 3254 -3260 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>8</label>. Choi, Y. E., Butterworth, M., Malladi, S., Duckett, C. S., Cohen, G. M., and<lb/> Bratton, S. B. (2009) The E3 ubiquitin ligase cIAP1 binds and ubiquitinates<lb/> caspase-3 and -7 via unique mechanisms at distinct steps in their pro-<lb/>cessing. J. Biol. Chem. 284, 12772-12782 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>9</label>. Peltzer, N., Darding, M., and Walczak, H. (2016) Holding RIPK1 on the<lb/> Ubiquitin leash in TNFR1 signaling. Trends Cell Biol. 26, 445-461<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>10</label>. Bertrand, M. J., Milutinovic, S., Dickson, K. M., Ho, W. C., Boudreault, A.,<lb/> Durkin, J., Gillard, J. W., Jaquith, J. B., Morris, S. J., and Barker, P. A. (2008)<lb/> cIAP1 and cIAP2 facilitate cancer cell survival by functioning as E3 ligases<lb/> that promote RIP1 ubiquitination. Mol. Cell 30, 689 -700 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>11</label>. Varfolomeev, E., Goncharov, T., Fedorova, A. V., Dynek, J. N., Zobel, K.,<lb/> Deshayes, K., Fairbrother, W. J., and Vucic, D. (2008) c-IAP1 and c-IAP2<lb/> are critical mediators of tumor necrosis factor ␣ (TNF␣)-induced NF-B<lb/> activation. J. Biol. Chem. 283, 24295-24299 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>12</label>. Haas, T. L., Emmerich, C. H., Gerlach, B., Schmukle, A. C., Cordier, S. M.,<lb/> Rieser, E., Feltham, R., Vince, J., Warnken, U., Wenger, T., Koschny, R.,<lb/> Komander, D., Silke, J., and Walczak, H. (2009) Recruitment of the linear<lb/> ubiquitin chain assembly complex stabilizes the TNF-R1 signaling com-<lb/>plex and is required for TNF-mediated gene induction. Mol. Cell 36,<lb/> 831-844 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>13</label>. Tokunaga, F., Sakata, S., Saeki, Y., Satomi, Y., Kirisako, T., Kamei, K.,<lb/> Nakagawa, T., Kato, M., Murata, S., Yamaoka, S., Yamamoto, M., Akira, S.,<lb/> Takao, T., Tanaka, K., and Iwai, K. (2009) Involvement of linear polyubiq-<lb/>uitylation of NEMO in NF-B activation. Nat. Cell Biol. 11, 123-132<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>14</label>. Gerlach, B., Cordier, S. M., Schmukle, A. C., Emmerich, C. H., Rieser, E.,<lb/> Haas, T. L., Webb, A. I., Rickard, J. A., Anderton, H., Wong, W. W.,<lb/> Nachbur, U., Gangoda, L., Warnken, U., Purcell, A. W., Silke, J., and Wal-<lb/>czak, H. (2011) Linear ubiquitination prevents inflammation and regulates<lb/> immune signalling. Nature 471, 591-596 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>15</label>. Tokunaga, F., Nakagawa, T., Nakahara, M., Saeki, Y., Taniguchi, M.,<lb/> Sakata, S., Tanaka, K., Nakano, H., and Iwai, K. (2011) SHARPIN is a<lb/> component of the NF-B-activating linear ubiquitin chain assembly com-<lb/>plex. Nature 471, 633-636 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>16</label>. Ikeda, F., Deribe, Y. L., Skånland, S. S., Stieglitz, B., Grabbe, C., Franz-<lb/>Wachtel, M., van Wijk, S. J., Goswami, P., Nagy, V., Terzic, J., Tokunaga,<lb/> F., Androulidaki, A., Nakagawa, T., Pasparakis, M., Iwai, K., et al. (2011)<lb/> SHARPIN forms a linear ubiquitin ligase complex regulating NF-B ac-<lb/>tivity and apoptosis. Nature 471, 637-641 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>17</label>. Mace, P. D., Linke, K., Feltham, R., Schumacher, F. R., Smith, C. A., Vaux,<lb/> D. L., Silke, J., and Day, C. L. (2008) Structures of the cIAP2 RING domain<lb/> reveal conformational changes associated with ubiquitin-conjugating en-<lb/>zyme (E2) recruitment. J. Biol. Chem. 283, 31633-31640 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>18</label>. Silke, J., Kratina, T., Chu, D., Ekert, P. G., Day, C. L., Pakusch, M., Huang,<lb/> D. C., and Vaux, D. L. (2005) Determination of cell survival by RING-<lb/>mediated regulation of inhibitor of apoptosis (IAP) protein abundance.<lb/> Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 102, 16182-16187 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>19</label>. Dueber, E. C., Schoeffler, A. J., Lingel, A., Elliott, J. M., Fedorova, A. V.,<lb/> Giannetti, A. M., Zobel, K., Maurer, B., Varfolomeev, E., Wu, P., Wallwe-<lb/>ber, H. J., Hymowitz, S. G., Deshayes, K., Vucic, D., and Fairbrother, W. J.<lb/> (2011) Antagonists induce a conformational change in cIAP1 that pro-<lb/>motes autoubiquitination. Science 334, 376 -380 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>20</label>. Lopez, J., John, S. W., Tenev, T., Rautureau, G. J., Hinds, M. G., Franca-<lb/>lanci, F., Wilson, R., Broemer, M., Santoro, M. M., Day, C. L., and Meier, P.<lb/> (2011) CARD-mediated autoinhibition of cIAP1&apos;s E3 ligase activity sup-<lb/>presses cell proliferation and migration. Mol. Cell 42, 569 -583 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>21</label>. Feltham, R., Bettjeman, B., Budhidarmo, R., Mace, P. D., Shirley, S., Con-<lb/>don, S. M., Chunduru, S. K., McKinlay, M. A., Vaux, D. L., Silke, J., and<lb/> Day, C. L. (2011) Smac mimetics activate the E3 ligase activity of cIAP1<lb/> protein by promoting RING domain dimerization. J. Biol. Chem. 286,<lb/> 17015-17028 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>22</label>. Plechanovova ´, A., Jaffray, E. G., Tatham, M. H., Naismith, J. H., and Hay,<lb/> R. T. (2012) Structure of a RING E3 ligase and ubiquitin-loaded E2 primed<lb/> for catalysis. Nature 489, 115-120 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>23</label>. Dou, H., Buetow, L., Sibbet, G. J., Cameron, K., and Huang, D. T. (2012)<lb/> BIRC7-E2 ubiquitin conjugate structure reveals the mechanism of ubiq-<lb/>uitin transfer by a RING dimer. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 19, 876 -883<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>24</label>. Dou, H., Buetow, L., Sibbet, G. J., Cameron, K., and Huang, D. T. (2013)<lb/> Essentiality of a non-RING element in priming donor ubiquitin for catal-<lb/>ysis by a monomeric E3. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 20, 982-986 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>25</label>. Buetow, L., Gabrielsen, M., Anthony, N. G., Dou, H., Patel, A., Aitkenhead,<lb/> H., Sibbet, G. J., Smith, B. O., and Huang, D. T. (2015) Activation of a<lb/> primed RING E3-E2-ubiquitin complex by non-covalent ubiquitin. Mol.<lb/> Cell 58, 297-310 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>26</label>. Branigan, E., Plechanovova ´, A., Jaffray, E. G., Naismith, J. H., and Hay, R. T.<lb/> (2015) Structural basis for the RING-catalyzed synthesis of K63-linked<lb/> ubiquitin chains. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 22, 597-602 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>27</label>. Koliopoulos, M. G., Esposito, D., Christodoulou, E., Taylor, I. A., and Rit-<lb/>tinger, K. (2016) Functional role of TRIM E3 ligase oligomerization and<lb/> regulation of catalytic activity. EMBO J. 35, 1204 -1218 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>28</label>. Sanchez, J. G., Chiang, J. J., Sparrer, K. M. J., Alam, S. L., Chi, M., Rogano-<lb/>wicz, M. D., Sankaran, B., Gack, M. U., and Pornillos, O. (2016) Mecha-<lb/>nism of TRIM25 catalytic activation in the antiviral RIG-I pathway. Cell<lb/> Rep. 16, 1315-1325 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>29</label>. Dawidziak, D. M., Sanchez, J. G., Wagner, J. M., Ganser-Pornillos, B. K.,<lb/> and Pornillos, O. (2017) Structure and catalytic activation of the TRIM23<lb/> RING E3 ubiquitin ligase. Proteins 85, 1957-1961 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>30</label>. Nomura, K., Klejnot, M., Kowalczyk, D., Hock, A. K., Sibbet, G. J., Vous-<lb/>den, K. H., and Huang, D. T. (2017) Structural analysis of MDM2 RING<lb/> separates degradation from regulation of p53 transcription activity. Nat.<lb/> Struct. Mol. Biol. 24, 578 -587 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>31</label>. Middleton, A. J., Budhidarmo, R., Das, A., Zhu, J., Foglizzo, M., Mace,<lb/> P. D., and Day, C. L. (2017) The activity of TRAF RING homo-and het-<lb/>erodimers is regulated by zinc finger 1. Nat. Commun. 8, 1788 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>32</label>. Wright, J. D., Mace, P. D., and Day, C. L. (2016) Secondary ubiquitin-RING<lb/> docking enhances Arkadia and Ark2C E3 ligase activity. Nat. Struct. Mol.<lb/> Biol. 23, 45-52 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>33</label>. Pruneda, J. N., Littlefield, P. J., Soss, S. E., Nordquist, K. A., Chazin, W. J.,<lb/> Brzovic, P. S., and Klevit, R. E. (2012) Structure of an E3:E2ϳUb complex<lb/> Activation of UbcH5BϳUb by cIAP1 and non-covalent ubiquitin<lb/> reveals an allosteric mechanism shared among RING/U-box ligases. Mol.<lb/> Cell 47, 933-942 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>34</label>. Bertrand, M. J., Lippens, S., Staes, A., Gilbert, B., Roelandt, R., De Medts, J.,<lb/> Gevaert, K., Declercq, W., and Vandenabeele, P. (2011) cIAP1/2 are direct E3<lb/> ligases conjugating diverse types of ubiquitin chains to receptor interacting<lb/> proteins kinases 1 to 4 (RIP1-4). PLoS One 6, e22356 CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>35</label>. Dynek, J. N., Goncharov, T., Dueber, E. C., Fedorova, A. V., Izrael-To-<lb/>masevic, A., Phu, L., Helgason, E., Fairbrother, W. J., Deshayes, K., Kirk-<lb/>patrick, D. S., and Vucic, D. (2010) c-IAP1 and UbcH5 promote K11-<lb/>linked polyubiquitination of RIP1 in TNF signalling. EMBO J. 29,<lb/> 4198 -4209 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>36</label>. Brzovic, P. S., Lissounov, A., Christensen, D. E., Hoyt, D. W., and Klevit,<lb/> R. E. (2006) A UbcH5/ubiquitin noncovalent complex is required for pro-<lb/>cessive BRCA1-directed ubiquitination. Mol Cell 21, 873-880 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>37</label>. Ranaweera, R. S., and Yang, X. (2013) Auto-ubiquitination of Mdm2<lb/> enhances its substrate ubiquitin ligase activity. J. Biol. Chem. 288,<lb/> 18939 -18946 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>38</label>. Li, S., Liang, Y. H., Mariano, J., Metzger, M. B., Stringer, D. K., Hristova,<lb/> V. A., Li, J., Randazzo, P. A., Tsai, Y. C., Ji, X., and Weissman, A. M. (2015)<lb/> Insights into ubiquitination from the unique clamp-like binding of the<lb/> RING E3 AO7 to the E2 UbcH5B. J. Biol. Chem. 290, 30225-30239<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>39</label>. Sakata, E., Satoh, T., Yamamoto, S., Yamaguchi, Y., Yagi-Utsumi, M., Ku-<lb/>rimoto, E., Tanaka, K., Wakatsuki, S., and Kato, K. (2010) Crystal structure<lb/> of UbcH5bϳubiquitin intermediate: insight into the formation of the self-<lb/>assembled E2ϳUb conjugates. Structure 18, 138 -147 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>40</label>. Cheung, H. H., Plenchette, S., Kern, C. J., Mahoney, D. J., and Korneluk,<lb/> R. G. (2008) The RING domain of cIAP1 mediates the degradation of<lb/> RING-bearing inhibitor of apoptosis proteins by distinct pathways. Mol.<lb/> Biol. Cell 19, 2729 -2740 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>41</label>. Nakatani, Y., Kleffmann, T., Linke, K., Condon, S. M., Hinds, M. G., and<lb/> Day, C. L. (2013) Regulation of ubiquitin transfer by XIAP, a dimeric RING<lb/> E3 ligase. Biochem. J. 450, 629 -638 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>42</label>. Yin, Q., Lin, S. C., Lamothe, B., Lu, M., Lo, Y. C., Hura, G., Zheng, L., Rich,<lb/> R. L., Campos, A. D., Myszka, D. G., Lenardo, M. J., Darnay, B. G., and Wu,<lb/> H. (2009) E2 interaction and dimerization in the crystal structure of<lb/> TRAF6. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 16, 658 -666 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>43</label>. Bosanac, I., Phu, L., Pan, B., Zilberleyb, I., Maurer, B., Dixit, V. M., Hy-<lb/>mowitz, S. G., and Kirkpatrick, D. S. (2011) Modulation of K11-linkage<lb/> formation by variable loop residues within UbcH5A. J. Mol. Biol. 408,<lb/> 420 -431 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>44</label>. Saha, A., Lewis, S., Kleiger, G., Kuhlman, B., and Deshaies, R. J. (2011)<lb/> Essential role for ubiquitin-ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme interaction in<lb/> ubiquitin discharge from Cdc34 to substrate. Mol. Cell 42, 75-83<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>45</label>. Wickliffe, K. E., Lorenz, S., Wemmer, D. E., Kuriyan, J., and Rape, M.<lb/> (2011) The mechanism of linkage-specific ubiquitin chain elongation by a<lb/> single-subunit E2. Cell 144, 769 -781 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>46</label>. Kaiser, S. E., Riley, B. E., Shaler, T. A., Trevino, R. S., Becker, C. H., Schul-<lb/>man, H., and Kopito, R. R. (2011) Protein standard absolute quantification<lb/> (PSAQ) method for the measurement of cellular ubiquitin pools. Nat.<lb/> Methods 8, 691-696 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>47</label>. Siepmann, T. J., Bohnsack, R. N., Tokgo ¨z, Z., Baboshina, O. V., and Haas,<lb/> A. L. (2003) Protein interactions within the N-end rule ubiquitin ligation<lb/> pathway. J. Biol. Chem. 278, 9448 -9457 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>48</label>. Winter, G. (2010) xia2: an expert system for macromolecular crystallog-<lb/>raphy data reduction. J. Appl. Cryst. 43, 186 -190 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>49</label>. Kabsch, W. (2010) XDS. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr. 66, 125-132<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>50</label>. McCoy, A. J., Grosse-Kunstleve, R. W., Adams, P. D., Winn, M. D., Sto-<lb/>roni, L. C., and Read, R. J. (2007) Phaser crystallographic software. J. Appl.<lb/> Crystallogr. 40, 658 -674 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>51</label>. Emsley, P., and Cowtan, K. (2004) Coot: model-building tools for molec-<lb/>ular graphics. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr. 60, 2126 -2132<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>52</label>. Adams, P. D., Grosse-Kunstleve, R. W., Hung, L. W., Ioerger, T. R., Mc-<lb/>Coy, A. J., Moriarty, N. W., Read, R. J., Sacchettini, J. C., Sauter, N. K., and<lb/> Terwilliger, T. C. (2002) PHENIX: building new software for automated<lb/> crystallographic structure determination. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crys-<lb/>tallogr. 58, 1948 -1954 CrossRef Medline</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

