<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_0"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <listBibl>

        References<lb/> 
        <bibl><label>1</label>. Dictionary of Natural Products 26.2. (2018) [online] http://dnp.chemnet-<lb/>base.com (Accessed January 11, 2018)<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>2</label>. Peters, R. J. (2010) Two rings in them all: the labdane-related diterpenoids.<lb/> Nat. Prod. Rep. 27, 1521-1530 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>3</label>. Chen, F., Tholl, D., Bohlmann, J., and Pichersky, E. (2011) The family of<lb/> terpene synthases in plants: a mid-size family of genes for specialized<lb/> metabolism that is highly diversified throughout the kingdom. Plant J. 66,<lb/> 212-229 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>4</label>. Zi, J., Mafu, S., and Peters, R. J. (2014) To gibberellins and beyond! Survey-<lb/>ing the evolution of (di)terpenoid metabolism. Annu. Rev. Plant Biol. 65,<lb/> 259 -286 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>5</label>. Zerbe, P., and Bohlmann, J. (2015) Plant diterpene synthases: exploring<lb/> modularity and metabolic diversity for bioengineering. Trends Biotechnol.<lb/> 33, 419 -428 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>6</label>. Hamberger, B., and Bak, S. (2013) Plant P450s as versatile drivers for<lb/> evolution of species-specific chemical diversity. Philos. Trans. R. Soc.<lb/> Lond. B Biol. Sci. 368, 20120426 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>7</label>. Banerjee, A., and Hamberger, B. (2018) P450s controlling metabolic bifur-<lb/>cations in plant terpene specialized metabolism. Phytochem. Rev. 17,<lb/> 81-111 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>8</label>. Pateraki, I., Andersen-Ranberg, J., Jensen, N. B., Wubshet, S. G., Heskes,<lb/> A. M., Forman, V., Hallström, B., Hamberger, B., Motawia, M. S., Olsen,<lb/> C. E., Staerk, D., Hansen, J., Møller, B. L., and Hamberger, B. (2017) Total<lb/> biosynthesis of the cyclic AMP booster forskolin from Coleus forskohlii.<lb/> eLife 6, e23001 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>9</label>. Ondari, M. E., and Walker, K. D. (2008) The taxol pathway 10-O-acetyl-<lb/>transferase shows regioselective promiscuity with the oxetane hydroxyl of<lb/> 4-deacetyltaxanes. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 130, 17187-17194 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>10</label>. Chau, M., Walker, K., Long, R., and Croteau, R. (2004) Regioselectivity of<lb/> taxoid-O-acetyltransferases: heterologous expression and characteriza-<lb/>tion of a new taxadien-5␣-ol-O-acetyltransferase. Arch. Biochem. Biophys.<lb/> 430, 237-246 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>11</label>. Cui, G., Duan, L., Jin, B., Qian, J., Xue, Z., Shen, G., Snyder, J. H., Song, J.,<lb/> Chen, S., Huang, L., Peters, R. J., and Qi, X. (2015) Functional divergence of<lb/> diterpene syntheses in the medicinal plant Salvia miltiorrhiza Bunge.<lb/> Plant Physiol. 169, 1607-1618 Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>12</label>. Gao, W., Hillwig, M. L., Huang, L., Cui, G., Wang, X., Kong, J., Yang, B.,<lb/> and Peters, R. J. (2009) A functional genomics approach to tanshinone<lb/> biosynthesis provides stereochemical insights. Org. Lett. 11, 5170 -5173<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>13</label>. Guo, J., Zhou, Y. J., Hillwig, M. L., Shen, Y., Yang, L., Wang, Y., Zhang, X.,<lb/> Liu, W., Peters, R. J., Chen, X., Zhao, Z. K., and Huang, L. (2013)<lb/> CYP76AH1 catalyzes turnover of miltiradiene in tanshinones biosynthesis<lb/> and enables heterologous production of ferruginol in yeasts. Proc. Natl.<lb/> Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 110, 12108 -12113 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>14</label>. Heskes, A. M., Sundram, T. C. M., Boughton, B. A., Jensen, N. B., Hansen,<lb/> N. L., Crocoll, C., Cozzi, F., Rasmussen, S., Hamberger, B., Hamberger, B.,<lb/> Staerk, D., Møller, B. L., and Pateraki, I. (2018) Biosynthesis of bioactive<lb/> diterpenoids in the medicinal plant Vitex agnus-castus. Plant J. 93,<lb/> 943-958 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>15</label>. Zerbe, P., Chiang, A., Dullat, H., O&apos;Neil-Johnson, M., Starks, C., Ham-<lb/>berger, B., and Bohlmann, J. (2014) Diterpene synthases of the biosyn-<lb/>thetic system of medicinally active diterpenoids in Marrubium vulgare.<lb/> Plant J. 79, 914 -927 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>16</label>. Chen, X., Berim, A., Dayan, F. E., and Gang, D. R. (2017) A (Ϫ)-kolavenyl<lb/> diphosphate synthase catalyzes the first step of salvinorin A biosynthesis<lb/> in Salvia divinorum. J Exp Bot. 68, 1109 -1122 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>17</label>. Pelot, K. A., Mitchell, R., Kwon, M., Hagelthorn, D. M., Wardman, J. F.,<lb/> Chiang, A., Bohlmann, J., Ro, D.-K., and Zerbe, P. (2017) Biosynthesis of<lb/> the psychotropic plant diterpene salvinorin A: discovery and character-<lb/>ization of the Salvia divinorum clerodienyl diphosphate synthase. Plant J.<lb/> 89, 885-897 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>18</label>. Caniard, A., Zerbe, P., Legrand, S., Cohade, A., Valot, N., Magnard, J.-L.,<lb/> Bohlmann, J., and Legendre, L. (2012) Discovery and functional charac-<lb/>terization of two diterpene synthases for sclareol biosynthesis in Salvia<lb/> sclarea(L.) and their relevance for perfume manufacture. BMC Plant Biol.<lb/> 12, 119 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>19</label>. Günnewich, N., Higashi, Y., Feng, X., Choi, K.-B., Schmidt, J., and Kutchan,<lb/> T. M. (2013) A diterpene synthase from the clary sage Salvia sclarea catalyzes<lb/> the cyclization of geranylgeranyl diphosphate to (8R)-hydroxy-copalyl<lb/> diphosphate. Phytochemistry 91, 93-99 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>20</label>. Schalk, M., Pastore, L., Mirata, M. A., Khim, S., Schouwey, M., Deguerry,<lb/> F., Pineda, V., Rocci, L., and Daviet, L. (2012) Toward a biosynthetic route<lb/> to sclareol and amber odorants. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 134, 18900 -18903<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>21</label>. Mint Evolutionary Genomics Consortium (2018) Phylogenomic mining<lb/> of the mints reveals multiple mechanisms contributing to the evolution of<lb/> chemical diversity in Lamiaceae. Mol. Plant. 11, 1084 -1096 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>22</label>. Coll, J., and Tandrón, Y. A. (2008) neo-Clerodane diterpenoids from<lb/> Ajuga: structural elucidation and biological activity. Phytochem. Rev. 7, 25<lb/> Mint diterpene synthases<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>23</label>. Klein Gebbinck, E. A., Jansen, B. J. M., and de Groot, A. (2002) Insect<lb/> antifeedant activity of clerodane diterpenes and related model com-<lb/>pounds. Phytochemistry 61, 737-770 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>24</label>. Li, R., Morris-Natschke, S. L., and Lee, K.-H. (2016) Clerodane diterpenes:<lb/> sources, structures, and biological activities. Nat. Prod. Rep. 33, 1166 -1226<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>25</label>. Vestri Alvarenga, S. A., Pierre Gastmans, J., do Vale Rodrigues, G.,<lb/> Moreno, P. R., and de Paulo Emerenciano, V. (2001) A computer-assisted<lb/> approach for chemotaxonomic studies: diterpenes in Lamiaceae. Phyto-<lb/>chemistry 56, 583-595 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>26</label>. Loub, W. D., Farnsworth, N. R., Soejarto, D. D., and Quinn, M. L. (1985)<lb/> NAPRALERT: computer handling of natural product research data.<lb/> J. Chem. Inf. Comput. Sci. 25, 99 -103 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>27</label>. Federhen, S. (2012) The NCBI Taxonomy database. Nucleic Acids Res. 40,<lb/> D136 -D143 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>28</label>. Li, B., Cantino, P. D., Olmstead, R. G., Bramley, G. L. C., Xiang, C.-L., Ma,<lb/> Z.-H., Tan, Y.-H., and Zhang, D.-X. (2016) A large-scale chloroplast phy-<lb/>logeny of the Lamiaceae sheds new light on its subfamilial classification.<lb/> Sci. Rep. 6, 34343 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>29</label>. Camacho, C., Coulouris, G., Avagyan, V., Ma, N., Papadopoulos, J., Bealer,<lb/> K., and Madden, T. L. (2009) BLASTϩ: architecture and applications.<lb/> BMC Bioinformatics 10, 421 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>30</label>. Pateraki, I., Andersen-Ranberg, J., Hamberger, B., Heskes, A. M., Martens,<lb/> H. J., Zerbe, P., Bach, S. S., Møller, B. L., Bohlmann, J., and Hamberger, B.<lb/> (2014) Manoyl oxide (13R), the biosynthetic precursor of forskolin, is syn-<lb/>thesized in specialized root cork cells in Coleus forskohlii. Plant Physiol.<lb/> 164, 1222-1236 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>31</label>. Jia, M., Potter, K. C., and Peters, R. J. (2016) Extreme promiscuity of a<lb/> bacterial and a plant diterpene synthase enables combinatorial biosynthe-<lb/>sis. Metab. Eng. 37, 24 -34 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>32</label>. Zerbe, P., Rodriguez, S. M., Mafu, S., Chiang, A., Sandhu, H. K., O&apos;Neil-<lb/>Johnson, M., Starks, C. M., and Bohlmann, J. (2015) Exploring diterpene<lb/> metabolism in non-model species: transcriptome-enabled discovery and<lb/> functional characterization of labda-7,13 E-dienyl diphosphate synthase<lb/> from Grindelia robusta. Plant J. 83, 783-793 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>33</label>. Urones, J. G., Marcos, I. S., Basabe, P., Diez, D., Garrido, N. M., Alonso, C.,<lb/> Oliva, I. M., Lithgow, A. M., Moro, R. F., Sexmero, M. J., and Lopez, C.<lb/> (1994) Compounds with the labdane skeleton from Halimium viscosum.<lb/> Phytochemistry 35, 713-719 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>34</label>. Suzuki, H., Noma, M., and Kawashima, N. (1983) Two labdane diterpe-<lb/>noids from Nicotiana setchellii. Phytochemistry 22, 1294 -1295 CrossRef<lb/> 35. Roengsumran, S., Petsom, A., Sommit, D., and Vilaivan, T. (1999) Labdane<lb/> diterpenoids from Croton oblongifolius. Phytochemistry 50, 449 -453<lb/> CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>36</label>. Yamada, Y., Komatsu, M., and Ikeda, H. (2016) Chemical diversity of<lb/> labdane-type bicyclic diterpene biosynthesis in Actinomycetales microor-<lb/>ganisms. J. Antibiot. (Tokyo) 69, 515-523 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>37</label>. Xiang, W., Li, R.-T., Song, Q.-S., Na, Z., and Sun, H.-D. (2004) ent-Clero-<lb/>danoids from Isodon scoparius. Helv. Chim. Acta 87, 2860 -2865 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>38</label>. Rudi, A., and Kashman, Y. (1992) Chelodane, Barekoxide, and Zaatirin-<lb/>three new diterpenoids from the marine sponge Chelonaplysilla erecta. J.<lb/> Nat. Prod. 55, 1408 -1414 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>39</label>. Ohsaki, A., Yan, L. T., Ito, S., Edatsugi, H., Iwata, D., and Komoda, Y.<lb/> (1994) The isolation and in vivo potent antitumor activity of clerodane<lb/> diterpenoid from the oleoresin of the Brazilian medicinal plant, Copaifera<lb/> langsdorfi desfon. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett. 4, 2889 -2892 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>40</label>. Monaco, P., Previtera, L., and Mangoni, L. (1982) Terpenes from the bled<lb/> resin of Araucaria hunsteinii. Rendiconto dell&apos;Academia delle scienze fisi-<lb/>che e matematiche 48, 465-470<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>41</label>. Barton, D. H. R., Cheung, H. T., Cross, A. D., Jackman, L. M., and Martin-<lb/>Smith, M. (1961) 1003. Diterpenoid bitter principles. Part III. The consti-<lb/>tution of clerodin. J. Chem. Soc. 10.1039/JR9610005061 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>42</label>. Arima, Y., Kinoshita, M., and Akita, H. (2007) Natural product synthesis<lb/> from (8aR)-and (8aS)-bicyclofarnesols: synthesis of (ϩ)-wiedendiol A,<lb/> (ϩ)-norsesterterpene diene ester and (Ϫ)-subersic acid. Tetrahedron:<lb/> Asymmetry 18, 1701-1711 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>43</label>. Wu, C.-L., and Lin, H. R. (1997) Labdanoids and bis(bibenzyls) from<lb/> Jungermannia species. Phytochemistry 44, 101-105 CrossRef<lb/> 44. Boalino, D. M., McLean, S., Reynolds, W. F., and Tinto, W. F. (2004)<lb/> Labdane Diterpenes of Leonurus sibiricus. J. Nat. Prod. 67, 714 -717<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>45</label>. Gray, C. A., Rivett, D. E. A., and Davies-Coleman, M. T. (2003) The abso-<lb/>lute stereochemistry of a diterpene from Ballota aucheri. Phytochemistry<lb/> 63, 409 -413 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>46</label>. Harris, L. J., Saparno, A., Johnston, A., Prisic, S., Xu, M., Allard, S., Kathire-<lb/>san, A., Ouellet, T., and Peters, R. J. (2005) The maize An2 gene is induced<lb/> by Fusarium attack and encodes an ent-copalyl diphosphate synthase.<lb/> Plant Mol. Biol. 59, 881-894 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>47</label>. Zhan, X., Bach, S. S., Hansen, N. L., Lunde, C., and Simonsen, H. T. (2015)<lb/> Additional diterpenes from Physcomitrella patens synthesized by copalyl<lb/> diphosphate/kaurene synthase (PpCPS/KS). Plant Physiol. Biochem. 96,<lb/> 110 -114 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>48</label>. Andersen-Ranberg, J., Kongstad, K. T., Nielsen, M. T., Jensen, N. B., Pat-<lb/>eraki, I., Bach, S. S., Hamberger, B., Zerbe, P., Staerk, D., Bohlmann, J.,<lb/> Møller, B. L., and Hamberger, B. (2016) Expanding the landscape of diter-<lb/>pene structural diversity through stereochemically controlled combinato-<lb/>rial biosynthesis. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 55, 2142-2146 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>49</label>. Peters, R. J., Flory, J. E., Jetter, R., Ravn, M. M., Lee, H.-J., Coates, R. M., and<lb/> Croteau, R. B. (2000) Abietadiene synthase from Grand Fir (Abies gran-<lb/>dis): characterization and mechanism of action of the &quot;Pseudomature&quot;<lb/> recombinant enzyme. Biochemistry 39, 15592-15602 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>50</label>. Bohlmann, F., and Czerson, H. (1979) Neue labdan-und pimaren-derivate<lb/> aus Palafoxia rosea. Phytochemistry 18, 115-118 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>51</label>. Mann, F. M., Prisic, S., Davenport, E. K., Determan, M. K., Coates,<lb/> R. M., and Peters, R. J. (2010) A single residue switch for Mg 2ϩ -depen-<lb/>dent inhibition characterizes plant class II diterpene cyclases from<lb/> primary and secondary metabolism. J. Biol. Chem. 285, 20558 -20563<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>52</label>. Li, J.-L., Chen, Q.-Q., Jin, Q.-P., Gao, J., Zhao, P.-J., Lu, S., and Zeng, Y.<lb/> (2012) IeCPS2 is potentially involved in the biosynthesis of pharmacolog-<lb/>ically active Isodon diterpenoids rather than gibberellin. Phytochemistry<lb/> 76, 32-39 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>53</label>. Potter, K., Criswell, J., Zi, J., Stubbs, A., and Peters, R. J. (2014) Novel<lb/> product chemistry from mechanistic analysis of ent-copalyl diphosphate<lb/> synthases from plant hormone biosynthesis. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl.<lb/> 53, 7198 -7202 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>54</label>. Potter, K. C., Zi, J., Hong, Y. J., Schulte, S., Malchow, B., Tantillo, D. J., and<lb/> Peters, R. J. (2016) Blocking deprotonation with retention of aromaticity in<lb/> a plant ent-copalyl diphosphate synthase leads to product rearrangement.<lb/> Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 55, 634 -638 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>55</label>. Hansen, N. L., Nissen, J. N., and Hamberger, B. (2017) Two residues de-<lb/>termine the product profile of the class II diterpene synthases TPS14 and<lb/> TPS21 of Tripterygium wilfordii. Phytochemistry 138, 52-56 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>56</label>. Schulte, S., Potter, K. C., Lemke, C., and Peters, R. J. (2018) Catalytic bases<lb/> and stereocontrol in Lamiaceae class II diterpene cyclases. Biochemistry<lb/> 57, 3473-3479 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>57</label>. Jin, B., Cui, G., Guo, J., Tang, J., Duan, L., Lin, H., Shen, Y., Chen, T., Zhang,<lb/> H., and Huang, L. (2017) Functional diversification of kaurene synthase-<lb/>like genes in Isodon rubescens. Plant Physiol. 174, 943-955 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>58</label>. Mafu, S., Potter, K. C., Hillwig, M. L., Schulte, S., Criswell, J., and Peters,<lb/> R. J. (2015) Efficient heterocyclisation by (di)terpene synthases. Chem.<lb/> Commun. (Camb.) 51, 13485-13487 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>59</label>. Xu, M., Wilderman, P. R., and Peters, R. J. (2007) Following evolution&apos;s<lb/> lead to a single residue switch for diterpene synthase product outcome.<lb/> Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 104, 7397-7401 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>60</label>. Jia, M., Zhou, K., Tufts, S., Schulte, S., and Peters, R. J. (2017) A pair of<lb/> residues that interactively affect diterpene synthase product outcome.<lb/> ACS Chem. Biol. 12, 862-867 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>61</label>. Hillwig, M. L., Xu, M., Toyomasu, T., Tiernan, M. S., Wei, G., Cui, G.,<lb/> Huang, L., and Peters, R. J. (2011) Domain loss has independently oc-<lb/>curred multiple times in plant terpene synthase evolution. Plant J. 68,<lb/> 1051-1060 CrossRef Medline<lb/> Mint diterpene synthases<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>62</label>. Pelot, K. A., Hagelthorn, D. M., Addison, J. B., and Zerbe, P. (2017) Bio-<lb/>synthesis of the oxygenated diterpene nezukol in the medicinal plant<lb/> Isodon rubescens is catalyzed by a pair of diterpene synthases. PLOS One<lb/> 12, e0176507 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>63</label>. Jia, M., O&apos;Brien, T. E., Zhang, Y., Siegel, J. B., Tantillo, D. J., and Peters, R. J.<lb/> (2018) Changing face: a key residue for the addition of water by sclareol<lb/> synthase. ACS Catal. 8, 3133-3137 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>64</label>. Helliwell, C. A., Chandler, P. M., Poole, A., Dennis, E. S., and Peacock, W. J.<lb/> (2001) The CYP88A cytochrome P450, ent-kaurenoic acid oxidase, cata-<lb/>lyzes three steps of the gibberellin biosynthesis pathway. Proc. Natl. Acad.<lb/> Sci. U.S.A. 98, 2065-2070 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>65</label>. Han, Q.-B., Cheung, S., Tai, J., Qiao, C.-F., Song, J.-Z., Tso, T.-F., Sun,<lb/> H.-D., and Xu, H.-X. (2006) Maoecrystal Z, a cytotoxic diterpene from<lb/> Isodon eriocalyx with a unique skeleton. Org. Lett. 8, 4727-4730 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>66</label>. Li, X.-N., Pu, J.-X., Du, X., Lou, L.-G., Li, L.-M., Huang, S.-X., Zhao, B.,<lb/> Zhang, M., He, F., Luo, X., Xiao, W.-L., and Sun, H.-D. (2010) Structure<lb/> and cytotoxicity of diterpenoids from Isodon eriocalyx. J. Nat. Prod. 73,<lb/> 1803-1809 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>67</label>. González, A. G., Andrés, L. S., Luis, J. G., Brito, I., and Rodríguez, M. L.<lb/> (1991) Diterpenes from Salvia mellifera. Phytochemistry 30, 4067-4070<lb/> CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>68</label>. Chen, Y.-L., Lan, Y.-H., Hsieh, P.-W., Wu, C.-C., Chen, S.-L., Yen, C.-T.,<lb/> Chang, F.-R., Hung, W.-C., and Wu, Y.-C. (2008) Bioactive cembrane<lb/> diterpenoids of Anisomeles indica. J. Nat. Prod. 71, 1207-1212 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>69</label>. Li, L.-M., Li, G.-Y., Pu, J.-X., Xiao, W.-L., Ding, L.-S., and Sun, H.-D. (2009)<lb/> Ent-kaurane and cembrane diterpenoids from Isodon sculponeatus and<lb/> their cytotoxicity. J. Nat. Prod. 72, 1851-1856 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>70</label>. Kirby, J., Nishimoto, M., Park, J. G., Withers, S. T., Nowroozi, F., Behrendt,<lb/> D., Rutledge, E. J. G., Fortman, J. L., Johnson, H. E., Anderson, J. V., and<lb/> Keasling, J. D. (2010) Cloning of casbene and neocembrene synthases from<lb/> Euphorbiaceae plants and expression in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Phyto-<lb/>chemistry 71, 1466 -1473 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>71</label>. Ennajdaoui, H., Vachon, G., Giacalone, C., Besse, I., Sallaud, C., Herzog,<lb/> M., and Tissier, A. (2010) Trichome specific expression of the tobacco<lb/> (Nicotiana sylvestris) cembratrien-ol synthase genes is controlled by both<lb/> activating and repressing cis-regions. Plant Mol. Biol. 73, 673-685<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>72</label>. Hamano, Y., Kuzuyama, T., Itoh, N., Furihata, K., Seto, H., and Dairi, T.<lb/> (2002) Functional analysis of eubacterial diterpene cyclases responsible<lb/> for biosynthesis of a diterpene antibiotic, terpentecin. J. Biol. Chem. 277,<lb/> 37098 -37104 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>73</label>. Dairi, T., Hamano, Y., Kuzuyama, T., Itoh, N., Furihata, K., and Seto, H.<lb/> (2001) Eubacterial diterpene cyclase genes essential for production of the<lb/> isoprenoid antibiotic terpentecin. J. Bacteriol. 183, 6085-6094 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>74</label>. Ikeda, H., Shin-Ya, K., Nagamitsu, T., and Tomoda, H. (2016) Biosyn-<lb/>thesis of mercapturic acid derivative of the labdane-type diterpene,<lb/> cyslabdan that potentiates imipenem activity against methicillin-re-<lb/>sistant Staphylococcus aureus: cyslabdan is generated by mycothiol-<lb/>mediated xenobiotic detoxification. J. Ind. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 43,<lb/> 325-342 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>75</label>. Keeling, C. I., Madilao, L. L., Zerbe, P., Dullat, H. K., and Bohlmann, J.<lb/> (2011) The primary diterpene synthase products of Picea abies levopima-<lb/>radiene/abietadiene synthase (PaLAS) are epimers of a thermally unstable<lb/> diterpenol. J. Biol. Chem. 286, 21145-21153 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>76</label>. Geuskens, R. B. M., Luteijn, J. M., and Schoonhoven, L. M. (1983) Anti-<lb/>feedant activity of some ajugarin derivatives in three lepidopterous spe-<lb/>cies. Experientia 39, 403-404 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>77</label>. Belles, X., Camps, F., Coll, J., and Piulachs, M. D. (1985) Insect antifeedant<lb/> activity of clerodane diterpenoids against larvae of Spodoptera littoralis<lb/> (Boisd.) (Lepidoptera). J. Chem. Ecol. 11, 1439 -1445 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>78</label>. Anderson, J. C., Blaney, W. M., Cole, M. D., Fellows, L. L., Ley, S. V.,<lb/> Sheppard, R. N., and Simmonds, M. S. J. (1989) The structure of two<lb/> new clerodane diterpenoid potent insect antifeedants from Scutellaria<lb/> woronowii (Juz); jodrellin A &amp; B. Tetrahedron Lett. 30, 4737-4740<lb/> CrossRef<lb/></bibl> 
        <bibl><label>79</label>. Challis, G. L. (2008) Genome mining for novel natural product discovery.<lb/> J. Med. Chem. 51, 2618 -2628 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>80</label>. Nützmann, H.-W., Huang, A., and Osbourn, A. (2016) Plant metabolic<lb/> clusters: from genetics to genomics. New Phytol. 211, 771-789 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>81</label>. Busta, L., and Jetter, R. (2017) Moving beyond the ubiquitous: the diversity<lb/> and biosynthesis of specialty compounds in plant cuticular waxes. Phy-<lb/>tochem. Rev. 17, 1275-1304 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>82</label>. Kodama, Y., Shumway, M., Leinonen, R., and International Nucleotide<lb/> Sequence Database Collaboration (2012) The sequence read archive: ex-<lb/>plosive growth of sequencing data. Nucleic Acids Res. 40, D54 -D56<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>83</label>. Benson, D. A., Cavanaugh, M., Clark, K., Karsch-Mizrachi, I., Lipman,<lb/> D. J., Ostell, J., and Sayers, E. W. (2013) GenBank. Nucleic Acids Res. 41,<lb/> D36 -D42 Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>84</label>. Scotti, M. T., Herrera-Acevedo, C., Oliveira, T. B., Costa, R. P. O., Santos<lb/> SYKde Rodrigues, O. R. P., Scotti, L., and Da-Costa, F. B. (2018) SistematX,<lb/> an online web-based cheminformatics tool for data management of sec-<lb/>ondary metabolites. Molecules 23, 103 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>85</label>. Heller, S. R., McNaught, A., Pletnev, I., Stein, S., and Tchekhovskoi, D.<lb/> (2015) InChI, the IUPAC International Chemical Identifier. J. Chemin-<lb/>form. 7, 23 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>86</label>. Haas, B. J., Papanicolaou, A., Yassour, M., Grabherr, M., Blood, P. D.,<lb/> Bowden, J., Couger, M. B., Eccles, D., Li, B., Lieber, M., MacManes, M. D.,<lb/> Ott, M., Orvis, J., Pochet, N., Strozzi, F., et al. (2013) De novo transcript<lb/> sequence reconstruction from RNA-seq using the Trinity platform for<lb/> reference generation and analysis. Nat. Protoc. 8, 1494 -1512 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>87</label>. Fu, L., Niu, B., Zhu, Z., Wu, S., and Li, W. (2012) CD-HIT: accelerated for<lb/> clustering the next-generation sequencing data. Bioinformatics 28,<lb/> 3150 -3152 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>88</label>. Sievers, F., Wilm, A., Dineen, D., Gibson, T. J., Karplus, K., Li, W., Lopez,<lb/> R., McWilliam, H., Remmert, M., Söding, J., Thompson, J. D., and Higgins,<lb/> D. G. (2011) Fast, scalable generation of high-quality protein multiple<lb/> sequence alignments using Clustal Omega. Mol. Syst. Biol. 7, 539 Medline<lb/></bibl>
        <bibl><label>89</label>. Stamatakis, A. (2014) RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis<lb/> and post-analysis of large phylogenies. Bioinformatics 30, 1312-1313<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>90</label>. Huerta-Cepas, J., Serra, F., and Bork, P. (2016) ETE 3: reconstruction,<lb/> analysis, and visualization of phylogenomic data. Mol. Biol. Evol. 33,<lb/> 1635-1638 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>91</label>. Hamberger, B., Ohnishi, T., Hamberger, B., Séguin, A., and Bohlmann, J.<lb/> (2011) Evolution of diterpene metabolism: sitka spruce CYP720B4 cata-<lb/>lyzes multiple oxidations in resin acid biosynthesis of conifer defense<lb/> against insects. Plant Physiol. 157, 1677-1695 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>92</label>. Sainsbury, F., Thuenemann, E. C., and Lomonossoff, G. P. (2009) pEAQ:<lb/> versatile expression vectors for easy and quick transient expression of<lb/> heterologous proteins in plants. Plant Biotechnol. J. 7, 682-693 CrossRef<lb/> Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>93</label>. Kuhn, S., Schlörer, N. E., Kolshorn, H., and Stoll, R. (2012) From chemical<lb/> shift data through prediction to assignment and NMR LIMS: multiple<lb/> functionalities of nmrshiftdb2. J. Cheminform. 4, P52 CrossRef<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>94</label>. Sun, H., Zhou, N., Wang, H., Huang, D., and Lang, Z. (2017) Processing<lb/> and targeting of proteins derived from polyprotein with 2A and LP4/2A as<lb/> peptide linkers in a maize expression system. PLoS One 12, e0174804<lb/> CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>95</label>. Emanuelsson, O., Nielsen, H., Brunak, S., and von Heijne, G. (2000) Pre-<lb/>dicting subcellular localization of proteins based on their N-terminal<lb/> amino acid sequence. J. Mol. Biol. 300, 1005-1016 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>96</label>. Lo ´pez-Pe ´rez, J. L., Thera ´on, R., del Olmo, E., and Dı ´az, D. (2007) NAPROC-<lb/>13: a database for the dereplication of natural product mixtures in bioassay-<lb/>guided protocols. Bioinformatics 23, 3256 -3257 CrossRef Medline<lb/> </bibl>
        <bibl><label>97</label>. Fischedick, J. T., Johnson, S. R., Ketchum, R. E. B., Croteau, R. B., and<lb/> Lange, B. M. (2015) NMR spectroscopic search module for Spektraris, an<lb/> online resource for plant natural product identification: taxane diterpe-<lb/>noids from Taxus ϫ media cell suspension cultures as a case study. Phy-<lb/>tochemistry 113, 87-95 CrossRef Medline</bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </text>
</tei>

