<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_12985_2015_Article_447.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


        <figure>

            <head>Fig. <label>1</label> </head>
 
            <figDesc>Correlations between intrahepatic HBV DNA (ihDNA) cccDNA, pregenomic RNA (pgRNA) and serum HBV DNA within HBeAg-positive patients.<lb/> pgRNA vs. cccDNA (a), ihDNA vs. pgRNA (b), HBV DNA vs. ihDNA (c), and HBV DNA vs. pgRNA (d). All values are log 10 copies/cell equivalent (cEq) if not<lb/> stated otherwise</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>Fig. <label>2</label> </head>
 
            <figDesc>Correlations between intrahepatic HBV DNA (ihDNA), cccDNA, pregenomic RNA (pgRNA) and serum HBV DNA within HBeAg-negative patients.<lb/> pgRNA vs. cccDNA (a), ihDNA vs pgRNA (b), and HBV DNA vs. ihDNA (c). All values are log 10 copies/cell equivalent (cEq) if not stated otherwise</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>Fig. <label>3</label> </head>
 
            <figDesc>Box plots of serum and intrahepatic levels of hepatitis B virus markers in HBeAg-positive and HBeAg-negative patients (a) and their ratios<lb/> (b and c). Each box shows median and 25 th and 75 th percentile, the bars 10 th and 90 th percentile, and open circles results outside the latter range.<lb/> cEq, cell equivalent</figDesc>
        </figure>


        <figure>

            <head>Fig. <label>4</label> </head>
            
            <figDesc>Flowchart showing differences in intrahepatic and serum viral load between HBeAg-positive and HBeAg-negative patients. Δe indicates<lb/> mean difference between levels in HBeAg-positive and HBeAg-negative patients. Three novel findings are pointed out: (i) a greater reduction of<lb/> HBV DNA in serum as compared with in the liver; (ii) an unchanged HBsAg/S RNA ratio; (iii) an increased S-RNA/cccDNA ratio, in HBeAg-negative<lb/> as compared with HBeAg-positive patients</figDesc>
        </figure>



    </text>
</tei>

