<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_submission_89"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<p>Recent advances in semiconductor growth technique have offered the opportunity to fabricate structure<lb/> with potential profiles of almost any shape. Closely perfect parabolic effective potential profile has been grown<lb/> with this technique. In these structures it is possible to form an approximate homogeneous electron gas within a<lb/> three dimensionals space volume that moves in an uniformed distributed background of positive charge. From<lb/> the technological point of view, parabolic quantum well (PQW) can be used as polarization insensitive electro<lb/> absorptive modulator <ref type="biblio">[1]</ref> and far infrared resonant tunneling devices <ref type="biblio">[2]</ref>. In this work exciton phenomena on<lb/> doped and undoped AlGaAs/GaAs PQWs were investigated by means of photoluminescence (PL)<lb/> measurements. The structures were grown by Molecular Beam Epitaxy on (100) GaAs substrates <ref type="biblio">[3]</ref>. <ref type="figure">Fig. 1<lb/></ref> shows the low temperature PL spectra for doped and undoped samples with 1000Å well width. We can see that<lb/> the spectra are divided by two spectral regions, one dominated by the GaAs bulk emissions (left side) and the<lb/> second by the PQW one (right side). We will discuss only PQW emission. On the undoped sample three<lb/> emissions are present (named A, B and C). By PL measurements in functions of temperature and power<lb/> excitation, corroborated by theoretical calculations, we were able to identify these emissions: emission A is<lb/> ascribed to the excitonic emission of 1s exciton on the PQW with bind energy of approximately one meV.<lb/> Emission B is associated to fundamental first electron to first heavy hole emission and the emission C to some<lb/> excited transitions. For the doped sample, stead of peaks, we observed a large emission related to the<lb/> recombination process of the Fermi electron gas formed inside the PQW with photogenerated holes. As can be<lb/> seen in the <ref type="figure">fig.1</ref>, an increase on the luminescence intensity occurs (signed by D) near to the end of the PL band.<lb/> This enhancement on the PL signal occurs only at low temperature. It rapidly vanishes as the temperature<lb/> increases, as can be observed at <ref type="figure">fig.2</ref>. This resonant emission is equivalent to the Mahan exciton on the<lb/> absorption process and is associated to scattering processes at the Fermi level.<lb/></p>

			<other>1.500 1.505 1.510 1.515 1.520 1.525 1.530<lb/> D<lb/> C<lb/> B A<lb/> T=8.5K<lb/> PQW emissions<lb/> GaAs emissions<lb/> Doped<lb/> Undoped PL int. (arb.units)<lb/> Energy (eV)<lb/> 1.500<lb/> 1.510<lb/> 1.520<lb/> 1.530<lb/> 30K<lb/> 20K<lb/> 15K<lb/> 8.5K<lb/> PL int. (arb. units)<lb/> Energy (eV)<lb/> L w =1000Å<lb/></other>

			<figure>
				<head>Figure 1.</head>
				<figDesc>Low temperature PL spectra of<lb/> doped and undoped PQW with well<lb/> width of 1000Å. (Symbols are defined on<lb/> the text).<lb/> </figDesc>
			</figure>

			<figure>
				<head>Figure 2.</head>
				<figDesc>PL spectra as a function of<lb/> temperature of the doped PQW sample.<lb/></figDesc>
			</figure>
			
	</text>
</tei>
