<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_submission_107"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<p>Exciton-polaritons are very promising bosonic quasiparticles for displaying collective phenomena at high temperatures.<lb/> Currently the most widely used approach to model a system of interacting Bose particles is based on solution of the<lb/> Gross-Pitaevskii equation <ref type="biblio">[1]</ref>. However, this approach has several drawbacks. First, it assumes complete coherence in<lb/> the system and processes of polariton-phonon scattering can hardly be accounted for properly. Second, the intermediate<lb/> regime (when Bose-Einstein condensate is not have been formed yet) can not be investigated.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>This background encouraged us to develop a new approach that merges profits of the GPe with those of quasi-classical<lb/> Boltzman equation <ref type="biblio">[2]</ref>. We strongly believe that state correlations should be considered explicitly and therefore<lb/> consider the system of interacting particles and keep track of the time evolution of both state populations and the<lb/> correlators between them. In the 1D channel the polariton-polariton and polariton-phonon interactions are accounted<lb/> for in respective appropriate ways <ref type="biblio">[3]</ref>. Coherent processes (free propagation of the particles, polariton-polariton<lb/> interactions) areconsidered using Liouville-von Neumann equation (see ref. <ref type="biblio">[3]</ref> for details) whereas processes of<lb/> polaritons on phonons scattering, loosing decoherence, are described by dint of Born-Markov approximation.<lb/></p> 
			
			<p>The formalism is suitable for arbitrary dimensions, but we focus on polaritons in a 1D channel. <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> is an illustration<lb/> of the hysteresis that occurs when pumping at some k (the pump is in units µeV /¯ h) for different temperatures. The<lb/> temperature dependence saturates above T 5 K, and the curves look more or less the same. On <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> one can see<lb/> the transport of a polariton droplet at t = 0.5 ps (inset) and t = 1.5 ps (main plot). The red curve corresponds to T = 1<lb/> K and there is a significant backscattered packet due to polariton-polariton interaction. Increasing the temperature<lb/> up to T = 20 K (black) this is suppressed by smoothing.<lb/></p>

			<figure>
				<head>Figure 1:</head>
				<figDesc>Threshold characteristic: illustration of the<lb/> bistability and hysteresis. We pump at k p = 1.25 · 10 6 m −1 .<lb/> Blue: T = 0.1 K, red: T = 1 K, black: T = 5K.<lb/></figDesc>
			</figure>

			<figure>
				<trash>−5 −2.5<lb/> 0 2.5<lb/> 5 0<lb/> 100<lb/> 200<lb/> 300<lb/> 400<lb/> 500<lb/> 600<lb/> Concentration (µm<lb/> −1<lb/> )<lb/> Coordinate (µm)<lb/> −5 −2.5<lb/> 0 2.5<lb/> 5 0<lb/> 200<lb/> 400<lb/> 600<lb/></trash>
				<head>Figure 2:</head>
				<figDesc>Polaritonic droplet transport in 1D channel for<lb/> different temperatures. Backscattering is suppressed at<lb/> some temperature due to scattering on phonons.<lb/></figDesc>
			</figure>

	</text>
</tei>
