<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>Introduction<lb/></head>

			<p>It is known that acupuncture stimulation affects blood<lb/> flow, and there are some studies for skin <ref type="biblio">(1)</ref>, muscle <ref type="biblio">(2)</ref><lb/> and brain <ref type="biblio">(3)</ref>. We examined whether acupuncture not<lb/> only stimulates a local area but also the blood flow of<lb/> other organs, thus clarifying how acupuncture stimulates<lb/> an organism. Since it is necessary to examine the effect<lb/> on organ blood flow according to different areas of<lb/> stimulation, the blood flow of various organs was<lb/> measured in anesthetized rats using colored microspheres<lb/> that can quantitatively measure multiple organ blood<lb/> flow. We examined how acupuncture stimulation of the<lb/> regions (Hsia-Kuan or Hoku) influenced the blood<lb/> flow of various organs. Although microsphere measure-<lb/>ment for regional blood flow has radiolabeled micro-<lb/>spheres <ref type="biblio">(4-6,7-17,18)</ref> and colored microspheres <ref type="biblio">(19-28)</ref>,<lb/> we used the colored ones in this experiment. There are<lb/> two techniques for colored microsphere measurement.<lb/> One technique can calculate blood flow by counting the<lb/> total number of microspheres in each sample <ref type="biblio">(19-23)<lb/></ref> and the other by extracting colored dye from the<lb/> microsphere s <ref type="biblio">(24-28)</ref>. We used the latter technique in<lb/> our experiment.<lb/></p>

			<head>Methods<lb/> Preparation<lb/></head>

			<p>After 24 h without food, Male Wistar rats (n ¼ 27, body<lb/> weight: 250-420 g, free water intake) were anesthetized<lb/> with intra-peritoneal injection (1.2 g/kg) of urethane.<lb/> After tracheotomy, a cannula was inserted and a<lb/> respirator artificially regulated breathing (respiratory<lb/> frequency: 90 cycles/min, tidal air: 10 ml/kg, SN-480-7,<lb/> Shinano, Japan). Pancuronium bromide (2 mg/kg) was<lb/> administrated from a catheter that was placed in the<lb/> jugular vein of rats. In addition, CO 2 concentration in<lb/> the expiration was monitored (1H26, NEC) and main-<lb/>tained at about 3%. A second catheter (PE-50) was<lb/> positioned in the right femoral artery to monitor blood<lb/> pressure. The blood pressure and heart rate were<lb/> recorded on a thermal array recorder (RTA-1200,<lb/> Nihon Kohden). A third catheter (PE-10) was inserted<lb/> into left ventricular via the right carotid artery for the<lb/> colored microsphere injection. And, a fourth catheter<lb/> (PE-50) was positioned in the left femoral artery for<lb/> withdrawal of blood samples by a syringe pump at a rate<lb/> of 0.84 ml/min (Model210, KD Scientific Inc. USA). The<lb/> rectal temperature was monitored using a thermistor and<lb/> maintained about 37.5 C by means of a heating pad<lb/> (MK-900, Muromachi Kikai Co.). In this experiment,<lb/> yellow and blue microspheres (15 AE 0.2 mm, Dye-Track<lb/> Triton Technology Inc. USA) were used to measure<lb/> organ blood flow.<lb/></p>

			<p>The experiment was divided into three groups. First<lb/> group comprised the controls (n ¼ 10, no stimulation).<lb/> Second group was stimulated with acupuncture for<lb/> 30 min at left ST-7 (n ¼ 10, ST-7 group). The third<lb/> group was stimulated by acupuncture for 30 min at<lb/> right LI-4 (n ¼ 7, LI-4 group). In the ST-7 group or LI-4<lb/> group, acupuncture was inserted into the left ST-7<lb/> (Hsia-Kuan, masseter muscle) or right LI-4 (Hoku)<lb/> point (LI-4 is located on the dorsum of the hand,<lb/> between the first and second finger) in the forelimb.<lb/> Acupuncture stimulation was given using rotation<lb/> (the needle was rotated right and left at 1 Hz) and was<lb/> repeated 10 times at intervals of 2 min.<lb/></p>

			<p>The position of the left ventricle catheter was confirmed<lb/> by autopsy at the end of experiment.<lb/></p>

			<head>Measurement of Blood Flow by Colored Microspheres<lb/></head>

			<p>The infusion of colored microspheres started at least<lb/> 60 min after surgery and confirmation of stabilized<lb/> blood pressure and heartbeats. The microspheres were<lb/> stirred with a test tube mixer (NS-80, Iuchiseieidou) for<lb/> 5 min before infusion. The reference blood was drawn<lb/> from 10 s before the microsphere infusion, and continued<lb/> for 75 s. The microsphere (yellow or blue) infusion<lb/> (20 s) was started 10 s after beginning to draw blood.<lb/> Saline (0.5 ml) was then infused for 30 s to flush the<lb/> microspheres in the catheter. In all experiments, yellow<lb/> microspheres (0.12-0.14 ml, 360 000-420 000 micro-<lb/>spheres) were injected first and blue (0.2-0.23 ml,<lb/> 600 000-690 000 microspheres) ones second. After yellow<lb/> injection, additional fluid was not replaced except by<lb/> injection of blue. The injection of blue microspheres<lb/> started 30 min after the first blood sampling was finished<lb/> in the control group. In ST-7 or LI-4 group, acupuncture<lb/> stimulation was applied after the first sampling. About<lb/> 30 min after inserting the acupuncture needle, blue micro<lb/> spheres were injected.<lb/></p>

			<p>After the second blood sampling, cardiac arrest was<lb/> achieved in the rats with potassium chloride. After the<lb/> main large blood vessels were bound with a ligature,<lb/> tissue samples that measure organ blood flow were<lb/> excised and weighed. In the control, ST-7 and LI-4<lb/> group both masseter (right and left) and trapezius<lb/> (right and left), or only masseter, kidney (right and<lb/> left), stomach, small intestine, brain (divided into two<lb/> samples, one including cerebrum and the other including<lb/> the cerebellum), lung, heart, spleen and liver were excised.<lb/></p>

			<p>Each tissue sample was put in a test tube, adding 4 M<lb/> KOH containing 2% Tween 80 (16 M KOH containing<lb/> 20% Tween 80 was added to the blood sample). Both<lb/> tissue and blood samples were put at 60 C for 4 h in the<lb/> dryer (FC-410, Toyo Seisakujyo). These samples were<lb/> stirred with a test tube mixer per 1 h. Afterwards, tissue<lb/> or blood samples were filtered under reduced pressure<lb/> through a polyester filter to collect the microspheres.<lb/> The filter and DMF (dimethylformamide) were put in the<lb/> micro test tubes to dissolve dye from the microspheres in<lb/> the solution after the filters dried. Then the filter was<lb/> removed from the tube, and the solution was centrifuged<lb/> (5 min, 4000 g and 3 min, 2000 g), and absorbance of the<lb/> supernatant fluid was measured by a spectrophotometer<lb/> (UV-1600, Shimadzu Seisakusho LTD.).<lb/> </p>

			<p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows examples of the absorbance by the<lb/> above processing. Since the peak of absorbance in yellow<lb/> microspheres appears at 448 nm wavelength and blue<lb/> appears at 672 nm (24,27), we measured 448 nm for<lb/> yellow microspheres in the blood sample of and 672 nm<lb/> for blue microspheres. Tissue samples containing both<lb/> microspheres were measured at wavelength absorbencies<lb/> of 448 nm and 672 nm. Tissue samples with no absor-<lb/>bency peak were deleted from our data.<lb/></p>

			<head>Calculation of Organ Blood Flow<lb/></head>

			<p>Organ blood flow was calculated using the equation<lb/> below:<lb/></p>

			<formula>Qm ¼ ðAm Â QrÞ=Ar<lb/></formula>

			<p>Qm shows blood flow of the tissues (ml/min/g). Qr shows<lb/> the withdrawal rate of the blood samples. Am shows the<lb/> absorbance (AU) of the microspheres per 1 g. Ar shows<lb/> the absorbance (AU) of all microspheres in the blood<lb/> samples.<lb/></p>

			<head>Statistical Analysis<lb/></head>

			<p>Data were expressed as the mean AE SD. The percentage<lb/> changes of blood flow were expressed as 100% the first<lb/> value of blood flow, and the percentage was showed<lb/> by box and whisker plot. Wilcoxon signed rank test,<lb/> Mann-Whitney U-Test, One-way or Two-way ANOVA<lb/> was used for data analysis. Differences of P50.05 were<lb/> considered statistically significant.<lb/></p>

			<head>Results<lb/></head>

			<head>Time Courses of Mean Blood Pressure During<lb/> the Experiment in Control, ST-7 and LI-4 Groups<lb/></head>

			<p>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the time course of mean blood pressure<lb/> (mmHg) in the control, ST-7 and LI-4 group. The mean<lb/> blood pressures before the first withdrawal in the control,<lb/> ST-7 and LI-4 were 76.0 AE 6.0, 80.7 AE 12.7 and<lb/> 86.4 AE 11.7. Although blood pressure of the control<lb/> group<lb/> tended<lb/> to<lb/> be<lb/> low,<lb/> there<lb/> was<lb/> no<lb/> significant difference among the three groups (P ¼ 0.15).<lb/> One-way ANOVA was applied to this analysis. The<lb/> temporal changes of blood pressure were also similar<lb/> among three groups, and no significant differences<lb/> (F(2,14) ¼ 1.94, P ¼ 0.17) and interaction (P ¼ 0.69)<lb/> among three groups. On the other hand, heart rate<lb/> (beats/min) before the first withdrawal of the control<lb/> group, ST-7 and LI-4 were 383.7 AE 25.3, 424.6 AE 40.3 and<lb/> 427.4 AE 27.6.There was no significant difference<lb/> [F(2,14) ¼ 3.02, P ¼ 0.07] and interaction (P ¼ 0.45)<lb/> among the three groups (data not shown). Two-way<lb/> ANOVA was applied to these analyses.<lb/></p>

			<head>Organ Blood Flow in the Control Group<lb/></head>

			<p>The second measurements of organ blood flow were<lb/> slightly lower than those of the first in every organ, with<lb/> significant differences in the muscle, kidney, stomach,<lb/> brain and spleen (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). Wilcoxon signed rank test<lb/> was applied to these analyses and the mean variations<lb/> (ml/min/g) of first and second organ blood flow in each<lb/> organ were as follows; kidney: À0.65; small intestine:<lb/> À0.49; lung: À0.33; spleen: À0.32; stomach: À0.26; brain:<lb/> À0.17; muscle: À0.05; heart: À0.03 and liver: À0.02.<lb/></p>

			<p>The first and second blood flow of the left masseter<lb/> muscle in the control group were 0.35 AE 0.24, 0.36 AE 0.45,<lb/> respectively (P ¼ 0.35, no figure), and right masseter<lb/> of the control group were 0.16 AE 0.18 and 0.12 AE 0.10,<lb/> and there was no significant difference (P ¼ 0.34,<lb/> no figure).<lb/></p>

			<head>Change of Organ Blood Flow in the ST-7 Group<lb/></head>

			<p>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the first and second organ blood flows in<lb/> the ST-7 group. Though the second blood flow was<lb/> slightly higher than the first blood flow in the muscle,<lb/> stomach, small intestine, brain and heart, there was<lb/></p>

			<figure>Figure 1. Variation of mean blood pressure in the control group,<lb/> ST-7 group, LI-4 group (mean AE SD), and the absorbance of the<lb/> reference blood samples (yellow and blue). It shows temporal variation of<lb/> mean blood pressure in control group (blank square) (n ¼ 10), ST-7 group<lb/> (blank circle) (n ¼ 10), LI-4 group (blank triangle) (n ¼ 7). The number of<lb/> horizontal respectively means time (seconds or minutes) of the first or<lb/> second reference blood sample withdrawal. (A) Start of the first reference<lb/> blood sample withdrawal, (B) end of the first reference blood sample<lb/> withdrawal, (C) start of the second reference blood sample withdrawal,<lb/> (D) end of the second reference blood sample withdrawal. The crossbar in<lb/> the figure means the period that the reference blood sample was<lb/> withdrawn. The absorbance in the figure indicated yellow (448 nm) and<lb/> blue (672 nm) in the each reference blood sample.<lb/> </figure>

			<figure>Figure 2. Organ blood flow in the control group (mean AE SD). It shows<lb/> blood flow of the first and second organ blood flow in the control<lb/> group (M, muscle; K, kidney; ST, stomach; SI, small intestine; B, brain;<lb/> LU, lung; HE, heart; SP, spleen and LI, liver). The black bar graph<lb/> expresses the first organ blood flow. The slant bar graph expresses the<lb/> second organ blood flow. S means the number of tissue sample.<lb/> *P50.05,**P50.01.<lb/></figure>

			<p>no significant difference between the first and second<lb/> blood flows in any organ. Wilcoxon signed rank test was<lb/> applied to these analyses. The mean variation (ml/min/g)<lb/> of each organ blood flow was: heart: þ1.07; brain: þ0.07;<lb/> small intestine: þ0.05; muscle: þ0.04; stomach: þ0.02;<lb/> liver: À0.02; lung: À0.03; spleen: À0.03 and kidney:<lb/> À0.04.<lb/></p>

			<p>The first and second blood flows of the left masseter on<lb/> the side receiving acupuncture stimulation were:<lb/> 0.13 AE 0.06, 0.23 AE 0.19 (data not shown). There was no<lb/> significant difference between the first and second values,<lb/> but we did observe a trend to increase (P ¼ 0.08,<lb/> Wilcoxon signed rank test). Meanwhile, the first and<lb/> second blood flows of the right masseter were 0.10 AE 0.05,<lb/> 0.12 AE 0.08, showing no change (P ¼ 0.40, data not<lb/> shown).<lb/></p>

			<p>A box and whisker plot of the percentage change (%)<lb/> of organ blood flow in the control group and ST-7 shows<lb/> significant differences in muscle, kidney, brain and heart,<lb/> applying a Mann-Whitney U-test to the analyses<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). Mean percentage change (%) of the blood<lb/> flow in each organ of the ST-7 group were: heart: þ76.0;<lb/> muscle: þ34.6; brain: þ18.1; lung: þ17.2; stomach:<lb/> þ15.3; small intestine: þ14.6; kidney: þ11.8; spleen:<lb/> À9.2 and liver: À9.2.<lb/></p>

			<p>Mean percentage change of the left masseter stimulated<lb/> by acupuncture in the ST-7 group was þ57.2. The value<lb/> of the right masseter in the ST-7 group that was not<lb/> stimulated was þ28.9. The control group values were:<lb/> left masseter: À10.8; right masseter: À11.3. While<lb/> the blood flow rate decreased in both masseters of<lb/> the control group, the blood flow rate of the left<lb/> masseter of the ST-7 group had increased more than<lb/> the right of the same group. However, this difference<lb/> between the left and right masseters of the ST-7<lb/> group was not statistically significant. (Mann-Whitney<lb/> U-test).<lb/></p>

			<head>Organ Blood Flow Change in the LI-4 Group<lb/></head>

			<p>Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref> shows the first and second organ blood flow<lb/> measurements of the LI-4 group. Though the second<lb/> blood flow increased slightly more than the first in the<lb/> brain, lung and heart, there was no significant difference.<lb/> There was a significant decrease in the muscle. Wilcoxon<lb/> signed rank test was applied to these analyses. Mean<lb/> variation (ml/min/g) of blood flow of each organ blood<lb/> flow was: heart: þ2.15; lung: þ0.16; brain: þ0.11; liver:<lb/> 0.00; stomach: À0.01; muscle: À0.05; small intestine:<lb/> À0.18; spleen: À0.54 and kidney: À0.90. Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows<lb/> the percentage change (%) of the control group and LI-4<lb/> group by box and whisker plot. There was no significant<lb/> difference between the control group and LI-4 group.<lb/> Mann-Whitney U-test was applied to these analyses.<lb/> Mean percentage change (%) of organ blood flow in LI-4<lb/> group were described subsequently; lung: þ46.3; heart:<lb/> þ34.7; brain: þ11.0; liver: þ7.4; small intestine: À1.1;<lb/> stomach: À10.8; kidney: À16.9; muscle: À30.0 and spleen:<lb/> À33.3.<lb/></p>

			<head>Discussion<lb/></head>

			<p>The colored microsphere technique used in this experi-<lb/>ment has various advantages for organ blood flow<lb/> measurement. It can measure blood flow of multiple<lb/> organs simultaneously. In principle, microspheres are<lb/> trapped at the peripheral capillary, and when infusion<lb/> volume increases, the measurement accuracy will rise<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(18)</ref>. However, disturbances may occur in the rat&apos;s<lb/> circulation. Kobayashi et al. <ref type="biblio">(22)</ref> described that a bolus<lb/> injection of less than one million colored microspheres<lb/> caused no significant hemodynamic disturbances in rats,<lb/></p>

			<figure>Figure 4. Percentage change of organ blood flow in the control group<lb/> and ST-7 group. It shows box and whisker plot of percentage change of<lb/> organ blood flow in the control group and ST-7 group (c, control<lb/> group; a, acupuncture group; M, muscle; K, kidney; ST, stomach;<lb/> SI, small intestine, B, brain; LU, lung; HE, heart; SP, spleen and LI,<lb/> liver). The values are shown the lower extreme, 10 and 25%, median, 75<lb/> and 90% and the upper extreme. *P50.05,**P50.01.<lb/></figure>

			<figure>Figure 3. Organ blood flow in the ST-7 group (mean AE SD). It shows<lb/> blood flow of the first and second organ blood flow in the ST-7 group.<lb/> S means the number of tissue sample.<lb/></figure>

			<p>and 500 000 colored microspheres were repeatedly<lb/> injected up to four times (cumulative dose of 2 000 000<lb/> colored microspheres) without producing any adverse<lb/> hemodynamic effects. Generally, blood vessels have the<lb/> following diameters: capillaries are 1-8 mm, arterioles are<lb/> 20-30 mm and arteriovenous anastomoses are 2-150 mm.<lb/> Therefore, if 15 mm microspheres are used, a measure-<lb/>ment of true capillaries or nutrient blood flow will<lb/> result <ref type="biblio">(22)</ref>, and many researchers use 15 mm microspheres<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(6,7-17,21,22,24-28,29-32)</ref>. In our experiment, we<lb/> used 15 mm colored microspheres with a density of<lb/> 1.0-1.09 g/ml and the colored microspheres were sus-<lb/>pended in distilled water. In this experiment, infusion<lb/> volume of blue microspheres increased more than<lb/> yellow microspheres, because blue needs a greater<lb/> number of microspheres than yellow to obtain the same<lb/> absorbance from colored dye extraction of blue and<lb/> yellow microspheres <ref type="biblio">(3)</ref>. Some values of mean organ<lb/> blood flow values (ml/min/g) in rats are reported by<lb/> measuring microspheres.<lb/></p>

			<p>The mean organ blood flow of other investigations<lb/> (ml/min/g) was also measured by microspheres in rats.<lb/> A comparison of the mean values of our experimental<lb/> results with conventional results is as follows:<lb/> muscle: 0.06-1.27 (0.20); kidney: 3.8-10.13 (3.91);<lb/> stomach: 0.5-2.38(0.74); small intestine: 1.7-4.63(2.77);<lb/> brain: 0.46-1.66(0.54); lung: 0.46-2.59(0.60); heart:<lb/> 3.11-6.17(4.03); spleen: 1.15-3.49(1.30) and liver:<lb/> 0.14-0.4(0.14) <ref type="biblio">(6,7,9-11,22,25,27,31,32)</ref>. The values in<lb/> parentheses show our results.<lb/></p>

			<p>Although blood flow has a different value for each per<lb/> organ, our results corresponded with those of past<lb/> reports. There was a significant decrease in muscle,<lb/> kidney, stomach, brain and spleen in the control group<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>) and the blood flow of other organs also tended to<lb/> decrease. Blood pressure decreased significantly from the<lb/> time of the first blood sampling and after the second.<lb/> Though we considered that the infusion volume of<lb/> microspheres in this experiment would not cause sig-<lb/>nificant change in blood flow, these results were beyond<lb/> expectation. Though the reason is unclear, it may have<lb/> been caused by microspheres being caught in capillaries.<lb/> In results of blood flow measurement using colored<lb/> microspheres and Laser Doppler in the small intestines<lb/> of anesthetized rats, Wahlberg et al. <ref type="biblio">(14)</ref> described<lb/> that blood flow and blood pressure decreased when<lb/> the second infusion of 120 000-140 000 microspheres<lb/> (cumulative dose of 240 000-280 000 microspheres) was<lb/> done. They suggested that microspheres trapped in<lb/> capillaries were the cause. From this evidence, we<lb/> consider that a low volume of microsphere infusion<lb/> is needed to achieve stable organ blood flow.<lb/></p>

			<p>There was a significant increase of blood flow in the<lb/> muscle, kidney, brain and heart between the control<lb/> group and ST-7 group (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). These results suggest that<lb/> acupuncture stimulation affected blood flow of multiple<lb/> organs. Lee <ref type="biblio">(33)</ref> reported that acupuncture stimulation<lb/> by twirling at GO-26 (located at midpoint of the<lb/> philtrum) for 30 min caused significant increase in<lb/> stroke volume and cardiac output, and a significant<lb/> decrease in total peripheral resistance in anesthetized<lb/> dogs. Meanwhile, mean blood pressure and heart rate did<lb/> not change significantly. In our experiment, we found no<lb/> significant temporal change of mean blood pressure and<lb/> heart rate between the control and ST-7 groups (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>),<lb/> when acupuncture was performed at the trigeminal area<lb/> (close to the area that Lee stimulated in the ST-7 group).<lb/> Perhaps that acupuncture might cause an increase in<lb/> stroke volume and decrease in total peripheral resistance.<lb/> As a result, although mean blood pressure did not change<lb/> significantly, it is still possible that blood flow of each<lb/> organ was affected.<lb/></p>

			<p>In the case of acupuncture to the left masseter, muscle<lb/> blood flow of the left masseter tended to increase more<lb/></p>

			<figure>Figure 6. Percentage change of organ blood flow in the control group<lb/> and LI-4 group. It shows box and whisker plot of percentage change of<lb/> organ blood flow in the control group and LI-4 group.<lb/> </figure>

			<figure>Figure 5. Organ blood flow in the LI-4 group (mean AE SD). It shows<lb/> blood flow of the first and second organ blood flow in the LI-4 group.<lb/> **P50.01.<lb/></figure>

			<p>than the right masseter (P ¼ 0.08). This phenomenon<lb/> suggests that acupuncture increased muscle blood flow by<lb/> some peripheral mechanism. Robert Porszasz et al. <ref type="biblio">(34)<lb/></ref> reported antidromic vasodilatation in the striated muscle<lb/> of rats, and there is a research paper suggesting that the<lb/> axon reflex in the skeletal muscle may occur with<lb/> acupuncture <ref type="biblio">(35)</ref>. From the above, we considered that<lb/> peripheral mechanisms such as antidromic vasodilation<lb/> and axon reflex may contribute to the increase of blood<lb/> flow of the area stimulated by acupuncture. However,<lb/> acupuncture not only increases blood flow of the<lb/> stimulated area, but also simultaneously increased multi-<lb/>ple organ blood flow including brain in comparison with<lb/> the control group, suggesting that organ blood flow in<lb/> the whole body in being influenced through the central<lb/> nervous system (CNS) without change in blood pressure.<lb/> It is also possible that polymodal receptors take part as<lb/> peripheral receptors of acupuncture stimulation.<lb/> Polymodal receptors are distributed throughout the<lb/> body and react to mechanical, nociceptive and chemical<lb/> stimulation. Polymodal receptors fully react by acupunc-<lb/>ture stimulation in this experiment <ref type="biblio">(36,37)</ref>. Polymodal<lb/> receptors also cause axon reflex in the skin <ref type="biblio">(36, 37)</ref>.<lb/> For these reasons, we consider that polymodal receptors<lb/> are the peripheral receptors of acupuncture stimulation.<lb/> Below, we describe our hypothesis for the mechanism of<lb/> acupuncture stimulation on blood flow of various organs<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>). Acupuncture stimulation increases blood flow of<lb/> the stimulated area by causing axon reflex via polymodal<lb/> receptors and increased stroke volume and cardiac<lb/> output, as well as a decrease in total peripheral resistance<lb/> via CNS at the same time.<lb/></p>

			<p>Furthermore, to examine organ blood flow with a<lb/> different stimulation point, LI-4 was selected, because<lb/> LI-4 is often used clinically in acupuncture treatment.<lb/> Our results differed from those of the ST-7 group in that<lb/> there was no significant difference between the control<lb/> and LI-4 groups (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>). This suggests that organ blood<lb/> flow is affected differently by stimulating different points.<lb/> We considered that the regulation mechanism of the<lb/> automatic nerve system is different, because ST-7<lb/> (trigeminal nerve area) and LI-4 (spinal nerve area)<lb/> have different innervations.<lb/></p>

			<p>Adachi et al. <ref type="biblio">(38)</ref> reported that noxious mechanical<lb/> stimulation of the skin on the hind paw, forepaw or face<lb/> caused a significant increase in cerebral blood flow in<lb/> anesthetized rats, whereas noxious mechanical stimula-<lb/>tion of the back failed to produce any significant changes<lb/> in cortical blood flow. They speculated that differences in<lb/> magnitude of changes in cortical blood flow and blood<lb/> pressure elicited by similar stimulation of different<lb/> cutaneous areas may be related to differences in<lb/> conduction of impulses and/or in density of innervations<lb/> of different skin areas. In addition, Noguchi et al. <ref type="biblio">(2)<lb/></ref> reported that electro-acupuncture stimulation of a hind<lb/> paw produced an increase in skeletal muscle blood flow<lb/> in muscle biceps femoral&apos;s of hind limbs accompanied by<lb/> an increase in systemic arterial blood pressure in<lb/> anesthetized rats. Ohsawa et al. <ref type="biblio">(39)</ref> reported that<lb/> acupuncture like stimulation (the needle was twisted<lb/> right and left) of an area corresponding to Tzu-San-Li<lb/> point in humans induced a decrease in mean arterial<lb/> pressure which was accompanied by a decrease in renal<lb/> sympathetic nerve activity in anesthetized rats, and it is<lb/> also known that electrical acupuncture stimulation of<lb/> Tzu-San-Li in anesthetized rats produce depressor of<lb/> mean arterial pressure <ref type="biblio">(40)</ref>. Inoue et al. <ref type="biblio">(41)</ref> reported that<lb/> manual acupuncture stimulation of 10 mm lateral to the<lb/> L6 vertebra spinous process in anesthetized rats (the<lb/> needle was rotated) did not produce consistent changes in<lb/> sciatic nerve blood flow, with increased and decreased<lb/> blood flow as well as no change in observed blood flow.<lb/> Sugiyama reported that manual acupuncture (the needle<lb/> was rotated) of the Tsu-San-Li point in human produced<lb/> an increase in muscle sympathetic nerve activity <ref type="biblio">(42)</ref>.<lb/> All these reports suggest that different methods or<lb/> regions of acupuncture stimulation influence blood<lb/> pressure and autonomic nerves differently.<lb/></p>

			<p>While conventional acupuncture research on the<lb/> circulatory system has targeted individual organs or<lb/> tissue blood flow, our method of using colored micro-<lb/>sphere may be the first time that we have been able to<lb/> grasp changes in multiple organ blood flow by acupunc-<lb/>ture at the same time. It is our hope that these results<lb/> have great significance for future acupuncture research.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
