<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>GLP-1 (glucagon-like peptide-1) is a peptide hormone pro-<lb/>duced by post-translational processing of proglucagon in the<lb/> intestinal L-cells <ref type="biblio">(1)</ref>. GLP-1 is an incretin that potentiates the<lb/> synthesis and release of insulin from pancreatic ␤-cells in a<lb/> glucose-dependent manner <ref type="biblio">(2)</ref> and has a number of other ben-<lb/>eficial effects that contribute to reducing blood sugar <ref type="biblio">(3-6)</ref>. In<lb/> addition, GLP-1 has been shown to reduce body weight <ref type="biblio">(3, 5, 7)</ref>,<lb/> which is favorable for many people with type 2 diabetes. Hence,<lb/> GLP-1-based therapies are becoming increasingly attractive for<lb/> the treatment of type 2 diabetes. The actions of GLP-1 are<lb/> mediated through the GLP-1 receptor (GLP-1R), <ref type="biblio">3</ref> which is a<lb/> seven-transmembrane G protein-coupled receptor (GPCR)<lb/> coupled to adenylyl cyclase <ref type="biblio">(8)</ref>. The human GLP-1R was first<lb/> cloned in 1992 and belongs to class B of GPCRs <ref type="biblio">(9)</ref>. This class<lb/> includes a wide range of receptors for peptide hormones like<lb/> glucagon, GLP-2 (glucagon-like peptide-2), glucose-<lb/>dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP), pituitary aden-<lb/>ylyl cyclase-activating polypeptide (PACAP), vasoactive<lb/> intestinal polypeptide, secretin, calcitonin, corticotrophin-<lb/>releasing factor, and parathyroid hormone (PTH) <ref type="biblio">(10)</ref>. The<lb/> receptors are distinguished by their large extracellular<lb/> N-terminal domain (ECD), which is important for ligand<lb/> binding and selectivity <ref type="biblio">(11, 12)</ref>. The current binding model<lb/> suggests a two-domain mechanism where the C-terminal<lb/> part of the ligand binds the ECD and the N-terminal part of<lb/> the ligand binds the extracellular loops and transmembrane<lb/> ␣-helices (TM domain), which leads to receptor activation<lb/> (reviewed in Ref. <ref type="biblio">13</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>The first structure of an isolated ECD of a class B GPCR<lb/> was solved recently by NMR spectroscopy <ref type="biblio">(14)</ref>. Subse-<lb/>quently, structures of ligand-bound ECDs were solved, includ-<lb/>ing the ECD of the human type 1 corticotrophin-releasing fac-<lb/>tor receptor 1 <ref type="biblio">(15)</ref>, the human type 1 PACAP receptor <ref type="biblio">(16)</ref>, the<lb/> human GIP receptor <ref type="biblio">(17)</ref>, the human GLP-1R <ref type="biblio">(18)</ref>, and the<lb/> human type 1 PTH receptor <ref type="biblio">(19)</ref>. The ECDs of class B receptors<lb/> have a common structure, the secretin recognition fold, which<lb/> is stabilized by three conserved disulfide bonds and five con-<lb/>served residues (Asp 67 , Trp 72 , Pro 86 , Gly 108, and Trp 110 in GLP-<lb/>1R). The receptor-bound ligands are primarily in ␣-helical con-<lb/>formation, and the C-terminal part of the ligands binds the<lb/> ECD in agreement with the two-domain binding mechanism.<lb/> Several receptor models have been proposed for full-length<lb/> class B receptors <ref type="biblio">(20 -23)</ref>. However, the orientation of the ECD<lb/> relative to the TM domain is uncertain.<lb/></p>

			<p>Exendin-4 is a 39-amino acid peptide, which was originally<lb/> isolated from the venom of the lizard Heloderma suspectum<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(24)</ref>. GLP-1 and exendin-4 are 50% identical, and exendin-4 is a<lb/> full agonist with similar affinity and potency for the full-length<lb/> GLP-1R <ref type="biblio">(25)</ref>. However, structure-activity studies have demon-<lb/>strated interesting differences between the binding modes of<lb/> GLP-1 and exendin-4. 1) The isolated ECD binds exendin-4<lb/> with high affinity (IC 50 of 6 nM) and GLP-1 with low affinity<lb/> (IC 50 Ͼ500 nM) <ref type="biblio">(26, 27)</ref>. 2) GLP-1 binding is more sensitive to<lb/> site-directed mutagenesis of the TM domain compared with<lb/> exendin-4 binding <ref type="biblio">(28 -30)</ref>. 3) GLP-1 is much more sensitive to<lb/> N-terminal truncation than exendin-4 <ref type="biblio">(31)</ref>. N-terminally trun-<lb/>cated exendin-4 variants maintain high affinity but are unable<lb/> to activate GLP-1R, i.e. competitive antagonist, whereas N-ter-<lb/>minal truncation of GLP-1 severely affects both binding and<lb/> activation <ref type="biblio">(31)</ref>. Clearly, the interaction between the N-terminal<lb/> part of GLP-1 and the TM domain is critical for binding and<lb/> activation of GLP-1R.<lb/></p>

			<p>Exendin-4(9 -39) is a truncated form of exendin-4, and a<lb/> competitive antagonist that maintains high affinity for GLP-1R<lb/> through interactions with the ECD (IC 50 value of 6 nM for the<lb/> isolated ECD) <ref type="biblio">(27, 32)</ref>. We recently solved the crystal structure<lb/> of the GLP-1R ECD in complex with exendin-4(9 -39) (18).<lb/> Exendin-4(9 -39) is ␣-helical in the ECD-bound conformation<lb/> except for the C-terminal segment, the so-called Trp cage <ref type="biblio">(33,<lb/> 34)</ref>. In solution, the helical propensity of exendin-4 is higher<lb/> than that of GLP-1 <ref type="biblio">(27, 33)</ref>. Biophysical studies showed a pos-<lb/>itive correlation between ␣-helical propensity in solution and<lb/> affinity for the GLP-1R ECD <ref type="biblio">(27)</ref>. Moreover, charged residues<lb/> of exendin-4 interact with the ECD in a manner not possible for<lb/> GLP-1 <ref type="biblio">(18)</ref>. Hence, the high affinity of exendin-4 for the ECD<lb/> may be a combination of high helical propensity in solution and<lb/> unique receptor interactions.<lb/></p>

			<p>Here, we report the crystal structure of the GLP-1R ECD in<lb/> complex with its endogenous agonist GLP-1. We supple-<lb/>mented the crystal structure with site-directed mutagenesis to<lb/> link the structural information of the isolated ECD with the<lb/> binding properties of the full-length receptor.<lb/></p>

			<head>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES<lb/></head>

			<p>Protein and Peptide Preparation-The GLP-1R ECD was<lb/> prepared as described previously <ref type="biblio">(27)</ref>. Briefly, N-terminal His 6 -<lb/>tagged ECD was expressed in Escherichia coli inclusion bodies,<lb/> isolated as inclusion body protein, solubilized in guanidine-HCl<lb/> and dithiothreitol, dialyzed against guanidine-HCl to remove<lb/> the dithiothreitol, and refolded using L-Arg and a 1:5 molar<lb/> ratio of reduced and oxidized glutathione. The refolded ECD<lb/> was purified by hydrophobic interaction chromatography and<lb/> size exclusion chromatography in 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 0.1<lb/> M Na 2 SO 4 , 2% glycerol. The His 6 tag was removed by thrombin<lb/> cleavage. The purified GLP-1R ECD consisted of four amino<lb/> acids, Gly-Ser-His-Met, of the linker attached to the N-termi-<lb/>nus of ECD (Arg 24 -Tyr 145 ), M r ϭ 14,723 g/mol after removal of<lb/> the His 6 tag. Native GLP-1(7-37)-OH was synthesized as<lb/> described previously <ref type="biblio">(12)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Purification and Crystallization of the GLP-1-bound Extra-<lb/>cellular Domain-The purified GLP-1R ECD was concentrated<lb/> to 1.2 mg/ml, mixed with 3-fold molar excess of GLP-1 (7-37)<lb/> (dissolved in 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5), and incubated overnight<lb/> at 4 °C. The GLP-1-bound ECD was purified by size exclusion<lb/> chromatography on a Superdex 75 column in 10 mM Tris-HCl,<lb/> pH 7.5, at a flow rate of 0.3 ml/min and characterized by SDS-<lb/>PAGE (supplemental Fig. <ref type="figure">S1</ref>). The complex was concentrated<lb/> to 4 mg/ml and crystallized by hanging drop vapor diffusion.<lb/> The crystallization conditions were initially identified using the<lb/> Crystal Screen from Hampton Research and subsequently opti-<lb/>mized to 0.1 M N(2-acetamido)iminodiacetic acid, pH 6.9, 14<lb/> volume % ()-2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol and 9 mM n-decyl--<lb/>D-thiomaltoside. Single crystals were flashed cooled in liquid N 2<lb/> using 30% glycerol in the cryo solution.<lb/></p>

			<p>Data Collection and Structure Determination-Diffraction<lb/> data were collected from a single crystal using beamline 1911-3<lb/> at MAX-lab (Lund, Sweden). The data were integrated and<lb/> scaled using XDS <ref type="biblio">(35)</ref>. The crystals belonged to space group<lb/> P2 1 22 1 with the unit cell dimensions a 35.7 Å, b 42.7 Å, and<lb/> c 95.1 Å. The phases and electron density map were obtained<lb/> by molecular replacement using Phaser running in the CCP4<lb/> program interface with one complex in the asymmetric unit.<lb/> Refinement was done using COOT <ref type="biblio">(36)</ref> and REFMAC5 <ref type="biblio">(37)</ref>.<lb/> Well defined electron density was obtained for GLP-1 residues<lb/> Thr 11 *-Val 33 * and for ECD residues Val 30 -Glu 128 . Poor den-<lb/>sity was observed for GLP-1 residues Gly 10 *, Lys 34 *, and Gly 35 *<lb/> and ECD residues Thr 29 and Asn 115. No electron density was<lb/> observed for His 7 *-Glu 9 * and Arg 36 *-Gly 37 * of GLP-1. Our<lb/> final structure contains GLP-1 residues Gly 10 *-Gly 35 * and ECD<lb/> residues Thr 29-Glu 128 , but it should be noted that the confor-<lb/>mation of Lys 34 * of GLP-1 is very uncertain, and because of the<lb/> poor density we have chosen to show Asn 115 as Gly. The final<lb/> GLP-1-bound ECD structure has 116 residues in preferred<lb/> regions, 5 in allowed regions and only 1 outlier (Glu 68 in the<lb/> ␤-turn between ␤ 1 and ␤ 2 shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1A</ref>) in the Ramachan-<lb/>dran plot. The structure containing 73 water molecules and a<lb/> detergent molecule (n-decyl-␤-D-thiomaltoside) has a working<lb/> R-factor of 0.181% and a free R-factor of 0.226%. Data collection<lb/> and refinement statistics are summarized in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. Coordi-<lb/>nates and structure factors are deposited in the Protein Data<lb/> Bank under accession code 3IOL. Molecular graphics were pre-<lb/>pared in PyMOL <ref type="biblio">(46)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Receptor Constructs-The cDNA encoding the human GLP-<lb/>1R was originally obtained from Dr. B. Thorens <ref type="biblio">(9)</ref> and sub-<lb/>cloned into the mammalian expression vector pcDNA3.1/<lb/> v5-His-TOPO (Invitrogen). The presence of the C-terminal<lb/> His 6 tag was previously shown not to influence the functional<lb/> response of the receptor <ref type="biblio">(12)</ref>. Site-directed mutagenesis of<lb/> GLP-1R was done using QuikChange TM (Stratagene). Plasmid<lb/> DNA was generated using the NucleoBond Xtra Maxi Plus kit<lb/> (Macherey-Nagel), and the desired mutations were confirmed<lb/> by dideoxynucleotide sequencing.<lb/></p>

			<p>Cell Culture and Receptor Expression-Human embryonic<lb/> kidney (HEK) 293 cells were maintained in Dulbecco&apos;s modified<lb/> Eagle&apos;s medium (BioWhittaker) supplemented with 10 volume<lb/> % fetal bovine serum and 1 volume % penicillin/streptomycin<lb/> (100 units/ml) in T175 flasks. HEK293 cells were transiently<lb/> transfected with 21 g of GLP-1R DNA using the FuGENE TM<lb/> transfection reagent (Roche Applied Science), harvested<lb/> 24 h after transfection, and used directly in functional exper-<lb/>iments or plasma membrane preparations as described pre-<lb/>viously <ref type="biblio">(12)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Functional Assay-Transiently transfected HEK293 cells<lb/> expressing wild-type GLP-1R or mutant receptors were har-<lb/>vested and resuspended in assay buffer (Flashplate,<lb/> PerkinElmer Life Sciences) to a cell density of 2.4 10 6 cells/<lb/> ml. GLP-1(7-37)-acid and exendin-4 were diluted in phos-<lb/>phate-buffered saline with 0.02 volume % Tween 20. Cells in<lb/> assay buffer (50 l) and GLP-1 or exendin-4 (50 l) were mixed<lb/> in 96-well FlashPlates (PerkinElmer Life Sciences), gently agi-<lb/>tated for 5 min, and incubated for 25 min at room temperature.<lb/> The resulting intracellular level of cAMP was measured accord-<lb/>ing to supplier&apos;s manual and analyzed by nonlinear regression/<lb/> sigmoidal dose-response fitting using Prism 5.0 (GraphPad<lb/> Software, Inc.).<lb/></p>

			<p>Receptor Binding Assay-Freshly<lb/> thawed plasma membrane prepara-<lb/>tions from transiently transfected<lb/> HEK293 cells expressing GLP-1R<lb/> (20 g protein/well) were pulled<lb/> through a 25-gauge needle three<lb/> times and diluted in assay buffer (50<lb/> mM HEPES, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 5 mM<lb/> EGTA, 0.005 volume % Tween 20,<lb/> pH 7.4). GLP-1 and exendin-4 were<lb/> diluted in assay buffer. The concen-<lb/>tration range was 1 pM to 100 nM<lb/> for GLP-1 and exendin-4. 125 I-GLP-<lb/>1(7-36)-amide (2.2 Ci/mol) was<lb/> dissolved in assay buffer and added<lb/> at 50,000 cpm per well to a final<lb/> concentration of 50 pM. Nonspe-<lb/>cific binding was determined with<lb/> 1 M GLP-1. Membrane prepara-<lb/>tion and radioligand were mixed in<lb/> 96-well 0.65-m filter plates (Milli-<lb/>pore) with either diluted GLP-1 or<lb/> exendin-4 and incubated for 1 h at<lb/> 37 °C. Subsequently, bound and<lb/> unbound radioligands were sepa-<lb/>rated by vacuum filtration (Milli-<lb/>pore vacuum manifold). The filters<lb/> were washed twice in 100 l of cold<lb/> assay buffer and left to dry. Data<lb/> were analyzed by nonlinear regres-<lb/>sion, and the expression level (B max )<lb/> was calculated using Prism 5.0<lb/> (GraphPad Software, Inc.).<lb/></p>

			<head>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION<lb/></head>

			<p>Purification, Crystallization, and<lb/> Structure Determination-The GLP-<lb/>1R ECD was expressed in E. coli<lb/> inclusion bodies, refolded, and purified as described previously<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(27)</ref>. A complex of GLP-1 and the ECD was purified by size<lb/> exclusion chromatography (supplemental Fig. S<ref type="figure">1</ref>). The purified<lb/> complex was characterized by SDS-PAGE (supplemental Fig.<lb/>  <ref type="figure">S1</ref>), concentrated, and crystallized by hanging drop vapor dif-<lb/>fusion. Diffraction data were collected from a single crystal<lb/> using the beamline 1911-3 at MAX-lab (Lund, Sweden), and<lb/> the structure of GLP-1 in complex with the GLP-1R ECD was<lb/> solved to 2.1 Å resolution by molecular replacement (Fig.<lb/> <ref type="figure">1A</ref>). We removed exendin-4(9 -39) from the structure of the<lb/> exendin-4(9 -39)-ECD complex (Protein Data Bank code<lb/> 3C59) and used the apo-form of GLP-1R ECD as the search<lb/> model for the molecular replacement. GLP-1 was then built<lb/> into the model; its position was unambiguous due to good elec-<lb/>tron density for most of the ligand. Data collection and refine-<lb/>ment statistics are summarized in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. Throughout the text,<lb/> GLP-1 and exendin-4 residues are designated with * and **,<lb/> respectively. Exendin-4 is numbered 1-39 and GLP-1 is num-<lb/>bered 7-37, due to post-translational processing. The aligned<lb/> sequences are illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">1B</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<figure>FIGURE 1. Structure of the GLP-1-bound ECD of the GLP-1R. A, stereoview of GLP-1 (blue) bound to the ECD<lb/> of the GLP-1R (␣-helix in black, ␤-strands in red, and loops in gray). Disulfide bridges are shown as orange sticks.<lb/> Residues Cys 62 -Asp 67 (␤ 1 ) and Ala 70 -Gly 75 (␤ 2 ) constitute the first region of antiparallel ␤-sheets, and the<lb/> second region is comprised of residues Gly 78 -Ser 84 (␤ 3 ) and His 99 -Thr 105 (␤ 4 ), which is shown in red. Our final<lb/> structure contains GLP-1 residues Gly 10 *-Gly 35 *. The residues that interact with GLP-1R ECD lie within Ala 24 *<lb/> and Val 33 *, which are shown as sticks. B, sequence alignment of GLP-1, exendin-4, GIP, GLP-2, glucagon, and<lb/> PACAP(1-27). Fully conserved residues are highlighted in yellow, and partially conserved residues are high-<lb/>lighted in green. The residues of GLP-1 and exendin-4 that interact with GLP-1R ECD are colored blue. The<lb/> underlined residues symbolize residues of GLP-1 in ␣-helical conformation when bound to the ECD. Residue<lb/> number 1 of exendin-4 corresponds to residue number 7 of GLP-1.<lb/></figure>

			<p>Structure of the GLP-1R Extracellular Domain-The crystal<lb/> structure of the ECD in the GLP-1-bound form shown here is<lb/> very similar to the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound form shown previ-<lb/>ously (root mean square deviation of 0.79 Å for C ␣ atoms of the<lb/> ECD) <ref type="biblio">(18)</ref>. The ligand-binding sites are identical, which is not<lb/> surprising given the competitive binding of GLP-1 and<lb/> exendin-4 for the full-length GLP-1R as well as the isolated<lb/> ECD <ref type="biblio">(27)</ref>. However, we have previously shown that divergent<lb/> residues in the two ligands are responsible for their different<lb/> physical properties in solution and their different affinity for<lb/> the ECD <ref type="biblio">(27)</ref>. As described below, these divergent residues give<lb/> rise to structural differences in the two ligand-bound forms of<lb/> the ECD at the level of specific side chain conformations.<lb/></p>

			<head>Structure of GLP-1 and Its Interactions with the Extracellular<lb/>Domain of GLP-1R-</head>

			<p>GLP-1 is a continuous ␣-helix from<lb/> Thr 13 * to Val 33 *, with a kink around Gly 22 *. The residues<lb/> between Ala 24 * and Val 33 * interact with the ECD (Fig. <ref type="figure">1, A and<lb/> B</ref>). The amphiphilic nature of this ␣-helical segment enables<lb/> hydrophilic and hydrophobic interactions through opposite<lb/> faces of the ␣-helix. The hydrophilic face is comprised by resi-<lb/>dues Gln 23 *, Lys 26 *, Glu 27 *, and Lys 34 *. Lys 26 * is the only one of<lb/> these that may interact directly with the ECD (Fig. <ref type="figure">2A</ref>). The side<lb/> chain of Lys 26 * may form a hydrogen bond with the side chain of<lb/> Glu 128 (3.0 Å), but the B-factor is rather high for both residues<lb/> (25 compared with 10 for well defined residues), suggesting<lb/> that this is not a strong interaction. In particular, the electron<lb/> density of the Lys 26 * side chain is rather weak. In exendin-4(9 -<lb/>39), the amphiphilic character is more pronounced, and the<lb/> ␣-helical conformation is further stabilized by intramolecular<lb/> interactions between Glu 16 **, Glu 17 **, Arg 20 **, Glu 24 **, and<lb/> Lys 27 ** on the hydrophilic face <ref type="biblio">(18)</ref>. In addition, Arg 20 ** and<lb/> Lys 27 ** interact with Glu 128 and Glu 127 of the ECD, respectively<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(18)</ref>. The corresponding intramolecular stabilization is not pos-<lb/>sible in GLP-1 due to a less favorable alignment of oppositely<lb/> charged residues (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B</ref>), and Glu 127 of the ECD is not<lb/> involved in binding of GLP-1 (Fig. <ref type="figure">2A</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>The hydrophobic face of GLP-1, which interacts with the<lb/> ECD, is defined by Ala 24 *, Ala 25 *, Phe 28 *, Ile 29 *, Leu 32 *, and<lb/> Val 33 * (Fig. <ref type="figure">2B</ref>). The importance of Phe 28 *, Ile 29 *, and Leu 32 * in<lb/> GLP-1 binding has been demonstrated previously by Ala scan-<lb/>ning of GLP-1 <ref type="biblio">(38)</ref>. Substitution of Phe 28 * with Ala had the<lb/> most severe effect on GLP-1 affinity in the Ala scan (IC 50 value<lb/> increased by 1300-fold), and indeed Phe 28 * is centrally posi-<lb/>tioned in the ligand-receptor interface emphasizing the impor-<lb/>tance of this hydrophobic ligand-receptor interaction. The<lb/> I29*A and L32*A substitutions also reduced GLP-1 affinity sig-<lb/>nificantly (IC 50 value increased by 93-and 17-fold, respectively)<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(38)</ref>. Trp 31 * is also on the hydrophobic face of GLP-1 but is<lb/> rather solvent-exposed and does not interact with the ECD<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">2B</ref>). Trp 31 * is conserved in the<lb/> glucagon peptide family (GLP-1,<lb/> exendin-4, glucagon, GIP, and<lb/> GLP-2, see Fig. <ref type="figure">1B</ref>), which implies a<lb/> unique role of this residue. How-<lb/>ever, substitution of Trp 31 * with Ala<lb/> only reduced the binding affinity of<lb/> GLP-1 slightly at the full-length<lb/> GLP-1R <ref type="biblio">(38)</ref>, so the role of Trp 31 * in<lb/> receptor binding is unclear.<lb/> </p>

			<p>Val 33 * is the final residue in the<lb/> ␣-helix of GLP-1, and it is the final<lb/> residue in the C terminus of GLP-1<lb/> that interacts with the ECD (Fig. <ref type="figure">2,<lb/> A and C</ref>). The side chain of Val 33 *<lb/> makes hydrophobic contacts with<lb/> Tyr 69 and Leu 123, and the backbone<lb/> carbonyl of Val 33 * interacts through<lb/> a hydrogen bond with one of the ter-<lb/>minal nitrogens of Arg 121 (Fig. <ref type="figure">2, A<lb/> and C</ref>). The other terminal nitrogen<lb/> of Arg 121 interacts with a water mol-<lb/></p>

			<figure>FIGURE 2. Interactions between GLP-1 and GLP-1R ECD. A, ribbon diagram of GLP-1 and its hydrophilic<lb/> interactions with GLP-1R ECD. GLP-1 is colored in cyan, and residues Gln 23 *, Lys 26 *, Glu 27 *, Trp 31 *, and Val 33 * are<lb/> illustrated as sticks. Receptor residues Arg 121 , Leu 123 , Glu 127 , and Glu 128 are shown as sticks. The surface of the<lb/> hydrophilic binding cavity of ECD is illustrated in gray. B, ribbon diagram of GLP-1 and its hydrophobic inter-<lb/>actions with GLP-1R ECD. GLP-1 residues Ala 24 *, Glu 27 *, Phe 28 *, Trp 31 *, and Leu 32 * are illustrated as sticks, and<lb/> so are ECD residues Leu 32 , Trp 39 , Asp 67 , and Arg 121 . The surface of the hydrophobic binding cavity of ECD is<lb/> illustrated in gray. C, ribbon diagram illustrating a common motif found in the GLP-1R ECD and in the GIP<lb/> receptor ECD. The side chain of Arg 121 interacts with the backbone carbonyls of Asp 67 and Leu 32 * through a<lb/> water molecule. GLP-1 residues Leu 32 * and Val 33 * are illustrated as sticks, and so are ECD residues Asp 67 and<lb/> Arg 121 .<lb/> </figure>

			<figure type="table">TABLE 1<lb/> Data collection and refinement statistics<lb/> The data set was collected from a single crystal. Values in parentheses are for the<lb/> highest resolution shell (2.2-2.1 Å).<lb/> Space group<lb/> P2 1 22 1<lb/> Unit cell dimensions (Å)<lb/> A<lb/> 35.7<lb/> B<lb/> 42.7<lb/> C<lb/> 95.1<lb/> Data collection<lb/> Wavelength<lb/> 1.0 Å<lb/> Resolution range<lb/> 95.1-2.1 Å (2.2-2.1 Å)<lb/> Total reflections<lb/> 73,811<lb/> Unique reflections<lb/> 10,348<lb/> Completeness<lb/> 97.9%<lb/> I/(I)<lb/> 14.0 (5.3)<lb/> R sym<lb/> 11.1 (44.9)<lb/> Refinement statistics<lb/> No. of non-hydrogen atoms<lb/> 1109<lb/> Resolution<lb/> 95.1-2.1 Å (2.155-2.100 Å)<lb/> Total reflections<lb/> 8786<lb/> Reflections in test set<lb/> 429<lb/> R work<lb/> 0.181 (0.187)<lb/> R free<lb/> 0.226 (0.255)<lb/> Average B-factors<lb/> 13.6<lb/> Root mean square deviation<lb/> Bond lengths<lb/> 0.02 Å<lb/> Bond angles<lb/> 1.7°<lb/> </figure>

			<p>ecule, which is also coordinated by the backbone carbonyl<lb/> groups of Asp 67 and Leu 32 * (Fig. <ref type="figure">2C</ref>). A water molecule is coor-<lb/>dinated by the same residues in the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound<lb/> ECD, and Arg 121 interacts with the backbone carbonyl of<lb/> Lys 27 ** of exendin-4(9 -39) in a manner similar to the interac-<lb/>tion with Val 33 * of GLP-1. Even though exendin-4 has a C-ter-<lb/>minal nine-residue extension, the so-called Trp cage, the extent<lb/> of the ␣-helix is similar for GLP-1 and exendin-4, and this par-<lb/>ticular length of the ␣-helix fits nicely into the ECD binding<lb/> pocket.<lb/></p>

			<p>Judging from the two ligand-bound ECD structures, the<lb/> hydrophobic ligand-receptor interface is highly conserved, and<lb/> the C-terminal ␣-helical structure of the ligands ends at the<lb/> same position with a similar arrangement of receptor interac-<lb/>tions mediated by the backbone of the ligand. Hence, the dif-<lb/>ferential affinity for the ECD may best be explained by the lower<lb/> ␣-helical propensity of GLP-1 in solution and by weaker recep-<lb/>tor interactions compared with exendin-4, as suggested previ-<lb/>ously <ref type="biblio">(27)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<head>Unique Structural Features of the GLP-1-bound Extracellu-<lb/>lar Domain-</head>

			<p>The divergent residues in GLP-1 and exendin-4<lb/> are not only responsible for the different physical properties<lb/> of the ligands in solution and their differential affinity for the<lb/> GLP-1R ECD, they also influence the conformation of certain<lb/> residues in the ECD structures. The crystal structure presented<lb/> here suggests that one diverging residue in the two ligands<lb/> (Val 33 * of GLP-1 and Lys 27 ** of exendin-4(9 -39)) causes a shift<lb/> in the conformations of four residues in (or close to) the binding<lb/> pocket of the ECD, namely Glu 127 , Leu 123 , Arg 121 , and Pro 119<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">3A</ref>). In exendin-4(9 -39), Lys 27 ** interacts with Glu 127,<lb/> and the positioning of the Lys 27 ** side chain appears to be<lb/> guided by a hydrophobic interaction with Leu 123 . In GLP-1,<lb/> Val 33 * is unable to interact with Glu 127 causing Glu 127 to<lb/> change rotamer conformation and point its side chain away<lb/> from GLP-1. The side chain of Leu 123 is flipped toward Arg 121 ,<lb/> which again is flipped toward<lb/> Pro 119 , thereby closing an otherwise<lb/> water-accessible cavity observed in<lb/> the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound struc-<lb/>ture (Fig. <ref type="figure">3A</ref>). The closing of this<lb/> cavity is assisted by a side chain flip<lb/> of Pro 119 toward Arg 121 . The appar-<lb/>ent GLP-1-specific conformations<lb/> affect the conserved core of the ECD<lb/> by rotating the guanidine group of<lb/> Arg 102 and by decreasing the dis-<lb/>tance between Asp 67 and Arg 102<lb/> compared with the exendin-4(9 -<lb/>39)-bound structure without affect-<lb/>ing the relative position and confor-<lb/>mation of Trp 72 and Trp 110 (Fig.<lb/> <ref type="figure">3B</ref>). This enables a direct interac-<lb/>tion through a hydrogen bond<lb/> between Asp 67 and Arg 102 unlike<lb/> what we observed in the exendin-<lb/>4(9 -39)-bound structure, where a<lb/> water molecule mediated the inter-<lb/>action between Asp 67 and Arg 102<lb/> (Fig. <ref type="figure">3B</ref>). The functional consequences of the ligand-specific<lb/> conformational differences are not known.<lb/></p>

			<head>Site-directed Mutagenesis of the GLP-1R-</head>

			<p>To link the struc-<lb/>tural information of the isolated ECD with the binding and<lb/> functional properties of the full-length receptor, we targeted<lb/> the ligand-binding site of the ECD by site-directed mutagene-<lb/>sis. The mutants were characterized by their ability to bind<lb/> GLP-1 and exendin-4, using the agonist 125 I-GLP-1 tracer, and<lb/> by their ability to stimulate cAMP production in response to<lb/> GLP-1 and exendin-4 (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). The main objective was to<lb/> search for mutations with differential effect on GLP-1 and<lb/> exendin-4. We initially focused on Glu 127 , which showed an<lb/> obvious conformational difference in the two ligand-bound<lb/> structures (Fig. <ref type="figure">3A</ref>), Glu 127 interacts directly with exendin-<lb/>4(9 -39) but not with GLP-1 <ref type="biblio">(18)</ref>. The ECD structures suggest<lb/> that the hydrogen-bonding potential of Glu 127 is important for<lb/> exendin-4 binding but not for binding of GLP-1, and this is<lb/> supported by the site-directed mutagenesis data (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).<lb/> Mutation of Glu 127 to Ala reduced the affinity for exendin-4 but<lb/> not for GLP-1 (6.8-versus 1.7-fold, respectively). Glu 128 inter-<lb/>acts with a positively charged residue in both GLP-1 and<lb/> exendin-4, which may explain why the E128A substitution did<lb/> not have a differential effect on the binding affinity of GLP-1<lb/> and exendin-4. The differential effect of the E127A mutation on<lb/> GLP-1 and exendin-4 binding is rather small compared with<lb/> the differential affinity of the isolated ECD shown previously<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(27)</ref>. Clearly, the superior helical propensity of exendin-4 con-<lb/>tributes strongly to its high affinity for the ECD.<lb/></p>

			<p>Several interactions are conserved in the two ECD structures,<lb/> and mutagenesis of the implicated receptor residues was not<lb/> expected to have differential effects on ligand binding (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).<lb/> Surprisingly, the L32A mutation reduced both the affinity<lb/> and potency of exendin-4 relative to GLP-1 (7.1-and 9.5-fold,<lb/> respectively, see Table <ref type="table">2</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>), demonstrating a ligand-<lb/>specific effect of the L32A mutation. Neither the potency nor<lb/></p>

			<figure>FIGURE 3. Differences between the GLP-1-and exendin-4(9 -39)-bound structure of ECD. Ribbon diagrams<lb/> showing significant differences in side chain conformations between the GLP-1-bound structure and the<lb/> exendin-4(9 -39)-bound structure of GLP-1R ECD. Receptor and ligand residues are highlighted in blue for the<lb/> GLP-1-bound structure and in orange for the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound structure. Water molecules in orange are<lb/> present only in the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound structure. A, one diverging residue, Val 33 * of GLP-1 and Lys 27 ** of<lb/> exendin-4(9 -39), causes a shift in the conformations of four residues, namely Glu 127 , Leu 123 , Arg 121 , and Pro 119 .<lb/> B, GLP-1-specific conformations affect the conserved core of the ECD by rotating the guanidine group of Arg 102<lb/> and by decreasing the distance between Asp 67 and Arg 102 compared with the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound struc-<lb/>ture without affecting the relative position of Trp 72 and Trp 110 .<lb/></figure>

			<p>the affinity of GLP-1 was affected by the L32A mutation (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>),<lb/> and the expression level of the receptor was similar to wild-type<lb/> GLP-1R, which confirmed the structural integrity of this<lb/> receptor mutant. Leu 32 is the first<lb/> residue in the ␣-helix of the GLP-1R<lb/> ECD, and it defines the border of<lb/> the hydrophobic binding cavity by<lb/> interacting with Ala 24 *, Ala 25 *, and<lb/> Phe 28 * (Fig. <ref type="figure">2B</ref>). The results suggest<lb/> that Leu 32 is important for the bind-<lb/>ing of exendin-4 but not for the<lb/> binding of GLP-1 to GLP-1R. It is<lb/> difficult to give a structural explana-<lb/>tion of the ligand-specific effect of<lb/> the L32A mutation by comparing<lb/> the two ligand-bound forms of the<lb/> ECD, because the structural differ-<lb/>ences in this region are quite subtle.<lb/> Nevertheless, the ligand-specific<lb/> effect of the L32A mutation sup-<lb/>ports the existence of differences in<lb/> the binding modes of GLP-1 and<lb/> exendin-4 to the full-length GLP-1R.<lb/> Clearly, the two-domain binding<lb/> mechanism of the full-length GLP-<lb/>1R is more complex than binding of<lb/> the isolated ECD.<lb/></p>

			<head>Conformation of GLP-1, Recep-<lb/>tor-bound and in Solution-</head>

			<p>GLP-1<lb/> is highly flexible in aqueous buffers,<lb/> whereas in trifluoroethanol a single-<lb/>stranded ␣-helix forms (Thr 13 * to<lb/> Lys 34 *) with a less defined ␣-helical<lb/> region around Gly 22 *, as demon-<lb/>strated by NMR spectroscopy <ref type="biblio">(33,<lb/> 39)</ref>. Structure-activity studies of<lb/> GLP-1 showed that side chain to<lb/> side chain cyclization by lactam<lb/> bridge formation of residues 16 -20<lb/> and 18 -22 were well tolerated. Cyclization of residues 11-15<lb/> improved potency for GLP-1R compared with the linear coun-<lb/></p>

			<figure>FIGURE 4. Functional and binding properties of the L32A GLP-1R mutant. Upper panel, stimulation of cAMP<lb/> production by transiently transfected HEK293 cells expressing the L32A mutant by GLP-1 (squares, A) and<lb/> exendin-4 (circles, B). Dashed dose-response curves represent cAMP production by GLP-1 and exendin-4 at the<lb/> wild-type GLP-1R, respectively. Lower panel, competition binding assay on plasma membranes from tran-<lb/>siently transfected HEK293 cells expressing the L32A mutant. GLP-1 binding curves are presented with squares<lb/> (C) and exendin-4 curves with circles (D). Dashed binding curves represent 125 I-GLP-1 displacement by GLP-1<lb/> and exendin-4 at the wild-type GLP-1R. Data are normalized according to 125 I-GLP-1 binding and correspond to<lb/> three independent experiments performed in duplicate.<lb/></figure>

			<figure type="table">TABLE 2<lb/> Functional and binding experiments with GLP-1R mutants<lb/> EC 50 and IC 50 values are given in pM and nM, respectively, and expression levels are given in fmol/mg total protein. Data represent the mean Ϯ S.E. of three or more<lb/> independent experiments performed in duplicate. The EC 50 or IC 50 values of GLP-1 and exendin-4 are compared with the wild-type GLP-1R using the unpaired t test.<lb/> Numbers in parentheses equal the relative difference between EC 50 or IC 50 values of GLP-1 and exendin-4 at each mutant compared with the wild-type receptor. ND means<lb/> not detectable, possibly due to no expression or no binding. * indicates p Ͻ 0.05; **, p Ͻ 0.01; and no asterisk means no significant difference.<lb/> Mutant<lb/> EC 50<lb/> IC 50<lb/> Expression level<lb/> GLP-1<lb/> Exendin-4<lb/> GLP-1<lb/> Exendin-4<lb/> pM<lb/> nM<lb/> fmol/mg<lb/> Wild type<lb/> 11 Ϯ 3.2<lb/> 5.5 Ϯ 1. 7<lb/> 1.0 Ϯ 0.20<lb/> 0.76 Ϯ 0.19<lb/> 5.5 Ϯ 0.16<lb/> L32A<lb/> 12 Ϯ 2.7 (1.1)<lb/> 52 Ϯ 24 (9.5)<lb/> 1.1 Ϯ 0.17 (1.1)<lb/> 5.4 Ϯ 1.5* (7.1)<lb/> 6.0 Ϯ 0.40<lb/> T35A<lb/> 30 Ϯ 7.4 (2.7)<lb/> 23 Ϯ 12 (4.2)<lb/> 3.1 Ϯ 0.80 (3.1)<lb/> 0.44 Ϯ 0.1** (0.6)<lb/> 0.38 Ϯ 0.01<lb/> V36A<lb/> 57 Ϯ 32 (5.2)<lb/> 36 Ϯ 20 (6.5)<lb/> 2.8 Ϯ 0.86 (2.8)<lb/> 0.98 Ϯ 0.34 (1.3)<lb/> 5.7 Ϯ 0.28<lb/> E68A<lb/> 15 Ϯ 2.4 (1.4)<lb/> 9.5 Ϯ 4.2 (1.7)<lb/> 1.9 Ϯ 0.90 (1.9)<lb/> 0.48 Ϯ 0.07 (0.6)<lb/> 5.7 Ϯ 0.07<lb/> Y69A<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> Y88A<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> L89A<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> ND<lb/> P90A<lb/> 55 Ϯ 12* (5.0)<lb/> 30 Ϯ 7.3* (5.5)<lb/> 2.8 Ϯ 1.6 (2.8)<lb/> 1.6 Ϯ 0.28 (2.1)<lb/> 5.6 Ϯ 0.22<lb/> R121A<lb/> 51 Ϯ 13* (4.6)<lb/> 44 Ϯ 10* (8.0)<lb/> 2.3 Ϯ 1.1 (2.3)<lb/> 1.2 Ϯ 0.02 (1.6)<lb/> 5.7 Ϯ 0.37<lb/> L123A<lb/> 17 Ϯ 4.6 (1.5)<lb/> 9.5 Ϯ 1.9 (1.7)<lb/> 1.1 Ϯ 0.38 (1.1)<lb/> 0.33 Ϯ 0.04 (0.4)<lb/> 2.6 Ϯ 0.09<lb/> E127A<lb/> 13 Ϯ 4.2 (1.2)<lb/> 11 Ϯ 0.45* (2.0)<lb/> 1.7 Ϯ 0.76 (1.7)<lb/> 5.2 Ϯ 2.0 (6.8)<lb/> 5.6 Ϯ 0.46<lb/> E127Q<lb/> 12 Ϯ 3.3 (1.1)<lb/> 6.8 Ϯ 1.4 (1.2)<lb/> 1.1 Ϯ 0.27 (1.1)<lb/> 0.82 Ϯ 0.15 (1.1)<lb/> 6.11 Ϯ 0.21<lb/> E128A<lb/> 28 Ϯ 6.2 (2.5)<lb/> 25 Ϯ 6.7* (4.5)<lb/> 2.7 Ϯ 0.91 (2.7)<lb/> 1.8 Ϯ 0.48 (2.4)<lb/> 6.0 Ϯ 0.49<lb/> E128Q<lb/> 10 Ϯ 3.0 (0.9)<lb/> 8.0 Ϯ 3.3 (1.5)<lb/> 0.66 Ϯ 0.11 (0.7)<lb/> 0.45 Ϯ 0.1 (0.6)<lb/> 5.2 Ϯ 0.12<lb/></figure>

			<p>terpart <ref type="biblio">(40, 41)</ref>. These data support the existence of an ␣-helical<lb/> conformation in the N-terminal part of GLP-1 when bound to<lb/> the full-length GLP-1R. It is interesting that in the ECD-bound<lb/> structure, the Thr 13 *-Glu 21 * segment of GLP-1 adopts an<lb/> ␣-helical conformation even though this segment does not<lb/> interact with the ECD. The C-terminal segment of GLP-1<lb/> (Ala 24 *-Val 33 *) is stabilized in a specific ␣-helical conformation<lb/> through binding to the ECD. This may subsequently stabilize an<lb/> ␣-helical conformation in the N-terminal part of the ligand<lb/> (Thr 13 *-Glu 21 *). This hypothesis is supported by the solution<lb/> structure of GLP-1 in different concentrations of trifluoroetha-<lb/>nol <ref type="biblio">(39)</ref>. GLP-1 is a random coil in pure water, but adding tri-<lb/>fluoroethanol enables the C-terminal segment of GLP-1 to<lb/> adopt an ␣-helix conformation. The C-terminal ␣-helix is grad-<lb/>ually extended toward the N-terminus of the peptide with<lb/> increasing concentrations of trifluoroethanol <ref type="biblio">(39)</ref>, and it seems<lb/> possible that a similar mechanism is initiated upon binding of<lb/> GLP-1 to the ECD. It was recently proposed that ␣-helix for-<lb/>mation of the ligand upon binding<lb/> to the ECD is an important step in<lb/> the activation of class B GPCRs <ref type="biblio">(23)</ref>.<lb/></p> 

			<p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">5A</ref>, the ␣-helix<lb/> of GLP-1 has a central distortion of<lb/> the backbone around Gly 22 *, which<lb/> is not observed in the exendin-4(9 -<lb/>39)-bound structure. The distortion<lb/> is also observed in the NMR struc-<lb/>tures of GLP-1 in solution <ref type="biblio">(39)</ref>.<lb/> However, we cannot exclude that<lb/> the kink observed in the crystal<lb/> structure is a result of crystal pack-<lb/>ing between the N-terminal part of<lb/> GLP-1 (Gly 10 *-Glu 21 *) and symme-<lb/>try-related ECDs rather than a func-<lb/>tionally important characteristic of<lb/> GLP-1 (Fig. <ref type="figure">5, B-D</ref>). Substitution of<lb/> Gly 22 * with Ala was previously shown<lb/> not to affect the functionality or the<lb/> binding affinity of GLP-1, which sug-<lb/>gests that flexibility around Gly 22 * is<lb/> not required for binding to or acti-<lb/>vation of GLP-1R <ref type="biblio">(38)</ref>. Interest-<lb/>ingly, Leu 32 of the ECD is positioned<lb/> right next to the kink of GLP-1 (Fig.<lb/> <ref type="figure">5A</ref>). Thus, we have demonstrated a<lb/> ligand-specific effect of the L32A<lb/> mutation and have shown that<lb/> ECD-bound GLP-1 has a kink right<lb/> next to Leu 32, whereas ECD-bound<lb/> exendin-4(9 -39) is straight. This<lb/> may be a coincidence, but it is<lb/> tempting to speculate that there is a<lb/> connection between the structural<lb/> difference of the ligands (kinked or<lb/> straight helix) and the differential<lb/> effect of the L32A mutant on bind-<lb/>ing of the ligands.<lb/></p>

			<p>A three-dimensional model of<lb/> GLP-1R was recently published <ref type="biblio">(21)</ref>. From the NMR structure<lb/> of GLP-1 in trifluoroethanol (Protein Data Bank code 1D0R<lb/> (39)), it was suggested that GLP-1 might assume one of two<lb/> forms when bound to GLP-1R, a slightly kinked ␣-helix or an<lb/> L-shaped -helix, and the authors concluded that the L-shaped<lb/> ␣-helix conformation of GLP-1 seemed more reasonable<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(21)</ref>. The crystal structure presented here is more compatible<lb/> with the kinked conformation of GLP-1.<lb/></p>

			<p>The structure of His 7 *-Gly 10 * was not determined in this<lb/> study probably due to the inherent flexibility in this part of<lb/> GLP-1 and other peptide ligands for class B receptors <ref type="biblio">(33, 39,<lb/> 42, 43)</ref>. The only structural evidence showing a unique confor-<lb/>mation comes from a structural study of PACAP(1-21) com-<lb/>paring micelle-and receptor-bound states. Residues 1-7 of<lb/> PACAP(1-21) adopt a specific -coil structure upon receptor<lb/> binding followed by an ␣-helical structure of residues 8 -21<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(44)</ref>. The relevance of the receptor-bound PACAP(1-21) struc-<lb/>ture for GLP-1 in particular is supported by a previous study of<lb/> </p>

			<figure>FIGURE 5. Crystal packing. A, superposition of ECD-bound GLP-1 (blue) and exendin-4(9 -39) (cyan). GLP-1<lb/> residue Gly 22 * denotes a kink in the ␣-helix, which is situated in close proximity to Leu 32 of the ECD. B, crystal<lb/> packing involving symmetry-related complex molecules. C, ribbon diagram of GLP-1 (blue) and its interactions<lb/> with the ligand of a symmetry-related molecule. Residues Tyr 19 *, Gln 23 *, and Glu 27 * are shown as sticks, and the<lb/> surface of the GLP-1R ECD is shown in gray. The packing of complex molecules allows Tyr 19 * to interact with<lb/> Gln 23 * (3 Å) and Glu 27 * (2.5 Å) in a symmetry-related ligand molecule. D, interactions between GLP-1 and<lb/> residues of symmetry-related ECD molecules. GLP-1 residues Thr 11 * , Thr 13 *, Ser 14 *, and Glu 21 * are shown as<lb/> sticks. The backbone carbonyl of Thr 11 * could form a weak hydrogen bond (3.2 Å) to the backbone amide of<lb/> Gln 112 , the backbone amide of Thr 13 * could form a hydrogen bond (2.9 Å) to the backbone carbonyl of Gln 112 ,<lb/> and the backbone amide of Ser 14 * may form a hydrogen bond (3 Å) to the side chain of Asp 114 . The side chain<lb/> of Glu 21 * forms a hydrogen bond to the backbone amide of Phe 80 (2.6 Å).<lb/></figure>

			<p>chimeric PACAP/GLP-1 peptides <ref type="biblio">(45)</ref>. Substituting five resi-<lb/>dues from the N-terminus of GLP-1 with those of PACAP (three<lb/> nonconserved, Fig. <ref type="figure">1B</ref>) had no effect on either the affinity or<lb/> potency for GLP-1R. Thus, on the basis of both sequence<lb/> homology and structure-activity, GLP-1 would be expected to<lb/> adopt a similar conformation upon binding to the GLP-1R TM<lb/> domain.<lb/></p>

			<head>Conclusion-</head>

			<p>The crystal structure presented here shows<lb/> the molecular details of GLP-1 binding to the GLP-1R ECD,<lb/> an essential step in the two-domain binding mechanism of<lb/> GLP-1R and class B GPCRs in general. Collectively, results<lb/> from structural characterization of GLP-1 in solution, struc-<lb/>ture-activity analyses of GLP-1 analogues, and the crystal struc-<lb/>ture of GLP-1 bound to the GLP-1R ECD presented here sug-<lb/>gest that GLP-1 is a continuous ␣-helix from Thr 13 * to Val 33 *<lb/> when bound to the full-length GLP-1R. This is important infor-<lb/>mation for the design of peptide therapeutics targeting GLP-<lb/>1R. GLP-1 and exendin-4 share the same binding site of the<lb/> GLP-1R ECD, but the ligand-specific effects on the ECD struc-<lb/>ture and the ligand-specific effects of receptor mutagenesis<lb/> support the existence of differences in the binding modes of<lb/> GLP-1 and exendin-4 to the full-length GLP-1R. The nature of<lb/> these differences as well as the active conformation of peptide<lb/> agonists (kinked or not) and a better understanding of the two-<lb/>domain binding mechanism await structural characterization<lb/> of the full-length GLP-1R.</p>

	</text>
</tei>
