<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>INTRODUCTION<lb/></head>

			<p>Despite renal replacement treatment, cardiovascular disease<lb/> is the prime cause of morbidity and mortality among end-<lb/>stage renal disease patients, leading to more than 50% of the<lb/> deaths in such patients <ref type="biblio">(1)</ref>. Structural and functional changes<lb/> such as increased intima-media thickness and decreased arte-<lb/>rial compliance are associated with a significant increase in<lb/> morbidity and mortality of cardiovascular disease <ref type="biblio">(2)</ref>. A carotid<lb/> intima-media thickness of &gt;0.09 cm and/or the presence of<lb/> discrete plaques are markers of generalized atherosclerosis and<lb/> have a positive graded association with cardiovascular risk<lb/> factors <ref type="biblio">(3)</ref>. Arterial compliance, an important vessel wall prop-<lb/>erty, reflects the buffering capacity of a vessel. A low arterial<lb/> compliance caused by arterial stiffening widens pulse pressure<lb/> amplitude by increasing systolic blood pressure and decreas-<lb/>ing diastolic blood pressure. Increased systolic blood pressure<lb/> induces left ventricular hypertrophy, whereas decreased dias-<lb/>tolic blood pressure impairs coronary blood flow. Wide pulse<lb/> pressure may be a major predictor of cardiac risk, especially<lb/> coronary mortality <ref type="biblio">(4-6)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Recent prospective studies have demonstrated that arterial<lb/> stiffness and early wave reflections are independent predictors<lb/> of all-cause and cardiovascular mortality in end-stage renal<lb/> disease patients and in the general population <ref type="biblio">(7-11)</ref>. Arterial<lb/> wall properties in end-stage renal disease patients may be asso-<lb/>ciated with many factors including non-specific factors such<lb/> as age, gender, smoking, blood pressure and diabetes, as well<lb/> as alterations more specific to end-stage renal disease, such as<lb/> fluid overload, hyperphosphatemia, parathyroid hormone activ-<lb/>ity, microinflammation and alterations in blood lipids <ref type="biblio">(12)</ref>.<lb/> The aim of the present study was to identify the main fac-<lb/>tor affecting wall properties of the elastic common carotid<lb/> artery in continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis patients.<lb/></p>

			<head>MATERIALS AND METHODS<lb/> </head>

			<head>Study subjects<lb/></head>

			<p>We enrolled 20 continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis<lb/> patients and 20 healthy, normotensive, age-and sex-matched<lb/> controls. Subject characteristics are listed in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. The<lb/> patient group comprised 10 men and 10 women, with a mean<lb/> age of 53.9±12.4 yr and a mean time undergoing continu-<lb/>ous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis of 16 months (range: 4-120<lb/> months).<lb/> </p>

			<p>Individuals with the following medical conditions were ex-<lb/>cluded; cardiac failure (New York Heart Association [NYHA]<lb/> class II and higher), unstable angina pectoris (NYHA class<lb/> II and higher), peripheral vascular disease, peripheral pitting<lb/> edema and pulmonary edema, above stage 3 hypertension<lb/> (systolic blood pressure &gt;180 mmHg or diastolic blood pres-<lb/>sure &gt;110 mmHg), severe malnutrition (serum albumin &lt;2.5<lb/> gm/dL), established infection and high-sensitivity C-reactive<lb/> protein levels &gt;5 mg/L, intact parathyroid hormone levels<lb/> &gt;200 pg/mL, serum total calcium levels &gt;11 mg/dL, and<lb/> serum phosphate levels &gt;7 mg/dL. In 11 patients the primary<lb/> kidney disease was associated with diabetes mellitus, while<lb/> in 9 patients it was not diabetes-related.<lb/></p>

			<head>Methods<lb/></head>

			<p>We compared arterial wall properties of controls and pati-<lb/>ents. After 15 min of supine rest, the compliance and intima-<lb/>media thickness of the right common carotid artery within<lb/> 1 cm to the bifurcation were measured three times using a<lb/> high-resolution B-mode 7.5-MHz transducer. Patients were<lb/> asked not to smoke, eat or drink for 4 hr before measurements<lb/> were performed, but were allowed to take their regular med-<lb/>ication. 11 of 20 patients were administered antihypertensive<lb/> drugs (calcium channel blocker, ACE inhibitor, beta-blocker,<lb/> alpha-blocker). None of the antihypertensives nor other vasoac-<lb/>tive drugs (calcium containing phosphorus binder, etc.) of the<lb/> patients were changed over 1 month. Blood pressure was mea-<lb/>sured 5 times consecutively in a sitting position using a con-<lb/>ventional sphygmomanometer by the same nurse on each<lb/> occasion. Mean arterial pressure was calculated using the fol-<lb/>lowing formula: (systolic blood pressure+2×diastolic blood<lb/> pressure)/3. Pulse pressure was calculated using the following<lb/> formula: systolic blood pressure-diastolic blood pressure.<lb/></p>

			<p>Intima-media thickness was defined as the distance from<lb/> the leading edge of the lumen-intima interface of the far wall<lb/> to the leading edge of the media-adventitia interface of the<lb/> far wall as validated by Pignoli et al. <ref type="biblio">(13)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Arterial compliance was defined by the arterial volume<lb/> change per unit of pressure. Systolic and end-diastolic arterial<lb/> diameter were measured three times and the compliance of<lb/> the common carotid artery was calculated using the Hayoz<lb/> formula (<ref type="formula">14</ref>):<lb/></p>

			<p>Arterial compliance (mm 2 /kPa)=( D× D)/2 P; where<lb/> D=arterial diameter (mm), D=changes in systolic and dias-<lb/>tolic arterial diameter, and P=pulse pressure.<lb/></p>

			<p>Stroke volume was measured using 2-dimensional echocar-<lb/>diography. Stroke volume=left ventricular outflow tract area<lb/> ×the systolic velocity integral; where left ventricular outflow<lb/> tract area= (D/2) 2 (D=LV diameter).<lb/></p>

			<p>Baseline echocardiography was performed using a Hewlett-<lb/>Packard Sonos 100 device equipped with a 2.25-MHz probe,<lb/> allowing M-mode, 2-dimensional and pulsed Doppler mea-<lb/>surements. Measurements were made according to the recom-<lb/>mendations of the American Society of Echocardiography <ref type="biblio">(15)</ref>.<lb/> Left ventricular mass was calculated according to the Penn<lb/> convection <ref type="biblio">(16)</ref>. Left ventricular hypertrophy was defined as<lb/> a left ventricular mass index &gt;136 g/m 2 in men and &gt;110<lb/> g/m 2 in women.<lb/></p>

			<p>In the patient group, blood hemoglobin levels were deter-<lb/>mined using a Coulter-Genis (Coulter, CA, U.S.A.) machine.<lb/> Blood phosphorus, total calcium and total CO2 levels were<lb/> measured using a Hitachi 747 automatic analyzer, with nor-<lb/>mal values considered 1.9-4.4 mg/dL, 8.2-10.4 mg/dL and<lb/> 22-28 mol/ L, respectively. Intact parathyroid hormone was<lb/> measured using a commercial immunoradiometric assay (Di-<lb/>agnostic products corporation, Los Angeles, CA, U.S.A.), with<lb/> the normal range considered 12-72 pg/mL. Serum albumin<lb/> was measured using a Hitachi 736-740 autoanalyzer (Hitachi<lb/> Ltd, Tokyo, Japan), and high-sensitivity C-reactive protein<lb/> was measured using the N High Sensitivity CRP kit (Dade<lb/> Behring, Marburg, Germany) which has a lower limit of 0.15<lb/> mg/L. Serum total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, HDL-choles-<lb/>terol and triglyceride levels were measured enzymatically using<lb/> a Hitachi 736-740 autoanalyzer. Analysis of the mean of the<lb/> previous three samples over the preceding 3-month period<lb/> was included.<lb/></p>

			<p>To evaluate the total Kt/V urea index (Kt/V) in the patient<lb/> group, the sum of the 24 hr residual and dialytic urea clear-<lb/>ances were divided by the urea distribution volume which<lb/> was calculated using Watson&apos;s normogram. Residual renal<lb/> function was estimated using the mean values of residual urea<lb/> and creatinine clearances.<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Variables<lb/>Control group<lb/> Patient group<lb/> Age (yr)<lb/> 59.1±10.1<lb/> 53.9±12.4<lb/> Men/Women (n)<lb/> 10/10<lb/> 10/10<lb/> DM/non-DM (n)<lb/> 0/20<lb/> 11/9<lb/> CAPD duration (mo)<lb/> 0<lb/> 16 (4-45)<lb/> Total Kt/V urea<lb/> 2.03±0.51<lb/> Residual renal function (mL/min)<lb/> 2.3 (1-5.6)<lb/> Serum albumin level (g/dL)<lb/> 4.4±0.2<lb/> 3.6±0.6*<lb/> h-s CRP (mg/L)<lb/> 0.50 (0.15-1.50) 2.40 (0.20-5.00)*<lb/> Serum calcium level (mg/dL)<lb/> 9.0±1.1<lb/> 8.6±0.8*<lb/> Serum phosphorus level (mg/dL)<lb/> 3.7±1.3<lb/> 5.0±1.9*<lb/> Ca×P product (mg/dL)<lb/> 32.15±1.53<lb/> 42.45±15.67*<lb/> Total cholesterol level (mg/dL)<lb/> 211±60<lb/> 191±39<lb/> LDL-cholesterol level (mg/dL)<lb/> 115±28<lb/> 111±31<lb/> HDL-cholesterol level (mg/dL)<lb/> 53±15<lb/> 44±9<lb/> PTH level (pg/mL)<lb/> 90.71±27.03<lb/> Table 1. Subject characteristics<lb/> Figures represent mean±S.D or median (range), *p&lt;0.05 versus control<lb/> group.<lb/> h-s CRP, high sensitivity C-reactive protein; Ca×P product, calcium×<lb/> phosphorus product; LDL, low density lipoprotein; HDL, high density<lb/> lipoprotein; PTH, parathyroid hormone.<lb/></figure>

			<p>Statistical analysis was performed using Student&apos;s unpaired<lb/> t-tests and Mann-Whitney U tests (SPSS Windows version<lb/> 9.0). Relationships between different parameters were assessed<lb/> using Spearman&apos;s correlation coefficient. Where appropriate,<lb/> stepwise regression analysis was performed to assess the con-<lb/>tribution of various variables to arterial wall properties. Results<lb/> are expressed as mean±SD or median (range). Differences<lb/> were considered significant if the p value was less than 0.05.<lb/></p>

			<head>RESULTS<lb/></head>

			<p>We found that for the control group, the common carotid<lb/> artery compliance was 0.268±0.127 mm 2 /kPa, which was<lb/> higher than that observed in the patient group, 0.163±0.082<lb/> mm 2 /kPa (p=0.018) (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). The intima-media thickness<lb/> of the common carotid artery was lower in the control group<lb/> (0.06±0.03 cm) than in the patient group (0.08±0.02 cm;<lb/> p=0.025). The control group left ventricular mass index (111.0<lb/> ±24.7 gm/m 2 ) was lower than that of the patient group<lb/> (174.0±54.8 gm/m 2 ; p=0.01) (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). In the control group,<lb/> systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, mean arterial<lb/> pressure and pulse pressure were 126±16 mmHg, 78±9<lb/> mmHg, 94±11 mmHg and 48±9 mmHg respectively,<lb/> with each being lower than the corresponding pressure in the<lb/> patient group; 152±18 mmHg, 88±10 mmHg, 109±12<lb/> mmHg and 63±13 mmHg, respectively (p=0.008, p=0.028,<lb/> p=0.031, p=0.015, respectively) (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>). Stroke volumes<lb/> were similar in each group; 66.32±26.85 mL/m 2 in the con-<lb/>trol group and 66.10±25.75 mL/m 2 in the patient group (p=<lb/> 0.45). Similarly, ejection fractions were similar for each group;<lb/> 60.32±6.35% in the control group and 61.10±20.75%<lb/> in the patient group (p=0.65) (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>In the patient group, common carotid artery compliance<lb/> was positively correlated with serum albumin concentration<lb/> (r=0.443; p=0.018) (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>), and common carotid artery inti-<lb/>ma-media thickness was negatively correlated with serum<lb/> albumin concentration (r=-0.418; p=0.025) (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<p>Stepwise regression analysis showed that the serum albu-<lb/>min concentration ( =0.467, p=0.044) was independently<lb/> associated with common carotid artery compliance (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>).<lb/></p>

			<figure type="table">Control group<lb/> Patient group<lb/> CCA-AC (mm 2 /kPa)<lb/> 0.268±0.127<lb/> 0.163±0.082*<lb/> CCA-IMT (cm)<lb/> 0.06±0.03<lb/> 0.08±0.02*<lb/> LVM/BSA (g/m 2 )<lb/> 111.0±24.7<lb/> 174.0±54.8*<lb/> SBP (mmHg)<lb/> 126±16<lb/> 152±18*<lb/> DBP (mmHg)<lb/> 78±9<lb/> 8 8 ±10*<lb/> MAP (mmHg)<lb/> 94±11<lb/> 109±12*<lb/> PP (mmHg)<lb/> 48±9<lb/> 6 3 ±13*<lb/> SV (mL/m 2 )<lb/> 66.32±26.85<lb/> 66.10±25.75<lb/> EF (%)<lb/> 60.32±6.35<lb/> 61.10±20.75<lb/> Table 2. Comparison of hemodynamic parameters in control and<lb/> patient groups<lb/> Figures represent mean±S.D. *p&lt;0.05 versus control group.<lb/> CCA-AC, common carotid artery-arterial compliance; CCA-IMT, common<lb/> carotid artery-intima media thickness; LVM/BSA, left ventricular mass/body<lb/> surface area; SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure;<lb/> MAP, mean arterial pressure; PP, pulse pressure; SV, stroke volume; EF,<lb/> ejection fraction.<lb/> </figure>

			<figure type="table">Common carotid artery compliance<lb/> Std. Error<lb/> p<lb/> Albumin<lb/> 0.467<lb/> 0.031<lb/> 0.044*<lb/> Table 3. Stepwise regression analysis with common carotid artery<lb/> compliance as a dependent variable<lb/> R2=0.218, F=4.734.<lb/> Selected variables: age, sex, presence of diabetes mellitus, serum albu-<lb/>min concentration, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein level, serum total cal-<lb/>cium and phosphorus concentrations, calcium×phosphorus product,<lb/> Total/HDL cholesterol, LDL/HDL cholesterol, parathyroid hormone level,<lb/> common carotid artery intima-media thickness, left ventricular mass index,<lb/> systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, mean arterial pressure,<lb/> pulse pressure and body mass index.<lb/></figure>

			<figure>CCA-AC (mm 2<lb/> /kPa)<lb/> 0.4<lb/> 0.3<lb/> 0.2<lb/> 0.1<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 2.5<lb/> 3.0<lb/> 3.5<lb/> 4.0<lb/> 4.5<lb/> 5.0<lb/> Serum albumin concentration (g/dL)<lb/> Fig. 1. Correlation between common carotid artery compliance and<lb/> serum albumin concentration.<lb/> CCA-AC, common carotid artery compliance.<lb/></figure> 

			<figure>r=0.443<lb/> p=0.018<lb/> CCA-IMT (cm)<lb/> 0.2<lb/> 0.1<lb/> 0.0<lb/> 2.5<lb/> 3.0<lb/> 3.5<lb/> 4.0<lb/> 4.5<lb/> 5.0<lb/> Serum albumin concentration (g/dL)<lb/> Fig. 2. Correlation between common carotid artery intima-media<lb/> thickness and serum albumin concentration.<lb/> CCA-IMT, common carotid artery intima-media thickness.<lb/> r=-0.418<lb/> p=0.025<lb/></figure>

			<head>DISCUSSION<lb/></head>

			<p>The present study showed that common carotid artery com-<lb/>pliance and intima-media thickness differed between normal<lb/> individuals and continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis<lb/> patients. In addition, the study revealed that in the patient<lb/> group, the compliance and the intima-media thickness were<lb/> related to the serum albumin level.<lb/></p>

			<p>Our finding that arterial wall compliance was lower in the<lb/> patient group compared to controls is in agreement with the<lb/> findings of others <ref type="biblio">(8, 12, 17)</ref>, and there are probably multi-<lb/>ple factors which contribute to this reduced compliance in<lb/> renal patients <ref type="biblio">(12)</ref>. In the present study, we found that serum<lb/> albumin concentration was an independent factor in reduced<lb/> compliance of the common carotid artery. This finding is con-<lb/>sistent with recent data suggesting hypoalbuminemia may<lb/> represent a state of accelerated atherosclerosis in dialysis pati-<lb/>ents <ref type="biblio">(18)</ref>. It appears longitudinal studies are needed to con-<lb/>firm the nature of the association between albumin levels and<lb/> atherosclerosis, and to elucidate the role of inflammation in<lb/> that association <ref type="biblio">(18)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>Traditionally, low albumin levels were believed to be the<lb/> result of inflammation, and there is evidence that atheroscle-<lb/>rosis is an inflammatory process <ref type="biblio">(19, 20)</ref>. In the dialysis pop-<lb/>ulation, there is increasing evidence of a link between inflam-<lb/>mation, signified by elevated C-reactive protein or interleu-<lb/>kin-6 levels, and cardiovascular mortality <ref type="biblio">(21, 22)</ref>. Therefore,<lb/> it is possible that poor nutrition, serum albumin levels and<lb/> atherosclerosis could be interlinked by inflammation. How-<lb/>ever, in contrast, a recent study <ref type="biblio">(23)</ref> showed that protein mal-<lb/>nutrition (diagnosed based upon total body nitrogen levels)<lb/> and hypoalbuminemia were independently predictive of mor-<lb/>tality, whereas only hypoalbuminemia was predictive of vas-<lb/>cular morbidity. That study suggested hypoalbuminemia<lb/> itself was pathogenically associated with vascular disease, but<lb/> dissociated this effect from protein malnutrition <ref type="biblio">(23)</ref>. In the<lb/> present study, we excluded patients with severe malnutrition<lb/> and those with a level of established infection above the upper<lb/> level of that observed in normal controls. Our data revealed<lb/> no relationship between serum high sensitivity C-reactive<lb/> protein levels and common carotid artery compliance in the<lb/> patient group. This finding suggests that the serum albumin<lb/> level itself is related to changes in compliance and intima-<lb/>media thickness in the elastic common carotid artery.<lb/></p>

			<p>Hypoalbuminemia may result in a hypercoagulable state<lb/> <ref type="biblio">(24)</ref> and may deplete L-arginine stores with a subsequent<lb/> reduction in nitric oxide synthesis <ref type="biblio">(24)</ref>. Nitric oxide causes<lb/> equipotent relaxation of arterial smooth muscle <ref type="biblio">(25)</ref> and in-<lb/>hibits platelet aggregation <ref type="biblio">(26)</ref>. In our stepwise regression<lb/> analysis, serum albumin levels were correlated with common<lb/> carotid artery compliance independent of age, blood pressure,<lb/> common carotid artery intima-media thickness, calcium and<lb/> phosphorus levels, lipid profile and high-sensitivity C-reac-<lb/>tive protein levels. Furthermore, the common carotid artery<lb/> intima-media thickness was found to be inversely proportional<lb/> to serum albumin levels. These results suggest that in the<lb/> patient group, the wall properties of the common carotid artery<lb/> are linked to serum albumin concentration.<lb/></p>

			<p>In the present study, although blood pressure in the patient<lb/> group was higher than in controls, there was no relationship<lb/> between blood pressure and compliance or intima-media thick-<lb/>ness of the common carotid artery. This finding that factors<lb/> other than blood pressure per se affect arterial wall compliance<lb/> is consistent with findings of the Tassin population study<lb/> showing that arterial compliance was lower in long-term nor-<lb/>motensive hemodialysis patients <ref type="biblio">(27)</ref>.<lb/></p>

			<p>The design of the present study (cross-sectional) meant that<lb/> it was unable to address whether hypoalbuminemia itself<lb/> reflects vascular events and mortality in the patient group.<lb/> Therefore, to determine the relationship between serum albu-<lb/>min level and vascular events in the patient group, longitu-<lb/>dinal follow-up studies with addition of nutritional markers<lb/> are needed. In addition, future studies will ideally have larger<lb/> and more homogenous subject groups compared to the pre-<lb/>sent study. While the present study did not examine patient<lb/> volume status using reliable and objective methods, contin-<lb/>uous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis patients have relatively<lb/> stable volume status compared to hemodialysis patients, and<lb/> we excluded patients with peripheral pitting edema and pul-<lb/>monary edema. Therefore, we believe the results obtained in<lb/> this study were not influenced by patient volume status.<lb/></p>

			<p>In conclusion, the present study showed that common ca-<lb/>rotid artery wall properties were independently associated with<lb/> serum albumin levels, suggesting that independent of other<lb/> factors, hypoalbuminemia can cause deleterious effects on arte-<lb/>rial wall properties in continuous ambulatory peritoneal dial-<lb/>ysis patients.</p>


	</text>
</tei>
