<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1128071-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1128071" kind="B1" date="20051012"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23215391" ucid="EP-1128071-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1128071</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20051012</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01102875-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01102875</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010214</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000050278-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000050278</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000225</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000130953-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000130953</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000428</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20050426</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F04D  29/40        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F04D  29/54        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F04D  29/66        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F04D  29/66        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">F04D29/54C3</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">F04D29/66C4C</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Lüfterzarge mit integriertem Resonator</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Resonator-integrated fan shroud</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Buse de ventilateur avec résonateur intégré</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>INOUE MTP KK</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>INOAC CORPORATION</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAKAMURA KENTARO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAKAMURA, KENTARO</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Nakamura, Kentaro, Inoac Corporation</last-name><address><street>Sakurai Works, 8-1, Higashichosen, Fujii-cho</street><city>Anjo-shi, Aichi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>INOAC CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>13-4, Meiekiminami 2 chome, Nakamura-ku Nagoya-shi</street><city>Aichi 450-0003</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name><address><street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street><city>81925 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>A hollow vessel 1 which is partitioned into one or a plurality of hollow chambers S by blow molding is used as a resonator 2, and the hollow vessel 1 is arranged to form a fan shroud body 3, and that a drain hole 13 is formed in a bottom portion and/or a lower side portion of the hollow vessel 1, and a communicating pipe 4 fitted to the hollow vessel 1 and an air intake duct 5 connected to the communicating pipe 4 are formed integrally with the hollow vessel 1. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">A hollow vessel 1 which is partitioned into one or
a plurality of hollow chambers S by blow molding is used as
a resonator 2, and the hollow vessel 1 is arranged to form
a fan shroud body 3, and that a drain hole 13 is formed in
a bottom portion and/or a lower side portion of the hollow
vessel 1, and a communicating pipe 4 fitted to the hollow vessel
1 and an air intake duct 5 connected to the communicating pipe
4 are formed integrally with the hollow vessel 1.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1128415-A2-00000001" he="118" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a fan shroud for
installation in an engine compartment of a vehicle.</p><p num="0002"><ref type="patent">EP-A-0 995 895</ref> (a reference under Art. 54(3) EPC)
describes a fan shroud and air intake arrangement for a
vehicle.</p><p num="0003"><ref type="patent">US-A-5,649,587</ref> describes another fan shroud and air
intake for a vehicle.</p><p num="0004">Recently, a demand for reducing noise of an automobile
to a low level has heightened year by year, and has become
particularly stringent concerning an intake system of an engine
77 (Figs. 14 to 17). A resonator 80, a side branch, or the
like has hitherto been used as a means for reducing the noise
from the intake system. Recently, however, in conjunction
with a reduction in the number of component parts and a tendency
toward a smaller space, the capacity of a muffler such as the
resonator 80 has tended to become small or to be disused.
Further, development of a substitute item such as a tuning
hole for a high-frequency band (100 Hz or higher) is under
way. In Figs. 14 to 17, reference numeral 70 denotes a fan;
reference numerals 71 and 72 denote air intake ducts; reference
numeral 73 denotes an air cleaner; reference numeral 74 denotes
an air intake duct (air cleaner hose); reference numeral 75 
denotes an intake connector; reference numeral 76 denotes
an intake manifold; reference numeral 78 denotes a radiator;
and reference numeral 79 denotes a fan shroud.</p><p num="0005">For example, <ref type="patent">US-A-5,649,587</ref> discloses automotive
radiator fan shrouds and, more particularly such shrouds
which are blow molded to include hollow compartments which
serve as reservoirs for fluids, such as coolant fluid, and/or
window and headlamp washer fluids, including air and other
gasses.</p><p num="0006">However, the situation is such that if an attempt is
made to reduce the noise in the low-frequency band (100 Hz
or lower), the large-capacity resonator must be still used.
The reason for this is that the increase in the capacity lowers
the frequency to be attenuated, and the amount of attenuation
can be made large.</p><p num="0007">Due to its large capacity, the low-frequency resonator
80 could be conventionally installed in a very limited specific
position inside the engine compartment. In addition, since
there is a limitation and the like in the installation of the
equipment, there has been a problem in that the intake passages
71, 72, and 74 become long. Further, with the conventional
resonator 80 made by injection molding or the like, only two
hollow chambers (chambers having two kinds of resonance
frequencies) at most could be formed. Additionally, since
the resonator 80 is fabricated separately, the cost tended 
to be high.</p><p num="0008">According to a first aspect of the invention, there
is provided a resonator-integrated fan shroud comprising
a fan shroud body containing a hollow chamber arranged to
function as a resonator, and a drain hole formed in a
bottom portion and/or a lower side portion of the hollow
chamber.</p><p num="0009">According to a first variant of the invention, the
resonator-integrated fan shroud may further comprise a
plurality of hollow chambers.</p><p num="0010">According to a second variant of the invention, a
hollow vessel forms the fan shroud body.</p><p num="0011">According to a third variant of the invention, the
hollow vessel may be partitioned into a plurality of
hollow chambers.</p><p num="0012">According to a fourth variant of the invention, the
resonator-integrated fan shroud further comprises a cover
member, which is formed in a vessel shape and has an
opening in one side, and which is joined to and
integrated with the fan shroud body to cover the opening
of the cover member, whereby the hollow chamber is formed
by the cover member and the fan shroud body.</p><p num="0013">According to a fifth variant of the invention, a
communicating pipe may be connected to an air intake
duct, wherein the communicating pipe is formed integrally
with the hollow chamber.</p><p num="0014">For a better understanding of the invention and to
show how the same may be carried into effect, reference 
will now be made, by way of example, to the accompanying
drawings, in which:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a perspective view of a first embodiment
of a resonator-integrated fan shroud in accordance with the
invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a perspective view of the resonator-integrated
fan shroud in accordance with a variation of the first embodiment,
in which two circular holes are provided ;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a perspective view of the resonator-integrated
fan shroud in accordance with another variation of the first
embodiment ;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a perspective view of the resonator-integrated
fan shroud in accordance with a still another variation of
the first embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a perspective view of the resonator-integrated
fan shroud in accordance with a still another variation of
the first embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 6 is a perspective view of a second embodiment
of a resonator-integrated fan shroud with an air intake duct
in accordance with the invention;</li><li>Fig. 7 is a perspective view of the resonator-integrated
fan shroud with an air intake duct in accordance with a variation
of the second embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 8 is a perspective view of the resonator-integrated
fan shroud with an air intake duct in accordance with another
variation of the second embodiment; </li><li>Fig. 9 is a perspective view of the resonator-integrated
fan shroud with an air intake duct in accordance with a still
another variation of the second embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 10 is an exploded perspective view of a third
embodiment of a resonator-integrated fan shroud in accordance
with the invention;</li><li>Fig. 11 is a perspective view in which the
resonator-integrated fan shroud shown in Fig. 10 is completed;</li><li>Fig. 12A is a cross-sectional view prior to joining
a cover member to a fan shroud body.</li><li>Fig. 12B is a cross-sectional view of a state in which
the cover member is joined to the fan shroud body.</li><li>Fig. 13 is a perspective viewof the resonator-integrated
fan shroud in accordance with a variation of the third embodiment.</li><li>Fig. 14 is an exploded perspective view explaining
the conventional art;</li><li>Fig. 15 is a plan view explaining Fig. 14;</li><li>Fig. 16 is a perspective view explaining the conventional
art ; and</li><li>Fig. 17 is a plan view explaining Fig. 16.</li></sl></p><p num="0015">The following describes a resonator-integrated fan
shroud with an air intake duct, in which a hollow vessel which
is partitioned into one or a plurality of hollow chambers by
blow molding is used as a resonator, and the hollow vessel is
arranged to form a fan shroud body, a drain hole
is formed in a bottom portion of the hollow vessel, and a
communicating pipe fitted to the hollow vessel and an air intake
duct connected to the communicating pipe are formed integrally
with the hollow vessel. </p><p num="0016">If the hollow vessel is used as the resonator, and
the hollow vessel is arranged to form the fan shroud body,
practically no space is required for installing the resonator
in addition to the fan shroud.</p><p num="0017">If the communicating pipe and the air intake duct are
integrally formed by blow molding or the like, the number of
component parts is reduced, leading to a reduction in the cost.</p><p num="0018">A drain hole makes it possible to easily
drain water and the like which entered the air intake duct
and condensed.</p><p num="0019">The following also describes a resonator-integrated fan shroud
comprising a fan shroud body and a cover member formed in the
shape of a vessel and having one side formed as an opening,
wherein a hollow box whose interior is hollow is formed as
the cover member is joined to and integrated with the fan shroud
body in a state in which the opening of the cover member is
oriented toward a wall surface of the fan shroud body, and
the hollow box is used as a resonator.</p><p num="0020">The resonator-integrated fan shroud may have a
communicating pipe to be connected to an air intake duct
formed integrally with the hollow vessel.</p><p num="0021">If the hollow box formed as the cover member is
joined to and integrated with the fan
shroud body in a state in which the opening of the cover member
is oriented toward the wall surface of the fan shroud body,
and this hollow box is used as a resonator, practically no
space is required for installing the resonator in addition
to the fan shroud. </p><p num="0022">If the communicating pipe is integrally formed, the
number of component parts is reduced, leading to a reduction
in the cost.</p><heading><u style="single">First Embodiment</u></heading><p num="0023">Figs. 1 to 5 are perspective views illustrating
resonator-integrated fan shrouds according to a first embodiment
of the present invention, and variants thereof.</p><p num="0024">This resonator-integrated fan shroud is a hollow vessel
1 fabricated by blow molding, the fan shroud which is
conventionally plate-shaped is formed in the shape of a hollow
box, and this hollow vessel 1 is used as a resonator 2.</p><p num="0025">First, a description will be given of the
resonator-integrated fan shroud of Fig. 1 according to the
present invention. A fan shroud body 3 concerning the fan
shroud is fabricated by blow molding, and the hollow vessel 
1 having a hollow interior is formed at this time. A hollow
chamber S is formed by resin-made plate portions (a front plate
portion 1a, a rear plate portion 1b, an upper plate portion
1c, a bottom plate portion 1d, left and right side plate portions
1e and 1f, and a cylindrical plate portion 1g in Fig. 1) with
a predetermined thickness t (see Fig. 9), which are obtained
by blow molding by blowing air in a state in which a parison
is clamped in a mold. The hollow chamber S having a space
in its interior is formed by making the depth D (D » t) of the
fan shroud body 3 larger than the plate thickness of the
conventional plate-shaped fan shroud. Although the hollow
vessel 1 may be formed by ordinary blow molding, the hollow
vessel 1 is formed by deep-drawing blow molding in a case where
the depth D is large. As for the fan shroud body 3, even if
the depth D is made somewhat large, no problem is generally
presented, and in many cases there is a spacewise leeway inside
a narrow engine compartment. This hollow chamber S is used
as a resonance box of the resonator 2.</p><p num="0026">A drain hole 13 is appropriately formed in the bottom
plate portion 1d, as necessary. The drain hole 13 can be formed
by post-processing, or may be also formed as a blow hole during
molding. By providing the drain hole 13, water which entered
the interior of the resonator 2, i.e., the hollow vessel 1,
through an air intake duct 5 (Fig. 6) and condensed water
can be smoothly drained outside the resonator. </p><p num="0027">Meanwhile, the hollow vessel 1 has a shape in which
the outer shape is cubic and a large circular hole O is formed
in the center, as shown. By making use of this circular hole
O, a cooling fan of a radiator can be attached to the hollow
vessel 1, and the hollow vessel 1 makes up the fan shroud body
3. Namely, the hollow vessel 1 is adapted to be used jointly
as a protector which is the fan shroud installed around the
cooling fan of the radiator. The shroud body 3 is appropriately
provided with screw holes B for attaching this fan shroud to
an unillustrated mating member, a fan attaching guide hole
P, ribs R for improving the efficiency of the fan, guides,
and the like (see Fig. 14).</p><p num="0028">In the fan shroud body 3 shown in Fig. 1, a hollow
cylindrical communicating pipe 4 is attached to a position
close to an upper end of the side plate portion le by one-piece
molding during blow molding. The communicating pipe 4 in this
case has a shape in which it is bent in an L-shape. To obtain
necessary performance and the like, the communicating pipe
4 can be molded as a separate piece, and can be assembled in
post-processing. Reference numeral 12 denotes a hole for a
communicating hole formed in the side plate portion le
corresponding to a proximal end portion of the communicating
pipe 4. Reference characters PL denote a parting line in blow
molding.</p><p num="0029">The resonator-integrated fan shroud may be formed in 
a shape such as the one shown in Fig. 2. Fig. 2 is a perspective
view of the resonator-integrated fan shroud according to one
variation of the first embodiment in which the
resonator-integrated fan shroud shown in Fig. 1 is modified.
This resonator-integrated fan shroud is provided with two
large circular holes O in which fans for cooling the radiator
are accommodated.</p><p num="0030">When the fan shroud body 3 concerning the fan shroud
is fabricated by blow molding, the plate portions (the front
plate portion 1a, the rear plate portion 1b, the upper plate
portion 1c, the bottom plate portion 1d, the left and right
side plate portions 1e and 1f, and the cylindrical plate portions
1g and 1h) with the predetermined thickness t (see Fig. 9)
are formed from the parison so as to form the hollow vessel
1. Further, during the blow molding of the hollow vessel 1
(it is, of course, possible to employ a method using vibrational
welding, thermal fusion, or the like in post-processing), upper
and lower central portions of the parisons of the hollow
cylindrical plate portions 1g and 1h are pushed and pressed
while forming partition walls 11, and are fused to parison
portions opposing thereto. Crushed portions 18 which have
been fused and joined are located at two portions in upper
and lower positions (four portions in total) of each of the
two hollow cylindrical plate portions 1g and 1h. The fan shroud
body 3 is divided into three partitioned hollow chambers S<sub>1</sub>, 
S<sub>2</sub>, and S<sub>3</sub> by the formation of the partition walls 11 and the
crushed portions 18. It should be noted that, in Fig. 2
(similarly in Figs. 6 and 8), the crushed portions 18 are
illustrated by hatching to facilitate an understanding.</p><p num="0031">The communicating pipes 4 are respectively attached
to positions on the upper plate portion 1c corresponding to
the three hollow chambers S<sub>1</sub>, S<sub>2</sub>, and S<sub>3</sub> by one-piece molding
with the fan shroud body 3. The holes 12 are necessarily formed
at the joints between the hollow chambers S<sub>1</sub>, S<sub>2</sub>, and S<sub>3</sub> and
the communicating pipes 4 by blow molding, allowing the hollow
chambers S and the communicating pipes 4 to communicate with
each other. The hollow chambers S in Fig. 2 respectively serve
as resonance boxes for the resonator 2. If the capacities
of the three hollow chambers S<sub>1</sub>, S<sub>2</sub>, and S<sub>3</sub> are made different,
the hollow vessel 1 (resonator 2) having three resonance
frequencies can be formed.</p><p num="0032">Meanwhile, the shape of the hollow vessel 1 is such
as to form the fan shroud body 3 which makes it possible to
incorporate two fans, thereby forming the resonator-integrated
fan shroud.</p><p num="0033">In addition, the resonator-integrated fan shroud may
be also formed as the hollow vessel 1 having a hollow interior,
as shown in Fig. 3. Fig. 3 is a perspective view of the
resonator-integrated fan shroud according to another variation
of the first embodiment in which the resonator-integrated fan 
shroud shown in Fig. 1 is modified.</p><p num="0034">Necessary equipment and the like are installed around
the fan shroud, and there are cases where there is a portion
19 where the depth D of the fan shroud body 3 cannot be made
large. This resonator-integrated fan shroud is designed to
cope with such a case, and the depth E is made small where
the necessary equipment and the like are present, while the
depth of the remaining portion is set as the depth D (D &gt; E).
Further, in a case where it is impossible to obtain a resonator
capacity commensurate with the frequency to be attenuated,
the hollow vessel 1 is jutted out in a direction in which space
can be secured, e.g., in a lateral direction, so as to secure
a necessary capacity 14, thereby reducing the noise. If an
empty space is available around the fan shroud, the shape of
the hollow vessel 1 is deformed to make effective use of the
empty space. The communicating pipe 4 is formed by a short
pipe, and is provided on the right side plate portion 1f in
Fig. 3. The other arrangements are similar to those of the
resonator-integrated fan shroud shown in Fig. 1, and a
description thereof will be omitted. The same reference
numerals as those in Fig. 1 denote identical portions or
corresponding portions.</p><p num="0035">In addition, the resonator-integrated fan shroud may
be formed in a shape such as the one shown in Fig. 3. Fig.
4 is a perspective view of the resonator-integrated fan shroud 
in which an upper half portion of the fan shroud is formed
as the hollow vessel 1 so as to be used jointly as the resonator
2. A lower half 6 of the fan shroud is formed as a separate
piece, the hollow vessel 1 formed by blow molding is used as
the resonator 2, and the hollow vessel 1 is made to carry the
shroud body 3 of the upper half of the fan shroud.</p><p num="0036">Fig. 5 shows a resonator-integrated fan shroud in which
the resonator-integrated fan shroud shown in Fig. 4 is further
developed, and during the blow molding of the hollow vessel
1, both upper corner ends of parison are crushed to integrally
form attaching portions 15. Reference numeral 151 denotes
a hole for attaching the fan shroud to a mating member. The
other arrangements of the resonator-integrated fan shroud in
Figs. 4 and 5 are similar to those of the resonator-integrated
fan shroud shown in Fig. 1, and a description thereof will
be omitted. The same reference numerals as those in Fig. 1
denote identical portions or corresponding portions.</p><heading><u style="single">Second embodiment</u></heading><p num="0037">Figs. 6 to 9 are perspective views illustrating
resonator-integrated fan shrouds each with an air intake duct
according to a second embodiment of the invention, and
variants thereof.</p><p num="0038">This resonator-integrated fan shroud with an air intake
duct is one in which the air intake duct 5 is further integrated
with the resonator-integrated fan shroud, such as the one shown 
in one of Figs. 1 to 5, by blow molding.</p><p num="0039">For example, the resonator-integrated fan shroud with
an air intake duct may be formed as shown in Fig. 6. In Fig.
6, the hollow vessel 1 which is partitioned and formed into
two hollow chambers S by blow molding is made to function as
the resonator 2, and the hollow vessel 1 is made to carry the
shroud body 3. Then, the communicating pipe 4 is attached
to the hollow vessel 1, and the air intake duct 5 is connected
to the communicating pipe 4 by one-piece molding.</p><p num="0040">The hollow vessel 1 has a lower center cut out to form
a passage 17 for the circular hole O. During the blow molding
of the hollow vessel 1, an upper central portion of the parison
of the hollow cylindrical plate portion 1g is pushed while
forming the partition wall 11, and is fused to a parison portion
opposing thereto, thereby forming the crushed portion 18 at
the same time. The fan shroud body 3 is divided into two
partitioned hollow chambers S<sub>1</sub> and S<sub>2</sub> by the formation of the
partition wall 11 and the crushed portion 18. The communicating
pipes 4 communicating with the respective hollow chambers S
are provided on the upper plate portion 1c by one-piece molding,
and the other end portions of the communicating pipes 4 are
set in a state of being joined to the air intake duct 5. The
air intake duct 5 shown in Fig. 6 is arranged parallel to the
upper plate portion 1c, and its right end is formed as an intake
port 51, while its left end is formed as an air-cleaner-side 
connecting port 52. The rectilinear air intake duct 5 having
an air passage 55 formed therein is made to communicate with
the hollow vessel 1 through each communicating pipe 4.</p><p num="0041">As shown in Fig. 7, in the resonator-integrated fan
shroud with an air intake duct, the air intake duct 5 may be
also formed integrally with the communicating pipe 4 of the
resonator-integrated fan shroud shown in Fig. 1. The
communicating pipe 4 shown in Fig. 7 is a straight short pipe
different from the one shown in Fig. 1, but the other portion
s (those of the resonator-integrated fan shroud) are similar
to those shown in Fig. 1, so that a description thereof will
be omitted. The air intake duct 5 with the air passage 55
formed therein has a form in which it extends along the left
side plate portion le shown in Fig. 7, and its upper end is
formed as the intake port 51, while its lower end is formed
as the air-cleaner-side connecting port 52.</p><p num="0042">In addition, the resonator-integrated fan shroud with
an air intake duct may be formed as shown in Fig. 8. This
resonator-integrated fan shroud with an air intake duct is
formed as the hollow vessel 1 having the shape of a box whose
lower side is cut away in an inverse U-shape, and four
communicating pipes 4 are formed integrally at predetermined
intervals on the upper plate portion 1c and the left side plate
portion le shown in Fig. 8. Further, the air intake duct 5
which extends along the upper plate portion 1c and the left 
side plate portion le shown in Fig. 8 is formed integrally
with the hollow vessel 1 and the communicating pipes 4. This
resonator-integrated fan shroud with an air intake duct is
formed by blow molding as the resonator 2 (shroud body 3) having
a single hollow chamber S as shown by the solid lines in Fig.
8. Subsequently, thermal fusion tools or the like are pressed
in the directions of unfilled arrows in the drawing in
post-processing so as to form the crushed portions 18 in the
same way as in Fig. 1, thereby partitioning the inner chamber
into the three chambers S<sub>1</sub>, S<sub>2</sub>, and S<sub>3</sub>. One communicating pipe
4 is made to communicate with each of the hollow chambers S<sub>1</sub>
and S<sub>3</sub>, and two communicating pipes 4 are made to communicate
with the hollow chamber S<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0043">In addition, the resonator-integrated fan shroud with
an air intake duct may be formed as shown in Fig. 9. In this
resonator-integrated fan shroud with an air intake duct, the
air intake duct 5 is attached by one-piece molding to a modified
article of the resonator-integrated fan shroud shown in Fig.
4. The upper half of the hollow vessel 1 making up the shroud
body 3 is fabricated by blow molding, but at that tie the upper
half of the hollow vessel 1 is further split into two parts
of left and right sides. Reference character K denotes a split
interval between the left and right hollow vessels 1.</p><p num="0044">The hollow vessel 1 having a hollow interior S is
fabricated by plate portions with the predetermined thickness 
t corresponding to the thickness of a parison. If the size
of the two hollow vessels 1 is varied, it is possible to obtain
the resonator 2 capable of attenuating different frequencies.
Further, the communicating pipe 4 is formed integrally on
the upper plate portion 1c with respect to the left and right
hollow vessels 1, and the other end of the communicating pipe
4 is integrally joined to the air intake duct 5. The air intake
duct 5 is disposed in parallel to the upper plate portion 1c.
Since the other arrangements are substantially similar to
those of Fig. 4, a description thereof will be omitted.</p><p num="0045">With the resonator-integrated fan shroud and the
resonator-integrated fan shroud with an air intake duct thus
constructed, the fan shroud body 3 which is conventionally
formed in a plate shape is formed as the hollow vessel 1, and
is jointly used as the resonator 2 for the air intake duct
5, and this arrangement is extremely effective in view of the
present situation where it is difficult to secure the space
for the resonator 2 in the engine compartment for which stepped-up
efforts are being made for making the space compact. The
resonator 2 having a large capacity can be obtained in the
limited space, and the silencing effect becomes large. The
resonator-integrated fan shroud and the resonator-integrated
fan shroud with an air intake duct in accordance with the invention
demonstrate power in the reduction of noise in a low-frequency
band which can be solved only by the inevitable use of the 
large-capacity resonator 2.</p><p num="0046">Since the fan shroud body 3 normally becomes large
as compared with the resonator capacity, if the hollow chamber
S is partitioned and formed into two or more chambers, it is
possible to reduce the noise in mutually different low-frequency
bands by varying the capacities of the hollow chambers, and
it is possible to further enhance its effect. It becomes possible
to provide tuning corresponding to various frequency bands
depending on the method of fitting between the hollow vessel
1 and the air intake duct 5 and by such as the adjustment of
the capacity of the hollow vessel 1, i.e., the resonator 2.
Tuning is possible not only for the low-frequency bands but
also for high-frequency bands.</p><p num="0047">Further, since the air intake duct 5 is essentially
disposed close to the fan shroud, the air intake passage is
favorably prevented from becoming long.</p><p num="0048">In addition, since the shroud body 3 is fabricated
by the blow-molded hollow vessel 1, and is jointly used as
the resonator 2, the manufacturing cost becomes lower than
the resonator 2 which is conventionally fabricated as a separate
piece. The communicating pipe 4 and the air intake duct 5
(primary-side air intake) can be integrally molded with the
hollow vessel 1, and, when so done, the manufacturing cost
can be further lowered. The number of components decreases,
and inventory control is facilitated. </p><p num="0049">It should be noted that the invention is not limited
to the ones shown in the foregoing first and second embodiments,
and various modifications are possible within the scope of
the invention depending on the object and applications. The
shapes, sizes, the number, the material, and the like of the
hollow vessel 1, the communicating pipe 4, the air intake duct
5, and the like may be appropriately selected in accordance
with the application. Although in the first and second
embodiments a description has been given of only the hollow
chamber S which is partitioned and formed into one to three
chambers, it goes without saying that the hollow vessel 1
partitioned and formed into a greater number of chambers may
be used as the resonator 2, and the hollow vessel 1 may be
formed as the shroud body 3. Although the hollow vessels 1
shown in Figs. 1 to 9 have shapes in which the fan attaching
hole or holes O are open in a cubic body, their shapes are
not limited to the same. In addition, although the
resonator-integrated fan shroud and the resonator-integrated
fan shroud with an air intake duct in accordance with the
embodiments are fabricated by blow molding, the invention is
not limited to the same, and they may be fabricated by assembling
component parts fabricated by, for instance, injection molding
or the like.</p><heading><u style="single">Third Embodiment</u></heading><p num="0050">Figs. 10 to 13 are diagrams illustrating a
resonator-integrated fan shroud according to a third
embodiment of the invention, and variants thereof. Fig.
10 is an exploded perspective view thereof,
Fig. 11 is an overall perspective view thereof, Fig. 12 is
a cross-sectional view of a state in which a fan shroud body
and a cover member are joined and fixed, and Fig. 13 is a
perspective view of the resonator-integrated fan shroud
according to a variation of the third embodiment.</p><p num="0051">In this resonator-integrated fan shroud, a pair of
cover members 106 each formed in the shape of a vessel and
having one side formed as an opening 106a are fitted to a side
wall of a fan shroud body 103 fabricated by injection molding,
blow molding, or the like, and the respective members are
integrated and formed into hollow shapes. Then, these hollow
boxes 101 are used as a resonator 102. This resonator-integrated
fan shroud is provided with two hollow chambers S<sub>1</sub> and S<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0052">The resonator-integrated fan shroud has the fan shroud
body 103 and the cover members 106.</p><p num="0053">The fan shroud body 103 is a surrounding plate installed
around a cooling fan of a radiator. Here, the fan shroud body
103 is a frame member forming an upper half portion of the
fan shroud, and has a base plate 131, left and right plate
portions 103e and 103f, and an upper plate portion 103c, as
shown in Fig. 10.</p><p num="0054">The base plate 131 is a plate-shaped member whose lower 
edge is cut away in a semicircular shape, and a relatively
wide and smooth surface is secured for it. An upper half portion
of a fan 170 is disposed in this cut-away semicircular hole
O<sub>1</sub>. The plate-shaped left and right plate portions 103e and
103f and upper plate portion 103c of predetermined widths are
formed by being bent orthogonally with respect to the base
plate 131 at left and right side edges and an upper edge portion
of the base plate 131 so as to protect the fan 170 and secure
mechanical strength. The shroud body 103 is appropriately
provided with screw holes B for attaching the fan shroud body
103 to an unillustrated mating member, a fan attaching guide
hole P, ribs R for improving the efficiency of the fan, guides,
and the like (see Fig. 14).</p><p num="0055">A half-split tubular portion 134 is formed uprightly
at a position close to the right-hand side on the upper plate
portion 103c of the fan shroud body 103 shown in Fig. 10.
A base plate portion 311 contiguous to proximal edges of the
half-split tubular portion 134 is curved such that this side
thereof in the drawing becomes convex in such a manner as to
surround the half-split tubular portion 134. The cover members
106 are respectively fitted to a rear surface of the base plate
at two positions and are joined thereto. However, as shown
in Fig. 12, a protrusion 133 where a portion corresponding
to the peripheral edge of the opening of each cover member
106 is built up by a predetermined height is formed. The two 
hollow boxes 101 are formed by respectively joining and fixing
the cover members 106 to the two protrusions 133 by welding
or the like.</p><p num="0056">It should be noted that, in the third embodiment, the
rear surface of the base plate (or the rear surface of the
fan shroud body 103) refers to the rear surface of the base
plate 31 (the fan shroud body 103) with respect to a radiator
178. An unillustrated radiator is disposed on the lower
left-hand side of Figs. 10 and 13, and the surface of the base
plate 131 opposing thereto is a front surface of the base plate
131, and the opposite surface is the rear surface of the base
plate. Similarly, the surface of the fan shroud body 103 opposing
the radiator is its front surface, and the opposite surface
is its rear surface.</p><p num="0057">The cover member 106 is a vessel-shaped member having
one side formed as the opening 106a. In the third embodiment,
two cover members 106 are used in Fig. 10, and each cover member
106 forms a box-shaped vessel whose one side is formed as the
opening 106a by means of a rear plate portion 106b at an innermost
position in the drawing, an upper plate portion 106c, a bottom
plate portion 106d, a left plate portion 106e, a right plate
portion 106f, and a slanting plate portion 106g. The cover
member 106 has its surface on this side in the drawing open.</p><p num="0058">A half-split tubular portion 164 is provided on the
upper plate portion 106c of the right-hand cover member 106 
at a position corresponding to the aforementioned half-split
tubular portion 134 in a mutually opposing manner. If the
half-split tubular portion 164 is joined to and integrated
with the half-split tubular portion 134 so as to be combined
in a state in which the opening 106a of the right-hand cover
member 106 is oriented toward the wall surface of the base
plate, the half-split tubular portions 164 and 134 form a hollow
cylindrical portion, and at the same time the hollow box 101
with its interior formed as a hollow S is formed by the cover
member 106 and the fan shroud body 103 (Fig. 11). This hollow
box 101 can be used as a resonance box of the resonator 102,
and the hollow cylindrical portion serves as a communicating
tube 104 allowing an unillustrated air intake duct and the
hollow box 101 to communicate with each other. On the upper
plate portion 106c of the left-hand cover member 106 shown
in Fig. 15, a communicating tube 104 formed of a hollow cylindrical
short pipe communicating with the interior of the vessel is
integrally formed with the cover member 106 from the outset.
As for the left-hand cover member 106 as well, if it is joined
to and integrated with the fan shroud body 103 in a state in
which its opening 106a is oriented toward a predetermined wall
surface of the base plate 131, the hollow box 101 with its
interior formed as the hollow S is formed by the cover member
106 and the fan shroud body 103.</p><p num="0059">A joining portion 161 at a peripheral edge of the opening 
of the cover body 106 for being joined and fixed to the fan
shroud body 103 is slightly protruded, as shown in Fig. 12,
thereby facilitating the joining operation such as welding
or the like. As the joining portion 161 at the peripheral
edge of the opening 106a of the cover member 106 and the protruded
portion 133 are made to abut against each other, thereby
positively sealing the opening 106a. It should be noted that,
in Fig. 10, the opening 106a and its surrounding portions are
illustrated in a simplified form, and a detailed illustration
of the joining portion 161 is omitted.</p><p num="0060">A drain hole is appropriately formed in the bottom
plate portion 106d, as necessary. The drain hole can be formed
in post-processing, or may be also formed as a blow hole during
molding. By providing the drain hole 163, water which entered
the interior of the resonator 102, i.e., the hollow vessel
101, through an air intake duct and condensed water can be
smoothly drained outside the system.</p><p num="0061">In the resonator-integrated fan shroud in accordance
with the invention, the fan shroud body 103 and the cover members
106 are molded in advance as separate pieces, and the respective
members are joined and integrated later. An empty space can
be secured around the fan shroud even in a narrow engine
compartment. Accordingly, the hollow boxes 101 for the
resonators are formed so as to allow the fan shroud body 103
to form portions of the resonators 102. Effective use is made 
of the vacant space on the rear surface side of the base plate
of the fan shroud body 103, and the base plate 131 is made
to play a partial role of forming the resonator 102, thereby
making maximum use of the space and effecting a reduction in
the cost.</p><p num="0062">In addition, with this resonator-integrated fan shroud,
the hollow box 101 may be formed either on the rear surface
or the front surface of the base plate 131, and may be formed
as shown in Fig. 13, for example. Although, in Figs. 10 to
12, the cover members 106 are joined to and integrated with
the rear surface of the fan shroud body 103 (base plate 131)
to form the hollow boxes 101, the hollow box 101 in this case
is provided on the front surface of the base plate 131, as shown
in Fig. 13. Not only the base plate 131 of the fan shroud
body 103 but also the upper plate portion 103c and the right
plate portion 103f also constitute portions of the hollow box
101.</p><p num="0063">In the same way as in Fig. 10, the cover member 106
forms a box-shaped vessel whose one side is formed as the opening
106a in which this side thereof in the drawing is open by
means of the rear plate portion 106b at an innermost position
in the drawing, the upper plate portion 106c, the bottom plate
portion 106d, and the left and right plate portions 106e and
106f (Fig. 13). However, widths of the upper plate portion
106c and the right plate portion 106f (the left plate portion 
in the exploded perspective view in Fig. 13) are smaller than
widths of the bottom plate portion 106d and the left plate
portion 106e (the right plate portion in the exploded perspective
view in Fig. 13) so that the hollow box 101 can be formed by
being joined and fixed to an upper right corner of the fan
shroud body 103. When joining is effected with the opening
6a of the cover member 106 oriented toward the wall surface
of the base plate 131 of the fan shroud body 103, the peripheral
edge of the opening 106a of the cover member 106 can be brought
into contact with the base plate 131, and the peripheral edge
of the opening of the cover member can be made to abut against
side edges of the upper plate portion 103c and the right plate
portion 103f.</p><p num="0064">When the cover member 106 and the fan shroud body 103
are joined and integrated, the hollow box 101 serving as the
resonator 102 is formed, and at the same time the half-split
tubular portion 164 fixed uprightly on the upper plate portion
106c of the cover member 106 forms a hollow cylinder in cooperation
with the half-split tubular portion 134 fixed uprightly on
the upper plate portion 103c of the fan shroud body 103, thereby
forming the communicating pipe 104. An open end of the
communicating pipe 104 is connected to an unillustrated air
intake duct, and the communicating pipe 104 allows the air
intake duct and the resonator 102 to communicate with each
other. It should be noted that, in Fig. 13, the protruded 
joining portion 161 and the protrusion 133 such as those shown
in Fig. 12 are not provided. The other arrangements are similar
to those of the resonator-integrated fan shroud shown in Figs.
10 to 12, so that a description thereof will be omitted.</p><p num="0065">With the resonator-integrated fan shroud thus
constructed, since a portion of the fan shroud body 103 is
jointly used as it is as a portion of the hollow box 101 so
as to form the resonator 102 for the air intake duct, it is
possible to make use of a narrow vacant space around the fan
shroud body 103. This arrangement is extremely effective in
view of the present situation where it is difficult to secure
the space for the resonator 102 in the engine compartment for
which stepped-up efforts are being made for making the space
compact. By making use of the base plate 131 of the fan shroud
body 103 which occupies a relatively large area, it is possible
to fabricate the resonator 102 having a large capacity, and
the silencing effect becomes large. The resonator-integrated
fan shroud in accordance with the invention demonstrates power
in the reduction of noise in a low-frequency band which can
be solved only by the inevitable use of the large-capacity
resonator 102. If the hollow chamber S is partitioned and
formed into two or more chambers, it is possible to reduce
the noise in mutually different low-frequency bands by varying
the capacities of the hollow chambers S, and it is possible
to further enhance its effect. It becomes possible to provide 
tuning corresponding to various frequency bands by such as
the adjustment of the capacity of the hollow vessel 101, i.e.,
the resonator 102. Tuning is possible not only for the
low-frequency bands but also for high-frequency bands.</p><p num="0066">Further, since the air intake duct is essentially
disposed close to the fan shroud, the air intake passage can
be favorably made short.</p><p num="0067">In addition, since a portion of the shroud body 103
is jointly used as the resonator 102, the manufacturing cost
becomes lower than the resonator 102 which is conventionally
fabricated as a separate piece. The communicating pipe 104
and a portion of the air intake duct (primary-side air intake)
can be integrally molded with the hollow vessel 101, and, when
so done, the manufacturing cost can be further lowered. The
number of components decreases, and inventory control is
facilitated.</p><p num="0068">As described above, the resonator-integrated fan shroud
and the resonator-integrated fan shroud with an air intake
duct in accordance with the invention make it possible to install
the resonator contributing to the reduction of noise in a
low-frequency band without taking up much space for installing
the resonator and without making the intake passages long,
and are extremely useful for the engine compartment for which
stepped-up efforts are being made for making the space compact.</p><p num="0069">In addition, the present invention
provides a fan shroud which makes it possible to install 
a resonator without taking up much space and without
making the intake passages long.</p><p num="0070">It should be noted that the invention is not limited
to the disclosure of the foregoing embodiment, and various
modifications are possible within the scope of the invention
depending on the object and applications. The shapes, sizes,
the number, the material, and the like of the hollow vessel
101, the fan shroud body 103, the communicating pipe 104, and
the like may be appropriately selected in accordance with the
application. Although in the embodiment a description has
been given of only the hollow chamber S which is partitioned
and formed into one or two chambers, it goes without saying
that the hollow vessel 101 partitioned and formed into a greater
number of chambers may be used as the resonator 102, and the
hollow vessel 101 may be formed as the shroud body 103.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lüfterhaube mit integriertem Resonator umfassend:
<claim-text><claim-text>einen Lüfterhaubenkörper (3; 103), der eine Hohlkammer
(S; 1; 101) enthält, die angeordnet ist, um als
Resonator (S; 2; 102) zu wirken; und</claim-text><claim-text>eine Ablassöffnung (13; 163), die in einem Bodenteil
und/oder einem unteren Seitenteil der Hohlkammer (S; 1;
101) angeordnet ist.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lüfterhaube mit integriertem Resonator nach Anspruch 1,
weiter umfassend eine Vielzahl an Hohlkammern (S; S1;
S2; S3; 1; 101).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lüfterhaube mit integriertem Resonator nach Anspruch 1
oder 2, wobei ein Hohlgefäß (1) den genannten
Lüfterhaubenkörper (3; 103) bildet.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lüfterhaube mit integriertem Resonator nach Anspruch 3,
rückbezogen auf Anspruch 2, wobei das Hohlgefäß (1) in
eine Vielzahl an Hohlkammern (S; S1; S2; S3) unterteilt
ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lüfterhaube mit integriertem Resonator nach Anspruch 1,
weiter umfassend:
<claim-text><claim-text>ein Abdeckelement (106), das in einer Gefäßform gebildet
ist und an einer Seite eine Öffnung (10a) aufweist, und
das mit dem Lüfterhaubenkörper (103) verbunden und in
diesen eingebaut ist, so dass die Öffnung (10a) des
Abdeckelements (10) abgedeckt ist, wobei die genannte
Hohlkammer (S; 101) durch das Abdeckelement (10) und den
Lüfterhaubenkörper (103) gebildet ist.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lüfterhaube mit integriertem Resonator nach einem der
vorhergehenden Ansprüche, weiter umfassend ein
Verbindungsrohr (4; 104), das mit einem Lufteinlasskanal
(5) verbindbar ist, wobei das Verbindungsrohr (4; 104)
fest mit der genannten Hohlkammer (S; 1; 101) verbunden
ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lüfterhaube mit integriertem Resonator nach Anspruch 6,
wobei der genannte Lufteinlasskanal (5) fest mit dem
Verbindungsrohr (4) verbunden ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Lüfterhaube mit integriertem Resonator nach Anspruch 6
oder 7, wobei die Hohlkammer (S; 1; 101) ein geblasenes
Formteil ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Fahrzeugmotorraum, ausgerüstet mit einem Lüfter und
einer Lüfterhaube gemäß einem der vorangehenden
Ansprüche.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A resonator-integrated fan shroud comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a fan shroud body (3; 103) containing a hollow
chamber (S; 1; 101) arranged to function as a resonator
(S; 2; 102); and</claim-text><claim-text>a drain hole (13; 163) formed in a bottom portion
and/or a lower side portion of the hollow chamber (S; 1;
101).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The resonator-integrated fan shroud according to
Claim 1, further comprising a plurality of hollow
chambers (S; S1; S2; S3; 1; 101).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A resonator-integrated fan shroud according to Claim
1 or 2, wherein a hollow vessel (1) forms said fan shroud
body (3; 103).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The resonator-integrated fan shroud according to
Claim 3 as dependent on Claim 2, wherein the hollow
vessel (1) is partitioned into a plurality of hollow
chambers (S; S1; S2; S3).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A resonator-integrated fan shroud according to Claim
1, further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a cover member (106), which is formed in a vessel
shape and has an opening (106a) in one side, and which is
joined to and integrated with the fan shroud body (103)
to cover the opening of the cover member (106), whereby
said hollow chamber (S;101) is formed by the cover member
(106) and said fan shroud body (103).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The resonator-integrated fan shroud according to any
preceding claim, further comprising a communicating pipe
(4;104) to be connected to an air intake duct (5), and
wherein the communicating pipe (4;104) is integrally
formed with said hollow chamber (S; 1; 101).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The resonator-integrated fan shroud according to
Claims 6, wherein said air intake duct (5) is integrally
connected to the communicating pipe (4).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The resonator-integrated fan shroud according to
Claim 6 or 7, wherein the hollow chamber (S; 1; 101) is a
blow molding.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A vehicle engine compartment provided with a fan and
a fan shroud according to any preceding claim.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Buse de ventilateur avec résonateur intégré,
comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>un corps de buse de ventilateur (3 ; 103) contenant
une chambre creuse (S ; 1 ; 101) disposée pour
fonctionner comme un résonateur (S ; 2 ; 102), et</claim-text><claim-text>un trou de vidange (13 ; 163) formé dans une partie
inférieure et/ou une partie latérale inférieure de la
chambre creuse (S ; 1 ; 101).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Buse de ventilateur avec résonateur intégré selon
la revendication 1, comprenant en outre, une série de
chambres creuses (S ; S1 ; S2 ; S3 ; 1 ; 101).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Buse de ventilateur avec résonateur intégré selon
la revendication 1 ou 2, où un réservoir creux (1) forme
ledit corps de buse de ventilateur (3 ; 103).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Buse de ventilateur avec résonateur intégré selon
la revendication 3 comme dépendant de la revendication 2;
où le réservoir creux (1) est divisé en une série de
chambres creuses (S ; S1 ; S2 ; S3).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Buse de ventilateur avec résonateur intégré selon
la revendication 1; comprenant en outre :
<claim-text><claim-text>un élément de recouvrement (106), qui est formé en
forme de récipient et qui a une ouverture (106a) sur une
face, et qui est joint à et intégré au corps de buse de
ventilateur (103), pour couvrir l'ouverture du membre de
recouvrement (106), où ladite chambre creuse (S ; 101)
est formée par le membre de recouvrement (106) et ledit
corps de buse de ventilateur (103).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Buse de ventilateur avec résonateur intégré selon
l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes,
comprenant en outre, un tuyau de communication (4 ; 104)
à connecter à une conduite d'amenée d'air (5) et dans
laquelle le tuyau de communication (4 ; 104) est formé de
manière solidaire à ladite chambre creuse (S ; 1 ; 101).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Buse de ventilateur avec résonateur intégré selon
la revendication 6, où ladite conduite d'amenée d'air (5)
est connectée de manière solidaire au tuyau de
communication (4).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Buse de ventilateur avec résonateur intégré selon
la revendication 6 ou 7, où la chambre creuse (S ; 1 ;
101) est un moulage par soufflage.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Compartiment moteur d'un véhicule, muni d'un
ventilateur et d'une buse de ventilateur selon l'une
quelconque des revendications précédentes.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20061220"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060113</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="EN" date="20061201"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION NOT FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20060920"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060713</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20060223"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60113893</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060223</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20051012"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGBIT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20051012"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040519"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040402</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20030305"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGBIT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20021030"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020827</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20020612"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20020612"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010829"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010829"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>