<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1136364-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1136364" kind="B1" date="20041229"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23238517" ucid="EP-1136364-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1136364</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20041229</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01660014-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01660014</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010123</date><lang>FI</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="FI-20000673-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>FI</country><doc-number>20000673</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000322</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20040712</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65B  11/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65B  11/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65B  61/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65B  61/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B65B11/02B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B65B61/10</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Foliebehandlungsvorrichtung und Umwickelvorrichtung</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Film treatment device and wrapping apparatus</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Dispositif de traitement de film et dispositif d'enveloppement</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HALOILA M OY AB</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>OY M. HALOILA AB</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SUOLAHTI YRJOE</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SUOLAHTI, YRJOE</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Suolahti, Yrjö</last-name><address><street>Oy M. Haloila Ab, Ruskontie 16</street><city>21250 Masku</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>OY M. HALOILA AB</last-name><address><street>Ruskontie 16</street><city>21250 Masku</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Tanskanen, Jarmo Tapio</last-name><address><street>Papula Oy, P.O. Box 981</street><city>00101 Helsinki</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>The invention relates to a film treatment device (1) in conjunction with a wrapping apparatus and to a wrapping apparatus provided with a film treatment device. The film treatment device comprises a cutting device (2) for the cutting of a plastic film web (F). The cutting device (2) comprises an elongated electric resistor (5) fastened by both ends with fastening elements (3, 4), against which resistor the film web can be pressed and cut via heating of the electric resistor. The cutting device (2) comprises a supporting element (6) disposed to support the electric resistor laterally substantially over the entire length of the electric resistor between the fastening elements (3, 4). &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">The invention relates to a film
treatment device (1) in conjunction with
a wrapping apparatus and to a wrapping
apparatus provided with a film treatment
device. The film treatment device comprises
a cutting device (2) for the cutting
of a plastic film web (F). The cutting
device (2) comprises an elongated
electric resistor (5) fastened by both
ends with fastening elements (3, 4),
against which resistor the film web can
be pressed and cut via heating of the
electric resistor. The cutting device
(2) comprises a supporting element (6)
disposed to support the electric resistor
laterally substantially over the entire
length of the electric resistor between
the fastening elements (3, 4).
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1136555-A1-00000001" he="110" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a film 
treatment device as defined in the preamble of claim 
1. Moreover, the invention concerns a wrapping apparatus 
as defined in the preamble of claim 11. </p><p num="0002">In prior art, various types of wrapping apparatus 
for wrapping a web of plastic film around an object 
to be packed are known. One of these types of 
wrapping apparatus comprises a film dispenser arranged 
to circulate around the object to be wrapped along a 
ring-like track while the object to be wrapped remains 
immovable during the wrapping operation. The movement 
of the film dispenser may be controlled by a circular 
guide rail or the film dispenser may be attached to a 
rotatable arm. The film runs from a roll in the film 
dispenser and is wrapped around the object. There are 
also wrapping apparatus in which the film dispenser is 
fixedly mounted on a column frame on a base and the 
object to be wrapped is circulated in relation to it 
on a rotating floor. </p><p num="0003">In conjunction with this type of wrapping apparatus, 
various film treatment devices are known e.g. 
from specifications <ref type="patent">WO 99/19216</ref>, <ref type="patent">US 4,993,209</ref>, <ref type="patent">FI 
91624</ref> and <ref type="patent">EP 0493 940</ref>. Typically, a film treatment device 
comprises gripping means which can hold the film 
web at the beginning and end of the wrapping operation. 
Moreover, the film treatment device comprises a 
cutting device for cutting the film web at the end of 
the wrapping operation, and hot sealing means for 
seaming superincumbent film layers together near the 
cut-off line so that the end of the web remains fastened 
to the film layer below it. </p><p num="0004">The cutting and seaming means presented in 
specification <ref type="patent">WO 99/19216</ref> comprises an infrared heat 
radiator disposed in a casing having apertures through 
which infrared radiation is directed through the film 
at a heat absorbing cutting and seaming stop block,  
 
which is thus heated and cuts the film, seaming the 
film layers placed against each other together. The 
use of an infrared heat source has the advantage of 
requiring practically no maintenance. However, the use 
of an infrared lamp involves the drawback of a relatively 
high price, requiring a high electric power and 
a bulky structure. Moreover, both the seaming and the 
cutting of the film are performed using the same heat 
source. The timing of the seaming and cutting operations 
cannot be adjusted independently of each other. 
If a wrapping film plastic type requires different 
cutting and seaming temperatures, then these cannot be 
adjusted independently of each other in each case. </p><p num="0005">In the wrapping apparatus presented in specification 
<ref type="patent">US 4,993,209</ref>, a seaming and cutting device is 
used in which the film is cut and seamed by blowing 
hot air at the film. The problem is a varying seaming 
quality and an inaccurate cut-off line. Heating the 
air to a sufficient temperature and bringing it to the 
cut-off line is also difficult and disadvantageous in 
respect of energy economy. </p><p num="0006">Specifications <ref type="patent">FI 91624</ref> and <ref type="patent">EP 0 493 940</ref> present 
devices for cutting a film in which the film is 
cut by a cutting blade. The problem with a cutting 
blade is its risky nature. When the operator is changing 
the film roll and feeding in a new film to allow 
the gripping means to take hold of it, his hand may 
touch the cutting blade placed close to the roll. </p><p num="0007">A film treatment device is known from the 
applicant's &quot;Octopus&quot; wrapping machine in which the 
cutting device comprises an electric resistance wire 
held fast at both ends by fastening elements and extending 
freely without support between the fastening 
elements so that it is surrounded by an air space on 
all sides. At the end of the wrapping operation, the 
film web is pressed against the resistance wire and an  
 
electric current is passed through the wire, the wire 
being thus heated so that it cuts the film web. </p><p num="0008">The problem is that a repeated fatigue inducing 
load is transmitted from the film web to the areas 
near the points of attachment of the resistance wire, 
producing with time a fatigue fracture and breaking 
the wire. In addition, the thin resistance wire (diameter 
about 0.6 mm) is susceptible to breakage if the 
operator of the machine incautiously presses it when 
fitting the end of the film web to the gripping means 
placed near it. A further problem is that, as the film 
web is bent over the resistance wire, the area of contact 
between the film and the circumference of the resistance 
wire is fairly large, which means that the 
entire contact area has to be burned in order to cut 
off the web, thus producing noxious impurities in the 
air. If e.g. a film web of a width of 0.5 m is bent 
into an angle of 120 degrees over a 0.6 mm resistance 
wire, then for each cut an area of 3.15 cm<sup>2</sup> of plastic 
needs to be burned, producing smoke. A further problem 
is that plastic crust adheres to the wire, deteriorating 
its functional quality. </p><p num="0009">Further, <ref type="patent">US 3,054,441</ref>, having the features of the 
preamble of claim 1, shows a film cutting device having 
a wedge supporting a hot wire along its length. </p><p num="0010">The object of the invention is to eliminate 
the above-mentioned problems. </p><p num="0011">A specific object of the invention is to disclose 
a film treatment device in which the durability 
of the electric resistance wire has been improved so 
that it practically requires no maintenance at all. A 
further object of the invention is to disclose a film 
treatment device that is safer and more reliable than 
earlier devices. An additional object of the invention 
is to disclose a film treatment device in which the 
amount of plastic burned in the cutting operation is 
minimized. </p><p num="0012">As for the features characteristic of the 
film treatment device and wrapping apparatus of the 
invention, reference is made to the claims below.  </p><p num="0013">According to the invention, 
that part of 
the supporting element which supports the electric resistor 
against the pressure of the film web is of a 
curved shape to give the electric resistor a curved 
shape, and the ends of the electric resistor are fastened 
to the supporting element so that at least one 
end is connected to the supporting element via a 
spring. 
The supporting element 
constitutes a back stop for the electric resistor 
against the pressure of the film, keeping the resistor 
continuously firmly immovable in position. </p><p num="0014">The invention has the advantage that the arrangement 
for supporting the electric resistor makes 
it possible to achieve the same advantages as in the 
case of a device using an infrared radiator but in a 
simpler manner and at a lower cost. The susceptibility 
to damage of the electric resistor is reduced and its 
useful life considerably prolonged while a safer and 
more reliable device is achieved. In addition, the invention 
makes it possible to use an electric resistor 
in which the part coming into contact with the film is 
as narrow as possible so that the amount of plastic 
material burned in conjunction with the cutting is 
minimized. Besides, no plastic material will adhere 
around the electric resistor. </p><p num="0015">In an embodiment of the device, the electric 
resistor is of a band-like structure and is in cross-section 
substantially the shape of a flat rectangle. 
The supporting element comprises a slot designed to 
receive the band-like electric resistor partially inside 
it. The walls of the slot support the broad sides 
of the band laterally from both sides while the bottom 
of the slot supports the narrow edge of the band. </p><p num="0016">In an embodiment of the device, the slot has 
been fitted to receive the electric resistor inside it 
with a clearance to allow repeated thermal elongation 
and contraction of the electric resistor band.  </p><p num="0017">The curvature of the electric resistor and the 
tension created in it by the spring are necessary to 
keep the electric resistor in the slot. Due to the 
curvature, the electric resistor is strained into a 
curved shape, which means that a force component directed 
at the support, such as the bottom of the slot, 
is generated in it, pressing the electric resistor toward 
the bottom of the slot and preventing it from 
slipping out of the slot when subjected to a lateral 
force that tends to pull it out of the slot. Without 
the curvature, the electric resistor might easily get 
out of the slot. </p><p num="0018">In an embodiment of the device, the electric 
resistor band comprises an outer edge which cuts the 
film, and an inner edge remaining inside the slot and 
resting on the bottom of the slot, which has a curvature 
designed to bend the electric resistor band into 
a curved shape. </p><p num="0019">In an embodiment of the device, the supporting 
element and the electric resistor are so fitted in 
the device that, while the electric resistor bends the 
film web stretched over it, the supporting element 
also bends the film web at points located on opposite 
sides of the electric resistor at a distance from its 
outer edge, so that after being cut, the film web 
tends to bend clear of the electric resistor. </p><p num="0020">In an embodiment of the device, the supporting 
element is made of an electrically insulating, 
substantially rigid and heat resistant material, e.g. 
phenol formaldehyde. </p><p num="0021">In an embodiment of the device, the thickness 
of the electric resistor band is of the order of about 
0.2 mm.  </p><p num="0022">In an embodiment of the device, the film 
treatment device comprises gripping means for gripping 
the film web. </p><p num="0023">In an embodiment of the device, the film 
treatment device comprises seaming means for seaming 
superimposed film layers together by means of heat. </p><p num="0024">In the following, the invention will be described 
in detail by the aid of a few examples of its 
embodiments with reference to the attached drawing, 
wherein 
<sl><li>Fig. 1 presents an axonometric diagram of an 
embodiment of the wrapping apparatus of the invention 
provided with a film treatment device according to the 
invention, seen in an oblique top view, </li><li>Fig. 2 presents an axonometric view of the 
film treatment device of the wrapping apparatus in 
Fig. 1, </li><li>Fig. 3 presents the film treatment device of 
Fig. 2 in side view, </li><li>Fig. 4 presents the film treatment device of 
Fig. 3 as seen from the direction IV-IV, </li><li>Fig. 5 presents detail A of Fig. 4, </li><li>Fig. 6 presents a diagrammatic section VI-VI 
through the device in Fig. 3, </li><li>Fig. 7 presents a side view of the supporting 
element of the cutting device of the invention with an 
electric resistor band in the slot, </li><li>Fig. 8 presents the supporting element and 
resistor band of Fig. 7 as seen from the direction 
VIII-VIII, </li><li>Fig. 9 presents a magnified section IX-IX of 
Fig. 7 with a plastic film bent over the supporting 
element and the outer edge of the electric resistor 
band so that the film can be cut, </li><li>Figures 10 - 23 illustrate the operation of 
the film treatment device at different stages during 
the wrapping process. </li></sl></p><p num="0025">Fig. 1 shows a wrapping apparatus designed 
for winding a wrapping film (wrapping film) about a 
stationary product P to be packaged. The wrapping apparatus 
comprises a framework 18 mounted on a fixed 
base. A movable framel9 can be moved vertically in relation 
to the framework 18. A circular ring guideway 
20 is disposed in a horizontal plane and supported by 
the movable frame 19 so that it can move vertically in 
relation to the framework. The wrapping apparatus comprises 
a film dispenser 16, which has been arranged to 
move at a constant speed, driven by a drive motor (not 
shown) provided in the film dispenser 16, along a circular 
path as guided by the ring guideway 20 around 
the product P being packed. During the wrapping operation, 
the ring guideway 20, supported by the movable 
frame 19, is moved vertically to allow the film to be 
wound as a spiral wrapping about the product. Movably 
mounted on the movable frame 19 is a portal beam 29 
with a film treatment device 1 mounted on it. By moving 
the portal beam 29 horizontally in relation to the 
movable frame 19, the film treatment device 1 can be 
moved towards and away from the product P being 
packed. </p><p num="0026">It is to be noted that the film treatment device 
1 described here can be employed in any wrapping 
machine, e.g. one in which the film dispenser is connected 
to a rotating crank that circulates the film 
dispenser about a stationary product to be wrapped, or 
in a wrapping machine in which the film dispenser is 
connected to a fixed column and the product is rotated 
to wind the film around it. </p><p num="0027">Fig. 2 - 6 present more detailed views of the 
film treatment device 1 and its components. As the device 
is, in other respects except for the arrangement 
of the invention for supporting the electric resistor 
5, of a type known in itself (general construction 
known e.g. from specification <ref type="patent">US 4,993,209</ref>), its  
 
structure will not be described here in detail except 
only as far as necessary for an understanding of the 
invention and the operation of the device. </p><p num="0028">As shown in Fig. 2 - 6, the film treatment 
device 1 comprises gripping means 12, 13 for gripping 
the film web. It also comprises seaming means 12, 14 
for seaming superimposed film layers together via the 
application of heat. In addition, the film treatment 
device comprises a cutting device 2 for cutting off 
the film web along a line near the seam. The film 
treatment device comprises a frame 12, which can be 
turned by a first power means 21 between a vertical 
and a horizontal position about a swiveling axis 22. 
The device further comprises a hold bar 13, which can 
be turned about the swiveling axis 22 by a second 
power means 23. As can be seen from Fig. 6, the gripping 
means consist of a gap 30 between the circumference 
of the round hold bar 13 and a planar surface 24 
of the frame 12 placed against the hold bar, said gap 
being fitted to hold in its grip a film web placed in 
it (see also Fig. 12 and 23). </p><p num="0029">The film treatment device 1 further comprises 
a backing bar 14, which can be turned by a third power 
means 25 about the swiveling axis 22 between a vertical 
and a horizontal position. The frame 12 comprises 
a second stop face 26, which is disposed against a 
third stop face 27 in the backing bar 14, forming the 
seaming means, which are heated by an electric seaming 
resistor 28 embedded inside the frame 12 close to the 
stop face 26. </p><p num="0030">The film dispenser 1 further comprises a cutting 
device 2 for cutting off the plastic film web F. 
The cutting device 2 is mounted on the frame 12 between 
the above-mentioned seaming means and gripping 
means. </p><p num="0031">The cutting device 2 is presented in greater 
detail in Fig. 7 - 9. The cutting device 2 comprises  
 
an elongated supporting element 6, which can be fastened 
to the frame 12. The supporting element 6 is 
made of a dielectric material of a substantially rigid 
and heat-resistant nature, such as phenol formaldehyde 
(PF), which is also called &quot;bakelite&quot;. The supporting 
element 6 is provided with a longitudinal slot 7, in 
which a band-like electric resistor 5 of a cross-sectional 
form resembling a flat rectangle is mounted 
with a clearance so as to allow thermal expansion and 
contraction of the band in the slot. The bottom 11 of 
the slot 7 supports the inner edge 10 of the electric 
resistor band 5 while the opposite walls support the 
two broad sides of the band. The outer edge 9 of the 
electric resistor band 5 extends somewhat upward from 
the surface of the supporting element 6. One end of 
the electric resistor band 5 is fixedly connected to 
the supporting element 6 with a fastening element 3. 
The other end of the electric resistor band 5 is connected 
to the supporting element 6 with a second fastening 
element 4, which comprises a slide block 31 
movable along a guide 32 formed in the supporting element, 
said slide block being loaded by a spring 8 in 
the longitudinal direction to keep the band 5 tight in 
the slot 7. As can be seen from Fig. 7, the bottom 11 
of the slot 7 has a slightly curved shape with a large 
radius R of curvature to bend the electric resistor 
band 5 into a corresponding curved shape. This again 
helps keep the band 5 in the slot 7. </p><p num="0032">Fig. 9 illustrates how the electric resistor 
5 bends the film web F stretched over it when the web 
is held in the grip of the seaming means on one side 
and of the gripping means on the other side of the resistor 
as illustrated in Fig. 23. The supporting element 
6 causes the film web to bend at points a and b, 
which are close to the electric resistor 5 on opposite 
sides of it but still at a distance from it so that, 
after the film web has been cut off by instantaneously  
 
heating the electric resistor, the ends of the film 
web F tend to bend out clear of the electric resistor 
5 as indicated with broken lines in Fig. 9. </p><p num="0033">The electric resistor band 5 used may be of a 
fairly thin construction as it is so well supported in 
the slot 7 in the supporting element 6. In one embodiment, 
the electric resistor band consists of a resistance 
band available under the trade name KANTHAL DSD, 
which has a width of 6 mm, a thickness of 0.2 mm and a 
specific resistance of 2.446 Ω/m. In the example embodiment, 
the resistor strip has a resistance of 1.3 Ω 
and it is supplied with a voltage of 24 V. The electric 
power is 500 W. </p><p num="0034">Fig. 10 - 23 are diagrammatic illustrations 
of the operation of the film treatment device 1 at 
different stages during the wrapping of a stationary 
package P. The film dispenser 16 is simply represented 
by a film roll 17 from which the film is delivered. </p><p num="0035">Fig. 10 (side view) and 11 (top view) illustrate 
the initial phase of the process of wrapping a 
package P, in which situation the film F is held in 
the grip of the frame 12 and the hold bar 13, as can 
also be seen from the magnified detail in Fig. 12, 
while the frame 12, hold bar 13 and backing bar 14 are 
in the vertical position. </p><p num="0036">Fig. 13 and 14 illustrate a situation at the 
beginning of the wrapping process when the assembly 
consisting of the frame 12, hold bar 13 and backing 
bar 14 has been turned about the swiveling axis 22 to 
the horizontal position with the film F still held in 
the grip of the frame 12 and hold bar 13, so that the 
film can be wound about the package P without being 
hindered by these parts. </p><p num="0037">In Fig. 15 and 16, the assembly of the frame 
12, hold bar 13 and backing bar 14 is still in the 
same position as in Fig. 11 and 12 and the film roll 
17 has made one complete circle and part of a second  
 
circle about the package P. The film end remaining under 
one film layer can now be released from the grip 
of the frame 12 and hold bar 13. </p><p num="0038">Fig. 17 and 18 illustrate a situation at a 
final phase of the wrapping operation. The backing bar 
14 has been turned about the swiveling axis 22 to the 
vertical position while the frame 12 and hold bar 13 
still remain in the horizontal position, and the backing 
bar 14 is left between the film and the package P 
as the film is wound over the backing bar 14. </p><p num="0039">Fig. 19 and 20 illustrate a situation where 
the film roll has made yet another circle about the 
package P after the situation in Fig. 17 and 18. The 
hold bar 13 has been turned about the swiveling axis 
22 into the vertical position and the film has been 
wound over the hold bar 13. The wrapping operation 
stops here. </p><p num="0040">Fig. 21 - 23 illustrate the final situation, 
where the frame has been turned about the swiveling 
axis 22 to the vertical position against the hold bar 
13 and backing bar 14 in order to cut and seam the 
film. The electric resistor band 5 is heated by passing 
an electric current through it, whereupon it burns 
through the film F, thus cutting it off. At the same 
time, the electric seaming resistor 28 inside the 
frame 12 is heated by passing an electric current 
through it, thus heating it so that it welds together 
the film layers now lying one over the other between 
the stop face 26 of the frame and the stop face 27 of 
the backing bar 14 so that the tail of the film is 
fastened to the film layer below it. After that, the 
frame 12 and the hold bar 13 are turned to the horizontal 
position and the film treatment device 1 is 
moved upward, thus drawing out the backing bar 14 from 
under the last film layers on the package. </p><p num="0041">After this, the wrapped package P can be 
taken away and a new one can be brought in to be  
 
wrapped, starting again from a situation as illustrated 
in Fig. 10 - 12. </p><p num="0042">The invention is not restricted to the examples 
of its embodiments described above; instead, many 
variations are possible within the scope of the inventive 
idea defined in the claims. </p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Folienbehandlungsvorrichtung (1) für eine Umwickelvorrichtung, wobei 
die Vorrichtung aufweist: eine Schneidvorrichtung (2) zum Schneiden 
einer Kunststofffolienbahn (F), wobei die Schneidvorrichtung (2) einen 
länglichen elektrischen Widerstand (5) aufweist, der an beiden Enden 
mittels Befestigungselementen (3, 4) befestigt ist, und gegen welchen 
Widerstand die Folienbahn gedrückt und durch Erhitzen des elektrischen 
Widerstands geschnitten werden kann, und ein Halteelemente (6), das 
so angeordnet ist, dass es den elektrischen Widerstand seitlich im 
wesentlichen über die gesamte Länge des elektrischen Widerstands 
zwischen den Befestigungselementen (3, 4) hält,dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass der Teil des 
Halteelements (6), der den elektrischen Widerstand (5) gegen den Druck 
der Folienbahn (F) hält, in einer Längsrichtung des elektrischen 
Widerstands eine gewölbte Gestalt aufweist, um dem elektrischen 
Widerstand eine gewölbte Gestalt zu verleihen; und dass die Enden des 
elektrischen Widerstands (5) an dem Halteelement so befestigt sind, 
dass mindestens ein Ende über eine Feder (8) mit dem Halteelement (6) 
verbunden ist. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass der 
elektrische Widerstand (5) eine bandartige Struktur aufweist und im 
Querschnitt im wesentlichen die Gestalt eines flachen Rechtecks 
aufweist; und dass das Halteelement (6) einen Schlitz (7) aufweist, der 
zum Aufnehmen des bandartigen elektrischen Widerstand ausgebildet 
ist. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 2, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass der Schlitz 
(7) zur Aufnahme des elektrischen Widerstand (5) mit Spielraum 
ausgebildet ist, um eine thermische Dehnung und Kontraktion des 
elektrischen Widerstandbandes zu ermöglichen. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 2 bis 3, dadurch gekennzeichnet, 
dass das elektrische Widerstandsband (5) eine äußere Kante (9), die die 
Folie schneidet, und eine innere Kante (10) aufweist, die innerhalb des 
Schlitzes (7) bleibt und auf dem Boden (11) des Schlitzes (7), der eine 
Wölbung aufweist, die dazu ausgelegt ist, das elektrische 
Widerstandsband in eine gewölbte Form zu biegen, aufliegt. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 1 bis 4, dadurch gekennzeichnet, 
dass das Halteelement (6) und der elektrische Widerstand (5) so 
angepasst sind, dass, während der elektrische Widerstand die über ihn 
gezogene Folienbahn (F) biegt, das Halteelement auch die Folienbahn 
(F) an Punkten (a, b) biegt, die an gegenüberliegenden Seiten des 
elektrischen Widerstands in einem Abstand davon angeordnet sind, so 
dass nach dem Schneiden die Folienbahn dazu neigt, sich frei vom 
elektrischen Widerstand zu biegen. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 1 bis 5, dadurch gekennzeichnet, 
dass das Halteelement (6) aus elektrisch isolierendem, im wesentlichen 
steifem und hitzebeständigem Material hergestellt ist. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 6, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass das 
Halteelement (6) aus Phenolformaldehyd hergestellt ist. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 2 bis 7, dadurch gekennzeichnet, 
dass die Dicke des elektrischen Widerstandsbandes (5) in der 
Größenordnung von ungefähr 0,2 mm liegt. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 1 bis 8, dadurch gekennzeichnet, 
dass die Folienbehandlungsvorrichtung (1) Greifermittel (12, 13) zum 
Ergreifen der Folienbahn aufweist. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 1 bis 9, dadurch gekennzeichnet, 
dass die Folienbehandlungsvorrichtung (1) Säummittel (12, 14) aufweist, 
um übereinander liegende Folienlagen mittels Wärme 
zusammenzuschweißen. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Umwickelvorrichtung zum Wickeln einer Kunststofffolienbahn (F) um 
einen zu verpackenden Gegenstand (P), wobei die Umwickelvorrichtung 
einen Folienspender (16) zum Wickeln einer Kunststofffolienbahn von 
einer Rolle (17) um den zu verpackenden Gegenstand und eine 
Folienbehandlungsvorrichtung (1) aufweist, enthaltend Greifermittel (12, 
13) zum Ergreifen der Folienbahn und eine Schneidvorrichtung (2) zum 
Schneiden der Folienbahn, wobei die Schneidvorrichtung einen 
länglichen elektrischen Widerstand (5) aufweist, der an beiden Enden 
mit Befestigungselementen (3, 4) befestigt ist und gegen welchen 
Widerstand die Folienbahn gedrückt und durch Erhitzen des elektrischen 
Widerstandes geschnitten werden kann, Säummittel (14, 15) zum 
Zusammenschweißen von übereinander liegenden Folienlagen, und ein 
Halteelement (6), das angeordnet ist, um den elektrischen Widerstand 
seitlich im wesentlichen über die gesamte Länge des elektrischen 
Widerstand zwischen den Befestigungselementen (3, 4) zu halten, 
dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass der Teil des Halteelements (6), der den 
elektrischen Widerstand (5) gegen den Druck der Folienbahn (F) hält, in 
einer Längsrichtung des elektrischen Widerstands eine gewölbte Gestalt 
aufweist, um dem elektrischen Widerstand eine gewölbte Gestalt zu 
verleihen; und dass die Enden des elektrischen Widerstands (5) an dem 
 
Halteelement so befestigt sind, dass mindestens ein Ende über eine 
Feder (8) mit dem Halteelement (6) verbunden ist. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Umwickelvorrichtung nach Anspruch 11, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass 
der elektrische Widerstand (5) eine bandartige Struktur aufweist und im 
Querschnitt im wesentlichen die Gestalt eines flachen Rechtecks 
aufweist; und dass das Halteelement (6) einen Schlitz (7) aufweist, der 
zum Aufnehmen des bandartigen elektrischen Widerstand ausgebildet 
ist. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Umwickelvorrichtung nach Anspruch 12, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass 
der Schlitz (7) zur Aufnahme des elektrischen Widerstandes (5) mit 
Spielraum ausgebildet ist, um eine thermische Dehnung und Kontraktion 
des elektrischen Widerstandbandes zu ermöglichen. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Umwickelvorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 12 oder 13, dadurch 
gekennzeichnet, dass das elektrische Widerstandsband (5) eine äußere 
Kante (9) aufweist, die die Folie schneidet, und eine innere Kannte (10) 
innerhalb des Schlitzes (7) bleibt und auf dem Boden (11) des Schlitzes 
(7), der eine Wölbung aufweist, die dazu ausgelegt ist, das elektrische 
Widerstandsband in eine gewölbte Form zu biegen, aufliegt. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Umwickelvorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 11 bis 14, dadurch 
gekennzeichnet, dass das Halteelement (6) und der elektrische 
Widerstand (5) so angepasst sind, dass, während der elektrische 
Widerstand die über ihn gezogene Folienbahn (F) biegt, das 
Halteelement auch die Folienbahn (F) an Punkten (a, b) biegt, die an 
gegenüberliegenden Seiten des elektrischen Widerstands in einem 
Abstand davon angeordnet sind, so dass nach dem Schneiden die 
Folienbahn dazu neigt, sich frei vom elektrischen Widerstand zu biegen. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Umwickelvorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 11 bis 15, dadurch 
gekennzeichnet, dass das Halteelement (6) aus elektrisch isolierendem, 
im wesentlichen steifem und hitzebeständigem Material hergestellt ist. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Umwickelvorrichtung nach Anspruch 16, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass 
das Halteelement (6) aus Phenolformaldehyd hergestellt ist. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Umwickelvorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 11 bis 17, dadurch 
gekennzeichnet, dass die Dicke des elektrischen Widerstandsbandes (5) 
in der Größenordnung von ungefähr 0,2 mm liegt. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Umwickelvorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 11 bis 18, dadurch 
gekennzeichnet, dass die Umwickelvorrichtung ein Rahmentragwerk 
(18), das auf einer ortsfesten Basis montiert ist; einen beweglichen 
Rahmen (19), der vertikal im Verhältnis zum Rahmentragwerk bewegt 
werden kann; eine kreisförmige Ringführungsbahn (20), die in einer 
horizontalen Ebene angeordnet ist und durch den beweglichen Rahmen 
gehalten wird, aufweist; wobei der Folienspender (16) so angeordnet ist, 
dass er sich längs der Ringführungsbahn um den zu verpackenden 
Gegenstand (P) bewegt; und dass die Folienbehandlungsvorrichtung (1) 
so am beweglichen Rahmen montiert ist, dass sie zu dem zu 
verpackenden Gegenstand (P) hin und von ihm weg bewegt werden 
kann. </claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Film treatment device (1) 
for a wrapping apparatus, said device comprising a 
cutting device (2) for the cutting of a plastic film 
web (F), which cutting device (2) comprises an elongated 
electric resistor (5) fastened by both ends by 
means of fastening elements (3, 4), against which resistor 
the film web can be pressed and cut via heating 
of the electric resistor, and a supporting element 
(6) disposed to support the electric resistor laterally 
substantially over the entire length of the electric 
resistor between the fastening elements (3, 4), 
characterized in that that part of the supporting 
element (6) which supports the electric resistor 
(5) against the pressure of the film web (F) is of 
a curved shape in a longitudinal direction of the 
electric resistor to give the electric resistor a 
curved shape; and that the ends of the electric resistor 
(5) are fastened to the supporting element so that 
at least one end is connected to the supporting element 
(6) via a spring (8). </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Device as defined in claim 1, characterized 
in that the electric resistor (5) is 
of a band-like structure and is in cross-section substantially 
the shape of a flat rectangle; and that the 
supporting element (6) comprises a slot (7) designed 
to receive the band-like electric resistor inside it. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Device as defined in claim 2, characterized 
in that the slot (7) has been fitted to 
receive the electric resistor (5) inside it with a 
clearance to allow for thermal elongation and contraction 
of the electric resistor band. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Device as defined in any one of claims 2 - 
3, characterized in that the electric resistor 
band (5) comprises an outer edge (9) which cuts 
the film, and an inner edge (10) remaining inside the 
slot (7) and resting on the bottom (11) of the slot 
 
(7), which has a curvature designed to bend the electric 
resistor band into a curved shape. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Device as defined in any one of claims 1 - 
4, characterized in that the supporting element 
(6) and the electric resistor (5) are so fitted 
that, while the electric resistor bends the film web 
(F) stretched over it, the supporting element also 
bends the film web (F) at points (a, b), which are located 
on opposite sides of the electric resistor at a 
distance from it, so that after being cut, the film 
web tends to bend clear of the electric resistor. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Device as defined in any one of claims 1 - 
5, characterized in that the supporting element 
(6) is made of electrically insulating, substantially 
rigid and heat resistant material. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Device as defined in claim 6, characterized 
in that the supporting element (6) is 
made of phenol formaldehyde. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Device as defined in any one of claims 2 - 
7, characterized in that the thickness of the 
electric resistor band (5) is of the order of about 
0.2 mm. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Device as defined in any one of claims 1 - 
8, characterized in that the film treatment 
device (1) comprises gripping means (12, 13) for gripping 
the film web. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Device as defined in any one of claims 1 
- 9, characterized in that the film treatment 
device (1) comprises seaming means (12, 14) for seaming 
superimposed film layers together by means of 
heat. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Wrapping apparatus for wrapping a plastic 
film web (F) around an article (P) to be packed, said 
wrapping apparatus comprising a film dispenser (16) 
for winding a plastic film web from a roll (17) around 
the article to be packed, and a film treatment device 
(1) comprising gripping means (12, 13) for gripping 
 
the film web and a cutting device (2) for cutting the 
film web, said cutting device comprising an elongated 
electric resistor (5) fastened by both ends with fastening 
elements (3, 4), against which resistor the 
film web can be pressed and cut via heating of the 
electric resistor, seaming means (14, 15) for seaming 
superimposed film layers together, and a supporting 
element (6) arranged to support the electric resistor 
laterally substantially over the entire length of 
electric resistor between the fastening elements (3, 
4), characterized in that that part of the 
supporting element (6) which supports the electric resistor 
(5) against the pressure of the film web (F) is 
of a curved shape in a longitudinal direction of the 
electric resistor to give the electric resistor a 
curved shape; and that the ends of the electric resistor 
(5) are fastened to the supporting element so that 
at least one end is connected to the supporting element 
(6) via a spring (8). </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Wrapping apparatus as defined in claim 
11, characterized in that the electric resistor 
(5) is of a band-like structure and in cross-section 
substantially the shape of a flat rectangle; 
and that the supporting element (6) comprises a slot 
(7) designed to receive the band-like electric resistor 
inside it. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Wrapping apparatus as defined in claim 
12, characterized in that the slot (7) has 
been fitted to receive the electric resistor (5) inside 
it with a clearance to allow for thermal elongation 
and contraction of the electric resistor band. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Wrapping apparatus as defined in claim 12 
or 13, characterized in that the electric resistor 
band (5) comprises an outer edge (9) which cuts 
the film, and an inner edge (10) remaining inside the 
slot (7) and resting on the bottom (11) of the slot 
 
(7), which has a curvature designed to bend the electric 
resistor band to a curved shape. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Wrapping apparatus as defined in any one 
of claims 11 - 14, characterized in that the 
supporting element (6) and the electric resistor (5) 
are so fitted that, while the electric resistor bends 
the film web (F) stretched over it, the supporting element 
also bends the film web (F) at points (a, b), which 
are located on opposite sides of the electric resistor 
at a distance from it, so that, after being cut, the 
film web tends to bend clear of the electric resistor. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Wrapping apparatus as defined in any one 
of claims 11 - 15, characterized in that the 
supporting element (6) is made of electrically insulting, 
substantially rigid and heat resistant material. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Wrapping apparatus as defined in claim 
16, characterized in that the supporting element 
(6) is made of phenol formaldehyde. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Wrapping apparatus as defined in any one 
of claims 11 - 17, characterized in that the 
thickness of the electric resistor band (5) is of the 
order of about 0.2 mm. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Wrapping apparatus as defined in any one 
of claims 11 - 18, characterized in that the 
wrapping apparatus comprises a framework (18) mounted 
on a fixed base; a movable frame (19) which can be 
moved vertically in relation to the framework; a circular 
ring guideway (20) disposed in a horizontal 
plane and supported by the movable frame; that the 
film dispenser (16) has been arranged to move along 
the ring guideway around the article (P) being packed; 
and that the film treatment device (1) is mounted on 
the movable frame so that it can be moved towards and 
away from the article (P) being packed. </claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif de traitement de film (1) pour appareil d'emballage, ledit 
dispositif comprenant un dispositif de coupe (2) pour la coupe d'un film plastique 
continu (F), lequel dispositif de coupe (2) comprend une résistance électrique 
allongée (5) fixée aux deux extrémités par des éléments de fixation (3, 4), contre 
laquelle résistance le film continu peut être appuyé et coupé par échauffement de 
la résistance électrique, et un élément de support (6) placé pour supporter la 
résistance électrique latéralement sur sensiblement toute la longueur de la 
résistance électrique entre les éléments de fixation (3, 4), caractérisé en ce que la 
partie de l'élément de support (6) qui supporte la résistance électrique (5) contre 
la pression du film continu (F) est de forme courbe dans une direction 
longitudinale de la résistance électrique pour donner à la résistance électrique une 
forme courbe; et en ce que les extrémités de la résistance électrique (5) sont 
fixées à l'élément de support de telle manière qu'au moins une extrémité est 
rattachée à l'élément de support (6) par un ressort (8). </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif selon la revendication 1, caractérisé en ce que la résistance 
électrique (5) est à structure en bande et présente en section transversale 
sensiblement la forme d'un rectangle plat; et en ce que l'élément de support (6) 
comprend une fente (7) conçue pour recevoir la résistance électrique en bande en 
son sein. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif selon la revendication 2, caractérisé en ce que la fente (7) est 
ajustée pour recevoir la résistance électrique (5) en son sein avec du jeu pour 
permettre la dilatation et la contraction thermiques de la bande de résistance 
électrique. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif selon la revendication 2 ou 3, caractérisé en ce que la bande de 
résistance électrique (5) comprend un bord extérieur (9) qui coupe le film, et un 
bord intérieur (10) restant à l'intérieur de la fente (7) et reposant sur le fond (11) 
de la fente (7), qui a une courbure conçue pour fléchir la bande de résistance 
électrique en une forme courbe. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif selon l'une quelconque des revendications 1 à 4, caractérisé en 
ce que l'élément de support (6) et la résistance électrique (5) sont ajustés de telle 
manière que, pendant que la résistance électrique courbe le film continu (F) tendu 
 
sur elle, l'élément de support courbe aussi le film continu (F) en des points (a, b), 
qui sont situés sur des côtés opposés de la résistance électrique à une certaine 
distance d'elle, si bien qu'après avoir été coupé, le film continu a tendance à se 
courber sans toucher la résistance électrique. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif selon l'une quelconque des revendications 1 à 5, caractérisé en 
ce que l'élément de support (6) est fait d'un matériau électriquement isolant, 
substantiellement rigide et résistant à la chaleur. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif selon la revendication 6, caractérisé en ce que l'élément de 
support (6) est fait de phénol-formaldéhyde. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif selon l'une quelconque des revendications 2 à 7, caractérisé en 
ce que l'épaisseur de la bande de résistance électrique (5) est de l'ordre d'environ 
0,2 mm. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif selon l'une quelconque des revendications 1 à 8, caractérisé en 
ce que le dispositif de traitement de film (1) comprend des moyens de serrage 
(12, 13) pour serrer le film continu. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif selon l'une quelconque des revendications 1 à 9, caractérisé en 
ce que le dispositif de traitement de film (1) comprend des moyens de soudage 
(12, 14) pour souder l'une à l'autre des couches de film superposées par 
application de chaleur. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Appareil d'emballage pour enrouler un film plastique continu (F) autour 
d'un article (P) à emballer, ledit appareil d'emballage comprenant un distributeur 
de film (16) pour enrouler un film plastique continu provenant d'une bobine (17) 
autour de l'article à emballer, et un dispositif de traitement de film (1) 
comprenant des moyens de serrage (12, 13) pour serrer le film continu et un 
dispositif de coupe (2) pour couper le film continu, ledit dispositif de coupe 
comprenant une résistance électrique allongée (5) fixée aux deux extrémités par 
des éléments de fixation (3, 4), contre laquelle résistance le film continu peut être 
appuyé et coupé par échauffement de la résistance électrique, des moyens de 
soudage (14, 15) pour souder l'une à l'autre des couches de film superposées, et 
un élément de support (6) agencé pour supporter la résistance électrique 
latéralement sur sensiblement toute la longueur de la résistance électrique entre 
 
les éléments de fixation (3, 4), caractérisé en ce que la partie de l'élément de 
support (6) qui supporte la résistance électrique (5) contre la pression du film 
continu (F) est de forme courbe dans une direction longitudinale de la résistance 
électrique pour donner à la résistance électrique une forme courbe; et en ce que 
les extrémités de la résistance électrique (5) sont fixées à l'élément de support de 
telle manière qu'au moins une extrémité est rattachée à l'élément de support (6) 
par un ressort (8). </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Appareil d'emballage selon la revendication 11, caractérisé en ce que la 
résistance électrique (5) est à structure en bande et présente en section 
transversale sensiblement la forme d'un rectangle plat; et en ce que l'élément de 
support (6) comprend une fente (7) conçue pour recevoir la résistance électrique 
en bande en son sein. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Appareil d'emballage selon la revendication 12, caractérisé en ce que la 
fente (7) est ajustée pour recevoir la résistance électrique (5) en son sein avec du 
jeu pour permettre la dilatation et la contraction thermiques de la bande de 
résistance électrique. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Appareil d'emballage selon la revendication 12 ou 13, caractérisé en ce 
que la bande de résistance électrique (5) comprend un bord extérieur (9) qui 
coupe le film, et un bord intérieur (10) restant à l'intérieur de la fente (7) et 
reposant sur le fond (11) de la fente (7), qui a une courbure conçue pour fléchir la 
bande de résistance électrique en une forme courbe. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Appareil d'emballage selon l'une quelconque des revendications 11 à 14, 
caractérisé en ce que l'élément de support (6) et la résistance électrique (5) sont 
ajustés de telle manière que, pendant que la résistance électrique courbe le film 
continu (F) tendu sur elle, l'élément de support courbe aussi le film continu (F) en 
des points (a, b), qui sont situés sur des côtés opposés de la résistance électrique à 
une certaine distance d'elle, si bien qu'après avoir été coupé, le film continu a 
tendance à se courber sans toucher la résistance électrique. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Appareil d'emballage selon l'une quelconque des revendications 11 à 15, 
caractérisé en ce que l'élément de support (6) est fait d'un matériau 
électriquement isolant, substantiellement rigide et résistant à la chaleur. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Appareil d'emballage selon la revendication 16, caractérisé en ce que 
l'élément de support (6) est fait de phénol-formaldéhyde. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Appareil d'emballage selon l'une quelconque des revendications 11 à 17, 
caractérisé en ce que l'épaisseur de la bande de résistance électrique (5) est de 
l'ordre d'environ 0,2 mm. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Appareil d'emballage selon l'une quelconque des revendications 11 à 18, 
caractérisé en ce que l'appareil d'emballage comprend une charpente (18) montée 
sur une base fixe; un châssis mobile (19) qui peut être déplacé verticalement par 
rapport à la charpente; un guide annulaire circulaire (20) placé dans un plan 
horizontal et supporté par le châssis mobile; en ce que le distributeur de film (16) 
a été agencé pour se déplacer le long du guide annulaire autour de l'article (P) en 
cours d'emballage; et en ce que le dispositif de traitement de film (1) est monté 
sur le châssis mobile de telle manière qu'il peut être rapproché et éloigné de 
l'article (P) en cours d'emballage. </claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20061220"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MC</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>TR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041229</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050131</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20051221"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050930</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20051125"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050616"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ES</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG2A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>2233592</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>T3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050509"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DK</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>T3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050331"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SC4A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AVAILABILITY OF NATIONAL TRANSLATION</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050124</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050315"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>NV</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>representative=s name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>E. BLUM &amp; CO. PATENTANWAELTE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20050203"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60107990</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050203</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050126"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20041231"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20041229"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20041229"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040407"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040220</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20030611"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20030502"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030301</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20020925"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20020925"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010926"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010926"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>