<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1132273-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1132273" kind="B1" date="20051109"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23246282" ucid="EP-1132273-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1132273</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20051109</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01301006-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01301006</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010205</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-522442" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>522442</doc-number><date>20000309</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-52244200-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>52244200</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000309</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20050524</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60T   8/40        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60T   8/40        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60T  13/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60T  13/66        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60T  13/66        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60T  13/74        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60T13/66B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60T13/74A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60T8/40J</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Elektrisches Bremssystem mit bedingter Beendigung des Anlegens der vollen Bremskraft beim Abstellen des Fahrzeugs</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Brake-by-wire system having conditioned full brake force application termination at key off</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Système de freinage par cable avec cessation conditionelle de la pleine force de freinage lors de l'arrèt du véhicule</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>FORD GLOBAL TECH LLC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>FORD GLOBAL TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>CROMBEZ DALE SCOTT</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>CURRAN PATRICK JOSEPH</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAPIER STEVEN LEE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>CROMBEZ, DALE SCOTT</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>CURRAN, PATRICK JOSEPH</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAPIER, STEVEN LEE</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>CROMBEZ, DALE SCOTT</last-name><address><street>9615, Ingram</street><city>Livonia, Michigan 48150</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>CURRAN, PATRICK JOSEPH</last-name><address><street>20415, Northville Place Apt. 2309</street><city>Northville, Michigan 48167</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>NAPIER, STEVEN LEE</last-name><address><street>43565, Applewood</street><city>Canton, Michigan 48188</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Ford Global Technologies, LLC</last-name><address><street>One Parklane Blvd 600 Parklane Towers East</street><city>Dearborn, MI 48126</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Messulam, Alec Moses</last-name><address><street>A. Messulam &amp;amp; Co. Ltd., 43-45 High Road</street><city>Bushey Heath, Herts WD23 1EE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>An electric powered brake system (10) for braking road-engaging wheels of a motor vehicle. An ignition switch for turning a motor of the vehicle on and off also controls the application of electric power to the electric powered brake system. A control and method for maintaining application of full electric power to the electric powered brake system when the ignition switch is operated from ON to OFF so long as at least one parameter related to a respective component of the vehicle and indicative of a need to maintain full electric power application to the brake system continues to exist and for discontinuing application of full electric power to the brake system when all of selected ones of several such parameters are indicative of lack of need to maintain full electric power application to the brake system. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">An electric powered brake system (10) for braking road-engaging
wheels of a motor vehicle. An ignition switch for
turning a motor of the vehicle on and off also controls the
application of electric power to the electric powered brake
system. A control and method for maintaining application of
full electric power to the electric powered brake system
when the ignition switch is operated from ON to OFF so long
as at least one parameter related to a respective component
of the vehicle and indicative of a need to maintain full
electric power application to the brake system continues to
exist and for discontinuing application of full electric
power to the brake system when all of selected ones of
several such parameters are indicative of lack of need to
maintain full electric power application to the brake
system.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1132215-A2-00000001" he="105" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">This invention relates generally to brake systems for
wheeled motor vehicles, and more specifically it relates to
a brake-by-wire system.</p><p num="0002">A brake-by-wire system may comprise a pedal that
depresses a master cylinder plunger to perform the service
brake function for a motor vehicle. The service brake
function is performed by selectively applying electrically
boosted hydraulic brakes or regenerative brakes. Hydraulic
brakes generally apply friction forces to the wheels to
dissipate energy as heat. Regenerative brakes may take any
of various forms, but are often considered to comprise a
rotary electric machine load that is applied to one or more
driven wheels. When a regenerative brake is applied, energy
flows from the wheels to operate the electric machine as a
generator that converts the energy into electricity. The
electricity is often used to charge an energy storage
device, such as a battery. Whether hydraulic or regenerative
brakes are applied is determined by an electronic brake
controller.</p><p num="0003">The ability to operate a motor vehicle is typically
controlled by a key-operated switch, sometimes referred to
as an ignition switch. Such switches may assume various
forms, but perhaps the most common in present motor vehicles
is a mechanical switch that is turned by a metal key. When
a proper key is used, the switch may operated from an OFF
position to additional positions, such as START, RUN (i.e.
ON), and ACCESSORY, to deliver electric power to electric
circuits and devices that perform certain functions related
to vehicle starting and operation.</p><p num="0004">Certain electric circuits need to be energised for a
brake-by-wire system to properly operate. Placing the
energisation of such circuits under the control of the
ignition switch is desirable so that they do not needlessly
drain the battery when the ignition switch is OFF. However, 
turning the ignition switch off to de-energise those
circuits may remove power from devices that when powered,
aid in reducing the pedal effort required to apply the
brakes via the master cylinder. Hence, brake pedal effort
may increase significantly when the ignition switch is
turned off.</p><p num="0005">Governmental regulation applicable to certain motor
vehicles proposes to mandate certain consistency in brake
pedal effort that is independent of whether the ignition
switch is OFF or ON. In the case of a brake system that
comprises only boosted hydraulic brakes, a vacuum reservoir
is used to provide a vacuum reserve that allows the booster
to aid the pedal effort for several brake applications after
the ignition switch is turned off to stop the engine. In
the case of certain brake-by-wire systems, the de-energisation
of associated electric circuits that occurs
when the ignition switch is turned off, precludes
continuance of the ability to aid the pedal effort that was
present when the ignition switch was on.</p><p num="0006">A preliminary novelty search developed the following
<ref type="patent">U.S. Patents: 5,139,121; 5,752,748; 5,769,509; 5,800,025;
5,834,854; and 5,923,096</ref>.</p><p num="0007"><ref type="patent">EP 0 937 622</ref> Toyota Jidosha KK, published 25 August
1999, describes an electrically controlled brake system shut
down by turn off of ignition switch with a delay time,
wherein an electric control device of the system has a
device for detecting a changeover of an ignition switch from
its on-state to its off-state, a device for detecting a
depression of a brake pedal beyond a predetermined depth,
and a device for shutting down the electrically controlled
brake system when a time count device has counted a
predetermined time duration with the brake pedal depression
detection device detecting no depression of the brake pedal
beyond the predetermined depth. </p><p num="0008">According to one aspect of the present invention there is
provided a motor vehicle comprising:
<sl><li>an electric powered brake system for braking road-engaging
wheels of the motor vehicle;</li><li>an ignition switch for turning a motor of the motor vehicle
on and off, including controlling the application of electric
power to the electric powered brake system;</li><li>and a control for maintaining application of full electric
power to the electric powered brake system when the ignition
switch is operated from ON to OFF so long as at least one
parameter of several parameters related to a respective component
of the vehicle and indicative of a need to maintain full electric
power application to the brake system continues to exist and for
discontinuing application of full electric power to the brake
system when all such parameters are indicative of lack of need to
maintain full electric power application to the brake system</li></sl>
   characterised in that the control is effective to reduce the
amount of electric power to the brake system when all such
parameters are indicative of lack of need to maintain full
electric power application to the brake system, and, at a later
time, to discontinue the application of all electric power to the
brake system provided that all such parameters have continued
until the said later time to be indicative of lack of need to
maintain full electric power application to the brake system. </p><p num="0009">Another aspect of the invention relates to a
method for use in a motor vehicle that has an electric
powered brake system for braking road-engaging wheels of the
vehicle according to claim 7.</p><p num="0010">The present invention will now be described further, by
way of example, with reference to the accompanying drawings,
in which:
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a general schematic diagram of a
representative brake-by-wire system;</li><li>Figure 2 is a flow diagram representing an example of discontinuing the application of full electric power to the brake system;
and</li><li>Figure 3 is a flow diagram representing an
embodiment of strategy in accordance with principles of the
present invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0011">Figure 1 shows a representative brake-by-wire system
10 comprising a hydraulic brake master cylinder 12 having a
plunger 14 which is adapted to be depressed by operation of
a brake pedal 16 to brake road-engaging wheels of a motor
vehicle. Braking may be accomplished either by hydraulic
brakes at individual wheels, such as 18, 20, 22, 24, or by 
regenerative braking, as determined by an electronic brake
controller 26. Hydraulic braking is applied through an ABS
unit 28. Boost for aiding hydraulic braking so as to reduce
pedal effort that would otherwise be required is derived
from a hydraulic power source 30 whose pressure is modulated
by a pressure modulation unit 32 under the control of brake
controller 26. For developing the proper modulation,
controller 26 senses brake pedal input with the use of one
or more of the following: stroke position sensor; master
cylinder pressure sensor; or any other sensor that may be
used to indicate pedal input.</p><p num="0012">Figure 1 includes a back-up hydraulic circuit path from
master cylinder 12 to ABS unit 28 through a switching valve
unit 34 that allows hydraulic brakes to alternatively be
applied directly by hydraulic pressure from master cylinder
12. The regenerative braking system does not expressly
appear in Figure 1.</p><p num="0013">The delivery of electric power for operating brake-by-wire
system 10 is controlled by the vehicle ignition switch,
not specifically shown in Figure 1. When that switch is
OFF, power is not delivered; when the switch is ON, power is
delivered. When the power is off, hydraulic power source 30
is unable to deliver the brake boost that it does when the
power is on. Hence, when the ignition switch is turned from
ON to OFF to shut down the vehicle powertrain (engine and/or
motor), brake boost is also lost.</p><p num="0014">The present invention provides continued power to
system 10, and hence continued brake boost, after the
ignition switch is turned off, based on the non-occurrence
of one or more particular events involving the vehicle.
When all such events have occurred, power is removed from
system 10 to avoid battery drain. The events are monitored
by monitoring certain parameters related to positions and/or
conditions of certain components of the vehicle.</p><p num="0015">Figure 2 shows a strategy of discontinuing the application of full electric power to the brake system.
The
strategy involves monitoring for the ignition switch to be 
operated to ON (step 50). When the ignition switch is ON
electric power is applied to system 10 (step 52).
Thereafter the strategy monitors for the ignition switch to
be operated to OFF (step 54). When the ignition switch is
OFF, a timer starts (step 56).</p><p num="0016">Power continues to be applied to system 10 based on the
non-occurrence of the following events: all vehicle wheels
not turning; brake pedal not applied; vehicle transmission
not in PARK position; parking brake applied. Hence step 60
monitors for all wheels not turning; step 62, for pedal 16
not being applied; step 64, for transmission in PARK; and
step 66 for parking brake applied. It can be seen that only
after all these events have occurred is the elapsed time on
the timer checked (step 68). If the elapsed time does not
exceed a defined minimum (X minutes, for example), steps 60,
62, 64, and 66 continue to be executed.</p><p num="0017">When the events monitored by steps 60, 62, 64, and 66
have all occurred, and the elapsed time exceeds the defined
minimum, power is removed from system 10. That concludes
the strategy. The monitored events are considered to be
indicative that there is no need for the service brakes to
be applied, and hence that it is appropriate to de-energise
system 10. Individual wheel speeds may determined by
respective wheel speed sensors; non-application of brake
pedal 12, from an associated sensor or switch; transmission
in PARK from an associated transmission, or gear selector,
switch; and parking brake applied from an associated sensor
or switch. A representative defined time for X is 10
minutes.</p><p num="0018">Figure 3 shows an embodiment of strategy that
utilises the steps as described above, but further
includes a series of steps that provide for a reduced power
sleep mode before power is completely removed from system
10. The timing step 56 does not commence until after the
events monitored by steps 60, 62, 64, and 66 have all
occurred. Power, but at a reduced level, continues to be
applied to system 10 after the monitored events have all 
occurred and the sleep mode commences. The monitored
events, and the state of the ignition switch, continue to be
monitored during the sleep mode (steps 72, 74, 76, 78, 80),
and if there is a change in any one of those events or the
ignition switch before the defined time X has elapsed, full
power is promptly re-applied to system 10, and the strategy
starts anew at step 54. It is only after there is no change
in any monitored event (steps 72, 74, 76, 78) or in the
ignition switch (step 80) after an elapsed time X, measured
in hours rather than minutes, 10 hours for example, that
power is completely disconnected from system 10. The sleep
mode may provide for more quickly powering up system 10.</p><p num="0019">From the foregoing, one can understand that the present
invention conditions the termination of brake boost at key
off. It is believed that the present invention can enhance
the effectiveness and acceptability of electrically-powered
brake-by-wire systems.</p><p num="0020">While a presently preferred embodiment has been
illustrated and described, it is to be appreciated that the
invention may be practised in various forms within the scope
of the following claims. Examples of such additional forms
include the non-use of certain events, or parameters,
already specifically mentioned above and/or the use of
certain events, or parameters, not previously mentioned
above, including occupant restraint engagement (i.e. seat
belt engagement), driver position, steering input,
accelerator pedal input, and clutch input. Furthermore,
monitoring of various events, or parameters, may occur
serially, as described above, or in parallel, or in various
serial and parallel combinations.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kraftfahrzeug, umfassend
ein elektrisch betriebenes Bremssystem zum Bremsen mit der Straße
eingreifender Räder des Kraftfahrzeugs;
einen Zündschalter zum Ein- und Ausschalten eines Motors des Kraftfahrzeugs
einschließlich des Steuerns der Anlegung von elektrischer Leistung an das elektrisch
betriebene Bremssystem;
und eine Steuerung zum Aufrechterhalten der Anlegung der vollen elektrischen
Leistung an das elektrisch betriebene Bremssystem, wenn der Zündschalter vom
eingeschalteten Zustand in den ausgeschalteten Zustand betätigt wird, so lange
als zumindest ein Parameter von mehreren Parametern, die mit einem jeweiligen
Bestandteil des Fahrzeugs in Zusammenhang stehen und einen Bedarf zur
Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der vollen elektrischen Leistung an das
Bremssystem anzeigen, weiterhin vorhanden ist, und zum Einstellen der Anlegung
der vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem, wenn alle diese
Parameter einen Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der
vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem anzeigen;dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß die Steuerung dazu wirksam ist, die Menge der
elektrischen Leistung zum Bremssystem zu verringern, wenn alle diese
Parameter einen Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der
vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem anzeigen, und, zu einer
späteren Zeit oder zu einem späteren Zeitpunkt, die Anlegung der gesamten
elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem einzustellen, sofern alle diese
Parameter bis zu dieser späteren Zeit oder diesem späteren Zeitpunkt damit
fortgefahren haben, einen Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der
Anlegung der vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem anzuzeigen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kraftfahrzeug nach Anspruch 1, wobei die Steuerung dazu wirksam ist, die
Anlegung der vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem
wiederherzustellen, falls einer dieser Parameter vor der späteren Zeit damit
aufhört, den Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der vollen
elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem anzuzeigen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kraftfahrzeug nach Anspruch 1 oder Anspruch 2, wobei die Parameter
zumindest zwei aus der Fahrzeugradgeschwindigkeit, der Stellung eines
Bremspedals zur Betätigung des Bremssystems, der Gangstellung eines Getriebes
des Fahrzeugs, und der Stellung einer Feststellbremse beinhalten.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kraftfahrzeug nach Anspruch 1 oder Anspruch 2, wobei die Parameter alle aus
der Fahrzeugradgeschwindigkeit, der Stellung eines Bremspedals zur Betätigung
des Bremssystems, der Gangstellung eines Getriebes des Fahrzeugs, und der
Stellung einer Feststellbremse beinhalten.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kraftfahrzeug nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, wobei die Steuerung
ferner eine Zeitgabefunktion ausführt, die erfüllt sein muß, bevor die Anlegung
der vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem eingestellt werden darf.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kraftfahrzeug nach Anspruch 5, wobei die Zeitgabefunktion beginnt, nachdem
der Zündschalter von EIN auf AUS betätigt wurde, und nachdem alle diese
Parameter den Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der vollen
elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem angezeigt haben.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Steuern der Anlegung von elektrischer Leistung an ein elektrisch
betriebenes Bremssystem eines Kraftfahrzeugs, umfassend ein elektrisch
betriebenes Bremssystem zum Bremsen mit der Straße eingreifender Räder des
Kraftfahrzeugs, einen Zündschalter zum Ein- und Ausschalten eines Motors des
Kraftfahrzeugs, und eine Steuerung zum Steuern der Anlegung von elektrischer
Leistung an das Bremssystem;
wobei das Verfahren das Aufrechterhalten der Anlegung der vollen elektrischen
Leistung an das elektrisch betriebene Bremssystem, wenn der Zündschalter vom
eingeschalteten Zustand in den ausgeschalteten Zustand betätigt wird, so lange
als zumindest ein Parameter von mehreren Parametern, die mit einem jeweiligen
Bestandteil des Fahrzeugs in Zusammenhang stehen und einen Bedarf zur
Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der vollen elektrischen Leistung an das
Bremssystem anzeigen, weiterhin vorhanden ist, und das Einstellen der Anlegung
der vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem, wenn alle diese
Parameter einen Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der
vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem anzeigen, umfaßt;dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß die Steuerung dazu wirksam ist, die Menge der
elektrischen Leistung zum Bremssystem zu verringern, wenn alle diese
Parameter einen Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der
vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem anzeigen, und, zu einer
späteren Zeit oder zu einem späteren Zeitpunkt, die Anlegung der gesamten
elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem einzustellen, sofern alle diese
Parameter bis zu dieser späteren Zeit oder zu diesem späteren Zeitpunkt damit
fortgefahren haben, einen Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der
Anlegung der vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem anzuzeigen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 7, wobei die Steuerung dazu wirksam ist, die
Anlegung der vollen elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem
wiederherzustellen, falls einer dieser Parameter vor der späteren Zeit damit aufhört,
den Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der vollen
elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem anzuzeigen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 7 oder Anspruch 8, wobei die Steuerung ferner eine
Zeitgabefunktion ausführt, die erfüllt sein muß, bevor die Anlegung der vollen
elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem eingestellt werden darf.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 9, wobei die Zeitgabefunktion beginnt, nachdem der
Zündschalter von EIN auf AUS betätigt wurde, und nachdem alle diese
Parameter den Mangel an Bedarf zur Aufrechterhaltung der Anlegung der vollen
elektrischen Leistung an das Bremssystem angezeigt haben.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor vehicle comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an electric powered brake system for braking road-engaging
wheels of the motor vehicle;</claim-text><claim-text>an ignition switch for turning a motor of the motor
vehicle on and off, including controlling the application of
electric power to the electric powered brake system;</claim-text><claim-text>and a control for maintaining application of full
electric power to the electric powered brake system when the
ignition switch is operated from ON to OFF so long as at
least one parameter of several parameters related to a
respective component of the vehicle and indicative of a need
to maintain full electric power application to the brake
system continues to exist and for discontinuing application
of full electric power to the brake system when all such
parameters are indicative of lack of need to maintain full
electric power application to the brake system;</claim-text></claim-text>
   characterised in that the control is effective to
reduce the amount of electric power to the brake system when
all such parameters are indicative of lack of need to
maintain full electric power application to the brake
system, and, at a later time, to discontinue the application
of all electric power to the brake system provided that all
such parameters have continued until the said later time to
be indicative of lack of need to maintain full electric
power application to the brake system.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor vehicle as claimed in Claim 1, in which
the control is effective to restore the application of full
electric power to the brake system if any of such parameters
ceases to be indicative of lack of need to maintain full
electric power application to the brake system prior to the
said later time.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor vehicle as claimed in Claim 1 or Claim 2,
in which the parameters include at least two of: vehicle
wheel speed, position of a brake pedal for operating the
brake system, gear position of a transmission of the
vehicle, and position of a parking brake of the vehicle.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor vehicle as claimed in Claim 1 or Claim 2,
in which the parameters include all of: vehicle wheel speed,
position of a brake pedal for operating the brake system,
gear position of a transmission of the vehicle, and position
of a parking brake of the vehicle.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor vehicle as claimed in any one of the
preceding claims, in which the control further executes a
timing function that must be satisfied before application of
full electric power to the brake system is allowed to be
discontinued.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A motor vehicle as claimed in Claim 5, in which
the timing function commences after the ignition switch has
been operated from ON to OFF and after all such parameters
have become indicative of lack of need to maintain full
electric power application to the brake system.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method of controlling the application of
electric power to an electric powered brake system of a
motor vehicle comprising an electric powered brake system
for braking road-engaging wheels of the motor vehicle, an
ignition switch for turning a motor of the motor vehicle on
and off, and a control for controlling the application of
electric power to the brake system;
   which method comprises maintaining application of full
electric power to the electric powered brake system when the
ignition switch is operated from ON to OFF so long as at
least one parameter of several parameters related to a
respective component of the vehicle and indicative of a need
to maintain full electric power application to the brake
system continues to exist, and discontinuing application of
full electric power to the brake system when all such
parameters are indicative of lack of need to maintain full
electric power application to the brake system;
   characterised in that the control is effective to
reduce the amount of electric power to the brake system when
all such parameters are indicative of lack of need to
maintain full electric power application to the brake
system, and, at a later time, to discontinue the application
of all electric power to the brake system provided that all
such parameters have continued until the said later time to
be indicative of lack of need to maintain full electric
power application to the brake system.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 7, in which the
control is effective to restore the application of full
electric power to the brake system if any of such parameters
ceases to be indicative of lack of need to maintain full
electric power application to the brake system prior to the
said later time.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 7 or Claim 8, in
which the control further executes a timing function that
must be satisfied before application of full electric power
to the brake system is allowed to be discontinued.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 9, in which the
timing function commences after the ignition switch has been
operated from ON to OFF and after all such parameters have
become indicative of lack of need to maintain full electric
power application to the brake system.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Véhicule à moteur comprenant : un système de freins alimenté électriquement
destiné à freiner les roues en contact avec la route du véhicule à moteur,
   un contacteur d'allumage destiné à mettre sous tension et à mettre hors circuit un
moteur du véhicule à moteur, comprenant la commande de l'application de l'alimentation
électrique au système de freins alimenté électriquement,
   et une commande destinée à maintenir l'application d'une alimentation électrique
complète au système de freins alimenté électriquement lorsque le contacteur d'allumage
est actionné de la position Fermé ou Actif à la position Ouvert ou Inactif dans la mesure
où au moins un paramètre parmi plusieurs paramètres associés à un composant respectif
du véhicule et indicatifs d'un besoin de maintenir une application d'alimentation
électrique complète au système de freins continue à exister et destinée à interrompre
l'application de la puissance électrique complète au système de freins lorsque la totalité de
ces paramètres indique une absence de besoin de maintenir une application d'alimentation
électrique complète au système de freins,
   caractérisé en ce que la commande est efficace pour réduire l'intensité du courant
électrique vers le système de freins lorsque tous ces paramètres indiquent une absence de
besoin de maintenir une application de puissance électrique complète au système de
freins, et, à un moment ultérieur, d'interrompre l'application de toute l'alimentation
électrique vers le système de freins à condition que tous ces paramètres jusqu'audit instant
ultérieur se soient poursuivis pour indiquer, ou aient continué d'indiquer, une absence de
besoin de maintenir une application d'alimentation électrique complète au système de
freins.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Véhicule à moteur selon la revendication 1, dans lequel la commande est
efficace pour restaurer l'application de l'alimentation électrique complète au système de
freins si l'un quelconque de ces paramètres cesse d'indiquer l'absence de besoin de
maintenir une application d'alimentation électrique complète au système de freins avant
ledit instant ultérieur.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Véhicule à moteur selon la revendication 1 ou la revendication 2, dans lequel
les paramètres comprennent au moins deux éléments parmi la vitesse de roue du véhicule,
la position d'une pédale de frein destinée à actionner le système de freins, une position de
rapport d'une transmission du véhicule, et d'une position d'un frein de stationnement du
véhicule.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Véhicule à moteur selon la revendication 1 ou la revendication 2, dans lequel
les paramètres comprennent la totalité de la vitesse de roue du véhicule, de la position
d'une pédale de frein destinée à actionner le système de freins, d'une position de rapport
d'une transmission de véhicule et d'une position d'un frein de stationnement du véhicule.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Véhicule à moteur selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans
lequel la commande exécute en outre une fonction de temporisation qui doit être satisfaite
avant qu'il ne soit permis que l'application de l'alimentation électrique complète au
système de freins soit interrompue.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Véhicule à moteur selon la revendication 5, dans lequel la fonction de
temporisation commence après que le contacteur d'allumage a été actionné depuis la
position Fermé à la position Ouvert et après que tous ces paramètres soient devenus
indicatifs d'une absence de besoin de maintenir une application d'alimentation électrique
complète au système de freins.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de commande de l'application de la puissance électrique à un système
de freins alimenté électriquement d'un véhicule à moteur comprenant un système de freins
alimenté électriquement destiné à freiner les roues du véhicule à moteur qui sont en
contact avec la route, un contacteur d'allumage destiné à mettre sous tension et à mettre
hors circuit un moteur du véhicule à moteur, et une commande destinée à commander
l'application d'une alimentation électrique au système de freins,
   lequel procédé comprend le maintien de l'application de l'alimentation électrique
complète au système de freins alimenté électriquement lorsque le contacteur d'allumage
est actionné depuis la position Fermé ou Actif à la position Ouvert ou Désactivé dans la
mesure où au moins un paramètre parmi plusieurs paramètres associés à un composant
respectif du véhicule et indique un besoin de maintenir une application d'alimentation
électrique complète au système de freins continue d'exister, et l'interruption de
l'application de l'alimentation électrique complète au système de freins lorsque tous ces
paramètres indiquent l'absence de besoin de maintenir une application d'alimentation
électrique complète au système de freins,
   caractérisé en ce que la commande est efficace pour réduire l'intensité de courant
électrique vers le système de freins lorsque la totalité de ces paramètres indiquent
l'absence de besoin de maintenir une application d'alimentation électrique complète au
système de freins, et, à un instant ultérieur, pour interrompre l'application de toute
l'alimentation électrique du système de freins à condition que tous ces paramètres,
jusqu'audit instant ultérieur, se soient poursuivis pour indiquer, ou aient continué
d'indiquer, l'absence de besoin de maintenir l'application d'alimentation électrique
complète au système de freins.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 7, dans lequel la commande est efficace pour
restaurer l'application de l'alimentation électrique complète au système de freins si l'un
quelconque de ces paramètres cesse d'indiquer l'absence de besoin de maintenir
l'application d'alimentation électrique complète au système de freins avant ledit instant
ultérieur.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 7 ou la revendication 8, dans lequel la
commande exécute en outre une fonction de temporisation qui doit être satisfaite avant
que l'application de l'alimentation électrique complète au système de freins soit autorisée
à être interrompue.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 9, dans lequel la fonction de temporisation
commence après que le contacteur d'allumage a été actionné depuis la position Fermé à la
position Ouvert et après que tous ces paramètres en soient venus à indiquer l'absence de
besoin de maintenir une application d'alimentation électrique complète au système de
freins.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20061018"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060810</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20060714"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RAP2" date="20060517"><legal-event-body><event-title>PATENT OWNER REASSIGNMENT (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Owner name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FORD GLOBAL TECHNOLOGIES, LLC.</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20051215"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60114682</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20051215</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20051109"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20051109"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RAP1" date="20051019"><legal-event-body><event-title>APPLICANT REASSIGNMENT (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Owner name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FORD GLOBAL TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040630"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040513</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20020605"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE FR GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20020502"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020225</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010912"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010912"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>