<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1134471-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1134471" kind="B1" date="20040512"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23241560" ucid="EP-1134471-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1134471</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20040512</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01106551-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01106551</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010315</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000075437-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000075437</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000317</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new" /><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F16K  31/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F16K  31/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">F16K31/06B4B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Elektromagnet für einen Durchflussregelschieber</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Electromagnetic driving device for a fluid control valve</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Tiroir électromagnétique</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>DENSO CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>DENSO CORPORATION</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>WATANABE MITSUHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>TACHIBANA SEIJI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAKANE HIROYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KAMIYA YOSHITAKA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SUDA NAOYA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>TACHIBANA, SEIJI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>WATANABE, MITSUHIRO</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAKANE, HIROYUKI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KAMIYA, YOSHITAKA</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SUDA, NAOYA</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>TACHIBANA, SEIJI</last-name><address><street>c/o Denso Corporation, 1-1, Showa-cho</street><city>Kariya-city, Aichi-pref., 448-8661</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>NAKANE, HIROYUKI</last-name><address><street>c/o Denso Corporation, 1-1, Showa-cho</street><city>Kariya-city, Aichi-pref., 448-8661</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>WATANABE, MITSUHIRO</last-name><address><street>c/o Denso Corporation, 1-1, Showa-cho</street><city>Kariya-city, Aichi-pref., 448-8661</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KAMIYA, YOSHITAKA</last-name><address><street>c/o Denso Corporation, 1-1, Showa-cho</street><city>Kariya-city, Aichi-pref., 448-8661</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>SUDA, NAOYA</last-name><address><street>c/o Denso Corporation, 1-1, Showa-cho</street><city>Kariya-city, Aichi-pref., 448-8661</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Denso Corporation</last-name><address><street>1-1, Showa-cho</street><city>Kariya-city, Aichi-pref., 448-8661</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Leson, Thomas Johannes Alois, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Tiedtke-Bühling-Kinne &amp;amp; Partner GbR, TBK-Patent, Bavariaring 4</street><city>80336 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>In an electromagnetic driving device, a fixing core (13) has a housing portion (14), in which a plunger (17) is housed to reciprocatingly move, and an attracting portion (16) toward which the plunger is attracted upon energizing a coil (20). The housing portion is provided with a ring portion (15), which is formed by machining an outer circumference wall thereof and whose thickness is thinner than that of a part of the housing portion adjacent to the ring portion to an extent that mechanical strength of the housing portion is not damaged practically. The ring portion is provided with a plurality of through-holes (15a) penetrating radially the wall thereof. Amagnetic flux area of the ring portion is limited due to the thin wall and the through-holes so that magnetic resistance is enlarged. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">In an electromagnetic driving device, a fixing core
(13) has a housing portion (14), in which a plunger (17)
is housed to reciprocatingly move, and an attracting portion
(16) toward which the plunger is attracted upon energizing
a coil (20). The housing portion is provided with a ring
portion (15), which is formed by machining an outer
circumference wall thereof and whose thickness is thinner
than that of a part of the housing portion adjacent to the
ring portion to an extent that mechanical strength of the
housing portion is not damaged practically. The ring
portion is provided with a plurality of through-holes (15a)
penetrating radially the wall thereof. Amagnetic flux area
of the ring portion is limited due to the thin wall and
the through-holes so that magnetic resistance is enlarged.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1134625-A1-00000001" he="120" wi="54" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to an electromagnetic
driving device according to the preamble claim 1
and a method of
manufacturing the electromagnetic driving device according
to the preambles of claims 4 and 5.</p><p num="0002">In a conventional electromagnetic driving device
having a fixing core in which a housing portion receiving
a movable element and an attracting portion attracting the
movable element are formed with separate pieces, axial
centers of the housing portion and the attracting portion
are likely to be offset due to their assembly errors.
Therefore, not to disturb a reciprocal movement of the
movable element even if the axial centers of the housing
and attracting portions are offset to a certain extent,
radial air gaps between the housing portion and the movable
element and between the attracting portion and the movable
element are larger by an offset amount of the axial centers
thereof. Since larger air gap causes a reduction of
attracting force, a more coil winding turn is required to
secure a predetermined attracting force. Increasing the
coil winding turn makes a body of the electromagnetic driving
device larger. </p><p num="0003">To eliminate the offset of the axial centers of the
housing and attracting portions, as disclosed in
<ref type="patent">JP-A-11-500509</ref> and <ref type="patent">JP-A-7-189852</ref>, is known an
electromagnetic driving device in which the housing and
attracting portions are integrally formed, for example,
by machining. However, when the housing and attracting
portions are integrally formed, magnetic flux generated
upon energizing the coil are likely to pass directly between
the housing portion and the attracting portion, not through
the moving element so that the attracting force is limited.</p><p num="0004">A valve disclosed in <ref type="patent">JP-A-11-500509</ref> is provided
between the housing and attracting portions with a thin
thickness throttling portion having a narrow area through
which magnetic flux pass for enlarging magnetic resistance.
The throttling portion serves to limit the magnetic flux
passing directly between the housing portion and the
attracting portion so that the attracting force of the
movable element may be secured.</p><p num="0005">To limit the magnetic flux passing directly between
the housing and attracting portions to an extent that the
attracting force is sufficiently secured, the thickness
of the throttling portion has to be remarkably thin. Thinner
the thickness, a mechanical strength of the throttle portion
is weaker so that the housing portion may be damaged.</p><p num="0006">Further, an electromagnetic actuator disclosed in
<ref type="patent">JP-A-7-189852</ref> is provided in a part of the housing portion
with a non-magnetic material portion for enlarging the 
magnetic resistance. In this case, if the non-magnetic
material portion is formed by diffusing the non-magnetic
material, for example, by laser radiation, a surface of
the non-magnetic material portion tends to be rough. As
the non-magnetic portion in the actuator disclosed in
<ref type="patent">JP-A-7-189852</ref> is not in slidable contact with the moving
element, the movement of the movable element is not disturbed
even if an inner circumferential wall of the non-magnetic
portion is rough. However, in the electromagnetic actuator
in which the non-magnetic material portion comes in slidable
contact with the movable element, the rough surface of the
non-magnetic portion causes likely to disturb a smooth
movement of the movable element. </p><p num="0007"><ref type="patent">DE-A1-197 27 414</ref> discloses a generic electromagnetic driving
device comprising a coil; a movable element; and a fixing
element having a housing portion in which the movable element is
housed to reciprocatingly move, and an attracting portion toward
which the movable element is attracted by magnetic flux to be
generated upon energizing the coil, wherein the housing portion
is provided at a position thereof radially opposed to the
movable element with a ring portion connected with the
attracting portion so that the housing portion and the
attracting portion are formed into an integral piece of a
magnetic material.</p><p num="0008">A similar electromagnetic driving device is disclosed in <ref type="patent">US-2
853 659</ref>.</p><p num="0009">It is the object of the present invention, to provide an
electromagnetic driving device that is compact and generates a
large attracting force without damaging a housing portion of a
fixing core, and also a method of manufacturing an
electromagnetic driving device.</p><p num="0010">The object is solved by the electromagnetic driving device
having the features of claim 1 as well as by the methods of
manufacturing an electromagnetic driving device having the
features of the new claims 4 and 5, respectively. </p><p num="0011">As the housing and attracting portions are integrally
formed and worked continuously by machining. Accordingly,
the offset of the axial centers of the housing and attracting
portions may be eliminated. This will result in minimizing
radial air gaps between the housing portion and the movable
element and between the attracting portion and the movable
element so that an attracting force between the attracting
portion and the movable element may be increased.</p><p num="0012">Further, one or more through-holes are formed to
enlarge magnetic resistance of the ring portion so that
magnetic flux flowing directly between the integrally formed
housing and attracting portions is limited. The magnetic
resistance may be increased by adjusting a number and each
diameter of the through-holes without reducing a thickness
of the ring portion. Therefore, a mechanical strength of
the housing portion is assured and the housing portion is
prevented from being damaged. </p><p num="0013">The thickness of the wall of the
ring portion is thinner that that of the housing portion
axially adjacent thereto to an extent that a mechanical
strength of the ring portion is not damaged practically.
This will contribute to enlarge magnetic resistance of the
ring portion, too.</p><p num="0014">As a method of manufacturing the magnetic driving
device, after forming one or more 
through-holes radially penetrating a wall of the ring
portion, resin molding is executed on an outer
circumferential surface of the fixing core including the
ring portion, while the through-hole is closed with a
blocking member abutting on an inner circumferential wall
of the ring portion. As a result, resin is not leaked via
the through-hole to an inside of the ring portion.</p><p num="0015">Further, it is another method that, after making a
radial thickness of the ring portion thinner than that of
a part of the housing portion axially adjacent thereto,
resin molding is executed on an outer circumferential
surface of the fixing core including the ring portion, while
the ring portion is supported by a blocking member abutting
on an inner circumferential wall of the ring portion so
that the ring portion is prevented from deforming due to
resin pressure.</p><p num="0016">Other features and advantages of the present invention
will be appreciated, as well as methods of operation and
the function of the related parts, from a study of the
following detailed description, the appended claims, and
the drawings, all of which form a part of this application.
In the drawings:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a cross sectional view showing a fluid control
valve according to a first embodiment of the present
invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is an enlarged view of a ring portion according
to the first embodiment; </li><li>Fig. 3A is a cross sectional view of a fixing core
before the fixing core is filled with resin for forming
an inner circumference spool thereon according to a
manufacturing method of the first embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 3B is a cross sectional view of a fixing core
after the fixing core is filled with resin for forming an
inner circumference spool thereon according to the
manufacturing method of the first embodiment;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a cross sectional view of a fixing core after
the fixing core is filled with resin for forming an inner
circumference spool thereon according to a first modified
manufacturing method;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a cross sectional view of a fixing core after
the fixing core is filled with resin for forming an inner
circumference spool thereon according to a second modified
manufacturing method;</li><li>Fig. 6 is a front view showing an outer wall of the
fixing core according to the second modified manufacturing
method;</li><li>Fig. 7 is an enlarged cross sectional view of a ring
portion according to a second embodiment of the present
invention;</li><li>Fig. 8 is an enlarged cross sectional view of a ring
portion according to a third embodiment of the present
invention;</li><li>Fig. 9 is an enlarged cross sectional view of a ring
portion according to a fourth embodiment of the present 
invention; and</li><li>Fig. 10 is an enlarged cross sectional view of a ring
portion according to a fifth embodiment of the present
invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0017">A plurality of preferred embodiments of the present
invention are described with reference to drawings.</p><heading>(First embodiment)</heading><p num="0018">Fig. 1 shows a fluid control valve according to a first
embodiment of the present invention.</p><p num="0019">The fluid control valve 1 is a spool type hydraulic
control valve for controlling operating oil to be supplied
to a hydraulic control apparatus of an automatic
transmission for a vehicle.</p><p num="0020">A linear solenoid 10, which serves as an
electromagnetic driving device, is composed of a cylindrical
yoke 11, an end plate 12, a fixing core 13, a plunger 17,
a shaft 18 and a coil 20. The yoke 11, the end plate 12
and the fixing core 13 constitute a fixing element and the
plunger 17 and the shaft 18 constitute a movable element.
The yoke 11, the end plate 12, the fixing core 13 and plunger
17 are made of magnetic material. The fixing core 13 is
fixed between the end plate 12 and a spool housing 31, in
which a spool 30 is slidably and reciprocatingly held, in
such a manner that both ends of the yoke 11 crimp the
respective circumferential peripheries of the spool housing
31 and the end plate 12. </p><p num="0021">The fixing core has a housing portion 14, in which
the plunger is housed so as to reciprocatingly move, and
an attracting portion 16, which generates a magnetic
attracting force for attracting the plunger 17. To prevent
the plunger 17 from being adhered to the housing portion
14, an inner circumferential surface of the housing portion
14 or an outer circumferential surface of the plunger is
coated or plated with non-magnetic material.</p><p num="0022">As shown in Fig. 2, the housing portion 14 is provided
at a position facing radially the plunger 17 with a ring
portion 15. The ring portion 15 is formed by machining in
a ring shape an outer circumferential wall of the housing
portion 14. A thickness of the ring portion 15 is thinner
than that of the housing portion 14 axially adjacent thereto
to an extent that a required mechanical strength of the
housing portion 14 is not damaged. The ring portion 15 is
provided with a plurality of radially penetrating
through-holes 15a. As the ring portion 15 is thin and has
a plurality of the through-holes 15a, an area of the ring
portion 15 through which magnetic flux pass is narrowed
and limited. The through-holes 15a are provided by laser
radiation, machining, press working or water jet working.</p><p num="0023">As shown in Fig. 1, the attracting portion 16 has an
opposing portion 16a, which is axially opposed to the plunger
17, and a taper portion 16b, which is located between the
opposing portion 16a and the ring portion 15 and whose
diameter is smaller toward the opposing portion 16a. The 
plunger 17 is provided at an end thereof on a side of the
opposing portion 16a with a taper portion 17a whose diameter
is smaller toward the attracting portion 19.</p><p num="0024">The shaft 18 is press fitted into the plunger 17 and
moves reciprocatingly together with the plunger 17. An end
of the shaft 18 abuts on an end of the spool 30.</p><p num="0025">The coil 20 is formed in a cylindrical shape by resin
molding and fixed by the yoke 11 and the fixing core 13.
When current is supplied to the coil 20 from a terminal
(not shown) connected in circuit with the coil 20, magnetic
flux flows through a magnetic circuit constituted by the
yoke 11, the plunger 17 and the fixing core 13 so that an
attracting force is generated between the attracting portion
16 of the fixing core 13 and the plunger 17. Accordingly,
the plunger 17 and the shaft 18 move downward in Fig. 1.
The downward movement of the plunger 17 in Fig. 1 is restricted
by a stopper 19.</p><p num="0026">The spool housing 31 holds the spool 30 so that the
spool 30 moves reciprocatingly therein. The spool housing
31 is provided with an input port 32, an output port 33,
a feedback port 34 and an ejecting port 35. Operating oil
is supplied and input to the input port 32 by a pump from
a tank (not shown). The operating oil is supplied to an
engaging device of an automatic trans mission (not shown)
from the output port 33. The output port 33 is in
communication with the feedback port 34 at a portion outside
the fluid control valve 1 so that a part of operating oil 
flew out from the output port 33 is introduced to the feedback
port 34. The feedback port 34 is in communication with a
feedback chamber 36. The operating oil is ejected from the
ejecting port 35 to the tank.</p><p num="0027">The spool 30 is provided in order from an opposite
side of the linear solenoid valve 10 with a large diameter
land 37, a large diameter land 38 and a small diameter land
39. A diameter of the small diameter land 39 is smaller
than that of the large diameter land 37 or 38. The spool
30 is always in contact with the shaft 18 of the linear
solenoid 10. The movement of the plunger 17 is transmitted
via the shaft 18 to the spool so that the spool 30 moves
reciprocatingly in the spool housing 31.</p><p num="0028">A spring 40, which is disposed on an opposite side
of the linear solenoid 10 and serves as biasing means, urges
the spool 30 toward the linear solenoid 10.</p><p num="0029">The feedback chamber 36 is located between the large
diameter land 38 and the small diameter land 39 to each
of which a force responsive to an outer diameter thereof
due to hydraulic oil in the feedback chamber 38 is applied.
Accordingly, the hydraulic oil in the feedback chamber 38
urges the spool 30 in an opposite direction of the linear
solenoid 10. Feedback of a part of the hydraulic oil output
by the fluid control valve 1 serves to prevent output pressure
from fluctuating due to a fluctuation of hydraulic pressure
to be supplied or input. The spool 3 0 is at rest at a position
where the biasing force of the spring 40 is balanced with 
a force of plunger 17 urging the spool 30 due to the
electromagnetic attracting force generated in the fixing
core 13 based on the current supplied to the coil and a
force which the spool 30 receives from the hydraulic oil
in the feedback chamber 36.</p><p num="0030">An amount of operating oil flowing from the input port
32 to the output port 33 depends on a seal length representing
a length by which the an inner circumferential wall 31a
of the spool housing 31 and an outer circumferential wall
of the large diameter land 38 overlap each other. As the
seal length is shorter, the amount of operating oil flowing
from the input port 32 to the output port 33 more increases.
On the contrary, as the seal length is longer, the amount
of operating oil flowing from the input port 32 to the output
port 33 more decreases. Similarly, an amount of operating
oil flowing from the output port 33 to the ejecting port
35 depends on the seal length with respect to an inner
circumferential wall 31b of the spool housing 31 and an
outer circumferential wall of the large diameter land 37.</p><p num="0031">An operation of the fluid control valve 1 is described
next.</p><heading>(1) On de-energizing the coil</heading><p num="0032">As shown in Fig. 1, when the coil 20 is not energized,
the spool 30 is at rest at a position where the biasing
force of the spring 40 is balanced with a feedback force
of the hydraulic oil. The input port 32 is in communication
with the output port and the amount of operating oil flowing 
from the input port 32 to the output port 33 more increases.
As the ejecting port 35 is closed so that hydraulic pressure
of the operating oil supplied to the automatic transmission
shows maximum.</p><heading>(2) On energizing the coil</heading><p num="0033">When the coil energized, the magnetic flux flowing
between the housing and attracting portions 14 and 16 is
limited since the ring portion 15 acts as the magnetic
resistance. Accordingly, the magnetic flux flows between
the housing portion 14 and the plunger 17 and between the
taper portions 17a of the plunger 17 and 16b of the attracting
portion 16. The magnetic flux passing directly between the
housing and the attracting portions 14 and 16 not via the
plunger 17 but via the ring portion 15 does not exert a
force of attracting the plunger 17. As the magnetic flux
is prevented from flowing directly between the housing and
the attracting force 14 and 16, the force of attracting
the plunger 17 more increases.</p><p num="0034">Upon energizing the coil 20, the plunger 17 is attracted
to the attracting portion 16 against the biasing force of
the spring 40 so that the spool 30 moves downward in Fig.
1. As the seal length with respect to the inner
circumferential wall 31a and the larger diameter land 38
becomes longer and the inner circumferential wall 31b and
the large diameter land 37 becomes shorter, the amount of
operating oil flowing from the input port 32 to the output
port 33 more decreases and the amount of operating oil flowing 
from the output port 33 to the ejecting port 35 more increases.
Accordingly, hydraulic pressure of the operating oil flew
out from the output port 33 decreases.</p><p num="0035">On the contrary, when the spool 30 is moved toward
the linear solenoid 10, the seal length with respect to
the inner circumferential wall 31a and the larger diameter
land 38 becomes shorter and the inner circumferential wall
31b and the large diameter land 37 becomes longer so that
the amount of operating oil flowing from the input port
32 to the output port 33 more increases and the amount of
operating oil flowing from the output port 33 to the ejecting
port 35 more decreases. Accordingly, hydraulic pressure
of the operating oil flew out from the output port 33
increases.</p><p num="0036">In the fluid control valve 1, the linear solenoid 10
is operative to adjust a force of urging the spool 30 toward
the linear solenoid 10 by controlling current to be supplied
to the coil 20 so that hydraulic pressure of operating oil
flew out from the output port 33 is adjusted. As an amount
of current supplied to the coil 20 increases, the
electromagnetic attracting force of the attracting portion
16 increases in proportion to the current amount so that
an urging force of the shaft 18 for moving the spool 30
in an opposite direction to the linear solenoid 10. The
spool 30 comes at rest at a position where the force acting
from the plunger 17 to the spool 30 due to the electromagnetic
attracting force and the force of urging the spool 30 in 
an opposite direction to the linear solenoid 10 due to the
hydraulic pressure of feed backed operating oil are balanced
with the biasing force of the spring 40. Accordingly, the
hydraulic pressure of operating oil flew out from the output
port 33 decreases in proportion to the amount of current
supplied to the coil 20.</p><p num="0037">Next, a method of manufacturing an inner circumference
spool 21, on which the coil 20 is wound, around the fixing
core 13 of the first embodiment.
<sl><li>(1) As shown in Fig. 3A, the thin thickness ring portion
15 is provided with the through-holes 15a. A pin 100 is
inserted into an inner circumference of the housing portion
14 to constitute a blocking member for closing openings
of the through-holes 15a.</li><li>(2) An outer circumference of the fixing core 13 is filled
with resin so that the inner circumference spool on which
the coil 20 is wound is formed.</li><li>(3) After the resin has hardened, the pin 100 is pulled
out, as shown in Fig. 3B.</li><li>(4) After winding the coil 20 on the inner circumference
spool 21, outer circumference of the coil 20 is further
filled with resin.</li></sl></p><heading>(Modification 1)</heading><p num="0038">A first modified method of manufacturing the inner
circumference spool 21 is described with reference to Fig.
4. Instead of inserting the pin 100 into the housing portion
14, operating oil 111 is supplied to an inside of a cylindrical 
cap member 110 and a cylindrical side wall of the cylindrical
cap member is held inside the housing portion 14 by hydraulic
pressure of operating oil 111 so that a resin leakage from
the through-holes 15a is prevented. The cylindrical cap
member 110 and the operating oil 111 constitute the blocking
member.</p><heading>(Modification 2)</heading><p num="0039">A second modified method of manufacturing the inner
circumference spool 21 is described with reference to Figs.
5 and 6.
<sl><li>(1) A pin 120 is inserted into the housing portion 14. An
outer diameter of the pin 120 is nearly equal to or slightly
smaller than an inner diameter of the housing portion 14.
The pin 120 is provided with a slit 121 extending
diametrically and axially and a tapered surface spreading
partly from the slit 121 on an opening side of the slit
121. The ring portion 15 is provided at positions facing
openings of the slit 121 opened radially with the
through-holes 15a, as shown in Fig. 6.</li><li>(2) A wedge rod 125 is pushed against the taper surface
122 of the pin 120 from a side opposite to an inserting
side of the pin 120. The pin 120 and the wedge rod 125
constitute the blocking member. The wedge rod 125 is
provided at an end thereof with a taper surface 126 whose
inclination angle is approximately similar to that of tha
taper surface 122 of the pin 120. As the taper surface 126
of the wedge rod 125 is pushed against the taper surface 
122 of the pin 120, the pin 120 receives force acting in
a direction of pushing and spreading radially outwardly
the pin 120 so that a leakage of resin from the through-holes
15a is prevented.</li></sl></p><p num="0040">According to the method of manufacturing the inner
circumference spool 21 mentioned above, the blocking member
serves to close the through-holes 15a to prevent the resin
for forming the inner circumference spool 21 from being
leaked from the trough-holes 15. Accordingly, the resin
never disturbs a reciprocal movement of the plunger 17.
Further, the blocking member not only closes the
through-holes 15a but also supports the thin thickness ring
portion 15 from an inside thereof so that the ring portion
15 is prevented from deforming due to pressure to be generated
when the resin hardens.</p><p num="0041">The method of manufacturing the inner circumference
spool 21 mentioned above is applicable not only to the first
embodiment in which the through-holes 15a are formed in
the ring portion 15 but also any of second to fifth embodiments
hereinafter.</p><heading>(Second embodiment)</heading><p num="0042">A second embodiment of the present invention is
described with reference to Fig. 7. Substantially same
structure and portions as the first embodiment are affixed
with the same reference numbers thereof.</p><p num="0043">According to the second embodiment, an outer
circumferential wall of the ring portion 15 has a plurality 
of recesses 50. The recesses 50 are formed by laser radiation,
form rolling or press working. The recesses 50 on the thin
thickness ring portion 15 serves to reduce a magnetic circuit
area and to enlarge a magnetic resistance.</p><heading>(Third embodiment)</heading><p num="0044">A third embodiment of the present invention is
described with reference to Fig. 8. Substantially same
structure and portions as the first embodiment are affixed
with the same reference numbers thereof.

According to the third embodiment, an outer circumferential
wall of the ring portion 15 has a plurality of ring shaped
grooves 55. The ring shaped grooves 55 are formed by laser
radiation, machining or form rolling. The ring shaped
grooves 55 on the thin thickness ring portion 15 serves
to reduce a magnetic circuit area and to enlarge a magnetic
resistance.</p><p num="0045">In the first to third embodiments mentioned above,
instead of forming the thin thickness ring portion 15 by
machining the outer circumference thereof, the thin
thickness ring portion 15 may be formed by machining an
inner circumference thereof. Further, in the second or
third embodiment, instead of forming the recesses 50 or
the ring shaped grooves 55 on the outer circumference of
the ring portion 15, the recesses 50 or the ring shaped
grooves 55 are formed on an inner circumference or on both
of inner and outer circumferences of the ring portion 15.</p><heading>(Fourth embodiment)</heading><p num="0046">A fourth embodiment of the present invention is
described with reference to Fig. 9. Substantially same
structure and portions as the first embodiment are affixed
with the same reference numbers thereof. A non-magnetic
diffusion layer 60 is provided in the thin thickness ring
portion 15 by diffusing non-magnetic material to an outer
circumference thereof to enlarge the magnetic resistance
of the ring portion 15. As the non-magnetic material is
not diffused to an inner circumference of the ring portion
15, an inner circumferential surface of the ring portion
15, which is in slidable contact with the movable element,
is prevented from becoming rough. Accordingly, the movable
element smoothly moves in the ring portion 15. The following
methods may be contemplated for diffusing the non-magnetic
material to the ring portion 15.
<sl><li>(1) To diffuse non-magnetic material in a gas environment
by laser radiation.</li><li>(2) To diffuse solid-state non-magnetic material by laser
radiation.</li><li>(3) To diffuse non-magnetic material in a gas environment
by shot blast.</li><li>(4) To diffuse non-magnetic material by melting injection.</li></sl></p><heading>(Fifth embodiment)</heading><p num="0047">A fourth embodiment of the present invention is
described with reference to Fig. 10. Substantially same
structure and portions as the first embodiment are affixed
with the same reference numbers thereof. According to the 
fifth embodiment, a non-magnetic portion 65 is formed to
enlarge the magnetic resistance in the thin thickness ring
shaped portion 15 by inducing strains in metallographical
structure of the ring portion 15. The following methods
may be contemplated for inducing the strains in
metallographical structure of the ring portion 15.
<sl><li>(1) To induce strains based on work hardening by form
rolling.</li><li>(2) To induce strains based on work hardening by press
working.</li><li>(3) To induce strains based on resin pressure to be
generated when the coil is fixed by resin.</li><li>(4) To induce strains based on heat by laser radiation.</li></sl></p><p num="0048">According to the embodiments mentioned above, as the
housing and attracting portions 14 and 16 of the fixing
core are integrally provided, the radial air gap between
the plunger 17 and the fixing element is small to a minimum
extent. Further, as the thin thickness ring portion 15 has
means for enlarging magnetic resistance as mentioned in
the above embodiments, magnetic flux flowing directly
between the housing and attracting portions 14 and 16 is
limited. Accordingly, the attracting force to the plunger
increases without enlarging the body of the electromagnetic
driving device or the fluid control valve. Furthermore,
even if the thickness of the ring portion is thicker, compared
with that of the conventional ring portion by which the
magnetic resistance is enlarged, the ring portion of the 
present invention can secure the same magnetic resistance
as the conventional ring portion. Moreover, the thicker
ring portion serves to more increase the mechanical strength
of the ring portion, which prevents the housing portion
from being damaged.</p><p num="0049">In the embodiments mentioned above, instead of making
the thickness of the ring portion 15, the ring portion 15
may be provided without forming the thin portion thereof
by adjusting (1) a total number and each diameter of the
through-holes, (2) a total number, each depth and each
largeness of the recesses 50, (3) a total number, each width
and each depth of the ring shaped grooves 55, (4) depth
by which the non-magnetic material is diffused or (5)
largeness of the strains.</p><p num="0050">The electromagnetic driving device of the present
invention is applicable not only to the electromagnetic
driving apparatus having the spool type hydraulic control
valve but also to any other type of electromagnetic driving
apparatus having fluid control valve or device in which
the attracting force to the movable element is larger without
enlarging the body thereof.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elektromagnetische Antriebsvorrichtung mit:
<claim-text><claim-text>einer Spule (20);</claim-text><claim-text>einem beweglichen Element (17, 18); und</claim-text><claim-text>einem Befestigungselement (11, 12, 13), das einen
Aufnahmeabschnitt (14) hat, in dem das bewegliche Element
aufgenommen ist, so dass es sich wechselseitig bewegt, und das
einen Anziehabschnitt (16) hat, in dessen Richtung das
bewegliche Element durch Magnetfluss angezogen wird, der nach
dem Erregen der Spule erzeugt wird, wobei der
Aufnahmeabschnitt an einer Stelle davon, die sich radial
gegenüberliegend zu dem beweglichen Element befindet, mit
einem Ringabschnitt (15) versehen ist, der mit dem
Anziehabschnitt verbunden ist, so dass der Aufnahmeabschnitt
und der Anziehabschnitt in einem einstückigen Teil aus einem
magnetischen Material ausgebildet sind, dadurch
gekennzeichnet, dass</claim-text><claim-text>der Ringabschnitt mit zumindest einem Durchgangsloch (15a)
versehen ist, das dessen Wand radial durchdringt, um das
Strömen des Magnetflusses zwischen dem Aufnahmeabschnitt und
dem Anziehabschnitt zu beschränken und den Magnetfluss über
das bewegliche Element zwischen dem Aufnahmeabschnitt und dem
Anziehabschnitt strömen zu lassen.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elektromagnetische Antriebsvorrichtung gemäß Anspruch 1,
wobei der Ringabschnitt in der Radialrichtung dünner als der
sonstige Abschnitt von dem Aufnahmeabschnitt und dem
Anziehabschnitt ist und das Durchgangsloch an einer Vielzahl
von Stellen in dem Ringabschnitt vorgesehen ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elektromagnetische Antriebsvorrichtung gemäß Anspruch 1
oder 2, ferner mit:
<claim-text><claim-text>einer zylindrischen Aufnahme (31), die eine Vielzahl von
Öffnungen (32, 33, 34, 35) hat, durch die ein Fluid strömt;</claim-text><claim-text>einem Spulenkern (30), der in der zylindrischen Aufnahme
zusammen mit dem beweglichen Element wechselseitig bewegt
wird, um Mengen des durch die entsprechenden Öffnungen
strömenden Fluids einzustellen; und</claim-text><claim-text>Vorspanneinrichtungen (40) zum Vorspannen des
Spulenkörpers in einer Richtung, die zu einer Richtung, in der
das wirkliche Element zu dem Anziehabschnitt angezogen wird,
entgegengesetzt ist.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Herstellen einer elektromagnetischen
Antriebsvorrichtung, die Folgendes hat:
<claim-text><claim-text>eine Spule (20), die um einen Spulenkörper (21) gewunden
ist,</claim-text><claim-text>ein bewegliches Element (17, 18) und</claim-text><claim-text>ein Befestigungselement (11, 12, 13), das einen
Aufnahmeabschnitt (14) hat, in dem das bewegliche Element
aufgenommen ist, so dass es sich wechselseitig bewegt, und</claim-text><claim-text>einen Anziehabschnitt (16), zu dem das bewegliche Element
durch Magnetfluss, der nach Erregung der Spule erzeugt wird,
angezogen wird, wobei der Aufnahmeabschnitt an einer Stelle,
die dem beweglichen Element radial gegenüber liegt, mit einem
Ringabschnitt (15) versehen ist, und wobei der
Aufnahmeabschnitt und der Anziehabschnitt einstückig
ausgebildet sind, wobei das Verfahren die folgenden Schritte
aufweist:
<claim-text><claim-text>Ausbilden von zumindest einem Durchgangsloch (15a), das
eine Wand des Ringabschnitts radial durchdringt; und</claim-text><claim-text>Ausführen von Kunstharzformgebung an einer
Außenumfangsfläche des Befestigungskerns einschließlich des
Ringabschnitts, während das Durchgangsloch mit einem
Blockierelement (100, 110&amp;111, 120&amp;125) geschlossen ist,
welches an einer Innenumfangsfläche des Ringabschnitts
anliegt, so dass über das Durchgangsloch kein Kunstharz zu
einer Innenseite des Ringabschnitts leckt.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Herstellen einer elektromagnetischen
Antriebsvorrichtung, die Folgendes hat:
<claim-text><claim-text>eine Spule (20), die um einen Spulenkörper (21) gewunden
ist, ein bewegliches Element (17, 18) und ein</claim-text><claim-text>Befestigungselement (11, 12, 13), das einen
Aufnahmeabschnitt (14) hat, in dem das bewegliche Element
aufgenommen ist, so dass es sich wechselseitig bewegt, und</claim-text><claim-text>einen Anziehabschnitt (16), zu dem das bewegliche Element
durch Magnetfluss, der durch Erregung der Spule erzeugt wird,
angezogen wird, wobei der Aufnahmeabschnitt an einer Stelle,
die dem beweglichen Element radial gegenüberliegt, mit dem
Ringabschnitt (15) versehen ist, und wobei der
Aufnahmeabschnitt und der Anziehabschnitt einstückig
ausgebildet sind, wobei das Verfahren die folgenden Schritte
aufweist:
<claim-text><claim-text>Ausführen der radialen Dicke des Ringabschnitts dünner als
die eines Teils des Aufnahmeabschnitts, der dazu axial
benachbart ist; und</claim-text><claim-text>Durchführen von Kunstharzformgebung an einer
Außenumfangsfläche des Befestigungskerns einschließlich des
Ringabschnitts, während der Ringabschnitt durch ein
Blockierelement (100, 110&amp;111, 120&amp;125) gestützt ist, welches
an einer Innenumfangswand des Ringabschnitts anliegt, so dass
verhindert wird, dass sich der Ringabschnitt aufgrund des
Kunstharzdrucks verformt.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Herstellen einer elektromagnetischen
Antriebsvorrichtung gemäß Anspruch 5, das ferner folgende
Schritte aufweist:
<claim-text><claim-text>Ausbilden zumindest eines Durchgangslochs (15a), das eine
Wand des Ringabschnitts radial durchdringt, wobei das
Blockierelement das Durchgangsloch so schließt, dass über das
Durchgangsloch kein Kunstharz zu einer Innenseite des
Ringabschnitts leckt.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An electromagnetic driving device comprising;
<claim-text><claim-text>a coil (20);</claim-text><claim-text>a movable element (17,18); and</claim-text><claim-text>a fiximg element (11,12,13) having a housing portion
(14) in which the movable element is housed to
reciprocatingly move, and an attracting portion (16) toward
which the movable element is attracted by magnetic flux to
be generated upon energizing the coil, wherein the housing
portion is provided at a position thereof radially opposed
to the movable element with a ring portion (15) connected
with the attracting portion so that the housing portion and
the attracting portion are formed into an integral piece of
a magnetic material,</claim-text></claim-text>characterized in that
the ring portion is provided with at least one through-hole
(15a) radially penetrating a wall thereof to restrict flow
of the magnetic flux between the housing portion and the
attracting portion and cause the magnetic flux to flow via
the movable element between the housing portion and the
attracting portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An electromagnetic driving device according to claim 1,
wherein the ring portion is thinner than the other portion
of the housing portion and the attracting portion in the
radial direction, and the through-hole is provided at a
plurality of locations in the ring portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An electromagnetic driving device according to claim 1
or 2,further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a cylindrical housing (31) having a plurality of ports
(32,33,34,35) through which fluid flows;</claim-text><claim-text>a spool (30) being reciprocatingly moved in the
cylindrical housing along with the movable element for
adjusting amounts of fluid flowing through the respective
ports; and</claim-text><claim-text>biasing means (40) for urging the spool in an opposite
direction to a direction in which the movable element is
attracted to the attracting portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method of manufacturing an electromagnetic driving
device having a coil (20) wound on a spool (21), a movable
element (17,18), and a fixing element (11,12,13) having a
housing portion (14) in which the movable element is housed
to reciprocatingly move, and an attracting portion (16)
toward which the movable element is attracted by magnetic
flux to be generated upon energizing the coil, wherein the
housing portion is provided at a position radially opposed
to the movable element with a ring portion (15), and the
housing portion and the attracting portion are integrally
formed, comprising steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>forming at least one of through-holes (15a) radially
penetrating a wall of the ring portion; and</claim-text><claim-text>executing resin molding on an outer circumferential surface
of the fixing core including the ring portion, while the
through-hole is closed with a blocking member (100,
110&amp;111, 120&amp;125) abutting on an inner circumferential wall
of the ring portion so that resin is not leaked via the
through-hole to an inside of the ring portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method of manufacturing an electromagnetic driving
device having a coil (20) wound on a spool (21), a movable
element (17,18), and a fixing element (11,12,13) having a
housing portion (14) in which the movable element is housed
to reciprocatingly move, and an attracting portion (16)
toward which the movable element is attracted by magnetic
flux to be generated upon energizing the coil, wherein the
housing portion is provided at a position radially opposed
to the movable element with a ring portion (15), and the
housing portion and the attracting portion are integrally
formed, comprising steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>making a radial thickness of the ring portion thinner
than that of a part of the housing portion axially adjacent
thereto; and</claim-text><claim-text>executing resin molding on an outer circumferential
surface of the fixing core including the ring portion,
while the ring portion is supported by a blocking member.
(100,110&amp;111,120&amp;125) abutting on an inner circumferential
wall of the ring portion so that the ring portion is
prevented from deforming due to resin pressure.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method of manufacturing an electromagnetic driving
device according to claim 5, further comprising steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>forming at least one of through-holes (15a) radially
penetrating a wall of the ring portion, wherein the
blocking member closes the through-hole so that resin is
not leaked via the through-hole to an inside of the ring
portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'entraínement électromagnétique, comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>une bobine (20) ;</claim-text><claim-text>un élément mobile (17, 18) ; et</claim-text><claim-text>un élément de fixation (11, 12, 13) ayant un boítier (14) dans lequel
l'élément mobile est logé pour aller et venir, et un moyen d'attraction (16) vers lequel
l'élément mobile est attiré par un flux magnétique destiné à être généré au moment de
l'excitation de la bobine, le logement comportant, à un emplacement de celui-ci
opposé de manière radiale par rapport à l'élément mobile, une partie annulaire (15)
reliée au moyen d'attraction de façon que le boítier et le moyen d'attraction forment
un morceau de matière magnétique d'une seule pièce,</claim-text></claim-text>caractérisé en ce que
la partie annulaire comporte au moins un trou traversant (15a) qui pénètre de manière
radiale dans une paroi de celle-ci pour limiter le passage du flux magnétique entre le
boítier et le moyen d'attraction et faire passer le flux magnétique par l'élément mobile
entre le boítier et le moyen d'attraction.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'entraínement électromagnétique selon la revendication 1,
dans lequel la partie annulaire est plus mince que l'autre partie du boítier et que le
moyen d'attraction dans la direction radiale, et le trou traversant est ménagé en
plusieurs endroits dans la partie annulaire.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif d'entraínement électromagnétique selon la revendication 1 ou
2, comprenant en outre :
<claim-text><claim-text>un logement cylindrique (31) comportant une pluralité d'orifices (32, 33, 34,
35) par lesquels passe un fluide ;</claim-text><claim-text>un tiroir (30) allant et venant dans le logement cylindrique avec l'élément
mobile pour régler le débit du fluide passant par les orifices respectifs ; et</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen de sollicitation (40) pour pousser le tiroir dans une direction
opposée à une direction dans laquelle l'élément mobile est attiré vers le moyen
d'attraction.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de fabrication d'un dispositif d'entraínement électromagnétique
comprenant une bobine (20) enroulée sur un mandrin (21), un élément mobile (17,
18) et un élément de fixation (11, 12, 13) ayant un moyen formant boítier (14) dans
lequel l'élément mobile est logé pour aller et venir, et un moyen d'attraction (16) vers
lequel l'élément mobile est attiré par un flux magnétique destiné à être généré au
moment de l'excitation de la bobine, le moyen formant boítier étant pourvu, à un
emplacement radialement opposé par rapport à l'élément mobile, d'une partie
annulaire (15), et le moyen formant boítier et le moyen d'attraction faisant corps l'un
avec l'autre, comprenant les étapes consistant à :
<claim-text><claim-text>former au moins un des trous traversants (15a) pénétrant de manière radiale
dans une paroi de la partie annulaire ; et</claim-text><claim-text>réaliser un moulage de résine sur une surface périphérique extérieure du
noyau de fixation comportant la partie annulaire, tandis que le trou traversant est
fermé par un élément d'obturation (100, 110 et 111, 120 et 125) butant contre une
paroi périphérique intérieure de la partie annulaire de façon que de la résine ne
s'échappe pas, par le trou traversant, à l'intérieur de la partie annulaire.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de fabrication d'un dispositif d'entraínement électromagnétique
comprenant une bobine (20) enroulée sur un mandrin (21), un élément mobile (17,
18) et un élément de fixation (11, 12, 13) ayant un moyen formant boítier (14) dans
lequel l'élément mobile est logé pour aller et venir, et un moyen d'attraction (16) vers
lequel l'élément mobile est attiré par un flux magnétique destiné à être généré au
moment de l'excitation de la bobine, le moyen formant logement étant pourvu, à un
emplacement opposé de manière radiale par rapport à l'élément mobile, d'une partie
annulaire (15), et le moyen formant logement et le moyen d'attraction faisant corps
l'un avec l'autre, comprenant les étapes consistant à :
<claim-text><claim-text>doter la partie annulaire d'une épaisseur radiale inférieure à celle d'une partie
du moyen formant boítier axialement adjacente à celle-ci ; et</claim-text><claim-text>réaliser un moulage de résine sur une surface périphérique extérieure du
noyau de fixation comportant la partie annulaire, tandis que la partie annulaire est
supportée par un élément d'obturation (100, 110 et 111, 120 et 125) butant contre une
paroi périphérique intérieure de la partie annulaire de façon que la partie annulaire ne
puisse pas se déformer sous l'effet de la résine sous pression.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de fabrication d'un dispositif d'entraínement électromagnétique
selon la revendication 5, comprenant en outre les étapes consistant à :<claim-text><claim-text>former au moins un des trous traversants (15a) pénétrant de manière radiale
dans une paroi de la partie annulaire, l'élément d'obturation fermant le trou traversant
de façon que de la résine ne s'échappe pas par le trou traversant vers l'intérieur de la
partie annulaire.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20050504"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050215</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20041231"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20040617"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60103199</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040617</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20040616"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20040512"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20040512"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20030903"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20030528"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030411</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20030502"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030303</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20021211"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20021211"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010919"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010919"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>