<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1129627-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1129627" kind="B1" date="20030502"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23212332" ucid="EP-1129627-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1129627</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20030502</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01610014-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01610014</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010227</date><lang>DA</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="DK-200000324-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>DK</country><doc-number>200000324</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000229</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new" /><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/14        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/18        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/18        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A23K1/14</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A23K1/16L</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A23K1/16M</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A23K1/18M1</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Natürlicher Futterzusatz, Verfahren zur Herstellung dieses Futterzusatzes, diesen Futterzusatz enthaltende Futtermischung sowie Verfahren zur Aufzucht von Farmtieren</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Natural feed additive, a method of preparing said feed additive, a feed mixture containing the feed additive as well as a method of breeding farm animals.</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Additif naturel pour l'alimentation animale, procédé permettant de préparer cet additif, mélange alimentaire contenant cet additif ainsi qu'une méthode pour l'élevage d'animaux de ferme</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>DANSK IND SYNDIKAT</name><address><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>NOR FEED AS</name><address><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>DANSK LANDBRUGS GROVVARESELSKAB A.M.B.A.</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>NOR-FEED A/S</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>ELGAARD TROELS</name><address><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>JENSEN JESPER MOLLER</name><address><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>ELGAARD, TROELS</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>JENSEN, JESPER MOLLER</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>ELGAARD, TROELS</last-name><address><street>Skibsbyggervej 21</street><city>2660 Brondby Strand</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>JENSEN, JESPER MOLLER</last-name><address><street>Kildemosevej 42</street><city>4100 Ringsted</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Dansk Landbrugs Grovvareselskab a.m.b.a.</last-name><address><street>Vesterbrogade 4a</street><city>1503 Copenhagen V</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></assignee><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>NOR-FEED A/S</last-name><address><street>Kanalholmen 2</street><city>2650 Hvidovre</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Zeuthen-Aagaard, Henrik</last-name><address><street>Chas. Hude A/S, 33 H.C. Andersens Boulevard</street><city>1780 Copenhagen V</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>A natural feed additive comprising an oligosaccharide, a first active component containing saponin based on material from the plants Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta and/or Trigonellan, as well as a second active component containing an antibacterially active substance based on material from the plants Citrus, hips, grapes, green pepper and plants of the family Lamiaceae. The feed additive turned out to be very efficient as an addition to animal feed in connection breeding of farm animals.</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">A natural feed additive comprising an oligosaccharide, a first active component
containing saponin based on material from the plants Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta
and/or Trigonellan, as well as a second active component containing an antibacterially
active substance based on material from the plants Citrus, hips, grapes,
green pepper and plants of the family Lamiaceae. The feed additive turned out to
be very efficient as an addition to animal feed in connection breeding of farm animals.</p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><heading>Technical Field</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a natural feed additive with natural active substances
or substances identical to natural substances, a feed mixture containing the additive
as well as a method of breeding farm animals.</p><heading><b>Background Art</b></heading><p num="0002">It is well-known to use antibiotic or chemotherapeutic substances as so-called
growth-promoters in connection with the breeding of farm animals. During recent
years there has been a focus on the problems caused by the widespread use of antibiotics
or chemotherapeutics as growth-promoters. Thus more and more pathogenic
micro-organisms can develop a resistance to the antibiotics in question which accordingly
become less effective. Furthermore, a risk applies of antibiotic residues remaining
in meat products with the result that human beings also consume antibiotics,
which in turn may have the result that micro-organisms infecting human beings with
diseases can develop a resistance. A continued use of antibiotics as growth-promoters
may increase the risk of an epidemic among animals and/or human beings which
cannot be combated by means of antibiotics. One of the hitherto used growth-promoters
has turned out to be carcenogenic as well.</p><p num="0003">In view of these problems attempts have been made to develop alternative methods
so as to ensure a disease-free breeding of farm animals without the use of antibiotics.
Furthermore the use of the classic growth-promoters in the pig production has already
ceased in some countries, such as in Denmark.</p><p num="0004">This cessation of the use of conventional growth-promoters in connection with the 
production of piglets in the weight ratio of 6 to 35 kg has turned out to cause problems
in up to 80% of all stocks. Typical symptoms are an increased occurrence of
diarrhoea requiring treatment and that the piglets do not flourish, and an increased
frequency of infections, especially caused by E. coli or Lawsonia, as well as dysentery
and diseases similar to dysentery.</p><p num="0005">In order to economize on the breeding of farm animals a demand for alternative
solutions exists accordingly, said alternative solutions being capable of preventing or
reducing these infections and diseases in farm animals while not being encumbered
with the risk of the classic growth-promoters of developing a resistance in the micro-organisms.
Such solutions can advantageously be based on natural active substances
or substances identical to natural active substances. These substances should
also have the same or preferably an improved effect on the growth and the utilization
of the animal feed of the animals compared to the classic growth-promoters in order
to ensure the acceptance of the farmer and within the animal feed industry.</p><p num="0006">It is known to use saponin-containing or flavonoid-containing plant materials in
animal feed for farm animals. Thus <ref type="patent">WO 91/10 370</ref> (Hult) describes a composition
for improving the environment as well as the state of health of animals, such as pigs
and horses. The composition comprises a mixture of saponin, especially sarsaponin
of Yucca schidigera, and garlic. The composition is admixed the animal feed and
causes a reduced release of ammonium and sulphur gases from the animals.</p><p num="0007"><ref type="patent">GB 2 321 583</ref> (Greene and Jennings) describes a feed supplement for animals, especially
horses. The feed supplement includes herbs, molasses and calcium oxide.
Examples of herbs are inter alia garlic, oregano, basil, thyme and fenugreek. The
mixture of molasses and calcium oxide causes a chemical reaction which in turn
results in formation of a herb-containing solid block which is lick-acceptable to
animals. The feed supplement is usable for animals, such as for instance sheeps and
pigs. </p><p num="0008">It is also known to use less digestible oligosaccharides which are hard to digest for
the farm animals, but which can be degraded by Bifido-bacteria in the intestinal
system. During this degrading process inter alia short-chained fatty acids are formed
which are digestible to the animals as source of energy. An improved growth of
Bifido-bacteria is obtained. As a result, the formation of lactic acid and acetic acid
is increased in the intestinal system, which in turn reduces the number of pathogenic
bacteria.</p><p num="0009">An example of the latter has been described in <ref type="patent">US 5 952 033</ref> (Anantharaman et al.)
in form of a cereal product containing fructo-oligosaccharide for instance in form of
inulin. The product has a useful effect in the digestive tract of human beings and
animals. The product can be used as an animal feed for pets and as a breakfast cereal.
Further examples of oligosaccharide-containing materials with a useful effect
in the digestive tract of human beings and animals have been described in <ref type="patent">US
4,865,852</ref>, <ref type="patent">EP 0171026</ref>, <ref type="patent">DK 160346</ref> and <ref type="patent">WO 96/03150</ref>.</p><p num="0010"><ref type="patent">EP 0 549 478</ref> (Matusani; Katta et al.) describes an animal feed containing
galacto-oligosaccharide. The animal feed reduces the tendency to diarrhoea and
ensures accordingly an increased growth. <ref type="patent">US 4 902 674</ref> (Coors Biotech; Speights)
describes a method and a composition for inhibiting the growth of salmonella in the
intestine of animals by means of fructo-oligosaccharide. <ref type="patent">US 4 873 229</ref> (Snow Brand
Milk Prod.; Deya et al.) describes an animal feed containing a galacto-oligosaccharide
in form of galactosyl-lactose or digalactosyl-lactose. The animal feed is
rather active in preventing diarrhoea and can accordingly indirectly improve the
growth and utilization of the animal feed of the animals.</p><p num="0011">As illustrated above literature reveals a multitude of proposals for improving the
health, the growth and the utilization of the animal feed in connection with breeding
of farm animals, but none of these proposals has turned out to be so effective that
they can replace the classic growth-promoters, such as tylosin phosphate and 
virginiamycin.</p><p num="0012">It turned out surprisingly that it is possible to produce a feed additive by using a
combination of an oligosaccharide, a saponin-containing material preferably from
plants and additional plant material containing natural antibacterial substances, where
said feed additive can match the classic growth-promoters with respect to efficiency.</p><heading><b>Brief Description of the Invention</b></heading><p num="0013">The present invention relates to a natural feed additive with natural, active substances
and/or substances identical to natural, active substances which comprise an
oligosaccharide-containing component, a first active component comprising saponin
and being obtained from a plant material originating from one or more plants selected
among the genera Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta and/or Trigonella, or which is a
synthetic material comprising corresponding active substances identical to natural
substances and a second active component comprising an antibacterially active substance
obtained from a plant material originating from one or more plants selected
among citrus fruits, hips, grapes, green pepper and plants of the labiatae family
(Lamiaceae), or which is a synthetic material comprising corresponding active substances
identical to natural substances, as well as possible conventional adjuvants or
additives.</p><p num="0014">The invention relates furthermore to a method of producing the feed additive, whereby
the oligosaccharide-containing component, the first active component and the
second active component are mixed in the dry state, adjuvants or additives optionally
also being added.</p><p num="0015">The extent of applicability of the invention appears from the following detailed
description. It should, however, be understood that the detailed description and the
specific examples are merely included to illustrate the preferred embodiments, and 
that various alterations and modifications within the scope of protection will be
obvious to persons skilled in the art on the basis of the detailed description.</p><heading><b>Detailed Description of the Invention</b></heading><p num="0016">The feed additive according to the invention is based on natural substances and/or
substances identical to natural substances in a combination which ensures flourishing
and healthy farm animals in a more natural way than the one obtained by the classic
growth-promoters. Thus it is possible to obtain the same daily growth as the one
obtained with the classic growth-promoters while the resistance problems associated
with said growth-promoters can simultaneously be avoided.</p><p num="0017">Examples of possible oligosaccharides in the feed additive according to the invention
are fructo-oligosaccharides, galacto-oligosaccharides and corresponding oligosaccharides,
such as mannan-oligosaccharides which are relatively indigestible for the farm
animals, but which have a regulating effect on the digestive system of said farm
animals and ensure a healthy bacterial flora especially in the intestine. Thus lactic
acid bacteria, such as Bifido-bacteria, are supported, and the growth of anaerobic,
undesirable bacteria, such as Campylobacter and Lawsonia, is suppressed.</p><p num="0018">Particularly preferred oligosaccharides are fructo-oligosaccharides of the formula
G-F<sub>n</sub>, where G is glucose and F is fructose and n is an integer typically between 3
and 9. Such fructo-oligosaccharides can be obtained from plants of the composite
family (Asteraceae), especially from the plants chicory (Cichorium intybus L.) or
Jerusalem artichoke (Helianthus tuberosus L.), by way of extraction and drying, cf.
for instance the description of <ref type="patent">DK 163 332 B</ref> (corresponding to <ref type="patent">US 5 127 956</ref>,
Hansen et al.) or by drying and grinding the oligosaccharide-containing plant parts
into powder.</p><p num="0019">It is also possible to produce oligosaccharides by way of synthesis based on mono 
and disaccharides, such as by a stepwise synthesis of saccharose and fructose by
employing the enzyme fructosyltransferase. Such synthetically structured oligosaccharides
can in theory also be used in the feed additive according to the invention,
but they are unlikely to be considered due to the costs involved.</p><p num="0020">The oligosaccharide-containing component is in the present description and in the
claims to be construed as an oligosaccharide-containing material obtained by synthesis
or preferably from one or more of the above plants or corresponding
oligosaccharide-containing plants by way of drying and grinding of the parts of a
plant including the active substances, or by another way of obtaining the active
substances, such as by way of extraction or pressing followed by isolation and/or
drying. As it is a question of natural materials, the content of the active substances
may vary. Therefore, the quantities indicated in the description and in the claims
must be related to a plant material including approximately 80% by weight of
oligosaccharide. Thus when a specific recipe indicates 35 g of oligosaccharide, and
the oligosaccharide-containing material available only includes 40% by weight of
oligosaccharide, it is according to the recipe necessary to use 70 g of the material in
question.</p><p num="0021">Saponins is a class of glycosides constituted by a sugar moiety, viz. the glucon
moiety, and a sapogenin moiety, viz. the aglucon moiety. Type examples of sugar
moieties of the saponins are: glucose, galactose and pentose. Saponins can be divided
into neutral saponins and acid saponins depending on the sapogenin moiety of said
saponin; in neutral saponins the sapogenin moiety is a steroide, whereas the sapogenin
moiety is a triterpene structure in acid saponins.</p><p num="0022">The first active component forming part of the feed additive according to the invention
comprises saponin-containing materials obtained from a plant material originating
from one or more plants selected among the genera Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta
and/or Trigonella, or it is a synthetic material comprising corresponding substances 
identical to natural substances. Such plant materials can according to literature include
high or low amounts of other substances possibly contributing to the activity.
Particularly preferred plant materials are obtained from the plants Quillaja saponaria,
Yucca schidigera or Trigonella foenum graecum (fenugreek). Less preferred plants
are Azadirachta indica (neem). The saponin-containing materials are natural binders
of volatile nitrogen-containing and sulphur-containing compounds, and they improve
the utilization by the animals of the nitrogen and fatty content in the animal feed. The
saponins have furthermore an environmentally improving effect because a reduced
amount of nitrogen and sulphur compounds is liberated together with the urine and
the faeces.</p><p num="0023">Some of the above saponin-containing materials have furthermore a weak, but
wide-spectrum antibacterial effect. Such slightly antibacterial materials are mainly
used on account of the content of saponin, and they are in the present description and
claims defined as part of the first active component, and they are not to be considered
included in the second active component in spite of said content of antibacterial
material.</p><p num="0024">The first active component is in the present description and claims to be construed
as a saponin-containing material obtained either from one or more of the above plants
or corresponding saponin-containing plants, or it is a synthetically produced material
identical to natural material. When the first active component has been obtained from
plants, it can be obtained by way of drying and grinding of the parts of a plant including
the active substances, or the active substances can be obtained in another
way, such as by extraction or pressing followed by an isolation and/or drying. As it
is a question of natural materials, the content of the active substances may vary.
Therefore, the quantities indicated in the description and in the claims must be related
to a plant material containing approximately 8% by weight of saponin.Thus when a
specific recipe indicates 35 g of Yucca-powder, and the Yucca-powder available only
contains 4% by weight of saponin, it is according to the recipe necessary to use 70 
g of the Yucca-powder in question.</p><p num="0025">It must be underlined that the saponin content is an essential ingredient of the first
active component, but that the plant materials also contain other substances possibly
being important for the effect of the feed additive according to the invention. When
it is desired to use a synthetically produced saponin-containing material identical to
natural saponin-containing material, this factor must be considered. In order to
ensure the presence of the necessary active substances it is at present preferred to use
materials based on plants as the first active component.</p><p num="0026">The second active component forming part of the feed additive according to the
invention comprises materials with a content if various antibacterially active substances,
which together with the remaining substances of said materials ensure the
effect of the second active component in the feed additive. It is assumed that in
particular three groups of active compounds present in varying quantities in the plants
in question render the substances of said groups usable as source of the materials
constituting the second active component according to the invention. These three
groups of active compounds are groups of compounds present in relatively high
concentrations in some plants.</p><p num="0027">One group of active compounds being found to be contained in materials usable as
the second active component according to the invention is a group of a number of
antibacterial, substituted phenols. Examples of such antibacterial, substituted phenols
are alkyl-substituted phenols, including dialkyl-substituted phenols with 1 to 5 carbon
atoms in the alkyl groups. Particularly interesting phenols are hydroxycymenes,
especially carvacrol and thymol.</p><p num="0028">Plant materials useful as sources of alkyl phenols, especially hydroxycymenes, comprise
inter alia plants of the genus Citrus and plants of the labiatae family, especially
oregano and thyme. Both oregano oil and thyme oil are rich in hydroxycymenes. </p><p num="0029">The second group of active compounds being found to be contained in materials
usable as the second active component according to the invention is a group of a
number of antibacterial terpenes. Examples of such antibacterial terpenes are pinene,
cymene, cineol, borneol and campher, which are found inter alia in plants of the
labiatae family, especially in oregano and thyme.</p><p num="0030">The third group of active compounds being found to be contained in materials useable
as the second active component according to the invention is a group of flavonoids.
Flavonoids are a class of compounds which are derivatives of flavone (=
2-phenyl-1,4-benzopyrone). In these derivatives, one or more of the H atoms in
flavone are substituted with hydroxy groups or methoxy groups. Flavonoids occur
in live tissue, where they are mainly bonded to sugar molecules.</p><p num="0031">Flavonoids are of wide occurence in plant materials, and in particular in citrus fruits,
hips, apricots, grapes, green pepper and onions suitable as flavonoid source.</p><p num="0032">The second active component is in the present description and claims to be construed
as a material obtained either from one or more of the plants <i>Citrus</i>, hips, grapes,
green pepper and/or plants of the labiatae family (Lamiaceae), or a synthetically
produced material identical to natural material. When the second active component
is obtained from plants, it is obtained by drying and grinding of the parts of a plant
containing the active substances, or the substances are obtained in another way, such
as by extraction or pressing followed by isolation and/or drying. As it is a question
of natural materials, the content of the active substances may vary.</p><p num="0033">Therefore the quantities indicated in the description and the claims must be related
to the content of active substances in the plant material. For instance when it is a
question of a flavonoid-containing plant material in which the antibacterial substances
especially include a high amount of flavonoids, then the second component can be
defined on the basis of a material containing approximately 8% by weight of flavonoid. 
Thus when a specific recipe indicates 35 g of Citrus-powder, and the Citrus-powder
available only contains 4% by weight of flavonoid, it is according to the
recipie necessary to use 70 g of the Citrus-powder in question.</p><p num="0034">Correspondingly, when it is a question of a plant material with a high content of
hydroxycymenes, then the second component can be defined on the basis of a material
containing approximately 8% by weight of hydroxycymenes. Thus when a specific
recipe indicates 35 g of oregano-powder, and the oregano-powder available only
contains 4% by weight of hydroxycymenes, it is according to the recipe necessary
to use 70 g of the oregano-powder in question.</p><p num="0035">It should be underlined that the plant materials applicable as the active component
may contain various active substances both within and outside the above three groups
of compounds, and that individually these active substances can be assumed to be
important for the effect of the feed additive according to the invention.</p><p num="0036">In order to ensure that the necessary active substances are present in the feed additive
according to the invention, it is at present preferred to use natural plant materials as
source of the second active component. Based on the present knowledge, synthetic
hydroxycymenes are apparently just as efficient as plant materials in the second
active component. The latter applies also to hydroxycymenes obtained by modification
of other substances from plant materials, such as by oxidation and aromatisation
of limonene.</p><p num="0037">Generally speaking, when it is considered to use a synthetically produced plant
material identical to natural plant materials, it is necessary to take into account a
possible need of other active substances in the second active component. It should for
instance be mentioned that materials obtained from Citrus in addition to the flavonoids
also contain antibacterial substances, such as Phlorin, as well as limonoids
which can bind ammonia. </p><p num="0038">Examples of plant materials useful as the second active component are such that
originate from citrus fruits, hips, grapes and green pepper, especially lemon, grapefruit,
hips and grapes because these plant materials are good flavonoid-sources, but
contain also other active substances having an antibacterial effect. Further examples
of plant materials suitably forming part as the second active component are plant
materials from the labiatae family (Lamiaceae), such as Satureia hortensis (savory),
Origanum vulgare (oregano), Thymus vulgaris (thyme) and Rosmarinus officinalis
(rosemary). These known spices have a supplemental effect as they clearly stimulate
the appetite of pigs, and furthermore they contain various active compounds, such
as hydroxycymenes and terpenes providing them with the desired wide-spectrum,
antibacterial effect.</p><p num="0039">Particularly preferred as source of the second antibacterial component are citrus
fruits, such as lemon or grapefruit with a high content of flavonoids. These materials
contain limonoids as well. Limonoids and flavonoids are functionally active and can
bind volatile nitrogen compounds and sulphur compounds formed in connection with
the digestion of the animal feed. In addition, the flavonoids have a wide-spectrum,
antibacterial effect.</p><p num="0040">The good results of the feed additive according to the invention are inter alia obtained
because some of the plant substances forming part of the additive possess flavour-improving
properties as well, and accordingly the feed additive is very attractive
to the farm animals, which in turn implies that an increased consumption of
animal feed can be expected.</p><p num="0041">Thus fenugreek can also act as a spice which is particularly attractive to pigs. An
example of a further group of plant materials having a flavour-improving effect is
found in the plant materials of the labiatae family (Lamiaceae), such as Satureia
hortensis (savory), Origanum vulgare (oregano), Thymus vulgaris (thyme) and
Rosmarinus officinalis (rosemary). </p><p num="0042">Suitable carriers for the active substances are preferably mineral, porous materials
optionally based on hydrated magnesium and/or aliminum silicates. Examples thereof
are sepiolite and other clay minerals of the sepiolite-palygorskite-family as well as
zeolites, such as klinoptilolite. Such carrier materials can adsorb and absorb the
active substances and release said substances at a suitable speed throughout the intestine
of the animals. Moreover, the carriers operate such that they absorb a number
of toxines in the gastro-intestinal tract of the animal, which in turn implies that they
contribute to the favourable effect of the feed additive according to the present invention.</p><p num="0043">It appears from the above that according to the present invention it is possible to
obtain a natural feed additive by combining an oligosaccharide-containing component,
a first active component containing saponin, as well as the second active component
containing an antibacterially active substance, where the feed additive has the
effect that it is possible to ensure healthy and flourishing farm animals, in particular
pigs, to a far higher degree than hitherto known.</p><p num="0044">The Applicant is not completely aware of how the interaction between the three
components according to the invention on one side and the intestinal flora of the
animals on the other side results in the novel, favourable effect on the animals.
However, it is obvious to frame the theory that the idea per se of combining the
components which
<sl><li>a) have a bacteria-regulating effect throughout the digestive system of the
animal, and which have a particularly, viz. indirectly, combating effect on
undesirable anerobic bacteria, such as Campylobacter and Lawsonia (oligosaccharides)
with</li><li>b) a first active component capable of binding volatile nitrogen and sulphur-containing
compounds in the gastro-intestinal tract of the animals,</li><li>c) as well as components with a wide-spectrum, antibacterial effect, such as
hydroxycymenes, terpenes, and flavonoids,</li></sl> 
results exactly in the balance between the digestive speed and the regulation of the
anaerobic and undesirable bacteria and the bacteria with a favourable effect, respectively,
in the gastro-intestinal tract of the animals which are necessary for keeping
the animals healthy and flourishing.</p><p num="0045">In this connection many other natural wide-spectrum, strongly antibacterial substances
might have the desired effect as the second active component.</p><p num="0046">Therefore it is possible within the scope of the invention as the second active component
to use any natural, wide-spectrum, strongly antibacterial substance having the
desired effect in a feed additive according to the invention.</p><p num="0047">In order to determine whether a specific material based on plants is useable as the
second active component in the feed additive according to the invention, a suitable
and simple way is to determine the inhibiting effect of the material, such as by the
agar-diffusion method, against representative bakteria, such as <i>Salmonella typhimurium,
Escherichia coli</i>, <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i> and <i>Streptococcus faecium</i>.</p><p num="0048">The carrier material should have a particle size where at least 50% by weight of the
particles are smaller than 350 µm, preferably at least 90% by weight of the particles
are smaller than 250 µm.</p><p num="0049">A preferred saponin-containing plant material useable as the first active component
can be obtained from cortex and twigs from the plant Quillaja saponaria. The plant
material to be used in the feed additive according to the invention can be suitably
processed, such as by the parts of the plant being dried and ground to a powder. The
active substances can alternatively be extracted by means of a solvent, such as an
aqueous solvent, and dried into a powder under lenient conditions. The content of the
active substances in the resulting powder can vary, but typically the content of saponin
is in the range of from 4 to 12% by weight. </p><p num="0050">The same procedure is followed for obtaining the other saponin-containing plant
materials suitable as the first active component in the feed additive according to the
invention. Thus the saponin-containing parts of the plant in question can either be
dried and ground into a powder or the active substances can be extracted by means
of a suitable extracting agent and followed by a drying and/or isolation of the active
substances.</p><p num="0051">Flavonoid-containing plant materials can as mentioned inter alia originate from the
fruit mass of citrus fruits, especially lemon or grapefruit, and they can in a financially
favourable manner be obtained from the fruit mass-containing residue remaining
as a by-product after the production of juice; again either by drying and grinding
into a powder or by extraction followed by isolation and/or drying.</p><p num="0052">Parts of a plant from citrus fruits, such as lemon and grapefruit and related types of
citrus, are particularly useful as starting material. As mentioned these fruits have a
relatively high content of limonoids and flavonoids, and in addition it is possible to
utilize their content of cyclic terpenes, such as limonene, which by a simple chemical
modification in form of oxidation and aromatisation can be converted into
hydroxycymenes.</p><p num="0053">Other antibacterial plant materials can be obtained in corresponding ways on the basis
of the parts of a plant containing the active substances.</p><p num="0054">The feed additive according to the invention can optionally comprise conventional
adjuvants and/or additives, such as dust-reducing agents and preservatives.</p><heading><b>Example 1</b></heading><p num="0055">For the production of 1 kg of feed additive the following materials are mixed in the
dry state: <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Nor-Spice® AB powder</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Quillaja powder</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fructo-oligosaccharide</entry><entry align="right">100 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fenugreek powder</entry><entry align="right">35 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sepiolite 100</entry><entry align="right">815 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0056">A mixing of the dried powdered materials results in 1000 g of additive. The additive
can be used in the animal feed for pigs. Usually an amount of 2 to 12 kg of additive
is used per 1000 kg of animal feed, especially 5 to 7 kg of additive per 1000 kg of
animal feed.</p><heading><b>Example 2</b></heading><p num="0057">For the production of 1 kg of feed additive the following materials are mixed in the
dry state:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Nor-Spice® AB powder</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yucca-powder</entry><entry align="right">30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fructo-oligosaccharide</entry><entry align="right">100 g </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fenugreek powder</entry><entry align="right">35 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Thyme powder</entry><entry align="right">20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sepiolite 100</entry><entry align="right">790 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0058">1000 g of feed additive are obtained which can be used for pigs in the same manner
as the additive of Example 1.</p><heading><b>Example 3</b></heading><p num="0059">For the production of 1 kg of feed additive the following materials are mixed in the
dry state:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2" align="left">Flavonoid-containing extract</entry></row><row><entry align="left">from green pepper</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Neem powder</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dried, ground Jerusalem artichokes</entry><entry align="right">200 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oregano powder</entry><entry align="right">20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Klinoptilolite</entry><entry align="right">730 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0060">1000 g of feed additive are obtained which can be used for pigs in the same manner
as the additive of Example 1.</p><heading><b>Example 4</b></heading><p num="0061">For the production of 1 kg of feed additive the following materials are mixed in the 
dry state:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Flavonoid-containing extract from hips</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yucca powder</entry><entry align="right">30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fructo-oligosaccharide</entry><entry align="right">100 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oregano powder</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rosemary powder</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sepiolite 60/100</entry><entry align="right">795 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>Example 5</b></heading><p num="0062">For the production of 1 kg of feed additive the following materials are mixed in the
dry state:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Flavonoid-containing extract from grapes</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yucca powder</entry><entry align="right">30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fructo-oligosaccharide</entry><entry align="right">100 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Savory powder</entry><entry align="right">25 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sepiolite 60/100</entry><entry align="right">820 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>Feeding experiments</b></heading><p num="0063">Feeding experiments were caried out with the feed additive according to Example 1
by addition of 5 to 7 kg of feed additive per 1000 kg of animal feed to piglets during
the period from the weaning, i.e. at an age of 3 to 4 weeks, and until an age of 75
to 80 days. The experiments were carried out in stocks where all stocks suffered
from problems of Lawsonia and E. coli. Within 3 to 7 days after the start of the
feeding, the problems of diarrhoea ceased and the piglets revealed more solid faeces.</p><p num="0064">The results of the feeding experiments appear from the following Table in comparison
with the results of the use of conventional growth-promoters based on a total
Danish average (source: Landsudvalget for svin (= &quot;The Danish National Committee
for Pigs&quot;), Rapport over E-kontrollens resultater (= &quot;Report on the results of the
efficiency control&quot;), October 1999, dated 12 January 2000, showing the observed
actual Danish data for the period October 1998 to October 1999. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center" /><entry align="center"><b>Number of pigs</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Weight start (kg)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Weight termi- nated (kg)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Growth g/day</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>FEs/kg Growth</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Mortality %</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Group 1</entry><entry align="left">977</entry><entry align="center">6.99</entry><entry align="center">30.80</entry><entry align="center">475</entry><entry align="center">1.78</entry><entry align="center">1.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Group 2</entry><entry align="left">1191</entry><entry align="center">6.65</entry><entry align="center">29.00</entry><entry align="center">445</entry><entry align="center">1.69</entry><entry align="center">2.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Group 3</entry><entry align="left">1202</entry><entry align="center">6.90</entry><entry align="center">26.20</entry><entry align="center">446</entry><entry align="center">1.96</entry><entry align="center">1.50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Group 4</entry><entry align="left">1271</entry><entry align="center">6.90</entry><entry align="center">27.50</entry><entry align="center">410</entry><entry align="center">1.89</entry><entry align="center">1.30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Group 5</entry><entry align="left">2053</entry><entry align="center">6.70</entry><entry align="center">31.20</entry><entry align="center">432</entry><entry align="center">1.85</entry><entry align="center">2.80</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Group 6</entry><entry align="left">5169</entry><entry align="center">5.70</entry><entry align="center">30.50</entry><entry align="center">447</entry><entry align="center">1.81</entry><entry align="center">1.50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Group 7</entry><entry align="left">2204</entry><entry align="center">6.80</entry><entry align="center">32.30</entry><entry align="center">451</entry><entry align="center">1.84</entry><entry align="center">1.20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Group 8</entry><entry align="left">1372</entry><entry align="center">5.82</entry><entry align="center">28.00</entry><entry align="center">406</entry><entry align="center">1.74</entry><entry align="center">2.30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Average per pig</entry><entry align="left">15439</entry><entry align="center">6.35</entry><entry align="center">29.95</entry><entry align="center">440</entry><entry align="center">1.82</entry><entry align="center">1.69</entry></row><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2" align="left">Conventional growth-promoters</entry><entry namest="3" align="center">7.20</entry><entry namest="4" align="center">29.80</entry><entry namest="5" align="center">422</entry><entry namest="6" align="center">2.00</entry><entry namest="7" align="center">3.20</entry></row><row><entry>FEs/kg growth: Consumption of food units from animal feed for pigs per kg and growth.</entry></row><row><entry>Mortality: The mortality in % of the piglets during the experimental period.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0065">Based on the present prices of feed mixtures, the feed additive according to the
invention and the pig prices, the financial index for the use of the animal feed for
pigs according to the invention can be calculated to be 103, where the index for
the use of conventional growth-promoters is 100. The calculation of the financial 
index does not even take into account that the pigs subjected to the experiments
weighed on average 0.85 kg less than the pigs of the control groups at the beginning
of the experiment. Nor is the saving taken into account which is obtained by
the fact that the use of the feed additive according to the invention ensures the
same results with respect to weight while being stabled 3 to 4 days less than the
control group.</p><p num="0066">At present no results with respect to the consumption of animal feed, the growth
and the mortality of the pigs are available for illustrating the effect of the use of
the additive in animal feed compared to the ordinary animal feed not admixed
growth-promoters. However, at the time of the introduction of the conventional
growth-promoters they turned out to be able to reduce the consumption of animal
feed by 10%.</p><p num="0067">The above description of the invention reveals that it is obvious that it can be varied
in many ways. Such variations are not to be considered a deviation from the
scope of the invention, and all such modifications which are obvious to persons
skilled in the art are also to be considered comprised by the scope of the succeeding
claims.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Natürlicher Futterzusatz mit natürlichen, wirksamen Substanzen oder/und
naturidentischen Substanzen, wobei der Futterzusatz umfasst
<claim-text><claim-text>a) einen Oligosaccharid-enthaltenden Bestandteil,</claim-text><claim-text>b) einen ersten Wirkstoff, der Saponin umfasst und der aus einem
Pflanzenmaterial erhalten wird, das von einer oder mehreren
Pflanzen, ausgewählt aus den Gattungen Yucca, Quillaja,
Azadirachta oder/und Trigonella stammt, oder einen ersten
Bestandteil, der ein synthetisches Material ist, das
naturidentische Saponinsubstanzen umfasst, und</claim-text><claim-text>c) einen zweiten Wirkstoff, der eine antibakteriell wirksame
Substanz umfasst, die aus einem Pflanzenmaterial erhalten
wird, das von einer oder mehreren Pflanzen, ausgewählt aus
Citrusfrüchten, Hagebutten, Weintrauben, grünem Pfeffer und
Pflanzen der Lippenblütler-Familie (Lamiaceae) stammt, oder
einen zweiten Bestandteil, der ein synthetisches Material ist,
das naturidentische antibakterielle Substanzen umfasst,</claim-text></claim-text>
ebenso wie gegebenenfalls konventionelle Adjuvantien oder Zusätze.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass das
Pflanzenmaterial von Zitrone, Grapefruit oder/und einer Pflanze stammt,
ausgewählt unter den Gattungen Satureia, Origanum, Thymus, Rosmarinus
oder Mentha.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, dadurch
gekennzeichnet, dass die Pflanzenmaterialien in Form von getrockneten
Pflanzenextrakten, gepressten Pflanzenextrakten oder/und getrockneten,
gemahlenen Bestandteilen einer Pflanze einen Teil des Futterzusatzes bilden.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, dadurch
gekennzeichnet, dass er in einer Menge an Futterzusatz, der für 1000 kg eines
Tierfutters berechnet ist,
<claim-text><claim-text>100 bis 3000 g eines Oligosaccharid-enthaltenden Bestandteils,</claim-text><claim-text>50 bis 2000 g des ersten Wirkstoffs,</claim-text><claim-text>50 bis 4000 g des zweiten Wirkstoffs umfasst.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach Anspruch 4, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass er in einer
Menge an Futterzusatz, der für 1000 kg eines Tierfutters berechnet ist,
<claim-text><claim-text>200 bis 1500 g eines Oligosaccharid-enthaltenden Bestandteils,</claim-text><claim-text>100 bis 1000 g des ersten Wirkstoffs,</claim-text><claim-text>100 bis 2000 g des zweiten Wirkstoffs umfasst.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach Anspruch 5, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass er in einer
Menge an Futterzusatz, der für 1000 kg eines Tierfutters berechnet ist,
<claim-text><claim-text>300 bis 1000 g eines Oligosaccharid-enthaltenden Bestandteils,</claim-text><claim-text>200 bis 500 g des ersten Wirkstoffs,</claim-text><claim-text>200 bis 1000 g des zweiten Wirkstoffs umfasst.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, dadurch
gekennzeichnet, dass der Oligosaccharid-enthaltende Bestandteil Fructo-Oligosaccaride
umfasst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach Anspruch 7, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass die
Oligosaccharide durchschnittlich 3 bis 9 Kohlehydrateinheiten umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, dadurch
gekennzeichnet, dass er ein für Tierfutter akzeptables Trägermaterial umfasst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach Anspruch 9, dadurch gekennzeichnet, das
Trägermaterial ein Tonmineral ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach Anspruch 10, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass das
Tonmineral ein Tonmineral des Zeolith-Typs ist, wie Klinoptilolith oder
Sepiolith.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach einem der Ansprüche 9 bis 11, dadurch gekennzeichnet,
dass das Trägermaterial eine Partikelgröße besitzt, wobei 50 Gewichts.-% der
Partikel kleiner als 350 µm sind.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futterzusatz nach Anspruch 12, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass das
Trägermaterial eine Partikelgröße besitzt, wobei 90 Gewichts.-% der Partikel
kleiner als 250 µm sind.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zur Herstellung eines Futterzusatzes nach einem der vorigen
Ansprüche, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass im trockenen Zustand
<claim-text><claim-text>a) ein Oligosaccharid-enthaltender Bestandteil,</claim-text><claim-text>b) ein erster Wirkstoff, der Saponin umfasst und der aus einem
Pflanzenmaterial erhalten wird, das von einer oder mehreren
Pflanzen, ausgewählt aus den Gattungen Yucca, Quillaja,
Azadirachta oder/und Trigonella stammt, oder ein erster
Bestandteil, der ein synthetisches Material ist, das
naturidentische Saponinsubstanzen umfasst, und</claim-text><claim-text>c) ein zweiter Wirkstoff, der eine antibakteriell wirksame Substanz
umfasst, die aus einem Pflanzenmaterial erhalten wird, das von
einer oder mehreren Pflanzen, ausgewählt aus Citrusfrüchten,
Hagebutten, Weintrauben, grünem Pfeffer und Pflanzen der
Lippenblütler-Familie (Lamiaceae) stammt, oder ein zweiter
Bestandteil, der ein synthetisches Material ist, das
naturidentische antibakterielle Substanzen umfasst</claim-text></claim-text>
gemischt werden und gegebenenfalls konventionelle Adjuvantien oder Zusätze
zu einem geeigneten Zeitpunkt zugegeben werden.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 14, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass im trockenen
Zustand
<claim-text><claim-text>a) ein Oligosaccharid-enthaltender Bestandteil,</claim-text><claim-text>b) ein erster Wirkstoff, der Saponin umfasst und der aus einem
Pflanzenmaterial erhalten wird, das von einer oder mehreren
Pflanzen, ausgewählt aus den Gattungen Yucca, Quillaja,
Azadirachta oder/und Trigonella stammt, oder ein erster
Bestandteil, der ein synthetisches Material ist, das
naturidentische Saponinsubstanzen umfasst, und</claim-text><claim-text>c) ein zweiter Wirkstoff, der eine antibakteriell wirksame Substanz
umfasst, die aus einem Pflanzenmaterial erhalten wird, das von
einer oder mehreren Pflanzen, ausgewählt aus Citrusfrüchten,
Hagebutten, Weintrauben, grünem Pfeffer und Pflanzen der
Lippenblütler-Familie (Lamiaceae) stammt, oder ein zweiter
Bestandteil, der ein synthetisches Material ist, das
naturidentische antibakterielle Substanzen umfasst und</claim-text><claim-text>d) ein für Tierfutter akzeptables Trägermaterial</claim-text></claim-text>
gemischt werden und gegebenenfalls konventionelle Adjuvantien oder Zusätze
zu einem geeigneten Zeitpunkt zugegeben werden.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futtergemisch für Nutztiere umfassend die Bestandteile des Futterzusatzes
nach einem der Ansprüche 1 bis 13 zusammen mit einem konventionellen
Tierfutter.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Futtergemisch nach Anspruch 16, umfassend 2 bis 12 kg eines
Futterzusatzes pro 1000 kg Futtergemisch.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Züchten von Nutztieren, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass die
Tiere mit einem Futtergemisch nach Anspruch 16 oder 17 gefüttert werden.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Natural feed additive with natural, active substances and/or substances identical
to natural substances, said feed additive comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>a) an oligosaccharide-containing component,</claim-text><claim-text>b) a first active component comprising saponin and being obtained from
a plant material originating from one or more plants selected among
the genera Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta and/or Trigonella, or the first component is a
synthetic material comprising saponin-substances identical to
natural substances, and</claim-text><claim-text>c) a second active component comprising an antibacterially active substance
obtained from a plant material originating from one or more
plants selected among citrus fruits, hips, grapes, green pepper and
plants of the labiatae family (Lamiaceae), or the second component is a synthetic material
comprising antibacterial substances identical to natural substances,</claim-text></claim-text>
as well as optionally conventional adjuvants or additives.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in claim 1, characterised in that the plant material
originates from lemon, grapefruit and/or a plant selected among the genera Satureia,
Origanum, Thymus, Rosmarinus or Mentha.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in any of the preceding claims, characterised in that
the plant materials form part of the feed additive in form of dried plant extracts,
pressed plant extracts and/or dried, ground parts of a plant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in any of the preceding claims, characterised in that
in an amount of feed additive calculated for 1000 kg of animal feed it comprises
<claim-text><claim-text>100 to 3000 g of oligosaccharide-containing component,</claim-text><claim-text>50 to 2000 g of the first active component,</claim-text><claim-text>50 to 4000 g of the second active component.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in claim 4, characterised in that in an amount of
feed additive calculated per 1000 kg of animal feed it comprises
<claim-text><claim-text>200 to 1500 g of oligosaccharide-containing component,</claim-text><claim-text>100 to 1000 g of the first active component,</claim-text><claim-text>100 to 2000 g of the second active component.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in claim 5, characterised in that in an amount of
feed additive calculated per 1000 kg of animal feed it comprises
<claim-text><claim-text>300 to 1000 g of oligosaccharide-containing component,</claim-text><claim-text>200 to 500 g of the first active component,</claim-text><claim-text>200 to 1000 g of the second active component.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in any of the preceding claims, characterised in that
the oligosaccharide-containing component comprises fructo-oligosaccharides.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in claim 7, characterised in that the oligosaccharides
on average comprise 3 to 9 saccharide units.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in any of the preceding claims, characterised in that
it comprises a carrier material acceptable for animal feed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in claim 9, characterised in that the carrier material
is a clay mineral.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in claim 10, characterised in that the clay mineral
is of the type zeolite, such as klinoptilolite, or sepiolite.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in any of the claims 9 to 11, characterised in that
the carrier material has a particle size, where 50% by weight of the particles are
smaller than 350 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed additive as claimed in claim 12, characterised in that the carrier material
has a particle size, where 90% by weight of the particles are smaller than 250
µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method of producing a feed additive as claimed in any of the preceding
claims, characterised by mixing in the dry state
<claim-text><claim-text>a) an oligosaccharide-containing component,</claim-text><claim-text>b) a first active component comprising saponin and being obtained from
a plant material originating from one or more plants selected among
the genera Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta and/or Trigonella, or the first component is a
synthetic material comprising saponin-substances identical to
natural substances, and</claim-text><claim-text>c) a second active component comprising an antibacterially active substance
obtained from a plant material originating from one or more
plants selected among citrus fruits, hips, grapes, green pepper and
plants of the labiatae family (Lamiaceae), or the second component is a synthetic material
comprising antibacterial substances identical to natural substances,
and optionally adding conventional adjuvants or additives at a suitable time.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 14, characterised by mixing in the dry state
<claim-text><claim-text>a) an oligosaccharide-containing component,</claim-text><claim-text>b) a first active component comprising saponin and being obtained from
a plant material originating from one or more plants selected among
the genera Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta and/or Trigonella, or the first component, is a
synthetic material comprising saponin-substances identical to
natural substances, and</claim-text><claim-text>c) a second active component comprising an antibacterially active substance
obtained from a plant material originating from one or more
plants selected among citrus fruits, hips, grapes, green pepper and
plants of the labiatae family (Lamiaceae), or the second substance is a synthetic material
comprising antibacterial substances identical to natural substances,
and</claim-text><claim-text>d) a carrier material acceptable in the animal feed,</claim-text></claim-text>
and optionally adding conventional adjuvants or additives at a suitable time.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed mixture for farm animals comprising the ingredients of the feed additive
as claimed in any of the claims 1 to 13 togeether with a conventional animal
feed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A feed mixture as claimed in claim 16 comprising 2 to 12 kg of a feed additive
per 1000 kg of feed mixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method of breeding farm animals, characterised in that the animals are fed
with a feed mixture as claimed in claim 16 or 17.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire naturel avec substances actives naturelles et/ou substances
identiques aux substances naturelles, ledit additif alimentaire comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>a) un composant contenant des oligosaccharides,</claim-text><claim-text>b) un premier composant actif comprenant de la saponine et étant obtenu à
partir d'une substance végétale provenant d'une ou de plusieurs plantes sélectionnées
parmi les genres Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta et/ou Trigonella, ou le premier
composant est un matériau synthétique comprenant des substances de saponine
identiques aux substances naturelles, et</claim-text><claim-text>c) un second composant actif comprenant une substance active d'un point de
vue antibactérien obtenue à partir d'une substance végétale provenant d'une ou de
plusieurs plantes sélectionnées parmi les agrumes, les cynorhodons, le raisin, le
poivron vert et des plantes de la famille des labiatae (Lamiaceae), ou le second
composant est un matériau synthétique comprenant des substances antibactériennes
identiques aux substances naturelles,</claim-text></claim-text>
   et, facultativement, des adjuvants ou additifs classiques.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon la revendication 1, caractérisé en ce que la substance
végétale provient du citron, du pamplemousse et/ou d'une plante sélectionnée parmi
les genres Satureia, Origanum, Thymus, Rosmarinus ou Mentha.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes,
caractérisé en ce que les substances végétales font partie de l'additif alimentaire sous
forme d'extraits de plantes séchées, d'extraits de plantes pressées et/ou de parties
moulues séchées d'une plante.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes,
caractérisé en ce que, dans une quantité d'additif alimentaire calculée pour 1000 kg
d'aliments pour animaux, il y a :<claim-text><claim-text>de 100 à 3000 g d'un composant contenant des oligosaccharides,</claim-text><claim-text>de 50 à 2000 g du premier composant actif,</claim-text><claim-text>de 50 à 4000 g du second composant actif.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon la revendication 4, caractérisé en ce que, dans une
quantité d'additif alimentaire calculée pour 1000 kg d'aliments pour animaux, il y a :
<claim-text><claim-text>de 200 à 1500 g d'un composant contenant des oligosaccharides,</claim-text><claim-text>de 100 à 1000 g du premier composant actif,</claim-text><claim-text>de 100 à 2000 g du second composant actif.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon la revendication 5, caractérisé en ce que, dans une
quantité d'additif alimentaire calculée pour 1000 kg d'aliments pour animaux, il y a
<claim-text><claim-text>de 300 à 1000 g d'un composant contenant des oligosaccharides,</claim-text><claim-text>de 200 à 500 g du premier composant actif,</claim-text><claim-text>de 200 à 1000 g du second composant actif.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes,
caractérisé en ce que le composant contenant des oligosaccharides comprend des
fructo-oligosaccharides.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon la revendication 7, caractérisé en ce que les
oligosaccharides comprennent en moyenne de 3 à 9 unités de saccharides.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes,
caractérisé en ce qu'il comprend une substance véhicule acceptable pour un aliment
pour animaux.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon la revendication 9, caractérisé en ce que la substance
véhicule est un minéral argileux.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon la revendication 10, caractérisé en ce que le minéral
argileux est du type zéolite, tel que la klinoptilolite ou la sépiolite.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon l'une quelconque des revendications 9 à 11, caractérisé
en ce que la substance véhicule possède une taille particulaire dans laquelle 50 % en
poids des particules sont inférieures à 350 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Additif alimentaire selon la revendication 12, caractérisé en ce que la substance
véhicule possède une taille particulaire dans laquelle 90 % en poids des particules
sont inférieures à 250 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de fabrication d'un additif alimentaire selon l'une quelconque des
revendications précédentes, caractérisé par le fait de mélanger, à l'état sec :
<claim-text><claim-text>a) un composant contenant des oligosaccharides,</claim-text><claim-text>b) un premier composant actif comprenant de la saponine et étant obtenu à
partir d'une substance végétale provenant d'une ou de plusieurs plantes sélectionnées
parmi les genres Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta et/ou Trigonella, ou le premier
composant est un matériau synthétique comprenant des substances de saponine
identiques aux substances naturelles, et</claim-text><claim-text>c) un second composant actif comprenant une substance active d'un point de
vue antibactérien obtenue à partir d'une substance végétale provenant d'une ou de
plusieurs plantes sélectionnées parmi les agrumes, les cynorhodons, le raisin, le
poivron vert et des plantes de la famille des labiatae (Lamiaceae), ou le second
composant est un matériau synthétique comprenant des substances antibactériennes
identiques aux substances naturelles,</claim-text></claim-text>
   et par le fait de mélanger, facultativement, des adjuvants ou additifs
classiques à un moment approprié.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 14, caractérisé par le fait de mélanger, à l'état sec :
<claim-text><claim-text>a) un composant contenant des oligosaccharides,</claim-text><claim-text>b) un premier composant actif comprenant de la saponine et étant obtenu à
partir d'une substance végétale provenant d'une ou de plusieurs plantes sélectionnées
parmi les genres Yucca, Quillaja, Azadirachta et/ou Trigonella, ou le premier
composant est un matériau synthétique comprenant des substances de saponine
identiques aux substances naturelles, et</claim-text><claim-text>c) un second composant actif comprenant une substance active d'un point de
vue antibactérien obtenue à partir d'une substance végétale provenant d'une ou de
plusieurs plantes sélectionnées parmi les agrumes, les cynorhodons, le raisin, le
poivron vert et des plantes de la famille des labiatae (Lamiaceae), ou le second
composant est un matériau synthétique comprenant des substances antibactériennes
identiques aux substances naturelles, et</claim-text><claim-text>d) une substance véhicule acceptable pour un aliment pour animaux,</claim-text></claim-text>
et par le fait de mélanger, facultativement, des adjuvants ou additifs
classiques à un moment approprié.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Mélange alimentaire pour animaux fermiers comprenant les ingrédients de
l'additif alimentaire selon l'une quelconque des revendications 1 à 13, conjointement
avec un aliment pour animaux classique.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Mélange alimentaire selon la revendication 16, comprenant de 2 à 12 kg d'un
additif alimentaire pour 1000 kg de mélange alimentaire.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Méthode d'élevage d'animaux fermiers, caractérisé en ce que les animaux sont
alimentés avec un mélange alimentaire selon la revendication 16 ou la revendication
17.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20070228"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>BE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CY</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DK</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ES</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>NL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>TR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030502</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030502</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030502</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030502</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030502</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030802</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030802</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030804</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030813</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050126"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MM4A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20040421"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040203</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20040305"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="NLV1" date="20031001"><legal-event-body><event-title>NL: LAPSED OR ANNULED DUE TO FAILURE TO FULFILL THE REQUIREMENTS OF ART. 29P AND 29M OF THE PATENTS ACT; NO LEGAL EFFECT FROM</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20030815"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>NV</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>representative=s name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PATENTANWALTSBUERO EDER AG</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20030611"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20030605"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60100219</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030605</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20030515"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20030507"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20030502"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RAP1" date="20021204"><legal-event-body><event-title>APPLICANT REASSIGNMENT (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Owner name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DANSK LANDBRUGS GROVVARESELSKAB A.M.B.A.</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Owner name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>NOR-FEED A/S</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20020522"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AT BE CH CY DE DK ES FI FR GB GR IE IT LI LU MC NL PT SE TR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20020410"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020129</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>