<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1116605-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1116605" kind="B1" date="20050622"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23199292" ucid="EP-1116605-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1116605</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20050622</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01300267-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01300267</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010112</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000005637-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000005637</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000114</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000005638-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000005638</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000114</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20041230</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C  15/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C  15/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C  15/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C  15/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60C15/00D2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60C15/06</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Luftreifen mit verbesserter Haltbarkeit der Wülste</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Pneumatic tire, having improved bead portion durability</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Bandage pneumatique ayant une meilleure durabilité des talons</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>BRIDGESTONE CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>BRIDGESTONE CORPORATION</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KATO HIROYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KIMURA TAKAHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KATO, HIROYUKI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KIMURA, TAKAHIRO</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KATO, HIROYUKI</last-name><address><street>17-6, Namiki-cho, Hachioji City</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KIMURA, TAKAHIRO</last-name><address><street>3-2-7, Ogawahigashi-cho, Kodaira City</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Bridgestone Corporation</last-name><address><street>10-1, Kyobashi 1-Chome, Chuo-Ku</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Whalley, Kevin</last-name><address><street>Marks &amp;amp; Clerk 90 Long Acre</street><city>London WC2E 9RA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>A pneumatic tire comprises at least one carcass ply (2) of steel cords, in which a wrap part (6) wound on a bead core (4) along its outer peripheral face is disposed in a turnup portion (2b) of the carcass ply (2) and at least one wire chafer (5) wound around the bead core (4) from a main body portion (2a) of the carcass ply (2) toward the turnup portion (2b) thereof in a widthwise direction (7) is embedded in the bead portion (1), and a shortest distance (L) of a start end (8) of the wire chafer (5) located at the side of the main body portion (2a) of the carcass ply (2) as measured outward from a normal line (n) drawn to an outer face (13) of the bead portion (1) at a first rim line position (9) in the radial direction (10) of the tire is located to be within a range of 15-25 mm, and a terminal end (11) of the wire chafer (5) located at the side of the turnup portion (2b) of the carcass ply (2) is arranged within a range defined between a vertical line (m) drawn from an outermost end position (12) of the bead core (4) in the radial direction to the outer face (13) of the bead portion (1) and said normal line (n). &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">A pneumatic tire comprises at least one carcass ply (2) of steel
cords, in which a wrap part (6) wound on a bead core (4) along its outer
peripheral face is disposed in a turnup portion (2b) of the carcass ply (2)
and at least one wire chafer (5) wound around the bead core (4) from a
main body portion (2a) of the carcass ply (2) toward the turnup portion
(2b) thereof in a widthwise direction (7) is embedded in the bead portion
(1), and a shortest distance (L) of a start end (8) of the wire chafer (5)
located at the side of the main body portion (2a) of the carcass ply (2) as
measured outward from a normal line (n) drawn to an outer face (13) of the
bead portion (1) at a first rim line position (9) in the radial direction (10) of
the tire is located to be within a range of 15-25 mm, and a terminal end
(11) of the wire chafer (5) located at the side of the turnup portion (2b) of
the carcass ply (2) is arranged within a range defined between a vertical
line (m) drawn from an outermost end position (12) of the bead core (4) in
the radial direction to the outer face (13) of the bead portion (1) and said
normal line (n).
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1116719-A3-00000001" he="88" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">This invention relates to pneumatic tires, particularly a pneumatic
tire having an improved bead portion durability. More particularly, it
relates to a pneumatic tire capable of preventing pulling-out of a ply cord
and occurrence of separation failure at an end position of a turnup portion
of a carcass ply and also effectively controlling failure of a bead portion
due to bending deformation of the bead portion around a rim flange under
an action of a high loading to improve the bead portion durability.

The invention is preferably applied to so-called heavy duty pneumatic radial
tires used under conditions of a high load and a high internal pressure such
as trucks, buses and the like.</p><p num="0002">In order to prevent pulling-out of a ply cord during the running of
the pneumatic tire under loading, as shown in Fig. 1a, a carcass ply 100 is
usually wound around a bead core 102 of a bead portion 101 from an inside
of the tire toward an outside thereof in a widthwise direction and a turnup
portion 103 thereof is embedded and fixed in rubber.</p><p num="0003">In the conventional tire having such a bead portion structure,
however, a sidewall portion 104 is subjected to a large bending deformation
during the running of the tire under loading, particularly under an
action of a large loading and hence pulling force F is applied to the carcass
ply 100 in a direction shown by an arrow in Fig. 1a, while a step difference
in stiffness is caused on the inside and outside of the tire in a radial direction
thereof about an end position 105 of the turnup portion 103 of the carcass
ply 100 and also stress concentration is repeatedly caused in the end 
position 105 and the neighbourhood thereof. As a result, there is a problem
that separation failure of the ply cord from rubber is apt to be caused and
results in the occurrence of cracking Cr in the bead portion as shown in
Fig. 1b.</p><p num="0004">As means for preventing such a separation failure to improve the
bead portion durability, there are various proposals that it is useful to
render a turnup portion 107 of a carcass ply 106 into a wrap part 109
winding on the bead core along its peripheral face as shown in Fig. 2a.</p><p num="0005">However, when a reinforcing layer such as a wire chafer or the
like is not arranged in the bead portion, a large bending deformation is
created in a direction shown by an arrow A about a rim flange 110 as
shown by a phantom line in Fig. 2b. As a result, cracking is apt to be created
in the bead portion of the tire contacting with the rim flange by repeating
such a bending deformation and in the worst case, there is a risk of causing
bead portion failure by the growth of such a crack.</p><p num="0006">As means for improving the bead portion durability of the tire
having the above bead portion structure, it is useful that at least one
reinforcing layer 112 wound around a bead core 111 from an inside of the
tire toward an outside thereof in a widthwise direction at a position outside
the carcass ply 110 is arranged in the bead portion to control the bending
deformation of the bead portion under the action of high loading applied to
the tire as shown in Fig. 3a.</p><p num="0007">As shown in Fig. 3b, however, stress concentrates in an end
position 113 of the reinforcing layer 112 and there is caused a fear of
creating cracking Cr of one bead portion and the like in such a
position 113. As a result, such a means can not effectively improve the
bead portion durability.
 
   Attention is also drawn to the disclosures of
<ref type="patent">EP-A-1 024 033</ref> (prior art under Article 54(3)EPC),
<ref type="patent">JP-A-2000219016</ref> and <ref type="patent">EP-A-0 776 776</ref>.</p><p num="0008">It is, therefore, an object of the invention to provide a pneumatic
tire capable of preventing pulling-out of a ply cord and occurrence of
separation failure at an end position of a turnup portion of a carcass ply and
also effectively controlling failure of a bead portion due to bending
deformation of the bead portion around a rim flange under an action of a
high loading to improve the bead portion durability. </p><p num="0009">In this case, the terms &quot;maximum air pressure&quot; and &quot;maximum
load capacity&quot; used herein are defined according to &quot;<ref type="npl">Year Book of The Tire
and Rim Association Inc.</ref>&quot; in USA, &quot;<ref type="npl">Standard Manual of The European
Tire and Rim Technical Organization</ref>&quot; in Europe or &quot;<ref type="npl">JATMA Year Book</ref>&quot; in
Japan.</p><p num="0010">Also, the term &quot;turnup portion of carcass ply&quot; used herein
includes a case that the carcass ply is wound around the bead core from an
outside of the tire toward an inside thereof in the widthwise direction in
addition to a case that the carcass ply is wound around the bead core from
an inside of the tire toward an outside thereof in the widthwise direction.</p><p num="0011">In addition, the carcass ply is a ply wherein many steel cords each
having both cut ends are arranged substantially in the radial direction but
also includes a ply wherein a single steel cord is folded at a position
corresponding to the turnup portion of the carcass ply and continuously
extended while detouring in a circumferential direction of the tire. </p><p num="0012">According to the invention, there is
provided a pneumatic tire having at least one carcass ply of steel
cords constituted with a main body portion toroidally extending from a
tread portion through a sidewall portion to a bead portion and a turnup
portion wound around a bead core embedded in the bead portion, a part or
whole of which turnup portion being a wrap part wound along a peripheral
face of the bead core, in which the main body portion of the carcass ply has
(i) a convexly curved shape toward an outer face of the tire or (ii) a combined
shape of the curve and straight line at a section in a widthwise direction of
the tire when the tire is mounted onto an approved rim and inflated at a
maximum air pressure under no load, and a straight line or a chord
connecting both ends of an arc drawn by the main body portion of the
carcass ply over a zone ranging from a turning point of the main body
portion on the bead core to any point in a length (H<sub>2</sub>) in a region corresponding to 15-35%
of a length (H<sub>1</sub>) in the radial direction of the tire defined between a standard line
passing through an axial center of the bead core and drawn in parallel to a
rotating axis of the tire and an outermost side of the main body portion in
the radial direction and separated from the standard line is inclined at an
angle of 45-65° with respect to an equatorial plane of the tire.</p><p num="0013">In a preferable embodiment of the invention,
the main body portion of the carcass ply has an arc shape convexly
extending toward the outer surface of the tire over a zone ranging from the
turning point of the main body on the bead core to any point in a region
corresponding to 17-25% of the length in the radial direction of the tire
separated from the standard line.</p><p num="0014">In another preferable embodiment, a maximum length of a vertical
line drawn from the arc to a chord connecting both ends of the arc is not 
less than 2 mm.</p><p num="0015">According to the invention, the occurrence of
separation failure at the turnup end of the carcass ply can be prevented by
wrapping the turnup portion of the carcass ply on the peripheral face of the
bead core, while the shape of the main body portion of the carcass ply in
the bead portion is regulated to increase lateral stiffness of the bead portion,
whereby outward fall-down deformation of the bead portion in the
widthwise direction during the running of the tire under loading or the like
can effectively be controlled to sufficiently prevent the occurrence of
fatigue breakage in the bead portion contacting with a rim flange or the
like.</p><p num="0016">The invention will be further described with reference to the
accompanying drawings, wherein:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a diagrammatic partial section view illustrating a
problem point in a bead portion structure of the conventional tire;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a diagrammatic partial section view illustrating a
problem point in the conventional tire adopting such a bead portion
structure that a carcass ply is wound around a bead core;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a diagrammatic partial section view illustrating a
problem point caused at an end position of a wire chafer arranged for
reinforcing the bead portion of Fig. 2; </li><li>Fig. 4 is a diagrammatic partial section view illustrating a
state of mounting a bead portion of a first embodiment of the pneumatic
tire according to the invention onto a rim;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a diagrammatic partial section view illustrating a
state of mounting a bead portion of a second embodiment of the pneumatic
tire according to the invention onto a rim; and</li><li>Fig. 6 is a schematic view illustrating a shape of a main body
portion of a carcass ply according to the invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0017">In Fig. 4 is shown a first embodiment of the bead portion in a pneumatic tire
according to the invention, wherein numeral 21 is a main body portion of a
carcass ply toroidally extending from a tread portion (not shown) through a
sidewall portion (not shown) to a bead portion 22. The main body portion
21 of the carcass ply is comprised of steel cords arranged at a cord angle of, 
preferably, about 70-90° with respect to an equatorial plane of the tire.</p><p num="0018">Further, a side portion of the carcass ply is turned around a bead
core 23 embedded in the bead portion 22 from an inside of the tire toward
an outside thereof in a radial direction of the tire and then wound along an
outer peripheral face of the bead core 23 to form a wrap part 24.</p><p num="0019">In the winding of the turnup portion, it is preferable that at least
one site of a portion of the wrap part 24 corresponding to corner parts of
the bead core 23 is subjected to a plastic deformation so as to more
accurately extend along the peripheral face of the bead core. In this way,
the wrap part 24 is effectively restrained by the bead core 23, whereby a fear
of causing the pulling-out of the carcass ply and the separation failure of
the wrap part can advantageously be removed.</p><p num="0020">Moreover, the plastic deformed site is preferably previously
formed in a portion corresponding to the wrap part 24 prior to the winding
of the carcass ply around the peripheral face of the bead core 23. In this
case, the plastic deformation can be always and accurately conducted as it
is expected, whereby the above effect can be more enhanced.</p><p num="0021">In the invention, the wrap part 24 can be more closed to the bead
core 23 through a bead filler 25 located adjacent the outer periphery of the bead
core by sandwiching the wrap part 24 between the bead core 23 and the
bead filler 25, so that the pulling-out of the carcass ply and the separation
failure of the wrap part can be more advantageously prevented.</p><p num="0022">It is more preferable that the wrap part 24 is extended along the
peripheral face of the bead core over a half periphery of the sectional
profile of the bead core.</p><p num="0023">In the invention, it is important that the main body portion 21 of
the carcass ply has a convexly curved shape toward an outer face of the tire
or a combined shape of the curve and straight line at a section in a 
widthwise direction of the tire when the tire is mounted onto an approved
rim and inflated at a maximum air pressure under no load, and a straight
line or a chord connecting both ends of an arc drawn by a part of the
main body portion 21 over a zone ranging from a turning point P of the
main body portion on the bead core 23 to any point in a region (a length H<sub>2</sub> in a radial direction of the tire)
corresponding to 15-35% of a length H<sub>1</sub> in the radial direction of the tire
defined between a standard line S passing through an axial center of the
bead core and drawn in parallel to a rotating axis of the tire and an
outermost side of the main body portion in the radial direction and
separated from the standard line is inclined at an angle  of 45-65° with
respect to an equatorial plane O of the tire.</p><p num="0024">The turning point P of the carcass ply is a turning start point of the
carcass ply against the bead core 23. More specifically, it means a point
that the carcass ply extending straight toward the bead core 23 or convexly
extending toward the outer surface of the tire is turned about the bead core
23 and convexly inflected toward the inner surface of the tire.</p><p num="0025">That is, when the convexly curved shape toward the outer face of
the tire or the combined shape of the curve and straight line is given to the
main body portion 21 of the carcass ply at the section in the widthwise
direction of the tire, a carcass line under an inflation of an internal pressure
can be closed to a natural equilibrium shape capable of controlling the
inward falling deformation in the section as compared with the
conventional one. Moreover, the term &quot;carcass line&quot; used herein means a
center line in a thickness direction of the carcass ply constituting the main
body portion at a section in the widthwise direction of the tire. Specifically,
the carcass line means a line at a center of the arranging position of the
cord embedded in the carcass ply when using one carcass ply, or a line
of a center in total ply thickness when using two or more carcass plies. </p><p num="0026">Furthermore, the inclination angle  of the zone 21a of the main
body portion 21 ranging from the position of any point in the length (H<sub>2</sub>) measured
from the standard line S in the radial direction of the tire up to the turning
point P at the section in the widthwise direction of the tire is made to be 45-65°
with respect to an equatorial plane O of the tire, whereby the main
body portion 21 in the bead portion is arranged so as to more shift toward
the outer surface of the tire as compared with the conventional carcass line
shown in Fig. 2a. As a result, the main body 21 is disposed in the vicinity
of thickness center of the bead portion, so that the rubber thickness from
the main body portion 21 to the outer surface of the tire can be thinned as
compared with that of the conventional tire to control the deformation of an
outer surface part of the bead portion in the circumferential direction of the
tire.</p><p num="0027">When the inclination angle  is less than 45°, the carcass line
approaches to the inner surface of the tire and becomes large in the
distance from the natural equilibrium shape, while when it exceeds 65°, the
distance from the natural equilibrium shape becomes also large and the
effect of suppressing the falling-down is decreased.</p><p num="0028">Furthermore, the reason why the position of any point in the length (H<sub>2</sub>) from
the standard line S in the radial direction of the tire is restricted to a range
of 15-35% of the length in the radial direction of the tire (H<sub>1</sub>) is due to the
fact that when the position is within the above range, it is advantageous to
make the carcass line in the inflation of the internal pressure close to the
natural equilibrium shape to suppress the falling-down.</p><p num="0029">Moreover, when the zone 21a of the main body portion 21 extends
straight, the inclination angle  is an angle of a straight line with respect to
the equatorial plane O, while when the zone 21a is curved as shown in Fig.
6, the inclination angle  is an angle of a chord 21b connecting both ends 
of an arc corresponding to the curved line of the zone 21 a to each other
with respect to the equatorial plane O.</p><p num="0030">Also, when the zone 21a of the main body portion 21 is
curved as shown in Fig. 6, it is preferable that a maximum length of a
vertical line h drawn from the arc to the chord connecting both ends of the
arc to each other is not less than 2 mm, because when the maximum length
of the vertical line h is not less than 2 mm, the carcass line becomes more
close to the natural equilibrium shape and the rubber thickness between the
main body portion and the outer surface of the tire can be more thinned.</p><p num="0031">For the same reason as mentioned above, it is more preferable
that when the zone 21a of the main body portion 21 is curved, the position
of any point in the length (H<sub>2</sub>) in the radial direction of the tire corresponds to 17-25%
of the length in the radial direction of the tire (H<sub>1</sub>) from the standard line S
defining the zone 21a.</p><p num="0032">The following examples are given in illustration of the invention. </p><p num="0033">There is provided a radial tire for truck and bus according to
the invention having a structure shown in Fig. 5 a carcass line of a main
body portion of a carcass ply defined in Table 1 and tire size of
435/45R22.5. For comparison, there is provided a comparative tire
having a structure of a main body portion of a carcass ply shown in Fig. 2a
and the same tire size as mentioned above. Then, these tires are subjected
to a drum test for the evaluation of durability.</p><p num="0034">That is, the tire is mounted onto a rim of 14.00x22.5, inflated
under an internal pressure of 900 kPa and then run on a drum at a speed of
60 km/h under a load corresponding to 1.95 times a maximum load
capacity to measure a running distance until the tire can not be run due to
the occurrence of troubles in the bead portion. The measured values are
shown in Table 2. Moreover, the bead portion durability is represented by
an index of the measured value on the basis that the comparative tire is 100,
in which the larger the index value, the better the durability.</p><p num="0035">With respect to these tires, a falling-down quantity of a main body
portion of a carcass ply is measured at a state that the tire is inflated under
the above internal pressure and loaded under the above load based on a
state that the internal pressure and load are not applied to the tire.

The falling-down quantity is represented by an index on the basis that the
comparative tire is 100.</p><p num="0036">Similarly, a deformation quantity in circumferential direction of
an outer surface of a bead portion is measured at a state that the tire is
inflated under the above internal pressure and loaded under the above load 
based on a state that the internal pressure and load are not applied to the
tire. The deformation quantity in circumferential direction is represented
by an index on the basis that the comparative tire is 100.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center" /><entry align="center">Comparative tire</entry><entry align="center">Invention tire</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carcass line</entry><entry align="center">Fig. 2a</entry><entry align="center">Fig. 5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H<sub>2</sub>/H<sub>1</sub></entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">22%</entry></row><row><entry align="left"> (°)</entry><entry align="center">33</entry><entry align="center">55</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Falling-down quantity</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">75</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Deformation quantity in circumferential direction</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">84</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bead portion durability</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">160</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0037">As seen from the above, according to the invention, the wrap part
wound around the bead core along the peripheral face thereof is formed in
the carcass ply and the shape of the main
body portion of the carcass ply is made adequate, whereby the bead portion
durability can largely be improved. Especially, the invention is useful in
so-called heavy duty pneumatic radial tires used under higher internal
pressure and load.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Luftreifen, der wenigstens eine Karkassenlage aus Stahlkords umfaßt, die einen
Hauptkörperabschnitt (21), der sich ringförmig von einem Laufflächenabschnitt durch
einen Seitenwandabschnitt bis zu einem Wulstabschnitt (22) erstreckt, und einen
hochgedrehten Abschnitt, gewickelt um einen in den Wulstabschnitt (22) eingebetteten
Wulstkern (23), hat, wobei ein Teil oder die Gesamtheit des hochgedrehten Abschnitts ein
längs einer Umfangsfläche des Wulstkerns (23) gewickelter Umschlagteil (24) ist, bei
dem der Hauptkörperabschnitt (21) der Karkassenlage, an einem Schnitt in einer
breitseitigen Richtung des Reifens, wenn der Reifen auf einer zugelassenen Felge
montiert und ohne Belastung mit einem maximalen Luftdruck aufgeblasen wird, (i) eine
zu einer Außenfläche des Reifens hin konvex gekrümmte Form oder (ii) eine kombinierte
Form aus der Kurve und der geraden Linie hat und eine gerade Linie oder eine Sehne, die
beide Enden eines Bogens verbindet, der durch den Hauptkörperabschnitt (21) oder die
Karkassenlage über einen Bereich gezogen wird, der von einem Wendepunkt (P) des
Hauptkörperabschnitts (21) am Wulstkem (23) zu einem beliebigen Punkt in der Länge
(H2) in einem Bereich reicht, der 15 bis 35% einer Länge (H1) in der Radialrichtung des
Reifens entspricht, definiert zwischen einer Standardlinie (S), die durch eine axiale Mitte
des Wulstkerns geht und parallel zu einer rotierenden Achse des Reifens gezogen wird,
und einer äußersten Seite des Hauptkörperabschnitts in der Radialrichtung und getrennt
von der Standardlinie, in einem Winkel von 45 bis 60° im Verhältnis zu einer
Äquatorialebene (O) des Reifens geneigt ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Luftreifen nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß der
Hauptkörperabschnitt (21) der Karkassenlage eine Bogenform hat, die sich konvex zur
Außenfläche des Reifens hin erstreckt, über einen Bereich, der vom Wendepunkt (P) des
Hauptkörpers am Wulstkem (23) zu einem beliebigen Punkt in einem Bereich reicht, der
17 bis 25% der Länge (H1) in der Radialrichtung des Reifens, getrennt von der
Standardlinie (S), entspricht.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Luftreifen nach Anspruch 2, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß eine maximale Länge
einer vertikalen Linie (h), die von dem Bogen zu einer Sehne gezogen wird, die beide
Enden des Bogens verbindet, nicht weniger als 2 mm beträgt.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A pneumatic tire comprising at least one carcass ply of steel cords
having a main body portion (21) toroidally extending from a tread portion
through a sidewall portion to a bead portion (22) and a turnup portion
wound around a bead core (23) embedded in the bead portion (22), a part
or whole of which turnup portion being a wrap part (24) wound along a
peripheral face of the bead core (23), in which the main body portion (21)
of the carcass ply has (i) a convexly curved shape toward an outer face of
the tire or (ii) a combined shape of the curve and straight line at a section
in a widthwise direction of the tire when the tire is mounted onto an
approved rim and inflated at a maximum air pressure under no load, and a
straight line or a chord connecting both ends of an arc drawn by the main
body portion (21) or the carcass ply over a zone ranging from a turning
point (P) of the main body portion (21) on the bead core (23) to any point
in the length (H2) in a region corresponding to 15-35% of a length (H1) in
the radial direction of the tire defined between a standard line (S) passing
through an axial center of the bead core and drawn in parallel to a rotating
axis of the tire and an outermost side of the main body portion in the radial
direction and separated from the standard line is inclined at an angle 45-65°
with respect to an equatorial plane (O) of the tire.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A pneumatic tire as claimed in claim 1, characterized in that the
main body portion (21) of the carcass ply has an arc shape convexly
extending toward the outer surface of the tire over a zone ranging from the
turning point (P) of the main body on the bead core (23) to any point in a
region corresponding to 17-25% of the length (H1) in the radial direction
of the tire separated from the standard line (S).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A pneumatic tire as claimed in claim 2, characterized in that a
maximum length of a vertical line (h) drawn from the arc to a chord
connecting both ends of the arc is not less than 2 mm.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bandage pneumatique comprenant au moins un pli de carcasse de cordes en acier
possédant une partie de corps principal (21) s'étendant toroïdalement à partir d'une partie
de bande de roulement à travers une partie de flanc jusqu'à une partie de talon (22) et une
partie de retournement enroulée autour d'une tringle (23) enrobée dans la partie de talon
(22), dont la partie de retournement est partiellement ou complètement une partie
d'enveloppage (24) enroulée le long de la face périphérique de la tringle (23), dans lequel
la partie de corps principal (21) du pli de carcasse possède (i) une forme courbée de
manière convexe vers la face extérieure du pneu ou (ii) une forme combinée de courbe et
de ligne droite dans une section dans la direction de la largeur du pneu lorsque le pneu est
monté sur une jante approuvée et gonflé à une pression d'air maximale en l'absence de
charge, et dans lequel la ligne droite ou corde reliant les deux extrémités d'un arc dessiné
par la partie de corps principal (21) ou pli de carcasse sur une zone s'étendant à partir
d'un point de retournement (P) de la partie de corps principal (21) sur la tringle (23)
jusqu'à un point quelconque à une longueur (H2) dans une région correspondant à 15-35%
de la longueur (H1) dans la direction radiale du pneu définie entre une ligne standard (S)
passant à travers le centre axial de la tringle et tracée parallèlement à l'axe de rotation du
pneu et le côté le plus extérieur de la partie de corps principal dans la direction radiale et
séparé de la ligne standard est inclinée selon un angle de 45-65° par rapport au plan
équatorial (O) du pneu.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bandage pneumatique comme revendiqué dans la revendication 1, caractérisé en
ce que la partie de corps principal (21) du pli de carcasse possède une forme d'arc
s'étendant de manière convexe vers la surface extérieure du pneu sur une zone s'étendant
à partir du point de retournement (P) du corps principal sur la tringle (23) jusqu'à un point
quelconque dans une région correspondant à 17-25% de la longueur (H1) dans la direction
radiale du pneu séparé de la ligne standard (S).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bandage pneumatique comme revendiqué dans la revendication 2, caractérisé en
ce que la longueur maximale d'une ligne verticale (h) dessinée à partir de l'arc vers une
corde reliant les deux extrémités de l'arc n'est pas inférieure à 2 mm.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20060607"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060323</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20060414"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20051201"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ES</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG2A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>2243403</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>T3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20050728"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60111581</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050728</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050622"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEESFRGBIT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050622"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIC1" date="20050126"><legal-event-body><event-title>CLASSIFICATION (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 29D 30/32 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 15/00 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 15/06 A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 3/04 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 9/00 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIC1" date="20050119"><legal-event-body><event-title>CLASSIFICATION (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 29D 30/32 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 15/00 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 15/06 A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 3/04 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 9/00 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RTI1" date="20050119"><legal-event-body><event-title>TITLE (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PNEUMATIC TIRE, HAVING IMPROVED BEAD PORTION DURABILITY</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20040526"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEESFRGBIT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040121"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031205</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20040102"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20031103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20030903"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20030903"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Countries concerned </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ALLTLVMKROSI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIC1" date="20030903"><legal-event-body><event-title>CLASSIFICATION (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 29D 30/32 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 15/00 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 15/06 A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>IPC </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7B 60C 9/00 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010718"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010718"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>
