<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1130889-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1130889" kind="B1" date="20060712"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23210327" ucid="EP-1130889-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1130889</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20060712</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01104739-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01104739</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010226</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000054918-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000054918</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000229</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20060131</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  13/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  13/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  17/30        20060101ALI20010720BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  17/30        20060101CLI20010720BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  29/06        20060101ALI20010720BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  29/06        20060101CLI20010720BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/274       20060101CLI20010720BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/2745      20060101ALI20010720BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/72        20060101CFI20010622BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/725       20060101AFI20010622BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04Q   7/32        20060101ALI20010720BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04Q   7/32        20060101CLI20010720BHEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">G06F17/30W5K</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04M1/2745D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04M1/2745S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04M1/725F1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04M1/725F1W</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Tragbares Telefon und Verfahren zur Anzeige des zuletzt besuchten Internetlesezeichens (bookmark) einer Liste an erster Stelle der Liste beim nächsten Zugriff auf die Liste</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Portable telephone and method for displaying the last accessed bookmark of a bookmark list as the first entry in the list when the list is accessed the next time</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Téléphone portable et procédé pour afficher le dernier signet (bookmark) accédé d' une liste en première position dans la liste lors du prochain accès à la liste</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>MATSUSHITA ELECTRIC IND CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>MATSUSHITA ELECTRIC INDUSTRIAL CO., LTD.</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>ISHIGAKI JUNJI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>ISHIGAKI, JUNJI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>ISHIGAKI, JUNJI</last-name><address><street>95-11, Ishikawa-cho</street><city>Hachioji-shi, Tokyo 192-0032</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Matsushita Electric Industrial Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>1006, Kadoma</street><city>Kadoma-shi, Osaka</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Grünecker, Kinkeldey, Stockmair &amp;amp; Schwanhäusser Anwaltssozietät</last-name><address><street>Maximilianstrasse 58</street><city>80538 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>The Bookmark list display control program rearranges and reads the sites in the Bookmark storage area in reverse chronological order of access to sites, then displays the Bookmark list (step 51). Next, it is determined whether the target (desired) site or URL is present or not (step 52). In case the target site or URL is present, the user is automatically connected to the target site or URL by selecting the target site or URL (step 53). In case the target site or URL is absent in step 52, the user selects the Bookmark input mode and enters a new site or URL (step 54). Then, the user stores the new site or URL in the Bookmark storage area, or in case the memory of the area is insufficient, the user overwrites an old Bookmark site with this new site (step 55). &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">The Bookmark list display control program rearranges and
reads the sites in the Bookmark storage area in reverse
chronological order of access to sites, then displays the
Bookmark list (step 51). Next, it is determined whether the
target (desired) site or URL is present or not (step 52). In
case the target site or URL is present, the user is automatically
connected to the target site or URL by selecting the target
site or URL (step 53). In case the target site or URL is absent
in step 52, the user selects the Bookmark input mode and enters
a new site or URL (step 54). Then, the user stores the new
site or URL in the Bookmark storage area, or in case the memory
of the area is insufficient, the user overwrites an old Bookmark
site with this new site (step 55).
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1130782-A2-00000001" he="102" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="p0001">The present invention relates to a URL display method in a portable telephone having the non-voice information communications mode (for example i-mode) function and a portable telephone using the URL display method. The invention is particularly to display the title or URL of a site that was selected last time at the top of a Bookmark list on the screen, when a site registered to the Bookmark is selected. The non-voice information communications mode is the operation mode for the online data service using digital portable telephones, wherein a service to connect to sites (programs) registered in a center, an internet connection service, a message service, and e-mail service (for example, i-mode mail) are available.</p><p num="p0002">Conventionally, in a portable telephone having the non-voice information communications mode function, the user can activate the Bookmark operation mode to display a Bookmark list. To call a site (program) registered to the Bookmark, the user selects a target site (program) or URL (Universal Resource Locator) with a Bookmark list displayed shown in Fig. 6. This connects the user to the target site or URL.</p><p num="p0003">Here, a &quot;site (program)&quot; is displayed in title name . The user can enter the operation mode of the online data browsing service by using a portable telephone having the non-voice information communications mode function and for example connect to a site to obtain stock price information, various event information or weather forecast information.</p><p num="p0004">In a portable telephone having the non-voice information communications mode function according to the related art, a site that has been registered to the Bookmark is displayed in a fixed position of the screen. In case the Bookmark list in Fig. 6 is displayed, position of each site in the list remains unchanged when the Bookmark list is displayed next time.</p><p num="p0005">The user can connect to the site (program) &quot;stock price&quot; shown in Fig. 6A without scrolling through the screen by using a navigation key. The problem is that the user has to scroll through the screen by using the navigation key to select the site &quot;weather&quot; shown in Fig. 6B.</p><p num="p0006"><ref type="patent">EP-A-0 953 926</ref> describes an aliasing technique, which permits a browser application to link to a remote resource location on a network, when the location of the remote resource is initially unknown or likely to be changed. A communication system comprises a wired section linking the Intemet to a network gateway, and a wireless section, including a carrier network and a remote browser. The remote browser is an application program that executes on a remote computing device, such as a mobile phone, or a personal digital assistant</p><p num="p0007">A mobile device operates the remote wireless browser. The mobile device requests and receives data from the Intemet and displays information on a display of the remote computing device.</p><p num="p0008">Alias information, in form of an alias table is downloaded by the network gateway to the remote computing device and stored in memory. When a user selects a link using the browser of the mobile device, said link is associated with an alias address of the requested resource. The alias address is an alias URL, which is converted into an actual URL to retrieve the requested resource. Further, the alias table is used to re-direct the remote wireless browser to the appropriate homepage and bookmarks according to the user, device or service.</p><p num="p0009"><ref type="patent">US-A-5 907 322</ref> relates to a system for bookmarking viewer-selected television broadcast events and displaying associated information such as websites that can be retrieved from the Intemet or other networks. A TV event marking system allows a viewer, by activating a select button on a remote control to mark specified broadcast events. Upon pressing this &quot;bookmark&quot; button, an activity record entry AR comprising data such as the date, time and channel, is stored into an electronic memory of a network access device.</p><p num="p0010">These AR entries are stored in an activity table, which is stored into a network access device or in the memory of a personal computing device. When the viewer decides to browse the websites associated with the bookmarked broadcast events, the network access device or the personal computing device transmits the activity table to a central database, which is connected to the internet or other networks.</p><p num="p0011">The activity table is used to determine which data in a database should be displayed to the viewer. When the viewer activates the download button, the stored activity table is transferred via the wireless interface or the I/O interface of the remote control, to a personal computing device.</p><p num="p0012">Upon pressing the network access button, the activity table is transmitted from the computing device to the database, and in response, the network address of the website associated with the viewers bookmark is sent by database to the computing device and the corresponding website will be generated.</p><p num="p0013">An object of the present invention is to provide a Universal Resource Locator display method in a portable telephone with a non-voice information communications mode function and such a portable telephone, which enable an easier access to information located on an Internet site.</p><p num="p0014">This object is achieved by the method and apparatus according to the new independent claims.</p><p num="p0015">Preferred embodiments are the subject matter of the dependent claims.</p><p num="p0016">The invention, proposed to solve such a problem, aims at providing a URL display method in a portable telephone adapted to display the title or URL of a site that was selected last time at the top of a bookmark list on the screen, when a site registered to the bookmark is selected, and a portable telephone using the URL display method.</p><p num="p0017">The first aspect of the invention is a URL display method in a portable telephone having the non-voice information communications mode function, characterized in that the URL display method is adapted to display the title or URL of a site at the top of a Bookmark list on the screen when the Bookmark list is displayed, the site or URL selected from the Bookmark list displayed with the Bookmark operation mode activated last time in order to obtain desired information. Via this configuration, it is possible to display the title or URL of a site that was selected last time at the top of a Bookmark list on the screen, when a site registered to the Bookmark is selected.</p><p num="p0018">The second aspect of the invention is a portable telephone adapted to obtain the information on a desired site or URL by using the URL display method according to the first aspect of the invention. Via this configuration, it is possible to obtain information on a desired site or URL via a simple operation.
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Fig. 1 is a front view showing a configuration of a portable telephone according to an embodiment of the invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 shows a circuit block for realizing the portable telephone in Fig. 1;</li><li>Fig. 3 shows an example of an icon screen displayed on the display of the portable telephone in Fig. 1 in the call incoming wait state;</li><li>Fig. 4 shows a transition of the display screen of a portable telephone to describe the embodiment of the invention;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a flowchart explaining the operation to display the title of the &quot;site (program) &quot; last time at the top of the screen;</li><li>Fig. 6 shows a Bookmark list display screen on a portable telephone according to the related art.</li></ul></p><p num="p0019">An embodiment of the invention will be described referring to Figs. 1 through 6. Fig. 1 is a schematic diagram showing the structure of portable telephone equipped with the non-voice information communications mode (for example i-mode) function according to the embodiment of the invention. In Fig. 1, the portable telephone according to the embodiment of the invention comprises an antenna 1, a incoming/charge lamp 2, a receiver 3, an LCD display 4, a left soft key 5 also serving as a telephone directory button, a call start button 6, a ten-digit keypad or dial keys 7, a warp (jump) key 8 for switching to the non-voice information communications operation mode, a transmitter 9, an external connection terminal 10, a voice/manner key 11, a power/end/hold key 12, a right soft key 13 also serving as a redial/clear button, a navigation key 14 for scrolling through the display in four directions (up, down, right and left) and determining the target display by pressing the center button, an earphone microphone terminal 15, and an infrared communications port 16.</p><p num="p0020">Fig. 2 shows a circuit block for realizing a portable telephone of the aforementioned configuration. In Fig. 2, the portable telephone receives radio waves via the antenna 1 at a receiver (not shown) in a radio communications section 18. Received information is transmitted to a controller 20. The controller 20 displays the received information such as the received telephone number on the display 4 such as an LCD. The controller 20 converts the received information to voice information and outputs in voice via a speaker (receiver) 3 of the receiver section. A transmitter (microphone) 9 receives the user's voice and transmits the voice to the controller 20, which transmits the voice information to the distant party via radio communications by way of a transmitter (not shown) in the radio communications section 18 and the antenna 1.</p><p num="p0021">The controller 20 stores voice information such as speech contents during conversation in a memory 26 or reads information therefrom. A ten-digit keypad operation section 22 inputs dial signals to the controller 20 via operation of the ten-digit keypad 7. A function key operation section 24 inputs operation of a function key, such as operation of the navigation key 14 to the controller 20. An infrared input/output section 28 transmits/receives infrared signals via the infrared communications port 16.</p><p num="p0022">The controller 20 makes control so that, in case the Bookmark operation mode is activated and a desired site or URL is selected from the Bookmark list shown on the display 4 and desired information is obtained, the site or URL selected last time is displayed at the top of the Bookmark list on the screen when the bookmark list is displayed next time. These circuit blocks are housed in the cabinet in Fig. 1.</p><p num="p0023">Fig. 3 shows an example of an icon screen displayed in the call incoming wait state. In this example, the icon screen is displayed in the shape the icon screen is displayed in a cross. From top to down in clockwise direction, an i-mode main icon, an i-mode mail icon, a telephone directory icon, a screen icon, and a menu icon in the center are respectively displayed. A selected icon screen is displayed in a scaled-up image to indicate which icon screen is currently selected.</p><p num="p0024">Fig. 4 shows a transition of the display screen of a portable telephone to describe the embodiment of the invention. In the portable telephone according to this embodiment, in order to call the Bookmark, the user selects the &quot;i-mode&quot; icon on the icon screen shown in Fig. 4A to display the &quot;i-mode main&quot; screen, then presses the up or down scroll key of the navigation key 14 to call the target site or URL.</p><p num="p0025">This displays the Bookmark list shown in Fig. 4B. The user calls a target &quot;site (program)&quot; or URL by using the up or down scroll key of the navigation key 14. In case the user does not operate the up or down scroll key of the navigation key 14 in Fig. 4B, he/she can call the highlighted site &quot;weather&quot; at the top of the screen display.</p><p num="p0026">Here, &quot;site (program)&quot; is displayed in title name. The user can connect to a site registered to the Bookmark to obtain stock price information or various event information by using a portable telephone (digital portable telephone) having the non-voice information communications mode (for example i-mode) function.</p><p num="p0027">In case the &quot;site (program) &quot; that the user wish to call is the &quot;professional baseball flash&quot; shown in Fig. 4C, the user presses the up or down scroll key of the navigation key 14 to select the site then uses the selection key of the navigation key 14 to validate the selection. This connects the user to the &quot;professional baseball flash&quot; as a target &quot;site (program) &quot;.</p><p num="p0028">While connection to a &quot;site (program)&quot; is complete as understood from in the foregoing description, in a portable telephone according to this embodiment, in case a target &quot;site (program)&quot; is called once from the Bookmark list, the &quot;site (program)&quot; called last time is displayed at the top of the Bookmark list on the screen next time as shown in Fig. 4D.</p><p num="p0029">In order to display the title of the &quot;site (program)&quot; called last time, the controller 20 in Fig. 2 activates a Bookmark list display control program for controlling display of the Bookmark list. When activated, the Bookmark list display control program sorts or rearranges the Bookmark-registered sites according to the latest access date and time stored in a predetermined area of the memory 26 that stores the sites, to display the Bookmark list in reverse chronological order of access to sites. This provides the user with an advantage that the user can easily call or connect to a site (program) that is frequently called, thus providing an easy-to-use site connection procedure.</p><p num="p0030">Fig. 5 is a flowchart explaining the operation to display the title of the &quot;site (program) &quot; last time at the top of the screen. In Fig. 5, the Bookmark list display control program rearranges and reads the sites in the Bookmark storage area in reverse chronological order of access to sites, then displays the Bookmark list (step 51). Next, it is determined whether the target (desired) site or URL is present or not (step 52). In case the target site or URL is present, the user is automatically connected to the target site or URL by selecting the target site or URL (step 53). In case the target site or URL is absent in step 52, the user selects the Bookmark input mode and enters a new site or URL (step 54). Then, the user stores the new site or URL in the Bookmark storage area, or in case the memory of the area is insufficient, the user overwrites an old Bookmark site with this new site (step 55).</p><p num="p0031">As mentioned earlier, the first aspect of the invention is a URL display method in a portable telephone having the non-voice information communications mode function, characterized in that the URL display method is adapted to display the title or URL of a site at the top of a Bookmark list on the screen when the Bookmark list is displayed, the site or URL selected from the Bookmark list displayed with the Bookmark operation mode activated last time in order to obtain desired information. This configuration has an advantage that it is possible to display the title or URL of a site that was selected last time at the top of a Bookmark list on the screen, when a site registered to the Bookmark is selected.</p><p num="p0032">The second aspect of the invention is a portable telephone adapted to obtain the information on a desired site or URL by using the URL display method according to the first aspect of the invention. This configuration has an advantage that it is possible to obtain information on a desired site or URL via a simple operation.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim id="c-de-01-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Anzeigen von einheitlichen Ortsangebem für Ressourcen in einem tragbaren Telefon, wobei das tragbare Telefon eine Betriebsfunktion zur Kommunikation nicht-sprachlicher Information umfasst, und das Verfahren folgende Schritte umfasst:
<claim-text>Aktivieren eines Lesezeichen-Betriebsmodus, und</claim-text><claim-text>Anzeigen des Titels oder einheitlichen Ortsangebers für Ressourcen einer Vielzahl von in einer Lesezeichenliste gespeicherten Seiten,</claim-text><b>gekennzeichnet durch</b>

das Anordnen des Titels oder einheitlichen Ortsangebers für Ressourcen der Vielzahl von in der Lesezeichenliste gespeicherten Seiten, so dass der Titel oder einheitliche Ortsangeber für Ressourcen der zuletzt abgerufenen Seite oben in der Lesezeichenliste angeordnet wird, und

wobei der Schritt des Anzeigens den Titel oder einheitlichen Ortsangeber für Ressourcen der Vielzahl von Seiten in der angeordneten Ordnung anzeigt.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Anzeigen einheitlicher Ortsangeber für Ressourcen gemäß Anspruch 1, <b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b> der Titel oder URL einer Seite in der umgekehrten chronologischen Ordnung eines Abrufes der Seite angezeigt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Anzeigen einheitlicher Ortsangeber für Ressourcen gemäß Anspruch 1, <b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b> der Titel oder einheitliche Ortsangeber für Ressourcen in der Lesezeichenliste in der Ordnung des Abrufes angeordnet und in der angeordneten Ordnung beim Anzeigen des Lesezeichens angezeigt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>Tragbares Telefon mit einer Betriebsfunktion zur Kommunikation nicht-sprachlicher Information, umfassend:
<claim-text>Aktivierungsmittel zum Aktivieren eines Lesezeichen-Betriebsmodus, und</claim-text><claim-text>Anzeigemittel zum Anzeigen des Titels oder einheitlichen Ortsangebers für Ressourcen einer Vielzahl von in einer Lesezeichenliste gespeicherten Seiten,</claim-text><b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b> das tragbare Telefon weiterhin umfasst:
<claim-text>eine Steuereinheit (20) zum Anordnen des Titels oder einheitlichen Ortsangebers für Ressourcen der Vielzahl von in der Lesezeichenliste gespeicherten Seiten, so dass die zuletzt abgerufene Seite oben in der Lesezeichenliste angeordnet wird, und</claim-text>
wobei das Anzeigemittel angepasst ist, den Titel oder einheitlichen Ortsangeber für Ressourcen der Vielzahl von Seiten in der angeordneten Ordnung anzuzeigen.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim id="c-en-01-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>A Universal Resource Locator display method in a portable telephone having a non-voice information communications mode function, comprising steps of

activating a bookmark operation mode, and

displaying the title or Universal Resource Locator of a plurality of sites registered in a bookmark list,
<b>characterized by</b>

arranging said plurality of sites registered in said bookmark listso that the latest accessed site is located at the top of said bookmark list, and

in that said displaying step displays the title or Universal Resource Locator of said plurality of sites in the arranged order.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>The Universal Resource Locator display method according to claim 1, <b>characterized in that</b> the title or URL of a site is displayed in reverse chronological order of access to the site.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>The Universal Resource Locator display method according to claim 1, <b>characterized in that</b> the title or Universal Resource Locator in the bookmark list is arranged in an accessed order and displayed in the arranged order when the bookmark is displayed.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>A portable telephone having a non-voice information communications mode function, comprising

means for activating a bookmark operation mode, and

means for displaying the title or Universal Resource Locator of a plurality of sites registered in a bookmark list,
<b>characterized by</b> further comprising:
<claim-text>a controller (20) for arranging said plurality of sites registered in said bookmark list, so that the latest accessed site is located at the top of said bookmark list, and</claim-text><claim-text>in that said displaying means is adapted to display the title or Universal Resource Locator of said plurality of sites in the arranged order.</claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim id="c-fr-01-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>Procédé d'affichage d'adresse URL dans un téléphone portable présentant une fonction de mode de communications d'information non vocale, comprenant les étapes consistant à

activer un mode de fonctionnement de signet, et

afficher le titre ou l'adresse URL d'une pluralité de sites enregistrés dans une liste de signets,
<b>caractérisé par</b>

l'agencement du titre ou de l'adresse URL de ladite pluralité de sites enregistrés dans ladite liste de signets, de sorte que le titre ou l'adresse URL du dernier site ayant fait l'objet d'un accès est situé au sommet de ladite liste de signets, et

en ce que ladite étape d'affichage affiche le titre ou l'adresse URL de ladite pluralité de sites dans l'ordre agencé.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>Procédé d'affichage d'adresse URL selon la revendication 1, <b>caractérisé en ce que</b> le titre ou l'URL d'un site est affiché dans l'ordre chronologique inverse de l'accès au site.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>Procédé d'affichage d'adresse URL selon la revendication 1, <b>caractérisé en ce que</b> le titre ou l'adresse URL dans la liste de signets est agencé dans un ordre d'accès et affiché dans l'ordre agencé lorsque le signet est affiché.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>Téléphone portable présentant une fonction de mode de communications d'information non vocale, comprenant

un moyen destiné à activer un mode de fonctionnement de signet, et

un moyen destiné à afficher le titre ou l'adresse URL d'une pluralité de sites enregistrés dans une liste de signets,
<b>caractérisé en ce qu'</b>il comprend en outre :
<claim-text>un contrôleur (20) destiné à agencer le titre ou l'adresse URL de ladite pluralité de sites enregistrés dans ladite liste de signets, de sorte que le dernier site ayant fait l'objet d'un accès est situé au sommet de ladite liste de signets, et</claim-text><claim-text><b>en ce que</b> ledit moyen d'affichage est conçu pour afficher le titre ou l'adresse URL de ladite pluralité de sites dans l'ordre agencé.</claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20070228"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060712</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20061012</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20070119"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20060824"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60121380</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060824</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20060712"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFIFRGBNLSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20060712"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040908"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040723</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20020605"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE FI FR GB NL SE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20020327"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020115</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010912"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010912"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIC1" date="20010912"><legal-event-body><event-title>CLASSIFICATION (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7H 04M 1/725 A, 7H 04M 1/2745 B, 7H 04Q 7/32 B, 7H 04L 29/06 B, 7G 06F 17/30 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFIFRGBNLSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>