<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1510473-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1510473" kind="A2" date="20050302"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="24287339" ucid="EP-1510473-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1510473</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20050302</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04025591-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04025591</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000714</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-371209" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>371209</doc-number><date>19990810</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-609782" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>609782</doc-number><date>20000705</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="EP-00115308-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00115308</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000714</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-37120999-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>37120999</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990810</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-60978200-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>60978200</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000705</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"/><term-of-grant/><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A01M   1/20        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A01M   1/20        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   9/015       20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   9/03        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   9/04        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   9/04        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   9/12        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   9/12        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   9/14        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L   9/14        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65D  83/14        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65D  83/14        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A01M1/20C2F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A01M1/20C2H</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A01M1/20C2L</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A01M1/20C2S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A01M1/20C4G</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L9/03</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L9/04G</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L9/12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L9/12F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L9/14</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Bifunktionaler Spender</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Dual function dispenser</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Distributeur avec double fonction</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0906873-A1" source="SEA" category="X" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0906873</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2594714-A1" source="SEA" category="X" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2594714</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4084732-A" source="SEA" category="X" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>4084732</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5567073-A" source="SEA" category="X" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>5567073</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5788155-A" source="SEA" category="A" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>5788155</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5875934-A" source="SEA" category="A" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>5875934</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id></patcit></patent-citations></citations><figures/></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>JOHNSON &amp; SON INC S C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>S. C. JOHNSON &amp; SON, INC.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>S. C. Johnson &amp;amp; Son, Inc.</last-name><address><street>1525 Howe Street</street><city>Racine, WI 53403</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>FURNER PAUL E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>UICK HEIDI J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>CONNELLY JOHN P</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>CONNELLY, JOHN P.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>FURNER, PAUL E.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>UICK, HEIDI J.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>CONNELLY, JOHN P.</last-name><address><street>851 Waterford Drive</street><city>Grayskale, IL 60030</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>FURNER, PAUL E.</last-name><address><street>33400 Orion Court</street><city>Racine, WI 53406</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>UICK, HEIDI J.</last-name><address><street>139 Greshell Lane</street><city>Racine, WI 53406</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Ruschke, Hans Edvard</last-name><address><street>Ruschke Hartmann Becker Pienzenauerstrasse 2</street><city>81679 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>Dual functional dispensers, wherein the dispensers comprise dispensing units independently capable of dispensing an actively dispersed spray or an evaporative long term dispersible material, comprise active dispensers in combination with passive dispensers of volatile materials. The passive dispenser may comprise a clip-on collar. The passively dispersible material may be selected from the group consisting of fragrances, air fresheners, deodorizers, odor eliminators, malodor counteractants, insecticides, insect repellants, medicinal substances, disinfectants, sanitizers, mood enhancers, and aroma therapy compositions. The actively dispersed material may be the same or different. Refill units for such dispensers may comprise a spray can and associated control means, and an evaporative dispenser of dispersible material, provided either separately or as an integral unit. </p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">Dual functional dispensers, wherein the dispensers comprise dispensing
units independently capable of dispensing an actively dispersed spray or an
evaporative long term dispersible material, comprise active dispensers in
combination with passive dispensers of volatile materials. The passive dispenser
may comprise a clip-on collar. The passively dispersible material may be selected
from the group consisting of fragrances, air fresheners, deodorizers, odor
eliminators, malodor counteractants, insecticides, insect repellants, medicinal
substances, disinfectants, sanitizers, mood enhancers, and aroma therapy
compositions. The actively dispersed material may be the same or different. Refill
units for such dispensers may comprise a spray can and associated control
means, and an evaporative dispenser of dispersible material, provided either
separately or as an integral unit.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1511361-A2-00000001" he="113" wi="53" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no"/></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Technical Field</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to dispensers for dispersible compositions,
such as fragrances and insect control materials. More particularly, the invention
relates to active, or instant action, dispensers which are adapted for use with a
replaceable cartridge containing a dispersible of choice, but are also capable of
long term passive, or continuous, release of a dispersible substance. In one
embodiment, the invention is related to devices for dispensing compositions, e.g.
fragrances, etc., in two ways: actively, as a burst or spray of the chosen composition,
to provide an immediate and intense air treatment; and passively, as an
evaporative composition, to continuously effect the atmosphere over extended
time periods at a slow release rate. The dispersible compositions to be dispensed
by either the active dispensing means or the passive means may include
such compositions as fragrances, air fresheners, deodorizers, odor eliminators,
odor counteractants, insecticides, insect repellants, medicinal substances,
disinfectants, sanitizers, mood enhancers, aroma therapy compositions, and the
like. It is to be understood that odor eliminators include such odor absorbers as
baking soda, zeolite, and charcoal, as well as more complex chemical odor
eliminators, and that insecticides and insect repellants are examples of insect
control compositions, which also include insect attractants or baits.</p><heading><u style="single">Background Art</u></heading><p num="0002">The prior art is generally aware of dispensers for dispensing materials by
way of an aerosol or pump activated spray dispenser into the air as minute
droplets or spray, either while the dispenser is wall mounted, sitting on a level 
surface such as a table top, or hand held. Such active dispensers are frequently
used for fragrances, or for air-freshening compositions. Adams et al, in <ref type="patent">U. S.
Patent No. 5,358,147</ref>, incorporated herein by reference, teach a spray dispensing
package comprising an outer shell and a refill cartridge that fits therein and
includes a spray valve, valve stem, and a spray nozzle. The outer shell has
guide surfaces to cooperate with the refill cartridge to allow the shell to slide
smoothly relative thereto when pressure is applied to the top surface of the shell
to activate the spray valve. The materials most commonly dispersed by active
dispensers include materials selected from the group consisting of fragrances, air
fresheners, deodorizers, insecticides, and insect repellants.</p><p num="0003">In addition to such active dispensers, which require an action on the part
of the consumer to result in the immediate dispensing of the dispersible composition,
dispensers which operate passively, through evaporation or sublimation of
vaporizable substances, without active physical participation by the consumer,
are also well known. Such passive dispensers frequently comprise a porous,
absorbent medium and an evaporation surface. Volatile dispersible substances
frequently dispensed passively include fragrances, air fresheners, deodorizers,
odor eliminators, malodor counteractants, insecticides, insect repellants, medicinal
substances, disinfectants, sanitizers, mood enhancers, aroma therapy
compositions, and other volatile materials easily dispersed by evaporation over
an extended period of time. Such passive dispensing means, frequently utilizing
a wick for liquid dispersibles, are well known in the prior art, as is the common
type of dispensing device comprising a container retaining and/or supporting a
body of gelatinous matter which, as it dries and shrinks, releases a dispersible
composition into the atmosphere by evaporation or volatilization. Other passive
products, such as impregnated plastic or ceramic substrates, or deodorant
blocks, are also used to dispense air-treating vapors into the atmosphere by
evaporation. Still other forms of such passive dispensers include liquid or gel
cartridges which contain a dispersible substance which is time releasable through
a porous covering of the cartridge, such as disclosed in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent 5,788,155</ref> of
Martin et al, the teachings of which are incorporated herein by reference. For 
purposes of the present invention, active dispensers shall be those which require
an action on the part of the consumer to dispense a dispersible composition,
which is dispersed as a burst or spray, as a direct result of the action of the
consumer, while passive dispensers shall be those which require no action by the
consumer at the time that the dispersible is dispensed, but dispense a dispersible
by evaporation, sublimation, or the like, over a period of time, at a relatively low
rate of dispersement when compared to the rate of dispersement of an active
dispenser. Removal of a cover, wrapping, or control means from a passive
dispenser is not to be considered an action to dispense the composition.</p><p num="0004">In the prior art, a number of attempts have been made to combine the
features of active and passive dispensers, to provide the ability to both enhance
the atmosphere with a burst of dispersible material for immediate effect, and to
provide for a longer lasting, continuous, evaporative effect. An example of such
an attempt is set forth in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 3,972,473</ref>, of Harrison, which teaches a
combined spray and evaporative air freshener comprising an aerosol container
with a valve actuator and spray orifice so situated that spray from the aerosol is
directed onto and collected by a shroud for the container. The liquid is allowed to
collect in a cup, from which it slowly evaporates, or the liquid contacts an absorptive
ring located within the shroud, which ring is activated by the spray to release
a highly concentrated fragrance, etc. This arrangement, however, does not
provide for immediate and direct release of dispersible substance into the
atmosphere, unless the shroud and ring are removed from the dispenser.
Another such dispenser, adapted for combined continuous and instant operation,
is described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 5,364,027</ref>, of Kuhn, wherein a deformable
container for a liquid dispersible substance is fitted with two immersion tube
channels, one terminating in a spray nozzle, the other containing a wick or similar
absorbent material providing for evaporation of the liquid. Also, Muoio, in <ref type="patent">U. S.
Patent No. 4,726,519</ref>, teaches a device for both instant and continuous dispensing
of an air treatment composition. The device includes a pressurized container
with a valve stem, an actuator-overcap, and an absorbent member adjacent to the
walls of the overcap. By means for simultaneously spraying the air-treating liquid 
into the air and discharging it into the absorbent member, the device provides
both simple spraying of the air freshener and recharging of a passive dispersal
means (the absorbent member). Further, the device of Dearling, <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No.
4,084,732</ref>, may be manipulated and adjusted for simultaneous spraying into the
air and recharging of a continuous dispensing means. In such prior art techniques,
it has been found that formulations suitable for active dispersement, or
spray usage, often were unsuitable for long term passive or continuous application,
or vice versa. For example, the intensity of a dispersant may be suitable for
one application method rather than the other, such as a material suitable for
passive dispensing may have far too much intensity to be used as a spray. As a
result, compromises were frequently necessary, which often resulted in the use of
a formulation which was not fully suitable for either means of dispensing. Thus,
the use of a single formulation to provide both instant and continuous effect
usually resulted in compromising one or the other, or both.</p><p num="0005">These various devices of the prior art, incorporated herein by reference,
have a number of practical problems and disadvantages which make them
ineffective and unacceptable for use in the real world. For example, these prior
art dispensers all rely upon a single source or reservoir of dispersible material,
and the continuous or passive dispensing is dependent upon the frequency and
duration of use of the active dispenser. As a result, consumers generally do not
accept such dispensers as being truly effective as either active or passive
dispensers. Also, the consumer is unable to choose between differing dispersibles
in a given dispenser, or to change the dispersible freely. Further, a major
problem relates to the dispensing habits of users of air fresheners, who frequently
use aerosol sprays to overcome strong and isolated malodors, such as in bathrooms
or kitchens, and are very accustomed to the intense and immediate nature
of such sprays. On the other hand, while many people use continuous air
fresheners or fragrancers in their homes, they generally are unaware of the
manner in which they function, and frequently replace them at an inappropriate
time, either before they have provided their full benefit, i.e. their maximum period
of utility, or long after they have been exhausted and are thus ineffectual. Most 
often in the prior art devices, one dispenser means would be exhausted or empty
of dispersible material long before the other, causing the consumer to effect
disposal, replacement or refill at an inappropriate time. For these reasons,
among others, there is a need for dual function dispensers, or dual use dispensers
of various forms of dispersible materials, which are simple to use, economically
produced, and readily refillable by the ultimate consumer. In addition, there
is a need for a dual function dispensing device for air treatment or other dispersible
material dispensing which is not dependent upon recharging of the passive
dispensing medium from the actively dispensed material, or vice-versa, and in
which the actively dispensed material and the passively dispensed material may
be the same or differ, but under normal conditions of use will be fully dispensed in
approximately the same period of time. That is, it is desirable that both materials
be completely used up or expended at about the same time, so that the consumer
will more readily recognize and react to the need for refilling, replacing, or
disposing of the dispenser. Moreover, it is also desirable for both the actively
dispensed medium and the passively dispensed medium to be individually
refillable or replaceable, so that the consumer may provide refills or replacements
for one or the other as appropriate, or as individually desired, and so that the
consumer may utilize differing materials in the two dispensing modes if so
desired. It is to be understood, therefore, that the terms " dual use" , " dual
function" , or " dual capacity" as used herein, are intended to designate dispensing
systems for the dispensing of two or more independently released dispersible
materials, from separate and independent sources or reservoirs.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0006">An object of the invention is to provide a multi-capacity dispenser for
dispersible materials, said dispenser comprising the combination of at least one
active dispenser for an actively dispersible material, said active dispenser
comprising a reservoir containing said actively dispersible material, and means to
actively dispense said actively dispersible material from said reservoir to the
atmosphere; at least one passive dispenser for a volatile dispersible material, 
said passive dispenser comprising a reservoir containing said volatile dispersible
material, and means to control volatilization of said volatile dispersible material;
and, optionally, a dispenser package encompassing said active dispenser or
dispensers and said passive dispenser or dispensers, said dispenser package
comprising a decorative body having at least one passage therein for dispensing
said actively dispersible material from said active dispenser or dispensers, and
openings therein for passively dispensing said volatile dispersible material, said
actively dispersible material and said volatile dispersible material being individually
and independently dispensable.</p><p num="0007">An object of the invention is to provide a dispensing package for dispensing
dispersible materials, said package comprising an outer shell, and a dispensing
unit which fits within said outer shell, said dispensing unit comprising at
least one spray can containing an actively dispersible material and means for
dispensing said actively dispersible material, said dispensing unit further comprising
at least one passive dispenser containing a volatile passively dispersible
material, said passive dispenser having a membrane bonded thereto which is
permeable to vapors of said volatile material, said outer shell being adapted to
receive and cooperatively engage said dispensing unit and having openings
therein corresponding to said permeable membrane whereby said volatile
passively dispersible material may be released to the atmosphere.</p><p num="0008">A further object is to provide a multi-capacity refill package for a dual
function dispenser of dispersible materials, said refill package comprising at least
one reservoir containing a spray dispersible material, means to spray such spray
dispersible material, and at least one evaporative dispenser for a volatile dispersible
material, said evaporative dispenser comprising at least one reservoir
containing said volatile material, said reservoir having a membrane bonded
thereto which is permeable to the gaseous form of said volatile material but
impermeable to liquid or solid forms thereof, and a vapor impermeable membrane
bonded to said reservoir containing said volatile material external to said permeable
membrane to prevent volatilization of said volatile material and adapted for
removal to permit volatilization of said volatile material. The permeable membrane 
may be selected so as to control the rate of dispersal of volatile material by
means of selected porosity of the membrane.</p><p num="0009">Still another object of the invention is to provide a dual capacity dispenser
for dispersible materials, said dispenser comprising the combination of an active
dispenser for an actively dispersible material, said active dispenser comprising a
reservoir containing said actively dispersible material, and means to actively
dispense said actively dispersible material from said reservoir to the atmosphere;
a passive dispenser for a volatile dispersible material, said passive dispenser
comprising a reservoir containing said volatile dispersible material, and means to
control volatilization of said volatile dispersible material; and means to combine
said passive dispenser with said active dispenser to form a single unitary dual
function dispenser.</p><p num="0010">As utilized herein, the term " means to control volatilization" shall be taken
to include heating, cooling, control of the degree of exposure of a dispersible
containing material to the atmosphere, covering a dispersible containing material
or solid material, or any other means by which volatilization may be enhanced,
limited, or prevented. For example, a solid gel block, in a suitable dish or bowl
container, may be subject to control of volatilization by partial or complete
removal of a cap fitting over the gel. Other examples of passive dispensers
having means to control volatilization would include solid blocks of dispersible, or
impregnated ceramic, plastic, or paper substrates, having removable cover
materials, or adjustable cap means to control air flow over the substrate, either by
means of adjustable vents or by means of a movable or removable cover or lid,
effecting control of the amount of surface area exposed to the atmosphere, and
thus controlling the rate of evaporation of the volatile. Also considered within the
scope of the term " means to control volatilization" would be control or selection
of the permeability of a membrane covering, enclosing, or encompassing a
volatile material, or control of the area of vent opening of a decorative body
encompassing a gel package of passively dispersed material. In such an example,
the dispenser package per se may be considered as a means to control
volatilization, if the dispenser package has vent holes therein to permit vapor 
escape. Likewise, it is possible for the dispenser package or shell to be the
passive material dispenser itself, as in the case of an impregnated plastic or
ceramic shell having a dispersible material incorporated in the pores thereof.</p><p num="0011">It is thus an object of the present invention to provide a dispenser for
dispersible materials which is able to simultaneously provide a burst of dispersible
material into the air and to passively dispense the same material or a different
material into the atmosphere by evaporation, over an extended time period. It is
a further object of this invention to provide a dispenser which will be easily and
conveniently refilled by the consumer upon exhaustion of the contents of one or
both dispersible material reservoirs of the dispenser, either by refilling or by
replacing the reservoirs for one or both dispersible materials. It is a still further
object of the invention to provide a means by which the consumer may spray a
dispersible substance into the atmosphere as desired, while providing a passive
long-term continuous action fragrancing means. It is a still further object of the
present invention to provide a dispenser in which the consumer may provide
varying effect, by utilization of differing refill units or replacement units for both
the actively dispensed material and the passively dispensed material. Still
further, it is an object of the invention that the consumer be able to vary, at will
and at his or her own discretion, the contents of either or both of the dispensing
modes of the dual function dispenser of this invention.</p><p num="0012">These and still other objects and advantages of the present invention will
be apparent from the description which follows. While the description which
follows frequently refers to an air freshener or fragrancing application, it is to be
understood that the invention is also applicable to other forms of dispersible
materials which may be dispensed either actively or passively, such as deodorizers,
odor eliminators, malodor counteractants, insecticides, insect repellants,
medicinal substances, disinfectants, sanitizers, mood enhancers, aroma therapy
compositions, and the like.</p><p num="0013">It is also to be understood that while this specification is written in terms of
dual use, i.e. two modes of operation, it is within the scope of the invention to use
three or more individual dispensers within the context of a single multiple use 
apparatus. Thus, the invention may encompass a dispenser comprising a single
active dispenser for providing a rapid burst of dispersible material, with two or
more associated passive dispensers, said dispensers containing the same or
different dispersants, for long term passive, evaporative dispensing of dispersible
materials. Similarly, two or more active dispensers may be utilized with one or
more passive dispensers, thus providing a dispenser of multiple dispersible
materials. Further, the term active dispenser, as used herein, is intended to
encompass, without limitation, all forms of rapid dispensers, inclusive of pressurized,
aerosol, bellows, air displacement, and pump action dispensers, including
reservoirs of compressed gaseous active material. While these dispensers are
frequently cylindrical in shape, with a spray nozzle or control at the top, it is
understood that various configurations and shapes of such active dispensers are
equally suitable. Likewise, the term passive dispenser, as used herein, is
intended to encompass, but not be limited to the various disclosed forms of
passive dispensers, including gel cartridges, impregnated porous structures, and
evaporative solid or liquid material dispensers including those utilizing wicking
and evaporation, with or without heat or other means to increase rates of vaporization,
such as fans. As previously indicated, active dispensers are to be
considered those in which a positive action is required by the consumer to obtain
dispensing of the dispersible material, said action constituting more than opening
of a package, removal of a vapor inhibiting barrier, or turning on a fan or heating
element. The following description is merely of the preferred embodiments,
provided in terms of air freshening or fragrancing for convenience, and the claims
should be looked to in order to understand the full scope of the invention.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0014"><sl><li>Figure 1 illustrates a perspective view of one example of a dual function
dispenser of the present invention.</li><li>Figure 2 illustrates an exploded sectional view of the dual capacity
dispenser of Figure 1, showing the relationship of various components thereof. </li><li>Figure 3 illustrates a dual capacity refill unit for the dispenser of Figures 1
and 2, said refill unit comprising a spray cartridge for active release of a dispersible,
and a gel cartridge assembly for passive release of a dispersible. The
continuous acting or passive dispersible is shown as provided in the form of a
twin cartridge which is configured so as to fit across the top of the active dispenser
in accordance with the present invention. Figure 4 represents an
exploded detail of the dual capacity refill unit of Figure 3, illustrating in greater
detail the relationship of a preferred embodiment of a passive dispenser to the
active dispenser of Figures 2 and 3.</li><li>Figure 5 represents a cross sectional view of the dispenser of the present
invention showing the relationship of the outside shell or case to the dual capacity
refill unit of Figure 3..</li><li>Figure 6 represents an example of a gel cartridge assembly suitable for
use in the dispenser of the present invention, comprising twin cartridges connected
end-to-end with a flexible hinge means, shown with the removable
membrane in place over the twin gel reservoirs.</li><li>Figure 7 represents a sectional view of the cartridge of Figure 6, taken
along lines 7-7 of Figure 6.</li><li>Figure 8 illustrates a perspective view of a preferred embodiment of a twin
gel cartridge refill assembly, illustrating the relationship of the gel reservoirs.</li><li>Figure 9 illustrates the top view of the twin gel cartridge of Figure 8.</li><li>Figure 10 is a sectional view of the cartridge of Figure 9, taken along lines
10-10 of Figure 9.</li><li>Figure 11 is a sectional view of the cartridge of Figure 9, taken along lines
11-11 of Figure 9.</li><li>Figure 12 is a perspective view of a dispenser package of the present
invention, comprising an aerosol active dispenser with a clip-on passive dispenser.</li><li>Figure 13 is a top view of the dispenser package of Figure 12, showing the
relationship of the individual dispenser units. </li><li>Figure 14 is a perspective view of a dispenser package comprising an
aerosol dispenser with an adhesively attached passive dispenser.</li><li>Figure 15 illustrates a cross sectional view of an alternative form of
dispenser package.</li><li>Figure 16 illustrates a cross sectional view of another form of dispenser,
incorporating a solid passively dispensed dispersible.</li><li>Figure 17 illustrates a perspective view of the dispenser package of Figure
16, showing the removable barrier film.</li><li>Figure 18 illustrates a low profile dispenser in exploded view.</li><li>Figure 19 illustrates a cross sectional view of the low profile dispenser
package of Figure 18.</li></sl></p><heading>BEST MODES FOR CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0015">The dispenser illustrated in Figure 1 represents a typical configuration of a
dual function dispenser of the present invention. Shown is a dispenser, 1,
comprising a shell or shroud, 2, a spray control button, 3, a spray tip 4, having
spray nozzle orifice 20, and a base, 5, which is joined to shell 2 by means of
cooperative latch mechanism 8 and latch opening 7. Vent openings, 6, are cut
through the shell, permitting air flow to and from the interior of the shell.</p><p num="0016">Figure 1 may also be seen to represent a configuration of the present
invention wherein the outer shell, 2, is in fact the passive dispenser per se.
Exemplary of such an embodiment would be a shell fashioned of porous plastic or
ceramic, impregnated with a volatile dispersible material. Not illustrated, but
within the scope of this concept, is a vapor impermeable wrap or enclosure over
the surface of such a shell, retaining the volatile dispersible until such time as the
wrap or enclosure is removed by the consumer, or a vapor impermeable packaging
containing the dual capacity dispenser, which upon removal of the dispenser
from the packaging permits evaporation of the volatile material from the outer
shell of the dispenser. Such a shell may comprise an impregnated ceramic, or an
inexpensive, easily moldable polymeric material such as polyethylene, polypropylene, 
or silicone, such as provided under the tradename POLYIFF, by International
Flavors and Fragrances. Such an impregnated dispenser shell may be
configured as shown in figure 1, with a spray control button, 3, a spray tip 4,
spray nozzle orifice 20, and base 5, joined to the shell 2 by means of cooperative
latch mechanism 8 and latch opening 7. Whereas vent openings, 6, as illustrated,
are cut through the shell to permit air flow to and from the interior of the
shell for release of a volatile material from a reservoir contained within the shell,
such openings may be omitted, or may be decorative only, when the shell is itself
the passive dispenser of a volatile dispersible. Also included within the scope of
this concept would be a spray device for active dispensing of a dispersible
material, said spray device being encompassed by a sachet of passively dispersible
volatile material.</p><p num="0017">As shown in Figure 2, the enclosure shell, or shroud, 2 encloses a dual
capacity refill unit 11, comprising a spray container 12, and a gel cartridge
dispenser 30. The shell or shroud, 2, is the exterior surface of the dispenser, and
as such is subject to visual inspection as well as being picked up and handled
during spray dispensing. Accordingly, the shell is desirably visually attractive and
of suitable dimensions that it may be left in view in the area of usage for greatest
effectiveness during evaporative dispensing. Preferably, the shell is constructed
of a durable, but economical, material such as plastic, glass, or ceramic. The gel
cartridge 30 is preferably a twin cartridge air freshener device of the type taught
in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 5,788,155</ref>, of Martin et al, incorporated herein in its entirety by
reference. Such an air freshener device comprises a pair of cartridge units
connected end-to-end by a flexible hinge portion, 31, adapted to engage, via
centering hole 33, the spray stem, 22, of a spray container, 12, and thus engaged,
to lie in parallel contiguous relationship to the lengthwise dimension of
said spray container. Thus positioned, as shown in Figures 2 - 5, the gel cartridges
overlay a substantial portion of the diameter and length of said spray
container, with the passive dispenser units on opposed sides of said spray
container, preferably proximate to the vent openings, 6, of the shell or shroud, 2.
It is to be noted that the vapor permeable side of the gel package faces to the 
outside, i.e. away from the spray container, so as to obtain the greatest available
permeation and flow of the volatile gel material through the permeable surface to
the atmosphere. Figures 6 - 10 illustrate suitable embodiments of a passive
dispenser unit of the invention, with figures 8-10 illustrating a preferred embodiment.
While the illustrations and the text of this description of the invention
speak in terms of twin gel cartridge units, it is to be understood that any number
of twin or individual passive dispensers may be used, spaced about the diameter
of the active dispenser container as desired, and comprising passive dispensers
of types other than gel dispensers, such as liquid containing cartridges, impregnated
plastic evaporative units, impregnated paper units, blotters, etc. It is also
to be understood that a single gel cartridge or passive dispenser unit may be
employed, located so as to abut one side of said spray container and shell
assembly, and to lie between said spray container and said shell, positioned
properly either by means of a cooperative fitting with the spray tip assembly of
said spray container and said spray container, positioning ribs or protrusions on
the inside of the shell, or a combination of such means. Further, one or more gel
cartridges of other passive dispenser units may be deployed in conjunction with
one or more active dispenser units, so as to provide a dispenser having a
multitude of possible dispersible materials. It is understood that the shell or
shroud of the dual capacity dispenser is preferably an enclosure for the active
and passive dispenser units, and as such thus creates an evaporation space for
the passive dispenser, which evaporation space communicates with the atmosphere
by way of the vents, 6. The shell may be structured so as to have internal
ribs and or protrusions to cooperatively engage the active dispenser or the
passive dispenser, or both, thus providing means by which the consumer is
prevented from improper placement of the dispensers within the shell. When twin
gel cartridge units, or plural single cartridge units, are employed, they may
contain the same or differing dispersible materials, and the consumer may
activate any or all of said cartridges at his or her option, by removal of outer
impermeable barrier membranes over the surfaces thereof, prior to engagement
with the shell. Thus, the consumer may choose to utilize only one passive 
dispenser unit at a time, providing longer life for the passive dispenser. Alternatively,
the consumer may choose to use multiple passive dispenser units simultaneously,
providing additional strength, or if differing dispersible materials are
employed, providing a blend of the consumers choice. In addition to the possible
use of the shell to comprise the passive dispenser itself, a dispensing shell may
be used to encompass another, independent, passive dispenser, such as single
or multiple gel cartridges, thus providing for dispensing of multiple passive
dispersibles. Moreover, it is also to be understood that the passive dispenser
means may lie outside the shell or shroud, or may be attached directly to the
active dispenser in the absence of a decorative shell or shroud, as shown, for
example, in Figures 12 - 19. It is also possible for the performance of the passive
dispenser to be enhanced, by such means as provision of a fan to more rapidly
draw air across the surface thereof, or by heating so as to cause more rapid
evaporation of the volatile material. </p><p num="0018">Figure 3 illustrates the combination of the individual components of a dual
capacity refill cartridge, 11. As shown, the gel cartridge assembly, 30, constituting
a twin cartridge dispenser unit, is centered upon the spray container 12, and
hangs downwardly on both sides thereof. Each gel cartridge, 32, comprises an
elongated shallow tray, 34, providing a reservoir for the storage of a volatile
medium, with a thin permeable membrane sealing said reservoir enclosure, a
volatile dispersant medium in the reservoir enclosure, and a thin removable
impermeable membrane which is laminated coextensively with the permeable
membrane to prevent premature volatilization of the dispersant.</p><p num="0019">Figure 4 further illustrates the relationship of the component parts of a dual
capacity refill unit, in exploded view, showing the gel cartridge 30, which is
configured to be fitted across the top of the spray container 12, by means of
centering hole 33 in central portion 31, designed to pass over the top surface, 26,
of the spray valve body, so as to come to rest in a force fit against the upper
vertical sides of the spray container. The spray container, 12, as illustrated,
comprises a reservoir can 18, formed from a can body onto which a standard
spray valve, such as an aerosol valve which may be a metering valve, or a pump
spray valve, having valve stem 22, is located by means of valve crimp 24. The
spray valve body has a top surface 26, which is useful in centering the spray can
in the shroud or shell into which the spray can is inserted either as a refill or as
the initial spray container. When positioned within the shroud or shell, the spray
can 18, having valve stem 22, is in fluid communication with spray nozzle orifice
20, via spray tip 4 as seen in Figure 2. The spray valve is appropriately actuated
by such means as a spray button, 3, as shown in Figures 1 and 2, or by such
other actuation means as may be selected by one skilled in the art. In operation,
the spray control button 3 is depressed, actuating the spray container 12, upon
demand. This results in a spray of dispersant being released from the spray
container as desired, to provide an immediate effect or to increase the potency of
dispersible available to the consumer. It is preferred that the spray container be
controlled by a dosage measuring spray valve, such that a specific amount of
dispersant is released from the spray container at each actuation. In such 
actuation control, merely holding the spray button down does not result in a
continuous spray of dispersible from the container, which is wasteful and less
efficient than controlled dosage spraying. In addition, the gel cartridge dispenser
releases dispersible at a predetermined and essentially constant rate, by evaporation,
as a result of the vapor impermeable membrane having been removed, or
peeled, from the cartridge gel reservoirs, 34. The dispersible gel, which may be
any of those known in the art, is restrained within the cartridge by a thin vapor
permeable membrane, which permits evaporation of the dispersible at a preestablished
rate.</p><p num="0020">Figure 5 represents a cross sectional view of a dual capacity dispenser of
the present invention. The dispenser, 1, comprises shell 2, base 5, and a dual
capacity refill unit 11, which in turn comprises spray container 12, and gel
cartridge passive dispenser 30, having gel reservoir 34. The shell comprises a
spray control button 3, with a spray tip 4, having spray nozzle orifice 22 therein
aligned with the valve stem 22 of the spray container. The shell interlocks with
base 5 by means of latch opening 7, which aligns with the base latch opening 8.
As illustrated, shell 2 also incorporates chamfer means 9, to receive and position
valve stem 22 of the spray container as it is inserted into the shell, thus assuring
proper alignment, as well as stop means, 10, to abut base 5, to prevent the
consumer from attempting to push the base and refill unit too far into the shell.
Also illustrated are rib protrusions 28, inside the shell, positioned to cooperatively
engage the chamfered portion 29 of the gel cartridge, so as to properly align the
gel cartridge with the face of the shell and with the centrally located spray
container 12. By this arrangement, the consumer is assured of being able to
simply and correctly insert a fresh dual capacity refill unit into the shell and base
assembly of the dispenser as desired or as necessary. Of course, the consumer
may also choose to insert only one individual refill unit rather than both an active
dispenser and a passive dispenser, if desired, thus replacing only the active
dispenser, or only the passive dispenser, at will.</p><p num="0021">The prior art is generally aware of aerosol dispensers for dispensing pressurized
materials into the air. See, for example, Adams et al, <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 
5,358,147</ref>, Miller et al, <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 5,862,960</ref>, and Miller et al, <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent
No. 5,875,934</ref>, all of which are incorporated herein by reference. These references
relate to aerosol dispensers having refill cartridges for dispensing such
compositions as perfumes into the air as an air freshener, or insect control
ingredients for home use. Such dispensers comprise an aerosol can to contain a
pressurized material to be dispensed, a nozzle having a delivery tube in fluid
communication with the can and a spray orifice through which the pressurized
material can escape from the delivery tube, and valve means for controlling the
release of the pressurized material into the nozzle delivery tube. In addition, PCT
published Application <ref type="patent">WO92/04419</ref> discloses aerosol compositions packaged
within a metering valve aerosol having a high level of perfume. Formulations and
metering valves such as described in this patent can be used in the device of the
present invention. Of particular utility in the present invention are those aerosol
cartridges which fit within the outer shell of the presently described dispenser, the
refill cartridge including a spray container having a can body and a valve including
a valve stem, such as described by Adams et al, <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 5,358,147</ref>.
The use of metering or metered dosage valves is of particular value, permitting
the dispenser of the present invention to enable the consumer to employ a predetermined
spray volume or dosage, and to utilize the spray feature of the
present invention for a predetermined number of applications. It has been found
to be particularly useful to use a spray dispenser having a container of approximately
60 to 200 ml capacity, preferably about 120 ml capacity, with a metering
valve which dispenses from about 50 to about 250 sprays, preferably from about
60 to about 150, and most preferably from about 90 to about 100 sprays from the
container before the container is empty or exhausted, dependent upon the needs
and/or usage patterns of the consumer.</p><p num="0022">Figure 6 represents an example of a gel cartridge assembly suitable for
use in the dispenser of the present invention, viewed from the side of the removable
impermeable membrane which seals the reservoir enclosure shut. The twin
cartridges, joined end-to-end by flexible central hinge portion 31, having a
centering hole 33 therein, may be folded over at seams 35, and fit over the top of 
a spray container, 12, the cartridges extending downwardly parallel to the length
of the spray container, as illustrated in Figures 2 - 5. While Figure 6 illustrates an
air freshener cartridge device suitable for use in the present invention having a
design printed upon the impermeable membrane which is removed to activate the
cartridge or cartridges, it is understood that no such design is necessary. As
illustrated in Figures 6 and 7, each of such twin cartridges, 32, is a structural
assembly comprising an elongated shallow tray, 34, having side walls with an
upper edge flange, 36, which forms a peripheral margin around the open space of
the tray, with a thin membrane, 38, which covers the open space of the tray 34
and is bonded to the flange peripheral margin. The membrane 38 forms a sealed
reservoir enclosure 39 within the tray interior, said membrane, 38, being permeable
to the vapor form of the volatile medium, 40, which is contained within the
reservoir enclosure, but not the liquid or solid form. A thin, peelable, impermeable
membrane, 41, is laminated coextensively with the permeable membrane to
prevent volatilization of the dispersant medium through the permeable membrane
38, from the reservoir enclosure, 39, prior to the intended utilization of the
cartridge. Activation of the cartridge is accomplished by removal, e.g. peeling, of
the impermeable membrane 41. A gel cartridge dispenser, 30, such as shown in
Figure 6, has a semi-rigid structure, and may be typically from about four to eight
inches in length, about one half to one inch in width, and about one sixteenth to
one half inch in thickness. A preferred volume of such a cartridge is sufficient to
hold from about 2 to 4 grams of gel, but the volume may vary to contain from 0.5
to about 10 grams of gel. Such a dispenser may be utilized by peeling the outer
impermeable membrane, 41, partially or completely from one cartridge, or peeling
said outer impermeable membrane from both of the twin cartridges, and folding
the dispenser at seam lines 35 of hinge 31 so as to place the twin cartridges
approximately parallel to each other, and inserting the valve stem, 22, and the top
surface of the spray valve body, 26, of a spray can, through hole 33, so as to
drape the passive dispenser down both sides of said spray can. It is clear that
the reservoir enclosure may take a variety of shapes, and that various configurations
thereof are possible, such as having ribs therein which serve both to 
reinforce the enclosure and to key the enclosure into a conformational slotted
space in the dispenser shell. It is also evident that single reservoir cartridges
may be provided, in which only one reservoir of dispersant is present, which may
be utilized in alternative forms of dual capacity dispensers, or in the dual capacity
dispenser of Figures 1 and 5, suitably modified for acceptance of such a single
reservoir passive dispenser.</p><p num="0023">As illustrated in Figures 8 - 11, a preferred cartridge assembly may be
configured to fit the side of the active spray container 12. As shown, the twin gel
cartridge 30, comprises a pair of reservoir enclosures 39 adjacent to a central
hinge portion having centering hole 33 and folding seams or hinge points 35. To
enable the individual dispenser cartridges to conform to the spray container when
the twin gel cartridge dispenser is folded and placed over the top thereof, the
reservoir enclosures are provided with a conforming configuration, 42, shaped to
fit about the side of the spray container and to accept the circumference thereof.
It has also been found advantageous that the cartridges angle slightly outwardly
from top to bottom of the spray container, at an angle of about 7 degrees from the
vertical as measured at the hinge point of the cartridge. This angle assists in
holding the refill unit in position in the shell, and contacting more of the content of
the cartridge tray with the permeable membrane, as well as bringing the permeable
membrane in closer proximity to the vent area of the shell or shroud of the
dispenser. The area of the shell which is cut away or removed to form the vent
area should be in proximity to the dispensing area of the cartridge, i.e. the area of
permeable membrane which is uncovered by removal of the impermeable surface
membrane. Further, it has been found advantageous that the open area of the
vents correspond to approximately 25 to 90 percent, preferably 40 to 60 percent,
and most preferably 45 to 55 percent of the surface area of the permeable
membrane through which the dispersant is released, to achieve control of the rate
of release of the dispersant so as to maintain the desired dispensing life. It is
desired that the dispenser have a useful life span of up to two months, about 60
days, preferably about one month, or thirty days. While this rate of dispensing
may, alternatively, be controlled by selection of the porosity of the permeable 
membrane and the volatility of the dispersant, it has been found that control of the
vent surface area ratio, i.e. the ratio of the area of the open vent in the shell to
the area of the exposed permeable membrane, is the simplest manner in which
one may directly effect the length of time that the cartridge will continue to
dispense vapor. That is, the greater the amount of vent area aligned with the
dispensing surface of the passive dispenser, the more rapidly said passive
dispenser will disperse its volatile content. It is also considered feasible that the
vent area be adjustable, by such means as sliding members which control the
area of vent opening which is open or closed, so as to permit more or less rapid
evaporation of the content of the cartridge, in accordance with the personal
preference or needs of the consumer. An example of such a sliding member
would be a plastic plate conforming to the inside of the shell proximate the vent
openings, and adapted to be removed, or displaced either vertically or horizontally
so as to adjust the area of vent openings which are open for circulation of air
from the interior to the exterior of the shell.</p><p num="0024">The elongated tray, 34, may be constructed by either injection or thermoform
molding of a thermoplastic polymer such as polyethylene, polypropylene,
polyvinyl chloride, and the like. In a preferred embodiment, end-to-end attached
trays 34, and interconnecting flexible hinge band 31, are thermoformed as a
unitary structure, and preferably include folding seams 35 to facilitate a 90
degree fold. The thin film vapor-impermeable membrane 41 is bonded to thin film
vapor-permeable membrane 38 in the form of a laminate. Vapor-impermeable
film 41 is peelable, so that its removal allows volatile dispersant ingredient 40 to
migrate through vapor-permeable membrane 38 and volatilize into the atmosphere.
Removable or peelable membrane 41 can be adapted for removal from
both cartridge units at the same time, or from each cartridge unit independently.
Vapor-permeable membrane 38 can be in the form of a flexible thin film of a
thermoplastic polymer such as polyethylene, isotactic polypropylene, cellulose
acetate, and the like. Membrane 38 permits migration of the enclosed volatile
dispersant ingredient 40, either as a liquid or a vapor, depending on the type of
membrane employed. Membrane 38 may be a microporous type, having submicron 
pores, such as isotactic hydrophobic polypropylene film sold under the
tradename CELGARD, by Celanese, Inc. Microporous thermoplastic polymer
films are described in <ref type="patent">Patent No. 3,055,297</ref>, incorporated herein by reference. It
is also advantageous that the vapor permeable membrane, 38, which encloses
the dispersible material in the gel cartridge be transparent, or minimally opaque,
so as to permit observation of the contents of the reservoir enclosure by the
consumer, so as to permit the consumer to judge the remaining life span of the
cartridge, and thus to observe when replacement is appropriate. This is also true
for cartridges in which the passive dispersible is in the form of an evaporative
solid or liquid rather that a gel.</p><p num="0025">Vapor impermeable membrane 41 may be in the form of a flexible thin film
such as aluminum foil or nylon film, which is peelable from its adhering bond to
vapor-permeable membrane 38. In a preferred embodiment, a laminate of
membrane 41 and membrane 38 is preformed, and then applied to tray 34 to
cover the open interior, and heat-sealed along periphery flange 36 to enclose the
reservoir content of dispersible ingredient 40. The dispersible ingredient 40 can
be any dispersible material which can migrate through membrane 38 and disperse
into the atmosphere in vapor form.</p><p num="0026">In addition to the configurations illustrated in Figures 1 - 11, it is possible
to provide dispensers such as illustrated in Figures 12 - 19, wherein the passive
dispenser may be attached directly to the spray container, or to the decorative
shell itself, or to an overcap for the spray container, for example.</p><p num="0027">In one embodiment, Figures 12 and 13 illustrate a dual capacity dispenser
comprising separate active and passive dispenser units, wherein the passive
dispenser is removably attached directly to the exterior circumference of the
active spray container. In this manner, the consumer may readily replace one or
the other dispenser without replacing both. As shown, a conventional spray
container, 51, such as an aerosol air freshener, may be provided with a clip-on
collar type of passive dispenser, 52. Such a clip-on dispenser may readily be
fashioned of economical materials, such as plastic, having sufficient elasticity that
it may readily be forced over the diameter of the spray container. Advantageously, 
as shown in Figure 13, such a clip-on dispenser may comprise a slot,
opening, or receptacle, 53, for positioning a gel cartridge dispenser 54, or other
passive dispenser, preferably in juxtaposition to vent openings 56 in said clip-on
dispenser, which permit circulation of air into and away from the passive dispenser,
54. Alternatively, the passive dispenser may simply comprise a single
gel dispenser cartridge, 54, which may be directly attached to the surface
diameter of the spray container, 51, or other form of active dispenser, by such
means as an adhesive backing, as shown in Figure 14. As such an externally
applied dispenser, the passive dispenser may take the form of a gel dispenser,
an impregnated plastic strip, a saturated porous medium, a plastic container of
the " break to activate" type, or any other suitable form of passive release
medium, suitably adhered to or attached to the active dispenser.</p><p num="0028">Still further, the passive dispenser means may be incorporated directly into
the cap or cover of an active dispenser, such as shown in Figure 15. This type of
active dispenser comprises a spray dispenser 51, such as an aerosol dispenser,
and refill cartridges therefore, with the outside cap or shell having the passive
dispenser, in the form of a gel dispenser, for example, built directly into the shell,
inserted therein, or attached thereto. This type of dispenser could be very similar
in appearance to the dispenser of Figure 1, but with the passive dispenser being
a separate unit, a part of the shell or cover rather than part of a dual refill unit. As
shown in Figure 15, spray dispenser 51 is encompassed or fitted with a dispenser
cap, 55, having interactive relationship with the spray mechanism, 57 of the spray
dispenser. A gel cartridge, 54, or other passive dispenser, is fitted into a receiving
pocket or slot in the dispenser cap 55, so as to place the evaporative surface
area thereof in juxtaposition with vent openings 56, in the dispenser cap.</p><p num="0029">Still another embodiment is shown in Figures 16 and 17, wherein the
overcap 55 is, in itself, a container or reservoir for a solid, liquid or gel passive
dispersible, 59. In this case, the impermeable barrier 58 may be external to the
vent openings, 56, in the shell or overcap. The overcap may be provided with
one or more vent areas, 56, which are sealed by the peelable or removable
impermeable barrier 58 when provided to the ultimate consumer, who then may 
choose to open one or more of said vent areas to obtain the desired level of
dispensing of passive dispersible. As in the previous embodiment, the overcap
55 may be designed so as to fit over and cooperatively engage the spray dispensing
means 57 of a spray dispenser can, 51. In this type of dispenser, merely
pushing downwardly on the overcap or shell will activate the spray dispensing
means, providing a burst of active dispersant. In such an embodiment, the
consumer may replace either or both of the active dispensing means (the spray
container and spray dispensing means assembly) and the passive dispensing
means (the overcap, containing the passive dispersant) at any given time. Since
each dispensing means may contain one of a number of different dispersants, a
large number of alternatives are available to the consumer.</p><p num="0030">Similarly, the dual capacity dispenser may take the form of a low profile
dispenser, comprising a low tray or container of passive dispersible partially or
entirely encircling or encompassing an active spray container, as shown in
Figures 18 and 19. In this embodiment, a low profile top housing, 60, having vent
openings 66 about all or part of its periphery, is fitted over a low profile passive
dispenser, 61, which encompasses a central spray dispenser, 62. As with the
previously discussed embodiment, the top housing, 60, may cooperatively
engage the spray dispenser mechanism 63 of the spray dispenser, such that
merely pushing downwardly on said top housing will cause a burst of active
dispersible to be released. The top housing may be removably attached to the
passive dispenser, 61, such as by threading, clip action, compression fit, or other
conventional joining means which permit ready removal. The passive dispenser,
61, comprises a container, 64, preferably having a low profile, which contains a
passive dispersible 65. The passive dispersible may constitute a solid, a liquid,
or a gel, and is protected by a peel away foil 67 or impermeable barrier which is
adhered to the top flange 68 of the container 64.</p><p num="0031">In addition to the above-described embodiments, other appropriate
arrangements combining an active dispensing means and a passive dispensing
means will be apparent to one skilled in the art. For example, a bellows means
for expulsion of saturated air would constitute a suitable active dispenser, since it 
is dependent upon an action of the consumer to deliver dispersible material to the
atmosphere, while saturation of the air to be dispensed may be accomplished by
evaporation of a dispersible from a reservoir of passively dispersible material into
a separate reservoir for dispersion by the action of the bellows. Further, passive
dispensers may be considered to include such means as heated substrates which
are impregnated or saturated with a liquid passive dispersible, as well as heated
gel cartridges, solid dispersibles, or the like. Still further, passive dispensers may
be combined with such air flow means as fans, either spring driven or electric, to
increase the distribution of passively dispensed dispersibles. Active dispensers
are understood to include pumps, aerosols, propellant driven dispensers, and
bladder contraction means or bellows. In addition to the dual capacity dispensers
described hereinabove, the invention includes dispensers having both active and
passive dispensers wherein the passive dispenser is heated and/or subjected to
forced air flow, such as in a battery operated or plug-in unit, wherein said unit
also comprises a button or nozzle activated dispenser, i.e. an active dispenser.
Such a dispenser would be of particular interest for such locations as a kitchen
counter, where it could be plugged into a wall outlet for enhanced passive
provision of an air freshener, while remaining available for a spray discharge of
an actively dispersed material such as a fragrance or deodorizer.</p><p num="0032">Typically, an ingredient suitable for inclusion in the evaporative cartridge,
or passive dispenser, for the present invention is a fragrance, air freshener,
deodorizer, odor eliminator, malodor counteractant, insecticide, insect repellant,
medicinal substance, disinfectant, sanitizer, mood enhancer, aroma therapy
composition, or the like, in liquid or gel form, although gels are preferred for the
present invention. Preferably, the fragrance or air freshener is a fragrance
comprising one or more volatile organic compounds which are available from
perfumery suppliers such as Firmenich Inc., Takasago Inc., Noville Inc., Quest
Co., International Flavors &amp; Fragrances, and Givaudan-Roure Corp. Most
conventional fragrance materials are volatile essential oils. The fragrance can be
a synthetically formed material, or a naturally derived oil such as oil of Bergamot,
Bitter Orange, Lemon, Mandarin, Caraway, Cedar Leaf, Clove Leaf, Cedar Wood, 
Geranium, Lavender, Orange, Origanum, Petitgrain, White Cedar, Patchouli,
Lavandin, Neroli, Rose absolute, and the like.</p><p num="0033">A wide variety of chemicals are known for perfumery, such as aldehydes,
ketones, esters, alcohols, terpenes, and the like. A fragrance can be relatively
simple in composition, or can be a complex mixture of natural and synthetic
chemical components. Synthetic types of fragrance compositions either alone or
in combination with natural oils are described in <ref type="patent"><ref type="patent">U. S. Patent Nos. 4,324,915;
4,411,829; and 4,434,306</ref></ref>; incorporated herein by reference. Other artificial liquid
fragrances include geraniol, geranyl acetate, eugenol, isoeugenol, linalool, linalyl
acetate, phenethyl alcohol, methyl ethyl ketone, methylionone, isobomyl acetate,
and the like.</p><p num="0034">A liquid fragrance may also be formed into a thixotropic gel by the addition
of a thickening agent, such as a cellulosic material, a polymeric thickener, or a
fumed silica of the type marketed under the Cabosil trademark by Cabot Corporation.
A fragrance ingredient can also be in the form of a crystalline solid, which
has the ability to sublime into the vapor phase at ambient temperatures. A
crystalline fragrance starting material can be selected from organic compounds
which include vanillin, ethyl vanillin, coumarin, tonalid, calone, heliotropene,
musk xylol, cedrol, musk ketone benzophenone, raspberry ketone, methyl
naphthyl ketone beta, phenyl ethyl salicylate, veltol, maltol, maple lactone,
proeugenol acetate, evemyl, and the like. This type of fragrance can contribute a
long term air-treatment capability to an air freshener dispenser device for use in
the present invention. Many of such fragrances are also suitable for adaptation
to be used in the spray dispensing mode of the present invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0035">A dual function air freshener was prepared in the configuration of Figure 1,
using an active liquid spray unit comprising a complex floral fragrance, comprising
Takasago RE 3792/E, and a passive time release cartridge having a gel
therein comprising a companion fragrance, Takasago RI 1962/2. The liquid
dispenser had a dose metering valve such that the refill unit was capable of 
spraying 90 measured sprays of the air freshener. The gel cartridge, after
removal of the impermeable membrane covering the gel, released air freshener
for a period of about 30 days, with a vent opening area in the shell of approximately
48 percent of the area of exposed gel. It was found that in normal usage,
both the spray dispenser and the gel dispenser were essentially exhausted or
empty after about 30 days.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0036">A dual function dispenser was prepared in accordance with the configuration
of Figure 1, having a spray dispenser of Takasago RE 3792/E fragrance, and
a vapor dispenser comprising a long term dispenser of Takasago RI 1962/2
fragrance. This dispenser was compared to a Glade® Plug-In dispenser having
the same fragrance as the passive dispenser, for a 30 day period, and found to
have greater utility in that an instant effect of the fragrance was readily available
from the active mode of the dual capacity dispenser. The passive dispenser, with
a 47% venting area, was found in acceptance testing to be " too strong" after 3
days by 3 percent of evaluators, while the plug-in was found to be " too strong"
after 3 days by 19 percent. Conversely, the passive mode of the dual capacity
dispenser was evaluated as " just right" by 88 percent, while the plug-in was so
evaluated by 79 percent. After 30 days, the passive mode of the dual capacity
dispenser was considered " just right" by 58 percent, and " too weak" by 37
percent of evaluators, while the plug-in was considered " just right" by 67 percent,
and " too weak" by only 19 percent of the evaluators. These evaluations
reflect the fact that the dual capacity passive mode dispenser was nearing
complete loss of dispersible material at the end of 30 days, while the plug-in unit
had a larger amount of dispersible material remaining and continued to dispense
such material at a higher rate than the other.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0037">A spray unit dispenser of a deodorizer composition is combined with a
passive dispenser of air freshener attached thereto by a clip-on collar. By 
spraying of the deodorizer, the consumer may address malodors or smoke as
desired, while the passive dispenser of the air freshener creates a background
atmosphere of a pleasant scent.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u></heading><p num="0038">A dual capacity refill unit was prepared, comprising a spray dispenser of a
complex floral fragrance, with a twin gel cartridge unit comprising a gel form of a
companion fragrance. Upon exhaustion of the dispenser reservoirs of Example 1,
this dual capacity refill unit was placed in the shell to replace the exhausted
active and passive dispensers. The dispenser unit was then available for
continued use for an additional period of time.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5</u></heading><p num="0039">A single gel cartridge comprising a complex floral fragrance is prepared,
and used to replace only the passive dispenser in the clip-on collar of the dual
capacity dispenser of Example 3, illustrating the freedom of the consumer to
replace one dispenser without replacement of the other.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 6</u></heading><p num="0040">A dual capacity dispenser is prepared for insect control. A spray dispenser
of insecticide is encircled with a low profile container of a volatile insect
repellant. The volatile material is covered by a foil, which is removed for activation
of the insect repellant. This dispenser is suitable for use as a long-term
insect repellant dispenser, with a spray unit for rapid attack upon insects if they
should appear to the consumer.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 7</u></heading><p num="0041">A spray can of sanitizer is prepared as an active dispenser, incorporating
an odor eliminator in the overcap as a passive dispenser. An aerosol air sanitizer,
comprising triethylene glycol plus a suitable fragrance as the dispersible
sanitizer spray, with a standard spray valve, is combined with a charcoal odor 
absorber, in the form of particulate carbon glued to a woven backing to maximize
air flow. This dual capacity dispenser is found to have great utility in the kitchen
and bath areas.</p><p num="0042">From the above discussion, examples, and Figures, it may be seen that
the present invention comprises a multiple capacity dual function dispenser for
dispersible ingredients, such as a fragrances or air fresheners. By dual use or
dual capacity, it is meant that at least two differing modes of distribution are
included and utilized in a single dispenser apparatus, and that the two are
independent of each other. In the preferred embodiment, the dispenser apparatus
comprises an active, short term, or immediate provider, such as a spray
dispenser, in conjunction with a long term or time effective passive dispenser of
the evaporation mode, i.e. a container of an evaporative medium.</p><p num="0043">Relative to the short term, or spray medium, it is preferred that metered
dosage spray containers be used, so that controlled amounts of medium are
released at any given time of use. In this manner, a predetermined number of
sprays, or applications, may be provided for, by predetermination of the volume of
the spray container, the pressurization thereof, and the volume of medium
released with each spray application by the consumer. In this manner, one may
predict, based upon statistical analysis of typical consumer utilization, the life
expectancy of the spray unit, and accordingly select a long term or evaporative
component of the dual capacity dispenser to have a similar life expectancy, at
normal or ambient temperatures of consumption. In such a manner, when both
modes of dispensing are exhausted at approximately the same time, the consumer
is most likely to note and react to the need for refill or replacement of the
dispenser. It is a preferred embodiment of the present invention that the spray
container and evaporative medium container, preferably a gel container, be
replaced at the same time, in the form of a dual capacity refill unit, comprising
both a spray container and a gel container of the same or complementary air
fresheners or fragrances. Such refill units may be provided as a unitary structure
or package for simultaneous purchase, or may be provided as complementary
structures or packages for separate purchase by the consumer for later combination 
and insertion into the shell or shroud of the dispenser, which need not be
replaced upon exhaustion or consumption of the contents thereof. As is the case
of the " Lasting Mist®" dispenser device commercially available from S. C.
Johnson &amp; Son, Inc. of Racine, Wisconsin, the dispenser of the present invention
may comprise a body that accepts a replaceable cartridge, which a user or
consumer inserts into an open cartridge receptacle. Thus, the dispenser may be
configured so as to accept a refill unit comprising a mated set of replacement
units for the spray container and the gel or evaporative medium container, or,
alternatively, the dispenser may be configured so that spray container and
evaporative medium container may be replaced independently of each other. It is
understood that by the term " independently of each other" , the simultaneous
replacement of both units is not precluded, but that it is intended that the consumer
has the option to replace either or both of the spray container and the
evaporative medium container at any given time, and that replacement of both at
one time is neither required nor precluded. Thus, the active and passive dispenser
units, and the refill units thereof, need not be attached to each other, or
for that matter, to the external shell or outside of the dual capacity dispenser. It
may readily be seen that refill units may be placed within the shell in an unattached
manner, with, for example, the passive unit merely resting between the
actives dispenser and the shell.</p><p num="0044">Spray containers suitable for use with the present invention may, in
general, comprise an aerosol or pump dispenser can comprising a containment
volume for the medium to be sprayed, and a valve stem which communicates with
a spray nozzle orifice of the dispenser. Said can may be activated by actuation
means included in the dispenser shell or shroud into which the can may be
inserted for use, or the spray container may come complete with actuation
means, e.g. a spray nozzle assembly, for use with alternate dispensers. The
spray container may be provided with a spray medium of choice, selected from
the various spray media available, such as fragrances, insecticides, medicinals,
etc, under pressure within the containment vessel, generally a metallic canister of
the type well known in the art. A valve stem and nozzle orifice are provided, 
providing a fluid communication between the pressurized media in the can, and
with the spray tip through which the pressurized media can escape from the valve
stem. The spray delivery system further includes valve means for controlling the
release of the pressurized material, into the spray orifice, the valve means being
manually operable by the user. Preferably the valve means is a conventional
aerosol valve. The preferred valve employed as the means for controlling the
release of the pressurized material or media is a valve that delivers a single,
metered discharge of pressurized material each time the valve stem is actuated.
In any event, the valve means is manually operable by the user of the dual
function dispenser. In general, the shell of the dispenser of the present invention
is so shaped as to be conveniently and comfortably held in the hand of the user
when it is desired to employ the spray medium. However, it is also desired that
the shell of the dispenser be so shaped as to be decorative and non-intrusive, so
that it may be left in plain view for dispensing of the evaporative medium. Thus,
the shell of the dispenser, and the dispenser means associated therewith, may
comprise a shell which is simply pressed downwardly to activate the spray
mechanism, while the dispenser is left in view on a counter or table top, as a
decorative item which acts as a passive dispenser of the same or a different
material as is dispensed by the spray.</p><p num="0045">Although it is possible for the aerosol can and associated hardware to be
permanently mounted within the shell or shroud of the dispenser of the invention,
it is preferred instead that inner surfaces of the dispenser shell be so configured
that the aerosol can, its associated valve stem, and the evaporative media
container and related structures may comprise a single unit which is removable
from the shell and replaceable by a refill unit comprising like elements.</p><p num="0046">An advantage of the present invention is the constant release of an air
freshener, for example, from the evaporative cartridge, or passive dispenser,
which thus provides a constant and long-term effect, while the consumer may, at
his or her option, increase the effect of the said air freshener by actuating the
spray container to obtain additional air freshener or fragrance, for example, as
desired or required. It is also considered within the scope of the present invention 
to utilize differing compositions for the active spray component and the
passive component, to provide differing effects. For example, the spray component
might be an odor eliminator, to allow one to overcome offensive odors such
as in a kitchen or bathroom, while the passive dispenser could be a perfume, to
provide a pleasant ambient scent to a room or given area when serious offensive
odors are not present. Similarly, one may provide a spray dispenser of an insect
repellant or insecticide, in conjunction with a long-term passive dispenser of
insecticide or insect growth regulator.</p><p num="0047">It is also to be understood that the term volatile material as used in
conjunction with the passively dispersed dispersant, is intended to refer to a
material which is subject to evaporation or vaporization as its primary means of
distribution. This is not to imply that the actively dispersed materials may not be
"volatile" in the normal sense of the word, since such materials as perfumes and
fragrances are obviously volatile. The distinction to be drawn is that distinction
between active dispersement and passive dispersement, with the term volatile
reserved herein to refer to those materials which are passively dispensed, i.e.
those which are dispersed by vaporization or volatilization .</p><p num="0048">Further, when it is indicated that the actively dispensed material and the
passively dispensed material may be " the same", it is not intended to imply that
the two are chemically identical, but that the two may belong to the same class or
group of suitable materials, such as to indicate that both are fragrances, both are
sanitizers, both are insecticides, and so forth. As previously indicated, it is well
known that a given specific composition may not function well as both a passive
dispersant and as an active, or sprayed, dispersant. However, when it is indicated
that the actively dispensed material and the passively dispensed material
" differ" , it is intended to imply that the two are not chemically identical, but not to
preclude the possibility that both belong to the same class or group of dispersants.
Thus, it is possible that the active and passive dispersibles may differ, but
may both be fragrances, for example.</p><p num="0049">While the present invention has been described with respect to what are at
present considered to be the preferred embodiments, it is to be understood that 
the invention is not to be limited to the disclosed embodiments. For example, the
disclosure has been exemplified in terms of fragrances and air fresheners, while it
is clear that other dispersible materials, such as insect repellents, and other
dispersibles mentioned hereinabove may be utilized. Accordingly, the invention is
intended to cover various modifications and equivalent arrangements within the
spirit and scope of the appended claims. The scope of the following claims is to
be accorded the broadest interpretation so as to encompass all such modifications
and equivalent formulations and functions.</p><heading><u style="single">INDUSTRIAL APPLICABILITY</u></heading><p num="0050">The practical usefulness of the dual function dispenser and refill cartridges
disclosed herein, with respect to the dispensing of dispersible media conventionally
delivered by an aerosol delivery system, or by evaporation, including, by way
of example only, air fragrancing or insect control dispersible ingredients and the 
like, will be readily apparent to those skilled in the art. Except for the aerosol
can, all the parts described may be made from suitable plastics by conventional
molding or other plastic fabrication techniques. The aerosol can may be made in
conventional ways from aluminum or other suitable metals, with a conventional
metered or unmetered valve means. The evaporative medium container may be
made from plastics, metal, paper, ceramic, or laminated stock, or combinations
thereof.</p></description><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A dual capacity dispenser (51, 52) comprising separate active and passive
dispenser units (51, 52), wherein the passive dispenser (52) is removably attached
directly to the exterior circumference of the active dispenser unit (51).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A dispenser according to claim 1, wherein the passive dispenser is formed
as a clip-on collar of a material having sufficient elasticity that it may be forced on
over the diameter of the active container.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A dispenser according to any preceding claim, wherein the passive
dispenser has a slot opening or a recepticle (53) for positioning a gel cartridge or
other passive dispenser unit (54).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A dispenser according to claim 3, wherein the slot opening or recepticle
(53) has vent openings (56) which permit circulation of air into and away from
the passive dispenser unit (54).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A dispenser according to claim 1, including a gel dispenser cartridge
attached to the active container by an adhesive backing.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A dispenser according to claim 1, wherein the passive dispenser is in the
form of an impregnated plastic strip, a saturated porous medium or plastic
container of the "break to activate" type.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A clip-on passive dispenser for a passively dispensable volatile material,
the dispenser comprising a body having a slot opening or recepticle (53) for
positioning a passive dispenser of the volatile material, a clip arm extending from
the body each lateral side of the clip-on dispenser for holding the clip-on
dispenser directly on the surface of an aerosol spray container, said dispenser
having sufficient elasticity that it may readily be forced over the diameter of the
spray container and be held on the container by the arms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A clip-on dispenser according to claim 7, wherein there are provided end
openings (56) which permit circulation of air into and away from the passive
dispenser (54).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A refill unit (51) for a dual function dispenser of at least two dispersible
materials, characterized in that said refill unit comprises a reservoir (51)
containing an actively dispersible material, said refill unit being adapted to
cooperatively engage an external independent passive dispenser (52, 54) of a
passively dispersible volatile material (40, 65).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A refill unit (51) as set forth in claim 9, wherein said actively dispersible
material is selected from the group consisting of fragrances, air fresheners,
deodorizers, odor eliminators, malodor counteractants, insecticides, insect
repellants, medicinal substances, disinfectants, sanitizers, mood enhancers, and
aroma therapy compositions.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A refill unit (51) as set forth in claim 10, wherein said actively dispersible
material and said passively dispersible volatile (40, 65) material are the same.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A refill unit (51) as set forth in claim 10, wherein said actively dispersible
material and said passively dispersible material (40, 65) differ.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20060329"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050706"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20050302"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041027</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AC" date="20050302"><legal-event-body><event-title>DIVISIONAL APPLICATION (ART. 76) OF:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>1076014</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050302"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>
