<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1130211-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1130211" kind="B1" date="20040428"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23211093" ucid="EP-1130211-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1130211</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20040428</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01500031-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01500031</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010201</date><lang>ES</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="ES-200000222-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>ES</country><doc-number>200000222</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000202</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new" /><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">E06B   9/28        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">E06B   9/322       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">E06B   9/80        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">E06B   9/80        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">E06B   9/88        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">E06B9/322</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">E06B9/88</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Motorisierte Antriebsvorrichtung von beweglichen Einrichtungen wie Rollos od.dgl. und Methode zur Bedienung</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Motor-reducing device for winding blinds and awnings and method of operation</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Dispositif d'entraînement pour volets roulant, jalousies ou autres semblables et méthode d'opération.</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>VILAPLANA LAURI SONIA</name><address><country>ES</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>VILAPLANA LAURI, SONIA</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>VICENTE MARTIN PINA</name><address><country>ES</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>VICENTE MARTIN, PINA</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>VICENTE MARTIN, PINA</last-name><address><street>Tibi, 8 - 3 C</street><city>03440 Ibi, Alicante</city><country>ES</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Vilaplana Lauri, Sonia</last-name><address><street>Tibi, 8</street><city>03440 Ibi, Alicante</city><country>ES</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Del Santo Abril, Natividad</last-name><address><street>Oficina Garcia Cabrerizo, S.L., Vitruvio, 23</street><city>28006 Madrid</city><country>ES</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GR</country><country>IT</country><country>MC</country><country>PT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>Consisting of an external tube (3) inside which an electric motor (14) is installed which acts through an electro-brake (13) and a planetary reducer (15) on a matrix ferrule (4) which is coupled to the inside of a polygonal drum (17) to which it transmits its movement, and in which the winding up/down of a blind or awning (18) takes place, its position being controlled by a linear potentiometer (16) joined to a prisoner nut (10) that can travel longitudinally in both directions with respect to a threaded rod (19) that is solidary with a toothed wheel (7) that is geared by the inside of a control ferrule (2) which received the movement from the polygonal drum (17) to the inside of which it is coupled. A printed circuit (11) memorises the extreme raising/lowering positions of the first operations carried out after having activated a restoration microswitch (5). &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">Consisting of an external tube (3) inside which an
electric motor (14) is installed which acts through an
electro-brake (13) and a planetary reducer (15) on a
matrix ferrule (4) which is coupled to the inside of a
polygonal drum (17) to which it transmits its movement,
and in which the winding up/down of a blind or awning
(18) takes place, its position being controlled by a
linear potentiometer (16) joined to a prisoner nut (10)
that can travel longitudinally in both directions with
respect to a threaded rod (19) that is solidary with a
toothed wheel (7) that is geared by the inside of a
control ferrule (2) which received the movement from the
polygonal drum (17) to the inside of which it is coupled.
A printed circuit (11) memorises the extreme
raising/lowering positions of the first operations
carried out after having activated a restoration microswitch
(5).
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1130782-A2-00000001" he="92" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">This invention refers to an electronic system for 
the adjustment of stops and start-up of blind and awning 
automatic winding motor-reducers and more specifically to a motor-reducing device for winding blinds and awnings as to a method of operation. The adjustment of the 
maximum stops for lowering and raising is carried out by 
means of an electronic plate controlled by a micro-processor 
with a single pressing action in each sense, 
from the final users control mechanism. The system is 
capable of adjusting the stops in such a way that cannot 
be cancelled from the control used by the final user. </p><p num="0002">There are adjustment systems that operate 
mechanically on the motor-reducer itself, which have 
serious disadvantages, such as the lack of space and the 
use of additional tools, which makes adjustment 
difficult. </p><p num="0003">German patent <ref type="patent">DE-A-4038923</ref> describes a motorization 
for blind winders that uses a prisoner nut to activate 
two extreme position stops. The stops are also installed 
on prisoner nuts so that their position can be altered by 
turning the'screws on which they are mounted. This system 
has two serious problems: on the one hand, the linear 
movement of the prisoner nut has to be transmitted to the 
opposite side of the motor-reducer device, which is 
performed by a flat metal strip that occupies space and 
restricts the size of the activation motor; and, on the 
other hand, the prisoner nut cannot move a great distance 
and because the micro-switches that are the extreme stops 
are relatively large, the assembly lacks prevision. It is 
also a totally mechanical device, subject to 
maladjustment and wear, and consequently to faults. </p><p num="0004">A considerable improvement on the previous system is 
the device described in US patent <ref type="patent">US-A-5.709.349</ref>. In this case 
the transmission of the linear movement of the prisoner  
 
bolt and the micro-switches that are the extreme stops 
have been eliminated. Instead, the mechanical blocking of 
a prisoner nut is used to produce an overload for the 
motor, which is detected by an electronic circuit. The 
system is more reliable from a mechanical viewpoint, but 
it implies the use of a costly electronic circuit to 
detect the motor overload. Adjustment is made by turning 
the casing that contains the prisoner nut, which is not 
very convenient. </p><p num="0005">A further step in the development of mechanically 
controlled motor-reducers is the device described in 
document <ref type="patent">EP-A-0 940 552</ref>. Here, the concept of interrupting 
the electric supply to the motor when the blind has 
reached its extreme positions has disappeared. Instead, 
it presents mechanical clutches that allow the motor to 
run in a vacuum, when the blind reaches the end of its 
path or meets with an obstacle on the way. This device 
has the least electric complication with the greatest 
mechanical complication. Although on paper it is very 
attractive, its reliability over time is to be doubted. </p><p num="0006">In view of the serious problems presented by 
mechanically controlled motor-reducer systems, there have 
been different attempts to use electronic controls of 
different kinds: document <ref type="patent">EP-A-0 552 459</ref> describes the use 
of virtual electronic stops by the use of an electronic 
control device in programming mode. The position of blind 
is determined by an impulse counter. The impulses are 
generated by a fixed Reed relay and numerous permanent 
magnets around the blind's winding drum. The control 
device has a programming mode and an operating mode and, 
consequently, the possibility of the final consumer 
acting on the motor-reducer is perfectly accessible, 
which is in no case convenient. </p><p num="0007">Along this line of electronic motor-reducer control, 
the device described in document <ref type="patent">US-A-5.540.264</ref> is possibly  
 
one of the most sophisticated systems. Here the impulse 
counter is abandoned and replaced with a series of 
inductive end stops, the position of which on the side 
guides of the blind is adjustable, and which are 
activated by permanent magnets on the' end of the blind. A 
linear inductive sensor, positioned along one of the side 
guides of the blind, produces an electro-driving force in 
proportion to its speed. Thus, there is total control 
over the movement of the blind, eliminating the impulse 
counter, in exchange for complex external wiring, which 
makes the system inappropriate for motorising existing 
installations. </p><p num="0008"><ref type="patent">DE-A-4 333 996</ref> describes a device provided with regulation potentiometers disposed in a remote control panel, adjacent to directional switches. </p><p num="0009">Other motor-reducers in which the adjustment is 
carried our from the final user's control mechanism work 
in the following way: 
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Press the control mechanism levers at the same time 
for more than 15 seconds (this operation automatically 
cancels previous adjustments). </li><li>Release the levers. </li><li>Press the raising lever and keep it pressed until the 
blind is in the desired position. </li><li>Release the lever. </li><li>Press both levers at the same time for more than one 
second. Release the lowering lever, keeping the 
raising lever pressed for more than one second. This 
operation memorises the upper stop limit. </li><li>Press the lowering lever and keep it pressed until the 
blind is in the desired position. </li><li>Release the lever. </li><li>Press both levers at the same time for more than one 
second. Release the raising lever, keeping the 
lowering lever pressed for more than one second. This 
operations memorises the lower stop limit. </li></ul></p><p num="0010">This system has a series of disadvantages, such as 
the fact that it is complicated, slow, and the stops can  
 
be cancelled by the final user's control mechanism. This 
can be very dangerous, because if a piece of furniture or 
any other object accidentally presses the control levers, 
the system would be out of control. This system also 
requires the use of an independent two-lever control 
device, which is more costly that opposite double-lever 
controls. </p><p num="0011">The motor-reducing device according to claim 1 and the related method of operation according to claim 2 
solve the disadvantages previously described, 
providing total control over the movement of the blind, 
but with adjustment operations independent from the final 
user's control operations. </p><p num="0012">The motor-reducing device that is the object of this 
invention incorporates a linear potentiometer that is an 
electric, virtual representation of the blind's position. 
This potentiometer is activated by a prisoner nut that 
receives the movement from a polygonal control ferrule 
adjusted to the inside of the blind drum, which in turn 
receives the movement from a matrix ferrule activated by 
an electric motor and a planetary reducer. This allows 
the matrix ferrule and the control ferrule to be 
positioned on opposite ends of the motor-reducing device, 
since the drum of the blind is used as the element that 
solidarises both ferrules. In this way, practically all 
the interior volume of the drum of the blind is used, 
which allows us to use larger components, gaining 
manoeuvring power and adjustment precision. </p><p num="0013">On the same end where the control ferrule is 
positioned, there is a restoration micro-switch, easily 
accessible from outside the motor-reducing device, but 
which can not be manipulated by the final user during 
normal operations. </p><p num="0014">With the device that is the object of this 
invention, the adjustment operation is simplified as 
follows:  <ul list-style="bullet"><li>We press and release the restoration micro-switch. </li><li>We press and release the raising or lowering control 
lever, depending on which of the stops we wish to 
memorise. </li><li>When we reach the desired stop position, we press 
either of the levers. The end position for raising or 
lowering is memorised. </li></ul></p><p num="0015">Consequently, the memorisation of the two upper and 
lower stops is carried out automatically in the two 
operations that immediately follow pressing the 
restoration micro-switch. </p><p num="0016">The device that is the object of this invention 
ensures, by means of the micro-processor, protection 
against possible accident during domestic use: 
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Detection of the motor-reducer failing to turn, which 
could be brought about by overloads or blockage. </li><li>Detection of the motor overheating, by means of a heat 
relay. </li></ul></p><p num="0017">The motor-reducing device that is the object of this 
invention ensures the availability of: 
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>A compact motor-reducing device, fully assembled, 
ready to install, that only requires being introduced 
inside the drum of the blind and connected to the 
electric supply. </li><li>A motor-reducing device with extremely simple and 
easy-to-control adjustment operations. </li><li>A motor-reducing device for which the adjustment 
operations can not be modified in an untimely manner 
by the final user. </li></ul></p><p num="0018">To complete the previous description and with a view 
to providing a better understanding of the 
characteristics of the invention, following is a detailed 
description based on a set of drawings that are attached 
to this description, where the following has been 
represented (orientatively, without limitation) :  <sl><li>Figure 1 shows a side section view of the device 
that is the object of the invention. </li><li>Figure 2 shows an upper section view of the device 
that is the object of the invention. </li><li>Figure 3 shows a III-III transversal section 
following the transmission of the movement from the 
control ferrule to the prisoner nut. </li><li>Figure 4 shows a IV-IV transversal section in which 
we see the transmission of the movement from the prisoner 
nut to the sliding potentiometer. </li><li>Figure 5 shows a V-V transversal section in which we 
see the recurring position of the planetary reducer and 
the coupling of the matrix ferrule to the inside of the 
drum of the blind. </li><li>Figure 6 shows the printed circuit electric diagram 
that contains the sliding potentiometer and the micro-processor. </li></sl></p><p num="0019">In these figures, the numerical references 
correspond to: 
<sl><li>1.- Motor-reducer support </li><li>2.- Control ferrule </li><li>3.- Exterior tube </li><li>4.- Matrix ferrule </li><li>5.- Restoration micro-switch </li><li>6.- External support of the printed circuit and threaded 
rod </li><li>7.- Gearing that activates the threaded rod </li><li>9.- Internal support of the printed circuit and threaded 
rod </li><li>10.- Prisoner nut </li><li>11.- Printed circuit </li><li>12.- Motor starter condenser </li><li>13.- Electro-brake </li><li>14.- Alternate current motor </li><li>15.- Planetary reducer  </li><li>16.- Potentiometer </li><li>17.- Winding drum </li><li>18.- Blind </li><li>19.- Threaded rod </li><li>20.- Control button </li><li>21.- Support guides for the prisoner nut </li><li>22.- Stabilising circuit </li><li>23.- Support for prisoner nut </li><li>24.- Micro-processor </li><li>25.- Planetary gearing </li><li>27.- Central pinion </li><li>29.- Toothed crown </li><li>33.- ADC converter </li></sl></p><p num="0020">As can be seen from figures 1 and 2, inside the drum 
(17) in which the blind is rolled, a tube (3) is 
introduced, inside which the entire motor-reducing device 
is positioned. This device consists of an electric motor 
(14) coupled to a planetary reducer (15) which transmits 
the movement to driving matrix (4) which is able to 
revolve around the fixed external tube (3), and is 
therefore liable to be coupled to the inside of the drum 
(17) in which the blind (18) is rolled. The control 
ferrule (2) has internal teeth that links to a gearing 
(17) which is solidary with a threaded rod (19) liable to 
cause the movement of a prisoner nut (10), which is 
lodged in a prisoner nut support (23) and slides along 
two guides (21), transmitting the movement to a linear 
potentiometer (16) which thus constitutes an electric 
representation of the physical position of the blind. A 
restoration micro-switch (5) is fixed to an external 
printed circuit and threaded rod support (6), and this 
end of the device is covered by the motor-reducer support 
(1), solidary with the external tube (3) which 
immobilised this assembly but allows the control ferrule 
(2) and the matrix ferrule (4) to turn freely.  </p><p num="0021">Two printed circuit and threaded rod supports (6) 
(9) are used for the assembly of the above mentioned 
items, made up of two metal plates, one of which also 
acts as an earthing connection, joining the printed 
circuit (11) on which the linear potentiometer (16) is 
installed to the external tube (3). On the internal 
printed circuit and threaded rod support (9) the electric 
motor (14) starter condenser (12) is installed. The 
external printed circuit and threaded rod support (6) 
fastens the restoration micro-switch (5) to the motor-reducer, 
also preventing the threaded rod activating 
mechanism (7) from moving out of place. </p><p num="0022">As can be seen from figures 1 and 5, the 
conventional design planetary reducer (15) has three 
recurring stages, of a similar structure, to attain 
global reduction of 150:1. Each of the stages consists of 
three planetary gearings (25) moved by a central pinion 
(27), which in turn revolve on a toothed crown (29) 
attached to the external tube (3) which is the casing for 
the motor-reducing device assembly that is the object of 
the invention. This circular movement of the shafts of 
the planetary gearings (25) is transmitted to the 
following central pinion (27) which links to the 
planetary gearings for the following stage. The matrix 
ferrule (4) is solidary with the shafts on which the 
planetary gearings (25) for the third and final stage are 
mounted. </p><p num="0023">Both the electric motor (14) and the electro-brake 
(13) are conventional and any of those available on the 
market can be used, with the only condition that they 
adjust as well as possible to the diameter of the 
external tube (3). </p><p num="0024">The printed circuit (11) contains a source of 
supply, a stabilising circuit and a micro-processor 
detection and control circuit. See figure 6.  </p><p num="0025">The source of supply is capable of generating 
sufficient voltage and current to support the entire 
electronic system. The different components used in the 
source of supply establish a current that will always 
circulate through the circuit. Both the resistances R1, 
R2, the condenser C1 and the diodes D1, D2, D3 and D4 are 
in charge of this function. Resistances R3 and R4 are for 
discharging the condenser C1 if there is no input 
current. </p><p num="0026">The stabilising circuit consists of condenser C2. 
Condenser C3 is made of polyester and rather than to 
stabilise the voltage it is used to avoid possible high 
frequency alterations. At this point of the circuit we 
will have a maximum stable voltage of 15 V. A 
conventional stabilising circuit (22) of the &quot;7805&quot; type 
stabilises the voltage at 5 V, and together with 
condenser C4, it avoids small signal alterations. </p><p num="0027">In the micro-processor detection and control 
circuit, from a stable voltage like we have now we will 
feed the ADC converter (analogic-digital converter) (33), 
the micro-processor and the linear potentiometer (16) 
which will give us the electric signal that is the 
reflection of the physical position of the blind. The ADC 
converter (33), taking into account the live value of the 
linear potentiometer (16), generates an output 
combination which the micro-processor (24) collects. 
Three levers are in charge of controlling the entire 
system. Marked as P1 and P3 in figure 6, these correspond 
to the control lever (20) and P2 corresponds to the 
restoration micro-switch (5). As can be seen on the 
drawing, there is a union between the input to lever P2 
and the pin WR of the ADC converter (33). This is due to 
the fact that the microprocessor (24) will at times act 
as input and at others as output, providing a signal to 
activate the internal register of the ADC converter (33).  
 
Resistances R7 and R8 are microprocessor outlets (24) 
with activate transistors T1 and T2. These in tun 
activate relays REL1 and REL2, respectively. Each relay 
is in charge of activating the motor in one sense or the 
other. In this system there is a small current absorption 
system. When one of the relays works, consumption is 
correct and therefore none of the components of the 
source of supply become heated. When no relay is 
functioning, the diodes of the source of supply could 
burn (not if they are of the right power rating). To 
avoid this, and for safety purposes, a system of T3 and 
T4 is installed, activated by resistances R6 and R15, 
which will work when no relay is functioning. They will 
thus drive the current through resistance R16, which will 
emulate the consumption of the relay. </p><p num="0028">One of the advantages of this system is the 
possibility of using, to manoeuvre the motor-reducing 
device, any of the dual control levers available on the 
market, since the electronic system is capable of 
absorbing an incorrect pressing or a double pressing. In 
a preferred embodiment, we have decided to use a SIMON 
ref. 31331-30 double control and its accessories, which 
is perfectly integrated in the style of electric switches 
used in homes and offices. </p><p num="0029">In the sample embodiment we have used an ADC 
converter (33) of the AD 0803/4-1 type, from PHILIPS 
SEMICONDUTORS and a micro-processor (24) of the PIC 16FBX 
type marketed by MICROCHIP TECHNOLOGY INC. </p><p num="0030">The motor-reducing device that is the object of the 
invention works as follows: </p><p num="0031">When the raising lever of the control mechanism (20) 
is released after being pressed, this simultaneously 
activates the electro-brake (13) and the motor (14) and 
the motor (14) will transmit the movement to the 
planetary reducer (15) which will turn the matrix ferrule  
 
(4). In turn, the matrix ferrule (4) makes the drum (17) 
turn that rolls the blind or awning (18), which transmits 
the movement to the control ferrule (2). The control 
ferrule (2) has internal teeth that makes the threaded 
rod activator gearing (7) turn. This gearing and the 
threaded rod (19) are solidary. The prisoner nut (10) 
moves sideways in one direction or the other depending on 
the direction in which the motor (14) is turning, moving 
the linear potentiometer (16) mounted on the printed 
circuit (11) where the signal adapter components are. 
Thus the entire system moves until either of the two 
levers on the control mechanism (26) are pressed, when 
the upper extreme position will be memorised. If we later 
attempted to raise the blind further, the manoeuvre would 
not be possible, since the upper stop has been recorded. </p><p num="0032">When the lowering lever is released after being 
pressed, all the above will happen as described, but 
turning in the opposite direction, and therefore 
recording the lower stop. From that moment, the mechanism 
is adjusted and we can proceed to use it normally. We can 
also stop the motor-reducer at any point that we wish 
between both stops, proceeding as previously described, 
but in this case these intermediate positions are not 
memorised. </p><p num="0033">As for the industrial application of the device that 
is the object of this invention, the motor-reducer will 
be presented as a compact assembly fully mounted inside 
the external tube (3) liable to be fixed to a wall by its 
solidary support (1). See figure 1. From this compact 
assembly the only projections are the restoration micro-switch 
(5) and the matrix (4) and control ferrules (2), 
and this is connected by a cable to the control mechanism 
(20). The assembly is introduced into the drum (17) of 
the blind (18), for which the matrix ferrule (4) has a 
light surface with a view to reducing the resistance  
 
produced by friction when this operation is performed. 
After introducing all the external tube (3) of the motor-reducer 
into the drum (17), the operation is completed by 
coupling the control ferrule (2) to the inside of the 
drum (17). The motor-reducer support (1) is attached to 
the wall by a set of screws, as can be seen in figure 4, 
thus immobilising the assembly. </p><p num="0034">Although in figure 1 the matrix ferrule (4) has been 
represented as if it nearly reaches the right-hand side 
of the blind, it is evident that its position will depend 
on the width of the blind. As long as the control ferrule 
(2) is always at one end of the drum (17), the matrix 
ferrule (4) will penetrate more or less into the drum(17) 
depending on its length. </p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Getriebemotor-Vorrichtung zum Aufrollen von 
Jalousien und Markisen bestehend aus einer externen Röhre 
(3) in deren Innerem ein Elektromotor (14) eingebaut ist, 
der mittels einer Elektrobremse (13) und einem 
Planetengetriebe (15) auf einer Basisschiene (4) 
funktioniert, das an einem Ende der Röhre angebracht ist 
und sich im Verhältnis zu dieser externen Röhre (3) frei 
drehen kann, wobei die Basisschiene (4) mit dem Inneren 
einer polygonalen Trommel (17) verbunden ist, an welche 
sie Ihre Bewegung überträgt und auf der sich eine 
Jalousie oder eine Markise (18) auf- und abrollen kann, 
Geräten zur elektrischen Darstellung der Position der 
Jalousie, die sich im Inneren der externen Röhre (3) 
befinden, einer Kontrollschiene (2) die an dem Ende, das 
der Basisschiene (4) der äußeren Röhre (3) 
gegenüberliegt, angebracht ist, und die durch die 
genannte polygonale Trommel (17) eine Bewegung erfährt, 
da sie mit dem Inneren dieser Trommel so verbunden ist, 
dass sie sich dreht und die Bewegung auf die Geräte zur 
elektrischen Darstellung der Position der Jalousie 
überträgt, gekennzeichnet dadurch, dass die genannte 
Getriebemotor-Vorrichtung mit einem Mikroschalter zum 
Wiederherstellen der Ausgangskonfiguration (5) 
ausgestattet ist, der sich am gleichen Ende der externen 
Röhre (3) befindet wie die Kontrollschiene (2); in der 
Art dass beim ersten Auf- und Abrollvorgang mit der 
Vorrichtung nach Betätigen des Reset-Mikroschalters (5) 
die Endpositionen gespeichert werden. </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Bedienen für eine Getriebemotor-Vorrichtung 
zum Aufrollen von Jalousien und Markisen, 
gekennzeichnet dadurch, dass eine Leiterplatte (11) beim 
ersten Auf- und Abrollvorgang mit der Vorrichtung nach 
 
Aktivierung eines Reset-Mikroschalters (5) die 
Endpositionen speichert, in der Art, dass bei den darauf 
folgenden Auf- und Abrollvorgängen die Auf- und 
Abrollendpositionen, die gespeichert wurden, nicht mehr 
geändert werden können, bis der Reset-Mikroschalter (5) 
erneut betätigt wird. </claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Motor-reducing device for winding blinds and awnings 
comprising an external tube (3) inside which an electric 
motor (14) is installed which acts through an electro-brake 
(13) and a planetary reducer (15) on a matrix 
ferrule (4) positioned at one end and that can freely 
turn in relation to cited external tube (3), and being 
the matrix ferrule (4) coupled to the inside of a 
polygonal drum (17) to which it transmits its movement, 
and in which a blind or awning (18) is wound up or down, 
means of electric representation of the position of the 
blind positioned inside the external tube (3), a control 
ferrule (2) positioned at the opposite end of the matrix 
ferrule (4) of the external tube (3) which, receiving 
movement from cited polygonal drum (17), to the inside of 
which is coupled in a rotating way, and transmitting the 
movement to the means of electric representation of the 
position of the blind, characterised in that said motor-reducing device comprises 
a restoration micro-switch (5) positioned on the same end 
of the external tube (3) in which is positioned the 
control ferrule (2); in such a way that it allows to 
memorise the extreme positions in the first 
raising/lowering operations carried out with the device 
after having activated the restoration micro-switch (5). </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Method of operation for a motor-reducing device for 
winding blinds and awnings, characterised in that a 
printed circuit (11) memorises the extreme positions of 
the first raising/lowering operations carried out after 
having activated a restoration micro-switch (5), so that 
in subsequent raising/lowering operations the extreme 
raising/lowering positions that have been memorised can 
not be altered until the restoration micro-switch (5) is 
activated again. </claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif moto-réducteur pour enrouler les 
persiennes et les bâches comprenant un tube externe (3) à 
l'intérieur duquel est installé un moteur électrique (14) 
fonctionnant au moyen d'un électro frein (13) et d'un 
réducteur planétaire (15) sur une férule motrice (4), 
situé à une extrémité et qui peut tourner librement par 
rapport au dit tube externe (3) ; la férule motrice (4) 
étant raccordée à l'intérieur d'un tambour polygonal (17) 
auquel elle transmet son mouvement, et sur lequel une 
persienne ou une bâche (18) s'enroulent ou se déroulent, 
des moyens de représentation électrique de la position de 
la persienne situés à l'intérieur du tube externe (3), 
une férule de contrôle (2) placée à l'extrémité opposée 
de la férule motrice (4) du tube externe (3) qui, en 
recevant le mouvement du dit tambour polygonal (17), est 
raccordée à l'intérieur de ce dernier de façon rotative, 
et transmet le mouvement aux moyens de représentation 
électrique de la position de la persienne, caractérisé en 
ce que le dit dispositif moto-réducteur comprend un 
micro-interrupteur de restauration (5) situé à 
l'extrémité même du tube externe (3) où se situe la 
férule de contrôle (2); de telle sorte qu'il permet de 
mémoriser les positions extrêmes lors de premières 
opérations de montée/descente effectuées avec le 
dispositif après avoir activé le micro-interrupteur de 
restauration (5). </claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé d'opération pour un dispositif moto-réducteur 
pour enrouler des persiennes et des bâches, 
caractérisé en ce qu'un circuit imprimé (11) mémorise les 
positions extrêmes des premières opérations de 
montée/descente effectuées après avoir activé un micro-interrupteur 
de restauration (5), de façon à ce que, lors 
 
des opérations de montée/descente suivantes, les 
positions extrêmes de montée/descente mémorisées ne 
peuvent varier que lors de la prochaine activation du 
micro-interrupteur de restauration (5). </claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20050420"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050131</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20050121"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20040930"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SC4A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AVAILABILITY OF NATIONAL TRANSLATION</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040727</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20040603"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60102961</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040603</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20040428"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGRITMCPT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIN1" date="20040428"><legal-event-body><event-title>INVENTOR (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>VICENTE MARTIN, PINA</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20030326"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030206</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20020522"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE FR GR IT MC PT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20020515"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020301</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>