<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1132916-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1132916" kind="B1" date="20040519"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23244579" ucid="EP-1132916-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1132916</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20040519</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01301915-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01301915</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010302</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000067210-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000067210</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000307</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new" /><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  23/03        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G11B  23/03        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B23/03A4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B23/03A6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">G11B23/03A8C</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Plattenkassette</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Disc cartridges</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Cartouche à disque</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SONY CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SONY CORPORATION</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KIKUCHI SHUICHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>IZU RIE</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KIKUCHI, SHUICHI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>IZU, RIE</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Izu, Rie, c/o Intell. Property Dept.</last-name><address><street>Sony Corp., 6-7-35 Kitashinagawa</street><city>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo 141</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Kikuchi, Shuichi, c/o Intell. Property Dept.</last-name><address><street>Sony Corp., 6-7-35 Kitashinagawa</street><city>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo 141</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>SONY CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>7-35 Kitashinagawa 6-chome Shinagawa-ku</street><city>Tokyo 141</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Goddard, Frances Anna</last-name><address><street>D Young &amp;amp; Co 21 New Fetter Lane</street><city>London EC4A 1DA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>In order to provide a shutter open/close mechanism (26) suitable for use with a cartridge body (6) whose front end is formed in an arbitrary shape for easily identifying the correct direction of insertion in a recorder/player, a guide recess (36) to support a shutter plate (25) movably is formed on a main side of the cartridge body (6) to be oblique relative to the width of the cartridge body (6). The shutter open/close mechanism (26) includes a guide member (31) supporting the shutter plate (25) and movably engaged in the guide recess (36), an operating member (32) to move the guide member (31), a transmission member (33) connecting the guide member (31) and operating member (32) to each other to transmit an operating force from the operating member (32) to the guide member (31), and support surfaces (37) formed on the cartridge body (6) to support the operating member (32) movably. The shutter open/close mechanism (26) further includes a shutter locking mechanism (38) disposed at the lateral side of the cartridge body (6) to lock the shutter plate (25) against movement. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">In order to provide a shutter open/close mechanism (26) suitable for use with a
cartridge body (6) whose front end is formed in an arbitrary shape for easily
identifying the correct direction of insertion in a recorder/player, a guide recess
(36) to support a shutter plate (25) movably is formed on a main side of the cartridge
body (6) to be oblique relative to the width of the cartridge body (6). The shutter
open/close mechanism (26) includes a guide member (31) supporting the shutter plate
(25) and movably engaged in the guide recess (36), an operating member (32) to move
the guide member (31), a transmission member (33) connecting the guide member (31)
and operating member (32) to each other to transmit an operating force from the
operating member (32) to the guide member (31), and support surfaces (37) formed on
the cartridge body (6) to support the operating member (32) movably. The shutter
open/close mechanism (26) further includes a shutter locking mechanism (38)
disposed at the lateral side of the cartridge body (6) to lock the shutter plate (25)
against movement.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1133703-A1-00000001" he="93" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a disc cartridge having therein a disc-shaped
recording medium such as an optical disc, magneto-optical disc or the like.</p><p num="0002">As the disc-shaped recording medium, a disc cartridge having a magneto-optical
disc for example encased therein has been proposed.</p><p num="0003">Referring now to FIG. 1, there is schematically illustrated a conventional disc
cartridge in the form of a perspective view. In FIG. 1, the disc cartridge is generally
indicated with a reference 201. The disc cartridge 201 includes a cartridge body 206
consisting of a pair of upper shell 211 and lower shell 212 assembled to each other.
These upper and lower shells 211 and 212 are made of a resin material. Each of the
upper and lower shells 211 and 212 of the cartridge body 206 has formed therein an
access opening 215 having a generally rectangular shape. The access openings 215
are opposite to each other. Thus, a part of the recording area of the magneto-optical
disc 205, extending between lead-in and lead-out areas, is exposed outside through the
openings 215 for data read and write.</p><p num="0004">The lower shell 212 of the cartridge body 206 has formed therein adjacent or
next to the access opening 215 a drive opening 217 through which a disc table (not 
shown) of a disc drive mechanism which drives to rotate the magneto-optical disc 205
comes into the cartridge body 206.</p><p num="0005">Further, the cartridge body 206 has a shutter member 220 mounted thereon as
shown in FIG. 1. Normally, the shutter member 220 covers or closes the access
openings 215 and drive opening 217. When the disc cartridge 201 is loaded into a
recorder/player, the shutter member 220 will be moved and thus the access and drive
openings 215 and 217 will be opened. The shutter member 220 consists of an upper
shutter portion which closes and opens the access openings 215 in the upper shell 211,
a lower shutter portion which closes and opens the access openings 215 and drive
opening 217 in the lower shell 212, and a connection to which each of the upper and
lower shutter portions is connected at one end thereof. Further, the cartridge body
206 has disposed therein an elastic member (not shown) to force the upper shutter
portion of the shutter member 220 in a direction in which the upper shutter portion
closes the access openings 215 and drive opening 217.</p><p num="0006">When the disc cartridge 201 constructed as in the above is loaded into the
recorder/player, the shutter member 220 is moved by a shutter open/close member of
the recorder/player to open the access openings 215 and drive opening 217. The disc
table of the disc drive mechanism (not shown) of the recorder/player comes into the
disc cartridge through the drive opening 217 to rotate the magneto-optical disc 205 in
the disc cartridge 201, while the write/read head of the recorder/player comes into the
disc cartridge 201 through the access openings 215 to write/read information to/from 
the magneto-optical disc 205.</p><p num="0007">In the aforementioned conventional disc cartridge 101, however, since the front
end thereof at which the disc cartridge 201 is first inserted into and removed from the
recorder/player is formed straight perpendicularly to the direction of insertion into the
recorder/player and both the main sides of the cartridge body 206 are formed generally
square, it is difficult to easily know the correct inserting direction of the disc cartridge
201 from its appearance.</p><p num="0008">Therefore, the conventional disc cartridge 201 is likely to be inserted in the wrong
direction into the recorder/player.</p><p num="0009">In the conventional disc cartridge 201, the shutter member 220 is moved under
the action of only the force of the elastic member to the position where it closes the
access openings 215 and drive opening 217. Since in the conventional disc cartridge
201, the shutter member 220 can thus be moved easily to the open position against the
force of the elastic member, there is a likelihood that the shutter member 220 is
inadvertently opened.</p><p num="0010">Document <ref type="patent">US4740949</ref> discloses a disc cartridge comprising an access opening formed
in the cartridge body, a shutter member provided movably to open and close the
access opening and means to open/close the shutter.</p><p num="0011">The document <ref type="patent">EP 0 973 163 A2</ref> discloses a disc cartridge
comprising an arcuate shaped front end. The shutter mechanism comprises two shutter
members that are pivotally connected to rotate at the same time and relative to each
other to open or close access to the disc-recording medium contained within the
cartridge body.</p><p num="0012">One shutter member is attached to a guide member, which has an arcuate form
corresponding to the shape of the front end and also corresponding to the shape of a
guide groove along which the guide member travels to effect rotational movement of
the shutter member.  </p><p num="0013">According to the present invention there is provided a disc cartridge
comprising: a disc-shaped recording medium; a cartridge body having formed therein a
disc compartment to house the disc-shaped recording medium; an access opening
formed in the cartridge body and through which a part of the recording area of the
disc-shaped recording medium, extending between lead-in and lead-out areas, is
exposed outside for data read and write; a shutter member provided movably to open
and close the access opening; and a shutter open/close mechanism including
: a guide recess formed in a main side of the cartridge
body, which guide recess is oblique in relation to a side of the cartridge body; a guide
member supporting the shutter member, which guide member is movably engaged in
the guide recess, movement of the guide member in the guide recess effecting
translational movement of the shutter member along a path defined by the guide
recess; an operating member to move the guide member; a transmission member
linking the guide member and the operating member to each other to transmit an
operating force from the operating member to the guide member; and support surfaces
formed on the cartridge body to support the operating member movably; and a shutter 
locking mechanism disposed on the lateral side of the cartridge body to inhibit the
shutter member from moving.</p><p num="0014">In the disc cartridge constructed as in the above, since the shutter member is
inhibited from moving by the shutter locking mechanism, it is held to close the access
opening.</p><p num="0015">Advantageously, a guide recess formed on a main side of the cartridge body to
be oblique relative to the width of the cartridge body allows the front end of the
cartridge body at which the disc cartridge is first inserted into the recorder/player to be
formed in an arbitrary shape for easier recognition of the correct direction of insertion
in the recorder/player, so that the disc cartridge can be prevented from being inserted
in the wrong direction into the recorder/player. Also, the shutter locking mechanism
provided matching the cartridge body whose front end is formed in the arbitrary shape
permits to lock and hold the shutter member in positions where it opens and closes the
access opening.</p><p num="0016">The invention will now be described by way of example with reference to the
accompanying drawings, throughout which like parts are referred to by like references,
and in which:
<sl><li>FIG. 1 is a perspective view of a conventional disc cartridge;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a perspective view of an embodiment of the disc cartridge according
to the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a perspective bottom view of the disc cartridge in FIG. 2;</li><li>FIG. 4 is a perspective bottom view of the disc cartridge in FIG. 2, with the
shutter plate being moved to the opened position;</li><li>FIG. 5 is an exploded perspective bottom view of the disc cartridge in FIG. 2, 
for explanation of the shutter plate of the disc cartridge;</li><li>FIG. 6 is an exploded perspective bottom view of the disc cartridge in FIG. 2;</li><li>FIG. 7 is an axial sectional view for explanation of the shutter plate and
concavity in which the shutter plate is moved;</li><li>FIG. 8 is a perspective view for explanation of the shutter open/close
mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 9 is an exploded perspective view for explanation of the shutter open/close
mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 10 is a perspective bottom view for explanation of a guide member of the
shutter open/close mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 11 is an axial sectional view for explanation of the guide member of the
shutter open/close mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 12 is a perspective view for explanation of an operating member of the
shutter open/close mechanism and shutter locking mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 13 is a plan view of the operating member and shutter locking mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 14 is a front view of the operating member and shutter locking mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 15 is a side elevation of the operating member and shutter locking
mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 16 is a perspective view for explanation of the shutter locking mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 17 is a cross section showing the locking member of the shutter locking
mechanism on the engagement projection; </li><li>FIG. 18 is an axial sectional view showing the engagement of the locking
member of the shutter locking mechanism with the engagement projection;</li><li>FIG. 19 is an axial sectional view for explanation of the shutter locking
mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 20 is a perspective view for explanation of the disengagement of the
locking member of the shutter locking mechanism from the engagement projection:</li><li>FIG. 21 is a cross section showing the abutment of the operating member of the
recorder/player to the unlocking member of the shutter locking mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 22 is a cross section showing the disengagement of the locking member
of the shutter locking mechanism from the engagement projection;</li><li>FIG. 23 is a plan view of the essential parts for explanation of the opening and
closing operation of the shutter open/close mechanism;</li><li>FIG. 24 is a perspective view of an example of the disc cartridge according
the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 25 is a perspective view of a variant of the optical disc;</li><li>FIG. 26 is a perspective view of an example of the disc cartridge according
to the present invention; and</li><li>FIG. 27 is an exploded perspective view of the disc cartridge in FIG. 26.</li></sl></p><p num="0017">Referring now to FIGS. 2 and 3, there is schematically illustrated in the form
of a perspective view the embodiment of the disc cartridge according to the present 
invention. The disc cartridge is generally indicated with a reference 1. As shown, the
disc cartridge 1 includes an optical disc 5 and a cartridge body 6 having the optical
disc 5 rotatably encased therein.</p><p num="0018">As will seen from FIGS. 2, 3 and 4, the optical disc 5 is formed to have a disc-like
form having a central hole 9. The optical disc 5 used herein is a CD (compact
disc)-R (recordable) to which information can additionally be written, for example.
It should be noted that the optical disc 5 may of course be an other optical disc such
as a phase-change optical disc, magneto-optical disc or the like, which is a CD-RW
(rewritable) in which information can be rewritable.</p><p num="0019">As shown in FIGS. 5 and 6, the cartridge body 6 consists of a pair of upper shell
11 and lower shell 12, assembled to each other. The upper and lower shells 11 and 12
are formed in the general shape of a box by injection molding of a resin such as
polycarbonate. Note that the upper and lower shells 11 and 12 may be formed, in
addition to polycarbonate, from a thermoplastic resin such as polystyrene, high-impact
polystyrene, acryl styrol, acryl butyl styrol, polypropylene, denatured PPO
(polyphenylene oxide) or the like.</p><p num="0020">As best shown in FIG. 6, the upper shell 11 and lower shell 12 has upright walls
13 and 14 formed along the respectively circumferences thereof. The upright
circumferential walls 13 and 14 are made to abut each other to form the
circumferential wall of the cartridge body 6 as shown in FIG. 6.</p><p num="0021">As shown in FIG. 6, each of the upper and lower shells 11 and 12 has formed 
in the inner side thereof a circular disc compartment 16 whose diameter is slightly
larger than that of the optical disc 5 and in which the optical disc 5 is rotatably housed.
The disc compartment 16 is formed, as shown in FIG. 6, by assembling circular
upright walls 17 and 18 formed on the inner sides of the upper and lower shells 11 and
12. The upright walls 17 and 18 are generally as high as the circumferential upright
walls 13 and 14 of the upper and lower shells 11 and 12. Thus, the upright circular
walls 17 and 18 isolate the disc compartment 16, in which the optical disc 5 is
provided, from the other inner space of the cartridge body 6.</p><p num="0022">Of the upper and lower shells 11 and 12, only front ends 20, of the upright
circumferential walls 13 and 14, at which the disc cartridge 1 is to be first inserted into
a recorder/player are formed generally circular as shown in FIGS. 2, 3 and 6.
Therefore, seeing the front end of the cartridge body 6 when going to load the disc
cartridge 1 into the recorder/player, he will easily know visually and by touching in
which direction he should insert the disc cartridge into the recorder/player. Namely,
the user will not insert the disc cartridge 1 in any wrong direction into the
recorder/player. Note that the front end 20 may be formed to have a polyhedral shape
or to be a combination of a curve and plane.</p><p num="0023">Also, the lower shell 12 has formed in the main side thereof a generally
rectangular access opening 21 through which a write/read mechanism (not shown) of
the recorder/player is to face the optical disc 5, as shown in FIG. 6.</p><p num="0024">Further, the lower shell 12 has formed in the main side thereof a circular drive 
opening 22 contiguous to the access opening 21 and through which a disc table (not
shown) of a disc drive mechanism of the recorder/player is allowed to enter the
cartridge body 6, as shown in FIG. 6.</p><p num="0025">As shown in FIG. 6, the lower shell 12 has formed near the center of the bottom
thereof a compartment 23 defined by an annular projection 24, in which a chucking
plate 10 is provided to clamp and hold the optical disc 5 at a center hole 9 thereof on
the disc table of the recorder/player. The chucking plate 10 is formed from a magnetic
metal such as stainless steel or the like to have a generally disc-like shape. It may be
formed from iron and plated with nickel, chrome or the like or painted for rust
prevention.</p><p num="0026">The aforementioned upper and lower shells 11 and 12 are assembled and joined
to each other by ultrasonic welding for example. Alternatively, the upper and lower
shells 11 and 12 may be designed so that they can be joined to each other with fixing
screws driven, through prepared holes formed near comers of the main side, for
example, of one of the shells, into screw holes formed in corresponding corners of the
main side of the other shell and opposite to the prepared holes in the other shell.</p><p num="0027">Also, as shown in FIGS. 3, 4 and 5, the cartridge body 6 has provided thereon
a shutter plate 25 provided thereon movably in directions of arrow a<sub>1</sub> and a<sub>2</sub> being
opposite to each other widthwise of the cartridge body 6 to open and close the access
opening 21 and drive opening 22, and a shutter open/close mechanism 26 to support
the shutter plate 25 movably. </p><p num="0028">The shutter plate 25 is made of a metal such as aluminum and formed flat to
have a thickness of about 0.3 mm for example as shown in FIGS. 6 and 7. Note that
the shutter plate 25 may be made of aluminum as the base and coated with Alumite or
painted for rust prevention and decoration. Also, the shutter plate 25 may be formed
by punching a thin sheet of stainless steel, polycarbonate, polystyrene, high-impact
polystyrene, acryl styrol, acryl butyl styrol or the like, and its thickness is not limited
to 0.3 mm but may appropriately be selected depending upon the material used.</p><p num="0029">As shown in FIGS. 3, 6 and 7, the shutter plate 25 is formed slightly larger than
the access opening 21 and drive opening 22, and it is fixed at one end thereof to the
shutter open/close mechanism 26.</p><p num="0030">As shown in FIGS. 5, 6 and 7, the cartridge body 6 has formed in the main side
of the lower shell 12 a generally rectangular concavity 28 in which the shutter plate 25
is disposed movably. As shown in FIG. 7, the concavity 28 is formed to have an area
a little larger than an area over which the shutter plate 25 is moved to open and close
the access opening 21 and drive opening 22 and a depth slightly larger than the
thickness of the shutter plate 25 that the shutter plate 25 will not project from the main
side of the cartridge body 6.</p><p num="0031">As will be seen from FIGS. 6, 8 and 9, the shutter open/close mechanism 26 is
disposed in the inner space of the cartridge body 6, outside the upright walls 17 and
18 of the disc compartment 16. As shown, the shutter open/close mechanism 26
includes a guide member 31 to support the shutter plate 25, an operating member 32 
to move the guide member 31, and a transmission member 33 linking the guide
member 31 and operating member 32 to each other to transmit an operating force from
the operating member 32 to the guide member 31.</p><p num="0032">Also, as shown in FIGS. 6, 8 and 9. the shutter open/close mechanism 26
includes a first pivot 34 to support the guide member 31 pivotably, a second pivot 35
to support the operating member 32 pivotably, a guide recess 36 to support the guide
member 31 movably, and support surfaces 37 to support the operating member 32
movably in the directions of arrows b<sub>1</sub> and b<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0033">As shown in FIG. 9, the shutter open/close mechanism 26 includes a shutter
locking mechanism 38 to inhibit the shutter plate 25 from moving by locking the
operating member 32.</p><p num="0034">As shown in FIGS. 8 and 9, the guide member 31 is formed from a
thermoplastic synthetic resin such as polypropylene to have the shape of a block. The
guide member 31 has formed on one side thereof a mount surface 40 to which the
shutter member 25 is fixed at one end thereof with fixing screws 42 driven in screw
holes 41 formed also in the mount surface 40.</p><p num="0035">As shown in FIGS. 9 and 10, the guide member 31 has one end thereof cut to
about a half of its thickness to have a curved face 45 corresponding to one end of the
transmission member 33. Thus the guide member 31 has an integral connecting end
44 to which the one end of the transmission member 33 is connected pivotably. The
connecting end 44 has formed through it a pivot hole 46 through which the first pivot 
34 is inserted, whereby the transmission member 33 is connected pivotably to the
guide member 31.</p><p num="0036">The guide member 31 is movably inserted in the guide recess 36 so as not to
project from the concavity 28 to above the main side of the cartridge body 6, as shown
in FIG. 11.</p><p num="0037">As shown in FIGS. 9 and 12, the operating member 32 has an operating piece
51 which is to be moved in the directions of arrows b<sub>1</sub> and b<sub>2</sub>, and a coupling 52
formed integrally with the operating piece 51 and pivotably connected to one end of
the transmission member 33. The operating member 32 has formed in a position
adjacent to the operating piece 51 engagement recesses 54 in which the upper and
lower shells 11 and 12 are engaged movably in the directions of arrows b<sub>1</sub> and b<sub>2</sub> as
shown in FIGS. 12 and 13.</p><p num="0038">The operating piece 51 is formed as a generally rectangular flat piece. It is
exposed outside the lateral side of the cartridge body 6 and has such a thickness that
it will not protrude from the lateral side of the cartridge body 6. Also the operating
piece 51 has formed on the outer surface thereof non-slip recesses 55 to prevent the
user's finger applied on the operating piece 51 from slipping when the user operates
the operating piece 51. The operating piece 51 has provided thereon a marking 56
such as an arrow to indicate the moving direction of the shutter plate 25 going to be
opened. As shown in FIGS. 12 and 13, the coupling 52 has formed through it a pivot
hole 57 through which the second pivot 35 is pivotably inserted. </p><p num="0039">Also, as shown in FIG. 12, the operating member 32 has a shutter locking
mechanism 38 to inhibit the shutter plate 25 from moving. The shutter locking
mechanism 38 includes a locking portion 61 to lock the operating member 32 against
movement, engagement projection 62 with which the locking portion 61 engages, and
an unlocking portion 63 to free the operating member 32 from being locked by the
locking portion 61, as shown in FIG. 12.</p><p num="0040">As shown in FIGS. 12, 13, 14 and 15, the locking portion 61 is formed integrally
with the coupling 52 of the operating member 32 to be elastically movable, and has an
engagement pawl 65 engaging with the engagement projection 62 of the cartridge body
6. The engagement pawl 65 is protruded to the lateral side of the cartridge body 6.</p><p num="0041">As shown in FIGS. 16, 17 and 18, the engagement projection 62 is provided at
the support surface 37 on the inner circumferential wall of the lateral side of the
cartridge body 6. The engagement projection 62 is formed linear generally
perpendicularly to the moving direction of the operating member 32.</p><p num="0042">As shown in FIGS. 12,13, 14 and 15, the unlocking portion 63 has an unlocking
pawl 66 formed integrally with the coupling 52 of the operating member 32 to be
elastically displaceable and in a position adjacent to the engagement pawl 65 of the
locking portion 61. The unlocking pawl 66 is outside the cartridge body 6. As shown
in FIGS. 12 and 13, the unlocking pawl 66 has formed on one lateral side thereof
directed towards the front end 20 of the cartridge body 6 an operating surface 67
having a generally circular section and which is to be pushed in the direction of arrow 
b<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0043">Therefore, the locking portion 61 and unlocking portion 63 of the shutter
locking mechanism 38 are movable along with the operating member 32 in the
directions of arrows b<sub>1</sub> and b<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0044">Further, as shown in FIG. 13, the operating member 32 has formed in a position
between the coupling 52 and operating piece 51 a generally circular cut 69 to allow the
locking portion 61 and unlocking portion 63 to easily be moved elastically in the
direction of arrows d<sub>1</sub> and d<sub>2</sub>. Therefore, when the operating member 32 is pushed at
the operating surface 67 of the unlocking portion 63 in the direction of arrow b<sub>2</sub>, the
locking portion 61 and unlocking portion 63 are easily moved elastically in the
direction of arrow d<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0045">As shown in FIGS. 9 and 19, the transmission member 33 has formed integrally
at one end thereof the first pivot 34 connected to the guide member 31 and integrally
at the other end a pair of support projections 71 to support the coupling of the
operating member to be pivotable. Each of the support projections 71 has formed
through it a pivot hole 72 and the second pivot 35 is inserted through the pivot holes
72. As shown in FIG. 19, in the transmission member 33, the second pivot 35 inserted
through the pivot holes 72 in the support projections 71 is further inserted through the
pivot hole 57 in the coupling 52 of the operating member 32 which is thus supported
pivotably. Note that the second pivot 35 is made of a stainless steel for example.</p><p num="0046">As shown in FIGS. 8 and 9, the transmission member 33 has a portion thereof 
near the coupling 44 of the guide member 31 formed generally circular convexly
towards the upright walls 13 and 14 of the cartridge body 6 in relation to a straight line
l<sub>0</sub> connecting the center of pivoting of the first pivot 34 and that of the second pivot
35. Also as shown in FIGS. 8 and 9, because of the generally circular portion of the
transmission member 33 near the coupling 44 of the guide member 31, an operating
force applied to the transmission member 33 longitudinally of the latter when the
shutter plate 25 is moved in the direction of arrow a<sub>1</sub> and thus the operating member
32 is moved in the direction of arrow b<sub>1</sub> acts as a component f<sub>1</sub> divided in a direction
parallel to the moving direction of the guide member 31. Thus, the guide member 31
can be moved. Note that the transmission member 33 may have a longitudinal
intermediate portion thereof formed swelling outwardly of the cartridge body 6.</p><p num="0047">Also, since the transmission member 33 has formed therein a cut 57 to prevent
interference with a guide wall 59 (which will further be described later) of the guide
recess 36 when the transmission member 33 is pivoted about the first or second pivot
34 or 35, as shown in FIG. 9, it can operate positively.</p><p num="0048">As shown in FIGS. 6 and 23, the guide recess 36 is formed linear in the lower
shell 12 obliquely relative to the width of the cartridge body 6, perpendicular to the
direction of insertion into the recorder/player. It is formed in a position adjacent to the
front end 20 of the lower shell 12 as shown. That is, as shown in FIG. 23, the guide
recess 36 is formed oblique with a predetermined angle <sub>1</sub>, smaller than 90°, relative
to a center line l<sub>1</sub> of the width of the cartridge body 6. As shown in FIG. 11, there is 
formed integrally with and projecting from the circumference of the guide recess 36
the guide wall 59 which is in sliding contact with the guide member 31. The guide
member 31 is movably inserted at one lateral side thereof in the guide recess 36 and
projects somewhat in the shutter moving concavity 28 of the lower shell 12. Also, the
guide recess 36 has a length which is a sum of the length of the guide member 31 and
the moving distance of the shutter plate 25, a little larger than the width of the access
opening 21 and drive opening 22.</p><p num="0049">As shown in FIGS. 6, 12 and 16, the support surfaces 37 formed on the lateral
sides of the upper and lower shells 11 and 12, parallel to the direction of insertion into
the recorder/player, define between them a guide concavity 75 in which the operating
piece 51 of the operating member 32 is disposed movably in the directions of arrows
b<sub>1</sub> and b<sub>2</sub>. The guide concavity 75 is formed to have a depth a little larger than the
thickness of the operating piece 51 of the operating member 32 as shown in FIGS. 12
and 16 so that the operating piece 51 will not project from the lateral side of the
cartridge body 6. Also, the guide concavity 75 is open at one end thereof at the front
end 20 of the cartridge body 6 such that a shutter operating member 81 of the
recorder/player, which will further be described later, can be introduced into the guide
concavity 75 in the direction of arrow b<sub>2</sub> from the open end of the guide concavity 75
at the front end 20 of the cartridge body 6.</p><p num="0050">Further, as shown in FIGS. 16, 17, 18 and 19, the guide concavity 75 has
formed therein between the upper and lower shells 11 and 12 an engagement slit 77 
open to near the engagement projection 62 and whose surfaces are movably engaged
in the engagement recesses 54, respectively, of the operating member 32. The
engagement slit 77 has a width s somewhat larger than the space between the bottoms
of the engagement recesses 54 of the operating member 32 as shown in FIG. 19.</p><p num="0051">Further, in the operating member 32, the engagement pawl 65 of the locking
portion 61 and unlocking pawl 66 of the unlocking portion 63 are formed to have a
predetermined width w a little smaller than the width s of the engagement slit 77 as
shown in FIGS. 16 and 18, so that they will not touch the surfaces of the engagement
slit 77. Therefore, the operating member 32 can be moved positively in the directions
of arrows b<sub>1</sub> and b<sub>2</sub> without being interfered with by the engagement pawl 65 and
unlocking pawl 66 projected inside the engagement slit 77.</p><p num="0052">In the aforementioned shutter locking mechanism 38, the engagement pawl 65
of the locking portion 61 is formed to project x<sub>1</sub> and engages with the engagement
projection 62 and the unlocking pawl 66 of the unlocking portion 63 is formed to
project x<sub>2</sub> from inside the guide slit 77 as shown in FIG. 21. The projection x<sub>2</sub> of the
unlocking pawl 66 is larger than the projection x<sub>1</sub> of the engagement pawl 65. Thus,
in the shutter locking mechanism 38, when the unlocking pawl 66 is pushed in by the
shutter operating member 81 of the recorder/player, the engagement pawl 65 is
disengaged from the engagement projection 62 as shown in FIGS. 21 and 22. That is,
the unlocking pawl 66 can be moved over a sufficiently long distance to unlock the
shutter. Therefore, in the shutter locking mechanism 38, as the unlocking pawl 66 is 
moved, the engagement pawl 65 is disengaged from the engagement projection 62
positively.</p><p num="0053">In the shutter open/close mechanism 26 constructed as in the above, the opening
and closing of the shutter plate 25 and operation of the shutter locking mechanism 38
will be described below with the accompanying drawings;</p><p num="0054">First, in the shutter open/close mechanism 26, when the shutter plate 25 has
been moved to the closing position where it closes the access opening 21 and drive
opening 22, the engagement pawl 65 of the shutter locking mechanism 38 is engaging
with the engagement projection 62 to lock the shutter plate 25 against movement as
shown in FIGS. 17 and 18.</p><p num="0055">In the shutter open/close mechanism 26, when the shutter plate 25 is moved in
the direction of arrow a<sub>2</sub> to open the access opening 21 and drive opening 22, the
operating member 32 and shutter locking mechanism 38 are operated by the shutter
operating member 81 of the recorder/player as shown in FIGS. 20 and 21. As shown
in FIGS. 20 and 21, the shutter operating member 81 has formed at the end thereof an
engagement surface 82, roughed for example, engaging with the non-slip recesses 55
on the operating piece 51 of the operating member 32. Also, the shutter operating
member 81 has formed thereon, by cutting, an abutment surface 83 having a generally
circular section and abutting the operating surface 67 of the unlocking pawl 66 of the
shutter locking mechanism 38. Note that the shutter operating member 81 may be
formed from a rubber or leaf spring capable of engaging with the operating piece 51 
and the engagement surface 82 may be coated with rubber in this case.</p><p num="0056">In the shutter locking mechanism 38, the abutment surface 83 of the shutter
operating member 81, having entered along the guide concavity 75 of the support
surface 37 in the direction of arrow b<sub>2</sub>, will abut the operating surface 67 of the
unlocking pawl 66 which in turn will be pushed into the engagement slit 77 of the
unlocking pawl 66, as shown in FIGS. 21 and 22.</p><p num="0057">In the shutter locking mechanism 38, as the unlocking pawl 66 is pushed by the
shutter operating member 81, the engagement pawl 65 of the locking portion 61 is
elastically moved in the direction of arrow d<sub>2</sub> so that the engagement pawl 65 is
disengaged from the engagement projection 62 as shown in FIGS. 21 and 22. In the
shutter locking mechanism 38, this disengagement of the engagement pawl 65 of the
locking portion 61 from the engagement projection 62 will allow the operating member
32 to be movable in the direction of arrow b<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0058">As shown in FIG. 22, the engagement surface 82 of the shutter operating
member 81, having further entered in the direction of arrow b<sub>2</sub>, will engage with the
non-slip recesses 55 on the operating piece 51. As the shutter operating member 81
is moved, the operating member 32 will be moved in the direction of arrow b<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0059">As the operating member 32 is moved in the direction of arrow b<sub>2</sub>, it will cause
the end of the transmission member 33 to pivot about the second pivot 35 in the
direction of arrow c<sub>2</sub>, as shown in FIG. 23. Since the transmission member 33 is thus
pivoted about the second pivot 35, it is pivoted about the first pivot 34 to move the 
guide member 31 in the direction of arrow a<sub>2</sub>. The guide member 31 is moved along
the guide recess 36 until it abuts one end of the guide recess 36. Then the guide
member 31 is stopped from being moved, and the shutter plate 25 is moved to a
position where the access opening 21 and drive opening 22 are opened.</p><p num="0060">Also in the shutter open/close mechanism 26, as the shutter plate 25 is moved
in the direction of arrow a<sub>1</sub> to close the access window 21 and drive opening 22, the
operating member 32 is moved in the direction of arrow b<sub>1</sub>, as shown in FIG. 23.</p><p num="0061">Since the operating member 32 is thus moved in the direction of arrow b<sub>1</sub> along
with the movement of the shutter operating member 81, it will cause the end of the
transmission member 33 to pivot about the second pivot 35 in the direction of arrow
c<sub>1</sub>. Also, since the transmission member 33 is thus pivoted about the second pivot 35,
it is pivoted about the first pivot 34 to move the guide member 31 in the direction of
arrow a<sub>1</sub>. As the guide member 31 is moved along the guide recess 36 until it abuts
one end of the guide recess 36 and thus stopped from being moved. Thus, the shutter
plate 25 is moved to a position where it closes the access window 21 and drive opening
22.</p><p num="0062">The transmission member 33 is pivoted about the second pivot 35 in the
direction of arrow c<sub>1</sub> to transmit the operating force from the operating member 32 in
the moving direction of the guide member 31. That is, the transmission member 33
can transmit the operating force in the moving direction of the guide member 31 since
its end portion near the connecting end 44 of the guide member 31 is formed circular 
convexly outwardly of the cartridge body 6 (towards the upright walls 13 and 14) in
relation to the straight line l<sub>0</sub>.</p><p num="0063">Also, in the shutter locking mechanism 38, as the shutter operating member 81
is moved in the direction of arrow b<sub>1</sub>, the unlocking pawl 66 of the unlocking portion
63 is elastically moved in the direction of arrow d<sub>1</sub> and the engagement pawl 65 of the
locking portion 61 is disengaged from the engagement projection 62 as shown in FIGS.
21 and 22. Therefore, in the shutter locking mechanism 38, the shutter plate 25 is
moved to the closing position where it closes the access opening 21 and drive opening
22, it is locked against movement and held in the closing position as shown in FIG. 21.</p><p num="0064">In the disc cartridge 1 constructed as in the above, the shutter plate 25 is
operated by the shutter open/close mechanism 26 to open and close the access opening
21 and drive opening 22 as will be described below with reference to the
accompanying drawings:</p><p num="0065">First, the disc cartridge 1 is set into the cartridge loader in the recorder/player
with the access opening 21 and drive opening 22 being closed by the shutter plate 25
as shown in FIG. 3.</p><p num="0066">When the disc cartridge 1 is set in the cartridge loader, the shutter operator (not
shown) of the recorder/player will move the operating member 32 of the shutter
open/close mechanism 26 in the direction of arrow b<sub>2</sub>. As shown in FIGS. 3, 4 and 23,
as the operating member 32 in the shutter open/close mechanism 26 is thus moved in
the direction of arrow b<sub>2</sub>, the transmission member 33 is moved longitudinally to move 
the guide member 31 along the guide recess 36 in the direction of arrow a<sub>2</sub>. Since the
guide member 31 is thus moved in the direction of arrow a<sub>2</sub>, the shutter plate 25 is
moved in the direction of arrow a<sub>2</sub> to open the access opening 21 and drive opening 22.</p><p num="0067">Then, the disc table of the disc rotation drive mechanism of the recorder/player
enters the disc cartridge 1 from the drive opening 22 to drive the optical disc 5 (this
is not illustrated), while the optical pickup of the recorder/player enters the disc
cartridge 1 from the access opening 21 to write and read information to and from the
optical disc 5.</p><p num="0068">As having been described in the foregoing, the guide recess 36 formed in the
main side of the cartridge body 6 to be oblique relative to the width of the cartridge
body 6 in the disc cartridge 1 allows to freely shape the front end 20 of the cartridge
body 6, at which the disc cartridge 1 is first inserted into the recorder/player. Thus,
since it is possible to easily know the correction direction of inserting the cartridge 6
into the recorder/player, the disc cartridge 1 cannot be inserted in any wrong direction
into the recorder/player.</p><p num="0069">Also, in the shutter open/close mechanism 26 of the disc cartridge 1, since the
transmission member 33 is provided as pivotably connected to the guide member 31
and operating member 32 by means of the first and second pivots 34 and 35, the
shutter plate 25 can be moved positively to open and close the access opening 21 and
drive opening 22.</p><p num="0070">In this disc cartridge 1, since the shutter locking mechanism 38 securely locks, 
against movement, the shutter plate 25 having been moved to the closing position
where it closes the access opening 21 and drive opening 22, the shutter plate 25 can
be prevented from being inadvertently opened, dust can be prevented from entering
into the cartridge body 6, and also the optical disc 5 encased in the cartridge body 6
can be prevented from being broken.</p><p num="0071">Further in this shutter locking mechanism 38, since the engagement pawl 65 of
the locking portion 61 can be disengaged from the engagement projection 62 by the
shutter operating member 81 of the recorder/player, so the shutter operating
mechanism of the recorder/player can be designed more simplified. That is, the
shutter operating mechanism of the recorder/player can be designed more easily for
example by providing the shutter operating member at a predetermined position inside
the cartridge holder in which the disc cartridge 1 according to the present invention is
to be held.</p><p num="0072">Further, in the disc cartridge 1 according to the present invention, since the
shutter open/close mechanism 26 is located outside the upright walls 17 and 18 of the
disc compartment 16 and in the space isolated from the disc compartment 16, abrasion
powder produced as the guide member 31, operating member 32 and transmission
member 33 are slid repeatedly is prevented to come into the disc compartment 16,
whereby information can be written and read to and from the optical disc 5 with a
highly improved reliability.</p><p num="0073">Note that the front end 20 of the aforementioned disc cartridge 1 is formed 
circular convexly in relation to the recorder/player but may of course be formed in any
other shape as shown in FIG. 24 for example. This example of the disc cartridge
according to the present invention, having the front end thereof formed otherwise than
in the above, will briefly be described below with reference to FIG. 24. The same
elements and portions in this variant shown in FIG. 24 as those in the disc cartridge
having been described in the foregoing will be indicated with the same references for
the convenience of illustration and will not be described any further.</p><p num="0074">As shown in FIG. 24, the other disc cartridge 2 is only different from the
aforementioned embodiment in that the cartridge body 91 has the front end 93 thereof
formed generally symmetrically triangular with respect to the center line l<sub>1</sub> of the width
of the cartridge body 91. Therefore, owing to this front end shape, the user can easily
know visually and by touching the correct direction of inserting the disc cartridge 2
into the reorder/player.</p><p num="0075">In the aforementioned disc cartridges 1 and 2, the front ends 20 and 93 are
formed symmetrically circular and/or polyhedral with respect to the center line l<sub>1</sub> of
the width of the cartridge bodies 6 and 91 but the front end may be formed
asymmetrical with respect to the center line l<sub>1</sub>.</p><p num="0076">Also, in the above disc cartridges 1 and 2, the cartridge bodies 6 and 91 have
the compartment 23 defined by the annular projection 24, in which the chucking plate
10 is provided to hold the optical disc 5. However, it should be noted that as shown
in FIG. 25, there may be fixed over a center hole 96 of the optical disc 95 a chucking 
plate 97 around which an annular projection 98 is formed.</p><p num="0077">In the disc cartridges 1 and 2, the shutter plate 25 is provided exposed outside.
However, a shutter cover may be provided to cover the moving range of the shutter
plate 25. This variant of the disc cartridge according to the present invention will be
described below with reference to the accompanying drawings. Note that the same
elements in this second variant in FIGS. 26 and 27 as those in the disc cartridges 1 and
2 will be indicated with the same references as in the aforementioned disc cartridges
1 and 2 and will not be described any further.</p><p num="0078">As shown in FIGS. 26 and 27, the disc cartridge is generally
indicated with a reference 3, and includes a cartridge body 101 formed from a set of
upper and lower shells 105 and 106. In the cartridge body 101, the upper shell 105 has
formed thereon a concavity 108 in which the shutter plate 25 is movable, as shown in
FIGS. 26 and 27. Further, the disc cartridge 3 includes a shutter cover 109 to cover
the concavity 108 as shown in FIGS. 26 and 27.</p><p num="0079">The concavity 108 in which the shutter plate 25 is movable is slightly larger in
area than the moving range of the shutter plate 25 moving over the access opening 21
and drive opening 22 and deeper than the thickness of the shutter plate 25 so that the
shutter plate 25 will not protrude to above the main side of the cartridge body 101.</p><p num="0080">The shutter cover 109 is formed from a resin such as polycarbonate or a metal
such as stainless steel, aluminum or the like to be generally rectangular and flat. The
shutter cover 109 is 0.2 to 0.5 mm thick. As shown in FIGS. 26 and 27, the shutter 
cover 109 has an opening 111 formed in the main side thereof and in a position
corresponding to the access opening 21 and drive opening 22. The opening 111 is
somehow larger in area than the access and drive openings 21 and 22 and slightly
smaller in area than the shutter plate 25.</p><p num="0081">The shutter cover 109 is attached in the concavity 108 with an adhesive tape 93
having an adhesive layer on either side thereof or an adhesive applied on the innerside
thereof facing the bottom of the concavity 108 along the peripheral edge thereof. The
adhesive tape 93 has a predetermined thickness which will assure a predetermined gap
in which the shutter plate 25 can be moved inside the concavity 108. The shutter
cover 109 thus attached in the concavity 108 covers the moving range of the shutter
plate 25 and guide recess 36 of the shutter open/close mechanism 26.</p><p num="0082">In the above disc cartridge 3, since the shutter cover 109 is provided as in the
above to cover the moving range of the shutter 25, it is possible to prevent dust from
coming into the cartridge body 101 from the clearance between the shutter plate 25
and cartridge body 101 when the shutter plate 25 is covering the access opening 21 and
drive opening 22. Also in the disc cartridge 3, since the guide recess 36 is covered by
the shutter cover 109, it is possible to prevent dust from coming into the cartridge body
101 from the guide recess 36. Therefore, in the disc cartridge 3, information can be
written or read to or from the magneto-optical disc 5 with an improved reliability.</p><p num="0083">The aforementioned disc cartridges 1, 2 and 3 are designed such that the optical
pickup approaches the optical disc through the access opening 21. However, it is 
should be noted that there may be provided in a position opposite to the access
opening 21 another access opening through which a magnetic field application head
or the like comes in and another shutter plate to open and close the access opening.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1)
   mit einem plattenförmigen Aufzeichnungsmedium (5),
   mit einem Kassettengehäuse (6), in dem ein Disk-Fach für die Aumahme des plattenförmigen
Aufzeichnungsmediums (5) ausgebildet ist,
   mit einer in dem Kassettengehäuse (6) ausgebildeten Zugangsöffnung (21), durch die ein
zwischen Einlauf- und Auslaufbereich liegender Teil des Aufzeichnungsbereichs des plattenförmigen
Aufzeichnungsmediums (5) für das Lesen und Schreiben von Daten außen frei liegt,
   mit einem beweglich angeordneten Verschlußglied (25) zum Öffnen und Verschließen der
Zugangsöffnung (21) und
   mit einem Mechanismus (26) zum Öffnen/Schließen des Verschlußglieds, der aufweist:
<claim-text><claim-text>eine Führungsnut (36), die in einer Hauptseite des Kassettengehäuses (6) ausgebildet ist,
wobei diese Führungsnut (36) relativ zu einer Seite des Kassettengehäuses (6) schräg angeordnet
ist,</claim-text><claim-text>ein Führungsglied (31), das das Verschlußglied (25) trägt, wobei dieses Führungsglied
(31) beweglich in die Führungsnut eingreift und die Bewegung des Führungsglieds (31) in der
Führungsnut (36) eine Translationsbewegung des Verschlußglieds (25) entlang eines durch die
Führungsnut (36) bestimmten Weges bewirkt,</claim-text><claim-text>und ein Betätigungsglied (32) zum Bewegen des Führungsglieds (31),</claim-text></claim-text>
   dadurch gekennzeichnet,
   daß der Mechanismus (26) zum Öffnen/Schließen des Verschlußglieds ferner aufweist:
<claim-text><claim-text>ein Übertragungsglied (33), das das Führungsglied (31) und das Betätigungsglied (32)
miteinander verbindet, um eine Betätigungskraft von dem Betätigungsglied (32) zu dem Führungsglied
(31) zu übertragen,</claim-text><claim-text>an dem Kassettengehäuse (6) ausgebildete Auflageflächen (37) zur beweglichen Lagerung
des Betätigungsglieds (32) und</claim-text><claim-text>einen an der Seitenfläche des Kassettengehäuses (6) angeordneten Verschlußblockiermechanismus
(38) zum Sperren des Verschlußglieds (25) gegen Bewegung.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1) nach Anspruch 1, bei der das Übertragungsglied (33) mit dem Führungsglied
(31) und/oder dem Betätigungsglied (32) schwenkbar verbunden ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1) nach Anspruch 1, bei der das Kassettengehäuse (6) einen kreisbogenförmig
und/oder polyedrisch ausgebildeten vorderen Endbereich aufweist, mit dem die Disk-Kassette
(1) zuerst in dem Rekorder und/oder Player einzuführen ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1) nach Anspruch 1, bei der das Betätigungsglied (32) auf einer im wesentlichen
senkrecht zur Bewegungsrichtung des Verschlußglieds (25) verlaufenden Seite des Kassettengehäuses
angeordnet ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1) nach Anspruch 1, bei der das Übertragungsglied (33) bzw. das Führungsglied
(31) in Richtungen bewegt werden, die im wesentlichen senkrecht zueinander verlaufen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1) nach Anspruch 1, bei der der Verschlußblockiermechanismus (38) ein
einstückig mit dem Betätigungsglied (32) des Mechanismus (26) zum Öffnen/Schließen des
Verschlußglieds ausgebildetes Blockierglied (61) zum Blockieren des Verschlußglieds (25)
gegen Bewegung aufweist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1) nach Anspruch 6, bei der das Blockierglied (61) mit einer Innenwand der
Seite des Kassettengehäuses (6) in Eingriff kommt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1) nach Anspruch 6, bei der der Verschlußblockiermechanismus (38) ein
einstückig mit dem Blockierglied (61) ausgebildetes Entriegehmgsglied (63) aufweist, das elastisch
bewegbar ist und das Blockierglied (61) elastisch bewegt, um eine Verriegelung des
Blockierglieds (61) aufzuheben.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1) nach Anspruch 6, bei der die Auflageflächen des Mechanismus (26) zum
Öffnen/Schließen des Verschlußglieds in den Seitenflächen des Kassettengehäuses ausgebildete
Auflagevertiefungen zur beweglichen Lagerung des Betätigungsglieds (32) aufweisen und das
Blockierglied (61) und/oder das Entriegelungsglied (63) kleiner ausgebildet sind als die Breite
der Auflagevertiefungen und beweglich in den Auflagevertiefungen angeordnet sind.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Disk-Kassette (1) nach Anspruch 9, bei der das Entriegelungsglied (63) außerhalb des Kassettengehäuses
(6) angeordnet ist.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a disc-shaped recording medium (5);</claim-text><claim-text>a cartridge body (6) having formed therein a disc compartment to house the disc-shaped
recording medium (5);</claim-text><claim-text>an access opening (21) formed in the cartridge body (6) and through which a part of
the recording area of the disc-shaped recording medium (5), extending between lead-in
and lead-out areas, is exposed outside for data read and write;</claim-text><claim-text>a shutter member (25) provided movably to open and close the access opening
(21); and
a shutter open/close mechanism (26)
including.</claim-text><claim-text>a guide recess (36) formed in a main side of the cartridge body (6), which guide
recess (36) is oblique in relation to a side of the cartridge body (6);</claim-text><claim-text>a guide member (31) supporting the shutter member (25), which guide member
(31) is movably engaged in the guide recess (36), movement of the guide member (31)
in the guide recess (36) effecting translational movement of the shutter member (25)
along a path defined by the guide recess (36);
an operating member (32) to move the guide member (31);</claim-text></claim-text>
   characterised in that the shutter mechanism (26) further includes;:
<claim-text><claim-text>a transmission member (33) linking the guide member (31) and the operating
member (32) to each other to transmit an operating force from the operating member
(32) to the guide member (31); and</claim-text><claim-text>support surfaces (37) formed on the cartridge body (6) to support the operating
member (32) movably; and</claim-text><claim-text>a shutter locking mechanism (38) disposed on the lateral side of the cartridge body
(6) to inhibit the shutter member (25) from moving.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) as set forth in Claim 1, wherein the transmission member
(33) is pivotably connected to the guide member (31) and/or operating member (32).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) as set forth in Claim 1, wherein the cartridge body (6) has a
front end, at which the disc cartridge (1) is to be first inserted into the recorder and/or
player, formed circular and/or polyhedral.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) as set forth in Claim 1, wherein the operating member (32) is
disposed on a lateral side of the cartridge body (6), generally perpendicular to the
moving direction of the shutter member (25).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) as set forth in Claim 1, wherein the transmission member
(33) and the guide member (31) are moved in directions generally perpendicular to
each other, respectively.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) as set forth in Claim 1, wherein the shutter locking
mechanism (38) includes a locking member (61) formed integrally with the operating
member (32) of the shutter open/close mechanism (38) to lock the shutter member (25)
against movement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) as set forth in Claim 6, wherein the locking member (61)
engages with an inner wall of the lateral side of the cartridge body (6).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) as set forth in Claim 6, wherein the shutter locking
mechanism (38) includes an unlocking member (63) formed integrally with the locking
member (61) to be elastically movable and which elastically moves the locking
member (61) to cancel a locking by the locking member (61).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) as set forth in Claim 6, wherein the support surfaces of the
shutter open/close mechanism (38) have support recesses formed in the lateral sides of
the cartridge body to support the operating member (32) movably and the locking
member (61) and/or unlocking member (63) are formed smaller than the width of the
support recesses and provided movably in the support recesses.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A disc cartridge (1) as set forth in Claim 9, wherein the unlocking member (63)
is provided outside of the cartridge body (6).</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) comportant :
<claim-text><claim-text>un support d'enregistrement en forme de disque
(5) ;</claim-text><claim-text>un corps de cartouche (6) ayant un compartiment
de disque formé dedans afin de loger le support
d'enregistrement en forme de disque (5);</claim-text><claim-text>une ouverture d'accès (21) formée dans le corps
de cartouche (6) et à travers laquelle une partie de la
zone d'enregistrement du support d'enregistrement en forme
de disque (5), s'étendant entre des zones avant et arrière,
est exposée à l'extérieur pour la lecture et l'écriture de
données;</claim-text><claim-text>un élément d'obturateur (25) prévu de façon
mobile afin d'ouvrir et fermer l'ouverture d'accès (21); et</claim-text><claim-text>un mécanisme d'ouverture/fermeture d'obturateur
(26) comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>un renfoncement de guidage (36) formé dans un
côté principal du corps de cartouche (6), lequel
renfoncement de guidage (36) est oblique par rapport au
côté du corps de cartouche (6);</claim-text><claim-text>un élément de guidage (31) supportant l'élément
d'obturateur (25), lequel élément de guidage (31) est
engagé de façon mobile dans le renfoncement de guidage
(36), le mouvement de l'élément de guidage (31) dans le
renfoncement de guidage (36) effectuant un mouvement de
translation de l'élément d'obturateur (25) le long d'un
passage défini par le renfoncement de guidage (36);</claim-text><claim-text>un élément d'actionnement (32) destiné à déplacer
l'élément de guidage (31);</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
   caractérisée en ce que le mécanisme d'obturateur
(26) comprend en outre :
<claim-text><claim-text>un élément de transmission (33) reliant l'élément
de guidage (31) et l'élément d'actionnement (32) l'un à
l'autre afin de transmettre une force d'actionnement de
l'élément d'actionnement (32) à l'élément de guidage (31);
et</claim-text><claim-text>des surfaces de support (37) formées sur le corps
de cartouche (6) afin de supporter l'élément d'actionnement
(32) de façon mobile; et</claim-text><claim-text>un mécanisme de blocage d'obturateur (38) disposé
sur le côté latéral du corps de cartouche (6) afin
d'empêcher l'élément d'obturateur (25) de se déplacer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) selon la revendication 1,
dans laquelle l'élément de transmission (33) est relié de
façon pivotante à l'élément de guidage (31) et/ou à
l'élément d'actionnement (32).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) selon la revendication 1,
dans laquelle le corps de cartouche (6) a une extrémité
avant, au niveau de laquelle la cartouche de disque (1)
doit être insérée en premier dans l'enregistreur et/ou le
lecteur, de forme circulaire et/ou polyèdre.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) selon la revendication 1,
dans laquelle l'élément d'actionnement (32) est disposé sur
un côté latéral du corps de cartouche (6), globalement
perpendiculaire à la direction de déplacement de l'élément
d'obturateur (25).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) selon la revendication 1,
dans laquelle l'élément de transmission (33) et l'élément
de guidage (31) sont déplacés dans des directions
globalement perpendiculaires l'une à l'autre,
respectivement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) selon la revendication 1,
dans laquelle le mécanisme de blocage d'obturateur (38)
comprend un élément de blocage (61) formé intégralement
avec l'élément d'actionnement (32) du mécanisme
d'ouverture/fermeture d'obturateur (38) afin de bloquer
l'élément d'obturateur (25) à l'encontre d'un mouvement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) selon la revendication 6,
dans laquelle l'élément de blocage (61) engage une paroi
interne du côté latéral du corps de cartouche (6).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) selon la revendication 6,
dans laquelle le mécanisme de blocage d'obturateur (38)
comprend un élément de déblocage (63) formé intégralement
avec l'élément de blocage (61) afin d'être élastiquement
mobile et qui déplace élastiquement l'élément de blocage
(61) afin d'annuler un blocage par l'élément de blocage
(61).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) selon la revendication 6,
dans laquelle les surfaces de support du mécanisme
d'ouverture/fermeture d'obturateur (38) ont des
renfoncements de support formés dans les côtés latéraux du
corps de cartouche afin de supporter l'élément
d'actionnement (32) de façon mobile et l'élément de blocage
(61) et/ou l'élément de déblocage (63) sont formés en étant
plus petits que la largeur des renfoncements de support et
prévus de façon mobile dans les renfoncements de support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Cartouche de disque (1) selon la revendication 9,
dans laquelle l'élément de déblocage (63) est prévu à
l'extérieur du corps de cartouche (6).</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20050511"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050222</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20050225"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20040624"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60103314</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040624</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20040616"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20040519"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20040519"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20030528"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030411</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20030514"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20030402"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030128</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20020821"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20020821"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010912"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010912"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>