<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1122871-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1122871" kind="B1" date="20050504"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23187396" ucid="EP-1122871-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1122871</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20050504</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01300836-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01300836</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010131</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000025572-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000025572</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000202</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20031002</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G05F   1/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G05F   1/10        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G05F   1/56        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H02J   1/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H02J   1/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H03K  17/08        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H03K  17/08        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H03K  17/082       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H03K  17/082       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H03K17/082B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T03K17:08T</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Steuerungsgerät für Leistungsversorgung und Verfahren</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Power supply control device and method</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Dispositif de control pour une alimentation de puissance et méthode</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>YAZAKI CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>YAZAKI CORPORATION</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>OHSHIMA SHUNZOU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>OHSHIMA, SHUNZOU</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>OHSHIMA, SHUNZOU</last-name><address><street>C/o Yazaki Parts Co., Ltd., 2464-48 Washizu</street><city>Kosai-shi, Shizuoka</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Yazaki Corporation</last-name><address><street>4-28 Mita 1-chome</street><city>Minato-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Haley, Stephen</last-name><address><street>GILL JENNINGS &amp;amp; EVERY, Broadgate House, 7 Eldon Street</street><city>London EC2M 7LH</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>When the supply of electric power from a power supply (101) to a load (102) is controlled in a switching manner by a semiconductor switch (QA), reference current generating device (R11, Q2, Q3) generates a reference current, andreference voltage generating device (QB) generates a reference voltage (VDSB) based on the reference current. Detector CMP1 detects a difference between a terminal voltage (VDSA) of the semiconductor switch (QA) and the reference voltage, and the semiconductor switch (QA) is on/off controlled in accordance with the difference between the terminal voltage (VDSA) of the semiconductor switch (QA) and the reference voltage.</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">When the supply of electric power from a power supply
(101) to a load (102) is controlled in a switching manner by
a semiconductor switch (QA), reference current generating
device (R11, Q2, Q3) generates a reference current, andreference
voltage generating device (QB) generates a reference voltage
(VDSB) based on the reference current. Detector CMP1 detects
a difference between a terminal voltage (VDSA) of the
semiconductor switch (QA) and the reference voltage, and the
semiconductor switch (QA) is on/off controlled in accordance
with the difference between the terminal voltage (VDSA) of the
semiconductor switch (QA) and the reference voltage.</p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a power supply control
device and method. More particularly, the invention relates
to a power supply control device having a semiconductor switch
which is controlled in accordance with a control signal supplied
to a control signal input terminal to control the supply of
electric power from a power supply to a load under the switching
control, and a power supply control method in use for the power
supply control device.</p><p num="0002">The power supply control device with a semiconductor
device, which arranged as shown in Fig. 8 is known. This power
supply control device, which is used in a vehicle, selectively
supplies electric power source from a battery to respective
loads, and controls the power supply to the load.</p><p num="0003">As shown, the related power supply control device is
arranged such that a shunt resistor RS and a drain (D) - source
(S) path of a thermal FET QF are connected in series in a power 
supply path for supplying an output voltage VB of a power supply
101 to a load 102 including head lights, power windows and others .
The power supply control device includes a driver 901 which
detects a current flowing through the shunt resistor RS and
controls the drive of the thermal FETQF by a hardware circuit,
an A/D converter 902 for translating the analogue value of a
current monitored by the driver 901 into the digital value,
and a microcomputer (CPU) 903.</p><p num="0004">The thermal FET QF is contained with a thermosensor (not
shown). The thermal FET QF as a semiconductor switch has an
overheat shut-off function to forcibly shut off the thermal
FET QF by a gate shut-off circuit contained therein when
temperature of the thermal FET QF rises in excess of a
predetermined temperature. In the figure, RG is a resistor,
and ZD1 is a Zener diode which keeps the voltage between the
gate G and the source S of the thermal FET QF at 12V, and when
overvoltage is applied to the gate G of the FET, forms a bypass
for a current caused by the overvoltage.</p><p num="0005">This related power supply control device has a protecting
function against an over current flowing through the load 102
or the drain-source path of the thermal FET QF. The driver
901 includes differential amplifiers 911 and 913, which serves 
as a current monitoring circuit, a differential amplifier 912
as a current restricting circuit, a charge/pump circuit 915,
and a drive circuit 914 which drives the gate G of the thermal
FET QF through the resistor RG based on an on/off control signal
from the microcomputer (referred to as MICROCOMPUTER) 903 and
the overcurrent judgement result output from the current
restricting circuit.</p><p num="0006">When the differential amplifier 912 judges on a voltage
drop through the shunt resistor RS that the current exceeds
a reference value (upper limit), viz., it detects overcurrent,
the drive circuit 914 turns off the thermal FET QF. Thereafter,
when the current decreases to below another reference value
(lower limit), it turns on the FET again.</p><p num="0007">The MICROCOMPUTER 903 monitors the current by the current
monitor circuit (differential amplifiers 911 and 913) at all
times. When an abnormal current in excess of a normal value
flows, the MICROCOMPUTER 903 stops the drive current for the
thermal FET QF to turn off the FET. When temperature of the
thermal FET QF exceeds a prescribed value before a drive signal
for the off control is output from the MICROCOMPUTER 903, the
overheat shut-off function operates to turn off the thermal
FET QF. </p><p num="0008">The related power supply control device mentioned above
needs the shunt resistor RS connected in series to the power
supply path, in order to make the current detection. In the
recent trend of large load currents, which induces reduction
of the resistance of the thermal FET QF, the heat loss by the
shut resistor is not negligible.</p><p num="0009">The overheat shut-off function and the overcurrent
restricting circuit operate when an almost perfect short occurs
in the load 102 or the wiring, and large current flows . However,
those fail to operate when a layer short, e.g., an imperfect
short having some short resistance, occurs and small short
current flows. A possible measure taken for the layer short
is that the MICROCOMPUTER 903 detects an abnormal current by
only using the monitor circuit and turns off the thermal FET
QF. A response of the MICROCOMPUTER basis control to such an
abnormal current is poor.</p><p num="0010">Since the shunt resistor RS, the MICROCOMPUTER 903 and
the like are indispensably used in the related power supply
control device, a large packaging space is required.
Additionally, those part and component are relatively expensive,
so that the resultant device is high in cost. </p><p num="0011">Accordingly, the present invention is directed to
solve the above problems and to eliminate the inconvenient
circumstances, and has an object to provide a power supply
control device and method which eliminates the shunt
resistor connected in series to the power supply path in
order to detect the current, hereby repressing the heat
loss, quickly responses to an abnormal current flowing when
a layer short, e.g., an imperfect short having some
resistance, occurs, and is easy to integrate and is low in
cost.</p><p num="0012"><ref typ="patent">EP-A-789458</ref> discloses a power supply control device
with reference current and reference voltage generating
devices and associated detector and controller. <ref typ="patent">EP-A-1017173</ref>,
which constitutes prior art under Article 54(3)
and 54 (4) EPC, also discloses a power supply control device
with reference current and voltage generating devices and
related detector and controller.</p><p num="0013">According to the present invention, there is provided
a power supply control device comprising:
<sl><li>a first semiconductor switch which controls a supply
of electric power from a power supply to a load in
accordance with a control signal;</li><li>a reference current generating device which generates
a constant reference current;</li><li>a reference voltage generating device which generates
a reference voltage based on said reference current and
connected in parallel to the first semiconductor switch,
wherein the voltage characteristic of the reference voltage
is substantially equal to a voltage between terminals of
the first semiconductor switch whenever the load current
reaches a predetermined over current value;</li><li>a detector which detects a difference between the
voltage between the terminals of said first semiconductor
switch and said reference voltage; and</li><li>a controller which controls on/off state of said first
semiconductor switch in accordance with said detected
difference.</li></sl></p><p num="0014">In the power supply control device, the reference
voltage generating device may include a second
semiconductor switch controlled in accordance with the
control signal, and the second semiconductor is connected
in series to the reference current generating device to
form a series circuit, which is connected in parallel to
the semiconductor switch and the load, whereby the
terminal-terminal voltage of the second semiconductor
switch is generated in the form of the reference voltage.</p><p num="0015">In the power supply control device, the reference
current generating device may generate the reference
current dependent on an output voltage of the power supply.</p><p num="0016">In the power supply control device, a voltage</p><p num="0017">characteristic of the reference voltage of the reference
voltage generating device may be substantially equal to a
voltage characteristic in a state that a target current
flows, which is in excess of a maximum current within a
range where the semiconductor switch and the load are
normally operable.</p><p num="0018">In the power supply control device, the semiconductor
switch and the second semiconductor switch are equivalent
to each other in a transient voltage characteristic of the
terminal-terminal voltage when each semiconductor switch
shifts its state from an off state to an on state.</p><p num="0019">The power supply control device may further include an
overheat protector operating such that when the
semiconductor switch is overheated, the overheat protector
turns off the semiconductor switch, to thereby protect the
semiconductor switch.</p><p num="0020">In the power supply control device, the semiconductor
switch, the reference voltage generating device, the
detector, the controller, and the overheat protector may be
formed on a same chip, and</p><p num="0021">in the power supply control device, the reference
current generating device may be located outside the chip.</p><p num="0022">The power supply control device may further comprise
a prohibiting device for prohibiting the controller from 
turning on and off the semiconductor switch for a fixed
period after the semiconductor switch is turned on.</p><p num="0023">The power supply control device may further include
a number-of-times controller operating such that the
number-of-times controller adds up the number of times the
controller turns on and off the semiconductor switch, and
when the number of on/off control times reaches a
predetermined number of times, the number-of-times
controller turns off the semiconductor switch.</p><p num="0024">According to the present invention, there is also
provided a power supply control method of power supply
device including a semiconductor switch controlled in
accordance with a control signal to control a supply of
electric power from a power supply to a load, said power
supply control method comprising the steps of:
<sl><li>generating a constant reference current;</li><li>generating a reference voltage based on said reference
current, wherein the voltage characteristic of the
reference voltage is substantially equal to a voltage
between terminals of the first semiconductor switch
whenever the load current reaches a predetermined over
current value;</li><li>detecting a difference between the voltage between the
terminals of said semiconductor switch and said reference
voltage; and</li><li>controlling on/off state of said semiconductor switch
in accordance with said detected difference.</li></sl></p><p num="0025">In the power supply control devices and in the power
supply control method, when the supply of electric power
from the power supply to the load is controlled by the
semiconductor switch in a switching manner, a reference
current is generated by the 
reference current generating device (reference current
generating step) . A reference voltage is generated based on
the reference current by the reference voltage generating device
(reference voltage generating step) . A difference between the
voltage between terminals of the semiconductor switch and the
reference voltage is detected by the detector (detecting step) .
The semiconductor switch is on/off controlled in accordance
with the detected voltage difference between the
terminal-terminal voltage and the reference voltage by the
controller (control step) .</p><p num="0026">The semiconductor switch (second and third semiconductor
switches to be described later) may be any of the following
switching elements: field effect transistors (FETs) and static
induced transistor (SITs), or emitter switched thyristors
(ESTs), MOS complex devices, e.g., MOS controlled thyristors
(MCTs), and insulated gate power devices, e.g., IGBT (insulated
gate bipolar transistors. Those switching elements may be of
the n-channel type or the p-channel type.</p><p num="0027">In particular, in the power supply control device, it
is preferable that the reference voltage generating device
includes a second semiconductor switch controlled in accordance
with the control signal. Further, the second semiconductor
is connected in series to the reference current generating device 
to form a series circuit. The series circuit is connected in
parallel to the semiconductor switch and the load. The
terminal-terminal voltage of the second semiconductor switch
is generated in the form of the reference voltage. It is
desirable that the reference current generating device, as in
the third power supply control device, generates a reference
current dependent on an output voltage of the power supply,
or that it is a constant current source, as in the fourth power
supply control device.</p><p num="0028">In the power supply control device, it is desirable that
a voltage characteristic of the reference voltage of the
reference voltage generating device is substantially equal to
a voltage characteristic in a state that a target current flows,
which is in excess of a maximum current within a range where
the semiconductor switch and the load are normally operable.
In the sixth power supply control device, it is desirable that
the semiconductor switch and the second semiconductor switch
are equivalent to each other in a transient voltage
characteristic of the terminal-terminal voltage when each
semiconductor switch shifts its state from an off state to an
on state.</p><p num="0029">In a case where an FET is used for the semiconductor switch,
the terminal-terminal voltage (between the drain and the source) 
of the FET forming a part of the power supply path varies depending
on states of the power supply path and the load, viz., a time
constant defined by wiring inductance and resistance of the
path and short resistance, in the voltage characteristic when
the FET shifts its state from an on state to an off state (the
descending voltage characteristic in the case of the n-channel
FET). In a normal operation where no short occurs, the
terminal-terminal voltage swiftly converges to a voltage value
below a reference voltage value. Where a short occurs, it does
not converge to below the reference voltage value. Where an
imperfect short having some resistance occurs, it takes a long
time till the terminal-terminal voltage converges to below the
reference voltage value.</p><p num="0030">The present invention utilizes the transient voltage
characteristic of the semiconductor switch when it shifts its
state from an off state to an on state. In the invention,
judgement is made as to whether or not the terminal-terminal
voltage of the semiconductor switch (or the current in the power
supply path), which forms a part of the power supply path, is
out of a normal state by detecting a difference between the
terminal-terminal voltage of the semiconductor switch and the
reference voltage generating device (reference voltage
generating step) . Overcurrent can be detected by the detector
(detecting step) if the voltage characteristic of the reference 
voltage is set to bear a closest resemblance to the voltage
characteristic in a state that a target current, which is in
excess of the maximum current within a normal operation range,
flows to the load.</p><p num="0031">Therefore, the power supply control device and method
of the invention does not need the shunt resistor, conventionally
used, which is connected in series to the power supply path
for the current detection. With this feature, the heat loss
of the device is suppressed. An abnormal current by a layer
short, such as an imperfect short having some short resistance,
as well as an overcurrent by a perfect short, can continuously
be detected by use of the hardware circuit or the program
processing by the MICROCOMPUTER or the like. Further, the
overcurrent can be detected without the shunt resistor.
Particularly, when the on/off control process for the
semiconductor switch is realized by a hardware circuit, there
is no need of using the MICROCOMPUTER. This feature brings
about the packaging space reduction, and considerable reduction
of the device cost.</p><p num="0032">In a case where, as in the power supply control device,
the power supply control device further comprises overheat
protector operating such that when the semiconductor switch
is overheated, the overheat protector turns off the 
semiconductor switch, to thereby protect the semiconductor
switch, when an imperfect short having some short resistance
occurs, the semiconductor switch is repeatedly turned on and
off by the controller, whereby the current is greatly varied.
That is, in this case, the periodic heating of the semiconductor
switch quickens the turning off of the semiconductor switch
by the overheat protector. In particular, the power supply
control device of the invention can process the abnormal current
caused by the imperfect short (layer short), which cannot be
processed by any way than the program processing by the
MICROCOMPUTER or the like in the conventional device, by using
only the hardware circuit contained in the power supply control
device per se, or not using the control from an external device,
such as MICROCOMPUTER. Therefore, the device circuit is
simplified, and hence the device cost is reduced.</p><p num="0033">In the power supply control device, it is preferable that
the semiconductor switch, the reference voltage generating
device, the detector, the controller, and the second reference
voltage generating device or the overheat protector are formed
on one and the same chip. In the ninth power supply control
device, the reference current generating device is preferably
located outside the chip. By fabricating those means and switch
into one chip in an integrating fashion, the device circuit
construction is reduced in size, the packing space is reduced, 
and the device cost is reduced. In the invention, the current
and the device cost is reduced. In the invention, the current
detection is based on the detection of a difference between
the terminal-terminal voltage of the semiconductor switch and
the reference voltage. With formation of the semiconductor
switch and the second semiconductor switch on one and the same
chip, the invention succeeds in eliminating (removing) common
mode error factors which will appears in both the main
semiconductor switch and the second semiconductor switch
(reference voltage generator) to the almost same extend in the
current detecting operation, i.e., adverse influences by power
voltage drift and temperature drift, and uneven quality among
lots. Additionally, with the feature that the reference
current generating device is located outside the chip, the
reference voltage (reference current) is made to be insensitive
to temperature variation of the chip. Accordingly, high
precision current detection is realized.</p><p num="0034">The power source terminal and the control signal input
terminal of the semiconductor switch are connected to the power
source terminal and the control signal input terminal of the
second semiconductor switch of the reference voltage generating
device, respectively. Further, the negative terminal of the
second semiconductor switch is connected to the reference
current generating device. With such an arrangement, judgement
is made as to whether or not current flowing through the power 
supply path is within a normal range or an abnormal range by
comparing a potential at the load terminal of the semiconductor
switch with that at the negative terminal of the second
semiconductorswitch. Thus, the terminals of the semiconductor
switch and the second semiconductor switch are commonized.
Accordingly, those switches may easily be integrated onto one
chip.</p><p num="0035">In the power supply control device, prohibiting device
prohibits the controller from turning on and off the
semiconductor switch for a fixed period after the semiconductor
switch is turned on. Usually, when the load starts its operation,
an inrush current usually flows into the power supply path.
The inrush current is much greater than the current in a
stationary state. If the controller executes the overcurrent
control for the inrush current, some time is taken till the
load is settled down into a stationary state. As a result,
the response of the load per se delays sometimes . The invention
solves this problem through the prohibiting control by the
prohibiting device.</p><p num="0036">In the power supply control device, number-of-times
controller adds up the number of times that the control means
turns on and off the semiconductor switch, and when the number
of on/off control times reaches a predetermined number of times, 
the number-of-times controller turns off the semiconductor
switch. When an overcurrent by a short circuit is detected,
the overheat protector quickly functions to make an overheat
shut-off (turn off) of the semiconductor switch. In the case
of the imperfect short, the semiconductor switch is repeatedly
turned on and off. The resultant periodic heating of the
semiconductor switch causes the overheat protector to function.
Accordingly, it is estimated that time taken till the overheat
shut-off is relatively long. In this connection, in the
invention, when the number of on/off controls reaches a
predetermined number of times, the semiconductor switch is
turned off. Therefore, even when the imperfect short occurs,
the turning-off of the semiconductor switch may be quickened
to a desired turning-off time.</p><p num="0037">In the Drawings;
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a circuit diagram showing a power supply control
device which is a first embodiment of the present invention.</li><li>Fig. 2 is a circuit diagram showing the detail of a
semiconductor switch (main control FET) used in the embodiment.</li><li>Fig. 3 is a graph showing operation characteristics of
a main control FET and a reference FET in the power supply control
device of the embodiment.</li><li>Fig. 4 is a waveform diagram showing variations of current
and voltage in the semiconductor switch in the power supply 
control device when the device suffers from a short and it
normally operates.</li><li>Fig. 5 is a circuit diagram showing a power supply control
device which is a second embodiment of the invention.</li><li>Fig. 6 is a circuit diagram showing a circuit additionally
used in a modification of the power supply control device.</li><li>Fig. 7 is a circuit diagram showing a second modification
of the power supply control device.</li><li>Fig. 8 is a circuit diagram showing a conventional power
supply control device with a semiconductor switch.</li></sl></p><p num="0038">The preferred embodiments of the present invention will
be described in the order of first embodiment, second embodiment
and modification, while referring to Figs. 1 through 7. In
the embodiment descriptions to be given hereafter, a power supply
control device and method is applied to a device which
selectively supplies power source from a battery to loads, such
as lamps, in a vehicle, and controls the supply of electric
power to the loads. It should be understood that the invention
may be applied to any form of the power supply control device
and method if it controls the supply of electric power from
a power supply to the load or loads in a switching manner.</p><p num="0039">Fig. 1 is a circuit diagram showing a power supply control 
device which is a first embodiment of the present invention.
Fig. 2 is a circuit diagram showing the detail of a semiconductor
switch (main control FET) used in the embodiment. Fig. 3 is
a graph showing operation characteristics of a main control
FET and a reference FET in the power supply control device of
the embodiment. Fig. 4 is a waveform diagram showing variations
of current and voltage in the semiconductor switch in the power
supply control device when the device suffers from a short and
it normally operates. Fig. 5 is a circuit diagram showing a
power supply control device which is a second embodiment of
the invention. Fig. 6 is a circuit diagram showing a circuit
additionally used in a modification of the power supply control
device. Fig. 7 is a circuit diagram showing a second
modification of the power supply control device.</p><p num="0040">A power supply control device, which forms a first
embodiment of the present invention, will be described in
accordance with Fig. 1. The power supply control device is
arranged such that a drain (D) - source (SA) path of a main
control FET QA as a semiconductor switch is inserted in a series
fashion in a path for supplying an output voltage VB of a power
supply 101 to a load 102. In this instance, the main control
FET QA is an NMOS FET having a DMOS structure. If required,
it may be a PMOS FET. </p><p num="0041">In the figure, a circuit section for driving and
controlling the main control FET QA includes a reference FET
(second semiconductor switch) QB, resistors R1 to R12, and RG,
a Zener diode ZD1, diodes D1 to D3, transistors Q1 to Q4, a
comparator CMP1, a drive circuit 111, and a switch SW1. In
the specification description to follow and the accompanying
drawings attached thereto, the resistors are denoted as R
followed by reference numerals and characters. Those
denotations specifically represent the resistors and
resistance values of those resistors. A circuit section 110a
enclosed with a dotted line indicates a circuit section to be
analog integrated onto a chip (this section will be referred
to a chip-circuitry section).</p><p num="0042">The load 102 includes for example, head lights, drive
motors for power windows and others, and starts to operate upon
turning-on of a related switch SW1 by a user. The drive circuit
111 contains transistors being connected in series; a source
transistor whose collector is connected to potential VP and
a sink transistor whose emitter is connected to ground potential
(GND) . In accordance with signals produced by turning on and
off a switch SW1, the source and sink transistors in the drive
circuit are turned on and off, so that a signal for driving
and controlling the main FET QA is produced. In the figure, 
VB indicates an output voltage of the power supply 101, e.g.,
12V, and VP stands for an output voltage of the charge pump
circuit, e.g., VB + 10V.</p><p num="0043">The detail of the main FET QA as the semiconductor switch
is as shown in Fig. 2. In Fig. 2, the main FET QA includes
an internal resistor RG, a temperature sensor 121, a latch
circuit 122 and an overheat shut-off FET QS. ZD1 represents
a Zener diode. The Zener diode keeps the voltage between the
gate G and the source SA at 12V. If more than 12V voltage is
applied between the gate G and source SA of FET, the Zener diode
forms a bypass for a current caused by the overvoltage.</p><p num="0044">The main FET QA of the embodiment has the following overheat
shut-off function. When a temperature sensor 121 detects that
temperature of the main FET QA rises to be in excess of a
predetermined temperature value, the detected information is
held by a latch circuit 122, and an overheat shut-off FET QS
is turned on so as to reduce a voltage between the gate TG and
source SA to be zero volt. In turn, the main FET QA is forcibly
turned off.</p><p num="0045">The temperature sensor 121 includes four diodes to be
connected in cascade, and is formed at a location near the main
FET QA by packaging requirements. With rising of temperature 
of the main FET QA, forward voltage drops of those diodes of
the temperature sensor 121 decrease. When the gate potential
of an FET Q51 decreases to a potential of an &quot;L&quot; level, a state
of the FET Q51 shifts from and an on state to an off state.
As a result, a gate potential of an FET Q54 is pulled up to
a potential at the gate control terminal G of the main FET QA.
The FET Q54 shifts its state from an off state to an on state,
so that &quot;1&quot; is latched in the latch circuit 122. At this time,
the output of the latch circuit 122 is put at &quot;H&quot; level, and
the overheat shut-off FET QS shifts its state from an off state
to an on state. IN turn, a potential at the true gate TG of
the main FET QA becomes the same potential at the source SA
so that FET QA turns off.</p><p num="0046">This embodiment of the power supply control device
provides such protection from over current that if there happens
to be a complete short circuit or a incomplete short circuit
between the wiring from source SA of FET QA to the load 102,
and the ground potential level, it prevents an over current
from flowing through FET QA. This protection will be explained
with reference to Fig. 1 as follows.</p><p num="0047">Reference current generating device, which will be found
in the claim description, is formed with a resistor R11 and
NPN transistors Q2 and Q3. As shown, the bases of the transistors 
Q2 and Q3 are interconnected, and the emitters of those
transistors are connected to ground potential. The collector
of the transistor Q3 is connected to one end of the resistor
R11 and the bases of the transistors Q2 and Q3. The other end
of the resistor R11 is connected to the collector of a transistor
Q1, which is used for dark-current measure as will be described
later. The collector of the other transistor Q2 is connected
to the source SB of the reference FET QB.</p><p num="0048">In the circuitry thus arranged, the collector current
IC(Q3) of the transistor Q3 is expressed by
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">IC(Q3) = {VB - (on-voltage of Q1) -<st32:break type="required" />
(on-voltage of Q3)}/R11.</st32:df>
The (on-voltage of Q1) and (on-voltage of Q3) are smaller than
the power voltage VB. Accordingly, those voltages may be
neglected, and then IC(Q3) ≒ VB/R11. From this, it is seen
that the collector current IC (Q3) is proportional to the power
voltage VB, and depends on the same.</p><p num="0049">The reference current generating device includes a current
mirror circuit. Accordingly, the collector current IC (Q2) of
the transistor Q2 is equal to the collector current IC(Q3) of
the transistor Q3; IC (Q2) = IC (Q3). The reference current Iref
flowing through the reference FET QB equals to IC (Q2), therefore,
it depends on the power voltage VB. In the case of Fig. 1, 
the two transistors Q2 and Q3 are provided outside the
chip-circuitry section or chip 110a. To satisfy IC (Q2) = IC (Q3),
those transistors Q2 and Q3 must be equal in dimension. It
is preferable that the transistors Q2 and Q3 are formed within
the chip 110a rather than outside the chip 110a so that formation
of the transistors having the same dimensions is easy, and the
integration in fabricating the power supply control device is
more enhanced.</p><p num="0050">The reference voltage generating device includes the
reference FET QB. The voltage between the drain and source
of the reference FET QB is the reference voltage to be generated.
The drain and gate of the reference FET QB are connected to
the drain D and true gate TG of the main control FET QA. The
source SB of the reference FET QB is connected to the collector
of the transistor Q2. In this circuit, the reference FET QB
and the main control FET QA are common in the drain D and the
gate TG have the common potentials in their drains and gates
respectively. This feature makes it easy to integrate them
onto one chip (110a).</p><p num="0051">The reference FET QB and the main control FET QA are formed
on one and the same chip (110a) by one fabricating process.
The current detecting method in the embodiment is based on the
difference between the voltage VDSA between the drain and source 
of the main control FET QA and the reference voltage VDSB between
those of the reference FET QB, which is detected by the comparator
CMP1. Thus, the reference FET QB and the main control FET
QA are fabricated onto one chip. Accordingly, the invention
succeeds in eliminating (removing) common mode error factors
witch sill appears in both the main semiconductor switch and
the second semiconductor switch (reference voltage generator)
to the almost in the current detecting operation, i.e., adverse
influences by power voltage drift and temperature drift, and
uneven quality among lots. Further, the resistor included in
the current mirror circuit (resistor R11) as the reference
current generating device is located outside the chip 110a.
With this feature, the reference voltage is made to be
insensitive to temperature variation of the chip 110a.
Accordingly, high precision current detection is realized.</p><p num="0052">In order that a current capacity of the reference FET
QB is smaller than that of the main control FET QA, a ratio
of the number of the parallel connected transistors forming
the reference FET QB and the number of the parallel connected
transistors forming the main FET QA is selected typically as
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">(number of the transistors of FET QB: 1) &lt;<st32:break type="required" />
(number of the transistors of FET QA: 1000)</st32:df></p><p num="0053">A resistance value of the resistor R11 is selected so
as to satisfy
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">IC(Q3) = IC (Q2) = Iref = IDQALimX (number of the transistors<st32:break type="required" />
of FET QB : 1)/(number of the transistors of FET QA: 1000) =<st32:break type="required" />
IDQALim/1000.</st32:df>
In the above relations, IDQALim is reference current value used
for judging whether or not the current of the load 102 is an
over current. Assuming that load resistance when a current
of the reference current value IDQALim flows, as a load current,
through the main FET QA is Rlim, the following relation holds
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">IDQALim = {(VB - (on-voltage of QA)}/RLim<st32:break type="required" />
≒ VB/Rlim</st32:df>
Since IC (Q3) ≒ VB/R11, then VB/R11 = VB/ (Rlim x 1000), and R11
= RLim x 1000. Here, Rlim is a load resistance value used for
judging whether or not the load is an over load, or abnormal.
Therefore, the resistance R11 is a fixed resistance value
determined corresponding to the reference resistance value
Rlim.</p><p num="0054">As described above, since the current of the reference
current value Iref, which flows through the reference FET QB
is VB/R11, the reference current value Iref depends on 
(proportional to) the power voltage VB. Accordingly, the
reference current value IDQALim is proportional to the power
voltage VB. However, the reference resistance value Rlim is
fixed, independent of the power voltage VB.</p><p num="0055">This will be described using numerical values. In an
example where when R11 = 2.4kΩ, the load resistance is 2.4Ω
(2.4kΩ/1000 = 2.4Ω), the drain-source voltage of the main FET
QA is equal to that of the reference FET QB; VDSA = VDSB. When
the load resistance decreases to below 2.4Ω, VDSA &gt; VDSB. This
state is judged to be an overload state. This will be described
by using the load current. When VB (power voltage) = 12V, current
of 5mA (collector current IC(Q3) of the transistor Q3) flows
through the resistor R11. When the load current is 5A (5mA
x 1000 = 5A), the drain-source voltage of the main control FET
QA is equal to that of the reference FET QB; VDSA = VDSB. When
the load current of 5A or larger flows, it is judged that it
is an overcurrent (overload). When the power voltage VB is
16V, the reference resistance value for overload judgement is
invariable at 2.4Ω, the reference current value for overload
judgement is 6.67A (16V/2.4Ω = 6.67A), and its value is changed
(increased) to be higher than 5A when VB = 12V.</p><p num="0056">So long as the load and the wiring are normal, the total
resistance of the load (= load resistance + wiring resistance) 
remains unchanged. For this reason, to judge whether or not
a state of the load including the wiring is normal, it is desirable
that the reference resistance value for the overload judgement
is set at a fixed value. This condition is satisfied by the
method employed in the embodiment, viz. the reference current
value Iref depends on the power voltage VB, since in the method,
the reference resistance value for the overload judgement is
set at a fixed value. However, a constant current method (second
embodiment) to be described later in which the reference current
value Iref is fixed independently of the power voltage, is more
preferable for a case where it is required to judge as to whether
or not the value of the current flowing through the load exceeds
a reference current value, while being independent of the power
voltage VB.</p><p num="0057">Where the circuit specifications mentioned above are
employed, the Reference current generating device and the
reference voltage generating device (reference FET QB) may be
minimized in circuit scale. The result is minimization of the
packaging space and reduction of the device cost.</p><p num="0058">The comparator CMP1 forms a part of &quot;detector&quot; used in
the claim descriptions. The source voltage VSA of the main
control FET QA is applied through the resistor R5 to the &quot;+&quot;
input terminal of the comparator CMP1. A source voltage VSB 
of the reference FET QB is applied through the resistor R6 to
the &quot;-&quot; input terminal of the comparator CMP1. When a potential
applied to the &quot;+&quot; input terminal of the comparator CMP1 is
higher than that applied to the &quot;-&quot; input terminal, its output
is valid (&quot;H&quot; level) . When a potential applied to the &quot;+&quot; input
terminal of the comparator is lower than that at the &quot;-&quot; input
terminal, the comparator output is invalid (&quot;L&quot;).</p><p num="0059">The reference voltage of the reference voltage generating
device, viz., a threshold value at which the output level of
the comparator CMP1 shifts from an &quot;H&quot; level to an &quot;L&quot; level,
may be changed to another value by adjusting the reference
current value Iref of the Reference current generating device.
Some possible ways of changing the setting of the reference
current value Iref of the Reference current generating device
(i.e., the reference of the reference voltage generating device)
are:
<sl><li>a) To locate the two transistors Q2 and Q3 outside the chip,
and to select their configurations and dimensions according
to required specifications.</li><li>b) To locate the resistor R11 outside the chip, and to select
its configuration and dimension according to required
specifications.</li><li>c) To use the combination of a) and b) above.</li><li>d) To change a resistance value of the resistor R11 within 
the chip.</li></sl></p><p num="0060">A value of the reference current (reference voltage) may
be set at a target value in a manner that a plurality of resistors
are disposed in parallel in the chip, and a desired resistor
is selected from among those plural resistors by means of
switching means when the chip is packaged or the bare chip is
mounted. By so doing, even when the power supply control device
is fabricated in an integrated fashion, a plurality of
specifications can be covered with one type of chip. With the
variable setting of the reference current (reference voltage),
it is possible to reliably detect the discrimination of the
perfect short from the imperfect short for each type of the
load (head lamps, drive motors or the like) . Device protection
against the short trouble is accurately performed.</p><p num="0061">The PNP transistor Q1 inserted between the power supply
101 and the resistor R1 is provided for dealing with a dark
current. Where the transistor Q1 is not used, even when the
power supply to the load 102 is not instructed, viz., the drive
control of the main control FET QA is not carried out, a path
of the dark current ranging from the power supply 101 to GND
(ground potential) exists. Accordingly, the electric power
of the power supply 101 is consumed, although its amount is
small, even when the switch SWlis in an off state. For reducing 
the electricity consumption of power supply 101 by the dark
current, the transistor Q1 is turned on when the switch SW1
is turned on (instruct to supply the power to the load 102),
and the transistor Q1 is turned off when the switch Sw1 is turned
off. Therefore, the path for dark current is cut off.</p><p num="0062">The resistors R1 to R3, and the diodes D2 and D3 form
a diode clamping circuit. When the transistor Q1 is in an on
state, VC &gt; VE holds where VC is a potential at a node between
the resistors R1 and R3, and VE is a potential at a node between
the resistors R3 and R2.</p><p num="0063">When VSA (source voltage of FET QA) ≧ VC - 0.7V (= forward
voltage drop of the diode), the source voltage VSA is applied
to the &quot;+&quot; input terminal of the comparator CMP1. When VSA
&lt; VC - 0.7V, a potential of (VC - 0.7V) is applied to the &quot;+&quot;
input terminal of the comparator CMP1, independently of the
source voltage VSA. Thus, even if the source voltage VSA drops,
the &quot;+&quot; input terminal of the comparator CMP1 is held at VC
- 0.7V and does not drop below this potential. The &quot;-&quot; input
terminal of the comparator CMP1 is held at a potential of VE
- 0.7V even if the source voltage VSB of the reference FET QB
drops to a value lower than the potential (VE - 0.7V).</p><p num="0064">With provision of the diode clamping circuit, even when
the main control FET QA and the reference FET QB shift their 
state to an off state and the source voltage VSA and the source
voltage VSB drop, the &quot;+&quot; input terminal and &quot;-&quot; input terminal
of the comparator CMP1 are clamped at (VC - 0.7V) and (VE -
0.7V), respectively. Since VC&gt;VE, the output of the comparator
CMP1 is set at &quot;H&quot; level. And the main control FET QA is reliably
controlled irrespective of the amplitudes of the source voltage
VSA and the source voltage VSB. It never happens that the
potential at the &quot;+&quot; input terminal and the &quot;-&quot; input terminal
of the comparator CMP1 drops to a reference potential value.
In this respect, the voltage withstand capability of the &quot;+&quot;
input terminal and &quot;-&quot; input terminal is improved.</p><p num="0065">An operation of the power supply control device of the
embodiment, viz., a power supply control method, will be
described with reference to Fig. 3. In gathering data plotted
in a graph of Fig. 3, the main control FET QA is a thermal FET,
&quot;HAF2001&quot;, manufactured by Hitachi Corporation in Japan.
Operation characteristics of the main control FET QA and the
reference FET QB are plotted where the power voltage VB = 12V.
In Fig. 3, the abscissa represents the drain-source VDS (VDSA
or VDSB), and the ordinate represents the drain current ID (IDQA
or 1000 × IDQB).</p><p num="0066">In Fig. 3, a one-dot chain line indicates a reference
value for the overload (overcurrent) when Iref (reference 
current) = 5mA. Since 1000 x Iref = 5A, it is depicted in (1)
as a horizontal line of 5A. This represents an operating line
of the reference FET QB when it is converted into that of the
main control FET QA. When the load and wiring are normal and
the main control FET QA and the reference FET QB are in an on
state, an operating point of the reference FET QB is a point
A in the figure. The operating point of the main control FET
QA is present between the origin and the point A. It is assumed
that the load is in an overload state and an overcurrent, for
instance, the drain current IDQA = 8A, flows. An operating
point of the main control FET QA at that moment is a point B.
At this time, IDQA (drain current of FET QA) &gt; 1000×Iref.
Accordingly, the output of the comparator CMP1 is at an &quot;L&quot;
level, and the main control FET QA and the reference FET QB
shift their state to an off state.</p><p num="0067">In Fig. 3, a dotted line (2) indicates a load line depicted
when the load is a resistive load and in an overload state,
and further it contains the operating point B. Here, the
resistive load is such a load that the inductance component
of the load and wiring is much smaller than the resistive
component. A specific example of it is a lamp load. When the
load is the resistive load, the operating point of the main
control FET QA moves from the point B to the right side along
the straight load line (2), with increase of the drain-source 
voltage VDSA. If the load line (2) intersects the reference
value line (1) for overload judgment at a point D, a relation
IDQA &gt; 1000 × Iref holds when the drain-source voltage VDSA lies
in a region on the left side of the point D. When the operating
point of the main control FET QA lies in a region on the right
side of the point D, a relation IDQA &lt; 1000×Iref holds. The
main control FET QA shifts its state to an on state.</p><p num="0068">Measures for preventing the main control FET from turning
on as soon as the operating point enters the region on the right
side of the point D are taken by the embodiment. The measure
utilizes such a phenomenon that when the gate drive of the main
control FET QA by the drive circuit 111 is turned off, a potential
at the output node of the drive circuit 111 becomes ground
potential by the sink transistor within the drive circuit 111.
By the utilization of the phenomenon, current is made to flow
through a path of base of the transistor Q4 → resistor R9 →
diode D1 → node N8 → GND (ground potential), whereby the
transistor Q4 is turned on. By so doing, the &quot;-&quot; input terminal
of the comparator CMP1 is kept at high potential, and even if
the operating point of the main control FET QA is on the right
side of the point D, it maintains its off state. In a case
where the potential at the &quot;-&quot; input terminal of the comparator
CMP1 is excessively pulled up to the high potential, when the
source voltage VSA and the source voltage VSB drop, a timing 
where a logic level at the output of the comparator CMP1 is
inverted from an &quot;L&quot; level to an &quot;H&quot; level by the diode clamping
circuit, delays. To prevent this, it is desirable to select
a resistance value of the resistor R10, which is connected
between the collector of the transistor Q4 and the &quot;-&quot; input
terminal of the comparator CMP1, so as to satisfy R10: R6 =
R1: R3.</p><p num="0069">In the diode clamping circuit, voltage VC obtained by
dividing the power voltage VB by a series circuit of the resistors
R1, R2 and R3 is
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">VC = VB·(R2+R3)/(R1+R2+R3)</st32:df>
When the forward voltage drop of the diode D2 is 0.7V, the
drain-source voltage VDSA of the main control FET QA whereupon
the potential at &quot;+&quot; input terminal being to be clamped by the
potential of VC - 0.7V is
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">VDSA = (VB - VC + 0.7)</st32:df>
In Fig. 3, this is depicted as a hatched vertical line located
near VDSA = 7.3V.</p><p num="0070">An intersection of the load line (2) and the vertical 
line is denoted as C1. When the operating point moves to and
enters a region on the right side of the point C1, the gate
drive of the main control FET QA by the drive circuit 111 is
turned on. After a time of the circuit operation delay elapses,
a potential at the output node N8 of the drive circuit 111 changes
from the &quot;L&quot; level to the &quot;H&quot; level. And the main control FET
QA is turned on again. During the operation delay time of the
drive circuit 111, the operating point further moves to the
right side. When the main control FET QA is turned on, the
operating point turns its moving direction to the left, and
starts to move.</p><p num="0071">When the potential at the output node N8 of the drive
circuit 111 goes high in logical level, the transistor Q4 shifts
its state to an off state. As a result, the pulling up action
of the potential at the &quot;-&quot; input terminal of the comparator
CMP1 by the transistor Q4 disappears. Accordingly, when the
operating point of the main control FET QA enters a region on
the left side of the point D, the drive circuit 111 is put in
an off control mode, and after the circuit operation delay time,
the main control FET QA is turned off. During the operation
delay time of the drive circuit 111, the point D shifts to the
left beyond the point D, and then changes its moving direction
and starts to move to the right. By repeating the above process,
the main control FET QA and the reference FET QB are repeatedly 
turned on and off.</p><p num="0072">In Fig. 3, a line (3) represents a load line when the
load is an inductive overload. Here, the inductive load means
such a load that an inductance component of the load and wiring
is much larger than a resistance component, and an example of
it is a motor load. When the load is an inductive load, the
operating line of the main control FET QA is a horizontal straight
line containing the point B as shown in the line (3). When
the main control FET QA shifts its state to an off state, the
operating point of the main control FET QA moves from the point
B to the right along the load line (3).</p><p num="0073">In the case of the inductive load, if the main control
FET QA and the reference FET QB turn off, both the main current
IDQA and the reference current Iref are unchanged until VDSA
reaches to the point C2 shown in Fig. 3. The point C2 denotes
intersection of the operating line (3) and the vertical line
at VB-VC +0.7V. In other words IDQA is always larger than one
thousand times Iref on the left side of the point C2 irrespective
of pulling up the &quot;-&quot; input terminal by the FET Q4 unlike the
resistive load. When the operating point of FETQA enters the
region on the right side of the point C2, the output of CMP1
turns from &quot;L&quot; level to &quot;H&quot; level. Since there is a delay time
in the drive circuit 111, operating point of FET QA goes on 
to the right side beyond the point C2 during the delay time.
When FET QA and QB begin to turn on, the operating point changes
the moving direction and starts to move to the left.</p><p num="0074">When the drain-source voltage VDS decreases and the
operating point of the main control FET QA reaches the point
C2, the drive circuit 111 is put in an off control mode. After
the operation delay time of the circuit, the main control FET
QA shifts its state to an off state. During the operation delay
time of the drive circuit 111, the operating points further
moves to the left beyond the point C2. When the potential at
the output node N8 of the drive circuit 111 changes from an
&quot;L&quot; level to an &quot;H&quot; level, the operating point changes its moving
direction and starts to move to the right, however. Repeating
the above process, the main control FET QA and the reference
FET QB are repeatedly turned on and off.</p><p num="0075">IDQB = IC (Q2), and when n x IDQB &gt; IDQA, the main control
FET QA and the reference FET QB are keep to be in an on state.
When n x IDQB &lt; IDQA, the main control FET QA and the reference
FET QB are turned on and off. Here, &quot;n&quot; is a ratio of the number
of transistors of the main control FET QA to that of the reference
FET QB, and IDQA and IDQB are the drain currents of the main
control FET QA and the reference FET QB. That is, when the
load current IDQA of the main control FET QA increases to be 
larger than a current which is n times as large as the reference
current value Iref (IC(Q2)), those FETs are repeatedly turned
on and off. After a predetermined time elapses, the main control
FET QA and the reference FET QB are turned off.</p><p num="0076">Figs. 4 (a) and 4 (b) are waveform diagrams showing
variations of current and voltage of the main control FET QA
in the power supply control device of the embodiment. Fig.
4(a) shows a waveform of a drain current ID of the FET, and
Fig. 4 (b) is a waveform of the drain-source VDS. A waveform
(2) represents a variation of the drain current ID in a normal
state. A waveform (3) indicates a variation of it in an overload
state (including a short of a wiring between the source and
the load). In the overload state ((3) in the figure), the main
control FET QA is repeatedly turned on and off, and a periodic
heating of the main control FET QA causes the overheat shut-off
protecting function to operate.</p><p num="0077">As described above, the power supply control device and
method of the invention succeeds in eliminating the shunt
resistor, conventionally used, connected in series to the
power supply path in order to detect the current, and can detect
an overcurrent with high precision without the shut resistor,
and represses the heat loss of the whole device. Further, the
power supply control device and method continuously detects, 
by the hardware circuit, an abnormal current flowing when a
layer short, e.g., an imperfect short having some resistance,
occurs, and as well an overcurrent caused when a perfect short
occurs.</p><p num="0078">The on/off control of the semiconductor switch can be
performed by only the hardware circuit which does not contain
the MICROCOMPUTER. Accordingly, the power supply control
device is reduced in packing space and device cost.</p><p num="0079">By the adjustment of the reference current value Iref
of the Reference current generating device, it is possible to
reliably detect the discrimination of the perfect short from
the imperfect short for each type of the load (head lamps, drive
motors or the like). Device protection against the short
trouble is accurately performed.</p><p num="0080">A power supply control device and method, which forms
a second embodiment of the present invention, will be described
with reference to Fig. 5. The power supply control device of
the embodiment is characteristically featured in that the
Reference current generating device is constructed as a constant
current source. Specifically, difference of the circuit
arrangement (Fig. 1) of the power supply control device of the 
first embodiment is that a resistor R13 is inserted between
the resistor R11 and the collector of the transistor Q1 in the
Reference current generating device, and a Zener diode ZD2 is
connected between the other end of the resistor R13 and ground
potential. In Fig. 5, a circuit section 110b enclosed with
a dotted line indicates a circuit section to be analog integrated
onto a chip (this section will be referred to a chip-circuitry
section).</p><p num="0081">In the circuit arrangement, the collector current IC (Q3)
is given by
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">IC(Q3) = {VZD2- (on-voltage of Q3)} / R11</st32:df>
where VZD2 is a Zener voltage of the Zener diode ZD2. Accordingly,
the collector current IC(Q3), or the reference current value
Iref, is a constant current, which is not dependent on the power
voltage VB.</p><p num="0082">The functions and modifications of the other elements,
and operations of the power supply control device and method
are substantially the same as of the first embodiment, and are
valid in the power supply control device and method of the
embodiment. </p><p num="0083">Modifications of the power supply control devices of the
first and second embodiments described above will be described
in the order of first modification and second modification,
with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p><p num="0084">The first modification is characteristically featured
in that a inrush current mask circuit 105 as shown in Fig. 6
is additionally used to the circuit arrangement (Fig. 1 or 5)
of the power supply control device of the first or second
embodiment.</p><p num="0085">When the load 102 (e.g., headlights) is turned on, inrush
current flows, which is several to several tens times as large
as a normal current in amplitude. The period that the inrush
current flows depends on the type and capacity of the load 102,
but is about 3msec to 20msec. If the overcurrent control as
described in the first or second embodiment is carried out during
the surge-current flowing period, some time is taken till the
load is settled down into a stationary state. As a result,
the response of the load per se delays sometimes. Specifically,
the headlights are delayed in lighting. The embodiment solves
this problem by adding the inrush current mask circuit 105
(corresponding to prohibiting device used in claims) to the 
circuit arrangement of Fig. 1 or Fig. 5.</p><p num="0086">In Fig. 6, the inrush current mask circuit 105 is made
up of FETs Q11 and Q12, a diode D11, resistors R15 to R18, and
a capacitor C11. Terminals N6 and N9 are connected to the nodes
N6 and N9 in the Fig.1 and the Fig. 5 circuit, respectively.
A terminal GND is earthen.</p><p num="0087">The operation of the inrush current mask circuit 105 will
be described. When the switch SW1 is turned on, the transistor
Q1 is turned on. The power voltage VB is applied to the gate
of the FET Q12 through the diode D11 and the resistor R16. The
power voltage VB is applied to the gate of the FET Q11 through
the diode D11 and the resistor R15.</p><p num="0088">The gate of the FET Q12 is connected to ground potential
through the capacitor C11. The capacitor C11 is not yet charged
immediately after the switch SW1 is turned on. In this state,
the gate potential of the FET Q12 is insufficiently high, and
the FET Q12 cannot shift its state to an on state. The FET
Q11 is in an on state during the off state of the FET Q12, and
pulls the potential at the &quot;-&quot; input terminal of the comparator
CMP1 to a lower potential. For this reason, even if large inrush
current flows, the output potential of the comparator CMP1 does
not go low in logic level. And the main control FET QA does 
not shift its state to an off state.</p><p num="0089">With time, the capacitor C11 is gradually charged through
the resistor R16, and in due time the FET Q12 shifts its state
to an on state. With this, the FET Q11 shifts its state to
an off state, the masking state terminates, and finally the
overcurrent detection control functions.</p><p num="0090">The resistor R17 is a discharge resistor for resetting
the capacitor C11 after the switch SW1 is turned off. Its
resistance is preferably selected so as to satisfy R16&lt;&lt;R17
in order to eliminate adversely affect the masking time. The
masking time is determined by a time constant of R16 x C11.
Where the circuitry is integrated into one chip in fabrication,
the masking time can be adjusted by appropriately adjusting
the capacitance of the capacitor C11 attached to the chip.</p><p num="0091">A power supply control device of the second modification
will be described with reference to Fig. 7. The power supply
control device of the modification is characteristically
featured in that an on/off counter circuit 107 is added to the
circuit arrangement (Fig. 1 or Fig. 5) of the power supply control
device of the first or second embodiment. In Fig. 7, a circuit
section 110d enclosed with a dotted line indicates a circuit 
section to be analog integrated onto a chip (this section will
be referred to a chip-circuitry section).</p><p num="0092">In the first or second embodiment, when an imperfect short
occurs, the main control FET QA is repeatedly turned on and
off, and the resultant periodic heating of the main control
FET QA causes the overheat shut-off function to operate.
Accordingly, the time taken till the overheat shutting off is
relatively long. This problem is solved in the following way
by the modification. Specifically, the modification
additionally uses the on/off counter circuit (number-of-times
controller) 107 to quicken the turning off of the main control
FET QA. The on/off counter circuit 107 turns off the main control
FET QA when the number of on/off times reaches a predetermined
time.</p><p num="0093">In Fig. 7, the on/off counter circuit 107 includes
transistors Q32 to Q34, FETs Q31 and Q35, diodes D31 to D33,
a Zener diode ZD31, resistors R31 to R38, and a capacitor C31.
The conductivity type of the FET Q31 is opposite to that of
the FET Q35. In Fig. 7, the FET Q31 is of the NMOS type, while
the FET Q35 is of the PMOS type, and those FETs are arranged
in a latch circuit.</p><p num="0094">The operation of the on/off counter circuit 107 will be 
described. Every time that the overcurrent control mode is
set up, and the main control FET QA is turned off (the gate
potential is set at an &quot;L&quot; level) during the on/off control
of the FET QA, the capacitor C31 is charged through the
transistors Q32 and Q34 and the resistor R32. The capacitor
C31 is charged only when the drain-source voltage VDSA goes
high in logic level during the off control (the gate potential
is at the &quot;L&quot; level), and is not charged when FET QA keeps to
be in the on state or in the off state continuously. The gate
potential of the FET Q31 is lower than a threshold value in
the initial stage, and is in an off state. With progress of
the charging of the capacitor C31, the gate potential increases
and the FET Q31 is turned on. At this time, the true gate of
the main control FET QA is connected to ground potential through
the diode D32, to turn off (off control) the main control FET
QA. At this time, the FET Q35 is also turned on. Accordingly,
the latch circuit including the FETs Q31 and Q35 holds
information to the effect that the on/off counter circuit 107
turned off the main control FET QA.</p><p num="0095">In the power supply control device (Fig. 7) of the second
modification, the drain of the FET Q31 is connected to the true
gate (TG) of the main control FET QA by way of the diode D32,
whereby the main control FET QA is directly on/off controlled.
The modification may be further modified in the following way. 
In a first case, a prohibiting gate (2-input AND gate) is provided
at the output of the comparator CMP1. A drain potential of
the FET Q31 is used for its prohibiting control signal (the
drain potential of the FET Q31 is input to the other input of
the two-input AND gate). In a second case, the drain of the
FET Q31 is connected through a resistor to the &quot;+&quot; input terminal
of the comparator CMP1. Also in those first and second cases,
it is necessary to form a latch circuit for holding information
that the on/off counter circuit 107 has turned off the main
control FET QA.</p><p num="0096">In a third case, after the on/off controls are added up,
the main control FET QA is turned off (off controlled) by the
overheat shut-off function, viz., by using a temperature sensor
121, a latch circuit 122 and an overheat shutting off FET QS
(see Fig. 2). Specifically, the FET Q35 and the resistor R38
are removed, the resistor R31 is connected to the output node
N8 in place of the collector of the transistor Q1, and the anode
of the diode D32 is connected to the anode of the temperature
sensor 121 (consisting of four diodes). In this case, when
the FET Q31 is turned on, potential at the anode of the temperature
sensor 121 (consisting of four diodes) is pulled down to a low
potential. Accordingly, the same conditions as in high
temperature state are set up, and the FET QS is turned on to
turn off (off control) the main control FET QA. </p><p num="0097">Further, in the power supply control device of this
modification, the number of on/off control times is judged based
on a quantity of charge stored in the capacitor C31 in the on/off
counter circuit 107. Alternatively, the on/off counter circuit
107 may be formed with a counter for directly counting the output
signal of the drive circuit 111. In the alternative, when a
count of the counter for counting the output signal of the drive
circuit 111 reaches a predetermined value, the FET Q31 (or
overheat shutting off FET QS) is turned on to turn off (off
control the FET QA.</p><p num="0098">In the circuit arrangement of the power supply control
device of each of the embodiments and their modifications, the
main control FET QA, the reference FET QB, the overheat shutting
off FET QS, and FETs Q11 to Q31 and Q51 to Q54 are of the n-channel
type, and other FETs are of the p-channel type. It is evident
that the conductivity types of those transistors may be reversed,
as a matter of course . In this case, the circuit must be modified
such that the gate potentials for turning on and off the
respective switching elements are reversed in terms of the logic
level, &quot;L&quot; level and &quot;H&quot; level. The same thing is true for
such a modification that the NPN type of the bipolar transistor
is changed to the PNP type, and vice versa. If required, IGBT
(insulated gate bipolar transistor) may be used in lieu of the 
main control FET QA and the reference FET QB.</p><p num="0099">As seen from the foregoing description, in the power
supply control device and method of the invention, when the
supply of electric power from the power supply to the load is
controlled by the semiconductor switch in a switching manner,
a reference current is generated by the Reference current
generating device (reference current generating step). A
reference voltage is generated based on the reference current
by the reference voltage generating device (reference voltage
generating step). A difference between the voltage between
terminals of the semiconductor switch and the reference voltage
is detected by the detector (detecting step). The
semiconductor switch is on/off controlled in accordance with
the detected voltage difference between the terminal-terminal
voltage and the reference voltage by the control means (control
step). The reference voltage generating device includes a
second semiconductor switch controlled in accordance with the
control signal. Further, the second semiconductor is connected
in series to the reference current generating device to form
a series circuit. The series circuit is connected in parallel
to the semiconductor switch and the load. The
terminal-terminal voltage of the second semiconductor switch
is generated in the form of the reference voltage. The reference
current generating device generates a reference current 
dependent on an output voltage of the power supply, or is a
constant current source, as in the fourth power supply control
device. Judgement is made as to whether or not the
terminal-terminal voltage of the semiconductor switch (or the
current in the power supply path), which forms a part of the
power supply path, is out of a normal state by detecting a
difference between the terminal-terminal voltage of the
semiconductor switch and the reference voltage generated by
the reference voltage generating device (reference voltage
generating step). The power supply control device and method
of the invention does not need the shunt resistor, conventionally
used, which is connected in series to the power supply path
for the current detection. With this feature, the heat loss
of the device is suppressed. An abnormal current by a layer
short, such as an imperfect short having some short resistance,
as well as an overcurrent by a perfect short, can continuously
be detected by use of the hardware circuit or the program
processing by the MICROCOMPUTER or the like. Particularly,
when the on/off control process for the semiconductor switch
is realized by a hardware circuit, there is no need of using
the MICROCOMPUTER. This feature brings about the packaging
space reduction, and considerable reduction of the device cost.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung, die umfasst:
<claim-text><claim-text>einen ersten Halbleiterschalter (QA), der eine Zufuhr von elektrischer Leistung von einer
Stromversorgung (VB) an eine Last (102) entsprechend einem Steuersignal (N8) steuert;</claim-text><claim-text>eine Bezugsstrom-Erzeugungseinrichtung (Q2, Q3, R11), die einen konstanten Bezugsstrom
erzeugt;</claim-text><claim-text>eine Bezugsspannungs-Erzeugungseinrichtung (QB), die eine Bezugsspannung (SB) basierend
auf dem Bezugsstrom erzeugt und mit dem ersten Halbleiterschalter (QA) parallel geschaltet
ist, wobei die Spannungscharakteristik der Bezugsspannung im Wesentlichen gleich
einer Spannung zwischen Anschlüssen des ersten Halbleiterschalters ist, wann immer der
Laststrom einen vorbestimmten Überstromwert erreicht;</claim-text><claim-text>einen Detektor (CMP1; SA, N6), der eine Differenz zwischen der Spannung zwischen den
Anschlüssen des ersten Halbleiterschalters und der Bezugsspannung erfasst, und</claim-text><claim-text>eine Steuereinheit (111), die den Ein/Aus-Zustand des ersten Halbleiterschalters entsprechend
der erfassten Differenz steuert.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 1, wobei die Bezugsspannungs-Erzeugungseinrichtung
(QB) einen zweiten entsprechend dem Steuersignal (N8) gesteuerten
Halbleiterschalter enhält, wobei der zweite Halbleiterschalter (QB) mit der Bezugsstrom-Erzeugungseinrichtung
(Q2, Q3, R11) in Reihe geschaltet ist, um eine Reihenschaltung zu
bilden, die mit dem ersten Halbleiterschalter (QA) und der Last (102) parallel geschaltet ist,
sodass eine Spannung (SB) zwischen Anschlüssen des zweiten Halbleiterschalters als die
Bezugsspannung erzeugt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 1, wobei der Bezugsstrom von einer
Ausgangsspannung der Stromversorgung (VB) abhängt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 1, wobei eine Spannungscharakteristik
der Bezugsspannung (SB) im Wesentlichen gleich einer Spannungscharakteristik in einem
Zustand ist, dass ein Zielstrom fließt, der über einem Maximalstrom in einem Bereich
liegt, wo der erste Halbleiterschalter (QA) und die Last (102) normalerweise betrieben werden.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 2, wobei der erste (QA) und zweite
Halbleiterschalter (QB) in einer Übergangsspannungs-Charakteristik der Spannung zwischen
den Anschlüssen des ersten und zweiten Halbleiterschalters einander gleichwertig sind,
wenn der erste und der zweite Halbleiterschalter ihren Zustand von dem Aus-Zustand in einen
Ein-Zustand ändern.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 1, die des Weiteren einen Überhitzungsschutz
(Q5) umfasst, der den ersten Halbleiterschalter (QA) abschaltet, wenn der Halbleiterschalter
überhitzt ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 1, die des Weiteren eine Verbotseinrichtung
umfasst, die verhindert, dass die Steuereinheit (111) den ersten Halbleiterschalter
für eine vorbestimmte Dauer ein- und ausschaltet, nachdem der erste Halbleiterschalter eingeschaltet
ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 1, die des Weiteren eine Häufigkeits-Steuereinheit
(107) umfasst, die eine Zahl von Malen zählt, die die Steuereinheit den
ersten Halbleiterschalter (QA) ein- und ausschaltet, wobei die Häufigkeits-Steuereinheit 107
den ersten Halbleiterschalter ausschaltet, wenn die Zahl von Malen eine vorbestimmte Zahl
von Malen erreicht.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 1, wobei der erste Halbleiterschalter
(QA), der Bezugsspannungsgenerator (QB), der Detektor (CMP1) und die Steuereinheit
(111) auf dem gleichen Chip gebildet sind.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 9, wobei der Bezugsstromgenerator
(Q2, Q3, R11) außerhalb des Chips gelegen ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 6, wobei der erste Halbleiterschalter
(QA), der Bezugsspannungsgenerator (QB), der Detektor (CMP1), die Steuereinheit (111)
und der Überhitzungsschutz (QS) auf dem gleichen Chip gebildet sind.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuereinrichtung nach Anspruch 11, wobei der Bezugsstromgenerator
(Q2, Q3, R11) außerhalb des Chips gelegen ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Stromversorgungs-Steuerverfahren der Stromversorgungseinrichtung, die einen Halbleiterschalter
(QA) enthält, der entsprechend einem Steuersignal (N8) gesteuert wird, um eine
Zufuhr von elektrischer Leistung von einer Stromversorgung (VB) an eine Last (102) zu
steuern, wobei das Stromversorgungs-Steuerverfahren die folgenden Schritte umfasst:
<claim-text><claim-text>Erzeugen eines konstanten Bezugsstromes;</claim-text><claim-text>Erzeugen einer Bezugsspannung (SB) basierend auf dem Bezugsstrom, wobei die Spannungscharakteristik
der Bezugsspannung (SB) im Wesentlichen gleich einer Spannung zwischen
Anschlüssen des ersten Halbleiterschalters (QA) ist, wann immer der Laststrom einen
vorbestimmten Überstromwert erreicht;</claim-text><claim-text>Erfassen einer Differenz (CMP1) zwischen der Spannung (SA) zwischen den Anschlüssen
des Halbleiterschalters und der Bezugsspannung (SB), und</claim-text><claim-text>Steuern (111, N8) des Ein/Aus-Zustands des Halbleiterschatters entsprechend der erfassten
Differenz.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first semiconductor switch (QA) which controls a supply
of electric power from a power supply (VB) to a load (102) in
accordance with a control signal (N8);</claim-text><claim-text>a reference current generating device (Q2, Q3, R11) which generates
a constant reference current;</claim-text><claim-text>a reference voltage generating device (QB) which generates
a reference voltage (SB) based on said reference current and
connected in parallel to the first semiconductor switch (QA),
wherein the voltage characteristic of the reference voltage
is substantially equal to a voltage between terminals of
the first semiconductor switch whenever the load current
reaches a predetermined over current value;</claim-text><claim-text>a detector (CMP1; SA, N6) which detects a difference between the
voltage between the terminals of said first semiconductor
switch and said reference voltage; and</claim-text><claim-text>a controller (111) which controls on/off state of said first
semiconductor switch in accordance with said detected
difference.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device according to claim 1,
wherein said reference voltage generating device (QB) includes
a second semiconductor switch controlled in accordance with
said control signal (N8), said second semiconductor switch (QB) is
connected in aeries to said reference current generating
device (Q2, Q3, R11) to form a series circuit which is connected in
parallel to said firs semiconductor switch (QA) and said load (102)
so that a voltage (SB) between terminals of said second
semiconductor switch is generated as said reference
voltage.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply device according to claim 1, wherein
said reference current depends on an output voltage of said
power supply (VB).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply device according to claim 1, wherein a
voltage characteristic of said reference voltage (SB) is
substantially equal to a voltage characteristic in a state
that a current which is in excess of a maximum current
within a range where said first semiconductor switch (QA) and
said load (102) are normally operated flows.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device according to claim 2,
wherein said first (QA) and second semiconductor switch (QB) are
equivalent to each other in a transient voltage
characteristic of said voltage between said terminals of
said first and second semiconductor switches when each said
first and second semiconductor switch shifts its state from
said off state to said on state.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device according to claim 1
further comprising an overheat protector (QS) which turns off
said first semiconductor switch (QA) when said semiconductor
switch is overheat.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device according to claim 1
further comprising a prohibiting device which prohibits
said controller (111) from turning on and off said first
semiconductor switch for a predetermined period after said
first semiconductor switch is turned on.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device according to claim 1
further comprising a number-of-times controller (107), which
counts a number of times that said controller turns on and
off said first semiconductor switch (QA), said number-of-times
controller (107) turns off said first semiconductor switch when
said number of times reaches a predetermined number of
times.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device according to claim 1,
wherein said first semiconductor switch (QA), said reference
voltage generator (QB), said detector (CMP1), and said controller (111) are
formed on a same chip.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device according to claim 9,
wherein said reference current generator (Q2, Q3, R11) is located outside
said chip.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device according to claim 6,
wherein said first semiconductor switch (QA), said reference
voltage generator (QB), said detector (CMP1), said controller (111), and said
overheat protector (QS) are formed on a same chip.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control device according to claim 11,
wherein said reference current generator (Q2, Q3, R11) is located outside
said chip.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A power supply control method of power supply device
including a semiconductor switch (QA) controlled in accordance
with a control signal (N8) to control a supply of electric power
from a power supply (VB) to a load (102), said power supply control
method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>generating a constant reference current (Q2, Q3, R11;</claim-text><claim-text>generating a reference voltage (SB) based on said reference
current, wherein the voltage characteristic of the
reference voltage (SB) is substantially equal to a voltage
between terminals of the first semiconductor switch (QA)
whenever the load current reaches a predetermined over
current value;</claim-text><claim-text>detecting a difference (CMP1) between the voltage (SA) between the
terminals of said semiconductor switch and said reference
voltage (SB); and</claim-text><claim-text>controlling (111,N8) on/off state of said semiconductor switch
in accordance with said detected difference.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>un premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur (QA) qui
commande la fourniture d'énergie électrique à une charge (102) à partir
d'une source d'alimentation (VB), conformément à un signal de commande
(N8);</claim-text><claim-text>un dispositif de génération de courant de référence (Q2, Q3,
R11) qui génère un courant de référence constant;</claim-text><claim-text>un dispositif de génération de tension de référence (QB) qui génère
une tension de référence (SB), sur la base du courant de référence,
et connecté en parallèle sur le premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur
(QA), dans lequel la caractéristique de tension de la tension
de référence est pratiquement égale à une tension entre des bornes du
premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur chaque fois que le
courant de charge atteint une valeur de surintensité prédéterminée;</claim-text><claim-text>un détecteur (CMP1; SA, N6) qui détecte une différence entre la
tension entre les bornes du premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur
et la tension de référence; et</claim-text><claim-text>une unité de commande (111) qui commande un état passant /
bloqué du premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur, conformément
à la différence détectée.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation selon la revendication
1, dans lequel le dispositif de génération de tension de référence
(QB) comprend un second élément de commutation à semiconducteur
commandé conformément au signal de commande (N8), ce second élément
de commutation à semiconducteur (QB) étant connecté en série
avec le dispositif de génération de courant de référence (Q2, Q3, R11)
pour former un circuit série qui est connecté en parallèle sur le premier
élément de commutation à semiconducteur (QA) et sur la charge (102), de
façon qu'une tension (SB) entre les bornes du second élément de commutation
à semiconducteur soit générée comme la tension de référence.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif d'alimentation selon la revendication 1, dans lequel
le courant de référence dépend d'une tension de sortie de la source
d'alimentation (VB).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif d'alimentation selon la revendication 1, dans lequel
une caractéristique de tension de la tension de référence (SB) est
pratiquement égale à une caractéristique de tension dans un état dans
lequel il circule un courant qui dépasse un courant maximal dans une
plage dans laquelle le premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur
(QA) et la charge (102) fonctionnent normalement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation selon la revendication
2, dans lequel les premier (QA) et second (QB) éléments de commutation
à semiconducteur sont équivalents l'un à l'autre en ce qui concerne
une caractéristique de tension transitoire de la tension entre les bornes
des premier et second éléments de commutation à semiconducteur, lorsque
chacun des premier et second éléments de commutation à semiconducteur
change d'état pour passer de l'état bloqué à l'état passant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation selon la revendication
1, comprenant en outre un élément de protection contre un échauffement
excessif (QS) qui bloque le premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur
(QA) lorsque cet élément de commutation à semiconducteur
est surchauffé.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation selon la revendication
1, comprenant en outre un dispositif d'interdiction qui interdit à l'unité
de commande (111) de commuter à l'état passant et à l'état bloqué le
premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur, pendant une durée
prédéterminée après que le premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur
a été commuté à l'état passant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation selon la revendication
1, comprenant en outre une unité de commande de nombre de fois
(107) qui compte un nombre de fois que l'unité de commande commute le
premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur (QA) à l'état passant
et à l'état bloqué, et cette unité de commande de nombre de fois (107)
bloque le premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur lorsque le
nombre de fois atteint un nombre de fois prédéterminé.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation selon la revendication
1, dans lequel le premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur
(QA), le générateur de tension de référence (QB), le détecteur (CMP1) et
l'unité de commande (111) sont formés sur une même puce.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation selon la revendication
9, dans lequel le générateur de courant de référence (Q2, Q3, R11)
est placé à l'extérieur de la puce.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation selon la revendication
6, dans lequel le premier élément de commutation à semiconducteur
(QA), le générateur de tension de référence (QB), le détecteur
(CMP1), l'unité de commande (111) et l'élément de protection contre un
échauffement excessif (QS) sont formés sur une même puce.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un dispositif de commande d'alimentation selon la revendication
11, dans lequel le générateur de courant de référence (Q2, Q3,
R11) est placé à l'extérieur de la puce.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Un procédé de commande d'alimentation pour un dispositif
d'alimentation incluant un élément de commutation à semiconducteur (QA)
commandé conformément à un signal de commande (N8), pour commander
la fourniture d'énergie électrique à une charge (102) à partir d'une
source d'alimentation (VB), ce procédé de commande d'alimentation comprenant
les étapes suivantes :
<claim-text><claim-text>on génère un courant de référence constant (Q2, Q3, R11);</claim-text><claim-text>on génère une tension de référence (SB) sur la base du courant
de référence, la caractéristique de tension de la tension de référence
(SB) étant pratiquement égale à une tension entre des bornes du premier
élément de commutation à semiconducteur (QA) chaque fois que le courant
de charge atteint une valeur de surintensité prédéterminée;</claim-text><claim-text>on détecte une différence (CMP1) entre la tension (SA) entre les
bornes de l'élément de commutation à semiconducteur, et la tension de
référence (SB); et</claim-text><claim-text>on commande (111, N8) l'état passant / bloqué de l'élément de
commutation à semiconducteur conformément à la différence détectée.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20060426"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060207</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20060310"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20050609"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60110475</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050609</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050601"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050504"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050504"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20030129"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20021213</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20030102"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE FR GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20021113"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020912</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20020403"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20020403"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIC1" date="20020403"><legal-event-body><event-title>CLASSIFICATION (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>7H 02M 3/00 A, 7H 03K 17/082 B</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010808"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010808"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>