<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1510230-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1510230" kind="A1" date="20050302"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="24287964" ucid="EP-1510230-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1510230</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050302</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04077727-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04077727</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000218</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-253383" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>253383</doc-number><date>19990219</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="EP-00908735-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00908735</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000218</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-25338399-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>25338399</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990219</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"/><term-of-grant/><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61M   5/142       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61M   5/142       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F04F   3/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">F04F   3/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61M5/142P10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61M5:142G4</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Medizinische Unterdruck-Infusionspumpe</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Negative pressure medical infusion pump</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Pompe d'infusion médicale à basse pression</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0488701-A1" source="SEA" category="X" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0488701</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4191181-A" source="SEA" category="XD" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>4191181</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5722957-A" source="SEA" category="A" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>5722957</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997040873-A1" source="SEA" category="A" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997040873</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id></patcit></patent-citations></citations><figures/></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>MEDICAL RES GROUP INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>MINIMED INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>MEDICAL RESEARCH GROUP, INC.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>MINIMED INC.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Medical Research Group, Inc.</last-name><address><street>12744 San Fernando Road</street><city>Sylmar, CA 91342-3728</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>MiniMed Inc.</last-name><address><street>12744 San Fernando Road</street><city>Sylmar, California 91342-3728</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>VAN ANTWERP WILLIAM P</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>DY NORMAN V</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>VAN ANTWERP, WILLIAM P.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>DY, NORMAN V.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>The designation of the inventor has not yet been filed</last-name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Reeve, Anna Elizabeth</last-name><address><street>Lloyd Wise, Commonwealth House, 1-19 New Oxford Street</street><city>London WC1A 1LW</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>A medication infusion pump (10; 110) comprises a housing (12;112), a medication chamber (14;114) defined within the housing (12;112), a pumping mechanism for supplying (16;116) the medication from the medication chamber (14;114) to a patient, a reservoir (28;122) defined within the housing (12;112) and adapted to apply a predetermined pressure less than ambient atmospheric pressure to the medication chamber (14;114), and a gas within the reservoir (28;122). The gas has a vapor pressure less than ambient atmospheric pressure at normal human physiological temperature. The gas is selected from the group consisting of cyclopentane, 2,2-dimethylbutane, 1,3-pentadiene, and 2-methyl-2-butene and does not have an adverse effect on ozone. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">A medication infusion pump (10; 110) comprises a housing (12;112), a
medication chamber (14;114) defined within the housing (12;112), a pumping
mechanism for supplying (16;116) the medication from the medication
chamber (14;114) to a patient, a reservoir (28;122) defined within the housing
(12;112) and adapted to apply a predetermined pressure less than ambient
atmospheric pressure to the medication chamber (14;114), and a gas within
the reservoir (28;122). The gas has a vapor pressure less than ambient
atmospheric pressure at normal human physiological temperature. The gas is
selected from the group consisting of cyclopentane, 2,2-dimethylbutane, 1,3-pentadiene,
and 2-methyl-2-butene and does not have an adverse effect on
ozone.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1510918-A2-00000001" he="85" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no"/></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><heading><u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to medication infusion pumps, more
particularly implantable infusion pumps.</p><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0002">Medication infusion pumps that supply a medication to a patient, in
particular implantable infusion pumps, are known. Known infusion pumps
typically include a housing that contains a medication chamber and a
propellant chamber, together with appropriate means for loading the selected
medication into the medication chamber and for supplying the medication to
the patient. One known type of infusion pump includes a reservoir containing
a gas at a pressure below atmospheric pressure. Such infusion pumps are
characterized as "negative pressure" pumps. Negative pressure pumps offer
the advantage of facilitating fill of the medication chamber by acting to draw in
the medication from a hypodermic needle or other supply source into the
medication chamber. Such pumps also have the advantage of inhibiting
undesirable leakage from the medication chamber.</p><p num="0003">Negative pressure infusion pumps are described, for example, in <ref type="patent">U.S.
Patent No. 4,191,181</ref> (<ref type="patent">France Pat. Pub. No. 2,370,481</ref>, <ref type="patent">Germany Pat. Pub.
No. 2652026</ref>, and <ref type="patent">Great Britain Pat. Pub. No. 1,554,083</ref>), to Frenetzki et al.;
<ref type="patent">U.S. Patent No. 4,373,527</ref> (<ref type="patent">France Pat. Pub. No. 2,537,873</ref>, <ref type="patent">Germany Pat.
Pub. No. 3247232</ref>, and <ref type="patent">Great Britain Pat. Pub. No. 2,132,090</ref>), to Fischell et
al.; <ref type="patent">U.S. Patent No. 4,511,355</ref> (<ref type="patent">European Pat Pub. No. 75,762</ref>), to Frenetzki
et al.; <ref type="patent">U.S. Patent No. 4,573,994</ref> (<ref type="patent">European Pat Pub. No. 95,506</ref>), to Fischell
et al.; and <ref type="patent">U.S. Patent No. 5,514,103</ref> (<ref type="patent">European Pat Pub. No. 687,475</ref>), to
Srisathapat et al. Each of these patent publications is hereby incorporated
herein by reference as if set forth herein. In a typical negative pressure 
infusion pump, a medication is drawn into the medication chamber under the
action of a gas maintained in a flexible reservoir at negative pressure. Once
the medication is drawn into the medication chamber, the medication is
subsequently delivered to the patient via a separate pumping mechanism.</p><p num="0004">Modern environmental concerns mandate that gases employed in
"negative pressure" pumps be environmentally benign. It is of particular
concern to avoid gases that have an adverse effect on ozone.</p><p num="0005">A need exists for a negative pressure infusion pump that employs an
environmentally acceptable gas in its gas reservoir.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u></heading><p num="0006">A first aspect of the invention provides a medication infusion pump
comprising
<sl><li>a) a housing,</li><li>b) a medication chamber defined within the housing,</li><li>c) means for supplying the medication from the medication
chamber to a patient,</li><li>d) a reservoir defined within the housing and adapted to apply a
predetermined pressure less than ambient atmospheric pressure to the
medication chamber, and</li><li>e) a gas within the reservoir, the gas having a vapor pressure less
than ambient atmospheric pressure at normal human physiological
temperature, characterised in that the gas is selected from the group
consisting of cyclopentane, 2,2-dimethylbutane, 1,3-pentadiene, and 2-methyl-2-butene
and does not have an adverse effect on ozone.</li></sl></p><p num="0007">Preferably, the medication infusion pump is adapted to be passively
refilled with a medication.</p><p num="0008">Preferably, the gas comprises a non-toxic gas.</p><p num="0009">In a preferred embodiment the gas has a vapor pressure less than 14.7
psia (101 kPa) at 37°C.</p><p num="0010">Preferably, the gas has a vapor pressure less than 10.7 psia (74 kPa)
at 37°C.</p><p num="0011">In a preferred embodiment, the gas is selected from the group
consisting of cyclopentane and dimethylbutane.</p><p num="0012">Preferably, the medication infusion pump comprises a plurality of gases
within the reservoir, wherein the plurality of gases has a combined vapor
pressure less than 14.7 psia (101 kPa) at 37°C.</p><p num="0013">Preferably, the medication chamber and the reservoir are separated by
a barrier which is resistant to gas.</p><p num="0014">A second aspect of the invention provides a medication infusion pump
for use in a method of supplying a medication to a patient from a medication
infusion pump, the infusion pump including a housing, a medication chamber
defined within the housing, a pumping mechanism for supplying the
medication from the medication chamber to the patient, and a reservoir
defined within the housing and adapted to apply a predetermined pressure
less than ambient atmospheric pressure to the medication chamber, the
method comprising the steps of
<sl><li>(i) filling the reservoir with a gas having a vapor pressure less than
ambient atmospheric pressure at normal human physiological
temperature, the gas being selected from the group consisting of 
cyclopentane, 2,2-dimethylbutane, 1,3-pentadiene, and 2-methyl-2-butene,
and wherein the gas does not have an adverse effect on
ozone,</li><li>ii) drawing the medication into the medication chamber by exertion
of the predetermined negative pressure on the medication, and</li><li>iii) dispensing the medication from the medication chamber via the
pumping mechanism.</li></sl></p><p num="0015">Other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will
become apparent to those skilled in the art from the following detailed
description. It is to be understood, however, that the detailed description and
specific examples, while indicating preferred embodiments of the present
invention, are given by way of illustration and not limitation.</p><heading><u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawings</u></heading><p num="0016">The invention may be more readily understood by referring to the
accompanying drawings in which
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a side sectional view of a negative pressure medication
infusion pump according to the present invention that employs a flexible
bladder as the gas reservoir, and</li><li>Fig. 2 is a schematic representation, partially cut-away, of a portion of
an alternative embodiment of a negative pressure medication infusion pump
according to the present invention that employs a corrugated gas reservoir.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u></heading><p num="0017">Gases are "non-toxic" for the purposes of this invention if they comply
with the standard established in ISO 10993. Gases are also "non-toxic" for 
the purposes of this invention if they are included in the inventory of the
United States Toxic Substances Control Act.</p><p num="0018">A gas is considered "non-ozone depleting" for the purposes of this
invention if (i) the gas has an Ozone Depletion Potential (ODP) less than 1.0,
more preferably less than about 0.10 (with the ODP of CFC-11=1.0) and
either (ii) the gas is not a Class I or Class II controlled substance as set forth
in Volume 40 of the United States Code of Federal Regulation Part 82,
Subpart A (40 C.F.R. Part 82, Subpart A), or (iii) the gas is subject to the
exemption provided for under 40 C.F.R. Part 82.4(s)(1) (use in a medical
device). Determination of the ODP of a gas is readily carried out by those
skilled in the art.</p><p num="0019">Gases useful according to the present invention have a vapor pressure
less than ambient atmospheric pressure at normal human physiological
temperature (37°C). More particularly, the gas has a vapor pressure less than
sea level atmospheric pressure (i.e. 14.7 psia (101 Pa) at 37°C. Preferably,
the gas has a vapor pressure less than 10.7 psia (74 kPa) at 37°C. Exemplary
gases include cyclopentane (vapor pressure 9.4 psia (65 kPa) at 37°C) and
2,2-dimethylbutane (vapor pressure 9.6 psia (66 kPa) at 37°C). Other useful
gases include 1,3-pentadiene (vapor pressure 12.50 psia (86 kPa) at 37°C),
2-methyl-2-butene (vapor pressure 14.24 psia (98 kPa) at 37°C), and methyl
iodide (vapor pressure 11.10 psia (77 kPa) at 37°C). Other branched chain
fluoroalkanes and fluoroalkenes are also suitable for use according to the
instant invention.</p><p num="0020">Gases having vapor pressures lower than 10.7 psia (74 kPa) at 37°C
are particularly desirable in that infusion pumps that employ such gases can
be effectively used even at relatively high altitudes. For example, the vapor
pressure of 2,2-dimethylbutane, 9.4 psia (65 kPa) corresponds to an altitude
of about 12,000 feet (3.7 kilometres) above sea level. The vapor pressure of 
cyclopentane, 9.6 psia (66 kPa) corresponds to an altitude of about 11,500
feet (3.5 kilometres). Thus, use of the foregoing preferred gases in
accordance with the present invention allows the infusion pump to be
employed in almost all major population centers and most mountain areas, as
well as in aircraft. When implanted in a human patient, these embodiments of
the infusion pump allow the patient to travel freely.</p><p num="0021">It is also contemplated that mixture of two or more gases are also
useful according to the instant invention, provided that the mixture is capable
of maintaining a pressure less than 14.7 psia (101 kPa), more preferably less
than 10.7 psia (74 kPa).</p><p num="0022">Desirably, the gas or gas mixture maintains the reservoir at a pressure
less than 14.7psia (101 kPa), more preferably less than 10.7psia (74kPa), at
37°C when the medication chamber is filled and also when the medication is
unfilled. The stability of the vapor pressure may be obtained by ensuring that
a sufficient quantity of the fill gas material (i.e. liquid phase and gas phase
material) is placed in the fill gas reservoir. This may be achieved by ensuring
that some liquid phase portion of the fill gas material remains in the reservoir
when the medication chamber is empty. It is also preferred that some of the fill
gas remain in the gaseous state when the medication chamber is full.</p><p num="0023">Turning now to Figure 1, a schematic representation of a first
embodiment of a medication infusion pump 10 according to the invention
includes a housing 12 within which a medication chamber 14 is defined. A
pumping mechanism 16 is provided for supplying a medication from
medication chamber 14 to a patient. The pumping mechanism 16 includes a
pump 18, control circuitry 20, battery 22 and catheter 24. Other known means
for supplying a medication from medication chamber 14 can also be
employed.</p><p num="0024">A medication is loaded into medication chamber 14, for example, via an 
inlet or refill fitting 26 adapted to receive a hypodermic needle (not shown).</p><p num="0025">Reservoir 28 is defined within housing 12. In the illustrated
embodiment, reservoir 28 is a flexible and expansible bag formed from a
polymeric material and secured within housing 12. Alternatively, reservoir 28
can be defined by a flexible membrane that extends across the interior of
housing 12. The selected gas or gas mixture is supplied to reservoir 28 at the
selected pressure by conventional means known to those skilled in the art.</p><p num="0026">A medication is loaded into medication chamber 14, for example, via an
inlet or refill fitting 26 adapted to receive a hypodermic needle (not shown).
Due to the negative pressure maintained in reservoir 28, the medication is
passively drawn into the medication chamber 14, and is subsequently
dispensed via pump 18.</p><p num="0027">In Figure 2, an alternative embodiment of a medication infusion pump
110 according to the invention employs a reservoir defined by a flexible
corrugated structure. Housing 112 has defined therein medication chamber
114. Pumping mechanism 116 for supplying the medication from medication
chamber 114 to a patient includes pump 118, control circuitry and battery (not
shown), and catheter 120.</p><p num="0028">Reservoir 122 is defined within housing 112 and is separated from
medication chamber 114 by flexible corrugated structure 124. Structure 124 is
preferably formed from a corrugated metal, for example titanium. The material
used to form structure 124 is preferably substantially impermeable to the gas
mixture, the selected medication, and any gases dissolved in the medication.
The selected gas or gas mixture is supplied to reservoir 122 by conventional
means known to those skilled in the art.</p><p num="0029">While particular preferred embodiments of the present invention have
been described above, it will be understood by those of skill in the art that 
many modifications and variations of the teachings may be made.</p><p num="0030">In a preferred embodiment preferably a medication infusion pump
comprises:
<sl><li>a) a housing,</li><li>b) a medication chamber defined within the housing,</li><li>c) means for supplying the medication from the medication
chamber to a patient,</li><li>d) a reservoir defined within the housing and adapted to apply a
predetermined negative pressure to the medication chamber,
and</li><li>e) a gas within the reservoir, the gas having a vapor pressure less
than ambient atmospheric pressure at normal human
physiological temperature.</li></sl></p><p num="0031">Preferably, the medication infusion pump is adapted to be passively
refilled with a medication, the medication infusion pump comprising a
reservoir that contains a gas having a vapor pressure less than ambient
atmospheric pressure at normal human physiological temperature.</p><p num="0032">Preferably, the gas comprises a non-ozone depleting gas.</p><p num="0033">Preferably, the gas comprises a non-toxic gas.</p><p num="0034">Preferably, the gas has a vapor pressure less than 14.7 psia at 37°C.</p><p num="0035">Preferably, the gas has a vapor pressure less than 10.7 psia at 37°C.</p><p num="0036">Preferably, the gas is selected from the group consisting of
cyclopentane, 2,2-dimethylbutane, 1 ,3-pentadiene and 2-methyl-2-butene. </p><p num="0037">Preferably, the gas is selected from the group consisting of
cyclopentane and dimethylbutane.</p><p num="0038">Preferably, the medication infusion pump comprises a plurality of gases
within the reservoir, wherein the plurality of gases has a combined vapor
pressure less than 14.7 psia at 37°C.</p><p num="0039">Preferably, the medication chamber and the reservoir are separated by
a barrier which is resistant to the gas.</p><p num="0040">In a preferred embodiment, a method of supplying a medication to a
patient from a medication infusion pump, the infusion pump including a
housing, a medication chamber defined within the housing, a pumping
mechanism for supplying the medication from the medication chamber to the
patient, and a reservoir defined within the housing and adapted to apply a
predetermined negative pressure to a medication within the medication
chamber, comprises the steps of
<sl><li>(i) filling the reservoir with a gas having a vapor pressure less than
ambient atmospheric pressure at normal human physiological temperature,</li><li>(ii) drawing the medication into the medication chamber by exertion of
the predetermined negative pressure on the medication, and</li><li>(iii) dispensing the medication from the medication chamber via the
pumping mechanism.</li></sl></p><p num="0041">Preferably, the gas comprises a non-ozone depleting gas.</p><p num="0042">Preferably, the gas comprises a non-toxic gas. In a preferred
embodiment, there is included a non-toxic and non-ozone depleting gas.</p><p num="0043">Preferably, the gas has a vapor pressure less than 14.7 psia at 37°C. </p><p num="0044">Preferably, the gas has a vapor pressure less than 10.7 psia at 37°C.</p><p num="0045">Preferably, the gas is selected from the group consisting of
cyclopentane, 2,2-dimethylbutane, I ,3-pentadiene and 2-methyl-2-butene.</p><p num="0046">Preferably, the gas is selected from the group consisting of
cyclopentane and 2,2-dimethylbutane.</p><p num="0047">Preferably, the medication pump is implanted within the body of the
patient.</p><p num="0048">Preferably, there is provided a medication infusion pump adapted to be
passively refilled with a medication wherein the medication infusion pump
includes a reservoir that contains a gas having a vapor pressure less than
ambient atmospheric pressure at normal human physiological temperature.</p></description><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A medication infusion pump (10; 110) comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a housing (12;112),</claim-text><claim-text>b) a medication chamber (14;114) defined within the housing
(12;112),</claim-text><claim-text>c) means for supplying (16;116) the medication from the
medication chamber (14;114) to a patient,</claim-text><claim-text>d) a reservoir (28;122) defined within the housing (12;112) and
adapted to apply a predetermined pressure less than ambient
atmospheric pressure to the medication chamber (14;114), and</claim-text><claim-text>e) a gas within the reservoir (28;122), the gas having a vapor
pressure less than ambient atmospheric pressure at normal human
physiological temperature, characterised in that the gas is selected
from the group consisting of cyclopentane, 2,2-dimethylbutane, 1,3-pentadiene,
and 2-methyl-2-butene and does not have an adverse
effect on ozone.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The medication infusion pump of claim 1, wherein the medication
infusion pump is adapted to be passively refilled with a medication.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The medication infusion pump of claim 1 wherein the gas comprises a
non-toxic gas.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The medication infusion pump of claim 1 wherein the gas has a vapor
pressure less than 14.7 psia (101 kPa) at 37°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The medication infusion pump of claim 4 wherein the gas has a vapor
pressure less than 10.7 psia (74 kPa) at 37°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The medication infusion pump of claim 1 wherein the gas is selected
from the group consisting of cyclopentane and dimethylbutane.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The medication infusion pump of claim 1 comprising a plurality of gases
within the reservoir (28;122), wherein the plurality of gases has a
combined vapor pressure less than 14.7 psia (101 kPa) at 37°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The medication infusion pump of claim 1 wherein the medication
chamber (14;114) and the reservoir (28;122) are separated by a barrier
(124) which is resistant to gas.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A medication infusion pump for use in a method of supplying a
medication to a patient from a medication infusion pump, the infusion
pump including a housing (12;112), a medication chamber (14;114)
defined within the housing (12;112), a pumping mechanism (16;116)
for supplying the medication from the medication chamber (14;114) to
the patient, and a reservoir (28;122) defined within the housing
(12;112) and adapted to apply a predetermined pressure less than
ambient atmospheric pressure to the medication chamber (14;114), the
method comprising the steps of
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) filling the reservoir with a gas having a vapor pressure less than
ambient atmospheric pressure at normal human physiological
temperature, the gas being selected from the group consisting of
cyclopentane, 2,2-dimethylbutane, 1,3-pentadiene, and 2-methyl-2-butene,
and wherein the gas does not have an adverse effect on
ozone,</claim-text><claim-text>ii) drawing the medication into the medication chamber by exertion
of the predetermined negative pressure on the medication, and</claim-text><claim-text>iii) dispensing the medication from the medication chamber via the
pumping mechanism.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20051123"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20051102"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050901</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIN1" date="20050406"><legal-event-body><event-title>INVENTOR (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DY, NORMAN V.</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>VAN ANTWERP, WILLIAM P.</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AC" date="20050302"><legal-event-body><event-title>DIVISIONAL APPLICATION (ART. 76) OF:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>1152785</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050302"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>