<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1126543-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1126543" kind="B1" date="20060823"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23217849" ucid="EP-1126543-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1126543</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20060823</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01101659-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01101659</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010129</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-505575" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>505575</doc-number><date>20000216</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-50557500-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>50557500</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000216</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20060228</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q   1/27        20060101CFI20010522BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q   1/28        20060101AFI20010522BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q   3/26        20060101ALI20010522BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q   3/26        20060101CLI20010522BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q  21/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q  21/28        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q  21/30        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q  21/30        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q  25/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01Q  25/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04B   7/185       20060101ALI20010522BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04B   7/185       20060101CLI20010522BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04B   7/204       20060101ALI20010522BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04B   7/204       20060101CLI20010522BHEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01Q1/28F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01Q3/26</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04B7/204B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">System und Verfahren zur Erzeugung von zwei aneinandergrenzenden Antennenstrahlungskeulenmustern mit Überlappung</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">System and method for producing overlapping two contiguous spot beam patterns</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Système et procédé pour la formation de deux diagrammes de faisceaux contigus se chevauchant</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>BOEING CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>THE BOEING COMPANY</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>PIETRUSIAK STEPHAN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>PIETRUSIAK, STEPHAN</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>PIETRUSIAK, STEPHAN</last-name><address><street>530 Showers Drive 7, #255</street><city>Mountain View, California 94040</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>THE BOEING COMPANY</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 3707, M.S. 13-08</street><city>Seattle, Washington 98124-2207</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Steil, Christian, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Witte, Weller &amp; Partner, Postfach 10 54 62</street><city>70047 Stuttgart</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>A method and apparatus for producing contiguous spot beam communications coverage on the Earth's surface (100) are disclosed. The apparatus comprises two contiguous beam patterns (200A, 200B; 316, 318). The first contiguous beam pattern (200A; 316) comprises a first set of cells (202A; 320-332) and has a first set of frequencies (F1; F1A-F7A). The second contiguous beam pattern (200B; 318) comprises a second set of cells (202B; 334-346) and has a second set of frequencies (F2; F1B-F7B). The second contiguous beam pattern (200B; 318) is spatially offset from the first contiguous beam pattern (200A; 316) such that an edge (214) of the first set of cells (202A; 320-332) is offset from an edge (212) of the second set of cells (202B; 334-346). Multiple two grid systems can maintain isolation performance of single grid system (Fig. 2C). &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">A method and apparatus for producing contiguous spot beam
communications coverage on the Earth's surface (100) are disclosed.
The apparatus comprises two contiguous beam patterns
(200A, 200B; 316, 318). The first contiguous beam pattern
(200A; 316) comprises a first set of cells (202A; 320-332) and
has a first set of frequencies (F1; F1A-F7A). The second contiguous
beam pattern (200B; 318) comprises a second set of
cells (202B; 334-346) and has a second set of frequencies (F2;
F1B-F7B). The second contiguous beam pattern (200B; 318) is
spatially offset from the first contiguous beam pattern (200A;
316) such that an edge (214) of the first set of cells (202A;
320-332) is offset from an edge (212) of the second set of
cells (202B; 334-346). Multiple two grid systems can maintain
isolation performance of single grid system (Fig. 2C).
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1126671-A1-00000001" he="104" wi="127" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="p0001">The present invention relates to a system for delivering contiguous spot coverage from a satellite, comprising: a first contiguous beam pattern comprising a first set of cells and having a first set of frequencies; and a second contiguous beam pattern comprising a second set of cells and having a second set of frequencies, the second contiguous beam pattern being spatially offset from the first contiguous beam pattern.</p><p num="p0002">The present invention further relates to a method for producing at least two contiguous spot beam patterns for communication from a satellite to the Earth's surface, comprising the steps of: producing a first contiguous spot beam pattern on the Earth's surface, the first contiguous spot beam pattern comprising a first set of cells and having a first set of frequencies; and producing a second contiguous spot beam pattern on the Earth's surface, the second contiguous spot beam pattern comprising a second set of cells and having a second set of frequencies.</p><p num="p0003">Such systems and methods are generally known. <ref type="patent">US 5,625,868</ref> discloses such a system.</p><p num="p0004"><ref type="patent">US 5,736,959</ref> discloses an Earth-fixed cell beam management method which may be employed to allocate beams generated by a constellation of low Earth orbit satellites flying in orbits below geo-synchronous altitudes. These beams are electronically steered so that they illuminate &quot;Earth-fixed cells&quot; as opposed to &quot;satellite-fixed cells&quot;. Beam steering apparatus using a spherical dielectric lens is disclosed. In a system that employs satellite-fixed cells, the &quot;footprint&quot; of the beams propagated by a spacecraft defines the zone on the ground called a &quot;cell&quot; which is illuminated by the spacecraft. This satellite-fixed cell moves constantly as the spacecraft moves around the globe. In sharp contrast, an &quot;Earth-fixed cell&quot; is a stationary region mapped onto the surface of the Earth that has permanent fixed boundaries, just like a city or a state. Although the rapidly moving satellites still shine their beams over the ground in rapidly moving footprints, the locations of the footprints at any given time do not determine the location of the unchanging Earth-fixed cells. The great advantage provided by using cells having boundaries that are fixed to an Earth-fixed grid is realized when a subscriber being served by one satellite must switch to another beam in the same satellite or to a second satellite because the first is moving out of range below the local horizon. With satellite-fixed cells, this &quot;hand-off&quot; involves the assignment to the terminal of a new communication channel within the new beam or new satellite. This assignment process takes time and consumes processing capacity at both the terminal and the satellite. It is also subject to blocking, call interruption, and call dropping if there is not an idle communication channel in the next serving beam or satellite. The Earth-fixed cell method avoids these problems by allocating communication channels (frequency, code, and/or time slot) on an Earth-fixed cell basis rather than on a satellite-fixed cell basis. Regardless of which satellite/beam is currently serving a particular cell, the terminal maintains the same channel assignment, thus ameliorating the &quot;hand-off&quot; problem.</p><p num="p0005"><ref type="patent">WO 99/35766</ref> discloses a method for beam management in a satellite communication system which simplifies cell-to-cell hand-off within a footprint of the satellite and between two or more satellites. The method includes the steps of providing multiple beam stripes extending across the footprint in a direction corresponding to the direction of flight of the satellite, grouping the beam stripes into one or more beam groups, and selectively associating hardware groups comprised of hardware resources to support beam groups.</p><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><heading>1. Field of the Invention.</heading><p num="p0006">This invention relates in general to antenna systems, and in particular to a dual coverage grid method for increased signal coverage.</p><heading>2. Description of Related Art.</heading><p num="p0007">Communications satellites have become commonplace for use in many types of communications services, e.g., data transfer, voice communications, television spot beam coverage, and other data transfer applications. As such, satellites must provide signals to various geographic locations on the Earth's surface. As such, typical satellites use customized antenna designs to provide signal coverage for a particular country or geographic area.</p><p num="p0008">In order to provide signal coverage over a large area, several approaches are used. A single beam with a wide beamwidth is sometimes used, but is limited in terms of power delivery over such a large geographic area. Typically, to cover a large geographic area, contiguous spot beams are used.</p><p num="p0009">Contiguous spot beams are generated by multiple antennas to cover a large geographic area with a small variation in measured signal strength at the ground. The contiguous beams typically generate a grid that provides a certain Effective Incident Radiated Power (EIRP) throughout the coverage area for the spacecraft. However the EIRP that can be delivered by a given spacecraft and/or antenna system is limited by amplifier power, bandwidth, and antenna size.</p><p num="p0010">Other advances for satellite communications have come in the personal communications system (PCS) system, or world-wide cellular telephony. Typical cellular telephony uses cell division to increase signal throughput in certain high-traffic areas. These smaller additional cells are created by installing additional antenna sites at each cell. Similarly, satellites can create smaller grid cells by using additional beams, transmitters, and antennas.</p><p num="p0011">However, since each satellite is limited in the number of antennas, transmitters, and beams that it can support, adding more hardware to the system is typically cost prohibitive.</p><p num="p0012">It can be seen, then, that there is a need in the art for antenna systems that can deliver contiguous spot beams over large geographic areas that can carry additional signals. It can also be seen that there is a need in the art for antenna systems that can deliver signals for mobile applications without signal interruption. It can also be seen that there is a need in the art for antenna systems that provide ease of mechanical design and construction to reduce spacecraft costs.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="p0013">To overcome the limitations in the prior art described above, and to overcome other limitations that will become apparent upon reading and understanding the present specification, the present invention discloses a method and apparatus for producing contiguous spot beam communications coverage on the Earth's surface.
The above-mentioned object is achieved by a system as mentioned at the outset, wherein the offset if such that each edge of the first set of cells is offset from a corresponding edge of the second set of cells.

The object is further achieved by a method as mentioned at the outset, further comprising the steps of spatially offsetting the first contiguous spot beam pattern from the second contiguous spot beam pattern such that each edge of the first set of cells is offset from a corresponding edge of the second set of cells.</p><p num="p0014">The first contiguous beam pattern comprises a first set of cells and has a first set of frequencies. The second contiguous beam pattern comprises a second set of cells and has a second set of frequencies. The second contiguous beam pattern is spatially offset from the first contiguous beam pattern such that an edge of the first set of cells is offset from an edge of the second set of cells.</p><p num="p0015">The method comprises the steps of producing a first contiguous spot beam pattern on the Earth's surface, producing a second contiguous spot beam pattern on the Earth's surface, and overlapping the first contiguous spot beam pattern and the second contiguous spot beam pattern such that an edge of the first contiguous spot beam pattern is offset from an edge of the second contiguous spot beam pattern.</p><p num="p0016">The present invention provides antenna systems that can deliver contiguous spot beams over large geographic areas that can carry additional signals. The present invention also provides antenna systems that can deliver signals for mobile applications without signal interruption. The present invention also provides antenna systems that provide ease of mechanical design and construction to reduce spacecraft costs.</p><heading><u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u></heading><p num="p0017">Referring now to the drawings in which like reference numbers represent corresponding parts throughout:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>FIG. 1 illustrates a typical satellite perspective of the Earth with multiple desired beam patterns;</li><li>FIGS. 2A-2D illustrate the grid overlay of the present invention;</li><li>FIGS. 3A-3B illustrate a typical reuse configuration employing the present invention; and</li><li>FIG. 4 is a flow chart illustrating the steps used to practice the present invention.</li></ul></p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</u></heading><p num="p0018">In the following description of the preferred embodiment, reference is made to the accompanying drawings which form a part hereof, and in which is shown by way of illustration a specific embodiment in which the invention may be practiced. It is to be understood that other embodiments may be utilized and structural changes may be made without departing from the scope of the present invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Overview Of Related Art</u></heading><p num="p0019">Contiguous spot beam coverage is commonly used in many satellite antenna designs, especially in applications that require higher antenna gains to compensate for severe propagation effects.</p><p num="p0020">FIG. 1 illustrates a typical satellite perspective of the Earth with multiple desired beam patterns. Earth 100 is shown from the perspective of a satellite, typically a satellite in geosynchronous orbit.</p><p num="p0021">The satellite provides communications signals, called beams, that provide the proper signal strength to communicate with antennas on the Earth's 100 surface. However, because of power limitations, desired coverage areas, etc., a single antenna cannot provide coverage for the entire visible portion of the Earth's 100 surface. Specific geographic areas are selected by the satellite designer for communications coverage. The satellite typically provides communications services in one or more selected geographic areas by using multiple antenna beams. Each beam has a signal strength that is typically higher in the center of the beam than at the edge of the beam.</p><p num="p0022">As shown in FIG. 1, a spacecraft typically must deliver a communications signal to desired locations on the surface of the Earth 100. As communications services demand increases, the size of the geographic locations increases as well.</p><p num="p0023">Location 102, shown in the Northern Hemisphere, is typically covered using spot beams 104, whereas location 106, shown in the Southern Hemisphere, is typically covered using spot beams 108. Each spot beam 104 and 108 delivers a peak signal strength at the center of the beam, and the signal strength tapers off towards the edge of each beam 104 and 108.</p><heading><u style="single">Overview Of The Invention</u></heading><p num="p0024">The current invention discloses a technique for using a dual antenna coverage grid offset by half a cell to enable the use of higher antenna directivities by selecting the beam from grid 1 or grid 2 with the highest directivity. This is achieved by having the same high-frequency re-use as a 1-grid system. Furthermore, by using half a cell offset from the first grid, the same control beams from the first grid can be used to control the second grid beams if GPS positioning is not used.</p><p num="p0025">This approach can be extended to three, four, or more grids to further optimize performance if desired. The extension to additional grids may require additional subbands for the system. For example, the triple point (intersection) beam placement in a three grid system yields higher average and lower directivity than a two grid system For a two grid system, a triple point system can only cover approximately half of the triple points in a hexagonal cell structure and the same minimum directivity points are still present approximately half of the time compared to the single grid system.</p><p num="p0026">Further, the present invention can be applied selectively throughout a grid system. For example, if there are only certain areas within the grid that require additional signal handling capability, the second grid can be overlayed only for those areas. Further, the second grid can be offset different amounts at the selective areas to maximize signal throughput.</p><heading><u style="single">Grid Overlay</u></heading><p num="p0027">FIGS. 2A-2D illustrate the grid overlay of the present invention. FIG. 2A illustrates a typical hexagonal grid pattern 200A generated by antennas on a satellite. This pattern can be generated by a phased array antenna, or by multiple antennas. Typical cell 202A covers a specific geographic area. Cell 204 is indicated as using frequency F1 throughout the cell. Frequency F1 is shown as being in a &quot;seven-cell reuse&quot; pattern, meaning that cells 204 that use frequency F1 are surrounded by six cells 202 not using frequency F1. Other frequency reuse patterns can also be used without deleterious effect on the present invention. Once frequency F1 is used in the seven cell reuse pattern across the entire pattern 200A, frequency F1 is no longer available for use within pattern 200A.</p><p num="p0028">FIG. 2B illustrates a typical hexagonal grid pattern 200B with typical cells 202B and cells 206 indicated as using frequency F2 throughout cells 206 in a seven cell reuse pattern. Once frequency F2 is used in the seven cell reuse pattern across the entire pattern 200B, frequency F2 is no longer available for use within pattern 200B.</p><p num="p0029">FIG. 2C illustrates the overlay of patterns 200A and 200B into pattern 208. Pattern 200A is shown as being offset from pattern 200B one half cell &quot;down&quot; from pattern 200B. The overlay pattern 208 effectively has cells 210 that are now one-half of the area of cells 202A, 202B, 204, and 206. This allows for greater signal throughput of the system.</p><p num="p0030">FIG. 2D is a magnified portion of FIG. 2C. Cell 210 is defined as the intersection of cell 202A from pattern 200A and cell 200B from pattern 200B. As a user travels through cell 202B and reaches edge 212, the signal strength of cell 202B is reaching the point where communication with the user may no longer be possible without a handoff to an adjacent cell 202B if only pattern 200B is being used. If the adjacent cell 202B is already at capacity, the user will not be able to continue communication. However, edge 212 is in the middle of cell 202A, which has sufficient signal strength to sustain communication paths, and a handoff is possible to the second pattern 200A without affecting the users in cells 202B. Similarly, when a user is travelling through cell 202A and reaches edge 214, the signal strength of cell 202A is reaching the point where communication with the user may no longer be possible without a handoff to an adjacent cell 202A. By using pattern 208, additional signal capacity is available for mobile users that approach edges 212 and 214 of cells 202A and 202B.</p><p num="p0031">Triple point 216 also falls within the boundaries of a cell 202B and as such allows for additional capacity for users at those geographic locations without excessive handoffs within pattern 200. Intersection point 218 can be handled within a single pattern 200A or 200B or can be switched between patterns 200A and 200B as desired.</p><p num="p0032">Although shown with an exact one-half cell offset between patterns 200A and 200B, other offsets can be performed. Further, the offset of pattern 200A with respect to pattern 200B can up and down, side to side, or any combination of up and down and side to side.</p><p num="p0033">The beam patterns 200A and 200B are typically created using a phased array antenna with beamweights for each antenna element to generate a desired pattern 200A or 200B. Minimum beam sizes are used to generate the smallest cell 202A size within pattern 200A. To further reduce the beam size, additional elements are required within the antenna system, which would then require additional hardware for support and result in additional weight on the spacecraft. By assigning proper beamweights to the beams, and using additional pattern 200B to generate pattern 208, the beam sizes are effectively reduced to one half of the beam size segmented into rectangular zones without adding any additional hardware or increasing the weight of the spacecraft.</p><p num="p0034">The improvement in directivity provided by pattern 208 depends on the difference between the peak signal strength at the center of the beam to the signal strength at the edge of the beam. The greater the difference, the greater the improvement using additional grids to cover the geographic area. For example, with a peak-to-edge signal strength (directivity) difference of 3 dB, the average directivity is improved by approximately 0.5 dB and the minimum required signal strength is improved by 0.84 dB. This allows for lower power mobile communications devices, lower power satellites, or any combination of the two ends of the communications link having a lower power of up to 0.84 dB in the exemplary system to continue communications. Such a reduction increases battery life in mobile communications devices, or could reduce launch weight of the satellite which reduces satellite costs.</p><p num="p0035">To determine which pattern, e.g., 200A or 200B, that a particular user will be assigned to, power measurements can be made on the signal strength either at the user end or at the satellite end, Global Positioning System (GPS) data can be used to determine the user location to switch between patterns 200A and 200B, or other heuristic methods can be used to determine when to place user in pattern 200A or 200B, or to switch user between pattern 200A and 200B.</p><heading><u style="single">Frequency Reuse Configuration</u></heading><p num="p0036">FIGS. 3A-3B illustrate a typical reuse configuration employing the present invention. Pattern 300 illustrates a typical seven cell reuse pattern, where cells 302 use frequency range F1, cells 304 use frequency range F2, cells 306 use frequency range F3, cells 308 use frequency range F4, cells 310 use frequency range F5, cells 312 use frequency range F6, and cells 314 use frequency range F7.</p><p num="p0037">To offset pattern 300 into a two pattern system, each frequency range F1-F7 is separated. For example, frequency range F1 is separated into frequency range F1A and frequency range F1B, where frequency range F1A uses a certain number of subbands within frequency range F1 and frequency range F1B uses other subbands within frequency range F1. Patterns 316 and 318 are shown, with pattern 316 having cells 320 using frequency range F1A, cells 322 use frequency range F2A, cells 324 use frequency range F3A, cells 326 use frequency range F4A, cells 328 use frequency range F5A, cells 330 use frequency range F6A, and cells 332 use frequency range F7A.</p><p num="p0038">Similarly, pattern 318 has cells 334 using frequency range F1B, cells 336 use frequency range F2B, cells 338 use frequency range F3B, cells 340 use frequency range F4B, cells 342 use frequency range F5B, cells 344 use frequency range F6B, and cells 346 use frequency range F7B.</p><p num="p0039">Patterns 316 and 318 are combined to form pattern 348. Pattern 348 now uses the same seven frequency ranges F1-F7, but divides the cells such that no subband is repeated within the seven-cell reuse pattern.</p><p num="p0040">FIG. 3B illustrates that the separation between cells is maintained after the separation of the subbands described in FIG. 3A. Pattern 300 has a distance 350 between the frequencies F1, where the distance 350 defines the cell distance in the reuse pattern. After separation, distance 350 is replaced by offset distance 352 between frequencies F1A in cells 320, and offset distance 354 between frequencies F1B in cells 334. As such, the separation between cells is maintained.</p><heading><u style="single">Process Chart</u></heading><p num="p0041">FIG. 4 is a flow chart illustrating the steps used to practice the present invention.</p><p num="p0042">Block 400 illustrates performing the step of producing a first contiguous spot beam pattern on the Earth's surface.</p><p num="p0043">Block 402 illustrates performing the step of producing a second contiguous spot beam pattern on the Earth's surface.</p><p num="p0044">Block 404 illustrates performing the step of overlapping the first contiguous spot beam pattern and the second contiguous spot beam pattern such that an edge of the first contiguous spot beam pattern is offset from an edge of the second contiguous spot beam pattern.</p><heading><u style="single">Conclusion</u></heading><p num="p0045">This concludes the description of the preferred embodiment of the invention. The following paragraphs describe some alternative methods of accomplishing the same objects. The present invention, although described with respect to RF systems, can also be used with optical systems to accomplish the same goals.</p><p num="p0046">In summary, the present invention discloses a method and apparatus for producing contiguous spot beam communications coverage on the Earth's surface are disclosed. The apparatus comprises two contiguous beam patterns. The first contiguous beam pattern comprises a first set of cells and has a first set of frequencies. The second contiguous beam pattern comprises a second set of cells and has a second set of frequencies. The second contiguous beam pattern is spatially offset from the first contiguous beam pattern such that an edge of the first set of cells is offset from an edge of the second set of cells.</p><p num="p0047">The method comprises the steps of producing a first contiguous spot beam pattern on the Earth's surface, producing a second contiguous spot beam pattern on the Earth's surface, and overlapping the first contiguous spot beam pattern and the second contiguous spot beam pattern such that an edge of the first contiguous spot beam pattern is offset from an edge of the second contiguous spot beam pattern.</p><p num="p0048">The foregoing description of the preferred embodiment of the invention has been presented for the purposes of illustration and description. It is not intended to be exhaustive or to limit the invention to the precise form disclosed. Many modifications and variations are possible in light of the above teaching. It is intended that the scope of the invention be limited not by this detailed description, but rather by the claims appended hereto.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim id="c-de-01-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>System zum Liefern einer aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelabdeckung von einem Satelliten, mit:
<claim-text>einem ersten aneinandergrenzenden Bündelmuster (200A; 316) mit einem ersten Satz von Zellen (202A; 320-332) und mit einem ersten Satz von Frequenzen (F1; F1A-F7A); und</claim-text><claim-text>einem zweiten aneinandergrenzenden Bündelmuster (200B; 318) mit einem zweiten Satz von Zellen (202B; 334-346) und mit einem zweiten Satz von Frequenzen (F2; F1B-F7B) wobei das zweite aneinandergrenzende Bündelmuster (200B; 318) gegenüber dem ersten aneinandergrenzenden Bündelmuster (200A; 316) räumlich versetzt ist und damit überlappt,</claim-text><claim-text><b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b></claim-text><claim-text>der Versatz derart ist, dass jeder Rand (214) des ersten Satzes von Zellen (202A; 316) gegenüber einem entsprechenden Rand (212) des zweiten Satzes von Zellen (202B; 318) versetzt ist.</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 1, <b>gekennzeichnet durch</b> ein drittes aneinandergrenzendes Bündelmuster, welches einen dritten Satz von Zellen aufweist und einen dritten Satz von Frequenzen aufweist, wobei das dritte aneinandergrenzende Bündelmuster räumlich gegenüber dem ersten aneinandergrenzenden Bündelmuster (200A) und gegenüber dem zweiten aneinandergrenzenden Bündelmuster (200B) derart versetzt ist, dass ein Rand des dritten Satzes von Zellen gegenüber dem Rand (214) des ersten Satzes von Zellen (202A) versetzt ist und gegenüber dem Rand (212) des zweiten Satzes von Zellen (202B) versetzt ist.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 1, <b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b> der Versatz ungefähr eine halbe Zellenbreite beträgt.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>System nach einem der Ansprüche 1 bis 3, <b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b> das erste aneinandergrenzende Bündelmuster (200A; 316) und das zweite aneinandergrenzende Bündelmuster (200B; 318) durch die gleiche Antenne erzeugt werden.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0005" num="0005"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 4, <b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b> die Antenne eine phasengesteuerte Gruppenantenne ist.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0006" num="0006"><claim-text>System nach einem der Ansprüche 1 bis 5, <b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b> der erste Satz von Frequenzen (F1A-F7A) und der zweite Satz von Frequenzen (F1B-F7B) Teilmengen eines ersten Frequenzbereichs (F1-F7) sind.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0007" num="0007"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Erzeugen von zumindest zwei aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelmustern für eine Kommunikation von einem Satelliten zur Erdoberfläche (100), das die folgenden Schritte aufweist:
<claim-text>Erzeugen eines ersten aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelmusters (200A; 316) auf der Erdoberfläche (100), wobei das erste aneinandergrenzende Punktbündelmuster einen ersten Satz von Zellen aufweist und einen ersten Satz von Frequenzen aufweist;</claim-text><claim-text>Erzeugen eines zweiten aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelmusters (200B; 318) auf der Erdoberfläche (100), wobei das zweite aneinandergrenzende Punktbündelmuster einen zweiten Satz von Zellen und einen zweiten Satz von Frequenzen aufweist und das erste aneinandergrenzende Bündelmuster (200A, 316) überlappt; und</claim-text><claim-text><b>gekennzeichnet durch</b></claim-text><claim-text>räumliches Versetzen des ersten aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelmusters (200A; 316) gegenüber dem zweiten aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelmuster (200B; 318) derart, dass jeder Rand (214) des ersten Satzes von Zellen gegenüber einem entsprechenden Rand (212) des zweiten Satzes von Zellen versetzt ist.</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0008" num="0008"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 7, <b>gekennzeichnet durch</b> die Schritte:
<claim-text>Erzeugen eines dritten aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelmusters auf der Erdoberfläche, wobei das dritte aneinandergrenzende Punktbündelmuster einen dritten Satz von Zellen aufweist und einen dritten Satz von Frequenzen aufweist; und</claim-text><claim-text>Überlappen des dritten aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelmusters mit dem ersten aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelmuster (200A; 316) und dem zweiten aneinandergrenzenden Punktbündelmuster (200B; 318) derart, dass ein Rand des dritten Satzes von Zellen gegenüber dem Rand (214) des ersten Satzes von Zellen (200A; 316) versetzt ist und gegenüber dem Rand (212) des zweiten Satzes von Zellen (200B; 318) versetzt ist.</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0009" num="0009"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 7 oder 8, <b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b> der Versatz ungefähr eine halbe Punktbündelbreite beträgt.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim id="c-en-01-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>A system for delivering contiguous spot coverage from a satellite, comprising:
<claim-text>a first contiguous beam pattern (200A; 316) comprising a first set of cells (202A; 320-332) and having a first set of frequencies (F1; F1A-F7A); and</claim-text><claim-text>a second contiguous beam pattern (200B; 318) comprising a second set of cells (202B; 334-346) and having a second set of frequencies (F2; F1B-F7B), the second contiguous beam pattern (200B; 318) being spatially offset from and substantially overlapping the first contiguous beam pattern (200A; 316)</claim-text><claim-text><b>characterized in that</b></claim-text><claim-text>the offset is such that each edge (214) of the first set of cells (202A; 316) is offset from a corresponding edge (212) of the second set of cells (202B; 318).</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>The system of Claim 1, <b>characterized by</b> a third contiguous beam pattern, comprising a third set of cells and having a third set of frequencies, the third contiguous beam pattern being spatially offset from the first contiguous beam pattern (200A) and the second contiguous beam pattern (200B) such that an edge of the third set of cells is offset from the edge (214) of the first set of cells (202A) and offset from the edge (212) of the second set of cells (202B).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>The system of Claim 1, <b>characterized in that</b> the offset is approximately one-half cell width.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>The system of any of Claims 1-3, <b>characterized in that</b> the first contiguous beam pattern (200A; 316) and the second contiguous beam pattern (200B; 318) are generated by the same antenna.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0005" num="0005"><claim-text>The system of Claim 4, <b>characterized in that</b> the antenna is a phased array antenna.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0006" num="0006"><claim-text>The system of any of Claims 1-5, <b>characterized in that</b> the first set of frequencies (F1A-F7A) and the second set of frequencies (F1B-F7B) are subsets of a first frequency range (F1-F7).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0007" num="0007"><claim-text>A method for producing at least two contiguous spot beam patterns (200A, 200B; 316, 318) for communications from a satellite to the Earth's surface (100), comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>producing a first contiguous spot beam pattern (200A; 316) on the Earth's surface (100), the first contiguous spot beam pattern comprising a first set of cells and having a first set of frequencies;</claim-text><claim-text>producing a second contiguous spot beam pattern (200B; 318) on the Earth's surface (100), the second contiguous spot beam pattern comprising a second set of cells and having a second set of frequencies and substantially overlapping the first contiguous beam pattern (200A,316); and</claim-text><b>characterized by</b>

spatially offsetting the first contiguous spot beam pattern (200A; 316) from the second contiguous spot beam pattern (200B; 318) such that each edge (214) of the first set of cells is offset from a corresponding edge (212) of the second set of cells.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0008" num="0008"><claim-text>The method of Claim 7, <b>characterized by</b> the steps of:
<claim-text>producing a third contiguous spot beam pattern on the Earth's surface, the third contiguous spot beam pattern comprising a third set of cells and having a third set of frequencies; and</claim-text><claim-text>overlapping the third contiguous spot beam pattern beam with the first contiguous spot beam pattern (200A; 316) and the second contiguous spot beam pattern (200B; 318) such that an edge of the third set of cells is offset from the edge (214) of the first set of cells (200A; 316) and offset from the edge (212) of the second set of cells (200B; 318).</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0009" num="0009"><claim-text>The method of Claim 7 or 8, <b>characterized in that</b> the offset is approximately one-half of a spot beam width.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim id="c-fr-01-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>Système permettant de délivrer une couverture de faisceau étroit contigu depuis un satellite, comprenant :
<claim-text>un premier diagramme de faisceau contigu (200A ; 316) comprenant un premier ensemble de cellules (202A ; 320-332) et possédant un premier ensemble de fréquences (F1 ; F1A-F7A); et</claim-text><claim-text>un second diagramme de faisceau contigu (200B; 318) comprenant un second ensemble de cellules (202B; 334-346) et possédant un second ensemble de fréquences (F2 ; F1B-F7B), le second diagramme de faisceau contigu (200B; 318) étant spatialement décalé de et chevauchant le premier diagramme de faisceau contigu (200A ; 316),</claim-text><claim-text><b>caractérisé en ce que</b></claim-text><claim-text>le décalage est tel que chaque bord (214) du premier ensemble de cellules (202A ; 316) est décalé d'un bord correspondant (212) du second ensemble de cellules (202B ; 318).</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>Système selon la revendication 1, <b>caractérisé par</b> un troisième diagramme de faisceau contigu, comprenant un troisième ensemble de cellules et possédant un troisième ensemble de fréquences, le troisième diagramme de faisceau contigu étant spatialement décalé du premier diagramme de faisceau contigu (200A) et du second diagramme de faisceau contigu (200B) de telle sorte qu'un bord du troisième ensemble de cellules soit décalé du bord (214) du premier ensemble de cellules (202A) et décalé du bord (212) du second ensemble de cellules (202B).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>Système selon la revendication 1, <b>caractérisé en ce que</b> le décalage est d'environ une moitié de largeur de cellule.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>Système selon l'une quelconque des revendications 1 à 3, <b>caractérisé en ce que</b> le premier diagramme de faisceau contigu (200A ; 316) et le second diagramme de faisceau contigu (200B; 318) sont générés par la même antenne.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0005" num="0005"><claim-text>Système selon la revendication 4, <b>caractérisé en ce que</b> l'antenne est une antenne à commande de phase.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0006" num="0006"><claim-text>Système selon l'une quelconque des revendications 1 à 5, <b>caractérisé en ce que</b> le premier ensemble de fréquences (F1A-F7A) et le second ensemble de fréquences (F1 B-F7B) sont des sous-ensembles d'une première gamme de fréquences (F1-F7).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0007" num="0007"><claim-text>Procédé de production d'au moins deux diagrammes de faisceaux étroits contigus (200A, 200B; 316, 318) en vue de communications entre un satellite et la surface de la terre (100), comprenant les étapes consistant à :
<claim-text>produire un premier diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu (200A ; 316) sur la surface de la terre (100), le premier diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu comprenant un premier ensemble de cellules et possédant un premier ensemble de fréquences ;</claim-text><claim-text>produire un second diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu (200B ; 318) sur la surface de la terre (100), le second diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu comprenant un second ensemble de cellules et possédant un second ensemble de fréquences chevauchant le premier diagramme de faisceau contigu (200A ; 316) ; et</claim-text><claim-text><b>caractérisé par</b></claim-text><claim-text>le décalage spatial du premier diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu (200A ; 316) par rapport au second diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu (200B; 318) de telle sorte que chaque bord (214) du premier ensemble de cellules soit décalé d'un bord correspondant (212) du second ensemble de cellules.</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0008" num="0008"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 7, <b>caractérisé par</b> les étapes consistant à :
<claim-text>produire un troisième diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu sur la surface de la terre, le troisième diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu comprenant un troisième ensemble de cellules et possédant un troisième ensemble de fréquences ; et</claim-text><claim-text>faire chevaucher le troisième diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu avec le premier diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu (200A ; 316) et le second diagramme de faisceau étroit contigu (200B ; 318) de telle sorte qu'un bord du troisième ensemble de cellules soit décalé du bord (214) du premier ensemble de cellules (200A ; 316) et décalé du bord (212) du second ensemble de cellules (200B ; 318).</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0009" num="0009"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 7 ou 8, <b>caractérisé en ce que</b> le décalage est d'environ une moitié de largeur de faisceau étroit.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20070330"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20061005"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60122401</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20061005</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20060823"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGBIT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20060823"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20050413"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050223</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20040728"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGBIT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20040623"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040423</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20031105"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20031105"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Countries concerned </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ALLTLVMKROSI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="RIN1" date="20011107"><legal-event-body><event-title>INVENTOR (CORRECTION)</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>inventor name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PIETRUSIAK, STEPHAN</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010822"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010822"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>