<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1130893-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1130893" kind="B1" date="20050413"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23210318" ucid="EP-1130893-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1130893</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20050413</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01301421-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01301421</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010219</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-516267" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>516267</doc-number><date>20000229</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-51626700-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>51626700</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000229</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20041029</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F   3/16        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F   3/16        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  13/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F  13/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  12/58        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04L  12/58        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   3/42        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   3/42        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   3/50        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   3/53        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   7/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   7/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04Q   3/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04Q   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04M7/00B4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04Q3/00D3</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04M201:60</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04M242:22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04M3:53T</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Vorrichtung in einem intelligenten Netzwerk zum Benachrichtigen und zum Hören ausgewählter e-Mails über ein öffentliches Telefonnetzwerk</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Intelligent-networked system with service for notifying and hearing selected e-mails via a public switched telephone network</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Système dans un réseau téléphonique intelligent permettant de notifier et écouter, via un réseau téléphonique publique, des messages éléctroniques (e-mails) séléctionnés</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>LUCENT TECHNOLOGIES INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>LUCENT TECHNOLOGIES INC.</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>CAI YIGANG</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HUA SHIYAN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>CAI, YIGANG</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>HUA, SHIYAN</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>CAI, YIGANG</last-name><address><street>1919 Nutmeg Lane</street><city>Naperville, Illinois 60565</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>HUA, SHIYAN</last-name><address><street>3011 Tangley Oaks Trail, Lisle</street><city>Dupage, Illinois 60532</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>LUCENT TECHNOLOGIES INC.</last-name><address><street>600 Mountain Avenue</street><city>Murray Hill, New Jersey 07974-0636</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Watts, Christopher Malcolm Kelway, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Lucent Technologies (UK) Ltd, 5 Mornington Road</street><city>Woodford Green Essex IG8 OTU</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>An intelligent-networked telecommunication system for audio playing of Electronic Mail (   E-Mail    ) messages uses the Service Control Point (SCP) of the Intelligent Network (IN) to route e-mail messages directed to subscribing customers to the customer's telephone number when the e-mail header matches the limitations stored in the subscribing customer's profile. The text of the e-mail message is converted to an audio message which can either be heard by the customer when a call is answered, or stored on an answering machine or in a voice mailbox. The present-inventive Notifying and Hearing Selective E-Mails (NHSE) system and method also includes features such as the subscribing customer being able to specify that audio e-mail messages will be truncated to a specified length, sending a special Caller ID message identifying the e-mail sender and subject of the message when the customer also has Caller ID service, and preceding the transmission of the audio e-mail message with a distinctive ringing pattern, to allow a subscribing customer the option of going     off-hook     to listen to the message, or allow the call to go directly to voice mail or an answering machine. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">An intelligent-networked telecommunication system for
audio playing of Electronic Mail (<img file="80000001.tif" id="img-EP-1130782-A2-80000001" he="4" wi="4" img-format="tif" img-content="ff" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /> 
E-Mail <img file="80010001.tif" id="img-EP-1130782-A2-80010001" he="4" wi="4" img-format="tif" img-content="ff" orientation="unknown" inline="no" />) messages uses
the Service Control Point (SCP) of the Intelligent Network
(IN) to route e-mail messages directed to subscribing customers
to the customer's telephone number when the e-mail
header matches the limitations stored in the subscribing
customer's profile. The text of the e-mail message is converted
to an audio message which can either be heard by the
customer when a call is answered, or stored on an answering
machine or in a voice mailbox. The present-inventive Notifying
and Hearing Selective E-Mails (NHSE) system and method
also includes features such as the subscribing customer being
able to specify that audio e-mail messages will be truncated
to a specified length, sending a special Caller ID
message identifying the e-mail sender and subject of the
message when the customer also has Caller ID service, and
preceding the transmission of the audio e-mail message with
a distinctive ringing pattern, to allow a subscribing customer 
the option of going <img file="80020001.tif" id="img-EP-1130782-A2-80020001" he="4" wi="4" img-format="tif" img-content="ff" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /> off-hook <img file="80030001.tif" id="img-EP-1130782-A2-80030001" he="4" wi="4" img-format="tif" img-content="ff" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /> to listen to the message,
or allow the call to go directly to voice mail or an
answering machine.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1130782-A2-00000001" he="73" wi="96" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><heading><b>1. Field of the Invention</b></heading><p num="0001">The present invention generally relates to networks for
providing telephone calls, and networks for providing Electronic
Mail messages.</p><heading><b>2. Background</b></heading><p num="0002">As is well known in the art, Electronic Mail (&quot;E-Mail&quot;)
consists of computer generated messages and files by
a sending party, which are intended to be electronically
transmitted and read by a receiving party.</p><p num="0003">It is desirable to allow telephone customers to have
access to e-mail messages in audio form while they are away
from computers. The prior art has attempted to fill this
need by providing such systems as the Octel™ Unified Messenger
System belonging to Lucent Technologies, Inc. Among the
noticeable limitations of that system and others is the fact
that e-mail messages are only available through a paging
system when a computer is not available to receive the e-mail
message. Additionally, these systems require the use
of Private Branch Exchange (PBX) systems tied into a server
having special software compatible with the particular audio
e-mail system. As a result of the special hardware and
software requirements, prior art audio e-mail systems are
not available for general Public Switched Telephone Network
(PSTN) customers.</p><p num="0004">To that end, it is desirable to provide an audio e-mail
system for converting text messages to audio messages, which 
system is potentially available to the masses of PSTN customers who have e-mail
accounts. And, this system should not require the customer to install any special
hardware or software.</p><p num="0005"><ref type="patent">EP-A-0 924 946</ref> (SIEMENS AG) discloses a system and method for exchanging
information between an e-mail service and a subscriber in a telecommunication
network. However, <ref type="patent">EP-A-0 924 946</ref> does not involve using a service control point
(SCP) to route the e-mail messages and calls. Further, it does not disclose storing a
subscriber's e-mail handling instructions or using such handling instructions and
information in the e-mail messages in order to route e-mail messages, see <ref type="patent">AT 410 377</ref>, <ref type="patent">CH 682 798</ref>, <ref type="patent">DE 44 29 353</ref>.</p><heading><b><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></b></heading><p num="0006">A method and system according to the invention are as set out in the
independent claims. Preferred forms are set out in the dependent claims.</p><p num="0007">In view of the aforementioned problems and deficiencies of the prior art, the
present invention provides in a telecommunication system, a method of providing to a
subscriber, an audio message converted from an electronic text message. The several
steps of the method include providing a plurality of telephonic devices for initiating and
receiving telephone calls, and providing an automated intelligent network (IN) for the
automated processing of telephone calls in the telecommunication system. The IN at
least includes a service control point (SCP) at least including control logic and an SCP
database, and the IN at least includes a plurality of switches coupled to telephone
devices.</p><p num="0008">The method further includes the steps of, via the switches, routing calls
authorized by the SCP to a destination number specified by a calling party, via the IN
and the SCP, receiving an electronic mail (e-mail) message specifying a subscriber as
the intended recipient of the e-mail message, and terminating a telephone call generated
by the IN to a telephone number specified by the subscriber in the SCP database.</p><p num="0009">The method also includes the steps of converting text in the e-mail message to
an audio message, and transmitting during the telephone call, an outgoing message at
least including the audio message.</p><p num="0010">The present invention also provides a telecommunication system adapted to
provide to a subscriber, an audio message converted from an electronic text message.
The system has 
several elements, including a plurality of telephonic devices
adapted to initiate and receive telephone calls, and
an IN adapted to automatically process telephone calls in
the telecommunication system, the IN at least including an
SCP having control logic and an SCP database, and the IN at
least including a plurality of switches coupled to telephone
devices. The system also at least includes a text-to-audio
converter adapted to convert text in an e-mail message to an
audio message.</p><p num="0011">The switches are adapted to route calls authorized by
the SCP to a destination number specified by a calling
party, while the IN and SCP are adapted to receive an e-mail
message specifying a subscriber as the intended recipient of
the e-mail message. The IN is also adapted to generate and
terminate a telephone call to a telephone number specified
by the subscriber in the SCP database, and to cause to be
transmitted during the telephone call, an outgoing message
at least including the audio message.</p><heading><b>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWING FIGURES</b></heading><p num="0012">Features and advantages of the present invention will
become apparent to those skilled in the art from the description
below, with reference to the following drawing
figures, in which:
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a schematic block diagram of the basic
hardware for the intelligent-networked telecommunication
system for implementing the present-inventive service for
Notifying and Hearing Selected E-mails (NHSE);</li><li>Figure 2 is a schematic block diagram the Service Control
Point (SCP) of the Intelligent Network (IN) of the present-inventive
telecommunication system; and </li><li>Figure 3 is a flowchart/algorithm detailing the handling
of an e-mail message by the present-inventive telecommunication
system.</li></sl></p><heading><b>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</b></heading><heading><b>1. NHSE Basic Hardware and Operation</b></heading><p num="0013">The basic hardware of the telephone service system
100/180 capable of implementing Notifying and Hearing Selected
E-Mails (NHSE) service is illustrated in Figure 1.
The present invention is compatible with PSTNs, and requires
no additional hardware or software for telephone customers
subscribing to the service.</p><p num="0014">Used in this specification, the terms &quot;termination&quot;
and &quot;terminating&quot; refer to connecting a call to a destination
number.</p><p num="0015">The system 100/180 combines a domestic network 100, as
in the United States, for example, and a foreign network
180, as in Europe, for example. The system 100/180 includes
a variety of telephonic devices as would be common in a general
telephone system. For example, a user can connect to
the network 100 using such devices as common telephones 102,
130 and 186. Also, a user can attempt to complete a telephone
call using a telephone that is part of a private
branch exchange (PBX) 126 as is known in the art. The telephones
typically include alphanumeric keypads for inputting
Dual-Tone-Multi-Frequency (DTMF) signals, or the like, as is
common.</p><p num="0016">The telephone lines in the system 100/180 are initially
connected to Local Exchange Centers (LECs), 104, 128, etc.,
as is also known in the art.</p><p num="0017">The system 100/180 includes intelligent networks 110
and 182. Intelligent Networks (INs) are software and hardware
hybrids that are used to automatically process telephone 
calls in a telephone system. A service control point
(SCP) 118 in the IN provides the logic that governs call
handling, etc., and contains a database that stores useful
information needed for various transactions. The IN also
contains several switches (e.g., 112, 124 and 184) for both
receiving calls to the network and physically routing calls
to destination numbers. Each switch contains a Service
Switching Point (SSP) such as the one 116 for interfacing
with calling parties and performing the actual call routing
under the instruction of the SCP.</p><p num="0018">The SCP and SSP may be connected with a high-speed link
utilizing, for example, the Intelligent Network Application
Protocol (INAP), as approved by the European Telecommunications
Standards Institute (ETSI) or International Telecommunication
Unit (ITU). It will be appreciated by those
skilled in the art that the SCP 118 can be implemented as a
networked database, not limited-to one geographic location.</p><p num="0019">A Service Management System (SMS) 120 is used by customers
to establish parameters for various services available
(such as the NHSE service of the present invention),
security codes, and any restrictions on the use of a telephone
line or account.</p><p num="0020">An Originating Call Processor (OCP) such as the one 115
is part of each switch, and transfers a received call to the
switch's SSP. A Terminating Call Processor (TCP) such as
the one 114 is also part of each switch, and handles the
termination of call processing to connect it to the destination
number. The interface between the SSP 116 and the OCP
115, and the interface between the SSP and TCP use a switch
internal message flow, or a common channel signaling link or
any type of protocol, as will be appreciated by those
skilled in the art. </p><p num="0021">As is common in present-day telephone systems, a voice
mailbox 106 allows the calling party of unanswered terminated
calls to leave a voice mail message for the called
party.</p><p num="0022">The switches (112, 124, 184, etc.) also have associated
Intelligent Peripherals (IPs) for the purpose of playing announcement
messages and prompting and collecting user information.
The IPs can be stand-alone units (125), or units
integrated (123) within the associated switch, or a unit
within the Service Node (SN) (not shown in Figure 1). In
the preferred embodiment, the functions of the IPs include
converting the text of e-mail messages to audio messages,
and played back to the intended subscribing customer.</p><p num="0023">As can be seen from Figures 1 and 2, the SCP 118 is
connected to a wide area network such as the Internet 210 to
monitor e-mail transmissions for those e-mail messages intended
for customers subscribing to the present-inventive
NHSE service. The SCP 118 connects to the Internet 210 by
way of an e-mail server 204. An SCP database 206 stores information
for the operation of the SCP and various services,
including NHSE. The SCP database also contains custom data
entered by subscribing customers reflecting the customers'
choices for handling e-mail messages received by the system
100/180. A service processor or SCP Control Unit 206 controls
the operation of the SCP and various services including
the present-inventive NHSE service.</p><p num="0024">When a customer subscribes to the present-inventive
NHSE service, he/she may establish service by following instructions
after dialing a predetermined telephone number;
or by sending a registration e-mail to the SCP or the SMS e-mail
server, or registration through a service web site on
the Internet. The customer can choose from among various
menu items after receiving prompts. A subscribing customer 
establishes an NHSE list to be stored in the SCP database.
In the preferred embodiment, the subscriber's NHSE list includes
his/her e-mail address, the telephone number where e-mail
messages are to be forwarded, e-mail truncation information
indicating whether the subscriber desires that e-mail
messages transmitted shall be truncated, and the truncation
length, and other selective information.</p><p num="0025">The selective information includes various items such
as a list of senders' e-mail addresses for messages from
those senders that the subscriber would like to have converted
and transmitted by the NHSE service, if desired, keywords
in the sender's e-mail address that will activate the
service, keywords in a received e-mail's subject or body
that will activate the service, the sending date or keywords
in the sending date of the e-mail which will activate the
service, and which level or priority will activate the service
(for example, the subscriber may desire that only messages
marked &quot;urgent&quot; should be forwarded by the NHSE
service). It will be appreciated by those skilled in the
art having read the above description that the subscriber
may simply elect to have all e-mail messages forwarded under
the present-inventive NHSE service, if desired.</p><p num="0026">After the audio e-mail message is played during a terminated
telephone call, the system can give the subscriber
the opportunity to input a code from a menu to have the message
stored directly into voice mail for customers also having
a voice mailbox maintained by the system. For example,
the announcement after the audio e-mail message can state:
&quot;If you would like to save this e-mail message in your
voice mailbox, please press '9'.&quot;</p><p num="0027">The system can also give the customer the opportunity
to have the e-mail message repeated one or more times. This 
may allow customers who have integrated telephone/answering
machines to record the next playing of the e-mail message.</p><p num="0028">The present inventive system and method briefly operate
as follows. When the SCP detects an e-mail message intended
for one of the NHSE subscribers, the SCP database is queried
for handling instructions. The header information in the e-mail
message is compared with the intended customer's NHSE
list to determine whether a match exists. If a match exists,
the SCP determines whether the subscriber also has
Caller ID service. If so, the SCP constructs Caller ID
header information to send to the subscriber's telephone
number. The Caller ID information can include an indication
that an e-mail message is being sent, the sender's e-mail
address, and the subject of the e-mail (which can be truncated
if necessary).</p><p num="0029">When the e-mail is forwarded to the subscriber's telephone
number, it is preceded by a distinctive ringing pattern,
allowing a subscriber to either answer the telephone
and hear the e-mail message, or ignore the call and have the
message stored by an answering device or in voice mail.
Along with the distinctive ringing pattern, the subscriber's
telephone number also receives Caller ID information identifying
the e-mail sender's address and the e-mail subject.</p><p num="0030">If the subscriber has chosen a truncation option, the
e-mail message is truncated according to the subscriber's
truncation instructions.</p><p num="0031">The intelligent peripheral of the SSP serving the subscriber
converts the text of the e-mail message into an
audio message. After a call from the SCP to the subscriber
is &quot;terminated,&quot; the audio version of the e-mail message
is played for the subscriber (or to default mechanisms such
as an answering machine or voice mail) by the intelligent
peripheral. </p><heading><b>2. NHSE Algorithm Description</b></heading><p num="0032">The handling of an e-mail message by the present-inventive
Notifying and Hearing Selected E-Mails (NHSE)
service is detailed below, with reference to the flowchart
of Figure 3.</p><p num="0033">At the beginning step (302) of the algorithm 300, the
SCP receives an e-mail message from the Internet indicating
an NHSE subscriber as the intended recipient. In Step 304,
the SCP determines whether information in the e-mail header
meets the forwarding requirements in the subscriber's NHSE
list information. If not, the e-mail is discarded by the
NHSE system (although the e-mail is still passed to the appropriate
Internet Service Provider in the preferred embodiment)
in Steps 306 and 322, with no further action.</p><p num="0034">If the e-mail message is to be forwarded to the customer,
the SCP checks the truncation option, and truncates
the e-mail message accordingly (Steps 308 and 310). The e-mail
header information is deleted in Step 312. To begin
the transfer of the e-mail message to the subscriber, the
SCP sends an InitialCallAttempt operation to the SSP (Step
314). Included in the InitialCallAttempt are the Destination
Routing Address (DestinationRoutingAddress), which is
the telephone number designated by the subscriber for receiving
NHSE e-mail messages, and the Alerting Pattern
(AlertingPattern) in the form of a distinctive ringing pattern
indicating that a telephone call contains an NHSE e-mail
message. The SCP also sends a RequestReportBCSM operation
to the SSP requesting an answer event report.</p><p num="0035">In response to the operations sent to it in Step 314,
the SSP uses the Destination Routing Address to originate
and route a telephone call to the subscriber (Step 316). In
Step 318 the TCP determines whether the subscriber also has
Caller ID service. If so, the TCP prepares a Caller ID information 
header including the e-mail sender's e-mail address
as the originating telephone number, and the e-mail
subject in place of the calling party's name (Step 320).</p><p num="0036">In Step 322 the subscriber's telephone rings with the
distinctive ringing pattern for the NHSE service. When the
telephone is answered in Step 324 (either by the subscriber,
an answering machine, or voice mail, for example), the SSP
sends an EventReportBCSM operation to the SCP (Step 326).
Upon receiving this latter operation, the SCP sends ConnectToResource
and PlayAnnouncement operations back to the
SSP (Step 328). Along with these operations, the SCP also
sends the e-mail message text. The ConnectToResource operation
connects the subscriber's line to the intelligent peripheral.
The PlayAnnouncement operation causes the IP to
convert the text of the e-mail message into an audio message,
and to playback the message to the subscriber (Step
330).</p><p num="0037">The NHSE algorithm 300 ends with Step 332. After the
audio e-mail message is played, the call can continue to be
processed as any other call.</p><p num="0038">Variations and modifications of the present invention
are possible, given the above description.</p><p num="0039">It is noted that nothing in the present invention is
inconsistent with, nor need interfere with normal e-mail operation.
That is, all e-mails sent over the Internet will
also continue to be handled by Internet Service Providers
(ISPs) and forwarded to a subscriber's computer or server as
per usual, unless the subscriber dictates otherwise. Therefore,
the present-inventive NHSE service is a supplement to 
typical e-mail service in its preferred use, although NHSE
service may serve as a subscriber's primary means of e-mail
receipt in alternative uses.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Bereitstellen eines e-Mail-Nachrichtenzustellungsdienstes
(electronic mail -
elektronische Post) für einen Teilnehmer am PSTN-Dienst
(öffentliches Telefonwählnetz), wobei das
PSTN ein intelligentes Netz für die automatisierte
Bearbeitung von Telefongesprächen enthält, wobei
das intelligente Netz einen Dienstesteuerungspunkt
SCP (service control point) und eine SCP-Datenbank
umfaßt, dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß das Verfahren
folgende Schritte umfaßt:
<claim-text><claim-text>Speichern der e-Mail-Bearbeitungsanweisungen des
Teilnehmers in der SCP-Datenbank, wobei die
Bearbeitungsanweisungen vom Teilnehmer kundenspezifisch
eingestellt werden können und die e-Mail-Adresse
des Teilnehmers, das vom Teilnehmer
bezeichnete Telefon für den Empfang von
Tonnachrichten und die e-Mail-Kürzungsanweisungen
des Teilnehmers umfassen;</claim-text><claim-text>über den SCP Empfangen einer e-Mail-Nachricht von
einem Sender über ein Netzelement, wobei die
Nachricht Kopfteilinformationen enthält und den
Teilnehmer als Zielempfänger der e-Mail-Nachricht
angibt;</claim-text><claim-text>Vergleichen von Informationen in der e-Mail-Nachricht
mit den in der SCP-Datenbank für den
Teilnehmer gespeicherten Bearbeitungsanweisungen;</claim-text><claim-text>Umwandeln des Textgehalts in der e-Mail-Nachricht
in eine Sprachnachricht gemäß den
Kürzungsanweisungen, und Herstellen einer
Verbindung mit dem vom Teilnehmer vorher
bezeichneten Telefon; und übertragen der
Sprachnachricht zu dem Teilnehmer über das vom
Teilnehmer bezeichnete Telefon.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1, wobei die
Bearbeitungsanweisungen weiterhin mindestens eine
aus einer Liste von e-Mail-Adressen von Sendern
für Nachrichten von denjenigen Sendern umfassen,
die der Teilnehmer gerne umgewandelt und zum
Telefon des Teilnehmers übertragen haben möchte;
eine Mehrzahl von Schlüsselworten in dem
Gegenstand oder Körper einer empfangenen e-Mail-Nachricht,
die den Dienst aktivieren werden, das
Sendedatum oder Schlüsselworte in dem Sendedatum
der Nachricht, die den Dienst aktivieren werden,
oder welche Prioritätsstufe den Dienst aktivieren
wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1, wobei die e-Mail-Nachricht
gemäß den vom Teilnehmer angegebenen
Kürzungsanweisungen gekürzt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1, weiterhin mit folgenden
Schritten:
<claim-text><claim-text>Bestimmen, ob der Teilnehmer auch an einem Anrufererkennungsdienst
zur Bereitstellung von Anrufererkennungsinformationen
teilnimmt; und</claim-text><claim-text>Übertragen von Anrufererkennungsinformationen zu
dem vom Teilnehmer bezeichneten Telefon, wobei die
Informationen eine Anzeige enthalten, daß ein vom
Teilnehmer empfangener Telefonanruf eine e-Mail-Nachricht
enthält.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 4, wobei die Anrufererkennungsinformationen
weiterhin die Identität
des Senders der e-Mail-Nachricht umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 4, wobei die Anrufererkennungsinformationen
weiterhin eine Gegenstandskennung
der e-Mail-Nachricht umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 4, wobei die Anrufererkennungsinformationen
weiterhin einen Teil des
Texts der e-Mail-Nachricht umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1, weiterhin mit dem
Schritt des Sendens eines ausgeprägten Ruftonmusters
entsprechend der Einschließung einer e-Mail-Nachricht
in dem Anruf.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1, wobei die e-Mail-Nachricht
nur dann zu einem Teilnehmer übertragen
wird, wenn die Kopfteilinformationen in der e-Mail-Nachricht
anzeigen, daß die Nachricht
dringend ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1, weiterhin mit folgenden
Schritten:
<claim-text><claim-text>Auffordern des Teilnehmers zur Eingabe eines Codes,
wobei der Code ein Signal an das intelligente Netz
zum Speichern der Sprachnachricht in einem
Sprachspeicher umfaßt; und</claim-text><claim-text>Speichern der Sprachnachricht in einem Sprachspeicher
bei Empfang des Codes.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1, weiterhin mit folgenden
Schritten:<claim-text><claim-text>Auffordern des Teilnehmers zur Eingabe eines
Codes, wobei der Code ein Signal an das
intelligente Netz zum Wiederholen des Abspielens
der Sprachnachricht umfaßt; und</claim-text><claim-text>Wiederholen des Abspielens der Sprachnachricht bei
Empfang des Codes.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System zum Bereitstellen einer von einer e-Mail-Nachricht
umgewandelten Sprachnachricht für einen
Telekommunikationsteilnehmer, mit folgendem:
<claim-text><claim-text>einem intelligenten Netz für die automatisierte
Verarbeitung von Telefongesprächen, wobei das
intelligente Netz einen Dienstesteuerungspunkt SCP
(service control point) und eine SCP-Datenbank
umfaßt; dadurch gekennzeichnet, daß</claim-text><claim-text>der SCP Verbindungsverarbeitungs-Steuerlogik und
eine SCP-Datenbank zum Speichern von Verbindungsbearbeitungsinformationen
und e-Mail-Bearbeitungsanweisungen
aufweist, wobei der SCP zum Empfangen
einer e-Mail-Nachricht geeignet ist, zum
Vergleichen von Kopfteilinformationen in dieser e-Mail-Nachricht
mit in der SCP-Datenbank gespeicherten
e-Mail-Bearbeitungsanweisungen und zum
Leiten der e-Mail-Nachricht zu einer durch einen
Ziel-Teilnehmer angegebenen Telefonnummer, wenn
dies von den Bearbeitungsanweisungen angezeigt
ist, wobei die e-Mail-Bearbeitungsanweisungen vom
Teilnehmer kundenspezifisch eingestellt werden
können und die e-Mail-Adresse des Teilnehmers, das
vom Teilnehmer bezeichnete Telefon zum Empfangen
von Sprachnachrichten und die e-Mail-Kürzungsanweisungen
des Teilnehmers umfassen; und</claim-text><claim-text>das intelligente Netz weiterhin einen Text-zu-Sprache-Wandler
zum Umwandeln von Text in dieser
e-Mail-Nachricht in eine Sprachnachricht umfaßt.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 12, wobei die Bearbeitungsanweisungen
weiterhin mindestens eine aus einer
Liste von e-Mail-Adressen von Sendern für
Nachrichten von denjenigen Sendern umfassen, die
der Teilnehmer gerne umgewandelt und zum Telefon
des Teilnehmers übertragen haben möchte; eine
Mehrzahl von Schlüsselworten in dem Gegenstand
oder Körper einer empfangenen e-Mail-Nachricht,
die den Dienst aktivieren werden, das Sendedatum
oder Schlüsselworte in dem Sendedatum der
Nachricht, die den Dienst aktivieren werden, oder
welche Prioritätsstufe den Dienst aktivieren wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 12, wobei die e-Mail-Nachricht
gemäß den vom Teilnehmer angegebenen
Kürzungsanweisungen gekürzt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 12, wobei der Dienstesteuerungspunkt
weiterhin geeignet ist, zu
bestimmen, ob der Teilnehmer an einem Anrufererkennungsdienst
zum Bereitstellen von Anrufererkennungsinformationen
und zum Übertragen von
Anrufererkennungsinformationen zu dem von
Teilnehmer bezeichneten Telefon teilnimmt, wobei
die Informationen eine Anzeige enthalten, daß ein
vom Teilnehmer empfangener Telefonanruf eine e-Mail-Nachricht
enthält.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 15, wobei die Anrufererkennungsinformationen
weiterhin die Identität
des Senders der e-Mail-Nachricht umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 16, wobei die Anrufererkennungsinformationen
weiterhin eine Gegenstandskennung
der e-Mail-Nachricht umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 17, wobei die Anrufererkennungsinformationen
weiterhin einen Teil des
Texts der e-Mail-Nachricht umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 12, wobei der Dienstesteuerungspunkt
weiterhin geeignet ist, ein
ausgeprägtes Ruftonmuster entsprechend der
Einschließung einer e-Mail-Nachricht in dem Anruf
zu senden.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 13, wobei die e-Mail-Nachricht
nur dann zu einem Teilnehmer übertragen
wird, wenn die Kopfteilinformationen in der e-Mail-Nachricht
anzeigen, daß die Nachricht
dringend ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 12, weiterhin mit folgendem:
<claim-text><claim-text>einer intelligenten Peripherie zum Auffordern des
Teilnehmers zur Eingabe eines Codes, wobei der
Code ein Signal an das Kommunikationssystem zum
Speichern der Sprachnachricht in einem Sprachspeicher
umfaßt; und</claim-text><claim-text>einem Sprachspeicher zum Speichern der Sprachnachricht
bei Empfang des Codes.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>System nach Anspruch 12, weiterhin mit folgendem:
<claim-text><claim-text>einer intelligenten Peripherie zum Auffordern des
Teilnehmers zur Eingabe eines Codes, wobei der
Code ein Signal an das Telekommunikationssystem
zum Wiederholen des Abspielens der Sprachnachricht
umfaßt; und</claim-text><claim-text>einem Sprachspeicher zum Wiederholen des Abspielens
der Sprachnachricht bei Empfang des Codes.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A method for providing an electronic mail e-mail message delivery service
for a subscriber to Public Switched Telephone Network PSTN service, the PSTN
including an intelligent network for the automated processing of telephone calls, the
intelligent network comprising a service control point SCP and an SCP database,
   CHARACTERIZED BY:
<claim-text><claim-text>the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>storing in the SCP database the subscriber's e-mail handling instructions, wherein the
handling instructions are customizable by the subscriber and comprise the subscriber's
e-mail address, the subscriber's designated telephone for receiving audio messages, and
the subscriber's e-mail truncation instructions;</claim-text><claim-text>via said SCP, receiving an e-mail message from a sender via a network element, the message
including header information and specifying the subscriber as an intended recipient of
the e-mail message;</claim-text><claim-text>comparing information in the e-mail message to the handling instructions stored
in the SCP database for the subscriber;</claim-text><claim-text>converting textual content in the e-mail message to an audio message according to said truncation intructions;</claim-text><claim-text>establishing a call to the telephone previously designated by the subscriber; and</claim-text><claim-text>transmitting the audio message to the subscriber via the telephone designated by
the subscriber.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 1, wherein the handling instructions further
comprise at least one of a list of senders' e-mail addresses for messages from those
senders that the subscriber would like to have converted and transmitted to the
subscriber's telephone, a plurality of keywords in a received e-mail message's subject
or body that will activate the service, the sending date or keywords in the sending date
of the message that will activate the service, or which level of priority will activate the
service.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 1, wherein the e-mail message is truncated
according to the truncation instructions specified by the subscriber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 1, further comprising the steps of:<claim-text><claim-text>determining of whether the subscriber also subscribes to a caller identification
service for providing caller identification information; and</claim-text><claim-text>transmitting caller identification information to the telephone designated by the
subscriber, the information including an indication that a telephone call received by the
subscriber contains an e-mail message.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 4, wherein the caller identification information
further comprises the identity of the sender of the e-mail message.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 4, wherein the caller identification information
further comprises a subject matter identifier of the e-mail message.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 4, wherein the caller identification information
further comprises a portion of the text of the e-mail message.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 1, further comprising the step of sending a
distinctive ringing pattern corresponding to the inclusion of an e-mail message in the
call.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 1, wherein the e-mail message is not transmitted
to a subscriber unless header information in the e-mail message indicates that the
message is urgent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 1, further comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>prompting the subscriber to enter a code, the code comprising
a signal to the intelligent network to store the audio message in a voice mailbox; and</claim-text><claim-text>storing the audio message in a voice mailbox upon receiving the code.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The method defined in claim 1, further comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>prompting the subscriber to enter a code, the code comprising
a signal to the intelligent network to repeat the playing of the audio message; and</claim-text><claim-text>repeating the playing of the audio message upon receiving the
code.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A system for providing to a telecommunications subscriber an audio
message converted from an e-mail message, the system comprising:<claim-text><claim-text>an intelligent network for the automated processing of telephone calls, the
intelligent network comprising a service control point SCP and an SCP database;</claim-text></claim-text>
   CHARACTERIZED BY:
<claim-text><claim-text>the SCP having call handling control logic and an SCP database for storing call
handling information and e-mail handling instructions, the SCP being adapted to receive an e-mail message, to
compare header information in said e-mail message
to e-mail handling instructions stored in the SCP database and to route the e-mail message to
a telephone number specified by an intended subscriber when the handling instructions
so indicate, wherein the e-mail handling instructions are customizable by the subscriber
and comprise the subscriber's email address, the subscriber's designated telephone for
receiving audio messages, and the subscriber's e-mail truncation instructions; and</claim-text><claim-text>the intelligent network further comprises a text-to-audio converter adapted to
convert text in said e-mail message to an audio message.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 12, wherein the handling instructions further
comprise at least one of a list of senders' e-mail addresses for messages from those
senders that the subscriber would like to have converted and transmitted to the
subscriber's telephone, a plurality of keywords in a received e-mail message's subject
or body that will activate the service, the sending date or keywords in the sending date
of the message that will activate the service, or which level of priority will activate the
service.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 12, wherein the e-mail message is truncated
according to the truncation instructions specified by the subscriber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 12, wherein the service control point is further
adapted to determine whether the subscriber subscribes to a caller identification service
for providing caller identification information and to transmit caller identification
information to the telephone designated by the subscriber, the information including an
indication that a telephone call received by the subscriber contains an e-mail message.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 15, wherein the caller identification
information further comprises the identity of the sender of the e-mail message.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 16, wherein the caller identification
information further comprises a subject matter identifier of the e-mail message.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 17, wherein the caller identification
information further comprises a portion of the text of the e-mail message.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 12, wherein the service control point is further
adapted to send a distinctive ringing pattern corresponding to the inclusion of an e-mail
message in the call.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 13, wherein the email message is not
transmitted to a subscriber unless header information in the e-mail message indicates
that the message is urgent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 12, further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an intelligent peripheral adapted to prompt the subscriber to enter a
code, the code comprising a signal to the telecommunication system to store
the audio message in a voice mailbox; and</claim-text><claim-text>a voice mailbox adapted to store the audio message upon receiving the code.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The system defined in claim 12, further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an intelligent peripheral adapted to prompt the subscriber to enter a
code, the code comprising a signal to the telecommunication system to repeat
the playing of the audio message; and</claim-text><claim-text>a voice mailbox adapted to repeat the playing of the audio message upon
receiving the code.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé de fourniture d'un service de livraison de
messages de courriel de courrier électronique pour
un abonné au service de réseau téléphonique public
commuté PSTN, le PSTN comprenant un réseau
intelligent pour le traitement automatisé des
appels téléphoniques, le réseau intelligent
comprenant un point de commande de services SCP et
une base de données SCP,CARACTERISE PAR :
<claim-text><claim-text>le procédé comprenant les étapes consistant à :
<claim-text><claim-text>mémoriser dans la base de données SCP les
instructions de gestion de courriel de l'abonné,
dans lequel les instructions de gestion sont
personnalisables par l'abonné et comprennent
l'adresse de courriel de l'abonné, le téléphone
désigné de l'abonné pour recevoir des messages
audio, et les instructions de troncature de
courriel de l'abonné ;</claim-text><claim-text>par ledit SCP, recevoir un message de courriel
d'un envoyeur par l'intermédiaire d'un élément de
réseau, le message comprenant des informations
d'en-tête et spécifiant l'abonné tel qu'un
destinataire prévu du message de courriel ;</claim-text><claim-text>comparer des informations dans le message de
courriel aux instructions de gestion mémorisées
dans la base de données SCP pour l'abonné ;</claim-text><claim-text>convertir du contenu textuel dans le message de
courriel en un message audio selon lesdites
instructions de troncature ;</claim-text><claim-text>établir un appel au téléphone précédemment désigné
par l'abonné ; et</claim-text><claim-text>transmettre le message audio à l'abonné par
l'intermédiaire du téléphone désigné par l'abonné.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 1, dans
lequel les instruction de gestion comprennent en
outre au moins une d'une liste d'adresses de
courriel d'envoyeurs pour des messages provenant
de ces envoyeurs que l'abonné aimerait avoir
convertis et transmis au téléphone de l'abonné,
une pluralité de mots-clés dans le sujet ou le
corps d'un message de courriel reçu qui activeront
le service, la date d'envoi ou des mots-clés dans
la date d'envoi du message qui activeront le
service, ou dont le niveau de priorité activera le
service.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 1, dans
lequel le message de courriel est tronqué selon
les instructions de troncature spécifiées par
l'abonné.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 1,
comprenant en outre les étapes consistant à :
<claim-text><claim-text>déterminer si l'abonné souscrit également à un
service d'identification d'appelant pour fournir
des informations d'identification d'appelant ; et</claim-text><claim-text>transmettre des informations d'identification
d'appelant au téléphone désigné par l'abonné, les
informations comprenant une indication qu'un appel
téléphonique reçu par l'abonné contient un message
de courriel.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 4, dans
lequel les informations d'identification
d'appelant comprennent en outre l'identité de
l'envoyeur du message de courriel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 4, dans
lequel les informations d'identification
d'appelant comprennent en outre un identifiant de
thème de sujet du message de courriel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 4, dans
lequel les informations d'identification
d'appelant comprennent en outre une partie du
texte du message de courriel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 1,
comprenant en outre l'étape d'envoi d'un modèle de
sonnerie distinctif correspondant à l'inclusion
d'un message de courriel dans l'appel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 1, dans
lequel le message de courriel n'est pas transmis à
moins que des informations d'en-tête dans le
message de courriel indiquent que le message est
urgent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 1,
comprenant en outre les étapes consistant à :
<claim-text><claim-text>inciter l'abonné à entrer un code, le code
comprenant un signal au réseau intelligent pour
mémoriser le message audio dans une boíte vocale ;
et à</claim-text><claim-text>mémoriser le message audio dans une boíte vocale
dès la réception du code.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Procédé défini selon la revendication 1,
comprenant en outre les étapes consistant à :
<claim-text><claim-text>inciter l'abonné à entrer un code, le code
comprenant un signal au réseau intelligent pour
répéter le passage du message audio ; et à</claim-text><claim-text>répéter le passage du message audio dès la
réception du code.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système de fourniture à un abonné de
télécommunication d'un message audio converti à
partir d'un message de courriel, le système
comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>un réseau intelligent pour le traitement
automatisé d'appels téléphoniques, le réseau
intelligent comprenant un point de commande de
services SCP et une base de données SCP,</claim-text></claim-text>CARACTERISE PAR :
<claim-text><claim-text>le SCP ayant la logique de commande de gestion
d'appel et une base de données SCP pour mémoriser
des informations de gestion d'appel et les
instructions de gestion de courriel, le SCP étant
adapté pour recevoir un message de courriel, pour
comparer des informations d'en-tête dans ledit
message de courriel à des instructions de gestion
de courriel mémorisées dans la base de données SCP
et pour acheminer le message de courriel au numéro
de téléphone spécifié par un abonné prévu lorsque
les instructions de gestion l'indiquent, dans
lequel les instructions de gestion de courriel
sont personnalisables par l'abonné et comprennent
l'adresse de courriel de l'abonné, le téléphone
désigné de l'abonné pour recevoir des messages
audio, et les instructions de troncature de
courriel de l'abonné ; et</claim-text><claim-text>le réseau intelligent comprend en outre un
convertisseur de texte vers audio adapté pour
convertir du texte dans ledit message de courriel
en un message audio.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 12, dans
lequel les instructions de gestion comprennent en
outre au moins une d'une liste d'adresses de
courriel d'envoyeurs pour des messages provenant
de ces envoyeurs que l'abonné aimerait avoir
convertis et transmis au téléphone de l'abonné,
une pluralité de mots-clés dans le sujet ou le
corps d'un message de courriel reçu qui activeront
le service, la date d'envoi ou des mots-clés dans
la date d'envoi du message qui activeront le
service, ou dont le niveau de priorité activera le
service.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 12, dans
lequel le message de courriel est tronqué selon
les instructions de troncature spécifiées par
l'abonné.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 12, dans
lequel le point de commande de services est en
outre adapté pour déterminer si l'abonné souscrit
à un service d'identification d'appelant pour
fournir des informations d'identification
d'appelant et pour transmettre des informations
d'identification d'appelant au téléphone désigné
par l'abonné, les informations comprenant une
indication qu'un appel téléphonique reçu par
l'abonné contient un message de courriel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 15, dans
lequel les informations d'identification
d'appelant comprennent en outre l'identité de
l'envoyeur du message de courriel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 16, dans
lequel les informations d'identification
d'appelant comprennent en outre un identifiant de
thème de sujet du message de courriel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 17, dans
lequel les informations d'identification
d'appelant comprennent en outre une partie du
texte du message de courriel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 12, dans
lequel le point de commande de services est en
outre adapté pour envoyer un modèle de sonnerie
distinctif correspondant à l'inclusion d'un
message de courriel dans l'appel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 13, dans
lequel le message de courriel n'est pas transmis à
un abonné à moins que des informations d'en-tête
dans le message de courriel indiquent que le
message est urgent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 12,
comprenant en outre:
<claim-text><claim-text>un périphérique intelligent adapté pour inciter
l'abonné à entrer un code, le code comprenant un
signal au système de télécommunication pour
mémoriser le message audio dans une boíte vocale;
et</claim-text><claim-text>une boíte vocale adaptée pour mémoriser le message
audio dès la réception du code.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Système défini selon la revendication 12,
comprenant en outre :
<claim-text><claim-text>un périphérique intelligent adapté pour inciter
l'abonné à entrer un code, le code comprenant un
signal au système de télécommunication pour
répéter le passage du message audio ; et</claim-text><claim-text>une boíte vocale adaptée pour répéter le passage
du message audio dès la réception du code.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20060405"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060116</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20060303"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20050519"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60109973</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050519</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050518"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050413"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050413"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20040506"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040421"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040305</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20040331"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040203</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20030813"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20030813"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Countries concerned </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ALLTLVMKROSI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>
