<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1129861-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1129861" kind="B1" date="20041103"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23211744" ucid="EP-1129861-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1129861</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20041103</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01104478-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01104478</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010228</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000055565-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000055565</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000301</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20040504</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41C   1/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41C   1/10        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/36        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/36        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/004       20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/004       20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/039       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03F   7/039       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41C1/10A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L41C1:10B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Bildaufzeichnungsmaterial und Flachdruckplatte mit diesem Bildaufzeichnungsmaterial</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Image-forming material and planographic printing original plate using same</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Matériau d'enregistrement d'images et plaque d'impression planographique utilisant celui-ci</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAKAMURA IPPEI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>NAKAMURA, IPPEI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>NAKAMURA, IPPEI</last-name><address><street>Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., 4000, Kawashiri</street><city>Yoshida-cho, Haibara-gun, Shizuoka-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>210 Nakanuma Minami-Ashigara-shi</street><city>Kanagawa 250-01</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name><address><street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street><city>81925 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>An image-forming material which has high sensitivity and is excellent in image-forming performance and which does not produce smudges on an optical system of an exposing apparatus, and a planographic printing original plate which uses this image-forming material and can produce images by an infrared laser for a direct plate-making process. These can be achieved by an image-forming material containing an infrared absorber having in the same molecule thereof two or more chromophoric groups which can absorb infrared radiation and are each bonded by a covalent bond.</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">An image-forming material which has high sensitivity and is
excellent in image-forming performance and which does not produce
smudges on an optical system of an exposing apparatus, and a
planographic printing original plate which uses this image-forming
material and can produce images by an infrared laser for a direct
plate-making process. These can be achieved by an image-forming
material containing an infrared absorber having in the same molecule
thereof two or more chromophoric groups which can absorb infrared
radiation and are each bonded by a covalent bond.</p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><heading>Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a positive-type or negative-type
image-forming material in which images can be recorded by
exposure to an infrared laser, characterized in that solubility of
exposed portions of a recording layer changes or hydrophilicity and
hydrophobicity of the exposed portions of the recording layer change,
and relates to a planographic printing original plate using the
material. Further, the present invention relates to an image-forming
material for use with an infrared laser, which is writable by exposure
to near-infrared region light from an infrared laser or the like and is
suitable for use in a planographic printing original plate that can be
prepared by a so-called direct plate-making process, enabling the
plate to be imaged directly according to digital signals, particularly
from a computer or the like, and relates to a planographic printing
original plate using the material.</p><heading>Description of the Related Art</heading><p num="0002">In recent years, owing to progress in technologies related to
solid-state lasers and semiconductor lasers that emit rays in regions
ranging from the near-infrared region to the infrared region, a system,
which uses these infrared lasers in a printing plate-making process so
that a printing plate is prepared directly according to digital data 
from a computer has drawn attention.</p><p num="0003"><ref type="patent">Japanese Patent Application Laid-Open (JP-A) No. 7-285275</ref>
discloses a material for a positive-type planographic printing plate for
use with an infrared laser in direct plate-making. That invention
relates to an image-forming material comprising a resin soluble in an
aqueous alkaline solution, a substance capable of generating heat by
absorbing light, and a positive-type photosensitive compound such as
a quinonediazide, wherein at image portions the positive-type
photosensitive compound acts as a dissolution inhibiting agent which
substantially reduces the solubility of the resin soluble in the aqueous
alkaline solution, and at non-image portions the positive-type
photosensitive compound is thermally decomposed to thereby lose
the dissolution inhibiting capability, and the image-forming material
can be removed by a development treatment to form an image.</p><p num="0004">After studies, the present inventors have found that a positive
image can be obtained without the addition of a quinonediazide to an
image-recording material. However, mere elimination of the
quinonediazide from the image recording material presents a
drawback that the stability of sensitivity with respect to concentration
of a developing solution, i.e., latitude in development, becomes poor.</p><p num="0005">Meanwhile, onium salts and compounds capable of forming
alkali-insoluble hydrogen bonds are known to act as an agent which
inhibits a polymer soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution from being
dissolved by the alkali. With regard to an image-forming material
for use with an infrared laser, <ref type="patent">WO 97/39,894</ref> describes that a 
composition which uses a cationic infrared absorbing dye as an agent
for inhibiting the polymer soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution
from being dissolved exhibits a positive-working phenomenon. This
positive working is that the infrared absorbing dye absorbs the laser
light and generates heat which deprives a polymeric film in an
irradiated region of dissolution inhibition, to thereby form an image.</p><p num="0006">However, this invention is associated with a problem that,
although image-forming performance of the photosensitive
composition at a surface irradiated with a laser is satisfactory, a
satisfactory effect cannot be obtained deeper in the photosensitive
material, because of diffusion of heat. As a result, an on-off
distinction between exposed areas and unexposed areas is insufficient
in a developing process with alkali. Any delivery method known to the art may be employed including those of <ref type="patent">U.S. Pat. Nos. 4,485,809, 4,600,001, and RE 33,727</ref>, as well as <ref type="patent">EPO No. 0 05 935</ref>. Consequently, a good image
was not obtained (i.e., sensitivity was low and latitude in
development was narrow). The term &quot;latitude in development&quot; as
used herein means the broadness, when the alkali concentrations
varies, of a range of the alkali concentrations of an alkaline
developing solution allowable for the creation of a good image.</p><p num="0007">An increase of exposure amount in order to obtain sufficient
latitude in development is associated with the problem that ablation
of the infrared absorber or other components in the photosensitive
layer occurs and, as a result, smudges are formed on an optical
system of an exposing apparatus. </p><p num="0008"><ref type="patent">EP 0 956 948 A1</ref> discloses an IR and UV radiation-sensitive composition and
lithographic plate comprising a diazo resin, a diazo ester, at least one novolac resin
and an IR-ray absorber.</p><p num="0009"><ref type="patent">EP 0 945 264 A1</ref> relates to an anionic infrared-ray absorbing agent, photosensitive
composition and planographic printing plate precursor using same.</p><p num="0010"><ref type="patent">EP 0 938 972 A1</ref> describes a photosensitive lithographic form plate using an
image-forming material. The image-forming material comprises an infrared light
absorbing agent having a hydrophobic group which changes to hydrophilic due to
heat.</p><p num="0011"><ref type="patent">EP 0 914 964 A2</ref> concerns a positive type photosensitive composition for infrared
lasers. These compositions may contain a substance which absorbs light in an
image-forming material.</p><p num="0012"><ref type="patent">EP 0 914 941 A1</ref> relates to a method for making positive working printing plates
from heat mode sensitive imaging elements. This method involves inter alia the
step of exposing imagewise to IR-radiation a heat mode imaging element having on
a lithographic base with a hydrophilic surface a first layer which top layer is
unpenetrable by an alkaline developer and contains a compound capable of
converting light into heat.</p><p num="0013"><ref type="patent">EP 0 913 253 A1</ref> discloses a positive photosensitive composition, positive
photosensitive lithographic printing plate and method for its treatment. The
photosensitive composition comprises at least (a) an alkali-soluble resin and (b) a
photothermal conversion material, which further contains (c) a compound capable
of crosslinking the alkali-soluble resin by thermal action.</p><p num="0014">The subject matter of <ref type="patent">EP 0 911 153 A1</ref> is an image-forming method. According to
this image-forming method an image-forming material is exposed to a laser, said
image-forming material comprising a support and provided thereon, a radiation
sensitive layer containing a dye having an absorption band in the wave length
region of from 700 nm to 1,200 nm. </p><p num="0015"><ref type="patent">JP-A-08-95197</ref> discloses a silver halide photographic photosensitive material
including a dye, which is an infrared ray absorber having at least two
chromophoric groups which can absorb an infrared ray and are bonded by a
covalent bond. The dye disclosed in this document is used for sensor detection.</p><p num="0016"><ref type="patent">EP 0 571 007 A1</ref> discloses a dye-donor element for use according laser-induced
thermal dye transfer. This dye-donor element comprises a support having
thereon a dye layer and an infrared-absorbing dye of 1,4-quinone type. One
specific embodiment of this dye may have two chromophoric groups.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0017">Accordingly, an object of the present invention is to provide an image-forming
material which has high sensitivity and is excellent in image-forming
performance and does not produce smudges on an optical system of an exposing
apparatus. A further object of the present invention is to provide a planographic
printing original plate which uses the material and which can form images by an
infrared laser for a direct plate-making process.</p><p num="0018">After a series of studies for the purpose of raising sensitivity and image-forming
performance, the present inventors found that the use of a specific
infrared absorber makes it possible to raise both the sensitivity and image-forming
performance and to inhibit ablation of the infrared absorber. Based on
these finding, the inventors have achieved the present invention. </p><p num="0019">A first aspect of the present invention is a an image-forming
material capable of recording an image by infrared
exposure, wherein the image-forming material contains at
least an infrared radiation absorber having in a molecule
thereof at least two chromophoric groups, each of which can
absorb an infrared ray and is bonded to another portion of
the molecule by a covalent bond

   wherein the image-forming material further comprises a
polymeric compound insoluble in water and soluble in an
aqueous alkaline solution, wherein image recording can be
effected by utilizing a change of solubility of the polymeric
compound in the aqueous alkaline solution.</p><p num="0020">A second aspect of the present invention is an image-forming
material capable of recording an image by infrared
exposure, wherein the image-forming material contains at
least an infrared radiation absorber having in a molecule
thereof at least two chromophoric groups, each of which can
absorb an infrared ray and is bonded to another portion of
the molecule by a covalent bond

   wherein the image-forming material further comprises a
polarity switchable material whose hydrophilicity and
hydrophobicity of the image-forming material are changed by
at least heat, wherein image recording can be effected by
utilizing change of the hydrophilictiy and hydrophobicity of
the image-forming material.</p><p num="0021">A third aspect of the present invention involves a
planographic printing original plate comprising a substrate,
and a recording layer provided on the substrate, the
recording layer containing an image-forming material capable
of recording an image by infrared exposure, wherein the
image-forming material contains at least an infrared
radiation absorber having in a molecule thereof at least two
chromophoric groups, each of which can absorb an infrared ray
and is bonded to another portion of the molecule by a
covalent bond. </p><p num="0022">A fourth aspect of the present invention is characterized by, in
the image-forming material or printing original plate according to any one of the above-mentioned
1st to 3rd aspects, wherein the infrared radiation absorber
is represented by the following general formula I:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">General formula I<st32:break type="required" />
(D)<st32:sub pos="post">n</st32:sub> - A</st32:df>
wherein A represents an organic group having a valency of at least 2;
n represents an integer of at least 2; and D represents a chromophoric
group having absorption in an infrared region, wherein one of the
chromophoric groups may be the same as and may be different from
another of the chromophoric groups; and, in a case where the
chromophoric group has an electric charge, an ion having an electric
charge opposite to the electric charge of the chromophoric group may
be present in order to neutralize the electric charge of the
chromophoric group.</p><p num="0023">Although the mechanism of the present invention is not clear,
it is presumed to be as follows. Because an infrared absorber having
in the same molecule thereof two or more chromophoric groups is 
used as the infrared absorber, the presence of the two or more
chromophoric groups that are adjacent to each other localizes the
distribution of a dye, and locally creates a portion which reaches a
high temperature. Further, because the linkage of the chromophoric
groups causes the dye to form a state of association and quickens a
relaxing process from an excited state, the amount of generated heat
increases. Presumably, these effects make it possible to achieve high
sensitivity and improvement of image-forming performance.</p><p num="0024">In addition, in comparison with an infrared absorber having
only one chromophoric group, the molecular weight of the infrared
absorber having two or more chromophoric groups is larger and, as a
result, scattering by ablation due to heat generation at a time of
exposure can be inhibited.</p><p num="0025">The chromophoric groups represented by D are preferably
bonded by covalent bonds. Since the chromophoric groups bonded
by covalent bonds are not dissociated even after being dissolved in a
solvent of a coating liquid for forming a recording layer, an increase
of distance between the chromophoric groups, by salt exchange with
other salt compounds in the coating liquid, does not occur. This
brings about the advantage that the effect of the chromophoric
groups does not diminish when a recording layer of a planographic
printing original plate is formed from the image-forming material.</p><p num="0026">A fifth aspect of the present invention is a planographic
printing original plate comprising a substrate, and a recording layer
provided on the substrate, the recording layer containing an image-forming 
material according to any one of the above-mentioned 1st to
4th aspects.</p><heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENST</heading><p num="0027">The present invention is explained in detail below.</p><heading>A. Image-forming material</heading><p num="0028">The image-forming material of the present invention is
characterized in that it contains at least an infrared absorber having in
a molecule thereof at least two chromophoric groups, each of which
can absorb the infrared radiation and is bonded to other portion of
the molecule bonded by the covalent bonds.</p><heading>-Infrared absorbers-</heading><p num="0029">The infrared absorber for use in the present invention is
characterized in that it has in a same molecule thereof at least two
chromophoric groups and each of the chromophoric group is bonded
to another portion of the molecule.</p><p num="0030">The infrared absorber is preferably an infrared absorber
represented by the general formula (I).
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">General formula (I)<st32:break type="required" />
(D)<st32:sub pos="post">n</st32:sub>-A</st32:df>
wherein A represents an organic group having a valency of at least 2;
n represents an integer of at least 2; and D represents a chromophoric
group having absorption in an infrared region, wherein one of the
chromophoric groups may be the same as and may be different from
another of the chromophoric groups; and, in a case where the 
chromophoric group has an electric charge, an ion having an electric
charge opposite to the electric charge of the chromophoric group may
be present in order to neutralize the electric charge of the
chromophoric group.</p><p num="0031">Although the chromophoric groups represented by D may be
the same or different, an infrared absorber whose chromophoric
groups have the same structure can be more easily prepared from the
standpoint of synthesis.</p><p num="0032">Similarly to an infrared absorber contained in a conventional
recording material capable of forming an image by exposure to the
infrared region, the function of the infrared absorber contained in the
image-forming material of the present invention is to generate heat by
infrared exposure so that recording is made by the heat thus
generated. For this reason, the image-forming material of the
present invention needs to contain an infrared absorber capable of
efficiently converting light of an infrared laser into heat. The
chromophoric groups of the infrared absorber to be used herein have
absorption in an infrared region. More specifically, the
chromophoric groups have absorption in a region ranging from 720
nm to 1200 nm and preferably have absorption peaks in the region
ranging from 720 nm to 1200 nm.</p><p num="0033">The infrared absorber having in the same molecule thereof
two or more chromophoric groups is explained in detail by specific
examples thereof. In the following exemplary compounds (IR-1)~(IR-51),
basic skeletons, organic groups (expressed as A<sup>1</sup>~A<sup>12</sup>) 
which each correspond to A, which functions as a linking group in
the formula (I), substituents (expressed as R<sup>1</sup>~R<sup>4</sup>) which are each
present in a chromophoric group, and counter ions X<sup>-</sup> due to an
electric charge borne by the chromophoric groups are indicated
specifically. However, it should be noted that the present
invention is not limited to these compounds. <img file="00120001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00120001" he="47" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00120002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00120002" he="134" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00130001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00130001" he="53" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00130002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00130002" he="71" wi="166" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00140001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00140001" he="53" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00140002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00140002" he="85" wi="168" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00140003.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00140003" he="52" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00140004.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00140004" he="43" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00150001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00150001" he="40" wi="103" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00150002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00150002" he="47" wi="170" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00150003.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00150003" he="52" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00150004.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00150004" he="43" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00160001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00160001" he="45" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00160002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00160002" he="43" wi="170" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00160003.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00160003" he="35" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00160004.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00160004" he="62" wi="169" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00170001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00170001" he="68" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00170002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00170002" he="48" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00170003.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00170003" he="78" wi="122" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00170004.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00170004" he="46" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00180001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00180001" he="70" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00180002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00180002" he="69" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00190001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00190001" he="77" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00190002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00190002" he="93" wi="167" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00200001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00200001" he="64" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00200002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00200002" he="40" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><p num="0034">Of these compounds, although synthesis of exemplary
compounds (IR-1)~(IR-49), whose two chromophoric groups are the
same, is easy, the chromophoric groups may be different from each
other, as shown in exemplary compounds (IR-50)~(IR-51).</p><p num="0035">Next, a method of making the infrared absorbers described
above is explained.</p><p num="0036">The infrared absorbers represented by the general formula (I)
can be prepared according to conventionally known techniques of
organic synthesis. More specifically, synthesis can be carried out
according to a synthesis method described, for example, in <ref type="patent">JP-A No.
8-95197</ref> and <ref type="patent">Japanese Patent No. 2758136</ref>. In cases where the
organic group (A) has a valency of 3 or more, it is not necessary that
all link sites are linked to dye portions, and a mixture of compounds
having 2 or more linked dye portions can be used.</p><p num="0037">The infrared absorber may be added to the image-forming
material such that the infrared absorber is added together with other
components to the image-forming layer. Alternatively, the infrared
absorber may be added to a layer that is formed when a planographic
printing original plate is prepared other than the recording layer.</p><p num="0038">In the present invention, the amount to be added of the
infrared absorber is 0.01 to 50% by weight, preferably 0.1 to 20% by
weight, and more preferably 0.5 to 15% by weight, based on weight of
total solids of the image-forming material. If the amount added is
less than 0.01% by weight, the image-forming performance becomes
worse, whereas if the amount added is more than 50% by weight, 
non-image portions may be smudged when the material is used as
the recording layer of the planographic printing original plate.</p><p num="0039">In addition to the infrared absorber, the image-forming
material of the present invention may contain a pigment or dye
capable of absorbing infrared radiation, in order to improve the
image-forming performance.</p><p num="0040">Pigments suitable for use in the present invention may be
commercially available pigments and the pigments described in
<ref type="npl">&quot;Color Index (C.I.) Handbook&quot;, &quot;Latest Pigment Handbook&quot; (Saishin
Ganryo Binran, edited by Japan Association of Pigment Technologies
(Nihon Ganryo Gijutsu Kyokai, 1977)</ref>, <ref type="npl">&quot;Latest Pigment Application
Technologies&quot; (Saishin Ganryo Oyo Gijutsu, CMC, 1986)</ref>, and
<ref type="npl">&quot;Printing Ink Technologies&quot; (Insatsu Inki Gijutsu, CMC, 1984)</ref>.</p><p num="0041">Examples of kinds of pigment include black pigments, yellow
pigments, orange pigments, brown pigments, red pigments, purple
pigments, blue pigments, green pigments, fluorescent pigments,
metal powder pigments, and polymers containing chemically
combined dyes. Specific examples of the pigments are insoluble azo
pigments, azo lake pigments, condensed azo pigments, chelated azo
pigments, phthalocyanine based pigments, anthraquinone based
pigments, perylene and perinone based pigments, thioindigo based
pigments, quinacridone based pigments, dioxazine based pigments,
isoindolinone based pigments, quinophthalone based pigments, dyed
lake pigments, azine pigments, nitroso pigments, nitro pigments,
natural pigments, fluorescent pigments, inorganic pigments, carbon 
black, and the like.</p><p num="0042">These pigments may be used without being surface-treated or
may be used after being surface-treated. Possible surface treatments
include a treatment wherein a resin or a wax is coated on the surface
of the pigment, a treatment wherein a surfactant is adhered to the
surface of pigment particles, and a treatment wherein a reactive
substance (e.g., a silane coupling agent, an epoxy compound, or a
polyisocyanate) is bound to the surface of the pigment particles.
These surface-treating methods are described in <ref type="npl">&quot;Properties and
Applications of Metal Soaps&quot; (Sachi Shobo Co., Ltd.)</ref>, <ref type="npl">&quot;Printing Ink
Technologies&quot; (Insatsu Inki Gijutsu, CMC, 1984)</ref>, and <ref type="npl">&quot;Latest Pigment
Application Technologies&quot; (Saishin Ganryo Oyo Gijutsu, CMC, 1986)</ref>.</p><p num="0043">The diameter of the pigment particles is preferably in the
range of 0.01 to 10 µm, more preferably in the range of 0.05 to 1 µm,
and most preferably in the range of 0.1 to 1 µm. If the diameter is
less than 0.01 µm, stability of a dispersion in a coating liquid for
forming the recording layer is insufficient, whereas if the diameter is
greater than 10 µm, uniformity of the photosensitive layer is poor.</p><p num="0044">A known dispersing technology employed in the preparation
of ink, toners, and the like can also be used for the purpose of
dispersing the pigment. Examples of a dispersing machine include
an ultrasonic dispersing machine, a sand mill, an attritor, a pearl mill,
a super mill, a ball mill, an impeller, a disperser, a KD mill, a colloid
mill, a dynatron, a three-roller mill, a pressurized kneader, and the
like. Details of these dispersing technologies are described in 
<ref type="npl">&quot;Latest Pigment Application Technologies&quot; (Saishin Ganryo Oyo
Gijutsu, CMC, 1986)</ref>.</p><p num="0045">Dyes suitable for use in the present invention are
commercially available dyes and the dyes described in <ref type="npl">&quot;Handbook of
Dyes&quot;, (edited by Association of Organic Synthetic Chemistry (Yuki
Gosei Kagaku Kyokai), 1970)</ref>. Specific examples of the dyes include
azo dyes, azo dyes in the form of a metallic complex salt, pyrazolone
azo dyes, anthraquinone dyes, phthalocyanine dyes, carbonium dyes,
quinoneimine dyes, methine dyes, cyanine dyes, diimmonium dyes,
and aminium dyes.</p><p num="0046">Of these pigments and dyes, pigments and dyes which absorb
infrared or near-infrared rays are particularly preferable for use in the
present invention because of suitability for use in combination with a
laser emitting infrared or near-infrared rays.</p><p num="0047">A pigment which absorbs infrared or near-infrared rays and is
suited for use in the present invention is carbon black. Examples of
dyes which absorb infrared or near-infrared rays and are suited for
use in the present invention include cyanine dyes described in, e.g.,
<ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 58-125246, 59-84356, 59-202829, and 60-78787</ref>; methine dyes
described in, e.g., <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 58-173696, 58-181690 and 58-194595</ref>;
naphthoquinone dyes described in, e.g., <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 58-112793, 58-224793,
59-48187, 59-73996, 60-52940, and 60-63744</ref>; squarylium dyes
described in, e.g., <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 58-112792</ref>; cyanine dyes described in <ref type="patent">U. K.
Patent No. 434,875</ref>; and dihydropyrimidinesquarylium dyes
described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 5,380,635</ref>. </p><p num="0048">Another compound suitable as a dye is a near-infrared ray
absorbing sensitizer described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 5,156,938</ref>. Also
particularly suitable are a substituted arylbenzo(thio)pyrylium salt
described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 3,881,924</ref>; a trimethinethiopyrylium salt
described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 57-142645</ref> (<ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 4,327,169</ref>);
pyrylium-based compounds described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 58-181051, 58-220143,
59-41363, 59-84248, 59-84249, 59-146063, and 59-146061</ref>; a
cyanine dye described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 59-216146</ref>; a
pentamethinethiopyrylium salt described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No.
4,283,475</ref>; pyrylium compounds described in <ref type="patent">Japanese Patent
Application Publication (JP-B) Nos. 5-13514 and 5-19702</ref>, EPOLIGHT™
III-178, EPOLIGHT™ III-130, EPOLIGHT™ III-125, and EPOLIGHT™ IV-62A
(all manufactured by Epolin Corp.) as commercially available
products; and the like.</p><p num="0049">Further examples of particularly preferred dyes are the near-infrared
absorbing dyes described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 4,756,993</ref> as
formulae (I) and (II).</p><p num="0050">Since these pigments or dyes are used in combination with the
specific infrared absorbers described previously, if a pigment or dye
is added, the amount to be added of the pigment or dye is preferably
0.01 to 20% by weight based on the weight of the total solids of the
image-forming material. If a dye is added, the amount of the dye is
particularly preferably 0.5 to 10% by weight. If a pigment is added,
the amount of the pigment is particularly preferably 0.1 to 5% by
weight. If the amount to be added of the pigment or dye is less than 
0.01 % by weight, the effect of addition of the pigment or dye cannot
be observed. On the other hand, if the amount to be added is more
than 20% by weight, the effect of raising sensitivity by the specific
infrared absorbers described previously may be adversely affected.</p><heading>- Components other than infrared absorbers -</heading><p num="0051">As other components of the image-forming material of the
present invention, components of various conventionally known
image-forming materials recordable by radiation in the infrared
region can be appropriately selected for use.</p><p num="0052">Of the image-forming materials whose solubility in an
aqueous alkaline solution is changed by infrared exposure, and
image-forming materials whose hydrophilicity and hydrophobicity
are changed by infrared exposure, there are two types; namely a
negative-type image-forming material whose developability is
lowered by exposure to infrared radiation, and a positive-type image-forming
material whose developability is raised by exposure to
infrared radiation.</p><p num="0053">Examples of the negative-type image-forming material include
a conventionally known negative-type polarity switchable material
(i.e., conversion from hydrophilicity to hydrophobicity), a radical-polymerizable
material, and an acid catalyst-crosslinkable material
(including cationic polymerization). Of these types, the radical-polymerizable
material and the acid catalyst-crosslinkable material
are preferable in view of plate life. In these materials, the radical or
acid to be generated by irradiation with light or heating becomes an 
initiator or catalyst which causes the compound constituting the
image-forming material to polymerize or crosslink so that image
portions are formed. In the materials, the sensitivity and other
properties of the material can be improved by a combination thereof
with the infrared absorber described previously.</p><p num="0054">Examples of the positive-type image-forming material include
a conventionally known positive-type polarity switchable material
(i.e., conversion from hydrophobicity to hydrophilicity), an acid
catalyst-decomposable material, and an interaction-breakable
material (heat-sensitive positive-type). Of these types, a positive-type,
polarity switchable material based on thermal decomposition of
a sulfonic ester, the acid catalyst-decomposable material, and the
interaction-breakable material are preferable in view of image quality.
In these materials, acid or thermal energy to be generated by
irradiation with light or heat breaks a bond of a layer-constituting
polymeric compound. As a result, the polymeric compound
becomes soluble in water or in an aqueous alkaline solution such that
the polymeric compound is removed by development processing and
non-image portions are formed. In these materials, the sensitivity
and other properties of the material can be improved by a
combination thereof with the infrared absorber described previously.</p><p num="0055">First, of the image-forming materials of the present invention,
details of the negative-type image-forming material are given below.</p><heading>&lt;Radical-polymerizable image-forming materials&gt;</heading><p num="0056">The radical-polymerizable image-forming material that can be 
used in the recording material of the planographic printing original
plate of the present invention contains, besides the infrared absorbers,
a compound that generates radicals by light or heat (this compound is
hereinafter referred to as a radical generator) and a compound
capable of undergoing radical polymerization (this compound is
hereinafter referred to as a polymerizable compound). For example,
infrared laser irradiation generates radicals from the radical generator
at portions exposed to the radiation and the radicals act as initiators
for the polymerizable compound, to cause radical polymerization and
to cure so that image portions are produced. Addition of the
specific infrared absorbers described previously to such radical-polymerizable
image-forming materials makes it possible to raise
sensitivity or to accelerate radical polymerization. A combination of
the radical generator and the polymerizable compound may be
appropriately selected from conventionally known combinations, as
long as the strength of a film produced by the radical polymerization
meets the requirements for the image recording layer. In addition,
in order to enhance reactivity of the radical generator, an accelerator
such as an onium salt, a reducing agent, or the like may be used
together therewith. Also preferred as components usable in the
radical-polymerizable image-forming material are, for example,
components listed as constituent components of a thermally
polymerizable recording layer described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 8-108621</ref> and
components listed as constituent components of a recording layer
described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 9-34110</ref>. </p><heading>(Radical generators)</heading><p num="0057">Known radical polymerization initiators that are in common
use for polymer synthesis reactions by radical polymerization can be
used without particular limitations as the radical generator for use in
the radical-polymerizable image-forming material. Examples of the
radical generator include azobisnitrile compounds such as 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile
and 2,2'-azobispropionitrile; organic peroxides
such as benzoyl peroxide, lauroyl peroxide, acetyl peroxide, t-butyl
perbenzoate, α-cumyl hydroperoxide, di-t-butyl peroxide,
diisopropylperoxy dicarbonate, t-butylperoxyisopropyl carbonate,
peroxy acids, alkylperoxy carbamates, and nitrosoarylacylamines;
inorganic peroxides such as potassium persulfate, ammonium
persulfate, and potassium perchlorate; azo or diazo compounds such
as diazo aminobenzene, p-nitrobenzene diazonium, azobis-substituted
alkanes, diazo thioethers, and arylazo sulfones;
nitrosophenylurea; tetraalkylthiuram disulfides such as
tetramethylthiuram disulfides; diaryl disulfides such as dibenzoyl
disulfide; dialkylxanthogenic acid disulfide; arylsulfinic acids;
arylalkylsulfonic acids; 1-alkanesulfinic acids; and the like.</p><p num="0058">When the planographic printing original plate, which has a
recording layer comprising the image-forming material containing
the infrared absorber for use in the present invention, is recorded on
with an infrared laser, sufficient sensitivity can be obtained even if a
radical generator whose activation energy is large is used, because the
temperature of the surface exposed to light reaches as high as 600°C 
or above (though the temperature depends on the energy of the
laser).</p><p num="0059">The activation energy for the radical generator to generate the
radical is preferably 125,5 KJ/mol (30 Kcal/mol) or more. Examples of such kinds
of radical generators include azobisnitrile compounds and organic
peroxides. Of these, preferred are compounds which have excellent
stability at room temperature, exhibit a high decomposition rate
when heated, and become colorless when decomposed. These
compounds are, for example, benzoyl peroxide, 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile,
and the like.</p><p num="0060">The radical generators may be used singly or in a combination
of two or more. The radical generator is used in an amount of 0.5-30%
by weight, preferably 2-10% by weight, based on the total weight
of solid components of the radical-polymerizable image-forming
material.</p><p num="0061">In addition, a compound that generates a radical by the
interaction with an onium salt, which is described later, can also be
suitably used. Specific examples of the compound include halides
(e.g., α-haloacetophenones, trichloromethyltriazines, and the like),
azo compounds, aromatic carbonyl compounds (e.g., benzoin esters,
ketals, acetophenones, o-acyloxyiminoketones, acylphosphine oxides,
and the like), hexaarylbisimidazole compounds, peroxides, and so on.
Preferred among these compounds are the bisimidazole compounds
disclosed as (A-1)~ (A-4) on page 16 of <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 9-34110</ref>.</p><p num="0062">This type of radical generator raises the sensitivity by 
interaction with an onium salt. Examples of the onium salt that can
be used in combination with the radical generator include
phosphonium salts, sulfonium salts, iodonium salts, and ammonium
salts described in paragraphs [0022]~[0049] of the above-cited patent
literature.</p><p num="0063">The amount to be added of the onium salt is 0.05-50% by
weight based on the total weight of the solid components of the
image-forming material, though the amount varies with the kinds
and states of the onium salt in use.</p><p num="0064">Onium salts, such as iodonium salts, sulfonium salts,
phosphonium salts, and diazonium salts, suitably usable as acid-generating
agents listed in the acid-crosslinking agents described
later, can be used singly as radical generators without being used in
combination with the radical generators described above. An
amount to be used of such onium salts is preferably 0.05-50% by
weight based on the total weight of the solid components of the
image-forming material, though the amount varies depending on the
kind and state of the onium salt to be used.</p><heading>(Polymerizable compounds)</heading><p num="0065">Conventionally known monomers having a polymerizable
group may be used without particular limitation as the polymerizable
polymeric compound that is polymerized and cured by the radical
generated from the radical generator. Specific examples of such
monomers include monofunctional acrylate esters, such as 2-ethylhexyl
acrylate, 2-hydroxyethyl acrylate, 2-hydroxypropyl 
acrylate, derivatives thereof, and compounds in which the acrylate is
replaced by methacrylate, itaconate, crotonate, maleate, or the like;
difunctional acrylate esters, such as polyethylene glycol diacrylate,
pentaerythritol diacrylate, bisphenol A diacrylate, diacrylate of ε-caprolactam
addition product of neopentyl glycol hydroxypivalate,
derivatives thereof, and compounds in which the acrylate is replaced
by methacrylate or the like as described above; and polyfunctional
acrylate esters, such as trimethylolpropane tri(meth)acrylate,
dipentaerythritol pentaacrylate, dipentaerythritol hexaacrylate,
pyrogallol triacrylate, derivatives thereof, and compounds in which
the acrylate is replaced by methacrylate or the like. Also suitably
used is a so-called prepolymer prepared by introducing acrylic acid
or methacrylic acid into an oligomer having a proper molecular
weight such that a photopolymerizable property is imparted.</p><p num="0066">Other examples include the compounds described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos.
58-212994, 61-6649, 62-46688, 62-48589, 62-173295, 62-187092, 63-67189,
and 1-244891</ref>. In addition, compounds which are described in
<ref type="npl">&quot;11290 Chemical Products&quot; (Kagaku Kogyo Nippou Co., Ltd.),
pp.286-289</ref> and compounds which are described in <ref type="npl">&quot;UV•EB Curing
Handbook (materials)&quot; (Koubunshi Kankoukai), pp.11-65</ref> can be
suitably used.</p><p num="0067">Among these compounds, compounds which have in the
molecule thereof two or more acryl or methacryl groups, are
preferable in the present invention. Desirably, these compounds
have a molecular weight of 10,000 or less and more preferably 5,000 
or less. In accordance with purpose, a single polymerizable
compound or a combination of two or more kinds of polymerizable
compound may be selected from the monomers and prepolymers
each having a polymerizable group, including those previously
illustrated, provided that the combination is free from any
compatibility or affinity problem, and can be used in the present
invention.</p><p num="0068">A compound having an ethylenically unsaturated group, in an
amount of preferably 20-80% by weight, more preferably 30-60% by
weight, based on the total weight of the solid components of the
image-forming material, is incorporated in the image-forming
material.</p><heading>(Binder resins)</heading><p num="0069">If necessary, a binder resin may be used in the radical-polymerizable
image-forming material. Examples of the binder
resin include polyester resins, polyvinyl acetal resins, polyurethane
resins, polyamide resins, cellulosic resins, olefinic resins, polyvinyl
chloride resins, (meth)acrylic resins, styrenic resins, polycarbonate,
polyvinyl alcohol, polyvinylpyrrolidone, polysulfone,
polycaprolacton resins, polyacrylonitrile resins, urea resins, epoxy
resins, phenoxy resins, rubber-based resins, and the like. In addition,
a resin which has in the molecule thereof an unsaturated bond, for
example, a diallyl phthalate resin or a derivative thereof or
chlorinated polypropylene, can be polymerized with the above-described
compound having an ethylenically unsaturated group and 
therefore can be suitably used, depending on applications. Resins
selected from the above-listed resins may be used singly or in a
combination as a binder resin.</p><p num="0070">The amount to be used of the binder resin is preferably 500
parts by weight or less, more preferably 200 parts by weight or less,
based on 100 parts by weight of the polymerizable compound.</p><heading>(Other compounds)</heading><p num="0071">The radical-polymerizable image-forming material may
contain conventionally known additives which are used together
with conventionally known photopolymerizable compounds, as long
as the effects of the present invention are not impaired.</p><p num="0072">An example of the additives is a thermal polymerization
inhibitor. Specific examples of the thermal polymerization inhibitor
include quinone and phenolic compounds such as hydroquinone,
pyrogallol, p-methoxyphenol, catechol, β -naphthol, 2,6-di-t-butyl-p-cresol,
and the like. These additives are used in an amount of less
than 10 parts by weight, preferably 0.01-5 parts by weight, per
100 parts by weight of the total of the polymerizable compound
having an ethylenically unsaturated bond and the binder resin.</p><p num="0073">Compounds that may be added as an oxygen quencher are
N,N-dialkylaniline derivatives such as the compounds described in
column 11, line 58 through column 12, line 35, of <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No.
4,772,541</ref>.</p><p num="0074">In addition, a plasticizer may be used in order to improve film
properties. Examples of the plasticizer include phthalic acid esters, 
trimellitic acid esters, adipic acid esters, saturated or unsaturated
carboxylic acid esters, citric acid esters, epoxidized soybean oil,
epoxidized linseed oil, stearic acid epoxides, orthophosphoric acid
esters, phosphorous acid esters, glycol esters, and so on.</p><p num="0075">An acid-generating agent is also preferably used in
combination as an additive which, when heated, generates an acid
and thus accelerates the decomposition of the radical generator.
Acid-generating agents, described in detail in the following
explanation of the acid-crosslinkable image-forming material, can be
used.</p><p num="0076">The above-described components, which are appropriately
selected, are dissolved in a suitable solvent and the resulting solution
is coated on a substrate so as to form a recording layer. The coating
weight after drying is preferably 0.01 to 5.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p><heading>&lt;Acid-crosslinkable image-forming material&gt;</heading><p num="0077">The acid-crosslinkable image-forming material of the present
invention contains, besides the infrared absorber, a compound which
generates an acid by the action of light or heat (this compound is
hereinafter referred to as an acid-generating agent), a compound
which can crosslink by catalytic action of the generated acid (this
compound is hereinafter referred to as a crosslinking agent), and a
binder polymer which can react with the crosslinking agent in the
presence of the acid to form a layer containing these compounds. In
the acid-crosslinkable image-forming material, light irradiation or
heating decomposes the acid-generating agent and causes the agent 
to generate an acid which accelerates the activity of the crosslinking
agent. Consequently, a strong crosslinked structure is formed
between the crosslinking agents themselves or between the
crosslinking agent and the binder polymer, which structure lowers
the alkali solubility of the material such that the material becomes
insoluble in a developing solution. The sensitivity of the material
can be raised by the addition of the infrared absorber.</p><p num="0078">Examples of components of the acid-crosslinkable image-forming
material having the above-described characteristics include
components of conventionally known image-forming materials such
as an image-forming material composed of a radiation-sensitive
composition described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 7-20629</ref>, which contains a resol
resin, a novolak resin, a latent Broensted acid, and an infrared
absorber. The term &quot;a latent Broensted acid&quot; as used herein means a
precursor which, when decomposed, produces a Broensted acid and
which is a compound having the characteristics of both the acid-generating
agent and the acid-crosslinking agent in the present
invention. The Broensted acid is believed to catalyze a matrix-forming
reaction between the resol resin and the novolak resin.
Examples of Broensted acids suitable to this purpose are
trifluoromethanesulfonic acid and hexafluorophosphonic acid.</p><p num="0079">In addition, an ionic latent Broensted acid is preferred.
Examples of such acids include onium salts, particularly iodonium
salts, sulfonium salts, phosphonium salts, selenonium salts,
diazonium salts, and arsonium salts. A nonionic latent Broensted 
acid can also be suitably used. Examples of such acids include the
following compounds: RCH<sub>2</sub>X, RCHX<sub>2</sub>, RCX<sub>3</sub>, R(CH<sub>2</sub>X)<sub>2</sub>, and
R(CH<sub>2</sub>X)<sub>3</sub> (where X is Cl, Br, F, CF<sub>3</sub>, or SO<sub>3</sub>; and R is an aromatic
group, an aliphatic group, or a group consisting of a combination of
an aromatic group and an aliphatic group).</p><p num="0080">In addition, an image-forming material described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No.
11-95415</ref>, which contains an acid-crosslinkable compound and a high-molecular-weight
binder, is also suitable as a component of the acid-crosslinkable
image-forming material. This material is an image-forming
material containing a compound, which, when irradiated
with active radiation, can generate an acid (for example, a salt, such
as a diazonium, a phosphonium, a sulfonium, an iodonium or the like,
an organohalogen compound, an ortho-quinonediazide
sulfonylchloride, or an organometal/organohalogen compound)
together with a compound which has at least one bond capable of
crosslinking in the presence of the above-mentioned acid (for
example, an amino compound having as a functional group at least
two of such groups as an alkoxymethyl group, a methylol group, an
acetoxymethyl group, and the like; an aromatic compound which is at
least di-substituted and has as a functional group an alkoxymethyl
group, a methylol group, an acetoxymethyl group, or the like; resol
resin; a furan resin; an acrylic resin synthesized from a specific
monomer; or the like). This material can be used as a component of
the image-forming material of the present invention.</p><p num="0081">Next, the acid-generating agent, crosslinking agent, binder 
polymer, and others, which are components other than the infrared
absorber of the acid-crosslinkable image-forming material of the
present invention, are explained, respectively.</p><heading>(Acid-generating agents)</heading><p num="0082">In the present invention, a compound that generates an acid
by light or heat (i.e., an acid-generating agent) denotes a compound
which is decomposed by infrared irradiation or by heating to 100°C
or a higher temperature and generates an acid. The acid to be
generated is preferably a strong acid having a pKa of 2 or less, such as
sulfonic acid or hydrochloric acid.</p><p num="0083">Onium salts such as iodonium salts, sulfonium salts,
phosphonium salts, and diazonium salts are some examples of acid-generating
agents preferably used in the present invention.
Specifically, the compounds described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 4,708,925</ref>
and <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 7-20629</ref> may be used. Particularly, iodonium salts,
sulfonium salts, and diazonium salts - all of which contain a
sulfonate ion as a counter ion - are preferred. As to the diazonium
salts, a diazonium compound described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 3,867,147</ref>,
a diazonium compound described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent No. 2,632,703</ref>, and
diazo resins described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 1-102456 and 1-102457</ref> are also
preferable. Examples of other preferable acid-generating agents
include benzyl sulfonates described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent Nos. 5,135,838 and
5,200,544</ref>; active sulfonic esters and disulfonyl compounds described
in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 2-100054, 2-100055 and 9-197671</ref>; and haloalkyl-substituted
s-triazines described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 7-271029</ref>. </p><p num="0084">These acid-generating agents, in an amount of 0.01-50% by
weight, preferably 0.1-40% by weight, and more preferably 0.5-30%
by weight based on the total weight of the solid components of the
image-forming material, are added to the image-forming material. If
the amount of the acid-generating agent is less than 0.01% by weight,
images cannot be obtained, and if the amount is more than 50% by
weight, stains are undesirably generated in non-image portions
during printing.</p><p num="0085">These compounds may be used singly or in a combination of
two or more. Moreover, because the above-listed acid-generating
agents can also be decomposed by ultraviolet irradiation, image
recording can be carried out not only by infrared irradiation but also
by ultraviolet irradiation if an image-forming material of the above-described
mode is used.</p><heading>(Acid-crosslinking agents)</heading><p num="0086">The crosslinking agent that can be used in the acid-crosslinkable
image-forming material of the present invention is not
particularly limited in so far as the crosslinking agent is a compound
which crosslinks by an acid. Preferred examples of the crosslinking
agent include phenol derivatives represented by the following
general formula (CA-I) (these derivatives are hereinafter occasionally
referred to as low-molecular-weight phenol derivatives), polynuclear
phenolic crosslinking agents represented by the following general
formula (CA-II) and having in the molecules thereof three or more
phenol rings each having two or three hydroxymethyl groups on the 
ring, mixtures of the low-molecular-weight phenol derivative and the
polynuclear phenolic crosslinking agent and/or a resol resin.
<img file="00400001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00400001" he="45" wi="75" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" />
Y:
<img file="00400002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00400002" he="27" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00400003.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00400003" he="34" wi="145" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00400004.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00400004" he="25" wi="80" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00400005.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00400005" he="35" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><p num="0087">In the formula, Ar<sup>1</sup> represents an aromatic hydrocarbon ring
which may have a substituent. R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> may be the same or
different, and respectively represent a hydrogen atom or a 
hydrocarbon group having 12 or less carbon atoms. R<sup>3</sup> represents a
hydrogen atom or a hydrocarbon group having 12 or less carbon
atoms. m represents an integer from 2 to 4. n represents an integer
from 1 to 3. X represents a bivalent linking group; Y represents a
monovalent functional group or bi- to quadrivalent linking group
having the above-illustrated partial structure, or a functional group
having the above-illustrated partial structure endstopped with a one
or more hydrogen atoms; Z is absent if Y is a terminal group, and
represents a mono- to quadrivalent functional group which is present
in accordance with the valency of the linking group Y.
<img file="00410001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00410001" he="55" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><p num="0088">In the formula, A represents a hydrocarbon linking group
having 1 to 20 carbon atoms and a valency of r; and r represents an
integer from 3 to 20. p represents an integer from 2 to 3.</p><p num="0089">The details of the phenol derivative represented by the general
formula (CA-I) are described in paragraphs [0098]~[0155] of the
specification of <ref type="patent">Japanese Patent Application No. 11-352210</ref> filed by
the present applicant. The details of the polynuclear phenolic
crosslinking agents, represented by the general formula (CA-II) and
having in the molecules thereof three or more phenol rings each 
having two or three hydroxymethyl groups on the ring, are also
described in paragraphs [0156]~[0165] of the specification of <ref type="patent">Japanese
Patent Application No. 11-352210</ref> filed by the present applicant.</p><p num="0090">These crosslinking agents may be used singly or in a
combination of two or more.</p><p num="0091">In the present invention, the crosslinking agent is added in an
amount of 5-70% by weight, preferably 10-65% by weight, based on
the total weight of the solid components of the acid-crosslinkable
image-forming material. If the amount of the crosslinking agent is
less than 5% by weight, film strength of image portions becomes
inferior when images are recorded, and if the amount is more than
70% by weight, storage stability is adversely affected.</p><heading>(Binder polymers)</heading><p num="0092">Examples of the binder polymer that can be used in the acid-crosslinkable
image-forming material of the present invention include
a polymer having in a side chain or main chain thereof an aromatic
hydrocarbon ring to which a hydroxyl group or an alkoxy group is
directly linked. From the standpoint of sensitivity, the alkoxy group
preferably has 20 or less carbon atoms. From the standpoint of
availability of raw materials, the aromatic hydrocarbon ring is
preferably a benzene ring, a naphthalene ring, or an anthracene ring.
Although these aromatic hydrocarbon rings may have substituents,
such as a halogen group, a cyano group or the like, other than the
hydroxyl group or alkoxy group, these aromatic hydrocarbon rings 
preferably have no substituents of the hydroxyl group or alkoxy
group in view of sensitivity.</p><p num="0093">A binder polymer that can be suitably used in the present
invention is a polymer having a structural unit represented by the
following general formula (Su-I), or a phenolic resin that is a novolak
resin or the like:
<img file="00430001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00430001" he="74" wi="74" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><p num="0094">In the formula, Ar<sup>2</sup> represents a benzene ring, a naphthalene
ring, or an anthracene ring; R<sup>4</sup> represents a hydrogen atom or a
methyl group; R<sup>5</sup> represents a hydrogen atom or an alkoxy group
having 20 or less carbon atoms; X<sup>1</sup> represents either a single bond or a
bivalent linking group which contains at least one atom selected from
C, H, N, O, and S and which has 0 to 20 carbon atoms; and k is an
integer from 1 to 4.</p><p num="0095">The binder polymer for use in the present invention may be a
homopolymer composed solely of the structural unit represented by
general formula (Su-I) or may be a copolymer composed of this
specific structural unit and a structural unit derived from another 
conventionally known monomer.</p><p num="0096">A proportion of the structural unit that is represented by the
general formula (Su-I) and contained in this copolymer is preferably
50-100% by weight and more preferably 60-100% by weight.</p><p num="0097">The weight average molecular weight of the polymer to be
used in the present invention is preferably 5,000 or more, and more
preferably 10,000 to 300,000, while the number average molecular
weight is preferably 1,000 or more and more preferably 2,000 to
250,000. The polydispersity index (weight average molecular
weight/number average molecular weight) is 1 or more and more
preferably falls within the range of 1.1 to 10.</p><p num="0098">Although the polymer may be a random polymer, a block
polymer, a graft polymer, or the like, the polymer is preferably a
random polymer.</p><p num="0099">Next, novolaks are described. Examples of novolak resin that
can be suitably used in the present invention include phenol novolaks,
o-, m-, or p-cresol novolaks, copolymers thereof, and novolaks
utilizing phenols substituted by a halogen atom, an alkyl group or the
like.</p><p num="0100">The weight average molecular weight of the novolak resin is
preferably 1,000 or more, and more preferably 2,000 to 20,000, while
the number average molecular weight is preferably 1,000 or more and
more preferably 2,000 to 15,000. The polydispersity index is 1 or
more and more preferably falls within the range of 1.1 to 10.</p><p num="0101">It is also a preferred mode to use, as the binder polymer, a 
polymer which has a heterocyclic group having an unsaturated bond
in the ring.</p><p num="0102">The term &quot;heterocyclic group&quot; as used herein means a group
which includes one or more heteroatoms other than carbon atoms
among the atoms constituting the ring. Nitrogen, oxygen, sulfur,
and silicon atoms are preferred as the heteroatoms to be used. The
use of a polymer having such a heterocyclic group is believed to
enhance chemical structural reactivity due to functioning of lone
pairs present in the heterocyclic ring, such that a film having superior
plate life is obtainable.</p><p num="0103">The binder polymers described above for use in the present
invention may be used singly or in a combination of two or more.
These polymers are added in an amount of 20-95 % by weight,
preferably 40-90% by weight, based on the total weight of the solid
components of the acid-crosslinkable image-forming material. If the
amount to be added is less than 20% by weight, film strength of
image portions becomes inferior when images are formed, and if the
amount to be added is more than 95% by weight, images are not
formed.</p><p num="0104">Next, of the image-forming materials of the present invention,
the interaction-breakable image-forming material (heat-sensitive
positive), the acid-decomposable image-forming material, and the
polarity switchable image-forming material, which are each a
positive-type, image-forming material, are explained, respectively.</p><heading>&lt;Interaction-breakable image-forming material (heat-sensitive 
positive)&gt;</heading><p num="0105">The interaction-breakable image-forming material comprises,
besides the infrared absorber, a polymer insoluble in water but
soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution.</p><p num="0106">In a case where the infrared absorber has in the molecule a
group, such as an ammonium or iminium group, capable of
interacting with the polymeric compound soluble in an aqueous
alkaline solution, the infrared absorber has, besides a light-to-heat
converting function of being infrared absorber, a function of being
compatibilized with the polymeric compound soluble in an aqueous
alkaline solution such that the solubility of the polymeric compound
in the aqueous alkaline solution is reduced and a function of
diminishing the above-described effect of reducing the solubility
when heated. Accordingly, it is also possible to form an image-forming
material even without the incorporation of a compound that
reduces the solubility of the polymeric compound in the aqueous
alkaline solution.</p><p num="0107">Examples of the polymeric compound soluble in an aqueous
alkaline solution include homopolymers having in the main chain
and/or side chain thereof an acidic group; copolymers thereof; and
mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0108">Among these polymers, a polymer which has in the polymer
main chain and/or side chain thereof any acidic group selected from
the following acidic groups (1)~(6) is preferable from the standpoint
of solubility and inhibition of dissolution in the aqueous alkaline 
solution.
<sl><li>(1) A hydroxyphenyl group (-Ar-OH)</li><li>(2) A sulfonamide group (-SO<sub>2</sub>NH-R)</li><li>(3) A substituted sulfonamide based acidic group (hereinafter
referred to as &quot;active imido group&quot;) (-SO<sub>2</sub>NHCOR,
-SO<sub>2</sub>NHSO<sub>2</sub>R, and -CONHSO<sub>2</sub>R)</li><li>(4) A carboxyl group (-CO<sub>2</sub>H)</li><li>(5) A sulfonic acid group (-SO<sub>3</sub>H)</li><li>(6) A phosphoric acid group (-OPO<sub>3</sub>H<sub>2</sub>)</li></sl></p><p num="0109">In (1)~(6) listed above, Ar represents a bivalent aryl linking
group which may have a substituent, and R represents a hydrocarbon
group which may have a substituent.</p><p num="0110">Of polymers soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution which
have acidic groups selected from (1)~(6) listed above, polymers
soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution which have (1) a phenolic
hydroxyl group, (2) a sulfonamide group, or (3) an active imido
group are preferable; and polymers soluble in an aqueous alkaline
solution which have (1) a phenolic hydroxyl group or (2) sulfonamide
group are particularly preferable from the standpoints of sufficiently
securing solubility in an alkaline developing solution, development
latitude, and film strength.</p><p num="0111">Examples of the polymers soluble in an aqueous alkaline
solution that have acidic groups selected from (1)~(6) include the
following.</p><p num="0112">Examples of (1) the polymer having a phenolic hydroxyl 
group and soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution include novolak
resins, such as a condensation polymerization product from phenol
and formaldehyde, a condensation polymerization product from m-cresol
and formaldehyde, a condensation polymerization product
from p-cresol and formaldehyde, a condensation polymerization
product from a m-cresol/p-cresol mixture and formaldehyde, and a
condensation polymerization product from phenol, cresol (which
may be m-cresol, p-cresol, or a mixture of m-cresol and p-cresol) and
formaldehyde; and a condensation polymerization product from
pyrogallol and acetone; and examples further include copolymers
produced by the copolymerization of compounds having a phenolic
hydroxyl group in the side chain.</p><p num="0113">Examples of compounds having a phenolic hydroxyl group
suited for use in the present invention include phenolic hydroxyl
group-containing acrylamides, methacrylamides, acrylates,
methacrylates, hydroxystyrenes, and the like.</p><p num="0114">From the standpoint of image-forming performance, it is
preferable that the polymer soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution
has a weight average molecular weight of 5.0 × 10<sup>2</sup> to 2.0 × 10<sup>4</sup> and a
number average molecular weight of 2.0 × 10<sup>2</sup> to 1.0 × 10<sup>4</sup>. These
polymers may be used singly or in a combination of two or more.
When these polymers are used in a combination, a condensation
polymerization product from a phenol bearing as a substituent an
alkyl group having 3 to 8 carbon atoms and formaldehyde, such as a
condensation polymerization product from t-butylphenol and 
formaldehyde or a condensation polymerization product from
octylphenol and formaldehyde; or alternatively, a polymer soluble in
an aqueous alkaline solution, which has a phenolic structure
comprising an aromatic ring bearing an electron-withdrawing group
and which is described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 2000-241972</ref> previously filed by
the present inventors, or the like may be used together.</p><p num="0115">Examples of (2) the polymer having a sulfonamide group and
soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution include polymers comprising
as main constituting components the smallest constituting units
derived from, for example, a compound having a sulfonamide group.
Examples of such compounds include compounds which have in the
molecules thereof at least one sulfonamide group having at least one
hydrogen atom linked to a nitrogen atom together with at least one
unsaturated bond capable of polymerizing. Of these compounds,
compounds which have low molecular weight and which have an
acryloyl group, allyl group, or vinyloxy group together with a
substituted or mono-substituted aminosulfonyl group or a
substituted sulfonylimino group are preferable. Examples of these
compounds include the compounds represented by the following
general formula (S-1)~(S-5). <img file="00500001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00500001" he="36" wi="177" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00500002.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00500002" he="37" wi="178" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00500003.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00500003" he="36" wi="178" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00500004.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00500004" he="35" wi="179" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00500005.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00500005" he="37" wi="179" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" />
In the formulae, X<sup>1</sup> and X<sup>2</sup> each independently represents
-O- or -NR<sup>27</sup>-. R<sup>21</sup> and R<sup>24</sup> each independently represents a
hydrogen atom or -CH<sub>3</sub>. R<sup>22</sup>, R<sup>25</sup>, R<sup>29</sup>, R<sup>32</sup> and R<sup>36</sup> each independently
represents an alkylene group, a cycloalkylene group, an arylene
group, or an aralkylene group, each of which groups has 1 to 12
carbon atoms and may have a substituent. R<sup>23</sup>, R<sup>27</sup>, and R<sup>33</sup> each 
independently represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group, a
cycloalkyl group, an aryl group, or an aralkyl group, each of which
groups has 1 to 12 carbon atoms and may have a substituent. R<sup>26</sup>
and R<sup>37</sup> each independently represents an alkyl group, a cycloalkyl
group, an aryl group, or an aralkyl group, each of which groups has 1
to 12 carbon atoms and may have a substituent. R<sup>28</sup>, R<sup>30</sup> and R<sup>34</sup> each
independently represents a hydrogen atom or -CH<sub>3</sub>. R<sup>31</sup> and R<sup>35</sup>
each independently represents a single bond or alternatively an
alkylene group, a cycloalkylene group, an arylene group, or an
aralkylene group, each of which groups has 1 to 12 carbon atoms and
may have a substituent. Y<sup>3</sup> and Y<sup>4</sup> each independently represents a
single bond or -CO-.</p><p num="0116">Among the compounds represented by the formulae (S-1)~(S-5),
m-aminosulfonylphenyl methacrylate, N-(p-aminosulfonylphenyl)methacrylamide,
N-(p-aminosulfonylphenyl)acrylamide,
and the like can be particularly
suitably used as materials for the positive-type planographic plate of
the present invention.</p><p num="0117">Examples of (3) the polymer having an active imido group and
soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution include polymers comprising
as main constituting components the smallest constituting units
derived from, for example, a compound having an active imido
group. Examples of such compound include a compound which has
in the molecule thereof at least one active imido group represented by
the formula given below together with at least one unsaturated bond 
capable of polymerizing.
<img file="00520001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00520001" he="35" wi="64" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><p num="0118">More specifically, N-(p-toluenesulfonyl)methacrylamide, N-(p-toluenesulfonyl)acrylamide,
and the like can be suitably used.</p><p num="0119">Examples of (4) the polymer having a carboxyl group and
soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution include polymers comprising
as main constituting components the smallest constituting units
derived from, for example, a compound having in the molecule
thereof at least one carboxyl group and at least one unsaturated bond
capable of polymerizing.</p><p num="0120">Examples of (5) the polymer having a sulfonic acid group and
soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution include polymers comprising
as main constituting components the smallest constituting units
derived from, for example, a compound having in the molecule
thereof at least one sulfonic acid group and at least one unsaturated
bond capable of polymerizing.</p><p num="0121">Examples of (6) the polymer having a phosphoric acid group
and soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution include polymers
comprising as main constituting components the smallest constituting
units derived from, for example, a compound having in the molecule
thereof at least one phosphoric acid group and at least one 
unsaturated bond capable of polymerizing.</p><p num="0122">The smallest constituting units, which have the acidic groups
selected from (1)~(6) listed above and make up the polymers soluble
in an aqueous alkaline solution, do not necessarily need to be of the
same kind. Therefore, a polymer which is made by copolymerizing
two or more kinds of the smallest constituting units each having the
same acidic group, or a polymer which is made by copolymerizing
two or more kinds of the smallest constituting units each having
different acidic groups, can also be used.</p><p num="0123">The copolymer described above contains preferably 10 mol%
or more, and more preferably 20 mol% or more, of a compound
which is to be copolymerized and has an acidic group selected from
(1)~(6) listed above in the copolymer. If the content is less than 10
mol%, the development latitude may not be sufficiently improved.</p><heading>&lt;Acid-decomposable image-forming material&gt;</heading><p num="0124">The acid-decomposable image-forming material comprises,
besides the infrared absorber, a compound which generates an acid
by the action of light or heat (i.e., an acid-generating agent), and a
compound whose chemical bond is severed by the generated acid
acting as a catalyst and thereby increases solubility in alkaline
developing solution (an acid-decomposable compound).</p><p num="0125">The acid-decomposable image-forming material may further
contain a polymeric compound as a binder component.
Alternatively, the acid-decomposable compound itself may be a
polymeric compound or a precursor thereof functioning as the binder 
component. The acid-generating agent and the binder component
may be those described in the explanation of the acid-crosslinkable
image-forming material.</p><heading>(Acid-decomposable compound)</heading><p num="0126">In the present invention, the compound whose chemical bond
is severed by an acid acting as a catalyst and thereby increases
solubility in the alkaline developing solution, is, in other words, a
compound having in the molecule thereof a bond decomposable by
an acid. Such a compound may be the compound described as &quot;(b)
a compound having at least one acid-decomposable bond&quot; in <ref type="patent">JP-A No.
9-171254</ref>. Preferred examples of the acid-decomposable bond
include a -(CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>n</sub>- group (where n is an integer from 2 to 5).</p><p num="0127">Among these compounds, use of a compound represented by
the following general formula (AD-I) is preferable from the
standpoint of sensitivity and developability.
<img file="00540001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00540001" he="45" wi="170" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><p num="0128">In the formula, R, R<sup>1</sup>, and R<sup>2</sup> each represents a hydrogen atom,
an alkyl group having 1 to 5 carbon atoms, an alkoxy group having 1
to 5 carbon atoms, a sulfo group, a carboxyl group, or a hydroxyl
group; p, q, and r each represents an integer from 1 to 3; and m and n
each represents an integer from 1 to 5. </p><p num="0129">In the general formula (AD-I), the alkyl group represented by
R, R<sup>1</sup>, or R<sup>2</sup> may be a straight-chain or branched alkyl group.
Examples of the alkyl group include a methyl group, an ethyl group,
a propyl group, an isopropyl group, a butyl group, a tert-butyl group,
a pentyl group, and the like. Examples of the alkoxy group include
a methoxy group, an ethoxy group, a propoxy group, an isopropoxy
group, a butoxy group, a tert-butoxy group, a pentoxy group, and the
like. The sulfo group and the carboxyl group include salts thereof.
Among the compounds represented by the general formula (AD-I),
particularly preferred compounds are those in which m and n are 1 or
2. The compounds represented by the general formula (AD-I) can be
synthesized by conventionally known methods.</p><p num="0130">Examples of the acid-decomposable compound that can be
used in the present invention include compounds having a C-O-C
bond described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 48-89603, 51-120714, 53-133429, 55-12995,
55-126236, and 56-17345</ref>; compounds having an Si-O-C bond
described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 60-37549 and 60-121446</ref>; and other acid-decomposable
compounds described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 60-3625 and 60-10247</ref>.
Further examples thereof include compounds having an Si-N
bond described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 62-222246</ref>; carbonic esters described in <ref type="patent">JP-A
No. 62-251743</ref>; orthocarbonic esters described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 62-209451</ref>;
orthotitanic esters described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 62-280841</ref>;
orthosilicic esters described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 62-280842</ref>; acetals, ketals, and
orthocarbonic esters described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 63-010153, 9-171254, 10-55067,
10-111564, 10-87733, 10-153853, 10-228102, 10-268507, 10-282648, 
10-282670</ref>, and <ref type="patent">EP-0884647A1</ref>; and compounds having a C-S
bond described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 62-244038</ref>.</p><p num="0131">Among the acid-decomposable compounds listed above,
particularly preferable are the compounds having a C-O-C bond,
compounds having an Si-O-C bond, orthocarbonic esters, acetals,
ketals, and silyl ethers described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 53-133429, 56-17345, 60-121446,
60-37549, 62-209451, 63-010153, 9-171254,10-55067,10-111564,
10-87733,10-153853,10-228102,10-268507,10-282648,10-282670</ref>, and
<ref type="patent">EP-0884647A1</ref>.</p><p num="0132">Among these acid-decomposable compounds, preferably used
are polymeric compounds which have in the main chain thereof
repeating acetal or ketal portions and whose solubility in an alkaline
developing solution is raised by the generated acid.</p><p num="0133">These acid-decomposable compounds may be used singly or
in a combination of two or more. These compounds are added in an
amount of 5-70% by weight, preferably 10-50% by weight, and more
preferably 15-35% by weight based on the total weight of the solid
components of the image-forming material. If the amount to be
added is less than 5% by weight, smudges on non-image portions
tend to occur easily, whereas if the amount to be added is more than
70% by weight, film strength in image portions become insufficient.</p><heading>&lt;Polarity switchable image-forming material&gt;</heading><p num="0134">The polarity switchable image-forming material comprises,
besides the infrared absorber, a polarity switchable substance which
is converted from a lipophilic substance to a hydrophilic substance by 
heat.</p><p num="0135">The polarity switchable substance which is converted from a
lipophilic substance to a hydrophilic substance by heat means a
substance which exhibits a change of state from a state having no
affinity, such as swelling or dissolution, with water at room
temperature to a state having affinity with water at room temperature.
This change may or may not be accompanied by a chemical reaction.
A change accompanied by a chemical reaction is preferable because
the degree of polarity conversion is larger. Examples of a polarity
conversion reaction include formation of a hydrophilic group by heat.
Examples of a hydrophilic substituent include an acidic group such as
phosphonic acid, sulfonic acid, carboxylic acid, sulfonamide, and
phenol; a hydroxyl group; an amino group; and an onium salt such as
an ammonium salt. A reaction which produces such a substituent
by heat is preferable. Examples of the polarity switchable substance
include carboxylate esters described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 7-186562</ref>,
photochromic compounds described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 9-240148, 4-44895,
8-3463, and 8-156401</ref>, the inorganic compounds described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No.
51-115101</ref>, and the compounds capable of generating sulfonic acid
described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 10-282672</ref>. Further, protective groups which
generate the above-described hydrophilic groups by heat are suitably
used. Examples of such protective groups include those described
in <ref type="npl">Protective Groups in Organic Synthesis (Greene Theodra W.and
Wuts Peter G. M., published by Wiley-Interscience Publication)</ref> and
<ref type="npl">Protecting Groups (Philip J. Kocienski, published by George Thieme 
Verlag Stuttgart)</ref>. These compounds may be polymers or
compounds having low molecular weights.</p><p num="0136">Preferably, reaction temperature is not lower than 80°C and
not higher than 300°C. Particularly preferably, the reaction
temperature is 120 to 200°C. If the reaction temperature is low,
storability becomes inferior, and if the reaction temperature is high,
sensitivity is reduced.</p><heading>Other components</heading><p num="0137">According to requirements, a variety of additives may be
added to the image-forming material of the present invention. For
example, it is preferable to add a substance such as an onium salt, an
aromatic sulfone compound, an aromatic sulfonic ester compound, a
polyfunctional amine or the like to an interaction-breakable image-forming
material, because addition thereof makes it possible to more
effectively inhibit the polymer soluble in an aqueous alkaline solution
from being dissolved in a developing solution,</p><p num="0138">Examples of the onium salt include diazonium salts,
ammonium salts, phosphonium salts, iodonium salts, sulfonium salts,
selenonium salts, and arsonium salts. The onium salts are added
preferably in an amount of 1-50% by weight, more preferably 5-30%
by weight, and particularly preferably 10-30% by weight based on the
total weight of the solid components of the image-forming material.</p><p num="0139">In addition to these additives, a cyclic acid anhydride, a
phenol, and an organic acid can also be used in order to raise the
sensitivity to a higher level. Examples of the cyclic acid anhydride 
include phthalic anhydride, tetrahydrophthalic anhydride,
hexahydrophthalic anhydride, 3,6-endoxy-Δ4-tetrahydrophthalic
anhydride, tetrachlorophthalic anhydride, maleic anhydride,
chloromaleic anhydride, α-phenylmaleic anhydride, succinic
anhydride, and pyromellitic anhydride, as described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent
No. 4,115,128</ref>. Examples of the phenol include bisphenol A, p-nitrophenol,
p-ethoxyphenol, 2,4,4'-trihydroxybenzophenone, 2,3,4-trihydroxybenzophenone,
4-hydroxybenzophenone, 4,4',4&quot;-trihydroxytriphenylmethane,
and 4,4',3&quot;,4&quot;-tetrahydroxy-3,5,3',5'-tetramethyltriphenylmethane.
Examples of the organic acid include
sulfonic acids, sulfinic acids, alkylsulfuric acids, phosphonic acids,
phosphoric esters, and carboxylic acids, as described in, e.g., <ref type="patent">JP-A
Nos. 60-88942 and 2-96755</ref>.</p><p num="0140">The proportion of the cyclic acid anhydride, phenol, or organic
acid in the image-forming material is preferably 0.05 to 20% by
weight, more preferably 0.1 to 15% by weight, and particularly
preferably 0.1 to 10% by weight.</p><p num="0141">Besides the compounds described above, compounds, such as
epoxy compounds, vinyl ethers, hydroxymethyl-bearing phenol
compounds and alkoxymethyl-bearing phenol compounds described
in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 8-276558</ref>, and crosslinkable compounds having an alkali-solubility
inhibiting effect which are proposed by the present
inventors and described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 9-32837</ref>, may be added
appropriately, according to purposes.</p><p num="0142">Further, in order to broaden a stable range of conditions of 
development, the image-forming material in the present invention
may contain a nonionic surfactant as described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 62-251740
and 3-208514</ref> and an amphoteric surfactant as described in <ref type="patent">JP-A
Nos. 59-121044 and 4-13149</ref>.</p><p num="0143">The image-forming material in the present invention may
contain a dye or a pigment as a printout agent which makes it
possible to produce a visible image immediately after exposure-induced
heating and also as an image coloring agent.</p><p num="0144">A typical example of the printout agent is a combination of a
compound which releases an acid by the exposure-induced heating (a
photoacid-releasing agent) and an organic dye capable of forming a
salt with the compound. Specific examples of the printout agent
include a combination of o-naphthoquinonediazide-4-sulfonyl
halogenide and an organic dye which forms a salt therewith, as
described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 50-36209 and 53-8128</ref>, and a combination of a
trihalomethyl compound and an organic dye which forms a salt
therewith, as described in <ref type="patent">JP-A Nos. 53-36223, 54-74728, 60-3626, 61-143748,
61-151644, and 63-58440</ref>. Examples of the trihalomethyl
compound are an oxazole-based compound and a triazine-based
compound, both of which provide good storability while standing
and a clear printout image.</p><p num="0145">A dye other than above-mentioned salt-forming organic dyes
can also be used as an image-coloring agent. Suitable dyes include
oil-soluble dyes and basic dyes, in addition to the salt-forming
organic dyes. Specific examples of these dyes include Oil Yellow™ No. 
101, Oil Yellow™ No. 103, Oil Pink™ No. 312, Oil Green™ BG, Oil Blue™ BOS,
Oil Blue™ No. 603, Oil Black™ BY, Oil Black™ BS, and Oil Black™ T-505 (all
manufactured by Orient Chemical Industries, Co., Ltd.), Victoria Pure
Blue™ Crystal Violet™(C. I. 42555), Methyl Violet™(C.I. 42535), Ethyl
Violet™ (C. I. 42600), Rhodamine B™ (C. I. 145170B), Malachite Green™ (C. I.
42000), and Methylene Blue™ (C. I. 52015). The dyes described in <ref type="patent">JP-A
No. 62-293247</ref> are particularly preferable. The amount to be added
of the dye may be 0.01 to 10% by weight, preferably 0.1 to 3% by
weight, based on the weight of the total solids of the image-forming
material.</p><p num="0146">If necessary, in order to impart flexibility to the layer, a
plasticizer is incorporated into the image-forming material of the
present invention. Examples of the plasticizer include butyl
phthalyl, polyethylene glycol, tributyl citrate, diethyl phthalate,
dibutyl phthalate, dihexyl phthalate, dioctyl phthalate, tricresyl
phosphate, tributyl phosphate, trioctyl phosphate, tetrahydrofurfuryl
oleate, and an oligomer or a polymer of acrylic acid or methacrylic
acid.</p><heading>B. Planographic printing original plates</heading><p num="0147">The planographic printing original plate of the present
invention includes the recording layer containing the image-forming
material described above. The planographic printing original plate
of the present invention can be prepared by coating a suitable
substrate with a coating liquid for forming the recording layer, which
coating liquid is prepared by dissolving the above-described image-forming 
material in a solvent according to requirements.</p><p num="0148">Some illustrative nonlimiting examples of the solvent include
ethylene dichloride, cyclohexanone, methyl ethyl ketone, methanol,
ethanol, propanol, ethylene glycol monomethyl ether, 1-methoxy-2-propanol,
2-methoxyethyl acetate, 1-methoxy-2-propyl acetate,
dimethoxyethane, methyl lactate, ethyl lactate, N,N-dimethylacetamide,
N,N-dimethylformamide, tetramethylurea, N-methylpyrrolidone,
dimethyl sulfoxide, sulfolane, γ -butyrolactone,
toluene, and water. These solvents may be used singly or in a
combination of two or more.</p><p num="0149">The concentration of the total components (total solids
including additives) in the solvent is preferably 1 to 50% by weight.
The coated amount (solids) after coating and drying on the substrate
varies according to application, but a desirable amount is generally
0.5 g to 5.0 g/m<sup>2</sup> for a photosensitive printing plate.</p><p num="0150">The coating liquid can be applied by various methods.
Example methods include bar coating, rotational coating, spraying,
curtain coating, dipping, air-knife coating, blade coating, and roll
coating. As the coating amount decreases, film characteristics of the
recording layer become poor, although apparent sensitivity increases.</p><p num="0151">In order to improve coatability, the coating liquid for forming
the recording layer of the present invention may contain a surfactant.
An example of this surfactant is a fluorine-based surfactant described
in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 62-170950</ref>. A preferred amount of the surfactant to be
added is 0.01 to 1% by weight, more preferably 0.05 to 0.5% by weight, 
based on weight of total solids of materials for the printing plate.</p><p num="0152">A substrate to be used for preparation of the planographic
printing original plate of the present invention is a dimensionally
stable plate. Specific examples of the substrate include paper, paper
laminated with a plastic (e.g., polyethylene, polypropylene,
polystyrene, or the like), metal plates (such as aluminum, zinc, and
copper), plastic films (such as diacetylcellulose, triacetylcellulose,
cellulose propionate, cellulose butyrate, cellulose butyrate acetate,
cellulose nitrate, polyethylene terephthalate, polyethylene,
polystyrene, polypropylene, polycarbonate, and polyvinyl acetal),
and paper or plastic films laminated or vapor-deposited with the
above-mentioned metals.</p><p num="0153">A polyester film or an aluminum plate is preferable as a
substrate for use in the planographic printing original plate of the
present invention. Of these materials, an aluminum plate is
particularly preferable, because the same has good dimensional
stability and is relatively cheap. Examples of the aluminum plate
include a pure aluminum plate and a plate of an aluminum alloy
containing aluminum as a main component together with traces of
other elements. A further example of the substrate is a plastic film
laminated or vapor-deposited with aluminum. Examples of the
other elements contained in the aluminum alloy include silicon, iron,
manganese, copper, magnesium, chromium, zinc, bismuth, nickel,
and titanium. The total content of the other elements in the
aluminum alloy is 10% by weight or less. Although aluminum 
particularly desirable for use in the present invention is pure
aluminum, the aluminum to be used in the present invention may
contain small amounts of other elements, because limitations of
purification technologies make production of perfectly pure
aluminum difficult. Accordingly, composition of the aluminum
plate for use in the present invention is not particularly limited, and a
conventionally known aluminum plate may be used appropriately as
a material in the present invention. The thickness of the aluminum
plate for use in the present invention is 0.1 to 0.6 mm,
preferably 0.15 to 0.4 mm, and particularly preferably 0.2 to 0.3 mm.</p><p num="0154">Prior to surface-roughening of the aluminum plate, if
necessary, a degreasing treatment is performed in order to remove
any rolling oil from the surface of the aluminum plate by means of,
for example, a surfactant, an organic solvent, an aqueous alkaline
solution, or the like.</p><p num="0155">The surface-roughening of the aluminum plate may be
performed by a variety of methods. Examples of these methods
include a method wherein the surface is mechanically roughened, a
method wherein the surface is roughened by being electrochemically
dissolved, and a method wherein the surface is selectively dissolved
in a chemical way. The mechanical methods may be conventionally
known methods such as ball ablation, brushing, blasting, and buffing.
One electrochemical method is electrolysis of the aluminum plate in
an electrolyte solution, such as a hydrochloric acid or a nitric acid,
using an a.c. current or a d.c. current. A combination of a 
mechanical method and an electrochemical method is also possible,
as described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 54-63902</ref>.</p><p num="0156">If necessary, the surface-roughened aluminum plate is then
subjected to an alkali-etching treatment and a neutralizing treatment
that follows. After that, if desired, the aluminum plate is subjected
to an anodizing treatment so as to increase water retention and wear
resistance of the surface. A variety of electrolytes capable of
producing a porous oxide layer can be used as an electrolyte for the
anodizing treatment of the aluminum plate. Generally, sulfuric acid,
phosphoric acid, oxalic acid, chromic acid, or a mixture of these acids
is used as the electrolyte. The concentration of the electrolyte may
be determined appropriately depending on the type of the electrolyte.</p><p num="0157">Conditions for anodizing vary depending on the type of
electrolyte solutions employed and cannot be stipulated
unqualifiedly. However, generally employed conditions are as
follows: concentration of the electrolyte solution is 1 to 80% by
weight; temperature of the solution is 5 to 70°C; current density is 5 to
60 A/dm<sup>2</sup>; voltage is 1 to 100V; and duration of electrolysis is 10
seconds to 5 minutes.</p><p num="0158">If the amount of an anodized layer is less than 1.0 g/m<sup>2</sup>, plate
life will be insufficient and non-image portions of a resulting
planographic printing plate are liable to form scratch marks, which
collect printing ink in printing operations to cause so-called &quot;scratch
smudging&quot;.</p><p num="0159">If necessary, a substrate whose surface is already anodized 
may be rendered hydrophilic by a surface treatment. Preferred
examples of this surface treatment include treating the surface with
an aqueous solution of an alkali metal silicate (such as sodium
silicate) as described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent Nos. 2,714,066, 3,181,461,
3,280,734, and 3,902,734</ref>, wherein the substrate is simply immersed or
electrolytically treated in an aqueous solution of sodium silicate.
Further examples are a treatment of the surface with an aqueous
solution of potassium fluorozirconate as described in <ref type="patent">JP-B No. 36-22063</ref>
and a treatment of the surface with an aqueous solution of
polyvinylsulfonic acid as described in <ref type="patent">U. S. Patent Nos. 3,276,868,
4,153,461 and 4,689,272</ref>.</p><p num="0160">The planographic printing original plate of the present
invention is prepared by forming the recording layer containing the
image-forming material of the present invention on the substrate. If
necessary, an undercoat layer may be formed between the recording
layer and the substrate.</p><p num="0161">Various organic compounds may be used as components of
the undercoat layer. Examples of an organic compound forming the
undercoat layer include carboxymethyl cellulose; dextrin; gum arabic;
phosphonic acids having an amino group, such as 2-aminoethylphosphonic
acid and the like; organic phosphonic acids
such as phenylphosphonic acid, naphthylphosphonic acid,
alkylphosphonic acid, glycerophosphonic acid,
methylenediphosphonic acid, ethylenediphosphonic acid, and the
like, which may each have a substituent group; organic phosphoric 
acids such as phenylphosphoric acid, naphthylphosphoric acid,
alkylphosphoric acid, glycerophosphoric acid, and the like, which
may each have a substituent group; organic phosphinic acids such as
phenylphosphinic acid, naphthylphosphinic acid, alkylphosphinic
acid, glycerophosphinic acid, and the like, which may each have a
substituent group; amino acids such as glycine, β -alanine, and the
like; and hydrochloric acid salts of amines having a hydroxyl group
such as triethanolamine and the like. These compounds may be
used singly or may be used in a combination of two or more.</p><p num="0162">The planographic printing original plate of the present
invention may have a protective layer or the like, if necessary.</p><p num="0163">In the case where the aforementioned radical-polymerizable
image-forming material is used for the recording layer, in order to
prevent polymerization inhibition due to oxygen, an overcoat layer
impermeable to oxygen may be disposed in a position adjacent to the
recording layer. The material forming the overcoat layer is
preferably a water-soluble resin such as polyvinyl alcohol,
carboxymethyl cellulose, hydroxyethyl cellulose, methyl cellulose,
polyvinylpyrrolidone, or the like. The proper thickness of the layer
is 0.2-3 <i>µ</i>m.</p><p num="0164">If necessary, the overcoat layer may contain as a filtering agent
a dye or a pigment which does not absorb light from a light source to
be used for recording.</p><p num="0165">The planographic printing original plate prepared as
described above is usually subjected to image-wise exposure and 
development.</p><p num="0166">Examples of a light source of actinic rays to be used for the
image-wise exposure include a solid-state laser and a semiconductor
laser, each emitting infrared rays having a wavelength of 720 to 1200
nm.</p><p num="0167">In the present invention, a light source emitting light whose
wavelength ranges from a near-infrared region to a far-infrared
region is preferable, and a solid-state laser or a semiconductor laser is
particularly preferable.</p><p num="0168">A conventionally known aqueous alkaline solution can be
used as a developing solution and also as a replenisher solution for
the planographic printing original plate of the present invention.
For example, the aqueous alkaline solution may contain an inorganic
alkali salt such as sodium silicate, potassium silicate, sodium tertiary
phosphate, potassium tertiary phosphate, ammonium tertiary
phosphate, sodium secondary phosphate, potassium secondary
phosphate, ammonium secondary phosphate, sodium carbonate,
potassium carbonate, ammonium carbonate, sodium
hydrogencarbonate, potassium hydrogencarbonate, ammonium
hydrogencarbonate, sodium borate, potassium borate, ammonium
borate, sodium hydroxide, ammonium hydroxide, potassium
hydroxide, or lithium hydroxide. In addition, an organic alkali can
also be used for preparation of the aqueous alkaline solution.
Examples of the organic alkali include monomethylamine,
dimethylamine, trimethylamine, monoethylamine, diethylamine, 
triethylamine, monoisopropylamine, diisopropylamine,
triisopropylamine, n-butylamine, monoethanolamine,
diethanolamine, triethanolamine, monoisopropanolamine,
diisopropanolamine, ethyleneimine, ethylenediamine, and pyridine.</p><p num="0169">These alkalis are used singly or in a combination of two or
more.</p><p num="0170">Of the above-mentioned alkalis, a particularly preferred
developing solution is an aqueous solution of a silicate, such as
sodium silicate, potassium silicate, or the like. This is because
adjustment of developing performance of the developing solution is
possible, by varying a ratio of silicon oxide SiO<sub>2</sub> to alkali metal oxide
M<sub>2</sub>O, each of which forms the silicate, and concentrations thereof, in
the solution. For example, the use of alkali metal silicates described
in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 54-62004</ref> and <ref type="patent">JP-B No. 57-7427</ref> is effective in the present
invention.</p><p num="0171">When an automated developing machine is used, it is
generally known that a replenishing system can be used to process a
large amount of PS plates without exchanging the developing
solution in the tank for a long period of time, by feeding the tank with
an aqueous solution (a replenisher solution) having an alkali strength
higher than that of the developing solution in the tank. This
replenishing system is suited for the present invention. If necessary,
the developing solution and the replenisher solution may contain a
surfactant or an organic solvent for such purposes as acceleration or
inhibition of development, dispersion of sludge resulting from 
development, and enhancement of affinity with ink of the image
portions of the printing plate. Examples of preferred surfactants
include anionic surfactants, cationic surfactants, nonionic surfactants,
and amphoteric surfactants.</p><p num="0172">Further, if necessary, the developing solution and the
replenisher solution may contain a reducing agent such as
hydroquinone, resorcinol, or a sodium or potassium salt of an
inorganic acid such as sulfite or hydrogensulfite; an organic
carboxylic acid; a defoaming agent; and an agent to convert hard
water into soft water.</p><p num="0173">The printing plate, after being processed with the developing
solution and the replenisher solution described above, is subjected to
a post-treatment such as a treatment with rinsing water, a treatment
with a rinsing solution containing a surfactant or the like, or a
treatment with a desensitizing solution containing gum arabic or a
starch derivative. A combination of these treatments may be
employed for post-treatment when the image-forming material of the
present invention is used as a printing plate.</p><p num="0174">In recent years, for the purpose of rationalization and
standardization of plate-making operations, automated developing
machines have been widely used in the processing of materials for
printing plates in the field of plate-making and the printing industry.
Generally, the automated developing machine is made up of a
developing section and a post-treating section, each including a
device for transferring a printing plate and a tank filled with a 
processing solution and equipped with a spraying device, wherein
the printing plate travels horizontally after exposure so as to be
processed by the solution, which is sprayed from nozzles after being
pumped up from the tank. Further, according to a new process, a
printing plate is immersed in and transferred through a processing
tank filled with a processing solution by means of immersed guide
rolls or the like. In the above-mentioned automated processing, the
processing can be performed by supplying replenisher solutions, in
amounts in accordance with processed volume and operational
period of time, to the processing solutions.</p><p num="0175">Further, a so-called single-use solution system, in which a
printing plate is processed with a substantially unused processing
solution, can also be employed in the present invention.</p><p num="0176">If unnecessary image portions (e.g., film edge marks of an
original film) are found on a planographic printing plate which has
been obtained by a procedure comprising image-wise exposure,
developing, water-washing and/or rinsing, and/or gum coating, the
unnecessary image portions are erased. The erasure is preferably
performed by a process comprising coating the unnecessary image
portions with an erasing solution, leaving the coating to remain on
the unnecessary image portions for a predetermined period of time,
and then removing the coating by washing with water, as described
in <ref type="patent">JP-B No. 2-13293</ref>. In addition to this process, also possible is a
process comprising irradiating the unnecessary image portions with
actinic rays guided by an optical fiber and then developing, as 
described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 59-174842</ref>.</p><p num="0177">If it is desired to impart a higher level of plate life to the
printing plate, the printing plate is subjected to a burning treatment.</p><p num="0178">When the printing plate undergoes the burning treatment, it is
desirable to treat the printing plate with a counter-etching solution,
which is described in, e.g., J<ref type="patent">P-B Nos. 61-2518 and 55-28062</ref>, and <ref type="patent">JP-A
Nos.62-31859 and 61-159655</ref>, prior to the burning treatment.</p><p num="0179">According to these treating methods, the planographic
printing plate is coated with the counter-etching solution using a
sponge or absorbent cotton soaked with the solution; the
planographic printing plate is immersed in a vat filled with the
counter-etching solution; or the planographic printing plate is coated
with the counter-etching solution using an automated coater. If the
coated amount is homogenized by squeezing or by means of
squeezing rollers after the coating, a better result is obtained.</p><p num="0180">A suitable coating amount of the counter-etching solution is
generally 0.03 to 0.8 g/m<sup>2</sup>(dry weight).</p><p num="0181">The planographic printing plate, after being coated with the
counter-etching solution, is dried and thereafter heated to a high
temperature, if necessary, by means of a burning processor (e.g.,
BURNING PROCESSOR™ BP-1300 manufactured by Fuji Photo Film
Co., Ltd.). Temperature and duration vary depending on the kinds
of components constituting the image, but desirable temperatures
and times are in a range of 180 to 300°C and 1 to 20 minutes.</p><p num="0182">After the burning treatment, if necessary, the planographic 
printing plate may be subjected to conventionally employed
treatments such as water-rinsing and gum-coating. However, if the
counter-etching solution contains a water-soluble polymeric
compound or the like, a so-called desensitizing treatment such as
gum-coating may be omitted.</p><p num="0183">The planographic printing plate thus prepared is mounted on
an offset printing machine or the like and is then used for printing a
large number of sheets.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0184">The present invention is further explained below by way of
examples. However, it must be noted that the scope of the present
invention is not limited to these examples.</p><heading>(Example 1: Examples of positive-type image-forming materials)</heading><heading>[Preparation of substrate]</heading><p num="0185">A 0.3 mm thick aluminum plate (type of material: 1050) was
cleaned with trichloroethylene and grained with a nylon brush using
an aqueous suspension of 400 mesh pumice powder. After being
well rinsed with water, the aluminum plate was etched by a process
of immersing the aluminum plate in a 25% aqueous solution of
sodium hydroxide at 45°C for 9 seconds, rinsing the aluminum plate
with water, immersing the aluminum plate in a 20% aqueous solution
of nitric acid for 20 seconds, and rinsing the aluminum plate with
water. In the process, an etched amount of the grained aluminum
plate was about 3 g/m<sup>2</sup>. After the process, the aluminum plate was 
subjected to an anodizing process of immersing the aluminum plate
in a 7% sulfuric acid solution as an electrolyte solution through which
a d. c. current with a density of 15 A/dm<sup>2</sup> was passed. This process
produced an anodized film of 3 g/m<sup>2</sup>. Then, the surface-treated
aluminum plate was rinsed with water and thereafter dried. The
aluminum plate was then coated with an undercoat solution given
below, and the coating was dried at 90°C for 1 minute. After drying,
a coated amount was 10 mg/m<sup>2</sup>.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2" align="left">Undercoat solution</entry></row><row><entry align="left">β-alanine</entry><entry align="left">0.5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">methanol</entry><entry align="left">95 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">water</entry><entry align="left">5 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0186">Next, the following coating liquid 1 for forming a
photosensitive layer was coated on the substrates obtained in the
above-described procedure with a coating amount of 1.8 g/m<sup>2</sup>. In
this way, a planographic printing original plate was obtained.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2">[Coating liquid 1 for forming a photosensitive layer]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">m-cresol/p-cresol novolac</entry><entry align="left">1.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(m to p ratio: 6:4; weight average molecular weight: 3,500; content of unreacted cresol: 0.5% by weight)

infrared absorber (exemplary compound IR-1)</entry><entry align="left">0.2 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">dye prepared by using 1-naphthalenesulfonic acid anions as counter anions of VICTORIA PURE BLUE™ BOH</entry><entry align="left">0.02 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">fluorine-based surfactant</entry><entry align="left">0.05 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(MEGAFAC™ F-177, manufactured by Dainippon Ink and Chemicals Inc.) </entry></row><row><entry align="left">γ -butyrolactone</entry><entry align="left">3 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">methyl ethyl ketone</entry><entry align="left">8 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1-methoxy-2-propanol</entry><entry align="left">7 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>(Examples 2 and 3)</heading><p num="0187">Planographic printing original plates were obtained in the
same way as in Example 1, except that the infrared absorber
incorporated in the coating liquid 1 for forming the photosensitive
layer of Example 1 was replaced with infrared absorbers shown in
Table 1.</p><heading>(Comparative Example 1)</heading><p num="0188">A planographic printing original plate was obtained in the
same way as in Example 1, except that the infrared absorber
incorporated in the coating liquid 1 for forming the photosensitive
layer of Example 1 was replaced with IR-792™ PERCHLORATE
(manufactured by Sigma-Aldrich Japan Inc.) having the following
structure.
<img file="00750001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00750001" he="65" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><heading>(Example 4)</heading><p num="0189">A substrate obtained in the same way as in Example 1 was
coated with the following coating liquid 2 for forming a
photosensitive layer with a coating amount of 1.6 g/m<sup>2</sup>. In this way,
a planographic printing original plate was obtained.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2">[Coating liquid 2 for forming a photosensitive layer]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">m-cresol/p-cresol novolac</entry><entry align="left">0.3 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(m to p ratio: 6:4; weight average molecular weight: 3,500; content of unreacted cresol: 0.5% by weight)

copolymer 1 obtained by the method described below</entry><entry align="left">0.7 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(described in Examples of <ref type="patent">JP-A No. 11-348443</ref>)

bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)sulfone</entry><entry align="left">0.1 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">infrared absorber (exemplary compound IR-1)</entry><entry align="left">0.15 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">p-toluenesulfonic acid</entry><entry align="left">0.002 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">dye prepared by using 1-naphthalenesulfonic acid anions as counter anions of VICTORIA PURE BLUE™ BOH</entry><entry align="left">0.02 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">fluorine-based surfactant</entry><entry align="left">0.05 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(MEGAFAC™ F-177, manufactured by Dainippon Ink and Inc.)Chemicals</entry></row><row><entry align="left">γ-butyrolactone</entry><entry align="left">8 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">methyl ethyl ketone</entry><entry align="left">8 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1-methoxy-2-propanol</entry><entry align="left">4 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0190">The copolymer 1 was prepared according to the following
method.</p><p num="0191">A 500 mL three-neck flask fitted with a stirrer, condenser, and
dropping funnel was charged with 31.0 g (0.36 mol) of methacrylic 
acid, 39.1 g (0.36 mol) of ethyl chloroformate, and 200 mL of
acetonitrile. The mixture was stirred while it was cooled in an ice
water bath. 36.4 g (0.36 mol) of triethylamine was added dropwise
from the dropping funnel to the mixture over a period of about 1
hour. After completion of the addition, the ice water bath was
removed and the mixture was stirred for 30 minutes at room
temperature.</p><p num="0192">51.7 g (0.30 mol) of p-aminobenzenesulfonamide was added to
the reaction mixture and the mixture was stirred for 1 hour while the
mixture was heated at 70°C using an oil bath. After completion of a
reaction, the mixture was poured into 1 L of water while the water
was stirred. The mixture thus obtained was stirred for 30 minutes.
A deposited substance was collected by filtration of the mixture.
The deposited substance was then slurried in 500 mL of water. The
slurry was filtered to obtain a solid substance. By drying the solid
substance, a white substance, i.e., N-(p-aminosulfonylphenyl)methacrylamide,
was obtained (46.9 g yield).</p><p num="0193">Next, a 100 mL three-neck flask fitted with a stirrer, condenser,
and dropping funnel was charged with 5.04 g (0.0210 mol) of N-(p-aminosulfonylphenyl)methacrylamide,
2.05 g (0.0180 mol) of ethyl
methacrylate, 1.11 g (0.021 mol) of acrylonitrile, and 20 g of N,N-dimethylacetamide.
The mixture was stirred while being heated at
65°C in a hot water bath. 0.15 g of &quot;V-65&quot; (manufactured by Wako
Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd.) was added to the mixture and the
resulting mixture was stirred for 2 hours under a nitrogen gas stream 
at 65°C. To this reaction mixture was added dropwise a mixture of
5.04 g of N-(p-aminosulfonylphenyl)methacrylamide, 2.05 g of ethyl
methacrylate, 1.11 g of acrylonitrile, 20 g of N,N-dimethylacetamide,
and 0.15 g of &quot;V-65&quot; from a dropping funnel over a period of 2 hours.
After completion of a addition, the mixture was stirred for 2 hours at
65°C. After completion of a reaction, 40 g of methanol was added to
the reaction mixture and the resulting mixture was cooled. The
mixture thus obtained was poured into 2 L of water while the water
was stirred. The mixture was stirred for 30 minutes. After that, a
deposited substance was collected by filtration of the mixture. By
drying the solid substance, 15 g of a white substance was obtained.
The weight average molecular weight of the copolymer 1 thus
obtained was measured by gel permeation chromatography (using a
polystyrene standard) and was found to be 53,000.</p><heading>(Examples 5 and 6)</heading><p num="0194">Planographic printing original plates were obtained in the
same way as in Example 4, except that the infrared absorber
incorporated in the coating liquid 2 for forming the photosensitive
layer in Example 4 was replaced with infrared absorbers shown in
Table 1.</p><heading>(Comparative Example 2)</heading><p num="0195">A planographic printing original plate was obtained in the
same way as in Example 4, except that the infrared absorber
incorporated in the coating liquid 2 for forming a photosensitive layer
in Example 4 was replaced with IR-792™ PERCHLORATE 
(manufactured by Sigma-Aldrich Japan Inc.).</p><heading>[Evaluation of performance of the planographic printing original
plates]</heading><p num="0196">The planographic printing original plates of Examples 1~6 and
the planographic printing original plates of Comparative Examples 1
and 2 obtained as above were subjected to the following tests to
evaluate performances based on the following criteria. Test results
are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>(Sensitivity)</heading><p num="0197">The planographic printing original plates obtained were
exposed to a semiconductor laser having an output power of 500 mW,
a wavelength of 830 nm, and a beam diameter of 17 µm (1/e<sup>2</sup>) at a
scanning speed of 5 m/second. After exposure, the presence or
absence of ablation was visually inspected. The exposed plates were
then developed using an automatic developing machine (PS
PROCESSOR 900 VR™ manufactured by Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd.) fed
with a developing solution DP-4™ and a rinsing solution FR-3™ (diluted
1:7), all manufactured by Fuji Film Co., Ltd. In this test, DP-4™ was
diluted with water at a 1:8 dilution ratio. Next, line width in non-image
portions obtained by using the developing solution was
measured, the amount of laser radiation energy corresponding to the
line width was sought, and this amount was treated as sensitivity.
The values of sensitivity thus measured and presence or absence of
ablation are shown in Table 1. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center" /><entry align="center">Infrared absorber</entry><entry align="center">Sensitivity (mJ/cm<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center">Ablation</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 1</entry><entry align="center">IR-1</entry><entry align="center">175</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 2</entry><entry align="center">IR-14</entry><entry align="center">175</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 3</entry><entry align="center">IR-48</entry><entry align="center">170</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">IR-792™ PERCHLORATE</entry><entry align="center">210</entry><entry align="center">Found in traces</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 4</entry><entry align="center">IR-1</entry><entry align="center">165</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 5</entry><entry align="center">IR-20</entry><entry align="center">160</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 6</entry><entry align="center">IR-46</entry><entry align="center">150</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative example 2</entry><entry align="center">IR-792™ PERCHLORATE</entry><entry align="center">195</entry><entry align="center">Found in traces</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0198">As can be seen from Table 1, it was found that the
planographic printing original plates using the image-forming
materials of the present invention have higher sensitivity, do not
cause ablation, and are superior in image-forming performance in
comparison with conventionally known planographic printing
original plates that use infrared absorbers having only one
chromophoric group.</p><heading>(Examples 7∼10: Examples of negative-type image-forming materials)</heading><p num="0199"><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2">[Coating liquid 3 for forming a photosensitive layer]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">diazonium salt</entry><entry align="left">0.15 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(having the structural formula described below and described in <ref type="patent">JP-A No.11-352679</ref>) </entry></row><row><entry align="left">infrared absorber (exemplary compound IR-1)</entry><entry align="left">0.10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">poly-p-hydroxystyrene resin</entry><entry align="left">1.5 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(having a weight average molecular weight of 10,000) crosslinking agent (having structural formula shown below)</entry><entry align="left">0.50 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">fluorine-based surfactant</entry><entry align="left">0.03 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(MEGAFAC™ F-177, manufactured by Dainippon Ink and Inc.) Chemicals</entry></row><row><entry align="left">methyl ethyl ketone</entry><entry align="left">15 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1-methoxy-2-propanol</entry><entry align="left">10 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">methyl alcohol</entry><entry align="left">5 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img file="00810001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00810001" he="75" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><img file="00820001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00820001" he="79" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><p num="0200">The above-described diazonium salt was prepared in the
following way.</p><p num="0201">2-nitrobenzene-1,3,5-triol (34 g), methyl chloroacetate (67 g),
and potassium carbonate (80 g) were caused to react in N,N-dimethylacetamide
(300 mL) at 80°C for 5 hours. After completion
of the reaction, the reaction product was extracted with ethyl acetate
and solvent was removed from the extract by distillation. A residue
was treated by silica gel column chromatography. In this way,
methyl 2-(3,5-bis((methoxycarbonyl)methoxy)-2-nitrophenoxy)acetate
(45 g) was obtained.</p><p num="0202">Methyl 2-(3,5-bis((methoxycarbonyl)methoxy)-2-nitrophenoxy)acetate
(39 g) thus obtained and n-hexylamine (156 g)
were caused to react in toluene (300 mL) at 100°C for 20 hours. After
completion of the reaction, the solvent was removed from the
reaction mixture by distillation. Next, ethyl acetate (300 mL) was
added to a residue and the reaction mixture was heated at a refluxing 
temperature and filtered. To a mixture of the obtained compound
and 2-propanol (300 mL) were added reduced iron (39 g) and an
aqueous solution of ammonium chloride (7.6 g of ammonium
chloride/30 mL of water) and the mixture was caused to react at 90°C
for 5 hours. After completion of the reaction, a reaction product was
extracted with dichloromethane. The extract was treated by silica
gel column chromatography.</p><p num="0203">The obtained compound was dissolved in methanol (200 mL).
After the solution was acidified with concentrated hydrochloric acid
(9 g), an aqueous solution of sodium sulfite (3.1 g of sodium
sulfite/15 mL of water) was gradually added to the acidified solution
as the same was being cooled. Two hours later, 2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenole-5-sulfonic
acid (10 g) was added, and, one
hour later, a reaction product was extracted with dichloromethane.
The extract was washed with water and solvent was removed by
distillation. In this way, the desired diazonium salt was obtained.</p><p num="0204">A substrate obtained in the same way as in Example 1 was
coated with the coating liquid, and the coating was dried at 100°C for
1 minute to thereby obtain a negative-type, planographic printing
original plate [C-1] for Example 7. Coated amounts after drying
were 1.3 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p><p num="0205">Planographic printing original plates [C-2]~[C-4] for Examples
8 to 10 were obtained in the same way as in Example 7, except that
the kind of the infrared absorber was changed as shown in Table 2.</p><p num="0206">The negative-type planographic printing original plates [C-1]~[C-4] 
thus obtained were exposed using a semiconductor laser
emitting infrared rays having a wavelength of 830 nm, i.e., the same
wavelength as for Example 1. After exposure, the plates [C-1]~[C-4]
were subjected to a heat treatment for 1 minute in an oven at 140°C.
The exposed plates were processed using the automatic developing
machine fed with the developing solution DP-4™ (diluted 1:8) and the
rinsing solution FR-3™ (diluted 1:7), both manufactured by Fuji Film
Co., Ltd. All of the planographic printing original plates [C-1]~[C-4]
provided good negative images.</p><heading>(Comparative Example 3)</heading><p num="0207">A negative-type planographic printing original plate [C-C]
was obtained in the same way as in Examples 7~10, except that the
infrared absorber incorporated in the coating liquid 3 for forming the
photosensitive layer in Examples 7~10 was replaced with IR-792™
PERCHLORATE.</p><p num="0208">The planographic printing original plate [C-C] thus obtained
was exposed, heat-treated, and developed as in Examples 7~10.
After that, the sensitivity was measured and ablation was inspected
for the same way as in Examples 1~6. The results are shown in
Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center" /><entry align="center">Plate material</entry><entry align="center">Infrared absorber</entry><entry align="center">Sensitivity (mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> )</entry><entry align="center">Ablation</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 7</entry><entry align="center">C-1</entry><entry align="center">IR-1</entry><entry align="center">135</entry><entry align="center">None </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 8</entry><entry align="center">C-2</entry><entry align="center">IR-13</entry><entry align="center">125</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 9</entry><entry align="center">C-3</entry><entry align="center">IR-42</entry><entry align="center">115</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 10</entry><entry align="center">C-4</entry><entry align="center">IR-48</entry><entry align="center">120</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example 3</entry><entry align="center">C-C</entry><entry align="center">IR-792™ PERCHLORATE</entry><entry align="center">155</entry><entry align="center">Found in traces</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0209">As can be seen from Table 2, it was found that, also in
planographic printing original plates using the negative-type image-forming
materials, planographic printing original plates using the
infrared absorbers of the present invention have higher sensitivity, do
not cause ablation, and are superior in image-forming performance in
comparison with a conventionally known planographic printing
original plate using a conventionally known infrared absorber.</p><heading>(Examples 11~12: Examples of negative-type image-forming
materials)</heading><p num="0210"><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2">[Coating liquid 4 for forming a photosensitive layer]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">iodonium salt having the structural formula shown below</entry><entry align="left">0.67 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">infrared absorber (exemplary compound IR-1)</entry><entry align="left">0.27 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">allyl methacrylate/methacrylic acid copolymer</entry><entry align="left">3.3 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(molar ratio: 87:13, MW=100,000)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">dipentaerythritol hexaacrylate</entry><entry align="left">3.3 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(DPHA, manufactured by Nippon Kayaku Co., Ltd.)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">dye prepared using 1-naphthalenesulfonic acid anions as counter anions of VICTORIA PURE BLUE™ BOH</entry><entry align="left">0.13 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">fluorine-based surfactant</entry><entry align="left">0.1 g </entry></row><row><entry align="left">(MEGAFAC™ F-177, manufactured by Dainippon Ink and Chemicals Inc.)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">methyl ethyl ketone</entry><entry align="left">33 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1-methoxy-2-propanol</entry><entry align="left">20 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">methyl alcohol</entry><entry align="left">26 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img file="00860001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00860001" he="53" wi="99" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p><p num="0211">A substrate obtained in the same way as in Example 1 was
coated with the coating liquid 4, and the coating was dried at 115°C
for 45 seconds to thereby obtain a negative-type planographic
printing original plate [D-1] for Example 11. The coated amount
after drying was 1.4 g/m<sup>2</sup>.</p><p num="0212">A planographic printing original plate [D-2] for Example 12
was obtained in the same way as in Example 11, except that the kind
of the infrared-ray absorber was changed as shown in Table 3.</p><p num="0213">The planographic printing original plates [D-1] and [D-2] thus
obtained were exposed using a semiconductor laser emitting infrared
rays having a wavelength of 830 nm, i.e., the same wavelength as for
Examples 1~10. After exposure, the planographic printing original
plates [D-1] and [D-2] were processed using the automatic developing
machine fed with a developing solution DN-3C™ (diluted 1:2) and the 
rinsing solution FR-3™ (diluted 1:7), both manufactured by Fuji Film
Co., Ltd. Both of the planographic printing original plates [D-1] and
[D-2] provided good negative images.</p><heading>(Comparative Example 4)</heading><p num="0214">A negative-type planographic printing original plate [D-C]
was obtained in the same way as in Examples 11 and 12, except that
the infrared absorber incorporated in the coating liquid 4 for forming
a photosensitive layer in Examples 11 and 12 was replaced with IR-786™
PERCHLORATE (manufactured by Sigma-Aldrich Japan Inc.).</p><p num="0215">The planographic printing original plate [D-C] thus obtained
was exposed, heat-treated, and developed as in Examples 11 and 12.
After that, sensitivity was measured and ablation was inspected in
the same way for Examples 1~10. The results are shown in Table 3.
<img file="00870001.tif" id="img-EP-1116060-B1-00870001" he="45" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center" /><entry align="center">Plate material</entry><entry align="center">Infrared absorber</entry><entry align="center">Sensitivity (mJ/cm<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center">Ablation</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 11</entry><entry align="center">D-1</entry><entry align="center">IR-6™</entry><entry align="center">160</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 12</entry><entry align="center">D-2</entry><entry align="center">IR-48™</entry><entry align="center">155</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative example 4</entry><entry align="center">D-C</entry><entry align="center">IR-786™ PERCHLORATE</entry><entry align="center">175</entry><entry align="center">Found in traces</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0216">As can be seen from Table 3, it was found that the
planographic printing original plates of Examples 11 and 12 have
higher sensitivity, do not cause ablation, and are superior in image-forming
performance in comparison with a conventionally known
planographic printing original plate that uses an infrared absorber
having only one chromophoric group.</p><p num="0217">As can be seen from the Examples described above, the use of
a specific infrared absorber makes it possible to obtain an image-forming
material which has high sensitivity, inhibits the formation of
ablation, and exhibits good image-forming performance.</p><p num="0218">In addition, it was found that a planographic printing original
plate using this image-forming material could be engraved in a direct
plate-making process using an infrared laser and exhibited high
sensitivity and good image-forming performance.</p><p num="0219">The image-forming material of the present invention has high
sensitivity to an infrared laser and is excellent in image-forming
performance. A planographic printing original plate using this
image-forming material can be engraved in a direct plate-making
process using an infrared laser, exhibits high sensitivity and a good
image-forming performance, and does not produce smudges on an
optical system of an exposing apparatus.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bilderzeugendes Material, das in der Lage ist, ein Bild
bei Infrarotbelichtung aufzuzeichnen, worin das
bilderzeugende Material mindestens einen
Infrarotstrahlungsabsorber enthält, der im Molekül
mindestens zwei chromophore Gruppen aufweist, von denen
jede einen Infrarotstrahl absorbieren kann und an einen
anderen Teil des Moleküls über eine kovalente Bindung
gebunden ist,dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass das bilderzeugende Material
ferner eine polymere Verbindung umfasst, die in Wasser
unlöslich und in einer wässrigen Alkalilösung löslich
ist, wobei man die Bildaufzeichnung bewirken kann, indem
man eine Löslichkeitsänderung der polymeren Verbindung
in der wässrigen Alkalilösung nutzt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bilderzeugendes Material, das in der Lage ist, ein Bild
bei Infrarotbelichtung aufzuzeichnen, worin das
bilderzeugende Material mindestens einen
Infrarotstrahlungsabsorber enthält, der im Molekül
mindestens zwei chromophore Gruppen aufweist, von denen
jede Infrarotstrahlung absorbieren kann und an einen
anderen Teil des Moleküls über eine kovalente Bindung
gebunden ist,dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass das bilderzeugende Material
ferner ein polaritätswechselndes Material umfasst,
dessen Hydrophilie und Hydrophobie des bilderzeugenden
Materials zumindest durch Wärme verändert wird, wobei
die Bilderzeugung bewirkt werden kann, indem man die
Änderung der Hydrophilie und Hydrophobie des
bilderzeugenden Materials nutzt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bilderzeugendes Material gemäß Anspruch 1 oder 2, worin
der Infrarotstrahlungsabsorber durch die folgende
allgemeine Formel (I) dargestellt wird,
(D)n-A
worin A eine organische Gruppe mit einer Valenz von
mindestens 2 bedeutet, n eine ganze Zahl von mindestens
2 bedeutet; und D eine chromophore Gruppe bedeutet, die
im Infrarotbereich absorbiert, wobei eine der
chromophoren Gruppen die gleiche sein kann wie die
andere der chromophoren Gruppen oder sich von dieser
unterscheiden kann; und für den Fall, dass die
chromophore Gruppe eine elektrische Ladung aufweist, ein
Ion mit einer der elektrischen Ladung der chromophoren
Gruppe entgegengesetzten Ladung vorhanden sein kann, um
die elektrische Ladung der chromophoren Gruppe zu
neutralisieren.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bilderzeugendes Material gemäß Anspruch 1 oder 2, worin
der Infrarotstrahlungsabsorber Licht mit einer
Wellenlänge im Bereich von 720 bis 1200 nm absorbiert.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Flachdruckoriginalplatte, welche ein Substrat und eine
auf dem Substrat vorgesehene Aufzeichnungsschicht
umfasst, worin die Aufzeichnungsschicht ein
bilderzeugendes Material enthält, das in der Lage ist,
ein Bild bei Infrarotbelichtung aufzuzeichnen, wobei das
bilderzeugende Material mindestens einen
Infrarotstrahlungsabsorber enthält, der im Molekül
mindestens zwei chromophore Gruppen aufweist, von denen
jede einen Infrarotstrahl absorbieren kann und an einen
anderen Teil des Moleküls über eine kovalente Bindung
gebunden ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Flachdruckoriginalplatte gemäß Anspruch 5, worin das
bilderzeugende Material ferner eine polymere Verbindung
umfasst, die in Wasser unlöslich und in einer wässrigen
Alkalilösung löslich ist, wobei die Bilderzeugung
bewirkt werden kann, indem man eine Löslichkeitsänderung
der polymeren Verbindung in der wässrigen Alkalilösung
nutzt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Flachdruckoriginalplatte gemäß Anspruch 5, worin das
bilderzeugende Material ferner ein polaritätswechselndes
Material umfasst, dessen Hydrophilie und Hydrophobie des
bilderzeugenden Materials sich zumindest durch Wärme
ändern, wobei die Bilderzeugung bewirkt werden kann, in
dem man die Änderung der Hydrophilie und Hydrophobie des
bilderzeugenden Materials nutzt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Flachdruckoriginalplatte gemäß einem der Ansprüche 5, 6
oder 7, worin der Infrarotstrahlungsabsorber durch die
folgende allgemeine Formel (I) dargestellt wird:
(D)n-A
worin A eine organische Gruppe mit einer Valenz von
mindestens 2 bedeutet, n eine ganze Zahl von mindestens
2 bedeutet; und D eine chromophore Gruppe bedeutet, die
im Infrarotbereich absorbiert, wobei eine der
chromophoren Gruppen die gleiche sein kann wie die
andere der chromophoren Gruppen oder sich von dieser
unterscheiden kann; und für den Fall, dass die
chromophore Gruppe eine elektrische Ladung aufweist, ein
Ion mit einer der elektrischen Ladung der chromophoren
Gruppe entgegengesetzten Ladung vorhanden sein kann, um
die elektrische Ladung der chromophoren Gruppe zu
neutralisieren.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Bilderzeugendes Material gemäß einem der Ansprüche 5, 6
oder 7, worin der Infrarotstrahlungsabsorber Licht mit
einer Wellenlänge im Bereich von 720 bis 1200 nm
absorbiert.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An image-forming material capable of recording an
image by infrared exposure, wherein the image-forming
material contains at least an infrared radiation absorber
having in a molecule thereof at least two chromophoric
groups, each of which can absorb an infrared ray and is
bonded to another portion of the molecule by a covalent bond
   characterized in that the image-forming material further
comprises a polymeric compound insoluble in water and soluble
in an aqueous alkaline solution, wherein image recording can
be effected by utilizing a change of solubility of the
polymeric compound in the aqueous alkaline solution.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An image-forming material capable of recording an
image by infrared exposure, wherein the image-forming
material contains at least an infrared radiation absorber
having in a molecule thereof at least two chromophoric
groups, each of which can absorb an infrared ray and is
bonded to another portion of the molecule by a covalent bond
   characterized in that the image-forming material further
comprises a polarity switchable material whose hydrophilicity
and hydrophobicity of the image-forming material are changed
by at least heat, wherein image recording can be effected by
utilizing change of the hydrophilictiy and hydrophobicity of
the image-forming material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An image-forming material according to claim 1 or 2,
wherein the infrared radiation absorber is represented by the
following general formula I:(D)n-A
wherein A represents an organic group having a valency of at
least 2; n represents an integer of at least 2; and D
represents a chromphoric group having absorption in an
infrared region, wherein one of the chromophoric groups may
be the same as or may be different from another of the
chromophoric groups; and, in a case where the chromophoric
group has an electric charge, an ion having an electric
charge opposite to the electric charge of the chromophoric
group may be present in order to neutralize the electric
charge of the chromophoric group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An image-forming material according to claim 1 or 2,
wherein the infrared radiation absorber absorbs light having
a wavelength within the range of 720 to 1200nm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A planographic printing original plate comprising a
substrate, and a recording layer provided on the substrate,
the recording layer containing an image-forming material
capable of recording an image by infrared exposure, wherein
the image-forming material contains at least an infrared
radiation absorber having in a molecule thereof at least two
chromophoric groups, each of which can absorb an infrared ray
and is bonded to another portion of the molecule by a
covalent bond.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A planographic printing original plate according to
claim 5 wherein the image-forming material further comprises
a polymeric compound insoluble in water and soluble in an
aqueous alkaline solution, wherein image recording can be
effected by utilizing a change of solubility of the polymeric
compound in the aqueous alkaline solution.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A planographic printing original plate according to
claim 5 wherein the image-forming material further comprises
a polarity switchable material whose hydrophilicity and
hydrophobicity of the image-forming material are changed by
at least heat, wherein image recording can be effected by
utilizing change of the hydrophilictiy and hydrophobicity of
the image-forming material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A planographic printing original plate according to
any of claims 5, 6 or 7 wherein the infrared radiation
absorber is represented by the following general formula I:
(D)n-A
wherein A represents an organic group having a valency of at
least 2; n represents an integer of at least 2; and D
represents a chromphoric group having absorption in an
infrared region, wherein one of the chromophoric groups may
be the same as or may be different from another of the
chromophoric groups; and, in a case where the chromophoric
group has an electric charge, an ion having an electric
charge opposite to the electric charge of the chromophoric
group may be present in order to neutralize the electric
charge of the chromophoric group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>An image-forming material according to any of claims
5, 6 or 7, wherein the infrared radiation absorber absorbs
light having a wavelength within the range of 720 to 1200nm.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Matériau de formation d'images capable
d'enregistrer une image par exposition infrarouge, dans
lequel le matériau de formation d'images contient au moins
un absorbeur de rayonnement infrarouge ayant dans sa
molécule au moins deux groupes chromophores, chacun d'eux
peut absorber un rayon infrarouge et est lié à une autre
partie de la molécule par une liaison covalente
   caractérisé en ce que le matériau de formation
d'images comprend en outre un composé polymère insoluble
dans l'eau et soluble dans une solution alcaline aqueuse,
dans lequel l'enregistrement d'image peut être effectué par
l'utilisation d'un changement de solubilité du composé
polymère dans la solution alcaline aqueuse.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Matériau de formation d'images capable d'enregistrer
une image par exposition infrarouge, dans lequel le
matériau de formation d'images contient au moins un
absorbeur de rayonnement infrarouge ayant dans sa molécule
au moins deux groupes chromophores, chacun d'eux peut
absorber un rayon infrarouge et est lié à une autre partie
de la molécule par une liaison covalente
   caractérisé en ce que le matériau de formation
d'images comprend en outre un matériau à polarité
commutable dont l'hydrophilicité et l'hydrophobicité du
matériau de formation d'images sont changées par au moins
la chaleur, dans lequel l'enregistrement d'image peut être
effectué par l'utilisation d'un changement de
l'hydrophilicité et de l'hydrophobicité du matériau de
formation d'image.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Matériau de formation d'images selon la revendication 1
ou 2, dans lequel l'absorbeur de rayonnement infrarouge est
représenté par la formule générale suivante :(D)n-A
dans laquelle A représente un groupe organique ayant une
valence d'au moins 2 ; n représente un nombre entier d'au
moins 2 ; et D représente un groupe chromophore ayant une
absorption dans une région de l'infrarouge, dans lequel un
des groupes chromophores peut être identique ou différent
d'un autre des groupes chromophores ; et, dans le cas où le
groupe chromophore a une charge électrique, un ion ayant
une charge électrique opposée à la charge électrique du
groupe chromophore peut être présent de façon à neutraliser
la charge électrique du groupe chromophore.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Matériau de formation d'images selon la revendication
1 ou 2, dans lequel l'absorbeur de rayonnement infrarouge
absorbe la lumière ayant une longueur d'onde dans la gamme
de 720 à 1200 nm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Plaque originale d'impression planographique
comprenant un substrat, et une couche d'enregistrement
prévue sur le substrat, la couche d'enregistrement
contenant un matériau de formation d'images capable
d'enregistrer une image par exposition infrarouge, dans
laquelle le matériau de formation d'images contient au
moins un absorbeur de rayonnement infrarouge ayant dans sa
molécule au moins deux groupes chromophores, chacun d'eux
peut absorber un rayon infrarouge et est lié à une autre
partie de la molécule par une liaison covalente.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Plaque originale d'impression planographique selon la
revendication 5 dans laquelle le matériau de formation
d'images comprend de plus un composé polymère insoluble
dans l'eau et soluble dans une solution alcaline aqueuse,
dans laquelle l'enregistrement d'image peut être effectué
en utilisant un changement de solubilité du composé
polymère dans la solution alcaline aqueuse.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Plaque originale d'impression planographique selon la
revendication 5, dans laquelle le matériau de formation
d'images comprend en outre un matériau à polarité
commutable dont l'hydrophilicité et l'hydrophobicité du
matériau de formation d'images sont changées par au moins
la chaleur, dans laquelle l'enregistrement d'image peut
être effectué en utilisant un changement de
l'hydrophilicité et de l'hydrophobicité du matériau de
formation d'images.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Plaque originale d'impression planographique selon
l'une quelconque des revendications 5, 6 ou 7, dans
laquelle l'absorbeur de rayonnement infrarouge est
représenté par la formule générale (I) suivante :
(D)n-A
dans laquelle A représente un groupe organique ayant une
valence d'au moins 2 ; n représente un nombre entier d'au
moins 2 ; et D représente un groupe chromophore ayant une
absorption dans une région de l'infrarouge, dans laquelle
un des groupes chromophores peut être identique ou
différent d'un autre des groupes chromophores ; et, dans le
cas où le groupe chromophore a une charge électrique, un
ion ayant une charge électrique opposée à la charge
électrique du groupe chromophore peut être présent de façon
à neutraliser la charge électrique du groupe chromophore.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Matériau de formation d'images selon l'une quelconque
des revendications 5, 6 ou 7, dans lequel l'absorbeur de
radiation infrarouge absorbe la lumière ayant une longueur
d'onde dans la gamme de 720 à 1200 nm.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20070411"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>732E</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20070228"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>BE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DK</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ES</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LU</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MC</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>NL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>TR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041103</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050203</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050203</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050203</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050228</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050228</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050228</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="EN" date="20051230"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION NOT FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20051130"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MM4A</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20051026"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20050804</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20050513"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="NLV1" date="20050502"><legal-event-body><event-title>NL: LAPSED OR ANNULED DUE TO FAILURE TO FULFILL THE REQUIREMENTS OF ART. 29P AND 29M OF THE PATENTS ACT; NO LEGAL EFFECT FROM</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20041215"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20041209"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60106796</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041209</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20041115"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20041103"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20041103"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20020703"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020522</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20020522"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AT BE CH CY DE DK ES FI FR GB GR IE IT LI LU MC NL PT SE TR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20020515"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020304</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010905"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>
