<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1510596-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1510596" kind="A2" date="20050302"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="24287103" ucid="EP-1510596-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1510596</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20050302</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04028410-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04028410</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001006</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-157866 P" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>157866 P</doc-number><date>19991006</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-676426" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>676426</doc-number><date>20000929</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="EP-00121284-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00121284</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001006</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-15786699-P" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>15786699</doc-number><kind>P</kind><date>19991006</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-67642600-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>67642600</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000929</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"/><term-of-grant/><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/34        20060101AFI20041215BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/34        20060101CFI20041215BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/44        20060101ALI20080111BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/44        20060101CLI20080111BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/02        20060101CLI20080111BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/3205      20060101ALI20080111BHEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C16/34</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C16/44A2</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Reinigung, Analyse und Abscheidung von Titanamide</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Purification, analysis and deposition of titanium amides</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Purification, analyse et dépôt des amides titaniques.</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-5139825-A" source="SEA" category="AD" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>5139825</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5763007-A" source="SEA" category="A" created-by-npl="N" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>5763007</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id></patcit></patent-citations></citations><figures/></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>AIR PROD &amp; CHEM</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</last-name><address><street>7201 Hamilton Boulevard</street><city>Allentown, PA 18195-1501</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>RIAHI SHANTIA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>CARSON DOUGLAS W</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>VRTIS RAYMOND NICHOLAS</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>JAHL MATTHIAS J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>CARSON, DOUGLAS W.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>JAHL, MATTHIAS J.</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>VRTIS, RAYMOND NICHOLAS</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>RIAHI, SHANTIA</name><address><country/></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>CARSON, DOUGLAS W.</last-name><address><street>1437 Eastview Court</street><city>Oceanside, CA 92056</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>VRTIS, RAYMOND NICHOLAS</last-name><address><street>1897 Sunset Drive</street><city>Whitehall, PA 18052</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>RIAHI, SHANTIA</last-name><address><street>1662 Ravine Road</street><city>Vista, CA 92083</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>JAHL, MATTHIAS J.</last-name><address><street>12718 Footman Court</street><city>Poway, CA 92064</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Schwabe - Sandmair - Marx</last-name><address><street>Stuntzstrasse 16</street><city>81677 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>The present invention is a process for enhancing the chemical vapor deposition of titanium nitride from a titanium containing precursor selected from the group consisting of tetrakis(dimethylamino)titanium, tetrakis(diethylamino)titanium and mixtures thereof, reacted with ammonia to produce the titanium nitride on a semiconductor substrate by the addition of organic amines, such as dipropylamine, in a range of approximately 10 parts per million by weight to 10% by weight, preferably 50 parts per million by weight to 1.0 percent by weight, most preferably 100 parts per million by weight to 5000 parts per million by weight to the titanium containing precursor wherein prior to the reaction, said titanium containing precursor is subjected to a purification process to remove hydrocarbon impurities from the titanium containing precursor. It is shown that addition of small amounts of organic amines enhance the deposition rate of titanium nitride, while the presence of hydrocarbons, such as n-decane, retard the deposition rate of titanium nitride.</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">The present invention is a process for enhancing the chemical vapor deposition
of titanium nitride from a titanium containing precursor selected from the group consisting
of tetrakis(dimethylamino)titanium, tetrakis(diethylamino)titanium and mixtures thereof,
reacted with ammonia to produce the titanium nitride on a semiconductor substrate by
the addition of organic amines, such as dipropylamine, in a range of approximately 10
parts per million by weight to 10% by weight, preferably 50 parts per million by weight to
1.0 percent by weight, most preferably 100 parts per million by weight to 5000 parts per
million by weight to the titanium containing precursor wherein prior to the reaction, said
titanium containing precursor is subjected to a purification process to remove
hydrocarbon impurities from the titanium containing precursor. It is shown that addition
of small amounts of organic amines enhance the deposition rate of titanium nitride, while
the presence of hydrocarbons, such as n-decane, retard the deposition rate of titanium
nitride.</p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><heading>CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading><p num="0001">This patent application is a continuation-in-part of <ref type="patent">US Provisional Patent
Application No. 60/157,866</ref> filed 6 October 1999.</p><heading>STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR
DEVELOPMENT</heading><p num="0002">Not applicable.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0003">Titanium compounds, such as titanium nitride are finding increasing usage in a
number of utilities, particularly in the production of electronic materials of construction for
integrated circuits for computer chips.</p><p num="0004">Titanium nitride provides enhanced electrical conductivity for electronic circuits
and exhibits excellent barrier properties for other metal depositions on silicon substrates.
As a result, the electronics device fabrication industry has found increasing usage of
titanium compound depositions for coatings prior to subsequent conductor metal
depositions.</p><p num="0005">Techniques for titanium nitride deposition from tetrakis(dimethylamino)titanium
(TDMAT) and tetrakis(diethylamino)titanium (TDEAT) are known in the literature. For
instance, <ref type="patent">US Patent No. 5,139,825</ref> discloses the deposition of titanium nitride from
TDMAT or TDEAT in reaction with ammonia under chemical vapor deposition (CVD)
conditions of 100 to 400°C, preferably 150 to 300°C, most preferably 200 to 250°C, 
under reduced pressure and using an inert carrier gas, such as nitrogen or helium, to
deposit titanium nitride on a heated substrate, such as a heated silicon containing
substrate.</p><p num="0006">However,the deposition rate of titanium nitride has been highly variable and does
not lend itself to repeatable, precise use in the electronic fabrication industry, where a
multitude of silicon wafers are processed simultaneously, and many batches of wafers
are processed consecutively. High yields of electronically acceptable wafers are
necessary for the titanium nitride process to be acceptable commercially to the
electronics fabrication industry. Additionally, the speed of deposition is critical to provide
economic processing of titanium nitride coated wafers in the hundred plus step
processing of blank silicon wafers to the final electrically acceptable individual integrated
circuits produced by the electronics fabrication industry.</p><p num="0007">The problems of low depostion rate and variable deposition rate for titanium
compounds deposited by CVD from titanium containing precursors is unexpectedly
overcome by the process of the present invention by the addtion of amine additives
and/or the removal of trace amounts of hydrocarbon impurities as will be set forth with
greater detail below.</p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0008">The present invention is a process for enhancing the chemical vapor deposition
of titanium nitride from a titanium containing precursor selected from the group consisting
of tetrakis(dimethylamino)titanium, tetrakis(diethylamino)titanium and mixtures thereof,
reacted with ammonia to produce the titanium nitride on a semiconductor substrate by
the addition of organic amines, such as dipropylamine, in a range of approximately 10
parts per million by weight to 10 percent by weight, preferably 50 parts per million by
weight to 1.0 percent by weight, most preferably 100 parts per million by weight to 5000 
parts per million by weight to the titanium containing precursor wherein prior to the
reaction, said titanium containing precursor is subjected to a purification process to
remove hydrocarbon impurities from the titanium containing precursor. It is shown that
addition of small amounts of organic amines enhance the deposition rate of titanium
nitride, while the presence of hydrocarbons, such as n-decane and analogous
hydrocarbons, retard the deposition rate of titanium nitride.</p><p num="0009">The Present Invention is also a process for determining a predicted deposition
rate of a batch of a titanium containing precursor in a chemical vapor deposition of a
titanium containing compound on a substrate, comprising; analyzing the organic amine
content of the batch to determine an analytical amine content, comparing the analytical
amine content against an amine content standard and determining the predicted
deposition rate from a deposition rate standard based upon the deviation of the analytical
amine content from the amine content standard, wherein the predicted deposition rate is
greater than the deposition rate standard when the analytical amine content is greater
than the amine content standard and the predicted deposition rate is less than the
deposition rate standard when the analytical amine content is less than the amine
content standard.</p><p num="0010">The Present Invention is further a process for determining a predicted deposition
rate of a batch of a titanium containing precursor in a chemical vapor deposition of a
titanium containing compound on a substrate, comprising; analyzing the hydrocarbon
content of the batch to determine an analytical hydrocarbon content, comparing the
analytical hydrocarbon content against an hydrocarbon content standard and
determining the predicted deposition rate from a deposition rate standard based upon a
deviation of the analytical hydrocarbon content from the hydrocarbon content standard,
wherein the predicted deposition rate is less than the deposition rate standard when the
analytical hydrocarbon content is greater than the hydrocarbon content standard and the 
predicted deposition rate is greater than the deposition rate standard when the analytical
hydrocarbon content is less than the hydrocarbon content standard.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0011"><sl><li>FIG 1 is a graph of the correlation of compounds classified as n-containing with
deposition rate (angstroms per minute). Linear Regression: Slope = 67.2, Intercept =
-3334, correlation coefficient, r = 0.924.</li><li>FIG 2 is a graph of the correlation of compounds classified as hydrocarbons with
deposition rate (angstroms per minute). Linear Regression: Slope = -111, Intercept =
9774, correlation coefficient, r = -0.797.</li><li>FIG 3 is a graph of the typical chromatogram of the SPME-sampled headspace of a
hydrolyzed TMDAT sample. GC Conditions: Injector Temperature: 190 °C; Oven
Program: 40°C for 2 minutes, Ramp at 25°C/minute, 250°C for 2 minutes; Detector:
thermal conductivity, temperature = 250°C; Column: DB-1, 30m long x 0.53 mm ID x 5
µm film.</li><li>FIG 4 is a graph of the variation of peak area with µg decane added. Conditions:
5 mL aqueous volume, 10 mL headspace, 100 µm PDMS fiber, 2 minute absorb, 1 min
desorb, thermal conductivity detector. 6 data points cover range of 0.4 to 1720 µg n-decane.</li><li>FIG 5 is a graph of the total hydrocarbon peak area as a function of sample
volume (1 µL = 1000 µg). Conditions: 5 mL aqueous volume, 10 mL headspace, 100 µm
PDMS fiber, 2 minute absorb, 1 min desorb, thermal conductivity detector.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0012">Titanium compounds are deposited on substrates, such as silicon containing
substrates by known techniques for reaction of titanium containing precursors with
ammonia under CVD conditions of elevated temperature and reduced pressure as set
forth in <ref type="patent">US Patent No. 5,139,825</ref>, the entire text of which is expressly incorporated
herein by reference.</p><p num="0013">The present invention is a process for enhancing the chemical vapor deposition
of titanium containing compounds, such as titanium nitride, from a titanium containing
precursor, such as tetrakis(dialkylamino)titanium, specifically those selected from the
group consisting of tetrakis(dimethylamino)titanium, tetrakis(diethylamino)titanium and
mixtures thereof, reacted with ammonia to produce the titanium containing compound on
a semiconductor substrate by the addition of organic amines, such as dipropylamine, in a
range of approximately 10 parts per million by weight to 10% by weight, preferably 50
parts per million by weight to 1.0 percent by weight, most preferably 100 parts per million
by weight to 5000 parts per million by weight to the titanium containing precursor under
chemical vapor deposition (CVD) conditions of 100 to 400°C, preferably 150 to 300°C,
most preferably 200 to 250°C, under reduced pressure and using an inert carrier gas,
such as nitrogen or helium, to deposit titanium nitride on a heated substrate, such as a
heated silicon containing substrate.</p><p num="0014">A method to predict the performance of the titanium nitride chemical vapor
deposition titanium containing precursors, such as tetrakis(dialkylamino)titanium,
preferably tetrakis(dimethylamine)titanium (TDMAT) and tetrakis(diethylamino)titanium
(TDEAT) has been developed. A precursor sample is hydrolyzed using water and then
extracted using either a classical solvent extraction or solid-phase microextraction. The
extract is analyzed by gas chromatography and the amount and nature of extracted
compounds can be used to predict the deposition performance of the chemical. </p><p num="0015">TDMAT and TDEAT can be hydrolyzed either directly into water or by introducing
onto ice and allowing the ice to thaw. The chosen approach depends on the sample
quantity to be hydrolyzed. Quantities below 0.1g are typically hydrolyzed directly into
water while larger quantities ( 0.1 to 5 g) use the ice variation to address safety concerns
and limit loss of volatile compounds owing to the exothermic hydrolysis reaction.</p><p num="0016">A typical procedure over ice consists of adding 10g of water to a sealable vessel (vial
or centrifuge tube), freezing the water, and then adding the desired quantity of TDMAT or
TDEAT. The vessel is sealed to avoid loss of volatile compounds and the ice is allowed
to thaw by leaving the vessel at room temperature. As the ice thaws, the liquid water
initiates hydrolysis of the TDMAT or TDEAT in a controlled manner.</p><p num="0017">Extraction is affected in two modes. Solid-phase microextraction (SPME) is a
solventless technique used in an increasing variety of analyses. The chosen fiber type
depends on the compound types of interest. The general analyses described here have
used a 100µm non-bonded polydimethylsiloxane coated fiber. Other types of fibers can
be substituted to enhance the extraction for specific classes of compounds. For
example, a 65µm polydimethylsiloxane/divinylbenzene fiber has been used to provide
better extraction efficiency for the nitrogen-containing compounds found in TDMAT and
TDEAT.</p><p num="0018">The exact SPME conditions are subject to optimization. Typically analyses have
used a 2 to 4 minute absorption in the headspace of the vial in which TDMAT or TDEAT
has been hydrolyzed, followed by a 1 minute desorption in the injection port of a gas
chromatograph. This serves to extract a majority of volatiles from the sample vial and
desorb them into the gas chromatograph for characterization. Longer or shorter times
may be used to optimize the extraction for specific compounds or reduce the analysis
time. </p><p num="0019">The classical solvent-based extraction can use any water immiscible solvent which
has an affinity for the extractable compounds. Diethylether, methylisobutylketone,
toluene, and methylene chloride have all been found to be suitable extractants. Of
these, methylene chloride is most frequently used since it has a low boiling point, is more
dense than water, and does not have impurities similar to those found in TDMAT and
TDEAT. The ratio of water to extraction solvent can be varied to adjust the extract
concentration to a level suitable for the gas chromatographic detector.</p><p num="0020">The extract (either SPME or solvent) are analyzed by gas chromatography. The
column type chosen depends on the degree of separation desired. The following
columns and gas chromatographic parameters have been successfully used to separate
TDMAT and TDEAT extractables.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2">Analysis Conditions 1:</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column Phase</entry><entry align="left">100% polydimethylsiloxane</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phase Thickness (µm)</entry><entry align="left">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column Length (m)</entry><entry align="left">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column diamater (mm)</entry><entry align="left">0.53</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flow rate (ml/min)</entry><entry align="left">8.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Injection Port Temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="left">190</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Inject Volume (µL)</entry><entry align="left">5, Splitless</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Initial Oven Temperature (°C) &amp; Time (min)</entry><entry align="left">50 °C / 5 minutes</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oven Ramp Rate</entry><entry align="left">10 °C/minute</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Final Oven Temperature and time</entry><entry align="left">250 °C/ 5 minutes</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detector</entry><entry align="left">Thermal Conductivity</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detector Temperature</entry><entry align="left">260 °C</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2">Analysis Conditions 2:</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column Phase</entry><entry align="left">100% polydimethylsiloxane</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phase Thickness (µm)</entry><entry align="left">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column Length (m)</entry><entry align="left">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column diamater (mm)</entry><entry align="left">0.53</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flow rate (ml/min)</entry><entry align="left">8.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Injection Port Temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="left">190</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Inject Volume (µL)</entry><entry align="left">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Initial Oven Temperature (°C) &amp; Time (min)</entry><entry align="left">50 °C / 5 minutes</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oven Ramp Rate</entry><entry align="left">20 °C/minute</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Final Oven Temperature and time</entry><entry align="left">250 °C/ 5 minutes</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detector</entry><entry align="left">Thermal Conductivity</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detector Temperature</entry><entry align="left">260°C</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="2">Analysis Conditions 3:</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column Phase</entry><entry align="left">95% polydimethylsiloxane/ 5% Divinylbenzene</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phase Thickness (µm)</entry><entry align="left">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column Length (m)</entry><entry align="left">60</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column diamater (mm)</entry><entry align="left">0.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flow rate (cm/sec)</entry><entry align="left">50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Injection Port Temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="left">190</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Inject Volume (µL)</entry><entry align="left">0.2, 1:100 Split</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Initial Oven Temperature (°C) &amp; Time (min)</entry><entry align="left">100 °C / 5 minutes</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oven Ramp Rate</entry><entry align="left">10 °C/minute</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Final Oven Temperature and time</entry><entry align="left">250 °C/ 5 minutes</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detector</entry><entry align="left">Mass Spectrometer (Finnegan GCQ)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detector Temperature</entry><entry align="left">260 °C</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0021">Mass spectrometry has been used to characterize the compounds found in TDMAT
and TDEAT. Chromatograms obtained with a gas chromatography with mass
spectrometer have been correlated to gas chromatography thermal conductivity
detection to allow rapid classification of the extracted compounds. Additional detectors
used for gas chromatography may be substituted for those indicated in the above tables
to provide more specific analyses. Flame ionization detector, nitrogen-phosphorus
detectors, photoionization detectors, electron-capture detectors, and atomic emission
detectors can be used to focus in on specific types of compounds and/or enhance the
sensitivity.</p><p num="0022">Calibration for the extracted compounds can be carried out by different approaches.
The calibration can be performed using the method of standard addition and also using 
external standards for the solid-phase microextraction variation of this analysis. It has
been found the choice between external calibration and the method of standard additions
depends on the type of compound being quantitated. Aliphatic hydrocarbons appear to
be fully extracted using both approaches and can be calibrated using external standards.
The nitrogen-containing species, are not fully extracted owing to affinity for the aqueous
phase and would required standard addition or matrix-matched calibration for accurate
quantitation.</p><p num="0023">The results from the analyses described above are used to predict the deposition
performance of the precursors. The compounds found in TDEAT and TDMAT may be
identified using the mass spectrometric variation of the analysis described above.
Typically, samples are found to contain unsaturated amines and also aliphatic
hydrocarbons, presumably derived from synthesis techniques.</p><p num="0024">Gas chromatographic retention times for different column systems can be
determined, preliminary compound identification, i.e., the class to which each compound
is assigned, and thermal conductivity detector response for extracted TDEAT can be
tabulated.</p><p num="0025">The utility of this approach to predict deposition performance is demonstrated by
Table 4 and FIGs 1 and 2. The compounds found through analysis have been grouped
into two main classifications, those which contain a nitrogen heteroatom (N), those which
do not (HC), and those for which could not be definitely assigned to one group or the
other (Unclass.). <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="6">Results from extract analysis (arbitrary units) along with measured deposition rate. (angstroms/minute)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Lot#</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Total</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>N</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>HC</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Unclass.</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Deposition Rate</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">129</entry><entry align="center">3471</entry><entry align="right">2829</entry><entry align="right">511</entry><entry align="right">131</entry><entry align="center">1.41</entry></row><row><entry align="center">135</entry><entry align="center">5568</entry><entry align="right">1265</entry><entry align="right">4219</entry><entry align="right">84</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">137</entry><entry align="center">2965</entry><entry align="right">2143</entry><entry align="right">669</entry><entry align="right">153</entry><entry align="center">1.37</entry></row><row><entry align="center">138</entry><entry align="center">2948</entry><entry align="right">954</entry><entry align="right">1464</entry><entry align="right">530</entry><entry align="center">1.12</entry></row><row><entry align="center">139</entry><entry align="center">3889</entry><entry align="right">1331</entry><entry align="right">1978</entry><entry align="right">580</entry><entry align="center">1.13</entry></row><row><entry align="center">140</entry><entry align="center">3467</entry><entry align="right">1355</entry><entry align="right">1694</entry><entry align="right">418</entry><entry align="center">1.12</entry></row><row><entry align="center">142</entry><entry align="center">1641</entry><entry align="right">1481</entry><entry align="right">98</entry><entry align="right">62</entry><entry align="center">1.19</entry></row><row><entry align="center">144</entry><entry align="center">2901</entry><entry align="right">2720</entry><entry align="right">123</entry><entry align="right">58</entry><entry align="center">1.42</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0026">FIGs 1 and 2 demonstrate a correlation between these two compound classes and
the deposition rate performance of the chemical. Individual compounds found within
these two main groupings may have a more specific effect on the deposition
performance. The procedure described above is capable of measuring these
compounds specifically and thereby predicting the deposition performance of TDMAT
and TDEAT.</p><p num="0027">An analytical method capable of detecting hydrocarbon impurities in
tetrakis(dimethylamine)titanium (TDMAT) has been developed in the present invention.
The method is capable of detecting microgram quantities of hydrocarbon resulting in
detection limits in the parts-per-million range. Owing to the number of species detected,
individual compound calibration was impractical. The total hydrocarbon content is
reported as n-decane and is semi-quantitative due to the assumption that all
hydrocarbons have the same sensitivity as n-decane. Method validity was demonstrated
by spiking a TDMAT sample with 6800 and 3580 parts per million (ppm) by weight of n-decane.
Recovery was 106 and 120% by weight, respectively.</p><p num="0028">Assay, or the determination of molecular impurities, of
tetrakis(dimethylamine)titanium (TDMAT) is difficult since this compound has a very low 
volatility and cannot be analyzed using gas chromatography. A variety of stationary
phases and temperature profiles have been unsuccessful at providing repeatable results
indicating the overall purity of TDMAT samples. The air and moisture reactivity prevent
analysis using reversed phase liquid chromatography, a common technique for nonvolatile
or thermally labile compounds. Normal phase liquid chromatography was
unsuccessful at providing an assay, presumably the result of reaction of the TDMAT with
polar sites on the column packings and residual moisture in the mobile phase.</p><p num="0029">The current practice evaluating the TDMAT assay consists of obtaining a proton
nuclear magnetic resonance spectrum (NMR) and examining the spectrum for any small
peaks not assignable to TDMAT. The current procedure is qualitative in nature since the
sample preparation has not been controlled, nor is there any form of standardization or
calibration. Since NMR is capable of detecting impurities at approximately the 1% level,
the presence of any signal resolved from the TDMAT signal indicated an assay of &lt;99%.
Conversely, the absence of peaks indicated an assay of &gt;99% (all percents by weight).</p><p num="0030">The reactivity of TDMAT with moisture was utilized to develop a method to determine
trace hydrocarbons present in TDMAT. Rather than avoiding decomposition, the entire
sample is completely hydrolyzed. After hydrolysis, the sample can be extracted to
separate hydrocarbons not hydrolyzed from titanium dioxide and water-soluble
impurities, such as dimethylamine. These hydrocarbons are surmised to originate from
the solvents used to synthesize TDMAT since they are not by-products of the synthesis
reaction. Extraction was accomplished using solid-phase microextraction. This
technique uses a glass fiber coated with polymethyldisiloxane to absorb species with a
high affinity for the coating. Polar compounds (water, dimethylamine) have a low affinity
for the coating and are absorbed to a lesser extent. In this manner a hydrolyzed sample
can be extracted quickly and in repeatable fashion with limited use of solvents. </p><p num="0031">The absorbed species are desorbed in the hot injection port of a gas chromatograph
(GC) and are analyzed in normal gas chromatographic fashion using a suitable detector.
Relatively little water and dimethylamine are transferred to the GC insuring good
detectability for the hydrocarbon impurities.</p><p num="0032">Solid-phase microextraction (SPME) was performed using SPME equipment
available from Supelco Inc. (Bellefonte, PA). The type of fiber used was a 100)µm non-bonded
polymethyldisiloxane (PDMS) coated fiber with manual sample introduction. A
weighed aliquot of TDMAT (0.010 to 0.100g) is injected via syringe into a 5mL volume of
distilled deionized water in a closed 15 mL vial resulting in immediate hydrolysis. Volatile
species are retained since the vial contains a septum and cap. Following a period of at
least 10 minutes to allow the sample to equilibrate with the ambient temperature, the vial
headspace is sampled using the SPME fiber for 2.0 minutes. The fiber is transferred to
the GC injection port and compounds are desorbed for 1.0 minute at a temperature of
190°C. A typical chromatogram is provided in FIG 3 along with the GC conditions.</p><p num="0033">At approximately 1 minute, a broad double-humped peak elutes, the result of air
leakage into the GC during SPME fiber introduction. The width of this peak is dependent
on the time the SPME fiber is kept in the injection port of the GC. Superimposed on this
peak is a large peak due to water adsorbed by the fiber, and a smaller peak which is due
to dimethylamine produced by the hydrolysis of TDMAT. No other high volatility
components are detected. After approximately 8 minutes retention time, a series of
peaks from the hydrocarbon impurities begin. The n-decane peak was identified by GC-mass
spectrometry and by spiking a sample with n-decane.</p><p num="0034">The GC response for the hydrocarbons is dependent on two primary factors, the
sensitivity of the detector for each compound and the affinity of the fiber coating for each
compound. To calibrate accurately, the identity of each compound must be determined 
and both these factors determined. Initial experiments utilized GC-mass spectrometry to
identify the impurities extracted from the TDMAT. Mass spectral library searches
indicated that most compounds were C<sub>9</sub> to C<sub>20</sub> alkanes and some aromatic species such
as alkylbenzenes. The total number of impurities found was greater than 30. Owing to
the spectral similarity of many alkanes, definite identification of all the impurities was not
possible. The decision was made to proceed with a semi-quantitative approach, using a
single compound to estimate the concentration for all the impurities. N-decane was
chosen as its volatility (indicated by GC retention time) was median for the range of
hydrocarbons detected. Its affinity for the fiber is therefore expected to be typical of all
the hydrocarbons. The detector used was thermal conductivity detector (TCD) which
provides approximately uniform response for these compounds. All results are for total
hydrocarbons, reported as parts-per-million n-decane (ppm). Calculations were
performed using the total hydrocarbon peak area, obtained by integrating all peaks
between 7 and 14 minutes. No peaks eluted after 14 minutes.</p><p num="0035">Calibration is performed by preparing a standard of n-decane in isopropanol.
Weighed portions of the isopropanol solution are added to 5 mL of distilled water in 15
mL vials and sample in the same manner as hydrolyzed TDMAT to construct the
calibration curve. Calibrations were also performed via standard addition to determine if
the method sensitivity was affected by the presence of hydrolyzed TDMAT.</p><p num="0036">The SPME fiber has a limited capacity. This capacity was determined by analyzing
standards of increasing concentration and by varying the TDMAT sample size. FIG 4
and FIG 5 show plots of peak area versus sample amount.</p><p num="0037">The linear range of FIG 4 demonstrates that the fiber capacity is approximately 250
µg of decane. TDMAT samples producing total peak area results above 12000 would
require a smaller sample size since the response of the fiber/detector combination is
non-linear when the fiber is overloaded. The maximum sample size is governed by the 
hydrocarbon concentration of the sample. For hydrocarbon concentrations below 1 % by
weight, the maximum TDMAT sample size is approximately the fiber capacity divided by
the hydrocarbon concentration. ( 250 µg / 0.01 = 25,000 µg TDMAT or 25 µL). FIG 5
evaluates sample size by evaluating linearity as the sample size is increased. Sample
volumes up to 25 µL produced a linear response indicating that the fiber capacity had not
been exceeded. Both the n-decane calibration experiment and the TDMAT sample size
indicate approximately the same fiber capacity assuming the total hydrocarbon impurity
is approximately 1% by weight.</p><p num="0038">The presence of a matrix effect was evaluated by preparing a calibration curve in an
aqueous matrix and one containing hydrolyzed TDMAT and comparing the slope or
sensitivity. See Table 5 below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="3">Calibration data for hydrocarbons (expressed as decane) in aqueous and TDMAT matrices. Aqueous slope = 35.4, Aqueous standard error of slope = 2.6, TDMAT slope = 36.5, TDMAT standard error of slope = 6.5.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">µg Decane Added</entry><entry align="left">Area (aqueous matrix)</entry><entry align="left">Area (TDMAT matrix)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">0.0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">2940,3631</entry></row><row><entry align="left">11.0</entry><entry align="left">526.8</entry><entry align="left">3881,4002</entry></row><row><entry align="left">22.5</entry><entry align="left">823.3, 905.5, 1087</entry><entry align="left">3681, 4204</entry></row><row><entry align="left">45.0</entry><entry align="left">1627,1673</entry><entry align="left">5032,5032</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0039">The 95% confidence intervals of the slopes overlap, indicating that the presence of
hydrolyzed TMDAT does not significantly affect slope sensitivity. To simplify analysis,
future calibration was performed only in an aqueous matrix. Calibration should be
performed at regular intervals or whenever the SPME fiber is changed since the 
sensitivity is primarily dependent on the fiber affinity for the hydrocarbons and will
change over time or among fibers.</p><p num="0040">The calibration data reveal that precision can be poor, particularly in the TDMAT
matrix. Precision was evaluated both for replicate analyses and over different days.
Replicate analyses had a relative standard deviation of between 5 and 15%. Precision
was not different with aqueous or TDMAT-matrix samples and some
unknown/uncontrolled factor appears to be responsible for the high variances measured.
A contributing factor to the poor precision is the small sample size. The high affinity of
the fiber for the hydrocarbons and the relatively high hydrocarbon concentration in
TDMAT requires a small sample size. Control of the fiber adsorption and desorption
time interval improved the precision. Owing to the poor precision for some analyses, it is
recommended that a minimum of three sample preparations and analyses be performed
on each sample. It is not possible to re-analyze (absorb and introduce into a GC) a
hydrolyzed sample due to depletion of the hydrocarbons in the headspace by the
extraction procedure.</p><p num="0041">Analysis reproducibility was evaluated by analyzing 2 samples on different days.
Table 6 provides these results.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="3">Analysis reproducibility study. Average ± 1 standard deviation. (sa) - result obtained by 4 level standard addition, (d) - duplicate analyses, aqueous calibration, (t) - triplicate analyses, aqueous calibration.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample</entry><entry align="left">Result - Day 1</entry><entry align="left">Result - Day 2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lot A</entry><entry align="left">6224 (sa)</entry><entry align="left">6131 ± 195 (d)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lot B</entry><entry align="left">16,222 ± 826 (d)</entry><entry align="left">16019 ± 1053 (t)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0042">No precision estimate is available for Lot A, Day 1, since only 1 unspiked sample was
analyzed. There is no significant difference (95% confidence) between results obtained
on different days. The Lot B, Day 2 result had a high standard deviation due to one
apparent outlier (individuals were 16327, 16885, and 14846). However, the low point
could not be discarded using any outlier test since a good estimate of the method
variance is not available. Arbitrary removal of the low point improves the precision to
16606 ± 395. This result is not significantly different than the day 1 analysis.</p><p num="0043">Potential loss of hydrocarbon during the hydrolysis step, which is exothermic, was
evaluated by spiking decane directly into a TDMAT sample and performing the entire
analysis procedure. Two different amounts of decane were added to two aliquots of a
TDMAT sample. Results are summarized in Table 7.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry namest="1" nameend="5">Spike and recovery study results for n-decane spiked into TDMAT. All samples were analyzed in duplicate and the average hydrocarbon content (in ppm n-decane) is listed.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Unspiked Result (ppm)</entry><entry align="left">Spiked Result (ppm)</entry><entry align="left">Spike Concentration (ppm)</entry><entry align="left">Difference (Spiked Unspiked) (ppm)</entry><entry align="left">Percent Recovery</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8988</entry><entry align="left">16238</entry><entry align="left">6801</entry><entry align="left">7250</entry><entry align="center">106.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8988</entry><entry align="left">13300</entry><entry align="left">3582</entry><entry align="left">4312</entry><entry align="center">120.4</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0044">The recovery of n-decane added to TDMAT was satisfactory. The initial unspiked
sample was analyzed 1 day prior to the spike samples indicating good day-to-day
reproducibility.</p><p num="0045">An analytical method, capable of detecting hydrocarbon impurities in TDMAT has
been developed in accordance with the present invention. The analytical procedure
described is semi-quantitative since only a single compound, n-decane, is used for 
calibration. Although the current precision has a relative standard deviation of 5 - 15%,
the method is able to detect hydrocarbon impurities and distinguish among different
sources.</p><p num="0046">Current method limitations are the high relative precision and the semi-quantitative
results. The method could be made quantitative in nature by identifying all the impurities
and calibrating for each or developing relative response factors for each compound
relative to n-decane. These relative response factors would need to take into account
the affinity of each compound for the PDMS fiber.</p><p num="0047">Alternative analysis for hydrocarbon impurities and analysis of amines was studied
using tetrakis(diethylamino)titanium. Tetrakis (diethylamino) titanium (TDEAT) is purified
by short path distillation on a 6" wiped film still (Pope Scientific, Inc., Milwaukee,
Wisconsin).</p><p num="0048">Short path distillation is a process whereby low volatility chemicals can be
separated without extensive exposure to heat that would otherwise have the potential to
decompose the chemical or its constitutents. Chemical is introduced into a downflow
heated tubular inner wall of a distillation still under vacuum conditions. Coaxially within
the tubular heated wall is a condenser. Liquid chemical is drawn down the inner surface
of the heated wall of the still and more volatile constituents are vaporized and condensed
on the coaxially positioned condenser. Separate collection outlets remove the resulting
condensate or distillate and the lower volatile liquid or residue at the base of the still.</p><p num="0049">The original process parameters did not reduce a variety of volatile impurities
down to an acceptable concentration. These parameters, which include feed rate, rotor
speed, vacuum, wall temperature, post-wall temperature, main condenser temperature,
prefraction condenser temperature, and prefraction flask temperature, were optimized to
reduce the volatile impurities to acceptable concentrations. </p><p num="0050">Purification of TDEAT has been performed by wiped film distillation by the inventors.
The original parameters were determined by calculation, and once put into practice, they
were found to yield acceptable results using the analytical techniques that were in use at
that time. The only assay method in use was NMR. As the inventors further developed
this product, the inventors devised a technique to analyze for volatile compounds such
as hydrocarbons and amines. This new assay technique highlighted a need for
improved purification abilities.</p><p num="0051">The original parameters included an evaporation (wall) temperature of 120°C. This
temperature, at low pressures, is higher than needed for TDEAT evaporation. Hence,
higher boiling volatiles will also evaporate off of the wall. The original condensation
(finger) temperature was 10°C, and this was low enough not only to condense TDEAT,
but to condense many other lower boiling volatiles. These absolute temperatures do not
take into account the changes in vacuum within the distillation chamber, and the vacuum
in the chamber is dependent on a variety of factors, including raw material composition
and feed rate.</p><p num="0052">Two approaches were taken to address this problem. The first is based on a change
from absolute temperatures to relative temperatures. In light of the inherent problem in
controlling vacuum, the difference in temperature between the wall and the finger
becomes more important than the absolute temperature of the wall or the finger. Contact
time between the wall and the liquid, a function of rotor speed, was also addressed. This
allows raw material with a variety of compositions to be run in this system.</p><p num="0053">The second approach was a focus on a more robust system. More precise
temperature control was required to implement the first approach. This included
improved measuring of the liquid on the wall, as well as a temperature measurement of
the liquid as it left the heated portion of the wall. It also required improved finger 
temperature measurement. The temperature of the prefraction flask was lowered to
insure the lower boiling volatiles did not evaporate again after they were collected.</p><p num="0054">Six experiments were done to examine the effects of parameter changes on purity.</p><heading>Experiment #1</heading><p num="0055">This experiment was a graduated increase in the finger temperature from 10°C to
70°C. With all other parameters held constant, the finger was set at 10°C, 30°C, 50°C,
and 70°C. Two liters of raw material was processed at each setting for a total raw
material usage of eight liters. A sample was taken at each finger temperature, and the
volume of prefraction at each temperature was recorded. The samples were analyzed
for hydrocarbon (HC) profile.</p><p num="0056">This Table 8 compares the HC levels in ppm at various finger temperatures in
Experiment #1. The numbers are high because almost all of the prefraction is HC. The
volume collected increases as the temperature increases, showing that the lower boiling
HC's do not condense on the finger. The HC for this lot was 2630.
<img file="00200001.tif" id="img-EP-1511361-A2-00200001" he="76" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" orientation="unknown" inline="no"/></p><heading>Experiment #2</heading><p num="0057">This experiment was an optimization of the run by setting relative temperatures
for the wall and finger. With the finger temperature constant at 70°C, the wall
temperature was increased until the main fraction was seen flowing into the receiver.
With the wall temperature held at that temperature, the finger temperature was increased
until flow into the main receiver stopped. The finger temperature was then lowered until
flow resumed.</p><p num="0058">Table 9 shows the relationship between the wall and finger temperatures in
Experiment #2. Flow can be started or stopped by changing the evaporation (wall)
temperature or the condensation (finger) temperature. These temperatures are only
applicable to this run. The evaporation temperature was increased first, until at 90°C,
product flowed. It continued to flow until the condensation temperature increased to
85°C, when it stopped. It restarted as the temperature was lowered to 84°C. The HC for
this lot was 1772 ppm.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="10"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Wall (temp)</entry><entry align="left">70</entry><entry align="left">75</entry><entry align="left">80</entry><entry align="left">85</entry><entry align="left">90</entry><entry align="left">90</entry><entry align="left">90</entry><entry align="left">90</entry><entry align="left">90</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Finger (temp)</entry><entry align="left">70</entry><entry align="left">70</entry><entry align="left">70</entry><entry align="left">70</entry><entry align="left">70</entry><entry align="left">75</entry><entry align="left">80</entry><entry align="left">85</entry><entry align="left">84</entry></row><row><entry align="left">flow into rec'r</entry><entry align="left">no</entry><entry align="left">no</entry><entry align="left">no</entry><entry align="left">no</entry><entry align="left">yes</entry><entry align="left">yes</entry><entry align="left">yes</entry><entry align="left">no</entry><entry align="left">yes</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Experiment #3</heading><p num="0059">This experiment examined the effect of rotor speed and feed rate on purity.
Another thermocouple was added to the middle exterior of the wall to better approximate
the exact temperature of the liquid on the interior wall. Another thermocouple was added
at the bottom exterior of the wall to approximate the temperature of the liquid as it exited
the heated area. With all other parameters held constant, the rotor speed was varied 
from 200 RPM to 350 RPM to estimate the retention time of liquid on the wall. Liquid
was introduced into the chamber at a fixed rate, and the length of time to reach the
bottom of the chamber was estimated. The rotor speed was then held constant and the
feed rate was varied to observe the effect of flooding the wall with liquid and under-supplying
the wall with liquid. Optimums for feed rate, rotor speed, and all temperatures
were considered reached when the bottom wall temperature was 5°C less than the finger
temperature.</p><p num="0060">Table 10 compares the relative (delta) temperature between the evaporation
temperature (bottom) of the liquid exiting the chamber and the condensation temperature
(finger) for Experiment #3. The bottom temperature is a function of rotor speed, feed
rate, and wall temperature.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="10"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Time(hr)</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="left">9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Finger</entry><entry align="left">80</entry><entry align="left">84</entry><entry align="left">83</entry><entry align="left">84</entry><entry align="left">85</entry><entry align="left">83</entry><entry align="left">83</entry><entry align="left">84</entry><entry align="left">84</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bottom</entry><entry align="left">98</entry><entry align="left">82</entry><entry align="left">72</entry><entry align="left">72</entry><entry align="left">62</entry><entry align="left">66</entry><entry align="left">69</entry><entry align="left">80</entry><entry align="left">70</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Delta</entry><entry align="left">18</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="left">23</entry><entry align="left">17</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">14</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Experiment #4</heading><p num="0061">This experiment examined the effect of distilling material with a low hydrocarbon
impurity level. Lot #141 was redistilled at the parameters of Lot #142 in Table 13, below,
using the newly determined optimization techniques.</p><p num="0062">Table 11 is a comparison of the process parameters for lot #141 and lot #143.
The values are typical, but did vary. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">finger (temp)</entry><entry align="left">wall (temp)</entry><entry align="left">speed (RPM)</entry><entry align="left">vacuum (mTorr)</entry><entry align="left">rate (Lt./hr</entry><entry align="left">HC (ppm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lot 141</entry><entry align="left">70</entry><entry align="left">120</entry><entry align="left">202</entry><entry align="left">500</entry><entry align="center">2.2</entry><entry align="left">2630</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lot 143</entry><entry align="left">84</entry><entry align="left">83</entry><entry align="left">275</entry><entry align="left">500</entry><entry align="center">2.2</entry><entry align="left">33</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Experiment #5</heading><p num="0063">This experiment examined the effect of packing the prefraction flask in dry ice to
prevent any captured volatiles from evaporating again. The raw material was vendor lot
material, which has seen typical HC levels of 5000 ppm.</p><heading>Experiment #6</heading><p num="0064">This experiment examined the ability of the optimized process parameters to purify
rework material and customer returns. This type of raw material is normally in the 3000
ppm range.</p><p num="0065">Table 12 records the parameters for these lots. The values are typical, but did
vary.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">finger (temp)</entry><entry align="left">wall middle</entry><entry align="left">wall bottom</entry><entry align="left">wall setpoint</entry><entry align="left">speed (RPM)</entry><entry align="left">vacuum (mTorr)</entry><entry align="left">rate (Lt./hr</entry><entry align="left">HC (ppm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lot 144</entry><entry align="left">84</entry><entry align="left">87</entry><entry align="left">80</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">275</entry><entry align="left">800</entry><entry align="center">0.6</entry><entry align="left">70</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lot 145</entry><entry align="left">84</entry><entry align="left">86</entry><entry align="left">72</entry><entry align="left">96</entry><entry align="left">275</entry><entry align="left">1000</entry><entry align="center">0.7</entry><entry align="left">242</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0066">Table 13 is a summary of the test lots. The ranges given are highs and lows.
without any attention to average values <tables><table><tgroup cols="10"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Lot</entry><entry align="center">HC</entry><entry align="center">finger temp</entry><entry align="center">wall setpoint</entry><entry align="center">wall middle</entry><entry align="center">wall bottom</entry><entry align="center">vacuum (mTorr)</entry><entry align="center">rate Lt./hr</entry><entry align="center">speed RPM</entry><entry align="center">yield %</entry></row><row><entry align="center">141</entry><entry align="left">2630</entry><entry align="left">10-70</entry><entry align="left">120</entry><entry align="left">---</entry><entry align="left">---</entry><entry align="left">240-950</entry><entry align="left">2.2</entry><entry align="left">202</entry><entry align="left">75</entry></row><row><entry align="center">142</entry><entry align="left">1772</entry><entry align="left">78-84</entry><entry align="left">70-95</entry><entry align="left">---</entry><entry align="left">---</entry><entry align="left">425-700</entry><entry align="left">1.0</entry><entry align="left">350</entry><entry align="left">77</entry></row><row><entry align="center">143</entry><entry align="left">33</entry><entry align="left">80-85</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">80-91</entry><entry align="left">66-82</entry><entry align="left">450-600</entry><entry align="left">.85</entry><entry align="left">200-350</entry><entry align="left">71</entry></row><row><entry align="center">144</entry><entry align="left">70</entry><entry align="left">82-84</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">83-91</entry><entry align="left">70-84</entry><entry align="left">800-1200</entry><entry align="left">.6</entry><entry align="left">275</entry><entry align="left">74</entry></row><row><entry align="center">145</entry><entry align="left">242</entry><entry align="left">84</entry><entry align="left">59-96</entry><entry align="left">85-87</entry><entry align="left">68-72</entry><entry align="left">500-1100</entry><entry align="left">.7</entry><entry align="left">275</entry><entry align="left">66</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0067">Hydrocarbon impurities can be effectively removed by using appropriate process
parameters. Because the vacuum inside of the wiped film chamber is dependent on a
number of factors including raw material impurity concentrations, feed rate, wall
temperature, vacuum pump condition, liquid nitrogen trap temperature, and prefraction
condenser trap temperature, absolute temperatures do not do a good job of optimizing
the equipment capabilities. Relative temperatures are better suited to removing volatile
impurities. The relative separation between the evaporation temperature and the
condensation temperature is the best indicator of a proper short path distillation. The
absolute temperature around which these two temperatures lie can vary according to the
vacuum inside of the chamber, but the relative temperatures between them should
remain constant.</p><p num="0068">Condensation temperature is a reasonably simple measurement, but
measurement at the finger point of entry and exit is recommended in addition to a bath
measurement. A true measurement of the liquid wiped on the wall is a bit more difficult.
The simplest way to do this is to attach a thermocouple to the unheated wall directly
below the heated wall. The liquid that has not evaporated flows down the wall at this 
point, and it should be just above the condensation temperature. If it is below that
temperature, the distillation is inefficient because some of the TDEAT is not being
evaporated. If it is much above the condensation temperature, impurities that should
remain liquid will have also evaporated, thus decreasing the purity of the main fraction.</p><p num="0069">It is also important to insure that there is enough contact time between the wall
and the liquid to effect evaporation efficiently. There is also the danger that if the wall
temperature is too high, "hotspot" decomposition of the liquid could occur even if the
exiting temperature is normal. There is also the possibility of a flow rate low enough that
all of the liquid evaporates, including some high boiling impurities, before reaching the
bottom of the chamber. This is done by matching the middle column temperature to the
bottom temperature. This ensures that the liquid has reached an evaporation
temperature halfway through the retention time, that no additional heating is occurring in
the remaining retention time, and that the flow rate is high enough to preclude
evaporation to dryness before reaching the chamber bottom.</p><p num="0070">There is a slight decrease in yield, about 10% by weight, due to an increase in
the heels and prefraction. However, this technique allows rework of the heels and
prefraction to extract the remaining TDEAT, and this offsets some of the loss in yield.
This technique looks promising for optimizing any chemical purified by short path
distillation.</p><heading>Example #7.</heading><p num="0071">It was suggested that absorption would be a useful technique for reducing HC
impurities. Samples were prepared that contained approximately 1:1 ratio by weight of
TDEAT with an absorbent. Lot #140 was chosen as the source for the TDEAT for this
experiment, and titanium oxide, activated carbon, and Puraspec 2221 (ICI) were chosen
as the absorbents. These samples were agitated daily by hand, and sampled for HC 
content after one week. There was no identifiable change in the TiO2 sample. Most of
the color in the carbon sample was removed, as was some of the HC. In the Puraspec
sample, the HC was lowered to 315 ppm, and some of the color was removed. Several
repeat SPME tests for HC were run on the Puraspec sample, and values of 133 and 159
ppm HC were detected.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Sample#</entry><entry align="left">140VT</entry><entry align="left">Q2006-A</entry><entry align="left">Q2006-B</entry><entry align="left">Q2006-C</entry><entry align="left">Q2006-D</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Item</entry><entry align="left">Lot 140VT</entry><entry align="left">control</entry><entry align="left">TiO2</entry><entry align="left">carbon</entry><entry align="left">Puraspec</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HC</entry><entry align="left">4800</entry><entry align="left">4403</entry><entry align="left">4818</entry><entry align="left">2646</entry><entry align="left">315</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Experiment #8.</heading><p num="0072">Experiment #7 was repeated to verify the results, but the ratio of absorbent to
TDEAT was decreased to a 1:2 ratio by weight An extra sample of a 50/50 blend of
carbon and Puraspec 2221 was included to determine if both color and HC could be
improved in one step. Also, an intermediate sample (Q2013D) was removed from the
Puraspec 2221 vial after two days to check the removal efficiency of the absorbent, as
well as a control sample (Q2013A-1) at the same time. The Puraspec lowered the HC
level from 5475 ppm to 2793 ppm in 24 hours. The vials were sampled again after one
week, and the results are tabulated below. The same trends were noted, although the
decrease in absorbent showed a decrease in HC removal. The blend was successful in
removing both color and HC, but neither was removed at the efficiency of each pure
adsorbent alone. Again, the carbon was noted as removing the most color, and the
Puraspec 2221 was noted as removing the most HC. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Sample#</entry><entry align="left">140VT</entry><entry align="left">Q2015-A</entry><entry align="left">Q2015-B</entry><entry align="left">Q2015-C</entry><entry align="left">Q2015-D</entry><entry align="left">Q2015-E</entry></row><row><entry align="left">item</entry><entry align="left">Lot 140VT</entry><entry align="left">TiO2</entry><entry align="left">Blend</entry><entry align="left">carbon</entry><entry align="left">Puraspec</entry><entry align="left">control</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HC</entry><entry align="left">4800</entry><entry align="left">4570</entry><entry align="left">1036</entry><entry align="left">4010</entry><entry align="left">650</entry><entry align="left">4937</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Experiment #9.</heading><p num="0073">An experiment for testing the scale-up possibilities of Puraspec 2221 was done.
In a glovebox, a flask was charged with 2009 grams of TDEAT and 204 grams of
Puraspec 2221. This is 10% by weight and an approximate 4 to 1 ratio by volume of
TDEAT to absorbent. The sealed flask was stirred with a stirbar apparatus for one week.
It was sampled at two days, four days, and one week. The sample at one week was
taken after the absorbent was filtered out. The filtration was done through a 10 micron
filter (Arbortech, Model# Polycap HD), and finally through a 0.2 micron filter (Balston,
Model# AAQ). The process yielded approximately 2kg.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Sample#</entry><entry align="left">Q2030-A</entry><entry align="left">Q2030-B</entry><entry align="left">Q2033-A</entry><entry align="left">Q2033</entry><entry align="left">Q2046</entry></row><row><entry align="left">item</entry><entry align="left">2 day control</entry><entry align="left">2 day absorbed</entry><entry align="left">4 day control</entry><entry align="left">4 day absorbed</entry><entry align="left">final</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HC</entry><entry align="left">2988</entry><entry align="left">1552</entry><entry align="left">1932</entry><entry align="left">678</entry><entry align="left">441</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0074">It appears that absorption is a viable method for removing HC from TDEAT. It
also shows promise as a method for removing some of the color impurities. Additional
techniques for this process have been considered. These include pressure filtration,
high/low temperature filtration, sequential filtration, banded chromatography, and
recirculated filter beds. </p><heading>Experiment # 10.</heading><p num="0075">An experiment was done to observe the effects of a series of flask to flask (one
plate) distillations. A 5 liter flask was filled with TDEAT (Lot 140) and distilled under
dynamic vacuum. A prefraction of 10% by weight was taken and a heel of 10% by
weight was left. The main fraction was sampled, and the process was repeated for a total
of three distillations. This method appears to be another way to remove the HC content
in TDEAT. This experiment indicates that each distillation reduces HC to approximately
one fourth of the starting HC.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Sample#</entry><entry align="left">140VT</entry><entry align="left">Q2010VT</entry><entry align="left">Q2032VT</entry><entry align="left">Q2041 VT</entry></row><row><entry align="left">item</entry><entry align="left">lot material</entry><entry align="left">1X</entry><entry align="left">2X</entry><entry align="left">3X</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HC</entry><entry align="left">4800</entry><entry align="left">1677</entry><entry align="left">469</entry><entry align="left">92</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Experiment # 11.</heading><p num="0076">An Oldershaw distillation system was built to examine TDEAT behavior in this
type of apparatus. The 5 liter reboiler was fitted with a 1" 5-plate Oldershaw column, and
the system was placed under a dynamic vacuum of 500 mTorr (+/- 200 mTorr). Two
runs were made in which a prefraction was taken and a main fraction was collected. The
first run was a rework of Lot #135, and the second was a batch using material from a
different source. The color in the main fractions was noted as much improved over the
raw color. This technique is also a usable method for removing hydrocarbons. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Sample#</entry><entry align="left">Q1093VT</entry><entry align="left">Q1097VT</entry><entry align="left">Q2002VT</entry><entry align="left">Q2014VT</entry></row><row><entry align="left">item</entry><entry align="left">run #1-raw</entry><entry align="left">run#1-main</entry><entry align="left">run#2-raw</entry><entry align="left">run#2-main</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HC</entry><entry align="left">9019</entry><entry align="left">1107</entry><entry align="left">3720</entry><entry align="left">1780</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0077">Based upon the results discussed above, the inventors for the first time have
been able to determine a methodology for predicting deposition rates for titanium
containing precursors based upon analyzed amine and hydrocarbon contents for various
batches or lots of commercially produced titanium containing precursors for end uses,
such as the electronics fabrication industry, where yield and throughput are critical to the
economics of integrated circuit manufacture.</p><p num="0078">Accordingly the present inventors have determined a process for determining a
predicted deposition rate of a batch of a titanium containing precursor in a chemical
vapor deposition of a titanium containing compound on a substrate, comprising;
analyzing the organic amine content of the batch to determine an analytical amine
content, comparing the analytical amine content against an amine content standard
(which can be compiled from averaging a series of amine content analyses) and
determining the predicted deposition rate from a deposition rate standard (which can be
compiled from averaging a series of titanium compound depositions) based upon the
deviation of the analytical amine content from the amine content standard, wherein the
predicted deposition rate is greater than the deposition rate standard when the analytical
amine content is greater than the amine content standard and the predicted deposition
rate is less than the deposition rate standard when the analytical amine content is less
than the amine content standard.</p><p num="0079">Similarly, the present inventors have determined a process for determining a
predicted deposition rate of a batch of a titanium containing precursor in a chemical 
vapor deposition of a titanium containing compound on a substrate, comprising;
analyzing the hydrocarbon content of the batch to determine an analytical hydrocarbon
content, comparing the analytical hydrocarbon content against an hydrocarbon content
standard (which can be compiled from averaging a series of hydrocarbon content
analyses) and determining the predicted deposition rate from a deposition rate standard
(which can be compiled from averaging a series of titanium compound depositions)
based upon a deviation of the analytical hydrocarbon content from the hydrocarbon
content standard, wherein the predicted deposition rate is less than the deposition rate
standard when the analytical hydrocarbon content is greater than the hydrocarbon
content standard and the predicted deposition rate is greater than the deposition rate
standard when the analytical hydrocarbon content is less than the hydrocarbon content
standard.</p><p num="0080">The present inventors have also determined a methodology for correlating the
analyzed amine contents and the analyzed hydrocarbon contents for a batch of titanium
containing precursor to determine a predicted deposition rate based upon the impact or
influence of both amine and hydrocarbon contents in such batches.</p><p num="0081">The present invention provides techniques to ascertain amine and hydrocarbon
content and/or impurities, respectively in titanium containing precursors for titanium
compound deposition so as to enhance the deposition rate of the titanium compound. At
the low ppm levels that effect enhancement of deposition rate (amine) or retard
deposition rate (hydrocarbon), it is critical to have analytical techniques sensitive enough
to detect such low levels of amine or hydrocarbon functionality. The detection of levels
of amine or hydrocarbon or the specific doping or spiking of amine with controlled
amounts of amine is important to be able to accurately and precisely predict the
deposition rate of commercial lots of titanium containing precursor for customers using
the titanium containing precursor to deposit titanium containing films, particu larly in the 
electronics fabrication industry, which requires precise recipies and reproducible results
to sustain mass production of high yields of acceptable integrated circuits and related
electronic devices.</p><p num="0082">In addtion, the discovery of the impact of amine content and hydrocarbon
impurities in titanium containing precursor deposition rates has led to the discovery of
novel and unexpected processes for enhancing the process of deposition of titanium
containing compounds, such as films, for integrated circuits and other electronic devices.
It is not obvious that amine addition to titanium containing precursors would enhance the
deposition rate of titanium compounds on a substrate because for many of the preferred
commercially viable titanium containing precursors, such as TDMAT and TDEAT, amine
functionality is a byproduct of the decomposition of such precursors during CVD
deposition of titanium nitride on semiconductor substrates from such precursors.</p><p num="0083">The present invention has been set forth with regard to several preferred
embodiments, but the full scope of the present invention should be ascertained from the
claims which follow. </p><heading>SEQUENCE LISTING</heading><p num="0084">Not applicable.</p></description><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process for enhancing the deposition of titanium containing materials on a substrate
from a titanium containing precursor by the reduction of hydrocarbon impurities
from the titanium containing precursor prior to deposition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1 wherein the deposition is a chemical vapour deposition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A process for determining a predicted deposition rate of a batch of a titanium containing
precursor in a chemical vapour deposition of a titanium containing compound
on a substrate, comprising: analyzing the hydrocarbon content of said batch
to determine an analytical hydrocarbon content, comparing said analytical hydrocarbon
content against an hydrocarbon content standard and determining said predicted
deposition rate from a deposition rate standard based upon the deviation of
the analytical hydrocarbon content from said hydrocarbon content standard.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The process of Claim 3 wherein said predicted deposition rate is less than the deposition
rate standard when said analytical hydrocarbon content is greater than said
hydrocarbon content standard and said predicted deposition rate is greater than said
deposition rate standard when said analytical hydrocarbon content is less than said
hydrocarbon content standard.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The process of Claim 3 wherein said analyzing the hydrocarbon content of said
batch is an analysis selected from the group consisting of solid-phase microextraction
and short path distillation on a wiped film still.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The process of Claim 3 wherein said titanium containing precursor is selected from
the group consisting of tetrakis(dimethylamino)titanium, tetrakis(diethylamino)titanium
and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20050302"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20041201</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AC" date="20050302"><legal-event-body><event-title>DIVISIONAL APPLICATION (ART. 76) OF:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>1091018</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20050302"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>
