<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1128644-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1128644" kind="B1" date="20051228"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23214271" ucid="EP-1128644-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1128644</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20051228</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01301516-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01301516</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010221</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000044509-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000044509</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000222</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20050705</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F   1/16        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G06F   1/16        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/03        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/03        20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/247       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/247       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/60        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/60        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/72        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M   1/725       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M  11/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04M  11/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04Q   7/32        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H04Q   7/32        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04M1/02A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04M1/03</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04M1/60T2B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H04M1/725F1B1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04M1:02A2B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T04M1:02A2B4</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Kommunikationsendgerät</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Communication terminal device</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Dispositif terminal de communication</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SONY CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SONY CORPORATION</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HINO ICHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KOSHIMURA KATSUMI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>HINO, ICHIRO</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KOSHIMURA, KATSUMI</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>HINO, ICHIRO</last-name><address><street>c/o Sony Corporation, 7-35, Kitashinagawa 6-chome</street><city>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>KOSHIMURA, KATSUMI</last-name><address><street>11-16-503 Nakamura-Minami 1-chome</street><city>Nerima-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>SONY CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>7-35, Kitashinagawa 6-chome, Shinagawa-ku</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Nicholls, Michael John</last-name><address><street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14, South Square Gray's Inn</street><city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>A communication terminal device is miniaturized in a shape handy to carry while maintaining the necessary operability. The terminal device is constituted by a first box for voice communication and a second box linked with-the first box via short-distance radio link for data input and data display. The first box is provided with minimum functions necessary for the voice communication so as to be small, whereas the second box can be provided with a keyboard high in operability and a relatively large display means so that display and input for data communication can be made conveniently. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">A communication terminal device is miniaturized in a shape
handy to carry while maintaining the necessary operability. The
terminal device is constituted by a first box for voice
communication and a second box linked with-the first box via short-distance
radio link for data input and data display. The first box
is provided with minimum functions necessary for the voice
communication so as to be small, whereas the second box can be
provided with a keyboard high in operability and a relatively large
display means so that display and input for data communication can
be made conveniently.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1129058-A1-00000001" he="110" wi="77" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a communication terminal
device suitably applied for example to a wireless telephone device
called a portable telephone terminal.</p><p num="0002">A variety of mobile telephone terminals used as a wireless
telephone device have been practically used. These conventional
portable telephone terminals comprises a box including a microphone
and a speaker for voice communication, a key input portion for
inputting a telephone number, a function command and so on, and a
display portion for displaying the telephone number and so on. This
basic constitution is common in all of the terminals.</p><p num="0003">Basically, the portable telephone terminal has to be made
small so that the user can always carry and transmit and/or receive
information at any place. However, if each of the components
described above is to be disposed within a single box, there is a
limit in the size and shape as the terminal.</p><p num="0004">Further, recently, some portable telephone terminals are
capable of not only making voice communication but also making data
transmission including such data as character data and image data.
In such a terminal capable of performing these functions, a
relatively large display portion has to be disposed as the display
portion, thus leading to a problem of increased size of the 
terminal.</p><p num="0005">Further, when inputting a character message, a common method used at
present is that the inputting of characters is made by using dialing keys and so on.
However, inputting the characters by using such a limited number of keys poses a
problem of low operability.</p><p num="0006">The present invention is made for the situation described above, and it is
therefore an object of the present invention to make it possible that the
communication terminal device is miniaturized in a shape for good portability
while maintaining the operability necessary for the communication terminal device.</p><p num="0007"><ref type="patent">US-A-5,983,073</ref> on which the pre-characterising portion of claim 1 is based
discloses a modular microcomputer-based communications system which includes a
notebook computer data telephone handset which may be connected together by wire
or short range radio link. <ref type="patent">EP-A-0669746</ref> discloses a cordless telephone system
having base stations and handsets, and which can communicate with a computer via
wire or radio link.</p><p num="0008">The present invention provides a portable communication terminal device as
defined in claim 1.</p><p num="0009">According to the above described invention, voice communication can be
made by using the communication means provided in the first housing. For data
transmission in which a character message, image data and so on are transmitted,
received data can be displayed in the display means provided in the second housing
whereas inputting operation of the necessary data can be performed by using the
inputting means provided in the second housing.</p><p num="0010">Embodiments of the invention will now be described, by way of example
only, with reference to the accompanying drawings in which:-
<sl><li>FIG. 1 is a block diagram showing a constitution according to a first
embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a perspective view showing an example of a telephone terminal
device according to the first embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a perspective view showing an example of a state in which a 
microphone of the terminal device in FIG. 2 is opened;</li><li>FIG. 4 is a perspective view showing a data inputting/outputting device
according to the first embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 5 is a perspective view showing a state in which the data
inputting/outputting device in FIG. 4 is closed;</li><li>FIG. 6 is a perspective view showing a state in which a display portion of the
data inputting/outputting device in FIG. 4 is pivoted;</li><li>FIG. 7 is a perspective view showing a state in which the 
data inputting/outputting device in FIG. 4 is closed (with the
display portion turned over);</li><li>FIG. 8 is a block diagram showing a constitution according
to a second embodiment of the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 9 is a perspective view showing an example of a
telephone terminal device according to the second embodiment of the
present invention; and</li><li>FIG. 10 is a perspective view showing an example of a state
in which an ear piece of the terminal device in FIG. 9 is detached.</li></sl></p><p num="0011">Hereinafter, a first embodiment of the present invention
will be described with reference to FIG. 1 to FIG. 7.</p><p num="0012">In the present embodiment, the present invention is
applicable to a wireless telephone device (portable telephone
terminal) in which voice communication and data transmission are
performed by wirelessly exchanging digital data of a predetermined
format with a station for example. According to the present
embodiment, a set of terminal device is constituted by a pair of
housings, namely portable telephone terminal 100 for performing
radio communication with the station (or another authorized terminal
device of the same kind), and data inputting/outputting device 200
for performing data inputting and outputting operation.</p><p num="0013">FIG. 1 is a block diagram showing the constitution of
portable telephone terminal 100 and data inputting/outputting device
200 as the components of the terminal device according to the
present embodiment. First, the constitution of portable telephone 
terminal 100 will be described. Portable telephone terminal 100
includes antenna 111 for performing radio communication &quot;a&quot; with the
station for a wireless telephone. Antenna 111 is connected with
receiving circuit 113 and transmitting circuit 114 via antenna
sharing device 112. Receiving circuit 113 performs receiving
operation of radio signals in a predetermined channel assigned for
the wireless telephone, whereas transmitting circuit 114 performs
transmitting operation of radio signals in a predetermined channel
assigned for the wireless telephone.</p><p num="0014">Receiving circuit 113 and transmitting circuit 114 are
connected with data processing portion 115. Data processing portion
115 performs such data processing operations of the received data as
decoding of the received data by receiving circuit 113, separating
of individual datum from the decoded data, and so on. As processing
operation of the data to be transmitted, data processing portion 115
performs such data processing operation as blocking of the data to
be transmitted, encoding of the blocked data, and so on. The
processed data is then supplied to transmitting circuit 114.</p><p num="0015">Data processing portion 115 is connected with sound
processing portion 116 for processing sound data for voice
communication. Sound processing portion 116 is connected with
speaker 117 and microphone 118 as means of the voice communication.
Sound processing portion 116 is supplied with sound data contained
in the received data supplied to data processing portion 115. The
sound data is then decoded, and converted into the analog sound
signal, which is supplied to speaker 117 as an output. On the other
hand, the sound signal outputted from microphone 118 is converted by 
sound processing portion 116 into the digital signal, and then
encoded, such as compression coded, into sound data of a
predetermined format, which is then supplied to data processing
portion 115.</p><p num="0016">The processings in receiving circuit 113, transmitting
circuit 114, data processing portion 115 and sound processing
portion 116, which have been described heretofore, are executed
under control of central processing unit (CPU) 120 which is a
microprocessor controlling various operations of portable telephone
terminal 100. CPU 120 is supplied with operation information of key
121 and jog dial 122 disposed in portable telephone terminal 100.
Key 121 includes only a limited number of keypads from a set of
keypads necessary as a telephone terminal, and these keypads are
disposed in terminal 100. Further, CPU 120 controls display on
display portion 130 constituted by a relatively small display panel.</p><p num="0017">Further, portable telephone terminal 100 according to the
present embodiment includes short-distance transmitting/receiving
circuit 123 of small transmission output capacity for short-distance
communication up to a few meters for example, and antenna 124
connected with this transmitting/receiving circuit 123. Received
data obtained at data processing portion 115 is processed for
transmission by transmitting/receiving circuit 123 for radio
transmission from antenna 124 in a predetermined band,and the signal
received at antenna 124 is processed for receiving by transmitting/receiving
circuit 123, whereas data received is supplied to data
processing portion 115. The frequency band for the transmission and
the reception performed by short-distance transmitting/receiving 
circuit 123 is the 2.4 GHz band of Blue Tooth, for example. The
transmission and reception by this transmitting/receiving circuit
123 are also executed under the control of CPU 120.</p><p num="0018">Next, constitution of data inputting/outputting device 200
will be described. Data inputting/outputting device 200 includes
short-distance transmitting/receiving circuit 212 of a small
transmission output capacity for short-distance communication up to
a few meters for example, and antenna 211 connected with this
transmitting/receiving circuit 212. By using transmitting/receiving
circuit 212 and antenna 211, short-distance, two-way radio
communication &quot;b&quot; can be made with transmitting/receiving circuit
123 and antenna 124 in portable telephone terminal 100.</p><p num="0019">Transmitting/receiving circuit 212 is connected with data
processing portion 213. Data processing portion 213 performs
processing operation necessary for data received by transmitting/receiving
circuit 212, and further, supplies data accumulated in
data processing portion 213 for transmission, from data processing
portion 213 to transmitting/receiving circuit 212 for radio
transmission to portable telephone terminal 100. This short-distance
radio communication &quot;b&quot; between portable telephone terminal
100 and data inputting/outputting device 200 is made for data
obtained at data inputting/outputting device 200 to be sent from
portable telephone terminal 100 to the wireless telephone link, and
for data received from the wireless telephone channels by portable
telephone terminal 100 to be forwarded to data inputting/outputting
device 200. Further, the short-distance radio communication &quot;b&quot; can
also be used for transmission of status data of portable telephone 
terminal 100 to the data inputting/outputting device 200. For
example, data indicating if portable telephone terminal 100 is
located in or out of the wireless telephone service area and data
about remaining charge in a battery incorporated in terminal 100 can
be transmitted.</p><p num="0020">Further, data inputting/outputting device 200 is provided
with display portion 220 so that data obtained at data processing
portion 213 can be displayed. For example, when character message
data is received, the character message can be displayed. Further,
when image data is received, the image (a still image or an
animation) can also be displayed. Display portion 220 can be used
in two display modes: One edge of the display portion is the upper
edge in one mode whereas the opposite edge becomes the upper edge in
the other mode. Setting status of the display portion of these
modes will be described later.</p><p num="0021">Further, data inputting/outputting device 200 is provided
with memory card insertion portion 214, so that received data and
data inputted by the user can be stored in a memory card inserted in
memory card insertion portion 214.</p><p num="0022">Processing operation performed in data inputting/outputting
device 200 is executed under the control of central processing unit
(CPU) 215 which is a microprocessor controlling various operations
in data inputting/outputting device 200. CPU 215 is supplied with
operation information of keyboard 216 disposed in data inputting/outputting
device 200. Keyboard 216 disposed in the data
inputting/outputting device 200 is provided with a relatively large
number of keypads assigned to an alphabet for example. </p><p num="0023">Keyboard 216 is used for inputting a message to be
transmitted. The inputted data can be displayed in display portion
220 for confirmation. If the confirmed data is to be transmitted,
then a predetermined operation is performed in data inputting/outputting
device 200, so that the data is sent to portable
telephone terminal 100, and then data is transmitted from portable
telephone terminal 100 to an intended destination identified by a
predetermined telephone number via the wireless telephone channels.
Therefore, it is possible to input the telephone number of the
destination upon transmission and to perform transmitting operation
on keyboard 216 of data inputting/outputting device 200.</p><p num="0024">FIG. 2 is a diagram showing an example of an outlook of
portable telephone terminal 100 according to the present embodiment
portable telephone terminal 100 according the present embodiment is
packaged in a very small housing having a length less than 10 cm for
example. According to this example, oblong display portion 130 is
disposed in a center portion of an upper surface, and speaker 117
for the voice communication is disposed thereabove. Further,
antenna 111 is disposed at the upper end and several key pads 121
are disposed on a side portion. According to FIG. 2, portable
telephone terminal 100 is provided with strap 101.</p><p num="0025">Display portion 130 shows only simple display relevant to
selected functions out of many displays necessary in the radio
telephoning. Specifically, according to the example in FIG. 2 for
example, the display includes a display of current day and time 131,
level display 132 of a plurality of levels indicating if portable
telephone terminal is within the wireless telephone service area, 
charge level display 133 of the battery incorporated in portable
telephone terminal 100, and arrival indication display 134 of a mail
and so on.</p><p num="0026">Further, according to the example shown in FIG. 2, the
microphone is foldable, i.e. arm 102 which is pivotable around pivot
fulcrum 102a is attached. As shown in FIG. 3, when arm 102 is
pivoted out, the microphone 118 attached in a tip portion thereof
comes at the farthest location from speaker 117. As shown in FIG.
3, by pivoting out arm 102, voice communication can be performed by
using microphone 118 and speaker 117.</p><p num="0027">It should be noted here that according to this example, some
of the key pads disposed as key pads 121 becomes exposed and
operable when arm 102 is pivoted out as shown in FIG. 3. Further,
according to this example, portable telephone terminal 100 is not
provided with keypads corresponding to numbers 0 to 9 and other
symbols for inputting a telephone number. The inputting of a
telephone number can be made for example, by operating jog dial 124.
Further, dialing to a telephone number which is registered in a
telephone number directory function, dialing to a telephone number
based on a transmission/reception history and so on can be made
simply by displaying the corresponding telephone number operating
jog dial 124.</p><p num="0028">FIG. 4 shows an example of an outlook of data inputting/outputting
device 200 according to this embodiment. Data inputting/outputting
device 200 according to the present embodiment is
packaged into a relatively small housing, having a length slightly
longer than 10 cm, a width of a few cm, and a thickness of 1 cm for 
example. Data inputting/outputting device 200 according to the
present example includes first member 201 and second member 202
connected pivotably with each other by a pivoting mechanism 203.
First member 201 has a surface provided with keyboard 216 including
a plurality of keypads assigned to an alphabet, numbers and various
functions. Further, a front edge portion is provided with dial key
216a and two keys 216b, 216c indicating the left and the right
directions respectively.</p><p num="0029">Further, first member 201 has a side surface provided with
an opening for memory card insertion portion 214 for inserting and
fitting of memory card 10 of a predetermined standard. Memory card
10 suitably used for the present example is a stick type (an oblong
plate type) memory card for example.</p><p num="0030">Second member 202 has a surface provided with display
portion 220 constituted by a display panel having an area occupying
most of the surface. Display portion 220 can display character data
and an image. In addition, level indication 221 showing whether or
not portable telephone terminal 100 is within the service area, and
battery charge level indication 222 of portable telephone terminal
100 can be displayed in an edge portion of the screen. Further,
display 223 prompting to a key operation for opening a menu screen,
and display 224 prompting to a key operation for opening a mode
selection screen are displayed.</p><p num="0031">Further, second member 202 provided with display portion 220
has base portion 204 directly attached to pivoting mechanism 203,
and therefore can be rotated by angle of 180 degrees so that an
upper surface can be turned around to become a back surface. 
Specifically, in data inputting/outputting device 200 according to
the present embodiment, pivoting mechanism 203 allows the two
members to make the smallest angle, thereby closing first member 201
and second member 202, so that second member 202 serves as lid to
cover keyboard 216, as shown in FIG. 5 for-example. At this time,
dial key 216a and two keys 216b, 216c disposed in the front edge
portion are not covered by second member 202 and are exposed. This
state shown in FIG. 5 is a normal closed state.</p><p num="0032">Further, first member 201 and second member 202 can be
pivoted to make a greater angle, and then second member 202 can be
rotated at angle of 180 degrees around the center portion as a
fulcrum between second member 202 and base portion 204 to turn
display portion 220 around as shown in FIG. 6. Under this state,
the two members can be pivoted to make the smallest angle by
pivoting mechanism 203, thereby closing first member 201 and second
member 202, so that second member 202 serves as the lid to cover
keyboard 216, with the display panel constituting display portion
220 exposed to the outside as shown in FIG. 7 for example.</p><p num="0033">It should be noted that if display portion 220 is turned
over as described above, the display made in display portion 220 is
made upside down. This inversion is performed for example by CPU
215 supplied with information from a detecting mechanism detecting
the state of second member 202 (normal or reversed) at base portion
204.</p><p num="0034">The state shown in FIG. 7 allows the user to see display on
display portion 220 in the closed state. Further, the user can
perform simple operations since dial key 216a and two keys 216b, 
216c in the front edge portion are exposed.</p><p num="0035">The device according to the present example, comprising the
two housings, one including portable telephone terminal 100 for
voice communication and the other including data inputting/outputting
device 200 for display and input, provides convenience in
that telephone conversation can be made only by using very small
portable telephone terminal 100. In this case, although there are
no dialing keys provided in portable telephone terminal 100, dialling
operation can be made very simply by using the jog dial and so on
resistering frequently used telephone numbers and so on in the
telephone directory function. Inputting operation of a telephone
number and so on can be made by using data inputting/outputting
device 200. That is, a user inputs information such as a telephone
number from keyboard 216 in data inputting/outputting device 200,
and then data processing such as modulation, which is necessary for
the transmission via Blue Tooth, is performed in data processing
portion 213 and transmitting/receiving portion 212. The processed
input information is then transmitted via antenna 211 to telephone
terminal 100. The input information transmitted to telephone
terminal 100 is received by antenna 124. The received information
is then inputted to transmitting/receiving portion 123, processed
for demodulation etc. and the demodulated information is stored in
the telephone directory function area and so on in memory 125 via
CPU 120. Registration of information such as telephone numbers is
thus completed.</p><p num="0036">Further, in order to read a character message received and
to input a character message to send, data inputting/outputting 
device 200 can be used conveniently because the relatively large
display panel and the keyboard allow efficient data inputting and
confirmation.</p><p num="0037">Further, according to the present invention, since portable
telephone terminal 100 and data inputting/outputting device 200 are
linked with each other by the short distance radio transmission,
there is no need for signal lines etc. to connect the two
components, leading to a convenience.</p><p num="0038">Next, a second embodiment of the present invention will be
described with reference to FIG. 8 to FIG. 10. In FIG. 8 to FIG.
10, elements corresponding to those in FIG. 1 to FIG. 7 described in
the first embodiment will be indicated by the same alpha-numerals
without description in detail.</p><p num="0039">According to the present embodiment, as in the first
embodiment, the present invention is applied to wireless telephone
device (portable telephone terminal) in which voice communication
and data communication are performed by wirelessly exchanging
digital data of a predetermined format with a station. According to
the present embodiment, a unit of the communication terminal device
is constituted by a pair of housings, namely portable telephone
terminal 100' for performing radio communication with the station
(or another authorized terminal device of the same kind), and data
inputting/outputting device 200 for performing data input and output
operation.</p><p num="0040">Further, according to the present embodiment, the speaker
portion of portable telephone terminal 100' can be detached from a
main body of the terminal and used as ear piece 300 as needed. </p><p num="0041">FIG. 8 is a block diagram showing a constitution of the
present embodiment. Portable telephone terminal 100' includes
microphone 118 as means for voice communication, but does not
include a speaker. Sound processing portion 116 is connected with a
terminal 116a for transmitting sound signals to ear piece 300.
Other circuit constitution is identical with that of portable
telephone terminal 100 shown in FIG. 1.</p><p num="0042">Portable telephone terminal 100' has an upper portion
formed with a place to be fitted by ear piece 300. Ear piece 300 is
provided with terminal 304a to be connected with the terminal 116a
of portable telephone terminal 100'. Terminal 304a is connected
with sound processing portion 304. Sound processing portion 304 is
connected with speaker 305 and microphone 306. Microphone 306 is of
a type capable of picking up the user's voice near an ear of the
user.</p><p num="0043">When ear piece 300 is fitted into the upper portion of
portable telephone terminal 100', sound processing portion 116 of
portable telephone terminal 100' and sound processing portion 304 of
ear piece 300 are directly connected with each other via terminals
116a, 304a. Then, if voice communication is made under this state,
the conversation is made by using speaker 305 in ear piece 300 and
microphone 118 incorporated in portable telephone terminal 100'. In
other words, microphone 306 in ear piece 300 is not used.</p><p num="0044">Further, ear piece 300 includes short-distance
transmitting/receiving circuit 302 of a small transmission output
capacity for short-distance communication up to a few meters for
example, antenna 301 connected with this transmitting/receiving 
circuit 302, and data processing portion 303 for processing data
received by transmitting/receiving circuit 302 and data to be
transmitted thereby. Transmitting/receiving circuit 302 and the
antenna 301 perform radio communication &quot;c&quot; with transmitting/receiving
circuit 123 and antenna 124 of portable telephone terminal
100'. Data processing portion 303 is connected with sound
processing portion 304 of ear piece 300. Through the radio
communication &quot;c&quot; between ear piece 300 detached from portable
telephone terminal 100' and portable telephone terminal 100', the
user can make a telephone dialogue only by using ear piece 300.</p><p num="0045">FIG. 9 is a diagram showing an example of an outlook of
portable telephone terminal 100' according to the present
embodiment. Portable telephone terminal 100' according the present
embodiment is packaged in a very small housing having a length less
than 10 cm for example. According to this example, oblong display
portion 130 is disposed in a center portion of an upper surface, and
speaker 117 for voice communication is disposed thereabove.
Further, antenna 111 is disposed at the upper end and several key
pads 121 are disposed on a side portion. According to FIG. 9,
portable telephone terminal 100 is provided with a strap 101.</p><p num="0046">Further, an upper portion is provided with attaching portion
140 for attaching ear piece 300. When ear piece 300 is attached to
attaching portion 140 from a backside of terminal 100', the speaker
305 in ear piece 300 is exposed so as to function as a speaker of
portable telephone terminal 100' for voice communication.</p><p num="0047">FIG. 10 is a diagram showing a state in which ear piece 300
is detached from portable telephone terminal 100'. Part of ear 
piece 300 provided with speaker 305 is formed to fit in a ear so
that the user can wear, and has a side surface provided with
microphone 306. By detaching ear piece 300 from portable telephone
terminal 100' and fitting into ear of the user, voice communication
becomes possible by using ear piece 300 only.</p><p num="0048">Data inputting/outputting device 200, which is not described
in particular for this embodiment, is the same as data inputting/outputting
device 200 described for the first embodiment.</p><p num="0049">As has been exemplified above, by using the terminal device
according to the present embodiment, voice communication is possible
as a normal portable telephone terminal, with the ear piece attached
to portable telephone terminal, and in addition, if the ear piece is
detached, the user can make the voice communication very
conveniently by only wearing the ear piece. (Portable telephone
terminal 100' must stay close to the user, however.) It should be
noted here that the ear piece may be provided with keypads for
selected functions.</p><p num="0050">Further, according to the second embodiment, the terminal
device comprises portable telephone terminal 100' and data
inputting/outputting device 200 and the ear piece is detachable from
the terminal main body 100'. Alternatively, a normal portable
telephone terminal not paired with data inputting/outputting device
200 may have its speaker portion as a detachable ear piece.</p><p num="0051">Further, according to the first and the second embodiments
described above, the communication terminal is portable telephone
terminal which uses radio telephone channels. However, the present
invention is also applicable to terminal devices using other 
communication links.</p><p num="0052">According to the present invention, voice communication can
be performed by using the communication means provided in the first
housing. Further, when transmitting such data as a character
message and image data, the display means provided in the second
housing can be used for displaying received data, and the inputting
means provided in the second housing can be used for inputting
necessary data. Therefore, the first housing can be provided with
only minimum necessary functions for the communication. For
example, there is no need to provide the dial key or a large display
panel, and therefore the first housing can be made very small
suitable for carrying. Further, by using the second housing,
received character message and image can be displayed on the
relatively large display panel. In addition, inputting of a message
to be transmitted can be made relatively easily, with an improved
operability. In this case, there is no need for a signal wire and
the like because the first housing and the second housing are
wirelessly connected.</p><p num="0053">With the above described arrangement, further, between the
region where the display means is disposed and the region where the
input means is disposed in the second housing, the angle adjusting
mechanism capable of variably changing an angle between the two
means is provided. Further, the inverting mechanism capable of
turning the display means by the angle of 180 degrees is provided.
These make possible to use the second housing in many different
ways.</p><p num="0054">Further, with the above described arrangement in the second 
housing, when the angle between the display means and the input
means is made the smallest, most of the input means are covered by
the region where the display means is disposed. However, part of
the input means are not covered and left exposed. These make
possible to perform simple operations by using the display means and
the exposed portion of the input means, with received data and so on
visible on the display.</p><p num="0055">Still further, the display means of the second housing is
arranged to display radio communication status of the first radio
communication means and data processing status of the first data
processing means in the first housing. This makes possible that the
user can check if the communication service is available and if
there is enough charge left in the battery simply from the display
on the display means in the second housing.</p><p num="0056">Having described preferred embodiments of the present
invention with reference to the accompanying drawings, it is to be
understood that the present invention is not limited to the above-mentioned
embodiments and that various changes and modifications can
be effected therein by one skilled in the art without departing from
the scope of the present invention as defined in the
appended claims.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Tragbare Kommunikationsendgeräteeinrichtung zum Bereitstellen von Ton- und
Datenkommunikation, die aufweist:
<claim-text><claim-text>eine erste Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (111-114) zur Funkkommunikation
mit einer vorher festgelegten Station oder einem anderen Endgerät,</claim-text><claim-text>eine Tonkommunikationseinrichtung (116, 117, 118) zum Bereitstellen der Tonkommunikation
über die erste Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (111-114);</claim-text><claim-text>eine Eingabeeinrichtung (216) zum Eingeben von Zeichendaten zur Übertragung
als Zeichennachrichten, und eine Anzeigeeinrichtung (220) zum Anzeigen empfangener Zeichendaten,
die Zeichennachrichten bilden, um dadurch die Datenkommunikation über die
erste Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (111-114) bereitzustellen;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wobei die Einrichtung ein erstes und zweites getrenntes tragbares Gehäuse (100,
200) aufweist,
   wobei das erste Gehäuse einen tragbaren Kommunikationsendgerätebereich (100)
bildet, der eine erste Datenverarbeitungseinrichtung (115), um Daten, die empfangen werden
oder durch die die erste Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (111-114) zu übertragen sind, zu
verarbeiten, eine zweite Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (123, 124), welche mit der ersten
Datenverarbeitungseinrichtung (115) zur Nahbereichs-Funkkommunikation verbunden ist,
und eine Speichereinrichtung (125) zur Datenspeicherung aufweist;
   wobei das zweite Gehäuse einen Informationsverarbeitungsbereich (200) aufweist,
der eine dritte Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (211, 212) zur Nahbereichs-Funkkommunikation
mit der zweiten Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (123, 124) im tragbaren Kommunikationsendgerätebereich
(100) und die zweite Datenverarbeitungseinrichtung (213) aufweist,
welche mit der dritten Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (211, 212) verbunden ist;
   dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
   die erste Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (111-114), die Tonkommunikationseinrichtung
(116, 117, 118), die Eingabeeinrichtung (216) und die Anzeigeeinrichtung (220)
zwischen den beiden tragbaren Gehäusen wie folgt verteilt sind:
<claim-text><claim-text>die erste Funkkommunikationseinrichtung 8111-114) und die Tonkommunikationseinrichtung
(116, 117, 118) im ersten Gehäuse vorgesehen sind, welche mit der ersten
Datenverarbeitungseinrichtung (115) verbunden sind, um die Tonkommunikation der tragbaren
Kommunikationsendgeräteeinrichtung bereitzustellen; die Eingabeeinrichtung (216) zum
Eingeben von Zeichendaten zur Übertragung einer Zeichennachricht und die Anzeigeeinrichtung
(220) im zweiten Gehäuse vorgesehen sind, welche mit der zweiten Datenverarbeitungseinrichtung
(213) verbunden sind, welche Daten verarbeitet, die empfangen werden oder die
als Zeichennachricht zu oder von der tragbaren Kommunikationsendgeräteeinrichtung zu
übertragen sind;</claim-text><claim-text>die Eingabeeinrichtung (216) des Datenverarbeitungsbereichs (200) betriebsfähig
ist, Information zur Speicherung in der Speichereinrichtung (125) über die dritte Funkkommunikationseinrichtung
(211, 212) und die zweite Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (123,
124) einzugeben;</claim-text><claim-text>die Anzeigeeinrichtung (220) im Datenverarbeitungsbereich (200) eingerichtet ist,
einen Status des tragbaren Kommunikationsendgerätebereichs (100) anzuzeigen; und</claim-text><claim-text>das zweite Gehäuse (200) einen Winkeleinstellungsmechanismus (203) aufweist,
der in der Lage ist, einen Winkel zwischen der Anzeigeeinrichtung (220) und der Eingabeeinrichtung
(216) variabel einzustellen, und einen Umkehrungsmechanismus, der in der Lage ist,
die Anordnung der Anzeigeeinrichtung (220) um einen Winkel von 180° zu drehen.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kommunikationsendgeräteeinrichtung nach Anspruch 1, wobei, wenn der Winkel
zwischen der Anzeigeeinrichtung (220) und der Eingabeeinrichtung (216) minimal ist, der
größte Teil der Eingabeeinrichtung (216) durch die Anzeigeeinrichtung (220) überdeckt ist,
jedoch ein Teil der Eingabeeinrichtung (216) nicht bedeckt ist, sondern frei bleibt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kommunikationsendgeräteeinrichtung nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche,
wobei die Anzeigeeinrichtung (220) den Funkkommunikationsstatus der ersten Funkkommunikationseinrichtung
(111-114) oder den Verarbeitungsstatus der ersten Datenverarbeitungseinrichtung
(115) anzeigt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kommunikationsendgeräteeinrichtung nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche,
wobei die Nahbereichs-Funkkommunikation zwischen der zweiten Funkkommunikationseinrichtung
(123, 124) und der dritten Funkkommunikationseinrichtung (211, 212) unter
Verwendung von Blue Tooth hergestellt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Kommunikationsendgeräteeinrichtung nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche,
wobei der tragbare Kommunikationsendgerätebereich (100) außerdem eine Datenanzeigeeinrichtung
(130) aufweist, um einen Status einer vorher festgelegten Funktion anzuzeigen.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A portable communication terminal device for providing voice and data
communication, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>first radio communication means (111-114) for radio communication with a
predetermined station or another terminal,</claim-text><claim-text>voice communication means (116, 117, 118) for providing said voice
communication via said first radio communication means (111-114);</claim-text><claim-text>input means (216) for inputting character data for transmission as character
messages, and display means (220) for displaying received character data forming
character messages, thereby to provide said data communication via said first radio
communication means (111-114);</claim-text><claim-text>the device comprising first and second separated portable housings (100,
200),</claim-text><claim-text>the first housing constituting a portable communication terminal portion
(100) including first data processing means (115) for processing data received or to
be transmitted by the first radio communication means (111-114), second radio
communication means (123, 124) connected with the first data processing means
(115) for short-distance radio communication, and memory means (125) for storage
of data;</claim-text><claim-text>the second housing constituting an information processing portion (200)
including third radio communication means (211, 212) for short-distance radio
communication with the second radio communication means (123, 124) in the
portable communication terminal portion (100) and second data processing means
(123) connected with the third radio communication means (211, 212);</claim-text></claim-text>
   characterised in that:
<claim-text><claim-text>the first radio communication means (111-114), voice communication means
(116, 117, 118), input means (216) and display means (220) are distributed as
between the two portable housings as follows:<claim-text><claim-text>the first radio communication means (111-114) and voice communication
means (116, 117, 118) are provided in the first housing connected with the first data
processing means (115) for providing said voice communication of said portable
communication terminal device; the input means (216) for inputting character data
for transmission as character messages and the display means (220) are provided in
said second housing connected to the second data processing means (213) which
processes data received or to be transmitted as character messages to or from said
portable communication terminal device;</claim-text><claim-text>the input means (216) of the data processing portion (200) is operable to input
information for storage in the memory means (125) via the third radio
communication means (211, 212) and the second radio communication means (123,
124);</claim-text><claim-text>the display means (220) in the data processing portion (200) is adapted to
display a status of the portable communication terminal portion (100); and</claim-text><claim-text>the second housing (200) comprises an angle adjusting mechanism (203)
capable of variably setting an angle between the display means (220) and the input
means, (216) and an inverting mechanism capable of turning the disposition of the
display means (220) by an angle of 180 degrees.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A communication terminal device according to claim 1, wherein, when the
angle between the display means (220) and the input means (216) is a minimum, the
majority of the input means (216) is covered by the display means (220), but part of
the input means (216) is not covered but remain exposed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A communication terminal device according to any one of the preceding
claims, wherein the display means (220) displays the radio communication status of
the first radio communication means (111-114) or processing status of the first
data processing means (115).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A communication terminal device according to any one of the preceding
claims, wherein the short-distance radio communication between the second radio
communication means (123, 124) and the third radio communication means (211,
212) is made using Blue Tooth.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A communication terminal device according to any one of the preceding
claims, wherein the portable communication terminal portion (100) further includes
data display means (130) for displaying a status of a predetermined function.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif de terminal de communication portable destiné à
permettre une communication vocale et de données, comprenant :
<claim-text><claim-text>un premier moyen de communication radio (111-114) pour une
communication radio avec une station prédéterminée ou un autre
terminal ;</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen de communication vocale (116, 117, 118) destiné à
permettre une communication vocale via ledit premier moyen de
communication radio (111-114) ;</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen d'entrée (216) destiné à entrer des données
caractères pour une transmission en tant que message de caractères, et
un moyen d'affichage (220) destiné à afficher des données caractères
reçues formant des messages de caractères, pour ainsi permettre ladite
communication de données via ledit premier moyen de communication
radio (111-114) ;</claim-text><claim-text>le dispositif comprenant des premier et second logements
portables séparés (100, 200),</claim-text><claim-text>le premier logement constituant une partie de terminal de
communication portable (100) comprenant un premier moyen de
traitement de données (115) destiné à traiter des données reçues ou à
transmettre par le premier moyen de communication radio (111-114), un
deuxième moyen de communication radio (123, 124) relié au premier
moyen de traitement de données (115) pour une communication radio à
courte distance, et un moyen de mémoire (125) pour le stockage de
données ;</claim-text><claim-text>le second logement constituant une partie de traitement
d'informations (200) comprenant un troisième moyen de communication
radio (211, 212) pour une communication radio à courte distance avec le
deuxième moyen de communication radio (123, 124) dans la partie de
terminal de communication portable (100) et un deuxième moyen de
traitement de données (123) relié au troisième moyen de communication
radio (211, 212) ;</claim-text></claim-text>
   caractérisé en ce que :
<claim-text><claim-text>le premier moyen de communication radio (111-114), le moyen
de communication vocale (116, 117, 118), le moyen d'entrée (216) et le
moyen d'affichage (220) sont répartis entre les deux logements portables
comme suit :
<claim-text><claim-text>le premier moyen de communication radio (111-114) et le
moyen de communication vocale (116, 117, 118) sont disposés dans le
premier logement relié au premier moyen de traitement de données (115)
pour établir ladite communication vocale dudit dispositif de terminal de
communication portable ; le moyen d'entrée (216) destiné à entrer des
données caractères pour transmission en tant que messages de caractères
et le moyen d'affichage (220) sont disposés ledit second logement relié au
deuxième moyen de traitement de données (213) qui traite les données
reçues ou à transmettre comme messages de caractères en provenance
ou à destination dudit dispositif de terminal de communication portable ;</claim-text><claim-text>le moyen d'entrée (216) de la partie de traitement de données
(200) peut fonctionner pour entrer des informations pour stockage dans le
moyen de mémoire (125) via le troisième moyen de communication radio
(211, 212) et le deuxième moyen de communication radio (123, 124) ;</claim-text><claim-text>le moyen d'affichage (220) dans la partie de traitement de
données (200) est adapté pour afficher un état de la partie de terminal de
communication portable (100) ; et</claim-text><claim-text>le second logement (200) comprend un mécanisme
d'ajustement d'angle (203) capable d'établir de manière variable un angle
entre le moyen d'affichage (220) et le moyen d'entrée (216), et un
mécanisme d'inversion capable de tourner la disposition du moyen
d'affichage (220) d'un angle de 180 degrés.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif de terminal de communication selon la revendication
1, dans lequel, lorsque l'angle entre le moyen d'affichage (220) et le
moyen d'entrée (216) est un minimum, la majeure partie du moyen
d'entrée (216) est couverte par le moyen d'affichage (220), mais une
partie du moyen d'entrée (216) n'est pas couverte mais reste exposée.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif de terminal de communication selon l'une quelconque
des revendications précédentes, dans lequel le moyen d'affichage (220)
affiche l'état de communication radio du premier moyen de
communication radio (111-114) ou l'état de traitement du premier moyen
de traitement de données (115).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif de terminal de communication selon l'une quelconque
des revendications précédentes, dans lequel la communication radio à
courte distance entre le deuxième moyen de communication radio (123,
124) et le troisième moyen de communication radio (211, 212) est réalisée
en utilisant la technologie Blue Tooth.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Dispositif de terminal de communication selon l'une quelconque
des revendications précédentes, dans lequel la partie de terminal de
communication portable (100) comprend en outre un moyen d'affichage
de données (130) pour afficher un état d'une fonction prédéterminée.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20061206"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060929</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20060908"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20060202"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60116160</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060202</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20051228"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20051228"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20040707"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040519</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20040609"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20040428"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040224</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20030917"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20030917"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Countries concerned </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ALLTLVMKROSI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010829"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010829"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>