<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1136456-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1136456" kind="B1" date="20060111"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23237807" ucid="EP-1136456-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1136456</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20060111</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01302595-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01302595</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010321</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-535672" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>535672</doc-number><date>20000323</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-53567200-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>53567200</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000323</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new"><intention-to-grant-date><date>20050420</date></intention-to-grant-date></dates-of-public-availability><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  37/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  37/02        20060101CFI20010703BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  37/027       20060101AFI20010703BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  37/07        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  37/10        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  37/12        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">D01F   9/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">D01F   9/08        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C03B37/027B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01D257:110</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M03B205:57</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Verfahren und Vorrichtung zum kontinuierlichen Kühlen einer heissen Faser mit Rückfuhr des Kühlgases</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Method and apparatus for hot continuous fiber cooling with cooling gas recirculation</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Procédé et dispositif de refroidissement en continu d'une fibre chaude avec recirculation du gaz de refroidissement</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>AIR PROD &amp; CHEM</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>ARSLANIAN GREGORY KHOSROV</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>EVANS MICHAEL HENRY</name><address><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SCHILLINGER JOSEPH ANTHONY</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>ARSLANIAN, GREGORY KHOSROV</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>EVANS, MICHAEL HENRY</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SCHILLINGER, JOSEPH ANTHONY</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>ARSLANIAN, GREGORY KHOSROV</last-name><address><street>6005 Planters Drive</street><city>Pipersville, PA 18947</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>EVANS, MICHAEL HENRY</last-name><address><street>Lamoriniere Straat 224</street><city>2018 Antwerpen</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>SCHILLINGER, JOSEPH ANTHONY</last-name><address><street>221 Krocks Road</street><city>Allentown, PA 18104</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</last-name><address><street>7201 Hamilton Boulevard</street><city>Allentown, PA 18195-1501</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Burford, Anthony Frederick</last-name><address><street>Beck Greener Fulwood House 12 Fulwood Place</street><city>London WC1V 6HR</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>Coolant gas recovery and reuse from a heat exchanger (2) is automatically interrupted when the oxygen content of the used gas exceeds a predetermined maximum concentration and is recommenced when the oxygen content falls below a predetermined minimum concentration. The mass flow of coolant gas (5) introduced into the passageway is controlled independently of its composition and, during normal operation, the mass flow ratio of coolant gas withdrawn (15,15') for recovery to coolant gas (5) introduced into the heat exchanger (2) is maintained constant. This ratio can be ramped up to the constant level in a predetermined manner on start up of fibre cooling and following recovery interruption. The invention provides both methods and apparatus and has particular application to Optical Fibre (1) manufacture. &lt;IMAGE&gt;</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">Coolant gas recovery and reuse from a heat exchanger (2) is automatically
interrupted when the oxygen content of the used gas exceeds a predetermined
maximum concentration and is recommenced when the oxygen content falls below a
predetermined minimum concentration. The mass flow of coolant gas (5) introduced into
the passageway is controlled independently of its composition and, during normal
operation, the mass flow ratio of coolant gas withdrawn (15,15') for recovery to coolant
gas (5) introduced into the heat exchanger (2) is maintained constant. This ratio can be
ramped up to the constant level in a predetermined manner on start up of fibre cooling
and following recovery interruption. The invention provides both methods and apparatus
and has particular application to Optical Fibre (1) manufacture.
<img file="00000001.tif" id="img-EP-1136555-A1-00000001" he="91" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" orientation="unknown" inline="no" /></p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="p0001">The present Application relates to the cooling of hot continuous fibres using a coolant gas and has particular, but not exclusive, application to the cooling of Optical Fibres with helium. It provides both methods of cooling and apparatus for cooling.</p><p num="p0002">The Optical Fibre industry faces increasing pressure to reduce manufacturing costs while maintaining the highest standards of product quality. A major part of the operating cost of an Optical Fibre production facility is taken up by utilities and, in an effort to reduce one expensive utility, attention has been directed to the cost of helium used as a heat exchange medium between the Optical Fibre as it passes vertically down the centre of a draw tower and the externally cooled wall of the draw tower tube. In conventional Optical Fibre manufacture, all the helium supplied to the draw tower is allowed to escape to atmosphere through the open ends of the draw tower. It has been proposed in, for example, <ref type="patent">JP-A-60-046954</ref>, <ref type="patent">JP-A-4-240129</ref> and <ref type="patent">EP-A-0094172</ref> to recover and re-use the helium.</p><p num="p0003">The level of technology involved in optical fibre manufacture is very high. The fibres are manufactured in a batch process with strict controls on diameter to micron levels. This requires a sophisticated level of control from the draw furnace, to fibre diameter measurement, fibre cooling, coating application and draw speed control. The optimum is to produce the longest single length of fibre with consistent diameter in the fastest possible time while maintaining the desired light transmissibility parameters. A significant challenge is found in starting the draw process; obtaining the maximum draw speed and stable operation as fast as possible. In view of the high level of control and the number of parameters that can effect the draw operation, recovering helium while maintaining stable operation presents a significant challenge. Changes affecting the efficiency of cooling in the draw tower can lead to off specification product, fibre breaks or coating problems which disrupt the fibre draw operation. It is economically sound to recover helium used in the draw process but not at the expense of increased production interruption and lost product. The final fibre product is worth much more than recovery of a utility gas, albeit an expensive one. Thus a stable, well defined, automated control system for helium recovery from an Optical Fibre manufacturing operation is required. This has not been satisfactorily achieved by the prior art proposals for helium reuse.</p><p num="p0004"><ref type="patent">JP-A-60-046954</ref> discloses a heat exchanger for cooling an Optical Fibre by contact with a helium or a helium/inert coolant gas mixture during passage through a passageway in a heat exchanger. The coolant gas is recirculated with addition of fresh helium and, when using a gas mixture, inert gas. The flow of the recirculated gas after said addition is controlled, in unspecified manner, by a valve and monitored by a flow meter. Optionally, the gas is cooled prior to entry into the passageway and/or the passageway is separately cooled.</p><p num="p0005"><ref type="patent">JP-A-4-240129</ref> acknowledges as prior art thereto a process of <ref type="patent">JP-A-60-046954</ref> in which an Optical Fibre is cooled by direct contact with a helium/nitrogen gas mixture as it is passed through a heat exchanger passageway countercurrent to the direction of gas flow. The gas is recirculated with addition of fresh helium and nitrogen. The recirculated gas after said addition is cooled prior to entry into the passageway and/or the passageway is separately cooled. It is stated that a problem with the process of <ref type="patent">JP-A-60-046954</ref> is the volume of helium required for cooling and the loss of helium gas and ingress of air at the ends of the heat exchanger passageway. <ref type="patent">JP-A-4-240129</ref> seeks to overcome this problem by purifying the recycled helium to remove <i>inter alia</i> air which enters the heat exchanger passageway from the ends thereof. No details of flow control are provided.</p><p num="p0006">In the embodiment of Figure 1 of <ref type="patent">JP-A-4-240129</ref>, recycled helium gas is withdrawn from an upper outlet of the heat exchanger passageway and pumped to a helium gas purifier to remove air therefrom. Helium gas exiting the purifier is pumped to a gas mixer where make-up helium is added from a helium gas source. The resultant gas mixture is then supplied to a gas inlet at the bottom of the passageway.</p><p num="p0007">The embodiment of Figure 2 of <ref type="patent">JP-A-4-240129</ref> differs from that of Figure 1 thereof in that the wall of the heat exchanger passageway is cooled and the made-up recirculated helium is cooled prior to return to the passageway.</p><p num="p0008"><ref type="patent">EP-A-0601601</ref> discloses the recirculation of coolant gas from a heat exchanger having a passageway in which a hot continuous fibre is cooled with coolant gas and is particularly concerned with the cooling of Optical Fibres using helium. The flow of coolant gas into and out of the passageway is controlled based on one or more of the flow rate of, concentration of impurities in, and the pressure of recirculation coolant gas exiting the passageway. It is stated that the means for controlling the flow may be &quot;at least one flow resistance means, such as valves, orifices, sintered filters, narrow pipes having smaller diameters than the recovery conduit or packed beds&quot; and that &quot;adjustment of the flow resistance means can be made manually or automatically based on the flow rate, pressure and/or composition of the coolant gas&quot; or &quot;the flow resistance means can be preset or pre-adjusted based on experience and calculation or based on the flow rate, pressure and/or composition of a coolant gas&quot;. The only exemplification in <ref type="patent">EP-A-0601601</ref> of monitored impurity in the coolant gas is that of oxygen concentration.</p><p num="p0009"><ref type="patent">EP-A-0094172</ref> discloses recirculation of nitrogen or other inert gas to and from a drier in which a solvent is evaporated. The flow of exhaust inert gas from the drier is controlled in response to the flow rate from the drier outlet and the oxygen concentration in the drier. The recirculated inert gas is pumped to a condenser unit where solvent is removed and returned in part to the main body of the drier and in part to the ends of the drier as inert gas curtains. If the gas outlet pressure falls below a predetermined level, the gas flow to the pump is made up with recirculated gas from the condensation unit. The distribution and amount of recycled gas and provision of make-up inert gas is controlled in response to the flow rate through the gas outlet; the flow rate through the gas inlet; the solvent concentration in the drier; the oxygen concentration in the drier; and the pressure in the recirculated flow from the condensation unit.</p><p num="p0010"><ref type="patent">EP-A-0820963</ref> discloses the recycle of helium from the fibre drawing step and at least one of the deposition and consolidation steps in an Optical Fibre manufacturing process. The used helium from these steps is partially purified to a low level purity and recycled to the fibre drawing process and/or further purified and recycled to at least one of the deposition, consolidation and fibre drawing steps. In an exemplified embodiment, provision is made to automatically vent purified recycle helium as a waste stream if the level of oxygen, chlorine, hydrogen chloride and moisture contaminants in the partially or fully purified recycle helium exceed predetermined levels.</p><p num="p0011"><ref type="patent">WO-A-9749960</ref> discloses the recycle of helium from the consolidation step in an Optical Fibre manufacturing process. The used helium from this step is either purified to a high level purity for recycle to the consolidation step or partially purified to a low level for usage in fibre draw or other process steps and subsequent purification for recycle to the consolidation and, optionally, other process steps. Helium from the fibre draw or other process steps can be purified and recycled independently of the recycle of helium to the consolidation step. In the exemplified embodiments, provision is made to automatically vent used or purified recycle helium to scrubbers if contaminant levels in the used or purified helium exceed predetermined levels.</p><p num="p0012">It is the primary object of this invention to provide a relatively simple and effective system for reusing helium gas in Optical Fibre manufacture which will cause the minimum affect on application to an existing draw tower operation using fresh helium. More particularly, it is an object to provide such a system which will not reduce the length, consistency of diameter, or light transmissibility parameters of fibre produced or the speed of production compared with the use of only fresh helium.</p><p num="p0013">The present invention provides an improvement in cooling a hot continuous fibre by simultaneously passing the fibre through an open ended passageway of a heat exchanger located in an ambient oxygen-containing atmosphere; introducing into the passageway a coolant gas comprising recirculated purified coolant gas and fresh coolant gas; allowing a portion of used coolant gas to leave the passageway at said open ends to limit ingress of ambient atmosphere into the passageway; removing, purifying and recirculating to the passageway a portion of the used coolant gas; and monitoring the oxygen content of said removed portion. The improvement is that the mass flow of coolant gas introduced into the passageway can be controlled independently of its composition by providing for automatic interruption of the removal of used coolant gas for purification and recirculation when the oxygen content of the used coolant gas exceeds a predetermined maximum concentration until such time as the oxygen content falls below a predetermined minimum concentration.</p><p num="p0014">In one presently preferred embodiment, the method of the invention comprises simultaneously passing the fibre at constant speed through an open ended passageway of a heat exchanger located in an ambient moisture- and oxygen-containing atmosphere; introducing into the passageway a coolant gas containing at least 95% helium and comprising recirculated purified coolant gas and fresh helium; allowing a portion of used coolant gas to leave the passageway at said open ends to limit ingress of ambient atmosphere into the passageway; removing, drying and recirculating to the passageway a portion of the used coolant gas; and monitoring the oxygen content of said removed portion, wherein said removal of used coolant gas for purification and recirculation is automatically interrupted when the oxygen content of the used coolant gas exceeds a predetermined maximum concentration and recommenced when the oxygen content falls below a predetermined minimum concentration; and the mass flow of coolant gas introduced into the passageway is maintained independently of its composition.</p><p num="p0015">In a presently more preferred embodiment, the method of the invention comprises simultaneously passing the fibre at constant speed through an open ended passageway of a heat exchanger located in an ambient moisture- and oxygen-containing atmosphere; introducing into the passageway a coolant gas containing at least 95% helium and comprising recirculated purified coolant gas and fresh helium; allowing a portion of used coolant gas to leave the passageway at said open ends to limit ingress of ambient atmosphere into the passageway; removing, drying and recirculating to the passageway a portion of the used coolant gas; and monitoring the oxygen content of said removed portion, wherein the mass flow of used coolant gas removed for purification and recirculation during normal operation is maintained at about 90% of mass flow of the coolant gas introduced into the passageway but said removal of used coolant gas is automatically interrupted when the oxygen content thereof exceeds a predetermined maximum concentration and recommenced when the oxygen content falls below a predetermined minimum concentration; said removal of used coolant gas is by a vacuum pump drawing used coolant gas from more than one said passageway and controlled to maintain a constant suction pressure; the mass flow of said removed gas portion from each passageway is regulated by a respective mass flow controller which is located upstream of said pump and regulates mass flow more rapidly than the vacuum pump can respond to corresponding changes in pressure levels; said interruption of flow from each passageway is by a shut-off valve located between said respective mass flow controller and pump; and the mass flow of coolant gas introduced into the passageway is maintained independently of its composition and is controlled by regulation of the pressure of said introduced coolant gas using respective pressure regulators on the fresh helium gas and the recirculated coolant gas set to provide recirculated coolant gas in preference to fresh coolant gas.</p><p num="p0016">The invention also provides an apparatus for cooling a hot continuous fibre by the improved method of the invention. The apparatus comprises:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>a heat exchanger for location in an ambient oxygen-containing atmosphere and having an open ended passageway to receive the hot continuous fibre for passage therethrough;</li><li>inlet means for introducing into the passageway a coolant gas comprising recirculated purified coolant gas and fresh coolant gas at a mass flow independent of said coolant gas composition.;</li><li>outlet means for removing a portion of used coolant gas from the passageway;</li><li>purifying means for purifying said removed portion of used coolant gas;</li><li>pumping means for recirculating said removed coolant gas portion from said outlet means to said inlet means via said purifying means;</li><li>oxygen analysis means for monitoring the oxygen content of said removed coolant gas portion;</li><li>recirculation flow control means for interrupting said removal of used coolant gas; and</li><li>signal means for activating said recirculation flow control means to automatically interrupt said removal of used coolant gas when the oxygen content measured by said oxygen analysis means exceeds a predetermined maximum concentration and to recommence said removal when said measured oxygen content falls below a predetermined minimum concentration.</li></ul></p><p num="p0017">In a presently preferred embodiment, the apparatus of the invention comprises:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>at least two heat exchangers for location in an ambient moisture- and oxygen- containing atmosphere, each exchanger having an open ended passageway to receive a respective hot continuous fibre for passage therethrough;</li><li>inlet means for individually introducing into each passageway a coolant gas comprising recirculated purified coolant gas and fresh coolant gas at a mass flow independent of said coolant gas composition and comprising respective pressure regulators on the fresh coolant gas and the recirculated coolant gas set to provide recirculated coolant gas in preference to fresh coolant gas;</li><li>respective outlet means for individually removing a portion of used coolant gas from each of the passageways;</li><li>purifying means for removing moisture from said removed portions of used coolant gas by freezing out the water content thereof;</li><li>pumping means for recirculating said removed coolant gas portions from said respective outlet means to said inlet means via said purifying means, said pumping means comprising a vacuum pump which is located upstream of said purifying means, connected to the respective outlet means and controlled to maintain a constant suction pressure;</li><li>respective oxygen analysis means for individually monitoring the oxygen content of said removed coolant gas portions;</li><li>respective mass flow control means for individually maintaining constant during normal operation the ratio of the mass flow of used coolant gas removed by each outlet means to the mass flow of the coolant gas introduced into the respective passageway by said inlet means, each said mass flow control means comprising a mass flow controller upstream of said vacuum pump and regulating mass flow from the respective passageway more rapidly than the pump can respond to corresponding changes in pressure levels;</li><li>respective recirculation flow control means for individually interrupting said removal of used coolant gas from each passageway and comprising a shut-off valve located between said respective mass flow controller and said vacuum pump; and</li><li>respective signal means for activating each said recirculation flow control means to automatically interrupt said removal of used coolant gas from the respective passageway when the oxygen content measured by the respective oxygen analysis means exceeds a predetermined maximum concentration and to recommence said removal when said measured oxygen content falls below a predetermined minimum concentration.</li></ul></p><p num="p0018">As mentioned previously, the invention has particular, but not exclusive application to the cooling of an Optical Fibre using helium. In such an application, maximum oxygen concentration permitted in the used gas typically will be about 2% and the minimum oxygen concentration typically about 1%. Preferably, the helium content of the coolant gas introduced into the passageway will be maintained within the range of 95% to 100%.</p><p num="p0019">Conveniently, the coolant gas is introduced into the passageway at about the mid-point thereof and the recirculation coolant gas removed at two locations each adjacent a respective open end of the passageway.</p><p num="p0020">Usually, the speed of the fibre and the mass flow of introduced coolant gas will be maintained constant during normal operation. Additionally or alternatively, the ratio of the mass flow of used coolant gas removed for purification and recirculation to the mass flow of the coolant gas introduced usually will be maintained constant at, for example, about 90:100 during normal operation. The proportion of used coolant gas removed for purification and recirculation during start up or following flow interruption can be gradually increased up to said mass flow .</p><p num="p0021">When the method of the invention is applied to the cooling of Optical Fibres using helium and for some other applications, it may be sufficient for the purification of the recirculated coolant gas to be simply removal of moisture. Especially in the case of the use of helium, the moisture removal conveniently is conducted by cooling the recirculated coolant gas to freeze out the water content thereof. Other contaminants, especially oxygen, can be removed by conventional techniques such as membrane separation or absorption.</p><p num="p0022">Usually, the oxygen concentration in the recirculated coolant gas is measured in a sample stream of used coolant gas removed from the passageway but it could be measured in the passageway itself. During normal operation, the analysed sample stream can be combined with the coolant gas removed for purification and recirculation to limit the loss of coolant gas.</p><p num="p0023">It is preferred that the used coolant gas is removed for purification and recirculation by a vacuum pump upstream of purification thereof. A mass flow controller can be located upstream of the pump to regulate the mass flow of the removed gas portion and a shut-off valve can be located between said mass flow controller and pump to interrupt and recommence recirculation in response to signals from the analyser.</p><p num="p0024">Usually Optical Fibre production involves the parallel supply to a plurality of draw towers (heat exchanger) of coolant gas from a common source and accordingly it is desirable that a coolant gas recirculation system should be able to separately recover used coolant gas from each draw tower but combine the recovered streams prior to purification thereof. In the method of the invention, this can readily and efficiently be achieved by using the same vacuum pump to draw used coolant gas from the passageways of more than one heat exchanger with independent interruption and mass flow regulation of used coolant gas removal from each passageway in response to the oxygen content of the used coolant gas from the respective passageway. Preferably, the pump is controlled to maintain a constant suction pressure and the respective mass flow controllers regulate mass flow from the respective passageways more rapidly than the pump can respond to corresponding changes in pressure levels. This difference in response times allows the mass flow controllers to operate with a defined pressure drop which can be optimised for the particular mass flow device to ensure that it operates within its optimum control range and hence maintain the control stability of the recovery system.</p><p num="p0025">The addition of fresh coolant gas to recirculated purified used coolant gas to provide the coolant gas introduced into the passageway conveniently is controlled by regulation of the pressure of said introduced coolant gas using respective pressure regulators on the fresh coolant gas and the recirculated coolant gas set to provide recirculated coolant gas in preference to fresh coolant gas.</p><p num="p0026">The invention is exemplified below with reference to the use of helium in the manufacture of Optical Fibres. However, it should be understood that both the method and apparatus aspects of the invention are generally applicable to the cooling of any hot continuous fibre with any coolant gas.</p><p num="p0027">The following is a description by way of example only and with reference to the accompanying drawings of a presently preferred embodiment of the present invention. In the drawings:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Figure 1 is a schematic drawing of apparatus in accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention for cooling Optical Fibres using helium and</li><li>Figure 2 is a schematic drawing of a coolant control system for use in the apparatus of Figure 1.</li></ul></p><p num="p0028">Referring to both Figures of the drawings, an Optical Fibre 1 (see Figure 2) is drawn from a furnace (not shown) and cooled in a draw tower 2 prior to coating in conventional manner. The draw tower 2 is of essentially conventional structure consisting of a vertical right hollow cylindrical column wall 3 which is cooled externally with, for example, chilled water or a glycol/water system. The fibre 1 passes vertically down the centre of a passageway 4 defined by the wall 3. A coolant gas in line 5 is introduced into the passageway 4 through an inlet 6, preferably at a mid-point of the draw tower 2. In normal operation, the coolant gas in line 5 consists of a mixture of recirculated coolant gas provided via line 7 from a storage tank 26 and make-up helium provided via line 8 from a pure helium gas supply 9. Composition of the coolant gas in line 5 is by regulation of the pressure in that line using respective pressure regulators 10,11 set to control at different pressure levels such that the recirculated coolant gas in line 7 is used in preference to make-up helium in line 8. It will be apparent that when there is no recirculated coolant gas, the coolant gas 5 consists entirely of pure helium provided from the gas supply 9.</p><p num="p0029">Under normal operating conditions, the mass flow of coolant gas into the draw tower 2 is fixed and is measured by a mass flow meter 12. The pressure is regulated by a pressure regulator 13 upstream of the mass flow meter 12 and a shut-off valve 14 is provided downstream of the mass flow meter 12 to open and close the inlet 6 to the draw tower 2.</p><p num="p0030">The coolant gas acts as a heat exchange medium between the Optical Fibre 1 and the cylindrical wall 3 to cool the fibre as it passes through the passageway 4. In conventional draw towers, all of the helium supplied through inlet 6 exits the passageway 4 through the ends thereof preventing ingress of the ambient atmosphere into the passageway 4 and contamination by coolant gas recirculation. As acknowledged above, it is known in the prior art to remove a substantial portion of the coolant gas from outlets 15, 15' adjacent respective open ends of the passageway 4. The coolant gas in the draw tower 2 is maintained at a pressure slightly above atmospheric pressure to limit ingress of ambient atmosphere into the passageway 4 but the helium withdrawn through the outlets 15, 15' is nevertheless contaminated by the diffusion of components, particularly moisture and oxygen, from the ambient atmosphere. If the withdrawn contaminated helium was recirculated directly to the draw tower 2 with make-up fresh helium, the contaminant content would increase and thereby reduce the heat exchange capacity of the coolant gas. As acknowledged above, it is known in the prior art to remove contaminants from the withdrawn gas during recirculation to the draw tower 2.</p><p num="p0031">In the present embodiment, the outlets 15, 15' are manifolded to a vacuum pump 16 which provides the driving force for recirculation and is controlled to maintain a constant suction pressure of, for example, 500 mbara. The flow through the two outlets 15, 15' is balanced by a single valve 17 controlling flow through one of the outlets 15'. The flow of withdrawn gas is controlled by a mass flow controller 18 upstream of the vacuum pump 16 and a shut-off valve 19 is provided between the mass flow controller 18 and the vacuum pump 16. The pump 16 reacts slower to changes in pressure level than the mass flow controller 18 is able to increase of control the mass flow rate of withdrawn gas to the pump.</p><p num="p0032">In normal operation, the shut-off valve 19 is open allowing recirculation of the withdrawn gas and the mass flow controller 18 maintains the mass flow of the withdrawn gas at a constant proportion, for example 90%, of the mass of coolant gas supplied to the passageway 4 via line 5 through inlet 6. However, during the early stages of start-up of fibre production or during an interruption in gas recirculation (see below), the shut-off valve is closed preventing recirculation of withdrawn gas. On commencement of coolant gas recovery at a relevant stage during the start-up or on recommencement of recirculation following an interruption, the shut-off valve 19 is opened but the mass flow controller 18 controlled to ramp up the mass flow rate to the normal proportion over a predetermined time period and at a predetermined rate of mass flow increase. This allows time for the fibre cooling control system (not shown) to adjust to the increase in the temperature of the fibre 1 leaving the draw tower 2 resulting from the reduction in cooling efficiency due to decreasing helium content in the coolant gas supplied via line 5 as the proportion of recirculated gas increases. The fibre coating is temperature controlled and hence a step change in fibre temperature could cause the fibre coating to bum or break, or a section of off-specification fibre to be produced.</p><p num="p0033">The mass flow controller 18 is calibrated for a mixture of 2% air in helium. If the helium concentration varies from 95% to 100% the error in flow reading on the mass flow controller is ±2%. Since this is approximately the same as the manufacturer's guaranteed error for flow measurement, which is ±2% of full scale, it has no impact on the accuracy of the control system. The measurement error is further reduced because of the use of flow ratio control. There is a relatively small composition difference between the coolant gas in line 5 and the recirculated coolant gas in line 7. The difference between the actual coolant gas composition and the coolant gas composition used to calibrate the mass flow devices has the same effect on the &quot;true flow&quot; measurement error of both the mass flow measuring devices. Using the ratio of these measured flows as the control variable cancels out the effect of the measurement error.</p><p num="p0034">A sample of the withdrawn gas is removed upstream of the mass flow controller 18 and fed via pump 21 to analyser 22 which constantly monitors the oxygen content of the withdrawn gas. Under normal operating conditions, the oxygen content remains below a predetermined maximum concentration of, for example, 2%. However, if the oxygen content exceeds that maximum concentration, a signal from the analyser 22 causes the shut-off valve 19 to close thereby isolating the vacuum pump 16 and interrupting flow of the withdrawn gas to the vacuum pump 16. This interruption limits the proportion of withdrawn gas to that supplying the analyser 22 and increases the flow of pure helium through line 8 and hence the helium content of the coolant gas supplied via line 5. The valve 19 remains closed until the oxygen concentration in the withdrawn gas detected by the analyser 22 falls below a predetermined concentration of, for example, 1%.</p><p num="p0035">When the valve 19 is open, the proportion of gas passing through the analyser 22 can be added to the body of recirculated gas downstream of the vacuum pump 16. In this case, the set point of the mass flow controller 18 is adjusted to compensate for this addition to recirculated gas.</p><p num="p0036">When the valve 19 is open, the withdrawn gas passes from the vacuum pump 16 to a purifier 23 for the removal of moisture and, optionally, oxygen and/or other contaminants. Preferably, moisture is removed by cooling the gas with, for example, liquid nitrogen to a temperature at which the moisture freezes out. Oxygen and other contaminants can be removed by conventional methods such as membrane separation or cryogenic absorption. However, in most Optical Fibre applications it will only be necessary to remove moisture from the recirculated coolant gas.</p><p num="p0037">Recirculation gas from the purifier is passed to a first storage vessel 24 and then via compressor 25 to a second storage vessel 26 from which the recirculated supply is withdrawn via line 7.</p><p num="p0038">As shown in Figure 1, several draw towers 2, 2', 2&quot; can be supplied via line 5 from a common source of coolant gas and can share a common recirculation circuit downstream of their respective shut-off valves 19, 19', 19&quot;. However, each draw tower 2, 2', 2&quot; has independent coolant gas supply and withdrawal components as indicated in Figure 1 by the absence or presence of the corresponding superscript. When coolant gas recovery from one of the draw towers is interrupted, there is enough hold up built into the vacuum manifold that the vacuum pump can slow down and return to control at a lower speed without major interruptions to helium recovery on other towers.</p><p num="p0039">The present invention constitutes a significant improvement over prior art methods of reusing helium as the draw tower coolant in Optical Fibre manufacture. As described below, the present method is simpler and provides more stable coolant flow control than that of <ref type="patent">EP-A-0601601</ref>.</p><p num="p0040">There is always a time delay between coolant helium entering the draw tower and exiting or being recovered at each end of the tower. As the recovery system recycles the coolant gas, the composition of the coolant gas changes until the system reaches a steady state where the difference in composition between inlet and recovered gas is constant, the recovered gas being complemented by the pure helium makeup gas to achieve the inlet flow and composition. Until this steady state is reached, the inlet mass flow controller of <ref type="patent">EP-A-0601601</ref> continuously changes the mass flow to the draw tower depending on the composition of the coolant gas. Continuous changes in the inlet mass flow affects the cooling of the fibre as it passes through the draw tower and influences the fibre properties most noticeably diameter which is a key parameter for process control of the overall fibre manufacturing process. The time delay between the coolant gas entering the draw tower and being recovered and measured by the outlet mass flow device(s) and then controlled and the changing composition causes cyclic composition changes as the amount of coolant gas recovered cycles with changing gas composition. In a multi- draw tower operation, the influence of other draw towers on the inlet composition will possibly prevent the composition of the inlet and outlet coolant gas streams from ever achieving constant levels and may even affect the overall balance of control if the control system is not correctly tuned.</p><p num="p0041">The use in the present invention of mass flow independent of inlet coolant composition minimises the effects of composition change on process control. The affect of change of coolant composition on draw tower cooling efficiency is much slower than a change in inlet mass flow and hence has minimum affect on the control of the overall fibre manufacturing process.</p><p num="p0042">It will be understood by those skilled in the art that the invention is not restricted to the specific details described above and that numerous modifications and variation can be made without departing from the scope of the following claims</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim id="c-de-01-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>Verfahren zum Kühlen einer kontinuierlichen, heißen Faser (1) mit den folgenden Schritten: gleichzeitiges Führen der Faser durch eine offen endende Passage (4) eines Wärmetauschers (2), der in einer Sauerstoff enthaltenden Umgebungsatmosphäre angeordnet ist; Einbringen eines Kühlmittelgases (über Leitung 5) in die Passage, welches rezirkuliertes, gereinigtes Kühlmittelgas (über Leitung 7) und frisches Kühlmittelgas (über Leitung 8) umfasst; einem Anteil des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases wird es gestattet, die Passage an den offenen Enden zu verlassen, um das Eindringen von Umgebungsatmosphäre in die Passage zu begrenzen; Entfernen und Reinigen und Rezirkulieren eines Anteils des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases (aus den Auslässen 15, 15') zu der Passage; und Überwachen des Sauerstoffgehaltes des entfernten Anteils, <b>dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass</b> das Entfernen des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases für die Reinigung und Rezirkulation automatisch unterbrochen wird, wenn der Sauerstoffgehalt des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases eine vorbestimmte Maximalkonzentration überschreitet; wobei mit dem Entfernen wieder begonnen wird, wenn der Sauerstoffgehalt unter eine vorbestimmte Minimalkonzentration fällt; und wobei der Massenstrom des Kühlmittelgases, das in die Passage eingebracht wird, unabhängig von seiner Zusammensetzung eingestellt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1, bei dem die Faser (1) eine optische Faser ist und das frische Kühlmittelgas (über Leitung 8) Helium ist.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 1 oder Anspruch 2, bei welchem die maximale Sauerstoffkonzentration ungefähr 2% ist und die minimale Sauerstoffkonzentration ungefähr 1 % ist.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 2 oder Anspruch 3, bei welchem der Heliumgehalt des Kühlmittelgases (über Leitung 5), das in die Passage (4) eingebracht wird, innerhalb des Bereiches von 95% bis 100% gehalten wird.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0005" num="0005"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem die Geschwindigkeit der Faser (1) und der Massenstrom des eingebrachten Kühlmittelgases bei Normalbetrieb konstant gehalten werden.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0006" num="0006"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem das Kühlmittelgas (über Leitung 5) in die Passage (4) ungefähr an deren Mittelpunkt eingebracht wird und das verwendete Kühlmittelgas (aus den Auslässen 15, 15'), das zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation entfernt wird, an zwei Stellen entfernt wird, welche jeweils benachbart zu einem jeweiligen offenen Ende der Passage liegen.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0007" num="0007"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem das Verhältnis des Massenstroms des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases (aus den Auslässen 15, 15'), das zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation entfernt wird, zu dem Massenstrom des eingebrachten Kühlmittelgases (über Leitung 5) während des Normalbetriebes konstant gehalten wird.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0008" num="0008"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem der Massenstrom des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases (aus den Auslässen 15, 15'), das zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation entfernt wird, ungefähr 90% des Massenstroms des eingebrachten Kühlmittelgases (über Leitung 5) beträgt.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0009" num="0009"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem der Anteil des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases (aus den Auslässen 15, 15'), das zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation entfernt wird, während des Anfahrens allmählich erhöht wird, bis zu einem vorbestimmten Verhältnis des Massenstroms des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases, das zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation entfernt wird, zu dem Massenstrom des eingebrachten Kühlmittelgases (über Leitung 5).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0010" num="0010"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem der Anteil des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases (aus den Auslässen 15, 15'), das zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation entfernt wird, in Abfolge auf die Unterbrechung allmählich erhöht wird, bis zu einem vorbestimmten Verhältnis des Massenstroms des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases, das zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation verwendet wird, zum Massenstrom des eingebrachten Kühlmittelgases (über Leitung 5).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0011" num="0011"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem die Reinigung die Entfernung von Feuchtigkeit umfasst.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0012" num="0012"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 11, bei welchem die Faser (1) eine optische Faser ist, das frische Kühlmittelgas (über Leitung 8) Helium ist und Feuchtigkeit entfernt wird durch das Kühlen des Anteils (aus den Auslässen 15, 15') des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases, der zur Rezirkulation verwendet wird, um dessen Wassergehalt herauszufrieren.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0013" num="0013"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem die Reinigung die Entfernung von Sauerstoff umfasst.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0014" num="0014"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem die Sauerstoffkonzentration in einem Probestrom verwendeten Kühlmittelgases (aus den Auslässen 15, 15') gemessen wird, das aus der Passage (4) verwendet wird.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0015" num="0015"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 14, bei welchem im Normalbetrieb der Probestrom mit dem Kühlmittelgas kombiniert wird, das zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation entfernt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0016" num="0016"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem das verwendete Kühlmittelgas, das zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation entfernt (aus den Auslässen 15, 15') wird, durch eine Unterdruckpumpe (16) stromaufwärts von seiner Reinigung entfernt wird; wobei der Massenstrom des entfernten Gasanteils durch einen Massenstromregler (18, 18', 18&quot;) stromaufwärts der Pumpe reguliert wird; und wobei die Strömung durch ein Absperrventil (19, 19', 19&quot;) unterbrochen wird, das zwischen dem Massenstromregler und der Pumpe angeordnet ist.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0017" num="0017"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 16, bei dem die Pumpe (16) verwendetes Kühlmittelgas (aus den Auslässen 15, 15') aus mehr als einer Passage (4) abzieht, mit unabhängiger Unterbrechung und Massenstromregelung der verwendeten Kühlmittelgasentfernung zur Reinigung und Rezirkulation aus jeder Passage in Reaktion auf den Sauerstoffgehalt der entsprechenden Passages.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0018" num="0018"><claim-text>Verfahren nach Anspruch 17, bei welchem die Pumpe (16) so eingestellt wird, dass ein konstanter Saugdruck aufrecht erhalten wird und die jeweiligen Massenstromregler (18, 18', 18&quot;) den Massenstrom aus der entsprechenden Passage (4) schneller regeln als die Pumpe auf entsprechende Änderungen im Druckniveau reagieren kann.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0019" num="0019"><claim-text>Verfahren nach einem der vorhergehenden Ansprüche, bei welchem eine Zugabe von frischem Kühlmittelgas (über Leitung 8) zum rezirkulierten, gereinigten, verwendeten Kühlmittelgas (7) zur Bereitstellung des Kühlmittelgases (über Leitung 5), das in die Passage (4) eingebracht wird, dadurch eingestellt wird, dass der Druck des eingebrachten Kühlmittelgases reguliert wird, und zwar unter Verwendung jeweiliger Druckregler (10, 11) an dem frischen Kühlmittelgas und dem rezirkulierten Kühlmittelgas, die so eingestellt werden, dass rezirkuliertes Kühlmittelgas bevorzugt gegenüber frischem Kühlmittelgas bereitgestellt wird.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0020" num="0020"><claim-text>Vorrichtung zum Kühlen einer kontinuierlichen, heißen Faser mit:
<claim-text>einem Wärmetauscher (2) zur Anordnung in einer Sauerstoff enthaltenden Umgebungsatmosphäre und mit einer offen endenden Passage (4) zur Aufnahme der kontinuierlichen, heißen Faser (1), welche durch sie hindurchgeht;</claim-text><claim-text>einer Einlasseinrichtung (6) zum Einbringen eines Kühlmittelgases in die Passage, welches rezirkuliertes, gereinigtes Kühlmittelgas (über Leitung 7) und frisches Kühlmittelgas (8) mit einem Massenstrom aufweist, der von der Kühlmittelgaszusammensetzung unabhängig ist;</claim-text><claim-text>einer Auslasseinrichtung (15, 15') zum Entfernen eines Anteils des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases aus der Passage;</claim-text><claim-text>einer Reinigungseinrichtung (23) zum Reinigen des entfernten Anteils des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases;</claim-text><claim-text>einer Pumpeinrichtung (16, 25) zum Rezirkulieren des entfernten Kühlmittelgasanteils aus der Auslasseinrichtung (15, 15') zur Einlasseinrichtung (6) über die Reinigungseinrichtung (23);</claim-text><claim-text>einer Sauerstoffanalyseeinrichtung (22) zum Überwachen des Sauerstoffgehaltes des entfernten Kühlmittelgasanteils;</claim-text><claim-text>einer Rezirkulationsströmungs-Einstellungseinrichtung (19) zum Unterbrechen der Entfernung verwendeten Kühlmittelgases; und</claim-text><claim-text>einer Signaleinrichtung zum Aktivieren der Rezirkulationsströmungs-Einstellungseinrichtung (19), um die Entfernung des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases automatisch zu unterbrechen, wenn der Sauerstoffgehalt, der durch die Sauerstoffanalyseeinrichtung (22) gemessen wird, eine vorbestimmte Maximalkonzentration überschreitet, und um die Entfernung wieder zu beginnen, wenn der gemessene Sauerstoffgehalt unter eine vorbestimmte Minimalkonzentration fällt.</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0021" num="0021"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 20, bei welcher die Einlasseinrichtung (6) Kühlmittelgas in die Passage (4) bei ungefähr deren Mittelpunkt einbringt und die Auslasseinrichtung (15, 15') verwendetes Kühlmittelgas bei zwei Stellen entfernt, die benachbart einem jeweiligen offenen Ende der Passage (4) liegen.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0022" num="0022"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 20 oder 21, die ferner eine Massenstromregeleinrichtung (18) umfasst, um während des Normalbetriebes das Verhältnis des Massenstromes des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases, das durch die Auslasseinrichtung (15, 15') entfernt wird, zu dem Massenstrom des Kühlmittelgases, das durch die Einlasseinrichtung (6) eingebracht wird, konstant zu halten.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0023" num="0023"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 22, bei welcher die Pumpeinrichtung eine Unterdruckpumpe (16) stromaufwärts der Reinigungseinrichtung (23) aufweist; wobei die Massenstromregeleinrichtung einen Massenstromregler (18) stromaufwärts der Pumpe (16) aufweist; und wobei die Rezirkulationsregelungseinrichtung ein Absperrventil (19) aufweist, das zwischen dem Massenstromregler (18) und der Pumpe (16) angeordnet ist.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0024" num="0024"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 23, bei welcher die Pumpe (16) mit der Auslasseinrichtung (15, 15') der einen Passage (4) verbunden ist, mit unabhängiger Unterbrechung (19, 19', 19&quot;) und unabhängiger Massenstromregelung (18, 18', 18&quot;) für die Entfernung des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases von jeder Passage (4) in Reaktion auf den Sauerstoffgehalt der jeweiligen Passage (4).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0025" num="0025"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 24, bei welcher die Pumpe (16) so eingestellt wird, dass ein konstanter Saugdruck aufrecht erhalten wird und die jeweiligen Massenstromregler (18, 18', 18&quot;) den Masseristrom aus den jeweiligen Passagen (4) schneller regulieren als die Pumpe (16) auf entsprechende Änderungen im Druckniveau reagieren kann.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0026" num="0026"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 20 bis 25, bei welcher die Reinigungseinrichtung (23) Feuchtigkeit von dem verwendeten Kühlmittelgas entfernt.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0027" num="0027"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 26, bei welcher die Reinigungseinrichtung (23) Feuchtigkeit durch das Kühlen des verwendeten Kühlmittelgases entfernt, um den Wassergehalt aus diesem auszufrieren.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0028" num="0028"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach Anspruch 26 oder Anspruch 27, bei welcher die Reinigungseinrichtung (23) ebenfalls Sauerstoff von dem verwendeten Kühlmittelgas entfernt.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-de-01-0029" num="0029"><claim-text>Vorrichtung nach einem der Ansprüche 20 bis 28, bei welcher die Einlasseinrichtung (6) jeweilige Druckregler (11, 10) an dem frischen Kühlmittelgas und dem rezirkulierten Kühlmittelgas aufweist, die eingestellt sind, um rezirkuliertes Kühlmittelgas bevorzugt gegenüber frischem Kühlmittelgas bereitzustellen.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim id="c-en-01-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>A method of cooling a hot continuous fibre (1) comprising simultaneously passing the fibre through an open ended passageway (4) of a heat exchanger (2) located in an ambient oxygen-containing atmosphere; introducing into the passageway a coolant gas (via line 5) comprising recirculated purified coolant gas (via line 7) and fresh coolant gas (via line 8); allowing a portion of used coolant gas to leave the passageway at said open ends to limit ingress of ambient atmosphere into the passageway; removing, purifying and recirculating to the passageway a portion of the used coolant gas (from outlets 15, 15'); and monitoring the oxygen content of said removed portion, <b>characterised in that</b> said removal of used coolant gas for purification and recirculation is automatically interrupted when the oxygen content of the used coolant gas exceeds a predetermined maximum concentration; said removal is recommenced when the oxygen content falls below a predetermined minimum concentration; and the mass flow of coolant gas introduced into the passageway is controlled independently of its composition.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 1 in which the fibre (1) is an Optical Fibre and the fresh coolant gas (via line 8) is helium.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 1 or Claim 2 in which said maximum oxygen concentration is about 2% and the minimum oxygen concentration is about 1%.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 2 or Claim 3 in which the helium content of the coolant gas (via line 5) introduced into the passageway (4) is maintained within the range of 95% to 100%.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0005" num="0005"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which the speed of the fibre (1) and the mass flow of introduced coolant gas is maintained constant during normal operation.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0006" num="0006"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which the coolant gas (via line 5) is introduced into the passageway (4) at about the mid-point thereof and the used coolant gas (from outlets 15, 15') removed for purification and recirculation is removed at two locations each adjacent a respective open end of the passageway.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0007" num="0007"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which the ratio of the mass flow of used coolant gas (from outlets 15, 15') removed for purification and recirculation to the mass flow of the coolant gas (via line 5) introduced is maintained constant during normal operation.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0008" num="0008"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which the mass flow of used coolant gas (from outlets 15, 15') removed for purification and recirculation is about 90% of mass flow of the coolant gas (via line 5) introduced.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0009" num="0009"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which the proportion of used coolant gas (from outlets 15, 15') removed for purification and recirculation during start up is gradually increased up to a predetermined ratio of the mass flow of used coolant gas removed for purification and recirculation to the mass flow of the coolant gas (via line 5) introduced.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0010" num="0010"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which the proportion of used coolant gas (from outlets 15, 15') removed for purification and recirculation following said interruption is gradually increased up to a predetermined ratio of the mass flow of used coolant gas removed for purification and recirculation to the mass flow of the coolant gas (via line 5) introduced.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0011" num="0011"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which said purification comprises removal of moisture.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0012" num="0012"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 11 in which the fibre (1) is an Optical Fibre, the fresh coolant gas (via line 8) is helium, and moisture is removed by cooling the used coolant gas portion (from outlets 15, 15') removed for recirculation to freeze out the water content thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0013" num="0013"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which said purification comprises the removal of oxygen.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0014" num="0014"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which the oxygen concentration is measured in a sample stream of used coolant gas (from outlets 15, 15') removed from the passageway (4).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0015" num="0015"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 14 in which, during normal operation, the sample stream is combined with the coolant gas removed for purification and recirculation.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0016" num="0016"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which the used coolant gas (from outlets 15, 15') removed for purification and recirculation is removed by a vacuum pump (16) upstream of purification thereof; the mass flow of the removed gas portion is regulated by a mass flow controller (18, 18', 18&quot;) upstream of said pump; and the flow is interrupted by a shut-off valve (19, 19', 19&quot;) located between said mass flow controller and pump.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0017" num="0017"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 16 in which said pump (16) draws used coolant gas (from outlets 15, 15') from more than one said passageway (4) with independent interruption and mass flow regulation of used coolant gas removal for purification and recirculation from each passageway in response to the oxygen content of the respective passageway.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0018" num="0018"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 17 in which said pump (16) is controlled to maintain a constant suction pressure and the respective mass flow controllers (18, 18', 18&quot;) regulate mass flow from the respective passageways (4) more rapidly than the pump can respond to corresponding changes in pressure levels.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0019" num="0019"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the preceding claims in which addition of fresh coolant gas (via line 8) to recirculated purified used coolant gas (via line 7) to provide the coolant gas (via line 5) introduced into the passageway (4) is controlled by regulation of the pressure of said introduced coolant gas using respective pressure regulators (10, 11) on the fresh coolant gas and the recirculated coolant gas set to provide recirculated coolant gas in preference to fresh coolant gas.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0020" num="0020"><claim-text>An apparatus for cooling a hot continuous fibre comprising:
<claim-text>a heat exchanger (2) for location in an ambient oxygen-containing atmosphere and having an open ended passageway (4) to receive the hot continuous fibre (1) for passage therethrough;</claim-text><claim-text>inlet means (6) for introducing into the passageway a coolant gas comprising recirculated purified coolant gas (via line 7) and fresh coolant gas (via line 8) at a mass flow independent of said coolant gas composition.;</claim-text><claim-text>outlet means (15,15') for removing a portion of used coolant gas from the passageway;</claim-text><claim-text>purifying means (23) for purifying said removed portion of used coolant gas;</claim-text><claim-text>pumping means (16, 25) for recirculating said removed coolant gas portion from said outlet means (15,15') to said inlet means (6) via said purifying means (23);</claim-text><claim-text>oxygen analysis means (22) for monitoring the oxygen content of said removed coolant gas portion;</claim-text><claim-text>recirculation flow control means (19) for interrupting said removal of used coolant gas; and</claim-text><claim-text>signal means for activating said recirculation flow control means (19) to automatically interrupt said removal of used coolant gas when the oxygen content measured by said oxygen analysis means (22) exceeds a predetermined maximum concentration and to recommence said removal when said measured oxygen content falls below a predetermined minimum concentration.</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0021" num="0021"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in Claim 20 in which the inlet means (6) introduces coolant gas into the passageway (4) at about the mid-point thereof and the outlet means (15,15') removes used coolant gas at two locations each adjacent a respective open end of the passageway (4).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0022" num="0022"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in Claim 20 or Claim 21 further comprising mass flow control means (18) for maintaining constant during normal operation the ratio of the mass flow of used coolant gas removed by said outlet means (15,15') to the mass flow of the coolant gas introduced by said inlet means (6).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0023" num="0023"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in Claim 22 in which the pumping means comprises a vacuum pump (16) upstream of said purifying means (23) ; said mass flow control means comprises a mass flow controller (18) upstream of said pump (16); and the recirculation control means comprises a shut-off valve (19) located between said mass flow controller (18) and said pump (16).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0024" num="0024"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in Claim 23 in which said pump (16) is connected to the outlet means (15,15') of than one said passageway (4) with independent interruption (19,19',19&quot;) and independent mass flow regulation (18,18',18&quot;) of used coolant gas removal from each passageway (4) in response to the oxygen content of the respective passageway (4).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0025" num="0025"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in Claim 24 in which said pump (16) is controlled to maintain a constant suction pressure and the respective mass flow controllers (18,18',18&quot;) regulate mass flow from the respective passageways (4) more rapidly than the pump (16) can respond to corresponding changes in pressure levels.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0026" num="0026"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in any one of Claims 20 to 25 in which said purifying means (23) removes moisture from the used coolant gas.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0027" num="0027"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in Claim 26 in which the purifying means (23) removes moisture by cooling the used coolant gas to freeze out the water content thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0028" num="0028"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in Claim 26 or Claim 27 in which said purifying means (23) also removes oxygen. form the used coolant gas.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-01-0029" num="0029"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in any one of Claims 20 to 28 in which the inlet means (6) comprises respective pressure regulators (11,10) on the fresh coolant gas and the recirculated coolant gas set to provide recirculated coolant gas in preference to fresh coolant gas.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim id="c-fr-01-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>Procédé de refroidissement de fibre chaude en continu (1) comprenant les étapes consistant à faire passer simultanément la fibre à travers un passage à extrémités ouvertes (4) d'un échangeur thermique (2) placé dans une atmosphère contenant de l'oxygène ambiant ; introduire dans le passage un gaz de refroidissement (via la conduite 5) comprenant un gaz de refroidissement purifié remis à circuler (via la conduite 7) et un gaz de refroidissement frais (via la conduite 8) ; permettre à une partie du gaz de refroidissement utilisé de quitter le passage aux dites extrémités ouvertes pour limiter l'entrée de l'atmosphère ambiante dans le passage ; enlever, purifier et remettre à circuler dans le passage une partie du gaz de refroidissement utilisé (depuis les orifices de sortie 15,15') ; et surveiller la teneur en oxygène de ladite partie enlevée, <b>caractérisé en ce que</b> ledit enlèvement dudit gaz de refroidissement utilisé pour purification et recirculation est interrompu automatiquement lorsque la teneur en oxygène dudit gaz de refroidissement utilisé dépasse une concentration maximale prédéterminée ; ledit enlèvement est recommencé lorsque la teneur en oxygène tombe en dessous d'une concentration minimale prédéterminée ; et l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement introduit dans le passage est commandé indépendamment de sa composition.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 1, dans lequel la fibre (1) est une fibre optique et le gaz de refroidissement frais (via la conduite 8) est de l'hélium.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 1 ou 2, dans lequel ladite concentration d'oxygène maximale est d'environ 2 % et la concentration d'oxygène minimale est d'environ 1 %.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 2 ou 3, dans lequel la teneur en hélium du gaz de refroidissement (via la conduite 5) introduit dans le passage (4) est maintenue à l'intérieur de la plage de 95 % à 100 %.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0005" num="0005"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel la vitesse de la fibre (1) et l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement introduit sont maintenus constants pendant le fonctionnement normal.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0006" num="0006"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel le gaz de refroidissement (via la conduite 5) est introduit dans le passage (4) à environ son point milieu et le gaz de refroidissement utilisé (depuis les orifices de sortie 15, 15') enlevé pour purification et recirculation est enlevé à deux emplacements chacun adjacent à une extrémité ouverte respective du passage.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0007" num="0007"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel le rapport de l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement utilisé (depuis les orifices de sortie 15, 15') enlevé pour purification et recirculation à l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement (via la conduite 5) introduit est maintenu constant pendant le fonctionnement normal.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0008" num="0008"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement utilisé (depuis les orifices de sortie 15, 15') enlevé pour purification et recirculation est d'environ 90 % de l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement (via la conduite 5) introduit.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0009" num="0009"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel la proportion du gaz de refroidissement utilisé (depuis les orifices de sortie 15, 15') enlevé pour purification et recirculation pendant le démarrage est progressivement accrue jusqu'à un rapport prédéterminé de l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement utilisé enlevé pour purification et recirculation à l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement (via la conduite 5) introduit.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0010" num="0010"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel la proportion du gaz de refroidissement utilisé (depuis les orifices de sortie 15, 15') enlevé pour purification et recirculation après ladite interruption est progressivement accrue jusqu'à un rapport prédéterminé de l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement utilisé enlevé pour purification et recirculation à l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement (via la conduite 5) introduit.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0011" num="0011"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel ladite purification comprend l'enlèvement de l'humidité.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0012" num="0012"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 11, dans lequel la fibre (1) est une fibre optique, le gaz de refroidissement frais (via la conduite 8) est de l'hélium, et l'humidité est enlevée en refroidissant la partie de gaz de refroidissement utilisée (depuis les orifices de sortie 15, 15') enlevé pour recirculation pour éliminer par congélation sa teneur en eau.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0013" num="0013"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel ladite purification comprend l'enlèvement de l'oxygène.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0014" num="0014"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel la concentration d'oxygène est mesurée dans un flux échantillon du gaz de refroidissement utilisé (depuis les orifices de sortie 15, 15') enlevé du passage (4).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0015" num="0015"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 14, dans lequel, pendant le fonctionnement normal, le flux échantillon est combiné avec le gaz de refroidissement enlevé pour purification et recirculation.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0016" num="0016"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel le gaz de refroidissement utilisé enlevé (depuis les orifices de sortie 15, 15') pour purification et recirculation est enlevé par une pompe à vide (16) en amont de sa purification ; l'écoulement massique de la partie de gaz enlevée est régulé par un contrôleur d'écoulement massique (18, 18', 18'') en amont de ladite pompe ; et l'écoulement est interrompu par une soupape de coupure (19, 19', 19'') positionnée entre ledit contrôleur d'écoulement massique et la pompe.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0017" num="0017"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 16, dans lequel ladite pompe (16) aspire le gaz de refroidissement utilisé (depuis les orifices de sortie 15, 15') à partir de plus qu'un dudit passage (4) avec une interruption indépendante et une régulation d'écoulement massique indépendante de l'enlèvement de gaz de refroidissement utilisé pour purification et recirculation à partir de chaque passage en réponse à la teneur en oxygène du passage respectif.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0018" num="0018"><claim-text>Procédé selon la revendication 17, dans lequel ladite pompe (16) est commandée pour maintenir une pression d'aspiration constante et les contrôleurs d'écoulement massique respectifs (18, 18', 18'') régulent l'écoulement massique provenant du passage (4) respectif plus rapidement que la pompe peut répondre aux changements correspondants des niveaux de pression.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0019" num="0019"><claim-text>Procédé selon l'une quelconque des revendications précédentes, dans lequel l'ajout de gaz de refroidissement frais (via la conduite 8) au gaz de refroidissement utilisé purifié remis à circuler (via la conduite 7) pour fournir le gaz de refroidissement (via la conduite 5) introduit dans le passage (4) est commandé par la régulation de la pression dudit gaz de refroidissement introduit en utilisant des régulateurs de pression (10, 11) respectifs sur le gaz de refroidissement frais et le gaz de refroidissement remis à circuler établis pour fournir le gaz de refroidissement remis à circuler en préférence au gaz de refroidissement frais.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0020" num="0020"><claim-text>Appareil pour refroidir une fibre chaude en continu comprenant :
<claim-text>un échangeur thermique (2) pour positionnement dans une atmosphère contenant de l'oxygène ambiant et ayant un passage à extrémités ouvertes (4) pour recevoir la fibre chaude en continu (1) pour passage à travers celui-ci ;</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen d'orifice d'entrée (6) pour introduire dans le passage un gaz de refroidissement comprenant un gaz de refroidissement purifié remis à circuler (via la conduite 7) et un gaz de refroidissement frais (via la conduite 8) à un écoulement massique indépendant de ladite composition du gaz de refroidissement ;</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen d'orifice de sortie (15, 15') pour enlever une partie du gaz de refroidissement utilisé du passage ;</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen de purification (23) pour purifier ladite partie enlevée du gaz de refroidissement utilisé ;</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen de pompage (16, 25) pour faire recirculer ladite partie de gaz de refroidissement enlevée dudit moyen d'orifice de sortie (15, 15') vers ledit moyen d'orifice d'entrée (6) via ledit moyen de purification (23) ;</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen d'analyse d'oxygène (22) pour surveiller la teneur en oxygène de ladite partie de gaz de refroidissement enlevée ;</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen de commande d'écoulement de recirculation (19) pour interrompre ledit enlèvement dudit gaz de refroidissement utilisé ; et</claim-text><claim-text>un moyen de signal pour activer ledit moyen de commande de l'écoulement de recirculation (19) pour interrompre automatiquement ledit enlèvement dudit gaz de refroidissement utilisé lorsque la teneur en oxygène mesurée par ledit moyen d'analyse d'oxygène (22) dépasse une concentration maximale prédéterminée et pour recommencer ledit enlèvement lorsque ladite teneur en oxygène mesurée tombe en dessous d'une concentration minimale prédéterminée.</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0021" num="0021"><claim-text>Appareil selon la revendication 20, dans lequel ledit moyen d'orifice d'entrée (6) introduit le gaz de refroidissement dans le passage (4) à environ son point milieu et le moyen d'orifice de sortie (15, 15') enlève le gaz de refroidissement utilisé à deux emplacements chacun adjacent à une extrémité ouverte respective du passage (4).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0022" num="0022"><claim-text>Appareil selon la revendication 20 ou 21, comprenant, en outre, un moyen de commande d'écoulement massique (18) pour maintenir constant pendant le fonctionnement normal le rapport de l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement utilisé enlevé par ledit moyen d'orifice de sortie (15, 15') à l'écoulement massique du gaz de refroidissement introduit par ledit moyen d'orifice d'entrée (6).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0023" num="0023"><claim-text>Appareil selon la revendication 22, dans lequel le moyen de pompage comprend une pompe à vide (16) en amont dudit moyen de purification (23) ; ledit moyen de commande d'écoulement massique comprend un contrôleur d'écoulement massique (18) en amont de ladite pompe (16) ; et le moyen de commande de recirculation comprend une soupape de coupure (19) positionnée entre ledit contrôleur d'écoulement massique (18) et ladite pompe (16).</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0024" num="0024"><claim-text>Appareil selon la revendication 23, dans lequel ladite pompe (16) est raccordée au moyen d'orifice de sortie (15, 15') dudit passage (4) avec une interruption indépendante (19, 19', 19'') et une régulation d'écoulement massique indépendante (18, 18', 18'') de l'enlèvement du gaz de refroidissement utilisé à partir de chaque passage (4) en réponse à la teneur en oxygène du passage (4) respectif.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0025" num="0025"><claim-text>Appareil selon la revendication 24, dans lequel ladite pompe (16) est commandée pour maintenir une pression d'aspiration constante et les contrôleurs d'écoulement massique respectifs (18, 18', 18'') régulent l'écoulement massique provenant des passages respectifs (4) plus rapidement que la pompe (16) peut répondre aux changements correspondants des niveaux de pression.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0026" num="0026"><claim-text>Appareil selon l'une quelconque des revendications 20 à 25, dans lequel ledit moyen de purification (23) enlève l'humidité du gaz de refroidissement utilisé.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0027" num="0027"><claim-text>Appareil selon la revendication 26, dans lequel le moyen de purification (23) enlève l'humidité en refroidissant le gaz de refroidissant utilisé pour éliminer par congélation la teneur en eau.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0028" num="0028"><claim-text>Appareil selon la revendication 26 ou 27, dans lequel ledit moyen de purification (23) enlève également l'oxygène du gaz de refroidissement utilisé.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-fr-01-0029" num="0029"><claim-text>Appareil selon l'une quelconque des revendications 20 à 28, dans lequel le moyen d'orifice d'entrée (6) comprend des régulateurs de pression (11, 10) respectifs sur le gaz de refroidissement frais et le gaz de refroidissement remis à circuler établis pour fournir le gaz de refroidissement remis à circuler en préférence au gaz de refroidissement frais.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="25" date="20070328"><legal-event-body><event-title>LAPSED IN A CONTRACTING STATE ANNOUNCED VIA POSTGRANT INFORM. FROM NAT. OFFICE TO EPO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>BE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DK</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ES</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>LU</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>MC</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>NL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PT</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>SE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060111</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060111</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060111</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060111</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060111</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060111</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060321</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060331</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060331</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060411</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060411</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060422</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060612</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="26" date="20061115"><legal-event-body><event-title>OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>opponent name </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>L'AIR LIQUIDE, SOCIETE ANONYME POUR L</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20061011</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20060804"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20060731"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>PL</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="NLV1" date="20060703"><legal-event-body><event-title>NL: LAPSED OR ANNULED DUE TO FAILURE TO FULFILL THE REQUIREMENTS OF ART. 29P AND 29M OF THE PATENTS ACT; NO LEGAL EFFECT FROM</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20060406"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60116566</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20060406</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20060208"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>IE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20060113"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>CH</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>EP</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20060111"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>B1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20030122"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AT BE CH CY DE DK ES FI FR GB GR IE IT LI LU MC NL PT SE TR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20020918"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020717</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20020502"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A3</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20020502"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010926"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A2</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>ATBECHCYDEDKESFIFRGBGRIEITLILUMCNLPTSETR</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010926"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>