<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document status="new" lang="EN" ucid="EP-1122087-B1" country="EP" doc-number="1122087" kind="B1" date="20030423"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="23188936" ucid="EP-1122087-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1122087</doc-number><kind>B1</kind><date>20030423</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01200254-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01200254</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010124</date><lang>EN</lang></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-498575" status="new"><document-id format="original" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>498575</doc-number><date>20000204</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-49857500-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>49857500</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000204</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><dates-of-public-availability status="new" /><term-of-grant /><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B32B  27/20        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B32B  27/20        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   7/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   7/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03C  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03C  11/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03G   8/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G03G   8/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41M7/00C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">G03C11/08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">G03G8/00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" status="new">Bildschutzschicht für die thermische Übertragung</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" status="new">Thermally transferable image-protecting layer</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" status="new">Couche protectrice d'images pour transfert par la chaleur</invention-title><citations /><figures /></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>EASTMAN KODAK CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>WEXLER ALLAN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>WEXLER, ALLAN</name><address><country /></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Wexler, Allan, Eastman Kodak Company</last-name><address><street>Patent Legal Staff, 343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650-2201</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><assignees><assignee format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY</last-name><address><street>343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></assignee></assignees><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Haile, Helen Cynthia</last-name><address><street>Kodak Limited Patent, W92-3A, Headstone Drive</street><city>Harrow, Middlesex HA1 4TY</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="EPO" status="new"><p>A transfer laminating element for laminating ink jet prints comprising a flexible, polymeric support having thereon a porous, fusible, transferable protection layer comprising fusible, thermoplastic polymeric particles in a polymeric binder, the protection layer having a thickness of between 2 and 100  mu m and a particle-to-binder ratio of between 95:5 and 70:30, the thermoplastic polymeric particles having a particle size of less than 10  mu m and a Tm or softening point of greater than 50 DEG C. and the polymeric binder having a Tg of less than 20  DEG  C.</p></abstract><abstract lang="EN" status="new"><p num="">A transfer laminating element for laminating ink jet prints
comprising a flexible, polymeric support having thereon a porous, fusible,
transferable protection layer comprising fusible, thermoplastic polymeric particles
in a polymeric binder, the protection layer having a thickness of between 2 and
100 µm and a particle-to-binder ratio of between 95:5 and 70:30, the
thermoplastic polymeric particles having a particle size of less than 10 µm and a
Tm or softening point of greater than 50°C. and the polymeric binder having a Tg
of less than 20 ° C.</p></abstract><description lang="EN" status="new"><p num="0001">This invention relates to an element for laminating ink jet prints,
more particularly to a polymeric support having thereon a porous, fusible,
transferable protection layer.</p><p num="0002">In a typical ink jet recording or printing system, ink droplets are
ejected from a nozzle at high speed towards a recording element or medium to
produce an image on the medium. The ink droplets, or recording liquid, generally
comprise a recording agent, such as a dye or pigment, and a large amount of
solvent. The solvent, or carrier liquid, typically is made up of water, an organic
material such as a monohydric alcohol, a polyhydric alcohol or mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0003">An ink jet recording element typically comprises a support
having on at least one surface thereof a base layer for absorbing fluid and an
ink-receiving or image-forming layer, and includes those intended for
reflection viewing, which have an opaque support, and those intended for
viewing by transmitted light, which have a transparent support.</p><p num="0004">Ink jet prints prepared by printing onto ink jet recording
elements are subject to environmental degradation such as water smearing and
light fade. For example, since ink jet dyes are water-soluble, they can migrate
from their location in the ink-receiving layer when water comes in contact
with the recording element after imaging.</p><p num="0005">To reduce the vulnerability of prints to degradation and to
enhance gloss, ink jet prints are often laminated. Typically, such
conventional lamination is a process whereby a continuous polymeric film
bearing an adhesive is brought into contact with the surface of the print. Heat
and/or pressure is then used to affix the continuous polymeric film to the print
surface. The continuous polymeric film then serves as a barrier layer that is
impermeable to water and further acts to diminish the fading of the print
image caused by light.</p><p num="0006">However, there is a problem with prior art laminating films
since they are typically supplied in roll format and must be cut, or less 
desirably torn, to separate the laminated print from the continuous roll of
laminating film. A requirement to cut adds expense to a laminator design that
is required to run in a continuous mode.</p><p num="0007"><ref typ="patent">US-A-5,662,976</ref> discloses an assembly for creating laminated
cards which comprises a sheet of card stock with a release coating and a sheet
of laminating film adhering to the release coating. A card form is cut into the
sheet of card stock, and a lamination strip, which is sufficiently large to fold
over so as to laminate both surfaces of the card, is cut into the lamination
sheet. After printing, the card and the lamination strip are removed, and the
lamination strip folded over to laminate the card. However, there is a problem
with this laminating film in that expensive cutting and perforating steps are
required to prepare the laminated card.</p><p num="0008"><ref typ="patent">US-A-5,387,573</ref> discloses a dye-donor element for thermal dye
transfer comprising a support and a transferable protection layer wherein the
transferable protection layer is less than 1µm thick and contains particles in an
amount of up to 75% of the transferable protection layer. However, there is
no disclosure in this patent that the protection layer can be used with ink jet
prints.</p><p num="0009"><ref typ="patent">EP-A-0 943 453</ref> relates to a thermal transfer sheet having a
releasable protective laminate prepared by laminating a protective layer composed
mainly of solvent-insoluble organic fine particles and a binder resin. However,
these organic fine particles are not capable of being fused to form a substantially
continuous film which is optically clear upon the application of heat and pressure.</p><p num="0010"><ref typ="patent">EP-A-0 487 727</ref> relates to a thermal transfer cover sheet containing
uan ionizing radiation-curing resin, silicone-modified resin and wax-containing
resin. However, there is no disclosure of particles which are capable of being
fused to form a substantially continuous film which is optically clear upon the
application of heat and pressure. </p><p num="0011"><ref typ="npl">Research Disclosure (1996) March, No. 383, Emsworth, Great
Britain, pp. 169-172, &quot;Protective layers for imaged transparent thermal dye
transfer receivers&quot;</ref> relates to a protective layer for imaged transparent thermal dye
transfer receivers comprising porous beads. However, there is no disclosure of
particles which are capable of being fused to form a substantially continuous film
which is optically clear upon the application of heat and pressure.</p><p num="0012">It is an object of the invention to provide a transfer laminating
element for laminating ink jet prints wherein the protection layer is
sufficiently thick to protect ink jet images from degradation by water, and yet
can be employed without resort to expensive cutting steps. It is another object
to provide a transfer laminating element for laminating an ink jet print of
arbitrary geometric shape. It is still another object to provide a transfer
laminating element that allows for the direct visual distinction between
laminated and unlaminated regions of the print.</p><p num="0013">These and other objects are provided by the present invention which
comprises a transfer laminating element for laminating inkjet prints
comprising a flexible, polymeric support having thereon a porous, fusible,
transferable protection layer comprising fusible, thermoplastic polymeric particles
in a polymeric binder, the protection layer having a thickness of between 2 and 
100 µm and a particle-to-binder ratio of between 95:5 and 70:30, the
thermoplastic polymeric particles having a particle size of less than 10 µm and a
Tm or softening point of greater than 50°C. and the polymeric binder having a Tg
of less than 20 ° C, said porous, fusible, transferable protection layer being capable
of forming a continuous film which is optically clear upon the
application of heat and pressure.</p><p num="0014">In using the invention, the transfer laminating element is contacted
with an ink jet image using heat and pressure to form a fused composite. Within the
composite, the porous, fusible, transferable protection layer fuses to become a
continuous film which is optically clear. After cooling below the Tg of
the polymer used to make the particles, the support is peeled from the composite.
The continuous film easily separates, without cutting, from the unfused
porous region, thereby forming a protection layer on the surface of the ink jet image.</p><p num="0015">As noted above, the particle-to-binder ratio in the protection layer
is between 95:5 and 70:30. If the particle-to-binder ratio is above the range stated,
the layer will not have any cohesive strength. If the particle-to-binder ratio is
below the range stated, the layer will not be porous, and on peeling the support
away from the cooled composite after laminating, a continuous film is present
which must be cut.</p><p num="0016">It is believed that when a fusible, transferable protection layer is
used which is porous, cutting is obviated by the weak cohesive strength at the
interface between the area of the continuous film formed on fusing
and the unfused, porous area. Thus, the interface acts as a micro-perforated edge
of the film that facilitates a clean rupture. Further, during the fusing step,
otherwise entrained air escapes via the interface between the
continuous film and the unfused, porous area.</p><p num="0017">The polymer used to make the fusible, thermoplastic polymeric
particles employed in the invention may be an amorphous polymer which has
softening point greater than 50°C., such as an amorphous polyester, e.g., Kao C ®
(Kao Corp.) or an acrylic polymer such as Carboset 526 ® (BF Goodrich Specialy
Chemicals); or a partially crystalline polymer having a Tm greater than 50°C.,
such as a partially crystalline polyester, e.g., Griltex Polyester® (EMS 
American Grilon Corp) or an ethylene-vinyl acetate copolymer such as Elvax ®
(DuPont Corp.); or a thermoplastic, modified cellulose such as Ethocel ® (Dow
Chemical Co.), etc. In a preferred embodiment, the fusible, thermoplastic
polymeric particles are made from an amorphous polyester having a silica shell.
In another preferred embodiment, the fusible, thermoplastic polymeric particles
contain a UV-absorber.</p><p num="0018">The fusible, thermoplastic polymeric particles used in the invention
may be made using various techniques, such as, for example, evaporative limited
coalescence as described in <ref typ="patent">US-A-4,833,060</ref>, limited coalescence as described in
<ref typ="patent">US-A-5,354,799</ref>, grinding as described in <ref typ="patent">US-A-4,304,360</ref>, or cryogenic grinding
as described in <ref typ="patent">US-A-4,273,294</ref>.</p><p num="0019">As noted above, the polymer used to make the fusible,
thermoplastic particles will have a Tm or softening point greater than 50°C,
preferably between 60°C and 150°C. The Tm is measured using a differential
scanning calorimeter (DSC). In a preferred embodiment, the Tm is between 60°C
and 120 ° C. A softening point of a polymer can be measured by the Ring and Ball
method as described in ASTM E28. In addition, the polymer used to make the
fusible, thermoplastic particles usually will have a Tg of less than 100°C,
preferably between 0°C and 90°C.</p><p num="0020">As noted above, the polymeric binder used in the invention has a
Tg of less than 20° C., preferably between -60°C and 20°C. The polymeric
binder used in the invention may be, for example, a polyurethane such as a
Witcobond ® Aqueous Urethane Dispersion (Witco Corp.), a vinyl acetate-ethylene
copolymer emulsion, an ethylene-vinyl chloride copolymer emulsion, a
vinyl acetate-vinyl chloride-ethylene terpolymer emulsion such as Airflex ® (Air
Products Corp.), or an acrylic emulsion such as Flexbond® (Air Products Corp).
In a preferred embodiment, the binder comprises a polyurethane.</p><p num="0021">A subbing/release layer may also be used to provide adhesion
between the porous, fusible, transferable protection layer and the support. The
subbing/release layer must be capable of initially adhering the protection layer to
the support and must be capable of subsequently releasing the protection layer 
from the support upon application of heat and pressure followed by cooling. Any
material that performs this adhesion/release function can be used. In general, a
coated subbing/release layer has a final coating weight of 90 mg/m<sup>2</sup>. Suitable
materials include, for example, lattices such as a terpolymer latex of acrylonitrile,
vinylidene chloride and acrylic acid, or partially hydrolyzed vinyl chloride-vinyl
acetate copolymers. Alternatively, a subbing/release layer can be generated
directly on the support surface by corona-discharge-treatment of the support prior
to applying the porous, fusible, transferable protection layer.</p><p num="0022">As the flexible, polymeric support for the invention, there may be
used, for example, various plastics including a polyester-type resin such as
poly(ethylene terephthalate), poly(ethylene naphthalate), polycarbonate resins,
polystyrene resins, polysulfone resins, methacrylic resins, cellophane, acetate
plastics, cellulose diacetate, cellulose triacetate, vinyl chloride resins and
polyester diacetate. The thickness of the support may be, for example, from 12 to
500 µm, preferably from 75 to 300 µm. In a preferred embodiment, the support is
a transparent poly(ethylene terephthalate) film.</p><p num="0023">Since the transfer lamination element may come in contact with
other image recording articles or the drive or transport mechanisms of laminating
devices, additives such as surfactants, lubricants, matte particles and the like may
be added to the element to the extent that they do not degrade the properties of
interest.</p><p num="0024">The protection layer described above may be coated by
conventional coating means onto the support such as wound wire rod coating, slot
coating, slide hopper coating, gravure, curtain coating and the like.</p><p num="0025">Ink jet inks used to prepare the images to be laminated by the
transfer lamination element of the invention are well-known in the art. The ink
compositions used in ink jet printing typically are liquid compositions comprising
a solvent or carrier liquid, dyes or pigments, humectants, organic solvents,
detergents, thickeners, preservatives, and the like. The solvent or carrier liquid
can be solely water or can be water mixed with other water-miscible solvents such
as polyhydric alcohols. Inks in which organic materials such as polyhydric 
alcohols are the predominant carrier or solvent liquid may also be used.
Particularly useful are mixed solvents of water and polyhydric alcohols. The dyes
used in such compositions are typically water-soluble direct or acid type dyes.
Such liquid compositions have been described extensively in the prior art
including, for example, <ref typ="patent">US-A-4,381,946</ref>; <ref typ="patent">US-A-4,239,543</ref> and <ref typ="patent">US-A-4,781,758</ref>.</p><p num="0026">Although the elements disclosed herein have been referred to
primarily as being useful for laminating ink jet prints, they also can be used to
protect images created employing other technologies such as photographic prints,
laser printer prints, prints made via offset lithography and the like.</p><p num="0027">The following examples further illustrates the invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1 -Lamination Test</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of Thermoplastic Polymeric Particles</u></heading><p num="0028">To 225 g ethyl acetate was added 22.5 g of Kao C® polyester resin
and 2.5 g UV absorber Escalol® 597 (ISP Corp.) and stirred to solution.
Separately, an aqueous solution was prepared of 375 g pH 4 buffer, 21 g Ludox
TM® colloidal silica (DuPont Corp.), and 4.5g of 10% poly(adipic acid-comethylaminoethanol).
The aqueous phase was placed in a Silverson mixer, the
organic phase was added and emulsified at 3,000 s<sup>-1</sup> (rev/min) for one minute.
The emulsion was then passed through a Microfluidizer (Microfluidics
Manufacturing model 110T) to further reduce the emulsion droplet size. After
evaporating the ethyl acetate, there was obtained a narrowly distributed population
of silica coated polyester beads, µm= 3.0 +/- .36 µm, with incorporated UV
absorber. Sufficient water was decanted to give a dispersion with 30% solids.</p><heading><u style="single">Coating Solutions</u></heading><p num="0029">A series of coating solutions at 24% solids were prepared, at
the particle-to-binder ratios shown in Table 1, by mixing the above polyester
particles and a polyurethane binder, Witcobond® 215, a 35% aqueous
polyurethane dispersion. </p><heading><u style="single">Solution 1 of the Invention (Particle:Binder 90:10)</u></heading><p num="0030">14.4 g of thermoplastic polymeric particles, 1.37 g of binder and
4.23 g of deionized water were mixed together to form a coating solution with a
particle-to-binder ratio of 90:10.</p><heading><u style="single">Solution 2 of the Invention (Particle:Binder 75:25)</u></heading><p num="0031">12.0 g of thermoplastic polymeric particles, 3.43 g of binder and
4.57 g of deionized water were mixed together to form a coating solution with a
particle-to-binder ratio of 75:25.</p><heading><u style="single">Control Solution 1 (Particle:Binder 50:50)</u></heading><p num="0032">8.0 g of thermoplastic polymeric particles, 6.86 g of binder and
5.14 g of deionized water were mixed together to form a coating solution with a
particle-to-binder ratio of 50:50.</p><heading><u style="single">Control Solution 2 (Particle:Binder 25:75)</u></heading><p num="0033">4.0 g of thermoplastic polymeric particles, 10.28 g of binder
and 5.72 g of deionized water were mixed together to form a coating solution with
a particle-to-binder ratio of 25:75.</p><heading><u style="single">Control Solution 3 (Particle:Binder 5:95)</u></heading><p num="0034">0.8 g of thermoplastic polymeric particles, 13.03 g of binder and
6.17 g of deionized water were mixed together to form a coating solution with a
particle-to-binder ratio of 5:95.</p><heading><u style="single">Coating</u></heading><p num="0035">Each of the above solutions were coated on 100µm thick, poly(ethylene
terephthalate) support using a wire wound rod, calibrated to give a wet laydown of
120µm. The support had been previously subbed with a terpolymer latex of
acrylonitrile, vinylidene chloride and acrylic acid. The coatings were air dried
forming Elements 1 and 2 of the invention with an unfused porous layer 
thickness of 57µm, and non-porous Control Elements 1-3 with a layer thickness of
30µm. All the elements were then cut to give 9.5 cm wide by 28 cm long
segments.</p><heading><u style="single">Lamination Test</u></heading><p num="0036">Ink jet images for lamination testing were printed on an ink jet receiver
consisting of a resin-coated paper receiver with an 102 mg/m<sup>2</sup> ink receiving layer,
comprised of 75% gelatin, 15% polyvinylpyrrolidone and 10% of a cationic latex
mordant. After imaging, a 9.5 cm wide by 28 cm long segment was cut from the
receiver. The protection layer of each of the above elements was then contacted
with the ink jet image and laminated by passing through the nip of a pair of heated
rollers. Laminating speed was 46 cm/minute, with the upper roller at 150°C and
at nip pressure of 0.41 MPa.</p><p num="0037">Only 10 cm of the 28 cm long segments, corresponding to the length of the
image, were passed into the nip. The fused composites were allowed to cool to
room temperature, and the support was then peeled away from the fused
composite. After fusing, the transferred protection layers from porous Elements 1
and 2 of the invention, having been compressed under heat and pressure, formed a
34µm thick non-porous continuous layer.</p><p num="0038">The same size image was also laminated with a 75µm thick commercial
laminating film, Seal ThermaShield R ®(Hunt Graphics Americas Co.) to provide
an additional Element, Control 4.</p><p num="0039">The elements were then evaluated for peel. Peel ratings from 1 to 5 are
listed below. A peel rating of 1 corresponds to a continuous film that extends
beyond the edge of the fused area and must be cut to separate it from the image,
i.e., failure. A rating of 5 corresponds to a clean break at the interface. The
following results were obtained: <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Element</entry><entry align="center">Particle/Binder Ratio</entry><entry align="center">Peel Rating</entry><entry align="left">Comment</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">90/10</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="left">Clean break at interface</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">75/25</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="left">Breaks at interface</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Control 1</entry><entry align="center">50/50</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="left">Continuous film that requires cutting</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Control 2</entry><entry align="center">25/75</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="left">Continuous film that requires cutting</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Control 3</entry><entry align="center">5/95</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="left">Continuous film that requires cutting</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Control 4</entry><entry align="center">0/100</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="left">Continuous film that requires cutting</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0040">The above results show that costly cutting steps can be eliminated using
the transfer laminating element employed in the process of the invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2 (Arbitrary Shaped Lamination Without Cutting)</u></heading><p num="0041">Circular images having a 4.4 cm diameter were printed on commercial
Kodak® photographic ink jet media using a Hewlett Packard® 895 printer. The
transfer laminating Element 1 prepared above was placed on top of the circular
image. A 5.1 cm diameter circular steel disk heated to 150°C was placed on the
laminating element, centered over the image, and pressed at 0.70 MPa for ten
seconds. After cooling, the laminating element was peeled from the composite,
leaving a fused circular film layer over the circular ink jet image. The above
process was repeated using Control Elements 1-4 described above. However, they
could not be separated from the circular image without cutting.</p><p num="0042">This example shows that the laminating element employed in the process
of the invention can be used to deposit protective layers in varying geometries
without requiring a cutting step. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 3 (Waterfastness of the Transferred Protection Layer)</u></heading><p num="0043">A pair of ink jet images was printed using each of five commercially
available ink jet printers on commercially available Kodak® photographic quality
ink jet paper. One member of the pair was then contacted with Element 1 of the
invention and passed through the nip of a pair of rollers. The other image was not
laminated. Laminating speed was 46 cm minute, with the upper roller at 150°C
and at nip pressure of 0.41 MPa. The composite was allowed to cool. Peeling
easily separated the support layer of the transfer laminate from the composite to
afford a laminated image.</p><heading><u style="single">Waterfastness and Smudge Tests</u></heading><p num="0044">With the prints laying image side up and on a flat surface, one drop of
water was placed near the left edge of the print and 2.54 cm from the top edge.
Likewise, a drop was place near the right edge of the print and 2.54 cm from the
top. After a minute exposure to the water drops, the right drop is wiped with a
Kim Wipe ® using light pressure (smudge test) and immediately afterward the
print is turned upright allowing the water drop on the left side to run to the bottom
of the print (drip test). The tested prints are hung and allowed to dry. They are
then rated on a subjective scale ranging from 1-No visible smearing or running to
5- Catastrophic running and/or smearing (image ruined) and reported below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><u style="single">Laminated</u></entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">Printer</u></entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">Smudge</u></entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">Drip</u></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Yes</entry><entry align="center">HP 895</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">No</entry><entry align="center">HP 895</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Yes</entry><entry align="center">Epson 900</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">No</entry><entry align="center">Epson 900</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Yes</entry><entry align="center">Lexmark 5700</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">No</entry><entry align="center">Lexmark 5700</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Yes</entry><entry align="center">Canon 4400</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">No</entry><entry align="center">Canon 4400</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0045">The above results show that the polymeric particles fuse and transfer to
form a continuous protective layer which functions as a barrier to effectively resist
water penetration into the ink jet prints.</p></description><claims lang="DE" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Übertragungslaminierelement zum Laminieren von Tintenstrahldrucken, das
einen flexiblen Polymerträger mit einer darauf angeordneten porösen, schmelzbaren,
übertragbaren Schutzschicht umfasst, die ihrerseits thermoplastische
Polymerpartikel in einem polymeren Bindemittel umfasst, wobei die Schutzschicht
eine Dicke zwischen 2 und 100 µm aufweist und ein Verhältnis von
Partikeln zu Bindemittel zwischen 95:5 und 70:30, wobei die thermoplastischen
Polymerpartikel eine Partikelgröße von kleiner als 10 um aufweisen und einen
Erweichungs- oder Tm-Punkt von größer als 50°C und wobei das polymere
Bindemittel eine Tg oder Glasübergangstemperatur von kleiner als 20°C
aufweist, wobei die poröse, schmelzbare, übertragbare Schutzschicht in der
Lage ist, einen Endlosfilm auszubilden, der bei Beaufschlagung mit Wärme und
Druck optisch klar ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Übertragungslaminierelement nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
eine Substrat-/Trennschicht zwischen dem Träger und der Schutzschicht angeordnet
ist, und dass die Substrat-/Trennschicht in der Lage ist, die Schutzschicht
an dem Träger festzuhalten und anschließend die Schutzschicht von
dem Träger bei Beaufschlagung mit Wärme und Druck sowie nachfolgender
Kühlung zu trennen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Übertragungslaminierelement nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
der Träger Poly(ethylenterephthalat) ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Übertragungslaminierelement nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
die thermoplastischen Polymerpartikel ein amorphes Polyester, ein teilweise
kristallines Polyester, ein Acrylpolymer, ein Ethylenvinylacetat-Copolymer oder
eine thermoplastische, modifizierte Cellulose umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Übertragungslaminierelement nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
die thermoplastischen Polymerpartikel ein amorphes Polyester mit einem Siliciumdioxidmantel
umfassen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Übertragungslaminierelement nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
die thermoplastischen Polymerpartikel ein UV-Absorbens enthalten.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Übertragungslaminierelement nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
das polymere Bindemittel ein Polyurethan, ein Vinylacetatethylen-Copolymer,
ein Ethylenvinylchlorid-Copolymer, ein Vinylacetat-Vinylchloridethylen-Terpolymer
oder ein Acrylpolymer ist.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Übertragungslaminierelement nach Anspruch 1, dadurch gekennzeichnet, dass
das polymere Bindemittel ein Polyurethan ist.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="EN" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>A transfer laminating element for laminating ink jet prints
comprising a flexible, polymeric support having thereon a porous, fusible,
transferable protection layer comprising fusible, thermoplastic polymeric particles
in a polymeric binder, said protection layer having a thickness of between 2
and 100 µm and a particle-to-binder ratio of between 95:5 and
70:30, said thermoplastic polymeric particles having a particle size of less than
10 µm and a Tm or softening point of greater than 50 ° C. and said
polymeric binder having a Tg of less than 20°C, said porous, fusible,
transferable protection layer being capable of forming a continuous
film which is optically clear upon the application of heat and pressure.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The element of Claim 1 wherein a subbing/release layer is
present between said support and said protection layer, said subbing/release layer
being capable of initially adhering said protection layer to said support and being
capable of subsequently releasing said protection layer from said support upon
application of heat and pressure followed by cooling.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The element of Claim 1 wherein said support is poly(ethylene
terephthalate).</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The element of Claim 1 wherein said fusible, thermoplastic
polymeric particles comprise an amorphous polyester, a partially crystalline
polyester, an acrylic polymer, an ethylene-vinyl acetate copolymer or a
thermoplastic, modified cellulose.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The element of Claim 1 wherein said fusible, thermoplastic
polymeric particles comprise an amorphous polyester having a silica shell.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The element of Claim 1 wherein said fusible, thermoplastic
polymeric particles contain a UV-absorber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The element of Claim 1 wherein said polymeric binder is
a polyurethane, a vinyl acetate-ethylene copolymer, an ethylene-vinyl chloride
copolymer, a vinyl acetate-vinyl chloride-ethylene terpolymer or an acrylic
polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>The element of Claim 1 wherein said polymeric binder is
a polyurethane.</claim-text></claim></claims><claims lang="FR" status="new"><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elément de lamination par transfert permettant de
laminer des épreuves pour jet d'encre comprenant un
support polymère souple revêtu d'une couche
protectrice transférable fusible poreuse comprenant
des particules polymères thermoplastiques fusibles
dans un liant polymère, ladite couche protectrice
ayant une épaisseur comprise entre 2 et 100 µm et un
rapport de particules au liant compris entre 95:5 et
70:30, lesdites particules polymères thermoplastiques
ayant une taille de particules inférieure à 10 µm et
une Tm ou point de ramollissement supérieur à 50°C et
ledit liant polymère ayant une Tg inférieure à 20°C,
ladite couche protectrice transférable fusible
poreuse étant capable de former un film continu
optiquement transparent après application d'une
source de chaleur et de pression.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elément selon la revendication 1, dans lequel on
utilise une couche substratante/pelliculable entre
ledit support et ladite couche protectrice, ladite
couche substratante/pelliculable étant capable de
faire adhérer au départ ladite couche protectrice sur
ledit support et étant capable ultérieurement de
pelliculer ladite couche protectrice dudit support
après application d'une source de chaleur et de
pression suivie d'une étape de refroidissement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elément selon la revendication 1, dans lequel ledit
support est du polytéréphtalate d'éthylène.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elément selon la revendication 1, dans lequel
lesdites particules polymères thermoplastiques
fusibles comprennent un polyester amorphe, un
polyester partiellement cristallin, un polymère
acrylique, un copolymère d'acétate vinylique et
d'éthylène ou de la cellulose modifiée
thermoplastique.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elément selon la revendication 1, dans lequel
lesdites particules polymères thermoplastiques
fusibles comprennent un polyester amorphe ayant une
coque de silice.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elément selon la revendication 1, dans lequel
lesdites particules polymères thermoplastiques
fusibles contiennent une substance absorbant dans
l'UV.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elément selon la revendication 1, dans lequel ledit
liant polymère est un polyuréthane, un copolymère
d'acétate de vinyle et d'éthylène, un copolymère
d'éthylène et de chlorure de vinyle, un terpolymère
d'acétate de vinyle, de chlorure de vinyle et
d'éthylène ou un polymère acrylique.</claim-text></claim><claim num="xx"><claim-text>Elément selon la revendication 1, dans lequel ledit
liant polymère est un polyuréthane.</claim-text></claim></claims><legal-status status="new"><legal-event country="EP" code="26N" date="20040414"><legal-event-body><event-title>NO OPPOSITION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20040126</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="ET" date="20040116"><legal-event-body><event-title>FR: TRANSLATION FILED</event-title></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REF" date="20030528"><legal-event-body><event-title>CORRESPONDS TO:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Document Number </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>60100195</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Country of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Date of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20030528</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>P</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20030423"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="REG" date="20030423"><legal-event-body><event-title>REFERENCE TO A NATIONAL CODE</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Country Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Ref Legal Event Code </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>FG4D</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AKX" date="20020502"><legal-event-body><event-title>PAYMENT OF DESIGNATION FEES</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DE FR GB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17Q" date="20020417"><legal-event-body><event-title>FIRST EXAMINATION REPORT</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20020228</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="17P" date="20020227"><legal-event-body><event-title>REQUEST FOR EXAMINATION FILED</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Effective Date </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>20011218</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AK" date="20010808"><legal-event-body><event-title>DESIGNATED CONTRACTING STATES:</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Kind Code of Ref Document </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>A1</event-attribute-value></event-attribute><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>Designated State(s) </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>DEFRGB</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event><legal-event country="EP" code="AX" date="20010808"><legal-event-body><event-title>EXTENSION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT TO</event-title><event-attributes><event-attribute><event-attribute-label>free format text </event-attribute-label><event-attribute-value>AL;LT;LV;MK;RO;SI</event-attribute-value></event-attribute></event-attributes></legal-event-body></legal-event></legal-status></patent-document>