<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="annotation.xsl"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="annotation.nvdl"?>
<fulltext-document system="ops.epo.org" fulltext-format="text-only" xmlns="http://www.epo.org/fulltext"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference data-format="docdb"><document-id><country>EP</country><doc-number>2281882</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id></publication-reference></bibliographic-data><description lang="EN"><p>Technical Field</p><p>[0001]  The present invention relates to a nucleic acid comprising a chimeric gene derived from hepatitis C viruses, a chimeric hepatitis C virus particle of the JFH-1 strain and a strain other than the JFH-1 strain (preferably a strain of genotype 1a, 1b, or 2a), a vector used for producing the virus particle, and a cell that produces the virus particle.</p><p>[0002]  The present invention also relates to a method for screening for an anti-HCV drug using the virus particle, a vaccine obtained by inactivating or attenuating the virus particle, and an anti-hepatitis C virus antibody that recognizes the virus particle as an antigen.</p><p>Background Art</p><p>[0003]  Hepatitis C virus (which may be simply referred to as "HCV" hereinafter) was discovered and identified as a causative virus of non-A and non-B hepatitis by Choo et al. in 1989 ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Choo, QL. et al., Science, 244: 359-362, 1989</bibl> ). HCV infection is a major cause for the progression with persistent infection from chronic hepatitis to cirrhosis and then hepatic cancer. It is said that there are approximately 170,000,000 HCV patients in the world and approximately 2,000,000 HCV patients in Japan. The major route of infection is transmission through blood. Since the screening of blood for transfusion was made available, the number of people newly infected with HCV dramatically decreased in Japan. However, it is considered that many virus carriers still remain.</p><p>[0004]  At present, HCV is mainly treated with the use of PEG-interferon or with the use of PEG-interferon in combination with an antiviral drug (i.e., ribavirin). HCV is currently classified into 6 different genotypes, and HCV of genotype 1b and of genotype 2a are major types in Japan. In the case of HCV of genotype 1b, in particular, viruses cannot be completely eliminated from the body via administration of interferon and ribavirin, and therapeutic effects are insufficient. Accordingly, development of novel antiviral drugs or vaccines aimed at preventing virus carriers from causing the disease to develop or at eliminating viruses has been awaited.</p><p>[0005]  The lack of effective animals that reflect virus infection besides chimpanzees and the lack of an effective in vitro virus culture system had been impediments to the development of therapeutic agents of HCV. In recent years, HCV replicon systems that enable evaluation of HCV-RNA replication have been developed ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Lohmann, V. et al., Science., 285: 110-113, 1999</bibl> ), and such systems resulted in important progress as a system for screening for HCV inhibitors associated with the inhibition of virus replication.</p><p>[0006]  HCV is a single-stranded (+) RNA virus having a genome length of approximately 9.6 kb, which has a gene encoding a precursor protein converted into 10 types of virus proteins (i.e., Core, E1, E2, p7, NS2, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A and NS5B proteins) upon post-translational cleavage by proteases. The replicon system was prepared by recombining the translation region of the HCV structural protein with a drug-resistant gene and inserting IRES of the encephalomyocarditis virus (EMCV) downstream thereof. RNA replication is observed in cells into which such recombinant RNA has been introduced. Even when a full-length genome RNA having the HCV structural protein region has been introduced into cells, however, release of virus particles into the culture solution has not been observed ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Pietschmann, T. et al., J. Virol., 76: 4008-4021, 2002</bibl> ).</p><p>[0007]  Recently, the HCV JFH-1 strain of genotype 2a isolated from a patient with fulminant hepatitis was discovered by Wakita et al., and the strain was found to be released as infectious virus particles in a culture medium of Huh-7 cells (hepatic cancer cell lines) ( <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 05080575A1</bibl> and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wakita, T. et al., Nat. Med., 11: 791-796, 2005</bibl> ). This in vitro culture system for infectious HCV particles is expected to serve as a useful screening tool in the development of anti-HCV agents and to be an effective means for preparation of HCV vaccines. Research on HCV particle production in in vitro culture systems has made progress, and the HCV genome capable of virus particle production was found to be chimeric HCV of the JFH-1 strain and an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain. Such chimeric HCV can be prepared by recombining the structural genes of the JFH-1 genome (i.e., Core, E1, E2 and p7 protein coding sections) with structural genes of other HCV strains.</p><p>[0008]  As chimeric HCV of the JFH-1 strain and an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain, the chimeric HCV of the J6CF strain (genotype 2a) and the JFH-1 strain ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Lindenbach, B. D. et al., Science, 309: 623-626, 2005</bibl> ), the chimeric HCV of the H77 strain (genotype 1a) and the JFH-1 strain ( <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 06096459A2</bibl> and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">MinKyung, Y. et al., J. Virol., 81: 629-638, 2007</bibl> ), and the chimeric HCV of the S52 strain (genotype 3a) and the JFH-1 strain ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gottwein, JM et al., Gastroenterology 133: 1614-1626, 2007</bibl> ) are known.</p><p>[0009]  Pietschmann, T. et al. (<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A., 103: 7408-7413, 2006</bibl> ) discloses that the amount of viruses produced from chimeric HCV of the J6CF structural gene and the JFH-1 non-structural gene is the highest and the the amount of infectious virus particles produced from chimeric HCV of the Con1 strain of genotype 1b and the JFH-1 strain is one tenth the former amount. As other chimeric HCV of a genotype 1b strain and the JFH-1 strain, <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 06022422A1</bibl> discloses that a genome (full-length genome replicon RNA) in which a region encoding the structural proteins of the TH strain is recombined with that of the JFH-1 genome, and a drug-resistant gene is inserted into a site upstream of such coding region was produced, the resulting genome is introduced into the Huh-7 cell, and then a drug-resistant strain is obtained, and infectious virus particles are produced into the culture supernatant, although productivity thereof is not clearly described.</p><p>[0010]  Under such circumstances, concerning genotype 1b for which the possibility of attaining a complete remission with current therapy techniques is small and of which the number of patients is large, there is a need for development of a method for producing HCV particles that can produce large quantities of infectious virus particles with the structure of genotype 1b, and that can be cultured in a persistent infection system.</p><p>Disclosure of the Invention</p><p>Problem to Be Solved by the Invention</p><p>[0011]  It is an object of the present invention to provide a method for efficiently producing HCV particles having the structural protein(s) of an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain of genotype 1a, 1b, or 2a and vaccines and the like comprising the resulting HCV particles.</p><p>Means for Solving the Problem</p><p>[0012]  The present inventors have conducted concentrated studies in order to solve the above problem. They examined the ability to produce HCV particles via cell culture and discovered an adaptive mutation that appears during HCV proliferation. They demonstrated that introduction of such adaptive mutation yields the significantly enhanced ability to produce HCV particles compared with wild-type strains before introduction of such mutation, and that HCV particles having the structural protein of the HCV strain of genotype 1a, 1b, or 2a can be prepared in a persistent infection system. This has led to the completion of the present invention.</p><p>[0013]  Specifically, the present invention relates to (1) to (22) below.</p><p>[0014]  (1) A nucleic acid comprising a chimeric gene derived from hepatitis C viruses comprising regions each encoding, Core protein, E1 protein, E2 protein and p7 protein derived from a hepatitis C virus strain other than JFH-1 strain; NS2 protein derived from JFH-1 strain or a hepatitis C virus strain other than JFH-1 strain, or a chimeric NS2 protein of NS2 protein derived from JFH-1 strain and NS2 protein derived from a hepatitis C virus strain other than JFH-1 strain; and NS3 protein, NS4A protein, NS4B protein, NS5A protein and NS5B protein derived from JFH-1 strain in that order in 5' to 3' direction,
wherein the 328th proline residue from the amino acid residue at N-terminus of the Core protein is substituted with an amino acid residue other than proline.</p><p>[0015]  (2) The nucleic acid according to (1) above, which comprises 5'-untranslated region of JFH-1 strain on the 5' side of the Core protein coding region and 3'-untranslated region of JFH-1 strain on the 3' side of the NS5B protein coding region.</p><p>[0016]  (3) The nucleic acid according to (1) or (2) above, wherein the hepatitis C virus strain other than JFH-1 strain is of genotype 1a, 1b, or 2a.</p><p>[0017]  (4) The nucleic acid according to any one of (1) to (3) above, wherein the hepatitis C virus strain other than JFH-1 strain is selected from the group consisting of TH strain, Con1 strain, J1 strain and derivative strains thereof.</p><p>[0018]  (5) The nucleic acid according to any one of (1) to (4) above, wherein the amino acid residue other than proline is selected from the group consisting of Ala, Leu, Ile, Val, Thr and Ser.</p><p>[0019]  (6) The nucleic acid according to any one of (1) to (5) above, wherein the nucleic acid is DNA comprising the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 1 of the sequence listing or a nucleotide sequence having 90% or more identity to the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 1, or RNA comprising the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 3 of the sequence listing or a nucleotide sequence having 90% or more identity to the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 3.</p><p>[0020]  (7) The nucleic acid according to any one of (1) to (5) above, wherein the nucleic acid is DNA comprising the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 2 of the sequence listing or a nucleotide sequence having 90% or more identity to the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 2, or RNA comprising the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 4 of the sequence listing or a nucleotide sequence having 90% or more identity to the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 4. </p><p>[0021]  (8) A vector comprising the nucleic acid according to any one of (1) to (7) above.</p><p>[0022]  (9) A chimeric hepatitis C virus particle comprising the nucleic acid according to any one of (1) to (7) above as a virus genome.</p><p>[0023]  (10) A cell which produces the chimeric hepatitis C virus particle according to (9) above.</p><p>[0024]  (11) The cell according to (10) above, wherein the cell is of Huh-7 strain or a derivative strain thereof.</p><p>[0025]  (12) A method for screening for an anti-hepatitis C virus substance comprising culturing, in the presence of a test substance: 
(a) the cell according to (10) or (11) above; or
(b) the chimeric hepatitis C virus particle according to (9) above and a hepatitis C virus-sensitive cell, and detecting replicon RNA or a virus particle derived from above-mentioned nucleic acid in the resulting culture.</p><p>[0026]  (13) A hepatitis C virus vaccine comprising the chimeric hepatitis C virus particle according to (9) above.</p><p>[0027]  (14) The hepatitis C virus vaccine according to (13) above, wherein the chimeric hepatitis C virus particle is inactivated or attenuated.</p><p>[0028]  (15) An anti-hepatitis C virus antibody which recognizes the chimeric hepatitis C virus particle according to (9) above as an antigen.</p><p>[0029]  (16) The nucleic acid according to (4) above, wherein the hepatitis C virus strain other than JFH-1 strain is TH strain or a derivative strain thereof. </p><p>[0030]  (17) The nucleic acid according to (5) above, wherein the amino acid residue other than proline is Ala or Thr.</p><p>[0031]  (18) A method for producing a chimeric hepatitis C virus particle comprising steps of
culturing the cell according to (10) or (11) above; and
recovering the chimeric hepatitis C virus particle according to (9) above.</p><p>[0032]  (19) A method for producing a hepatitis C virus vaccine comprising steps of: 
inactivating or attenuating the chimeric hepatitis C virus particle according to (9) above to prepare an inactivated or attenuated chimeric hepatitis C virus particle; and
formulating the inactivated or attenuated chimeric hepatitis C virus particle into a hepatitis C virus vaccine.</p><p>[0033]  (20) A method for producing an anti-hepatitis C virus antibody comprising a step of immunizing an animal (excluding a human) with the chimeric hepatitis C virus particle according to (9) above that is or is not inactivated or attenuated.</p><p>[0034]  (21) The method according to (20) above, wherein the anti-hepatitis C virus antibody is a polyclonal or monoclonal antibody.</p><p>[0035]  (22) The method according to (20) above, wherein the anti-hepatitis C virus antibody is a humanized antibody.</p><p>Effects of the Invention</p><p>[0036]  The nucleic acid comprising a chimeric gene derived from hepatitis C viruses of the present invention can be used for producing chimeric HCV particles exhibiting significantly higher productivity than wild-type HCV particles. The chimeric HCV particles of the present invention are advantageous over wild-type HCV particles in terms of their significantly high ability to be produced and their high infectivity with cells. Thus, the utility value thereof is high for a vaccine for HCV prevention or treatment or as a tool used for inducing an antibody reacting with HCV.</p><p>[0037]  This description includes the contents of the description and/or drawings of <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Japanese Patent Application No. 2008-116193</bibl> , which is a priority document of the present application.</p><p>Brief Description of the Drawings</p><p>[0038]  
Fig. 1 shows a method for preparing the pTH/JFH1 plasmid. In the pJFH1 sequence, a nucleotide sequence encoding amino acid residues 1 to 846 of the amino acid sequence of the JFH-1 Core protein when the amino acid residue at the N-terminus of the JFH-1 is designated as amino acid residue 1 is substituted with a nucleotide sequence encoding amino acid residues 1 to 843 of the amino acid sequence of the Core protein of the TH strain when the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the TH strain is designated as amino acid 1.
Fig. 2 shows changes in concentrations of the HCV Core protein in the culture supernatant assayed during each passage in repetitive subcultures conducted after introducing RNA synthesized from pTH/JFH1 into the Huh-7 cell. The amount of the Core protein in the culture supernatant continued to decrease until day 23, and it increased thereafter and maintained a constantly high level after day 34.
Fig. 3A shows a method for preparing the pTH/JFH1(PA) plasmid.
Fig. 3B shows a method for preparing the pTH/JFH1(PT) plasmid.
Fig. 4 shows changes in concentrations of the HCV Core protein in the culture supernatant assayed during each passage in repetitive subcultures conducted after introducing RNAs synthesized from pTH/JFH1, pTH/JFH1(PA) and pTH/JFH1(PT) into the Huh-7 cells. As with the case shown in Fig. 2, the Core protein amount of TH/JFH-1 continued to decrease until 29 days after introduction but it increased thereafter. In the case of the cells into which TH/JFH-1(PA) and TH/JFH-1(PT) had been introduced, however, a large quantity of Core protein was observed in the culture supernatant from the initial stage after the introduction, and the quantities of both core proteins were maintained at higher levels than that of TH/JFH-1.
Fig. 5A shows changes in concentrations of the HCV Core protein in the culture supernatant until 96 hours had passed since RNAs synthesized from pTH/JFH1 and pTH/JFH1(PA) had been introduced into the Huh-7 cells. The amount of Core protein produced in the culture supernatant of TH/JFH-1(PA) became greater 48 hours after RNA introduction and later, than that of TH/JFH-1.
Fig. 5B shows the infectious titer attained when uninfected Huh-7 cells are inoculated with the culture supernatants obtained in Fig. 5A. The infectious titer in the culture supernatant of TH/JFH-1(PA) became greater 48 hours after RNA introduction and later, than that of TH/JFH-1.The table shown in Fig. 6 shows the results of quantification of concentrations of HCV Core protein in the culture supernatants obtained by the experiments shown in Fig. 5, the infectious titers for the Huh-7 cells, and concentrations of HCV Core protein in the cells. The proportion of Core protein after 96 hours relative to that of Core proteins in the cells after 4 hours represents the degree of autonomous replication of RNAs of TH/JFH-1 and of TH/JFH-1(PA) in the cells. The efficiency of HCV Core secretion serves as an indicator of the efficiency of HCV particle secretion in the culture supernatant. Such efficiency was calculated by dividing the amount of Core protein in the culture supernatant after 96 hours by the sum of the amount of Core protein in the culture supernatant after 96 hours and the amount of Core protein in the cell after 96 hours. The efficiency of HCV particle secretion in the culture supernatant in the cells into which RNA of TH/JFH-1(PA) had been introduced was higher than that of TH/JFH-1.</p><p>Best Modes for Carrying out the Invention</p><p>[0039]  In general, the nucleic acid of the present invention comprises a chimeric gene of HCV comprising a nucleotide sequence encoding non-structural proteins of the JFH-1 strain and a nucleotide sequence encoding structural proteins of an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain. In addition, the nucleic acid of the present invention comprises a nucleotide sequence encoding the E1 protein having a given amino acid mutation.</p><p>[0040]  Specifically, the nucleic acid of the present invention comprises: 
(1) a chimeric gene derived from the hepatitis C viruses comprising regions each encoding the Core protein, the E1 protein, the E2 protein and the p7 protein derived from a hepatitis C virus strain other than the JFH-1 strain, the NS2 protein derived from the JFH-1 strain or a hepatitis C virus strain other than the JFH-1 strain, or the chimeric NS2 protein of the NS2 protein derived from the JFH-1 strain and the NS2 protein derived from a hepatitis C virus strain other than the JFH-1 strain, and the NS3 protein, the NS4A protein, the NS4B protein, the NS5A protein, and the NS5B protein derived from the JFH-1 strain in that order in the 5' to 3' direction; and
(2) a nucleotide sequence encoding a combined protein (i.e., a precursor protein) in which the amino acid residue 328 when an amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein; i.e., a methionine residue, is designated as amino acid residue 1 (or amino acid residue 137 when the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the E1 protein is designated as amino acid residue 1); i.e., the proline residue is substituted with an amino acid residue other than proline.</p><p>[0041]  The NS2 protein of the nucleic acid of the present invention may be derived from the JFH-1 strain, it may be derived from an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain, and it may be a chimeric protein comprising part of the NS2 protein derived from an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain and remaining part of the NS2 protein derived from the JFH-1 strain. In such a case, such chimeric protein has functions similar to those of the wild-type NS2 protein. When part of the NS2 protein derived from an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain is composed of an amino acid sequence from the N-terminus to amino acid 33 of the NS2 protein, for example, the remaining part of the NS2 protein derived from the JFH-1 strain consists of an amino acid sequence from amino acid 34 to the C terminus.</p><p>[0042]  Examples of the chimeric gene derived from hepatitis C viruses include DNA consisting of nucleotides 341 to 9433 of SEQ ID NO: 1 or 2 of the sequence listing and RNA consisting of nucleotides 341 to 9433 of SEQ ID NO: 3 or 4 of the sequence listing.</p><p>[0043]  According to an embodiment of the present invention, the nucleic acid of the present invention can further comprise the 5'-untranslated region of the JFH-1 strain on the 5' side of the Core protein coding region and the 3'-untranslated region of the JFH-1 strain on the 3' side of the NS5B protein coding region.</p><p>[0044]  According to an embodiment of the present invention, the HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain is of genotype 1a, 1b, or 2a. Examples of strains of genotype 1b include the TH strain, the Con1 strain, the J1 strain and derivative strains thereof. An example of a strain of genotype 1 a is the H77 strain. An example of a strain of genotype 2a is the J6CF strain. Examples of preferable strains are those of genotype 1b as exemplified above. The TH strain or a derivative strain thereof is more preferable. In the present invention, the 328th amino acid residue from the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein derived from the exemplified strain must be mutated into an amino acid residue other than proline.</p><p>[0045]  According to another embodiment of the present invention, the amino acid residue other than proline is, for example, Ala, Leu, Ile, Val, Thr, or Ser, and it is preferably Ala or Thr.</p><p>[0046]  According to an embodiment of the present invention, the nucleic acid is DNA comprising the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 1 or RNA comprising the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 3. According to another embodiment, the nucleic acid is DNA comprising the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 2 or RNA comprising the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 4. Such nucleic acids are chimeric nucleic acids derived from the JFH-1 strain and the TH strain. The nucleic acid as shown in SEQ ID NO: 1 or 3 has a nucleotide sequence identical to that of the nucleic acid as shown in SEQ ID NO: 2 or 4, except that the former sequence comprises a codon (nucleotides 1322 to 1324) encoding Ala as the 328th amino acid residue from the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein while the nucleic acid as shown in SEQ ID NO: 2 or 4 comprises a codon (nucleotides 1322 to 1324) encoding Thr as the 328th amino acid residue from the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein.</p><p>[0047]  Further, the amino acid sequence encoded by the nucleotide sequence corresponding to ORF of DNA as shown in SEQ ID NO: 1 (i.e., the sequence from the N terminus of Core to the C terminus of NS5B) is shown in SEQ ID NO: 6. The amino acid sequence encoded by the nucleotide sequence corresponding to ORF of DNA as shown in SEQ ID NO: 2 (i.e., the sequence from the N terminus of Core to the C terminus of NS5B) is shown in SEQ ID NO: 7.</p><p>[0048]  The nucleotide sequence of the present invention may comprise a nucleotide sequence having 90% or more, preferably 95% or more, and more preferably 98% to 99% or more identity to the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 1, 2, 3, or 4. In such a case, the 1,322nd to 1,324th residues from the 5' terminus of the nucleotide sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 1, 2, 3, or 4 encode amino acid residues other than proline (see above).</p><p>[0049]  The amino acid sequence of the present invention may comprise an amino acid sequence having 90% or more, preferably 95% or more, and more preferably 98% to 99% or more identity to the amino acid sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 5 or 6. In such a case, the 328th residue from the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein encodes an amino acid residue other than proline (see above).</p><p>[0050]  This is because, as several genotypes of HCV, which is an RNA virus, are known, the structural region, the non-structural region, and/or the (5'- or 3'-) untranslated region of HCV are likely to undergo mutation.</p><p>[0051]  In the present invention, the term "the 328th amino acid residue from the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein" used above refers to an amino acid residue that is aligned at the same position as that of the 328th amino acid residue of the sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 5, 6, or 7 in the amino acid sequence comprising a region from the N terminus of HCV Core to the C terminus of NS5B that is aligned with the amino acid sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 5, 6, or 7 of the sequence listing (i.e., the sequence from the N terminus of Core to the C terminus of NS5B). Also, the condition in which "the 328th amino acid residue from the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein derived from the exemplified strain is substituted with an amino acid residue other than proline" is a condition in which an amino acid residue in a given amino acid sequence that is aligned at the same position as that of the 328th amino acid residue of the sequence as shown in SEQ ID NO: 5 is an amino acid residue other than proline.</p><p>[0052]  The term "% identity" used with reference to two sequences herein refers to a function of the number of positions that two nucleotide or amino acid sequences share, and it refers to a percentage of the number of matched positions relative to the total number of positions when two sequences are aligned with or without the introduction of a gap. % identity can be determined with the use of mathematical algorithms, such as BLASTN, BLASTX, or Gapped BLAST (e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Karlin and Altschul, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A., 90: 5873-5877, 1993</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Altschul et al., Nucleic Acids Res., 25: 3389-3402, 1997</bibl> ).</p><p>[0053]  The present invention provides a vector or a chimeric HCV particle comprising the above nucleic acid. Such chimeric HCV particle can be produced with higher efficiency in a cell culture system, compared with a wild-type particle, and it has higher infectivity. Advantages such as high-efficiency production or high infectivity result from mutation of the 328th amino acid residue from the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein with an amino acid residue other than Pro (preferably Ala or Thr), which are apparent from the results shown in Figs. 4 and 5.</p><p>[0054]  The nucleic acid, the vector, and the chimeric HCV particle of the present invention can be prepared via conventional molecular biological, virological, or other techniques within the scope of the technology of the relevant field. Such techniques are described in academic documents, patent documents, specialized books, and the like. Examples of such documents include <bibl type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Sambrook et al., Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual (vol. 3, 2001, CSHL PRESS )</bibl>, <bibl type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Mahy et al., Virology: a practical approach (1985, IRL PRESS )</bibl>, <bibl type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Ausubel et al., Current Protocols in Molecular Biology (vol. 3, 1995, John Wiley &amp; Sons )</bibl>, and <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">US Patent No. 4,683,202</bibl> (Cetus Corporation; PCR).</p><p>[0055]  In order to produce the nucleic acid or infectious HCV particles of the present invention, a polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is carried out with the use of a vector prepared via cloning of cDNA of genome RNA derived from the JFH-1 strain or an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain as a template and the forward and the reverse primers designed based on the sequence of the cDNA, so that the target sequence portion can be amplified. As shown in Fig. 1 or 3, specifically, a plurality of different PCR products having overlapping sequences are synthesized, such PCR products are mixed, the resultant is used as a template, and PCR is carried out using a forward primer comprising the 5' end of the target nucleic acid and a reverse primer comprising the 5' end of a complementary strand of such nucleic acid, so that the target nucleic acid can be amplified. The ends of the synthesized nucleic acids are cleaved with restriction enzymes and ligated to the pJFH1 plasmid that was cleaved with the same enzyme ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wakita, T. et al., Nat. Med., 11: 791-796, 2005</bibl> ; <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 2004/104198</bibl> ). The basic technique of such procedure is also described in, for example, <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 04104198 A1</bibl> , <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 06022422 A1</bibl> , <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wakita, T. et al., Nat. Med., 11: 791-796, 2005</bibl> , and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Lindenbach, B. D. et al., Science, 309: 623-626, 2005</bibl> .</p><p>[0056]  PCR is carried out in the presence of a template, primers, dNTPs, heat-resistant polymerase, and Mg&lt;2+&gt;-containing buffer, and a step of 94[deg.]C to 98[deg.]C for about 10 to 60 seconds, 55[deg.]C to 58[deg.]C for about 10 to 60 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for about 30 to 60 seconds is repeated 20 to 40 times, although PCR conditions are not limited thereto.</p><p>[0057]  In general, the HCV genome is RNA comprising the 5'-untranslated region, the Core protein coding region, the E1 protein coding region, the E2 protein coding region, the p7 protein coding region, the NS2 protein coding region, the NS3 protein coding region, the NS4A protein coding region, the NS4B protein coding region, the NS5A protein coding region, the NS5B protein coding region, and the 3'-untranslated region. In contrast, the nucleic acid of the present invention capable of producing infectious HCV particles is composed of virus genome RNA of two or more types of HCV strains or DNA encoding such RNA.</p><p>[0058]  The nucleic acid of the present invention comprises, for example, the 5'-untranslated region, the region encoding part of the NS2 protein, the NS3 protein coding region, the NS4A protein coding region, the NS4B protein coding region, the NS5A protein coding region, the NS5B protein coding region, and the 3'-untranslated region, which are derived from the JFH-1 strain, and the Core protein coding region, the E1 protein coding region, the E2 protein coding region, the p7 protein coding region, and the region encoding remaining part of the NS2 protein, which are derived from an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain. The 5' untranslated region may be derived from an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain.</p><p>[0059]  According to another embodiment of the present invention, the chimeric nucleic acid of the present invention comprises the 5'-untranslated region, the Core protein coding region, the E1 protein coding region, the E2 protein coding region, the p7 protein coding region and the NS2 protein coding region, which are derived from an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain and the NS3 protein coding region, the NS4A protein coding region, the NS4B protein coding region, the NS5A protein coding region, the NS5B protein coding region and the 3'-untranslated region, which are derived from the JFH-1 strain.</p><p>[0060]  According to another embodiment of the present invention, the nucleic acid of the present invention comprises the 5'-untranslated region derived from the JFH-1 strain; the Core protein coding region, the E1 protein coding region, the E2 protein coding region, the p7 protein coding region and the region encoding part of the NS2 protein derived from the TH strain; and the region encoding another part of the NS2 protein, NS3 protein coding region, the NS4A protein coding region, the NS4B protein coding region, the NS5A protein coding region, the NS5B protein coding region, and the 3'-untranslated region derived from the JFH-1 strain. As long as the Core protein coding region, the E1 protein coding region, the E2 protein coding region, and the p7 protein coding region are derived from the TH strain, however, the chimeric nucleic acid is not limited thereto.</p><p>[0061]  Hereafter, use of the vector, the infectious HCV particles, HCV particle-producing cells, and HCV particles of the present invention are described in greater detail.</p><p>(1) Vector preparation</p><p>[0062]  The hepatitis C virus (HCV) genome is a single-stranded (+) RNA comprising approximately 9,600 nucleotides. This genomic RNA comprises a 5'-untranslated region (also referred to as "5' NTR" or "5' UTR"), a translational region composed of structural regions and non-structural regions, and a 3'-untranslated region (also referred to as "3' NTR" or "3' UTR"). In the structural regions, HCV structural proteins are encoded and, in the non-structural regions, a plurality of non-structural proteins are encoded.</p><p>[0063]  Such HCV structural proteins (Core, E1, E2 and p7) and non-structural proteins (NS2, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A and NS5B) are first translated as a continuous polyprotein (i.e., precursor protein) from the translational region, subjected to limited degradation by protease in infected cells, and released and produced. Among such structural and non-structural proteins (i.e., HCV virus proteins), Core is a core protein, and E1 and E2 are envelope proteins. It is known that non-structural proteins are associated with replication of the virus itself, NS2 has metalloprotease activity, and NS3 has serine protease activity (one-third of the N-terminal side) and helicase activity (two-thirds of the C-terminal side). Further, it is reported that NS4A is a cofactor for protease activity of NS3, and NS5B has RNA-dependent RNA polymerase activity.</p><p>[0064]  HCV is coated with a coat referred to as an envelope. The envelope comprises a component derived from the membrane of a host cell and proteins derived from the virus. The proteins that constitute the HCV envelope comprise envelope protein 1 (referred to as "E1"), envelope protein 2 (referred to as "E2") and p7. In particular, E1 and E2 each have a transmembrane region at the C terminus, and E1 and E2 are anchored to the HCV membrane through such transmembrane region. Thus, the E1 and the E2 proteins of HCV are exposed to the outside, and HCV adheres to and infects cells via E1 and/or E2.</p><p>[0065]  According to phylogenetic analysis using nucleotide sequences of the HCV strain, HCV is classified into 6 types (i.e., genotypes 1 to 6) and such genotypes are further classified into several subtypes. In addition, the nucleotide sequences of the full-length genomes of a plurality of HCV genotypes are determined ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Simmonds, P. et al., Hepatology, 10: 1321-1324, 1994</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Choo, Q. L. et al., Science, 244: 359-362, 1989</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Okamoto, H. et al., J. Gen. Virol., 73: 673-679, 1992</bibl> ; and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Mori, S. et al., Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 183: 334-342, 1992</bibl> ). Specific examples of known strains are as follows: the HCV strain of genotype 1a (e.g., the H77 strain (GenBank Accession No. AF011751)); the HCV strains of genotype 1b (e.g., the J1 strain (GenBank Accession No. D89815), the Con1 strain (GenBank Accession No. AJ238799; it may be referred to as the Con-1 or con1 strain), and the TH strain ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wakita, T. et al., J. Biol. Chem., 269, 14205-14210, 1994</bibl> , <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">JP Patent Publication (kokai) No. 2004-179 A</bibl> )); and the HCV strains of genotype 2a (e.g., the JFH-1 strain (GenBank Accession No. AB047639); it may be referred to as the JFHI strain), the J6CF strain (GenBank Accession No. AF177036), the JCH-1 strain (GenBank Accession No. AB047640), the JCH-2 strain (GenBank Accession No. AB047641), the JCH-3 strain (GenBank Accession No. AB047642), the JCH-4 strain (GenBank Accession No. AB047643), the JCH-5 strain (GenBank Accession No. AB047644), and the JCH-6 strain (GenBank Accession No. AB047645)). In addition, the HC-J8 strain (GenBank Accession No. D01221) is known as the HCV strain of genotype 2b, the NZL1 strain (GenBank Accession No. D17763) and the S52 strain (GenBank Accession No. ) are known as the HCV strains of genotype 3a, the Tr-Kj strain (GenBank Accession No. D49374) is known as the HCV strain of genotype 3b, and the ED43 strain (GenBank Accession No. ) is known as the HCV strain of genotype 4a, for example. The list of the GenBank Accession numbers of other strains has already been reported ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Tokita, T. et al., J. Gen. Virol., 79: 1847-1857, 1998</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Cristina, J. &amp; Colina, R., Virol. J., 3:1-8, 2006</bibl> ).</p><p>[0066]  The genomic nucleotide sequences of the JFH-1 strain and HCV strains other than the JFH-1 strain of the present invention are available from the above documents or GenBank, HCV strains other than the JFH-1 strain of the aforementioned genotypes may be selected, and a strain of genotype 1a, 1b, or 2a is preferable.</p><p>[0067]  The chimeric HCV gene can be prepared by performing PCR using the vector prepared via cloning of cDNA of HCV genome RNA as a template and synthesized DNA as a primer, amplifying necessary regions of the HCV genes, and ligating the resultants.</p><p>[0068]  Further, cDNA of the chimeric HCV gene is ligated to an adequate restriction site located downstream of a promoter (e.g., the T7 promoter) of the pJFH1 plasmid ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wakita, T. et al., Nat. Med., 11:791-796, 2005</bibl> , <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 2004/104198</bibl> ) to prepare a vector used for synthesizing HCV genome RNA. Upon introduction of RNA transcribed from such vector into a cell such as the Huh-7 cell, virus replication and packaging take place, and infectious HCV particles can then be produced.</p><p>(2) HCV particle preparation</p><p>[0069]  RNA may be synthesized from HCV cDNA cloned under the control of a promoter, and the resulting RNA may be intoduced into a cell to prepare a chimeric HCV particle.</p><p>[0070]  Specifically, chimeric HCV particles can be prepared by a method comprising a step of culturing a cell that produces such HCV particles and a step of recovering such HCV particles. The cell that produces HCV particles can be obtained by infecting an HCV-sensitive cell (i.e., a cell capable of producing HCV particles) with the chimeric HCV particles of the present invention.</p><p>[0071]  Examples of the promoter include, but are not limited to, T7 promoter, SP6 promoter, and T3 promoter, with T7 promoter being preferable.</p><p>[0072]  A method for preparing the RNA in vitro using, as a template, a nucleic acid into which HCV cDNA has been cloned under the control of T7 promoter can be carried out with the use of, for example, the MEGAscript T7 kit (Ambion). </p><p>[0073]  Cells into which RNA is introduced may be any cells that are capable of producing HCV particles, and examples include Huh-7, HepG2, IMY-N9, HeLa, 293 and 293T cells or cells derived from any thereof. Examples of preferable cells include Huh-7 cells or Huh7.5 cells derived therefrom and Huh7.5.1 cells. In addition, cells which express CD81 and/or Claudin1 genes in Huh-7, HepG2, IMY-N9, HeLa, 293, or 293T cells may also be used ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Lindenbach, B. D. et al., Science, 309: 623-626, 2005</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Evans, M. J. et al., Nature, 446: 801-805, 2007</bibl> ; and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Akazawa, D. et al., J. Virol., 81: 5036-5045, 2007</bibl> ).</p><p>[0074]  Examples of methods for introducing RNA into cells include calcium phosphate coprecipitation, a DEAE-dextran method, lipofection, microinjection, and electroporation. Lipofection and electroporation are preferable, and electroporation is more preferable.</p><p>[0075]  When cDNA is introduced into cells, HCV cDNA may be expressed in a system involving the use of an RNA polymerase I promoter and a terminator ( <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 27037428 A1</bibl> ).</p><p>[0076]  The capacity of the cells for virus particle production can be detected with the use of antibodies to proteins that constitute an HCV particle released in culture solution, such as a Core protein, an E1 protein and an E2 protein. Also, HCV genome RNA contained in the HCV virus particles in a culture medium may be amplified via RT-PCR using specific primers to detect the HCV genome RNA of interest, so that the presence of HCV virus particles can be indirectly detected.</p><p>[0077]  Whether or not the prepared viruses are infectious can be evaluated by culturing cells into which HCV RNA has been introduced, bringing the resulting supernatant into contact with HCV permissive cells (e.g., Huh-7 cells or derivative strains thereof), and immunologically staining the cells with an anti-Core antibody, for example, after 48 hours to count the number of infected cells. Alternatively, the evaluation can be carried out by subjecting a cell extract to electrophoresis on SDS-polyacrylamide gel and detecting core proteins via Western blotting. </p><p>(3) Acquisition of particle-producing cell line</p><p>[0078]  For efficient replication of the HCV genome, it is necessary that a mutation occur in the nucleotide sequence of the genome ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Lohmann, V. et al., J. Virol. 75: 1437-1449, 2001</bibl> ). A mutation that enhances replication is referred to as an "adaptive mutation." The cells into which the HCV genome RNA has been introduced as prepared in (2) above may be subjected to subculture to obtain cell lines that continuously produce HCV particles. By continuing such culture, an adaptive mutation may occasionally take place in the HCV genome, and the production of HCV particles may be significantly enhanced.</p><p>[0079]  A typical example of the use of such phenomenon is a technique in which genomic RNA of the chimeric HCV is introduced into a cell and a mutant exhibiting the improved ability to produce the virus is selected. An example of such mutation is permissive mutation of chimeric HCV particles of the H77 strain and the JFH-1 strain ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">MinKyung Y. et al., J Virol., 81: 629-638, 2007</bibl> ). Permissive mutation randomly takes place depending on the virus strain, design of the chimeric HCV genome (the construct), and conditions of experimentation. Accordingly, such mutation is not necessarily applicable to genotype 1b. This necessitates the performance of an experiment for each construct of interest to obtain permissive mutants.</p><p>[0080]  A mutation of a single amino acid residue significantly changes the replication capacity of HCV and the ability to produce the HCV particle. Mutations vary depending on the HCV genotype, the type of cell used for culture, and the experiment. Since nucleic acid mutation that is necessary for a mutation of a single amino acid residue cannot be detected via hybridization, the HCV gene sequence must be subjected to sequencing in order to detect such mutation.</p><p>[0081]  Thus, an HCV genome sequence that is capable of producing a large quantity of HCV particles can be found by isolating HCV genome RNA from such cells and determining the nucleotide sequence. </p><p>[0082]  In order to inspect whether or not such mutation is associated with the capacity for HCV replication or ability to produce the HCV particle, further, it is necessary to introduce a mutation into the original HCV genome and inspect whether or not the capacity for HCV replication or ability to produce the HCV particle is reproduced. In order to introduce a mutation into the original HCV genome, PCR may be carried out, or a commercially available mutagenesis kit (e.g., KOD -Plus- Mutagenesis Kit, Toyobo Co., Ltd.) may be used.</p><p>[0083]  In addition, whether or not such mutation is specific for the HCV genome used or is effective for other HCV genomes can also be confirmed by reintroducing a mutation into an HCV genome that has not experienced mutation.</p><p>[0084]  In the present invention, when the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein of the TH/JFH-1 strain (Example 1 below) was designated as amino acid residue 1, a mutation from proline residue, the 328th amino acid residue (amino acid 328) (or the 137th amino acid (amino acid 137) when the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the E1 protein was designated as amino acid residue 1) into alanine or threonine is found. The 328th amino acid residue from the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein is the same in the Con1 strain (GenBank Accession No. AJ238799) and the J1 strain (GenBank Accession No. D89815) of genotype 1b, the H77 strain of genotype 1a ((GenBank Accession No. AF011751), the JFH-1 strain of genotype 2a (GenBank Accession No. AB047639), and the J6CF strain (GenBank Accession No. AF177036), in addition to the TH strain. It is suggested that a mutation of proline into another amino acid, and preferably a mutation thereof into alanine or threonine, would be effective for any HCV strain having proline as the 328th amino acid residue from the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein, in addition to the TH strain.</p><p>(4) Use of HCV particles</p><p>[0085]  HCV particles are preferable for applications as vaccines and antigens used for preparing anti-HCV antibodies. </p><p>[0086]  Specifically, HCV particles can be used as vaccines without modification, but HCV particles can be attenuated or inactivated via a method known in the art. The virus can be inactivated by adding and mixing an inactivator such as formalin, ([beta]-propiolactone, or glutardialdehyde in, for example, a virus suspension and allowing the inactivator to react with the virus ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Appaiahgari, M. B. &amp; Vrati, S., Vaccine, 22: 3669-3675, 2004</bibl> ). Attenuated vaccines can be obtained by infecting cultured animal cells or animals (excluding humans) with chimeric HCV particles and repeating subculture to attenuate the pathogenicity. Alternatively, pathogenicity can be attenuated by negatively modifying a region associated with HCV proliferation or infection, for example, the Core-NS5B region, via genetic engineering.</p><p>[0087]  Thus, the HCV vaccine of the present invention can be produced by a method comprising a step of inactivating or attenuating the chimeric HCV particles of the present invention to prepare the inactivated or attenuated chimeric HCV particles and a step of preparing the inactivated or attenuated chimeric HCV particles into the form of HCV vaccines.</p><p>[0088]  The vaccine of the present invention can be formulated into a dosage form of, for example, a solution or suspension. The vaccine can be prepared in a solid state (e.g., a lyophilized preparation) that is suitable for dissolution or suspension it in a solution, so that the vaccine can be reconstituted immediately before use. Alternatively, such solid or preparation can be emulsified in the presence of a pharmaceutical surfactant or encapsulated in liposomes.</p><p>[0089]  Active immunogenic ingredients, such as HCV particles, are often mixed with excipients that are pharmaceutically acceptable and compatible with the active ingredients. Examples of adequate excipients include water, physiological saline, dextrose, glycerol, ethanol, and mixtures thereof.</p><p>[0090]  Further, the vaccine can contain a minor amount of an auxiliary agent (e.g., a humidifier or emulsifier), a pH buffer, and/or an adjuvant that enhances vaccine efficacy, where needed.</p><p>[0091]  Examples of the effective adjuvant include, but are not limited to, aluminum hydroxide, N-acetyl-muramyl-L-threonyl-D-isoglutamine (thr-MDP), N-acetyl-nor-muramyl-L-alanyl-D-isoglutamine (referred to as CGP11637 or nor-MDP), N-acetylmuramyl-L-alanyl-D-isoglutaminyl-L-alanine-2-(1'-2'-dipalmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-hydr oxyphosphoryloxy)-ethylamine (referred to as CGP19835A or MTP-PE), and RIBI. RIBI contains three components extracted from bacteria; i.e. monophosphoryl lipid A, trehalose dimycolate, and a cell wall skeleton (HPL+TDM+CWS), in 2% squalene/Tween&lt;(R)&gt; 80 emulsion.</p><p>[0092]  Efficacy of an adjuvant can be determined by assaying the amount of antibodies resulting from administration of a vaccine comprising HCV particles to a mammalian animal.</p><p>[0093]  The vaccine of the present invention is generally administered parenterally, by injection such as subcutaneous injection or intramuscular injection, for example. Examples of other formulations that are suitable as other forms of dosage include suppositories and, optionally, oral preparations.</p><p>[0094]  Optionally, one or more compounds having adjuvant activity can be added to the HCV vaccine. An adjuvant is a non-specific stimulant to the immune system. Such substance enhances the immune response of a host against HCV vaccines. Specific examples of adjuvants that are known in the art include Freund's complete and incomplete adjuvants, vitamin E, a nonionic block copolymer, muramyl dipeptide, saponin, mineral oil, vegetable oil, and Carbopol. Examples of adjuvants that are particularly suitable for mucosal application include E. coli thermolabile toxin (LT) and Cholera toxin (CT). Examples of other adequate adjuvants include aluminum hydroxide, aluminum phosphate or aluminum oxide, an oil emulsion (e.g., Bayol&lt;(R)&gt; or Marcol 52&lt;(R)&gt;), saponin, and a vitamin E solubilizate. Accordingly, the vaccine of a preferable embodiment of the present invention comprises an adjuvant.</p><p>[0095]  Concerning an injectable solution for subcutaneous, intracutaneous, intramuscular, or intravenous administration, other specific examples of a pharamaceutically acceptable carrier or diluent that is used for administration in combination with the HCV vaccine of the present invention in the injectable solution include a stabilizer, a carbohydrate (e.g., sorbitol, mannitol, starch, sucrose, glucose, or dextran), a protein (e.g., albumin or casein), a protein-containing substance (e.g., bovine serum or skimmed milk), and buffer (e.g., phosphate buffer).</p><p>[0096]  Examples of conventional binders and carriers that are used for suppositories include polyalkylene glycol and triglyceride. Such suppositories can be prepared from a mixture comprising 0.5% to 50%, and preferably 1% to 20% active ingredients by weight. Oral preparations comprise excipients that are generally used. Examples of excipients include mannitol, lactose, starch, magnesium stearate, saccharin sodium, cellulose, and magnesium carbonate of pharmaceutical grade.</p><p>[0097]  The vaccine of the present invention can be in the form of a solution, suspension, tablet, pill, capsule, sustained-release preparation, or powder, and its active ingredients (virus particles or part thereof) account for 10% to 95%, and preferably 25% to 70% thereof by weight.</p><p>[0098]  The vaccine of the present invention is administered in a manner suitable for a dosage form and in an amount that can exert preventive and/or therapeutic effects. The amount to be administered is generally 0.01 [micro]g to 100,000 [micro]g antigen per dose. Such amount varies depending on the patient to be treated, the capacity of the patient for antibody synthesis in the immune system, and the desired degree of protection. Also, the amount varies depending on the route of administration, such as oral, subcutaeous, intracutaneous, intramuscular, or intravenous administration.</p><p>[0099]  The vaccine of the present invention can be administered according to a single-administration schedule, and preferably according to a multiple-administration schedule. In the case of a multiple-administration schedule, 1 to 10 separate administrations are performed at the time of initiation of inoculation, and another administration can then be performed with a time interval that is necessary for maintaining and/or enhancing the immune response. For example, the second administration can be performed 1 to 4 months after the first. Where needed, administration may be subsequently performed several months after the first. The administration regimen is, at least partially, determined according to the needs of individual, and the regimen depends on the judgment made by a doctor.</p><p>[0100]  Further, the vaccine comprising the HCV particles of the present invention may be administered with another immunosuppressant agent (e.g., immunoglobulin).</p><p>[0101]  Further, the present invention provides a method in which the vaccine comprising the HCV particles of the present invention is administered to a healthy individual to induce an immune response to HCV in such healthy individual, and the vaccine is used for preventing new HCV infection. The present invention also provides a method in which the vaccine comprising the HCV particles of the present invention is administered to a patient infected with HCV to induce a potent immune response to HCV in vivo, and the vaccine is thus used as a therapeutic vaccine that eliminates HCV.</p><p>[0102]  The HCV particles of the present invention are also useful as antigens used for preparing antibodies. The antibodies that recognize the HCV particles of the present invention used as antigens can be used for preventing or treating HCV infection as passive immunotherapeutic agents. Any antibodies can be used without limitation, and examples thereof include polyclonal antibodies, monoclonal antibodies, human antibodies, humanized antibodies, chimeric antibodies, fragments of any thereof (e.g., Fc, Fab and (Fab')2), single-stranded antibodies (e.g., scFv), camel antibodies, and polyvalent antibodies (e.g., divalent and trivalent antibodies). Any antibodies can be used, and examples include IgG, IgE, IgM, IgD, IgA and IgY antibodies. Examples of the classes thereof include IgG1 to IgG4 and IgAl to IgA2. Further, antibodies may involve chemical modification, such as glycosylation, PEG-modification, acetylation, phosphorylation, or amidation.</p><p>[0103]  The anti-HCV antibodies can be prepared by a method comprising a step of administering the chimeric HCV particles, which are or are not inactivated or attenuated, of the present invention to animals (excluding humans), and preferably to mammalians or birds.</p><p>[0104]  Examples of mammalians include mice, rats, rabbits, goats, sheep, horses, cattle, guinea pigs, dromedaries, Bactrian camels, and lamas. Dromedaries, Bactrian camels, and lamas are suitable for preparing an antibody consisting of the H chain. Examples of birds include chickens, geese and ostriches.</p><p>[0105]  The blood serum may be taken from an animal to which the HCV particles of the present invention have been administered, in order to obtain antibodies of interest by well-known methods. Examples of such methods include ammonium sulfate fractionation, ion exchange chromatography, Protein A or Protein G-binding affinity chromatography, and gel filtration chromatography.</p><p>[0106]  In addition, hybridomas that produce monoclonal antibody-producing cells can be prepared with the use of cells or tissue (e.g., B cells, spleen cells and lymph nodes) of the animals immunized with the HCV particles of the present invention and myeloma cells (e.g., myeloma cells derived from mice or rats). Methods for producing hybridomas are well-known in the art, and the method described in, for example, <bibl type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Antibodies: A Laboratory Manual (Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, 1988 )</bibl> or <bibl type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Tan Kuron Kotai Jikken Manual (Manual of Monoclonal Antibody Experiments), Toyama and Ando (ed.), Kodansha Ltd., 1987</bibl> ) can be employed.</p><p>[0107]  Monoclonal antibody-producing cells may be prepared via cell fusion or via other methods involving introduction of DNA of a cancer gene or infection with Epstein-Barr for immotalization of B lymphocytes. </p><p>[0108]   Humanized antibodies and human antibodies can be prepared via phage display (e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Brinkman et al., J. Immunol. Methods, 182: 41-50, 1995</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Ames et al., J. Immunol. Methods, 184: 177-186, 1995</bibl> ; <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 98/46645</bibl> ; <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 98/50433</bibl> ; and <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 98/24893</bibl> ) or with the use of human antibody-producing mice (e.g., KM mice (Kirin Pharma Co., Ltd.) or Xeno mice (Abgenix/Amgen)).</p><p>[0109]  The monoclonal, polyclonal, human, or humanized antibodies obtained by such techniques are useful for diagnosis, therapy, and prevention of HCV.</p><p>[0110]  The antibodies prepared with the use of the HCV particles of the present invention are administered with pharmaceutically acceptable solubilizers, additives, stabilizers, buffers, or the like. Such antibodies may be administered via any route. Subcutaneous, intracutaneous, or intramuscular administration is preferable, and intravenous administration is more preferable.</p><p>[0111]  A preferable example of an antiody prepared with the use of the HCV particles of the present invention is an anti-hepatitis C virus antiody that recognizes the chimeric hepatitis C virus (HCV) particles of the present invention (i.e., the chimeric HCV particles comprising the nucleic acid of the present invention as the virus genome) as antigens. Such anti-hepatitis C virus antibodies can be prepared so as to react with the chimeric HCV particles of the present invention. Such anti-hepatitis C virus antibodies can bind to (react with) not only the chimeric HCV particles of the present invention, but they can also bind to (react with) a wide variety of other hepatitis C virus particles to inhibit the functions thereof, regardless of the process for producing the same.</p><p>[0112]  In addition, the HCV particles of the present invention (i.e., the chimeric HCV particles) or cells that produce such particles can be used for screening for anti-HCV substances.</p><p>[0113]  Specifically, this method for screening for an anti-hepatitis C virus substance comprises culturing, in the presence of a test substance: 
(a) the cell that produces chimeric HCV particles; or
(b) the chimeric HCV particle and hepatitis C virus-sensitive cell, and detecting replicon RNA or a virus particle derived from the above-mentioned nucleic acid contained in the chimeric HCV particles of the present invention in the culture product.</p><p>[0114]  According to the above method, anti-HCV substances are selected as those capable of inhibiting virus infection or proliferation. In the present invention, the term "replicon RNA" mainly refers to RNA capable of automonous replication, which is prepared via modification of the HCV virus genome. The term "capable of automonous replication" used herein refers to the capacity for automonously reproducing (i.e., replicating) a nucleic acid copy in a cell, as with plasmid DNA. An example of a known subgenome replicon RNA is recombinant RNA prepared via recombination of the translational region of the HCV structural protein with a drug-resistant gene and insertion of IRES of EMCV (encephalomyocarditis virus) into a site downstream of such recombined region. RNA replication is observed in cells into which such recombinant RNA has been introduced. The term "full-length genome replicon RNA" refers to RNA capable of automonous replication of RNA derived from the full-length HCV genome when it has been introduced into cells. A typical example is recombinant RNA prepared by inserting a drug resistant gene (or a reporter gene) and IRES into a space between the 5'-untranslated region and the gene encoding the HCV core protein of RNA derived from the full-length HCV genome. The term "replicon RNA derived from a nucleic acid" used in the above method refers to replicon RNA transcribed from such nucleic acid. Examples of hepatitis C virus-sensitive cells include, but are not limited to, cells exemplified as cells into which HCV-derived RNA is to be introduced in the section "(2) HCV particle preparation" above (e.g., Huh-7, HepG2, IMY-N9, HeLa, 293 and 293T cells or derivative cells thereof).</p><p>Examples</p><p>[0115]  Hereafter, the present invention is described in greater detail with reference to the examples, although the technical scope of the present invention is not limited thereto. In the examples below, the TH strain is exemplified as an HCV strain other than the JFH-1 strain, and strains other than the designated strain can also be prepared.</p><p>Example 1: Construction of TH/JFH-1 plasmid</p><p>[0116]  As cDNA of HCV genome RNA, cDNA of the TH/JFH-1 chimera comprising 5' UTR that is from the JFH-1 strain of genotype 2a (GenBank Accession No. AB047639, <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kato, T. et al., Gastroenterology, 125: 1808-1817, 2003</bibl> ), a region from the Core protein to the N terminal 33 amino acids of the NS2 protein that is from the TH strain of genotype 1b ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wakita, T. et al., J. Biol. Chem., 269: 14205-14210, 1994</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Moradpour, D. et al., Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun., 246: 920-924, 1998</bibl> ; and <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 2006/022422</bibl> ), and a region from the N-terminal amino acid 34 of NS2 to 3' UTR that is from the JFH-1 strain of genotype 2a, was prepared.</p><p>[0117]  SEQ ID NO: 5 shows the amino acid sequence of a protein encoded by TH/JFH-1. Fig. 1 shows a method for preparing such plasmid.</p><p>[0118]  Specifically, cDNA corresponding to the entire genome RNA region derived from the JFH-1 strain was cloned into the pUC19 plasmid, and the resulting plasmid DNA, pJFH1 ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wakita, T. et al., Nat. Med., 11: 791-796, 2005</bibl> ; <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 2004/104198</bibl> ), and pTH comprising part of the virus genome TH strain isolated from a hepatitis C patient ( <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 2006/022422</bibl> ) were used.</p><p>[0119]  pJFH1 was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 [micro]l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers -21M13 (SEQ ID NO: 8) and MS98 (SEQ ID NO: 9) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro]l of Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 45 seconds 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 1.</p><p>[0120]  Subsequently, pTH was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 [micro]l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers MS97 (SEQ ID NO: 10) and MS96 (SEQ ID NO: 11) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro]l of Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 45 seconds 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 2.</p><p>[0121]  Subsequently, pJFH1 was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 [micro]l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers MS99 (SEQ ID NO: 12) and MS89 (SEQ ID NO: 13) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro]l of Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 45 seconds 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 3.</p><p>[0122]  PCR products were purified from agarose gel and eluted with the use of 50 [micro]l of EB buffer attached to the QIAquick Gel Extraction kit (QIAGEN). DNAs of PCR product No. 1, PCR product No. 2, and PCR product No. 3 were mixed in amounts of 1 [micro]l each, the resultant was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 [micro]l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers -21M13 (SEQ ID NO: 8) and MS89 (SEQ ID NO: 13) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro]l of Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 2 minutes 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 4.</p><p>[0123]  pJFH1 and the purified PCR product No. 4 were digested with the restiction enzymes, EcoRI and SpeI, and the DNA fragments were separated via agarose gel electrophoresis, followed by purification. These two DNA fragments were mixed with Ligation high (New England Biolabs), and the two DNA fragments were ligated to each other. The vector was designated as pTH/JFH1. This pTH/JFH1 vector is a nucleotide sequence encoding a chimeric gene having the 5'-untranslated region derived from the JFH-1 strain; a region encoding the Core, E1, E2, and p7 poteins and the N-terminal 33 amino acid residues of NS2 protein derived from the TH strain; a region encoding the NS2 protein starting at amino acid residue 34 at the N-terminus and the NS3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A and NS5B proteins and the 3'-untranslated region of the JFH-1 strain.</p><p>Example 2: in vitro RNA synthesis and introduction thereof into cell</p><p>[0124]  pTH/JFH1 was cleaved with XbaI, and the resultant was then subjected to phenol/chloroform extraction and ethanol precipitation. Subsequently, the XbaI cleavage fragment was treated with Mung Bean Nuclease, and an 3' terminal extra nucleotide sequence derived from the XbaI recognition sequence was removed. Further, proteinase K treatment, phenol/chloroform extraction, and ethanol precipitation were carried out to purify the DNA fragments. The cleaved plasmids were used as templates, and the reaction was allowed to proceed at 37[deg.]C for 3 hours using the MEGAscript T7 kit (Ambion) to synthesize HCV RNA. After the reaction, the synthesized RNA was treated with DNaseI and extracted with acidic phenol, followed by purification via ethanol precipitation.</p><p>[0125]  The Huh7 cells (3 x 10&lt;6&gt; cells) and 10 [micro]g of HCV RNA were suspended in 400 [micro]l of the Cytomix solution (120 mM KCl, 0.15 mM CaCl2, 10 mM K2HPO4/KH2PO4, 25 mM Hepes, 2 mM EGTA, 5 mM MgCl2, 20 mM ATP, and 50 mM Glutathione), the suspension was transferred to a 4-mm cuvette, and electroporation was carried out using the Gene Pulser (BioRad) at 260 V and 950 [micro]F. Thereafter, the cells into which HCV RNA had been introduced were seeded on a 10 cm&lt;2&gt; dish and then subcultured. </p><p>Example 3: Production of HCV particles with cells into which TH/JFH-1 RNA had been introduced</p><p>[0126]  At the time of subculture of cells into which TH/JFH-1 RNA had been introduced, the HCV Core protein contained in the culture supernatants was quantified using the HCV antigen ELISA test kit (Ortho) to confirm the production of HCV particles. As a result, the amount of HCV Core protein in the culture supernatant continued to decrease until 23 days after the introduction with the elapse of time, such amount began to increase 26 days after the introduction, and a constantly high amount of production was observed 34 days after the introduction (Fig. 2). Thus, it was considered that TH/JFH-1 RNA did not have the high capacity for virus production when it was introduced into Huh7 cell but it would acquire a high capacity for virus production upon introduction of an adaptive mutation necessary for virus production into the virus genome.</p><p>Example 4: Analysis of HCV genome sequence in cell infected with TH/JFH-1 virus, which had undergone subculture</p><p>[0127]  In order to inspect an adaptive mutation that is necessary for the TH/JFH-1 virus to be produced in high amounts, total RNA was extracted from infected cells 34 days after RNA introduction, and the sequence of the HCV genome contained therein was analyzed.</p><p>[0128]  Total RNA was extracted using Trizol (Invitrogen) and transcribed into cDNA. This cDNA was divided into 5 DNA fragments via PCR, ligated to the pGEM-T Easy vector (Promega), and transformed into E. coli DH5a to obtain colonies. Plasmids were extracted from 10 colonies using the QIAprep Mini kit (QIAGEN), and the nucleotide sequences of the DNA fragments were confirmed.</p><p>[0129]  As a result, proline CCU (P) in the E1 region of the TH strain was found to have been substituted with alanine ACU (A) or threonine GCU (T). Proline corresponds to amino acid 328 when methionine; i.e., the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the Core protein of the TH strain ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wakita, T. et al., J. Biol. Chem., 269, 1994, pp. 14205-14210</bibl> ;<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> Moradpour et al., Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun., 246, 1998, pp. 920-924</bibl> ; and <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 2006/022422</bibl> ) was designated as amino acid residue 1 or amino acid residue 137 when the amino acid residue at the N terminus of the E1 protein was designated as amino acid residue 1.</p><p>[0130]  SEQ ID NO: 6 shows the amino acid sequence of TH/JFH-1 (PA) and SEQ ID NO: 7 shows the amino acid sequence of TH/JFH-1 (PT).</p><p>Example 5: Construction of TH/JFH-1 mutant plasmid</p><p>[0131]  A plasmid having an adaptive mutation necessary for the TH/JFH-1 virus to be produced in high amounts described in Example 4 was constructed. Fig. 3 shows a method for preparing a plasmid.</p><p>[0132]  Specifically, pTH/JFH1 was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 [micro]l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers MS 151 (SEQ ID NO: 14) and MS 165 (SEQ ID NO: 15) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro]l of Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 1 minute 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 5.</p><p>[0133]  Subsequently, pTH/JFH1 was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 [micro]l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers MS 164 (SEQ ID NO: 16) and MS156 (SEQ ID NO: 17) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro]l of Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 1 minute 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 6. </p><p>[0134]   PCR products were purified from agarose gel and eluted with the use of 50 [micro]l of EB buffer attached to the QIAquick Gel Extraction kit (QIAGEN). DNAs of PCR product No. 5 and PCR product No. 6 were mixed in amounts of 1 [micro]l each, the resultant was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers MS 151 (SEQ ID NO: 14) and MS 156 (SEQ ID NO: 17) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro]l of Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 1 minute and 30 seconds 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 7 (Fig. 3A).</p><p>[0135]  Subsequently, pTH/JFH1 was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 [micro]l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers MS151 (SEQ ID NO: 14) and MS163 (SEQ ID NO: 18) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro]l of Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 1 minute 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 8.</p><p>[0136]  Subsequently, pTH/JFH1 was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 [micro]l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers MS 162 (SEQ ID NO: 19) and MS 156 (SEQ ID NO: 17) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro] lof Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 1 minute 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 9. </p><p>[0137]   PCR products were purified from agarose gel and eluted with the use of 50 [micro]l of EB buffer attached to the QIAquick Gel Extraction kit (QIAGEN). DNAs of PCR product No. 8 and PCR product No. 9 were mixed in amounts of 1 [micro]l each, the resultant was used as a template, 10 [micro]l of 5x buffer and 1 [micro]l of the 10 mM dNTP mixture attached to the Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase kit (FINNZYMES), and 2.5 [micro]l each of 10 [micro]M primers MS 151 (SEQ ID NO: 14) and MS 156 (SEQ ID NO: 17) were added, and deionized water was added to bring the total amount to 49.5 [micro]l in the end. Thereafter, 0.5 [micro]l of Phusion DNA Polymerase (FINNZYMES) was added thereto, and PCR was carried out. PCR was carried out by repeating a cycle of 98[deg.]C for 10 seconds, 58[deg.]C for 30 seconds, and 72[deg.]C for 1 minute and 30 seconds 30 times. The resulting PCR product was designated as PCR product No. 10 (Fig. 3B).</p><p>[0138]  pTH/JFH1 and the purified PCR product No. 7 were digested with the Acc65I restiction enzyme and the DNA fragments were separated via agarose gel electrophoresis, followed by purification. These two DNA fragments were mixed with Ligation high (New England Biolabs), and the two DNA fragments were ligated to each other. The vector was designated as pTH/JFH-1(PA). This pTH/JFH1 (PA) vector comprises a nucleotide sequence encoding a chimeric gene having the 5'-untranslated region derived from the JFH-1 strain; a region encoding the Core, E1, E2 and p7 proteins and the N-terminal 33 amino acid residues of NS2 protein derived from the TH strain; a region encoding the NS2 protein starting at amino acid residue 34 at the N-terminus and the NS3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A and NS5B proteins, and the 3'-untranslated region of the JFH-1 strain, wherein amino acid 328, when methionine as the amino acid at the N terminus of the Core protein is designated as amino acid 1, is alanine.</p><p>[0139]  Subsequently, pTH/JFH and the purified PCR product No. 10 were digested with the Acc651 restiction enzyme and the DNA fragments were separated via agarose gel electrophoresis, followed by purification. These two DNA fragments were mixed with Ligation high (New England Biolabs), and the two DNA fragments were ligated to each other. The vector was designated as pTH/JFH1(PT). This pTH/JFH1 (PT) vector comprises a nucleotide sequence encoding a chimeric gene having the 5'-untranslated region derived from the JFH-1 strain; a region encoding the Core, E1, E2, and p7 proteins and the N-terminal 33 amino acid residues of NS2 protein derived from the TH strain; a region encoding the NS2 protein starting at amino acid residue 34 at the N-terminus and the NS3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A and NS5B proteins, and the 3'-untranslated region of the JFH-1 strain, wherein amino acid 328, when methionine as the amino acid at the N terminus of the Core protein is designated as amino acid 1, is threonine.</p><p>[0140]  The nucleotide sequences of pTH/JFH1 (PA) and pTH/JFH1 (PT) are shown in SEQ ID NOs: 1 and 2, respectively, in the sequence listings.</p><p>Example 6: Preparation of TH/JFH-1 (PA) and TH/JFH-1 (PT) viruses</p><p>[0141]  Plasmids prepared in Example 5 were cleaved with XbaI, and the resultants were then subjected to phenol/chloroform extraction and ethanol precipitation. Subsequently, the XbaI cleavage fragments were treated with Mung Bean Nuclease, and the 3'-terminal extra nucleotide sequences derived from the XbaI recognition sequence were removed. Further, proteinase K treatment, phenol/chloroform extraction, and ethanol precipitation were carried out to purify the DNA fragments. The cleaved plasmids were used as templates to synthesize HCV RNAs using the MEGAscript T7 kit (Ambion).</p><p>[0142]  The Huh-7 cells (3 x 10&lt;6&gt; cells) and 10 [micro]g of HCV RNA were suspended in 400 [micro]l of the Cytomix solution (120 mM KCl, 0.15 mM CaCl2, 10 mM K2HPO4/KH2PO4, 25 mM Hepes, 2 mM EGTA, 5 mM MgCl2, 20 mM ATP, and 50 mM Glutathione), the suspension was transferred to a 4-mm cuvette, and electroporation was carried out using the Gene Pulser (BioRad) at 260 V and 950 [micro]F. Thereafter, the cells into which HCV RNA had been introduced were seeded on a 10 cm&lt;2&gt; dish and then subcultured.</p><p>[0143]  At the time of subculture of cells into which TH/JFH-1 RNA, TH/JFH-1 (PA) RNA (SEQ ID NO: 3), and TH/JFH-1 (PT) RNA (SEQ ID NO: 4) prepared in Example 2 had been introduced, the HCV Core protein contained in the culture supernatants were quantified using the HCV antigen ELISA test kit (Ortho) to confirm the production of HCV particles. From the initial stage to the late stage of culture, the amount of HCV Core protein contained in the culture supernatant of cells into which RNA without mutation had been introduced was compared with that into which RNA with mutation had been introduced. As a result, the latter amount was found to be higher (Fig. 4).</p><p>Example 7: Evaluation of infectivity of virus into which mutation had been introduced</p><p>[0144]  The infectivity of viruses produced from cells into which TH/JFH-1(PA) RNA had been introduced was compard with that of wild-type TH/JFH-1. Changes in the amount of HCV Core protein in the cells and in the culture supernatants 4, 24, 48, 72 and 96 hours after RNA introduction were analyzed, and the infectivity of the culture supernatant was.analyzed.</p><p>[0145]  Specifically, TH/JFH-1 and TH/JFH-1(PA) RNA were synthesized in the same manner as in Example 6, 3 x 10&lt;6&gt; Huh-7 cells and 10 [micro]g of HCV RNA were suspended in 400 [micro]l of the Cytomix solution (120 mM KCl, 0.15 mM CaCl2, 10 mM K2HPO4/KH2PO4, 25 mM Hepes, 2 mM EGTA, 5 mM MgCl2, 20 mM ATP, and 50 mM glutathione), the suspension was transferred to a 4-mm cuvette, and electroporation was carried out using the Gene Pulser (BioRad) at 260 V and 950 [micro]F. Thereafter, the cells into which HCV RNA had been introduced were seeded on a 10 cm&lt;2&gt; dish, the culture supernatant was collected 4, 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours later, the collected culture supernatant was filtered through a 0.45-[micro]m filter (Millipore), and the HCV Core proteins were quantified using the HCV antigen ELISA test kit (Ortho). The 10 cm&lt;2&gt; dish from which the culture supernatant had been removed was washed with PBS, cells were scraped off using 500 [micro]l of PBS and a scraper (Sumitomo Bakelite Co., Ltd.), and the cells were recovered via centrifugation. Passive Lysis Buffer (100 [micro]l, Promega) was added to the recovered cells to prepare a lysate, and the HCV Core proteins contained therein were quantified using the HCV antigen ELISA test kit (Ortho) as in the case of the culture supernatant.</p><p>[0146]  The culture supernatant was serially diluted with a culture medium to quantify the infectious titer thereof in the following manner. The Huh-7 cells were seeded on a 96-well polylysine-coated plate (Coming) at 1 x 10&lt;4&gt; cells/well, culture was conducted for a whole day, the culture medium was exchanged with the culture supernatant which had been serially diluted with a culture medium, and culture was conducted for an additional 3 days. Thereafter, the culture medium was discarded, the cells were washed 3 times with PBS, and the cells were immobilized with methanol for 15 minutes. Subsequently, the wells were blocked with the use of Block Ace (Dainippon Sumitomo Pharma Co., Ltd.) containing 0.3% Triton-X 100 and allowed to react with the anti-HCV Core-specific antibodies (clone 2H9). Subsequently, the wells were washed with PBS and the cells were allowed to react with the Alexa488-labeled anti-mouse IgG antibodies (Invitrogen). Thereafter, the wells were washed with PBS, the number of infectious foci of each well was counted under a fluorescent microscope (Olympus Corporation), and the infectious titer of each culture supernatant was calculated in terms of the focus-forming unit (FFU).</p><p>[0147]  As a result, the rate of the HCV Core protein secretion into the culture supernatant and the infectious titer of the culture supernatant were found to be higher in the cells into which TH/JFH-1(PA) RNA had been introduced than in cells into which wild-type TH/JFH-1 had been introduced (Figs. 5 and 6). It was demonstrated that a mutation of proline 328 in TH/JFH-1 (SEQ ID NO: 5) would enhance HCV particle production.</p><p>Industrial Applicability</p><p>[0148]  HCV particles that are provided by the method of the present invention exhibit high levels of expression, ability to be produced, and infectivity. Thus, such HCV particles can be preferably used for preventive or therapeutic vaccines for HCV. In addition, the HCV particles of the present invention can be used as tools for inducing antibodies reacting with HCV.</p><p>[0149]  All publications, patents, and patent applications cited herein are incorporated herein by reference in their entirety. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
</p></description></fulltext-document>