<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="annotation.xsl"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="annotation.nvdl"?>
<fulltext-document system="ops.epo.org" fulltext-format="text-only" xmlns="http://www.epo.org/fulltext"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference data-format="docdb"><document-id><country>EP</country><doc-number>2338492</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id></publication-reference></bibliographic-data><description lang="EN"><p>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</p><p>[0001]    The invention relates to the field of Alzheimer disease, more precisely to compounds for the treatment of Alzheimer disease.</p><p>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</p><p>[0002]    Amyloid diseases or amyloidoses include a number of disease states having a wide variety of outward symptoms. These disorders have in common the presence of abnormal extracellular deposits of protein fibrils, known as "amyloid fibrils", "amyloid deposits" or "amyloid plaques" that are usually about 10-100 nm in diameter and are localized to specific organs or tissue regions. Such plaques are composed primarily of a naturally occurring soluble protein or peptide. These insoluble deposits are composed of generally lateral aggregates of fibrils that are approximately 10-15 nm in diameter. Though diverse in their occurrence, all amyloid deposits have common morphologic properties, stain with specific dyes (e.g. Thioflavin T, Congo red), and have a characteristic red-green birefringent appearance in polarized light after staining.</p><p>[0003]    Amyloid-related diseases are characterized by the type of protein present in the deposit. For example, neurodegenerative diseases such as scrapie, bovine spongiform encephalitis, Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease and the like are characterized by the appearance and accumulation of a protease-resistant form of a prion protein (referred to as AScr or PrP-27) in the central nervous system. Similarly, Alzheimer's disease, another neurodegenerative disorder, is characterized by the deposition of amyloid plaques and neurofibrillary tangles. In this case, the plaque and blood vessel amyloid is formed by the deposition of fibrillar amyloid beta protein. Other diseases such as adult-onset diabetes (Type 11 diabetes) are characterized by the localized accumulation of amyloid in the pancreas.</p><p>[0004]    Each amyloidogenic protein has the ability to fold into beta-sheets and to form insoluble fibrils, which get deposited extracellularly or intracellularly. Each amyloidogenic protein, although different in amino acid sequence, has the same property of forming fibrils and binding to other elements such as proteoglycan, amyloid P and complement component. Moreover, each amyloidogenic protein has amino acid sequences, which, although different, can catalyze the formation of beta-sheet cells. As per example, the amyloid beta fibrils have been associated with dead neuronal cells and microgliosis in patients with Alzheimer's disease. When tested in vitro, the amyloid beta peptide was shown to be capable of triggering an activation process of microglia (brain macrophages), which would explain the presence of microgliosis and brain inflammation found in the brain of patients with Alzheimer's disease.</p><p>[0005]    In another type of amyloidosis seen in patients with Type II diabetes, the amyloidogenic protein IAPP has been shown to induce beta-islet cell toxicity in vitro. Hence, appearance of IAPP fibrils in the pancreas of Type II diabetic patients could contribute to the loss of the beta islet cells (Langerhans) and organ dysfunction.</p><p>[0006]    One of the most prominent amyloid diseases is Alzheimer's disease, which is a progressive neurodegenerative disease affecting approximately 0.5-1% of the total population in the western world. Alzheimer's disease is characterized by the deposition of large numbers of amyloid plaques in the brain.</p><p>[0007]    The molecular mechanisms responsible for the development of the idiopathic cases of Alzheimer disease (AD) are unknown. Growing evidence indicates that cerebral elevation and accumulation of A[beta] peptide mediate many aspects of AD pathogenesis. The main constituent of the amyloid plaques is the amyloid beta peptide (A[beta]), a 40-42 amino-acid protein that is produced through cleavage of the amyloid precursor protein (APP). This deposition is assumed to cause the pathology of the disease by different ways and most approaches to prevent Alzheimer's disease is aimed at reducing, removing, or preventing the formation of amyloid plaques or to inhibiting the down-stream path ways activated by this amyloid plaques.</p><p>[0008]    However there is still the need of further molecules for the treatment of Alzheimer's disease.</p><p>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</p><p>[0009]    The inventors have shown that A[beta] oligomers generate glutamate-independent inward currents, dysregulate Ca&lt;2+&gt; homeostasis and induce cell death through both NMDA and AMPA receptors in cultured neurons or in enthorinal cortex-hippocampus organotypic slices (Figure 1). In this apoptotic neuronal death caspase-dependent and independent pathways are involved. The inventors have surprisingly seen that A[beta] induced changes of [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! and provoke mitochondrial Ca&lt;2+&gt; overload, mitochondrial membrane depolarization and ROS generation. Moreover the inventors had surprisingly seen that antagonists of NMDA and AMPA receptor reduce deleterious events in mitochondria, indicating that AMPA receptors initiate the A[beta]-induced Ca&lt;2+&gt; dysregulation in neurons (Figures 2-5). These data indicate that A[beta] induced Ca&lt;2+&gt; dysregulation in neurons during amyloid protein deposition associated diseases and point to the AMPA receptors as a therapeutic target to limit tissue damage in said diseases.</p><p>[0010]    Thus, in an aspect, the invention relates to an AMPA receptor inhibitor for use in the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins.</p><p>[0011]    In another aspect, the invention relates to a method of inhibiting Ca&lt;2+&gt;-triggered central nervous system cell death which comprises contacting central nervous system cells with an AMPA receptor inhibitor under conditions effective to inhibit Ca&lt;2+-&gt;triggered central nervous system cell death, wherein the inhibitor inhibits the Ca&lt;2+&gt; flow through the AMPA receptor.</p><p>[0012]    In another aspect, the invention relates to NMDA receptor inhibitor for use in the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins.</p><p>[0013]    In another aspect, the invention relates with a method for identifying a compound useful for inhibiting the cellular death induced by amyloid proteins deposition for the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins comprising: 
a) putting in contact a cell with an amyloid protein,;
b) putting the cell resulting from step a) with the test compound; and
c) determining the levels of Ca&lt;2+&gt; and/or the levels of AMPA receptor activation in said cell ,wherein if the levels of Ca&lt;2+&gt; and /or the levels of AMPA receptor activation in said cell after the treatment of said cell with the test compound are lower than before the treatment, the test compound is able to inhibiting the cellular death induced by amyloid proteins deposition and useful for the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins. </p><p>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE FIGURES</p><p>[0014]    
Figure 1. A[beta] oligomers activate NMDA receptors and induce Ca&lt;2+&gt; influx into neurons. (A) A[beta] (1 [micro]M) evokes inward, non-desensitizing currents when applied together with glycine in Mg&lt;2+&gt;-free medium. A[beta]-activated currents are blocked by AP5 (100 [micro]M), a selective NMDA receptor antagonist. TTX (1 [micro]M) and calcium-free extracellular bath solution do not attenuate A[beta]-induced inward currents. (B) A[beta] (5 [micro]M) induces a rapid increase in [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]!, an effect that is blocked by NMDA receptor antagonists, MK801, AP5 and memantine, or by removal of Ca&lt;2+&gt; from the perfusate. Voltage-gated Ca&lt;2+&gt; channel inhibitors nifedipine and verapamil do not diminish A[beta] response.
Figure 2. A[beta] oligomers activate AMPA receptors and increase [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! in neurons. (A) A[beta] (1 [micro]M) together with CTZ (100 [micro]M) evokes inward, non-desensitizing currents in the presence of Mg&lt;2+&gt;. Currents are blocked by the AMPA/kainate receptor antagonist CNQX (30 [micro]M). (B) A[beta] in conjunction with CTZ induces [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! increase, that is partially blocked by CNQX and AP5, and further reduced by both antagonists applied together.
Figure 3. A[beta] oligomers trigger neuronal apoptotic death by activating NMDA and AMPA/kainate receptors. (A) Dose-response toxicity of A[beta] oligomers in cortical neurons in culture as measured 24 h later with the LDH viability assay. (B) Toxicity is prevented by co-application of A[beta] oligomers (5 [micro]M) with NMDA receptor antagonists AP5 (100 [micro]M), MK801 (50 [micro]M) and memantine (50 [micro]M), and with AMPA/kainate receptor antagonist CNQX (30 [micro]M). (C) A[beta] induced-toxicity was reduced by the broad-spectrum caspase-inhibitor ZVAD (50 [micro]M), by caspase-3 inhibitor DEVD (100 [micro]M) and by PARP-1 inhibitor DPQ (30 [micro]M). (* p&lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01 for each comparison between A[beta] alone and the co-applied with GluR antagonist or the corresponding inhibitor).
Figure 4. Blockade of glutamate receptors attenuates A[beta]-induced mitochondrial alterations. Neurons, loaded with Rhod-2 AM, were exposed to (A) FCCP (25 [micro]M) used as an internal control to release Ca&lt;2+&gt; from mitochondria, or to (B and C) A[beta] alone (5 [micro]M) or together with NMDA receptor antagonists. (B and C) [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]mit induced by A[beta] is reduced by NMDA receptor antagonists. Recordings in (B) illustrate average +- SEM responses of 74 cells from at least 5 experiments, and (C) histogram represents average +- SEM of area under Ca&lt;2+&gt; curve for each condition. (D and E) Cultures were first exposed to A[beta] alone or in conjunction with GluR antagonists for 2 hours, and cells were immediately loaded with the corresponding dyes to monitor ROS generation (D) and mitochondrial depolarization (E) by fluorimetry. NMDA and AMPA/kainate receptor antagonists prevent the increase in radical oxygen species and mitochondrial depolarization produced by A[beta]. * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01 for each antagonist versus A[beta].
Figure 5. MK801 and CNQX reduce A[beta]-induced [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! rises and abolish cell death in entorhinal cortex-hippocampus organotypic cultures. Cultures were fixed at 7 DIV and characterized by immunofluorescence with antibodies to neurofilaments (NFL) and cholinergic terminals (ChAT). (A, B) Hippocampus and entorhinal cortex showed profuse staining with NFL antibody. (C) Square shows the magnification in (A) of neuronal fibers from entorhinal cortex entering in CA1. (D) Cholinergic fibers revealed with ChAT in the entorhinal cortex (ECx) at high magnification. (E) A[beta] (20 [micro]M in the pipette) induces a rapid increase in [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! in hippocampus, an effect that is blocked by NMDA receptor antagonists MK801 (50 [micro]M; n=9) and by AMPA receptor antagonist CNQX (30 [micro]M; n=43) and further reduced by both antagonists applied together (n=50). Kainate (Kai) 1 mM also increases [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! in the same selected neurons. (F and G) Histogram and representative fields showing A[beta] (100 nM, 4 days) toxicity in cultures treated after 7 DIV and protection when oligomers are applied in conjunction with MK801 (10 [micro]M) or CNQX (30 [micro]M). Scale bar in (G) represents 500 [micro]m. (F) Bars (gray value/area) represent neuronal cell death occurs in A[beta]-treated hippocampus and entorhinal cortex. MK801 and CNQX mainly blocked the cell damage in both areas. Bars in (F) represent the average +- SEM from 5 experiments. # &lt; 0.05 for comparison A[beta] vs control treatments. * p &lt; 0.05 for comparison of A[beta] vs antagonist treatment.</p><p>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</p><p>THERAPEUTIC METHODS OF THE INVENTION</p><p>[0015]    The authors of the present invention have surprisingly found that A[beta] oligomers activates NMDA and AMPA receptor in neurons and that this activation causes an increase in basal [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! levels. Moreover, the inventors have shown that A[beta] induces mitochondrial Ca&lt;2+&gt; overload and that this effect can be prevented by NMDA receptors antagonists.</p><p>[0016]    This finding opens the possibility for improved therapies for diseases associated with deposition of amyloid proteins such Alzheimer by using AMPA receptor inhibitors.</p><p>[0017]    Thus, in a first aspect, the invention relates to an AMPA receptor inhibitor for use in the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins.</p><p>[0018]    Although a variety of subjects can be treated, it is particularly preferred that the subject be a human being.</p><p>[0019]    "AMPA receptors" or "AMPARs", as used herein, refers to proteins that are members of the ionotropic class of glutamate receptors. AMPA ([alpha]-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazole proprionic acid). Th e [alpha]-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid receptor (also known as AMPA receptor, AMPAR, or quisqualate receptor) is a non-NMDA-type ionotropic transmembrane receptor for glutamate that mediates fast synaptic transmission in the central nervous system (CNS). Its name is derived from its ability to be activated by the artificial glutamate analog, AMPA.</p><p>[0020]    AMPARs are composed of four types of subunits, designated as GluR1 (GRIA1), GluR2 (GRIA2), GluR3 (GRIA3), and GluR4, alternatively called GluRA-D2 (GRIA4), which combine to form tetramers ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Shi S.H. et al. Science 284 (5421): 1811-6</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Song I. et al. Trends Neurosci. 25 (11): 578-88</bibl> ). Most AMPARs are heterotetrameric, consisting of symmetric 'dimer of dimers' of GluR2 and either GluR1, GluR3 or GluR4. (<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Mayer, M. L. 2005. 15 (3), 282-288</bibl>; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Greger IH, et al. 2007. Trends Neurosci. 30 (8): 407-16</bibl> ).</p><p>[0021]    AMPARs subunits differ most in their c-terminal sequence, which determines their interactions with scaffolding proteins. All AMPARs contain PDZ-binding domains, but which PDZ domain they bind to differs. For example, GluR1 binds to SAP97 through SAP97's class I PDZ domain ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Leonard AS, et al. J. Biol. 1998. Chem. 273 (31): 19518-24</bibl> ), while GluR2 binds to PICK1 ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Greger IH, et al. 2002. Neuron 34 (5): 759-72</bibl> ) and GRIP/ABP. Of note, AMPARs cannot directly bind to the common synaptic protein PSD-95 due to incompatible PDZ domains. </p><p>[0022]    Phosphorylation of AMPARs can regulate channel localization, conductance, and open probability. GluRl has four known phosphorylation sites at serine 818 (S818), S831, threonine 840, and S845 (other subunits have similar phosphorylation sites, but GluR1 has been the most extensively studied). S818 is phosphorylated by PKC, and is necessary for long term potentiation (LTP; for GluR1's role in LTP, see below). ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Boehm J. et al. 2006 Neuron 51 (2): 213-25</bibl> ). S831 is phosphorylated by CaMKII during LTP, which helps deliver GluR1-containing AMPAR to the synapse, ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Hayashi Y. et al., 2000. Science 287 (5461): 2262-7</bibl> ) and increases their single channel conductance. The T840 site was more recently discovered, and has been implicated in LTD. Finally, S845 is phosphorylated by both PKA which regulates its open probability ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Delgado JY, 2007. J. Neurosci. 27 (48): 13210-21</bibl> ).</p><p>[0023]    In humans different genes coding for the different AMPAR subunits exist: GRIA1 (transcript variant 1: NM_000827.3 (SEQ ID NO:1), transcript variant 2: NM_001114183.1 (SEQ ID NO:2)) GRIA2 (transcript variant 1: NM_001083619.1 (SEQ ID NO:3), transcript variant 2: NM_000826.3 (SEQ ID NO:4), transcript variant 3: NM_001083620.1 (SEQ ID NO:5)) GRIA3 (transcript variant 1: NM_000828.4 (SEQ ID NO:6), transcript variant 2: NM_007325.4 (SEQ ID NO:7)) GRIA4 (transcript variant 1: NM_000829.3 (SEQ ID NO:8), transcript variant 2: NM_001077243.2 (SEQ ID NO:9), transcript variant 3: NM_001077244.1 (SEQ ID NO:10), transcript variant 4: NM_001112812.1 (SEQ ID NO:11)).</p><p>[0024]    In mice: Gria1 (NP_032191.2 (SEQ ID NO:12)), Gria2 (NP_038568.2, (SEQ ID NO:13)), Gria 3 (NM_016886.2, (SEQ ID NO:14)), Gria4 (NM_019691.4, (SEQ ID NO:15)).</p><p>[0025]    In Rat: Gria1 (NM_031608.1, (SEQ ID NO:16)), Gria2 (NM_017261, (SEQ ID NO:17)), Gria3 (NM_032990.2, (SEQ ID NO:18)), Gria4 (NM_017263.2, (SEQ ID NO:19)).</p><p>[0026]    In chimpanzee: Gria1 (XP_527092.2, (SEQ ID NO:20)), Gria2 (XP_001141570.1, (SEQ ID NO:21)), Gria3 (XR_023006.1, (SEQ ID NO:22)), Gria4 (XP_522168.2, (SEQ ID NO:23)).</p><p>[0027]    Each AMPAR has four sites to which an agonist (such as glutamate) can bind, one for each subunit ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Mayer, M. L. 2005. Current Opinion in Neurobiology, 15 (3), 282-288</bibl> ). The binding site is believed to be formed by the n-tail, and the extracellular loop between transmembrane domains three and four ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Armstrong N, 1998. Nature 395 (6705): 913-7</bibl> ). When an agonist binds, these two loops move towards each other, opening the pore. The channel opens when two sites are occupied, and increases its current as more binding sites are occupied. Once open, the channel may undergo rapid desensitization, stopping the current. The mechanism of desensitization is believed to be due to a small change in angle of one of the parts of the binding site, closing the pore. AMPARs open and close quickly, and are thus responsible for most of the fast excitatory synaptic transmission in the central nervous system.</p><p>[0028]    In another aspect, the invention relates to a method for the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins comprising the administration to a subject in need thereof of a composition comprising a therapeutical effective amount of an AMPA receptor inhibitor.</p><p>[0029]    As used herein, the terms "treat", "treatment" and "treating" refer to the amelioration of one or more symptoms associated with a disease that results from the administration of a therapeutically effective amount of the composition of the invention or a pharmaceutical preparation comprising thereof, to a subject in need of said treatment. Thus, "treatment" as used herein covers any treatment of a disease, disorder or condition of a mammal, particularly a human, and includes: (a) preventing the disease or condition from occurring in a subject which may be predisposed to the disease or condition but has not yet been diagnosed as having it; (b) inhibiting the disease or condition, i.e., arresting its development; or (c) relieving the disease or condition, i.e., causing regression of the disease or condition or amelioration of one or more symptoms of the disease or condition. The population of subjects treated by the method includes a subject suffering from the undesirable condition or disease, as well as subjects at risk for development of the condition or disease. Thus, one of skill in the art realizes that a treatment may improve the patient's condition, but may not be a complete cure of the disease. As used herein, the terms "disorder" and "disease" are used interchangeably to refer to an abnormal or pathological condition in a subject that impairs bodily functions and can be deadly.</p><p>[0030]    The phrase "therapeutically effective amount" is used herein to mean an amount sufficient to prevent, and preferably reduce by at least about 25 percent, more preferably by at least 50 percent, most preferably by at least 90 percent, a clinically significant change in a feature of pathology. As related to the present invention, the term may also mean an amount sufficient to ameliorate or reverse one or more symptoms associated with a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins, such as Alzheimer's disease. In particular, a "therapeutically effective amount" of the treatment may result in amelioration, reduction or elimination of at least one of the following symptoms: memory impairment, persistent sadness or anxiety, feelings of emptiness, hopelessness, pessimism, guilt, worthlessness, helplessness, a loss of interest or pleasure in hobbies and activities that were once enjoyed, decreased energy, or fatigue, difficulty concentrating, remembering, or making decisions, insomnia, early-morning awakening, or oversleeping, appetite and/or weight loss or overeating and weight gain, thoughts of death or suicide and suicide attempts, restlessness, irritability, and persistent physical symptoms that do not respond to treatment, such as headaches, digestive disorders, and chronic pain. When applied to an individual active ingredient, administered alone, the term refers to that ingredient alone. When applied to a combination, the term refers to combined amounts of the active ingredients that result in the therapeutic effect, whether administered in combination, serially or simultaneously.</p><p>[0031]    The term "subject" refers to an animal, preferably a mammal including a non-primate (e.g. a cow, pig, horse, cat, dog, rat, or mouse) and a primate (e.g. a monkey or a human). In a preferred embodiment, the subject is a dog. In a more preferred embodiment, the subject is a primate which, in a still more preferred embodiment, said primate is a human.</p><p>[0032]    In the context of the present invention, "a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins" includes diseases associated with the accumulation of amyloid protein which can either be restricted to one organ, i.e. "localized amyloidosis" or spread to several organs, which is denoted "systemic amyloidosis". Diseases associated with deposition of amyloid proteins that can be treated with the compositions according to the present invention include, without limitation, the disease shown below. 
&lt;tb&gt;Disease&lt;sep&gt;Featured protein
&lt;tb&gt;Alzheimer's disease&lt;sep&gt;Beta amyloid
&lt;tb&gt;Inclusion body myositis (IBM),&lt;sep&gt;Beta amyloid
&lt;tb&gt;Type 2 diabetes mellitus&lt;sep&gt;IAPP (Amylin) 
&lt;tb&gt;Parkinson's disease&lt;sep&gt;Alpha-synuclein
&lt;tb&gt;Transmissible spongiform encephalopathy (Mad Cow Disease)&lt;sep&gt;Prion
&lt;tb&gt;Huntington's Disease&lt;sep&gt;Huntingtin
&lt;tb&gt;Medullary carcinoma of the thyroid&lt;sep&gt;Calcitonin
&lt;tb&gt;Cardiac arrhythmias&lt;sep&gt;Atrial natriuretic factor
&lt;tb&gt;Atherosclerosis&lt;sep&gt;Apolipoprotein AI
&lt;tb&gt;Rheumatoid arthritis&lt;sep&gt;Serum amyloid A
&lt;tb&gt;Aortic medial amyloid&lt;sep&gt;Medin
&lt;tb&gt;Prolactinomas&lt;sep&gt;Prolactin
&lt;tb&gt;Familial amyloid polyneuropathy&lt;sep&gt;Transthyretin
&lt;tb&gt;Hereditary non-neuropathic systemic amyloidosis&lt;sep&gt;Lysozyme
&lt;tb&gt;Dialysis related amyloidosis&lt;sep&gt;[beta]2-Microglobulin
&lt;tb&gt;Finnish amyloidosis&lt;sep&gt;Gelsolin
&lt;tb&gt;Lattice corneal dystrophy&lt;sep&gt;Keratoepithelin
&lt;tb&gt;Cerebral amyloid angiopathy&lt;sep&gt;Beta amyloid
&lt;tb&gt;Cerebral amyloid angiopathy (Icelandic type)&lt;sep&gt;Cystatin
&lt;tb&gt;Systemic AL amyloidosis&lt;sep&gt;Immunoglobulin light chain AL</p><p>[0033]    In a preferred embodiment, the disease is a disease associated with deposition of beta amyloid such as Alzheimer, Inclusion body myositis (IBM), cerebral amyloid angiopathy, loss of memory, hereditary cerebral haemorrhage Dutch-type, diabetes II, Parkinson disease, Down's Syndrome, Pick disease, multiple systemic atrophy (ASM), progressive supracraneal paralysis, multiple sclerosis, ischemia, cerebral lesion, schizophrenia, etc.</p><p>[0034]    The term "amyloid beta peptide" is used herein interchangeably with Abeta, amyloid beta protein, "A beta", "beta AP", "A beta peptide" or "A[beta] peptide" or "A[beta]" and refers to a family of peptides that are the principal chemical constituent of the senile plaques and vascular amyloid deposits (amyloid angiopathy) found in the brain in patients of Alzheimer's disease (AD), Down's Syndrome, and Hereditary Cerebral Hemorrhage with Amyloidosis of the Dutch-Type (HCHWA-D), etc. In whatever form, amyloid beta peptide is a fragment of beta-amyloid precursor protein (APP) which comprises a variable number of amino acids, typically 39-43 amino acids. "A[beta](1-42)", as used herein, relates to a 42 amino acids peptide corresponding to amino acids 672 to 713 of APP and which is produced by the sequential proteolytic cleavage of the amyloid precursor protein by the [beta]- and [gamma]-secretases.</p><p>AMPA receptor inhibitors</p><p>[0035]    "AMPA receptor inhibitors", as used herein, relates to any compound capable of causing a decrease in the AMPA hemichannel activity, including those compounds which prevent expression of the AMPA hemichannel gene, leading to reduced AMPA mRNA or protein levels as well as compounds that inhibit AMPA causing a decrease in the cations (Ca&lt;2+,&gt; Na&lt;+&gt;, K&lt;+&gt;, etc) flow through the channel. In a particular embodiment, the AMPA receptor inhibitor is an AMPA blocker or antagonist. An "AMPA blocker or antagonist" as used herein relates to any compound capable of binding to the AMPA molecule, either inside of the pore or at other part of the receptor important for the receptor function such as the phosphorylation sites described previously. The binding of the compound would then block the flow of the cations through the AMPA receptor. If the blocker acts as an antagonist, the compound would blocks or dampen an agonist-mediated response. The antagonists binding will disrupt the interaction and inhibit the function of an agonist or inverse agonist at receptors. Antagonists mediate their effects by binding to the active site or to allosteric sites on receptors, or they may interact at unique binding sites not normally involved in the biological regulation of the receptor's activity. Antagonist activity may be reversible or irreversible depending on the longevity of the antagonist-receptor complex, which, in turn, depends on the nature of antagonist receptor binding.</p><p>[0036]    Compounds leading to the inhibition of an AMPA receptor can be identified using standard assays such as methods for measuring the cation (e.g. Ca&lt;2+&gt;) flow through the channel, using standard electrophysiology methods and receptor-binding assays as described in Matzen et al. ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Matzen L. et al. 1997. J. Med. Chem., 40 (4), pp 520-527</bibl> ) and Hajnóczky et al. ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">G. Hajnóczky, et al. 1995. Cell 82 415-424</bibl> ), or in this specification (see Example, "Methods", "Electrophysiology"). The mitochondrial and cytosolic concentration of the cations can be also measured using, for example, fluorescent indicators for said cations, such as the Ca&lt;2+&gt; dyes described by Grynkiewicz et al. ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">G. Grynkiewicz, et al. 1985. J. Biol. Chem. 260, 3440-3450</bibl> ) or in this specification (see methods, "Ca&lt;2+&gt; imaging in the cytosol" and "Measurement of mitochondrial Ca&lt;2+,,&gt;).</p><p>[0037]    The determination of the inhibiting or blocking capacities of the compound on the biological activity of AMPA receptor can be detected using the above described standard assays.</p><p>[0038]    The blocking capacities can be expressed as the affinity of the inhibitor, the potency of the inhibitor or the specificity of said inhibitor.</p><p>[0039]    The affinity of a drug is calculated using the equilibrium dissociation constant of the receptor-drug complex, KD. KD is the ratio of rate constants for the reverse (k2) and forward (k1) reaction between the drug and receptor and the drug-receptor complex. KD is also the drug concentration at which receptor occupancy is half of maximum. Drugs with a high KD (low affinity) dissociate rapidly from receptors; conversely, drugs with a low KD (high affinity) dissociate slowly from receptors. The affinity of a drug for a receptor describes how avidly the drug binds to the receptor (ie, the KD). The affinity can be measured using equilibrium binding techniques such as the ones described by in Kessler et al. ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kessler M et al., Molecular Pharmacology January 1996 vol. 49 no. 1:123-131</bibl> ).</p><p>[0040]    In a preferred embodiment, the AMPA receptor inhibitor has a KD between of between 0.001 nM and 10 [micro]M, preferably between 0.01 [micro]M and 1 [micro]M, preferably between 0.01 nM and 100 nM, preferably between 0.1 nM and 10 nM.</p><p>[0041]    Potency refers to the concentration (EC50) or dose (ED50) of a drug required to produce 50% of the drug's maximal effect. (http://www.ncgc.nih.gov/guidance/section3.html). EC50 equals KD when there is a linear relationship between occupancy and response. Often, signal amplification occurs between receptor occupancy and response, which results in the EC50 for response being much less (i.e., positioned to the left on the abscissa of the log dose-response curve) than KD for receptor occupancy. Potency depends on both the affinity of a drug for its receptor, and the efficiency with which drug-receptor interaction is coupled to response. The dose of drug required to produce an effect is inversely related to potency. In general, low potency is important only if it results in a need to administer the drug in large doses that are impractical. The ED50 for a quantal dose-response relationship is the dose at which 50% of individuals exhibit the specified quantal effect. In a preferred embodiment, the AMPA receptor inhibitor has a IC50 of between 0.001 nM and 10 [micro]M, preferably between 0.01 nM and 1 [micro]M, preferably between 0.1nM and 100 nM, preferably between 0.1 nM and 10 nM.</p><p>[0042]    Efficacy (also referred to as intrinsic activity) of a drug is the ability of the drug to elicit a response when it binds to the receptor. In some tissues, agonists demonstrating high efficacy can result in a maximal effect, even when only a small fraction of the receptors are occupied. Efficacy is not linked to potency of a drug.</p><p>[0043]    The median inhibitory concentration or IC50 is the concentration of an antagonist that reduces a specified response to 50% of the maximal possible effect.</p><p>[0044]    The higher specificity of a compound for a define molecule refers to the ability of the compound for inhibiting the define molecule in a substantially higher manner in respect to the ability of the compound for inhibiting other molecule.</p><p>[0045]    In a preferred embodiment, the inhibitor is a selective AMPA receptor inhibitor.</p><p>[0046]    The language "selective AMPA receptor inhibitor" refers to a compound capable of inhibiting the activity of AMPA receptor while not substantially inhibiting the activity of at least one receptor form the same family (such as NMDA receptor) or a molecule from a different family at the same compound concentration For example, a selective AMPA receptor inhibitor may have an AMPA receptor inhibitory activity 2, 5, 10, 20, 50, 100, 500, or 1000-fold more potent than its NMDA inhibitory activity. In certain embodiments, the AMPA receptor inhibitory activity of a selective AMPA receptor inhibitor is at least 5-fold, 10-fold, or 20-fold more potent than the inhibitory activity for other molecule such as NMDA of the compound.</p><p>[0047]    Exemplary, non-limitative, AMPA receptor inhibitors that can be used in the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins, according to the instant invention are described under 1 to 21 in Table I or in the patent <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">US2004049039A</bibl> . 
Table I
&lt;tb&gt;AMPA receptor inhibitors
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;Compound
&lt;tb&gt;1&lt;sep&gt;CFM-2
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;1-(4'-Aminophenyl)-3,5-dihydro-7,8-dimethoxy-4H-2,3-ben zodiazepin-4-one
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;2&lt;sep&gt;CNQX
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;6-Cyano-7-nitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;3&lt;sep&gt;CNQX disodium salt
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;6-Cyano-7-nitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione disodium
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;4&lt;sep&gt;CP 465022 hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;3-(2-Chlorophenyl)-2-[2-[6-[(diethylamino)methyl]-2-pyridinyl]ethenyl]-6-fluoro-4(3H)-quinazolinone hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
 
&lt;tb&gt;5&lt;sep&gt;DNQX
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;6,7-Dinitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;6&lt;sep&gt;DNQX disodium salt
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;6,7-Dinitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione disodium salt
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;7&lt;sep&gt;Evans Blue tetrasodium salt
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;6,6-[(3,3'-Dimethyl[1,1'-biphenyl]-4,4'-diyl)bis(azo)bi s[4-amino- 5-hydroxy-1,3-naphthalenedisulphonic acid] tetrasodium salt.
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;8&lt;sep&gt;GYKI 47261 dihydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;4-(8-Chloro-2-methyl-11H-imidazo[1,2-c][2,3]benzodiazep in-6-benzeneamine dihydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
 
&lt;tb&gt;9&lt;sep&gt;NBQX
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;2,3-Dioxo-6-nitro-1,2,3,4-tetrahydrobenzo[f]quinoxaline -7-sulfonamide and 6,7-Dinitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione disodium salt
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 </p><p>&lt;tb&gt;10&lt;sep&gt;Philanthotoxin 74 or PhTx-74
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(S)-N-[7-[(4-Aminobutyl)amino]heptyl]-4-hydroxy-a-[(1-o xobutyl)amino]benzenepropanamide dihydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;11&lt;sep&gt;SYM 2206
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(+-)-4-(4-Aminophenyl)-1,2-dihydro-1-methyl-2-propylcarb amoyl-6,7-methylenedioxyphthalazine
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;12&lt;sep&gt;UBP 282 or 3-CBW
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(aS)-a-Amino-3-[(4-carboxyphenyl)methyl]-3,4-dihydro-2, 4-dioxo-1(2H)-pyrimidinepropanoic acid
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
 
&lt;tb&gt;13&lt;sep&gt;YM 90K hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;1,4-Dihydro-6-(1H-imidazol-1-yl)-7-nitro-2,3-quinoxalin edione hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;14&lt;sep&gt;ZK 200775 (MPQX)
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;[[3,4-Dihydro-7-(4-morphofinyl)-2,3-dioxo-6-(trifluorom ethyl)-1(2H)-quinoxafinyl]methyl]phosphonic acid
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;15&lt;sep&gt;LY 303070
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;16&lt;sep&gt;LY300164
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
 
&lt;tb&gt;17&lt;sep&gt;An inhibitory antibody capable of specifically binding and inhibiting the activity of an AMPA receptor.
&lt;tb&gt;18&lt;sep&gt;A ribozyme or a DNA enzyme specific for the sequence of an AMPAR.
&lt;tb&gt;19&lt;sep&gt;An interfering RNA specific for the sequence of an AMPA receptor.
&lt;tb&gt;20&lt;sep&gt;An inhibiting peptide specific for an AMPA receptor.
&lt;tb&gt;21&lt;sep&gt;An AMPA receptor - specific antisense nucleic acid</p><p>AMPA receptor inhibitory antibodies</p><p>[0048]    Antibodies against an epitope located in either the pore or an external part of the AMPA molecule may effectively inhibit the function of this protein and, therefore, can be used as blocker or inhibitor in the compositions of the present invention. Thus, "Inhibitory antibody", as used herein, refers to antibodies which are capable of inhibiting at least partially the biological activities of the AMPA receptor.</p><p>[0049]    The determination of the inhibiting capacity on the biological activity of the AMPA receptor is detected using standard assays to measure the cation released through the AMPA receptor using methods described before.</p><p>[0050]    Inhibiting antibodies or fragments specific for an AMPA receptor may be readily available, or may be readily produced using conventional molecular biology techniques. For example, using immunogens derived from, for example, AMPA receptor molecule it is possible to obtain anti-protein/anti-peptide antisera or monoclonal antibodies by using standard protocols (See, for example, <bibl type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Antibodies: A Laboratory Manual ed. by Harlow and Lane (Cold Spring Harbor Press: 1988 )</bibl>). A mammal, such as a mouse, a hamster or rabbit can be immunized with an immunogenic form of the peptide (e.g., AMPA receptor or an antigenic fragment thereof, which is capable of eliciting an antibody response). Techniques for conferring immunogenicity on a protein or peptide, include conjugation to carriers or other techniques, are well known in the art. An immunogenic portion of a polypeptide can be administered in the presence of adjuvant. The progress of immunization can be monitored by detection of antibody titers in plasma or serum. Standard ELISA or other immunoassays can be used with the immunogen as antigen to assess the levels of antibodies. In a preferred embodiment, the antibodies forming part of the compositions of the invention are immuno-specific for antigenic determinants of AMPA receptor (or a variant at least 80%, 85%, 90%, 95%, or 98% identical thereto). In certain embodiment, the immunospecific subject antibodies do not substantially cross react with a non-vertebrate (such as yeast) AMPA receptor related protein. By "not substantially cross react", it is meant that the antibody has a binding affinity for a non-homologous protein which is at least one order of magnitude, more preferably at least 2 orders of magnitude, and even more preferably at least 3 orders of magnitude less than the binding affinity of the antibody for a AMPA receptor.</p><p>[0051]    Thus, the antibody which can be used for the purposes of the instant invention as a AMPA receptor inhibitory antibody, hereinafter referred to as the "antibody of the invention", is capable of binding an epitope of the AMPA receptor; typically, at least 6, 8, 10, or 12, contiguous amino acids are required to form an epitope, however, epitopes which involve non-contiguous amino acids may require more, e.g., at least 15, 25, or 50 amino acid. The term "antibody of the invention" includes, for example, polyclonal antibodies, monoclonal antibodies, Fab and single chain Fv (scFv) fragments thereof, bispecific antibodies, heteroconjugates, human and humanized antibodies. Such antibodies may be produced in a variety of ways, including hybridoma cultures, recombinant expression in bacteria or mammalian cell cultures, and recombinant expression in transgenic animals. Also antibodies can be produced by selecting a sequence from a library of sequences expressed in display systems such as filamentous phage, bacterial, yeast or ribosome. There is abundant guidance in the literature for selecting a particular production methodology, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Chadd and Chamow, Curr. Opin. Biotechnol., 12:188-194 (2001 )</bibl>. The choice of manufacturing methodology depends on several factors including the antibody structure desired, the importance of carbohydrate moieties on the antibodies, ease of culturing and purification, and cost. Many different antibody structures may be generated using standard expression technology, including full-length antibodies, antibody fragments, such as Fab and Fv fragments, as well as chimeric antibodies comprising components from different species. Antibody fragments of small size, such as Fab and Fv fragments, having no effector functions and limited pharmokinetic activity may be generated in a bacterial expression system. Single chain Fv fragments show low immunogenicity and are cleared rapidly from the blood.</p><p>[0052]    The antibodies of the invention may be polyclonal antibodies. Such polyclonal antibodies can be produced in a mammal, such as a non-human mammal, for example, following one or more injections of an immunizing agent, and preferably, an adjuvant. Typically, the immunizing agent and/or adjuvant will be injected into the mammal by a series of subcutaneous or intraperitoneal injections. The immunizing agent may include AMPA receptors or fragments thereof or a fusion protein thereof or a cell expressing AMPA receptors. Such proteins, fragments or preparations are introduced into the non-human mammal in the presence of an appropriate adjuvant. Other form of administration of an immunogen is as a trasmembrane protein in the surface of a cell (methods described in, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Spiller et al. J. Immunol. Methods, 224: 51-60 (1999 )</bibl>). These cells can be either cells which naturally express the antigen or in which this expression can be obtained after transfecting the cell with a DNA construct that contains among other DNA sequences those coding the antigen, those necessary for its sufficient expression in the cell. This approach is possible not only when the cell membrane is the natural site in which the antigen is expressed even the antigen once synthesized in the cell is directed at these location by a signal peptide which is added at the antigen coding sequence. If the serum contains polyclonal antibodies to undesired epitopes, the polyclonal antibodies can be purified by immunoaffinity chromatography.</p><p>[0053]    Alternatively, said antibodies may be monoclonal antibodies. Monoclonal antibodies may be produced by hybridomas, wherein a mouse, hamster, or other appropriate host animal, is immunized with an immunizing agent to elicit lymphocytes that produce or are capable of producing antibodies that will specifically bind to the immunizing agent, e.g. <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kohler and Milstein, Nature 256:495 (1975 )</bibl>. The immunizing agent will typically include a AMPA receptor or a fragment thereof or a fusion protein thereof and optionally a carrier or a crude protein preparation which has been enriched for a AMPA receptor or a cell expressing any of said proteins. Such proteins, fragments or preparations are introduced into the non-human mammal in the presence of an appropriate adjuvant. Other form of administration of an immunogen is as a trasmembrane protein in the surface of a cell (methods described in, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Spiller et al. J. Immunol. Methods, 224: 51-60 (1999 )</bibl>). These cells can be everyone which naturally express the antigen in its cell membrane or in which this expression can be obtained after transfecting the cell with a DNA construct that contains among other DNA sequences those coding the antigen, those necessary for its sufficient expression in the cell. This approach is possible not only when the cell membrane is the natural site in which the antigen is expressed even the antigen once synthesized in the cell is directed at these location by a signal peptide which is added at the antigen coding sequence. Alternatively, lymphocytes may be immunized in vitro. Generally, spleen cells or lymph node cells are used if non-human mammalian sources are desired, or peripheral blood lymphocytes ("PBLs") are used if cells of human origin are desired. The lymphocytes are fused with an immortalized cell line using a suitable fusing agent, such as polyethylene glycol, to produce a hybridoma cell. In general, immortalized cell lines are myeloma cells of rat, mouse, bovine or human origin. The hybridoma cells are cultured in a suitable culture medium that preferably contains one or more substances that inhibit the growth or survival of unfused, immortalized cells. Clones are isolated using the limiting dilution method and the culture medium (supernatant) in which the hybridoma cells are cultured can be assayed for the presence of monoclonal antibodies directed against AMPA receptors by conventional techniques, such as by flow cytometry or by immunoprecipitation or by other in vitro binding assay, such as RIA or ELISA. Clones can also be cultured in vivo as ascites tumours in an animal.</p><p>[0054]    Preferably, the binding specificity of monoclonal antibodies produced by a clone of hybridoma cells is determined by immunoprecipitation or by an in vitro binding assay, such as radioimmunoassay (RIA) or enzyme-linked immunoabsorbent assay (ELISA) or by immunofluorescent techniques such as fluorescence microscopy or flow cytometry. The monoclonal antibodies secreted by the subclones are suitably separated from the culture medium, ascites fluid, or serum by conventional immunoglobulin purification procedures such as, for example, protein A-Sepharose, hydroxylapatite chromatography, gel electrophoresis, dialysis, or affinity chromatography.</p><p>[0055]    The monoclonal antibodies may also be made by recombinant DNA methods, such as those described in <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">US 4,816,567</bibl> . DNA encoding the monoclonal antibodies of the invention can be isolated from a AMPA receptor-specific hybridoma cells and sequenced by using conventional procedures, e.g., by using oligonucleotide probes that are capable of binding specifically to genes encoding the heavy and light chains of murine antibodies. The hybridoma cells serve as a preferred source of such DNA. Once isolated, the DNA may be inserted into an expression vector, which is then transfected into host cells such as simian COS cells, Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cells, or myeloma cells that do not otherwise produce immunoglobulin protein, to obtain the synthesis of monoclonal antibodies in the recombinant host cells. The DNA also may be modified, for example, by substituting the coding sequence for the murine heavy and light chain constant domains for the homologous human sequences, or by covalently joining to the immunoglobulin coding sequence all or part of the coding sequence for a non-immunoglobulin polypeptide. The non-immunoglobulin polypeptide can be substituted for the constant domains of an antibody of the invention, or can be substituted for the variable domains of one antigen-combining site of an antibody of the invention to create a chimeric bivalent antibody.</p><p>[0056]    Another method of generating specific antibodies, or antibody fragments, reactive against a target molecule is to screen expression libraries encoding immunoglobulin genes, or portions thereof, expressed in bacteria, yeast, filamentous phages, ribosomes or ribosomal subunits and other display systems. These methods normally use large libraries of antibody sequences or antibody fragment sequences obtained from diverse sources such healthy donors or patients or animals healthy or not. These sequences are cloned and expressed in an appropriate system and selected by its binding affinity for the antigen. Diverse approaches have been described to select antibodies or fragments with desired properties e.g. neutralizing, agonist, etc ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Fernández, Curr. Op. Biotech., 15: 364-373 (2004 )</bibl>; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Schmidt, Eur. J. Biochem., 268: 1730-1738 (2001 )</bibl>). In an embodiment, antibodies and antibody fragments characteristic of hybridomas of the invention can also be produced by recombinant means by extracting messenger RNA, constructing a cDNA library, and selecting clones which encode segments of the antibody molecule.</p><p>[0057]    The antibodies may also be engineered to alter its clinical uses. Numerous approaches make use of the molecular biology and genetic techniques such as the good knowledge of the genetics ad structure of the immunoglobulins to construct different modifications of immunoglobulin molecule with the aim of improve its properties for clinical or other uses. Some of them tend to reduce the immunogenicity of the molecule in the species in which should be used and the resultant molecule has a sequence more homologous with this species. Various methods have been used to obtain mAbs of human origin avoiding the non ethically admissible proceedings in healthy humans. In other approaches the molecular weigh and size are reduced e.g. in order of improving the distribution of the molecule into solid tumours. Other possibilities are conjugation in a molecule of binding domains for more than one target molecule (bispecific antibody or also triespecific, etc) or the conjugation of an antibody or a fragment with another molecule with the desired function e.g. a toxic agent, a hormone, growth factor, a immunomodulating agent (immunosuppressor or immunostimulator), an inhibitor of cell growth, etc. In general all the resultant molecules retain almost one variable domain of an antibody which gives the high specificity and affinity characteristic of the antigen-antibody binding. Some examples of these constructions are: 
Chimeric antibodies: These refers to antibodies constructed with variable regions from an antibody of some species (normally a mammal in which the mAb was generated) and constant regions of other species (the one in which the chimeric antibody is to be used);
Humanized antibodies: By "humanized antibody" is meant an antibody derived from a non-human antibody, typically a murine antibody, that retains the antigen-binding properties of the parent antibody, but which is less immunogenic in humans. This may be achieved by various methods, including (a) grafting the entire non-human variable domains onto human constant regions to generate chimeric antibodies; (b) grafting only the non-human complementarity determining regions (CDRs) into human framework and constant regions with or without retention of critical framework residues; and (c) transplanting the entire non-human variable domains, but "cloaking" them with a human-like section by replacement of surface residues. Methods for humanizing non-human antibodies have been described in the art. Preferably, a humanized antibody has one or more amino acid residues introduced into it from a source which is non-human. These non-human amino acid residues are often referred to as "import" residues, which are typically taken from an "import" variable domain. Humanization can be essentially performed following the method of Winter and co-workers ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Jones et al., Nature, 321:522-525 (1986 )</bibl>; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Reichmann et al., Nature, 332:323-327 (1988 )</bibl>; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Verhoeyen et al., Science, 239:1534-1536 (1988 )</bibl>), by substituting hypervariable region sequences for the corresponding sequences of a human antibody. ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Carter et al., Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 89:4285 (1992 )</bibl>; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Presta et al., J. Immunol., 151:2623 (1993 )</bibl>). It is further important that antibodies be humanized with retention of high affinity for the antigen and other favorable biological properties. To achieve this goal, according to a preferred method, humanized antibodies are prepared by a process of analysis of the parental sequences and various conceptual humanized products using three-dimensional models of the parental and humanized sequences.
Primatized antibodies: A next step in this approach of making an antibody more similar at humans' are the so called primatized antibodies, i.e. a recombinant antibody which has been engineered to contain the variable heavy and light domains of a monkey (or other primate) antibody, in particular, a cynomolgus monkey antibody, and which contains human constant domain sequences, preferably the human immunoglobulin gamma 1 or gamma 4 constant domain (or PE variant). The preparation of such antibodies is described in <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Newman et al., Biotechnology, 10: 1458-1460 (1992 )</bibl>; <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">US 5,658,570</bibl>  and <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">US 6,113,898</bibl> . These antibodies have been reported to exhibit a high degree of homology to human antibodies, i.e., 85-98%, display human effector functions, have reduced immunogenicity, and may exhibit high affinity to human antigens. Another highly efficient means for generating recombinant antibodies is disclosed by <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Newman, Biotechnology, 10: 1455-1460 (1992 )</bibl>.
Human antibodies: By "human antibody" is meant an antibody containing entirely human light and heavy chain as well as constant regions, produced by any of the known standard methods. As an alternative to humanization, human antibodies can be generated. For example, it is now possible to produce transgenic animals (e.g., mice) that are capable, upon immunization, of producing a full repertoire of human antibodies in the absence of endogenous immunoglobulin production. For example, it has been described that the homozygous deletion of the antibody heavy-chain joining region PH) gene in chimeric and germ-line mutant mice results in complete inhibition of endogenous antibody production. Transfer of the human germ-line immunoglobulin gene array in such germ line mutant mice will result in the production of human antibodies after immunization. See, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Jakobovits et al., Proc. Mad. Acad. Sci. USA, 90:255 1 (1993 )</bibl>; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Jakobovits et al., Nature, 362:255-258 (1993 )</bibl>. Alternatively, phage display technology ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">McCafferty et al., Nature 348:552-553 (1990 )</bibl>) can be used to produce human antibodies and antibody fragments in vitro, from immunoglobulin variable (V) domain gene repertoires from donors. According to this technique, antibody V domain genes are cloned in-frame into either a major or minor coat protein gene of a filamentous bacteriophage, such as M13 or fd, and displayed as functional antibody fragments on the surface of the phage particle. Because the filamentous particle contains a single-stranded DNA copy of the phage genome, selections based on the functional properties of the antibody also result in selection of the gene encoding the antibody exhibiting those properties. Thus, the phage mimics some of the properties of the B cell. Phage display can be performed in a variety of formats; for their review see, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Johnson, Kevin S. and Chiswell, David J., Current Opinion in Structural Biology 3:564-57 1 (1993 )</bibl>. Human antibodies may also be generated by in vitro activated B cells or SCID mice with its immune system reconstituted with human cells. Once obtained a human antibody, its coding DNA sequences can be isolated, cloned and introduced in an appropriate expression system i.e. a cell line preferably from a mammal which subsequently express and liberate into culture media from which the antibody can be isolated.
Antibody fragments: An antibody fragment is a fragment of an antibody such as, for example, Fab, F(ab')2, Fab' and scFv. Various techniques have been developed for the production of antibody fragments. Traditionally, these fragments were derived via proteolytic digestion of intact antibodies but more recently these fragments can be produced directly by recombinant host cells. In other embodiments, the antibody of choice is a single chain Fv (scFv) fragment which additionally may be monospecific or bispecific. Papain digestion of antibodies produces two identical antigen-binding fragments, called "Fab" fragments, each with a single antigen-binding site, and a residual "Fc" fragment, which name reflects its ability to crystallize readily. Pepsin treatment yields an F(ab')2 fragment that has two antigen-binding sites and is still capable of cross-linking antigen. "Fv" is the minimum antibody fragment which contains a complete antigen-recognition and antigen-binding site. This region consists of a dimer of one heavy chain and one light chain variable domain in tight, non-covalent association. It is in this configuration that the three hypervariable regions of each variable domain interact to define an antigen-binding site on the surface of the VH-VL dimer. Collectively, the six hypervariable regions confer antigen-binding specificity to the antibody. However, even a single variable domain (or half of an Fv comprising only three hypervariable regions specific for an antigen) has the ability to recognize and bind antigen, although at a lower affinity than the entire binding site. The Fab fragment also contains the constant domain of the light chain and the first constant domain (CHI) of the heavy chain. Fab' fragments differ from Fab fragments by the addition of a few residues at the carboxy terminus of the heavy chain CHI domain including one or more cysteines from the antibody hinge region. Fab'-SH is the designation herein for Fab' in which the cysteine residue(s) of the constant domains bear at least one free thiol group. F(ab')Z antibody fragments originally were produced as pairs of Fab' fragments which have hinge cysteines between them. Other chemical couplings of antibody fragments are also known. "Single-chain Fv" or "scFv" antibody fragments comprise the VH and VL domains of an antibody, wherein these domains are present in a single polypeptide chain. Preferably, the Fv polypeptide further comprises a polypeptide linker between the VH and VL domains which enables the scFv to form the desired structure for antigen binding. For a review of scFv see <bibl type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Pluckthun in The Pharmacology of Monoclonal Antibodies, vol. 113, Rosenburg and Moore eds., Springer-Verlag, N.Y., pp. 269-315 (1994 )</bibl>. The term "diabodies" refers to small antibody fragments with two antigen-binding sites, which fragments comprise a heavy-chain variable domain (VH) connected to a light chain variable domain (VL) in the same polypeptide chain (VH-VL). By using a linker that is too short to allow pairing between the two domains on the same chain, the domains are forced to pair with the complementary domains of another chain and create two antigen-binding sites. Diabodies are described more fully in, for example, <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">EP 404,097</bibl> ; <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 93/11161</bibl> ; and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Hollinger et al., Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 90:6444-6448 (1993 )</bibl>.
Bispecific antibodies: Bispecific antibodies are antibodies that have binding specificities for at least two different epitopes. Methods for making bispecific antibodies are known in the art. Traditional production of full length bispecific antibodies is based on the coexpression of two immunoglobulin heavy chain-light chain pairs, where the two chains have different specificities ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Millstein et al., Nature, 305:537-539 (1983 )</bibl>). Because of the random assortment of immunoglobulin heavy and light chains, these hybridomas (quadromas) produce a potential mixture of 10 different antibody molecules, of which only one has the correct bispecific structure. Purification of the correct molecule, which is usually done by affinity chromatography steps, is rather cumbersome, and the product yields are low. Similar procedures are disclosed in <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO 93/08829</bibl> , and in <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Traunecker et al., EMBO J, 10:3655-3659 (1991 )</bibl>.</p><p>AMPA receptor-specific ribozymes</p><p>[0058]    Ribozyme molecules designed to catalytically cleave a target mRNA transcripts can also be used to prevent translation of AMPA receptor mRNAs. Accordingly, in another embodiment, the compositions of the invention comprise ribozymes specifically directed to the AMPA receptor mRNA. Ribozymes are enzymatic RNA molecules capable of catalyzing the specific cleavage of RNA. (For a review, see <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Rossi, Current Biology 4:469-471, 1994</bibl> ). The mechanism of ribozyme action involves sequence specific hybridization of the ribozyme molecule to complementary target RNA, followed by an endonucleolytic cleavage event. The composition of ribozyme molecules preferably includes one or more sequences complementary to a target mRNA, and the well known catalytic sequence responsible for mRNA cleavage or a functionally equivalent sequence (see, e.g., <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">U.S. Pat. No. 5,093,246</bibl> , incorporated herein by reference in its entirety).</p><p>[0059]    While ribozymes that cleave mRNA at site specific recognition sequences can be used to destroy target mRNAs, the use of hammerhead ribozymes is preferred. Hammerhead ribozymes cleave mRNAs at locations dictated by flanking regions that form complementary base pairs with the target mRNA. Preferably, the target mRNA has the following sequence of two bases: 5'-UG-3'. The construction and production of hammerhead ribozymes is well known in the art and is described more fully in <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Haseloff and Gerlach, Nature 334: 585-591, 1988</bibl> ; and see <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">PCT Appln. No. WO89/05852</bibl> , the contents of which are incorporated herein by reference. Hammerhead ribozyme sequences can be embedded in a stable RNA such as a transfer RNA (tRNA) to increase cleavage efficiency in vivo ( <bibl type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Perriman et al., Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 92: 6175-79, 1995</bibl> ; <bibl type="book" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">de Feyter, and Gaudron, Methods in Molecular Biology, Vol. 74, Chapter 43, "Expressing Ribozymes in Plants", edited by Turner, P. C, Humana Press Inc., Totowa, N.J .</bibl>). In particular, RNA polymerase III-mediated expression of tRNA fusion ribozymes are well known in the art (see, <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kawasaki et al., Nature 393: 284-9, 1998</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kuwabara et al., Nature Biotechnol. 16: 961-5, 1998</bibl> ; and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kuwabara et al., Mol. Cell. 2: 617-27, 1998</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Koseki et al., J Virol 73: 1868-77, 1999</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kuwabara et al., Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 96: 1886-91, 1999</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Tanabe et al., Nature 406: 473-4, 2000</bibl> ). There are typically a number of potential hammerhead ribozyme cleavage sites within a given target CDNA sequence. Preferably the ribozyme is engineered so that the cleavage recognition site is located near the 5' end of the target mRNA to increase efficiency and minimize the intracellular accumulation of non-functional mRNA transcripts. Furthermore, the use of any cleavage recognition site located in the target sequence encoding different portions of the C-terminal amino acid domains of, for example, long and short forms of target would allow the selective targeting of one or the other form of the target, and thus, have a selective effect on one form of the target gene product.</p><p>[0060]    Gene targeting ribozymes necessarily contain a hybridizing region complementary to two regions, each of at least 5 and preferably each 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19 or 20 contiguous nucleotides in length of a target mRNA, such as an mRNA of a sequence represented in the AMPA receptor genes. In addition, ribozymes possess highly specific endoribonuclease activity, which autocatalytically cleaves the target sense mRNA. The present invention extends to ribozymes which hybridize to a sense mRNA encoding a target gene such as a therapeutic drug target candidate gene, thereby hybridizing to the sense mRNA and cleaving it, such that it is no longer capable of being translated to synthesize a functional polypeptide product. </p><p>[0061]    The ribozymes used in the compositions of the present invention also include RNA endoribonucleases (hereinafter "Cech-type ribozymes") such as the one which occurs naturally in Tetrahymena thermophila (known as the IVS, or L-19 IVS RNA) and which has been extensively described by Thomas Cech and collaborators ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Zaug et al., Science 224:574-578, 1984</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Zaug et al., Science 231: 470-475, 1986</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Zaug et al., Nature 324: 429-433, 1986</bibl>; published  <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">International patent application No. WO88/04300</bibl>  by University Patents Inc.; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Been, et al., Cell 47: 207-216, 1986</bibl> ). The Cech-type ribozymes have an eight base pair active site which hybridizes to a target RNA sequence whereafter cleavage of the target RNA takes place. The invention encompasses those Cech-type ribozymes which target eight base-pair active site sequences that are present in a target gene or nucleic acid sequence.</p><p>[0062]    Ribozymes can be composed of modified oligonucleotides (e.g., for improved stability, targeting, etc.) and should be delivered to cells which express the target gene in vivo. A preferred method of delivery involves using a DNA construct "encoding" the ribozyme under the control of a strong constitutive pol III or pol II promoter, so that transfected cells will produce sufficient quantities of the ribozyme to destroy endogenous target messages and inhibit translation. Because ribozymes, unlike antisense molecules, are catalytic, a lower intracellular concentration is required for efficiency.</p><p>[0063]    In certain embodiments, a ribozyme may be designed by first identifying a sequence portion sufficient to cause effective knockdown by RNAi. The same sequence portion may then be incorporated into a ribozyme. In this aspect of the invention, the gene-targeting portions of the ribozyme or RNAi are substantially the same sequence of at least 5 and preferably 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19 or 20 or more contiguous nucleotides of a target nucleic acid, such as a nucleic acid of any of the human acid ceramidase or choline kinase sequences. In a long target RNA chain, significant numbers of target sites are not accessible to the ribozyme because they are hidden within secondary or tertiary structures ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Birikh et al., Eur J Biochem 245: 1-16, 1997</bibl> ). To overcome the problem of target RNA accessibility, computer generated predictions of secondary structure are typically used to identify targets that are most likely to be single-stranded or have an "open" configuration (see <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Jaeger et al., Methods Enzymol 183: 281-306, 1989</bibl> ). Other approaches utilize a systematic approach to predicting secondary structure which involves assessing a huge number of candidate hybridizing oligonucleotides molecules (see <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Milner et al., Nat Biotechnol 15: 537-41, 1997</bibl> ; and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Patzel and Sczakiel, Nat Biotechnol 16: 64-8, 1998</bibl> ). Additionally, <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">U.S. Pat. No. 6,251,588</bibl> , the contents of which are hereby incorporated herein, describes methods for evaluating oligonucleotide probe sequences so as to predict the potential for hybridization to a target nucleic acid sequence. The method of the invention provides for the use of such methods to select preferred segments of a target mRNA sequence that are predicted to be single-stranded and, further, for the opportunistic utilization of the same or substantially identical target mRNA sequence, preferably comprising about 10-20 consecutive nucleotides of the target mRNA, in the design of both the RNAi oligonucleotides and ribozymes of the invention.</p><p>AMPA receptor-specific RNA interference (RNAi)</p><p>[0064]    In another embodiment, the inhibitors of the AMPA receptor that form part of the compositions of the invention are RNAi which are capable of knocking down the expression of an AMPA receptor or any component gene necessary for an AMPA receptor function. RNAi is a process of sequence-specific post-transcriptional gene repression which can occur in eukaryotic cells. In general, this process involves degradation of an mRNA of a particular sequence induced by double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) that is homologous to that sequence. For example, the expression of a long dsRNA corresponding to the sequence of a particular single-stranded mRNA (ss mRNA) will labilize that message, thereby "interfering" with expression of the corresponding gene. Accordingly, any selected gene may be repressed by introducing a dsRNA which corresponds to all or a substantial part of the mRNA for that gene. It appears that when a long dsRNA is expressed, it is initially processed by a ribonuclease III into shorter dsRNA oligonucleotides of as few as 21 to 22 base pairs in length. Accordingly, RNAi may be effected by introduction or expression of relatively short homologous dsRNAs. Indeed, the use of relatively short homologous dsRNAs may have certain advantages as discussed below.</p><p>[0065]    The double stranded oligonucleotides used to effect RNAi are preferably less than 30 base pairs in length and, more preferably, comprise about 25, 24, 23, 22, 21, 20, 19, 18 or 17 base pairs of ribonucleic acid. Optionally the dsRNA oligonucleotides of the invention may include 3' overhang ends. Exemplary 2-nucleotide 3' overhangs may be composed of ribonucleotide residues of any type and may even be composed of 2'-deoxythymidine residues, which lowers the cost of RNA synthesis and may enhance nuclease resistance of siRNAs in the cell culture medium and within transfected cells (see <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Elbashir et al., Nature 411: 494-8, 2001</bibl> ). Longer dsRNAs of 50, 75, 100 or even 500 base pairs or more may also be utilized in certain embodiments of the invention. Exemplary concentrations of dsRNAs for effecting RNAi are about 0.05 nM, 0.1 nM, 0.5 nM, 1.0 nM, 1.5 nM, 25 nM or 100 nM, although other concentrations may be utilized depending upon the nature of the cells treated, the gene target and other factors readily discernable to the skilled artisan. Exemplary dsRNAs may be synthesized chemically or produced in vitro or in vivo using appropriate expression vectors. Exemplary synthetic RNAs include 21 nucleotide RNAs chemically synthesized using methods known in the art (e.g., Expedite RNA phosphoramidites and thymidine phosphoramidite (Proligo, Germany). Synthetic oligonucleotides are preferably deprotected and gel-purified using methods known in the art (see, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Elbashir et al., Genes Dev. 15: 188-200, 2001</bibl> ). Longer RNAs may be transcribed from promoters, such as T7 RNA polymerase promoters, known in the art. A single RNA target, placed in both possible orientations downstream of an in vitro promoter, will transcribe both strands of the target to create a dsRNA oligonucleotide of the desired target sequence. Any of the above RNA species will be designed to include a portion of nucleic acid sequence represented in a target nucleic acid, such as, for example, a nucleic acid that hybridizes, under stringent and/or physiological conditions, to the polynucleotide encoding human a AMPA receptor.</p><p>[0066]    The specific sequence utilized in design of the oligonucleotides may be any contiguous sequence of nucleotides contained within the expressed gene message of the target. Programs and algorithms, known in the art, may be used to select appropriate target sequences. In addition, optimal sequences may be selected utilizing programs designed to predict the secondary structure of a specified single stranded nucleic acid sequence and allowing selection of those sequences likely to occur in exposed single stranded regions of a folded mRNA. Methods and compositions for designing appropriate oligonucleotides may be found, for example, in <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">U.S. Pat. No. 6,251,588</bibl> , the contents of which are incorporated herein by reference. Messenger RNA (mRNA) is generally thought of as a linear molecule which contains the information for directing protein synthesis within the sequence of ribonucleotides, however studies have revealed a number of secondary and tertiary structures that exist in most mRNAs. Secondary structure elements in RNA are formed largely by Watson-Crick type interactions between different regions of the same RNA molecule. Important secondary structural elements include intramolecular double stranded regions, hairpin loops, bulges in duplex RNA and internal loops. Tertiary structural elements are formed when secondary structural elements come in contact with each other or with single stranded regions to produce a more complex three dimensional structure. A number of researchers have measured the binding energies of a large number of RNA duplex structures and have derived a set of rules which can be used to predict the secondary structure of RNA (see, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Jaeger et al., Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 86: 7706, 1989</bibl> ; and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Turner et al., Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biophys. Chem. 17:167, 1988</bibl> ). The rules are useful in identification of RNA structural elements and, in particular, for identifying single stranded RNA regions which may represent preferred segments of the mRNA to target for silencing RNAi, ribozyme or antisense technologies. Accordingly, preferred segments of the mRNA target can be identified for design of the RNAi mediating dsRNA oligonucleotides as well as for design of appropriate ribozyme and hammerhead ribozyme compositions of the invention.</p><p>[0067]    Several different types of molecules have been used effectively in the RNAi technology. Small interfering RNA (siRNA), sometimes known as short interfering RNA or silencing RNA, are a class of 20-25 nucleotide-long double-stranded RNA molecules that play a variety of roles in biology. Most notably, siRNA is involved in the RNA interference (RNAi) pathway where the siRNA interferes with the expression of a specific gene. In addition to their role in the RNAi pathway, siRNAs also act in RNAi-related pathways, e.g., as an antiviral mechanism or in shaping the chromatin structure of a genome. Synthetic siRNAs have been shown to be able to induce RNAi in mammalian cells. This discovery led to a surge in the use of siRNA/RNAi for biomedical research and drug development.</p><p>[0068]    MicroRNA (miRNA) are a related class of gene regulatory small RNAs, typically 21-23 nt in length. They typically differ from siRNA because they are processed from single stranded RNA precursors and show only partially complementary to mRNA targets. Initial studies have indicated that miRNAs regulate gene expression post-transcriptionally at the level of translational inhibition at P-Bodies in the cytoplasm. However, miRNAs may also guide mRNA cleavage similar to siRNAs. This is often the case in plants where the target sites are typically highly complementary to the miRNA. While target sites in plant mRNAs can be found in the 5'UTR, open-reading frames and 3'UTR, in animals, it is the 3' UTR that is the main target. miRNAs are first transcribed as part of a primary microRNA (pri-miRNA). This is then processed by the Drosha with the help of Pasha/DGCR8 (=Microprocessor complex) into pre-miRNAs. The ca. 75 nt pre-miRNA is then exported to the cytoplasm by exportin-5, where it is then diced into 21-23 nt siRNA-like molecules by Dicer. In some cases, multiple miRNAs can be found on the pri-miRNA.</p><p>[0069]    Short hairpin RNA (shRNA) is yet another type of RNA that may be used to effect RNAi. It is a sequence of RNA that makes a tight hairpin turn that can be used to silence gene expression. shRNA is transcribed by RNA polymerase III.</p><p>[0070]    Currently, short-interfering RNAs (siRNAs) and short-hairpin RNAs (shRNAs) are being extensively used to silence various genes to silence functions carried out by the genes. It is becoming easier to harness RNAi to silence specific genes, owing to the development of libraries of readymade shRNA and siRNA gene-silencing constructs by using a variety of sources. For example, RNAi Codex, which consists of a database of shRNA related information and an associated website, has been developed as a portal for publicly available shRNA resources and is accessible at http://codex.cshl.org. RNAi Codex currently holds data from the Hannon-Elledge shRNA library and allows the use of biologist-friendly gene names to access information on shRNA constructs that can silence the gene of interest. It is designed to hold user-contributed annotations and publications for each construct, as and when such data become available. <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Olson et al. (Nucleic Acids Res. 34(Database issue): D153-D157, 2006</bibl> , incorporated by reference) have provided detailed descriptions about features of RNAi Codex, and have explained the use of the tool. All these information may be used to help design the various siRNA or shRNA targeting AMPA receptor or other proteins of interest.
Illustrative, non-limitative, examples of interfering RNA specific for the sequence of an AMPA receptor include those described by <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Passafaro M, et al. Nature. 2003 424(6949):677-81</bibl> . </p><p>GluR2 siRNA1:</p><p>[0071]    
 </p><p>GluR2 siRNA2:</p><p>[0072]    
 </p><p>AMPA receptor specific-inhibiting peptides</p><p>[0073]    An "AMPA receptor specific-inhibiting peptide" as used herein, relates to a peptide that biologically mimics regions of the protein sequence of the AMPA receptor that are involve in the AMPA receptor activity and thus they would inhibit the physiological activity of the receptor.</p><p>[0074]    The screening or design of an AMPA receptor specific-inhibiting peptide can be done as described in <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Olson, G.L et al (J. Med. Chem., 36, 3039-3049, 1993 )</bibl> or in <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gillespie, P.et al. (Biopolymers, 43:191-217 1997 )</bibl>.</p><p>[0075]    Illustrative, non-limitative, examples of inhibiting peptides specific for an AMPA receptor include: 
GluR1(Ser&lt;831&gt;) rat: LIPQQ(pS)INEAIK(SEQ ID NO:26)
GluR1(Ser&lt;831&gt;) rat2 : LIPQQSINEAIK(SEQ ID NO: 27)
GluR4 rat: KHTGTAIRQSSGLAVIASDLP (SEQ ID NO: 28)</p><p>AMPA receptor-specific antisense nucleic acids</p><p>[0076]    In a further embodiment, the invention relates to the use of the isolated "antisense" nucleic acids to inhibit expression, e.g., by inhibiting transcription and/or translation of AMPA receptors nucleic acids. The antisense nucleic acids may bind to the potential drug target by conventional base pair complementarity, or, for example, in the case of binding to DNA duplexes, through specific interactions in the major groove of the double helix. In general, these methods refer to the range of techniques generally employed in the art, and include any methods that rely on specific binding to oligonucleotide sequences.</p><p>[0077]    An antisense construct of the present invention can be delivered, for example, as an expression plasmid which, when transcribed in the cell, produces RNA which is complementary to at least a unique portion of the cellular mRNA which encodes a AMPA receptor polypeptide. Alternatively, the antisense construct is an oligonucleotide probe, which is generated ex vivo and which, when introduced into the cell causes inhibition of expression by hybridizing with the mRNA and/or genomic sequences of a target nucleic acid. Such oligonucleotide probes are preferably modified oligonucleotides, which are resistant to endogenous nucleases, e.g., exonucleases and/or endonucleases, and are therefore stable in vivo. Exemplary nucleic acid molecules for use as antisense oligonucleotides are phosphoramidate, phosphothioate and methylphosphonate analogs of DNA (see also <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">U.S. Pat. Nos. 5,176,996 ; 5,264,564 ; and 5,256,775</bibl> ). Additionally, general approaches to constructing oligomers useful in antisense therapy have been reviewed, for example, by <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Van der Krol et al., BioTechniques 6: 958-976, 1988</bibl> ; and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Stein et al., Cancer Res 48: 2659-2668, 1988</bibl> .</p><p>[0078]    With respect to antisense DNA, oligodeoxyribonucleotides derived from the translation initiation site, e.g., between the -10 and +10 regions of the target gene, are preferred. Antisense approaches involve the design of oligonucleotides (either DNA or RNA) that are complementary to mRNA encoding the target polypeptide. The antisense oligonucleotides will bind to the mRNA transcripts and prevent translation. Absolute complementarity, although preferred, is not required. In the case of double-stranded antisense nucleic acids, a single strand of the duplex DNA may thus be tested, or triplex formation may be assayed. The ability to hybridize will depend on both the degree of complementarity and the length of the antisense nucleic acid. Generally, the longer the hybridizing nucleic acid, the more base mismatches with an RNA it may contain and still form a stable duplex (or triplex, as the case may be). One skilled in the art can ascertain a tolerable degree of mismatch by use of standard procedures to determine the melting point of the hybridized complex.</p><p>[0079]    Oligonucleotides that are complementary to the 5' end of the mRNA, e.g., the 5' untranslated sequence up to and including the AUG initiation codon, should work most efficiently at inhibiting translation. However, sequences complementary to the 3' untranslated sequences of mRNAs have recently been shown to be effective at inhibiting translation of mRNAs as well ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wagner, Nature 372: 333, 1994</bibl> ). Therefore, oligonucleotides complementary to either the 5' or 3' untranslated, non-coding regions of a gene could be used in an antisense approach to inhibit translation of that mRNA. Oligonucleotides complementary to the 5' untranslated region of the mRNA should include the complement of the AUG start codon. Antisense oligonucleotides complementary to mRNA coding regions are less efficient inhibitors of translation but could also be used in accordance with the invention. Whether designed to hybridize to the 5', 3' or coding region of mRNA, antisense nucleic acids should be at least six nucleotides in length, and are preferably less that about 100 and more preferably less than about 50, 25, 17 or 10 nucleotides in length.</p><p>[0080]    It is preferred that in vitro studies are first performed to quantitate the ability of the antisense oligonucleotide to inhibit gene expression. It is preferred that these studies utilize controls that distinguish between antisense gene inhibition and nonspecific biological effects of oligonucleotides. It is also preferred that these studies compare levels of the target RNA or protein with that of an internal control RNA or protein. Results obtained using the antisense oligonucleotide may be compared with those obtained using a control oligonucleotide. It is preferred that the control oligonucleotide is of approximately the same length as the test oligonucleotide and that the nucleotide sequence of the oligonucleotide differs from the antisense sequence no more than is necessary to prevent specific hybridization to the target sequence.</p><p>[0081]    The antisense oligonucleotides can be DNA or RNA or chimeric mixtures or derivatives or modified versions thereof, single-stranded or double-stranded. The oligonucleotide can be modified at the base moiety, sugar moiety, or phosphate backbone, for example, to improve stability of the molecule, hybridization, etc. The oligonucleotide may include other appended groups such as peptides (e.g., for targeting host cell receptors), or agents facilitating transport across the cell membrane (see, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Letsinger et al., Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 86: 6553-6556, 1989</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Lemaitre et al., Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 84: 648-652, 1987</bibl> ; <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">PCT Publication No. WO88/09810</bibl> ) or the blood-brain barrier (see, e.g., <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO89/10134</bibl> ), hybridization-triggered cleavage agents (see, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Krol et al., BioTechniques 6: 958-976, 1988</bibl> ) or intercalating agents (see, e.g., <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Zon, Pharm. Res. 5: 539-549, 1988</bibl> ). To this end, the oligonucleotide may be conjugated to another molecule, e.g., a peptide, hybridization triggered cross-linking agent, transport agent, hybridization-triggered cleavage agent, etc.</p><p>[0082]    The antisense oligonucleotide may comprise at least one modified base moiety which is selected from the group including but not limited to 5-fluorouracil, 5-bromouracil, 5-chlorouracil, 5-iodouracil, hypoxanthine, xantine, 4-acetylcytosine, 5-(carboxyhydroxytiethyl) uracil, 5-carboxymethylaminomethyl-2-thiouridine, 5-carboxymethylaminomethyluracil, dihydrouracil, beta-D-galactosylqueosine, inosine, N6-isopentenyladenine, 1-methylguanine, 1-methylinosine, 2,2-dimethylguanine, 2-methyladenine, 2-methylguanine, 3-methylcytosine, 5-methylcytosine, N6-adenine, 7-methylguanine, 5-methylaminomethyluracil, 5-methoxyaminomethyl-2-thiouracil, beta-D-mannosylqueosine, 5'-methoxycarboxymethyluracil, 5-methoxyuracil, 2-methylthio-N6-isopentenyladenine, uracil-5-oxyacetic acid (v), wybutoxosine, pseudouracil, queosine, 2-thiocytosine, 5-methyl-2-thiouracil, 2-thiouracil, 4-thiouracil, 5-methyluracil, uracil-5-oxyacetic acid methylester, uracil-5-oxyacetic acid (v), 5-methyl-2-thiouracil, 3-(3-amino-3-N-2-carboxypropyl) uracil, (acp3)w, and 2,6-diaminopurine.</p><p>[0083]    The antisense oligonucleotide may also comprise at least one modified sugar moiety selected from the group including but not limited to arabinose, 2-fluoroarabinose, xylulose, and hexose. The antisense oligonucleotide can also contain a neutral peptide-like backbone. Such molecules are termned peptide nucleic acid (PNA)-oligomers and are described, e.g., in <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Perry-O'Keefe et al., Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 93: 14670, 1996</bibl> , and in <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Eglom et al., Nature 365: 566, 1993</bibl> . One advantage of PNA oligomers is their capability to bind to complementary DNA essentially independently from the ionic strength of the medium due to the neutral backbone of the DNA. In yet another embodiment, the antisense oligonucleotide comprises at least one modified phosphate backbone selected from the group consisting of a phosphorothioate, a phosphorodithioate, a phosphoramidothioate, a phosphoramidate, a phosphordiamidate, a methylphosphonate, an alkyl phosphotriester, and a formacetal or analog thereof.</p><p>[0084]    In yet a further embodiment, the antisense oligonucleotide is an alpha-anomeric oligonucleotide. An alpha-anomeric oligonucleotide forms specific double-stranded hybrids with complementary RNA in which, contrary to the usual antiparallel orientation, the strands run parallel to each other ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gautier et al., Nucl. Acids Res. 15: 6625-6641, 1987</bibl> ). The oligonucleotide is a 2'-0-methylribonucleotide ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Inoue et al., Nucl. Acids Res. 15: 6131-6148, 1987</bibl> ), or a chimeric RNA-DNA analogue ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Inoue et al., FEBS Lett. 215: 327-330, 1987</bibl> ).</p><p>[0085]    While antisense nucleotides complementary to the coding region of a target mRNA sequence can be used, those complementary to the transcribed untranslated region may also be used. </p><p>[0086]    In certain instances, it may be difficult to achieve intracellular concentrations of the antisense sufficient to suppress translation on endogenous mRNAs. Therefore a preferred approach utilizes a recombinant DNA construct in which the antisense oligonucleotide is placed under the control of a strong pol III or pol II promoter. The use of such a construct to transfect target cells will result in the transcription of sufficient amounts of single stranded RNAs that will form complementary base pairs with the endogenous potential drug target transcripts and thereby prevent translation. For example, a vector can be introduced such that it is taken up by a cell and directs the transcription of an antisense RNA. Such a vector can remain episomal or become chromosomally integrated, as long as it can be transcribed to produce the desired antisense RNA. Such vectors can be constructed by recombinant DNA technology methods standard in the art. Vectors can be plasmid, viral, or others known in the art, used for replication and expression in mammalian cells. Expression of the sequence encoding the antisense RNA can be by any promoter known in the art to act in mammalian, preferably human cells. Such promoters can be inducible or constitutive. Such promoters include but are not limited to: the SV40 early promoter region ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bernoist and Chambon, Nature 290: 304-310, 1981</bibl> ), the promoter contained in the 3' long terminal repeat of Rous sarcoma virus ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Yamamoto et al., Cell 22: 787-797, 1980</bibl> ), the herpes thymidine kinase promoter ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Wagner et al., Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 78: 1441-1445, 1981</bibl> ), the regulatory sequences of the metallothionein gene ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Brinster et al, Nature 296: 39-42, 1982</bibl> ), etc. Any type of plasmid, cosmid, YAC or viral vector can be used to prepare the recombinant DNA construct, which can be introduced directly into the tissue site.</p><p>[0087]    Alternatively, target gene expression can be reduced by targeting deoxyribonucleotide sequences complementary to the regulatory region of the gene (i.e., the promoter and/or enhancers) to form triple helical structures that prevent transcription of the gene in target cells in the body (see generally, <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Helene, Anticancer Drug Des. 6(6): 569-84, 1991</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Helene et al., Ann. N.Y. Acad. Sci., 660: 27-36, 1992</bibl> ; and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Maher, Bioassays 14(12): 807-15, 1992</bibl> ).</p><p>[0088]    Nucleic acid molecules to be used in triple helix formation for the inhibition of transcription are preferably single stranded and composed of deoxyribonucleotides. The base composition of these oligonucleotides should promote triple helix formation via Hoogsteen base pairing rules, which generally require sizable stretches of either purines or pyrimidines to be present on one strand of a duplex. Nucleotide sequences may be pyrimidine-based, which will result in TAT and CGC triplets across the three associated strands of the resulting triple helix. The pyrimidine-rich molecules provide base complementarity to a purine-rich region of a single strand of the duplex in a parallel orientation to that strand. In addition, nucleic acid molecules may be chosen that are purine-rich, for example, containing a stretch of G residues. These molecules will form a triple helix with a DNA duplex that is rich in GC pairs, in which the majority of the purine residues are located on a single strand of the targeted duplex, resulting in CGC triplets across the three strands in the triplex.</p><p>[0089]    Alternatively, the potential target sequences that can be targeted for triple helix formation may be increased by creating a so called "switchback" nucleic acid molecule. Switchback molecules are synthesized in an alternating 5'-3',3'-5' manner, such that they base pair with first one strand of a duplex and then the other, eliminating the necessity for a sizable stretch of either purines or pyrimidines to be present on one strand of a duplex.</p><p>[0090]    In certain embodiments, the antisense oligonucleotides are morpholino antisenses. Morpholinos are synthetic molecules which are the product of a redesign of natural nucleic acid structure. Usually 25 bases in length, they bind to complementary sequences of RNA by standard nucleic acid base-pairing. Structurally, the difference between morpholinos and DNA is that while morpholinos have standard nucleic acid bases, those bases are bound to morpholine rings instead of deoxyribose rings, and linked through phosphorodiamidate groups instead of phosphates. Replacement of anionic phosphates with the uncharged phosphorodiamidate groups eliminates ionization in the usual physiological pH range, so morpholinos in organisms or cells are uncharged molecules. Morpholinos are not chimeric oligos; the entire backbone of a morpholino is made from these modified subunits. Morpholinos are most commonly used as single-stranded oligos, though heteroduplexes of a morpholino strand and a complementary DNA strand may be used in combination with cationic cytosolic delivery reagents.</p><p>[0091]    Unlike many antisense structural types (e.g., phosphorothioates), morpholinos do not degrade their target RNA molecules. Instead, morpholinos act by "steric blocking," binding to a target sequence within an RNA and simply getting in the way of molecules which might otherwise interact with the RNA. Morpholino oligos are often used to investigate the role of a specific mRNA transcript in an embryo, such as eggs or embryos of zebrafish, African clawed frog (Xenopus), chick, and sea urchin, producing morphant embryos. With appropriate cytosolic delivery systems, morpholinos are effective in cell culture.</p><p>[0092]    Bound to the 5'-untranslated region of messenger RNA (mRNA), morpholinos can interfere with progression of the ribosomal initiation complex from the 5' cap to the start codon. This prevents translation of the coding region of the targeted transcript (called "knocking down" gene expression). Morpholinos provide a convenient means of knocking down expression of the protein and learning how that knockdown changes the cells or organism. Some morpholinos knock down expression so effectively that after degradation of preexisting proteins the targeted proteins become undetectable by Western blot.</p><p>[0093]    Morpholinos can also interfere with pre-mRNA processing steps, usually by preventing the splice-directing snRNP complexes from binding to their targets at the borders of introns on a strand of pre-RNA. Preventing U1 (at the donor site) or U2/U5 (at the polypyrimidine moiety and acceptor site) from binding can cause modified splicing, commonly leading to exclusions of exons from the mature mRNA. Targeting some splice targets results in intron inclusions, while activation of cryptic splice sites can lead to partial inclusions or exclusions. Targets of U11/U12 snRNPs can also be blocked. Splice modification can be conveniently assayed by reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and is seen as a band shift after gel electrophoresis of RT-PCR products.</p><p>[0094]    Morpholinos have also been used to block miRNA activity, ribozyme activity, intronic splice silencers, and splice enhancers. U2 and U12 snRNP functions have been inhibited by Morpholinos. Morpholinos targeted to "slippery" mRNA sequences within protein coding regions can induce translational frameshifts. Activities of Morpholinos against this variety of targets suggest that Morpholinos can be used as a general-purpose tool for blocking interactions of proteins or nucleic acids with mRNA.</p><p>[0095]    A person skilled in the art would understand that the AMPA receptor can be formed by homomultimeric assemblies by using the same subunits (e.g. only GluR1 (GRIA1), GluR2 (GRIA2), GluR3 (GRIA3),or GluR4 subunits in one receptor ), or in the form of heteromultimeric assemblies (e.g. with both GluR1 (GRIA1) or GluR2 (GRIA2)subunits in one receptor). Thus the inhibition of the AMPA receptor by the AMPA receptor inhibitor is going to depend on the multimeric assembly of the hemichannel.</p><p>[0096]    Thus, the AMPA receptor inhibitors can be combinations of specific inhibitors for the different subunits.</p><p>[0097]    In an embodiment the AMPA receptor is selected from a homomultimeric hemichannel form by GluR1 (GRIA1), GluR2 (GRIA2), GluR3 (GRIA3), or GluR4 subunits. In another embodiment, the AMPA receptor is selected from heteromultimeric assemblies of GluR1 (GRIA1), GluR2 (GRIA2), GluR3 (GRIA3), or GluR4. In a preferred embodiment, the AMPA receptor is a heterotetrameric, consisting of symmetric 'dimer of dimers' of GluR2 and either GluR1, GluR3 or GluR4.</p><p>[0098]    In a particular embodiment the AMPA receptor inhibitor is selected from the compounds of Table I, including combinations thereof. In a preferred embodiment the AMPA receptor is selected from the group consisting of CFM-2, CNQX, CNQX disodium salt, CP 465022 hydrochloride, DNQX, DNQX disodium salt, Evans Blue tetrasodium salt, GYKI 47261 dihydrochloride, NBQX, Philanthotoxin 74 or PhTx-74, SYM 2206, UBP 282 or 3-CBW, YM 90K hydrochloride, ZK 200775 (MPQX).</p><p>[0099]    Effective amounts of the AMPA receptor inhibitor will depend upon the mode of administration, frequency of administration, nature of the treatment, age and condition of the individual to be treated, and the type of pharmaceutical composition used to deliver the compound into a living system. Effective levels of AMPA receptor inhibitor may range from 50 nM to 5 [micro]M (given to experimental animals as 20-30 mg/kg twice daily for ten days), depending upon the compound, system, experimental and clinical endpoints, and toxicity thresholds. While individual doses vary, optimal ranges of effective amounts may be determined by one of ordinary skill in the art. For AMPA receptor inhibitors that are involved in clinical trials for other indications, the safe and effective dosages identified in such trials can be considered when selecting dosages for treatments according to the present invention.</p><p>[0100]    The AMPA receptor inhibitor used according to the methods of the present invention can be administered alone or as a pharmaceutical composition, which includes the compound(s) and a pharmaceutically-acceptable carrier. The AMPA receptor blockers are typically provided as a pharmaceutical composition. The pharmaceutical composition can also include suitable excipients, or stabilizers, and can be in solid or liquid form such as, tablets, capsules, powders, solutions, suspensions, or emulsions. Typically, the composition will contain from about 0.01 to 99 percent, preferably from about 5 to 95 percent of active compound(s), together with the carrier.</p><p>[0101]    The AMPA receptor inhibitor, when combined with pharmaceutically or physiologically acceptable carriers, excipients, or stabilizers, whether in solid or liquid form such as, tablets, capsules, powders, solutions, suspensions, or emulsions, can be administered orally, parenterally, subcutaneously, intravenously, intramuscularly, intraperitoneally, by intranasal instillation, by implantation, by intracavitary or intravesical instillation, intraocularly, intraarterially, intralesionally, transdermally, or by application to mucous membranes, such as, that of the nose, throat, and bronchial tubes (i.e., inhalation).</p><p>[0102]    For most therapeutic purposes, the AMPA receptor inhibitor can be administered orally as a solid or as a solution or suspension in liquid form, via injection as a solution or suspension in liquid form, or via inhalation of a nebulized solution or suspension. The solid unit dosage forms can be of the conventional type. The solid form can be a capsule, such as an ordinary gelatin type containing the compounds of the present invention and a carrier, for example, lubricants and inert fillers such as, lactose, sucrose, or cornstarch. In another embodiment, these compounds are tableted with conventional tablet bases such as lactose, sucrose, or cornstarch in combination with binders like acacia, cornstarch, or gelatin, disintegrating agents, such as cornstarch, potato starch, or alginic acid, and a lubricant, like stearic acid or magnesium stearate.</p><p>[0103]    For injectable dosages, solutions or suspensions of these materials can be prepared in a physiologically acceptable diluent with a pharmaceutical carrier. Such carriers include sterile liquids, such as water and oils, with or without the addition of a surfactant and other pharmaceutically and physiologically acceptable carrier, including adjuvants, excipients or stabilizers. Illustrative oils are those of petroleum, animal, vegetable, or synthetic origin, for example, peanut oil, soybean oil, or mineral oil. In general, water, saline, aqueous dextrose, and related sugar solution, and glycols, such as propylene glycol or polyethylene glycol, are preferred liquid carriers, particularly for injectable solutions.</p><p>[0104]    For use as aerosols, the compound in solution or suspension may be packaged in a pressurized aerosol container together with suitable propellants, for example, hydrocarbon propellants like propane, butane, or isobutane with conventional adjuvants. The materials of the present invention also may be administered in a non-pressurized form such as in a nebulizer or atomizer.</p><p>[0105]    For transdermal routes, the compound is present in a carrier which forms a composition in the form of a cream, lotion, solution, and/or emulsion. The composition can be included in a transdermal patch of the matrix or reservoir type as are conventional in the art for this purpose.</p><p>[0106]    It is contemplated the use of combinations of the AMPA receptor inhibitors described in Table I.</p><p>[0107]    It is also contemplated that administration of the AMPA receptor inhibitor can be carried out in combination with other suitable therapeutic treatments which are useful for treating a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins, thus, in other embodiment, the AMPA receptor inhibitor can be combined with other drugs for the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins such as acetylcholinesterase inhibitors, memantine, donepezil, rivastigmine, galantamine, etc.</p><p>[0108]    In a preferred embodiment the drug for the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins is a NMDA receptor inhibitor.</p><p>[0109]    Table II include illustrative, non-limitative, NMDA receptor inhibitors. 
Table II
&lt;tb&gt;NMDA receptor inhibitors
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;NMDA receptor inhibitor
&lt;tb&gt;1&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;1-Aminocyclobutane-1-carboxylic acid 
&lt;tb&gt;2&lt;sep&gt;D-AP5 and DL-AP5 (2-APV, D-APV)
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 </p><p>&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;D-(-)-2-Amino-5-phosphonopentanoic acid
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;DL-2-Amino-5-phosphonopentanoic acid
&lt;tb&gt;3&lt;sep&gt;L-AP5
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;L-(+)-2-Amino-5-phosphonopentanoic acid
&lt;tb&gt;4&lt;sep&gt;D-AP7 and D1-AP7
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 </p><p>&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;D-(-)-2-Amino-7-phosphonoheptanoic acid
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;DL-2-Amino-7-phosphonoheptanoic acid
&lt;tb&gt;5&lt;sep&gt;Arcaine sulfate
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;N,N'-1,4-Butanediylbisguanidine sulfate 
&lt;tb&gt;6&lt;sep&gt;(R)-4-Carboxyphenylglycine
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(R)-4CPG
&lt;tb&gt;7&lt;sep&gt;CGP 37849
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(E)-(+-)-2-Ammo-4-methyl-5-phosphono-3-pentenoic acid
&lt;tb&gt;8&lt;sep&gt;CGP 39551
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(E)-(+-)-2-Ammo-4-methyl-5-phosphono-3-pentenoic acid ethyl ester
&lt;tb&gt;9&lt;sep&gt;CGP 78608 hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;[(1S)-1-[[(7-Bromo-1,2,3,4-tetrahydro-2,3-dioxo-5-quino xafinyl)methyl]amino]ethyl]phosphonic acid hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;10&lt;sep&gt;CGS 19755
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;cis-4-[Phosphomethyl]-piperidine-2-carboxylic acid
&lt;tb&gt;11&lt;sep&gt;7-Chlorokynurenic acid
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;7-Chloro-4-hydroxyquinoline-2-carboxylic acid 
&lt;tb&gt;12&lt;sep&gt;(2R,3S)-Chlorpheg
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(2R,3 S)-b-p-Chlorophenylglutamic acid
&lt;tb&gt;13&lt;sep&gt;CNQX
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;6-Cyano-7-nitroquinoxafine-2,3-dione
&lt;tb&gt;14&lt;sep&gt;Co 101244 hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;1-[2-(4-Hydroxyphenoxy)ethyl]-4-[(4-methylphenyl)methyl]-4-piperidinol hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;15&lt;sep&gt;(R)-CPP and (RS)-CPP
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;3-((R)-2-Carboxypiperazin-4-yl)-propyl-1-phosphonic acid
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(RS)-3-(2-Carboxypiperazin-4-yl)-propyl-1-phosphonic acid
&lt;tb&gt;16&lt;sep&gt;D-CPP-ene
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;D-4-[(2E)-3-Phosphono-2-propenyl]-2-piperazinecarboxyli c acid 
&lt;tb&gt;17&lt;sep&gt;Dextromethorphan hydrobromide
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(9a, 13a, 14a)-3 -Methoxy-17-methylmorphinan hydrobromide
&lt;tb&gt;18&lt;sep&gt;5,7-Dichlorokynurenic acid
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;5,7-Dichloro-4-hydroxyquinoline-2-carboxylic acid
&lt;tb&gt;19&lt;sep&gt;(+-)-1-(1,2-Diphenylethyl)piperidine maleate
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;20&lt;sep&gt;Eliprodil
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;a-(4-Chlorophenyl)-4-[(4-fluorophenyl)methyl]-1-piperid ineethanol
&lt;tb&gt;21&lt;sep&gt;Felbamate
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;2-Phenyl-1,3-propanedioldicarbamate
&lt;tb&gt;22&lt;sep&gt;Flupirtine maleate
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;N-[2-Amino-6-[[4-fluorophenyl)methyl]amino]-3-pyridinyl]carbamic acid ethyl ester maleate 
&lt;tb&gt;23&lt;sep&gt;Gavestinel
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;4,6-Dichloro-3-[(1E)-3-oxo-3-(phenylamino)-1-propenyl]-1H-indole-2-carboxylic acid sodium salt
&lt;tb&gt;24&lt;sep&gt;(S)-(-)-HA-966
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;S)-(-)-3-Amino-1-hydroxypyrrolidin-2-one
&lt;tb&gt;25&lt;sep&gt;HU 211
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(6aS,10aS)-3-(1,1 -Dimethylheptyl)-6a,77,10, 10a-tetrahyd ro-1-hydroxy-6,6-dimethyl-6H-dibenzo[b,d]pyran-9-methan ol
&lt;tb&gt;26&lt;sep&gt;N-(4-Hydroxyphenylacetyl)spermine
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;N-(N-(4-Hydroxyphenylacetyl)-3-aminopropyl)-(N'-3-aminopropyl)-1,4-butanediamine
&lt;tb&gt;27&lt;sep&gt;Ifenprodil hemitartrate and threo Ifenprodil hemitartrate
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(1R*,2S*)-erythro-2-(4-Benzylpiperidino)-1-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1-propanol hemitartrate
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(1S*,2S*)-threo-2-(4-Benzylpiperidino)-1-(4-hydroxyphen yl)-1-propanol hemitartrate
&lt;tb&gt;28&lt;sep&gt;Ketamine hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;2-(2-Chlorophenyl)-2-(methylamino)cyclohexanone hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;29&lt;sep&gt;L-689,560
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;trans-2-Carboxy-5,7-dichloro-4-phenylaminocarbonylamino-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroquinoline
&lt;tb&gt;30&lt;sep&gt;L-701,252
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;7-Chloro-3-(cyclopropylcarbonyl)-4-hydroxy-2(1H)-quinolinone
&lt;tb&gt;31&lt;sep&gt;L-701,324
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;7-Chloro-4-hydroxy-3-(3-phenoxy)phenyl-2(1H)-quinolinone 
&lt;tb&gt;31&lt;sep&gt;Loperamide hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;4-(4-Chlorophenyl)-4-hydroxy-N,N-dimethyl-a,a-diphenyl- 1-piperidinebutanamide hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;33&lt;sep&gt;LY 233053
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(2R*,4S*)-4-(1H-Tetrazol-5-ylmethyl)-2-piperidinecarbox ylic acid
&lt;tb&gt;34&lt;sep&gt;LY 235959
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;[3S-(3a,4aa,6b,8aa)]-Decahydro-6-(phosphonomethyl)-3-is oquinolinecarboxylic acid)
&lt;tb&gt;35&lt;sep&gt;Norketamine hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;2-Amino-2-(2-chlorophenyl)cyclohexanonehydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;36&lt;sep&gt;Pentamidine isethionate
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;4,4'-(Pentamethylenedioxy)dibenzamidine bis-2-hydroxyethanesulfonate salt 
&lt;tb&gt;37&lt;sep&gt;Phencyclidine hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;1-(1-Phenylcyclohexyl)piperidine hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;38&lt;sep&gt;PMPA (NMDA antagonist)
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;4-(Phosphonomethyl)-2-piperazinecarboxylic acid
&lt;tb&gt;39&lt;sep&gt;PPDA
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;2S*,3R*)-1-(Phenanthren-2-carbonyl)piperazine-2,3-dicarboxylic acid
&lt;tb&gt;40&lt;sep&gt;PPPA
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(2R*,4S*)-4-(3-Phosphonopropyl)-2-piperidinecarboxylic acid
&lt;tb&gt;41&lt;sep&gt;Remacemide hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;2-Amino-N-(1-methyl-1,2-diphenylethyl)acetamidehydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;42&lt;sep&gt;Ro 04-5595 hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;1-[2-(4-Chlorophenyl)ethyl]-1,2,3,4-tetrahydro-6-methox y-2-methyl-7-isoquinolinol hydrochloride 
&lt;tb&gt;43&lt;sep&gt;Ro 25-6981 maleate
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(aR,bS)-a-(4-Hydroxyphenyl)-b-methyl-4-(phenylmethyl)-1 -piperidinepropanol maleate
&lt;tb&gt;44&lt;sep&gt;Ro 61-8048
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;3,4-Dimethoxy-N-[4-(3-nitrophenyl)-2-thiazolyl]benzenes ulfonamide
&lt;tb&gt;45&lt;sep&gt;Ro 8-4304 hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;4-[3-[4-(4-Fluorophenyl)-1,2,3,6-tetrahydro-1(2H)-pyrid inyl]-2-hydroxypropoxy]benzamide hydrochloride
&lt;tb&gt;46&lt;sep&gt;SDZ 220-040
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;(S)-a-Amino-2',4'-dichloro-4-hydroxy-5-(phosphonomethyl)-[1,1'-biphenyl]-3-propanoic acid
&lt;tb&gt;47&lt;sep&gt;SDZ 220-581
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;S)-a-Amino-2'-chloro-5-(phosphonomethyl)[1,1'-biphenyl]-3-propanoic acid
&lt;tb&gt;48&lt;sep&gt;Synthalin sulfate
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;N,N'-1,10-Decanediylbisguanidine sulfate 
&lt;tb&gt;49&lt;sep&gt;TCS 46b
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;1,3-Dihydro-5-[3-[4-(phenylmethyl)-1-2H-benzimidazol-2- one
&lt;tb&gt;50&lt;sep&gt;Memantine
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;Dimethyladamantan
&lt;tb&gt;51&lt;sep&gt;An inhibitory antibody capable of specifically inhibiting the activity of a NMDA receptor.
&lt;tb&gt;52&lt;sep&gt;A ribozyme or a DNA enzyme specific for the sequence of a NMDA receptor.
&lt;tb&gt;53&lt;sep&gt;An interfering RNA specific for the sequence of a NMDA receptor.
&lt;tb&gt;54&lt;sep&gt;An inhibiting peptide specific for a NMDA receptor. Conantokin-R
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
&lt;tb&gt;&lt;sep&gt;
 
 
&lt;tb&gt;55&lt;sep&gt;A NMDA receptor specific antisense nucleic acid.</p><p>[0110]    In a particular embodiment, the NMDA inhibitor is an inhibitory antibody, a ribozyme, an interfering RNA, an inhibiting peptide specific for a NMDA or a NMDA receptor specific antisense nucleic acid. </p><p>[0111]    The definition, design strategy, synthesis, etc., of inhibitory antibodies, ribozyme, interfering RNA, inhibiting peptides specific for a NMDA specific antisense nucleic acid is essentially the same as it was described previously for AMPA receptor.</p><p>[0112]    Suitable NMDA receptor inhibitors include, between others, the compounds described in Table II. In a particular embodiment, the NMDA inhibitor is the antagonist memantine.</p><p>[0113]    Another aspect of the invention refers to a pharmaceutical composition which comprises of at least one NMDA receptor inhibitor, either wide spectrum or selective of a receptor subgroup, along with at least one pharmaceutically accepted excipient. Accepted excipients and ways of administration have been previously described.</p><p>[0114]    Another aspect of the invention refers to a pharmaceutical composition which comprises of at least one NMDA receptor inhibitor, either wide spectrum or selective of a receptor subgroup, along with at least one pharmaceutically accepted excipient for the treatment of Alzheimer.</p><p>[0115]    A further aspect of the present invention relates to a method of treating a subject with a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins. This method involves administering an AMPA receptor inhibitor to the subject under conditions effective to treat a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins.</p><p>[0116]    This aspect of the present invention is carried out in substantially the same manner as described above.</p><p>[0117]    Another aspect of the present invention relates to a method of inhibiting Ca&lt;2+&gt;-triggered central nervous system cell death which comprises contacting central nervous system cells with an AMPA receptor inhibitor under conditions effective to inhibit Ca&lt;2+&gt;-triggered central nervous system cell death, wherein the inhibitor inhibits the Ca&lt;2+&gt; flow through the AMPA receptor. Causes of such central nervous system cell death include deposition of amyloid proteins. In a particular embodiment, this method can be used with brain or spinal cord cells which are neural cells (e.g., neurons, oligodendrocytes, or astrocytes) as well as with endothelial cells. Preferably, all of these cell types are from humans. In this case, the AMPA receptor inhibitor inhibits the release of cations through the AMPA receptor. In a preferred embodiment, the cells are neurons.</p><p>[0118]    In a particular embodiment, this method additionally comprises the contacting of a CNS cell with a NMDA receptor inhibitor under conditions effective to inhibit Ca&lt;2+&gt;-triggered brain or spinal cord cell death. This method can be also used with brain or spinal cord cells which are neural cells (e.g., neurons, oligodendrocytes, or astrocytes) as well as with endothelial cells. Preferably, all of these cell types are from humans. In this case, the NMDA receptor inhibitor inhibits the ion flow through the NMDA receptor.</p><p>[0119]    AMPA receptor inhibitors and NMDA receptor inhibitors have been described previously.</p><p>[0120]    In another embodiment the invention relates with a NMDA receptor inhibitor for use in the treatment of Alzheimer.</p><p>SCREENING METHODS OF THE INVENTION</p><p>[0121]    In another aspect the invention relates with a method for identifying a compound useful for inhibiting the cellular death induced by amyloid proteins deposition for the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins comprising: 
a) putting in contact a cell with an amyloid protein,;
b) putting the cells resulting from step a) with the test compound; and
c) determining the levels of Ca&lt;2+&gt; and/or the levels of AMPA receptor activation in said cell,wherein if the levels of Ca&lt;2+&gt; and /or the levels of AMPA receptor activation in said cell after the treatment of said cell with the test compound are lower tahn before the treatment, the test compound is able to inhibiting the cellular death induced by amyloid proteins deposition and useful for the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins.</p><p>[0122]    Disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins and AMPA receptors have been described previously.</p><p>[0123]    In a first step [step a)], the method of the invention for identifying a therapeutic agent or screening method of the invention comprises putting in contact a cell with an amyloid protein. The different amyloid proteins have been described previously. In a preferred embodiment, the amyloid protein used in step a) is the A[beta] peptide.</p><p>[0124]    In the present invention, as "cell" it is understand any single cell in culture alone or a plurality of cells in culture or forming part of a 3D (three-dimensional) structure such an organotypic culture. Thus, in the present invention the wording "culture" includes any of the above mention possibilities.</p><p>[0125]    Examples of cells that can be use in the method of the invention for identifying a therapeutic agent or screening method of the invention are, without limitation , primary cultures obtained from divers tissues as skin, blood, brain etc; immortalized cells obtained from primary cultures such as osteoblast, mioblast, fibroblast, stem cells, etc. In a preferred embodiment, the cells used are from neuronal origin (primary cultures of neurons or immortalized cells cultures like SN4741, IMR32, N-TERA, PC12, GN11, C1300).</p><p>[0126]    In another embodiment, the cells form a 3D structure denominated organotypic culture. In the present invention "organotypic culture" is any tridimensional culture form tissue that maintains in a high degree the structure, cellular connections and physiological characteristics from the tissue/organ where it has been extracted or dissected. ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gahwiler, 1981 J. Neurosci. Meth. 4, 329-42</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gahwiler 1984 Neuroscience. 11:751-60</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gahwiler 1988 Trends Neurosc. 11:484-9</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Stoppini et al. 1991 J. Neuroscience Methods 37:173-82</bibl> ).</p><p>[0127]    Organotypic cultures can be extracted from any organ wherein the influence of amyloid protein deposition associated cellular death, such as the 1-42 A[beta] depossition associated celular death, wants to be studied.</p><p>[0128]    In a particular embodiment, the tissue is brain tissue. As a person skilled in the art would understand, the organotypic culture used in the method of the invention, may contain many different regions of the brain and it will be made attending to the particular needs of each assay.</p><p>[0129]    Methods for making an organotypic culture are known by the person skilled in the art ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gahwiler, 1981 J. Neurosci. Meth. 4, 329-42</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gahwiler 1984 Neuroscience. 11:751-60</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gahwiler 1988 Trends Neurosc. 11:484-9</bibl> ; <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Stoppini et al. 1991 J. Neuroscience Methods 37:173-82</bibl> ). The brain can be from any non-human animal, preferible a vertebrate, such as mammal like a mice, a rat, etc. Said animal can a genetically modify animal or a non-genetically modify animal. Said genetically modify animals can be transgenic animals, namely animals that present inserted in their genome the sequence of a gene of interest (e.g. YFP as described in <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Winter SM et al., 2007 Respir Physiol Neurobiol. 159:108-14</bibl> ). Also animals with a blocked expression of a gene (i.e. knock out mice) can be used. Methods for the generation of said animals are well known by the person skilled in the art.</p><p>[0130]    One example of a brain organotypic culture is shown in the present application (see methods "Preparation of organotypic cultures").</p><p>[0131]    The cellular (or organotypic) culture is maintained in conditions that permit the survival of the cells of said cultures. Said conditions included, between others, adequate humidity, temperature, gases concentration, nutrients (culture medium) etc. Special incubators, well known by the person skilled in the art, can be used for reaching the previously mention conditions. The culture conditions would be defined for each particular cultured.</p><p>[0132]    Different cell culture mediums are known by the person skilled in the art ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Vergni et al., 2009 PLoS ONE4(4):e5278 , Chechneva et al., 2006 Neurobiol of Dis. 23(2):247-59</bibl> ).</p><p>[0133]    The expression "putting in contact a cell with an amyloid protein" refers to any process where the cell are put in contact with a amyloid protein such as the A[beta] peptide, and includes any possible "in vitro" way of putting extracellular in contact said amyloid protein or any way of introducing said proteins to the cells.</p><p>[0134]    The amyloid proteins can be purchased or produced using chemical or biological synthesis as it is described in the examples of the present invention.</p><p>[0135]    The concentrations of the amyloid protein such as the A[beta] peptide used in the screening method of the invention, when using cell cultures can be from between 0.001 [micro]M and 40 [micro]M, 0.05 [micro]M and 30 [micro]M, preferably between 0.15 [micro]M y 10 [micro]M, 0.3 and 5 [micro]M, 0.1 [micro]M y 2 [micro]M. In a preferred embodiment, the cell culture is a neuronal cell culture and the concentration of A[beta] peptide is from between 0.5 [micro]M and 3 [micro]M and more preferably de 1.25 [micro]M. In another particular embodiment, the culture is an brain organotypic culture and the A[beta] peptide concentration is from 10 nM and 1 [micro]M, preferably 100 nM.</p><p>[0136]    The step (b) of the screening method of the invention comprises the step of contacting the cell (i.e. single cell, a cell population or a organotypic culture) obtained in step a) with a compound whose capacity to inhibit the cellular death induced by amyloid proteins deposition through the AMPA receptor wants to be assessed. According to the present invention, "putting in contact" a cell with the candidate compound includes any possible way of taking the candidate compound extracellular or inside the cell (or cell population, or organotypic culture). Thus, in the event that the candidate compound is a molecule with low molecular weight, it is enough to add said molecule to the culture medium. In the event that the candidate compound is a molecule with a high molecular weight (for example, biological polymers such as a nucleic acid or a protein), it is necessary to provide the means so that this molecule can access the cell interior. In the event that the candidate molecule is a nucleic acid, conventional transfection means can be used, as described previously for the introduction of the DNA construct. In the event that the candidate compound is a protein, the cell can be put in contact with the protein directly or with the nucleic acid encoding it coupled to elements allowing its transcription / translation once they are in the cell interior. To that end, any of the aforementioned methods can be used to allow its entrance in the cell interior. Alternatively, it is possible to put the cell in contact with a variant of the protein to be studied which has been modified with a peptide which can promote the translocation of the protein to the cell interior, such as the Tat peptide derived from the HIV-1 TAT protein, the third helix of the Antennapedia homeodomain protein from D. melanogaster, the VP22 protein of the herpes simplex virus and arginine oligomers ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Lindgren, A. et al., 2000, Trends Pharmacol. Sci, 21:99-103</bibl> , <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Schwarze, S.R. et al., 2000, Trends Pharmacol. Sci., 21:45-48</bibl> , <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Lundberg, M et al., 2003, Mol. Therapy 8:143-150</bibl>  and <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Snyder, E.L. and Dowdy, S.F., 2004, Pharm. Res. 21:389-393</bibl> ).</p><p>[0137]    The compound to be assayed is preferably not isolated but forms part of a more or less complex mixture derived from a natural source or forming part of a library of compounds. Examples of libraries of compounds which can be assayed according to the method of the present invention include, but are not limited to, libraries of peptides including both peptides and peptide analogs comprising D-amino acids or peptides comprising non-peptide bonds, libraries of nucleic acids including nucleic acids with phosphothioate type non-phosphodiester bonds or peptide nucleic acids, libraries of antibodies, of carbohydrates, of compounds with a low molecular weight, preferably organic molecules, of peptide mimetics and the like. In the event that a library of organic compounds with a low molecular weight is used, the library can have been preselected so that it contains compounds which can access the cell interior more easily. The compounds can thus be selected based on certain parameters such as size, lipophilicity, hydrophilicity, capacity to form hydrogen bonds.</p><p>[0138]    The compounds to be assayed can alternatively form part of an extract obtained from a natural source. The natural source can be an animal, plant source obtained from any environment, including but not limited to extracts of land, air, marine organisms and the like.</p><p>[0139]    The incubation of the test compound is made a t different concentrations and times of incubation. The use of negative and positive controls is highly recommendable.</p><p>[0140]    The third step [step c)] comprises the determination of the levels of Ca&lt;2+&gt; and/or the levels of AMPA receptor activation in said cell treated with the candidate compound.</p><p>[0141]    The Ca&lt;2+&gt; measured can be cytosolic or mitochondrial. Methods that can be used for the determination of the levels of the cytosolic or mitochondrial Ca&lt;2+&gt; have been described previously. The methods for determining the AMPA receptor activation in said cell treated with the candidate compound are well known by the person skilled in the art and included without limiting, electrophysiology methods or receptor binding assays. Alternately, FRET-biosensors can be used.</p><p>[0142]    In a particular embodiment, the third step of the screening method of the invention comprises additionally the measurements of the cell death levels or the viability of the culture. Methods for measuring the cell death levels or the viability of the culture are well known by the person skilled in the art. Non limitative examples are described in the present applications (see methods, "Cell viability and toxicity assays")</p><p>[0143]    In general it is consider that the compound would be potentially useful for the treatment of a disease associated with deposition of amyloid proteins, like disease associated with deposition of the A[beta]peptide such as Alzheimer, if the levels of Ca&lt;2+&gt; and /or the levels of AMPA receptor activation in said cell after the treatment of said cell with the test compound are lower than before the treatment.</p><p>[0144]    It is consider that the levels of Ca&lt;2+&gt; and /or the levels of AMPA receptor activation in said cell after the treatment of said cell with the test compound are lower than before the treatment, when the Ca&lt;2+&gt; and /or AMPA receptor activation levels are 2, 5, 10, 15, 20, 30, 40, 50, or 100 times lower than before the treatment of the cells with the compound. </p><p>[0145]    A person skilled in the art understands that if the lysis of the cell it is required for the measurements of the Ca&lt;2+&gt; and/or AMPA receptor activation levels, then it would be necessary the use of a second culture that has not been treated with the test compound for comparing the results.</p><p>EXAMPLE 1</p><p>1. Materials and methods</p><p>1.1 Drugs and culture medium</p><p>[0146]    Neurobasal medium, B27 supplement, foetal bovine serum, horse serum and other culture reagents were from Gibco (Invitrogen, Barcelona, Spain). Receptor antagonists MK801, DAP5 (AP5), and memantine were all obtained from Tocris (Cookson, Bristol, UK). CNQX and other chemicals were from Sigma (St Louis, MO, USA). The general caspase inhibitor ZVAD and the caspase-3 specific inhibitor DEVD were purchased in Peptides International (Louisville, KY, USA). DPQ, the PARP-1 inhibitor, was obtained from Calbiochem (La Jolla, CA, USA).</p><p>1.2 Preparation of A[beta] oligomers</p><p>[0147]    A[beta]1-42 oligomers were prepared as reported previously ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">W.L. Klein, et al. 2002. Neurochem. Int. 41 345-352</bibl> ). Briefly, A[beta]1-42 (ABX, Radeberg, Germany) was initially dissolved to 1 mM in hexafluoroisopropanol (Sigma; St Louis, MO, USA) and separated into aliquots in sterile microcentrifuge tubes. Hexafluoroisopropanol was totally removed under vacuum in a speed vac system and the peptide film was stored desiccated at -80 [deg.]C. For the aggregation protocol, the peptide was first resuspended in dry DMSO (Sigma; St Louis, MO, USA) to a concentration of 5 mM and Hams F-12 (PromoCell, Labclinics, Barcelona, Spain) was added to bring the peptide to a final concentration of 100 [micro]M and incubated at 4[deg.]C for 24 h. The preparation was then centrifuged at 14,000 x g for 10 min at 4[deg.]C to remove insoluble aggregates and the supernatants containing soluble A[beta]1-42 was transferred to clean tubes and stored at 4[deg.]C. </p><p>1.3 Cortical cell culture</p><p>[0148]    Primary neuron cultures were obtained from the cortical lobes of E18 Sprague-Dawley rat embryos according to previously described procedures ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gottlieb M. et al. 2006. Neurobiol. Dis. 23 374-386</bibl> .) Cells were resuspended in B27 Neurobasal medium plus 10% FBS (Sigma; St Louis, MO, USA) and then seeded onto poly-1-ornithine-coated glass coverslips at 1x10&lt;5&gt; cells per coverslip (12 mm in diameter) and 48-well plates at 1.5 x 10&lt;5&gt; per well. One day later, the medium was replaced by serum-free-, B27-supplemented Neurobasal medium. The cultures were essentially free of astrocytes and microglia; they were maintained at 37[deg.]C and 5% CO2. Cultures were used 8-10 days after plating.</p><p>1.4 Preparation of organotypic cultures</p><p>[0149]    Brain was removed and two hemispheres were separated in HBSS. Thalamus and midbrain was removed and each hemisphere sliced with a tissue chopper (McIlwan Tissue Chopper, Campden Instruments Ltd, Lafayette, IN, USA) in order to obtain coronal slices of 400 [micro]m of thickness. Entorhinal cortex, in connection with hippocampus, were isolated under a dissection microscope, 2 slices plated on each Millicell CM culture inserts (Millipore Ibérica, Madrid, Spain) and maintained in Neurobasal medium supplemented with 0.5% B27, 25% horse serum, 25% HBSS and 25 mg/ml gentamycin at 37[deg.]C. Experiments were performed at 7-10 days in vitro. Cultures were immunostained with antibodies to neurofilament-L (NFL 1:200; Cell Signaling Technology, Boston; MA) and choline acetyltransferase (ChAT 40 [micro]g/ml; Chemicon, Millipore Ibérica, Spain) and labelling was revealed with fluorescent goat anti-rabbit and donkey anti-goat secondary antibodies respectively (Alexa Fluor 488, Invitrogen, Barcelona, Spain)</p><p>1. 5 Electrophysiology</p><p>[0150]    Whole-cell recordings were performed at room temperature using the EPC-7 patch-clamp amplifier (HEKA Elektronik, Lambrecht, Germany). Currents were recorded at a holding membrane potential of -70 mV. Extracellular bath solution with a pH of 7.3 contained the following (in mM): 140 NaCl, 5 KCl, 2.5 CaCl2, 1 MgCl2, 10 HEPES and 10 mM glucose. Patch-clamp pipettes (3-5 M[Omega]) were filled with internal solution at a pH of 7.3 containing the following (in mM): 140 K-gluconate, 1 CaCl2, 2 MgCl2, 10 HEPES, 10 EGTA, 2 Mg-ATP, 0.2 Na-GTP.</p><p>1.6 Ca&lt;2+&gt; imaging in the cytosol</p><p>[0151]    [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! was determined according to the method described previously ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">G. Grynkiewicz, et al. 1985. J. Biol. Chem. 260:3440-3450</bibl> ). Neurons were loaded with fura-2 AM (5 [micro]M; Molecular Probes, Invitrogen, Barcelona, Spain) in culture medium for 30 min at 37[deg.]C. Cells were washed in HBSS containing 20 mM HEPES, pH 7.4, 10 mM glucose, and 2 mM CaCl2 (incubation buffer) for 10 min at room temperature. Experiments were performed in a coverslip chamber continuously perfused with incubation buffer at 4 ml/min. The perfusion chamber was mounted on the stage of a inverted epifluorescence microscope (Zeiss Axiovert 35; Oberkochen, Germany) equipped with a 150 W xenon lamp Polychrome IV (T.I.L.L. Photonics, Martinsried, Germany) and a Plan Neofluar 40 x oil immersion objective (Zeiss). Cells were visualized with a high-resolution digital black/white CCD camera (ORCA C4742-80-12 AG; Hamamatsu Photonics Iberica). [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! was estimated by the 340/380 ratio method, using a Kd value of 224 nM. At the end of the assay, in situ calibration was performed with the successive addition of 10 mM ionomycin and 2 M Tris/50 mM EGTA, pH 8.5. Data were analyzed with Excel (Microsoft, Seattle, WA, USA) and Prism (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA) software.</p><p>1. 7 Measurement of mitochondrial Ca&lt;2+&gt;</p><p>[0152]    Rhod-2 AM (Molecular Probes, Invitrogen, Barcelona, Spain) was used to measure mitochondrial Ca&lt;2+&gt; according to the previous procedure with modifications ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">G. Hajnóczky, L.D. et al. 1995. Cell 82 415-424</bibl> ) Rhod2-AM has a net positive charge, which facilitates its sequestration into mitochondria due to membrane potential-driven uptake. Cells were loaded with 2 [micro]M rhod2-AM for 6 hours. The residual cytosolic fraction of the dye was eliminated when the cells were kept in culture for an additional 18h after loading, whereas the mitochondrial dye fluorescence was maintained. Fluorescence images of rhod-2 were acquired using 550 nm excitation and 590 nm emission. The fluorescence of rhod-2 was not calibrated in terms of [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]mit since it is not a ratiometric dye.</p><p>1.8 Measurement of Ca&lt;2+&gt; in organotypic slices</p><p>[0153]    Ca&lt;2+&gt; levels in hippocampus were monitored by fluorescence microscopy using the Ca&lt;2+&gt; indicator fluo-4 (Molecular Probes, Invitrogen, Barcelona, Spain). Slices were incubated with fluo-4-AM (5 [micro]M and 0.01 % of pluronic acid) for 45 min at 37 [deg.]C. Experiments were performed in a chamber continuously perfused with incubation buffer. Drugs were perfused by a micromanifold with a quartz/polyimide tube of 200 [micro]m ID, attached to a micromanipulator in order to perfuse the drugs directly to the cells. The perfusion chamber was mounted on the stage of a Leica DMLFSA up-right microscope equipped with a 150 W xenon lamp Polychrome V (T.I.L.L. Photonics, Martinsried, Germany) and a HCX Apo 40 x water immersion objective (Leica). Cells were visualized with a CCD camera (EM CCD 9100; Hamamatsu Photonics Iberica, Barcelona, Spain).</p><p>1.9. Cell viability and toxicity assays</p><p>[0154]    Cortical neurons at 8-10 days in culture were exposed for 24 hours to A[beta] oligomers. Antagonists and inhibitors were added to the cultures 30 min before the A[beta]. Twenty four hours after drug application, cellular damage was estimated by measuring the level of lactate dehydrogenase released (LDH; Cytotox 96&lt;(R)&gt;, Promega, Madison, WI) from damaged cells into the culture media. Data were normalized to the activity of LDH released from vehicle-treated cells (100%) and calculated as a percentage of the control. Results were expressed as the means +- SEM of at least three independent experiments performed in triplicates.</p><p>[0155]    Hippocampus-entorhinal cultures were exposed to A[beta] oligomers at 100 nM for 4 days. Antagonists were added to cultures 30 min before the A[beta]. Cell death in organotypic cultures was evaluated by cellular uptake of propidium iodide (PI). Slices were stained by adding 10 [micro]M PI into the culture for 2 h at 37[deg.]C and washed with PBS by two times for 10 min. Slices were fixed with 4% PFA in PBS for 40 min at room temperature [24]. Afterwards, the slices were excited with 510-560 nm light and the emitted fluorescence acquired at 610 nm using a rhodamine filter on an inverted fluorescence microscope (Cell Observer Z1, Zeiss). PI fluorescence images were captured with a Plan NeoFluar 2.5 x objective (Zeiss), using an EM CCD camera (Hamamatsu, C9100-13), controlled by Axio Vision program (Zeiss). Images were analyzed with the ImageJ analysis program (NIH, MD, USA) and neuronal cell death was expressed as the percentage of the mean gray value of each treatment vs. control.</p><p>1.10 Measurement of intracellular reactive oxygen species</p><p>[0156]    Neurons were exposed to A[beta] oligomers alone or with GluR antagonists as described. Cells were loaded with CM-H2DCFDA at 30 [micro]M to assay the ROS levels. Calcein-AM (1 [micro]M; Molecular Probes, Invitrogen, Barcelona, Spain) was used to quantify the number of cells within the reading field. Fluorescence was measured using a Synergy-HT fluorimeter (Bio-Tek Instruments Incl, Beverly, MA, USA; excitation at 485 nm, emission at 527 nm). All experiments (n&gt;=3) were performed at least in quadruplicate and plotted as means +- SEM.</p><p>1.11Analysis of mitochondrial membrane potential</p><p>[0157]    Neurons were exposed to A[beta] oligomers alone or in presence of different drugs and changes in mitochondrial membrane potential were monitored by reduction of JC-1 (Molecular Probes, Invitrogen, Barcelona, Spain), according to the manufacturer protocol. Briefly, after drug treatment, cells were loaded with 3 [micro]M JC-1 for 15 min at 37[deg.]C and were washed with HBSS without phenol red by two times to eliminate the excess of dye. In the cytosol the monomeric form of this dye fluoresces green (excitation at 485 nm, emission at 527 nm), whereas within the mitochondrial matrix highly concentrated JC-1 forms aggregates that fluoresce red (excitation at 485 nm, emission at 590 nm). Both JC-1 monomers and aggregates were detectable using a Synergy-HT fluorimeter (Bio-Tek Instruments Incl, Beverly, MA, USA) and the changes in mitochondrial potential were calculated as the red/green ratio in each condition. All experiments (n&gt;=3) were performed at least in triplicate and plotted as meant SEM.</p><p>1.12 Statistical Analysis </p><p>[0158]    Data are presented as means +- SEM. Statistical analysis was carried out with the Student t test and, in all instances, a value ofp &lt; 0.05 was considered significant.</p><p>2. Results</p><p>2.1 A[beta] oligomers activate NMDA and AMPA receptors in neurons</p><p>[0159]    Dysregulation of intracellular Ca&lt;2+&gt; homeostasis may underlie A[beta] peptide toxicity in AD but the mechanisms are unknown. Here, we tested whether the activation of ionotropic GluRs is involved in neuronal response to A[beta] 1-42 oligomeric peptide. Previous studies have shown that A[beta] oligomers produce reversible synapse loss ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">G.M. Shankar, et al. 2007. J. Neurosci. 27 2866-2875</bibl> ), neuronal oxidative stress and dynamin-1 degradation through an NMDA receptor dependent mechanism. First, using electrophysiological recording and Ca&lt;2+&gt; imaging methods, it was studied whether soluble A[beta] oligomers interact with NMDA receptor in neurons. Whole-cell patch-clamp recording was used to examine the effects of A[beta] oligomers on cortical neurons in culture. In conditions which favour NMDA receptor activation (glycine 100 [micro]M and no Mg&lt;2+&gt;), A[beta] oligomers (1 [micro]M) induced an inward current in the majority of neurons examined (816 +- 101 pA; n=30). Preincubation of APS (100 [micro]M), a competitive NMDA antagonist, reduced the peak of the currents (n=7). Silencing neural activity with TTX (1[micro]M) or using a calcium-free extracellular bath solution did not attenuate the response to A[beta] oligomers suggesting a direct interaction of the peptide with NMDA receptors (n= 11 and 13 respectively; Fig 1A).</p><p>[0160]    To characterize further the properties of A[beta] responses, we next monitored the concentration of intracellular Ca&lt;2+&gt; [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! in cultured cortical neurons. We found that oligomeric A[beta] (5 [micro]M) caused a robust and sustained increase in [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! (270 nM, n=42), which is nearly abolished by coapplication of NMDA receptor antagonists AP5, MK801 and memantine (n=70). Similarly, A[beta] applied in Ca&lt;2+&gt;-free extracellular buffer containing EGTA 50 [micro]M greatly reduced [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! rise (n=11). In contrast, the voltage-gated Ca&lt;2+&gt; channel inhibitors nifedipine and verapamil were ineffective (n=66; Fig 1B).</p><p>[0161]    Together these results provide evidence indicating that A[beta] oligomers activate NMDA receptors in cortical cultured neurons. </p><p>[0162]    Previous results have shown that A[beta](1-42) but not A[beta](1-40) closely interacts with synaptic AMPA receptors. Because of that, we next examined whether A[beta] oligomers also activate AMPA receptors in cultured neurons. In the presence of Mg&lt;2+&gt; and no glycine, A[beta] (1[micro]M) alone elicited a small current (43 +- 14 pA, n= 6) and co-applied with cyclothiazide (CTZ), an inhibitor of AMPA receptor desensitization, activated a sustained current (n=18; Fig 2A) that was blocked by the AMPA/kainate antagonist CNQX (n= 6; Fig 2A). We then measured the effects of antagonists of NMDA or AMPA receptor on [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! in neurons exposed to A[beta] plus CTZ (5 [micro]M and 100 [micro]M, respectively; Fig 2B). In these experimental conditions, A[beta] oligomers increased the [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! in 308 +- 44.7 nM (100 % of Ca&lt;2+&gt; increase, control value, n=23) a level that was substantially reduced by CNQX 30 [micro]M (50 +- 4 % of control, n=17) and by AP5 100 [micro]M (45 +- 2 % of control, n=17; Fig. 2B). Co-incubation with CNQX and AP5 further reduced [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! to 14 +- 2 % of control (n=18; Fig. 2B). Any facilitatory role of AMPA receptors on A[beta]-induced NMDA receptor response was excluded since in physiological conditions (2 mM Mg&lt;2+&gt;, 0.1 mM Gly) CNQX did not modify the A[beta]-produced inward current (98.3 +- 6.8 % A[beta] + CNQX vs 100 % A[beta] alone, n=6). These results indicate that A[beta] oligomers in presence of CTZ activate AMPA receptors and, in these conditions, the contribution of both receptors to Ca&lt;2+&gt; influx is substantial.</p><p>2.2 A[beta] oligomers trigger apoptotic neuronal death through NMDA and AMPA receptors.</p><p>[0163]    As illustrated above, NMDA and AMPA receptor activation by A[beta] oligomers in neurons causes an increase in basal [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! levels. Because GluRs mediate Ca&lt;2+&gt;-dependent-neuronal cell death, we tested whether activation of these receptors by A[beta] is toxic to neurons. Incubation of A[beta] oligomers for 24h caused neuronal death in a dose-dependent manner (Fig 3A). In turn, A[beta] toxicity (5 [micro]M; 15.2 +-1.8 % cell death vs. non-treated cells) was greatly attenuated by NMDA receptor antagonists AP5 100 [micro]M, MK801 50 [micro]M and memantine 50 [micro]M and by AMPA/kainate receptor antagonist CNQX 30 [micro]M (Fig. 3B).</p><p>[0164]    Oligomeric A[beta] peptides induce mitochondrial dependent-apoptotic cell death in cultured neurons. Damage to mitochondria can result in both caspase-dependent and -independent cell death. To characterize whether these two types of apoptosis are involved in GluR-mediated A[beta] toxicity, we used the pan-caspase inhibitor ZVAD-F, a caspase-3 inhibitor Ac-DEVD-F and the nuclear enzyme poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase-1 (PARP-1) inhibitor DPQ. We observed that ZVAD-F (50 [micro]M), DEVD (100 [micro]M) and DPQ (30 [micro]M) reduced A[beta]-induced cell death (Fig. 3C). A[beta] toxicity decreased further by blocking simultaneously caspase-3 and PARP-1 with DEVD + DPQ (Fig. 3C). These results indicate that A[beta] oligomers induce caspase-3- and PARP-1-dependent neuronal death via activation of NMDA and AMPA receptors.</p><p>2.3 A[beta] oligomers induce mitochondrial damage by activating glutamate receptors</p><p>[0165]    To characterize further the signalling cascades triggered by A[beta] oligomers, we next studied mitochondrial Ca&lt;2+&gt; uptake in neurons with rhod-2 AM, a cationic indicator which loads selectively into respiring mitochondria. To assess that feature, we used FCCP 25 [micro]M, a protonophore that collapses the mitochondria membrane potential and releases Ca&lt;2+&gt; from mitochondria. As expected, FCCP induced a rapid and transitory reduction of rhod-2 fluorescence (Fig 4A). In these loading conditions, we assayed the effects of A[beta] oligomers on [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]mit. A[beta] 5 [micro]M increased [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]mit levels with respect to the control assay (incubation buffer). Ca&lt;2+&gt; rise was reduced by NMDA antagonist MK801, AP5 and memantine (Fig 4B and C). These results indicate that A[beta] induces mitochondrial Ca&lt;2+&gt; overload and that this effect can be prevented by NMDA receptors antagonists.</p><p>[0166]    The results shown that NMDA antagonists reduce A[beta]-generated oxidative stress (Fig. 4D) and mitochondrial depolarization (Fig. 4E) in cortical neurons. Incubation of neurons with A[beta] (5 [micro]M; 2 hours) increased ROS levels to 124 +- 7.8 % and reduced the mitochondrial potential to 75 +- 3% with respect to control (100%, non-treated cells). Both parameters were partially restored by NMDA receptor antagonists AP5 (102 +- 11 % and 90 +- 2 %, respectively) and MK801 (104 +- 3.4 % and 85 +- 3 %, respectively) and by AMPA receptor antagonist CNQX (106 +- 6.3 % and 86 +- 3 %, respectively; Fig.4D and E).</p><p>[0167]    Taken together, these results demonstrate that both NMDA and AMPA receptors mediate A[beta]-induced mitochondrial dysfunction. </p><p>2.4 Blockade of NMDA and AMPA receptors protect from A[beta]-induced toxicity in entorhinal cortex-hippocampus organotypic slices.</p><p>[0168]    Next it was examined if A[beta]oligomers induce Ca&lt;2+&gt; and cell death in a more integral preparation. To that end, rganotypic cultures from entorhinal cortex and hippocampus, two regions that are profoundly affected early in Alzheimer's disease and cause cardinal symptoms of short-term memory loss were used ( <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">De Lacoste, M.C. et al. 1993. Neurobiol. Aging 14 1-16</bibl> ).</p><p>[0169]    Slices for organotypic cultures were prepared as to preserve major connections between entorhinal cortex and hippocampus. Thus, neurofilament immunofluorescence with antibodies to NFL revealed axons entering the hippocampus from the entorhinal cortex and layer preservation of these structures (Fig. 5A, B and C). In addition, antibodies to choline acetyltransferase show cholinergic fibers and terminals in entorhinal cortex (Fig. 5 D).</p><p>[0170]    To monitor the effects of A[beta] in these cultures, we measured Ca&lt;2+&gt; levels after application of A[beta] to neurons from CA1 in organotypic slices. We found that oligomeric A[beta] (20 [micro]M in the pipette) increased [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! in those cells, and that this response was greatly reduced by MK801 (50 [micro]M, n=9) and CNQX (30 [micro]M, n=43) treatment (Fig 5E). A[beta]-induced [Ca&lt;2+&gt;]! decreased further by blocking simultaneously NMDA and AMPA receptors with MK801+CNQX (n=50; Fig 5E). In turn, Ca&lt;2+&gt; responses elicited by kainate (1 mM) served as a positive control to evaluate the integrity of the culture (Fig. 5E).</p><p>[0171]    Finally, to test A[beta] toxicity cultures were chronically incubated with low concentrations of A[beta] oligomers (100 nM) for 4 days, and used PI fluorescence to measure cell death. PI uptake in slices exposed to A[beta] showed 4.1 +- 1.0 and 3.8 +- 0.9 fold over the control slices (n=7) in hippocampus and entorhinal cortex respectively (Fig. 5F-G). Instead, co-incubation of GluR antagonists MK801 (10 [micro]M) or CNQX (30 [micro]M) with A[beta] oligomers reduced PI uptake to 0.9 +- 0.2 and 1.3 +- 0.4 fold in hippocampus and to 1.2 +- 0.4 and 0.73 +- .01 fold in entorhinal cortex as compared to control slices treated with MK801 or CNQX alone (Fig 5F-G). </p><p>[0172]    Overall, these results indicate that A[beta] induces cytosolic Ca&lt;2+&gt; overload and cell death in organotypic cultures, and that antagonists of NMDA and AMPA receptors prevent both effects. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
</p></description></fulltext-document>