<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document country="US" doc-number="20070000361" kind="A1" ucid="US-20070000361-A1" lang="EN" date="20070104" family-id="33476138" date-produced="20090604" status="new"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="76991301" ucid="US-20070000361-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>US</country><doc-number>20070000361</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20070104</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-55569104-A" us-series-code="10" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>55569104</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040521</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="SE-0300818-W" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>SE</country><doc-number>0300818</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20030521</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="SE-2004000800-W" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>SE</country><doc-number>2004000800</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20040521</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B25B  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B25B  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B26B  27/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B26B  27/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   1/00        20060101AFI20070104BHUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   1/00        20060101CFI20070104BHUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   1/01        20060101CLI20070104BHUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   1/48        20060101ALI20070104BHUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B26D   1/547       20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B62D  65/00        20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B62D  65/08        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-national country="US" status="new"><main-classification>083013</main-classification><further-classification>0832001</further-classification><further-classification>083651</further-classification></classification-national><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B25B  11/00C1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B26B  27/00A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B26D   1/547</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60J  10/00G10</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new">Method and a device for removing vehicle windows</invention-title></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>ERICSON ROLF</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>ERICSON ROLF</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>ERICSON ROLF</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Ericson</last-name><first-name>Rolf</first-name><address><city>Falun</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><correspondence-address sequence="1" format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>YOUNG &amp; THOMPSON</last-name><address><address-1>745 SOUTH 23RD STREET</address-1><address-2>2ND FLOOR</address-2><city>Arlington</city><state>VA</state><postcode>22202</postcode><country>US</country></address></addressbook></correspondence-address></parties><international-convention-data><pct-or-regional-filing-data ucid="SE-2004000800-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>SE</country><doc-number>2004000800</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20040521</date></document-id></pct-or-regional-filing-data></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new"><p num="p-0001">A method for the non-destructive removal of very small fixed window elements (<b>40</b>) from vehicles uses a cutting wire that is threaded through the adhesive bonding a window element to a vehicle, that is placed in a loop around the perimeter of the window element and that is pulled by wire wind-up elements (<b>3</b>) of a window element removal device. The device (<b>1</b>) is fitted to a window element frame (<b>41</b>), is expanded into firm clamping engagement with the window element frame (<b>41</b>) and is locked in the position firmly engaging the window element frame (<b>41</b>). The wire wind-up elements (<b>3</b>) are then operated until the wire cuts through the adhesive at the edge of the side window element around the entire perimeter thereof. </p></abstract><description lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new"><?summary-of-invention description="Summary of Invention" end="lead"?><heading>TECHNICAL FIELD </heading><p num="p-0002"> The present invention relates in general to fixed window elements of vehicles. In particular, the invention relates to a method and a device for removing a fixed side window from a vehicle. </p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION </heading><p num="p-0003"> The removal of fixed vehicle glazing in one piece for replacement or salvage purposes involves penetrating and cutting through the adhesive seal bonding a window element to an associated frame of a vehicle. Throughout the years, various methods for the removal of mainly vehicle windshields and rear windows have been suggested and practiced. Among such known methods are those where a knife or similar tool is used to cut through the adhesive bond and an outward pressure is simultaneously applied to the windshield, see e.g. <ref type="patent">U.S. Pat. No. 6,101,702</ref>. Other methods make use of a wire that is threaded through the adhesive bond and that is moved back and forth to cut through the seal all around the perimeter of the windshield, see e.g. <ref type="patent">U.S. Pat. No. 4,995,153</ref> and <ref type="patent">U.S. Pat. No. 5,629,093</ref>. All of the described methods are comparatively time-consuming and cumbersome and involve an apparent risk of damaging both the actual window element and interior or exterior parts of the vehicle. </p><p num="p-0004"> An improved method for the removal of vehicle windshields is described in my pending <ref type="patent">U.S. patent application Ser. No. 326,763</ref>. This method is based on the combined use of two separate tools that at spaced locations are secured to the windshield by means of suction cups and that each comprise means for winding up one end of the wire threaded through the adhesive bond of the windshield. Due to the considerable space required for the two separate hand tools and their re-positioning during the cutting operation, this method is specifically designed for the removal of windshields. </p><p num="p-0005"> Recently, there has been an increased interest in the non-destructive removal of fixed side window elements from vehicles. One of the main reasons for this is that insurance companies are becoming more and more reluctant to pay for the replacement of fixed side windows that are undamaged after an accident but that will have to be removed in order to perform high quality body repair and paint work. In such situations, it has up to the present day been common practice to crush the window element, with the resulting cleaning and additional cost of a new window element. The only remaining options are to use one of the above described time-consuming, cumbersome and possibly damaging methods employing a knife or a manually operated wire. Additionally, such methods often cause damages also to the actual window element, so that the window element will have to be replaced anyway. </p><p num="p-0006"> A specific problem in this respect arises for the very small and at present, mostly generally triangular, fixed side windows (sometimes referred to as “quarter lights”) that are becoming more and more frequent on modern automobiles. For such small side windows the use of the above mentioned pair of suction cup tools is quite out of the question, since the dimensions of said windows are often such that they would at best allow the application of a single suction cup. Therefore, there is a specific demand for a tool that would permit the efficient removal of such small side window elements from a vehicle frame. </p> <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION </heading><p num="p-0007"> The invention provides a solution overcoming the above discussed problems experienced with the prior known techniques for removing very small fixed window elements from vehicles. </p><p num="p-0008"> It is a basic object of the invention to provide an improved method for the effective non-destructive removal of very small fixed side window elements from a vehicle. </p><p num="p-0009"> It is a further object of the invention to provide an improved device for performing the method of the invention, for the effective non-destructive removal of very small side window elements. </p><p num="p-0010"> Briefly, the invention provides a method for removing very small fixed vehicle side windows using a cutting wire that is threaded through the window element adhesive, that is placed in a loop around the perimeter of the window element and that is forced to cut through the adhesive around the entire window element by being pulled by means of wire wind-up means of a window element removal device that is fixed relative to the window. According to the invention said device is fitted to a window element frame, is expanded into firm clamping engagement with the window element frame and is locked in said position firmly engaging the window element frame. The wire wind-up means are then operated until the wire cuts through the adhesive at the edge of the side window element around the entire perimeter thereof. The suggested method permits the use of a very compact device, both with regard to the actual space occupied thereby and with regard to the operation thereof. Therefore, said method provides a unique possibility for secure and effective non-destructive removal of very small fixed side window elements from vehicles. </p> <p num="p-0011"> According to another aspect of the present invention, the invention provides a window element removal device for use in performing the method of the invention, said means having cutting wire wind-up means and spaced attachment means supported by a common handle. According to the invention said attachment means each comprise at least one engagement member for engaging a window element frame and by means for allowing adjustment of the mutual distance between the first and second attachment means and for locking the attachment means in a position engaging said window element frame, to thereby mechanically clamp the device to the frame. The suggested tool is very compact and may be fitted to very small fixed side window elements. </p> <p num="p-0012"> These and further objects of the invention are met by the invention as defined in the appended patent claims. </p><p num="p-0013"> Advantages offered by the present invention, in addition to those described above, will be readily appreciated upon reading the below detailed description of embodiments of the invention.</p> <?summary-of-invention description="Summary of Invention" end="tail"?><?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS </heading><p num="p-0014"> The present invention and further objects, features and advantages thereof will be more fully understood by reference to the following detailed description of embodiments of the invention when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, where: </p><p num="p-0015"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is a top elevational view of a first embodiment of a device of the invention; </p><p num="p-0016"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> is a side elevational view of the device illustrated in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>; </p><p num="p-0017"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a partially schematic cross section along line A-A through a first attachment means of the device illustrated in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>; </p><p num="p-0018"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a partial view from below of the first attachment means of the device illustrated in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>; </p><p num="p-0019"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is a partial top plan view of a second attachment means of the device illustrated in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>; </p><p num="p-0020"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> is a side view of an engagement member of the second attachment means illustrated in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>; </p><p num="p-0021"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates the first embodiment of the device of the invention attached to the frame surrounding a small side window element of a vehicle; </p><p num="p-0022"> FIGS. <b>5</b>A-C illustrate the sequence of operations for removing a small side window element using a device of the present invention; </p><p num="p-0023"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a second embodiment of the device of the invention, attached to the frame surrounding a small side window element of a vehicle; </p><p num="p-0024"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. illustrates a third embodiment of the device of the invention attached to the frame surrounding a small side window element of a vehicle; </p><p num="p-0025"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a forth embodiment of the device of the invention attached to the frame surrounding a small side window element of a vehicle; and </p><p num="p-0026"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates a fifth embodiment of the device of the invention, having a modified adjustment means for expanding the device.</p><?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?><?detailed-description description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF EMBODIMENTS </heading><p num="p-0027"> An exemplary illustrative embodiment of the device or tool <b>1</b> according to the invention is illustrated in FIGS. <b>1</b>A-B, <b>2</b>A-B and <b>3</b>A-<b>3</b>B. The basic design of this tool <b>1</b> is based on that of a hand tool that is presently used in the inventors own system “Roll out 2000®” for cutting the sealant/adhesive bonding a vehicle windshield to the vehicle body and thus for removing such a windshield. In said basic design, the tool <b>1</b> has an elongate handle <b>2</b> connected to a wire wind-up means <b>3</b> and first and second tool attachment means <b>5</b>,<b>6</b> that are supported by each end section <b>2</b>A, <b>2</b>B of the handle <b>2</b>. </p><p num="p-0028"> In contrast to the above mentioned, known tool the wire wind-up means <b>3</b> of the tool <b>1</b> of the present invention is preferably provided with two winch mechanisms <b>7</b>,<b>8</b>. Said winch mechanisms <b>7</b>,<b>8</b> are supported on a bracket <b>4</b> that is attached to the tool <b>1</b>, generally at a mid-portion of the handle <b>2</b>. In this embodiment the pair of winch mechanisms <b>7</b>,<b>8</b> are provided side by side, at a distance from each other, along a line being approximately parallel to a centre axis C of the handle <b>2</b>. Said two winch mechanisms <b>7</b>,<b>8</b> on the tool <b>1</b> may be of the same general kind as the single one of the presently used hand tool. More particularly, such a winch mechanism <b>7</b>,<b>8</b> has a roller <b>9</b> for receiving and winding up a cutting wire <b>42</b> (indicated in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and in FIGS. <b>5</b>A-C). The wire <b>42</b> may be inserted into an eccentrically positioned opening <b>10</b> for holding the wire <b>42</b> to the roller <b>9</b> during winding-up rotation of the roller <b>9</b>. The winding-up roller <b>9</b> is rotatable in a winding-up direction WU(see <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>) and is provided with an internal locking mechanisms (not specifically illustrated) that normally prevents rotation of the roller <b>9</b> in the opposite direction. Each winch mechanism <b>7</b>,<b>8</b> has a release button <b>11</b> for releasing the locking mechanism so that the roller <b>9</b> may also be rotated in an opposite direction UW (<figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>) to unwind the wire <b>42</b>. </p><p num="p-0029"> Furthermore, in the tool <b>1</b> of the present invention, the first and second tool attachment means <b>5</b>,<b>6</b> each consist of frame engagement members <b>12</b> and <b>13</b>, <b>14</b>, respectively, for engaging a receiving frame <b>41</b> of a small fixed side window element <b>40</b>. In other words, here the engagement members <b>12</b>-<b>14</b> replace the suction cups of the known tool. The mutual distance between the tool attachment means <b>5</b>,<b>6</b> and thereby the overall length L of the tool <b>1</b>, see specifically <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>, is adjustable, so that the tool <b>1</b> is adaptable to the dimensions of the frame <b>41</b> of the window element <b>40</b> to be removed. The adjustability preferably provides a stepless adjustment of the overall length of the tool, the application of a separating force between the first and second attachment means <b>5</b>,<b>6</b> and the fixing of a mounted tool in the adjusted position, as will be described further below. </p><p num="p-0030"> In the illustrated embodiment of the invention said adjustability is provided by slidably receiving a rod-like carrier <b>16</b> of the first attachment means <b>5</b> in a central channel <b>2</b>C of the handle <b>2</b>. In this basic embodiment the separating force is applied simply by forcing, apart the first and second attachment means <b>5</b>,<b>6</b> by hand. The adjusted position of the carrier <b>16</b> and thereby of the overall length L of the tool <b>1</b> is then fixed by means of a locking means <b>17</b> consisting of a locking lever <b>17</b>A, preferably spring biased, that is mounted on the handle <b>2</b> and that in an inner end (not shown), extendable into the central bore <b>2</b>C of the handle, carries a stop means, such as a stop screw or stop pin, that by manipulation of the lever <b>17</b>A is brought into locking engagement with the carrier <b>16</b>. Although the details of the locking means <b>17</b> are not illustrated in detail, various types of such locking, means for fixing a rod in a selected position in a tabular channel, are well known to the man skilled in the art. Likewise, it shall be emphasized that the simple locking means <b>17</b> of the exemplifying embodiment is only used for illustrative purposes and <b>2</b>A of the handle <b>2</b>, such as schematically indicated at <b>17</b>′ in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>. </p><p num="p-0031"> Specifically, in the illustrated embodiment, and with specific reference to FIGS. <b>2</b>A-B, the first tool attachment means <b>5</b> comprises the above discussed carrier rod <b>16</b> that it an outer free end thereof carries one single, comparatively large engagement member <b>12</b> having a general disc shape. Said engagement member <b>12</b> has an outer circumferential window frame receiving channel <b>15</b> formed at its outer circumference, and in a bottom surface thereof is formed a recess <b>18</b> accommodating a further, generally disc shaped wire guide member <b>19</b>. The wire guide member <b>19</b> is provided with an outer circumferential cutting wire guide groove <b>20</b> and carries a shaft <b>21</b> by means of which it is rotatably and axially displaceably journalled in a sleeve <b>22</b> attached to an upper side of the first attachment means <b>12</b>. </p><p num="p-0032"> With regard to the axial displacement of the wire guide member <b>19</b> it is biased by a compression spring <b>23</b> that is positioned around the shaft <b>21</b>, at a position between the sleeve <b>22</b> and an operating knob <b>24</b> attached to an upper free end of the shaft <b>21</b>, so that the guide member is biased into a position where it is accommodated in the recess <b>18</b> of the engagement member <b>12</b>. By pushing the knob <b>24</b> the guide member <b>19</b> will be displaced from the recess <b>18</b> to expose the wire guide groove <b>20</b> and to allow the introduction of a cutting wire <b>42</b> into said groove <b>42</b>. By virtue of the biasing of the guide member <b>19</b>, the cutting wire <b>42</b> will then be “trapped” in the groove <b>20</b> as the knob is released. <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> illustrates a cutout <b>26</b> that is formed at the outer circumference of the recess <b>18</b> of the engagement member <b>12</b> and that serves to maintain the wire <b>42</b> in the guide member during installation of the tool <b>1</b>, as will be described further below. Likewise, a layer <b>25</b> of relatively soft protective material is preferably glued to the bottom surface of the guide member <b>19</b>, to avoid that the rotating guide member <b>19</b> damages the window element <b>40</b> during attachment and operation of the tool <b>1</b>. </p><p num="p-0033"> A second attachment means <b>6</b>, see especially FIGS. <b>3</b>A-B, is connected to the handle <b>2</b> at the opposite end section <b>2</b>B thereof and consists of a base plate <b>30</b> that has a general triangular shape and that is releasably connected to the handle <b>2</b> by means of a connector <b>31</b>. The connector <b>31</b> is secured to the base plate <b>30</b> at one of its corners and carries a spring biased pin <b>32</b> that may be brought into engagement with a bore <b>37</b> (schematically indicated in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>) in the handle <b>2</b> end section <b>2</b>B, to thereby releasably secure the attachment means <b>6</b> to the handle <b>2</b>. In the illustrated embodiment the second attachment means <b>6</b> comprises two second engagement members <b>13</b>, <b>14</b> that are secured to the base plate <b>30</b> at the respective remaining corners thereof by means of bolts <b>33</b>. The respective engagement members <b>13</b>, <b>14</b> consist of a body <b>34</b> having a circumferential window frame receiving channel <b>35</b> formed adjacent a lower free end thereof. </p><p num="p-0034"> The frame receiving channel <b>35</b> is preferably formed with such a width that even with the window frame <b>41</b> received therein it will still be able to accommodate also the cutting wire <b>42</b> for guiding purposes, as will be described below. Alternatively a separate wire guide groove (not illustrated) is formed in the body <b>34</b>, above the frame receiving channel <b>35</b>. The body <b>34</b> of the respective engagement member <b>13</b>, <b>14</b> is carried by an arm <b>36</b> that at one end is connected to the area of the upper end of the body <b>34</b> and that at its other end is secured to the base plate <b>30</b> by means of the above mentioned bolt <b>33</b>. By loosening the bolts <b>33</b> the engagement members <b>13</b>, <b>14</b> may be rotated individually, as illustrated in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, to a position that fits a specific window element that is to be removed. </p><p num="p-0035"> Rotation of the respective winding-up roller <b>9</b> of the wind-up means <b>3</b> is performed by means of a wrench-like handle <b>43</b> (see <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>), such as a ratchet wrench or other similar means, engaging a socket <b>44</b> provided at an upper end of each roller <b>9</b>. The two adjacent winch mechanisms <b>7</b>,<b>8</b> of the tool <b>3</b> are preferably each rotatable in the same directions WU and UW, respectively, for the winding-up and unwinding of the cutting wire <b>42</b>. It is perceived by the user to be most practical to wind up the two wire ends by rotating the associated winches in the same direction and in particular in combination with the use of a ratchet wrench that would otherwise have to be re-adjusted whenever it is moved from one winch to the other. </p><p num="p-0036"> The operation of the above described device/tool <b>1</b> in performing the method of the invention will now be explained with specific reference to <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>A-C. Initially, a cutting wire <b>42</b> is inserted through the adhesive normally bonding a fixed vehicle side window element <b>40</b> to a schematically indicated receiving frame <b>41</b>, see especially <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, of a vehicle that is not specifically illustrated. A length of the cutting wire <b>42</b> is inserted through the adhesive bonding between a side edge <b>40</b>A of the window element <b>40</b> and the frame <b>41</b> by means of a commonly used hollow needle, not illustrated. The length of the wire <b>42</b> is adapted to the size of the window element <b>40</b>, as will be clarified below. In particular, at an insertion point IP, both ends <b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>D of the wire <b>42</b> are inserted from a first side of the window <b>40</b>, normally an outside thereof, to a second side of the window <b>40</b>, which is normally the inside thereof, so that said free ends <b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>D are disposed inside the vehicle. </p><p num="p-0037"> For the best performance, the insertion point IP is chosen to be close to and to one side of the most pointed corner <b>40</b>B (see <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) of the window element <b>40</b> that may be referred to as the “difficult corner” of the window element. The wire end section <b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>B on the inside is significantly longer than the other wire end section <b>42</b>D, <b>42</b>E on the inside. The portion <b>42</b>C, <b>42</b>F of the wire <b>42</b> that is on the first side/outside of the window <b>40</b> is arranged in a closed loop around the perimeter of the window <b>40</b>, as will be seen in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>. The user may pull a bit on both ends on the inside so that the wire <b>42</b> is snugly applied around the edge <b>40</b>A of the window element <b>1</b> on the outside thereof, as shown in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>. </p><p num="p-0038"> Next, the tool <b>1</b> is brought to the vicinity of the window element <b>40</b>, where the guide member <b>19</b> of the first attachment means <b>5</b> is displaced from the recess <b>18</b> by pushing the knob <b>24</b>. This will expose the wire guide groove <b>20</b> and allow the introduction of the long end section <b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>B of the cutting wire <b>42</b> into said groove <b>42</b>. In order to securely maintain the wire section <b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>B in the glude member <b>19</b> groove <b>20</b> during installation of the tool <b>1</b>, the wire is positioned in the cutout <b>26</b> of the engagement member <b>12</b>, and then the knob is released so that the guide member is moved back into the recess <b>18</b> by virtue of the biasing of the guide member <b>19</b> and so that the cutting wire <b>42</b> will then be “trapped” in the groove <b>20</b>. </p><p num="p-0039"> The tool <b>1</b> is now fitted to the window element frame <b>41</b> with the first attachment means <b>5</b> positioned at a second corner <b>40</b>C of the window element <b>40</b> that is approximately opposite to the “difficult corner <b>40</b>B. The locking means <b>17</b> is released and the first and second attachment means <b>5</b> and <b>6</b> of the tool <b>1</b> are moved apart so that the engagement member <b>12</b> of the first attachment means <b>5</b> securely engages the window element frame <b>41</b> at or in the vicinity of said second corner <b>40</b>C and that the engagement members <b>13</b>, <b>14</b> of the second attachment means <b>6</b> firmly engage side edges of the frame <b>41</b> converging towards the first, “difficult corner” <b>40</b>B of the window element <b>40</b>. Installation of the tool <b>1</b> is then completed by applying an expansion force to firmly clamp the tool <b>1</b> to the frame and by finally engaging the locking means <b>17</b> again. The first wire end <b>42</b>A, and specifically its further adjacent inside wire section <b>42</b>B is now guided around the rotating wire guide member <b>19</b>, in its associated groove <b>14</b>. The wire end <b>42</b>A is attached to the roller <b>9</b> of one of the winch mechanisms <b>7</b>, as described above. In particular, the first wire end <b>42</b>A is attached to the winch mechanism roller <b>9</b> that is most distant from the first attachment means <b>5</b> guiding this wire end section <b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>B, for reasons to be described further below. Operating the wrench <b>43</b> activates the winch mechanism <b>7</b>, so that the wire is pulled and the tension thereof is increased. As the tension in the wire <b>42</b>A-<b>42</b>C is further increased, the wire <b>42</b> will start cutting through the adhesive between the window element <b>40</b> and the frame <b>41</b> in a direction towards the “difficult corner” <b>40</b>B. Depending upon the dimensions of the window element <b>40</b> the inside wire section <b>42</b>B will, during this initial cutting operation be guided by the engagement member <b>13</b> of the second attachment means <b>6</b> or not. </p><p num="p-0040"> This initial operation, tensioning the first wire section <b>42</b>A-C serves an important purpose in addition to the cutting action, since it is used to establish that the wire ends are not crossed at the insertion point IP. In case the wire ends were crossed at the insertion point. IP the tensioning of the first wire section <b>42</b>A-C would inevitably have the effect that the crossed, loose wire section <b>42</b>D-F would be brought along in the cutting movement of the tensioned wire section. As soon as it has been established that the wire sections are not crossed, the second end <b>42</b>D of the wire <b>42</b> may be attached to its associated winch mechanism S. At this stage it is optional whether to complete the operation of the first winch mechanism <b>7</b> or to alternatingly operate the two winches <b>7</b>,<b>8</b> until their associated wire sections <b>42</b>A-C, <b>42</b>D-F reach a meeting point P (see <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>), where the two wire section will meet to complete the cutting-loose of the window <b>40</b> from the frame <b>41</b>. Similarly to what was mentioned above, the other inside wire section <b>42</b>E may, during the corresponding cutting action, be guided by the other engagement member <b>14</b> of the second attachment means <b>6</b> or not. </p><p num="p-0041"> In the first case, the wire section <b>42</b>A-C is wound tip on the roller <b>9</b> of the first winch mechanism <b>7</b> and the cutting point moves from the insertion point IP and all the way up to the meeting point MP, until operation of the second winch mechanism <b>8</b> is initiated. In said first case it is not necessary to attach the second, loose wire end <b>42</b>D during the operation of the first winch <b>7</b>, since the wire <b>42</b> is prevented from sliding along the outer edges of the window <b>40</b> by the friction between the adhesive and the Wire <b>42</b>. However, in the latter case, the second end <b>42</b>D of the wire is attached to the winch mechanism. <b>8</b> as soon as it has been established that the wire sections do not cross, and the two winch mechanisms are operated alternatingly, until both wire sections <b>42</b>A-C and <b>42</b>D-F meet at the meeting point MP. </p><p num="p-0042"> By arranging the wire ends <b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>D so that they are attached to the respective winch mechanism roller <b>9</b> being most distant from the associated engagement means <b>5</b>,<b>6</b> and so that the wire ends cross in the area of the winch mechanisms, a favorable cutting angle is maintained during the fill cutting operation for both wire sections <b>42</b>A-C, <b>15</b>D-F. This means that effective cutting is achieved all around the perimeter of the window <b>40</b> without requiring any adjustment of the position of the single tool <b>1</b>. </p><p num="p-0043"> The method and device of the present invention are unique in that they permit secure non-destructive removal of very small fixed side windows from vehicles, since the tool is clamped directly to the window element frame and therefore eliminates the need for the relatively large suction cups that may only be secured to a window of certain minimum size. </p><p num="p-0044"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-8</figref> illustrate examples of possible modified arrangements of attachment means by the tool of the invention. Thus, <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a tool <b>101</b> of the invention secured to a window element frame <b>141</b> of a generally diamond shape window element <b>140</b>. Here, the tool <b>101</b> differs from that of the first embodiment in that the second attachment means <b>106</b> comprises a single engagement member <b>12</b> that is identical to the one of the first attachment means <b>5</b>, except that it is non-adjustably secured to the handle <b>2</b>. This second attachment means <b>106</b> likewise engages the window element frame <b>141</b> adjacent a sharp “difficult corner” <b>140</b>B of the diamond shape window element <b>140</b>. </p><p num="p-0045"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates a further embodiment of the tool <b>201</b> of the invention that is likewise secured to the diamond shape window element <b>140</b> of <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. In this case the second attachment means <b>206</b> consists of a modified base plate <b>230</b> that in addition to the engagement members <b>13</b>, <b>14</b> of the first embodiment carries a further engagement member <b>214</b> that fits directly onto the frame <b>141</b> at a corner <b>140</b>B of the window element <b>140</b>. </p><p num="p-0046"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates yet another embodiment of the inventive tool <b>301</b> secured to the, window element frame <b>341</b> of a window element <b>340</b> having the shape of a triangle with two equal sides. In this case the second attachment means <b>6</b> corresponds to that of the first embodiment whereas the first attachment means <b>305</b> consists of two engagement members <b>12</b> that are adjustably attached to a common base <b>335</b>, which is in turn supported by an adjustable rod-like carrier <b>16</b> like that of the first embodiment. The engagement members <b>12</b> are thereby adjustable so that they engage the window element frame <b>341</b> at the corners of the base of the triangle. Finally, <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates an embodiment of the inventive tool <b>401</b> where the adjustability of the overall tool length for adaption to a specific window element and die application of the separating force that secures the tool <b>401</b> to a window element frame (not illustrated) is achieve by means of a modified adjustment means <b>417</b>, consisting of a rack <b>416</b> that forms the carrier of the first attachment means <b>405</b> and that cooperates with a rotatably journalled nut member <b>417</b>A at the corresponding end section of the handle <b>402</b>. With such a means a stepless adjustment of the tool length may be performed and a controlled separating force may be applied to secure the tool <b>401</b> in position. </p><p num="p-0047"> The invention has been described in connection with what is presently considered to be the most practical and preferred embodiments, but it is to be understood that the invention is not to be limited to tie disclosed embodiments. Thus the invention is not restricted to configurations where adjustment of the tool length and the application of the tool expanding and clamping force is performed manually or with purely mechanical means, but also covers embodiments where said adjustment and force application is performed by means of pressurized fluid, such as by a pneumatic cylinder provided in or constituting the handle, or by means of an electric motor. In another variant, both of the first and second attachment means may be adjustable in position for adapting the overall length of the device <b>1</b>. Also, the tool has been disclosed in preferred embodiments where two winches are provided side by side on the handle to provide easy cutting operation. However, this does not preclude the use of a tool having the inventive characteristics but having only one single winch. With such an embodiment, a window element would be removed just as securely, but the operation would more inefficient and time consuming. </p><p num="p-0048"> The invention is therefore intended to cover various modifications and equivalent arrangements included within the spirit and scope of the appended claims. </p><?detailed-description description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?></description><claims lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new"><claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001"><claim-text><b>1</b>. A method of removing a fixed side window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) from a vehicle, said side window element having a first side and a second side and having an edge area (<b>40</b>A) being bonded to a receiving frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>) of the vehicle with an adhesive, by means of a device(<b>1</b>;<b>101</b>;<b>201</b>;<b>301</b>;<b>401</b>) having wire wind-up means (<b>3</b>) for pulling a cutting wire (<b>42</b>) through said adhesive and attachment means (<b>5</b>; <b>305</b>; <b>405</b>,<b>6</b>; <b>106</b>; <b>206</b>) for fixing said device relative to the window element, characterized by; 
<claim-text>fitting said device (<b>1</b>;<b>101</b>;<b>201</b>;<b>301</b>;<b>401</b>) to the window element frame(<b>41</b>); </claim-text><claim-text>expanding the device(l; <b>101</b>; <b>201</b>; <b>301</b>; <b>401</b>) to place the attachment means (<b>5</b>; <b>305</b>; <b>405</b>,<b>6</b>; <b>106</b>; <b>206</b>) in firm engagement with the window element frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>); </claim-text><claim-text>locking the device in said position firmly engaging the window element frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>); and </claim-text><claim-text>arranging a cutting wire (<b>42</b>) in a loop around the window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) and pulling the wire (<b>42</b>) by means of the wire wind-up means (<b>3</b>) until the wire cuts through the adhesive at the edge of the side window element around the entire perimeter thereof. </claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002"><claim-text><b>2</b>. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized by; 
<claim-text>inserting first and second ends (<b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>D) of the wire (<b>42</b>) from the first side of the side window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) through the adhesive to the second side of the side window element to form a loop of the wire on said first side thereof, and applying the loop of the wire along the edge of the side window element between the side window element and the frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>); </claim-text><claim-text>attaching the first end (<b>42</b>A) of the wire to a first wire wind-up mechanism (<b>7</b>) of the tool (<b>1</b>; <b>101</b>; <b>201</b>; <b>301</b>; <b>401</b>) secured to the window element frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>) and pulling the first end of the wire (<b>42</b>) with the first wire wind-up mechanism (<b>7</b>) to tension the wire; </claim-text><claim-text>attaching the second end (<b>42</b>D) of the wire to a second wire wind-up mechanism (<b>8</b>) of said tool; and </claim-text><claim-text>pulling the first and second ends of the wire until the wire cuts through the adhesive at the edge of the side window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) around the entire perimeter thereof. </claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003"><claim-text><b>3</b>. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that the tool (<b>1</b>;<b>101</b>;<b>201</b>;<b>301</b>;<b>401</b>) is maintained in its initial position on the window element frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>) during the entire process of cutting loose the window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) from the frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004"><claim-text><b>4</b>. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, characterized in that the first and second ends (<b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>D) of the wire are pulled one at a time by the associated wind-up mechanisms (<b>7</b>,<b>8</b>) until associated wire sections (<b>42</b>B-C, <b>42</b>E-F) reach a meeting point (MP) where the wire (<b>42</b>) has cut through the adhesive at the edge (<b>40</b>A) of the side window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) around the entire perimeter thereof. </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005"><claim-text><b>5</b>. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, characterized in that the first end (<b>42</b>A) of the wire (<b>42</b>) is pulled by its associated wind-up mechanism (<b>7</b>) until a corresponding section (<b>42</b>B, <b>42</b>C) of the wire has cut through the adhesive at the edge (<b>40</b>A) of the side window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) up to a meeting point(MP), before the second end (<b>42</b>D) of the wire is pulled by its associated wind-up mechanism (<b>8</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006"><claim-text><b>6</b>. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, characterized in that the first and second ends (<b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>D) of the wire arealternatingly pulled by the associated wind-up mechanisms (<b>7</b>,<b>8</b>) until associated wire sections (<b>42</b>B-C, <b>42</b>E-F) reach a meeting point (MP) where the wire (<b>42</b>) has cut through the adhesive at the edge (<b>40</b>A) of the side window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) around the entire perimeter thereof. </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007"><claim-text><b>7</b>. A device (<b>1</b>; <b>101</b>; <b>201</b>; <b>301</b>; <b>401</b>) for removing a side window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) fixed to a window element frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>) of a vehicle, having wire wind-up means (<b>3</b>) and spaced first and second attachment means (<b>5</b>; <b>305</b>; <b>405</b>, and <b>6</b>; <b>106</b>; <b>206</b> respectively) that are supported at respective ends (<b>2</b>A and <b>2</b>B, respectively) of a common handle (<b>2</b>; <b>402</b>), characterized in that said first and second attachment means (<b>5</b>; <b>305</b>; <b>405</b>, and <b>6</b>; <b>106</b>; <b>206</b> respectively) each comprise at least one engagement member (<b>12</b>; and <b>13</b>,<b>14</b>; <b>12</b>; <b>214</b> respectively) for engaging the window element frame and by adjustment means (<b>16</b>,<b>17</b>; <b>416</b>,<b>417</b>) for allowing adjustment of the mutual distance between the engagement members of the first and second attachment means and for locking the attachment means in a position engaging said window element frame to thereby mechanically clamp the device to the frame. </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008"><claim-text><b>8</b>. A device (<b>1</b>; <b>101</b>; <b>201</b>; <b>301</b>; <b>401</b>) according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, characterized in that the engagement member or members (<b>12</b>) of said first attachment means (<b>5</b>; <b>305</b>; <b>405</b>) is/are provided with a circumferential channel (<b>15</b>) for receiving a section of the window element frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009"><claim-text><b>9</b>. A device(<b>1</b>; <b>101</b>; <b>201</b>; <b>301</b>; <b>401</b>) according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, characterized in that the engagement member or members (<b>12</b>) of at least said first attachment means (<b>5</b>; <b>305</b>; <b>405</b>) is/are provided with a rotating wire guide member (<b>19</b>) having an outer circumferential guide groove (<b>20</b>) for receiving a cutting wire (<b>42</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010"><claim-text><b>10</b>. A device (<b>1</b>; <b>101</b>; <b>201</b>; <b>301</b>; <b>401</b>) according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, characterized by a recess (<b>18</b>) formed in a bottom surface of the engagement member (<b>12</b>), in that the wire guide member (<b>19</b>) is accommodated in said recess and is maintained therein by a biasing force and in that the wire guide member is axially displaceable out from the recess, against the biasing force, to expose said wire guide groove (<b>20</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011"><claim-text><b>11</b>. A device (<b>1</b>;<b>101</b>;<b>201</b>;<b>301</b>; <b>401</b>) according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, characterized in that the engagement member or members (<b>13</b>,<b>14</b>; <b>12</b>; <b>214</b>) of said second attachment means (<b>6</b>; <b>106</b>; <b>206</b>) is/are each provided with a circumferential channel (<b>35</b>; <b>15</b>) for receiving a section of the window element frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012"><claim-text><b>12</b>. A device (<b>1</b>;<b>101</b>;<b>201</b>;<b>301</b>;<b>401</b>) according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, characterized in that the frame receiving channel (<b>35</b>; <b>15</b>) of the engagement member or members (<b>13</b>,<b>14</b>; <b>12</b>; <b>214</b>) of said second attachment means (<b>6</b>; <b>106</b>; <b>206</b>) has a width sufficient for receiving not only the window element frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>) but also a cutting wire (<b>42</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013"><claim-text><b>13</b>. A device(<b>1</b>; <b>401</b>) according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, specifically intended for side window elements (<b>40</b>) having a generally triangular shape, characterized in that the first attachment means (<b>5</b>; <b>405</b>) comprises one single first engagement member (<b>12</b>) and in that the second attachment means (<b>6</b>) comprises two second engagement members (<b>13</b>,<b>14</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014"><claim-text><b>14</b>. A device (<b>1</b>) according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, characterized by two wire wind-up mechanisms (<b>7</b>,<b>8</b>) supported by the handle (<b>2</b>) at a distance from each other. </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015"><claim-text><b>15</b>. A device(<b>1</b>; <b>101</b>; <b>201</b>; <b>301</b>; <b>401</b>) according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, characterized in that the engagement member or members (<b>12</b>) of at least said first attachment means (<b>5</b>; <b>305</b>; <b>405</b>) is/are provided with a rotating wire guide member (<b>19</b>) having an outer circumferential guide groove (<b>20</b>) for receiving a cutting wire (<b>42</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016"><claim-text><b>16</b>. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, characterized in that the tool (<b>1</b>;<b>101</b>;<b>201</b>;<b>301</b>;<b>401</b>) is maintained in its initial position on the window element frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>) during the entire process of cutting loose the window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) from the frame (<b>41</b>; <b>141</b>; <b>341</b>). </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017"><claim-text><b>17</b>. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, characterized in that the first and second ends (<b>42</b>A, <b>42</b>D) of the wire are pulled one at a time by the associated wind-up mechanisms (<b>7</b>,<b>8</b>) until associated wire sections (<b>42</b>B-C, <b>42</b>E-F) reach a meeting point (MP) where the wire (<b>42</b>) has cut through the adhesive at the edge (<b>40</b>A) of the side window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) around the entire perimeter thereof. </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018"><claim-text><b>18</b>. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, characterized in that the first end (<b>42</b>A) of the wire (<b>42</b>) is pulled by its associated wind-up mechanism (<b>7</b>) until a corresponding section (<b>42</b>B, <b>42</b>C) of the wire has cut through the adhesive at the edge (<b>40</b>A) of the side window element (<b>40</b>; <b>140</b>; <b>340</b>) up to a meeting point(MP), before the second end (<b>42</b>D) of the wire is pulled by its associated wind-up mechanism (<b>8</b>).</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure id="figure-D00000" num="00000"><img id="EMI-D00000" he="109.60mm" wi="69.15mm" file="US20070000361A1-20070104-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00001"  num="00001"><img id="EMI-D00001" he="250.61mm" wi="166.45mm" orientation="landscape" file="US20070000361A1-20070104-D00001.TIF"  alt="embedded image"  img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"  inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00002" num="00002"><img id="EMI-D00002" he="244.77mm" wi="166.79mm" orientation="landscape" file="US20070000361A1-20070104-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00003" num="00003"><img id="EMI-D00003" he="220.64mm" wi="163.41mm" orientation="landscape" file="US20070000361A1-20070104-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00004" num="00004"><img id="EMI-D00004" he="241.30mm" wi="145.46mm" file="US20070000361A1-20070104-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00005" num="00005"><img id="EMI-D00005" he="237.57mm" wi="169.25mm" file="US20070000361A1-20070104-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00006" num="00006"><img id="EMI-D00006" he="247.90mm" wi="175.43mm" orientation="landscape" file="US20070000361A1-20070104-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00007" num="00007"><img id="EMI-D00007" he="244.01mm" wi="165.69mm" orientation="landscape" file="US20070000361A1-20070104-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00008" num="00008"><img id="EMI-D00008" he="213.61mm" wi="138.77mm" orientation="landscape" file="US20070000361A1-20070104-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></figure></drawings><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>
