<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><patent-document country="WO" doc-number="1995010826" kind="A1" ucid="WO-1995010826-A1" lang="EN" family-id="20391447" status="new" date-produced="20090507" date="19950420"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-1995010826-A1" status="new" fvid="78034314"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1995010826</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>19950420</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="SE-9400967-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>SE</country><doc-number>9400967</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>19941014</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="SE-9303411-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>SE</country><doc-number>9303411</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19931015</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>6</edition><main-classification>G08B  19/02</main-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G08B  19/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G08B  19/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">G08B  19/02</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">DEVICE FOR INDICATING ICE FORMATION</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">DISPOSITIF SIGNALANT LA FORMATION DE VERGLAS</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="CH-506850-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>CH</country><doc-number>506850</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3305851-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3305851</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4210021-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4210021</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4819480-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4819480</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>AGENZIA INTERNATIONAL AB</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BOSTROEM ROLAND</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NACHEBIA BEZAN</name><address><country>RU</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OLINGSBERG RAGNVALD</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant> <applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TAITS DIMITRI</name><address><country>RU</country></address></addressbook></applicant> <applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AGENZIA INTERNATIONAL AB</name> </addressbook></applicant> <applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BOSTROEM, ROLAND</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NACHEBIA, BEZAN</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OLINGSBERG, RAGNVALD</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TAITS, DIMITRI</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BOSTROEM ROLAND</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NACHEBIA BEZAN</name><address><country>RU</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OLINGSBERG RAGNVALD</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TAITS DIMITRI</name><address><country>RU</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BOSTROEM, ROLAND</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NACHEBIA, BEZAN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OLINGSBERG, RAGNVALD</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TAITS, DIMITRI</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention refers to a device for indicating ice formation, when necessary also already existing ice, on a surface exposed to ice formation of an object, by using a sensor (2) comprising a temperature difference measuring device, preferably a Peltier element (4), that has one of its contact surfaces (5) in thermal contact with the surface (6) exposed to ice formation. According to the invention, the ice formation is detected through measurement of the change in heat flow which occurs at said contact surface (5) due to the heat released in connection with ice formation, which measurement is carried out by connecting a voltage indicator to the connecting lines (11, 12) of the Peltier element. After having established that ice has formed, these wires can, if the sensor is a Peltier element (4), be connected to a current source (33) for alternate heating and temperature sensoring of said contact surface (5), whereby the surface temperature will remain 0  DEG C as long as there is ice and considerably higher if there is no ice, which in turn is indicated by an indicator (22) that is connected to the voltage indicator.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention concerne un dispositif indiquant la formation de verglas et, si besoin est, le verglas existant, sur une surface d'un objet exposée à la formation de verglas au moyen d'un capteur (2) doté d'un dispositif de mesure d'écart de température, de préférence un élément Peltier (4), dont une surface de contact (5) est en contact thermique avec la surface (6) exposée à la formation de verglas. Dans le dispositif selon l'invention, la formation de verglas est détectée par la mesure du changement de flux de chaleur au niveau de ladite surface de contact (5) résultant de la chaleur dégagée par rapport à la formation de verglas, ladite mesure étant réalisée par connexion d'un indicateur de tension aux lignes de connexion (11, 12) de l'élément Peltier. Une fois la formation de verglas constatée, ces fils peuvent être connectés à une source de courant (33), si le capteur est un élément Peltier (4), de manière à assurer en alternance le chauffage et le captage de ladite surface de contact (5), la température de la surface étant de 0  DEG C tant qu'il y a du verglas. La température de ladite surface est, en revanche, nettement supérieure lorsqu'il n'y a pas de verglas, condition signalée par un indicateur (22) connecté à l'indicateur de tension.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>--><p num="p0001">DEVICE FOR INDICATING ICE FORMATION</p><p num="p0002">The present invention relates to a device for indicating ice formation, which device is of the kind stated in the preamble of the accompanying claim 1 .</p><p num="p0003">A device of this kind can for example have the properties, as shown in the Swiss Patent publication 506 850, to indicate a commencing ice formation on a road surface. Here, a sensor with a Peltier element encompassed in a cap is embedded in the road surface coating at a short distance below the surface. Further, at a distance apart from each other, two temperature sensors are embedded in the road surface coating and are by means of two electric wires connected to a connecting device inside the cap. The Peltier element's lower contact surface is connected to a metal plate, which plate constitutes a heat dissipating reference surface to the road surface, and its upper contact surface is connected to one of the temperature sensors by a thick conductor made of copper. The contact surfaces are connected to a current source with such a polarity that the upper contact surface is cooled and in turn cools the copper conductor and the adjacent temperature sensor. This means that when the outside temperature is decreasing and the road surface is cooled towards 0°C, this will primarily result in a freezing into ice of moisture or present water on to the temperature sensor, which is cooled by the Peltier element. The formation of ice is remotely recorded as a temperature raise by the cooled temperature sensor by means of an apparatus for signal processing which is suitably placed and connected to the two temperature sensors. If the outside temperature decreases further, moisture and water on the road surface will freeze as well as on the second temperature sensor. This second sensor will also give rise to an indication of a temperature leap in the apparatus for signal processing as a sign that ice formation on the road surface has occured. The distance between the temperature raises represents the time of fore-warning by means of which the indication of a present risk for ice formation is alarmed.</p><p num="p0004">The device is however afflicted with several deficiencies. First, if a continuous decrease of temperature does not occur after the artificially cooled temperature sensor has indicated ice formation, a false warning occurs. Second, the device demands quite a lot of space and thus it is difficult to integrate into, for example a metal sheet. The third and most serious deficiency is however the fact that ice formation often occurs without any temperature increase in the surface of interest. For example, this is the case of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
slow cooling down of a wet surface. In connection with the formation of ice, an equalization of the temperature only takes place at 0°C, and thereafter the temperature decreases after all the water has frozen. Thus, in this case there will be no indication of occured ice formation.</p><p num="p0005">The purpose of the invention is to produce a simplified device, that will secure the indication of ice formation almost in the very moment it occurs, and which also can be used to control how long the formed ice remains, another important aspect of the problem of detecting ice. Further, the device must be easy to integrate with different objects where ice may form.</p><p num="p0006">By endowing the device for indication of ice formation with the characteristics stated in the accompanying claims, the above stated purposes have been obtained through this invention. As the changes of temperature of the measuring surface is an unreliable indicator of the occurance of ice formation, according to what is stated above, the heat flow that always is released when ice forms will be used instead according to claim 1. The major quantity of heat resleased in connection with the formation of ice will penetrate the measuring object, and will thereby affect the heat flow that passes through the object. A commonly used method for recording heat flow is to measure the temperature difference between two closely spaced points in the direction of the heat flow. Especially useful is a Peltier element which is used in this invention.</p><p num="p0007">The device according to the invention will be extremely compact and easy to integrate with different surfaces. The sensor in itself may be designed as an easily integrated, small canister a few millimeters thick and containing a Peltier element or its equivalent, and which can, by a small number of conducting wires, be remotely affected, first to passively sense the released latent heat of ice formation, and thereafter to actively, by periodic, short-term heating of the measuring surface cause a melting of an extremely thin layer adjacent to the measuring surface, causing the temperature of this layer to become 0"C, followed by momentuous passive sensing indicating whether ice formation has occured or not. Note especially that the device is insensitive to the purity of the ice layer, for example contents of sand, and also for its surface nature as well as for possible vibrations etc.</p><p num="p0008">The invention is described in more detail in the following description taken in connection with the accomapying drawing which schematically shows two examples of devices in 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/> -->
accordance with the invention. Figure 1 is is a cross-sectional view of a sensor embedded in a road surface coating. Figure 2 is a schematic block diagram of a simple design of a device for indication of ice formation only. Figure 3 is an example of a graph showing the generated electric voltage released from the sensor, and Figure 4 is a schematic block diagram of a more complete device which will indicate ice formation as well as already existing ice.</p><p num="p0009">Figure 1 shows a road surface coating 1 , into which a sensor 2 is embedded. The sensor 2 consists of a circular cap 3 with an open top made of metal which contains a Peltier element 4 with a primary contact surface 5 in thermal contact with a circular metal plate 6, and a second contact surface 7 in thermal contact with the bottom 8 of the cap 3, into which a bottom temperature sensor 9, for example a thermistor, complete with lines 13, 14 is embedded. On top of the road surface coating 1 and the metal plate 6 of the sensor, an ice layer 10 has formed. The Peltier element 4 is accustomly provided with two poles P1 and P2 and connecting lines 1 1 , 12, to which a voltage indicator can be connected for passive sensing of the the temperature difference between the contact surfaces, or to which a current source 33 can be connected for active generation of increasing or decreasing of the temperature of the contact surface 5 depending on the direction of the current.</p><p num="p0010">In Figure 2, the sensor 2 is shown with its lines 1 1 , 12 and 13, 14 connected to a signal processing device 21 .</p><p num="p0011">Figure 3 shows the voltage curve characteristics, measured at the lines 1 1 , 12. When ice formation starts at the point marked A, some of the heat released in connection with the ice formation penetrates the metal plate 6 and continues penetrating the Peltier element 4, thus causing a change in the temperature difference between the contact surfaces 5 and 7 of the element, and by this also causing a change in the thermoelectric output voltage from the element. The thermoelectric voltage, which can be registered by an ordinary voltage indicator, is proportional to the rate of ice formation. At normal rates of ice formation, a heat affection occurs of the magnitude 0,1 °C in temperature difference across the Peltier element. By modern Peltier elements, this temperature difference equals a change in voltage of a few mV. When the formation of ice has ended, point B, the signal returns to approximately the same magnitude as at the time of the beginning of ice formation, point A. The signal character at the time of the beginning of ice formation will always be distinct and the curve slope dV/dt is great and significant, and it can be used as a criteria for identifying the signal and for 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
discriminating this particular signal from signals that depend on other disturbances in the heat flow, such as wind effects, contacts with unfamiliar objects etc. Other signal criteria consist of the signal reaching a certain magnitude, being of a certain duration, having the correct polarity, e g that the heat affecting the device shall be directed from outside and into the device, and, of course, that the temperature registered by the temperature sensor 9 through the lines 13, 14 is less than or equal to 0°C. If all these criteria are met, the signal will proceed to the ice formation indicator 22. Any indication of a vanishing ice layer will not be obtained by this design.</p><p num="p0012">For this purpose, the device is with advantage designed according to what is shown in Figure 4. A switch 31 is connected between the sensor 2 and the signal processing device 21 and this switch is controlled by a timer 32. Also connected to the switch 31 is a current source 33. The signal processing device 21 has two input connections 34, 35 of which one is used before the timer is started in order to detect the commencing ice formation, and the other is used to detect the presence of ice. Further, the thermistor 9 is adjusted in order to indicate the voltage 0 when the temperature is equal to 0°C, thus its output voltage will be proportional to the temperature at the bottom 8 of the cap 3.</p><p num="p0013">Initially, the switch 31 will be set in a position where the sensor 2 is connected to the input connection 34 of the signal processing device 21 . The function of the device is here as described in connection with Figures 1 - 3. This position can be initiated by the temperature sensor 9, at a time when it indicates a given temperature, for example 5"C. Thus, when there appears an indication for commencing ice formation, the timer 32 will switch to a cyclical mode of the switch 31 . First, the current source 33 is connected to the sensor 2, with such an effect to cause an extremely thin layer of ice adjacent to the metal plate 6 to melt. Thus, the temperature of this layer will be 0°C. Hereafter, the timer 32 connects the sensor 2 to the input connection 35 of the signal processing device 21 , e g the heating ends and a thermoelectric voltage will instead be fed to input connection 35 from the Peltier element. This thermoelectric voltage is proportional to the temperature of the lower contact surface 7 and the bottom 8 of the cap 3, e g the temperature measured by the thermistor 9. In the signal processing device 21 he two electric voltages, the voltage from the Peltier element 4 and the voltage from the thermistor 9, are compared. As the Peltier element and the thermistor measure the very same temperature difference, they are in concordance, and the indicator 22 thus will 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
indicate the presence of ice. As long as the ice layer exists, the timer 32 will continue to cyclicly connect the current source 33 to the sensor 22 for a short duration and thereafter the sensor 2 to the input connection 35 of the signal processing device 21 and so on, until the ice has vanished. When the ice has vanished, the temperature of the metal plate 6 will no longer be 0°C, but considerably higher and thus the voltage from the sensor 2 will be considerably higher than the voltage from the thermistor 9, which voltage is of an unaltered magnitude. In this case, the indicator 22 will indicate that there no longer exists an ice layer on the surface. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>CLAI MS</claim-text><claim-text>1. A device for indicating the formation of ice (10) on a measuring surface (6) of an object (1) exposed to ice formation, for example a road surface, the wing of an air plane or an electric power line, by using a sensor (2) reacting to the heat influence into the measuring surface (6) which arises due to the heat released in connection with ice formation, characterized in that the sensor (2) comprises a Peltier element (4) with two contact surfaces (5, 7) for measurement of a temperature difference between the contact surfaces and with the first contact surface (5) in good thermal contact with the measuring surface (6) and the second contact surface in good thermal contact with a reference surface within the object (1) at a distance from the measuring surface (6), in addition to which a signal processing device (21) connectable to the contact surfaces (5, 7) is arranged, in order to indicate, and preferably initiate an indicator (22), when a predetermined course of signal occurs.</claim-text><claim-text>2. A device according to claim 1, characterized in that a timer (32) is arranged to alternately, at preset time intervals, connect either a current source (33) or the signal processing device (21) to the contact surfaces (5,7) of the Peltier element (4), the current of the source (33) being adapted such, that a thin layer of ice (10) in contact with the measuring surface (6) is brought to melt as long as an ice cover i present.</claim-text><claim-text>3. A device according to claims 1 or 2 for indication of ice formation on an exposed surface, characterized in that the sensor (2) comprises a metal cap (3) which has an open top and is embedded in the surface (1) exposed for ice formation, and in which the Peltier element (4) is placed with its first contact surface (5) in thermal contact with a covering plate (6) mounted in the opening of the cap, and the second contact surface (7) in thermal contact with the bottom of the cap (8).</claim-text><claim-text>4. A device according to any of claims 1 -3, charachterized in that the indicator (22) is arranged to be initiated by a course of signal of the signal processing device (21) with a change in voltage that has a predetermined magnitude, duration, slope and polarity at a temperature less than or equal to 0°C. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>