<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<patent-document country="WO" doc-number="2008070731" kind="A2" ucid="WO-2008070731-A2" lang="EN" date="20080612" family-id="39493704" date-produced="20090522" status="new"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="89358667" ucid="WO-2008070731-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2008070731</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20080612</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-2007086524-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>2007086524</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20071205</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-56765206-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>56765206</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20061206</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10G  47/00        20060101CFI20080612BHUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10G  47/02        20060101AFI20080612BHUS        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><invention-title lang="EN" load-source="docdb" status="new">INTEGRATED UNSUPPORTED SLURRY CATALYST PRECONDITIONING PROCESS</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" load-source="docdb" status="new">PROCÉDÉ DE PRÉCONDITIONNEMENT D'UN CATALYSEUR CONSTITUÉ DE BOUE NON SUPPORTÉ ET INTÉGRÉ</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-20040256286-A1" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>20040256286</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="Y" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20050006283-A1"  status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>20050006283</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="Y" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20060058175-A1" status="new"><document-id format="epo"  status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>20060058175</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA"  category="Y" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4721606-A"  status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>4721606</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="Y" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>BRAIT AXEL</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>CHEVRON USA INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>REYNOLDS BRUCE E</name> <address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>BRAIT, AXEL</name> </addressbook> </applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>CHEVRON U.S.A. INC.</name> </addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>REYNOLDS, BRUCE E.</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>BRAIT AXEL</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>REYNOLDS BRUCE E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>BRAIT, AXEL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>REYNOLDS, BRUCE E.</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" source="national office" load-source="docdb" status="new"><p>A process for slurry hydroprocessing, which involves preconditioning a slurry catalyst for activity improvement in vacuum residuum hydroprocessing units. Preconditioning the slurry catalyst raises its temperature, thereby reducing shock on the catalyst slurry as it enters the hydroprocessing reactor.</p></abstract><abstract lang="FR" source="national office" load-source="docdb" status="new"><p>Procédé d'hydrotraitement de boue, qui implique le préconditionnement d'un catalyseur constitué de boue pour une amélioration de l'activité dans les unités d'hydrotraitement des matières résiduelles sous vide. Le préconditionnement du catalyseur constitué de boue augmente sa température, ce qui réduit le choc sur la boue catalytique lorsqu'elle pénètre dans le réacteur d'hydrotraitement.</p></abstract><description lang="EN" load-source="epoque" status="new"><p><pre xml:space="preserve" listing-type="other">
INTEGRATED UNSUPPORTED SLURRY CATALYST

PRECONDITIONING PROCESS

FIELD OF THE INVENTION

A process for slurry hyd reprocessing, which involves preconditioning a slurry catalyst for activity improvement in vacuum residuum hydroprocessing units.

BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION

Slurry catalyst compositions, means for their preparation and their use in hydroprocessing of heavy feeds are known in the refining arts. Some examples are discussed below:

<ref type="patent">U.S. Patent No. 4,710,486</ref> discloses a process for the preparation of a dispersed Group VIB metal sulfide hydrocarbon oil hydroprocessing catalyst. Process steps include reacting aqueous ammonia and a Group VIB metal compound, such as molybdenum oxide or tungsten oxide, to form a water soluble oxygen-containing compound such as ammonium molybdate or tungstate.

<ref type="patent">U.S.
 Patent No. 4,970,190</ref> discloses a process for the preparation of a dispersed Group VIB metal sulfide catalyst for use in hydrocarbon oil hydroprocessing. This catalyst is promoted with a Group VIII metal. Process steps include dissolving a Group VIB metal compound, such as molybdenum oxide or tungsten oxide, with ammonia to form a water soluble compound such as aqueous ammonium molybdate or ammonium tungstate.

Slurry hydroprocessing processes frequently operate at higher temperatures than those at which slurries comprising catalysts are synthesized and stored. For example, the slurry hydrocracking process of <ref type="patent">U.S. Publication No. 20060054533</ref> typically operates at a temperature of at least 800&lt;0&gt;F, with a hydrogen pressure from about 1500 psi to about 3500 psi.
 The slurry catalysts generally enter the reactor (or initial reactor, if more than one) of the vacuum residuum hyd reprocessing unit at a temperature around 45O&lt;0&gt;F and a hydrogen pressure of about 400 psi. This temperature and pressure differential shocks the highly active slurry catalyst and promotes the production of coke. Coke production decreases the effiency of conversion by this catalyst.

SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION

This application discloses a process for slurry hydroprocessi[pi]g, particularly slurry hydrocracking , in which the slurry catalyst is preconditioned prior to its entry into the reactor(s) of the vacuum residuum slurry hyd reprocess ing process.
 Preconditioning the slurry catalyst raises its temperature, thereby reducing shock on the catalyst slurry as it enters the hyd reprocess ing reactor.

The process of this invention is summarized as follows:

A process for the hydroprocessing of heavy oils, having at least one reaction stage, said process comprising the following steps:

(a) contacting a hydrocarbon feed stream under slurry hydroprocessing conditions with a hydrogen stream and a stream comprising slurry hydroprocessing catalyst, in a vacuum residuum slurry hydroprocessing unit, and recovering a product stream along with a stream comprising spent slurry hydroprocessing catalyst and unconverted hydrocarbon feed;


(b) passing the stream comprising spent slurry hydroprocessing catalyst and unconverted hydrocarbon feed to a deoiling unit, where it is combined with a solvent, products and gases then being recovered, as well as a stream comprising spent slurry catalyst;

(c) passing the stream comprising spent slurry catalyst to a metals recovery unit, where it is contacted with an ammonium leach solution in order to recover ammonium sulfate and compounds comprising Group VIII and Group VIB metals;

(d) passing the compounds comprising Group VIII and Group VIB metals to a catalyst synthesis unit, where they are contacted with ammonia, hydrogen sulfide gas, hydrocarbon stream, hydrogen and a small amount of water to create an active slurry catalyst in oil, the oil comprising ammonium sulfate;


(e) passing the effluent of step (d) into a preconditioning unit in order to increase the temperature and reduce shock on the slurry catalyst, wherein the effluent is contacted with hydrogen and is decomposed into hydrogen sulfide and ammonia, streams which are removed from the preconditioning unit;

(f) passing the effluent for step (e ), which comprises the active slurry catalyst in oil to storage or to a vacuum residuum slurry hydroprocessing unit.

BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE FIGURE

The Figure illustrates the process disclosed in this invention for vacuum residuum slurry hydroprocessing using preconditioned slurry catalyst.

DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION

Stream 1 , which comprises hydrogen, enters the vacuum residuum slurry hydroprocessing unit (VRHU) 10.
 Hydroprocessing processes which may be employed in this invention include hydrocracking, hydrotreating, hydrodesulfurization, hydrodenitrification, and hydrodemetallization. Hydrocracking is the preferred process, however. Also entering VRHU 10 is a feed stream 2(vacuum residuum is a common feed), hydrogen stream 3 and slurry catalyst stream 26 (which maybe admixed with Stream 3 comprising water). The slurry hydrocracking process typically operates at a temperature of at least 800&lt;0&gt;F, with a hydrogen pressure from about 1500 psi to about 3500 psi. The slurry catalyst, following preconditioning, generally enters the reactor (or initial reactor, if more than one) of the vacuum residuum hydroprocessing unit at a temperature around 700&lt;0&gt;F and a hydrogen pressure of about 2000 psi.

Products exit VRHU 10 through stream 55.
 Stream 4, the spent slurry catalyst stream comprising unconverted oil, enters a deoiling unit 20 where it is contacted by a solvent (stream 6) such as toluene or naphtha in order to remove products and gases (stream 5). Deoiling involves solid concentration and liquid removal, which may employ cross flow filtration, centrifugation, drying and quenching steps.

Stream 7 comprises deoiled spent slurry catalyst. Stream 7 enters the metals recovery unit (MRU 30). Enriched air enters the MRU 30 through stream 8. Stream 9 is a solvent suitable for metals extraction, such as ketoxime. Through a series of solvent extractions and crystallization steps in MRU 30, the metals from the oil stream are recovered, along with a byproduct of ammonium sulfate (stream 27). Vanadium is removed through stream 11 as V2O5.
 Spent metals extraction solvent is removed through stream 12 and wastewater is removed through stream 13.

The Group VIII metal employed in the CASH process is often nickel. Nickel is recovered as a nickel sulfate stream ( stream 14) and is passed to the catalyst synthesis unit (CSU 40). A portion of the nickel sulfate stream (stream 16) can be diverted to control the amount of nickel entering the catalyst synthesis unit (CSU 40). Recovered Group Vl metals, such as molybdenum, exit the MRU in stream 15. If the metal is molybdenum, it is recovered as an ammonium dimolybdate stream (stream 15) which is passed to the catalyst synthesis unit (CSU 40). A light hydrocarbon or VGO (vacuum gas oil) (stream 17) enters into the catalyst synthesis unit (CSU 40) along with a small amount of water (stream 18). Stream 19 comprises hydrogen.
 In the catalyst synthesis unit (CSU 40), conditions include a temperature in the range from 80&lt;0&gt;F to 200[deg.] F, preferably in the range from 100&lt;0&gt;F to 180[deg.] F, and most preferably in the range from 13O&lt;0&gt;F to 16O&lt;0&gt;F. Pressure is in the range from 100 to 3000 psig, preferably in the range from 200 to 1000 psig, and most preferably from 300 to 500 psig.

The ingredients are mixed in the CSU 40 to form an active slurry catalyst in oil. A small amount of ammonium sulfate, formed from the nickel sulfate and ammonia gas added to the CSU 40, is also present in this stream. The small stream of water (stream 18) acts to keep the small amount of ammonium sulfate in solution. This prevents precipitation in the equipment. The active slurry catalyst in oil (stream 21) enters into a catalyst preconditioning unit (CPU 50).
 Hydrogen enters the CPU 50 through stream 24.

The process conditions of the catalyst preconditioning unit (CPU 50) include temperature ranges from about 400&lt;0&gt;F to about 1000&lt;0&gt;F, preferably from about 500[deg.] to about 800&lt;0&gt;F, and most preferably from about 600&lt;0&gt;F to about 700&lt;0&gt;F. Pressure ranges from about 100 to about 3000 psi, preferably from 300 to about 2500 psi and more preferably from about 500 to about 2000 psi. The hydrogen rate is in the range from 2500 to 7500 scf/bbl, preferably from 500 to 6000 scf/bbl. Preconditioning of ammonium sulfate into hydrogen sulfide and ammonia requires about 2 hours.
 Residence time in the catalyst preconditioning unit (CPU) for the mixture comprising oil, slurry and ammonium sulfate is from 1.5 to three hours, preferably about 2 hours.

For every mole of hydrogen sulfide gas produced in the catalyst preconditioning unit (CPU 50 ) unit, 2 moles of ammonia are produced.

The CPU 50 is a continuously stirred tank reactor (CSTR or alternately, perfectly mixed reactor). This type of reactor is employed in order to prevent catalyst agglomeration. The residuum feedstock 2 to the process of the present invention is generally a high boiling hydrocarbonaceous material having a normal boiling range mostly above 600&lt;0&gt;F often having a normal boiling point range wherein at least 80% v/v of the feed boils between 600&lt;0&gt;F and 1500&lt;0&gt;F., or between 80O&lt;0&gt;F and 145O&lt;0&gt;F.
 Residuum feedstocks usefully processed in the present invention may contain more than 500 ppm asphaltenes or 1000 ppm asphaltenes, and may contain as much as 10,000 ppm asphaltenes or more. The residuum feedstocks also usually contain more than 10 ppm metals and greater than 0.1% by weight sulfur. The metals are believed to be present as organometallic compounds, but the concentrations of metals referred to herein are calculated as parts per million pure metal. The contaminating metals in the feed typically include nickel, vanadium and iron. The sulfur is present as organic sulfur compounds and the wt % sulfur is calculated based on elemental sulfur.
 Typical feedstocks for the present invention include deasphalted residua or crude, crude oil atmospheric distillation column bottoms (reduced crude oil or atmospheric column residuum), or vacuum distillation column bottoms (vacuum residua).

EXAMPLE

Typical vacuum residuum feed properties are listed in the following table:

API gravity at 60/60 3.9

Sulfur (wt%) 5.58

Nitrogen (ppm) 5770

Nickel (ppm) 93

Vanadium (ppm) 243

Carbon (wt%) 83.57

Hydrogen (wt%) 10.04

MCRT (wt%) 17.2

Viscosity (R) 212[deg.] F (cSt) 3727

Pentane Asphaltenes (wt%) 13.9

Fraction Boiling above 1050&lt;0&gt;F (wt%) 81 Typical process conditions used for heavy oil upgrading are listed as following:


Total pressure (psig) 2500

Mo/Oil ratio (%) 1.5

LHSV 0.25

Reactor temperature (T) 700-725&lt;0&gt;F

H2 gas rate (SCF/B) 7500

Two batches of slurry catalyst streams obtained as described above were sent to the vacuum residuum hydrocracking (VRHU) unit for use as catalyst. The first batch was sent to the VRHU directly from the catalyst synthesis unit or from storage, without preliminary preconditioning.

The second batch was preconditioned in hydrogen as shown in the Figure prior to entering the VRHU.

Side by side comparison of VRHU performance results for conditioned slurry catalyst v. unconditioned slurry catalyst, are provided in the table below:

Without With

Preconditionin[alpha] Preconditioning

Hydrodenitrogenation:
 80.5% 89.4%

Hydrodemetallization 97.2 98.6

Conversion of 1000F+ fraction 96.5 99.1

Conversion of 650F+ 69.8 74.1

Fraction

Conversion of 800F+

Fraction 88.3 91.8

The improvement is approximately equivalent to increasing the fresh catalyst dosage to the VRHU by 30%.
</pre></p></description><claims lang="EN" load-source="epoque" status="new"><claim num="1"><claim-text>WHAT IS CLAIMED IS: 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 1 A process for the hydroprocessing of heavy oils, having at least one reaction stage, said process comprising the following steps: 

</claim-text><claim-text>(a) contacting a hydrocarbon feed stream under slurry hydroprocessing conditions, with a hydrogen stream and a stream comprising slurry hydrocracking catalyst in a vacuum residuum slurry hydroprocessing unit, and recovering a product stream, along with a stream comprising spent slurry hydroprocessing catalyst and unconverted hydrocarbon feed; 

</claim-text><claim-text>(b) passing the stream comprising spent slurry hydroprocessing catalyst and unconverted hydrocarbon feed to a deoiling unit, where it is combined with a solvent, products and gases then being recovered, as well as a stream comprising spent slurry catalyst; 

</claim-text><claim-text>(c) passing the stream comprising spent slurry catalyst to a metals recovery unit, where it is contacted with an ammonium leach solution in order to recover ammonium sulfate and compounds comprising Group VlII and Group VIB metals; 

</claim-text><claim-text>(d) passing the compounds comprising Group VIII and 

</claim-text><claim-text>Group VIB metals to a catalyst synthesis unit, where they are contacted with ammonia, hydrogen sulfide gas, hydrocarbon stream, hydrogen and a small amount of water to create an active slurry catalyst in oil, the oil comprising ammonium sulfate; (e) passing the effluent of step (d) into a preconditioning unit in order to increase the temperature and reduce shock on the slurry catalyst, wherein the effluent is contacted with hydrogen and is decomposed into hydrogen sulfide and ammonia, streams which are removed from the preconditioning unit; 

</claim-text><claim-text>(f) passing the effluent for step (e ), which comprises the active slurry catalyst in oil to storage or to a vacuum residuum slurry hydroprocessing unit. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 2 The process of claim 1 , wherein water is added to the hydrocarbon feed stream prior to its entrance into the vacuum residuum slurry hydroprocessing unit. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 3 The process of Claim 1 , wherein slurry hydroprocessing conditions are selected from the group consisting of hydrocracking, hydrotreating, hydrodesulfurization, hydrodenitrification, and hydrodemetallization. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 4 The process of Claim 3, where in the process is slurry hydrocracking. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 5 The process of Claim 3, wherein the slurry hydrocracking process typically operates at a temperature of at least 8OO0F, with a hydrogen pressure from about 1500 psi to about 3500 psi 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 6 The process of Claim 1 , wherein hydrocarbon feedstocks which may be upgraded by slurry hydroprocessing have a normal boiling range above 600&lt;0&gt;F. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 7 The process of Claim 1 , in which the solvent employed in the deoiling unit, is toluene. Claim 8 The process of Claim 1 , wherein the stream comprising spent slurry catalyst is subjected to a series of solvent extractions and crystallization steps in the metals recovery unit in order to recover ammonium sulfate as well as compounds comprising Group VIII and Group VIB metals; 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 9 The process of Claim 8, wherein the Group VIII metal is nickel and the Group VIB metal is molybdenum. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 10 The process of Claim 8, in which the Group VIII metal compound is nickel sulfate and the Group VIB metal compound, is molybdenum dimolybdate. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 11 The process of Claim 1 , wherein the hydrocarbon stream of step (b) comprises a light hydrocarbon or vacuum gas oil. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 12 The process of Claim 1 , wherein conditions in the catalyst synthesis unit comprise a temperature in the range from 80&lt;0&gt;F to 200&lt;0&gt;F, preferably in the range from 100&lt;0&gt;F to 180&lt;0&gt;F, and most preferably in the range from 13O&lt;0&gt;F to 16O&lt;0&gt;F. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 13 The process of Claim 1 , wherein conditions in the catalyst synthesis unit comprise a pressure in the range from 100 to 3000 psig, preferably in the range from 200 to 1000 psig, and most preferably from 300 to 500 psig. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 14 The process of Claim 1 , in which a small stream of water is added to the catalyst synthesis unit in order to prevent agglomeration of ammonium sulfate. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 15 The process of Claim 1 , wherein conditions in the preconditioning unit comprise a temperature in the range from about 400&lt;0&gt;F to about 1000&lt;0&gt;F, preferably from about 500[deg.] to about 800&lt;0&gt;F, and most preferably from about 6OO0F to about 700&lt;0&gt;F. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 16 The process of Claim 1 , wherein conditions in the preconditioning unit comprise a pressure in the range from about 100 to about 3000 psi, preferably from 300 to about 2500 psi and more preferably from about 500 to about 2000 psi. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 17 The process of Claim 1 , wherein the hydrogen flow rate in the preconditioning unit is in the range from 2500 to 7500 scf/bbl and preferably from 5000 to 6000 scf/bbl. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 18 The process of Claim 1 , in which the residence time in the preconditioning unit is from 1.5 to three hours, preferably about 2 hours. 

</claim-text><claim-text>Claim 19 The process of Claim 1 , in which the preconditioning unit i is a constant stirred tank reactor.
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>
