<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="annotation.xsl"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="annotation.nvdl"?>
<fulltext-document system="ops.epo.org" fulltext-format="text-only" xmlns="http://www.epo.org/fulltext"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference data-format="docdb"><document-id><country>WO</country><doc-number>2011069562</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id></publication-reference></bibliographic-data><description lang="EN"><p>Human papillomavirus like structures prod uced i n a non- fermentative system based on insect larva 
 Field of the invention 
The invention pertains to the field of pharmacy, particularly to the sector of vaccine production and most particularly to the production of antigens, specifically L1 protein from Human Papillomavirus (HPV) in insect larvae as living biofactories. The antigens obtained thereof are useful for preparing efficient vaccines against HPV. 
State of the Art Human papillomavirus (HPV) is recognized as the main causative agent of invasive carcinomas of the uterine cervix (Sigurdsson et al., 2007). Cervical cancer is the most common cancer affecting women in developing countries, where 80% of deaths caused by this type of cancer occur. Among other considerations, affordability and cost-effectiveness of vaccination are the most important factors for application of HPV vaccines in developing countries. Two HPV types, HPV1 6 and HPV1 8, account for 60-70% of all cervical cancer cases worldwide (Ho et al., 1998; Muhoz et al., 2003). The inability to propagate HPV in vitro has led to the development of alternative approaches to antigen production for vaccine development (Carter et al., 1991 ; Rose et al., 1993; Xi and Banks, 1991 ). Successful development of papillomavirus vaccines is dependent upon the use of nondenatured, conformationally correct capsid antigens forming pentamers or VLPs (Bonnez, Rose, and Reichman, 1 992; Christensen and Kreider, 1990; Christensen et al., 1 990; Christensen et al ., 1992). The viral capsid is primarily composed of 72 pentamers (capsomers) of the major late L1 protein, in association with 12 or more copies of the L2 protein. The L1 pentamers have the intrinsic property of self-assembly into empty capsids, referred to as virus like particles (VLPs) (Hagensee, Yaegashi, and Galloway, 1 993; Kirnbauer et al ., 1992; Kirnbauer et al ., 1 993; Rose et al ., 1994; Zhou et al., 1993). VLPs are structurally and immunologically similar to infectious viruses, as determined by electron microscopy and their ability to bind conformation-dependent monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) (Kirnbauer et al., 1992). Conformational epitopes have been identified on the surface of HPV L1 VLPs (Christensen and Kreider, 1990). It is now well established that those epitopes are responsible for the activity of neutralizing antibodies (Christensen et al., 1994; White et al., 1998; White et al., 1999) and it has been demonstrated that high levels of neutralizing antibodies can be generated after immunization with HPV VLPs (Harro et al., 2001 ). Vaccines based on L1 capsid protein VLPs from several high risk HPV types have been proved to be effective against HPV infections. Raising high levels of neutralizing antibodies against each HPV type is believed to be the primary mechanism of protection, gained by vaccination. On June 8, 2006, the US FDA approved Gardasil, a prophylactic HPV vaccine from Merck. The vaccine showed protection against initial infection with the most common cancer inducers papillomaviruses, HPV types 16 and 18, but also against the warts- induced strains 6 and 1 1 . GlaxoSmithKline obtained in 2007 the approval for another prophylactic vaccine targeting H PV types 1 6 and 1 8, known as Cervarix. Those vaccines are made up with recombinant protein L1 , expressed in yeast or in insect cells by recombinant baculoviruses infection (Gardasil and Cervarix respectively), self-assembled into VLPs similar to the wild-type virus. The use of these production systems based on fermentation technologies are expensive which is one of the reasons that justify the elevated price of the vaccines in the market, (a complete round of vaccination costs around 450 $). There are disclosures concerning the production of proteins derived from L1 of HPV. Those L1 derived proteins lack of several amino acids (<bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">US6551597</bibl>), or they are encoded by cDNA sequences which translation starting point or a particular encoding codon is d i s p l a ced i n so m e n u c l eot i d e s (<bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">EP129821 1</bibl> ;<bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">EP1207203</bibl> ; <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">EP1471 147</bibl>) , or they have an amino acid (His 202) substituted (<bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">EP0662132</bibl>). There are other prior art documents which disclose capsomers with L1 epitope but which are not able to form VLPs (<bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WO99/01557</bibl>). In recent years, biotechnology has provided for the tools that allow the use of living organisms to produce recombinant vaccines with high efficiency but at a very low production costs. One of these alternatives is the use of insects as bioreactors (Liu, DeCarolis, and Beek, 2007; <bibl type="patent" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">EP0688227</bibl>). Recently, It has been described the obtention of rotavirus VLPs from infected Spodoptera frugiperda larvae using baculovirus, opening the option to get vaccines against rotavirus from insect larvae (Molinari, Peralta, and Taboga, 2008). There are other examples of recombinant subunit vaccines against infectious agents obtained from insects used as bioreactors (Chimeno Zoth et al., 2009; Hu, Yao, and Wu, 2008; Johansson, Price, and Kilbourne, 1995; Matsuoka et al., 1996; Pang et al., 2002). We currently have in clinical studies an insect larvae-derived recombinant subunit vaccine against rabbit hemorrhagic disease virus (RHDV) (Perez-Filgueira et al., 2007). 
HPV infection is a necessary factor in the development of nearly all cases of cervical cancer. Although the widespread use of Pap tests (Papanicolau test) has reduced the incidence and lethal ity of cervical cancer in developed countries, the disease still kills several hundred thousand women per year worldwide. More than any other cancer, cervical cancer reflects striking global health inequity. It is the second most common cancer among women worldwide, with about 493,000 new cases diagnosed annually. Of 274,000 deaths due to cervical cancer each year, more than 80% occur in developing countries, and this proportion is expected to increase to 90% by 2020 (Agosti and Goldie, 2007). Affecting relatively young women, it is the largest single cause of years of life lost by cancer in the developing world. Considerations for policymakers debating the use of HPV vaccine in any particular country include among other factors cost-effectiveness of vaccination relative to other programs competing for resources. The factors with the greatest influence on the cost-effectiveness of vaccination will be the price of the vaccine and the costs of a program to reach adolescents. These make urgent to develop lower production costs HPV vaccines for developing countries. 
The major structural protein of the HPV capsid, L1 , is one of the antigens of choice for the development of prophylactic vaccines. It is well known that expression of the L1 by recombinant baculoviruses in insect cell cultures is sufficient for the formation of VLPs which are highly immunogenic (Rose et al., 1993). Interestingly one of the two approved prophylactic HPV vaccines is expressed in insect cell cultures by fermentation technology by recombinant baculoviruses (Cervarix). However, although this technology platform is very efficient in recombinant protein production and generates highly immunogenic self-assembled L1 derived VLPs, the production costs increase the vaccine price at levels that can not be easily applied for HPV prevention programs in developing countries. To overcome this problem, other heterologous systems to produce L1 have been developed as bacteria, eukaryotic cell cultures or transgenic plants (Aires et al., 2006; Fernandez-San Millan et al., 2008; Fraillery et al., 2007; Heino, Dillner, and Schwartz, 1995; Kim et al., 2007; Maclean et al., 2007). However, none of them allow a significant cost reduction that would boost its wide use in developing countries. The main objective of this invention was the search for an HPV vaccine production technology that facilitate a potential dramatic cost reduction in order to facilitate its application in developing countries or extend the vaccination to other susceptible population . For such purpose, we have explored in th is invention th e u se of a n on-fermentative system based on insect larvae, particularly of Trichoplusia ni (T. ni) , as biofactories in combination with a recombinant baculovirus to produce HPV VLPs. 
Figure legends 
Figure 1. L1 protein expression, (a) Coomassie and Immunoblot analysis of L1 protein expression in infected larvae. BacNi is used as negative control of the infection, (b) Coomassie of soluble (1 ) and insoluble (2) proteins. Proteins were extracted from 0.5 mg larvae fresh weight. Purified 6xHis-L1 expressed in insect cells (L1 ) was used as a positive control (2 [mu]g). (c) Time-dose assays measured by ELISA and immunoblot. (d) L1 accumulation in larvae analysed by ELISA. The result is the average of the analysis of three independent larvae batches infected with baculovirus. As comparison, expression in chloroplast transgenic tobacco plants and baculovirus-infected insect cells is also shown . In insect cells 1 g of pelleted cells comes from 55 ml of culture. 
Figure 2. Purification of VLPs from Trichoplusia ni larvae, (a) Detection of L1 by ELISA in fractions of a CsCI gradient (fraction 1 corresponds to the bottom tube). The Cam Vir-1 anti-L1 mAb was used as primary antibody. The dotted l ine indicates the density of the d ifferent fractions, (b) Immunoblot of the different fractions of larvae extracts using the same antibody. The band corresponds to the L1 monomeric form, (c) Electron microscopy of negatively stained VLPs from fraction 4 of the CsCI gradient. I and III from larvae extracts; II and IV from insect cell extracts, (d) Sucrose sedimentation analysis of L1 derived from larvae extracts, detected by ELISA with the Cam Vir-1 mAb. Soluble proteins from larvae and insect cells were fractionated by sucrose gradient centrifugation (fraction 1 corresponds to the tube bottom). The dotted line indicates the refractive index of the different fractions. The arrow indicates the fraction in which the standard (corresponding to capsomers' size) migrated. 
Figure 3. Analysis of the L1 -induced antibody response in mice. Titres of antibodies induced by larvae-derived L1 protein against native yeast-derived VLPs. Balb/c mice were intraperitoneally immunized. Groups of mice immunized with A: partially purified larvae-derived VLPs ; B: partially purified negative control-larvae extracts; C: partially purified VLPs from insect cells. Data are presented as measures for individual mouse. 
Description of the invention 
In present invention we have surprisingly obtained high yield production of L1 protein of HPV, in insect larvae (T. ni) that self-assembles forming the same type of HPV-like pentamers or VLPs that have been found in other expression systems which are currently used in vaccine formulations against this important infectious disease. One gram of the infected insect larvae biomass of the invention is able to produce, in optimal conditions, 18-21 mg of totally soluble recombinant L1 protein. Th is means a 2.5 times the L1 production yields obtained i n i n sect cel l cu l tu res a nd 5 t i m es more p rod u ct ivity th a n transplastomic tobacco plants per biomass unit (Fernandez-San Millan et al ., 2008). Therefore, the yield of the process of present invention is higher when com pared with other systems for production of recom binant proteins, particularly virus like capside proteins or VLPs, existing in the state of the art. Another interesting feature of the insect larvae platform technology of present invention is that the system requires lower amounts of baculovirus inocula than the insect cell cultures for protein expression optimization. Th is is of great interest from a practical point of view since the production cost of the baculovirus stocks could be also reduced. Furthermore, the necessity to generate high titre virus stocks and the difficulty to get them would be also avoided with the insect larvae expression system. As a way of example, for the same number of protein producing cells (10&lt;9&gt;), when the insect larvae biofactory of present invention is used, only 10&lt;4&gt; virus are needed. While in the cells systems existing in the state of the art for producing recombinant proteins, 7x10&lt;8&gt; virus would be needed. Additionally, recombinant baculoviruses can be propagated in insect larvae without the need of insect cell cultures avoiding any possibility of the use of any animal compound (ie. animal sera) in the production process, which may transmit pathogens or prions to the vaccine recipients. 
The reactivity of the larva-derived L1 structures with the conformational-specific anti-HPV antibody H16.V5 mAb, (provided by Neil Christensen, Pennsylvania State University) shows a correct conformation of the HPV VLPs generated in the larva system . Add itionally, the data obtained from CsCI or sucrose sedimentation gradients related to sedimentation coefficient of L1 structures obtained from larva, as well as the electron microscopy observations, corroborates that VLPs formed are similar to that obtained by other vaccine production systems. As L1 protein expressed in insect cells, L1 obtained by infected larvae was present in CsCI gradient fractions at a density of 1 .27 g/mL, in which it is known that HPV VLPs migrates. In addition, as observed by sucrose gradient sedimentation, L1 structural pattern found in larva overlaps with that obtained in insect cell cultures. Electron microscopy negative staining of sedimentation fractions revealed also the presence of indistinguisible VLPs to that produced in insect cell cultures (Fig. 2c). Mice immunized with HPV VLPs derived from larva or insect cell cultures showed very good humoral immune responses, with antibody titers higher than 1/10,000 after two vaccine boosts. Up to date, capsomers are considered to be a cost-effective alternative to VLP-based vaccines because they can be produced in bacterial expression systems and because of their high degree of stability. However, it has been already demonstrated that VLPs induced, independently of the route of immunization, significantly higher titers of neutralizing antibodies than capsomers (Fligge et al., 2001 ). The insect larvae expression system of present invention is a very competitive alternative to bacterial expression systems in terms of production costs, with the advantage of the insect cells in terms of facilitate high complex structures formation such L1 VLPs instead only capsomers as those produced in bacteria systems. 
For countries with a gross domestic product of less than $1 ,000 per capita, the per-dose cost may need to be as low as $1 to $2 to make vaccination both cost- effective and affordable (Agosti and Goldie, 2007). Without a doubt, one of the greatest barriers to the introduction of this vaccine is price. Using the insect larvae expression system of present invention, the high production costs of current HPV vaccines would be dramatically reduced, allowing their distribution in developing countries, where the highest incidence of this disease occurs. It is important to remark that with every 5-year delay in bringing vaccination to developing countries, 1 .5 million to 2 million more women will die (Agosti and Goldie, 2007). 
The present invention could be the clue to afford the challenge of a viable worldwide vaccination because its simplicity, easily testing and manufacture of such complex vaccines at a low cost. The scalability of vaccine production in the insect larva platform of the invention is immediate. In less than 5 weeks it is possible to generate a new recombinant baculovirus and initiate a massive production in larva without minor optimization procedures. 
The technology of production of proteins using insect larvae as biofactory, disclosed in present invention, had never been applied to the production of HPV proteins, more precisely, of L1 protein from HPV. The main goal in this invention was to exploit all possibilities of insect larva as biofactories to produce an effective HPV vaccine, always thinking in a dramatic reduction of production costs. In the present study we describe the expression of the L1 protein from HPV type 16 in 7. ni larvae. L1 protein self-assembled forming VLPs in the larvae tissues and the immune response of larva-derived VLPs compared to that induced by VLPs obtained in insect cell cultures in immunized mice, was similar. 
One embodiment of present invention is a process of production of human papillomavirus (HPV) like pentamers or virus-like particles (VLPs) characterized by the following steps: a) Amplifying a cDNA encoding for a protein present in the HPV capside and cloning said amplified cDNA into a donor vector giving a recombinant donor vector b) Transforming the recombinant donor vector of previous step a) into a host cell containing a baculovirus bacmid and resulting in a recombinant bacmid c) Transfecting insect cells with the recombinant bacmid of previous step b) d) Incubating the insect cells of step c) in suitable conditions and during proper time for getting a recombinant baculovirus stock e) Infecting insect larvae with the baculovirus of step d) f) Rearing the insect larvae infected in previous step e) in suitable conditions and during proper time for getting virus-like pentamers or VLPs g) Recovering virus-like pentamers or VLPs 
In one preferred embodiment for the process of invention the cDNA encodes protein L1 of the virus capsid, preferably from HPV16 genotype. In one preferred embodiment for the process of invention the cDNA is amplified by using a pair of primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 and SEQ ID NO: 2. 
In one preferred embodiment for the process of invention the host cell of step b) is E. coli. In one preferred embodiment for the process of invention the insect larvae of steps e) or f) are Trichoplusia ni. 
In one preferred embodiment for the process of invention the infection of larva of step e) is carried out at a dose ranging 4 x 10&lt;3&gt; to 10&lt;5&gt; pfu/larva 
In one preferred embodiment for the process of invention the recovery of virus- like pentamers or VLPs in step g) is achieved up to 72-90 hours post-infection (hpi) 
In one preferred embodiment for the process of invention the insect cells used in step c) are from Spodoptera frugiperda 
Another preferred embodiment of present invention are the primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 or SEQ ID NO:2 
Another preferred embodiment of present invention are vectors comprising a cDNA encoding for protein L1 of HPV16, amplified using the pair of primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 and SEQ ID NO:2. 
Another preferred embodiment of present invention are bacmids comprising a cDNA encoding for protein L1 of HPV16, amplified using the pair of primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 and SEQ ID NO:2. 
Another preferred em bod i ment of present invention are recom binant baculovirus comprising a cDNA encoding for protein L1 of HPV16, amplified using the pair of primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 and SEQ ID NO:2. Another preferred embodiment of present invention are insect cells transfected with recombinant baculovirus comprising a cDNA encoding for protein L1 of HPV16, amplified using the pair of primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 and SEQ ID NO:2. 
Another preferred embodiment of present invention are insect larvae infected with a recombinant vector, preferentially a virus, carrying a cDNA encoding for L1 protein from HPV, preferably for L1 protein from HPV16. Preferably insect larvae are infected with a recombinant baculovirus carrying a cDNA encoding for L1 protein from HPV, preferably for L1 protein from HPV16. 
Additionally, a preferred embodiment of present invention is the use of the primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 and SEQ ID NO:2, in recombinant protein production 
Additionally, a preferred embodiment of present invention is the use of the vectors comprising a cDNA encoding for protein L1 of HPV16, amplified using the pair of primers represented by SEQ I D NO : 1 and SEQ I D NO:2, for producing recombinant protein L1 of HPV, preferably protein L1 of HPV16 Additionally, a preferred embodiment of present invention is the use of the bacmid comprising a cDNA encoding for protein L1 of HPV16, amplified using the pair of primers represented by SEQ I D NO: 1 and SEQ I D NO:2, for producing recombinant protein L1 of HPV, preferably protein L1 of HPV16 
Additionally, a preferred embodiment of present invention is the use of the recombinant baculovirus comprising a cDNA encoding for protein L1 of HPV16, amplified using the pair of primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 and SEQ ID NO:2, for producing recombinant protein L1 of HPV, preferably protein L1 of HPV16. 
Additionally, a preferred embodiment of present invention is the use of the insect cells transfected with a bacmid comprising a cDNA encoding for protein L1 of HPV16, amplified using the pair of primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 and SEQ ID NO:2, for producing a recombinant baculovirus stock suitable for production of recombinant protein L1 of HPV, preferably protein L1 of HPV16. Additionally, a preferred embodiment of present invention is the use of the insect larvae infected with a vector or virus, preferentially with a baculovirus, comprising a cDNA encoding for a protein of the capside of HPV, preferably for L1 of HPV16, amplified using the pair of primers represented by SEQ ID NO:1 and SEQ ID NO:2, in recombinant protein production of HPV-like pentamers or VLPs, preferably of L1 protein from HPV16. 
Moreover, a preferred embodiment of present invention is the use of HPV-like pentamers or VLPs, obtained according to the process of the invention, for producing vaccines, formulated with adjuvants suitable for human use Finally, another embodiment of present invention consists in a method of prevention of infection by H PV of mammals, preferential ly humans, by immunization with a composition comprising HPV-like pentamers or VLPs obtained according to the process of invention previously described and, optionally, at least one suitable adjuvant. Appropriate adjuvants as selected from a list of them validated for human use (See EMEA/CHMP/VEG/134716/2004). 
Adjuvants help antigen to elicit an early, high and long-lasting immune response with less antigen, thus saving on vaccine production costs. In recent years, adjuvants received much attention because of the development of purified, subunit and synthetic vaccines which are poor immunogens and require adjuvants to evoke the immune response. With the use of adjuvants immune response can be selectively modulated to major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class I or MHC class II and Th1 or Th2 type, which is very important for protection against diseases caused by intracellular pathogens such as viruses, parasites and bacteria (Mycobacterium). A number of problems are encountered in the development and use of adjuvants for human vaccines. The biggest issue with the use of adjuvants for human vaccines, particularly routine childhood vaccines, is the toxicity and adverse side-effects of most of the adjuvant formulations. At present the choice of adjuvants for human vaccination reflects a compromise between a requirement for adjuvanticity and an acceptable low level of side-effects. Other problems with the development of adjuvants include restricted adjuvanticity of certain formulations to a few antigens, use of aluminum adjuvants as reference adjuvant preparations under suboptimal conditions, non-availability of reliable animal models, use of non- standard assays and biological differences between animal models and humans leading to the failure of promising formulations to show adjuvanticity in clinical trials. The most common adjuvants for human use today are still aluminum hydroxide and aluminum phosphate, although calcium phosphate and oil emulsions also have some use in human vaccinations. During the last 15 years much progress has been made on development, isolation and chemical synthesis of alternative adjuvants such as derivatives of muramyl dipeptide, monophosphoryl l ipid A, l iposomes, QS21 , MF-59 and immunostimulating complexes (ISCOMS). Other areas in adjuvant research which have received much attention are the control led release of vaccin e antig ens usi ng biodegradable polymer microspheres and reciprocal enhanced immunogenicity of protein-polysaccharide conjugates. Biodegradable polymer microspheres are being evaluated for targeting antigens on mucosal surfaces and for controlled release of vaccines with an aim to reduce the number of doses required for primary immun ization . Reciprocal enhanced immunogen icity of protein- polysaccharide conjugates will be useful for the development of combination vaccines (Gupta RK, Siber GR, 1995). 
Although the disclosure of present invention is based on producing HPV16 L1 protein, the technology of the invention can be applied by the man skilled in the art equally either in the production of L1 protein from another HPV genotypes, as HPV18, as a way of non-exhaustive example. In an analogous manner, the invention can be equally applied in the production of another proteins from HPV, different from L1 , as L2 or proteins of series E, also as a way of non-limited example. 
For the purpose of present invention the following terms should be defined as follows: H PV l i ke structures should be interpreted mainly preferably as capsid pentamers or virus like particles (VLPs) 
Living biofactories: living organism transformed or infected in order to produce a protein (exogenous or endogenous) of interest Bacmid: plasmid DNA containing all essential baculovirus genes 
Vector: plasmid or virus used for expression of foreign genes. Donor vector should be interpreted for the purpose of present invention as a plasmid, wherein the amplified cDNA encoding for a protein from HPV is cloned at the beginning of the process; Recombinant donor vector is the result of such a cloning between the donor vector (plasmid) and the amplified cDNA. Donor vector facilitates the transposition of the foreign gene into the bacmid containing all essential baculovirus genes 
VLPs (Virus Like Particles): proteins that form a virus' outer shell and the surface proteins, without the virus genome required for replication. For the purposes of present invention the terms VLPs and HPV-like pentamers should be considered as equivalents because both terms mean the self assembly of capsid proteins into empty capsids which show structural and immunological features similar (hence the introduction of the suffix "like") to the infectious virus. 
Baculovirus: family of large rod-shaped viruses that can be d ivided to two genera: nucleopolyhedrovirus (NPV) and granulovirus (GV). 
Recombinant Baculovirus: Baculovirus based vector containing a foreign gene inserted into its genome 
Viral stock: Virus inoculum amplified in cells or in an infected organism that is used for further infections Transfering: to move to a different place, region, or situation 
Amplifying: increase the volumen or number of copies of any specific compound Cloning: a DNA sequence, such is a gene, that is transferred from one organism to another and replicated by genetic engineering techniques, with the purpose of making multiple identical copies of such DNA sequence.. 
Transfecting: introduction into a cell of purified nucleic acids, resulting in subsequent replication of the DNA in the cell, for example with a viral nucleic acid, resulting in subsequent replication of the virus in the cell 
Rearing: take care of insects life cycle 
Incubating: to maintain under specific conditions organisms in order to promote a particular reaction, growth or development HPV genotype: a group of human papilloma viruses sharing a specific genetic constitution 
Capsid: the protein shell that surrounds the viral DNA 
Larva: the newly hatched, wingless, often wormlike form of many insects before metamorphosis Fifth instar larva: larva in the last stage of development before metamorphosis to the next development step cDNA: DNA copy from a messenger RNA 
Host cell: cell that support the replication of a specific virus 
Recombinant protein: a protein encoded from recombinant cDNA Primer: a nucleic acid strand that serves as a starting point for DNA replication 
Insect cell: cell derived from any kind of insect organism 
Vaccine: a biological preparation that improves immunity to a particular disease. A vaccine typically contains a small part of an agent that resembles a microorganism. Inoculation: is the placement of something where it will grow or reproduce, and is most commonly used in respect of the introduction of a pathogen, a vaccine, or an antigenic substance into the body of a human or an animal 
Pfu: plaque forming units Hpi: hours post infection 
Self-assembling: is a term used to describe processes in which a disordered system of pre-existing components forms an organized structure or pattern as a consequence of specific local interactions among the components themselves, without external direction. Efficient vaccine production: more than a 100% increase in productivity with respect other production systems or more than 10mg/g of biomass
Low production costs for L1 HPV, VLPs vaccines: a reduction of costs higher than 80% 
Lower amount of Baculovirus stock: reduction of 10&lt;4&gt; times the virus needed to generate the same amount of recombinant protein in the larva system 
Suitable conditions for incubation of insect cells: conditions of temperature and media needed to grow insect cells in vitro under a fermentation system or a monolayer culture 
Proper time for incubation of insect cells: time needed to generate a productive infection and an optimal production of the recombinant protein 
Suitable conditions for rearing of insect larvae baculovirus infected cells: conditions of temperature and humidity, among others, needed to generate a productive baculovirus infection of insect larva in which most of its cells are infected and produce the recombinant protein Proper time for rearing insect larvae baculovirus infected cells: the time needed to generate a widespread baculovirus infection in larva cells Recovering VLPs: methods used to obtain the L1 protein from baculovirus- infected insect cells or larva, that consists on zonal centrifugation in sucrose or caesium chloride, as well as affin ity purification columns using specific antibodies or exclusion size chromatography Deposit of microorganisms 
A deposit of a strain of Escherichia coli containing a DNA construction comprising the cDNA encoding L1 protein from HPV16 (plasmid pGT L1 (16)) has been made on 22.09.09 in the Spanish Culture Type Collection (CECT) located in Valencia University, Campus Burjassot, Research Building 46100 Burjassot (Valencia) SPAIN, under number: CECT7608. 
Detailed description of the invention 
Example 1 : Construction of the recombinant Baculovirus expression vector 
HPV-16 L1 cDNA (GenBank Accession AF472508) was amplified by PCR with the following primers in order to introduce the Afl III and Not I sites: 5'- CCACATGTCTCTTTGGCTGCCTAGCG-3' ( S E Q I D N O : 1 ) and 5'- GCGGCCGCTCGAGTTA CAGCTTACGTTTTTTGC-3' (SEQ ID NO: 2). The L1 gene thus amplified was cloned into the pGEM-T vector (Promega), digested with Not I , treated with al kal ine phosphatase and introduced into the pFastBac(TM)1 vector of the Bac-to-Bac Baculovirus Expression System (Invitrogen). The final clone was sequenced, and used to transform DHI OBac(TM) E. coli cells for the transposition into the recombinant bacmid. A minimum of 1 [mu]g of this bacmid was used to transfect 1 x 10&lt;6&gt; Spodoptera frugiperda Sf-21 cells using Cellfectin Reagent (Invitrogen). The P1 viral stock was obtained after 72 h of incubation at 28[deg.]C. The baculovirus was amplified following the manufacturer's instructions. Example 2: Larvae and insect cell infection 
Trichoplusia ni (T. ni) Cabbage looper larvae were reared under level-2 biosafety conditions following previously described methodology (Perez- Filgueira et al., 2006). For all experiments, fifth-instar larvae were injected with the recombinant baculoviruses near the proleg (forward the body cavity) using 10 [mu][Iota] of different pfu/larva doses, as indicated on each experiment. At different postinfection times, larvae were collected, immediately frozen and kept at -20[deg.]C until processed. 
Preconfluent monolayers of Sf-21 insect cells were infected with 10 pfu (plaque forming units) of the recombinant baculoviruses and harvested 72 hpi (hours post-infection). 
Example 3: Western blot and Coomassie staining analysis 
T. ni larvae were homogenized in 10 vol of phosphate buffered saline 0.5 M NaCI, pH 7.4 (PBS-HS) and sonicated for 20 seconds. After centrifugation at 20000 g for 5 min, the supernatant was considered the soluble fraction. Sf-21 cells were disrupted with RIPA extraction buffer (150 mM NaCI, 1 % NP-40, 0.1 % SDS, 50 mM Tris pH 8,5 mM [beta]-mercaptoethanol and a protein inhibitor cocktail (Complete, Roche, Germany), kept on ice for 30 min, centrifuged at 5000 rpm for 5 min, and the supernatant was collected for further assays. Proteins were separated on 10% SDS (w/v) polyacrylamide gels (SDS- 
PAGE) and were stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue G-250 (BioRad) or transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes (Hybond C, GE Healthcare). The membranes were blocked overnight in PBS with 0.1 % (v/v) Tween 20 (PBS-T) and 4% skimmed milk (PBS-TM), and incubated for 1 h with a primary antibody, Cam Vir-1 (Abeam) diluted 1 :25000 in PBS-TM. After 2 washes of 10 min in PBS-T, membranes were incubated for 1 h with a peroxidase-conjugated rabbit anti-mouse IgG (Sigma) diluted 1 :25000 in PBS-TM. After washing, the specific signal was detected using the Advanced ECL system (GE Healthcare) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Example 4: ELISA quantification of HPV-16 L1 protein 
Infected or uninfected larvae or insect cells soluble protein extracts were pelleted at 1500 rpm. Samples were resuspended in 10 vol (w/v) of PBS-HS, sonicated for 10 s, and centrifuged at 20000 g for 5 min at 4[deg.]C to remove cellular debris. Samples were incubated in a 96 well polyvinyl chloride microtiter plate (Costar, Corning) overnight at 4[deg.]C. Wells were blocked with PBS-TM 1 % skimmed milk for 1 h at RT, washed three times with PBS-T and incubated with anti-L1 H 1 6.V5 mAb (provided by Neil Christensen , Pennsylvan ia State University) at 1 :500 in PBS-TM (1 h at 37[deg.]C). Wells were washed three times with PBS-T and incubated with a 1 : 1500 dilution of a rabbit anti-mouse IgG- peroxidase conjugate in PBS-TM (1 h at 37[deg.]C). After three washes with PBS-T, plates were developed with ABTS [2 , 2'-azino-bis (3-ethylbenzthiazoline-6- sulfonic) acid] (Roche). The reaction was read at 405 nm in a microtiter plate reader (Multiskan Ex, Labsystems). The standard curve to calculate the amount of recombinant protein with H 16.V5 mAb was made by plating purified VLPs produced in insect cells by baculovirus infection, as described below. VLPs were used in the range of 30-150 ng per well diluted in 1 00 mM PBS pH 7.4 buffer. Larvae extracts containing L1 protein were diluted (1 :1000 to 1 :8000) to fit within the linear range of the standards Example 5: Purification of VLPs 
Insect cells 
For the production of VLPs, Sf-21 insect cells were grown to a density of 1 -1 .2 x 10&lt;6&gt; cells/mL on BD BaculoGold(TM) TNM-FH Insect Med ium (BD Biosciences) supplemented with 50 [mu]g mL gentamycin, 50 units/mLe penicillin and 50 [mu]g mL streptomycin in 75 cm&lt;2&gt; flasks. Cells were then infected at a m.o.i (multiplicity of infection) of 1 -5 and 72 hpi (hours post-infection) cells were pelleted by centrifugation at 1000 g for 5 min. 
500 mg of pelleted infected insect cells were resuspended in 8 mL PBS-HS and sonicated for 2 min. Extracts were layered onto a 40% sucrose cushion and centrifuged in a swinging bucket rotor (Kontron TST41 14) for 2 h at 140000 g at 4[deg.]C. The resulting pellets were resuspended in 10 mL of a 27% (w/v) CsCI in PBS-HS solution and centrifuged for 20 h at 260,000 g in a swinging bucket rotor at 1 0[deg.]C . 500 [mu][Iota]_ fractions were collected and their densities were measured with a refractometer. The desired fractions were dialyzed overnight against PBS-HS. 
Larvae 
For extraction of larvae VLPs, 500 mg of fresh weight larvae were homogenized in a blender with 8 mL of PBS-HS and sonicated for 2 min. After centrifugation at 20000 g for 5 min at 4[deg.]C, supernatants were layered onto a 40% sucrose cushion. The rest of the protocol was similar to that used for insect cell VLP extraction. 
Example 6: Electron microscopy and immunogold labelling 
For negative staining, 20 [mu][Iota]_ of samples of the positive fractions in the CsCI gradient were dialyzed against PBS-HS on floating filter pads (0.2 [mu][eta][eta] pore size, Millipore). Samples were placed onto carbon-coated copper grids (400 mesh size) covered with Formvar membrane and stained with 1 % uranyl acetate solution for 1 min. Samples were inspected under a ZEISS EM 910 transmission electron microscope (TEM) operating at 60 and 80 kV. Example 7: Analysis of L1 assembly by sucrose sedimentation 
To identify different assembly forms of L1 , soluble extracts from insect cells and larvae (200 mg/ 2ml_ PBS-HS) were prepared as previously described for western blotting. Samples were loaded onto linear 10 to 65% (w/v) sucrose gradients. After 2 h centrifugation at 150000 g in a swinging bucket rotor, 20 fractions of 500 [mu][Iota]_ were collected, determined their density by refractometry and analysed by ELISA with the Cam Vir-1 (Abeam) antibody. Sedimentation of L1 capsomers was calibrated with catalase from bovine l iver (Sigma) as sedimentation marker (1 1 .3S). Example 8: Immunization of animals 
Female Balb/c mice were purchased from Harlan Iberica (Barcelona, Spain). Groups of 8-week-old mice (n= 6) were immunized by intraperitoneal injection (0.2 ml_) with CsCI purified VLPs from larvae (as described before) in presence of complete Freund's adjuvant. The amount of VLPs injected was 5 [mu]g pe r mou se . As a n eg ative co ntrol , a g rou p of m i ce ( n = 6 ) was intraperitoneally immunized with larvae extracts from BacNi (baculovirus with no insert) infected larvae as negative control. As a positive control, a group of mice (n= 6) was intraperitoneally immunized with 5 [mu]g of VLPs from insect cell cultures purified by CsCI. Animals were boosted at days 21 and 35 (using incomplete Freund's Adjuvant). Blood samples were collected from the facial vein at days 0, 21 , 35 and 50. Pooled sera were titrated against purified VLPs produced in yeast (Gardasil, Merck) by ELISA in microtitre plates coated overnight at 4[deg.]C with 50 [mu][iota] of yeast-derived VLPs (100 ng of L1 -VLPs per well) diluted in PBS (pH 7.4). Subsequently, the wells were blocked 1 h at room temperature with PBS-TM and then incubated 1 h at 37[deg.]C with serial dilutions of pooled sera in PBS-TM. Then, plates were incubated for 1 h at 37[deg.]C with a goat anti-mouse IgG antibody horseradish peroxidase conjugate. Washes were performed between each step with PBS-T. Plates were developed by adding ABTS. Absorbance at 405 nm was measured in a microtiter plate reader. Antibody titres were expressed as the highest serum dilution to yield twice the absorbance mean of pre-immune sera. 
Example 9: Expression of HPV-16 L1 in Sf-21 cells and insect larvae 
HPV-16 L1 ORF was cloned into the baculovirus transfer vector pFasBac g iving the plasmid named pL1 , which was used to obtain a recombinant baculovirus (BacL1 ) as described in Example 1 . To study the expression of the L1 protein in T. ni insect larvae, SDS-PAGE of soluble and insoluble protein larvae fractions was made using as a control an insect cell His-tag L1 protein purified by affinity chromatography. Coomassie blue-stained gels showed that L1 was easily identified as a major band with mobility around 55 kDa (Fig. 1 a). 
 Most L1 protein was detected in the soluble fraction with identical mobility to that observed with L1 protein expressed in insect cells. The specificity of the expressed protein was further characterized by western blot using the Cam Vir- 1 antibody (Fig. 1 b). 
Once the L1 expression was demonstrated, the optimal L1 expression conditions induced by BacL1 in larvae were analized.. Fifth instar larvae were inoculated with three different doses of BacL1 virus. Samples were processed at different times post-inoculation and analyzed by western blot. A 55 KDa band corresponding to the L1 protein was accumulated in inoculated larvae in a time- dependent manner (Fig. 1 c). A specific ELISA quantification also confirmed these observations (Fig. 1 c), determining optimal conditions for L1 expression with an infection dose of 4 x 10&lt;4&gt;-10&lt;5&gt; pfu/larva at 72 hpi. At later post-inoculation time the larvae productivity use to drop dramatically. 
In order to determine the larvae expression efficiency we compared it with the insect cell commercial system and a recently described method of chloroplast transformation of tobacco for L1 vaccine production (Fernandez-San Millan et al ., 2008) was carried out. As it is shown in figu re 1 d , the L1 recombinant protein reached accumulation levels ranging from 18 to 21 mg per g of insect biomass (about four insect larva). Insect larvae produced about 2.5 and 5 ti mes more L 1 prote i n th an insect cell cultures and transgenic chloroplasts respectively per biomass unit. Therefore, insect larvae are the most efficient expression system for L1 protein described to date. 
Example 10: Characterization of larvae produced virus-like particles. 
Since a successful development of a papilloma vaccine is dependent upon conformationally correct capsid antigens forming pentamers or VLPs, we investigated the L1 self-assembling in larvae tissues. For that purpose, total soluble protein fractions obtained from BacL1 -infected larvae were used for HPV VLPs purification using CsCI and sucrose gradients. A clear antigenic peak measured by ELISA, using the Cam Vir-1 anti-L1 mAb as primary antibody, was detected in the fraction 4, collected from the CsCI gradient both with material derived from insect cell cultures or insect larvae (Fig . 2a). L1 protein was mainly present in CsCI gradient fractions at a density of 1 .27 g/mL, suggesting the presence of VLPs. In both systems the peaks of L1 protein derived from insect cells and larvae overlapped indicating that complex structures were very similar in densities (Fig. 2a). Fractions where the maximum L1 was found either in cells or in larvae extracts were also positive in immunoblot assay (Fig. 2b). 
Analysis of fraction 4 of the CsCI gradient by electron microscopy using negative staining showed structures that correspond in shape and size to previously described HPV VLPs. They consisted of spherical particles of about 55 nm in diameter with a regular array of capsomeres. Smaller, larger, and irregular spheres as well as tubular structures were also seen (Fig. 2c). These structures have been already described by others in plants (Biemelt et al., 2003; Maclean et al., 2007) but also in insect cells (Le Cann et al., 1995; Volpers et al., 1994). Soluble proteins from infected larvae and insect cell cultures were also submitted to sucrose sedimentation analysis in order to address L1 self- assembly patterns. Gradient fractions were collected and analyzed by ELISA with the Cam Vir-1 mAb. Results revealed that the L1 antigen assembled into similar structures independently of the production method used (insect cell cultures or larvae), presenting overlapping peaks of L1 distribution at specific sucrose densities measured by refractometry (Fig. 2d). Either there were nor capsomers in fraction 17 nor monomers in fraction 20. 
Example 11 : Immunogenicity of purified HPV 16 VLPs produced in insect larva To investigate the immunogenicity of larvae-derived HPV VLPs, mice (5 
Balb/c per group) were intraperitoneally immunized with 5 g of purified VLPs derived from larvae and the immune response was compared to that induced by similar preparations derived from Sf-21 insect cells. Animals were boosted at days 21 and 35 after the first vaccine dose. The L1 -specific humoral responses in mice were analyzed by L1 VLPs-based ELISA using native yeast-derived VLPs as antigen to coat the plates (Fig . 3). At day 50 post inoculation, all innnnunized animals reached titres higher than 1 /1 0,000. In the case of the animals immunized with the purified VLPs from larvae the titres were even higher than those derived from mice immunized with insect cells derived VLPs (Fig. 3). All control mice immunized with extracts from infected larvae with a non-related baculovirus and equally processed d id not show any specific immune response cross-reactive with L1 protein (Fig. 3). 
References 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Agosti, J. M., and Goldie, S. J. (2007). Introducing HPV vaccine in developing countries-key challenges and issues. N Engl J Med 356(19), 1908-10</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Aires, K. A., Cianciarullo, A. M ., Carneiro, S. M ., Villa, L. L, Boccardo, E., Perez-Martinez, G., Perez-Arellano, I., Oliveira, M. L, and Ho, P. L. (2006). Production of h u man papil lomavirus type 1 6 L 1 virus-like particles by recombinant Lactobacillus casei cells. Appl Environ Microbiol 72(1 ), 745-52</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Biemelt, S., Sonnewald, U ., Galmbacher, P., Willmitzer, L, and Muller, M. (2003). Production of human papillomavirus type 16 virus-like particles in transgenic plants. J Virol 77(17), 921 1 -20</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bonnez, W., Rose, R. C , and Reichman, R. C. (1 992). Antibody-mediated neutralization of human papillomavirus type 1 1 (HPV-1 1 ) infection in the nude mouse: detection of HPV-1 1 mRNAs. J Infect Dis 165(2), 376-80</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Carter, J. J., Yaegashi, N., Jenison, S. A., and Galloway, D. A. (1991 ). Expression of h u man papil lomavirus proteins in yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Virology 182(2), 513-21</bibl> . 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Chimeno Zoth, S., Gomez, E., Carballeda, J. M., Taboga, O., Carrillo, E., and Berinstein , A. (2009). Potential use of the hemaggl utin in-neuraminidase glycoprotein of Newcastle disease virus expressed in Rachiplusia nu larvae as an immunogen for chickens. Clin Vaccine Immunol 16(5), 775-8</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Christensen, N . D., Hopfl, R., DiAngelo, S. L, Cladel, N . M., Patrick, S. D., Welsh , P . A. , Budgeon , L. R. , Reed , C . A. , and Kreider, J . W. (1 994). Assembled baculovirus-expressed human papillomavirus type 1 1 L1 capsid protein virus-like particles are recognized by neutralizing monoclonal antibodies and induce high titres of neutralizing antibodies. J Gen Virol 75 ( Pt 9), 2271 -6</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Christensen, N. D., and Kreider, J. W. (1990). Antibody-mediated neutralization in vivo of infectious papillomaviruses. J Virol 64(7), 3151 -6</bibl>. <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Christensen, N. D., Kreider, J. W., Cladel, N. M., Patrick, S. D., and Welsh, P. A. (1990). Monoclonal antibody-mediated neutralization of infectious human papillomavirus type 1 1 . J Virol 64(1 1 ), 5678-81</bibl> . 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Christensen, N. D., Kreider, J. W., Shah, K. V., and Rando, R. F. (1992). Detection of human serum antibodies that neutralize infectious human papillomavirus type 1 1 virions. J Gen Virol 73 ( Pt 5), 1261 -7</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Fernandez-San Millan, A., Ortigosa, S. M., Hervas-Stubbs, S., Corral-Martinez, P., Segui-Simarro, J. M., Gaetan, J., Coursaget, P., and Veramendi, J. (2008). Human papillomavirus L1 protein expressed in tobacco chloroplasts self- assembl es i nto vi ru s-like particles that are h ig h ly im m u nogen ic. Plant Biotechnol J 6(5), 427-41</bibl> . 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Fligge, C, Giroglou, T., Streeck, R. E., and Sapp, M. (2001 ). Induction of type- specific neutralizing antibodies by capsomeres of human papillomavirus type 33. Virology 283(2), 353-7</bibl>. <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Fraillery, D., Baud, D., Pang, S. Y., Schiller, J., Bobst, M., Zosso, N., Ponci, F., and Nardelli-Haefliger, D. (2007). Salmonella enterica serovar Typhi Ty21 a expressing human papillomavirus type 16 L1 as a potential live vaccine against cervical cancer and typhoid fever. Clin Vaccine Immunol 14(10), 1285-95</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gupta RK, Siber GR. (1995). Adjuvants for human vaccines-current status, problems and future prospects. Vaccine 14:1263-76</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Hagensee, M. E., Yaegashi, N., and Galloway, D. A. (1993). Self-assembly of human papillomavirus type 1 capsids by expression of the L1 protein alone or by coexpression of the L1 and L2 capsid proteins. J Virol 67(1 ), 315-22</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Harro, C. D., Pang, Y. Y., Roden, R. B., Hildesheim, A., Wang, Z., Reynolds, M. J., Mast, T. C, Robinson, R., Murphy, B. R., Karron, R. A., Dillner, J., Schiller, J . T. , and Lowy, D. R. (2001 ). Safety and immunogen icity trial in ad ult volunteers of a human papillomavirus 16 L1 virus-like particle vaccine. J Natl Cancer Inst 93(4), 284-92</bibl>. <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Heino, P., Dillner, J., and Schwartz, S. (1995). Human papillomavirus type 16 capsid proteins produced from recombinant Semliki Forest virus assemble into virus-like particles. Virology 214(2), 349-59</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Ho, G. Y., Bierman, R., Beardsley, L, Chang, C. J., and Burk, R. D. (1998). Natural history of cervicovaginal papillomavirus infection in young women. N Engl J Med 338(7), 423-8</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Hu, Y. C, Yao, K., and Wu, T. Y. (2008). Baculovirus as an expression and/or delivery vehicle for vaccine antigens. Expert Rev Vaccines 7(3), 363-71</bibl> . 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Johansson, B. E., Price, P. M., and Kilbourne, E. D. (1995). Immunogenicity of influenza A virus N2 neuraminidase produced in insect larvae by baculovirus recombinants. Vaccine 13(9), 841 -5</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kim, S. N ., Jeong, H. S., Park, S. N., and Kim, H . J. (2007). Purification and im m unogen icity study of hu man papil lomavirus type 1 6 L 1 protein in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. J Virol Methods 139(1 ), 24-30</bibl>. <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kirnbauer, R., Booy, F., Cheng, N., Lowy, D. R., and Schiller, J. T. (1992). Papillomavirus L1 major capsid protein self-assembles into virus-like particles that are highly immunogenic. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 89(24), 12180-4</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Kirnbauer, R., Taub, J., Greenstone, H., Roden, R., Durst, M., Gissmann, L, Lowy, D. R., and Schiller, J. T. (1993). Efficient self-assembly of human papillomavirus type 16 L1 and L1 -L2 into virus-like particles. J Virol 67(12), 6929-36</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Le Cann, P., Chabaud, M., Leboulleux, D., Mougin, C, Mayelo, V., Legrand, M. C, Calvet, C, Afoutou, J. M ., Coll-Seck, A. M., and Coursaget, P. (1995). Detection of antibodies to L1 , L2, and E4 proteins of human papillomavirus types 6, 1 1 , and 16 by ELISA using synthetic peptides. J Med Virol 45(4), 410- 4</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Liu, Y., DeCarolis, N., and Beek, N. (2007). Protein production with recombinant baculoviruses in lepidopteran larvae. Methods Mol Biol 388, 267-80</bibl>. <bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Maclean , J . , Koekemoer, M . , Ol ivier, A. J . , Stewart, D . , H itzeroth , I I , Rademacher, T., Fischer, R., Williamson, A. L, and Rybicki, E. P. (2007). Optimization of human papillomavirus type 16 (HPV-1 6) L1 expression in plants: comparison of the suitability of different HPV-16 L1 gene variants and different cell-compartment localization. J Gen Virol 88(Pt 5), 1460-9</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Matsuoka, H., Kobayashi, J., Barker, G. C, Miura, K., Chinzei, Y., Miyajima, S., Ish ii, A. , and Sinden , R. E. (1 996). Induction of anti-malarial transmission blocking immunity with a recombinant ookinete surface antigen of Plasmodium berghei produced in silkworm larvae using the baculovirus expression vector system. Vaccine 14(2), 120-6</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Molinari, P., Peralta, A., and Taboga, O. (2008). Production of rotavirus-like particles in Spodoptera frugiperda larvae. J Virol Methods 147(2), 364-7</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Muhoz, N., Bosch, F. X., de Sanjose, S., Herrero, R., Castellsague, X., Shah, K. V., Snijders, P. J ., and Meijer, C. J . (2003). Epidemiologic classification of human papillomavirus types associated with cervical cancer. N Engl J Med 348(6), 518-27</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Pang, A. L, Hashimoto, C. N., Tarn, L. Q., Meng, Z. Q., Hui, G. S., and Ho, W. K. (2002). In vivo expression and immunological studies of the 42-kilodalton carboxyl-terminal processing fragment of Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 1 in the baculovirus-silkworm system. Infect Immun 70(6), 2772- 9</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Perez-Filgueira, D. M ., Gonzalez-Camacho, F., Gallardo, C, Resino-Talavan, P., Blanco, E., Gomez-Casado, E., Alonso, C, and Escribano, J . M . (2006). Optimization and validation of recombinant serological tests for African Swine Fever diagnosis based on detection of the p30 protein produced in Trichoplusia ni larvae. J Clin Microbiol 44(9), 31 14-21</bibl> . 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Perez-Filgueira, D. M., Resino-Talavan, P., Cubillos, C, Angulo, I., Barderas, M. G., Barcena, J., and Escribano, J. M. (2007). Development of a low-cost, insect larvae-derived recombinant subunit vaccine against RHDV. Virology 364(2), 422-30</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Rose, R. C, Bonnez, W., Da Rin, C, McCance, D. J., and Reichman, R. C. (1994). Serological differentiation of human papillomavirus types 1 1 , 16 and 18 using recombinant virus-like particles. J Gen Virol 75 ( Pt 9), 2445-9</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Rose, R. C , Bonnez, W. , Reich man , R. C , and Garcea , R. L. (1 993). Expression of human papillomavirus type 1 1 L1 protein in insect cells: in vivo and in vitro assembly of viruslike particles. J Virol 67(4), 1936-44</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Sigurdsson, K. , Taddeo, F . J . , Bened i ktsdotti r, K. R. , Ol afsdotti r, K. , Sigvaldason, H., Oddsson, K., and Rafnar, T. (2007). HPV genotypes in CIN 2- 3 lesions and cervical cancer: a population-based study. Int J Cancer 121 (12), 2682-7</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Volpers, C, Schirmacher, P., Streeck, R. E., and Sapp, M. (1994). Assembly of the major and the minor capsid protein of human papillomavirus type 33 into virus-like particles and tubular structures in insect cells. Virology 200(2), 504-12</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">White, W. I., Wilson, S. D., Bonnez, W., Rose, R. C, Koenig, S., and Suzich, J. A. (1998). In vitro infection and type-restricted antibody-mediated neutralization of authentic human papillomavirus type 16. J Virol 72(2), 959-64</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">White, W. I., Wilson, S. D., Palmer-Hill, F. J., Woods, R. M., Ghim, S. J., Hewitt, L. A., Goldman, D. M., Burke, S. J., Jenson, A. B., Koenig, S., and Suzich, J. A. (1999). Characterization of a major neutralizing epitope on human papillomavirus type 16 L1 . J Virol 73(6), 4882-9</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Xi, S . Z. , and Ban ks, L. M . (1 991 ). Baculovirus expression of the human papillomavirus type 16 capsid proteins: detection of L1 -L2 protein complexes. J Gen Virol 72 ( Pt 12), 2981 -8</bibl>. 
<bibl type="journal" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Zhou, J ., Stenzel, D. J ., Sun, X. Y., and Frazer, I . H. (1993). Synthesis and assembly of infectious bovine papillomavirus particles in vitro. J Gen Virol 74 ( Pt 4), 763-8</bibl>.</p></description></fulltext-document>