<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <acknowledgments>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported by the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</fundingAgency> through the <projectName>SFB 649 "Economic Risk"</projectName>. http://sfb649.wiwi.hu-berlin.de ISSN 1860-5664</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>ACKNOWLEDGMENT. We are grateful to <individual>Dr. G.D. Niswender</individual> (<affiliation>Animal Reproduction and Biotechnology Laboratory, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO, U.S.A.</affiliation>) for providing antisera to estradiol-17β (GDN 244) and testosterone (GDN 250).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the personal of <otherInstitution>UTSW Microarray Core</otherInstitution> for assistance with these experiments and to <individual>Janet Young</individual> for administrative assistance. We are thankful to <individual>Thomas Südhof</individual> and <individual>Katsuhiko Tabuchi</individual> for a generous gift of Lenti-NLS-GFP-Cre virus. This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Hereditary Disease Foundation</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>NINDS R01 NS38082</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>R01 NS056224 (IB)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NINDS R01 NS043466 (SZ)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>NIH GM59419 (GH)</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>Ara Parseghian Medical Research Foundation (JR)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank <individual>Ewa Latkowska</individual> for her excellent technical support. This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Polish Ministry of Science and Higher Education</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>2670/B/P01/2008/34</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>0757/B/P01/2009/37</grantNumber>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Dr. Chunhua Weng</individual> from <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation> and <individual>Dr. Cui Tao</individual> from <affiliation><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></affiliation> who participated in the evaluation. The authors also thank the technical support from <individual>Mr. Craig Stancl</individual> from Mayo Clinic. The study is supported in part by the <projectName>SHARP Area 4: Secondary Use of EHR Data (90TR000201)</projectName>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The data and views presented here are those of the authors alone and do not reflect or imply the formal views of the U.S. Food and Drug Administration or any other entity. This study was supported by the National Center for  Toxicological   . Many of the experiments described in this research utilized a HeLa cell line. <individual><individual>Henrietta Lacks</individual></individual>, and the HeLa cell line that was established from her tumor cells without her knowledge or consent in 1951, have made significant contributions to scientific progress and advances in human health. We are grateful to Henrietta Lacks, now deceased, and to her surviving family members for their contributions to biomedical research.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The human seminal vesicles were provided by the <researchInstitution>National Disease Research Interchange</researchInstitution>. We thank <individual>Christine Monfort</individual> for statistical analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>To <individual>Dr Marize Miagostovich</individual> and <individual>Ms Eliana Saraiva</individual> for the help during laboratorial diagnosis and the technical support from <individual>Ms Mariana Lopes</individual> and <individual>Ms Maryrose Lavatori</individual>. To <individual>Dr Joseli Lannes-Vieira</individual>, <affiliation>Department of Immunology</affiliation>, <individual>Fiocruz</individual>, and <individual>Dr Ricardo Galler</individual> for critically reviewing the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to the parents and children from the urban slums of Vellore for their enthusiastic participation and support. We also thank <individual>Drs. Rajiv Sarkar</individual>, <individual>Deepthi Kattula</individual> and field workers for their tireless monitoring of the cohorts and all the support staff of the <researchInstitution>Division of Gastrointestinal Sciences, Christian Medical College, Vellore</researchInstitution>, who made the studies possible.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was done as part of the IDEFICS Study and is published on behalf of its European Consortium (http://www.idefics.eu). We gratefully acknowledge the financial support of the <fundingAgency>European Community</fundingAgency> within the <grantNumber>Sixth RTD Framework Programme Contract No. 016181 (FOOD)</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Carl Tryggers Stiftelse for Vetenskaplig Forskning and Stiftelsen Samariten</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>B. Zeppenfeld</individual> and <individual>A. Daniel</individual> for excellent technical assistance. Antibody against Oxa1p was a kind gift of <individual>J. W. de Gier</individual>, <affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics, the Arrhenius Laboratory for Natural Sciences, Stockholm University, Stockholm, Sweden</affiliation>. The research was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, Sonderforschungsbereich TR-1</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Fonds der Chemischen Industrie</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank all the employees of the <affiliation>Icelandic Heart Preventive Clinic (Hjartavernd)</affiliation> for their skilful contribution to the data collection. the <fundingAgency>Medical Faculty and the Research Fund of the University of Iceland</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Icelandic Research Council</fundingAgency> supported this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank <individual>Michel Cantou</individual> for the sampling of bivalves, <individual>Enric Saiz</individual> and <individual>Rosa Maria Borrat Padrosa</individual> for providing Paracartia grani eggs, <individual>Maximillien Cuny</individual> and <individual>Benoît Moirod</individual> for their help with PCR analyses, <individual>Maëva Robert</individual> for sequencing and <individual>Emmanuelle Omnes</individual> for histological slide preparation. The present study was supported by the <projectName>GELAMED</projectName> project through a grant allocated by the <fundingAgency>MEEDDM (Ministère de l"Ecologie, de l"Energie, du Développement Durable et de la Mer, France)</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>Total foundation, France</fundingAgency> to D. Bonnet (<grantNumber>Programme 189 -« Recherche » 18902 C</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The outcome of this work owes to the entire staff of the <affiliation>l'Institut national de la Recherche Halieutique Morocco</affiliation>. That each finds here the expression of our profound gratitude.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was funded by the <fundingAgency>Australian Research Council (DE120101549)</fundingAgency>. We acknowledge the <researchInstitution>services of Metabolomics Australia</researchInstitution> for the analysis of metabolite concentrations and</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by grants <grantNumber>IGA NT 11062-5/2010</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>MSM6198959205</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the following individuals for their contribution to this report: <individual>R. Duran</individual>, <individual>J.L. Martinez</individual>, <individual>B. McKown</individual>, <individual>R. Romero</individual>, <individual>D. Powell</individual> (<affiliation>Portage, Inc.</affiliation>) and <individual>E. Pulliam</individual> (<affiliation>TPMC, Inc.</affiliation>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>NH, AK, RB: We thank <individual>D. Cicuzza</individual>, <individual>W. Hoffmann</individual>, and <individual>T.R. Wentworth</individual> for their critical review of a previous version of this manuscript. We also thank <individual>D. Gamble</individual> (<affiliation>UNCW</affiliation>) for permission to re-use NH: I thank the individuals and organizations that directly had a hand in the completion of this project; without their expertise, opinions, edits, financial assistance, and permission to access private property, this work would not have been possible. the <otherInstitution>North Carolina State Parks</otherInstitution> graciously allowed me to collect plants from the shorelines of five Carolina bay lakes in Bladen County, North Carolina. the <otherInstitution>North Carolina Wildlife Resources Commission</otherInstitution> was kind enough to grant access to Horseshoe Lake and Little Singletary Lake. I thank <individual>Glenn</individual> and <individual>Carol Lewis</individual> for offering their land as an easement to Little Singletary Lake; they were very gracious, and I thoroughly enjoyed listening to Glenn's stories of Native American artifacts, lake history, black bears, and wildfires. <individual><individual>Dr. Clemuel Johnson</individual></individual> graciously gave permission to survey Bakers Lake Natural Area and I am very thankful for his generosity. <individual>Stephen Clark</individual>, son-in-law of Dr. Clemuel Johnson, also provided valuable information regarding wildlife use of Bakers Lake and surrounding natural areas. "Chick" <individual>Gaddy</individual> provided valuable information concerning Carolina bays and associated South Carolina natural community types. <individual>Mr. Gaddy</individual>'s enthusiastic disposition and knowledge of South Carolina ecosystems was very beneficial to this study and I am truly grateful for his time. <individual>Garrett German</individual> provided a wealth of information concerning waterfowl use of Carolina bay lakes. <individual>Rob Richardson</individual> and <individual>Justin Nawrocki</individual> of the <affiliation>NCSU</affiliation></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Competitive State</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported in part by <fundingAgency>NASA</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>SSERVI NNA14AB01A</grantNumber>, a <fundingAgency>Jackson School of Geosciences Postdoctoral Fellowship</fundingAgency> to N.D., and funding from <fundingAgency>Peking University</fundingAgency> to N.Z. Computational work was supported by <fundingAgency>Center for Computation and Visualization at Brown University</fundingAgency> and the Pawsey Supercomputing Centre with funding from the <fundingAgency>Australian Government and the Government of Western Australia</fundingAgency>. The input files for reproducing the numerical models can be accessed at nan_zhang@pku.edu.cn. This paper benefited from thoughtful reviews by <individual>Andrew Dombard</individual>, <individual>Walter Kiefer</individual> and an anonymous reviewer.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <individual>Profs. Ye.B. Stadnik</individual>, <individual>I.S. Guliyev</individual>, <individual>F.G. Dadashev</individual>, and <individual>I.Ya. Skyarenko</individual> for assistance in performing these studies.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work has been financially supported by an individual discovery grant from <fundingAgency>NSERC (Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</fundingAgency>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. Thanks to <individual>Maria Eugenia Gómez</individual> for finding the original reference of Bouguer's law. the <projectName>DENIS project</projectName> is supported by the <fundingAgency>SCIENCE and the Human Capital and Mobility plans of the European Commission</fundingAgency> under grants <grantNumber>CT920791</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>CT940627</grantNumber>, by the <fundingAgency>French Institut National des Sciences de l'Univers, the Ministère de l'Éducation Nationale</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, in Germany</fundingAgency> by the <fundingAgency>State of Baden-Würtemberg, in Spain</fundingAgency> by the <fundingAgency>DGICYT, in Italy</fundingAgency> by the <fundingAgency>Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche</fundingAgency>, by the <fundingAgency>Austrian Fonds zur Förderung der wissenschaftlichen Forschung und</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Michael Heinz</individual>, <individual>Paul Cliften</individual>, and the <affiliation>Genome Technology Access Center (GTAC) in the Department of Genetics</affiliation> for help</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank <individual>Julia Stockinger</individual> and <individual>David Schwarzenbacher</individual> for their excellent technical support and <individual>Johannes A Mayr</individual> for comments and suggestions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Leonice Lourenço Poyares</individual>, <affiliation>Institute of Biomedical Sciences, University of São Paulo, Brazil</affiliation>, for excellent technical assistance. Research supported by <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>FAPESP</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>. F. Goulart-Silva is the recipient of a FAPESP fellowship (<grantNumber>#08/56446-9</grantNumber>), and M.T. Nunes is the recipient of a <fundingAgency>CNPq</fundingAgency> fellowship.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge <individual>D Sabatini</individual> (<affiliation>Whitehead Institute</affiliation>) for providing mutagenized KBM7 cells and <individual>V Amarnath</individual> (<affiliation>Vanderbilt University</affiliation>) for providing reagents and advice. We thank <individual>V Vijayan</individual>, <individual>K Amarnath</individual>, <individual>T Peterson</individual>, and members of the <researchInstitution>O'Shea lab</researchInstitution> for advice and assistance. We thank <individual>A Darnell</individual> for critical reading of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The equivalence of (I) and (II) is well known.  Divinsky (1973)  has proved the equivalence of (II) and (III) for associative rings. Though in the lecture notes by <fundingAgency>Wiegandt</fundingAgency> (1974)  only associative rings are considered, there the proof of the equivalence of (II) and (III) is based on methods of  Leavitt and <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Yu-lee Lee</fundingAgency></fundingAgency> (<grantNumber><grantNumber>1969</grantNumber></grantNumber>) , Yu-lee  Lee (1969)  and  Watters (1969)  and it works for alternative rings too. For semigroups with 0 the proofs are analogous to those for associative rings. Finally, the <otherInstitution>equivalence of (I)</otherInstitution>, <fundingAgency>(IV)</fundingAgency> and (V) has been established in this paper. ADDED IN PROOF. For associative rings A. D. Sands has proved the same statement in his paper "Strong upper radicals", <individual>Quart. J. Math. Oxford</individual>,  <grantNumber>27</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>1976</grantNumber>), 21-24.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The first author is grateful for the partial financial support through the <fundingAgency>French National Research Agency</fundingAgency> (Grant <grantNumber>ANR-11-BS09-0008</grantNumber>, LOTERIE).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The notion of the third-sector, with which <individual>Michael Dunford</individual> closes his discussion of Lipietz, is crucial to a truly millennial discourse and practice. It is one that has been central in the approach to urban and social development that we put forward in this journal. Can the third sector release the imagination and the vision to which governments, or their current advisers, seem blind? Can the Dome become an icon of what we can, in the new century, leave behind? Meanwhile, William Gibson's bridge, discussed below by <individual>Richard Skeates</individual>, and the now demolished Kowloon Walled City in Hong Kong, present images for the liberated zones, related movements and sympathetic governments-local, regional and national -of the future.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank the continued support of the <otherInstitution>Phillip Island Nature Parks</otherInstitution> and its staff and volunteers involved in the continuous monitoring of penguins in Phillip Island since 1968. <individual>Y.Afán</individual> produced the video and improved figures design. Our analysis benefits enormously from earlier discussions with <individual>B. Raymond</individual>, <individual>C. Bulman</individual>, <individual>B. Fulton</individual>, <individual>S. Connie</individual>, <individual>D. Oro</individual>, <individual>M. Genovart</individual>, <individual>A. Sanz</individual> and <individual>M. Louzao</individual>, and with the helpful comments of <individual>Sara Maxwell</individual> and two anonymous reviewers.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>C. Clayton</individual>, <individual>T. Hobman</individual>, <individual>Y. Nagamine</individual>, <individual>C. Ender</individual>, <individual>R. Pillai</individual>, <individual>C. Artus</individual>, and <individual>E. Bertrand</individual> for providing plasmids and/or antibodies. S.N.B. is a recipient of a longterm <fundingAgency>HFSP</fundingAgency> fellowship. the <researchInstitution>Friedrich Miescher Institute</researchInstitution> is supported by the <fundingAgency>Novartis Research Foundation</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank all the individuals from each of the SWEET countries who gave up their valuable time to participate in this study and were prepared to share their experiences with us.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <otherInstitution>ParkLands Foundation</otherInstitution> for allowing us to conduct this research on their property and <individual>Victoria A. Borowicz</individual> and <individual>Scott K. Sakaluk</individual> for assistance with this research.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to <individual>Ms Mieko Imai</individual> and <individual>Ms Tomoko Yamabe</individual> for data management, and to <individual>Dr Haruhiko Fukuda</individual> for direction of the JCOG data center and oversight of management of the study. This work was supported in part by <projectName>Grants-in-Aid for Cancer Research and for the Second-Term Comprehensive 10-Year Strategy for Cancer Control</projectName> from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Health, Labour, and Welfare (Tokyo)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge grant support from <fundingAgency>GE Healthcare</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>1R01 AR062581-01A1</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>1R21 AR063894-01A1</grantNumber>), and the <fundingAgency>VA Clinical Science Research and Development Service</fundingAgency> (Career Development Grant <grantNumber>1IK2CX000749</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Contract grant sponsors: <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Telethon</fundingAgency></fundingAgency> (<grantNumber><grantNumber>GGP13213</grantNumber></grantNumber>), <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>U.S. National Institute of Health</fundingAgency></fundingAgency> (<grantNumber><grantNumber>AR059646</grantNumber></grantNumber> and <grantNumber><grantNumber>AR053349</grantNumber></grantNumber>); <fundingAgency>Ministero dell' Istruzione, dell' Università e della Ricerca, Fondo Innovazione in Ricerca</fundingAgency>. This work was supported by Telethon grant GGP13213 to FP, VS, and CR; by U.S. National Institute of Health Grants AR059646 and AR053349 (subcontracts to FP) and a by <fundingAgency>MIUR-FIR</fundingAgency> grant to EP. "the <otherInstitution>EuroBioBank and Telethon Network of Genetic Biobanks</otherInstitution> (GTB07001D) are gratefully acknowledged for providing biological samples". We thank <individual>Dr. Rosanna Asselta</individual> (<affiliation>University of Milan</affiliation>) for helpful advice and assistance in haplotype analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funding for the World Vegetable Center's general research activities is provided by core donors: <fundingAgency>Republic of China (Taiwan)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>UK aid</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>United States Agency for International Development (USAID)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Australian Centre for International Agricultural Research (ACIAR)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Germany</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Thailand</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Philippines</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Korea</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Japan</fundingAgency>. In addition we like to thank <otherInstitution>Global Crop Diversity Trust</otherInstitution> for contribution to meetings and to this open-access publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>Dr. Michael W. Hess</individual> (<affiliation>Division of Histology and Embryology, Medical University of Innsbruck, Austria</affiliation>) for generally allowing us access to a transmission electron microscope. This</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Work on mistranslation in the Ibba Lab is supported by funding from the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MCB 1412611</grantNumber>), an <fundingAgency>Ohio State University Center for RNA Biology Fellowship</fundingAgency> (to K.M.) and <fundingAgency>NIH Training Grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>T32 GM008512</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>GM086252</grantNumber> (to A.M.).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors gratefully acknowledge the financial support by the <fundingAgency>Polish Ministry of Higher Education</fundingAgency> (Grant no. <grantNumber>15.11.170.576</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by grants from <fundingAgency>Italian MIUR</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>FIRB RBAP10Z7FS_002</grantNumber>) to SC and from <fundingAgency>University of Ferrara (Italy)</fundingAgency> to V.B. We thank <individual>Mr. Cosmo Rossi</individual> for his technical expertise in producing xenografts.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Higher Education Malaysia</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) Asian CORE Program</fundingAgency> titled "<projectName>Establishment of research and education network on coastal marine science in Southeast Asia</projectName>". We would like to express our appreciation to <individual>Dr. Norio Nagao</individual>, <individual>Mr. Hideyuki Takatsuji</individual>, <individual>Mr. Zainuddin Ibrahim</individual>, <individual>Mr. Husdy Salleh</individual> and <individual>Mr. Soed Mokhtar</individual> for their assistance in the field sampling. We would also like to thank <individual>Dr. Htay Aung</individual>, <individual>Dr. Azman Abdul Rahim</individual>, <individual>Mr. Zuhaimi Samad</individual> and <individual>Miss Fatin Zahidah Zainal</individual> for their help with the illustrations and <individual>Dr. Shuhei Nishida</individual> for reading the manuscript and for his invaluable comments. We are grateful to our referees for their comments that helped improve the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments The study is funded by the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Organization for Health Research and Development</fundingAgency>, grant number <grantNumber>300020012</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Shane Waters thanks the <affiliation>University of Adelaide</affiliation> for his Postgraduate Award and the <researchInstitution>Australian Centre for Plant Functional Genomics</researchInstitution> for support. This work was supported by the <grantNumber>DP120100900</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>LP120100201</grantNumber> grants from the <fundingAgency>Australian Research Council</fundingAgency> awarded to MH.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research work is an output of the research project "<projectName>Modelling of selected indicators and processes in drinking water supplies</projectName>", reg. no.: FAST-S-17-4643 and also a project "<projectName>Influence of hydraulic conditions in the water supply network on selected indicators of drinking water quality</projectName>", reg. no.: FAST-J-17-4475. Both of them was supported through the internal grant agency of the <fundingAgency>Brno University of Technology</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors have no conflicts of interest associated with the material presented in this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <researchInstitution>Diamond Light Source</researchInstitution> for access to beamlines I02, I03, I04, I04-1 and I24 (proposal numbers MX6638 and MX8659). The work was funded by the <fundingAgency>BBSRC</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>BB/ L02022X/1</grantNumber>), a Kelvin-Smith Scholarship from the <fundingAgency>University of Glasgow</fundingAgency> and a <fundingAgency>Sir Henry Wellcome Fellowship</fundingAgency> awarded to R.G.: award number <grantNumber>106077/Z/14/Z</grantNumber>. During this work I.J. was supported by a studentship from the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency>: award number <grantNumber>093592/Z/10/Z</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>M. I. Ransome is supported by the <fundingAgency>NHMRC Biomedical Fellowship</fundingAgency>. A. J. Hannan is supported by the <fundingAgency>ARC Future Fellowship</fundingAgency> (FT3) and his research has been funded by <fundingAgency>NHMRC Project Grants</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors received editorial support from <individual>Eva Polk</individual>, Ph.D., at Excerpta Medica in the preparation of this manuscript, which was funded by <fundingAgency>Celgene Corporation</fundingAgency>. The authors are fully responsible for all content and editorial decisions for this manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The work was partially supported by Research Funds from the <fundingAgency>County of Västra Götaland, Sweden</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I couldn't possibly include all references since there are thousands. Instead I would like to acknowledge the contributions made by all scientists in the field of human genomics, comparative genomics, epigenetics and the related areas of my article. All of the relevant background articles are available at the NCBI website, particularly the PubMed.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Mental Health</fundingAgency> , <fundingAgency>NIMH</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>1 R01 MH0820-54</grantNumber>) to Drs. Klump, Boker, Burt, Keel, Neale, and Dr. Cheryl  Sisk. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institute of Mental Health. p  &lt;  .001. Abbreviations: MBPD, Minnesota Borderline Personality Disorder Scale. SCID-II, Structured Interview for DSM-IV Axis II Personality Disorders Screener. STAB, Subtypes of Antisocial Behavior Survey. MEBS, Minnesota Eating Behaviors Survey. The twin correlation is significantly greater than 0 at p  &lt;  .001.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments I appreciate the valuable editorial suggestions and corrections by <individual>John F. Kern</individual>, of <affiliation>Winnetka</affiliation>, IL. I am grateful to <individual>Bob Buchanan</individual>, <individual>Dee Benson</individual> and <individual>Carole Mayo</individual> for their support. I thank <individual>Govindjee</individual> for his invitation, his extensive editing (especially in providing the reference list), his patience and above all his ever-lasting persistence and encouragement that has led to the completion of this letter.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work has been partially supported by the <fundingAgency>EC funded project Swan-iCare</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>FP7-ICT</grantNumber>, Project No. 317894) and "<projectName>TEAChER: TEach AdvanCEd Reconfigurable architectures and tools</projectName>" project funded by <fundingAgency>DAAD</fundingAgency> (2014).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Conceived and designed the experiments: RB JP KP. Performed the experiments: RB MDR. Analyzed the data: RB JP. Wrote the paper: RB JP KP.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank an anonymous referee. Also, we are very grateful to <individual>Professor Peter P. Eggleton</individual> for sharing his binary evolution code. This work was sponsored by the <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (Grant Nos. <grantNumber>11463002</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>11373020</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Open Foundation of key Laboratory for the Structure and evolution of Celestial Objects, Chinese Academy of Science</fundingAgency> (Grant Nos. <grantNumber>OP201405</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>OP201404(B615015)</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Science Foundation of Jimei University</fundingAgency> (Grant No. <grantNumber>C613030</grantNumber>), and <fundingAgency>Science and Technology Foundation of Guizhou Province</fundingAgency> (Grant LKK[2013]  No. 20).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. Development of the Medusa GC/MS systems, calibrations, and measurements were carried out as part of the <projectName>international <otherInstitution>AGAGE</otherInstitution> research program</projectName> and supported by the <fundingAgency>NASA Upper Atmospheric Research Program</fundingAgency> in the US with grants <grantNumber>NNX07AE89G</grantNumber> to MIT, <grantNumber>NNX07AF09G</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>NNX07AE87G</grantNumber> to <affiliation><affiliation><affiliation><affiliation>SIO</affiliation></affiliation></affiliation></affiliation>, <fundingAgency>Defra</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency><affiliation><researchInstitution>NOAA</researchInstitution></affiliation></fundingAgency> in the UK, <fundingAgency><researchInstitution><affiliation>CSIRO</affiliation></researchInstitution></fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Australian Government Bureau of Meteorology in Australia</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual><individual>J. P. Severinghaus</individual></individual> (SIO) for the Megadunes firn samples from Antarctica, <individual>J. E. Shields</individual> (SIO) for an air-age estimate of the deepest and oldest Megadunes firn air samples used in this work, <individual>V. V. Petrenko</individual> and J. P. Severinghaus (SIO) for the ancient NH ice samples from the Pâkitsoq site in Greenland. We especially thank <individual>E. J. Dlugokencky</individual>, <individual>J. W. Elkins</individual>, <individual>B. D.Hall</individual>, and <individual>S. A. Montzka</individual> (NOAA/<affiliation><researchInstitution>GMD</researchInstitution></affiliation>), <individual>C. D. Keeling</individual> (deceased) and <individual>R. F. Keeling</individual> (SIO), <individual>N. Schmidbauer</individual>, <individual>O. Hermansen</individual>, <individual>C. R. Lunder</individual> (<affiliation><researchInstitution>NILU</researchInstitution></affiliation>), and <individual>R. C. Rhew</individual> (<affiliation>UCB</affiliation>) for air samples. We thank <individual>R. A. Rasmussen</individual> and the <researchInstitution>Oregon Graduate Institute (OGI)</researchInstitution> for originally collecting the Cape Meares Northern Hemispheric samples which were provided by NOAA/GMD, NILU, and CSIRO. We are indebted to the staff at the AGAGE sites for their continuing contributions to produce high quality measurements of atmospheric trace gases. In particular, we thank <individual>G. Spain</individual> (<affiliation>Mace Head</affiliation>), <individual>R. Dickau</individual> (<affiliation>Trinidad Head</affiliation>), <individual>J. Mühle</individual> et al.:  Perfluorocarbons in the global atmosphere <individual>P. Sealy</individual> (<affiliation>Ragged Point</affiliation>), <individual>M. C. Cunningham</individual> (<affiliation>Cape Matatula</affiliation>), <individual>C. G. Rickard</individual>, and <individual>J. Z. Ward</individual> (<affiliation>Cape Grim</affiliation>). In addition, we thank <individual>M. Leist</individual> (CSIRO) for his excellent technical support of the Cape Grim Medusa system. We are especially thankful to <individual>R. Knapp</individual>, <individual>J. Marks</individual>, and <individual>C. Bayliss</individual> (<affiliation>International Aluminium Institute, IAI</affiliation>), <individual>M. Ison</individual> (<affiliation>Australian Aluminium Council, AAC</affiliation>) and the two anonymous reviewers for their insightful comments and reviews which contributed to the improvement of this manuscript. Edited by: J. Kaiser</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funding: This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Cancer Institute</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>P01 CA018029</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>CA033084</grantNumber>, and the <fundingAgency>Leukemia and Lymphoma Society SCOR program</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>LLS-7008-09</grantNumber>. AGC is supported by a <fundingAgency>Walker Fellowship Award</fundingAgency>, and GBR was supported by a <fundingAgency>Leukemia Lymphoma Society Special Fellow Award</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>4442-09</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Marian Boguñá</individual>, <individual>Alessandro Flammini</individual>, and <individual>Romualdo Pastor-Satorras</individual> for a critical reading of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author is grateful to <individual>Drs P. Husby</individual> and <individual>I. Romslo</individual> for helpful discussions. The technical assistance of <individual>Mrs A. Iden</individual> is greatly acknowledged. The study was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Norwegian Research Council for Science and the Humanities</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was carried out with the support of Cooperative Research Program for Agriculture Science  &amp;  Technology Development (Project no. <grantNumber>PJ010156022014</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Rural Development Administration, Republic of Korea</fundingAgency>. The authors specifically thank the staff and crew of the <affiliation>National Center for InterUniversity Research Facilities (Seoul National University)</affiliation> for assistance with the NMR and GC/MS experiments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We particularly wish to thank the <otherInstitution>SL Division</otherInstitution> for the efficient operation of the LEP accelerator at all energies and for their continuing close cooperation with our experimental group. We thank our colleagues from <otherInstitution>CEA</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>DAPNIA/SPP</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>CE-Saclay</otherInstitution> for their efforts over the years on the time-of-flight and trigger systems which we continue to use. In addition to the support staff at our own institutions we are pleased to acknowledge the References</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>81472390/ H1619</grantNumber>,<grantNumber>81472762/H1609</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>National Funds for developing local colleges and universities</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>B16056001</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>General Project</fundingAgency>  (<grantNumber>1201410188</grantNumber>)   We thank <otherInstitution>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Malignant Tumor Epigenetics and Gene Regulation</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Sun Yat-Sen Memorial Hospital</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Sun Yat-Sen University</otherInstitution> for flow cytometry analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Accession numbers for previously reported CTV nucleotide sequences used in this report are: T36 (U166034), <fundingAgency>VT</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>U56902</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>T385 (Y18420), SY568 (AF001623)</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>T30</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AF260651</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>C268</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AJ599770</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>C269</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AJ579774</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>C270</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AJ579771</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>T300</grantNumber>(<grantNumber>AJ579763</grantNumber>), T305(<grantNumber>AJ579776</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>T312</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AJ579765</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>T32</grantNumber>(<grantNumber>AJ579766</grantNumber>), T346(<grantNumber>AJ579768</grantNumber>), T388 (<grantNumber>AJ579777</grantNumber>)  ,</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was partially supported by the <projectName>CONACyT projects</projectName> No. 29250E and 27676E, and the project IN114998 funded by the <fundingAgency>DGAPA-UNAM</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Steven Kalb,</individual> <individual>Yankai Li</individual>, <individual>Tim Cummings</individual>, <individual>Bryan Hammons</individual>, <individual>Deborah Farr</individual> and <individual>Justin Carter</individual> assisted with this research.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <researchInstitution>Werfen/Instrumentation Laboratory</researchInstitution> for providing us with the test kits for the inter-center comparison.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments We thank <individual>Petra Laspe</individual> and <individual>Antje Apel</individual> for invaluable technical assistance. This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>German Cancer Aid (Deutsche Krebshilfe)</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft DFG</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>GRK1034</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>Dr. Rick G. Pleijhuis</individual> for kindly developing a user-friendly web-based calculator based on our updated models to facilitate the use of our models. G.J. The study funders did not participate in the design of the study; the collection, analysis, or interpretation of the data; the writing of the manuscript; or the decision to manuscript submission.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to the <fundingAgency>Spanish government project</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>TEC2010-20224-C02-01</grantNumber> and the <fundingAgency>European project ECOAL-MGT -SUDOE Program</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank the referee for his suggestions which helped in improving the paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Foremost we thank <individual>Dr. Robert C. Drewes</individual> who continues to initiate, coordinate and lead multiorganism biotic surveys on São Tomé and Príncipe. We thank <individual>Eng</individual>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank the referee, especially for pointing out [1, Theorem 2] which simplified the proof of Theorem 5.1 considerably.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Key International Cooperation Program of the National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (project no. <grantNumber>31110103916</grantNumber>; Beijing, P.R. China), the <fundingAgency>Agricultural Science and Technology Innovation Program</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>ASTIP-IAS08</grantNumber>; Beijing, P. R. China), and the <fundingAgency>China Agriculture Research System</fundingAgency> (project no. <grantNumber>CARS-42</grantNumber>; Beijing, P. R. China).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I would like to thank the following people for all their help and professional support in the completion of this book: <otherInstitution>George Banks</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Menu Development</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>British Airways, London</otherInstitution>. <individual>Scott Chapman</individual>, Senior Partner, <otherInstitution>Medical Litigation</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Tress, Cox and Maddox, Sydney, Australia</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Collecting trips in Asia were funded through <grantNumber>USDA-ARS Specific Cooperative Agreements 58-5320-9-382 and 58-5320-4-018</grantNumber>, managed by the <fundingAgency>University of Hawaii's College of Tropical Agriculture and Human Resources (UH-CTAHR)</fundingAgency>. A study trip in Australia was covered by <fundingAgency>Farm Bill funding</fundingAgency> (project <grantNumber>3.0251</grantNumber>), through a <projectName>Cooperative Agreement between USDA and UH-CTAHR</projectName>. Additional support was provided by <projectName>USDA-NIFA Hatch projects</projectName> HAW00942-H and HAW00956-H, administered UH-CTAHR. We also thank <individual>Anthony R. Clarke</individual> for reviewing an earlier version of the manuscript and <individual>Richard A.I. Drew</individual> and <individual>David L. Hancock</individual> for their insight, mentoring and long hours discussing the relationships among species in the OFF complex and the higher classification of dacine fruit flies. <individual>Desley Tree</individual> and <individual>Justin Bartlett</individual> provided access to the impressive QDAF fruit fly collection in Brisbane. The use or mention of a trademark or proprietary product does not constitute an endorsement, guarantee, or warranty of the product and does not imply its approval to the exclusion of other suitable products by the U.S. Department of Agriculture, an equal opportunity employer.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>CLL Global Research Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <projectName>EUCAAD 200755 project</projectName> funded under the auspices of the <fundingAgency>EU Seventh Framework Programme</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Cancer and Allergy Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Research Council/SIDA/ SAREC</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Iranian Ministry of Health and Medical Education</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Cancer Society</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Cancer Society in Stockholm</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>King Gustaf Vth Jubilee Fund</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Vinnova</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Karolinska Institutet Foundations</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Stockholm County Council</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the <otherInstitution>Career Training Interexchange program</otherInstitution> that facilitated the training period of Maitane Olabarrieta within the USGS. Maitane Olabarrieta also acknowledges funding from the ''<fundingAgency>Cantabria Campus International Augusto Gonzalez Linares Program</fundingAgency>.'' We would also like to thank <individual>Giovanni Coco</individual>, <individual>John C. Warner</individual>, and <individual>Falk Feddersen</individual> for their support with this work and constructive suggestions. We are also grateful to the developers of the COAWST modeling system, SWAN, and ROMS models. WRG was supported by <fundingAgency>ONR</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>N00014-13-1-0368</grantNumber>. The authors would also like to thank <individual>Sergio Fagherazzi</individual>, <individual>Xavier Bertin</individual>, and the third journal reviewer for their suggestions. The data and numerical results used in this paper will made available upon request to the main author.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <projectName>Red Wolf Recovery Program</projectName>, specifically <individual>Rebecca Bartel</individual>, <individual>Art Beyer</individual>, <individual>Chris Lucash</individual>, <individual>Ford Mauney</individual>, <individual>Michael Morse</individual> and <individual>Ryan Nordsven</individual> for their support. We also thank <individual>Kristin Brzeski</individual> for constructive comments on the manuscript. The findings and conclusions in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the <otherInstitution>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the families and patients who have participated in this research study. We acknowledge <individual>Hilde Van Esch</individual> for help with patient recruitment, and we thank <individual>Yi Mu</individual>, <researchInstitution>UC Davis Department of Public Health Sciences</researchInstitution>, for assistance with data management and analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. I would like to thank the referee for his/her careful reading and valuable comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are thankful to the <otherInstitution>Marine Products Export Development Authority (MPEDA, Kochi)</otherInstitution>, the <fundingAgency>Chief Executive of National Fisheries Development Board</fundingAgency>, <individual>Hyderabad</individual> and <individual>Dr.R.Jaya Kumar</individual>, Senior Scientist, <researchInstitution>CMFRI Mandapam</researchInstitution>. We are also grateful to <individual>Sri. Rama Sankar Naik</individual>, <affiliation>IAS, Commissioner of Fisheries, Andhra Pradesh, India</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Cancer Institute</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>R37-CA-057030</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The project described was supported by Grant Number <grantNumber>OH 03970</grantNumber> from <fundingAgency>CDC-NIOSH</fundingAgency> to MFB and <grantNumber>AR051212</grantNumber> from <fundingAgency>NIAMS</fundingAgency> to AEB, the <fundingAgency>Sandler Foundation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>NS-10414</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS, in destruction process)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Ministère de l'Enseignement Supérieur et de la Recherche</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Fondation NRJ -Institut de France</fundingAgency> to JOC and MR. FS was partly supported by a <fundingAgency>HFSP</fundingAgency> long term fellowship <grantNumber>LT 00743/1998-B</grantNumber> and partly by personal fundings.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank the <researchInstitution>Medical Research Center of Peking University Third Hospital</researchInstitution> for technical guidance. PC3 and HEK293 cells were kindly donated by <individual>Wei Zhang</individual>, PhD from the <affiliation>Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Science</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>No conflicts declared.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Thereares o many people to thank for this book that it could've</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>Simone Duis</individual> and <individual>Natalia Pavlova</individual> for help with surgeries, <individual>Laetitia Baud</individual> for assistance with animal care, <individual>Quentin Barraud</individual> and <individual>Julie Kreider</individual> for histological analyses and anatomical reconstructions, and <individual>Samuel Gex</individual> for help with building the robotic device.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I thank <individual>M. T. Mponda</individual> for her patience and extra time devoted to typing the original manuscript. I also thank <individual>D. E. C. Mughogho</individual> for his moral support and reviewing of the initial draft. Lastly I thank the anonymous referees of my paper for their useful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The assistance of <individual>Mrs L.K. Frymovich</individual> in preparing the manuscript for publication is greatly appreciated.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author would like to thank <individual>Graeme Chamberlin</individual>, <individual>Barry Williams</individual> and <individual>Chris Davies</individual> for their comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements We thank <individual>Professor Anders Lund</individual> for giving us access to the <educationalInstitution>EPR lab at IFM-Chemical Physics, Linköping University</educationalInstitution> and <individual>Professor Sandra S. Eaton</individual>, <affiliation>University of Denver</affiliation>, for advice concerning EPR data analysis. We acknowledge <individual>Professor Mikael Lindgren</individual> and <individual>Dr. Malin Persson</individual> for valuable discussions and advice. We also gratefully acknowledge <individual>Dr. Christian Altenbach</individual>, <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>, for providing his software for determining inter-residue distances. This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Swedish Foundation for Strategic Research (PH)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Research Council (BHJ, PH, and UC)</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Knut and Alice Wallenberg Foundation</fundingAgency> (BHJ, PH, and UC)</fundingAgency>. PH is a Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences Research Fellow supported by a grant from the Knut and Alice Wallenberg Foundation.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Ronald L. Jacobs</individual>, Chair</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Aiping Lin</individual> at the <researchInstitution>Yale W.M. Keck Biostatistics Resource</researchInstitution> for analysis of microarray data. Supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> to SG.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The statistical evaluation by <individual>Michael Obermayer</individual> (<affiliation>GKM Gesellschaft für Therapieforschung mbH, Munich</affiliation>) is acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to acknowledge the <fundingAgency>Research Council of University of Tehran</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Iran National Science Foundation (IN SF )</fundingAgency> for the grants provided for them. They also would like to sincerely thank <individual>Professor Ian Thompson</individual> for his valuable help regarding the FRESCO code.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by a <fundingAgency>VHS Medical Center Research Grant, Republic of Korea</fundingAgency> (grant number: <grantNumber>VHSMC 15012</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>NHLBI R01 HL64794</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I am grateful to <individual>Mrs Nicolette Budden</individual>, <individual>Mrs Stella Oates</individual> and <individual>Mrs Catherine Wright</individual> for assistance in the preparation of this article. I also wish to thank <individual>Professor A. Hewish FRS</individual>, <individual>Sir Maurice Wilkes FRS</individual>, <individual>Professor K. Suchy</individual>, <individual>Dr R. P. Mercier</individual>, <individual>Dr A. J. M. Garrett</individual>, <individual>Dr M. Rycroft</individual> and a number of others for helpful comments on the article in draft form. I also thank the <otherInstitution>Society's referee</otherInstitution> for advice. Librarians at <educationalInstitution>St John's College, Cambridge</educationalInstitution>, and at <educationalInstitution>Churchill College, Cambridge</educationalInstitution>, kindly assisted with access to archival material. <individual>Kenneth Budden</individual> left very extensive autobiographical material on computer disks, which I have used and occasionally quoted. The frontispiece photograph was taken by Walter Bird and is reproduced with permission from the Godfrey Argent Studio.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank dental students <individual>Barbara Mikecs</individual>, <individual>Júlia Németh</individual>, <individual>Péter Csányi</individual>, and <individual>Adél Ruszin</individual> for their assistance in collecting data. This study was funded by the <fundingAgency>Research Fund of the Faculty of Dentistry, Semmelweis University, Hungary</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>4030511599</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>5111141075</grantNumber>), and the <fundingAgency>Hungarian Scientific Research Fund</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>OTKA K112364</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>K-112964</grantNumber>). The Mucograft was kindly donated by the manufacturer (<fundingAgency>Geistlich Pharma AG, Switzerland</fundingAgency>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <fundingAgency>INSS (Japan)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>EDF (France)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Areva (France)</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>EPRI (US)</fundingAgency> for supporting their <projectName>SCC-related research</projectName>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <otherInstitution><fundingAgency>AstraZeneca</fundingAgency></otherInstitution> for providing AZ-4217, <individual>Mark Smith</individual> (<affiliation>Imperial College, London</affiliation>) and <individual>Yuchio Yanagawa</individual> (<affiliation>Gunma University, Maebashi</affiliation>) for VGlut2-GFP and GAD67-GFP tissue, respectively. This work was funded by <fundingAgency>Medical Research Council</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MR/K003291/1</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Diabetes UK</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>12/0004458</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>British Heart Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>PG/15/44/31574</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council CASE</fundingAgency> (with AstraZeneca) award (<grantNumber>BB/I015663/1</grantNumber>) to MLJA and by a grant to LKH from the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>WT098012</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the subjects who participated in the study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Autochthonous. EndodontidcB. World-wide, on all continents and islands. ' Primitive Zonitidit were probably evolved at a very early time, but the group attained its main development in the Csenogaeic faunas.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We gratefully acknowledge financial support from <fundingAgency>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq)</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo (FAPESP)</fundingAgency>, <grantNumber>Proc. 95/3636-3</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by a restricted grant from <fundingAgency>Roche</fundingAgency>. The funder had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Ada Tam</individual>, <individual>Hao Zhang</individual> and <individual>Lee Blosser</individual> of the <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Core Flow Cytometry</affiliation> facilities for their assistance with flow cytometry and cell sorting.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study was supported by <fundingAgency>University of Udine, Italy</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Associazione "Mi Fido di Te" ONLUS</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Fondazione Cassa di Risparmio di Città di Castello, Italy</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The VHR imagery was provided by the <otherInstitution>US Department of State (USDS) Humanitarian Information Unit</otherInstitution>, under the NextView License. The authors thank the <affiliation>FAO-SWALIM</affiliation> staff, without whom the field campaign would not have been possible. Finally, the authors thank <individual>Dr Roberto Colombo</individual> of the <affiliation>University of Milan-Bicocca</affiliation> for the field spectroscopy equipment used in the field campaign.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Rick van Leeuwen</individual>, <individual>Wouter Verhesen</individual>, <individual>Kevin Custers</individual>, and <individual>Hans Duimel</individual> for their technical support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. This research was supported by grants to RL, BZ and KV from the <fundingAgency>Swedish Cancer Society</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Stockholm Cancer Society</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Research Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Childhood Cancer Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Stockholm County Council</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Karolinska Institutet</fundingAgency> Research Fund and the European Union FP6 (Chemores)</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>FP7 (Apo-Sys)</fundingAgency>. VOK was supported by a fellowship from the <fundingAgency>Swedish Institute</fundingAgency> and Karolinska Institutet and AHV from the <fundingAgency>Wenner-Gren Foundation</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to acknowledge con-</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This manuscript benefited from careful and constructive reviews by <individual>J. P. Brun</individual> Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study is funded by <fundingAgency>Medtronic Inc.</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge <individual>J. A. Hoyos</individual> for a critical reading of this manuscript and useful comments. The financial supports from <fundingAgency>CNPq</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>FAPESP</fundingAgency>, under grants <grantNumber>15/04451-2</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>307620/2015-8</grantNumber>, are also acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgement: The authors wish to thank <individual>H. Dong</individual>, <individual>J. Guzman</individual>, and <individual>I. Tice</individual> for their discussions and pointing out references  [2, 13, 14]  on regularity of Stokes problems in a domain with corners. Y. Guo's research is supported in part by <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>C</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>10828103</grantNumber> and NSF grant <grantNumber>DMS-0905255</grantNumber>, and T. Nguyen's research was supported in part by the NSF under grant <grantNumber>DMS-1405728</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <individual>Christian Lafarge</individual> for animal care and <individual>Anne Diot</individual> and <individual>Corine Pouyet</individual> for participation in tissue protein synthesis determination. The authors had no conflicts of interest. This research was supported by the <fundingAgency>Proteus Bilateral Programme</fundingAgency> between Slovenia (<researchInstitution>Slovenian Research Agency</researchInstitution>) and France (<otherInstitution>French Research Ministry</otherInstitution>). The contribution of each author was as follows: T. P., conception and design, tissue sampling, data processing, drafting and revision of the manuscript; L. M. and D. R., conception and design, tissue sampling, revision of manuscript; M. C. R., protein synthesis rate determinations; C. B., design, tissue sampling, blood cell counts and MPO determinations, data processing; J. S., conception and design, tissue sampling, data processing, revision of manuscript; P. P. M., conception and design, animal experiment, tissue sampling and revision of manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors gratefully acknowledge <fundingAgency>BAU-USDA Soybean Project</fundingAgency>, for financial assistance to conduct this experiment.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The following list of presents was read, and thanks ordered to be returned to the respective donors:</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments KS-A, RM, XY, CL, LG and MV wish to thank <individual>Changyu Fan</individual> and <individual>Yun Shen</individual> for providing informatics support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The publication of this article was funded by the <fundingAgency>Qatar National Library</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> with Grant <grantNumber>BCS 9207007</grantNumber>. Drs Petrie and Collins were research residents supported by the <fundingAgency>Department of Orthopaedics</fundingAgency>. No benefits in any form have been received or will be received from a commercial party related directly or indirectly to the subject of this article.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank the women for their participation in this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like thank the financial support from the <fundingAgency>Portuguese Foundation for Science and</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by a Grant from the <fundingAgency>National High Technology Research and Development Program of China</fundingAgency> (<projectName>863 Program</projectName>, no. <grantNumber>2014AA093501</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (Project nos. <grantNumber>30672742</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>30873353</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>30930113</grantNumber>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the paper. <individual>Dr. Ling Xu</individual> and <individual>Dr. Jin Yu</individual> are co-first authors.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering (NIBIB)</fundingAgency> Grant No. <grantNumber>R01-EB-002091</grantNumber> and through a <projectName>NIBIB American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Administrative Supplement</projectName>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We gratefully acknowledge the contribution of participating parents and children, general practitioners, hospitals, midwives and pharmacies in Rotterdam.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Competing Interests: The authors declare that they have no conflict of interests. Contributors/Acknowledgement: All authors participated equally in designing and estimation of current research. Views and opinions expressed in this study are the views and opinions of the authors, Asian Journal of Agriculture and Rural Development shall not be responsible or answerable for any loss, damage or liability etc. caused in relation to/arising out of the use of the content.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The encapsulating style of delivery was proposed by <individual>Charlie Perkins</individual>. <individual>Jim Solomon</individual> has been instrumental in shaping this document into its present form.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank <individual>Dr. Solomon S. Senok</individual> at <affiliation>Alfaisal University, Saudi Arabia</affiliation> for critically reading the manuscript, improving English text and providing constructive comments on the manuscript. This work was supported by</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Special thanks to <individual>Dr. Wil Linkugel</individual> for encouraging the continued exploration of Franklin Roosevelt's 1932 campaign orations and drawing the author's attention to this particular speech and <individual>Mr. Andrew Crick</individual> for his editorial assistance throughout the project.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Kohki Yoshimoto</individual> for the use of atg mutants and <individual>Dr. Shinya Wada</individual> for the use of GFP-ATG8 transgenic plants.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Ms. Meehye Kim</individual> for technical assistance. This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Korean Academy of Tuberculosis and Respiratory Diseases</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Authors are grateful to the <affiliation>Leeds group</affiliation> of <individual>Prof. A.A. Watson</individual> for the array disposition and maintenance, in particular <individual>J. Beaman</individual>, <individual>J. Lloyd-Evans</individual>, <individual>P. Ogden</individual> and <individual>M. Patel</individual>. The same gratitude is due to the <affiliation>Palermo group</affiliation> of <individual>Prof. L. Scarsi</individual> for the PLASTEX and RPC operations. A particular thanks are to <individual>Dr. J. Knapp</individual> and <individual>Dr. D. Heck</individual> for their indispensable help in installing and running CORSIKA 4.50 Monte Carlo in Naples.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are thankful to <individual>KB Low</individual> for providing wild-type M13 and to <individual>S Alonzo</individual>, KB Low, <individual>D Vasseur</individual>, and <individual>GP Wagner</individual> for useful discussion. We are also grateful to <individual>J Bull</individual> for suggesting we explore a model of phage loss. We thank <individual>S Wielgoss</individual> and two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on the paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research is supported in part by <fundingAgency>ROC NSC</fundingAgency> under contract number <grantNumber>NSC97-2221-E-128-005-MY3</grantNumber>. Also, the author would like to thank <individual>Prof Horng-Twu Liaw</individual> and <individual>Mr Shin-Han Wu</individual> of <affiliation>Shih-Hsin University</affiliation> and <individual>Mr Chih-Ta Yen</individual> of <affiliation>National Taiwan University of Science and Technology</affiliation> for their help in this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge the <researchInstitution>National Collaborative Research Infrastructure (NCRIS) of Australia</researchInstitution> for providing access to bioinformatics computational pipelines used in this study and the <fundingAgency>Research Institute of Forestry, Chinese Academy of Forestry</fundingAgency> for financial support (<grantNumber>ZD200902</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funded by a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Institute on Aging</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>R01 AG023090</grantNumber>). The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institute on Aging or the National Institutes of Health.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>International Center for Advanced Renewable Energy and Sustainability at Washington University in St. Louis, Missouri</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Johns Hopkins Global Center on Childhood Obesity</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>2001656847</grantNumber>). We thank the study participants for their cooperation and <individual>Leslie Duling</individual> and <individual>Nora Geary</individual> for their help in study coordination, data collection, and data management.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors gratefully acknowledge <otherInstitution>Solvay Engineering Plastics</otherInstitution> for supporting this work and for providing material data and specimens. This work benefited from the financial support of the <fundingAgency>French Minister for Research (ANRT)</fundingAgency> (Grant no: <grantNumber>CNRS 079212: UM2 121532</grantNumber>) and was performed in the framework of the <projectName>European DURAFIP project</projectName> (<projectName>FUI project</projectName> supported by <fundingAgency>Oseo</fundingAgency>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thanks all those administrators and practitioners who participated in the study. A special acknowledgement is given to the funder of the research project the <educationalInstitution>Centre jeunesse de Montréal Institut Universitaire</educationalInstitution>. Its contribution makes this project possible.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>PRGS</fundingAgency> under the Grant No. <grantNumber>GRS100323</grantNumber>, <affiliation>Universiti Malaysia Pahang, Malaysia</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank all of the study participants. We also thank <individual>James Hicks</individual> for his editorial assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank the <fundingAgency>Australian Partnership for Advanced Computing (APAC)</fundingAgency> for generous grants of supercomputer time which have enabled this project. Support from the <fundingAgency>South Australian Partnership for Advanced Computing (SAPAC)</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>National Facility for Lattice Gauge Theory</fundingAgency> is also gratefully acknowledged. DBL thanks <researchInstitution>Jefferson Lab</researchInstitution> for their kind hospitality where the majority of this research was performed. This work is supported by the <fundingAgency>Australian Research Council</fundingAgency> and by <fundingAgency>DOE</fundingAgency> contract <grantNumber>DE-AC05-84ER40150</grantNumber> under which SURA operates Jefferson Lab.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Kelli Hellenbrand</individual> and <individual>Sara Pladziewicz</individual> for helping the volunteer scans. Grant sponsors: <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency>: <grantNumber>R01NS066982-01</grantNumber>; <grantNumber>R21EB009441-01</grantNumber>; <grantNumber>R01EB006882-01</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was funded by <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>GM116381</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>HG008140</grantNumber>, and by the <fundingAgency>Howard Hughes Medical Institute</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual>Jeffrey Spence</individual> and <individual>Yun S Song</individual> for technical assistance. We also thank <individual>Ziyue Gao</individual>, <individual>Arbel Harpak</individual>, <individual>Molly Przeworski</individual>, <individual>Joshua Schraiber</individual>, and <individual>Aylwyn Scally</individual> for comments and discussion, as well as two anonymous reviewers. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments <fundingAgency>Leiden University</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>NWO BSIK/BRICKS</fundingAgency> supported this research under Grant <grantNumber>#642.066.603</grantNumber>. Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>South China Chinese Medicine Collaborative Innovation Center</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>A1-AFD01514A05</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Characteristic Key Discipline Construction Fund of Chinese Internal Medicine of Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine</fundingAgency> (2013)(2014)(2015).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank all researchers involved during the project, especially to the staff of <educationalInstitution>TecPes (Laboratorio de Tecnología Pesquera) at Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso</educationalInstitution> (<individual>T Melo</individual>, <individual>CF Hurtado</individual>, <individual>D Queirolo</individual>, <individual>E Gaete</individual>, <individual>I Montenegro</individual> and <individual>R Escobar</individual>). Additional thanks to members of "<affiliation>Programa de Conservación de Tiburones, Chile"</affiliation> and <affiliation>ELASMOLAB</affiliation> staff at <affiliation>Universidad Austral de Chile</affiliation> for their valuable help with logistics, sampling and dissection help during fieldwork, especially <individual>J Lamilla</individual>, <individual>F Concha</individual>, <individual>H Flores</individual>, <individual>Y Concha-Perez</individual> and <individual>A Isla</individual>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I thank <individual>K. Wang</individual> for providing the research environment required to perform these experiments and for helpful discussions, <individual>G. Seabold</individual>, <individual>E. Tytell</individual>, and <individual>M. Yoshizawa</individual> for critically reading the manuscript, <individual>G. Ashida</individual> for helpful discussions, and <individual>K. Nakao</individual> and <individual>R. Renden</individual> for additional scientific comments on the manuscript. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Oliver Rauhut</individual> (<affiliation>Bayerische Staatssammlung für Paläontologie und Geologie, München</affiliation>), <individual>Miriam Zelditch</individual> (<affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>), <individual>Johannes Knebel</individual> (<affiliation>Ludwig Maximilians University, München</affiliation>), <individual>Stefan Richter</individual> (<affiliation>University of Rostock</affiliation>), <individual>Walter Joyce</individual> and <individual>Eduardo Ascarrunz</individual> (both <affiliation>University of Fribourg</affiliation>) for discussion, and <individual>Michel Laurin</individual> (<affiliation>Sorbonne Universités, Paris</affiliation>) for comments on an earlier version of the manuscript. We further thank <individual>Matthew Lamanna</individual> (<affiliation>Carnegie Museum of Natural History, Pittsburgh</affiliation>), <individual>Alex Downs</individual> (<affiliation>Ruth Hall Museum, Ghost Ranch</affiliation>), <individual>David Gillette</individual> (<affiliation>Museum of Northern Arizona, Flagstaff</affiliation>) and <individual>Xu Xing</individual> (<affiliation>Institute of Vertebrate Paleontology and Paleoanthropology, Beijing</affiliation>) for access to collections. This study benefitted especially from critical comments of <individual>Jesús Marugán-Lobón</individual> (<affiliation>Universidad Autónoma de Madrid</affiliation>) and three anonymous reviewers.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Y. Polyrakis</individual> and seminar participants in the <otherInstitution>Conference on Ordered Spaces and Applications</otherInstitution> (Athens, November 2011) for helpful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The sketch for  Fig. 1  was adapted from www.biologieunterrricht. info/-Media/umrisse-mensch.jpeg, licensed by <fundingAgency>Creative Commons</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author acknowledges the assistance provided by officials of the <otherInstitution>Government of Pakistan</otherInstitution>. the <otherInstitution>united Nations</otherInstitution> and its specialized agencies. and non-governmental organizations engaged in providing help to Afghan refugees in Pakistan. The author is particularly grateful to the <otherInstitution>united Nations Population Fund (<otherInstitution>UNFPA</otherInstitution>)</otherInstitution> for allowing him to use material collected during a mission undertaken on their behalf in early 1989. Views expressed are the author"s own and not na€essarily those of the UNFPA.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This project has been supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>MCB RAS</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Russian Foundation for Basic Research</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>14-04-00004</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>13-04-01878-a</grantNumber>). This research was partially carried out using the equipment provided by the <otherInstitution>IBCH</otherInstitution> core facility (CKP IBCH). Diffraction experiments were carried out on beam-</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank all the <otherInstitution>ACCLAIM/COPD</otherInstitution> study investigators and <otherInstitution>Covance Inc.</otherInstitution> We also thank <individual>Dr Sharon Gladwin</individual> from Complete Medical Communications, who provided medical writing support. This study was funded by <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Almirall</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, S. A., Barcelona, Spain</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Forest Laboratories</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, Inc, NY, USA</fundingAgency>. Competing interests PWJ has received fees from a number of pharmaceutical companies, including Almirall, for speaking at meetings and for consulting and participating in advisory board meetings, and has also received support for research from <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>GSK</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>. SIR has consulted on or participated in advisory boards for numerous pharmaceutical companies, including Almirall, GSK, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>AstraZeneca</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Novartis</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Nycomed</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>. He has received industry-sponsored grants from AstraZeneca, <fundingAgency>Biomarck</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Centocor</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Mpex</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Nabi</fundingAgency>, Novartis and <fundingAgency>Otsuka</fundingAgency>. AA has received fees for speaking and consultancy, as well as funds for research, from Almirall, GSK, AstraZeneca, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Boehringer Ingelheim</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Esteve</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Chiesi</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>. PC has received fees for speaking and consultancy from Centocor, AstraZeneca, Chiesi, GSK, Boehringer Ingelheim, Nycomed, Novartis and Almirall, as well as research grants from <fundingAgency>Schering Plough and Centocor</fundingAgency>. HM has received funds for research and fees for consulting from a number of pharmaceutical companies. LF has served as a consultant to, and received lecture fees and grant support from, Nycomed, AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, Chiesi, GSK, Merck Sharp  &amp;  Dohme and Novartis. JFD has served on advisory boards for Almirall and Forest Laboratories. EDB has received remuneration for consulting and serving on advisory boards for Almirall, and his institution has received grants for taking part in clinical trials sponsored by Almirall and Forest Laboratories. NJG has received honoraria for presentations on COPD treatment at meetings sponsored by Almirall and Forest Laboratories, as well as payments for advisory board consultations. His institution has received research grants from Almirall and Forest Laboratories. RL and EGG are employees of Almirall. CC is an employee of Forest Laboratories, and holds stock and options in the company.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Lyle Sensenbrenner</individual> for his critical review of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>JSPS KAKENHI</fundingAgency> Grant Number <grantNumber>23500211</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>www.nature.com/scientificreports/</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We gratefully acknowledge financial support by <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, Sonderforschungsbereich 412, University of Stuttgart</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Work on this project was supported by an operating grant of the <fundingAgency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</fundingAgency>, infrastructure grants from the <fundingAgency>Canadian Foundation</fundingAgency> for Innovation and generous philanthropic support by the <individual>A. Irwin</individual> family. DB was supported by a <fundingAgency>Canada Graduate Scholarship</fundingAgency>, and MM received an <fundingAgency>Ontario Trillium fellowship</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the referee for providing valuable comments, and <individual>Jarle Brinchmann</individual>, <individual>David Sobral</individual>, and <individual>Simone Weinmann</individual> for useful discussions. We acknowledge funding from <fundingAgency>ERC</fundingAgency> grant HIGHZ No. <grantNumber>227749</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank Gena Lattin, MS for her assistance with data collection. RS is the recipient of a <fundingAgency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, National Institutes of Health (NIH) career development award</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>K23 HD052553</grantNumber>. This project was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Children's Health Research Center at University of Utah and Primary Children's Foundation</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements: The authors thank <individual>Dr M.C. Yadavannavar</individual> at <affiliation>BLDE University</affiliation> for his assistance with data collection, <individual>Dr Veena Algur</individual> for her assistance with translation of study materials, and the adolescents and their families for participation in this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the <researchInstitution>Unit of Support for Technical and Scientific Research (UATRS, CNRST)</researchInstitution> for the X-ray measurements. Supplementary data and figures for this paper are available from the IUCr electronic archives (Reference: BT5773).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to the <educationalInstitution>department of chemistry, Niger Delta University</educationalInstitution>, PMB 071. <otherInstitution>Wilberforce Island</otherInstitution>. <otherInstitution>Bayelsa State</otherInstitution>. Nigeria, where both the experimental determination of proximate and mineral analysis were conducted.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. The authors wish to thank <individual>W. Bode</individual> (<affiliation>Martinsried</affiliation>) for helpful suggestions, <individual>M. Dumbsky</individual> for expert technical assistance, <individual>H. Hof</individual> (<affiliation>Mannheim</affiliation>) for help in the preparation of anti-</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <otherInstitution>Wildlife Conservation Society (Russia)</otherInstitution>, <individual>Eugenia Bragina</individual> for the invaluable help in writing the report, <individual>Irina Maslova</individual>, <individual>Yuri Petrunenko</individual> and <individual>Alexander Nikanorov</individual> for valuable comments</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The writers are indebted to <individual>E. Navarro Raga</individual>, <individual>P. Gómez Garcia</individual> and <individual>M.T. Mínguez Hernández</individual> from the <affiliation>SCSIE Electron Microscopy Unit at the University of Valencia</affiliation> for their useful technical help, and <individual>M. Palomo Navarro</individual> for assistance with sample collection. <individual>Ramirez P</individual> and <individual>Menendez R</individual> are</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported by the <fundingAgency>College of Agriculture and Life Sciences</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Graduate School</fundingAgency>, and a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>GM-21205</grantNumber>). I thank <individual>Dr. T. Ishikawa</individual> for providing the TS mutants and <individual>Dr. R. K. Littlewood</individual> for permission to present unpublished data from his Ph. D. dissertation on growth of the extrachromosomal mutants. The excellent technical assistance of <individual>Ms. P. Riese</individual> is acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported in part by funding from the <fundingAgency>University of California Office of the President's Office of Research and Graduate Studies</fundingAgency>. Authors acknowledge the <otherInstitution>UC BRAID</otherInstitution> for project and data management support; <individual>Verónica Hoyo, Ph.D.</individual> (<affiliation>UCSD</affiliation>) for her help in editing and graphics, and <individual>John Heldens</individual> and <individual>Dan Redline</individual>, former program directors at <affiliation>UCSF</affiliation> and <affiliation>UCD</affiliation>, respectively, for their contributions to the developmental stages of this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <otherInstitution>Centers for Disease Control (CDC)</otherInstitution> for A/California/04/09 virus and <individual>Ron Fouchier</individual> (<affiliation>Erasmus University, Rotterdam, The Netherlands</affiliation>) for A/Netherlands/603/09 virus. We thank <individual>Krisna Wells</individual> for editing the manuscript, <individual>Martha McGregor</individual>, <individual>Rebecca Moritz</individual>, <individual>Anthony Hanson</individual>, <individual>Hideaki Ishida</individual>, <individual>Hideaki Tsuchiya</individual>, <individual>Ryuzo Torii</individual>, <individual>Naoki Yamamoto</individual>, <individual>Kosuke Soda</individual>, <individual>Naoki Nomura</individual>, and <individual>Hiromi Yoshida</individual> for excellent technical assistance. We also thank <individual>Takashi Umemura</individual>, <individual>Yuji Sunden</individual>, and <individual>Tomohisa Tanaka</individual> for pathological analyses of virus-infected pigs.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported by a Grant from the <fundingAgency>Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>K12130</grantNumber>) and funds from <fundingAgency>Michigan AgBioResearch</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to <individual><individual>Dr Ulrich Desselberger</individual></individual>, <individual>Dr James Richards</individual> and <individual>Prof. Andrew Lever</individual> (<affiliation><affiliation>University of Cambridge</affiliation></affiliation>) for the generous gift of the full-length cDNA copies of RV genomic segments for in vitro transcription; <individual>Dr John Patton</individual> for sharing a DNA clone pQE60g8C for expressing group C rotavirus NSP2. The authors would like to thank Dr Ulrich Desselberger (University of Cambridge) for critical reading of the manuscript; <individual>Prof. Takeshi Kobayashi</individual> (<affiliation>University of Osaka</affiliation>) for his valuable advice and discussions on the rotavirus reverse genetics system established in his laboratory. We thank <individual>Dr John T. Patton</individual> (<affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>), <individual>Prof Peter Stockley</individual>, <individual>Dr Roman Tuma</individual> and <individual>Mr Jack Bravo</individual> (<affiliation>University of Leeds</affiliation>) for valuable discussions and comments during the preparation of the manuscript. Available at Dryad Digital Repository under a CC0 Public Domain Dedication</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The encouragement and constructive criticism of earlier versions of this paper by many friends and colleagues, especially <individual>Robert Austin</individual>, <individual>Martin Johanson</individual>, <individual>Sam MacAulay</individual>, <individual>Volker Mahnke</individual>, <individual>Ram Mudambi</individual>, <individual>Rajneesh Narula</individual>, <individual>Christos Pitelis</individual> and <individual>John Steen</individual>, are gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Ms Chiori Fukuyama</individual> for her skillful technical assistance. This study was supported by <fundingAgency>Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research on Priority Areas</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>17016065</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>16062101</grantNumber>, to R. Ueda) from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education, Culture, Science, Sports, and Technology, Japan</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Grants-in-Aid for Cancer Research</fundingAgency> from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Health, Labor, and Welfare, Japan</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>17S-1</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>17-16</grantNumber>, to S. Iida).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The work of N.E.M. is partially supported by <fundingAgency>P.P.A.R.C. (U.K.)</fundingAgency>. E.W. wishes to thank <fundingAgency>Oriel College (Oxford)</fundingAgency> for financial support and the <educationalInstitution>Department of Physics, University of Newcastle (Newcastle-upon-Tyne)</educationalInstitution> and <otherInstitution>CERN Theory Division</otherInstitution> for hospitality.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>Lucilla Scuto</individual> (<affiliation>Central Core Lab, EuroImaging, Rome</affiliation>) for careful assistance in collecting digital images from the suburban centres, and in storing echo and ECG readings. We are also grateful to <individual>Dr Tarcisio Vago</individual>, <individual>Ospedale Luigi Sacco</individual> (Milan, Italy) for assaying NT-proBNP, and to <individual>Margareth Becker</individual> for her help in editing the manuscript. They funding body had no role in the concept or design of the study, or in the data reporting.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported in part by <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health Grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>R03 CA108364 (L.E.W.)</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>P50 CA116199 (H.G.)</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R01 ES011740</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>R01 CA131274 (Q.W.)</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>P30 CA016672</grantNumber> (<fundingAgency>M. D. Anderson Cancer Center</fundingAgency>). We thank <individual>Margaret Lung</individual> for her assistance in recruiting the subjects; <individual>Yawei Qiao</individual>, <individual>Kejing Xu</individual>, <individual>Zhensheng Liu</individual>, <individual>Jianzhong He</individual>, and <individual>Yinyan Li</individual> for their laboratory assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was published with the kind financial support of <fundingAgency>Bulgarian Science Fund</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements This trial was funded and sponsored by <fundingAgency>Cancer Research UK</fundingAgency> (grant number <grantNumber>C357/A12197</grantNumber>). Also supported by the <fundingAgency>Christie NHS Foundation trust</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>European Union FP6 Programme 'ATTACK'</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Manchester Cancer Research Centre Biobank</fundingAgency>. Sincere thanks go to all the patients and their families who participated in this trial.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that they have received no funding for the research reported.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Susanne Schwanz</individual> for technical support, <individual>Oliver Gould</individual> for his help with the figure design, and <individual>Clemens Kunz</individual> (<affiliation>Friedrich-Schiller University Jena</affiliation>) for help with the formation of defined damages in the samples utilized for self-healing experiments. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Helmholtz-Association</fundingAgency> through programme-oriented funding.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Dr. Peter Hasselbacher</individual> kindly provided the histologic and immunofluorescent studies of the skin biopsy. <individual>Dr. F. C. McDuffie</individual> generously performed the monoclonal rheumatoid factor assays.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This book could not have existed without <individual>Conor Sally</individual>, who rejects all thanks and recognition but debated every comma on every page and supported me at every stage. I could not ask for a better friend, partner, cheerleader or taskmaster and will never be able to express the depths of my love and gratitude.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the participants in the study. Funding. No funding or sponsorship was received for this study or publication of this article. The article processing charges were funded by the authors.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is founded by the <fundingAgency>German Research Foundation (DFG)</fundingAgency> (Contract <grantNumber>CH 943/2-1</grantNumber>). The authors would like to thank <individual>Wolfgang Dittus</individual>, and <individual>Stefan Paetel</individual> from <affiliation>Zentrum für Sonnenenergie-und Wasserstoff-Forschung Baden-Württemberg</affiliation> for preparing the CIGS absorber layer for this work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments that improved the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>David Rand</individual>, <individual>Hugo Sequeira</individual>, <researchInstitution>LIAAD-INESC Porto LA</researchInstitution>, <educationalInstitution>Centro de Matemática da Universidade do Minho</educationalInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Fundação Calouste Gulbenkian</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution><fundingAgency>Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia (FCT)</fundingAgency></otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>PRODYN-ESF</otherInstitution>, and <individual>Jorge Carneiro</individual> and <individual>Jorge Zubelli</individual> for all the encouragement and helpful comments. We thank the <fundingAgency>Programs POCTI</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>POSI by FCT and Ministério da Ciência</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Tecnologia e do Ensino Superior</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Centro de Matemática da Universidade do Minho (CMAT)</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Centro de Matemática da Universidade do Porto (CMUP)</fundingAgency> for their financial support. Bruno Oliveira gratefully acknowledges financial support from <projectName>PRODEP III</projectName> by <fundingAgency>FSE</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>EU</fundingAgency> and Miguel Ferreira gratefully acknowledges financial support from Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia (FCT) given through a PhD scholarship.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements: We thank <individual>Dr. F. Leal</individual> for technical assistance in FPLC analysis and <individual>N.S.D. Skinner</individual> for proofreading the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments The authors are grateful to <individual>Nicky Wilkinson</individual> for advice on data protection issues and <individual>Adrian Smith</individual> and <individual>Dr. <individual>Cesar Pichardo-Almarza</individual></individual> for testing the on-line analysis tools and reporting tools during the development of the DISRUPT postprandial database. We also thank <individual>Drs. Pieter Groot</individual>, <individual>Charlotte Walden</individual> and Cesar Pichardo-Almarza for proof-reading of the manuscript. the <projectName>DISRUPT project</projectName> was funded by a <fundingAgency>BBSRC Industry Interchange Program</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>IIP/ 0307/009</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments. This work was funded by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (Grants <grantNumber>OCE-0647667</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>OCE-1537890</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>AGS-1036062</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>AGS-1036006</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>AGS-1444294</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</fundingAgency> (Grant <grantNumber>NA07OAR4310094</grantNumber>), and the <fundingAgency>Natural Environment Research Council</fundingAgency> (Grant <grantNumber>NE/ J020893/1</grantNumber>). The authors thank the anonymous reviewers for thoroughly and critically evaluating the manuscript. They are also grateful to the crew of the <otherInstitution>R/V Knorr</otherInstitution> for supporting us while chasing storms and that of the NOAA ship <individual>Ronald H. Brown</individual> for their support during SO GasEx. Data from the HiWinGS cruise will be made available via anonymous ftp (ftp1. esrl.noaa.gov/psd3/cruises/HIWINGS_2013/Collective_</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Xiaoxiao Bai</individual> for helpful comments on the manuscript. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Patrick and Catherine Weldon Donaghue Medical Research Foundation</fundingAgency>, and by the <fundingAgency>Betsy and Jonathan Blattmachr family</fundingAgency>. Li Yang was supported by the <fundingAgency>China Scholarship Council</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We most thank <individual>Dr. Behnam Baghianimoghadam</individual> for his consultation in the translation, editing and publication of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Ms. K. Arnold</individual> for excellent help with receptorbinding assays; <individual>Dr. Susan Potter-Perigo</individual> for preparing the purified proteoglycans; <individual>Dr. Robert W. Mahley</individual> for stimulating discussions and support; <individual>Drs. Stanley C. Rall</individual>, <individual>Eva-Hurt Camejo</individual>, <individual>German Camejo</individual> and <individual>Karl H. Weisgraber</individual> for comments on the manuscript; <individual>S. Ordway</individual> and <individual>G. Howard</individual> for editorial assistance; and <individual>J. Carroll</individual> and <individual>S. Gonzales</individual> for graphics. J. Borén was supported by a <fundingAgency>Howard Hughes Postdoctoral Fellowship for Physicians</fundingAgency>. This work was also supported by <fundingAgency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>HL-47660</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HL-18645, DK-02456</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>HL-30086</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements: The authors would like to thank <individual>Rob Aalberse</individual> for critically reading the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <affiliation>Jefferson Lab physics and accelerator divisions</affiliation> for their contributions. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>US Department of Energy</fundingAgency> (including contract <grantNumber>DE-AC02-06CH11357</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>US National Science Foundation</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Israel Science Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Korea Science Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>US-Israeli Bi-National Scientific Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Killam Trusts Fund</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Walter C. Sumner Foundation and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</fundingAgency> (SFB 443). Jefferson Science Associates operates the <fundingAgency>Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility</fundingAgency> under DOE contract <grantNumber>DE-AC05-06OR23177</grantNumber>. The polarimeter was funded by the US National Science Foundation, grants <grantNumber>PHY 9213864</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>PHY 9213869</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The uuthor ~s indebted to <individual>Drs. M. L~ant</individual> and <individual>M.V.S. Raju</individual> for help ~n lran.slathag the manuscript in to English. Mauuscript .criticism by <individual>Dr.s, G. Marbaix</individual>, <individual>G. Huez</individual> and <individual>A. Buray ~s</individual> also acknowledged. Sarko~'l was a .generous gift from <otherInstitution>CIBA-Geigy Corporation</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was nancially supported by the <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (No. <grantNumber>81630093</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>81874293</grantNumber>). We thank <individual>Mr Hongbo Zheng</individual> and <individual>Ms Ke Xu</individual> for the NMR measurements. <individual>Ms Yanan Qiao</individual> and <individual>Dr Jiaozhen Zhang</individual> are also acknowledged for the X-ray diffraction analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The excellent assistance of <individual>Susan V. Castro, PhD</individual>, in the preparation of the manuscript is gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The reverse transcriptase was a gift from <individual>Dr J. Beard</individual>. We thank <individual>Drs M. Jacquet</individual> and <individual>N. Affara</individual> for helpful discussion, <individual>Christian Sahuquillo</individual> for his excellent technical assistance, and <individual>Denise Baron</individual> for typing the manuscript. A. F. was supported by a long-term <fundingAgency>European Molecular Biology Organisation fellowship</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments. This work was supported in part by <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health Grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>5P50CA127003</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R01CA149222</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R01CA118 553</grantNumber>, and <fundingAgency>National Cancer Institute Cancer Center Support</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>5P30CA06516</grantNumber>. We thank <individual>Dana-Farber</individual>/<affiliation>Harvard Cancer Center in Boston, MA</affiliation>, for the use of the Pathology Specimen Locator Core, which provided data on KRAS mutation testing.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The radar measurements used in this study can be obtained from the Madrigal database at http://jro.igp.gob.pe. The Jicamarca Radio Observatory is a facility of the Instituto Geofisico del Peru operated with support from the <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> AGS-1433968 through Cornell University. Work at UT Dallas was supported by NSF <grantNumber>AGS-1261107</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>AFOSR FA9550-13-1-0095</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>[25] Acknowledgments. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>NASA Tropical Rainfall Measuring Mission (TRMM) Program</fundingAgency>. The authors would also like to thank <individual>V. N. Bringi</individual> of <affiliation>Colorado State University</affiliation> and <individual>Bob Meneghini</individual> at <affiliation>NASA/GSFC</affiliation> for their discussions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The Pennington Center Longitudinal Study is registered at ClinicalTrials.gov (Identifier NCT00959270). Special thanks to <individual>Connie Murla</individual> and <individual>Aimee Stewart</individual> for data management, as well as the many clinical scientists and staff of the <researchInstitution>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</researchInstitution> who have contributed data to the development of the Pennington Center Longitudinal Study. V C 2012 The Obesity Society</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is supported by <fundingAgency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAA)</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>P20 AA017837 (LEN and CMC)</grantNumber> and <fundingAgency>NIH Metabolism Training Grant</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>T32-DK007319 (DAD)</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to acknowledge the families for their participation and support and <individual>Dr. Dilek Aktas</individual> for discussion. Our work was supported in part by the grant from the <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health/National Human Genome Research Institute</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, number <grantNumber><grantNumber>1U54HG006542</grantNumber></grantNumber>. Grant sponsor: National Institutes of Health/National Human Genome Research Institute; Grant number: 1U54HG006542.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the following awards: <fundingAgency>MRC Milstein award</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>G0801721</grantNumber> (to MIH), <fundingAgency>NERC research grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>NE/ J01074X/1</grantNumber> (to MIH) and <grantNumber>NE/M015033/1</grantNumber> (to MIH/BW), <fundingAgency>Norwich Research Park (NRP) Translational Award</fundingAgency> (to BW/MIH), and a <fundingAgency>BBSRC NPRONET</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>BB/L013754/1</grantNumber>) <fundingAgency>Proof of Concept award</fundingAgency> (to MIH/BW). RD is funded by a <fundingAgency>Norwich Research Park BBSRC Doctoral Training Program Studentship</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>BB/M011216/1</grantNumber> and ZQ is funded by the BBSRC via <fundingAgency>Institute Strategic Programme Grant</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>BB/J004561/1</grantNumber> to the John Innes Centre. The authors declare no conicts of interest. We thank <individual>Catherine Tremlett</individual>, <individual>Andrew Hart</individual> and <individual>Ashleigh Crane</individual> at the <affiliation>Norfolk and Norwich University Hospital</affiliation> for the VRE strain and <individual>Justin O'Grady</individual> at the <affiliation>UEA Medical School</affiliation> for the MRSA strain. We are also grateful to <individual>Dr Jioji Tabudravu</individual>, <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation>, for his kind comments. KAW would like to thank the <researchInstitution>South African Centre for High Performance Computing</researchInstitution> for access to computational resources.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to express our gratitude to <individual>Drs H.Tanida</individual>, <individual>S.Y.Park</individual>, <individual>S.Adachi</individual> and <individual>T.Hikima</individual> for their help in the data collection at SPring-8. This work was supported by grants for the`<projectName>Research for the Future</projectName>' Program from the <fundingAgency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>97L00501</grantNumber>) and for the <projectName>National Project on Protein Structural and Functional Analyses</projectName> from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank many colleagues in hospital and in practice, particularly <individual>Dr. K. Shirley Smith</individual> and others at the <otherInstitution>London Chest Hospital</otherInstitution>, who have kindly referred patients needing valvotomy. We are especially indebted to <individual>Mr. J. R. Belcher</individual>, who has taken an active part in the surgical management of the Middlesex Hospital patients.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to the <educationalInstitution>Centre for Chemistry and Biotechnology and Deakin University, Australia</educationalInstitution> for supporting biofuel research. The authors thank <individual>Mr R Chaudhary</individual>, <individual>Dr R Kanwar</individual>, <individual>Prof J R Kanwar</individual> (<affiliation>Medical School, Deakin University</affiliation>) and A/<individual>Prof TTsuzuki</individual> (<affiliation>University of Canberra</affiliation>), for providing the magnetic nanoparticles. The authors are also grateful to the <otherInstitution>Electron Microscopy</otherInstitution> facility at the <educationalInstitution>Institute for Frontier Materials (IFM), Deakin University, Australia</educationalInstitution> for conducting the SEM work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank our coworkers in the laboratory for their valuable discussions and suggestions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Ms. Masayo Tada</individual> for her excellent technical assistance and measurements of serum and hepatic enzymes and components. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Gifu City Subsidiary</fundingAgency> for project creation "<projectName>Industry-AcademicGovernment Cooperation Project Subsidiary</projectName>".</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Inha University</fundingAgency> research grant (No. <grantNumber>53670</grantNumber>). We thank <individual>Prof. Jin Min Kim</individual> for insightful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are thankful to Director, <researchInstitution>CSIR-National Botanical Research Institute (CSIR-NBRI)</researchInstitution>, <individual>Lucknow</individual> for the facilities and for the financial support from the <fundingAgency>network projects (CSIR-INDEPTH), New Delhi, India</fundingAgency>. APS is thankful to <educationalInstitution>University Grant Commission, New Delhi, India</educationalInstitution> and GD is thankful to <fundingAgency>CSIR, New Delhi</fundingAgency> for the <grantName>award of Junior/Senior Research Fellowship</grantName> and <educationalInstitution>Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR)</educationalInstitution> for his Ph.D. registration. Award of <grantName>Fast Track Scientist</grantName> to SM from <fundingAgency>DST</fundingAgency> is gratefully acknowledged. <grantName>Award of Emeritus scientist (CSIR) project</grantName> to RDT is gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. First and foremost, we thank <individual>P. J. Zinke</individual> for an insightful paper that inspired generations of ecologists. We are grateful to Will Pearse for statistical advice. We also thank the authors of the many published studies that we reviewed for this manuscript and two anonymous reviewers whose comments improved this manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Work at UB and UWM was supported by <fundingAgency>National Science</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge funding by the <fundingAgency>German-Israeli Foundation</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>DFG</fundingAgency> (Grant No. <grantNumber>SA1031/6</grantNumber> and <fundingAgency>Excellenzcluster QUEST</fundingAgency>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>B Anderson</individual>, <individual>R Pantelic</individual>, <individual>K Goldie</individual>, and <individual>M Chami</individual> for expert technical assistance, <individual>S A Müller</individual> for extensive comments on the manuscript, <individual>M Kuhn</individual> for plasmid and strain contribution, <individual>K Namba</individual> for discussions and <individual>Martin Jacquot</individual> for support with the supercomputing infrastructure of <educationalInstitution>University of Basel</educationalInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank <individual>Dr Steven J. Hamilton</individual>, 619C89 is a highly cleared drug, mainly by undergoing Woodend Hospital, Aberdeen and <individual>Professor Charles</individual> extensive hepatic biotransformation. Previous studies in F. George, <otherInstitution>Southhampton General Hospital</otherInstitution>, for contributing healthy volunteers showed that no intact 619C89 was patients to this study. We would also like to thank the nurses excreted in urine (data to be published). Even though at the clinical sites for collecting blood samples and <individual>Mr Gary</individual> plasma protein binding for 619C89 is high (# 96%) the Layton for the statistical analysis. plasma clearance of 619C89 is approximately 65% of hepatic plasma flow (1.35 l h−1 kg−1) which suggests that 619C89 is a drug with a moderate-to-high extraction ratio in humans. Second, the steady-state volume of distribution of 619C89 is large, apparently related to a References</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledging such citizenship as a ''social fiction,'' Azoulay nonetheless offers it as</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>TGT thanks <individual>Ms. J. Sridevi</individual>, <researchInstitution><fundingAgency>CSIR</fundingAgency>-Central Leather Research Institute</researchInstitution>, <individual>Chennai</individual> for EPR measurements and CSIR for nan-cial support. SCS and RSS thank <fundingAgency>IISER-TVM</fundingAgency> for computational facilities and nancial support. The authors thank <individual>Abbey M. Philip</individual> for suggesting the possibility of simulating EPR using EasySpin.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was funded by <fundingAgency>Istanbul University</fundingAgency> <grantName>Scientific Research Project</grantName> <grantNumber>33202</grantNumber>. We thank <individual>Mr David F Chapman</individual> for editing the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present study was produced from the master thesis of <individual>Deniz</individual> YILDIRIM, DVM (<educationalInstitution>Afyon Kocatepe University, Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Afyonkarahisar, Turkey</educationalInstitution>, 2011). We would like to extend our thanks to <individual>Dr. Kürşat KAV</individual>, a deceased faculty member at the <educationalInstitution>Microbiology Department of Veterinary Medical School of Selçuk University</educationalInstitution> for his valuable technical assistance and we cordially convey our deep sorrow for his untimely death and commemorate him with mercy.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study was funded by a grant from the <fundingAgency>US Agency for International Development</fundingAgency> and technical oversight was provided by <otherInstitution>MEASURE Evaluation</otherInstitution>. Secondary data analysis was conducted with permission of all collaborating authors.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are supported in part by <fundingAgency>NIMH</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>5R01MH054636</grantNumber>. MBV is supported by a <fundingAgency>National Defense Science and Engineering Graduate Fellowship (NDSEG)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>National Eye Institute</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>EY03991</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>P30-EY012576</grantNumber>, and <researchInstitution>Research to Prevent Blindness</researchInstitution>. We thank <individual>Dr Serena Fabbrini</individual> for providing Sap-3 isomer.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Author contributions : Dr Yeager is the guarantor of the paper and takes responsibility for the integrity of the work as a whole, from inception to published article. Dr Yeager: conceived of the study, conducted experiments, interpreted data, wrote and revised the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Ms Nguyen: conducted experiments, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Mr Belchenko: conducted experiments, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Ms Colvin: conducted experiments, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Dr Takatsuki: conducted experiments, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Dr Ivy: provided patient access, interpreted data, provided funding, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Dr Stenmark: interpreted data, provided funding, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Financial /nonfi nancial disclosures: The authors have reported to CHEST the following confl icts of interest: the <educationalInstitution>University of Colorado, Denver</educationalInstitution> has a contractual relationship with the pharmaceutical industry (<otherInstitution>Actelion</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Gilead</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution><fundingAgency>Pfi zer</fundingAgency></otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>United Therapeutics</otherInstitution>) for Dr Ivy to provide consultation. All monies are sent directly to the University of Colorado, Denver. Dr Stenmark has received pharmaceutical company grant monies from Pfi zer. Drs Yeager and Takatsuki, Mss Nguyen and Colvin, and Mr Belchenko have reported that no potential confl icts of interest exist with any companies/organizations whose products or services may be discussed in this article.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was partially financed by the <grantName>RECUPERA-2020</grantName> (an agreement between <fundingAgency>CSIC</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Spanish <fundingAgency>MINECO</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>EU-FEDER</fundingAgency></fundingAgency> funds) and <grantNumber>AGL2014-52465-C4-4-R</grantNumber> Projects (MINECO, EU-FEDER funds). Research of Torres-Sá nchez and Peña were financed by <fundingAgency>FPI</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Ramon y Cajal Programs</fundingAgency>, respectively (<fundingAgency>Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness</fundingAgency>). The authors thank <individual>Mr. Bernardo Crespo</individual> for allowing developing our field work in his farm.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Patric Jern</individual> for critical reading of the manuscript and useful suggestions. We thank associate professors <individual>Ewa Lundgren</individual> and <individual>Anders Liss</individual> for their valuable help with collecting samples. The study was supported by funds at the <fundingAgency>Academic Hospital, Uppsala, Sweden</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Cláudia Maria Valete-Rosalino, Armando de Oliveira Schubach and Madson Pedro da Silva Leite were responsible for the design of the study. Madelon Novato Ribeiro, José Liporage Teixeira and Monique Reis da Fonseca collected data. All authors were responsible for conducting the study and managing data; Madelon Novato Ribeiro, Cláudia Maria Valete-Rosalino, Raquel de Vasconcellos Carvalhaes de Oliveira, Maria Inês Fernandes Pimentel and Armando de Oliveira Schubach analyzed and interpreted data, and prepared manuscript; all authors reviewed and approved manuscript. We are grateful to <individual>Jacline Novato Ribeiro</individual>, <individual>Margareth de Araújo Silva</individual>, <individual>Michele Aparecida Ferreira Moreira de Oliveira</individual>, <individual>Fátima Peres Lima Dantas</individual> and <individual>Felipe Maia Maquieira da Silva</individual> for their help with the patients before the interviews. We also thank <individual>Dr. Sandro Javier BedoyaPacheco</individual> for help with the database. This study was funded by <fundingAgency>PAPES-FIOCRUZ</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq)</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Carlos Chagas Filho Foundation for Research Support in the State of Rio de Janeiro (FAPERJ)</fundingAgency>. Funding agencies had no interference in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis and interpretation of the data; and preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>Professor L. Ernster</individual> and <individual>Dr P. Gellerfors</individual> for their helpful discussion and suggestions, and <individual>Miss B. Persson</individual> for excellent technical assistance. The work was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>Swedish Cancer Society</fundingAgency> and by an <grantName>EMBO short-term fellowship</grantName> to F.G.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to <individual>Professor G. F. Azzone</individual> for helpful discussions and for reading the manuscript. The expert technical assistance of <individual>Mr Luciano</individual></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author would like to thank <individual>Prof. F. Klinkhamer</individual> and <individual>Prof. E. M. C. Abreu</individual> for useful discussions. The author would also like to thank <individual>Prof. U.Tirnakli</individual> for sending reference  [22] .</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful for financial support from the <fundingAgency>Henan Administration of Science and Technology</fundingAgency> (grant No. <grantNumber>0111030700</grantNumber>). Supplementary data and figures for this paper are available from the IUCr electronic archives (Reference: BV2111).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author is grateful to <individual>Brian Brush</individual> for his helpful comments and suggestions and acknowledges the financial support from the <grantName>College of Business Administration Miles Research Grant</grantName> at <fundingAgency>Marquette University</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge the support from the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (projects <grantNumber>137630</grantNumber> to U.S. and <grantNumber>160055</grantNumber> to H.B.). Special thanks go to the technical and scientific members of the <researchInstitution>Geneva and Zurich research groups</researchInstitution> who helped at all stages of this study. H.B. thanks <individual>Peter Hochuli</individual> (<affiliation>University of Zurich</affiliation>), <individual>Jean Guex</individual> and <individual>Torsten Vennemann</individual> (both <affiliation>University of Lausanne</affiliation>), and <individual>Helmut Weissert</individual> and <individual>Stefano Bernasconi</individual> (both <affiliation>ETH Zurich</affiliation>) for long term and highly stimulating scientific discussions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author would like to thank <individual>Prof. Dr. Ronald H. W. Hoppe</individual> and <individual>Prof. Dr. H.-J. Bungartz</individual> for the kind invitation to deliver a plenary lecture at the Annual Meeting of GAMM at Augsburg in March of 2002. The content of paper is based on that lecture. The author would also like to thank <individual>Ryuta Suzuki</individual> for discussions leading to a better presentation of the material in this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The last author would like to thank <individual>George Lowther</individual> for the idea of non-linear bounds, <individual>Michael Greinecker</individual> for his hints on dealing with kernels, and other users of MathStackexchange and MathOverflow for their valuable comments regarding measure theory and coupling.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Pr André Dufour</individual> for his help with statistical analyses.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We want to particularly acknowledge the patients enrolled in this study for their participation and the <researchInstitution>Basque Biobank for Research-OEHUN</researchInstitution> for its collaboration providing the human samples and the clinical information used in this project with appropriate ethics approval. Our gratefulness to <individual>Dr. Juan Burgos</individual> for the selection of the human samples and <individual>Dr. Felix Royo</individual> for helping with statistical analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank <individual>E. Brockmann</individual> and two anonymous reviewers for their helpful reviews. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS-INSU)</fundingAgency>,</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>[56] Acknowledgments. We are grateful for the advice of <individual>Deborah</individual></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to gratefully acknowledge the contribution of <individual>E.L. Aronson</individual></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Felix Kahlhoefer</individual>, <individual>Matthew McCullough</individual>, <individual>Ian Shoemaker</individual>, <individual>John March-Russell</individual> and <individual>Stephen West</individual> for discussions. MD and CM also wish to thank <individual>Michael Spannowsky</individual> for 'stimulating' discussions. We thank <individual>Gary Steigman</individual> for pointing out an error in eq. (10) in an early version of this work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This paper is a product of the <projectName>UK Natural Environment Research Council's Valuing Nature Network</projectName> with additional support from the <fundingAgency>Economic and Social Research Council and UK Department for International Development</fundingAgency>. We thank all participants in the <projectName>VNN project workshops</projectName> for their inputs.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank <individual>Dr. Haruhiko MORI</individual>  (17)</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>HL 69723 (S.M.S)</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Yoshiko Miyake</individual>, <individual>Yoko Shiozawa</individual>, <individual>Seiichi Kotoda</individual>, <individual>Yoshiharu Tsuru</individual>, <individual>Toshihiro Nagai</individual>, <individual>Koji Shimoda</individual>, and <individual>Toshio Terashima</individual> for excellent technical assistance. We are also grateful to <individual>Kazuto Yamazaki</individual>, <individual>Keiko Fukada</individual>, and <individual>Takeshi Suzuki</individual> for their comments on the manuscript. This study was supported in part by research grants from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education, Science and Culture, Japan</fundingAgency>, and by the <fundingAgency>Program for Promotion of Fundamental Studies in Health Science of the National Institute of Biomedical Innovation</fundingAgency> (to K. Fukuda).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the villagers of Dielmo for their participation and continued collaboration in this project. We thank the administrative authority of <otherInstitution>Institut Pasteur of Dakar</otherInstitution> for their continuous support. We particularly thank the field workers for their sustained contribution to the project and in generating and maintaining the malaria databases. We thank the reviewers for their comments that have greatly improved the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank all those colleagues who have recently collaborated with us in the realization of the <projectName>µSR experiments</projectName> in the IBS. In particular: <individual>Alex Amato</individual>, <individual>Pietro Bonfà</individual>, <individual>Lucia Bossoni</individual>, <individual>Sean Giblin</individual>, <individual>Rustem Khasanov</individual>, <individual>Gianrico Lamura</individual>, <individual>Hubertus Luetkens</individual>, <individual>Marcello Mazzani</individual> and <individual>Toni Shiroka. Pietro Carretta</individual> and <individual>Samuele Sanna</individual> also acknowledge the financial support from <fundingAgency>Fondazione Cariplo</fundingAgency> (research grant no. <grantNumber>2011-0266</grantNumber>) for the research activity on IBS. Giacomo Prando acknowledges support from the <fundingAgency>Leibniz-Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst (DAAD)Post-Doc Fellowship Program</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</fundingAgency>. We are indebted to <individual>Professor Dr A. Trebst</individual> for many helpful discussions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Dr Sophie Rushton-Smith</individual> provided editorial assistance in the preparation of this manuscript, which was funded by the <fundingAgency>Association Naturalia et Biologia</fundingAgency>. <individual>Ph.Gabriel Steg</individual> has the following disclosures:</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the <educationalInstitution>School of Biological Sciences and Department of Biochemistry, University of Nairobi (UoN)</educationalInstitution> for providing research facilities for use in this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author is grateful to <individual>Dr. Ibrahim ElAgib</individual> of <affiliation>King Saud University, College of Sciences, Physics  &amp;  Astronomy Department</affiliation>, for valuable discussions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>NIH/NCI</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber># CA125456 (SBE)</grantNumber>, and a grant from the <fundingAgency>Israel-USA Bi-national Science Foundation</fundingAgency> <grantNumber># 2005331 (SBE)</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was conducted in the framework of the <grantName>EU-funded BIOMAHE Marie CurieToK Project</grantName> (<grantNumber>MTKD-CT-2004-509232</grantNumber>) and was partially supported by the <fundingAgency>Italian Ministry of University and Research (MUR)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is a joint work between <fundingAgency>ISAE/DMIA, ON-ERA/DTIM</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>UC Berkeley/EECS</fundingAgency>. G. Lasnier has been funded by the <fundingAgency>RTRA-FCS STAE Foundation</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments. Thanks to <individual>Will Stefanov</individual> (<affiliation>Department of Geology</affiliation>) and <individual>Jim Clark</individual> (<affiliation>Department of Chemistry</affiliation>) for valuable assistance in obtaining optical analyses and electron microprobe measurements. Thanks also to <individual>Bob Leighty</individual> and <individual>Kim Feely</individual> for sharing personal</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Dipartimento <educationalInstitution>di Scienze Neurologiche, Università di Bologna, Bologna, Italy</educationalInstitution>. Published: 28 September 2015</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>DMS-1517085</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by a Grant from the <fundingAgency>Korean Healthcare Technology R &amp; D Project, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Republic of Korea</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>HI10C1740</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The journal is published in one volume per year consisting of five numbers (one double number). The annual subscription price 1998 is DM 725,-; foreign $470.00 incl. postage and handling; personal rate DM 215,-; foreign $ 140.00. Single copy DM 140,-. The publisher must be notified of a cancellation of a subscription not later than three months before the end of the calendar year. After that date the subscription is automatically prolonged for another year. Authorization to photocopy items for internal or personal use, or the internal or personal use of specific clients, is granted by WILEY-VCH Verlag Berlin GmbH, provided that the base fee of US $ 17.50 per copy, plus US $ .50 per page is paid directly to Copyright Clearance Center, 27 Congress Street, SALEM, MA 01970, USA. For those organizations that have been granted a photocopy license by CCC, a separate system of payment has been arranged. The fee code for users of the Transactional Reporting Service is: 0863-0593/98 $ 17.50 + .50. All rights reserved (including those of translations into foreign languages). No part of this issue may be reproduced in any form, by photoprint, microfilm, or any other means, nor transmitted or translated into a machine language, without written permission from the publishers.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The editors would like to acknowledge both the significant contribution made by <individual>Pamela Walt</individual>], whose hard work, organisation and language skills made the original manuscript for this book possible, and the expert and patient assistance of <individual>Helen Green</individual> with the production of drafts of this text. Acknowledgements xi</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Conceived and designed the experiments: <otherInstitution>OS PT PA</otherInstitution>. Performed the experiments: <otherInstitution>OS PT CB JL MU</otherInstitution>. Analyzed the data: <otherInstitution>OS PT CB JL MU PP PA</otherInstitution>. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PP. Wrote the paper: PA.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>Editor Juan Pedro Rodríguez-López</individual> and to two anonymous reviewers for their constructive recommendations on how to improve this manuscript. MAM is grateful to <fundingAgency>audi Aramco</fundingAgency> for their sponsorship of this research programme. <fundingAgency>Areva</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>BHPBilliton</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>ConocoPhillips</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Nexen</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Saudi Aramco</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Shell</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Tullow Oil</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Woodside</fundingAgency> are thanked for their sponsorship of the wider <projectName>FRG-ERG research programme</projectName> at the <educationalInstitution>University of Leeds</educationalInstitution>, of which this study forms a part.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to gratefully acknowledge <individual>Dr Robert Greef</individual> for valuable suggestions with the optical set up and characterisation of the samples. Thanks to the financial support from the <fundingAgency>Faculty of Engineering</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Environment at the University of Southampton</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Engineering and Physical Sciences research council (EPSRC)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author wish to thank specialis <individual>ALFatlawy</individual> whom diagnose the study cases and <individual>Baha H ALAmiedi ,Ph.D</individual> for the help extended by him <affiliation>college of dentistry, university of Babyl governerate</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <projectName>Intramural Research Program</projectName> of the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual>Pr. Mamadou Dembele</individual>, <individual>Dr Mohamed Keita</individual>, <individual>Dr Mamadou Traore</individual>, <affiliation>PPD study monitors</affiliation>, <otherInstitution>NIAID DSMB</otherInstitution>, <individual>Etsegenet Meshesha</individual>, <individual>Dick Sakai</individual>, <individual>Drissa Sow</individual>, and the volunteers in the villages for their support. We would also like to acknowledge <individual>Hong Zhou</individual>, <individual>Sam Moretz</individual>, <individual>Ababacar Diouf</individual> and <individual>Greg Tullo</individual> for the GIA work and the <researchInstitution>PATH/Malaria Vaccine Initiative</researchInstitution> for their support of the GIA Reference Center.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr Hideki Takahashi</individual> in <affiliation>Michigan State University</affiliation> for providing sultr1;1 sultr1;2 double mutant, and <individual>Professor Pradipsinh Rathod</individual> in <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation> for E. coli GS245(DE3)pLysS strain. We thank <individual>Phillip SanMiguel</individual> and the <researchInstitution>Purdue Agricultural Genomics Center</researchInstitution> for the short read sequencing and analysis. We thank <individual>Elena Yakubova</individual> and <individual>Brett Lahner</individual> for ICP-MS analysis, <individual>Dr Andrea Raab</individual> for use of the HPLC facility, and the <researchInstitution>Microscopy and Histology Core Facility</researchInstitution> at the <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation> for using the confocal laser-scanning microscopy.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledged experts in the technologies key to maritime operations. Acquisition and maintenance strategies which will strengthen the public/private relationships to produce quality products and services faster and at competitive prices.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge funding from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>R01GM118675</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>R21EB021651</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>CHE-1351933</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present research was partly supported by <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (No. <grantNumber>31672071</grantNumber>), and <fundingAgency>Special Funds of Central Colleges Basic Scientific Research Operating Expenses</fundingAgency> (No. <grantNumber>2452015096</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank all volunteers for their participation in the study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>L Chamberlain</individual> and <individual>B Martin</individual> for sharing their Acyl-RAC protocol, Y and <individual>M Fukata</individual> for the DHHC plasmids and the <researchInstitution>PEGylation protocol</researchInstitution>, <individual>P Bastiaens</individual> for the APT plasmids and <individual>Sylvia Ho</individual> for generating the shRNA ZDHHC6 construct. The research leading to these results has received funding from the <fundingAgency>European Research Council</fundingAgency> under the <projectName>European Union's Seventh Framework Programme</projectName> (<grantNumber>FP/2007(FP/ -2013)/ERC Grant</grantNumber> Agreement n. <grantNumber>340260 -PalmERa</grantNumber>'. This work was also supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (to GvdG and to VH), the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Centre of Competence in Research (NCCR) Chemical Biology</fundingAgency> (to GvdG) and the <fundingAgency>Swiss SystemsX.ch initiative</fundingAgency> evaluated by the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation (LipidX)</fundingAgency> (to GvdG and to VH). TD is a recipient of an <grantName>iPhD fellowship</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>Swiss SystemsX.ch initiative</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The research leading to these results has in part been funded by the <fundingAgency>ESA project GHG-CCI</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>DLR grant SADOS</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>EU project ACCENT-Plus</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>University</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>State of Bremen</fundingAgency>. Russell R. Dickerson was supported by <fundingAgency>NASA/AQAST</fundingAgency>. We thank <researchInstitution>ESA</researchInstitution> and <researchInstitution>DLR</researchInstitution> for providing the SCIAMACHY Level 1 data and the <researchInstitution>SCIA-MACHY calibration team</researchInstitution> (<researchInstitution>DLR</researchInstitution>, <researchInstitution>SRON</researchInstitution>, <educationalInstitution>University of Bremen, ESA</educationalInstitution>, and others) for continuously improving the quality of the spectra. We acknowledge the use of data from the <otherInstitution>U.S. Energy Information Administration</otherInstitution> and the <otherInstitution>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</otherInstitution>. We also thank the <otherInstitution>European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF)</otherInstitution> for providing the meteorological reanalysis data. Fracking well</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to acknowledge the <otherInstitution>Irish Cattle Breeding Federation (ICBF)</otherInstitution> for access to estimates of sire merit.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments: We thank <individual>Steve Berman</individual> and <individual>Edwin Asturias</individual> for their guidance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Bernhard Geiger</individual> for providing liver MR images, as well as <individual>Ali Khamene</individual> and <individual>Frank Sauer</individual> for their support. This work is funded by <fundingAgency>Siemens Corporate Research and Institute for Mathematics and its Applications (IMA)</fundingAgency> at the <fundingAgency>University of Minnesota</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was conducted by the financial grant provided by <fundingAgency>JSS University, Mysore</fundingAgency>. Authors sincerely acknowledge their support and encouragement.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. Work of the third author is partially supported by <projectName>STARTproject</projectName> <grantNumber>Y237</grantNumber> of the <fundingAgency>Austrian Science Fund</fundingAgency> and by the <fundingAgency>MNZZS of Serbia 144016</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We cordially thank <individual>Dr. Gerd Neugebauer</individual> for his help in creating a subset of a bibtex data base using BibTool, as well as <individual>Dr. Ricardo</individual> <individual>A. Chávez Montes</individual>, <individual>Prof. Magnus Palmblad</individual> and <individual>Martin Fenner</individual> for comments on the manuscript. Warm thanks also go to <individual>Anubhav Kumar</individual> and <individual>Jennifer König</individual> for proofreading.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy, US Department of Energy</fundingAgency> under grant <grantNumber>DE-FG36-08G018006</grantNumber>. One of us (GMK) ~cknowledges support under an <fundingAgency>NDSEG graduate fellowship</fundingAgency>. We also acknowledge use of facilities supported by the <otherInstitution>Center for Science and Engineering of Materials</otherInstitution>, an NSF MRSEC.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I would like to thank <individual>Mr. Emile A. Minoli</individual> for contributions in Chapters 2 and 3. The cover page shows <individual>Daniel Minoli</individual> (center front) with a slide rule next to an AM radio the student trio built based on discrete electronic components. Students <individual>Melvin Lee</individual> (left front) and <individual>Steven Lightburn</individual> (right front) part of the student trio are with <individual>Mr. Tepper</individual> (middle front), electronics teacher in a <educationalInstitution>Technical Electronics Laboratory in Hight School in Brooklyn, NY</educationalInstitution> in the fall of 1970. Two second-row students are unidentified. As this textbook shows, electronics and electronics density has come a long way in the past 35 years, and will continue to do so under the thrust of nanotechnology.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>All sequences were performed at the <researchInstitution>Molecular Biology Unit, Institut Pasteur de Montevideo</researchInstitution>. The authors thank <individual>Natalia Rego</individual> and <individual>Horacio Botti</individual> for helpful discussion and suggestions, <individual>Hugo Naya</individual> for sharing the bioinformatic facilities of <researchInstitution>UBI</researchInstitution> <researchInstitution>Institut Pasteur Montevideo</researchInstitution> and <individual>Marissa Vignali</individual> and <individual>Peter Myler</individual> (<affiliation>Seattle Biomedical Research Institute; Seattle, WA USA</affiliation>) for helpful suggestions in library construction and sequencing.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <individual>Thomas O. Mason</individual> for numerous stimulating discussions. Initial simulations for amorphous Zn-Sn-In-O under strain were performed by <individual>Rabi Khanal</individual>. The work was performed under the collaborative <projectName>MRSEC program</projectName> at <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation> and supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation (NSF)</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>DMR-1121262</grantNumber>. Computational resources are provided by the <projectName>NSF-supported XSEDE program</projectName> and by <otherInstitution>Department of Energy NERSC</otherInstitution> facilities.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. This work was developed under the <grantName>MINECO predoctoral grants</grantName> <grantNumber>BES-2014-067894</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>EEBB-I-16-11044</grantNumber>, cofunded by the <fundingAgency>European Social Fund</fundingAgency>. The work at University of Barcelona was partly supported by the <fundingAgency>Spanish MINECO</fundingAgency> under the project <grantNumber>AYA2013-42614-P</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>AYA2016-77939-P</grantNumber> with partial support by the <fundingAgency>European Regional Development Fund (ERDF/FEDER)</fundingAgency>. RGH acknowledges the financial support of the <fundingAgency>University of Alcalá</fundingAgency> under project <grantNumber>CCG2015/EXP-055</grantNumber> and the <fundingAgency>Spanish MINECO</fundingAgency> under project <grantNumber>ESP2015-68266-R</grantNumber>. Funding of this work was also partially provided by the <fundingAgency>Spanish MINECO</fundingAgency> under the <projectName>project MDM-2014-0369</projectName> of <affiliation>ICCUB (Unidad de Excelencia "Marıá de Maeztu")</affiliation>. The editor thanks <individual>R. Du Toit Strauss</individual> and an anonymous referee for their assistance in evaluating this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments All images are by <individual>Francesco Gherardini</individual> unless otherwise noted.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Statistical analysis. A t-test (two tailed) was performed for statistical analysis if not otherwise specified. An F-test was used to determine equal or unequal variance in the t-test. *, ** and *** indicate P valueo0.05,o0.01 ando0.001, respectively. Data availability. Solid-state NMR data is available at: https://www.repository. cam.ac.uk/handle/1810/254646. The authors declare that all other relevant data supporting the findings of this study are available within the article and its Supplementary Information Files or on request from the corresponding authors.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank members of the <researchInstitution>Hutter lab</researchInstitution> for critically reading the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The results in this paper may also be applicable to robustness to source distribution. We considered robustness in the observation channel. However, some of results also apply almost without change to robustness in the input distribution. Ornstein'sd-distance  [18] ,  [13]  is also a meaningful distance when the uncertainty is in the input distribution, but requires the cost function to be specific. Such problems for the specific case of minimum mean square estimation were considered in  [25] . The important general problem merits further research.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>J.-Y. Zimmer</individual> for his helpful comments and suggestions. Thanks also to the <fundingAgency>Wallonia-Brussels International</fundingAgency> for the <grantName>Ph.D. scholarship</grantName> (S. Boukraa).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The Biodiversity Data Enrichment Hackathon was supported by the <fundingAgency>EU-funded proiBiosphere project (Coordination and policy development in preparation for a European Open Biodiversity Knowledge Management System, addressing Acquisition, Curation, Synthesis, Interoperability and Dissemination</fundingAgency>, grant No <grantNumber>312848</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Naturalis Biodiversity Center</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was carried out while BC was at the <educationalInstitution>California Institute of Technology</educationalInstitution>, and partially when both BC and KB were visiting the <researchInstitution>Isaac Newton Institute, Cambridge, UK</researchInstitution>. It is a pleasure to thank <individual>Prof. L. C. Evans</individual> for useful discussions. We are also grateful for the support of the <fundingAgency>U.S. National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>CMS 9457573</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>Air-Force Office of Scientific Research</fundingAgency> through a <grantName>MURI grant</grantName> (<grantNumber>F49602-98-1-0433</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The program was partially supported by <fundingAgency>NASA Lewis Research Center</fundingAgency> (Grant No. <grantNumber>NAG 3-782</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>Office of Naval Research</fundingAgency> (Contract No. <grantNumber>NO0014-85-K-0182 P005</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Serena Dudek</individual>, <individual>Kelly Carstens</individual>, and <individual>Deborah Park</individual> for critical reading of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Nathan L. Vanderford</individual> for critical reading and editing of this manuscript. This work was supported by grants from <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>RO1CA125454</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Susan G Komen Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>KG081310</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Mary Kay Ash Foundation</fundingAgency> (to B.P. Zhou) and <grantName>pre-doctoral fellowship</grantName> (<grantNumber>BC101068</grantNumber>) from <fundingAgency>DoD Breast Cancer Research Program</fundingAgency> (to Y. Lin).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <educationalInstitution>Core Facility and Laboratory Animal Unit of the LKS Faculty of Medicine</educationalInstitution>, the <affiliation>University of Hong Kong</affiliation> for technical support. We are thankful to <individual>Dr Terence Kin-Wah Lee</individual>, <individual>Dr. Stephanie Kwai-Yee Ma</individual> and <individual>Dr Judy Wai-Ping Yam</individual> for their helpful discussion on the study and comments on the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The S.E.R.C and A.F.R.C. are gratefully acknowledged for financial support. Thanks are due to <individual>Dr. C. Roessner</individual>, <affiliation>Texas A &amp; M University, TX, U.S.A.</affiliation>, for providing the E coli hemB expression system, to <individual>Mr D. Barton</individual> and <individual>Mr. P. Skelton</individual> (<affiliation>Cambridge</affiliation>) for electro-spray mass-spectrometry determinations, and to <individual>Dr. J. Cheung</individual>, <individual>Queen Mary</individual> and <affiliation>Wesffield College, London</affiliation>, for deprotecting the 3-oxo-1-hexylamine.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to acknowledge <individual>Paula Weston</individual> and <individual>Melinda Golde</individual> for their great work in processing human fetal prostate tissue sections. Also, we would like to recognize <individual>Dr. Simon Hayward</individual> for his support and guidance regarding the pathology of the human fetal tissue.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge the facilities of the <researchInstitution>Department of Biotechnology, Government of India, New Delhi (DBT)</researchInstitution> under <projectName>M.Sc. Biotechnology program</projectName>. Facilities of  <researchInstitution>DBT's Bioinformatics Sub Center</researchInstitution> are also gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Health Bureau of Zhejiang Province</fundingAgency> (grant no. <grantNumber>2013KYA108</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Health and Family Planning Commission of Zhejiang Province</fundingAgency> (grant nos. <grantNumber>2013KYA108</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>2014KYA260</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was funded by the <grantName>Dennis Cooper Hematology Young Investigator Award</grantName> and grant <grantNumber>P30 CA016359</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>National Cancer Institute</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work has been carried out in the scope of <projectName>INCO-DC project</projectName> <grantNumber>ERBIC18CT97016</grantNumber> 'Development of a simple technology in drinking water treatment for nitrate and pesticide removal', financed by the <fundingAgency>European Commission</fundingAgency>. Thanks to <individual>Fred Rainey</individual> for supplying the sequence and manuscript for T. hydrothermalis in advance of their publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Michel Desjardins</individual> for making the Phosphorimager system available to us. We also thank <individual>Sonia Broccoli</individual> for critical reading of the manuscript. This work was supported by Grants <grantNumber>FNR 12667</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>CIHR (to M.D.)</fundingAgency> and <grantNumber>GM54226</grantNumber> from <fundingAgency>NIGMS</fundingAgency> (to Y.-C.T.-D). M.D. is a <grantName>chercheur-boursier senior</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>FRSQ</fundingAgency>. C.H. holds a studenship award from the <fundingAgency>FRSQ</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to acknowledge the help of 161</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors gratefully acknowledge the financial support by the <fundingAgency>Research Program of Universities of Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>NJ10245</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank <individual>Graham Mc Geoch</individual>, Chief <affiliation>Clinical Editor, Health Pathways, Canterbury District Health Board</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgement. I wish to thank <individual>Professor Janusz Brzdȩk</individual> for paying my attention to the problem and for his most valuable suggestions during the preparation of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments This research was funded by the <fundingAgency>European</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank the <researchInstitution>Staglin IMHRO Center for Cognitive Neuroscience</researchInstitution> for their expert technical assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS. We are grateful to <individual>Y. Asari</individual>, <individual>C. Tanaka</individual>, <individual>M. Noda</individual>, <individual>R. Haraguchi</individual>, <individual>M. Matsuhashi</individual>, <individual>K. Akashi</individual>, <individual>S. Satoh</individual>, <individual>N. Machida</individual>, <individual>A. Yoshioka</individual>, and <individual>I. Izumi</individual>, for their technical assistance. We thank <individual>Y. Hashimoto</individual>, <individual>H. Yanagawa</individual>, and <individual>Y. Konno</individual> for their critical comments and <individual>C. L. Bridgman</individual> for her critical reading of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Yunde Zhao</individual> and <individual>Youfa Cheng</individual> for sharing seed and reagents prior to publication. We thank <individual>Judy Callis</individual> and <individual>John Labavitch</individual> for helpful discussions on this project. Some seed stocks were obtained from the <otherInstitution>ABRC</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funding: This research was funded by the <fundingAgency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</fundingAgency> (grant number <grantNumber>R01HS018372</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is partially financed by the <fundingAgency>ERDF European Regional Development Fund</fundingAgency> through the <projectName>COMPETE Programme</projectName> and by <fundingAgency>National Funds</fundingAgency> through the <fundingAgency>FCT Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia</fundingAgency> within <projectName>project SELF-PVP</projectName> (<grantNumber>FCOMP-01-0124-FEDER-013070</grantNumber>)</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank the <educationalInstitution>Electron Microscopy Unit, Universidade da Coruna</educationalInstitution>, for the fachties. This study was partially funded by the <fundingAgency>Servicio de M e d~o Arnbiente Natural</fundingAgency>,</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Y. Fujita</individual> and <individual>Barry Gumbiner</individual> for constructs and <individual>Marc Mumby</individual> for PP2Ac antibody. This research was supported in part by <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>GM56362</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>CA142823</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author wish to thank <individual>E. Brod</individual>, <individual>R. Pedersen</individual>, <individual>A.F. Øgaard</individual> and <individual>T.K. Haraldsen</individual> for advice on experimental setup and obtaining waste materials. The author also wishes to thank two anonymous reviewers and the editor for useful advice and editing of the manuscript. This study was funded by <fundingAgency>CORE Organic II "IMproved Phosphorus Resource efficiency in Organic agriculture Via recycling and Enhanced biological mobilisation" (IMPROVE-P)</fundingAgency>, which aims to design improved P recycling systems for organic farming.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported in part by <projectName>CONACYT project</projectName> <grantNumber>32415-E</grantNumber> and <projectName>DGAPA, UNAM project</projectName> <grantNumber>IN-110200</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to the <fundingAgency>National Institutes for Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>GM094919 (EUREKA)</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>Science Foundation of Ireland</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>08/IN.1/B2070</grantNumber>) for support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <individual>Dr. Ian Macara</individual> for providing the wildtype and GAP-deficient p190RhoGAP expression vectors. We also wish to thank <individual>Christy Cloonan</individual> for excellent technical assistance, <individual>Dr. Channing Der</individual> for the Lsc construct, <individual>Geneva Arthur</individual> for preparation of the manuscript, and the members of the <affiliation>Burridge laboratory</affiliation> and <individual>Dr. Leslie Petch</individual> for thoughtful discussions. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>GM29860</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge use of beamline BL17U1 at the <researchInstitution>Shanghai Synchrotron Radiation Facility (China)</researchInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This paper was supported by the research fund from <fundingAgency>Samsung Medison, Inc.</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The research was carried out due to the grant of <fundingAgency>Russian Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (project <grantNumber>#17-17-01143</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The first author's research is partially supported by grants from <fundingAgency>National Advanced Technology Research</fundingAgency> and</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>P.A. Baikov</individual>, <individual>A.G. Grozin</individual>, and <individual>O.V. Tarasov</individual> for help with checking the analytical results for the contribution (i). This research has been supported by the <fundingAgency>Russian Foundation for Basic Research</fundingAgency>, project <grantNumber>96-01-00654</grantNumber>, and by the grant <grantNumber>BMBF 057KA92P</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge <individual>James Blanchard</individual>, <individual>Andrea Hunter</individual> and <individual>Rachel Spitzer</individual> for their participation; <individual>Kerri Wazny</individual> for providing technical support; and the <fundingAgency>Canadian Partnership for Women and Children's Health (CanWaCH)</fundingAgency> for their support in this collaborative effort. CanWaCH is a collaboration of more than 80 Canadian organizations that are working to improve maternal, newborn, child and adolescent health in low-and middle-income countries.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are very grateful to <individual>Pete Alcock</individual> and <individual>John Mohan</individual> for their leadership, support and encouragement, and to <individual>Jane Parry</individual> and <individual>Rebecca Taylor</individual> for earlier collaborations on the topic of internships. We would also like to thank the anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgment: We thank <individual>Cyrus Shahpar, MPH</individual>, and <individual>Sophia Sterling, MPH</individual>, for data assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments: This project/research has been made possible with the support of the <fundingAgency>Dutch Province of Limburg</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Internalized violence begat despair, heightened suspicion, justified spying, and raised the temptation to deal with the growing instability with yet more violence. When the first 42 AGI, Estado, lima, 74/13, 29/04/1817, VC Pezuela to <individual>Secr de Estado</individual>; Santa Fe, 57/35. This is the file series that got lost in the mail; see AGI series cards 211-212; Estado, Americas, 88/3, "Memorial en nombre dl; Fernando VII."</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>"Scientific Exchange Programme between the New Member States of the EU and Switzerland"</fundingAgency> (<grantName>Sciex-NMS</grantName>, project <grantNumber>10.140</grantNumber>) and by the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (grant <grantNumber>31003A_140766</grantNumber>). The study was also funded by the <fundingAgency>National Science Centre in Kraków, Poland</fundingAgency> (grant nos. <grantNumber>2013/11/B/ST10/00276</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>2014/12/T/ST10/00675</grantNumber>). The authors thank the crew of <otherInstitution>R/V Oceania</otherInstitution> for their assistance during the fieldwork. <individual>Mateusz Ostrowski</individual> is thanked for helping with the granulometric analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Yue Zhao</individual>, <affiliation>MSc, Concordia University, Montreal, Quebec</affiliation>, and <individual>Linda Kwakkenbos, PhD</individual>, <affiliation>Lady Davis Institute for Medical Research, Jewish General Hospital, Montreal, Quebec</affiliation>, for assistance with translation. They were not compensated for their contributions. No funding body had any involvement in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; and preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Ethics Human subjects: This study was approved by the local ethics committee (<grantNumber>CSE01321</grantNumber>; <affiliation>University of Glasgow, College of Science and Engineering</affiliation>) and conducted in conformity with the Declaration of Helsinki. All participants provided informed written consent before participating in the experiment and received monetary compensation for their participation.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke intramural program (MNB and NAS)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Columbia University Center for Motor Neuron Biology and Disease (NAS)</fundingAgency> and by <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health Grant NS047357 (CAS and FJA)</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual>Chris Henderson</individual>, <individual>Tom Jessell</individual>, <individual>George Mentis</individual> and <individual>Michael O'Donovan</individual> for their support and critical comments on this manuscript. We also thank <individual>Ms Jackie Sisco</individual> with her help preparing semithin histological sections of muscle spindles.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Professors Dr. Mofazzal Hossain</individual> and <individual>Dr. Mizanur Rahman</individual>, <fundingAgency>Department of Horticulture (BSMRAU)</fundingAgency>, are thanked for allowing the junior author to set yellow pan traps for collecting parasitic Hymenoptera in their experimental plots. We thank <individual>J. Read</individual> (<affiliation>CNC</affiliation>) for preparing the excellent images and compiling the plates.</acknowledgment>
    </acknowledgments>
</TEI>