<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <acknowledgments>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported by the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</fundingAgency> through the <projectName>SFB 649 "Economic Risk"</projectName>. http://sfb649.wiwi.hu-berlin.de ISSN 1860-5664</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>ACKNOWLEDGMENT. We are grateful to <individual>Dr. G.D. Niswender</individual> (<affiliation>Animal Reproduction and Biotechnology Laboratory, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO, U.S.A.</affiliation>) for providing antisera to estradiol-17β (GDN 244) and testosterone (GDN 250).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the personal of <otherInstitution>UTSW Microarray Core</otherInstitution> for assistance with these experiments and to <individual>Janet Young</individual> for administrative assistance. We are thankful to <individual>Thomas Südhof</individual> and <individual>Katsuhiko Tabuchi</individual> for a generous gift of Lenti-NLS-GFP-Cre virus. This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Hereditary Disease Foundation</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>NINDS R01 NS38082</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>R01 NS056224 (IB)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NINDS R01 NS043466 (SZ)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>NIH GM59419 (GH)</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>Ara Parseghian Medical Research Foundation (JR)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank <individual>Ewa Latkowska</individual> for her excellent technical support. This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Polish Ministry of Science and Higher Education</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>2670/B/P01/2008/34</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>0757/B/P01/2009/37</grantNumber>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Dr. Chunhua Weng</individual> from <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation> and <individual>Dr. Cui Tao</individual> from <affiliation><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></affiliation> who participated in the evaluation. The authors also thank the technical support from <individual>Mr. Craig Stancl</individual> from Mayo Clinic. The study is supported in part by the <projectName>SHARP Area 4: Secondary Use of EHR Data (90TR000201)</projectName>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The data and views presented here are those of the authors alone and do not reflect or imply the formal views of the U.S. Food and Drug Administration or any other entity. This study was supported by the National Center for  Toxicological   . Many of the experiments described in this research utilized a HeLa cell line. <individual><individual>Henrietta Lacks</individual></individual>, and the HeLa cell line that was established from her tumor cells without her knowledge or consent in 1951, have made significant contributions to scientific progress and advances in human health. We are grateful to Henrietta Lacks, now deceased, and to her surviving family members for their contributions to biomedical research.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The human seminal vesicles were provided by the <researchInstitution>National Disease Research Interchange</researchInstitution>. We thank <individual>Christine Monfort</individual> for statistical analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>To <individual>Dr Marize Miagostovich</individual> and <individual>Ms Eliana Saraiva</individual> for the help during laboratorial diagnosis and the technical support from <individual>Ms Mariana Lopes</individual> and <individual>Ms Maryrose Lavatori</individual>. To <individual>Dr Joseli Lannes-Vieira</individual>, <affiliation>Department of Immunology</affiliation>, <individual>Fiocruz</individual>, and <individual>Dr Ricardo Galler</individual> for critically reviewing the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to the parents and children from the urban slums of Vellore for their enthusiastic participation and support. We also thank <individual>Drs. Rajiv Sarkar</individual>, <individual>Deepthi Kattula</individual> and field workers for their tireless monitoring of the cohorts and all the support staff of the <researchInstitution>Division of Gastrointestinal Sciences, Christian Medical College, Vellore</researchInstitution>, who made the studies possible.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was done as part of the IDEFICS Study and is published on behalf of its European Consortium (http://www.idefics.eu). We gratefully acknowledge the financial support of the <fundingAgency>European Community</fundingAgency> within the <grantNumber>Sixth RTD Framework Programme Contract No. 016181 (FOOD)</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Carl Tryggers Stiftelse for Vetenskaplig Forskning and Stiftelsen Samariten</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>B. Zeppenfeld</individual> and <individual>A. Daniel</individual> for excellent technical assistance. Antibody against Oxa1p was a kind gift of <individual>J. W. de Gier</individual>, <affiliation>Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics, the Arrhenius Laboratory for Natural Sciences, Stockholm University, Stockholm, Sweden</affiliation>. The research was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, Sonderforschungsbereich TR-1</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Fonds der Chemischen Industrie</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank all the employees of the <affiliation>Icelandic Heart Preventive Clinic (Hjartavernd)</affiliation> for their skilful contribution to the data collection. the <fundingAgency>Medical Faculty and the Research Fund of the University of Iceland</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Icelandic Research Council</fundingAgency> supported this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank <individual>Michel Cantou</individual> for the sampling of bivalves, <individual>Enric Saiz</individual> and <individual>Rosa Maria Borrat Padrosa</individual> for providing Paracartia grani eggs, <individual>Maximillien Cuny</individual> and <individual>Benoît Moirod</individual> for their help with PCR analyses, <individual>Maëva Robert</individual> for sequencing and <individual>Emmanuelle Omnes</individual> for histological slide preparation. The present study was supported by the <projectName>GELAMED</projectName> project through a grant allocated by the <fundingAgency>MEEDDM (Ministère de l"Ecologie, de l"Energie, du Développement Durable et de la Mer, France)</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>Total foundation, France</fundingAgency> to D. Bonnet (<grantNumber>Programme 189 -« Recherche » 18902 C</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The outcome of this work owes to the entire staff of the <affiliation>l'Institut national de la Recherche Halieutique Morocco</affiliation>. That each finds here the expression of our profound gratitude.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was funded by the <fundingAgency>Australian Research Council (DE120101549)</fundingAgency>. We acknowledge the <researchInstitution>services of Metabolomics Australia</researchInstitution> for the analysis of metabolite concentrations and</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by grants <grantNumber>IGA NT 11062-5/2010</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>MSM6198959205</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the following individuals for their contribution to this report: <individual>R. Duran</individual>, <individual>J.L. Martinez</individual>, <individual>B. McKown</individual>, <individual>R. Romero</individual>, <individual>D. Powell</individual> (<affiliation>Portage, Inc.</affiliation>) and <individual>E. Pulliam</individual> (<affiliation>TPMC, Inc.</affiliation>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>NH, AK, RB: We thank <individual>D. Cicuzza</individual>, <individual>W. Hoffmann</individual>, and <individual>T.R. Wentworth</individual> for their critical review of a previous version of this manuscript. We also thank <individual>D. Gamble</individual> (<affiliation>UNCW</affiliation>) for permission to re-use NH: I thank the individuals and organizations that directly had a hand in the completion of this project; without their expertise, opinions, edits, financial assistance, and permission to access private property, this work would not have been possible. the <otherInstitution>North Carolina State Parks</otherInstitution> graciously allowed me to collect plants from the shorelines of five Carolina bay lakes in Bladen County, North Carolina. the <otherInstitution>North Carolina Wildlife Resources Commission</otherInstitution> was kind enough to grant access to Horseshoe Lake and Little Singletary Lake. I thank <individual>Glenn</individual> and <individual>Carol Lewis</individual> for offering their land as an easement to Little Singletary Lake; they were very gracious, and I thoroughly enjoyed listening to Glenn's stories of Native American artifacts, lake history, black bears, and wildfires. <individual><individual>Dr. Clemuel Johnson</individual></individual> graciously gave permission to survey Bakers Lake Natural Area and I am very thankful for his generosity. <individual>Stephen Clark</individual>, son-in-law of Dr. Clemuel Johnson, also provided valuable information regarding wildlife use of Bakers Lake and surrounding natural areas. "Chick" <individual>Gaddy</individual> provided valuable information concerning Carolina bays and associated South Carolina natural community types. <individual>Mr. Gaddy</individual>'s enthusiastic disposition and knowledge of South Carolina ecosystems was very beneficial to this study and I am truly grateful for his time. <individual>Garrett German</individual> provided a wealth of information concerning waterfowl use of Carolina bay lakes. <individual>Rob Richardson</individual> and <individual>Justin Nawrocki</individual> of the <affiliation>NCSU</affiliation></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Competitive State</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported in part by <fundingAgency>NASA</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>SSERVI NNA14AB01A</grantNumber>, a <fundingAgency>Jackson School of Geosciences Postdoctoral Fellowship</fundingAgency> to N.D., and funding from <fundingAgency>Peking University</fundingAgency> to N.Z. Computational work was supported by <fundingAgency>Center for Computation and Visualization at Brown University</fundingAgency> and the Pawsey Supercomputing Centre with funding from the <fundingAgency>Australian Government and the Government of Western Australia</fundingAgency>. The input files for reproducing the numerical models can be accessed at nan_zhang@pku.edu.cn. This paper benefited from thoughtful reviews by <individual>Andrew Dombard</individual>, <individual>Walter Kiefer</individual> and an anonymous reviewer.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <individual>Profs. Ye.B. Stadnik</individual>, <individual>I.S. Guliyev</individual>, <individual>F.G. Dadashev</individual>, and <individual>I.Ya. Skyarenko</individual> for assistance in performing these studies.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work has been financially supported by an individual discovery grant from <fundingAgency>NSERC (Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</fundingAgency>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. Thanks to <individual>Maria Eugenia Gómez</individual> for finding the original reference of Bouguer's law. the <projectName>DENIS project</projectName> is supported by the <fundingAgency>SCIENCE and the Human Capital and Mobility plans of the European Commission</fundingAgency> under grants <grantNumber>CT920791</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>CT940627</grantNumber>, by the <fundingAgency>French Institut National des Sciences de l'Univers, the Ministère de l'Éducation Nationale</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, in Germany</fundingAgency> by the <fundingAgency>State of Baden-Würtemberg, in Spain</fundingAgency> by the <fundingAgency>DGICYT, in Italy</fundingAgency> by the <fundingAgency>Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche</fundingAgency>, by the <fundingAgency>Austrian Fonds zur Förderung der wissenschaftlichen Forschung und</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Michael Heinz</individual>, <individual>Paul Cliften</individual>, and the <affiliation>Genome Technology Access Center (GTAC) in the Department of Genetics</affiliation> for help</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank <individual>Julia Stockinger</individual> and <individual>David Schwarzenbacher</individual> for their excellent technical support and <individual>Johannes A Mayr</individual> for comments and suggestions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Leonice Lourenço Poyares</individual>, <affiliation>Institute of Biomedical Sciences, University of São Paulo, Brazil</affiliation>, for excellent technical assistance. Research supported by <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>FAPESP</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>. F. Goulart-Silva is the recipient of a FAPESP fellowship (<grantNumber>#08/56446-9</grantNumber>), and M.T. Nunes is the recipient of a <fundingAgency>CNPq</fundingAgency> fellowship.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge <individual>D Sabatini</individual> (<affiliation>Whitehead Institute</affiliation>) for providing mutagenized KBM7 cells and <individual>V Amarnath</individual> (<affiliation>Vanderbilt University</affiliation>) for providing reagents and advice. We thank <individual>V Vijayan</individual>, <individual>K Amarnath</individual>, <individual>T Peterson</individual>, and members of the <researchInstitution>O'Shea lab</researchInstitution> for advice and assistance. We thank <individual>A Darnell</individual> for critical reading of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The equivalence of (I) and (II) is well known.  Divinsky (1973)  has proved the equivalence of (II) and (III) for associative rings. Though in the lecture notes by <fundingAgency>Wiegandt</fundingAgency> (1974)  only associative rings are considered, there the proof of the equivalence of (II) and (III) is based on methods of  Leavitt and <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Yu-lee Lee</fundingAgency></fundingAgency> (<grantNumber><grantNumber>1969</grantNumber></grantNumber>) , Yu-lee  Lee (1969)  and  Watters (1969)  and it works for alternative rings too. For semigroups with 0 the proofs are analogous to those for associative rings. Finally, the <otherInstitution>equivalence of (I)</otherInstitution>, <fundingAgency>(IV)</fundingAgency> and (V) has been established in this paper. ADDED IN PROOF. For associative rings A. D. Sands has proved the same statement in his paper "Strong upper radicals", <individual>Quart. J. Math. Oxford</individual>,  <grantNumber>27</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>1976</grantNumber>), 21-24.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The first author is grateful for the partial financial support through the <fundingAgency>French National Research Agency</fundingAgency> (Grant <grantNumber>ANR-11-BS09-0008</grantNumber>, LOTERIE).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The notion of the third-sector, with which <individual>Michael Dunford</individual> closes his discussion of Lipietz, is crucial to a truly millennial discourse and practice. It is one that has been central in the approach to urban and social development that we put forward in this journal. Can the third sector release the imagination and the vision to which governments, or their current advisers, seem blind? Can the Dome become an icon of what we can, in the new century, leave behind? Meanwhile, William Gibson's bridge, discussed below by <individual>Richard Skeates</individual>, and the now demolished Kowloon Walled City in Hong Kong, present images for the liberated zones, related movements and sympathetic governments-local, regional and national -of the future.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank the continued support of the <otherInstitution>Phillip Island Nature Parks</otherInstitution> and its staff and volunteers involved in the continuous monitoring of penguins in Phillip Island since 1968. <individual>Y.Afán</individual> produced the video and improved figures design. Our analysis benefits enormously from earlier discussions with <individual>B. Raymond</individual>, <individual>C. Bulman</individual>, <individual>B. Fulton</individual>, <individual>S. Connie</individual>, <individual>D. Oro</individual>, <individual>M. Genovart</individual>, <individual>A. Sanz</individual> and <individual>M. Louzao</individual>, and with the helpful comments of <individual>Sara Maxwell</individual> and two anonymous reviewers.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>C. Clayton</individual>, <individual>T. Hobman</individual>, <individual>Y. Nagamine</individual>, <individual>C. Ender</individual>, <individual>R. Pillai</individual>, <individual>C. Artus</individual>, and <individual>E. Bertrand</individual> for providing plasmids and/or antibodies. S.N.B. is a recipient of a longterm <fundingAgency>HFSP</fundingAgency> fellowship. the <researchInstitution>Friedrich Miescher Institute</researchInstitution> is supported by the <fundingAgency>Novartis Research Foundation</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank all the individuals from each of the SWEET countries who gave up their valuable time to participate in this study and were prepared to share their experiences with us.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <otherInstitution>ParkLands Foundation</otherInstitution> for allowing us to conduct this research on their property and <individual>Victoria A. Borowicz</individual> and <individual>Scott K. Sakaluk</individual> for assistance with this research.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to <individual>Ms Mieko Imai</individual> and <individual>Ms Tomoko Yamabe</individual> for data management, and to <individual>Dr Haruhiko Fukuda</individual> for direction of the JCOG data center and oversight of management of the study. This work was supported in part by <projectName>Grants-in-Aid for Cancer Research and for the Second-Term Comprehensive 10-Year Strategy for Cancer Control</projectName> from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Health, Labour, and Welfare (Tokyo)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge grant support from <fundingAgency>GE Healthcare</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>1R01 AR062581-01A1</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>1R21 AR063894-01A1</grantNumber>), and the <fundingAgency>VA Clinical Science Research and Development Service</fundingAgency> (Career Development Grant <grantNumber>1IK2CX000749</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Contract grant sponsors: <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Telethon</fundingAgency></fundingAgency> (<grantNumber><grantNumber>GGP13213</grantNumber></grantNumber>), <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>U.S. National Institute of Health</fundingAgency></fundingAgency> (<grantNumber><grantNumber>AR059646</grantNumber></grantNumber> and <grantNumber><grantNumber>AR053349</grantNumber></grantNumber>); <fundingAgency>Ministero dell' Istruzione, dell' Università e della Ricerca, Fondo Innovazione in Ricerca</fundingAgency>. This work was supported by Telethon grant GGP13213 to FP, VS, and CR; by U.S. National Institute of Health Grants AR059646 and AR053349 (subcontracts to FP) and a by <fundingAgency>MIUR-FIR</fundingAgency> grant to EP. "the <otherInstitution>EuroBioBank and Telethon Network of Genetic Biobanks</otherInstitution> (GTB07001D) are gratefully acknowledged for providing biological samples". We thank <individual>Dr. Rosanna Asselta</individual> (<affiliation>University of Milan</affiliation>) for helpful advice and assistance in haplotype analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funding for the World Vegetable Center's general research activities is provided by core donors: <fundingAgency>Republic of China (Taiwan)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>UK aid</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>United States Agency for International Development (USAID)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Australian Centre for International Agricultural Research (ACIAR)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Germany</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Thailand</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Philippines</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Korea</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Japan</fundingAgency>. In addition we like to thank <otherInstitution>Global Crop Diversity Trust</otherInstitution> for contribution to meetings and to this open-access publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>Dr. Michael W. Hess</individual> (<affiliation>Division of Histology and Embryology, Medical University of Innsbruck, Austria</affiliation>) for generally allowing us access to a transmission electron microscope. This</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Work on mistranslation in the Ibba Lab is supported by funding from the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MCB 1412611</grantNumber>), an <fundingAgency>Ohio State University Center for RNA Biology Fellowship</fundingAgency> (to K.M.) and <fundingAgency>NIH Training Grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>T32 GM008512</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>GM086252</grantNumber> (to A.M.).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors gratefully acknowledge the financial support by the <fundingAgency>Polish Ministry of Higher Education</fundingAgency> (Grant no. <grantNumber>15.11.170.576</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by grants from <fundingAgency>Italian MIUR</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>FIRB RBAP10Z7FS_002</grantNumber>) to SC and from <fundingAgency>University of Ferrara (Italy)</fundingAgency> to V.B. We thank <individual>Mr. Cosmo Rossi</individual> for his technical expertise in producing xenografts.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Higher Education Malaysia</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) Asian CORE Program</fundingAgency> titled "<projectName>Establishment of research and education network on coastal marine science in Southeast Asia</projectName>". We would like to express our appreciation to <individual>Dr. Norio Nagao</individual>, <individual>Mr. Hideyuki Takatsuji</individual>, <individual>Mr. Zainuddin Ibrahim</individual>, <individual>Mr. Husdy Salleh</individual> and <individual>Mr. Soed Mokhtar</individual> for their assistance in the field sampling. We would also like to thank <individual>Dr. Htay Aung</individual>, <individual>Dr. Azman Abdul Rahim</individual>, <individual>Mr. Zuhaimi Samad</individual> and <individual>Miss Fatin Zahidah Zainal</individual> for their help with the illustrations and <individual>Dr. Shuhei Nishida</individual> for reading the manuscript and for his invaluable comments. We are grateful to our referees for their comments that helped improve the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments The study is funded by the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Organization for Health Research and Development</fundingAgency>, grant number <grantNumber>300020012</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Shane Waters thanks the <affiliation>University of Adelaide</affiliation> for his Postgraduate Award and the <researchInstitution>Australian Centre for Plant Functional Genomics</researchInstitution> for support. This work was supported by the <grantNumber>DP120100900</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>LP120100201</grantNumber> grants from the <fundingAgency>Australian Research Council</fundingAgency> awarded to MH.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research work is an output of the research project "<projectName>Modelling of selected indicators and processes in drinking water supplies</projectName>", reg. no.: FAST-S-17-4643 and also a project "<projectName>Influence of hydraulic conditions in the water supply network on selected indicators of drinking water quality</projectName>", reg. no.: FAST-J-17-4475. Both of them was supported through the internal grant agency of the <fundingAgency>Brno University of Technology</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors have no conflicts of interest associated with the material presented in this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <researchInstitution>Diamond Light Source</researchInstitution> for access to beamlines I02, I03, I04, I04-1 and I24 (proposal numbers MX6638 and MX8659). The work was funded by the <fundingAgency>BBSRC</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>BB/ L02022X/1</grantNumber>), a Kelvin-Smith Scholarship from the <fundingAgency>University of Glasgow</fundingAgency> and a <fundingAgency>Sir Henry Wellcome Fellowship</fundingAgency> awarded to R.G.: award number <grantNumber>106077/Z/14/Z</grantNumber>. During this work I.J. was supported by a studentship from the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency>: award number <grantNumber>093592/Z/10/Z</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>M. I. Ransome is supported by the <fundingAgency>NHMRC Biomedical Fellowship</fundingAgency>. A. J. Hannan is supported by the <fundingAgency>ARC Future Fellowship</fundingAgency> (FT3) and his research has been funded by <fundingAgency>NHMRC Project Grants</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors received editorial support from <individual>Eva Polk</individual>, Ph.D., at Excerpta Medica in the preparation of this manuscript, which was funded by <fundingAgency>Celgene Corporation</fundingAgency>. The authors are fully responsible for all content and editorial decisions for this manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The work was partially supported by Research Funds from the <fundingAgency>County of Västra Götaland, Sweden</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I couldn't possibly include all references since there are thousands. Instead I would like to acknowledge the contributions made by all scientists in the field of human genomics, comparative genomics, epigenetics and the related areas of my article. All of the relevant background articles are available at the NCBI website, particularly the PubMed.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Mental Health</fundingAgency> , <fundingAgency>NIMH</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>1 R01 MH0820-54</grantNumber>) to Drs. Klump, Boker, Burt, Keel, Neale, and Dr. Cheryl  Sisk. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institute of Mental Health. p  &lt;  .001. Abbreviations: MBPD, Minnesota Borderline Personality Disorder Scale. SCID-II, Structured Interview for DSM-IV Axis II Personality Disorders Screener. STAB, Subtypes of Antisocial Behavior Survey. MEBS, Minnesota Eating Behaviors Survey. The twin correlation is significantly greater than 0 at p  &lt;  .001.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments I appreciate the valuable editorial suggestions and corrections by <individual>John F. Kern</individual>, of <affiliation>Winnetka</affiliation>, IL. I am grateful to <individual>Bob Buchanan</individual>, <individual>Dee Benson</individual> and <individual>Carole Mayo</individual> for their support. I thank <individual>Govindjee</individual> for his invitation, his extensive editing (especially in providing the reference list), his patience and above all his ever-lasting persistence and encouragement that has led to the completion of this letter.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work has been partially supported by the <fundingAgency>EC funded project Swan-iCare</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>FP7-ICT</grantNumber>, Project No. 317894) and "<projectName>TEAChER: TEach AdvanCEd Reconfigurable architectures and tools</projectName>" project funded by <fundingAgency>DAAD</fundingAgency> (2014).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Conceived and designed the experiments: RB JP KP. Performed the experiments: RB MDR. Analyzed the data: RB JP. Wrote the paper: RB JP KP.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank an anonymous referee. Also, we are very grateful to <individual>Professor Peter P. Eggleton</individual> for sharing his binary evolution code. This work was sponsored by the <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (Grant Nos. <grantNumber>11463002</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>11373020</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Open Foundation of key Laboratory for the Structure and evolution of Celestial Objects, Chinese Academy of Science</fundingAgency> (Grant Nos. <grantNumber>OP201405</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>OP201404(B615015)</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Science Foundation of Jimei University</fundingAgency> (Grant No. <grantNumber>C613030</grantNumber>), and <fundingAgency>Science and Technology Foundation of Guizhou Province</fundingAgency> (Grant LKK[2013]  No. 20).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. Development of the Medusa GC/MS systems, calibrations, and measurements were carried out as part of the <projectName>international <otherInstitution>AGAGE</otherInstitution> research program</projectName> and supported by the <fundingAgency>NASA Upper Atmospheric Research Program</fundingAgency> in the US with grants <grantNumber>NNX07AE89G</grantNumber> to MIT, <grantNumber>NNX07AF09G</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>NNX07AE87G</grantNumber> to <affiliation><affiliation><affiliation><affiliation>SIO</affiliation></affiliation></affiliation></affiliation>, <fundingAgency>Defra</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency><affiliation><researchInstitution>NOAA</researchInstitution></affiliation></fundingAgency> in the UK, <fundingAgency><researchInstitution><affiliation>CSIRO</affiliation></researchInstitution></fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Australian Government Bureau of Meteorology in Australia</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual><individual>J. P. Severinghaus</individual></individual> (SIO) for the Megadunes firn samples from Antarctica, <individual>J. E. Shields</individual> (SIO) for an air-age estimate of the deepest and oldest Megadunes firn air samples used in this work, <individual>V. V. Petrenko</individual> and J. P. Severinghaus (SIO) for the ancient NH ice samples from the Pâkitsoq site in Greenland. We especially thank <individual>E. J. Dlugokencky</individual>, <individual>J. W. Elkins</individual>, <individual>B. D.Hall</individual>, and <individual>S. A. Montzka</individual> (NOAA/<affiliation><researchInstitution>GMD</researchInstitution></affiliation>), <individual>C. D. Keeling</individual> (deceased) and <individual>R. F. Keeling</individual> (SIO), <individual>N. Schmidbauer</individual>, <individual>O. Hermansen</individual>, <individual>C. R. Lunder</individual> (<affiliation><researchInstitution>NILU</researchInstitution></affiliation>), and <individual>R. C. Rhew</individual> (<affiliation>UCB</affiliation>) for air samples. We thank <individual>R. A. Rasmussen</individual> and the <researchInstitution>Oregon Graduate Institute (OGI)</researchInstitution> for originally collecting the Cape Meares Northern Hemispheric samples which were provided by NOAA/GMD, NILU, and CSIRO. We are indebted to the staff at the AGAGE sites for their continuing contributions to produce high quality measurements of atmospheric trace gases. In particular, we thank <individual>G. Spain</individual> (<affiliation>Mace Head</affiliation>), <individual>R. Dickau</individual> (<affiliation>Trinidad Head</affiliation>), <individual>J. Mühle</individual> et al.:  Perfluorocarbons in the global atmosphere <individual>P. Sealy</individual> (<affiliation>Ragged Point</affiliation>), <individual>M. C. Cunningham</individual> (<affiliation>Cape Matatula</affiliation>), <individual>C. G. Rickard</individual>, and <individual>J. Z. Ward</individual> (<affiliation>Cape Grim</affiliation>). In addition, we thank <individual>M. Leist</individual> (CSIRO) for his excellent technical support of the Cape Grim Medusa system. We are especially thankful to <individual>R. Knapp</individual>, <individual>J. Marks</individual>, and <individual>C. Bayliss</individual> (<affiliation>International Aluminium Institute, IAI</affiliation>), <individual>M. Ison</individual> (<affiliation>Australian Aluminium Council, AAC</affiliation>) and the two anonymous reviewers for their insightful comments and reviews which contributed to the improvement of this manuscript. Edited by: J. Kaiser</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funding: This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Cancer Institute</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>P01 CA018029</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>CA033084</grantNumber>, and the <fundingAgency>Leukemia and Lymphoma Society SCOR program</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>LLS-7008-09</grantNumber>. AGC is supported by a <fundingAgency>Walker Fellowship Award</fundingAgency>, and GBR was supported by a <fundingAgency>Leukemia Lymphoma Society Special Fellow Award</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>4442-09</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Marian Boguñá</individual>, <individual>Alessandro Flammini</individual>, and <individual>Romualdo Pastor-Satorras</individual> for a critical reading of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author is grateful to <individual>Drs P. Husby</individual> and <individual>I. Romslo</individual> for helpful discussions. The technical assistance of <individual>Mrs A. Iden</individual> is greatly acknowledged. The study was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Norwegian Research Council for Science and the Humanities</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was carried out with the support of Cooperative Research Program for Agriculture Science  &amp;  Technology Development (Project no. <grantNumber>PJ010156022014</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Rural Development Administration, Republic of Korea</fundingAgency>. The authors specifically thank the staff and crew of the <affiliation>National Center for InterUniversity Research Facilities (Seoul National University)</affiliation> for assistance with the NMR and GC/MS experiments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We particularly wish to thank the <otherInstitution>SL Division</otherInstitution> for the efficient operation of the LEP accelerator at all energies and for their continuing close cooperation with our experimental group. We thank our colleagues from <otherInstitution>CEA</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>DAPNIA/SPP</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>CE-Saclay</otherInstitution> for their efforts over the years on the time-of-flight and trigger systems which we continue to use. In addition to the support staff at our own institutions we are pleased to acknowledge the References</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>81472390/ H1619</grantNumber>,<grantNumber>81472762/H1609</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>National Funds for developing local colleges and universities</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>B16056001</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>General Project</fundingAgency>  (<grantNumber>1201410188</grantNumber>)   We thank <otherInstitution>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Malignant Tumor Epigenetics and Gene Regulation</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Sun Yat-Sen Memorial Hospital</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Sun Yat-Sen University</otherInstitution> for flow cytometry analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Accession numbers for previously reported CTV nucleotide sequences used in this report are: T36 (U166034), <fundingAgency>VT</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>U56902</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>T385 (Y18420), SY568 (AF001623)</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>T30</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AF260651</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>C268</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AJ599770</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>C269</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AJ579774</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>C270</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AJ579771</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>T300</grantNumber>(<grantNumber>AJ579763</grantNumber>), T305(<grantNumber>AJ579776</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>T312</grantNumber> (<grantNumber>AJ579765</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>T32</grantNumber>(<grantNumber>AJ579766</grantNumber>), T346(<grantNumber>AJ579768</grantNumber>), T388 (<grantNumber>AJ579777</grantNumber>)  ,</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was partially supported by the <projectName>CONACyT projects</projectName> No. 29250E and 27676E, and the project IN114998 funded by the <fundingAgency>DGAPA-UNAM</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Steven Kalb,</individual> <individual>Yankai Li</individual>, <individual>Tim Cummings</individual>, <individual>Bryan Hammons</individual>, <individual>Deborah Farr</individual> and <individual>Justin Carter</individual> assisted with this research.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <researchInstitution>Werfen/Instrumentation Laboratory</researchInstitution> for providing us with the test kits for the inter-center comparison.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments We thank <individual>Petra Laspe</individual> and <individual>Antje Apel</individual> for invaluable technical assistance. This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>German Cancer Aid (Deutsche Krebshilfe)</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft DFG</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>GRK1034</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>Dr. Rick G. Pleijhuis</individual> for kindly developing a user-friendly web-based calculator based on our updated models to facilitate the use of our models. G.J. The study funders did not participate in the design of the study; the collection, analysis, or interpretation of the data; the writing of the manuscript; or the decision to manuscript submission.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to the <fundingAgency>Spanish government project</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>TEC2010-20224-C02-01</grantNumber> and the <fundingAgency>European project ECOAL-MGT -SUDOE Program</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank the referee for his suggestions which helped in improving the paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Foremost we thank <individual>Dr. Robert C. Drewes</individual> who continues to initiate, coordinate and lead multiorganism biotic surveys on São Tomé and Príncipe. We thank <individual>Eng</individual>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank the referee, especially for pointing out [1, Theorem 2] which simplified the proof of Theorem 5.1 considerably.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Key International Cooperation Program of the National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (project no. <grantNumber>31110103916</grantNumber>; Beijing, P.R. China), the <fundingAgency>Agricultural Science and Technology Innovation Program</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>ASTIP-IAS08</grantNumber>; Beijing, P. R. China), and the <fundingAgency>China Agriculture Research System</fundingAgency> (project no. <grantNumber>CARS-42</grantNumber>; Beijing, P. R. China).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I would like to thank the following people for all their help and professional support in the completion of this book: <otherInstitution>George Banks</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Menu Development</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>British Airways, London</otherInstitution>. <individual>Scott Chapman</individual>, Senior Partner, <otherInstitution>Medical Litigation</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Tress, Cox and Maddox, Sydney, Australia</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Collecting trips in Asia were funded through <grantNumber>USDA-ARS Specific Cooperative Agreements 58-5320-9-382 and 58-5320-4-018</grantNumber>, managed by the <fundingAgency>University of Hawaii's College of Tropical Agriculture and Human Resources (UH-CTAHR)</fundingAgency>. A study trip in Australia was covered by <fundingAgency>Farm Bill funding</fundingAgency> (project <grantNumber>3.0251</grantNumber>), through a <projectName>Cooperative Agreement between USDA and UH-CTAHR</projectName>. Additional support was provided by <projectName>USDA-NIFA Hatch projects</projectName> HAW00942-H and HAW00956-H, administered UH-CTAHR. We also thank <individual>Anthony R. Clarke</individual> for reviewing an earlier version of the manuscript and <individual>Richard A.I. Drew</individual> and <individual>David L. Hancock</individual> for their insight, mentoring and long hours discussing the relationships among species in the OFF complex and the higher classification of dacine fruit flies. <individual>Desley Tree</individual> and <individual>Justin Bartlett</individual> provided access to the impressive QDAF fruit fly collection in Brisbane. The use or mention of a trademark or proprietary product does not constitute an endorsement, guarantee, or warranty of the product and does not imply its approval to the exclusion of other suitable products by the U.S. Department of Agriculture, an equal opportunity employer.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>CLL Global Research Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <projectName>EUCAAD 200755 project</projectName> funded under the auspices of the <fundingAgency>EU Seventh Framework Programme</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Cancer and Allergy Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Research Council/SIDA/ SAREC</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Iranian Ministry of Health and Medical Education</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Cancer Society</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Cancer Society in Stockholm</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>King Gustaf Vth Jubilee Fund</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Vinnova</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Karolinska Institutet Foundations</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Stockholm County Council</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the <otherInstitution>Career Training Interexchange program</otherInstitution> that facilitated the training period of Maitane Olabarrieta within the USGS. Maitane Olabarrieta also acknowledges funding from the ''<fundingAgency>Cantabria Campus International Augusto Gonzalez Linares Program</fundingAgency>.'' We would also like to thank <individual>Giovanni Coco</individual>, <individual>John C. Warner</individual>, and <individual>Falk Feddersen</individual> for their support with this work and constructive suggestions. We are also grateful to the developers of the COAWST modeling system, SWAN, and ROMS models. WRG was supported by <fundingAgency>ONR</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>N00014-13-1-0368</grantNumber>. The authors would also like to thank <individual>Sergio Fagherazzi</individual>, <individual>Xavier Bertin</individual>, and the third journal reviewer for their suggestions. The data and numerical results used in this paper will made available upon request to the main author.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <projectName>Red Wolf Recovery Program</projectName>, specifically <individual>Rebecca Bartel</individual>, <individual>Art Beyer</individual>, <individual>Chris Lucash</individual>, <individual>Ford Mauney</individual>, <individual>Michael Morse</individual> and <individual>Ryan Nordsven</individual> for their support. We also thank <individual>Kristin Brzeski</individual> for constructive comments on the manuscript. The findings and conclusions in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the <otherInstitution>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the families and patients who have participated in this research study. We acknowledge <individual>Hilde Van Esch</individual> for help with patient recruitment, and we thank <individual>Yi Mu</individual>, <researchInstitution>UC Davis Department of Public Health Sciences</researchInstitution>, for assistance with data management and analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. I would like to thank the referee for his/her careful reading and valuable comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are thankful to the <otherInstitution>Marine Products Export Development Authority (MPEDA, Kochi)</otherInstitution>, the <fundingAgency>Chief Executive of National Fisheries Development Board</fundingAgency>, <individual>Hyderabad</individual> and <individual>Dr.R.Jaya Kumar</individual>, Senior Scientist, <researchInstitution>CMFRI Mandapam</researchInstitution>. We are also grateful to <individual>Sri. Rama Sankar Naik</individual>, <affiliation>IAS, Commissioner of Fisheries, Andhra Pradesh, India</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Cancer Institute</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>R37-CA-057030</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The project described was supported by Grant Number <grantNumber>OH 03970</grantNumber> from <fundingAgency>CDC-NIOSH</fundingAgency> to MFB and <grantNumber>AR051212</grantNumber> from <fundingAgency>NIAMS</fundingAgency> to AEB, the <fundingAgency>Sandler Foundation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>NS-10414</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS, in destruction process)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Ministère de l'Enseignement Supérieur et de la Recherche</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Fondation NRJ -Institut de France</fundingAgency> to JOC and MR. FS was partly supported by a <fundingAgency>HFSP</fundingAgency> long term fellowship <grantNumber>LT 00743/1998-B</grantNumber> and partly by personal fundings.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank the <researchInstitution>Medical Research Center of Peking University Third Hospital</researchInstitution> for technical guidance. PC3 and HEK293 cells were kindly donated by <individual>Wei Zhang</individual>, PhD from the <affiliation>Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Science</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>No conflicts declared.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Thereares o many people to thank for this book that it could've</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>Simone Duis</individual> and <individual>Natalia Pavlova</individual> for help with surgeries, <individual>Laetitia Baud</individual> for assistance with animal care, <individual>Quentin Barraud</individual> and <individual>Julie Kreider</individual> for histological analyses and anatomical reconstructions, and <individual>Samuel Gex</individual> for help with building the robotic device.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I thank <individual>M. T. Mponda</individual> for her patience and extra time devoted to typing the original manuscript. I also thank <individual>D. E. C. Mughogho</individual> for his moral support and reviewing of the initial draft. Lastly I thank the anonymous referees of my paper for their useful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The assistance of <individual>Mrs L.K. Frymovich</individual> in preparing the manuscript for publication is greatly appreciated.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author would like to thank <individual>Graeme Chamberlin</individual>, <individual>Barry Williams</individual> and <individual>Chris Davies</individual> for their comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements We thank <individual>Professor Anders Lund</individual> for giving us access to the <educationalInstitution>EPR lab at IFM-Chemical Physics, Linköping University</educationalInstitution> and <individual>Professor Sandra S. Eaton</individual>, <affiliation>University of Denver</affiliation>, for advice concerning EPR data analysis. We acknowledge <individual>Professor Mikael Lindgren</individual> and <individual>Dr. Malin Persson</individual> for valuable discussions and advice. We also gratefully acknowledge <individual>Dr. Christian Altenbach</individual>, <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>, for providing his software for determining inter-residue distances. This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Swedish Foundation for Strategic Research (PH)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Research Council (BHJ, PH, and UC)</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Knut and Alice Wallenberg Foundation</fundingAgency> (BHJ, PH, and UC)</fundingAgency>. PH is a Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences Research Fellow supported by a grant from the Knut and Alice Wallenberg Foundation.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Ronald L. Jacobs</individual>, Chair</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Aiping Lin</individual> at the <researchInstitution>Yale W.M. Keck Biostatistics Resource</researchInstitution> for analysis of microarray data. Supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> to SG.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The statistical evaluation by <individual>Michael Obermayer</individual> (<affiliation>GKM Gesellschaft für Therapieforschung mbH, Munich</affiliation>) is acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to acknowledge the <fundingAgency>Research Council of University of Tehran</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Iran National Science Foundation (IN SF )</fundingAgency> for the grants provided for them. They also would like to sincerely thank <individual>Professor Ian Thompson</individual> for his valuable help regarding the FRESCO code.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by a <fundingAgency>VHS Medical Center Research Grant, Republic of Korea</fundingAgency> (grant number: <grantNumber>VHSMC 15012</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>NHLBI R01 HL64794</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I am grateful to <individual>Mrs Nicolette Budden</individual>, <individual>Mrs Stella Oates</individual> and <individual>Mrs Catherine Wright</individual> for assistance in the preparation of this article. I also wish to thank <individual>Professor A. Hewish FRS</individual>, <individual>Sir Maurice Wilkes FRS</individual>, <individual>Professor K. Suchy</individual>, <individual>Dr R. P. Mercier</individual>, <individual>Dr A. J. M. Garrett</individual>, <individual>Dr M. Rycroft</individual> and a number of others for helpful comments on the article in draft form. I also thank the <otherInstitution>Society's referee</otherInstitution> for advice. Librarians at <educationalInstitution>St John's College, Cambridge</educationalInstitution>, and at <educationalInstitution>Churchill College, Cambridge</educationalInstitution>, kindly assisted with access to archival material. <individual>Kenneth Budden</individual> left very extensive autobiographical material on computer disks, which I have used and occasionally quoted. The frontispiece photograph was taken by Walter Bird and is reproduced with permission from the Godfrey Argent Studio.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank dental students <individual>Barbara Mikecs</individual>, <individual>Júlia Németh</individual>, <individual>Péter Csányi</individual>, and <individual>Adél Ruszin</individual> for their assistance in collecting data. This study was funded by the <fundingAgency>Research Fund of the Faculty of Dentistry, Semmelweis University, Hungary</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>4030511599</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>5111141075</grantNumber>), and the <fundingAgency>Hungarian Scientific Research Fund</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>OTKA K112364</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>K-112964</grantNumber>). The Mucograft was kindly donated by the manufacturer (<fundingAgency>Geistlich Pharma AG, Switzerland</fundingAgency>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <fundingAgency>INSS (Japan)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>EDF (France)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Areva (France)</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>EPRI (US)</fundingAgency> for supporting their <projectName>SCC-related research</projectName>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <otherInstitution><fundingAgency>AstraZeneca</fundingAgency></otherInstitution> for providing AZ-4217, <individual>Mark Smith</individual> (<affiliation>Imperial College, London</affiliation>) and <individual>Yuchio Yanagawa</individual> (<affiliation>Gunma University, Maebashi</affiliation>) for VGlut2-GFP and GAD67-GFP tissue, respectively. This work was funded by <fundingAgency>Medical Research Council</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MR/K003291/1</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Diabetes UK</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>12/0004458</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>British Heart Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>PG/15/44/31574</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council CASE</fundingAgency> (with AstraZeneca) award (<grantNumber>BB/I015663/1</grantNumber>) to MLJA and by a grant to LKH from the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>WT098012</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the subjects who participated in the study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Autochthonous. EndodontidcB. World-wide, on all continents and islands. ' Primitive Zonitidit were probably evolved at a very early time, but the group attained its main development in the Csenogaeic faunas.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We gratefully acknowledge financial support from <fundingAgency>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq)</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo (FAPESP)</fundingAgency>, <grantNumber>Proc. 95/3636-3</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by a restricted grant from <fundingAgency>Roche</fundingAgency>. The funder had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Ada Tam</individual>, <individual>Hao Zhang</individual> and <individual>Lee Blosser</individual> of the <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Core Flow Cytometry</affiliation> facilities for their assistance with flow cytometry and cell sorting.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study was supported by <fundingAgency>University of Udine, Italy</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Associazione "Mi Fido di Te" ONLUS</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Fondazione Cassa di Risparmio di Città di Castello, Italy</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The VHR imagery was provided by the <otherInstitution>US Department of State (USDS) Humanitarian Information Unit</otherInstitution>, under the NextView License. The authors thank the <affiliation>FAO-SWALIM</affiliation> staff, without whom the field campaign would not have been possible. Finally, the authors thank <individual>Dr Roberto Colombo</individual> of the <affiliation>University of Milan-Bicocca</affiliation> for the field spectroscopy equipment used in the field campaign.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Rick van Leeuwen</individual>, <individual>Wouter Verhesen</individual>, <individual>Kevin Custers</individual>, and <individual>Hans Duimel</individual> for their technical support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. This research was supported by grants to RL, BZ and KV from the <fundingAgency>Swedish Cancer Society</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Stockholm Cancer Society</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Research Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Childhood Cancer Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Stockholm County Council</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Karolinska Institutet</fundingAgency> Research Fund and the European Union FP6 (Chemores)</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>FP7 (Apo-Sys)</fundingAgency>. VOK was supported by a fellowship from the <fundingAgency>Swedish Institute</fundingAgency> and Karolinska Institutet and AHV from the <fundingAgency>Wenner-Gren Foundation</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to acknowledge con-</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This manuscript benefited from careful and constructive reviews by <individual>J. P. Brun</individual> Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study is funded by <fundingAgency>Medtronic Inc.</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge <individual>J. A. Hoyos</individual> for a critical reading of this manuscript and useful comments. The financial supports from <fundingAgency>CNPq</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>FAPESP</fundingAgency>, under grants <grantNumber>15/04451-2</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>307620/2015-8</grantNumber>, are also acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgement: The authors wish to thank <individual>H. Dong</individual>, <individual>J. Guzman</individual>, and <individual>I. Tice</individual> for their discussions and pointing out references  [2, 13, 14]  on regularity of Stokes problems in a domain with corners. Y. Guo's research is supported in part by <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>C</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>10828103</grantNumber> and NSF grant <grantNumber>DMS-0905255</grantNumber>, and T. Nguyen's research was supported in part by the NSF under grant <grantNumber>DMS-1405728</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <individual>Christian Lafarge</individual> for animal care and <individual>Anne Diot</individual> and <individual>Corine Pouyet</individual> for participation in tissue protein synthesis determination. The authors had no conflicts of interest. This research was supported by the <fundingAgency>Proteus Bilateral Programme</fundingAgency> between Slovenia (<researchInstitution>Slovenian Research Agency</researchInstitution>) and France (<otherInstitution>French Research Ministry</otherInstitution>). The contribution of each author was as follows: T. P., conception and design, tissue sampling, data processing, drafting and revision of the manuscript; L. M. and D. R., conception and design, tissue sampling, revision of manuscript; M. C. R., protein synthesis rate determinations; C. B., design, tissue sampling, blood cell counts and MPO determinations, data processing; J. S., conception and design, tissue sampling, data processing, revision of manuscript; P. P. M., conception and design, animal experiment, tissue sampling and revision of manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors gratefully acknowledge <fundingAgency>BAU-USDA Soybean Project</fundingAgency>, for financial assistance to conduct this experiment.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The following list of presents was read, and thanks ordered to be returned to the respective donors:</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments KS-A, RM, XY, CL, LG and MV wish to thank <individual>Changyu Fan</individual> and <individual>Yun Shen</individual> for providing informatics support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The publication of this article was funded by the <fundingAgency>Qatar National Library</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> with Grant <grantNumber>BCS 9207007</grantNumber>. Drs Petrie and Collins were research residents supported by the <fundingAgency>Department of Orthopaedics</fundingAgency>. No benefits in any form have been received or will be received from a commercial party related directly or indirectly to the subject of this article.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank the women for their participation in this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like thank the financial support from the <fundingAgency>Portuguese Foundation for Science and</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by a Grant from the <fundingAgency>National High Technology Research and Development Program of China</fundingAgency> (<projectName>863 Program</projectName>, no. <grantNumber>2014AA093501</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (Project nos. <grantNumber>30672742</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>30873353</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>30930113</grantNumber>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the paper. <individual>Dr. Ling Xu</individual> and <individual>Dr. Jin Yu</individual> are co-first authors.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering (NIBIB)</fundingAgency> Grant No. <grantNumber>R01-EB-002091</grantNumber> and through a <projectName>NIBIB American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Administrative Supplement</projectName>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We gratefully acknowledge the contribution of participating parents and children, general practitioners, hospitals, midwives and pharmacies in Rotterdam.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Competing Interests: The authors declare that they have no conflict of interests. Contributors/Acknowledgement: All authors participated equally in designing and estimation of current research. Views and opinions expressed in this study are the views and opinions of the authors, Asian Journal of Agriculture and Rural Development shall not be responsible or answerable for any loss, damage or liability etc. caused in relation to/arising out of the use of the content.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The encapsulating style of delivery was proposed by <individual>Charlie Perkins</individual>. <individual>Jim Solomon</individual> has been instrumental in shaping this document into its present form.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank <individual>Dr. Solomon S. Senok</individual> at <affiliation>Alfaisal University, Saudi Arabia</affiliation> for critically reading the manuscript, improving English text and providing constructive comments on the manuscript. This work was supported by</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Special thanks to <individual>Dr. Wil Linkugel</individual> for encouraging the continued exploration of Franklin Roosevelt's 1932 campaign orations and drawing the author's attention to this particular speech and <individual>Mr. Andrew Crick</individual> for his editorial assistance throughout the project.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Kohki Yoshimoto</individual> for the use of atg mutants and <individual>Dr. Shinya Wada</individual> for the use of GFP-ATG8 transgenic plants.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Ms. Meehye Kim</individual> for technical assistance. This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Korean Academy of Tuberculosis and Respiratory Diseases</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Authors are grateful to the <affiliation>Leeds group</affiliation> of <individual>Prof. A.A. Watson</individual> for the array disposition and maintenance, in particular <individual>J. Beaman</individual>, <individual>J. Lloyd-Evans</individual>, <individual>P. Ogden</individual> and <individual>M. Patel</individual>. The same gratitude is due to the <affiliation>Palermo group</affiliation> of <individual>Prof. L. Scarsi</individual> for the PLASTEX and RPC operations. A particular thanks are to <individual>Dr. J. Knapp</individual> and <individual>Dr. D. Heck</individual> for their indispensable help in installing and running CORSIKA 4.50 Monte Carlo in Naples.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are thankful to <individual>KB Low</individual> for providing wild-type M13 and to <individual>S Alonzo</individual>, KB Low, <individual>D Vasseur</individual>, and <individual>GP Wagner</individual> for useful discussion. We are also grateful to <individual>J Bull</individual> for suggesting we explore a model of phage loss. We thank <individual>S Wielgoss</individual> and two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on the paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research is supported in part by <fundingAgency>ROC NSC</fundingAgency> under contract number <grantNumber>NSC97-2221-E-128-005-MY3</grantNumber>. Also, the author would like to thank <individual>Prof Horng-Twu Liaw</individual> and <individual>Mr Shin-Han Wu</individual> of <affiliation>Shih-Hsin University</affiliation> and <individual>Mr Chih-Ta Yen</individual> of <affiliation>National Taiwan University of Science and Technology</affiliation> for their help in this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge the <researchInstitution>National Collaborative Research Infrastructure (NCRIS) of Australia</researchInstitution> for providing access to bioinformatics computational pipelines used in this study and the <fundingAgency>Research Institute of Forestry, Chinese Academy of Forestry</fundingAgency> for financial support (<grantNumber>ZD200902</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funded by a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Institute on Aging</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>R01 AG023090</grantNumber>). The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institute on Aging or the National Institutes of Health.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>International Center for Advanced Renewable Energy and Sustainability at Washington University in St. Louis, Missouri</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Johns Hopkins Global Center on Childhood Obesity</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>2001656847</grantNumber>). We thank the study participants for their cooperation and <individual>Leslie Duling</individual> and <individual>Nora Geary</individual> for their help in study coordination, data collection, and data management.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors gratefully acknowledge <otherInstitution>Solvay Engineering Plastics</otherInstitution> for supporting this work and for providing material data and specimens. This work benefited from the financial support of the <fundingAgency>French Minister for Research (ANRT)</fundingAgency> (Grant no: <grantNumber>CNRS 079212: UM2 121532</grantNumber>) and was performed in the framework of the <projectName>European DURAFIP project</projectName> (<projectName>FUI project</projectName> supported by <fundingAgency>Oseo</fundingAgency>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thanks all those administrators and practitioners who participated in the study. A special acknowledgement is given to the funder of the research project the <educationalInstitution>Centre jeunesse de Montréal Institut Universitaire</educationalInstitution>. Its contribution makes this project possible.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>PRGS</fundingAgency> under the Grant No. <grantNumber>GRS100323</grantNumber>, <affiliation>Universiti Malaysia Pahang, Malaysia</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank all of the study participants. We also thank <individual>James Hicks</individual> for his editorial assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank the <fundingAgency>Australian Partnership for Advanced Computing (APAC)</fundingAgency> for generous grants of supercomputer time which have enabled this project. Support from the <fundingAgency>South Australian Partnership for Advanced Computing (SAPAC)</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>National Facility for Lattice Gauge Theory</fundingAgency> is also gratefully acknowledged. DBL thanks <researchInstitution>Jefferson Lab</researchInstitution> for their kind hospitality where the majority of this research was performed. This work is supported by the <fundingAgency>Australian Research Council</fundingAgency> and by <fundingAgency>DOE</fundingAgency> contract <grantNumber>DE-AC05-84ER40150</grantNumber> under which SURA operates Jefferson Lab.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Kelli Hellenbrand</individual> and <individual>Sara Pladziewicz</individual> for helping the volunteer scans. Grant sponsors: <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency>: <grantNumber>R01NS066982-01</grantNumber>; <grantNumber>R21EB009441-01</grantNumber>; <grantNumber>R01EB006882-01</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was funded by <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>GM116381</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>HG008140</grantNumber>, and by the <fundingAgency>Howard Hughes Medical Institute</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual>Jeffrey Spence</individual> and <individual>Yun S Song</individual> for technical assistance. We also thank <individual>Ziyue Gao</individual>, <individual>Arbel Harpak</individual>, <individual>Molly Przeworski</individual>, <individual>Joshua Schraiber</individual>, and <individual>Aylwyn Scally</individual> for comments and discussion, as well as two anonymous reviewers. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments <fundingAgency>Leiden University</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>NWO BSIK/BRICKS</fundingAgency> supported this research under Grant <grantNumber>#642.066.603</grantNumber>. Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>South China Chinese Medicine Collaborative Innovation Center</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>A1-AFD01514A05</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Characteristic Key Discipline Construction Fund of Chinese Internal Medicine of Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine</fundingAgency> (2013)(2014)(2015).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank all researchers involved during the project, especially to the staff of <educationalInstitution>TecPes (Laboratorio de Tecnología Pesquera) at Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso</educationalInstitution> (<individual>T Melo</individual>, <individual>CF Hurtado</individual>, <individual>D Queirolo</individual>, <individual>E Gaete</individual>, <individual>I Montenegro</individual> and <individual>R Escobar</individual>). Additional thanks to members of "<affiliation>Programa de Conservación de Tiburones, Chile"</affiliation> and <affiliation>ELASMOLAB</affiliation> staff at <affiliation>Universidad Austral de Chile</affiliation> for their valuable help with logistics, sampling and dissection help during fieldwork, especially <individual>J Lamilla</individual>, <individual>F Concha</individual>, <individual>H Flores</individual>, <individual>Y Concha-Perez</individual> and <individual>A Isla</individual>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I thank <individual>K. Wang</individual> for providing the research environment required to perform these experiments and for helpful discussions, <individual>G. Seabold</individual>, <individual>E. Tytell</individual>, and <individual>M. Yoshizawa</individual> for critically reading the manuscript, <individual>G. Ashida</individual> for helpful discussions, and <individual>K. Nakao</individual> and <individual>R. Renden</individual> for additional scientific comments on the manuscript. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Oliver Rauhut</individual> (<affiliation>Bayerische Staatssammlung für Paläontologie und Geologie, München</affiliation>), <individual>Miriam Zelditch</individual> (<affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>), <individual>Johannes Knebel</individual> (<affiliation>Ludwig Maximilians University, München</affiliation>), <individual>Stefan Richter</individual> (<affiliation>University of Rostock</affiliation>), <individual>Walter Joyce</individual> and <individual>Eduardo Ascarrunz</individual> (both <affiliation>University of Fribourg</affiliation>) for discussion, and <individual>Michel Laurin</individual> (<affiliation>Sorbonne Universités, Paris</affiliation>) for comments on an earlier version of the manuscript. We further thank <individual>Matthew Lamanna</individual> (<affiliation>Carnegie Museum of Natural History, Pittsburgh</affiliation>), <individual>Alex Downs</individual> (<affiliation>Ruth Hall Museum, Ghost Ranch</affiliation>), <individual>David Gillette</individual> (<affiliation>Museum of Northern Arizona, Flagstaff</affiliation>) and <individual>Xu Xing</individual> (<affiliation>Institute of Vertebrate Paleontology and Paleoanthropology, Beijing</affiliation>) for access to collections. This study benefitted especially from critical comments of <individual>Jesús Marugán-Lobón</individual> (<affiliation>Universidad Autónoma de Madrid</affiliation>) and three anonymous reviewers.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Y. Polyrakis</individual> and seminar participants in the <otherInstitution>Conference on Ordered Spaces and Applications</otherInstitution> (Athens, November 2011) for helpful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The sketch for  Fig. 1  was adapted from www.biologieunterrricht. info/-Media/umrisse-mensch.jpeg, licensed by <fundingAgency>Creative Commons</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author acknowledges the assistance provided by officials of the <otherInstitution>Government of Pakistan</otherInstitution>. the <otherInstitution>united Nations</otherInstitution> and its specialized agencies. and non-governmental organizations engaged in providing help to Afghan refugees in Pakistan. The author is particularly grateful to the <otherInstitution>united Nations Population Fund (<otherInstitution>UNFPA</otherInstitution>)</otherInstitution> for allowing him to use material collected during a mission undertaken on their behalf in early 1989. Views expressed are the author"s own and not na€essarily those of the UNFPA.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This project has been supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>MCB RAS</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Russian Foundation for Basic Research</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>14-04-00004</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>13-04-01878-a</grantNumber>). This research was partially carried out using the equipment provided by the <otherInstitution>IBCH</otherInstitution> core facility (CKP IBCH). Diffraction experiments were carried out on beam-</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank all the <otherInstitution>ACCLAIM/COPD</otherInstitution> study investigators and <otherInstitution>Covance Inc.</otherInstitution> We also thank <individual>Dr Sharon Gladwin</individual> from Complete Medical Communications, who provided medical writing support. This study was funded by <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Almirall</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, S. A., Barcelona, Spain</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Forest Laboratories</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, Inc, NY, USA</fundingAgency>. Competing interests PWJ has received fees from a number of pharmaceutical companies, including Almirall, for speaking at meetings and for consulting and participating in advisory board meetings, and has also received support for research from <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>GSK</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>. SIR has consulted on or participated in advisory boards for numerous pharmaceutical companies, including Almirall, GSK, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>AstraZeneca</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Novartis</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Nycomed</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>. He has received industry-sponsored grants from AstraZeneca, <fundingAgency>Biomarck</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Centocor</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Mpex</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Nabi</fundingAgency>, Novartis and <fundingAgency>Otsuka</fundingAgency>. AA has received fees for speaking and consultancy, as well as funds for research, from Almirall, GSK, AstraZeneca, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Boehringer Ingelheim</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Esteve</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency><fundingAgency><fundingAgency>Chiesi</fundingAgency></fundingAgency></fundingAgency>. PC has received fees for speaking and consultancy from Centocor, AstraZeneca, Chiesi, GSK, Boehringer Ingelheim, Nycomed, Novartis and Almirall, as well as research grants from <fundingAgency>Schering Plough and Centocor</fundingAgency>. HM has received funds for research and fees for consulting from a number of pharmaceutical companies. LF has served as a consultant to, and received lecture fees and grant support from, Nycomed, AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, Chiesi, GSK, Merck Sharp  &amp;  Dohme and Novartis. JFD has served on advisory boards for Almirall and Forest Laboratories. EDB has received remuneration for consulting and serving on advisory boards for Almirall, and his institution has received grants for taking part in clinical trials sponsored by Almirall and Forest Laboratories. NJG has received honoraria for presentations on COPD treatment at meetings sponsored by Almirall and Forest Laboratories, as well as payments for advisory board consultations. His institution has received research grants from Almirall and Forest Laboratories. RL and EGG are employees of Almirall. CC is an employee of Forest Laboratories, and holds stock and options in the company.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Lyle Sensenbrenner</individual> for his critical review of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>JSPS KAKENHI</fundingAgency> Grant Number <grantNumber>23500211</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>www.nature.com/scientificreports/</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We gratefully acknowledge financial support by <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, Sonderforschungsbereich 412, University of Stuttgart</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Work on this project was supported by an operating grant of the <fundingAgency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</fundingAgency>, infrastructure grants from the <fundingAgency>Canadian Foundation</fundingAgency> for Innovation and generous philanthropic support by the <individual>A. Irwin</individual> family. DB was supported by a <fundingAgency>Canada Graduate Scholarship</fundingAgency>, and MM received an <fundingAgency>Ontario Trillium fellowship</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the referee for providing valuable comments, and <individual>Jarle Brinchmann</individual>, <individual>David Sobral</individual>, and <individual>Simone Weinmann</individual> for useful discussions. We acknowledge funding from <fundingAgency>ERC</fundingAgency> grant HIGHZ No. <grantNumber>227749</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank Gena Lattin, MS for her assistance with data collection. RS is the recipient of a <fundingAgency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, National Institutes of Health (NIH) career development award</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>K23 HD052553</grantNumber>. This project was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Children's Health Research Center at University of Utah and Primary Children's Foundation</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements: The authors thank <individual>Dr M.C. Yadavannavar</individual> at <affiliation>BLDE University</affiliation> for his assistance with data collection, <individual>Dr Veena Algur</individual> for her assistance with translation of study materials, and the adolescents and their families for participation in this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the <researchInstitution>Unit of Support for Technical and Scientific Research (UATRS, CNRST)</researchInstitution> for the X-ray measurements. Supplementary data and figures for this paper are available from the IUCr electronic archives (Reference: BT5773).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to the <educationalInstitution>department of chemistry, Niger Delta University</educationalInstitution>, PMB 071. <otherInstitution>Wilberforce Island</otherInstitution>. <otherInstitution>Bayelsa State</otherInstitution>. Nigeria, where both the experimental determination of proximate and mineral analysis were conducted.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. The authors wish to thank <individual>W. Bode</individual> (<affiliation>Martinsried</affiliation>) for helpful suggestions, <individual>M. Dumbsky</individual> for expert technical assistance, <individual>H. Hof</individual> (<affiliation>Mannheim</affiliation>) for help in the preparation of anti-</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <otherInstitution>Wildlife Conservation Society (Russia)</otherInstitution>, <individual>Eugenia Bragina</individual> for the invaluable help in writing the report, <individual>Irina Maslova</individual>, <individual>Yuri Petrunenko</individual> and <individual>Alexander Nikanorov</individual> for valuable comments</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The writers are indebted to <individual>E. Navarro Raga</individual>, <individual>P. Gómez Garcia</individual> and <individual>M.T. Mínguez Hernández</individual> from the <affiliation>SCSIE Electron Microscopy Unit at the University of Valencia</affiliation> for their useful technical help, and <individual>M. Palomo Navarro</individual> for assistance with sample collection. <individual>Ramirez P</individual> and <individual>Menendez R</individual> are</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported by the <fundingAgency>College of Agriculture and Life Sciences</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Graduate School</fundingAgency>, and a grant from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>GM-21205</grantNumber>). I thank <individual>Dr. T. Ishikawa</individual> for providing the TS mutants and <individual>Dr. R. K. Littlewood</individual> for permission to present unpublished data from his Ph. D. dissertation on growth of the extrachromosomal mutants. The excellent technical assistance of <individual>Ms. P. Riese</individual> is acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported in part by funding from the <fundingAgency>University of California Office of the President's Office of Research and Graduate Studies</fundingAgency>. Authors acknowledge the <otherInstitution>UC BRAID</otherInstitution> for project and data management support; <individual>Verónica Hoyo, Ph.D.</individual> (<affiliation>UCSD</affiliation>) for her help in editing and graphics, and <individual>John Heldens</individual> and <individual>Dan Redline</individual>, former program directors at <affiliation>UCSF</affiliation> and <affiliation>UCD</affiliation>, respectively, for their contributions to the developmental stages of this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <otherInstitution>Centers for Disease Control (CDC)</otherInstitution> for A/California/04/09 virus and <individual>Ron Fouchier</individual> (<affiliation>Erasmus University, Rotterdam, The Netherlands</affiliation>) for A/Netherlands/603/09 virus. We thank <individual>Krisna Wells</individual> for editing the manuscript, <individual>Martha McGregor</individual>, <individual>Rebecca Moritz</individual>, <individual>Anthony Hanson</individual>, <individual>Hideaki Ishida</individual>, <individual>Hideaki Tsuchiya</individual>, <individual>Ryuzo Torii</individual>, <individual>Naoki Yamamoto</individual>, <individual>Kosuke Soda</individual>, <individual>Naoki Nomura</individual>, and <individual>Hiromi Yoshida</individual> for excellent technical assistance. We also thank <individual>Takashi Umemura</individual>, <individual>Yuji Sunden</individual>, and <individual>Tomohisa Tanaka</individual> for pathological analyses of virus-infected pigs.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported by a Grant from the <fundingAgency>Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>K12130</grantNumber>) and funds from <fundingAgency>Michigan AgBioResearch</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to <individual><individual>Dr Ulrich Desselberger</individual></individual>, <individual>Dr James Richards</individual> and <individual>Prof. Andrew Lever</individual> (<affiliation><affiliation>University of Cambridge</affiliation></affiliation>) for the generous gift of the full-length cDNA copies of RV genomic segments for in vitro transcription; <individual>Dr John Patton</individual> for sharing a DNA clone pQE60g8C for expressing group C rotavirus NSP2. The authors would like to thank Dr Ulrich Desselberger (University of Cambridge) for critical reading of the manuscript; <individual>Prof. Takeshi Kobayashi</individual> (<affiliation>University of Osaka</affiliation>) for his valuable advice and discussions on the rotavirus reverse genetics system established in his laboratory. We thank <individual>Dr John T. Patton</individual> (<affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>), <individual>Prof Peter Stockley</individual>, <individual>Dr Roman Tuma</individual> and <individual>Mr Jack Bravo</individual> (<affiliation>University of Leeds</affiliation>) for valuable discussions and comments during the preparation of the manuscript. Available at Dryad Digital Repository under a CC0 Public Domain Dedication</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The encouragement and constructive criticism of earlier versions of this paper by many friends and colleagues, especially <individual>Robert Austin</individual>, <individual>Martin Johanson</individual>, <individual>Sam MacAulay</individual>, <individual>Volker Mahnke</individual>, <individual>Ram Mudambi</individual>, <individual>Rajneesh Narula</individual>, <individual>Christos Pitelis</individual> and <individual>John Steen</individual>, are gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Ms Chiori Fukuyama</individual> for her skillful technical assistance. This study was supported by <fundingAgency>Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research on Priority Areas</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>17016065</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>16062101</grantNumber>, to R. Ueda) from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education, Culture, Science, Sports, and Technology, Japan</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Grants-in-Aid for Cancer Research</fundingAgency> from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Health, Labor, and Welfare, Japan</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>17S-1</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>17-16</grantNumber>, to S. Iida).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The work of N.E.M. is partially supported by <fundingAgency>P.P.A.R.C. (U.K.)</fundingAgency>. E.W. wishes to thank <fundingAgency>Oriel College (Oxford)</fundingAgency> for financial support and the <educationalInstitution>Department of Physics, University of Newcastle (Newcastle-upon-Tyne)</educationalInstitution> and <otherInstitution>CERN Theory Division</otherInstitution> for hospitality.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>Lucilla Scuto</individual> (<affiliation>Central Core Lab, EuroImaging, Rome</affiliation>) for careful assistance in collecting digital images from the suburban centres, and in storing echo and ECG readings. We are also grateful to <individual>Dr Tarcisio Vago</individual>, <individual>Ospedale Luigi Sacco</individual> (Milan, Italy) for assaying NT-proBNP, and to <individual>Margareth Becker</individual> for her help in editing the manuscript. They funding body had no role in the concept or design of the study, or in the data reporting.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported in part by <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health Grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>R03 CA108364 (L.E.W.)</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>P50 CA116199 (H.G.)</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R01 ES011740</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>R01 CA131274 (Q.W.)</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>P30 CA016672</grantNumber> (<fundingAgency>M. D. Anderson Cancer Center</fundingAgency>). We thank <individual>Margaret Lung</individual> for her assistance in recruiting the subjects; <individual>Yawei Qiao</individual>, <individual>Kejing Xu</individual>, <individual>Zhensheng Liu</individual>, <individual>Jianzhong He</individual>, and <individual>Yinyan Li</individual> for their laboratory assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was published with the kind financial support of <fundingAgency>Bulgarian Science Fund</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements This trial was funded and sponsored by <fundingAgency>Cancer Research UK</fundingAgency> (grant number <grantNumber>C357/A12197</grantNumber>). Also supported by the <fundingAgency>Christie NHS Foundation trust</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>European Union FP6 Programme 'ATTACK'</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Manchester Cancer Research Centre Biobank</fundingAgency>. Sincere thanks go to all the patients and their families who participated in this trial.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that they have received no funding for the research reported.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Susanne Schwanz</individual> for technical support, <individual>Oliver Gould</individual> for his help with the figure design, and <individual>Clemens Kunz</individual> (<affiliation>Friedrich-Schiller University Jena</affiliation>) for help with the formation of defined damages in the samples utilized for self-healing experiments. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Helmholtz-Association</fundingAgency> through programme-oriented funding.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Dr. Peter Hasselbacher</individual> kindly provided the histologic and immunofluorescent studies of the skin biopsy. <individual>Dr. F. C. McDuffie</individual> generously performed the monoclonal rheumatoid factor assays.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This book could not have existed without <individual>Conor Sally</individual>, who rejects all thanks and recognition but debated every comma on every page and supported me at every stage. I could not ask for a better friend, partner, cheerleader or taskmaster and will never be able to express the depths of my love and gratitude.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the participants in the study. Funding. No funding or sponsorship was received for this study or publication of this article. The article processing charges were funded by the authors.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is founded by the <fundingAgency>German Research Foundation (DFG)</fundingAgency> (Contract <grantNumber>CH 943/2-1</grantNumber>). The authors would like to thank <individual>Wolfgang Dittus</individual>, and <individual>Stefan Paetel</individual> from <affiliation>Zentrum für Sonnenenergie-und Wasserstoff-Forschung Baden-Württemberg</affiliation> for preparing the CIGS absorber layer for this work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments that improved the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>David Rand</individual>, <individual>Hugo Sequeira</individual>, <researchInstitution>LIAAD-INESC Porto LA</researchInstitution>, <educationalInstitution>Centro de Matemática da Universidade do Minho</educationalInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Fundação Calouste Gulbenkian</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution><fundingAgency>Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia (FCT)</fundingAgency></otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>PRODYN-ESF</otherInstitution>, and <individual>Jorge Carneiro</individual> and <individual>Jorge Zubelli</individual> for all the encouragement and helpful comments. We thank the <fundingAgency>Programs POCTI</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>POSI by FCT and Ministério da Ciência</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Tecnologia e do Ensino Superior</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Centro de Matemática da Universidade do Minho (CMAT)</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Centro de Matemática da Universidade do Porto (CMUP)</fundingAgency> for their financial support. Bruno Oliveira gratefully acknowledges financial support from <projectName>PRODEP III</projectName> by <fundingAgency>FSE</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>EU</fundingAgency> and Miguel Ferreira gratefully acknowledges financial support from Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia (FCT) given through a PhD scholarship.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements: We thank <individual>Dr. F. Leal</individual> for technical assistance in FPLC analysis and <individual>N.S.D. Skinner</individual> for proofreading the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments The authors are grateful to <individual>Nicky Wilkinson</individual> for advice on data protection issues and <individual>Adrian Smith</individual> and <individual>Dr. <individual>Cesar Pichardo-Almarza</individual></individual> for testing the on-line analysis tools and reporting tools during the development of the DISRUPT postprandial database. We also thank <individual>Drs. Pieter Groot</individual>, <individual>Charlotte Walden</individual> and Cesar Pichardo-Almarza for proof-reading of the manuscript. the <projectName>DISRUPT project</projectName> was funded by a <fundingAgency>BBSRC Industry Interchange Program</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>IIP/ 0307/009</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments. This work was funded by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (Grants <grantNumber>OCE-0647667</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>OCE-1537890</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>AGS-1036062</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>AGS-1036006</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>AGS-1444294</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</fundingAgency> (Grant <grantNumber>NA07OAR4310094</grantNumber>), and the <fundingAgency>Natural Environment Research Council</fundingAgency> (Grant <grantNumber>NE/ J020893/1</grantNumber>). The authors thank the anonymous reviewers for thoroughly and critically evaluating the manuscript. They are also grateful to the crew of the <otherInstitution>R/V Knorr</otherInstitution> for supporting us while chasing storms and that of the NOAA ship <individual>Ronald H. Brown</individual> for their support during SO GasEx. Data from the HiWinGS cruise will be made available via anonymous ftp (ftp1. esrl.noaa.gov/psd3/cruises/HIWINGS_2013/Collective_</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Xiaoxiao Bai</individual> for helpful comments on the manuscript. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Patrick and Catherine Weldon Donaghue Medical Research Foundation</fundingAgency>, and by the <fundingAgency>Betsy and Jonathan Blattmachr family</fundingAgency>. Li Yang was supported by the <fundingAgency>China Scholarship Council</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We most thank <individual>Dr. Behnam Baghianimoghadam</individual> for his consultation in the translation, editing and publication of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Ms. K. Arnold</individual> for excellent help with receptorbinding assays; <individual>Dr. Susan Potter-Perigo</individual> for preparing the purified proteoglycans; <individual>Dr. Robert W. Mahley</individual> for stimulating discussions and support; <individual>Drs. Stanley C. Rall</individual>, <individual>Eva-Hurt Camejo</individual>, <individual>German Camejo</individual> and <individual>Karl H. Weisgraber</individual> for comments on the manuscript; <individual>S. Ordway</individual> and <individual>G. Howard</individual> for editorial assistance; and <individual>J. Carroll</individual> and <individual>S. Gonzales</individual> for graphics. J. Borén was supported by a <fundingAgency>Howard Hughes Postdoctoral Fellowship for Physicians</fundingAgency>. This work was also supported by <fundingAgency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>HL-47660</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HL-18645, DK-02456</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>HL-30086</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements: The authors would like to thank <individual>Rob Aalberse</individual> for critically reading the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <affiliation>Jefferson Lab physics and accelerator divisions</affiliation> for their contributions. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>US Department of Energy</fundingAgency> (including contract <grantNumber>DE-AC02-06CH11357</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>US National Science Foundation</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Israel Science Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Korea Science Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>US-Israeli Bi-National Scientific Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Killam Trusts Fund</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Walter C. Sumner Foundation and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</fundingAgency> (SFB 443). Jefferson Science Associates operates the <fundingAgency>Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility</fundingAgency> under DOE contract <grantNumber>DE-AC05-06OR23177</grantNumber>. The polarimeter was funded by the US National Science Foundation, grants <grantNumber>PHY 9213864</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>PHY 9213869</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The uuthor ~s indebted to <individual>Drs. M. L~ant</individual> and <individual>M.V.S. Raju</individual> for help ~n lran.slathag the manuscript in to English. Mauuscript .criticism by <individual>Dr.s, G. Marbaix</individual>, <individual>G. Huez</individual> and <individual>A. Buray ~s</individual> also acknowledged. Sarko~'l was a .generous gift from <otherInstitution>CIBA-Geigy Corporation</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was nancially supported by the <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (No. <grantNumber>81630093</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>81874293</grantNumber>). We thank <individual>Mr Hongbo Zheng</individual> and <individual>Ms Ke Xu</individual> for the NMR measurements. <individual>Ms Yanan Qiao</individual> and <individual>Dr Jiaozhen Zhang</individual> are also acknowledged for the X-ray diffraction analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The excellent assistance of <individual>Susan V. Castro, PhD</individual>, in the preparation of the manuscript is gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The reverse transcriptase was a gift from <individual>Dr J. Beard</individual>. We thank <individual>Drs M. Jacquet</individual> and <individual>N. Affara</individual> for helpful discussion, <individual>Christian Sahuquillo</individual> for his excellent technical assistance, and <individual>Denise Baron</individual> for typing the manuscript. A. F. was supported by a long-term <fundingAgency>European Molecular Biology Organisation fellowship</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments. This work was supported in part by <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health Grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>5P50CA127003</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R01CA149222</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R01CA118 553</grantNumber>, and <fundingAgency>National Cancer Institute Cancer Center Support</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>5P30CA06516</grantNumber>. We thank <individual>Dana-Farber</individual>/<affiliation>Harvard Cancer Center in Boston, MA</affiliation>, for the use of the Pathology Specimen Locator Core, which provided data on KRAS mutation testing.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The radar measurements used in this study can be obtained from the Madrigal database at http://jro.igp.gob.pe. The Jicamarca Radio Observatory is a facility of the Instituto Geofisico del Peru operated with support from the <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> AGS-1433968 through Cornell University. Work at UT Dallas was supported by NSF <grantNumber>AGS-1261107</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>AFOSR FA9550-13-1-0095</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>[25] Acknowledgments. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>NASA Tropical Rainfall Measuring Mission (TRMM) Program</fundingAgency>. The authors would also like to thank <individual>V. N. Bringi</individual> of <affiliation>Colorado State University</affiliation> and <individual>Bob Meneghini</individual> at <affiliation>NASA/GSFC</affiliation> for their discussions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The Pennington Center Longitudinal Study is registered at ClinicalTrials.gov (Identifier NCT00959270). Special thanks to <individual>Connie Murla</individual> and <individual>Aimee Stewart</individual> for data management, as well as the many clinical scientists and staff of the <researchInstitution>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</researchInstitution> who have contributed data to the development of the Pennington Center Longitudinal Study. V C 2012 The Obesity Society</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is supported by <fundingAgency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAA)</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>P20 AA017837 (LEN and CMC)</grantNumber> and <fundingAgency>NIH Metabolism Training Grant</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>T32-DK007319 (DAD)</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to acknowledge the families for their participation and support and <individual>Dr. Dilek Aktas</individual> for discussion. Our work was supported in part by the grant from the <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health/National Human Genome Research Institute</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, number <grantNumber><grantNumber>1U54HG006542</grantNumber></grantNumber>. Grant sponsor: National Institutes of Health/National Human Genome Research Institute; Grant number: 1U54HG006542.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the following awards: <fundingAgency>MRC Milstein award</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>G0801721</grantNumber> (to MIH), <fundingAgency>NERC research grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>NE/ J01074X/1</grantNumber> (to MIH) and <grantNumber>NE/M015033/1</grantNumber> (to MIH/BW), <fundingAgency>Norwich Research Park (NRP) Translational Award</fundingAgency> (to BW/MIH), and a <fundingAgency>BBSRC NPRONET</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>BB/L013754/1</grantNumber>) <fundingAgency>Proof of Concept award</fundingAgency> (to MIH/BW). RD is funded by a <fundingAgency>Norwich Research Park BBSRC Doctoral Training Program Studentship</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>BB/M011216/1</grantNumber> and ZQ is funded by the BBSRC via <fundingAgency>Institute Strategic Programme Grant</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>BB/J004561/1</grantNumber> to the John Innes Centre. The authors declare no conicts of interest. We thank <individual>Catherine Tremlett</individual>, <individual>Andrew Hart</individual> and <individual>Ashleigh Crane</individual> at the <affiliation>Norfolk and Norwich University Hospital</affiliation> for the VRE strain and <individual>Justin O'Grady</individual> at the <affiliation>UEA Medical School</affiliation> for the MRSA strain. We are also grateful to <individual>Dr Jioji Tabudravu</individual>, <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation>, for his kind comments. KAW would like to thank the <researchInstitution>South African Centre for High Performance Computing</researchInstitution> for access to computational resources.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to express our gratitude to <individual>Drs H.Tanida</individual>, <individual>S.Y.Park</individual>, <individual>S.Adachi</individual> and <individual>T.Hikima</individual> for their help in the data collection at SPring-8. This work was supported by grants for the`<projectName>Research for the Future</projectName>' Program from the <fundingAgency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>97L00501</grantNumber>) and for the <projectName>National Project on Protein Structural and Functional Analyses</projectName> from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank many colleagues in hospital and in practice, particularly <individual>Dr. K. Shirley Smith</individual> and others at the <otherInstitution>London Chest Hospital</otherInstitution>, who have kindly referred patients needing valvotomy. We are especially indebted to <individual>Mr. J. R. Belcher</individual>, who has taken an active part in the surgical management of the Middlesex Hospital patients.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to the <educationalInstitution>Centre for Chemistry and Biotechnology and Deakin University, Australia</educationalInstitution> for supporting biofuel research. The authors thank <individual>Mr R Chaudhary</individual>, <individual>Dr R Kanwar</individual>, <individual>Prof J R Kanwar</individual> (<affiliation>Medical School, Deakin University</affiliation>) and A/<individual>Prof TTsuzuki</individual> (<affiliation>University of Canberra</affiliation>), for providing the magnetic nanoparticles. The authors are also grateful to the <otherInstitution>Electron Microscopy</otherInstitution> facility at the <educationalInstitution>Institute for Frontier Materials (IFM), Deakin University, Australia</educationalInstitution> for conducting the SEM work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank our coworkers in the laboratory for their valuable discussions and suggestions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Ms. Masayo Tada</individual> for her excellent technical assistance and measurements of serum and hepatic enzymes and components. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Gifu City Subsidiary</fundingAgency> for project creation "<projectName>Industry-AcademicGovernment Cooperation Project Subsidiary</projectName>".</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Inha University</fundingAgency> research grant (No. <grantNumber>53670</grantNumber>). We thank <individual>Prof. Jin Min Kim</individual> for insightful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are thankful to Director, <researchInstitution>CSIR-National Botanical Research Institute (CSIR-NBRI)</researchInstitution>, <individual>Lucknow</individual> for the facilities and for the financial support from the <fundingAgency>network projects (CSIR-INDEPTH), New Delhi, India</fundingAgency>. APS is thankful to <educationalInstitution>University Grant Commission, New Delhi, India</educationalInstitution> and GD is thankful to <fundingAgency>CSIR, New Delhi</fundingAgency> for the <grantName>award of Junior/Senior Research Fellowship</grantName> and <educationalInstitution>Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR)</educationalInstitution> for his Ph.D. registration. Award of <grantName>Fast Track Scientist</grantName> to SM from <fundingAgency>DST</fundingAgency> is gratefully acknowledged. <grantName>Award of Emeritus scientist (CSIR) project</grantName> to RDT is gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. First and foremost, we thank <individual>P. J. Zinke</individual> for an insightful paper that inspired generations of ecologists. We are grateful to Will Pearse for statistical advice. We also thank the authors of the many published studies that we reviewed for this manuscript and two anonymous reviewers whose comments improved this manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Work at UB and UWM was supported by <fundingAgency>National Science</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge funding by the <fundingAgency>German-Israeli Foundation</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>DFG</fundingAgency> (Grant No. <grantNumber>SA1031/6</grantNumber> and <fundingAgency>Excellenzcluster QUEST</fundingAgency>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>B Anderson</individual>, <individual>R Pantelic</individual>, <individual>K Goldie</individual>, and <individual>M Chami</individual> for expert technical assistance, <individual>S A Müller</individual> for extensive comments on the manuscript, <individual>M Kuhn</individual> for plasmid and strain contribution, <individual>K Namba</individual> for discussions and <individual>Martin Jacquot</individual> for support with the supercomputing infrastructure of <educationalInstitution>University of Basel</educationalInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank <individual>Dr Steven J. Hamilton</individual>, 619C89 is a highly cleared drug, mainly by undergoing Woodend Hospital, Aberdeen and <individual>Professor Charles</individual> extensive hepatic biotransformation. Previous studies in F. George, <otherInstitution>Southhampton General Hospital</otherInstitution>, for contributing healthy volunteers showed that no intact 619C89 was patients to this study. We would also like to thank the nurses excreted in urine (data to be published). Even though at the clinical sites for collecting blood samples and <individual>Mr Gary</individual> plasma protein binding for 619C89 is high (# 96%) the Layton for the statistical analysis. plasma clearance of 619C89 is approximately 65% of hepatic plasma flow (1.35 l h−1 kg−1) which suggests that 619C89 is a drug with a moderate-to-high extraction ratio in humans. Second, the steady-state volume of distribution of 619C89 is large, apparently related to a References</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledging such citizenship as a ''social fiction,'' Azoulay nonetheless offers it as</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>TGT thanks <individual>Ms. J. Sridevi</individual>, <researchInstitution><fundingAgency>CSIR</fundingAgency>-Central Leather Research Institute</researchInstitution>, <individual>Chennai</individual> for EPR measurements and CSIR for nan-cial support. SCS and RSS thank <fundingAgency>IISER-TVM</fundingAgency> for computational facilities and nancial support. The authors thank <individual>Abbey M. Philip</individual> for suggesting the possibility of simulating EPR using EasySpin.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was funded by <fundingAgency>Istanbul University</fundingAgency> <grantName>Scientific Research Project</grantName> <grantNumber>33202</grantNumber>. We thank <individual>Mr David F Chapman</individual> for editing the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present study was produced from the master thesis of <individual>Deniz</individual> YILDIRIM, DVM (<educationalInstitution>Afyon Kocatepe University, Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Afyonkarahisar, Turkey</educationalInstitution>, 2011). We would like to extend our thanks to <individual>Dr. Kürşat KAV</individual>, a deceased faculty member at the <educationalInstitution>Microbiology Department of Veterinary Medical School of Selçuk University</educationalInstitution> for his valuable technical assistance and we cordially convey our deep sorrow for his untimely death and commemorate him with mercy.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study was funded by a grant from the <fundingAgency>US Agency for International Development</fundingAgency> and technical oversight was provided by <otherInstitution>MEASURE Evaluation</otherInstitution>. Secondary data analysis was conducted with permission of all collaborating authors.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are supported in part by <fundingAgency>NIMH</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>5R01MH054636</grantNumber>. MBV is supported by a <fundingAgency>National Defense Science and Engineering Graduate Fellowship (NDSEG)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>National Eye Institute</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>EY03991</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>P30-EY012576</grantNumber>, and <researchInstitution>Research to Prevent Blindness</researchInstitution>. We thank <individual>Dr Serena Fabbrini</individual> for providing Sap-3 isomer.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Author contributions : Dr Yeager is the guarantor of the paper and takes responsibility for the integrity of the work as a whole, from inception to published article. Dr Yeager: conceived of the study, conducted experiments, interpreted data, wrote and revised the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Ms Nguyen: conducted experiments, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Mr Belchenko: conducted experiments, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Ms Colvin: conducted experiments, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Dr Takatsuki: conducted experiments, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Dr Ivy: provided patient access, interpreted data, provided funding, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Dr Stenmark: interpreted data, provided funding, helped draft and revise the manuscript, and approved the fi nal article for publication. Financial /nonfi nancial disclosures: The authors have reported to CHEST the following confl icts of interest: the <educationalInstitution>University of Colorado, Denver</educationalInstitution> has a contractual relationship with the pharmaceutical industry (<otherInstitution>Actelion</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Gilead</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution><fundingAgency>Pfi zer</fundingAgency></otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>United Therapeutics</otherInstitution>) for Dr Ivy to provide consultation. All monies are sent directly to the University of Colorado, Denver. Dr Stenmark has received pharmaceutical company grant monies from Pfi zer. Drs Yeager and Takatsuki, Mss Nguyen and Colvin, and Mr Belchenko have reported that no potential confl icts of interest exist with any companies/organizations whose products or services may be discussed in this article.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was partially financed by the <grantName>RECUPERA-2020</grantName> (an agreement between <fundingAgency>CSIC</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Spanish <fundingAgency>MINECO</fundingAgency></fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency><fundingAgency>EU-FEDER</fundingAgency></fundingAgency> funds) and <grantNumber>AGL2014-52465-C4-4-R</grantNumber> Projects (MINECO, EU-FEDER funds). Research of Torres-Sá nchez and Peña were financed by <fundingAgency>FPI</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Ramon y Cajal Programs</fundingAgency>, respectively (<fundingAgency>Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness</fundingAgency>). The authors thank <individual>Mr. Bernardo Crespo</individual> for allowing developing our field work in his farm.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Patric Jern</individual> for critical reading of the manuscript and useful suggestions. We thank associate professors <individual>Ewa Lundgren</individual> and <individual>Anders Liss</individual> for their valuable help with collecting samples. The study was supported by funds at the <fundingAgency>Academic Hospital, Uppsala, Sweden</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Cláudia Maria Valete-Rosalino, Armando de Oliveira Schubach and Madson Pedro da Silva Leite were responsible for the design of the study. Madelon Novato Ribeiro, José Liporage Teixeira and Monique Reis da Fonseca collected data. All authors were responsible for conducting the study and managing data; Madelon Novato Ribeiro, Cláudia Maria Valete-Rosalino, Raquel de Vasconcellos Carvalhaes de Oliveira, Maria Inês Fernandes Pimentel and Armando de Oliveira Schubach analyzed and interpreted data, and prepared manuscript; all authors reviewed and approved manuscript. We are grateful to <individual>Jacline Novato Ribeiro</individual>, <individual>Margareth de Araújo Silva</individual>, <individual>Michele Aparecida Ferreira Moreira de Oliveira</individual>, <individual>Fátima Peres Lima Dantas</individual> and <individual>Felipe Maia Maquieira da Silva</individual> for their help with the patients before the interviews. We also thank <individual>Dr. Sandro Javier BedoyaPacheco</individual> for help with the database. This study was funded by <fundingAgency>PAPES-FIOCRUZ</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq)</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Carlos Chagas Filho Foundation for Research Support in the State of Rio de Janeiro (FAPERJ)</fundingAgency>. Funding agencies had no interference in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis and interpretation of the data; and preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>Professor L. Ernster</individual> and <individual>Dr P. Gellerfors</individual> for their helpful discussion and suggestions, and <individual>Miss B. Persson</individual> for excellent technical assistance. The work was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>Swedish Cancer Society</fundingAgency> and by an <grantName>EMBO short-term fellowship</grantName> to F.G.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to <individual>Professor G. F. Azzone</individual> for helpful discussions and for reading the manuscript. The expert technical assistance of <individual>Mr Luciano</individual></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author would like to thank <individual>Prof. F. Klinkhamer</individual> and <individual>Prof. E. M. C. Abreu</individual> for useful discussions. The author would also like to thank <individual>Prof. U.Tirnakli</individual> for sending reference  [22] .</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful for financial support from the <fundingAgency>Henan Administration of Science and Technology</fundingAgency> (grant No. <grantNumber>0111030700</grantNumber>). Supplementary data and figures for this paper are available from the IUCr electronic archives (Reference: BV2111).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author is grateful to <individual>Brian Brush</individual> for his helpful comments and suggestions and acknowledges the financial support from the <grantName>College of Business Administration Miles Research Grant</grantName> at <fundingAgency>Marquette University</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge the support from the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (projects <grantNumber>137630</grantNumber> to U.S. and <grantNumber>160055</grantNumber> to H.B.). Special thanks go to the technical and scientific members of the <researchInstitution>Geneva and Zurich research groups</researchInstitution> who helped at all stages of this study. H.B. thanks <individual>Peter Hochuli</individual> (<affiliation>University of Zurich</affiliation>), <individual>Jean Guex</individual> and <individual>Torsten Vennemann</individual> (both <affiliation>University of Lausanne</affiliation>), and <individual>Helmut Weissert</individual> and <individual>Stefano Bernasconi</individual> (both <affiliation>ETH Zurich</affiliation>) for long term and highly stimulating scientific discussions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author would like to thank <individual>Prof. Dr. Ronald H. W. Hoppe</individual> and <individual>Prof. Dr. H.-J. Bungartz</individual> for the kind invitation to deliver a plenary lecture at the Annual Meeting of GAMM at Augsburg in March of 2002. The content of paper is based on that lecture. The author would also like to thank <individual>Ryuta Suzuki</individual> for discussions leading to a better presentation of the material in this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The last author would like to thank <individual>George Lowther</individual> for the idea of non-linear bounds, <individual>Michael Greinecker</individual> for his hints on dealing with kernels, and other users of MathStackexchange and MathOverflow for their valuable comments regarding measure theory and coupling.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Pr André Dufour</individual> for his help with statistical analyses.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We want to particularly acknowledge the patients enrolled in this study for their participation and the <researchInstitution>Basque Biobank for Research-OEHUN</researchInstitution> for its collaboration providing the human samples and the clinical information used in this project with appropriate ethics approval. Our gratefulness to <individual>Dr. Juan Burgos</individual> for the selection of the human samples and <individual>Dr. Felix Royo</individual> for helping with statistical analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank <individual>E. Brockmann</individual> and two anonymous reviewers for their helpful reviews. This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS-INSU)</fundingAgency>,</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>[56] Acknowledgments. We are grateful for the advice of <individual>Deborah</individual></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to gratefully acknowledge the contribution of <individual>E.L. Aronson</individual></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Felix Kahlhoefer</individual>, <individual>Matthew McCullough</individual>, <individual>Ian Shoemaker</individual>, <individual>John March-Russell</individual> and <individual>Stephen West</individual> for discussions. MD and CM also wish to thank <individual>Michael Spannowsky</individual> for 'stimulating' discussions. We thank <individual>Gary Steigman</individual> for pointing out an error in eq. (10) in an early version of this work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This paper is a product of the <projectName>UK Natural Environment Research Council's Valuing Nature Network</projectName> with additional support from the <fundingAgency>Economic and Social Research Council and UK Department for International Development</fundingAgency>. We thank all participants in the <projectName>VNN project workshops</projectName> for their inputs.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank <individual>Dr. Haruhiko MORI</individual>  (17)</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>HL 69723 (S.M.S)</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Yoshiko Miyake</individual>, <individual>Yoko Shiozawa</individual>, <individual>Seiichi Kotoda</individual>, <individual>Yoshiharu Tsuru</individual>, <individual>Toshihiro Nagai</individual>, <individual>Koji Shimoda</individual>, and <individual>Toshio Terashima</individual> for excellent technical assistance. We are also grateful to <individual>Kazuto Yamazaki</individual>, <individual>Keiko Fukada</individual>, and <individual>Takeshi Suzuki</individual> for their comments on the manuscript. This study was supported in part by research grants from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education, Science and Culture, Japan</fundingAgency>, and by the <fundingAgency>Program for Promotion of Fundamental Studies in Health Science of the National Institute of Biomedical Innovation</fundingAgency> (to K. Fukuda).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the villagers of Dielmo for their participation and continued collaboration in this project. We thank the administrative authority of <otherInstitution>Institut Pasteur of Dakar</otherInstitution> for their continuous support. We particularly thank the field workers for their sustained contribution to the project and in generating and maintaining the malaria databases. We thank the reviewers for their comments that have greatly improved the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank all those colleagues who have recently collaborated with us in the realization of the <projectName>µSR experiments</projectName> in the IBS. In particular: <individual>Alex Amato</individual>, <individual>Pietro Bonfà</individual>, <individual>Lucia Bossoni</individual>, <individual>Sean Giblin</individual>, <individual>Rustem Khasanov</individual>, <individual>Gianrico Lamura</individual>, <individual>Hubertus Luetkens</individual>, <individual>Marcello Mazzani</individual> and <individual>Toni Shiroka. Pietro Carretta</individual> and <individual>Samuele Sanna</individual> also acknowledge the financial support from <fundingAgency>Fondazione Cariplo</fundingAgency> (research grant no. <grantNumber>2011-0266</grantNumber>) for the research activity on IBS. Giacomo Prando acknowledges support from the <fundingAgency>Leibniz-Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst (DAAD)Post-Doc Fellowship Program</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</fundingAgency>. We are indebted to <individual>Professor Dr A. Trebst</individual> for many helpful discussions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Dr Sophie Rushton-Smith</individual> provided editorial assistance in the preparation of this manuscript, which was funded by the <fundingAgency>Association Naturalia et Biologia</fundingAgency>. <individual>Ph.Gabriel Steg</individual> has the following disclosures:</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the <educationalInstitution>School of Biological Sciences and Department of Biochemistry, University of Nairobi (UoN)</educationalInstitution> for providing research facilities for use in this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author is grateful to <individual>Dr. Ibrahim ElAgib</individual> of <affiliation>King Saud University, College of Sciences, Physics  &amp;  Astronomy Department</affiliation>, for valuable discussions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>NIH/NCI</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber># CA125456 (SBE)</grantNumber>, and a grant from the <fundingAgency>Israel-USA Bi-national Science Foundation</fundingAgency> <grantNumber># 2005331 (SBE)</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was conducted in the framework of the <grantName>EU-funded BIOMAHE Marie CurieToK Project</grantName> (<grantNumber>MTKD-CT-2004-509232</grantNumber>) and was partially supported by the <fundingAgency>Italian Ministry of University and Research (MUR)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is a joint work between <fundingAgency>ISAE/DMIA, ON-ERA/DTIM</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>UC Berkeley/EECS</fundingAgency>. G. Lasnier has been funded by the <fundingAgency>RTRA-FCS STAE Foundation</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments. Thanks to <individual>Will Stefanov</individual> (<affiliation>Department of Geology</affiliation>) and <individual>Jim Clark</individual> (<affiliation>Department of Chemistry</affiliation>) for valuable assistance in obtaining optical analyses and electron microprobe measurements. Thanks also to <individual>Bob Leighty</individual> and <individual>Kim Feely</individual> for sharing personal</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Dipartimento <educationalInstitution>di Scienze Neurologiche, Università di Bologna, Bologna, Italy</educationalInstitution>. Published: 28 September 2015</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>DMS-1517085</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by a Grant from the <fundingAgency>Korean Healthcare Technology R &amp; D Project, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Republic of Korea</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>HI10C1740</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The journal is published in one volume per year consisting of five numbers (one double number). The annual subscription price 1998 is DM 725,-; foreign $470.00 incl. postage and handling; personal rate DM 215,-; foreign $ 140.00. Single copy DM 140,-. The publisher must be notified of a cancellation of a subscription not later than three months before the end of the calendar year. After that date the subscription is automatically prolonged for another year. Authorization to photocopy items for internal or personal use, or the internal or personal use of specific clients, is granted by WILEY-VCH Verlag Berlin GmbH, provided that the base fee of US $ 17.50 per copy, plus US $ .50 per page is paid directly to Copyright Clearance Center, 27 Congress Street, SALEM, MA 01970, USA. For those organizations that have been granted a photocopy license by CCC, a separate system of payment has been arranged. The fee code for users of the Transactional Reporting Service is: 0863-0593/98 $ 17.50 + .50. All rights reserved (including those of translations into foreign languages). No part of this issue may be reproduced in any form, by photoprint, microfilm, or any other means, nor transmitted or translated into a machine language, without written permission from the publishers.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The editors would like to acknowledge both the significant contribution made by <individual>Pamela Walt</individual>], whose hard work, organisation and language skills made the original manuscript for this book possible, and the expert and patient assistance of <individual>Helen Green</individual> with the production of drafts of this text. Acknowledgements xi</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Conceived and designed the experiments: <otherInstitution>OS PT PA</otherInstitution>. Performed the experiments: <otherInstitution>OS PT CB JL MU</otherInstitution>. Analyzed the data: <otherInstitution>OS PT CB JL MU PP PA</otherInstitution>. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PP. Wrote the paper: PA.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>Editor Juan Pedro Rodríguez-López</individual> and to two anonymous reviewers for their constructive recommendations on how to improve this manuscript. MAM is grateful to <fundingAgency>audi Aramco</fundingAgency> for their sponsorship of this research programme. <fundingAgency>Areva</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>BHPBilliton</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>ConocoPhillips</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Nexen</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Saudi Aramco</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Shell</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Tullow Oil</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Woodside</fundingAgency> are thanked for their sponsorship of the wider <projectName>FRG-ERG research programme</projectName> at the <educationalInstitution>University of Leeds</educationalInstitution>, of which this study forms a part.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to gratefully acknowledge <individual>Dr Robert Greef</individual> for valuable suggestions with the optical set up and characterisation of the samples. Thanks to the financial support from the <fundingAgency>Faculty of Engineering</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Environment at the University of Southampton</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Engineering and Physical Sciences research council (EPSRC)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author wish to thank specialis <individual>ALFatlawy</individual> whom diagnose the study cases and <individual>Baha H ALAmiedi ,Ph.D</individual> for the help extended by him <affiliation>college of dentistry, university of Babyl governerate</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <projectName>Intramural Research Program</projectName> of the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual>Pr. Mamadou Dembele</individual>, <individual>Dr Mohamed Keita</individual>, <individual>Dr Mamadou Traore</individual>, <affiliation>PPD study monitors</affiliation>, <otherInstitution>NIAID DSMB</otherInstitution>, <individual>Etsegenet Meshesha</individual>, <individual>Dick Sakai</individual>, <individual>Drissa Sow</individual>, and the volunteers in the villages for their support. We would also like to acknowledge <individual>Hong Zhou</individual>, <individual>Sam Moretz</individual>, <individual>Ababacar Diouf</individual> and <individual>Greg Tullo</individual> for the GIA work and the <researchInstitution>PATH/Malaria Vaccine Initiative</researchInstitution> for their support of the GIA Reference Center.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr Hideki Takahashi</individual> in <affiliation>Michigan State University</affiliation> for providing sultr1;1 sultr1;2 double mutant, and <individual>Professor Pradipsinh Rathod</individual> in <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation> for E. coli GS245(DE3)pLysS strain. We thank <individual>Phillip SanMiguel</individual> and the <researchInstitution>Purdue Agricultural Genomics Center</researchInstitution> for the short read sequencing and analysis. We thank <individual>Elena Yakubova</individual> and <individual>Brett Lahner</individual> for ICP-MS analysis, <individual>Dr Andrea Raab</individual> for use of the HPLC facility, and the <researchInstitution>Microscopy and Histology Core Facility</researchInstitution> at the <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation> for using the confocal laser-scanning microscopy.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledged experts in the technologies key to maritime operations. Acquisition and maintenance strategies which will strengthen the public/private relationships to produce quality products and services faster and at competitive prices.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge funding from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>R01GM118675</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>R21EB021651</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>CHE-1351933</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present research was partly supported by <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (No. <grantNumber>31672071</grantNumber>), and <fundingAgency>Special Funds of Central Colleges Basic Scientific Research Operating Expenses</fundingAgency> (No. <grantNumber>2452015096</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank all volunteers for their participation in the study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>L Chamberlain</individual> and <individual>B Martin</individual> for sharing their Acyl-RAC protocol, Y and <individual>M Fukata</individual> for the DHHC plasmids and the <researchInstitution>PEGylation protocol</researchInstitution>, <individual>P Bastiaens</individual> for the APT plasmids and <individual>Sylvia Ho</individual> for generating the shRNA ZDHHC6 construct. The research leading to these results has received funding from the <fundingAgency>European Research Council</fundingAgency> under the <projectName>European Union's Seventh Framework Programme</projectName> (<grantNumber>FP/2007(FP/ -2013)/ERC Grant</grantNumber> Agreement n. <grantNumber>340260 -PalmERa</grantNumber>'. This work was also supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (to GvdG and to VH), the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Centre of Competence in Research (NCCR) Chemical Biology</fundingAgency> (to GvdG) and the <fundingAgency>Swiss SystemsX.ch initiative</fundingAgency> evaluated by the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation (LipidX)</fundingAgency> (to GvdG and to VH). TD is a recipient of an <grantName>iPhD fellowship</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>Swiss SystemsX.ch initiative</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The research leading to these results has in part been funded by the <fundingAgency>ESA project GHG-CCI</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>DLR grant SADOS</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>EU project ACCENT-Plus</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>University</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>State of Bremen</fundingAgency>. Russell R. Dickerson was supported by <fundingAgency>NASA/AQAST</fundingAgency>. We thank <researchInstitution>ESA</researchInstitution> and <researchInstitution>DLR</researchInstitution> for providing the SCIAMACHY Level 1 data and the <researchInstitution>SCIA-MACHY calibration team</researchInstitution> (<researchInstitution>DLR</researchInstitution>, <researchInstitution>SRON</researchInstitution>, <educationalInstitution>University of Bremen, ESA</educationalInstitution>, and others) for continuously improving the quality of the spectra. We acknowledge the use of data from the <otherInstitution>U.S. Energy Information Administration</otherInstitution> and the <otherInstitution>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</otherInstitution>. We also thank the <otherInstitution>European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF)</otherInstitution> for providing the meteorological reanalysis data. Fracking well</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to acknowledge the <otherInstitution>Irish Cattle Breeding Federation (ICBF)</otherInstitution> for access to estimates of sire merit.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments: We thank <individual>Steve Berman</individual> and <individual>Edwin Asturias</individual> for their guidance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Bernhard Geiger</individual> for providing liver MR images, as well as <individual>Ali Khamene</individual> and <individual>Frank Sauer</individual> for their support. This work is funded by <fundingAgency>Siemens Corporate Research and Institute for Mathematics and its Applications (IMA)</fundingAgency> at the <fundingAgency>University of Minnesota</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was conducted by the financial grant provided by <fundingAgency>JSS University, Mysore</fundingAgency>. Authors sincerely acknowledge their support and encouragement.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. Work of the third author is partially supported by <projectName>STARTproject</projectName> <grantNumber>Y237</grantNumber> of the <fundingAgency>Austrian Science Fund</fundingAgency> and by the <fundingAgency>MNZZS of Serbia 144016</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We cordially thank <individual>Dr. Gerd Neugebauer</individual> for his help in creating a subset of a bibtex data base using BibTool, as well as <individual>Dr. Ricardo</individual> <individual>A. Chávez Montes</individual>, <individual>Prof. Magnus Palmblad</individual> and <individual>Martin Fenner</individual> for comments on the manuscript. Warm thanks also go to <individual>Anubhav Kumar</individual> and <individual>Jennifer König</individual> for proofreading.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy, US Department of Energy</fundingAgency> under grant <grantNumber>DE-FG36-08G018006</grantNumber>. One of us (GMK) ~cknowledges support under an <fundingAgency>NDSEG graduate fellowship</fundingAgency>. We also acknowledge use of facilities supported by the <otherInstitution>Center for Science and Engineering of Materials</otherInstitution>, an NSF MRSEC.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I would like to thank <individual>Mr. Emile A. Minoli</individual> for contributions in Chapters 2 and 3. The cover page shows <individual>Daniel Minoli</individual> (center front) with a slide rule next to an AM radio the student trio built based on discrete electronic components. Students <individual>Melvin Lee</individual> (left front) and <individual>Steven Lightburn</individual> (right front) part of the student trio are with <individual>Mr. Tepper</individual> (middle front), electronics teacher in a <educationalInstitution>Technical Electronics Laboratory in Hight School in Brooklyn, NY</educationalInstitution> in the fall of 1970. Two second-row students are unidentified. As this textbook shows, electronics and electronics density has come a long way in the past 35 years, and will continue to do so under the thrust of nanotechnology.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>All sequences were performed at the <researchInstitution>Molecular Biology Unit, Institut Pasteur de Montevideo</researchInstitution>. The authors thank <individual>Natalia Rego</individual> and <individual>Horacio Botti</individual> for helpful discussion and suggestions, <individual>Hugo Naya</individual> for sharing the bioinformatic facilities of <researchInstitution>UBI</researchInstitution> <researchInstitution>Institut Pasteur Montevideo</researchInstitution> and <individual>Marissa Vignali</individual> and <individual>Peter Myler</individual> (<affiliation>Seattle Biomedical Research Institute; Seattle, WA USA</affiliation>) for helpful suggestions in library construction and sequencing.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <individual>Thomas O. Mason</individual> for numerous stimulating discussions. Initial simulations for amorphous Zn-Sn-In-O under strain were performed by <individual>Rabi Khanal</individual>. The work was performed under the collaborative <projectName>MRSEC program</projectName> at <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation> and supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation (NSF)</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>DMR-1121262</grantNumber>. Computational resources are provided by the <projectName>NSF-supported XSEDE program</projectName> and by <otherInstitution>Department of Energy NERSC</otherInstitution> facilities.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. This work was developed under the <grantName>MINECO predoctoral grants</grantName> <grantNumber>BES-2014-067894</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>EEBB-I-16-11044</grantNumber>, cofunded by the <fundingAgency>European Social Fund</fundingAgency>. The work at University of Barcelona was partly supported by the <fundingAgency>Spanish MINECO</fundingAgency> under the project <grantNumber>AYA2013-42614-P</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>AYA2016-77939-P</grantNumber> with partial support by the <fundingAgency>European Regional Development Fund (ERDF/FEDER)</fundingAgency>. RGH acknowledges the financial support of the <fundingAgency>University of Alcalá</fundingAgency> under project <grantNumber>CCG2015/EXP-055</grantNumber> and the <fundingAgency>Spanish MINECO</fundingAgency> under project <grantNumber>ESP2015-68266-R</grantNumber>. Funding of this work was also partially provided by the <fundingAgency>Spanish MINECO</fundingAgency> under the <projectName>project MDM-2014-0369</projectName> of <affiliation>ICCUB (Unidad de Excelencia "Marıá de Maeztu")</affiliation>. The editor thanks <individual>R. Du Toit Strauss</individual> and an anonymous referee for their assistance in evaluating this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments All images are by <individual>Francesco Gherardini</individual> unless otherwise noted.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Statistical analysis. A t-test (two tailed) was performed for statistical analysis if not otherwise specified. An F-test was used to determine equal or unequal variance in the t-test. *, ** and *** indicate P valueo0.05,o0.01 ando0.001, respectively. Data availability. Solid-state NMR data is available at: https://www.repository. cam.ac.uk/handle/1810/254646. The authors declare that all other relevant data supporting the findings of this study are available within the article and its Supplementary Information Files or on request from the corresponding authors.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank members of the <researchInstitution>Hutter lab</researchInstitution> for critically reading the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The results in this paper may also be applicable to robustness to source distribution. We considered robustness in the observation channel. However, some of results also apply almost without change to robustness in the input distribution. Ornstein'sd-distance  [18] ,  [13]  is also a meaningful distance when the uncertainty is in the input distribution, but requires the cost function to be specific. Such problems for the specific case of minimum mean square estimation were considered in  [25] . The important general problem merits further research.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>J.-Y. Zimmer</individual> for his helpful comments and suggestions. Thanks also to the <fundingAgency>Wallonia-Brussels International</fundingAgency> for the <grantName>Ph.D. scholarship</grantName> (S. Boukraa).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The Biodiversity Data Enrichment Hackathon was supported by the <fundingAgency>EU-funded proiBiosphere project (Coordination and policy development in preparation for a European Open Biodiversity Knowledge Management System, addressing Acquisition, Curation, Synthesis, Interoperability and Dissemination</fundingAgency>, grant No <grantNumber>312848</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Naturalis Biodiversity Center</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was carried out while BC was at the <educationalInstitution>California Institute of Technology</educationalInstitution>, and partially when both BC and KB were visiting the <researchInstitution>Isaac Newton Institute, Cambridge, UK</researchInstitution>. It is a pleasure to thank <individual>Prof. L. C. Evans</individual> for useful discussions. We are also grateful for the support of the <fundingAgency>U.S. National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>CMS 9457573</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>Air-Force Office of Scientific Research</fundingAgency> through a <grantName>MURI grant</grantName> (<grantNumber>F49602-98-1-0433</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The program was partially supported by <fundingAgency>NASA Lewis Research Center</fundingAgency> (Grant No. <grantNumber>NAG 3-782</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>Office of Naval Research</fundingAgency> (Contract No. <grantNumber>NO0014-85-K-0182 P005</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Serena Dudek</individual>, <individual>Kelly Carstens</individual>, and <individual>Deborah Park</individual> for critical reading of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Nathan L. Vanderford</individual> for critical reading and editing of this manuscript. This work was supported by grants from <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>RO1CA125454</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Susan G Komen Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>KG081310</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Mary Kay Ash Foundation</fundingAgency> (to B.P. Zhou) and <grantName>pre-doctoral fellowship</grantName> (<grantNumber>BC101068</grantNumber>) from <fundingAgency>DoD Breast Cancer Research Program</fundingAgency> (to Y. Lin).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <educationalInstitution>Core Facility and Laboratory Animal Unit of the LKS Faculty of Medicine</educationalInstitution>, the <affiliation>University of Hong Kong</affiliation> for technical support. We are thankful to <individual>Dr Terence Kin-Wah Lee</individual>, <individual>Dr. Stephanie Kwai-Yee Ma</individual> and <individual>Dr Judy Wai-Ping Yam</individual> for their helpful discussion on the study and comments on the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The S.E.R.C and A.F.R.C. are gratefully acknowledged for financial support. Thanks are due to <individual>Dr. C. Roessner</individual>, <affiliation>Texas A &amp; M University, TX, U.S.A.</affiliation>, for providing the E coli hemB expression system, to <individual>Mr D. Barton</individual> and <individual>Mr. P. Skelton</individual> (<affiliation>Cambridge</affiliation>) for electro-spray mass-spectrometry determinations, and to <individual>Dr. J. Cheung</individual>, <individual>Queen Mary</individual> and <affiliation>Wesffield College, London</affiliation>, for deprotecting the 3-oxo-1-hexylamine.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to acknowledge <individual>Paula Weston</individual> and <individual>Melinda Golde</individual> for their great work in processing human fetal prostate tissue sections. Also, we would like to recognize <individual>Dr. Simon Hayward</individual> for his support and guidance regarding the pathology of the human fetal tissue.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge the facilities of the <researchInstitution>Department of Biotechnology, Government of India, New Delhi (DBT)</researchInstitution> under <projectName>M.Sc. Biotechnology program</projectName>. Facilities of  <researchInstitution>DBT's Bioinformatics Sub Center</researchInstitution> are also gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Health Bureau of Zhejiang Province</fundingAgency> (grant no. <grantNumber>2013KYA108</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Health and Family Planning Commission of Zhejiang Province</fundingAgency> (grant nos. <grantNumber>2013KYA108</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>2014KYA260</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was funded by the <grantName>Dennis Cooper Hematology Young Investigator Award</grantName> and grant <grantNumber>P30 CA016359</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>National Cancer Institute</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work has been carried out in the scope of <projectName>INCO-DC project</projectName> <grantNumber>ERBIC18CT97016</grantNumber> 'Development of a simple technology in drinking water treatment for nitrate and pesticide removal', financed by the <fundingAgency>European Commission</fundingAgency>. Thanks to <individual>Fred Rainey</individual> for supplying the sequence and manuscript for T. hydrothermalis in advance of their publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Michel Desjardins</individual> for making the Phosphorimager system available to us. We also thank <individual>Sonia Broccoli</individual> for critical reading of the manuscript. This work was supported by Grants <grantNumber>FNR 12667</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>CIHR (to M.D.)</fundingAgency> and <grantNumber>GM54226</grantNumber> from <fundingAgency>NIGMS</fundingAgency> (to Y.-C.T.-D). M.D. is a <grantName>chercheur-boursier senior</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>FRSQ</fundingAgency>. C.H. holds a studenship award from the <fundingAgency>FRSQ</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to acknowledge the help of 161</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors gratefully acknowledge the financial support by the <fundingAgency>Research Program of Universities of Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>NJ10245</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank <individual>Graham Mc Geoch</individual>, Chief <affiliation>Clinical Editor, Health Pathways, Canterbury District Health Board</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgement. I wish to thank <individual>Professor Janusz Brzdȩk</individual> for paying my attention to the problem and for his most valuable suggestions during the preparation of this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments This research was funded by the <fundingAgency>European</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank the <researchInstitution>Staglin IMHRO Center for Cognitive Neuroscience</researchInstitution> for their expert technical assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS. We are grateful to <individual>Y. Asari</individual>, <individual>C. Tanaka</individual>, <individual>M. Noda</individual>, <individual>R. Haraguchi</individual>, <individual>M. Matsuhashi</individual>, <individual>K. Akashi</individual>, <individual>S. Satoh</individual>, <individual>N. Machida</individual>, <individual>A. Yoshioka</individual>, and <individual>I. Izumi</individual>, for their technical assistance. We thank <individual>Y. Hashimoto</individual>, <individual>H. Yanagawa</individual>, and <individual>Y. Konno</individual> for their critical comments and <individual>C. L. Bridgman</individual> for her critical reading of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Yunde Zhao</individual> and <individual>Youfa Cheng</individual> for sharing seed and reagents prior to publication. We thank <individual>Judy Callis</individual> and <individual>John Labavitch</individual> for helpful discussions on this project. Some seed stocks were obtained from the <otherInstitution>ABRC</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funding: This research was funded by the <fundingAgency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</fundingAgency> (grant number <grantNumber>R01HS018372</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is partially financed by the <fundingAgency>ERDF European Regional Development Fund</fundingAgency> through the <projectName>COMPETE Programme</projectName> and by <fundingAgency>National Funds</fundingAgency> through the <fundingAgency>FCT Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia</fundingAgency> within <projectName>project SELF-PVP</projectName> (<grantNumber>FCOMP-01-0124-FEDER-013070</grantNumber>)</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank the <educationalInstitution>Electron Microscopy Unit, Universidade da Coruna</educationalInstitution>, for the fachties. This study was partially funded by the <fundingAgency>Servicio de M e d~o Arnbiente Natural</fundingAgency>,</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Y. Fujita</individual> and <individual>Barry Gumbiner</individual> for constructs and <individual>Marc Mumby</individual> for PP2Ac antibody. This research was supported in part by <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>GM56362</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>CA142823</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author wish to thank <individual>E. Brod</individual>, <individual>R. Pedersen</individual>, <individual>A.F. Øgaard</individual> and <individual>T.K. Haraldsen</individual> for advice on experimental setup and obtaining waste materials. The author also wishes to thank two anonymous reviewers and the editor for useful advice and editing of the manuscript. This study was funded by <fundingAgency>CORE Organic II "IMproved Phosphorus Resource efficiency in Organic agriculture Via recycling and Enhanced biological mobilisation" (IMPROVE-P)</fundingAgency>, which aims to design improved P recycling systems for organic farming.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported in part by <projectName>CONACYT project</projectName> <grantNumber>32415-E</grantNumber> and <projectName>DGAPA, UNAM project</projectName> <grantNumber>IN-110200</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to the <fundingAgency>National Institutes for Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>GM094919 (EUREKA)</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>Science Foundation of Ireland</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>08/IN.1/B2070</grantNumber>) for support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <individual>Dr. Ian Macara</individual> for providing the wildtype and GAP-deficient p190RhoGAP expression vectors. We also wish to thank <individual>Christy Cloonan</individual> for excellent technical assistance, <individual>Dr. Channing Der</individual> for the Lsc construct, <individual>Geneva Arthur</individual> for preparation of the manuscript, and the members of the <affiliation>Burridge laboratory</affiliation> and <individual>Dr. Leslie Petch</individual> for thoughtful discussions. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>GM29860</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge use of beamline BL17U1 at the <researchInstitution>Shanghai Synchrotron Radiation Facility (China)</researchInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This paper was supported by the research fund from <fundingAgency>Samsung Medison, Inc.</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The research was carried out due to the grant of <fundingAgency>Russian Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (project <grantNumber>#17-17-01143</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The first author's research is partially supported by grants from <fundingAgency>National Advanced Technology Research</fundingAgency> and</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>P.A. Baikov</individual>, <individual>A.G. Grozin</individual>, and <individual>O.V. Tarasov</individual> for help with checking the analytical results for the contribution (i). This research has been supported by the <fundingAgency>Russian Foundation for Basic Research</fundingAgency>, project <grantNumber>96-01-00654</grantNumber>, and by the grant <grantNumber>BMBF 057KA92P</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge <individual>James Blanchard</individual>, <individual>Andrea Hunter</individual> and <individual>Rachel Spitzer</individual> for their participation; <individual>Kerri Wazny</individual> for providing technical support; and the <fundingAgency>Canadian Partnership for Women and Children's Health (CanWaCH)</fundingAgency> for their support in this collaborative effort. CanWaCH is a collaboration of more than 80 Canadian organizations that are working to improve maternal, newborn, child and adolescent health in low-and middle-income countries.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are very grateful to <individual>Pete Alcock</individual> and <individual>John Mohan</individual> for their leadership, support and encouragement, and to <individual>Jane Parry</individual> and <individual>Rebecca Taylor</individual> for earlier collaborations on the topic of internships. We would also like to thank the anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgment: We thank <individual>Cyrus Shahpar, MPH</individual>, and <individual>Sophia Sterling, MPH</individual>, for data assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments: This project/research has been made possible with the support of the <fundingAgency>Dutch Province of Limburg</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Internalized violence begat despair, heightened suspicion, justified spying, and raised the temptation to deal with the growing instability with yet more violence. When the first 42 AGI, Estado, lima, 74/13, 29/04/1817, VC Pezuela to <individual>Secr de Estado</individual>; Santa Fe, 57/35. This is the file series that got lost in the mail; see AGI series cards 211-212; Estado, Americas, 88/3, "Memorial en nombre dl; Fernando VII."</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>"Scientific Exchange Programme between the New Member States of the EU and Switzerland"</fundingAgency> (<grantName>Sciex-NMS</grantName>, project <grantNumber>10.140</grantNumber>) and by the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (grant <grantNumber>31003A_140766</grantNumber>). The study was also funded by the <fundingAgency>National Science Centre in Kraków, Poland</fundingAgency> (grant nos. <grantNumber>2013/11/B/ST10/00276</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>2014/12/T/ST10/00675</grantNumber>). The authors thank the crew of <otherInstitution>R/V Oceania</otherInstitution> for their assistance during the fieldwork. <individual>Mateusz Ostrowski</individual> is thanked for helping with the granulometric analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Yue Zhao</individual>, <affiliation>MSc, Concordia University, Montreal, Quebec</affiliation>, and <individual>Linda Kwakkenbos, PhD</individual>, <affiliation>Lady Davis Institute for Medical Research, Jewish General Hospital, Montreal, Quebec</affiliation>, for assistance with translation. They were not compensated for their contributions. No funding body had any involvement in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; and preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Ethics Human subjects: This study was approved by the local ethics committee (<grantNumber>CSE01321</grantNumber>; <affiliation>University of Glasgow, College of Science and Engineering</affiliation>) and conducted in conformity with the Declaration of Helsinki. All participants provided informed written consent before participating in the experiment and received monetary compensation for their participation.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke intramural program (MNB and NAS)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Columbia University Center for Motor Neuron Biology and Disease (NAS)</fundingAgency> and by <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health Grant NS047357 (CAS and FJA)</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual>Chris Henderson</individual>, <individual>Tom Jessell</individual>, <individual>George Mentis</individual> and <individual>Michael O'Donovan</individual> for their support and critical comments on this manuscript. We also thank <individual>Ms Jackie Sisco</individual> with her help preparing semithin histological sections of muscle spindles.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>Professors Dr. Mofazzal Hossain</individual> and <individual>Dr. Mizanur Rahman</individual>, <fundingAgency>Department of Horticulture (BSMRAU)</fundingAgency>, are thanked for allowing the junior author to set yellow pan traps for collecting parasitic Hymenoptera in their experimental plots. We thank <individual>J. Read</individual> (<affiliation>CNC</affiliation>) for preparing the excellent images and compiling the plates.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was funded by a grant from the <fundingAgency>US National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> to DH (<grantNumber>GM64798</grantNumber>). the <projectName>SSRL Structural Molecular Biology Program</projectName> is supported by the <fundingAgency>Department of Energy, Office of Biological and Environmental Research</fundingAgency>, and by the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health, National Center for Research Resources, Biomedical Technology Program</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</fundingAgency>. We thank SSRL scientist <individual>Clyde Smith</individual> for excellent support. AP was funded in part by a <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship</fundingAgency>. SR was funded by the <fundingAgency>Max-Planck Society Germany</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual>James Fraser</individual> (<affiliation>UCSF</affiliation>) and <individual>Artem Lyubimov</individual> (<affiliation>Stanford</affiliation>) for guidance and review on refinements of diffraction data and members of the <researchInstitution>Herschlag laboratory</researchInstitution> for discussions and comments on the manuscript. We thank <individual>Celerino Abad-Zapatero</individual> and <individual>Vincent Stoll</individual> for information about their published D101S AP structure. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is supported by <fundingAgency>Philips Healthcare/Radiological Society of North America Research Seed</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>#RSD1104</grantNumber>, the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Health (Director's New Innovator Award</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>1DP2OD007246-01</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>1R21CA152627</grantNumber>), and <fundingAgency>Morris Animal Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>D09CA-083</grantNumber>). Q.Y. was funded at UIUC from the <fundingAgency>NIH National Cancer Institute Alliance for Nanotechnology in Cancer "Midwest Cancer Nanotechnology Training Center</fundingAgency>" Grant <grantNumber>R25 CA154015A</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Medical Research Council UK</fundingAgency> (MRC; awards <grantNumber>MC_UU_12020/5</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>MC_UU_12024/2</grantNumber> to PJM, and award <grantNumber>MC_UU_12024/1</grantNumber> to AS), a <grantName>Marie Curie European Re-integration</grantName> Grant (<grantNumber>SNAP-PD</grantNumber>) awarded by the <fundingAgency>European Union</fundingAgency>, and the <grantName>Wellcome Trust (Investigator Award</grantName> <grantNumber>101821</grantNumber> to PJM). FNG and EK were supported by the <fundingAgency>MRC and University of Oxford Clarendon Fund Scholarships</fundingAgency>. FV was supported by an <fundingAgency>MRC studentship</fundingAgency>. RS was in receipt of a <grantName>Wellcome Trust Clinical Fellowship</grantName> (<grantNumber>WT_RS_109030/Z/15/Z</grantNumber>). We thank <individual>T Harkany</individual> and <individual>R Faram</individual> for early insights on secretagogin, and <individual>G Hazell</individual>, <individual>B Micklem</individual>, <individual>L Norman</individual>, <individual>K Whitworth</individual>, <individual>J Janson</individual>, <individual>L Conyers</individual> and <individual>C Johnson</individual> for technical support. We also thank <individual>G. Silberberg</individual> and <individual>K. Meletis</individual> for their expert insights.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank the <otherInstitution>Consumption Markets  &amp;  Culture editor</otherInstitution> <individual>Jonathan Schroeder</individual>, and the three anonymous reviewers for their valuable suggestions and comments. The authors also gratefully acknowledge the candor and generosity of their informants.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>R. A. J. Warren</individual> for his valuable suggestions in preparing this manuscript, <individual>Linda Sandercock</individual> for assistance in preparing Strep. lividans genomic DNA, and <individual>Bradley McLean</individual> for helpful insights and discussion. This research was supported by the <fundingAgency>Protein Engineering Network of Centres of Excellence</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Natural Sciences and Research Council of Canada</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>CBD Technologies Inc.</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia</fundingAgency>, under grants <grantName>Dana Lonjakan Penerbitan</grantName> (<grantNumber>UKM-DLP-2014</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments: The authors thank <individual>Assia Benabdallah</individual> for discussions on the subject of the present article.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Disclosure forms provided by the authors are available with the full text of this article at NEJM.org.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Jan Johansson</individual> and <individual>Kristiina Nygren</individual> for their assistance and help during field work and implementation of the experiment. We are grateful to <individual>Eddie von Wachenfeldt</individual> and <individual>Therese Carlsson</individual> for help with the collection of the water samples. We greatly appreciate help from <individual>Jan Bengtsson</individual>, <individual>Kalle Mälson</individual>, and <individual>Allan Rohde</individual> with the study site selection. We thank <individual>Helmut Hillebrand</individual>, <individual>Paul del Giorgio</individual>, <individual>Ingvar Sundh</individual>, and several members of the <otherInstitution>Microbial Ecology group</otherInstitution> at our department for fruitful discussions and constructive comments on earlier drafts of the manuscript. Constructive comments by an anonymous reviewer also greatly improved the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to express our gratitude to the <fundingAgency>Research Council of the University of Mazandaran</fundingAgency> for partial financial support of this work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <otherInstitution>A2B2C</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>ISCB-SC</otherInstitution> and <otherInstitution>ISCB</otherInstitution> for their continuous support, at different levels, to all our initiatives. We would also like to recognize <educationalInstitution>Universidad Nacional de San Martín</educationalInstitution> for sharing the infrastructure needed to host the event. Finally we thank all those students that offered their time for reviewing the abstracts and all those that attended the 2SAJIB.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The fruitful collaboration with the <otherInstitution>''What Works for Women and Girls'</otherInstitution>' project greatly improved this study and we would like to extend our gratitude to <individual>Melanie Croce-Galis</individual> and <individual>Karen Hardee</individual> for their invaluable contributions and support. Our sincere thanks to all members of the <otherInstitution>UNAIDS expert reference group</otherInstitution> for their detailed and constructive guidance throughout the project, namely <individual>Avni Amin</individual>, <individual>Michael Bartos</individual>, <individual>Louise Binder</individual>, <individual>Lori Bollinger</individual>, <individual>Briana Buehler</individual>, <individual>Lynn Collins</individual>, <individual>Nazneen Damji</individual>, <individual>Susana Fried</individual>, <individual>Berthilde Gahongayire</individual>, <individual>Claudia Garcia Moreno</individual>, <individual>Kreena Govender</individual>, <individual>Nyaradzai Gumbonzvanda</individual>, <individual>Musimbi Kanyoro</individual>, <individual>Shannon Kowalski</individual>, <individual>Renee Mckenzie</individual>, <individual>Daniella Ligiero</individual>, <individual>Rolake Odetoyinbo</individual>, <individual>Amissa Briana Bongo Ondimba</individual>, <individual>Anna Seymour</individual>, <individual>Alice Welbourn</individual> and <individual>Anandi Yuvaraj</individual>. We are also grateful to the authors of selected publications for sharing documents we were not able to access, including author manuscripts that were still under preparation or in press.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was funded by <fundingAgency>Instituto de Salud Carlos III ISCIII FIS/FEDER</fundingAgency> Grants <grantNumber>PI11/02070</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>PI14/00900</grantNumber> (to AG) and <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health, NIH Awards</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>R03 AR049420</grantNumber> (to SWS) and <grantNumber>R01 AR052889</grantNumber> (to JTE).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was funded by <fundingAgency>Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>81360310</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>31106237</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>31260276</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>81271330</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>31471187</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>31171215</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>w8110305</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The investigators are grateful to all collaborating institutions for their support. Our thanks are due to <individual>Drs. Patrick Breysse</individual>, <individual>Peter Lees</individual> and <individual>Timothy Buckley</individual> of the <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University School of Hygiene and Public Health</affiliation> for many valuable suggestions and for loaning several pumps for the monitoring activity; to the <researchInstitution>Institute for Health Systems Hyderabad</researchInstitution>, for their role in administering the household level questionnaire and to the <fundingAgency>World Bank (ESMAP) unit</fundingAgency>, who funded the study. Our special thanks are also due to <individual>Kseniya Lvovsky</individual>, <individual>Sameer Akbar</individual> and <individual>Priti Kumar</individual> of the <otherInstitution>World Bank</otherInstitution> for their technical inputs while executing the project. Finally, we are extremely grateful to the members of the households for their graciousness in allowing the use of their premises for the monitoring activities.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</fundingAgency> (grants <grantNumber>SFB630</grantNumber> to C.K. and C.A.S. and <fundingAgency>Forschungszentrum</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>FZ82</grantNumber> to C.K.) and by the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (grants <grantNumber>GM102864</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>AI044639</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>AI070383</grantNumber> to P.J.T.). A.C. was supported by the <fundingAgency>Chemical Biology Training Program</fundingAgency> (<grantName>NIH</grantName> grant <grantNumber>T32GM092714</grantNumber>) and by the <fundingAgency>Medical Scientist Training Program</fundingAgency> (<grantName>NIH</grantName> grant <grantNumber>T32GM008444</grantNumber>). J.S. was supported by a grant of the <fundingAgency>German Excellence Initiative</fundingAgency> to the Graduate School of Life Sciences, University of Wuerzburg. We thank the staff at the beamline 14.1 (BESSY II) operated by the <otherInstitution>Helmholtz-Zentrum Berlin</otherInstitution> and at the <otherInstitution>ESRF beamlines ID 14-1 and ID 29</otherInstitution> for technical support. Funding Sources: <grantName>NIH</grantName> grants <grantNumber>GM102864</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>AI044639</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>AI070383</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>T32GM092714</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>T32GM008444</grantNumber> <grantName>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</grantName> grants <grantNumber>SFB630</grantNumber> and <grantName>Forschungszentrum</grantName> <grantNumber>FZ82</grantNumber></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. We thank two anonymous reviewers for thoughtful comments that improved the paper, <individual>Sarah Brosnan</individual> for encouragement and patience, and <individual>Joe Halpern</individual>, <individual>Oren Kolodny</individual> and <individual>Shimon Edelman</individual> for productive discussions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <educationalInstitution>Gentner Lab at the University of California, San Diego</educationalInstitution>, for their logistical and technical support, and <individual>Molly Dickens</individual>, <individual>Scott MacDougall-Shackleton</individual>, and <individual>Luke Remage-Healey</individual> for their thoughtful discussion of this project. We also thank our four anonymous reviewers for their comments and suggestions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The data of this study have been excerpted from the PhD thesis of the author. The authors thank <individual>Assoc Prof Abbas Yousefi Rad</individual>, <individual>Assoc Prof Ayşe Esra Karakoç</individual> and <individual>Sefer Erman Yılmaz, MD</individual> for collecting clinical specimens, <individual>Onur Candan, PhD</individual>, for comments and suggestions and <individual>Çağla Kılıç MSc</individual>, for her contribution to this study. This work was financed by <fundingAgency>Hacettepe University Scientific Research Project</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>014D01601002</grantNumber> and the <fundingAgency>Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey (TUBITAK) with PhD Scholarship</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>2211/C</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Y. Takasu</individual> and <individual>S. Igarashi</individual> for experimental assistance. This work was supported in part by <projectName>Grant for Basic Scientific Research Projects</projectName> from the <fundingAgency>Sumitomo Foundation and The Kurata Memorial Hitachi Science and Technology Foundation</fundingAgency>. We thank <individual>Kao Corporation</individual> for kindly providing the LDAO.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I am grateful to the <otherInstitution>President and Council of the Association</otherInstitution> for honouring me in their invitation to deliver the <grantName>John Snow Lecture</grantName> for 2001, and to the <otherInstitution>Editor of Anaesthesia</otherInstitution> for arranging to publish it.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgement. We are thankful to the anonymous <individual>AE</individual> and the two referees for their suggestions, which helped us to improve the presentation of the paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank the four reviewers for their constructive and critical comments that helped to improve the quality and presentation of our work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Irma Thesleff</individual> for support and discussions, and <individual>Merja M€ akinen</individual>, <individual>Riikka Santalahti</individual>, <individual>Maria Sanz-Navarro</individual>, <individual>Raija Savolainen</individual>, and <individual>Nina Tiusanen</individual> for technical assistance. This work was financially supported by <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation Sinergia</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>CRSI33_125459</grantNumber>, the <fundingAgency>Academy of Finland</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Sigrid Jus elius Foundation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Jane and Aatos Erkko Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Ella and Georg Ehrnrooth Foundation</fundingAgency>, and <grantNumber>RO1 DC013072</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>RO3 DC007349</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Authors thank all the participants for agreeing to take part in the study, and <individual>Marion Bonnard</individual>, <individual>Camélia Boukhris</individual>, <individual>Florence Brisson</individual>, <individual>Elsa Brune</individual>, <individual>Lucien Coudrin</individual>, <individual>Anne-Sophie Courtois</individual>, <individual>Delphine De Guibert</individual>, <individual>Sébastien Douabin</individual>, <individual>Marc Fedele</individual>, <individual>Gwenaëlle Felard</individual>, <individual>Fanny Gohars</individual>, <individual>Samantha Guimaron</individual>, <individual>Morgane Hamouric</individual>, <individual>Aurore Lamberet</individual>, <individual>Laurence Lebas</individual>, <individual>Raphaël Leroux</individual>, <individual>Sébastien Le Texier</individual>, <individual>Andre Madrid</individual>, <individual>Edmond Oriol</individual>, <individual>Louise Perrier</individual>, <individual>Ouriel Rosenblum</individual>, <individual>Hélène Spriet</individual>, <individual>Philippe Taillet</individual>, <individual>Xavier Taillet</individual> for assessing the videos.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. M. R.-C. was in charge of the interpretation of the articles reviewed and manuscript design and editing. E. S.-C. and C. M.-P. had responsibility for research information and manuscript writing. All authors contributed to discuss and had input writing the article. All authors contributed equally to the literature search, analysis of the data published, manuscript writing and revisions of the article. All authors approved the final version of the manuscript. The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>WH would like to acknowledge the <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (No. <grantNumber>21171088</grantNumber>) for financial aid. Supplementary data and figures for this paper are available from the <otherInstitution>IUCr electronic archives</otherInstitution> (Reference: RZ2684).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Institute for Basic Science (IBS)</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>[IBS-R004-A2-2017-a00]</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We pass to selection in society. Does it take place here among variations which have been utilised just as it does among animals? We know its mechanism in the latter. The strong, possessed of variations which are perfectly adapted to the situation, are perpetuated, while the feeble who possess variations which are imperfectly adapted are eliminated.. The law is the same with man</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The Mayor of the City welcomed us and presided at the</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>Cornelius Peter</individual> for his help with molecular lab work and <individual>Joumin Rangkasan</individual> who assisted with fieldwork. This project was carried out by <fundingAgency>CCP</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>PSH</fundingAgency> as part of their undergraduate honours degree dissertation. We thank <individual>Rudiger Bieler</individual>, <individual>Siong Kiat Tan</individual> and an anonymous reviewer for their constructive comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the staff of the <educationalInstitution>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine at Juntendo University</educationalInstitution>, <educationalInstitution>Department of Cardiology at Tokyo Women's Medical University</educationalInstitution> and <educationalInstitution>Department of Cardiology at Teikyo University School of Medicine</educationalInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>John Harris</individual> at <otherInstitution>Public Health England</otherInstitution> for providing data on reported outbreaks of infectious intestinal disease</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Brita G Bruun</individual> for critically reading the manuscript</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>is study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo (FAPESP)</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cientí�co e Tecnol�gico (CNPq)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank: the originators of all three input datasets as well as the supporters of the remote sensing systems that are used to build such datasets; the students of <educationalInstitution>INTR 204 at William and Mary</educationalInstitution> for testing these methods; <researchInstitution>Dan Freiss of the mangrove lab in Singapore</researchInstitution> and the <otherInstitution>Moore Foundation</otherInstitution> for reviewing drafts of this paper; and the referees and editors at <otherInstitution>GEB</otherInstitution> for help with editing the paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Author Contributions: S.S. and E.Y. conceived and designed the experiments; S.S. performed the experiments; S.S., J.J, X.Q., and E.B. analyzed the data; E.Y. and H.G. contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools; S.S. and E.Y. wrote the paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>Kuan Liu</individual>, Sales Engineer from <affiliation>Majorbio, Shanghai</affiliation>, for the technology guidance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Assistant Professor Efthimia Petinaki</individual> (<affiliation>Department of Microbiology, School of Medicine, University of Thessaly, Greece</affiliation>) for bla vim Kp isolate detection in 2005. The authors are grateful to <individual>Professor Alkiviadis Vatopoulos</individual>, <individual>Dr Panagiota Giakkoupi</individual> and <individual>Dr Kyriaki Tryfinopoulou</individual> (<affiliation>Department of Microbiology, National School of Public Health, Athens, Greece</affiliation>; <affiliation>Central Public Health Laboratory, Vari, Greece</affiliation>) for their constant assistance in epidemiological surveillance of CR-Kp over the last decade. The study was supported by funding from the <fundingAgency>Department of Microbiology, School of Medicine, University of Patras, Greece</fundingAgency>. The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. The study was approved by the <otherInstitution>Ethical Committee of University Hospital of Patras</otherInstitution> (no. 18208/18-9-2013).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research has been supported by the <fundingAgency>President's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief (PEP-FAR)</fundingAgency> through the <fundingAgency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</fundingAgency>. This information is distributed solely for the purpose of predissemination peer review under applicable information quality guidelines. It has not been formally disseminated by the <otherInstitution>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention/Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry, Atlanta, Georgia, USA</otherInstitution>. <otherInstitution>Instituto Nacional de Saúde (INS)</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Maputo Central Hospital</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Ministry of Health Fundação Ariel Glaser contra o SIDA Pediátrico (Ariel)</otherInstitution>. The findings and conclusions in this report are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official position of the <otherInstitution>US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</otherInstitution>. Use of trade names is for identification purposes only and does not constitute endorsement by the <otherInstitution>U.S. Centers for Disease Control</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The collaborations from <individual>Qiming Jin</individual>, <individual>Jim Sugai</individual>, <individual>Hector Rios</individual>, <individual>Reinhard Gruber</individual>, <individual>Yang-jo Seol</individual>, <individual>Gaia Pellegrini</individual>, and <individual>Darnell Kaigler</individual> are greatly appreciated. Dr Giannobile's work was supported in part by <fundingAgency>NIH/NIDCR DE 13397</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgment. The authors are most grateful to <individual>Professor K. Ogasawara</individual> of the <affiliation>Pharmaceutical Institute, Tohoku University</affiliation>, for his useful advice during this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the <researchInstitution>National Genotyping Center at Academia Sinica, Taipei, Taiwan</researchInstitution>, for their genotyping service.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The EPIC study was funded by <fundingAgency>"Europe Against Cancer" Programme of the European Commission (SANCO)</fundingAgency>; <fundingAgency>Ligue contre le Cancer (France)</fundingAgency>; <fundingAgency>Soci et e 3M (France)</fundingAgency>; <fundingAgency>Mutuelle G en erale de l'Education Nationale; Institut</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Prof. Rongxiang Fang</individual>'s group from the <affiliation>Institute of Microbiology, Chinese Academy of Sciences</affiliation> for providing the cDNA library of small brown planthopper for yeast two-hybrid screening. We also thank <individual>Prof. Gerald Reeck</individual> from <affiliation>Kansas State University</affiliation> for comments and language suggestions. This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Strategic Priority</fundingAgency></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Additional file 3:  Figure S2 . Sequence Entropy of type I European PRRSV Strains. Multiple sequence alignment of the genomes [Olot/91-GenBank:KF203132, GenBank:M96262, GenBank:GU737264, GenBank: A26843, GenBank:GQ461593, GenBank:FJ349261, GenBank:DQ489311, GenBank:JF802085, GenBank:GU047344, GenBank:GU047345, GenBank: AY588319, GenBank:AY366525, GenBank:GU067771, GenBank:EU076704, GenBank:DQ864705] were generated with MUSCLE and entropy analysed with Hyphy  [25] . Higher entropies denote regions with higher variability.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>R. Rosenfeld</individual> for useful discussions. This research was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq) (AAN)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Coordenadoria de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Ensino Superior (CAPES) (AM)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Fundação de Amparoà Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo (FAPESP) (AAN)</fundingAgency>, and by <fundingAgency>Programa de Apoio a Núcleos de Excelência (PRONEX)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Conceived and designed the experiments: WN BIE. Performed the experiments: WN. Analyzed the data: WN BIE. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: WN BIE. Wrote the paper: WN BIE.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>M Peter</individual>, <individual>G Schlenstedt</individual>, <individual>J Woolford</individual>, <individual>K Karbstein</individual>, and <individual>M Seedorf</individual> for generously sharing strains and antibodies, and <individual>N Schä uble</individual>, <individual>M Hondele</individual> and <individual>K Weis</individual> for help with ATPase assays. We thank all members of the <researchInstitution>Panse laboratory</researchInstitution>, in particular <individual>J Thorner</individual> <affiliation>UC Berkeley</affiliation>, for enthusiastic discussions, <individual>J Petkowski</individual> for structure-guided analysis, <individual>M Altvater</individual> for microscopy, and the <researchInstitution>Institute of Medical Microbiology UZH</researchInstitution> for continued support. V G Panse is supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NCCR in RNA and Disease, ETH Zurich</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Novartis Foundation</fundingAgency>, <individual>Olga Mayenfisch Stiftung</individual> and a Starting Grant Award (<grantNumber>EURIBIO260676</grantNumber>) from the <fundingAgency>European Research Council</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The paper is based on the <projectName>Basic Research Project</projectName> of the <researchInstitution>Korea Institute of Geoscience and Mineral Resources (KIGAM)</researchInstitution> funded by the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Knowledge Economy of Korea</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors have obtained financial support from the <fundingAgency>Volkswagenstiftung (Germany)</fundingAgency> within the program "<projectName>Nachwuchsgruppen an Universitäten</projectName>". The simulations were performed at the <otherInstitution>Paderborn Center for Parallel Computing in Germany</otherInstitution> and on a workstation cluster at the <educationalInstitution>Institut für Theoretische Physik, Universität Göttingen, Germany</educationalInstitution>. We thank <individual>M. Jungsbluth</individual> for helpful remarks.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Harry C. Dietz</individual> for providing CAGA  12</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work has been carried out with the support of <fundingAgency>Rolls-Royce plc</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>DERA</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>MoD</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>DTI</fundingAgency>. The authors would also like to thank <individual>Professor T.V. Jones</individual> and <individual>Dr C.R.B. Day</individual> for their help and guidance, and <individual>Mr K. Walton</individual> and <individual>Mr T. Godfrey</individual> for their practical assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I thank numerous colleagues and collaborators whose intellectual and technical contributions continue to be instrumental to this investigation.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank all researchers and institutions which provided samples for this study (all are listed in  Table S1 ). We thank to <individual>P. Matějů</individual> for help in laboratory.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The paper was supported by the research grant of <fundingAgency>Chungbuk National University</fundingAgency> in 2012.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This paper was written using data made available by the <otherInstitution>Cystic Fibrosis Trust</otherInstitution> as submitted to the Port CF database by all UK CF Centres between 2007-2012.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Laura Brown</individual>, <individual>Sam Demas</individual>, <individual>Sharon Farb</individual>, <individual>Kevin Guthrie</individual>, <individual>Charles Henry</individual>, <individual>Lisa Hinchliffe</individual>, <individual>Ross Housewright</individual>, <individual>Anne Kenney</individual>, <individual>Robert Kieft</individual>, <individual>Marita LaMonica</individual>, <individual>William Mayer</individual>, and <individual>Jennifer Rutner</individual> for helpful suggestions in developing the questionnaire and/or framing our findings. Final responsibility remains ours alone.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge the studies conducted by  Yoshimura et al. (2014) ,  Elkon et al. (2015)  and  Waldhaus et al. (2015)  for providing open access to mouse gene expression data. JAL-E has received funding from <fundingAgency>Meniere Society, UK</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Luxembourg National Research Fund</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>INTER/Mobility/17/11772209</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was financially supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Schweizerische Nationalfonds zur Förderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung (SNF)</fundingAgency> and by the <fundingAgency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS)</fundingAgency> through <fundingAgency>Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research</fundingAgency> (Grant No. <grantNumber>16K06712</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are thankful to the <affiliation>Vice Chancellor, OUAT, Bhubaneswar, Odisha, India</affiliation>, for providing the necessary facilities to carry out this work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>[53] Acknowledgments. Financial support for the data collection of this research was provided by the <fundingAgency>World Bank</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Water and Sanitation Program</fundingAgency>. We are grateful to <individual>Clarissa Brocklehurst</individual> for comments on the data collection, analysis, and interpretation and to <individual>Govind Subedi</individual>, <individual>Yogendra Gurung</individual>, <individual>Keshab Adhikari</individual>, <individual>Dhanendra Shakya</individual>, <individual>Laxman Kunwar</individual>, and <individual>Bal Krishna Mabuhang</individual> for help with the survey. Thanks are also due to <individual>Jon Strand</individual>, three anonymous reviewers, and the <otherInstitution>Associate Editor</otherInstitution> for their helpful comments and suggestions. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in this paper are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the <projectName>World Bank or the Water and Sanitation Program</projectName>. The authors alone remain responsible for any errors in the paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This book embodies what is special about what CiE is trying to do in taking computational research beyond the constraints of "normal science," while building a cohesive research community around fundamental issues of computability.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the <otherInstitution>Ibn Sina Hospital</otherInstitution> physicians for their assistance in collecting and compiling the data for this study, and <individual>Gae 0 Decker-Garrad</individual> for editorial assistance and preparation of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><individual>K. Conrad</individual>, Principal Investigator) . The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of<otherInstitution>NIOSH</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are very thankful to <individual>Mrs. Anjuman Ara Begum</individual>, Lecturer, <affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Jahangirnagar University, Savar</affiliation>, for this expert planning, sincere direction, supervision, invaluable advices and continuous follow up from the very beginning of this work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to acknowledge the support of <fundingAgency>NASA</fundingAgency> under <grantNumber>NRA-NAS2-37143</grantNumber> on "<projectName>Research in Intelligent Systems</projectName>."</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Al-Quds University</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Belgium government</fundingAgency>. The authors thank the <researchInstitution>Palestinian Central Bureau of Statistics</researchInstitution> for providing the sampling frame and the <fundingAgency>Greek State Scholarship Foundation</fundingAgency> for their support to the second author C. Jildeh in her PhD study. H. Al Sabbah is postdoctoral researcher funded by the <fundingAgency>Fulbright Scholarship, Tufts University, Boston, USA</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I would like to acknowledge the linguistic revision by <individual>Eugenia Lamont</individual>, <affiliation>Medical University of Graz</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank the <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>21273081</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>21673085</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Natural Funds of Guangdong Province</fundingAgency> (grant no. <grantNumber>2015A030311050</grantNumber>) for providing the nance support for this project. We also appreciate the</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the Principal of <otherInstitution>Amrita Sai Institute of Science and Technology</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Paritala</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>Chanchikacharla</otherInstitution> and the head of the department of <otherInstitution>Civil Engineering</otherInstitution>, for their kind support during the experimental investigation. The authors express their profound thanks to <individual>Dr. Sasidhar, Professor</individual>, <affiliation>Amrita Sai Institute of Science and Technology</affiliation> for his critical reading and suggestions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>US and BT would like to acknowledge financial support by the <fundingAgency>German Research Council (DFG)</fundingAgency> within the <grantNumber>CRC701</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge the expertise of <individual>K. Molin</individual> and <individual>Professor Enevold Falsen</individual> (<affiliation>CCUG</affiliation>) for their technical and scientific assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to express their indebtedness to all laboratory staff who sacrificed their time and effort to comply with the special requirements, and spent significant time on performing these tests without complaint in order to achieve the highest possible quality in this trial. Furthermore, we would also like to acknowledge all center principal investigators and personnel who contributed their time and effort to this study. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (BIPI)</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Pfizer Inc</fundingAgency>. Writing, editorial support, and formatting assistance was provided by <individual>Jane M. Gilbert, BSc</individual>, CMPP, of <affiliation>Envision Scientific Solutions</affiliation>, which was contracted, and compensated by <fundingAgency>BIPI</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Pfizer Inc</fundingAgency> for these services.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>To <individual>Dr Moacir Paranhos Silva</individual> (<affiliation>Institute of Heath Sciences, UFBA</affiliation>), for his technical assistance on splenic punctures.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We gratefully acknowledge financing by the <fundingAgency>International Fund for Agricultural Development, Rome, aid agencies of Switzerland (DCA)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>West Germany (GTZ)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Austria</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Canada (IDRC)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Denmark</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Netherlands</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Italy</fundingAgency>, as well as <fundingAgency>FAO</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Rome</fundingAgency>, and thank <individual>S. KorangAmoakoh</individual>, <individual>J. M. A. Anga</individual> and <individual>K. Kouame</individual> for their help in the field and <individual>E. V. Doku</individual> for information. We thank our colleagues at IITA for reviewing the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author is grateful to the referee and <individual>Professor H. P. Dikshit</individual> for some helpful suggestions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank members of the <researchInstitution>Schwab lab</researchInstitution> for valuable discussions; <individual>K. Cadwell</individual> (<affiliation>New York University School of Medicine</affiliation>) for Salmonella enterica Typhimurium; <individual>K. Manova</individual>, <individual>S. Fujisawa</individual>, and <individual>Y. Romin</individual> (<affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center Molecular Cytology Core Facility</affiliation>) for assistance with microscopy and image analysis; and <individual>B. Breart</individual> (<affiliation>Institut Pasteur, Paris, France</affiliation>) and <individual>J. Cyster</individual> (<affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>) for critical reading of the manuscript. This work was funded by <grantNumber>NIH R01 AI085166</grantNumber> to S.R.S.; <grantNumber>NIH T32 AI100853</grantNumber> to V.F. and A.M.; and <grantNumber>NIH R01 NIH DA019674</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>NS084398</grantNumber> to J.C.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>F.P.D. Cotterill</individual>, <individual>T. van der Niet</individual> and <individual>J.W. Kadereit</individual> for comments on drafts of the paper; <individual>D. Franke</individual> for assistance with graphics; <individual>J. Fagúndez</individual>, <individual>A. Hitchcock</individual>, <individual>R. Turner</individual>, <individual>M. Muasya</individual>, <individual>C. Stirton</individual>, <individual>R. Clark</individual>, <individual>B. Bytebier</individual>, <individual>M. Pimentel</individual>, <individual>F. Ojeda</individual>, <individual>C. Merry</individual>, and many others for providing samples; and <otherInstitution>Cape Nature</otherInstitution> and <otherInstitution>South Africa National Parks</otherInstitution> for assistance with permits. The authors gratefully acknowledge the computing time granted on the supercomputer Mogon at <educationalInstitution>Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</educationalInstitution> (https://hpc.uni-mainz.de/).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments We are grateful to <individual>Dr. Ivo Lieberam</individual> for providing us with the GFAP::CD14 cell line and for reading the manuscript, and to <individual>Dr. Kevin Eggan</individual> for the HB9::GFP cell lines.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the participants for their time and personal information and Ms.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are thankful to the <educationalInstitution>Albertina Sisulu Executive Leadership Programme in Health, University of Pretoria</educationalInstitution> for their contribution towards the publication of this paper. Also, we are most grateful for the <fundingAgency>African Doctoral Dissertation Research Fellowship Award</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>ADDRF Award 2015Á2017 ADF 002</grantNumber>) provided by the <fundingAgency>African Population and Health Research Centre</fundingAgency> in partnership with the <otherInstitution>International Development Research Centre</otherInstitution> that helped make the wider PhD study from which this paper was drawn possible. Our heartfelt thanks also goes to the <otherInstitution>Ministry of Health</otherInstitution> and the <otherInstitution>Health Services Board of the Republic of Zimbabwe</otherInstitution>, the <otherInstitution>Zimbabwe Association of Church Hospitals, Epworth Local Board</otherInstitution>, and the <otherInstitution>Epworth community in Zimbabwe</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors, not the supporting groups listed earlier, had complete responsibility for the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; and preparation, review, and approval of the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Krishna Palaniappan</individual>, <individual>Ernest Szeto</individual>, <individual>Yuri Grechkin</individual>, <individual>Iain Anderson</individual>, and <individual>Athanasios Lykidis</individual>, for their contribution to the development and maintenance of IMG ER.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author is indebted to <individual>Léo Ducas</individual>, whose initial ideas and suggestions on this topic motivated work on this paper. The author further thanks <individual>Vadim Lyubashevsky</individual> and <individual>Oded Regev</individual> for their comments on the relevance of a subexponential time CVPP algorithm requiring (super)exponential space. The author is supported by the <fundingAgency>SNSF ERC Transfer</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>CRETP2-166734 FELICITY</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank the elderly people who participated in this study, the staff in the day-service centers who cooperated, colleagues in the laboratory who advised us, and the families who supported us. The research in this article did not generate any raw data.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by research funds from the <fundingAgency>Dong-A University</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Catherine Szente MD</individual>, paediatrician (<affiliation>Dreilandpraxis, Basel, Switzerland</affiliation>) for performing the clinical review.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank the <otherInstitution>CDC Emergency Operations Center</otherInstitution> for providing us the data as well as the FBI for providing us the data and for helpful comments and suggestions on the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors have not declared any conflict of interests.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study is funded by the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Health Research Public Health Research Programme</fundingAgency>. The authors would like to thank <otherInstitution>Aileen Ireland, Research Secretary</otherInstitution>, for her help in preparing the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Florida Department of Health</fundingAgency> <fundingAgency>James and Esther King Biomedical Research Program</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>07KB-07</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Neurological Diseases and Stroke</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>RO1NS52839</grantNumber> to AEW).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The We are very thankful to Almighty Allah; whose grace and blessed mercy enabled us to complete this work with full devotion and legitimacy. We are grateful to <individual>Mr. Fakhruddin</individual> and <individual>Mr. Nasir Rashid</individual> (<affiliation>Department of Computer Science and IT, University of Malakand</affiliation>) for their invaluable support and guidance throughout this research work. We also want to thank our friends and family for their encouragement; without whose support we could not have lived through this dream of ours.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by a grant from <fundingAgency>State Forestry Administration, P.R. China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>010-413255</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Our thanks to <individual>Lubomír Masner</individual> for discussion, insight, and inspration; to A.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The flat 2-torus P2 is a closed minimal hypersurface in the flat 3-torus T3\ the equatorial 2-sphere S2 in the 3-sphere 53 is a closed minimal hypersurface. Both these examples illustrate the theorem.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>[16] Acknowledgments. I thank <individual>Benno Blumenthal</individual> for the IRI Data Library, and <individual>Suzana Camargo</individual>, <individual>Tony Barnston</individual>, <individual>Alessandra Giannini</individual>, <individual>Vincent Moron</individual>, <individual>Ousmane Ndiaye</individual> and <individual>Sylwia Trzaska</individual> for their comments and suggestions. IRI is supported by its sponsors and <fundingAgency>NOAA Office of Global Programs</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>NA07GP0213</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>null</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Christoph Kolling</individual> for obtaining synovial <projectName>tissue for our research project</projectName> (approved by the local ethical committee). We thank <individual>Maria Comazzi</individual>, <individual>Peter Künzler</individual> and <individual>Ferenc Pataky</individual> for excellent technical assistance. We thank <individual>Prof. Dr. Beat A. Michel</individual> for his support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is supported by <fundingAgency>National Cancer Institute</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>R01CA136933</grantNumber> to D.C.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Doctoral Scientific Research Foundation of Henan University of Science and Technology, China</fundingAgency> (grant no. <grantNumber>09001677</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <projectName>Project 61201153</projectName> supported by <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Research Project of CCF-Qimingxingchen Hongyan</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>CCFVenustechRP2016004</grantNumber>), and the <fundingAgency>National 973 Program of China</fundingAgency> under Grant <grantNumber>2012CB315805</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author would like to express his deepest gratitude to <individual>Dr. Andrzej Jankowski</individual> for the close cooperation of the development the IGrC approach.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>CONACyT</fundingAgency> (grant <grantNumber>83049</grantNumber>). Supplementary data and figures for this paper are available from the IUCr electronic archives (Reference: GG2086).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>A.E.R. and D.M.F. acknowledge support from <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>R24GM115277</grantNumber>. Author Contributions: All authors wrote and revised this review with A.K.D collating the final version and submission.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the two referees, <individual>Matthew Jackson</individual>, and <individual>Albin Erlanson</individual> for their helpful suggestions. S.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Y Hirata</individual> (<affiliation>RIKEN</affiliation>) and <individual>H Kondo</individual> (<affiliation>RIKEN</affiliation>) for their experimental supports in proteome analysis, and <individual>K Honda</individual> (RIKEN) for preparing allantopyrone A beads. We are grateful to <educationalInstitution>Emeritus Professor Don R Phillips of La Trobe University</educationalInstitution> for critical reading of this manuscript. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>UGAS</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Iwate University Student Research Grant Project</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Grant-in-Aid for JSPS Fellows</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements Open access funding provided by <fundingAgency>University of Graz</fundingAgency>. Philipp Berghofer is a recipient of a <grantName>DOC Fellowship of the Austrian Academy of Sciences</grantName> at the <fundingAgency>Department for Philosophy at the University of Graz</fundingAgency>. I wish to thank <individual>Sonja Rinofner-Kreidl</individual>, <individual>George Heffernan</individual>, <individual>Elijah Chudnoff</individual>, and <individual>Walter Hopp</individual> for many enlightening discussions. Also, many thanks to <individual>Harald Wiltsche</individual>, <individual>Michi Wallner</individual>, <individual>Marian David</individual>, and an anonymous referee for many important clarifications.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments: We wish to acknowledge the tremendous contributions of many individuals who made this study possible. Our Uganda Virus Research Institute field team consisted of <individual>Simon Wakaalo</individual>, <individual>David Drajole Andabati</individual>, <individual>Jackson Olweny</individual>, the late <individual>Wilfred Cwinyaai</individual>, and <individual>Nicholos Owor</individual> (in addition to authors N.B., G.A.M., and L.A.A.). Key field assistance was also provided by <individual>Ali Sebbi</individual>, <affiliation>Environmental Health Officer for Nebbi District</affiliation>, <individual>Santos Angualia</individual>, <affiliation>Assistant Environmental Health Officer for Vurra Subcounty</affiliation>, and <individual>Appolo Midra</individual>, <fundingAgency>Assistant Environmental Health Officer for Logiri Subcounty</fundingAgency>. We wish to especially recognize the lifetime contributions of author <individual>Asaph Ogen-Odoi</individual>, who died in December 2006 while conducting field work to control the large plague outbreak mentioned in this paper that immediately followed this study. His contributions to this study and to the understanding and control of plague in Uganda can never be overestimated.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to the following for permission to reproduce copyright material:</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>ST designed, performed, and coordinated all experiments, developed, analyzed, and interpreted all data and models, and wrote manuscript. AVR developed the growth model. KLH helped with analysis of co-culture mutations and edited manuscript. CEA and SS helped with design and execution of experiments and edited manuscript. MAG and JAR performed proteomics</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <otherInstitution>OMiC Co. (Chengdu, China)</otherInstitution> for assistance with the bioinformatics analysis. This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Natural Sciences Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (nos. <grantNumber>81130062</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>81173236</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>30973743</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>European Commission</fundingAgency> under Grant Agreement No. <grantNumber>PITN-GA-2012-317488-CONTEST</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>EPSRC Engineering Fellowship for Growth -PRINTSKIN</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>EP/M002527/1</grantNumber>), and <fundingAgency>EPSRC First Grant</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>EP/M002519/1</grantNumber>). The authors are thankful to the support received for this work from <fundingAgency>James Watt Nanofabrication Centre (JWNC)</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Electronics Systems Design Centre (ESDC)</fundingAgency> in the University of Glasgow.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to express deep sense of gratitude to our guide <individual>Prof. R.D.Komati</individual> for providing us with an opportunity to carry out the <projectName>project on Smart Helmet Safety System</projectName> and for her help whenever required.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This project is supported by <fundingAgency>Carnegie Mellon University's Mobility21 National University Transportation Center</fundingAgency>, which is sponsored by the <fundingAgency>US Department of Transportation</fundingAgency>. We would also like to thank <individual>Adam Harley</individual>, <individual>Leonid Keselman</individual> and <individual>Rui Zhu</individual> for their helpful comments and suggestions.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors gratefully acknowledge the contribution of <individual>Carolyn Pelham</individual> and <individual>Kevin Adrian</individual> for their outstanding care and oversight of mice for the duration of this diet study. The research described herein was generously supported by funds provided by the <fundingAgency>Barnum Foundation and Zell Family Foundation at Northwestern University</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Nathan and Isabel Miller Family Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>IDP Foundation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>R21 CA123041-01 (PJG)</grantNumber>, and <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>R01 CA161283-01 (PJG)</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was financially supported by <fundingAgency>National Natural Sciences Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>81372446</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>National S &amp; T Major Project</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>2011ZX09102-001-10</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>2015ZX09102010</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Joint Acknowledgment/Disclosure Statement: This work was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>Commonwealth Fund, New York, NY</fundingAgency>. We acknowledge the contributions of the anonymous reviewers for numerous helpful suggestions. None of the authors reported a conflict of interest with respect to this project. Disclosures: Health Research  &amp;  Educational Trust is the publisher of HSR. Disclaimers: None.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Achim Stephan</individual>, <individual>Andrea Wittmann</individual>, <individual>Norman Mack</individual> and <individual>David Westermann</individual> for generous support with the whole-genome sequencing, the FISH and the preparation of the tumor sections. <individual>Ivo Buchhalter</individual> is gratefully acknowledged for support with the analysis of the whole-genome sequencing data. We thank <individual>Till Milde</individual> for the patient-derived xenograft model.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Terminology was used according to the recommendations by the <otherInstitution>European consortium</otherInstitution> <projectName>"Systematic Evaluation of the ground based (micro-) gravity simulation paradigms available in Europe"</projectName> (ESA contract 4200022650)  [52] . We gratefully acknowledge financial support by <fundingAgency>DLR</fundingAgency> (grant no. <grantNumber>50WB0912</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Italian Space Agency, Rome</fundingAgency> , (<grantName>grant MoMa/ERMEIS</grantName>)and the <fundingAgency>Fondazione Banco di Sardegna, Sassari</fundingAgency> (grant <grantNumber>968/2010.0373</grantNumber>). We also gratefully acknowledge the support of (in alphabetic order) <individual>Miriam Christen</individual>, <individual>Karl-Heinrich Grote</individual>, <individual>Sonja Krammer</individual>, <individual>Liliana Layer</individual>, <individual>Jutta Müller</individual>, <individual>Marianne Ott</individual>, <individual>Irina Rau</individual> and <individual>Monika Sebele</individual>. We are indebted to <otherInstitution>Partec GmbH (Münster, Germany)</otherInstitution> for providing the CyFlow SL for on-site analysis at ESRANGE Space Port and their excellent support. We thank <otherInstitution>PromoCell (Heidelberg, Germany)</otherInstitution> for the excellent collaboration in this project and for their individual service and custom production of material. We gratefully acknowledge the support of the <otherInstitution>European Space Agency</otherInstitution>, especially <individual>Rene Demets</individual> and <individual>Antonio Verga</individual>, of the <otherInstitution>Swedish Space Cooperation</otherInstitution>, especially <individual>Per Holm</individual>, <individual>Franz Gronmayer</individual>, <individual>Matthias Abrahamsson</individual> and <individual>Gunnar Florin</individual>, the <otherInstitution>Center for Concepts in Mechatronics (CCM)</otherInstitution>, especially <individual>Edwin Langerak</individual>, and <otherInstitution>Dutch Space</otherInstitution>, especially <individual>Guus Borst</individual>. We thank <individual>Ms. Naomi Shepherd</individual> for editing the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is dedicated to the memory of <individual>Dr Joaquin Mateu</individual> (Barcelona, 9/1/1921-18/1/2015, who really discovered and first studied C. aliai. The authors are grateful to <individual>Dr Thierry Deuve</individual> (<affiliation>Muséum National d'Histoire Naturelle, Paris</affiliation>) for some important advices. A particular thank is also due to <individual>Mr Jaroslav Kaláb</individual> (<affiliation>Kuřim, Czechia</affiliation>) and to <individual>Dr Massimo Meregalli</individual> (<affiliation>Department of Animal and Human Biology, University of Turin, Italy</affiliation>) for information on habitats and photos, and to <individual>Prof. Ronald Hedrick</individual> (<affiliation>School of Veterinary Medicine, University of California, Davis, CA, USA</affiliation>) for his assistance in editing the English text of the manuscript. Re-establishment of Carabus (Cathoplius) aliai  Escalera, 1944...</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment><educationalInstitution>Stanford University</educationalInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study was supported by <fundingAgency>National Forest Funds</fundingAgency>, transferred to the <fundingAgency>Tatra National Park</fundingAgency> in 2016.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This project is partially supported by the <fundingAgency>Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>41376095</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>41350110226</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Scientific Research Foundation for the Returned Overseas Chinese Scholars</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>20101174</grantNumber>), and <fundingAgency>Zhejiang University Ocean Sciences Seed Grant</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>2012HY012B</grantNumber>). The authors wish to thank <individual>Weiming Wu</individual> for his help and discussions on sediment transport modeling over the years.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the respective health bureaus in Ethiopia and Tanzania for their support during the study. We also thank members of the study teams in Tanzania (<individual>Celine Mandara</individual>, <individual>Johari Sadi</individual>, <individual>Rashid Madebe</individual>, <individual>August Nyaki</individual>, <individual>Hatibu Athumani</individual>, <individual>Thomas Semdoe</individual> and <individual>Seth Nguhu</individual>) and Ethiopia (<individual>Diriba Dabushe</individual>, <individual>Tsehay Orlando</individual>, <individual>Tewabech Lemma</individual> and <fundingAgency>Arega Tsegaye</fundingAgency>), health facility staff and all study participants in the respective countries for voluntarily taking part in this study. The master students, <individual>Maria Tusell Rabassa</individual>, <individual>Sabri Kardi</individual>, <individual>Marwa Mani</individual> and <individual>Hadeel Ali</individual> are dully acknowledged for conducting molecular analysis of pfmdr-1 and pfubp-1 variation. Seed funding for the study sites in Ethiopia was obtained from <fundingAgency>Medical Research Council UK-G0600718</fundingAgency>. The molecular studies on all samples were supported by a <fundingAgency>Swedish Research Link Grant</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are deeply grateful to the referee for careful reading and many useful suggestions. We would like to thank <individual>Prof. Kamran Divaani-Aazar</individual> for useful discussions, and also the <fundingAgency>Azarbaijan Shahid Madani University</fundingAgency>, for the financial support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was conducted while <individual>Kouji Urushihara</individual> was visiting SUNY-Binghamton as a research fellow of the <educationalInstitution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science at Osaka Kyoiku University</educationalInstitution>. The work was supported by <fundingAgency>NIMH</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>33881</grantNumber> to Ralph R. Miller, by <fundingAgency>Grant-in-Aid for JSPS Fellows</fundingAgency> to Kouji Urushihara, and by <grantName>Grant-in-Aid for Special Purpose</grantName> from <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan</fundingAgency> to Kouji Urushihara (<grantNumber>19539004</grantNumber>). The authors would like to thank <individual>Eric Curtis</individual>, <individual>Sean Gannon</individual>, <individual>Ryan Green</individual>, <individual>Mario Laborda</individual>, <individual>Bridget McConnell</individual>, <individual>Lisa Ng</individual>, <individual>Heather Sissons</individual>, <individual>Gonzalo P. Urcelay</individual>, and <individual>James Witnauer</individual> for their comments on an earlier version of this manuscript. We also thank <individual>Danielle Beaumont</individual> and <individual>Wan Yui See</individual> for their assistance in running the experiments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by a <grantName>Grant-in-Aid for Innovative Collaborative Research Projects</grantName> and a <grantName>Special Research Grant-in-Aid for the Development of Characteristic Education</grantName> from <fundingAgency>Showa University</fundingAgency>. Funding was also provided by <fundingAgency>JSPS KAKENHI</fundingAgency> (Grant nos. <grantNumber>16591815</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>17591895</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>18591989</grantNumber>, and 20592128).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We sincerely thank <individual>Martin Könemann</individual> for providing us the organic dye. We are grateful of <individual>Marc A. Verschuuren</individual> for the fabrication of the samples.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>21373028</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>National Key Program for Basic Research of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>2015CB251100</grantNumber>), Major achievements <projectName>Transformation Project for Central University in Beijing</projectName> and <projectName>Beijing Science and Technology Project</projectName>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank <individual>William T. Starmer</individual>, <affiliation>Department of Biology, Syracuse University</affiliation>, for his guidance and thoughtful suggestions during the course of this work and for his critical review of this manuscript. We also want to express our appreciation to <individual>Barry Goldman</individual>, <individual>Monsanto Corp</individual>., for his insights regarding the possible data bias and into the lifestyle of many of the 906 bacteria included in this study and his time spent reading the drafts. We would also like to thank <individual>Laura Welch</individual> for her editorial comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are indebted to anonymous referees who helped us to improve this text. The first author is thankful to <otherInstitution>Ministry of Education, Sciences and Technological Development of Serbia</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I would like to thank <individual>Bill Lenhart</individual> who provided the inspiration for Theorem 3. I would also like to thank <individual>David Avis</individual>, <individual>Herbert Edelsbrunner</individual>, and <individual>Meier Katchalski</individual>, who helped in various aspects of writing this paper. Finally, I would like to thank the referees for helping to simplify the proofs in this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors do not have any conflicts of interests to disclose.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish the thank <individual>Dr. Emmanuel Srofenyoh</individual>, <individual>Dr. Adeyemi Olufolabi</individual>, and <individual>Dr. Margaret Sedensky</individual> for their input in the development of Kybele's partnership model and its expansion both within and across boundaries.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Marc de Meyer</individual>, curator of the <affiliation>Entomological Collection of the Royal Museum of Central Africa, Tervuren, Belgium</affiliation> for his kind permission to access material deposited in this collection. To <individual>Dr. Wilfrida Decraemer</individual>, <individual>Dr. Yves Samyn</individual>, <individual>Dr. Marie-Lucie Susini</individual> and <individual>Dr. Alain Drumont</individual> for their assistance during the visit of the senior author to the <researchInstitution>Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences (RBINS), Brussels</researchInstitution>. To <individual>Julien Cillis</individual> (<affiliation>RBINS</affiliation>) for technical help with SEM. To <individual>MSc. Yamir Arias</individual>, <individual>MSc. Eduardo Furrazola</individual> and <individual>Lic. Susett González</individual> (<affiliation>Instituto de Ecología y Sistemática</affiliation>) for their help with the micrographs. To <individual>Dr. Pedro Reyes-Castillo</individual> (<affiliation>Instituto de Ecología, Veracruz, México</affiliation>) and <individual>Dr. Stéphane Boucher</individual> (<affiliation>Museum of Natural History, Paris, France</affiliation>) for the identification of the hosts. We are indebted to <individual>Dr. Pedro Herrera</individual> (<affiliation>Instituto de Ecología y Sistemática</affiliation>) for his review of the English language. The visit to collections in Belgium to access the material and SEM techniques was supported by the <fundingAgency>Belgian Development Cooperation through the Belgian Focal Point of the Global Taxonomy Initiative (GTI)</fundingAgency>, 2010 and 2012 calls. Open access to this paper was supported by the <fundingAgency>Encyclopedia of Life (EOL) Open Access Support Project (EOASP)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This book is the result of 2 years of intensive of work by many individuals and many organizations. Acknowledgment is made to all who have participated in the process. In particular, thanks are due to all the members of the <otherInstitution>Gender Working Group</otherInstitution> (see Appendix A) for their expertise and commitment. Special thanks are extended to <individual>Shirley Malcolm</individual>, <individual>Farkhonda Hassan</individual>, <individual>Sonia Correa</individual>, and <individual>Marilyn Carr</individual> for serving as the informal editorial board for this publication, and to the contributors, who were willing to set aside other intentions and divert their efforts to the work of the <otherInstitution>UN Commission on Science and Technology for Development</otherInstitution>. The work was made possible through generous financial contributions from the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Ministry of Foreign Affairs</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>International Development Research Centre (Canada)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>United States Agency for International Development</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish Agency for Research Cooperation with Developing Countries</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>United Nations Development Fund for Women (UNIFEM)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Carnegie Corporation of New York (USA)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>World Women's Veterinary Association</fundingAgency>, and <individual>Mr William Hewlett</individual>. In addition, the following organizations made substantial nonfinancial contributions in time, and their substantive assistance is deeply appreciated: the <otherInstitution>Gender, Science, and Development Programme of the International Federation of Institutes for Advanced Study</otherInstitution>, the <otherInstitution>Board on Science and Technology for International Development (US National Academy of Sciences)</otherInstitution>, and the <otherInstitution>Third World Organization of Women in Science</otherInstitution>. Thanks are due also to the <otherInstitution>Government of the Netherlands</otherInstitution>, the <otherInstitution>Government of Costa Rica</otherInstitution>, and the <otherInstitution>Inter-American Institute for Cooperation on Agriculture</otherInstitution> for hosting the meetings of the Working Group. The review of the United Nations system was carried out by <otherInstitution>UNIFEM</otherInstitution>, which responded positively and enthusiastically to the Commission's request that it act as the "lead agency" in this review. UNIFEM's contribution, both in conducting the review and in helping to host and organize the initial meeting of the Gender Working Group, is deeply appreciated. Finally, I would like to acknowledge the work of the Secretariat in facilitating all the activities of the Gender Working Group. In particular, I thank <individual>Elizabeth McGregor</individual>, the Director of Studies, for her professional contribution and personal support and enthusiasm throughout the 2-year process.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the Vanguard Project participants and study team members <individual>Mary Lou Miller</individual> and <individual>Arn Schilder</individual>. We also thank <individual>Bonnie Devlin</individual> and <individual>Marcus Greatheart</individual> for administrative support. Drs. Lampinen and Hogg are supported by the <fundingAgency>Michael Smith Foundation for Health Research</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thanks the mothers and the children that participated in these surveys, <individual>Paul Chipeta</individual> and the other <otherInstitution>ACTia</otherInstitution> field staff. We are grateful to <individual>Professor Alan Fenwick</individual>, <fundingAgency>Imperial College London</fundingAgency>, for the purchase and donation of funds for the SEA-ELISA kits. Special thanks go to <individual>Professor Anthony Butterworth</individual> and <individual>Dr. Liz Corbett</individual> for their hospitality and local assistance in Blantyre. We are also grateful for the comments of <individual>Dr. Lester Chitsulo</individual> and <individual>Dr. Amaya Bustinduy</individual> which improved our manuscript, as well as the suggestions from the referees. The study was funded in part from the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust and LSTM Research Development Funding</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Markus M€ uschen</individual> for providing of CML Jurl-MK1 cells, <individual>Dr. Shi-Qi Wu</individual> and <individual>Mr. Michael Lu</individual> for providing assistance in fluorescence microscopy analysis of GFP expression, and <individual>Mr. Jonathan Harbert</individual> for the technical support in HE staining and CD45 immunohistochemistry detection. This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>R01 CA120512</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>ARRA-R01CA120512</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Winzer Fund from Department of Pathology (CHLA/USC</fundingAgency>) to L.W.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This chapter was written in connection with scientific project VEGA no. <grantNumber>1/0892/13</grantNumber>. Financial support from this Ministry of Education's scheme is also gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Office of Basic Energy Sciences, Department of Chemical Sciences, US Department of Energy</fundingAgency>, under contract <grantNumber>W-31-109-ENG-38</grantNumber>. We would like to thank <individual>Dr M. Bowman</individual> for helpful discussion during the course of this work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank <educationalInstitution>King Abdulaziz City for Science and Technology and King Saud University</educationalInstitution> for their support of this work and allowing them to use their equipment and laboratories.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funding to support this study and the preparation of this manuscript was provided by <fundingAgency>Auxilium Pharmaceuticals</fundingAgency>. An Auxilium employee co-authored this paper and was involved in the study design, analysis and interpretation of data, writing of the report, and final approval to submit. The authors thank <individual>Lynanne McGuire, PhD</individual>, of <affiliation>MedVal Scientific Information Services, LLC</affiliation>, for providing medical writing and editorial assistance. This manuscript was prepared according to the <otherInstitution>International Society for Medical Publication Professionals' "Good publication practice</otherInstitution> for communicating companysponsored medical research: the GPP2 Guidelines." Research funding: Auxilium, GlaxoSmithKline. Advisor/ consultant: Abbott, Auxilium, Endo. All authors contributed equally and were involved in study design, data acquisition, or data analysis/interpretation and in drafting and/or critically revising the manuscript. All authors reviewed the final manuscript and gave approval for submission.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Akcnowledgement This work arises from a question addressed by <individual>A. Teta</individual> and has largely profited from useful discussions with <individual>F. Nier</individual>  and <individual>C.A. Pillet</individual> . The author is also indebted to <individual>S. Naboko</individual> and <individual>H. Neidhardt</individual> for their important remarks.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>Dr Takao Shimizu</individual> of <affiliation>Tokyo University</affiliation> for encouraging our study and <individual>Ms Mutsumi Takano</individual> for technical assistance. This work was funded by <grantName>Grants-in-Aid for scientific research</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>21390016</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>23112503</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>23659029</grantNumber> to F.O. and <grantNumber>22791267</grantNumber> to M.K.). This work was also supported by <projectName>Global COE Program</projectName> from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan</fundingAgency> (to M.K.), by the <projectName>joint research program</projectName> of the <fundingAgency>Institute for Molecular and Cellular Regulation, Gunma University</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>10004</grantNumber>) (to F.O. and T.K.), and by <projectName>2010 Japan-Korean joint research project</projectName>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors are grateful to <fundingAgency>ICAR New Delhi</fundingAgency> for providing financial assistance. We also acknowledge the <otherInstitution>Forest, Wild life and Police Departments of Govt. of Jammu and Kashmir</otherInstitution> for their valuable support during field study. Special thanks are due to <individual>Dr. Paul H Williams</individual>, Research Entomologist, <affiliation>BMNH London</affiliation> for confirmation of species identification.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>To the <otherInstitution>National Center of Coffee Researches (CENICAFE, Colombia)</otherInstitution> for supplying the data on infestation of the coffee berry borer. The second and third authors were partially supported by <fundingAgency>CNPq</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are thankful for the staff at the <otherInstitution>NOAA Aircraft Operations Center</otherInstitution> and the <otherInstitution>WP-3D</otherInstitution> flight crew for help in instrumenting the aircraft and for conducting the flights.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Foundation of Henan Polytechnic University for Doctor Teachers</fundingAgency>, and the authors thank <individual>Ms Q. F. Wang</individual> for her support with the single-crystal Xray diffraction data collection. Supplementary data and figures for this paper are available from the IUCr electronic archives (Reference: PV2174).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author is grateful for the financial support and the facilities provided by the <fundingAgency>King Fahd University of Petroleum and Minerals</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledged the cooperation of<otherInstitution>Pakistan Council for Scientific  &amp; Industrial Research (PCSIR), Lahore-Pakistan</otherInstitution> to provide its facilities. We are thankful to <individual>Ms. Farzana Bashir</individual> and <individual>Mr. Rauf Ahmed</individual> for the help during sample analysis.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Lise Hald Schultz</individual> and <individual>Herdis Berg Johansen</individual> for excellent technical assistance. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Nyckelfonden at Örebro University Hospital, Sweden</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Jacqueline Le Grand</individual> for providing help during field sampling, and <individual>Roger Kerouel</individual> and <individual>Philippe Cann</individual> for chemical analyses. We are grateful to the referees and to the editor for their very useful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Funding Acknowledgement: This work was funded by <grantNumber>R00AG035002</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>5R01DK080792</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R00HL098459</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>1R01AG031890</grantNumber>. The Nurses' Health study is supported by <fundingAgency>CA87969</fundingAgency>, <grantNumber>DK58845</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>DK58785</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>NIDDK</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>NICHD of the National Institutes of Health (NIH)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are very grateful to all participants in the study. We also wish to thank the project team members <individual>Maria Cortes</individual>, <individual>António Carlos da Silva</individual>, <individual>Maria do Rosário Horta</individual>, <individual>Mário Carreira</individual>, <individual>Violeta Alarcão</individual>, <individual>Fernanda Silva</individual>, <individual>Miguel Lemos</individual> and <individual>Claúdia Maurício</individual>. The authors wish to acknowledge the valuable feedback and reviews provided by <individual>Prof. Gilles Dussault</individual>. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>[IME/SAUESA/81760/ 2006</grantNumber>].</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>Experimental Psychology Society</fundingAgency> and by a <fundingAgency>European Research Council</fundingAgency> grant (<grantNumber>ERC-2013-StG-336050</grantNumber>)  under the <projectName>FP7</projectName>, both to M.R.L.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Nancy Lea Eik-Nes</individual> for revision of the paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank all our military collaborators from the <otherInstitution>Peruvian Navy</otherInstitution> who played an important role by collecting the data for the analysis. We are indebted to them for their commitment to this project and involvement representing the Peruvian Navy Health Directorate. We thank <individual>Heather Tatum</individual>, <individual>Leilani Thomas</individual>, and <individual>Peter Browning</individual> for excellent specimen management of serum samples at the <researchInstitution>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</researchInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by funding from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> grant [<grantNumber>CA142642-02 2010-2015</grantNumber> to PPC, DKB, APK; <grantNumber>2T32CA009594</grantNumber> to BB]. We thank <individual>Douglas K. Bishop</individual> for helpful conversations.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Sijin Wen acknowledges the support from the <fundingAgency>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>U54GM104942</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We wish to thank <individual>Yiji Xia</individual> for providing xlg2 and xlg3 mutants.  The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank <affiliation>APEC Climate Center, Busan</affiliation>, for providing the necessary facilities to pursue this study. The work was done during the <projectName>YSSP program</projectName> by the first author under the supervision of second author at APEC Climate Center, Busan. The station datasets provided by the <otherInstitution>Sri Lanka Meteorological Department and Mahaweli Authority of Sri Lanka</otherInstitution> are duly acknowledged. This research was also supported by a Grant (<grantNumber>16RDRP-B076564-03</grantNumber>) from regional development research program funded by <fundingAgency>Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport of Korean government</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Science Foundation</fundingAgency> from the <fundingAgency>Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>LQ14H290002</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Zhejiang Provincial Administration of Traditional Chinese Medicine</fundingAgency> (no. <grantNumber>2014ZB012</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>81272472</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Technology Services of Jilin Province Scientific and Technological Project</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>20150414028GH</grantNumber>; <grantNumber>20150520035JH</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>American Heart Association and Miami Heart Research Institute</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>Miss Guri Christiansen</individual> and <individual>Mrs. Michele Lartigot</individual> for their technical assistance and to <individual>Mrs. Elsbeth Scheidegger</individual> for her assistance and care of the marmosets. We thank <individual>Miss Susi Naegeli</individual> for typing the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to <individual>Professor YJ Lee</individual> of <affiliation>Chungbuk National University</affiliation> and <individual>Dr JY Kim</individual> of the <affiliation>Korea Institute of Geosciences and Mineral Resources</affiliation> for their helpful comments and suggestion. Dr Yum acknowledges work <fundingAgency>Korea Research Foundation Grant</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>KRF-2000-042-D00096</grantNumber>) for partial financial support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work is supported in part by <fundingAgency>NASA</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>NNX07AH65G</grantNumber> and the <fundingAgency>Smithsonian Institution</fundingAgency>. This work has made use of the <projectName>NASA/IPAC Extragalactic Database (NED)</projectName> which is operated by the <educationalInstitution>Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology</educationalInstitution>, under contract with the <otherInstitution>National Aeronautics and Space Administration</otherInstitution>. We thank <individual>John ZuHone</individual> and <individual>Ryan Johnson</individual> for helpful discussions. Facilities: <otherInstitution>CXO (ACIS-I, ACIS-S)</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>VLA</otherInstitution></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work has partly been supported by the <fundingAgency>European Commission</fundingAgency> under contract number <grantNumber>H2020-ICT-645403-ROBDREAM</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. The authors thank the <otherInstitution>Space Weather Prediction Center of NOAA</otherInstitution> and <otherInstitution>SIDC</otherInstitution> for providing access to their archived space weather alerts. The MIRACLE network is operated as an international collaboration under the leadership of the <educationalInstitution>Finnish Meteorological Institute</educationalInstitution>. The IMAGE magnetometer data are collected as a joint European collaboration. <otherInstitution>INAF-IAPS (Italy)</otherInstitution> and the <educationalInstitution>University of Oulu (Finland)</educationalInstitution> maintain the ITACA ASCs and the ASC in Sodankylä. <researchInstitution>National Institute on Polar Research (Japan)</researchInstitution> is acknowledged for their service of auroral images which was used in RAF testing. <individual>A. Ketola</individual>, <individual>L. Häkkinen</individual>, <individual>S. Mäkinen</individual>, <individual>P. Posio</individual>, <individual>K. Pajunpää</individual> and <individual>A. Koistinen</individual> (all in FMI Observation Unit) are acknowledged for their persistent and professional work for MIRACLE observations. <individual>P. Janhunen</individual> (FMI) gave valuable advice in the analysis of W/V curves. Edited by: J. Pulliainen</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank the <affiliation>NIH Protein Structure Initiative</affiliation> for generous support of the <projectName>PHENIX project</projectName> (<grantNumber>1P01 GM063210</grantNumber>). This work was supported in part by the <projectName>US Department of Energy under Contract No</projectName>. <grantNumber>DE-AC02-05CH11231</grantNumber>. RJR is supported by a <fundingAgency>Principal Research Fellowship</fundingAgency> from the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust (UK)</fundingAgency>. The authors would like to thank <individual>Gerard Kleywegt</individual> for pointing out the differences between PDB entries 1zen and 1b57 and an anonymous reviewer for unusually extensive and insightful questions and comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments RvM received a scholarship of the <fundingAgency>Technology Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>STW Project 7180</grantNumber>). <individual>Nicola Tien</individual> is acknowledged for many useful comments and stimulating discussions. The comments of two anonymous reviewers was greatly appreciated. Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>A. DeLong</individual>, <individual>R. Offringa</individual>, <individual>J. Friml</individual> and <individual>J. Xu</individual> for providing published materials, and <individual>J. Xu</individual> for helpful comments on this manuscript. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Academic Research Funds</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MOE2009-T2-2-111</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R-154-000-468-112</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R-154-000-598-112</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>R-154-000-506-112</grantNumber>) from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education-Singapore</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Singapore National Research Foundation, under its Competitive Research Programme</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>NRF2010NRF-CRP002-018</grantNumber>), and the intramural resource support from <educationalInstitution>National University of Singapore</educationalInstitution> and <researchInstitution>Temasek Life Sciences Laboratory</researchInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank the <otherInstitution>Senex Energy Ltd</otherInstitution> management team and the <otherInstitution>APPEA Technical Program Committee</otherInstitution> for the opportunity to publish this paper. The authors wish to thank <individual>Alan Sansome</individual> of <affiliation>DMITRE</affiliation> for assistance in the reconnaissance of data, <individual>James Crowley</individual> for technical reviews and support during the writing of this paper, <individual>Michaela Farrow of Schlumberger</individual> for her ongoing assistance, <individual>David Warner</individual> and <individual>Bob Frears</individual> for technical review, <individual>Tony Kennaird</individual> for assistance with core analysis, and <individual>Mark Riley</individual> and <individual>Ian Moffat</individual> of <affiliation>Precipice Training</affiliation> who provided insightful opinions and facilitated numerous interesting discussions during interpretation. The authors also wish to thank previous investigators for documenting the stratigraphic complexity of the Cooper Basin. The views presented in this paper are those of the authors at the time of publication and do not necessarily reflect those of Senex Energy Ltd management.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <researchInstitution>Northwestern University MicroCT</researchInstitution> facility for use of the microCT. We also thank <individual>K. Ignatiev</individual> for expert technical assistance and help with 3D-renderings and the members of the <affiliation>Developmental Systems Biology Core</affiliation> for stimulating discussions. H.G.S. received a Schweppe Career Award.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments Funding for this study was provided by the <fundingAgency>National Insitute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>R01-DA032550</grantNumber>. The original data collection was funded by <grantNumber>R01-DA11796</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>R01-MH57005</grantNumber>. Dr. Johnson's work was supported by <grantNumber>K01-DA31738</grantNumber>. Dr. Matson's work was supported by <grantNumber>K01-DA035387</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank all members of the <educationalInstitution>Department of Molecular Genetics of the Tokyo Medical and Dental University</educationalInstitution> who provided helpful discussion. This study was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan</fundingAgency> (JSPS KAKENHI no. <grantNumber>15598477</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to thank <individual>Doug Robinson</individual> (<affiliation>JMP Life Sciences</affiliation>) for help with array analysis, <individual>Charles Vanderburg</individual> (<affiliation>MGH Department of Neurology</affiliation>) for technical help and <individual>Matthew J Niederst</individual> for providing patient-derived cell lines. This work was supported by <fundingAgency>NIH RO1 CA207186 (DAH)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>HHMI (DAH, MNR)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>National Institute of Health/National Institute of Dental  &amp;  Craniofacial Research</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>K08DE020139 (SMR)</grantNumber> and the <fundingAgency>Burroughs Wellcome Fund (MNR)</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>INRIA FRM</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>ERC-NERVI</fundingAgency> number <grantNumber>227747</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>European Union Project</fundingAgency> # <grantNumber>FP7-269921</grantNumber> (BrainScales), and <fundingAgency>Mathemacs</fundingAgency> # <grantNumber>FP7-ICT-2011.9.7</grantNumber></acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>on May 19, 2008.    Address correspondence to: hershko@tx.technion.ac.il.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors wish to express their appreciation to all study participants on the <otherInstitution>TwinsUK</otherInstitution>, <otherInstitution>KORA</otherInstitution> and <otherInstitution>EGCUT</otherInstitution> studies for donating their blood samples and time.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Drs Ralf Klessen</individual>, <individual>Volker Springel</individual> and <individual>Meng Xiang-Grüß</individual> for making available some of the numerical tools that we used for the calculations presented in this paper. We furthermore thank the referee for his comments on an earlier version of this paper, that significantly improved the quality of the publication.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The research reported herein was supported by the <fundingAgency>Center's Partnership Program</fundingAgency>. The findings and conclusions expressed are solely those of the authors and do not represent the views or policy of the partners or the <researchInstitution>Center for Retirement Research at Boston College</researchInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgment. The authors' would like to express their thanks to the reviewers for helpful suggestions and comments towards the improvement of this paper. The first author M.A. Pathan would like to thank the <fundingAgency>Department of Science and Technology, Government of India</fundingAgency>, for the financial assistance for this work under project number <grantNumber>SR/S4/MS:794/12</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Bei Wei</individual>, and <individual>Drs. Martin Enge</individual>, <individual>Bernhard Schmierer</individual> and <individual>Minna Taipale</individual> for critical review of the manuscript, and <individual>Sandra Augsten</individual>, <individual>Lijuan Hu</individual>, <individual>Anna Zetterlund</individual>, and <individual>Sini Miettinen</individual> for technical assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Preparation of this article was supported by Grants <grantNumber>DA026594</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>National Institute on Drug Abuse</fundingAgency> and <grantNumber>AA021888</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</fundingAgency> to Seth J. Schwartz, and by <fundingAgency>National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences Grant</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>1UL1TR000460</grantNumber> to José Szapocznik. We thank <individual>Maria-Rosa Velazquez</individual>, <individual>Tatiana Clavijo</individual>, <individual>Mercedes Prado</individual>, <individual>Alba Alfonso</individual>, <individual>Aleyda Marcos</individual>, <individual>Daisy Ramirez</individual>, <individual>Lissette Ramirez</individual>, and</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>[23] Acknowledgments. This research is supported by <fundingAgency>NOAA</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>GC01-229</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>ATM0650552</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>ATM0652145</grantNumber> and <fundingAgency>NSFC (National Natural Science Foundation of China)</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>40528006</grantNumber>. The authors thank the valuable comments from <individual>A. Timmerman</individual> and careful editing of the manuscript by <individual>A. Barcilon</individual> and <individual>Diane Henderson</individual>. SOEST contribution XXXX.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Grant <grantNumber>PN-II-RU-RP-2008-4-7</grantNumber> of the <fundingAgency>Romanian MEC</fundingAgency> We thank <individual>J.M. Crolet</individual> for his remarks.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>A100) to the three aforementioned heterodontosaurids (Lycorhinus, Abrictosaurus, Heterodontosaurus) and 37 other ornithischian ingroups in an analysis of 221 characters. Reanalysis of 218 of these characters (3 are uninformative) confirms their result; heterodontosaurids join a basal polytomy at the base of Ornithischia in a strict consensus of the many minimum length trees. Resolution of heterodontosaurid monophyly or relationships among heterodontosaurids was possible only when Echinodon, Lycorhinus and three other poorly known ornithischians (Zephyrosaurus, Talenkauen,  Yandusaurus)  were removed from the analysis  (Fig. 103C ). With these poorly known taxa removed, there are 27 minimum length trees (468 steps) with heterodontosaurid interrelationships resembling that in  Sereno (1986) : "BMNH A100" is more closely related to Heterodontosaurus than Abrictosaurus (Butler et al. 2007: fig. 4, node 4;  Fig.  103C ). In  Sereno (1986)  and the present study, "BMNH A100" is referred to Lycorhinus angustidens, and so the proposed relationships are the same  (Figs 102, 103C) . Pisanosaurus was positioned outside all other ornithischians. The link between "BMNH A100" and Heterodontosaurus, however, is supported by two synapomorphies that have broader distribution among heterodontosaurids. Increase in size of distal premaxillary teeth (Butler et al. 2008: character 114), is present to some degree in both Echinodon  (Fig. 19B)  and Abrictosaurus (Figs 31, 35). "Heterodont dentary dentition" : character 124) is a poorly constructed character that refers in part to the presence of a dentary caniniform tooth in "BMNH A100" and Heterodontosaurus. Echinodon, Lycorhinus and Abrictosaurus were scored as lacking such "heterodonty", although from the information in this study it is clear that Echinodon (Figs 16B, C, 19B)  and Lycorhinus angustidens  (Fig. 3)  clearly have a dentary caniniform tooth and the corresponding dentary crown in Abrictosaurus  (Figs 31, 32)  is not truly primitive in form (i.e., labiolingually compressed, subtriangular).  Zheng et al. (2009)  added Tianyulong to the dataset in , which added one more genus to the heterodontosaurid polytomy. Norman et al. (2011: 59)   also used the dataset in , restricting their reanalysis to "diagnosable heterodontosaurids" and a total of 14 ingroups. Thus they excluded Fruitadens, Lycorhinus, and Tianyulong, leaving three heterodontosaurids in the analysis (Abrictosaurus, "BMNH A100", Heterodontosaurus). Like previous hypotheses  (Sereno 1986; , their resolution positioned "BMNH A100" closer to Heterodontosaurus than Abrictosaurus  (Norman et al. 2011:    fig. 41 ;  Fig. 103E ) on the basis of the weak evidence cited above.  Butler et al. (2010)  added six characters (for a total of 227) and two heterodontosaurids (Tianyulong, Fruitadens) to the previous dataset . They corrected character state scores for Echinodon and ordered a subset of the multistate characters (112, 135, 137, 138, 174). Their reanalysis yielded an unresolved basal</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank <individual>Dr. Jan Löwe</individual> for providing B/r H266 strain, and <individual>Dr. Alexey Melnikov</individual> and <individual>Dr. Pavel Serdobintsev</individual> for their help in the development of the optical set up. The reported study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Russian Science Foundation</fundingAgency>, research project no. <grantNumber>14-34-00023</grantNumber>. The work was carried out using the unique set up "Laser tweezers".</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgment The authors thank <individual>R. J. Toohill</individual> (<affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin, Milwaukee</affiliation>) for reviewing the manuscript. Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are indebted to the participating families, the midwife research assistants (<individual>L Douhaud</individual>, <individual>S Bedel</individual>, <individual>B Lortholary</individual>, <individual>S Gabriel</individual>, <individual>M Rogeon</individual>, and <affiliation>M Malinbaum</affiliation>) for data collection, the psychologists (<individual>Marie-Claire Cona</individual> and <individual>Marielle Paquinet</individual>) and <individual>P Lavoine</individual>, <individual>J Sahuquillo</individual> and <individual>G Debotte</individual> for checking, coding, and data entry. We also thank <individual>S Kern</individual> for providing the</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The study team gratefully acknowledge financial assistance received from the physicians of Ontario through The <fundingAgency>P.S.I. Foundation</fundingAgency> and from <fundingAgency>HealthForceOntario</fundingAgency> (a joint initiative of the <fundingAgency>Ontario Ministry of Health and LongTerm Care</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Ontario Ministry of Training, Colleges and Universities</fundingAgency>). We extend thanks to <individual>Mavis Leong</individual> and <individual>Allan Kostyniuk</individual> for their help with the chart audit, to <individual>Shari Gruman</individual> for formatting the paper, and to the <otherInstitution>IMPACT</otherInstitution> team for contributing to the development of our collaborative model of care for complex elderly patients. Ross Upshur is supported by</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Yasin M. Abul-Huda acknowledges the support of the <fundingAgency>National Defense Science and Engineering (NDSEG) Fellowship</fundingAgency> as well as the <fundingAgency>Rackham Merit Fellowship (RMF)</fundingAgency>. The part of this work conducted at Stanford University was performed under the auspices of the <fundingAgency>Department of Energy-sponsored Predictive Science Alliance Program (PSAAP) at Stanford University</fundingAgency>. The authors would like to thank an anonymous reviewer for inviting us to develop the model of Sec. V further into its current form.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This research was possible due to support from <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (Grant # <grantNumber>2R44DK061164</grantNumber>). The authors would like to thank <individual>Gordon Hirschman</individual> and <individual>Lynn Bardsley</individual> of <affiliation>Infoscitex, Inc for</affiliation> their kind input during the course of this study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors thank patients for their participation and the <fundingAgency>Spanish HIV HGM BioBank</fundingAgency> supported by <fundingAgency>ISC III</fundingAgency> (Grant nu <grantNumber>RD09/0076/00103</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>FIPSE</fundingAgency> and collaborating centres for the clinical samples provided.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</fundingAgency> (<fundingAgency>NIDDK</fundingAgency>) <grantNumber>R01-073944</grantNumber> to BL, from the <fundingAgency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>MOP97858</grantNumber> to MDM, and from <fundingAgency>Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency>  (<grantNumber>81371173</grantNumber>)</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We gratefully acknowledge <fundingAgency>AIRC</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>IG-12085</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Ente Cassa  di Risparmio di Firenze</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MODECRF 130504</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>University of Pisa</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>PRA_2015_0055</grantNumber>) for generous financial support. The authors wish to thank <individual>Maria Agostina Cinellu</individual> of the <affiliation>Department of Chemistry and Pharmacy, University of Sassari</affiliation>, for the gift of a sample of Aubipy c .</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments: We thank the physicians, nurses, and clinical staff at the <otherInstitution>Disease Control and Prevention Center</otherInstitution> for their excellent work.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>1 We discarded two years of data (1982, 1983), as the study authors reported that the control area was sprayed with fenitrothion (a phosphorothioate (organophosphate) insecticide) at the end of 1982. In the South Korean study, Kim and colleagues introduced three slightly different interventions to three rice field plots measuring about 300 m² to 600 m² (Kim 2002). They compared these with a control area of three rice field plots of similar size. They introduced either Tilapia mossambicus and Aplocheilus latipes (treatment A) or Aphyocypris chinensis and Tilapia mossambicus (treatment B and treatment</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Authors appreciate technical support by <individual>Yu Sub Sung, PhD</individual> at the <affiliation>Biomedical Imaging Infrastructure in the Department of Radiology, Asan Medical Center</affiliation>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Drs Harry Rozmiarek</individual> and <individual>John Cebra</individual> for valuable support and advice. Dr Cebra's untimely death while this manuscript was in review has saddened all of us, and will surely have a negative impact on the field of gnotobiology. This study was supported by <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health Grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>DK 55852</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>P30-DK 50306</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>RR12211</grantNumber>; we thank the <otherInstitution>Morphology Core in the Center for Digestive and Liver Disease</otherInstitution> for histological preparations.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>In this research, JPG was supported by <fundingAgency>EPSRC</fundingAgency> under Grant No. <grantNumber>GR/S54074/01</grantNumber>. DK was supported initially by the <fundingAgency>Director, Office of Science, Office of Basic Energy Sciences, Chemical Sciences, Geosciences, and Biosciences Division, U.S. Department of Energy</fundingAgency>, under Contract No. <grantNumber>DE-AC02-05CH11231</grantNumber>. RLJ and DC were supported initially by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>CHE-0543158</grantNumber> and later by <fundingAgency>Office of Naval Research</fundingAgency> Grant No. <grantNumber>N00014-07-1-0689</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. This work was jointly supported by the <fundingAgency>Na- Topical Editor C</fundingAgency>. Jacobi thanks two anonymous referees for their help in evaluating this paper.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank the reviewers for their comments and suggestions which helped improve the presentation and readability of the paper. The ®rst author is grateful for the time provided by <otherInstitution>General Motors Corporation</otherInstitution> for the work on revising the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The goal of this study is to elucidate the prehistory of populations as reflected in their genetic variation. It does not intend to evaluate the self-identification or cultural identity of any group, which consist of more than simply genetic ancestry. We sincerely thank all the donors of genetic samples for their participation in this investigation, <individual>Rem Sukernik</individual> and <individual>Dejan Matić</individual> for assistance with sample collection, <individual>Mark Stoneking</individual> for helpful discussion, <individual>Torsten Blass</individual> and <individual>Gabriel Renaud</individual> for assistance with R and the haplotype sharing analysis, and two anonymous reviewers for comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to thank all lab staff who performed mouse breeding and biochemical analyses at <educationalInstitution>AstraZeneca and the University of Cambridge</educationalInstitution> for this project. We wish to thank <individual>Jane Lö</individual> fvenmark for invaluable help during the early stages of the project. We would like to thank the animal care staff at the institutions involved for their work on this project. We also thank <individual>Ian McFarlane</individual>, <individual>Lyn Carter</individual> and <individual>Jeremy Skepper</individual> for providing technical help. Funding. The work presented in this paper was supported by</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The financial support from the <fundingAgency>Grant Agency of the Czech Academy of Sciences</fundingAgency> (grant no. <grantNumber>GA AV IAAA401990701</grantNumber>) is greatly acknowledged. The authors also wish to express their thanks to <individual>Anna Vasatkova</individual> and <individual>Vaclav Diopan</individual> for excellent technical assistance and to <individual>Veronika Kohoutkova</individual> for the English corrections.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was partially supported by <fundingAgency>PRONEX/FAPESQ-PB, CNPq and CAPES (PROCAD)</fundingAgency>. We are indebted to <individual>Prof. Mark Alford</individual> for his comments on reference  [22]  and for pointing out to us reference  [8] .</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The author thanks <individual>Akihiro Munemasa</individual> and <individual>Etsuko Bannai</individual> for the collaborations on some of the materials presented in this paper. The author thanks <individual>Tbshitake Kohno</individual> for introducing and explaining to the author about fusion algebras and conformal field theory. The author also thanks <individual>Mitsuhiro Kato</individual> and <individual>Yasuhiko Yamada</individual> for the valuable discussions while the author visited High Energy Physics Laboratory at Tsukuba in February 1991.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would like to warmly thank <individual>Dr. Brigitte McGregor</individual> for her assistance with the immunohistochemistry. S.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>It is a pleasure to thank <individual>A. Athenodorou</individual>, <individual>E. Bennett</individual>, <individual>G. Bergner</individual>, <individual>F. Bursa</individual>, <individual>L. Del Debbio</individual>, <individual>D. Henty</individual>, <individual>E. Kerrane</individual>, <individual>A. Patella</individual>, <individual>T. Pickup</individual>, <individual>C. Pica</individual>, <individual>A. Rago</individual>, <individual>E. Rinaldi</individual>, <individual>R. Sabin</individual> for their valuable contributions to the collaborations on which this work is based. Numerical computations were executed in part on the Blue Gene/P machine in <educationalInstitution>Swansea University</educationalInstitution> and the ULGQCD cluster in the <educationalInstitution>University of Liverpool</educationalInstitution> (part of the DiRAC facility supported by <otherInstitution>STFC</otherInstitution>), on the HPC Wales cluster in Cardiff, supported by the <otherInstitution>ERDF</otherInstitution> through the WEFO (part of the Welsh Government), on the BlueGene/Q system at the Hartree Centre (supported by STFC) and on the BlueGene/Q system at the <educationalInstitution>University of Edinburgh</educationalInstitution> (part of the DiRAC2 facility supported by STFC). This work has been supported by <fundingAgency>STFC</fundingAgency> (grant <grantNumber>ST/G000506/1</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank all the anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments and suggestions which have helped improve this paper. We would also thank the <otherInstitution>Editors and the Editorial Office</otherInstitution> for their diligence.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank <individual>Dr. Stephen Gunther</individual> and <individual>Thomas Kontry</individual> for providing us with [ 125 I]iodoANP. The excellent technical support of <individual>Margaret Gosselin</individual>, <individual>Nancy Pazdziorko</individual>, and <individual>Greg Hodder</individual> is deeply appreciated. We also thank <individual>Ms. Doris King</individual> and <individual>Virginia King</individual> for preparing the manuscript.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements Supported by the <fundingAgency>US Public Health Service</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>DK067287</grantNumber> to JMC), the <fundingAgency>UCSD Digestive Diseases Research Development Center</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>DK080506</grantNumber>), and the <fundingAgency>San Diego State University/UCSD Comprehensive Cancer Center Partnership</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>CA132379</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>CA13238</grantNumber>). Disclosure All authors declare no conflict or competing interest for this manuscript. Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Pró-Reitoria de Pesquisa of Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais</fundingAgency> which provided financial aid to the translation of this manuscript into English language.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This paper was supported by the <fundingAgency>Israel Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (Grant <grantNumber>159/10</grantNumber> awarded to Ram Frost), by a <fundingAgency>Marie Curie IIF fellowship</fundingAgency> awarded to <individual>Blair Armstrong</individual> (<grantNumber>PIIF-GA-2013-627784</grantNumber>), and by the <fundingAgency>NICHD</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>RO1 HD 067364</grantNumber> awarded to Ken Pugh and Ram Frost, and <grantNumber>PO1 HD 01994</grantNumber> awarded to Haskins Laboratories).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements We thank <individual>Mr. Alberto Parisi</individual> for technical support.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We thank the DESY directorate for their strong support and encouragement. The remarkable achievements of the HERA machine group were essential for the successful completion of this work and are gratefully acknowledged. We also thank <individual>G. Kramer</individual> for useful discussions and <individual>B. Pötter</individual> for providing the JetViP calculation.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Jacobi, Eugen 967A Jacobs, Gertrud 838, 839A Jacobson, Ludwig 909A Jäckh, Ernst 615, 1073 Jaeger, Fritz 276, 364, 731 Jagemann, Eugen von 601A Jaschke, Rudolf Theodor von 725A Jaspers, Gertrud 636A Jaspers, Karl 636A Jastrow, Ignaz 195, 196A, 280, 414</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This project was funded by <fundingAgency>Horticulture Australia Limited in partnership with AusVeg</fundingAgency> (project number <grantNumber>VG07126</grantNumber>; program 2AE1) and <fundingAgency>USDA-ARS CRIS Project</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>5358-21000-035-00</grantNumber>. We gratefully acknowledge the bean growers and processors who allowed access to their fields for sampling. Travel of Dr Gent to Australia was also partially funded by the <fundingAgency>University of Tasmania's Visiting Scholar Program</fundingAgency>. Thanks are also extended to <individual>Craig Palmer</individual>, <individual>Stacey Pilkington</individual>, <individual>Dr Jason Scott</individual>, <individual>Thomas O'Malley</individual>, <individual>Phillip Beveridge</individual>, <individual>Gordon Tuck</individual>, and <individual>Phil Gardam</individual>, <educationalInstitution>University of Tasmania</educationalInstitution>, for excellent technical assistance.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Fundação Araucária (FA)</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento do Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES)</fundingAgency>. The sponsors had no involvement in the study design, collection, analysis and interpretation of data, writing or revision of the report or in the decision of publishing. The authors would like to express their gratitude for the technical assistance of <individual>Aparecida Pinto Munhos Hermoso</individual>, <individual>Célia Akemi Gasparetto</individual>, <individual>Irene Aparecida Bernardino</individual>, and <individual>Luiz Saraiva Arraes</individual>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>[22] Acknowledgments. We wish to thank the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> for financial support to R. Dugdale and F. Wilkerson (<fundingAgency>JGOFS-Synthesis and Modeling Program (SMP)</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>OCE-01354430</grantNumber>), F. Chai (<grantNumber>SMP OCE-137272</grantNumber>), and M. Lyle (<grantNumber>OCE-9811272</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>EPS 0132626</grantNumber>). We would like to dedicate this paper to <individual>Jack Dymond</individual>, a close friend and colleague. His insights into biogeochemical cycling will be missed by us all. This is US JGOFS contribution 1048.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I would like to thank the two anonymous reviewers for their comments and suggestions, as well as the <fundingAgency>DZ Bank Stiftung</fundingAgency> for the financial support during the study.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> funds through a supplement (LMF) to IMPAACT (<grantNumber>U01 AI068632</grantNumber>), a <fundingAgency>fellowship (SCO) award</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>T32 HD07233</grantNumber>), the 1032 study team in Chiang Mai (<grantNumber>U01 AI41089</grantNumber> The authors would like to thank <individual>Rob Hall</individual> for his assistance in pyrosequencing subject samples at the <researchInstitution>Bumgarner laboratory</researchInstitution>. )</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present study is supported as a <fundingAgency>National Science and Technology Major Project</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>2013ZX10005002</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We would like to thank <individual>Dr. Craig McGowan</individual> for the use of his equipment and ProAnalyst license in order to track the videos used in this experiment.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We are grateful to <individual>Eric Jensen</individual> for his technical assistance, to <individual>Dr. Carolyn Kerr</individual> for carrying out the anesthesia, and to <individual>Dr. Gary Bouck</individual> for performing the surgeries. <otherInstitution>Thames Valley Veterinary Services</otherInstitution>, in particular <individual>Jackie Taylor</individual> and <individual>Cathy Cavanagh</individual>, provided additional animal care. We also thank the referring veterinarians and owners of the volunteer pets. We are indebted to <individual>Dr. Raoul Pereira</individual>, <individual>Dr. Charles McKenzie</individual>, and <individual>Dr. Frank Prato</individual> for their many valuable suggestions involving the MR protocol. Image analysis was performed using the Xstatpak program developed by <individual>J. Davis</individual>. Contrast agents were provided by <otherInstitution>Schering AG</otherInstitution>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>We acknowledge the financial support of Széchenyi 2020 under the <grantNumber>EFOP-3.6.1-16-2016-00015</grantNumber>. Author Contributions: >Gábor Pintér and Henrik Zsiborács wrote the paper and did the calculations. Gábor Pintér was responsible for the economic aspects, while Henrik Zsiborács focused on technology. Nóra Hegedűsné Baranyai helped with the calculation process and she created the graphs and tables in the paper. Alec Wiliams looked into the international context of the subject and revised the grammar.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>I would like to express my gratitude to <individual>Prof. F.W.Hehl</individual>, <individual>P.S.Letelier</individual> and <individual>A.Wang</individual> for helpful discussions on the subject of this paper. Financial support from <fundingAgency>UERJ</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>CNPq</fundingAgency>. is gratefully acknowledged.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Kakenhi</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>15H05569</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>15H01417</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Life Science Foundation of Japan</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Inoue Foundation</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>Public Health Research Foundation</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgements. -The authors thank <individual>Dr. Bogdan Kralj</individual> of the <affiliation>Mass Spectrometry Centre at Jozef Stefan Institute (Ljubljana)</affiliation> and <individual>Janez Plavec</individual> of the <affiliation>Slovenian National NMR Centre</affiliation>. This investigation was supported by the <otherInstitution>Ministry of Science and Technology of Slovenia</otherInstitution> (<projectName>P-0515</projectName>) and <projectName>COST-D8 Programme</projectName>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The experimental results presented in the paper were obtained in the framework of the <projectName>TRE3 research project</projectName>, funded by the <fundingAgency>Fondazione CARITRO -Cassa di Risparmio di Trento e Rovereto (Trento, Italy)</fundingAgency>. The industrial partners X-<individual>Lam Dolomiti</individual> (<affiliation>Castel Ivano, Italy</affiliation>) and <fundingAgency>Rothoblaas (Cortaccia, Italy</fundingAgency>) are gratefully acknowledged for providing the materials used in the tests. <individual>Mario Pinna</individual> and <individual>Diego Magnago</individual> are gratefully acknowledged for preparation and running all the tests. Further acknowledgements are extended to <individual>Dr. Tiziano Sartori</individual>, who provided some useful remark on typical light-timber frame wall systems.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This work was supported, in part, by a grant from the <fundingAgency>NIH/ NIMH</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MH095325</grantNumber>, K.S. and H.M.L., Multiple PI).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors would express their gratitude to <individual>Professor Keiichi Noguchi</individual> for technical advice. This work was partially supported by the <fundingAgency>Mukai Science and Technology Foundation, Tokyo, Japan</fundingAgency>.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments. We are grateful to <individual>C. Johnson</individual> for sending us an early version of [J]  and to <individual>D. Nakano</individual> for helpful conversations. We also thank the referee for helpful comments.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The authors acknowledge expert advice and contributions from <individual>Chris Westlake</individual>, <individual>Guowei Fang</individual>, <individual>Ben Chih</individual>, <individual>Andy Peterson</individual>, <individual>Cecile Chalouni</individual>, <individual>John S. Beck</individual>, <individual>Darryl Y. Nishimura</individual>, <individual>Charles C. Searby</individual>, <individual>Martin Griebel</individual>, <individual>John Neveu</individual>, <individual>Bogdan Budnik</individual>, <individual>Renee Robinson</individual>, <individual>Alex Loktev</individual>, <individual>Jorge Torres</individual>, <individual>Saikat Mukhopadhyay</individual>, <individual>Dirk Siepe</individual> and <individual>Kevin Wright</individual>. We acknowledge the following support: <fundingAgency>JJM</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NIH Medical Scientist Training Program</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>GM07365-33</grantNumber>; <fundingAgency>RHG</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research VIDI</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>016.066.354</grantNumber> and the <fundingAgency>EU FP7 "Syscilia"</fundingAgency> project 241955; <fundingAgency>LMB</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Cardiovascular Center Interdisciplinary Research Fellowship, University of Iowa</fundingAgency>; <fundingAgency>JFO</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NIH grant</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>DK071108</grantNumber>; <fundingAgency>DCS</fundingAgency>, NIH Grant <grantNumber>CA112369</grantNumber>; <fundingAgency>J.B.V.,</fundingAgency> <fundingAgency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>MOP-102758</grantNumber>; <fundingAgency>DAD</fundingAgency>, <grantNumber>KL2RR025015</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>R01NS064077</grantNumber>; <fundingAgency>J.F.R., NIH Grant</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>R01-AR054396</grantNumber>, the <fundingAgency>March of Dimes</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Burroughs Wellcome Fund</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Packard Foundation</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>Sandler Family Supporting Foundation</fundingAgency>; <fundingAgency>VCS</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>NIH Grants</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>R01-EY11298</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R01-EY017168</grantNumber>, the <fundingAgency>Roy J. Carver Charitable Trust</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Carver Endowment for Molecular Ophthalmology</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Research to Prevent Blindness</fundingAgency>. VCS is an HHMI investigator. FH is an HHMI Investigator, a Doris Duke Distinguished Clinical Scientist, and a Frederick G. L. Huetwell Professor. FH acknowledges support from the <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grants (<grantNumber>DK1068306</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>DK1069274</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>DK090917</grantNumber>).</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>This study was funded by grant <grantNumber>1 R21 HD068736-01</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</fundingAgency>, a component of the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</fundingAgency>. Additional support came from <fundingAgency>NICHD award</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>K01 HD075834</grantNumber>. The content of this publication is the responsibility solely of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of NICHD or NIH.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Conceived and designed the experiments: <fundingAgency>CI CO ET</fundingAgency>. Performed the experiments: <projectName>CI AL GT ON ES SB CO ET</projectName>. Analyzed the data: <fundingAgency>CI AL CO ET. Contributed</fundingAgency> to the writing of the manuscript: CI CO ET.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>The present article was extracted from proposal No. 92-01-21-6745 approved by the <educationalInstitution>Student Research Committee of Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran</educationalInstitution>. Thanks also go to the farmers who sincerely cooperated during the project.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Writing assistance was provided by <individual>Anna Abt, Ph.D.</individual>, of <affiliation>ETHOS Health Communications in Yardley, Pennsylvania</affiliation>, and was supported financially by <fundingAgency>Novo Nordisk Inc., Plainsboro, New Jersey</fundingAgency>, in compliance with international Good Publication Practice guidelines.</acknowledgment>
        <acknowledgment>Acknowledgments This work is supported by the <fundingAgency>Dutch Technology Foundation STW</fundingAgency> under the <projectName>VIDI-Innovation Impulse program</projectName>, grant <grantNumber>DLR.6198</grantNumber>.</acknowledgment>
    </acknowledgments>
</TEI>