<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Sharing of Very Short IBD Segments between <lb/>Humans, Neandertals, and Denisovans <lb/>Gundula Povysil and Sepp Hochreiter <lb/>Institute of Bioinformatics, Johannes Kepler University, Linz, Austria <lb/>Institute of Bioinformatics, Johannes Kepler University Linz <lb/>Research Report <lb/>Institute of Bioinformatics <lb/>Johannes Kepler University Linz <lb/>A-4040 Linz, Austria <lb/>Tel. +43 732 2468 4520 <lb/>Fax +43 732 2468 4539 <lb/>http://www.bioinf.jku.at <lb/> 2 <lb/> Abstract <lb/>Abstract <lb/>We analyze the sharing of very short identity by descent (IBD) segments between humans, <lb/>Neandertals, and Denisovans to gain new insights into their demographic history. Short IBD <lb/>segments convey information about events far back in time because the shorter IBD segments are, <lb/>the older they are assumed to be. The identification of short IBD segments becomes possible <lb/>through next generation sequencing (NGS), which offers high variant density and reports variants <lb/>of all frequencies. However, only recently HapFABIA has been proposed as the first method for <lb/>detecting very short IBD segments in NGS data. HapFABIA utilizes rare variants to identify IBD <lb/>segments with a low false discovery rate. <lb/>We applied HapFABIA to the 1000 Genomes Project whole genome sequencing data to <lb/>identify IBD segments which are shared within and between populations. Some IBD segments are <lb/>shared with the reconstructed ancestral genome of humans and other primates. These segments are <lb/>tagged by rare variants, consequently some rare variants have to be very old. Other IBD segments <lb/>are also old since they are shared with Neandertals or Denisovans, which explains their shorter <lb/>lengths compared to segments that are not shared with these ancient genomes. The Denisova <lb/>genome most prominently matched IBD segments that are shared by Asians. Many of these seg-<lb/>ments were found exclusively in Asians and they are longer than segments shared between other <lb/>continental populations and the Denisova genome. Therefore, we could confirm an introgression <lb/>from Deniosvans into ancestors of Asians after their migration out of Africa. While Neandertal-<lb/>matching IBD segments are most often shared by Asians, Europeans share a considerably higher <lb/>percentage of IBD segments with Neandertals compared to other populations, too. Again, many <lb/>of these Neandertal-matching IBD segments are found exclusively in Asians, whereas Neandertal-<lb/>matching IBD segments that are shared by Europeans are often found in other populations, too. <lb/>Neandertal-matching IBD segments that are shared by Asians or Europeans are longer than those <lb/>observed in Africans. This hints at a gene flow from Neandertals into ancestors of Asians and <lb/>Europeans after they left Africa. Interestingly, many Neandertal-or Denisova-matching IBD seg-<lb/>ments are predominantly observed in Africans -some of them even exclusively. IBD segments <lb/>shared between Africans and Neandertals or Denisovans are strikingly short, therefore we assume <lb/>that they are very old. This may indicate that these segments stem from ancestors of humans, <lb/>Neandertals, and Denisovans and have survived in Africans. <lb/>Note: We present preliminary results on chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes Project. This <lb/>preprint will be soon completed with results from the other chromosomes. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Contents <lb/></note>

			<div type="toc">Contents <lb/>1 Introduction . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>1.1 IBD for Inferring Population Structure . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>1.2 HapFABIA for Extracting Short IBD Segments . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>2 IBD Segments on Chr. 1 of the 1000 Genomes Data . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>2.1 The 1000 Genomes Data . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>2.2 Summary Statistics of the Detected Short IBD Segments . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes . . . . . . <lb/>3.1 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Human Populations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.1.1 Sharing Between All Human Populations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.1.2 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Continental Populations . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.2 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Human and Ancient Genomes . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.2.1 IBD Sharing Between Human Populations and Ancient Genomes . . . . . <lb/>3.2.2 Densities of Population Proportions and Ancient Genomes . . . . . . . . . <lb/>4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>4.1 Relating the IBD Length to Years from Present . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>4.1.1 Exponential Distributed IBD Lengths . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>4.1.2 Correction for the Assumptions of IBD Length Distributions . . . . . . . . <lb/>4.1.3 Length Correction for IBD with Ancient Genomes . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>4.2 Histograms of Lengths of IBD Segments for the Different Genomes . . . . . . . . <lb/>4.3 IBD Segment Lengths of Human Populations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>4.4 Lengths of IBD Segments that Match the Denisova or Neandertal Genome . . . . <lb/>4.4.1 Lengths of IBD Segments that Match the Denisova Genome . . . . . . . . <lb/>4.4.2 Lengths of IBD Segments that Match the Neandertal Genome . . . . . . . <lb/>4.4.3 Lengths of IBD Segments that Match Neandertal &amp; Denisova . . . . . . . <lb/>5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>6 Conclusion . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>A Are Rare Variants Recent or Old? . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>B Population Groups of the 1000 Genomes Project . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/></div>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">1 Introduction <lb/></note>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The recent advent of next generation sequencing technologies made whole genome sequencing <lb/>of thousands of individuals feasible (47). These sequencing techniques have been extended to <lb/>allow sequencing of ancient DNA which enabled researchers to assemble the DNA of hominid <lb/>individuals that lived ten thousands of years ago (15, 31, 35, 37). These advances in biotechnology <lb/>could help to answer one of the most fundamental questions of humanity: &quot;Where do we come <lb/>from?&quot; <lb/>In 2012, the 1000 Genomes Project Consortium (48) published first results on the genomes of <lb/>more than thousand individuals from 14 populations stemming from Europe, East Asia, Africa, <lb/>and the Americas. Reviewing the differences in genetic variation within and between populations, <lb/>the authors found evidence of past events such as bottlenecks or admixtures, but also regions <lb/>which seemed to be under a strong selective pressure. Gravel et al. (14) used the sequence data <lb/>of the individuals from the Americas of the 1000 Genomes Project to quantify the contributions <lb/>of European, African, and Native American ancestry to these populations, to estimate migration <lb/>rates and timings, as well as to develop a demographic model. <lb/>Green et al. (15) were the first to analyze a draft sequence of the Neandertal genome derived <lb/>from the bones of three individuals from Vindija Cave in Croatia that died about 40,000 years <lb/>ago. They found that non-African individuals share more alleles with the Neandertal genome <lb/>than sub-Saharan Africans. Until then evidence from mtDNA (9, 25, 42) and the Y chromosome <lb/>(24) suggested that Neandertals lived isolated in Europe and Asia until they were replaced by <lb/>anatomically modern humans. Although this theory still holds if differences in allele sharing are <lb/>attributed to the existence of an ancient population substructure within Africa (10, 29), ancient <lb/>admixture events between Neandertals and anatomically modern humans outside of Africa are <lb/>considered as a more plausible explanation (15, 28, 40, 56). Further studies (31, 55) reported more <lb/>Neandertal DNA preserved in modern East Asians than Europeans, hinting at some admixture after <lb/>the separation of ancestors of Europeans and Asians. Prüfer et al. (35) confirmed higher rates of <lb/>sharing for non-Africans using a high-quality genome sequence of a Neandertal from Denisova <lb/>Cave in the Altai Mountains of Siberia. The authors further report that populations in Asia and <lb/>America have more regions of Neandertal origin than populations in Europe. <lb/>A bone of a sister group of Neandertals, named Denisovans after the cave in the Altai Moun-<lb/>tains of Siberia, was sequenced first at low (37) and later at high coverage (31). Studies on <lb/>the low coverage draft sequence, as well as on the high coverage sequence, reported contribu-<lb/>tions from Denisovans to the gene pool of present-day individuals in Southeast Asia and Oceania <lb/>(31, 37, 38, 43). Additionally to the clear signal of the Denisova genome found in Oceanians, <lb/>Prüfer et al. (35) detected some regions of Denisovan origin in East and Southeast Asians and <lb/>also in populations of the Americas, but only very few in Europeans. The authors further report <lb/>gene flow from Neandertals and an unknown archaic population into Denisovans indicating that <lb/>interbreeding among distinct hominid populations was more common than previously thought. <lb/> Using the high coverage Altai Neandertal genome Sankararaman et al. (39) screened the 1000 <lb/>Genomes Project data for Neandertal ancestry with the genomes of the West African Yoruba <lb/>individuals from Ibadan, Nigeria, as a reference panel that are assumed to harbor no Neandertal <lb/>ancestry. They again found more Neandertal ancestry in East-Asians than in Europeans, but also <lb/>very low levels in African Luhya individuals from Webuye, Kenya. The authors further looked for <lb/>regions in the genome with very high or very low Neandertal ancestry that both might be due to <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">1 Introduction <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>selective pressure. Vernot and Akey (53) searched for signatures of introgression in the sequences <lb/>of Asian and European individuals of the 1000 Genomes Project and compared them with the <lb/>Altai Neandertal genome. They confirmed more Neandertal DNA in East Asians than Europeans <lb/>and looked for different levels of introgression along the genome. <lb/>In this study we propose to use short segments of identity by descent (IBD) to infer the popula-<lb/>tion structure of humans and to gain insights into the genetic relationship of humans, Neandertals <lb/>and Denisovans. <lb/>1.1 IBD for Inferring Population Structure <lb/>A DNA segment is identical by state (IBS) in two or more individuals if they all have identical <lb/>nucleotide sequences in this segment. An IBS segment is identical by descent (IBD) in two or <lb/>more individuals if they have inherited it from a common ancestor, that is, the segment has the <lb/>same ancestral origin in these individuals. Rare variants can be utilized for distinguishing IBD <lb/>from IBS without IBD because independent origins are highly unlikely for such variants. In other <lb/>words, IBS generally implies IBD for rare variants, which is not true for common variants (44, <lb/>Ch. 15.3, p. 441). <lb/>IBD detection methods have already been successfully used for inferring population structure. <lb/>Gusev et al. (16) looked for long IBD segments shared within and between populations to estimate <lb/>the demographic history of Ashkenazi Jewish individuals. Using similar models Palamara et al. <lb/>(34) and Carmi et al. (7) reconstructed the demographic history of Ashkenazi Jewish and Kenyan <lb/>Maasai individuals. Botigué et al. (3) confirmed gene flow from North Africans into Southern <lb/>Europeans via patterns of long shared IBD segments. Ralph and Coop (36) tried to quantify the <lb/>recent shared ancestry of different European populations by looking for long segments of shared <lb/>DNA. Gravel et al. (14) similarly tried to draw conclusions of the genetic history of populations <lb/>in the Americas using the respective data of the 1000 Genomes Project. <lb/>Except for Gravel et al. all of these studies were performed on SNP microarray data as IBD <lb/>segments could not reliably be detected in large sequencing data. Sequencing data has higher <lb/>marker density and also captures rare variants in contrast to SNP microarray data, therefore they <lb/>would allow for a finer resolution of the length of IBD segments. Furthermore all previous studies <lb/>based on microarrays were limited to long IBD segments that stem from a very recent common <lb/>ancestor. However, shorter IBD segments would convey information about events farther back in <lb/>time because the shorter IBD segments are, the older they are assumed to be. Therefore, existing <lb/>studies were not able to resolve demographic histories at a fine scale and very far back into the <lb/>past. <lb/>1.2 HapFABIA for Extracting Short IBD Segments <lb/>We recently developed HapFABIA (19) (see http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkt1013 ) to <lb/>identify very short segments of identity by descent (IBD) that are tagged by rare variants (the so <lb/>called tagSNVs) in large sequencing data. HapFABIA identifies 100 times smaller IBD segments <lb/>than current state-of-the-art methods: 10 kbp for HapFABIA vs. 1 Mbp for state-of-the-art <lb/>methods. HapFABIA utilizes rare variants (≤5% MAF) to distinguish IBD from IBS without IBD <lb/>because independent origins of rare minor alleles are highly unlikely (44, Ch. 15.3,p. 441). More <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">1 Introduction <lb/></note>

			<body>importantly, rare variants make juxtapositions of smaller IBD segments unlikely which prevents <lb/>the summary of several small IBD segment into one long IBD segment. Consequently, the length <lb/>of IBD segments is estimated more accurately than with previous methods. <lb/>In experiments with artificial, simulated, and real genotyping data HapFABIA outperformed <lb/>its competitors in detecting short IBD segments (19). HapFABIA is based on biclustering (20) <lb/>which in turn uses machine learning techniques derived from maximizing the posterior in a Bayes <lb/>framework (8, 21, 22, 23, 30, 41, 45, 46). <lb/>HapFABIA is designed to detect short IBD segments in genotype data that were obtained from <lb/>next generation sequencing (NGS), but can also be applied to DNA microarray data. Especially <lb/>in NGS data, HapFABIA exploits rare variants for IBD detection. Rare variants convey more <lb/>information on IBD than common variants, because random minor allele sharing is less likely <lb/>for rare variants than for common variants (5). In order to detect short IBD segments, both the <lb/>information supplied by rare variants and the information from IBD segments that are shared <lb/>by more than two individuals should be utilized (5). HapFABIA uses both. The probability of <lb/>randomly sharing a segment depends <lb/>(a) on the allele frequencies within the segment, where lower frequency means lower prob-<lb/>ability of random sharing, and <lb/>(b) on the number of individuals that share the allele, where more individuals result in lower <lb/>probability of random segment sharing. <lb/>The shorter the IBD segments, the higher the likelihood that they are shared by more individuals. <lb/>A segment that contains rare variants and is shared by more individuals has higher probability <lb/>of representing IBD (18, 27). These two characteristics are our basis for detecting short IBD <lb/>segments by HapFABIA. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">2 IBD Segments on Chr. 1 of the 1000 Genomes Data <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>2 IBD Segments on Chr. 1 of the 1000 Genomes Data <lb/>2.1 The 1000 Genomes Data <lb/>We used HapFABIA to extract short IBD segments from the 1000 Genomes Project genotyping <lb/>data (48), more specifically, the phase 1 integrated variant call set (version 3) containing phased <lb/>genotype calls for SNVs, short indels, and large deletions. This data set consists of 1,092 individu-<lb/>als (246 Africans, 181 Admixed Americans, 286 East Asians, and 379 Europeans), 38.2M SNVs, <lb/>2.4M short indels, and 14k large deletions. We removed 36 individuals because they showed <lb/>cryptic relatedness to others. The final data set consisted of 1056 individuals (228 Africans, 175 <lb/>Admixed Americans, 277 East Asians, and 376 Europeans). Chromosome 1 contains 3,007,196 <lb/>SNVs that are on average 83 bp apart and have an average minor allele frequency (MAF) of 0.066. <lb/>2,280,175 (75.8%) SNVs are rare (MAF ≤ 0.05 including privates), 664,225 (22.1%) are private <lb/>(minor allele is observed only once), 33,100 (1.1%) have an MAF of zero, and 693,921 (23.1%) <lb/>are common (MAF &gt; 0.05). We kept only the rare SNVs for IBD detection and excluded private <lb/>ones. <lb/>Chromosome 1 was divided into intervals of 10,000 SNVs with adjacent intervals overlapping <lb/>by 5,000 SNVs. After removing common and private SNVs, we applied HapFABIA with default <lb/>parameters to these intervals ignoring phase information since previous analysis revealed many <lb/>phasing errors. <lb/>2.2 Summary Statistics of the Detected Short IBD Segments <lb/>HapFABIA found 105,652 different very short IBD segments on chromosome 1. These contained <lb/>635,280 rare tagSNVs, which amounts to 27.9% of the rare variants (39.3% if private SNVs are <lb/>excluded) and 21% of all SNVs. The distance between centers of IBD segments had a median of <lb/>1.1 kbp and a mean of 2.4 kbp and ranged from 0 (overlapping IBD segments) to several Mbp. The <lb/>number of individuals that shared the same IBD segment was between 2 and 113, with a median <lb/>of 5 and a mean of 10.7. IBD segments were tagged by 8 to 223 tagSNVs, with a median of 13 <lb/>and a mean of 18.8. The length of IBD segments ranged from 62 base pairs to 21 Mbp, with a <lb/>median of 25 kbp and a mean of 27 kbp. IBD lengths are computed as described in Section 4.1, to <lb/>match the assumptions for the distribution of IBD segment lengths as derived in other publications <lb/>(4, 16, 50, 51). <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient <lb/>Genomes <lb/>3.1 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Human Populations <lb/>3.1.1 Sharing Between All Human Populations <lb/>We were interested in the distribution of IBD segments among different populations. The main <lb/>continental population groups are Africans (AFR), Asians (ASN), Europeans (EUR), and Ad-<lb/>mixed Americans (AMR), where AMR consist of Colombian, Puerto Rican, and Mexican indi-<lb/>viduals. Table 1 lists the number of IBD segments that are shared between particular continental <lb/>populations. The vast majority (101,209) of the detected IBD segments (105,652) is shared by <lb/>Africans (at least one African possesses the segment), of which 64,894 are exclusively found in <lb/>Africans. Only 9,003 and 4,793 IBD segments are shared by Europeans and Asians, respectively. <lb/>558 IBD segments are exclusively found in Europeans and 1,452 exclusively in Asians. Admixed <lb/>Americans share 207 IBD segments with Asians, but 1,008 with Europeans. Gravel et al. (14) <lb/>reported recently that Admixed Americans, especially Colombians and Puerto Ricans, show a <lb/>large proportion of European ancestry, which is also reflected in our results. If we additionally <lb/>consider sharing with AFR, we obtain similar figures that are again consistent with the AMR ad-<lb/>mixture: 4,325 IBD segments have AFR/AMR/EUR sharing while only 621 IBD segments have <lb/>AFR/AMR/ASN sharing. According to results of the 1000 Genomes Project Consortium (48), <lb/>individuals with African ancestry carry much more rare variants than those of European or Asian <lb/>ancestry supporting our finding that most IBD segments are shared by Africans. We found that <lb/>few IBD segments are shared between two continental populations (Table 1 &quot;Pairs of Popula-<lb/>tions&quot;) confirming recently published results (13, 48) (see also Section 3.1.2). The relatively large <lb/>number of shared IBD segments between Africans and Europeans was due to many shared IBD <lb/>segments between the AFR sub-group ASW (Americans with African ancestry from SW US) and <lb/>Europeans. This tendency was also observed in the 1000 Genomes Project via the fixation index <lb/>F ST estimated by Hudson ratio of averages and via shared haplotype length around f 2 variants <lb/>(48). The high content of European DNA segments in ASW is consistent with the finding that in <lb/>African Americans a median proportion of 18.5% is European (6). <lb/>Overall, we conclude that IBD segments that are shared across continental populations, in <lb/>particular by Africans, date back to a time before humans moved out of Africa. Consequently, <lb/>the rare variants that tag these short IBD segments arose before this time. See Section A, for a <lb/>discussion of the question whether rare variants are recent or old. <lb/>3.1.2 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Continental Populations <lb/>We found that most IBD segments are observed in only one continental population, which are, in <lb/>most cases, Africans. However, for non-Africans, we saw a considerable sharing of IBD segments <lb/>across continental groups. The sharing between continental populations seems to contradict state-<lb/>ments in other publications. For example, Gravel et al. (13) report that sharing of SNVs between <lb/>continental groups is low. <lb/>Nevertheless, sharing between continental groups has also been reported in the publication of <lb/>the 1000 Genomes Project (48). The authors observed 17% of low-frequency variants in the range <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1: Number of IBD segments that are shared by particular continental populations. <lb/>Single Population <lb/>All Populations <lb/>AFR <lb/>AMR <lb/>ASN <lb/>EUR <lb/>AFR/AMR/ASN/EUR <lb/>64,894 <lb/>378 <lb/>1,452 <lb/>558 <lb/>1,127 <lb/>Pairs of Populations <lb/>Triplets of Populations <lb/>AFR/AMR AFR/ASN AFR/EUR <lb/>AFR/AMR/ASN <lb/>AFR/AMR/EUR <lb/>28,710 <lb/>387 <lb/>986 <lb/>621 <lb/>4,325 <lb/>AMR/ASN AMR/EUR ASN/EUR <lb/>AFR/ASN/EUR <lb/>AMR/ASN/EUR <lb/>207 <lb/>1,008 <lb/>351 <lb/>159 <lb/>489 <lb/>AFR = Africans (228), AMR = Admixed Americans (175), ASN = East Asians (277), and EUR = <lb/>Europeans (376). <lb/>0.5-5% and 53% of rare variants at 0.5% in a single continental group, which means that 83% of <lb/>the low-frequency variants and 47% of the rare variants are shared between continental popula-<lb/>tions. They also describe sharing of f 2 variants between Finnish (FIN) and African individuals. f 2 <lb/>variants are those variants for which their minor allele is observed in exactly 2 individuals. They <lb/>are rarer than most SNVs that tag our extracted IBD segments because, on average, 6 individuals <lb/>possess an IBD segment. According to Gravel et al. (13), sharing between continental groups de-<lb/>creases with rarer variants. Thus, in our extracted IBD segments, we would expect to find sharing <lb/>between continental groups considerably more often than for f 2 variants. Furthermore, the 1000 <lb/>Genomes Project Consortium (48) reports that f 2 variants that are shared between populations with <lb/>no recent common ancestry are present on very short haplotypes with a median length of 15 kb. <lb/>They conclude that these haplotypes are likely to reflect recurrent mutations and chance ancient <lb/>coalescent events. This statement also supports our findings of IBD sharing between continental <lb/>groups, but we can exclude recurrent mutations as a likely explanation because IBD segments are <lb/>shared between multiple individuals. <lb/>3.2 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Human and Ancient Genomes <lb/>Since short IBD segments are thought to be very old, we wondered whether some IBD segments <lb/>match bases of ancient genomes, such as Neandertal and Denisova. Ancient short IBD segments <lb/>may reveal gene flow between ancient genomes and ancestors of modern humans and, thereby, <lb/>may shed light on different out-of-Africa hypotheses (2). 31X coverage whole genome sequencing <lb/>data for the Denisova, as well as, the Altai Neandertal genome of 52X coverage were provided by <lb/>the Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology (31, 35). Considering only the variants <lb/>of the 1000 Genomes Project, 0.6% of the Denisova bases and 0.3% of the Neandertal bases were <lb/>not determined, 92.0% and 91.3%, respectively, matched bases of the human reference, and 8% <lb/>and 9%, respectively, matched either the human minor allele or were different from human alleles. <lb/>As additional information in the 1000 Genomes Project data, bases of the reconstructed common <lb/>ancestor of human, chimpanzee, gorilla, orang utan, macaque, and marmoset genomes were given. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>3.2.1 IBD Sharing Between Human Populations and Ancient Genomes <lb/>We tested whether IBD segments that match particular ancient genomes to a large extent are found <lb/>more often in certain populations than expected randomly. For each IBD segment, we computed <lb/>two values: The first value was the proportion of tagSNVs that match a particular ancient genome, <lb/>which we call &quot;genome proportion&quot; of an IBD segment (e.g. &quot;Denisova proportion&quot;). The second <lb/>value was the proportion of individuals that possess an IBD segment and are from a certain pop-<lb/>ulation as opposed to the overall number of individuals that possess this IBD segment. We call <lb/>this value the &quot;population proportion&quot; of an IBD segment (e.g. &quot;Asian proportion&quot;). Consider the <lb/>following illustrative examples. If an IBD segment has 20 tagSNVs of which 10 match Denisova <lb/>bases with their minor allele, then we obtain 10/20 = 0.5 = 50% as the Denisova proportion. If <lb/>an IBD segment is observed in 6 individuals of which 4 are Africans and 2 Europeans, then the <lb/>African proportion is 4/6 = 0.67 = 67% and the European proportion is 0.33 = 33%. A correlation <lb/>between a genome proportion and a population proportion would indicate that this ancient genome <lb/>is overrepresented in this specific population. Often human IBD segments that are found in ancient <lb/>genomes have already been present in the ancestral genome of humans and other primates. These <lb/>IBD segments would confound the interbreeding analysis based on IBD sharing between modern <lb/>human populations and Neandertals or Denisovans. Therefore, we removed those IBD segments <lb/>from the data before the following analysis. <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>-0.1 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>Denisova Pearson&apos;s Correlation Coefficient <lb/>Figure 1: Pearson&apos;s correlation between population proportions and the Denisova genome propor-<lb/>tion. Asians have a significantly larger correlation to the Denisova genome than other populations. <lb/>Many IBD segments that match the Denisova genome are exclusively found in Asians, which has a <lb/>large effect on the correlation coefficient. Europeans still have a significantly larger correlation to <lb/>the Denisova genome than the average. Mexicans (MXL) have also a surprisingly high correlation <lb/>to the Denisova genome while Iberians (IBS) have a low correlation compared to other Europeans. <lb/>Pearson&apos;s product moment correlation test and Spearman&apos;s rank correlation test both showed <lb/>highly significant correlations between the Denisova genome and Asians, the Denisova genome <lb/>and Europeans, the Neandertal genome and Asians, and the Neandertal genome and Europeans. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>-0.3 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>-0.1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>Neandertal Pearson&apos;s Correlation Coefficient <lb/>Figure 2: Pearson&apos;s correlation between population proportions and the Neandertal genome pro-<lb/>portion. Europeans and Asians have significantly larger correlations to the Neandertal genome <lb/>than other populations. Asians have slightly higher correlation coefficients than Europeans. Again, <lb/>Mexicans (MXL) have a surprisingly high correlation to the Neandertal genome while Iberians <lb/>(IBS) have a low correlation compared to other Europeans. <lb/>Figure 1 shows Pearson&apos;s correlation coefficients for the correlation between population pro-<lb/>portion and the Denisova genome proportion. Asians have a significantly larger correlation to the <lb/>Denisova genome than other populations (p-value &lt; 5e-324). Many IBD segments that match <lb/>the Denisova genome are exclusively found in Asians, which has a large effect on the correlation <lb/>coefficient. Europeans have still a significantly larger correlation to the Denisova genome than <lb/>the average (p-value &lt; 5e-324). Surprisingly, Mexicans (MXL) have a high correlation to the <lb/>Denisova genome too, while Iberians (IBS) have a low correlation compared to other Europeans. <lb/>These unexpected correlations can be explained through the fact that of all European populations <lb/>Iberians show the highest rates of African gene flow (1, 3, 32) whereas Mexicans show a high pro-<lb/>portion of Native American ancestry which in turn might also reflect gene flow from Asia (14, 33). <lb/>Figure 2 shows Pearson&apos;s correlation coefficients for the correlation between population propor-<lb/>tion and the Neandertal genome proportion. Europeans and Asians have a significantly larger <lb/>correlation to the Neandertal genome than other populations (p-value &lt; 5e-324). Asians have <lb/>slightly higher correlation coefficients than Europeans. Again Mexicans (MXL) have surprisingly <lb/>high correlation to the Neandertal genome while Iberians (IBS) have a low correlation compared <lb/>to other Europeans. <lb/>However, correlation tests are sensitive to accumulations of minor effects. Therefore, we <lb/>focused subsequently on strong effects, i.e. large values of genome proportions and large values <lb/>of population proportions. <lb/>We define an IBD segment to match a particular ancient genome if the genome proportion <lb/>is 30% or higher. Only 8% of the Denisova and 9% of the Neandertal bases (about 10% of the <lb/>called bases) match the minor allele of the human genome on average. Therefore, we require <lb/>an odds ratio of 3 to call an IBD segment to match an ancient genome. We found many more <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>IBD segments that match the Neandertal or the Denisova genome than expected randomly. This <lb/>again supports the statement that the detected short IBD segments are old and some of them date <lb/>back to times of the ancestors of humans, Neandertals, and Denisovans. IBD segments that match <lb/>the Denisova genome often match the Neandertal genome, too, thus these segments cannot be <lb/>attributed to either one of these genomes. Therefore, we introduce the &quot;Archaic genome&quot; (genome <lb/>of archaic hominids ancestral to Denisova and Neandertal), to which IBD segments are attributed <lb/>if they match both the Denisova and the Neandertal genome. <lb/>To test for an enrichment of Denisova-, Neandertal-, or Archaic-matching IBD segments in <lb/>different subpopulations, we used Fisher&apos;s exact test for count data. Again, we first excluded those <lb/>IBD segments that were also present in the reconstructed ancestral genome of humans and other <lb/>primates. IBD segments were then classified as being shared by at least one individual of a certain <lb/>population or not and either matching or not matching the ancient genome. <lb/>−50 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>−100 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>Denisova Odds <lb/>Figure 3: Odds scores of Fisher&apos;s exact test for an enrichment of Denisova-matching IBD segments <lb/>in different populations are represented by colored dots. The arrows point from the region the <lb/>populations stem from to the region of sample collection. IBD segments that are shared by Asians <lb/>match the Denisova genome significantly more often than IBD segments that are shared by other <lb/>populations (red dots). Africans show the lowest matching with the Denisova genome (dark blue <lb/>dots). Surprisingly, Admixed Americans have higher odds for Denisova sharing than Europeans <lb/>(green and turquoise vs. light blue dots). <lb/>Figure 3 shows the odds scores of the Fisher&apos;s exact tests for an enrichment of Denisova-<lb/>matching IBD segments in different populations. As expected, Asians show the highest odds <lb/>for IBD segments matching the Denisova genome (odds ratio of 5.44 and p-value of 1.2e-102), <lb/>while Africans have the lowest odds (odds ratio of 0.22 and p-value of 9.4e-71). Surprisingly, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Admixed Americans show more sharing than Europeans (odds ratio of 2.63 vs. 2.11), although <lb/>the difference is not very prominent. In general these results reflect previous findings. Meyer <lb/>et al. (31) and Prüfer et al. (35) noted that Denisovans show more sharing with modern East <lb/>Asians and South Americans (called Admixed Americans here) than with Europeans. Within the <lb/>Asian populations Han Chinese from South (CHS) have slightly higher odds for matching the <lb/>Denisova genome than Han Chinese from Beijing (CHB), while Japanese (JPN) have the lowest <lb/>odds (Figure 4). Skoglund et al. (43) also report a particularly high affinity between Southeast <lb/>Asians and the Denisova genome, in contrast to Meyer et al. (31) who find higher levels of sharing <lb/>for individuals from North China compared to those of the south. Within the European populations <lb/>we see the highest odds for Utah residents with ancestry from northern and western Europe (CEU) <lb/>followed by Finnish (FIN), Iberians from Spain (IBS), and British from England and Scotland <lb/>(GBR). Toscani in Italy (TSI) show the lowest levels of sharing, but all odds are between 1.56 and <lb/>2.11 (Figure 5). <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>110 <lb/>120 <lb/>130 <lb/>140 <lb/>150 <lb/>5.4 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>Denisova Odds <lb/>Figure 4: Odds scores of Fisher&apos;s exact test for an enrichment of Denisova-matching IBD segments <lb/>in Asian populations are represented by colored dots. Within the Asian populations Han Chinese <lb/>from South (CHS) have slightly higher odds for matching the Denisova genome than Han Chinese <lb/>from Beijing (CHB) (red dot vs. green dot), while Japanese (JPN) have the lowest odds (blue dot). <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>−10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>Denisova Odds <lb/>Figure 5: Odds scores of Fisher&apos;s exact test for an enrichment of Denisova-matching IBD seg-<lb/>ments in European populations are represented by colored dots. Utah residents with ancestry from <lb/>northern and western Europe (CEU) are symbolized by a dot in Central Europe. Within the Euro-<lb/>pean populations we see the highest odds (red dot) for Utah residents with ancestry from northern <lb/>and western Europe (CEU) followed by Finnish (FIN), Iberians from Spain (IBS), and British <lb/>from England and Scotland (GBR). Toscani in Italy (TSI) show the lowest levels of sharing (blue <lb/>dot), but all odds are between 1.56 and 2.11. <lb/>Figure 6 shows the odds scores of the Fisher&apos;s exact tests for an enrichment of Neandertal-<lb/>matching IBD segments in different populations. As expected, Asians again show the highest <lb/>odds for IBD segments matching the Neandertal genome (odds ratio of 27.49 and p-value &lt; 5e-<lb/>324), while Africans have the lowest odds (odds ratio of 0.03 and p-value &lt; 5e-324). In contrast <lb/>to the Denisova results, here Europeans show clearly more matching with the Neandertal genome <lb/>than Admixed Americans (odds ratio of 12.66 vs. 2.90). In general these results reflect previous <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>findings. Other studies (15, 28) have reported significantly more sharing between Neandertals and <lb/>non-Africans than with Africans. Wall et al. (55) noted that Neandertals contributed more DNA to <lb/>modern East Asians than to Europeans. Within the Asian populations Han Chinese from Beijing <lb/>(CHB) have slightly higher odds for matching the Neandertal genome than Han Chinese from <lb/>South (CHS), while Japanese (JPN) lie in between (Figure 4). Within the European populations <lb/>a north to south decline can be seen with Finnish (FIN) having the highest odds for matching the <lb/>Neandertal genome followed by British from England and Scotland (GBR) and Utah residents with <lb/>ancestry from northern and western Europe (CEU). Toscani in Italy (TSI) and Iberians from Spain <lb/>(IBS) show the lowest levels of matching (Figure 8). An explanation for the latter two low odds <lb/>for Neandertal matching is that according to Ralph et al. (36) Iberians and Italians show reduced <lb/>rates of shared ancestry compared to the rest of Europe. Also Botigué et al. (3) found higher IBD <lb/>sharing between North Africans and individuals from Southern Europe which would decrease the <lb/>amount of DNA sharing with Neandertals. Sankararaman et al. (39) achieved a similar ranking <lb/>for Neandertal ancestry using a different approach, but stated that because of the high standard <lb/>deviation among individuals from the same population, small differences may be due to statistical <lb/>noise. The same holds true for our results since a single individual with very high Neandertal <lb/>ancestry can lead to inflated odds for a population. Nevertheless, since all Asian populations show <lb/>especially high odds, we can exclude that all results are just due to noise. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>−50 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>−100 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>Neandertal Odds <lb/>Figure 6: Odds scores of Fisher&apos;s exact test for an enrichment of Neandertal-matching IBD seg-<lb/>ments in different populations are represented by colored dots. The arrows point from the region <lb/>the populations stem from to the region of sample collection. IBD segments that are shared by <lb/>Asians match the Denisova genome significantly more often than IBD segments that are shared <lb/>by other populations (red dots). Africans show the lowest matching with the Neandertal genome <lb/>(dark blue dots). Europeans show more matching than Admixed Americans (green vs. light blue <lb/>dots). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>110 <lb/>120 <lb/>130 <lb/>140 <lb/>150 <lb/>24 <lb/>25 <lb/>26 <lb/>27 <lb/>Neandertal Odds <lb/>Figure 7: Odds scores of the Fisher&apos;s exact tests for an enrichment of Neandertal-matching IBD <lb/>segments in Asian populations are represented by colored dots. Within the Asian populations Han <lb/>Chinese from Beijing (CHB) have slightly higher odds for matching the Neandertal genome than <lb/>Han Chinese from South (CHS) (red dot vs. blue dot), while Japanese (JPN) lie in between (orange <lb/>dot). <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>−10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>Neandertal Odds <lb/>Figure 8: Odds scores of the Fisher&apos;s exact tests for an enrichment of Neandertal-matching IBD <lb/>segments in European populations are represented by colored dots. Utah residents with ancestry <lb/>from northern and western Europe (CEU) are symbolized by a dot in Central Europe. Within <lb/>the European populations a north to south decline can be seen with Finnish (FIN) having the <lb/>highest odds for matching the Neandertal genome (red dot) followed by British from England <lb/>and Scotland (GBR) and Utah residents with ancestry from northern and western Europe (CEU) <lb/>(orange and green dots). Toscani in Italy (TSI) and Iberians from Spain (IBS) show the lowest <lb/>levels of matching (blue dots). <lb/>In order to concentrate on strong effects in terms of population proportions, we investigated <lb/>which population has the majority proportion for an IBD segment that matches a particular genome <lb/>-the population to which the majority of the individuals possessing this segment belong to. <lb/>Figure 9 shows the population with the majority proportion for each IBD segment. The IBD seg-<lb/>ments are presented for each genome, where the colors show the populations with majority pro-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>portion for the according IBD segment. More than half of the Neandertal-matching IBD segments <lb/>have Asians or Europeans as majority population proportions. However, still many Neandertal-<lb/>matching segments are mainly shared by Africans which to some extend contradicts the hypothesis <lb/>of Prüfer et al. (35) that Neandertal ancestry in Africans is due to back-to-Africa gene flow. For <lb/>the Archaic genome (intersection of Neandertal-and Denisova-matching IBD segments), IBD <lb/>segments dominated by Asians or Europeans are also enriched if compared to all IBD segments <lb/>found on chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes Project data (we will call the set of these seg-<lb/>ments &quot;human genome&quot;). The enrichment by Asian or European IBD segments is lower for the <lb/>Denisova genome, but still significant, especially for Asian segments. Furthermore, as can be seen <lb/>in Figure 9, more IBD segments are found that match the Neandertal genome than segments that <lb/>match the Denisova genome. One explanation for this is that the unknown ancient gene flow into <lb/>Denisovans mentioned by Prüfer et al. (35) replaced some segments from the common ancestor of <lb/>Neandertals and Denisovans in the Denisova genome. Therefore, these segments are only shared <lb/>by modern humans and Neandertals although they might have been introduced by the aforemen-<lb/>tioned common ancestor. <lb/>Next we wanted to know which populations share an IBD segment that matches a particular <lb/>genome, that is, we asked whether this IBD segment is found in this population or not. Figure 10 <lb/>shows for each genome (human and ancient) and each IBD segment, whether a population shares <lb/>this IBD segment or not. IBD segments that match the Neandertal or the Archaic genome are <lb/>found more often in Asians and Europeans than all IBD segments (human genome). This effect is <lb/>not as prominent for IBD segments that match the Denisova genome, but still significant. <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>Human <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Archaic <lb/>Population <lb/>AFR <lb/>AMR <lb/>ASN <lb/>EUR <lb/>Majority Population Proportion per Genome <lb/>Figure 9: For each IBD segment, the population with the majority proportion is determined. IBD <lb/>segments are given for each matching genome, where the color indicates the population that has <lb/>majority proportion. For the human genome, 4,000 random IBD segments were chosen. More than <lb/>half of the Neandertal-matching IBD segments have Asians or Europeans as majority population. <lb/>The Archaic genome (Neandertal and Denisova) shows also an enrichment of IBD segments that <lb/>are found mostly in Asians or Europeans. Denisova-matching IBD segments are often shared <lb/>mainly by Asians. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Human <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Archaic <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>AFR AMR ASN EUR <lb/>AFR AMR ASN EUR <lb/>AFR AMR ASN EUR <lb/>AFR AMR ASN EUR <lb/>With <lb/>Without <lb/>IBD Segments With/Without Populations per Genome <lb/>Figure 10: For each genome and each IBD segment, the color indicates whether a population <lb/>contains this segment (&quot;With&quot;) or not (&quot;Without&quot;). For the human genome, 4,000 random IBD <lb/>segments were chosen. IBD segments that match the Neandertal or the Archaic genome are found <lb/>more often in Asians and Europeans than all IBD segments (human). This effect is not as promi-<lb/>nent for IBD segments that match the Denisova genome. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>3.2.2 Densities of Population Proportions and Ancient Genomes <lb/>We plotted densities of population proportions for IBD segments that match a particular ancient <lb/>genome (30% or more SNVs match) and for those that do not match that genome. Figure 11 <lb/>shows the density of Asian proportions of Denisova-matching IBD segments (pink) vs. the density <lb/>of Asian proportions of non-Denisova-matching IBD segments (cyan). Figure 12 shows analo-<lb/>gous densities for Europeans. In comparison to all populations the density of Denisova-matching <lb/>IBD segments that are observed in Asians and Europeans is higher than for non-matching IBD <lb/>segments. This can be seen by the higher densities of matching IBD segments (pink) compared to <lb/>densities of non-matching IBD segments (cyan) if the population proportions are not very close to <lb/>zero -or, conversely, it can be seen at the lower peak at zero (less IBD segments that match the <lb/>Denisova genome without Asian or European sharing). Many Denisova-matching IBD segments <lb/>are shared exclusively among Asians which is indicated by the high density at a population pro-<lb/>portion of 1 (pink density in Figure 11). Population proportion of 1 means that IBD segments are <lb/>only shared among Asians. <lb/>Figures 14 and 15 show analogous densities as in Figures 11 and 12, but for the Neandertal <lb/>genome. The differences we already observed for the Denisova genome are even more prominent <lb/>for the Neandertal: Neandertal-matching IBD segments are observed even more often in Asians <lb/>and Europeans than non-matching IBD segments if compared to all segments of the respective <lb/>category. The higher densities (pink) at a population proportion not close to zero are now more <lb/>prominent -or conversely, the lower peak at zero for Neandertal-matching IBD segments be-<lb/>comes clearer (less IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome without Asian or European <lb/>sharing). For Asians, the peak at 1 in Figure 14 is even higher, representing IBD segments that <lb/>are shared exclusively among Asians. IBD segment sharing exclusively within one continental <lb/>population is very common, as the blue peaks at 1 in Figure 11 and Figure 14 show. <lb/>Figures 13 and 16 show the same densities for Africans. Both the density of African propor-<lb/>tions of Denisova-matching and the same density for Neandertal-matching IBD segments have <lb/>two peaks: one at a low and one at a high proportion of Africans. For Neandertal-matching IBD <lb/>segments, the density at low proportions of Africans is even larger than for high proportions. Thus, <lb/>IBD segments that match ancient genomes are either shared by a very low or a very high proportion <lb/>of Africans. The low proportion of African density peak hints at admixture of ancestors of modern <lb/>humans and Denisovans / Neandertals outside of Africa or the back to Africa gene flow mentioned <lb/>by Prüfer et al. (35). The density peak at high proportions of Africans may be due to ancient DNA <lb/>segments shared by hominid groups that were lost in other continental populations. This finding <lb/>could support the hypothesis that ancient population substructure in Africa also allowed for the <lb/>occurrence of different continental patterns of DNA sharing between modern humans and ancient <lb/>genomes (10, 15). <lb/>IBD segments that match the &quot;Archaic genome&quot; are those IBD segments that match both the <lb/>Denisova and Neandertal genome. Population proportion densities for the Archaic genome are <lb/>presented in Figures 17, 18, and 19 for Asians, Europeans, and Africans, respectively. For the <lb/>Archaic genome we see the same figure as for the Neandertal and the Denisova genome: the <lb/>African density is bimodal that means either it is dominated by Africans or it contains no or only <lb/>few Africans. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>7 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Asian proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Not Denisova <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Asian proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Not Denisova <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 11: Panel A: Density of Asian proportions of Denisova-matching IBD segments (pink) <lb/>vs. density of Asian proportions of non-Denisova-matching IBD segments (cyan). IBD segments <lb/>were extracted from phased genotyping data of chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes Project. <lb/>Dotted lines indicate the respective means. Panel B: The same densities as in Panel A but zoomed <lb/>in. <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>6 <lb/>9 <lb/>12 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>European proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Not Denisova <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>European proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Not Denisova <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 12: Panel A: Density of European proportions of Denisova-matching IBD segments (pink) <lb/>vs. density of European proportions of non-Denisova-matching IBD segments (cyan). IBD seg-<lb/>ments were extracted from phased genotyping data of chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes Project. <lb/>Dotted lines indicate the respective means. Panel B: The same densities as in Panel A but zoomed <lb/>in. <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>African proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Not Denisova <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>African proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Not Denisova <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 13: Panel A: Density of African proportions of Denisova-matching IBD segments (pink) <lb/>vs. density of African proportions of non-Denisova-matching IBD segments (cyan). IBD segments <lb/>were extracted from phased genotyping data of chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes Project. <lb/>Dotted lines indicate the respective means. Peaks for non-Denisova-matching IBD segments are <lb/>found at 0.5, 0.66, 0.33, 0.75, and 0.8, which corresponds to 1/2, 2/3, 1/3, 3/4, 4/5 (number <lb/>of Africans / total number of individuals that have the IBD segment). The density of African <lb/>proportions of Denisova-matching IBD segments has two peaks: one at a low and one at a high <lb/>proportion of Africans. Panel B: The same densities as in Panel A but zoomed in. <lb/>0.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Asian proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Not Neandertal <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Asian proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Not Neandertal <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 14: Panel A: Density of Asian proportions of Neandertal-matching IBD segments (pink) <lb/>vs. density of Asian proportions of non-Neandertal-matching IBD segments (cyan). IBD segments <lb/>were extracted from phased genotyping data of chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes Project. <lb/>Dotted lines indicate the respective means. Many Neandertal-enriched IBD segments are shared <lb/>mainly or exclusively by Asians as the peak at a proportion close to 1 shows. Panel B: The same <lb/>densities as in Panel A but zoomed in. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>European proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Not Neandertal <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>European proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Not Neandertal <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 15: Panel A: Density of European proportions of Neandertal-matching IBD segments <lb/>(pink) vs. density of European proportions of non-Neandertal-matching IBD segments (cyan). <lb/>IBD segments were extracted from phased genotyping data of chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes <lb/>Project. Dotted lines indicate the respective means. Many Neandertal-enriched IBD segments are <lb/>shared mainly or exclusively by Asians as the peak at a proportion close to 1 shows. Neandertal-<lb/>enriched IBD segments are shared by Europeans but fewer segments are shared exclusively among <lb/>Europeans than for Asians (see Figure 14). Panel B: the same density zoomed in. <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>African proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Not Neandertal <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>African proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Not Neandertal <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 16: Panel A: Density of African proportions of Neandertal-matching IBD segments (pink) <lb/>vs. density of African proportions of non-Neandertal-matching IBD segments (cyan). IBD seg-<lb/>ments were extracted from phased genotyping data of chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes Project. <lb/>Dotted lines indicate the respective means. Peaks for non-Neandertal-matching IBD segments are <lb/>found at 0.5, 0.66, 0.33, 0.75, and 0.8, which corresponds to 1/2, 2/3, 1/3, 3/4, 4/5 (number of <lb/>Africans / total number of individuals that have the IBD segment). The density of African pro-<lb/>portions of Neandertal-matching IBD segments has two peaks: one at a low and one at a high <lb/>proportion of Africans. The density of low proportions of Africans is even larger than the density <lb/>of high proportions. Panel B: the same density zoomed in. <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Asian proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Archaic <lb/>Not Archaic <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Asian proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Archaic <lb/>Not Archaic <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 17: Panel A: Density of Asian proportions of Archaic-genome-matching IBD segments <lb/>(pink) vs. density of Asian proportions of non-Archaic-genome-matching IBD segments (cyan). <lb/>IBD segments were extracted from phased genotyping data of chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes <lb/>Project. Dotted lines indicate the respective means. Panel B: the same density zoomed in. <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>European proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Archaic <lb/>Not Archaic <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>European proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Archaic <lb/>Not Archaic <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 18: Panel A: Density of European proportions of Archaic-genome-matching IBD seg-<lb/>ments (pink) vs. density of European proportions of non-Archaic-genome-matching IBD seg-<lb/>ments (cyan). IBD segments were extracted from phased genotyping data of chromosome 1 of <lb/>the 1000 Genomes Project. Dotted lines indicate the respective means. Many Archaic-genome-<lb/>enriched IBD segments are shared mainly or exclusively by Asians as the peak at a proportion <lb/>close to 1 shows. Panel B: the same densities zoomed in. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">3 Sharing of IBD Segments Between Populations and With Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>African proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Archaic <lb/>Not Archaic <lb/>A <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>African proportion of IBD segment occurrence <lb/>Density <lb/>Matching Genome <lb/>Archaic <lb/>Not Archaic <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 19: Panel A: Density of African proportions of Archaic-genome-matching IBD segments <lb/>(pink) vs. density of African proportions of non-Archaic-genome-matching IBD segments (cyan). <lb/>IBD segments were extracted from phased genotyping data of chromosome 1 of the 1000 Genomes <lb/>Project. Dotted lines indicate the respective means. Peaks for non-Archaic-genome-matching IBD <lb/>segments are found at 0.5, 0.66, 0.33, 0.75, and 0.8, which corresponds to 1/2, 2/3, 1/3, 3/4, 4/5 <lb/>(number of Africans / total number of individuals that have the IBD segment). The density of <lb/>African proportions of Archaic-genome-matching IBD segments has two peaks: one at a low and <lb/>one at a high proportion of Africans. Panel B: the same density zoomed in. <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<body>4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/>4.1 Relating the IBD Length to Years from Present <lb/>We aim to establish a relation between the length of an IBD segment and the time of the most <lb/>recent common ancestor of the individuals that possess the IBD segment. The shorter the IBD <lb/>segment is, the older it is assumed to be, the further in the past the most recent common ancestor <lb/>should be found. For IBD length distributions, mathematical models have already been estab-<lb/>lished. However, these models assume IBD segment sharing between only two individuals. <lb/>4.1.1 Exponential Distributed IBD Lengths <lb/>The length of an IBD segment is exponentially distributed with a mean of 100/(2g) cM (centi-<lb/>Morgans), where g is the number of generations which separate the two haplotypes that share a <lb/>segment from their common ancestor (4, 16, 34, 50, 51). Ulgen and Li (52) recommend to use <lb/>a recombination rate, cM-to-Mbp ratio, of 1, however it varies from 0 to 9 along a chromosome <lb/>(57). <lb/>We are not able to perform reliable age estimations of the IBD segments based on their <lb/>length. <lb/>We encountered severe problems in estimating the age of IBD segments based on their length: <lb/>The original ancestor DNA sequence is assumed to have a length of 1 Morgan before it is <lb/>broken up by recombinations. However, founder genomes cannot be assumed to be distin-<lb/>guishable across the length of 1 Morgan. <lb/>It is assumed that recombinations are random and all resulting segments have the same <lb/>chance to survive. However, e.g. after population admixture or introgression of ancient <lb/>genomes into ancestors of humans, recombined segments may have different fitness and <lb/>some may vanish due to the high selective pressure. Thus, after such events the selective <lb/>pressure leads to a bias of the IBD length distribution which makes the estimation of their <lb/>age intractable. <lb/>The age estimations are based on the mean, thus it is assumed that there are enough re-<lb/>combination events in each generation to average out random effects. Therefore, for few <lb/>admixture/introgression events (few matings/offspring) these estimations are not reliable. <lb/>Due to these problems, we do not present age estimation at this point of our investigation. <lb/>4.1.2 Correction for the Assumptions of IBD Length Distributions <lb/>The IBD length distribution was derived from sharing between two individuals, but we consider <lb/>IBD sharing among many individuals and compute the raw IBD segment length as the maximal <lb/>IBD sharing of any two individuals that possess the IBD segment. This results in overestimation <lb/>of the lengths, because it is the maximum of all pairwise sharings. We also observed a second <lb/>cause for raw IBD segments being longer than expected by the exponential distribution. The more <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>individuals share an IBD segment, the more likely it is to find two individuals that share random <lb/>minor alleles which would falsely extend the IBD segment. <lb/>Therefore, we corrected the raw lengths of IBD segments by locating the first tagSNV from <lb/>the left (upstream) which is shared by at least 3/4 of the individuals that possess the IBD segment. <lb/>This tagSNV is the left break point for the IBD segment. Analogously, we determined the right <lb/>break point by the first tagSNV from the right (downstream) that is shared by at least 3/4 of the <lb/>individuals. The distance between these break points is the (corrected) length of an IBD segment. <lb/>4.1.3 Length Correction for IBD with Ancient Genomes <lb/>We are interested in IBD between modern human and ancient genomes. However, the human IBD <lb/>segment length is not an appropriate measure for the length of IBD with ancient genomes because <lb/>only a part of the IBD segment may match an ancient genome (see Figure 33). <lb/>We corrected the IBD segment lengths to obtain the IBD lengths between human and ancient <lb/>genomes. The corrected length of an IBD segment is the length of the &quot;ancient part&quot; that matches <lb/>a particular ancient genome. This &quot;ancient part&quot; must contain at least 8 tagSNVs, which is the <lb/>minimum number of tagSNVs per IBD segments. First, the left (upstream) break point of the <lb/>&quot;ancient part&quot; of an IBD segment genome is detected. This left break point was defined as the first <lb/>location in the IBD segment from the left (upstream), where at least 4 out of 8 tagSNVs match <lb/>the ancient genome. From the right (downstream), the right break point of the &quot;ancient part&quot; of an <lb/>IBD segment was detected analogously. Since not all bases of the ancient genomes were called, <lb/>we modified the definition of the break points and required at least 6 bases of the 8 tagSNVs to be <lb/>called of which 3, have to match the ancient genome. If either the left or right break point of an <lb/>&quot;ancient part&quot; could not be found, then this IBD segment does not contain an &quot;ancient part&quot; and <lb/>was excluded from all further analyses. <lb/>Matching of an IBD segment and an ancient genome for IBD segment lengths analyses was <lb/>defined as: <lb/>1. at least 15% of the tagSNVs of the IBD segment must match the ancient genome, <lb/>2. the &quot;ancient part&quot; of the IBD segment must contain at least 8 tagSNVs, and <lb/>3. 30% of the tagSNVs in the &quot;ancient part&quot; of the IBD segment must match the ancient <lb/>genome. <lb/>4.2 Histograms of Lengths of IBD Segments for the Different Genomes <lb/>Figure 20 shows the histograms of IBD segment lengths for all IBD segments (human genome) <lb/>and for IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome. For the human genome a peak at 24,200 <lb/>bp is visible, whereas, for the Neandertal genome, peaks are at 6,000 and 22,000 bp. It can be <lb/>seen that IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome are shorter, thus also older. <lb/>Figure 21 shows the histograms of IBD segment lengths for all IBD segments that match <lb/>the Denisova and the &quot;Archaic&quot; genome (&quot;Archaic genome&quot; contains IBD segments that match <lb/>both the Denisova and Neandertal genome). For the Denisova genome, we have a peak at 4,000 <lb/>bp, whereas, for the Archaic genome, peaks are at 11,000 bp and 24,000 bp. The peaks for the <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Counts <lb/>Histogram IBD Lengths Chr. 1 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Counts <lb/>Histogram Neandertal IBD Lengths Chr. 1 <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 20: Panel A: Histogram of the IBD segment lengths for all IBD segments found in the 1000 <lb/>Genomes Project data (human genome). The global peak is at 24,200 bp. Panel B: Histogram of <lb/>the IBD segment lengths for IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome. Peaks at 6,000 bp <lb/>and 22,000 bp are indicated. <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Counts <lb/>Histogram Denisovan IBD Lengths Chr. 1 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Counts <lb/>Histogram Archaic IBD Lengths Chr. 1 <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 21: Panel A: Histogram of the IBD segment lengths for IBD segments that match the <lb/>Denisova genome. A peak at 4,000 bp is indicated. Panel B: Histogram of the IBD segment <lb/>lengths for IBD segments that match both the Neandertal and the Denisova genome (&quot;Archaic <lb/>genome&quot;). Peaks at 6,000 bp and 24,000 bp are indicated. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>Archaic genome are almost at the same positions as the corresponding peaks for the Denisova <lb/>and Neandertal genome. IBD segment sharing between humans, Neandertals, and Denisovans <lb/>may have two different reasons. First, the IBD segments may stem from a common ancestor and <lb/>are passed on in each of these hominid groups. Secondly, IBD segment sharing may be caused <lb/>by an introgression of one hominid group into another. For the former the IBD segments are <lb/>supposed to be on average shorter than for the latter scenario. Therefore, the peaks at shortest, and <lb/>hence oldest, IBD segments must be assumed to stem from a common ancestor of Neandertals and <lb/>Denisovans. Some of these IBD segments may have been lost either in Neandertals or Denisovans <lb/>(at least in the specimens analyzed) and are therefore not attributed to the Archaic genome but to <lb/>one of the other two groups. Introgression of Neandertals into the Denisova genome or vice versa <lb/>and a subsequent gene flow into humans can explain long, therefore more recent, IBD segments <lb/>that are attributed to the Archaic genome. This hypothesis is supported by the results of Prüfer et <lb/>al. (35) which show evidence of Neandertal gene flow into Denisovans. <lb/>4.3 IBD Segment Lengths of Human Populations <lb/>Figure 22 shows the density of the lengths of IBD segments that are private to Asians vs. the <lb/>density of the lengths of IBD segments that are private to Europeans. Since IBD segments are <lb/>private to each continental population, the densities are based on disjoint IBD segment sets. Both <lb/>show three peaks at similar lengths. Asians show a global peak at 26,500 bp, while Europeans <lb/>show a global peak at 25,300 bp. The other peaks are around 21,000 bp and 49,000 bp. For Asians <lb/>the peak at 49,000 bp is larger than for Europeans resulting in a lower global peak. <lb/>Figure 23A shows the density of lengths of IBD segments that are private to Asians vs. lengths <lb/>of IBD segments that are only shared between Asians and Africans. Figure 23B shows the same <lb/>plot for Europeans instead of Asians. A small difference is visible in the global peaks of length <lb/>distributions of IBD segments that are private to a continental population and those shared with <lb/>Africans (blue dashed lines): 26,500 vs. 19,000 bp for Asians and 25,300 vs. 23,500 bp for <lb/>Europeans. Segments that are also shared with Africans show an enrichment at shorter lengths <lb/>compared to segments that are private to either Asians or Europeans. <lb/>Figure 24A shows the density of lengths of IBD segments that are private to Asians vs. lengths <lb/>of IBD segments that are shared between Asians, Europeans, and Africans. Figure 24B shows the <lb/>same plot for Europeans instead of Asians. Of course, the peaks for Asians and Europeans are the <lb/>same as in Figure 23. Again segments that are shared by all three continental populations show an <lb/>enrichment at shorter lengths compared to segments that are private to either Asians or Europeans. <lb/>We already assumed that IBD segments that are shared by all population groups predate the Out-<lb/>of-Africa split and therefore have to be very old. These results confirm our assumptions since we <lb/>show that these segments are very short. <lb/>Next we investigated the effect on the length distribution if IBD segments are removed that <lb/>are shared by Africans. Figure 25A shows the density of lengths of IBD segments that are private <lb/>to Asians vs. the density of IBD segment lengths shared by Asians and Europeans, but not by <lb/>Africans. In Figure 25B, the same plot as in Figure 25A is shown, but now compared to IBD <lb/>segments that are private to Europeans. In Figure 24A and B, the density for IBD segments that <lb/>are shared with Africans, has high values for shorter IBD segments (blue). In Figure 25A and <lb/>B, this range of high values vanishes, because IBD segments that are shared with Africans are <lb/>removed. A higher density region at longer segment length becomes visible for IBD segments that <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<body>are shared by Europeans and Asians, but not by Africans compared to segments that are private to <lb/>either Asians or Europeans. <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>Asian <lb/>European <lb/>IBD Length Distributions Chr. 1: European vs. Asian <lb/>Figure 22: Density of lengths of IBD segments that are private to Asians vs. the analogous density <lb/>for Europeans. Interesting peaks are marked by dashed lines. Asians have a global peak at 26,500 <lb/>bp (red), while Europeans have the global peaks at 25,300 bp (blue). Both have smaller peaks at <lb/>21,000 bp and 49,000 bp. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>Asian <lb/>Asian/African <lb/>IBD Length Distributions Chr. 1: Asian vs. Asian/African <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>European <lb/>European/African <lb/>IBD Length Distributions Chr. 1: European vs. European/African <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 23: Panel A: Density of lengths of IBD segments that are private to Asians vs. density <lb/>of IBD segment lengths shared only by Asians and Africans. Panel B: Density of lengths of <lb/>IBD segments that are private to Europeans vs. density of IBD segment lengths shared only by <lb/>Europeans and Africans. African-Asian IBD segments have peaks at 19,000 bp, 24,000 bp, and <lb/>52,500 bp (blue dashed lines in panel B). African-European IBD segments have a global peak at <lb/>23,500 bp and smaller peaks at 11,000 bp, 29,500 bp, 48,000 bp, and 52,000 bp (blue dashed lines <lb/>in panel B). The global Asian peak is at 26,500 bp (red dashed line in panel A), while the global <lb/>peak for Europeans is at 25,300 bp (red dashed line in panel B). Both have smaller peaks at 21,000 <lb/>bp and 49,000 bp. <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>Asian <lb/>European/Asian/African <lb/>IBD Length Distributions Chr. 1: European/Asian/African vs. Asian <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>European <lb/>European/Asian/African <lb/>IBD Length Distributions Chr. 1: European/Asian/African vs. European <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 24: Panel A: Density of lengths of IBD segments that are private to Asians vs. density of <lb/>IBD segment lengths shared by Asians, Europeans, and Africans. Panel B: Density of lengths of <lb/>IBD segments that are private to Europeans vs. density of IBD segment lengths shared by Asians, <lb/>Europeans, and Africans. Again segments that are shared by all three continental populations <lb/>show an enrichment at shorter lengths compared to segments that are private to either Asians or <lb/>Europeans (blue vs. red). <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<body>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>Asian <lb/>European/Asian <lb/>IBD Length Distributions Chr. 1: European/Asian vs. Asian (No AFR) <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>European <lb/>European/Asian <lb/>IBD Length Distributions Chr. 1: European/Asian vs. European (No AFR) <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 25: Panel A: Density of lengths of IBD segments that are private to Asians vs. density <lb/>of IBD segment lengths shared by Asians and Europeans, but not by Africans meaning African-<lb/>sharing IBD segments are removed as opposed to Figure 24A. Panel B: The same plot as in panel <lb/>A, but IBD segments that are shared by Europeans and Asians are compared to IBD segments that <lb/>are private to Europeans. African-sharing IBD segments are removed as opposed to Figure 24B. <lb/>Both panels show that removing IBD segments shared with Africans in turn removes the higher <lb/>densities at lower segment lengths that were present in Figure 24. Instead the densities for longer <lb/>segment lengths are higher for IBD segments shared between Europeans and Asians (no Africans) <lb/>compared to segments that are private to either Asians or Europeans. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>4.4 Lengths of IBD Segments that Match the Denisova or Neandertal Genome <lb/>4.4.1 Lengths of IBD Segments that Match the Denisova Genome <lb/>Figure 26A shows the density of the lengths of all IBD segments (human genome) vs. the density <lb/>of the lengths of IBD segments that match the Denisova genome. The length density of all IBD <lb/>segments has a peak at 25,000 bp, while the length distribution of IBD with the Denisova genome <lb/>has a peak at 5,000 bp. Clearly, segments of IBD with the Denisova genome are shorter and <lb/>therefore older than those solely shared among present day humans (red density above blue at <lb/>the left hand side). We were interested in how different populations share the Denisova genome. <lb/>Figure 26B shows densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Denisova genome and <lb/>are enriched by a particular continental population. For all populations combined as well as for <lb/>Africans and Europeans, a density peak is visible between 5,000 and 6,000 bp. Europeans have <lb/>their global peak at 13,500 bp and additional peaks at 19,500 bp, 28,000 bp, and 37,500 bp. <lb/>Denisova-matching segments that are shared by Asians are generally longer with a global peak at <lb/>31,000 bp and additional smaller peaks at 9,500 bp, 20,000 bp, and 39,500 bp. These densities <lb/>seem to reveal that there was a gene flow from Denisovans into the Asian genome outside Africa. <lb/>However, also Europeans show some hints of introgression from the Denisovans after migration <lb/>out of Africa. <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Denisova <lb/>All <lb/>IBD Length Distributions: All vs. Denisova Chr. 1 <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Populations <lb/>Denisova All <lb/>Denisova African <lb/>Denisova Asian <lb/>Denisova European <lb/>Denisova−Matching IBD Length Distributions per Population Chr. 1 <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 26: Panel A: Density of the lengths of all IBD segments vs. the lengths of IBD segments <lb/>that match the Denisova genome. The dashed lines indicate the peaks at 9,000 bp for the Denisova <lb/>and 24,200 bp for the human genome. Panel B: Densities of lengths of IBD segments that match <lb/>the Denisova genome and are enriched in a particular population. The dashed lines indicate density <lb/>peaks. For all populations combined as well as for Africans and Europeans, a density peak is <lb/>visible between 5,000 and 6,000 bp. Europeans have their global peak at 13,500 bp and additional <lb/>peaks at 19,500 bp, 28,000 bp, and 37,500 bp. Denisova-matching segments that are shared by <lb/>Asians are generally longer with a global peak at 31,000 bp and additional smaller peaks at 9,500 <lb/>bp, 20,000 bp, and 39,500 bp. <lb/>These peaks can be seen more clearly if only IBD segments are considered that are private <lb/>to a population. Figure 27A shows densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Denisova <lb/>genome and are private to a population. For all populations together, the peak of the length density <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<body>is at 6,000 bp; for IBD segments private to Africans, it is at 7,000 bp; for IBD segments private <lb/>to Europeans, it is at 12,000bp; and for IBD segments private to Asians, it is at 27,000 bp. The <lb/>density of IBD lengths that match the Denisova genome and are private to Asians is also high <lb/>around 40,000 bp and 54,000 bp. Europeans have an additional peak at 46,000 bp. Figure 27B <lb/>shows densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Denisova genome and are private to <lb/>Africans vs. IBD segments that are not observed in Africans. The global peak for Africans is <lb/>at 5,000 bp, while the density of lengths of IBD segments that are not observed in Africans has <lb/>a global peak at 27,000 bp. Africans have older segments probably stemming from common <lb/>ancestors of Denisovans and humans. For non-African populations, the high densities for longer <lb/>IBD segments hint at an introgression from Denisovans after migration out of Africa. <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>6e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Populations <lb/>Denisova All <lb/>Denisova African <lb/>Denisova Asian <lb/>Denisova European <lb/>Denisova−Matching IBD Length Distributions per Exclusive Population Chr. 1 <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>6e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>Africans <lb/>No Africans <lb/>Denisova IBD Length Distributions: Africans vs. No Africans Chr. 1 <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 27: Panel A: Densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Denisova genome and <lb/>are private to a population. The peaks are at 6,000 for all IBD segments matching the Denisova <lb/>genome, 7,000 for Africans, 12,000 for Europeans, and 27,000 for Asians. Panel B: Densities <lb/>of lengths of IBD segments that match the Denisova genome and are private to Africans vs. IBD <lb/>segments that are not observed in Africans. The global peak for Africans is at 5,000 bp, while the <lb/>density of lengths of IBD segments that are not observed in Africans has a global peak at 27,000 <lb/>bp. <lb/>4.4.2 Lengths of IBD Segments that Match the Neandertal Genome <lb/>Figure 28A shows the density of the lengths of all IBD segments (human genome) vs. the density <lb/>of the lengths of IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome. The length density of all <lb/>IBD segments has a peak at 25,000 bp, while the length distribution of IBD segments with the <lb/>Neandertal genome (the part of the IBD segment that matches the Neandertal genome) has peaks <lb/>at 5,500 bp, 23,000 bp, and 41,000 bp. Figure 28B shows densities of lengths of IBD segments that <lb/>match the Neandertal genome and are enriched in a particular continental population. The peaks of <lb/>the length distribution for IBD segments that are shared by all populations combined are at 6,000 <lb/>bp and 23,000 bp. Africans have their global peak also around 6,000 bp. Europeans have their <lb/>global peak at 24,000 bp and additional peaks at 39,000 bp and 52,000 bp. The density of lengths <lb/>of IBD segments that are private to Asians and match the Neandertal genome has a global peak at <lb/>27,000 bp and a second peak around 42,000 bp. The density peak for Africans is clearly separated <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>from the density peaks for Europeans and Asians which almost match each other. This hints at <lb/>introgression from the Neandertals into anatomically modern humans that were the ancestors of <lb/>Europeans and Asians after these humans left Africa. The higher density of short IBD segments <lb/>which are prominent in Africans in the range of 5,000-15,000 bp hints at old DNA segments that <lb/>humans share with the Neandertal genome. Again our results contradict the hypothesis of Prüfer <lb/>et al. (35) that Neandertal ancestry in Africans is due to back-to-Africa admixture, but instead hint <lb/>at an earlier gene-flow within Africa. <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>All <lb/>IBD Length Distributions: All vs. Neandertal Chr. 1 <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Populations <lb/>Neandertal All <lb/>Neandertal African <lb/>Neandertal Asian <lb/>Neandertal European <lb/>Neandertal−Matching IBD Length Distributions per Population Chr. 1 <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 28: Panel A: Density of the lengths of all IBD segments vs. the lengths of IBD segments <lb/>that match the Neandertal genome. The dashed lines indicate the peaks of densities at 25,000 bp <lb/>for all IBD segments (blue) and at 5,500 bp, 23,000 bp, and 41,000 bp for Neandertal-matching <lb/>segments (red). Panel B: Densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome <lb/>and are enriched in a particular population. The dashed lines indicate the density peaks around <lb/>6,000 bp for Africans, 6,000 bp and 23,000 bp for all populations combined, 27,000 bp and 42,000 <lb/>bp for Asians, and 24,000 bp, 39,000 bp, and 52,000 bp for Europeans. <lb/>Next we considered IBD segments that are private to a continental population. Figure 29A <lb/>shows densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome and are private <lb/>to a population. The peaks are at 6,000 bp for Africans and at 7,000 bp and 24,000 bp for all <lb/>humans combined. The density for Europeans has peaks at 15,500 bp, 26,500 bp, 42,000 bp and <lb/>55,500 bp. Asians have density peaks at 26,000 bp and 41,000 bp. The densities of Asians and <lb/>Europeans agree well with each other. They have peaks at longer segment lengths compared to <lb/>Africans. Therefore, we were interested in IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome and <lb/>that are private to Africans and those which are not observed in Africans hence shared by either <lb/>Asians or Europeans or both. Figure 29B shows densities of lengths of IBD segments that match <lb/>the Neandertal genome and are private to Africans vs. IBD segments that are not observed in <lb/>Africans. The peak for Africans is around 5,000 bp, while IBD segments that are not observed in <lb/>Africans have a global length density peak at 25,000 bp and smaller peaks at 14,000 bp and 41,000 <lb/>bp. Most prominently, non-African IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome are enriched <lb/>in regions of longer segment lengths. <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<body>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Populations <lb/>Neandertal All <lb/>Neandertal African <lb/>Neandertal Asian <lb/>Neandertal European <lb/>Neandertal−Matching IBD Length Distributions per Exclusive Population Chr. 1 <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>6e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>Africans <lb/>No Africans <lb/>Neandertal IBD Length Distributions: Africans vs. No Africans Chr. 1 <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 29: Panel A: Densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome and <lb/>are private to a population. The major peaks are at 6,000 bp for Africans, 7,000 bp and 24,000 bp <lb/>for all humans combined, 15,500 bp, 26,500 bp for Europeans, and 26,000 bp for Asians. Panel <lb/>B: Densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Neandertal genome and are private to <lb/>Africans vs. IBD segments that are not observed in Africans. The peak for Africans is around <lb/>5,000 bp, while IBD segments that are not observed in Africans have a global length density peak <lb/>at 25,000 and smaller peaks at 14,000 bp and 41,000 bp. Most prominently, non-African IBD <lb/>segments that match the Neandertal genome are enriched in regions of longer segment lengths <lb/>(blue density). <lb/>4.4.3 Lengths of IBD Segments that Match Neandertal &amp; Denisova <lb/>IBD segments that match the &quot;Archaic genome&quot; are IBD segments that match both the Neandertal <lb/>and the Denisova genome. Segments matching the Archaic genome stem either from a genome of <lb/>archaic hominids which were ancestors of Neandertals and Denisovans or they stem from intro-<lb/>gression of one hominid group into another. Garrigan et al. (12) were the first to present evidence <lb/>for a prolonged period of ancestral population subdivision followed by relatively recent interbreed-<lb/>ing in the history of human populations. Later, Wall et al. (54) found evidence that suggests that <lb/>admixture between diverged hominid groups may have been a common feature of human evolu-<lb/>tion. Recently Prüfer et al. (35) published findings that suggest gene flow from Neandertals into <lb/>Denisovans as well as an additional ancestral component in Denisovans from an unknown ancient <lb/>population. <lb/>Figure 30A shows the density of the lengths of all IBD segments (human genome) vs. the <lb/>density of the lengths of IBD segments that match the Archaic genome. For the human genome, <lb/>the global density peak is again at 25,000 bp. For IBD with the Archaic genome, the global density <lb/>peak is at 6,000 bp, but smaller peak at 15,500 bp and 24,500 bp can be observed. Figure 30B <lb/>shows densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Archaic genome and are enriched in <lb/>a particular continental population. The global density peak for all populations as well as for <lb/>Africans can be seen around 6,000 bp. Europeans and Asians have peaks around 9,000 bp, 16,000 <lb/>bp, 26,000 bp, and 42,000 bp. Similar to IBD segments matching the Denisova or Neandertal <lb/>genome separately, segments shared by Europeans or Asians are longer than segments shared by <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>Africans. <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Archaic <lb/>All <lb/>IBD Length Distributions: All vs. Archaic Chr. 1 <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Populations <lb/>Archaic All <lb/>Archaic African <lb/>Archaic Asian <lb/>Archaic European <lb/>Archaic−Matching IBD Length Distributions per Population Chr. 1 <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 30: Panel A: Density of the lengths of all IBD segments vs. the lengths of IBD segments <lb/>that match the Archaic genome. The dashed lines indicate the peaks of densities at 6,000 bp and <lb/>25,000 bp as well as the smaller peaks at 15,500 bp and 24,500 bp. Panel B: Densities of lengths <lb/>of IBD segments that match the Archaic genome and are enriched in a particular population. The <lb/>dashed lines indicate the density peaks with the global peak for all populations combined as well <lb/>as for Africans around 6,000 bp. Europeans and Asians have peaks at longer segment lengths <lb/>ranging from 9,000 bp to 42,000 bp. <lb/>Next we considered IBD segments that are private to a continental population. Figure 31A <lb/>shows densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Archaic genome and are private to a <lb/>population. All populations combined, as well as each population separately have a peak between <lb/>7,000 bp and 10,000 bp. Asians have their global peak between 17,500 bp and 26,000 bp. IBD <lb/>segments that are private to Europeans have an additional peak at 34,000 bp. Figure 31B shows <lb/>densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Archaic genome and are private to Africans vs. <lb/>IBD segments that are not observed in Africans. The global peak for Africans is at 5,000 bp, while <lb/>lengths of IBD segments that are not observed in Africans have peaks at 15,000 bp and 26,500 bp. <lb/>However, Africans have also a peak at 33,000 bp. Most prominently, non-African IBD segments <lb/>that match the Archaic genome are enriched at larger segment lengths. This enrichment seems to <lb/>be caused by events after humans migrated out of Africa. The introgression from the Neandertal <lb/>into ancestors of modern humans may also have introduced a part of the Denisova genome that <lb/>has been contained in the Neandertal genome, or vice versa. We would consider this part of the <lb/>human genome as matching the Archaic genome. <lb/></body>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">4 Analyses of Lengths of IBD Segments <lb/></note>

			<body>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Populations <lb/>Archaic All <lb/>Archaic African <lb/>Archaic Asian <lb/>Archaic European <lb/>Archaic−Matching IBD Length Distributions per Exclusive Population Chr. 1 <lb/>0e+00 <lb/>1e−05 <lb/>2e−05 <lb/>3e−05 <lb/>4e−05 <lb/>5e−05 <lb/>6e−05 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>60000 <lb/>IBD Length <lb/>Density <lb/>Population <lb/>Africans <lb/>No Africans <lb/>Archaic IBD Length Distributions: Africans vs. No Africans Chr. 1 <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 31: Panel A: Densities of lengths of IBD segments that match the Archaic genome and <lb/>are private to a population. The peaks are between 7,000 bp and 10,000 bp for all populations <lb/>combined, as well as each population separately. Asians have their global peak between 17,500 <lb/>bp and 26,000 bp while Europeans have an additional peak at 34,000 bp. Panel B: Densities <lb/>of lengths of IBD segments that match the Archaic genome and are private to Africans vs. IBD <lb/>segments that are not observed in Africans. The global peak for Africans is at 5,000 bp, while <lb/>lengths of IBD segments that are not observed in Africans have peaks at 15,000 bp and 26,500 <lb/>bp. However, Africans have also a peak at 33,000 bp. Non-African IBD segments that match the <lb/>Archaic genome are enriched at larger segment lengths (blue density). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes <lb/> Figure 32 shows a typical example of an IBD segment that matches the Denisova genome and is <lb/>shared exclusively among Asians. Figure 33 shows an IBD segment that matches the Denisova <lb/>genome and is shared by Africans and one Admixed American. <lb/>Figure 34 shows an example of an IBD segment that matches the Neandertal genome and is <lb/>shared by Europeans, Asians, Admixed Americans, and Americans with African ancestry from <lb/>SW US. Figure 35 shows an example of an IBD segment that matches the Neandertal genome and <lb/>is shared by Europeans and Asians. Figure 36 shows an IBD segment that matches the Neandertal <lb/>genome and is found exclusively in Asians. <lb/>Figure 37 shows an example of an IBD segment matching the Neandertal and the Denisova <lb/>genome shared by Asians, Admixed Americans, and Americans with African ancestry from SW <lb/>US. Figure 38 shows an example of an IBD segment matching the Neandertal and the Denisova <lb/>genome shared by Africans and Admixed Americans. <lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>chr: 1 || pos: 47,679,010 || length: 33kbp || #SNPs: 21 || #Samples: 17 <lb/>47,662,706 <lb/>47,670,130 <lb/>47,677,630 <lb/>47,685,130 <lb/>47,692,630 <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Ancestor <lb/>model L <lb/>NA19067_JPT <lb/>NA18985_JPT <lb/>NA18961_JPT <lb/>NA18949_JPT <lb/>NA18939_JPT <lb/>NA18639_CHB <lb/>NA18636_CHB <lb/>NA18628_CHB <lb/>NA18605_CHB <lb/>NA18592_CHB <lb/>NA18566_CHB <lb/>HG00689_CHS <lb/>HG00653_CHS <lb/>HG00596_CHS <lb/>HG00536_CHS <lb/>HG00525_CHS <lb/>HG00458_CHS <lb/>Figure 32: Example of an IBD segment matching the Denisova genome shared exclusively among <lb/>Asians. The data analyzed by HapFABIA were genotypes from chromosome 1 of the 1000 <lb/>Genomes Project. The rows give all individuals that contain the IBD segment and columns con-<lb/>secutive SNVs. Major alleles are shown in yellow, minor alleles of tagSNVs in violet, and minor <lb/>alleles of other SNVs in cyan. The row labeled &quot;model L&quot; indicates tagSNVs identified by Hap-<lb/>FABIA in violet. The rows &quot;Ancestor&quot;, &quot;Neandertal&quot;, and &quot;Denisova&quot; show bases of the respective <lb/>genomes in violet if they match the minor allele of the tagSNVs (in yellow otherwise). For the <lb/>&quot;Ancestor genome&quot; we used the reconstructed common ancestor sequence that was provided as <lb/>part of the 1000 Genomes Project data. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>chr: 1 || pos: 197,808,917 || length: 44kbp || #SNPs: 134 || #Samples: 36 <lb/>197,786,925 <lb/>197,793,161 <lb/>197,799,461 <lb/>197,805,761 <lb/>197,812,061 <lb/>197,818,361 <lb/>197,824,661 <lb/>197,830,909 <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Ancestor <lb/>model L <lb/>NA20356_ASW <lb/>NA20340_ASW <lb/>NA20298_ASW <lb/>NA20281_ASW <lb/>NA20276_ASW <lb/>NA20126_ASW <lb/>NA19982_ASW <lb/>NA19920_ASW <lb/>NA19901_ASW <lb/>NA19761_MXL <lb/>NA19703_ASW <lb/>NA19462_LWK <lb/>NA19456_LWK <lb/>NA19437_LWK <lb/>NA19435_LWK <lb/>NA19404_LWK <lb/>NA19376_LWK <lb/>NA19352_LWK <lb/>NA19351_LWK <lb/>NA19334_LWK <lb/>NA19321_LWK <lb/>NA19190_YRI <lb/>NA19175_YRI <lb/>NA19172_YRI <lb/>NA19131_YRI <lb/>NA19117_YRI <lb/>NA19099_YRI <lb/>NA19095_YRI <lb/>NA19044_LWK <lb/>NA18917_YRI <lb/>NA18912_YRI <lb/>NA18873_YRI <lb/>NA18861_YRI <lb/>NA18858_YRI <lb/>NA18520_YRI <lb/>NA18505_YRI <lb/>Figure 33: Example of an IBD segment matching the Denisova genome shared by Africans and <lb/>one Admixed American. Only the first part of the IBD segment matches the Denisova genome and <lb/>part of the IBD segment is shared by the majority of individuals. Many tagSNVs are also present <lb/>in the reconstructed ancestor sequence, but they are not present in the Neandertal genome. See <lb/>Figure 32 for a description. <lb/></body>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>chr: 1 || pos: 212,974,708 || length: 53kbp || #SNPs: 121 || #Samples: 42 <lb/>212,947,981 <lb/>212,955,108 <lb/>212,962,308 <lb/>212,969,508 <lb/>212,976,708 <lb/>212,983,908 <lb/>212,991,108 <lb/>212,998,308 <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Ancestor <lb/>model L <lb/>NA20814_TSI <lb/>NA20799_TSI <lb/>NA20775_TSI <lb/>NA20757_TSI <lb/>NA20581_TSI <lb/>NA20538_TSI <lb/>NA20530_TSI <lb/>NA20512_TSI <lb/>NA20363_ASW <lb/>NA20299_ASW <lb/>NA19785_MXL <lb/>NA19681_MXL <lb/>NA19000_JPT <lb/>NA18990_JPT <lb/>NA18973_JPT <lb/>NA18952_JPT <lb/>NA18622_CHB <lb/>NA18548_CHB <lb/>NA18537_CHB <lb/>NA12763_CEU <lb/>NA12750_CEU <lb/>NA12275_CEU <lb/>NA12004_CEU <lb/>NA11920_CEU <lb/>NA11892_CEU <lb/>NA10847_CEU <lb/>NA07347_CEU <lb/>HG01620_IBS <lb/>HG01618_IBS <lb/>HG01488_CLM <lb/>HG01461_CLM <lb/>HG01389_CLM <lb/>HG00736_PUR <lb/>HG00699_CHS <lb/>HG00583_CHS <lb/>HG00349_FIN <lb/>HG00318_FIN <lb/>HG00312_FIN <lb/>HG00116_GBR <lb/>HG00111_GBR <lb/>HG00100_GBR <lb/>HG00096_GBR <lb/>Figure 34: Example of an IBD segment matching the Neandertal genome shared by Europeans, <lb/>Asians, Admixed Americans, and Americans with African ancestry from SW US. See Figure 32 <lb/>for a description. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<body>chr: 1 || pos: 82,757,288 || length: 15kbp || #SNPs: 35 || #Samples: 16 <lb/>82,750,016 <lb/>82,753,053 <lb/>82,756,153 <lb/>82,759,253 <lb/>82,762,353 <lb/>82,764,560 <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Ancestor <lb/>model L <lb/>NA19068_JPT <lb/>NA18986_JPT <lb/>NA18963_JPT <lb/>NA18945_JPT <lb/>NA18577_CHB <lb/>NA18571_CHB <lb/>NA18550_CHB <lb/>NA18547_CHB <lb/>NA18525_CHB <lb/>HG00556_CHS <lb/>HG00404_CHS <lb/>HG00381_FIN <lb/>HG00366_FIN <lb/>HG00343_FIN <lb/>HG00324_FIN <lb/>HG00310_FIN <lb/>Figure 35: Example of an IBD segment matching the Neandertal genome shared by Europeans <lb/>and Asians. See Figure 32 for a description. <lb/></body>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>chr: 1 || pos: 227,164,945 || length: 47kbp || #SNPs: 65 || #Samples: 23 <lb/>227,141,338 <lb/>227,147,574 <lb/>227,153,874 <lb/>227,160,174 <lb/>227,166,474 <lb/>227,172,774 <lb/>227,179,074 <lb/>227,185,374 <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Ancestor <lb/>model L <lb/>NA18948_JPT <lb/>NA18642_CHB <lb/>NA18632_CHB <lb/>NA18619_CHB <lb/>NA18602_CHB <lb/>NA18595_CHB <lb/>NA18593_CHB <lb/>NA18577_CHB <lb/>NA18576_CHB <lb/>NA18563_CHB <lb/>NA18561_CHB <lb/>NA18559_CHB <lb/>NA18550_CHB <lb/>NA18542_CHB <lb/>NA18534_CHB <lb/>HG00708_CHS <lb/>HG00705_CHS <lb/>HG00663_CHS <lb/>HG00654_CHS <lb/>HG00608_CHS <lb/>HG00596_CHS <lb/>HG00525_CHS <lb/>HG00479_CHS <lb/>Figure 36: Example of an IBD segment matching the Neandertal genome shared exclusively <lb/>among Asians. See Figure 32 for a description. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<body>chr: 1 || pos: 160,204,408 || length: 41kbp || #SNPs: 72 || #Samples: 23 <lb/>160,183,713 <lb/>160,192,028 <lb/>160,200,428 <lb/>160,208,828 <lb/>160,217,228 <lb/>160,225,103 <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Ancestor <lb/>model L <lb/>NA19758_MXL <lb/>NA19701_ASW <lb/>NA19068_JPT <lb/>NA19057_JPT <lb/>NA18992_JPT <lb/>NA18978_JPT <lb/>NA18951_JPT <lb/>NA18942_JPT <lb/>NA18940_JPT <lb/>NA18643_CHB <lb/>NA18636_CHB <lb/>NA18615_CHB <lb/>NA18571_CHB <lb/>NA18559_CHB <lb/>HG01455_CLM <lb/>HG00699_CHS <lb/>HG00698_CHS <lb/>HG00684_CHS <lb/>HG00634_CHS <lb/>HG00610_CHS <lb/>HG00476_CHS <lb/>HG00442_CHS <lb/>HG00437_CHS <lb/>Figure 37: Example of an IBD segment matching the Neandertal and the Denisova genome shared <lb/>by Asians, Admixed Americans, and Americans with African ancestry from SW US. See Figure 32 <lb/>for a description. <lb/></body>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">5 Examples of IBD Segments that Match Ancient Genomes <lb/></note>

			<body>chr: 1 || pos: 36,504,059 || length: 39kbp || #SNPs: 119 || #Samples: 24 <lb/>36,484,539 <lb/>36,492,854 <lb/>36,501,254 <lb/>36,509,654 <lb/>36,518,054 <lb/>36,523,579 <lb/>Denisova <lb/>Neandertal <lb/>Ancestor <lb/>model L <lb/>NA20348_ASW <lb/>NA20344_ASW <lb/>NA20339_ASW <lb/>NA20336_ASW <lb/>NA20322_ASW <lb/>NA20317_ASW <lb/>NA19749_MXL <lb/>NA19444_LWK <lb/>NA19443_LWK <lb/>NA19429_LWK <lb/>NA19324_LWK <lb/>NA19223_YRI <lb/>NA19207_YRI <lb/>NA19197_YRI <lb/>NA19190_YRI <lb/>NA19131_YRI <lb/>NA19129_YRI <lb/>NA19096_YRI <lb/>NA18861_YRI <lb/>NA18504_YRI <lb/>NA18499_YRI <lb/>NA18489_YRI <lb/>HG01271_CLM <lb/>HG01052_PUR <lb/>Figure 38: Example of an IBD segment matching the Neandertal and the Denisova genome shared <lb/>by Africans and Admixed Americans. See Figure 32 for a description. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">6 Conclusion <lb/></note>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<body>6 Conclusion <lb/>We applied HapFABIA to the 1000 Genomes Project data to extract very short identity by descent <lb/>(IBD) segments and analyzed the IBD sharing patterns of human populations, Neandertals, and <lb/>Denisovans. <lb/>Some IBD segments are shared with (1) the reconstructed ancestral genome of humans and <lb/>other primates, (2) the Neandertal genome, and/or (3) the Denisova genome. We could confirm an <lb/>introgression from Denisovans into ancestors of Asians after their migration out of Africa. Further-<lb/>more, IBD sharing hints at a gene flow from Neandertals into ancestors of Asians and Europeans <lb/>after they left Africa (to a larger extend into ancestors of Asians). Interestingly, many Neandertal-<lb/>or Denisova-matching IBD segments are predominantly observed in Africans -some of them <lb/>even exclusively. IBD segments shared between Africans and Neandertals or Denisovans are <lb/>strikingly short, therefore we assume that they are very old. This may indicate that these segments <lb/>stem from ancestors of humans, Neandertals, and Denisovans and have survived in Africans. <lb/>In the near future the 1000 Genomes Project will be completed by genome sequences from <lb/>additional populations, the UK10K project extents the subset of European genomes, and, most <lb/>importantly, more ancient genomes will be successfully sequenced (Ust-Ishim, El Sidrón, etc.). <lb/>Therefore, we expect that the analysis of the population structure by sharing patterns of very short <lb/>IBD segments will become an increasingly important method in population genetics and its results <lb/>will become more and more fine-grained. <lb/></body>

			<page>50 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">A Are Rare Variants Recent or Old? <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Appendices <lb/>A Are Rare Variants Recent or Old? <lb/>Rare variants are found to be old which might seem to contradict results of other researchers. <lb/>However, the conclusion that rare variants are, in general, recent does not contradict our re-<lb/>sults. On the contrary, that the majority of IBD segments extracted by HapFABIA is found in <lb/>Africans can explain why three times as many variants with 0.5-5% minor allele frequency are <lb/>found in Africans as in Europeans or Asians in the 1000 Genomes Project (48). In particular, <lb/>if rare variants are caused by a recent population growth, then the numbers found by the 1000 <lb/>Genomes Project (48) are difficult to interpret. We want to discuss two reasons why rare variants <lb/>may be old. <lb/>(I) Many rare variants are old, however, most rare variants may be recent, e.g. because of a <lb/>recent growth in population. We did not consider private variants and have a bias toward less <lb/>rare variants because, the more individuals share an IBD segment, the higher its significance, <lb/>the more likely it is detected by HapFABIA. In our analysis, only 39% of the rare variants (not <lb/>counting private variants) are in IBD segments. Therefore, the remaining majority of rare and <lb/>private variants might be recent. <lb/>The vast majority of IBD segments is found in Africans. This would explain why Africans <lb/>have more rare and low-frequency variants than Europeans or Asians. The publication of the 1000 <lb/>Genomes Project (48) reports: <lb/>&quot;individuals from populations with substantial African ancestry (YRI, LWK and ASW) <lb/>carry up to three times as many low-frequency variants (0.5-5% frequency) as those <lb/>of European or East Asian origin,&quot; <lb/>Table S14 in the supplementary information of the publication of the 1000 Genomes Project (48) <lb/>provides the number of derived variants per individual in each population in its last rows (DAF <lb/>denotes &quot;derived allele frequency&quot;, i.e. the frequency of the mutation): <lb/>African <lb/>European <lb/>ASW <lb/>LWK <lb/>YRI <lb/>CEU <lb/>FIN <lb/>GBR <lb/>IBS <lb/>TSI <lb/>DAF &lt;0.5% 116,216 152,267 122,978 <lb/>30,034 <lb/>32,918 <lb/>31,944 <lb/>36,129 <lb/>33,425 <lb/>DAF 0.5-5% 558,996 649,303 683,239 143,987 146,737 146,802 155,270 146,066 <lb/>Asian <lb/>Admixed American <lb/>CHB <lb/>CHS <lb/>JPT <lb/>CLM <lb/>MXL <lb/>PUR <lb/>DAF &lt;0.5% <lb/>36,081 <lb/>40,974 <lb/>45,107 <lb/>45,184 <lb/>38,654 <lb/>48,892 <lb/>DAF 0.5-5% 119,668 118,137 120,115 189,257 163,737 214,430 <lb/>Recent variants are supposed to be derived variants. The table shows about four times more <lb/>variants with derived allele frequency of 0.5-5% in Africans than in other populations (if we ignore <lb/>the Admixed Americans that have African admixture). For derived allele frequency &lt; 0.5%, we <lb/>observe 2.5 times more variants in Africans than in Europeans or Asians. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">A Are Rare Variants Recent or Old? <lb/></note>

			<page>51 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">(II) Many rare variants are old, however, compared to common SNPs, they are recent, i.e. the <lb/>temporal relations remain, but variants are dated further back. We state in the manuscript that <lb/>many rare variants are old and from times before humans migrated out of Africa. However, many <lb/>common SNPs are even older and stem from common ancestors of human and chimpanzee. This <lb/>means that many rare variants are old, but compared to common SNPs they are recent. <lb/>The fact that common SNPs are old is supported by findings of the Chimpanzee Consortium. In <lb/>Hacia et al. (17) it was found that, of 397 human SNP sites, 214 were ancestral (shared with <lb/>common ancestors of chimpanzee and human). Of the ancestral SNPs, 1/4 had the minor allele as <lb/>ancestral allele. For the chimpanzee genome (49), it was found that <lb/>&quot;Of ∼7.2 million SNPs mapped to the human genome in the current public database, <lb/>we could assign the alleles as ancestral or derived in 80% of the cases according to <lb/>which allele agrees with the chimpanzee genome sequence&quot; <lb/>and that <lb/>&quot;a significant proportion of derived alleles have high frequencies: 9.1% of derived <lb/>alleles have frequency ≥ 80%.&quot; <lb/>According to (49, Suppl. Fig. S9) about 25% of the derived alleles have frequency ≥ 50% in <lb/>which case the minor allele is the ancestral allele. <lb/>That some SNPs are very old and that some haplotypes are shared between humans and chim-<lb/>panzee was also found in Leffler et al. (26): <lb/>&quot;We conducted a genome-wide scan for long-lived balancing selection by looking <lb/>for combinations of SNPs shared between humans and chimpanzees. In addition to <lb/>the major histocompatibility complex, we identified 125 regions in which the same <lb/>haplotypes are segregating in the two species,&quot; <lb/>In a recent publication (11), it was found that <lb/>&quot;The average age across all SNVs was 34,200 ± 900 years (± s.d.) in European <lb/>Americans and 47,600 ± 1,500 years in African Americans, and these estimates were <lb/>robust to sequencing errors [...]&quot;. <lb/> The authors further write <lb/>&quot;SNVs shared between European Americans and African Americans were signifi-<lb/>cantly older (104,400 years and 115,800 years for European Americans and African <lb/>Americans, respectively)&quot;. <lb/>These figures are visualized as bar plots in Figure 39. <lb/></div>

			<page>52 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">A Are Rare Variants Recent or Old? <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">se that resulted in changes within groups (t-test; P , 0.00001 by <lb/>mutation; Supplementary Fig. 10a). These differences in average <lb/>le age are probably due to varying intensities of selective constraint <lb/>ong different classes of SNVs 12 . Consistent with this prediction, we <lb/>erved significantly higher values of the neutrality index, a measure <lb/>he direction and degree of departure from neutral evolution, in <lb/>omic regions enriched for younger variants (Spearman&apos;s correla-<lb/>; P 5 0.004 and P 5 0.001 for European Americans and African <lb/>ericans, respectively; Supplementary Fig. 11), indicating a higher <lb/>den of deleterious SNVs. <lb/>o more directly identify putatively deleterious SNVs, we used four <lb/>ctional prediction methods (SIFT 13 , PolyPhen2 (ref. 14), a likelihood <lb/>o test 15 , MutationTaster 16 ) applicable to non-synonymous SNVs <lb/>and two conservation-based methods ( <lb/>plicable to all SNVs (Supplementary Inf <lb/>inverse relationship between average SN <lb/>thods that predicted a variant to be delet <lb/>predicted to be deleterious by multiple <lb/>(on average) more intense purifying sele <lb/>interest in disease mapping studies. The <lb/>predicted to be deleterious by all 6 metho <lb/>European Americans and African Ame <lb/>were less than 5,000 years old (92.9% and <lb/>and African Americans, respectively). <lb/>The strengths and weaknesses of fu <lb/>vary substantially and as a result the a <lb/>0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>100 <lb/>DAF <lb/>Proportion of SNVs (%) <lb/>a <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>Mutation age (×1,000) <lb/>Cumulative proportion <lb/>of SNVs (%) <lb/>b <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>c <lb/>Average mutation age (×1,000) <lb/>Average mutation age (×1,000) <lb/>All <lb/>Shared <lb/>Specific <lb/>d <lb/>Splice <lb/>Nonsense Non-synonymous Synonymous <lb/>0 10 20 30 40 50 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>re 1 | The vast majority of protein-coding single-nucleotide variants <lb/>se recently. a, The site-frequency spectrum for European Americans <lb/>s, red) and African Americans (AAs, blue). DAF, derived allele frequency. <lb/>umulative proportion of SNVs for a given allele age. The inset highlights the <lb/>ulative proportion of SNVs that are estimated to have arisen in the last <lb/>50,000 years. The x axis denotes allele age (3 <lb/>the cumulative proportion of SNVs (%). c, A <lb/>found in both the European Americans and <lb/>SNVs found in only one population (specific <lb/>of variants. Error bars represent s.d. <lb/>EA <lb/>those that resulted in changes within groups (t-test; P , 0.00001 by <lb/>permutation; Supplementary Fig. 10a). These differences in average <lb/>allele age are probably due to varying intensities of selective constraint <lb/>among different classes of SNVs 12 . Consistent with this prediction, we <lb/>observed significantly higher values of the neutrality index, a measure <lb/>of the direction and degree of departure from neutral evolution, in <lb/>genomic regions enriched for younger variants (Spearman&apos;s correla-<lb/>tion; P 5 0.004 and P 5 0.001 for European Americans and African <lb/>Americans, respectively; Supplementary Fig. 11), indicating a higher <lb/>burden of deleterious SNVs. <lb/>To more directly identify putatively deleterious SNVs, we used four <lb/>functional prediction methods (SIFT 13 , PolyPhen2 (ref. 14), a likelihood <lb/>ratio test 15 , MutationTaster 16 ) applicable to non-synonymous SNVs <lb/>and two conservation-based methods (GERP11 17 and PhyloP 18 ) ap-<lb/>plicable to all SNVs (Supplementary Information). We found a strong <lb/>inverse relationship between average SNV age and the number of me-<lb/>thods that predicted a variant to be deleterious (Fig. 2a, b). Thus, SNVs <lb/>predicted to be deleterious by multiple methods probably experience <lb/>(on average) more intense purifying selection and may be of particular <lb/>interest in disease mapping studies. The age of non-synonymous SNVs <lb/>predicted to be deleterious by all 6 methods was 3,000 and 6,200 years in <lb/>European Americans and African Americans, respectively, and 88.7% <lb/>were less than 5,000 years old (92.9% and 80.6% in European Americans <lb/>and African Americans, respectively). <lb/>The strengths and weaknesses of functional prediction methods <lb/>vary substantially and as a result the accuracy of any single method <lb/>0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>100 <lb/>DAF <lb/>Proportion of SNVs (%) <lb/>a <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>Mutation age (×1,000) <lb/>Cumulative proportion <lb/>of SNVs (%) <lb/>b <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>c <lb/>Average mutation age (×1,000) <lb/>Average mutation age (×1,000) <lb/>All <lb/>Shared <lb/>Specific <lb/>d <lb/>Splice <lb/>Nonsense Non-synonymous Synonymous Non-coding <lb/>0 10 20 30 40 50 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>EA <lb/>AA <lb/>Figure 1 | The vast majority of protein-coding single-nucleotide variants <lb/>arose recently. a, The site-frequency spectrum for European Americans <lb/>(EAs, red) and African Americans (AAs, blue). DAF, derived allele frequency. <lb/>b, Cumulative proportion of SNVs for a given allele age. The inset highlights the <lb/>cumulative proportion of SNVs that are estimated to have arisen in the last <lb/>50,000 years. The x axis denotes allele age (31,000) and the y axis indicates the <lb/>the cumulative proportion of SNVs (%). c, Average age for all SNVs, SNVs <lb/>found in both the European Americans and African Americans (shared), and <lb/>SNVs found in only one population (specific). d, Average age for different types <lb/>of variants. Error bars represent s.d. <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>a <lb/>Average mutation age (×1,000) <lb/>Average mutation age (×1,000) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>6 <lb/>No. methods (non-synonymous SNVs) <lb/>b <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>No. methods other SNVs <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>Mutation age (×1,000) <lb/>c <lb/>Deleterious SNVs (%) <lb/>EA <lb/>AA <lb/>&lt; 5,000 years <lb/>≥ 5,000 years <lb/>Figure 2 | Characteristics of allele age for deleterious single-nucleotide <lb/>variants. a, b, Average age of non-synonymous and other SNVs as a function of <lb/>the number of methods that predict the variant to be deleterious. Pie charts <lb/>represent the proportion of SNVs that arose less than (black) or more than <lb/>proportion of SNVs predicted to be deleterious and SNV age. Note, greater <lb/>than 99% of deleterious SNVs are estimated to have arisen in the past <lb/>150,000 years. Solid lines represent a locally weighted scatterplot smoothing <lb/>(LOESS) fit to the data. <lb/>LETTER RESEARCH <lb/>Figure 39: Left: Average age of all SNVs, &quot;Shared&quot; SNVs found both in European Americans <lb/>(red) and in African Americans (blue), and SNVs found in only one population (&quot;Specific&quot;). Right: <lb/>Average age for different functional types of variants. Both plots are taken from Fu et al. (11). <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">B Population Groups of the 1000 Genomes Project <lb/></note>

			<page>53 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">B Population Groups of the 1000 Genomes Project <lb/>The subpopulations of the 1000 Genomes Project are given in Table 2 and the locations, where the <lb/>individuals reside, are shown on the map in Figure 40. <lb/>Table 2: Overview of population groups of the 1000 Genomes Project. <lb/>Pop #Ind <lb/>Grp Location <lb/>ASW 122 AFR Americans with African ancestry from SW US <lb/>YRI 176 AFR Yoruba in Ibadan, Nigeria <lb/>LWK 194 AFR Luhya from Webuye, Kenya <lb/>CLM 120 AMR Colombians in Medellin, Colombia <lb/>MXL 132 AMR Mexicans from Los Angeles, California <lb/>PUR 110 AMR Puerto Ricans <lb/>CEU 170 EUR Utah residents with ancestry from northern and western Europe <lb/>FIN 186 EUR Finnish <lb/>GBR 178 EUR British from England and Scotland <lb/>IBS <lb/>28 EUR Iberians from Spain <lb/>TSI 196 EUR Toscani in Italy <lb/>CHB 194 ASN Han Chinese from Beijing <lb/>CHS 200 ASN Han Chinese from South <lb/>JPT 178 ASN Japanese from Tokyo, Japan <lb/>The column labeled &quot;Pop&quot; gives the population, &quot;#Ind&quot; reports the number of individuals, &quot;Grp&quot; gives the <lb/>continental group, and &quot;Location&quot; the location from where the individuals stem. <lb/></div>

			<page>54 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B Population Groups of the 1000 Genomes Project <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Figure S2. 1000 Genomes Project Phase I populations <lb/>Populations collected as part of the HapMap Project (blue) and the 1000 Genomes Project (green) <lb/>include: Europe (IBS (Iberian Populations in Spain), GBR (British from England and Scotland ), CEU <lb/>(Utah residents with ancestry from northern and western Europe), FIN (Finnish in Finland), TSI <lb/>(Toscani in Italia)); East Asia (JPT (Japanese in Tokyo, Japan), CHB (Han Chinese in Beijing, China), <lb/>CHS (Han Chinese South)); Africa (ASW (African Ancestry in SW USA), YRI (Yoruba in Ibadan, <lb/>Nigeria), LWK (Luhya in Webuye, Kenya)); Americas (MXL (Mexican Ancestry in Los Angeles, CA, <lb/>USA), PUR (Puerto Ricans in Puerto Rico), CLM (Colombians in Medellín, Colombia)). A -Total <lb/>number of samples sequenced; B -Source of DNA (blood (bld) or LCL); C -Gender composition <lb/>(Male/Female); D -Number that are part of mother-father-child trios (t), parent-child duos (d) or <lb/>singletons (s); for trios and duos, only parent samples were sequenced. <lb/>TSI <lb/>A. 98 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 50m/48f <lb/>D. 98s <lb/>FIN <lb/>A. 93 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 35m/58f <lb/>D. 93s <lb/>EUROPE <lb/>AMERICAS <lb/>AFRICA <lb/>EAST ASIA <lb/>CEU <lb/> A. 85 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 45m/40f <lb/>D. 78t/3d/4s <lb/>GBR <lb/>A. 89 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 41m/48f <lb/>D. 3d/86s <lb/>IBS <lb/>A. 14 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 7m/7f <lb/>D. 14t <lb/>JPT <lb/>A. 89 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 50m/39f <lb/>D. 89s <lb/>CHB <lb/>A. 97 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 44m/53f <lb/>D. 97s <lb/>CHS <lb/>A. 100 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 50m/50f <lb/>D. 100t <lb/>LWK <lb/>A. 97 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 48m/49f <lb/>D. 4d/93s <lb/>YRI <lb/>A. 88 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 43m/45f <lb/>D. 65t/21d/2s <lb/>ASW <lb/>A. 61 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 24m/37f <lb/>D. 28t/22d/11s <lb/>PUR <lb/>A. 55 <lb/>B. 35bld/20LCL <lb/>C. 28m/27f <lb/>D. 47t/8d <lb/>CLM <lb/>A. 60 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 29m/31f <lb/>D. 55t/5d <lb/>MXL <lb/>A. 66 <lb/>B. All LCL <lb/>C. 31m/35f <lb/>D. 59t/3d/4s <lb/>New 1000 Genomes <lb/>HapMap 3 <lb/>Los Angeles, <lb/>USA <lb/>Utah, <lb/>USA <lb/>Southwest, <lb/>USA <lb/>Ibadan, <lb/>Nigeria <lb/>Webuye, <lb/>Kenya <lb/>Spain <lb/>Great Britain <lb/>Finland <lb/>Italy <lb/>Tokyo, <lb/>Japan <lb/>Beijing, China <lb/>Hu Nan and Fu Jian <lb/>Provinces, China <lb/>Medellín, <lb/>Colombia <lb/>Puerto Rico <lb/>Figure 40: Map indicating the locations of the populations the 1000 Genomes Project phase I. <lb/>Figure taken from (48). <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">REFERENCES <lb/></note>

			<page>55 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] A. Auton, K. Bryc, A. R. Boyko, K. E. Lohmueller, J. Novembre, A. Reynolds, A. Indap, <lb/>M. H. Wright, J. D. Degenhardt, R. N. Gutenkunst, K. S. King, M. R. Nelson, and C. D. <lb/>Bustamante. Global distribution of genomic diversity underscores rich complex history of <lb/>continental human populations. Genome Research, 19(5):795-803, 2009. <lb/>[2] M. G. B. Blum and M. Jakobsson. Deep divergences of human gene trees and models of <lb/>human origins. Mol. Biol. Evol., 28(2):889-898, 2011. <lb/>[3] L. R. Botigué, B. M. Henn, S. Gravel, B. K. Maples, C. R. Gignoux, E. Corona, G. Atzmon, <lb/>E. Burns, H. Ostrer, C. Flores, J. Bertranpetit, D. Comas, and C. D. Bustamante. Gene <lb/>flow from north africa contributes to differential human genetic diversity in southern europe. <lb/>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 110(29):11791-11796, 2013. <lb/>[4] S. R. Browning. Estimation of pairwise identity by descent from dense genetic marker data <lb/>in a population sample of haplotypes. Genetics, 178(4):2123-2132, 2008. <lb/>[5] S. R. Browning and B. L. Browning. Identity by descent between distant relatives: Detection <lb/>and applications. Annu. Rev. Genet., 46:617-633, 2012. <lb/>[6] K. Bryc, A. Auton, M. R. Nelson, J. R. Oksenberg, S. L. Hauser, S. Williams, A. Froment, J.-<lb/>M. Bodo, C. Wambebe, S. A. Tishkoff, et al. Genome-wide patterns of population structure <lb/>and admixture in west africans and african americans. P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 107(2):786-<lb/>791, 2009. <lb/>[7] S. Carmi, P. F. Palamara, V. Vacic, T. Lencz, A. Darvasi, and I. Pe&apos;er. The variance of <lb/>identity-by-descent sharing in the wright-fisher model. Genetics, 193(3):911-928, 2013. <lb/>[8] D.-A. Clevert, A. Mitterecker, A. Mayr, G. Klambauer, M. Tuefferd, A. DeBondt, W. Talloen, <lb/>H. W. H. Göhlmann, and S. Hochreiter. cn.FARMS: a latent variable model to detect copy <lb/>number variations in microarray data with a low false discovery rate. Nucleic Acids Res., <lb/>39(12):e79, 2011. <lb/>[9] M. Currat and L. Excoffier. Modern humans did not admix with neanderthals during their <lb/>range expansion into europe. PLoS Biol, 2(12):e421, 11 2004. <lb/>[10] A. Eriksson and A. Manica. Effect of ancient population structure on the degree of polymor-<lb/>phism shared between modern human populations and ancient hominins. Proceedings of the <lb/>National Academy of Sciences, 109(35):13956-13960, 2012. <lb/>[11] W. Fu, T. D. O&apos;Connor, G. Jun, H. M. Kang, G. Abecasis, S. M. Leal, S. Gabriel, D. Alt-<lb/>shuler, J. Shendure, D. A. Nickerson, et al. Analysis of 6,515 exomes reveals the recent <lb/>origin of most human protein-coding variants. Nature, 493(7431):216-220, 2013. <lb/>[12] D. Garrigan, Z. Mobasher, S. B. Kingan, J. A. Wilder, and M. F. Hammer. Deep haplotype <lb/>divergence and long-range linkage disequilibrium at xp21.1 provide evidence that humans <lb/>descend from a structured ancestral population. Genetics, 170(4):1849-1856, 2005. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>56 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REFERENCES <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[13] S. Gravel, B. M. Henn, R. N. Gutenkunst, A. R. Indap, G. T. Marth, A. G. Clark, F. Yu, R. A. <lb/>Gibbs, The 1000 Genomes Project, and C. D. Bustamante. Demographic history and rare <lb/>allele sharing among human populations. P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 108(29):11983-11988, <lb/>2011. <lb/>[14] S. Gravel, F. Zakharia, A. Moreno-Estrada, J. K. Byrnes, M. Muzzio, J. L. Rodriguez-Flores, <lb/>E. E. Kenny, C. R. Gignoux, B. K. Maples, W. Guiblet, J. Dutil, M. Via, K. Sandoval, <lb/>G. Bedoya, T. K. Oleksyk, A. Ruiz-Linares, E. G. Burchard, J. C. Martinez-Cruzado, C. D. <lb/>Bustamante, and The 1000 Genomes Project. Reconstructing native american migrations <lb/>from whole-genome and whole-exome data. PLoS Genet, 9(12):e1004023, 2013. <lb/>[15] R. E. Green, J. Krause, A. W. Briggs, T. Maricic, U. Stenzel, M. Kircher, N. Patterson, <lb/>H. Li, W. Zhai, M. H. Fritz, et al. A draft sequence of the Neandertal genome. Science, <lb/>328(5979):710-722, 2010. <lb/>[16] A. Gusev, P. F. Palamara, G. Aponte, Z. Zhuang, A. Darvasi, P. Gregersen, and I. Pe&apos;er. The <lb/>architecture of long-range haplotypes shared within and across populations. Mol. Biol. Evol., <lb/>29(2):473-486, 2012. <lb/>[17] J. G. Hacia, J.-B. Fan, O. Ryder, L. Jin, K. Edgemon, G. Ghandour, R. A. Mayer, B. Sun, <lb/>L. Hsie, C. M. Robbins, et al. Determination of ancestral alleles for human single-nucleotide <lb/>polymorphisms using high-density oligonucleotide arrays. Nat. Genet., 22(2):164-167, <lb/>1999. <lb/>[18] B. V. Halldorsson, D. Aguiar, R. Tarpine, and S. Istrail. The Clark phaseable sample <lb/>size problem: long-range phasing and loss of heterozygosity in GWAS. J. Comput. Biol., <lb/>18(3):323-333, 2011. <lb/>[19] S. Hochreiter. HapFABIA: Identification of very short segments of identity by descent char-<lb/>acterized by rare variants in large sequencing data. Nucleic Acids Research, 41(22):e202, <lb/>2013. <lb/>[20] S. Hochreiter, U. Bodenhofer, M. Heusel, A. Mayr, A. Mitterecker, A. Kasim, S. VanSanden, <lb/>D. Lin, W. Talloen, L. Bijnens, H. W. H. Göhlmann, Z. Shkedy, and D.-A. Clevert. FABIA: <lb/>factor analysis for bicluster acquisition. Bioinformatics, 26(12):1520-1527, 2010. <lb/>[21] S. Hochreiter, D.-A. Clevert, and K. Obermayer. A new summarization method for <lb/>Affymetrix probe level data. Bioinformatics, 22(8):943-949, 2006. <lb/>[22] G. Klambauer, K. Schwarzbauer, A. Mayr, D.-A. Clevert, A. Mitterecker, U. Bodenhofer, and <lb/>S. Hochreiter. cn.MOPS: mixture of poissons for discovering copy number variations in next <lb/>generation sequencing data with a low false discovery rate. Nucleic Acids Res., 40(9):e69, <lb/>2012. <lb/>[23] G. Klambauer, T. Unterthiner, and S. Hochreiter. Dexus: identifying differential expression <lb/>in rna-seq studies with unknown conditions. Nucleic Acids Research, 41(21):e198, 2013. <lb/>[24] J. Krause, C. Lalueza-Fox, L. Orlando, W. Enard, R. E. Green, H. A. Burbano, J.-J. Hublin, <lb/>C. Hänni, J. Fortea, Marco de la Rasilla, J. Bertranpetit, A. Rosas, and S. Pääbo. The <lb/>derived foxp2 variant of modern humans was shared with neandertals. Current Biology, <lb/>17(21):1908-1912, 2007. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">REFERENCES <lb/></note>

			<page>57 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[25] M. Krings, A. Stone, R. W. Schmitz, H. Krainitzki, M. Stoneking, and S. Pääbo. Neandertal <lb/>dna sequences and the origin of modern humans. Cell, 90(1):19-30, 1997. <lb/>[26] E. M. Leffler, Z. Gao, S. Pfeifer, L. Ségurel, A. Auton, O. Venn, R. Bowden, R. Bontrop, <lb/>J. D. Wall, G. Sella, et al. Multiple instances of ancient balancing selection shared between <lb/>humans and chimpanzees. Science, 339(6127):1578-1582, 2013. <lb/>[27] G. Leibon, D. N. Rockmore, and M. R. Polla. A SNP streak model for the identification of <lb/>genetic regions identical-by-descent. Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol., 7(1):Article v16, 2008. <lb/>[28] K. Lohse and L. A. F. Frantz. Neandertal admixture in eurasia confirmed by maximum <lb/>likelihood analysis of three genomes. Genetics, 2014. <lb/>[29] R. K. Lowery, G. Uribe, E. B. Jimenez, M. A. Weiss, K. J. Herrera, M. Regueiro, and R. J. <lb/>Herrera. Neanderthal and denisova genetic affinities with contemporary humans: Introgres-<lb/>sion versus common ancestral polymorphisms. Gene, 530(1):83-94, 2013. <lb/>[30] C. C. Mahrenholz, I. Abfalter, U. Bodenhofer, R. Volkmer, and S. Hochreiter. Complex net-<lb/>works govern coiled coil oligomerization -predicting and profiling by means of a machine <lb/>learning approach. Mol. Cell. Proteomics, 10:M110.004994, 2011. <lb/>[31] M. Meyer, M. Kircher, M.-T. Gansauge, H. Li, F. Racimo, S. Mallick, J. G. Schraiber, F. Jay, <lb/>K. Prüfer, C. deFilippo, et al. A high-coverage genome sequence from an archaic denisovan <lb/>individual. Science, 338(6104):222-226, 2012. <lb/>[32] P. Moorjani, N. Patterson, J. N. Hirschhorn, A. Keinan, L. Hao, G. Atzmon, E. Burns, H. Os-<lb/>trer, A. L. Price, and D. Reich. The history of african gene flow into southern europeans, <lb/>levantines, and jews. PLoS Genet, 7(4):e1001373, 2011. <lb/>[33] A. Moreno-Estrada, S. Gravel, F. Zakharia, J. L. McCauley, J. K. Byrnes, C. R. Gig-<lb/>noux, P. A. Ortiz-Tello, R. J. Martínez, D. J. Hedges, R. W. Morris, C. Eng, K. Sandoval, <lb/>S. Acevedo-Acevedo, P. J. Norman, Z. Layrisse, P. Parham, J. C. Martínez-Cruzado, E. G. <lb/>Burchard, M. L. Cuccaro, E. R. Martin, and C. D. Bustamante. Reconstructing the population <lb/>genetic history of the caribbean. PLoS Genet, 9(11):e1003925, 2013. <lb/>[34] P. F. Palamara, T. Lencz, A. Darvasi, and I. Pe&apos;er. Length distributions of identity by descent <lb/>reveal fine-scale demographic history. Am. J. Hum. Genet., 91(5):809-822, 2012. <lb/>[35] K. Prüfer, F. Racimo, N. Patterson, F. Jay, S. Sankararaman, S. Sawyer, A. Heinze, G. Re-<lb/>naud, P. H. Sudmant, C. d. Filippo, H. Li, S. Mallick, M. Dannemann, Q. Fu, M. Kircher, <lb/>M. Kuhlwilm, M. Lachmann, M. Meyer, M. Ongyerth, M. Siebauer, C. Theunert, A. Tandon, <lb/>P. Moorjani, J. Pickrell, J. C. Mullikin, S. H. Vohr, R. E. Green, I. Hellmann, P. L. F. Johnson, <lb/>H. Blanche, H. Cann, J. O. Kitzman, J. Shendure, E. E. Eichler, E. S. Lein, T. E. Bakken, <lb/>L. V. Golovanova, V. B. Doronichev, M. V. Shunkov, A. P. Derevianko, B. Viola, M. Slatkin, <lb/>D. Reich, J. Kelso, and S. Paabo. The complete genome sequence of a neanderthal from the <lb/>altai mountains. Nature, 505(7481):43-49, 2014. <lb/>[36] P. Ralph and G. Coop. The geography of recent genetic ancestry across europe. PLoS Biol, <lb/>11(5):e1001555, 2013. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>58 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REFERENCES <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[37] D. Reich, R. E. Green, M. Kircher, J. Krause, N. Patterson, E. Y. Durand, B. Viola, A. W. <lb/>Briggs, U. Stenzel, P. L. Johnson, et al. Genetic history of an archaic hominin group from <lb/>denisova cave in siberia. Nature, 468:1053-1060, 2010. <lb/>[38] D. Reich, N. Patterson, M. Kircher, F. Delfin, M. R. Nandineni, I. Pugach, A. M. Ko, Y. C. <lb/>Ko, T. A. Jinam, M. E. Phipps, et al. Denisova admixture and the first modern human <lb/>dispersals into Southeast Asia and Oceania. Am. J. Hum. Genet., 89(4):516-528, 2011. <lb/>[39] S. Sankararaman, S. Mallick, M. Dannemann, K. Prufer, J. Kelso, S. Paabo, N. Patterson, and <lb/>D. Reich. The genomic landscape of neanderthal ancestry in present-day humans. Nature, <lb/>507(7492):354-357, 2014. <lb/>[40] S. Sankararaman, N. Patterson, H. Li, S. Pääbo, and D. Reich. The date of interbreeding <lb/>between neandertals and modern humans. PLoS Genet, 8(10):e1002947, 2012. <lb/>[41] K. Schwarzbauer, U. Bodenhofer, and S. Hochreiter. Genome-wide chromatin remodeling <lb/>identified at GC-rich long nucleosome-free regions. PLoS ONE, 7(11):e47924, 2012. <lb/>[42] D. Serre, A. Langaney, M. Chech, M. Teschler-Nicola, M. Paunovic, P. Mennecier, M. Hofre-<lb/>iter, G. Possnert, and S. Pääbo. No evidence of neandertal mtdna contribution to early modern <lb/>humans. PLoS Biol, 2(3):e57, 03 2004. <lb/>[43] P. Skoglund and M. Jakobsson. Archaic human ancestry in east asia. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. <lb/>USA, 108(45):18301-18306, 2011. <lb/>[44] T. Strachan and A. P. Read. Human Molecular Genetics. Garland Science/Taylor &amp; Francis <lb/>Group, London and New York, 3rd edition, 2004. <lb/>[45] W. Talloen, D.-A. Clevert, S. Hochreiter, D. Amaratunga, L. Bijnens, S. Kass, and <lb/>H. Göhlmann. I/NI-calls for the exclusion of non-informative genes: a highly effective <lb/>filtering tool for microarray data. Bioinformatics, 23(21):2897-2902, 2007. <lb/>[46] W. Talloen, S. Hochreiter, L. Bijnens, A. Kasim, Z. Shkedy, and D. Amaratunga. Filtering <lb/>data from high-throughput experiments based on measurement reliability. Proc. Natl. Acad. <lb/>Sci. USA, 107(46):173-174, 2010. <lb/>[47] The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium. A map of human genome variation from population-<lb/>scale sequencing. Nature, 467(7319):1061-1073, 2010. <lb/>[48] The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium. An integrated map of genetic variation from 1,092 <lb/>human genomes. Nature, 491(7422):56-65, 2012. <lb/>[49] The Chimpanzee Sequencing and Analysis Consortium. Initial sequence of the chimpanzee <lb/>genome and comparison with the human genome. Nature, 437:69-87, 2005. <lb/>[50] A. Thomas, N. J. Camp, J. M. Farnham, K. Allen-Brady, and L. A. Cannon-Albright. Shared <lb/>genomic segment analysis. mapping disease predisposition genes in extended pedigrees us-<lb/>ing SNP genotype assays. Ann. Hum. Genet., 72(Pt 2):279-287, 2008. <lb/>[51] A. Thomas, M. H. Skolnick, and C. M. Lewis. Genomic mismatch scanning in pedigrees. <lb/>Math. Med. Biol., 11(1):1-16, 1994. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">REFERENCES <lb/></note>

			<page>59 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[52] A. Ulgen and W. Li. Comparing single-nucleotide-polymorphism marker-based and mi-<lb/>crosatellite marker-based linkage analyses. BMC Genet., 6:S13, 2005. <lb/>[53] B. Vernot and J. M. Akey. Resurrecting surviving neandertal lineages from modern human <lb/>genomes. Science, 343(6174):1017-1021, 2014. <lb/>[54] J. D. Wall, K. E. Lohmueller, and V. Plagnol. Detecting ancient admixture and estimating <lb/>demographic parameters in multiple human populations. Mol. Biol. Evol., 26(8):1823-1827, <lb/>2009. <lb/>[55] J. D. Wall, M. A. Yang, F. Jay, S. K. Kim, E. Y. Durand, L. S. Stevison, C. Gignoux, A. Wo-<lb/>erner, M. F. Hammer, and M. Slatkin. Higher levels of Neanderthal ancestry in East Asians <lb/>than in Europeans. Genetics, 194(1):199-209, 2013. <lb/>[56] M. A. Yang, A.-S. Malaspinas, E. Y. Durand, and M. Slatkin. Ancient structure in africa <lb/>unlikely to explain neanderthal and non-african genetic similarity. Molecular Biology and <lb/>Evolution, 29(10):2987-2995, 2012. <lb/>[57] A. Yu, C. Zhao, Y. Fan, W. Jang, A. J. Mungall, P. Deloukas, A. Olsen, N. A. Doggett, <lb/>N. Ghebranious, K. W. Broman, et al. Comparison of human genetic and sequence-based <lb/>physical maps. Nature, 409:951-953, 2001. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
