<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Assessing the prevalence of mycoplasma contamination in cell culture via a survey of <lb/>NCBI&apos;s RNA-seq archive <lb/>Anthony O. Olarerin-George 1 , John B. Hogenesch 1** <lb/>1 Department of Pharmacology and the Institute for Translational Medicine and Therapeutics, <lb/>Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA <lb/>**To whom correspondence should be addressed. Email: hogenesc@mail.med.upenn.edu <lb/>Running Title: Mycoplasma contamination in RNA-Seq data <lb/>Keywords: Mycoplasma, RNA-Seq, contamination <lb/>2 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Mycoplasmas are notorious contaminants of cell culture and can have profound effects on <lb/>host cell biology by depriving cells of nutrients and inducing global changes in gene expression. <lb/>Because they are small, they can escape filtration in culture media. Because they lack cell walls, <lb/>they are resistant to commonly used antibiotics. Over the last two decades, sentinel testing has <lb/>revealed wide-ranging contamination rates in mammalian culture. To obtain an unbiased <lb/>assessment from hundreds of labs, we analyzed sequence data from 9395 rodent and primate <lb/>samples from 884 series (or projects) in the NCBI Sequence Read Archive. We found 11% of <lb/>these series were contaminated (defined as ≥ 100 reads/million mapping to mycoplasma in one <lb/>or more samples). Ninety percent of mycoplasma-mapped reads aligned to ribosomal RNA. <lb/>Interestingly, series using poly(A)-selection, which should bias against mycoplasma detection, <lb/>had comparable contamination rates as non-poly(A)-selected series. We also examined the <lb/>relationship between mycoplasma contamination and host gene expression in a single cell RNA-<lb/>seq dataset and found 61 host genes (P &lt; 0.001) were significantly associated with mycoplasma-<lb/>mapped read counts. Lastly, to estimate the potential economic cost of this widespread <lb/>contamination, we queried NIH RePORTER to find grants with the terms &quot;cell culture&quot; or &quot;cell <lb/>lines&quot;. Funding for these totaled over $3 billion, suggesting hundreds of millions of dollars in <lb/>research are potentially affected. In all, this study suggests mycoplasma contamination is still <lb/>prevalent today and poses substantial risk to research quality, with considerable financial <lb/>consequences. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Mycoplasmas are small parasitic bacteria of the class mollicutes. There are over 180 <lb/>species infecting a wide range of hosts. Mycoplasmas are common to the human respiratory and <lb/>urogenital tracts (Taylor-Robinson 1996). Some species are pathogenic. For example, M. <lb/>pneumoniae causes atypical pneumonia (Chanock et al. 1962). Also, M. genitalium infection is <lb/>linked to pelvic inflammatory disease (Tully et al. 1981). <lb/>In addition to their impact on human health, mycoplasmas are widespread contaminants <lb/>of cell culture. In 1956, researchers from Johns Hopkins reported mycoplasma contamination of <lb/>HeLa cells used in their lab (Robinson and Wichelhausen 1956). By the early 1990s, the US <lb/>Food and Drug Administration had tested over 20,000 cell cultures and found 15% contaminated <lb/>with mycoplasma (Rottem and Barile 1993). A study in 1991 from Argentina found 70% of the <lb/>200 samples tested were contaminated (Coronato and Coto 1991). More recently, a 2002 report <lb/>by the Deutsche Sammlung von Mikroorganismen und Zellkulturen (DSMZ) in Germany found <lb/>28% of the 440 cell lines tested (mostly leukemia-lymphoma) were contaminated (Drexler and <lb/>Uphoff 2002). Hence, mycoplasma contamination in cell culture is a long-standing and persistent <lb/>problem. <lb/>Preventing mycoplasma contamination is difficult. For one, mycoplasma cells are small <lb/>(0.3-0.8 uM in diameter) and pleomorphic (Razin 2006), allowing them to pass through standard <lb/>filtration membranes. Secondly, mycoplasmas lack cell walls. This makes them impervious to <lb/>cell culture antibiotics that inhibit cell wall synthesis, such as penicillin. Effective antibiotics do <lb/>exist, however, their continuous use in cell culture is not recommended due to possible <lb/>cytotoxicity. Third, mycoplasmas are able to reach high concentrations in the media of infected <lb/>cells without noticeable turbidity (Young et al. 2010). This makes detection via visual inspection <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>difficult. Lastly, while the primary source of mycoplasma contamination is likely other cell <lb/>cultures, mycoplasmas from lab personnel are a potential source as well (Drexler and Uphoff <lb/>2002). <lb/>Mycoplasmas have one of the smallest prokaryotic genomes (~0.6 Mb). This comes at a <lb/>price, as mycoplasmas lack key genes essential for the synthesis of macromolecule precursors <lb/>and energy metabolism (Razin et al. 1998). As a result, mycoplasmas alter and depend on host <lb/>cell biology for survival (Rottem and Naot 1998; Rottem 2003). For example, M. orale can <lb/>compete for arginine in culture media, impacting host cell growth (Gill and Pan 1970). Also, M. <lb/>hyorhinis endonucleases can degrade host cell DNA, providing DNA precursors for the parasite <lb/>(Paddenberg et al. 1998). Further, mycoplasma infection can dysregulate hundreds of host genes <lb/>(Hopfe et al. 2013). It is therefore imperative that cultured cells are free of mycoplasma <lb/>contamination to ensure the interpretability, reproducibility and reliability of results obtained <lb/>from their use. <lb/>In this study we sought to evaluate the prevalence of mycoplasma contamination in cell <lb/>culture today. High throughput RNA-sequencing data is growing at an exponential rate and is <lb/>providing an unprecedented view of the constituency of RNA molecules in a sample. We posited <lb/>that mycoplasma sequences in RNA-Seq data from primate and rodent specimens would be <lb/>indicative of contamination. Further, because these samples come from hundreds of <lb/>geographically distinct labs, it offers a more comprehensive view of contamination. Hence, we <lb/>surveyed RNA-Seq data from archives at NCBI for mycoplasma sequences. We also evaluated <lb/>the relationship between mycoplasma contamination and host gene expression in a Burkitt&apos;s <lb/>lymphoma cell line. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>RESULTS <lb/>Acquisition and characterization of RNA-Seq data <lb/>We assessed the feasibility of working with the large volume of sequencing data in <lb/>NCBI&apos;s Sequence Read Archive (SRA). At the time of this study, there were 884 series (or <lb/>projects) of type &quot;expression profiling by high throughput sequencing&quot; or &quot;non-coding RNA <lb/>profiling by high throughput sequencing&quot; from primates and rodents (Supplemental data 1). <lb/>These were comprised of 9395 samples with downloadable sequence files. To make the analysis <lb/>manageable, we downloaded just the first million reads of each of the samples using NCBI&apos;s <lb/>SRA toolkit. For samples with paired-end reads, we assessed only the first read. The resulting <lb/>dataset contained 6.4 billion reads and filled 2TB of disk space. <lb/>Mapping of reads to mycoplasma <lb/>We mapped the reads to mycoplasma in two steps. First, we aligned the reads to four <lb/>complete mycoplasma genomes (M. hominis ATCC 23114, M. hyorhinis MCLD, M. fermentans <lb/>M64 and A. laidlawii PG-8A) with Bowtie (Langmead et al. 2009). Less than 2% (112,547,232) <lb/>of the reads mapped to one or more of the mycoplasma species. This corresponded to 1,280,951 <lb/>unique sequence reads (Supplemental data 2). Next, we eliminated non-specific bowtie aligned <lb/>reads. These were reads that mapped to sequences from other sources as well as or better than <lb/>they did mycoplasma. For example, reads that mapped to the putative host species or to other <lb/>bacteria were eliminated. To accomplish this, we aligned the unique bowtie-mapped reads to <lb/>NCBI&apos;s nucleotide collection (nt) database with standalone BLAST+ (Altschul et al. 1990). The <lb/>nt database is a comprehensive collection of ~20 million DNA sequences from species spanning <lb/>the phylogeny of life and viruses. These sequences include entries from Refseq, GenBank, <lb/>EMBL and DDBJ. Of the 1,280,951 unique bowtie aligned reads, 474,219 (37%) aligned best to <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>mycoplasma as assessed by BLAST E-values (Supplemental Table 1). Ninety percent of all <lb/>BLAST-confirmed reads aligned to ribosomal sequences (Figure 1). <lb/>Mycoplasma contamination in cultured vs non-cultured cells <lb/>Mycoplasma contamination is predominantly found in cultured samples (e.g. cell lines) <lb/>and not in non-cultured samples (e.g. tissues) (Miller et al. 2003). Hence, we posited that non-<lb/>cultured samples in our study would be underrepresented for mycoplasma contamination and <lb/>provide a baseline for the expected number of mycoplasma-mapped reads in a given sample (i.e. <lb/>serve as a negative control). We mined the text of the sample descriptions from NCBI&apos;s Gene <lb/>Expression Omnibus (GEO) for keywords indicating if the samples were cultured or not (see <lb/>Methods). We estimated that 57% of the samples (n = 5328) were cultured and 43% (n = 4067) <lb/>were not (Supplemental Table 2). In series with cultured samples, 11% (52/484) had at least one <lb/>sample with 100 or more reads per million (RPM) that mapped to mycoplasma (see full <lb/>distribution in Figure 2A). In contrast, none of the 344 series with non-cultured samples met this <lb/>criterion (Figure 2A). Further, more samples had reads mapping to M. hyorhinis, than the other <lb/>tested mycoplasma species (Figure 2B, 2C). Fewer samples had reads mapping to A. laidlawii. <lb/>Surprisingly, for 39 samples (all cultured), more than 10 4 RPM (i.e &gt;1% of reads) mapped to one <lb/>or more of the mycoplasma species (Figure 2A, Supplemental Table 2). <lb/>Mycoplasma contamination in poly(A)-vs non-poly(A)-selected samples <lb/>Polyadenylation marks transcripts for degradation in bacteria (Dreyfus and Régnier 2002, <lb/>9). Hence, we hypothesized that poly(A)-selected samples would be underrepresented for <lb/>mycoplasma contamination. We mined the text of the sample descriptions from NCBI&apos;s GEO for <lb/>keywords indicating if the samples were poly(A)-selected or not (see Methods). We estimated <lb/>that 26% (n = 2431) of the samples were poly(A) selected and 74% (n = 6964) were not <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Supplemental Table 2). The latter category was broad and included samples that were depleted <lb/>of ribosomal RNA, size-selected for small RNAs, immunoprecipitated via RNA binding proteins <lb/>and others. Unexpectedly, there was no significant difference in the fraction of series with <lb/>mycoplasma-mapped reads in the poly(A) and non-poly(A) series (Figure 3A). In general, more <lb/>samples had reads mapping to M. hyorhinis than the other mycoplasma species. Fewer samples <lb/>had reads mapping to A. laidlawii (Figure 3B, 3C). <lb/>Effect of mycoplasma contamination on host gene expression <lb/>Next, we wanted to determine the effect of mycoplasma contamination on host gene <lb/>expression. To do this, we searched for series that contained comparable contaminated and non-<lb/>contaminated samples. This was rare as mycoplasma contamination in one sample typically <lb/>guaranteed contamination of all samples of the same cell line/type in the series. Hence, we <lb/>instead focused on contaminated series with large numbers of replicate samples and varied <lb/>amounts of mycoplasma-mapped reads. Our goal was to identify host genes whose expression <lb/>levels were statistically associated with the number of mycoplasma-mapped reads. We found one <lb/>such series (GSE49321) containing seven contaminated samples from the Burkitt&apos;s lymphoma <lb/>cell line DG-75. Interestingly, each sample represented expression data from a single cell. The <lb/>number of mycoplasma-mapped reads ranged from ~10,000 to 36,000 RPM (Figure 4A). We <lb/>downloaded the full RNA-seq datasets for these samples, aligned them to the human reference <lb/>genome using STAR (Dobin et al. 2013), and obtained read counts for genes using HTSeq <lb/>(Anders et al. 2014). We then used DESeq2 (Love et al. 2014) to generate generalized linear <lb/>models of host gene expression as a function of mycoplasma-mapped reads. Sixty-one genes <lb/>were statistically associated with mycoplasma-mapped read counts (Wald test, Benjamini-<lb/>Hochberg adjusted P &lt; 0.001; Supplemental Table 3). We found no significant enrichment in <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>gene annotations using DAVID (Huang et al. 2009). The top 16 genes are shown in Figure 4A. <lb/>Finally, we evaluated the likelihood of obtaining significant genes by chance in our analysis. We <lb/>randomly permuted the gene expression counts of the samples and repeated the analysis 1000 <lb/>times. The number of significant genes was consistently less than that of the observed set for <lb/>various p-value cutoffs examined (P &lt; 0.002, Figure 4B). <lb/>Economic impact of mycoplasma contamination <lb/>To assess the potential financial impact of mycoplasma contamination, we first tallied the <lb/>cost of NIH-funded research involving cultured cells. We queried the NIH Research Portfolio <lb/>Online Reporting tools (RePORT) database for grants from 2013-2014 containing the keywords <lb/>&quot;cell culture&quot; or &quot;cell line&quot;. A total of $3.17 billion in funded grants across the 27 NIH institutes <lb/>and centers contained these terms (Figure 5). Using the contamination rate of 11% from our <lb/>earlier results (Figure 2), we estimated that some portion of approximately $350 million of NIH-<lb/>funded research is potentially affected. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>This study was inspired by a recent incident of mycoplasma contamination in our lab. We <lb/>wondered how often this occurred in other labs. There have been several such surveys over the <lb/>last three decades (Rottem and Barile 1993; Coronato and Coto 1991; Drexler and Uphoff 2002). <lb/>These studies used DNA fluorescent staining or PCR-based methods to detect mycoplasma <lb/>contamination in collected samples. The contamination rates varied from 15% to 70%. Further, a <lb/>recent analysis of DNA sequences from the 1000 Genomes project suggested 7% of the samples <lb/>were contaminated (Langdon 2014). This study represents the first unbiased (and one of the most <lb/>extensive) surveys for mycoplasma contamination. We leveraged publicly available RNA-Seq <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>datasets in GEO to determine the prevalence of contamination today. Importantly, these entries <lb/>were comprised of various sample types under different experimental conditions and originated <lb/>from multiple institutions. We estimated that about 11% of GEO series were contaminated based <lb/>on a cutoff of 100 mycoplasma-mapped RPM in one or more samples. However, this is likely an <lb/>underestimate. For one, in our analysis, we discarded mycoplasma-mapped reads that were not <lb/>unique to mycoplasma. Some of these included reads that mapped to other bacteria and hence <lb/>could not be unambiguously associated with mycoplasma. While they may or may not be <lb/>mycoplasma, they are bacterial. Secondly, Figure 1 suggests that a cutoff of 10 mycoplasma-<lb/>mapped RPM was equally powerful to discriminate between cultured and non-cultured samples. <lb/>At this cutoff, the contamination rate was closer to 15%. Nonetheless, no matter the exact rate, <lb/>our study suggests mycoplasma contamination remains a significant and costly problem. <lb/>We also identified interesting characteristics of mycoplasma contamination in RNA-seq <lb/>data. Notably, we found that the rate of mycoplasma contamination was similar for poly(A)-<lb/>selected and non-poly(A)-selected series (Figure 2). This was unexpected because 1) 90% of the <lb/>mycoplasma-mapped reads mapped to rRNA (Figure 1B) 2) Bacteria transcripts are degraded <lb/>upon polyadenylation (Dreyfus and Régnier 2002) and 3) the mycoplasma genome lacks <lb/>homologs for polyadenylating enzymes (Sarkar 1996; Portnoy and Schuster 2008). One <lb/>explanation for this result is that the AT-rich mycoplasma genome (~28% GC-content) may <lb/>result in higher susceptibility of transcripts to oligo-dT mediated capture. This is perhaps a <lb/>desirable outcome as contamination in future RNA-Seq experiments may be easily ascertained <lb/>without masking from the enrichment method. <lb/>We mapped sequence reads to four complete mycoplasma genomes: M. hominis, M. <lb/>hyorhinis, M. fermentans, and A. laidlawii. M. hominis and M. fermentans are associated with <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>human diseases; the former, pelvic inflammatory disease, the latter, rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>(Johnson et al. 2000; Taylor-Robinson 2007). M. hyorhinis is commensal in the respiratory tract <lb/>of pigs (Kobisch and Friis 1996). A. laidlawii has a broad host range but is typically found in <lb/>cattle. As such, A. laidlawii was linked to contamination of commercial bovine serum in the <lb/>1970s (Drexler and Uphoff 2002). These four species, along with M. orale and M. arginini, are <lb/>found in 90-95% of mycoplasma contaminated cell lines (Drexler and Uphoff 2002). In our <lb/>study, we found A. laidlawii was least represented in contaminated samples (Figures 2B-C, 3B-<lb/>C). This may be indicative of the reduced likelihood of contamination from bovine serum as <lb/>commercial products are now routinely 0.1 micron sterile-filtered. <lb/>Lastly, we identified 61 genes associated with mycoplasma contamination in a single cell <lb/>RNA-seq dataset. Unfortunately, we could not identify series containing contaminated and non-<lb/>contaminated samples. Therefore, we measured the association between the number of <lb/>mycoplasma-mapped reads per sample and host gene expression in a contaminated series. <lb/>Consequently, directionality of effect could not be determined. That is, differences in the extent <lb/>of mycoplasma contamination may have driven host gene expression or differences in host gene <lb/>expression (especially as it relates to variability of single cells) may have conferred resistance <lb/>(relatively speaking) to contamination or impacted mycoplasma gene expression. It is also <lb/>possible that the associations seen here are not biological per se, but instead indicative of some <lb/>technical artifacts associated with the presence of the AT-rich mycoplasma transcripts in the <lb/>sample. Nonetheless, this is equally problematic as it effects the interpretation of the results. <lb/>Hence, further controlled studies are needed to fully understand the effect of contamination on <lb/>the quality of RNA-Seq data and possibly how to account for this in data analysis. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>To try to estimate the potential economic cost of this widespread contamination, we <lb/>searched for grants that used the terms &quot;cell culture&quot; or &quot;cell lines&quot; in NIH RePorter. This <lb/>analysis found &gt; $3 billion dollars was invested in this research in 2013-2014. If we assume that <lb/>the contamination rate for our set is the same as the average NIH sponsored lab, this puts some <lb/>portion of ~ $350 million at risk. We are heavy users of cell culture, with approximately 50% of <lb/>our consumables budget going to these experiments. Other labs may be closer to 10%. So <lb/>somewhere between dozens and ~$100m are at risk. Put simply, the economic impact of this <lb/>problem is significant. <lb/>Lastly, our study has broader implications for the analysis of high-throughput sequencing <lb/>data. Too often in our analysis pipelines, we disregard unmapped reads as technical artifacts or <lb/>attribute them to problematic or unsequenced regions of the reference genome. While this may <lb/>be true most of the time, this study suggests such reads warrant further investigation-<lb/>particularly when they constitute a large number of the total reads. We focused on mycoplasma <lb/>in this study as a proof of concept due to its known prevalence. However, the methods used here <lb/>are easily applicable to other known (and unknown) contaminants of cell culture including other <lb/>bacteria, yeast and viruses. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>All Perl scripts used in this study are available as supplemental files. Directions for their use are <lb/>located in the README file. The BLAST analysis was performed through Amazon Web <lb/>Services (8-core, 70GB of RAM). All other analyses were done on the high-performance <lb/>computing cluster of the Penn Genomics Frontier Institute. <lb/>Obtaining sequence files <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>GEO series IDs and descriptions for all RNA-seq experiments were obtained through the GEO <lb/>DataSets Advanced Search Builder (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gds/advanced). Results were <lb/> limited on the query parameter &quot;DataSet Type&quot; for &quot;expression profiling by high throughput <lb/>sequencing&quot; and &quot;non coding rna profiling by high throughput sequencing&quot;. The results were <lb/>further filtered to include only primates (Homo sapiens, Pan troglodytes, Macaca mulatta, <lb/>Macaca fascicularis, Pan paniscus, Gorilla gorilla) and rodents (Mus musculus, Rattus <lb/>novergicus). SOFT files for all the GEO series were downloaded. From these files, the sample <lb/>IDs were obtained and used to download the corresponding raw sequences using the fastq-dump <lb/>utility of the SRA toolkit (http://eutils.ncbi.nih.gov/Traces/sra/?view=software). <lb/>Identifying poly(A)-selected and cultured samples from sample descriptions <lb/>SOFT files were parsed and searched for keywords under certain headings. For example, poly(A) <lb/>selection was assumed if the library source or extraction protocols contained the keywords <lb/>&quot;polyA&quot; or &quot;oligo-dT&quot; and similar variants. A sample was considered cultured if its description <lb/>contained the keywords &quot;cell line&quot;, &quot;fibroblast&quot;, &quot;MEFs&quot;, &quot;ESC&quot;, &quot;immortalized&quot;, &quot;DMEM&quot;, <lb/>&quot;RPMI&quot;, &quot;Ham&apos;s&quot;, &quot;McCoy&quot;, &quot;cultured&quot;, &quot;passaged&quot;, &quot;propagated&quot;, &quot;grown&quot; and similar <lb/>variants of these keywords. <lb/>Mapping sequence reads to mycoplasma genomes <lb/>The mycoplasma genomes used in this study were downloaded from NCBI genomes: M. <lb/>hominis ATCC 23114 (NC_013511.1), M. hyorhinis MCLD (NC_017519.1), M. fermentans <lb/>M64 (NC_014921.1) and A. laidlawii PG-8A (NC_010163.1). RNA-seq reads were mapped to <lb/>these genomes with Bowtie using the default parameters (Langmead et al. 2009). If a read was <lb/>paired-end, only the first read was used in the analysis. <lb/>Filtering non-mycoplasma-specific sequences from bowtie results <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>All unique bowtie mapped reads were aligned to NCBI&apos;s nucleotide (nt) database using <lb/>standalone BLAST+ (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK1763/). The following parameters <lb/>were used: -db nt -num_threads 8 -outfmt &quot;7 std sscinames&quot; -max_target_seqs 100. A bowtie-<lb/>mapped read was considered unique to mycoplasma if: 1) the scientific name matched <lb/>&quot;Mycoplasma&quot; or &quot;Acholeplasma laidlawii&quot; in the BLAST output and 2) the entry from 1) was <lb/>the best BLAST hit (i.e. with the lowest E-value). <lb/>Mycoplasma effect on host gene expression <lb/>The complete sequences for the 7 samples comprising series GSE49321were downloaded with <lb/>the SRA toolkit. The sequences were aligned to the human genome (hg19) using STAR (Dobin <lb/>et al. 2013) with the following optional parameters: --runMode alignReads --runThreadN 8. Read <lb/>counts for each gene were determined using HTSeq with the following optional parameters: -s no <lb/>-m intersection-nonempty. Gene expression (counts) was modeled as a function of mycoplasma-<lb/>mapped reads using DESeq2. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">DATA ACCESS <lb/>The sequence files used in this study were obtained from the SRA at NCBI and are freely <lb/>available for download from the source. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank David Lipman, Don Preuss, and Eugene Yaschenko at NCBI for their advice on the <lb/>best ways to query and download the large volume of sequencing data available in SRA. We also <lb/>thank Nick Lahens for assistance working with AWS and his thorough review of the manuscript. <lb/>This work is supported by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke <lb/>(1R01NS054794-06 to JBH), the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA-<lb/></div>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">D12AP00025, to John Harer, Duke University), and by the Penn Genome Frontiers Institute <lb/>under a HRFF grant with the Pennsylvania Department of Health. <lb/></div>

			<body>FIGURE LEGENDS <lb/>Figure 1. Gene breakdown of mycoplasma-mapped reads. <lb/>RNA-seq reads were aligned to four mycoplasma genomes using bowtie. Non-specific reads <lb/>were filtered with BLAST. Of the resulting 472,219 mycoplasma-mapped reads, 90% mapped to <lb/>ribosomal RNA. <lb/>Figure 2. Mycoplasma contamination in cultured vs non-cultured samples and series. <lb/>A) Fraction of contaminated series (containing cultured samples or not) for various cutoffs of <lb/>mycoplasma-mapped reads per million (column graphs; primary y-axis). Red stars indicate the p-<lb/>values of the respective comparisons (secondary y-axis; Fisher&apos;s exact test). Fraction of <lb/>contaminated B) cultured or C) non-cultured samples for various cutoffs of mycoplasma-mapped <lb/>reads per million, broken down by the indicated mycoplasma species. <lb/>Figure 3. Mycoplasma contamination in poly(A)-vs non-poly(A)-selected samples and <lb/>series. <lb/>A) Fraction of contaminated series (containing poly(A)-selected samples or not) for various <lb/>cutoffs of mycoplasma-mapped reads per million (column graphs; primary y-axis). Red stars <lb/>indicate the p-values of the respective comparisons (secondary y-axis; Fisher&apos;s exact test). <lb/>Fraction of contaminated B) poly(A)-or C) non-poly(A)-selected samples for various cutoffs of <lb/>mycoplasma-mapped reads per million, broken down by the indicated mycoplasma species. <lb/>Figure 4. Association between host gene expression and mycoplasma-mapped reads from <lb/>single-cell RNA-seq <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>A) Scatter plots of mycoplasma-mapped reads per million and host cell gene expression in <lb/>single cell (DG-75) RNA-seq. Gene symbols are indicated in the upper right corner of the <lb/>respective plots. P-values from the association test are indicated in the bottom left. B) To assess <lb/>the likelihood of obtaining significant genes by chance, the mycoplasma counts were permuted <lb/>1000 times. The analysis was repeated with each permutation. The expected number of <lb/>significant genes is plotted in red. The observed number of significant genes is in black. Error <lb/>bars are standard deviations. <lb/>Figure 5. NIH-funded grants involving cell culture <lb/>The NIH RePorter was queried for grants from 2013-2014 that involved the culturing of cells. <lb/>The results are broken up by the 27 NIH institutes and centers. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Altschul SF, Gish W, Miller W, Myers EW, Lipman DJ. 1990. Basic local alignment search tool. <lb/>J Mol Biol 215: 403-410. <lb/>Anders S, Pyl PT, Huber W. 2014. HTSeq A Python framework to work with high-throughput <lb/>sequencing data. http://biorxiv.org/lookup/doi/10.1101/002824 (Accessed March 15, <lb/>2014). <lb/>Chanock RM, Hayflick L, Barile MF. 1962. Growth on artificial medium of an agent associated <lb/>with atypical pneumonia and its identification as a PPLO. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 48: <lb/>41-49. <lb/>Coronato S, Coto CE. 1991. [Prevalence of Mycoplasma orale as a contaminant of cell cultures <lb/>in Argentina]. Rev Argent Microbiol 23: 166-171. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Dobin A, Davis CA, Schlesinger F, Drenkow J, Zaleski C, Jha S, Batut P, Chaisson M, Gingeras <lb/>TR. 2013. STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner. Bioinformatics 29: 15-21. <lb/>Drexler HG, Uphoff CC. 2002. Mycoplasma contamination of cell cultures: Incidence, sources, <lb/>effects, detection, elimination, prevention. Cytotechnology 39: 75-90. <lb/>Dreyfus M, Régnier P. 2002. The Poly(A) Tail of mRNAsBodyguard in Eukaryotes, Scavenger <lb/>in Bacteria. Cell 111: 611-613. <lb/>Gill P, Pan J. 1970. Inhibition of cell division in L5178Y cells by arginine-degrading <lb/>mycoplasmas: the role of arginine deiminase. Can J Microbiol 16: 415-419. <lb/>Hopfe M, Deenen R, Degrandi D, Köhrer K, Henrich B. 2013. Host Cell Responses to Persistent <lb/>Mycoplasmas -Different Stages in Infection of HeLa Cells with Mycoplasma hominis <lb/>ed. Y.A. Kwaik. PLoS ONE 8: e54219. <lb/>Huang DW, Sherman BT, Lempicki RA. 2009. Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene <lb/>lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources. Nat Protoc 4: 44-57. <lb/>Johnson S, Sidebottom D, Bruckner F, Collins D. 2000. Identification of Mycoplasma <lb/>fermentans in synovial fluid samples from arthritis patients with inflammatory disease. J <lb/>Clin Microbiol 38: 90-93. <lb/>Kobisch M, Friis NF. 1996. Swine mycoplasmoses. Rev Sci Tech Int Off Epizoot 15: 1569-1605. <lb/>Langdon WB. 2014. Mycoplasma contamination in the 1000 Genomes Project. BioData Min 7: <lb/>3. <lb/>Langmead B, Trapnell C, Pop M, Salzberg SL. 2009. Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment <lb/>of short DNA sequences to the human genome. Genome Biol 10: R25. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Love MI, Huber W, Anders S. 2014. Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for <lb/>RNA-Seq data with DESeq2. http://biorxiv.org/lookup/doi/10.1101/002832 (Accessed <lb/>June 8, 2014). <lb/>Miller CJ, Kassem HS, Pepper SD, Hey Y, Ward TH, Margison GP. 2003. Mycoplasma <lb/>infection significantly alters microarray gene expression profiles. BioTechniques 35: <lb/>812-814. <lb/>Paddenberg R, Weber A, Wulf S, Mannherz HG. 1998. Mycoplasma nucleases able to induce <lb/>internucleosomal DNA degradation in cultured cells possess many characteristics of <lb/>eukaryotic apoptotic nucleases. Cell Death Differ 5: 517-528. <lb/>Portnoy V, Schuster G. 2008. Mycoplasma gallisepticum as the first analyzed bacterium in <lb/>which RNA is not polyadenylated. FEMS Microbiol Lett 283: 97-103. <lb/>Razin S. 2006. The Genus Mycoplasma and Related Genera (Class Mollicutes). In <lb/>SpringerReference, Springer-Verlag, Berlin/Heidelberg <lb/>http://www.springerreference.com/index/doi/10.1007/SpringerReference_3750 (Accessed <lb/>August 7, 2013). <lb/>Razin S, Yogev D, Naot Y. 1998. Molecular biology and pathogenicity of mycoplasmas. <lb/>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev MMBR 62: 1094-1156. <lb/>Robinson LB, Wichelhausen RH. 1956. Contamination of human cell cultures by <lb/>pleuropneumonialike organisms. Science 124: 1147-1148. <lb/>Rottem S. 2003. Interaction of mycoplasmas with host cells. Physiol Rev 83: 417-432. <lb/>Rottem S, Barile MF. 1993. Beware of mycoplasmas. Trends Biotechnol 11: 143-151. <lb/>Rottem S, Naot Y. 1998. Subversion and exploitation of host cells by mycoplasmas. Trends <lb/>Microbiol 6: 436-440. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Sarkar N. 1996. Polyadenylation of mRNA in bacteria. Microbiol Read Engl 142 ( Pt 11): 3125-<lb/>3133. <lb/>Taylor-Robinson D. 1996. Infections due to species of Mycoplasma and Ureaplasma: an update. <lb/>Clin Infect Dis Off Publ Infect Dis Soc Am 23: 671-682; quiz 683-684. <lb/>Taylor-Robinson D. 2007. The role of mycoplasmas in pregnancy outcome. Best Pract Res Clin <lb/>Obstet Gynaecol 21: 425-438. <lb/>Tully JG, Taylor-Robinson D, Cole RM, Rose DL. 1981. A newly discovered mycoplasma in the <lb/>human urogenital tract. Lancet 1: 1288-1291. <lb/>Young L, Sung J, Stacey G, Masters JR. 2010. Detection of Mycoplasma in cell cultures. Nat <lb/>Protoc 5: 929-934. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>ribosomal RNA <lb/>ibosomal protein <lb/>ABC transporter <lb/>pyruvate/lactate <lb/>dehydrogenase <lb/>other <lb/>0% <lb/>20% <lb/>40% <lb/>60% <lb/>80% 100% <lb/>90.0% <lb/>1.3% <lb/>0.3% <lb/>0.2% <lb/>8.2% <lb/>Mycoplasma-mapped reads <lb/> 14 <lb/>12 <lb/>10 <lb/> 8 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>Fraction of series <lb/>Mycoplasma-mapped reads / million reads <lb/>-log 10 p-value <lb/>≥1 <lb/>≥10 1 ≥10 2 ≥10 3 ≥10 4 ≥10 5 <lb/>cultured <lb/>non-cultured <lb/>p-value <lb/>≥1 <lb/>≥10 1 ≥10 2 ≥10 3 ≥10 4 ≥10 5 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>A. laidlawii <lb/>M. fermentans <lb/>M. hominis <lb/>M. hyorhinis <lb/>any <lb/>Mycoplasma-mapped reads / million reads <lb/>Fraction of cultured samples <lb/>≥1 <lb/>≥10 1 ≥10 2 ≥10 3 ≥10 4 ≥10 5 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>Mycoplasma-mapped reads / million reads <lb/>Fraction of non-culuted samples <lb/>A. laidlawii <lb/>M. fermentans <lb/>M. hominis <lb/>M. hyorhinis <lb/>any <lb/>C <lb/>≥1 <lb/>≥10 1 ≥10 2 ≥10 3 ≥10 4 ≥10 5 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>Mycoplasma-mapped reads / million reads <lb/>A. laidlawii <lb/>M. fermentans <lb/>M. hominis <lb/>M. hyorhinis <lb/>any <lb/>Fraction of poly(A)-selected samples <lb/>A. laidlawii <lb/>M. fermentans <lb/>M. hominis <lb/>M. hyorhinis <lb/>≥1 <lb/>≥10 1 ≥10 2 ≥10 3 ≥10 4 ≥10 5 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>Mycoplasma-mapped reads / million reads <lb/>Fraction of non-poly(A)-selected samples <lb/>Mycoplasma-mapped reads / million reads <lb/>≥1 <lb/>≥10 1 ≥10 2 ≥10 3 ≥10 4 ≥10 5 <lb/>14 <lb/>12 <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>-log 10 p-value <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>Fraction of series <lb/>polyA <lb/>non-polyA <lb/>p-value <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>A <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>10000 20000 30000 10000 20000 30000 10000 20000 30000 10000 20000 30000 <lb/>host gene expression (read count) <lb/>MTMR1 <lb/>CD27-AS1 <lb/>RCBTB2 <lb/>CD22 <lb/>LPP <lb/>LMO7 <lb/>SLC25A19 <lb/>RBFOX2 <lb/>TAMM41 <lb/>ATP9B <lb/>FAM114A2 <lb/>SLAMF6 <lb/>TTC37 <lb/>TMEM159 <lb/>FBXL3 <lb/>MTFMT <lb/>P = 8.4 x 10 -12 <lb/>P = 4.7 x 10 -8 <lb/>P = 5.5 x 10 -8 <lb/>P = 1.9 x 10 -8 <lb/>P = 1.6 x 10 -8 <lb/>P = 9.9 x 10 -10 <lb/>P = 1.4 x 10 -8 <lb/>P = 2.7 x 10 -9 <lb/>P = 2.7 x 10 -8 <lb/>P = 9.9 x 10 -10 <lb/>P = 9.9 x 10 -10 <lb/>P = 1.4 x 10 -11 <lb/>P = 3.6 x 10 -7 <lb/>P = 4.3 x 10 -7 <lb/>P = 1.7 x 10 -7 <lb/>P = 5.5 x 10 -8 <lb/>mycoplasma-mapped reads/million reads <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>observed <lb/>expected <lb/>-log 10 p-value <lb/>
			Significant genes <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q q q q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>CIT <lb/>NIOSH <lb/>NINR <lb/>FIC <lb/>NLM <lb/>NIMHD <lb/>NCCAM <lb/>NIAAA <lb/>NIDCD <lb/>NIBIB <lb/>NCATS <lb/>OD <lb/>NIDCR <lb/>NIDA <lb/>NIAMS <lb/>NIA <lb/>NICHD <lb/>NEI <lb/>NIMH <lb/>NIEHS <lb/>NHGRI <lb/>NINDS <lb/>NIGMS <lb/>NIDDK <lb/>NHLBI <lb/>NIAID <lb/>NCI <lb/>$0 <lb/>$200,000,000 <lb/>$400,000,000 <lb/>$600,000,000 <lb/>$800,000,000 <lb/>Funding in FY2013−2014 <lb/>Institute </body>


	</text>
</tei>
