<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Non--respiratory functions of Saccharomyces cerevisiae <lb/>mitochondria are required for optimal attractiveness to <lb/>Drosophila melanogaster <lb/>Kelly M. Schiabor 1 , Allison S. Quan 1 and Michael B. Eisen 1,2 <lb/>1 Department of Molecular and Cell Biology, and 2 Howard Hughes Medical Institute, <lb/>University of California, Berkeley, CA. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>While screening a large collection of wild and laboratory yeast isolates for their <lb/>ability to attract Drosophila melanogaster adults, we noticed a large difference in fly <lb/>preference for two nearly isogenic strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae, BY4741 and <lb/>BY4742. Using standard genetic analyses, we tracked the preference difference to <lb/>the lack of functional mitochondria the stock of BY4742 used in the initial <lb/>experiment. We used gas chromatography coupled with mass spectroscopy to <lb/>examine the volatile compounds produced by BY4741 and the mitochondria--<lb/>deficient BY4742, and found they differed significantly. We found that several ethyl <lb/>esters are present at much higher levels in strains with functional mitochondria, <lb/>even in fermentative conditions. We confirmed the role of these ethyl esters in <lb/>attraction by examining an EEB1Δ strain which reduces ethyl ester production. We <lb/>found that nitrogen levels in the substrate affect the production of these <lb/>compounds, and that they are produced at high levels by strains with functional <lb/>mitochondria in the fermentation of natural substrates. Collectively these <lb/>observations demonstrate the effect core metabolic processes have in mediating the <lb/>interaction between yeasts and insect vectors, and highlight the importance of non--<lb/>respirative mitochondrial functions in yeast ecology. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/> Since the early 20th century, the vinegar fly Drosophila melanogaster and the <lb/>brewer&apos;s yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae, have been the preeminent model species <lb/>of molecular biology. Although generally studied by separate sets of researchers in <lb/>the lab, these species are found together in nature on fermenting fruit substrates -<lb/>an interaction that has received surprisingly little attention. <lb/>Their co--occurrence is no coincidence: each species benefits from the <lb/>presence of the other. Ethanol produced by S. cerevisiae protects D. melanogaster <lb/>larvae from predators [1], and D. melanogaster larvae preferentially feed on S. <lb/>cerevisiae, which provides a complete nutritional source for larval development [2, <lb/>3]. The non--motile S. cerevisiae, in turn, rely on D. melanogaster and other insects to <lb/>move to fresh, nutrient--rich substrates [4], and the burrowing activities of D. <lb/>melanogaster larvae expose nutritional sources to the yeast that would have been <lb/>otherwise inaccessible [5]. <lb/>Given the benefits that each species gains from this interaction, it is not <lb/>surprising that both yeast and fly appear to have evolved molecular mechanisms to <lb/>actively maintain their co--localization. <lb/>It is well known to anyone who keeps fruits in their kitchen that D. <lb/>melanogaster are attracted to fermenting fruit: an effect mediated almost entirely by <lb/>volatile molecules produced by yeasts, and not the fruity substrate [2], although the <lb/>substrate can have a significant effect on what compounds are produced[6--12]. <lb/>Numerous volatile compounds produced by S. cerevisiae activate specific odorant <lb/>receptor neurons in the D. melanogaster antennae, which are relayed to the odor <lb/>representation center of the fly brain, the antennal lobe [13, 14], and elicit specific <lb/>attractive and repulsive responses [2] [15--22]. <lb/>The response to individual compounds is complex, and includes various <lb/>types of attraction and avoidance behaviors. A small pulse of ethyl butyrate, for <lb/>example, is sufficient to keep a fly flying towards the source of the odorant for <lb/>twenty minutes without additional application of the odor, but this tracking is much <lb/>less pronounced for acetic acid, another attractive yeast--produced volatile [17]. <lb/>Mixtures of yeast--produced volatile compounds, more akin to what flies would <lb/>experience in nature, produce more complex, context--dependent responses [16]. <lb/>Different yeast species produce varying volatile bouquets, even when grown <lb/>on identical substrates [6, 8, 12, 23--26]. This variance in volatile bouquets is <lb/>observed across S. cerevisiae strains as well[24]. Further, fly species, and also <lb/>different D. melanogaster strains, show varying preferences for yeast strains and <lb/>species [27--29]. <lb/></body>

			<body>We became interested in the possibility that the large repertoire of genetic <lb/>tools available for these species would allow us to exploit these different types of <lb/>variation to better understand the molecular details of this interaction. As a first <lb/>step, we examined the response of a single D. melanogaster strain to different S. <lb/>cerevisiae strains grown under identical conditions. <lb/>Results <lb/>Two nearly isogeneic lab strains vary in their attractiveness to D. <lb/>melanogaster <lb/>We used a simple preference assay (see Methods) to screen a large panel of S. <lb/>cerevisiae strains, collected from diverse environments with varied histories of <lb/>laboratory use and propagation, for their attractiveness to a wild--caught D. <lb/>melanogaster line (Raleigh 437). We found considerable variation in the <lb/>attractiveness across the strains (corroborating the results of [24]). As we were <lb/>ultimately interested in exploring the genetic basis (in yeast) for this varied D. <lb/>melanogaster attractiveness, we also included the two nearly isogeneic haploid S. <lb/>cerevisiae strains, BY4741 and BY4742, which had been used to generate the <lb/>systematic yeast deletion collection [30]. We were astonished to find that traps <lb/>baited with BY4741, the MAT a parent, consistently attracted more flies when <lb/>directly competing against traps baited with BY4742, the MATα parent (Figure 1). <lb/>The remainder of this paper is focused on understanding the origins of this <lb/>preference difference. <lb/>Attraction difference between BY4741 and BY4742 is associated with <lb/>functional mitochondria <lb/>Outside of the mating type locus, these strains ostensibly differed at two <lb/>metabolic marker loci: MET17 (deleted in BY4741) and LEU2 (deleted in BY4742). <lb/>Given the known relationship between amino acid metabolism and volatile <lb/>compound production [6, 9, 10, 31--35], we suspected that the difference in <lb/>behavioral response to these two strains could be traced to their respective <lb/>auxotrophies. We therefore crossed BY4741 and BY4742 and dissected several <lb/>tetrads to obtain haploid strains with all eight possible genotypes at the three <lb/>variable loci (MAT, LEU2 and MET15). However, when we tested these strains using <lb/>our choice assay against BY4742, we found that all eight genotypes were strongly <lb/>preferred to BY4742, including the MATα; MET15; leu2∆ strain, which has the <lb/>identical three--locus genotype as BY4742 (Figure 2A). We tested a subset of these <lb/>strains against BY4741, and found that the flies preferred each strain equally <lb/>(Figure 2B). <lb/>This non--autosomal inheritance pattern immediately suggested <lb/>mitochondrial linkage. We tested both parental strains and all progeny for growth <lb/>on glycerol, a non--fermentable carbon source, and found that all of the strains grew <lb/>normally, except for BY4742 (Figure S1). This result confirmed a respiration <lb/>deficiency in the BY4742 strain used in this study, which we refer to hereon as <lb/>BY4742p, for petite. <lb/>To corroborate that the absence of a functional mitochondria reduces the <lb/>attractiveness of yeast strains to D. melanogaster, we tested an independent BY4742 <lb/>isolate (BY4742g, for grande), with a functional mitochondria <lb/>(MATα;his3;leu2;lys2;ura3), <lb/>as <lb/>well <lb/>the <lb/>MRPL16Δ <lb/>strain <lb/>(MATα;his3;leu2;lys2;ura3;mrpl16) from the same deletion collection. MRPL16 <lb/>encodes for the large subunit of the mitochondrial ribosomal protein, the deletion of <lb/>which results in a respiration deficiency. We found that the independent BY4742g <lb/>was equally as attractive as BY4741, while MRPL16Δ strain was less attractive than <lb/>BY4741. Following the trend found with BY4741, we found BY4742g was also more <lb/>attractive than both BY4742p and the MRPL16Δ strain (Figure 3). This further <lb/>confirms that D. melanogaster are more attracted to S. cerevisiae strains possessing <lb/>
            functional mitochondria. <lb/>BY4741 and BY4742p strains produce different volatile bouquets, influenced <lb/>by their mitochondrial status <lb/>In the choice assay used here, D. melanogaster are selecting between <lb/>different yeast strains based primarily on how they smell. Thus, the absence of <lb/>functional mitochondria must be affecting the volatile compounds produced by the <lb/>yeast strains. We used GC--MS to characterize and quantify the volatile compounds <lb/>associated with both BY4741 and BY4742p grown on YPD plates, and, as expected, <lb/>found significant differences (Figure 4A). <lb/>To vary mitochondrial engagement, we next examined the volatile profiles of <lb/>BY4741 and BY4742p in liquid YPD cultures under both anaerobic and aerobic <lb/>conditions. The anaerobic and aerobic BY4742p cultures produced nearly identical <lb/>chromatograms (Figure S2). In contrast, the anaerobic and aerobic BY4741 cultures <lb/>differed, with the anaerobic BY4741 culture resembling the BY4742p culture, and <lb/>the aerobic BY4741 culture showing a marked increase in the same set of <lb/>compounds found at higher levels in BY4741 compared to BY4742p plates (Figure <lb/>S2; see also Figure S3 which shows a similar comparison for one of the sporulated <lb/>strains with identical genotype to BY4741). These potential attractants include: <lb/>ethyl acetate, isoamyl alcohol, isoamyl acetate, ethyl hexanoate, phenylethyl alcohol, <lb/>and ethyl octanoate (Table 1). <lb/>The affect of mitochondria on the volatile profile of a strain is, at least <lb/>superficially, an unexpected result. S. cerevisiae exhibit a phenomenon known as the <lb/>Crabtree effect, in which they preferentially ferment glucose to ethanol, even in the <lb/>presence of oxygen [36, 37]. Thus, we would not expect the absence of a functional <lb/>mitochondria to have a significant effect until available glucose has been depleted <lb/>and the yeast are forced to respire. However, our data clearly indicate that the <lb/>mitochondria are having a significant phenotypic effect during both fermentation <lb/>and respiration. <lb/>One possibility is that there is a low level of respiration in cultures that are <lb/>primarily fermenting. If respiration alone is driving attraction, then we would <lb/>expect older cultures, which should have higher rates of respiration, to be more <lb/>attractive. However, we found exactly the opposite: younger cultures of BY4741 are <lb/>more attractive than older cultures, suggesting that attractiveness is not entirely <lb/>respiration dependent (Figure 4B). <lb/>When we compared the volatile compounds produced by the older and <lb/>younger cultures using GC--MS we found that several of the potential attractants <lb/>(isoamyl alcohol, phenylethyl alcohol) continued to grow in concentration in the <lb/>older, respiring cultures, while the rest (isoamyl acetate, and the ethyl esters) <lb/>disappeared (Figure 4B). These results suggest that individual metabolites vary in <lb/>levels of attractiveness. We classified the esters: ethyl acetate, isoamyl acetate, ethyl <lb/>hexanoate, and ethyl octanoate, which are highest in the younger plates, as primary <lb/>attractants. We classified isoamyl alcohol and phenylethyl alcohol as secondary <lb/>attractants, as our results suggest these compounds are not as attractive as the <lb/>esters. <lb/>Overall, these observations suggested that high levels of esters produced by <lb/>BY4741 during our early time point are primarily driving attraction, and that they <lb/>are not strictly associated with respiration. Instead, they appear to arise from a <lb/>separate mitochondria--linked process. <lb/>EEB1 Δ strain affects ethyl ester production and attraction <lb/>To further investigate ethyl esters as attractants, we next tested the EEB1∆ <lb/>strain from the BY4741 knockout collection (MATa;his3;leu2;met15;ura3;eeb1). <lb/>Both EEB1 and its paralog EHT1 have been implicated in medium chain ethyl ester <lb/>production, with most of the function attributed to EEB1 [38, 39]. We found the <lb/>EEB1∆ strain to be less attractive than BY4741 in our behavioral assay when strains <lb/>were grown for the standard incubation time (Figure 5). GC--MS analysis confirmed <lb/>a decrease in the production of both isoamyl acetate and ethyl esters in the EEB1∆ <lb/>strain, further implicating these compounds as important attractants in these <lb/>cultures (Figure 5). <lb/>Nitrogen source affects both the production of identified attractants and fly <lb/>preference <lb/>Although it is not widely appreciated, the mitochondria is required for <lb/>several metabolic processes not related to respiration [40]. For example, both <lb/>
            proline catabolism and branched chain amino acid anabolism have biochemical <lb/>steps that occur within the mitochondria [41, 42]. We therefore reasoned that <lb/>varying nitrogen sources -especially those with and without amino acids, or with <lb/>different distributions of amino acids -might lead to the differential engagement of <lb/>the mitochondria, different volatile compound production, and different <lb/>attractiveness to flies. <lb/>To test this we grew a prototropic, wild caught S. cerevisiae strain, T73, on <lb/>media containing equivalent carbon source (5% glucose) and varying types and <lb/>levels of nitrogen (Table 2). We collected GC--MS data for each condition and tested <lb/>all pairwise comparisons between these media in our behavioral assay. We found <lb/>that varying the nitrogen source had a dramatic effect on the types and levels of <lb/>volatile compounds produced by the culture, including the identified attractants <lb/>from our BY4741 strain (Figure 6). Further, the level of the attractive compounds <lb/>produced matched with behavior: the culture that produced higher combined levels <lb/>of attractive compounds in each pairwise comparison was always more attractive to <lb/>D. melanogaster (Figure 6). <lb/>Interestingly, across all pairwise comparisons, the most attractive medium <lb/>tested was the synthetic complete medium (SC), which most closely matched the <lb/>nutrient composition of a fruit, the natural substrate of S. cerevisiae. Like fruit, SC <lb/>media contained a mixed pool of amino acids as a nitrogen source and high levels of <lb/>sugar (5% glucose) (Table 2). This nutritional composition makes sense for ester <lb/>production. The high levels of sugar allow for uninhibited fermentation, while the <lb/>amino acid based nitrogen supply can be more efficiently consumed when the <lb/>mitochondria are functioning. Ethyl esters are formed from the fermentation <lb/>byproducts, ethanol and aliphatic acids, largely via EEB1 activity. The reaction <lb/>requires ATP, which will be far more abundant in fermenting cells with functional <lb/>mitochondria [38, 39]. We propose that D. melanogaster have evolved to sense these <lb/>esters specifically and use them as a signal of S. cerevisiae fermenting a sugar--rich <lb/>fruit substrate, an ideal oviposition site for D. melanogaster females. <lb/>The prototrophic strain, T73, grown on a natural fruit substrate produces the <lb/>highest levels of identified attractants <lb/>Based on the results of our nitrogen experiments, we collected GC--MS <lb/>profiles of T73 grown on pureed grape agar. The GC--MS profiles for these cultures <lb/>were dominated by our identified attractants. These cultures contained the highest <lb/>level of ethyl esters and isoamyl acetate seen in this study (Figure 7). These grape--<lb/>based fermentations were extremely attractive to D. melanogaster and reliably <lb/>attracted more flies than the most attractive media from previous comparisons (5% <lb/>SC) (Figure 7). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>S. cerevisiae is a versatile microbe that can survive and propagate on many <lb/>nutritional sources. Different combinations of substrate and genotype impose <lb/>unique metabolic demands on the yeast, leading to the production of distinct <lb/>volatile profiles. These characteristic volatile fingerprints can, in turn, signal to <lb/>other organisms, such as D. melanogaster, information about the substrate, and, <lb/>potentially, its suitability for their purposes. In this work, we have identified a piece <lb/>of the volatile vocabulary that helps bring together S. cerevisiae and D. melanogaster <lb/>in nature. <lb/>Our research shows that mitochondria affect S. cerevisiae metabolism even <lb/>during periods of fermentation, and that these metabolic alterations dramatically <lb/>influence the volatile small molecules produced and released by S. cerevisiae. In this <lb/>way, S. cerevisiae cells with and without functional mitochondria, grown on the <lb/>same substrate, produce different volatile profiles. We have shown that D. <lb/>melanogaster are able to sense the differences in the volatiles produced by these <lb/>strains and prefer the volatile &quot;fingerprint&quot; produced by yeast strains with <lb/>mitochondria. Using GC--MS, we identified the molecular compounds produced at <lb/>higher levels in the attractive cultures and tagged these compounds as <lb/>mitochondrially--associated attractants. <lb/>We also found that varying the type of nitrogen provided to a culture changes <lb/>the levels and varieties of volatiles it produces, including our mitochondrially--<lb/>associated attractants. This makes sense, as metabolism of many nitrogen sources <lb/>are known to be associated with mitochondria. We found the highest levels of our <lb/>attractants when the wild--caught S. cerevisiae strain was grown on a media <lb/>substrate with a nutritional composition similar to that of fruit. Like fruit, the media <lb/>contained high levels of fermentable sugars and a mixture of amino acids as a <lb/>nitrogen source -a nutritional scenario lending towards a combination of <lb/>fermentation and mitochondrial activity. <lb/>Together these results suggest that D. melanogaster&apos;s preference towards <lb/>mitochondrially--associated metabolites may have an ecological basis. We <lb/>hypothesize that D. melanogaster have tuned their senses towards these <lb/>mitochondria--associated attractants, as these compounds are produced when S. <lb/>cerevisiae are actively fermenting a fruit, where the combination of yeast and <lb/>ethanol produce an ideal environment for D. melanogaster larvae to develop and <lb/>remain protected from other microbial threats. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Behavioral setup: <lb/>A custom--crafted behavior arena and assay protocol was developed for these <lb/>experiments. Five behavior assays were conducted in parallel. Twenty--two hours <lb/>(4pm) prior to starting a trial, the specific yeast strains to be tested were streaked <lb/>from stock plates (stored at 4C and re--streaked from freezer stock (--80C) every two <lb/>weeks) onto freshly prepared 60x15mm Petri dish plates (see &apos;Media Preparation&apos; <lb/>for details). Plates were then transferred to 30C incubator and grown overnight. <lb/>Twenty--two hours later (2pm, following day) plates were removed from incubator <lb/>and behavioral traps were assembled for the assay. <lb/>To construct the traps, the cultures were topped with a custom--designed and <lb/>3D printed lid (uPrint Plus), which was then secured into place with Parafilm. The <lb/>custom lid allowed for the attachment of a 50 mL Falcon tube (bottom sawed off to <lb/>create a long, open tube) above the plate. A small piece of metal mesh was secured <lb/>between the adapter and falcon tube to allow for the volatiles emitted from the <lb/>culture to dissipate up through the Falcon tube, while physically separating the plate <lb/>from the Falcon tube chamber. The Falcon tube chamber was finally topped with a <lb/>funnel fashioned out of Whatman Grade 1 Filter paper (15.0cm diameter). The <lb/>funnel was secured in place by a small piece of lab tape (Figure S4). <lb/>
            The constructed traps were next transferred into the behavior chambers: 24&quot; <lb/>high, 12&quot; diameter clear, open--ended, acrylic cylinders (TAP plastics) fitted with <lb/>closable sleeve that allowed for placement and removal of both the traps and flies <lb/>(Figure S4). Behavior chambers were kept in a large room with over--head, diffuse <lb/>lighting that remained on for the entirety of the trial. The chambers were vacuumed <lb/>and cleaned with water and ethanol before each trail. Four traps were placed in <lb/>each cleaned arena, two for each yeast strain under analysis. Each strain pair was <lb/>tested in three different orientations: 2X2 (with the same strain next to each other) <lb/>in each orientation and a diamond orientation (with the same stain across from the <lb/>other).  One hundred and twenty 4--10 day old D. melanogaster were added into the <lb/>behavioral chamber between 3 and 3:30 pm (see &quot;Fly Husbandry and Handling&quot; <lb/>section for details). The traps were removed from the chambers 18h later, between <lb/>10 and 10:30 am. Before removal the orientation of each trap in each arena was <lb/>recorded. Flies in each trap were then sexed, counted, and recorded. These raw <lb/>counts were used to determine the preference for each strain in each arena. The <lb/>raw data can be found in Spreadsheet 1. <lb/>Calculation of Fly Preference (Preference Index): <lb/>To quantify and compare independent behavioral trials, we used a simple <lb/>preference index: <lb/>Every behavioral trial contained four traps. Two baited with yeast strain &quot;A&quot; and <lb/>two baited with strain &quot;B&quot;. One hundred and twenty 4--10 day old D. melanogaster <lb/>were added into each behavioral trial: <lb/>A= Total D. melanogaster caught in both traps baited yeast strain &quot;A&quot; in the trial <lb/>B= Total D. melanogaster caught in both traps baited yeast strain &quot;B&quot; in the trial <lb/>Preference Index (PI)= A--B/(A+B)/2 <lb/>Fly Husbandry and Handling: <lb/>D. melanogaster line Raleigh 437 was obtained from Bloomington Stock <lb/>Center for use in these experiments. All D. melanogaster used in behavioral assays <lb/>were raised using the same regimen.  A &quot;time course&quot; for each line was maintained <lb/>for the duration of the experiments. The time course consisted of pushing 3 vials of <lb/>25 flies into fresh media (CSM formula) topped with dried yeast pellets (Red Star) <lb/>daily. The 25 flies were refreshed with 4--day--old flies from a stock population every <lb/>10 days. The time course of vials was kept at 18C and the eggs laid in each vial were <lb/>allowed to develop (~18 day generation time). After ~18 days, each seeded vial <lb/>was checked daily for newly eclosed flies. All flies hatching off of on a given day <lb/>were transferred into fresh vials and stored in a 25C incubator for at least 4 days to <lb/>ensure full development and maturation to adulthood. The entire process was <lb/>repeated daily to maintain each strain. <lb/>To prepare flies for a behavioral trial, aged 4--10 day old flies were removed <lb/>from the 25C incubator and anaesthetized using CO2 and counted into groups of <lb/>120. The groups were visually inspected to insure roughly equal numbers of males <lb/>and females. The flies were transferred into a vial of fresh food and allowed to <lb/>recover and eat for 2--4 hours before being added into the behavior chamber. <lb/>A stock of Raleigh 437 was maintained at 18C and transferred to fresh media <lb/>monthly. <lb/>Media Preparation: <lb/>5% YPD for behavioral assays and strain storage was prepared weekly using <lb/>the following recipe (for 1L): 20g Peptone (BD Bacto Peptone), 10g Yeast Extract <lb/>(Amresco Yeast Extract, Bacteriological, Ultra Pure Grade), 50g Dextrose (Fisher <lb/>Scientific Dextrose Anhydrous), 20g Agar (BD Bacto Agar), Water to 1L. Solution <lb/>was mixed and heated to boiling on a magnetic stir plate. Liquid YPD was prepared <lb/>using (for 1L): 20g Peptone, 10g Yeast Extract, 50g Dextrose, Water to 1L. The <lb/>solution was stirred for five minutes and filter sterilized using Nalgene vacuum <lb/>filtration system (0.22 micron). <lb/>The following additional recipes were used in this experiment: <lb/>5% SC (for 1L): 1.7g YNB without amino acids and ammonium sulfate (BD Difco), <lb/>2.0g SC Amino acid mixture (MP Biomedicals), 50g Dextrose, 20g Agar, Water to 1L. <lb/>5%YNB (for 1L): 6.7g YNB without amino acids (BD Difco), 50g Dextrose, 20g Agar, <lb/>Water to 1L. <lb/>Grape Agar (for 1L): 1.7g YNB without amino acids and ammonium sulfate, 1L <lb/>organic grapes (v/v) (thoroughly washed and pureed in food processor), 20g Agar, <lb/>Water to 1L. <lb/>Yeast strains: <lb/>Strain <lb/>Genotype <lb/>Source <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>MATa;his3;leu2;met15;ura3 <lb/>ATCC <lb/>BY4742p <lb/>MATα;his3;leu2;lys2;ura3 <lb/>This Study <lb/>BY4742g <lb/>MATα;his3;leu2;lys2;ura3 <lb/>ATCC <lb/>MRPL16Δ (BY4742) MATα;his3;leu2;lys2;ura3;mrpl16 <lb/>Calahan et al (2011)[43] <lb/>EEB1Δ (BY4741) <lb/>MATa;his3;leu2;met15;ura3;eeb1 <lb/>ATCC <lb/>T73 (ATCC28383) <lb/>Wild isolate <lb/>Hyma and Faye(2011)[44] <lb/>Tetrad Experiment: <lb/>Twenty tetrads were obtained using a standard sporulation protocol <lb/>(Methods in Yeast Genetics, 2005). Briefly, BY4741 and BY4742p were mixed on a <lb/>YPD agar plate to encourage mating. Diploid colonies were selected by replica <lb/>plating onto a selective media (Met(--);Lys(--)) transferred to liquid &quot;YPA&quot; media for 1 <lb/>day, spun down and resuspended in &quot;Minimal Spo&quot; for at least 3 days. Ascii were <lb/>dissolved and tetrads dissected. After incubation, tetrads were genotyped by replica <lb/>plating onto selective media for MAT, LYS, and MET loci. Genotyped tetrads were <lb/>grown in YPD and prepared as freezer stocks using standard protocol (Methods in <lb/>Yeast Genetics, 2005). Freezer stocks of each stain were used to start cultures for all <lb/>behavior experiments. <lb/>Strain <lb/>Genotype <lb/>Source <lb/>1A (YME01) MATα;met15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>1B (YME02) <lb/>MATα;met15;LYS2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>1C (YME03) <lb/>MATa;MET15;LYS2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>1D (YME04) MATa;MET15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>3A (YME05) MATα;MET15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>3B (YME06) <lb/>MATa;met15;LYS2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>3C (YME07) <lb/>MATα;MET15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>3D (YME08) MATa;met15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>4A (YME09) MATa;MET15;LYS2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>4B (YME10) <lb/>MATα;met15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>4C (YME11) <lb/>MATa;met15;LYS2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>4D (YME12) MATα;MET15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>10A (YME13) MATa;met15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>10B (YME14) MATα;MET15;LYS2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>10C (YME15) MATa;MET15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>10D (YME16) MATα;met15;LYS2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>18A (YME17) MATa;met15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>18B (YME18) MATα;met15;lys2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>18C (YME19) MATa;MET15;LYS2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>18D (YME20) MATα;MET15;LYS2;his3;ura3;leu2 <lb/>This study <lb/>GC--MS protocol: <lb/>Sample analysis was performed on Agilent 7890A/5975C GC--MS equipped <lb/>with a HP--5MS (30m x 0.25mm, i.d., 0.25micrometers film thickness) column. <lb/>To sample the headspace of a plate culture, a conditioned, Twister stir bar <lb/>(10 mm in length, 0.5mm film thickness, 24microliters polydimethylsiloxane <lb/>volume) was suspended from the lid of the Petri dish using rare earth magnets for <lb/>40 minutes at room temperature. The Twister was then dried using a Kimwipe, <lb/>placed in a Gerstel thermal desorption sample tube, topped with a transport <lb/>adapter, and loaded into sampling tray. <lb/>Automated sampling and analysis was performed using the Gerstel MPS <lb/>system and MAESTRO integrated into Chemstation software. <lb/>Samples were thermally desorbed using the Gerstel Thermal Desorption Unit <lb/>(TDU), followed by injection into the column with a Gerstel Cooled Injection System <lb/>(CIS--4). Temperature program for desorption was 30C (.40 min), then 60C/min to <lb/>250C(hold for 5 mins). Temperature of the transfer line was set at 275C. The <lb/>injection was cooled with liquid nitrogen to --100C with a hold time (.60min).  The <lb/>injector inlet was operated in the Solvent Vent mode, with a vent pressure of 9.1473 <lb/>psi, a vent flow of 30mls/min, and a purge flow of 6mls/min (for .01 min). <lb/>The following GC--MS method parameters was used for each sample: The GC <lb/>temperature program was 40C (2 mins), then 4C/min to 140C (hold 0 mins), then <lb/>15C/min to 195C (hold for 0 min). The carrier gas head pressure was 9.1473 psi for <lb/>a flow rate of 1.2mL/min. The GC was operated in the constant flow mode. The MS <lb/>was operated in EI mode with the electron voltage set at autotune values. The <lb/>detector was set to scan from 30 to 300amu at a threshold of 150 with 3 samples <lb/>for a scanning rate of 2.69 scans/second. The MSD transfer line temperature was set <lb/>at 280C. The ion source and quadrupole temperatures were set at 230C and 150C, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>GC--MS data files were visually inspected using Chemstation. TIC peaks were <lb/>identified using the NIST O8 database via Chemstation. Datafiles were transferred, <lb/>parsed, and analyzed using custom written Matlab scripts (see &quot;Scripts <lb/>Supplement&quot;). <lb/>Aerobic and anaerobic yeast cultures: <lb/>Pairs of 100mL 5% YPD cultures were inoculated with BY4741 or BY4742p <lb/>cells (stored on a solid 5% YPD plate at 4C) and topped with either a loose foil cap <lb/>or fermentation bung (Ferm--Rite) to create aerobic and anaerobic growth <lb/>conditions for each strain. Cultures were grown for 21h shaking at room <lb/>temperature. After this growth period, cultures were removed from shaker, and an <lb/>O.D. reading was taken to ensure similar cell densities across each aerobic and <lb/>anaerobic culture pair. 50mL of each culture was transferred to a .22 micron <lb/>vacuum filter (MilliQ Steri--Flip) to remove yeast from the culture medium. 20mL of <lb/>the culture medium was then transferred into 20mL amber glass vials (Sigma), a <lb/>conditioned Twister stir bar (Gerstel) was added, and the vial was capped with a <lb/>silica--lined screw cap (Sigma). The Twister stir bars were spun in the medium at <lb/>300rpm for 40min, rinsed with MilliQ water, dried with a Kimwipe, and transferred <lb/>onto the GC--MS for analysis (see &quot;GC--MS protocol&quot; for details). <lb/>Glycerol plate growth: <lb/>BY4741 and BY472p and tetrads representing each genotype were streaked <lb/>from 5% YPD stock plates onto 5% glycerol plates. Plates were incubated at 30C for <lb/>48h and visually inspected for growth. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>KMS would like to thank Meru Sadhu for help with tetrad dissection experiment, <lb/>Tommy Kaplan and Peter Combs for advice on Matlab scripts, Steven Kuntz for <lb/>advice on figures, and Kyle Barrett for support. MBE would like to thank Barbara <lb/>Dunn, whose fascination with yeast ecology in the Botstein lab in the 1990s inspired <lb/>these experiments. <lb/></div>

			<body>Table 1: Identified chemical attractants: <lb/>Compound <lb/>CAS# <lb/>Retention <lb/>Time (min)* NIST* MW* <lb/>Quality <lb/>(% Match)* <lb/>Ethyl Acetate <lb/>141--78--6 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2019 <lb/>88 <lb/>86 <lb/>Isoamyl Alcohol <lb/>123--51--3 <lb/>4 <lb/>2124 <lb/>88 <lb/>90 <lb/>Isoamyl Acetate <lb/>123--92--2 <lb/>7.5 13474 <lb/>130 <lb/>90 <lb/>Ethyl Hexanote <lb/>123--66--0 <lb/>11.7 20902 <lb/>144 <lb/>98 <lb/>Phenylethyl Alcohol 60--12--8 <lb/>15.7 <lb/>9921 <lb/>122 <lb/>91 <lb/>Ethyl Octanoate <lb/>106--32--1 <lb/>18.8 39512 <lb/>172 <lb/>90 <lb/>*Retention time, NIST, Molecular Weight (MW), and Quality are based on BY4741 <lb/>chromatogram (061014_02.CDF) <lb/>Table 2: Nitrogen composition of media used in this study: <lb/>Media <lb/>Ammonium Sulfate (per L) Amino Acids (per L) Glucose (per L) <lb/>YNB <lb/>5.0g <lb/>0 <lb/>5.0g <lb/>SC <lb/>0 <lb/>2.0g <lb/>5.0g <lb/>YPD <lb/>&gt;5.0g* <lb/>&gt;2.0g* <lb/>5.0g <lb/>*YPD is a complete media source made by combining yeast extract and peptone as a <lb/>nutrient and nitrogen source. The exact nitrogen composition of these products is <lb/>unknown, but each is used in excess in a typical YPD media recipe (represented <lb/>above as &gt;5.0g/L and &gt;2.0g/L) <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Kacsoh, B.Z., et al., Fruit Flies Medicate Offspring After Seeing Parasites, in <lb/>Science2013. p. 947--950. <lb/>2. <lb/>Becher, P.G., et al., Yeast, not fruit volatiles mediate Drosophila melanogaster <lb/>attraction, oviposition and development. Functional Ecology, 2012. 26: p. 822--<lb/>828. <lb/>3. <lb/>Sang, J. and R.C. King, Nutritional Requirements of Axenically Cultured <lb/>Drosophila Melanogaster Adults. Journal of Experimental Biology, 1961. 33: p. <lb/>45--72. <lb/>4. <lb/>Reuter, M., G. Bell, and D. Greig, Increased outbreeding in yeast in response to <lb/>dispersal by an insect vector. Current biology : CB, 2007. 17(3): p. R81--3. <lb/>5. <lb/>Stamps, J.A., et al., Drosophila regulate yeast density and increase yeast <lb/>community similarity in a natural substrate. PLOS ONE, 2012. 7(7): p. e42238. <lb/>6. <lb/>Barbosa, C., A. Mendes--Faia, and A. Mendes--Ferreira, The nitrogen source <lb/>impacts major volatile compounds released by Saccharomyces cerevisiae <lb/>during alcoholic fermentation. International Journal of Food Microbiology, <lb/>2012. 160(2): p. 87--93. <lb/>7. <lb/>Barbosa, C., et al., Nitrogen addition influences formation of aroma compounds, <lb/>volatile acidity and ethanol in nitrogen deficient media fermented by <lb/>Saccharomyces cerevisiae wine strains. Journal of bioscience and <lb/>bioengineering, 2009. 108(2): p. 99--104. <lb/>8. <lb/>Torrea, D., et al., Comparison of inorganic and organic nitrogen <lb/>supplementation of grape juice -Effect on volatile composition and aroma <lb/>profile of a Chardonnay wine fermented with Saccharomyces cerevisiae yeast. <lb/>Food Chemistry, 2011. 127(3): p. 1072--1083. <lb/>9. <lb/>Hernández--Orte, P., et al., Addition of amino acids to grape juice of the Merlot <lb/>variety: Effect on amino acid uptake and aroma generation during alcoholic <lb/>fermentation. Food Chemistry, 2006. 98(2): p. 300--310. <lb/>10. Hernández--Orte, P., J.F. Cacho, and V. Ferreira, Relationship between varietal <lb/>amino acid profile of grapes and wine aromatic composition. Experiments with <lb/>model solutions and chemometric study. Journal of agricultural and food <lb/>chemistry, 2002. 50(10): p. 2891--2899. <lb/>11. Beltran, G., et al., Influence of the Timing of Nitrogen Additions during <lb/>Synthetic Grape Must Fermentations on Fermentation Kinetics and Nitrogen <lb/>Consumption. Journal of agricultural and food chemistry, 2005. 53(4): p. 996--<lb/>1002. <lb/>12. Vilanova, M., et al., Assimilable nitrogen utilisation and production of volatile <lb/>and non--volatile compounds in chemically defined medium by Saccharomyces <lb/>cerevisiae wine yeasts. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology, 2007. 77(1): <lb/>p. 145--157. <lb/>13. Nara, K., et al., A large--scale analysis of odor coding in the olfactory epithelium. <lb/>The Journal of neuroscience : the official journal of the Society for <lb/>Neuroscience, 2011. 31(25): p. 9179--9191. <lb/>14. Hallem, E.A. and J.R. Carlson, Coding of odors by a receptor repertoire. Cell, <lb/>2006. 125(1): p. 143--160. <lb/>15. Stökl, J., et al., A deceptive pollination system targeting drosophilids through <lb/>olfactory mimicry of yeast. Current biology : CB, 2010. 20(20): p. 1846--1852. <lb/>16. Turner, S.L. and A. Ray, Modification of CO2 avoidance behaviour in Drosophila <lb/>by inhibitory odorants. Nature, 2009. 461(7261): p. 277--281. <lb/>17. Krishnan, P., B.J. Duistermars, and M.A. Frye, Odor identity influences tracking <lb/>of temporally patterned plumes in Drosophila. BMC Neuroscience, 2011. <lb/>12(1). <lb/>18. Azanchi, R., K.R. Kaun, and U. Heberlein, Competing dopamine neurons drive <lb/>oviposition choice for ethanol in Drosophila. Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 2013. 110(52): p. <lb/>21153--21158. <lb/>19. Richgels, P.K. and S.M. Rollmann, Genetic variation in odorant receptors <lb/>contributes to variation in olfactory behavior in a natural population of <lb/>Drosophila melanogaster. Chemical senses, 2012. 37(3): p. 229--240. <lb/>20. Montague, S.A., D. Mathew, and J.R. Carlson, Similar odorants elicit different <lb/>behavioral and physiological responses, some supersustained. The Journal of <lb/>neuroscience : the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience, 2011. <lb/>31(21): p. 7891--7899. <lb/>21. Stensmyr, M.C., et al., Novel natural ligands for Drosophila olfactory receptor <lb/>neurones. Journal of Experimental Biology, 2003. 206(Pt 4): p. 715--724. <lb/>22. Suh, G.S.B., et al., A single population of olfactory sensory neurons mediates an <lb/>innate avoidance behaviour in Drosophila. Nature, 2004. 431(7010): p. 854--<lb/>859. <lb/>23. Arguello, J.R., et al., Can yeast (S. cerevisiae) metabolic volatiles provide <lb/>polymorphic signaling? PLOS ONE, 2013. 8(8): p. e70219. <lb/>24. Palanca, L., et al., Quantifying variation in the ability of yeasts to attract <lb/>Drosophila melanogaster. PLOS ONE, 2013. 8(9): p. e75332. <lb/>25. Rossouw, D., T. Naes, and F.F. Bauer, Linking gene regulation and the exo--<lb/>metabolome: a comparative transcriptomics approach to identify genes that <lb/>impact on the production of volatile aroma compounds in yeast. BMC <lb/>genomics, 2008. 9: p. 530. <lb/>26. Steyer, D., et al., QTL mapping of the production of wine aroma compounds by <lb/>yeast. BMC genomics, 2012. 13(1): p. 573. <lb/>27. Cha, D.H., et al., A four--component synthetic attractant for Drosophila suzukii <lb/>(Diptera: Drosophilidae) isolated from fermented bait headspace. Pest <lb/>management science, 2014. 70(2): p. 324--331. <lb/>28. Dobzhansky, T., et al., Differential Attraction of Species of Drosophila to <lb/>Different Species of Yeasts. Ecology, 1956. 37(3): p. 544. <lb/>29. Vacek, D.C., et al., Feeding and oviposition preferences of Drosophila buzzatii <lb/>for microbial species isolated from its natural environment. Biological Journal <lb/>of the Linnean Society, 1985. 24(2): p. 175--187. <lb/>30. Winzeler, E.A., et al., Functional Characterization of the S. cerevisiae Genome <lb/>by Gene Deletion and Parallel Analysis. Science, 1999. 285. <lb/>31. Garde--Cerdán, T. and C. Ancín--Azpilicueta, Effect of the addition of different <lb/>quantities of amino acids to nitrogen--deficient must on the formation of esters, <lb/>alcohols, and acids during wine alcoholic fermentation. LWT --Food Science <lb/>and Technology, 2008. 41(3): p. 501--510. <lb/>32. Procopio, S., et al., Significant amino acids in aroma compound profiling during <lb/>yeast fermentation analyzed by PLS regression. LWT --Food Science and <lb/>Technology, 2013. 51(2): p. 423--432. <lb/>33. Swiegers, J.H. and I.S. Pretorius, Yeast Modulation of Wine Flavor. Advances in <lb/>Applied Microbiology, 2005. 57: p. 131--175. <lb/>34. Styger, G., et al., Genetic analysis of the metabolic pathways responsible for <lb/>aroma metabolite production by Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Applied <lb/>Microbiology and Biotechnology, 2013. 97(10): p. 4429--4442. <lb/>35. Jiménez--Martí, E., et al., The nature of the nitrogen source added to nitrogen <lb/>depleted vinifications conducted by a Saccharomyces cerevisiae strain in <lb/>synthetic must affects gene expression and the levels of several volatile <lb/>compounds. Antonie van Leeuwenhoek, 2007. 92(1): p. 61--75. <lb/>36. Crabtree, H.G., The carbohydrate metabolism of certain pathological <lb/>overgrowths. Biochem. J., 1928. 22(5): p. 1289--1298. <lb/>37. De Deken, R.H., The Crabtree Effect: A Regulatory System in Yeast. Journal of <lb/>General Microbiology, 1966. 44(2): p. 149--156. <lb/>38. Saerens, S.M.G., et al., Production and biological function of volatile esters in <lb/>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Microbial Biotechnology, 2010. 3(2): p. 165--177. <lb/>39. Saerens, S.M.G., et al., Parameters Affecting Ethyl Ester Production by <lb/>Saccharomyces cerevisiae during Fermentation. Applied and …, 2008. 74(2). <lb/>40. Blank, L.M., L. Kuepfer, and U. Sauer, Large--scale 13C--flux analysis reveals <lb/>mechanistic principles of metabolic network robustness to null mutations in <lb/>yeast. Genome biology, 2005. 6(6): p. R49. <lb/>41. Kohlhaw, G.B., Leucine biosynthesis in fungi: entering metabolism through the <lb/>back door. Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev., 2003. 67(1): p. 1--15--table of contents. <lb/>42. Wang, S.S. and M.C. Brandriss, Proline utilization in Saccharomyces cerevisiae: <lb/>sequence, regulation, and mitochondrial localization of the PUT1 gene product. <lb/>Mol. Cell. Biol., 1987. 7(12): p. 4431--4440. <lb/>43. Calahan, D., et al., Genetic Analysis of Desiccation Tolerance in Saccharomyces <lb/>cerevisiae, in Genetics2011. p. 507--519. <lb/>44. Hyma, K.E., et al., Divergence in wine characteristics produced by wild and <lb/>domesticated strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae., in FEMS Yeast Res.2011. p. <lb/>540--551. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figure 1: D. melanogaster are preferentially attracted to BY4741 over nearly <lb/>isogenic BY4742 <lb/>We compared D. melanogaster preference for different yeast strains using an open--<lb/>flight preference assay. Each black dot represents the results of a single open--flight <lb/>preference trial between lab stocks of BY4741 and BY4742. The preference index <lb/>(PI) for each trial is defined as: PI= (A--B)/(A+B/2), where A = total flies caught in <lb/>BY4741 baits and B= total flies caught in BY4742 baits. This value represents the <lb/>direction of the preference (positive for A, negative for B) as well as the normalized <lb/>degree of preference by the percentage over the expected. Red dashed lines <lb/>represent the two--tailed standard deviation and the red &quot;+&quot; represents the mean of <lb/>all trials. <lb/>Preference <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>BY4742 <lb/>Figure 2: Genetic analysis of D. melanogaster preference for BY4741 over BY4742 <lb/>suggests mitochondrial inheritance. <lb/>To test if behavioral preference is associated with genotype, BY4741 and BY4742 <lb/>were crossed and sporulated and the resulting haploid segregants genotyped at the <lb/>MAT, MET15, and LYS2 loci. Segregants from five tetrads, collectively covering <lb/>spores of every genotype, were tested against BY4742 in our behavioral assay. The <lb/>red &quot;+&quot; represents the mean preference index of three trials. A) Tetrad spores of all <lb/>genotypes phenocopy the BY4741 parent, suggesting a mitochondrial inheritance <lb/>pattern.  B) Two tetrads were tested against both BY4741 (blue &quot;+&quot;s), with the &quot;+&quot; <lb/>representing the mean preference index of five behavioral trials. We found no <lb/>preference between each tetrad spore and BY4741, all of which possess functional <lb/>mitochondria. As shown in (A), all spores were preferred over BY4742, which does <lb/>not possess functional mitochondria. <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>BY4742 <lb/>BY4742 <lb/>BY4742 <lb/>BY4742 <lb/>BY4742 <lb/>Preference Index <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>a − − <lb/>α + + <lb/>a + − <lb/>α − + <lb/>α − − <lb/>a − − <lb/>α + + <lb/>a + + <lb/>α − − <lb/>α − + <lb/>a + + <lb/>a + − <lb/>α + − <lb/>a − + <lb/>α + − <lb/>a − + <lb/>a + + <lb/>α − − <lb/>a − + <lb/>α + − <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>Preference Index <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>a − − <lb/>α − − <lb/>a + + <lb/>α + + <lb/>α − − <lb/>α − + <lb/>a + + <lb/>a + − <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 2 <lb/>Figure 3: Mitochondrial status of S. cerevisiae affects D. melanogaster preference. <lb/>Pairwise behavioral results between BY4741 and various BY4742 strains, each with <lb/>a different mitochondrial status confirm role of mitochondria in D. melanogaster <lb/>preference. BY4742p is the original isolate, BY4742g is an independent BY4742 <lb/>strain with functional mitochondria, and BY4742 ∆MRPL16 is a strain from the <lb/>deletion collection known to genetically disrupt mitochondrial function. Each black <lb/>dot represents the preference index for each trial (see Figure 1). Red dashed lines <lb/>represent the two--tailed standard deviation and the red &quot;+&quot; represents the mean of <lb/>all trials. <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>BY4742p <lb/>BY4742g <lb/>BY4742 <lb/>∆MRPL16 <lb/>P r e fe r e n c e In d e x <lb/>-1 <lb/>1 <lb/>P r e fe r e n c e In d e x <lb/>P r e fe r e n c e In d e x <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>P r e fe r e n c e In d e x <lb/>-1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Figure 3 <lb/>Figure 4: GC--MS identifies volatile compounds that likely underlie D. melanogaster <lb/>preference for S. cerevisiae strains with functional mitochondria <lb/>A) To evaluate the effect of mitochondrial status on volatile compound production, <lb/>we performed GC--MS on one day old BY4741 and BY4742p cultures. The average <lb/>total ion chromatograms (TIC) for BY4741 is plotted on the positive y--axis, while the <lb/>TIC for BY4742p is plotted on the negative y--axis. The preference data from Figure 3 <lb/>for these two strains is shown to the left of the panel. Peaks marked with stars <lb/>represent compounds at higher abundance in BY4741 and represent potential <lb/>attractants. Compound names are given for all starred peaks. B) To evaluate if the <lb/>differences were due to the respiration defect in BY4742p, we used GC--MS to <lb/>compare the volatile profiles of one--day--old BY4741 cultures and respiration--<lb/>dominated, three day old BY4741 cultures; D. melanogaster exhibits a strong <lb/>preference for the one--day--old cultures. The one day BY4741 TIC is plotted on the <lb/>positive y--axis, and the three--day--old BY4741 TIC on the negative y--axis. One day <lb/>BY4741 cultures produce higher levels of a subset of the attractants (red stars), <lb/>while the others grow in the three--day cultures (blue stars). <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.8 <lb/>−0.6 <lb/>−0.4 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.8 <lb/>−0.6 <lb/>−0.4 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>Ethyl Hexanoate <lb/>Isoamyl Acetate <lb/>Ethyl Octanoate <lb/>Ethyl Acetate <lb/>Phenylethyl Alcohol <lb/>Isoamyl Alcohol <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>BY4742p <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>(1day) <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>(3day) <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Preference Index <lb/>Preference Index <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Ethyl Hexanoate <lb/>Isoamyl Acetate <lb/>Ethyl Octanoate <lb/>Ethyl Acetate <lb/>Phenylethyl Alcohol <lb/>Isoamyl Alcohol <lb/>Figure 4 <lb/>Figure 5: Deletion of EEB1 decreases ethyl ester production and affects D. <lb/>melanogaster preference. <lb/>Results of preference assay comparing BY4741 and BY4741 ∆EEB1 (left), along with <lb/>averaged TICs for GC--MS analysis of for BY4741 (positive y--axis) and BY4741 <lb/>∆EEB1 (negative y--axis). Both TICs were normalized together so that the maximum <lb/>value across both experiments was set to 1. <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>∆EEB1 <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.8 <lb/>−0.6 <lb/>−0.4 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>Ethyl Hexanoate <lb/>Isoamyl Acetate <lb/>Ethyl Octanoate <lb/>Ethyl Acetate <lb/>Phenylethyl Alcohol <lb/>Isoamyl Alcohol <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>Preference Index <lb/>Figure 5 <lb/>Figure 6: Nitrogen source affects levels of identified attractants and fly behavioral <lb/>preference in a prototrophic S. cerevisiae strain,. <lb/>We performed pairwise preference assays and GC--MS on a prototrophic strain of S. <lb/>cerevisiae (T73) grown on yeast extract, peptone, dextrose media (YPD), yeast <lb/>nitrogen base media (YNB) and synthetic complete media (SC) which vary in types <lb/>and levels of nitrogen. The pairwise D. melanogaster behavioral results have been <lb/>added to each side of the triangle representing the three pairwise comparisons. GC--<lb/>MS data is plotted using triangular Barycentric coordinates (the point for a given <lb/>compound is placed at the center of mass if the vertices are assigned a mass <lb/>corresponding to the GC--MS signal for that compound in the corresponding sample). <lb/>The variation in each attractant for every pairwise comparison can be read by <lb/>looking at how the compounds segregate across the midpoint of the relevant side <lb/>(drawn on figure as dashed line for emphasis). Primary attractants are plotted in <lb/>red and secondary attractants are plotted in blue. Attractants, in combination, track <lb/>with observed behavioral preferences, but no single attractant can explain all <lb/>behavioral results. <lb/>EtHx <lb/>IsAc <lb/>EtOc <lb/>EtAc <lb/>PAo <lb/>IsAo <lb/>S <lb/>YN <lb/>YP <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>Preference Index <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>P r e f e r e n c e I n d e x <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>P r e f e r e n c e I n d e x <lb/>EtAc: Ethyl Acetate <lb/>IsAc: Isoamyl Acetate <lb/>EtHx: Ethyl Hexanoate <lb/>EtOc: Ethyl Octanoate <lb/>IsAo: Isoamyl Alcohol <lb/>PAo: Phenylethyl Alcohol <lb/>Figure 6 <lb/>Figure 7: Primary attractants are detected at extremely high levels when T73 is <lb/>grown on its natural substrate, grape. <lb/>Behavioral results comparing the prototrophic strain T73 grown on grape media <lb/>and synthetic complete media (SC) (left). Average TIC for GC--MS data of T73 grown <lb/>on grape media (positive y--axis) and on synthetic complete media (SC) (negative y--<lb/>axis). Both TICs were normalized together so that the maximum value across both <lb/>experiments was set to one. <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.8 <lb/>−0.6 <lb/>−0.4 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>Ethyl Hexanoate <lb/>Isoamyl Acetate <lb/>Ethyl Octanoate <lb/>Ethyl Acetate <lb/>Phenylethyl Alcohol <lb/>Isoamyl Alcohol <lb/>T73 <lb/>T73 SC <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>Preference Index <lb/>Figure 7 <lb/></body>

            <div type="annex">Supplemental Figure 1: Confirmation of mitochondrial deficiency in BY4742p <lb/>BY4741, BY4742p, and tetrads (labeled by genotype) grown on glycerol to check for <lb/>ability of each strain to respire. All strains except BY4742p showed visible growth. <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>BY4742 <lb/>MATα; MET15; lys2 MATα; MET15; LYS2 MATα; met15; lys2 MATα; met15; LYS2 <lb/>MATa; MET15; lys2 <lb/>MATa; met15; lys2 <lb/>MATa; MET15; LYS2 <lb/>MATa; met15; LYS2 <lb/>Figure S1 <lb/>Supplemental Figure 2: Comparison of GC--MS profiles of aerobically and <lb/>anaerobically grown BY4741 and BY4742p cultures <lb/>Averaged TICs for: A) BY4741 grown both aerobically and anaerobically and B) <lb/>BY4742p grown aerobically and anaerobically in 5% YPD. TICs in each panel were <lb/>normalized together so that the maximum value across both experiments was set to <lb/>one. In each comparison, aerobic cultures are plotted on the positive y--axis and the <lb/>anaerobic cultures plotted on the negative y--axis. <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.8 <lb/>−0.6 <lb/>−0.4 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.8 <lb/>−0.6 <lb/>−0.4 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>Ethyl Hexanoate <lb/>Isoamyl Acetate <lb/>Ethyl Octanoate <lb/>Ethyl Acetate <lb/>Phenylethyl Alcohol <lb/>Isoamyl Alcohol <lb/>BY4741 Aerobic <lb/>BY4742p Aerobic <lb/>BY4742p Anaerobic <lb/>BY4741 Anaerobic <lb/>Figure S2 <lb/>Supplemental Figure 3: Tetrad produces GC--MS profile similar to BY4741 at <lb/>identified attractants. <lb/>Averaged TICs for BY4741, BY4742p and a selected tetrad (MATα;MET15;lys2). <lb/>BY4741 and BY4742p are plotted on the positive y--axis and the tetrad on the <lb/>negative y--axis in each panel. TICs in each panel were normalized together so that <lb/>the maximum value across both experiments was set to one. <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.8 <lb/>−0.6 <lb/>−0.4 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.8 <lb/>−0.6 <lb/>−0.4 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>BY4741 <lb/>BY4742p <lb/>MATα; MET15; lys2 <lb/>MATα; MET15; lys2 <lb/>Ethyl Hexanoate <lb/>Isoamyl Acetate <lb/>Ethyl Octanoate <lb/>Ethyl Acetate <lb/>Phenylethyl Alcohol <lb/>Isoamyl Alcohol <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>Figure S3 <lb/> Supplemental Figure 4: Images of the behavioral trap (A) and behavioral arena (B) <lb/>explained in &quot;Behavioral setup&quot; section of Methods. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Figure S4 </div>

	</text>
</tei>
