<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Behavioral individuality reveals genetic control of <lb/>phenotypic variability <lb/>Julien F. Ayroles 1,2,3, † , Sean M. Buchanan 4 , Chelsea Jenney 1,4,5 , Kyobi Skutt-Kakaria 1,5 , <lb/>Jennifer Grenier 3 , Andrew G. Clark 3 , Daniel L. Hartl 1 , Benjamin L. de Bivort 1,4,5, † <lb/>1 -Dept. of Organismic and Evolutionary Biology, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA. <lb/>2 -Harvard Society of Fellows, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA. <lb/>3 -Dept. of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA. <lb/>4 -Rowland Institute at Harvard, Cambridge, MA 02142, USA. <lb/>5 -Center for Brain Science, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA. <lb/> † Corresponding authors: ayroles@fas.harvard.edu, debivort@oeb.harvard.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/> Variability is ubiquitous in nature and a fundamental feature of complex systems. Few studies, however, have <lb/>investigated variance itself as a trait under genetic control. By focusing primarily on trait means and ignoring the <lb/>effect of alternative alleles on trait variability, we may be missing an important axis of genetic variation contributing <lb/>to phenotypic differences among individuals 1,2 . To study genetic effects on individual-to-individual phenotypic <lb/>variability (or intragenotypic variability), we used a panel of Drosophila inbred lines 3 and focused on locomotor <lb/>handedness 4 , in an assay optimized to measure variability. We discovered that some lines had consistently high <lb/>levels of intragenotypic variability among individuals while others had low levels. We demonstrate that the degree <lb/>of variability is itself heritable. Using a genome-wide association study (GWAS) for the degree of intragenotypic <lb/>variability as the phenotype across lines, we identified several genes expressed in the brain that affect variability in <lb/>handedness without affecting the mean. One of these genes, Ten-a implicated a neuropil in the central complex 5 of <lb/>the fly brain as influencing the magnitude of behavioral variability, a brain region involved in sensory integration <lb/>and locomotor coordination 6 . We have validated these results using genetic deficiencies, null alleles, and inducible <lb/>RNAi transgenes. This study reveals the constellation of phenotypes that can arise from a single genotype and it <lb/>shows that different genetic backgrounds differ dramatically in their propensity for phenotypic variability. Because <lb/>traditional mean-focused GWASs ignore the contribution of variability to overall phenotypic variation, current <lb/>methods may miss important links between genotype and phenotype. <lb/>Keywords: Drosophila, behavior, handedness, variability, vQTL, Tenascin accessory, Ten-a, heritability, DGRP <lb/>Abbreviations: DGRP: Drosophila Genome Reference Panel; ANOMV: Analysis of means for variance; QTL: <lb/>quantitative trait loci, GWAS: genome wide association study, MAD: median absolute deviation. GWAS: genome <lb/>wide association study, CI: confidence interval. <lb/></front>

			<body>Quantitative genetics was founded on a concept in which <lb/>phenotypic variation is explained solely by differences in mean <lb/>phenotypes among genotypes. Under this models, intragenotypic <lb/>variability is assumed to be attributable to non-genetic <lb/>environmental perturbations 1 . There is however, growing <lb/>evidence for the importance of genetic control of variance 2,7,8 <lb/>and that variance itself is a quantitative trait. Although studies of <lb/>morphology 9-11 and animal breeding 12,13 have long noted the <lb/>heterogeneity of variance among genotypes, this axis of <lb/>variation has received little attention compared to the effect of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body>genetic variation on trait means. As a result, the mechanisms by <lb/>which variable phenotypes arise from a uniform genetic <lb/>background are still poorly understood, particularly in the <lb/>context of behavior, where variability may be a critical <lb/>determinant 14,15 . Most recently with the advent of genome-wide <lb/>association studies, several groups 7,8,16,17 have mapped <lb/>quantitative traits loci affecting variance (vQTLs) by comparing <lb/>phenotypic variances among individuals that share genotypes. <lb/>These studies examine the average effect of QTL alleles across <lb/>genetic backgrounds and heterogeneous environmental across <lb/>individuals 18 , in the process losing any specific effects intrinsic <lb/>to each individual. <lb/>Here, we examine diversity that is typically hidden in population <lb/>averages, by examining phenotypic variability among <lb/>individuals with the same genotype. This is the variation that we <lb/>would observe if we could generate a large number of copies of <lb/>individuals of the same genotype in a common environment, and <lb/>measure a trait across them (an experiment for which isogenic <lb/>lines 2,9-11,18 are especially suited). In this case phenotypic <lb/>differences among genetically identical individuals result from <lb/>subtle micro-environmental perturbations and stochasticity in <lb/>development, while differences in variability among genotypes <lb/>reflects genetic differences in developmental stability 11 . While <lb/>intragenotypic variability contributes to phenotypic variation in a <lb/>population, this source of variation is not usually estimable <lb/>because, with few exceptions, each individual in an outbred <lb/>diploid population possesses a unique instance of its genotype. <lb/>As a consequence we have little understanding of the causes and <lb/>consequences of inter-individual intragenotypic variability. It <lb/>nevertheless has wide ranging implications. In evolutionary <lb/>biology, variability offers an adaptive solution to environmental <lb/>changes 19,20 . In medical genetics, diseased states emerge beyond <lb/>a phenotypic threshold, and high variability genotypes will <lb/>produce a larger proportion of individuals exceeding that <lb/>threshold than low variability genotypes, even if they have the <lb/>same mean. While intragenotypic variability has been discussed <lb/>in animal behavior, particularly in the context of the emergence <lb/>of personality 14,21 , to date no genes have been associated with <lb/>behavioral variability that do not also affect the mean. <lb/>To study this problem, we used a panel of Drosophila inbred <lb/>lines where, for each line, we can phenotype a large number of <lb/>individuals of the same genetic background, age, and rearing <lb/>environment. This allowed us to empirically estimate the <lb/>magnitude of intragenotypic variability. Specifically, we <lb/>measured the locomotor behavior of flies walking freely in Y-<lb/>shaped mazes 3 , focusing on the variability in locomotor <lb/>handedness (left-right turning bias). The precision and high-<lb/>throughput nature of our assays allows a large number of flies to <lb/>be measured per genotype and permits robust estimates of the <lb/>sampling error on variance itself. We tracked two hours of <lb/>locomotor behavior of 110 individuals (on average) from each of <lb/>159 lines from the Drosophila Genetic Reference Panel (DGRP) <lb/>in a randomized block design. For each individual fly, we <lb/>recorded the time and left-right direction of each turn in the <lb/>maze (Fig 1a), estimating a turn bias score as the fraction of <lb/>turns that were to the right. Flies performing more than 50 turns <lb/>were analyzed, and completed 413 turns per trial on average. <lb/>We began by comparing the mean turning bias and found no <lb/>significant genetic variation across lines (Supplementary Fig <lb/>1). In other words, averaged across individuals within a line, <lb/>each lines are unhanded, making an equal proportion of left and <lb/>right turns. We verified the lack of genetic variation for turning <lb/>bias within lines by crossing pairs of males and females with <lb/>matched turning biases (e.g., two strongly right-biased parents). <lb/>For all crosses, the phenotypic mean and variance of the <lb/>distribution of the F1 generation was statistically <lb/>indistinguishable from the distribution of the parental line <lb/>(Supplementary Fig 2). Handedness therefore provides an ideal <lb/>framework to study the genetics of variability because genetic <lb/>effects on variability are not confounded by mean effects. Next, <lb/>using parametric (ANOVA) and non-parametric (bootstrapping) <lb/>statistical approaches, we compared levels of intragenotypic <lb/>variability across lines and found highly significant among-line <lb/>differences in variability, implying that the abundance of <lb/>individuals that were either strongly left-or right-biased was <lb/>itself variable among lines. This indicates that the degree of <lb/>intragenotypic variability itself is under genetic control in these <lb/>lines (Fig 1b, Supplementary table 1). In order to obtain <lb/>further evidence that intragenotypic variability is heritable, we <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1 -Intragenotypic variability of locomotor handedness <lb/>varies across DGRP lines. a. Diagram of the Y-maze used to quantify <lb/>individual locomotor behavior. Plot at right illustrates 200 sequential <lb/>turns for 7 representative individual flies. A turn bias of 0.05 indicates <lb/>that this particular fly turned right 5% of the time (black stripes indicate <lb/>right turns and green stripes left turns). b. Sorted distribution of the <lb/>standard deviations of within-line individual turn bias, for 159 DGRP <lb/>lines. Red and blue filled dots are significant, exceeding their <lb/>corresponding tick-marked 99.9% confidence intervals, estimated by <lb/>permutation. See table S1 for experimental sample sizes. Cyan and <lb/>yellow highlighted dots are significant at p &lt; 0.001 based on non-<lb/>parametric bootstrap. c. Distributions of turning bias across individuals <lb/>for three representative DGRP lines with low, intermediate and high <lb/>intragenotypic variability. Each dot represents the turning bias of a <lb/>single fly within that line. Lines are beta distribution fits, chosen <lb/>because they model over-dispersed binomial distributions. <lb/>mated two high-variance and two low-variance lines to each <lb/>other and measured turning bias in the resulting progeny <lb/>(phenotyping an average of 183 individuals per cross). <lb/>Intercrosses between high-variance lines led to high variance F1 <lb/>progeny and crosses with low-variance lines yielded low <lb/>variance F1 progeny (Fig 2, Supplementary table 1). In both <lb/>cases the variability in the F1 progenies was statistically <lb/>indistinguishable from that of the parents. <lb/>It is conceivable that some lines might be better than others at <lb/>buffering microenvironmental perturbations, in which case the <lb/>degree of intragenotypic variability among lines would be <lb/>correlated across traits. To test this possibility, we scored <lb/>additional phenotypes from our Y-maze data, namely, the total <lb/>number of turns (a measure of overall activity); the mutual left-<lb/>right information between successive turns; and the regularity of <lb/>turn timing. We also analyzed other phenotypes previously <lb/>measured on the DGRP (starvation resistance 22 , chill coma <lb/>recovery 22 , startle response 22 , and night sleep 23 ). We found <lb/>significant genetic variation for variability in all these <lb/>phenotypes, confirming that genetic control of variability is <lb/>ubiquitous across phenotypes. On the other hand, we found no <lb/>evidence that the variances of these traits are correlated across <lb/>phenotypes (with the sole exception of mean absolute deviation <lb/>(MAD) of turn bias and turn timing regularity) (Supplementary <lb/>Fig 3). This suggests that the genetic basis for intragenotypic <lb/>variability is trait-specific (and implicates many independent loci <lb/>controlling this often-ignored trait). <lb/>The DGRP lines have been fully sequenced 22 , allowing for <lb/>whole-genome association mapping using the variability (i.e. <lb/>MAD) of turning bias as a trait. While the DGRP is <lb/>underpowered to study the architecture of complex traits due to <lb/>the relatively small number of lines (n=159 in this study), it is a <lb/>good resource to identify candidate genes for experimental <lb/>follow up 3,24 . To that end, we performed an association study <lb/>using a series of locus-specific mixed linear models (accounting <lb/>for relatedness between lines as well as experimental block <lb/>effect) and found 36 polymorphisms in 22 genes associated with <lb/>variability in turning bias using a nominal p-value 3,22 of 5 x 10 -6 <lb/>(Supplementary table 2). These genes are strongly enriched for <lb/>expression in the central nervous system both in adults and in <lb/>larvae (adult CNS enrichment in adult FET p &lt; 0.001 and in <lb/>larvae FET p &lt; 0.01, data from FlyAtlas 25 ) (Supplementary Fig <lb/>4). Among these, the synaptic target recognition gene Tenascin <lb/>accessory (Ten-a, GWAS p &lt; 3 × 10 -6 ) (Fig 3a) caught our <lb/>attention, Ten-a is a transmembrane signaling protein involved in <lb/>synapse formation 26,27 , critical to the development of the brain <lb/>central complex 5 (a brain structure implicated in sensory <lb/>integration and locomotion 4-6,28 ) and is highly conserved from <lb/>insects to mammals 29 . In order to validate the role of Ten-a in <lb/>modulating variability in turning bias, we used a null allele (Ten-<lb/>a cbd-KS9635 ), a deficiency overlapping Ten-a (Df(1)Ten-a 26 ), and <lb/>expression knock-down using RNAi (UAS-TRiP.JF03375 30 ). In <lb/>all cases, disrupting Ten-a increases the variability in turning <lb/>bias with no effect on the mean (Figs 3b,c and 4). The effect of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2 -Intragenotypic variability for turning bias is heritable. a. <lb/>Distribution of F1 turn biases resulting from high variance line 105 <lb/>reciprocally crossed to high variance line 45 (Brown-Forsythe p = 0.08; <lb/>n105x105 = 235 n45x45 = 315; n105*45 = 223; n45*105 = 135). b. Distribution <lb/>of F1 turn biases resulting from low variance line 535 reciprocally <lb/>crossed to low line variance line 796 (Brown-Forsythe p = 0.02; n535x535 <lb/>= 197; n796x796 = 265; n796*535 = 160; n535*796 = 234). In both panels, the <lb/>progeny are presented on the off diagonal. Lines are beta distribution <lb/>fits. Points are individual flies. For both 2a. and 2b., p-values comparing <lb/>F1 to parents ranged form 0.14 to 0.99, uncorrected for multiple <lb/>comparisons. <lb/>Figure 3 -Effect of Ten-a mutation on intragenotypic variability. a. <lb/>Intragenotypic variability (MAD) in turn bias of flies harboring <lb/>alternative alleles of the Ten-a SNP identified in our GWAS (n = 159, <lb/>GWAS p &lt; 3 × 10 -6 ). b. Turn bias MAD of a homozygous Ten-a null <lb/>allele (cbd 1 ; red) and heterozygous control (blue). bk indicates the <lb/>Ten-a + genetic background Berlin-K. ncbd1/Bk = 59, ncbd1/cbd1 = 99, <lb/>Brown-Forsythe p = 0.0074, bootstrapping p &lt; 0.001. c. Turn bias MAD <lb/>of a line bearing a homozygous deficiency overlapping Ten-a (red) and <lb/>heterozygous control (blue). nDf(1)-Bk = 100, nDf(1)Ten-a = 97, Brown-<lb/>Forsythe p = 1.5 -11 , bootstrapping p &lt; 0.001. *** p &lt; 0.001. Right plots <lb/>in all panels are corresponding beta distribution fits of the distribution <lb/>of turn bias scores within each experimental group. Shaded regions are <lb/>95% CIs on the beta fits, estimated by bootstrap resampling; CIs in (a) <lb/>small compared to line thickness. Error bars are +/-one standard error <lb/>estimated by bootstrap resampling. <lb/>RNAi knock-down suggests a quantitative relationship between <lb/>Ten-a mean expression and variance in turning bias. <lb/>The bias in handedness of a given fly is a fixed property of that <lb/>individual (e.g. a young adult with a strong left bias will display <lb/>this bias throughout its life 4 ). This suggests that handedness may <lb/>be wired during development. To determine if there is a critical <lb/>developmental period when Ten-a expression is required to <lb/>regulate variability, we used temperature-inducible RNAi to <lb/>knock down Ten-a in sliding 3-day windows (Fig 4a and b). We <lb/>found that knocking down Ten-a expression in mid-pupae <lb/>increases the resulting adults&apos; variability (Fig 4d). This stage <lb/>coincides with a spike in Ten-a expression 31,32 (Fig 4c) and the <lb/>formation of the central complex 5 . Further, Buchanan et al 4 <lb/>mapped a set of neurons within the central complex (i.e. <lb/>protocerbral bridge columnar neurons) that regulates the <lb/>magnitude of left-right turn bias, and therefore the magnitude of <lb/>intragenotypic variability. <lb/>Our use of inbred lines allowed us to estimate a parameter <lb/>(intragenotypic variability) that otherwise could not be observed <lb/>and uncovers the spectrum of phenotypes a given genotype can <lb/>produce. Because all phenotypic variation in handedness in a <lb/>population is (surprisingly) attributable to intragenotypic <lb/>variability, it highlights the importance of genetic control of <lb/>variability. The significance to medical genetics is far-reaching, <lb/>specifically for attempts to predict phenotype from genotypes <lb/>(e.g., &quot;missing heritability 33 &quot;). Within evolutionary biology, this <lb/>is significant for understanding evolutionary trajectories or <lb/>forces maintaining polymorphisms 9,19,34 . An individual drawn <lb/>from a high-variability genotype has the potential to explore a <lb/>wider range of phenotypic space than one with a low-variability <lb/>genotype (far beyond what may be determined by the mean <lb/>effect alone, Supplementary Fig 5). This could be advantageous <lb/>in evolutionary adaptation, but in human genetics it could be <lb/>deleterious when an extreme phenotype enhances disease risk. <lb/>Recent progress in single-cell technology18 now makes it <lb/>possible to measure cell to cell variation within an individual <lb/>genotype, enabling the study of intragenotypic variability in <lb/>human phenotypes such as drug response and cancer <lb/>progression. This study adds to an emerging body of work <lb/>suggesting that in order to understand variation in complex <lb/>traits, we must also understand the contribution of intragenotypic <lb/>variability. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4 -Disruption of Ten-a expression in mid-pupa affect behavioral variance. a. Time-courses of sliding window Ten-a RNAi induction. <lb/>Flies laid eggs for 24 h prior the start of the experiment and were reared at 20 o C (gray) until three days of RNAi induction at 30 o C (orange). Flies <lb/>were then returned to 20 o C until they were tested 3 to 5 days post-eclosion. b. Fraction of flies at any developmental stage during the course of the <lb/>experiment. Numbers indicate sample sizes. c. Ten-a expression level over development. Expression level derived from modENCODE 22 . d. Effect of <lb/>temperature inducible Ten-a RNAi on the variability of turning bias over development. Knock down effect varied significantly with the timing of the <lb/>induction window (p = 0.0027) estimated by a bootstrapping omnibus test (see Methods), with a knock down starting on day 7 greatly increasing <lb/>variability. This knockdown window coincides with the peak of Ten-a expression during pupation. Grey regions represent +/-standard error, <lb/>estimated by bootstrapping. To the right, the controls, tub ts /+ and Ten-a RNAi /+, measured after 3 day 30 o C windows starting on days 3, 7 and 13, show <lb/>no effect (p &lt; 0.47 and p &lt; 0.13 respectively). Numbers above data indicate sample sizes. Vertical guide lines associate data points across panels. <lb/>Methods <lb/>All raw data, data acquisition software and analysis scripts are <lb/>available at http://lab.debivort.org/genetic-control-of-<lb/>phenotypic-variability. <lb/>Drosophila stocks <lb/>The DGRP was created as a community resource for the genetics <lb/>mapping of complex traits 3 . It consists of a collection of <lb/>isofemale lines derived from a single field collection from the <lb/>Raleigh NC farmers market, followed by 20 generations of full-<lb/>sib mating that rendered most loci homozygous within lines <lb/>(expected F= 0.986 22 ). As a result, the genetic variation that was <lb/>present between individual flies in the natural population is now <lb/>captured between lines in the panel. This allows us to measure <lb/>any phenotype on a given genotypic background and phenotype <lb/>the same genotype a large number of times in any environment. <lb/>Completion of the genome sequencing for all lines combined <lb/>with Drosophila&apos;s generally rapid decay in linkage <lb/>disequilibrium between polymorphic sites makes the DGRP a <lb/>powerful tool to identify genetic polymorphisms that affect <lb/>quantitative phenotypes 3 . The DGRP lines are available from the <lb/>Drosophila Stock Center (http://flystocks.bio.indiana.edu). We <lb/>used a total of 159 lines in this study (lines with the highest <lb/>inbreeding coefficient -list is provided along with data at: http:// <lb/>lab.debivort.org/genetic-control-of-phenotypic-variability. Stock <lb/>used for Ten-a validation: Berlin-K, central-body-defect KS96 28 , <lb/>Df1-Ten-a 5 , and RNAi TRiP.JF03375 30 <lb/>All flies were reared on standard fly media (Scientiis and <lb/>Harvard University BioLabs fly food facility), in a single 25°C <lb/>incubator at 30-40% relative humidity with a 12/12h light/dark <lb/>cycle. Before each assay flies were fully randomized across: <lb/>blocks, lines, Y-maze arrays and position on the array. At least 3 <lb/>strains were assayed simultaneous on each array. <lb/>Variance, variation, variability: <lb/>The similarity between concepts of variance, variation and <lb/>variability may lead to some confusion. The meanings of these <lb/>terms are reviewed in Wagner and Altenberg 40 . In accordence <lb/>with their definition, we used the terms variance 2,18 to describe <lb/>the standard statistical dispersion parameter (σ 2 ) or estimates of <lb/>it derived from observations (s 2 ). Variability refers to the <lb/>potential of an organism or genotype to vary phenotypically. <lb/>Variation refers to the realized (observable) differences between <lb/>individuals or genotypes. <lb/>Phenotypic assay <lb/>Studying variance as a trait poses a number of challenges <lb/>including: the large sample size required (precise estimates of <lb/>variance requires a larger number of observations than needed to <lb/>estimate means), the experimental design (as to not confound <lb/>sources of error), and potential measurement error of the <lb/>phenotype itself 18 . It is with these considerations in mind that we <lb/>developed a high throughput assay aimed at monitoring the <lb/>behavior of individual flies placed into individual Y-mazes 4 (Fig <lb/>1.a). Each experiment examines one array of 120 Y-mazes <lb/>(refered to as maze-arrray). Mazes were illuminated from below <lb/>with white LEDs (5500K, LuminousFilm), imaged with 2MP <lb/>digital cameras (Logitech), and the X-Y positions of each fly&apos; <lb/>centroids were automatically tracked and recorded with software <lb/>custom written in LabView (National Instruments). Further <lb/>details about the assay are provided in 4 , code available at http:// <lb/>lab.debivort.org/neuronal-control-of-locomotor-handedness/. <lb/>While various statistics can be computed to estimate the degree <lb/>of variability of a distribution, in this study we use one the most <lb/>robust metrics, the Median Absolute Deviation (MAD) 8,17 . It is <lb/>defined as the median of the absolute deviation from each <lb/>observation&apos;s median: MAD = median (|Xi -median(Xi)|). <lb/>Where Xi is the phenotypic score of an individual fly within a <lb/>line. MAD scores were computed for each line for each <lb/>phenotype. <lb/>Only females were used in this experiment and only lines <lb/>yielding data from a minimum of 75 individuals were included. <lb/>Before each assay flies were very lightly anesthetized, rapidly <lb/>transferred to an individual Y-maze and given a recovery period <lb/>of 20 minutes before the start of the assay. Fly behavior in the <lb/>mazes was monitored for two hours. This assay generated four <lb/>phenotypes: (1) The handedness or left/right turning bias in the <lb/>arms of the maze summed over all L/R decisions. A turning bias <lb/>score of 0.8 for a given fly would indicate that this individual <lb/>made left turns 80% of the time at the maze&apos;s junction over the <lb/>two hour period. This simple phenotype is particularly well <lb/>suited for this study given that it is measured without error and <lb/>the high number turns for any given fly ensure a robust estimate <lb/>of the turning bias and it variance for each fly. (2) The number of <lb/>turns over the 2 hour period, an estimate of overall locomotor <lb/>activity. (3) The &quot;switchiness&quot; or the mutual left-right <lb/>information between successive turns right/left turn sequence <lb/>(e.g. LLLLLRRRRR: low switchiness, high mutual information; <lb/>LLRLLRRRLR: moderate switchiness, low mutual information; <lb/>LRLRLRLRLR: high switchiness, high mutual information) <lb/>defined as: <lb/>(N⟨L,R⟩+N⟨R,L⟩)/(2NRNL/N) <lb/>where N⟨L,R⟩ is the number of left turns followed by right turns, <lb/>N⟨R,L⟩ is the number of right turns followed by left turns NR is the <lb/>number of right turns, NL is the number of left turns, and N is the <lb/>total number of turns. (4) The regularity of turn timing: a fly <lb/>with a high score makes turns uniformly throughout the <lb/>experiment while a low score would characterize a fly making a <lb/>small number of dense streaks of turns but is inactive for dozens <lb/>of minutes at a time. It is defined as MAD(ITIs)/(7200/N) where <lb/>ITIs is the vector of inter-turn intervals in seconds. The left/right <lb/>turning bias is the main focus of this study, additional traits were <lb/>measured to illustrate that the degree of variability across traits <lb/>is not correlated between lines. <lb/>Quantitative genetic analysis <lb/>Analysis of Means: In order to determine if there was genetic <lb/>variation segregating in the DGRP affecting the mean turning <lb/>bias, we partitioned the variance for line means using the <lb/>ANOVA model: <lb/>Y = µ + Lrandom+ Brandom + L*B random + A + X + A*X + e <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>where Y is turning bias score of each fly; L is the effect of line <lb/>treated as random B is the effect of block treated as random, X <lb/>the box effect, A the maze-array effect and e is the error variance <lb/>(Supplementary Table 1). ANOVA implemented using PROC <lb/>MIXED in SAS 9.3. <lb/>Variance heterogeneity: We used several statistical approaches to <lb/>estimate heterogeneity of variance for turning bias between lines <lb/>(Supplementary Table 1). (1) The Brown-Forsythe test which is <lb/>based on a one way ANOVA and relies the absolute deviation <lb/>from the median 8,36 . (2) Non parametric bootstrapping in which <lb/>we first pooled all the turn bias scores for all individual flies <lb/>across lines, then resampled each line experimental group from <lb/>this pool, matching the sample size. Lines in which the MAD of <lb/>the resampled group was closer to the MAD of the pooled data, <lb/>in fewer than 10 of 10,000 resamples, were taken as significant. <lb/>This tests the null hypothesis that each group is drawn from an <lb/>identical distribution of observations, using MAD as a test <lb/>statistic. (3) A nonparametric version of the Analysis of Mean for <lb/>Variances (ANOMV) 37,38 . This approach compares the group <lb/>means of the Median absolute deviation MAD to the overall <lb/>mean MAD under the null hypotheses that the group MAD <lb/>means equals each line specific MAD. Implemented in SAS <lb/>9.3 37 . (4) Finally we used the same ANOVA model described <lb/>above for the analysis of mean but used the absolute deviation <lb/>from the median 8,9 as a measure for each fly as the dependent <lb/>variable. Implemented using PROC MIXED in SAS 9.3. <lb/>Phenotypic correlation between traits: We assesed 4 traits as <lb/>measured in this study and 4 additional traits gathered from the <lb/>literature (standard deviation for starvation, startle response, <lb/>chillcoma recovery 3 , coefficient of environmental variation for <lb/>night sleep 23 ). Phenotypic correlation between traits was <lb/>computed as the pearson product-moment correlation. P-values <lb/>are not corrected for multiple comparison. Implemented using <lb/>PROC GLM in SAS 9.3. <lb/>High and low variance lines intercrosses <lb/>In order to confirm that variability was heritable, we crossed <lb/>respectively high and low variability lines to each other. We <lb/>crossed high variability lines 45 to lines 105 and low variability <lb/>lines 796 to 535. 10 females and 5 males were used for each <lb/>cross. Flies were reared and phenotyped using the same <lb/>protocoled described above. Note that parental behavior was re-<lb/>measured concurrently with F1 behavior following a <lb/>corresponding self-cross (e.g. 45 x 45). We assessed statistical <lb/>significance between parental lines and their progeny using the <lb/>Brown-Forsythe test and a bootstrapping two-tailed z-test (with <lb/>n = 10,000 resamples). We resampled the turn bias of the parents <lb/>and for each iteration calculated the MAD of turning bias then <lb/>compared the MAD for the F1 progeny to their parents. <lb/>Genome wide association mapping <lb/>GWAS was performed using the code and approach decribed in 22 <lb/>(dgrp2.gnets.ncsu.edu). In a first step phenotypic stores were <lb/>adjusted for the potential effect of Wolbachia and known large <lb/>inversions segregating in this panel (namely: In(2L)t, In(2R)NS, <lb/>In(3R)P, In(3R)K, and In(3R)Mo) none of them were associated <lb/>with variability turning bias. We then fitted a series of loci <lb/>specific mixed linear model using the model: <lb/>Y = µ + Sb + Iu + e <lb/>Where Y is the MAD of turning bias of each DGRP lines, S is <lb/>the design matrix for the fixed SNP effect b, I is the incidence <lb/>matrix for the random polygenic effect u, and e is the residual 22 . <lb/>A total of 1,931,250 SNPs and indels were used in this analyses <lb/>with the minor alleles present in at least 7 DGRP lines, using <lb/>only biallelic sites. Polymorphisms segregating within lines were <lb/>discarded and for each SNP a least 60 DGRP lines had to have <lb/>been genotyped to be analyzed. Given the number lines available <lb/>in the DGRP, GWAS will generally be underpowered 24 , however <lb/>our goal is not to describe the overall genetic architecture of <lb/>each of these phenotypes, rather we seek to identify interesting <lb/>candidate genes that would provide some insight into the genetic <lb/>basis of variance control. For this reason we used a liberal <lb/>threshold of p &lt; 10 -6 . <lb/>The analysis for tissue enrichment was based on FlyAtlas data <lb/>which are publically available 39 . For each tissue, we used <lb/>FlyAtlas AffyCalls 25 to determine which genes were expressed <lb/>in which tissue (using a conservative filter of four out four <lb/>present calls). To determine significance we used a Fisher exact <lb/>test comparing the expected number of gene expressed in each <lb/>tissue across the entire genome to the observed number of gene <lb/>expressed in each tissue in our gene list. <lb/>Validation of Ten-a effect on variability: <lb/>Ten-a null and deficency: The turning bias and MAD turning <lb/>bias of homozygotes of both the null allele Ten-a cbd-KS963 5 and <lb/>deficiency overlapping Ten-a Df(1)Ten-a 6 where compared to <lb/>heterozygous animals over their genetic background, Berlin-K. <lb/>Time course knockdown of Ten-a RNAi: Ten adult Ptub-<lb/>Gal80ts;Ptub-Gal4/Sb females were crossed to three UAS-Ten-a <lb/>RNAi y1,v1;P(TRiP.JF03375)attP2 males for RNAi induction. <lb/>Flies were allowed to mate for 24 hours at 20°C at which point <lb/>the parents were passaged out and the bottles containing F1 eggs <lb/>were returned to 20°C until the beginning of their heat shock <lb/>window. Flies were exposed for 72 hours to 30°C temperature, <lb/>in 72 hour sliding window each day over 14 windows (fig 4a). <lb/>All flies assayed were between three and five days post-eclosion. <lb/>In parallel, each day developing flies of the same genotype were <lb/>examined and counted to determine the fraction of flies in each <lb/>developmental stage at the time of RNAi induction (fig 4b). <lb/>Stages containing larval animals were microwaved to melt the <lb/>media, poured through a sieve and larval carcasses counted <lb/>under a dissecting scope. Controls were performed using Ptub-<lb/>Gal80ts;Ptub-Gal4/Sb females crossed to Canton-S males and <lb/>C a n t o n -S f e m a l e s c r o s s e d t o U A S -Te n -a R N A i <lb/>y1,v1;P(TRiP.JF03375)attP2 males (fig 4d), otherwise treated <lb/>identically. <lb/>Ten-a expression: Data for Ten-a expression over developmental <lb/>time (Fig 4c) were downloaded from FlyBase 32 and derived from <lb/>ModEncode 31 (modENCODE DDC ids: modENCODE_4433, <lb/>_4435 and _4439 through _4462). This data reflects animals <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>synchronized by developmental stage to within two hours. To <lb/>make this data comparable to our experimental groups, in which <lb/>egg-laying occurred over 24h, we corresponded the <lb/>developmental stages of the FlyBase data to our developmental <lb/>stage time course (fig 4b), linearly interpolated the expression <lb/>values and applied a 24h sliding window average to the <lb/>interpolated data, mimicking the dispersion effects of our longer <lb/>egg-collection window. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors have no financial interests related to this work. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>JFA and BLdB designed the experiments, JFA, SMB, CJ, BLdB, <lb/>JG, and KSK carried out the experiments, JFA and BLdB <lb/>analysed the data. JFA, SMB, AGC, BLdB, DLH and KSK, <lb/>wrote the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We are grateful to Ian Dworkin, Mia Levene, Noah Zaitlen, and <lb/>Eric Stone for comments, discussions and helpful feedback on <lb/>the manuscript. This work was supported by grants: NIH R01 <lb/>AI064950 to A.G.C., Harvard Society of Fellows Fellowship and <lb/>Harvard Milton Funds to J.F.A, and the Rowland Junior <lb/>Fellowship to B.L.d.B. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Lynch, M. &amp; Walsh, B. Genetics and analysis of quantitative traits. <lb/>Sinauer Associates 1 st edition (1998). <lb/>2. Hill, W. G. &amp; Mulder, H. A. Genetic analysis of environmental <lb/>variation. Genet Res 92, 381-395 (2010). <lb/>3. Mackay, T. F. C. et al. The Drosophila melanogaster Genetic <lb/>Reference Panel. Nature 482, 173-178 (2012). <lb/>4. Buchanan, S. M., Kain, J. S. &amp; de Bivort, B. L. Neuronal control of <lb/>locomotor handedness in Drosophila. 1-14 (2014). <lb/>5. Cheng, X. et al. Ten-a Affects the Fusion of Central Complex <lb/>Primordia in Drosophila. PLoS ONE 8, e57129 (2013). <lb/>6. Young, J. M. &amp; Armstrong, J. D. Building the central complex in <lb/>Drosophila: the generation and development of distinct neural <lb/>subsets. J Comp Neur 518, 1525-41 (2010). <lb/>7. Yang, J. et al. FTO genotype is associated with phenotypic variability <lb/>of body mass index. Nature 490, 267-272 (2012). <lb/>8. Shen, X., Pettersson, M., Rönnegård, L. &amp; Carlborg, Ö. Inheritance <lb/>Beyond Plain Heritability: Variance-Controlling Genes in <lb/>Arabidopsis thaliana. PLoS Genet. 8, e1002839 (2012). <lb/>9. Dworkin, I. A study of canalization and developmental stability in the <lb/>sternopleural bristle system of Drosophila melanogaster. Evolution <lb/>59, 1500-1509 (2005). <lb/>10. Mackay, T. F. &amp; Lyman, R. F. Drosophila bristles and the nature of <lb/>quantitative genetic variation. Philos Trans R Soc B 360, 1513-1527 <lb/>(2005). <lb/>11. Willmore, K. E., Young, N. M. &amp; Richtsmeier, J. T. Phenotypic <lb/>variability: Its components, measurement and underlying <lb/>developmental processes. Evol Biol 34, 99-120 (2007). <lb/>12. SanCristobal-Gaudy, M. &amp; Bodin, L. Genetic components of litter <lb/>size variability in sheep. Select Evo 33, 249-271 (2001). <lb/>13. Sorensen, D. &amp; Waagepetersen, R. Normal linear models with <lb/>genetically structured residual variance heterogeneity: a case study. <lb/>Genet Res 82, 207-22 (2003). <lb/>14. Stamps, J. A. &amp; Groothuis, T. Developmental perspectives on <lb/>personality: implications for ecological and evolutionary studies of <lb/>individual differences. Philos Trans R Soc B 365, 4029-4041 (2010). <lb/>15. Stamps, J. A., Saltz, J. B. &amp; Krishnan, V. V. Genotypic differences <lb/>in behavioural entropy: unpredictable genotypes are composed of <lb/>unpredictable individuals. Anim Behav 86, 641-649 (2013). <lb/>16. Rönnegård, L. &amp; Valdar, W. Detecting major genetic loci controlling <lb/>phenotypic variability in experimental crosses. Genetics 188, 435-<lb/>447 (2011). <lb/>17. Rönnegård, L. &amp; Valdar, W. Recent developments in statistical <lb/>methods for detecting genetic loci affecting phenotypic variability. <lb/>BMC Genet 13, 63 (2012). <lb/>18. Geiler-Samerotte, K. A. et al. The details in the distributions: why <lb/>and how to study phenotypic variability. Curr Opin Biotech 24, 752-<lb/>759 (2013). <lb/>19. Queitsch, C., Sangster, T. A. &amp; Lindquist, S. Hsp90 as a capacitor of <lb/>phenotypic variation. Nature 417, 618-24 (2002). <lb/>20. Gibson, G. &amp; Wagner, G. Canalization in evolutionary genetics: a <lb/>stabilizing theory? Bioessays 4, 372-80 (2000). <lb/>21. Kain, J. S., Stokes, C., &amp; de Bivort, B. L. Phototactic personality in <lb/>fruit flies and its suppression by serotonin and white. P Natl Acad Sci <lb/>USA 109, 19834-19839 (2012). <lb/>22. Huang, W. et al. Natural variation in genome architecture among <lb/>205 Drosophila melanogaster Genetic Reference Panel lines. <lb/>Genome Res 24, 113-1208 (2014). <lb/>23. Harbison, S. T., McCoy, L. J. &amp; Mackay, T. F. Genome-wide <lb/>association study of sleep in Drosophila melanogaster. BMC <lb/>Genomics 14, 281 (2013). <lb/>24. Turner, T. L. &amp; Miller, P. M. Investigating natural variation in <lb/>Drosophila courtship song by the evolve and resequence approach. <lb/>Genetics 191, 633-642 (2012). <lb/>25. Robinson, S. W., Herzyk, P., Dow, J. A. T. &amp; Leader, D. P. FlyAtlas: <lb/>database of gene expression in the tissues of Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster. Nucl Acids Res 41, D744-50 (2013). <lb/>26. Hong, W., Mosca, T. J. &amp; Luo, L. Teneurins instruct synaptic partner <lb/>matching in an olfactory map. Nature 484, 201-207 (2012). <lb/>27. Mosca, T. J., Hong, W., Dani, V. S., Favaloro, V. &amp; Luo, L. Trans-<lb/>synaptic Teneurin signalling in neuromuscular synapse organization <lb/>and target choice. Nature 484, 237-41 (2012). <lb/>28. Strauss, R. The central complex and the genetic dissection of <lb/>locomotor behaviour. Curr Opin Neuro 6, 633-38 (2002). <lb/>29. Tucker, R. P., Beckmann, J., Leachman, N. T. &amp; Schöler, J. <lb/>Phylogenetic analysis of the teneurins: conserved features and <lb/>premetazoan ancestry. Mol Biol Evol 29, 1019-29 (2011). <lb/>30. Perkins, L. A., Holderbaum, L. &amp; Perrimon, N. Update to the TRiP <lb/>stock collection. (2009). <lb/>31. modENCODE Consortium. Identification of functional elements <lb/>and regulatory circuits by Drosophila modENCODE. Science 330, <lb/>1787-97 (2010). <lb/>32. Gelbart, W. M. &amp; Emmert, D. B. FlyBase high throughput <lb/>expression pattern data. (2013). <lb/>33. Gibson, G. Hints of hidden heritability in GWAS. Nat. Genet 42, <lb/>558-60 (2010). <lb/>34. Carter, A. &amp; Houle, D. Artificial selection reveals heritable variation <lb/>for developmental instability. Evolution 65, 3558-64 (2011). <lb/>35. Huang, W. et al. Epistasis dominates the genetic architecture of <lb/>Drosophila quantitative traits. Proc Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. 109, <lb/>15553-15559 (2012). <lb/>36. Brown, M. B. &amp; Forsythe, A. B. Robust Tests for the Equality of <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Variances. J Am Stat Assoc 69, 364-367 (1974). <lb/>37. Nelson, P. R., Wludyka, P. S. &amp; Copeland, K. The analysis of <lb/>means: a graphical method for comparing means, rates, and <lb/>proportions. SIAM (2005). <lb/>38. Wludyka, P. S. Two non-parametric, analysis-of-means-type tests <lb/>for homogeneity of variances. J App Stat 26, 243-256 (1999). <lb/>39. Chintapalli, V. R., Wang, J., Herzyk, P., Davies, S. A. &amp; Dow, J. A. <lb/>Data-mining the FlyAtlas online resource to identify core functional <lb/>motifs across transporting epithelia. BMC Genomics 14, 518 (2013). <lb/>40. Wagner, G &amp; Altenberg L. Complex adaptations and the evolution <lb/>of evolvability. Evolution 50, 967-976 (1996). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary materials <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Figure 1 -Turn bias variability is correlated neither with the mean of turning bias nor residual genetic variation within line. <lb/>a. Distribution of the mean turning bias for each line, ranked by the MAD of turning bias (grey dots, scale on the right axis). Tick marks represent a <lb/>99.9% CI around the mean. There is no significant difference between lines in mean turning bias. Each lines are on average un-handed, making equal <lb/>portions of left and right turns. ANOVA p-value &lt; 0.87. b. No relationship between the mean turning bias and intragenotypic variability (r 2 = 0.0004, <lb/>p-value = 0.80). c. No relationship between intragenotypic variability and residual genetic variation segregating within line (r 2 = 0.0005, p-value = <lb/>0.78), data from 35 . <lb/>Supplementary Figure 2 -No genetic variation segregating within lines is associated with turning bias. <lb/>Crosses between extreme left turning parents (at left) and crosses between extreme right turning parent (at right) produce unbiased F1 with a 50/50 <lb/>left-right turning bias. Data modified from 4 . <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Figure 3 -Intragenotypic variability in various phenotypes is predominantly uncorrelated. Scatter plots of pairs of measures <lb/>of intragenotypic variability. Points are DGRP lines. Red line is linear fit with 95% confidence interval in gray. Standard deviation for starvation <lb/>resistance, chill coma recovery and startle response were calculated based on data from 22 . CVE for night sleep data from 23 . For starvation resistance n <lb/>per line = 40, chillcoma n per line = 50, startle response n per line = 40, night sleep n per line = 32. <lb/>Supplementary Figure 4 -GWAS p-value distributions. a.-log10(p-value) plotted along each chromosomal position for all SNPs. Colors and <lb/>letters indicate chromosome arms b. QQ plot comparing observed p-value to a uniform distribution of expected p-value (lambda = 1.07). <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Figure 5 -Consequences of intragenotypic variability on the fraction of a hypothetical population exceeding a disease <lb/>threshold. a. Visual representation of the effects of variance on the prevalence of phenotype exceeding a threshold, such as a disease. Genotype 1 <lb/>and 2 differ in their degree of intragenotypic variability. The sets of circles at left represent the range of possible outcomes for each genotype. <lb/>Generally, each individual in an outbred diploid organism is a unique instance of its genotype. By contrast, our experiments with inbred lines allow <lb/>us to consider multiple individuals from the same distribution. An individual drawn at random from genotype 1 (high variability) may land in the tail <lb/>of the distribution, potentially in disease space. On the other hand an individual drawn randomly from genotype 2 never gets a chance to explore the <lb/>phenotypic space explored by genotype 1, even if it is just as much of an outlier within its respective distribution. b. For a hypothetical normally-<lb/>distributed population, we computed the fraction passing a disease threshold as a function of changes in variance. The distribution mean was set at 1 <lb/>and the disease threshold was set at 2. It is evident that the fraction of the population passing the disease threshold strongly depends on the variability. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Table 1 -Statistics for analysis of mean and variance across DGRP lines for turning bias. df: degrees of freedom; F: F ratio <lb/>statistic; p: p-value for F ratio statistic. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Ayroles et al., 2014 -preprint version <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Table 2 -Top GWAS hits for MAD of turning bias. </div>


	</text>
</tei>
