<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/> Data and Text Mining <lb/>ENVIRONMENTS and EOL: identification of Environment Ontolo-<lb/>gy terms in text and the annotation of the Encyclopedia of Life <lb/>Evangelos Pafilis 1, * , Sune P Frankild 2 , Julia Schnetzer 3,4 , Lucia Fanini 1 , Sarah Faulwet-<lb/>ter 1 , Christina Pavloudi 1 , Aikaterini Vasileiadou 1 , Patrick Leary 5 , Jennifer Hammock 6 , <lb/>Katja Schulz 6 , Cynthia Sims Parr 6 , Christos Arvanitidis 1 and Lars Juhl Jensen 2, * <lb/>1 Institute of Marine Biology, Biotechnology and Aquaculture, Hellenic Centre for Marine Research, P.O. Box <lb/>2214, Heraklion, 71003, Crete, Greece, 2 Disease Systems Biology Program, Novo Nordisk Foundation Center for <lb/>Protein Research, Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences, University of Copenhagen, Blegdamsvej 3b, 2200 <lb/>Copenhagen, Denmark, 3 Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, Celsiusstr. 1, 28359, Bremen, Germany, <lb/>4 Jacobs University gGmbH, School of Engineering and Sciences, Campusring 1, 28759, Bremen, Germany, <lb/>5 Marine Biological Laboratory, 7 MBL Str, Woods Hole, MA 02543, US and 6 National Museum of Natural History, <lb/>Smithsonian Institution, PO Box 37012, MRC 163, Washington, DC 20013-7012, US <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Summary: The association of organisms to their environments is a <lb/>key issue in exploring biodiversity patterns. This knowledge has <lb/>traditionally been scattered, but textual descriptions of taxa and their <lb/>habitats are now being consolidated in centralized resources. How-<lb/>ever, structured annotations are needed to facilitate large-scale <lb/>analyses. Therefore, we developed ENVIRONMENTS, a fast dic-<lb/>tionary-based tagger capable of identifying Environment Ontology <lb/>terms in text. We evaluate the accuracy of the tagger on a new <lb/>manually curated corpus of 600 Encyclopedia Of Life (EOL) species <lb/>pages. We use the tagger to associate taxa with environments by <lb/>tagging EOL text content monthly, and integrate the results into the <lb/>EOL to disseminate them to a broad audience of users. <lb/>Availability and implementation: The software and the corpus are <lb/>available under the open-source BSD and the CC-BY-NC-SA 3.0 <lb/>licenses, respectively, at http://environments.hcmr.gr <lb/>Contact: pafilis@hcmr.gr; lars.juhl.jensen@cpr.ku.dk <lb/></front>

			<body>1 INTRODUCTION <lb/>The Encyclopedia of Life (EOL; http://eol.org/) is a web resource <lb/>offering biodiversity knowledge summaries of the world&apos;s species <lb/>to a vast audience (Parr et al., 2014). It currently aggregates con-<lb/>tent from more than 250 providers. These include textual descrip-<lb/>tions about the biology, such as habitat, of more than 900,000 taxa. <lb/>The Environment Ontology (ENVO) project aims to provide a <lb/>controlled, structured vocabulary to support annotation of organ-<lb/>isms with environmental descriptors (Buttigieg et al., 2013). The <lb/>ontology comprises ~1600 terms and is part of recommended se-<lb/>quence metadata standards (Yilmaz et al., 2011). Having the envi-<lb/>ronmental information contained in EOL annotated in the form of <lb/>ENVO terms, rather than as free text, would enhance search capa-<lb/>bilities and enable users to easily compile summary statistics on, <lb/>for example, the ecological distribution of any taxa. However, <lb/>manually annotating all EOL entries with ENVO terms would be <lb/></body>

			<front>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. <lb/></front>

			<body>highly time demanding. An attractive alternative is to use text min-<lb/>ing to automatically tag ENVO terms. So far, the few efforts to <lb/>perform named entity recognition of environments have focused on <lb/>tagging bacteria biotopes (Bossy et al., 2013) or made use of ge-<lb/>neric tools, not optimized for the task (Thessen and Parr, 2014). <lb/>Here we present ENVIRONMENTS, a tagger capable of identi-<lb/>fying ENVO terms with sufficient accuracy and speed to be useful <lb/>for annotating large text corpora. To benchmark the method, we <lb/>developed a new gold standard corpus of manually annotated EOL <lb/>taxon pages. Last but not least, we have extended the EOL web <lb/>resource with ENVO terms for each taxon, which are automatically <lb/>mined from their textual descriptions. <lb/>2 ENVIRONMENT ONTOLOGY TERM TAGGER <lb/>ENVIRONMENTS identifies ENVO terms in text using the same <lb/>fast dictionary-based tagging engine as in Pafilis et al., 2013. The <lb/>command-line tool requires only a single parameter, namely the <lb/>path to a folder with the text files to be processed. <lb/>We constructed a dictionary based on ENVO by extracting all <lb/>names and synonyms from the OBO file, excluding broad syno-<lb/>nyms, obsolete terms, terms describing foods rather than environ-<lb/>ments, and terms representing organisms and tissues, which are <lb/>better captured by other ontologies. Names connected to multiple <lb/>terms were assigned to the one that best captures its meaning, by <lb/>ranking the terms based on whether the name was the primary <lb/>name, an exact synonym, a narrow synonym, or a related synonym <lb/>of the term. Because ENVO usually lists only the singular noun <lb/>forms, we automatically generated plural and adjective forms. <lb/>A small fraction of the names will result in many false positives <lb/>due to homonymy. We created a block list of such names by in-<lb/>specting text for all names that appeared more than 2000 times in <lb/>Medline and EOL. To find important synonyms missing in ENVO, <lb/>we tagged the habitat and ecology sections of 1,342,968 EOL pag-<lb/>es with even identifiers, and inspected all words occurring more <lb/>than 100 times in untagged text segments. Based on this analysis <lb/>and false negatives found in the development part of the curated <lb/>corpus, we added 142 synonyms to the dictionary. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">E. Pafilis et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>3 MANUALLY CURATED CORPUS <lb/>To construct an evaluation corpus that covers diverse environment <lb/>types, we retrieved 313,269 EOL species pages representing the <lb/>clades Actinopterygii, Annelida, Arthropoda, Aves, Chlorophyta, <lb/>Mammalia, Mollusca, Streptophyta. From these we extracted the <lb/>sections about behavior, biology, dispersal, distribution, ecology, <lb/>habitat, legislation, migration, reproduction, and trophic strategy. <lb/>After discarding very short (&lt;100 words) and very long (&gt;1,000 <lb/>words) pages, we randomly selected 75 species from each of the <lb/>eight clades. The resulting 600 species pages were randomly dis-<lb/>tributed among six annotators; 20% of the pages were given to two <lb/>annotators to allow for assessment of inter-annotator agreement. <lb/>Each person independently annotated ENVO terms in the text, with <lb/>no knowledge of which pages had been assigned to a second anno-<lb/>tator. Based on the shared abstracts we find that the median pair-<lb/>wise Cohen&apos;s kappa is 0.65, implying that the overall inter-<lb/>annotator agreement (IAA) is acceptable despite the difficulty of <lb/>the annotation task. The corpus was partitioned so that pages with <lb/>even and odd EOL identifiers were used for development and final <lb/>evaluation, respectively. <lb/>4 PERFORMANCE EVALUATION <lb/>Since the ENVIRONMENTS tagger recognizes names within text <lb/>and links them to ENVO terms, we benchmarked both aspects of <lb/>its performance. To quantify to which extent the tagger recognizes <lb/>the same text fragments as the annotators, we calculated precision <lb/>and recall at the mention level, considering both exact and partially <lb/>overlapping matches as true positives. On the evaluation part of the <lb/>corpus, this resulted in 87.8% precision and 77.0% recall, corre-<lb/>sponding to an F1 score of 82.0%. For the matches that were con-<lb/>sidered true positive for the recognition task, we further evaluated <lb/>if the tagger linked them to the same ENVO terms as the annota-<lb/>tors did. In 87.1% of cases, the tagger and the annotator agreed on <lb/>at least one ENVO term. <lb/>5 ANNOTATION OF ENCYCLOPEDIA OF LIFE <lb/>To realize the full potential of any text-mining system, it is im-<lb/>portant that it is adopted by the broad community and that its re-<lb/>sults are disseminated to the intended end users. To this end, we <lb/>have integrated the ENVIRONMENTS tagger with the EOL web <lb/>resource to provide users with ENVO terms for each taxon. Each <lb/>month, we rerun the tagger on all English text in environment-<lb/>related sections of EOL. As of October 2014, this gave rise to <lb/>1,077,522 annotations of ENVO terms for 234,582 EOL taxa. <lb/>We make these environment annotations available to end users <lb/>in three different ways. First, we show them within the EOL taxon <lb/>web pages, which provide links to the relevant paragraphs in the <lb/>textual descriptions for each ENVO term (Figure 1). Second, they <lb/>can be queried through the web interface or the application pro-<lb/>gramming interface of the new EOL/Traitbank semantic web data <lb/>repository of organismal traits (http://eol.org/traitbank). Third, the <lb/>full annotation dataset can be downloaded in tab-delimited format <lb/>from http://downloads.jensenlab.org/EOL. <lb/>6 FUTURE WORK <lb/>The ENVIRONMENTS tagger is applicable to other large sources <lb/>of text than EOL. For example, it can be applied to text fields, such <lb/>as isolation source, in Genbank (Hirschman et al., 2008). Com-<lb/>bined with the SPECIES tagger (Pafilis et al., 2013), it can also be <lb/>used to extract species-environment pairs from the scientific litera-<lb/>ture, like legacy biodiversity literature (Gwinn and Rinaldo, 2009). <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>Funding: This work was supported by the Encyclopedia Of Life <lb/>Rubenstein Fellows Program [CRDF EOL-33066-13/E33066], the <lb/>LifeWatchGreece Research Infrastructure [384676-94/GSRT/ <lb/>NSRF(C&amp;E)], and the Novo Nordisk Foundation Center for Pro-<lb/>tein Research [NNF14CC0001]. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest: none declared. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Bossy,R. et al. (2013) BioNLP shared Task 2013-An Overview of the Bacteria Bio-<lb/>tope Task. ACL 2013, Proceedings of the BioNLP Shared Task 2013 Workshop, <lb/>161-169. <lb/>Buttigieg,P.L. et al. (2013) The environment ontology: contextualising biological and <lb/>biomedical entities. J. Biomed. Semantics, 4, 43. <lb/>Gwinn,N.E. and Rinaldo,C. (2009) The Biodiversity Heritage Library: sharing biodi-<lb/>versity literature with the world. IFLA J., 35, 25-34. <lb/>Hirschman,L. et al. (2008) Habitat-Lite: a GSC case study based on free text terms for <lb/>environmental metadata. OMICS, 12, 129-36. <lb/>Pafilis,E. et al. (2013) The SPECIES and ORGANISMS Resources for Fast and <lb/>Accurate Identification of Taxonomic Names in Text. PLoS One, 8, e65390. <lb/>Parr,C.S. et al. (2014) The Encyclopedia of Life v2: Providing Global Access to <lb/>Knowledge About Life on Earth. Biodivers. Data J., 2, e1079. <lb/>Thessen,A.E. and Parr,C.S. (2014) Knowledge extraction and semantic annotation of <lb/>text from the encyclopedia of life. PLoS One, 9, e89550. <lb/>Yilmaz,P. et al. (2011) Minimum information about a marker gene sequence <lb/>(MIMARKS) and minimum information about any (x) sequence (MIxS) specifica-<lb/>tions. Nat. Biotechnol., 29, 415-20. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figure 1. Top: The &quot;Overview&quot; tab of the EOL taxon pages show a subset <lb/>of the ENVO terms obtained through text mining; an extended list of such <lb/>terms is available in the &quot;Data&quot; tab. Bottom: The latter list provides links <lb/>to the EOL text sections where each term was found (highlighted in bold). </body>


	</text>
</tei>
