<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Minimum Information for Reporting Next Generation Sequence Genotyping <lb/>(MIRING): Guidelines for Reporting HLA and KIR Genotyping via Next Generation <lb/>Sequencing <lb/>Authors: Steven J. Mack(1), Robert P. Milius(2), Benjamin D. Gifford(3), Jürgen <lb/>Sauter(4), Jan Hofmann(4), Kazutoyo Osoegawa (5), James Robinson(6,7), Mathijs <lb/>Groeneweg(8), Gregory S. Turenchalk(9), Alex Adai(9), Cherie Holcomb(10), Erik H. <lb/>Rozemuller(11), Maarten T. Penning(11), Michael L. Heuer (2),Chunlin Wang(12), <lb/>Marc L. Salit(13, 14), Alexander H. Schmidt(4), Carlheinz Müller(15), Tim <lb/>Hague(16), Gottfried Fischer(17), Marcelo Fernandez-Viňa(5), Jill A Hollenbach(18), <lb/>Paul J. Norman(19), Martin Maiers(2). <lb/>1:Children&apos;s Hospital Oakland Research Institute, Oakland, CA, USA; <lb/>2:National Marrow Donor Program, Minneapolis, MN, USA; <lb/>3:One Lambda, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Brown Deer, WI, USA; <lb/>4:DKMS German Bone Marrow Donor Center, Tübingen, Germany; <lb/>5:Department of Pathology, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA; <lb/>6:Anthony Nolan Research Institute, Royal Free Hospital, London, UK; <lb/>7:University College London Cancer Institute, University College London, London, <lb/>UK; <lb/>8: Maastricht University Medical Centre, Maastricht, The Netherlands; <lb/>9: Bioinformatics, Roche Sequencing, Pleasanton, CA, USA; <lb/>10:Roche Molecular Systems, Pleasanton, CA, USA; <lb/>11:GenDX, Utrecht, Netherlands; <lb/>12:Stanford Genome Technology Center, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA; <lb/>13:National Institute of Standards and Technology, Stanford, CA, USA; <lb/>14:Department of Bioengineering, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA; <lb/>15:Zentrales Knochenmarkspender-Register Deutschland, Ulm, Germany; <lb/>16:Omixon, Budapest, Hungary; <lb/>17:Medical University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria; <lb/>18:Department of Neurology, University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA; <lb/>19:Department of Structural Biology, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA. <lb/>Corresponding Author: <lb/>Steven J. Mack <lb/>Email: SJMACK@CHORI.ORG <lb/>Address: Children&apos;s Hospital Oakland Research Institute <lb/>5700 Martin Luther King Jr. Way <lb/>Oakland, CA 94609 <lb/> Short Title: <lb/>MIRING for HLA and KIR NGS <lb/>Key Words: <lb/>NGS, HLA, KIR, MIRING, genotyping, data standards <lb/>Abbreviations: <lb/>BAM -Binary Alignment/Map <lb/>CSB -Consensus Sequence Block <lb/>dbGAP -Genotype and Phenotype Database <lb/>EMBL -European Molecular Biology Laboratory <lb/>ENA -European Nucleotide Archive <lb/>GL -Genotype List <lb/>GRC -Genome Reference Consortium <lb/>GTR -Genetic Testing Registry <lb/>HLA -Human Leukocyte Antigen <lb/>HIEDFS -HLA Information Exchange Data Format Standards <lb/>HIPAA -Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act <lb/>IEC -International Electrotechnical Commission <lb/>IDAWG -Immunogenomic Data Analysis Working Group <lb/>IHIW -International HLA and Immunogenetics Workshop <lb/>IMGT -ImMunoGeneTics <lb/>INGSDC -Immunogenomic Next Generation Sequencing Data Consortium <lb/>INSDC -International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration <lb/>IPD -Immuno Polymorphism Database <lb/>ISO -International Organization for Standardization <lb/>IUBMB -International Union of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology <lb/>IUPAC -International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry <lb/>KIR -Killer-cell Immunoglobulin-like Receptor <lb/>MIBBI -Minimum Information for Biological and Biomedical Investigations <lb/>MIRING -Minimum Information for Reporting Immunogenomic NGS Genotypes <lb/>NCBI -National Center for Biotechnology Information <lb/>NGS -Next Generation Sequencing <lb/>OID -Organization Identifier <lb/>PIPEDA -Personal Information Protection and Electronics Documents Act <lb/>SBT -Sanger sequencing Based Typing <lb/>SFF -Standard Flowgram Format <lb/>SRA -Sequence Read Archive <lb/>SSOP -Sequence-Specific Oligonucleotide Probe <lb/>SSP -Sequence-Specific Priming <lb/>URI -Uniform Resource Identifier <lb/>VCF -Variant Call Format <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The development of next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies for HLA and <lb/>KIR genotyping is rapidly advancing knowledge of genetic variation of these highly <lb/>polymorphic loci. NGS genotyping is poised to replace older methods for clinical use, <lb/>but standard methods for reporting and exchanging these new, high quality <lb/>genotype data are needed. The Immunogenomic NGS Consortium, a broad <lb/>collaboration of histocompatibility and immunogenetics clinicians, researchers, <lb/>instrument manufacturers and software developers, has developed the Minimum <lb/>Information for Reporting Immunogenomic NGS Genotyping (MIRING) reporting <lb/>guidelines. MIRING is a checklist that specifies the content of NGS genotyping results <lb/>as well as a set of messaging guidelines for reporting the results. A MIRING message <lb/>includes five categories of structured information -message annotation, reference <lb/>context, full genotype, consensus sequence and novel polymorphism -and <lb/>references to three categories of accessory information -NGS platform <lb/>documentation, read processing documentation and primary data. These eight <lb/>categories of information ensure the long-term portability and broad application of <lb/>this NGS data for all current histocompatibility and immunogenetics use cases. In <lb/>addition, MIRING can be extended to allow the reporting of genotype data generated <lb/>using pre-NGS technologies. Because genotyping results reported using MIRING are <lb/>easily updated in accordance with reference and nomenclature databases, MIRING <lb/>represents a bold departure from previous methods of reporting HLA and KIR <lb/>genotyping results, which have provided static and less-portable data. More <lb/>information about MIRING can be found online at miring.immunogenomics.org. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Next-generation sequencing (NGS) offers high-throughput generation of phased <lb/>sequences for the highly polymorphic human leucocyte antigen (HLA) and killer-cell <lb/>immunoglobulin-like receptor (KIR) genes, allowing their rapid, high-resolution <lb/>genotyping. In some cases, these methods offer full-gene sequence results[1-3]. In <lb/>general, all NGS methods offer higher resolution and lower ambiguity genotypes <lb/>than standard methods such as &quot;Sanger&quot; sequencing based typing (SBT), and <lb/>sequence-specific oligonucleotide probe (SSOP) or primer (SSP) methods[2-5], and <lb/>do not require the use of secondary genotyping methods to resolve ambiguities. <lb/>Any method for genotyping HLA and KIR using genomic DNA requires at least three <lb/>components: the genotyping instrument, reference sequences, and analysis software. <lb/>The genotyping instrument generates primary sequence data, which is interpreted <lb/>by the analysis software, using the reference sequences to identify the subject&apos;s <lb/>genotype. A wide variety of instruments, reference sequence resources, and data <lb/>analysis programs are available for both NGS and pre-NGS genotyping approaches, <lb/>and are used in different combinations. <lb/>In some cases, the different methods may not generate the same results for a given <lb/>subject. Such discrepancies may derive from the instrumentation, reference <lb/>sequences, software, or a combination of these components. However, as <lb/>Hollenbach et al.[6] have described, there is no standard format for reporting a <lb/>genotyping result or for documenting the components that were applied to generate <lb/>that result. In the absence of such documentation, the source of discrepancies in <lb/>genotyping results is rarely identifiable. In addition, it becomes impossible to <lb/>directly relate the HLA and KIR genotypes of subjects genotyped using different <lb/>methods, as genetic differences between individuals may not be distinguishable <lb/>from methodological differences between genotyping approaches. This lack of <lb/>clarity has important implications for meta-analytical approaches to population or <lb/>disease association studies that seek to combine and compare data across different <lb/>studies. In general, ambiguity regarding the source of genotyping discrepancies <lb/>impedes technical advances and optimization, and frustrates reproducible research. <lb/>Guidelines for reporting and documenting genotyping results are essential for <lb/>evaluating HLA and KIR genotypes generated using different instruments, reference <lb/>sequences or data-analysis programs. The active and ongoing development of NGS <lb/>methods requires the adoption of a single extensible and adaptable standard for <lb/>reporting and documenting NGS genotyping results. <lb/>Here we describe the Minimum Information for Reporting NGS Genotyping <lb/>(MIRING) checklist, a set of Minimum Information for Biological and Biomedical <lb/>Investigations (MIBBI)[7, 8] reporting guidelines developed by a consortium of <lb/>immunogenomic researchers and clinicians, NGS instrument manufacturers and <lb/>software developers, HLA and KIR sequence database developers and <lb/>administrators, bone marrow donor registries and donor centers. <lb/>2. Description of MIRING <lb/>2.1 MIRING Development <lb/>The standard reporting of HLA and KIR genotypes is a long unmet need of the <lb/>histocompatibility and immunogenetics community [6, 9-13]. The specific need for <lb/>NGS genotype reporting guidelines emerged from a survey of Immunogenomic data <lb/>management and analysis practices[14], carried out by the Immunogenomic Data <lb/>Analysis Working Group (IDAWG) as part of the 16 th International HLA and <lb/>Immunogenetics Workshop (IHIW)[15]. The survey uncovered a lack of consistency <lb/>between laboratories and the resulting impact on downstream analytical results. <lb/>The development of MIRING began with the formation of the Immunogenomic Next <lb/>Generation Sequencing Data Consortium (INGSDC) (ngs.immunogenomics.org) by <lb/>the IDAWG and the HLA Information Exchange Data Format Standards (HIEDFS) <lb/>group. The INGSDC met several times between 2012 and 2014, and identified the <lb/>minimum information needed to accurately report NGS genotyping results for the <lb/>HLA and KIR genes for clinical and research applications. Further MIRING <lb/>development took place as part of the BeTheMatch Foundation&apos;s Data Standards <lb/>&apos;Hackathon&apos; for NGS-based typing held in September of 2014 <lb/>(dash.immunogenomics.org). MIRING is currently being evaluated as part of the 17 th <lb/>IHIW (ihiws.org/informatics-of-genomic-data/). <lb/>2.2 MIRING Goals <lb/>To meet the current needs of the histocompatibility and immunogenetics <lb/>community for reporting and exchanging NGS genotype data, the elements of a <lb/>MIRING message were designed with the following goals: <lb/>1. To facilitate downstream analyses and data management for current research and <lb/>clinical use cases for molecular genotyping data in the histocompatibility and <lb/>immunogenetics field. <lb/>2. To permit the re-analysis of NGS HLA or KIR genotyping results in the context of <lb/>past, present and (foreseeable) future molecular nomenclatures and methods of <lb/>describing HLA and KIR allele diversity. <lb/>3. To permit the comparison and evaluation of genotyping performance between <lb/>different NGS platforms and analysis methods. <lb/>4. To enable molecular genotyping results generated using SBT, SSOP and SSP <lb/>genotyping technologies to be incorporated if required. <lb/>5. That the MIRING elements be sufficient to permit the accurate reporting of NGS <lb/>data generated for other highly-polymorphic regions of the human genome. <lb/>2.3. MIRING Elements <lb/>MIRING is a checklist of elements that must be included in a NGS HLA or KIR <lb/>genotyping result, and a set of messaging guidelines for transmitting that NGS HLA <lb/>or KIR genotyping result. Genotyping reports can be generated from a MIRING <lb/>message. The MIRING guidelines include semantic definitions for a MIRING <lb/>message, but are not intended to impose syntactic constraints on the message; they <lb/>are principles that must be met, regardless of the structure of the message. <lb/>MIRING comprises eight primary elements, and their constituents (Table 1). <lb/>Elements 1-5 constitute the MIRING message, suitable for reporting a genotyping <lb/>result. Elements 6-8 constitute the contextual resource for MIRING messages, but <lb/>are not included in MIRING messages. Where possible, MIRING elements are <lb/>consistent with established formats for describing genetic and genomic data (e.g., <lb/>FASTA[16-18], FASTQ[19], Variant Call Format (VCF)[20] and Genotype List (GL) <lb/>String formats[21]), and leverage existing genetic and genomic data-resources (e.g., <lb/>the IMGT/HLA and IPD-KIR Databases[22], the NCBI Genetic Testing Registry <lb/>(GTR)[23] and International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration <lb/>(INSDC)[24]). <lb/>MIRING Element 1: Message Annotation <lb/>Each MIRING message must include a unique identifier that links the message <lb/>contents to external information excluded from the MIRING message. For example, <lb/>individual subject identifiers protected by the U.S. Health Insurance Portability and <lb/>Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPAA)[25], the Canadian Personal Information <lb/>Protection and Electronic Documents Act (PIPEDA)[26], and EU Directive <lb/>95/46/EC[27] are excluded from MIRING messages, and should be reported and <lb/>transmitted outside the scope of the message. MIRING message annotation must <lb/>allow unambiguous identification of the organization that generated the message, as <lb/>well as the unambiguous identification of any MIRING message generated by that <lb/>organization. For example, organizations can be identified unambiguously using an <lb/>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)/International Electrotechnical <lb/>Commission (IEC) standard 6523 organization identifier (OID)[28, 29]. MIRING <lb/>message annotation must also include contact information for the organization that <lb/>generated the message, along with references to the location and availability of <lb/>platform (MIRING element 6) and read processing (MIRING element 7) <lb/>documentation, and the primary data (MIRING element 8) from which the MIRING <lb/>message was generated. <lb/>MIRING Element 2: Reference Context <lb/>Comparison to specific well-characterized and annotated reference sequences is <lb/>crucial for NGS genotyping of HLA and KIR genes. These sequences are stored in a <lb/>variety of databases, including the Genome Reference Consortium (GRC)[30] and <lb/>IMGT/HLA and IPD-KIR Databases[22]. Clear identification both of the database <lb/>versions and of the individual sequences applied in an NGS genotyping must be <lb/>included in each MIRING message. For example, GRCh38.p2 or IMGT/HLA Database <lb/>release 3.18.0 describe the current versions of the GRC human genome and <lb/>IMGT/HLA Databases, respectively; GL000251.2. and HLA00001 are the accession <lb/>numbers for the GRCh38.p2 alternate reference locus number 2 and IMGT/HLA <lb/>Database HLA-A*01:01:01:01 allele, respectively. <lb/>Any reference database or individual reference sequence used to generate a NGS <lb/>genotype should be documented as part of MIRING element 2. To allow the <lb/>assessment of the confidence in the genotyping, this documentation should indicate <lb/>whether or not the database is public, and if a public database is curated. If no <lb/>reference database is used, this should also be indicated. For instances when either <lb/>previously unexplored gene features (e.g., HLA-DRB5 introns) or a genomic region <lb/>that is unrepresented in any genomic alignment (e.g., DR1 or DR8 haplotypes of the <lb/>HLA-DRB region[31]) is being sequenced, the absence of available reference <lb/>sequence at the time of the genotyping should be noted. <lb/>MIRING Element 3: Full Genotype <lb/>Some NGS methods provide phased, full-gene resolution data. However, many NGS <lb/>genotyping approaches do not return such results, and genotyping ambiguity [6] is <lb/>not resolved. In order to evaluate genotyping results across specimens, NGS <lb/>instruments, genotyping and analysis methods, the complete set of alleles and <lb/>genotype combinations that are possible for a given set of sequence data using a <lb/>given reference sequence database must be provided. <lb/>GL String[21] format can be used to describe the genotype at each locus, including <lb/>genotyping ambiguity and known allelic phase between loci. A &quot;best guess,&quot; estimate <lb/>or imputation of an unambiguous genotype should not be included in a MIRING <lb/>message. When available, a reference to an external uniform resource identifier <lb/>(URI) for the GL String should be included as well. <lb/>In addition, genes that were specifically targeted, but yielded no sequence data <lb/>
			should be explicitly identified. Due to structural variation among the HLA[31] and <lb/>KIR loci[32-34], genes that are present in some individuals may be completely <lb/>absent in others. For example, individuals homozygous for HLA-DRB1*01 alleles <lb/>have no HLA-DRB3, HLA-DRB4 or HLA-DRB5 genes[31], and individuals homozygous <lb/>for the KIR A haplotype have no KIR2DS1, KIR2DS3/5 or KIR2DL5A genes[32]. When <lb/>a gene could have been detected by a given NGS instrument, but no sequence for <lb/>that gene is generated for a subject, the locus in question should be identified in the <lb/>MIRING message, with the genotype reported as &quot;Absent&quot; for that locus. <lb/>MIRING Element 4: Consensus Sequence <lb/>Depending on the NGS approach applied, consensus sequence for an individual <lb/>reported allele may be generated as a single, gene-length consensus sequence block <lb/>(CSB), or as shorter phased or unphased CSBs (e.g., corresponding to individual <lb/>exons). These sequences should be written using the single-letter symbols for <lb/>nucleotide bases and incompletely specified bases defined by the International <lb/>Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry (IUPAC) and International Union of <lb/>Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (IUBMB)[35]. Two CSBs would be reported for <lb/>heterozygous individuals where complete phase was known for a given gene. <lb/>Each CSB should be accompanied by MIRING elements 4.2.1-4.2.7, which identify <lb/>the CSB, the reference sequence (as defined in MIRING element 2) to which it has <lb/>been aligned along with its position and identity to that reference sequence, or the <lb/>absence of a reference sequence, any phase and continuity between CSBs, and the <lb/>inferred copy number for each CSB. For diploid loci, the copy number values for <lb/>homologous CSBs should sum to 2; however, due to copy number variation of some <lb/>HLA and KIR genes[31, 32], some individuals are truly haploid for a given gene (copy <lb/>number of 1), while others may have more than two copies of a given gene (e.g., <lb/>copy number of 3 or 4). For example, some individuals have four copies of the <lb/>KIR2DS3 and KIR2DL5 genes[32]. <lb/>A CSB can be described in FASTA format by including a header line that comprises <lb/>MIRING elements 4.2.1-4.2.7, formatted as defined in Table 1 and illustrated in <lb/>Figure 1. Although this header format should be used for FASTA presentation of <lb/>CSBs in a genotyping report, MIRING elements 4.2.1 -4.2.7 can be recorded <lb/>separately and differently within a MIRING message. <lb/>MIRING Element 5: Novel Sequence Polymorphisms <lb/>The HLA and KIR genes are highly polymorphic, and the number of alleles reported <lb/>to public databases is expected to increase dramatically with the use of NGS <lb/>genotyping[36]. In the context of a MIRING message, novel polymorphism includes <lb/>nucleotide sequence variants not yet present in a curated, public reference sequence <lb/>database (e.g., the IMGT/HLA Database). The explicit identification of novel <lb/>polymorphisms is an important element of both clinical and research genotyping, <lb/>and must be documented in a MIRING message. Depending on how a MIRING <lb/>message is generated, a CSB (as defined in MIRING element 4) representing novel <lb/>sequence variants may have been submitted to a non-curated public reference <lb/>sequence database [e.g., GenBank or the European Molecular Biology Laboratory <lb/>(EMBL) European Nucleotide Archive (ENA)] as a novel sequence. <lb/>Novel sequence variants can be described through the use of MIRING elements 5.1-<lb/>5.8, which define the reference sequence, variant position, variant sequence, quality <lb/>score and quality filter status, and (if available) a GenBank or EMBL-ENA accession <lb/>number for the novel sequence (e.g. L28096). This accession number can be <lb/>included in the GL String (MIRING element 4.2.2, e.g. HLA-DRB1*L28096). <lb/>Use of MIRING elements 5.1-5.8 is sufficient to describe novel sequence variants in <lb/>VCF as part of a genotyping report. A GenBank or EMBL-ENA accession number can <lb/>be linked to the variant identifier (MIRING element 5.3) in the VCF meta-data. <lb/>However, actual VCF is not a required component of a MIRING message, and MIRING <lb/>elements 5.1-5.8 can be recorded separately and differently within a MIRING <lb/>message. <lb/>MIRING Element 6: Platform Documentation <lb/>The specifics of each instrument and methodological approach (e.g., whole-genome <lb/>sequencing, target enrichment, targeted amplicon sequencing) applied to generate <lb/>the primary read data (MIRING element 8) upon which the genotyping result is <lb/>based should be documented. This documentation can take the form of a citation to <lb/>a peer-reviewed publication or a reference to a structured documentation of the <lb/>instrument and methodology in a publically accessible resource (e.g., the NCBI&apos;s <lb/>Genetic Testing Registry (GTR)). This documentation is not included in the MIRING <lb/>message, but the reference to the resource must be included in MIRING element 1. <lb/>MIRING Element 7: Read Processing Documentation <lb/>After the primary read data (MIRING element 8) have been generated by the NGS <lb/>instrument, they may be scrutinized for quality and length, modified or subjected to <lb/>various bioinformatics filters before allele calls are made and a genotype result is <lb/>generated. To enable the replication of the genotyping result and the evaluation of <lb/>the bioinformatics process itself, the software and version used for both the <lb/>genotyping and the processing steps applied must be documented. While these read <lb/>processing steps are idiosyncratic to the combination of NGS components that have <lb/>been applied in the genotyping effort, they can be accommodated in the NCBI&apos;s <lb/>Sequence Read Archive (SRA) Analysis XSD XML Schema[37, 38]. Each MIRING <lb/>message should reference a report, based on the Analysis XSD or an equivalent, <lb/>describing each program or script applied in the processing of reads, the order in <lb/>which they were applied, the software versions and the pertinent parameters used. <lb/>Where possible, this report should be associated with the primary read data <lb/>(MIRING element 8), or made available by the MIRING message generator. This <lb/>report should not be included in the MIRING message, but a reference to the <lb/>location of the read processing documentation, or instructions for obtaining access <lb/>to that documentation, should be included in MIRING element 1. <lb/>MIRING Element 8: Primary Data <lb/>The reads generated by the NGS instrument applied for the typing should be made <lb/>available for re-analysis, either via deposition in a public database [e.g., the SRA, <lb/>NCBI&apos;s Genotype and Phenotype database (dbGAP) or an equivalent] or directly <lb/>from the data generators. Primary data should take the form of unmapped reads <lb/>with quality scores (e.g. Sanger FASTQ, SFF[39], or unmapped BAM including <lb/>quality scores). The primary data are not included in the MIRING message, but a <lb/>reference to the location of the primary data, or instructions for obtaining access to <lb/>those data, should be included in MIRING element 1. <lb/>Because each MIRING message is assigned a unique identifier (MIRING element 1), it <lb/>is possible for a MIRING message generator to produce multiple distinct messages <lb/>for a single specimen from one set of primary data. Depending on read processing <lb/>parameters applied and references used, each message may use a different subset of <lb/>reads. Therefore, the MIRING message generator must maintain an archive for a <lb/>given set of primary data, which identifies the reads pertinent to each MIRING <lb/>message. When the primary data are publically available (as defined as part of <lb/>MIRING element 1), the MIRING message generator must make this information <lb/>available as well. <lb/> 3. Strengths and Limitations of MIRING <lb/>
			MIRING represents a bold departure from previous methods of reporting HLA and <lb/>KIR genotyping results. Previously, genotyping results have been maintained as <lb/>static entities constrained by the existing references and nomenclature, with <lb/>insufficient reference context and sequence information provided to foster genotype <lb/>reassessment. By contrast, MIRING elements 3-5 are dynamic in that they can <lb/>change with the reference context (MIRING element 2) -for instance when the <lb/>database is updated. By providing access to the primary read data, and by including <lb/>the consensus sequence in the MIRING message, the genotype and novel <lb/>polymorphism information in a MIRING message can be updated with each <lb/>reference allele sequence database revision. <lb/>The MIRING checklist identifies the minimum information needed to provide <lb/>adequate documentation of an NGS HLA and KIR genotype. This documentation <lb/>should be sufficient to reproduce or permit the reinterpretation of the reported <lb/>genotype from the primary read data, and to allow informed comparisons of <lb/>genotyping results for the same subject generated using different NGS genotyping <lb/>instruments, reference sequences and analytical software. In cases when such <lb/>genotyping results differ, use of MIRING messages to report those genotypes should <lb/>facilitate the rapid identification of the sources of such discrepancies. <lb/>Many pieces of information pertinent to a genotyping experiment are not included <lb/>in MIRING messages. Protected subject identifiers, phenotypic and demographic <lb/>subject details, specimen details (e.g., preparation, quantification), specifics of the <lb/>activity for which the genotyping effort was undertaken, descriptions and selection <lb/>criteria for the loci genotyped, interpretations of the genotyping result (e.g., a &apos;best <lb/>call&apos; for ambiguous genotypes, or identifying a donor as a match to a patient), and <lb/>funding sources for the genotyping are excluded from MIRING messages. Although <lb/>this information can be associated with MIRING messages as part of a larger <lb/>message if required, MIRING&apos;s main purpose is to document those elements of a <lb/>genotyping experiment that foster the archival utility of the genotyping result. <lb/>The MIRING checklist has been developed via community consensus, in order to <lb/>meet the data management and exchange needs of the histocompatibility and <lb/>immunogenetics community. Much of the information included in a MIRING <lb/>message will not be pertinent to all current HLA and KIR genotyping use cases (e.g., <lb/>clinical care, basic research, instrument validation, software development), but all <lb/>such use cases can be met using the same MIRING message. Applications that parse <lb/>MIRING messages and provide information tailored to each use case will make use <lb/>of the same message. Given the rapid exploration of NGS technologies and <lb/>methodologies, use of MIRING messages will allow the transparent evaluation of <lb/>different instruments and genotyping approaches, encouraging improvement and <lb/>standardization of all NGS methods. <lb/>The elements of the MIRING checklist allow MIRING messages to pertain to a single <lb/>locus or multiple loci, but not to multiple subjects. Data for discrete subjects are <lb/>reported in distinct MIRING messages, and multiple messages can be generated for <lb/>each subject. Proper management of MIRING message identifiers then becomes an <lb/>essential part of the MIRING messaging system. A central repository for MIRING <lb/>messages will greatly facilitate and simplify the exchange of genotyping results <lb/>among centers and researchers. <lb/>As illustrated in Figure 2, the elements of a MIRING message can be divided into <lb/>distinct categories. MIRING elements 6-8 are specific to NGS methodologies, but are <lb/>not included in the MIRING message. Therefore, MIRING messaging could be <lb/>extended to include other genotyping methodologies (e.g., SBT, SSOP or SSP) by <lb/>expanding the scope of information reported in elements 6-8, without changing the <lb/>structure or content of MIRING elements 1-5. Only the details of the MIRING <lb/>message would change; for example, CSBs would decrease in length for SSOP-and <lb/>SSP-based MIRING messages, to accommodate the shorter length of the hybridized <lb/>sequences[40], and ambiguity in the full genotypes reported would increase. CSB <lb/>copy number values would change from 1 (haploid) to 2 (diploid) for most Sanger <lb/>sequencing-based MIRING messages (unless sequencing was applied to isolated <lb/>chromosomes, or on the basis of group-specific amplification[41]). <lb/>Although, the MIRING checklist was developed with HLA and KIR genotypes in mind, <lb/>it can be applied to report genotype data for any highly-polymorphic genetic system. <lb/>In addition, MIRING is sufficiently flexible that it can accommodate future <lb/>developments in sequencing technology. As the cost of generating high-quality <lb/>genomic information decreases, the need to report and exchange these data in a <lb/>straightforward and reproducible manner will increase. As genomic data <lb/>accumulate, specific genes, haplotype-blocks and chromosomal regions will be <lb/>revealed as medically relevant, and their polymorphism can be documented and <lb/>reported via a MIRING message. <lb/>4. Conclusions <lb/>MIRING messages foster the portability of HLA and KIR genotype data in a standard <lb/>format, allowing the dynamic re-analysis of these medically important results in the <lb/>context of continual genomic discovery. The data recorded in a MIRING message are <lb/>essential for the systematic traceability of a NGS genotyping result; this traceability <lb/>is critical for reproducible research and the meaningful archiving of modern <lb/>genotyping results. The MIRING checklist is sufficiently broad in scope that <lb/>genotyping results generated using NGS technologies, older genotyping technologies <lb/>and future methods can be accommodated in a MIRING message. Reporting of NGS <lb/>genotype data as MIRING messages promotes transparency across varying <lb/>applications of NGS components, facilitating comparison, and therefore the <lb/>improvement and ongoing development of NGS technology. Finally, the widespread <lb/>application of the MIRING checklist for exchanging NGS genotyping results will <lb/>allow the leveraging of public data resources for meta-analysis, study replication <lb/>and new discovery. More information about MIRING can be found online at <lb/>miring.immunogenomics.org. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) grants <lb/>U01AI067068 (SJM and JAH), awarded by the National Institute of Allergy and <lb/>Infectious Disease (NIAID), and R01GM109030 (SJM and JAH), awarded by the <lb/>National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS), and by Office of Naval <lb/>Research (ONR) grant N00014-08-1-1207 (MM and RPM). The content presented is <lb/>solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the <lb/>official views of the NIH, NIAID, NIGMS, ONR, Department of Defense or United <lb/>States Government. We thank all of the participants in the INGSDC for their input <lb/>and useful discussions regarding the development of MIRING. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>Literature Cited <lb/>1. Erlich, H., HLA DNA typing: past, present, and future. Tissue Antigens, 2012. <lb/>80(1): p. 1-11. <lb/>2. De Santis, D., et al., 16(th) IHIW : review of HLA typing by NGS. Int J <lb/>Immunogenet, 2013. 40(1): p. 72-6. <lb/>3. Ozaki, Y., et al., HLA-DRB1, -DRB3, -DRB4 and -DRB5 genotyping at a super-<lb/>high resolution level by long range PCR and high-throughput sequencing. <lb/>Tissue Antigens, 2014. 83(1): p. 10-6. <lb/>4. Sanchez-Mazas, A. and D. Meyer, The relevance of HLA sequencing in <lb/>population genetics studies. J Immunol Res, 2014. 2014: p. 971818. <lb/>5. Lange, V., et al., Cost-efficient high-throughput HLA typing by MiSeq amplicon <lb/>sequencing. BMC Genomics, 2014. 15: p. 63. <lb/>6. Hollenbach, J.A., et al., A community standard for immunogenomic data <lb/>reporting and analysis: proposal for a STrengthening the REporting of <lb/>Immunogenomic Studies statement. Tissue Antigens, 2011. 78(5): p. 333-44. <lb/>7. Kettner, C., et al., Meeting Report from the Second &quot;Minimum Information for <lb/>Biological and Biomedical Investigations&quot; (MIBBI) workshop. Stand Genomic <lb/>Sci, 2010. 3(3): p. 259-66. <lb/>8. Taylor, C.F., et al., Promoting coherent minimum reporting guidelines for <lb/>biological and biomedical investigations: the MIBBI project. Nat Biotechnol, <lb/>2008. 26(8): p. 889-96. <lb/>9. Mack, S.J., et al., Population samples and genotyping technology. Tissue <lb/>Antigens, 2007. 69 Suppl 1: p. 188-91. <lb/>10. Single, R.M., et al., 14th International HLA and Immunogenetics Workshop: <lb/>report of progress in methodology, data collection, and analyses. Tissue <lb/>Antigens, 2007. 69 Suppl 1: p. 185-7. <lb/>11. Mack, S.J., et al. Proposal for HLA data validation. 2008 June, 2008 [cited 2014 <lb/>October 26]; Available from: <lb/>https://immport.niaid.nih.gov/docs/standards/Proposal_For_HLA_Data_Vali <lb/>dation_Version_2.doc. <lb/>12. Bochtler, W., et al., An update to the HLA Nomenclature Guidelines of the World <lb/>Marrow Donor Association, 2012. Bone Marrow Transplant, 2013. 48(11): p. <lb/>1387-8. <lb/>13. Helmberg, W., et al., Virtual DNA analysis as a platform for interlaboratory <lb/>data exchange of HLA DNA typing results. Tissue Antigens, 1999. 54(4): p. <lb/>379-85. <lb/>14. Hollenbach, J.A., et al., 16(th) IHIW: immunogenomic data-management <lb/>methods. report from the immunogenomic data analysis working group <lb/>(IDAWG). Int J Immunogenet, 2013. 40(1): p. 46-53. <lb/>15. Middleton, D. and S.G.E. Marsh, 16th International HLA and Immunogenetics <lb/>Workshop (IHIW) Introduction. Int J Immunogenet, 2013. 40(1): p. 1. <lb/>16. Lipman, D.J. and W.R. Pearson, Rapid and sensitive protein similarity searches. <lb/>Science, 1985. 227(4693): p. 1435-41. <lb/>17. Pearson, W.R. and D.J. Lipman, Improved tools for biological sequence <lb/>comparison. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, 1988. 85(8): p. 2444-8. <lb/>18. Neuwald, A.F., et al., Extracting protein alignment models from the sequence <lb/>database. Nucleic Acids Research, 1997. 25: p. 1665-1677. <lb/>19. Cock, P.J., et al., The Sanger FASTQ file format for sequences with quality scores, <lb/>and the Solexa/Illumina FASTQ variants. Nucleic Acids Res, 2010. 38(6): p. <lb/>1767-71. <lb/>20. Danecek, P., et al., The variant call format and VCFtools. Bioinformatics, 2011. <lb/>27(15): p. 2156-8. <lb/>21. Milius, R.P., et al., Genotype List String: a grammar for describing HLA and KIR <lb/>genotyping results in a text string. Tissue Antigens, 2013. 82(2): p. 106-12. <lb/>22. Robinson, J., J.A. Halliwell, and S.G.E. Marsh, IMGT/HLA and the Immuno <lb/>Polymorphism Database. Methods Mol Biol, 2014. 1184: p. 109-21. <lb/>23. Rubinstein, W.S., et al., The NIH genetic testing registry: a new, centralized <lb/>database of genetic tests to enable access to comprehensive information and <lb/>improve transparency. Nucleic Acids Res, 2013. 41(Database issue): p. D925-<lb/>35. <lb/>24. Nakamura, Y., G. Cochrane, and I. Karsch-Mizrachi, The International <lb/>Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration. Nucleic Acids Res, 2013. <lb/>41(Database issue): p. D21-4. <lb/>25. An Act To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to improve portability and <lb/>continuity of health insurance coverage in the group and individual markets, to <lb/>combat waste, fraud, and abuse in health insurance and health care delivery, to <lb/>promote the use of medical savings accounts, to improve access to long-term <lb/>care services and coverage, to simplify the administration of health insurance, <lb/>and for other purposes. (Brief title: Health Insurance Portability and <lb/>Accountability Act of 1996). (PL 104-191, 21 Aug. 1996). 1996, <lb/>http://www.constitution.org/uslaw/sal/110_statutes_at_large.pdf: United <lb/>States Statutes at Large 110. p. 1936-2103. <lb/>26. An Act to support and promote electronic commerce by protecting personal <lb/>information that is collected, used or disclosed in certain circumstances, by <lb/>providing for the use of electronic means to communicate or record <lb/>information or transactions and by amending the Canada Evidence Act, the <lb/>Statutory Instruments Act and the Statute Revision Act (Brief title: Personal <lb/>Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act), April 13, 2000, <lb/>http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/PDF/P-8.6.pdf: Statutes of Canada 2000, <lb/>Chapter 5. <lb/>27. Directive 95/46/EC on the protection of individuals with regard to the <lb/>processing of personal data and on the free movement of such data, E.P.a.t. <lb/>Council, Editor October 24, 1995: Official Journal L281, 23.11.1995, p31-50. <lb/>p. 20. <lb/>28. 32, I.I.J.S. Information technology -Structure for the identification of <lb/>organizations and organization parts -Part 1: Identification of organization <lb/>identification schemes. 1998 [cited 2014 October 26]; Available from: <lb/>https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/#iso:std:iso-iec:6523:-1:ed-1:v1:en. <lb/>29. 32, I.I.J.S. Information technology -Structure for the identification of <lb/>organizations and organization parts -Part 2: Registration of organization <lb/>identification schemes. 1998 [cited 2014 October 26]; Available from: <lb/>https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/#iso:std:iso-iec:6523:-2:ed-1:v1:en. <lb/>30. Church, D.M., et al., Modernizing reference genome assemblies. PLoS Biol, <lb/>2011. 9(7): p. e1001091. <lb/>31. Andersson, G., Evolution of the human HLA-DR region. Front Biosci, 1998. <lb/>27(3): p. d739-45. <lb/>32. Pyo, C.W., et al., Different patterns of evolution in the centromeric and <lb/>telomeric regions of group A and B haplotypes of the human killer cell Ig-like <lb/>receptor locus. PLoS One, 2010. 5(12): p. e15115. <lb/>33. Uhrberg, M., et al., Human diversity in killer cell inhibitory receptor genes. <lb/>Immunity, 1997. 7(6): p. 753-63. <lb/>34. Norman, P.J., et al., Co-evolution of human leukocyte antigen (HLA) class I <lb/>ligands with killer-cell immunoglobulin-like receptors (KIR) in a genetically <lb/>diverse population of sub-Saharan Africans. PLoS Genet, 2013. 9(10): p. <lb/>e1003938. <lb/>35. Cornish-Bowden, A., Nomenclature for incompletely specified bases in nucleic <lb/>acid sequences: recommendations 1984. Nucleic Acids Res, 1985. 13(9): p. <lb/>3021-30. <lb/>36. Klitz, W., P. Hedrick, and E.J. Louis, New reservoirs of HLA alleles: pools of rare <lb/>variants enhance immune defense. Trends Genet, 2012. 28(10): p. 480-6. <lb/>37. SRA Handbook [Internet], in Analusis Submission Guide, National Center for <lb/>Biotechnology Information (US), Editor 2010-. Overview. 2009 May 1 <lb/>(Updated 2014 Mar 5). Bethesda (MD). <lb/>38. Kodama, Y., M. Shumway, and R. Leinonen, The Sequence Read Archive: <lb/>explosive growth of sequencing data. Nucleic Acids Res, 2012. 40(Database <lb/>issue): p. D54-6. <lb/>39. Malde, K., Flower: extracting information from pyrosequencing data. <lb/>Bioinformatics, 2011. 27(7): p. 1041-2. <lb/>40. Helmberg, W., Storage and utilization of HLA genomic data--new approaches <lb/>to HLA typing. Rev Immunogenet, 2000. 2(4): p. 468-76. <lb/>41. Witter, K., et al., Group-specific amplification of HLA-DQA1 revealed a number <lb/>of genomic full-length sequences including the novel HLA alleles DQA1*01:10 <lb/>and DQA1*01:11. Tissue Antigens, 2014. 83(1): p. 49-51. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>FIGURE LEGENDS <lb/>Figure 1. FASTA Consensus Sequence Blocks with MIRING Headers <lb/>Two consensus sequence blocks (CSBs) for representing phased exon 2 and exon 3 <lb/>sequences for an HLA-A allele. <lb/>(A) Block 0, (B) Block 1, (C) Guide to interpreting the MIRING headers. <lb/>1: Reference sequence for CSB 0 is IMGT/HLA Database release version 3.18.0 <lb/>A_nuc.fasta HLA00005 HLA-A*02:01:01:01. Reference sequence for CSB 1 is <lb/>IMGT/HLA Database release version 3.18.0 A_nuc.fasta HLA10254 HLA-A*66:01:02. <lb/>Figure 2. MIRING Checklist Categories <lb/>The eight elements of the MIRING checklist are either included in a MIRING message <lb/>or exist as accessory data that are referenced in the MIRING message. MIRING <lb/>message elements 1 and 2 and 6-8 are static in that they pertain to events that <lb/>occurred when the genotyping instrument was applied to generate the primary read <lb/>data. MIRING elements 3-5 are dynamic in that they can change if MIRING element <lb/>2, changes (e.g., a future release of the IPD-KIR database may result in a change to <lb/>the ambiguity level of a genotype). MIRING elements 6-8 are also specific to NGS <lb/>platforms. Valid MIRING messages could be generated on the basis of Sanger <lb/>sequence-based typing (SBT), sequence-specific oligonucleotide probe (SSOP) and <lb/>priming (SSP) methods, requiring changes to the content of MIRING elements 6-8 <lb/>alone. <lb/>Figure 1. FASTA Consensus Blocks with MIRING Headers <lb/>(A) <lb/>&gt;0|0|74|0|1|1|0 <lb/>GCTCTCACTCCATGAGGTATTTCTTCACATCCGTGTCCCGGCCCGGCCGC <lb/>GGGGAGCCCCGCTTCATCGCAGTGGGCTACGTGGACGACACGCAGTTCGT <lb/>GCGGTTCGACAGCGACGCCGCGAGCCAGAGGATGGAGCCGCGGGCGCCGT <lb/>GGATAGAGCAGGAGGGTCCGGAGTATTGGGACGGGGAGACACGGAAAGTG <lb/>AAGGCCCACTCACAGACTCACCGAGTGGACCTGGGGACCCTGCGCGGCTA <lb/>CTACAACCAGAGCGAGGCCG <lb/>(B) <lb/>&gt;1|1|344|0|1|1|0 <lb/>GTTCTCACACCATCCAGAGGATGTATGGCTGCGACGTGGGGCCGGACGGG <lb/>CGCTTCCTCCGCGGGTACCAGCAGGACGCTTACGACGGCAAGGATTACAT <lb/>CGCCCTGAACGAGGACCTGCGCTCTTGGACCGCGGCGGACATGGCGGCTC <lb/>AGATCACCCAGCGCAAGTGGGAGACGGCCCATGAGGCGGAGCAGTGGAGA <lb/>GCCTACCTGGAGGGCAGGTGCGTGGAGTGGCTCCGCAGATACCTGGAGAA <lb/>CGGGAAGGAGACGCTGCAGCGCACGG <lb/>(C) <lb/>Figure 2. MIRING Checklist Categories <lb/>Table 1. Definition of MIRING Elements and Formats <lb/>Number <lb/>Element <lb/>Components <lb/>Messaging Instructions and Notes <lb/>1 <lb/>Message Annotation <lb/>1.1 <lb/>Unique MIRING Message Identifier <lb/>Identifies the MIRING message generator (e.g., an <lb/>International Organization for Standardization <lb/>(ISO)/International Electrotechnical Commission (IEC) <lb/>standard 6523 organization identifier (OID)[28, 29]) <lb/>and the specific MIRING message. <lb/>1.2 <lb/>Message Generator Contact Information <lb/>Email, mailing address, website, phone number, etc. <lb/>1.3 <lb/>Platform Documentation (MIRING element 6) <lb/>Reference <lb/>e.g., citation of a peer-reviewed publication or an <lb/>entry in the National Center for Biotechnology <lb/>Information (NCBI) Genetic Testing Registry (GTR) <lb/>(ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gtr/) <lb/>1.4 <lb/>Read Processing Documentation (MIRING <lb/>element 7) Reference <lb/>A reference to the location of a structured report <lb/>documenting the use of programs/scripts (including <lb/>parameters and order of use) to process the primary <lb/>read data in order to make allele calls. <lb/>1.5 <lb/>Primary Data Availability <lb/>A: Public, and available as defined in MIRING element <lb/>1.6 <lb/>B: Private, and potentially available by contacting the <lb/>message generator as defined in MIRING element 1.2 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>Primary Data (MIRING element 8) Reference <lb/>Provided when permitted. <lb/>e.g., referenced to data in the NCBI Sequence Read <lb/>Archive (SRA) (ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/) <lb/>2 <lb/>Reference Context <lb/>2.1 <lb/>Reference Sequence Database Version for Allele <lb/>Calling <lb/>Identify for each locus included in the message <lb/>2.2 <lb/>Individual Reference Sequences Applied <lb/>Identify the source database and accession number of <lb/>each individual sequence applied in the message. <lb/>2.2.1 <lb/>Reference Sequence Identifier <lb/>A unique identifier ranging from 0 to n-1, where n is <lb/>the number of reference sequences in MIRING <lb/>element 2.2. <lb/>2.3 <lb/>Reference Sequence Source Type <lb/>Specified for MIRING elements 2.1 and 2.2 <lb/>A: Public and curated <lb/>B: Public and uncurated <lb/>C: Not public <lb/>D: No reference <lb/>3 <lb/>Full Genotype <lb/>Defined in MIRING elements 3.1 and 3.2 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>Pertinent Locus/Loci <lb/>Genetic loci as defined in an International Nucleotide <lb/>Sequence Database Collaboration (INSDC) <lb/>resource[24]. All of the loci tested as part of the work <lb/>reported in the MIRING message should be included. <lb/>3.2 <lb/>Formatted Genotype <lb/>If a genotype is detected for a given locus, report that <lb/>genotype in Genotype List (GL) String format[21], or <lb/>an equivalent format. If a locus is identified in MIRING <lb/>element 3.1, but no sequence data are generated for <lb/>that locus, report that genotype as &apos;Absent&apos; in the GL <lb/>String. <lb/>3.3 <lb/>Genotype Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) <lb/>e.g., derived from the GL Service (gl.nmdp.org) <lb/>4 <lb/>Consensus <lb/>Sequence <lb/>The use of MIRING elements 4.1 and 4.2 to describe <lb/>the consensus sequence allows the sequences to be <lb/>reported in FASTA format[16-18]. FASTA format is not <lb/>a required component of a MIRING message, but a <lb/>FASTA formatted component of a MIRING-derived <lb/>genotype report should use the pipe-delimited <lb/>header format described in 4.2. <lb/>4.1 <lb/>Consensus Sequence Block (CSB) <lb/>A contiguous nucleotide sequence organized in the 5&apos; <lb/>to 3&apos; direction and written using IUPAC and IUBMB <lb/>nucleotide base symbols[35]. Multiple sequence <lb/>blocks may be included in a MIRING message. <lb/>4.2 <lb/>Consensus Sequence Descriptor <lb/>For FASTA representations of consensus sequence, <lb/>assign each CSB a pipe-delimited descriptor <lb/>comprised by MIRING elements 4.2.1 -4.2.7. <lb/>4.2.1 <lb/>Consensus Sequence Block Identifier <lb/>Ranges from 0 to n-1, where n is the number of CSBs <lb/>included in the message. CSB identifier numbers must <lb/>increase in the 5&apos; to 3&apos; order of CSBs. <lb/>4.2.2 <lb/>Reference Sequence Identifier <lb/>MIRING Element 2.2.1 pertinent to each CSB. If the <lb/>reference sequence is identified as being of type D <lb/>(no Reference; MIRING element 2.3) the entire CSB is <lb/>considered to be a novel polymorphism, but does not <lb/>need to be independently documented as part of <lb/>MIRING element 5. <lb/>4.2.3 <lb/>Reference Sequence Coordinate <lb/>The position in the reference sequence (MIRING <lb/>element 2.2.1) (indexed from 0) corresponding to the <lb/>1st position of the CSB. <lb/>4.2.4 <lb/>Phase Set <lb/>When phase information is available, identify the <lb/>lowest numbered CSB (using MIRING element 4.2.2) <lb/>sharing phase with a given CSB; assign the lowest <lb/>numbered CSB in a phase set its own CSB identifier. <lb/>If no phase information is available for a given CSB, <lb/>assign that CSB its own CSB identifier <lb/>4.2.5 <lb/>Copy Number <lb/>1 to n, where n is the number of distinct sequences <lb/>represented by the CSB (e.g., haploid = 1, diploid = 2, <lb/>etc.). <lb/>4.2.6 <lb/>Reference Sequence Match <lb/>1: CSB exactly matches the sequence range (MIRING <lb/>element 4.2.3) of the reference sequence (MIRING <lb/>Element 2.2.1). <lb/>0: CSB does not exactly match the sequence range of <lb/>the reference sequence. <lb/>When reference sequence match = 0, a description of <lb/>novel polymorphisms (MIRING element 5) is expected <lb/>unless value for MIRING element 2.3 = D. <lb/>4.2.7 <lb/>Sequence Continuity <lb/>1: no sequence gaps occur between a given CSB and <lb/>the preceding CSB in the same phase set. <lb/>0: there is no phase information for this consensus <lb/>sequence block, or there is a sequence gap between <lb/>this CSB and the preceding CSB. <lb/>5 <lb/>Novel <lb/>Polymorphisms <lb/>Define novel polymorphisms (identified in MIRING <lb/>element 4.2.6) using MIRING elements 5.1 -5.8. <lb/>These elements allow novel polymorphisms to be <lb/>reported using variant call format (VCF)[20] or an <lb/>equivalent. VCF is not a required component of a <lb/>MIRING message, but a VCF component of a MIRING-<lb/>derived genotype report should use the format <lb/>described in elements 5.1-5.8. <lb/>5.1 <lb/>Reference <lb/>MIRING element 2.2.1 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>Position <lb/>The position in the reference sequence (MIRING <lb/>element 2.2.1) (indexed from 1) corresponding to the <lb/>position of the reported variant sequence. <lb/>5.3 <lb/>Variant Identifier <lb/>A composite value comprised by the CSB identifier <lb/>including the variant, and a number ranging from 0 to <lb/>n-1, where n is the number of sequence variants <lb/>reported, separated by a pipe (e.g. 0|12). <lb/>5.4 <lb/>Reference Sequence <lb/>The sequence in the reference (MIRING element <lb/>2.2.1) at the position (MIRING element 5.2). <lb/>5.5 <lb/>Variant Sequence <lb/>The variant sequence identified at the position <lb/>(MIRING element 5.2). This is the equivalent of the <lb/>VCF ALT column[20]. <lb/>5.6 <lb/>Quality Score <lb/>Quality score for the sequence variant reported in <lb/>MIRING element 5.5. This is the equivalent of the VCF <lb/>QUAL column[20]. <lb/>5.7 <lb/>Quality Filter Status <lb/>PASS or FAIL value for MIRING element 5.6 <lb/>5.8 <lb/>INSDC Accession Number <lb/>When possible, provide a GenBank or EMBL-ENA <lb/>accession number for the novel sequence <lb/>6 <lb/>Platform <lb/>Documentation <lb/>A peer-reviewed publication, or the identifier of a <lb/>record deposited in the NCBI GTR or an equivalent <lb/>resource, documenting the specific details of the <lb/>methodology and pertinent versions of the platform <lb/>and instrument-dependent analysis software applied <lb/>to obtain the unmapped reads and quality scores <lb/>(MIRING element 8). <lb/>Relevant platform-dependent information must <lb/>include: instrument version, instrument-dependent <lb/>software version identifier(s), reagent versions and <lb/>lot number, sequence read lengths, expected <lb/>amplicon/insert length, reference sequences applied, <lb/>and sequence feature/region targeted. <lb/>Inclusion of primer target locations is optional. <lb/>7 <lb/>Read Processing <lb/>Documentation <lb/>The specific details of the instrument-independent <lb/>processing of the primary data (MIRING element 8), <lb/>documented using the SRA Analysis XSD XML <lb/>Schema[37] or an equivalent; e.g., instrument-<lb/>independent analysis software version identifier(s), <lb/>analysis software parameters used, details of the <lb/>cutoff values and reference sequences (defined in <lb/>MIRING element 2) used to filter the data for read <lb/>quality and/or mapping quality, along with the final <lb/>read depth obtained and a confidence score of the <lb/>zygosity for the SNPs used to infer the final genotype. <lb/>This information is not included in the MIRING <lb/>message, but must be associated with the primary <lb/>data (MIRING element 8) by the message generator, <lb/>and can be accessed using MIRING element 1. <lb/>8 <lb/>Primary Data <lb/>When permitted, unmapped reads with quality scores <lb/>(e.g., Sanger FASTQ[19] or standard flowgram format <lb/>(SFF)[39] formatted files), as generated by the <lb/>instrument (defined in MIRING element 6), must be <lb/>retained and should be made available as the primary <lb/>NGS data. Adapter sequences may be excluded from <lb/>the primary data. These primary data are not <lb/>included in the MIRING message, but are accessed <lb/>using MIRING element 1. </body>


	</text>
</tei>
