<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Yildizoglu et al. <lb/>1 <lb/>Estimating information flow through a memory system: <lb/>the utility of meta-analytic methods for genetics <lb/>Tugce Yildizoglu 1, 2 , Jan-Marek Weislogel 1, 2 , Farhan Mohammad 1, 2 , Edwin S.-Y. Chan 3, 4 , Pryseley N. <lb/>Assam 3, 4 and Adam Claridge-Chang 1, 2, 5, * <lb/>1. Program in Neuroscience and Behavioral Disorders, Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School, Singapore <lb/>138673 <lb/>2. Institute for Molecular and Cell Biology, Singapore 138673 <lb/>3. Singapore Clinical Research Institute, Singapore 138669 <lb/>4. Centre for Quantitative Medicine, Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School, Singapore 169857 <lb/>5. Department of Physiology, National University of Singapore, Singapore 138673 <lb/>* Corresponding author. Program in Neuroscience and Behavioral Disorders, Duke-NUS Graduate Medical <lb/>School, 61 Biopolis Drive, Singapore 138673. claridge-chang.adam@duke-nus.edu.sg <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>ABSTRACT <lb/>Critics of significance testing claim that this statistical framework promotes discrepancies by using <lb/>arbitrary thresholds (α) to impose reject/accept dichotomies on continuous data, which is not reflective <lb/>of the biological reality of quantitative phenotypes. Here we explore this idea and evaluate an alternative <lb/>approach, demonstrating the potential for meta-analysis and related estimation methods to resolve <lb/>discordance generated by the use of traditional significance tests. We selected a set of behavioral studies <lb/>proposing differing models of the physiological basis of Drosophila olfactory memory and used <lb/>systematic review and meta-analysis approaches to define the true role of lobular specialization within <lb/>the brain. The mainstream view is that each of the three lobes of the Drosophila mushroom body play <lb/>specialized roles in short-term aversive olfactory memory [1-5], but a number of studies have made <lb/>divergent conclusions based on their discordant experimental findings [6-8]. Multivariate meta-<lb/>regression models revealed that short-term memory lobular specialization is not in fact supported by the <lb/>data, and identified the cellular extent of a transgenic driver as the major predictor of its effect on short-<lb/>term memory. Our findings demonstrate that meta-analysis, meta-regression, hierarchical models and <lb/>estimation methods in general can be successfully harnessed to identify knowledge gaps, synthesize <lb/>divergent results, accommodate heterogeneous experimental design and quantify genetic mechanisms. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>LAY SUMMARY <lb/>Significance testing is a statistical method widely used to assess the effect of gene variation, particularly <lb/>in genetic models e.g., mice and flies. While many traits vary continuously, significance testing is <lb/>designed to produce a simple yes/no outcome that is unsuitable for smoothly varying effects. For <lb/>decades, statistical texts have proposed that significance testing has a distorting effect. We examined the <lb/>influence of significance testing in vinegar fly research on short-term olfactory memory, an extensively-<lb/>studied quantitative phenotype in a major model genetic system. Significance tests have been previously <lb/>used to show that a particular brain sub-region -the gamma lobe -is highly specialized for short-term <lb/>memory. We re-analyzed published data using estimation methods that place emphasis on <lb/>quantification: meta-analysis and hierarchical models. We show that the gamma lobe shares memory <lb/>processing roles with two other brain lobes. Using neuronal cell count data, we also show an absence of <lb/>even relative specialization, revealing that memory processing is distributed across neurons in all three <lb/>lobes. We propose that significance testing distorts other areas of genetic analysis in similar ways; our <lb/>data indicate that this can be ameliorated with the adoption of estimation statistics instead. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Contradictory results from research are commonplace. Discordance stems from sampling error and <lb/>methodological differences, both sources of variability that are largely unavoidable. One concern is the <lb/>widespread acceptance of weak significance testing power; a recent report revealed that many <lb/>neuroscience studies have a test power below 40% [9], and the same pattern is likely to be seen across <lb/>other disciplines. However, critics of significance testing itself claim that this statistical framework <lb/>needlessly accentuates differences. The numerous conceptual and practical limitations of significance <lb/>tests [10] include the inherent volatility of p-values, even when there is moderate statistical power [11]. <lb/>Simulation demonstrates that test results from different studies can easily be discordant due to sampling <lb/>error alone, even assuming flawless methodological standardization [11]. Moreover, significance testing <lb/>may exacerbate discordance by using an arbitrary threshold to force a binary outcome (reject/accept) <lb/>from continuous data [12]. To illustrate, a pair of alpha 0.05 tests on two replicated experiments with <lb/>identical effect sizes could produce p-values of 0.049 and 0.051: in the significance testing framework <lb/>these results are starkly discordant, when in reality the biological outcome is all-but the same [12]. The <lb/>arbitrary reject/accept dichotomy might also lead to the false impression that a substantial (but non-<lb/>statistically significant) effect is irrelevant. Conversely, a highly powered sample size could give the <lb/>misleading impression that a minuscule (but statistically significant) effect is of great importance [11]. <lb/>Thus, some consider that fields relying solely on significance testing to draw their conclusions are <lb/>particularly susceptible to discrepancies and may be incapable of resolving apparent irreproducibility. <lb/>In medical research, the complementary methods of systematic review and meta-analysis are <lb/>routinely used to synthesize evidence from multiple studies and to reconcile divergent findings [13]. <lb/>However, such approaches are rarely applied to basic research fields like neuroscience. Taking a <lb/>mainstream sub-field of neuroscience as an example, a PubMed search in late 2014 with the phrase <lb/>&quot;meta-analysis AND (learning OR memory) AND mouse&quot; identified fewer than ten studies in a field of <lb/>&gt;35,000 articles. We therefore decided to ask whether meta-analytic methods could be used to evaluate <lb/>the possible influence of significance testing dichotomization. In seeking a suitable research field we <lb/>required an unresolved hypothesis for which the published studies included adequate sample sizes for <lb/>meaningful analysis, and used a standardized protocol so that the data would not be dominated by <lb/>sampling error (weak statistical power) and methodological heterogeneity. We selected the investigation <lb/>of the neuronal mechanisms of olfactory memory in Drosophila melanogaster. Olfactory memory in <lb/>Drosophila is measured using the classical T-maze olfactory conditioning assay, where groups of flies <lb/>are conditioned by pairing an odor with an electric shock and subsequently assessed for their ability to <lb/>avoid the conditioned odor when given a choice of two different odors presented at the end of the maze <lb/>arms. A particular strength of the T-maze is its use of hundreds or thousands of animals in a single <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>experiment [14], which helps to minimize the sampling error that is often inherent in rodent assays and <lb/>assays using smaller numbers of insects [15,16]. In addition, both the T-maze apparatus and the training <lb/>regime is largely standardized between labs [14]. <lb/>Thirty years of T-maze experiments have elucidated many of the genetic, molecular and neural <lb/>mechanisms of olfactory learning [1-5,17]. A landmark study showed that restoring the adenylyl cyclase <lb/>gene rutabaga (rut) to a brain structure called the mushroom body is sufficient for short-term olfactory <lb/>memory [6], connecting memory formation to cyclic adenosine monophosphate-mediated plasticity <lb/>[18]. Experiments using inhibition of synaptic transmission by temperature-sensitive shibire (shi) [19-<lb/>21] showed that neurotransmission from the mushroom body is essential [20,22]. Targeted expression of <lb/>genes in specific neuronal circuits is possible with the use of transgenic &apos;driver&apos; lines [23]. <lb/>Manipulations based on rut restoration and shi inactivation form the foundation of a large number of <lb/>studies aiming to further define the role of the mushroom body in olfactory learning. The mushroom <lb/>body itself exists as three anatomically distinct lobes, αβ, α′β′, and γ [24]; studies on middle-and long-<lb/>term memory (MTM and LTM) have revealed distinct lobe requirements in the different memory phases <lb/>[21,25-28]. However, the three lobes&apos; specializations remain unclear when it comes to short-term <lb/>memory (STM). While the mainstream view is that rut activity in the γ lobes is sufficient to rescue STM <lb/>[8], some studies have alternately concluded that rut restoration can only partially rescue [7], or is <lb/>merely of importance to STM [6]. There is similar controversy on the role of rut activity in the αβ lobes, <lb/>with rut restoration said to have either no effect [8], or to partially rescue STM for certain odors [7]. <lb/>In the present study, we aimed to evaluate the mainstream view that there is strong lobular <lb/>specialization of STM function in the mushroom body, and to assess the extent to which the varying <lb/>perspectives on this subject resulted from significance testing&apos;s forced dichotomization. Using meta-<lb/>analytic methods, we examined the proposals that restoration of rut function to the γ lobes alone is <lb/>sufficient to rescue wild type STM and that only shi function in the γ lobes is necessary for STM. In <lb/>both cases, meta-analysis of published studies spanning more than a decade found no evidence for <lb/>strong lobular specialization. A subsequent analysis with multi-level meta-regression, an advanced <lb/>estimation technique, revealed that numbers of mushroom body cells explained nearly all transgenic <lb/>effects. These results confirm claims made by statistical texts that systematic review, meta-analysis and <lb/>related estimation methods can be applied to resolve currently conflicting data and give new quantitative <lb/>perspectives. In addition to its role in review, we conclude that routine use of both basic and advanced <lb/>estimation methods would aid the planning, analysis and interpretation of research. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>6 <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Systematic literature review of rutabaga and shibire interventions in short-term aversive olfactory <lb/>memory <lb/>The review yielded ten studies that fulfilled the criteria (Figure 1A). Seven studies contained 81 experiments <lb/>related to rutabaga restoration [6-8,22,29-31], with a total of 748 experimental iterations and 745 control <lb/>iterations (see Table 1). Each iteration is the mean of two half-PI scores, which typically each use 50-100 <lb/>flies, thus representing an estimated total of 150,000-300,000 assayed flies. Table 1 also lists the 5 studies <lb/>that contained 37 experiments related to shibire-mediated inactivation [7,20,21,25,29], 263 experimental <lb/>iterations and 265 control iterations, giving a total of 50,000-100,000 flies. <lb/>Experimental variability <lb/>Despite standardization of aspects of the T-maze, some methodological variation between studies was <lb/>observed, including different control genotypes, varying odor pairs, temperatures, shock voltages, humidity <lb/>and post-training delay times prior to testing (Table 1). These differences, along with other uncontrolled <lb/>variables common to behavioral experiments, would explain the variability seen in data from control <lb/>experiments (Figure 1B). We found considerable heterogeneity in several of the meta-analyses. In the six rut <lb/>analyses, overall heterogeneity was low in three (I 2 &lt; 50%), and high in three (I 2 &gt; 75%); subgroup <lb/>heterogeneity (i.e. variance due to genotype differences) was low in four, and high in two (Figures 6-11). In <lb/>the shi analyses, overall heterogeneity was high in two and moderate in one, while their subgroup <lb/>heterogeneity values were 34%, 64% and 80%. <lb/>Rutabaga function is required for 60% of wild type learning <lb/>We aimed to estimate the learning contribution made by restoring rutabaga function to each of the three <lb/>lobes. The meta-analyses on rutabaga experiments produced 6 meta-analytical estimates of the effects of <lb/>manipulating rut in the mushroom body lobes (Figure 2B). Data pooled from rut 1 and rut 2080 reveal that the <lb/>strong rut hypomorphic alleles reduce learning to 40% of wild type (-60% [95CI -56, -64]) (Figure 2B, 6). <lb/>The forest plot in Figure 2A illustrates the individual effect sizes from 36 experiments and pooled effect <lb/>sizes of the rut alleles (complete forest plot is shown in Figure 6). The data exhibit substantial overall <lb/>heterogeneity (I 2 = 76%) and genotype subgroup heterogeneity (I 2 =88%). This heterogeneity may derive from <lb/>the methodological variation noted above, but in the case of the strong rut alleles we note that the weakest <lb/>effect is seen in the rut 2080 ; UAS-rut subgroup (-45% [95CI -38, -52]), suggesting leaky expression from the <lb/>transgene as one possible source (i.e. expression from the UAS-rut transgene independent of GAL4 <lb/>transcriptional activation). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Rutabaga restoration to the γ lobes rescues 26% of wild type STM <lb/>Some studies have reported that complete rescue requires rut restoration in both αβ and γ lobes [7], while <lb/>others report that restoring rut activity in the γ lobe is sufficient to rescue STM, and that the αβ lobes&apos; rut <lb/>activity has little or no STM role [8]. We used the meta-analytic data to specifically examine the lobular <lb/>specialization hypothesis (Figures 5-10). The overall rutabaga loss-of-function effect was used as a <lb/>reference point to which we compared the lobe restorations, shown in Figure 2B. Restoring rut function to <lb/>each of the lobes revealed partial rescue: α′β′ rescues by 6% [95CI -1.5, 13.5], αβ rescues by 12% [95CI 2, <lb/>22] and γ rescues by 26% [95CI 17, 35]. When rutabaga was restored to both the αβ and the γ lobes, <lb/>memory was rescued by 52% [95CI 50, 55]. Restoring rutabaga to all three lobes gave only 1% additional <lb/>improvement (53% [95CI 47, 59]) compared to the rescue in the αβ + γ lobes, therefore rut in the α′β′ cells <lb/>appears to have a minor effect on STM. Of the enhancer trap drivers included in the γ meta-analysis, 201Y <lb/>contains a minority of αβ cells [32]. A variant analysis that removed 201Y from the γ group and reassigned it <lb/>to the αβ + γ group resulted in weaker effects for both: only 20% [95CI 10, 31] γ rescue, while αβ + γ rescue <lb/>was reduced to 49% [95CI 46, 52]. Taken together, these results are incompatible with the hypothesis that <lb/>restoring rut activity to the γ lobe alone is sufficient to rescue the rut -phenotype. From the lobe perspective, <lb/>we conclude that normal STM requires rut function in both αβ + γ lobes. <lb/>Heating flies above 30°C impairs short-term memory <lb/>Using the temperature-sensitive alleles of shibire to block neurotransmission requires heating flies to over <lb/>30°C, which can lead to additional heat-related effects [28]. Researchers accommodate this possibility with <lb/>separate &apos;heat control&apos; flies that do not express shi ts . We estimated the magnitude of this effect by meta-<lb/>analysis, shown in Figure 3A (complete forest plot in Figure 11). Data pooled from 23 such experiments <lb/>with three types of genotype (wild type, Driver-GAL4/+ and UAS-shi ts /+) revealed that the overall effect of <lb/>heating flies from the permissive temperature (20-26°C) to 30-35°C is a 17% [95CI 12, 22] reduction in <lb/>memory. This decrement can be expected to affect the UAS-shi ts inactivation data from the same studies, so <lb/>we used 83% of wild type memory in Figure 3B as the zero reference point to estimate the specific effects of <lb/>lobe inactivation. <lb/>Neurotransmission from the αβ + γ lobes accounts for 61% of STM <lb/>Drivers that express in both the αβ and γ lobes reduced performance by 61% [95CI 50, 72] relative to heated <lb/>control flies. Inactivating the αβ lobes produced a 25% [95CI 14, 37] reduction in STM. The best estimate <lb/>for γ lobe inactivation is a 6% reduction [95CI 35% reduction, 24% increase] relative to heated controls. <lb/>This γ lobe estimate appears to be negligible, but has very wide confidence intervals and is drawn from only <lb/>a single experiment with three iterations. Surprisingly, the literature review found no &lt;5 min STM data on <lb/>the impact of shibire ts inactivation of either the entire mushroom body (All lobes) or the α′β′ lobes (empty <lb/>columns in Figure 3B); at the time of the review the only studies reporting results for these interventions <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>examined later memory, at 15 min or beyond [28]. The substantial decrement in the αβ lobe inactivation <lb/>experiments (25% reduction) is incompatible with the idea that this lobe plays only a negligible role in STM. <lb/>The paucity of data for γ, α′β′ and All lobes in STM highlights an area that would benefit from future <lb/>experimental attention. <lb/>Cell number accounts for the majority of driver variation <lb/>Observing high heterogeneity (I 2 ) in some of the meta-analyses, we attempted to identify the source of <lb/>variability, and examine the original hypothesis from a different perspective. Electrophysiological evidence <lb/>[33] and anatomical connectivity analysis [34] indicate that the Kenyon cells, the intrinsic neurons of the <lb/>mushroom body, are randomly connected to their olfactory input neurons. The lack of structured <lb/>connectivity suggests that, for some or all odor-related functions, individual Kenyon cells are <lb/>interchangeable; thus raising the possibility that a cell&apos;s lobular identity might be less important than its <lb/>participation in a stochastically nominated odor-responsive ensemble. As three of the seven relevant meta-<lb/>analyses showed driver heterogeneity as accounting for more than half of their variance, we asked whether <lb/>the number of cells captured by a driver could explain some of the unaccounted variance. We extracted cell <lb/>count data from an anatomical study that counted Kenyon cells for many of the drivers [32]. The driver-<lb/>specific meta-analytic STM estimates were subjected to an initial simple linear regression against the <lb/>drivers&apos; available cell counts in both rut restoration and shi ts inactivation. These indicated that cell numbers <lb/>accounted for about 80% of the driver memory variance (rut R 2 = 0.79 [95CI 0.39, 0.94], p=2.5 x 10 -4 ; shi ts <lb/>R 2 = 0.77 [95CI 0.14, 0.96], p=8.4 x 10 -3 ). As simple linear regression is unable to account for the full <lb/>complexity of such hierarchical data, we constructed hierarchical, multivariate, weighted meta-regression <lb/>models accommodating other variables that might explain some of the variance induced by differences in <lb/>experimental design. These models were also able to account for the clustering of experiments within studies <lb/>and for the shared control design in rut experiments, and included weighted estimates for each driver by the <lb/>number of contributing experiments (described fully in Methods). The hierarchical meta-regression model of <lb/>rut showed a strong relationship with driver cell count, generalized-R 2 = 0.84 [95CI 0.79, 0.89] (Figure 4A). <lb/>The meta-regression model of shi data similarly revealed a large effect size for the cell count relationship, <lb/>generalized-R 2 = 0.88 [95CI 0.84, 0.92] (Figure 4B). Compared with simple linear regression, the <lb/>hierarchical models revealed stronger trends with substantially improved precision. These results are <lb/>incompatible with the strong lobular specialization hypothesis of rut and shi function. Rather, drawing on <lb/>data from thousands of T-maze iterations (N = 1008, 1006) while accounting for experimental heterogeneity, <lb/>they constitute compelling evidence that each driver&apos;s extent of neuronal expression can account for the <lb/>majority of that driver&apos;s short-term memory effect. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Kenyon cells in different lobes make equivalent contributions to STM <lb/>Different Kenyon cell drivers&apos; varying impact on learning is primarily a result of how many cells they are <lb/>expressed in: cell count as the overwhelmingly dominant factor therefore excludes highly specialized roles <lb/>for rut and shi in different lobes&apos; Kenyon cells. However, it is possible that minor quantitative differences <lb/>explain the remaining unaccounted for 12-16 % of STM variance in the meta-regression models. Within the <lb/>overall memory-cell count trend in Figure 4A, several drivers&apos; estimates do not fall on the regression line. To <lb/>account for such deviations from the overall cell number trend, we aimed to factor out cell number and focus <lb/>specifically on the potency of each neuron captured by a driver. We built new models in which the learning <lb/>effect size of each driver line was first divided by the number of expressing cells, and weighted hierarchical <lb/>meta-regression models were then used to perform synthesis by lobular category. These models produced <lb/>estimates of a typical Kenyon cell&apos;s effectiveness within each lobe category (Figure 4C &amp; D). The rut <lb/>rescue-per-cell data and the shi loss-per-cell data both show that there are no substantial differences between <lb/>any lobe categories. In summary, when cell numbers are taken into account, the evidence does not support <lb/>the strong lobular specialization hypothesis. Instead, it shows that lobular rut function is non-specialized and <lb/>that STM makes use of all available functioning Kenyon cells. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>DISCUSSION <lb/>Previous studies using significance testing concluded that differences between mushroom body lobes exist <lb/>that reflect functional specializations in the various memory phases (STM, MTM and LTM). These <lb/>conclusions about lobular specialization included the idea that γ lobe rut function is sufficient for STM <lb/>formation. The aim of the present study was to specifically examine the strong lobular specialization STM <lb/>hypothesis. Surprisingly, the synthetic evidence is incompatible with lobular specialization, and supports the <lb/>alternative idea that STM function is generalized across lobes. <lb/>Meta-analysis of strong rut hypomorphic alleles confirmed that they cause a 60% reduction in STM. <lb/>As previously reported in the literature, the other 40% must be mediated by other molecular factors either in <lb/>the Kenyon cells or elsewhere. Restoring rut activity with lobe-targeting drivers revealed that partial rescue <lb/>occurs in both the γ and αβ lobes (mean 26% and 12%), with a partial rescue even in the α′β′ lobes (mean <lb/>6%). To rescue the majority of lost function, rut had to be expressed in both αβ and γ lobes (Figure 2B). <lb/>These data are incompatible with the hypothesis that the lobes&apos; rut activity in the γ lobe is absolutely or <lb/>strongly specialized for STM. With the synthesized evidence failing to support strong lobular specialization <lb/>of rut in STM (Figure 2B), we considered an alternative hypothesis: that cell extent is the main predictor of a <lb/>transgenic driver&apos;s STM impact. Indeed, multivariate meta-regression models incorporating cell count show <lb/>that the dominant factor influencing STM is the number of Kenyon cells targeted by a specific driver line, <lb/>for both rut and shi effects (Figure 4A, B). This result refutes the hypothesis that the mushroom lobes are <lb/>specialized for aversive STM function. Rather, the linear relationships lead us to conclude that the different <lb/>lobes&apos; cells have similar potency for STM with regard to rut and shi-dependent memory processes. <lb/>Despite the paucity of experiments for shi in the γ, α′β′ and All lobes categories, the available data <lb/>were sufficient to allow construction of a precise model of the relationship between driver cell count and <lb/>memory. If STM relied on neurotransmission from a highly inter-dependent Kenyon cell ensemble, we <lb/>would anticipate that shi ts inhibition of small subsets of these cells would have a large effect. Instead, the <lb/>observed linear trend between driver cell count and STM impact (Figure 4B) supports a model in which shi-<lb/>dependent memory function in the αβ and γ cells occurs autonomously in individual cells or small groups of <lb/>cells. It appears that strong qualitative specialization of lobular neurotransmission emerges over the <lb/>subsequent minutes and hours as later memory forms [26,28]. <lb/>This investigation serves as a case study in how meta-analysis and related estimation methods can <lb/>help animal behavior research specifically, and biological analysis in general. Recent commentary has <lb/>focused attention on reproducibility [9,35,36] and replication [37]; both of these issues are in part connected <lb/>to significance testing. An encouraging aspect that was revealed as a part of this study is that the existing <lb/>published data could support precise estimation with hierarchical modeling, suggesting firm data integrity. <lb/>Significance testing remains the dominant statistical methodology in neuroscience and many other life <lb/>sciences [38], despite its tendency to amplify interpretive variation with arbitrary thresholds. For this and <lb/>other reasons, significance testing has been controversial in the behavioral sciences for half a century [39], <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>11 <lb/>but alternatives have yet to be implemented and adopted by the field. Estimation is an alternative data <lb/>analysis framework that places the emphasis on effect sizes and the meta-analytic perspective. Exhortations <lb/>in editorials and textbooks for researchers to favor estimation statistics for data analysis [10,11,40,41] have <lb/>so far had little effect: neuroscience, biology, psychology and economics remain predominantly significance <lb/>testing fields. This study shows how systematic review in conjunction with several meta-analytic techniques <lb/>enable the synthesis of relevant available evidence so as to address inconsistencies in a field and reveal <lb/>unexpected patterns in published data. Estimation as a fundamental statistical framework is also suitable for <lb/>use in primary research; modern statistical texts advise that reporting effect sizes with their confidence <lb/>intervals, along with the use of graphical methods, are the rightful priorities of primary data analysis <lb/>[11,12,40]. Hierarchical models can similarly be applied routinely to analyze primary data with complex <lb/>experimental designs, such as behavior experiments conducted in different labs [42] or by differing protocols <lb/>within a lab [43,44], replacing basic methods such as ANOVA. The methods demonstrated above represent a <lb/>superior statistical framework for all phases of biological research: planning, analysis, interpretation and <lb/>review. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Eligibility criteria and information sources <lb/>All information was sourced with searches of PubMed. To be eligible for consideration for inclusion in the <lb/>systematic review each study was required to meet the following criteria: containing olfactory STM <lb/>experiments on Drosophila melanogaster using the classic T-maze apparatus and a single training cycle [14]; <lb/>reporting of the relevant control and experimental data as a Performance Index (PI); detailing the relevant <lb/>genotypes and the number of experimental iterations (N or sample size). In addition, as STM is thought to <lb/>begin to transition to MTM shortly after training [17], we defined STM as using a post-training delay of 5 <lb/>minutes or less. All studies selected contained transgenic manipulations of the Kenyon cells targeted to one <lb/>or more of the 3 lobes (αβ, α′β′, and γ). For the systematic review of rut function in the Kenyon cells, studies <lb/>included use of a hypomorphic allele of the rut gene, transgenic drivers and UAS-rut expression constructs. <lb/>Experiments using temporally controlled expression of rut were excluded to eliminate the possibility of <lb/>heterogeneity associated with incomplete restoration due to variations in expression longevity or strength. <lb/>For the systematic review of endocytosis-dependent neurotransmission in the Kenyon cells, studies included <lb/>a UAS-shi ts transgene in combination with transgenic drivers and heat treatment. Experiments that shifted <lb/>shi ts flies to different temperatures between training and testing were excluded to eliminate the possibility of <lb/>heterogeneity due to these manipulations; only experiments using the conventional permissive-restrictive <lb/>(cool-warm) comparison were included. Following the lead of the great majority of the STM literature, we <lb/>did not attempt to analyze the acquisition, storage and retrieval phases of STM. <lb/>Database search <lb/>The systematic literature search was conducted as follows and is shown as a diagram in Figure 1A. On the <lb/>11th July 2013, the search phrase ((((Drosophila) AND (learning OR memory)) AND (mushroom OR <lb/>Kenyon)) AND (&quot;2000&quot;[Date -Publication] : &quot;3000&quot;[Date -Publication]) NOT review[Publication Type] <lb/>was used to query PubMed, and the resulting 279 records were downloaded as two .nbib files. These files <lb/>were imported into Papers2 software, and then exported as EndNote .xml. This file was loaded into EndNote <lb/>X4, copied into Excel, and then imported into Apple Numbers with all bibliographic information including <lb/>Title and Abstract stored in one row per record. This was then used to screen the records&apos; titles, abstracts and <lb/>was also used to record the results of the full text screen and the detailed experimental design screen. <lb/>Study selection <lb/>We designed the literature selection process to identify experiments that examined aversive olfactory STM <lb/>(testing five minutes or less after training) in Drosophila as observed in the classic T-maze apparatus. We <lb/>further aimed to focus the analysis on the two kinds of experiments most commonly used to understand the <lb/>role of the three mushroom body lobes and the mushroom body intrinsic neurons (Kenyon cells). The first <lb/>type of experiments was the usage of transgenic rutabaga (rut) to restore adenylyl cyclase function to one or <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>more lobes in rut mutant flies; the second type included experiments targeting transgenic temperature-<lb/>sensitive SHIBIRE (SHI TS ) protein to the lobes to disable dynamin-dependent neurotransmission. The SHI TS <lb/>proteins form part of the dynamin endocytosis complex and poison its function when flies are transferred to <lb/>the restrictive temperature [45]. The exact odor pairs under investigation were explicitly disregarded in this <lb/>analysis; rather, experiments containing the full variety odor pairs were included to enable us to arrive at the <lb/>most general conclusion about mushroom body function. <lb/>Two investigators (TY and JMW) performed the literature review independently and discrepancies <lb/>were resolved collaboratively with a third investigator (ACC). The 279 records yielded from the PubMed <lb/>search were screened in four stages to systematically exclude studies: title review, abstract reading, full text <lb/>scan and a detailed review of experimental design. This process is described in Figure 1A; we used title and <lb/>abstract information to discover a set of Drosophila behavioral studies that were likely to include aversive <lb/>olfactory conditioning in adult fly (n = 65 studies) and then scanned these full text articles to find rutabaga <lb/>restoration or shibire ts experiments in the MB lobes. The final stage in the selection (&quot;Experimental Design&quot; <lb/>in Figure 1) excluded three studies that did not meet the eligibility criteria listed above: one did not use or <lb/>report an isogenic permissive control [46]; a second did not report sample sizes and used a post-training <lb/>interval of 15 minutes [28], i.e. 10 minutes later than the original criterion and 12 minutes later than other <lb/>studies included; a third used pharmacogenetic temporal control of rut restoration [47]. <lb/>Data item extraction <lb/>Two investigators (TY and JMW) extracted data independently using the measuring tool in Adobe Acrobat <lb/>Pro; any discrepancies between the two extractions were resolved collaboratively. The following data were <lb/>collected from each of the included experiments: author, year of publication, figure and panel numbers, <lb/>genotype, mean Performance Index (PI) [48] with corresponding SEMs and the number of experimental <lb/>iterations (N) for each mean PI value for each intervention and its related control group. To calculate STM <lb/>percentages we identified a non-intervention control for each experiment, using the control that was the most <lb/>similar to the experimental animals. For the rut restorations the closest available controls ranged from <lb/>otherwise isogenic rut + siblings to generic wild type (e.g. Canton-S). For the shi ts experiments, including the <lb/>heat-effect experiments, we used the permissive temperature controls. We also extracted experimental <lb/>conditions: time delay between training and testing, odor pair, temperature, voltage, current type and relative <lb/>humidity. One study&apos;s rut restoration data were plotted with superimposed error bars, precluding their <lb/>extraction and inclusion in the review [25]. <lb/>Driver line classification <lb/>Driver lines were classified by lobe expression pattern according to the original studies themselves, except <lb/>for the MB247 line which was thought to drive expression in all lobes [21], but is now characterized as <lb/>primarily driving expression in the αβ and γ lobes [26,32]. In addition, while several studies used 201Y as a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>γ driver, there is more recent evidence that 201Y also drives in a minority of αβ cells [32]; we <lb/>accommodated this by doing primary analysis counting 201Y as γ, but also doing a variation in which it was <lb/>counted as αβ + γ. <lb/>Summary measures <lb/>For each experiment we calculated the intervention&apos;s effect as a percentage change relative to the control PI. <lb/>All the meta-analyses were carried out for the percentage change metric as well as the raw change in PI; the <lb/>results were equivalent. We chose to report data as percentage changes for easier interpretation. The <lb/>histogram in Figure 1B shows that control PI scores vary considerably across experiments; using a <lb/>percentage change re-scales the phenotypes to each experiment&apos;s wild type memory. A percentage not only <lb/>reports how far a phenotype is from wild type memory but also sets a lower bound (0% memory). The <lb/>standard error of each percentage change was calculated using the delta method approximation [49,50]. <lb/>Synthesis of results <lb/>Review Manager software {ReviewManagerRevM:wk} was used to perform nine meta-analyses: six on the <lb/>rutabaga data, three on the shibire data. One random effects model meta-analysis was carried out for each <lb/>mushroom body lobe and any available combinations; within each meta-analysis a subgroup analysis was <lb/>performed for each driver line, except for the rut mutant and heat effect controls analyses, where genotype <lb/>subgroups were used. Table 1 gives full details, Review Manager file is provided as Supporting Dataset 1. <lb/>Complete forest plots of the six rut and four shi meta-analyses are shown in Figures 5-13. No meta-analysis <lb/>was possible for rut restoration to the γ lobes as only one published experiment was found. Subgroup <lb/>analysis of the driver lines was pre-specified. The I 2 statistic was used as a measure of the percentage <lb/>contribution of heterogeneity to the total variance in each meta-analysis, including subgroup heterogeneity <lb/>[51]. For ease of interpretation, summary plots showed learning as a percentage of wild type learning; these <lb/>were calculated by addition of the impairment effect size to 100%. We report p-values from a two-sample t-<lb/>test with unequal group variances in the rut and shi summary plots, and from a t-distribution transformation <lb/>for the cell count regression. Otherwise, percentage effect sizes and their 95% confidence intervals were <lb/>used to interpret all results [11]. All 95% confidence intervals are given in the form: [95CI lower, upper]. <lb/>Meta-regression approach <lb/>Driver cell count data were extracted from a single anatomical study [32]. Initial examination of the <lb/>relationship was done with MATLAB&apos;s simple linear regression function (LinearModel.fit.m) on the mean <lb/>! <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>values. However, this method does not account for many important aspects of the data. To accommodate the <lb/>complex nature of the data, we performed multivariate hierarchical weighted meta-regression analyses of the <lb/>driver effects using generalized linear mixed models (GLMM) in SAS version 9.3 software (SAS Institute, <lb/>Cary, North Carolina; PROC GLIMMIX). For experiment k with appropriate control group j in study i, the <lb/>outcome ijk <lb/>PI (raw change or relative percentage change) was modeled using GLMM taking into account the <lb/>following: <lb/>• The meta-analytic nature of the data: each ijk <lb/>PI was estimated with a certain level of precision in the <lb/>primary study/experiment. <lb/>ijk <lb/>PI were weighted in the GLMM by their corresponding precision or <lb/>inverse variance ( <lb/>) <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>/ <lb/>1 <lb/>ijk <lb/>P <lb/>Var <lb/>with more weight assigned to more precise ijk <lb/>PI , as in the meta-analyses. <lb/>• Relevant experimental design factors ( ) <lb/>ik <lb/>X were corrected for in the GLMM to reduce the variance <lb/>induced by differences in design factors between individual experiments and studies. Univariate and <lb/>multivariate GLMM models were developed by including one and more-than-one design factors as <lb/>independent variables in the GLMM respectively. <lb/>• Clustering: multiple experiments are clustered (nested) within each study and this clustering may <lb/>introduce extra variability or dependence due to laboratory and personnel preferences (practice) in <lb/>conducting experiments. Studies were modeled as clusters ( ) <lb/>i <lb/>b through a random effect with variance <lb/>τ . <lb/>• Shared Controls: rut restorations within experiments were calculated based on a shared control, which <lb/>created dependencies (correlation) between rut restoration effects that shared control groups. <lb/>Therefore residuals ( ) <lb/>ijk <lb/>ε <lb/>based on the same (shared) controls were correlated and residuals based on <lb/>different controls were independent. Due to convergence issues arising from a paucity of data we <lb/>assumed a constant correlation ( ρ ) between residuals based on the same shared controls and modeled <lb/>the residual variance-covariance matrix ( ) <lb/>Σ with a block compound symmetry structure -blocked by <lb/>shared controls, leading to conditionally independent residuals. A simple constant-variance diagonal <lb/>variance-covariance matrix was used for the shi experiments, as matched controls were available, <lb/>leading to independent residuals. <lb/>Coupling all these aspects together yielded the following univariate and multivariate weighted GLMM: <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>( <lb/>and <lb/>, <lb/>0 <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>( <lb/>, <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>( <lb/>where <lb/>), <lb/>, <lb/>0 <lb/>( <lb/>~), , <lb/>0 <lb/>( <lb/>~, <lb/>&apos; <lb/>&apos; <lb/>&apos; <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>≠ <lb/>Σ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>= ∑ <lb/>jk <lb/>i <lb/>ijk <lb/>k <lb/>ij <lb/>ijk <lb/>ijk <lb/>ijk <lb/>ijk <lb/>i <lb/>ijk <lb/>i <lb/>ij <lb/>j <lb/>i <lb/>ij <lb/>ijk <lb/>Corr <lb/>Corr <lb/>Corr <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>b <lb/>b <lb/>X <lb/>PI <lb/>ε <lb/>ε <lb/>ε <lb/>ε <lb/>ρ <lb/>ε <lb/>ε <lb/>ε <lb/>τ <lb/>ε <lb/>β <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Construction of models <lb/>Model construction started with inspection of all the available independent variables based on univariate <lb/>GLMM. From Table 1, these variables included which pair of odors was used (&apos;ODOR PAIR&apos;), experimental <lb/>temperature (&apos;TEMPERATURE), delay time between testing and training (&apos;TIME&apos;), shock voltage <lb/>(&apos;VOLTAGE&apos;), voltage type (&apos;AC/DC&apos;) and relative humidity (&apos;RH&apos;). The data are provided in Supporting <lb/>Dataset 2. It was noted that the ODOR PAIR variable consisted of numerous categories, which would <lb/>dramatically increase the degrees of freedom, so we considered replacing this with an approximation of the <lb/>variable instead. Since benzaldehyde is known to stimulate gustatory receptors as well as olfactory receptors <lb/>(and thus might have a different dependency on mushroom body function from other odorants), we used the <lb/>presence or absence of benzaldehyde (&apos;BENZALDEHYDE&apos;) as a proxy for ODOR PAIR. Of these <lb/>variables, RH, AC/DC and VOLTAGE were both censored in a large proportion of experiments, and (for <lb/>non-censored experiments) had mainly trivial and non-statistical effects on learning; these variables were <lb/>excluded from subsequent models. TIME and BENZALDEHYDE data were available for all experiments. <lb/>For rut experiments, both variables showed substantial and statistical influences on learning (TIME <lb/>generalized-R 2 = 0.26 [95CI 0.15, 0.36]; BENZALDEHYDE generalized-R 2 = 0.28 [95CI 0.17, 0.39]), so <lb/>these were incorporated into further multivariate meta-regression models. For the shi experiments, only <lb/>TIME had a substantial influence on learning outcome (TIME generalized-R 2 = 0.12 [95CI 0.04, 0.21]). <lb/>Multivariate GLMM were used to account for and extract the effect of the relevant independent variables by <lb/>obtaining residuals from the respective multivariate GLMM. We calculated a residual learning effect by <lb/>summarizing the residuals by drivers and rescaling them by subtracting the wild type memory reference <lb/>value (shi = 83%; rut = 40%). The residual learning effect was regressed against cell counts in a linear meta-<lb/>regression that was weighted by sample size (the number of experiments contributing to each driver). The <lb/>learning-per-cell model was built by first dividing each driver&apos;s effect (and standard error) by its cell counts, <lb/>and then fitting a multivariate GLMM with lobe categories as the main independent variable, while adjusting <lb/>for other relevant experimental design factors. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We thank Jonathan Flint, Leslie Griffith, Ajay Mathuru, Joanne Yew, Gero Miesenböck, Scott Waddell, <lb/>Daniel Stettler and members of the Claridge-Chang Lab for their helpful comments on earlier versions. We <lb/>also wish to thank Lucy Robinson of Insight Editing London for assistance in manuscript preparation. TY, <lb/>JMW and ACC were supported by a Biomedical Research Council block grant to the Neuroscience Research <lb/>Partnership and the Institute of Molecular and Cell Biology. ACC received additional support from Duke-<lb/>NUS Graduate Medical School, a Nuffield Department of Medicine Fellowship, a Wellcome Trust block <lb/>grant to the University of Oxford and A*STAR Joint Council Office grant 1131A008. TY was supported in <lb/>part by a Singapore Pre-Graduate Award from the A*STAR Graduate Academy. PNA and ESYC are <lb/>supported by a National Medical Research Council block grant to the Singapore Clinical Research Institute. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">JMW, TY and ACC did the systematic review; JMR and TY performed the data extraction, TY performed <lb/>the meta-analyses; FM performed the linear regression analysis; PNA built the meta-regression models; <lb/>ACC, PNA and ESYC guided the project; ACC wrote the manuscript with contributions from the other <lb/>authors. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. <lb/>Keene AC, Waddell S (2007) Drosophila olfactory memory: single genes to complex neural circuits. <lb/>Nat Rev Neurosci 8: 341-354. doi:10.1038/nrn2098. <lb/>2. <lb/>Busto GU, Cervantes-Sandoval I, Davis RL (2010) Olfactory learning in Drosophila. Physiology <lb/>(Bethesda, Md) 25: 338-346. doi:10.1152/physiol.00026.2010. <lb/>3. <lb/>Kahsai L, Zars T (2011) Learning and memory in Drosophila: behavior, genetics, and neural systems. <lb/>Int Rev Neurobiol 99: 139-167. doi:10.1016/B978-0-12-387003-2.00006-9. <lb/>4. <lb/>Davis RL (2011) Traces of Drosophila memory. Neuron 70: 8-19. doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2011.03.012. <lb/>5. <lb/>Perisse E, Burke C, Huetteroth W, Waddell S (2013) Shocking revelations and saccharin sweetness in <lb/>the study of Drosophila olfactory memory. Curr Biol 23: R752-R763. doi:10.1016/j.cub.2013.07.060. <lb/>6. <lb/>Zars T, Fischer M, Schulz R, Heisenberg M (2000) Localization of a short-term memory in <lb/>Drosophila. Science 288: 672-675. <lb/>7. <lb/>Akalal D-BG, Wilson CF, Zong L, Tanaka NK, Ito K, et al. (2006) Roles for Drosophila mushroom <lb/>body neurons in olfactory learning and memory. Learning &amp; Memory 13: 659-668. <lb/>doi:10.1101/lm.221206. <lb/>8. <lb/>Blum AL, Li W, Cressy M, Dubnau J (2009) Short-and long-term memory in Drosophila require <lb/>cAMP signaling in distinct neuron types. Curr Biol 19: 1341-1350. doi:10.1016/j.cub.2009.07.016. <lb/>9. <lb/>Button KS, Ioannidis JPA, Mokrysz C, Nosek BA, Flint J, et al. (2013) Power failure: why small <lb/>sample size undermines the reliability of neuroscience. Nat Rev Neurosci 14: 365-376. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nrn3475. <lb/>10. <lb/>Cohen J (1994) The earth is round (p &lt; .05). American Psychologist 49: 997-1004. <lb/>11. <lb/>Cumming G (2012) Understanding the New Statistics: Effect Sizes, Confidence Intervals, and Meta-<lb/>Analysis. 1 pp. <lb/>12. <lb/>Ellis PD (2010) The Essential Guide to Effect Sizes: Statistical Power, Meta-Analysis, and the <lb/>Interpretation of Research Results. Cambridge University Press. 1 pp. <lb/>13. <lb/>Borenstein M, Hedges LV, Higgins J, Rothstein HR (2011) Introduction to meta-analysis. John Wiley <lb/>&amp; Sons, Ltd. <lb/>14. <lb/>Tully T, Quinn W (1985) Classical conditioning and retention in normal and mutant Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster. J Comp Physiol [A] 157: 263-277. <lb/>15. <lb/>Heisenberg M, Wolf R (1979) On the fine structure of yaw torque in visual flight orientation of <lb/>Drosophila melanogaster. Journal of Comparative Physiology A 130: 113-130. <lb/>16. <lb/>Claridge-Chang A, Roorda RD, Vrontou E, Sjulson L, Li H, et al. (2009) Writing Memories with <lb/>Light-Addressable Reinforcement Circuitry. Cell 139: 405-415. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2009.08.034. <lb/>17. <lb/>Heisenberg M (2003) Mushroom body memoir: from maps to models. Nat Rev Neurosci 4: 266-275. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nrn1074. <lb/>18. <lb/>Levin LR, Han PL, Hwang PM, Feinstein PG, Davis RL, et al. (1992) The Drosophila learning and <lb/>memory gene rutabaga encodes a Ca2+/Calmodulin-responsive adenylyl cyclase. Cell 68: 479-489. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>19. <lb/>Kitamoto T (2001) Conditional modification of behavior in Drosophila by targeted expression of a <lb/>temperature-sensitive shibire allele in defined neurons. J Neurobiol 47: 81-92. <lb/>20. <lb/>Dubnau J, Grady L, Kitamoto T, Tully T (2001) Disruption of neurotransmission in Drosophila <lb/>mushroom body blocks retrieval but not acquisition of memory. Nature 411: 476-480. <lb/>doi:10.1038/35078077. <lb/>21. <lb/>McGuire SE, Le PT, Davis RL (2001) The role of Drosophila mushroom body signaling in olfactory <lb/>memory. Science 293: 1330-1333. doi:10.1126/science.1062622. <lb/>22. <lb/>McGuire SE, Le PT, Osborn AJ, Matsumoto K, Davis RL (2003) Spatiotemporal rescue of memory <lb/>dysfunction in Drosophila. Science 302: 1765-1768. doi:10.1126/science.1089035. <lb/>23. <lb/>Brand AH, Perrimon N (1993) Targeted gene expression as a means of altering cell fates and <lb/>generating dominant phenotypes. Development 118: 401-415. <lb/>24. <lb/>Crittenden JR, Skoulakis EM, Han KA, Kalderon D, Davis RL (1998) Tripartite mushroom body <lb/>architecture revealed by antigenic markers. Learn Mem 5: 38-51. <lb/>25. <lb/>Schwaerzel M, Heisenberg M, Zars T (2002) Extinction antagonizes olfactory memory at the <lb/>subcellular level. Neuron 35: 951-960. <lb/>26. <lb/>Krashes MJ, Keene AC, Leung B, Armstrong JD, Waddell S (2007) Sequential use of mushroom <lb/>body neuron subsets during drosophila odor memory processing. Neuron 53: 103-115. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2006.11.021. <lb/>27. <lb/>Weislogel J-M, Bengtson CP, Muller MK, Hortzsch JN, Bujard M, et al. (2013) Requirement for <lb/>nuclear calcium signaling in Drosophila long-term memory. Sci Signal 6: ra33. <lb/>doi:10.1126/scisignal.2003598. <lb/>28. <lb/>Cervantes-Sandoval I, Martin-Pena A, Berry JA, Davis RL (2013) System-like consolidation of <lb/>olfactory memories in Drosophila. J Neurosci 33: 9846-9854. doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0451-<lb/>13.2013. <lb/>29. <lb/>Schwaerzel M, Monastirioti M, Scholz H, Friggi-Grelin F, Birman S, et al. (2003) Dopamine and <lb/>octopamine differentiate between aversive and appetitive olfactory memories in Drosophila. J <lb/>Neurosci 23: 10495-10502. <lb/>30. <lb/>Thum AS, Jenett A, Ito K, Heisenberg M, Tanimoto H (2007) Multiple memory traces for olfactory <lb/>reward learning in Drosophila. J Neurosci 27: 11132-11138. doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2712-<lb/>07.2007. <lb/>31. <lb/>Scheunemann L, Jost E, Richlitzki A, Day JP, Sebastian S, et al. (2012) Consolidated and labile odor <lb/>memory are separately encoded within the Drosophila brain. J Neurosci 32: 17163-17171. <lb/>doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3286-12.2012. <lb/>32. <lb/>Aso Y, Grübel K, Busch S, Friedrich AB, Siwanowicz I, et al. (2009) The mushroom body of adult <lb/>Drosophila characterized by GAL4 drivers. J Neurogenet 23: 156-172. <lb/>doi:10.1080/01677060802471718. <lb/>33. <lb/>Murthy M, Fiete I, Laurent G (2008) Testing odor response stereotypy in the Drosophila mushroom <lb/>body. Neuron 59: 1009-1023. doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2008.07.040. <lb/>34. <lb/>Caron SJC, Ruta V, Abbott LF, Axel R (2013) Random convergence of olfactory inputs in the <lb/>Drosophila mushroom body. Nature 497: 113-117. doi:10.1038/nature12063. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>35. <lb/>Reducing our irreproducibility (2013) Reducing our irreproducibility. Nature 496. <lb/>36. <lb/>Ioannidis JPA (2005) Why Most Published Research Findings Are False. PLoS Med 2: e124. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pmed.0020124. <lb/>37. <lb/>Ioannidis JPA (2012) Why science is not necessarily self-correcting. Perspectives on Psychological <lb/>Science 7: 645-654. Available: http://pps.sagepub.com/content/7/6/645.full. <lb/>38. <lb/>Hentschke H, Stüttgen MC (2011) Computation of measures of effect size for neuroscience data sets. <lb/>Eur J Neurosci 34: 1887-1894. doi:10.1111/j.1460-9568.2011.07902.x. <lb/>39. <lb/>Morrison DE, Henkel RE, editors (1970) The Significance Test Controversy. Chicago: Transaction <lb/>Publishers. 1 pp. <lb/>40. <lb/>Altman DG, Machin D, Bryant TN, Gardner MJ, editors (2000) Statistics with confidence: <lb/>confidence intervals and statistical guidelines. 2nd ed. BMJ Books. <lb/>41. <lb/>Ziliak ST, McCloskey DN (2008) The Cult of Statistical Significance: How the Standard Error Costs <lb/>Us Jobs, Justice, and Lives. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press. 1 pp. <lb/>42. <lb/>Crabbe JC, Wahlsten D, Dudek BC (1999) Genetics of mouse behavior: interactions with laboratory <lb/>environment. Science 284: 1670-1672. <lb/>43. <lb/>Sorge RE, Martin LJ, Isbester KA, Sotocinal SG, Rosen S, et al. (2014) Olfactory exposure to males, <lb/>including men, causes stress and related analgesia in rodents. Nat Methods 11: 629-632. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nmeth.2935. <lb/>44. <lb/>Richter SH, Garner JP, Würbel H (2009) Environmental standardization: cure or cause of poor <lb/>reproducibility in animal experiments? Nat Methods 6: 257-261. doi:10.1038/nmeth.1312. <lb/>45. <lb/>Narayanan R, Ramaswami M (2001) Endocytosis in Drosophila: progress, possibilities, <lb/>prognostications. Exp Cell Res 271: 28-35. doi:10.1006/excr.2001.5370. <lb/>46. <lb/>Thum AS, Knapek S, Rister J, Dierichs-Schmitt E, Heisenberg M, et al. (2006) Differential potencies <lb/>of effector genes in adult Drosophila. J Comp Neurol 498: 194-203. doi:10.1002/cne.21022. <lb/>47. <lb/>Mao Z, Roman G, Zong L, Davis RL (2004) Pharmacogenetic rescue in time and space of the <lb/>rutabaga memory impairment by using Gene-Switch. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 101: 198-203. <lb/>doi:10.1073/pnas.0306128101. <lb/>48. <lb/>Quinn W, Harris W, Benzer S (1974) Conditioned behavior in Drosophila melanogaster. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A 71: 708-712. <lb/>49. <lb/>Oehlert GW (1992) A Note on the Delta Method. The American Statistician 46: 27-29. <lb/>50. <lb/>Cramer H (1946) Mathematical Models of Statistics. Princeton NJ: Princeton University Press. <lb/>51. <lb/>Higgins J, Thompson SG, Deeks JJ, Altman DG (2003) Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses. <lb/>BMJ: British Medical Journal 327: 557-560. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE AND TABLE LEGENDS <lb/>Figure 1. Review overview. <lb/>A. Flow chart of systematic literature review procedure. The literature was reviewed in a five stage process, <lb/>starting with a PubMed search that yielded 279 articles, followed by four screens of increasing detail, <lb/>reviewing the article title, abstract full text and experimental design. A total of ten articles, two of which <lb/>included relevant data for both rutabaga and shibirets experiments, were used in the meta-analyses. B. <lb/>Histogram of performance indices for all control experiments identified by the review. <lb/>Figure 2. Meta-analyses of rutabaga mutant lines and targeted transgenic restoration. <lb/>Short-term memory data are expressed as percentages. A. A summary forest plot of learning changes <lb/>observed in 340 experiments with rut mutant lines, with subgroups showing the differences between the <lb/>various rut alleles and strains. Learning is expressed as a percentage change relative to wild type. The red <lb/>diamond on the bottom line indicates that the overall impairment in learning in the rut hypomorphs relative <lb/>to wild type controls is -60% [95CI -56%, -64%]. The complete forest plot is given in Figure 5. B. Summary <lb/>estimates from the rut mutant meta-analysis and five meta-analyses of lobular restoration experiments. <lb/>Learning is displayed as a percentage of wild type learning. The markers indicate the proportion of learning <lb/>relative to wild type expressed as a percentage; error bars are 95% confidence intervals. To the right of the <lb/>markers are numbers for the amount of rescue (R =) relative to the rut hypomorphs. N(E) and N(C) are the <lb/>experimental and control iterations respectively. Except for the α′β′ lobes (p=0.17), all lobe categories <lb/>showed a statistically significant partial rescue of learning (αβ p=0.029, γ p&lt;1 x 10-45, αβ+γ p=1.1 x 10-16, <lb/>all lobes p&lt;1 x 10-45) when compared with rut learning. <lb/>Figure 3. Meta-analyses of shibire ts inhibition of neurotransmission in the mushroom body lobes. <lb/>Learning data are expressed as percentages. A. A summary forest plot of learning changes in heat treatment <lb/>controls, with subgroups showing the differences between 3 types of controls. Learning is expressed as a <lb/>percentage change relative to wild type. The red diamond on the bottom line indicates that the overall <lb/>impairment in learning in flies exposed to elevated temperature is -17% [95CI -12%, -22%]. A complete <lb/>forest plot is shown in Figure 11. B. Summary estimates from the heat exposure controls and three meta-<lb/>analyses of lobular inactivation experiments. Colored markers correspond to diamonds in panel A. Learning <lb/>at the restrictive temperature is shown as a percentage of learning at the permissive temperature; error bars <lb/>are 95% confidence intervals. To the right of the markers are numbers learning impairment (∆* =) relative to <lb/>the synthetic heat effect control. N(R) and N(P) are the restrictive and permissive iterations respectively. The <lb/>αβ lobes (p=0.0001) and the αβ+γ combination (p&lt;1 x 10-45) show statistically significant impairment while <lb/>the γ lobes do not (p=0.7071). The γ lobe bar is in grey as it derives from only a single experiment with few <lb/>replicates. There were no data in the literature on the α′β′ lobes or drivers that encompass all mushroom body <lb/>lobes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4. The extent of drivers&apos; Kenyon cell expression accounts for the majority of short-term <lb/>olfactory memory effects. <lb/>The estimated Kenyon cell counts for drivers were taken from Aso et al. 2009. The memory effect sizes are <lb/>derived from nested, weighted, multivariate meta-regression models that adjusted for confounding variables <lb/>that contributed to heterogeneity. A. Bubble plot of rut restoration; the cell count of driver lines accounts for <lb/>84% of the variance of the learning effects of rut restoration (p &lt; 0.0001). Each bubble&apos;s area indicates that <lb/>estimate&apos;s weight in the regression model; the blue fit line has a slope of 0.023% per cell [95CI 0.016, <lb/>0.030]. The grey line indicates the level of no rescue, i.e. the learning level of rut mutants. B. For shi ts <lb/>inactivation, 88% of the learning variance is attributable to the number of cells encompassed by the driver (p <lb/>&lt; 0.0001). The blue fit line has a slope of -0.034 % per cell [95CI -0.046, -0.0216]; the grey line indicates <lb/>the level of no effect, i.e. the learning expected from the effect of heat alone. C. Learning effect per cell in <lb/>mushroom body sub-regions from rut restoration in different lobes and combinations, adjusted for <lb/>heterogeneity effects. Error bars are confidence intervals; there are no statistical differences between rut lobe <lb/>categories. D. The shi ts learning effect per cell in two lobes and their combination. There are no statistical <lb/>differences between shi ts lobe categories. <lb/>Figure 5. Forest plot of rut mutant learning changes. <lb/>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. This figure is a detailed version of the same <lb/>plot in the main article, but uses proportional reductions instead of percentage changes. The subgroups are <lb/>different driver lines, the red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the percentage change <lb/>relative to control. <lb/>Figure 6. Forest plot of rut restoration in the αβ lobes. <lb/>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the <lb/>red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>Figure 7. Forest plot of rut restoration in the α′β′ lobes. <lb/>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the <lb/>red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>Figure 8. Forest plot of rut restoration in the γ lobes. <lb/>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the <lb/>red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>Figure 9. Forest plot of rut restoration in the αβ and γ lobes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Yildizoglu et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the <lb/>red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>Figure 10. Forest plot of rut restoration in all lobes of the mushroom body. <lb/>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the <lb/>red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>Figure 11. Forest plot of the effect on STM of elevating flies from permissive to restrictive <lb/>temperatures. <lb/>This figure is a detailed version of the same plot in the main article, but uses proportional reductions instead <lb/>of percentage changes. Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are <lb/>different driver lines, the red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change <lb/>relative to control. <lb/>Figure 12. Forest plot of experiments using shi ts to inactivate neurotransmission from the αβ lobes. <lb/>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the <lb/>red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>Figure 13. Forest plot of experiments using shi ts to inactivate neurotransmission from the αβ + γ lobes. <lb/>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the <lb/>red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. <lb/>All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel and genotype/s. We name the most <lb/>precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. Odor pair, range <lb/>experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled <lb/>&apos;0*&apos; were reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts; current type is omitted if not <lb/>reported in the original study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the <lb/>original article. <lb/>Supporting Dataset 1. Meta-analyses of rut and shi STM experiments Review Manager file. <lb/>The file used to calculate and plot the meta-analyses shown in Figures 2, 3, 5-13. <lb/>Supporting Dataset 2. Spreadsheet used for meta-regression of rut and shi STM experiments. <lb/>The Excel file used as input to SAS for model construction. <lb/>PubMed search n=279 articles <lb/>n = 60 articles excluded <lb/>Not in English = 4 <lb/>Not Drosophila = 14 <lb/>Focus on development, physiology or <lb/>anatomy = 35 <lb/>Focus on larva = 7 <lb/>n=152 articles excluded <lb/>Focus on a novel gene = 27 <lb/>Focus on development, physiology or <lb/>anatomy = 29 <lb/>Human disease model = 17 <lb/>Focus on larva = 3 <lb/>Review or modeling paper = 19 <lb/>Not associative aversive olfactory <lb/>learning or memory =57 <lb/>n = 219 articles <lb/>n = 67 articles <lb/>n=10 articles in meta-analysis <lb/>• n=7 used in rutabaga analysis <lb/>• n=5 used in shibire ts analysis <lb/>n=54 articles excluded <lb/>No data on rutabaga or shibire in the MB <lb/>lobes = 47 <lb/>No STM T-maze data = 7 <lb/>Title Screen <lb/>Abstract Screen <lb/>Full Text Screen <lb/>n = 13 articles <lb/>Experimental <lb/>Design <lb/>n=3 articles excluded <lb/>No shi ts permissive control = 1 <lb/>Post-training wait &gt;5 min = 1 <lb/>Not lifelong transgenic rut expression = 1 <lb/>Figure 1. Review overview. A. Flow chart of systematic literature review procedure. The litera-<lb/>ture was reviewed in a five stage process, starting with a PubMed search that yielded 279 <lb/>articles, followed by four screens of increasing detail, reviewing the article title, abstract full text <lb/>and experimental design. A total of ten articles, two of which included relevant data for both <lb/>rutabaga and shibire ts experiments were used in the meta-analyses. B. Histogram of perfor-<lb/>mance indices for all control experiments identified by the review. <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>Performance index <lb/>Number of experiments <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>57 57 <lb/>rut 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>Figure N(E) N(C) <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>1A <lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>2A <lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>rut 2080 <lb/>23 23 <lb/>1C <lb/>1 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>12 12 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>18 18 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>12 12 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>24 24 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>18 18 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>12 12 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>18 18 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>12 12 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3F <lb/>2F <lb/>5A <lb/>5B <lb/>3A <lb/>3D <lb/>5C <lb/>2B <lb/>2A <lb/>2C <lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>17 17 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>18 18 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>12 12 <lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>238 238 <lb/>rut 2080 ; GAL4 <lb/>2A <lb/>1C <lb/>S4A <lb/>2A <lb/>S4A <lb/>S4A <lb/>2D <lb/>2E <lb/>3C <lb/>3E <lb/>3B <lb/>10 10 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>1A <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>14 14 <lb/>rut 1 <lb/>5A <lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>12 12 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>6 16 <lb/>Thum 2007 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>1D <lb/>1 <lb/>1C <lb/>2A <lb/>6A <lb/>4B <lb/>4A <lb/>3A <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>rut 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>5A <lb/>340 340 <lb/>Overall rutabaga Effect <lb/>Article <lb/>A <lb/>-100 <lb/>-50 <lb/>0 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>90 <lb/>N(E)|N(C) <lb/>rutabaga <lb/>340|340 <lb/>αβ <lb/>127|127 <lb/>αʹβʹ <lb/>24|24 <lb/>80 <lb/>70 <lb/>60 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>αβ+γ <lb/>89|87 <lb/>all lobes <lb/>26|27 <lb/>γ <lb/>141|141 <lb/>12 <lb/>6 <lb/>26 <lb/>52 <lb/>53 <lb/>R = 0 <lb/>Percentage of wild type learning <lb/>Learning Impairment of Rutabaga <lb/>(Percentage Change of PI) <lb/>B <lb/>25 <lb/>Impaired Learning <lb/>Figure 2. Meta-analyses of rutabaga mutant lines and targeted transgenic restoration; short-term memory data are <lb/>expressed as percentages. A. A summary forest plot of learning changes observed in 340 experiments with rut mutant <lb/>lines, with subgroups showing the differences between the different rut alleles and strains. Learning is expressed as a <lb/>percentage change relative to wild type. The red diamond on the bottom line indicates the overall impairment in learn-<lb/>ing in the rut hypomorphs relative to wild type controls is -60% [95CI -56%, -64%]. The complete forest plot is given <lb/>in Figure 5. B. Summary estimates from the rut mutant meta-analysis and five meta-analyses of lobular restoration <lb/>experiments. Learning is displayed as a percentage of wild type learning. The markers indicate the proportion of learn-<lb/>ing relative to wild type expressed as a percentage; error bars are 95% confidence intervals. To the right of the markers <lb/>are numbers for the amount of rescue (R =) relative to the rut hypomorphs. N(E) and N(C) are the experimental and <lb/>control iterations respectively. <lb/>e <lb/>e <lb/>es = 7 <lb/>e <lb/>e ies s <lb/>ed s is i <lb/>si ni i n <lb/>i es ue <lb/>e nin <lb/>= <lb/>-45 <lb/>= <lb/>es <lb/>-45 <lb/>) when compared with rut <lb/>learning. <lb/>-50 <lb/>-25 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>Article <lb/>Figure N(R) <lb/>167 <lb/>N(P) <lb/>168 <lb/>Overall Heat Effect <lb/>A <lb/>Learning Response to an Increase in Temperature <lb/>(Percentage Change of Performance Index) <lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2002 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Wild type (+/+) <lb/>12 12 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>9 <lb/>6 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>10 13 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>10 10 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>6 10 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>10 6 <lb/>Driver-GAL4/+ <lb/>74 75 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>10 10 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>10 13 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>10 6 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>9 <lb/>6 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>6 10 <lb/>Dubnau 2001 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2002 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2002 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>81 81 <lb/>UAS-shi ts /+ <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>Percentage of Permissive Control <lb/>80 <lb/>70 <lb/>60 <lb/>90 <lb/>all lobes <lb/>N(R)|N(P) <lb/>+/+ <lb/>12|12 <lb/>GAL4 <lb/>74|75 <lb/>UAS-shi ts <lb/>81|81 <lb/>αβ <lb/>57|57 <lb/>α&apos;β&apos; <lb/>0|0 <lb/>γ <lb/>3|4 <lb/>αβ+γ <lb/>36|36 <lb/>0|0 <lb/>controls <lb/>167|168 <lb/>100 <lb/>Impaired Learning <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>Improved Learning <lb/>∆* = 0 <lb/>-25 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-61 <lb/>4E <lb/>4A <lb/>4F <lb/>4D <lb/>4C <lb/>4B <lb/>3A <lb/>2AB <lb/>3C <lb/>3C <lb/>1E <lb/>2AB <lb/>3C <lb/>4A <lb/>1E <lb/>2AB <lb/>2AB <lb/>2AB <lb/>4C <lb/>4F <lb/>4E <lb/>4B <lb/>4D <lb/>Figure 3. Meta-analyses of shibire ts inhibition of neurotransmission in the mushroom body lobes. Learning data are <lb/>expressed as percentages. A. A summary forest plot of learning changes in heat treatment controls, with subgroups <lb/>showing the differences between 3 types of controls. Learning is expressed as a percentage change relative to wild <lb/>type. The red diamond on the bottom line indicates that the overall impairment in learning in flies exposed to elevated <lb/>temperature is -17% [95CI -12%, -22%]. A complete forest plot in shown in Figure 11. B. Summary estimates from <lb/>the heat exposure controls and three meta-analyses of lobular inactivation experiments. Colored markers correspond <lb/>to diamonds in panel A. Learning at the restrictive temperature is shown as a percentage of learning at the permissive <lb/>temperature; error bars are 95% confidence intervals. To the right of the markers are numbers learning impairment ( <lb/>=) relative to the synthetic heat effect control. N(R) and N(P) are the restrictive and permissive iterations respectively. <lb/>
			e <lb/>es = <lb/>nd e <lb/>in i n <lb/>-45 s <lb/>s is i <lb/>si ni i n i <lb/>i en <lb/>i e e <lb/>es d n <lb/>= 7 7 <lb/>e <lb/>e <lb/>is in e s i de i es <lb/>n <lb/>sin e e e i en i e i e i ns <lb/>e e <lb/>e e n d <lb/>in e i e u e n e <lb/>es d i e s <lb/>en <lb/>ss <lb/>us <lb/>d <lb/>es <lb/>MB247 <lb/>c739 <lb/>17d <lb/>H24 <lb/>NP1131 <lb/>201Y <lb/>OK107 <lb/>c305a <lb/>c772 <lb/>238Y <lb/>c309 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>Learning relative to wild type (%) <lb/>Control <lb/>rut restoration <lb/>R 2 = 0.84 [95CI 0.79, 0.89] <lb/>c739 <lb/>17d <lb/>MB247 <lb/>201Y <lb/>c309 <lb/>c747 <lb/>c772 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>shi inactivation <lb/>R 2 = 0.88 [95CI 0.84, 0.92] <lb/>Control <lb/>Learning relative to wild type (%) <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Driver cell count <lb/>Driver cell count <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>Learning effect per cell (%) <lb/>Learning effect per cell (%) <lb/>αβ <lb/>α′β′ <lb/>γ <lb/>αβ+γ <lb/>All <lb/>αβ <lb/>γ <lb/>αβ+γ <lb/>Figure 4. The extent of drivers&apos; Kenyon cell expression accounts for the majority of short-term olfactory memory effects. The <lb/>estimated Kenyon cell counts for drivers were taken from Aso et al. 2009. The memory effect sizes are derived from nested, <lb/>weighted, multi-variate meta-regression models that adjusted for confounding variables that contributed to heterogeneity. A. <lb/>Bubble plot of rut restoration; the cell count of driver lines accounts for 84% of the variance of the learning effects of rut restoration <lb/>(p &lt; 0.0001). Each bubble&apos;s area indicates that estimate&apos;s weight in the regression model; the blue fit line has a slope of 0.023% <lb/>per cell [95CI 0.016, 0.030]. The grey line indicates the level of no rescue, i.e. the learning level of rut mutants. B. For shi ts inactiva-<lb/>tion, 88% of the learning variance is attributable to the number of cells encompassed by the driver (p &lt; 0.0001). The blue fit line <lb/>has a slope of -0.034 % per cell [95CI -0.046, -0.0216]; the grey line indicates the level of no effect, i.e. the learning expected from <lb/>the effect of heat alone. C. Learning effect per cell in mushroom body sub-regions from rut restoration in different lobes and combi-<lb/>nations, adjusted for heterogeneity effects. Error bars are confidence intervals; there are no statistical differences between rut <lb/>lobe categories. D. The shi ts learning effect per cell in two lobes and their combination. There are no statistical differences <lb/>between shi ts lobe categories. <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>1A <lb/>2A <lb/>1C <lb/>1 <lb/>3F <lb/>2A <lb/>2B <lb/>5C <lb/>3D <lb/>3A <lb/>5B <lb/>5A <lb/>2F <lb/>2C <lb/>3B <lb/>3E <lb/>3C <lb/>2E <lb/>2D <lb/>S4 <lb/>S4 <lb/>S4 <lb/>2A <lb/>2A <lb/>1C <lb/>1A <lb/>5A <lb/>3A <lb/>4A <lb/>4B <lb/>6A <lb/>2A <lb/>1 <lb/>1D <lb/>1C <lb/>5A <lb/>Impaired Learning <lb/>Improved Learning <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Figure 5. Forest plot of rut mutant learning changes. Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. This <lb/>figure is a detailed version of the same plot in the main article, but uses proportional reductions instead of percentage <lb/>changes. The subgroups are different driver lines, the red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the <lb/>percentage change relative to control. <lb/>Fig <lb/>3D <lb/>3F <lb/>3E <lb/>1 <lb/>5A <lb/>3B <lb/>3A <lb/>3C <lb/>4B <lb/>6A <lb/>SFig4 <lb/>1 <lb/>Impaired Learning Improved Learning <lb/>-50 <lb/>-100 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>Figure 6. Forest plot of rut restoration in the <lb/>lobes. Each data set is identified by the source <lb/>article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the red diamond indicates the over-<lb/>all estimated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>4A <lb/>5A <lb/>5A <lb/>Impaired Learning <lb/>Improved Learning <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Figure 7. Forest plot of rut restoration in the <lb/>lobes. Each data set is identified by the source article and <lb/>figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the red diamond indicates the overall estimated value <lb/>range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>2C <lb/>2B <lb/>2A <lb/>1 <lb/>SFig4 <lb/>2D <lb/>2F <lb/>2E <lb/>5A <lb/>4A <lb/>6A <lb/>1 <lb/>Impaired Learning Improved Learning <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>-0.25 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>Figure 8. Forest plot of rut restoration in the lobes. Each data set is identified by the source article <lb/>and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the red diamond indicates the overall esti-<lb/>mated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>1 <lb/>3A <lb/>2A <lb/>5A <lb/>1C <lb/>1D <lb/>2A <lb/>1 <lb/>3A <lb/>6A <lb/>5A <lb/>5C <lb/>5B <lb/>SFig4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>-0.2 -0.1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>Impaired Learning Improved Learning <lb/>Figure 9. Forest plot of rut restoration in the <lb/>nd <lb/>es <lb/>d <lb/>se is iden i ied <lb/>e s u e <lb/>i e nd i u e ne <lb/>e su <lb/>u s e di e en d i e ines e ed di <lb/>nd indi es e e <lb/>es i <lb/>ed <lb/>ue n e <lb/>e proportional <lb/>n e e i e <lb/>n <lb/>3A <lb/>5A <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>-0.2 -0.1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>Impaired Learning Improved Learning <lb/>Figure 10. Forest plot of rut restoration in all lobes of the mushroom body. Each data set is identified <lb/>by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver lines, the red diamond indi-<lb/>cates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>2AB <lb/>3C <lb/>2AB <lb/>2AB <lb/>2AB <lb/>1E <lb/>3A <lb/>2AB <lb/>3C <lb/>3C <lb/>1E <lb/>4F <lb/>4F <lb/>4E <lb/>4B <lb/>4D <lb/>4C <lb/>4A <lb/>4A <lb/>4D <lb/>4E <lb/>4B <lb/>4C <lb/>Impaired Learning Improved Learning <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>-0.25 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>Figure 11. Forest plot of the effect on STM from elevating flies from permissive to restrictive tempera-<lb/>tures. This figure is a detailed version of the same plot in the main article, but uses proportional reduc-<lb/>tions instead of percentage changes. Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. <lb/>The subgroups are different driver lines, the red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range <lb/>for the proportional change relative to control. <lb/>2AB <lb/>4A <lb/>4B <lb/>4C <lb/>4D <lb/>4E <lb/>4F <lb/>Impaired Learning Improved Learning <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Figure 12. Forest plot of experiments using shi ts to inactivate neurotransmission from the <lb/>lobes. <lb/>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver <lb/>lines, the red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative <lb/>to control. <lb/>2AB <lb/>3C <lb/>1E <lb/>3A <lb/>3C <lb/>3A <lb/>Impaired Learning Improved Learning <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Figure 13. Forest plot of experiments using shi ts to inactivate neurotransmission from the <lb/>lobes. <lb/>Each data set is identified by the source article and figure panel. The subgroups are different driver <lb/>lines, the red diamond indicates the overall estimated value range for the proportional change relative <lb/>to control. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>
			Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of included experiments. All experiments are listed and identified by their study, figure panel <lb/>and genotype/s. We name the most precise genotype possible based on the information given in the original article. <lb/>Odor pair, range experimental temperature or temperature range, the nature of the conditioning shock and the relative <lb/>humidity (RH) are also listed. The time delay between training and testing is listed in minutes; those labelled &apos;0*&apos; were <lb/>reported as following training &apos;immediately.&apos; Shock is listed in volts, current type is omitted if not reported in the original <lb/>study. Cells containing a dash indicate that the information was not found in the original article. <lb/>Study <lb/>Fig. Genotype, Experimental <lb/>Genotype, Control <lb/>N(E) N(C) Odor Pair <lb/>Experimental <lb/>Temp. <lb/>°C <lb/>Experimental <lb/>Temp. <lb/>°C <lb/>Shock <lb/>(V) <lb/>Time <lb/>(min) <lb/>RH <lb/>(%) <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 /Y; 17d; UAS-rut <lb/>17d/+ <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 /Y; 189Y; UAS-rut <lb/>189Y/+ <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>S4 rut 2080 ; c739; UAS-rut <lb/>c739/+ <lb/>7 <lb/>7 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3A rut 2080 ; c739; UAS-rut <lb/>c739/+ <lb/>12 12 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3B rut 2080 ; c739; UAS-rut <lb/>c739/+ <lb/>10 10 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3C rut 2080 ; c739; UAS-rut <lb/>c739/+ <lb/>12 12 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3D rut 2080 ; 17d; UAS-rut <lb/>17d/+ <lb/>24 24 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3E rut 2080 ; 17d; UAS-rut <lb/>17d/+ <lb/>12 12 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3F rut 2080 ; 17d; UAS-rut <lb/>17d/+ <lb/>12 12 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>4B rut 2080 /Y; c739; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ;+;UAS-rut <lb/>12 12 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>6A rut 2080 /Y; c739; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ;+;UAS-rut <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 5A rut 1 ; 17d; UAS-rut <lb/>wild type <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>24 24 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>3 <lb/>
			70 <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the α&apos;β&apos; (prime) lobes <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>4A rut 2080 /Y; c305a; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ;+;UAS-rut <lb/>8 <lb/>8 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 5A rut 1 ; c305a; UAS-rut <lb/>wild type <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>24 24 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>3 <lb/>70 <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 5A rut 1 ; c320; UAS-rut <lb/>wild type <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>24 24 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>3 <lb/>70 <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 /Y; +; H24/UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 /Y; 201Y; UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>S4 rut 2080 /Y; +; H24/UAS-rut <lb/>+; H24 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2A rut 2080 /Y; +; H24/UAS-rut <lb/>+; H24 <lb/>18 18 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2B rut 2080 /Y; +; H24/UAS-rut <lb/>+; H24 <lb/>18 18 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2C rut 2080 /Y; +; H24/UAS-rut <lb/>+; H24 <lb/>12 12 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2D rut 2080 ; NP1131; UAS-rut <lb/>+; NP1131 <lb/>17 17 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2E rut 2080 ; NP1131; UAS-rut <lb/>+; NP1131 <lb/>17 17 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2F rut 2080 ; NP1131; UAS-rut <lb/>+; NP1131 <lb/>18 18 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>4A rut 2080 /Y; 201Y; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>8 <lb/>8 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>6A rut 2080 /Y; 201Y; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 5A rut 1 ; NP1131; UAS-rut <lb/>wild type <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>24 24 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>3 <lb/>70 <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in all lobes <lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 /Y; 30Y/UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 /Y; 238Y; UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>3A rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut; OK107 <lb/>+/rut 2080 ;+;UAS-rut <lb/>7 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 5A rut 1 ; +; UAS-rut; OK107 <lb/>wild type <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>24 24 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>3 <lb/>70 <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>rutabaga rescue in the αβγ lobes <lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 /Y; +; MB247/UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 /Y; c772; UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>2A rut 2080 ; +; MB247/UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>5 <lb/>5 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>2A rut 2080 ; c772; UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>5 <lb/>5 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>S4 rut 2080 ; c739; H24/UAS-rut <lb/>+; c739; H24 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>1C rut 2080 ; UAS-rut; MB247 <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>26 26 <lb/>130 <lb/>3 <lb/>80 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>5A rut 2080 ; c739; H24/UAS-rut <lb/>+; c739; H24 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>5B rut 2080 ; c739; H24/UAS-rut <lb/>+; c739; H24 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>5C rut 2080 ; c739; H24/UAS-rut <lb/>+; c739; H24 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Thum 2007 <lb/>1D rut 2080 ; +; MB247/UAS-rut <lb/>MB247/+ <lb/>8 <lb/>8 MCH-OCT <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>0* <lb/>-<lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>3A rut 2080 /Y; +; MB247/UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>7 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>3A rut 2080 /Y; c309; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>7 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>6A rut 2080 /Y; c739/201Y; UAS-rut +/rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 5A rut 1 ; MB247/UAS-rut <lb/>wild type <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>24 24 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>3 <lb/>70 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 <lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>2A rut 2080 <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>5 <lb/>5 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>1C rut 2080 <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>26 26 <lb/>130 <lb/>3 <lb/> 80 <lb/> Blum 2009 <lb/>1A rut 2080 <lb/>rut 2080 / + <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>rutabaga 2080 with Driver/s <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3C rut 2080 ; c739 <lb/>c739/+ <lb/>12 12 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2C rut 2080 ; H24 <lb/>+; H24 <lb/>18 18 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3F rut 2080 ; 17d <lb/>17d/+ <lb/>12 12 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>5C rut 2080 ; c739; H24 <lb/>+; c739; H24 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2A rut 2080 ; H24 <lb/>+; H24 <lb/>12 12 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2E rut 2080 ; NP1131 <lb/>+; NP1131 <lb/>18 18 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3A rut 2080 ; c739 <lb/>c739/+ <lb/>12 12 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>5A rut 2080 ; c739; H24 <lb/>+; c739; H24 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3B rut 2080 ; c739 <lb/>c739/+ <lb/>10 10 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2D rut 2080 ; NP1131 <lb/>+; NP1131 <lb/>17 17 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>3E rut 2080 ; 17d <lb/>17d/+ <lb/>12 12 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/> Akalal 2006 <lb/> 3D rut 2080 ; 17d <lb/>17d/+ <lb/>24 24 MCH-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2F rut 2080 ; NP1131 <lb/>+; NP1131 <lb/>18 18 OCT-BEN <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>5B rut 2080 ; c739; H24 <lb/>+; c739; H24 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>2B rut 2080 ; H24 <lb/>+; H24 <lb/>18 18 MCH-OCT <lb/>21-25 21-25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>2A rut 2080 ; c772 <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>5 <lb/>5 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>2A rut 2080 ; MB247 <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>5 <lb/>5 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>S4 rut 2080 ; c379 <lb/>c739/+ <lb/>7 <lb/>7 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>S4 rut 2080 ; H24 <lb/>+; H24 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>S4 rut 2080 ; c379; H24 <lb/>+; c739; H24 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>1C rut 2080 ; MB247 <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>26 26 <lb/>130 <lb/>3 <lb/>80 <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 2080 ; UAS-rut <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>3A rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>4A rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>8 <lb/>8 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>4B rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>12 12 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>6A rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>+/rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>McGuire 2003 <lb/>2A rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>5 <lb/>5 OCT-BEN <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>1C rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>26 26 <lb/>130 <lb/>3 <lb/>80 <lb/>Thum 2007 <lb/>1D ; <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>25 25 <lb/>90 DC <lb/>0* <lb/>-<lb/>Zars 2000 <lb/>1 <lb/>rut 2080 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>8 MCH-BEN <lb/>120 <lb/>1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga <lb/>rutabaga 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>rutabaga 1 ; UAS-rut <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 5A rut 1 ; +; UAS-rut <lb/>wild type <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>24 24 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>3 <lb/>70 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>rutabaga 1 <lb/>Blum 2009 <lb/>1A rut 1 <lb/>rut 1 /+ <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>22 22 <lb/>60 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>Scheunemann 2012 5A rut 1 <lb/>wild type <lb/>8 <lb/>
			8 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>24 24 <lb/>120 AC <lb/>3 <lb/>70 <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβ (alphabeta) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts the αβ <lb/>UAS-shibire ts of the αβ (alphabeta) <lb/>ts of the αβ lobes <lb/>Rest. Perm. <lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>2AB <lb/>c739; UAS-shi <lb/>c739; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4A <lb/>ts1 <lb/>c739; UAS-shi <lb/>MCH-BEN 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal <lb/>4B <lb/>c739; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>c739; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>10 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4C <lb/>c739; <lb/>c739; ts1 <lb/>9 OCT-BEN 32-35 21-25 90DC <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal <lb/>4D <lb/>17d; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>17d; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>6 <lb/>10 MCH-BEN 32-35 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4E <lb/>17d; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>17d; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>10 10 MCH-OCT 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4F <lb/>17d; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>17d; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>13 10 OCT-BEN 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the αβγ lobes <lb/>Dubnau 2001 <lb/>3A <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 /c309 <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 /c309 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>-<lb/>0* <lb/>-<lb/>Dubnau 2001 <lb/>3A <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 /c747 <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 /c747 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>-<lb/>0* <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>2AB <lb/>MB247; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>MB247; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Schwaerzel 2002 <lb/>3C <lb/>MB247/UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>MB247/UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>34 <lb/>26 <lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>85 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2002 <lb/>3C <lb/>c772/UAS-shi ts2 <lb/>c772/UAS-shi ts2 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>34 <lb/>26 <lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>85 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>1E <lb/>MB247/UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>MB247/UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>34 <lb/>26 <lb/>130 <lb/>3 <lb/>80 <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>UAS-shibire ts inactivation of the γ (gamma) lobes <lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>2AB <lb/>201Y; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>201Y; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 OCT-BEN <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>Wild type heat effect controls <lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>2AB <lb/>wCS10 wCS10 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Schwaerzel 2002 <lb/>3C <lb/>Canton-S Canton-S <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>34 <lb/>26 <lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>85 <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Driver heat effect controls <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4A <lb/>17d/+ 17d/+ <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4D <lb/>17d/+ 17d/+ <lb/>10 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4B <lb/>c739/+ c739/+ <lb/>6 <lb/>10 OCT-BEN 32-35 21-25 90DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4E <lb/>17d/+ 17d/+ <lb/>10 10 MCH-BEN 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4F <lb/>c739/+ c739/+ <lb/>10 13 MCH-OCT 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4C <lb/>c739/+ c739/+ <lb/>9 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>2AB <lb/>201Y 201Y <lb/>5 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>2AB <lb/>c739 c739 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>2AB <lb/>247 247 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>1E <lb/>247/+ 247/+ <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>34 <lb/>26 <lb/>130 <lb/>3 <lb/>80 <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>UAS-shi ts heat effect controls <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4E <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>10 10 MCH-BEN 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4A <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4F <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>10 13 OCT-BEN 32-35 21-25 90DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4D <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>10 <lb/>6 MCH-BEN 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4C <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>9 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Akalal 2006 <lb/>4B <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>w; UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>6 <lb/>10 OCT-BEN 32-35 21-25 90 DC <lb/>3 <lb/>60-68 <lb/>Dubnau 2001 <lb/>3A <lb/>shi ts1 /+ <lb/>shi ts1 /+ <lb/>6 <lb/>6 MCH-OCT <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>-<lb/>0* <lb/>-<lb/>McGuire 2001 <lb/>2AB <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>90 <lb/>3 <lb/>-<lb/>Schwaerzel 2002 <lb/>3C <lb/>UAS-shi ts2 /+ <lb/>UAS-shi ts2 /+ <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>34 <lb/>26 <lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>85 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2002 <lb/>3C <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 /+ <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 /+ <lb/>6 <lb/>6 OCT-BEN <lb/>34 <lb/>26 <lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>85 <lb/>Schwaerzel 2003 <lb/>1E <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 /+ <lb/>UAS-shi ts1 /+ <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>EA-IA <lb/>34 <lb/>26 <lb/>130 <lb/>3 <lb/>80 </body>


	</text>
</tei>
