<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Rodent anxiety meta-analyses page 1 <lb/>Major anxiety-related interventions in rodent defense behaviors: <lb/>systematic review and meta-analyses <lb/> Rodent anxiety meta-analyses page 2 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Assays measuring defense behavior assays in rodents, including the elevated plus maze, <lb/>open field and light-dark box assays, have been widely used in preclinical models of <lb/>anxiety to study the ability of therapeutic interventions to modulate the anxiety-like state. <lb/>However, many important proposed anxiety-modulating factors, including genes, drugs and <lb/>stressors have had paradoxical effects in different rodent studies. We performed a <lb/>systematic review and meta-analysis of the literature on the effect of aimed to evaluate <lb/>whether some supposed anxiety-targeted interventions actually had only trivial effects on <lb/>rodent defense behaviors. Using PubMed search phrases to identify articles, a systematic <lb/>review was conducted on a panel of anxiety-linked factors: 5-HT1A receptor, SERT, pain, <lb/>restraint, social isolation, corticotropin-releasing hormone and Crhr1. Articles were included <lb/>if they contained rodent defense behavior data for one of the anxiety interventions. <lb/>Systematic meta-analyses were conducted for interventions with fifteen or fewer studies; <lb/>randomly sampled meta-analyses of fifteen studies were conducted for interventions for <lb/>which more than fifteen studies were available. Synthesis of the data was performed using <lb/>random effects models of Hedges&apos; g. Publication bias was found to affect several <lb/>literatures. Surprisingly, three of the ten purported anxiety-related interventions had small <lb/>and/or non-statistically significant effects. The literature supports seven of the ten factors <lb/>as being strongly connected to anxiety-related behavior. <lb/></front>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>The anxiety disorders are among the costliest classes of mental disorders, both in morbidity <lb/>and economic cost (DiLuca and Olesen, 2014; Baldwin et al., 2014). Development of <lb/>anxiety-reducing (anxiolytic) drugs has been a major focus of the pharmaceutical industry <lb/>and academic neuropsychiatric research, though no new drug types have been adopted <lb/>since the introduction of selective serotonin uptake inhibitors (SSRIs) and other <lb/>antidepressants for the treatment of anxiety disorders (Tone, 2009; Griebel and Holmes, <lb/>2013). Anxiety research relies on similarities between human emotional behavior and <lb/>behaviors in animals (Darwin, 1998), specifically rat and mouse (Prut and Belzung, 2003). <lb/>While there are many rodent behavioral paradigms that aim to model anxiety-like behaviors, <lb/>three related assays that specifically aim to measure anxiety-related defense behavior <lb/>(ARDEB) have been established, also referred to as the approach-avoidance conflict tests <lb/>(Griebel and Holmes, 2013). These assays are the elevated plus maze (EPM), the light-dark <lb/>box (LD) and the open field (OF), the first, second and fifth most widely used assays in <lb/>animal anxiety research, respectively (Griebel and Holmes, 2013). All three arena types used <lb/>in these assays contain a sheltered domain (e.g., the closed arms in EPM) and an exposed <lb/>region. It is thought that avoidance of the exposed portions of the chamber reports on <lb/>anxiety-like states in the rodent brain. These assays are generally accepted as preclinical <lb/>assays of anxiety disorders, by reference to classic studies that validated them with a panel <lb/>of drugs known to have anxiety-modulating effects in humans (Crawley and Goodwin, 1980; <lb/>Pellow et al., 1985; Simon et al., 1994). <lb/>Rodent research has been implicated in the largely frustrated efforts to develop new <lb/>types of anxiolytics (Griebel and Holmes, 2013). The literature regarding defense behavior is <lb/>contradictory about the size and even the direction of many interventions that are proposed <lb/>to be anxiolytic or anxiogenic (together &apos;anxiotropic&apos;) (Prut and Belzung, 2003; Griebel and <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note>

            <page>page 4 <lb/></page>

            <body>Holmes, 2013). This is true even for some anxiety-related genes with major clinical <lb/>relevance, such as Htt, the target of SSRIs. As with the assessment of clinical anxiety <lb/>interventions (Baldwin et al., 2014), a solid evidence base of the effect of &apos;mainstream&apos; <lb/>anxiety interventions in the rodent ARDEB assays is necessary to guide decisions about <lb/>further basic research and therapeutic development (Vesterinen et al., 2014). In light of the <lb/>widespread discordance, we proposed the hypothesis that some of the purported anxiety-<lb/>related factors had no substantial effect on ARDEB. We will refer to this as the &quot;no-ARDEB-<lb/>effect hypothesis.&quot; Secondary goals of this survey were to examine patterns in ARDEB <lb/>evidence: gaps in the literature, heterogeneity and publication bias <lb/>To estimate the effect sizes of anxiotropic interventions, we first used an ad hoc <lb/>literature search to identify ten claimed anxiety interventions and followed this with <lb/>systematic reviews on all. From the articles identified, systematic or randomly sampled <lb/>meta-analyses were performed, depending on the numbers of eligible articles available. The <lb/>majority of purported anxiety-related interventions showed substantial effects on ARDEB. <lb/>However, three supposed anxiotropic interventions showed only small and/or non-<lb/>statistically significant effects on ARDEB. Our study also indicated that the Htt literature <lb/>appears to be affected by publication bias. <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 5 <lb/></page>

            <body>METHODS <lb/>Literature review <lb/>Genes, drugs and environmental interventions that had been proposed to be involved in <lb/>anxiety were identified by a literature search of review articles on the field of anxiety. Based <lb/>on the history of anxiety research (Tone, 2009; Griebel and Holmes, 2013), a list of ten <lb/>anxiotropic interventions were selected to be included in the systematic review, either due <lb/>to their direct clinical importance (e.g., diazepam), their role as an example of a class of <lb/>proposed anxiety-related factors (e.g., isolation), or their connection to a clinically important <lb/>drug (e.g., Htt). A systematic review was conducted to identify published articles <lb/>addressing experimental outcomes in rodents from the EPM, OF, or LD assays for these <lb/>interventions. A comprehensive literature set for each genetic, pharmacological or <lb/>environmental intervention was generated by a PubMed search using specific search <lb/>phrases (Table 1). The selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) will be the subject of a <lb/>separate study currently in preparation, due to their clinical importance (Baldwin et al., <lb/>2014), the very large number of studies conducted on them (Griebel and Holmes, 2013), <lb/>and their controversial efficacy (Kirsch et al., 2008). <lb/>Eligibility criteria and study selection <lb/>Bibliographic data (including PubMed ID, date of publication, title and abstract) of studies <lb/>identified in the systematic review were exported to a spreadsheet using the PubMed <lb/>export function. Each article on this list was then reviewed at four levels of detail (title, <lb/>abstract, full text and a detailed review of experimental design) to determine their eligibility <lb/>for the review. Studies were required to be written in English and to have reported ARDEB <lb/>in adult rats or mice. We required that each included study contain (1) primary behavior <lb/>data from either an OF, EPM, or LD experiment for the intervention of interest, (2) suitable <lb/>controls were reported and (3) the relevant statistics were reported (mean, standard error or <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses </note>

            <page>page 6 <lb/></page>

            <body>standard deviation, and sample sizes of both control and intervention groups). Since the <lb/>focus of this study was the direct effects of anxiety-related interventions on ARDEB, <lb/>experiments that used combination treatments were excluded. For drug and environmental <lb/>interventions, possible confounding effects of the role of developmental stage were <lb/>reduced by excluding studies not performed in adult rodents. For gene knockout and <lb/>overexpression interventions, only experiments using a lifetime loss of function were <lb/>included in the meta-analyses. <lb/>Selection of non-anxiety-related interventions <lb/>Studies of the effect of non-anxiety-related interventions on ARDEB were harder to find, <lb/>perhaps due to the bias against publishing negative results, and/or reduced likelihood of <lb/>mentioning them in abstracts. PubMed searches in this area failed to identify any useful <lb/>studies. Instead, a conventional ad hoc literature search was used to find reports of the <lb/>effects of adenylyl cyclase 1 (two articles) and synaptotagmin (one article) on anxiety-<lb/>related behaviors. <lb/>Data inclusion in meta-analyses <lb/>Of the ten systematic reviews, eight identified fewer than or equal to fifteen eligible studies <lb/>and two identified more than fifteen (Table 1). For the first group, we used all available data <lb/>in their respective systematic meta-analyses. As our aim was to survey the wider rodent <lb/>ARDEB literature and not focus on any single manipulation, for interventions with more than <lb/>fifteen eligible studies, a maximum of fifteen studies was randomly selected for inclusion. <lb/>Sampling was done by randomly sorting the PubMed IDs in Excel and selecting the first <lb/>fifteen articles in each re-ordered list. The included studies used the two-independent-<lb/>groups design with sample sizes typically N = ~10 control animals and N = ~10 intervention <lb/>animals. Thus randomly sampling fifteen studies would bring the total iterations to N = <lb/>~150, ~150. From the significance testing perspective, assuming modest heterogeneity (an <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 7 <lb/></page>

            <body>assumption that is false in a minority of cases) and a two-tailed t-test with alpha = 0.05 for <lb/>a moderate (d = 0.5) effect size, such sample sizes would have power of ~99% (Faul et al., <lb/>2007). From the estimation perspective, precision would be predicted to improve by nearly <lb/>4-fold (= √150 ÷ √10) relative to primary results, also assuming modest heterogeneity. <lb/>Data items and extraction <lb/>The following data were collected from each of the included studies: authors, year of <lb/>publication, figure and panel numbers, species, genotype, and mean, standard error of the <lb/>mean and sample size (N) of each intervention and its related control group. Graphically <lb/>presented data were extracted from Portable Document Format (PDF) files with the <lb/>Measuring Tool in Adobe Acrobat Pro. A sample of ten randomly selected experiments <lb/>were re-extracted by a second reader to compare the effect of individual extractions; the <lb/>difference between the two extractions was g = 0.03 [95% confidence interval (95CI) 0.01, <lb/>0.05] on average, a negligible influence on meta-analytic effect sizes. <lb/>Summary measures <lb/>The following behavioral metrics were extracted from the articles: in OF studies, percent or <lb/>total time spent at the center; in EPM studies, percent or total time spent on the open arm; <lb/>in LD studies, percent or total time spent in the bright area. To synthesize these time-based <lb/>metrics from the three assays, all estimates were standardized to Hedges&apos; g, where g is a <lb/>preferred variant of Cohen&apos;s d that uses the pooled standard deviation and is corrected for <lb/>bias using Hedges&apos; method (Cumming, 2012; Borenstein et al., 2011). The conventional <lb/>adjectives to describe effect size (trivial, small, moderate, large) are used where appropriate <lb/>(Cumming, 2012). <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 8 <lb/></page>

            <body>Synthesis of results <lb/>Meta-analyses of experimental outcomes, including the calculation of weighted mean effect <lb/>sizes (Hedges&apos; g), 95% confidence intervals, I 2 heterogeneity values, and p values using the <lb/>random effects model, were performed with the metafor package in R (http://CRAN.R-<lb/>project.org/package=metafor) (Viechtbauer, 2010). All error bars in forest plots are 95% <lb/>confidence intervals; forest plots were generated with metafor and custom R scripts and <lb/>formatted in Adobe Illustrator. <lb/>Assessment of bias across studies <lb/>Publication bias was assessed using Egger&apos;s linear regression test for funnel plot <lb/>asymmetry (Egger et al., 1997). The standard normal deviate (Hedges&apos; g / standard error) <lb/>for each study was regressed against the study&apos;s precision (1 / standard error) using the <lb/>&quot;lm&quot; function in R (http://www.R-project.org/). For studies that had evidence of publication <lb/>bias (p-value ≤ 0.05), the trim-and-fill method (Duval and Tweedie, 2000) was employed to <lb/>estimate the effects of publication bias on the effect size estimate. Funnel plots and trim-<lb/>and-fill adjustments were performed with the &apos;metafor&apos; package in R (Viechtbauer, 2010). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note>

            <page>page 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>RESULTS <lb/>Review selection criteria identified 179 eligible articles <lb/>The flow-chart in Figure 1 summarizes the study selection process. In total, 585 articles <lb/>were identified by the initial PubMed searches. According to the selection criteria described <lb/>above, 249 studies were excluded based on their titles and a further 65 were excluded <lb/>based on their abstracts. The full text of the remaining 271 articles were screened for <lb/>criteria related to experimental paradigm, methods, and relevant variables, resulting in the <lb/>exclusion of a further 92 studies. A total of 179 articles were considered eligible for <lb/>inclusion in the review. Random selection of a maximum of fifteen studies for each <lb/>intervention reduced the final number to 87 articles for use in the meta-analyses. <lb/>Characteristics of included experiments <lb/>The characteristics of all included studies are given in Table 3. In brief, 87 studies <lb/>comprising 97 EPM experiments, 37 OF experiments and 22 LD experiments were <lb/>identified. Studies were published between 1993 and 2013 and included data from 109 <lb/>experiments conducted on mice and 48 experiments on rats. ARDEB studies of diazepam <lb/>used a median dosage of 1 mg/kg, with minimum and maximum dosages of 0.5 mg/kg and <lb/>5 mg/kg respectively. This dose range is similar to or higher than commonly used by <lb/>patients. <lb/>Heterogeneity <lb/>Statistically significant heterogeneity was found in (8/12) of the meta-analyses. Only two <lb/>meta-analyses had high heterogeneity (I 2 &gt; 75%): Htr1a overexpression, and physical <lb/>restraint (Higgins et al., 2003). Three of the meta-analyses, Htr1a knockouts and Htt <lb/>knockouts and isolation, had moderate heterogeneity (50% &lt; I 2 &lt; 75%). However, the <lb/>majority (seven meta-analyses) had low heterogeneity (I 2 &lt; 50%). As most of these <lb/>syntheses contained data from more than one assay type, it is encouraging that most had <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 10 <lb/></page>

            <body>low or moderate heterogeneity; this outcome is compatible with the idea that the three <lb/>ARDEB assays are testing similar aspects of rodent behavior. <lb/>Publication bias <lb/>Censorship of statistically non-significant results can result in the overstatement of effect <lb/>sizes in meta-analyses, for example this effect has a profound influence on the literature on <lb/>rodent models of stroke (Sena et al., 2010). Publication bias in the ARDEB literature was <lb/>assessed for the five meta-analyses that had at least ten experiments (Table 2) (Sterne et <lb/>al., 2011). Funnel plots and Egger&apos;s linear regression test for asymmetry revealed that three <lb/>of these literatures showed statistically significant bias (Figure 2; Table 2). Funnel plot <lb/>asymmetry can arise from publication bias, the censorship of experiments showing small <lb/>and/or statistically non-significant effect sizes (the file drawer effect) (Sterne et al., 2011). <lb/>For the three biased data sets, we used trim-and-fill adjustment to correct for the funnel <lb/>plot asymmetry and estimate the number of hypothesized missing studies (Duval and <lb/>Tweedie, 2000). We conclude that the literatures of diazepam, Htt knockout and social <lb/>isolation effects on ARDEB are affected by publication bias. <lb/>Diazepam produces a moderate reduction in defense behaviors <lb/>Diazepam is an important minor tranquilizer that was used for several decades as the first <lb/>line of treatment for anxiety disorders (Tone, 2009) and, along with other benzodiazepines, <lb/>is still used extensively to control anxiety (Baldwin et al., 2014). Recent clinical meta-<lb/>analysis studies have found support for the efficacy of benzodiazepines in the short-term <lb/>treatment of anxiety disorders (Baldwin et al., 2014). However, a published review of <lb/>diazepam effects in open field studies revealed widespread disagreement between with 29 <lb/>studies supporting an anxiolytic effect and 23 supporting either an anxiogenic effect or no <lb/>effect (Prut and Belzung, 2003). We reviewed the available literature on diazepam for the <lb/>three major rodent ARDEB assays: EPM, OF and LD. For the meta-analysis, data was <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>extracted from a randomized subset of fifteen studies (out of 62 eligible papers) (Brioni et <lb/>al., 1994; Faria et al., 1997; Boerngen-Lacerda and Souza-Formigoni, 2000; LaBuda and <lb/>Fuchs, 2001; Hui et al., 2002; Chen et al., 2004; Jain et al., 2005; Jászberényi et al., 2009; <lb/>Frassetto et al., 2010; Wanasuntronwong et al., 2012; Onusic et al., 2002; Birkett et al., <lb/>2011; Costa et al., 2011; Choleris et al., 2001; González-Pardo et al., 2006). Calculation of <lb/>an average Hedges&apos; g (Cumming, 2012) revealed that diazepam had a moderate effect on <lb/>ARDEB, with a -0.89 g [95CI -1.12, -0.6] reduction compared with untreated control animals <lb/>(Figure 3). However, Egger&apos;s regression indicated the source literature was affected by <lb/>publication bias, trim-and-fill adjustment reduced the effect size to -0.64 g [95CI -0.37, -<lb/>0.91], a -0.25 g reduction in the anxiolytic effect of this drug. The meta-analysis had a low <lb/>level of heterogeneity, indicating that the assay type, laboratory, dosage, species, strain <lb/>and other possible sources of experimental variation played a relatively minor role. <lb/>5-HT1A receptor function influences ARDEB <lb/>Following negative publicity regarding the adverse effects of benzodiazepines (Tone, 2009), <lb/>pharmaceutical companies focused on the serotonergic system (Griebel and Holmes, 2013). <lb/>Of the fourteen mammalian serotonergic receptors, the serotonin receptor 5-HT1A has <lb/>been targeted for its proposed connection with anxiety disorders and depression (Samuels <lb/>et al., 2014). More than 1200 articles describe experiments relating 5-HT1A agonism to <lb/>anxiety (Griebel and Holmes, 2013). However, a substantial proportion of those articles <lb/>reported that 5-HT1A agonists or knockout of the Htr1a gene either produced no effect on <lb/>anxiety or an effect that was opposite to the receptor&apos;s proposed mode of action (Griebel <lb/>and Holmes, 2013). We performed systematic reviews of gene manipulations of Htr1a. <lb/>Meta-analysis of data from eleven knockout articles (Ramboz et al., 1998; Gross et al., <lb/>2002; Groenink et al., 2003; Gleason et al., 2010; Freeman-Daniels et al., 2011; Ferrés-Coy <lb/>et al., 2013; Klemenhagen et al., 2006; Parks et al., 1998; Vinkers et al., 2010; Zanettini et <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 12 <lb/></page>

            <note place="footnote">al., 2010; Jain et al., 2012) revealed that removal of Htr1a produced a moderate increase <lb/>(Hedges&apos; g = 0.68 [95CI 0.38, 0.97] , p = 8.9 x 10 -06 ) in ARDEB phenotypes (Figure 4A). The <lb/>three studies of Htr1a overexpression found by the review (Kusserow et al., 2004; Bert et <lb/>al., 2006; Audero et al., 2013) indicate that this intervention moderately decreased ARDEB, <lb/>but this was not statistically significant (g = -0.52 [95CI -1.26, 0.23], p = 0.18; Figure 4B). <lb/>Overall, these results indicate there remains discordance regarding 5-HT1A function. While <lb/>the knockout has a moderate anxiogenic effect, Htr1a overexpression does not have a <lb/>statistically significant impact. A large cumulative sample size contributes to the ineffective <lb/>overexpression result (N = 144). These results verify the no-ARDEB effect hypothesis for <lb/>this treatment, indicating that Htr1a overexpression does not influence rodent defense <lb/>behaviors. <lb/>Anxiotropic effects of the serotonin transporter <lb/>The serotonin transporter (SERT) is the target for the selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors <lb/>(SSRIs), a class of drugs used to treat depression and anxiety (Baldwin et al., 2014). Meta-<lb/>analysis of thirteen knockout studies (Holmes et al., 2003b; 2003a; Lira et al., 2003; Li et al., <lb/>2004; Carroll et al., 2007; Kalueff et al., 2007a; Olivier et al., 2008; Line et al., 2011; <lb/>Schipper et al., 2011; Zhao et al., 2006; Kalueff et al., 2007b; Moya et al., 2011; Pang et al., <lb/>2011) revealed a large anxiogenic ARDEB effect (g = 0.88 [95CI -1.26, 0.23] , p = 5.2 x 10 -14 ; <lb/>Figure 5A) produced by knocking out the SERT gene, Htt. However, a funnel plot and <lb/>Egger&apos;s regression revealed a pronounced bias in reported effect sizes (Egger&apos;s test p = 6.7 <lb/>X 10 -6 , Table 2). Trim-and-fill adjustment filled the left segment of the funnel plot with ten <lb/>imputed data points so as to obtain a symmetric funnel plot, reducing the effect size to g = <lb/>0.57 [95CI 0.29, 0.86]. <lb/>Only two articles studying the effect of Htt overexpression on ARDEB were found <lb/>(Jennings et al., 2006; Line et al., 2011). Meta-analysis revealed a large anxiolytic effect (g = <lb/></note>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 13 <lb/></page>

            <body>-0.94 [95CI -1.69, -0.20], p = 0.013; Figure 5B) in EPM and OF assays (no LD articles were <lb/>found). The transporter gene knockout and overexpression effects clearly connect Htt <lb/>function to ARDEB/ However, the direction of effects is the opposite of what would be <lb/>expected from the clinical application of Htt inhibitors, given that SSRI reduction of Htt <lb/>function is thought to have a therapeutic anxiety-reducing effect. <lb/>The effects of environmental stressors in ARDEB <lb/>Environmental stressors have physiological effects on animals that promote the anxiety-like <lb/>state (van Praag, 2003). To survey a range of stress modalities we chose acute pain, bodily <lb/>restraint and social isolation for review; all three are known to promote anxiety in humans <lb/>(Sherif and Oreland, 1995). The systematic review identified only five papers measuring the <lb/>effect of acute pain on ARDEB (Schellinck et al., 2003; Benbouzid et al., 2008; Parent et al., <lb/>2012; Leite-Almeida et al., 2012; Matsuzawa-Yanagida et al., 2008), but meta-analysis of <lb/>these indicated a very large anxiogenic effect (g = 1.49 [95CI 1.12, 1.87], p = 5.8 x 10 -15 ; <lb/>Figure 6A). <lb/>Review of fifteen studies of rodent bodily restraint (Carvajal et al., 2004; Lunga and <lb/>Herbert, 2004; Estanislau and Morato, 2005; Hsu et al., 2007; Locchi et al., 2008; Nosek et <lb/>al., 2008; Rylkova et al., 2009; Granjeiro et al., 2011; Reis et al., 2011; Anand et al., 2012; <lb/>Walf and Frye, 2012; Busnardo et al., 2013; Liu et al., 2013; Ouagazzal et al., 2003; <lb/>Chesworth et al., 2012) indicated that it had an overall moderate anxiogenic effect in EPM <lb/>and OF assays (g = 0.70 [ 95% CI 0.82 -1.32], p = 0.027; Figure 6B). The restraint meta-<lb/>analysis indicated a high level of heterogeneity, I 2 = 87%; a sub-group analysis by assay <lb/>type revealed that the different assays were not the source of this variability (data not <lb/>shown). <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 14 <lb/></page>

            <body>Meta-analysis of fifteen articles (Rodgers and Cole, 1993; Haller et al., 2000; <lb/>Blednov et al., 2001; Cheeta et al., 2001; Lapiz et al., 2001; Wright and Ingenito, 2001; <lb/>Majercsik et al., 2003; Moragrega et al., 2003; Abramov et al., 2004; Wei et al., 2007; Koike <lb/>et al., 2009; Santos et al., 2010; Cuenya et al., 2012; Lukkes et al., 2009; Hermes et al., <lb/>2011) on social isolation revealed it had a small anxiogenic effect (g = 0.37 [95CI 0.15, <lb/>0.58], p = 7.8 x 10 -4 ; Figure 6C). However, Egger&apos;s regression revealed funnel plot <lb/>asymmetry, while trim-and-fill adjustment reduced the anxiogenic effect to only 0.15 g <lb/>[95CI -0.10, 0.40], a small and statistically non-significant effect on ARDEB (Figure 2). It <lb/>appears that, unlike the physical stressors, social isolation does not have an influence on <lb/>ARDEB, thus supporting the no-ARDEB hypothesis. <lb/>The role of CRH and its receptor on ARDEB <lb/>Several neuropeptide-related genes involved in stress signaling have been linked to anxiety, <lb/>notably the peptide, corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH; also known as corticotropin-<lb/>releasing factor) (Kormos and Gaszner, 2013) and its receptor, CRHR1. Two studies that <lb/>examined the effects of Crh knockouts on ARDEB were found (Weninger et al., 1999), which <lb/>revealed only a small effect (g = 0.30 [95CI -0.32, 0.92], p = 0.34; Figure 7A). This supports <lb/>the idea that CRH does not influence ARDEB, and supports the no-ARDEB hypothesis. <lb/>However, the meta-analytic result may suffer from insufficient power as the cumulative <lb/>sample size was only 41. <lb/>CRH exerts its biological action via two receptors known as CRHR1 and CRHR2. <lb/>The two receptors are pharmacologically distinct and only the former has been widely <lb/>studied in the context of anxiety (Owens and Nemeroff, 1991; Paez-Pereda et al., 2011). <lb/>Meta-analysis (Liebsch et al., 1995; 1999; Smith et al., 1998; Müller et al., 2003; Gammie <lb/>and Stevenson, 2006; Trimble et al., 2007) found that, in contrast to the Crh knockout, <lb/>deletion of Crhr1 had a large anxiolytic effect on ARDEB (g = -1.0 [95CI -1.30, -0.70], p = <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 15 <lb/></page>

            <body>6.64 x 10 -11 ; Figure 7B). The discordance between Crh and Crhr1 knockout effects has <lb/>previously been attributed to the action of either urocortin or another unidentified peptide <lb/>ligand of Crhr1 (Dunn and Swiergiel, 1999). <lb/>Genes with no purported effect on anxiety <lb/>Some of the interventions in the systematic review were found to have modest effects on <lb/>ARDEB. We aimed to contextualize the magnitude of proposed anxiety factors with factors <lb/>that the literature has not connected with anxiety. Such factors are not generally mentioned <lb/>in anxiety reviews and it is difficult to identify them with PubMed searches as they are less <lb/>likely to be published or, when published, are unlikely to be the focus of a study and thus <lb/>may not be mentioned in the abstract. We adopted an ad hoc search for systems <lb/>unimportant to anxiety, which identified adenylyl cyclase 1 (Storm et al., 1998; Krishnan et <lb/>al., 2008) and synaptotagmin 1 (Powell et al., 2004) as being proposed to have no anxiety-<lb/>related activity. Meta-analyses confirmed that both interventions have very small (Hedges&apos; g <lb/>&lt; 0.3) and non-statistically significant effects on ARDEB (Figure 8A-B). These results <lb/>indicate that anxiety factors generally appear to have an ARDEB effect that is at least twice <lb/>the magnitude of factors believed to be unimportant to anxiety. <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 16 <lb/></page>

            <body>DISCUSSION <lb/>Summary of evidence <lb/>Inspection of the forest plots reveals that all of the primary publication sets include <lb/>experimental effect sizes that are discordant, either in direction (anxiolytic versus <lb/>anxiogenic) and/or magnitude. The generality of discordance in the literature emphasizes <lb/>the critical utility of meta-analysis to behavioral neuroscience. Of ten analyses of putative <lb/>anxiotropic interventions, seven yielded substantial meta-analytic effect sizes that were <lb/>statistical and three produced non-statistically significant effect sizes, once publication bias <lb/>was accounted for (Figure 9). Overall, these results verify the no-ARDEB-effect hypothesis <lb/>in a minority of cases (Htr1a overexpression, Crh and social isolation): their consensus <lb/>effect sizes are comparable with &apos;non-anxiety&apos; genes like Syt1. However, the majority of <lb/>putative anxiety-related genes do have at least moderate effects on the rodent defense <lb/>behaviors. The synthetic data strongly confirm that diazepam, the serotonergic system, <lb/>environmental stressors, and Crhr1 influence an anxiety-like process in the mouse brain. <lb/>Knowledge gaps, publication bias and heterogeneity <lb/>We found no knowledge gaps per se, as all the purported anxiety-related factors had at <lb/>least two studies. Only Htt overexpression, Crh knockouts and the non-anxiety genes had <lb/>total experimental iterations below N = 64, 64, the sample size needed for 80% power to <lb/>detect a 0.5 standard deviation effect size. However, the Ht1a overexpression and CRH <lb/>knockout meta-analytic results remain imprecise (Figure 9), indicating that more work could <lb/>be done here. Of the five intensively published factors (15 studies or more), three were <lb/>affected by publication bias, suggesting that publication bias affects a majority of literatures <lb/>in this area. Heterogeneity was encouragingly low for the literatures of most of the factors <lb/>reviewed, suggesting that laboratory, strain, assay type and protocol variations play a <lb/>relatively minor role in these experiments. <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 17 <lb/></page>

            <body>Gains of function in Htr1a has a weak effect on ARDEB <lb/>Meta-analysis of Htr1a overexpression revealed that is has a moderate anxiolytic effect, but <lb/>that this is not statistically significant. Substantial numbers of animals were used to obtain <lb/>this results (N = 72, 72), though the meta-analysis also displayed a high level of <lb/>heterogeneity (I 2 = 59%). That overexpression of Htr1a has a weak effect suggests that <lb/>aiming to increase 5-HT1A function may be a poor strategy to reduce anxiety, despite the <lb/>pronounced Htr1a knockout outcome. This conclusion is supported by recent clinical meta-<lb/>analyses that have concluded that drugs targeting 5-HT1A -the azapirones -appear <lb/>inferior to benzodiazepines for generalized anxiety disorder (Chessick et al., 2006) and that <lb/>there is insufficient evidence to support azapirone use in panic disorder (Imai et al., 2014). <lb/>The Htt-SSRI paradox in defense behaviors <lb/>Drugs that target SERT, the SSRIs, are recommended as the first line of pharmacological <lb/>treatment for anxiety (Baldwin et al., 2014). Blocking SERT-mediated transport (reuptake) of <lb/>serotonin from the synaptic cleft is the proposed mechanism of anxiety reduction (Perez-<lb/>Caballero et al., 2014). Rodent studies of chronic SSRI effects on ARDEB have been <lb/>inconclusive (Perez-Caballero et al., 2014; Griebel and Holmes, 2013). Given the the <lb/>inhibitors&apos; clinical use, it is surprising that Htt knockouts have elevated anxiety relative to <lb/>controls and that Htt overexpression reduces ARDEB phenotypes. The reason for this <lb/>discordance is not clear. In some cases the authors of the primary Htt knockout studies <lb/>have not discussed this paradox (Moya et al., 2011; Schipper et al., 2011; Carroll et al., <lb/>2007; Kalueff et al., 2007a). Other authors have remarked that the underlying reason <lb/>remains unclear (Lira et al., 2003; Holmes et al., 2003b) or have questioned the validity of <lb/>ARDEB assays (Pang et al., 2011). Primary study authors have also proposed two <lb/>explanatory hypotheses. The first is that increased anxiety arises from developmental <lb/>alterations present in Htt knockouts not present in chronically drug-treated animals (Olivier <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 18 <lb/></page>

            <body>et al., 2008; Zhao et al., 2006; Holmes et al., 2003b). This hypothesis could be tested with <lb/>conditional knockdown models, i.e. in animals with Htt only deleted at the adult stage. <lb/>While systematic review did not identify any published reports of post-developmental Htt <lb/>knockout experiments (e.g., using floxed Htt), researchers have looked at the anxiety-<lb/>related effects of conditionally ablating the Pet-1 gene. Pet-1 is a transcription factor with <lb/>an expression pattern that overlaps closely with Htt&apos;s expression pattern. In mice with Pet-1 <lb/>removed in adulthood, mRNA levels of Htt are also reduced substantially (Liu et al., 2010). <lb/>Like Htt knockouts, these mice show increased anxiety-like behaviors in multiple ARDEB <lb/>assays (Liu et al., 2010), eroding confidence in the developmental alteration hypothesis. A <lb/>second hypothesis to explain the Htt/SSRI paradox is that there is a J-shaped relationship <lb/>between Htt function and anxiety, i.e., both wild-type and knock-out animals would have <lb/>higher anxiety relative to animals with intermediate function (Olivier et al., 2008). Further <lb/>study is required to fully understand the role of Htt and SSRIs in ARDEB. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>This study supports the hypothesis that some mainstream anxiety-related interventions <lb/>have trivial or unconfirmed effects in rodent defense behavior assays. However, this study <lb/>also confirms a drug, two environmental stressors and a number of genes as authentic <lb/>ARDEB influencers. These verified anxiety-related interventions (diazepam, Htr1a gene <lb/>knockout, Htt gene knockout, Htt gene overexpression, acute pain, restraint and Crhr1 <lb/>gene knockout) can be used as reference manipulations to validate other animal models of <lb/>anxiety-like behavior. <lb/>Meta-analysis has the ability to aggregate information and resolve discordance in <lb/>the primary literature. This ability may be particularly useful in behavioral neuroscience <lb/>where most primary articles describe experiments with low power (or precision) (Button et <lb/>al., 2013). Precise estimation of effect magnitude is important both to build quantitative <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 19 <lb/></page>

            <body>models of brain function and to improve the ability of preclinical studies to predict clinical <lb/>efficacy. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses </note>

            <page>page 20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Abramov, U., Raud, S., Kõks, S., Innos, J., Kurrikoff, K., Matsui, T., and Vasar, E. (2004). <lb/>Targeted mutation of CCK(2) receptor gene antagonises behavioural changes induced <lb/>by social isolation in female, but not in male mice. Behav Brain Res 155, 1-11. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.bbr.2004.03.027. <lb/>Anand, R., Gulati, K., and Ray, A. (2012). Pharmacological evidence for the role of nitric <lb/>oxide in the modulation of stress-induced anxiety by morphine in rats. Eur J Pharmacol <lb/>676, 71-74. doi:10.1016/j.ejphar.2011.11.032. <lb/>Audero, E., Mlinar, B., Baccini, G., Skachokova, Z. K., Corradetti, R., and Gross, C. (2013). <lb/>Suppression of serotonin neuron firing increases aggression in mice. J Neurosci 33, <lb/>8678-8688. doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2067-12.2013. <lb/>Baldwin, D. S., Anderson, I. M., Nutt, D. J., Allgulander, C., Bandelow, B., Boer, den, J. A., <lb/>Christmas, D. M., Davies, S., Fineberg, N., Lidbetter, N., et al. (2014). Evidence-based <lb/>pharmacological treatment of anxiety disorders, post-traumatic stress disorder and <lb/>obsessive-compulsive disorder: A revision of the 2005 guidelines from the British <lb/>Association for Psychopharmacology. J Psychopharmacol (Oxford) 28, 403-439. <lb/>doi:10.1177/0269881114525674. <lb/>Benbouzid, M., Pallage, V., Rajalu, M., Waltisperger, E., Doridot, S., Poisbeau, P., Freund-<lb/>Mercier, M. J., and Barrot, M. (2008). Sciatic nerve cuffing in mice: a model of sustained <lb/>neuropathic pain. Eur J Pain 12, 591-599. doi:10.1016/j.ejpain.2007.10.002. <lb/>Bert, B., Fink, H., Hörtnagl, H., Veh, R. W., Ben Davies, Theuring, F., and Kusserow, H. <lb/>(2006). Mice over-expressing the 5-HT1A receptor in cortex and dentate gyrus display <lb/>exaggerated locomotor and hypothermic response to 8-OH-DPAT. Behav Brain Res <lb/>167, 328-341. doi:10.1016/j.bbr.2005.09.020. <lb/>Birkett, M. A., Shinday, N. M., Kessler, E. J., Meyer, J. S., Ritchie, S., and Rowlett, J. K. <lb/>(2011). Acute anxiogenic-like effects of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors are <lb/>attenuated by the benzodiazepine diazepam in BALB/c mice. Pharmacol Biochem <lb/>Behav 98, 544-551. doi:10.1016/j.pbb.2011.03.006. <lb/>Blednov, Y. A., Stoffel, M., Chang, S. R., and Harris, R. A. (2001). GIRK2 deficient mice. <lb/>Evidence for hyperactivity and reduced anxiety. Physiol Behav 74, 109-117. <lb/>Boerngen-Lacerda, R., and Souza-Formigoni, M. L. (2000). Does the increase in locomotion <lb/>induced by ethanol indicate its stimulant or anxiolytic properties? Pharmacol Biochem <lb/>Behav 67, 225-232. <lb/>Borenstein, M., Hedges, L. V., Higgins, J., and Rothstein, H. R. (2011). Introduction to meta-<lb/>analysis. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. <lb/>Brioni, J. D., O&apos;Neill, A. B., Kim, D. J., Buckley, M. J., Decker, M. W., and Arneric, S. P. <lb/>(1994). Anxiolytic-like effects of the novel cholinergic channel activator ABT-418. J <lb/>Pharmacol Exp Ther 271, 353-361. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 21 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>Busnardo, C., Alves, F. H. F., Crestani, C. C., Scopinho, A. A., Resstel, L. B. M., and <lb/>Corrêa, F. M. A. (2013). Paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus glutamate <lb/>neurotransmission modulates autonomic, neuroendocrine and behavioral responses to <lb/>acute restraint stress in rats. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol 23, 1611-1622. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.euroneuro.2012.11.002. <lb/>Button, K. S., Ioannidis, J. P. A., Mokrysz, C., Nosek, B. A., Flint, J., Robinson, E. S. J., and <lb/>Munafò, M. R. (2013). Power failure: why small sample size undermines the reliability of <lb/>neuroscience. Nat Rev Neurosci 14, 365-376. doi:10.1038/nrn3475. <lb/>Carroll, J. C., Boyce-Rustay, J. M., Millstein, R., Yang, R., Wiedholz, L. M., Murphy, D. L., <lb/>and Holmes, A. (2007). Effects of mild early life stress on abnormal emotion-related <lb/>behaviors in 5-HTT knockout mice. Behav Genet 37, 214-222. doi:10.1007/s10519-<lb/>006-9129-9. <lb/>Carvajal, C. C., Vercauteren, F., Dumont, Y., Michalkiewicz, M., and Quirion, R. (2004). <lb/>Aged neuropeptide Y transgenic rats are resistant to acute stress but maintain spatial <lb/>and non-spatial learning. Behav Brain Res 153, 471-480. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.bbr.2004.01.004. <lb/>Cheeta, S., Irvine, E., and File, S. E. (2001). Social isolation modifies nicotine&apos;s effects in <lb/>animal tests of anxiety. Br J Pharmacol 132, 1389-1395. doi:10.1038/sj.bjp.0703991. <lb/>Chen, S. W., Kong, W. X., Zhang, Y. J., Li, Y. L., Mi, X. J., and Mu, X. S. (2004). Possible <lb/>anxiolytic effects of taurine in the mouse elevated plus-maze. Life Sci. 75, 1503-1511. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.lfs.2004.03.010. <lb/>Chessick, C. A., Allen, M. H., Thase, M., Batista Miralha da Cunha, A. B. C., Kapczinski, F. <lb/>F. K., de Lima, M. S. M. L., and Santos Souza, dos, J. J. S. S. (2006). Azapirones for <lb/>generalized anxiety disorder. Cochrane database of systematic reviews (Online), <lb/>CD006115. doi:10.1002/14651858.CD006115. <lb/>Chesworth, R., Yulyaningsih, E., Cappas, E., Arnold, J., Sainsbury, A., and Karl, T. (2012). <lb/>The response of neuregulin 1 mutant mice to acute restraint stress. Neurosci Lett 515, <lb/>82-86. doi:10.1016/j.neulet.2012.03.024. <lb/>Choleris, E., Thomas, A. W., Kavaliers, M., and Prato, F. S. (2001). A detailed ethological <lb/>analysis of the mouse open field test: effects of diazepam, chlordiazepoxide and an <lb/>extremely low frequency pulsed magnetic field. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 25, 235-260. <lb/>Costa, C. A. R. de A., Kohn, D. O., de Lima, V. M., Gargano, A. C., Flório, J. C., and Costa, <lb/>M. (2011). The GABAergic system contributes to the anxiolytic-like effect of essential oil <lb/>from Cymbopogon citratus (lemongrass). J Ethnopharmacol 137, 828-836. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.jep.2011.07.003. <lb/>Crawley, J., and Goodwin, F. K. (1980). Preliminary report of a simple animal behavior <lb/>model for the anxiolytic effects of benzodiazepines. Pharmacol Biochem Behav 13, <lb/>167-170. <lb/>Cuenya, L., Fosacheca, S., Mustaca, A., and Kamenetzky, G. (2012). Effects of isolation in <lb/>adulthood on frustration and anxiety. Behav Processes 90, 155-160. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 22 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>doi:10.1016/j.beproc.2012.01.003. <lb/>Cumming, G. (2012). Understanding the New Statistics: Effect Sizes, Confidence Intervals, <lb/>and Meta-Analysis. <lb/>Darwin, C. (1998). The Expression of the Emotions in Man and Animals. Project Gutenberg. <lb/>DiLuca, M., and Olesen, J. (2014). The Cost of Brain Diseases: A Burden or a Challenge? <lb/>Neuron 82, 1205-1208. doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2014.05.044. <lb/>Dunn, A. J., and Swiergiel, A. H. (1999). Behavioral responses to stress are intact in CRF-<lb/>deficient mice. Brain Res 845, 14-20. <lb/>Duval, S., and Tweedie, R. (2000). Trim and fill: A simple funnel-plot-based method of <lb/>testing and adjusting for publication bias in meta-analysis. Biometrics 56, 455-463. <lb/>Egger, M., Davey Smith, G., Schneider, M., and Minder, C. (1997). Bias in meta-analysis <lb/>detected by a simple, graphical test. BMJ 315, 629-634. <lb/>Estanislau, C., and Morato, S. (2005). Prenatal stress produces more behavioral alterations <lb/>than maternal separation in the elevated plus-maze and in the elevated T-maze. Behav <lb/>Brain Res 163, 70-77. doi:10.1016/j.bbr.2005.04.003. <lb/>Faria, M. S., Muscará, M. N., Moreno Júnior, H., Teixeira, S. A., Dias, H. B., De Oliveira, B., <lb/>Graeff, F. G., and De Nucci, G. (1997). Acute inhibition of nitric oxide synthesis induces <lb/>anxiolysis in the plus maze test. Eur J Pharmacol 323, 37-43. <lb/>Faul, F., Erdfelder, E., Lang, A.-G., and Buchner, A. (2007). G*Power 3: a flexible statistical <lb/>power analysis program for the social, behavioral, and biomedical sciences. Behav Res <lb/>Methods 39, 175-191. <lb/>Ferrés-Coy, A., Santana, N., Castañé, A., Cortés, R., Carmona, M. C., Toth, M., Montefeltro, <lb/>A., Artigas, F., and Bortolozzi, A. (2013). Acute 5-HT₁A autoreceptor knockdown <lb/>increases antidepressant responses and serotonin release in stressful conditions. <lb/>Psychopharmacology (Berl) 225, 61-74. doi:10.1007/s00213-012-2795-9. <lb/>Frassetto, S. S., Alves, I. O., Santos, M. M., Schmidt, A. E. S., Lopes, J. J., Oliveira, P. A., <lb/>Vinagre, A. S., and Pereira, P. (2010). Absence of sibutramine effect on spontaneous <lb/>anxiety in rats. Arq Bras Endocrinol Metabol 54, 375-380. <lb/>Freeman-Daniels, E., Beck, S. G., and Kirby, L. G. (2011). Cellular correlates of anxiety in <lb/>CA1 hippocampal pyramidal cells of 5-HT1A receptor knockout mice. <lb/>Psychopharmacology (Berl) 213, 453-463. doi:10.1007/s00213-010-2030-5. <lb/>Gammie, S. C., and Stevenson, S. A. (2006). Intermale aggression in corticotropin-releasing <lb/>factor receptor 1 deficient mice. Behav Brain Res 171, 63-69. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.bbr.2006.03.017. <lb/>Gleason, G., Liu, B., Bruening, S., Zupan, B., Auerbach, A., Mark, W., Oh, J. E., Gal-Toth, <lb/>J., Lee, F., and Toth, M. (2010). The serotonin1A receptor gene as a genetic and <lb/>prenatal maternal environmental factor in anxiety. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 107, 7592-<lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 23 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>7597. doi:10.1073/pnas.0914805107. <lb/>González-Pardo, H., Conejo, N. M., and Arias, J. L. (2006). Oxidative metabolism of limbic <lb/>structures after acute administration of diazepam, alprazolam and zolpidem. Prog <lb/>Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry 30, 1020-1026. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.pnpbp.2006.03.026. <lb/>Granjeiro, E. M., Gomes, F. V., Guimarães, F. S., Corrêa, F. M. A., and Resstel, L. B. M. <lb/>(2011). Effects of intracisternal administration of cannabidiol on the cardiovascular and <lb/>behavioral responses to acute restraint stress. Pharmacol Biochem Behav 99, 743-748. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.pbb.2011.06.027. <lb/>Griebel, G., and Holmes, A. (2013). 50 years of hurdles and hope in anxiolytic drug <lb/>discovery. Nat Rev Drug Discov 12, 667-687. doi:10.1038/nrd4075. <lb/>Groenink, L., Pattij, T., De Jongh, R., Van der Gugten, J., Oosting, R. S., Dirks, A., and <lb/>Olivier, B. (2003). 5-HT1A receptor knockout mice and mice overexpressing <lb/>corticotropin-releasing hormone in models of anxiety. Eur J Pharmacol 463, 185-197. <lb/>doi:10.1016/S0014-2999(03)01281-0. <lb/>Gross, C., Zhuang, X., Stark, K., Ramboz, S., Oosting, R., Kirby, L., Santarelli, L., Beck, S., <lb/>and Hen, R. (2002). Serotonin1A receptor acts during development to establish normal <lb/>anxiety-like behaviour in the adult. Nature 416, 396-400. doi:10.1038/416396a. <lb/>Haller, J., Halász, J., and Makara, G. B. (2000). Housing conditions and the anxiolytic <lb/>efficacy of buspirone: the relationship between main and side effects. Behav Pharmacol <lb/>11, 403-412. <lb/>Hermes, G., Li, N., Duman, C., and Duman, R. (2011). Post-weaning chronic social isolation <lb/>produces profound behavioral dysregulation with decreases in prefrontal cortex <lb/>synaptic-associated protein expression in female rats. Physiol Behav 104, 354-359. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.physbeh.2010.12.019. <lb/>Higgins, J., Thompson, S. G., Deeks, J. J., and Altman, D. G. (2003). Measuring <lb/>inconsistency in meta-analyses. BMJ: British Medical Journal 327, 557-560. <lb/>Holmes, A., Lit, Q., Murphy, D. L., Gold, E., and Crawley, J. N. (2003a). Abnormal anxiety-<lb/>related behavior in serotonin transporter null mutant mice: the influence of genetic <lb/>background. Genes Brain Behav 2, 365-380. <lb/>Holmes, A., Yang, R. J., Lesch, K.-P., Crawley, J. N., and Murphy, D. L. (2003b). Mice <lb/>lacking the serotonin transporter exhibit 5-HT(1A) receptor-mediated abnormalities in <lb/>tests for anxiety-like behavior. Neuropsychopharmacology 28, 2077-2088. <lb/>doi:10.1038/sj.npp.1300266. <lb/>Hsu, H.-R., Chen, T.-Y., Chan, M.-H., and Chen, H.-H. (2007). Acute effects of nicotine on <lb/>restraint stress-induced anxiety-like behavior, c-Fos expression, and corticosterone <lb/>release in mice. Eur J Pharmacol 566, 124-131. doi:10.1016/j.ejphar.2007.03.040. <lb/>Hui, K. M., Huen, M. S. Y., Wang, H. Y., Zheng, H., Sigel, E., Baur, R., Ren, H., Li, Z. W., <lb/>Wong, J. T.-F., and Xue, H. (2002). Anxiolytic effect of wogonin, a benzodiazepine <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 24 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>receptor ligand isolated from Scutellaria baicalensis Georgi. Biochem. Pharmacol. 64, <lb/>1415-1424. <lb/>Imai, H., Tajika, A., Chen, P., Pompoli, A., Guaiana, G., Castellazzi, M., Bighelli, I., Girlanda, <lb/>F., Barbui, C., Koesters, M., et al. (2014). Azapirones versus placebo for panic disorder <lb/>in adults. Cochrane database of systematic reviews (Online) 9, CD010828-CD010828. <lb/>doi:10.1002/14651858.CD010828.pub2. <lb/>Jain, A., Dvorkin, A., Fonio, E., Golani, I., and Gross, C. T. (2012). Validation of the <lb/>dimensionality emergence assay for the measurement of innate anxiety in laboratory <lb/>mice. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol 22, 153-163. doi:10.1016/j.euroneuro.2011.07.001. <lb/>Jain, N. S., Hirani, K., and Chopde, C. T. (2005). Reversal of caffeine-induced anxiety by <lb/>neurosteroid 3-alpha-hydroxy-5-alpha-pregnane-20-one in rats. Neuropharmacology <lb/>48, 627-638. doi:10.1016/j.neuropharm.2004.11.016. <lb/>Jászberényi, M., Bagosi, Z., Thurzó, B., Földesi, I., Szabó, G., and Telegdy, G. (2009). <lb/>Endocrine, behavioral and autonomic effects of neuropeptide AF. Horm Behav 56, 24-<lb/>34. doi:10.1016/j.yhbeh.2009.02.006. <lb/>Jennings, K. A., Loder, M. K., Sheward, W. J., Pei, Q., Deacon, R. M. J., Benson, M. A., <lb/>Olverman, H. J., Hastie, N. D., Harmar, A. J., Shen, S., et al. (2006). Increased <lb/>expression of the 5-HT transporter confers a low-anxiety phenotype linked to <lb/>decreased 5-HT transmission. J Neurosci 26, 8955-8964. <lb/>doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5356-05.2006. <lb/>Kalueff, A. V., Fox, M. A., Gallagher, P. S., and Murphy, D. L. (2007a). Hypolocomotion, <lb/>anxiety and serotonin syndrome-like behavior contribute to the complex phenotype of <lb/>serotonin transporter knockout mice. Genes Brain Behav 6, 389-400. <lb/>doi:10.1111/j.1601-183X.2006.00270.x. <lb/>Kalueff, A. V., Jensen, C. L., and Murphy, D. L. (2007b). Locomotory patterns, <lb/>spatiotemporal organization of exploration and spatial memory in serotonin transporter <lb/>knockout mice. Brain Res 1169, 87-97. doi:10.1016/j.brainres.2007.07.009. <lb/>Kirsch, I., Deacon, B. J., Huedo-Medina, T. B., Scoboria, A., Moore, T. J., and Johnson, B. <lb/>T. (2008). Initial severity and antidepressant benefits: a meta-analysis of data submitted <lb/>to the Food and Drug Administration. PLoS Med 5, e45. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pmed.0050045. <lb/>Klemenhagen, K. C., Gordon, J. A., David, D. J., Hen, R., and Gross, C. T. (2006). Increased <lb/>fear response to contextual cues in mice lacking the 5-HT1A receptor. <lb/>Neuropsychopharmacology 31, 101-111. doi:10.1038/sj.npp.1300774. <lb/>Koike, H., Ibi, D., Mizoguchi, H., Nagai, T., Nitta, A., Takuma, K., Nabeshima, T., Yoneda, <lb/>Y., and Yamada, K. (2009). Behavioral abnormality and pharmacologic response in <lb/>social isolation-reared mice. Behav Brain Res 202, 114-121. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.bbr.2009.03.028. <lb/>Kormos, V., and Gaszner, B. (2013). Role of neuropeptides in anxiety, stress, and <lb/>depression: from animals to humans. Neuropeptides 47, 401-419. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 25 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>doi:10.1016/j.npep.2013.10.014. <lb/>Krishnan, V., Graham, A., Mazei-Robison, M. S., Lagace, D. C., Kim, K.-S., Birnbaum, S., <lb/>Eisch, A. J., Han, P.-L., Storm, D. R., Zachariou, V., et al. (2008). Calcium-sensitive <lb/>adenylyl cyclases in depression and anxiety: behavioral and biochemical consequences <lb/>of isoform targeting. Biol Psychiatry 64, 336-343. doi:10.1016/j.biopsych.2008.03.026. <lb/>Kusserow, H., Davies, B., Hörtnagl, H., Voigt, I., Stroh, T., Bert, B., Deng, D. R., Fink, H., <lb/>Veh, R. W., and Theuring, F. (2004). Reduced anxiety-related behaviour in transgenic <lb/>mice overexpressing serotonin 1A receptors. Molecular Brain Research 129, 104-116. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.molbrainres.2004.06.028. <lb/>LaBuda, C. J., and Fuchs, P. N. (2001). The anxiolytic effect of acute ethanol or diazepam <lb/>exposure is unaltered in mu-opioid receptor knockout mice. Brain Res Bull 55, 755-<lb/>760. <lb/>Lapiz, M. D., Mateo, Y., Durkin, S., Parker, T., and Marsden, C. A. (2001). Effects of central <lb/>noradrenaline depletion by the selective neurotoxin DSP-4 on the behaviour of the <lb/>isolated rat in the elevated plus maze and water maze. Psychopharmacology (Berl) 155, <lb/>251-259. <lb/>Leite-Almeida, H., Cerqueira, J. J., Wei, H., Ribeiro-Costa, N., Anjos-Martins, H., Sousa, N., <lb/>Pertovaara, A., and Almeida, A. (2012). Differential effects of left/right neuropathy on <lb/>rats&apos; anxiety and cognitive behavior. Pain 153, 2218-2225. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.pain.2012.07.007. <lb/>Li, Q., Holmes, A., Ma, L., Van de Kar, L. D., Garcia, F., and Murphy, D. L. (2004). Medial <lb/>hypothalamic 5-hydroxytryptamine (5-HT)1A receptors regulate neuroendocrine <lb/>responses to stress and exploratory locomotor activity: application of recombinant <lb/>adenovirus containing 5-HT1A sequences. J Neurosci 24, 10868-10877. <lb/>doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3223-04.2004. <lb/>Liebsch, G., Landgraf, R., Engelmann, M., Lörscher, P., and Holsboer, F. (1999). Differential <lb/>behavioural effects of chronic infusion of CRH 1 and CRH 2 receptor antisense <lb/>oligonucleotides into the rat brain. J Psychiatr Res 33, 153-163. <lb/>Liebsch, G., Landgraf, R., Gerstberger, R., Probst, J. C., Wotjak, C. T., Engelmann, M., <lb/>Holsboer, F., and Montkowski, A. (1995). Chronic infusion of a CRH1 receptor <lb/>antisense oligodeoxynucleotide into the central nucleus of the amygdala reduced <lb/>anxiety-related behavior in socially defeated rats. Regul. Pept. 59, 229-239. <lb/>Line, S. J., Barkus, C., Coyle, C., Jennings, K. A., Deacon, R. M., Lesch, K. P., Sharp, T., <lb/>and Bannerman, D. M. (2011). Opposing alterations in anxiety and species-typical <lb/>behaviours in serotonin transporter overexpressor and knockout mice. Eur <lb/>Neuropsychopharmacol 21, 108-116. doi:10.1016/j.euroneuro.2010.08.005. <lb/>Lira, A., Zhou, M., Castanon, N., Ansorge, M. S., Gordon, J. A., Francis, J. H., Bradley-<lb/>Moore, M., Lira, J., Underwood, M. D., Arango, V., et al. (2003). Altered depression-<lb/>related behaviors and functional changes in the dorsal raphe nucleus of serotonin <lb/>transporter-deficient mice. Biol Psychiatry 54, 960-971. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 26 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>Liu, C., Maejima, T., Wyler, S. C., Casadesus, G., Herlitze, S., and Deneris, E. S. (2010). <lb/>Pet-1 is required across different stages of life to regulate serotonergic function. Nat <lb/>Neurosci 13, 1190-1198. doi:10.1038/nn.2623. <lb/>Liu, J., Garza, J. C., Li, W., and Lu, X.-Y. (2013). Melanocortin-4 receptor in the medial <lb/>amygdala regulates emotional stress-induced anxiety-like behaviour, anorexia and <lb/>corticosterone secretion. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol 16, 105-120. <lb/>doi:10.1017/S146114571100174X. <lb/>Locchi, F., Dall&apos;olio, R., Gandolfi, O., and Rimondini, R. (2008). Olanzapine counteracts <lb/>stress-induced anxiety-like behavior in rats. Neurosci Lett 438, 146-149. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.neulet.2008.04.017. <lb/>Lukkes, J. L., Mokin, M. V., Scholl, J. L., and Forster, G. L. (2009). Adult rats exposed to <lb/>early-life social isolation exhibit increased anxiety and conditioned fear behavior, and <lb/>altered hormonal stress responses. Horm Behav 55, 248-256. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.yhbeh.2008.10.014. <lb/>Lunga, P., and Herbert, J. (2004). 17Beta-oestradiol modulates glucocorticoid, neural and <lb/>behavioural adaptations to repeated restraint stress in female rats. Journal of <lb/>Neuroendocrinology 16, 776-785. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2826.2004.01234.x. <lb/>Majercsik, E., Haller, J., Leveleki, C., Baranyi, J., Halász, J., and Rodgers, R. J. (2003). The <lb/>effect of social factors on the anxiolytic efficacy of buspirone in male rats, male mice, <lb/>and men. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry 27, 1187-1199. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.pnpbp.2003.09.013. <lb/>Matsuzawa-Yanagida, K., Narita, M., Nakajima, M., Kuzumaki, N., Niikura, K., Nozaki, H., <lb/>Takagi, T., Tamai, E., Hareyama, N., Terada, M., et al. (2008). Usefulness of <lb/>antidepressants for improving the neuropathic pain-like state and pain-induced anxiety <lb/>through actions at different brain sites. Neuropsychopharmacology 33, 1952-1965. <lb/>doi:10.1038/sj.npp.1301590. <lb/>Moragrega, I., Carrasco, M. C., Vicens, P., and Redolat, R. (2003). Spatial learning in male <lb/>mice with different levels of aggressiveness: effects of housing conditions and nicotine <lb/>administration. Behav Brain Res 147, 1-8. <lb/>Moya, P. R., Fox, M. A., Jensen, C. L., LaPorte, J. L., French, H. T., Wendland, J. R., and <lb/>Murphy, D. L. (2011). Altered 5-HT2C receptor agonist-induced responses and 5-HT2C <lb/>receptor RNA editing in the amygdala of serotonin transporter knockout mice. BMC <lb/>Pharmacol. 11, 3. doi:10.1186/1471-2210-11-3. <lb/>Müller, M. B., Zimmermann, S., Sillaber, I., Hagemeyer, T. P., Deussing, J. M., Timpl, P., <lb/>Kormann, M. S. D., Droste, S. K., Kühn, R., Reul, J. M. H. M., et al. (2003). Limbic <lb/>corticotropin-releasing hormone receptor 1 mediates anxiety-related behavior and <lb/>hormonal adaptation to stress. Nat Neurosci 6, 1100-1107. doi:10.1038/nn1123. <lb/>Nosek, K., Dennis, K., Andrus, B. M., Ahmadiyeh, N., Baum, A. E., Solberg Woods, L. C., <lb/>and Redei, E. E. (2008). Context and strain-dependent behavioral response to stress. <lb/>Behav Brain Funct 4, 23. doi:10.1186/1744-9081-4-23. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 27 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>Olivier, J. D. A., Van Der Hart, M. G. C., Van Swelm, R. P. L., Dederen, P. J., Homberg, J. <lb/>R., Cremers, T., Deen, P. M. T., Cuppen, E., Cools, A. R., and Ellenbroek, B. A. (2008). <lb/>A study in male and female 5-HT transporter knockout rats: an animal model for anxiety <lb/>and depression disorders. Neuroscience 152, 573-584. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.neuroscience.2007.12.032. <lb/>Onusic, G. M., Nogueira, R. L., Pereira, A. M. S., and Viana, M. B. (2002). Effect of acute <lb/>treatment with a water-alcohol extract of Erythrina mulungu on anxiety-related <lb/>responses in rats. Braz J Med Biol Res 35, 473-477. <lb/>Ouagazzal, A.-M., Moreau, J.-L., Pauly-Evers, M., and Jenck, F. (2003). Impact of <lb/>environmental housing conditions on the emotional responses of mice deficient for <lb/>nociceptin/orphanin FQ peptide precursor gene. Behav Brain Res 144, 111-117. <lb/>Owens, M. J., and Nemeroff, C. B. (1991). Physiology and pharmacology of corticotropin-<lb/>releasing factor. Pharmacol Rev 43, 425-473. <lb/>Paez-Pereda, M., Hausch, F., and Holsboer, F. (2011). Corticotropin releasing factor <lb/>receptor antagonists for major depressive disorder. Expert Opin Investig Drugs 20, 519-<lb/>535. doi:10.1517/13543784.2011.565330. <lb/>Pang, R. D., Wang, Z., Klosinski, L. P., Guo, Y., Herman, D. H., Celikel, T., Dong, H.-W., and <lb/>Holschneider, D. P. (2011). Mapping functional brain activation using [14C]-<lb/>iodoantipyrine in male serotonin transporter knockout mice. PLoS ONE 6, e23869. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0023869. <lb/>Parent, A. J., Beaudet, N., Beaudry, H., Bergeron, J., Bérubé, P., Drolet, G., Sarret, P., and <lb/>Gendron, L. (2012). Increased anxiety-like behaviors in rats experiencing chronic <lb/>inflammatory pain. Behav Brain Res 229, 160-167. doi:10.1016/j.bbr.2012.01.001. <lb/>Parks, C. L., Robinson, P. S., Sibille, E., Shenk, T., and Toth, M. (1998). Increased anxiety of <lb/>mice lacking the serotonin1A receptor. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 95, 10734-10739. <lb/>Pellow, S., Chopin, P., File, S. E., and Briley, M. (1985). Validation of open:closed arm <lb/>entries in an elevated plus-maze as a measure of anxiety in the rat. J Neurosci Methods <lb/>14, 149-167. <lb/>Perez-Caballero, L., Torres-Sanchez, S., Bravo, L., Mico, J. A., and Berrocoso, E. (2014). <lb/>Fluoxetine: a case history of its discovery and preclinical development. Expert Opin <lb/>Drug Discov 9, 567-578. doi:10.1517/17460441.2014.907790. <lb/>Powell, C. M., Schoch, S., Monteggia, L., Barrot, M., Matos, M. F., Feldmann, N., Südhof, <lb/>T. C., and Nestler, E. J. (2004). The presynaptic active zone protein RIM1alpha is critical <lb/>for normal learning and memory. Neuron 42, 143-153. <lb/>Prut, L., and Belzung, C. (2003). The open field as a paradigm to measure the effects of <lb/>drugs on anxiety-like behaviors: a review. Eur J Pharmacol 463, 3-33. <lb/>doi:10.1016/S0014-2999(03)01272-X. <lb/>Ramboz, S., Oosting, R., Amara, D. A., Kung, H. F., Blier, P., Mendelsohn, M., Mann, J. J., <lb/>Brunner, D., and Hen, R. (1998). Serotonin receptor 1A knockout: an animal model of <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 28 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>anxiety-related disorder. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 95, 14476-14481. <lb/>Reis, D. G., Scopinho, A. A., Guimarães, F. S., Corrêa, F. M. A., and Resstel, L. B. M. <lb/>(2011). Behavioral and autonomic responses to acute restraint stress are segregated <lb/>within the lateral septal area of rats. PLoS ONE 6, e23171. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0023171. <lb/>Rodgers, R. J., and Cole, J. C. (1993). Influence of social isolation, gender, strain, and prior <lb/>novelty on plus-maze behaviour in mice. Physiol Behav 54, 729-736. <lb/>Rylkova, D., Shah, H. P., Small, E., and Bruijnzeel, A. W. (2009). Deficit in brain reward <lb/>function and acute and protracted anxiety-like behavior after discontinuation of a <lb/>chronic alcohol liquid diet in rats. Psychopharmacology (Berl) 203, 629-640. <lb/>doi:10.1007/s00213-008-1409-z. <lb/>Samuels, B. A., Mendez-David, I., Faye, C., David, S. A., Pierz, K. A., Gardier, A. M., Hen, <lb/>R., and David, D. J. (2014). Serotonin 1A and Serotonin 4 Receptors: Essential <lb/>Mediators of the Neurogenic and Behavioral Actions of Antidepressants. <lb/>Neuroscientist. doi:10.1177/1073858414561303. <lb/>Santos, dos, L., de Andrade, T. G. C. S., and Graeff, F. G. (2010). Social separation and <lb/>diazepam withdrawal increase anxiety in the elevated plus-maze and serotonin turnover <lb/>in the median raphe and hippocampus. J Psychopharmacol (Oxford) 24, 725-731. <lb/>doi:10.1177/0269881109106954. <lb/>Schellinck, H. M., Stanford, L., and Darrah, M. (2003). Repetitive acute pain in infancy <lb/>increases anxiety but does not alter spatial learning ability in juvenile mice. Behav Brain <lb/>Res 142, 157-165. doi:10.1016/S0166-4328(02)00406-0. <lb/>Schipper, P., Nonkes, L. J. P., Karel, P., Kiliaan, A. J., and Homberg, J. R. (2011). Serotonin <lb/>transporter genotype x construction stress interaction in rats. Behav Brain Res 223, <lb/>169-175. doi:10.1016/j.bbr.2011.04.037. <lb/>Sena, E. S., van der Worp, H. B., Bath, P. M. W., Howells, D. W., and Macleod, M. R. <lb/>(2010). Publication bias in reports of animal stroke studies leads to major overstatement <lb/>of efficacy. PLoS Biol 8, e1000344. doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1000344. <lb/>Sherif, F., and Oreland, L. (1995). Effect of the GABA-transaminase inhibitor vigabatrin on <lb/>exploratory behaviour in socially isolated rats. Behav Brain Res 72, 135-140. <lb/>Simon, P., Dupuis, R., and Costentin, J. (1994). Thigmotaxis as an index of anxiety in mice. <lb/>Influence of dopaminergic transmissions. Behav Brain Res 61, 59-64. <lb/>Smith, G. W., Aubry, J. M., Dellu, F., Contarino, A., Bilezikjian, L. M., Gold, L. H., Chen, R., <lb/>Marchuk, Y., Hauser, C., Bentley, C. A., et al. (1998). Corticotropin releasing factor <lb/>receptor 1-deficient mice display decreased anxiety, impaired stress response, and <lb/>aberrant neuroendocrine development. Neuron 20, 1093-1102. <lb/>Sterne, J. A. C., Sutton, A. J., Ioannidis, J. P. A., Terrin, N., Jones, D. R., Lau, J., Carpenter, <lb/>J., Rücker, G., Harbord, R. M., Schmid, C. H., et al. (2011). Recommendations for <lb/>examining and interpreting funnel plot asymmetry in meta-analyses of randomised <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 29 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>controlled trials. BMJ 343, d4002. <lb/>Storm, D. R., Hansel, C., Hacker, B., Parent, A., and Linden, D. J. (1998). Impaired <lb/>cerebellar long-term potentiation in type I adenylyl cyclase mutant mice. Neuron 20, <lb/>1199-1210. <lb/>Tone, A. (2009). The Age of Anxiety: A History of America&apos;s Turbulent Affair with <lb/>Tranquilizers. New York: Basic Books. <lb/>Trimble, N., Johnson, A. C., Foster, A., and Greenwood-van Meerveld, B. (2007). <lb/>Corticotropin-releasing factor receptor mice show decreased anxiety and <lb/>colonic sensitivity. Neurogastroenterol Motil 754-760. doi:10.1111/j.1365-<lb/>2982.2007.00951.x. <lb/>van Praag, H. M. (2003). Can stress cause depression? Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol <lb/>Psychiatry 28, 891-907. doi:10.1016/j.pnpbp.2004.05.031. <lb/>Vesterinen, H. M., Sena, E. S., Egan, K. J., Hirst, T. C., Churolov, L., Currie, G. L., Antonic, <lb/>A., Howells, D. W., and Macleod, M. R. (2014). Meta-analysis of data from animal <lb/>studies: a practical guide. J Neurosci Methods 221, 92-102. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.jneumeth.2013.09.010. <lb/>Viechtbauer, W. (2010). Conducting meta-analyses in R with the metafor package. Journal <lb/>of Statistical Software 36, 1-48. Available at: http://www.jstatsoft.org/v36/i03/paper. <lb/>Vinkers, C. H., Oosting, R. S., van Bogaert, M. J. V., Olivier, B., and Groenink, L. (2010). <lb/>Early-life blockade of 5-HT(1A) receptors alters adult anxiety behavior and <lb/>benzodiazepine sensitivity. Biol Psychiatry 67, 309-316. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.biopsych.2009.08.013. <lb/>Walf, A. A., and Frye, C. A. (2012). Gestational or acute restraint in adulthood reduces levels <lb/>of 5α-reduced testosterone metabolites in the hippocampus and produces behavioral <lb/>inhibition of adult male rats. Front Cell Neurosci 6, 40. doi:10.3389/fncel.2012.00040. <lb/>Wanasuntronwong, A., Tantisira, M. H., Tantisira, B., and Watanabe, H. (2012). Anxiolytic <lb/>effects of standardized extract of Centella asiatica (ECa 233) after chronic <lb/>immobilization stress in mice. J Ethnopharmacol 143, 579-585. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.jep.2012.07.010. <lb/>Wei, X. Y., Yang, J. Y., Dong, Y. X., and Wu, C. F. (2007). Anxiolytic-like effects of oleamide <lb/>in group-housed and socially isolated mice. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol <lb/>Psychiatry 31, 1189-1195. doi:10.1016/j.pnpbp.2007.04.008. <lb/>Weninger, S. C., Dunn, A. J., Muglia, L. J., Dikkes, P., Miczek, K. A., Swiergiel, A. H., <lb/>Berridge, C. W., and Majzoub, J. A. (1999). Stress-induced behaviors require the <lb/>corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH) receptor, but not CRH. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA <lb/>96, 8283-8288. <lb/>Wright, R. C., and Ingenito, A. J. (2001). Prevention of isolation-induced hypertension by <lb/>intrahippocampal administration of a nonpeptide kappa-opioid receptor agonist. <lb/>Hippocampus 11, 445-451. doi:10.1002/hipo.1059. <lb/></listBibl>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 30 <lb/></page>

            <listBibl>Zanettini, C., Carola, V., Iacono, Lo, L., Moles, A., Gross, C., and D&apos;Amato, F. R. (2010). <lb/>Postnatal handling reverses social anxiety in serotonin receptor 1A knockout mice. <lb/>Genes Brain Behav 9, 26-32. doi:10.1111/j.1601-183X.2009.00531.x. <lb/>Zhao, S., Edwards, J., Carroll, J., Wiedholz, L., Millstein, R. A., Jaing, C., Murphy, D. L., <lb/>Lanthorn, T. H., and Holmes, A. (2006). Insertion mutation at the C-terminus of the <lb/>serotonin transporter disrupts brain serotonin function and emotion-related behaviors in <lb/>mice. Neuroscience 140, 321-334. doi:10.1016/j.neuroscience.2006.01.049. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note>

            <page>page 31 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURES AND TABLES <lb/>Figure 1. Flow chart of the systematic literature review of 10 anxiotropic interventions. <lb/>The literature was reviewed in a four-stage process, starting with a PubMed search that <lb/>yielded 792 articles, followed by three screens of increasing detail, reviewing the article <lb/>title, abstract, and full text for experimental design. A total of 91 articles were used in the <lb/>meta-analysis. Further details are given in Table 1 and the Methods section. <lb/>Figure 2. Funnel plots of five meta-analyses. <lb/>Where at least ten experiments were available for meta-analysis, the effect sizes (Hedges&apos; <lb/>g) of the experiments are plotted against their respective standard errors. Points on each <lb/>plot represent individual experiments. The triangle bounded by dotted lines indicates the <lb/>area where 95% of studies are expected to fall, in the absence of both publication bias and <lb/>study heterogeneity. <lb/>Figure 3. Meta-analysis of diazepam on rodent anxiety related behavior. <lb/>Meta-analysis of rodent diazepam effect sizes, shown as a forest plot of standardized effect <lb/>sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the 95% confidence intervals of g. The weighted <lb/>average mean effect size of all studies is represented by the central vertices of a red <lb/>diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and treatment <lb/>samples sizes (N C , N T ) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus maze <lb/>(EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). The I 2 of 41% indicates a low level of <lb/>heterogeneity. <lb/>Figure 4. Meta-analyses of serotonin receptor 1A interventions on rodent anxiety-<lb/>related behaviors. <lb/>Meta-analysis of effect sizes of serotonin-targeted interventions is shown as a forest plot of <lb/>standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the 95% confidence intervals of g. <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 32 <lb/></page>

            <body>The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by the central vertices <lb/>of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and <lb/>treatment samples sizes (N C , N T ) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus <lb/>maze (EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). Effects of: A. Serotonin receptor gene <lb/>Htr1a knockout models. B. Htr1a overexpression. <lb/>Figure 5. Meta-analyses of serotonin transporter interventions on rodent anxiety-<lb/>related behaviors. <lb/>Meta-analysis of effect sizes of serotonin-targeted interventions is shown as a forest plot of <lb/>standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the 95% confidence intervals of g. <lb/>The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by the central vertices <lb/>of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and <lb/>treatment samples sizes (N C , N T ) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus <lb/>maze (EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). Effects of: A. Serotonin transporter <lb/>gene (Htt) knockout models B. Htt overexpression models. <lb/>Figure 6. Meta-analyses of experiments on the stress-anxiety relationship in rodents. <lb/>Meta-analysis of effect sizes of stress-anxiety interventions, shown as a forest plot of <lb/>standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the 95% confidence intervals of g. <lb/>The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by the central vertices <lb/>of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and <lb/>treatment samples sizes (N C , N T ) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus <lb/>maze (EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). Effects of: A. Acute pain. B. Restraint <lb/>stress (immobilization). C. Social isolation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note>

            <page>page 33 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 7. Meta-analyses of the effects of stress signaling genes on anxiety-related <lb/>behaviors. <lb/>Meta-analysis of effect sizes of stress signaling genes, shown as a forest plot of <lb/>standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the 95% confidence intervals of g. <lb/>The weighted average mean effect of all studies is represented by the central vertices <lb/>of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and <lb/>treatment samples sizes (N C , N T ) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus <lb/>maze (EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). Effects of: A. Crh gene knockout <lb/>models. B. Crhr1 gene knockout models. <lb/>Figure 8. Meta-analyses of interventions known to be unrelated to anxiety. <lb/>Meta-analysis of effect sizes of non-anxiety-related interventions, shown as a forest plot of <lb/>standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the 95% confidence intervals of g. <lb/>The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by the central vertices <lb/>of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and <lb/>treatment samples sizes (N C , N T ) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus <lb/>maze (EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). Effects of: A. Adcy1 gene knockout <lb/>models. B. Synaptotagmin gene (Syt1) mutation models. <lb/>Figure 9. Summary effect sizes of all meta-analyses. <lb/>The weighted mean effect sizes of all 12 interventions are shown here. Each mean effect <lb/>size is represented by the central vertices of a diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% <lb/>confidence intervals. The horizontal axis is Hedges&apos; g, the standard deviation change <lb/>relative to control animals. Color indicates direction (green = anxiolytic, red = anxiogenic) <lb/>and statistical significance (grey = statistically non-significant). The diamonds for the <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Rodent anxiety meta-analyses</note> 

            <page>page 34 <lb/></page>

            <body>diazepam, social isolation, and Htt KO meta-analyses represent the summary effect sizes <lb/>after trim-and-fill bias correction. <lb/>Table 1. Summary of systematic reviews of anxiety-related interventions in mouse and <lb/>rat. <lb/>The PubMed query phrases used to identify articles that might contain data relevant to the <lb/>interventions and assays of interest are detailed. Title, abstract and full-text searches were <lb/>performed to identify articles meeting the selected criteria. Where there were fewer than <lb/>fifteen articles meeting the selection criteria, all relevant data in all articles found were used <lb/>for data extraction and meta-analysis. Where there were more articles, we took a random <lb/>sample of fifteen papers and used only relevant data therein for meta-analysis. <lb/>Table 2. Results of Egger&apos;s linear regression test for funnel plot asymmetry across six <lb/>meta-analyses <lb/>Where at least ten experiments were available for meta-analysis, Egger&apos;s linear regression <lb/>test for funnel plot asymmetry was performed. For each meta-analysis, the number of <lb/>studies included, the vertical intercept of the linear regression, the corresponding 95% <lb/>confidence interval for the intercept, and the p-value of Egger&apos;s test are listed. <lb/>Table 3. Characteristics of included experiments. <lb/>Characteristics of experiments from included studies are listed with Pubmed ID, year of <lb/>study, and figure panel. The assay type, assay duration, variable used in experiment, route <lb/>of injection, drug dosage, treatment duration, species, strain and gender are also detailed. <lb/>Assay duration and treatment duration are listed in minutes. Dosage is listed in mg per kg <lb/>body weight of animal. Cells containing NA indicate that the information is not available for <lb/>the underlying intervention. <lb/>Figure 1. Flow chart of the systematic literature review of 10 anxiotropic interventions. The <lb/>literature was reviewed in a four-stage process, starting with a PubMed search that yielded 585 <lb/>articles, followed by three screens of increasing detail, reviewing the article title, abstract, and <lb/>full text for experimental design. A total of 87 articles were used in the meta-analysis. Further <lb/>details are given in Table 1 and the Methods section. <lb/>585 articles identified in PubMed search <lb/>for 10 anxiety related interventions using <lb/>the search phrases given in Table1 <lb/>249 excluded <lb/>336 articles included <lb/>Title Screen <lb/>Abstract Screen <lb/>65 excluded <lb/>271 articles included <lb/>Full text Screen <lb/>92 excluded <lb/>179 articles included <lb/>Random sampling <lb/>87 articles in meta-analyses <lb/> 92 excluded <lb/> Figure 2: Funnel plots of six meta-analyses. A-E. Where at least fifteen studies were available for meta-analysis, <lb/>the effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g) of the experiments are plotted against their respective standard errors. Points on <lb/>plot represent individual experiments. The triangle bounded by dotted lines indicates the area where 95% of studies <lb/>are expected to fall, in the absence of both publication bias and study heterogeneity. F. Trim and fill anlysis <lb/>diazepam <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>Htr1a knockout <lb/>Htt knockout <lb/>1 <lb/>Hedges&apos; g <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Hedges&apos; g <lb/>3 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Hedges&apos; g <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Standard Error <lb/>Standard Error <lb/>Standard Error <lb/>Hedges&apos; g <lb/>E <lb/>Standard Error <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>isolation <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>F <lb/>−2 −1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>restraint <lb/>D <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>Standard Error <lb/>Hedges&apos; g <lb/>diazepam <lb/>Htt knockout <lb/>isolation <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Hedges&apos; g <lb/>corrected <lb/>(trim-and-fill) <lb/>uncorrected <lb/>diazepam g − <lb/>1 −1 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc Nt Assay <lb/>irkett 2 11 <lb/>irkett 2 11 <lb/>irkett 2 11 <lb/>on ale − 2 <lb/>oleris 2 1 <lb/>osta 2 11 <lb/>irkett 2 11 <lb/>irkett 2 11 <lb/>irkett 2 11 <lb/>nusic 2 2 <lb/>rassetto 2 1 <lb/>as eren i 2 <lb/>ain 2 <lb/>en 2 <lb/>Hui 2 2 <lb/>a uda 2 1 <lb/>oerngen− 2 <lb/>aria 1 <lb/>rioni 1 <lb/>rioni 1 <lb/>rioni 1 <lb/>rioni 1 <lb/>rioni 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>13 <lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>13 <lb/>1 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>anasuntron ong 2 12 <lb/>anasuntron ong 2 12 <lb/>anasuntron ong 2 12 <lb/>anasuntron ong 2 12 <lb/>anasuntron ong 2 12 <lb/>anasuntron ong 2 12 <lb/>Figure 3: Meta-analysis of diazepam on rodent anxiety related behavior. Meta-analysis of rodent <lb/>diazepam effect sizes, shown as a forest plot of standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate <lb/>the 95% confidence intervals of g. The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by <lb/>the central vertices of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and <lb/>treatment samples sizes (NC, NT) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus maze (EPM), <lb/>open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). The I 2 of 41% indicates a low level of heterogeneity. <lb/>Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>− <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Figure 4: Meta-analyses of serotonin receptor 5-HT1A related genetic interventions on <lb/>rodent anxiety-related behaviors. Meta-analysis of effect sizes of serotonin-targeted interven-<lb/>tions is shown as a forest plot of standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the 95% <lb/>confidence intervals of g. The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by <lb/>the central vertices of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. <lb/>Control and treatment samples sizes (NC, NT) and the assay types of the studies are given; <lb/>elevated plus maze (EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). Effects of: A. Serotonin receptor <lb/>gene Htr1a knockout models. B. Htr1a overexpression. <lb/>Ht1a-KO g = 0.68, p = 8.9 x 10 − , I 2 = 59 % <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc <lb/>Nt <lb/>Assay <lb/>Jain 2012 <lb/>Zanettini 2010 <lb/>Vinkers 2010 <lb/>Gleason 2010 <lb/>Groenink 2003 <lb/>Gross 2002 <lb/>Ramboz 1998 <lb/>Parks 1998 <lb/>Klemenhagen 2006 <lb/>Groenink 2003 <lb/>Ferres− 2 13 <lb/>reeman− 2 11 <lb/>Gleason 2010 <lb/>Groenink 2003 <lb/>Gross 2002 <lb/>Ramboz 1998 <lb/>14 <lb/>38 <lb/>11 <lb/>9 <lb/>16 <lb/>7 <lb/>20 <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>43 <lb/>9 <lb/>8 <lb/>7 <lb/>25 <lb/>14 <lb/>34 <lb/>11 <lb/>9 <lb/>16 <lb/>7 <lb/>20 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>39 <lb/>9 <lb/>8 <lb/>7 <lb/>25 <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>A <lb/>−2 −1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>ifference from controls (S ) <lb/>2 <lb/>Ht1a-OE g − 2 <lb/>1 2 = 79 % <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc <lb/>Nt <lb/>Assay <lb/>Audero 2013 <lb/>Kusserow 2004 <lb/>Audero 2013 <lb/>Bert 2006 <lb/>Bert 2006 <lb/>Kusserow 2004 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>11 <lb/>13 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>15 <lb/>13 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>B <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>ifference from controls (S ) <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>A <lb/>Htt KO g <lb/>2 1 −1 , I 2 = 54.6 % <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc <lb/>Nt <lb/>Assay <lb/>ang 2 11 <lb/>o a 2 11 <lb/>Olivier 2008 <lb/>Kalueff 2007 <lb/>Kalueff 2007 <lb/>Kalueff 2007 <lb/>Carroll 2007 <lb/>Zhao 2006 <lb/>Zhao 2006 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Carroll 2007 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Sc i er 2 11 <lb/>ine 2 11 <lb/>Olivier 2008 <lb/>Kalueff 2007 <lb/>Kalueff 2007 <lb/>Carroll 2007 <lb/>Li 2004 <lb/>Lira 2003 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>Holmes 2003 <lb/>25 <lb/> 1 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>8 <lb/>30 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>30 <lb/>1 <lb/>13 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>9 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>30 <lb/>11 <lb/>20 <lb/>1 <lb/>13 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/> 1 <lb/>28 <lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>7 <lb/>29 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>29 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>7 <lb/>12 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>29 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/> OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>LD <lb/> LD <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Htt OE g − <lb/>1 2 = 47 % <lb/>Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc <lb/>Nt <lb/>Assay <lb/>Jennings 2006.2 <lb/>ine 2 11 <lb/>Jennings 2006 <lb/>Jennings 2006 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>OF <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 5: Meta-analyses of Serotonin transporter related genetic interventions on rodent <lb/>anxiety-related behaviors. Meta-analysis of effect sizes of serotonin-targeted interventions is <lb/>shown as a forest plot of standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the 95% confi-<lb/>dence intervals of g. The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by the <lb/>central vertices of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control <lb/>and treatment samples sizes (NC, NT) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus <lb/>maze (EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). Effects of: A. Serotonin transporter gene (Htt) <lb/>knockout models.. B. Htt overexpression models. <lb/>Figure 6: Meta-analyses of experiments on the stress-anxiety relationship in rodents. Meta-analysis of effect sizes of <lb/>stress-anxiety interventions, shown as a forest plot of standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the 95% <lb/>confidence intervals of g. The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by the central vertices of a <lb/>red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and treatment samples sizes (NC, NT) and <lb/>the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus maze (EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark box (LD). Effects of: A. <lb/>Acute pain. B. Restraint stress (immobilization). C. Social isolation. <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>acute pain g 1 <lb/>1 −1 2 = 0 % <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc Nt Assay <lb/>Parent 2 12 <lb/>Matsuzawa 2 <lb/>Parent 2 12 <lb/>eite 2 <lb/>Matsuzawa 2 <lb/>en ou id 2 <lb/>Schellinck 2003 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>OF <lb/>LD <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>A <lb/>Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>B Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>Abramo 2 <lb/>Abramo 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>Isolation g <lb/>3 <lb/>1 -2 <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc Nt Assay <lb/>Hermes 2 11 <lb/>ukkes <lb/>2 <lb/>ei <lb/>2 <lb/>uen a 2 12 <lb/>dos Santos 2 1 <lb/>oike H 2 <lb/>oike H 2 <lb/>ei <lb/>2 <lb/>Moragrega 2003 <lb/>Majercsik 2003 <lb/>Majercsik 2003 <lb/>Majercsik 2003 <lb/>Majercsik 2003 <lb/>Majercsik 2003 <lb/>Majercsik 2003 <lb/>Majercsik 2003 <lb/>rig t 2 1 <lb/>a i <lb/>2 1 <lb/>a i 2 1 <lb/>eeta S 2 1 <lb/>eeta S 2 1 <lb/>eeta S 2 1 <lb/>ledno 2 1 <lb/>Haller J 2000 <lb/>Haller J 2000 <lb/>odgers 1 3 <lb/>odgers 1 3 <lb/>odgers 1 3 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>32 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>32 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>33 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>LD <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>C <lb/>Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>restraint g <lb/>3 2 <lb/>−2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc Nt <lb/>Assay <lb/>es ort 2 12 <lb/>es ort 2 12 <lb/>osek 2 <lb/>osek 2 <lb/>Ouagazzal 2003 <lb/>iu 2 13 <lb/>usnardo 2 13 <lb/>alf 2 12 <lb/>nand 2 12 <lb/>eis 2 11 <lb/>ran eiro 2 11 <lb/>lko a 2 <lb/>osek 2 <lb/>osek 2 <lb/>occ i 2 <lb/>Hsu 2 <lb/>Hsu 2 <lb/>Estanislau 2 <lb/>unga 2 <lb/>ar a al 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>LD <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>Figure 7: Meta-analyses of the effects of stress signaling genes on anxiety-related behaviors. Meta-analysis <lb/>of effect sizes of stress signaling genes, shown as a forest plot of standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars <lb/>indicate the 95% confidence intervals of g. The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by <lb/>the central vertices of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and treat-<lb/>ment samples sizes (NC, NT) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus maze (EPM), open field <lb/>(OF) and light-dark box (LD). Effects of: A. Crh gene knockout models. B. Crhr1 gene knockout models. <lb/>−1 <lb/>− <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Crh−KO g <lb/>3 <lb/>3 2 <lb/>Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc <lb/>Nt Assay <lb/>eninger 1 <lb/>unn 1 <lb/>12 <lb/>8 <lb/>12 EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>A <lb/>Crhr1−KO g −1 <lb/>1 −11 2 <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc <lb/>Nt Assay <lb/>uller 2 3 <lb/>Smit 1 <lb/>rim le 2 <lb/>ammie 2 <lb/>uller 2 3 <lb/>ie sc 1 <lb/>Smit 1 <lb/>ie sc 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>21 <lb/>2 <lb/>8 <lb/>11 <lb/>LD <lb/>LD <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>EPM <lb/>B <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>Figure 8: Interventions with no effect on anxiety-related behaviors. Meta-analysis of effect sizes of non-<lb/>anxiety-related interventions, shown as a forest plot of standardized effect sizes (Hedges&apos; g). Error bars indicate the <lb/>95% confidence intervals of g. The weighted average mean effect size of all studies is represented by the central <lb/>vertices of a red diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. Control and treatment samples <lb/>sizes (NC, NT) and the assay types of the studies are given; elevated plus maze (EPM), open field (OF) and light-dark <lb/>box (LD). Effects of: A. Adcy1 gene knockout models. B. Synaptotagmin gene (Syt1) mutation models. <lb/>AC1−KO g = 0.24, p = 0.28, I 2 = 0 % <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc Nt Assay <lb/>Krishnan V 2008 <lb/>Storm DR 1998 <lb/>Krishnan V 2008 <lb/>Krishnan V 2008 <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>8 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>OF <lb/>OF <lb/>LD <lb/>EPM <lb/>A <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Syt1−KO g − 2 <lb/>2 2 = 0 % <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>−1 <lb/>− <lb/>0.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Nc Nt Assay <lb/>Powell CM 2004 <lb/>Powell CM 2004 <lb/>24 <lb/>1 <lb/>20 <lb/>19 <lb/>LD <lb/>EPM <lb/>B <lb/>Difference from controls (SD) <lb/>
            Crhr1 KO <lb/>Htt OE <lb/>Diazepam <lb/>Htr1a OE <lb/>Syt1 KO <lb/>Isolation <lb/>Ac1 KO <lb/>Crh KO <lb/>Htt KO <lb/>Htr1a KO <lb/>Restraint <lb/>Acute Pain <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>Anxiolytic <lb/>g <lb/>Anxiogenic <lb/>Figure 9. Summary effect sizes of all meta-analyses. The weighted mean effect sizes <lb/>of all 12 interventions are shown here. Each mean effect size is represented by the central <lb/>vertices of a diamond; the outer vertices indicate the 95% confidence intervals. The hori-<lb/>ontal a is is Hedges&apos; g, the standard deviation change relative to control animals. Color <lb/>indicates direction (green = anxiolytic, red = anxiogenic) and statistical significance (grey <lb/>= statistically non-significant). The diamonds for the diazepam, social isolation, and Htt KO <lb/>meta-analyses represent the summary effect sizes after trim-and-fill bias correction. <lb/>Table 1. Summary of systematic reviews of anxiety-related interventions in mouse and rat. The <lb/>PubMed query phrases used to identify articles that might contain data relevant to the interventions and <lb/>assays of interest are detailed. Title, abstract and full-text searches were performed to identify articles <lb/>meeting the selected criteria. Where there were fewer than ten articles meeting the selection criteria, all <lb/>relevant data in all articles found were used for data extraction and meta-analysis. Where there were <lb/>more articles, we took a random sample of ten papers and used only relevant data therein for meta-<lb/>analysis. <lb/>Intervention <lb/>Table 1. Summary of systematic reviews of anxiety-related interventions in mouse and rat. The <lb/>PubMed query phrases used to identify articles that might contain data relevant to the interventions and <lb/>assays of interest are detailed. Title, abstract and full-text searches were performed to identify articles <lb/>meeting the selected criteria. Where there were fewer than ten articles meeting the selection criteria, all <lb/>relevant data in all articles found were used for data extraction and meta-analysis. Where there were <lb/>more articles, we took a random sample of ten papers and used only relevant data therein for meta-<lb/>analysis. <lb/>Table 1. Summary of systematic reviews of anxiety-related interventions in mouse and rat. The <lb/>PubMed query phrases used to identify articles that might contain data relevant to the interventions and <lb/>assays of interest are detailed. Title, abstract and full-text searches were performed to identify articles <lb/>meeting the selected criteria. Where there were fewer than ten articles meeting the selection criteria, all <lb/>relevant data in all articles found were used for data extraction and meta-analysis. Where there were <lb/>more articles, we took a random sample of ten papers and used only relevant data therein for meta-<lb/>analysis. <lb/>Table 1. Summary of systematic reviews of anxiety-related interventions in mouse and rat. The <lb/>PubMed query phrases used to identify articles that might contain data relevant to the interventions and <lb/>assays of interest are detailed. Title, abstract and full-text searches were performed to identify articles <lb/>meeting the selected criteria. Where there were fewer than ten articles meeting the selection criteria, all <lb/>relevant data in all articles found were used for data extraction and meta-analysis. Where there were <lb/>more articles, we took a random sample of ten papers and used only relevant data therein for meta-<lb/>analysis. <lb/>Table 1. Summary of systematic reviews of anxiety-related interventions in mouse and rat. The <lb/>PubMed query phrases used to identify articles that might contain data relevant to the interventions and <lb/>assays of interest are detailed. Title, abstract and full-text searches were performed to identify articles <lb/>meeting the selected criteria. Where there were fewer than ten articles meeting the selection criteria, all <lb/>relevant data in all articles found were used for data extraction and meta-analysis. Where there were <lb/>more articles, we took a random sample of ten papers and used only relevant data therein for meta-<lb/>analysis. <lb/>Query phrase used in PubMed for study selection <lb/>Articles <lb/>identified <lb/>by <lb/>phrase <lb/>Articles <lb/>meeting <lb/>criteria <lb/>Articles <lb/>in meta-<lb/>analysis <lb/>Diazepam <lb/>Ht1a knockout <lb/>Ht1a over-expression <lb/>Htt knockout <lb/>Htt over-expression <lb/>Pain <lb/>Restraint <lb/>Isolation <lb/>Adcy1 knockout <lb/>Synaptotagmin <lb/>(acute diazepam AND anxiety)) AND ((elevated plus <lb/>maze OR open field OR light-dark) AND (rats OR rat OR <lb/>mice OR mouse OR Mus) <lb/>96 <lb/>61 <lb/>15 <lb/>(serotonin1A receptor OR 5-HT1A receptor AND <lb/>knockout AND anxiety) <lb/>77 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>(serotonin1A receptor) OR 5-HT1A receptor) AND (over-<lb/>expression OR over-expression OR over-expressing) <lb/>AND anxiety <lb/>13 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>(serotonin transporter knockout OR knockdown OR <lb/>deletion OR antisense AND anxiety AND (elevated plus <lb/>maze OR open field OR light-dark) AND (rats OR rat OR <lb/>mice OR mouse OR Mus) <lb/>27 <lb/>13 <lb/>13 <lb/>(serotonin transporter AND anxiety AND (elevated plus <lb/>maze OR open field OR light-dark) AND (increased OR <lb/>over-expression OR overexpressing OR transgenic)) <lb/>AND (rats OR rat OR mice OR mouse OR Mus) <lb/>13 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>(Inflammatory pain AND anxiety OR neuropathic pain <lb/>AND anxiety AND (elevated plus maze OR open field OR <lb/>light-dark))) AND (rats OR rat OR mice OR mouse OR <lb/>Mus) <lb/>42 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>(acute restraint AND anxiety AND (elevated plus maze <lb/>OR open field OR light-dark) AND (rats OR rat OR mice <lb/>OR mouse OR Mus) <lb/>75 <lb/>15 <lb/>15 <lb/>(social Isolation OR single housing)) AND anxiety) AND <lb/>(elevated plus maze OR plus-maze OR open field OR <lb/>OFT OR light-dark)) AND (rats OR rat OR mice OR <lb/>mouse OR Mus) <lb/>147 <lb/>65 <lb/>15 <lb/>Ad hoc literature search <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>Ad hoc literature search <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Crh knockout <lb/>Crhr1 knockout <lb/>(CRF OR CRH OR Corticotropin releasing factor AND <lb/>knockout AND anxiety AND (elevated plus maze OR <lb/>open field OR light-dark))) AND (rats OR rat OR mice OR <lb/>mouse OR Mus) <lb/>34 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>(Corticotropin releasing factor receptor 1-deficient mice) <lb/>OR CRH1 receptor antisense oligodeoxynucleotide OR <lb/>Crhr1 null mutants OR Corticotropin-releasing hormone <lb/>receptor antisense) <lb/>61 <lb/>6 <lb/> 6 <lb/> Intercept [95% CI] <lb/>P-value <lb/>Hedges&apos; g [95% CI] <lb/>P-value <lb/>Studies <lb/>Added <lb/>Hedges&apos; g [95% CI] P-value <lb/>Diazepam <lb/>29 <lb/>-5.33 [ -7.97 --2.69 ] <lb/>5.0 X 10 -4 <lb/>-0.89 [ -1.12 --0.66 ] <lb/>4.07 X 10 <lb/>-14 <lb/>8 <lb/>-0.64 [ -0.91 --0.37 ] <lb/>2.56 X 10 <lb/>-6 <lb/>5HT1A KO <lb/>16 <lb/>1.43 [ -0.59 -3.45 ] <lb/>0.19 <lb/>Social Isolation <lb/>30 <lb/>2.22 [ 0.45 -3.99 ] <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.37 [ 0.15 -0.58 ] <lb/>7.87 X 10 -4 <lb/>7 <lb/>0.15 [ -0.10 -0.40 ] <lb/>0.24 <lb/>mSerT KO <lb/>29 <lb/>3.83 [ 2.48 -5.18 ] <lb/>6.7 X 10 -6 <lb/>0.88 [ 0.65 -1.10 ] <lb/>5.18 X 10 -14 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.57 [ 0.29 -0.86 ] <lb/>9.71 X 10 -5 <lb/>Restraint <lb/>20 <lb/>2.93 [ -0.34 -6.19 ] <lb/>0.096 <lb/>Table 2: Results of Egger&apos;s Linear Regression Test and Trim-and-fill for 5 Meta-Analyses <lb/>N.A. <lb/>After trim-and-fill <lb/>N.A. <lb/>Meta-analysis <lb/>No. of <lb/>Experiments <lb/>Egger&apos;s Linear Regression Test <lb/>Original (before trim-and-fill) <lb/>S o n ere are t e results of Egger&apos;s est and t e trim-and-fill o eration for meta-anal ses t at ad 1 studies or <lb/>Egger&apos;s est -alues <lb/>are s o n in bold or t e trim-and-fill o eration t e effect si e for 3 meta-anal ses are <lb/>s o n efore and after trim-and-fill as erformed <lb/>t t e m not a le to im ute ne studies to <lb/>eliminate or reduce a non-negati e linear interce t </body>


	</text>
</tei>
