<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>High Frequency Haplotypes are Expected Events, not Historical Figures <lb/>Elsa G. Guillot 1 and Murray P. Cox 1,* <lb/>1 Statistics and Bioinformatics Group, Institute of Fundamental Sciences, Massey <lb/>University, Palmerston North, New Zealand <lb/>* Corresponding author <lb/>Contact: <lb/>Institute of Fundamental Sciences <lb/>Massey University <lb/>Private Bag 11 222 <lb/>Palmerston North 4442 <lb/>New Zealand <lb/>Email: m.p.cox@massey.ac.nz <lb/>Phone: +64-6-356 9099 x84747 <lb/>Fax: +64-6-350 5682 <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Cultural transmission of reproductive success states that successful men have more <lb/>children and pass this higher fecundity on to their offspring. Observed in modern <lb/>human populations from genealogies and surname studies 1 , in a genetic setting <lb/>cultural transmission of reproductive success would cause particular male lines to <lb/>dominate on the Y chromosome. Balaresque and colleagues 2 interrogated a Y <lb/>chromosome dataset from Central Asia to determine whether they could reconstruct <lb/>historic instances of this behavior. Screening 8 microsatellites on the Y chromosome <lb/>in 5,321 Central Asian men (distribution in Figure 1), they identified 15 haplotypes <lb/>that were &apos;unusually frequent,&apos; which they defined as those haplotypes carried by <lb/>more than 20 men (grey bars). The authors connect these lineages to prominent <lb/>historical figures, including Genghis Khan and Giocangga. <lb/>However, high frequency haplotypes are expected simply by chance. In neutrally <lb/>evolving systems, haplotype frequency distributions follow a Zipfian power law 3 : <lb/>most lineages are carried by only a few men (Figure 1, left side), while a small <lb/>number of lineages are carried by many men (Figure 1, right side). The observed Y <lb/>chromosome distribution follows a power law, thus providing strong preliminary <lb/>evidence that this Y chromosome dataset is selectively neutral. However, to more <lb/>explicitly test whether the observed high frequency haplotypes are actually unusually <lb/>frequent, we simulated genetic data under the standard coalescent, a neutral model <lb/>that does not include cultural transmission of reproductive success. We modeled the <lb/>evolution of 5,321 Y chromosomes, each carrying 8 fully linked microsatellites, to <lb/>match the observed data. The code for these simulations, including details of <lb/>parameter values, is available online 4 . Simulations were first run across a sweep of θ <lb/>values to find the best match with the observed Y chromosome data. The least squares <lb/>fit between observed and simulated distributions was minimized at θ = 131, so one <lb/>million simulations were run at this value. We found that 27.2% of the simulations <lb/>contain 15 or more haplotypes carried by more than 20 men, thus illustrating that such <lb/>high frequency haplotypes are actually quite common. The observed Y chromosome <lb/>haplotype frequency distribution clearly falls within the 95% confidence intervals of <lb/>the simulations (Figure 1, red shading). <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>The most parsimonious explanation is therefore that the high frequency haplotypes <lb/>observed in Central Asia are simply expected chance events, and an explanation <lb/>invoking cultural transmission of reproductive success is not necessary to account for <lb/>them. As no other evidence is presented to support proposed links to famous historical <lb/>men, these haplotypes instead most likely reflect the chance proliferation of random <lb/>male lines, probably from historically unrecorded, culturally undistinguished, but <lb/>biologically lucky Central Asian men. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 Kolk M: Multigenerational transmission of family size in contemporary Sweden. <lb/>Popul Stud 2014; 68: 111-129. http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00324728.2013.819112 <lb/>2 Balaresque P, Poulet N, Cussat-Blanc S et al: Y-chromosome descent clusters and <lb/>male differential reproductive success: Young lineage expansions dominate Asian <lb/>pastoral nomadic populations. Eur J Hum Genet 2015; In Press. <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ejhg.2014.285 <lb/>3 Berestycki J, Berestycki N, Limic V: Asymptotic sampling formulae for Λ-<lb/>coalescents. Ann I H Poincaré-Pr 2014; 50: 715-731. <lb/>http://projecteuclid.org/euclid.aihp/1403276996 <lb/>4 http://elzaguillot.github.io/Allele-Frequency-Spectrum-simulations <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1 Microsatellite haplotype frequency distribution. The distribution (black <lb/>and grey bars) is identical to Figure 2 of Balaresque et al 2 . Grey bars indicate <lb/>the 15 haplotypes that are described as &apos;unusually frequent.&apos; Red shading <lb/>indicates the 95% confidence intervals of haplotype frequencies from one million <lb/>simulations. All of the high frequency haplotypes (grey bars) fall within these <lb/>95% confidence bounds. <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ + + <lb/>+ + <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ + + + + <lb/>+ + <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ + <lb/>++ ++ + <lb/>+ <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>50 100 <lb/>500 <lb/>Haplotype frequency <lb/>Number of events (log) </body>


	</text>
</tei>
