<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Title: <lb/>How many dinosaur species were there? <lb/>True richness estimated using a Poisson sampling model (TRiPS) <lb/>Jostein Starrfelt* 1 and Lee Hsiang Liow 1 <lb/>1 Centre for Ecological and Evolutionary Synthesis, Department of Biosciences, University of Oslo, <lb/>Norway, P.O. Box 1066 Blindern, NO-0316 OSLO, Norway. <lb/>*Corresponding author. Email: jostein.starrfelt@ibv.uio.no <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The fossil record is a rich source of information about biological diversity in the past. However, the fossil <lb/>record is not only incomplete but has inherent biases due to geological, physical, chemical and biological <lb/>factors such that not all individuals or species are equally likely to be discovered at any point in time or <lb/>space. In order to use the fossil record to reconstruct temporal dynamics of diversity, biased sampling <lb/>must be explicitly taken into account. Here, we introduce an approach that utilizes the variation in the <lb/>number of times each species is observed in the fossil record to estimate both sampling bias and true <lb/>richness. We term our technique TRiPS (True Richness estimated using a Poisson Sampling model) and <lb/>explore its robustness to violation of its assumptions via simulations before applying it to an empirical <lb/>dataset. We then venture to estimate sampling bias and absolute species richness of dinosaurs in the <lb/>geological stages of the Mesozoic. Using TRiPS, we present new estimates of species richness trajectories <lb/>of the three major dinosaur clades; the sauropods, ornithischians and theropods, casting doubt on the <lb/>Jurassic-Cretaceous extinction event and demonstrating that all dinosaur groups are subject to <lb/>considerable sampling bias throughout the Mesozoic. <lb/>Keywords: Dinosauria, Poisson, taxonomic richness, fossil record, sampling bias, Ornithischia, <lb/>Sauropodomorpha, Theropoda, diversity curve. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>One of the main goals of paleobiology is to reconstruct diversity using information from the fossil record. <lb/>While the patterns of diversity in space and through time are interesting in themselves, understanding the <lb/>dynamics of taxon richness is also the first step in elucidating the biotic and abiotic forces that shape the <lb/>spatial and temporal variation in taxon diversity. In other words, we need an accurate picture of patterns <lb/>of past diversity to understand processes that operate on long time scales. As in all study systems where <lb/>data samples in themselves cannot be assumed a complete picture of the underlying population, richness <lb/>studies based on the fossil record must consider the incompleteness of the fossil record. <lb/>Not all organisms enter the fossil record or have the same potential of doing so. Once created, a fossil <lb/>record (a physical record of the existence of organisms that were alive in the past) is subject to eternal <lb/>loss through erosion, subduction and other physical processes. Whether or not a fossilized organism can <lb/>be found is also affected by variability in outcrop accessibility. Last but not least, sampling intensity <lb/>encompassing factors including academic/commercial interest, geographic location and sampling design <lb/>also influence information from the fossil record we have access to. While some of these factors <lb/>contribute to noise in our inference of historical patterns and processes, and thus only cloud biological <lb/>signals, some may cause systematic bias so as to yield misleading results if the data are interpreted at face <lb/>value or with inappropriate methods. <lb/>Several classes of approaches for estimating richness using an incomplete fossil record have been <lb/>developed. These might be loosely grouped into subsampling approaches, phylogenetic corrections and <lb/>residual approaches. It is not our purpose to give a full overview of the approaches available, which have <lb/>variously been reviewed elsewhere (see e.g. 1,2), but we briefly describe these in order to clarify why we <lb/>have developed a new approach here. Subsampling approaches, including rarefaction (reviewed in 1) and <lb/>SQS (3,4), attempt to standardize temporal (or spatial) samples so as to achieve comparable relative <lb/>richness across samples. Phylogenetic approaches use phylogenetic hypotheses of the clade in question to <lb/>infer ghost lineages that are not observed in the fossil record but did exist as implied by the given <lb/>phylogenetic hypothesis (5). These ghost lineages are thus assumed to give a minimum estimate of the <lb/>lineages we have failed to observe in the fossil record. The residual approach (see also many chapters in <lb/>McGowan &amp; Smith 2,6,7) assumes that a given proxy for sampling (e.g. outcrop area or number of fossil <lb/>bearing collections) captures the biases that might influence our observations and uses that to model how <lb/>a completely sampling-driven signal would appear. Deviations from such a model are thought to reveal <lb/>the real troughs and peaks in richness. In all of these three approaches, we can only hope to estimate <lb/>relative richness through time and not true richness. Additionally, none of these approaches attempts to <lb/>estimate the bias itself, i.e. the differential sampling across time, space or taxa. Without an estimate of <lb/>sampling bias that is separate from richness estimates, it is not possible to use these approaches to shed <lb/>light on the Common Cause Hypothesis; where a common factor affects both biological dynamics and <lb/>sampling (8,9). <lb/>Here, we introduce an approach that explicitly models the sampling process while estimating richness, <lb/>using multiple observations of fossils belonging to an organismal group. We named it TRiPS (True <lb/>Richness estimated using a Poisson Sampling model). While we and others have used the simultaneous <lb/>estimation of extinction, speciation and sampling processes to study diversification processes (10-13), <lb/>there has not been a direct attempt to use multiple observations of fossil species to estimate true richness, <lb/>rather than relative richness,while simultaneously and explicitly estimating sampling, as far as we are <lb/>aware. Specifically, TRiPS assumes that a particular species, if observed multiple times in a given time <lb/>interval, has a relatively high probability of fossilization and modern day discovery. We use this type of <lb/>information across related species that are likely to have similar fossilization potential and modern day <lb/>discovery rates to estimate the number of species we might be missing and hence the true number of <lb/>
			species that might have existed. <lb/>Dinosaurs are used as an example to illustrate our approach, not least because there is a lot of interest in <lb/>estimating the both the absolute (14-16) and relative temporal richness (17-21) of dinosaur taxa. As <lb/>earlier analyses suggests that the three major dinosaur groups Sauropodomorpha, Ornithischia and <lb/>Theropoda exhibit both different diversity dynamics and differential impact of sampling bias (e.g. 7,22), <lb/>we estimate sampling rates and true richness for all dinosaurs as well as these groups independently. We <lb/>present stage-specific dinosaur sampling rates (i.e. bias) and dinosaur species richness through the <lb/>Mesozoic as estimated from TRiPS, compare our estimates with those discussed in the literature and <lb/>present simulations that explore the power of our approach and the sensitivity of TRiPS to violations of <lb/>key assumptions. <lb/>Methods and data. <lb/>Data <lb/>We downloaded records of Dinosauria, Ornithischia, Sauropodomorpha and Theropoda separately from <lb/>the Paleobiology Database (PaleoDB, https://paleobiodb.org/#/, download August 13 th 2015) using the R <lb/>toolbox paleobioDB (23). Each row of data downloaded from the PaleoDB is associated with an observed <lb/>taxon, its location and age range, and their metadata. Only data where identifications were made to the <lb/>species level and where reported age ranges were specified to stage level were in used in our subsequent <lb/>analyses. Note that while most of the Dinosauria records were assigned to Ornithischia, <lb/>Sauropodomorpha or Theropoda, 179 occurrences representing 67 species are not associated with any of <lb/>these groupings. We summarize the data in Table 1 but also supply the raw data we downloaded as <lb/>supporting information. For each species we tallied the number of observations in each stage in the <lb/>Mesozoic, generating an observation count matrix. The reported age range of a given record can span <lb/>several geological stages. In such cases, we assigned a stage within its age range with a probability that is <lb/>proportional to the duration of those stages. Because of this random assignment of records to stages <lb/>within the given age range, we performed TRiPS analyses (described below) on 100 replicated occurrence <lb/>count matrices and used the median estimated sampling rate for species richness estimation. We also <lb/>analyzed genus level data but because both richness and sampling dynamics are similar to species level <lb/>dynamics, we refer readers to the SI for genus level estimates. <lb/>Model: Fossil sampling as a Poisson process <lb/>Here, we treat the process of fossil sampling, which we will estimate from records from the PaleoDB (see <lb/>previous section) as the combined processes of fossilization and detection. We assume that sampling can <lb/>be viewed as a homogenous Poisson process inside a particular time interval. For our data, the Poisson <lb/>intensity or rate at which species are sampled is assumed constant for the duration of a geological stage. <lb/>Formally, let the Poisson intensity λ t be the parameter controlling the sampling process in a given time <lb/>interval t. The number of observations O i,t for a species i in that time interval t with duration d t has a <lb/>Poisson distribution with mean λ t d t . The likelihood of the sampling rate λ t given O i,t occurrences in that <lb/>interval is then <lb/>| , , <lb/>= <lb/>, <lb/>, ! <lb/>(1) <lb/>Here we explicitly assume that a species detected in a time interval is extant during that whole time <lb/>interval. Because any species that is represented in the database must have left at least one detected fossil <lb/>we must condition the likelihood of λ t on O i,t &gt; 0. The likelihood of λ t is then <lb/>| , , <lb/>= <lb/>, <lb/>, ! <lb/>1 − <lb/>(2) <lb/>The maximum likelihood estimate for the sampling rate of a group of species in a given interval is found <lb/>by maximizing the product of eq (2) over all the observed species (n t ) belonging to that group; <lb/>= max <lb/>, <lb/>, ! <lb/>1 − <lb/>(3) <lb/>If our data consist of only single records (i.e. O i,t = 1, for all i), estimating using maximum likelihood <lb/>will yield an estimate of 0. Hence, the minimum data requirement for estimating the fossilization rate is a <lb/>dataset where at least one of the species has more than one observation. <lb/>We assume that sampling rates estimated are constant for all species within a clade in the same time <lb/>interval (i.e. the sampling rates estimated are time-specific but not species-specific). We can then <lb/>
			estimate the probability of detecting a species from this group as 1-Poiss(0, *dt), i.e. 1 minus the <lb/>probability of not detecting a species if it was actually extant, according to the Poisson process. We <lb/>further use this binomial probability in deriving the most likely true richness. The binomial probability of <lb/>a species sampled during an interval d t is <lb/>! &quot; #$, = 1 − %&amp;&apos;(( 0, <lb/>= 1 − <lb/>* <lb/>(4) <lb/>where Poiss(0, d t ) is the probability of 0 sampling events in one lineage with a rate in a bin of <lb/>duration d t . The last step in estimating the true richness in a given time interval is to find the true species <lb/>richness (n true ) that maximizes the binomial likelihood <lb/>+ ,-. | ! &quot; #$, , + = / <lb/>+ ,-. <lb/>+ 0 ! &quot; #$, <lb/>1 − ! &quot; #$, <lb/>123 <lb/>(5) <lb/>where p binom,t is the binomial probability calculated from the estimated sampling intensity (eq 4) using <lb/>maximum likelihood (eq 3) and n t is the observed number of species in the time interval. Thus the value <lb/>n true that maximizes eq 5 is the maximum likelihood estimate of the true richness where n t species were <lb/>observed. <lb/>To quantify the uncertainty surrounding the estimate of the sampling rate and the true species richness we <lb/>utilize the relationship between the χ 2 distribution and log likelihood profiles (see e.g. 24). For the <lb/>confidence bounds on the maximum likelihood estimate we find the range of values for λ that satisfy <lb/>the inequality <lb/>2 /log / 8 | , , <lb/>0 − log / <lb/>| , , <lb/>00 &lt; : ; &lt; <lb/>(6) <lb/>where : ; &lt; is the upper quantile function of the χ 2 distribution with 1 degree of freedom. Similarly the <lb/>upper and lower confidence bounds for the estimated true richness + ,-. is found using the lower and <lb/>upper confidence bounds on the sampling probability (p binom,t ) summarizing the uncertainty surrounding <lb/>both sampling and richness estimates. <lb/>TRiPS thus yields maximum likelihood estimates and confidence intervals of true species richness for a <lb/>given time interval by estimating a sampling rate (detected fossils per species per million year). This <lb/>sampling rate can be transformed into a time interval specific sampling probability (probability of fossil <lb/>detection per species) and thereby appropriately take the duration of time interval into account. In other <lb/>words, we do not need to conform the data to equal durations as commonly done (18,e.g. 25). The <lb/>sampling rates estimated from TRiPS are thus directly comparable across unequal geological intervals. <lb/>Note that while we have described TRiPS using species observations it can also be directly applied to <lb/>genera or lineages defined in other ways. In fact, groupings believed to exhibit similar sampling rates <lb/>might be combined, whether or not they actually are taxonomic clades. <lb/>We estimate the sampling rates and richness for all dinosaurs and Ornithischia, Sauropodomorpha and <lb/>Theropoda in each geological stage in the Mesozoic, data permitting. <lb/>Simulations using a birth-death-fossilization process <lb/>To evaluate our method&apos;s applicability and power we performed a large number of continuous time birth-<lb/>death (BD) simulations, coupled with a fossilization scheme, which we interpret as sampling. In a classic <lb/>BD process a lineage either gives rise to a new species or goes extinct at a certain rate; our fossilization <lb/>scheme adds a third potential event: that of a lineage leaving a fossil. We are thus simulating a &apos;fossil <lb/>record&apos; given a set of parameters controlling the dynamics and sampling of the simulated clade, and then <lb/>using TRiPS to estimate the true number of species in these simulations. Our birth-death-fossilize model <lb/>has 6 parameters which we all will vary; speciation and extinction rate (in per species per time unit), <lb/>sampling rate (fossils per species per time unit), number of species at the start of the simulation and <lb/>number of time units (in continuous time) to run the simulation. The final parameter scales the variability <lb/>of sampling rates between individual species; where the sampling rate is a clade mean and each species <lb/>has a sampling rate drawn from a normal distribution with a given coefficient of variation. For our <lb/>simulations these 6 parameters were either set to zero or drawn from a given distribution. <lb/>In case of no biological dynamics and identical sampling rates for all lineages TRiPS will consistently <lb/>recover true richness. In two rounds of simulations, we explicitly investigate the robustness of our <lb/>approach to violations of TRiPS&apos;s two main assumptions, 1) equal sampling rates for all species in the <lb/>clade in question and 2) and negligible species turnover within a time interval. We then use the results of <lb/>our simulations to aid interpretation of our estimates based on dinosaur records. <lb/>In the first round of simulations speciation and extinction rates were set to 0 (i.e. no changes in species <lb/>richness), durations of time simulated ranged from 1 to 20 time units (uniform distribution), the number <lb/>of species between 10 and 500 (uniform distribution), mean sampling rates from 0.002 to 1.5 fossils per <lb/>species per time unit (log uniform distribution), coefficient of variation of sampling rate across species <lb/>from 0 to 0.1 (uniform distribution). Each species thus has its own unique sampling rate drawn from a <lb/>normal distribution with means and variance differing across simulations. We ran 1000 simulations in this <lb/>set. <lb/>
			The second round of simulations we simulated BD process with speciation and extinction rates &gt; 0 which <lb/>leads to species turnover. Speciation and extinction rates were drawn from log-uniform distributions <lb/>spanning 0.005 to 0.158 per species per time unit and interval durations ranging from 2 to 20 time units <lb/>(uniform distribution). The number of initial species was also varied in the range 10 through 250 (uniform <lb/>distribution). Mean sampling rates of all species were allowed to vary from 0.01 to 0.5 fossils per species <lb/>per time unit (log uniform). As in the first round, we also varied the variability in sampling across species <lb/>within a simulation (coefficient of variation in the range 0 to 0.1, uniform distribution). We ran 100.000 <lb/>simulations in which the parameter values were sampled using a latin-square hypercube to best span all <lb/>combinations of parameters. We tracked the records of observations of species through time, and then <lb/>analyzed these data with TRiPS. These simulations allowed us to explore the effects of violating TRiPS&apos;s <lb/>assumption that a species, if found in a given time interval, is extant during the entire time interval. We <lb/>evaluated TRiPS&apos;s ability to infer sampling rates and true species richness by 1) tabulating the number of <lb/>simulations in which the true species richness was inside the predicted confidence interval and 2) <lb/>estimating the bias in the maximum likelihood prediction of species richness <lb/>= &gt;,. ? . − = @? -@A = @? -@A <lb/>⁄ <lb/>. Details and code for the simulations are presented in the supporting <lb/>information, and also available on the websites of the authors. <lb/>Implementation <lb/>All aspects of the data analysis was performed in R (R Core Team 26). Code necessary for the analysis, <lb/>combined with scripts to directly download relevant (and thus updated) data from Paleobiology Database <lb/>will be made available on the authors&apos; website (or other appropriate repository). The birth-death-fossilize <lb/>model was implemented and analyzed in MatLab (27) and code and simulation data are also available. <lb/>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>Why (and when to) use TRiPS to estimate richness: simulations and comparisons <lb/>Estimating taxon richness using data collected from the fossil record and compiled into databases, such as <lb/>the PaleoDB, is not a trivial exercise as fossilization, outcrop exposure and modern day sampling and data <lb/>compilation are heterogeneous processes. The approach we have developed capitalize on the readily <lb/>availability of fossil observation data in the PaleoDB. Unlike commonly used approaches, including <lb/>subsampling (1,25,28) and bias-corrected residual analysis (7,29), that also use such data, our approach, <lb/>TRiPS, estimates true rather than relative richness by utilizing information on sampling which is inherent <lb/>in PaleoDB. In addition, unlike the residual approach, we do not make presuppositions that an external <lb/>time series can be used to correct for sampling. This is important because such external time series (e.g. <lb/>amount of outcrop, sea level) may constitute a factor driving both richness and sampling as postulated by <lb/>the Common Cause Hypothesis (8,9) or be an effect of such a third factor. Also, in some cases, assumed <lb/>proxy time series can be dubious; for instance using formation counts as a sampling proxy there will <lb/>always be a correlation between proxy and richness, regardless of the degree of sampling (30,31) <lb/>In TRiPS, we tackle bias in the fossil record directly by estimating rates of sampling. This also allows us <lb/>to disentangle sampling and richness dynamics such that tests of links between potential drivers can be <lb/>done on sampling and richness independently (see also 32). An advantage of TRiPS is that our treatment <lb/>of sampling allows sampling probabilities to be directly comparable between intervals of unequal <lb/>duration. One assumption we do explicitly make which cannot be true most of the time, is that a species <lb/>detected in a given time interval is extant during that whole time interval. This is because most species are <lb/>unlikely to become extinct exactly at the late boundary of a time interval or originate exactly at the early <lb/>boundary of a time interval. While other methods for estimating richness also assume that turnover is <lb/>clumped at interval boundaries (see e.g. 28, p. 74), we do need to examine the robustness of our estimates <lb/>to the violation of this crucial assumption. <lb/>Our first round simulations show that when speciation and extinction rates are 0 (and hence where there <lb/>are no changes in species richness through time) but species in the group are allowed to vary in their <lb/>sampling rates, TRiPS still work remarkably well with more than 98% of our 1000 simulations yielding <lb/>confidence intervals of richness that included the true richness value, with no clustering of the &apos;failures&apos; <lb/>in any part of parameter space. Hence, even if species vary in their potential for fossilization and <lb/>detection, TRiPS still yields adequate results. <lb/>In the second round, where speciation and extinction rates are not zero, most simulated species do not <lb/>span the whole interval in which they were sampled. Across the whole parameter space simulated (see <lb/>previous section) TRiPS analysis yielded confidence intervals including the true richness in 71% of <lb/>simulations and true sampling rates were inside the confidence interval in 67% of simulations (see SI for <lb/>effect of all parameter ranges on the success). In other words, TRiPS has reasonable success at capturing <lb/>true species richness despite large deviations from the assumption that species are extant throughout the <lb/>time interval they were sampled in, i.e. even with turnover within a time interval. At moderate levels of <lb/>sampling and shorter durations (of time intervals) TRiPS works very well (Fig 1). <lb/>While richness dynamics within time intervals reduce the probability of correct inferences of both <lb/>sampling rates and true richness according to TRiPS, cases in which true values fall outside of estimated <lb/>confidence intervals are not unreasonable: across such &quot;failure&quot; cases, the correlations between estimated <lb/>and true sampling and richness are 0.91 and 0.93 respectively, and the mean bias in the estimated richness <lb/>is smaller than across all that are deemed &apos;successful&apos;. Many cases of &apos;failure&apos; seem to be due to an <lb/>unwarranted narrowness of confidence intervals rather than a complete breakdown of approach. <lb/>We note two caveats to the estimates from TRiPS. First, although the ability to estimate proper bounds on <lb/>richness is relatively robust to deviations from our assumptions under our simulations, TRiPS does give <lb/>biased maximum likelihood estimates of richness when there are within-bin dynamics such that estimates <lb/>are usually lower than the true richness (see Fig SI 3). The estimated richness is thus best treated as <lb/>possibly minimum richness estimate, particularly for intervals in which there is reason to believe that the <lb/>changes in true richness have been substantial, such as in long geological stages. Second, with longer <lb/>
			simulations (which gives more time for in-bin dynamics) and higher sampling, rates TRiPS fails more <lb/>often (Fig. 1). On the other hand, one of the benefits of our explicit approach is that it is straightforward <lb/>to simulate a birth-death-fossilization process and check whether or not the empirical estimates of <lb/>sampling rates and richness can be thought to be robust to violation of the assumption of negligible <lb/>turnover within an interval (see below). It is also worth highlighting that other approaches for <lb/>reconstructing past richness also fall victim to deviations from constant richness (see e.g. 28), even <lb/>though such violations have not been explicitly examined by published simulations as far as we know. <lb/>Varying sampling estimates among clades and through time <lb/>The sampling estimates from TRiPS (Fig. 2 and Table 1) clearly show that sampling rates and <lb/>probabilities for dinosaurs do not monotonically increase through the Mesozoic, but exhibit a <lb/>combination of high and low sampling regimes. This observation runs counter to the common held belief <lb/>that younger geological strata exhibit a higher level of fossil sampling (e.g. 17,19). Sampling probabilities <lb/>are particularly high during the first two stages of Jurassic (Hettangian (201.3 -199.3 Myr) and <lb/>Sinemurian (199.3-190.8 Myr)), the Tithonian (152.1-145 Myr), the Albian (113-100.5 Myr) and the <lb/>Maastrichtian (72.1-66 Myr) but these high sampling intervals are interspersed with lower ones. Note that <lb/>sampling rates (λ) and sampling probabilities (! &quot; #$, ) while sharing some commonalities, are not the <lb/>same. For instance, the Norian (Nor) has relatively low sampling rates (λ t ), i.e. sampling events per <lb/>lineage per million years, but the probability of a species being sampled, given that it was extant in the <lb/>Norian is quite high (&gt;0.74 for all groups, see Table 1). In general, the relative changes in sampling <lb/>dynamics are similar for our genus level analyses although sampling rates and probabilities are naturally <lb/>higher for genera (SI Fig 6 &amp; 7). <lb/>Our sampling estimates are often quite different across boundaries for which high taxon turnovers have <lb/>been noticed previously. For instance, sampling estimates are low in the Rhaetian (208.5-201.3 Myr) but <lb/>high in the Hettangian (201.3-199.3 Myr), indicating that differential sampling processes were occurring <lb/>across the Triassic-Jurassic boundary. The Jurassic-Cretaceous boundary (Tithonian-Berriasian) also <lb/>shows a significant drop in sampling, indicating that the previously noted diversity loss (17) may, at least <lb/>in part, be a sampling signal. While our estimates corroborate that the last two stages of the late <lb/>Cretaceous have high sampling rates (7,18,33), the Santonian has extremely low sampling rates, at odds <lb/>with a previous analysis of sampling bias (22). The Hettangian exhibits very high sampling rates, which <lb/>leads to binomial sampling probabilities at the same level as the following Sinemurian stage, despite the <lb/>Sinemurian lasting almost five times as long. <lb/>The three clades have notably different sampling estimates from stage to stage and also when compared <lb/>with one another, with binomial sampling probabilities spanning from about 0.1 to almost 1. Theropods <lb/>show higher sampling rates relative to ornithischians and sauropods in Triassic but much lower rates in <lb/>the early stages of the Cretaceous. This runs counter to earlier conclusions that richness trajectories of <lb/>Theropoda and Ornithischia seems to largely be driven by sampling bias, whereas sauropodomorphs are <lb/>less affected by bias in the fossil record (21,22). <lb/>Comparing our empirical sampling rate estimates with the second set of simulations that violated key <lb/>assumptions of TRiPS (Fig. 1), we find most of our empirical estimates fall within parameter ranges in <lb/>which we are able to retrieve true richness estimates reliably. This is with the caveat that the simulated <lb/>speciation and extinction rates are realistic for dinosaurs. <lb/>Our estimates of differential sampling across stages give a very different picture of bias than what the <lb/>residual approach would. To reiterate, the residual approach assumes that a chosen external time series <lb/>fully captures the sampling bias, and uses a model of fixed diversity to predict how richness would look if <lb/>only biased sampling drove the detected signal. In many cases, at least for dinosaurs, the number of fossil <lb/>collections from different intervals that contains at least one dinosaur (DBCs) are often used as a proxy <lb/>for sampling (19,22,34). DBC should capture some of the sampling bias inherent in the dinosaur fossil <lb/>record, but a valid question is how much sampling bias it captures. To explore this, we compare our <lb/>proxy-free sampling estimates to DBCs. We performed correlation tests of the binomial sampling <lb/>probabilities estimated and the linearly detrended log10 number of collections for all downloaded <lb/>dinosaur occurrences. Pearson product-moment correlations for the four taxonomic groups were: 0.55 <lb/>(p&lt;0.003), 0.51 (p&lt;0.019), 0.69 (p&lt; 0.001) and 0.68 (p&lt;0.001), for Dinosauria, Ornithischia, <lb/>Sauropodomorpha and Theropoda sampling probabilities, respectively, indicating that there is a common <lb/>signal in DBCs and our estimated sampling probabilities. However, not only is there remaining sampling <lb/>bias not captured by DBC introducing noise (since correlations are &lt;1), but possibly also adding bias if <lb/>used in richness estimation of dinosaurs. <lb/>Dinosaur richness during the Mesozoic <lb/>The species richness estimates from TRiPS shares dynamics with those painted by both the raw counts of <lb/>species and range-through species richness using the same dataset (Fig 3A). However, only in about half <lb/>the stages are the range-through estimates within the confidence interval of TRiPS estimates. Genus <lb/>richness dynamics are similar to species dynamics (SI figure) and indicate that for at least this dataset <lb/>using these analyses, genus level estimates can be a proxy for species estimates, corroborating Jablonski <lb/>and Finarell (35)&apos;s findings. While genus richness estimates are lower, they are similar to species <lb/>estimates, unsurprisingly given there are few dinosaur species per genera (1.38 identified species per <lb/>genera in our data). Earlier attempts to estimate true taxon richness using ecological richness estimators <lb/>(e.g. 14), species-area curves (16,36) and using estimated durations of genera in a diversification <lb/>framework (15), they do not explicitly estimate sampling bias. Dodson (1990) estimated the total number <lb/>of dinosaur genera to be 900-1200 for the whole Mesozoic, with about 100 genera at any one geological <lb/>stage. Our estimates are more in line with Wang and Dodson&apos;s (14) estimates of genus richness based on <lb/>the Abundance Coverage Estimator, a metric frequently used in ecology, which inferred that the final <lb/>stages of the Cretaceous saw 200-300 genera of dinosaurs roaming our planet (our estimates are 279 and <lb/>305 genera for Campanian and Maastrichtian respectively (see Fig SI 7)). Wang and Dodson&apos;s (2006) <lb/>mixture of epoch and stage level (late Cretaceous only) genus richness estimates are difficult to compare <lb/>
			directly with our stage level only analysis. They estimated that, across the Mesozoic, genus richness of <lb/>dinosaurs was 1844, with only 527 genera actually having been observed. In our downloaded data there <lb/>are 1272 genera for dinosaurs, showing an immense increase in dinosaur occurrences compiled from the <lb/>literature since 2006. Calculating a mean binomial sampling probability for genera across the Mesozoic <lb/>using our stage specific sampling probabilities (weighted by estimated richness per stage) yields an <lb/>overall binomial probability of 0.80 (0.74 -0.86), and estimates of true number of genera for the whole <lb/>Mesozoic is 1580 (CI: 1448-1761), slightly below Wang &amp; Dodson&apos;s 1844. A Mesozoic mean sampling <lb/>probability at the species level (again, weighted by estimated richness from each stage) yield estimates of <lb/>total dinosaur species richness at 2983 (CI: 2462 -3660). <lb/>The literature on dynamics of dinosaur species richness is vast, varied and sometime contradictory. Rather <lb/>than exhaustively comparing our estimates to those from all of the recent literature, we extract salient <lb/>points from Brusatte&apos;s (17) review for our discussion. According to Brusatte (2012, pg. 247), it is <lb/>currently accepted that dinosaurs did not rapidly diversify when they appeared around the start of the Late <lb/>Triassic. Rather, sauropodomorphs diversified during the final part of the Triassic, while ornithischians <lb/>and theropods increased in richness in the early Jurassic (17,33). While this pattern is in part corroborated <lb/>by our analysis for sauropods, sampling rates for ornithischians cannot be estimated with confidence for <lb/>any interval in the Triassic. In contrast to the received view (17,33), our estimates show that theropods <lb/>underwent diversification already in the Triassic, with estimated species richness being higher in Rhaetian <lb/>than the Hettangian, albeit with rather weak confidence (figure 2, Table 1). Sauropodomorphs, on the <lb/>other hand, exhibit rather high levels of both observed and estimated species richness already in the <lb/>Norian, and our estimate of sauropodomorph species richness during the Rhaetian is so high that it not <lb/>even surpassed by the diversity in the final stages of the Cretaceous, nor the supposed diversity peak in <lb/>the mid-Jurassic (37). In other words, our results indicate that a sauropodomorphs peak is reached in the <lb/>Rhaetian, and not in the Norian as earlier studies (22), due to the estimated low sampling for this clade in <lb/>this final stage of the Triassic. <lb/>The Jurassic-Cretaceous boundary (~145 Myr) is believed to have experienced clear diversity loss <lb/>(17,21,22), which Brusatte (2012) claims is particularly pronounced for Sauropodomorphs. Though the <lb/>observed species counts partially corroborates this, the sampling rates for the early part of the Cretaceous <lb/>are estimated to be much lower than late Jurassic (Fig 2), yielding only very small negative changes in <lb/>absolute species richness in the Jurassic-Cretaceous boundary (compare Tithonian and Berriasian in Table <lb/>1) for Sauropodomorpha and no clear signal of richness loss for the other groups. Genus level analyses <lb/>(see Fig SI 7) estimate that the number of Sauropodomorph genera in Berriasian is in fact ~10% higher <lb/>than in the Tithonian. It is also worth emphasizing that the confidence intervals for the estimated species <lb/>diversity are much wider in Berriasian compared to Tithonian, implying that an actual increase in the true <lb/>richness across this boundary cannot be excluded. The fact that the lower sampling rates during the <lb/>Berriasian is clear in all subgroups as well as for all dinosaurs (for both species and genus level analysis) <lb/>suggest that this &quot;clear diversity loss&quot;, might be an artefact of sampling bias and that the &apos;major extinction&apos; <lb/>of dinosaurs across the Jurassic-Cretaceous boundary (21,22,37-39) might be less severe than previously <lb/>thought. <lb/>In his review of the dinosaur literature, Brusatte (2012) also states that the dynamics of species richness <lb/>for the whole Mesozoic did not show a continual increase, but rather a collection of troughs and peaks. <lb/>This general statement is corroborated by our estimates. In particular, there is general agreement that not <lb/>only is there no decline in richness prior to the end-Cretaceous extinction, there is in fact a sharp increase <lb/>in diversity in the late Cretaceous (Brusatte 2012). <lb/>This Cretaceous increase in dinosaur diversity has been put in the context of the Cretaceous explosion of <lb/>terrestrial life (termed the Cretaceous Terrestrial Revolution (KTR)) (18,20,40) which saw the rapid rise <lb/>of flowering plants, insects and mammals. It has thus been hypothesized that the radiation of angiosperms <lb/>preceded the late Cretaceous increase in dinosaur diversity (18). Brusatte (2012) and Lloyd et al. (7,18) <lb/>attributes this increase in dinosaur richness in the two final stages of the Cretaceous to a sampling artifact <lb/>since these intervals show a high volume of fossiliferous rocks, thus arguing against the dinosaurs being a <lb/>part of the KTR. Our analysis corroborates Brusatte and Lloyd&apos;s claims that the final two stages both have <lb/>high sampling rates compared to earlier stages in the Late Cretaceous (Fig 2), indicating that, at least for <lb/>theropods and sauropodomorphs, there is little evidence of high diversification during the Late Cretaceous. <lb/>Nevertheless, ornithischians seem to reach an all-time diversity high in the final 20 million years of the <lb/>Cretaceous (Fig 2 and Table 1), increasing from a mere 11 species in the Coniacian to around 177 in the <lb/>Campanian. It is also worth noting that our reconstructed richness trajectory for sauropods shows a <lb/>relatively steady (but shallow) increase in richness the last 60 million years before the end of the <lb/>Cretaceous. Our estimated sampling rates for the Santonian (86.3-83.6 Ma) are remarkably low for all <lb/>groups (also in the preceding stage for sauropodomorphs), which indicates that the high level of diversity <lb/>of ornithischians and theropods was reached earlier (Santonian) than the consensus view that only the two <lb/>last stages of the Cretaceous show elevated richness (17). <lb/>This late Cretaceous increase in dinosaur diversity has also been framed as a debate on whether or not <lb/>dinosaurs showed a decline in species richness prior to the Cretaceous-Paleogene extinction event <lb/>(7,14,17,20,21,41). Brusatte et al. (2015) argues that, while there was no global long-term decline prior to <lb/>the end-Cretaceous extinction, there is evidence for ceratopsids and hadrosaurids (members of <lb/>Ornithischia) exhibiting declines in both species richness and morphological disparity in the final 15 Ma <lb/>of the Cretaceous (41). On the other hand, Lloyd (2012) claims sauropods and ornithischians both show <lb/>long-term declines throughout most of the Cretaceous while Barrett et al. (21) highlight a negative trend <lb/>in taxic diversity for theropods and ornithischians in the last two stages of the Cretaceous, but suggests a <lb/>&apos;radiation&apos; of sauropods in Late Cretaceous (see also 37). Our analysis indicates that ornithischians <lb/>decreased in richness (about 10 % reduction) in the last stage of the late Cretaceous (Fig 3, Table 1), but <lb/>shows no negative longer-term trend for any of the groups. The apparent trough in richness in the <lb/>Santonian and Coniacian for Sauropodomorphs and Theropods seem to be the result of poor sampling, <lb/>and not a true biological signal (Fig 2, Table 1), and sauropods show a marginal, but steady increase in <lb/>richness across most of the Cretaceous in contrast to their claimed radiation (21,37). <lb/>It is largely accepted that the Oxfordian (163.5-157.3 million years ago) exhibits remarkably low diversity, <lb/>perhaps even the most depauperate stage throughout the Age of the Dinosaurs (7,e.g. 17), and particularly <lb/>so for sauropodomorphs (22). Our approach, in contrast, estimates the sampling probability in this <lb/>particular stage to be the culprit of this trough and especially so for sauropodomorphs (see Fig 3 &amp; Table <lb/>1). Instead of inferring low species richness in this stage, our estimates indicate the sauropodomorph <lb/>richness has quadrupled from the previous stage (Callovian), and a great richness increase is also evident <lb/>in ornithischians and the dinosaurs as a whole. More intense sampling efforts, both in the field and in <lb/>museum collections, and detailed analysis on the observations from the Oxfordian are clearly needed. <lb/>Conclusions and future directions <lb/>To properly paint the picture of past species richness, including the identification of periods of high <lb/>diversification rates and major extinction events, the bias inherent the fossil record that may mislead and <lb/>confound our inferences needs to be taken into account. Here we have detailed TRiPS, a new approach <lb/>for estimating both temporally varying sampling and species richness. The application of TRiPS to a <lb/>global dataset of dinosaur records indicates that several of the commonly held beliefs about the species <lb/>richness trajectory of dinosaurs might be effects of either sampling bias or the use of methods that might <lb/>have introduced new biases to richness estimates through their assumptions. <lb/>As a tool that estimates both sampling rates directly and true richness, TRiPS is pregnant with <lb/>possibilities and have applicability to a range of other paleontological questions. Richness and sampling <lb/>estimates from TRiPS allow us to test the Common Cause Hypothesis in a straightforward manner if <lb/>potential common drivers can be measured in the geological record. Estimates of sampling can be used in <lb/>predicting true ranges of a given species, if we can make the assumption that species have the same <lb/>temporally varying sampling rates. The two forms of sampling estimates may help paleontologists focus <lb/>their sampling and taxonomic efforts in time intervals (or geographic regions) which require most effort <lb/>given the specific questions we wish to answer as a community. While the application of TRiPS we <lb/>demonstrated here attempts to estimate global richness of dinosaurs and its major subclades, TRiPS can <lb/>be applied to any collection of lineages that are assumed or shown to have similar sampling rates, and <lb/>could also be used to estimate taxonomic richness on local to continental contexts. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data accessibility statement. <lb/>All data were downloaded from Paleobiology Database (https://paleobiodb.org/#/). A copy of the <lb/>download will be made available on the authors&apos; website together with the necessary code for <lb/>reproducing the results. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests statement. <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>JS conceived the study, performed the analysis and wrote the manuscript with substantial contributions to writing <lb/>and interpretation by LHL. Both authors gave final approval for publication. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements: <lb/>Kjetil Lysne Voje is acknowledged for fruitful discussions surrounding the initial idea, and Fakutsi is <lb/>recognized for inspiration. This work would not be possible without vertebrate paleontologists who <lb/>contributed primary data and the authorizers and enterers of the PaleoDB who compiled these primary <lb/>data. Major contributors to the downloaded PaleoDB data are Matthew Carrano (59,8%), John Alroy <lb/>(13,9%), Mark Uhen (8,9%), Anna Behrensmeyer (4,6) and Philip Mannion (3,1%). This is PaleoDB <lb/>Publication XXX. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding Statement <lb/>The research reported herein was funded by Norwegian Research Council Grant 235073/F20 to L.H. <lb/>Liow. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Supporting Information <lb/>Online Supporting information contains details of the simulations, results regarding these simulations, <lb/>estimated sampling rates with confidence intervals, results from estimating sampling from all 100 <lb/>replicated datasets detailed in the main text as well as estimated sampling rates and true richness counts <lb/>for dinosaur genera. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References. <lb/>1. <lb/>Bush AM, Markey MJ, Marshall CR. Removing bias from diversity curves: the effects of spatially <lb/>organized biodiversity on sampling-standardization. Paleobiology. 2004;30(4):666-86. <lb/>2. <lb/>McGowan AJ, Smith AB. Comparing the Geological and Fossil Records: Implications for <lb/>Biodiversity Studies. Geological Society of London; 2011. 247 p. <lb/>3. <lb/>Alroy J. The shifting balance of diversity among major marine animal groups. Science. <lb/>2010;329(5996):1191-4. <lb/>4. <lb/>Alroy J. Geographical, environmental and intrinsic biotic controls on Phanerozoic marine <lb/>diversification. Palaeontology. 2010 Nov 16;53(6):1211-35. <lb/>5. <lb/>Norell M a, Novacek MJ. Congruence Between Superpositional and Phylogenetic Patterns: <lb/>Comparing Cladistic Patterns With Fossil Records. Cladistics. 1992;8(4):319-37. <lb/>6. <lb/>McGowan AJ, Smith AB. Are global Phanerozoic marine diversity curves truly global ? A study <lb/>of the relationship between regional rock records and global Phanerozoic marine diversity. <lb/>Paleobiology. 2008;34(1):80-103. <lb/>7. <lb/>Lloyd GT. A refined modelling approach to assess the influence of sampling on palaeobiodiversity <lb/>curves: new support for declining Cretaceous dinosaur richness. Biol Lett. 2012;8(1):123-6. <lb/>8. <lb/>Peters SE. Geologic constraints on the macroevolutionary history of marine animals. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A. 2005;102(35):12326-31. <lb/>9. <lb/>Peters SE, Heim NA. The geological completeness of paleontological sampling in North America. <lb/>Paleobiology. The Paleontological Society; 2010 Jan;36(1):61-79. <lb/>10. <lb/>Conroy MJ, Nichols JD. Testing for Variation in Taxonomic Extinction Probabilities: A Suggested <lb/>Methodology and Some Results. Paleobiology. 1984;10(3):228-337. <lb/>11. Nichols JD, Morris RW, Brownie C, Pollock KH. Sources of variation in extinction rates, turnover, <lb/>and diversity of marine invertebrate families during the Paleozoic. Paleobiology. 1986;12(4):421-<lb/>32. <lb/>12. <lb/>Foote M. Origination and Extinction through the Phanerozoic: A New Aproach. J Geol. <lb/>2003;111(2):125-48. <lb/>13. <lb/>Liow LH, Finarelli JA. A dynamic global equilibrium in carnivoran diversification over 20 million <lb/>years A dynamic global equilibrium in carnivoran diversification over 20 million years. Proc R <lb/>Soc London, B. 2014;281:20132312. <lb/>14. <lb/>Wang SC, Dodson P. Estimating the diversity of dinosaurs. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2006 Sep <lb/>12;103(37):13601-5. <lb/>15. <lb/>Dodson P. Counting dinosaurs: how many kinds were there? Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. <lb/>1990;87(19):7608-12. <lb/>16. <lb/>Russell DA. China and the lost worlds of the dinosaurian era. Hist Biol. 1995;10(1):3-12. <lb/>17. <lb/>Brusatte SL. Macroevolution and Extinction. Dinosaur Paleobiology. 2012. p. 242-61. <lb/>18. <lb/>Lloyd GT, Davis KE, Pisani D, Tarver JE, Ruta M, Sakamoto M, et al. Dinosaurs and the <lb/>Cretaceous Terrestrial Revolution. Proc R Soc London, B. 2008 Nov 7;275(1650):2483-90. <lb/>19. <lb/>Butler RJ, Benson RBJ, Carrano MT, Mannion PD, Upchurch P. Sea level, dinosaur diversity and <lb/>sampling biases: investigating the &quot;common cause&quot; hypothesis in the terrestrial realm. Proc Biol <lb/>Sci. 2011;278(September 2010):1165-70. <lb/>20. <lb/>Fastovsky DE, Huang Y, Hsu J, Martin-McNaughton J, Sheehan PM, Weishampel DB. Shape of <lb/>Mesozoic dinosaur richness. Geology. 2004;32(10):877-80. <lb/>21. <lb/>Barrett PM, McGowan AJ, Page V. Dinosaur diversity and the rock record. Proc Biol Sci. 2009 Jul <lb/>22;276(1667):2667-74. <lb/>22. <lb/>Mannion PD, Upchurch P, Carrano MT, Barrett PM. Testing the effect of the rock record on <lb/>diversity: a multidisciplinary approach to elucidating the generic richness of sauropodomorph <lb/>dinosaurs through time. Biol Rev Camb Philos Soc. 2011 Feb;86(1):157-81. <lb/>23. <lb/>Varela S, González-Hernández J, Sgarbi LF, Marshall C, Uhen MD, Peters SE, et al. paleobioDB: <lb/>an R package for downloading, visualizing and processing data from the Paleobiology Database. <lb/>Ecography (Cop). 2015 Apr 2;38(4):419-25. <lb/>24. <lb/>Solow AR, Smith WK. On Fossil Preservation and the Stratigraphic Ranges of Taxa On fossil <lb/>preservation and the stratigraphic ranges of taxa. Paleobiology. 1997;23(3):271-7. <lb/>25. <lb/>Alroy J, Marshall CR, Bambach RK, Bezusko K, Foote M, Hansen TA, et al. Effects of Sampling <lb/>Standardization on Estimates of Phanerozoic Marine Diversification. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. <lb/>2001;11:6261-6. <lb/>26. <lb/>Team RC. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. Vienna, Austria: R <lb/>Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2015. <lb/>27. <lb/>MATLAB. version 8.2.0.701 (R2013b). Natick, Massachusetts: The Mathworks Inc.; 2013. <lb/>28. <lb/>Alroy J. Fair sampling of taxonomic richness and unbiased estimation of origination and <lb/>extinction rates. Quant methods Paleobiol. 2010;16:55-80. <lb/>29. <lb/>Smith AB, Gowan AJM. THE SHAPE OF THE PHANEROZOIC MARINE <lb/>PALAEODIVERSITY CURVE : HOW MUCH CAN BE PREDICTED FROM THE <lb/>SEDIMENTARY ROCK RECORD OF WESTERN EUROPE ? 2007;50:765-74. <lb/>30. <lb/>Benton MJ, Dunhill AM, Lloyd GT, Marx FG. Assessing the quality of the fossil record: insights <lb/>from vertebrates. Geol Soc London, Spec Publ. 2011 Dec 13;358(1):63-94. <lb/>31. <lb/>Benton MJ. Palaeodiversity and formation counts: redundancy or bias? Palaeontology. 2015;n/a -<lb/>n/a. <lb/>32. <lb/>Liow LH, Reitan T, Harnik PG. Ecological interactions on macroevolutionary time scales: clams <lb/>and brachiopods are more than ships that pass in the night. Ecol Lett. 2015;n/a -n/a. <lb/>33. <lb/>Upchurch P, Mannion PD, Benson RBJ. Geological and anthropogenic controls on the sampling of <lb/>the terrestrial fossil record : a case study from the Dinosauria. In: Mcgowan AJ, Smith AB, editors. <lb/>Comparing the Geological and Fossil Records. 2011. p. 209-40. <lb/>34. <lb/>Brusatte SL, Benton MJ, Ruta M, Lloyd GT. Superiority, competition, and opportunism in the <lb/>evolutionary radiation of dinosaurs. Science. 2008;321(5895):1485-8. <lb/>35. <lb/>Jablonski D, Finarelli JA. Congruence of morphologically-defined genera with molecular <lb/>phylogenies. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2009 May 19;106(20):8262-6. <lb/>36. <lb/>Le Loeuff J. Paleobiogeography and biodiversity of Late Maastrichtian dinosaurs: How many <lb/>dinosaur species went extinct at the Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary? Bull la Soc Geol Fr. <lb/>2012;183(6):547-59. <lb/>37. <lb/>Upchurch P, Barrett PM. Phylogenetic and taxic perspectives on sauropod diversity. The <lb/>Sauropods: evolution and paleobiology. Berkeley: University of California Press; 2005. p. 104-24. <lb/>38. <lb/>Benson RBJ, Mannion PD. Multi-variate models are essential for understanding vertebrate <lb/>diversification in deep time. Biol Lett. 2011; <lb/>39. <lb/>Mannion PD, Benson RBJ, Butler RJ. Vertebrate palaeobiodiversity patterns and the impact of <lb/>sampling bias. Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Palaeoecol. 2013;372:1-4. <lb/>40. <lb/>Weishampel DB, Dodson P, Osólska H. The Dinosauria. 2nd ed. University of California Press; <lb/>2004. <lb/>41. <lb/>Brusatte SL, Butler RJ, Barrett PM, Carrano MT, Evans DC, Lloyd GT, et al. The extinction of the <lb/>dinosaurs. Biol Rev. 2015 Jul 28;90(2):628-42. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figures and table with captions <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>Simulation and estimation results. The grayscale indicates how often TRiPS is successful (the proportion of simulations inside a square that had a <lb/>95 % confidence interval that include the true richness) across mean sampling rates and time interval durations. All simulations presented here <lb/>violate both the assumption of constant richness within time interval dynamics and identical sampling rates for species, but TRiPS still manages to <lb/>capture the true richness in a large part of parameter space. Speciation and extinction rates are log uniformly distributed between 0.005 and 0.158. <lb/>Sampling rates for all dinosaurs (red squares), ornithischians (blue circles), sauropodomorphs (green triangles), theropods (purple diamonds) are <lb/>plotted against their corresponding stage durations (see Table 1 for 8 rates that had sampling rates higher than 0.5 not plotted here). <lb/>Figure 2. Sampling estimates from TRiPS for all dinosaurs, ornithischian, sauropodomorph and theropod species considered separately. A. <lb/>Estimated sampling rates (λ) in sampling events per species per million years. B. Estimated binomial sampling probabilities (! &quot; #$, ) of species <lb/>within the plotted time interval. In both panels, estimates are in red (squares and full line) for all dinosaurs, blue for Ornithischia (circle and dashed <lb/>line), green for Sauropodomorpha (triangles with dotted line) and purple for Theropoda (diamonds with dash-dotted line). Confidence intervals on <lb/>all rates and probabilities and estimates from 100 replicated occurrence counts (see main text) are reported in the SI. For abbreviations of stage <lb/>names see Table 1. <lb/>Figure 3. Species richness estimates from TRiPS. A. Dinosauria. B. Ornithischia. C. Sauropodomorpha. D. Theropoda. Black circles connected by <lb/>full line indicates observed species counts, triangles connected by dotted line indicate range-through species counts while colored line and shading <lb/>indicate maximum likelihood estimate and 95% confidence intervals for the true species richness estimated using TRiPS. Corresponding sampling <lb/>estimates can be seen in Fig 2. <lb/></body>

			576 <lb/>

			<body>Interval details (Ma) <lb/>Dinosauria <lb/>Ornithischia <lb/>Sauropodomorpha species richness <lb/>Theropoda species richness <lb/>1751 species with 4694 occurrences <lb/>521 species with 1485 occurrences <lb/>391 species with 979 occurrences <lb/>772 species with 2051 occurrences <lb/>Species richness <lb/>Sampling <lb/>probability <lb/>Species richness <lb/>Sampling <lb/>probability <lb/>Species richness <lb/>Sampling <lb/>probability <lb/>Species richness <lb/>Sampling <lb/>probability <lb/>Stage (Abbr) <lb/>Start <lb/>End <lb/>Duration <lb/>Nobs <lb/>(RT) <lb/>Ntrue (CI) <lb/>Nobs <lb/>(RT) <lb/>Ntrue (CI) <lb/>Nobs <lb/>(RT) <lb/>Ntrue (CI) <lb/>Nobs <lb/>(RT) <lb/>Ntrue (CI) <lb/>Cretaceous <lb/>Late <lb/>Maastrichtian <lb/>(Maa) <lb/>72,1 <lb/>66 <lb/>6,1 <lb/>375 <lb/>(397) <lb/>393 (383 -<lb/>407) <lb/>0,95 (0,94 -0,96) <lb/>144 <lb/>(154) <lb/>157 (148 -<lb/>171) <lb/>0,91 (0,89 -0,93) <lb/>54 (60) <lb/>54 (54 -57) <lb/>0,99 (0,98 -0,99) <lb/>170 <lb/>(178) <lb/>177 (171 -<lb/>185) <lb/>0,96 (0,95 -0,97) <lb/>Campanian <lb/>(Cam) <lb/>83,6 <lb/>72,1 <lb/>11,5 <lb/> 324 <lb/> (341) <lb/>359 (343 -<lb/>381) <lb/>0,9 (0,88 -0,92) <lb/>160 <lb/>(169) <lb/>177 (167 -<lb/>193) <lb/>0,9 (0,87 -0,92) <lb/>35 (44) <lb/>54 (39 -90) <lb/>0,64 (0,49 -0,76) <lb/>118 <lb/>(131) <lb/>125 (120 -<lb/>136) <lb/>0,94 (0,91 -0,96) <lb/>Santonian (San) <lb/>86,3 <lb/>83,6 <lb/>2,7 <lb/>40 (58) <lb/>273 (93 -<lb/>1373) <lb/>0,15 (0,04 -0,33) <lb/>13 (21) <lb/>86 (18 -2288) <lb/>0,15 (0,01 -0,5) <lb/>9 (15) <lb/>46 (10 -1307) <lb/>0,19 (0,01 -0,59) <lb/>18 (30) <lb/>97 (28 -813) <lb/>0,18 (0,03 -0,46) <lb/>Coniacian <lb/>(Con) <lb/>89,8 <lb/>86,3 <lb/>3,5 <lb/>35 (52) <lb/>63 (41 -122) <lb/>0,55 (0,37 -0,71) <lb/>10 (16) <lb/>11 (10 -22) <lb/>0,85 (0,64 -0,95) <lb/>8 (14) <lb/>41 (9 -1200) <lb/>0,19 (0,01 -0,59) <lb/>18 (30) <lb/>46 (22 -163) <lb/>0,39 (0,16 -0,63) <lb/>Turonian (Tur) <lb/>93,9 <lb/>89,8 <lb/>4,1 <lb/>71 (90) <lb/>189 (119 -<lb/>343) <lb/>0,38 (0,25 -0,51) <lb/>20 (27) <lb/>44 (23 -131) <lb/>0,45 (0,22 -0,69) <lb/>15 (20) <lb/>55 (20 -305) <lb/>0,27 (0,08 -0,55) <lb/>34 (51) <lb/>91 (49 -222) <lb/>0,37 (0,2 -0,56) <lb/>Cenomanian <lb/>(Cen) <lb/>100,5 <lb/>93,9 <lb/>6,6 <lb/>90 (113) <lb/>205 (142 -<lb/>327) <lb/>0,44 (0,32 -0,55) <lb/>29 (39) <lb/>78 (40 -203) <lb/>0,37 (0,19 -0,57) <lb/>21 (26) <lb/>49 (25 -150) <lb/>0,42 (0,2 -0,66) <lb/>40 (55) <lb/>79 (51 -148) <lb/>0,5 (0,34 -0,66) <lb/>Early <lb/>Albian (Alb) <lb/>113 <lb/>100, <lb/>5 <lb/>12,5 <lb/>122 <lb/>(138) <lb/>138 (128 -<lb/>155) <lb/>0,88 (0,84 -0,91) <lb/>43 (51) <lb/>44 (43 -50) <lb/>0,96 (0,93 -0,98) <lb/>28 (33) <lb/>38 (29 -62) <lb/>0,72 (0,57 -0,84) <lb/>50 (62) <lb/>60 (52 -78) <lb/>0,82 (0,74 -0,89) <lb/>Aptian (Apt) <lb/>125 <lb/>113 <lb/>12 <lb/>199 <lb/>(224) <lb/>353 (291 -<lb/>444) <lb/>0,56 (0,49 -0,63) <lb/>49 (59) <lb/>68 (54 -99) <lb/>0,71 (0,59 -0,81) <lb/>25 (33) <lb/>33 (26 -55) <lb/>0,74 (0,58 -0,85) <lb/>124 <lb/>(139) <lb/>307 (218 -<lb/>465) <lb/>0,4 (0,31 -0,5) <lb/>Barremian <lb/>(Bar) <lb/>129,4 <lb/>125 <lb/>4,4 <lb/>93 (123) <lb/>204 (145 -<lb/>315) <lb/>0,45 (0,35 -0,56) <lb/>26 (37) <lb/>37 (28 -63) <lb/>0,69 (0,53 -0,81) <lb/>13 (23) <lb/>25 (13 -99) <lb/>0,51 (0,21 -0,79) <lb/>54 (75) <lb/>241 (114 -<lb/>659) <lb/>0,22 (0,1 -0,38) <lb/>Hauterivian <lb/>(Hau) <lb/>132,9 <lb/>129, <lb/>4 <lb/>3,5 <lb/>35 (70) <lb/>106 (53 -292) <lb/>0,33 (0,16 -0,53) <lb/>12 (22) <lb/>22 (12 -85) <lb/>0,54 (0,22 -0,82) <lb/>3 (13) <lb/>5 (3 -63) <lb/>0,51 (0,12 -0,87) <lb/>21 (43) <lb/>192 (38 -<lb/>4721) <lb/>0,11 (0,01 -0,39) <lb/>Valanginian <lb/>(Val) <lb/>139,8 <lb/>132, <lb/>9 <lb/>6,9 <lb/>40 (66) <lb/>96 (56 -211) <lb/>0,41 (0,25 -0,59) <lb/>14 (23) <lb/>26 (15 -79) <lb/>0,53 (0,27 -0,77) <lb/>9 (18) <lb/>17 (9 -63) <lb/>0,52 (0,24 -0,78) <lb/>17 (31) <lb/>83 (25 -698) <lb/>0,2 (0,04 -0,49) <lb/>Berriasian (Ber) <lb/>145 <lb/>139, <lb/>8 <lb/>5,2 <lb/>42 (63) <lb/>88 (55 -171) <lb/>0,48 (0,31 -0,64) <lb/>16 (21) <lb/>26 (17 -65) <lb/>0,6 (0,35 -0,81) <lb/>10 (16) <lb/>26 (11 -152) <lb/>0,37 (0,11 -0,68) <lb/>14 (28) <lb/>37 (16 -197) <lb/>0,37 (0,11 -0,68) <lb/>Jurassic <lb/>Late <lb/>Tithonian (Tit) <lb/>152,1 <lb/>145 <lb/>7,1 <lb/>105 <lb/>(121) <lb/>113 (107 -<lb/>123) <lb/>0,93 (0,9 -0,95) <lb/>25 (30) <lb/>26 (25 -32) <lb/>0,93 (0,87 -0,97) <lb/>43 (48) <lb/>45 (43 -50) <lb/>0,96 (0,92 -0,97) <lb/>34 (45) <lb/>38 (34 -50) <lb/>0,87 (0,79 -0,93) <lb/>Kimmeridgian <lb/>(Kim) <lb/>157,3 <lb/>152, <lb/>1 <lb/>5,2 <lb/>83 (100) <lb/>100 (88 -120) <lb/>0,83 (0,76 -0,88) <lb/>20 (25) <lb/>24 (20 -38) <lb/>0,81 (0,66 -0,91) <lb/>34 (39) <lb/>42 (35 -60) <lb/>0,8 (0,68 -0,88) <lb/>25 (37) <lb/>28 (25 -40) <lb/>0,86 (0,75 -0,93) <lb/> Oxfordian <lb/>(Oxf) <lb/>163,5 <lb/>157, <lb/>3 <lb/>6,2 <lb/>54 (66) <lb/>156 (89 -330) <lb/>0,34 (0,21 -0,5) <lb/>17 (20) <lb/>57 (22 -301) <lb/>0,3 (0,09 -0,59) <lb/>13 (16) <lb/>93 (19 -2476) <lb/>0,14 (0,01 -0,47) <lb/>25 (32) <lb/>55 (30 -139) <lb/>0,45 (0,25 -0,66) <lb/>Mid <lb/>Callovian (Cal) <lb/>166,1 <lb/>163, <lb/>5 <lb/>2,6 <lb/>34 (45) <lb/>80 (45 -190) <lb/>0,42 (0,24 -0,62) <lb/>6 (12) <lb/>11 (6 -64) <lb/>0,53 (0,18 -0,84) <lb/>13 (19) <lb/>24 (14 -72) <lb/>0,52 (0,28 -0,74) <lb/>14 (25) <lb/>58 (18 -496) <lb/>0,24 (0,05 -0,56) <lb/>Bathonian (Bat) <lb/>168,3 <lb/>166, <lb/>1 <lb/>2,2 <lb/>19 (31) <lb/>29 (20 -64) <lb/>0,64 (0,41 -0,82) <lb/>1 (5) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>11 (16) <lb/>13 (11 -30) <lb/>0,8 (0,53 -0,94) <lb/>6 (13) <lb/>19 (6 -553) <lb/>0,31 (0,02 -0,78) <lb/>Bajacian (Baj) <lb/>170,3 <lb/>168, <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>14 (24) <lb/>48 (16 -394) <lb/>0,29 (0,06 -0,64) <lb/>2 (6) <lb/>3 (2 -117) <lb/>0,58 (0,05 -0,96) <lb/>7 (11) <lb/>29 (7 -853) <lb/>0,24 (0,02 -0,68) <lb/>5 (11) <lb/>15 (5 -488) <lb/>0,31 (0,02 -0,78) <lb/>Aalenian (Aal) <lb/>174,1 <lb/>170, <lb/>3 <lb/>3,8 <lb/>8 (14) <lb/>21 (8 -190) <lb/>0,37 (0,08 -0,74) <lb/>2 (3) <lb/>2 (2 -22) <lb/>0,8 (0,25 -0,99) <lb/>2 (4) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>3 (9) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>Early <lb/>Toarcian (Toa) <lb/>182,7 <lb/>174, <lb/>1 <lb/>8,6 <lb/>10 (16) <lb/>61 (13 -1721) <lb/>0,16 (0,01 -0,52) <lb/>1 (2) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>5 (8) <lb/>15 (5 -488) <lb/>0,31 (0,02 -0,78) <lb/>3 (8) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>Pliensbachian <lb/>(Pli) <lb/>190,8 <lb/>182, <lb/>7 <lb/>8,1 <lb/>18 (26) <lb/>63 (24 -334) <lb/>0,28 (0,08 -0,57) <lb/>2 (3) <lb/>3 (2 -117) <lb/>0,58 (0,05 -0,96) <lb/>5 (9) <lb/>13 (5 -394) <lb/>0,37 (0,03 -0,84) <lb/>11 (20) <lb/>40 (13 -355) <lb/>0,27 (0,05 -0,61) <lb/>Sinemurian <lb/>(Sin) <lb/>199,3 <lb/>190, <lb/>8 <lb/>8,5 <lb/>162 <lb/>(171) <lb/>180 (169 -<lb/>197) <lb/>0,9 (0,87 -0,92) <lb/>35 (38) <lb/>41 (36 -55) <lb/>0,84 (0,74 -0,9) <lb/>39 (44) <lb/>45 (40 -58) <lb/>0,86 (0,78 -0,91) <lb/>58 (63) <lb/>61 (58 -69) <lb/>0,94 (0,91 -0,96) <lb/>Hettangian <lb/>(Het) <lb/>201,3 <lb/>199, <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>92 (107) <lb/>115 (101 -<lb/>140) <lb/>0,79 (0,73 -0,85) <lb/>15 (19) <lb/>19 (15 -36) <lb/>0,77 (0,56 -0,91) <lb/>14 (20) <lb/>23 (14 -58) <lb/>0,6 (0,35 -0,81) <lb/>40 (49) <lb/>44 (40 -55) <lb/>0,89 (0,83 -0,94) <lb/>Triassic <lb/>Late <lb/>Rhaetian (Rha) <lb/>208,5 <lb/>201, <lb/>3 <lb/>7,2 <lb/>39 (55) <lb/>166 (72 -562) <lb/>0,23 (0,09 -0,43) <lb/>0 (2) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>17 (23) <lb/>155 (30 -<lb/>3982) <lb/>0,11 (0,01 -0,39) <lb/>21 (31) <lb/>58 (27 -202) <lb/>0,36 (0,15 -0,6) <lb/>Norian (Nor) <lb/>227 <lb/>208, <lb/>5 <lb/>18,5 <lb/>75 (80) <lb/>93 (81 -115) <lb/>0,8 (0,73 -0,86) <lb/>2 (2) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>38 (42) <lb/>51 (40 -76) <lb/>0,74 (0,61 -0,84) <lb/>29 (31) <lb/>32 (29 -40) <lb/>0,91 (0,83 -0,95) <lb/>Carnian (Car) <lb/>237 <lb/>227 <lb/>10 <lb/>19 (24) <lb/>41 (22 -126) <lb/>0,45 (0,22 -0,69) <lb/>1 (1) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>4 (7) <lb/>10 (4 -340) <lb/>0,37 (0,03 -0,84) <lb/>13 (15) <lb/>23 (13 -70) <lb/>0,56 (0,28 -0,79) <lb/>Ladinian (Lad) <lb/>242 <lb/>237 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 (3) <lb/>4 (3 -40) <lb/>0,68 (0,18 -0,96) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>1 (1) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>1 (1) <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>577 <lb/>Table 1. Sampling and richness observations and estimates for all dinosaurs, ornithischians, sauropodomorphs and theropods. Details of the start, <lb/>578 <lb/>end and duration of all intervals used (as downloaded from PaleobioDB) are shown in the first 3 columns. Observed species richness N obs (range <lb/>579 <lb/>through in parenthesis), the maximum likelihood estimated true richness N true (confidence intervals in parenthesis) and the maximum likelihood <lb/>580 <lb/>estimated sampling probability (confidence intervals) are then given for each group in each stage. NA indicates combinations of intervals and <lb/>581 <lb/>groups in which there was not enough data to estimate sampling rates, and thus no estimated true richness. Sampling probabilities in bold indicate <lb/>582 <lb/>estimates outside the range of Fig 1. <lb/></body>

			583 <lb/>584


	</text>
</tei>
