<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Glucose modulates Drosophila longevity and immunity independent of the microbiota. <lb/>Anthony Galenza, Jaclyn Hutchinson, Bart Hazes, Shelagh D. Campbell and Edan Foley. <lb/>University of Alberta, Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of <lb/>Virology. <lb/>Running Title: nutrition, the microbiome, and health in Drosophila <lb/>Correspondence: <lb/>Edan Foley <lb/>Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology <lb/>University of Alberta <lb/>Edmonton <lb/>Alberta <lb/>T6G 2S2 <lb/>Canada. <lb/>Tel.: (780) 492-0935 <lb/>Fax: (780) 492-7521 <lb/>Email: efoley@ualberta.ca <lb/>Key words: Drosophila, nutrition, microbiome, protein to carbohydrate, ageing <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>ABSTRACT <lb/>The acquisition of nutrients is essential for maintenance of metabolic processes in all <lb/>organisms. Nutritional imbalance contributes to myriad metabolic disorders that include <lb/>malnutrition, diabetes, and even cancer. Recently, the importance of macronutrient ratio of food <lb/>has emerged as a critical factor to determine health outcomes. Here we show that individual <lb/>modifications to a completely defined diet markedly impact multiple aspects of organism <lb/>wellbeing in Drosophila melanogaster. Through a longitudinal survey of several diets we <lb/>demonstrate that increased levels of dietary glucose significantly improve longevity and <lb/>immunity in adult Drosophila. Our metagenomic studies, show that relative macronutrient levels <lb/>not only influence the host, but also have a profound impact on microbiota composition. <lb/>However, we found that elevated dietary glucose extended the lifespan of adult flies even when <lb/>raised in a germ-free environment. Furthermore, when challenged with a chronic enteric <lb/>infection, flies fed a diet with added glucose had increased survival times even in the absence of <lb/>an intact microbiota. Thus, in contrast to known links between the microbiota and animal health, <lb/>our findings uncover a novel microbiota-independent response to diet that impacts host <lb/>wellbeing. As dietary responses are highly conserved in animals, we believe our results offer a <lb/>general understanding of the association between glucose metabolism and animal health. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Recent developments in the production, distribution and consumption of food <lb/>fundamentally transformed our relationship with our nutritional environment. The near limitless <lb/>availability of ready-made, high-calorie meals is a prominent contributor to the emergence of <lb/>metabolic disorders as a major health challenge in many nations, and there is an increased <lb/>emphasis on the importance of nutritional awareness to optimize individual health outcomes <lb/>(Simpson et al., 2015). In this context, the obvious health benefits of a nutritionally replete diet <lb/>fuel a multi-billion dollar health and nutrition industry that centers on the pursuit of a &quot;balanced&quot; <lb/>diet. However, functional definitions of health and nutritional balance are more complex than <lb/>may seem apparent and require more than a steady intake of specific amounts of nutrients. <lb/>Dietary influence on longevity has been extensively studied in several vertebrate and <lb/>invertebrate models (Fontana and Partridge, 2015; Tatar et al., 2014). Initial, widely reported <lb/>observations showed that caloric restriction promotes a longer lifespan in rats, and this was <lb/>supported by subsequent studies in mice, Drosophila, worms, and yeast (Dilova et al., 2007; <lb/>Fontana et al., 2010). Recent long-term experiments yielded mixed observations on the benefits <lb/>of caloric restriction for primates (Colman et al., 2014; Mattison et al., 2012). However, the two <lb/>studies in question differed considerably in their experimental protocols, making comparisons <lb/>difficult. Exploration of the basis for extended longevity in models of caloric restriction <lb/>emphasized the relative contributions of individual nutrients to animal lifespan (Lee et al., 2015; <lb/>Simpson and Raubenheimer, 2009; Solon-Biet et al., 2015b). These studies revealed that diets <lb/>with low protein to carbohydrate ratios significantly extended the lifespans of mice and <lb/>Drosophila (Lee et al., 2008; Solon-Biet et al., 2014). More recent studies have focused on <lb/>additional dietary contributions to health and lifespan that include the time of consumption <lb/>(Jakubowicz et al., 2013; Mattson et al., 2014), duration of fasting between meals (Harvie et al., <lb/>2011; Honjoh et al., 2009), as well as relative amounts of amino acids in the diet (Miller et al., <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>2005; Wu et al., 2013). When considered as a whole, these studies point to a remarkably <lb/>nuanced relationship between the uptake of dietary nutrients and animal wellbeing. <lb/>Many studies of the interplay between nutrition and health overlook microbial <lb/>contributions. In particular, we know very little about the relationship between the intestinal <lb/>microflora, host diet, and host intestinal immunity. We consider this a particularly relevant <lb/>aspect of health and lifespan, as diet and health are intimately linked by the intestinal microbiota <lb/>(Flint et al., 2012). Diet shapes the composition of the intestinal microflora, which, in turn, <lb/>influences events as diverse as nutrient allocation, intestinal physiology, immune responses, <lb/>and the onset of chronic diseases. For example, the intestinal microbiota facilitates the uniquely <lb/>restricted diet of the koala (Osawa et al., 1992); orchestrates the establishment of immune <lb/>structures in mammals (Hooper et al., 2012); and contributes to the containment, or <lb/>dissemination of pathogenic microbes in a number of experimental models (Round and <lb/>Mazmanian, 2009; Wlodarska et al., 2015). The genetically accessible model system Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster is a particularly valuable tool to reveal key aspects of relationships between diet, <lb/>the microbiota and the host (Erkosar and Leulier, 2014; Ma et al., 2015). The fly gut shares <lb/>numerous similarities with mammalian counterparts that include developmental origin, cellular <lb/>composition, and metabolic pathways (Lemaitre and Miguel-Aliaga, 2013). Additionally, while <lb/>the mammalian gut contains 500-1000 separate bacterial species, the fly gut is far simpler to <lb/>study with 5-30 aerotolerant, cultivable commensal species (Broderick and Lemaitre, 2012; <lb/>Buchon et al., 2013). A number of recent publications established clear mechanistic <lb/>relationships between the intestinal microflora of flies and events as diverse as nutritional <lb/>regulation (Newell and Douglas, 2014; Storelli et al., 2011; Wong et al., 2014), activation of pro-<lb/>growth pathways (Shin et al., 2011; Storelli et al., 2011), control of immune pathways (Broderick <lb/>et al., 2014; Erkosar et al., 2014), and selection of mates (Sharon et al., 2010). <lb/>Previous studies with Drosophila as a tool to explore host-diet-microbiota relationships <lb/>relied on partially defined oligdic diets. Recently, Piper et al. established a protocol to prepare a <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>holidic diet for Drosophila, in which the exact composition and concentration of every ingredient <lb/>is known (Piper et al., 2014). This allows for precise manipulation of nutrient availability in <lb/>dietary studies, as individual components can be modified to a specified quantity and effects on <lb/>the organism can be observed. <lb/>In this study, we investigated how dietary modifications, inspired in part by popular <lb/>human diets, affect the health of a fly. Specifically, we made five separate modifications to the <lb/>original holidic recipe that include the addition of supplementary glucose, starch, casein, palmitic <lb/>acid, or ethanol. Respectively, these additions represent diets with higher levels of simple sugar, <lb/>complex sugar, protein, saturated fatty acids, or alcohol. We investigated several aspects of <lb/>overall health and nutrition and found that relatively modest dietary modifications exert profound <lb/>impacts on the lifespan, immune response, and microfloral composition of the host. Of the five <lb/>dietary modifications tested, we found that the elevation of dietary glucose emerged as the most <lb/>beneficial manipulation, with effects that included an extended lifespan, increased locomotion, <lb/>and enhanced immunity against an enteric pathogen. We were particularly intrigued by the <lb/>relationship between diet, the microbiome, longevity and immunity, as this issue has not been <lb/>tackled in a systematic study to date. We found that dietary supplementation of glucose greatly <lb/>increased the diversity of the intestinal microbiome. However, when we eliminated the <lb/>microbiota from flies, we found that the health benefits of increased glucose were largely <lb/>independent of the microbiota. Combined, our observations establish that elevated levels of <lb/>dietary glucose provide numerous benefits to fly health and immunity, and that these benefits do <lb/>not require an intestinal microbiota. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Diet and Age Modify Adult Metabolism in Drosophila. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>We initially measured the relationship between age, diet and metabolism in adult flies. For these <lb/>assays, we raised flies on a recently described holidic diet, or a holidic diet supplemented with <lb/>glucose, starch, casein, palmitic acid, or ethanol. The supplementary regimes allowed us to <lb/>interrogate the impacts of increased levels of simple or complex sugars, protein, saturated fatty <lb/>acids, or moderate amounts of alcohol on a common experimental model. We measured the <lb/>weight, protein content, triglyceride levels and glucose levels of male and female flies raised on <lb/>the respective diets for five days, ten days, or twenty days. We found that age exerted a <lb/>significant influence on the weight, protein content, and triglyceride content of adult flies, while <lb/>diet exerted moderate effects on protein levels (Figure 1A and B). In contrast, we found that diet <lb/>significantly affected triglyceride and glucose levels in flies. Specifically, we found that <lb/>supplementation of a holidic diet with extra glucose greatly increased triglyceride and glucose <lb/>levels in older flies compared to age-matched controls raised on the holidic diet (Figure 1C). <lb/>These data suggest that increased availability of dietary glucose elevates energy stores, <lb/>particularly in older flies, without significant effects on weight or protein content. <lb/>Elevated Glucose Availability Extends Adult Longevity. <lb/>Our data overlap with previous suggestions that dietary modifications have considerable <lb/>impacts on the metabolic profile of flies (Wong et al., 2014). Numerous studies implicate the <lb/>availability of nutrients and calories in the control of animal longevity, with a frequent implication <lb/>that caloric or dietary restriction extends life. However, recent studies also suggest that relative <lb/>amounts of macronutrients in the diet are important determinants of Drosophila lifespan (Lee et <lb/>al., 2008). Importantly, this hypothesis has not been tested with a defined diet in Drosophila. To <lb/>address this issue, we determined the lifespans of adult male and female flies raised under <lb/>defined dietary conditions. We found that dietary modifications had slightly different effects on <lb/>the longevity of male and female flies (Table 1, Figure 2A). In general, dietary modifications that <lb/>diminished lifespans, such as supplementation with palmitic acid or protein, had more <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>pronounced effects on female flies than male flies, while dietary modifications that extended <lb/>lifespans, such as addition of ethanol or glucose had more pronounced effects on male flies <lb/>than females (Figure 2A). We found that elevated glucose availability had a particularly marked <lb/>impact on longevity in male flies, with a median lifespan extension of 31%. A recent meta-<lb/>analysis suggested that the longevity benefits of dietary restriction are adaptations to laboratory <lb/>culture, not a physiological response observed in the wild (Nakagawa et al., 2012). To test if the <lb/>benefits of glucose addition are restricted to lab-raised flies, we fed adult male Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster captured in the wilds of Edmonton (Canada) an unmodified diet or one <lb/>supplemented with glucose. As with our lab strains, we found that elevated levels of dietary <lb/>glucose significantly increased the lifespan of wild flies (Figure 2B and D). <lb/>Restoration of a complete diet reverts lifespan-extension benefits of dietary restriction In <lb/>Drosophila (Mair et al., 2003). To determine if the benefits of glucose were permanent or <lb/>transient, we measured the longevity of male flies raised on a holidic diet, or male flies raised on <lb/>a holidic diet supplemented with extra glucose for the first five days, the first ten days, or the <lb/>duration of adult life. Our results show that longer periods of dietary supplementation with <lb/>glucose have more significant effects on lifespan (Figure 2C and D). For example, <lb/>supplementation of the adult diet with glucose for the first ten days of life extended median <lb/>survival rates by 12%, while permanent addition of extra glucose extended median survival <lb/>rates by 32%. These data suggest that overall levels of dietary glucose reversibly influence the <lb/>lifespan of adult Drosophila. <lb/>Elevated Levels of Dietary Glucose Promote Immunity Against an Intestinal Pathogen. <lb/>As malnutrition impairs immune functions in Drosophila (Vijendravarma et al., 2015), we asked if <lb/>defined dietary modifications influence host responses to challenges with an intestinal <lb/>pathogen. Drosophila is an established model for infection with the enteric pathogen Vibrio <lb/>cholerae (Blow et al., 2005). To determine if diet altered survival time during a V. cholerae <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>infection, we raised adult female flies on defined diets for ten days and measured survival after <lb/>delivering a lethal infectious dose of Vibrio. We chose female flies for these studies, as they <lb/>outlive male flies challenged with the same pathogen, allowing us to explore the effect of diet on <lb/>survival to a greater extent. We found that flies on a holidic diet had a median survival of 49 <lb/>hours after infection (Figure 3A and B). Supplementation with casein led to a slight decrease in <lb/>median survival, while the other dietary modifications all showed an increase in median lifespan. <lb/>Flies that were raised on increased glucose showed the most significant extension in survival <lb/>during infection ( =19.82, p&lt;0.0001). These data establish that defined nutritional regimes <lb/>influence the ability of Drosophila to combat an enteric infection, and in particular, that increased <lb/>levels of glucose significantly elevate the survival times for adult flies. <lb/>Diet Influences Locomotion. <lb/>As health and lifespan are commonly connected to physical activity, we asked if defined diets <lb/>influence activity in adult Drosophila. For these assays, we compared locomotion in flies raised <lb/>on a holidic diet to flies raised on the same diet supplemented with either glucose or ethanol. <lb/>We chose glucose and ethanol, as both treatments extended median survival rates in adults. In <lb/>each case, we trained flies with twelve-hour cycles of light and dark for five days, followed by <lb/>five days of constant darkness. This approach allowed us to determine the effects of diet on <lb/>activity, as well as the establishment and maintenance of circadian rhythms. We found that fly <lb/>locomotion quickly adapted to defined cycles of light and dark irrespective of the diet, with peak <lb/>activity levels after transitions to periods of light and sharp drops in locomotion after transitions <lb/>to periods of dark (Figure 4A, days 1-5). For all treatments, adult flies maintained this <lb/>behavioural pattern during the subsequent five days of constant darkness (Figure 4A, days 6-<lb/>10). We observed a clear peak of activity that corresponded to a twenty-four hour period for <lb/>days 1-5 and days 6-10, with a less prominent period of eight hours during days 1-5 irrespective <lb/>of the diet (Figure 4B). Combined, these data show that the individual diets do not affect the <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>ability of adult flies to maintain a circadian rhythm. However, examination of the data in Figures <lb/>4A and B suggest that diet influences general locomotion. To quantify the extent of this effect, <lb/>we tallied total daily movements for flies raised on the respective diets. We found that <lb/>supplementation with glucose greatly enhanced fly activity, while supplementation with ethanol <lb/>had a sedative effect. Addition of extra glucose to the medium boosted daily activity levels by <lb/>39% relative to the control population on a holidic diet, while provision of moderate amounts of <lb/>ethanol decreased daily locomotion by roughly 27% (Figure 4C). <lb/>Dietary Glucose Supplementation Alters Microbiota Composition and Increases <lb/>Diversity. <lb/>The studies detailed above uncover a number of effects of defined dietary modifications on the <lb/>health of adult flies. As the microbiota of the host is known to affect these factors, we assessed <lb/>the impact of defined diets on the intestinal microbiota. For these assays, we raised adults on <lb/>modified diets and performed 16S DNA sequencing on bacterial DNA isolated from their <lb/>intestinal tracts. Males and females raised on an unmodified holidic diet had similar microbiota <lb/>that were dominated by the Acetobacter genus (Figure 5A). We found that simple alterations to <lb/>this holidic diet resulted in profound changes in microbiota composition and diversity (Figure <lb/>5B). For example, when flies were raised on a diet supplemented with casein, the microbiota <lb/>shifted to predominantly Lactobacillus species. In contrast, supplementation with glucose <lb/>resulted in the largest increase in microbiota diversity (Shannon: Females=2.387, Males=1.789). <lb/>We also noticed a different response between males and females to the same dietary <lb/>modification, as seen for a diet supplemented with ethanol (Shannon: Females=2.383, <lb/>Males=0.193). Our data suggest that both host diet and sex markedly impact the composition of <lb/>intestinal microbiota, with supplementary glucose contributing to the greatest increase in <lb/>species diversity. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Glucose Increases Lifespan and Survival to Infection Independent of the Microbiota. <lb/>At this stage, our data reveal wide-ranging impacts of dietary glucose supplementation on adult <lb/>flies, with significant effects on longevity, locomotion, energy stores, microfloral composition, <lb/>and immunity. Given the established links between intestinal microflora diversity and host health <lb/>(Norman et al., 2015), we asked if the microbiota is required for the beneficial effects of glucose <lb/>supplementation on longevity. For these assays, we fed adult male flies an unmodified holidic <lb/>diet or one supplemented with glucose and raised the flies under conventional or germ-free <lb/>conditions. Consistent with recent reports (Clark et al., 2015; Petkau et al., 2014), we found that <lb/>flies raised under germ-free conditions outlived their conventionally-reared counterparts (Figure <lb/>6A and B). Similar to our earlier experiments, we found that elevated dietary glucose increased <lb/>the median lifespan of adult flies by 25% compared to an unmodified diet. Strikingly, we found <lb/>that elimination of the microbiome did not affect the lifespan of flies raised on diets with elevated <lb/>glucose, suggesting that glucose levels influence host longevity independently of the <lb/>microbiome. <lb/>These unexpected observations prompted us to ask if the glucose-mediated <lb/>improvements to survival after challenges with Vibrio challenges require a microbiome. To <lb/>assess this, we fed adult Drosophila an unmodified holidic diet or one supplemented with <lb/>glucose and raised the flies under conventional or germ-free conditions. We then measured <lb/>survival after delivering a lethal infectious dose of Vibrio. As expected, we found that <lb/>conventional flies on an unmodified diet had a median survival of 49.5 hours (Figure 7A). <lb/>Removal of the microbiome significantly improved survival after infection with Vibrio (Figure 7B). <lb/>As before, we found that elevated dietary glucose significantly improved survival compared to <lb/>an unmodified diet ( <lb/>=17.390, p=&lt;0.0001). Remarkably, elimination of the microflora did not <lb/>alter the survival rates of flies raised on a high glucose diet and challenged with Vibrio. <lb/>Combined, the data in Figures 6 and 7 establish that the microfloral shifts associated with <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>transition to a high glucose diet are not essential for the immunological and lifespan benefits of <lb/>such a diet. <lb/>Increased Lifespan From Glucose is Independent of Intestinal Insulin Signaling. <lb/>Our observation that glucose promotes antibacterial defenses independently of an intact <lb/>intestinal microbiota suggests direct effects of glucose on host intestinal physiology. As previous <lb/>studies showed that high-sugar diets cause insulin resistance in Drosophila (Musselman et al., <lb/>2011), and inhibition of insulin signalling in the gut promotes longevity (Biteau et al., 2010), we <lb/>reasoned that elevated dietary glucose leads to insulin insensitivity in the intestine of adult flies, <lb/>thereby extending the lifespans of the fly. To test this hypothesis, we generated a temperature <lb/>sensitive esgGAL4, GAL80 ts /+ ; UASInR/+ (esg ts &gt;InR) Drosophila strain to control insulin <lb/>receptor activity in midgut progentiors. In this strain, the combination of esgGAL4 and GAL80 ts <lb/>transgenic elements induce insulin receptor (InR) activity in midgut progenitors of adult flies at <lb/>the restrictive temperature of 29°C. As described in a previous study (Biteau et al., 2010), <lb/>activation of the insulin receptor decreased the lifespans of adult flies compared to esgGAL4, <lb/>GAL80 ts /+ (esg ts /+) (Figure 8A and B). However, we found that esg ts &gt;InR flies raised on a diet <lb/>with added glucose significantly outlived esg ts &gt;InR counterparts raised on an unmodified diet. In <lb/>fact, the lifespan extensions observed upon addition of glucose were comparable for esg ts &gt;InR <lb/>and esg ts controls (Figure 8B). These data suggest that a high glucose diet extends adult <lb/>Drosophila lifespan independent of insulin receptor activity in the gut. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>DISCUSSION <lb/>The acquisition and allocation of nutrients is essential for maintenance of the intricate <lb/>cellular processes that define multicellular life. Nutritional imbalances are at the heart of global <lb/>health challenges that range from malnutrition to diabetes and meaningful solutions require a <lb/>complete appreciation of the effects of complex diets on host wellbeing. We used Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster as a tool to model the longitudinal consequences of defined diets in a common <lb/>experimental system. The holidic diet allowed us to manipulate relative nutrient levels with far <lb/>more precision than has been possible previously. Apart from the potentially whimsical <lb/>observation of a proverbial &quot;sugar rush&quot;, we noticed a number of benefits of elevated levels of <lb/>dietary glucose for adult flies. Increases to the levels of dietary glucose extended longevity, <lb/>improved resistance to enteric infection, and increased diversity of the intestinal microbiota. The <lb/>range of phenotypes suggests broad physiological responses to altered levels of dietary <lb/>glucose. <lb/>Consistent with two recent reports (Clark et al., 2015; Petkau et al., 2014), we found that <lb/>elimination of the adult microflora extended the lifespan of flies raised on a holidic diet. <lb/>However, it is important to emphasize that the relationship between microfloral presence and fly <lb/>longevity is by no means resolved, as other groups reported negative (Brummel et al., 2004) or <lb/>neutral (Ren et al., 2007) effects of germ-free culture conditions on adult longevity. We consider <lb/>it possible that the phenotypic variation between labs reflects differences between the <lb/>respective Drosophila genotypes, diets, or microbiomes. Despite the phenotypic similarities <lb/>between flies raised under germ-free conditions and flies raised on a high glucose diet, we <lb/>established that glucose does not require a microbiome to improve immunity or longevity. <lb/>Instead, our data suggest that host-intrinsic responses are key to the benefits of elevated levels <lb/>of dietary glucose. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>At first glance, the health benefits of elevated glucose appear incongruous with <lb/>conventional dietary wisdoms, as chronic ingestion of carbohydrates is linked to metabolic <lb/>disorders such as diabetes, and caloric restriction enhances longevity in many model <lb/>organisms. However, recent studies established that dietary ratios of protein and carbohydrate <lb/>(P:C) exert a substantial influence on the health of flies and mice, with several phenotypic <lb/>benefits for animals raised on diets with low P:C ratios (Bruce et al., 2013; Grandison et al., <lb/>2009; Lee et al., 2008; Mirzaei et al., 2014; Piper et al., 2011; Solon-Biet et al., 2014; Solon-Biet <lb/>et al., 2015a; Solon-Biet et al., 2015c). Consistent with this hypothesis, we showed that addition <lb/>of glucose, an effective drop in P:C ratio, boosted longevity, while addition of casein, an <lb/>effective increase in P:C ratio, reduced the lifespan of adult flies. Our studies extended these <lb/>observations to show that low P:C ratios improve immune responses to an intestinal pathogen, <lb/>and that elevated P:C ratios are detrimental to survival after infection with Vibrio cholerae. Of <lb/>note, the strength of the phenotypes differed for male and female flies, suggesting <lb/>endocrinological regulation of dietary effects on lifespan. <lb/>To date, there are few studies that explore interplays between nutrient access, <lb/>microfloral composition and animal health. In a preliminary set of experiments, we found that <lb/>germ-free flies resisted chronic intestinal challenges with Vibrio cholerae better than <lb/>conventional flies. The fly response to enteric infection is remarkably sophisticated and includes <lb/>the expression of bactericidal AMPs through the Immune Deficiency (IMD) response (Lemaitre <lb/>and Miguel-Aliaga, 2013). A previous study demonstrated that mutations in the IMD pathway <lb/>extend the lifespan of flies challenged with Vibrio cholerae (Wang et al., 2013), suggesting <lb/>deleterious contributions from IMD to the pathogenesis of Vibrio cholerae. As intestinal IMD <lb/>activity is lower in flies raised under germ-free conditions (Broderick et al., 2014), we speculate <lb/>that germ-free flies are better equipped to deal with Vibrio infections due to diminished intestinal <lb/>IMD activity. However, our data do not exclude alternative explanations such as effects of <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>glucose on the expression of pathogenicity factors by Vibrio. Future studies are required to <lb/>determine the mechanistic basis for dietary alterations of intestinal immune responses. <lb/>As nutritional status influences intestinal immunity in Drosophila (Vijendravarma et al., <lb/>2015), we asked if dietary modifications improve immune responses to Vibrio by modification of <lb/>the intestinal microflora. Several studies demonstrated that diet influences composition of the <lb/>fly&apos;s microbiota (Staubach et al., 2013; Wong et al., 2013). However, these studies relied on <lb/>substantial alterations to partially defined diets. We used the holidic diet to examine the effects <lb/>of specific macronutrients on microbiome makeup. Our results showed that remarkably simple <lb/>dietary changes, such as alterations to relative glucose or protein levels, drastically alter the <lb/>microbiota of adult flies. However, at least in the case of glucose, these modifications do not <lb/>directly influence the lifespan or immune response, as germ-free flies and their conventionally <lb/>reared counterparts have indistinguishable viability profiles when raised on diets with elevated <lb/>glucose. <lb/>As a cautionary note, we cannot exclude that some dietary modifications act at least <lb/>partially through effects on the microbiota in Drosophila. For example, a recent study <lb/>established that the commensal fungus Isatchenkia orientalis promotes amino acid uptake in <lb/>nutritionally deprived Drosophila (Yamada et al., 2015). In our study, we found that flies fed a <lb/>diet supplemented with moderate amounts of ethanol lived longer and survived infection better <lb/>than control flies raised on an unmodified diet. Since wild flies develop in and consume <lb/>decomposed fruit, ethanol is likely a common constituent of their environment. As ethanol is a <lb/>fuel source for Acetobacter, a prominent fly commensal that modifies insulin and TOR signals in <lb/>the midgut (Shin et al., 2011; Storelli et al., 2011), it remains possible that the lifespan extension <lb/>we see from ethanol depends on the microbiota. <lb/>Since we observed benefits from glucose independent of the microbiota, we were <lb/>interested in the host response to glucose that extends lifespan. High dietary glucose lowers <lb/>insulin sensitivity in flies (Musselman et al., 2011), and decreased insulin activity in the gut <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>increases lifespan in the fly (Biteau et al., 2010). These observations led us to speculate that <lb/>glucose increases longevity through reduced insulin receptor activity in the gut. However, our <lb/>results showed that overexpression of the insulin receptor in intestinal progenitor cells did not <lb/>impair the lifespan benefits of added glucose, suggesting that outputs from the gut insulin <lb/>receptor do not influence the benefits of elevated dietary glucose. Animals respond to their <lb/>nutritional environment through complex signal transduction pathways such as TOR and insulin <lb/>in several organs, and both pathways influence lifespan and health in numerous model <lb/>organisms (Harrison et al., 2009; Kapahi and Zid, 2004; Kapahi et al., 2004; Scialo et al., 2015; <lb/>Tatar et al., 2003; Vellai et al., 2003). In the case of flies, the gut, fat body, and insulin-producing <lb/>neurons coordinate the uptake and distribution of macronutrients (Buch et al., 2008). A more <lb/>extensive analysis of the physiological benefits of increased glucose will likely require dissection <lb/>of TOR and insulin responses in these tissues. <lb/>In summary, this study complements an emerging body of literature that low dietary P:C <lb/>ratios extend the lifespan of Drosophila. In addition, we show that alterations to P:C ratios <lb/>generate significant phenotypes in locomotion, immunity, and microfloral diversity. Despite the <lb/>links between the intestinal microflora and animal health, we established that glucose acts <lb/>directly on the host to increase lifespan and responses to cholerae infections. As physiological <lb/>responses to diet are extensively conserved throughout the animal kingdom, we believe our <lb/>findings may be of relevance to a general appreciation of the relationship between glucose <lb/>consumption and animal health. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Fly Husbandry <lb/>All experiments were performed with virgin female and male adult flies raised at 29°C. w 1118 flies <lb/>were used as a control genotype unless otherwise mentioned. The esgGAL4 flies described in <lb/>this study have been described elsewhere (Buchon et al., 2009). The wild Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster population was derived from a single pregnant female captured in EF&apos;s kitchen in <lb/>Edmonton (Canadan) in the summer of 2014. Adult flies were raised on a holidic medium <lb/>developed by Piper et al. using the Oaa stock recipe and 100 mM biologically available nitrogen <lb/>(Piper et al., 2014). Modifications to this diet include: the additions of simple sugar (100 g/L D-<lb/>glucose), complex sugar (50 g/L starch), protein (70 g/L casein), fatty acid (50 g/L palmitic acid), <lb/>and alcohol (1% ethanol). Germ-free flies were generated by raising adults on food <lb/>supplemented with an antibiotic cocktail (100 µg/mL ampicillin, 50 µg/mL vancomycin, 100 <lb/>µg/mL neomycin, and 100 µg/mL metronidazole). Survival assays were performed with approx. <lb/>50 flies housed at 10 flies/vial and transferred to fresh vials weekly. <lb/>Metabolic Assays <lb/>All metabolic assays were performed as described in (Wong et al., 2014) in 96-well plates using <lb/>commercial kits: the DC Protein Assay kit (Bio-Rad, 500-0116), Triglyceride Assay kit (Sigma, <lb/>TG-5-RB), and Glucose (GO) Assay kit (Sigma, GAGO20). Colorimetric readings were obtained <lb/>using a microplate spectrophotometer (PerkinElmer, Envision Multilabel Reader). <lb/>Locomotion Assay <lb/>Holidic medium was added to small glass tubes capped with a plastic stopper. A single fly was <lb/>placed in each tube. The tube was then closed with yarn and then placed into monitors of the <lb/>TriKinetics DAMSystem. Fly activity was monitored for 10 days at 23°C. A 12 h light/ 12 h dark <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>cycle for 5 days was used for circadian training followed by 5 days in permanent dark. <lb/>Infection Protocol <lb/>Samples of 40-50 adult female flies at 15 flies/vial, were raised for 10 days at 29°C. Flies were <lb/>starved by placing in empty vials for 2 h prior to infection. Flies were then maintained in vials <lb/>containing a cellulose acetate plug infused with 3 mL of V. cholerae C6706 (10 8 -10 9 cells/mL) in <lb/>LB, and viability was monitored over a 5-day period. <lb/>Microbiota sequencing. <lb/>Samples of 10 adult male or female flies were raised for 10 days at 29°C. Intestinal tracts were <lb/>dissected as described elsewhere and bacterial genomic DNA was isolated with the Ultraclean <lb/>Microbial DNA Isolation Kit (MO-BIO, 12224). Bacterial 16S DNA was amplified with primers <lb/>AGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG (forward) and GGCTACCTTGTTACGACTT (reverse). Samples <lb/>were purified with a QIAquick PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen, 28104). Samples were prepared for <lb/>sequencing using a Nextera XT DNA Library Preparation Kit (Illumina, FC-131-1024), and DNA <lb/>libraries were sequenced using a MiSeq Desktop Sequencer (Illumina). Taxonomy assignment <lb/>was based on the SILVA SSU Ref NR99 database release 115, using in-house developed <lb/>software. <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<div type="funding">FUNDING INFORMATION <lb/>This research was supported by an operating grant from the Canadian Institutes of Health <lb/>Research to EF (MOP 77746). AG was supported by a Frederick Banting and Charles Best <lb/>Canada Graduate Scholarship (CIHR CGS-M), and a Walter H. Johns Graduate Fellowship <lb/>(UofA). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the <lb/>decision to submit the work for publication. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>Jeff Reeve (Alberta Transplant Applied Genomics Centre) assisted with preparation of <lb/>actograms. The Applied Genomics Core at the University of Alberta assisted with microbial <lb/>sequencing. esgGAL4, GAL80 ts flies were provided by Bruno Lemaitre, and UAS-InR flies were <lb/>provided by Kirst King-Jones. <lb/></div>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Biteau, B., Karpac, J., Supoyo, S., Degennaro, M., Lehmann, R., Jasper, H., 2010. Lifespan <lb/>extension by preserving proliferative homeostasis in Drosophila. PLoS Genet 6, e1001159. <lb/>Blow, N.S., Salomon, R.N., Garrity, K., Reveillaud, I., Kopin, A., Jackson, F.R., Watnick, P.I., <lb/>2005. Vibrio cholerae infection of Drosophila melanogaster mimics the human disease <lb/>cholera. PLoS Pathog 1, e8. <lb/>Broderick, N.A., Buchon, N., Lemaitre, B., 2014. Microbiota-induced changes in drosophila <lb/>melanogaster host gene expression and gut morphology. MBio 5, e01117-01114. <lb/>Broderick, N.A., Lemaitre, B., 2012. Gut-associated microbes of Drosophila melanogaster. <lb/>Gut Microbes 3, 307-321. <lb/>Bruce, K.D., Hoxha, S., Carvalho, G.B., Yamada, R., Wang, H.D., Karayan, P., He, S., Brummel, <lb/>T., Kapahi, P., Ja, W.W., 2013. High carbohydrate-low protein consumption maximizes <lb/>Drosophila lifespan. Exp Gerontol 48, 1129-1135. <lb/>Brummel, T., Ching, A., Seroude, L., Simon, A.F., Benzer, S., 2004. Drosophila lifespan <lb/>enhancement by exogenous bacteria. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 101, 12974-12979. <lb/>Buch, S., Melcher, C., Bauer, M., Katzenberger, J., Pankratz, M.J., 2008. Opposing effects of <lb/>dietary protein and sugar regulate a transcriptional target of Drosophila insulin-like <lb/>peptide signaling. Cell Metab 7, 321-332. <lb/>Buchon, N., Broderick, N.A., Chakrabarti, S., Lemaitre, B., 2009. Invasive and indigenous <lb/>microbiota impact intestinal stem cell activity through multiple pathways in Drosophila. <lb/>Genes Dev 23, 2333-2344. <lb/>Buchon, N., Broderick, N.A., Lemaitre, B., 2013. Gut homeostasis in a microbial world: <lb/>insights from Drosophila melanogaster. Nat Rev Microbiol 11, 615-626. <lb/>Clark, R.I., Salazar, A., Yamada, R., Fitz-Gibbon, S., Morselli, M., Alcaraz, J., Rana, A., Rera, M., <lb/>Pellegrini, M., Ja, W.W., Walker, D.W., 2015. Distinct Shifts in Microbiota Composition <lb/>during Drosophila Aging Impair Intestinal Function and Drive Mortality. Cell Rep 12, 1656-<lb/>1667. <lb/>Colman, R.J., Beasley, T.M., Kemnitz, J.W., Johnson, S.C., Weindruch, R., Anderson, R.M., 2014. <lb/>Caloric restriction reduces age-related and all-cause mortality in rhesus monkeys. Nat <lb/>Commun 5, 3557. <lb/>Dilova, I., Easlon, E., Lin, S.J., 2007. Calorie restriction and the nutrient sensing signaling <lb/>pathways. Cell Mol Life Sci 64, 752-767. <lb/>Erkosar, B., Defaye, A., Bozonnet, N., Puthier, D., Royet, J., Leulier, F., 2014. Drosophila <lb/>microbiota modulates host metabolic gene expression via IMD/NF-kappaB signaling. PLoS <lb/>One 9, e94729. <lb/>Erkosar, B., Leulier, F., 2014. Transient adult microbiota, gut homeostasis and longevity: <lb/>novel insights from the Drosophila model. FEBS Lett 588, 4250-4257. <lb/>Flint, H.J., Scott, K.P., Louis, P., Duncan, S.H., 2012. The role of the gut microbiota in nutrition <lb/>and health. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol 9, 577-589. <lb/>Fontana, L., Partridge, L., 2015. Promoting health and longevity through diet: from model <lb/>organisms to humans. Cell 161, 106-118. <lb/>Fontana, L., Partridge, L., Longo, V.D., 2010. Extending healthy life span--from yeast to <lb/>humans. Science 328, 321-326. <lb/>Grandison, R.C., Piper, M.D., Partridge, L., 2009. Amino-acid imbalance explains extension of <lb/>lifespan by dietary restriction in Drosophila. Nature 462, 1061-1064. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Harrison, D.E., Strong, R., Sharp, Z.D., Nelson, J.F., Astle, C.M., Flurkey, K., Nadon, N.L., <lb/>Wilkinson, J.E., Frenkel, K., Carter, C.S., Pahor, M., Javors, M.A., Fernandez, E., Miller, R.A., <lb/>2009. Rapamycin fed late in life extends lifespan in genetically heterogeneous mice. Nature <lb/>460, 392-395. <lb/>Harvie, M.N., Pegington, M., Mattson, M.P., Frystyk, J., Dillon, B., Evans, G., Cuzick, J., Jebb, <lb/>S.A., Martin, B., Cutler, R.G., Son, T.G., Maudsley, S., Carlson, O.D., Egan, J.M., Flyvbjerg, A., <lb/>Howell, A., 2011. The effects of intermittent or continuous energy restriction on weight loss <lb/>and metabolic disease risk markers: a randomized trial in young overweight women. Int J <lb/>Obes (Lond) 35, 714-727. <lb/>Honjoh, S., Yamamoto, T., Uno, M., Nishida, E., 2009. Signalling through RHEB-1 mediates <lb/>intermittent fasting-induced longevity in C. elegans. Nature 457, 726-730. <lb/>Hooper, L.V., Littman, D.R., Macpherson, A.J., 2012. Interactions between the microbiota <lb/>and the immune system. Science 336, 1268-1273. <lb/>Jakubowicz, D., Barnea, M., Wainstein, J., Froy, O., 2013. Effects of caloric intake timing on <lb/>insulin resistance and hyperandrogenism in lean women with polycystic ovary syndrome. <lb/>Clin Sci (Lond) 125, 423-432. <lb/>Kapahi, P., Zid, B., 2004. TOR pathway: linking nutrient sensing to life span. Sci Aging <lb/>Knowledge Environ 2004, PE34. <lb/>Kapahi, P., Zid, B.M., Harper, T., Koslover, D., Sapin, V., Benzer, S., 2004. Regulation of <lb/>lifespan in Drosophila by modulation of genes in the TOR signaling pathway. Curr Biol 14, <lb/>885-890. <lb/>Lee, D., Hwang, W., Artan, M., Jeong, D.E., Lee, S.J., 2015. Effects of nutritional components <lb/>on aging. Aging Cell 14, 8-16. <lb/>Lee, K.P., Simpson, S.J., Clissold, F.J., Brooks, R., Ballard, J.W., Taylor, P.W., Soran, N., <lb/>Raubenheimer, D., 2008. Lifespan and reproduction in Drosophila: New insights from <lb/>nutritional geometry. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 105, 2498-2503. <lb/>Lemaitre, B., Miguel-Aliaga, I., 2013. The digestive tract of Drosophila melanogaster. Annu <lb/>Rev Genet 47, 377-404. <lb/>Ma, D., Storelli, G., Mitchell, M., Leulier, F., 2015. Studying host-microbiota mutualism in <lb/>Drosophila: Harnessing the power of gnotobiotic flies. Biomed J 38, 285-293. <lb/>Mair, W., Goymer, P., Pletcher, S.D., Partridge, L., 2003. Demography of dietary restriction <lb/>and death in Drosophila. Science 301, 1731-1733. <lb/>Mattison, J.A., Roth, G.S., Beasley, T.M., Tilmont, E.M., Handy, A.M., Herbert, R.L., Longo, D.L., <lb/>Allison, D.B., Young, J.E., Bryant, M., Barnard, D., Ward, W.F., Qi, W., Ingram, D.K., de Cabo, R., <lb/>2012. Impact of caloric restriction on health and survival in rhesus monkeys from the NIA <lb/>study. Nature 489, 318-321. <lb/>Mattson, M.P., Allison, D.B., Fontana, L., Harvie, M., Longo, V.D., Malaisse, W.J., Mosley, M., <lb/>Notterpek, L., Ravussin, E., Scheer, F.A., Seyfried, T.N., Varady, K.A., Panda, S., 2014. Meal <lb/>frequency and timing in health and disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 111, 16647-16653. <lb/>Miller, R.A., Buehner, G., Chang, Y., Harper, J.M., Sigler, R., Smith-Wheelock, M., 2005. <lb/>Methionine-deficient diet extends mouse lifespan, slows immune and lens aging, alters <lb/>glucose, T4, IGF-I and insulin levels, and increases hepatocyte MIF levels and stress <lb/>resistance. Aging Cell 4, 119-125. <lb/>Mirzaei, H., Suarez, J.A., Longo, V.D., 2014. Protein and amino acid restriction, aging and <lb/>disease: from yeast to humans. Trends Endocrinol Metab 25, 558-566. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Musselman, L.P., Fink, J.L., Narzinski, K., Ramachandran, P.V., Hathiramani, S.S., Cagan, R.L., <lb/>Baranski, T.J., 2011. A high-sugar diet produces obesity and insulin resistance in wild-type <lb/>Drosophila. Dis Model Mech 4, 842-849. <lb/>Nakagawa, S., Lagisz, M., Hector, K.L., Spencer, H.G., 2012. Comparative and meta-analytic <lb/>insights into life extension via dietary restriction. Aging Cell 11, 401-409. <lb/>Newell, P.D., Douglas, A.E., 2014. Interspecies interactions determine the impact of the gut <lb/>microbiota on nutrient allocation in Drosophila melanogaster. Appl Environ Microbiol 80, <lb/>788-796. <lb/>Norman, J.M., Handley, S.A., Baldridge, M.T., Droit, L., Liu, C.Y., Keller, B.C., Kambal, A., <lb/>Monaco, C.L., Zhao, G., Fleshner, P., Stappenbeck, T.S., McGovern, D.P., Keshavarzian, A., <lb/>Mutlu, E.A., Sauk, J., Gevers, D., Xavier, R.J., Wang, D., Parkes, M., Virgin, H.W., 2015. Disease-<lb/>specific alterations in the enteric virome in inflammatory bowel disease. Cell 160, 447-460. <lb/>Osawa, R., Blanshard, W.H., O&apos;Callaghan, P.G., 1992. Microflora of the pouch of the koala <lb/>(Phascolarctos cinereus). J Wildl Dis 28, 276-280. <lb/>Petkau, K., Parsons, B.D., Duggal, A., Foley, E., 2014. A deregulated intestinal cell cycle <lb/>program disrupts tissue homeostasis without affecting longevity in Drosophila. J Biol Chem <lb/>289, 28719-28729. <lb/>Piper, M.D., Blanc, E., Leitao-Goncalves, R., Yang, M., He, X., Linford, N.J., Hoddinott, M.P., <lb/>Hopfen, C., Soultoukis, G.A., Niemeyer, C., Kerr, F., Pletcher, S.D., Ribeiro, C., Partridge, L., <lb/>2014. A holidic medium for Drosophila melanogaster. Nat Methods 11, 100-105. <lb/>Piper, M.D., Partridge, L., Raubenheimer, D., Simpson, S.J., 2011. Dietary restriction and <lb/>aging: a unifying perspective. Cell Metab 14, 154-160. <lb/>Ren, C., Webster, P., Finkel, S.E., Tower, J., 2007. Increased internal and external bacterial <lb/>load during Drosophila aging without life-span trade-off. Cell Metab 6, 144-152. <lb/>Round, J.L., Mazmanian, S.K., 2009. The gut microbiota shapes intestinal immune responses <lb/>during health and disease. Nat Rev Immunol 9, 313-323. <lb/>Scialo, F., Sriram, A., Naudi, A., Ayala, V., Jove, M., Pamplona, R., Sanz, A., 2015. Target of <lb/>rapamycin activation predicts lifespan in fruit flies. Cell Cycle, 0. <lb/>Sharon, G., Segal, D., Ringo, J.M., Hefetz, A., Zilber-Rosenberg, I., Rosenberg, E., 2010. <lb/>Commensal bacteria play a role in mating preference of Drosophila melanogaster. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A 107, 20051-20056. <lb/>Shin, S.C., Kim, S.H., You, H., Kim, B., Kim, A.C., Lee, K.A., Yoon, J.H., Ryu, J.H., Lee, W.J., 2011. <lb/>Drosophila microbiome modulates host developmental and metabolic homeostasis via <lb/>insulin signaling. Science 334, 670-674. <lb/>Simpson, S.J., Le Couteur, D.G., Raubenheimer, D., 2015. Putting the balance back in diet. <lb/>Cell 161, 18-23. <lb/>Simpson, S.J., Raubenheimer, D., 2009. Macronutrient balance and lifespan. Aging (Albany <lb/>NY) 1, 875-880. <lb/>Solon-Biet, S.M., McMahon, A.C., Ballard, J.W., Ruohonen, K., Wu, L.E., Cogger, V.C., Warren, <lb/>A., Huang, X., Pichaud, N., Melvin, R.G., Gokarn, R., Khalil, M., Turner, N., Cooney, G.J., Sinclair, <lb/>D.A., Raubenheimer, D., Le Couteur, D.G., Simpson, S.J., 2014. The ratio of macronutrients, <lb/>not caloric intake, dictates cardiometabolic health, aging, and longevity in ad libitum-fed <lb/>mice. Cell Metab 19, 418-430. <lb/>Solon-Biet, S.M., Mitchell, S.J., Coogan, S.C., Cogger, V.C., Gokarn, R., McMahon, A.C., <lb/>Raubenheimer, D., de Cabo, R., Simpson, S.J., Le Couteur, D.G., 2015a. Dietary Protein to <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Carbohydrate Ratio and Caloric Restriction: Comparing Metabolic Outcomes in Mice. Cell <lb/>Rep 11, 1529-1534. <lb/>Solon-Biet, S.M., Mitchell, S.J., de Cabo, R., Raubenheimer, D., Le Couteur, D.G., Simpson, S.J., <lb/>2015b. Macronutrients and caloric intake in health and longevity. J Endocrinol 226, R17-28. <lb/>Solon-Biet, S.M., Walters, K.A., Simanainen, U.K., McMahon, A.C., Ruohonen, K., Ballard, J.W., <lb/>Raubenheimer, D., Handelsman, D.J., Le Couteur, D.G., Simpson, S.J., 2015c. Macronutrient <lb/>balance, reproductive function, and lifespan in aging mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 112, <lb/>3481-3486. <lb/>Staubach, F., Baines, J.F., Kunzel, S., Bik, E.M., Petrov, D.A., 2013. Host species and <lb/>environmental <lb/>effects on bacterial <lb/>communities associated with Drosophila in the <lb/>laboratory and in the natural environment. PLoS One 8, e70749. <lb/>Storelli, G., Defaye, A., Erkosar, B., Hols, P., Royet, J., Leulier, F., 2011. Lactobacillus <lb/>plantarum promotes Drosophila systemic growth by modulating hormonal signals through <lb/>TOR-dependent nutrient sensing. Cell Metab 14, 403-414. <lb/>Tatar, M., Bartke, A., Antebi, A., 2003. The endocrine regulation of aging by insulin-like <lb/>signals. Science 299, 1346-1351. <lb/>Tatar, M., Post, S., Yu, K., 2014. Nutrient control of Drosophila longevity. Trends Endocrinol <lb/>Metab 25, 509-517. <lb/>Vellai, T., Takacs-Vellai, K., Zhang, Y., Kovacs, A.L., Orosz, L., Muller, F., 2003. Genetics: <lb/>influence of TOR kinase on lifespan in C. elegans. Nature 426, 620. <lb/>Vijendravarma, R.K., Narasimha, S., Chakrabarti, S., Babin, A., Kolly, S., Lemaitre, B., <lb/>Kawecki, <lb/>T.J., <lb/>2015. <lb/>Gut <lb/>physiology <lb/>mediates <lb/>a <lb/>trade-off <lb/>between <lb/>adaptation <lb/>to <lb/>malnutrition and susceptibility to food-borne pathogens. Ecol Lett 18, 1078-1086. <lb/>Wang, Z., Hang, S., Purdy, A.E., Watnick, P.I., 2013. Mutations in the IMD pathway and <lb/>mustard counter Vibrio cholerae suppression of intestinal stem cell division in Drosophila. <lb/>MBio 4, e00337-00313. <lb/>Wlodarska, M., Kostic, A.D., Xavier, R.J., 2015. An integrative view of microbiome-host <lb/>interactions in inflammatory bowel diseases. Cell Host Microbe 17, 577-591. <lb/>Wong, A.C., Chaston, J.M., Douglas, A.E., 2013. The inconstant gut microbiota of Drosophila <lb/>species revealed by 16S rRNA gene analysis. ISME J 7, 1922-1932. <lb/>Wong, A.C., Dobson, A.J., Douglas, A.E., 2014. Gut microbiota dictates the metabolic <lb/>response of Drosophila to diet. J Exp Biol 217, 1894-1901. <lb/>Wu, Z., Song, L., Liu, S.Q., Huang, D., 2013. Independent and additive effects of glutamic acid <lb/>and methionine on yeast longevity. PLoS One 8, e79319. <lb/>Yamada, R., Deshpande, S.A., Bruce, K.D., Mak, E.M., Ja, W.W., 2015. Microbes Promote <lb/>Amino Acid Harvest to Rescue Undernutrition in Drosophila. Cell Rep. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>FIGURE LEGENDS <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1: (A) Two-way ANOVA analysis of data from C. Significant P values are highlighted in <lb/>bold typeface. (B) Heat map summary of P values from A. (C) Longitudinal analysis of weight, <lb/>protein, triglyceride and glucose content in male and female flies fed the indicated diets. Each <lb/>column shows the result of three separate measurements at the indicated times, except for <lb/>columns indicated with an &quot;X&quot;, which show the values of two separate measurements. Mean <lb/>values for each diet and time point were compared with the means of unmodified diets at the <lb/>same time with a Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons. *, p &lt; 0.05; ** p &lt; 0.01. <lb/>Figure 2: (A) Heat map summary of Chi-square values from table 1 showing the effects of the <lb/>respective diets on the longevity of male and female flies. Longer values correspond to <lb/>extended lifespans, and shorter values correspond to diminished lifespans. (B) Survival curves <lb/>of a wild strain of male Drosophila raised on an unmodified diet or on a diet supplemented with <lb/>glucose. (C) Survival curves of male Drosophila raised on an unmodified diet, or on a diet <lb/>supplemented with glucose for 5 days, 10 days, or permanently. (D) Results of Log-rank <lb/>(Mantel-Cox) test of data in panel B and C. All 2 and p values are relative to unmodified. <lb/>Figure 3: (A) Survival curves of female flies raised on unmodified or modified holidic diets for <lb/>ten days and then challenged by a chronic infection with V. cholerae C6706. (B) Results of Log-<lb/>rank (Mantel-Cox) test of data in panel A. All 2 and p values are relative to wild type. <lb/>Figure 4: (A) Actograms showing average hourly activity of flies fed an unmodified diet (holidic), <lb/>or a holidic diet supplemented with glucose or ethanol as indicated. Results are the mean of 20 <lb/>individual measurements, and error bars indicate standard errors. Shaded areas indicate <lb/>periods of darkness. (B) Periodograms of days 1-5 and 6-10 for flies raised on the respective <lb/>diets. (C) Total daily activity of flies raised on the respective diets. <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5: (A) Heat map summary showing abundance of bacterial genera present at greater <lb/>than 1% in midguts of male and female flies raised on different diets for 10 days. Each sample <lb/>consists of 5 flies. Abundance of each bacterial genus in a sample ranges from 0% (grey) to <lb/>100% (dark red) as indicated by the scale. (B) Summary showing the number of reads from 16S <lb/>sequencing and the results from both Shannon and Gini-Simpson diversity values of each <lb/>sample. <lb/>Figure 6: (A) Survival curves of males fed a holidic diet with or without glucose and raised <lb/>under conventional or germ-free (GF) conditions. (B) Results of Log-rank (Mantel-Cox) test of <lb/>data in panel A. <lb/>Figure 7: (A) Survival curves of chronically infected female flies fed a holidic diet with or without <lb/>glucose and raised under conventional or germ-free (GF) conditions. (B) Results of Log-rank <lb/>(Mantel-Cox) test of data in panel A. <lb/>Figure 8: (A) Survival curves of male esg&gt;InR or esg/+ flies raised on an unmodified holidic diet <lb/>or one supplemented with glucose. (B) Results of Log-rank (Mantel-Cox) test of data in panel A. <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1: <lb/>MALES <lb/>Diet <lb/>Median survival <lb/>Chi square <lb/>P value <lb/>Holidic <lb/>26 <lb/>Starch <lb/>29 <lb/>0.0005998 <lb/>0.9805 <lb/>Protein <lb/>25 <lb/>2.279 <lb/>0.1312 <lb/>Palmitic acid <lb/>25 <lb/>0.8032 <lb/>0.3701 <lb/>Diet <lb/>Median survival <lb/>Chi square <lb/>P value <lb/>Holidic <lb/>26 <lb/>Ethanol <lb/>28 <lb/>3.908 <lb/>0.0480 <lb/>Glucose <lb/>34 <lb/>34.35 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>FEMALES <lb/>Diet <lb/>Median survival <lb/>Chi square <lb/>P value <lb/>Holidic <lb/>38 <lb/>Starch <lb/>35.5 <lb/>3.685 <lb/>0.0549 <lb/>Protein <lb/>35 <lb/>6.332 <lb/>0.0119 <lb/>Palmitic acid <lb/>33 <lb/>8.796 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>Diet <lb/>Median survival <lb/>Chi square <lb/>P value <lb/>Holidic <lb/>31 <lb/>Ethanol <lb/>31.5 <lb/>0.8556 <lb/>0.3550 <lb/>Glucose <lb/>33 <lb/>6.832 <lb/>0.0090 <lb/>Table 1: Median survivals of male and female adult Drosophila raised on the respective diets. <lb/>Each table corresponds to a group of experiments that were performed at the same time and <lb/>under identical experimental conditions. For each sub-table, Chi square, and P values were <lb/>calculated with GraphPad Prism 6.0 and are reported relative to the corresponding control flies <lb/>raised on the holidic diet. </body>


	</text>
</tei>
