<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Expression of segment polarity genes in brachiopods <lb/>supports a nonsegmental ancestral role of engrailed for <lb/>bilaterians <lb/>Bruno C. Vellutini 1 and Andreas Hejnol 2* <lb/>1,2 Sars International Centre for Marine Molecular Biology, University of Bergen, <lb/>Thormøhlensgate 55, 5008 Bergen, Norway. <lb/>1 Email: bruno.vellutini@uib.no <lb/>2 Email: andreas.hejnol@uib.no <lb/>* Corresponding author. <lb/>Keywords: Brachiopoda, larvae, segmentation, boundary, engrailed, wnt1, hedgehog, <lb/>pax6, pax2/5/8 <lb/> Abstract <lb/>Brachiopods are benthic marine invertebrates that live enclosed in a bivalved shell. <lb/>Despite having a reduced and unsegmented trunk in the adult stage, brachiopod larvae <lb/>show putative segmented structures such as transverse ectodermal boundaries and <lb/>iterated coelomic sacs. Several molecular mechanisms of segmentation have been <lb/>described in animals considered to be segmented (i.e., the distantly related annelids, <lb/>arthropods and vertebrates), but far less is known about the role of these &quot;segmenta-<lb/>tion genes&quot; in other organisms. Here we investigate the expression of the arthropod <lb/>segment polarity genes engrailed, wnt1 and hedgehog in the development of bra-<lb/>chiopods-a group more closely related to the segmented annelids. Expression of <lb/>engrailed correlates with the development of an anterior nonsegmental ectodermal <lb/>boundary in the embryos of Terebratalia transversa and Novocrania anomala. Sur-<lb/>prisingly, wnt1 is expressed as a stripe adjacent to engrailed in T. transversa in the <lb/>same manner as in the parasegment boundaries of insects. Expression of hedgehog, <lb/>however, is restricted to the endoderm and is not compatible with a segment polarity <lb/>role. In addition, the putative engrailed regulators pax6 and pax2/5/8 encircle the <lb/>whole embryo and demarcate this anterior ectodermal boundary before engrailed. We <lb/>conclude brachiopod larvae might have a common anterior patterning involving the <lb/>expression of pax6, pax2/5/8 and engrailed. Despite key differences to other segment <lb/>boundaries (e.g., hedgehog expression), we show the characteristic adjacent stripes of <lb/>engrailed and wnt1 can occur in a nonsegmental ectodermal boundary. A comparison <lb/>among bilaterians suggests the ancestral expression of engrailed during early develop-<lb/>ment was nonsegmental and conceivably related to the embryonic head/trunk bound-<lb/>ary. Our data implies that engrailed was independently recruited to the segment <lb/>boundaries of annelids and arthropods and to other different developmental bound-<lb/>aries during evolution. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Background <lb/>Animals with bilateral symmetry show a great diversity of serially repeated structures <lb/>along the body. Neural ganglia, excretory organs, coeloms, and a variety of other tis-<lb/>sues can be individually arranged in a serial manner or combined into repetitive body <lb/>segments. The repetition of parts with anteroposterior polarity along the body axis is a <lb/>defining characteristic of animal segmentation (Budd 2001; Hannibal &amp; Patel 2013; <lb/>Minelli &amp; Fusco 2004). Groups like annelids (e.g., earthworms), arthropods (e.g., <lb/>insects) and vertebrates (e.g., humans) segment their embryonic tissues from anterior <lb/>to posterior and have a major part of their adult body organized into repeated units. <lb/>Therefore, these groups have been the main focus of studies on the evolution of seg-<lb/>mentation. <lb/>Comparative developmental data revealed a number of similarities in the molecular <lb/>mechanisms of segmentation between arthropods and vertebrates (Damen 2007; <lb/>Davis &amp; Patel 1999; Kimmel 1996; Patel 2003; Seaver 2003; Tautz 2004), that were <lb/>taken as evidence to support the homology of bilaterian segmentation (De Robertis <lb/>1997, 2008; Dray et al. 2010; Kimmel 1996). However, annelids, arthropods and ver-<lb/>tebrates belong to distinct branches of bilaterally symmetrical animals, spiralians, <lb/>ecdysozoans and deuterostomes, respectively (Figure 1A), suggesting alternatively <lb/>that these molecular similarities are evolutionary convergences (Abouheif et al. 1997; <lb/>Chipman 2010; Minelli &amp; Fusco 2004). The sole comparison between such distantly <lb/>related groups can be misleading for tracing the evolution of a character (e.g., trunk <lb/>segmentation) because the ancestral conditions of related taxa are unknown. Since <lb/>developmental mechanisms can be coopted to nonhomologous structures (Shubin et <lb/>al. 2009), knowing the phylogenetic context of a character is essential to distinguish <lb/>homology from convergence. Furthermore, segmentation is not restricted to annelids, <lb/>arthropods and vertebrates. It also occurs in other bilaterians usually considered as <lb/>pseudosegmented or unsegmented (Budd 2001; Minelli &amp; Fusco 2004; Scholtz 2002). <lb/>To fully understand the conservation of gene networks in the evolution of segmenta-<lb/>tion, it is important to uncover the expression and role of genes guiding body segmen-<lb/>tation of annelids, arthropods and vertebrates in the development of other animals, as <lb/>well as to understand their relationship to other serially repeated structures. <lb/>A crucial mechanism of segmentation is the ability to establish tissue boundaries dur-<lb/>ing animal development (Dahmann et al. 2011). One of the best studied developmen-<lb/>tal boundaries are the parasegmental boundaries of the fruit fly Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster. Fly segmentation occurs by the simultaneous division of the trunk into <lb/>fourteen parasegments, developmental regions that lie out of register with the larval <lb/>segments (Martinez-Arias &amp; Lawrence 1985). At the molecular level, the parasegment <lb/>boundary is established by the abutting domains of engrailed (en) and wingless (wnt1) <lb/>(Ingham et al. 1988) and maintained by a positive feedback loop mediated by hedge-<lb/>hog (hh) (Ingham &amp; Martinez Arias 1992). Therefore, en, wnt1 and hh are commonly <lb/>referred to as segment polarity genes (Ingham 1991; Martinez Arias et al. 1988; <lb/>Tabata &amp; Kornberg 1994), and their expression and function seems to be conserved <lb/>among the body segments of other arthropods (Damen 2007; Hughes &amp; Kaufman <lb/>2002; Mellenthin et al. 2006; Nagy 1994). Similarity in the expression of segment <lb/>polarity genes was used to claim homology of arthropod and annelid segmentation <lb/>(Dray et al. 2010; Prud&apos;homme et al. 2003), however their role in annelids is unclear. <lb/>In Platynereis dumerilii, the expression of en, wnt1 and hh supports a role in estab-<lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>lishing the segment boundaries of this animal (Prud&apos;homme et al. 2003), whereas <lb/>other annelid species do not show a spatial correlation of these genes with the seg-<lb/>mental boundaries (Seaver &amp; Kaneshige 2006). Thus, it is of utmost importance to <lb/>investigate the segment polarity genes in groups closely related to annelids and arthro-<lb/>pods to infer their ancestral developmental functions, and verify if similar expression <lb/>patterns are deployed in different morphological structures. <lb/>Brachiopods are bivalved marine invertebrates closely related to annelids (Laumer et <lb/>al. 2015) (Figure 1A). Even though adult brachiopods do not have a segmented trunk, <lb/>the larval stages of different groups show putative repeated structures in different <lb/>parts of their body. Externally, brachiopod larvae exhibit two to four lobes along the <lb/>anteroposterior axis divided by transverse ectodermal boundaries. In the past, brachio-<lb/>pod larval lobes were homologized to annelid segments (Balfour 1880), but the obser-<lb/>vation that the ectodermal boundaries do not involve the underlying mesoderm weak-<lb/>ened this hypothesis (Conklin 1902). Mesoderm morphology, however, is variable <lb/>between brachiopod species, and can be unsegmented or indeed partitioned into two <lb/>or four pairs of coelomic sacs (Hyman 1959; Nielsen 1991). The existence of brachio-<lb/>pod larvae with serially arranged mesodermal coelomic sacs has revived the idea that <lb/>brachiopods had a segmented ancestor (Balavoine &amp; Adoutte 2003; Temereva &amp; <lb/>Malakhov 2011). Therefore, the putative segmentation of brachiopod larvae is key to <lb/>comprehend the evolution of segmentation mechanisms because it provides a closer <lb/>phylogenetic comparison for the role of the segment polarity genes in the annelids. <lb/>To investigate the developmental and molecular background of the repeated structures <lb/>of brachiopod larvae, we studied the trilobed larva with unsegmented mesoderm of <lb/>Terebratalia transversa (John A. Long and Stephen A. Stricker 1991) (Figure 1B), <lb/>and the bilobed larva with four pairs of coelomic sacs of Novocrania anomala (Free-<lb/>man 2000; Nielsen 1991) (Figure 1B). In these two species of brachiopods, we ana-<lb/>lyzed the expression of the segment polarity genes en, wnt1, and the core components <lb/>of the Hedgehog signaling pathway to test whether their expression correlate with the <lb/>development of the ectodermal and mesodermal boundaries of T. transversa and N. <lb/>anomala larvae. Furthermore, we examined upstream control genes of en and discov-<lb/>ered unexpected similarities in the molecular profile of a brachiopod larval lobe <lb/>boundary and a vertebrate brain boundary. <lb/>Results <lb/>Ectodermal and mesodermal boundaries of larval brachiopods <lb/>In T. transversa, gastrulation occurs by invagination and results in a radially symmet-<lb/>ric gastrula (Figure 2A). After anteroposterior axis elongation (Figure 2B), the <lb/>embryos adopt the definitive bilateral morphology (Figure 2C). At this stage, a trans-<lb/>verse ectodermal furrow (indentation of the epidermis) appears around the circumfer-<lb/>ence of the bilateral gastrula extending from the blastopore lips above the midline to <lb/>most of the dorsal side (Figure 2C; Figure 3A). Epidermal cells abutting the posterior <lb/>border of the furrow are more elongated along the furrow outline when compared to <lb/>the isodiametric shape of anterior and posterior cells (Figure 3B). The ectodermal fur-<lb/>row at the bilateral gastrula is the first morphological manifestation of the boundary <lb/>between the apical and mantle lobes in T. transversa (apical/mantle boundary). At <lb/>subsequent developmental stages, this furrow deepens and clearly divides the apical <lb/>lobe from the remainder of the embryo (Figure 2D; Figure 3C,D). T. transversa <lb/>exhibits a third lobe at the posterior end, the pedicle lobe (Figure 2E). The boundary <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>between the mantle and pedicle lobes (mantle/pedicle boundary) is identified by the <lb/>narrowing of the posterior portion of the embryo (Figure 2D) and by the subsequent <lb/>outgrowth of the mantle lobe (Figure 2E). The morphology of the mantle/pedicle <lb/>boundary differs from the apical/mantle boundary because it is demarcated by an <lb/>ectodermal fold, rather than an indentation furrow. Thus, despite the superficial <lb/>impression of ectodermal segmentation in the brachiopod trilobed larva, these bound-<lb/>aries are not repeated, but unique structures of the larval body. N. anomala also gas-<lb/>trulates by invagination and elongates along the anteroposterior axis (Figure 2F-H). <lb/>Its apical and mantle lobes are demarcated by an ectodermal furrow, as seen in T. <lb/>transversa (Figure 2H-J; Figure 3E-G), but the larva of N. anomala does not form a <lb/>pedicle lobe (Figure 2J; Figure 3H). Thus, the morphology of the apical/mantle <lb/>boundary is conserved between both species suggesting it is an ancestral feature of <lb/>larval brachiopods. <lb/>In the trilobed larva of T. transversa, the mesoderm is unsegmented and has a distinct <lb/>anterior portion in the apical lobe, an umbrella-like mesoderm in the mantle lobe con-<lb/>nected to the chaetae sacs and, finally, an arrowhead-shaped pedicle portion (Figure <lb/>3I-L). Unlike T. transversa, the mesoderm of N. anomala has lateral constrictions <lb/>individualizing each of the four pairs of coelomic sacs (Figure 3M) while remaining <lb/>interconnected more medially in the ventral side (Figure 3N). From the second, third <lb/>and fourth coelomic pouches we observe dorsal projections of the mesoderm associ-<lb/>ated to the three pairs of chaetae sac primordia (Figure 3N,O). In the bilobed larva, <lb/>this arrangement is compacted and an extensive musculature develops; coelomic spa-<lb/>ces are reduced (Figure 3O,P). Thus, the segmented appearance of N. anomala meso-<lb/>derm is related to its partitioning into coelomic sacs with tight association to the seri-<lb/>ated chaetae sacs on the dorsal side. <lb/>Expression of the segment polarity genes hh, en and wnt1 <lb/>In order to understand the developmental and phylogenetic relationship of the ecto-<lb/>dermal and mesodermal boundaries of brachiopods with those of the body segments <lb/>of arthropods and annelids, we analyzed the expression of the segment polarity genes <lb/>en, wnt1 and hh during the embryonic development of T. transversa and N. anomala. <lb/>Expression of hh localizes to the blastoporal lip and invaginating endomesoderm dur-<lb/>ing the early gastrulation of T. transversa (Figure 4A1); in later stages it is restricted <lb/>to the endoderm (Figure 4A2-A4). In N. anomala, we detected a transverse ventral <lb/>stripe of hh near the animal pole and (additionally) along the blastoporal lip at the <lb/>asymmetric gastrula (Figure 4B1). Endodermal transcripts only became visible at the <lb/>bilateral gastrula (Figure 4B2). The anterior ventral stripe of hh expression in N. <lb/>anomala is reduced and disappears in the bilobed larva while endodermal transcripts <lb/>continue to be expressed (Figure 4B3-B4). Therefore, the expression of hh orthologs <lb/>in T. transversa and N. anomala does not correlate spatially or temporally with the <lb/>development of the ectodermal larval lobe boundaries. <lb/>Since the Hedgehog ligand can signal across embryonic layers, we further analyzed <lb/>the expression of the Hedgehog receptors ptc and smo and the transcription factor gli. <lb/>Transcripts are expressed in the mesoderm of T. transversa and N. anomala, as well as <lb/>in the ectodermal apical and mantle territories (Additional file 1: Figure S1). Alto-<lb/>gether, the expression of hh and downstream pathway components does not support a <lb/>connection of this signaling pathway with the ectodermal boundaries of both brachio-<lb/>pod species. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Transcripts of T. transversa en were first detected in the radial gastrula as an almost <lb/>complete ring in the midregion of the embryo (Additional file 2: Figure S2A). Expres-<lb/>sion fades at the anterior end and subsequently clears from the posterior end leaving a <lb/>pair of lateral domains of en in the late radial gastrula (Additional file 2: Figure S2A-<lb/>H) and asymmetric gastrula (Figure 4C1). These domains extend ventrally and dor-<lb/>sally without reaching the blastopore on the ventral side (Figure 4C2). Transcripts of <lb/>en border the apical/mantle furrow in the subsequent stage (Figure 4C3) and fade in <lb/>the developed larvae (Figure 4C4). In N. anomala a single dorsal ectodermal stripe of <lb/>en expression occurs in the radial gastrula (Additional file 2: Figure S2I) and a second <lb/>stripe emerges at the posterior end of the asymmetric gastrula (Figure 4D1; Additional <lb/>file 2: Figure S2J). Similar to T. transversa, en stripes extend ventrally without reach-<lb/>ing the embryo midline (Figure 4D1-D3) and fade in the developed larva (Figure D4). <lb/>Therefore, expression of en is consistent between the two species, with the <lb/>apical/mantle furrow forming immediately anterior to a pair of en stripes. <lb/>In addition to the striped domains demarcating the apical/mantle furrow, we identified <lb/>two more posterior en territories on the ventral and dorsal regions of larval bra-<lb/>chiopods, localized in the anterior-most region of the pedicle lobe. A pair of en ecto-<lb/>dermal bands initiate on the ventral side of T. transversa associated with the blasto-<lb/>pore (Figure 4C2). On the opposite side, at the center of the dorsal surface, we <lb/>detected a triangular-shaped domain of en expression (Figure 4C2; Additional file 2: <lb/>Figure S2N-O). Expression is still present in the trilobed larva of T. transversa (Fig-<lb/>ure 4C4). A reciprocal dorsal domain also occurs in N. anomala bilateral gastrula <lb/>(Additional file 2: Figure S2K) and localizes to the shell rudiment in the bilobed larva <lb/>(Additional file 2: Figure S2L,M). <lb/>Until the asymmetric gastrula, transcripts of en in T. transversa are restricted to the <lb/>ectoderm (Figure 4C1,G). Mesodermal expression of en only initiates at the bilateral <lb/>gastrula (Figure 4C2,H). A thin line of en-expressing cells suggests contiguous <lb/>expression between ectoderm and mesoderm (Figure 4C2,J). Transcripts of en form a <lb/>pair of mesodermal bands posterior to the ventral projections of the mantle mesoderm <lb/>(Figure 4I,K,L). In the asymmetric gastrula of N. anomala we only detected weak en <lb/>expression in the mesoderm (Figure 4M). Expression of en becomes stronger localiz-<lb/>ing directly inner to the lateral ectodermal domains (Figure 4N). This region corre-<lb/>sponds to the posterior portion of the second pair of coelomic pouches. Transcripts of <lb/>en are also detected in the posterior region of the third pair of coeloms in the bilobed <lb/>larva, but not in the first or fourth coelomic sacs (Figure 4O-R). Expression in the <lb/>second coelomic sac localizes to the medial portion of the mesoderm (Figure 4P,Qi) <lb/>while the expression in the third coelomic sac is more lateral and ventral (Figure 4P <lb/>inset, Qii). Overall, the mesodermal expression of en occurs in contiguity with the <lb/>preceding ectodermal domains in both species. <lb/>Expression of wnt1 in the asymmetric gastrula of T. transversa is associated with the <lb/>posterior portion of the blastopore (Figure 4E1) and shows no spatial correlation to <lb/>the lateral en domains (Figure 5A). At the bilateral gastrula, a transverse pair of <lb/>stripes of wnt1 expression appears in the apical lobe of T. transversa bordering the <lb/>apical/mantle furrow anteriorly (Figure 4E2). The expression abuts en at the <lb/>apical/mantle furrow without overlap (Figure 5B). In the pedicle lobe, en partially <lb/>overlaps with the posterior domain of wnt1 (Figure 4E2; Figure 5B). Transcripts of <lb/>wnt1 are not present on the dorsal surface at this stage (Figure 4E2; Additional file 2: <lb/>Figure S2P). As the apical/mantle furrow deepens in the bilobed larva, wnt1 and en <lb/>transcripts resolve into well-defined non-overlapping stripes in T. transversa (Figure <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>5C). Stripes demarcate precisely the morphological furrow at the apical/mantle <lb/>boundary of T. transversa with wnt1 positioned anterior and en positioned posterior to <lb/>the furrow (Figure 5C). At the bilobed larva, wnt1 expression initiates on the dorsal <lb/>side (Figure 4E3; Additional file 2: Figure S2Q) and we observe tight coexpression of <lb/>en and wnt1 at the dorsal and ventral domains (Figure 5C). Expression of wnt1 in the <lb/>apical lobe fades in the trilobed larva (Figure 4E4) while an additional stripe of wnt1 <lb/>encircles a subdivision of the pedicle lobe (Figure 4E4). <lb/>Differently, N. anomala does not have wnt1 domains in the apical lobe and transcripts <lb/>are exclusively localized at the posterior end associated with the blastopore (Figure <lb/>4F1-F4). While en and wnt1 are coexpressed on the ventral and dorsal territories of T. <lb/>transversa, we did not detect any coexpression sites for these genes in N. anomala. <lb/>Thus, the expression of wnt1 at the apical/mantle furrow is not consistent between <lb/>brachiopods, and only T. transversa has wnt1 stripes demarcating the morphology of <lb/>the furrow. <lb/>Expression of the putative engrailed regulators pax6, pax2/5/8 and <lb/>fgf8/17/18 <lb/>The only gene consistently related to the apical/mantle furrow in both brachiopod lar-<lb/>vae is en. Early expression of en, however, does not encircle the circumference of the <lb/>embryo (Figure 4C1) suggesting that there must be factors upstream positioning the <lb/>apical/mantle boundary. Regulators of en are mostly known from the body segmenta-<lb/>tion of fruit flies and the brain development of vertebrates. In D. melanogaster, activ-<lb/>ity of even-skipped (eve or evx) position en stripes by repressing sloppy paired (slp or <lb/>foxg), which in turn limits en expression anterior to the parasegment boundary (Cadi-<lb/>gan et al. 1994; Fujioka et al. 2002). However, expression of eve and slp does not cor-<lb/>relate to the en domains at the apical/mantle boundary of T. transversa; eve is <lb/>expressed at the posterior end of the pedicle lobe, while slp is expressed at the anterior <lb/>portion of the apical lobe (Santagata et al. 2012). In the vertebrate brain, en and wnt1 <lb/>play a crucial role in the establishment of the mid/hindbrain boundary (Rhinn &amp; <lb/>Brand 2001). In the midbrain, pax2 regulates the expression of en in a positive feed-<lb/>back loop, while it represses pax6 (Okafuji et al. 1999). Expression of pax6 in the <lb/>forebrain downregulates the expression of en1 and pax2 in the midbrain, while en was <lb/>shown to directly repress the expression of pax6 (Araki &amp; Nakamura 1999; Mat-<lb/>sunaga et al. 2000; Scholpp et al. 2003). The regulation between pax6, en and <lb/>pax2/5/8 results in complementary expression patterns that define the boundary <lb/>between the diencephalon and mesencephalon (Araki &amp; Nakamura 1999; Matsunaga <lb/>et al. 2000) dependent on fgf8 signaling from the mid/hindbrain boundary (Scholpp et <lb/>al. 2003). Thus, we analyzed the expression of the brachiopod orthologs of pax6, <lb/>pax2/5/8 and fgf8/17/18 in relation to the en expression and the development of the <lb/>apical/mantle furrow. <lb/>Expression of pax6 in the larva of T. transversa localizes to the apical lobe and is <lb/>related to eye development (Passamaneck et al. 2011). During earlier stages in T. <lb/>transversa, however, we detected pax6 transcripts in a broad pair of anterior domains <lb/>(Figure 6A1). The expression of pax6 occupies the entire anterior half of the radial <lb/>gastrula and localizes to the apical lobe in subsequent stages (Figure 6A2-A4). <lb/>Expression of pax6 in N. anomala initiates as an apical ring in the radial gastrula (Fig-<lb/>ure 6B1) and localizes to the apical lobe during later stages (Figure 6B2-B4). In both <lb/>species the posterior limit of pax6 expression borders the apical/mantle furrow. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>T. transversa pax2/5/8 expression begins as a posterior half-ring in the radial gastrula <lb/>(Figure 6C1) and shows a narrow overlap with the pax6 territory at the future <lb/>apical/mantle furrow (Figure 7A,B). In the asymmetric gastrula pax2/5/8 transcripts <lb/>cover the whole extension of the mantle ectoderm except chaetae sac primordia and <lb/>blastoporal lips (Figure 6C2). The lateral domains of en expression are contained <lb/>within the mantle lobe domain of pax2/5/8 (Figure 7G). The anterior limit of pax2/5/8 <lb/>expression extends across the apical/mantle furrow (Figure 6C3,C4) and overlaps <lb/>with pax6 expression at the posteriormost region of the apical lobe (Figure 7C,D). <lb/>The fact that the pax2/5/8 domain transpasses the ectodermal furrow was corroborated <lb/>by the combined expression with en (Figure 7H-J). The arrangement between pax6, <lb/>pax2/5/8 and en domains is maintained in the bilobed larva (Figure 7D,J) but dissoci-<lb/>ates at the onset of mantle outgrowth. Expression of pax6 becomes restricted dorsally, <lb/>and pax2/5/8 expression localizes to the edge of the growing mantle lobe (Figure <lb/>7E,F). Similar to T. transversa, N. anomala pax2/5/8 expression occurs in a pos-<lb/>terodorsal territory in the mantle lobe (Figure 6D1) limited by the apical lobe (Figure <lb/>6D2,D3). Differently than T. transversa, we observe mesodermal expression of <lb/>pax2/5/8 in N. anomala, which correlates with coelom formation (Figure 6D4). Tran-<lb/>scripts of pax2/5/8 are localized to two pairs of domains between the chaetae sacs of <lb/>N. anomala larval mesoderm (Figure 6D4). In summary, pax6 and pax2/5/8 are <lb/>expressed in early complementary domains encircling the whole embryo with a nar-<lb/>row overlap. The posterior limit of pax6 matches the apical/mantle furrow and abuts <lb/>the lateral patches of en contained within the mantle lobe domain of pax2/5/8. <lb/>In the vertebrate brain, fgf8 expression borders the mid/hindbrain boundary with the <lb/>adjacent expression of wnt1 (Danielian &amp; McMahon 1996). We detected transcripts of <lb/>fgf8/17/18 in an anterior half-ring of T. transversa radial gastrula (Figure 6E1). In the <lb/>asymmetric gastrula, fgf8/17/18 is expressed in transverse ventral bands reaching the <lb/>blastopore lips and two pairs of circular spots positioned laterally and dorsally (Figure <lb/>6E2). A new domain at the anterior tip and an additional pair of lateral spots are acti-<lb/>vated in the bilateral gastrula (Figure 6E3). The circular spots of fgf8/17/18 positive <lb/>cells correspond to the developing chaetae sacs (Figure 7K,N) and are cleared from <lb/>en and pax2/5/8 expression (Figure 7I,K). Ventral bands of fgf8/17/18 do not border <lb/>the stripes of en posterior to the furrow (Figure 7L,M). In the bilobed larva of T. <lb/>transversa the expression in the chaetae sacs becomes interconnected, the ventral <lb/>domains in the apical lobe faded and a new domain appeared at the posterior tip (Fig-<lb/>ure 6E4). In N. anomala, fgf8/17/18 is not expressed in the radial gastrula (Figure <lb/>6F1). Expression initiates in the asymmetric gastrula with an anterior ventral band and <lb/>a more posterior domain encircling the vegetal portion near the blastopore (Figure <lb/>6F2). The anterior band extends dorsally while the posterior domain forms a band that <lb/>demarcates the anterior-most region of the mantle lobe (Figure 6F3). Similarly to T. <lb/>transversa, chaetae primordia also express fgf8/17/18 (Figure 6F3,F4). Thus, the <lb/>expression of fgf8/17/18 is mainly associated with the chaetae sacs in both species and <lb/>does not show clear correlation with ectodermal boundaries. <lb/>Over-activation of the Wnt pathway in T. transversa <lb/>Because Wnt signaling has an essential role in the axial patterning of metazoans <lb/>(Petersen &amp; Reddien 2009), we investigated if perturbing the canonical Wnt pathway <lb/>affects the development of larval boundaries in T. transversa. Over-activation of the <lb/>Wnt pathway with 1-azakenpaullone (Kunick et al. 2004) at the mid-blastula and <lb/>radial gastrula stage leads to the posteriorization of the embryonic axis (e.g. expansion <lb/>of the pedicle lobe) and a correspondent anterior shift in the expression domains of <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>en, wnt1 and pax6 in T. transversa (Figure 8). Embryos treated at the mid-blastula <lb/>stage show no morphological or molecular traces of a mantle lobe (Figure 8B,R,S), <lb/>but form a distinct anterior portion which folds over the over-developed pedicle lobe <lb/>(Figure 8R). Interestingly, embryos treated at a later stage (radial gastrula) develop <lb/>bilateral stubs, which we interpret as incipient mantle tissue due to their mid-body <lb/>position (Figure 8J). Finally, the ectodermal furrow does not form at the expected api-<lb/>cal/mantle boundary in embryos treated at the radial gastrula (Figure 8J; Additional <lb/>file 3: Figure S3). While all treated embryos show an anterior shift in the expression <lb/>of en, wnt1 and pax6, early treatments at the mid-blastula stage entirely abolish the <lb/>anterior domains of en and wnt1 (Figure 8D,F), but do not suppress the expression of <lb/>pax6 (Figure 8H). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Segmentation is an unequivocal feature of annelids, arthropods and vertebrates, and <lb/>widespread to different degrees in other animals with bilateral symmetry, yet we have <lb/>little idea on how segmentation mechanisms have evolved and how the segmented <lb/>structures between these lineages are related. One approach to better understand the <lb/>evolution of segmentation is to expand the taxonomic sampling. Studying common <lb/>segmentation genes in other animals can help distinguish which molecular pathways <lb/>are unique to segmentation and reveal additional-and possibly ancestral-roles of <lb/>these genes. In this sense, brachiopods are well suited because their larval bodies have <lb/>putative segmented structures divided by ectodermal and mesodermal boundaries. <lb/>But, do larval brachiopods have any kind of body segmentation? <lb/>Larval brachiopods do not have body wall segmentation <lb/>The body wall of T. transversa larva is divided into three lobes by two transverse <lb/>ectodermal boundaries. If these lobes were repeated units, we would expect to find <lb/>similar morphological characters and molecular topologies at these boundaries. <lb/>Instead, the apical/mantle boundary is demarcated by an indentation furrow while the <lb/>mantle/pedicle boundary is demarcated by an ectodermal fold. These morphological <lb/>differences indicate the lobe boundaries of a trilobed brachiopod larva are not <lb/>repeated, but unique structures of the larval body. In addition, the molecular profiles <lb/>at the apical/mantle and mantle/pedicle boundaries differ, further supporting the idea <lb/>that the body wall of brachiopod larvae has no segmentation. <lb/>We found a mosaic of similarities and differences in the patterns of gene expression of <lb/>T. transversa and N. anomala. By checking the consistency of a particular domain <lb/>between the two brachiopod species, we determined which expression patterns are <lb/>likely to reflect the ground pattern of brachiopod development. Therefore, the <lb/>apical/mantle boundary is characterized by the early overlapping expression of pax6 <lb/>and pax2/5/8 in the apical and mantle lobes, respectively, with the latter containing a <lb/>pair of lateral en domains (Figure 9A). Expression of en expands lining the posterior <lb/>border of the furrow with the abutting domain of pax6 anteriorly (Figure 9A). Surpris-<lb/>ingly, the pedicle lobe domain of en in the trilobed larva of T. transversa has a recip-<lb/>rocal domain in the bilobed larva of N. anomala, even though there is no morphologi-<lb/>cal evidence of a pedicle lobe or mantle/pedicle boundary in the latter. This observa-<lb/>tion suggests that two pairs of lateral en domains is the ancestral condition for bra-<lb/>chiopods independent of the trilobed or bilobed larval morphology. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Over-activation of the Wnt pathway abolishes en and wnt1 but not pax6 <lb/>expression at the apical/mantle boundary <lb/>Over-activation of the Wnt pathway caused an expansion of the pedicle lobe and of <lb/>the domains of gene expression therein, suppressed the formation of the mantle lobe <lb/>and of the apical/mantle furrow, and shifted other expression domains anteriorly. <lb/>Because embryos treated at the mid-blastula stage show no morphological or molecu-<lb/>lar traces of a mantle lobe, we suggest the boundary between the anterior and poste-<lb/>rior portions of treated larvae does not correspond to any of the wild type boundaries, <lb/>but to a unique apical/pedicle boundary defined by an ectodermal fold. However, <lb/>embryos treated at later stages (radial gastrula) show bilateral stubs of mantle tissue, <lb/>suggesting the specification of the mantle lobe of T. transversa might initiate between <lb/>mid-blastula and radial gastrula stage. The period between mid-blastula and early gas-<lb/>trulation can also play a role in the positioning of the anterior domains of en and wnt1 <lb/>-but not in the establishment of pax6 expression. Disturbance of en and wnt1 expres-<lb/>sion in the mid-blastula treatments suggests these anterior domains are not yet estab-<lb/>lished in the embryo, and their positioning is affected by the over-activation of the <lb/>Wnt pathway. Differently, the consistent expression of pax6 between mid-blastula and <lb/>radial gastrula treatments indicates the anterior domain of pax6 was not affected by <lb/>the azakenpaullone, suggesting its specification must occur before the mid-blastula <lb/>stage or be independent of the Wnt pathway. Thus, our experimental data suggests <lb/>that disturbing T. transversa Wnt signaling affects the development of the mantle lobe <lb/>and the morphology of the apical/mantle boundary, and that pax6 might have an ear-<lb/>lier upstream role in the embryonic body patterning of brachiopods. <lb/>Candidate genes are not iterated through all four partitions of N. <lb/>anomala mesoderm <lb/>While there is little evidence for body wall segmentation in larval brachiopods, the <lb/>mesoderm of N. anomala is clearly divided into four pairs of coelomic sacs. Do any <lb/>of the genes correlate with its mesoderm segmentation? Expression of en borders the <lb/>posterior boundary of coelomic sacs in the mesoderm of N. anomala. However, these <lb/>mesodermal domains are only detected in the second and third coelomic sacs. Inter-<lb/>estingly, the mesodermal domains initiate adjacent to the preceding ectodermal <lb/>domains of en suggesting the ectoderm might signal to the mesoderm during brachio-<lb/>pod development. Thus, en expression is compatible with a segmentation role only in <lb/>two out of four coeloms of the mesoderm of N. anomala. In fact, none of the other <lb/>genes expressed in the mesoderm of N. anomala (pax2/5/8, ptc, smo and gli) show <lb/>iterated patterns throughout the four coelomic sacs. In addition, en, ptc, smo and gli, <lb/>but not pax2/5/8, are also expressed in the unsegmented mesoderm of T. transversa <lb/>indicating that it is premature to assume a segmentation role for these genes in the <lb/>mesoderm of N. anomala. How does the gene expression in the mesoderm of N. <lb/>anomala compare to the segmented mesoderm of other animals? <lb/>Expression of en in annelids is restricted to mesodermal patches and does not resem-<lb/>ble the patterns in brachiopods (Prud&apos;homme et al. 2003; Seaver &amp; Kaneshige 2006). <lb/>Even though, in both brachiopods and annelids, en expression in the mesoderm seems <lb/>to be connected to the en expression in the ectoderm (Seaver &amp; Kaneshige 2006). <lb/>Expression of en in N. anomala mesoderm, despite not being repeated, is similar to <lb/>the more distantly related amphioxus (Holland et al. 1997) and onychophorans (Eriks-<lb/>son et al. 2009; Wedeen et al. 1997) with en expression localized to the posterior por-<lb/>tion of mesodermal somites. However, the actual role of a posterior en domain in the <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>mesoderm is unknown and requires further investigation in these animals. In contrast, <lb/>the role of en in the body wall segmentation has been thoroughly studied. <lb/>Gene expression does not support a typical segment polarity role in <lb/>brachiopods <lb/>Segment polarity genes are the hallmark of arthropod segmentation. We investigated <lb/>whether the expression of en, wnt1 and hh orthologs in brachiopods is compatible <lb/>with a putative segment polarity role. The parasegment of arthropods is characterized <lb/>by a cell population expressing en and hh adjacent to an anterior cell population <lb/>expressing wnt1, ptc, smo and gli (Figure 9C). This stands in contrast to brachiopods <lb/>where transcripts of hh are not detected in en-expressing cells, and ptc, smo, and gli <lb/>are not coexpressed with wnt1 at any developmental stage (Figure 9C). Thus, these <lb/>differences in the gene expression do not support the presence of a typical segment <lb/>polarity role in larval brachiopods. <lb/>On the other hand, we made the striking observation that en and wnt1 are expressed as <lb/>adjacent stripes demarcating the apical/mantle furrow of the brachiopod T. transversa. <lb/>Such spatial arrangement is not only a characteristic feature of D. melanogaster <lb/>parasegments, but a well conserved pattern in the segmentation of other arthropods <lb/>(Damen 2007; Hughes &amp; Kaufman 2002; Mellenthin et al. 2006; Nagy 1994). <lb/>Remarkably, the adjacent expression of en and wnt1 also demarcates the segment <lb/>boundaries of one annelid, P. dumerilii (Prud&apos;homme et al. 2003). It was suggested <lb/>that this similarity reflects an evolutionary conservation of segmentation supporting <lb/>the homology between annelid segments and arthropod parasegments (Prud&apos;homme <lb/>et al. 2003). However, distinguishing homology from convergence requires the recov-<lb/>ery of the ancestral character state for each group, which in turn requires the compara-<lb/>tive analysis of ingroup variability. While en and wnt1 have a conserved role in <lb/>arthropod segmentation, the expression of segment polarity genes in annelids is more <lb/>variable and does not support a role in segment formation (Seaver 2003). <lb/>First, the spatial relationship of en expression and segment boundaries differs between <lb/>species. It occurs at the posterior portion of segments in the leech Helobdella triseri-<lb/>alis (Lans et al. 1993; Wedeen &amp; Weisblat 1991) and Capitella teleta (Seaver &amp; <lb/>Kaneshige 2006), at the anterior portion in P. dumerilii (Prud&apos;homme et al. 2003) and <lb/>Chaetopterus sp. (Seaver et al. 2001), and not associated with segments in Hydroides <lb/>elegans (Seaver &amp; Kaneshige 2006) and Pristina leidyi (Bely &amp; Wray 2001). Second, <lb/>en expression can be restricted to individual cells (Bely &amp; Wray 2001; Lans et al. <lb/>1993; Wedeen &amp; Weisblat 1991), discontinuous patches (Seaver &amp; Kaneshige 2006) <lb/>or fuller stripes lining the segment boundary (Prud&apos;homme et al. 2003); only the latter <lb/>supporting a role in segment formation. Third, the temporal relationship of en expres-<lb/>sion and the morphological segmentation varies, and only in P. dumerilii and C. teleta <lb/>is en expressed in stripes before the morphology is visible (Prud&apos;homme et al. 2003; <lb/>Seaver &amp; Kaneshige 2006). In fact, with the exception of P. dumerilii (Dray et al. <lb/>2010; Prud&apos;homme et al. 2003), the expression of en is not compatible with a segmen-<lb/>tation role in most annelids investigated so far, i.e., the leech H. triserialis (Lans et al. <lb/>1993; Seaver &amp; Shankland 2001; Wedeen &amp; Weisblat 1991), P. leidyi (Bely &amp; Wray <lb/>2001), Chaetopterus sp. (Seaver et al. 2001), C. teleta and H. elegans (Seaver &amp; <lb/>Kaneshige 2006). <lb/>Expression of other segment polarity genes in annelids is much less known but still <lb/>inconsistent between species. In P. dumerilii, expression of both wnt1 and hh supports <lb/>a role in segment formation (Dray et al. 2010; Prud&apos;homme et al. 2003). In contrast, <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>data from the only other annelid where wnt1 has been investigated does not support a <lb/>role in segmentation (Seaver &amp; Kaneshige 2006). Expression of hh is also not com-<lb/>patible with a segmentation role in Helobdella robusta (Kang et al. 2003) or C. teleta <lb/>(Seaver &amp; Kaneshige 2006). Therefore, expression of segment polarity genes is vari-<lb/>able even within the homologous segments of annelids. For this reason, the ancestral <lb/>character state regarding the expression of en, wnt1 and hh in annelids and their rela-<lb/>tion to segmentation remains unresolved. <lb/>In summary, the expression of segment polarity genes is greatly conserved in arthro-<lb/>pods, but variable in annelids and brachiopods (inconsistent wnt1 expression between <lb/>T. transversa and N. anomala). This variation weakens the idea that segment polarity <lb/>genes had an ancestral segmentation role in annelids and renders uncertain if wnt1 <lb/>was expressed at the apical/mantle boundary of a brachiopod ancestor. It suggests the <lb/>adjacent expression of en and wnt1 might be a convergent pattern between one <lb/>annelid (P. dumerilii) and one brachiopod (T. transversa). However, additional data in <lb/>annelids are needed to recover the ancestral state for the expression of wnt1 and hh <lb/>and maybe expose the developmental basis for the recurrent evolution of segment <lb/>polarity like patterns. In any case, we show that abutting stripes of en and wnt1 are not <lb/>exclusive for the body segmentation of annelids and arthropods-it also occurs in a <lb/>nonsegmental boundary of a larval brachiopod. The similarities can reflect the homol-<lb/>ogy of developmental mechanisms of boundary formation, not linked to segmentation, <lb/>or simply the cooption of an ancestral molecular network to various developmental <lb/>boundaries. <lb/>Ancestral expression of engrailed was nonsegmental <lb/>As discussed above, wnt1 expression is variable in the studied brachiopod species. If <lb/>we strictly consider the genes with consistent expression (i.e., pax6, pax2/5/8 and en), <lb/>the apical/mantle boundary of brachiopods is more similar to a vertebrate brain <lb/>boundary than to an annelid segment boundary. In the vertebrate brain an anterior <lb/>domain of pax6 initially overlaps with the more posterior expression of pax2/5/8 and <lb/>en and defines the position of the di/mesencephalon boundary by mutual repression <lb/>(Araki &amp; Nakamura 1999; Matsunaga et al. 2000). The spatial correlation of these <lb/>genes regarding the apical/mantle furrow of brachiopods is similar to the patterns <lb/>defining the di/mesencephalon boundary (Figure 9B). Since there is no morphological <lb/>evidence that a vertebrate brain is homologous to brachiopod larval lobes, this simi-<lb/>larity in gene expression is likely the result of convergent evolution. In protostomes, <lb/>even though pax6 is recurrently associated to anterior structures, the expression of <lb/>pax2/5/8 is variable and not complementary to pax6 (Additional file 4: Table S1). <lb/>However, data on the expression of pax6 and pax2/5/8 are still scarce outside arthro-<lb/>pods and it is unclear if the brachiopod pattern is ancestral to protostomes. In contrast, <lb/>the complementary patterns of pax6 and pax2/5/8 expression occur in the ectoderm of <lb/>hemichordates (Pani et al. 2012) and cephalochordates (Glardon et al. 1998; Kozmik <lb/>et al. 1999) suggesting this is a conserved feature of deuterostomes. In fact, deuteros-<lb/>tomes share a similar arrangement of gene products along the anteroposterior axis, a <lb/>feature likely conserved in their last common ancestor (Lowe et al. 2015). Thus, if <lb/>bilaterians had a conserved molecular cassette related to the patterning of the antero-<lb/>posterior axis, such genes could have become associated to the various morphological <lb/>structures evolved within each lineage and been independently recruited to similar <lb/>developmental roles. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>We consider the idea above by reviewing the expression of en, a gene more widely <lb/>studied across bilaterians. The comparison reveals the majority of groups have bilat-<lb/>eral or dorsal domains of en in the ectoderm as its earliest instance of embryonic <lb/>expression (Figure 10). Interestingly, many domains correlate to some kind of epithe-<lb/>lial boundary such as the apical/mantle boundary of larval brachiopods, head/trunk <lb/>and segment boundaries of annelids, shell borders in molluscs, arthropod head/trunk <lb/>and segment boundaries, seam cells in nematodes, collar/trunk boundary in hemichor-<lb/>dates, brain boundaries in vertebrates and somite boundaries in cephalochordates <lb/>(Additional file 4: Table S1). Such data indicates that the last common bilaterian <lb/>ancestor had en expressed during early embryogenesis and that these homologous <lb/>domains became associated to a variety of developmental boundaries. Can we identify <lb/>the ancestral character state for the expression of en in bilaterians? <lb/>Annelids and brachiopods share a pair of lateral en domains that localize to the <lb/>head/trunk and apical/mantle boundary, respectively. In D. melanogaster the first <lb/>stripe of en occurs at the cephalic furrow (Fjose et al. 1985) and in hemichordates en <lb/>is expressed at the collar/trunk boundary (Pani et al. 2012). Thus, comparative data <lb/>suggests that en might have been associated to the interface between an anterior (e.g., <lb/>head) and a posterior region of the embryo (e.g., trunk), a division shared by most <lb/>bilaterians. From this ancestral embryonic domain(s), en was coopted independently <lb/>to trunk segmentation in the arthropod parasegments, annelid segments, brachiopod <lb/>larval boundaries and other developmental boundaries. This phenomenon can explain <lb/>the mosaic of similarities and differences between gene expression and morphological <lb/>characters in the Bilateria. Nevertheless, testing this idea requires the resolution of the <lb/>basal bilaterian relationships to clarify the ancestral morphological characters as well <lb/>as comparative gene expression studies in a number of other protostomes like gas-<lb/>trotrichs, rotifers, chaetognaths, nemerteans and priapulids. Only then will we have <lb/>better support to establish the ancestral character states for each lineage and under-<lb/>stand the interplay between molecular pathways and morphological characters during <lb/>animal evolution. It is important to note that the homology of en domains during the <lb/>early embryogenesis of bilaterians suggested by comparative data, does not imply the <lb/>conservation of en function in boundary development. Thus, ancestral homologous <lb/>domains might have functionally diverged within the different morphological contexts <lb/>of Bilateria. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In conclusion, we show that a fine-grained comparative approach is crucial to distin-<lb/>guish ancestral and derived traits. Brachiopods have a conserved expression of pax6, <lb/>pax2/5/8 and en, which correlates to the morphology at the apical/mantle boundary. <lb/>We found that a nonsegmental ectodermal boundary can express en and wnt1 simi-<lb/>larly to arthropod parasegments and that this might be a convergent pattern. In addi-<lb/>tion, a comparative analysis suggests the ancestral bilaterian had a pair of en domains <lb/>that were coopted to different developmental boundaries during evolution. Therefore, <lb/>arthropods and annelids might have independently recruited pre-existing boundary <lb/>formation mechanisms for body segmentation (Martindale &amp; Hejnol 2009). This argu-<lb/>mentation is supported by recent phylogenies with improved resolution in the Proto-<lb/>stomia, which challenge the homology between annelid and arthropod segments, and <lb/>suggest an spiralian ancestor without trunk segmentation (Laumer et al. 2015; Struck <lb/>et al. 2014). Overall, gene expression data in a comparative phylogenetic context is a <lb/>promising approach to deconstruct segmentation into more fundamental developmen-<lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>tal mechanisms and recover the evolutionary relationships between the great diversity <lb/>of segmented structures of bilaterians. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Sample collection <lb/>We collected adult brachiopods by dredging rocky ocean floor in Friday Harbor, USA <lb/>(T. transversa) and Raunefjorden near Bergen, Norway (N. anomala) during repro-<lb/>ductive season, January and September/October respectively. Fertilization of ripe <lb/>gametes was conducted in the laboratory as described previously (Freeman 1993, <lb/>2000) and the representative developmental stages were fixed in 4% formaldehyde for <lb/>1h, washed in PTw (1x PBS + 0.1% Tween-20) and kept in PTw at 4°C for antibody <lb/>staining and in 100% methanol at -20°C for in situ hybridization. <lb/>Immunohistochemistry <lb/>We permeabilized the embryos with several washes in PTx (1x PBS + 0.2% Triton X-<lb/>100) for 2h and blocked with two washes of 1h in PTx + 0.1% BSA (Bovine Serum <lb/>Albumin) succeeded by 1h incubation in PTx + 5% NGS (Normal Goat Serum). Sam-<lb/>ples were incubated with the primary antibodies (mouse anti-Tyrosinated Tubulin <lb/>1:500 and rabbit anti-Synapsin II 1:500) stored overnight at 4°C on a nutator. We <lb/>removed the primary antibodies with three 5 min and four 30 min washes in PTx + <lb/>0.1% BSA, blocked in PTx + 5% NGS for 1h and incubated nutating overnight at 4°C <lb/>with the secondary antibodies (Alexa Fluor 594 anti-mouse and Alexa Fluor 647 anti-<lb/>rabbit 1:200). Secondary antibodies were removed with three 5 min followed by sev-<lb/>eral washes in PTx + 0.1% BSA for 2h. We stained nuclei by incubating permeabi-<lb/>lized embryos in DAPI 1:500 or Sytox Green 1:1000 for 2h. Nuclei staining was com-<lb/>bined with f-actin staining by the addition of BODIPY FL Phallacidin 5 U/mL previ-<lb/>ously evaporated to remove methanol. <lb/>Gene cloning and orthology <lb/>We identified orthologous genes by reciprocal BLAST searches using known <lb/>sequences against the transcriptomes of T. transversa and N. anomala. We performed <lb/>PCR gene specific primer pairs on cDNA of each brachiopod species synthesized with <lb/>the SMARTer RACE cDNA Amplification kit (Clontech). We used RACE primers to <lb/>clone T. transversa en and pax6. All other T. transversa (Ttra) and N. anomala (Nano) <lb/>genes were cloned with regular primer pairs (Additional file 5: Table S2). <lb/>Primers were designed with Primer3 (Untergasser et al. 2012). Orthology was <lb/>assigned by aligning amino acid sequences of brachiopods against annotated genes <lb/>using MAFFT 7.215 (Katoh &amp; Standley 2013), retaining only informative portions of <lb/>the alignment with GBlocks 0.91b with relaxed parameters (Talavera &amp; Castresana <lb/>2007) and running a Maximum Likelihood phylogenetic analysis with RAxML 8.1.17 <lb/>(Stamatakis 2014) using automatic model recognition and rapid bootstrap (Additional <lb/>file 6: Figure S4). <lb/>Alignments were manually verified using UGENE (Okonechnikov et al. 2012). <lb/>Resulting trees from the maximum likelihood analysis were rendered into cladograms <lb/>using the ETE Toolkit (Huerta-Cepas et al. 2010). Source files, alignments and scripts <lb/>are available online (Vellutini &amp; Hejnol 2015). <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>In situ hybridization <lb/>We synthesized antisense DIG-labeled riboprobes with MEGAscript kit (Ambion) and <lb/>performed colorimetric in situ hybridization according to an established protocol <lb/>(Martín-Durán et al. 2012). Whole mount double fluorescent in situ hybridization was <lb/>performed with the above protocol, but hybridizing the samples with a DIG-labeled <lb/>and a DNP-labeled riboprobes. Samples were first incubated overnight at 4°C with <lb/>Anti-DIG-POD conjugate diluted 1:250 in blocking buffer. After PTw washes, we <lb/>developed the reaction with the TSA reagent kit Cy3 (Perkin Elmer). POD activity <lb/>was inactivated by incubating 45 min in 0.1% H2O2 in PTw at room temperature fol-<lb/>lowed by a 15 min incubation at 67°C in a detergent solution (50% formamide, 2x <lb/>SSC, 1% SDS) and incubated overnight at 4°C with Anti-DNP-POD conjugate diluted <lb/>1:100 in blocking buffer. Second probe was developed in the same manner with the <lb/>TSA reagent kit Cy5 (PerkinElmer). <lb/>Imaging and image processing <lb/>Specimens were mounted in 80% Glycerol in PBS, 97% 2,2&apos;-Thiodiethanol <lb/>(Asadulina et al. 2012; Staudt et al. 2007) or Murray&apos;s Clear (2:1 benzyl benzoate and <lb/>benzyl alcohol solution) after a quick dehydration series in isopropanol (70%, 85%, <lb/>95%, 100%). After colorimetric in situ hybridization we imaged samples with a Zeiss <lb/>AxioCam HRc mounted on a Zeiss Axioscope A1 using differential interference con-<lb/>trast technique (Nomarski). Fluorescent in situ hybridization and immunostainings <lb/>were imaged in a Confocal Leica TCS SP5 and the resulting confocal stacks were pro-<lb/>cessed in Fiji (Schindelin et al. 2012). We adjusted the levels of the final panels to <lb/>improve the contrast using Fiji for confocal stacks and GIMP for photomicrographs. <lb/>We created vector graphics and assembled the figure plates using Inkscape. <lb/>Inhibitor experiments with 1-azakenpaullone <lb/>We sampled developing embryos of T. transversa from wild type cultures and incu-<lb/>bated with a final concentration of 1 and 10 µM 1-azakenpaullone diluted in seawater. <lb/>Embryos were picked at the mid-blastula and radial gastrula stage and fixed for <lb/>immunohistochemistry and in situ hybridization at the bilateral gastrula and trilobed <lb/>larval stage. Controls were treated with the highest concentration of dimethyl sulfox-<lb/>ide (DMSO) contained in the experimental samples, 1% DMSO in seawater. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Availability of supporting data <lb/>The dataset containing the source files, alignments and scripts for gene orthology <lb/>inference are available in the figshare repository at <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1473087 (Vellutini &amp; Hejnol 2015). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">List of abbreviations <lb/>DMSO: dimethyl sulfoxide, PTw: 1x PBS + 0.1% Tween-20, PTx: 1x PBS + 0.2% <lb/>Triton X-100, en: engrailed, hh: hedgehog, ptc: patched, smo: smoothened <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>BCV and AH designed the study. BCV performed the experiments and analyzed the <lb/>data. BCV and AH and wrote the manuscript. Both authors read and approved the <lb/>final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Chema Martín-Durán for crucial discussions and help with in situ <lb/>hybridization experiments, Carmen Andrikou and Kevin Pang for improving the man-<lb/>uscript, all members of S9 Lab for continuous support, and the staff of Friday Harbor <lb/>Labs and Espeland Marine Biological Station for the help with collections. Alessandro <lb/>Minelli for comments on an earlier draft. The study was funded by the core budget of <lb/>the Sars Centre and received support from the Meltzer Research Fund. <lb/></div>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Abouheif, E., Akam, M., Dickinson, W.J., Holland, P.W., Meyer, A., Patel, N.H., Raff, <lb/>R.A., Roth, V.L. &amp; Wray, G.A. (1997) Homology and developmental genes. Trends <lb/>Genet. 13, 432-433. <lb/>Ahzhanov, A. &amp; Kaufman, T.C. (2000) Evolution of distinct expression patterns for <lb/>engrailed paralogues in higher crustaceans (Malacostraca). Dev. Genes Evol. 210, <lb/>493-506. <lb/>Araki, I. &amp; Nakamura, H. (1999) Engrailed defines the position of dorsal di-mesen-<lb/>cephalic boundary by repressing diencephalic fate. Development 126, 5127-5135. <lb/>Arendt, D., Tessmar, K., Campos-Baptista, M.-I.M. de, Dorresteijn, A. &amp; Wittbrodt, J. <lb/>(2002) Development of pigment-cup eyes in the polychaete Platynereis dumerilii and <lb/>evolutionary conservation of larval eyes in Bilateria. Development 129, 1143-1154. <lb/>Asadulina, A., Panzera, A., Verasztó, C., Liebig, C. &amp; Jékely, G. (2012) Whole-body <lb/>gene expression pattern registration in Platynereis larvae. Evodevo 3, 27. <lb/>Balavoine, G. &amp; Adoutte, A. (2003) The segmented Urbilateria: A testable scenario. <lb/>Integr. Comp. Biol. 43, 137-147. <lb/>Balfour, F.M. (1880) A treatise on comparative embryology. Macmillan; Company. <lb/>Baratte, S., Andouche, A. &amp; Bonnaud, L. (2007) Engrailed in cephalopods: A key <lb/>gene related to the emergence of morphological novelties. Dev. Genes Evol. 217, 353-<lb/>362. <lb/>Bassham, S., Cañestro, C. &amp; Postlethwait, J.H. (2008) Evolution of developmental <lb/>roles of Pax2/5/8 paralogs after independent duplication in urochordate and vertebrate <lb/>lineages. BMC Biol. 6, 35. <lb/>Bely, A.E. &amp; Wray, G.A. (2001) Evolution of regeneration and fission in annelids: <lb/>Insights from engrailed-and orthodenticle-class gene expression. Development 128, <lb/>2781-2791. <lb/>Bitner, M.A. &amp; Cohen, B.L. (2013) Brachiopoda. In: eLS. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. <lb/>Boell, L.A. &amp; Bucher, G. (2008) Whole-mount in situ hybridization in the rotifer Bra-<lb/>chionus plicatilis representing a basal branch of lophotrochozoans. Dev. Genes Evol. <lb/>218, 445-451. <lb/>Brivanlou, A.H. &amp; Harland, R.M. (1989) Expression of an engrailed-related protein is <lb/>induced in the anterior neural ectoderm of early Xenopus embryos. Development 106, <lb/>611-617. <lb/>Brown, S.J., Patel, N.H. &amp; Denell, R.E. (1994) Embryonic expression of the single <lb/>Tribolium engrailed homolog. Dev. Genet. 15, 7-18. <lb/>Budd, G.E. (2001) Why are arthropods segmented? Evol. Dev. 3, 332-342. <lb/>Byrne, M., Cisternas, P.A., Elia, L. &amp; Relf, B. (2005) Engrailed is expressed in larval <lb/>development and in the radial nervous system of Patiriella sea stars. Dev. Genes Evol. <lb/>215, 608-617. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Cadigan, K.M., Grossniklaus, U. &amp; Gehring, W.J. (1994) Localized expression of <lb/>sloppy paired protein maintains the polarity of Drosophila parasegments. Genes Dev. <lb/>8, 899-913. <lb/>Callaerts, P., Munoz-Marmol, A.M., Glardon, S., Castillo, E., Sun, H., Li, W.-H., <lb/>Gehring, W.J. &amp; Salo, E. (1999) Isolation and expression of a Pax-6 gene in the <lb/>regenerating and intact Planarian Dugesia(G)tigrina. Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences 96, 558-563. <lb/>Cañestro, C., Bassham, S. &amp; Postlethwait, J. (2005) Development of the central ner-<lb/>vous system in the larvacean Oikopleura dioica and the evolution of the chordate <lb/>brain. Dev. Biol. 285, 298-315. <lb/>Cassata, G., Shemer, G., Morandi, P., Donhauser, R., Podbilewicz, B. &amp; Baumeister, <lb/>R. (2005) Ceh-16/engrailed patterns the embryonic epidermis of Caenorhabditis ele-<lb/>gans. Development 132, 739-749. <lb/>Chipman, A.D. (2010) Parallel evolution of segmentation by co-option of ancestral <lb/>gene regulatory networks. Bioessays 32, 60-70. <lb/>Chisholm, A.D. &amp; Horvitz, H.R. (1995) Patterning of the Caenorhabditis elegans <lb/>head region by the Pax-6 family member vab-3. Nature 377, 52-55. <lb/>Conklin, E.G. (1902) The embryology of a brachiopod, Terebratulina septentrionalis <lb/>Couthouy. Proc. Am. Philos. Soc. 41, 41-76. <lb/>Czerny, T., Bouchard, M., Kozmik, Z. &amp; Busslinger, M. (1997) The characterization <lb/>of novel Pax genes of the sea urchin and Drosophila reveal an ancient evolutionary <lb/>origin of the Pax2/5/8 subfamily. Mech. Dev. 67, 179-192. <lb/>Dahmann, C., Oates, A.C. &amp; Brand, M. (2011) Boundary formation and maintenance <lb/>in tissue development. Nat. Rev. Genet. 12, 43-55. <lb/>Damen, W.G.M. (2002) Parasegmental organization of the spider embryo implies that <lb/>the parasegment is an evolutionary conserved entity in arthropod embryogenesis. <lb/>Development 129, 1239-1250. <lb/>Damen, W.G.M. (2007) Evolutionary conservation and divergence of the segmenta-<lb/>tion process in arthropods. Dev. Dyn. 236, 1379-1391. <lb/>Danielian, P.S. &amp; McMahon, A.P. (1996) Engrailed-1 as a target of the Wnt-1 sig-<lb/>nalling pathway in vertebrate midbrain development. Nature 383, 332-334. <lb/>Davis, C.A., Holmyard, D.P., Millen, K.J. &amp; Joyner, A.L. (1991) Examining pattern <lb/>formation in mouse, chicken and frog embryos with an En-specific antiserum. Devel-<lb/>opment 111, 287-298. <lb/>Davis, G.K. &amp; Patel, N.H. (1999) The origin and evolution of segmentation. Trends <lb/>Cell Biol. 9, M68-72. <lb/>De Robertis, E.M. (1997) Evolutionary biology. The ancestry of segmentation. Nature <lb/>387, 25-26. <lb/>De Robertis, E.M. (2008) The molecular ancestry of segmentation mechanisms. Proc. <lb/>Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 105, 16411-16412. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Denes, A.S., Jékely, G., Steinmetz, P.R.H., Raible, F., Snyman, H., Prud&apos;homme, B., <lb/>Ferrier, D.E.K., Balavoine, G. &amp; Arendt, D. (2007) Molecular architecture of annelid <lb/>nerve cord supports common origin of nervous system centralization in Bilateria. Cell <lb/>129, 277-288. <lb/>Derobert, Y., Baratte, B., Lepage, M. &amp; Mazan, S. (2002) Pax6 expression patterns in <lb/>Lampetra fluviatilis and Scyliorhinus canicula embryos suggest highly conserved <lb/>roles in the early regionalization of the vertebrate brain. Brain Res. Bull. 57, 277-280. <lb/>DiNardo, S. &amp; O&apos;Farrell, P.H. (1987) Establishment and refinement of segmental pat-<lb/>tern in the Drosophila embryo: Spatial control of engrailed expression by pair-rule <lb/>genes. Genes Dev. 1, 1212-1225. <lb/>Dolecki, G.J. &amp; Humphreys, T. (1988) An engrailed class homeo box gene in sea <lb/>urchins. Gene 64, 21-31. <lb/>Dougan, S. &amp; DiNardo, S. (1992) Drosophila wingless generates cell type diversity <lb/>among engrailed expressing cells. Nature 360, 347-350. <lb/>Dray, N., Tessmar-Raible, K., Le Gouar, M., Vibert, L., Christodoulou, F., Schipany, <lb/>K., Guillou, A., Zantke, J., Snyman, H., Béhague, J., Vervoort, M., Arendt, D. &amp; Bal-<lb/>avoine, G. (2010) Hedgehog signaling regulates segment formation in the annelid <lb/>Platynereis. Science 329, 339-342. <lb/>Ekker, M., Wegner, J., Akimenko, M.A. &amp; Westerfield, M. (1992) Coordinate embry-<lb/>onic expression of three zebrafish engrailed genes. Development 116, 1001-1010. <lb/>Eriksson, B.J., Samadi, L. &amp; Schmid, A. (2013) The expression pattern of the genes <lb/>engrailed, pax6, otd and six3 with special respect to head and eye development in <lb/>Euperipatoides kanangrensis Reid 1996 (Onychophora: Peripatopsidae). Dev. Genes <lb/>Evol. 223, 237-246. <lb/>Eriksson, B.J., Tait, N.N., Budd, G.E. &amp; Akam, M. (2009) The involvement of <lb/>engrailed and wingless during segmentation in the onychophoran Euperipatoides <lb/>kanangrensis (Peripatopsidae: Onychophora) (Reid 1996). Dev. Genes Evol. 219, <lb/>249-264. <lb/>Farzana, L. &amp; Brown, S.J. (2008) Hedgehog signaling pathway function conserved in <lb/>Tribolium segmentation. Dev. Genes Evol. 218, 181-192. <lb/>Fjose, A., McGinnis, W.J. &amp; Gehring, W.J. (1985) Isolation of a homoeo box-contain-<lb/>ing gene from the engrailed region of Drosophila and the spatial distribution of its <lb/>transcripts. Nature 313, 284-289. <lb/>Fleig, R. (1990) Engrailed expression and body segmentation in the honeybee Apis <lb/>mellifera. Rouxs. Arch. Dev. Biol. 198, 467-473. <lb/>Franke, F.A. &amp; Mayer, G. (2014) Controversies surrounding segments and paraseg-<lb/>ments in onychophora: Insights from the expression patterns of four &quot;segment polarity <lb/>genes&quot; in the peripatopsid Euperipatoides rowelli. PLoS One 9, e114383. <lb/>Franke, F.A., Schumann, I., Hering, L. &amp; Mayer, G. (2015) Phylogenetic analysis and <lb/>expression patterns of Pax genes in the onychophoran Euperipatoides rowelli reveal a <lb/>novel bilaterian Pax subfamily. Evol. Dev. 17, 3-20. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Freeman, G. (1993) Regional specification during embryogenesis in the articulate bra-<lb/>chiopod Terebratalia. Dev. Biol. 160, 196-213. <lb/>Freeman, G. (2000) Regional specification during embryogenesis in the craniiform <lb/>brachiopod Crania anomala. Dev. Biol. 227, 219-238. <lb/>Fujioka, M., Yusibova, G.L., Patel, N.H., Brown, S.J. &amp; Jaynes, J.B. (2002) The <lb/>repressor activity of Even-skipped is highly conserved, and is sufficient to activate <lb/>engrailed and to regulate both the spacing and stability of parasegment boundaries. <lb/>Development 129, 4411-4421. <lb/>Gabriel, W.N. &amp; Goldstein, B. (2007) Segmental expression of Pax3/7 and engrailed <lb/>homologs in tardigrade development. Dev. Genes Evol. 217, 421-433. <lb/>Glardon, S., Callaerts, P., Halder, G. &amp; Gehring, W.J. (1997) Conservation of Pax-6 in <lb/>a lower chordate, the ascidian Phallusia mammillata. Development 124, 817-825. <lb/>Glardon, S., Holland, L.Z., Gehring, W.J. &amp; Holland, N.D. (1998) Isolation and devel-<lb/>opmental expression of the amphioxus Pax-6 gene (AmphiPax-6): Insights into eye <lb/>and photoreceptor evolution. Development 125, 2701-2710. <lb/>Hannibal, R.L. &amp; Patel, N.H. (2013) What is a segment? Evodevo 4, 35. <lb/>Hartmann, B., Lee, P.N., Kang, Y.Y., Tomarev, S., Couet, H.G. de &amp; Callaerts, P. <lb/>(2003) Pax6 in the sepiolid squid Euprymna scolopes: Evidence for a role in eye, sen-<lb/>sory organ and brain development. Mech. Dev. 120, 177-183. <lb/>Hatta, K., Bremiller, R., Westerfield, M. &amp; Kimmel, C.B. (1991) Diversity of expres-<lb/>sion of engrailed-like antigens in zebrafish. Development 112, 821-832. <lb/>Heller, N. &amp; Brändli, A.W. (1999) Xenopus Pax-2/5/8 orthologues: Novel insights <lb/>into Pax gene evolution and identification of Pax-8 as the earliest marker for otic and <lb/>pronephric cell lineages. Dev. Genet. 24, 208-219. <lb/>Hohagen, J., Herlitze, I. &amp; Jackson, D.J. (2015) An optimised whole mount in situ <lb/>hybridisation protocol for the mollusc Lymnaea stagnalis. BMC Dev. Biol. 15, 19. <lb/>Holland, L.Z., Kene, M., Williams, N.A. &amp; Holland, N.D. (1997) Sequence and <lb/>embryonic expression of the amphioxus engrailed gene (AmphiEn): The metameric <lb/>pattern of transcription resembles that of its segment-polarity homolog in drosophila. <lb/>Development 124, 1723-1732. <lb/>Holland, N.D., Holland, L.Z., Honma, Y. &amp; Fujii, T. (1993) Engrailed expression dur-<lb/>ing development of a lamprey, Lampetra japonica: A possible clue to homologies <lb/>between agnathan and gnathostome muscles of the mandibular arch. Dev. Growth Dif-<lb/>fer. 35, 153-160. <lb/>Huerta-Cepas, J., Dopazo, J. &amp; Gabaldón, T. (2010) ETE: A python Environment for <lb/>Tree Exploration. BMC Bioinformatics 11, 24. <lb/>Hughes, C.L. &amp; Kaufman, T.C. (2002) Exploring myriapod segmentation: The expres-<lb/>sion patterns of even-skipped, engrailed, and wingless in a centipede. Dev. Biol. 247, <lb/>47-61. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Hyman, L.H. (1959) The lophophorate coelomates-Phylum brachiopoda. In: The <lb/>invertebrates: Smaller coelomate groups. McGraw-Hill Book Company, Inc, New <lb/>York, pp. 568. <lb/>Imai, K.S., Satoh, N. &amp; Satou, Y. (2002) Region specific gene expressions in the cen-<lb/>tral nervous system of the ascidian embryo. Mech. Dev. 119 Suppl 1, S275-7. <lb/>Ingham, P.W. (1991) Segment polarity genes and cell patterning within the <lb/>Drosophila body segment. Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev. 1, 261-267. <lb/>Ingham, P.W. &amp; Martinez Arias, A. (1992) Boundaries and fields in early embryos. <lb/>Cell 68, 221-235. <lb/>Ingham, P.W., Baker, N.E. &amp; Martinez-Arias, A. (1988) Regulation of segment polar-<lb/>ity genes in the Drosophila blastoderm by fushi tarazu and even skipped. Nature 331, <lb/>73-75. <lb/>Jacobs, D.K., Wray, C.G., Wedeen, C.J., Kostriken, R., DeSalle, R., Staton, J.L., <lb/>Gates, R.D. &amp; Lindberg, D.R. (2000) Molluscan engrailed expression, serial organi-<lb/>zation, and shell evolution. Evol. Dev. 2, 340-347. <lb/>Jiang, D. &amp; Smith, W.C. (2002) An ascidian engrailed gene. Dev. Genes Evol. 212, <lb/>399-402. <lb/>John A. Long and Stephen A. Stricker (1991) Brachiopoda. In: A. C. Giese, J. S. <lb/>Pearse, and V. Pearse (Eds), Reproduction of marine invertebrates: Echinoderms and <lb/>lophophorates. The Boxwood Press, Pacific Grove, California, pp. 47-84. <lb/>Joyner, A.L. (1996) Engrailed, Wnt and Pax genes regulate midbrain-hindbrain devel-<lb/>opment. Trends Genet. 12, 15-20. <lb/>Kang, D., Huang, F., Li, D., Shankland, M., Gaffield, W. &amp; Weisblat, D.A. (2003) A <lb/>hedgehog homolog regulates gut formation in leech (Helobdella). Development 130, <lb/>1645-1657. <lb/>Katoh, K. &amp; Standley, D.M. (2013) MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software <lb/>version 7: Improvements in performance and usability. Mol. Biol. Evol. 30, 772-780. <lb/>Kimmel, C.B. (1996) Was urbilateria segmented? Trends Genet. 12, 329-331. <lb/>Kornberg, T., Sidén, I., O&apos;Farrell, P. &amp; Simon, M. (1985) The engrailed locus of <lb/>Drosophila: In situ localization of transcripts reveals compartment-specific expres-<lb/>sion. Cell 40, 45-53. <lb/>Kozmik, Z., Holland, N.D., Kalousova, A., Paces, J., Schubert, M. &amp; Holland, L.Z. <lb/>(1999) Characterization of an amphioxus paired box gene, AmphiPax2/5/8: Develop-<lb/>mental expression patterns in optic support cells, nephridium, thyroid-like structures <lb/>and pharyngeal gill slits, but not in the midbrain-hindbrain boundary region. Develop-<lb/>ment 126, 1295-1304. <lb/>Kunick, C., Lauenroth, K., Leost, M., Meijer, L. &amp; Lemcke, T. (2004) 1-azaken-<lb/>paullone is a selective inhibitor of glycogen synthase kinase-3 beta. Bioorg. Med. <lb/>Chem. Lett. 14, 413-416. <lb/>Lans, D., Wedeen, C.J. &amp; Weisblat, D.A. (1993) Cell lineage analysis of the expres-<lb/>sion of an engrailed homolog in leech embryos. Development 117, 857-871. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Laumer, C.E., Bekkouche, N., Kerbl, A., Goetz, F., Neves, R.C., Sørensen, M.V., <lb/>Kristensen, R.M., Hejnol, A., Dunn, C.W., Giribet, G. &amp; Worsaae, K. (2015) Spiralian <lb/>phylogeny informs the evolution of microscopic lineages. Curr. Biol. 25, 2000-2006. <lb/>Lowe, C.J. &amp; Wray, G.A. (1997) Radical alterations in the roles of homeobox genes <lb/>during echinoderm evolution. Nature 389, 718-721. <lb/>Lowe, C.J., Clarke, D.N., Medeiros, D.M., Rokhsar, D.S. &amp; Gerhart, J. (2015) The <lb/>deuterostome context of chordate origins. Nature 520, 456-465. <lb/>Lowe, C.J., Wu, M., Salic, A., Evans, L., Lander, E., Stange-Thomann, N., Gruber, <lb/>C.E., Gerhart, J. &amp; Kirschner, M. (2003) Anteroposterior patterning in hemichordates <lb/>and the origins of the chordate nervous system. Cell 113, 853-865. <lb/>Manzanares, M., Marco, R. &amp; Garesse, R. (1993) Genomic organization and develop-<lb/>mental pattern of expression of the engrailed gene from the brine shrimp Artemia. <lb/>Development 118, 1209-1219. <lb/>Manzanares, M., Williams, T.A., Marco, R. &amp; Garesse, R. (1996) Segmentation in the <lb/>crustacean Artemia: Engrailed staining studied with an antibody raised against the <lb/>Artemia protein. Rouxs. Arch. Dev. Biol. 205, 424-431. <lb/>Marie, B. &amp; Bacon, J.P. (2000) Two engrailed-related genes in the cockroach: <lb/>Cloning, phylogenetic analysis, expression and isolation of splice variants. Dev. <lb/>Genes Evol. 210, 436-448. <lb/>Martindale, M.Q. &amp; Hejnol, A. (2009) A developmental perspective: Changes in the <lb/>position of the blastopore during bilaterian evolution. Dev. Cell 17, 162-174. <lb/>Martinez Arias, A., Baker, N.E. &amp; Ingham, P.W. (1988) Role of segment polarity <lb/>genes in the definition and maintenance of cell states in the Drosophila embryo. <lb/>Development 103, 157-170. <lb/>Martinez-Arias, A. &amp; Lawrence, P.A. (1985) Parasegments and compartments in the <lb/>Drosophila embryo. Nature 313, 639-642. <lb/>Martín-Durán, J.M., Janssen, R., Wennberg, S., Budd, G.E. &amp; Hejnol, A. (2012) <lb/>Deuterostomic development in the protostome Priapulus caudatus. Curr. Biol. 22, <lb/>2161-2166. <lb/>Matsunaga, E., Araki, I. &amp; Nakamura, H. (2000) Pax6 defines the di-mesencephalic <lb/>boundary by repressing En1 and Pax2. Development 127, 2357-2365. <lb/>McCauley, D.W. &amp; Bronner-Fraser, M. (2002) Conservation of Pax gene expression <lb/>in ectodermal placodes of the lamprey. Gene 287, 129-139. <lb/>Mellenthin, K., Fahmy, K., Ali, R.A., Hunding, A., Da Rocha, S. &amp; Baumgartner, S. <lb/>(2006) Wingless signaling in a large insect, the blowfly Lucilia sericata: A beautiful <lb/>example of evolutionary developmental biology. Dev. Dyn. 235, 347-360. <lb/>Minelli, A. &amp; Fusco, G. (2004) Evo-devo perspectives on segmentation: Model organ-<lb/>isms, and beyond. Trends Ecol. Evol. 19, 423-429. <lb/>Moshel, S.M., Levine, M. &amp; Collier, J.R. (1998) Shell differentiation and engrailed <lb/>expression in the Ilyanassa embryo. Dev. Genes Evol. 208, 135-141. <lb/>Nagy, L.M. (1994) Insect segmentation. A glance posterior. Curr. Biol. 4, 811-814. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Navet, S., Andouche, A., Baratte, S. &amp; Bonnaud, L. (2009) Shh and Pax6 have uncon-<lb/>ventional expression patterns in embryonic morphogenesis in Sepia officinalis <lb/>(Cephalopoda). Gene Expr. Patterns 9, 461-467. <lb/>Nederbragt, A.J., Loon, A.E. van &amp; Dictus, W.J.A.G. (2002) Expression of Patella <lb/>vulgata orthologs of engrailed and dpp-bMP2/4 in adjacent domains during mollus-<lb/>can shell development suggests a conserved compartment boundary mechanism. Dev. <lb/>Biol. 246, 341-355. <lb/>Nielsen, C. (1991) The development of the brachiopod Crania (Neocrania) anomala <lb/>(O. F. Müller) and its phylogenetic significance. Acta Zool. 72, 7-28. <lb/>Njølstad, P.R. &amp; Fjose, A. (1988) Insitu hybridization patterns of zebrafish homeobox <lb/>genes homologous to Hox-2.1 and En-2 of mouse. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. <lb/>Okafuji, T., Funahashi, J. &amp; Nakamura, H. (1999) Roles of Pax-2 in initiation of the <lb/>chick tectal development. Brain Res. Dev. Brain Res. 116, 41-49. <lb/>Okonechnikov, K., Golosova, O., Fursov, M. &amp; UGENE team (2012) Unipro <lb/>UGENE: A unified bioinformatics toolkit. Bioinformatics 28, 1166-1167. <lb/>Omori, A., Akasaka, K., Kurokawa, D. &amp; Amemiya, S. (2011) Gene expression analy-<lb/>sis of Six3, Pax6, and Otx in the early development of the stalked crinoid Metacrinus <lb/>rotundus. Gene Expr. Patterns 11, 48-56. <lb/>O&apos;Brien, E.K. &amp; Degnan, B.M. (2003) Expression of Pax258 in the gastropod stato-<lb/>cyst: Insights into the antiquity of metazoan geosensory organs. Evol. Dev. 5, 572-<lb/>578. <lb/>Pani, A.M., Mullarkey, E.E., Aronowicz, J., Assimacopoulos, S., Grove, E.A. &amp; <lb/>Lowe, C.J. (2012) Ancient deuterostome origins of vertebrate brain signalling centres. <lb/>Nature 483, 289-294. <lb/>Passamaneck, Y.J., Furchheim, N., Hejnol, A., Martindale, M.Q. &amp; Lüter, C. (2011) <lb/>Ciliary photoreceptors in the cerebral eyes of a protostome larva. Evodevo 2, 6. <lb/>Patel, N.H. (2003) The ancestry of segmentation. Dev. Cell 5, 2-4. <lb/>Patel, N.H., Martin-Blanco, E., Coleman, K.G., Poole, S.J., Ellis, M.C., Kornberg, <lb/>T.B. &amp; Goodman, C.S. (1989) Expression of engrailed proteins in arthropods, <lb/>annelids, and chordates. Cell 58, 955-968. <lb/>Petersen, C.P. &amp; Reddien, P.W. (2009) Wnt signaling and the polarity of the primary <lb/>body axis. Cell 139, 1056-1068. <lb/>Pfeffer, P.L., Gerster, T., Lun, K., Brand, M. &amp; Busslinger, M. (1998) Characterization <lb/>of three novel members of the zebrafish Pax2/5/8 family: Dependency of Pax5 and <lb/>Pax8 expression on the Pax2.1 (noi) function. Development 125, 3063-3074. <lb/>Prud&apos;homme, B., Rosa, R. de, Arendt, D., Julien, J.-F., Pajaziti, R., Dorresteijn, <lb/>A.W.C., Adoutte, A., Wittbrodt, J. &amp; Balavoine, G. (2003) Arthropod-like expression <lb/>patterns of engrailed and wingless in the annelid Platynereis dumerilii suggest a role <lb/>in segment formation. Curr. Biol. 13, 1876-1881. <lb/>Püschel, A.W., Gruss, P. &amp; Westerfield, M. (1992) Sequence and expression pattern of <lb/>pax-6 are highly conserved between zebrafish and mice. Development 114, 643-651. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Quigley, I.K., Xie, X. &amp; Shankland, M. (2007) Hau-Pax6A expression in the central <lb/>nervous system of the leech embryo. Dev. Genes Evol. 217, 459-468. <lb/>Quiring, R., Walldorf, U., Kloter, U. &amp; Gehring, W.J. (1994) Homology of the eyeless <lb/>gene of Drosophila to the Small eye gene in mice and Aniridia in humans. Science <lb/>265, 785-789. <lb/>Rajakumar, V. &amp; Chamberlin, H.M. (2007) The Pax2/5/8 gene egl-38 coordinates <lb/>organogenesis of the C. elegans egg-laying system. Dev. Biol. 301, 240-253. <lb/>Rhinn, M. &amp; Brand, M. (2001) The midbrain-hindbrain boundary organizer. Curr. <lb/>Opin. Neurobiol. 11, 34-42. <lb/>Santagata, S., Resh, C., Hejnol, A., Martindale, M.Q. &amp; Passamaneck, Y.J. (2012) <lb/>Development of the larval anterior neurogenic domains of Terebratalia transversa <lb/>(Brachiopoda) provides insights into the diversification of larval apical organs and the <lb/>spiralian nervous system. Evodevo 3, 3. <lb/>Schindelin, J., Arganda-Carreras, I., Frise, E., Kaynig, V., Longair, M., Pietzsch, T., <lb/>Preibisch, S., Rueden, C., Saalfeld, S., Schmid, B., Tinevez, J.-Y., White, D.J., <lb/>Hartenstein, V., Eliceiri, K., Tomancak, P. &amp; Cardona, A. (2012) Fiji: An open-source <lb/>platform for biological-image analysis. Nat. Methods 9, 676-682. <lb/>Scholpp, S., Lohs, C. &amp; Brand, M. (2003) Engrailed and Fgf8 act synergistically to <lb/>maintain the boundary between diencephalon and mesencephalon. Development 130, <lb/>4881-4893. <lb/>Scholtz, G. (2002) The articulata hypothesis -or what is a segment? Org. Divers. <lb/>Evol. 2, 197-215. <lb/>Seaver, E.C. (2003) Segmentation: Mono-or polyphyletic? Int. J. Dev. Biol. 47, 583-<lb/>595. <lb/>Seaver, E.C. &amp; Kaneshige, L.M. (2006) Expression of &apos;segmentation&apos; genes during <lb/>larval and juvenile development in the polychaetes Capitella sp. i and H. elegans. <lb/>Dev. Biol. 289, 179-194. <lb/>Seaver, E.C. &amp; Shankland, M. (2001) Establishment of segment polarity in the ecto-<lb/>derm of the leech Helobdella. Development 128, 1629-1641. <lb/>Seaver, E.C., Paulson, D.A., Irvine, S.Q. &amp; Martindale, M.Q. (2001) The spatial and <lb/>temporal expression of Ch-en, the engrailed gene in the polychaete Chaetopterus, <lb/>does not support a role in body axis segmentation. Dev. Biol. 236, 195-209. <lb/>Shubin, N., Tabin, C. &amp; Carroll, S.B. (2009) Deep homology and the origins of evolu-<lb/>tionary novelty. Nature 457, 818-823. <lb/>Stamatakis, A. (2014) RAxML version 8: A tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-<lb/>analysis of large phylogenies. Bioinformatics 30, 1312-1313. <lb/>Staudt, T., Lang, M.C., Medda, R., Engelhardt, J. &amp; Hell, S.W. (2007) 2,2&apos;-thiodi-<lb/>ethanol: A new water soluble mounting medium for high resolution optical <lb/>microscopy. Microsc. Res. Tech. 70, 1-9. <lb/>Struck, T.H., Wey-Fabrizius, A.R., Golombek, A., Hering, L., Weigert, A., Bleidorn, <lb/>C., Klebow, S., Iakovenko, N., Hausdorf, B., Petersen, M., Kück, P., Herlyn, H. &amp; <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Hankeln, T. (2014) Platyzoan paraphyly based on phylogenomic data supports a non-<lb/>coelomate ancestry of Spiralia. Mol. Biol. Evol. 31, 1833-1849. <lb/>Tabata, T. &amp; Kornberg, T.B. (1994) Hedgehog is a signaling protein with a key role in <lb/>patterning Drosophila imaginal discs. Cell 76, 89-102. <lb/>Talavera, G. &amp; Castresana, J. (2007) Improvement of phylogenies after removing <lb/>divergent and ambiguously aligned blocks from protein sequence alignments. Syst. <lb/>Biol. 56, 564-577. <lb/>Tarpin, M., Gehring, W.J. &amp; Bièrne, J. (1999) Reverse homeosis in homeotically <lb/>reconstructed ribbonworms. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 96, 11900-11903. <lb/>Tautz, D. (2004) Segmentation. Dev. Cell 7, 301-312. <lb/>Temereva, E.N. &amp; Malakhov, V.V. (2011) The evidence of metamery in adult bra-<lb/>chiopods and phoronids. Invert Zool 8, 91-112. <lb/>Tomarev, S.I., Callaerts, P., Kos, L., Zinovieva, R., Halder, G., Gehring, W. &amp; Piatig-<lb/>orsky, J. (1997) Squid Pax-6 and eye development. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 94, <lb/>2421-2426. <lb/>Untergasser, A., Cutcutache, I., Koressaar, T., Ye, J., Faircloth, B.C., Remm, M. &amp; <lb/>Rozen, S.G. (2012) Primer3-new capabilities and interfaces. Nucleic Acids Res. 40, <lb/>e115-e115. <lb/>Vellutini, B.C. &amp; Hejnol, A. (2015) Gene orthology for the brachiopod segmentation <lb/>project. <lb/>Wada, H., Saiga, H., Satoh, N. &amp; Holland, P.W. (1998) Tripartite organization of the <lb/>ancestral chordate brain and the antiquity of placodes: Insights from ascidian Pax-<lb/>2/5/8, Hox and Otx genes. Development 125, 1113-1122. <lb/>Walther, C. &amp; Gruss, P. (1991) Pax-6, a murine paired box gene, is expressed in the <lb/>developing CNS. Development 113, 1435-1449. <lb/>Wanninger, A. &amp; Haszprunar, G. (2001) The expression of an engrailed protein during <lb/>embryonic shell formation of the tusk-shell, Antalis entalis (mollusca, scaphopoda). <lb/>Evolution and Development 3, 312-321. <lb/>Wedeen, C.J. &amp; Weisblat, D.A. (1991) Segmental expression of an engrailed-class <lb/>gene during early development and neurogenesis in an annelid. Development 113, <lb/>805-814. <lb/>Wedeen, C.J., Kostriken, R.G., Leach, D. &amp; Whitington, P. (1997) Segmentally iter-<lb/>ated expression of an engrailed-class gene in the embryo of an australian ony-<lb/>chophoran. Dev. Genes Evol. 207, 282-286. <lb/>Whitington, P.M., Meier, T. &amp; King, P. (1991) Segmentation, neurogenesis and forma-<lb/>tion of early axonal pathways in the centipede, Ethmostigmus rubripes (Brandt). <lb/>Rouxs. Arch. Dev. Biol. 199, 349-363. <lb/>Wollesen, T., Rodríguez Monje, S.V., Todt, C., Degnan, B.M. &amp; Wanninger, A. (2015) <lb/>Ancestral role of pax2/5/8 in molluscan brain and multimodal sensory system devel-<lb/>opment. BMC Evol. Biol. 15, 231. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Yaguchi, S., Nakajima, Y., Wang, D. &amp; Burke, R.D. (2006) Embryonic expression of <lb/>engrailed in sea urchins. Gene Expr. Patterns 6, 566-571. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figures <lb/>Figure 1. Phylogenetic relationships between bilaterally symmetrical animals and the <lb/>morphological features of larval brachiopods. (A) Phylogenetic tree showing the three <lb/>major bilaterian clades, Deuterostomia, Ecdysozoa and Spiralia. Animal groups <lb/>regarded as truly segmented are marked in bold. The lineage of brachiopods is marked <lb/>in red. Tree based on (Laumer et al. 2015). (B) Putative segmented traits of the larvae <lb/>of the brachiopods T. transversa and N. anomala. Tree based on (Bitner &amp; Cohen <lb/>2013). <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Developmental stages of the trilobed larva of T. transversa (A-E) and the <lb/>bilobed larva of N. anomala (F-J). Each panel shows a ventral view (top) and lateral <lb/>view (bottom) of a maximum intensity projection of embryos stained with DAPI. <lb/>Anterior is top in all panels and ventral is to the right in all lateral views. White <lb/>arrowheads mark the apical/mantle boundary and black arrowheads mark the <lb/>mantle/pedicle boundary. al: apical lobe, ml: mantle lobe, pl: pedicle lobe. Scale bars <lb/>= 20 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3. Morphology of the ectodermal and mesodermal boundaries in the larvae of <lb/>the brachiopods T. transversa and N. anomala. (A,E) Outline of the apical/mantle fur-<lb/>row in the epidermis of the bilateral gastrula in ventral view. (B,F) Lateral view show-<lb/>ing the epidermal surface of the bilateral gastrula showing the membrane outlines of <lb/>epithelial cells. Boxes mark the regions corresponding to the insets on the right side <lb/>(i-iii). (C,G) Outline of the apical/mantle furrow in the epidermis of the bilobed larva <lb/>in ventral view. (D,H) Lateral view showing the epidermal surface of the bilobed <lb/>larva showing the membrane outlines of epithelial cells. (I,M) Mesoderm morphology <lb/>at the bilateral gastrula in a ventral view. (J,N) Same stage, but lateral view. (K,O) <lb/>Bilobed larva showing a more medial (left) and a more lateral (right) slices of and <lb/>embryo in lateral view. (L,P) Ventral view of a T. transversa trilobed larva (L) and a <lb/>developed bilobed larva of N. anomala (P) showing the final arrangement of the larval <lb/>mesoderm. Nuclei stained with DAPI (blue) and cytoplasmic staining (gray) obtained <lb/>by mounting specimens stained with BODIPY FL in Thiodiethanol (A,C,E,G). Cell <lb/>membrane outlines (F-Actin) stained with BODIPY FL mounted in Murray&apos;s Clear <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>(B,D,F,H). Mesoderm evidenced by the antibody Anti-Synapsin II (vermillion) with <lb/>the counter staining of tyrosinated tubulin (green), F-Actin (white) and DAPI (blue) <lb/>(I-P). Anti-Synapsin II cross-react with an unknown component of T. transversa <lb/>mesoderm and was used as a marker; this reaction is weaker and less specific in N. <lb/>anomala. The four coelomic sacs of N. anomala are indicated by numerals 1-4 from <lb/>anterior to posterior. cs: chaetae sac, g: gut, vp: ventral projection, am: apical meso-<lb/>derm, mm: mantle mesoderm, pm: pedicle mesoderm. White arrowheads mark the <lb/>apical/mantle boundary and black arrowheads mark the mantle/pedicle boundary. <lb/>Anterior is top and ventral is to the right in lateral views for all panels. Scale bars = 20 <lb/>µm (B,D,F,H,I-P), 10 µm (A,C,E,G). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4. Whole mount in situ hybridization of hh, en and wnt1 orthologs in represen-<lb/>tative developmental stages of the brachiopods T. transversa and N. anomala. Ante-<lb/>rior is top in all and ventral is to the right in all lateral views. (A-B) Expression <lb/>of hh. (C-D) Expression of en. (E-F) Expression of wnt1. Line drawings represent <lb/>expression at the bilateral gastrula stage. (G-L) Expression of en in the mesoderm of <lb/>T. transversa. White dashed lines are highlighting the mesoderm. (G) Asymmetric <lb/>gastrula with no mesodermal expression of en. (H) Onset of mesodermal en in the <lb/>bilateral gastrula in a ventral and lateral view (inset). Specimens are the same of Fig-<lb/>ure 1C. (I) Resolved bands of en in the mesoderm of the bilobed larva in a ventral and <lb/>lateral view (inset). (J) Connection between ectoderm and mesoderm expression of en <lb/>in a bilateral gastrula. (K) Lateral view of bilobed larva. Black dashed lines mark the <lb/>position of the optical sections of a posterior view of the same embryo (insets i-iii). <lb/>(L) Line drawings represent expression at the bilobed stage of T. transversa. (M-R) <lb/>Expression of en in the mesoderm of N. anomala. (M) Asymmetric gastrula with no <lb/>mesodermal staining of en in a ventral and posterior view (inset). (N) Strong en <lb/>domains in the mesoderm of the bilateral gastrula adjacent to the ectodermal domains <lb/>at the posterior region of coelomic sac &quot;2&quot;. Inset shows the mesoderm in a posterior <lb/>view. (O) Two pairs of mesodermal domains of en in the coeloms &quot;2&quot; and &quot;3&quot; of the <lb/>bilobed larva. (P) Detail of en expression in the bilobed larva in the coeloms &quot;2&quot; and <lb/>&quot;3&quot; (inset). (Q) Lateral view and optical sections of a posterior view of a bilobed larva <lb/>showing the expression in the coelomic sacs (insets). (R) Line drawings represent <lb/>expression at the bilobed stage of N. anomala. White arrowheads mark the <lb/>apical/mantle boundary and black arrowheads mark the mantle/pedicle boundary. <lb/>Double arrowheads mark the ectodermal expression of en while arrows point to the <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>mesodermal domains. Asterisk marks area of unspecific staining due to the rudiment <lb/>of larval shell (C4). The four coelomic sacs of N. anomala are indicated by numerals <lb/>1-4 from anterior to posterior. cs: chaetae sacs. Scale bars = 20 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5. Whole mount double fluorescent in situ hybridization with en (vermillion) <lb/>and wnt1 (green) in T. transversa. (A) Asymmetric gastrula. Same specimens of Fig-<lb/>ure 1B. (B) Bilateral gastrula. Same specimens of Figure 1C. (C) Bilobed larva. Ven-<lb/>tral view is the same specimen of Figure 1D. Ventral and lateral views are maximum <lb/>intensity projections. Slice view shows additional counter staining with DAPI (gray). <lb/>Merge (yellow) shows the coexpression of en and wnt1. Scale bars = 20 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6. Whole mount in situ hybridization of pax6, pax2/5/8 and fgf8/17/18 <lb/>orthologs in representative developmental stages of the brachiopods T. transversa and <lb/>N. anomala. (A-B) Expression of pax6. (C-D) Expression of pax2/5/8. (E-F) Expres-<lb/>sion of fgf8/17/18. Anterior is top in all panels and ventral is to the right in all lateral <lb/>views. Line drawings represent expression at the bilateral gastrula stage. White arrow-<lb/>heads mark the apical/mantle boundary and black arrowheads mark the mantle/pedicle <lb/>boundary. Scale bars = 20 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 7. Whole mount double fluorescent in situ hybridization of pax6 + pax2/5/8 <lb/>(A-F), en + pax2/5/8 (G-J) and en + fgf8/17/18 (K-N) in the brachiopod T. <lb/>transversa. (A) Radial gastrula. (B,G) Asymmetric gastrula. (C,H,I,K,L) Bilateral gas-<lb/>trula. (D,J,M,N) Bilobed larva. (E,F) Trilobed larva. Anterior is top in all panels and <lb/>ventral is to the right in all lateral views. Side panels show the relation between gene <lb/>expression and the apical/mantle boundary (striped yellow line). White arrowheads <lb/>mark the apical/mantle boundary and black arrowheads mark the mantle/pedicle <lb/>boundary. Scale bars = 20 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 8. Effects of the over-activation of the canonical Wnt pathway on the mor-<lb/>phology and gene expression during the embryonic development of T. transversa. We <lb/>treated developing embryos of T. transversa with 1 and 10 µM 1-azakenpaullone <lb/>diluted in seawater with the following incubation periods: mid-blastula to bilateral <lb/>gastrula stage (A-H), radial gastrula to bilateral gastrula stage (I-P) and mid-blastula <lb/>to trilobed larval stage (Q-F&apos;). (A, B) Control and treated samples from mid-blastula <lb/>to bilateral gastrula. Embryos did not elongate and the disposition of corpuscular bod-<lb/>ies (cb)-cells of unknown function that protrude out of the epithelium-is disrupted. <lb/>(I, J) Control and treated samples from radial gastrula to bilateral gastrula. Embryos <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>do not have a well defined apical/mantle furrow and show bilateral stubs correspon-<lb/>dent to incipient mantle lobe tissue. Treated embryos show no sign of chaetae forma-<lb/>tion. (C-L) Expression of en in control and treated embryos. Control embryos have an <lb/>apical/mantle stripe, a ventral and a dorsal domain of en. Early (mid-blastula) and late <lb/>(radial gastrula) treatments show a posterior laterodorsal en domain, but only in the <lb/>latter we detected an anterior en domain consisting of scattered ectodermal cells and a <lb/>broad mesodermal domain in the anterior end (arrowhead). (E-N) Expression of wnt1 <lb/>in control and treated embryos. Control embryos have wnt1 expressed around the pos-<lb/>terior lip of the blastopore. In the treated samples there is an expansion of this poste-<lb/>rior domain, occupying half of the blastopore length. Only embryos treated at the <lb/>radial gastrula stage show an anterior expression domain of wnt1 at the apical plate <lb/>(arrowhead), separated from the posterior domain by a subterminal band clear of <lb/>expression. (G-P) Expression of pax6 in control and treated embryos. Control <lb/>embryos have pax6 transcripts contained in the apical lobe. In all treated embryos the <lb/>expression of pax6 shifts anteriorly localizing to the apical plate (arrowheads). (Q-S) <lb/>Control and treated samples from mid-blastula to larva. (Q) Morphology of control <lb/>larvae incubated with DMSO is consistent with a wild type trilobed larva of T. <lb/>transversa. The apical lobe has a row of corpuscular bodies at its posterior portion <lb/>just above the apical/mantle furrow. The mantle lobe has outgrown with the extensive <lb/>underlying mesoderm and musculature, and the pedicle lobe shows dorsal putative <lb/>gland cells (gc). (R-S) Morphology of treated embryos developed into larvae reveals <lb/>an expansion of posterior structures. Larval body has a distinct anterior portion cov-<lb/>ered by corpuscular bodies and an unclosed blastoporal opening at its center (R). <lb/>Higher concentrations of 1-azakenpaullone (10 µM) resulted in a diminished anterior <lb/>portion (S). Morphology of the posterior portion resembles an over-developed pedicle <lb/>lobe with putative gland cells on the dorsal side. The anterior and posterior regions of <lb/>treated embryos are demarcated by an ectodermal fold. We neither detected signs of <lb/>chaetae sacs nor evidence for the presence of a mantle lobe. (T-X) Expression of en <lb/>in wild type, control and treated embryos. Wild type expression of en consists of a <lb/>ventral and a dorsal domain in the pedicle lobe (T, arrowheads; same specimen as Fig-<lb/>ure 4C4). Control embryos have a similar pattern, although regions of unspecific <lb/>staining in the pedicle lobe (*) obfuscate the signal (U, arrowhead). Treated embryos <lb/>show a broader expression domain of en encircling the embryo at the anterior portion <lb/>of the pedicle lobe, similar to wild type and controls (W, X). At 10 µM, en is also <lb/>expressed in the mesoderm at the anterior end (X, arrowhead). (Y-B&apos;) Expression of <lb/>wnt1 in wild type, control and treated embryos. Wild type expression of wnt1 colocal-<lb/>izes with en expression (T), except for an additional posterior domain at the pedicle <lb/>lobe (Y, same specimen as Figure 4E4). Control embryos also display shell back-<lb/>ground (*), but signal at the dorsal side is visible (Z, arrowhead). Transcripts of wnt1 <lb/>in treated embryos occupy the same territories as en (W, X), except for the absence of <lb/>wnt1 in the anterior mesoderm (B&apos;). (C&apos;-F&apos;) Expression of pax6 in wild type, control <lb/>and treated embryos. Wild type expression of pax6 occurs in the dorsal portion of the <lb/>apical lobe (arrowhead). We did not detect transcripts of pax6 in control (D&apos;) or <lb/>treated embryos (E&apos;, F&apos;). Scores represent the number of embryos with the phenotype <lb/>shown in the panel against the total number of embryos analyzed: (C) 34/48, (D) <lb/>36/41, (E) 25/26, (F) 27/33, (G) 25/26, (H) 13/18, (K) 28/36, (L) 58/88 (21/88 without <lb/>anterior mesodermal domain), (M) 56/59, (N) 57/72 (12/72 without anterior domain), <lb/>(O) 28/31, (P) 51/53, (U) 30/33, (W) 38/43, (X) 47/66 (11/66 without anterior meso-<lb/>dermal domain), (Z) 13/24, (A&apos;) 34/38, (B&apos;) 37/41, (D&apos;) 24/24, (E&apos;) 36/36, (F&apos;) 29/29. <lb/>Asterisks (*) mark unspecific staining due to the secretion of the larval shell in T. <lb/></body>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>transversa. cb: corpuscular bodies, gc: putative gland cells, al: apical lobe, ml: mantle <lb/>lobe, pl: pedicle lobe, cs: chaetae sacs. Scale bars = 20 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 9. Summary of brachiopod gene expression and comparison to other organ-<lb/>isms. (A) Expression of genes related to the apical/mantle boundary with consistent <lb/>expression between the brachiopods T. transversa and N. anomala (pax6, pax2/5/8 <lb/>and en). (B) Spatial relationship between the expression of pax6, pax2/5/8 and en in <lb/>the di/mesencephalon boundary of the vertebrate brain and the apical/mantle bound-<lb/>ary in the brachiopod larval body. (C) Expression patterns of the segment polarity <lb/>genes en, wnt1, hh, ptc and gli in relation to the parasegments of an arthropod (D. <lb/>melanogaster), larval lobes of a brachiopod (T. transversa) and the trunk segments of <lb/>an annelid (P. dumerilii). White boxes with black border indicate the expected local-<lb/>ization of transcripts for a segment polarity role which are absent in T. transversa. <lb/>Asterisks mark expression patterns that are variable between T. transversa and N. <lb/>anomala. <lb/></body>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 10. Comparative en expression in bilaterians. Phylogenetic tree based on <lb/>(Laumer et al. 2015) and data compiled on Table S1. Dark boxes indicate en is <lb/>expressed in the ectoderm (left column) and mesoderm (right column). Boxes with <lb/>asterisk indicate the tissue where en is first expressed (ectoderm or mesoderm). Light <lb/>boxes mark when en is not found in the ectoderm or mesoderm. Drawings show <lb/>expression of en (vermillion) in embryonic stages of representative groups. Structures <lb/>associated with en expression in each group are listed on the right. <lb/></body>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Additional files <lb/>Additional file 1: Figure S1. Whole mount in situ hybridization of the Hedgehog <lb/>pathway orthologs in representative developmental stages of the brachiopods T. <lb/>transversa and N. anomala. (A,B) Expression of T. transversa ptc and N. anomala <lb/>ptc1. (C,D) Expression of smo. (E,F) Expression of gli. In the radial gastrula, tran-<lb/>scripts of ptc, smo and gli occur in the mesoderm of T. transversa (A1,C1,E1). Tran-<lb/>scripts of ptc are expressed in the mesoderm and endoderm of T. transversa of subse-<lb/>quent stages (A2-A4), except at the posterior pedicle mesoderm (A3,A4). N. anomala <lb/>ptc1 is not expressed in the radial gastrula (B1). Expression is restricted to the anterior <lb/>mesoderm of the asymmetric gastrula (B2); dorsal and anterior ectodermal spots are <lb/>also present at this stage. Transcripts of ptc1 remain in the ventral mesoderm associ-<lb/>ated with the first, second and third coelomic sacs (B3) and fade in the bilobed larva <lb/>of N. anomala (B4). T. transversa smo is ubiquitously expressed in the mesoderm dur-<lb/>ing gastrulation (C1-C3). In the asymmetric and bilateral gastrula we observed a con-<lb/>spicuous anterior smo ectodermal domain as well as expression on the dorsal side <lb/>(C2,C3). Expression was cleared from the anterior mesoderm in the trilobed larva <lb/>(C4). We first detected the expression of N. anomala smo in the asymmetric gastrula <lb/>covering most of the mesoderm except for the anterior portion correspondent to the <lb/>first coelomic sac (D2); a dorsal ectodermal domain is also present. The expression <lb/>fades in the bilateral gastrula and smo is not detected in the bilobed larva (D3,D4). T. <lb/>transversa gli is expressed in the whole mesoderm of the radial and asymmetric gas-<lb/>trula (E1,E2) and in two ectodermal domains, anterior region of the apical lobe and <lb/>mantle lobe (E2). Expression becomes restricted to patches in the mantle mesoderm <lb/>and the ectodermal domains resolve into stripes in the anterior portion of the apical <lb/>and mantle lobes (E3). Finally, in the trilobed larva transcripts of gli are restricted to <lb/>the mantle and pedicle mesoderm (E4). N. anomala gli is expressed in the forming <lb/>second to fourth coelomic pouches but not the in the first (F2-F4) and the expression <lb/></div>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">covers most of the mesoderm in the bilobed larva (F4). Overall, the expression of the <lb/>Hedgehog pathway components are localized to the endoderm and mesoderm and do <lb/>not correlate with the development of ectodermal boundaries in both brachiopod <lb/>species. Anterior is top in all panels and ventral is to the right in all lateral views. <lb/>White arrowheads mark the apical/mantle boundary and black arrowheads mark the <lb/>mantle/pedicle boundary. Scale bars = 20 µm. <lb/></div>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Additional file 2: Figure S2. Additional details about the embryonic expression of en <lb/>and wnt1 in the brachiopods T. transversa and N. anomala. (A-E) Dynamic progres-<lb/>sion of en transcripts at the radial gastrula of T. transversa in blastoporal view. <lb/>(F,G,H) Lateral views correspondent to (B,D,E), respectively, with anterior to the <lb/>right side. (I) Dorsal (left) and lateral view (right) of N. anomala radial gastrula show-<lb/>ing faint en stripe (arrow). (J) Dorsal view of N. anomala asymmetric gastrula with <lb/>two stripes of en (arrows). (K) Dorsal view of N. anomala bilateral gastrula. (L) Con-<lb/>spicuous dorsal domain of en associated with the shell rudiment in the bilobed larva <lb/>of N. anomala in lateral view (arrow). (M) Developed larva of N. anomala with shell <lb/>primordium. Original area with en signal is outlined by white dashed line. Surround-<lb/>ing area is likely unspecific staining related to the shell deposition. (N) Dorsal view of <lb/>a T. transversa bilateral larva showing en expression. (O) Same view as (N) showing <lb/>en expression at the subsequent bilobed larva stage. (P) Absence of wnt1 expression <lb/>on the dorsal side of T. transversa bilateral gastrula. (Q) Same view as (P) showing <lb/>dorsal wnt1 domain of T. transversa bilobed larva. Scale bars = 20 µm. <lb/></div>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Additional file 3: Figure S3. Perturbation of the apical/mantle boundary during over-<lb/>activation of Wnt pathway in T. transversa. We treated developing embryos of T. <lb/>transversa from radial gastrula to bilateral gastrula stage with 1 µM and 10 µM 1-aza-<lb/>kenpaullone diluted in seawater. (A-C) Stereo images showing a maximum intensity <lb/>projection of the epithelial surface of embryos stained for F-actin (cell membranes in <lb/>white). (D-F) Maximum intensity projections of five inner slices (left) and orthogonal <lb/>views (right) of the same embryos as above, but including a nuclei staining (blue) to <lb/>highlight the position of corpuscular bodies. Control sample incubated with DMSO <lb/>show the characteristic ectodermal furrow at the apical/mantle boundary (A, D). <lb/>Embryos treated with 1 µM (B, E) and 10 µM (C, F) 1-azakenpaullone do not form a <lb/>furrow at the apical/mantle boundary. Embryos treated with 1 µM (E) and 10 µM (F) <lb/>1-azakenpaullone do not form a. Absence of an ectodermal furrow at the apical/man-<lb/>tle boundary (arrowheads). White line marks the area between the expected furrow <lb/>position and the mantle lobe stub in treated embryos (E, F). Scale bars = 20 µm. <lb/></div>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Additional file 4: Table S1. Summary of embryonic expression of en, pax6 and pax2/5/8 across bilaterians. Dashes represent absence of expression <lb/>and question marks represent missing data. Expression information based on Cephalochordata en (Holland et al. 1997), pax6 (Glardon et al. 1998) and <lb/>pax2/5/8 (Kozmik et al. 1999); Urochordata en (Cañestro et al. 2005; Imai et al. 2002; Jiang &amp; Smith 2002), pax6 (Glardon et al. 1997) and pax2/5/8 <lb/>(Bassham et al. 2008; Cañestro et al. 2005; Wada et al. 1998); Vertebrata en (Brivanlou &amp; Harland 1989; Danielian &amp; McMahon 1996; Davis et al. <lb/>1991; Ekker et al. 1992; Hatta et al. 1991; Holland et al. 1993; Joyner 1996; Njølstad &amp; Fjose 1988; Patel et al. 1989), pax6 (Derobert et al. 2002; <lb/>Püschel et al. 1992; Walther &amp; Gruss 1991) and pax2/5/8 (Heller &amp; Brändli 1999; McCauley &amp; Bronner-Fraser 2002; Pfeffer et al. 1998); Hemichor-<lb/>data en, pax6 and pax2/5/8 (Lowe et al. 2003; Pani et al. 2012); Echinodermata en (Byrne et al. 2005; Dolecki &amp; Humphreys 1988; Lowe &amp; Wray <lb/>1997; Yaguchi et al. 2006) and pax6 (Omori et al. 2011); Nematoda en (Cassata et al. 2005), pax6 (Chisholm &amp; Horvitz 1995) and pax2/5/8 (Rajaku-<lb/>mar &amp; Chamberlin 2007); Tardigrada en (Gabriel &amp; Goldstein 2007); Onychophora en (Eriksson et al. 2009; Franke &amp; Mayer 2014), pax6 (Eriksson et <lb/>al. 2013; Franke et al. 2015) and pax2/5/8 (Franke et al. 2015); Arthropoda en (Ahzhanov &amp; Kaufman 2000; Brown et al. 1994; Damen 2002; <lb/>DiNardo &amp; O&apos;Farrell 1987; Dougan &amp; DiNardo 1992; Farzana &amp; Brown 2008; Fjose et al. 1985; Fleig 1990; Kornberg et al. 1985; Manzanares et al. <lb/>1993, 1996; Marie &amp; Bacon 2000; Mellenthin et al. 2006; Patel et al. 1989; Whitington et al. 1991), pax6 (Quiring et al. 1994) and pax2/5/8 (Czerny <lb/>et al. 1997); Rotifera pax6 (Boell &amp; Bucher 2008); Platyhelminthes pax6 (Callaerts et al. 1999); Mollusca en (Baratte et al. 2007; Hohagen et al. 2015; <lb/>Jacobs et al. 2000; Moshel et al. 1998; Nederbragt et al. 2002; Wanninger &amp; Haszprunar 2001), pax6 (Hartmann et al. 2003; Navet et al. 2009; <lb/>Tomarev et al. 1997) and pax2/5/8 (O&apos;Brien &amp; Degnan 2003; Wollesen et al. 2015); Annelida en (Bely &amp; Wray 2001; Lans et al. 1993; Prud&apos;homme et <lb/>al. 2003; Seaver &amp; Kaneshige 2006; Seaver et al. 2001; Wedeen &amp; Weisblat 1991), pax6 (Arendt et al. 2002; Denes et al. 2007; Quigley et al. 2007) <lb/>and pax2/5/8 (Denes et al. 2007); Nemertea pax6 (Tarpin et al. 1999). <lb/>taxon <lb/>en (ectoderm) <lb/>en (mesoderm) <lb/>pax6 <lb/>pax2/5/8 <lb/>Cephalochordata <lb/>Bilateral domains in the <lb/>brain. <lb/>Transverse stripes at poste-<lb/>rior region of first eight <lb/>somites. <lb/>Anterior third of neural <lb/>plate. <lb/>Bilateral clusters at the neu-<lb/>ral plate around fifth <lb/>somite. <lb/>Urochordata <lb/>Anterior neuroectoderm. <lb/>-<lb/>Animal hemisphere in two <lb/>bilaterally arranged <lb/>domains. <lb/>Bilateral pair of neural tube <lb/>cells (coexpressed or inter-<lb/>calated with en). <lb/>Vertebrata <lb/>Mid/hindbrain boundary. <lb/>Posterior portion of somites <lb/>after morphology (muscle <lb/>pioneers). <lb/>Anterior domain bordering <lb/>the di/mesencephalon bor-<lb/>der and developing eyes. <lb/>Mid/hindbrain boundary. <lb/>Pronephros, otic vesicle, <lb/>endostyle. <lb/>Hemichordata <lb/>Transverse stripe anterior to <lb/>collar/trunk boundary. <lb/>-<lb/>Anterior domain bordering <lb/>the collar/trunk boundary, <lb/>overlap with en domain. <lb/>Posterior expression (trunk) <lb/>adjacent to en. <lb/></div>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Echinodermata <lb/>Pair of serotonin positive <lb/>cells around the mouth. <lb/>Adult nervous system. <lb/>Lining coelomic sacs. <lb/>Anterior wall of the archen-<lb/>teron in the late gastrula. <lb/>? <lb/>Chaetognatha <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Nematoda <lb/>Bilateral row of epidermal <lb/>cells (seam cells) and ante-<lb/>rior neurons. <lb/>-<lb/>Anterior head cells. <lb/>Egg-laying system during <lb/>organogenesis. <lb/>Tardigrada <lb/>Transverse stripes corre-<lb/>sponding to posterior <lb/>region of underlying <lb/>endomesodermal pouches <lb/>before ectodermal segmen-<lb/>tation. <lb/>-<lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Onychophora <lb/>Segmental transverse <lb/>stripes at posterior region <lb/>of segment with no precise <lb/>boundaries. <lb/>Pair of domains in pre-<lb/>somitic mesoderm before <lb/>segments, but sequentially <lb/>after morphology. <lb/>Cephalic lobe expression <lb/>posterior of the protocere-<lb/>bral/ocular segment. <lb/>Segmental expression <lb/>matching nephridial open-<lb/>ings. <lb/>Arthropoda <lb/>Segmental transverse <lb/>stripes at parasegmental <lb/>boundary and posterior <lb/>region of segment before <lb/>morphology. Posterior of <lb/>imaginal discs, adult <lb/>abdominal segments and <lb/>nervous system. <lb/>Transient segmental expres-<lb/>sion. <lb/>Forming brain, eye primor-<lb/>dia, ventral nerve cord and <lb/>lateral sense organs. <lb/>Few cells per segment. <lb/>Scalidophora <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Rotifera <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Anterior bilateral patches. <lb/>? <lb/>Micrognathozoa <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Gnathostomulida <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Platyhelminthes <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Eyes. <lb/>? <lb/>Gastrotricha <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/></div>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Mollusca <lb/>Delimiting shell compart-<lb/>ment. <lb/>-<lb/>Optic region, brain and <lb/>arms. <lb/>Apical pole during embryo-<lb/>genesis, anterior region of <lb/>the mantle, sensory systems <lb/>and cephalopod brain. <lb/>Annelida <lb/>Variable. Segmental <lb/>expression mainly associ-<lb/>ated to neurons but can <lb/>occur before morphology. <lb/>Mesodermal derivatives <lb/>(nephrostome). <lb/>Anterior bilateral patches <lb/>abutting the prototroch and <lb/>eyes. Nervous system <lb/>before segmentation. <lb/>Trunk nervous system. <lb/>Nemertea <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Anterior dorsolateral <lb/>patches in regenerating <lb/>eyes. <lb/>? <lb/>Brachiopoda <lb/>Two lateral pairs with ante-<lb/>rior domain bordering the <lb/>apical/mantle boundary. <lb/>Posterior portion of two <lb/>coelomic sacs. <lb/>Broad anterior domain bor-<lb/>dering the apical/mantle <lb/>boundary. <lb/>Expressed in the mantle <lb/>lobe. <lb/>Phoronida <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>Bryozoa <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/>? <lb/></div>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Additional file 5: Table S2. Gene specific primer pairs used for molecular cloning in <lb/>T. transversa (Ttra) and N. anomala (Nano), and gene accession numbers in NCBI. <lb/>gene <lb/>primers <lb/>NCBI accession <lb/>Ttra en <lb/>R1 CCATCAGATGAAGAGCCAGACCATTTCG KT253953 <lb/>R2 AGTTTTGCTCGTTTGTTTTGGAACC <lb/>Ttra fgf8 <lb/>F CCGATAGCTTTGGAAGCAAG <lb/>KT253954 <lb/>R CAATGCCAACAATTCAACCA <lb/>Ttra gli <lb/>F CCAGTGAAGCATCTCAAGTGTCG <lb/>KT253955 <lb/>R CGGTTGCGTGCCATACTATTTTG <lb/>Ttra hh <lb/>F AGTGGGAGTTCAGATGGACG <lb/>KT253956 <lb/>R ATGCTCTCACACGGTCTCAA <lb/>Ttra pax6 <lb/>F1 GGATAGTGGAACTGGCACACAGCGGAG KT253957 <lb/>F2 CGGATGTGTGAGCAAGATCCTCGGGAG <lb/>Ttra pax258 <lb/>F TTGCCTGGGAAATACGGGAC <lb/>KT253958 <lb/>R ATCCAGCTGGTTGACTGGTG <lb/>Ttra ptc <lb/>F TTACAGCAGTCAAGAAAGTGGTCG <lb/>KT253959 <lb/>R TGGGGTTGGATGGATGTTAGC <lb/>Ttra smo <lb/>F TGGTCACATTCATTGTCCACCTG <lb/>KT253960 <lb/>R ATCCTCGGTTTCCTCCTTCTCG <lb/>Ttra wnt1 <lb/>F TAGCACACACAGGCAAGATAGTCC <lb/>KT253961 <lb/>R GGAGTAGCAAGTGGAAATGGGG <lb/>Nano en <lb/>F ATGTACTCACAGGAGGAGCCACTC <lb/>KT253962 <lb/>R AGTTGCAGAGCCAATCCGTG <lb/>Nano fgf8 <lb/>F CAACACGGACACTCCAGAAA <lb/>KT253963 <lb/>R TATACGGGCTGTTGGTGTCA <lb/>Nano gli <lb/>F TCAACAAGGCTACAGTCAGC <lb/>KT253964 <lb/>R TGCCTTTTATCCTCGTGACG <lb/>Nano hh <lb/>F ACCTGAGCAGACGACCAGTT <lb/>KT253965 <lb/>R AAAATCCCCCAGTTCAAACC <lb/>Nano pax6 <lb/>F GCAACAGAAGTCAACATGCC <lb/>KT253966 <lb/>R GACAGGCTGATGGATTGAGG <lb/>Nano pax258 F TGGCTGTGTGAGCAAGATACTCG <lb/>KT253967 <lb/>R CTGTGAGGAGAGGAGGCATTGTAG <lb/>Nano ptc1 <lb/>F GGACCCATCCAGCTTTTAGG <lb/>KT253968 <lb/>R ATCCTGTGTCCAGTCAATGC <lb/>Nano smo <lb/>F GCATCCTCTGTACGTGAAGC <lb/>KT253969 <lb/>R CTCGTACCCAGTGGTTTACG <lb/>Nano wnt1 <lb/>F CGAGGAACTAAGTGGTGGACATTAG <lb/>KT253970 <lb/>R TTTCCATCAAGCCCCCTTGG <lb/></div>

			<page>48 <lb/>49 <lb/>50 <lb/>51 <lb/>52 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Additional file 6: Figure S4. Orthology assignment for the brachiopod candidate <lb/>genes used in this study. (A) hh. (B) gli. (C) ptc. (D) smo. (E) en. (F) pax. (G) fgf. (H) <lb/>wnt. Cladograms show branch support values and brachiopod orthologs in red. </div>


	</text>
</tei>
