<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Climatic warming strengthens a positive feedback <lb/>between alpine shrubs and fire <lb/>James S. Camac * ,1,2,3 , Richard J. Williams 4 , Carl-Henrik Wahren 3 , Ary A. Hoffmann 5 <lb/>&amp; Peter A. Vesk 2 <lb/>1 Department of Biological Sciences, Macquarie University, Sydney, NSW 2109, Australia. <lb/>2 The Centre of Excellence for Environmental Decisions, School of BioSciences, The University <lb/>of Melbourne, Melbourne, Victoria 3010, Australia. <lb/>3 Research Centre for Applied Alpine Ecology, La Trobe University, Melbourne, Victoria 3086, <lb/>Australia. <lb/>4 CSIRO Land and Water, Tropical Ecosystems Research Centre, PMB 44 Winnellie, Northern <lb/>Territory 0821, Australia. <lb/>5 Bio21 Institute, School of BioSciences, The University of Melbourne, Victoria 3010, Australia. <lb/>* Email for correspondence: james.camac@gmail.com <lb/> 1 <lb/> Climate change is expected to increase fire activity and woody plant encroachment in arctic <lb/>and alpine landscapes. However, it is unknown whether increases in woody species and fire <lb/> will interact to exacerbate changes in structure, function and composition of these ecosys-<lb/>tems. Here we use field surveys and experimental manipulations to examine warming and <lb/>fire effects on recruitment, growth and survival of seedlings of evergreen obligate seeding <lb/>alpine shrubs. We find that fire substantially increased shrub seedling establishment (up <lb/>to 32-fold) and that warming doubled tall shrub seedling growth rates and could increase <lb/>survival. Warming had limited or no effect on shrub recruitment, post-fire gap-infilling by <lb/>grass, or competitive effects of grass on shrub seedling growth and survival. These findings <lb/>indicate that rising temperatures coupled with more frequent or severe fires will likely exac-<lb/>erbate increases in tall evergreen shrubs by increasing recruitment, doubling growth rates, <lb/>and potentially increasing shrub survival. <lb/></front>

			<body>Accurately forecasting the effects of climatic warming on vegetation dynamics requires an <lb/>understanding of the mechanisms by which climate and vegetation interact. Most forecasting <lb/>models include the direct effects of climatic conditions on species distributions, but largely ig-<lb/>nore biotic interactions and the type, frequency and severity of disturbances that are also likely to <lb/>change 1-3 . Because disturbance strongly influences recruitment opportunities, and thus, composi-<lb/>tion and structure of plant communities and biomes worldwide 4, 5 , it has the capacity to exacerbate <lb/>or diminish how climate affects vegetation. Seedlings are the life stage most vulnerable to climate <lb/>and disturbance, and the life stage which determines the long-term persistence of a species and <lb/>its capacity to establish in new areas. Consequently, it is imperative to understand how seedlings <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>respond to both changing climate and disturbance regimes 6, 7 . <lb/>Field manipulative experiments have been widely used to investigate the effects of climate <lb/>change on plant communities. These experiments have provided invaluable information on how <lb/>climate change directly influences plant phenology 8, 9 , reproduction 10 , morphology 11 , growth 12 , <lb/>floristic composition 13 and biotic interactions 14 . However, because disturbances vary both spatially <lb/>and temporally, most have focused on mature plant responses in relatively undisturbed vegetation 7 . <lb/>As such, few field climate experiments have been conducted on seedlings or vegetation in post-<lb/>disturbance conditions (but see 15-17 ). Consequently, little is known about how climate change in-<lb/>fluences seedling demographic rates 7 and thus, vegetation recovery in post-disturbance conditions. <lb/>We consider these issues in Australian alpine heathland. <lb/>In alpine and arctic ecosystems, warming experiments and long-term monitoring have doc-<lb/>umented significant increases in the growth and cover of woody species 18-20 . The frequency and <lb/>extent of wildfires have also increased in these environments over recent decades, a trend expected <lb/>to continue 21-24 . In alpine and tundra ecosystems, current evidence from long-term and experimen-<lb/>tal studies indicate that shrub recruitment and encroachment is highest in disturbed areas 25-27 , that <lb/>climatic warming is likely to increase woody species growth rates 20, 28, 29 , and that shrubs are the <lb/>most flammable component of these ecosystems 30-32 . The combination of this evidence indicates <lb/>that more frequent or severe fire may increase recruitment opportunities for woody species, which <lb/>when coupled with higher growth and survival rates caused by rising temperatures, will exacerbate <lb/>shrub expansion 33, 34 and ultimately increase the likelihood of fire 20, 31, 32 . In effect, warming could <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>strengthen an existing feedback loop that not only has the potential to cause rapid changes in the <lb/>composition and structure of alpine and arctic vegetation, but also has serious social, biodiversity <lb/>and carbon sequestration consequences 35 . <lb/>While paleoecological studies have indicated that such a feedback may exist 31, 32 , there is a <lb/>paucity of information on multiple mechanisms that may strengthen, mitigate or break this feed-<lb/>back loop (Fig. 1a). For example, we have little information on whether fire will stimulate shrub <lb/>seedling recruitment in alpine or tundra ecosystems, nor do we know how rates of seedling growth <lb/>and survival will be affected under warmer, more exposed, post-fire conditions. Furthermore, we <lb/>do not know how tussock grasslands (the other dominant community in these ecosystems) will <lb/>respond to warmer post-fire conditions, whether grasses have competitive, facilitative or no effect <lb/>on shrub seedling vital rates, or whether such effects are altered by warmer post-fire conditions. <lb/>We examine these unknowns and their impacts on the feedback between climatic warming, <lb/>shrubs and fire in Australian alpine vegetation. As with tundra ecosystems, the Australian Alps <lb/>have experienced rapid changes in climate. Since 1979, mean growing season temperatures have <lb/>risen by approximately 0.4°C and annual precipitation has fallen by 6% 36 , with a consequent de-<lb/>cline in snow pack depth 37 . These climatic changes have been correlated with a 10 to 20% increase <lb/>in shrub cover and a 25% decline in graminoids cover 36 . Much of the Australian Alps has also been <lb/>burnt by recent wildfires, the frequency and severity of which are expected to increase 24, 38 . <lb/>We took advantage of recent fires in alpine open heathland, a plant community that occupies <lb/>ca. 25% of the Australian alpine landscape 38 . Under global warming, this plant community is likely <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>to encroach upon grasslands and is itself susceptible to shrub thickening 39 . To determine drivers <lb/>of shrub establishment and how warmer post-fire conditions affect shrub cover, we combined field <lb/>observations with a warming experiment that used seedlings of four Australian evergreen obligate <lb/>seeding shrubs: Grevillea australis (Proteaceae; a tall shrub), Asterolasia trymalioides (Rutaceae; <lb/>a prostrate shrub), Phebalium squamulosum (Rutaceae; a tall shrub) and Prostanthera cuneata <lb/>(Lamiaceae; a tall shrub). This combination of data sources allowed us to examine: 1) landscape <lb/>scale drivers of shrub seedling establishment; 2) how warmer post-fire conditions influence rates <lb/>of grass recovery and shrub seedling recruitment, growth and mortality; 3) how proximity to grass <lb/>affect shrub seedling demographic rates; and 4) whether such grass effects change under warmer <lb/>post-fire conditions. <lb/>Drivers of shrub seedling establishment. We first investigated how altitude, Topographic Wet-<lb/>ness Index (TWI), adult density, fire and fire severity (as measured by post-fire twig diameters-see <lb/>Supplementary Methods) influenced the density of Grevillea and Asterolasia seedlings (the two <lb/>dominant shrubs of alpine open heathland). In 2011-12, we estimated seedling density for both <lb/>species across 40 alpine sites and found that the abundances of Grevillea (Fig. 2) and Asterola-<lb/>sia (Supplementary Fig. S1) seedlings were strongly influenced by the occurrence of fire. Sites <lb/>burnt in 2003 had seedling densities between 14 and 32 times higher than unburnt sites. The mean <lb/>seedling density of Grevillea, was 1.3/m 2 at burnt sites and 0.04/m 2 at unburnt sites. Asterolasia <lb/>had similar mean densities: 1.63 and 0.12 seedlings/m 2 at burnt and unburnt sites, respectively. For <lb/>both species, seedling density was also higher in severely burnt sites (i.e. sites with larger post-<lb/>fire twig diameters). As expected, pre-fire adult density positively influenced Grevillea seedling <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>density. For both shrub species, we detected no change in seedling density along a 190 m altitu-<lb/>dinal range (equivalent to a 1.5°C change in mean temperature 40 ). The field warming experiment <lb/>(see below) indicates that this lack of elevation response in Grevillea is due to rates of recruitment <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. S2) and mortality (see below) largely being insensitive to a 1°C change in <lb/>temperature. We detected no strong effect of Topographic Wetness Index for either species. <lb/>Experimental warming effects on shrub seedling growth. As shrub seedlings were more abun-<lb/>dant in burnt vegetation, we investigated how warmer post-fire conditions affected seedling growth <lb/>and mortality rates. Seedlings of Grevillea, Asterolasia, Phebalium and Prostanthera emerging <lb/>after a wildfire were transplanted into experimentally burnt plots. These plots were either enclosed <lb/>in Open Top Chambers (OTCs) whose temperature was 1°C warmer than control plots subjected to <lb/>current ambient conditions. After 1813 days (1087 growing season days) or 5 years&apos; growth, mean <lb/>seedling heights of the tall shrubs (Grevillea, Phebalium and Prostanthera) growing in post-fire <lb/>bare ground were greater in warmed plots relative to controls by 9.7, 3.8 and 13.8 cm, respectively <lb/>(Fig. 3a). Warming increased heights of both Grevillea and Prostanthera seedlings in all years, <lb/>while Phebalium did not respond to the warming treatment until the second growing season. By <lb/>contrast, seedlings of the prostrate shrub, Asterolasia, showed no difference in growth rate between <lb/>warmed and control plots in any year. For each species, we also observed similar treatment trends <lb/>with stem diameter growth (Supplementary Fig. S3). Accounting for initial height and assuming <lb/>logistic growth, the rates of change in mean annual predicted height of Grevillea, Phebalium and <lb/>Prostanthera were 2.4, 1.4 and 1.9 times that observed in control plots, respectively. According to <lb/>this model, a 6 cm seedling (the mean initial height of seedlings used in this experiment) attains <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>maximum height 39 years sooner 38 (Grevillea) or 17 years sooner (Phebalium and Prostanthera) <lb/>when warmed by 1°C (Fig. 3b). Asterolasia was predicted to reach its maximum height in approx-<lb/>imately 22 to 24 years, irrespective of warming treatment. <lb/>We validated the Grevillea and Asterolasia growth responses observed in experimentally <lb/>warmed plots by examining the effect of elevation on maximum heights of post-fire recruits across <lb/>30 open heathland sites burnt in 2003. Here, a 190 m altitudinal range is equivalent to a mean <lb/>ambient temperature difference of approximately 1.5°C 40 , which is comparable to that observed <lb/>between experimentally warmed and control plots (1°C). In response to shifts in temperature, the <lb/>maximum height of Grevillea post-fire recruits was expected to decrease with elevation, whereas <lb/>Asterolasia seedlings were not expected to show this pattern. Our experimental predictions were <lb/>verified (Supplementary Fig. S4). Mean maximum height of Grevillea seedlings in burnt open <lb/>heathland were 8 cm taller at 1670 m a.s.l compared to seedlings at 1860 m a.s.l. (22 cm vs 14 <lb/>cm; a difference comparable to our experimental findings). In contrast, mean maximum height of <lb/>Asterolasia seedlings did not vary significantly with elevation. Topographic Wetness Index and <lb/>fire severity had no detectable influence on maximum seedling heights in either species. <lb/>Experimental warming on shrub seedling mortality. After five years and across all plots, 34% <lb/>(172 out of 511) of all seedlings growing in burnt bare ground patches had died. Most deaths <lb/>occurred in Asterolasia (65) followed by Phebalium (63), Grevillea (31) and Prostanthera (13). <lb/>Prostanthera showed the largest treatment effect (Fig. 4), with annual mortality rates estimated to <lb/>be near 0% in warmed plots and 4% in control plots. This significant decrease in mortality may <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>be a consequence of OTCs reducing the severity of spring frosts by rising minimum ambient and <lb/>soil temperatures by 0.9°C and 1.6°C, respectively (see Supplementary Fig S5-7). Warming also <lb/>reduced mean seedling mortality in Grevillea and Phebalium (Fig. 4); however, for both species, <lb/>the effect was highly uncertain (i.e. credible intervals overlap). By contrast, annual mortality rates <lb/>in the prostrate shrub, Asterolasia, were marginally higher in warmed plots, but again this effect <lb/>was highly uncertain (Fig. 4). <lb/>Effects of tussock grass proximity on shrub seedling growth and mortality rates. Climate <lb/>change is expected to alter biotic interactions because their strength and direction depend strongly <lb/>on climatic conditions, particularly in alpine and arctic ecosystems 14, 41 . Here, we assess the inter-<lb/>active effects of warming and grass proximity on the growth and survival of Grevillea seedlings <lb/>transplanted into various sized inter-tussock gaps (Fig. 5). We detected a strong positive effect <lb/>of warming treatment on growth rates and a marginal, yet not significant, decrease in mortality. <lb/>However, we did not detect significant inter-tussock gap size effects or an interaction between gap <lb/>size and warming treatment on either growth or mortality rates (i.e. coefficient credible intervals <lb/>overlap zero). <lb/>Experimental warming and rates of gap infilling by tussock grass. Despite having little impact <lb/>on shrub seedling growth and mortality rates, tussock grass may still limit shrub recruitment, and <lb/>thus, shrub expansion, by infilling post-fire bare ground gaps (whether by vegetative growth or <lb/>seedlings) faster under warmer conditions. Using five years of post-fire inter-tussock gap size <lb/>changes in warmed and unwarmed plots we found that gaps were being infilled by tussock grasses <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Fig. 6). However, the rate at which this occurred was very slow, with a 10 cm radius gap predicted <lb/>to decrease by approximately 2 cm over a ten year period. We also detected no significant effect <lb/>of a 1°C temperature rise on the rate of infilling. <lb/>Strengthening of the warming-shrub-fire feedback. Here we quantified several unknown inter-<lb/>actions between fire, shrub-grass relationships and climate to extend a conceptual model of alpine <lb/>shrub dynamics under climate change (Fig. 1b). We showed how these interactions strengthen a <lb/>hypothesized feedback loop that can rapidly increase shrub cover in alpine and tundra ecosystems 31 . <lb/>The combination of rising temperatures and more frequent or severe fire creates conditions that <lb/>allow shrub seedlings to establish in greater densities, and for tall shrubs, double their growth <lb/>rates and potentially increase their survival. These demographic effects will ultimately result <lb/>in shrub thickening and expansion into grasslands. Coupled with field 30 , experimental 42 and <lb/>paleoecological 31 evidence, which indicate that shrubs are the most flammable component of alpine <lb/>and tundra ecosystems, our results suggest that flammable fuel loads will accumulate faster and <lb/>cover a larger proportion of the alpine and arctic landscapes under a warmer environment. This <lb/>further strengthens the feedback 31, 32 by potentially increasing the frequency or severity of fires, <lb/>which then creates further recruitment opportunities for shrubs with little demographic impact of <lb/>neighbouring tussock grass. <lb/>While we have addressed several unknowns associated with this feedback between climatic <lb/>warming, shrubs and fire, there are others we have not addressed that may also strengthen, weaken <lb/>or break this feedback. The most obvious mechanism that will break this cycle involves shorter <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>fire intervals that prevent obligate seeding shrubs reaching reproductive age and thereby exhausting <lb/>the seedbank. However, this scenario is unlikely for the majority of alpine (or tundra) landscapes, <lb/>including in Australia, where current fire intervals of 50 to 100 years would need to decrease to less <lb/>than 20 years-the time estimated for the species in this study to reach reproductive maturity 43 . <lb/>Furthermore, if reproductive output is related to plant size 44 , then climatic warming may allow <lb/>obligate seeding species to reach reproductive maturity sooner, and consequently, may increase <lb/>species resilience to short fire intervals. Nevertheless, these factors and others such as changes in <lb/>snow pack 45 , soil moisture 46 or herbivory 47 require further research because they are likely to be <lb/>altered by the interactive effects of climate and disturbance in unpredictable ways 20 . <lb/>Our findings provide mechanistic understanding as to why shrub cover has increased, of-<lb/>ten at the expense of grasslands, in many alpine and arctic ecosystems 20, 27, 33, 34 . But more im-<lb/>portantly, our results provide evidence for underlying processes that could result in a warming-<lb/>fire-shrub feedback that has been hypothesized in paleoecological studies 31, 32 . Based on current <lb/>observations and predictions, average global temperature has already increased by 0.85°C since <lb/>1880 and is expected to rise by as much as 4.8°C by 2100 48 . In alpine and tundra environments, <lb/>temperatures 49 , shrub cover 20 and the frequency and severity of fire 21-24 have all increased in the <lb/>last few decades. These changes mean that the warming-shrub-fire feedback loop identified here <lb/>has already strengthened, which could cause grasslands and other non-woody communities to tran-<lb/>sition to an alternative state with more shrubs and more fire, both of which are likely to have <lb/>consequences for carbon sequestration, water supply and biodiversity. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Methods <lb/>We investigated shrub dynamics in open heathland because it is a common and highly flammable <lb/>plant community in the Australian Alps above 1600 m a.s.l 30 . It is also an ecotone between closed <lb/>heathland (&gt;70% shrub cover) and tussock grassland consisting of Grevillea australis shrubs in-<lb/>terspersed among a Poa hiemata sward. Aerial photography has revealed that the plant community <lb/>has acted as an invasion front of shrub expansion into grassland and has itself experienced shrub <lb/>thickening by closed heathland dominants such as Prostanthera cuneata 39 . <lb/>Open Top Chamber Experiment. In March 2010, at 1750 m a.s.l, we burnt 32 randomly selected <lb/>mature (60 cm tall and 1.5 m 2 ) Grevillea australis shrubs in open heathland to create patches of <lb/>bare ground approximately 0.7 m 2 surrounded by burnt tussock grass, simulating disturbance in <lb/>open heathland burnt by wildfire. After creating the bare ground patches we collected seedlings of <lb/>dominant alpine shrub species from a nearby (&lt;2 km) site of similar altitude burnt by a late 2006 <lb/>wildfire. We collected shrub seedlings of two dominant open heathland species Grevillea australis <lb/>(Proteaceae; a tall shrub) and Asterolasia trymalioides (Rutaceae; a prostrate shrub), a dominant <lb/>closed heathland species Prostanthera cuneata (Lamiaceae; a tall shrub) that typically grows on <lb/>warmer aspects and a species common to both open and closed heathland Phebalium squamulosum <lb/>(Rutaceae; a tall shrub). All four species are killed by fire 50 . <lb/>A total of 640 seedlings, 256 Grevillea (half used in Poa inter-tussock experiment-see <lb/>below) and 128 for each of Asterolasia, Prostanthera and Phebalium were used. Four seedlings <lb/>per species were randomly selected and transplanted into a 4×4 square grid in the center of each <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>burnt patch, with 14 cm between individuals and the edge of the patch dominated by resprouting <lb/>tussock grass Poa hiemata. To examine interactions between tussock grass and shrub seedlings we <lb/>also randomly transplanted four additional Grevillea australis into various sized inter-tussock gaps <lb/>between burnt Poa hiemata immediately surrounding the bare ground (Supplementary Fig. S8). <lb/>The experimental site was fenced to prevent grazing by deer and horses. We detected no obvious <lb/>signs of rabbit or invertebrate herbivory within our plots. <lb/>To simulate near-term warmer conditions indicated by the IPCC 48 , we randomly assigned <lb/>Open Top Chambers (OTCs) to half (16) the plots, with the remainder treated as unwarmed con-<lb/>trols. OTCs were placed over plots, ensuring all seedlings (including inter-tussock shrub seedlings) <lb/>occurred within the 1.1 m 2 open top to minimise edge effects. OTCs were placed out at the start <lb/>of the growing season (October) where they remained until snowfall (early June). This procedure <lb/>was repeated for five growing seasons from May 2010 to May 2015. <lb/>Microclimatic conditions were measured hourly using Onset Micro Stations (Onset Com-<lb/>puter Corporation, Bourne, MA, USA) at four control and four OTC plots. Across 5 growing <lb/>seasons (1087 growing season days), OTCs simulated warmer conditions at the lower end of IPCC <lb/>projections 48 (Supplementary Fig. S5-7). OTCs passively increased average ambient and soil tem-<lb/>peratures by 1°C, and 0.9°C, respectively. Minimum and maximum temperatures were also raised <lb/>in both ambient air (min: 0.9°C; max: 2.4°C) and soil (min: 1.6°C; max: 1°C). Chambers only <lb/>marginally decreased soil moisture by 0.2% and relative humidity by 1.2%. <lb/>Seedling survival, maximum height and stem diameter (nearest mm measured with Vernier <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>calipers) were initially recorded in May 2010 and then subsequently re-measured at the end of each <lb/>growing season (May-June). At the same time, we recorded the distance to the nearest tussock or <lb/>grass seedling in each of four cardinal directions for shrub seedlings growing in inter-tussock <lb/>gaps. Thus, changes in inter-tussock gap size could be due to either vegetative growth or seedling <lb/>establishment. We did not measure individual characteristics (e.g. height and basal diameter) of <lb/>surrounding tussock grass because we could not distinguish individuals, and because height varied <lb/>throughout the season. Numbers of natural Grevillea australis recruits establishing within the plots <lb/>were also recorded for the first two seasons. <lb/>Seedling gradient study. We used 40 long-term open heathland sites established after the 2003 <lb/>fires 50 consisting of 30 burnt sites and 10 sites thought to be unburnt for over 70 years. In the <lb/>summer of 2011-12, at each site, seedling density/m 2 was estimated using 40 quadrats, each 1 m 2 , <lb/>that were evenly distributed in groups of 10 along four 50 m transects, with 10 m between transect <lb/>lines, subsampling an area of 2000 m 2 . Within plots we recorded the number and maximum <lb/>height of Grevillea and Asterolasia seedlings. For unburnt sites we counted the number of mature <lb/>Grevillea plants (&gt;0.5 m 2 ) within 5 m of each transect. In burnt sites, this required counting the <lb/>number of skeletons (there were no living adults at any burnt site) that still persisted post-fire. We <lb/>were unable to estimate numbers of adult Asterolasia because this species does not have a persistent <lb/>woody skeleton post-fire. Site level data, elevation and Topographic Wetness Index (TWI) were <lb/>obtained from a 30 m resolution digital elevation model. Lastly, for burnt sites, fire severity was <lb/>estimated by twig diameters, collected immediately after the 2003 fires 50 . <lb/>Data analysis. In total we built 11 hierarchical models to examine factors influencing post-fire <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>recovery of tussock grass and shrub seedling establishment, growth and mortality. For each model <lb/>we used Bayesian inference and fitted models in R 3.2.2 using package rstan 2.8.1. Data and <lb/>source code for reproducing analysis and figures are available at: https://github.com/ <lb/>jscamac/Alpine_Shrub_Experiment. Additional information about experimental design <lb/>and analysis can be found in Supplementary Methods. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This research was funded through Australian Research Council Linkage Grants, partnered through <lb/>the Department of Sustainability and Environment, Parks Victoria, Commonwealth Scientific and <lb/>Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO). Funding was also received from the Centre of Excel-<lb/>lence for Environmental Decisions (CEED) and Holsworth Research Committee. J.S.C was a <lb/>recipient of an Australian Postgraduate Award. Monica Camac, Brad Farmilo, Monica Hursburgh, <lb/>Paulius Kviecinskas, Karen Stott, Imogen Fraser, Sarah Bartlett, Paul Smart, Steven Rumbold, <lb/>Lachlan Yourn and Chris Jones provided assistance with field measurements. William Morris <lb/>and John Baumgartner provided coding advice and Warwick Papst provided field logistic advice. <lb/>Daniel Falster and Richard Fitzjohn for developing software that enabled these analyses to be <lb/>readily reproducible. Special thanks to David Bowman, Anaïs Gibert, John Morgan, Kimberley <lb/>Millers, Michaela Plein and Inka Veltheim for their comments on this manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>J.C. conceived, designed and performed the experiments, field surveys and analysis; C-H.W, R.W, <lb/>A.H and P.V. supervised the development of this work, aided in data collection and provided sta-<lb/>tistical advice. All authors contributed to the writing of this manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing financial interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing financial interests. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Guisan, A. &amp; Thuiller, W. Predicting species distribution: offering more than simple habitat <lb/>models. Ecology Letters 8, 993-1009 (2005). <lb/>2. Tucker, C. M., Rebelo, A. G. &amp; Manne, L. L. Contribution of disturbance to distribution and <lb/>abundance in a fire-adapted system. Ecography 35, 348-355 (2012). <lb/>3. Giannini, T. C., Chapman, D. S., Saraiva, A. M., Alves-dos Santos, I. &amp; Biesmeijer, J. C. <lb/>Improving species distribution models using biotic interactions: a case study of parasites, <lb/>pollinators and plants. Ecography 36, 649-656 (2013). <lb/>4. Bond, W. J., Woodward, F. I. &amp; Midgley, G. F. The global distribution of ecosystems in a <lb/>world without fire. New Phytologist 165, 525-538 (2005). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>5. Turner, M. G. Disturbance and landscape dynamics in a changing world. Ecology 91, 2833-<lb/>2849 (2010). <lb/>6. Walck, J. L., Hidayati, S. N., Dixon, K. W., Thompson, K. &amp; Poschlod, P. Climate change and <lb/>plant regeneration from seed. Global Change Biology 17, 2145-2161 (2011). <lb/>7. Briceño, V. F., Hoyle, G. L. &amp; Nicotra, A. B. Seeds at risk: How will a changing alpine <lb/>climate affect regeneration from seeds in alpine areas? Verónica F. Briceño, Gemma L. Hoyle <lb/>&amp; Adrienne B. Nicotra. Alpine Botany 125, 59-68 (2015). <lb/>8. Hoffmann, A. A. et al. Phenological changes in six Australian subalpine plants in response to <lb/>experimental warming and year-to-year variation. Journal of Ecology 98, 927-937 (2010). <lb/>9. Dorji, T. et al. Plant functional traits mediate reproductive phenology and success in response <lb/>to experimental warming and snow addition in Tibet. Global Change Biology 19, 459-472 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>10. Klady, R. A., Henry, G. H. R. &amp; Lemay, V. Changes in high arctic tundra plant reproduction in <lb/>response to long-term experimental warming. Global Change Biology 17, 1611-1624 (2011). <lb/>11. Hudson, J. M. G. &amp; Henry, G. H. R. Increased plant biomass in a High Arctic heath community <lb/>from 1981 to 2008. Ecology 90, 2657-2663 (2009). <lb/>12. Hollister, R. D., Webber, P. J. &amp; Bay, C. Plant response to temperature in Northern Alaska: <lb/>Implications for predicting vegetation change. Ecology 86, 1562-1570 (2005). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>13. Elmendorf, S. C. et al. Global assessment of experimental climate warming on tundra vegeta-<lb/>tion: heterogeneity over space and time. Ecology Letters 15, 164-175 (2012). <lb/>14. Klanderud, K. Climate change effects on species interactions in an alpine plant community. <lb/>Journal of Ecology 93, 127-137 (2005). <lb/>15. Munier, A., Hermanutz, L., Jacobs, J. D. &amp; Lewis, K. The interacting effects of tempera-<lb/>ture, ground disturbance, and herbivory on seedling establishment: implications for treeline <lb/>advance with climate warming. Plant Ecology 210, 19-30 (2010). <lb/>16. Graae, B. J. et al. Strong microsite control of seedling recruitment in tundra. Oecologia 166, <lb/>565-576 (2010). <lb/>17. Camac, J. S. et al. Modeling rates of life form cover change in burned and unburned alpine <lb/>heathland subject to experimental warming. Oecologia 178, 615-628 (2015). <lb/>18. Sturm, M., Racine, C. H. &amp; Tape, K. Climate change: increasing shrub abundance in the <lb/>Arctic. Nature 411, 546-547 (2001). <lb/>19. Walker, M. D. et al. Plant community responses to experimental warming across the tundra <lb/>biome. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 103, 1342-1346 (2006). <lb/>20. Myers-Smith, I. H. et al. Shrub expansion in tundra ecosystems: dynamics, impacts and <lb/>research priorities. Environmental Research Letters 6, 045509 (2011). <lb/>21. Westerling, A., Hidalgo, H., Cayan, D. &amp; Swetnam, T. W. Warming and earlier spring increase <lb/>western US forest wildfire activity. Nature 313, 940 (2006). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>22. Flannigan, M. D., Krawchuk, M. A., de Groot, W. J., Wotton, B. M. &amp; Gowman, L. M. <lb/>Implications of changing climate for global wildland fire. International Journal of Wildland <lb/>Fire 18, 483-507 (2009). <lb/>23. Qiu, J. Tundra&apos;s burning. Nature 461, 34-36 (2009). <lb/>24. Bradstock, R., Penman, T., Boer, M., Price, O. &amp; Clarke, H. Divergent responses of fire to <lb/>recent warming and drying across south-eastern Australia. Global Change Biology 20, 1412-<lb/>1428 (2014). <lb/>25. Williams, R. J. &amp; Ashton, D. H. The composition structure and distribution of heathland and <lb/>grassland communities in the subalpine tract of the Bogong High Plains Victoria Australia. <lb/>Austral Ecology 12, 57-72 (1987). <lb/>26. Batllori, E., Camarero, J. J., Ninot, J. M. &amp; Gutiérrez, E. Seedling recruitment, survival and <lb/>facilitation in alpine Pinus uncinatatree line ecotones. Implications and potential responses to <lb/>climate warming. Global Ecology and Biogeography 18, 460-472 (2009). <lb/>27. Frost, G. V., Epstein, H. E., Walker, D. A., Matyshak, G. &amp; Ermokhina, K. Patterned-ground <lb/>facilitates shrub expansion in Low Arctic tundra. Environmental Research Letters 8, 015035 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>28. Arft, A. M. et al. Responses of Tundra plants to experimental to experimental warming: <lb/>meta-analysis of the International Tundra Experiment. Ecological Monographs 69, 491-511 <lb/>(1999). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>29. Elmendorf, S. C. et al. Plot-scale evidence of tundra vegetation change and links to recent <lb/>summer warming. Nature Climate Change 2, 453-457 (2012). <lb/>30. Williams, R. J., Wahren, C.-H., Bradstock, R. A. &amp; Muller, W. J. Does alpine grazing reduce <lb/>blazing? A landscape test of a widely-held hypothesis. Austral Ecology 31, 925-936 (2006). <lb/>31. Higuera, P. E. et al. Frequent fires in ancient shrub tundra: Implications of paleorecords for <lb/>arctic environmental change. PLoS ONE 3, e0001744 (2008). <lb/>32. Higuera, P. E., Brubaker, L. B., Anderson, P. M., Hu, F. S. &amp; Brown, T. A. Vegetation mediated <lb/>the impacts of postglacial climate change on fire regimes in the south-central Brooks Range, <lb/>Alaska. Ecological Monographs 79, 201-219 (2009). <lb/>33. Racine, C. H., Jandt, R., Meyers, C. &amp; Dennis, J. Tundra fire and vegetation change along a <lb/>hillslope on the Seward Peninsula, Alaska, U.S.A. Arctic Antarctic and Alpine Research 36, <lb/>1-10 (2004). <lb/>34. Lantz, T. C., Marsh, P. &amp; Kokelj, S. V. Recent shrub proliferation in the Mackenzie Delta <lb/>uplands and microclimatic implications. Ecosystems 16, 47-59 (2013). <lb/>35. Mack, M. C. et al. Carbon loss from an unprecedented Arctic tundra wildfire. Nature 475, <lb/>489-492 (2011). <lb/>36. Wahren, C.-H. et al. Experimental warming and long-term vegetation dynamics in an alpine <lb/>heathland. Australian Journal of Botany 61, 36-51 (2013). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>37. Sánchez-Bayo, F. &amp; Green, K. Australian snowpack disappearing under the influence of global <lb/>warming and solar activity. Arctic Antarctic and Alpine Research 45, 107-118 (2013). <lb/>38. Williams, R. J. et al. Alpine Ecosystems. In Lindenmayer, D. B., Burns, E., Thurgate, N. &amp; <lb/>Lowe, A. (eds.) Biodiversity and Environmental Change: Monitoring, Challenges and Direc-<lb/>tions, 167-212 (CSIRO Publishing, Melbourne, 2014). <lb/>39. McDougall, K. L. Aerial photographic interpretation of vegetation changes on the Bogong <lb/>High Plains, Victoria, between 1936 and 1980. Austral Ecology 51, 251-256 (2003). <lb/>40. Brown, J. A. H. &amp; Millner, F. C. Aspects of meterology and hydrology in the Australian Alps. <lb/>In Good, R. B. (ed.) The Scientific Significance of the Australian Alps, 122-171 (Proceedings <lb/>of the first Fenner Conference on the Environment, Canberra, 1989). <lb/>41. Callaway, R. et al. Positive interactions among alpine plants increase with stress. Nature 417, <lb/>844-848 (2002). <lb/>42. Fraser, I. P., Williams, R. J., Murphy, B. P., Camac, J. S. &amp; Vesk, P. A. Fuels and <lb/>landscape flammability in an Australian alpine environment. Austral Ecology (2016). <lb/>doi:10.1111/aec.12355. <lb/>43. Williams, R. J. et al. Large fires in Australian alpine landscapes: their part in the historical <lb/>fire regime and their impacts on alpine biodiversity. International Journal of Wildland Fire <lb/>17, 793-808 (2008). <lb/>44. Wenk, E. H. &amp; Falster, D. S. Quantifying and understanding reproductive allocation schedules <lb/>in plants. Ecology and Evolution 5, 5521-5538 (2015). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>45. Wipf, S., Stoeckli, V. &amp; Bebi, P. Winter climate change in alpine tundra: plant responses to <lb/>changes in snow depth and snowmelt timing. Climatic Change 94, 105-121 (2009). <lb/>46. Engler, R. et al. 21st century climate change threatens mountain flora unequally across Europe. <lb/>Global Change Biology 17, 2330-2341 (2011). <lb/>47. Post, E. &amp; Pedersen, C. Opposing plant community responses to warming with and without <lb/>herbivores. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 105, 12353-12358 (2008). <lb/>48. IPCC. Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to <lb/>the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (Cambridge <lb/>University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA, 2013). <lb/>49. Chapin III, F. S. et al. Role of land-surface changes in arctic summer warming. Nature 310, <lb/>657-660 (2005). <lb/>50. Camac, J. S., Williams, R. J., Wahren, C.-H., Morris, W. K. &amp; Morgan, J. W. Post-fire regen-<lb/>eration in alpine heathland: Does fire severity matter? Austral Ecology 38, 199-207 (2013). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figures <lb/>Increased ambient <lb/>temperature <lb/>Fire <lb/>Shrub seedling <lb/>growth &amp; survival <lb/>Shrub establishment <lb/>Tussock grass <lb/>Bare ground <lb/>M o re g re e n h o u s e <lb/>g a s e s <lb/>More flammable fuel <lb/>Does warming alter grass <lb/>post-fire recovery? <lb/>Does proximity to grass influence <lb/>shrub seedling growth and survival <lb/>Does warming alter shrub seedling <lb/>growth and survival? <lb/>Does warming alter shrub <lb/>recruitment in bare ground? <lb/>Does fire stimulate <lb/>shrub recruitment? <lb/>Increased ambient <lb/>temperature <lb/>Fire <lb/>Shrub seedling <lb/>growth &amp; survival <lb/>Shrub establishment <lb/>Tussock grass <lb/>Landscape <lb/>flammability <lb/>Bare ground <lb/>M o re g re e n h o u s e <lb/>g a s e s <lb/>More flammable fuel <lb/>Faster <lb/>accumulation of <lb/>flammable fuels <lb/>If fire interval &lt; 20 <lb/>years <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>Landscape <lb/>flammability <lb/>Figure 1 Conceptual diagram illustrating positive warming-shrub-fire feedback loop. (a) <lb/>Hypothesised positive feedback loop between fire, climatic warming and landscape flammability. <lb/>Solid blue lines = known mechansims; Dashed black lines = mechansims that may exacerbate <lb/>or diminish this feedback loop but which we have a paucity of information on. (b) Feedback loop <lb/>based on new evidence obtained from experimental and field surveys conducted in this study. <lb/>Also includes an example of a potential, but unlikely, effect (red dotted line) that could break this <lb/>feedback. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>Adult density <lb/>TWI <lb/>Altitude <lb/>Severity <lb/>Unburnt <lb/>Intercept <lb/>−4 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>log coefficients <lb/>a <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>Unburnt <lb/>Burnt <lb/>Seedlings / m 2 <lb/>b <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>12.5 <lb/>Minimum Twig diameter (mm) <lb/>Seedlings / m 2 <lb/>c <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>1700 <lb/>1750 <lb/>1800 <lb/>1850 <lb/>Altitude (m) <lb/>Seedlings / m 2 <lb/>d <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>Topographic wetness index <lb/>Seedlings / m 2 <lb/>e <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Adults/ m 2 <lb/>Seedlings / m 2 <lb/>f <lb/>Figure 2 Mean Grevillea australis seedling density along gradients of burning, fire severity <lb/>(twig diameter), altitude, Topographic Wetness Index (TWI) and adult density. (a) Centered <lb/>and standardized model coefficients (on the log scale); and effects of: (b) burning, (c) fire severity, <lb/>(d) altitude, (e) topographic wetness and (f) adult density, in areas burnt by the 2003 fires. All bars <lb/>and shaded areas indicate 95% Bayesian Credible Intervals. <lb/> 401 <lb/>402 <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>Asterolasia <lb/>Grevillea <lb/>Phebalium <lb/>Prostanthera <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>2010 <lb/>2012 <lb/>2014 <lb/>2010 <lb/>2012 <lb/>2014 <lb/>2010 <lb/>2012 <lb/>2014 <lb/>2012 <lb/>2014 <lb/>Observation year <lb/>Observed height (cm) <lb/>a <lb/>Asterolasia <lb/>Grevillea <lb/>Phebalium <lb/>Prostanthera <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>Year <lb/>Projected height (cm) <lb/>b <lb/>Figure 3 Observed and projected growth trajectories of four dominant Australian alpine <lb/>shrubs. (a) Observed height growth: Thick lines with error bars represent mean (± 95% con-<lb/>fidence intervals) observed heights at each May census. Thin lines represent individual growth <lb/>trajectories. (b) Mean (± 95% Bayesian Credible Interval) projected growth trajectories. In all <lb/>cases, red and orange lines = seedlings growing in warmed (OTC) conditions and blue and light <lb/>blue lines = seedlings growing in control conditions. Projections were based on an logistic growth <lb/>model using initial seedling size of 6 cm (the mean initial height observed in the OTC experiment) <lb/>and mean maximum heights observed in long-unburnt sites (i.e. 34, 67, 66 &amp; 70 cm for Asterola-<lb/>sia, Grevillea, Phebalium, &amp; Prostanthera, respectively). <lb/> 403 <lb/>404 <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>Asterolasia Grevillea Phebalium Prostanthera <lb/>Species <lb/>Annual probability of death <lb/>Figure 4 Mean (± 95% Bayesian Credible Interval) annual probability of death for each <lb/>species growing in control (blue) and warmed (red) conditions. <lb/> 405 <lb/>406 <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>warmed x gap <lb/>gap <lb/>warmed <lb/>intercept <lb/>−0.05 0.00 0.05 0.10 0.15 0.20 0.25 <lb/>Growth coefficients <lb/>a <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>Inter−tussock gap radius (cm) <lb/>logistic growth rate parameter (R) <lb/>b <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>warmed x gap <lb/>gap <lb/>warmed <lb/>intercept <lb/>−4 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Mortality coefficents (cloglog scale) <lb/>c <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>Inter−tussock gap radius (cm) <lb/>Annual probability of death <lb/>d <lb/>Figure 5 Experimental warming and inter-tussock gap size effects on Grevillea australis <lb/>seedlings. Top rows = Growth rate effects, Second row = Mortality effects. (a &amp; c) Centered <lb/>and standardized model coefficients; (b &amp; d) growth and mortality rate response curves along an <lb/>inter-tussock gap size gradient in warmed (red) and control (blue) conditions. All error bars and <lb/>shading are 95% Bayesian Credible Intervals. <lb/> 407 <lb/>408 <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>q <lb/>q <lb/>otc <lb/>Intercept <lb/>−0.05 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>log coefficients <lb/>a <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>Year <lb/>Inter−tussock gap radius (cm) <lb/>b <lb/>Figure 6 Effects of warming on rates of gap infilling by tussock grass. (a) Model coefficients <lb/>and (b) projected temporal change in size for an average 10 cm inter-tussock gap in warmed (red) <lb/>and unwarmed (blue) conditions. All error bars and shading are 95% Bayesian Credible Intervals. <lb/> 409 <lb/>410 <lb/></body> 

			<page>27 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
