<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>No &apos;small genome attraction&apos; artifact: A response to Harish et al. <lb/>&apos;Did viruses evolve as a distinct supergroup from common ancestors of <lb/>cells?&apos; <lb/>Arshan Nasir 1 , Kyung Mo Kim 2 and Gustavo Caetano-Anollés 3* <lb/>1 Department of Biosciences, COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Islamabad <lb/>45550, Pakistan <lb/>2 Biological Resource Center, Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology, <lb/>Jeongeup, Republic of Korea <lb/>3 Evolutionary Bioinformatics Laboratory, Department of Crop Sciences, University of <lb/>Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL 61820, USA <lb/> *Corresponding author: gca@illinois.edu <lb/>In a recent eLetter and associated preprint, Harish, Abroi, Gough and Kurland <lb/>criticized our structural phylogenomic methods, which support the early cellular <lb/>origin of viruses. Their claims include the argument that the rooting of our trees is <lb/>artifactual and distorted by small genome (proteome) size. Here we uncover their <lb/>aprioristic reasoning, which mingles with misunderstandings and misinterpretations <lb/>of cladistic methodology. To demonstrate, we labeled the phylogenetic positions of <lb/>the smallest proteomes in our phylogenetic trees and confirm that the smallest <lb/>genomes were neither attracted towards the root nor caused any distortions in the <lb/>four-supergroup tree of life. Their results therefore stem from confusing outgroups <lb/>with ancestors and handpicking problematic taxa to distort tree reconstruction. In <lb/>doing so, they ignored the details of our rooting method, taxa sampling rationale, <lb/>the plethora of evidence given in our study supporting the ancient origin of the viral <lb/>supergroup and also recent literature on viral evolution. Indeed, our tree of life <lb/>uncovered many viral monophyletic groups consistent with ICTV classifications and <lb/>showed remarkable evolutionary tracings of virion morphotypes onto a revealing <lb/>tree topology. <lb/> Harish et al. would like to see the origin of Eukarya at the base of the Tree of Life (ToL) <lb/>[1]. So, in their commentary [2,3], they begin by questioning our phylogenomic analysis, <lb/>which is supported by large-scale structural and functional data and well-established <lb/>comparative genomics, phylogenomics, and multidimensional scaling approaches [4]. <lb/>Their writings [2,3] fail to acknowledge recent literature, including our recent <lb/>invalidation of both their rationale [5] and their own phylogenetic methodologies [6], <lb/>which we showed counter modern evolutionary thinking. While our critique remains <lb/>unanswered, here we recap how their argumentation and misguided experimentation is <lb/>used to &quot;mud the waters&quot; (sensu [2]) of cladistics understanding. A quick fact-checking <lb/>exercise is presented in Table 1 and described in the following sections. <lb/>1. Their claim that our rooting approach uses outgroup taxa is incorrect. We do not <lb/>&quot;use a hypothetical pseudo-outgroup, … an artificial all-zero taxon … to root the ToL&quot; <lb/>[2] nor &quot;an ancestor that is assumed to be an empty set of protein domains&quot; as outgroup <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>to &quot;create specific phylogenetic artifacts&quot; [3]. No outgroup taxon (presumably extant or <lb/>artificial) was ever used/defined in our study [4], demonstrating they are confusing <lb/>outgroups with ancestors (Table 1). We are therefore puzzled by the indirectly rooted <lb/>ToLs they build in their attempt to mimic and undermine our methods [3], as well as the <lb/>putative sensitivity to addition of new taxa, especially because these taxa represent <lb/>organisms that engage in extreme forms of cellular endosymbiosis (please read below for <lb/>the rationale for why then viruses were included). Even their tree searches were <lb/>conducted differently, failing to minimize Farris&apos; f-values and being dependent on the <lb/>location of the root. Contrary to their claims, our rooting method is grounded in early and <lb/>well-established cladistic formalizations [7,8] and is direct because it polarizes character <lb/>transformations with information solely present in the taxa being studied (the ingroup), <lb/>distinguishing ancestral from derived character states and rooting the trees both <lb/>empirically and a posteriori. In fact, and crucially, our rooted trees comply with <lb/>Weston&apos;s generality criterion [9,10], which states that as long as ancestral characters are <lb/>preponderantly retained in descendants, ancestral character states will always be more <lb/>general than their derivatives given their nested hierarchical distribution in rooted <lb/>phylogenies. Biologically, domain structures spread by recruitment in evolution when <lb/>genes duplicate and diversify, genomes rearrange, and genetic information is exchanged. <lb/>This is a process of accumulation and retention of iterative homologies, such as serial <lb/>homologues and paralogous genes [10], which is global, universal and largely unaffected <lb/>by proteome size. This same process is widely used to generate rooted phylogenies from <lb/>paralogous gene sequences. The Lundberg method [8], which does not attach outgroup <lb/>taxa to the ingroup as they claim, simply enables rooting by the generality criterion [11]. <lb/>2. Their confusion of a priori and a posteriori character polarization questions their <lb/>understanding of cladistic methodology. Their claim that we use the pseudo-outgroup to <lb/>polarize character state changes a priori is inconsistent with our methodology of first <lb/>reconstructing an undirected network and then polarizing character transformations with <lb/>a direct method that complies with Weston&apos;s rule [4]. They miss the fact that rooting is <lb/>not a neutral procedure. While the length of the most parsimonious trees is unaffected by <lb/>the position of the root, making a priori polarization unnecessary [7], rooting impacts the <lb/>homology statements of the undirected networks [7,8]. &quot;The length of a tree is unaffected <lb/>by the position of the root but is certainly not unaffected by the inclusion of a root&quot; [12]. <lb/>3. Their claim that small genome size affects rooting and induces attraction artifacts is <lb/>conceptually and empirically false. Their recitation that organisms and viruses with <lb/>small genomes (irrespective of their taxonomic affiliation) would be attracted to basal <lb/>branches of our trees is incorrect. During searches of tree space and prior to rooting, we <lb/>optimize character change in unrooted networks. This allows unrestricted gains and <lb/>losses of domain occurrence or abundance throughout their branches. Thus, rooting plays <lb/>no role in defining unrooted tree topology and cannot be distorted by genome size, which <lb/>is a property of taxa (not individual characters changing in trees). This was already <lb/>described in our supplementary text [4] and made explicit in a recent phylogenetic <lb/>reconstruction study [13]. Polarization is only applied empirically a posteriori: (a) <lb/>considering character spread in nested branches while accounting unproblematically for <lb/>homoplasy (Weston&apos;s rule), (b) searching for most parsimonious solutions with Lundberg <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>while treating homologies as taxic hypotheses, and (c) allowing gradual and punctuated <lb/>build-up of evolutionary emergence of protein structures, including gain and loss, that <lb/>complies with the principle of spatiotemporal continuity (PC), Leibnitz&apos;s lex continui. <lb/>These three mutually supportive technical and biological axiomatic criteria were <lb/>confirmed experimentally by Venn group distribution in ToDs and by visualizing clouds <lb/>of proteomes in temporal space (see Figs. 5 and 8 of [4]). Felsenstein&apos;s suggestion of <lb/>inverse polarization [14] of our ordered (Wagner) characters, which can be polarized in <lb/>only two directions, produced suboptimal trees (e.g., Figs. 3 and 4 of [6]). Empirically, <lb/>plotting the node distance (nd) for each terminal node (i.e. taxa) from the root node of a <lb/>ToL -on a scale from 0 (most basal) to 1 (most recent) -against the genome sizes of taxa <lb/>showed substantial scatter (rho = 0.80), poor lineal fits (several peaks and troughs with <lb/>100 iterations of the LOWESS fitting method and a smoothing of q = 0.05), shallow <lb/>monotonic increases (flat lines in Archaea and Bacteria), and no distortions/mixing of <lb/>taxa among the four supergroups, viruses, Archaea, Bacteria and Eukarya. Figure 1A <lb/>shows the plot for viral taxa located at the base of the rooted ToL. Genomes of similar <lb/>sizes were scattered throughout the nd axis suggesting that genome size was not a <lb/>significant determinant of taxa position in our trees. Similarly, genome size scatter for <lb/>individual nd increased towards the base of the trees, including scatter for supergroups <lb/>(rho values of 0.55, 0.63, 0.75 and 0.85 for viruses, Archaea, Bacteria and Eukarya <lb/>respectively), debunking the alleged basal attraction artifact. The order of appearance of <lb/>supergroups matched their proteomic complexity, from simple to complex, which also <lb/>matched scaling patterns of use and reuse of structural domains in proteomes [6]. This <lb/>emerging property of trees supports evolution&apos;s PC. <lb/>Labeling the phylogenetic positions of the smallest proteomes in our trees confirmed that <lb/>the smallest genomes were neither attracted towards the root nor caused distortions in the <lb/>four-supergroup ToL (see also Fig. 7A in [4]). Here, Figure 1B showcases the <lb/>phylogenetic positions of the &quot;smallest&quot; proteomes in each of the four supergroups <lb/>(Archaea, Bacteria, Eukarya, and viruses) in our ToL. For clarification, the smallest <lb/>proteomes included Ignicoccus hospitalis (Archaea, 213 fold superfamilies), <lb/>Lactobacillus delbrueckii (Bacteria, 261), Ashbya gossypii (Eukarya, 326), and the bat <lb/>cyclovirus (virus, 1). We also labeled the 9 viruses (4 RNA and 5 dsDNA) that produced <lb/>phylogenetic distortions in the trees of Harish et al. [3]. Following the Harish et al. [3] <lb/>logic, one should expect for the smallest proteomes to &quot;fight&quot; for the basal position <lb/>within each of the four-supergroup subtrees or appear together closest to the root, <lb/>irrespective of their taxonomic affiliation [2,3]. Contrary to that, the smallest proteomes <lb/>appeared at well-derived positions (see arrow pointers) and did not cause any <lb/>phylogenetic distortions or mixing of taxa from different supergroups! Even the smallest <lb/>virus (the 1.7kb bat cyclovirus encoding a single fold superfamily) did not appear at the <lb/>cluster of basal RNA viruses but was clustered with its closest evolutionary relative, the <lb/>Dragonfly cyclovirus at more derived positions (red arrow in Figure 1B and at nd = 0.11 <lb/>in Figure 1A). Thus, claims that &quot;the rooting in viral lineages is an inevitable <lb/>consequence of pre-specifying &apos;0&apos; or &apos;absence&apos; as the ancestral state&quot;, that &quot;the position <lb/>of the root depends on the smallest genome in the sample&quot; [2], and that we &quot;recognized <lb/>anomalous effects of including small genomes in reconstructing the ToL&quot; [3] are <lb/>therefore conceptually and empirically false. The contradictory results obtained by Harish <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>et al. [2,3] therefore stem from (i) their misunderstanding of our rooting approach and <lb/>cladistics, and (ii) intentionally/unintentionally missing the taxa sampling rationale that <lb/>was well explained in our study [4]. To clarify, we took great care in sampling an equal <lb/>number of cellular organisms from each supergroup (34 each) and at least five viruses <lb/>from each family/order (87 viral families and 266 viruses were represented in our trees <lb/>[4]). Indeed, our ToL (Figure 7 in [4]) revealed many monophyletic groups of viruses that <lb/>were consistent with ICTV classifications and was far more complicated than <lb/>showed/claimed by Harish et al. [3]. In turn, and in their haste to claim phylogenetic <lb/>distortions, Harish et al. [3] likely handpicked problematic taxa (only 9 viruses in <lb/>comparison to our 266) to claim phylogenetic distortions and to misguide the <lb/>interpretation of our phylogenomic methodology (please also see Section 5). This was a <lb/>crucial mistake since we had explicitly stated that taxa must be sampled broadly for the <lb/>success of genome composition based phylogenies (see supplementary material in [4]). <lb/>Even, the addition of the extremely reduced Rickettsia prowazeki and Nanoarchaeum <lb/>equitans genomes (originally excluded because of their lifestyles) to our dataset, did not <lb/>cause any topological distortions to our trees (data not shown), in contradiction to claims <lb/>of Harish et al. [3]. <lb/>4. Confusion of characters and taxa bootstraps their preconceptions. In rushing their <lb/>unsupported claim that the rooting of trees of structural domains (ToDs) is also unreliable <lb/>and affected by small genome size, they wrongly considered ToDs as being <lb/>&quot;uninterpretable in terms of the definition of the (domain) superfamilies which it <lb/>comprises&quot;, because homology &quot;within&quot; superfamilies &quot;can be ascertained based on <lb/>similarity of sequence, structure and function&quot;. But superfamilies are the taxa and <lb/>proteomes the characters, and definitions of taxa (superfamily hidden Markov models) do <lb/>not need to follow either definitions of characters (superfamily growth in proteomes) or <lb/>statements of homology tested in ToDs. What is &apos;uninterpretable&apos; however is the putative <lb/>effect of genome size on ToDs, since each proteome embodies a character, which by <lb/>definition (Kluge&apos;s Auxiliary Principle) is independent of others. So fiction bootstraps <lb/>their preconceptions, including the idea that domains, the evolutionary units of proteins, <lb/>do not evolve. Are 1,200 structural folds fortuitous findings or the makings of intelligent <lb/>cause? Where does significant evolutionary signal of the ToDs, including a match to the <lb/>geological record [15], come from? Even an exploration of the mapping of functions in <lb/>genotype space shows the centrality of structure in defining evolutionary constraints [16]. <lb/>5. Their analysis failed to avoid sampling pitfalls and problematic taxa. They confused <lb/>exclusion of taxa engaged in obligate parasitism and symbiosis in cellular organisms with <lb/>avoidance of genome size attraction artifacts, when in fact our intention was to exclude <lb/>organisms with ill-defined hologenomes of holobiont collectives (the host and its <lb/>associated organismal communities), which are known to complicate definitions of taxa <lb/>[17,18]. No such attempt was extended to the viral supergroup since one hallmark of <lb/>viruses is harboring a life cycle with strict dependence on a host. We explored their <lb/>dataset and found that sampling of taxa was limited and imbalanced (Table 1) and <lb/>included questionable taxa that were likely cherry-picked from extreme proteomic <lb/>outliers (e.g. Fig. 1C in [4]), and sometimes selected outside our initial sampling (e.g. <lb/>Cand. Nausia deltocephalinicola). For example, Cand. Tremblaya princeps included in <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>their trees (Figure 2B in [3]) is part of a three-pronged endosymbiotic organismal system <lb/>(bug in a bug in a bug) [19]. Its genome encodes only 55 universal domain superfamilies. <lb/>It is not considered an independent organism since it depends on its host (Planococcus <lb/>citri) and its endosymbiont (Cand. Moranella endobia) to synthesize essential metabolites <lb/>[20]. To quote López-Madrigal et al. &quot;The genome sequence reveals that &apos;Ca. Tremblaya <lb/>princeps&apos; cannot be considered an independent organism but that the consortium with its <lb/>gammaproteobacterial symbiotic associate represents a new composite living being&quot; <lb/>[20]. Similarly, Cand. N. deltocephalinicola is an obligate endosymbiont of leafhoppers, <lb/>which harbors the smallest known bacterial genome and encodes only 53 universal <lb/>superfamilies [21]. These extreme proteomic outliers do not bias tree reconstructions <lb/>because of their size nor induce &quot;grossly erroneous rootings&quot; [3]. Instead, their <lb/>hologenomes arise from relatively modern genomic exchanges and recruitments likely <lb/>resulting from complex trade-off relationships that complicate the dissection of their <lb/>evolutionary origin and their definition as single taxon in phylogenetic data matrix. <lb/>Phylogenetically, they represent &apos;problematic&apos; taxa that should be excluded from analysis <lb/>pending further understanding of their genetic make up. The intentional inclusion of <lb/>problematic taxa is expected to generate biased reconstructions; see [22] for a dinosaur <lb/>phylogeny example and the detection of problematic taxa with double decay analysis. <lb/>Instead, our decision to exclude organisms that do not engage in free-living relationships <lb/>avoids these kinds of pitfalls [23]. In contrast to the effect of lifestyles, comparing trees <lb/>built from information-related and nonrelated domain families uncovered that tree <lb/>reconstruction is refractory to biases resulting from horizontal gene transfer [23], a much <lb/>more serious putative effect on tree reconstruction. <lb/>They state that our Venn diagrams and summary statistics of domain distributions in <lb/>supergroups are unconvincing in light of other comparative genomic analyses [24,25]. <lb/>However, Abroi and Gough [24] argued that viruses may be a source of new protein fold <lb/>architectures, a conclusion strongly supported by our Venn analysis, and Abroi [25] <lb/>showcases the distribution and sharing of domain superfamilies between viral replicon <lb/>types and cells, which is remarkably consistent with our analysis [4]. There are no <lb/>irreconcilable differences between these studies. Instead, our phylogenomic analysis <lb/>dissects the alternative evolutionary scenarios that can be posed with the comparative <lb/>method [4,25]. For example, we also mapped virus-host information to the Venn <lb/>distribution of protein fold superfamilies and identified 68 fold superfamilies that were <lb/>(remarkably) shared by archaeo-, bacterio-, and eukaryoviruses (Fig. 3 in [4]). These <lb/>superfamilies included many ancient folds involved in cellular metabolism and hinted <lb/>towards an origin of viruses predating the origin of modern cells. Harish et al. [3] <lb/>therefore I ignore the plethora of evidence given in our article (Figs. 1-8 in [4]) <lb/>supporting the ancient origin of viruses and instead rely on customized phylogenetic trees <lb/>to claim invalidity of our results. <lb/>Conclusions. Harish et al. [2,3] believe we root our ToLs a priori with an indirect <lb/>method and an outgroup taxon they confuse with an ancestor, when in fact we root our <lb/>ToLs a posteriori using a direct method compliant both with Weston&apos;s rule and <lb/>experimentation. They claim our rooting method attracts organisms and viruses with <lb/>small genomes to the base of rooted trees when in fact tree topology is established during <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>unrooted tree optimization and prior to character polarization. It is ironic that attempts to <lb/>controvert our direct methods of character polarization come from authors that are <lb/>themselves proponents of the use of polarized characters, but with arbitrary <lb/>transformation costs carefully engineered a priori to attract large eukaryotic genomes to <lb/>the base of their trees [1]. These characters violate the &apos;triangle inequality&apos; [26], a <lb/>fundamental property conferring metricity to phylogenetic distances. Its violation <lb/>invalidates phylogenetic reconstruction [27]. Quoting the cladistics opinion of W. C. <lb/>Wheeler [26] on the validity of characters with arbitrary transformation costs: &quot;Although <lb/>the matrix character optimization algorithm does not require metricity, biologically odd <lb/>results may occur otherwise. As an example, an additional state could be added to an <lb/>existing set, with very low transformation cost to all other elements (σ k,0 &lt; ½ min σ i,j ). <lb/>The median state at all internal 2 vertices (V \ L) would then be this new state for all <lb/>trees, no matter what the leaf conditions were&quot; (page 184). He further illustrates the <lb/>unforeseen consequences of optimization with non-metric distances using the well-<lb/>known NP-hard &apos;traveling salesman problem&apos;, a salesman that wishes to visit a number of <lb/>cities while minimizing travel time. This is a notorious task known to require <lb/>considerable travelling optimization. The use of non-metric distances however makes a <lb/>city have zero distance to all other cities, creating a &apos;wormhole&apos; in space-time that allows <lb/>to reach all cities at zero cost. Such bizarre property has dire consequences for the <lb/>recovery of a correct tree and invalidates the Harish et al. [1] approach. Add to this the <lb/>fact that their loss-favoring step matrices require that they be solely optimized on a rooted <lb/>tree, making rooted tree reconstruction prone to &apos;large genome attraction&apos; artifacts. In <lb/>addition to this self-inconsistency, transformation costs also violate genomic scaling and <lb/>processes responsible for scale-free behavior of proteins, challenging evolution&apos;s PC and <lb/>artificially forcing biological innovations to the base of universal trees [6], effectively <lb/>resulting in an ancestral clumping of irreducible complexity. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. A. Harish, A. Tunlid, C. G. Kurland, Rooted phylogeny of the three superkingdoms. <lb/>Biochimie 95, 1593-1604 (2013). <lb/>2. A. Harish, A. Abroi, J. Gough, C.G. Kurland, eLetter concerning Nasir and Caetano-<lb/>Anollés&apos; conclusions about the origins of viruses. Sci Adv, eLetter <lb/>http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/1/8/e1500527.e-letters# <lb/>3. A. Harish, A. Abroi, J. Gough, C.G. Kurland, Did viruses evolve as a distinct <lb/>supergroup from common ancestors of cells? bioRxiv preprint server (posted Apr. 18, <lb/>2016), doi: http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/049171. <lb/>4. A. Nasir, G. Caetano-Anolles, A phylogenomic data-driven exploration of viral origins <lb/>and evolution. Sci. Adv. 1, e1500527 (2015). <lb/>5. A. Nasir, K.M. Kim, G. Caetano-Anolles, Authors&apos; response to Harish et al.: No &apos;small <lb/>genome <lb/>attraction&apos; <lb/>artifact. <lb/>Sci <lb/>Adv, <lb/>eLetter <lb/>http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/1/8/e1500527.e-letters# <lb/>6. K. M. Kim, A. Nasir, G. Caetano-Anollés, The importance of using realistic <lb/>evolutionary models for retrodicting proteomes. Biochimie 99, 129-137 (2014). <lb/>7. J. S. Farris, Methods for computing Wagner trees. Syst. Zool. 19, 83-92 (1970). <lb/>8. J. Lundberg, Wagner networks and ancestors. Syst. Zool. 18, 1-32 (1972). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>9. P. H. Weston, Indirect and direct methods in systematics, in Ontogeny and <lb/>Systematics, C, J. Humphries, Ed. (Columbia University Press: New York, 1988), pp. <lb/>27-56. <lb/>10. P. H. Weston, Methods for rooting cladistic trees, in Models in Phylogeny <lb/>Reconstruction, Systematics Association Special Volume No. 52, D. J. Siebert, R. W. <lb/>Scotland, D. M. Williams, Eds. (Clarendon Press, Oxford, 1994), pp. 125-155. <lb/>11. H. N. Bryant, Hypothetical ancestors and rooting in cladistic analysis. Cladistics 13, <lb/>337-348 (1997). <lb/>12. A. V. Brower, M. C. de Pinna, Homology and errors. Cladistics 28, 529-538 (2012). <lb/>13. A. Nasir, K. M. Kim, G. Caetano-Anollés, Global patterns of protein domain gain and <lb/>loss in superkingdoms. PLoS Comput. Biol. 10, e1003452 (2014). <lb/>14. J. Felsenstein, The statistical approach to inferring phylogeny and what it tells us <lb/>about parsimony and character compatibility, in Cladistics: Perspectives on the <lb/>Reconstruction of Evolutionary History, T. Duncan, T. F. Stuessy, Eds. (Columbia <lb/>University Press, New York, 1984), pp. 169-191. <lb/>15. M. Wang, Y.-Y., Jiang, K.M. Kim, G. Qu, H.-F. Ji, H.-Y. Zhang, G. Caetano-<lb/>Anollés, A molecular clock of protein folds and its power in tracing the early history <lb/>of aerobic metabolism and planet oxygenation. Mol. Biol. Evol. 28, 567-582 (2011). <lb/>16. E. Ferrada, A. Wagner, Evolutionary innovations and the organization of protein <lb/>functions in genotype space. PLoS ONE 5, e14172 (2010). <lb/>17. E. Rosenberg, I. Zilber-Rosenberg, The hologenome concept: human, animal and <lb/>plant microbiota (Springer, 2013). <lb/>18. P. J. Keeling, Endosymbiosis: bacteria sharing the load. Curr Biology 21, R623-R624 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>19. J. P. McCutcheon, C. D. von Dohlen, An interdependent metabolic patchwork in the <lb/>nested symbiosis of mealybugs. Current Biology. 21, 1366-1372 (2011) <lb/>20. S. López-Madrigal, A. Lattore, M. Porcar, A. Moya, R. Gil, Complete genome <lb/>sequence of &quot;Candidatus Tremblaya princeps&quot; strain PCVAL, an intriguing <lb/>translational machine below the living-cell status. J Bacteriol 193 19: 5587-5588 <lb/>(2011) <lb/>21. G. M. Bennett, N. A. Moran, Small, smaller, smallest: the origins and evolution of <lb/>ancient dual symbioses in a Phloem-feeding insect. Genome Biol. Evol. 5, 1675-1688 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>22. M. Wilkinson, J.L. Thorley, P. Upchurch. A chain is no longer than its weakest link: <lb/>double decay analysis of phylogenetic hypotheses. Syst. Biol. 49, 754-776 (2000). <lb/>23. K. M Kim, G. Caetano-Anollés. The evolutionary history of protein fold families and <lb/>proteomes confirms that the archaeal ancestor is more ancient than the ancestors of <lb/>other superkingdoms. BMC Evol. Biol. 12, 13 (2012). <lb/>24. A. Abroi, J. Gough, Are viruses a source of new protein folds for organisms? -<lb/>Virosphere structure space and evolution. Bioessays 33, 626-635 (2011). <lb/>25. A. Abroi, A protein domain-based view of the virosphere-host relationship. <lb/>Biochimie 119, 231-243 (2015). <lb/>26. W. C. Wheeler, Systematics: a course of lectures (John Wiley &amp; Sons, Hoboken, <lb/>New Jersey, 2012). <lb/>27. W. C. Wheeler, The triangle inequality and character analysis. Mol. Biol. Evol. 10, <lb/>707-712 (1993). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Fact-checking the narrative of Harish et al. [2,3]. A somehow similar table <lb/>fact-checking can be found in our eLetter response [5]. <lb/>Fiction <lb/>Fact <lb/>Discussed in: <lb/>We root trees with the <lb/>&quot;outgroup comparison <lb/>method&quot; [2] <lb/>We do not rely on outgroup taxa and indirect methods. <lb/>Instead, we root trees with Weston&apos;s generality criterion <lb/>(a direct method) implemented using Lundberg [8]. <lb/>Section 1 <lb/>We use an &quot;an artificial all-<lb/>zero taxon… an &apos;all-absent&apos; <lb/>hypothetical ancestor&quot; [2,3] <lb/>We do not combine outgroups and ancestors, an approach <lb/>known to be invalid [11]. <lb/>Section 1 <lb/>&quot;Including the hypothetical <lb/>ancestor during tree estimation <lb/>amounts to a priori character <lb/>polarization&quot; [3] <lb/>We polarize character transformations a posteriori, <lb/>empirically and most parsimoniously, and complying with <lb/>Weston&apos;s generality criterion. <lb/>Section 2 <lb/>&quot;Unrooted trees describe <lb/>relatedness of taxa based on <lb/>graded compositional <lb/>similarities of characters&quot; [3] <lb/>The search of tree space using maximum parsimony as an <lb/>optimality criterion is defined by homology relationships <lb/>not graded compositional similarities. <lb/>&quot;Accordingly, we can expect <lb/>the &apos;all-zero&apos; pseudo-outgroup <lb/>to cluster with … proteomes <lb/>described by the largest <lb/>number of &apos;0s&apos; in the data <lb/>matrix&quot; [2,3] <lb/>During phylogenetic searches, we first optimize character <lb/>change in unrooted networks using the Wagner algorithm <lb/>[7]. The topology of rooted trees cannot be predicted from <lb/>patterns in character state vectors of ingroup or outgroup <lb/>taxa and cannot be affected by genome size. <lb/>Section 3 <lb/>&quot;The rooting in viral lineages <lb/>is an inevitable consequence of <lb/>pre-specifying &apos;0&apos; or &apos;absence&apos; <lb/>as the ancestral state&quot; [2] <lb/>Character polarization plays no role in defining unrooted <lb/>tree topology and cannot be distorted by genome size, a <lb/>property of taxa, not characters. This claim is also <lb/>debunked empirically by labeling the positions of smallest <lb/>proteomes in our trees (please see the Figure). <lb/>Section 3 <lb/>&quot;Including viruses in the <lb/>analyses draws the root <lb/>towards the smaller viral <lb/>proteomes&quot; [3] <lb/>A simple node distance (nd) versus genome size plot <lb/>dispels their putative &apos;small genome attraction artifact&apos; <lb/>(Figure 1A). <lb/>Section 3 <lb/>&quot;Detailed reexamination [of <lb/>our] phylogenomic approach <lb/>suggests that small genomes <lb/>systematically distort <lb/>phylogenetic reconstructions&quot; <lb/>[3] <lb/>They reconstruct trees (their Figs. 1 and 2) using an <lb/>incorrect outgroup-driven mimic of our method to <lb/>fictionalize both our conclusions and methodologies. <lb/>Trees describes phylogenetic relationships between <lb/>limited and imbalanced taxa selected from extreme <lb/>outliers (instead of using objective taxon selection criteria <lb/>already explained in [4]). <lb/>Sections 3 and 5 <lb/>The tree of structural domains <lb/>(ToD) &quot;appears <lb/>uninterpretable in terms of the <lb/>definition of superfamilies <lb/>which it comprises&quot; [2] <lb/>Harish et al. confuse characters and taxa and extend their <lb/>unsubstantiated claims to ToDs. To build ToDs, domain <lb/>homologies are defined with robust hidden Markov <lb/>models and delimit taxa. Their proteomic abundances are <lb/>used as characters. ToDs contain significant phylogenetic <lb/>signal that follows a molecular clock linking the <lb/>molecular and geological records [15]. <lb/>Section 4 <lb/>&quot;Half of the sampled <lb/>proteomes were analyzed (Figs. <lb/>1 and 2) for computational <lb/>simplicity&quot; [3] <lb/>They included only 16 eukaryal, 17 archaeal, 17 bacterial, <lb/>and 5-9 viral proteomes, which only represent 16% of our <lb/>taxa [4]! Sampling was limited and imbalanced and taxa <lb/>selection followed no rationale. <lb/>Section 5 <lb/>&quot;Rooting experiments (Figs. 1 <lb/>When running their experimental mimic, they cherry-<lb/>Section 5 <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>and 2) clearly show that the <lb/>position of the root depends on <lb/>the smallest genome in the <lb/>sample when an all-zero <lb/>outgroup is used&quot; [3] <lb/>picked extreme outliers, such as Candidatus Tremblaya <lb/>princeps, and Cand. Nasuia deltocephalinicola, which <lb/>were excluded from our phylogenies because taxon <lb/>definition was compromised by extreme reduction and ill-<lb/>defined hologenome make-up. They also included only 9 <lb/>viruses to distort tree reconstruction while we included <lb/>266 viruses from tens of families following an already <lb/>explained rationale for properly surveying taxonomic <lb/>groups for the success of genome-composition <lb/>phylogenies [4]. <lb/>The exclusion of highly <lb/>reduced &apos;parasitic&apos; proteomes <lb/>appears to be inconsistent with <lb/>the inclusion of viruses [3] <lb/>Our exclusion and inclusion of taxa followed clear <lb/>rationale. Exclusion of organisms engaging in obligate <lb/>parasitism and symbiosis and representing genomic <lb/>outliers ensured integrity of definition of taxa. Inclusion <lb/>of representatives of all viral groups portrayed the entire <lb/>viral supergroup, which is unified by its parasitic lifestyle. <lb/>Section 5 <lb/>&quot;Inferences based on statistical <lb/>distributions of superfamilies <lb/>alone are unconvincing, <lb/>especially in light of other <lb/>recent analyses&quot; [2] <lb/>The other recent analyses that are mentioned [24,25] <lb/>failed to couple the comparative genomic studies to <lb/>phylogenomic reconstructions, which in our case [4] <lb/>helped weed out evolutionary scenarios (e.g. Fig. 5 of <lb/>[25]) that were non-significant or incompatible with <lb/>reconstructed history. <lb/>Section 6 <lb/>&quot;We emphasize that for an <lb/>unrooted ToL as well as for <lb/>rooting by other methods <lb/>(referring to [1]), small <lb/>proteome size is not an <lb/>irreconcilable feature of <lb/>genome-trees&quot; [3] <lb/>Harish et al. are proponents of polarized characters with <lb/>arbitrary transformation costs [1], which violate the <lb/>&apos;triangle inequality&apos; of phylogenetic distances and are <lb/>engineered to attract large genomes to the base of their <lb/>trees [6]. Their use of unrealistic evolutionary <lb/>assumptions does have irreconcilable consequences for <lb/>the correct reconstruction of trees [6]. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1. Trees of proteomes are robust and insensitive to the effects of genome size. <lb/>A. Scatter plot describing the relationship between genome size and node distance (nd) <lb/>for viral taxa used in our study [4]. For clarification, our data set included 266 viral <lb/>proteomes including up to 5 viral representatives from each known viral family/order and <lb/>belonging to each of the seven replicon types seen in viruses, as in [4]. The blue line <lb/>describes the nature of the relationship, as determined by the Locally Weighted <lb/>Regression Scatter Plot Smoothing (LOWESS) method, which obtains a smoothed curve <lb/>by fitting successive regression functions. The red arrow indicates the smallest virus of <lb/>the genomic set, the bat cyclovirus (1.7kb genome and encoding a single fold superfamily <lb/>domain). High scatter values of the plot (rho = 0.55) indicate no &apos;small genome <lb/>attraction&apos; artifact that would pull small genomes toward the base of the tree, i.e. towards <lb/>nd = 0. (B) The single most parsimonious tree (length = 45,935, retention index = 0.83, <lb/>g 1 = -0.31) describing the evolution of 102 cellular organisms and 266 viruses (described <lb/>in [4]). The smallest proteomes in each cellular supergroup are represented by black <lb/>arrows (see text for description). The smallest viral proteome (bat cyclovirus) is labeled <lb/>with a red arrow. Viruses sampled by Harish et al. [3] are indicated with dashed arrows. <lb/>The names of taxa are not shown because they would not be visible. Instead, the positions <lb/>of terminals were colored according to supergroup, green (Eukarya), blue (Bacteria), <lb/>black (Archaea) and red (viruses). </body>


	</text>
</tei>
