<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_05_-_PMID_17035732"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>© <lb/> 2 0 0 6 L A N D E S B I O S C I E N C E . D O N O T D I S T R I B U T E . <lb/> www.landesbioscience.com <lb/> Autophagy <lb/></front>
			
			<page>45 <lb/> </page>
			 
			<front>[Autophagy 3:1, 45-47, January/February 2007]; ©2007 Landes Bioscience <lb/> 
			 
			Gregory Lavieu 1, * <lb/>Francesca Scarlatti 2 <lb/> Giusy Sala 2 <lb/> Thierry Levade 3 <lb/> Riccardo Ghidoni 2 <lb/> Joëlle Botti 1,4 <lb/> Patrice Codogno 1,4 <lb/>

			1  INSERM U504; Institut Andre Lwoff; Villejuif, France <lb/> 2 Laboratory of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology; San Paolo Medical School; <lb/>Milan, Italy <lb/> 3 INSERM U466; Institut Louis Bugnard; Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de <lb/>Rangueil; Toulouse, France <lb/> 4 INSERM U576; Faculte de Pharmacie; Universite Paris Sud; Chatenay-Malabry, <lb/>France <lb/>*Correspondence to: Gregory Lavieu; Columbia University; Department of <lb/>Physiology and Cellular Biophysics; Russ Berrie Pav Rm519; 1150 St. Nicholas Ave.; <lb/>New York, New York 10032 USA; Tel.: 212.851.5560; Fax: 212.851.5562; Email: <lb/>gl2204@columbia.edu <lb/>Received 09/18/06; Accepted 09/18/06 <lb/>Previously published online a an Autophagy E-publication: <lb/>http://www.landesbioscience.com/journals/autophagy/abstract.php?id=3416 <lb/>

			KEY WORDS <lb/> cell death, sphingosine 1-phosphate, sphingosine <lb/>kinase, ceramide, cancer, sphingolipids <lb/> Addendum to: <lb/> Regulation of Autophagy by Sphingosine Kinase 1 and Its <lb/>Role in Cell Survival during Nutrient Starvation <lb/> G. Lavieu, F. Scarlatti, G. Sala, S. Carpentier, T. Levade, <lb/>R. Ghidoni, J. Botti and P. Codogno <lb/>J Biol Chem 2006; 281:8518-27 <lb/> Addenda <lb/> Is Autophagy the Key Mechanism by Which the Sphingolipid Rheostat <lb/>Controls the Cell Fate Decision? <lb/> ABSTRACT <lb/> Sphingolipids are major constituents of biological membrane and some of them <lb/>behave as second messengers involved in the cell fate decision. Ceramide and sphingosine <lb/>1-phosphate (S1P) constitute a rheostat system in which ceramide promotes cell death and <lb/>S1P increases cell survival. We have shown that both sphingolipids are able to trigger <lb/>autophagy with opposing outcomes on cell survival. Here we discuss and speculate on <lb/>the diverging functions of the autophagic pathways induced by ceramide and S1P, <lb/>respectively. <lb/></front> 
			
			<body>CERAMIDE AND S1P BOTH TRIGGER AUTOPHAGY <lb/> The metabolism of sphingolipids is a dynamic process generating second messengers <lb/>such as ceramide and S1P. 1 The formation of ceramide is followed by a deacylation to form <lb/>sphingosine, which is subsequently phosphorylated by sphingosine kinases (SK), leading <lb/>to S1P formation. It is now generally accepted that ceramide and S1P have contrasting <lb/>roles on the response to cell stress. 2 Ceramide is associated with cell growth arrest and cell <lb/>death induction, whereas S1P stimulates proliferation and maintains survival in numerous <lb/>cell types. <lb/>Our group has investigated the correlation between sphingolipid metabolism, the <lb/>autophagic capacities and the cell signaling pathways; we showed that ceramide and S1P <lb/>are able to induce autophagy in a breast cancer cell line. 3,4 <lb/> First, we showed that ceramide could mediate tamoxifen-induced autophagy, which <lb/>represents a model of autophagic cell death. 5 It was shown that tamoxifen induced an <lb/>increase of endogenous ceramide levels responsible for a robust accumulation of Beclin1 <lb/>and an inhibition of Akt/PKB phosphorylation, which tend to increase the autophagic <lb/>response. In addition, we also showed that treatment by short permeant ceramide <lb/>(C2-ceramide) mimicked these effects. Accordingly, pharmacological inhibition of <lb/>endogenous long chain ceramide biosynthesis by fumonisin B1 (FB1), prevents autophagic <lb/>induction by tamoxifen. Interestingly, Kondo and colleagues have shown, that treatment <lb/>of glioma cells with C2-ceramide increased autophagy and cell death by activating Bnip3, <lb/>a proapoptotic mitochondrial protein. 6 These modulatory effects on protein expression <lb/>appear to constitute three alternative steps for ceramide to regulate autophagy. <lb/>The fact that ceramide and S1P constitute a rheostat system involved in the control of <lb/>cell death, prompted us to investigate the role of S1P on autophagy. Surprisingly, we <lb/>observed that the increase of S1P levels after sphingosine kinase 1 overexpression is able to <lb/>induce autophagy. 3 This S1P-induced autophagy correlates with the inhibition of the <lb/>mTOR activity (without alteration of Akt/PKB phosphorylation) and a moderate increase <lb/>in the amount of Beclin 1. In addition, SK1 activity increased during nutrient starvation, <lb/>and inhibition of SK1 by siRNA prevented autophagy and exacerbated cell death with <lb/>apoptotic hallmarks induced by starvation. These results suggest that autophagy is a novel <lb/>function of S1P in cell survival. <lb/> TWO DIFFERENT AUTOPHAGIC PROCESSES CONTROLLED BY SPHINGOLIPIDS? <lb/> The above observations reinforced the ambiguous involvement of autophagy in the cell <lb/>lifetime. However, some key differences were noted between ceramide and S1P-induced <lb/>autophagy that could account for the decision of the cell to survive or die. Distinctions <lb/>appear in the step of signaling pathway alteration (ceramide acts upstream of S1P), in the <lb/>amplitude of the autophagic response (ceramide could trigger a stronger response) and in <lb/> the nature of the stress (only SK <lb/>activity increased after starvation) <lb/>(Fig. 1). <lb/>Ceramide acts upstream of <lb/>S1P by inhibiting Akt/PKB <lb/>phosphorylation, which is associ-<lb/>ated with autophagy suppression <lb/>and reduction of cell viability. 7,8 <lb/> S1P acts only at the level of <lb/>mTOR, independently of the <lb/>PI3K arm, in a direct or indirect <lb/>manner, as suggested by the <lb/>inhibition of phosphorylation of <lb/>mTOR substrates (p70S6K, <lb/>4E-BP1). Does this observation <lb/>mean that in comparison with S1P, <lb/>ceramide has a broad-spectrum <lb/>of targets potentially linked to <lb/>cell death induction. <lb/>Although Beclin 1 is a common <lb/>target for both sphingolipids, a <lb/>major difference appears. Only <lb/>ceramide induces a strong <lb/>accumulation of Beclin 1 (2.5 fold <lb/>higher than after S1P enhance-<lb/>ment, according to Fig. 6 of <lb/>Lavieu et al. 3 ). Because the inter-<lb/>action between Bcl-2 and Beclin 1 <lb/>is required to maintain autophagy <lb/>in a physiological range, 9 it is tempting to speculate that the strong <lb/>increase of Beclin 1 induced by ceramide changes the ratio of Beclin <lb/>1/Bcl-2 in a range incompatible with survival. Moreover, it was <lb/>shown by Bektas et al. 10 that the increase of SK activity is tightly <lb/>associated with the enhancement of Bcl-2 expression. This observa-<lb/>tion, in addition to the moderate accumulation of Beclin 1 after <lb/>SK1 overexpression seems to be compatible with the Bcl-2/Beclin 1 <lb/>rheostat hypothesis. Does it mean that the autophagic response trig-<lb/>gered by S1P is gentler than ceramide-induced autophagy and com-<lb/>patible with cell survival? Interestingly, a fine analysis of the data from <lb/>Lavieu et al. 3 (see Fig. 2), tends to support this suggestion, even <lb/>though the method used to induce autophagy by the two lipids is <lb/>different (treatment by exogenous short-chain ceramide for <lb/>ceramide-induced autophagy vs. enforced expression of SK1 for the <lb/>S1P-induced autophagy). The GFP-LC3 dot formation is lower in <lb/>the case of S1P-induced autophagy (approximately 1.6 fold lower <lb/>than after C2-ceramide treatment). The ceramide response seems to <lb/>be also faster than the S1P response (4 hours vs. at least one day). <lb/>However, this point would deserve further study by analyzing the <lb/>effect of ceramide and S1P on the interaction between Bcl-2 and <lb/>Beclin 1. <lb/>One of the major differences between the two responses is the <lb/>nature of the stress situation, since only S1P-induced autophagy <lb/>occurs after nutrient starvation. We have shown that starvation <lb/>induced both autophagy and an increase of SK activity. This last <lb/>point was equally observed in yeast suggesting a general role for SK <lb/>during the starvation response. 11 We have shown that the <lb/>knock-down of SK1 expression by siRNA inhibits starvation-<lb/>induced autophagy and increased cell death. For this reason we <lb/>proposed that S1P is a mediator of starvation-induced autophagy <lb/>which is now well established as a survival mechanism. 12 <lb/> Surprisingly, the amount of endogenous ceramide during starvation <lb/>remained unchanged (from 15 min to 48 h) and the autophagic <lb/>response after inhibition of ceramide biosynthesis by FB1 treatment <lb/>was unaffected. These results suggest that ceramide is excluded from <lb/>the regulation of starvation-induced autophagy. Does it mean that <lb/>ceramide-induced autophagy and S1P-induced autophagy are <lb/>mutually exclusive responses? Study of enzymes that regulate the <lb/>balance between ceramide and S1P could be one of the ways to <lb/>resolve these questions. <lb/>While the above discussion deals with sphingolipids as second <lb/>messengers and their role in signal transduction, we should not forget <lb/>that these molecules are constituents of biological membranes and <lb/>that, because of their biophysical properties, modulate membrane <lb/>functions. For example it is now established that ceramide is respon-<lb/>sible for a negative curvature of the membrane. 13 Moreover, it was <lb/>shown that alteration of ceramide biosynthesis results in changes of <lb/>the vacuole morphology in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae.  14 <lb/> Additionally, studies have described a change in SK1 localization, <lb/>which is usually cytosolic. For example, SK1 is recruited to the <lb/>nascent phagosome in human macrophages during the phagocytosis <lb/>of mycobacterium tuberculosis.  15 What is the significance of this <lb/>enzyme delocalization? Where is localized SK1 during autophagy? It <lb/>is an attractive possibility to contemplate that, in addition to its sig-<lb/>naling activity, ceramide and other lipids could play a structural role <lb/>in the autophagosome biogenesis. Progress in microscopy and the <lb/>development of fluorescent probes for sphingolipid trafficking <lb/>analysis need to be considered in order to identify the origin of the <lb/>autophagosome, an old and still unanswered question. 16 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Sphingolipids Trigger Autophagy <lb/> </note>
			
			<page>46 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">Autophagy <lb/>2007; Vol. 3 Issue 1 <lb/> </note>
			
			Figure 1. Hypothetical model for ceramide and S1P-induced autophagy and their consequences on cell fate. An <lb/>increase of endogenous ceramide promotes a robust accumulation of Beclin 1 and an autophagic response <lb/>associated with cell death. An increase of S1P level (after starvation) induces a mild accumulation of Beclin 1 and <lb/>promotes cell survival by inhibiting the induction of apoptosis. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Sphingolipids Trigger Autophagy <lb/></note>
		
		<back>
			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Spiegel S, Milstien S. Sphingosine-1-phosphate: An enigmatic signalling lipid. Nat Rev <lb/>Mol Cell Biol 2003; 4:397-407. <lb/>2. Ogretmen B, Hannun YA. Biologically active sphingolipids in cancer pathogenesis and <lb/>treatment. Nat Rev Cancer 2004; 4:604-16. <lb/>3. Lavieu G, Scarlatti F, Sala G, Carpentier S, Levade T, Ghidoni R, Botti J, Codogno P. <lb/>Regulation of autophagy by sphingosine kinase 1 and its role in cell survival during nutri-<lb/>ent starvation. J Biol Chem 2006; 281:8518-27. <lb/>4. Scarlatti F, Bauvy C, Ventruti A, Sala G, Cluzeaud F, Vandewalle A, Ghidoni R, Codogno <lb/>P. Ceramide-mediated macroautophagy involves inhibition of protein kinase B and upreg-<lb/>ulation of beclin 1. J Biol Chem 2004; 279:18384-91. <lb/>5. Bursch W, Hochegger K, Torok L, Marian B, Ellinger A, Hermann RS. Autophagic and <lb/>apoptotic types of programmed cell death exhibit different fates of cytoskeletal filaments. <lb/>J Cell Sci 2000; 113:1189-98. <lb/>6. Daido S, Kanzawa T, Yamamoto A, Takeuchi H, Kondo Y, Kondo S. Pivotal role of the cell <lb/>death factor BNIP3 in ceramide-induced autophagic cell death in malignant glioma cells. <lb/>Cancer Res 2004; 64:4286-93. <lb/>7. Arico S, Petiot A, Bauvy C, Dubbelhuis PF, Meijer AJ, Codogno P, Ogier-Denis E. The <lb/>tumor suppressor PTEN positively regulates macroautophagy by inhibiting the phos-<lb/>phatidylinositol 3-kinase/protein kinase B pathway. J Biol Chem 2001; 276:35243-6. <lb/>8. Degenhardt K, Mathew R, Beaudoin B, Bray K, Anderson D, Chen G, Mukherjee C, Shi <lb/>Y, Gelinas C, Fan Y, Nelson DA, Jin S, White E. Autophagy promotes tumor cell survival <lb/>and restricts necrosis, inflammation, and tumorigenesis. Cancer Cell 2006; 10:51-64. <lb/>9. Pattingre S, Tassa A, Qu X, Garuti R, Liang XH, Mizushima N, Packer M, Schneider MD, <lb/>Levine B. Bcl-2 antiapoptotic proteins inhibit Beclin 1-dependent autophagy. Cell 2005; <lb/>122:927-39. <lb/>10. Bektas M, Jolly PS, Muller C, Eberle J, Spiegel S, Geilen CC. Sphingosine kinase activity <lb/>counteracts ceramide-mediated cell death in human melanoma cells: Role of Bcl-2 expres-<lb/>sion. Oncogene 2005; 24:178-87. <lb/>11. Lanterman MM, Saba JD. Characterization of sphingosine kinase (SK) activity in <lb/> Saccharomyces cerevisiae and isolation of SK-deficient mutants. Biochem J 1998; 332:525-31. <lb/>12. Boya P, Gonzalez-Polo RA, Casares N, Perfettini JL, Dessen P, Larochette N, Metivier D, <lb/>Meley D, Souquere S, Yoshimori T, Pierron G, Codogno P, Kroemer G. Inhibition of <lb/>macroautophagy triggers apoptosis. Mol Cell Biol 2005; 25:1025-40. <lb/>13. Montes LR, Ruiz-Arguello MB, Goni FM, Alonso A. Membrane restructuring via <lb/>ceramide results in enhanced solute efflux. J Biol Chem 2002; 277:11788-94. <lb/>14. Faergeman NJ, Feddersen S, Christiansen JK, Larsen MK, Schneiter R, Ungermann C, <lb/>Mutenda K, Roepstorff P, Knudsen J. Acyl-CoA-binding protein, Acb1p, is required for <lb/>normal vacuole function and ceramide synthesis in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Biochem J <lb/>2004; 380:907-18. <lb/>15. Thompson CR, Iyer SS, Melrose N, VanOosten R, Johnson K, Pitson SM, Obeid LM, <lb/>Kusner DJ. Sphingosine kinase 1 (SK1) is recruited to nascent phagosomes in human <lb/>macrophages: Inhibition of SK1 translocation by Mycobacterium tuberculosis. J Immunol <lb/>2005; 174:3551-61. <lb/>16. Reggiori F, Klionsky DJ. Autophagosomes: Biogenesis from scratch? Curr Opin Cell Biol <lb/>2005; 17:415-22. <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.landesbioscience.com <lb/>Autophagy <lb/></note>

			<page>47 </page>
		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
