<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Title: Metabolite exchange within the microbiome produces compounds that influence <lb/>Drosophila behavior <lb/>Authors: Caleb N. Fischer 1 , Eric Trautman 2 , Jason M. Crawford 2 , Eric V. Stabb 3 , <lb/>Nichole A. Broderick 1,4* , and Jo Handelsman 1 <lb/>Affiliations: <lb/>1 Department of Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, Yale University, New <lb/>Haven, CT, USA <lb/>2 Department of Chemistry, Yale University, New Haven, CT, USA <lb/>3 Department of Microbiology, University of Georgia, Athens, GA, USA <lb/>4 Department of Molecular and Cell Biology, University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT, USA <lb/>*To whom correspondence should be addressed: E-mail: nichole.broderick@uconn.edu <lb/>Abstract: <lb/>Animals host multi-species microbial communities (microbiomes) whose <lb/>properties may result from inter-species interactions; however current understanding of <lb/>host-microbiome interactions is derived mostly from studies in which is it is difficult to <lb/>elucidate microbe-microbe interactions. In exploring how Drosophila melanogaster <lb/>acquires its microbiome, we found that a microbial community influences Drosophila <lb/>olfactory and egg-laying behaviors differently than individual members. Drosophila <lb/>prefers a Saccharomyces-Acetobacter co-culture to the same microorganisms grown <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>individually and then mixed, a response mainly due to the conserved olfactory receptor, <lb/>Or42b. Acetobacter metabolism of Saccharomyces-derived ethanol was necessary, and <lb/>acetate and its metabolic derivatives were sufficient, for co-culture preference. <lb/>Preference correlated with three emergent co-culture properties: ethanol catabolism, a <lb/>distinct volatile emission profile, and yeast population decline. We describe a molecular <lb/>mechanism by which a microbial community affects animal behavior. Our results <lb/>support a model whereby emergent metabolites signal Drosophila to acquire its <lb/>preferred multispecies microbiome. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction: <lb/>Multispecies microbial communities (microbiomes) influence animal biology in <lb/>diverse ways (1): microbiomes modulate disease (2), metabolize nutrients (3), <lb/>synthesize vitamins (4), and modify behavior (5). A central goal in host-microbiome <lb/>studies is to understand the molecular mechanisms underpinning these diverse <lb/>microbiome functions. <lb/>Some aspects of microbial community function are the product of interspecies <lb/>interactions (6-9). For example, microorganisms modulate the metabolomes of <lb/>neighboring species (10) and microbial metabolites (e.g., antibiotics) alter bacterial <lb/>transcriptional responses (11). Despite current understanding of microbial inter-species <lb/>interactions in vitro, some of which has been elucidated in exquisite detail, the <lb/>consequences of microbial interspecies interactions within host-associated microbiomes <lb/>are just beginning to be explored experimentally. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Insight into host-associated microbiome function has stemmed mostly from <lb/>whole-microbiome (e.g., re-association of germ-free hosts with whole microbiomes (12)) <lb/>and modeling microbiome function based on gene annotation (13) or single-<lb/>microorganism (e.g., re-association of germ-free hosts with a single microorganism <lb/>(14)) studies. However, these approaches tend to reveal only limited insight into <lb/>interspecies microbial interactions, which can provide hosts with essential services. For <lb/>example, termite symbionts carry genes necessary for metabolism of different parts of <lb/>complex carbohydrates (15), yet their function has not been demonstrated in vivo; co-<lb/>occurring human gut symbionts share polysaccharide breakdown products <lb/>cooperatively (16, 17), but the consequences of such interactions for the host are <lb/>unknown; inter-species bacterial interactions protect Hydra from fungal infection (18), <lb/>but the mechanism of host protection is unclear. The need to understand the effects of <lb/>inter-species microbiome interactions motivated our current work. <lb/>Attractive model systems in which to study the outcomes of inter-species <lb/>microbial interactions for host biology would include a tractable host that harbors a <lb/>simple multispecies microbiome. Here, we report the use of Drosophila melanogaster to <lb/>study interactions in a simple microbiome and their consequences for host behavior. <lb/>The Drosophila microbiome consists largely of yeasts, acetic acid bacteria, and <lb/>lactic acid bacteria (19-22). Drosophila ingests microbiome members from the <lb/>environment (e.g., fermenting fruit, (22-26)), a behavior posited as a mechanism for <lb/>Drosophila to select, acquire, and maintain its microbiome (21, 25). Drosophila behavior <lb/>toward environmental microorganisms has focused on yeasts (27-31). While yeasts <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>attract Drosophila via ester production (28, 29), lactic and acetic acid bacteria produce <lb/>metabolites (e.g., acids) that may repel Drosophila, based on olfactory avoidance of <lb/>high acid concentrations (32). One motivation of our study was to analyze Drosophila <lb/>behavior toward the yeast and bacteria that dominate the Drosophila microbiome. <lb/>Yeast and bacteria are largely studied within separate Drosophila sub-disciplines, <lb/>despite their shared habitat (21). Yeasts serve as food, providing Drosophila vitamins, <lb/>sterols, and amino acids (21). Lactic and acetic acid bacteria are gut microbiome <lb/>members (33) promoting larval development (34, 35), increasing resistance to <lb/>pathogens (25), inducing intestinal stem cell proliferation (36), and reducing adult sugar <lb/>and lipid levels (37, 38). Since microorganisms that are traditionally considered &apos;food&apos; <lb/>co-exist with those considered &quot;microbiome&apos; in fruit fermentations and the two groups <lb/>provide Drosophila with different services, we hypothesized that Drosophila might detect <lb/>a beneficial community via metabolites that are produced cooperatively by the desirable <lb/>symbionts. Alternatively, Drosophila might detect a different metabolite as the signal for <lb/>each symbiont. <lb/>Fruit undergoes a well-characterized ripening process in which cell-wall <lb/>degrading enzymes and amylases convert the firm, starchy tissue into soft, sugar-rich <lb/>fruit (39-41). The high sugar content supports microbial colonization and fermentation <lb/>by Drosophila-associated microorganisms, including yeasts, lactic acid bacteria, and <lb/>acetic acid bacteria (23, 42). Drosophila avoids &apos;green&apos; fruit and is attracted to &apos;overripe&apos; <lb/>fruit (43), yet it is unclear whether Drosophila behavior is influenced by the fruit <lb/>microbiome and its metabolic properties. To this end, we developed a model fruit <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>fermentation system that afforded measurement of microbial populations, microbial <lb/>metabolites, and Drosophila behavior. <lb/>Here we demonstrate the importance of emergent microbiome metabolism-<lb/>quantitatively different or unique metabolites produced by the microbiome, but not by <lb/>any of its members in isolation-on behavior, suggesting that Drosophila modulates its <lb/>chemical intake by selecting a beneficial microbiome. <lb/>Results: <lb/>To determine whether Drosophila responds to emergent microbial community <lb/>metabolites, we used the T-maze olfactory assay to analyze Drosophila behavioral <lb/>responses to several Drosophila microbiome members grown individually or in <lb/>communities (Figure 1A, Table S1, Figure 1-figure supplement 1). When the strains <lb/>were grown individually, Drosophila was strongly attracted to yeasts, moderately <lb/>attracted to acetic acid bacteria, and neutral or slightly repelled by lactic acid bacteria <lb/>(Figure 1B, C). Because strains within a microbial group attracted Drosophila similarly, a <lb/>representative yeast, acetic acid bacterium, and lactic acid bacterium were used to test <lb/>the effect of interactions between microbiome members on Drosophila behavior. <lb/>Drosophila preferred microbial communities grown together to microorganisms grown <lb/>individually and then mixed prior to analysis (defined throughout as a separate-culture <lb/>mixture, Figure 1D). Focusing on a model Saccharomyces cerevisiae and Acetobacter <lb/>malorum community, we found that when tested against apple juice medium (AJM), <lb/>Drosophila preferred the community to the separate-culture mixture or individual <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>members (Figure 1E). In sum, Drosophila detects, and prefers, microorganisms growing <lb/>together to a mixture of the same strains combined after they had completed growth. <lb/>We next measured the attractiveness and other properties of the co-culture over <lb/>time. When grown alone, the microorganisms had similar growth profiles (Figure 2A). <lb/>However, when grown with A. malorum, S. cerevisiae populations first increased, then <lb/>decreased between 60 and 72 h, and were undetectable by 96 h (Figure 2A). The <lb/>decrease in S. cerevisiae viable counts mirrored a decrease in pH (Figure 2-figure <lb/>supplement 1A). Drosophila did not prefer the co-culture relative to the separate-culture <lb/>mixture at 34 h, slightly preferred the co-culture at 48 and 54 h, and strongly preferred <lb/>the co-culture at 60 through 96 h (Figure 2B). Drosophila preference for the co-culture <lb/>correlated with lower pH and S. cerevisiae populations, despite Drosophila olfactory <lb/>avoidance of acid (32) and reliance on yeast for nutrition (44) (Figure 2C, D). Drosophila <lb/>preference did not correlate with viable A. malorum populations (Figure 2-figure <lb/>supplement 1B). Drosophila preference for the co-culture increased relative to sterile <lb/>media during 34-96 h of growth, which is consistent with the increase in Drosophila <lb/>attraction being due to a property of the co-culture rather than to a decrease in <lb/>attraction to the separate-culture mixture (Figure 2-figure supplement 1C). In sum, <lb/>several properties of the microbial community (e.g. S. cerevisiae density, pH) parallel <lb/>Drosophila detection of, and preference for, the co-culture. <lb/>Mutants in broadly and narrowly tuned ionotropic and olfactory receptors (Irs and <lb/>Ors, respectively, (45, 46)) were used to evaluate the role of Drosophila olfactory <lb/>reception in discriminating the co-culture from the separate-culture mixture during and <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>immediately following peak attraction (Figure 3-figure supplement 1). During the most <lb/>attractive phase of the co-culture (e.g. 67-115 h), Or83b and Or42b showed significant <lb/>attraction to the co-culture, whereas no role was detected for Irs or Or35a (Figure 3). As <lb/>the co-culture proceeded (e.g. 139-163 h), attraction decreased and the role of Or42b <lb/>and Or83b waned (Figure 3). Or83b is a required co-receptor for all other Or gene <lb/>products (47) and Or42b, one of the most conserved olfactory receptors, detects esters <lb/>and 1,1-diethoxyethane (48-50).These results suggest that Or42b enables Drosophila to <lb/>distinguish the co-culture from the separate-culture mixture. Our results suggest that a <lb/>non-Or83b factor explains ~40% of Drosophila co-culture preference (Figure 3). <lb/>Previous work found that Or83b is fully responsible for Drosophila attraction to apple <lb/>cider vinegar (51), suggesting that the behavioral circuit activated by inter-species <lb/>interactions of the co-culture is distinct from the circuit activated by apple cider vinegar. <lb/>We speculated that the emergent property of co-culture attractiveness might <lb/>arise from a distinct metabolic profile of the co-culture. Using gas chromatography-mass <lb/>spectrometry (GC-MS), we identified volatiles unique to or differentially produced in the <lb/>co-culture compared to the separate-culture mixture. Five co-culture volatiles (ethanol, <lb/>isobutanol, isoamyl alcohol, acetic acid, isoamyl acetate) were confirmed with standards <lb/>(Table 1-figure supplements 1-2) and quantified with standard curves (Table 1-figure <lb/>supplement 3). The alcohol concentrations were lower, and acetic acid and isoamyl <lb/>acetate were unique in the co-culture relative to the other experimental groups (Table <lb/>1). The molecular profile was reminiscent of ethanol catabolism as the unique co-culture <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>metabolic process. We therefore hypothesized that ethanol catabolism was the <lb/>emergent metabolic process. <lb/>We next measured ethanol and acetic acid levels over time (24-156 h) and <lb/>compared the chemical dynamics to Drosophila preference. Consistent with a <lb/>relationship between ethanol catabolism, acetic acid anabolism, and Drosophila <lb/>attraction, ethanol levels declined and acetic acid accumulated in the co-culture at a <lb/>similar time of Drosophila co-culture preference (Figure 4A). Furthermore, as ethanol <lb/>catabolism and acetic acid anabolism proceeded (36-96 h), Drosophila attraction toward <lb/>the co-culture increased until 96 h, at which point it decreased, consistent with lower <lb/>turnover of ethanol at the end of ethanol catabolism (Figure 4A, black line). <lb/>We hypothesized that Drosophila preferred the community during peak ethanol <lb/>turnover (e.g. co-cultures at ~72 h of growth) compared with the community pre-ethanol <lb/>catabolism (e.g. co-culture at ~36 h of growth) or during late-stage ethanol catabolism, <lb/>in which ethanol turnover is low (e.g. co-culture at ~144 h of growth; Figure 4A). <lb/>Consistent with our hypothesis, Drosophila preferred the co-culture in the middle stage <lb/>of ethanol catabolism to earlier or later stages of ethanol catabolism (Figure 4B). <lb/>We hypothesized that Drosophila preference for communities during peak <lb/>ethanol turnover reflected fitness benefits derived from ingesting metabolites associated <lb/>with different staged communities. To test this hypothesis, we measured Drosophila <lb/>survival when given ethanol and acetic acid concentrations characteristic of microbial <lb/>cultures at different stages of ethanol catabolism. Drosophila survival was highest when <lb/>given metabolites associated with middle-staged ethanol catabolism compared with pre-<lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>or end-stage ethanol catabolism (Figure 4C). In sum, our results are consistent with <lb/>Drosophila preference providing benefits associated with consumption of microbial <lb/>community-generated metabolites. <lb/>To test directly whether ethanol catabolism underpinned Drosophila co-culture <lb/>preference, we evaluated Drosophila preference for the co-culture harboring a mutant in <lb/>adhA, which encodes pyrroloquinoline quinone-dependent alcohol dehydrogenase <lb/>(PQQ-ADH-I), the enzyme that converts yeast-derived ethanol into acetaldehyde on <lb/>path to acetic acid (34). Co-cultures using either A. malorum or A. pomorum wild-type <lb/>(WT) along with S. cerevisiae were equally attractive to Drosophila (Figure 5-figure <lb/>supplement 1). Drosophila preferred the co-culture containing A. pomorum WT versus a <lb/>separate-culture mixture; however, Drosophila did not prefer the co-culture containing <lb/>A. pomorum adhA versus a separate-culture mixture (Figure 5A), suggesting that <lb/>ethanol catabolism is necessary for Drosophila to discriminate between the two <lb/>conditions. Drosophila preferred the co-culture containing A. pomorum WT to the co-<lb/>culture containing A. pomorum adhA (Fig. 5A). Moreover, Drosophila preferred to lay <lb/>eggs in the co-culture containing A. pomorum WT to the co-culture containing A. <lb/>pomorum adhA, further substantiating the importance of ethanol catabolism in <lb/>Drosophila biology, as egg-laying decisions are crucial to reproductive success (Figure <lb/>5B). <lb/>We next identified additional metabolites unique to the co-culture using solid-<lb/>phase microextraction gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (SPME GC-MS). Acetic <lb/>acid, six acetate esters, an acetaldehyde metabolic derivative (acetoin), a putative <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>acetaldehyde metabolic derivative (2,4,5-trimethyl-1,3-dioxolane), and two unknown <lb/>metabolites were more abundant in the co-culture relative to the separate-culture <lb/>mixture or co-culture with A. pomorum lacking adhA (Table 2, Table 2-figure <lb/>supplements 1-2). To determine the molecular basis for Drosophila co-culture <lb/>preference, select metabolites were added to the co-culture containing A. pomorum <lb/>adhA. Esters and acetic acid, but not esters alone, were sufficient to fully restore A. <lb/>pomorum adhA attractiveness to A. pomorum WT levels (Figure 5A). <lb/>Although acetate and its metabolic derivatives were sufficient for Drosophila co-<lb/>culture preference, acetaldehyde is a reactive intermediate during ethanol catabolism <lb/>whose metabolic derivatives might be increased in microbial communities compared <lb/>with individual microbial cultures. Consistent with this idea, acetoin was moderately <lb/>increased in the co-culture compared with the separate-culture mixture (Table 2-figure <lb/>supplement 1); strikingly, acetoin was increased ~27-fold in the tri-culture (S. cerevisiae, <lb/>A. malorum, and L. plantarum) compared to the co-culture (Figure 6A, B, Figure 6-<lb/>figure supplement 1) and was attractive to Drosophila (Figure 6-figure supplement 2). In <lb/>sum, emergent metabolites from 2-and 3-membered communities, including <lb/>acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives, attract Drosophila. <lb/>To investigate further the potential role of acetaldehyde and its metabolic <lb/>derivatives in Drosophila behavior, we performed a dose response in which <lb/>acetaldehyde was added to the separate-culture mixture (Figure 6-figure supplement <lb/>3A) to evaluate its ability to induce attractiveness to co-culture levels. Even at the lowest <lb/>tested levels, acetaldehyde supplementation stimulated the separate-culture mixture to <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>attractiveness levels equal to the co-culture (Figure 6-figure supplement 3A); moreover, <lb/>acetaldehyde and its metabolic derivatives &apos;over-restored&apos; preference of the separate-<lb/>culture mixture beyond WT co-culture levels at its most attractive dose (Figure 6-figure <lb/>supplement 3A). Finally, three acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives-acetoin, 1,1-<lb/>diethoxyethane (an acetal), and 2,3-butanedione-were sufficient to induce the <lb/>attractiveness of the separate-culture mixture to WT co-culture levels using <lb/>concentrations of each metabolite at or below the physiological concentration of acetoin <lb/>found in the tri-culture (Figure 6-figure supplement 3B). Creating a pure metabolite <lb/>mixture comprised of key metabolic groups produced by microbial communities and <lb/>identified in this study (esters, acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives, alcohols, acid) <lb/>attracted Drosophila similarly to the co-culture (Figure 6-figure supplement 4A, B). <lb/>Interestingly, the acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives alone were sufficient and the most <lb/>attractive (Figure 6-figure supplement 4C, D), supporting acetaldehyde metabolic <lb/>derivatives as potent Drosophila attractants. <lb/>Overall, our results suggest that both esters and acetaldehyde metabolic <lb/>derivatives are keystone microbial community metabolites that attract Drosophila. We <lb/>next created a simple 9-metabolite mixture in water (containing only 1 acid, 4 esters, <lb/>and 4 acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives) and measured Drosophila preference toward <lb/>this mixture in relation to the yeast-acetic acid bacteria co-culture, the yeast-acetic acid <lb/>bacteria-lactic acid bacteria microbial community, or apple cider vinegar (ACV). The <lb/>defined mixture used concentrations for each acetaldehyde metabolic derivative similar <lb/>to the concentration of acetoin in the tri-culture and ester and acid concentrations that <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>were in the range of detected in the co-culture. The defined 9-metabolite mixture was <lb/>more attractive than all other conditions (Figure 6-figure supplement 5). In sum, <lb/>acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives and esters are potent Drosophila attractants whose <lb/>detection may signal the presence of actively metabolizing, multispecies microbial <lb/>communities. <lb/>Discussion: <lb/>Here, we have demonstrated how emergent properties of a microbial <lb/>community-volatile profile, population dynamics, and pH-influence Drosophila <lb/>attraction, survival, and egg-laying behaviors. Our study is the first to identify the <lb/>consequences of microbe-microbe metabolic exchange on animal behavior and <lb/>discovers additional microbial interactions for further mechanistic study (Figure 1D). <lb/>Microbe-microbe metabolic exchange generates unique and quantitatively <lb/>different volatiles from those resulting from individual microbial metabolism (Tables 1 &amp; <lb/>2, Figure 7). Acetobacter-generated acetate coupled to Saccharomyces-derived <lb/>alcohols spawn diverse acetate esters (Table 1 &amp; Table 2). We hypothesize that more <lb/>complex and diverse communities, comprising alcohol-producing yeasts, acetate-<lb/>producing Acetobacter, and lactate-producing Lactobacillus, will generate a wider array <lb/>of attractive esters (Figure 7). The community of S. cerevisiae, A. malorum, and L. <lb/>plantarum emitted higher levels of acetoin and attracted Drosophila more strongly than <lb/>the co-culture of S. cerevisiae and A. malorum (Figure 1D, Figure 6). Acetoin and 2,3-<lb/>butanedione are formed by an α-acetolactate intermediate in bacteria and directly from <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>acetaldehyde in yeast (52). We therefore hypothesize that communities of yeasts and <lb/>bacteria may emit high levels of attractive acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives (Figure <lb/>7). <lb/>Drosophila behavioral studies have mostly focused on yeasts, even though <lb/>Drosophila evolved in a bacterial-rich environment. Our results suggest that non-yeast <lb/>microorganisms, especially when grown in microbial communities, affect Drosophila <lb/>behaviors. We reason that additional investigations that couple chemical microbial <lb/>ecology with Drosophila behavior will herald the discovery of microbe-influenced <lb/>behaviors and microbial community-generated metabolites. <lb/>This study demonstrates the coordination of ethanol synthesis and catabolism by <lb/>S. cerevisiae and Acetobacter, respectively, and the role of ethanol in Drosophila <lb/>behavior and survival. Non-Saccharomyces Drosophila microbiome members also <lb/>make ethanol (53) and diverse acetic acid bacteria catabolize ethanol, generalizing our <lb/>findings to other microbial community combinations. Ethanol can have deleterious or <lb/>beneficial fitness consequences for Drosophila depending on concentration (54, 55) and <lb/>ecological context (56). Our results show that Drosophila uses products of inter-species <lb/>microbiome metabolism to detect a community that titrates ethanol concentration <lb/>optimally for the host. Work that further dissects the consequences of acetic acid and <lb/>ethanol concentrations on Drosophila biology and investigates other community-level <lb/>metabolic profiles will be of interest to enrich the chemical and ecological portrait of the <lb/>Drosophila microbiome. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Our work raises questions about the consequences of the observed behavior on <lb/>microbiome assembly and stability in the Drosophila intestine. Drosophila possesses <lb/>specific and regionalized gut immune responses to the microbiome (57-60) implying a <lb/>tolerant environment in which privileged microbiome members are maintained and <lb/>reproduce in the Drosophila intestine. Other work suggests that Drosophila acquires its <lb/>adult microbiome from exogenous sources, that adult microbiome abundance drops <lb/>without continuous ingestion of exogenous microorganisms, and that the microbiome <lb/>can be shaped by diet (19, 25, 26). As such, a combination of internal mechanisms, <lb/>exogenous factors, and host behavior likely sculpt the microbiome; determining the <lb/>relative contribution of each will be important moving forward. Complicating our <lb/>understanding of the contribution of these factors is the opaque distinction between <lb/>&apos;microbiome&apos; and &apos;food&apos;, since both are ingested from the environment (61). To dissect <lb/>the formation and stability of the Drosophila microbiome, the fate of ingested <lb/>microorganisms needs to be monitored and microbial intestinal reproduction needs to <lb/>be surveyed as a function of Drosophila behavior, age, immune status, microbiome <lb/>membership, and nutritional state (e.g. using synthetic diets without yeast; (34, 62)). <lb/>In sum, our results support a model in which the Drosophila olfactory system is <lb/>tuned to fruity (e.g., esters) and buttery (several acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives, <lb/>such as 2,3-butanedione) smelling metabolites promoted by microbe-microbe <lb/>interactions. We anticipate that accounting for microbial interactions in diverse host-<lb/>microbe studies will lead to new insights into diverse aspects of microbial-animal <lb/>symbioses. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements: <lb/>We thank Dr. Fabian Staubach (Stanford University, USA), Dr. Angus Chandler <lb/>(University of California, Berkeley, USA), Dr. Matthew Goddard (The University of <lb/>Auckland, New Zealand), Dr. Dan Jarosz (Stanford University, USA) and the Phaff <lb/>Yeast Culture Collection (UC Davis, USA) for microbial strains. We thank Dr. Ryan <lb/>Joseph and Dr. Karen Menuz (Yale University/University of Connecticut) for help with <lb/>the Drosophila behavioral experiments; the Yale West Campus Analytical Core for use <lb/>of the GC-MS; Dr. Terence Wu and Dr. Eric Patridge (Yale University, USA) for advice <lb/>and experimental help with the GC-MS; Dr. Scott Strobel and Michelle Legaspi for use <lb/>of and help with SPME GC-MS; Dr. John Carlson (Yale University, USA) for the T-maze <lb/>and several Drosophila lines. We also thank Dr. Won Jae Lee (Seoul National <lb/>University, S. Korea) for the A. pomorum WT and adhA strains, and John Carlson, Craig <lb/>Crews, and Andrew Goodman (Yale University, USA) for helpful discussions. This work <lb/>was supported by National Institutes of Health Grants NIDDKRC12T32GM007499-36, <lb/>5T32HG003198-10, 1R01GM099563, 7RC1DK086831. The raw data for the <lb/>metabolomics <lb/>experiments <lb/>can <lb/>be <lb/>found <lb/>at <lb/>https://figshare.com/account/home#/projects/4735. <lb/></div>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/> E <lb/> Fig. 1. Drosophila detection of microbe-microbe metabolic <lb/>exchange. (A) T-maze setup and quantification. (B) Drosophila <lb/>behavior toward yeasts (blue), acetic acid bacteria (red), and lactic <lb/>acid bacteria (brown) (Table S1). Mean ± SEM of 12-36 replicates <lb/>(n=2-6 experiments). Each T-maze replicate uses a technical <lb/>replicate of a microbial culture and one cohort of Drosophila <lb/>maintained in separate vials for 3-5 days. Mock (two empty tubes), <lb/>ACV (25% apple cider vinegar versus water), and benzaldehyde <lb/>(1% versus paraffin oil (PO)). A one-sample t-test assessed <lb/>deviance from 0. Symbols: NS p &gt;0.05; * p ≤0.05; ** p ≤0.01; *** p <lb/>≤0.001; **** p ≤0.0001. (C) Mean Drosophila behavior toward each <lb/>microorganisms was graphed according to microbial group and <lb/>analyzed by one-way ANOVA. (D) Drosophila behavior toward <lb/>community combinations of a representative yeast, acetic acid <lb/>bacterium, and lactic acid bacterium in relation to their separate-<lb/>culture mixture (grown individually and mixed; Sc = S. cerevisiae; <lb/>Am= A. malorum; Lp = L. plantarum cs) grown for 96 h; Drosophila <lb/>preference for the three-versus two-membered community is the <lb/>last column. Mean ± SEM of 12-18 replicates (n=2-3 experiments). <lb/>A one-sample t-test assessed deviance from 0. (E) Drosophila <lb/>olfactory behavior toward the S. cerevisiae and A. malorum <lb/>community and its constituent parts relative to media grown for 48-<lb/>60 h. Mean ± SEM of 18-30 replicates (n=5 experiments). <lb/>Differences between groups were assessed by ANOVA. A Tukey&apos;s <lb/>multiple comparison test was used to assess significant differences <lb/>between groups (p≤0.05), as indicated by unique letters. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>C <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>Fig. 2. Drosophila temporal preference for metabolic exchange. (A) S. cerevisiae and A. malorum viable <lb/>populations. Mean ± SEM of 2-3 experiments with one pooled replicate (2-3 cultures derived from the <lb/>same colony) per experiment. Limit of detection is 20 CFU/mL. (B) Drosophila olfactory behavior toward <lb/>co-cultured S. cerevisiae and A. malorum versus its separate-culture mixture as a function of culture age. <lb/>Mean ± SEM of 16-18 replicates from three experiments. A t-test against a hypothetical value of zero <lb/>assessed deviance from 0. Symbols: NS p &gt;0.05; * p ≤0.05; ** p ≤0.01; *** p ≤0.001; **** p ≤0.0001. (C) <lb/>Relationship between pH and Drosophila preference for the S. cerevisiae and A. malorum co-culture <lb/>versus the separate-culture mixture. Each data point represents the pH of a co-culture and the mean RI <lb/>of Drosophila toward the same co-culture. A linear standard curve with an unconstrained slope was <lb/>generated and compared to a null model with slope=0. The data fit to an unconstrained slope better than <lb/>to the null model (p&lt;0.0001, slope = -0.3295). (D) Relationship between S. cerevisiae populations and <lb/>Drosophila preference for the co-culture versus the separate-culture mixture. Each data point represents <lb/>viable S. cerevisiae populations of the culture along with the mean RI value toward the co-culture <lb/>containing S. cerevisiae. A semilog standard curve with an unconstrained slope was generated and <lb/>compared to a null model with slope=0. The data fit to an unconstrained slope better than to the null <lb/>model (p&lt;0.0001, slope = -0.0349). <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 3. Role of olfactory receptor mutants in Drosophila detection of inter-species microbial interactions. <lb/>Culture were grown at and after peak Drosophila attraction. Differences were assessed by a one-way <lb/>ANOVA within each culture age. A Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test was used to assess significant <lb/>differences between groups (p≤0.05), as indicated by unique letters. Mean +/-SEM of 12-24 replicates <lb/>per time point per fly condition (n=2-4 experiments per time point). <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Fig. 4 Drosophila behavior, survival, and ethanol catabolism. A) Dynamics of ethanol, acetic acid and <lb/>Drosophila co-culture preference. Acetic acid was only detected in the co-culture. The abundance was <lb/>derived from a linear regression calculated from standards (figs. S6). Chemical data is the mean ± SEM <lb/>of two values calculated from two experiments with three replicates per experiment (except acetic acid <lb/>and ethanol concentrations at 144 and 156 h, which are from one experiment with three replicates). <lb/>Drosophila co-culture preference is the mean value of the preference shown in Figure 2B. B) Drosophila <lb/>preference for stages of ethanol catabolism. 72 h is &apos;mid&apos; stage; 36 h is &apos;early&apos; stage and 144 is &apos;late&apos; <lb/>stage. The co-culture contains S. cerevisiae and A. malorum grown for the time indicated. AJM= apple <lb/>juice media. Data points represent the mean ± SEM of the combined results of two experiments with 8-10 <lb/>total replicates per group. A t-test assessed whether the values were different from zero. C) Drosophila <lb/>survival in the presence of acetic acid (AA), ethanol (EtOH) or the combination of the two in water. <lb/>Groupings were based on concentrations of metabolites estimated from pre-ethanol catabolism (9.4% <lb/>ethanol, High EtOH), middle-staged ethanol catabolism (1.4% ethanol, 2.8% acetic acid, Mod. EtOH ) and <lb/>post ethanol catabolism (3.42% acetic acid, High AA). Data represent mean +/-SEM of 5-6 replicates of <lb/>one representative experiment of two. Mod. EtOH was significantly different from High EtOH condition <lb/>from 108 h onward and High AA condition from 72 h onward (assessed by two-way ANOVA comparing <lb/>time and condition, p≤0.05, Tukey&apos;s correction). Negative Cntrl is water and Positive Cntrl is Shield&apos;s &amp; <lb/>Sang M3 Insect Medium. <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>Fig. 5. Role of ethanol catabolism in Drosophila olfactory and egg-laying behaviors. (A) Drosophila <lb/>olfactory behavior toward specified conditions. Mean ± SEM of 2-7 experiments with 10-42 total <lb/>replicates. Differences were assessed by a one-way ANOVA. A Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test was <lb/>used to assess significant differences between groups (p≤0.05), as indicated by unique letters. Esters <lb/>include ethyl acetate, isoamyl acetate, 2-phenethyl acetate, isobutyl acetate, 2-methylbutyl acetate, and <lb/>methyl acetate; acid is acetic acid. Amounts added are based on physiological amounts in co-cultures <lb/>and are found in Table 2. The co-culture contains S. cerevisiae and the specified A. pomorum strain. <lb/>acid= acetic acid (B) Drosophila was given a choice to lay eggs in a co-culture containing S. cerevisiae <lb/>and A. pomorum wild-type (WT) or S. cerevisiae and A. pomorum adhA. The co-cultures were grown for <lb/>96 h and mixed 1:1 with a 1.6% agarose solution. Drosophila was allowed to lay eggs for eight hours. <lb/>Difference between the two groups was assessed by an unpaired t-test (**** p≤0.0001). Mean ± SEM of <lb/>16-18 replicates from two experiments. <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>Fig. 6. Acetoin as an attractive metabolite increased in the 3-membered communitiys A) Representative <lb/>chromatogram of the tri-culture (S. cerevisiae-A. malorum-L. plantarum) compared to the co-culture (S. <lb/>cerevisiae and A. malorum). B) Estimated quantification of is based on a linear regression of acetoin <lb/>(figure 6-figure supplement 1). Relative quantification of acetoin in the tri-culture (one replicate with A. <lb/>malorum and one replicate with A. pomorum from separate days) and the co-culture (one replicate with A. <lb/>malorum and two replicates with A. pomorum from separate days). Difference in peak areas was <lb/>assessed by an unpaired two-tailed t-test (** p≤0.01). <lb/>2.85 <lb/>2.95 <lb/>3.05 <lb/>3.15 <lb/>0 <lb/>250 <lb/>500 <lb/>500 <lb/>1750 <lb/>3000 <lb/>Retention Time (min) <lb/>Extracted Ion Current <lb/>(m/z 88.05) <lb/>Acetoin <lb/>Tri-culture <lb/>(~0.28%) <lb/>Co-culture <lb/>(~0.01%) <lb/>Standard <lb/>(0.01%) <lb/>T r i -c u l t u r e C <lb/>o -c u l t u r e <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>Relative Peak Area <lb/>** <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 7. Model of microbe-microbe metabolite exchange. Bolded are metabolites increased due to <lb/>microbe-microbe interactions. <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Summary of volatiles detected using GC-MS <lb/>Identity <lb/>Standard <lb/>confirmation <lb/>Relative quantification <lb/>(co-culture: separate-culture mixture) <lb/>Ethanol <lb/>Y <lb/>5.0-12.6-fold reduced <lb/>Isobutanol <lb/>Y <lb/>7.3-24.7-fold reduced <lb/>Isoamyl acetate <lb/>Y <lb/>unique to co-culture <lb/>Isoamyl alcohol <lb/>Y <lb/>3.6-6.4-fold reduced <lb/>Acetic acid <lb/>Y <lb/>unique to co-culture <lb/>Table 1. Relative abundance of volatiles in the co-culture (S. cerevisiae and A. malorum grown together) <lb/>compared to the separate-culture mixture (S. cerevisiae and A. malorum grown separately, and their <lb/>quantities added in during anaylsis). GC-MS captured volatiles with XAD-4 beads suspended above the <lb/>cultures during growth; subsequently, beads were methanol-extracted (n=6 experiments, Table 1-figure <lb/>supplements 1-2). Quantification is based on two experiments in which a linear regression was computed <lb/>with standards (Table 1-figure supplement 3). Quantification is based on beads suspended above the <lb/>cultures between 84 and 96 h of culture growth. <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2. Estimated concentrations of key metabolites in the co-culture using SPME GC-MS <lb/>Metabolite <lb/>Lin. reg. eq. 1 <lb/>Lin. reg. eq. 2 <lb/>Normalized <lb/>Peak <lb/>Area <lb/>(single <lb/>experiment) <lb/>Normalized Peak <lb/>Area <lb/>(Average, <lb/>All experiments) <lb/>Estimated <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Isobutyl acetate <lb/>Y=4151X -0.1319 <lb/>Y=3252X -0.07251 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>1.16 <lb/>0.00023 <lb/>Isoamyl acetate <lb/>y=8158X <lb/>Y = 7800X <lb/>0.78 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>0.00026 <lb/>2-Phenethyl acetate <lb/>Y=5129X -0.04011 <lb/>Y=6972X -0.2013 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>0.00028 <lb/>2-Methylbutyl acetate <lb/>acetate <lb/>Y=8995X -0.05042 <lb/>Y=8087X-0.1307 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>0.00023 <lb/>Methyl acetate <lb/>Y=75.22X +0.004457 <lb/>NA <lb/>0.018 <lb/>0.040 <lb/>0.00033 <lb/>Ethyl acetate <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>~0.02* <lb/>Acetic acid <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>~3.0* <lb/>Acetoin <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>~0.01* <lb/>Table 2. Estimated concentrations of differentially concentrated or unique metabolites in the co-culture. <lb/>Linear regression equations (Lin. reg. eqs. 1 and 2) were estimated from individual experiments in which <lb/>peak areas of different concentrations of metabolites were fitted with a linear regression (Table 2-figure <lb/>supplement 2). Normalized peak areas correspond to the specified metabolites in co-cultures containing <lb/>S. cerevisiae and A. malorum. Separate estimates were derived from a normalized peak area estimated <lb/>from a single experiment (co-culture and standard samples were from a run with similar internal standard <lb/>signal) or from the mean normalized peak area estimated from all experiments (co-cultures were run over <lb/>four days, standards were run on two days). The final estimated concentration was an average of all <lb/>estimated concentrations (n=4 estimates (two from each standard regression equation times two <lb/>estimates of the normalized peak area), execpt for methyl acetate, n=2 estimates). The estimated <lb/>concentrations (exept acetoin) were added to the co-culture containing A. pomorum adhA (Figure 5A). <lb/>*Ethyl acetate, acetic acid and acetoin concentrations were estimated from standards in Table 2-figure <lb/>supplement 1. <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS <lb/> 549 <lb/> LAB = lactic acid bacteria; AAB = acetic acid bacteria <lb/> 550 <lb/> Table S1. Microorganisms and their sources used in this study <lb/>Organism <lb/>Clade Source <lb/>Saccharomyces cerevisiae <lb/>Yeast <lb/>Drosophila pinicola, Phaff culture collection <lb/>S. cerevisiae Y9 <lb/>Yeast <lb/>Ragi (similar to Sake wine) fermentation (30) <lb/>S. cerevisiae YB-210 <lb/>Yeast <lb/>Banana; ARSC culture collection (63) <lb/>Pichia membranefaciens <lb/>Yeast <lb/>D. melanogaster in Handelsman Laboratory <lb/>Candida californica <lb/>Yeast <lb/>Bananas and D. melanogaster habitat in Stamps laboratory; <lb/>Phaff culture collection <lb/>Hanseniaspora uvarum <lb/>Yeast <lb/>Bananas and D. melanogaster habitat in Stamps laboratory; <lb/>Phaff culture collection <lb/>Lactobacillus plantarum cs <lb/>LAB <lb/>D. melanogaster in Handelsman Laboratory (25) <lb/>L. brevis_lab <lb/>LAB <lb/>D. melanogaster in Handelsman Laboratory <lb/>L. fermentum <lb/>LAB <lb/>D. melanogaster in Handelsman Laboratory <lb/>L. brevis_wild <lb/>LAB <lb/>Wild-caught D. melanogaster (19) <lb/>Leuconostoc sp_Fabian <lb/>LAB <lb/>Wild-caught D. melanogaster (64) <lb/>L. plantarum <lb/>LAB <lb/>D. melanogaster in Handelsman Laboratory <lb/>Leuconostoc durionis <lb/>LAB <lb/>Wild-caught D. melanogaster (64) <lb/>Acetobacter pasteurianus_lab AAB <lb/>D. melanogaster in Handelsman Laboratory <lb/>A. cerevisiae <lb/>AAB <lb/>D. melanogaster in Handelsman Laboratory <lb/>A. malorum <lb/>AAB <lb/>D. melanogaster in Handelsman Laboratory <lb/>A. indonensiensis <lb/>AAB <lb/>D. melanogaster in Handelsman Laboratory <lb/>A. pasteurianus_wild <lb/>AAB <lb/>Wild-caught D. melanogaster (19) <lb/>A. orleanensis <lb/>AAB <lb/>Wild-caught D. melanogaster (19) <lb/>A. pomorum <lb/>AAB <lb/>D. melanogaster in Won-Jae Lee Laboratory (34) <lb/>A. pomorum adhA <lb/>AAB <lb/>Mutant derivative of A. pomorum (34) <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1-figure supplement 1. Drosophila melanogaster olfactory behavior toward different culture <lb/>volumes of Saccharomyces cerevisiae and Acetobacter malorum. The top three experimental groups are <lb/>controls: Mock (empty tube versus empty tube) recapitulates alternating of test and control arms, as in all <lb/>experimental groups; apple cider vinegar (ACV (25% in water)) is the positive control and tested against <lb/>water only; Benzaldehyde (1%) is the negative control and is a 100-fold dilution of benzaldehyde in <lb/>paraffin oil (PO) tested against paraffin oil only. In all experimental groups, 10µl of total volume was used; <lb/>the culture amount is specified, when appropriate, on the right-hand portion of the plot. The remaining <lb/>volume in the microbial groups is water. Media control (AJM) is always 5µl of AJM mixed with 5µl of <lb/>water. Data points represent the mean +/-SEM combined from three experiments (n=12 per experimental <lb/>group). A t-test was performed against a hypothetical value of 0 to test for significance and is denoted by <lb/>the following system (consistent throughout manuscript): NS p &gt;0.05; * p ≤0.05; ** p ≤0.01; *** p ≤0.001; <lb/>**** p ≤0.0001. Based on this analysis, we used a total microbial culture volume of 5 µl throughout the <lb/>manuscript, unless otherwise noted. <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>10 -1 10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 10 5 10 6 10 7 10 8 10 9 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>A. malorum viable cell density (CFU/ mL) <lb/>Response Index <lb/>(versus mix) <lb/>R 2 = 0.1012 <lb/>p= 0.1132, <lb/>Do not reject null hypothesis of slope=0 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Figure 2-figure supplement 1. Properties of the co-culture and its relationship to Drosophila preference <lb/>(A) pH of experimental groups as a function of microbial growth time. Mean pH ± SEM of three <lb/>experiments with one pooled replicate per experiment. (B) Relationship between A. malorum populations <lb/>and Drosophila preference for the co-culture versus the separate-culture mixture. Each data point <lb/>represents viable A. malorum populations in the co-culture along with the mean RI value toward the co-<lb/>culture containing A. malorum. A semi-log standard curve with an unconstrained slope was generated <lb/>and compared to a null model with slope=0. The data do not fit to an unconstrained slope better than to <lb/>the null slope= 0 model (p=0.1132). (C) Drosophila attraction to the co-culture versus sterile media as a <lb/>function of co-culture age (grown 34 h -127 h). Mean RI ± SEM of three experiments with 16-18 total <lb/>replicates. T-test against a hypothetical value of 0 was performed. NS p &gt;0.05; * p ≤0.05; ** p ≤0.01; *** p <lb/>≤0.001; **** p ≤0.0001 Significance denoted beside or within bars of each experimental group. ACV = <lb/>apple cider vinegar (25% in water); PO = paraffin oil. <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 3-figure supplement 1. A) Attraction of wild-type Drosophila to different aged co-cultures (grown <lb/>67-163 h, S. cerevisiae and A. malorum). Mean ± SEM of 12-24 replicates per group (n=2-4 <lb/>experiments). One-way ANOVA assessed significance between groups. A Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison <lb/>test was used to assess significant differences between groups (p≤0.05), as indicated by unique letters. <lb/>B) Corresponding viable counts at different times of microbial growth. Mean ± SEM of 2-3 replicates. <lb/>29 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>Table 1-figure supplement 1. Extracted ion chromatograms of the five metabolites detected by gas chromatography-mass <lb/>spectrometry (GC-MS). (A) Schematic depicting the experimental setup (B-F) Representative extracted ion chromatograms <lb/>from one replicate (out of three total) of one experiment (out of 3-4 total) of m/z values corresponding to major metabolites <lb/>identified in the experimental conditions along with appropriate standards. Acetic acid (B), isoamyl alcohol (C), isoamyl <lb/>acetate (D) isobutanol (E), and ethanol (F) were identified as the five major metabolites in the co-culture (S. cerevisiae and <lb/>A. malorum). Isoamyl alcohol (C), ethanol (E), and isobutanol (F) were identified as the major metabolites in S. cerevisiae <lb/>grown alone. Extracted ion chromatograms were constructed using the m/z value in the title of each graph. For acetic acid <lb/>and isobutanol, the m/z value used corresponds to the molecular weight of the molecule. For ethanol, the m/z used <lb/>corresponds to the molecular weight minus one (hydrogen). For isoamyl alcochol, the m/z used corresponds to the loss of <lb/>the hydroxyl group (depicted), which may have picked up a hydrogen and been lost as water. For isoamyl acetate, the m/z <lb/>value corresponds to the molecule shown within the graph. In all cases, figures showing the complete mass spectra <lb/>between the metabolite and standard are found in Table 1-figure supplement 2. Microorganisms were grown 72-96 hours. <lb/>8.0 <lb/>8.2 <lb/>8.4 <lb/>8.6 <lb/>0 <lb/>50000 <lb/>100000 <lb/>Retention Time (min) <lb/>Extracted Ion Current <lb/>(m/z 87.1) <lb/>Standard: Isoamyl acetate (1mM) <lb/>Co-culture <lb/>(S.cerevisiae and <lb/>A.malorum) <lb/>Isoamyl acetate <lb/>S.cerevisiae <lb/>A.malorum <lb/>Media <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>G <lb/>B <lb/>H <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>D <lb/>J <lb/>E <lb/>K <lb/>F <lb/>L <lb/>Table 1-figure supplement 2. Representative spectra of acetic acid (A-B), isoamyl alcohol (C-E), <lb/>isoamyl acetate (F-G), ethanol (H-J) and isobutanol (K-L) in standard and experimental samples. <lb/>Standard concentrations are denoted on individual graphs. All mass spectra are one replicate (out of 3-4 <lb/>experiments with three replicates per experiment). <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>2×10 6 <lb/>4×10 6 <lb/>6×10 6 <lb/>8×10 6 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 60.05) <lb/>Acetic acid <lb/>R 2 =0.9945 <lb/>Y=2.488e6X-344526 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>5.0×10 4 <lb/>1.0×10 5 <lb/>1.5×10 5 <lb/>2.0×10 5 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 74.1) <lb/>Isobutanol <lb/>R 2 =0.9947 <lb/>Y=5.224e6X+6380 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>5.0×10 5 <lb/>1.0×10 6 <lb/>1.5×10 6 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 87.1) <lb/>Isoamyl acetate <lb/>R 2 =1.00 <lb/>Y=4.546e7X-13906 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>1×10 6 <lb/>2×10 6 <lb/>3×10 6 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 45.1) <lb/>Ethanol <lb/>R 2 =0.9995 <lb/>Y=863224X+19449 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>1×10 6 <lb/>2×10 6 <lb/>3×10 6 <lb/>4×10 6 <lb/>5×10 6 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 70.1) <lb/>Isoamyl alcohol <lb/>R 2 =0.9986 <lb/>Y=1.386e8X-109155 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>2×10 6 <lb/>4×10 6 <lb/>6×10 6 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 60.05) <lb/>Acetic acid <lb/>R 2 =0.8849 <lb/>Y=1.464e6X-187355 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>2×10 5 <lb/>4×10 5 <lb/>6×10 5 <lb/>8×10 5 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 74.1) <lb/>Isobutanol <lb/>R 2 =0.7723 <lb/>Y=1.694e7X <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>5.0×10 5 <lb/>1.0×10 6 <lb/>1.5×10 6 <lb/>2.0×10 6 <lb/>2.5×10 6 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 87.1) <lb/>Isoamyl acetate <lb/>R 2 =0.9652 <lb/>Y=6.642e7X <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>1×10 6 <lb/>2×10 6 <lb/>3×10 6 <lb/>4×10 6 <lb/>5×10 6 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 45.1) <lb/>Ethanol <lb/>R 2 =0.6319 <lb/>Y=930217X+89015 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>1×10 6 <lb/>2×10 6 <lb/>3×10 6 <lb/>4×10 6 <lb/>5×10 6 <lb/>Concentration (%) <lb/>Abundance <lb/>(m/z value 70.1) <lb/>Isoamyl alcohol <lb/>R 2 =0.9026 <lb/>Y=1.507e8X <lb/>A <lb/>D <lb/>F <lb/>I <lb/>B <lb/>E <lb/>G <lb/>J <lb/>C <lb/>H <lb/>Table 1-figure supplement 3. Estimation of volatile quantity using GC-MS. Separate experiments are <lb/>graphed in panels (A-E) and (F-J). (A-E) Data points represent the value of a single replicate per <lb/>concentration for each standard. The abundance of a single m/z value at a specific retention time was <lb/>chosen for each standard. The values were fitted with a linear regression and the equation was used to <lb/>estimate the concentration of the five metabolites in the experimental samples from the same experiment. <lb/>(F-J) Data points represent the mean ± SEM of three replicates for a given concentration for each <lb/>standard. The abundance of a single m/z value at a specific retention time was chosen for each standard. <lb/>The values were fitted with a linear regression. The equation was used to estimate the concentration of <lb/>the 5 metabolites in the experimental samples from the same experiment. When applicable an equation <lb/>was calculated when the line was forced to go through X,Y=0,0; these equations were used to calculate <lb/>the concentrations of isoamyl alcohol, isoamyl acetate, and isobutanol. <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5-figure supplement 1. Drosophila behavior toward the co-culture using A. malorum or A. <lb/>pomorum. Drosophila behavior toward co-cultures grown for 96 h using A. malorum or A. pomorum <lb/>versus a media control (AJM = apple juice medium). Result of two experiments with six replicates each. <lb/>Data points represent mean ± SEM. An unpaired two-tailed t-test assessed whether Drosophila behavior <lb/>toward the co-cultures was different (NS p &gt; 0.05). <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>A. malorum <lb/>A. pomorum <lb/>A. malorum <lb/>A. pomorum <lb/>A <lb/>Methyl acetate <lb/>B <lb/>Ethyl acetate <lb/>C <lb/>Isobutyl acetate <lb/>D <lb/>Isoamyl acetate <lb/>E <lb/>2-Methylbutyl acetate <lb/>F <lb/>2-Phenethyl acetate <lb/>G <lb/>Acetic acid <lb/>H <lb/>Acetoin <lb/>I <lb/>Putative: 1,3-dioxolane,2,4,5-trimethyl <lb/>J <lb/> Unknowns <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2-figure supplement 1. Extracted ion chromatograms of differentially emitted or unique <lb/>metabolites in the co-culture according to solid phase microextraction gas chromatography-mass <lb/>spectrometry (SPME GC-MS). Specific metabolites are displayed above each panel. For each panel, the <lb/>left-most plot compares the co-culture containing S. cerevisiae and A. malorum to S. cerevisiae grown <lb/>alone, A. malorum grown alone, or media (AJM (apple juice medium)); the right-most plot compares the <lb/>co-culture containing S. cerevisiae and A. pomorum wild-type to the co-culture containing S. cerevisiae <lb/>and A. pomorum adhA, since A. pomorum adhA is required for Drosophila co-culture preference (Figure <lb/>5A). The two plots within the same panel contain the same standard. The y-axis for each plot is the ion <lb/>current for a m/z value that discriminates the metabolite of interest over a specific retention time window. <lb/>The following m/z values were chosen for each metabolite based on standards or, in the cases of putative <lb/>and unknown metabolites (I and J) were chosen from the experimental groups: (A) m/z 74.04 (B) m/z <lb/>88.08 (C) m/z 73.03 (D) 87.05 (E) 74.02 (F) 104.04 (G) 60.05 (H) 88.05 (I) 101.06 (J) 101.06. Each panel <lb/>is one representative replicate of 1 experiment (out of 3-5 total replicates in three experiments). <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>F <lb/>B <lb/>G <lb/>C <lb/>H <lb/>D <lb/>I <lb/>E <lb/>Table 2-figure supplement 2. <lb/>Normalized <lb/>peak <lb/>areas <lb/>corresponding to metabolites <lb/>in a defined metabolite mixture <lb/>(from SPME GC-MS). A linear <lb/>regression was calculated to <lb/>quantify the metabolites in the <lb/>co-culture. Each concentration <lb/>is from one replicate. A-E and <lb/>F-I <lb/>are <lb/>two <lb/>separate <lb/>experiments. Linear regression <lb/>was used to estimate the <lb/>concentration <lb/>of <lb/>the <lb/>metabolites in the co-culture <lb/>containing S. cerevisiae and A. <lb/>malorum (Table 2) and to <lb/>complement the co-culture <lb/>containing A. pomorum adhA <lb/>(Figure 5A). <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6-figure supplement 1. Acetoin linear regression. The curve is based on maximum m/z values <lb/>(88.05) of three concentrations of acetoin. One replicate per concentration (n=1 experiment). The linear <lb/>regression was used to estimate acetoin concentrations in the tri-culture and the co-culture (Figure 6B). <lb/></body>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6-figure supplement 2. Role of esters alone or esters with acetoin in complementing co-culture <lb/>with A. pomomrum adhA. Mean +/-SEM of three experiments with 16-18 total replicates. A one-way <lb/>ANOVA assessed whether groups were different. A Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test was used to assess <lb/>significant differences between groups (p≤0.05), as indicated by unique letters. Esters include ethyl <lb/>acetate, isoamyl acetate, 2-phenethyl acetate, isobutyl acetate, 2-methylbutyl acetate, and methyl <lb/>acetate. Esters added are based on physiological amounts in co-cultures and are calculated in Table 2 <lb/>and Table 2-figure supplement 2). Acetoin is added in a similar amount as the tri-culture (Figure 6A, <lb/>0.3%). Sc = S. cerevisiae, Ap = A. pomorum. <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 6-figure supplement 3. Acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives can complement the co-culture containing <lb/>A. pomorum adhA, although their physiological concentrations are unknown. (A) Dose response of <lb/>acetaldehyde was given to the co-culture containing A. pomorum adhA (along with a constant dose of 3.0% <lb/>acetic acid). Metabolite additions were added to the culture in the noted percentages, allowed to sit 35 minutes <lb/>at room temperature, mixed 1:1 in water, and assessed for Drosophila attractivess. Mean ± SEM of 1-7 <lb/>experiments with 12-42 total replicates per group. The experimental groups from one experiment were run in <lb/>two separate groups during the day. Differences between groups were tested by one-way ANOVA. A Tukey&apos;s <lb/>multiple comparison test was used to assess significant differences between groups (p≤0.05), as indicated by <lb/>unique letters. (B) Role of acetic acid, acetaldehyde, or specified acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives in <lb/>complementing the co-culture containing A. pomorum adhA. Acetic acid (3.0%) and acetaldehyde (0.75%) <lb/>were added and allowed to sit at room temperature for 35 minutes, mixed 1:1 in water, and Drosophila <lb/>attraction was assayed. 2,3-butanedione (0.15%), 1,1-diethoxyethane (0.01%), and acetoin (0.15%) were <lb/>added to the culture, mixed 1:1 with water, and Drosophila behavior was assayed. Mean ± SEM of 2-7 <lb/>experiments with 5-6 replicates per experiment. Differences between groups were tested by one-way ANOVA. <lb/>A Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test was used to assess significant differences between groups (p≤0.05), as <lb/>indicated by unique letters. Sc = S. cerevisiae, Ap = A. pomorum. <lb/></body>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>Figure 6-figure supplement 4. Drosophila behavior toward metabolite <lb/>mixtures and their component parts (A) Drosophila behavior toward 21 <lb/>metabolite mixtures versus AJM (50% in water). Methods Table 4 <lb/>contains the concentrations of all mixtures (in 50% AJM). The co-culture <lb/>(S. cerevisiae and A. malorum, purple bar) was grown for 96 h. The pink <lb/>bar is metabolite mixture #21 and most closely resembled the co-culture. <lb/>Mean ± SEM of 4-6 replicates per experimental group. Groups were run <lb/>over five different days. (B) Relative Drosophila attraction to a co-culture <lb/>grown for 96 h and metabolite mixture #21. Mean ± SEM of three <lb/>experiments with 17-18 replicates per group. One-way ANOVA assessed <lb/>whether the groups were different. A Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test <lb/>was used to assess significant differences between groups (p≤0.05), as <lb/>indicated by unique letters. (C) The sufficiency of individual groupings <lb/>within metabolite mixture #21 to attract Drosophila. The individual <lb/>grouping are as follows: acetaldaldehyde metabolic derivatives (1,1-<lb/>diethoxyethane; acetoin; 2,3-butanedione); alcohols (ethanol; isobutanol; <lb/>isoamyl alcohol; 2-methyl, 1-butanol; benzeneethanol); esters (isoamyl <lb/>acetate; ethyl acetate; isobutyl acetate; 2-phenethyl acetate; butyl <lb/>acetate; 2-methylbutyl acetate; methyl acetate; phenethyl benzoate; <lb/>propyl acetate; ethyl isobutyrate; ethyl hexanoate; isovaleric acid; butyl <lb/>ester; ethyl octanoate; ethyl decanoate; ethyl laurate); and acetic acid <lb/>(acetic acid). Concentrations are in Methods Table 4. Mean ± SEM of six <lb/>replicates of one experiment (except the acetaldehyde metabolic <lb/>derivative group which is 12 replicates from 2 experiments). A t-test <lb/>against a hypothetical value of 0 was performed. p &gt;0.05; * p ≤0.05; ** p <lb/>≤0.01; *** p ≤0.001; **** p ≤0.0001 <lb/>(D) The same groups used in C <lb/>were used and removed from metabolite mix #21. The difference <lb/>between the co-culture (Sc-Am) and each group was assessed by one-<lb/>way ANOVA. A Tukey&apos;s multiple comparison test was used to assess <lb/>significant differences between groups (p≤0.05), as indicated by unique <lb/>letters. Mean ± SEM of six replicates of one experiment are shown. <lb/></body>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6-figure supplement 5. Drosophila behavior toward water amended with 9 metabolites (9-<lb/>metabolite mixture) versus 3 different apple cider vinegars (ACV), a co-culture (Sc-Am = S. cerevisiae <lb/>and A. malorum), or tri-culture (Sc-Am-Lp = S. cerevisiae, A. malorum, L. plantarum cs). Cultures were <lb/>grown for 72 h and mixed 1:1 with water, as in all other experiments. Data points represent the Mean ± <lb/>SEM of two experiments with twelve total replicates. A one-way ANOVA assessed whether each group <lb/>was different from the mock condition (empty tube versus empty tube). p &gt;0.05; * p ≤0.05; ** p ≤0.01; *** <lb/>p ≤0.001; **** p ≤0.0001. The acetoin concentration was similar to that calculated from the tri-culture <lb/>(Figure 6A, 0.3%). The concentrations of all 9 metabolites can be found in the materials and methods. <lb/></body>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Fly maintenance <lb/>Fly stocks, genotypes, and sources are listed in Methods Table 1. Drosophila melanogaster was reared at <lb/>25°C on a 12h:12h light: dark cycle on autoclaved food (5% yeast, 10% dextrose, 7% cornmeal, 0.6% <lb/>propionic acid, 0.7% agar). <lb/>Microbial strains <lb/>Microorganisms used in this study are listed and described in table S1. Microorganisms were streaked <lb/>onto yeast-peptone dextrose (YPD; 1% yeast extract (Becton Dickinson, and Company, Franklin Lakes, <lb/>NJ, USA), 2% peptone (Becton Dickinson, and Company, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA), and 2% dextrose <lb/>(Avantor Performance Materials, Center Valley, PA, USA)) or Man, de Rosa, Sharpe (MRS, Fisher <lb/>Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) plates from a freezer stock. <lb/>T-maze olfactory attraction assays <lb/>The T-maze apparatus was a kind gift of the Carlson Laboratory. Flies were wet-starved for 15-26 hours <lb/>prior to T-maze olfactory experiments by placing flies into vials containing Kimwipes (Kimberly Clark, <lb/>Dallas, TX, USA) soaked with 2 mL of milliQ water. Flies were collected within 4 days (&lt;65 flies per vial) <lb/>of emergence and matured on autoclaved food. Flies between 3 and 10 days-old were used in <lb/>experiments. <lb/>Single microbial colonies were picked from rich media (MRS and YPD) plates and grown overnight. <lb/>Cultures were washed 1X in PBS, diluted 100-fold, and 10µl was aliquoted into 3mL of apple juice media <lb/>(AJM, apple juice (Martinelli&apos;s Gold Medal, Watsonville, CA, USA), pH adjusted to 5.3 with 5M NaOH, with <lb/>0.5% yeast extract). Media was filtered with a 0.22 µM-size pore attached to a 250-mL polystyrene bottle <lb/>(Corning, NY, USA). For co-culture experiments, 1e3-1e5 CFU of each microorganism was placed <lb/>simultaneously into AJM. Microorganisms were grown in 14-mL round bottom polypropylene tubes <lb/>(Corning Science, Tamaulipas, Mexico) at 28°C, 200rpm for the time noted in individual experiments. The <lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>microbial culture was diluted 1:1 with sterile milliQ water (0.22 µM filter (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA)) <lb/>and placed directly onto autoclaved 10 mM round Whatman filter paper (GE Healthcare Life Science, <lb/>Pittsburgh, PA, USA) placed near the bottom of 15mL CentriStar centrifuge tubes (Corning, NY). A total <lb/>volume of 10 µl was used for all experiments. <lb/>Tubes containing microorganisms and Drosophila were placed into the behavioral room (20-25°C, 50-<lb/>70% humidity maintained by a humidifier (Sunbeam Tower Humidifier, Boca Raton, FL, USA) and <lb/>equilibrated for 10 minutes prior to the beginning of the experiment. Flies (~40-130) were knocked into the <lb/>T-maze apparatus, rested for ~1 min, and then allowed to choose from the test and control arms for 2 min <lb/>in the dark. The test arm was alternated from one side of the apparatus to the other every experimental <lb/>replicate. A Response Index (RI) was computed to analyze preference for the test arm (flies in test arm-<lb/>flies in control arm)/(total flies). <lb/>Chemicals <lb/>Chemicals can be found in Methods table 2. <lb/>Microbial populations and pH <lb/>Selective plates were used to distinguish S. cerevisiae from A. malorum. MRS containing 50 µg/mL <lb/>cycloheximide selected for A. malorum while MRS containing 10 µg/mL chloramphenicol and 20 µg/mL <lb/>tetracycline selected for S. cerevisiae. pH of filtered cultures (0.22 µM) was measured using a Beckman <lb/>Coulter pH meter (Model Phi510, Fullerton, CA, USA). <lb/>Gas chromatography-Mass spectrometry <lb/>Microbial samples were grown in AJM for a specified amount of time in 14-mL round bottom tubes fitted <lb/>with an autoclaved tissue strainer (250 µM nylon mesh (Thermo Scientific Pierce, Grand Island, NY) <lb/>holding between 0.03 and 0.05 grams of autoclaved Amberlite XAD-4 resin (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, <lb/>USA) prewashed in water and methanol. After microbial growth, XAD-4 from two cultures was dumped <lb/></body>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>into an autoclaved glass vial. XAD-4 was swirled with 900µl methanol for 30 seconds. 500-750µl of <lb/>methanol was removed for GC-MS analysis. Quantification for table S2 was derived from beads <lb/>suspended above the cultures from 84-96 h of growth. Quantification for Fig. 2D was derived from beads <lb/>suspended above the culture every 12 h; time points on the graph refer to the end point of the 12-h span <lb/>(e.g. 84 h corresponds to beads suspended from 72-84 h of growth). <lb/>Samples (5 µl of methanol-extracted samples) were injected into the GC-MS (Agilent 7890A/5975C) at <lb/>250 °C using helium as the carrier gas at a flow rate of 1.1 mL per minute (column head pressure 13 psi). <lb/>The following chromatography temperature program was used for experiments to initially identify <lb/>metabolites in the co-culture and individually grown microorganisms: 40°C for 3 min ramped at 1.7°C per <lb/>minute to 200 °C (held for 3 min) then to 220°C at 3 °C per min and held for a further 5 min. The total run <lb/>time was 111.78 min. For experiments focused on the five major metabolites, a shorter program was used <lb/>that maintained the same first 10 min of the previous method (all 5 volatiles eluted within 9 min). The <lb/>chromatography temperature program was 40°C for 3 min, ramped at 1.7°C per min to 46.8°C and held <lb/>for 3 min, then ramped at 60°C per min until 220°C and held for 5 min. The total run time was 17.9 min. <lb/>The mass spectrometer was run in electron-impact (EI) mode at 70 eV. The temperatures of the transfer <lb/>line, quadrupole, and ionization source were 220°C, 180°C, and 230°C respectively. The ionization was <lb/>off during the first 4 min to avoid solvent overloading with a source temperature of 230°C. Mass spectra <lb/>were recorded in the range of 35-300 m/z. Full scan mode was used at a scan rate of 6 scans/sec. The <lb/>electron multiplier voltage was set in the relative mode to autotune procedure. <lb/>In the initial experiments peaks were manually picked using Agilent Chemstation Software. Volatiles <lb/>associated with peaks were searched against the National Institute of Standards (NIST) 11 database. <lb/>Subsequent experiments focused on the 5 major volatiles identified in the initial experiments by <lb/>performing extracted ion chromatograms using an ion that successfully identified a standard at a specific <lb/>retention time. Quantification was performed by tabulating the maximum abundance of the ion at a <lb/></body>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<body>characteristic retention time and using a linear regression equation from a dose-response of the <lb/>standards (fig. S6). <lb/>Headspace solid phase microextraction (SPME) Gas chromatography-Mass spectrometry <lb/>A Waters GCT Premier gas chromatography time of flight mass spectrometer (Milford, MA) with a DB-<lb/>5MS column (30m x 0.25 mm ID x 0.25 μm film thickness; Agilent) was used. Live cultures were <lb/>transferred to autoclaved glass vials (20 mL, 23 X 75 mm, Supelco, Bellefonte, PA, USA) with screw caps <lb/>(18mm, 35 Shore A, Supelco, Bellefonte, PA, USA) after growing for 72 h. <lb/>The glass vials containing live microbial cultures were analyzed via a 50/30μm <lb/>carboxen/divinylbenzene/polydimethylsiloxane Stableflex solid-phase micro-extraction (SPME) fiber. The <lb/>extraction methodology was based on previous studies using SPME to extract volatiles form vinegars (65, <lb/>66). The syringe was inserted through the membrane of the caps and sampled the volatiles for 30 min at <lb/>45°C; subsequently, metabolites were desorbed for 30 sec at 240C and baked for an additional 4.5 min in <lb/>the injection port. The gas chromatograph was fitted with a microchannel plate (MCP) detector. The <lb/>temperature program of the column was as follows: 40°C for 5 min, 2°C a min for 17.5 min followed by <lb/>25°C a min for 10 min. A final hold time of 5 min at 325°C was used. The carrier gas was helium. A split <lb/>ratio of 250 was used based on better peak resolution. An internal standard of cineole (Sigma-Aldrich, St. <lb/>Louis, MO, USA) was run with each sample and used to compute relative abundances. The mass <lb/>detector was in the range of 40 to 650 m/z. <lb/>To analyze the data, MassLynx software was used. The response threshold was set to an absolute area <lb/>of 10.00. The software automatically picked out peaks and computed peak areas. To obtain a relative <lb/>quantification, peaks were compared across samples and normalized to the internal standard. Peaks <lb/>were first searched against the NIST5 database to identify potential hits. Most potential metabolites were <lb/>confirmed by a standard mixture in 50% AJM. The standard mixtures are in Methods Table 3. <lb/></body>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<body>Chemical complementation of co-culture containing A. pomorum PQQ-ADH-I <lb/>A co-culture containing S. cerevisiae and A. pomorum WT or A. pomorum PQQ-ADH-I was grown for 72 <lb/>h before use in the T-maze. For the physiological concentrations of acetate-derived metabolites, <lb/>concentrations were added as in table S3 and then mixed 1:1 with water prior to behavioral analysis. For <lb/>the acetaldehyde metabolic derivatives chemical complementation group, a 1:1 mixture of the mutant co-<lb/>culture: water was supplemented with 1,1-diethoxyethane, 2,3-butanedione, and acetoin at final <lb/>concentrations of 0.01%, 0.15% and 0.15%, respectively and used immediately in the T-maze. Acetic <lb/>acid and/or acetaldehyde were added to the culture, allowed to sit at RT for 35 min, mixed 1:1 with water <lb/>and then placed into the T-maze vials. <lb/>Standard curves were used to calculate the concentrations of individual metabolites (fig. S10). The <lb/>standard curves were generated on 2 separate experiments in which 3 concentrations of each standard <lb/>was used. The concentrations of the metabolites were independently calculated from the standard curve <lb/>equations generated on the two separate days. Estimated concentrations from each standard curve <lb/>equation were averaged (table S3). The experimental data is based on the peak areas of the <lb/>S.cerevisiae-A. malorum co-culture. <lb/>Ester, acid, and acetaldehyde metabolic derivative mixture <lb/>The 9-metabolite mixture contains 1.5% acetic acid, 0.0003% isoamyl acetate, 0.0003% 2-phenethyl <lb/>acetate, 0.01% ethyl acetate, 0.002% ethyl lactate, 0.3% 1,1-diethoxyethane, 0.3% 2,3-butanediol, 0.3% <lb/>2,3-butanedione, and 0.3% acetoin in filtered milliQ water. <lb/>Drosophila survival in the presence of ethanol and acetic acid <lb/>Adult male flies (0-3 d-old) were collected and matured for 1 day on fly food. Flies were then placed into <lb/>vials containing kimwipes with 5 mL of either Shields &amp; Sang Insect Medium (Sigma, St. Louis, MO; <lb/>positive control), MilliQ water (negative control), or MilliQ water with ethanol (9.4%), acetic acid (3.42%), <lb/>or ethanol and acetic acid (1.4 and 2.8% respectively). Survival was assessed every 12 h for 7 d. For <lb/></body>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<body>each condition 5 mL was given at 0 and 12 h and every 24 h thereafter. Experimental replicates were <lb/>considered separate vials (5-6 per group). Each replicate contained 8-31 flies. <lb/>Egg-laying preference assay <lb/>Egg-preference assay was adapted from Joseph et al 2009 (67). Microbial cultures grown for 96 h were <lb/>heated to 65°C for 10 min, mixed 1:1 with 1.6% agarose and poured into a 35 mm petri dish separated in <lb/>two by a straight-edge razor blade. Flies were starved for ~18 h prior to the experiment. The 35 mm petri <lb/>dish was placed within clear flat top boxes with dimensions 2 5/16&quot; X 2 5/16&quot; X 5 1/16&quot; (TAP plastics, San <lb/>Leandro, CA, USA). The test and control sides were alternated for each replicate. Drosophila aged 4-10 <lb/>days (n=50-100) was allowed to lay eggs for 8 h. After the assay, the number of eggs on deposited on <lb/>each choice was tabulated and an egg-laying index was computed analogously to the olfactory response <lb/>index. <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>Data analysis was performed in Prismv6.0b. Specific statistical tests are noted for individual experiments. <lb/></body>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<body>Chemical <lb/>Company <lb/>Location <lb/>Paraffin Oil <lb/>EMD chemicals <lb/>Gibbstown, NJ, USA <lb/>Apple Cider Vinegar <lb/>Heinz <lb/>Pittsburgh, PA, USA <lb/>Apple <lb/>Cider <lb/>Vinegar <lb/>(unpasteurized) <lb/>Bragg (Fig. 3C only) <lb/>Santa Barbara, CA, USA <lb/>Apple Cider Vinegar <lb/>Pastorelli (Fig. 3C only) <lb/>Chicago, IL, USA <lb/>Benzaldehyde <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>2-Methyl-1-Propanol (Isobutanol) <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Isopentyl Acetate (Isoamyl Acetate) <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/> Methods Table 1. Drosophila melanogaster stocks used in experiments <lb/>Notation <lb/>Gene <lb/>Mutant <lb/>Genotype <lb/>Source <lb/>CS <lb/>NA <lb/>w+-Canton-S <lb/>John Carlson Laboratory <lb/>Or83b <lb/>Or83b <lb/>w-Canton-S;;orco2 <lb/>John Carlson Laboratory <lb/>Ir64a <lb/>Ir64a <lb/>w[1118]; Mi{ET1}Ir64a[MB05283] <lb/>Bloomington Stock Center <lb/>Ir75a <lb/>Ir75a <lb/>y[1] w[67c23]; Mi{ET1}Ir75a[MB00253] <lb/>Bloomington Stock Center <lb/>W-CS <lb/>NA <lb/>w-Canton-S <lb/>John Carlson Laboratory <lb/>Balancer NA <lb/>w-CS;Sp/Cyo;Dr/TM3B <lb/>John Carlson Laboratory <lb/>Ir25a <lb/>Ir25a <lb/>w <lb/>1118 ; Mi{ET1}Ir25a <lb/>MB09568 <lb/>Bloomington Stock Center <lb/>Ir8a <lb/>Ir8a <lb/>Ir8a <lb/>1 ; Bl <lb/>1 L <lb/>2 /CyO <lb/>Bloomington Stock Center <lb/>Ir76b <lb/>Ir76b <lb/>y1 w67c23; Mi{ET1}Ir76bMB00216 <lb/>Bloomington Stock Center <lb/>Or42b <lb/>Or42b <lb/>w; or42b/or42b; +/+ <lb/>John Carlson Laboratory <lb/>Or35a <lb/>Or35a <lb/>W; or35a/or35a; +/+ <lb/>John Carlson Laboratory <lb/></body>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<body>Isoamyl Alcohol <lb/>Avantor Performance Materials <lb/>Center Valley, PA, USA <lb/>Acetic Acid, glacial <lb/>Avantor Performance Materials <lb/>Center Valley, PA, USA <lb/>Methanol <lb/>Avantor Performance Materials <lb/>Center Valley, PA, USA <lb/>Ethanol, 200 proof <lb/>Decon Laboratories <lb/>King of Prussia, PA, USA <lb/>Acetal (1,1, diethoxyethane) <lb/>Fisher <lb/>Pittsburgh, PA, USA <lb/>Acetaldehyde <lb/>Acros Organics <lb/>Grand Island, NY <lb/>Ethyl acetate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>1-pentanol <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Benzeneethanol (2-phenylethanol) <lb/>Fisher <lb/>Pittsburgh, PA, USA <lb/>Isobutyl acetate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>2-phenethyl acetate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Butyl acetate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>2-methylbutyl acetate <lb/>TCI <lb/>Tokyo, Japan <lb/>Methyl acetate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Acetoin acetate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Phenethyl formate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Phenethyl benzoate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>acetoin <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>2,3-butanedione <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>2-methyl-1-butanol <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Ethyl lactate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>1-hexanol <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Phenylacetic acid <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>2,3-butanediol <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Ethyl octanoate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Ethyl decanoate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/></body>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Ethyl hexanoate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Ethyl laurate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Ethyl isobutyrate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>phenylacetaldehyde <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/>Butyl isovalerate <lb/>TCI <lb/>Tokyo, Japan <lb/>Propyl acetate <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA <lb/> 1107 <lb/> Methods Table 3. Metabolite mixture concentrations used for identification and quantification in SPME GC-<lb/>MS <lb/>Metabolite <lb/>Met mix 1 <lb/>Met mix 2 <lb/>Met mix 3 <lb/>Ethanol <lb/>0.20% <lb/>1.00% <lb/>2.00% <lb/>Isobutanol <lb/>0.0040% <lb/>0.0010% <lb/>0.000250% <lb/>Acetic acid <lb/>2.80% <lb/>4.320% <lb/>1.920% <lb/>Isoamyl alcohol <lb/>0.00150% <lb/>0.0030% <lb/>0.0060% <lb/>Isoamyl acetate (1-butanol, 3-methyl acetate) <lb/>0.00050% <lb/>0.000167% <lb/>0.00150% <lb/>Acetal (1,1-Diethoxyethane) <lb/>0.020% <lb/>0.10% <lb/>0.0050% <lb/>Acetaldehyde <lb/>0.020% <lb/>NONE <lb/>0.0040% <lb/>Ethyl acetate <lb/>0.0050% <lb/>0.10% <lb/>0.020% <lb/>Benzeneethanol (2-phenylethanol) <lb/>0.00360% <lb/>0.00040% <lb/>0.00120% <lb/>Isobutyl acetate <lb/>0.000260% <lb/>0.0000867% 0.0000289% <lb/>2-Phenethyl acetate <lb/>0.000260% <lb/>0.0000867% 0.0000289% <lb/>2-Methylbutyl acetate (1-butanol 2-methyl acetate) <lb/>0.0010% <lb/>0.00033% <lb/>0.00011% <lb/>Methyl acetate <lb/>0.0000867% 0.0000289% 0.000260% <lb/>2-Methyl, 1-butanol <lb/>0.00030% <lb/>0.00150% <lb/>0.00450% <lb/>2,3-Butanedione <lb/>NONE <lb/>0.010% <lb/>0.0020% <lb/>Acetoin (1g/10mL h20, 10%) <lb/>0.01% <lb/>0.020% <lb/>0.040% <lb/></body>

			<page>50 <lb/></page>

			<body>2,3-Butanediol <lb/>NONE <lb/>0.10% <lb/>0.020% <lb/>Propyl acetate <lb/>0.000020% <lb/>0.0000020% NONE* <lb/>*1/2 experiments had a concentration of 0.0000 <lb/>1108 <lb/></body>

			<page>51 <lb/></page>

			<body>Methods Table 4. Composition of metabolite mixtures 1-21 used in figure S14 <lb/>1109 <lb/>Volatile <lb/>Metabolite mixture <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>14 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>19 <lb/>20 <lb/>21 <lb/>Ethanol <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.2850 <lb/>0.2850 <lb/>0.2850 <lb/>0.2850 <lb/>0.2850 <lb/>0.2850 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>0.5700 <lb/>Isobutanol <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>None <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>Acetic acid <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>1.4400 <lb/>Isoamyl alcohol <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>Isoamyl acetate <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>1,1-diethoxyethane <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0300 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>None <lb/>0.0033 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0200 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0300 <lb/>0.0500 <lb/>0.0500 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>acetaldehyde <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>ethyl acetate <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>1-pentanol <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>benzeneethanol <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>isobutyl acetate <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>2-phenethyl acetate <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>butyl acetate <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>2-methylbutyl acetate <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>methyl acetate <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>2-acetoxy-3-butanone <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>phenethyl formate <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>phenethyl benzoate <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>2-methy, 1-butanol <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>2,3butanedione <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0500 <lb/>0.1500 <lb/>acetion (10% m/v, H20) <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0030 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.0500 <lb/>0.150 <lb/> propyl acetate <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>ethyl isobutyrate <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>ethyl hexanoate <lb/> None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>isovaleric acid, butyl ester <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>ethyl octanoate <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/> ethyl decanoate <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>ethyl laurate <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>The percent composition (v/v) of the metabolite mixtures used in fig. S1 <lb/>1110 <lb/></body>

			<page>52 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Mcfall-Ngai M, Hadfield MG, Bosch TCG, Carey HV, Domazet-Loso T, Douglas AE, Dubilier <lb/>N, Eberl G, Fukami T, Gilbert SF, Hentschel U, King N, Kjelleberg S, Knoll AH, Kremer N, <lb/>Mazmanian SK, Metcalf JL, Nealson K, Pierce NE, Rawls JF, Reid A, Ruby EG, Rumpho M, <lb/>Sanders JG, Tautz D, Wernegreen JJ. 2013. Animals in a bacterial world, a new imperative for <lb/>the life sciences. PNAS 110:3229-3236. <lb/>2. <lb/>van Nood E, Vrieze A, Nieuwdorp M, Fuentes S, Zoetendal EG, de Vos WM, Visser CE, <lb/>Kuijper EJ, Bartelsman JFWM, Tijssen JGP, Speelman P, Dijkgraaf MGW, Keller JJ. 2013. <lb/>Duodenal infusion of donor feces for recurrent Clostridium difficile. N Engl J Med 368:407-415. <lb/>3. <lb/>Zhu L, Wu Q, Dai J, Zhang S, Wei F. 2011. Evidence of cellulose metabolism by the giant panda <lb/>gut microbiome. PNAS 108:17714-17719. <lb/>4. <lb/>Degnan PH, Taga ME, Goodman AL. 2014. Vitamin B12 as a modulator of gut microbial ecology. <lb/>Cell Metab 20:769-778. <lb/>5. <lb/>Bravo JA, Forsythe P, Chew MV, Escaravage E, Savignac HM, Dinan TG, Bienenstock J, <lb/>Cryan JF. 2011. Ingestion of Lactobacillus strain regulates emotional behavior and central GABA <lb/>receptor expression in a mouse via the vagus nerve. PNAS 108:16050-16055. <lb/>6. <lb/>Rath CM, Dorrestein PC. 2012. The bacterial chemical repertoire mediates metabolic exchange <lb/>within gut microbiomes. Curr Opin Microbiol 15:147-154. <lb/>7. <lb/>Manor O, Levy R, Borenstein E. 2014. Mapping the inner workings of the microbiome: genomic-<lb/>and metagenomic-based study of metabolism and metabolic interactions in the human <lb/>microbiome. Cell Metab 20:742-752. <lb/>8. <lb/>Gerber GK. 2014. The dynamic microbiome. FEBS Letters 588:4131-4139. <lb/>9. <lb/>Gonzalez A, King A, Robeson MS, Song S, Shade A, Metcalf JL, Knight R. 2012. <lb/>Characterizing microbial communities through space and time. Current Opinion in Biotechnology <lb/>23:431-436. <lb/>10. <lb/>Derewacz DK, Covington BC, McLean JA, Bachmann BO. 2015. Mapping microbial response <lb/>metabolomes for induced natural product discovery. ACS chemical biology 10:1998-2006. <lb/>11. <lb/>Goh E-B, Yim G, Tsui W, McClure J, Surette MG, Davies J. 2002. Transcriptional modulation of <lb/>bacterial gene expression by subinhibitory concentrations of antibiotics. PNAS 99:17025-17030. <lb/>12. <lb/>Ridaura VK, Faith JJ, Rey FE, Cheng J, Duncan AE, Kau AL, Griffin NW, Lombard V, <lb/>Henrissat B, Bain JR, Muehlbauer MJ, Ilkayeva O, Semenkovich CF, Funai K, Hayashi DK, <lb/>Lyle BJ, Martini MC, Ursell LK, Clemente JC, Van Treuren W, Walters WA, Knight R, <lb/>Newgard CB, Heath AC, Gordon JI. 2013. Gut microbiota from twins discordant for obesity <lb/>modulate metabolism in mice. Science 341:1241214. <lb/>13. <lb/>Costello EK, Lauber CL, Hamady M, Fierer N, Gordon JI, Knight R. 2009. Bacterial community <lb/>variation in human body habitats across space and time. Science 326:1694-1697. <lb/>14. <lb/>Ivanov II, Atarashi K, Manel N, Brodie EL, Shima T, Karaoz U, Wei D, Goldfarb KC, Santee <lb/>CA, Lynch SV, Tanoue T, Imaoka A, Itoh K, Takeda K, Umesaki Y, Honda K, Littman DR. <lb/>2009. Induction of intestinal Th17 cells by segmented filamentous bacteria. Cell 139:485-498. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>53 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>15. <lb/>Poulsen M, Hu H, Li C, Chen Z, Xu L, Otani S, Nygaard S, Nobre T, Klaubauf S, Schindler <lb/>PM, Hauser F, Pan H, Yang Z, Sonnenberg ASM, de Beer ZW, Zhang Y, Wingfield MJ, <lb/>Grimmelikhuijzen CJP, de Vries RP, Korb J, Aanen DK, Wang J, Boomsma JJ, Zhang G. <lb/>2014. Complementary symbiont contributions to plant decomposition in a fungus-farming termite. <lb/>PNAS 111:14500-14505. <lb/>16. <lb/>Rakoff-Nahoum S, Coyne MJ, Comstock LE. 2014. An ecological network of polysaccharide <lb/>utilization among human intestinal symbionts. Current Biology 24:40-49. <lb/>17. <lb/>Rakoff-Nahoum S, Foster KR, Comstock LE. 2016. The evolution of cooperation within the gut <lb/>microbiota. Nature 533:255-259. <lb/>18. <lb/>Fraune S, Anton-Erxleben F, Augustin R, Franzenburg S, Knop M, Schröder K, Willoweit-<lb/>Ohl D, Bosch TC. 2015. Bacteria-bacteria interactions within the microbiota of the ancestral <lb/>metazoan Hydra contribute to fungal resistance. ISME J 9:1543-1556. <lb/>19. <lb/>Chandler JA, Lang JM, Bhatnagar S, Eisen JA, Kopp A. 2011. Bacterial communities of diverse <lb/>Drosophila species: ecological context of a host-microbe model system. PLoS Genet 7:e1002272. <lb/>20. <lb/>Chandler JA, Eisen JA, Kopp A. 2012. Yeast communities of diverse Drosophila species: <lb/>comparison of two symbiont groups in the same hosts. Applied and Environmental Microbiology <lb/>78:7327-7336. <lb/>21. <lb/>Broderick NA, Lemaitre B. 2012. Gut-associated microbes of Drosophila melanogaster. Gut <lb/>Microbes 3:307-321. <lb/>22. <lb/>Camargo R, Phaff HJ. 1957. Yeasts occurring in Drosophila flies and in fermenting tomato fruits <lb/>in northern California. J Food Science 22:367-372. <lb/>23. <lb/>Barata A, Malfeito-Ferreira M, Loureiro V. 2012. The microbial ecology of wine grape berries. Int <lb/>J Food Microbiol 153:243-259. <lb/>24. <lb/>Erkosar B, Storelli G, Defaye A, Leulier F. 2013. Host-intestinal microbiota mutualism: &quot;learning <lb/>on the fly&quot;. Cell Host &amp; Microbe 13:8-14. <lb/>25. <lb/>Blum JE, Fischer CN, Miles J, Handelsman J. 2013. Frequent replenishment sustains the <lb/>beneficial microbiome of Drosophila melanogaster. MBio 4:e00860-13. <lb/>26. <lb/>Broderick NA, Buchon N, Lemaitre B. 2014. Microbiota-induced changes in Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster host gene expression and gut morphology. MBio 5:e01117-14. <lb/>27. <lb/>Becher PG, Flick G, Rozpędowska E, Schmidt A, Hagman A, Lebreton S, Larsson MC, <lb/>Hansson BS, Piškur J, Witzgall P, Bengtsson M. 2012. Yeast, not fruit volatiles mediate <lb/>Drosophila melanogaster attraction, oviposition and development. Functional Ecology 26:822-828. <lb/>28. <lb/>Christiaens JF, Franco LM, Cools TL, De Meester L, Michiels J, Wenseleers T, Hassan BA, <lb/>Yaksi E, Verstrepen KJ. 2014. The fungal aroma gene ATF1 promotes dispersal of yeast cells <lb/>through insect vectors. Cell Rep 9:425-432. <lb/>29. <lb/>Schiabor KM, Quan AS, Eisen MB. 2014. Saccharomyces cerevisiae mitochondria are required <lb/>for optimal attractiveness to Drosophila melanogaster. PLoS ONE 9:e113899. <lb/>30. <lb/>Palanca L, Gaskett AC, Günther CS, Newcomb RD, Goddard MR. 2013. Quantifying variation <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>54 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>in the ability of yeasts to attract Drosophila melanogaster. PLoS ONE 8:e75332. <lb/>31. <lb/>Venu I, Durisko Z, Xu J, Dukas R. 2014. Social attraction mediated by fruit flies&apos; microbiome. J <lb/>Exp Biol 217:1346-1352. <lb/>32. <lb/>Ai M, Min S, Grosjean Y, Leblanc C, Bell R, Benton R, Suh GSB. 2010. Acid sensing by the <lb/>Drosophila olfactory system. Nature 468:691-695. <lb/>33. <lb/>Wong CNA, Ng P, Douglas AE. 2011. Low-diversity bacterial community in the gut of the fruitfly <lb/>Drosophila melanogaster. Environ Microbiol 13:1889-1900. <lb/>34. <lb/>Shin SC, Kim S-H, You H, Kim B, Kim AC, Lee K-A, Yoon J-H, Ryu J-H, Lee W-J. 2011. <lb/>Drosophila microbiome modulates host developmental and metabolic homeostasis via insulin <lb/>signaling. Science 334:670-674. <lb/>35. <lb/>Storelli G, Defaye A, Erkosar B, Hols P, Royet J, Leulier F. 2011. Lactobacillus plantarum <lb/>promotes Drosophila systemic growth by modulating hormonal signals through TOR-dependent <lb/>nutrient sensing. Cell Metab 14:403-414. <lb/>36. <lb/>Buchon N, Broderick NA, Chakrabarti S, Lemaitre B. 2009. Invasive and indigenous microbiota <lb/>impact intestinal stem cell activity through multiple pathways in Drosophila. Genes Dev 23:2333-<lb/>2344. <lb/>37. <lb/>Newell PD, Douglas AE. 2014. Interspecies interactions determine the impact of the gut <lb/>microbiota on nutrient allocation in Drosophila melanogaster. Applied and Environmental <lb/>Microbiology 80:788-796. <lb/>38. <lb/>Wong AC-N, Dobson AJ, Douglas AE. 2014. Gut microbiota dictates the metabolic response of <lb/>Drosophila to diet. J Exp Biol 217:1894-1901. <lb/>39. <lb/>El-Zoghbi M. 1994. Biochemical changes in some tropical fruits during ripening. Food Chem <lb/>49:33-37. <lb/>40. <lb/>Abu-Goukh A-BA, Bashir HA. 2003. Changes in pectic enzymes and cellulase activity during <lb/>guava fruit ripening. Food Chem 83:213-218. <lb/>41. <lb/>Mao WW, Kinsella JE. 1981. Amylase activity in banana fruit: properties and changes in activity <lb/>with ripening. J Food Science 46:1400-1403. <lb/>42. <lb/>Barbe JC, De Revel G, Joyeux A, Bertrand A, Lonvaud-Funel A. 2001. Role of botrytized <lb/>grape micro-organisms in SO2 binding phenomena. J Appl Microbiol 90:34-42. <lb/>43. <lb/>Turner SL, Ray A. 2009. Modification of CO2 avoidance behaviour in Drosophila by inhibitory <lb/>odorants. Nature 461:277-281. <lb/>44. <lb/>Anagnostou C, Dorsch M, Rohlfs M. 2010. Influence of dietary yeasts on Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster life-history traits. Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata 136:1-11. <lb/>45. <lb/>Abuin L, Bargeton B, Ulbrich MH, Isacoff EY, Kellenberger S, Benton R. 2011. Functional <lb/>architecture of olfactory ionotropic glutamate receptors. Neuron 69:44-60. <lb/>46. <lb/>Hallem EA, Carlson JR. 2006. Coding of odors by a receptor repertoire. Cell 125:143-160. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>55 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>47. <lb/>Larsson MC, Domingos AI, Jones WD, Chiappe ME, Amrein H, Vosshall LB. 2004. Or83b <lb/>encodes a broadly expressed odorant receptor essential for Drosophila olfaction. Neuron 43:703-<lb/>714. <lb/>48. <lb/>Mathew D, Martelli C, Kelley-Swift E, Brusalis C, Gershow M, Samuel ADT, Emonet T, <lb/>Carlson JR. 2013. Functional diversity among sensory receptors in a Drosophila olfactory circuit. <lb/>PNAS 110:E2134-43. <lb/>49. <lb/>Asahina K, Louis M, Piccinotti S, Vosshall LB. 2009. A circuit supporting concentration-<lb/>invariant odor perception in Drosophila. Journal of Biology 8:1-19. <lb/>50. <lb/>Stökl J, Strutz A, Dafni A, Svatos A, Doubsky J, Knaden M, Sachse S, Hansson BS, <lb/>Stensmyr MC. 2010. A deceptive pollination system targeting Drosophilids through olfactory <lb/>mimicry of yeast. Current Biology 20:1846-1852. <lb/>51. <lb/>Semmelhack JL, Wang JW. 2009. Select Drosophila glomeruli mediate innate olfactory attraction <lb/>and aversion. Nature 459:218-223. <lb/>52. <lb/>Linda F Chuang EBC. 1968. Biosynthesis of diacetyl in bacteria and yeast. J Bacteriol 95:2083-<lb/>2089. <lb/>53. <lb/>Ruyters S, Mukherjee V, Verstrepen KJ, Thevelein JM, Willems KA, Lievens B. 2015. <lb/>Assessing the potential of wild yeasts for bioethanol production. J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol 42:39-<lb/>48. <lb/>54. <lb/>Ranganathan S, Davis DG, Hood RD. 1987. Developmental toxicity of ethanol in Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster. Teratology 36:45-49. <lb/>55. <lb/>Azanchi R, Kaun KR, Heberlein U. 2013. Competing dopamine neurons drive oviposition choice <lb/>for ethanol in Drosophila. PNAS 110:21153-21158. <lb/>56. <lb/>Kacsoh BZ, Lynch ZR, Mortimer NT, Schlenke TA. 2013. Fruit flies medicate offspring after <lb/>seeing parasites. Science 339:947-950. <lb/>57. <lb/>Lhocine N, Ribeiro PS, Buchon N, Wepf A, Wilson R, Tenev T, Lemaitre B, Gstaiger M, Meier <lb/>P, Leulier F. 2008. PIMS modulates immune tolerance by negatively regulating Drosophila innate <lb/>immune signaling. Cell Host &amp; Microbe 4:147-158. <lb/>58. <lb/>Ryu J-H, Kim S-H, Lee H-Y, Bai JY, Nam Y-D, Bae J-W, Lee DG, Shin SC, Ha E-M, Lee W-J. <lb/>2008. Innate immune homeostasis by the homeobox gene caudal and commensal-gut mutualism <lb/>in Drosophila. Science 319:777-782. <lb/>59. <lb/>Paredes JC, Welchman DP, Poidevin M, Lemaitre B. 2011. Negative regulation by amidase <lb/>PGRPs shapes the Drosophila antibacterial response and protects the fly from innocuous <lb/>infection. Immunity 35:770-779. <lb/>60. <lb/>Costechareyre D, Capo F, Fabre A, Chaduli D, Kellenberger C, Roussel A, Charroux B, <lb/>Royet J. 2016. Tissue-specific regulation of Drosophila NF-KB pathway activation by <lb/>peptidoglycan recognition protein SC. J Innate Immun 8:67-80. <lb/>61. <lb/>Broderick NA. 2016. Friend, foe or food? Recognition and the role of antimicrobial peptides in gut <lb/>immunity and Drosophila-microbe interactions. Philos Trans R Soc Lond, B, Biol Sci <lb/>371:20150295. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>56 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>62. <lb/>Piper MDW, Blanc E, Leitão-Gonçalves R, Yang M, He X, Linford NJ, Hoddinott MP, Hopfen <lb/>C, Soultoukis GA, Niemeyer C, Kerr F, Pletcher SD, Ribeiro C, Partridge L. 2014. A holidic <lb/>medium for Drosophila melanogaster. Nat Methods 11:100-105. <lb/>63. <lb/>Jarosz DF, Brown JCS, Walker GA, Datta MS, Ung WL, Lancaster AK, Rotem A, Chang A, <lb/>Newby GA, Weitz DA, Bisson LF, Lindquist S. 2014. Cross-kingdom chemical communication <lb/>drives a heritable, mutually beneficial prion-based transformation of metabolism. Cell 158:1083-<lb/>1093. <lb/>64. <lb/>Staubach F, Baines JF, Künzel S, Bik EM, Petrov DA. 2013. Host species and environmental <lb/>effects on bacterial communities associated with Drosophila in the laboratory and in the natural <lb/>environment. PLoS ONE 8:e70749. <lb/>65. <lb/>Callejón RM, González AG, Troncoso AM, Morales ML. 2008. Optimization and validation of <lb/>headspace sorptive extraction for the analysis of volatile compounds in wine vinegars. Journal of <lb/>Chromatography A 1204:93-103. <lb/>66. <lb/>Xiao Z, Dai S, Niu Y, Yu H, Zhu J, Tian H, Gu Y. 2011. Discrimination of chinese vinegars based <lb/>on headspace solid-phase microextraction-gas chromatography mass spectrometry of volatile <lb/>compounds and multivariate analysis. J Food Science 76:1125-1135. <lb/>67. <lb/>Joseph RM, Devineni AV, King IFG, Heberlein U. 2009. Oviposition preference for and <lb/>positional avoidance of acetic acid provide a model for competing behavioral drives in Drosophila. <lb/>PNAS 106:11352-11357. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
