<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:0705.4500v1 [hep-ex] 31 May 2007 <lb/>Determination of the ψ(3770), ψ(4040), ψ(4160) and ψ(4415) <lb/>resonance parameters <lb/> M. Ablikim 1 , J. Z. Bai 1 , Y. Ban 12 , X. Cai 1 , H. F. Chen 17 , H. S. Chen 1 , H. X. Chen 1 , <lb/>J. C. Chen 1 , Jin Chen 1 , Y. B. Chen 1 , Y. P. Chu 1 , Y. S. Dai 19 , L. Y. Diao 9 , Z. Y. Deng 1 , <lb/>Q. F. Dong 15 , S. X. Du 1 , J. Fang 1 , S. S. Fang 1a , C. D. Fu 15 , C. S. Gao 1 , Y. N. Gao 15 , S. D. Gu 1 , <lb/>Y. T. Gu 4 , Y. N. Guo 1 , Z. J. Guo 16b , F. A. Harris 16 , K. L. He 1 , M. He 13 , Y. K. Heng 1 , <lb/>J. Hou 11 , H. M. Hu 1 , J. H. Hu 3 T. Hu 1 , G. S. Huang 1c , X. T. Huang 13 , X. B. Ji 1 , X. S. Jiang 1 , <lb/>X. Y. Jiang 5 , J. B. Jiao 13 , D. P. Jin 1 , S. Jin 1 , Y. F. Lai 1 , G. Li 1d , H. B. Li 1 , J. Li 1 , R. Y. Li 1 , <lb/>S. M. Li 1 , W. D. Li 1 , W. G. Li 1 , X. L. Li 1 , X. N. Li 1 , X. Q. Li 11 , Y. F. Liang 14 , H. B. Liao 1 , <lb/>B. J. Liu 1 , C. X. Liu 1 , F. Liu 6 , Fang Liu 1 , H. H. Liu 1 , H. M. Liu 1 , J. Liu 12e , J. B. Liu 1 , <lb/>J. P. Liu 18 , Jian Liu 1 , Q. Liu 1 , R. G. Liu 1 , Z. A. Liu 1 , Y. C. Lou 5 , F. Lu 1 , G. R. Lu 5 , J. G. Lu 1 , <lb/>C. L. Luo 10 , F. C. Ma 9 , H. L. Ma 2 , L. L. Ma 1f , Q. M. Ma 1 , Z. P. Mao 1 , X. H. Mo 1 , J. Nie 1 , <lb/>S. L. Olsen 16 , R. G. Ping 1 , N. D. Qi 1 , H. Qin 1 , J. F. Qiu 1 , Z. Y. Ren 1 , G. Rong 1 , X. D. Ruan 4 , <lb/>L. Y. Shan 1 , L. Shang 1 , C. P. Shen 1 , D. L. Shen 1 , X. Y. Shen 1 , H. Y. Sheng 1 , H. S. Sun 1 , <lb/>S. S. Sun 1 , Y. Z. Sun 1 , Z. J. Sun 1 , X. Tang 1 , G. L. Tong 1 , G. S. Varner 16 , D. Y. Wang 1g , <lb/>L. Wang 1 , L. L. Wang 1 , L. S. Wang 1 , M. Wang 1 , P. Wang 1 , P. L. Wang 1 , W. F. Wang 1h , <lb/>Y. F. Wang 1 , Z. Wang 1 , Z. Y. Wang 1 , Zheng Wang 1 , C. L. Wei 1 , D. H. Wei 1 , Y. Weng 1 , <lb/>N. Wu 1 , X. M. Xia 1 , X. X. Xie 1 , G. F. Xu 1 , X. P. Xu 6 , Y. Xu 11 , M. L. Yan 17 , H. X. Yang 1 , <lb/>Y. X. Yang 3 , M. H. Ye 2 , Y. X. Ye 17 , G. W. Yu 1 , C. Z. Yuan 1 , Y. Yuan 1 , S. L. Zang 1 , Y. Zeng 7 , <lb/>B. X. Zhang 1 , B. Y. Zhang 1 , C. C. Zhang 1 , D. H. Zhang 1 , H. Q. Zhang 1 , H. Y. Zhang 1 , <lb/>J. W. Zhang 1 , J. Y. Zhang 1 , S. H. Zhang 1 , X. Y. Zhang 13 , Yiyun Zhang 14 , Z. X. Zhang 12 , <lb/>Z. P. Zhang 17 , D. X. Zhao 1 , J. W. Zhao 1 , M. G. Zhao 1 , P. P. Zhao 1 , W. R. Zhao 1 , Z. G. Zhao 1i , <lb/>H. Q. Zheng 12 , J. P. Zheng 1 , Z. P. Zheng 1 , L. Zhou 1 , K. J. Zhu 1 , Q. M. Zhu 1 , Y. C. Zhu 1 , <lb/>Y. S. Zhu 1 , Z. A. Zhu 1 , B. A. Zhuang 1 , X. A. Zhuang 1 , B. S. Zou 1 <lb/>(BES Collaboration) <lb/>1 Institute of High Energy Physics, Beijing 100049, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>2 China Center for Advanced Science and Technology(CCAST), Beijing 100080, People&apos;s Re-<lb/>public of China <lb/>3 Guangxi Normal University, Guilin 541004, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>4 Guangxi University, Nanning 530004, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>5 Henan Normal University, Xinxiang 453002, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>6 Huazhong Normal University, Wuhan 430079, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>7 Hunan University, Changsha 410082, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>8 Jinan University, Jinan 250022, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>9 Liaoning University, Shenyang 110036, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>10 Nanjing Normal University, Nanjing 210097, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>11 Nankai University, Tianjin 300071, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>12 Peking University, Beijing 100871, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>13 Shandong University, Jinan 250100, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>14 Sichuan University, Chengdu 610064, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>15 Tsinghua University, Beijing 100084, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>16 University of Hawaii, Honolulu, HI 96822, USA <lb/> 1 <lb/> 17 University of Science and Technology of China, Hefei 230026, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>18 Wuhan University, Wuhan 430072, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>19 Zhejiang University, Hangzhou 310028, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>a Current address: DESY, D-22607, Hamburg, Germany <lb/>b Current address: Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD 21218, USA <lb/>c Current address: University of Oklahoma, Norman, Oklahoma 73019, USA <lb/>d Current address: Universite Paris XI, LAL-Bat. 208-BP34, 91898 ORSAY Cedex, France <lb/>e Current address: Max-Plank-Institut fuer Physik, Foehringer Ring 6, 80805 Munich, Ger-<lb/>many <lb/>f Current address: University of Toronto, Toronto M5S 1A7, Canada <lb/>g Current address: CERN, CH-1211 Geneva 23, Switzerland <lb/>h Current address: Laboratoire de l&apos;Accélérateur Linéaire, Orsay, F-91898, France <lb/>i Current address: University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA <lb/>Abstract <lb/>R measurement data taken with the BESII detector at center-of-mass energies <lb/>between 3.7 and 5.0 GeV is fitted to determine resonance parameters (mass, total <lb/>width, electron width) of the high mass charmonium states, ψ(3770), ψ(4040), <lb/>ψ(4160) and ψ(4415). Various effects, including the relative phases between the <lb/>resonances, interferences, the energy-dependence of the full widths, and the initial <lb/>state radiative correction, are examined. The results are compared to previous <lb/>studies. <lb/></front>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The total cross section for hadron production in e + e − annihilation is usually parameterized in <lb/>terms of the ratio R, which is defined as R = σ(e + e − → hadrons)/σ(e + e − → µ + µ − ), where the <lb/>denominator is the lowest-order QED cross section, σ(e + e − → µ + µ − ) = σ 0 <lb/>µµ = 4πα 2 /3s. The <lb/>measured R values are consistent with the three-color quark model predictions. At the open <lb/>flavor thresholds where resonance structures show up, measurements of R value are used to <lb/>determine resonance parameters. For the high mass charmonium resonances, the ψ(3770) was <lb/>measured by MARK-I [1], DELCO [2], MARK-II [3] and BES [4][5]; the ψ(4040) and ψ(4160) <lb/>were measured by DASP [6]; and the ψ(4415) was measured by DASP [6] and MARK-I [7]. <lb/>There were also some other measurements of R values as reported in Refs. [8, 9, 10], but <lb/>no attempt was made to determine resonance parameters. The resonance parameters in the <lb/>Particle Data Group (PDG)&apos;s compilation remained unchanged for more than 20 years up <lb/>to the 2004 edition [11]. The resonance parameters for the three high mass resonances were <lb/>updated by PDG2006 [12], based on K. Seth&apos;s evaluation [13] using combined BESII [14] and <lb/>Crystal Ball [10] data. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>The most recent and precise R measurements between 2-5 GeV were made by BESII [14]. <lb/>Experimentally, R for both the continuum and the wide resonance region is given by <lb/>R exp = <lb/>N obs <lb/>had − N bg <lb/>σ 0 <lb/>µµ Lǫ trg ǫ had (1 + δ obs ) <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/>where N obs <lb/>had is the number of observed hadronic events, N bg is the number of the residual <lb/>background events, L is the integrated luminosity, (1 + δ obs ) is the effective correction factor <lb/>of the initial state radiation (ISR) [10][15], ǫ had is the detection efficiency for hadronic events <lb/>determined by the Monte Carlo simulation without bremsstrahlung being simulated, and ǫ trg is <lb/>the trigger efficiency. The determination of R values and resonance parameters are intertwined; <lb/>the factor (1 + δ obs ) in Eq. (1) contains contributions from the resonances and depends on the <lb/>resonance parameters. Therefore, the procedure to calculate (1 + δ obs ) requires a number of <lb/>iterations before stable results can be obtained. <lb/>In this work, we perform a global fit over the entire center-of-mass energy region from 3.7 <lb/>to 5.0 GeV covering the four resonances, ψ(3770), ψ(4040), ψ(4160) and ψ(4415), and include <lb/>interference effects among the resonances. We also adopt energy-dependent full widths, and <lb/>introduce relative phases between the resonances. Finally, the new R values due to the updated <lb/>resonant parameters are compared to the published ones [14]. <lb/>2 Fitting of the resonant parameters <lb/>The phenomenological models and formulas used in our fitting are briefly described below. <lb/>2.1 Breit-Wigner form <lb/>The relativistic Breit-Wigner amplitude for e + e − → resonance → final state f is <lb/>T f <lb/>r (W ) = <lb/>M r Γ ee <lb/>r Γ f <lb/>r <lb/>W 2 − M 2 <lb/>r + iM r Γ r <lb/>e iδr , <lb/>(2) <lb/>where W ≡ E cm ≡ <lb/>√ <lb/>s is the center-of-mass energy, the index r represents the resonance to <lb/>be studied, M r is the nominal mass, Γ r is the full width, Γ ee <lb/>r is the electron width, Γ f <lb/>r is the <lb/>hadronic width for the decaying channel f , and δ r is the phase. <lb/>The high mass charmonia decay into several two-body final states f . According to the <lb/>Eichten model [16] and experimental data [17], the decay channels (including their conjugate <lb/>states) are: <lb/>ψ(3770) ⇒ D D; <lb/>ψ(4040) ⇒ D D, D * D * , D D * , D s Ds ; <lb/>ψ(4140) ⇒ D D, D * D * , D D * , D s Ds , D s <lb/>D * <lb/>s ; <lb/>ψ(4415) ⇒ D D, D * D * , D D * , D s Ds , D s <lb/>D * <lb/>s , D * <lb/>s <lb/>D * <lb/>s , D D1 , D D * <lb/>2 . <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>The total squared inclusive amplitude of the resonances is the incoherent sum over all <lb/>different decay channels f , <lb/>|T res | 2 = <lb/>f <lb/>| <lb/>r <lb/>T f <lb/>r (W )| 2 . <lb/>(3) <lb/>The resonant cross section expressed as the R value is then given by <lb/>R res = <lb/>σ res <lb/>σ 0 <lb/>µµ <lb/>= <lb/>12π <lb/>s <lb/>|T res | 2 . <lb/>(4) <lb/>2.2 Energy-dependence of the full width <lb/>The full width of a broad resonance depends on the energy. A phenomenological model derived <lb/>from quantum mechanics is used to describe the behavior of Γ f <lb/>r (W ), which depends on the <lb/>momentum and the orbital angular momentum L of the decaying final state [18], <lb/>Γ f <lb/>r (W ) = Γr <lb/>2M r <lb/>M r + W L <lb/>Z 2L+1 <lb/>f <lb/>B L <lb/>, <lb/>(5) <lb/>where, Γr is a parameter to be determined by fitting experimental data, Z f ≡ ρP f , ρ is the <lb/>radius of the interaction with the order of a few fermis (the value is insensitive to the physical <lb/>results), P f is the decay momentum, and 2M r /(M r + W ) is a relativistic correction factor. <lb/>The energy-dependent partial wave functions B L are given in Ref. [18]: <lb/>B 0 = 1, B 1 = 1 + Z 2 , B 2 = 9 + 3Z 2 + Z 4 , <lb/>B 3 = 225 + 45Z 2 + 6Z 4 + Z 6 . <lb/>(6) <lb/>When the resonance decays to several hadronic channels, the total hadronic width is the <lb/>sum of all its partial widths, <lb/>Γ had <lb/>r (W ) = <lb/>f <lb/>Γ f <lb/>r (W ). <lb/>(7) <lb/>The total width of the resonance r is expressed as <lb/>Γ r (W ) = 3Γ ee <lb/>r + Γ had <lb/>r (W ), <lb/>(8) <lb/>where the universality of the leptons is used, i.e. Γ ee <lb/>r = Γ µµ <lb/>r = Γ τ τ <lb/>r , and Γ ee <lb/>r is the experimental <lb/>electron width, which includes the contribution from the vacuum polarization effect. <lb/>2.3 Continuum background <lb/>The contribution of continuum background originating from initial light quark pairs uū, d <lb/>d <lb/>and ss, which is written as R <lb/>(uds) <lb/>QCD , may be predicted by pQCD above 2 GeV[12]. Being close <lb/>to the production threshold, the continuum open-cc background can only be described by <lb/>phenomenological models or empirical expressions. Since there are many possible channels <lb/>above the open-charm threshold, and their cross sections are expected to vary smoothly, we <lb/>parametrize, for simplicity, the continuum charm background with a second order polynomial, <lb/>R (c) <lb/>con = C 0 + C 1 (W − 2M D ± ) + C 2 (W − 2M D ± ) 2 , <lb/>(9) <lb/>where C 0 , C 1 and C 2 are free parameters, and M D ± is the mass of the lightest meson D ± . <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.4 Fitting scheme <lb/>We fit the experimental data with MINUIT [19] using a least squares method, with χ 2 defined <lb/>as [20] <lb/>χ 2 = <lb/>i <lb/>[f c R exp (W i ) − R the (W i )] 2 <lb/>[f c ∆ R <lb/>(i) <lb/>exp ] 2 <lb/>+ <lb/>(f c − 1) 2 <lb/>σ 2 <lb/>c <lb/>, <lb/>(10) <lb/>where W i stands for the energy of the measured point. The experimental quantity <lb/>R exp = <lb/>N obs <lb/>had − N bg <lb/>σ 0 <lb/>µµ Lǫ trg ǫ had <lb/>, <lb/>(11) <lb/>and the corresponding theoretical quantity <lb/>R the = (1 + δ obs )R the , <lb/>(12) <lb/>where, <lb/>R the = R con + R res , <lb/>(13) <lb/>and <lb/>R con = R <lb/>(uds) <lb/>(QCD) + R (c) <lb/>con . <lb/>(14) <lb/>∆ R <lb/>(i) <lb/>exp in Eq. (10) is the combined statistical and uncommon systematic errors of R exp (W i ); <lb/>the error common to all the points σ c (∼ 3.3%) is not included. In each iteration, the resonant <lb/>parameters in the calculation of (1 + δ obs ) and R the are updated to new values. f c is a scale <lb/>factor which reflects the influence of the common error on the fitting. R <lb/>(uds) <lb/>(QCD) is derived from <lb/>pQCD [21]. <lb/>The free parameters in the fit are M r , Γ ee <lb/>r , δ r in Eq. (2), Γr in Eq.(5), and C 0 , C 1 , C 3 in <lb/>Eq. (9). Only relative values of the phases can be extracted, so for simplicity, the phase of <lb/>ψ(3770) is set to zero. <lb/>3 Results and discussion <lb/>The resonant parameters of the high mass charmonia determined in this work, together with <lb/>those in PDG2004, PDG2006 and the results given in Ref. [13] are listed in Table 1. The <lb/>updated R values between 3.7 and 5.0 GeV and the fit curves are illustrated in Fig. 1. The fit <lb/>yields χ 2 /d.o.f = 1.06, which indicates a reasonable fit. <lb/>In order to understand the uncertainty of the model-dependence, alternative choices and <lb/>combinations of Breit-Wigner forms, energy dependence of the full width predicted by quantum <lb/>mechanics model [18] or the effective interaction theory [22], and continuum charm background <lb/>described by a second order polynomial or the phenomenological form used by DASP [6] are <lb/>used. We find that the results are sensitive to the form of the energy dependent total width, but <lb/>not sensitive to the form of background. The DASP background function has six continuum <lb/>production channels, while the effective interaction theory predicts different energy-dependence <lb/>of the hadronic width for different decay channels. However in both cases the best fits give <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>unreasonable results. This may be understood as the inclusive data can not supply enough <lb/>information to determine the relative strength of different decay channels. To understand <lb/>the detailed structures and components of the high mass charmonia states, it is necessary to <lb/>collect data at each peak with sufficiently high statistics, and to develop more reliable physical <lb/>models. This is one of the physics tasks of a tau charm factory, and might be further studied <lb/>with BESIII that is under construction. <lb/>It is worth noting that the change of the resonance parameters affects the effective initial <lb/>state radiative correction factors, and thus affects the R values. Fig. 2 shows comparison <lb/>between the R values published in [14] and the updated values in this work; the difference <lb/>varies with the resonant structure. In general the relative difference is within 3%, and for a <lb/>few energy points the maximum difference is about 6%. Our results are in agreement with <lb/>the previous experiments in most cases, but large differences are observed in some of the <lb/>parameters, such as the mass of the ψ(4160). This is mainly due to the reconsideration of the <lb/>radiative correction factors, and the inclusion of interferences between the resonances. <lb/>Table 1: The resonance parameters of the high mass charmonia in this work together <lb/>with the values in PDG2004 [11], PDG2006 [12] and K. Seth&apos;s evaluations [13] based on <lb/>Crystal Ball and BES data. The total width Γ tot ≡ Γ r (M) in Eq.(8). <lb/>ψ(3770) <lb/>ψ(4040) <lb/>ψ(4160) <lb/>ψ(4415) <lb/>PDG2004 <lb/>3769.9±2.5 <lb/>4040±10 <lb/>4159±20 <lb/>4415±6 <lb/>PDG2006 <lb/>3771.1±2.4 4039±1.0 <lb/>4153±3 <lb/>4421±4 <lb/>M <lb/>CB (Seth) <lb/>-<lb/>4037±2 <lb/>4151±4 <lb/>4425±6 <lb/>(MeV/c 2 ) <lb/>BES (Seth) <lb/>-<lb/>4040±1 <lb/>4155±5 <lb/>4455±6 <lb/>BES (this work) 3771.4±1.8 4038.5±4.6 4191.6±6.0 4415.2±7.5 <lb/>PDG2004 <lb/>23.6±2.7 <lb/>52±10 <lb/>78±20 <lb/>43±15 <lb/>PDG2006 <lb/>23.0±2.7 <lb/>80±10 <lb/>103±8 <lb/>62±20 <lb/>Γ tot <lb/>CB (Seth) <lb/>-<lb/>85±10 <lb/>107±10 <lb/>119±16 <lb/>(MeV) <lb/>BES (Seth) <lb/>-<lb/>89±6 <lb/>107±16 <lb/>118±35 <lb/>BES (this work) 25.4±6.5 <lb/>81.2±14.4 72.7±15.1 73.3±21.2 <lb/>PDG2004 <lb/>0.26±0.04 0.75±0.15 0.77±0.23 0.47±0.10 <lb/>PDG2006 <lb/>0.24±0.03 0.86±0.08 0.83±0.07 0.58±0.07 <lb/>Γ ee <lb/>CB (Seth) <lb/>-<lb/>0.88±0.11 0.83±0.08 0.72±0.11 <lb/>(keV) <lb/>BES (Seth) <lb/>-<lb/>0.91±0.13 0.84±0.13 0.64±0.23 <lb/>BES (this work) 0.18±0.04 0.81±0.20 0.50±0.27 0.37±0.14 <lb/>δ (degree) BES (this work) <lb/>0 <lb/>133±68 <lb/>301±61 <lb/>246±86 <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.7 3.8 3.9 4.0 4.1 4.2 4.3 4.4 4.5 4.6 4.7 4.8 4.9 5.0 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>R exp <lb/>R the <lb/>R con <lb/>R int <lb/>R res <lb/>R BW <lb/>R <lb/>Ecm(GeV) <lb/>χ <lb/>2 /d.o.f=1.05 <lb/>Figure 1: The fit to the R values for the high mass charmonia structure. The dots <lb/>with error bars are the updated R values. The solid curve shows the best fit, and the <lb/>other curves show the contributions from each resonance R BW , the interference R int , the <lb/>summation of the four resonances R res = R BW + R int , and the continuum background <lb/>R con respectively. <lb/>3.7 3.8 3.9 4.0 4.1 4.2 4.3 4.4 4.5 4.6 4.7 4.8 4.9 5.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>R old <lb/>R now <lb/>R <lb/>Ecm(GeV) <lb/>3.7 3.8 3.9 4.0 4.1 4.2 4.3 4.4 4.5 4.6 4.7 4.8 4.9 5.0 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>∆R/R <lb/>old <lb/>Ecm(GeV) <lb/>∆R=R now -R old <lb/>(I) <lb/>(II) <lb/>Figure 2: (I) The comparison of R values between the values published in Ref. [14] <lb/>(triangles: R old ) and the updated values in this work (points: R now ). (II) The relative <lb/>differences between the two sets of R values. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">The BES collaboration thanks the staff of BEPC and computing center for their hard efforts. <lb/>This work is supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China un-<lb/>der contracts Nos. No.19991480, No.19805009, No.19825116, 10491300, 10225524, 10225525, <lb/>10425523, the Chinese Academy of Sciences under contract No. KJ 95T-03, the 100 Tal-<lb/>ents Program of CAS under Contract Nos. U-11, U-24, U-25, and the Knowledge Innovation <lb/>Project of CAS under Contract Nos. U-602, U-34 (IHEP), the National Natural Science Foun-<lb/>dation of China under Contract No. 10225522 (Tsinghua University), and the Department of <lb/>Energy under Contract No.DE-FG02-04ER41291 (U. Hawaii). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] MARK-I Collaboration, P. A. Rapidis et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 39 (1977) 526. <lb/>[2] DELCO Collaboration, W. Bacino et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 40 (1978) 671. <lb/>[3] MARK-II Collaboration, R. H. Schindler et al., Phys. Rev. D 21 (1980) 2716. <lb/>[4] BES Collaboration, M. Ablikim et al., hep-ex/0612056. <lb/>[5] BES Collaboration, M. Ablikim et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 97, (2006) 121801. <lb/>[6] DASP Collaboration, R. Brandelik et al., Phys. Lett. B 76 (1978) 361. <lb/>[7] J. Siegrist et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 36 (1976) 700. <lb/>[8] MARK-I Collaboration, J. Siegrist et al., Phys. Rev. D 26, (1982) 969. <lb/>[9] L. Criegee and G. Knies, Phys. Rept. 83, (1982) 151. <lb/>[10] Crystal Ball Collaboration, A. Osterfeld et al., Report No. SLAC-PUB-4160 (1986) (un-<lb/>published). <lb/>[11] Particle Data Group, S. Eidelman et al., Phys. Lett. B 592, (2004) 310. <lb/>[12] Particle Data Group, W.-M. Yao et al., J. Phys. G 33, (2006) 928. <lb/>[13] K. K. Seth, Phys. ReV. D 72 (2005) 017501. <lb/>[14] BES Collaboration, J. Z. Bai et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 88, (2002) 101802. <lb/>[15] H. M. Hu et al., High Energy Physics and Nuclear Physics, 25, (2001) 701 (in Chinese). <lb/>[16] E. Eichten et al., Phys. Rev. D 21, (1980) 203. <lb/>[17] T. Barnes et al., Phys. Rev. D 72, (2005) 054026. <lb/>[18] J. M. Blatt and V. F. Weisskopf, Theoretical Nuclear Physics, Wiley, New York, (1952) <lb/>361. <lb/>[19] CERN Program Library entry D 506. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[20] X. H. Mo and Y. S. Zhu, High Energy Physics and Nuclear Physics, 27, (2003) 747. <lb/>[21] S. G. Gorishnii et al., Phys. Lett. B 259, (1991) 144. <lb/>[22] Gao Chongshou, Group Theory and its applications in particle physics, Higher Education <lb/>Press, (1992) 282 (in Chinese). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
