<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:0706.2045v2 [hep-ex] 20 Aug 2007 <lb/>BELLE Preprint 2007-25 <lb/>KEK Preprint 2007-14 <lb/>BELLE <lb/>Measurement of Branching Fraction and Time-Dependent CP <lb/>Asymmetry Parameters in B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S Decays <lb/>J. Dalseno, 18 I. Adachi, 7 H. Aihara, 40 T. Aushev, 16, 11 A. M. Bakich, 36 V. Balagura, 11 <lb/>A. Bay, 16 U. Bitenc, 12 I. Bizjak, 12 A. Bozek, 24 M. Bračko, 7, 17, 12 T. E. Browder, 6 <lb/>Y. Chao, 23 A. Chen, 21 B. G. Cheon, 5 R. Chistov, 11 I.-S. Cho, 45 Y. Choi, 35 <lb/>Y. K. Choi, 35 M. Danilov, 11 M. Dash, 44 A. Drutskoy, 3 S. Eidelman, 1 A. Go, 21 H. Ha, 14 <lb/>K. Hayasaka, 19 M. Hazumi, 7 D. Heffernan, 29 T. Hokuue, 19 H. J. Hyun, 15 K. Inami, 19 <lb/>A. Ishikawa, 40 H. Ishino, 41 M. Iwasaki, 40 Y. Iwasaki, 7 N. J. Joshi, 37 D. H. Kah, 15 <lb/>J. H. Kang, 45 P. Kapusta, 24 N. Katayama, 7 H. Kawai, 2 T. Kawasaki, 26 H. Kichimi, 7 <lb/>H. J. Kim, 15 Y. J. Kim, 4 K. Kinoshita, 3 P. Križan, 46, 12 P. Krokovny, 7 R. Kumar, 30 <lb/>C. C. Kuo, 21 A. Kuzmin, 1 Y.-J. Kwon, 45 J. S. Lee, 35 S. E. Lee, 34 T. Lesiak, 24 J. Li, 6 <lb/>A. Limosani, 7 S.-W. Lin, 23 D. Liventsev, 11 F. Mandl, 9 T. Matsumoto, 42 S. McOnie, 36 <lb/>T. Medvedeva, 11 W. Mitaroff, 9 H. Miyake, 29 H. Miyata, 26 G. R. Moloney, 18 E. Nakano, 28 <lb/>M. Nakao, 7 S. Nishida, 7 O. Nitoh, 43 S. Ogawa, 38 T. Ohshima, 19 S. Okuno, 13 Y. Onuki, 32 <lb/>W. Ostrowicz, 24 H. Ozaki, 7 P. Pakhlov, 11 G. Pakhlova, 11 C. W. Park, 35 H. Park, 15 <lb/>K. S. Park, 35 R. Pestotnik, 12 L. E. Piilonen, 44 H. Sahoo, 6 Y. Sakai, 7 O. Schneider, 16 <lb/>J. Schümann, 7 R. Seidl, 8, 32 A. Sekiya, 20 K. Senyo, 19 M. E. Sevior, 18 M. Shapkin, 10 <lb/>H. Shibuya, 38 J. B. Singh, 30 A. Sokolov, 10 A. Somov, 3 S. Stanič, 27 M. Starič, 12 <lb/>H. Stoeck, 36 K. Sumisawa, 7 T. Sumiyoshi, 42 F. Takasaki, 7 M. Tanaka, 7 G. N. Taylor, 18 <lb/>Y. Teramoto, 28 X. C. Tian, 31 T. Tsukamoto, 7 S. Uehara, 7 K. Ueno, 23 T. Uglov, 11 <lb/>Y. Unno, 5 S. Uno, 7 P. Urquijo, 18 G. Varner, 6 S. Villa, 16 A. Vinokurova, 1 C. C. Wang, 23 <lb/>C. H. Wang, 22 Y. Watanabe, 41 R. Wedd, 18 E. Won, 14 B. D. Yabsley, 36 A. Yamaguchi, 39 <lb/>Y. Yamashita, 25 M. Yamauchi, 7 Z. P. Zhang, 33 V. Zhilich, 1 and A. Zupanc 12 <lb/>(The Belle Collaboration) <lb/>1 Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics, Novosibirsk <lb/>2 Chiba University, Chiba <lb/>3 University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio 45221 <lb/>4 The Graduate University for Advanced Studies, Hayama <lb/>5 Hanyang University, Seoul <lb/>6 University of Hawaii, Honolulu, Hawaii 96822 <lb/>7 High Energy Accelerator Research Organization (KEK), Tsukuba <lb/>Typeset by REVT E X <lb/></front>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>8 University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, Illinois 61801 <lb/>9 Institute of High Energy Physics, Vienna <lb/>10 Institute of High Energy Physics, Protvino <lb/>11 Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics, Moscow <lb/>12 J. Stefan Institute, Ljubljana <lb/>13 Kanagawa University, Yokohama <lb/>14 Korea University, Seoul <lb/>15 Kyungpook National University, Taegu <lb/>16 Swiss Federal Institute of Technology of Lausanne, EPFL, Lausanne <lb/>17 University of Maribor, Maribor <lb/>18 University of Melbourne, School of Physics, Victoria 3010 <lb/>19 Nagoya University, Nagoya <lb/>20 Nara Women&apos;s University, Nara <lb/>21 National Central University, Chung-li <lb/>22 National United University, Miao Li <lb/>23 Department of Physics, National Taiwan University, Taipei <lb/>24 H. Niewodniczanski Institute of Nuclear Physics, Krakow <lb/>25 Nippon Dental University, Niigata <lb/>26 Niigata University, Niigata <lb/>27 University of Nova Gorica, Nova Gorica <lb/>28 Osaka City University, Osaka <lb/>29 Osaka University, Osaka <lb/>30 Panjab University, Chandigarh <lb/>31 Peking University, Beijing <lb/>32 RIKEN BNL Research Center, Upton, New York 11973 <lb/>33 University of Science and Technology of China, Hefei <lb/>34 Seoul National University, Seoul <lb/>35 Sungkyunkwan University, Suwon <lb/>36 University of Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales <lb/>37 Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai <lb/>38 Toho University, Funabashi <lb/>39 Tohoku University, Sendai <lb/>40 Department of Physics, University of Tokyo, Tokyo <lb/>41 Tokyo Institute of Technology, Tokyo <lb/>42 Tokyo Metropolitan University, Tokyo <lb/>43 Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, Tokyo <lb/>44 Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia 24061 <lb/>45 Yonsei University, Seoul <lb/>46 University of Ljubljana, Ljubljana <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/> We present a measurement of the branching fraction and time-dependent CP violation param-<lb/>eters for B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S decays. These results are obtained from a 414 fb −1 data sample that <lb/>contains 449× 10 6 B B pairs collected at the Υ (4S) resonance with the Belle detector at the KEKB <lb/>asymmetric-energy e + e − collider. We obtain the branching fraction, <lb/>B (B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S ) = [3.4 ± 0.4 (stat) ± 0.7 (syst)] × 10 −3 , <lb/>which is in agreement with the current world average. We also obtain an upper limit on the product <lb/>branching fraction for a possible two-body decay, <lb/>B (B 0 → D + <lb/>s1 (2536)D * − )B (D + <lb/>s1 (2536) → D * + K 0 <lb/>S ) &lt; 7.1 × 10 −4 (90% CL). <lb/>In the traditional 2-parameter time-dependent CP analysis, we measure the CP violation param-<lb/>eters, <lb/>A CP = −0.01 +0.28 <lb/>−0.28 (stat) ± 0.09 (syst) <lb/>D sin 2φ 1 = 0.06 +0.45 <lb/>−0.44 (stat) ± 0.06 (syst). <lb/>No evidence for either mixing-induced or direct CP violation is found. In a 3-parameter fit sensitive <lb/>to cos 2φ 1 performed in the half-Dalitz spaces, s − ≤ s + and s − &gt; s + , where s ± ≡ m 2 (D * ± K 0 <lb/>S ), <lb/>we extract the CP violation parameters, <lb/>J c /J 0 = 0.60 +0.25 <lb/>−0.28 (stat) ± 0.08 (syst) <lb/>2J s1 /J 0 sin 2φ 1 = −0.17 +0.42 <lb/>−0.42 (stat) ± 0.09 (syst) <lb/>2J s2 /J 0 cos 2φ 1 = −0.23 +0.43 <lb/>−0.41 (stat) ± 0.13 (syst). <lb/>A large value of J c /J 0 would indicate a significant resonant contribution from a broad unknown <lb/>D * * + <lb/>s <lb/>state. Although the sign of the factor, 2J s2 /J 0 , can be deduced from theory, no conclusion <lb/>can be drawn regarding the sign of cos 2φ 1 given the errors. <lb/>PACS numbers: 11.30.Er, 12.15.Hh, 13.25.Hw <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>CP violation in the Standard Model is due to a complex phase in the Cabibbo-Kobayashi-<lb/>Maskawa (CKM) quark-mixing matrix [1, 2]. At present, CP violation has been clearly <lb/>observed by the BaBar [3] and Belle [4] collaborations in the decay B 0 → J/ψ K 0 <lb/>S , while <lb/>many other modes provide additional information on CP violating parameters. One such <lb/>decay is B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S , where sin 2φ 1 can, in principle, be extracted from the time-<lb/>dependent rate asymmetry [5], <lb/>Γ (t) − Γ (t) <lb/>Γ (t) + Γ (t) <lb/>= A CP cos (∆m d t) + D sin 2φ 1 sin (∆m d t). <lb/>(1) <lb/>Γ (t) is the decay rate for B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S at proper time, t, after production while Γ (t) <lb/>represents the charge conjugate rate. ∆m d is the mass difference between the two B 0 mass <lb/>eigenstates, A CP is the direct CP violating component and sin 2φ 1 measures mixing induced <lb/>CP violation. The factor, D, is the dilution of the CP asymmetry and may arise from two <lb/>sources. The contribution from different waves in the amplitude of B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>influences the CP mixture and polarization of the final state. Furthermore, if an inter-<lb/>mediate D * + K 0 <lb/>S resonance exists, additional dilution of the CP asymmetry occurs as the <lb/>decay becomes self-tagging. CP contamination from penguins and final state interactions <lb/>are expected to be small in this mode [5]. <lb/>If resonant structure were to exist, cos 2φ 1 may also be extracted, assuming no direct CP <lb/>violation, from the time-dependent rate asymmetry [5], <lb/>Γ (t) − Γ (t) <lb/>Γ (t) + Γ (t) <lb/>= η y <lb/>J c <lb/>J 0 <lb/>cos (∆m d t) − <lb/>2J s1 <lb/>J 0 <lb/>sin 2φ 1 + η y <lb/>2J s2 <lb/>J 0 <lb/>cos 2φ 1 sin (∆m d t), <lb/>(2) <lb/>in the half-Dalitz space, s − ≤ s + or s − &gt; s + . The Dalitz variables are defined as s ± ≡ <lb/>m 2 (D * ± K 0 <lb/>S ) and η y = +1 (−1) if s − ≤ s + (s − &gt; s + ). J c , J 0 , J s1 and J s2 are integrals over <lb/>the half-Dalitz space, s − &gt; s + , of |a| 2 + |ā| 2 , |a| 2 − |ā| 2 , the real component, ℜ (āa * ) and <lb/>the imaginary component, ℑ (āa * ), respectively, where a (ā) are the decay amplitudes of <lb/>B 0 ( B0 ) → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S . Note that J s2 is non-zero only if B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S has a resonant <lb/>component: in this case, J c may be large. <lb/>This measurement of the branching fraction and CP violating parameters in B 0 → <lb/>D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S is based on a 414 fb −1 data sample that contains 449 × 10 6 B B pairs, collected <lb/>with the Belle detector at the KEKB asymmetric-energy e + e − (3.5 on 8 GeV) collider [7]. <lb/>Operating with a peak luminosity that exceeds 1.6 × 10 34 cm −2 s −1 , the collider produces the <lb/>Υ (4S) resonance ( <lb/>√ s = 10.58 GeV) with a Lorentz boost of βγ = 0.425, opposite to the <lb/>positron beamline direction, z. Since the B 0 and B0 mesons are approximately at rest in the <lb/>Υ (4S) Center-of-Mass System (CMS), the difference in decay time between the B B pair, <lb/>∆t, can be determined from the displacement in z between the final state decay vertices, <lb/>∆t ≃ <lb/>(z CP − z Tag ) <lb/>βγc <lb/>≡ <lb/>∆z <lb/>βγc <lb/>. <lb/>(3) <lb/>The subscripts, CP and Tag, denote the reconstructed final state, B CP , and the final state <lb/>from which the flavor is identified, B Tag . The quantity, ∆t, can be substituted for t in (1) <lb/>and (2) due to coherent B B production at the Υ (4S) resonance [6]. <lb/>The Belle detector is a large-solid-angle magnetic spectrometer that consists of a silicon <lb/>vertex detector (SVD), a 50-layer central drift chamber (CDC), an array of aerogel threshold <lb/>Cherenkov counters (ACC), a barrel-like arrangement of time-of-flight scintillation counters <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>(TOF), and an electromagnetic calorimeter comprised of CsI (Tl) crystals (ECL) located <lb/>inside a superconducting solenoid coil that provides a 1.5 T magnetic field. An iron flux-<lb/>return located outside of the coil is instrumented to detect K 0 <lb/>L mesons and to identify muons <lb/>(KLM). The detector is described in detail elsewhere [8]. Two inner detector configurations <lb/>were used. A 2.0 cm beampipe and a 3-layer silicon vertex detector (SVD1) was used for <lb/>the first sample of 152 ×10 6 B B pairs, while a 1.5 cm beampipe, a 4-layer silicon detector <lb/>(SVD2) and a small-cell inner drift chamber was used to record the remaining 297 ×10 6 B <lb/>B <lb/>pairs [9]. <lb/>We reconstruct B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S from D * + → D 0 π + <lb/>slow and D + π 0 <lb/>slow requiring at <lb/>least one D 0 π + <lb/>slow decay. D 0 and D + candidates are reconstructed from D 0 → K − π + , <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π + π − , K − π + π 0 , K − π + π + π − , K − K + and D + → K − π + π + , K − K + π + ; cases with two <lb/>D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π + π − decays are rejected. We also reconstruct K 0 <lb/>S → π + π − and π 0 → γγ. The <lb/>reconstruction of the charge conjugates in the above decay chain is implied. <lb/>According to Monte Carlo (MC) studies, continuum background does not give a significant <lb/>contribution to this mode, so only a loose requirement on the ratio of the second to zeroth <lb/>Fox-Wolfram moment [10] is used, R 2 &lt; 0.4. Charged tracks satisfy loose criteria on their <lb/>impact parameters relative to the interaction point (IP), |dr| &lt; 0.4 cm and |dz| &lt; 5.0 cm <lb/>with some additional SVD requirements [11]. With information obtained from the CDC, <lb/>ACC and TOF, particle identification (PID), or K/π separation is determined with the <lb/>likelihood ratio, L K /(L K + L π ). Here, L i is the likelihood that the particle is of type i. <lb/>Candidate π 0 &apos;s are selected from pairs of photons with energies greater than 30 MeV. The <lb/>π 0 momentum is required to be greater than 200 MeV/c in the laboratory frame. Charged <lb/>slow pions used in the reconstruction of D * &apos;s, are not subject to impact parameter or PID <lb/>cuts. Similarly, the π 0 momentum cut is not applied to slow π 0 &apos;s used to reconstruct D * &apos;s. <lb/>We generate signal MC with EvtGen [12] using a detector simulation based on <lb/>GEANT3 [13]. All mass windows are chosen from correctly reconstructed signal MC by <lb/>fitting the mass distributions with double Gaussians and applying a 3σ cut on the wider <lb/>Gaussian. This method is applied to π 0 , K 0 <lb/>S , D and the D * − D mass difference for D * <lb/>selection. When multiple B mesons are reconstructed, the candidate with the smallest value <lb/>of <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>mass ≡ <lb/>i <lb/>χ 2 (X), where χ 2 (X) ≡ <lb/>|mass (X) − mass (X) PDG | 2 <lb/>σ (X) 2 <lb/>, <lb/>(4) <lb/>is selected. We sum over the prompt K 0 <lb/>S , the two daughter D mesons and the two daughter <lb/>D * &apos;s where σ (X) is the width of the narrow Gaussian found in the fit to the invariant mass <lb/>of particle X. <lb/>As we reconstruct the decay chain, vertexing algorithms are applied to K 0 <lb/>S and D mesons <lb/>from their charged daughters. The vertex of the B is determined from the pseudo-tracks <lb/>of the two daughter D mesons with an IP constraint. We do not include the slow pions in <lb/>the vertex fit due to their poor resolution. The prompt K 0 <lb/>S pseudo-track is also excluded <lb/>as its decay vertex has a relatively large displacement from the IP. However, both the slow <lb/>pion and K 0 <lb/>S candidate are constrained to originate from the B vertex determined by the D * <lb/>mesons and their momentum is recalculated to improve the resolution of the B candidate. <lb/>The B decay is described by the variables M bc ≡ (E CMS <lb/>beam ) 2 − (p CMS <lb/>B <lb/>) 2 and ∆E ≡ E CMS <lb/>B <lb/>− <lb/>E CMS <lb/>beam . The M bc signal shape is modeled by a Gaussian while the background is modeled <lb/>with an ARGUS function [14]. In ∆E, the signal shape is represented by a double Gaussian <lb/>and the background with a linear function. With the signal shape determined from MC, <lb/>we define the signal box to be 3σ of the Gaussian in M bc by 3σ of the narrow Gaussian in <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>∆E, which is 5.27 GeV/c 2 &lt; M bc &lt; 5.29 GeV/c 2 and −0.04 GeV &lt; ∆E &lt; 0.04 GeV. The <lb/>reconstruction efficiency, which includes all intermediate branching fractions, is determined <lb/>from phase space signal MC to be (6.59 ± 0.13) × 10 −5 for SVD1 and (9.58 ± 0.16) × 10 −5 <lb/>for SVD2, giving an average efficiency of (8.57 ± 0.15) × 10 −5 . The noticeable difference <lb/>in efficiency between SVD1 and SVD2 is due to the better performance of SVD2 with low <lb/>momentum tracking. With the signal shape fixed from signal MC, we perform an extended <lb/>two dimensional maximum likelihood fit to obtain the yield (Fig. 1), Y = 131.2 +14.8 <lb/>−14.1 (stat) <lb/>events. Using <lb/>B (B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S ) = <lb/>Y <lb/>ǫ N (B B) <lb/>, <lb/>(5) <lb/>where ǫ is the average detection efficiency and N (B B) is the number of B B pairs, we obtain <lb/>the branching fraction, <lb/>B (B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S ) = [3.4 ± 0.4 (stat) ± 0.7 (syst)] × 10 −3 , <lb/>(6) <lb/>which relies on the assumption of equal production of neutral and charged B meson pairs <lb/>from the Υ (4S). <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>bc <lb/>M <lb/>5.2 <lb/>5.22 5.24 5.26 5.28 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events / ( 0.002 GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>bc <lb/>M <lb/>5.2 <lb/>5.22 5.24 5.26 5.28 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events / ( 0.002 GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>E (GeV) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-0.2 -0.12 -0.04 0.04 0.12 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>Events / ( 0.008 GeV ) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>E (GeV) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-0.2 -0.12 -0.04 0.04 0.12 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>Events / ( 0.008 GeV ) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>FIG. 1: M bc − ∆E fit projections. The solid curve shows the fit result. <lb/>Systematic errors are estimated from various sources such as the number of B B events, <lb/>the uncertainty in the efficiency and the PDG errors on branching fractions [15]. The K 0 <lb/>S , <lb/>π 0 , PID and tracking systematics are determined from the efficiency ratio of data to MC as <lb/>calculated by independent studies at Belle. We also include the difference in yield between <lb/>fits with signal shape parameters obtained directly from data, and obtained from MC, as a <lb/>systematic error. The wider ∆E Gaussian in the fit to data is fixed, from MC, relative to <lb/>the narrow floating Gaussian. Peaking background due to fake π 0 <lb/>slow &apos;s is also accounted for <lb/>by investigating the D * + sideband. We also include possible efficiency variations across the <lb/>Dalitz plane by comparing the average efficiency of phase space signal MC with the average <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>efficiency as determined from bins of m (D * ± K 0 <lb/>S ) using data weights. The systematics are <lb/>summarized in Table I. <lb/>Source <lb/>Systematic error (%) <lb/>Number of B B pairs <lb/>1.3 <lb/>MC reconstruction efficiency <lb/>1.7 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S , π 0 and PID efficiency <lb/>5.8 <lb/>Daughter branching fractions <lb/>8.4 <lb/>Tracking efficiency <lb/>11.9 <lb/>Signal shape <lb/>10.4 <lb/>π 0 peaking background <lb/>4.7 <lb/>Dalitz efficiency dependence <lb/>2.6 <lb/>Total <lb/>19.8 <lb/>TABLE I: B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S branching fraction systematics. <lb/>The D * ± K 0 <lb/>S spectrum inside the signal box is examined to search for resonant structure. <lb/>Fig. 2(a) shows the background subtracted D * ± K 0 <lb/>S raw yield versus invariant mass overlaid <lb/>with reconstructed phase space obtained from signal MC. The background is taken from a <lb/>sideband defined to be 5.20 GeV/c 2 &lt; M bc &lt; 5.26 GeV/c 2 and −0.2 GeV &lt; ∆E &lt; 0.2 GeV. <lb/>From this plot, the data inside the signal box does not appear to be entirely consistent with <lb/>phase space, but neither is there any easily identifiable peak. <lb/>We extract the signal yield of B 0 → D + <lb/>s1 (2536)D * − from the mass difference, ∆m = <lb/>m (D * + K 0 <lb/>S )−m (D * + )−m (K 0 <lb/>S ), in the signal box. Note that while this form of ∆m has been <lb/>chosen, the K 0 <lb/>S was fitted to its nominal mass. A Breit-Wigner function convolved with a <lb/>Gaussian is chosen to model the signal shape, while a simple threshold function, P Bkg (∆m) = <lb/>c∆m 1/2 , is chosen to describe the background, where c is a normalizing constant. In the fit <lb/>to signal MC, the Breit-Wigner mass and width are fixed to their respective generated values <lb/>while the Gaussian is floated to determine the effects of detector smearing. In the fit to data, <lb/>the same smearing Gaussian is used, but the Breit-Wigner width is conservatively increased <lb/>to the current upper limit on the D + <lb/>s1 (2536) width, 2.3 MeV/c 2 [15]. The fitted yield is <lb/>Y (B 0 → D + <lb/>s1 (2536)D * − ) = 6.2 +4.0 <lb/>−3.4 (stat) events, and is shown in Fig. 2(b). The detection <lb/>efficiency in this region is found to be (3.08 ± 0.40) × 10 −5 for SVD1 and (3.98 ± 0.36) × 10 −5 <lb/>for SVD2, giving an average efficiency of (3.68 ± 0.38) × 10 −5 , and we obtain the product of <lb/>branching fractions, <lb/>B (B 0 → D + <lb/>s1 (2536)D * − )B (D + <lb/>s1 (2536) → D * + K 0 <lb/>S ) = [3.8 +2.4 <lb/>−2.1 (stat) +0.8 <lb/>−0.7 (syst)] × 10 −4 , (7) <lb/>where the systematics were determined in the same way as for B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S . Thus, <lb/>the upper limit is found to be <lb/>B (B 0 → D + <lb/>s1 (2536)D * − )B (D + <lb/>s1 (2536) → D * + K 0 <lb/>S ) &lt; 7.1 × 10 −4 (90% CL). <lb/>(8) <lb/>To obtain the ∆t distribution, we reconstruct the tag-side vertex from the tracks not <lb/>used to reconstruct the CP -side [11], and employ the flavor tagging routine described in <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>) <lb/>2 <lb/>) (GeV/c <lb/>S <lb/>K <lb/>*+ <lb/>m(D <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>3.3 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events / ( 0.05 GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>) (GeV/c <lb/>S <lb/>) -m(K <lb/>*+ <lb/>) -m(D <lb/>S <lb/>K <lb/>*+ <lb/>m(D <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 0.02 0.03 0.04 0.05 0.06 0.07 0.08 0.09 0.1 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events / ( 0.004 GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>) (GeV/c <lb/>S <lb/>) -m(K <lb/>*+ <lb/>) -m(D <lb/>S <lb/>K <lb/>*+ <lb/>m(D <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 0.02 0.03 0.04 0.05 0.06 0.07 0.08 0.09 0.1 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events / ( 0.004 GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>FIG. 2: (a) Background subtracted D * + K 0 <lb/>S raw yield vs. invariant mass with a superimposed <lb/>reconstructed phase space histogram from signal MC. (b) Measured distribution of m (D * + K 0 <lb/>S ) − <lb/>m (D * + ) − m (K 0 <lb/>S ) in the signal box. The solid line shows the fit results. <lb/>Ref. [16]. Due to imperfect flavor tagging, both a flavor tag, q, and the dilution factor of <lb/>flavor tagging, r, are assigned to each event. The r distribution is divided into 6 bins. <lb/>In the 2-parameter fit, the time-dependent ∆t distribution of B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S is given <lb/>by the probability density function (PDF), <lb/>P Sig (∆t, q) ≡ <lb/>e −|∆t|/τ B 0 <lb/>4τ B 0 <lb/>1−q∆w +q (1−2w)[A CP cos (∆m d ∆t)+D sin 2φ 1 sin (∆m d ∆t)] , <lb/>(9) <lb/>where q is the tagged flavor, and w, ∆w account for imperfect flavor tagging. w is the <lb/>probability of mis-tagging an event, ∆w is the difference between B 0 and B0 in w and they <lb/>are both determined from flavor specific control samples [16]. A CP and D sin 2φ 1 are the <lb/>two free parameters in this fit. To account for differences between true ∆t and reconstructed <lb/>∆t, P Sig is convolved with a resolution function described in Ref. [11], <lb/>P Sig (∆t, q) = <lb/>+∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/>P Sig (∆t ′ , q)R Sig (∆t − ∆t ′ )d(∆t ′ ), <lb/>(10) <lb/>which describes the effects of detector resolution and the effect of charm decays on the tag-<lb/>side. The effect of the approximation in Eq. 3 is also included in the resolution function. The <lb/>background PDF is modeled by an exponential lifetime component and a prompt component <lb/>given by a delta function, <lb/>P Bkg (∆t) ≡ (1 − f δ ) <lb/>e −|∆t|/τ Bkg <lb/>2τ Bkg <lb/>+ f δ δ (∆t − µ δ ), <lb/>(11) <lb/>where τ Bkg is the effective lifetime of the background and µ δ sets the ∆t location of the <lb/>prompt component. The PDF, P Bkg , is convolved with a resolution function that takes the <lb/>form of a double Gaussian, to give the background PDF, P Bkg . The background function <lb/>parameters are determined from the sideband data defined by 5.20 GeV/c 2 &lt; M bc &lt; 5.26 <lb/>GeV/c 2 and −0.2 GeV &lt; ∆E &lt; 0.2 GeV. To account for events with large |∆t| that are not <lb/>modeled by either the signal or background PDFs, an outlier background Gaussian, P Ol , is <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>also included. The probability that an event is a signal event is assigned from the M bc − ∆E <lb/>PDF based on the event&apos;s position inside the signal box, <lb/>f Sig (M bc , ∆E, r) ≡ <lb/>p (r)P Sig (M bc , ∆E) <lb/>p (r)P Sig (M bc , ∆E) + (1 − p (r))P Bkg (M bc , ∆E) <lb/>, <lb/>(12) <lb/>where p (r) is the purity in the signal region of each r-bin. Finally, the full time-dependent <lb/>CP violation PDF is written as, <lb/>P (∆t, q, M bc , ∆E, r) = (1 − f Ol ) f Sig (M bc , ∆E, r)P Sig (∆t, q) + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>[1 − f Sig (M bc , ∆E, r)]P Bkg (∆t) + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>f Ol P Ol (∆t). <lb/>(13) <lb/>A control sample, B0 → D * + D0 K − , is selected for which no CP violation is expected. <lb/>For this sample, the time-dependent fit reveals no CP violation, <lb/>A CP ( B0 → D * + D0 K − ) = 0.09 ± 0.13 (stat) <lb/>S CP ( B0 → D * + D0 K − ) = 0.01 ± 0.20 (stat), <lb/>(14) <lb/>where S CP represents the component of mixing induced CP violation. We then determine <lb/>the CP asymmetry parameters of B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S , <lb/>A CP = −0.01 +0.28 <lb/>−0.28 (stat) ± 0.09 (syst) <lb/>D sin 2φ 1 = 0.06 +0.45 <lb/>−0.44 (stat) ± 0.06 (syst), <lb/>(15) <lb/>and the fit results are shown in Fig. 3. <lb/>The sources of systematic errors are addressed as follows. The uncertainties in the vertex <lb/>reconstruction are the dominant sources of error. These include uncertainties in the IP <lb/>profile, charged track selection based on track helix errors, helix parameter corrections, <lb/>∆t and vertex goodness-of-fit selection, and SVD misalignment. Toy MC samples showed <lb/>some small fitting bias for CP parameters due to low statistics in each sample. We take <lb/>this bias as a systematic. The parameters for w and ∆w, resolution function, physics <lb/>parameters, background shape and signal fraction were varied by ±1σ. We estimate that <lb/>the CP eigenstate component of the background does not exceed 10% of the total. The <lb/>effect of CP asymmetry in the background was estimated by changing the background PDF <lb/>to be composed of 10% CP eigenstates with CP parameters at the physical limits. We also <lb/>investigate the effect of mis-reconstructed signal events using signal MC. This is achieved <lb/>by comparing the fit result of the signal MC sample with another fit on the same sample, <lb/>which required that the events were reconstructed correctly. Tag-side interference comes <lb/>from CP violation on the tag-side [17], and is estimated with B → D * lν. We generate MC <lb/>pseudo-experiments and perform an ensemble test to obtain systematic biases [18]. The <lb/>systematics are summarized in Table II. <lb/>In the 3-parameter fit, the time-dependent ∆t distribution assuming no direct CP viola-<lb/>tion, is given by <lb/>P Sig (∆t, q) ≡ <lb/>e −|∆t|/τ B 0 <lb/>4τ B 0 <lb/>1 − q∆w + q (1 − 2w) × <lb/>η y <lb/>J c <lb/>J 0 <lb/>cos (∆m d ∆t) − <lb/>2J s1 <lb/>J 0 <lb/>sin 2φ 1 + η y <lb/>2J s2 <lb/>J 0 <lb/>cos 2φ 1 sin (∆m d ∆t) . <lb/>(16) <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 -2 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Events / (2.5 ps) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>20 <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 -2 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Events / (2.5 ps) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>20 <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>(b) <lb/>(a) <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 -2 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Raw Asymmetry <lb/>-1 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>-0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 -2 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Raw Asymmetry <lb/>-1 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>-0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>(d) <lb/>(c) <lb/>FIG. 3: 2-parameter fit results of B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S . (a) and (b) show the background subtracted <lb/>∆t distribution for poor tags (0.0 &lt; r ≤ 0.5) and good tags (0.5 &lt; r ≤ 1.0). Background <lb/>subtraction is performed by subtracting the background PDF from the raw ∆t distribution. The <lb/>solid curve represents B 0 tagged candidates and the dashed curve represents B0 tagged candidates. <lb/>(c) and (d) show the B 0 − B0 raw asymmetry, (N B 0 − N B0 )/(N B 0 + N B0 ), where N B 0 (N B0 ) is the <lb/>number of B 0 ( B0 ) tags in ∆t for poor tags and good tags, respectively. <lb/>We obtain the time-dependent CP parameters, <lb/>J c /J 0 = 0.60 +0.25 <lb/>−0.28 (stat) ± 0.08 (syst) <lb/>2J s1 /J 0 sin 2φ 1 = −0.17 +0.42 <lb/>−0.42 (stat) ± 0.09 (syst) <lb/>2J s2 /J 0 cos 2φ 1 = −0.23 +0.43 <lb/>−0.41 (stat) ± 0.13 (syst), <lb/>(17) <lb/>and the corresponding fit curves are shown in Fig. 4. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Source <lb/>δ(A CP ) <lb/>δ(D sin 2φ 1 ) <lb/>Vertex reconstruction <lb/>0.064 <lb/>0.021 <lb/>Wrong tag fraction <lb/>0.020 <lb/>0.030 <lb/>Resolution function <lb/>0.019 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>Fit bias <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Physics parameters <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Background ∆t <lb/>0.016 <lb/>0.019 <lb/>Signal fraction <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>Mis-reconstructed events <lb/>0.014 <lb/>0.038 <lb/>Tag-side interference <lb/>0.053 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Total <lb/>0.090 <lb/>0.058 <lb/>TABLE II: Time-dependent CP asymmetry systematics: 2-parameter fit. <lb/>The systematics are determined in much the same way as in the 2-parameter fit. However, <lb/>since BaBar claims evidence for a B 0 → D + <lb/>s1 (2536)D * − contribution to the D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>final state [19], and resonant structure is more important in the 3-parameter fit, we excluded <lb/>the D + <lb/>s1 (2536) region, m (D * ± K 0 <lb/>S ) &lt; 2.6 GeV/c 2 , and took the difference in the results as a <lb/>systematic. The systematics are summarized in Table III. <lb/>Source <lb/>δ(J c /J 0 ) <lb/>δ(2J s1 /J 0 sin 2φ 1 ) <lb/>δ(2J s2 /J 0 cos 2φ 1 ) <lb/>Vertex reconstruction <lb/>0.066 <lb/>0.071 <lb/>0.081 <lb/>Wrong tag fraction <lb/>0.021 <lb/>0.033 <lb/>0.032 <lb/>Resolution function <lb/>0.014 <lb/>0.039 <lb/>0.045 <lb/>Fit bias <lb/>0.029 <lb/>0.018 <lb/>0.031 <lb/>Physics parameters <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Background ∆t <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.019 <lb/>0.012 <lb/>Signal fraction <lb/>0.020 <lb/>0.009 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>Mis-reconstructed events <lb/>0.020 <lb/>0.007 <lb/>0.026 <lb/>Tag-side interference <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>D + <lb/>s1 (2536) <lb/>0.019 <lb/>0.013 <lb/>0.069 <lb/>Total <lb/>0.084 <lb/>0.094 <lb/>0.127 <lb/>TABLE III: Time-dependent CP asymmetry systematics: 3-parameter fit. <lb/>In summary, we measure the branching fraction (Eq. 6) and CP parameters of B 0 → <lb/>D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S with a 2-parameter fit (Eq. 15), and 3-parameter fit (Eq. 17) with 414 fb −1 at the <lb/>Belle detector. An upper limit on the branching fraction of the intermediate two-body decay <lb/>B 0 → D + <lb/>s1 (2536)D * − (Eq. 8) is also obtained. In the 2-parameter fit, there is no evidence for <lb/>direct CP violation and a large dilution of sin 2φ 1 is implied. In the 3-parameter fit, J c /J 0 <lb/>appears to be non-zero; a large value of this parameter could indicate the presence of a broad <lb/>unknown D * * + <lb/>s <lb/>state. As in the 2-parameter fit, a large dilution of the CP asymmetry from <lb/>polarization and resonant structure is implied since 2J s1 /J 0 sin 2φ 1 is consistent with zero. <lb/>According to [5], 2J s2 /J 0 , is expected to be positive if this unknown wide resonance exists. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 -2 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Events / (2.5 ps) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 -2 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Events / (2.5 ps) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>(b) <lb/>(a) <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 -2 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Raw Asymmetry <lb/>-1 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>-0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 -2 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Raw Asymmetry <lb/>-1 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>-0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>(d) <lb/>(c) <lb/>FIG. 4: 3-parameter fit results of B 0 → D * + D * − K 0 <lb/>S . (a) and (b) show the background subtracted <lb/>∆t distribution for good tags (0.5 &lt; r ≤ 1.0) in the region, s − ≤ s + and s − &gt; s + . The solid curve <lb/>represents B 0 tags and the dashed curve represents B0 tags. (c) and (d) show the B 0 − B0 raw <lb/>asymmetry in ∆t for each half-Dalitz space and for good tags only. <lb/>The parameter, 2J s2 /J 0 cos 2φ 1 , has been measured, however, a model-dependent inference <lb/>on the sign of cos 2φ 1 is not possible with current precision. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank the KEKB group for the excellent operation of the accelerator, the KEK <lb/>cryogenics group for the efficient operation of the solenoid, and the KEK computer group <lb/>and the National Institute of Informatics for valuable computing and Super-SINET network <lb/>support. We acknowledge support from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, <lb/>and Technology of Japan and the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science; the Australian <lb/>Research Council and the Australian Department of Education, Science and Training; the <lb/></div>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">National Science Foundation of China and the Knowledge Innovation Program of the Chinese <lb/>Academy of Sciences under contract No. 10575109 and IHEP-U-503; the Department of <lb/>Science and Technology of India; the BK21 program of the Ministry of Education of Korea, <lb/>the CHEP SRC program and Basic Research program (grant No. R01-2005-000-10089-0) of <lb/>the Korea Science and Engineering Foundation, and the Pure Basic Research Group program <lb/>of the Korea Research Foundation; the Polish State Committee for Scientific Research; <lb/>the Ministry of Education and Science of the Russian Federation and the Russian Federal <lb/>Agency for Atomic Energy; the Slovenian Research Agency; the Swiss National Science <lb/>Foundation; the National Science Council and the Ministry of Education of Taiwan; and the <lb/>U.S. Department of Energy. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] N. Cabibbo, Phys. Rev. Lett. 8, 214 (1964). <lb/>[2] M. Kobayashi and T. Maskawa, Prog. Theor. Phys. 49, 652 (1973). <lb/>[3] B. Aubert et al. (BaBar Collab.), Phys. Rev. Lett. 89, 201802 (2002). <lb/>[4] K. Abe et al. (Belle Collab.), Phys. Rev. D 66, 071102 (2002). <lb/>[5] T. E. Browder, A. Datta, P. J. O&apos;Donnell and S. Pakvasa, Phys. Rev. D 61, 054009 (2000). <lb/>[6] A. B. Carter and A. I. Sanda, Phys. Rev. Lett. 45, 952 (1980); A. B. Carter and A. I. Sanda, <lb/>Phys. Rev. D 23, 1567 (1981); I. I. Bigi and A. I. Sanda, Nucl. Phys. 193, 85 (1981). <lb/>[7] S. Kurokawa and E. Kikutani, Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A 499, 1 (2003), and other papers <lb/>included in this volume. <lb/>[8] A. Abashian et al. (Belle Collab.), Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A 479, 117 (2002). <lb/>[9] Z. Natkaniec et al. (Belle SVD2 Group), Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A 560, 1(2006). <lb/>[10] G. C. Fox and S. Wolfram, Phys. Rev. Lett. 41, 1581 (1978). <lb/>[11] H. Tajima et al., Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A 533, 370 (2004). <lb/>[12] D. J. Lange, Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A 462, 152 (2001). <lb/>[13] R. Brun et al., GEANT 3.21, CERN DD/EE/84-1 (1984). <lb/>[14] H. Albrecht et al. (ARGUS Collab.), Z. Phys. C 48, 543 (1990). <lb/>[15] W.-M. Yao et al., Journal of Physics G 33, 1 (2006) <lb/>[16] H. Kakuno et al., Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A 533, 516 (2004). <lb/>[17] O. Long, M. Baak, R. N. Cahn and D. Kirkby, Phys. Rev. D 68, 034010 (2003). <lb/>[18] K. F. Chen et al., Phys. Rev. D 72, 012004 (2005). <lb/>[19] B. Aubert et al. (BaBar Collab.), Phys. Rev. D 74, 091101(R) (2006). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
