<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:0708.2604v4 [hep-ex] 27 May 2008 <lb/>Measurements of time-dependent CP violation in B 0 → ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S decays <lb/> H. Sahoo, 6 T. E. Browder, 6 K. Trabelsi, 7 I. Adachi, 7 H. Aihara, 40 K. Arinstein, 1 T. Aushev, 16, 11 S. Bahinipati, 2 <lb/>A. M. Bakich, 35 V. Balagura, 11 E. Barberio, 19 A. Bay, 16 I. Bedny, 1 K. Belous, 10 U. Bitenc, 12 A. Bondar, 1 <lb/>A. Bozek, 25 M. Bračko, 18, 12 M.-C. Chang, 3 Y. Chao, 24 A. Chen, 22 W. T. Chen, 22 B. G. Cheon, 5 R. Chistov, 11 <lb/>I.-S. Cho, 45 Y. Choi, 34 J. Dalseno, 19 M. Dash, 44 A. Drutskoy, 2 S. Eidelman, 1 B. Golob, 17, 12 H. Ha, 14 J. Haba, 7 <lb/>K. Hara, 20 T. Hara, 30 K. Hayasaka, 20 H. Hayashii, 21 M. Hazumi, 7 D. Heffernan, 30 Y. Hoshi, 38 W.-S. Hou, 24 <lb/>Y. B. Hsiung, 24 H. J. Hyun, 15 K. Inami, 20 A. Ishikawa, 31 H. Ishino, 41 R. Itoh, 7 M. Iwasaki, 40 N. J. Joshi, 36 <lb/>D. H. Kah, 15 J. H. Kang, 45 P. Kapusta, 25 N. Katayama, 7 H. Kichimi, 7 H. J. Kim, 15 Y. J. Kim, 4 K. Kinoshita, 2 <lb/>S. Korpar, 18, 12 Y. Kozakai, 20 P. Križan, 17, 12 P. Krokovny, 7 R. Kumar, 46 C. C. Kuo, 22 Y. Kuroki, 30 Y.-J. Kwon, 45 <lb/>J. S. Lee, 34 M. J. Lee, 33 S. E. Lee, 33 T. Lesiak, 25 J. Li, 6 A. Limosani, 19 D. Liventsev, 11 F. Mandl, 9 A. Matyja, 25 <lb/>S. McOnie, 35 T. Medvedeva, 11 W. Mitaroff, 9 K. Miyabayashi, 21 H. Miyake, 30 H. Miyata, 27 Y. Miyazaki, 20 <lb/>R. Mizuk, 11 G. R. Moloney, 19 E. Nakano, 29 M. Nakao, 7 Z. Natkaniec, 25 S. Nishida, 7 O. Nitoh, 43 S. Noguchi, 21 <lb/>S. Ogawa, 37 T. Ohshima, 20 S. Okuno, 13 S. L. Olsen, 6, 8 P. Pakhlov, 11 G. Pakhlova, 11 H. Palka, 25 C. W. Park, 34 <lb/>H. Park, 15 L. S. Peak, 35 R. Pestotnik, 12 L. E. Piilonen, 44 Y. Sakai, 7 O. Schneider, 16 C. Schwanda, 9 A. J. Schwartz, 2 <lb/>K. Senyo, 20 M. E. Sevior, 19 M. Shapkin, 10 C. P. Shen, 8 H. Shibuya, 37 J.-G. Shiu, 24 B. Shwartz, 1 A. Somov, 2 <lb/>S. Stanič, 28 M. Starič, 12 K. Sumisawa, 7 T. Sumiyoshi, 42 F. Takasaki, 7 M. Tanaka, 7 G. N. Taylor, 19 <lb/>Y. Teramoto, 29 I. Tikhomirov, 11 S. Uehara, 7 K. Ueno, 24 Y. Unno, 5 S. Uno, 7 P. Urquijo, 19 Y. Usov, 1 G. Varner, 6 <lb/>K. E. Varvell, 35 K. Vervink, 16 S. Villa, 16 C. H. Wang, 23 P. Wang, 8 X. L. Wang, 8 Y. Watanabe, 13 R. Wedd, 19 <lb/>E. Won, 14 H. Yamamoto, 39 Y. Yamashita, 26 C. C. Zhang, 8 Z. P. Zhang, 32 V. Zhulanov, 1 and A. Zupanc 12 <lb/>(Belle Collaboration) <lb/> 1 Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics, Novosibirsk <lb/>2 University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio 45221 <lb/>3 Department of Physics, Fu Jen Catholic University, Taipei <lb/>4 The Graduate University for Advanced Studies, Hayama <lb/>5 Hanyang University, Seoul <lb/>6 University of Hawaii, Honolulu, Hawaii 96822 <lb/>7 High Energy Accelerator Research Organization (KEK), Tsukuba <lb/>8 Institute of High Energy Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing <lb/>9 Institute of High Energy Physics, Vienna <lb/>10 Institute of High Energy Physics, Protvino <lb/>11 Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics, Moscow <lb/>12 J. Stefan Institute, Ljubljana <lb/>13 Kanagawa University, Yokohama <lb/>14 Korea University, Seoul <lb/>15 Kyungpook National University, Taegu <lb/>16 École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), Lausanne <lb/>17 Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, University of Ljubljana, Ljubljana <lb/>18 University of Maribor, Maribor <lb/>19 University of Melbourne, School of Physics, Victoria 3010 <lb/>20 Nagoya University, Nagoya <lb/>21 Nara Women&apos;s University, Nara <lb/>22 National Central University, Chung-li <lb/>23 National United University, Miao Li <lb/>24 Department of Physics, National Taiwan University, Taipei <lb/>25 H. Niewodniczanski Institute of Nuclear Physics, Krakow <lb/>26 Nippon Dental University, Niigata <lb/>27 Niigata University, Niigata <lb/>28 University of Nova Gorica, Nova Gorica <lb/>29 Osaka City University, Osaka <lb/>30 Osaka University, Osaka <lb/>31 Saga University, Saga <lb/>32 University of Science and Technology of China, Hefei <lb/>33 Seoul National University, Seoul <lb/>34 Sungkyunkwan University, Suwon <lb/>35 University of Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales <lb/>36 Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>37 Toho University, Funabashi <lb/>38 Tohoku Gakuin University, Tagajo <lb/>39 Tohoku University, Sendai <lb/>40 Department of Physics, University of Tokyo, Tokyo <lb/>41 Tokyo Institute of Technology, Tokyo <lb/>42 Tokyo Metropolitan University, Tokyo <lb/>43 Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, Tokyo <lb/>44 Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia 24061 <lb/>45 Yonsei University, Seoul <lb/>46 Panjab University, Chandigarh <lb/>We report improved measurements of time-dependent CP violation parameters for B 0 (B 0 ) → <lb/>ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S . This analysis is based on a data sample of 657 × 10 6 BB pairs collected at the Υ(4S) res-<lb/>onance with the Belle detector at the KEKB energy-asymmetric e + e − collider. We fully reconstruct <lb/>one neutral B meson in the ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S CP -eigenstate decay channel, and the flavor of the accompa-<lb/>nying B meson is identified to be either B 0 or B 0 from its decay products. CP violation parameters <lb/>are obtained from the asymmetries in the distributions of the proper-time intervals between the two <lb/>B decays: S ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>= +0.72 ± 0.09(stat) ± 0.03(syst), A ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>= +0.04 ± 0.07(stat) ± 0.05(syst). <lb/>These results are in agreement with results from measurements of B 0 → J/ψK 0 . <lb/>PACS numbers: 11.30.Er, 12.15.Hh, 13.25.Hw <lb/></front>

			<body>In the standard model, CP violation in B 0 meson de-<lb/>cays originates from an irreducible complex phase in the <lb/>3 × 3 Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa (CKM) mixing ma-<lb/>trix [1]. In the decay chain Υ(4S) → B 0 B 0 → f CP f tag , <lb/>where one of the B mesons decays at time t CP to a CP <lb/>eigenstate f CP and the other decays at time t tag to a fi-<lb/>nal state f tag that distinguishes between B 0 and B 0 , the <lb/>decay rate has a time dependence [2] given by <lb/>P(∆t) = <lb/>e −|∆t|/τ B 0 <lb/>4τ B 0 <lb/>1 + q • S fCP sin(∆m d ∆t) <lb/>+ A fCP cos(∆m d ∆t) . (1) <lb/>Here S fCP and A fCP are the CP violation parameters, <lb/>τ B 0 is the neutral B lifetime, ∆m d is the mass dif-<lb/>ference between the two neutral B mass eigenstates, <lb/>∆t = t CP −t tag , and the b-flavor charge q equals +1 (−1) <lb/>when the tagging B meson is a B 0 (B 0 ). For f CP final <lb/>states resulting from a b → ccs transition, the standard <lb/>model predicts S fCP = −ξ f sin 2φ 1 [3] and A fCP ≃ 0, <lb/>where ξ f = +1 (−1) for CP -even (CP -odd) final states <lb/>and φ 1 is one of the three interior angles of the CKM uni-<lb/>tarity triangle, defined as φ 1 ≡ π − arg(V * <lb/>tb V td /V * <lb/>cb V cd ). <lb/>Measurements of CP asymmetries in b → ccs transitions <lb/>have been reported by Belle [4, 5] and BaBar [6]. Results <lb/>from our previously published B 0 → ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S analysis <lb/>were based on a 140 fb −1 data sample corresponding to <lb/>152×10 6 BB pairs [4]. Here we report new measurements <lb/>with an improved analysis [7] incorporating an additional <lb/>465 fb −1 data sample for a total of 605 fb −1 (657 × 10 6 <lb/>BB pairs). <lb/>At the KEKB energy-asymmetric e + e − (3.5 on 8.0 <lb/>GeV) collider [8], the Υ(4S) is produced with a Lorentz <lb/>boost of βγ = 0.425 nearly along the z axis, which is de-<lb/>fined as opposite to the positron beam direction. Since <lb/>the B 0 and B 0 are approximately at rest in the Υ(4S) <lb/>center-of-mass system (cms), ∆t can be determined from <lb/>the displacement in z between the two decay vertices: <lb/>∆t ≃ ∆z/(βγc), where c is the speed of light. <lb/>The Belle detector is a large-solid-angle magnetic spec-<lb/>trometer that consists of a silicon vertex detector (SVD), <lb/>a 50-layer central drift chamber (CDC), an array of <lb/>aerogel threshold Cherenkov counters (ACC), a barrel-<lb/>like arrangement of time-of-flight scintillation counters <lb/>(TOF), and an electromagnetic calorimeter (ECL) com-<lb/>prised of CsI(Tl) crystals located inside a superconduct-<lb/>ing solenoid coil that provides a 1.5 T magnetic field. An <lb/>iron flux-return located outside the coil is instrumented <lb/>to detect K 0 <lb/>L mesons and to identify muons (KLM). The <lb/>detector is described in detail elsewhere [9]. Two dif-<lb/>ferent inner detector configurations were used. For the <lb/>first sample of 152 × 10 6 BB pairs, a 2.0 cm radius <lb/>beampipe and a 3-layer silicon vertex detector (SVD-I) <lb/>were used; for the latter 505 × 10 6 BB pairs, a 1.5 cm <lb/>radius beampipe, a 4-layer silicon detector (SVD-II), and <lb/>a small-cell inner drift chamber were used [10]. <lb/>We reconstruct ψ(2S) mesons in the l + l − decay chan-<lb/>nel (l = e or µ) and J/ψπ + π − decay channel. J/ψ <lb/>mesons are reconstructed in the l + l − decay channel <lb/>and include the bremsstrahlung photons that are within <lb/>50 mrad of each of the e + and e − tracks [denoted as <lb/>e + e − (γ)]. The invariant mass of the J/ψ candidates is re-<lb/>quired to be within −0.150 GeV/c 2 &lt; M e + e − (γ) −m J/ψ &lt; <lb/>+0.036 GeV/c 2 and −0.060 GeV/c 2 &lt; M µ + µ − − m J/ψ &lt; <lb/>+0.036 GeV/c 2 , where m J/ψ denotes the world-average <lb/>J/ψ mass [11], and M e + e − (γ) and M µ + µ − are the re-<lb/>constructed invariant masses of the e + e − (γ) and µ + µ − <lb/>candidates, respectively. For the ψ(2S) → l + l − can-<lb/>didates, the same procedure is used. In this case, the <lb/>invariant mass is required to be within −0.150 GeV/c 2 <lb/>&lt; M e + e − (γ) − m ψ(2S) &lt; +0.036 GeV/c 2 and −0.060 <lb/>GeV/c 2 &lt; M µ + µ − − m ψ(2S) &lt; +0.036 GeV/c 2 , where <lb/>m ψ(2S) denotes the world-average ψ(2S) mass [11]. For <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>the ψ(2S) → J/ψπ + π − candidates, ∆M ≡ M l + l − π + π − − <lb/>M l + l − is required to be within 0.580 GeV/c 2 &lt; ∆M &lt; <lb/>0.600 GeV/c 2 . To reduce the fraction of incorrectly <lb/>reconstructed ψ(2S) signal candidates, we select π + π − <lb/>pairs with an invariant mass greater than 400 MeV/c 2 . <lb/>The K 0 <lb/>S selection criteria are the same as those de-<lb/>scribed in Ref. [12]; the invariant mass of the pion pairs <lb/>is required to satisfy 0.482 GeV/c 2 &lt; M π + π − &lt; 0.514 <lb/>GeV/c 2 . <lb/>We combine the ψ(2S) and K 0 <lb/>S to form a neutral B <lb/>meson. The B candidates are identified using two kine-<lb/>matic variables: the energy difference ∆E ≡ E cms <lb/>B <lb/>− <lb/>E cms <lb/>beam and the beam-energy-constrained mass M bc ≡ <lb/>(E cms <lb/>beam ) 2 − (p cms <lb/>B ) 2 , where E cms <lb/>beam is the beam energy in <lb/>the cms, and E cms <lb/>B <lb/>and p cms <lb/>B <lb/>are the cms energy and mo-<lb/>mentum, respectively, of the reconstructed B candidate. <lb/>In order to improve the ∆E resolution, the masses of the <lb/>selected J/ψ and ψ(2S) candidates are constrained to <lb/>their nominal masses using mass-constrained kinematic <lb/>fits. For the CP asymmetry fit, we select the candidates <lb/>in the ∆E-M bc signal region defined as |∆E| &lt; 0.03 GeV <lb/>and 5.27 GeV/c 2 &lt; M bc &lt; 5.29 GeV/c 2 . To suppress <lb/>background from e + e − → qq (q = u, d, s, or c) contin-<lb/>uum events, we require that the event-shape variable R 2 <lb/>be less than 0.5, where R 2 is the ratio of second to zeroth <lb/>Fox-Wolfram moments [13]. <lb/>The b flavor of the accompanying B meson is identi-<lb/>fied by a tagging algorithm [14] that categorizes charged <lb/>leptons, kaons, and Λ baryons found in the event. The <lb/>algorithm returns two parameters: the b-flavor charge q, <lb/>and r, which measures the tag quality and varies from <lb/>r = 0 for no flavor discrimination to r = 1 for unam-<lb/>biguous flavor assignment. If r &lt; 0.1, the accompanying <lb/>B meson provides negligible tagging information and we <lb/>set the wrong tag probability to 0.5. Events with r &gt; 0.1 <lb/>are divided into six r intervals. <lb/>The vertex position for the f CP decay is reconstructed <lb/>using charged tracks that have a minimum number of <lb/>SVD hits [15]. A constraint on the interaction point is <lb/>also used with the selected tracks; the interaction point <lb/>profile is convolved with the finite B-flight length in the <lb/>plane perpendicular to the z axis. The pions from K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>decays are not used for vertexing. The typical vertex <lb/>reconstruction efficiency and z resolution are 95% and <lb/>78 µm, respectively [12]. The f tag vertex determina-<lb/>tion is obtained with well-reconstructed tracks that are <lb/>not assigned to f CP . The typical vertex reconstruc-<lb/>tion efficiency and z resolution are 93% and 140 µm, <lb/>respectively [12]. After all selection criteria are ap-<lb/>plied, we obtain 1618 and 1202 events for the l + l − and <lb/>J/ψπ + π − modes in the ∆E-M bc fit region defined as 5.2 <lb/>GeV/c 2 &lt; M bc &lt; 5.3 GeV/c 2 and −0.1 GeV &lt; ∆E &lt; <lb/>0.1 GeV, of which 680 and 712, respectively, are in the <lb/>signal region. <lb/>Figure 1 shows the reconstructed variables ∆E and <lb/>M bc after flavor tagging and vertex reconstruction. The <lb/>signal yield is obtained from an extended unbinned <lb/>maximum-likelihood fit to the ∆E-M bc distribution. We <lb/>model the shape for the signal component using the prod-<lb/>uct of a double Gaussian for ∆E and a single Gaussian <lb/>for M bc whereas the combinatorial background is de-<lb/>scribed by the product of a first-order polynomial for <lb/>∆E and an ARGUS [16] function for M bc . For the <lb/>ψ(2S) → J/ψπ + π − mode, there is a background com-<lb/>ponent that peaks like the signal (peaking background) <lb/>in the ∆E-M bc signal region. This peaking background is <lb/>mainly due to the J/ψK 1 (1270) 0 , J/ψK * (892) − π + and <lb/>J/ψK 0 <lb/>S π + π − modes, with no real ψ(2S) → J/ψπ + π − in <lb/>the final state. The fraction of such peaking events is es-<lb/>timated to be 1% from the ∆M sidebands in data. The <lb/>E (GeV) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-0.1 -0.08 -0.06-0.04-0.02 0 0.02 0.04 0.06 0.08 0.1 <lb/>Events / ( 0.002 GeV ) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>E (GeV) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-0.1 -0.08 -0.06-0.04-0.02 0 0.02 0.04 0.06 0.08 0.1 <lb/>Events / ( 0.002 GeV ) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>bc <lb/>M <lb/>5.2 5.21 5.22 5.23 5.24 5.25 5.26 5.27 5.28 5.29 5.3 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events / ( 0.002 GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>350 <lb/>400 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>bc <lb/>M <lb/>5.2 5.21 5.22 5.23 5.24 5.25 5.26 5.27 5.28 5.29 5.3 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events / ( 0.002 GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>350 <lb/>400 <lb/>FIG. 1: (color online). (a) ∆E distribution within the M bc <lb/>signal region, (b) M bc distribution within the ∆E signal re-<lb/>gion for B 0 → ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S . The solid curves show the fits to the <lb/>signal plus background distributions, while the dashed curves <lb/>show the background contributions. The small contribution <lb/>from peaking backgrounds is discussed in the text. <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>signal and background shapes for each decay mode are <lb/>determined from Monte Carlo (MC) events; these shapes <lb/>are adjusted for small differences between MC and data <lb/>using a control sample of B + → ψ(2S)K + [17] events, <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE I: Number of signal B candidates (Nsig) and esti-<lb/>mated signal purity (p) in the signal region after flavor tagging <lb/>and vertex reconstruction. <lb/>Mode <lb/>Nsig <lb/>p <lb/>ψ(2S)(l + l − )K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>628 ± 26 <lb/>0.92 ± 0.01 <lb/>ψ(2S)(J/ψπ + π − )K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>656 ± 26 <lb/>0.92 ± 0.01 <lb/>which have a final state similar to the signal but with <lb/>higher statistics. This sample, where no CP asymme-<lb/>try is expected, is also used to check the potential bias <lb/>in the measurements of CP violation parameters. The <lb/>signal yields and purity in the ∆E-M bc signal region af-<lb/>ter flavor tagging and vertex reconstruction are listed in <lb/>Table I. We define the purity as the ratio of the signal <lb/>yield to the total number of candidate events in the signal <lb/>region. <lb/>We determine S fCP and A fCP by performing an un-<lb/>binned maximum-likelihood fit to the observed ∆t distri-<lb/>bution for the candidate events in the signal region. The <lb/>likelihood function is <lb/>L(S fCP , A fCP ) = <lb/>i <lb/>P i (S fCP , A fCP ; ∆t i ), <lb/>(2) <lb/>where the product includes events in the signal region. <lb/>We only use events with vertices that satisfy |∆t| &lt; 70 ps <lb/>and ξ &lt; 250, where ξ is the χ 2 of the vertex fit calculated <lb/>only in the z direction. The probability density function <lb/>(PDF) is given by <lb/>P i = (1 − f ol ) <lb/>f sig P sig (∆t ′ )R sig (∆t i − ∆t ′ ) <lb/>+ f peak P peak (∆t ′ )R sig (∆t i − ∆t ′ ) <lb/>+ (1 − f sig − f peak )P bkg (∆t ′ )R bkg (∆t i − ∆t ′ ) d(∆t ′ ) <lb/>+ f ol P ol (∆t i ). <lb/>(3) <lb/>The signal fraction f sig and the peaking fraction f peak <lb/>depend on the r region and are calculated on an event-<lb/>by-event basis as a function of ∆E and M bc . The PDF <lb/>for signal events, P sig (∆t), is given by Eq. 1 and modified <lb/>to incorporate the effect of incorrect flavor assignment; <lb/>the parameters τ B 0 and ∆m d are fixed to their world-<lb/>average values [11]. The distribution is then convolved <lb/>with a resolution function R sig (∆t) to take into account <lb/>the finite vertex resolution. The resolution function pa-<lb/>rameters, along with the wrong tag fractions for the six <lb/>r intervals, w l (l = 1, 6) and possible differences in w l <lb/>between B 0 and B 0 decays (∆w l ) are determined us-<lb/>ing a high-statistics control sample of semileptonic and <lb/>hadronic b → c decays [4, 12]. The PDF for non-peaking <lb/>background events, P bkg (∆t), is modeled as a sum of ex-<lb/>ponential and prompt components and is convolved with <lb/>a sum of two Gaussians, which parameterizes the reso-<lb/>lution function R bkg (∆t). Parameters in P bkg (∆t) and <lb/>R bkg (∆t) are determined from a fit to the ∆t distribu-<lb/>tion of events in the ∆E-M bc data sideband (M bc &lt; 5.26 <lb/>GeV/c 2 , −0.03 GeV &lt; ∆E &lt; 0.20 GeV). The PDF for <lb/>peaking background events, P peak (∆t), is the same as <lb/>P sig (∆t) with CP parameters fixed to zero. The term <lb/>P ol (∆t) is a broad Gaussian function that represents an <lb/>outlier component with a small fraction f ol . The only free <lb/>parameters in the final fit are S fCP and A fCP ; these are <lb/>determined by maximizing the likelihood function given <lb/>by Eq. 2. <lb/>The unbinned maximum-likelihood fit to the 1300 <lb/>events in the signal region results in the CP violation <lb/>parameters, <lb/>S ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S = +0.72 ± 0.09(stat) ± 0.03(syst), <lb/>A ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S = +0.04 ± 0.07(stat) ± 0.05(syst), <lb/>where the systematic uncertainties listed are described <lb/>below. We define the raw asymmetry in each ∆t bin by <lb/>(N + − N − )/(N + + N − ), where N + (N − ) is the number of <lb/>observed candidates with q = +1 (−1). Figure 2 shows <lb/>the observed ∆t distributions for q = +1 and q = −1 <lb/>with no requirement on the tagging quality (top), and <lb/>the raw asymmetry for events with good tagging quality <lb/>(r &gt; 0.5) (bottom). <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>Events/(1 ps) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>q = +1 <lb/>q = -1 <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>Raw Asymmetry <lb/>-1 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>-0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>FIG. 2: (color online). The top plot shows the ∆t distribu-<lb/>tions for q = +1 and q = −1 with no requirement on r. The <lb/>dashed curve is the sum of backgrounds while the solid curves <lb/>are the sum of signal and backgrounds. The bottom plot is <lb/>the raw asymmetry of well-tagged events (r &gt; 0.5, 45% of <lb/>the total). The solid curve shows the result of the unbinned <lb/>maximum-likelihood fit. <lb/>The systematic errors on S fCP and A fCP , summarized <lb/>in Table II, are evaluated by fitting the data with each <lb/>fixed parameter varied by its 1 standard deviation (σ) er-<lb/>ror. The MC-determined parameters are varied by ±2σ <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>to take into account possible imperfect modeling in the <lb/>MC. We repeat the CP fit procedure with the new value, <lb/>add the differences in S, A quadratically, and then assign <lb/>the result as the systematic error. The largest contribu-<lb/>tion to S fCP comes from vertex reconstruction (0.026). <lb/>This includes the uncertainties in the interaction point <lb/>profile (the smearing used to account for the B flight <lb/>length is varied by −10 µm and +20 µm), the tag side <lb/>track selection criteria, the helix parameter correction, <lb/>the |∆t| range (varied by ±30 ps), the vertex quality <lb/>cut ξ (changed to ξ &lt; 150 and ξ &lt; 500), the ∆z mea-<lb/>surement, and imperfect SVD alignment. The last two <lb/>are obtained from a study of J/ψK 0 <lb/>S . Each physics pa-<lb/>rameter (τ B 0 , ∆m d ) is varied by the error in its world-<lb/>average value [11]. Systematic errors due to uncertain-<lb/>ties in wrong tag fractions are estimated by varying the <lb/>parameters w l , ∆w l in each r region by their ±1σ er-<lb/>rors. Systematic errors due to uncertainties in the reso-<lb/>lution function are estimated by varying each resolution <lb/>parameter obtained from data (MC) by ±1σ (±2σ). The <lb/>∆E, M bc parameters and signal fraction in each r region <lb/>are varied to estimate the systematic errors. No signifi-<lb/>cant bias is seen by fitting a large sample of MC events. <lb/>The systematic errors from uncertainties in the peaking <lb/>background are obtained by varying the peaking fraction, <lb/>shape, as well as its CP asymmetry parameters. The sys-<lb/>tematic errors from uncertainties in the background ∆t <lb/>shape are estimated by varying each background param-<lb/>eter by its statistical error. We also include the effects of <lb/>interference between CKM-favored and CKM-suppressed <lb/>B → D transitions in the f tag final state [18]. We add <lb/>each contribution above in quadrature to obtain the total <lb/>systematic uncertainty. <lb/>We perform various cross-checks for this measurement. <lb/>A fit to the first data sample (SVD-I) results in the CP <lb/>violation parameter, S = 0.97 ± 0.18, which is consistent <lb/>with our previous result [4]. A fit to the CP asymmetries <lb/>of the control sample gives the CP violation parameters, <lb/>S = 0.02 ± 0.05 and A = −0.03 ± 0.03, which are consis-<lb/>tent with no CP asymmetry. A fit to the sideband events <lb/>in the B 0 → ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S data sample gives an asymmetry <lb/>consistent with zero (S = 0.02 ± 0.21, A = −0.04 ± 0.10). <lb/>A lifetime fit to B 0 → ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S and B + → ψ(2S)K + <lb/>gives τ B 0 = 1.51 ± 0.05 ps and τ B + = 1.62 ± 0.03 ps, <lb/>respectively, which are consistent with the world-average <lb/>values. We also examine the CP violation parameters <lb/>separately for the ψ(2S) → l + l − (S = 0.84 ± 0.13, A = <lb/>0.14 ± 0.09) and ψ(2S) → J/ψπ + π − (S = 0.61 ± 0.13, <lb/>A = −0.09 ± 0.10) decay modes. We find that all results <lb/>are consistent within errors. <lb/>In summary, we have performed improved measure-<lb/>ments of CP violation parameters sin 2φ 1 and A fCP for <lb/>B 0 → ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S using 657 × 10 6 BB events. These <lb/>measurements supersede our previous result [4] and <lb/>are in agreement with results from measurements of <lb/>B 0 → J/ψK 0 [19]. Combining the results from B 0 → <lb/>J/ψK 0 [5] and B 0 → ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S decays, we obtain a new <lb/>Belle average sin 2φ 1 = 0.650 ± 0.029 ± 0.018. <lb/>TABLE II: Systematic uncertainties. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>∆S ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>∆A ψ(2S)K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>Vertexing <lb/>0.026 <lb/>0.028 <lb/>Wrong tag fraction <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.023 <lb/>Resolution function <lb/>0.007 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>Fit bias <lb/>0.012 <lb/>0.011 <lb/>Physics parameters <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Peaking background <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>PDF shape and fraction <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Background ∆t shape <lb/>0.003 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Tag side interference <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.036 <lb/>Total <lb/>0.031 <lb/>0.053 <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank the KEKB group for excellent operation of <lb/>the accelerator, the KEK cryogenics group for efficient <lb/>solenoid operations, and the KEK computer group and <lb/>the NII for valuable computing and Super-SINET net-<lb/>work support. We acknowledge support from MEXT <lb/>and JSPS (Japan); ARC and DEST (Australia); NSFC <lb/>(China); DST (India); MOEHRD, KOSEF and KRF <lb/>(Korea); KBN (Poland); MES and RFAAE (Russia); <lb/>ARRS (Slovenia); SNSF (Switzerland); NSC and MOE <lb/>(Taiwan); and DOE (USA). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] N. Cabibbo, Phys. Rev. Lett. 10, 531 (1963); <lb/>M. Kobayashi and T. Maskawa, Prog. Theor. Phys. 49, <lb/>652 (1973). <lb/>[2] A. B. Carter and A. I. Sanda, Phys. Rev. D 23, 1567 <lb/>(1981); I. I. Bigi and A. I. Sanda, Nucl. Phys. B 193, 85 <lb/>(1981). <lb/>[3] Another naming convention β(= φ1) is also used in the <lb/>literature. <lb/>[4] K. Abe et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 71, <lb/>072003 (2005). <lb/>[5] K-F. Chen et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>98, 031802 (2007). <lb/>[6] B. Aubert et al. (BaBar Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>99, 171803 (2007). <lb/>[7] This analysis is improved compared to our previous pub-<lb/>lication [4]. The peaking backgrounds are estimated di-<lb/>rectly from the data sidebands. The signal and peaking <lb/>fraction in the time-dependent PDF are determined for <lb/>each r-bin. In addition to the lepton tracks from the J/ψ, <lb/>we use the prompt π + π − tracks in the vertex reconstruc-<lb/>tion for the ψ(2S)(J/ψπ + π − )K 0 <lb/>S decay mode. Only lep-<lb/>ton tracks from the J/ψ were used in the previous anal-<lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>ysis. <lb/>[8] S. Kurokawa and E. Kikutani, Nucl. Instrum. Methods <lb/>Phys. Res., Sect. A 499, 1 (2003), and other papers in-<lb/>cluded in this volume. <lb/>[9] A. Abashian et al. (Belle Collaboration), Nucl. Instrum. <lb/>Methods Phys. Res., Sect. A 479, 117 (2002). <lb/>[10] Z. Natkaniec (Belle SVD2 Group), Nucl. Instrum. Meth-<lb/>ods Phys. Res., Sect. A 560, 1 (2006). <lb/>[11] W.-M. Yao et al., J. Phys. G 33, 1 (2006). <lb/>[12] K-F. Chen et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 72, <lb/>012004 (2005). <lb/>[13] G. C. Fox and S. Wolfram, Phys. Rev. Lett. 41, 1581 <lb/>(1978). <lb/>[14] H. Kakuno et al., Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., <lb/>Sect. A 533, 516 (2004). <lb/>[15] H. Tajima et al., Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., <lb/>Sect. A 533, 370 (2004). <lb/>[16] H. Albrecht et al. (ARGUS Collaboration), Phys. Lett. <lb/>B 241, 278 (1990). <lb/>[17] Throughout this paper, the inclusion of the charge-<lb/>conjugate decay mode is implied unless otherwise stated. <lb/>[18] O. Long, M. Baak, R. N. Cahn and D. Kirkby, Phys. <lb/>Rev. D 68, 034010 (2003). <lb/>[19] See http://www.slac.stanford.edu/xorg/hfag/ for up-<lb/>dated results. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
