<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Measurement of the cross section for W-boson production in association <lb/>with jets in p <lb/>p collisions at <lb/>s <lb/>p 1:96 TeV <lb/> T. Aaltonen, 23 J. Adelman, 13 T. Akimoto, 54 M. G. Albrow, 17 B. A ´lvarez Gonza ´lez, 11 S. Amerio, 42 D. Amidei, 34 <lb/>A. Anastassov, 51 A. Annovi, 19 J. Antos, 14 M. Aoki, 24 G. Apollinari, 17 A. Apresyan, 47 T. Arisawa, 56 A. Artikov, 15 <lb/>W. Ashmanskas, 17 A. Attal, 3 A. Aurisano, 52 F. Azfar, 41 P. Azzi-Bacchetta, 42 P. Azzurri, 45 N. Bacchetta, 42 W. Badgett, <lb/>A. Barbaro-Galtieri, 28 V. E. Barnes, 47 B. A. Barnett, 25 S. Baroiant, 7 V. Bartsch, 30 G. Bauer, 32 P.-H. Beauchemin, 33 <lb/>F. Bedeschi, 45 P. Bednar, 14 S. Behari, 25 G. Bellettini, 45 J. Bellinger, 58 A. Belloni, 22 D. Benjamin, 16 A. Beretvas, 17 <lb/>J. Beringer, 28 T. Berry, 29 A. Bhatti, 49 M. Binkley, 17 D. Bisello, 42 I. Bizjak, 30 R. E. Blair, 2 C. Blocker, 6 B. Blumenfeld, <lb/>A. Bocci, 16 A. Bodek, 48 V. Boisvert, 48 G. Bolla, 47 A. Bolshov, 32 D. Bortoletto, 47 J. Boudreau, 46 A. Boveia, 10 B. Brau, <lb/>A. Bridgeman, 24 L. Brigliadori, 5 C. Bromberg, 35 E. Brubaker, 13 J. Budagov, 15 H. S. Budd, 48 S. Budd, 24 K. Burkett, 17 <lb/>G. Busetto, 42 P. Bussey, 21 A. Buzatu, 33 K. L. Byrum, 2 S. Cabrera, 16,s M. Campanelli, 35 M. Campbell, 34 F. Canelli, 17 <lb/>A. Canepa, 44 D. Carlsmith, 58 R. Carosi, 45 S. Carrillo, 18,m S. Carron, 33 B. Casal, 11 M. Casarsa, 17 A. Castro, 5 P. Catastini, <lb/>D. Cauz, 53 M. Cavalli-Sforza, 3 A. Cerri, 28 L. Cerrito, 30,q S. H. Chang, 27 Y. C. Chen, 1 M. Chertok, 7 G. Chiarelli, 45 <lb/>G. Chlachidze, 17 F. Chlebana, 17 K. Cho, 27 D. Chokheli, 15 J. P. Chou, 22 G. Choudalakis, 32 S. H. Chuang, 51 K. Chung, 12 <lb/>W. H. Chung, 58 Y. S. Chung, 48 C. I. Ciobanu, 24 M. A. Ciocci, 45 A. Clark, 20 D. Clark, 6 G. Compostella, 42 M. E. Convery, <lb/>J. Conway, 7 B. Cooper, 30 K. Copic, 34 M. Cordelli, 19 G. Cortiana, 42 F. Crescioli, 45 C. Cuenca Almenar, 7,s J. Cuevas, 11,p <lb/>R. Culbertson, 17 J. C. Cully, 34 D. Dagenhart, 17 M. Datta, 17 T. Davies, 21 P. de Barbaro, 48 S. De Cecco, 50 A. Deisher, 28 <lb/>G. De Lentdecker, 48,e G. De Lorenzo, 3 M. Dell&apos;Orso, 45 L. Demortier, 49 J. Deng, 16 M. Deninno, 5 D. De Pedis, 50 <lb/>P. F. Derwent, 17 G. P. Di Giovanni, 43 C. Dionisi, 50 B. Di Ruzza, 53 J. R. Dittmann, 4 M. D&apos;Onofrio, 3 S. Donati, 45 P. Dong, <lb/>J. Donini, 42 T. Dorigo, 42 S. Dube, 51 J. Efron, 38 R. Erbacher, 7 D. Errede, 24 S. Errede, 24 R. Eusebi, 17 H. C. Fang, 28 <lb/>S. Farrington, 29 W. T. Fedorko, 13 R. G. Feild, 59 M. Feindt, 26 J. P. Fernandez, 31 C. Ferrazza, 45 R. Field, 18 G. Flanagan, <lb/>R. Forrest, 7 S. Forrester, 7 M. Franklin, 22 J. C. Freeman, 28 I. Furic, 18 M. Gallinaro, 49 J. Galyardt, 12 F. Garberson, 10 <lb/>J. E. Garcia, 45 A. F. Garfinkel, 47 H. Gerberich, 24 D. Gerdes, 34 S. Giagu, 50 V. Giakoumopolou, 45,b P. Giannetti, 45 <lb/>K. Gibson, 46 J. L. Gimmell, 48 C. M. Ginsburg, 17 N. Giokaris, 15,b M. Giordani, 53 P. Giromini, 19 M. Giunta, 45 V. Glagolev, <lb/>D. Glenzinski, 17 M. Gold, 36 N. Goldschmidt, 18 A. Golossanov, 17 G. Gomez, 11 G. Gomez-Ceballos, 32 M. Goncharov, 52 <lb/>O. Gonza ´lez, 31 I. Gorelov, 36 A. T. Goshaw, 16 K. Goulianos, 49 A. Gresele, 42 S. Grinstein, 22 C. Grosso-Pilcher, 13 <lb/>R. C. Group, 17 U. Grundler, 24 J. Guimaraes da Costa, 22 Z. Gunay-Unalan, 35 C. Haber, 28 K. Hahn, 32 S. R. Hahn, 17 <lb/>E. Halkiadakis, 51 A. Hamilton, 20 B.-Y. Han, 48 J. Y. Han, 48 R. Handler, 58 F. Happacher, 19 K. Hara, 54 D. Hare, 51 M. Hare, <lb/>S. Harper, 41 R. F. Harr, 57 R. M. Harris, 17 M. Hartz, 46 K. Hatakeyama, 49 J. Hauser, 8 C. Hays, 41 M. Heck, 26 A. Heijboer, <lb/>B. Heinemann, 28 J. Heinrich, 44 C. Henderson, 32 M. Herndon, 58 J. Heuser, 26 S. Hewamanage, 4 D. Hidas, 16 C. S. Hill, 10,d <lb/>D. Hirschbuehl, 26 A. Hocker, 17 S. Hou, 1 M. Houlden, 29 S.-C. Hsu, 9 B. T. Huffman, 41 R. E. Hughes, 38 U. Husemann, 59 <lb/>J. Huston, 35 J. Incandela, 10 G. Introzzi, 45 M. Iori, 50 A. Ivanov, 7 B. Iyutin, 32 E. James, 17 B. Jayatilaka, 16 D. Jeans, 50 <lb/>E. J. Jeon, 27 S. Jindariani, 18 W. Johnson, 7 M. Jones, 47 K. K. Joo, 27 S. Y. Jun, 12 J. E. Jung, 27 T. R. Junk, 24 T. Kamon, 52 <lb/>D. Kar, 18 P. E. Karchin, 57 Y. Kato, 40 R. Kephart, 17 U. Kerzel, 26 V. Khotilovich, 52 B. Kilminster, 38 D. H. Kim, 27 <lb/>H. S. Kim, 27 J. E. Kim, 27 M. J. Kim, 17 S. B. Kim, 27 S. H. Kim, 54 Y. K. Kim, 13 N. Kimura, 54 L. Kirsch, 6 S. Klimenko, 18 <lb/>M. Klute, 32 B. Knuteson, 32 B. R. Ko, 16 S. A. Koay, 10 K. Kondo, 56 D. J. Kong, 27 J. Konigsberg, 18 A. Korytov, 18 <lb/>A. V. Kotwal, 16 J. Kraus, 24 M. Kreps, 26 J. Kroll, 44 N. Krumnack, 4 M. Kruse, 16 V. Krutelyov, 10 T. Kubo, 54 S. E. Kuhlmann, <lb/>T. Kuhr, 26 N. P. Kulkarni, 57 Y. Kusakabe, 56 S. Kwang, 13 A. T. Laasanen, 47 S. Lai, 33 S. Lami, 45 S. Lammel, 17 <lb/>M. Lancaster, 30 R. L. Lander, 7 K. Lannon, 38 A. Lath, 51 G. Latino, 45 I. Lazzizzera, 42 T. LeCompte, 2 J. Lee, 48 J. Lee, 27 <lb/>Y. J. Lee, 27 S. W. Lee, 52,r R. Lefe `vre, 20 N. Leonardo, 32 S. Leone, 45 S. Levy, 13 J. D. Lewis, 17 C. Lin, 59 C. S. Lin, 28 <lb/>J. Linacre, 41 M. Lindgren, 17 E. Lipeles, 9 A. Lister, 7 D. O. Litvintsev, 17 T. Liu, 17 N. S. Lockyer, 44 A. Loginov, 59 M. Loreti, <lb/>L. Lovas, 14 R.-S. Lu, 1 D. Lucchesi, 42 J. Lueck, 26 C. Luci, 50 P. Lujan, 28 P. Lukens, 17 G. Lungu, 18 L. Lyons, 41 J. Lys, 28 <lb/>R. Lysak, 14 E. Lytken, 47 P. Mack, 26 D. MacQueen, 33 R. Madrak, 17 K. Maeshima, 17 K. Makhoul, 32 T. Maki, 23 <lb/>P. Maksimovic, 25 S. Malde, 41 S. Malik, 30 G. Manca, 29 A. Manousakis, 15,b F. Margaroli, 47 C. Marino, 26 C. P. Marino, 24 <lb/>A. Martin, 59 M. Martin, 25 V. Martin, 21,k M. Martı ´nez, 3 R. Martı ´nez-Balları ´n, 31 T. Maruyama, 54 P. Mastrandrea, 50 <lb/>T. Masubuchi, 54 M. E. Mattson, 57 P. Mazzanti, 5 K. S. McFarland, 48 P. McIntyre, 52 R. McNulty, 29,j A. Mehta, 29 <lb/>P. Mehtala, 23 S. Menzemer, 11,l A. Menzione, 45 P. Merkel, 47 C. Mesropian, 49 A. Messina, 35 T. Miao, 17 N. Miladinovic, <lb/>J. Miles, 32 R. Miller, 35 C. Mills, 22 M. Milnik, 26 A. Mitra, 1 G. Mitselmakher, 18 H. Miyake, 54 S. Moed, 22 N. Moggi, 5 <lb/>C. S. Moon, 27 R. Moore, 17 M. Morello, 45 P. Movilla Fernandez, 28 J. Mu ¨lmensta ¨dt, 28 A. Mukherjee, 17 Th. Muller, 26 <lb/>R. Mumford, 25 P. Murat, 17 M. Mussini, 5 J. Nachtman, 17 Y. Nagai, 54 A. Nagano, 54 J. Naganoma, 56 K. Nakamura, 54 <lb/> PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 011108(R) (2008) <lb/>RAPID COMMUNICATIONS <lb/>1550-7998= 2008=77(1)=011108(9) <lb/>011108-1 <lb/>© 2008 The American Physical Society <lb/> I. Nakano, 39 A. Napier, 55 V. Necula, 16 C. Neu, 44 M. S. Neubauer, 24 J. Nielsen, 28,g L. Nodulman, 2 M. Norman, 9 <lb/>O. Norniella, 24 E. Nurse, 30 S. H. Oh, 16 Y. D. Oh, 27 I. Oksuzian, 18 T. Okusawa, 40 R. Oldeman, 29 R. Orava, 23 K. Osterberg, <lb/>S. Pagan Griso, 42 C. Pagliarone, 45 E. Palencia, 17 V. Papadimitriou, 17 A. Papaikonomou, 26 A. A. Paramonov, 13 B. Parks, <lb/>S. Pashapour, 33 J. Patrick, 17 G. Pauletta, 53 M. Paulini, 12 C. Paus, 32 D. E. Pellett, 7 A. Penzo, 53 T. J. Phillips, 16 <lb/>G. Piacentino, 45 J. Piedra, 43 L. Pinera, 18 K. Pitts, 24 C. Plager, 8 L. Pondrom, 58 X. Portell, 3 O. Poukhov, 15 N. Pounder, 41 <lb/>F. Prakoshyn, 15 A. Pronko, 17 J. Proudfoot, 2 F. Ptohos, 17,i G. Punzi, 45 J. Pursley, 58 J. Rademacker, 41,d A. Rahaman, 46 <lb/>V. Ramakrishnan, 58 N. Ranjan, 47 I. Redondo, 31 B. Reisert, 17 V. Rekovic, 36 P. Renton, 41 M. Rescigno, 50 S. Richter, 26 <lb/>F. Rimondi, 5 L. Ristori, 45 A. Robson, 21 T. Rodrigo, 11 E. Rogers, 24 S. Rolli, 55 R. Roser, 17 M. Rossi, 53 R. Rossin, 10 P. Roy, <lb/>A. Ruiz, 11 J. Russ, 12 V. Rusu, 17 H. Saarikko, 23 A. Safonov, 52 W. K. Sakumoto, 48 G. Salamanna, 50 O. Salto ´,3 L. Santi, 53 <lb/>S. Sarkar, 50 L. Sartori, 45 K. Sato, 17 A. Savoy-Navarro, 43 T. Scheidle, 26 P. Schlabach, 17 E. E. Schmidt, 17 M. A. Schmidt, <lb/>M. P. Schmidt, 59 M. Schmitt, 37 T. Schwarz, 7 L. Scodellaro, 11 A. L. Scott, 10 A. Scribano, 45 F. Scuri, 45 A. Sedov, 47 <lb/>S. Seidel, 36 Y. Seiya, 40 A. Semenov, 15 L. Sexton-Kennedy, 17 A. Sfyria, 20 S. Z. Shalhout, 57 M. D. Shapiro, 28 T. Shears, <lb/>P. F. Shepard, 46 D. Sherman, 22 M. Shimojima, 54,o M. Shochet, 13 Y. Shon, 58 I. Shreyber, 20 A. Sidoti, 45 P. Sinervo, 33 <lb/>A. Sisakyan, 15 A. J. Slaughter, 17 J. Slaunwhite, 38 K. Sliwa, 55 J. R. Smith, 7 F. D. Snider, 17 R. Snihur, 33 M. Soderberg, 34 <lb/>A. Soha, 7 S. Somalwar, 51 V. Sorin, 35 J. Spalding, 17 F. Spinella, 45 T. Spreitzer, 33 P. Squillacioti, 45 M. Stanitzki, 59 <lb/>R. St. Denis, 21 B. Stelzer, 8 O. Stelzer-Chilton, 41 D. Stentz, 37 J. Strologas, 36 D. Stuart, 10 J. S. Suh, 27 A. Sukhanov, 18 <lb/>H. Sun, 55 I. Suslov, 15 T. Suzuki, 54 A. Taffard, 24,f R. Takashima, 39 Y. Takeuchi, 54 R. Tanaka, 39 M. Tecchio, 34 P. K. Teng, <lb/>K. Terashi, 49 J. Thom, 17,h A. S. Thompson, 21 G. A. Thompson, 24 E. Thomson, 44 P. Tipton, 59 V. Tiwari, 12 S. Tkaczyk, 17 <lb/>D. Toback, 52 S. Tokar, 14 K. Tollefson, 35 T. Tomura, 54 D. Tonelli, 17 S. Torre, 19 D. Torretta, 17 S. Tourneur, 43 W. Trischuk, <lb/>Y. Tu, 44 N. Turini, 45 F. Ukegawa, 54 S. Uozumi, 54 S. Vallecorsa, 20 N. van Remortel, 23 A. Varganov, 34 E. Vataga, 36 <lb/>F. Va ´zquez, 18,m G. Velev, 17 C. Vellidis, 45,b V. Veszpremi, 47 M. Vidal, 31 R. Vidal, 17 I. Vila, 11 R. Vilar, 11 T. Vine, 30 <lb/>M. Vogel, 36 I. Volobouev, 28,r G. Volpi, 45 F. Wu ¨rthwein, 9 P. Wagner, 44 R. G. Wagner, 2 R. L. Wagner, 17 J. Wagner-Kuhr, <lb/>W. Wagner, 26 T. Wakisaka, 40 R. Wallny, 8 S. M. Wang, 1 A. Warburton, 33 D. Waters, 30 M. Weinberger, 52 W. C. Wester III, <lb/>B. Whitehouse, 55 D. Whiteson, 44,f A. B. Wicklund, 2 E. Wicklund, 17 G. Williams, 33 H. H. Williams, 44 P. Wilson, 17 <lb/>B. L. Winer, 38 P. Wittich, 17,h S. Wolbers, 17 C. Wolfe, 13 T. Wright, 34 X. Wu, 20 S. M. Wynne, 29 A. Yagil, 9 K. Yamamoto, <lb/>J. Yamaoka, 51 T. Yamashita, 39 C. Yang, 59 U. K. Yang, 13,n Y. C. Yang, 27 W. M. Yao, 28 G. P. Yeh, 17 J. Yoh, 17 K. Yorita, 13 <lb/>T. Yoshida, 40 G. B. Yu, 48 I. Yu, 27 S. S. Yu, 17 J. C. Yun, 17 L. Zanello, 50 A. Zanetti, 53 I. Zaw, 22 X. Zhang, 24 <lb/>Y. Zheng, 8,c and S. Zucchelli 5 <lb/>
            (CDF Collaboration) a <lb/>1 Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica, Taipei, Taiwan 11529, Republic of China <lb/>2 <lb/>Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, Illinois 60439, USA <lb/>3 <lb/>Institut de Fisica d&apos;Altes Energies, Universitat Autonoma de Barcelona, E-08193, Bellaterra (Barcelona), Spain <lb/>4 Baylor University, Waco, Texas 76798, USA <lb/>5 <lb/>Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare, University of Bologna, I-40127 Bologna, Italy <lb/>6 <lb/>Brandeis University, Waltham, Massachusetts 02254, USA <lb/>7 <lb/>University of California, Davis, Davis, California 95616, USA <lb/>8 University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California 90024, USA <lb/>9 <lb/>University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, California 92093, USA <lb/>10 <lb/>University of California, Santa Barbara, Santa Barbara, California 93106, USA <lb/>11 <lb/>Instituto de Fisica de Cantabria, CSIC-University of Cantabria, 39005 Santander, Spain <lb/>12 <lb/>Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania 15213, USA <lb/>13 <lb/>Enrico Fermi Institute, University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois 60637, USA <lb/>14 <lb/>Comenius University, 842 48 Bratislava, Slovakia; Institute of Experimental Physics, 040 01 Kosice, Slovakia <lb/>15 <lb/>Joint Institute for Nuclear Research, RU-141980 Dubna, Russia <lb/>16 <lb/>Duke University, Durham, North Carolina 27708 <lb/>17 <lb/>Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory, Batavia, Illinois 60510, USA <lb/>18 <lb/>University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32611, USA <lb/>19 <lb/>Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare, I-00044 Frascati, Italy <lb/>20 <lb/>University of Geneva, CH-1211 Geneva 4, Switzerland <lb/>21 <lb/>Glasgow University, Glasgow G12 8QQ, United Kingdom <lb/>22 <lb/>Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138, USA <lb/>23 <lb/>Division of High Energy Physics, Department of Physics, University of Helsinki and Helsinki Institute of Physics, <lb/>FIN-00014, Helsinki, Finland <lb/></front>

            <note place="headnote">T. AALTONEN et al. <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 011108(R) (2008) <lb/>RAPID COMMUNICATIONS <lb/></note>

            <page>011108-2 <lb/></page>

            <front>24 <lb/>University of Illinois, Urbana, Illinois 61801, USA <lb/>25 <lb/>The Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland 21218, USA <lb/>26 <lb/>Institut fu ¨r Experimentelle Kernphysik, Universita ¨t Karlsruhe, 76128 Karlsruhe, Germany <lb/>27 <lb/>Center for High Energy Physics: Kyungpook National University, Daegu 702-701, Korea; <lb/>Seoul National University, Seoul 151-742, Korea; <lb/>Sungkyunkwan University, Suwon 440-746, Korea; <lb/>Korea Institute of Science and Technology Information, Daejeon, 305-806, Korea; <lb/>Chonnam National University, Gwangju, 500-757, Korea <lb/>28 <lb/>Ernest Orlando Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, California 94720, USA <lb/>29 <lb/>University of Liverpool, Liverpool L69 7ZE, United Kingdom <lb/>30 <lb/>University College London, London WC1E 6BT, United Kingdom <lb/>31 <lb/>Centro de Investigaciones Energeticas Medioambientales y Tecnologicas, E-28040 Madrid, Spain <lb/>32 Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139, USA <lb/>33 <lb/>Institute of Particle Physics: McGill University, Montre ´al, Canada H3A 2T8; <lb/>and University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada M5S 1A7 <lb/>34 <lb/>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109, USA <lb/>35 <lb/>Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan 48824, USA <lb/>36 <lb/>University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, New Mexico 87131, USA <lb/>37 <lb/>Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois 60208, USA <lb/>38 <lb/>The Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio 43210, USA <lb/>39 <lb/>Okayama University, Okayama 700-8530, Japan <lb/>40 <lb/>Osaka City University, Osaka 588, Japan <lb/>41 <lb/>University of Oxford, Oxford OX1 3RH, United Kingdom <lb/>42 <lb/>University of Padova, Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare, Sezione di Padova-Trento, I-35131 Padova, Italy <lb/>43 <lb/>LPNHE, Universite Pierre et Marie Curie/IN2P3-CNRS, UMR7585, Paris, F-75252 France <lb/>44 <lb/>University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104, USA <lb/>45 <lb/>Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare Pisa, Universities of Pisa, Siena <lb/>and Scuola Normale Superiore, I-56127 Pisa, Italy <lb/>46 <lb/>University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania 15260, USA <lb/>47 <lb/>Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana 47907, USA <lb/>48 University of Rochester, Rochester, New York 14627, USA <lb/>49 The Rockefeller University, New York, New York 10021, USA <lb/>50 <lb/>Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare, Sezione di Roma 1, University of Rome &apos;&apos;La Sapienza,&apos;&apos; I-00185 Roma, Italy <lb/>51 Rutgers University, Piscataway, New Jersey 08855, USA <lb/>52 <lb/>Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, Texas 77843, USA <lb/>53 Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare, University of Trieste/Udine, Italy <lb/>54 <lb/>University of Tsukuba, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305, Japan <lb/>55 <lb/>Tufts University, Medford, Massachusetts 02155, USA <lb/>s IFIC(CSIC-Universitat de Valencia), 46071 Valencia, Spain. <lb/>r Texas Tech University, Lubbock, TX 79409., USA <lb/>q Queen Mary, University of London, London, E1 4NS, England. <lb/>p University de Oviedo, E-33007 Oviedo, Spain. <lb/>o Nagasaki Institute of Applied Science, Nagasaki, Japan. <lb/>n University of Manchester, Manchester M13 9PL, England. <lb/>m Universidad Iberoamericana, Mexico D.F., Mexico. <lb/>l University of Heidelberg, D-69120 Heidelberg, Germany. <lb/>k University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh EH9 3JZ, United Kingdom. <lb/>j University College Dublin, Dublin 4, Ireland. <lb/>i University of Cyprus, Nicosia CY-1678, Cyprus. <lb/>h Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853., USA <lb/>g University of California Santa Cruz, Santa Cruz, CA 95064., USA <lb/>f University of California Irvine, Irvine, CA 92697., USA <lb/>e University Libre de Bruxelles, B-1050 Brussels, Belgium. <lb/>d University of Bristol, Bristol BS8 1TL, United Kingdom. <lb/>c Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100864, China. <lb/>b University of Athens, 15784 Athens, Greece. <lb/>a With visitors from <lb/></front>

            <note place="headnote">MEASUREMENT OF THE CROSS SECTION FOR W-. . . <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 011108(R) (2008) <lb/>RAPID COMMUNICATIONS <lb/></note>

            <page>011108-3 <lb/></page>

            <front>56 <lb/>Waseda University, Tokyo 169, Japan <lb/>57 Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan 48201, USA <lb/>58 <lb/>University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin 53706, USA <lb/>59 Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut 06520, USA <lb/>(Received 26 November 2007; published 31 January 2008) <lb/> We present a measurement of the cross section for W-boson production in association with jets in p <lb/>p <lb/>collisions at <lb/>s <lb/>p 1:96 TeV. The analysis uses a data sample corresponding to an integrated luminosity of <lb/>320 pb ÿ1 collected with the CDF II detector. W bosons are identified in their electron decay channel and <lb/>jets are reconstructed using a cone algorithm. For each W n-jet sample (n 1 ÿ 4) we measure the <lb/>differential cross section dp <lb/>p ! W n-jet=dE nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>BW ! e with respect to the transverse <lb/>energy E T of the nth-highest E T jet above 20 GeV, and the total cross section p <lb/>p ! W <lb/>n-jet; E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>&gt; 25 GeV BW ! e, for a restricted W ! e decay phase space. The cross sections, <lb/>corrected for all detector effects, can be directly compared to particle level W jets predictions. We <lb/>present here comparisons to leading order and next-to-leading order predictions. <lb/>DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.77.011108 <lb/>PACS numbers: 14.70.Fm, 12.38.Qk, 13.85.Ni, 13.87.Ce <lb/></front>

            <body>Final states containing a vector boson V (V W, Z) and <lb/>multiple jets [V jets] are a key signal channel for <lb/>important standard model (SM) processes such as t <lb/>t or <lb/>single top production, as well as a search channel for the <lb/>Higgs boson and for physics beyond the SM. The produc-<lb/>tion of V jets via quantum chromodynamics (QCD) <lb/>presents a very large background to these processes. The <lb/>ability to describe it accurately is therefore crucial, as well <lb/>as being a stringent test of the power of perturbative QCD <lb/>predictions. Consequently, a precise measurement of the <lb/>cross section for QCD V jets production is an impor-<lb/>tant component of the hadron collider experimental pro-<lb/>gram. In this paper, we report a measurement [1] of the <lb/>differential cross sections for direct W ! e n-jet <lb/>production as a function of the transverse energy E jet <lb/>T [2] <lb/>of the nth-leading jet (the highest E T jet for W 1-jet, <lb/>the second highest E T jet for W 2-jet, etc.), for n <lb/>1 ÿ 4 and E jet <lb/>T &gt; 20 GeV. We also provide the total cross <lb/>section <lb/>n W ! e n-jet; E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>&gt; 25 GeV <lb/>for n 1 ÿ 4. In order to minimize the dependence of <lb/>the measurement on the modeling of the W boson produc-<lb/>tion and decay kinematics, we quote cross sections defined <lb/>within a limited W decay phase space: E ele <lb/>T &gt; 20 GeV, <lb/>j ele j &lt; 1:1, E <lb/>T &gt; 30 GeV, and m W <lb/>T &gt; 20 GeV=c 2 [2]. <lb/>The range of E jet <lb/>T extends up to 350 GeV in the W 1-jet <lb/>sample, a significant increase in the measured phase space <lb/>compared to previous V jets measurements [3,4]. <lb/>Furthermore, the differential spectra presented here are <lb/>for the first time corrected for all detector effects and <lb/>represent absolute particle level cross sections [5] free, <lb/>within systematic uncertainties, of any experimental bias. <lb/>As such, they provide a benchmark which can be directly <lb/>used for background estimates and for the validation and <lb/>tuning of QCD phenomenological models. At the end of <lb/>this paper we present, as examples, comparisons of our <lb/>results with some of the available predictions. It is impor-<lb/>tant to note that the cross section is not corrected for effects <lb/>resulting from the interaction between the proton and <lb/>antiproton remnants (the &apos;&apos;underlying event&apos;&apos;). Such a <lb/>correction would introduce into the measurement a depen-<lb/>dence on theoretical models of the underlying event. <lb/>This analysis uses 320 18 pb ÿ1 of data collected us-<lb/>ing the CDF II [6] detector during the Tevatron Run II <lb/>period. The CDF II detector is a general-purpose detector <lb/>designed to study p <lb/>p collisions at the Fermilab Tevatron. <lb/>Inside a 1.4 T solenoidal magnetic field, a large open-cell <lb/>drift chamber and an eight-layer silicon system provide <lb/>precise charged-particle tracking information. Outside the <lb/>solenoid electromagnetic and hadronic sampling calorim-<lb/>eters surround the tracking volume, allowing for the mea-<lb/>surement of particle energies over the range jj &lt; 3:6. <lb/>Finely segmented detectors located at electromagnetic <lb/>shower maximum are used for electron identification. <lb/>Forward gas Cerenkov detectors measure the fraction of <lb/>bunch crossings that result in an inelastic p <lb/>p collision and <lb/>thereby determine the instantaneous luminosity delivered <lb/>to the experiment. <lb/>The selection of W ! e events proceeds as follows. An <lb/>online trigger system selects events containing an electro-<lb/>magnetic calorimeter cluster with E T &gt; 18 GeV associ-<lb/>ated with a high p T track. Offline, electron candidates <lb/>are required to pass standard identification cuts [7] and to <lb/>have E ele <lb/>T &gt; 20 GeV. The sample is enriched with events <lb/>containing a neutrino by requiring that the missing trans-<lb/>verse energy E 6 T [2], corrected for the jet energy scale (see <lb/>below) and the potential presence of muons [8], satisfies <lb/>E 6 T &gt; 30 GeV. To reduce background contamination fur-<lb/>ther, the W transverse mass [2] m W <lb/>T is required to satisfy <lb/>m W <lb/>T &gt; 20 GeV=c 2 . In addition, Z ! e e ÿ events are re-<lb/>jected by a veto algorithm [7]. <lb/>The jets in each W ! e event are reconstructed using <lb/>the JETCLU cone algorithm [9] with cone radius R <lb/>2 2 <lb/>p <lb/>0:4. Starting from seed locations corre-<lb/>sponding to calorimeter towers with E T &gt; 1 GeV, all <lb/>nearby towers with E T &gt; 0:1 GeV are used to search for <lb/>stable cones. To resolve ambiguities with overlapping <lb/>cones, cones sharing an energy fraction greater than 0.75 <lb/>are merged into a single jet; otherwise the shared towers <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T. AALTONEN et al. <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 011108(R) (2008) <lb/>RAPID COMMUNICATIONS <lb/></note>

            <page>011108-4 <lb/></page>

			<body>are assigned to the closest jet. We apply a jet energy scale <lb/>(JES) correction [10] such that the measured E jet <lb/>T is on <lb/>average equal to the summed E T of the particles within <lb/>the jet cone that are the result of the p <lb/>p ! W X inter-<lb/>action. Jets are required to have E jet <lb/>T &gt; 20 GeV and jj &lt; <lb/>2:0. <lb/>To ensure negligible overlap of electron and jet energy <lb/>deposits, events are rejected if any jet lies within R <lb/>0:52 of the W decay electron [3]. Using this jet definition, <lb/>we divide the inclusive W ! e candidate events into <lb/>W n-jet samples, and in each sample form the E jet <lb/>T <lb/>spectrum of the nth E T -ordered jet. <lb/>The processes which contribute background events to <lb/>our W candidate sample can be divided into two categories: <lb/>&apos;&apos;leptonic&apos;&apos; and &apos;&apos;multijet.&apos;&apos; The leptonic background con-<lb/>tains real electrons and/or neutrinos from boson decay and <lb/>includes W ! , Z ! e e ÿ , WW, W, and top pair <lb/>production. The multijet background arises from QCD <lb/>interaction events in which one or more jets are incorrectly <lb/>reconstructed in the detector as electrons and have mis-<lb/>measured energy, resulting in large event E 6 T . Background <lb/>estimation proceeds as follows. For each W n-jet <lb/>sample, a background-enriched event sample is con-<lb/>structed by removing the E 6 T &gt; 30 GeV requirement in <lb/>the W selection. Multijet, leptonic, and signal E 6 T histo-<lb/>grams are then fit to the data in the range [0, 100] GeV. The <lb/>measured E 6 T spectrum, and the result of the fit, are shown <lb/>in Fig. 1 for the W 1-jet sample. For this fit the <lb/>leptonic background and signal processes are modeled by <lb/>applying the W event selection minus the E 6 T &gt; 30 GeV <lb/>requirement to detector simulated Monte Carlo event <lb/>samples of these processes. The multijet background is <lb/>modeled using an event sample selected from the same <lb/>320 pb ÿ1 analysis dataset by requiring that at least two of <lb/>the electron identification criteria fail. Kinematic cuts are <lb/>unchanged, resulting in a background-dominated sample <lb/>that accurately reflects the kinematic distributions of the <lb/>multijet background events in the signal sample. It is <lb/>necessary to correct this multijet sample for 5% contami-<lb/>nation from signal and leptonic background events, esti-<lb/>mated by applying the multijet selection criteria to the <lb/>Monte Carlo simulations of these processes. In the fit, <lb/>only the normalizations of the multijet and signal E 6 T histo-<lb/>grams are allowed to float. The normalization of the W ! <lb/>and Z ! e e ÿ histograms relative to the signal is fixed <lb/>by the well-established relationships between these cross <lb/>sections [11]. The normalizations of the WW, W, and top <lb/>pair production histograms are determined using the re-<lb/>cently measured cross sections for these processes [12]. <lb/>Once the fit is performed, the background fractions in each <lb/>W n-jet sample are obtained by integrating the re-<lb/>spective histograms, with their fitted normalization, above <lb/>the E 6 T cut of 30 GeV. These fractions are then used to <lb/>normalize the jet E T distributions of each background <lb/>model relative to the candidates to give the background <lb/>correction as a function of E jet <lb/>T . This method offers a more <lb/>accurate description of the kinematics of the multijet back-<lb/>ground when compared with previous approaches [3]. <lb/>Figure 1 demonstrates a successful modeling of the E 6 T <lb/>spectrum. Similarly good agreement was found in the <lb/>electron E T and m W <lb/>T <lb/>distributions across all jet <lb/>multiplicities. <lb/>Rarely, reconstructed jets may originate from separate <lb/>p <lb/>p interactions in the same bunch crossing. To account for <lb/>this effect, corrections to the measured cross sections are <lb/>computed by multiplying the number of overlapping p <lb/>p <lb/>interactions, estimated using the primary vertex multiplic-<lb/>ity in the signal sample, with the rate of jet production in <lb/>&apos;&apos;minimum-bias&apos;&apos; events selected independently of activity <lb/>in the central detector. The corrections are less than 2% in <lb/>the lowest E jet <lb/>T bins and decrease rapidly with increasing <lb/>E jet <lb/>T . <lb/>The total background fraction increases with increasing <lb/>jet multiplicity and transverse energy. At low E jet <lb/>T it is 10% <lb/>(40%) in the 1-jet (4-jet) sample, rising to 90% at the <lb/>highest E jet <lb/>T for all jet multiplicities. Multijet events con-<lb/>tribute 70% of the overall background in the 1-jet sam-<lb/>ple. At high jet multiplicities and high E jet <lb/>T the contribution <lb/>from top pair production becomes increasingly important, <lb/>climbing to 50% (80%) of the total background in the 2-jet <lb/>(3, 4-jet) sample. The systematic uncertainty on the back-<lb/>ground estimate is 15% at low E jet <lb/>T independent of the jet <lb/>multiplicity, rising to 50% (20%) at the highest E jet <lb/>T in the <lb/>1-jet (4-jet) sample. At low jet multiplicities, this is domi-<lb/>nated by the limited statistics of the multijet background <lb/>sample. At high jet multiplicities, the 12% uncertainty on <lb/>the measured top pair production cross section dominates <lb/>the total systematic. <lb/>We have used fully simulated signal Monte Carlo <lb/>samples to correct the event yield for the efficiency of <lb/>the W ! e selection criteria. Samples for each jet multi-<lb/>plicity n were obtained using the ALPGEN v1.3 [13] event <lb/>generator for the W n-parton final state, and the PYTHIA <lb/>v6.3 [14] Monte Carlo program for the parton shower and <lb/>Missing Transverse Energy (GeV) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 <lb/>Events / 2GeV <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>6000 <lb/>7000 <lb/>8000 <lb/>1 jet <lb/>≥ <lb/>) + <lb/>ν <lb/>e <lb/>→ <lb/>W( <lb/>CDF II <lb/>Combined <lb/>W+jet <lb/>multi-jet <lb/>leptonic <lb/>FIG. 1 (color online). The results of fitting the signal and <lb/>background E 6 T template distributions to the data in the W <lb/>1-jet sample before the final E 6 T cut is applied. <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">MEASUREMENT OF THE CROSS SECTION FOR W-. . . <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 011108(R) (2008) <lb/>RAPID COMMUNICATIONS <lb/></note>

            <page>011108-5 <lb/></page>

            <body>hadronization. PYTHIA includes an underlying event model, <lb/>hereafter referred to as TUNE A, which has been tuned to <lb/>describe Tevatron data [15]. The efficiency correction fac-<lb/>tor is defined as the ratio of two subsets of the generated <lb/>signal events: in the numerator, the number of recon-<lb/>structed events which pass the W ! e selection criteria, <lb/>and in the denominator, the number of generator-level <lb/>events which pass the electron, neutrino and transverse-<lb/>mass cuts corresponding to our cross section definition. <lb/>This is found to be 60 3%, independent of event jet <lb/>multiplicity and kinematics within the quoted uncertainty. <lb/>By comparing Z ! e e ÿ measured and simulated event <lb/>samples, we confirm that electron identification efficien-<lb/>cies are well reproduced by our Monte Carlo across all <lb/>measured phase space to within 5%. This uncertainty also <lb/>covers the observed variation in efficiency obtained by <lb/>changing the number of final state partons in the ALPGEN <lb/>matrix element (ME) calculation and the parton showering <lb/>program from PYTHIA to HERWIG v6.5 [16]. Additionally, <lb/>the W candidate event yield must be corrected to account <lb/>for the efficiency of the online trigger to accept high E T <lb/>electrons. This is independent of jet kinematics and found <lb/>to be 96:2 0:6% [7]. <lb/>A further correction to the event yield is required to form <lb/>particle level W ! e n-jet cross sections as a func-<lb/>tion of E jet <lb/>T . This correction factor accounts for the effect of <lb/>calorimeter jet energy resolution on the measured cross <lb/>section and is determined as follows. Using the ALPGEN-<lb/>PYTHIA simulated signal samples, two cross sections in <lb/>each E jet <lb/>T bin are determined: one defined by clustering <lb/>generator-level particles into jets, the other by clustering <lb/>after detector reconstruction, using the same calorimeter <lb/>level jet definition (including JES correction) as the one <lb/>used in the data. The correction factor for each bin is then <lb/>defined as the ratio of the particle to calorimeter level cross <lb/>section in that bin. To avoid dependence of such a correc-<lb/>tion on the assumed particle level E jet <lb/>T distribution, an <lb/>iterative procedure is used to reweight the events at the <lb/>particle level until the particle level E jet <lb/>T distribution agrees <lb/>with the corresponding data-unfolded distribution to within <lb/>the systematic uncertainties of the measurement. The cor-<lb/>rection factors vary between 0.95 and 1.2 over the mea-<lb/>sured range of E jet <lb/>T . <lb/>The total systematic uncertainty on the cross section <lb/>introduced by the jet energy measurement ranges between <lb/>5% and 20%, increasing with increasing E jet <lb/>T . This is domi-<lb/>nated by the approximately 3% [10] uncertainty on the JES <lb/>correction. The effect of this uncertainty on the cross <lb/>section is estimated by applying this variation to an <lb/>ALPGEN-PYTHIA simulated signal sample reweighted to <lb/>match the data. The sensitivity of the measurement to jet <lb/>energy resolution uncertainties, estimated by varying the <lb/>calorimeter resolution in the simulation, is much smaller <lb/>by comparison. <lb/>The measured differential cross sections dW ! <lb/>e n-jet=dE nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>are listed in Table I. For each in-<lb/>clusive jet multiplicity sample the cross sections are given <lb/>with respect to the E T of the nth-leading jet in the sample, <lb/>E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>. The quoted statistical uncertainties are on the event <lb/>yield in each bin. The systematic uncertainties are the sum <lb/>in quadrature of the effects introduced by the uncertainty <lb/>on the background estimation, acceptance correction, and <lb/>jet energy measurement. A 5.8% uncertainty in the inte-<lb/>grated luminosity is not included, since this uncertainty is <lb/>completely correlated between different E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>bins. In <lb/>summary, the total systematic uncertainty on the measured <lb/>cross sections is &lt;20% at low E jet <lb/>T increasing to 50%-80% <lb/>TABLE I. The measured cross section dW ! e <lb/>n-jet=dE nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>for each E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>-bin (n 1 ÿ 4), with statistical <lb/>(first) and systematic (second) uncertainties. An overall 5.8% <lb/>uncertainty on the integrated luminosity is not included. <lb/>E 1st-jet <lb/>T <lb/>(GeV) <lb/>d=dE 1st-jet <lb/>T <lb/>(pb/GeV) <lb/>20 ÿ 25 <lb/>4:46 0:07 0:29 <lb/>25 ÿ 30 <lb/>2:80 0:06 0:21 <lb/>30 ÿ 35 <lb/>1:92 0:05 0:17 <lb/>35 ÿ 40 <lb/>1:31 0:04 0:14 <lb/>40 ÿ 50 <lb/>0:839 0:023 0:093 <lb/>50 ÿ 60 <lb/>0:498 0:018 0:063 <lb/>60 ÿ 75 <lb/>0:259 0:011 0:038 <lb/>75 ÿ 90 <lb/>0:158 0:008 0:024 <lb/>90 ÿ 110 <lb/>0:056 0:005 0:011 <lb/>110 ÿ 150 <lb/>0:0225 0:0023 0:0044 <lb/>150 ÿ 195 <lb/>0:0035 0:0011 0:0023 <lb/>195 ÿ 350 <lb/>0:000 39 0:000 22 0:000 38 <lb/>E 2nd-jet <lb/>T <lb/>(GeV) <lb/>d=dE 2nd-jet <lb/>T <lb/>(pb/GeV) <lb/>20 ÿ 25 <lb/>0:874 0:033 0:097 <lb/>25 ÿ 30 <lb/>0:483 0:025 0:066 <lb/>30 ÿ 35 <lb/>0:286 0:020 0:045 <lb/>35 ÿ 40 <lb/>0:190 0:017 0:034 <lb/>40 ÿ 50 <lb/>0:095 0:009 0:019 <lb/>50 ÿ 60 <lb/>0:057 0:007 0:012 <lb/>60 ÿ 75 <lb/>0:0269 0:0046 0:0066 <lb/>75 ÿ 95 <lb/>0:0107 0:0022 0:0028 <lb/>95 ÿ 190 <lb/>0:00059 0:00039 0:00049 <lb/>E 3rd-jet <lb/>T <lb/>(GeV) <lb/>d=dE 3rd-jet <lb/>T <lb/>(pb/GeV) <lb/>20 ÿ 25 <lb/>0:184 0:016 0:036 <lb/>25 ÿ 30 <lb/>0:087 0:012 0:024 <lb/>30 ÿ 35 <lb/>0:037 0:008 0:013 <lb/>35 ÿ 45 <lb/>0:020 0:006 0:011 <lb/>45 ÿ 80 <lb/>0:0015 0:0012 0:0013 <lb/>E 4th-jet <lb/>T <lb/>(GeV) <lb/>d=dE 4th-jet <lb/>T <lb/>(pb/GeV) <lb/>20 ÿ 25 <lb/>0:0422 0:0087 0:0079 <lb/>25 ÿ 35 <lb/>0:0074 0:0039 0:0036 <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">T. AALTONEN et al. <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 011108(R) (2008) <lb/>RAPID COMMUNICATIONS <lb/></note>

            <page>011108-6 <lb/></page>

            <body>at high E jet <lb/>T . At low E jet <lb/>T this is dominated by the <lb/>uncertainty on the jet energy scale, whereas at high E jet <lb/>T <lb/>it is dominated by the background uncertainty. We <lb/>also provide the total cross section n W ! <lb/>e n-jet; E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>&gt; 25 GeV for n 1 ÿ 4: 1 <lb/>53:5 0:6stat 4:6syst 3:1lum pb; 2 6:8 <lb/>0:2stat 1:0syst 0:4lum pb; <lb/>3 0:84 <lb/>0:10stat 0:21syst 0:05lum pb; and 4 <lb/>0:074 0:039stat 0:035syst 0:004lum pb. The <lb/>choice of E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>&gt; 25 GeV is made in order to provide a <lb/>benchmark measurement that is less sensitive to the impact <lb/>of the underlying event, largest at low E jet <lb/>T (see below). We <lb/>include for completeness the total inclusive p <lb/>p ! W <lb/>BW ! e cross section for the restricted W ! e decay <lb/>phase space: 0 798 2stat 40syst 46lum pb. <lb/>We proceed to compare the measured cross sections to <lb/>some of the available theoretical predictions. Leading or-<lb/>der (LO) perturbative QCD calculations exist for the ma-<lb/>trix element of V n partons, with n 6. They are <lb/>included in Monte Carlo event generators [13,17,18] where <lb/>the initial and final state partons are evolved through a <lb/>perturbative parton shower (PS) and eventually hadron-<lb/>ized. Additionally, the generator may include a model of <lb/>the underlying event. In this LO plus PS approach, ambi-<lb/>guities may arise as a result of the hard emission of gluon <lb/>radiation during the parton shower evolution. For example, <lb/>a V n-parton event may be reconstructed, after the <lb/>shower, with a jet multiplicity n j Þ n, and the question <lb/>naturally arises as to whether the event should or should <lb/>not be counted in the estimate of the n j -jet cross section. <lb/>This problem has been studied extensively in the literature, <lb/>leading to the development of three merging algorithms, <lb/>usually known as CKKW [19], Lonnblad&apos;s [20], and MLM <lb/>[21]. A merging algorithm ensures that a given configura-<lb/>tion in the multijet phase space enters into the calculation <lb/>once and only once. <lb/>We present here the first comparisons of W jets <lb/>implementations of the CKKW and MLM schemes to <lb/>data. We use an implementation of the CKKW scheme <lb/>hereafter referred to as SMPR [22]. Details of the genera-<lb/>tion parameters and systematic uncertainties are given in <lb/>[22] for the SMPR model and in [23] for the MLM model. <lb/>The former uses MADGRAPH v4 [17] for the ME generation, <lb/>PYTHIA v6.3 for the PS, and CTEQ6L1 [24] parton distri-<lb/>bution functions (PDFs), the latter uses ALPGEN v2.12, <lb/>HERWIG v6.5, and CTEQ5L [25] PDFs, respectively. <lb/>Following generation, the SMPR and MLM predictions <lb/>are formed by clustering the final state particles into jets <lb/>using the JETCLU algorithm. The uncertainties on these <lb/>predictions cover variation of the renormalization scale <lb/>by a factor 0.5-2. This dominates the overall uncertainty <lb/>in the absolute rates [23]. <lb/>In addition, we present comparisons of our data with <lb/>next-to-leading order (NLO) predictions for W 1 and <lb/>W 2 jets obtained with the MCFM [26] program. These <lb/>were generated using the CTEQ6.1M PDFs [24] and a <lb/>renormalization <lb/>and <lb/>factorization <lb/>scale <lb/>m 2 <lb/>W p W <lb/>T 2 <lb/>q <lb/>. We define an uncertainty due to the choice <lb/>of by generating with a lower scale, p jet <lb/>T , and a <lb/>higher scale, 2 <lb/>m 2 <lb/>W p W <lb/>T 2 <lb/>q <lb/>. Additionally, the <lb/>variation due to the uncertainty on the PDFs has been <lb/>computed using the Hessian method [24]. This PDF un-<lb/>certainty is also broadly applicable to the SMPR and MLM <lb/>predictions. <lb/>In the case of the NLO predictions, the final states are <lb/>not evolved through a parton shower nor hadronized. Jets <lb/>are reconstructed with a cone algorithm R 0:4, such that <lb/>two partons are merged if they are within 1:3 R of each <lb/>other and within R of the resulting jet centroid [27]. This is <lb/>still considered to be sufficient to give a reasonable de-<lb/>scription of the perturbative structure of the jet [28]. <lb/>However, before comparing with data, the nonperturbative <lb/>effects of hadronization and the underlying event have to <lb/>be considered. We have estimated, using PYTHIA TUNE A, <lb/>the impact of these two effects. The effect of the under-<lb/>lying event is to increase the cross section with respect to <lb/>the parton level, while the effect of hadronization is to <lb/>decrease it. The magnitude of both effects decreases <lb/>asymptotically with increasing E jet <lb/>T . Below 50 GeV the <lb/>hadronization effect dominates, leading to an overall de-<lb/>crease of the cross section with respect to the parton level <lb/>that is within 10%. At higher E jet <lb/>T , the correction is driven <lb/>by the underlying event leading to an increase of at most <lb/>5%. A detailed study of this correction is outside the scope <lb/>of this paper, and we do not apply any such corrections to <lb/>the MCFM predictions. <lb/>The upper plot of Fig. 2 shows, as a function of the jet <lb/>multiplicity n, the ratio of data to theory for the total cross <lb/>sections n W ! e n-jet; E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>&gt; 25 GeV. <lb/>Theory <lb/>σ <lb/>/ <lb/>Data <lb/>σ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>MLM uncertainty <lb/>CDF II / MLM <lb/>SMPR uncertainty <lb/>CDF II / SMPR <lb/>CDF II / MCFM <lb/>MCFM Scale uncertainty <lb/>MCFM PDF uncertainty <lb/>Inclusive Jet Multiplicity (n) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>n-1 <lb/>σ <lb/>/ <lb/>n <lb/>σ <lb/>R = <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>CDF II <lb/>MCFM <lb/>MLM <lb/>SMPR <lb/>FIG. 2 (color online). Top: the ratio of data to theory for the <lb/>total cross sections n W ! e n-jet; E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>&gt; <lb/>25 GeV as a function of the jet multiplicity n. Bottom: <lb/>n = nÿ1 for data, MLM, SMPR, and MCFM. Inner (outer) error <lb/>bars denote the statistical (total) uncertainties on the measured <lb/>cross sections. <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">MEASUREMENT OF THE CROSS SECTION FOR W-. . . <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 011108(R) (2008) <lb/>RAPID COMMUNICATIONS <lb/></note>

            <page>011108-7 <lb/></page>

            <body>The lower plot shows the ratio n = nÿ1 . In Fig. 3 <lb/>the ratios of the measured differential cross sections <lb/>dW ! e n-jet=dE nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>to the predictions are <lb/>shown for n 1 ÿ 3. The difference observed in Fig. 2 <lb/>between the measured cross sections and SMPR or MLM <lb/>predictions reflects the LO nature of these calculations. All <lb/>the predictions show good agreement with the data in the <lb/>cross section ratios n = nÿ1 . Figure 3 shows that the <lb/>variation in the W n-jet cross section as a function of <lb/>E jet <lb/>T is better reproduced by the SMPR prediction than by <lb/>the MLM. A possible explanation is the absence of a tuned <lb/>underlying event model in the HERWIG component of the <lb/>MLM prediction. We observe good agreement between the <lb/>MCFM predictions and data in both total and differential <lb/>cross section comparisons. <lb/>In summary, we have used 320 pb ÿ1 of CDF II data to <lb/>measure the differential cross section dp <lb/>p ! W <lb/>n-jet=dE nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>BW ! e as a function of the trans-<lb/>verse energy of the nth-leading jet, and the total cross <lb/>section n p <lb/>p ! W n-jet; E nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>&gt; 25 GeV <lb/>BW ! e, for n 1 ÿ 4 in a restricted W ! e decay <lb/>phase space. The cross sections, corrected for all detector <lb/>effects, can be directly compared to the particle level <lb/>predictions of W jets Monte Carlo generators. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank the Fermilab staff and the technical staffs of <lb/>the participating institutions for their vital contributions. <lb/>We also thank J. Campbell, M. Mangano, and S. Mrenna. <lb/>This work was supported by the U.S. Department of <lb/>Energy and National Science Foundation; the Italian <lb/>Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare; the Ministry of <lb/>Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of <lb/>Japan; the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research <lb/>Council of Canada; the National Science Council of the <lb/>Republic of China; the Swiss National Science <lb/>Foundation; the A. P. Sloan Foundation; the <lb/>Bundesministerium fu ¨r Bildung und Forschung, <lb/>Germany; the Korean Science and Engineering <lb/>Foundation and the Korean Research Foundation; the <lb/>Science and Technology Facilities Council and the Royal <lb/>Society, UK; the Institut National de Physique Nucleaire et <lb/>Physique des Particules/CNRS; the Russian Foundation for <lb/>Basic Research; the Comisio ´n Interministerial de Ciencia y <lb/>Tecnologı ´a, Spain; the European Community&apos;s Human <lb/>Potential Programme; the Slovak R&amp;D Agency; and the <lb/>Academy of Finland. <lb/></div>

            <listBibl>[1] B. Cooper, Ph.D. thesis, University College London, 2006; <lb/>A. Messina, Ph.D. thesis, Universita `di Roma &apos;&apos;La <lb/>Sapienza&apos;&apos;, 2004. <lb/> [2] We use a cylindrical coordinate system along the proton <lb/>direction in which () is the polar (azimuthal) angle. We <lb/>define ÿ lntan=2, p T p sin, E T E sin, <lb/>E 6 T ÿj <lb/>P <lb/>i E i <lb/>T ni j where ni is a unit vector in the azimu-<lb/>thal plane that points from the beamline to the ith calo-<lb/>rimeter tower, and m W <lb/>T <lb/>2E ele <lb/>T E 6 T 1 ÿ cosE ele <lb/>T ;E 6 T <lb/>q <lb/>. <lb/> [3] T. Affolder et al. (CDF Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 63, <lb/>072003 (2001); F. Abe et al. (CDF Collaboration), Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 81, 1367 (1998). <lb/>[4] V. M. Abazov et al. (D0 Collaboration), Phys. Lett. B 658, <lb/>112 (2008). <lb/>[5] A. Abulencia et al. (CDF Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 74, <lb/>071103(R) (2006). <lb/>[6] D. Acosta et al. (CDF Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 71, <lb/>032001 (2005). <lb/></listBibl>

            <body>Theory <lb/>σ <lb/>/ <lb/>Data <lb/>σ <lb/>Theory <lb/>σ <lb/>/ <lb/>Data <lb/>σ <lb/>Theory <lb/>σ <lb/>/ <lb/>Data <lb/>σ <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1.5 <lb/>CDF II / MCFM <lb/>Scale uncertainty <lb/>PDF uncertainty <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>CDF II / MLM <lb/>Scale uncertainty <lb/>(GeV) <lb/>T <lb/>First Jet E <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>350 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>CDF II / SMPR <lb/>Scale uncertainty <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>CDF II / MCFM <lb/>Scale uncertainty <lb/>PDF uncertainty <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>CDF II / MLM <lb/>Scale uncertainty <lb/>(GeV) <lb/>T <lb/>Second Jet E <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>CDF II / SMPR <lb/>Scale uncertainty <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>CDF II / MLM <lb/>Scale uncertainty <lb/>(GeV) <lb/>T <lb/>Third Jet E <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>CDF II / SMPR <lb/>Scale uncertainty <lb/>FIG. 3 (color online). Ratio of the measured cross sections <lb/>dW ! e n-jet=dE nth-jet <lb/>T <lb/>to the MLM, SMPR and MCFM <lb/>predictions for n 1 (top), n 2 (middle) and n 3 (bottom). <lb/>MCFM predictions are not available for n 3. Inner (outer) <lb/>error bars denote the statistical (total) uncertainties on the <lb/>measured cross sections. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T. AALTONEN et al. <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 011108(R) (2008) <lb/>RAPID COMMUNICATIONS <lb/></note>

            <page>011108-8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[7] A. Abulencia et al. (CDF Collaboration), J. Phys. G 34, <lb/>2457 (2007). <lb/>[8] A. Abulencia et al. (CDF Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 74, <lb/>072006 (2006). <lb/>[9] F. Abe et al. (CDF Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 45, 1448 <lb/>(1992). <lb/>[10] A. Bhatti et al., Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., <lb/>Sect. A 566, 375 (2006). <lb/>[11] W.-M. Yao et al., J. Phys. G 33, 1 (2006). <lb/>[12] M. S. Neubauer (CDF and D0 Collaborations), arXiv:hep-<lb/>ex/0605066; A. Abulencia et al. (CDF Collaboration), <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 97, 082004 (2006). <lb/>[13] M. L. Mangano et al., J. High Energy Phys. 07 (2003) 001. <lb/>[14] T. Sjostrand, S. Mrenna, and P. Skands, J. High Energy <lb/>Phys. 05 (2006) 026. <lb/>[15] D. Acosta et al. (CDF Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 70, <lb/>072002 (2004). <lb/>[16] G. Corcella et al., J. High Energy Phys. 01 (2001) 010. <lb/>[17] F. Maltoni and T. Stelzer, J. High Energy Phys. 02 (2003) <lb/>027. <lb/>[18] T. Gleisberg et al., J. High Energy Phys. 02 (2004) 056; N. <lb/>Lavesson and L. Lonnblad, J. High Energy Phys. 07 <lb/>(2005) 054; C. G. Papadopoulos and M. Worek, Eur. <lb/>Phys. J. C 50, 843 (2007). <lb/>[19] S. Catani et al., J. High Energy Phys. 11 (2001) 063; <lb/>F. Krauss, J. High Energy Phys. 08 (2002) 015. <lb/>[20] L. Lonnblad, J. High Energy Phys. 05 (2002) 046. <lb/>[21] M. L. Mangano et al., J. High Energy Phys. 01 (2007) 013. <lb/>[22] S. Mrenna and P. Richardson, J. High Energy Phys. 05 <lb/>(2004) 040. <lb/>[23] J. Alwall et al., arXiv:0706.2569. <lb/>[24] J. Pumplin et al., J. High Energy Phys. 07 (2002) 012. <lb/>[25] H. L. Lai et al., Eur. Phys. J. C 12, 375 (2000). <lb/>[26] J. Campbell and R. K. Ellis, Phys. Rev. D 65, 113007 <lb/>(2002). <lb/>[27] S. D. Ellis and D. E. Soper, Phys. Rev. D 48, 3160 (1993). <lb/>[28] J. M. Campbell, J. W. Huston, and W. J. Stirling, Rep. <lb/>Prog. Phys. 70, 89 (2007). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">MEASUREMENT OF THE CROSS SECTION FOR W-. . . <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 011108(R) (2008) <lb/>RAPID COMMUNICATIONS <lb/></note>

            <page>011108-9 </page>

	</text>
</tei>
