<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:0806.4945v1 [hep-ex] 30 Jun 2008 <lb/>FERMILAB-PUB-08-212-E, BNL-XXXXX-2008-YY, arXiv:ZZZZZZZ [hep-ex] <lb/> Testing Lorentz Invariance and CPT Conservation with NuMI Neutrinos in the <lb/>MINOS Near Detector <lb/>P. Adamson, 9 C. Andreopoulos, 19 K. E. Arms, 15 R. Armstrong, 12 D. J. Auty, 23 D. S. Ayres, 1 B. Baller, 9 G. Barr, 17 <lb/>W. L. Barrett, 28 B. R. Becker, 15 A. Belias, 19 R. H. Bernstein, 9 D. Bhattacharya, 18 M. Bishai, 4 A. Blake, 6 <lb/>G. J. Bock, 9 J. Boehm, 10 D. J. Boehnlein, 9 D. Bogert, 9 C. Bower, 12 E. Buckley-Geer, 9 S. Cavanaugh, 10 <lb/>J. D. Chapman, 6 D. Cherdack, 26 S. Childress, 9 B. C. Choudhary, 9 S. J. Coleman, 29 A. J. Culling, 6 J. K. de Jong, 11 <lb/>M. V. Diwan, 4 M. Dorman, 14, 19 S. A. Dytman, 18 C. O. Escobar, 7 J. J. Evans, 14, 17 E. Falk Harris, 23 <lb/>G. J. Feldman, 10 M. V. Frohne, 3 H. R. Gallagher, 26 M. C. Goodman, 1 P. Gouffon, 20 R. Gran, 16 E. W. Grashorn, 15 <lb/>N. Grossman, 9 K. Grzelak, 27, 17 A. Habig, 16 D. Harris, 9 P. G. Harris, 23 J. Hartnell, 23, 19 R. Hatcher, 9 K. Heller, 15 <lb/>A. Himmel, 5 A. Holin, 14 J. Hylen, 9 G. M. Irwin, 22 M. Ishitsuka, 12 D. E. Jaffe, 4 C. James, 9 D. Jensen, 9 <lb/>T. Kafka, 26 S. M. S. Kasahara, 15 J. J. Kim, 21 G. Koizumi, 9 S. Kopp, 25 M. Kordosky, 29, 14 D. J. Koskinen, 14 <lb/>A. Kreymer, 9 S. Kumaratunga, 15 K. Lang, 25 J. Ling, 21 P. J. Litchfield, 15 R. P. Litchfield, 17 L. Loiacono, 25 <lb/>P. Lucas, 9 J. Ma, 25 W. A. Mann, 26 M. L. Marshak, 15 J. S. Marshall, 6 N. Mayer, 12 A. M. McGowan, 1, 15 <lb/>J. R. Meier, 15 M. D. Messier, 12 C. J. Metelko, 19 D. G. Michael, 5, * J. L. Miller, 13, * W. H. Miller, 15 S. R. Mishra, 21 <lb/>C. D. Moore, 9 J. Morfín, 9 L. Mualem, 5 S. Mufson, 12 S. Murgia, 22 J. Musser, 12 D. Naples, 18 J. K. Nelson, 29 <lb/>H. B. Newman, 5 R. J. Nichol, 14 T. C. Nicholls, 19 J. P. Ochoa-Ricoux, 5 W. P. Oliver, 26 R. Ospanov, 25 <lb/>J. Paley, 12 V. Paolone, 18 A. Para, 9 T. Patzak, 8 Ž. Pavlović, 25 G. Pawloski, 22 G. F. Pearce, 19 C. W. Peck, 5 <lb/>D. A. Petyt, 15 R. Pittam, 17 R. K. Plunkett, 9 A. Rahaman, 21 R. A. Rameika, 9 T. M. Raufer, 19 B. Rebel, 9 <lb/>J. Reichenbacher, 1 P. A. Rodrigues, 17 C. Rosenfeld, 21 H. A. Rubin, 11 M. C. Sanchez, 1, 10 N. Saoulidou, 9 <lb/>J. Schneps, 26 P. Schreiner, 3 P. Shanahan, 9 W. Smart, 9 A. Sousa, 17 B. Speakman, 15 P. Stamoulis, 2 M. Strait, 15 <lb/>N. Tagg, 26 R. L. Talaga, 1 M. A. Tavera, 23 J. Thomas, 14 J. Thompson, 18, * M. A. Thomson, 6 J. L. Thron, 1 <lb/>G. Tinti, 17 G. Tzanakos, 2 J. Urheim, 12 P. Vahle, 29, 14 B. Viren, 4 M. Watabe, 24 A. Weber, 17 R. C. Webb, 24 <lb/>A. Wehmann, 9 N. West, 17 C. White, 11 S. G. Wojcicki, 22 T. Yang, 22 M. Zois, 2 K. Zhang, 4 and R. Zwaska 9 <lb/>(The MINOS Collaboration) <lb/> 1 Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, Illinois 60439, USA <lb/>2 Department of Physics, University of Athens, GR-15771 Athens, Greece <lb/>3 Physics Department, Benedictine University, Lisle, Illinois 60532, USA <lb/>4 Brookhaven National Laboratory, Upton, New York 11973, USA <lb/>5 Lauritsen Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California 91125, USA <lb/>6 Cavendish Laboratory, University of Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 0HE, United Kingdom <lb/>7 Universidade Estadual de Campinas, IF-UNICAMP, CP 6165, 13083-970, Campinas, SP, Brazil <lb/>8 APC -Université Paris 7 Denis Diderot, 10, rue Alice Domon et Léonie Duquet, F-75205 Paris Cedex 13, France <lb/>9 Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory, Batavia, Illinois 60510, USA <lb/>10 Department of Physics, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138, USA <lb/>11 Physics Division, Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, Illinois 60616, USA <lb/>12 Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana 47405, USA <lb/>13 Physics Department, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Virginia 22807, USA <lb/>14 Department of Physics and Astronomy, University College London, Gower Street, London WC1E 6BT, United Kingdom <lb/>15 University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota 55455, USA <lb/>16 Department of Physics, University of Minnesota -Duluth, Duluth, Minnesota 55812, USA <lb/>17 Subdepartment of Particle Physics, University of Oxford, Oxford OX1 3RH, United Kingdom <lb/>18 Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania 15260, USA <lb/>19 Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, Chilton, Didcot, Oxfordshire, OX11 0QX, United Kingdom <lb/>20 Instituto de Física, Universidade de São Paulo, CP 66318, 05315-970, São Paulo, SP, Brazil <lb/>21 Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of South Carolina, Columbia, South Carolina 29208, USA <lb/>22 Department of Physics, Stanford University, Stanford, California 94305, USA <lb/>23 Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Sussex, Falmer, Brighton BN1 9QH, United Kingdom <lb/>24 Physics Department, Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, Texas 77843, USA <lb/>25 Department of Physics, University of Texas at Austin, 1 University Station C1600, Austin, Texas 78712, USA <lb/>26 Physics Department, Tufts University, Medford, Massachusetts 02155, USA <lb/>27 Department of Physics, Warsaw University, Ho ża 69, PL-00-681 Warsaw, Poland <lb/>28 Physics Department, Western Washington University, Bellingham, Washington 98225, USA <lb/>29 Department of Physics, College of William &amp; Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia 23187, USA <lb/>(Dated: August 14, 2019) <lb/>A search for a sidereal modulation in the MINOS near detector neutrino data was performed. If <lb/>present, this signature could be a consequence of Lorentz and CPT violation as predicted by a class <lb/>of extensions to the Standard Model. No evidence for a sidereal signal in the data set was found, <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>implying that there is no significant change in neutrino propagation that depends on the direction of <lb/>the neutrino beam in a sun-centered inertial frame. Upper limits on the magnitudes of the Lorentz <lb/>and CPT violating terms in these extensions to the Standard Model lie between 0.01-1% of the <lb/>maximum expected, assuming a suppression of these signatures by factor of 10 −17 . <lb/>PACS numbers: 11.30.Cp,14.60.Pq <lb/></front>

			<body>At experimentally accessible energies, signals for <lb/>Lorentz and CPT violation can be described by a class <lb/>of extensions to the Standard Model often referred to <lb/>as the SME [1, 2]. This SME theory is an observer-<lb/>independent framework that contains all the Lorentz vio-<lb/>lating (LV) terms involving particle fields in the Standard <lb/>Model of particle physics and gravitational fields in the <lb/>General Theory of Relativity. Since the Standard Model <lb/>is thought to be the low-energy limit of a more funda-<lb/>mental theory that unifies quantum physics and gravity <lb/>at the Planck scale, m P ≃ 10 19 GeV, it is suggested <lb/>in [2] that the violations of Lorentz and CPT symme-<lb/>tries predicted by the SME provide a link to Planck scale <lb/>physics. Although the magnitude of LV signatures in the <lb/>accessible energy limit are suppressed a factor of or-<lb/>der the electroweak scale divided by the Planck scale, <lb/>m W /m P ∼ 10 −17 [3], these low-energy probes of new <lb/>physics have been explored in many ways with current <lb/>experimental technologies [4]. <lb/>The SME framework predicts several unconventional <lb/>phenomena, among which is one that arises from the de-<lb/>pendence of the neutrino oscillation probability on the <lb/>direction of neutrino propagation [3, 5]. For experiments <lb/>like MINOS [6] with both beam neutrino source and de-<lb/>tector fixed on the Earth&apos;s surface, the Earth&apos;s sidereal <lb/>rotation causes the direction of neutrino propagation p to <lb/>change with respect to the Sun-centered inertial frame in <lb/>which the SME is formulated [7]. The theory predicts <lb/>that this rotation introduces a sidereal variation in the <lb/>number of neutrinos detected from the beam. The LSND <lb/>collaboration [7] did not see this signal. In this paper we <lb/>use a sample of neutrinos identified in the MINOS near <lb/>detector (ND) in a search for this sidereal signal. The <lb/>neutrinos were generated by the Neutrinos at the Main <lb/>Injector (NuMI) neutrino beam at Fermilab [8], a beam <lb/>whose flavor composition is 98.7% ν µ + νµ [6]. <lb/>According to the SME, the probability that one of <lb/>these ν µ oscillates to flavor ν x , where x is e or τ , over <lb/>a distance L from its production to detection due to <lb/>Lorentz and CPT violation is given by [5] <lb/>P νµ→νx ≃ L 2 [(C) µx + (A c ) µx cos (ω ⊕ T ⊕ ) <lb/>+(A s ) µx sin (ω ⊕ T ⊕ ) + (B c ) µx cos (2ω ⊕ T ⊕ ) <lb/>+(B s ) µx sin (2ω ⊕ T ⊕ )] 2 , <lb/>(1) <lb/>where ω ⊕ = 2π/(23 h 56 m 04.0982 s ) is the Earth&apos;s side-<lb/>real frequency and T ⊕ is the local sidereal time of the <lb/> * Deceased. <lb/>neutrino detection. For the MINOS ND, &lt; L &gt;∼ 750 m. <lb/>In this equation, the expressions for (A c ) µx , (A s ) µx , and <lb/>(C) µx include both CPT and Lorentz violating terms; the <lb/>expressions for (B c ) µx and (B s ) µx include only Lorentz <lb/>violating terms. Since CPT violation implies Lorentz vi-<lb/>olation in field theory [9], there are no terms that depend <lb/>on CPT violation alone. These parameters are combi-<lb/>nations of the SME coefficients (a L ) µ and (c L ) µν that <lb/>describe LV [5]. The magnitude of the coefficients in <lb/>eq. (1) also depend on the neutrino propagation direc-<lb/>tion. For the NuMI beam line, the direction vectors of <lb/>the beam are defined by colatitude χ = (90 • − latitude) <lb/>= 90. • − 41.84056333 • , θ = 93.346 • , and φ = 23.909 • . <lb/>Here θ and φ are the beam zenith and azimuthal angles; <lb/>θ is measured from the z-axis which points toward the <lb/>zenith; φ is defined from the x-axis which is along the <lb/>detector axis and increases away from the NuMI target. <lb/>The y-axis makes a right handed coordinate system. The <lb/>explicit relationships between the SME coefficients and <lb/>the beam direction are found in [5]. In eq.(1), the CPT <lb/>violating terms depend on L and the Lorentz violating <lb/>terms depend on L × E ν , where E ν is the neutrino en-<lb/>ergy. This unconventional behavior is to be compared <lb/>with the L/E ν dependence of the oscillation probability <lb/>resulting from non-zero neutrino masses [10]. <lb/>The MINOS ND [11] is a magnetized 0.98 kton steel <lb/>scintillator tracking calorimeter that lies 103 m under-<lb/>ground at Fermilab and it is made of 282 4 × 6 m 2 oc-<lb/>tagonal planes. Each plane is comprised of a 2.54 cm <lb/>thick steel plate and a layer of scintillator strips with di-<lb/>mensions of 4.1 cm × 1 cm. Each scintillator strip is <lb/>coupled via wavelength-shifting fiber to one pixel of a <lb/>64-pixel Hamamatsu M64 PMT [12]. The ND readout <lb/>continuously integrates the PMT charges, while the data <lb/>acquisition accepts data above a threshold of 0.25 photo-<lb/>electrons. <lb/>Protons with mean energy of 120 GeV/c are extracted <lb/>from the Main Injector giving a beam spill of 10 µs du-<lb/>ration and period of approximately 2.4 s. The number <lb/>of protons delivered to the target for each spill (POT) <lb/>was measured using toroidal beam current transform-<lb/>ers. The uncertainty in the number of POT for each <lb/>spill is ±1.0% [6]. Neutrino events in the ND fiducial <lb/>volume were selected based on their timing and spatial <lb/>information [8, 13]. The neutrinos were separated into <lb/>charged current-like (CC) or neutral current-like (NC) <lb/>events, as described in [8]. CC ν µ events, identified by a <lb/>µ − track [6], were selected for further analysis to maxi-<lb/>mize the ν µ → ν x oscillation signal in MINOS. <lb/>Standard beam quality cuts [6] were applied to select <lb/>spills for the analysis. In addition, data quality cuts were <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE I: Run Parameters <lb/>CC Events <lb/>POT <lb/>Run Dates <lb/>Run I 1.82 × 10 6 1.25 × 10 20 May05 -Feb06 <lb/>Run II 1.62 × 10 6 1.14 × 10 20 Sept06 -Mar07 <lb/>applied to remove runs in which there were detector prob-<lb/>lems, including cooling system failures, magnetic coil fail-<lb/>ures, or an incorrectly configured readout trigger. <lb/>The data were taken during two run periods. The pa-<lb/>rameters for these two runs are given in Table I. The <lb/>numbers of events and POT given are the numbers re-<lb/>maining in the sample after all cuts have been made. <lb/>Since the sidereal phase histograms in this analysis re-<lb/>quire accurate event timing, we describe how time stamps <lb/>are generated. The spill time is determined by the Global <lb/>Positioning System (GPS) receiver located in the ND <lb/>hall that reads out absolute Universal Coordinated Time <lb/>(UTC) and is accurate to 200 ns [14]. The Main Injec-<lb/>tor accelerates protons to 120 GeV/c and the spills are <lb/>extracted to NuMI using a pulsed dipole magnet. The <lb/>GPS time of the extraction magnet signal is recorded <lb/>and defines the spill time [14]. <lb/>Each neutrino event was tagged with the local sidereal <lb/>time (LST) of its spill -the GPS spill time converted <lb/>to sidereal time. The local sidereal phase of an event is <lb/>given by LST×(ω ⊕ /2π) and has a range of 0-1. Event <lb/>times were not corrected for their time within a spill, an <lb/>approximation that introduces no significant systematic <lb/>error into the analysis. <lb/>The events in each spill were placed into a single bin in <lb/>a histogram spanning 0-1 in local sidereal phase (LSP). <lb/>The POT in the spill were binned into a second LSP <lb/>histogram. By dividing these two histograms, we get the <lb/>number of ν µ events/POT as a function of LSP. This <lb/>final histogram gives the normalized neutrino event rate <lb/>in which we search for sidereal variations. <lb/>We used 32 bins for the LSP histograms. This binning <lb/>was chosen to search for sidereal variations with a Fast <lb/>Fourier Transform (FFT) [15] and the algorithm works <lb/>most efficiently for 2 N bins. Since eq.(1) puts power into <lb/>harmonic frequencies associated with Fourier terms to <lb/>nω ⊕ , and for this analysis n = 1-4, we chose N = 5 as <lb/>the minimal binning that retains these harmonic terms. <lb/>Each bin spans 0.031 in LSP or 45 min in sidereal time. <lb/>The histograms of the ν µ events/POT as a function of <lb/>LSP for Run I and Run II are given in Fig. 1. The dif-<lb/>ferences in the average event rates are due primarily to <lb/>different relative positions of the target and magnetic fo-<lb/>cusing horns for the two runs. <lb/>We performed an FFT analysis on the Run I and Run <lb/>II sidereal phase histograms in Fig. 1 and we computed <lb/>the weighted mean of the powers returned for the even <lb/>(cos ) and odd (sin ) powers for harmonic frequencies out <lb/>to 4ω ⊕ T ⊕ . The weighting factors were the mean event <lb/>rates for each run. The resulting mean powers, p(F F T ), <lb/>are listed in Table II. <lb/>Local Sidereal Phase <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>POT <lb/>14 <lb/>Events/10 <lb/>1.40 <lb/>1.45 <lb/>1.50 <lb/>1.55 <lb/>Run I <lb/>Run II <lb/>FIG. 1: The local sidereal phase histograms for Run I and <lb/>Run II. Superposed are fits to a constant sidereal rate. <lb/>TABLE II: Weighted mean of Run I and Run II FFT powers <lb/>in first four even/odd harmonic coefficients; PF is the proba-<lb/>bility that the mean power is a noise fluctuation. <lb/>cos () <lb/>p(FFT) PF <lb/>sin () <lb/>p(FFT) PF <lb/>(ω⊕T⊕) -0.002 0.91 (ω⊕T⊕) <lb/>0.024 0.18 <lb/>(2ω⊕T⊕) 0.011 0.54 (2ω⊕T⊕) 0.011 0.54 <lb/>(3ω⊕T⊕) -0.006 0.74 (3ω⊕T⊕) -0.004 0.83 <lb/>(4ω⊕T⊕) -0.016 0.37 (4ω⊕T⊕) 0.023 0.20 <lb/>These results were tested for several possible system-<lb/>atic effects. We found that systematic increases or de-<lb/>creases in the event rate of 5% in 6 months do not affect <lb/>these results. We also searched for systematic changes <lb/>in the rates from day to night and found no variations <lb/>&gt; 0.1%. In addition, we searched and found no sidereal <lb/>modulation in the CC/NC ratio for these data. This test <lb/>shows that there are no systematic effects associated with <lb/>neutrino production in the beam that affect this sidereal <lb/>analysis. <lb/>We constructed 1,000 simulated experiments for both <lb/>runs without a sidereal signal to test the significance of <lb/>the powers given in Table II. We used the data them-<lb/>selves to construct these experiments. We first generated <lb/>1,000 sets of sidereal phases for Run I and Run II, with <lb/>each set having the same number of entries as spills in the <lb/>run. The phases were drawn randomly from the sidereal <lb/>phase distribution constructed from the start times for <lb/>each spill in the Run I or Run II data set. We then put <lb/>the events for each spill in the run into 1,000 separate <lb/>histograms according to the scrambled sidereal phase as-<lb/>signed. The number of POT for that spill was entered <lb/>into a second set of 1,000 histograms according to the <lb/>same set of sidereal phases. The division of each event <lb/>histogram by its corresponding POT histogram results in <lb/>the simulated experiments -histograms of the number of <lb/>ν µ events/POT as a function of LSP without a signal. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>FFT Power <lb/>-0.15 -0.1 -0.05 0 0.05 0.1 0.15 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>3 <lb/>10 <lb/>cos terms <lb/>sin terms <lb/>FIG. 2: The distributions for the even (cos ) and the odd <lb/>(sin ) mean powers for harmonic frequencies to 4ω⊕T⊕ from <lb/>the FFT analysis of 1,000 simulated experiments in Run I and <lb/>Run II. Superposed on these distributions is a Gaussian fit of <lb/>width σ = 1.8 × 10 −2 . This fit was obtained independently <lb/>for both distributions. Values outside of the vertical lines are <lb/>more than 3σ from the mean. <lb/>We performed the same FFT analysis on each of the <lb/>1,000 Run I and 1,000 Run II simulated experiments as <lb/>was done with the sidereal phase histograms in Fig. 1. <lb/>The powers returned by these FFTs give the fluctua-<lb/>tion spectrum expected from sidereal phase histograms <lb/>in which there is no sidereal signal. As for the data, we <lb/>computed the weighted mean power for each harmonic <lb/>in a pair of simulated Run I and Run II experiments. <lb/>The distributions for the even (cos ) and the odd (sin ) <lb/>mean powers for harmonic frequencies out to 4ω ⊕ T ⊕ are <lb/>shown superposed in Fig. 2. Clearly these even and odd <lb/>distributions are nearly identical. In addition, a Gaus-<lb/>sian of width σ = 1.8 × 10 −2 has been superposed onto <lb/>these two distributions in Fig. 2. This fit was obtained <lb/>independently for both distributions. We use this Gaus-<lb/>sian to estimate the probability that the powers returned <lb/>by the FFT analysis of the sidereal phase histograms in <lb/>Fig. 1 are due to statistical fluctuations. <lb/>Table II gives the probability, P F , that the mean power <lb/>represents a noise fluctuation. It was calculated as the <lb/>probability of drawing a value of the weighted mean <lb/>power for the two data sets at least as large as found <lb/>from the parent Gaussian distribution in Fig. 2. Since <lb/>the largest fluctuation in the FFT power in the Fig. 1 <lb/>histogram is 1.32σ we conclude that no term reaches the <lb/>level of a 3σ detection. We have determined that these <lb/>results are insensitive to the exact choice of the zero point <lb/>of sidereal phase. This model-independent result implies <lb/>that there is no significant change in normalized neutrino <lb/>event rate that depends on the direction of the neutrino <lb/>beam in a sun-centered inertial frame. In the context of <lb/>the SME, this result is inconsistent with the detection of <lb/>TABLE III: Limits to SME coefficients for νµ → νx in terms <lb/>of the suppression factor mW /mP ∼ 10 −17 ; aL have units of <lb/>(GeV) and cL are unitless. <lb/>×10 −17 <lb/>×10 −17 <lb/>a X <lb/>L <lb/>3.0 × 10 −3 a Y <lb/>L <lb/>3.0 × 10 −3 <lb/>c T X <lb/>L <lb/>0.9 × 10 −5 c T Y <lb/>L <lb/>0.9 × 10 −5 <lb/>c XX <lb/>L <lb/>5.6 × 10 −4 c Y Y <lb/>L <lb/>5.5 × 10 −4 <lb/>c XY <lb/>L <lb/>2.7 × 10 −4 c Y Z <lb/>L <lb/>1.2 × 10 −4 <lb/>c XZ <lb/>L <lb/>1.3 × 10 −4 -<lb/>-<lb/>LV. <lb/>In the absence of a sidereal signal, we can establish up-<lb/>per limits on the SME coefficients (a L ) µ and (c L ) µν that <lb/>describe LV [5] using the standard MINOS Monte Carlo <lb/>simulation. The simulation includes weighting to account <lb/>for hadron production off the NuMI target [6]. In this <lb/>simulation, events are generated by modeling the NuMI <lb/>beam line, including the hadron production by the 120 <lb/>GeV/c protons on target, the propagation of the hadrons <lb/>through the focusing elements and 675 m decay pipe to <lb/>the beam absorber, and the calculation of the probabil-<lb/>ity that any neutrinos generated traverse the ND. The <lb/>ND neutrino event simulation takes the neutrinos from <lb/>the NuMI simulation, along with an energy determined <lb/>by decay kinematics, and uses this information as in-<lb/>put into the simulation of the ND. With the known L <lb/>and E ν for the simulated neutrino events, as well as the <lb/>beam direction, we can inject a Lorentz-violating signal <lb/>into eq.(1). The construction of MC-generated sidereal <lb/>phase histrograms is described elsewhere [16]. <lb/>The limits on the LV coefficients (a L ) µ and (c L ) µν <lb/>were determined from a set of 200 simulated experi-<lb/>ments. First we set all but one LV coefficient to zero. <lb/>We next weighted the simulated neutrino events in each <lb/>histogram by its survival probability computed accord-<lb/>ing to eq.(1), assuming the LV coefficient is small. We <lb/>then increased the magnitude of the nonzero coefficient <lb/>until one of the FFT powers in the simulated phase his-<lb/>togram was 3σ away from the mean of the distribution <lb/>in Fig. 2. An average of the 200 determinations of each <lb/>SME coefficient, scaled in terms of the suppression factor <lb/>m W /m p ∼ 10 −17 , is given in Table III. This procedure, <lb/>by which we vary one parameter at a time to determine <lb/>the limits, could miss fortuitous cancellations of SME co-<lb/>efficients thereby masking a signal. However, we consider <lb/>such cancellations in Nature to be highly unlikely. <lb/>In summary, we find no significant evidence for side-<lb/>real variations in the MINOS ND neutrino data. When <lb/>framed in the SME theory [5], this result leads to the <lb/>conclusion that we have detected no evidence for the vio-<lb/>lation of Lorentz and CPT invariance. Based on these re-<lb/>sults, we computed limits on the LV SME coefficients and <lb/>find that their magnitude is &lt; 1% of the suppression fac-<lb/>tor m W /m P ∼ 10 −17 . For the a L -type SME coefficients, <lb/>the MINOS limits are a factor of 3 lower than those re-<lb/>ported by LSND [7]; for the c L -type SME coefficients, the <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>MINOS limits are at least 4 orders of magnitude lower <lb/>than LSND&apos;s. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We gratefully acknowledge the many valuable con-<lb/>versations with Alan Kostelecký during the course of <lb/>this work. This work was supported by the US DOE, <lb/>the UK STFC, the US NSF, the State and University <lb/>of Minnesota, the University of Athens, Greece, and <lb/>Brazil&apos;s FAPESP and CNPq. We are grateful to the <lb/>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources, the crew <lb/>of the Soudan Underground Laboratory, and the staff of <lb/>Fermilab for their contribution to this effort. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] G. Amelino-Camelia et al., AIP Conf. Proc. 758, 30 <lb/>(2005), gr-qc/0501053; R. Bluhm, Lec. Notes Phys. 702, <lb/>191 (2006), hep-ph/0506054. <lb/>[2] D. Colladay and V. A. Kostelecký, Phys. Rev. D 55, 6760 <lb/>(1997); D. Colladay and V. A. Kostelecký, Phys. Rev. D <lb/>58, 116002 (1998); V. A. Kostelecký, Phys. Rev. D 69, <lb/>105009 (2004). <lb/>[3] V. A. Kostelecký and M. Mewes, Phys. Rev. D 69, <lb/>0160005 (2004). <lb/>[4] S. Reinhardt et al., Nature Physics 3, 861 (2007); H. <lb/>Mueller et al., Phys. Rev. Lett., 99, 050401 (2007); V. <lb/>W. Hughes et al., Phys. Rev. Lett., 87, 111804 (2001); Y. <lb/>B. Hsiung et al., Nucl. Phys. Proc. Suppl, 86, 312 (2000); <lb/>J. Link et al., Phys. Lett. B, 556, 7, (2003); B. Aubert <lb/>et al., Phys. Rev. D, 70, 012007 (2004); J.B.R. Battat <lb/>et al., Phys. Rev. Lett., 99, 241103 (2007); P. Wolf et <lb/>al., Phys. Rev. Lett., 96, 060801 (2006); H. Demelt et <lb/>al., Phys. Rev. Lett, 83, 4694 (1999); B. Heckel et al., <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett., 97, 021603 (2006); M.D. Messier, in <lb/>Proceedings of the Third Meeting on CPT and Lorentz <lb/>Symmetry, edited by V.A. Kostelecký (World Scientific, <lb/>2005), p.84. <lb/>[5] V. A. Kostelecký and M. Mewes, Phys. Rev. D 70, 076002 <lb/>(2004). <lb/>[6] P. Adamson et al., Phys. Rev. D 77, 072002 (2008). <lb/>[7] L. B. Auerbach et al., Phys. Rev. D 72, 076004 (2005). <lb/>[8] D. G. Michael et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 97, 191801 (2006). <lb/>[9] O. W. Greenberg, Phys. Rev. Lett. 89, 231602 (2002). <lb/>[10] H. Nunokawa, S. J. Parke, and R. Zukanovich Funchal, <lb/>Phys. Rev. D 72, 013009 (2005), hep-ph/0503283. <lb/>[11] D. G. Michael et al. (2008), arXiv:0805.3170 [physics.ins-<lb/>det]. <lb/>[12] N. Tagg et al., Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A539, 668 (2005), <lb/>physics/0408055. <lb/>[13] P. Adamson et al. (2008), in preparation. <lb/>[14] P. Adamson et al., Phys. Rev. D 76, 072005 (2007). <lb/>[15] W. H. Press, B. Flannery, S. Teukolsky, and W. Vet-<lb/>terling, Numerical Recipes in C (Cambridge University <lb/>Press, 1999). <lb/>[16] B. J. Rebel and S. L. Mufson, in Proceedings of the Fourth <lb/>Meeting on CPT and Lorentz Symmetry, edited by V. A. <lb/>Kostelecký (World Scientific, 2008), arXiv:0802.3785 <lb/>[hep-ph]. </listBibl>

	</text>
</tei>
