<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> ournal of  Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics <lb/> An IOP and SISSA journal <lb/> J <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of <lb/>the Universe <lb/> Krzysztof Bolejko  1,2  and Lars Andersson  3,4 <lb/> 1  School of Physics, University of Melbourne, VIC 3010, Australia <lb/> 2  Nicolaus Copernicus Astronomical Center, Bartycka 18, 00-716 Warsaw, <lb/>Poland <lb/> 3  Department of Mathematics, University of Miami, Coral Gables, FL 33124, <lb/>USA <lb/> 4  Albert Einstein Institute, Am Mühlenberg 1, D-14467 Golm, Germany <lb/>E-mail: bolejko@camk.edu.pl and larsa@math.miami.edu <lb/>Received 25 July 2008 <lb/>Accepted 8 September 2008 <lb/>Published 3 October 2008 <lb/>Online at stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003 <lb/> doi:10.1088/1475-7516/2008/10/003 <lb/> Abstract.  In this paper we consider the relation between the volume <lb/>deceleration parameter obtained within the Buchert averaging scheme and the <lb/>deceleration parameter derived from supernova observation. This work was <lb/>motivated by recent findings that showed that there are models which despite <lb/>having Λ = 0 have volume deceleration parameter q  vol  &lt; 0. This opens the <lb/>possibility that back-reaction and averaging effects may be used as an interesting <lb/>alternative explanation to the dark energy phenomenon. <lb/>We have calculated q  vol  in some Lemaˆ tre–Tolman models. For those models <lb/>which are chosen to be realistic and which fit the supernova data, we find that <lb/> q  vol  &gt; 0, while those models which we have been able to find which exhibit <lb/> q  vol  &lt; 0 turn out to be unrealistic. This indicates that care must be exercised in <lb/>relating the deceleration parameter to observations. <lb/> Keywords:  dark energy theory, supernova type Ia, cosmological constant <lb/>experiments, superclusters and voids <lb/> ArXiv ePrint:  0807.3577 <lb/> c <lb/></front>

			<front> 2008 IOP Publishing Ltd and SISSA <lb/></front>

			<front>1475-7516/08/10003+15$30.00 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/></note>  

			<note place="headnote">Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<toc> Contents <lb/> 1. Introduction <lb/>2 <lb/>2. The Buchert scheme <lb/>4 <lb/>3. The Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model <lb/>5 <lb/>4. The apparent and average accelerations <lb/>6 <lb/>5. Connection between the deceleration parameter and observations <lb/>7 <lb/>6. Conclusions <lb/>9 <lb/>Acknowledgments <lb/>11 <lb/>Appendix. Model specification <lb/>11 <lb/>References <lb/>14 <lb/></toc>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Accelerated expansion, modeled by a positive cosmological constant, is an essential <lb/>element of the current standard cosmological model of the Universe. The accelerated <lb/>expansion was originally motivated by supernova observations [1] and is supported by <lb/>many other types of cosmological observations. Observational data are, in modern <lb/>cosmology, analyzed almost exclusively within the framework of homogeneous and <lb/>isotropic Friedmann models [2]. This analysis leads to the concordance model, which <lb/>provides a remarkably precise fit to cosmological observations. In this situation, if the <lb/>Ehlers–Geren–Sachs theorem [3] and &apos;almost EGS theorem&apos; [4] are invoked  5  , then it seems <lb/>that an assumption of large scale homogeneity of the Universe can be justified. This on <lb/>the other hand implies that the Universe must be filled with dark energy which currently <lb/>drives the acceleration of the Universe. <lb/>However, the concordance model is not the only one which can fit cosmological <lb/>observations. Anti-Copernican inhomogeneous models which assume the existence of a <lb/>local Gpc scale void also fit cosmological observations [6] (see [7] for a review). Moreover, <lb/>on small and medium scales our Universe is not homogeneous. Therefore, one may <lb/>ask whether Friedmann models can describe our Universe correctly. In particular, it <lb/>is important to ask what is the best way to fit a homogeneous model to a realistic and <lb/>inhomogeneous Universe. This problem, known as the fitting problem, was considered <lb/>by Ellis and Stoeger [8]. In considering the fitting problem, it becomes apparent that <lb/>a homogeneous model fitted to inhomogeneous data can evolve quite differently from <lb/>the real Universe. The difference between the evolutions of homogeneous models and <lb/>an inhomogeneous Universe is caused by back-reaction effects, due to the non-linearity <lb/>of the Einstein equation. Unfortunately, in the standard approach, the back-reaction is <lb/></body> 

			<note place="footnote">5  These theorems imply that if anisotropies in the cosmic microwave background radiation are small for all <lb/>fundamental observers then the Universe is locally almost spatially homogeneous and isotropic. However, as <lb/>shown in [5] the almost Robertson–Walker geometry also requires smallness of the Weyl curvature. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<body>rarely taken into account—in most cases when modeling our Universe on a local scale <lb/>Newtonian mechanics is employed and on large scales the Friedmann equations (or linear <lb/>perturbations of Friedmann background) are used [9]. Such an approach to cosmology <lb/>is often encouraged by the &apos;no-go&apos; theorem which states that the Universe can be very <lb/>accurately described by the conformal Newtonian metric perturbed about a spatially flat <lb/>background, even if δρ/ρ  0. In such a case the back-reaction is negligible [10, 11]. <lb/>However, the results obtained by van Elst and Ellis [12] and recently by Kolb, Marra <lb/>and Matarrese [13] show that the application of &apos;no-go&apos; theorem is limited. Therefore, <lb/>one should be aware that in the absence of an analysis of the back-reaction and other <lb/>effects caused by inhomogeneities in the Universe, there remains the possibility that the <lb/>observed accelerated expansion of the Universe is only apparent [14]. The direct study <lb/>of the dynamical effects of inhomogeneities is difficult. Due to the non-linearity of the <lb/>Einstein equations, the solution of the Einstein equations for the homogeneous matter <lb/>distribution leads in principle to a different description of the Universe than an average of <lb/>an inhomogeneous solution to the exact Einstein equations (even though inhomogeneities <lb/>when averaged over a sufficiently large scale might tend to be zero). <lb/>Neither the analysis of the evolution of a general matter distribution nor the numerical <lb/>evolution of cosmological models employing the full Einstein equations are available at <lb/>the level of detail which would make them useful for this problem. There are currently <lb/>several different approaches which attempt to take back-reaction effects into account. One <lb/>approach is based on exact solutions—see for example [15]. Another and more popular <lb/>approach is based on averaging. <lb/>In the averaging approach to back-reaction, one considers a solution to the Einstein <lb/>equations for a general matter distribution and then an average of various observable <lb/>quantities is taken. If a simple volume average is considered then such an attempt <lb/>leads to the Buchert equations [16]. The Buchert equations are very similar to the <lb/>Friedmann equations except for the back-reaction term which is in general non-vanishing, <lb/>if inhomogeneities are present. For a review on back-reaction and the Buchert averaging <lb/>scheme the reader is referred to [17, 18]. Within this framework and using spherically <lb/>symmetric inhomogeneous models Nambu and Tanimoto [19], Paranjape and Singh [20], <lb/>Kai et al [21], Chuang et al [22], provided explicit examples that one can obtain negative <lb/>values of the volume deceleration parameter even if Λ = 0. Another interesting example <lb/>was presented by Räsänen [17, 23] where it was shown that the total volume deceleration <lb/>parameter of two isolated and locally decelerating regions can also be negative. <lb/>There are however important ambiguities in the application of an averaging procedure. <lb/>The average itself not only depends on a choice of volume but also on a choice of time <lb/>slicing. This is very crucial in cosmology. Once inhomogeneities are present the age of <lb/>the Universe is not everywhere the same. Namely, the big bang in inhomogeneous models <lb/>is not a single event, so the average taken over a hypersurface of constant cosmic time <lb/> t is different from the average taken over a hypersurface of constant age of the Universe <lb/> t−t  B  [24]. Moreover, the results of the averaging procedure vary if the discrepancy between <lb/>the average cosmic time and the local time is introduced (the local time is the time which <lb/>is measured by local clocks; the cosmic time is the time which appears in the averaged <lb/>homogeneous model). This phenomenon was studied by Wiltshire [25], and has been <lb/>used in an ambitious alternative concordance model. The model proposed by Wiltshire <lb/>introduces some additional assumptions which allow to some extent a comparison of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<body> averaged quantities with observations. Such a comparison shows quite good agreement <lb/>with observations [26]. Thus, while serious fundamental questions remain concerning <lb/>Wiltshire&apos;s approach, it is another example of an approach where one does not need dark <lb/>energy to fit cosmological observations. <lb/>The averaging procedure is also gauge dependent. For example using different gauge <lb/>one can obtain that the back-reaction mimics not dark energy but dark matter [27]. The <lb/>averaging schemes in the literature, therefore, have been criticized, and their inherent <lb/>ambiguities (and in some cases obscurity) have been discussed; cf e.g. [10]. A key point <lb/>is that it is far from obvious whether the average quantities, such as the acceleration <lb/>of the averaged Universe, are really the quantities which are measured in astronomical <lb/>observations. In particular, an operational analysis is to a large extent lacking in the <lb/>discussions of averaging. Thus, it is important to test the averaging procedures with the <lb/>exact and inhomogeneous solutions of the Einstein equations. Within exact models each <lb/>quantity can easily be calculated and then compared with its averaged counterpart. This <lb/>paper aims to perform such an analysis within the Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model. <lb/>The structure of this paper is as follows. Buchert&apos;s averaging procedure is presented <lb/>in section 2, and some background on the Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model is given in section 3. <lb/>The volume and distance deceleration parameters are introduced in section 4. Finally, <lb/>in section 5, we discuss the relation between the deceleration parameters, supernova <lb/>observations and models of cosmic structures. <lb/> 2. The Buchert scheme <lb/> If the averaging procedure is applied to the Einstein equations, then for irrotational and <lb/>pressureless matter the following equations are obtained [16]: <lb/>3 <lb/>¨ <lb/> a <lb/> a <lb/> = −4πGρ + Q, <lb/> (1) <lb/>3 <lb/>˙ <lb/> a  2 <lb/> a  2  = 8πGρ − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> R − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Q, <lb/> (2) <lb/> Q ≡  2 <lb/>3 <lb/>  Θ  2  − Θ  2  − 2σ  2  , <lb/> (3) <lb/>where R is an average of the spatial Ricci scalar  (3)  R, Θ is the scalar of expansion, σ <lb/> is the shear scalar, and  is the volume average over the hypersurface of constant time: <lb/> A = ( <lb/> d  3  x <lb/> √ −h)  −1  <lb/> d  3  x <lb/> √ −hA. The scale factor a is defined as follows: <lb/> a = (V /V  0  )  1/3  , <lb/> (4) <lb/>where V  0  is an initial volume. <lb/>Equations (1) and (2) are very similar to the Friedmann equations, where Q = 0, and <lb/> ρ and R depend on time only. In fact, they are kinematically equivalent to a Friedmann <lb/>model that has an additional scalar field source [28]. However the Buchert equation does <lb/>not form a closed system. To close these equations one has to introduce some further <lb/>assumptions [16]. As can be seen from (3), if the dispersion of expansion is large, Q can <lb/>be large as well and one can get acceleration (¨ a &gt; 0) without employing the cosmological <lb/>constant. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<body>3. The Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model <lb/> The Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model  6  [30] is a spherically symmetric, pressure free and <lb/>irrotational solution of the Einstein equations. Its metric is of the following form: <lb/>ds  2  = c  2  dt  2  − <lb/> R  2  (r, t) <lb/> 1 + 2E(r) <lb/>dr  2  − R  2  (t, r) dΩ  2  , <lb/> (5) <lb/>where dΩ  2  = dθ  2  + sin  2  θ dφ  2  . Because of the signature (+, −, −, −), the E(r) function <lb/>must obey E(r) ≥ −1/2. The prime   denotes ∂  r  . <lb/>The Einstein equations reduce, in the Λ = 0 case, to the following two: <lb/> κρ(r, t)c  2  = <lb/>2M   (r) <lb/> R  2  (r, t)R   (r, t) <lb/>, <lb/> (6) <lb/>1 <lb/> c  2 <lb/> ˙ <lb/> R  2  (r, t) = 2E(r) + <lb/>2M(r) <lb/> R(r, t) <lb/>, <lb/> (7) <lb/>where M(r) is another arbitrary function and κ = 8πG/c  4  . The dot ˙ denotes ∂  t  . <lb/>When R   = 0 and M   = 0, the density becomes infinite. This happens at shell <lb/>crossings. This is a singularity additional to the big bang that occurs at R = 0, M   = 0. <lb/>By setting the initial conditions appropriately the shell crossing singularity can be avoided <lb/>(see [31] for detailed discussion). <lb/>Equation (7) can be solved by simple integration: <lb/>  R <lb/> 0 <lb/> d ˜ <lb/> R <lb/> 2E + (2M/ ˜ <lb/> R) <lb/> = c [t − t  B  (r)] , <lb/> (8) <lb/>where t  B  appears as an integration constant and is an arbitrary function of r. This means <lb/>that the big bang is not a single event as in the Friedmann models, but occurs at different <lb/>times at different distances from the origin. <lb/>The scalar of the expansion is equal to <lb/>Θ = <lb/>˙ <lb/> R  <lb/> R   + 2 <lb/>˙ <lb/> R <lb/>R <lb/>. <lb/> (9) <lb/>The shear tensor is of the following form: <lb/> σ  α β  = <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/> ˙ <lb/> R  <lb/> R   − <lb/> ˙ <lb/> R <lb/>R <lb/> diag(0, 2, −1, −1), <lb/> (10) <lb/>and thus σ  2  ≡ (1/2)σ  αβ  σ  αβ  = (1/3)( ˙ <lb/> R   /R   − ˙ <lb/> R/R)  2  . <lb/>The spatial Ricci scalar in the Lemaˆ tre–Tolman is equal to <lb/> (3) <lb/> R = − <lb/> 4 <lb/> R  2 <lb/> E + <lb/> E   R <lb/>R  <lb/> . <lb/> (11) <lb/></body> 

			<note place="footnote"> 6  The pressure free and irrotational solution of the Einstein equations for spherically symmetric space–time is <lb/>often called the Tolman, Tolman–Bondi, or Lemaˆ tre–Tolman–Bondi model. However, it is more justified to refer <lb/>to this solution as the Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model (cf [29]). <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<body>4. The apparent and average accelerations <lb/> The deceleration parameter within the Friedmann models is defined as <lb/> q = − <lb/> ¨ <lb/> aa <lb/> ˙ <lb/> a  2  , <lb/> (12) <lb/>where a is the scale factor. By analogy we can define the deceleration parameter which is <lb/>based on the averaging scheme. Substituting (4) into (12) and using (1) and (2) we get <lb/> q  vol  = − <lb/>−4πGρ + Q <lb/> 8πGρ − 1/2R − 1/2Q <lb/> . <lb/> (13) <lb/>We refer to this deceleration parameter as the volume deceleration parameter, q  vol  , since it <lb/>is positive when the second derivative of volume is negative and negative when the second <lb/>derivative of volume is positive (and of sufficiently large value). <lb/>On the other hand one can introduce a deceleration parameter defined relative to <lb/>the distance. Within homogeneous models the distance to a given redshift is larger for <lb/>accelerating models than for decelerating ones. Taylor expanding the luminosity distance <lb/>in the Friedmann model we obtain <lb/> D  L  = <lb/>dD  L <lb/> dz <lb/> z=0 <lb/> z + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>d  2  D  L <lb/> dz  2 <lb/> z=0 <lb/> z  2  + O(z  3  ) <lb/>= <lb/> c <lb/>H  0 <lb/> z + <lb/> c <lb/> 2H  0 <lb/> (1 − q)z  2  + O(z  3  ). <lb/>(14) <lb/>Employing a similar procedure in the case of the Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model we get <lb/> D  L  = <lb/> cR  <lb/> ˙ <lb/> R  <lb/> z + <lb/> c <lb/> 2 <lb/> R  <lb/> ˙ <lb/> R  <lb/> 1 + <lb/> R   ¨ <lb/> R  <lb/> ˙ <lb/> R  2 <lb/> + <lb/> cR  <lb/> R   ˙ <lb/> R  <lb/> − <lb/> c ˙ <lb/> R  <lb/> ˙ <lb/> R  2 <lb/> z  2  + O(z  3  ). <lb/>(15) <lb/>Thus by comparing (15) with (14), the Hubble and the deceleration parameters in the <lb/>Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model can be defined as <lb/> H  dis <lb/>0  = <lb/>˙ <lb/> R  <lb/> R   , <lb/>q  dis <lb/>0  = − <lb/> R   ¨ <lb/> R  <lb/> ˙ <lb/> R  2 <lb/> − <lb/> cR  <lb/> R   ˙ <lb/> R  <lb/> + <lb/> c ˙ <lb/> R  <lb/> ˙ <lb/> R  2 <lb/> . <lb/> (16) <lb/>The above quantities are defined at the origin (r = 0). However, following Partovi and <lb/>Mashhoon [32] we can extend the above quantities to any r. Then, the coefficients of <lb/>Taylor expansion are <lb/>dD  L <lb/> dz <lb/>= 2R + ˙ <lb/> R <lb/> dt <lb/>dz <lb/>+ R   dr <lb/>dz <lb/>d  2  D  L <lb/> dz  2  = 2R + 4 ˙ <lb/> R <lb/> dt <lb/>dz <lb/>+ 4R   dr <lb/>dz <lb/>+ ¨ <lb/> R <lb/> dt <lb/>dz <lb/>  2 <lb/> + 2 ˙ <lb/> R   dt <lb/>dz <lb/>dr <lb/>dz <lb/>+ R  <lb/> dr <lb/>dz <lb/>  2 <lb/> + ˙ <lb/> R <lb/> d  2  t <lb/> dz  2  + R   d  2  r <lb/> dz  2  , <lb/> (17) <lb/>and we obtain <lb/> H  dis  = <lb/> dD  L <lb/> dz <lb/>  −1 <lb/> , <lb/>q  dis  = 1 − H  dis  d  2  D  L <lb/> dz  2  . <lb/> (18) <lb/>We refer to this deceleration parameter as the distance deceleration parameter. Although <lb/>of physical importance is the luminosity distance and its ability of fitting the supernova <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<body>Figure 1. The residual Hubble diagram for models 1–4. The black dashed line <lb/>presents Δm for the ΛCDM model. <lb/> data, q  dis  is of great usefulness. It allows us, without solving the geodesic equations, to <lb/>easily check whether a model being considered can be used to fit supernova data. As we <lb/>will see in the next section, models which fit supernova data have at least in some regions <lb/> q  dis  &lt; 0. <lb/> 5. Connection between the deceleration parameter and observations <lb/> Let us first focus on supernova observations. There is already a considerable literature <lb/>on inhomogeneous models which are able to fit the supernova observations without the <lb/>cosmological constant [6]. We shall examine four such models in this section. For each <lb/>of these models we shall calculate the volume and distance deceleration parameters and <lb/>compare them with each other. The four models to be considered present a very good fit <lb/>to supernova data. The supernova data consists of 182 supernovae from the Riess gold <lb/>sample [33]. The χ  2  test values for models 1–4 are respectively 183.6, 184.3, 164.7, and <lb/>178.5 (for comparison the χ  2  of fitting the ΛCDM model is 165.3). The residual Hubble <lb/>diagram for these models is presented in figure 1. The deceleration parameters for models <lb/>1–4 are presented in figure 2. The left panel presents the distance deceleration parameter <lb/>(as defined by (18)—where dt/dz and dr/dz were calculated for the radial geodesic). <lb/>The distance deceleration parameter is positive at the origin, but soon becomes negative. <lb/>Moreover, a very similar shape is obtained if instead of q  dis  (as defined by (18)), q  dis <lb/>0 <lb/> (as defined by (16)) is used. Thus, q  dis  (or even q  dis <lb/>0  , if treated as a function of r) can <lb/>be regarded as a useful test for checking whether a given model is able to fit supernova <lb/>data. However, the most significant feature is that the volume deceleration parameter, <lb/>which is presented in the right panel of figure 2, is strictly positive. Thus, the ability of <lb/>reproducing the supernova data does not require that the volume deceleration parameter <lb/>is negative. This raises the question of whether the average acceleration has any relation to <lb/>the observed acceleration of the Universe; and if yes, are models with average acceleration <lb/>also able to fit supernova data? <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<body>Figure 2. The distance deceleration parameter (left panel) and the volume <lb/>deceleration parameter (right panel) for models 1–4. <lb/> Figure 3. The current density distribution (left panel) and deceleration parameter <lb/>(right panel) for model 5. <lb/> Let us now focus on models of cosmic structures. It was recently shown that using <lb/>a perturbative approach, back-reaction cannot explain the apparent acceleration [34]. <lb/>However, because of the large density fluctuations within cosmic structures, results <lb/>obtained in terms of the perturbation framework might be questionable. Moreover, <lb/>in view of the fact that there are known examples of exact inhomogeneous models <lb/>with negative volume deceleration parameter and Λ = 0, it is worthwhile to check <lb/>whether realistically evolving models of cosmic structures can have negative values of the <lb/>deceleration parameter. First, let us consider a model of galaxy clusters with the Navarro– <lb/>Frenk–White density distribution [35] (left panel of figure 3). Although the NFW profile <lb/>describes virialized systems  7  , the use of this profile will prove to be very instructive. The <lb/>average deceleration parameter q  vol  for model 5 is presented in the right panel of figure 3. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 7  The Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model which evolves from a smooth density profile at last scattering to a high value <lb/>profile like the NFW profile is always characterized by a collapse central region; within this models are at the <lb/>current instant collapsing. Thus such systems cannot be considered as virialized systems. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/> </note>

			<body>Figure 4. The current density distribution (left panel) and volume deceleration <lb/>parameter (right panel) for models of cosmic structures (models 6, 7). <lb/> As can be seen, in this case the deceleration parameter is positive (curve 5a). However, it <lb/>is possible to modify this model so that q  vol  becomes negative—curve 5b in the right panel <lb/>of figure 3. This was obtained by choosing the E function which is of large positive value <lb/>(for details see the appendix). However, after such a modification this model becomes <lb/>unrealistic. Specifically, the age of the Universe in this model becomes unrealistically <lb/>small. The bang time function t  B  in this model is of large amplitude, around 11.44 × 10  9 <lb/> y. This means that the actual age of the Universe in this model is approximately a few <lb/>hundred thousand years. <lb/>Now let us examine the volume deceleration parameter within models of cosmic voids <lb/>and superclusters. Figure 4 presents density distribution of realistically evolving cosmic <lb/>structures (void—curve 6, supercluster—curve 7). It can be seen from the right panel <lb/>of figure 4 that the volume deceleration parameter within these models is positive. As <lb/>above, we can modify our models in such a way that the volume deceleration parameter <lb/>is negative, but again this leads to a very large amplitude of t  B  . For example, in model <lb/>8, whose density and the volume deceleration parameter are presented in figure 5, the  8 <lb/> volume deceleration parameter is negative. However, the bang time function in model 8 <lb/>is of amplitude ≈11 × 10  9  y, which leads to an unrealistically small age of the Universe. <lb/> 6. Conclusions <lb/> In this paper we have studied the relation between the volume deceleration parameter <lb/>obtained within the Buchert averaging scheme and the deceleration parameter derived <lb/>from the observations of supernovae. This work was motivated by recent results showing <lb/>that there are models for which, despite Λ being zero, the average expansion rate is <lb/>accelerating, i.e. ¨ <lb/> a &gt; 0 (where a is defined by relation (4)). This opens the possibility that <lb/>back-reaction and averaging effects may be used as an interesting alternative explanation <lb/>to the dark energy phenomenon. <lb/></body> 

			<note place="footnote">8  Employing a model of qualitatively similar features to model 8, Hossain [36] showed that the observer situated <lb/>at the origin in order to successfully employ the Friedmann model has to assume the existence of dark energy. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<body>Figure 5. The current density distribution (left panel) and deceleration parameter <lb/>(right panel) for model 8. <lb/> We have compared the quantities obtained within the exact and inhomogeneous <lb/>models with their average counterparts. We focused on the supernova observations and <lb/>models of cosmic structures. For this purpose the Lemaˆ tre–Tolman model was employed. <lb/>It was shown numerically that the averaging of models which fit the supernova observations <lb/>does not lead to volume acceleration (¨ a &lt; 0 for these averaged models and hence q  vol  &gt; 0). <lb/>It was also shown that realistically evolving models of cosmic structures have also q  vol  &gt; 0. <lb/>It was possible to modify these models in such a way that after the averaging, q  vol  &lt; 0. <lb/>This was obtained by choosing the E function of positive amplitude—as was recently <lb/>proved by Sussman [37] this is a necessary condition for obtaining q  vol  &lt; 0. However, in <lb/>models with realistic density distributions, in such case, E  1  M/R ≈ 10  −7  –10  −6  ; <lb/>hence, as seen from (8), t  B  ≈ t (recall that c × 10  10  y ≈ 3 Gpc). Thus, within such models, <lb/>the age of the Universe is unrealistically small. <lb/>Our analysis has been performed for the limited class of Lemaˆ tre–Tolman models, <lb/>which due to their spherical symmetry are arguably too simple to give a full understanding <lb/>of averaging and back-reaction problems. However, we conclude that, within this class, <lb/>the volume deceleration parameter q  vol  is not a quantity which can be directly related to <lb/>observations. <lb/>It is possible that the volume deceleration parameter q  vol  becomes negative only after <lb/>averaging over scales which are larger than 100 Mpc. On such large scales the structure <lb/>of the Universe becomes too complicated to be fully described by spherically symmetric <lb/>models. However, it is intriguing that models which fit the supernova observations and <lb/>for which the distance deceleration parameter, q  dis  , is negative still have q  vol  &gt; 0. This <lb/>suggests that the volume deceleration q  vol  does not have a clear interpretation in terms of <lb/>observable quantities. It does not, of course, mean that averaging and back-reaction effects <lb/>cannot potentially be employed to explain the phenomenon of dark energy. However, our <lb/>work here indicates that such a potential solution of the dark energy problem should <lb/>be based upon methods different to those related to the volume deceleration parameter. <lb/>Rather than showing that q  vol  &lt; 0, the averaging approach should explain observations— <lb/>reproduce correct values of distances to supernovae, the correct shape of the CMB power <lb/>spectrum, etc. An interesting, quasi-Friedmannian approach was recently suggested <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<body>in [38]. In this approach, back-reaction is modeled in terms of the morphon field [28]. <lb/>In such a case a Universe is described by a homogeneous model with the spatial curvature <lb/>being just a function of time. As shown in [38], such an approach leads to agreement with <lb/>supernova and CMB data without the need for dark energy, but requires q  vol  &lt; 0. <lb/></body> 

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/> We would like to thank Henk van Elst and Thomas Buchert for useful discussions and <lb/>comments. KB would like to thank Peter and Patricia Gruber and the International <lb/>Astronomical Union for a PPGF Fellowship; the support of the Polish Astroparticle <lb/>Network (621/E-78/SN-0068/2007) is also acknowledged. KB is also grateful to LA <lb/>and the Albert Einstein Institute, where part of this research was carried out, for their <lb/>hospitality. LA acknowledges the support of the NSF with grants DMS-0407732 and <lb/>DMS-0707306 to the University of Miami. <lb/></div> 

			<div type="annex">Appendix. Model specification <lb/> There are three arbitrary functions of the radial coordinate in the Lemaˆ tre–Tolman case. <lb/>However only two functions are independent and the third one is specified by the choice <lb/>of the radial coordinate. The models considered in this paper are defined as follows: <lb/>(i) Models 1 and 2 <lb/>The radial coordinate is chosen as the present day value of the areal distance r := R  0  . <lb/>Models 1 and 2 are specified by the present day density distribution and the bang <lb/>time function. The density distribution is parameterized by <lb/> ρ(t  0  , r) = ρ  b <lb/> 1 + δ  ρ  − δ  ρ  exp <lb/> − <lb/> r  2 <lb/> σ  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (A.1) <lb/>where ρ  b  = Ω  m  × (3H  2 <lb/>0  )/(8πG), Ω  m  = 0.27, H  0  = 70 km s  −1  Mpc <lb/> −1  . In model 1 <lb/> ρ  δ  = 1.9, σ = 0.9 Mpc, and in model 2 ρ  δ  = 1.5, σ = 0.5 Mpc. In these models <lb/>the big bang is assumed to occur simultaneously at every point, i.e. t  B  = 0. The <lb/>functions M and E are then calculated using equations (6) and (8) respectively. The <lb/>background density ρ  b  in all models (1–8) is chosen as the density of a Friedmann <lb/>model (Ω  m  = 0.27, H  0  = 70 km s  −1  ) and the time instants are calculated using the <lb/>following formula [9]: <lb/> t(z) = <lb/>1 <lb/> H  0 <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> z <lb/> d˜  <lb/> (1 + ˜ <lb/> z) <lb/> Ω  mat  (1 + ˜ <lb/> z)  3  + Ω  K  (1 + ˜ <lb/> z)  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (A.2) <lb/>where Ω  K  = 1 − Ω  m  . The last scattering instant (t  LS  ) is set to take place when <lb/> z = 1089 and the current instant (t  0  ) when z = 0—t  LS  = 4.98 × 10  5  y, and <lb/> t  0  = 11.4421 × 10  9  y. <lb/>(ii) Models 3 and 4 <lb/>As above, the radial coordinate is chosen as the present day value of the areal distance <lb/> r := R  0  . These two models are defined by the current expansion rate, and the <lb/>assumption that ρ(t  0  , r) = ρ  b  . The expansion rate is parametrized using <lb/> H  T  (t  0  , r) = <lb/>˙ <lb/> R <lb/>R <lb/> = H  0 <lb/> 1 − δ  H  + δ  H  exp <lb/> − <lb/> r  2 <lb/> σ  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (A.3) <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<div type="annex">where H  0  δ  H  = 9.6 km s  −1  Mpc <lb/> −1  , σ = 0.6 Mpc, and H  0  δ  H  = 12 km s  −1  Mpc <lb/> −1  , <lb/> σ = 1.2 Mpc for models 3 and 4 respectively. In these models, density is assumed <lb/>to be homogeneous at the current epoch. The function M is then calculated using <lb/>the above relation and equation (7). It should be noted that the H  T  is one of several <lb/>generalizations of the Hubble constant; in the Friedmann model it is H  0  = ˙ <lb/> a/a. <lb/> Besides the transverse Hubble parameter, H  T  , one can also define the radial Hubble <lb/>parameter, H  R  (see equation (16)), and the volume Hubble parameter defined as <lb/> H  V  = (1/3)Θ = H  R  + 2H  T  . <lb/>(iii) Model 5a <lb/>The radial coordinate is chosen as the present day value of the areal distance, <lb/>i.e. r := R  0  . The model is defined by density distributions given at the present <lb/>instant and at last scattering. The density distribution at the current instant is <lb/>parametrized by <lb/> ρ(t  0  , r) = ρ  b <lb/> δ <lb/> (r/r  s  )(1 + r/r  s  )  2  , <lb/> (A.4) <lb/>where δ = 28170 and r  s  = 191 kpc. This is a Navarro, Frenk, and White galaxy <lb/>cluster profile [35]. As can be seen, this profile is singular at the origin but this <lb/>problem can be overcome by matching the NFW profile with a singularity free profile, <lb/>as f (r) = −ar  2  + b. <lb/> The density profile at last scattering is assumed to be homogeneous; thus the areal <lb/>distance at last scattering is <lb/> R(t  LS  , r) = <lb/> M <lb/>κρ  LS  c  2 <lb/>  1/3 <lb/> . <lb/> (A.5) <lb/>The function M(r) is then calculated from equation (6). Function E can be calculated <lb/>by subtracting solutions of (8) for t  LS  and t  0  (for details see [39]). The function E is <lb/>presented in the left panel of figure A.1. <lb/>(iv) Model 5b <lb/>The radial coordinate is chosen as the present day value of the areal distance, r := R  0  . <lb/>The model is defined by density distribution given by (A.4) and E of the following <lb/>form: <lb/> E(r) = 10  3  sin <lb/> 10  −3  r Mpc  −1  <lb/> . <lb/> (A.6) <lb/>This profile is presented in the left panel of figure A.1 and the bang time function t  B <lb/> in the right panel. <lb/>(v) Models 6 and 7 <lb/>The radial coordinate is chosen as the value of the areal distance at last scattering <lb/>instant, r := R  LS  . Models 6 and 7 are defined by the assumption that t  B  = 0 and the <lb/>density distribution, which at last scattering is of the following form: <lb/> ρ(t  LS  , r) = ρ  b <lb/> 1 − δ exp (−aa  2  r  2  ) + γ exp <lb/> − <lb/> r − c <lb/>d <lb/>  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (A.7) <lb/>where  = 1 kpc  −1  ; δ = 1.2 × 10  −3  and 2 × 10  −3  for models 6 and 7 respectively; <lb/> γ = 14.62 × 10  −4  and 8.03 × 10  −4  for models 6 and 7 respectively; a = 0.01 and 0.04 <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<div type="annex">Figure A.1. The left panel presents the function E(r) for models 5a and 5b. <lb/>Please note that the y-scale in the upper part of the left panel is different than <lb/>in the lower part. Right panel: bang time function for model 5b. <lb/> Figure A.2. The functions E(r) (left panel) and t  B  (r) (right panel) for model 8. <lb/> for models 6 and 7 respectively; c = 18 and 12 for models 6 and 7 respectively; and <lb/> d = 6 and 5 for models 6 and 7 respectively. The bang time function for both of these <lb/>models is t  B  = 0. The mass function M(r) is calculated from equation (6), and the <lb/>function E(r) is calculated from equation (8). <lb/>(vi) Model 8 <lb/>The radial coordinate is chosen as a present day value of the areal distance: r := R  0  . <lb/>The density distribution is of the following form: <lb/> ρ(t  0  , r) = 6.2ρ  b  exp (−4 × 10  −8  (r)  2  ), <lb/>(A.8) <lb/>and the function E is <lb/> E(r) = <lb/> H  0 <lb/> c <lb/>r <lb/>  2 <lb/> exp (10  −3  r), <lb/> (A.9) <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<div type="annex">which except for [exp (10  −3  r)] is the same as the E(r) profile in the empty Universe. <lb/>This profile is presented in the left panel of figure A.2 and the bang time function t  B <lb/> in the right panel. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Perlmutter S et al , 1997 Astrophys. J. 483 565 [SPIRES] <lb/>Riess A G et al , 1998 Astrophys. J. 116 1009 [SPIRES] <lb/>Perlmutter S et al , 1999 Astrophys. J. 517 565 [SPIRES] <lb/>[2] Hinshaw G et al , 2008 Astrophys. J. Suppl. Ser. submitted arXiv:0803.0732 <lb/>Tegmark M et al , 2006 Phys. Rev. D 74 123507 [SPIRES] <lb/>Percival W J et al , 2002 Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc. 337 1068 <lb/>[3] Ehlers J, Geren P and Sachs R K, 1968 J. Math. Phys. 9 1344 [SPIRES] <lb/>[4] Stoeger W R, Maarteens R and Ellis G F R, 1995 Astrophys. J. 443 1 [SPIRES] <lb/>[5] Nilsson U S, Uggla C, Wainwright J and Lim W C, 1999 Astrophys. J. 521 L1 [SPIRES] <lb/>[6] Dąbrowski M P and Hendry M A, 1998 Astrophys. J. 498 67 [SPIRES] <lb/>Célérier M N, 2000 Astron. Astrophys. 353 63 [SPIRES] <lb/>Iguchi H, Nakamura T and Nakao K, 2002 Prog. Theor. Phys. 108 809 [SPIRES] <lb/>God lowski W, Stelmach J and Szydd lowski M, 2004 Class. Quantum Grav. 21 3953 [SPIRES] <lb/>Alnes H and Amarzguioui M, 2006 Phys. Rev. D 74 103520 [SPIRES] <lb/>Alnes H, Amarzguioui M and Grøn Ø, 2006 Phys. Rev. D 73 083519 [SPIRES] <lb/>Chung D J H and Romano A E, 2006 Phys. Rev. D 74 103507 [SPIRES] <lb/>Alnes H and Amarzguioui M, 2007 Phys. Rev. D 75 023506 [SPIRES] <lb/>Enqvist K and Mattsson T, 2007 J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. JCAP07(2007)02019 [SPIRES] <lb/>Alexander S, Biswas T, Notari A and Vaid D, 2007 arXiv:0712.0370 <lb/>Biswas T, Mansouri R and Notari A, 2007 J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. JCAP12(2007)017 [SPIRES] <lb/>Brouzakis N, Tetradis N and Tzavara E, 2007 J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. JCAP02(2007)013 [SPIRES] <lb/>Brouzakis N, Tetradis N and Tzavara E, 2008 J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. JCAP04(2008)008 [SPIRES] <lb/>[arXiv:astro-ph/0703586] <lb/>Marra V, Kolb E W, Matarrese S and Riotto A, 2007 Phys. Rev. D 76 123004 [SPIRES] <lb/>Biswas T and Notari A, 2008 J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. JCAP06(2008)021 [SPIRES] <lb/>Bolejko K, 2008 PMC Phys. A 2 1 [arXiv:astro-ph/0512103] <lb/>García-Bellido J and Haugbølle T, 2008 J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. JCAP04(2008)003 [SPIRES] <lb/>Enqvist K, 2008 Gen. Rel. Grav. 40 451 [SPIRES] <lb/>Khosravi Sh, Kourkchi E, Mansouri R and Akrami Y, 2008 Gen. Rel. Grav. 40 1047 [SPIRES] <lb/>Bolejko K and Wyithe J S B, 2008 arXiv:0807.2891 <lb/>Yoo C-M, Kai T and Nakao K-i, 2008 arXiv:0807.0932 <lb/>[7] Célérier M N, 2007 New Adv. Phys. 1 29 <lb/>[8] Ellis G F R and Stoeger W, 1987 Class. Quantum Grav. 4 1697 [SPIRES] <lb/>[9] Peebles P J E, 1993 Principles of Physical Cosmology (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press) <lb/>[10] Ishibashi A and Wald R M, 2006 Class. Quantum Grav. 23 235 [SPIRES] <lb/>[11] Kasai M, Asada H and Futamase T, 2006 Prog. Theor. Phys. 115 827 [SPIRES] <lb/>[12] van Elst H and Ellis G F R, 1998 Class. Quantum Grav. 15 3545 [SPIRES] <lb/>[13] Kolb E W, Marra V and Matarrese S, 2008 arXiv:0807.0401 <lb/>[14] Ellis G F R, 2008 Nature 452 158 [SPIRES] <lb/>[15] Hellaby C, 1988 Gen. Rel. Grav. 20 1203 [SPIRES] <lb/>Lu T H C and Hellaby C, 2007 Class. Quantum Grav. 24 4107 [SPIRES] <lb/>McClure M and Hellaby C, 2007 arXiv:0709.0875 <lb/>[16] Buchert T, 2000 Gen. Rel. Grav. 32 105 [SPIRES] <lb/>[17] Räsänen S, 2006 J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. JCAP11(2006)003 [SPIRES] <lb/>[18] Buchert T, 2008 Gen. Rel. Grav. 40 467 [SPIRES] <lb/>[19] Nambu Y and Tanimoto M, 2005 arXiv:gr-qc/0507057 <lb/>[20] Paranjape A and Singh T P, 2006 Class. Quantum Grav. 23 6955 [SPIRES] <lb/>[21] Kai T, Kozaki H, Nakao K, Nambu Y and Yoo C M, 2007 Prog. Theor. Phys. 117 229 [SPIRES] <lb/>[22] Chuang C H, Gu J A and Hwang W Y P, 2008 Class. Quantum Grav. 25 175001 [SPIRES] <lb/>[23] Räsänen S, 2006 Int. J. Mod. Phys. D 15 2141 [SPIRES] <lb/>[24] Räsänen S, 2004 J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. JCAP11(2004)010 [SPIRES] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JCAP10(2008)003 <lb/> Apparent and average accelerations of the Universe <lb/></note> 

			<listBibl>[25] Wiltshire D L, 2007 New J. Phys. 9 377 <lb/>Wiltshire D L, 2007 Phys. Rev. Lett. 99 251101 [SPIRES] <lb/>[26] Leith B M, Ng S C C and Wiltshire D L, 2008 Astrophys. J. 672 L91 [SPIRES] <lb/>[27] Khosravi S, Kourkchi E and Mansouri R, 2007 arXiv:0709.2558 <lb/>[28] Buchert T, Larena J and Alimi J-M, 2006 Class. Quantum Grav. 23 6379 [SPIRES] <lb/>[29] Krasinski A, 1997 Gen. Rel. Grav. 29 637 [SPIRES] <lb/>Krasinski A, 1997 Gen. Rel. Grav. 29 931 [SPIRES] <lb/>Pleba´ ski J and Krasi´ ski A, 2006 Introduction to General Relativity and Cosmology (Cambridge: <lb/>Cambridge University Press) <lb/>[30] Lemaˆ tre G, 1933 Ann. Soc. Sci. Bruxelles A 53 51 (1997 Gen. Rel. Grav. 29 641 (reprinted)) <lb/>Tolman R C, 1934 Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. USA 20 169 (1997 Gen. Rel. Grav. 29 935 (reprinted)) <lb/>[31] Hellaby C and Lake K, 1985 Astrophys. J. 290 381 [SPIRES] <lb/>Hellaby C and Lake K, 1986 Astrophys. J. 300 461 (erratum) <lb/>[32] Partovi M H and Mashhoon B, 1984 Astrophys. J. 276 4 [SPIRES] <lb/>[33] Riess A G et al , 2007 Astrophys. J. 659 98 [SPIRES] <lb/>[34] Li N and Schwarz D J, 2007 arXiv:0710.5073 <lb/>Paranjape A and Singh T P, 2008 arXiv:0806.3497 <lb/>[35] Navarro J F, Frenk C S and White S D M, 1996 Astrophys. J. 462 563 [SPIRES] <lb/>[36] Hossain G M, 2007 arXiv:0709.3490 <lb/>[37] Sussman R A, 2008 arXiv:0807.1145 <lb/>[38] Larena J, Alimi J-M, Buchert T, Kunz M and Corasaniti P-S, 2008 arXiv:0808.1161 <lb/>[39] Krasi´ ski A and Hellaby C, 2002 Phys. Rev. D 65 023501 [SPIRES] <lb/></listBibl> 

			<note place="footnote"> Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics 10 (2008) 003 (stacks.iop.org/JCAP/2008/i=10/a=003) <lb/></note>

			<page> 15 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
