<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:0809.4366v2 [hep-ex] 4 Sep 2009 <lb/>BELLE Preprint 2009-19 <lb/>KEK Preprint 2009-19 <lb/>Measurement of CP asymmetries in B 0 → K 0 π 0 decays <lb/>M. Fujikawa, 27 Y. Yusa, 51 J. Dalseno, 24, 44 M. Hazumi, 8 K. Sumisawa, 8 H. Aihara, 47 K. Arinstein, 1, 35 <lb/>V. Aulchenko, 1, 35 T. Aushev, 21, 14 T. Aziz, 43 A. M. Bakich, 42 V. Balagura, 14 E. Barberio, 25 K. Belous, 12 <lb/>V. Bhardwaj, 37 M. Bischofberger, 27 A. Bondar, 1, 35 A. Bozek, 31 M. Bračko, 23, 15 T. E. Browder, 7 <lb/>Y. Chao, 30 A. Chen, 28 B. G. Cheon, 6 S.-K. Choi, 5 Y. Choi, 41 W. Dungel, 11 S. Eidelman, 1, 35 M. Feindt, <lb/>P. Goldenzweig, 3 H. Ha, 18 J. Haba, 8 B.-Y. Han, 18 K. Hara, 26 Y. Hasegawa, 40 K. Hayasaka, 26 H. Hayashii, 27 <lb/>Y. Horii, 46 Y. Hoshi, 45 W.-S. Hou, 30 H. J. Hyun, 20 T. Iijima, 26 K. Inami, 26 H. Ishino, 48, * R. Itoh, 8 <lb/>M. Iwasaki, 47 Y. Iwasaki, 8 T. Julius, 25 J. H. Kang, 52 H. Kawai, 2 C. Kiesling, 24 H. O. Kim, 20 S. K. Kim, 39 <lb/>Y. I. Kim, 20 Y. J. Kim, 4 K. Kinoshita, 3 B. R. Ko, 18 S. Korpar, 23, 15 M. Kreps, 17 P. Krokovny, 8 T. Kuhr, 17 <lb/>R. Kumar, 37 T. Kumita, 49 Y.-J. Kwon, 52 S.-H. Kyeong, 52 S.-H. Lee, 18 J. Li, 7 C. Liu, 38 D. Liventsev, 14 <lb/>R. Louvot, 21 S. McOnie, 42 K. Miyabayashi, 27 H. Miyata, 33 Y. Miyazaki, 26 T. Mori, 26 Y. Nagasaka, 9 <lb/>E. Nakano, 36 M. Nakao, 8 S. Nishida, 8 K. Nishimura, 7 O. Nitoh, 50 T. Nozaki, 8 T. Ohshima, 26 S. Okuno, <lb/>S. L. Olsen, 7 H. Ozaki, 8 P. Pakhlov, 14 G. Pakhlova, 14 C. W. Park, 41 H. Park, 20 H. K. Park, 20 R. Pestotnik, <lb/>L. E. Piilonen, 51 M. Rozanska, 31 Y. Sakai, 8 O. Schneider, 21 A. J. Schwartz, 3 K. Senyo, 26 M. Shapkin, 12 <lb/>V. Shebalin, 1, 35 C. P. Shen, 7 J.-G. Shiu, 30 J. B. Singh, 37 A. Sokolov, 12 E. Solovieva, 14 S. Stanič, 34 M. Starič, 15 <lb/>T. Sumiyoshi, 49 G. N. Taylor, 25 Y. Teramoto, 36 K. Trabelsi, 8 S. Uehara, 8 Y. Unno, 6 S. Uno, 8 P. Urquijo, 25 <lb/>Y. Usov, 1, 35 G. Varner, 7 K. Vervink, 21 A. Vinokurova, 1, 35 C. H. Wang, 29 P. Wang, 10 Y. Watanabe, 16 <lb/>R. Wedd, 25 E. Won, 18 B. D. Yabsley, 42 Y. Yamashita, 32 C. C. Zhang, 10 Z. P. Zhang, 38 and A. Zupanc 15 <lb/>(The Belle Collaboration) <lb/>1 Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics, Novosibirsk <lb/>2 Chiba University, Chiba <lb/>3 University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio 45221 <lb/>4 The Graduate University for Advanced Studies, Hayama <lb/>5 Gyeongsang National University, Chinju <lb/>6 Hanyang University, Seoul <lb/>7 University of Hawaii, Honolulu, Hawaii 96822 <lb/>8 High Energy Accelerator Research Organization (KEK), Tsukuba <lb/>9 Hiroshima Institute of Technology, Hiroshima <lb/>10 Institute of High Energy Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing <lb/>11 Institute of High Energy Physics, Vienna <lb/>12 Institute of High Energy Physics, Protvino <lb/>13 INFN -Sezione di Torino, Torino <lb/>14 Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics, Moscow <lb/>15 J. Stefan Institute, Ljubljana <lb/>16 Kanagawa University, Yokohama <lb/>17 Institut für Experimentelle Kernphysik, Universität Karlsruhe, Karlsruhe <lb/>18 Korea University, Seoul <lb/>19 Kyoto University, Kyoto <lb/>20 Kyungpook National University, Taegu <lb/>21 École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), Lausanne <lb/>22 Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, University of Ljubljana, Ljubljana <lb/>23 University of Maribor, Maribor <lb/>24 Max-Planck-Institut für Physik, München <lb/>25 University of Melbourne, School of Physics, Victoria 3010 <lb/>26 Nagoya University, Nagoya <lb/>27 Nara Women&apos;s University, Nara <lb/>28 National Central University, Chung-li <lb/>29 National United University, Miao Li <lb/>30 Department of Physics, National Taiwan University, Taipei <lb/>31 H. Niewodniczanski Institute of Nuclear Physics, Krakow <lb/>32 Nippon Dental University, Niigata <lb/>33 Niigata University, Niigata <lb/>34 University of Nova Gorica, Nova Gorica <lb/>35 Novosibirsk State University, Novosibirsk <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>36 Osaka City University, Osaka <lb/>37 Panjab University, Chandigarh <lb/>38 University of Science and Technology of China, Hefei <lb/>39 Seoul National University, Seoul <lb/>40 Shinshu University, Nagano <lb/>41 Sungkyunkwan University, Suwon <lb/>42 University of Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales <lb/>43 Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai <lb/>44 Excellence Cluster Universe, Technische Universität München, Garching <lb/>45 Tohoku Gakuin University, Tagajo <lb/>46 Tohoku University, Sendai <lb/>47 Department of Physics, University of Tokyo, Tokyo <lb/>48 Tokyo Institute of Technology, Tokyo <lb/>49 Tokyo Metropolitan University, Tokyo <lb/>50 Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, Tokyo <lb/>51 IPNAS, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia 24061 <lb/>52 Yonsei University, Seoul <lb/> We report measurements of CP violation parameters in B 0 → K 0 π 0 decays based on a data <lb/>sample of 657 × 10 6 B B pairs collected with the Belle detector at the KEKB e + e − asymmetric-<lb/>energy collider. We use B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 decays for both mixing-induced and direct CP violating <lb/>asymmetry measurements and B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 decays for the direct CP violation measurement. The <lb/>CP violation parameters obtained are sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 <lb/>= +0.67 ± 0.31(stat) ± 0.08(syst) and A K 0 π 0 = <lb/>+0.14 ± 0.13(stat) ± 0.06(syst). The branching fraction of B 0 → K 0 π 0 decay is measured to be <lb/>B(B 0 → K 0 π 0 ) = (8.7 ± 0.5(stat.) ± 0.6(syst.)) × 10 −6 . The observed A K 0 π 0 value differs by 1.9 <lb/>standard deviations from the value expected from an isospin sum rule. <lb/>PACS numbers: 11.30.Er, 12.15.Hh, 13.25.Hw <lb/></front>

			<body>Decays of B mesons mediated by b → s penguin am-<lb/>plitudes play an important role in both measuring the <lb/>Standard Model (SM) parameters and in probing new <lb/>physics. In the SM, CP violation arises from a single <lb/>irreducible Kobayashi-Maskawa (KM) phase [1], in the <lb/>weak-interaction quark-mixing matrix. In the decay se-<lb/>quences Υ(4S) → B 0 B0 → f CP f tag , where one of the B <lb/>mesons decays at time t CP to a CP eigenstate f CP and <lb/>the other decays at time t tag to a final state f tag that <lb/>distinguishes between B 0 and B0 , the decay rate has a <lb/>time dependence given by <lb/>P(∆t) = <lb/>e −|∆t|/τ B 0 <lb/>4τ B 0 <lb/>1 + q • S f sin(∆m d ∆t) <lb/>+ A f cos(∆m d ∆t) . (1) <lb/>Here, S f and A f are parameters that describe mixing-<lb/>induced and direct CP violation, respectively, τ B 0 is the <lb/>B 0 lifetime, ∆m d is the mass difference between the <lb/>two B 0 mass eigenstates, ∆t = t CP − t tag , and the b-<lb/>flavor charge, q = +1(−1) when the tagged B meson is a <lb/>B 0 ( B0 ). The SM predicts S f = −ξ f sin 2φ 1 and A f ≃ 0 <lb/>to a good approximation for most of the decays that pro-<lb/>ceed via b → sq q (q = c, s, d, u) quark transitions [2], <lb/>where ξ f = +1(−1) corresponds to CP -even (-odd) final <lb/>states and φ 1 is an angle of the unitarity triangle. The <lb/>final state K 0 <lb/>S π 0 is a CP eigenstate with CP eigenvalue <lb/>ξ f = −1 while K 0 <lb/>L π 0 is a CP eigenstate with ξ f = +1. <lb/>However, even within the SM, in B 0 → K 0 π 0 decay <lb/>modes, both S K 0 π 0 and A K 0 π 0 could be shifted due to <lb/>the contribution of a color-suppressed tree diagram that <lb/>has a V ub coupling [3]. The resulting effective parameter <lb/>sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 can be evaluated in the 1/m b expansion and/or <lb/>using SU(3) flavor symmetry [4], whereas the shift in <lb/>A K 0 π 0 is predicted by applying an isospin sum rule to <lb/>the recent measurements of B meson decays into Kπ fi-<lb/>nal states [5]. The sum rule for the decay rates gives <lb/>the following relation to within a few percent precision <lb/>determined by SU(2) flavor symmetry [6], <lb/>A K + π − + A K 0 π + <lb/>B(K 0 π + )τ B 0 <lb/>B(K + π − )τ B + <lb/>= <lb/>A K + π 0 <lb/>2B(K + π 0 )τ B 0 <lb/>B(K + π − )τ B + <lb/>+ A K 0 π 0 <lb/>2B(K 0 π 0 ) <lb/>B(K + π − ) <lb/>. <lb/>(2) <lb/>Here, B represents the branching fraction of a decay <lb/>mode. Since the branching fractions and CP asymme-<lb/>tries of other B → Kπ decay modes have been mea-<lb/>sured with good precision [7, 8], A K 0 π 0 is constrained in <lb/>this framework with a small error. Therefore, a signif-<lb/>icant discrepancy between the measured and expected <lb/>values of A K 0 π 0 would indicate a new physics contri-<lb/>bution to the sum rule. The expected uncertainty in <lb/>A K 0 π 0 can be reduced by improved measurement of the <lb/>B 0 → K 0 π 0 branching fraction. Furthermore, recent <lb/>measurements that show an unexpectedly large difference <lb/>between A K + π − and A K + π 0 [8, 9] makes an improved <lb/>measurement of A K 0 π 0 particularly interesting. In this <lb/>paper, in addition to the B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 mode, we measure <lb/>the CP asymmetry in B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 decay for the first <lb/>time, in order to maximize sensitivity to the direct CP <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>violation parameter, A K 0 π 0 . <lb/>At the KEKB asymmetric-energy e + e − (3.5 GeV on <lb/>8 GeV) collider [10], the Υ(4S) is produced with a <lb/>Lorentz boost of βγ = 0.425 nearly along the direction <lb/>opposite to the positron beam line (z-axis). Since B 0 and <lb/>B0 mesons are approximately at rest in the Υ(4S) center-<lb/>of-mass system (CM), ∆t can be determined from the <lb/>displacement in z between the f CP and f tag decay ver-<lb/>tices: ∆t ≃ (z CP − z tag )/(βγc) ≡ ∆z/(βγc). For K 0 <lb/>S π 0 <lb/>decays, the vertex position of the CP side is determined <lb/>from the K 0 <lb/>S decay products and the K 0 <lb/>S mesons are re-<lb/>quired to decay within the silicon vertex detector (SVD) <lb/>for the time dependent CP violation measurement. Since <lb/>we cannot obtain vertex information from K 0 <lb/>L π 0 decays, <lb/>only the parameter A K 0 π 0 is measured by comparing the <lb/>decay rates of B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 and B0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 . The sub-<lb/>set of B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 events for which we cannot obtain <lb/>∆t from the decay vertex reconstruction are treated sim-<lb/>ilarly. <lb/>Previous measurements of CP violation in B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 <lb/>decay have been reported by Belle [11] and BABAR [12]. <lb/>The previous result from Belle was based on 532 × 10 6 <lb/>B B pairs. In this report, all results are based on a data <lb/>sample that contains 657 × 10 6 B B pairs, collected with <lb/>the Belle detector at the KEKB operating at the Υ(4S) <lb/>resonance. <lb/>The Belle detector is a large-solid-angle magnetic spec-<lb/>trometer that consists of SVD, a 50-layer central drift <lb/>chamber (CDC), an array of aerogel threshold Cherenkov <lb/>counters (ACC), a barrel-like arrangement of time-of-<lb/>flight scintillation counters (TOF), and an electromag-<lb/>netic calorimeter (ECL) comprised of CsI(Tl) crystals lo-<lb/>cated inside a superconducting solenoid coil that provides <lb/>a 1.5 T magnetic field. An iron flux-return located out-<lb/>side of the coil is instrumented to detect K 0 <lb/>L mesons and <lb/>to identify muons (KLM). The detector is described in de-<lb/>tail elsewhere [13]. Two configurations of the inner detec-<lb/>tors were used. A 2.0 cm -radius beampipe and a 3-layer <lb/>silicon vertex detector were used for the first sample of <lb/>152 × 10 6 B B pairs, while a 1.5 cm -radius beampipe, a 4-<lb/>layer silicon detector and a small-cell inner drift chamber <lb/>were used to record the remaining 505×10 6 B B pairs [14]. <lb/>Charged particle tracks are reconstructed with the <lb/>SVD and CDC. Photons are identified as isolated ECL <lb/>clusters that are not matched to any charged particle <lb/>track. We reconstruct π 0 candidates from pairs of pho-<lb/>tons that have energies larger than the following thresh-<lb/>olds: 50 MeV for the barrel region and 100 MeV for the <lb/>endcap regions, where the barrel region covers the polar <lb/>angle range 32 • &lt; θ &lt; 130 • , and the endcap regions cover <lb/>the forward and backward regions. The invariant mass <lb/>of reconstructed π 0 &apos;s are required to be in the range be-<lb/>tween 0.115 GeV/c 2 and 0.152 GeV/c 2 . We reconstruct <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S candidates from pairs of oppositely charged tracks <lb/>having invariant mass between 0.480 GeV/c 2 and 0.516 <lb/>GeV/c 2 , which corresponds to three standard deviations <lb/>in a Gaussian fit to the signal Monte Carlo (MC) samples. <lb/>The flight direction of each K 0 <lb/>S candidate is required to <lb/>be consistent with the direction of its vertex displacement <lb/>with respect to the interaction point (IP). Candidate K 0 <lb/>L <lb/>mesons are selected from ECL and/or KLM hit patterns <lb/>that are not associated with any charged tracks and con-<lb/>sistent with the presence of a shower induced by a K 0 <lb/>L <lb/>meson [15]. <lb/>For reconstructed B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 candidates, we iden-<lb/>tify B meson decays using the beam-constrained mass <lb/>M bc ≡ (E CM <lb/>beam ) 2 − (p CM <lb/>B ) 2 and the energy difference <lb/>∆E ≡ E CM <lb/>B <lb/>− E CM <lb/>beam , where E CM <lb/>beam is the beam energy <lb/>in the CM, and E CM <lb/>B <lb/>and p CM <lb/>B <lb/>are the CM energy and <lb/>momentum of the reconstructed B candidate, respec-<lb/>tively. The signal candidates used for measurements of <lb/>CP violation parameters are selected by requiring 5.27 <lb/>GeV/c 2 &lt; M bc &lt; 5.29 GeV/c 2 and −0.15 GeV &lt; ∆E &lt; <lb/>0.1 GeV. For B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 candidates, we can only mea-<lb/>sure the flight direction of the K 0 <lb/>L , so M bc is calculated <lb/>by assuming the parent B 0 to be at rest in the CM. The <lb/>signal is selected by requiring M bc &gt; 5.255 GeV/c 2 . In <lb/>the B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 analysis, if there are multiple candi-<lb/>dates, we select the candidate that has the smallest χ 2 of <lb/>the π 0 mass-constrained fit for the daughter photons. In <lb/>the B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 case, the candidate having the smallest <lb/>cos θ exp is chosen, where θ exp is the angle between the <lb/>measured K 0 <lb/>L flight direction and that expected from the <lb/>π 0 momentum assuming the parent B 0 to be at rest in <lb/>the CM frame. <lb/>The dominant background for the signal is from con-<lb/>tinuum e + e − → uū, d d, ss or cc events. To distinguish <lb/>the spherical B B signal events from these jet-like back-<lb/>grounds, we combine a set of variables that character-<lb/>ize the event topology, i.e., modified-Fox-Wolfram mo-<lb/>ments [16, 17, 18], into a signal (background) likelihood <lb/>variable L sig(bkg) , and impose requirements on the like-<lb/>lihood ratio R s/b ≡ L sig /(L sig + L bkg ): R s/b &gt; 0.3 and <lb/>R s/b &gt; 0.5 for B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 and B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 candidates, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>The b-flavor of the accompanying B meson is deter-<lb/>mined from inclusive properties of particles that are not <lb/>associated with the reconstructed B 0 → K 0 π 0 decays. <lb/>To represent the tagging information, we use two param-<lb/>eters, the b-flavor charge, q and its quality factor, r [19]. <lb/>The parameter r is an event-by-event, MC determined <lb/>flavor-tagging dilution factor that ranges from r = 0 for <lb/>no flavor discrimination to r = 1 for unambiguous fla-<lb/>vor assignment. For events with r &gt; 0.1, the wrong tag <lb/>fractions for six r intervals, w l (l = 1-6), and their differ-<lb/>ences between B 0 and B0 decays, ∆w l , are determined <lb/>using a high-statistics control sample of semi-leptonic and <lb/>hadronic b → c decays [20, 21]. If r &lt; 0.1, we set the <lb/>wrong tag fraction to 0.5, in which case the accompany-<lb/>ing B meson does not provide tagging information and <lb/>such events are not used for the CP violation parame-<lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>ter measurement. The total effective tagging efficiency <lb/>is estimated to be 0.29 ± 0.01, where &quot;effective&quot; means <lb/>a summation over the products of tagging efficiency and <lb/>r 2 of all types of tags used. <lb/>The vertex position for the B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 decay is recon-<lb/>structed using charged pions from the K 0 <lb/>S decay and an <lb/>IP constraint [22]. Each charged pion track is required <lb/>to have more than 1(2) hit(s) on SVD r − φ (z) strips. <lb/>The f tag vertex is obtained with well-reconstructed tracks <lb/>that are not assigned to the B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 decay. <lb/>Figures 1 and 2 show the distribution of the selection <lb/>variables for B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 and B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 candidates. <lb/>The signal yields are obtained from multi-dimensional <lb/>extended unbinned maximum likelihood fits to these dis-<lb/>tributions. The M bc , ∆E and R s/b signal shapes for <lb/>B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 are modeled with three-dimensional his-<lb/>tograms determined from MC, while the continuum back-<lb/>ground shapes in M bc and ∆E are modeled with an AR-<lb/>GUS function [23] and a linear function, respectively, <lb/>whose shape and normalization are floated in the fit. The <lb/>data from a sideband region (5.20 GeV/c 2 &lt; M bc &lt; 5.26 <lb/>GeV/c 2 and 0.05 &lt; ∆E &lt; 0.20 GeV) are used to de-<lb/>termine the continuum background shape in R s/b . For <lb/>B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 , the signal shape in M bc is determined <lb/>from MC samples and the continuum background shape <lb/>is modeled with an ARGUS function. The signal shape in <lb/>R s/b is determined from MC simulation. The continuum <lb/>R s/b shape is determined using Υ(4S) off-resonance data. <lb/>The shape of each variable in the B B background com-<lb/>ponent is modeled using MC events. The signal yield is <lb/>extracted in each r-bin for B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 candidates with <lb/>r-dependent R s/b shapes. For B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 , the ratio <lb/>of B B background to signal is evaluated from MC simu-<lb/>lated events and the B B background contribution is then <lb/>fixed according to that of the signal in the fit. <lb/>We perform a fit to B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 candidates using a <lb/>signal shape with correction factors (to account for small <lb/>differences between data and MC) obtained from B + → <lb/>K + π 0 . The signal yield is 634 ± 34, where the error is <lb/>statistical only. The average signal detection efficiency <lb/>is calculated from MC to be (22.3 ± 0.1)%. We obtain <lb/>a B 0 → K 0 π 0 branching fraction of (8.7 ± 0.5 ± 0.6) × <lb/>10 −6 using only B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 candidates, where the first <lb/>error is statistical and the second is systematic. The <lb/>systematic uncertainty for the B 0 → K 0 π 0 branching <lb/>fraction is estimated by varying the correction factors <lb/>obtained from B + → K + π 0 by ±1σ (+3.6/−2.4%) and <lb/>varying histogram probability density functions (PDF&apos;s) <lb/>bin-by-bin by ±2σ (+1.5/−1.6%). Uncertainties in the <lb/>number of B B pairs (1.4%), MC statistics (0.2%), K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>(4.9%) and π 0 reconstruction efficiencies (2.8%) are also <lb/>included. <lb/>The signal yield of B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 is 285 ± 52, where the <lb/>error is statistical only. We evaluate the systematic un-<lb/>certainty for the B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 signal yield by smearing <lb/>the PDF shapes of M bc , R s/b and r used in the fit. The <lb/>dominant contribution is from the continuum background <lb/>shape and the total systematic error is 20%. Taking into <lb/>account both statistical and systematic errors, the signif-<lb/>icance of B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 is 3.7σ. <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>bc <lb/>M <lb/>5.2 5.22 5.24 5.26 5.28 5.3 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events / (0.002 GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>E (GeV) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-0.3 -0.2 -0.1 0 <lb/>0.1 0.2 <lb/>Events / (0.01 GeV) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>s/b <lb/>R <lb/>0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 <lb/>Events / (0.1) <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>FIG. 1: M bc -∆E-R s/b fit projections of B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 candi-<lb/>dates. The open histogram with the solid curve shows the <lb/>fit result, the filled histogram is the B B background, and <lb/>the dashed histogram is the sum of continuum and B B back-<lb/>grounds. Each plot requires signal enhanced conditions for <lb/>the other variables: 5.27 GeV/c 2 &lt; M bc &lt; 5.29 GeV/c 2 , <lb/>−0.15 GeV &lt; ∆E &lt; 0.1 GeV and R s/b &gt; 0.7. <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>bc <lb/>M <lb/>5.25 5.26 5.27 5.28 5.29 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events / (0.006 GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>s/b <lb/>R <lb/>0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 <lb/>Events / 0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>FIG. 2: B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 fit projections for events with good tags: <lb/>background subtracted M bc (left) and R s/b (right). The open <lb/>solid histogram shows the fit result. The filled histogram is <lb/>the B B background and the open dashed histogram is the <lb/>sum of continuum and B B background. <lb/>We determine sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 and A K 0 <lb/>S π 0 for B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 <lb/>by performing an unbinned maximum-likelihood fit to <lb/>the observed ∆t distribution. The PDF expected for the <lb/>signal distribution, P(∆t; sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 , A K 0 <lb/>S π 0 , q, w l , ∆w l ), is <lb/>given by Eq. (1) fixing τ B 0 and ∆m d to their world aver-<lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>ages [24] and incorporating the effect of wrong flavor as-<lb/>signment. The distribution is convolved with the proper-<lb/>time interval resolution function, R sig (∆t), which takes <lb/>into account the finite vertex resolution. The resolution <lb/>is determined by a multi-parameter fit to the ∆t distribu-<lb/>tions of high-statistics control samples of B 0 → J/ψK 0 <lb/>S <lb/>decays [20, 21], where the K 0 <lb/>S is used for vertex recon-<lb/>struction. We determine the following likelihood for each <lb/>event, <lb/>P i = (1 − f ol ) <lb/>f sig P sig (∆t ′ )R sig (∆t i − ∆t ′ ) <lb/>+ (1 − f sig )P bkg (∆t ′ )R bkg (∆t i − ∆t ′ ) d(∆t ′ ) <lb/>+ f ol P ol (∆t i ). <lb/>(3) <lb/>The signal probability, f sig , depends on r and is calcu-<lb/>lated in each region on an event-by-event basis as a func-<lb/>tion of M bc , R s/b and, where applicable, ∆E from the <lb/>shapes given in Figs. 1 and 2. P bkg is a PDF for contin-<lb/>uum and B B backgrounds. The background PDF&apos;s are <lb/>determined from M bc and ∆E sideband data for contin-<lb/>uum and, MC and data for B B. The term, P ol (∆t) is <lb/>a broad Gaussian function that represents a small out-<lb/>lier component with a fraction f ol [20, 21]. The free pa-<lb/>rameters in the final fits are sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 and A K 0 <lb/>S π 0 , which <lb/>are determined by maximizing the likelihood function <lb/>L = Π i P i (∆t i ; sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 , A K 0 <lb/>S π 0 ) where the product is over <lb/>all events. <lb/>The B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 and B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 candidates that do <lb/>not have vertex information are only used for the deter-<lb/>mination of A K 0 π 0 . Since ∆t vanishes by integration, Eq. <lb/>(3) becomes simpler: <lb/>P i = f sig P sig (q) + (1 − f sig )P bkg (q), <lb/>(4) <lb/>where P bkg (q = ±1) = 0.5 since we assign no tag in-<lb/>formation for the continuum background meaning that <lb/>the number of events tagged as q = +1 and q = −1 are <lb/>equal. Since no CP violation is expected in the back-<lb/>ground outlier component, we include the f ol term in the <lb/>P bkg PDF. The signal PDF is obtained by integrating <lb/>the time-dependent decay rate Eq. (1) from −∞ to +∞: <lb/>P sig (q; A K 0 <lb/>L π 0 ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 + <lb/>qA K 0 π 0 <lb/>1 + τ 2 <lb/>B 0 ∆m 2 <lb/>d <lb/>. <lb/>(5) <lb/>We obtain the fit results sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 = +0.67 ± 0.31 and <lb/>A K 0 π 0 = +0.14 ± 0.13 for B 0 → K 0 π 0 . Fits to individ-<lb/>ual modes yield sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 = +0.67 ± 0.31 and A K 0 <lb/>S π 0 = <lb/>+0.15 ± 0.13 for B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 , and A K 0 <lb/>L π 0 = −0.01 ± 0.45 <lb/>for B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 , where the errors are statistical only. <lb/>Fig. 3 shows the background subtracted ∆t distribu-<lb/>tions for B 0 and B0 tags as well as the asymmetry for <lb/>B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 candidates. The dominant sources of sys-<lb/>tematic errors are summarized in Table I. The systematic <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Events / (2.5 ps) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>Tags <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>t (ps) <lb/>∆ <lb/>-6 -4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>Asymmetry <lb/>-1 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>FIG. 3: The top plot shows the background subtracted ∆t dis-<lb/>tribution for B 0 and B0 tags where the solid (broken) curve <lb/>represents the ∆t curve for B 0 ( B0 ) in the good tag region <lb/>0.5 &lt; r ≤ 1.0. The bottom plot shows the background sub-<lb/>tracted asymmetry defined as (N Sig <lb/>B0 − N Sig <lb/>B 0 )/(N Sig <lb/>B0 + N Sig <lb/>B 0 ) in <lb/>each ∆t bin where N Sig <lb/>B 0 (N Sig <lb/>B0 )) is the B 0 ( B0 ) signal yield <lb/>extracted in that ∆t bin. The solid curve shows the CP <lb/>asymmetry result expected from the fit. <lb/>uncertainty from wrong tag fractions, physics parame-<lb/>ters, resolution function, background ∆t and background <lb/>fractions are studied by varying each parameter by its er-<lb/>ror. A possible fit bias is examined by fitting a large num-<lb/>ber of pseudo-experiments. The systematic uncertainty <lb/>for the vertex reconstruction is estimated by changing the <lb/>charged track selection criteria. The dominant effect for <lb/>∆A K 0 π 0 comes from misalignment between the SVD and <lb/>CDC. The tag side interference is evaluated from pseudo-<lb/>experiments in which the effect of possible CP violation <lb/>in B 0 → f tag decays is taken into account [25]. As a <lb/>cross-check, we fit the B 0 lifetime using the same event <lb/>sample that is used for the B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 CP violation pa-<lb/>rameter measurement and obtain τ B 0 = 1.46 ± 0.18 ps, <lb/>which is consistent with the PDG world average [24]. <lb/>In summary, we use B 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 decays to measure <lb/>the branching fraction and CP violation parameters for <lb/>B 0 → K 0 π 0 . We use B 0 → K 0 <lb/>L π 0 decays to measure the <lb/>direct CP violation parameter. Our results are <lb/>B(B 0 → K 0 π 0 ) = (8.7 ± 0.5 ± 0.6) × 10 −6 <lb/>(6) <lb/>A K 0 π 0 = +0.14 ± 0.13 ± 0.06 <lb/>(7) <lb/>sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 <lb/>= +0.67 ± 0.31 ± 0.08, <lb/>(8) <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE I: Systematic uncertainties in sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 and A K 0 π 0 . <lb/>Source <lb/>∆ sin 2φ eff <lb/>1 <lb/>∆A K 0 π 0 <lb/>Wrong tag fraction <lb/>0.007 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>Physics parameters <lb/>0.007 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Resolution function <lb/>0.063 <lb/>0.007 <lb/>Background ∆t shape <lb/>0.015 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>Background fraction <lb/>0.029 <lb/>0.022 <lb/>Possible fit bias <lb/>0.010 <lb/>0.020 <lb/>Vertex reconstruction <lb/>0.013 <lb/>0.022 <lb/>Tag side interference <lb/>0.014 <lb/>0.054 <lb/>Total <lb/>0.077 <lb/>0.064 <lb/>where the first and second errors listed are statistical <lb/>and systematic, respectively. These results are consis-<lb/>tent with previous measurements [11, 12]; the value for <lb/>the branching fraction is the most precise single measure-<lb/>ment to-date. We test the isospin sum rule (Eq. 2) by <lb/>inserting our measured values for the branching fraction <lb/>and A K 0 π 0 . For the other parameters we use the most <lb/>recent world average values [26]. We find the isospin re-<lb/>lationship to be only marginally satisfied; the level of <lb/>disagreement is 1.9σ. Specifically, the difference between <lb/>our measurement of A K 0 π 0 ×B(K 0 π 0 ) and that predicted <lb/>by Eq. 2 is 1.9σ. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank the KEKB group for the excellent opera-<lb/>tion of the accelerator, the KEK cryogenics group for the <lb/>efficient operation of the solenoid, and the KEK com-<lb/>puter group and the National Institute of Informatics <lb/>for valuable computing and SINET3 network support. <lb/>We acknowledge support from the Ministry of Educa-<lb/>tion, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology (MEXT) <lb/>of Japan, the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science <lb/>(JSPS), and the Tau-Lepton Physics Research Center of <lb/>Nagoya University; the Australian Research Council and <lb/>the Australian Department of Industry, Innovation, Sci-<lb/>ence and Research; the National Natural Science Foun-<lb/>dation of China under contract No. 10575109, 10775142, <lb/>10875115 and 10825524; the Department of Science and <lb/>Technology of India; the BK21 and WCU program of the <lb/>Ministry Education Science and Technology, the CHEP <lb/>SRC program and Basic Research program (grant No. <lb/>R01-2008-000-10477-0) of the Korea Science and Engi-<lb/>neering Foundation, Korea Research Foundation (KRF-<lb/>2008-313-C00177), and the Korea Institute of Science and <lb/>Technology Information; the Polish Ministry of Science <lb/>and Higher Education; the Ministry of Education and <lb/>Science of the Russian Federation and the Russian Fed-<lb/>eral Agency for Atomic Energy; the Slovenian Research <lb/>Agency; the Swiss National Science Foundation; the Na-<lb/>tional Science Council and the Ministry of Education of <lb/>Taiwan; and the U.S. Department of Energy. This work <lb/>is supported by a Grant-in-Aid from MEXT for Science <lb/>Research in a Priority Area (&quot;New Development of Fla-<lb/>vor Physics&quot;), and from JSPS for Creative Scientific Re-<lb/>search (&quot;Evolution of Tau-lepton Physics&quot;). <lb/></div>

			<front> * now at Okayama University, Okayama <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>[1] M. Kobayashi and T. Maskawa, Prog. Theor. Phys. 49, <lb/>652 (1973). <lb/>[2] Y. Grossman and M. P. Worah, Phys. Lett. B395, 241 <lb/>(1997); R. Fleischer, Int. J. Mod. Phys. A A, 2459 ()1997; <lb/>M. Ciuchini, E. Franco, G. Martinelli, A. Masiero and L. <lb/>Silvestrini, Phys. Rev. Lett. 79, 978 (1997); D. London <lb/>and A. Soni, Phys. Lett. B 407, 61 (1997). <lb/>[3] J. Zupan, arXiv:0707.1323 [hep-ph] (2007). <lb/>[4] R. Fleischer, S. Jager, D. Pirjol and J. Zupan, Phys Rev. <lb/>D78, 111501 (2008). <lb/>[5] M. Gronau and J. L. Rosner, Phys. Rev. D74, 057503 <lb/>(2006); Phys. Lett. B666, 467 (2008). <lb/>[6] M. Gronau, Phys. Lett. B627, 82 (2005). <lb/>[7] K. Abe et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. 99, <lb/>121601 (2007). <lb/>[8] B. Aubert et al. (BABAR Collaboration), Phys. Rev. <lb/>D76, 091102 (2007). <lb/>[9] S. W. Lin et al. (Belle Collaboration), Nature 452, 332-<lb/>335 (2008). <lb/>[10] S. Kurokawa and E. Kikutani, Nucl. Instr. and. Meth. <lb/>A499, 1 (2003), and other papers included in this volume. <lb/>[11] K. Abe et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D76, <lb/>091103 (2007). <lb/>[12] B. Aubert et al. (BABAR Collaboration), Phys. Rev. <lb/>D77, 012003 (2008), Phys. Rev. D79 052003 (2009). <lb/>[13] A. Abashian et al. (Belle Collabolation), Nucl. Instr. and <lb/>Meth. A 479, 117 (2002). <lb/>[14] Z. Natkaniec et al. (Belle SVD2 Group), Nucl. Instr. and <lb/>Meth. A 560, 1(2006). <lb/>[15] K. Abe et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. 87 <lb/>091802 (2001); Phys. Rev. D66, 071102 (2002). <lb/>[16] K. Abe et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. 87, <lb/>101801 (2001). <lb/>[17] K. Abe et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Lett. B511, <lb/>151 (2001). <lb/>[18] S. H. Lee, K. Suzuki, et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 91, 261801 (2003). <lb/>[19] H. Kakuno et al., Nucl. Instr. and Meth.A 533 516 <lb/>(2004). <lb/>[20] K. F. Chen et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D72, <lb/>012004 (2005). <lb/>[21] K. Abe et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D71, <lb/>072003 (2005). <lb/>[22] K. Sumisawa et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett. 95, 061801 (2005). <lb/>[23] H. Albrecht et al. (ARGUS Collaboration), Phys. Lett. <lb/>B241, 278 (1990). <lb/>[24] C. Amsler et al. (Particle Data Group), Phys. Lett. <lb/>B667, 1 (2008). <lb/>[25] O. Long, M. Baak, R. N. Cahn and D. Kirkby, Phys. <lb/>Rev. D68, 034010 (2003). <lb/>[26] E. <lb/>Barberio <lb/>et <lb/>al., <lb/>arXiv:0808.1297 <lb/>[hep-ex] <lb/>(2009) <lb/>and <lb/>online <lb/>web <lb/>update <lb/>http://www.slac.stanford.edu/xorg/hfag/rare/index.html. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
