<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:0908.0188v3 [hep-ex] 3 Dec 2009 <lb/>Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) <lb/>collisions to LHC energies <lb/>Ajay Kumar Dash 1 and Bedangadas Mohanty 2 <lb/>1 Institute Of Physics, Bhubaneswar 751005, India 2 Variable Energy Cyclotron <lb/>Centre, Kolkata 700064, India <lb/> E-mail: ajay@iopb.res.in,bmohanty@veccal.ernet.in <lb/>Abstract. The multiplicity (N ch ) and pseudorapidity distribution (dN ch /dη) of <lb/>primary charged particles in p+p collisions at Large Hadron Collider (LHC) energies <lb/>of <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 10 and 14 TeV are obtained from extrapolation of existing measurements <lb/>at lower <lb/>√ <lb/>s. These distributions are then compared to calculations from PYTHIA <lb/>and PHOJET models. The existing <lb/>√ <lb/>s measurements are unable to distinguish <lb/>between a logarithmic and power law dependence of the average charged particle <lb/>multiplicity ( N ch ) on <lb/>√ <lb/>s, and their extrapolation to energies accessible at LHC give <lb/>very different values. Assuming a reasonably good description of inclusive charged <lb/>particle multiplicity distributions by Negative Binomial Distributions (NBD) at lower <lb/>√ <lb/>s to hold for LHC energies, we observe that the logarithmic <lb/>√ <lb/>s dependence of <lb/>N ch are favored by the models at midrapidity. The dN ch /dη versus η for the <lb/>existing measurements are found to be reasonably well described by a function with <lb/>three parameters which accounts for the basic features of the distribution, height at <lb/>midrapidity, central rapidity plateau and the higher rapidity fall-off. Extrapolation <lb/>of these parameters as a function of <lb/>√ <lb/>s is used to predict the pseudorapidity <lb/>distributions of charged particles at LHC energies. dN ch /dη calculations from PYTHIA <lb/>and PHOJET models are found to be lower compared to those obtained from the <lb/>extrapolated dN ch /dη versus η distributions for a broad η range. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>The Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at CERN is designed for colliding proton-proton <lb/>beams upto <lb/>√ s = 14 TeV [1]. Collisions at these unprecedented high energies will <lb/>provide opportunities for new physics [1]. In order to fully exploit the enormous <lb/>physics potential it is important to have a complete understanding of the reaction <lb/>mechanism. The particle multiplicity distributions, one of the first measurements to <lb/>be made at LHC, will be used to test various particle production models based on <lb/>different physics mechanism and also provide constrains on model features. Some of <lb/>these models are based on string fragmentation mechanism [2] and some are based on <lb/>Pomeron exchange [3]. <lb/>In this paper, we first make a compilation of the existing data on the average <lb/>charged particle multiplicity (at midrapidity and full rapidity range) and charged <lb/>particle pseudorapidity distribution as a function of <lb/>√ s. Then we judiciously extrapolate <lb/>the measurements to obtain prediction of N ch (for midrapidity and full rapidity range), <lb/>charged particle multiplicity distributions and dN ch /dη distributions at LHC energies <lb/>of <lb/>√ s = 10 and 14 TeV. These results are also compared to calculations from PYTHIA <lb/>[2] and PHOJET [3] monte carlo models. Energy dependence of average number of <lb/>particles produced in p+p(p) collisions can be used to distinguish various models [4]. <lb/>A statistical model [5] and some hydrodynamical models [6] predict a dependence of <lb/>N ∼ s 1/4 , whereas multiperipheral models [7] and Feynman&apos;s scaling [8] lead to the <lb/>dependence as N ∼ ln(s). Such a logarithmic dependence and on higher powers of <lb/>ln(s) is also predicted by Regge-Mueller model [9]. Arguments based on simple phase <lb/>space considerations [10] however predict a power law dependence as N ∼ s 1/3 . In this <lb/>work we show that for the N ch data available at various <lb/>√ s, we cannot distinguish <lb/>the logarithmic and power law dependences on <lb/>√ s. However the measurements at <lb/>the LHC energies will provide a clear answer. The pseudorapidity distributions on <lb/>the other hand is found to be described by a form which resembles a generalized <lb/>Fermi distribution. Such distributions have been used to explain the pseudorapidity <lb/>distributions of produced particles in hadronic collisions at ISR [11] and heavy-ion <lb/>collisions at RHIC [12]. <lb/>The compiled experimental data presented in this paper corresponds to Non Singly <lb/>Diffractive (NSD) events for minimum bias triggers. The charged particle data were <lb/>corrected for secondary interactions, gamma conversions, short lived decays (K 0 <lb/>S , Λ), <lb/>reconstruction efficiency and acceptance effects by the experiments. To match the <lb/>experimental conditions, the model simulations presented are also corrected for short <lb/>lived decays. A transverse momentum (p T ) cut of greater than 100 MeV/c are usually <lb/>used in realistic experimental conditions, as for example in ALICE experiment at LHC. <lb/>Model simulations using PYTHIA and PHOJET suggest, a 6% ± 2% effect on the <lb/>charged hadron multiplicity due to a 100 MeV/c cut-off in p T at <lb/>√ s = 10-14 TeV. The <lb/>error of 2% comes from the difference in results from PYTHIA and PHOJET models. <lb/>At LHC, while most of the experiments will have mid-rapidity measurements of charged <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>particle multiplicity, ALICE experiment has the possibility to measure the distributions <lb/>over -5.0 &lt; η &lt; 3.5 range [1]. The CMS and ATLAS experiments will have a more <lb/>limited coverage of |η| &lt; 2.5 units [1]. <lb/>The model results presented are from PYTHIA using version 6.4 (ATLAS tuned) <lb/>and those from PHOJET with version 1.12 (default settings). It may be mentioned <lb/>that recently a new tuned version of PYTHIA has been released [13]. The PHOJET <lb/>model combines the ideas based on a dual parton model [14] on soft process of <lb/>particle production and uses lowest-order perturbative QCD for hard process. Regge <lb/>phenomenology is used to parameterize the total, elastic and inelastic cross-sections. <lb/>The initial and final state parton shower are generated in leading log-approximation. <lb/>PYTHIA on the other hand uses string fragmentation as a process of hadronization <lb/>and tends to use the perturbative parton-parton scattering for low to high p T particle <lb/>production. Although there are several other theoretical predictions on total cross <lb/>section expected at LHC energies [15], current work focuses on how a judicious <lb/>extrapolation from existing multiplicity data compares to the calculations from some of <lb/>the available models [2, 3]. <lb/>2. Multiplicity distribution <lb/>ch <lb/>N <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>) <lb/>ch <lb/>P(N <lb/>−4 <lb/>10 <lb/>−3 <lb/>10 <lb/>−2 <lb/>10 <lb/>−1 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>η <lb/>| <lb/>p <lb/>900 GeV p <lb/>p <lb/>540 GeV p <lb/>p <lb/>200 GeV p <lb/>ch <lb/>N <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>) <lb/>ch <lb/>P(N <lb/>−4 <lb/>10 <lb/>−3 <lb/>10 <lb/>−2 <lb/>10 <lb/>−1 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>| &lt; 5.0 <lb/>η <lb/>| <lb/>p <lb/>900 GeV p <lb/>p <lb/>540 GeV p <lb/>p <lb/>200 GeV p <lb/>Figure 1. Multiplicity distribution for charged particles in p+p collisions at various <lb/>center of mass energies at midrapidity (left panel) and full rapidity (right panel) <lb/>ranges [16]. The errors are statistical. The solid lines are NBD fit to the data points <lb/>using the function given in Eqn. 1. <lb/>The measurements of charged particle multiplicity distribution has been found to <lb/>be well described by negative binomial distribution (NBD) at midrapidity and also for <lb/>the full rapidity region in p+p [16]. The NBD distribution has a form, <lb/>P NBD ( N ch , k; n) = <lb/>Γ(n + k) <lb/>Γ(n + 1)Γ(k) <lb/>• <lb/>( N ch /k) n <lb/>( N ch /k + 1) n+k , <lb/>(1) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>s (GeV) <lb/>√ <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>3 <lb/>10 <lb/>4 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt; <lb/>ch <lb/>&lt;N <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>Data Full rapidity <lb/>PYTHIA6.4 Full rapidity <lb/>PHOJET1.12 Full rapidity <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>η <lb/>Data | <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>η <lb/>PYTHIA6.4 | <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>η <lb/>PHOJET1.12 | <lb/>2 <lb/>s)) <lb/>√ <lb/>s) + c (ln( <lb/>√ <lb/>a + b ln( <lb/>c&apos; <lb/>s) <lb/>√ <lb/>a&apos; + b&apos; ( <lb/>s (GeV) <lb/>√ <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>3 <lb/>10 <lb/>4 <lb/>10 <lb/>1/k <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>Data Full rapidity <lb/>PYTHIA6.4 Full rapidity <lb/>PHOJET1.12 Full rapidity <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>η <lb/>Data | <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>η <lb/>PYTHIA6.4 | <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>η <lb/>PHOJET1.12 | <lb/>s) <lb/>√ <lb/>ln( <lb/>β <lb/>+ <lb/>α <lb/>Figure 2. NBD fit parameters N ch (left panel) and 1/k (right panel) to multiplicity <lb/>distributions in p+p collisions at various center of mass energies [16]. The lines are <lb/>fits to the data points using the function forms as discussed in text. Also shown for <lb/>comparison are the results from PYTHIA and PHOJET models at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 200, 540 and <lb/>900 GeV. <lb/>The NBD has two parameters, N ch and k. Where the parameter k is an interesting <lb/>quantity, 1/k → 0 would correspond to Poisson distribution (independent particle <lb/>production) and k = 1 would correspond to Geometric distribution. Under the limit <lb/>of large multiplicity (N ch → Large), the NBD distribution goes over to a Gamma <lb/>Distribution. Some of the measured multiplicity distributions at midrapidity (|η| &lt; 0.5) <lb/>and over full pseudorapidity range (|η| &lt; 5.0) are fitted to NBD distribution and are <lb/>shown in Fig. 1 left and right panels respectively. The NBD parameters N ch and k <lb/>extracted are plotted in Fig. 2 left and right panels respectively. The CDF experiment <lb/>results are not used in the current studies as they have multiplicity distributions with <lb/>a high p T cut-off of 400 MeV/c measured within |η| &lt; 1 [17]. PYTHIA and PHOJET <lb/>model calculations suggest that there is more than 50% loss in the average number of <lb/>charged particles due to a p T cut-off of 400 MeV/c at midrapidity. Since all other results <lb/>presented have a much smaller p T cut-off ∼ 100 MeV/c, inclusion of CDF results would <lb/>make this comparative study heavily dependent on the model based extrapolation to <lb/>lower p T regions. <lb/>It is observed from Fig. 2 that both at midrapidity and full rapidity range the <lb/>N ch increases with <lb/>√ s while the k value decreases with <lb/>√ s. The <lb/>√ s region for which <lb/>measurements exists, the N ch dependence can be described reasonably well by both <lb/>the following expressions (as shown in Fig. 2), <lb/>N ch = a + b ln( <lb/>√ <lb/>s) + c (ln( <lb/>√ <lb/>s)) 2 <lb/>(2) <lb/>and <lb/>N ch = a ′ + b ′ ( <lb/>√ <lb/>s) c ′ , <lb/>(3) <lb/>where a, b, c, a ′ , b ′ and c ′ are fit parameters. The values of a, b, c, a ′ , b ′ and c ′ at <lb/>midrapidity are 3.8 ± 0.1, 1.5 ± 0.2, 0.45 ± 0.1, 2.3 ± 0.14, 1.5 ± 0.13 and 1.2 ± 0.26 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>respectively. For full rapidity coverage the values of a, b, c, a ′ , b ′ and c ′ are 1.3 ± 0.3, <lb/>0.62 ± 0.17, 0.59 ± 0.02, -10.5 ± 0.86, 9.9 ± 0.69 and 0.22 ± 0.01 respectively. It is <lb/>noted that extrapolation of the power law function to LHC energies seems to lead to <lb/>a sudden increase in average charged particle multiplicity at midrapidity. Such a large <lb/>unexpected jump in the multiplicities at midrapidity already seems to put constraints on <lb/>applicability of such a functional form. As will be seen later in Fig. 4 such a functional <lb/>form will lead to a probability distribution of charged particle multiplicity at midrapidity <lb/>not showing the characteristic drop at higher multiplicity. Such a drop is expected <lb/>from PYTHIA, PHOJET models and is seen for available experimental data shown in <lb/>Fig. 1. In Fig. 2 the average number of charged particles from experiments at <lb/>√ s = 200, <lb/>540 and 900 GeV are compared to corresponding results from PYTHIA and PHOJET <lb/>models. Both the models seem to be in reasonable agreement with the measurements <lb/>at midrapidity and full rapidity. <lb/>The 1/k dependence on <lb/>√ s has the form α + β ln( <lb/>√ s), where α and β are fit <lb/>parameters. For midrapidity the values of α and β are 0.65 ± 0.03 and 0.07 ± 0.03 <lb/>respectively. For full rapidity case, the values of α and β are -0.11 ± 0.006 and 0.06 ± <lb/>0.001 respectively. The results from PYTHIA and PHOJET models are also shown. At <lb/>higher energies the results from PHOJET is in better agreement with the measurements <lb/>compared to those from PYTHIA. For the midrapidity measurements PHOJET model <lb/>calculations fail to match the data for <lb/>√ s = 200 GeV. <lb/>We have examined the charged particle multiplicity distribution from E735 <lb/>Collaboration for p+p collisions at <lb/>√ s = 1800 GeV [18]. The multiplicity distribution <lb/>is found to be well explained using the sum of two NBD functions instead of a single <lb/>NBD as for the rest of the data discussed above. The sum of two NBD is given as, <lb/>F = ωP 1 <lb/>NBD ( N ch 1 , k 1 ; n) + (1 − ω)P 2 <lb/>NBD ( N ch 2 , k 2 ; n) <lb/>(4) <lb/>where P 1 <lb/>NBD and P 2 <lb/>NBD have the same form as in Eqn 1, ω is the weight factor, <lb/>N ch 1 and N ch 2 , k 1 and k 2 are the respective NBD parameters. The fit to the E735 <lb/>data by this function is shown in Fig. 3. The values of various parameters obtained from <lb/>the fit are, N ch 1 = 36.5 ± 1.7, N ch 2 = 86.9 ± 2.6, k 1 = 2.8 ± 0.2, k 2 = 10.3 ± 0.8 <lb/>and ω = 0.18 ± 0.03. The overall average value of the charged particle multiplicity is <lb/>44.4. Since this data could not be fitted to a single NBD, in contrast to the data from <lb/>other energies discussed in this paper, we have not included this measurement in our <lb/>extrapolation studies. Further it is observed from the Fig. 2 that the two extrapolations <lb/>discussed in Eqns 2 and 3 tend to differ only above <lb/>√ s = 2000 GeV. The physics reason <lb/>attributed to a different shape of multiplicity distribution at <lb/>√ s = 1800 GeV compared <lb/>to those at lower energies is due to multiple parton interactions [18]. These result are <lb/>also indicative of the deviation from the KNO (Koba, Nielsen and Olesen) scaling [19]. <lb/>The weight factor shows the second NBD distribution dominates among the two. It <lb/>will certainly be interesting to find out if this feature is more pronounced at the LHC <lb/>energies. <lb/>The extrapolated values of N ch and k at both midrapidity and full rapidity regions <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>ch <lb/>N <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Relative Cross Section <lb/>−3 <lb/>10 <lb/>−2 <lb/>10 <lb/>−1 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>p <lb/>1800 GeV p <lb/>Double NBD fit <lb/>Figure 3. Relative cross-section of charged particles produced in p+p collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s <lb/>= 1800 GeV [18] fitted to a sum of to NBD functions. See text for more details. <lb/>Table 1. Extrapolated NBD parameters N ch and k for different <lb/>√ <lb/>s at midrapidity <lb/>and full rapidity range for p+p collisions at <lb/>√ s = 10 and 14 TeV. <lb/>Eqn. <lb/>√ s (TeV) <lb/>N ch <lb/>k <lb/>η range <lb/>Eqn. 2 <lb/>10 <lb/>9.6 ± 1.1 <lb/>1.2 ± 0.14 |η| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>Eqn. 2 <lb/>10 <lb/>56.7 ± 3.8 2.2 ± 0.09 |η| &lt; 5.0 <lb/>Eqn. 3 <lb/>10 <lb/>25.0 ± 11.5 1.24 ± 0.14 |η| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>Eqn. 3 <lb/>10 <lb/>63.7 ± 11.3 2.2 ± 0.09 |η| &lt; 5.0 <lb/>Eqn. 2 <lb/>14 <lb/>10.8 ± 1.3 1.20 ± 0.14 |η| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>Eqn. 2 <lb/>14 <lb/>60.7 ± 4.0 2.14 ± 0.09 |η| &lt; 5.0 <lb/>Eqn. 3 <lb/>14 <lb/>36.2 ± 18.5 1.20 ± 0.14 |η| &lt; 0.5 <lb/>Eqn. 3 <lb/>14 <lb/>69.4 ± 12.2 2.14 ± 0.09 |η| &lt; 5.0 <lb/>using the functional forms as in Eqns 2 and 3 for <lb/>√ s = 10 and 14 TeV are given in <lb/>the Table 1. Note the difference in values of N ch depending on the dependence on <lb/>√ s <lb/>as per Eqn. 2 (logarithmic dependence) or Eqn. 3 (power law dependence). Knowing <lb/>these values (parameters of NBD function) we can predict the multiplicity distributions <lb/>for both midrapidity and full rapidity ranges at <lb/>√ s = 10 and 14 TeV using Eqn. 1. <lb/>These distributions for both midrapidity regions and full rapidity regions are shown in <lb/>Fig. 4 and Fig. 5 respectively. The left panels are for <lb/>√ s = 10 TeV and right panels <lb/>are for <lb/>√ s = 14 TeV. The results when compared to PYTHIA and PHOJET model <lb/>calculations show that the extrapolation of N ch using Eqn. 2 is favored by the models <lb/>at midrapidity. The extrapolated results show no such preference to models in full <lb/>rapidity region. In general PYTHIA results are found to be higher compared to those <lb/>from PHOJET calculations. Actual experimental measurements at LHC will confirm <lb/>the preferred N ch dependence on <lb/>√ s. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>ch <lb/>N <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>) <lb/>ch <lb/>P(N <lb/>−5 <lb/>10 <lb/>−4 <lb/>10 <lb/>−3 <lb/>10 <lb/>−2 <lb/>10 <lb/>−1 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>≤ <lb/>| <lb/>η <lb/>| <lb/>10 TeV PYTHIA <lb/>10 TeV PHOJET <lb/>Extrapolation Log <lb/>Extrapolation power law <lb/>ch <lb/>N <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>) <lb/>ch <lb/>P(N <lb/>−5 <lb/>10 <lb/>−4 <lb/>10 <lb/>−3 <lb/>10 <lb/>−2 <lb/>10 <lb/>−1 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>≤ <lb/>| <lb/>η <lb/>| <lb/>14 TeV PYTHIA <lb/>14 TeV PHOJET <lb/>Extrapolation Log <lb/>Extrapolation power law <lb/>Figure 4. Estimated multiplicity distribution for charged particles in p+p collisions <lb/>at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 10 (left panel) and 14 TeV (right panel) in midrapidity. Solid and dashed lines <lb/>are distributions obtained from N ch extrapolation using Eqns. 2 and 3 respectively. <lb/>The dotted lines reflects errors in multiplicity distributions due to extrapolation of the <lb/>parameters N ch and k. The results are compared to corresponding calculations from <lb/>PYTHIA and PHOJET. <lb/>ch <lb/>N <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>) <lb/>ch <lb/>P(N <lb/>−5 <lb/>10 <lb/>−4 <lb/>10 <lb/>−3 <lb/>10 <lb/>−2 <lb/>10 <lb/>−1 <lb/>10 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>≤ <lb/>| <lb/>η <lb/>| <lb/>10 TeV PYTHIA <lb/>10 TeV PHOJET <lb/>Extrapolation Log <lb/>Extrapolation power law <lb/>ch <lb/>N <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>) <lb/>ch <lb/>P(N <lb/>−5 <lb/>10 <lb/>−4 <lb/>10 <lb/>−3 <lb/>10 <lb/>−2 <lb/>10 <lb/>−1 <lb/>10 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>≤ <lb/>| <lb/>η <lb/>| <lb/>14 TeV PYTHIA <lb/>14 TeV PHOJET <lb/>Extrapolation Log <lb/>Extrapolation power law <lb/>Figure 5. Same as Fig. 4 for full rapidity region. <lb/>3. Pseudorapidity distribution <lb/>The pseudorapidity distributions of charged particles from the existing data at <lb/>√ s = <lb/>53, 200, 546 and 900 GeV [20] can be described by the following functional form, <lb/>dN <lb/>dη <lb/>= <lb/>C + η <lb/>1 + exp η−η 0 <lb/>δ <lb/>(5) <lb/>This formula is chosen to describe the central plateau and the fall off in the <lb/>fragmentation region of the distribution by means of the parameters η 0 and δ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>η <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>η <lb/>d <lb/>ch <lb/>dN <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>p <lb/>900 GeV p <lb/>p <lb/>546 GeV p <lb/>p <lb/>200 GeV p <lb/>p <lb/>53 GeV p <lb/>NSD <lb/>η <lb/>−10 −8 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>η <lb/>d <lb/>ch <lb/>dN <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>CDF − 1800GeV (NSD) <lb/>UA5 − 900GeV (NSD) <lb/>UA5 − 546GeV (NSD) <lb/>UA5 − 200GeV (NSD) <lb/>UA5 − 53GeV (NSD) <lb/>PYTHIA6.4 <lb/>PHOJET1.12 <lb/>Figure 6. Left panel: Pseudorapidity distribution for charged particles in p+p <lb/>collisions at various center of mass energies [20]. The solid lines are fit to the data points <lb/>using the function given in Eqn. 5. Right panel: Comparison of the pseudorapidity <lb/>distributions for charged particles at various <lb/>√ <lb/>s to PYTHIA and PHOJET model <lb/>calculations. <lb/>Table 2. Parameters C, η 0 and δ for different <lb/>√ <lb/>s. <lb/>Collision <lb/>√ s (GeV) <lb/>C <lb/>η 0 <lb/>δ <lb/>p+p <lb/>53 <lb/>2.4 ± 0.23 1.5 ± 0.17 1.12 ± 0.1 <lb/>p+p <lb/>200 <lb/>2.5 ± 0.07 2.5 ± 0.05 1.10 ± 0.04 <lb/>p+p <lb/>546 <lb/>3.0 ± 0.10 2.9 ± 0.07 1.15 ± 0.04 <lb/>p+p <lb/>900 <lb/>3.6 ± 0.10 3.0 ± 0.05 1.36 ± 0.05 <lb/>respectively. The term C + η, C is a fit parameter, describes the magnitude of the <lb/>distribution and the dip at the η = 0. A similar form has been used to describe the p+p <lb/>data at ISR energies [11] and heavy-ion collisions at RHIC [12]. The distribution is a <lb/>generalization of Fermi distribution and recent work suggests a relation of this functional <lb/>form to string percolation model [21]. <lb/>The values of the parameters C, η 0 and δ obtained by fitting the data distributions <lb/>with Eqn. 5 are given in Table 2 and the fits to data are shown in Fig. 6 (left <lb/>panel). The value of parameters C and η 0 are found to increase with increasing <lb/>√ s. The value of the parameter δ is found to be approximately independent of <lb/>√ s <lb/>within errors. The constancy of δ is another way of demonstrating the concept of <lb/>limiting fragmentation [22]. In such a scenario, multiplicity density in pseudorapidity <lb/>when plotted as a function of pseudorapidity shifted by beam rapidity is expected <lb/>to be independent of pseudorapidity at forward rapidities [12]. Shown in the right <lb/>panel of Fig. 6 are the comparisons of the experimentally measured charged particle <lb/>pseudorapidity distributions to those from the PYTHIA and the PHOJET calculations. <lb/>The CDF measurements [23] are not used to obtain the parameters C, η 0 and δ for <lb/>making predictions at LHC energies as discussed later, because of their very limited η <lb/>coverage. It is observed that for the lowest beam energy studied, <lb/>√ s = 53 GeV, both <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>η <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>η <lb/>d <lb/>ch <lb/>dN <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>Extrapolation <lb/>10 TeV PYTHIA (NSD) <lb/>10 TeV PHOJET (NSD) <lb/>η <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>η <lb/>d <lb/>ch <lb/>dN <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>Extrapolation <lb/>14 TeV PYTHIA (NSD) <lb/>14 TeV PHOJET (NSD) <lb/>Figure 7. Expected pseudorapidity distribution (solid lines) for charged particles in <lb/>p+p collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 10 (left panel) and 14 TeV (right panel). This is obtained <lb/>from the extrapolation using the existing data from p+p collisions at lower energies. <lb/>The dotted lines indicate the uncertainties associated with the extrapolation. Also <lb/>shown for comparison are the expected dN ch /dη from PYTHIA and PHOJET model <lb/>calculations for p+p collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 10 and 14 TeV. <lb/>PYTHIA and PHOJET are in very good agreement with the experimental data. As the <lb/>beam energy increases PYTHIA results seems to be in better agreement with the data. <lb/>While for the top energy ( <lb/>√ s = 1800 GeV [17]) studied the error bars are large to make <lb/>a conclusion on which of the two models have better agreement with the data. <lb/>Using the average value of δ and extrapolating the value of C and η 0 to <lb/>√ s = 10 and <lb/>14 TeV, we are able to predict the full pseudorapidity distribution for charged particles. <lb/>The extrapolation is done by fitting the variation of C with <lb/>√ s with a functional form <lb/>C = 3.7 + 1.15 ln( <lb/>√ <lb/>s) + 0.25 (ln( <lb/>√ <lb/>s)) 2 <lb/>(6) <lb/>and the variation of η 0 with <lb/>√ s as <lb/>η 0 = 3.1 + 0.4 ln( <lb/>√ <lb/>s). <lb/>(7) <lb/>The values of C obtained are 7.63 ± 0.87 and 8.43 ± 1.04 for <lb/>√ s = 10 and 14 TeV <lb/>respectively. Those for η 0 are 4.01 ± 0.14 and 4.15 ± 0.15 for <lb/>√ s = 10 and 14 TeV <lb/>respectively. Assuming the functional form given in Eqn. 5 is valid for <lb/>√ s = 10 and <lb/>14 TeV and using the parameter values obtained as above, we can now predict the <lb/>full pseudorapidity distribution of charged particles at <lb/>√ s = 10 and 14 TeV. These <lb/>distributions are shown in Fig. 7 along with expectations calculated from PYTHIA and <lb/>PHOJET models for the same collisions. The left panel shows the results for <lb/>√ s = 10 <lb/>TeV and right panel shows the results for <lb/>√ s = 14 TeV. <lb/>It is observed that at both <lb/>√ s = 10 and 14 TeV, the predictions from a judicious <lb/>extrapolation of existing data in general are above the model predictions. The PYTHIA <lb/>results are close to the lower error band (dotted lines) for η &lt; 4. The values <lb/>from PYTHIA are higher than those from PHOJET model calculation over a large <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>pseudorapidity range presented. In general all the three distributions have almost similar <lb/>shape. The differences between the models could arise due to several reasons. The event <lb/>generation in PYTHIA is mainly designed to describe the possible hard interactions in <lb/>p+p(p) collisions. It also combines sophisticated models dealing with soft hadronic <lb/>interactions [2]. However in the case of PHOJET, the main approach is to describe <lb/>the soft component of hadron-hadron, photon-hadron interactions at high energies. It <lb/>combines the hard component calculated by perturbative QCD at the partonic level [3]. <lb/>Due to the different underlying theoretical models used PYTHIA has larger model <lb/>parameters which can be adjusted in order to better reproduce the data compared <lb/>to PHOJET. Another difference lies in the parametrisation used get the p+p(p) cross-<lb/>sections. PYTHIA uses those derived from the Pomeron exchange model while the <lb/>PHOJET uses the optical theorem and cross-sections are corrected for high energies <lb/>using the unitarity principle. <lb/>4. Summary <lb/>We have obtained the N ch , N ch distribution and dN ch /dη versus η for <lb/>√ s = 10 and <lb/>14 TeV using extrapolations of existing data. The results have been compared to cal-<lb/>culations from PYTHIA and PHOJET. Measurements at midrapidity at LHC will help <lb/>distinguish whether N ch has a power law or a logarithmic dependence on <lb/>√ s. The <lb/>shape of dN ch /dη versus η obtained from the extrapolation of information from existing <lb/>measurements are very similar to those calculated from models. PYTHIA calculations <lb/>of N ch and dN ch /dη distributions seem to be higher compared to those from PHOJET <lb/>model. The N ch distributions from models suggest the multiplicity distribution at LHC <lb/>energies may not be well described by a single NBD distribution, already such a be-<lb/>haviour has been seen at <lb/>√ s = 1.8 TeV [18]. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>Financial assistance from the Department of Atomic Energy, Government of India is <lb/>gratefully acknowledged. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] B. Alessandro, et al., ALICE Collaboration, J. Phys. G 32 (2006) 1295; F. Carminati, et al., ALICE <lb/>Collaboration, J. Phys. G 30 (2004) 1517; David G. d&apos;Enterria,et al., CMS Collaboration, J. Phys. <lb/>G 34 (2007) 2307; G. L. Bayatian, et al.,CMS Collaboration, J. Phys. G 34 (2007) 995; G. Aad, et <lb/>al., ATLAS Collaboration, arXiv:0901.0512; A. Augusto Alves et al., LHCb Collaboration, JINST <lb/>3 (2008) S08005. <lb/>[2] T. Sjostrand, et al., Computer Physics Commun. 135 (2001) 238; T. Sjostrand and M. van Zijl, Phys. <lb/>Rev. D 36 (1987) 2019; T. Sjostrand and P. Skands, Eur. Phys. J. C 39 (2005) 129; T. Sjostrand <lb/>and P. Skands, JHEP 0605 (2006) 026. <lb/>[3] R. Engel, Z. Phys. C 66 (1995) 203; R. Engel, J. Ranft and S. Roesler, Phys. Rev. D 52 (1995) <lb/>1459. <lb/>[4] S. N. Ganguli and P.K. Malhotra, Phys. Lett. B 42 (1972) 83; P. Carruthers and Minh Duong-Van, <lb/>Phys. Lett. B 114 (1982) 169. <lb/>[5] E. Fermi, Prog. Theor. Phys. 5 (1950) 570; Phys. Rev. 81 (1951) 683; P. Carruthers, Ann. NY. <lb/>Acad. Sci. 229 (1974) 91. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Extrapolation of Multiplicity distribution in p+p(p) collisions to LHC energies <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[6] S. Z. Belenjki and L. D. Landau, Suppl. Nuovo Cim. 3 (1956) 15. <lb/>[7] C. E. DeTar, Phys. Rev. D 3 (1971) 128. <lb/>[8] R. P. Feynman, Phys. Rev. Lett. 23 (1969) 1415. <lb/>[9] A. H. Mueller, Phys. Rev. D 2 (1970) 2945; S. Rai Choudhury and D.P. Majumdar, Nucl. Phys. B <lb/>61 (1973) 502. <lb/>[10] H. Satz, Nuovo Cim. 37 (1965) 1407; E. L. Berger and A. Krzywicki, Phys. Lett. B 36 (1971) 380. <lb/>[11] W. Thome et al., Nucl. Phys. B 129, 365 (1977). <lb/>[12] J. Adams et al., STAR Collaboration, Phys. Rev. Lett. 95 (2005) 062301;Phys. Rev. C 73 (2006) <lb/>03490 6; B. I. Abelev, et al., STAR Collaboration, arXiv:0906.2260; B. B. Back, et al., PHOBOS <lb/>Collaboration, Phys. Rev. Lett. 91 (2003) 052303; B. B. Back, et al., PHOBOS Collaboration, <lb/>Phys. Rev. C 72 (2005) 031901; B. Alver, et al., PHOBOS Collaboration, Phys. Rev. Lett. 102 <lb/>(2009) 142301. <lb/>[13] P. Z. Skands, arXiv:0905.3418. <lb/>[14] A. Capella, et al., Phys. Rep. 236 (1994) 225. <lb/>[15] V. A. Abromovsky and N.V. Radchenko, arXiv:0812.2465; P.Z. Skands, FERMILAB-CONF-07-<lb/>706-T, 2009; M. Bahr et al., arXiv:0905.4671; A. Achilli et al., Phys. Lett. B 659 (2008) 137; M. <lb/>Bahr et al., JHEP 0901 (2009) 065. <lb/>[16] R.E. Ansorge, et al., UA5 Collaboration, Z. Phys. C 43 (1989) 357; R.E. Ansorge, et al., UA5 <lb/>Collaboration, Z. Phys. C 37 (1988) 191; G. J. Alner et al., UA5 Collaboration, Phys. Lett. B 160 <lb/>(1985) 193; Phys. Lett. B 167 (1986) 476; Phys. Lett. B 160 (1985) 199. <lb/>[17] D.E. Acosta, et al., CDF Collaboration, Phys. Rev. D 65 (2002) 072005. <lb/>[18] T. Alexopoulos, et al., E735 Collaboration, Phys. Lett. B 435 (1998) 453. <lb/>[19] Z. Koba, H.B. Nielsen, P. Olesen, Nucl. Phys. B 40 (1972) 317. <lb/>[20] G. J. Alner, et al., UA5 Collaboration, Z. Phys. C 33 (2004) 1. <lb/>[21] J. Dias de Deus and J.G. Milhano, Nucl. Phys. A 795 (2007)98. <lb/>[22] J. Benecke, et al., Phys. Rev. 188 (1969) 2159. <lb/>[23] F. Abe, et al., CDF Collaboration, Phys. Rev. D 41 (1990) 2330. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
