<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Updated reference genome sequence and annotation of Mycobacterium bovis <lb/>AF2122/97 <lb/>Kerri M. Malone <lb/>a <lb/>, Damien Farrell <lb/>a <lb/>, Tod P. Stuber <lb/>b <lb/>, Olga T. Schubert <lb/>c* <lb/>, Ruedi <lb/>Aebersold <lb/>c <lb/>, Suelee Robbe-Austerman <lb/>b <lb/>and Stephen V. Gordon <lb/>a,e,f,g# <lb/>a <lb/>School of Veterinary Medicine, University College Dublin, Ireland; <lb/>b <lb/>Diagnostic Bacteriology Laboratory, National Veterinary Services Laboratories, <lb/>Ames, Iowa, USA; <lb/>c <lb/>Department of Biology, Institute of Molecular Systems Biology, ETH Zurich, CH-8093, <lb/>Switzerland; <lb/>e <lb/>School of Medicine, University College Dublin, Ireland; <lb/>f <lb/>School of Biomolecular and Biomedical Science, University College Dublin, Ireland; <lb/>g <lb/>UCD Conway Institute of Biomolecular and Biomedical Research, University College <lb/>Dublin, Ireland <lb/>*Present address: Department of Human Genetics, University of California, Los <lb/>Angeles, USA <lb/>Running title <lb/>Mycobacterium bovis AF2122/97: an update <lb/># <lb/>Address correspondence to Stephen V. Gordon, stephen.gordon@ucd.ie <lb/>Keywords <lb/>Mycobacterium bovis, AF2122/97, bovine tuberculosis, reference genome, re-<lb/>sequencing, re-annotation. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>We report an update to the reference genome of the bovine tuberculosis bacillus <lb/>Mycobacterium bovis AF2122/97 generated using an integrative multi-&apos;omics <lb/>approach. <lb/>Updates <lb/>include <lb/>42 <lb/>new <lb/>CDS, <lb/>14 <lb/>modified <lb/>annotations, <lb/>26 <lb/>SNP <lb/>corrections, and disclosure that the RD900 locus, previously described as absent <lb/>from the genome, is in fact present. <lb/></front>

			<body>Genome Announcement <lb/>The Mycobacterium tuberculosis complex (MTBC) is a collection of genetically <lb/>related mycobacterial species that cause tuberculosis (TB) in human and animal <lb/>hosts. Mycobacterium bovis, the causative agent of bovine tuberculosis (bTB), is the <lb/>most widely studied animal-adapted MTBC member; bTB exacts a tremendous global <lb/>economic toll through productivity losses and disease control costs, while zoonotic <lb/>transmission of M. bovis infection is a threat to human health (Abernethy et al., <lb/>2013; De Garine-Wichatitsky et al., 2013; Kazoora et al., 2016; Khattak et al., 2016; <lb/>Malama et al., 2014; Muller et al., 2013). <lb/>M. bovis AF2122/97 was the first bovine MTBC strain to be fully sequenced <lb/>and provided a reference genome (Garnier et al., 2003). Initial comparisons of the M. <lb/>bovis AF2122/97 genome with that of the human-adapted M. tuberculosis H37Rv <lb/>reference genome revealed high nucleotide sequence identity (&gt; 99%), no unique <lb/>genes per se in M. bovis AF2122/97 and a number of genomic deletions that led to a <lb/>reduced genome size (Garnier et al., 2003). M. bovis AF2122/97 continues to serve <lb/>as an MTBC reference genome despite last being updated in 2003; by comparison, <lb/>the genome annotation of the reference M. tuberculosis H37Rv strain is currently on <lb/>release 27 (Lew et al., 2013). An updated reference M. bovis genome will provide an <lb/>essential resource for the TB research community and as a basis for comparative <lb/>studies into animal-and human-adapted MTBC members. <lb/>To update the M. bovis AF2122/97 genome and annotation, a low-passage <lb/>stock taken from the original M. bovis AF2122/97 seed stock was re-sequenced and <lb/>re-annotated using a combination of DNA-, RNA-sequencing and proteomics data. All <lb/>nucleic acid and protein samples were derived from exponentially grown cultures. <lb/>Short read DNA sequencing libraries were prepared using the Nextera XT <lb/>DNA Library Preparation Kit (Illumina®) and sequenced on the MiSeq® system <lb/>(Illumina®), generating 250bp paired-end reads that were trimmed using Sickle (Q <lb/>&gt;30), with 60X reference coverage (Joshi NA, 2011). <lb/>For PacBio RS II sequencing, <lb/>enzymatically extracted DNA was prepared using large insert library (6kb-8kb) size <lb/>selection (van Soolingen et al., 1991). Two SMRT cells were used for an output of <lb/>542,585,804 bases, a mean read length of 8,141, and 86X reference coverage. DNA <lb/>sequencing datasets were analysed using a combination of de novo assembly (short <lb/>reads, SOAPdenovo (Xie et al., 2014); long reads, Canu (Koren S, 2016)) and <lb/>nucleotide variant identification methods (short reads, Stampy, SAMtools and <lb/>VCFtools (Li, 2011; Li et al., 2009; Lunter and Goodson, 2011); long reads, Pilon <lb/>(Walker et al., 2014); MUMmer (Kurtz et al., 2004)). This allowed for the update of <lb/>the genome nucleotide sequence and the identification of genomic regions that <lb/>were misassembled, or missed entirely, in the original sequencing project. Re-<lb/>annotation <lb/>of <lb/>the M. bovis AF2122/97 genome was achieved by automatic <lb/>annotation transfer from M. tuberculosis H37Rv (Version 27) (Otto et al., 2011) and a <lb/>proteogenomic analysis using both M. bovis AF2122/97 shotgun MS/MS, SWATH MS <lb/>datasets and M. tuberculosis H37Rv SWATH MS datasets (Schubert et al., 2013). <lb/>Overall, 26 single nucleotide polymorphisms were identified. Strikingly, the <lb/>large sequence polymorphism RD900, originally described as deleted from M. bovis <lb/>2122/97 (Bentley et al., 2012), was found to be present; recombination between <lb/>repeat structures flanking the RD900 locus in clones used for the original shotgun <lb/>sequencing genome project may have led to loss of RD900. Furthermore, 42 novel <lb/>coding sequences were identified while 14 existing annotations were modified. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Nucleotide sequence accession number(s): This Whole Genome Shotgun project <lb/>had been deposited in DDBj/ENA/Genbank under the accession no. PRJEB15187. The <lb/>genome version described in this paper is BX248333.2. SWATH MS data can be found <lb/>on PeptideAtlas under identifier: PASS00932. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements: <lb/>The work was supported by funding from the Department for Agriculture, Food and <lb/>the <lb/>Marine <lb/>(MycobactDiagnosis <lb/>11/RD/EMIDA/1), <lb/>Science <lb/>Foundation <lb/>Ireland <lb/>(08/IN.1/B2038), SystemsX.ch (through the project TbX) and a research grant from <lb/>Institut Mérieux. We would like to thank Dr. Gerard Cagney (UCD School of <lb/>Biomolecular <lb/>and <lb/>Biomedical <lb/>Science) <lb/>and <lb/>Dr. <lb/>Kieran <lb/>Wynne <lb/>(UCD <lb/>Conway <lb/>Proteomics Core) for shotgun mass spectrometric analysis of M. bovis samples. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>ABERNETHY, D. A., UPTON, P., HIGGINS, I. M., MCGRATH, G., GOODCHILD, A. V., <lb/>ROLFE, S. J., BROUGHAN, J. M., DOWNS, S. H., CLIFTON-HADLEY, R., MENZIES, <lb/>F. D., DE LA RUA-DOMENECH, R., BLISSITT, M. J., DUIGNAN, A. &amp; MORE, S. J. <lb/>2013. Bovine tuberculosis trends in the UK and the Republic of Ireland, 1995-<lb/>2010. Vet Rec, 172, 312. <lb/>BENTLEY, S. D., COMAS, I., BRYANT, J. M., WALKER, D., SMITH, N. H., HARRIS, S. R., <lb/>THURSTON, S., GAGNEUX, S., WOOD, J., ANTONIO, M., QUAIL, M. A., GEHRE, <lb/>F., ADEGBOLA, R. A., PARKHILL, J. &amp; DE JONG, B. C. 2012. The genome of <lb/>Mycobacterium africanum West African 2 reveals a lineage-specific locus and <lb/>genome erosion common to the M. tuberculosis complex. PLoS Negl Trop Dis, <lb/>6, e1552. <lb/>DE GARINE-WICHATITSKY, M., CARON, A., KOCK, R., TSCHOPP, R., MUNYEME, M., <lb/>HOFMEYR, M. &amp; MICHEL, A. 2013. A review of bovine tuberculosis at the <lb/>wildlife-livestock-human interface in sub-Saharan Africa. Epidemiol Infect, <lb/>141, 1342-56. <lb/>GARNIER, T., EIGLMEIER, K., CAMUS, J. C., MEDINA, N., MANSOOR, H., PRYOR, M., <lb/>DUTHOY, S., GRONDIN, S., LACROIX, C., MONSEMPE, C., SIMON, S., HARRIS, <lb/>B., ATKIN, R., DOGGETT, J., MAYES, R., KEATING, L., WHEELER, P. R., <lb/>PARKHILL, J., BARRELL, B. G., COLE, S. T., GORDON, S. V. &amp; HEWINSON, R. G. <lb/>2003. The complete genome sequence of Mycobacterium bovis. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A, 100, 7877-82. <lb/>JOSHI NA, F. J. 2011. Sickle: A sliding-window, adaptive, quality-based trimming tool <lb/>for FastQ files [Online]. Available: https://github.com/najoshi/sickle <lb/>[Accessed]. <lb/>KAZOORA, H. B., MAJALIJA, S., KIWANUKA, N. &amp; KANEENE, J. B. 2016. Knowledge, <lb/>Attitudes <lb/>and <lb/>Practices <lb/>Regarding <lb/>Risk <lb/>to <lb/>Human <lb/>Infection <lb/>due <lb/>to <lb/>Mycobacterium <lb/>bovis <lb/>among <lb/>Cattle <lb/>Farming <lb/>Communities <lb/>in <lb/>Western <lb/>Uganda. Zoonoses Public Health. <lb/>KHATTAK, I., MUSHTAQ, M. H., AHMAD, M. U., KHAN, M. S. &amp; HAIDER, J. 2016. <lb/>Zoonotic tuberculosis in occupationally exposed groups in Pakistan. Occup <lb/>Med (Lond). <lb/>KOREN S, W. B., BERLIN K, MILLER JR, PHILLIPPY AM 2016. Canu: scalable and <lb/>accurate long-read assembly via adaptive k-mer weighting and repeat <lb/>separation. bioRxiv. <lb/>KURTZ, S., PHILLIPPY, A., DELCHER, A. L., SMOOT, M., SHUMWAY, M., ANTONESCU, <lb/>C. &amp; SALZBERG, S. L. 2004. Versatile and open software for comparing large <lb/>genomes. Genome Biology, 5. <lb/>LEW, J. M., MAO, C., SHUKLA, M., WARREN, A., WILL, R., KUZNETSOV, D., XENARIOS, <lb/>I., ROBERTSON, B. D., GORDON, S. V., SCHNAPPINGER, D., COLE, S. T. &amp; <lb/>SOBRAL, B. 2013. Database resources for the tuberculosis community. <lb/>Tuberculosis (Edinb), 93, 12-7. <lb/>LI, H. 2011. A statistical framework for SNP calling, mutation discovery, association <lb/>mapping and population genetical parameter estimation from sequencing <lb/>data. Bioinformatics, 27, 2987-93. <lb/>LI, H., HANDSAKER, B., WYSOKER, A., FENNELL, T., RUAN, J., HOMER, N., MARTH, G., <lb/>ABECASIS, G., DURBIN, R. &amp; GENOME PROJECT DATA PROCESSING, S. 2009. <lb/>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools. Bioinformatics, 25, <lb/>2078-9. <lb/>LUNTER, G. &amp; GOODSON, M. 2011. Stampy: a statistical algorithm for sensitive and <lb/>fast mapping of Illumina sequence reads. Genome Res, 21, 936-9. <lb/>MALAMA, S., MUMA, J., MUNYEME, M., MBULO, G., MUWONGE, A., SHAMPUTA, I. <lb/>C., DJONNE, B., GODFROID, J. &amp; JOHANSEN, T. B. 2014. Isolation and <lb/>molecular characterization of Mycobacterium tuberculosis from humans and <lb/>cattle in Namwala District, Zambia. Ecohealth, 11, 564-70. <lb/>MULLER, B., DURR, S., ALONSO, S., HATTENDORF, J., LAISSE, C. J., PARSONS, S. D., <lb/>VAN HELDEN, P. D. &amp; ZINSSTAG, J. 2013. Zoonotic Mycobacterium bovis-<lb/>induced tuberculosis in humans. Emerg Infect Dis, 19, 899-908. <lb/>OTTO, T. D., DILLON, G. P., DEGRAVE, W. S. &amp; BERRIMAN, M. 2011. RATT: Rapid <lb/>Annotation Transfer Tool. Nucleic Acids Res, 39, e57. <lb/>SCHUBERT, O. T., MOURITSEN, J., LUDWIG, C., ROST, H. L., ROSENBERGER, G., <lb/>ARTHUR, P. K., CLAASSEN, M., CAMPBELL, D. S., SUN, Z., FARRAH, T., <lb/>GENGENBACHER, M., MAIOLICA, A., KAUFMANN, S. H., MORITZ, R. L. &amp; <lb/>AEBERSOLD, R. 2013. The Mtb proteome library: a resource of assays to <lb/>quantify the complete proteome of Mycobacterium tuberculosis. Cell Host <lb/>Microbe, 13, 602-12. <lb/>VAN SOOLINGEN, D., HERMANS, P. W., DE HAAS, P. E., SOLL, D. R. &amp; VAN EMBDEN, J. <lb/>D. 1991. Occurrence and stability of insertion sequences in Mycobacterium <lb/>tuberculosis complex strains: evaluation of an insertion sequence-dependent <lb/>DNA polymorphism as a tool in the epidemiology of tuberculosis. J Clin <lb/>Microbiol, 29, 2578-86. <lb/>WALKER, B. J., ABEEL, T., SHEA, T., PRIEST, M., ABOUELLIEL, A., SAKTHIKUMAR, S., <lb/>CUOMO, C. A., ZENG, Q. D., WORTMAN, J., YOUNG, S. K. &amp; EARL, A. M. 2014. <lb/>Pilon: An Integrated Tool for Comprehensive Microbial Variant Detection and <lb/>Genome Assembly Improvement. Plos One, 9. <lb/>XIE, Y., WU, G., TANG, J., LUO, R., PATTERSON, J., LIU, S., HUANG, W., HE, G., GU, S., <lb/>LI, S., ZHOU, X., LAM, T. W., LI, Y., XU, X., WONG, G. K. &amp; WANG, J. 2014. <lb/>SOAPdenovo-Trans: de novo transcriptome assembly with short RNA-Seq <lb/>reads. Bioinformatics, 30, 1660-6. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
