<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>Effects of a space modulation on the behavior of a 1D alternating Heisenberg spin-1/2 model <lb/>This article has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the full text article. <lb/>2011 J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 246002 <lb/>(http://iopscience.iop.org/0953-8984/23/24/246002) <lb/>Download details: <lb/>IP Address: 145.64.134.241 <lb/>The article was downloaded on 27/05/2011 at 09:40 <lb/>Please note that terms and conditions apply. <lb/>View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for more <lb/>Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>IOP PUBLISHING <lb/>JOURNAL OF PHYSICS: CONDENSED MATTER <lb/>J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 (2011) 246002 (9pp) <lb/>doi:10.1088/0953-8984/23/24/246002 <lb/>Effects of a space modulation on the <lb/>behavior of a 1D alternating Heisenberg <lb/>spin-1/2 model <lb/>Saeed Mahdavifar 1,4 and Jahanfar Abouie 2,3,4 <lb/>1 Department of Physics, University of Guilan, 41335-1914, Rasht, Iran <lb/>2 Department of Physics, Shahrood University of Technology, Shahrood 36199-95161, Iran <lb/>3 School of Physics, Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences (IPM), <lb/>Tehran 19395-5531, Iran <lb/>E-mail: Mahdavifar@guilan.ac.ir and Jahan@shahroodut.ac.ir <lb/>Received 12 March 2011, in final form 27 April 2011 <lb/>Published 26 May 2011 <lb/>Online at stacks.iop.org/JPhysCM/23/246002 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The effects of a magnetic field (h) and a space modulation (δ) on the magnetic properties of a <lb/>one-dimensional antiferromagnetic-ferromagnetic Heisenberg spin-1/2 model have been <lb/>studied by means of numerical exact diagonalization of finite size systems, the nonlinear σ <lb/>model, and a bosonization approach. The space modulation is considered on the <lb/>antiferromagnetic couplings. At δ = 0, the model is mapped to a gapless Lüttinger liquid phase <lb/>by increasing the magnetic field. However, the space modulation induces a new gap in the <lb/>spectrum of the system and the system experiences different quantum phases which are <lb/>separated by four critical fields. By opening the new gap, a magnetization plateau appears at <lb/>1 <lb/>2 M sat . The effects of the space modulation are reflected in the emergence of a plateau in other <lb/>physical functions such as the F-dimer and the bond-dimer order parameters, and the pair-wise <lb/>entanglement. <lb/>(Some figures in this article are in colour only in the electronic version) <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>The effects of a magnetic field on the magnetic properties of <lb/>low-dimensional quantum magnets at zero temperature have <lb/>attracted much attention in recent years. One of the very <lb/>interesting phenomena is the appearance of a magnetization <lb/>plateau in the magnetization curve. This behavior can be <lb/>viewed as an essentially macroscopic quantum phenomena, <lb/>and has gained much attention recently. When a plateau <lb/>appears the energy gap is opened, which can in some senses be <lb/>regarded as a kind of generation of the Haldane conjecture [1]. <lb/>In a seminal work, Oshikawa, Yamanaka, and Affleck studied <lb/>the magnetization of a general class of Heisenberg spin chains <lb/>in the presence of a magnetic field. They showed that the <lb/>plateaus can appear when the magnetization per site m is <lb/>topologically quantized by n(s − m) = integer, where s <lb/>is the magnitude of the spin, and n is the period of the <lb/>4 The authors have contributed equally to this work. <lb/>ground state determined by the explicit spatial structure of the <lb/>Hamiltonian [2]. <lb/>The bond alternating Heisenberg spin-1/2 chains which <lb/>are obtained by a space modulation in the exchange <lb/>couplings [3-9] are a particular class of the low-dimensional <lb/>quantum magnets to observe the magnetization plateau at <lb/>zero temperature. The bond alternating antiferromagnetic-<lb/>ferromagnetic spin-1/2 chains have a gap in the spin excitation <lb/>spectrum and reveal extremely rich quantum behaviors in <lb/>the presence of an external magnetic field [10-13]. By <lb/>tuning the magnetic field, the excitation gap is reduced and <lb/>reaches zero at the first critical field. Simultaneously, the <lb/>magnetization starts to increase up to its saturation value, <lb/>0.5, at the second critical field. More enhancement of the <lb/>field reopens the gap and the saturation plateau appears in the <lb/>magnetization curve. These models have only two plateaus at <lb/>zero and saturation values of the magnetization. It has been <lb/>found that a space modulation in the exchange couplings can <lb/>affect the behavior of the field induced magnetization. For <lb/></body>

			<front>0953-8984/11/246002+09$33.00 <lb/>© 2011 IOP Publishing Ltd Printed in the UK &amp; the USA <lb/></front>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 (2011) 246002 <lb/>S Mahdavifar and J Abouie <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1. Schematic representation of a tetrameric spin chain. <lb/>example the bond alternating ferromagnetic-ferromagnetic-<lb/>antiferromagnetic (F-F-AF) trimerized Heisenberg spin-1/2 <lb/>chains have exotic behaviors by changing the magnetic <lb/>field [14]. This model can be realized in Cu compounds <lb/>such as 3CuCl 2 •2 dx. The magnetization has a plateau at <lb/>M <lb/>M sat = 1 <lb/>3 , where M and M sat are the magnetization and <lb/>its saturated values, respectively [15, 16]. The mid-plateaus <lb/>have also appeared in the bond alternating ferromagnetic-<lb/>antiferromagnetic-antiferromagnetic (F-AF-AF) trimerized <lb/>Heisenberg spin-1/2 chains [17]. It has also been shown <lb/>that the static structure factor does not vary with the external <lb/>magnetic field at the plateau state [18]. <lb/>The other examples are the tetrameric bond alternating <lb/>ferromagnetic-ferromagnetic-antiferromagnetic-antiferroma-<lb/>gnetic (F-F-AF-AF) Heisenberg spin models. A realiza-<lb/>tion for the spin-1/2 chain with F-F-AF-AF alternations <lb/>is the compound Cu(3 − Clpy) 2 (N 3 ) 2 (3 − Clpy = 3 − <lb/>chloropyridine) [19]. In such a spin-1 <lb/>2 system, there is a gap <lb/>from the singlet ground state to the triplet excited states in the <lb/>absence of a magnetic field. At M <lb/>M sat = 1 <lb/>2 , a plateau appears <lb/>in the magnetization curve by applying a magnetic field [20]. <lb/>The temperature dependence of the magnetization, magnetic <lb/>susceptibility and specific heat have also been studied in the <lb/>mid-plateau state of this model by means of the transfer-matrix <lb/>renormalization group method [21]. <lb/>In this paper, by considering a different bond alternating <lb/>Heisenberg spin-1/2 chain, we study the other physical <lb/>properties of the mid-plateau state such as the string order <lb/>and pair-wise entanglement, F-dimer and bond-dimer order <lb/>parameters. The Hamiltonian of the model is <lb/>H = −J F <lb/>N/2 <lb/>j =1 <lb/>S 2 j • S 2 j +1 <lb/>+ J AF <lb/>N/2 <lb/>j =1 <lb/>[1 + (−1) j δ]S 2 j −1 • S 2 j − h <lb/>N <lb/>j =1 <lb/>S z <lb/>j , <lb/>(1) <lb/>where S j is the spin-1 <lb/>2 operator on the j th site. J F and <lb/>J ± <lb/>AF = J AF (1 ± δ) denote the F (J F &gt; 0) and AF (J AF &gt; 0) <lb/>couplings, respectively. δ is the space modulation parameter <lb/>and h is proportional to the external magnetic field. The <lb/>unit cell of the model has been shown in figure 1. The <lb/>bond alternating spin-1/2 AF-F chains are good candidates <lb/>for studying the Lüttinger liquid phase. A suitable realization <lb/>of the bond alternating AF-F spin chain is the Cu based <lb/>(CH 3 ) 2 NH 2 CuCl 3 compound. Linked-cluster calculations and <lb/>bulk measurements show that DMACuCl 3 is also a realization <lb/>of the spin-1/2 alternating AF-F chain with nearly the same <lb/>strength of AF and F couplings [22]. A space modulation <lb/>changes the AF couplings alternately and influences the <lb/>quantum properties of the system. <lb/>Using the exact diagonalization of a finite size system and <lb/>employing the conformal field theory, it has already been found <lb/>that for δ = 0 a magnetization plateau exists at half of the <lb/>saturation value [23]. Moreover, the width of the mid-plateau <lb/>is dependent on the values of δ, and the critical exponent for <lb/>the plateau width is obtained by the level spectroscopy method. <lb/>In the present work the different properties of the model such <lb/>as F-dimer and bond-dimer order parameters, the string order <lb/>parameter, and the pair-wise entanglement of the plateau state <lb/>are studied. <lb/>The outline of the paper is as follows. In section 2 we <lb/>discuss the model in the strong AF coupling limit and derive an <lb/>effective spin chain Hamiltonian. In section 3 we summarize <lb/>the results of the analytical field theory studies. In section 4, <lb/>the results of the exact diagonalization Lanczos method are <lb/>presented. Finally, we discuss and summarize our results in <lb/>section 5. <lb/>2. Effective Hamiltonian <lb/>The easiest way to obtain the effective model, which manifestly <lb/>displays a mechanism for the generation of the sequence of <lb/>new scales, is to start from the limit of a noninteracting block <lb/>of pairs J F = 0 and strong magnetic field h <lb/>J AF [24]. <lb/>In the limiting case of strong AF coupling J AF <lb/>J F and <lb/>J AF <lb/>δ J AF the model can be mapped to an effective spin <lb/>chain Hamiltonian [12]. At J AF <lb/>J F , the system behaves <lb/>as a nearly independent block of pairs. Indeed, an individual <lb/>block of spin pairs may be in a singlet or a triplet state with the <lb/>corresponding eigenvalues given by <lb/>E ± (S) = − 3 <lb/>4 J ± <lb/>AF , <lb/>E ± (T 1 ) = 1 <lb/>4 J ± <lb/>AF − h, <lb/>E ± (T 0 ) = 1 <lb/>4 J ± <lb/>AF , <lb/>E ± (T −1 ) = 1 <lb/>4 J ± <lb/>AF + h. <lb/>(2) <lb/>When h is small, the ground state consists of a product of pair <lb/>singlets. As the magnetic field h increases the energy of the <lb/>triplet state |T 1 decreases and at h = J ± <lb/>AF forms together <lb/>with the singlet state, a doublet of almost degenerate low <lb/>energy states, split from the remaining high energy two triplet <lb/>states. Thus, for a strong enough magnetic field we have a <lb/>situation when the singlet |S and triplet |T 1 states create a <lb/>new effective spin τ = 1/2 system. On the new singlet-triplet <lb/>subspace and up to a constant, we easily obtain the effective <lb/>Hamiltonian <lb/>H eff = − <lb/>J F <lb/>2 <lb/>N/2 <lb/>j =1 <lb/>[τ x <lb/>j τ x <lb/>j +1 + τ <lb/>y <lb/>j τ <lb/>y <lb/>j +1 + 1 <lb/>2 τ z <lb/>j τ z <lb/>j +1 ] <lb/>− h eff <lb/>0 <lb/>N/2 <lb/>j =1 <lb/>τ z <lb/>j − h eff <lb/>1 <lb/>N/2 <lb/>j =1 <lb/>(−1) j τ z <lb/>j , <lb/>(3) <lb/>where h eff <lb/>0 <lb/>= h − J AF + J F <lb/>4 and h eff <lb/>1 <lb/>= δ J AF . Thus, the <lb/>effective Hamiltonian is nothing but the X X Z Heisenberg <lb/>chain, with anisotropy <lb/>= 1/2 in a uniform and staggered <lb/>longitudinal magnetic field. The full phase diagram of this <lb/>model has been investigated by Alcaraz and Malvezzi [25] <lb/>and the nature of the ground state phase transition has been <lb/>pointed out in [26]. The other properties can be found in recent <lb/>works such as [2, 27-29]. To find a clearer picture for the low <lb/>energy spectrum of the effective model (3), using the numerical <lb/>Lanczos method, we have computed the energy gap of the <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 (2011) 246002 <lb/>S Mahdavifar and J Abouie <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2. Difference between the two lowest energy levels of the <lb/>effective Hamiltonian versus the magnetic field h eff <lb/>0 , for chains with <lb/>different lengths N = 16, 20 and exchange parameters J F = 1.0, <lb/>J AF = 9/2, and δ = 1/9. <lb/>effective model. The numerical results are shown in figure 2 <lb/>for a chain of lengths N = 16, 20 and the exchange parameters <lb/>J F = 1.0, J AF = 9/2, and δ = 1/9. As seen from figure 2, <lb/>at h eff <lb/>0 = 0 or h = J AF − J F <lb/>4 , the effective model reduces <lb/>to the X X Z spin chain in a staggered longitudinal magnetic <lb/>field. The ground state of this model is in the gapped Néel <lb/>phase. By changing h eff <lb/>0 from zero i.e. decreasing (increasing) <lb/>h from the value h = J AF − J F <lb/>4 , the energy gap decreases and <lb/>reaches zero at finite values of the magnetic field h eff,− <lb/>0 <lb/>(h eff,+ <lb/>0 <lb/>). <lb/>Consequently, there is a plateau in the magnetization curve <lb/>of the effective model at 0 &lt; h eff <lb/>0 &lt; h eff,+ <lb/>0 <lb/>. By decreasing <lb/>(increasing) h further, the energy gap remains zero down (up) <lb/>to critical field h eff,1 <lb/>0 <lb/>(h eff,2 <lb/>0 <lb/>) and, after these gapless regions, <lb/>it is reopened and behaves linearly with the magnetic field <lb/>h eff <lb/>0 . Correspondingly, in these regions the magnetization of <lb/>the effective model starts to change from zero and is saturated <lb/>at the critical field (h eff,2 <lb/>0 <lb/>). <lb/>3. Field theory predictions <lb/>In this section we will study the model (1) in the language of <lb/>two continuum field theories. We have employed the nonlinear <lb/>σ model and bosonization approaches to obtain the energy gap, <lb/>the critical fields, and magnetization plateaus of the model. <lb/>3.1. Nonlinear σ model <lb/>The O(3) nonlinear σ model (NLσ M) is a semiclassical <lb/>approach which is based on certain properties of a field theory <lb/>in (1 + 1) dimensions. In 1983 Haldane predicted theoretically <lb/>the existence of a finite gap between the ground state and <lb/>the first excited state of antiferromagnetic Heisenberg integer <lb/>spin chains [1]. He also conjectured that the half-odd integer <lb/>spin chains are gapless. The Hamiltonian of a homogeneous <lb/>spin chain is mapped to a O(3) NLσ M with an additional <lb/>topological term. The topological term is 0 if spins of the chain <lb/>are integer and π if they are half-odd integer. <lb/>In the following we will investigate the low temperature <lb/>behaviors of the alternating spin chain (1). For convenience <lb/>in the calculations, let us write the Hamiltonian (1) in the <lb/>following form: <lb/>H = −J F <lb/>N/4 <lb/>j =1 <lb/>(S (1) <lb/>2 j −1 • S (2) <lb/>2 j −1 + S (1) <lb/>2 j • S (2) <lb/>2 j ) <lb/>+ J AF <lb/>N/4 <lb/>j <lb/>[(1 + δ)S (2) <lb/>2 j −1 • S (1) <lb/>2 j + (1 − δ)S (2) <lb/>2 j • S (1) <lb/>2 j +1 ] <lb/>+ h <lb/>j <lb/>S z <lb/>j , <lb/>(4) <lb/>where 0 <lb/>δ <lb/>1. Using the spin coherent states <lb/>representation for the spin operators, i.e. S = sΩ, we can <lb/>write the Hamiltonian in terms of the classical spin vectors. <lb/>By introducing three classical fields n, L, and Δ the classical <lb/>vectors are written in the following forms: <lb/>Ω <lb/>(i) <lb/>2 j −1 = −n 2 j −1 1 − <lb/>a <lb/>s <lb/>L 2 j −1 <lb/>2 1/2 <lb/>+ <lb/>a <lb/>s <lb/>L 2 j −1 <lb/>− (−1) i a <lb/>s <lb/>Δ 2 j −1 , <lb/>Ω <lb/>(i) <lb/>2 j = n 2 j 1 − <lb/>a <lb/>s <lb/>L 2 j <lb/>2 1/2 <lb/>+ <lb/>a <lb/>s <lb/>L 2 j + (−1) i a <lb/>s <lb/>Δ 2 j , <lb/>(5) <lb/>where i = 1, 2 and a is the lattice constant. Typically, for a <lb/>quantum antiferromagnetic Heisenberg chain it is convenient <lb/>to write the spin vectors in terms of a unimodular Néel field <lb/>(n) and one ferromagnetic canting field (L). However, for an <lb/>alternating AF-F Heisenberg spin chain, the main difficulty <lb/>arises from the fact that it is inhomogeneous and writing a <lb/>continuous action out of the discrete Hamiltonian is not a trivial <lb/>task [30]. Using another field which describes the variation of <lb/>the Néel fields inside the two spin-blocks such as Δ we can <lb/>map the Hamiltonian (4) to the following O(3) NLσ M: <lb/>A = <lb/>1 <lb/>2g <lb/>L <lb/>0 <lb/>L T <lb/>0 <lb/>dx dx 0 [(∂ x n) 2 + (∂ x 0 n) 2 ] − i W, (6) <lb/>where W is the winding number, L T = cβ, x 0 = cτ , and we <lb/>have considered the case h = 0. By defining α = J F <lb/>J AF , the <lb/>coupling constant g and the velocity of spin excitations c are <lb/>given in terms of α and δ as <lb/>g = <lb/>1 − δ 2 <lb/>2(1+α) <lb/>s 1 − δ 2 <lb/>4 − 1 <lb/>2(1+α) <lb/>1/2 , <lb/>c = J AF as 1 − <lb/>δ 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>− <lb/>1 <lb/>2(1 + α) <lb/>1/2 <lb/>. <lb/>(7) <lb/>The topological term is obtained as follows: <lb/>= 2π <lb/>sδα <lb/>1 + α − δ 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/>(8) <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 (2011) 246002 <lb/>S Mahdavifar and J Abouie <lb/></note>

			<body>where for α = 0 or δ = 0 the topological term is zero and <lb/>the model is always gapped and the spin excitation velocity <lb/>is <lb/>√ <lb/>2 <lb/>2 J AF as. Moreover, the α = 1 and δ = 0 is the special <lb/>case of AF-F Heisenberg spin chains in which the topological <lb/>term is always 0. This result is in good agreement with the <lb/>result presented in [30]. For any other values of α and δ, the <lb/>Hamiltonian is mapped to a non-integrable O(3) NLσ M with <lb/>in the interval [0, π]. This model is also gapped and the gap <lb/>value is dependent on α and δ. <lb/>Now, let us study the model in the presence of the <lb/>magnetic field. Since, the model is always gapped in the <lb/>absence of a magnetic field we are allowed to consider = 0. <lb/>The Hamiltonian (4) is mapped to the following NLσ M in <lb/>which the effect of the magnetic field is clearly seen: <lb/>A = <lb/>1 <lb/>2g <lb/>d 2 x (∂ x n) 2 + ∂ x 0 n − <lb/>i <lb/>c <lb/>h × n <lb/>2 <lb/>. (9) <lb/>To obtain more physical insight from the effects of <lb/>the magnetic field, it may be more physically trans-<lb/>parent to work with two fields (θ , φ) where n = <lb/>(sin θ sin φ, sin θ cos φ, cos θ). Here θ is co-latitude and φ is <lb/>azimuthal angle. Selecting magnetic field in the z direction, the <lb/>action (9) takes the following form: <lb/>A = <lb/>1 <lb/>2g <lb/>d 2 x (∂ μ θ) 2 + sin 2 θ (φ ) 2 + <lb/>1 <lb/>c 2 (φ • − ih) 2 , <lb/>(10) <lb/>where θ is the angle of h and n. In the term, h × n, the <lb/>magnetic field induces a hard-axis anisotropy. In other words, <lb/>the magnetic field tries to align all spins with n in the plane <lb/>normal to h. Thus for the high field regime, h &gt; |φ • |, the <lb/>deviation of Néel field n from the plane is small. Thus an <lb/>expansion to quadratic order in ϑ is valid. The action is <lb/>A = <lb/>1 <lb/>2g <lb/>L <lb/>0 <lb/>L T <lb/>0 <lb/>d 2 μ (−h 2 − φ∂ 2 <lb/>μ φ − 2ih∂ x 0 φ <lb/>+ (∂ μ ϑ) 2 − ϑ 2 [(∂ x 0 φ) 2 −h 2 − 2ih∂ x 0 φ]), <lb/>(11) <lb/>whereh = h/c and the fluctuations have been separated to the <lb/>in-plane and out-of-plane fluctuations. <lb/>Using a spin stiffness analysis, 1/N expansion and a <lb/>renormalization group approach, the magnetization and spin <lb/>correlation functions of a spin ladder in an applied magnetic <lb/>field [31, 32] have already been computed. The magnetization <lb/>( i <lb/>S i <lb/>N ) is given by M = 1 <lb/>N <lb/>∂ F <lb/>∂h , where F = − 1 <lb/>β ln Z <lb/>is the Helmholtz free energy and Z = DϑDφe −A . The <lb/>separable nature of fluctuations allows us to give the results of <lb/>M = M o + M i which is a summation of both out-of-plane and <lb/>in-plane contributions. At low enough temperatures and small <lb/>value of c/ h one can find that the out-of-plane contribution is <lb/>a constant, M o = 1/2, which corresponds to a uniform state. <lb/>The in-plane contribution has two terms, one is linear in the <lb/>field and the other has a sawtooth form (see [32]). In total, M i <lb/>has a step-like form in which the width of the steps scales as <lb/>1/N. Thus the sawtooth form is the finite size correction and in <lb/>the thermodynamic limit N → ∞ the in-plane magnetization <lb/>is only linear. <lb/>For our tetramerized spin chain the magnetization is given <lb/>by <lb/>M −1 + <lb/>h <lb/>gc <lb/>. <lb/>(12) <lb/>Application of a high enough magnetic field will cause spin <lb/>alignment, or saturation with a maximum magnetization, M s = <lb/>s. This effect should be considered in the NLσ M approach by <lb/>a Lagrange multiplier. At zero magnetic field the system is <lb/>gapped and the magnetization is zero. Tuning the magnetic <lb/>field decreases the gap until the first critical field, h c 1 , where <lb/>magnetization starts to increase. At the second critical field, <lb/>where the magnetization is saturated, the gap reopens and spins <lb/>are fully aligned in the magnetic field direction. <lb/>The critical fields which are attained by means of NLσ M <lb/>are as follows: <lb/>h c 1 = gc, <lb/>h c 2 = 3 <lb/>2 gc. <lb/>(13) <lb/>3.2. Bosonization <lb/>In this section we concentrate our attention on the low <lb/>energy and long wavelength excitations by using bosonization <lb/>language. Let us consider the Hamiltonian (3). In our analysis <lb/>of the model (3) we closely follow the route developed in <lb/>the [27]. In the absence of both magnetic fields, h eff <lb/>0 = 0 and <lb/>h eff <lb/>1 = 0, we have the X X Z spin-1/2 chain with F coupling <lb/>and anisotropy parameter = 1/2. This model is critical and <lb/>the long wavelength excitations are described by the following <lb/>Gaussian theory: <lb/>H = <lb/>v <lb/>2 <lb/>dx [(∂ x θ) 2 + (∂ x φ) 2 ], <lb/>(14) <lb/>where θ(x) and φ(x) are dual bosonic fields, ∂ t φ = v∂ x θ , and <lb/>satisfy the following commutation relations: <lb/>[φ(x), θ (y)] = i (y − x), <lb/>(15) <lb/>[φ(x), θ (x)] = <lb/>i <lb/>2 <lb/>. <lb/>(16) <lb/>v is the spin excitation&apos;s velocity and is fixed by the Bethe <lb/>ansatz solution as <lb/>v = <lb/>J F <lb/>2 <lb/>K <lb/>2K − 1 <lb/>sin <lb/>π <lb/>2K <lb/>, <lb/>(17) <lb/>where the Lüttinger parameter K (the inverse of a boson&apos;s <lb/>radius [33]) is given as a function of as <lb/>K = <lb/>π <lb/>2 arccos <lb/>. <lb/>(18) <lb/>Thus K increases monotonically along the X X Z critical line <lb/>−1 &lt; <lb/>1 from its minimal value K = 1/2 (for the <lb/>isotropic AF <lb/>= −1 case) to unity at <lb/>= 0 (for the <lb/>noninteracting case) and goes to infinity at <lb/>= 1 which <lb/>is the F instability point. Meanwhile the boson radius has <lb/>its maximum value (2π) −1/2 for the isotropic AF chains and <lb/>decreases by changing in and goes to zero at the F instability <lb/>point. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 (2011) 246002 <lb/>S Mahdavifar and J Abouie <lb/></note>

			<body>The maximum value of the spin excitation velocity occurs <lb/>where K ∼ 1/2 or <lb/>= −1. It decreases monotonically by <lb/>increasing K and reaches the zero value at K = ∞ ( = 1). <lb/>The continuum limit of the Hamiltonian (3) is obtained by <lb/>writing spin operators in terms of bosonic fields: <lb/>τ z <lb/>n = <lb/>K <lb/>π <lb/>∂ x φ + <lb/>(−1) n a <lb/>π <lb/>sin[ <lb/>√ <lb/>4π K φ(x)], <lb/>τ + <lb/>n = <lb/>1 <lb/>√ <lb/>2π <lb/>e −i <lb/>√ π <lb/>K θ(x) ((−1) n b sin[ <lb/>√ <lb/>4π K φ(x)] + c), <lb/>(19) <lb/>where a, b, and c are non-universal real constants of the order <lb/>of unity and they depend on the parameter <lb/>[34, 35]. In <lb/>the above transformations we have made the rotations τ ± <lb/>n → <lb/>(−1) n τ ± <lb/>n and τ z <lb/>n → τ z <lb/>n on the standard bosonic version <lb/>of the spin operators, as found extensively in the literature. <lb/>Using (19), the effective Hamiltonian density is given as <lb/>H = <lb/>v <lb/>2 <lb/>[(∂ x θ) 2 + (∂ x φ) 2 ] + <lb/>h eff <lb/>1 <lb/>πa 0 <lb/>sin[ <lb/>√ <lb/>4π K φ] <lb/>− h eff <lb/>0 <lb/>K <lb/>π <lb/>∂ x φ. <lb/>(20) <lb/>The mapped model is nothing but the massive sine-<lb/>Gordon (SG) model with an additional topological term. Let <lb/>us first consider the SG model without the topological term <lb/>h eff <lb/>0 = 0 or at the magnetic field value h = J AF − J F <lb/>4 . As has <lb/>been discussed in many places, in the interval 1 &lt; K &lt; 2 the <lb/>spectrum of the SG model contains a soliton and anti-soliton <lb/>with mass M. The exact relation between the soliton mass and <lb/>the bare mass h eff <lb/>1 is as follows [36]: <lb/>M = C(K )h eff <lb/>1 <lb/>2−K <lb/>1 <lb/>, <lb/>C(K ) = <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2ν <lb/>√ <lb/>π 1 <lb/>2 + 1 <lb/>2ν <lb/>(1 − K <lb/>2 ) <lb/>2 <lb/>K <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2−K <lb/>. <lb/>(21) <lb/>By substituting K = 3/2 and h eff <lb/>1 = δ J AF in (21) the soliton <lb/>mass or equivalently the excitation gap is given as M ∼ <lb/>2 <lb/>J F (δ J AF ) 2 . Tuning h eff <lb/>0 adds a gradient term to the gapped SG <lb/>model. This term creates a shift in the field φ. Actually, in the <lb/>absence of the topological term the excitation spectrum of the <lb/>model is gapped and the field φ is stuck on one of the minima <lb/>where sin <lb/>√ <lb/>6π = −1. This corresponds to a staggered AF <lb/>order in the effective spin chain. Tuning the uniform field <lb/>h eff <lb/>0 , the number of particles is decreased and the minimum is <lb/>shifted. A challenge between the two uniform and staggered <lb/>fields causes the system to experience a different phase when <lb/>|h eff <lb/>0 | &gt; M [37]. This phase transition occurs at h − <lb/>c where the <lb/>excitation gap has reopened. <lb/>Consequently the width of the magnetization plateau is <lb/>obtained as <lb/>h + <lb/>c − h − <lb/>c <lb/>4 <lb/>J F <lb/>(δ J AF ) 2 , <lb/>(22) <lb/>where h + <lb/>c and h − <lb/>c are the middle critical field and are given by <lb/>h ± <lb/>c = J AF 1 + <lb/>α <lb/>4 <lb/>± <lb/>2δ 2 <lb/>α <lb/>. <lb/>(23) <lb/>Summarizing, implementing two continuum field theories <lb/>we found that the model has four critical fields. <lb/>Figure 3. Difference between the two lowest energy levels of the <lb/>original Hamiltonian versus the magnetic field h for chains with <lb/>different lengths N = 16, 20 and exchange parameters J F = 1.0, <lb/>J AF = 9/2, and δ = 1/9. <lb/>4. Numerical results <lb/>To explore the nature of the spectrum and the quantum phase <lb/>transition, we have used the Lanczos method to diagonalize <lb/>numerically chains with length up to N = 28. <lb/>First, we have computed the three lowest energy <lb/>eigenvalues of chains with J F = 1.0, different values of the <lb/>length and AF exchanges. To get the energies of the few <lb/>lowest eigenstates we consider chains with periodic boundary <lb/>conditions. <lb/>In figure 3, we present the results of these calculations <lb/>for the exchanges J F = 1.0, J AF = 9/2, δ = 1/9, and <lb/>chain sizes N = 16, 20. We define the excitation gap as <lb/>a gap on the first excited state. As seen in figure 3, in the <lb/>strong limit of AF exchange, this difference is characterized <lb/>by the indistinguishable (within the used numerical accuracy) <lb/>dependence on the chain length and shows a universal linear <lb/>decrease with increasing magnetic field. At h = 0 the spectrum <lb/>of the model is gapped. Tuning the magnetic field the energy <lb/>gap decreases linearly with h and vanishes at h c 1 . This is the <lb/>first level crossing between the ground state energy and the first <lb/>excited state energy. The spectrum remains gapless for h c 1 &lt; <lb/>h &lt; h − <lb/>c , whereas the gap is reopened when h &gt; h − <lb/>c . After an <lb/>increase and a decrease the spin gap goes to zero and vanishes <lb/>at h + <lb/>c . On further increasing the field h &gt; h + <lb/>c , the spectrum <lb/>remains gapless up to the critical saturation field h c 2 . Finally, <lb/>at h &gt; h c 2 the gap is reopened and for a sufficiently large field <lb/>becomes proportional to h. Oscillations of the energy gap in <lb/>regions h c 1 &lt; h &lt; h − <lb/>c and h c 2 &lt; h &lt; h + <lb/>c are the result of level <lb/>crossings in finite size systems. To find the critical fields we <lb/>have used the phenomenological renormalization group (PRG) <lb/>method [12]. The critical field values are given as follows: <lb/>h c 1 = 3.80 ± 0.01, <lb/>h c 2 = 4.71 ± 0.01, <lb/>h c − = 3.99 ± 0.01, <lb/>h c + = 4.58 ± 0.01. <lb/>(24) <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 (2011) 246002 <lb/>S Mahdavifar and J Abouie <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 4. The magnetization along the field, M z , as a function of the <lb/>applied magnetic field, h, for chains with exchanges J F = 1.0, <lb/>J AF = 9/2, δ = 1/9 and lengths N = 20, 24, 28. In the inset, the <lb/>magnetization on a site as a function of the site number j is plotted <lb/>for a value of the magnetic field in the region of the mid-plateau. <lb/>To study the magnetic order of the ground state of the <lb/>system, we start with the magnetization process. First, we <lb/>have implemented the Lanczos algorithm on finite chains to <lb/>calculate the lowest eigenstate. The magnetization along the <lb/>field axis is defined as <lb/>M z = <lb/>1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>j =1 <lb/>GS|S z <lb/>j |GS , <lb/>(25) <lb/>where the notation Gs| • • • |Gs represents the ground state <lb/>expectation value. In figure 4, we have plotted M z as a <lb/>function of the magnetic field h, and for a chain with exchange <lb/>parameters J F = 1.0, J AF = 9/2, δ = 1/9, and different <lb/>lengths N = 20, 24, 28. As is clearly seen in figure 4 besides <lb/>the standard singlet and saturation plateaus at h &lt; h c 1 and <lb/>h &gt; h c 2 respectively, we observe a plateau at M = 1 <lb/>2 M sat . <lb/>Observed oscillations of the magnetization at h c 1 &lt; h &lt; h − <lb/>c <lb/>and h + <lb/>c &lt; h &lt; h c 2 result from the level crossing between <lb/>the ground and the first excited states of this model in the <lb/>gapless phases. To check that the mid-plateau is not a finite <lb/>size effect, we performed size scaling [38] of its width and <lb/>found that the size of the plateau interpolates to finite value <lb/>when N −→ ∞. In the inset of figure 4 we have plotted the <lb/>magnetization on site, M z <lb/>j = GS|S z <lb/>j |GS , as a function of the <lb/>site number j for a value of the magnetic field corresponding <lb/>to the plateau at M z = 0.5M z <lb/>sat . To obtain an accurate estimate <lb/>of the function M z <lb/>j , we have calculated it for system sizes of <lb/>N = 12, 16, 20, 24, 28. The thermodynamic limit (N → ∞) <lb/>of the finite size results is obtained by the extrapolation method <lb/>and used for plotting. As we observe, the system shows a well <lb/>pronounced modulation of the on-site magnetization, where <lb/>magnetization on odd bonds is larger than on even bonds. This <lb/>distribution remains almost unchanged within the plateau for <lb/>h − <lb/>c &lt; h &lt; h c + . <lb/>Figure 5. The string correlation function, O Str (l, N), as a function of <lb/>the applied magnetic field h, for chains with exchanges J F = 1.0, <lb/>J AF = 9/2, δ = 1/9 and lengths N = 20, 24, 28. <lb/>By analyzing the numerical results for the energy gap <lb/>(figure 3), we found that the spectrum is gapped in the absence <lb/>of the magnetic field which is one of the properties of the <lb/>Haldane phase. The Haldane phase can be recognized from <lb/>studying the string order parameter. The string correlation <lb/>function in a chain of length N, defined only for odd l, is [39] <lb/>O Str (l, N) = − exp iπ <lb/>2 j +l+1 <lb/>2 j +1 <lb/>S z <lb/>k <lb/>. <lb/>(26) <lb/>In particular, we calculated the string correlation function for <lb/>different finite chain lengths. Since the present model has a <lb/>SU (2) symmetry in the absence of a magnetic field, we only <lb/>consider the z component of the string correlation function. <lb/>In figure 5, we have plotted O Str (l, N) as a function of h for <lb/>the chain with exchanges J F = 1.0, J AF = 9/2, δ = 1/9 <lb/>and lengths N = 20, 24, 28. As can be seen from this <lb/>figure, at h &lt; h c 1 , the string correlation function O Str (l, N) <lb/>is saturated and the tetrameric chain system is in the Haldane <lb/>phase. The Haldane phase remains stable even in the presence <lb/>of a magnetic field less than h c 1 . <lb/>An additional insight into the nature of different phases <lb/>can be obtained by studying the correlation functions. We <lb/>define the following weak and strong bond dimerization order <lb/>parameters; <lb/>d w <lb/>r = <lb/>4 <lb/>N <lb/>N/2 <lb/>j odd =1,3,5,... <lb/>GS|S 2 j −1 • S 2 j |GS , <lb/>(27) <lb/>and <lb/>d s <lb/>r = <lb/>4 <lb/>N <lb/>N/2 <lb/>j even =2,4,6,... <lb/>GS|S 2 j −1 • S 2 j |GS , <lb/>(28) <lb/>where summations are taken over the weak and strong AF <lb/>bonds. In figure 6 we have plotted d w <lb/>r and d s <lb/>r versus magnetic <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 (2011) 246002 <lb/>S Mahdavifar and J Abouie <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 6. The AF bond dimerization order parameter as a function of <lb/>the applied field h for chains with exchanges J F = 1.0, J AF = 9/2, <lb/>δ = 1/9 and lengths N = 20, 24, 28. <lb/>field h for chains of lengths N = 20, 24, 28 with the exchange <lb/>parameters J F = 1.0, J AF = 9/2, and δ = 1/9. As seen from <lb/>this figure, at h &lt; h c 1 spins on all AF bonds are in a singlet <lb/>state d w <lb/>r = d s <lb/>r <lb/>−0.75, while at h &gt; h c 2 , d r is equal to <lb/>the saturation value d w <lb/>r = d s <lb/>r ∼ 1/4 and F long-range order <lb/>along the field axis is present. However, in the considered <lb/>case of strong AF exchanges (J ± <lb/>AF <lb/>J F ) and high critical <lb/>fields, quantum fluctuations are substantially suppressed and <lb/>calculated averages of on-AF-bond spin correlations are very <lb/>close to their nominal values. <lb/>On the other hand, for intermediate values of the magnetic <lb/>field, at h c 1 &lt; h &lt; h c 2 the data presented in figure 6 give us the <lb/>possibility to trace the mechanism of singlet-pair melting with <lb/>increasing magnetic field. As follows from figure 6 at h slightly <lb/>above h c 1 spin singlet pairs start to melt in all antiferromagnetic <lb/>bonds simultaneously and almost with the same intensity. With <lb/>further increase of h, melting of weak AF bonds becomes more <lb/>intense; however, at h = h − <lb/>c the process of melting stops. <lb/>As seen in figure 6, weak AF bonds are polarized; however, <lb/>their polarization is far from the saturation value d w <lb/>r <lb/>0.15, <lb/>while the strong AF bonds still manifest strong on-site singlet <lb/>features with d s <lb/>r <lb/>−0.65. Postponement of the melting stops <lb/>at h = h + <lb/>c , but for h &gt; h + <lb/>c strong AF bonds start to melt more <lb/>intensively while the polarization of weak AF bonds increases <lb/>slowly. Finally at h = h c 2 both subsystems of AF bonds <lb/>achieve an identical, almost fully polarized state. Note, that <lb/>the almost symmetric fluctuations in on-AF-bond correlations <lb/>increase in d w <lb/>r at h h − <lb/>c , decrease in d s <lb/>r at h h + <lb/>c , and reflect <lb/>the enhanced role of quantum fluctuations in the vicinity of <lb/>quantum critical points. <lb/>In our previous paper [13], we introduced a mean field <lb/>order parameter which can distinguish a gapless LL phase from <lb/>the other gapped phases. This order parameter is the F-dimer <lb/>Figure 7. The F-dimer order parameter as a function of the applied <lb/>field h, for the chains with exchanges J F = 1.0, J AF = 9/2, and <lb/>δ = 1/9 and lengths N = 12, 16, 20, and 24. The appearance of a <lb/>non-zero plateau in the curve is clear. <lb/>order parameter which is defined as <lb/>P F = Re S − <lb/>2n S + <lb/>2n+1 . <lb/>(29) <lb/>The F-dimer order parameter has a considerable value in <lb/>the Lüttinger liquid phase and behaves differently in the <lb/>other gapped phases. The effects of a small value of space <lb/>modulation on this parameter are shown in figure 7. We have <lb/>plotted P F versus magnetic field h for chain of lengths N = 12, <lb/>16, 20, and 24 with the exchange parameters J F = 1.0, <lb/>J AF = 9/2, and δ = 1/9. As can be seen, in the Haldane phase, <lb/>h &lt; h c 1 , the quantum fluctuations suppress the F correlations <lb/>and the F-dimer parameter is close to zero value. Right after <lb/>the first critical field, the F-dimer parameter increases rapidly <lb/>up to the second critical field. In the intermediate region, <lb/>h c − &lt; h &lt; h c + , the F-dimer parameter shows a non-zero <lb/>plateau which behaves in the same way as the other parameters. <lb/>By increasing the field, the F-dimer decreases and goes to <lb/>zero at the saturation critical field h = h c 2 . The intermediate <lb/>region is a gapped phase and we expect the zero value for the <lb/>defined LL parameter, P F . However, the gap does not affect the <lb/>behavior of P F and a plateau appears in the curve. <lb/>5. Pair-wise entanglement <lb/>In this section we focus on the entanglement of two spins <lb/>in different phases of the system. The entanglement which <lb/>has no classical counterpart is employed to study the quantum <lb/>correlations of different states. Concurrence is a measure of <lb/>the bipartite entanglement which is defined as [40, 41] <lb/>C lm = 2 max{0, C (1) <lb/>lm , C (2) <lb/>lm }, <lb/>(30) <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 (2011) 246002 <lb/>S Mahdavifar and J Abouie <lb/></note>

			<body>where <lb/>C (1) <lb/>lm = (g xx <lb/>lm − g <lb/>yy <lb/>lm ) 2 + (g <lb/>xy <lb/>lm + g <lb/>yx <lb/>lm ) 2 <lb/>− ( 1 <lb/>4 − g zz <lb/>lm ) 2 − <lb/>M z <lb/>l − M z <lb/>m <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/>C (2) <lb/>lm = (g xx <lb/>lm + g <lb/>yy <lb/>lm ) 2 + (g <lb/>xy <lb/>lm − g <lb/>yx <lb/>lm ) 2 <lb/>− ( 1 <lb/>4 + g zz <lb/>lm ) 2 − <lb/>M z <lb/>l + M z <lb/>m <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>(31) <lb/>and g <lb/>αβ <lb/>lm = S α <lb/>l S <lb/>β <lb/>m is the correlation function between spins l <lb/>and m. The numerical Lanczos results on the concurrence for <lb/>the 1D tetrameric spin-1/2 model are shown in figure 8. We <lb/>have plotted the entanglement of two spins which are located <lb/>at the same strong, weak, and F bond versus h, chain length <lb/>N = 28, and the exchange parameters J F = 1.0, J AF = 9/2, <lb/>and δ = 1/9. In the Haldane phase, h &lt; h c 1 , the spins <lb/>on all AF bonds make a singlet state. In this state which <lb/>is a maximally entangled state, g xx <lb/>lm = g <lb/>yy <lb/>lm = g zz <lb/>lm = −1 <lb/>4 , <lb/>C S = C W = 1, and C F is zero. For h &gt; h c 1 the values of C S <lb/>and C W fall down with increasing magnetic field. Indeed the <lb/>quantum correlations of the two spins with strong AF and weak <lb/>F interactions are decreased by increasing the magnetic field. <lb/>However, an enhancement on the entanglement of the two <lb/>spins with ferromagnetic interaction (SF) is observed. It means <lb/>that the magnetic field increases the quantum correlations of <lb/>the two spins which are interacting ferromagnetically. This <lb/>is a dual effect of the magnetic field which increases the <lb/>quantum correlations of two SFs and decreases the quantum <lb/>correlations of two weak antiferromagnets (SWAs) and two <lb/>strong antiferromagnets (SSAs). In the intermediate gapless <lb/>region h c 1 &lt; h &lt; h − <lb/>c , the quantum correlations of SWAs and <lb/>SSAs diminish down to h = h − <lb/>c and the concurrences C W <lb/>and C S reduce to ∼0.1 and ∼0.9 respectively. However, the <lb/>quantum correlations of SF grow up to the critical field h c − and <lb/>the entanglement reaches the value ∼0.25. At the plateau state, <lb/>the gap of the system is reopened and a plateau emerges in the <lb/>curve of concurrences. In the intermediate gapped phase the <lb/>values of the concurrences C S , C W , and C F are 0.9, 0.1, and <lb/>0.25, respectively. Indeed in the plateau state there are three <lb/>types of quantum correlations in the system. These correlators <lb/>are the source of the mid-plateaus in the different parameters <lb/>of the system such as magnetization, bond-dimer, and F-dimer <lb/>parameters. Indeed all of these quantum correlators exist only <lb/>at the mid-plateau states. In the full saturated state all of them <lb/>disappear and the entanglement of the state is exactly zero. <lb/>To see the finite size effects, we have plotted in the inset <lb/>of figure 8(a) the concurrence between two SSAs as a function <lb/>of h for different chain sizes N = 16, 20, 24, and 28. It can be <lb/>seen that there is no size effect on the numerical results and the <lb/>concurrence behaves as a thermodynamic limit in the gapped <lb/>regions. <lb/>To get more insight into the mid-plateau state, we have <lb/>computed numerically the entanglement between the spins <lb/>with different separation distances. The concurrence between <lb/>an SSA and an arbitrary spin, say S m has been plotted versus <lb/>the separation distance m, in figure 8(b). The entanglement <lb/>Figure 8. (a) The concurrence as a function of the applied field h, for <lb/>chains with exchanges J F = 1.0, J AF = 9/2, and δ = 1/9 and length <lb/>N = 28. Inset plot: the concurrence between two spins on a strong <lb/>bond as a function of h for different chain sizes N = 16, 20, 24 and <lb/>28. (b) Concurrence of two spins versus separation distance m. <lb/>of two such spins is decreased by increasing m and goes to <lb/>zero at the finite value of m = 7. The same behavior is also <lb/>observed for the entanglement between an SWA and the spin <lb/>S m with respect to m. The entanglement between SWAs and <lb/>S m goes to zero at m = 9. This means that in the plateau state <lb/>the range of the quantum correlations between an SWA and S m <lb/>is longer than the range between an SSA and S m . This is the <lb/>other feature of the mid-plateau state. <lb/>It is also remarkable that from our numerical results we <lb/>found that the concurrence of two spins that are not on the <lb/>same bond is equal to zero in the gapped Haldane and saturated <lb/>F phases, which is in complete agreement with the analytical <lb/>results. <lb/>6. Conclusion <lb/>In this paper, we have focused on the magnetic properties of <lb/>a bond alternating antiferromagnetic-ferromagnetic spin-1/2 <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 23 (2011) 246002 <lb/>S Mahdavifar and J Abouie <lb/></note>

			<body>Heisenberg chain. Using two analytical approaches and <lb/>a numerical method we have studied the effects of an <lb/>external magnetic field and a space modulation on the <lb/>ground state properties of the system. In the limit where <lb/>the antiferromagnetic couplings are dominant, we mapped <lb/>the model (1) to an effective X X Z Heisenberg chain with <lb/>anisotropy parameter <lb/>= 1/2 in the presence of effective <lb/>uniform and staggered longitudinal magnetic fields. This <lb/>model has different quantum phases which are distinguished <lb/>by four critical fields. To find the critical fields we employed <lb/>two field theoretical approaches: the nonlinear σ model and <lb/>bosonization, and the numerical exact diagonalization Lanczos <lb/>method. Working on the spin coherent states representation, <lb/>we mapped the model (1) to a nonlinear σ model with an <lb/>additional topological term. The topological term is dependent <lb/>on the space modulation δ and the parameter α = J F <lb/>J AF . For any <lb/>values of α and δ, the Hamiltonian mapped to a non-integrable <lb/>O(3) nonlinear σ model with <lb/>in the interval [0, π]. In <lb/>the absence of a magnetic field the model is always gapped <lb/>and the gap value depends on α and δ. By analyzing our <lb/>nonlinear σ model in the presence of the magnetic field, we <lb/>obtained only the two critical fields. To dominate this vacancy <lb/>and to find the other two critical fields we also bosonized the <lb/>effective Hamiltonian of the X X Z chain (3). Our bosonization <lb/>procedure showed that the width of the mid-plateau is a <lb/>function of δ J AF . It has been shown that the plateau width <lb/>scales as a power low with exponent value 2 and vanishes at <lb/>δ = 0. <lb/>Moreover, we implemented the Lanczos method to <lb/>numerically diagonalize chains with finite length up to N = <lb/>28. Using the exact diagonalization technique, we calculated <lb/>the energy gap, magnetization, the string, the F-dimer, and the <lb/>bond-dimer order parameters and various correlation functions <lb/>for different values of the external magnetic field. In good <lb/>qualitative agreement with our analytical results, we showed <lb/>clearly that a space modulation on the antiferromagnetic <lb/>exchanges leads to generation of a gap in the excitation <lb/>spectrum of the system and, correspondingly, a magnetization <lb/>mid-plateau at M <lb/>M sat. = 1 <lb/>2 . We found that a non-zero plateau also <lb/>creates in the plot of the F-dimer, bond-dimer order parameters. <lb/>To obtain more physical insight into the mid-plateau state <lb/>we also investigated the pair-wise entanglement between two <lb/>different spins of the system. As a measure of entanglement, <lb/>the concurrence between two arbitrary spins was computed as <lb/>a function of magnetic field. A plateau also appeared in the <lb/>concurrence at the middle gapped state. In the plateau state <lb/>there are three types of quantum correlations in the system. In <lb/>the plateau state the range of the quantum correlations between <lb/>a spin on the weak antiferromagnetic bond and a S m is longer <lb/>than the range of the quantum correlations of a spin on the <lb/>strong antiferromagnetic bond and S m . <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>JA thanks A Langari for his fruitful discussions on the <lb/>manuscript. We are grateful to G I Japaridze for very useful <lb/>comments. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Haldane F D M 1983 Phys. Rev. Lett. 50 1153 <lb/>[2] Oshikawa M, Yamanaka M and Affleck I 1997 Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>78 1984 <lb/>[3] Takada S 1992 J. Phys. Soc. Japan 61 428 <lb/>[4] Hida K and Takada S 1992 J. Phys. Soc. Japan 61 1879 <lb/>[5] Hida K 1993 J. Phys. Soc. Japan 62 439 <lb/>[6] Hida K 1992 Phys. Rev. B 46 8268 <lb/>[7] Kohmoto M and Tasaki H 1992 Phys. Rev. B 46 3486 <lb/>[8] Yamanaka M, Hatsugai Y and Kohmoto M 1993 Phys. Rev. B <lb/>48 9555 <lb/>[9] Hida K 1994 J. Phys. Soc. Japan 63 2514 <lb/>[10] Sakai T 1995 J. Phys. Soc. Japan 64 251 <lb/>[11] Yamamoto S and Funase K 2005 Low Temp. Phys. 31 740 <lb/>[12] Mahdavifar S and Akbari A 2008 J. Phys. Soc. Japan <lb/>77 024710 <lb/>[13] Abouie J and Mahdavifar S 2008 Phys. Rev. B 78 184437 <lb/>[14] Ajiro Y, Asano T, Inami T, Aruga-Katori H and Goto T 1994 <lb/>J. Phys. Soc. Japan 63 859 <lb/>[15] Hida K 1994 J. Phys. Soc. Japan 63 2359 <lb/>[16] Okamoto K 1996 Solid State Commun. 98 245 <lb/>[17] Gu B, Su G and Gao S 2006 Phys. Rev. B 73 134427 <lb/>[18] Gong S-S, Gu B and Su G 2008 Phys. Lett. A 372 2322 <lb/>[19] Escuer A, Vicente R, El Fallah M S, Goher M A S and <lb/>Mautner F A 1998 Inorg. Chem. 37 4466 <lb/>[20] Lu H T, Su Y H, Sun L Q, Chang J, Liu C S, Luo H G and <lb/>Iang T 2005 Phys. Rev. B 71 144426 <lb/>[21] Gong S-S, Gao S and Su G 2009 Phys. Rev. B 80 014413 <lb/>[22] Stone M B, Tian W, Lumsden M D, Granroth G E, Mandrus D, <lb/>Chung J-H, Harrison N and Nagler S E 2007 Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>99 087204 <lb/>[23] Chen W, Hida K and Nakano H 1999 J. Phys. Soc. Japan <lb/>68 625 <lb/>[24] Mila F 1998 Eur. Phys. J. B 6 201 <lb/>[25] Alcaraz F C and Malvezzi A L 1995 J. Phys. A: Math. Gen. <lb/>28 1521 <lb/>[26] Okamoto K and Nomura K 1994 J. Phys. A: Math. Gen. <lb/>27 5773 <lb/>[27] Japaridze G I and Pogossyan E 2006 J. Phys.: Condens. Matter <lb/>18 9297 <lb/>Japaridze G I and Mahdavifar S 2009 Eur. Phys. J. B 68 59 <lb/>[28] Fouet J-B, Tchernyshyov O and Mila F 2004 Phys. Rev. B <lb/>70 174427 <lb/>[29] Mahdavifar S 2007 Eur. Phys. J. B 55 371 <lb/>[30] Bosquet M and Jolicoeur Th 2000 Eur. Phys. J. B 14 47 <lb/>[31] Loss D and Maslov D L 1995 Phys. Rev. Lett. 74 178 <lb/>[32] Normand B, Kyriakidis J and Loss D 2000 Ann. Phys., Lpz. <lb/>9 133 <lb/>[33] Eggert S and Affleck I 1992 Phys. Rev. B 46 10866 <lb/>[34] Hikihara T and Furusaki A 1998 Phys. Rev. B 58 583(R) <lb/>[35] Takayoshi S and Masahiro S 2010 Phys. Rev. B 82 214420 <lb/>[36] Zamolodchikov Al B 1995 Int. J. Mod. Phys. A 10 1125 <lb/>[37] Japaridze G I and Nersesyan A A 1978 JETF Pis. 27 356 <lb/>Japaridze G I and Nersesyan A A 1978 JETP Lett. 27 334 <lb/>(Engl. Transl.) <lb/>Japaridze G I and Nersesyan A A 1979 J. Low Temp. Phys. <lb/>37 95 <lb/>Pokrovsky V L and Talapov A L 1979 Phys. Rev. Lett. 42 65 <lb/>[38] Zhitomirsky M E, Honecker A and Petrenko O A 2000 Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 85 027207 <lb/>[39] Hida K 1999 Phys. Rev. Lett. 83 3297 <lb/>[40] Wooters W K 1998 Phys. Rev. Lett. 80 2245 <lb/>[41] Amico L, Fazio R, Osterloh A and Vedal V 2008 Rev. Mod. <lb/>Phys. 80 517 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
