<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett. 72 (2022) 128845 <lb/>Available online 11 June 2022 <lb/>0960-894X/© 2022 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Multigram-scale total synthesis of (±)-ambreinolide by a diastereoselective <lb/>polyene cyclization <lb/>Paul Wienecke a , Helmar Görls b , Hans-Dieter Arndt a, * <lb/>a Friedrich-Schiller-Universität Jena, Institut für Organische Chemie und Makromolekulare Chemie, Humboldtstr. 10, D-07743 Jena, Germany <lb/>b Friedrich-Schiller-Universität Jena, Institut für Anorganische und Analytische Chemie, Humboldtstr. 8, D-07743 Jena, Germany <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Natural products <lb/>Biomimetic synthesis <lb/>Terpenes <lb/>Total synthesis <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>Ambreinolide is a natural terpenoid with great value for perfume industry and natural product synthesis. Herein <lb/>we report a novel total synthesis of ambreinolide on multigram-scale that employs a regio-and diaster-<lb/>eoselective, high yielding, proton-initiated polyene cyclization using a catalyst easily generated in situ. Molecular <lb/>structures were unambiguously confirmed by X-ray crystallography. <lb/></front>

			<body>Ambergris (&quot;grey amber&quot;) is a coprolite from the sperm whale <lb/>(Physeter macrocephalus) digestive tract, probably arising from gut irri-<lb/>tation by indigestible squid beaks. Its unique scent led to its use as a <lb/>flavoring agent, incense, and as a perfume base since antiquity. It still is <lb/>one of the best fixatives known for perfume production to date. 1 How-<lb/>ever, the trade of ambergris jetsam is banned by many countries, 2 and a <lb/>shrinking sperm whale population and increasing pollution make <lb/>ambergris extremely rare. 3 Therefore, it is typically substituted by syn-<lb/>thetic alternatives. <lb/>As a component of the ambergris&apos; odorless fraction, ambreinolide (1, <lb/>Fig. 1), contributes to its extraordinary fixative properties. 3 It is believed <lb/>to arise from ambreine (2), the main constituent of ambergris, by slow <lb/>autoxidative degradation in the open sea. 4 Furthermore, it was found in <lb/>several plants used for medical applications. 5-11 Several syntheses <lb/>feature ambreinolide (1) as an intermediate or as a starting materi-<lb/>al. 12-20 Its terpene framework is typical for the drimane <lb/>sesquiterpenoids. 21 <lb/>Previously reported syntheses of ambreinolide (1) mainly rely on <lb/>transformations of other complex natural products which are not always <lb/>easy to access. 12,14,15,22-26 An acid-mediated polyene cyclization of the <lb/>far more simple farnesylacetic acid was reported early on by Stork, but <lb/>gave less than 3% yield of racemic ambreinolide (1). 27 A more pro-<lb/>ductive modification of this procedure uses 2-nitropropane as a non-<lb/>benign solvent. 15,16 However, in our hands, this procedure was diffi-<lb/>cult to reproduce and generated numerous byproducts which were <lb/>difficult to separate, resulting in low overall yields. <lb/>In order to develop a novel, scalable total synthesis of ambreinolide <lb/>(1) from a polyene precursor, its structure was retrosynthetically <lb/>simplified to enone 3 (Scheme 1), which may be accessed from phenolic <lb/>derivatives 4 by reductive dearomatization. This terpenoid could rapidly <lb/>arise from suitably protected dienes 5 by a proton-initiated, diaster-<lb/>eoselective polycyclization reaction that is terminated by the electron-<lb/>rich arene nucleus. Diene 5 was planned to be synthesized from easily <lb/>available geranyl acetate (6) and a benzylic Grignard (7). Key to this <lb/>plan was the development of a scalable polyene cyclization. 28 <lb/>Aiming to investigate and develop such a synthesis, the phenolic <lb/>polyene 9 was prepared from geranyl acetate (6) by employing S N 2-<lb/>selective substitution with a cuprate derived from Grignard reagent 7 <lb/>(Scheme 2). 29 Subsequent demethylation of anisole 5a afforded the <lb/>phenol 5b in very good yields. <lb/>After unsuccessful attempts to promote polyene cyclizations of this <lb/>precursor with simple reagents, we turned our attention to Yamamoto&apos;s <lb/>Lewis-acid assisted chiral Brønsted acids (LBAs) 30 and related reagents <lb/>for stereoselective protonation. 31 These reagents are formed by coordi-<lb/>nation of a Lewis acid to a weak Brønsted acid, in order to increase its <lb/>acidity, and to confine the putative protonation vector. 32 Enantiose-<lb/>lective polyene cyclizations with LBAs of type 8, formed from chiral <lb/>BINOL derivatives with tin tetrachloride in situ, have been reported. 28 <lb/>Owing to the preferred protonation of the terminal alkene, comparable <lb/>to terpene cyclases, this method is considered biomimetic. 33-37 <lb/>We employed monobenzylated S-BINOL 10 as the Brønsted acid for <lb/>studying the intended polyene cyclization and investigated different <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail address: hd.arndt@uni-jena.de (H.-D. Arndt). <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters <lb/>journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/bmcl <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmcl.2022.128845 <lb/>Received 31 March 2022; Received in revised form 31 May 2022; Accepted 8 June 2022 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters 72 (2022) 128845 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>protecting groups for phenol 5b (Table 1, entries 1-7) for achieving the <lb/>desired regioselectivity and for obtaining proper reactivity. <lb/>Weakly electron-poor acylated phenols were found promising with <lb/>respect to regio-and diastereoselectivity (entries 1-3). In these cases, <lb/>additional exposure to BF 3 •OEt 2 was required to complete bicyclization <lb/>to tricycles 4c-f from mixtures with monocyclized alkenes 9. Never-<lb/>theless, the products were isolated as the desired single diastereo-and <lb/>regioisomers in very good yields. The pivaloyl protection provided best <lb/>yield and enantioselectivity (entry 3). Introduction of a phenyl-<lb/>carbamate group instead led to reduced enantiomeric excess (entry 4). <lb/>Less electron-withdrawing protecting groups like dimethylcarbamate <lb/>and TBDPS (entries 5-6) resulted in inseparable product mixtures. The <lb/>strongly electron-withdrawing triflate disabled the second cyclization <lb/>step (entry 7). <lb/>Although the pivaloyl-protected phenol 5e was most productive, we <lb/>observed only moderate enantioselectivity (62% e.e.). Therefore, a se-<lb/>ries of different BINOL derivatives 11-21 were tested as alternative <lb/>reagents. Unfortunately, all modifications led to decreased enantiose-<lb/>lectivity or discouraging of activity (entries 8-18). Changing the <lb/>solvent or employing less active LBAs at higher temperature remained <lb/>unsuccessful. The application of an antimony pentachloride based LBA 38 <lb/>resulted in fully racemic product in this case (data not shown). <lb/>A mechanistic rationale delineated from Yamamoto&apos;s studies on <lb/>LBA-induced asymmetric polyene cyclization is depicted in Scheme 3. <lb/>LBA complexes 8 likely chelate SnCl 4 in an equatorial-equatorial <lb/>fashion. The only moderately face selective protonation traverses pu-<lb/>tative transition state I in which steric repulsion between the BINOL <lb/>moiety and the polyene substrate is minimized, and the n-π* interaction <lb/>between an oxygen lone pair and the terminal double bond is facili-<lb/>tated. 33 Initial protonation could lead to a concerted transition state II <lb/>that produces decaline 4e directly by bicyclization. Alternatively, the <lb/>polyene cyclization may proceed stepwise by involving the aryl-shielded <lb/>intermediate III. This would give first the alkene isomers 9. After a <lb/>second protonation carbocationic intermediate IV would transform to <lb/>decaline 4e with high trans-selectivity. 35 The stepwise mechanism may <lb/>be predominant considering the initial formation of alkenes 9 in large <lb/>amounts (Table 1), with some bicyclization occurring in this application. <lb/>To our delight, we found the simple LBA (±)-BINOL⋅SnCl 4 used in a <lb/>sub-stochiometric amount to preserve full regio-and diastereoselectivity, <lb/>and to give high yields for the desired bicyclization (Scheme 4) after <lb/>addition of BF 3 •OEt 2 . Unfortunately, lowering the amount of catalyst or <lb/>using BF 3 •OEt 2 or SnCl 4 alone produced product mixtures. Further <lb/>optimization led to a one-pot procedure without the necessity to isolate <lb/>intermediates, while BINOL can easily be recovered and reused. 38 <lb/>Removal of the pivaloyl protecting group from bicyclization product 4e <lb/>provided highly crystalline phenol 4b in very good yield on decagram <lb/>scale (Scheme 4). X-ray single-crystal structure analysis confirmed the <lb/>desired trans configuration. <lb/>Methylation of phenol 4b gave anisole 4a quantitatively (Scheme 5). <lb/>Birch reduction and acidic hydrolysis of the resulting enol ether afforded <lb/>enone 3 selectively in very good yield. <lb/>Treatment of enone 3 with mCPBA induced Baeyer-Villiger oxidation <lb/>and subsequent enol epoxidation, 24 to cleanly yield epoxy lactone 22 <lb/>(Scheme 6). Wolff-Kishner-type conditions led to base-induced rear-<lb/>rangement and formation of intermediate hydrazone 23, which con-<lb/>verted to acid 24 with heating. 24,39 Upon exposure to sulfuric acid in <lb/>acetic acid, carboxylic acid 24 underwent a cationic cyclization to <lb/>selectively give ambreinolide (±)-1 in an overall yield of 65% from <lb/>enone 3. X-ray single-crystal structure analysis confirmed the desired <lb/>structure of the obtained product (Fig. 2). We synthesized 7.7 g of <lb/>ambreinolide (±)-1 in a single lab batch, demonstrating the scalability <lb/>and robustness of this total synthesis route. <lb/>In summary, we have developed a novel total synthesis of racemic <lb/>ambreinolide, providing convenient access to (±)-1 on multigram-scale. <lb/>This material is not only highly valuable per se, but also an attractive <lb/>starting material for the synthesis of structurally related natural prod-<lb/>ucts. Key was the development of a regio-and diastereoselective, high-<lb/>yielding polyene cyclization induced by the LBA (±)-BINOL⋅SnCl 4 , of <lb/>which the BINOL component can be easily recycled. These results will <lb/>contribute to future terpene total synthesis projects and increase <lb/>accessibility of rare materials from nature for human use. <lb/></body>
				
			<div type="conflict">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial <lb/>interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence <lb/>the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>
			
			<body>Fig. 1. Structures of ambreinolide (1) and ambreine (2). <lb/>Scheme 1. Retrosynthetic planning for the synthesis of ambreinolide (1). <lb/>Scheme 2. Synthesis of phenol-terminated diene 9. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">P. Wienecke et al. <lb/> Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters 72 (2022) 128845 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 <lb/>Optimization <lb/>of <lb/>enantioselective <lb/>polyene <lb/>cyclization <lb/>of <lb/>dienes <lb/>5 <lb/>with <lb/>reagents <lb/>8 <lb/>from <lb/>10-21. <lb/>Entry <lb/>Cmp. <lb/>R 1 = <lb/>BINOL <lb/>Step 1 a <lb/>Step 2 <lb/>Ratio (4:9) b <lb/>Yield [%] c <lb/>Yield [%] c <lb/>ee [%] d <lb/>1 <lb/>5c <lb/>Ac <lb/>10 <lb/>3.1:6.9 <lb/>86 <lb/>93 (4c) <lb/>52 <lb/>2 <lb/>5d <lb/>Bz <lb/>10 <lb/>2.0:8.0 <lb/>85 <lb/>94 (4d) <lb/>58 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>10 <lb/>2.4:7.6 <lb/>92 <lb/>92 (4e) <lb/>62 <lb/>4 <lb/>5f <lb/>C(O)NHPh <lb/>10 <lb/>3.4:6.6 <lb/>90 <lb/>92 (4f) <lb/>52 <lb/>5 <lb/>5g <lb/>C(O)NMe 2 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.6:9.4 <lb/>90 <lb/>product mixture <lb/>6 <lb/>5h <lb/>TBDPS <lb/>10 <lb/>1.1:8.9 <lb/>87 <lb/>product mixture <lb/>7 <lb/>5i <lb/>Tf <lb/>10 <lb/>0.0:1.0 <lb/>84 <lb/>product mixture <lb/>8 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>11 <lb/>2.8:7.2 <lb/>96 <lb/>93 (4e) <lb/>44 <lb/>9 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>12 <lb/>2.8:7.2 <lb/>94 <lb/>92 (4e) <lb/>42 <lb/>10 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>13 <lb/>2.8:7.2 <lb/>94 <lb/>91 (4e) <lb/>30 <lb/>11 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>14 <lb/>1.3:8.7 <lb/>95 <lb/>92 (4e) <lb/>58 <lb/>12 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>15 <lb/>1.0:9.0 <lb/>92 <lb/>91 (4e) <lb/>48 <lb/>13 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>16 <lb/>low conversion <lb/>-<lb/>14 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>17 <lb/>no conversion <lb/>-<lb/>15 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>18 <lb/>no conversion <lb/>-<lb/>16 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>19 <lb/>1.4:8.6 <lb/>94 <lb/>91 (4e) <lb/>54 <lb/>17 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>20 <lb/>3.9:6.1 <lb/>90 <lb/>90 (4e) <lb/>54 <lb/>18 <lb/>5e <lb/>Piv <lb/>21 <lb/>no conversion <lb/>-<lb/>a Reactions were conducted at 0.3 mmol scale. <lb/>b Determined by 1 H NMR analysis. <lb/>c Isolated yields of products 4c-4f. <lb/>d Determined by HPLC analysis. <lb/>Scheme 3. Proposed mechanism for LBA-induced asymmetric polyene cyclization. <lb/>P. Wienecke et al. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters 72 (2022) 128845 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement <lb/>P. W. gratefully thanks the Deutsche Bundesstiftung Umwelt for a <lb/>doctoral fellowship. This work benefitted from funding by the DFG <lb/>through SFB1127/2 ChemBioSys-Project ID 239748522 (subproject <lb/>C03) and equipment grant INST 275/442-1 FUGG. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Supplementary data <lb/>Crystallographic data (excluding structure factors) has been depos-<lb/>ited with the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre as supplementary <lb/>publication CCDC-2162308 for 1, and CCDC-2162309 for 4b. Copies of <lb/>these data can be obtained free of charge on application to CCDC, 12 <lb/>Union Road, Cambridge CB2 1EZ, UK [E-mail: deposit@ccdc.cam.ac. <lb/>uk]. Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://do <lb/>i.org/10.1016/j.bmcl.2022.128845. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Clarke R. The origin of ambergris. LAJAM. 2006;5:7-21. https://doi.org/10.5597/ <lb/>lajam00087. <lb/>[2] Rowland SR, Sutton PA. Chromatographic and spectral studies of jetsam and <lb/>archived ambergris. Nat. Prod. Res. 2017;31:1752-1757. https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>14786419.2017.1290618. <lb/>[3] Ohloff G. The Fragrance of Ambergris. In: Theimer ET, ed. Fragrance Chemistry: The <lb/>Science of the Sense of Smell. London, UK: Academic Press; 1982:535-573. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-685850-1.50020-6. <lb/>[4] Lederer E. Chemistry and biochemistry of some mammalian secretions and <lb/>excretions. J. Chem. Soc. 1949;2115-2125. https://doi.org/10.1039/ <lb/>JR9490002115. <lb/>[5] Aumeeruddy-Elafi Z, Gurib-Fakim A, Mahomoodally F. Antimicrobial, antibiotic <lb/>potentiating activity and phytochemical profile of essential oils from exotic and <lb/>endemic medicinal plants of Mauritius. Ind. Crops. Prod. 2015;71:197-204. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2015.03.058. <lb/>[6] Sebastião NN, Cordeiro IJS, dos Santos AF, Gaspar JF, Martins C, Rueff J, <lb/>Diakanamwa C, Sant&apos;Ana AEG, de Mendonça DIMD. 8,15-Epoxylabdane and <lb/>norlabdane diterpenoids from Eragrostis viscosa. Phytochemistry. 2010;71: <lb/>798-803. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2010.02.003. <lb/>[7] Malafronte A, dal Piaza F, Cioffi G, Bracab A, Leonea A, de Tommasi N. Secondary <lb/>Metabolites from the Aerial Parts of Salvia Aethiopis L. Nat. Prod. Commun. 2008;3: <lb/>877-880. https://doi.org/10.1177/1934578X0800300610. <lb/>[8] Ucar MB, Ucar G. Lipophilic extractives and main components of black pine cones. <lb/>Chem. Nat. Compd. 2008;44:380-383. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10600-008-9071-<lb/>6. <lb/>[9] Topcu G, Ulubelen A, Tam TCM, Che CT. Norditerpenes and Norsesterterpenes <lb/>from Salvia yosgadensis. J. Nat. Prod. 1996;59:113-116. https://doi.org/10.1021/ <lb/>np960028h. <lb/>[10] Dolmazon R, Albrand M, Bessiere JM, Mahmout Y, Wernerowska D, <lb/>Kolodziejczyk K. Diterpenoids from Kyllinga erecta. Phytochemistry. 1995;38: <lb/>917-919. https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(94)00745-F. <lb/>[11] Schumacher JN, Vestal L. Isolation and identification of some components of <lb/>Turkish tobacco. Tob. Sci. 1974;18:43-48. <lb/>[12] Fujiwara N, Kinoshita M, Akita H. New total synthesis of (+)-ambrein. Tetrahedron <lb/>Asym. 2006;17:3037-3045. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tetasy.2006.11.015. <lb/>[13] Awano K, Ishizaki S, Takazawa O, Kitahara T. Analysis of ambergris tincture. <lb/>Flavour Fragr. J. 2005;20:18-21. https://doi.org/10.1002/ffj.1413. <lb/>[14] Kinoshita M, Nakamura D, Fujiwara N, Akita H. Total synthesis of (-)-(8R, 10S)-<lb/>and (+)-(8S, 10R)-8-hydroxypolypoda-13,17,21-triene based on enzymatic <lb/>resolution. J. Mol. Catal. B: Enzym. 2003;22:161-172. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>S1381-1177(03)00028-6. <lb/>[15] Tanimoto H, Oritani T. Synthesis of (+)-ambrein. Tetrahedron. 1997;53: <lb/>3527-3536. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040-4020(97)00103-8. <lb/>[16] Oritani T, Yamashita K, Matsui M. Synthesis of ambrein. Agric. Biol. Chem. 1990;54: <lb/>571-573. https://doi.org/10.1080/00021369.1990.10869941. <lb/>[17] Coste-Manière IC, Zahra JP, Waegell B. Synthesis of ambergris fragrance chemicals <lb/>from sclareol, involving palladium catalysed key steps. Tetrahedron Lett. 1988;29: <lb/>1017-1020. https://doi.org/10.1016/0040-4039(88)85323-1. <lb/>[18] Cambie RC, Palmer BD. Chemistry of the Podocarpaceae. LVII. The preparation of <lb/>some 1,3-dioxans with ambergris-type odours. Aust. J. Chem. 1981;34:1265-1284. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1071/CH9811265. <lb/>[19] Pelletier SW, Lajsic S, Ohtsuka Y, Djarmati Z. Naturally occurring terpenes. <lb/>Synthesis of (+)-and (±)-14,15-bisnor-8α-hydroxylabd-11(e)-en-13-one, (+)-<lb/>drimane-8,11-diol, and (-)-drimenol. J. Org. Chem. 1975;40:1607-1609. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1021/jo00899a019. <lb/>[20] Corey EJ, Hess HJ, Proskow S. Synthesis of a β-amyrin derivative, olean-11,12; <lb/>13,18-diene. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1963;85:3979-3983. https://doi.org/10.1021/ <lb/>ja00907a016. <lb/>[21] Jansen BJM, de Groot A. Occurrence, biological activity and synthesis of drimane <lb/>sesquiterpenoids. Nat. Prod. Rep. 2004;21:449-477. https://doi.org/10.1039/ <lb/>B311170A. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Scheme 4. Optimized synthesis of phenol 4b. Molecular structure and atom <lb/>numbering of phenol 4b in the solid state shown. The ellipsoids represent a <lb/>probability of 30 %. Hydrogen atoms are omitted for clarity. <lb/>Scheme 5. Synthesis of enone 3. <lb/>Scheme 6. Synthesis of (±)-ambreinolide 1. <lb/>Fig. 2. Molecular structure and atom numbering scheme of (±)-ambreinolide <lb/>(1). The ellipsoids represent a probability of 30 %. Hydrogen atoms are omitted <lb/>for clarity. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">P. Wienecke et al. <lb/> Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters 72 (2022) 128845 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[22] Kukovinets OS, Zainullin RA, Odinokov VN, Kislitsyn MI, Roshchin VI, Galin FZ, <lb/>Tolstikov GA. Ozonolysis of alkenes and study of reactions of polyfunctional <lb/>compounds: LXIV. Synthesis of ambreinolide and 8α,13-epoxy-14,15,16-<lb/>trisnorlabd-12-ene proceeding from isoabienol ozonolysis. Russ. J. Org. Chem. <lb/>2001;37:235-237. https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1012331013282. <lb/>[23] Urones JG, Basabe P, Marcos IS, Gonzàlez JL, Jiménez V, Sexmero JM, <lb/>Lithgow AM. Ambergis compounds from labdanolic acid. Tetrahedron. 1992;48: <lb/>9991-9998. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040-4020(01)92289-6. <lb/>[24] Abad A, Agulló C, Arnó M, Cuñat AC, Zaragozà RJ. Synthesis of (+)-ambreinolide <lb/>from abietic acid. J. Org. Chem. 1989;54:5123-5125. https://doi.org/10.1021/ <lb/>jo00282a030. <lb/>[25] Ohloff G, Vial C. Permanganate oxidation of ambrein and the absolute <lb/>configuration of dihydro-ɣ-ionone (supplement and rectification). Helv. Chim. Acta. <lb/>1977;60:2767-2769. https://doi.org/10.1002/hlca.19770600829. <lb/>[26] Schenk HR, Gutmann H, Jeger O, Ruzicka L. Zur Kenntnis der Diterpene. 62. <lb/>Mitteilung. Über eine neue, ergiebige Partialsynthese des Ambreinolids. Helv. <lb/>Chim. Acta. 1952;35:817-824. https://doi.org/10.1002/hlca.19520350319. <lb/>[27] Stork G, Burgstahler AW. The stereochemistry of polyene cyclization. J. Am. Chem. <lb/>Soc. 1955;77:5068-5077. https://doi.org/10.1021/ja01624a038. <lb/>[28] Barrett AGM, Ma TK, Mles T. Recent developments in polyene cyclizations and <lb/>their applications in natural product synthesis. Synthesis. 2019;51:67-82. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1055/s-0037-1610382. <lb/>[29] Bäckvall JE, Sellén M, Grant B. Regiocontrol in copper-catalyzed Grignard <lb/>reactions with allylic substrates. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1990;12:6615-6621. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1021/ja00174a024. <lb/>[30] Ishihara K, Kaneeda M, Yamamoto H. Lewis acid assisted chiral brønsted acid for <lb/>enantioselective protonation of silyl enol ethers and ketene bis(trialkylsilyl) <lb/>acetals. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1994;116:11179-11180. https://doi.org/10.1021/ <lb/>ja00103a052. <lb/>[31] Yamamoto H, Futatsugi K. &quot;Designer acids&quot;: combined acid catalysis for <lb/>asymmetric synthesis. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 2005;44:1924-1942. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1002/anie.200460394. <lb/>[32] Ishibashi H, Ishihara K, Yamamoto H. Chiral proton donor reagents: tin <lb/>tetrachloride-coordinated optically active binaphthol derivatives. Chem. Rec. <lb/>2002;2:177-188. https://doi.org/10.1002/tcr.10020. <lb/>[33] Ishihara K, Nakamura S, Yamamoto H. The first enantioselective biomimetic <lb/>cyclization of polyprenoids. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1999;121:4906-4907. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1021/ja984064+. <lb/>[34] Nakamura S, Ishihara K, Yamamoto H. Enantioselective biomimetic cyclization of <lb/>isoprenoids using lewis acid-assisted chiral brønsted acids: Abnormal claisen <lb/>rearrangements and successive cyclizations. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2000;122: <lb/>8131-8140. https://doi.org/10.1021/ja001165a. <lb/>[35] Ishihara K, Ishibashi H, Yamamoto H. Enantioselective Biomimetic cyclization of <lb/>homo(polyprenyl)arenes. A new entry to (+)-podpcarpa-8,11,13-triene <lb/>diterpenoids and (-)-tetracyclic polyprenoid of sedimentary origin. J. Am. Chem. <lb/>Soc. 2001;123:1505-1506. https://doi.org/10.1021/ja003541x. <lb/>[36] Ishihara K, Ishibashi H, Yamamoto H. Enantio-and diastereoselective stepwise <lb/>cyclization of polyprenoids induced by chiral and achiral LBAs. A new entry to <lb/>(-)-ambrox, (+)-podocarpa-8,11,13-triene diterpenoids, and (-)-tetracyclic <lb/>polyprenoid of sedimentary origin. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2002;124:3647-3655. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/ja0124865. <lb/>[37] Ishibashi H, Ishihara K, Yamamoto H. A new artificial cyclase for polyprenoids: <lb/>enantioselective total synthesis of (-)-chromazonarol, (+)-8-epi-puupehedione, <lb/>and )-11&apos;-deoxytaondiol methyl ether. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2004;126: <lb/>11122-11123. https://doi.org/10.1021/ja0472026. <lb/>[38] Surendra K, Corey EJ. Highly enantioselective proton-initiated polycyclization of <lb/>polyenes. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2012;134:11992-11994. https://doi.org/10.1021/ <lb/>ja305851h. <lb/>[39] Chang CWJ, Pelletier SW. The rearrangement of a diterpene epoxy ε-lactone <lb/>system. Tetrahedron Lett. 1966;7:5483-5487. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040-4039 <lb/>(00)70127-4. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">P. Wienecke et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>