<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/>Available online 23 September 2020 <lb/>1386-5056/© 2020 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Review article <lb/>Successfully implementing a national electronic health record: a rapid <lb/>umbrella review <lb/>Orna Fennelly a, b, * , 1 , Caitriona Cunningham b , Loretto Grogan c , Heather Cronin d , <lb/>Conor O&apos;Shea e , Miriam Roche f , Fiona Lawlor g , Neil O&apos;Hare b, h,2 <lb/>a Insight Centre for Data Analytics, University College Dublin, Ireland <lb/>b School of Public Health, Physiotherapy and Sports Science, University College Dublin, Ireland <lb/>c Office of the Nursing and Midwifery Services Director, Health Service Executive (HSE), Ireland <lb/>d National Rehabilitation Hospital, Dublin, Ireland <lb/>e Irish College of General Practitioners, Ireland. <lb/>f Maternal and Newborn Clinical Management System National Project Team, HSE, Ireland <lb/>g St. James&apos; Hospital, Dublin, Ireland <lb/>h Ireland East Hospital Group, HSE, Ireland <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Electronic Health Record <lb/>Electronic Medical Record <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Review <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>Aim: To summarize the findings from literature reviews with a view to identifying and exploring the key factors <lb/>which impact on the success of an EHR implementation across different healthcare contexts. <lb/>Introduction: Despite the widely recognised benefits of electronic health records (EHRs), their full potential has <lb/>not always been achieved, often as a consequence of the implementation process. As more countries launch <lb/>national EHR programmes, it is critical that the most up-to-date and relevant international learnings are shared <lb/>with key stakeholders. <lb/>Methods: A rapid umbrella review was undertaken in collaboration with a multidisciplinary panel of knowledge-<lb/>users and experts from Ireland. A comprehensive literature review was completed (2019) across several search <lb/>engines (PubMed, CINAHL, Scopus, Embase, Web of Science, IEEE Xplore, ACM Digital Library, ProQuest, <lb/>Cochrane) and Gray literature. Identified studies (n = 5,040) were subject to eligibility criterion and identified <lb/>barriers and facilitators were analysed, reviewed, discussed and interpreted by the expert panel. <lb/>Results: Twenty-seven literature reviews were identified which captured the key organizational, human and <lb/>technological factors for a successful EHR implementation according to various stakeholders across different <lb/>settings. Although the size, type and culture of the healthcare setting impacted on the organizational factors, <lb/>each was deemed important for EHR success; Governance, leadership and culture, End-user involvement, Training, <lb/>Support, Resourcing, and Workflows. As well as organizational differences, individual end-users have varying Skills <lb/>and characteristics, Perceived benefits and incentives, and Perceived changes to the health ecosystem which were also <lb/>critical to success. Finally, the success of the EHR technology depended on Usability, Interoperability, Adaptability, <lb/>Infrastructure, Regulation, standards and policies, and Testing. <lb/>Conclusion: Fifteen inter-linked organizational, human and technological factors emerged as important for suc-<lb/>cessful EHR implementations across primary, secondary and long-term care settings. In determining how to <lb/>employ these factors, the local context, individual end-users and advancing technology must also be considered. <lb/>* Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail addresses: orna.fennelly@ucdconnect.ie (O. Fennelly), caitriona.g.cunningham@ucd.ie (C. Cunningham), loretto.grogan1@hse.ie (L. Grogan), Heather. <lb/>Cronin@nrh.ie (H. Cronin), conoshea@gmail.com (C. O&apos;Shea), mroche@stjames.ie (M. Roche), fiona.lawlor@hse.ie (F. Lawlor), neil.ohare@ucd.ie (N. O&apos;Hare). <lb/>1 Present address: Irish Centre for High End Computing (ICHEC), National University of Galway, Ireland. <lb/>2 Present address: Group Chief Information Office, Children&apos;s Health Ireland. <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics <lb/>journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/ijmedinf <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2020.104281 <lb/>Received 10 July 2020; Received in revised form 27 August 2020; Accepted 19 September 2020 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Capturing and effectively using clinical information and knowl-<lb/>edge to ensure a quality, safe and sustainable healthcare service is <lb/>widely recognised as important [1,2] and data from electronic health <lb/>records (EHRs) have been vital to decision-making on public health <lb/>policies during the COVID-19 pandemic [3]. An EHR provides a <lb/>longitudinal record of information regarding the health status of an <lb/>individual in computer-processible form across practices and spe-<lb/>cialists, and enables authorised access to clinical records in real-time <lb/>[4,5]. As well as expanding the capacity to utilise clinical data for <lb/>monitoring of patient outcomes and conducting audits and research <lb/>[6,7], the EHR provides access to patient information in a timely <lb/>manner, enabling healthcare professionals (HCPs) to spend more time <lb/>with patients 8 , reducing duplication of tests and work, and improving <lb/>the safety and quality of care provided [4,7,9-14]. Additionally, <lb/>integration of other functions and software, such as clinical decision <lb/>support and bar code medication administration, further expand its <lb/>potential benefits [15,16]. <lb/>Electronic patient records (EPRs) or electronic medical records <lb/>(EMRs) also offer many of these benefits but solely contain the records <lb/>from an individual organization. Whilst shared or summary care records <lb/>and patient portals respectively store and facilitate access to specific <lb/>patient information required by HCPs [17] and patients [18]. Despite <lb/>the number of benefits which can be derived from these systems, chal-<lb/>lenges have been met in implementing a fully interoperable EHR be-<lb/>tween primary and secondary care [13,19], often attributed to the <lb/>implementation process as opposed to the product supplied by the EHR <lb/>vendor [20,21]. Therefore, the implementation process is critical [22] <lb/>and must be considered as an ongoing process beginning during pro-<lb/>curement and continuing throughout each phase of design, develop-<lb/>ment, testing, &apos;Go Live&apos; and optimization. <lb/>Whilst hospital information systems (HIS) in the USA have been in <lb/>existence since the 1960s [23], HIS are a more recent phenomenon in <lb/>the Republic of Ireland where public healthcare is managed by the <lb/>Health Service Executive (HSE) which co-exists with a private health <lb/>system. The Office of the Chief Information Officer (CIO) has overall <lb/>responsibility for embedding technology within the health infra-<lb/>structure [24] and to date, EPRs have been implemented in some <lb/>individual private and public hospitals and the majority of general <lb/>practitioner (GP) offices (i.e., private primary care physicians often <lb/>with HSE contracts), as well as for specific cohorts of patients (e.g., <lb/>maternal and newborn, and epilepsy) [25]. However, many other <lb/>hospitals and HSE primary care (i.e., community) centres remain <lb/>largely paper-based. With an EHR in the pipeline [24,26], three na-<lb/>tional projects have been planned by eHealth Ireland which is led by <lb/>the Office of the CIO; Acute EHR, Community EHR and the Shared <lb/>and Integrated Care Record. Therefore, this is an opportune time for <lb/>policy-makers and other key stakeholders to review the learnings <lb/>from the implementations of health information technology (HIT) <lb/>both in Ireland and internationally. <lb/>However, a vast amount of literature is published on topics such as <lb/>EHRs which renders it difficult for policy-makers to remain up-to-date <lb/>[27,28], perhaps amplifying the &quot;know-do&quot; gap. Additionally, <lb/>healthcare is a complex and adaptive system which needs to be <lb/>recognized and acknowledged when attempting to replicate successes <lb/>in another context [29]. The EHR programme in Ireland is also <lb/>already underway and therefore, it&apos;s critical that knowledge is <lb/>generated to provide actionable and relevant key considerations in a <lb/>timely manner aligned with the policy and decision-making cycles <lb/>[30]. Therefore, the aim of this review is to identify and explore the <lb/>key factors which promote a successful EHR implementation across <lb/>healthcare settings, with active collaboration from key stakeholders <lb/>in the Irish context. <lb/>2. Methods <lb/>2.1. Design <lb/>A rapid umbrella review was conducted and guided by the World <lb/>Health Organisation (WHO) practical guide for Rapid Reviews to <lb/>Strengthen Health Policy and Systems [31]. Unlike a systematic review, an <lb/>umbrella review also known as a review of reviews, compiles evidence <lb/>from several research syntheses across different healthcare contexts and <lb/>stakeholder groups [32,33]. Active collaboration with an expert panel of <lb/>knowledge users facilitated the acceleration of the systematic review <lb/>process [30] and to facilitate uptake and use of these findings by plan-<lb/>ners and decision-makers, the synthesized findings were also presented <lb/>in a report format [34]. <lb/>2.2. Expert panel of knowledge users <lb/>A multi-disciplinary panel of experts and knowledge users (n = 10) <lb/>were engaged and involved throughout the review process to inform its <lb/>methodology, validate the generalizability and relevance of the review <lb/>findings [35], and ensure it reflects current thinking and is useful [27]. <lb/>The panel was convened in January 2019 by the Office of Nursing and <lb/>Midwifery Services Director (HSE) and comprised of those currently <lb/>involved in large HIT implementation projects across primary and sec-<lb/>ondary care at local and national levels in Ireland, as well as clinicians, <lb/>health service researchers and academic partners from healthcare and <lb/>health informatic backgrounds (Table 1). Five consultative in-person <lb/>group meetings and several individual meetings and email exchanges <lb/>within the group were conducted throughout the review process. <lb/>2.3. Research question and search strategy <lb/>An initial exploratory scope of the EHR literature in the PubMed <lb/>database was reviewed by the expert panel and the final research <lb/>question, methodology and search strategy were developed and agreed. <lb/>A large number of search terms to describe &quot;Electronic Health Record&quot;, <lb/>&quot;Implementation&quot; and &quot;Literature Review&quot; were identified from previous <lb/>systematic reviews [7,36-40], additional literature [17], medical sub-<lb/>ject heading and controlled vocabulary and via consultation with the <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Positions held by the members of the Expert Panel (n = 10). <lb/>National Clinical Information Officer for Nursing and Midwifery, HSE. <lb/>Professor of Health Informatics, UCD. <lb/>Group Chief Information Officer, Ireland East Hospital Group, HSE. <lb/>ICT Project Manager, Office of the Clinical Information Officer, HSE. <lb/>Senior Clinical Psychologist, National Rehabilitation Hospital, Dublin. <lb/>Clinical Health and Social Care Professional Lead in the Clinical Management System, <lb/>National Rehabilitation Hospital. <lb/>Associate Professor in Physiotherapy, UCD. <lb/>Business Manager, National MN-CMS Project Team. <lb/>Community EHR Senior Project Manager, HSE. <lb/>General Practitioner (GP). <lb/>National Co-ordinator of the GPIT Project at the Irish College of General Practitioners. <lb/>Senior Professional Officer, Northern Ireland Practice and Education Council for <lb/>Nursing and Midwifery. <lb/>EPR Project Manager, St. James&apos; Hospital, Dublin. <lb/>Engagement and Delivery Lead, Informatics Directorate, St. James&apos;s Hospital, Dublin. <lb/>Physiotherapist. <lb/>Note: Some members of the expert panel had more than one position. Health <lb/>Service Executive (HSE), government-funded organisation responsible for the <lb/>provision of health and personal social services; UCD, University College Dublin; <lb/>Ireland East Hospital Group, one of seven hospital groups in Ireland comprising <lb/>of 11 hospitals and four community healthcare organisations; ICT, Information <lb/>Communication Technology; Maternal and Newborn Clinical Management <lb/>System (MN-CMS), an EHR for all women and babies being cared for across <lb/>maternity and new born services in Ireland; GPIT, General Practice Information <lb/>Technology; EPR, Electronic Patient Record. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>expert panel and an experienced information technologist at the Health <lb/>Sciences Library, UCD [Appendix]. The search string was tailored to the <lb/>indexing language of each database and in March 2019, it was executed <lb/>across PubMed, CINAHL, Scopus, Embase, Web of Science, IEEE Xplore, <lb/>ACM Digital Library, ProQuest and Cochrane, with limitations of English <lb/>language and published since 2010. Grey literature including reports <lb/>and conference proceedings were also searched (international Health <lb/>Informatics Societies, the World Health Organization (WHO), European <lb/>e-health network, Kings Fund, Gartner and Lenus). Panellists also drew <lb/>on their expertise to identify any additional relevant sources [35]. <lb/>2.4. Identification of literature reviews <lb/>Identified articles were calibrated in the citation management soft-<lb/>ware Endnote version x9.2 and titles and abstracts were screened by one <lb/>researcher using the inclusion and exclusion criteria agreed with the <lb/>expert panel (Table 2). Full text articles were then accessed and screened <lb/>by the same researcher, with any doubts regarding inclusion or exclu-<lb/>sion discussed with the panel to overcome any risk of errors or in-<lb/>consistencies associated with using one reviewer [31]. In line with our <lb/>chosen rapid review methodology, a quality assessment of identified <lb/>reviews was not conducted. <lb/>2.5. Data extraction and synthesis <lb/>A standardized data extraction form was developed and included <lb/>authors, year of publication, study design, participants, healthcare <lb/>setting, included studies and findings related to factors impacting on the <lb/>implementation (i.e., themes and/or paragraphs as required). Following <lb/>data extraction, a qualitative content analysis of the factors impacting <lb/>on the EHR implementation was undertaken by the researcher [41]. <lb/>Using an iterative process, a list of codes representing the identified <lb/>factors from each of the literature reviews was formed [42]. The expert <lb/>panel reviewed these codes via an adapted nominal group technique, <lb/>which saw collated appraisals distributed amongst the panellists [43] to <lb/>assess whether they were comprehensive of the literature and their own <lb/>experiences, and to determine whether the findings could be transferred <lb/>to Irish contexts and settings [42]. Having reached a final consensus <lb/>regarding the factors for a successful EHR implementation, these factors <lb/>were further categorized into a theoretical framework [10] and resulted <lb/>in the generation of key considerations [42]. <lb/>3. Results <lb/>3.1. Characteristics of literature reviews <lb/>Of the 5,040 articles retrieved, 27 literature reviews were identified <lb/>which captured factors deemed important for the successful imple-<lb/>mentation of EHRs, as well as other HIT implementations (Fig. 1). <lb/>Fifteen were classified as systematic reviews, whilst the others were <lb/>umbrella reviews (n = 3), scoping reviews (n = 2), interpretive review <lb/>(n = 1), literature review with a meta-narrative (n = 1) and other non-<lb/>systematic literature reviews (n = 5). Overlap in included publications <lb/>existed across the literature reviews with 974 unique studies, literature <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Criteria for inclusion and exclusion of identified literature reviews. <lb/>Inclusion Criteria <lb/>Exclusion criteria <lb/>Literature review (i.e., provides a comprehensive <lb/>search and summary of previous research). <lb/>Primary studies and editorial <lb/>discussions. <lb/>Reviewed the implementation of an electronic <lb/>health record (EHR) and/or EHR component <lb/>including EMRs, EPRs and computer physician <lb/>order entries. <lb/>Not conducted within a <lb/>healthcare organisation. <lb/>Identified factors impacting on EHR <lb/>implementation including barriers, facilitators. <lb/>Conducted within a healthcare organisation. <lb/>Fig. 1. PRISMA Flow Diagram. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3 <lb/>Identified literature reviews which reviewed the key factors for a successful EHR implementation. <lb/>Author <lb/>(Year) <lb/>Design <lb/>Focus <lb/>Setting/ <lb/>participants <lb/>Studies <lb/>Inclusion <lb/>criteria <lb/>Identified factors <lb/>Ajami and <lb/>Bagheri-<lb/>tadi [12] <lb/>Non-<lb/>systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Barriers to EHR <lb/>adoption <lb/>Physicians in hospital <lb/>or community <lb/>20 <lb/>n/a <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Vendor trust &amp; <lb/>experience <lb/>Communication <lb/>among users <lb/>Training <lb/>Formal training <lb/>Support <lb/>Expert &amp; technical <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Time &amp; cost <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Workflow <lb/>disruption <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Computer literacy <lb/>&amp; skill <lb/>Ability to select &amp; <lb/>effectively install <lb/>system <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Lack of incentives <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>health ecosystem <lb/>Concerns about <lb/>data entry, patient <lb/>acceptance, <lb/>security &amp; privacy <lb/>Interfaces with <lb/>doctor-patient <lb/>relationship <lb/>Usability <lb/>Complexity <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Inadequate data <lb/>exchange <lb/>Interinstitutional <lb/>integration <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Access to computers <lb/>Reliability, speed &amp; <lb/>wireless <lb/>connectivity <lb/>Physical space <lb/>Ben-Zion <lb/>et al. <lb/>[52] <lb/>Literature <lb/>review and <lb/>prescriptive <lb/>analysis <lb/>Success factors for <lb/>EHR adoption <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>55 <lb/>2001-2013 <lb/>English <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Firm strategy <lb/>Scope &amp; project <lb/>controls <lb/>Interactions across <lb/>communities <lb/>Motivation to <lb/>collaborate <lb/>Culture change <lb/>Knowledge <lb/>management <lb/>Process change <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>IT alignment with <lb/>firm strategy <lb/>Support <lb/>Executive <lb/>management <lb/>Process change <lb/>Training <lb/>Process change <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>IT resources &amp; cost <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Process change <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Economic <lb/>competitiveness <lb/>Motivation to <lb/>collaborate <lb/>Usability <lb/>Accessibility &amp; <lb/>usability <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>IT integration with <lb/>external networks <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>IT innovation <lb/>System Architecture <lb/>&amp; Infrastructure <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Shared language &amp; <lb/>narratives <lb/>IT integration with <lb/>external networks <lb/>Boonstra <lb/>et al. <lb/>[36] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>EHR <lb/>implementation <lb/>lessons <lb/>Project team, doctors, <lb/>nurses, technical &amp; <lb/>clerical personnel, <lb/>administrators, IT <lb/>personnel, <lb/>psychiatrists, directors, <lb/>CEOs, CIOs, managers, <lb/>vendors, healthcare <lb/>practitioners, <lb/>pharmacists in <lb/>hospitals <lb/>21 <lb/>Up until <lb/>2013 <lb/>English <lb/>Peer-<lb/>reviewed <lb/>Empirical <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Large not-for-profit <lb/>teaching hospital <lb/>Readiness for <lb/>change <lb/>Mature vendor <lb/>Culture supporting <lb/>collaboration &amp; <lb/>teamwork <lb/>Little bureaucracy <lb/>&amp; considerable <lb/>flexibility <lb/>Comprehensive <lb/>implementation <lb/>strategy <lb/>Interdisciplinary <lb/>implementation <lb/>group <lb/>Champions among <lb/>clinical staff <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>Participation of <lb/>clinical staff <lb/>Training <lb/>Support <lb/>Real-time support <lb/>Management <lb/>support <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Financial <lb/>capabilities <lb/>Sufficient number <lb/>of staff <lb/>Workflows <lb/>System fitting <lb/>hospital&apos;s needs <lb/>Creating a fit by <lb/>adapting <lb/>technology &amp; work <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Previous <lb/>experience of HIT <lb/>Resistance of <lb/>clinical staff <lb/>Perceived changes <lb/>to healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Ensuring care <lb/>activities <lb/>Usability <lb/>User-friendly <lb/>software <lb/>Adequate <lb/>safeguards <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Hardware <lb/>System reliability <lb/>(speed, availability <lb/>&amp; lack of failures) <lb/>Adaptability <lb/>Vendor willing to <lb/>adapt <lb/>Boonstra <lb/>et al. <lb/>[53] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Barriers to <lb/>acceptance of EMRs <lb/>Physicians in any <lb/>healthcare <lb/>organisations <lb/>22 <lb/>1998-2009 <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Vendor uncertainty <lb/>Lack of <lb/>participation <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Start-up &amp; ongoing <lb/>costs <lb/>Time to select, <lb/>learn &amp; convert <lb/>patient records <lb/>Interference with <lb/>doctor-patient <lb/>relationship <lb/>Privacy or security <lb/>concerns <lb/>Usability <lb/>(continued on next page) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3 (continued ) <lb/>Author <lb/>(Year) <lb/>Design <lb/>Focus <lb/>Setting/ <lb/>participants <lb/>Studies <lb/>Inclusion <lb/>criteria <lb/>Identified factors <lb/>Lack of leadership <lb/>Organizational size <lb/>&amp; type <lb/>Change Process <lb/>Training <lb/>Technical training <lb/>Support <lb/>Technical support <lb/>External party <lb/>support <lb/>Support from <lb/>organizational <lb/>culture, other <lb/>colleagues &amp; <lb/>management level <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Lack computer <lb/>skills <lb/>Need for control <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Return on <lb/>investment <lb/>More time per <lb/>patient <lb/>Lack of belief in <lb/>EMRs <lb/>Lack of incentives <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Time required to <lb/>enter data <lb/>Complexity <lb/>Limitations <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Interconnectivity/ <lb/>standardization <lb/>Adaptability <lb/>Lack of <lb/>customizability <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Reliability <lb/>Computers/ <lb/>hardware <lb/>Castillo <lb/>et al. 11 <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>EHR adoption <lb/>Physicians in inpatients <lb/>&amp; <lb/>outpatients in <lb/>hospitals &amp; <lb/>primary care <lb/>68 <lb/>1985-2010 <lb/>English <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Communication <lb/>among users <lb/>Support <lb/>Technical &amp; expert <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Workflow impact <lb/>Perceived benefits <lb/>and incentives <lb/>User attitude <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Cresswell <lb/>and <lb/>Sheikh <lb/>[54] <lb/>Interpretive <lb/>review <lb/>Organisational <lb/>barriers to HIT <lb/>implementation <lb/>and adoption <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>13 <lb/>1997-2010 <lb/>Systematic <lb/>reviews <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Open <lb/>communication <lb/>channels <lb/>Senior leadership &amp; <lb/>&quot;champion&quot; <lb/>Strong <lb/>organizational <lb/>leadership &amp; <lb/>management <lb/>Avoidance of <lb/>&quot;scope creep&quot; <lb/>Appropriate <lb/>implementation <lb/>approach <lb/>Plan for potentially <lb/>extreme <lb/>contingencies <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>On-going <lb/>involvement of key <lb/>stakeholders <lb/>Support <lb/>Lead professional <lb/>support <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Costs &amp; additional <lb/>time available <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Fits in with <lb/>existing <lb/>organizational <lb/>processes <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>IT literacy &amp; <lb/>general <lb/>competencies of <lb/>users <lb/>Personal &amp; peer <lb/>attitudes <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Offers relative <lb/>advantages over <lb/>existing practices <lb/>Useful <lb/>Early demonstrable <lb/>benefits <lb/>Usability <lb/>Perceived ease of <lb/>use <lb/>Supports inter-<lb/>professional roles <lb/>and working <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Interoperable with <lb/>existing technology <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>considerations <lb/>Adaptability <lb/>Testing <lb/>Field testing of early <lb/>prototypes <lb/>De Grood <lb/>et al. <lb/>[55] <lb/>Scoping <lb/>review <lb/>Barriers to and <lb/>opportunities for e-<lb/>health technology <lb/>adoption <lb/>Physicians in any <lb/>healthcare <lb/>organisations <lb/>74 <lb/>1995-2015 <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Ownership &amp; size of <lb/>practice <lb/>Training <lb/>Support <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Cost <lb/>Lack of time &amp; <lb/>workload <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Pre-analysis of <lb/>data <lb/>Proof of utility <lb/>Productivity <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Privacy &amp; security <lb/>concerns <lb/>Liability issues <lb/>Patient and <lb/>physician <lb/>interaction <lb/>Threatened clinical <lb/>autonomy <lb/>Usability <lb/>Design <lb/>Fritz et al. <lb/>[48] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Success criteria for <lb/>EMR <lb/>implementation <lb/>Hospital or community <lb/>in low resource <lb/>countries <lb/>47 <lb/>English <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Political <lb/>Organizational <lb/>Training <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Financial <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Ethical <lb/>Usability <lb/>Functionality <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Technical <lb/>Gagnon <lb/>et al. <lb/>[44] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Barriers and <lb/>facilitators to <lb/>implementing <lb/>Physicians, nurses, <lb/>other HCPs, admin, <lb/>34 <lb/>Empirical <lb/>Design <lb/>e-<lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Work process <lb/>Skills and <lb/>Perceived changes <lb/>to healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>(continued on next page) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3 (continued ) <lb/>Author <lb/>(Year) <lb/>Design <lb/>Focus <lb/>Setting/ <lb/>participants <lb/>Studies <lb/>Inclusion <lb/>criteria <lb/>Identified factors <lb/>electronic <lb/>prescription <lb/>management in <lb/>primary care <lb/>prescribing <lb/>Link with <lb/>primary <lb/>care <lb/>Other <lb/>professionals&apos; <lb/>performance <lb/>Developer &amp; vendor <lb/>Implementation <lb/>strategies <lb/>Characteristics of <lb/>the health structure <lb/>Influence of <lb/>leadership <lb/>Macro <lb/>organisational <lb/>elements <lb/>Professional <lb/>interaction <lb/>Support <lb/>Support &amp; <lb/>promotion by <lb/>colleagues <lb/>Organisational <lb/>support <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Time issues <lb/>Resources <lb/>Cost issues <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Agreement with e-<lb/>prescribing <lb/>Familiarity with <lb/>technology <lb/>Patients&apos; attitudes <lb/>&amp; preferences <lb/>Self-efficacy <lb/>Socio-<lb/>demographic <lb/>characteristic <lb/>Confidence in e-<lb/>prescribing <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Perceived <lb/>usefulness <lb/>Impact on clinical <lb/>uncertainty <lb/>Risk-benefit <lb/>equation <lb/>Outcome <lb/>expectancy <lb/>Time saving <lb/>Privacy and security <lb/>concerns <lb/>Patient/clinician <lb/>interaction <lb/>Autonomy <lb/>Impact on <lb/>professional <lb/>security <lb/>Usability <lb/>Design <lb/>Content appropriate <lb/>&amp; satisfactory <lb/>Generic substitution <lb/>options <lb/>Data accuracy &amp; <lb/>legibility <lb/>Ease of use <lb/>Efficiency <lb/>Patient security <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>System reliability or <lb/>dependability <lb/>Gesulga <lb/>et al. <lb/>[56] <lb/>Structured <lb/>literature <lb/>review <lb/>Barriers to the <lb/>implementation of <lb/>adoption of EHR or <lb/>EMR readiness <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>38 <lb/>English <lb/>Until July <lb/>2016 <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Change in culture <lb/>Lack of project <lb/>planning <lb/>Implementation <lb/>issues <lb/>Number of vendors <lb/>Competitiveness <lb/>External factors <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>Involvement in <lb/>design &amp; <lb/>implementation <lb/>Training <lb/>Lack of education &amp; <lb/>training <lb/>Support <lb/>Administrative &amp; <lb/>policy support <lb/>Upgrading &amp; <lb/>maintaining the <lb/>system <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Lack of technical <lb/>expertise <lb/>Inadequate staff <lb/>Implementation, <lb/>maintenance, <lb/>initial, equipment <lb/>&amp; training cost <lb/>Lack of available <lb/>funding <lb/>Increase of nurses <lb/>&amp; physician&apos;s <lb/>workload <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Communication <lb/>among users on <lb/>data entry <lb/>Reduces <lb/>productivity &amp; <lb/>disturbs workflow <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>User resistance <lb/>Lack of computer <lb/>skills <lb/>Provider or <lb/>patients age <lb/>Illiteracy <lb/>Physicians&apos; <lb/>experience with <lb/>poor products <lb/>Lack of capacity <lb/>Unrealistic <lb/>expectation about <lb/>ease of installation <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Lack of awareness <lb/>of EHR/EMR &amp; <lb/>importance <lb/>Concern that <lb/>system will <lb/>become obsolete <lb/>Concern on return <lb/>on investment <lb/>Waiting to see if <lb/>subsidies develop <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Affects physician-<lb/>patient interaction <lb/>Concerns about <lb/>privacy &amp; <lb/>confidentiality <lb/>Physicians&apos; legal <lb/>liability <lb/>Usability <lb/>User access <lb/>limitation <lb/>Data accuracy &amp; <lb/>quality <lb/>Capacity to use real-<lb/>time data <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Centralized <lb/>healthcare database <lb/>National health <lb/>information <lb/>network <lb/>Data Security <lb/>Hardware <lb/>functionality issues <lb/>Internet <lb/>connectivity <lb/>Network <lb/>communication <lb/>infrastructure <lb/>Network speed <lb/>Lack of IT facilities <lb/>&amp; equipment <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Lack of health <lb/>information data <lb/>standards <lb/>Health terminology <lb/>&amp; classification <lb/>Risk of new <lb/>regulatory <lb/>requirements <lb/>Gill et al. <lb/>[57] <lb/>Scoping <lb/>review <lb/>Adoption of EHRs <lb/>or EMRs <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>39 <lb/>Case <lb/>studies <lb/>English <lb/>2010-2015 <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>Use of stakeholders <lb/>throughout the <lb/>process <lb/>Training <lb/>Sufficient time <lb/>spent on training <lb/>clinicians <lb/>Support <lb/>Executive <lb/>Usability <lb/>System designed &amp; <lb/>built as per <lb/>requirements <lb/>Kruse et al. <lb/>[58] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Facilitators &amp; <lb/>barriers to the <lb/>Public health <lb/>55 <lb/>2012-2017 <lb/>English <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>Disease <lb/>management <lb/>Complex <lb/>Ease of use <lb/>(continued on next page) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3 (continued ) <lb/>Author <lb/>(Year) <lb/>Design <lb/>Focus <lb/>Setting/ <lb/>participants <lb/>Studies <lb/>Inclusion <lb/>criteria <lb/>Identified factors <lb/>adoption of an EHR <lb/>for population <lb/>health <lb/>culture <lb/>Communication <lb/>Support <lb/>Limited staff <lb/>support <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Cost <lb/>Financial assistance <lb/>Productivity loss <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Resistance to <lb/>change <lb/>Perceived benefits <lb/>and incentives <lb/>Critical thinking/ <lb/>treatment <lb/>decisions <lb/>Quality <lb/>Surveillance <lb/>Preventative care <lb/>Decision support <lb/>Health outcomes <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Privacy concerns <lb/>Usability <lb/>Accessibility/ <lb/>utilization <lb/>Satisfaction <lb/>Data management / <lb/>Missing data &amp; <lb/>errors <lb/>Efficiency <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>No standards <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Current technology <lb/>Kruse et al. <lb/>[51] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Barriers to EHR <lb/>adoption <lb/>Any patient care facility <lb/>in the USA <lb/>21 <lb/>2012-2016 <lb/>English <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Need <lb/>organizational <lb/>cultural change <lb/>Facility location <lb/>Competitiveness <lb/>Consensus within <lb/>the practice <lb/>External factors <lb/>Eligibility criteria <lb/>Training <lb/>Support <lb/>Technical support <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Initial &amp; <lb/>maintenance/ <lb/>ongoing costs <lb/>Insufficient time <lb/>Effort needed to <lb/>select system <lb/>Staff shortages <lb/>Productivity loss <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Workflow <lb/>challenges <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Resistance to <lb/>changing work <lb/>habits <lb/>Physician attitude <lb/>Race &amp; income <lb/>disparities <lb/>Provider or patient <lb/>age <lb/>User acceptance <lb/>IMGs less likely to <lb/>adopt <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Financial <lb/>incentives <lb/>Return on <lb/>investment <lb/>Perceived <lb/>usefulness <lb/>Penalties <lb/>Medical errors <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Privacy concerns <lb/>Physician <lb/>autonomy <lb/>Usability <lb/>Technical concerns <lb/>Inability to easily <lb/>input historic <lb/>medical record data <lb/>Complexity of <lb/>system <lb/>Limitations of <lb/>system <lb/>Missing data <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Degree of <lb/>integration <lb/>Adaptability <lb/>Agility to make <lb/>changes <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Technical <lb/>infrastructure <lb/>Upgrades <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Clarity of Federal <lb/>and State policies <lb/>Kruse et al. <lb/>[50] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Barriers &amp; <lb/>facilitators to EHR <lb/>adoption <lb/>Any patient care facility <lb/>in the USA <lb/>36 (31 <lb/>unique) <lb/>2012-2015 <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Facility location <lb/>Implementation <lb/>issues <lb/>External factors <lb/>Organizational <lb/>cultural change <lb/>Hospital size <lb/>Project planning <lb/>Alignment with <lb/>strategy <lb/>Competitiveness <lb/>Communication <lb/>Training <lb/>Support <lb/>Maintenance <lb/>Executive <lb/>management <lb/>support <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Cost <lb/>Time-consuming <lb/>Lack of tech <lb/>assistance <lb/>Staff shortages/ <lb/>overworked <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>User/patient <lb/>resistance <lb/>Lack of tech <lb/>experience <lb/>Provider or patient <lb/>age <lb/>Race &amp; income <lb/>disparities <lb/>IMGs less likely to <lb/>adapt <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>User perception/ <lb/>perceived lack of <lb/>usefulness <lb/>Incentives <lb/>Long run cost <lb/>savings <lb/>Error reduction <lb/>Improved <lb/>Usability <lb/>Transition of data <lb/>Missing data <lb/>Access to patient <lb/>data <lb/>Efficiency <lb/>Privacy &amp; security <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Ability to transfer <lb/>information <lb/>Continuity of care <lb/>document <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Upgrades <lb/>Lack of <lb/>infrastructure &amp; <lb/>space for systems <lb/>Adaptability <lb/>Lack of agility to <lb/>make changes <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Standard protocols <lb/>for data exchange <lb/>(continued on next page) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3 (continued ) <lb/>Author <lb/>(Year) <lb/>Design <lb/>Focus <lb/>Setting/ <lb/>participants <lb/>Studies <lb/>Inclusion <lb/>criteria <lb/>Identified factors <lb/>population health <lb/>Medical error <lb/>Kruse et al. <lb/>[46] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Adoption factors for <lb/>EHR introduction <lb/>LTC <lb/>22 <lb/>2009-2014 <lb/>English <lb/>USA-based <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Project planning <lb/>Facility <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Implementation <lb/>issues <lb/>Cultural change <lb/>External factors <lb/>Training <lb/>Training <lb/>Implementation <lb/>issues <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Cost <lb/>Staff retention <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Error reduction <lb/>Cost savings <lb/>Health outcomes <lb/>User perceptions <lb/>Time savings <lb/>Perceived changes <lb/>to the healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Usability <lb/>Implementation <lb/>issues <lb/>Clinical and <lb/>administrative <lb/>efficiency <lb/>Security <lb/>Access &amp; transfer to <lb/>information <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Implementation <lb/>issues <lb/>Kruse et al. <lb/>[59] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Internal <lb/>organizational and <lb/>external <lb/>environmental <lb/>factors associated <lb/>with adoption of <lb/>HIT <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>17 <lb/>1993-2013 <lb/>English <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Competitiveness <lb/>Location &amp; size <lb/>Interdependence <lb/>Ownership <lb/>Strategic alliances <lb/>Communication <lb/>among users <lb/>Physician <lb/>arrangements <lb/>Teaching status <lb/>Support <lb/>Technical &amp; expert <lb/>Unity of effort <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Payers <lb/>Capital <lb/>expenditure <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Workflow impact <lb/>Complexity of care <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Patients &amp; users <lb/>User attitude <lb/>toward information <lb/>Computer anxiety <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Lluch [19] <lb/>Literature <lb/>review <lb/>Organisational <lb/>barriers to HIT <lb/>implementation <lb/>OECD and EFTA <lb/>countries <lb/>79 <lb/>2007-2010 <lb/>English <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Hierarchy <lb/>Teamwork &amp; <lb/>cooperation <lb/>Centre of gravity <lb/>and autonomy <lb/>Training <lb/>Training, IT/HIT <lb/>skills <lb/>Support <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Changes in work <lb/>processes &amp; <lb/>routines <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Training, IT/HIT <lb/>skills <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Incentives <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Autonomy <lb/>Face-to-face <lb/>interaction versus <lb/>new ways of <lb/>working <lb/>Trust &amp; liability <lb/>Accountability to <lb/>employer &amp; policy <lb/>makers <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Information &amp; <lb/>decision processes <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Lack of legal <lb/>framework <lb/>Mair et al. <lb/>[60] <lb/>Explanatory <lb/>systematic <lb/>review of <lb/>reviews <lb/>Factors that <lb/>promote or inhibit <lb/>e-health technology <lb/>implementation <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>37 <lb/>Literature <lb/>reviews <lb/>1990-2009 <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Coherence <lb/>Cognitive <lb/>participation <lb/>Addressing <lb/>organizational <lb/>issues <lb/>Reflexive <lb/>monitoring <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>Cognitive <lb/>participation <lb/>Training <lb/>Roles, <lb/>responsibilities &amp; <lb/>training <lb/>Support <lb/>Addressing <lb/>organizational <lb/>issues <lb/>Roles, <lb/>responsibilities &amp; <lb/>training <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Addressing <lb/>organizational <lb/>issues <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Cognitive <lb/>participation <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Cognitive <lb/>participation <lb/>Confidence and <lb/>accountability <lb/>Reflexive <lb/>monitoring <lb/>Perceived changes <lb/>to the healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Effects on <lb/>healthcare tasks <lb/>Confidence and <lb/>accountability <lb/>Usability <lb/>Effects on <lb/>healthcare tasks <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Addressing <lb/>organizational <lb/>issues <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Addressing <lb/>organizational <lb/>issues <lb/>McGinn <lb/>et al. <lb/>[49] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>EHR <lb/>implementation <lb/>barriers and <lb/>facilitators <lb/>Physicians, HCPs, <lb/>pharmacists, admin, <lb/>midwives, social <lb/>workers, patients in <lb/>health services <lb/>comparable to Canada <lb/>60 <lb/>1999-2009 <lb/>Empirical <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Lack of time &amp; <lb/>workload <lb/>Cost issues <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Familiarity &amp; <lb/>Productivity <lb/>Motivation to use <lb/>EHR <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Privacy &amp; security <lb/>concerns <lb/>Usability <lb/>Perceived ease of <lb/>use <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>(continued on next page) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3 (continued ) <lb/>Author <lb/>(Year) <lb/>Design <lb/>Focus <lb/>Setting/ <lb/>participants <lb/>Studies <lb/>Inclusion <lb/>criteria <lb/>Identified factors <lb/>ability with EHR <lb/>Perceived benefits <lb/>and incentives <lb/>Patient &amp; health <lb/>professional <lb/>interaction <lb/>Design or technical <lb/>concerns <lb/>Design or technical <lb/>concerns <lb/>Nguyen <lb/>et al. [7] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>EHR impact and <lb/>issues <lb/>Clinicians, patients, <lb/>doctors, nurses, <lb/>management, <lb/>administration, <lb/>organizations &amp; IT staff <lb/>across primary, <lb/>secondary, LTC, <lb/>ambulatory &amp; <lb/>community care <lb/>98 <lb/>2001-2011 <lb/>English <lb/>Empirical <lb/>Peer <lb/>-reviewed <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Organizational <lb/>Adoption rate <lb/>Systems <lb/>development <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>Systems <lb/>development <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Training <lb/>Service quality <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Support <lb/>Service quality <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Organizational <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Changes to <lb/>workflow <lb/>Skills and <lb/>attitudes <lb/>Attitudes <lb/>Adoption rate <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Attitude <lb/>Quality and safety <lb/>of care <lb/>Administrative <lb/>efficiency &amp; cost <lb/>reduction <lb/>Changes to <lb/>workload &amp; <lb/>productivity <lb/>Clinical <lb/>documentation <lb/>practice &amp; quality <lb/>Information <lb/>quality <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Clinician-patient <lb/>relationships <lb/>Systems quality <lb/>Usability <lb/>Systems quality <lb/>Information quality <lb/>Adoption rate <lb/>User satisfaction &amp; <lb/>use <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Systems quality <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Service quality <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Systems <lb/>development <lb/>Testing <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Nguyen <lb/>et al. [7] <lb/>Literature <lb/>review <lb/>Organisational <lb/>success factors for <lb/>HIT <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>36 <lb/>English <lb/>Peer-<lb/>reviewed <lb/>2001-2013 <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Champion <lb/>Openness of the <lb/>organization to <lb/>change &amp; <lb/>innovation <lb/>Collaboration with <lb/>vendors <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>End-user <lb/>participation <lb/>Collaboration <lb/>among <lb/>administration, IT <lb/>&amp; clinical functions <lb/>Training <lb/>Support <lb/>Technical support <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Sufficient <lb/>resources <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Collaboration <lb/>among <lb/>administration, IT, <lb/>&amp; clinical <lb/>functions <lb/>Perceived benefits <lb/>and incentives <lb/>Incentives <lb/>Provision of <lb/>information <lb/>System, service &amp; <lb/>information quality <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>quality <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Regulation <lb/>O&apos;Donnell <lb/>et al. <lb/>[13] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review and <lb/>evidence <lb/>synthesis <lb/>EMR adoption <lb/>Physicians in primary <lb/>care <lb/>33 <lb/>1996-2017 <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Organization <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Training <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Support <lb/>Quality of <lb/>information, system <lb/>&amp; service <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Funding &amp; <lb/>incentives <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Use &amp; user <lb/>satisfaction <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>People <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Net benefits in <lb/>terms of care <lb/>quality, <lb/>productivity &amp; <lb/>access <lb/>Funding &amp; <lb/>incentives <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Use &amp; user <lb/>satisfaction <lb/>Usability <lb/>Quality of <lb/>information, system <lb/>&amp; service <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Quality of <lb/>information, system <lb/>&amp; service <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Quality of <lb/>information, system <lb/>&amp; service <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>Legislation, policy <lb/>&amp;governance <lb/>119 <lb/>2004-2009 <lb/>(continued on next page) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3 (continued ) <lb/>Author <lb/>(Year) <lb/>Design <lb/>Focus <lb/>Setting/ <lb/>participants <lb/>Studies <lb/>Inclusion <lb/>criteria <lb/>Identified factors <lb/>Police et al. <lb/>[45] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>Benefits and <lb/>barriers to HIT <lb/>implementation <lb/>Physicians in primary <lb/>care <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Practice-based <lb/>predictors &amp; <lb/>barriers <lb/>External policies &amp; <lb/>organizational <lb/>barriers <lb/>Impact of practice <lb/>culture <lb/>Training <lb/>Educational <lb/>barriers <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Financial barriers <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Staff-related <lb/>barriers <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Technological <lb/>barriers <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Technological <lb/>barriers <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Technological <lb/>barriers <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>External policies &amp; <lb/>organizational <lb/>barriers <lb/>Technological <lb/>barriers <lb/>Ratwani <lb/>et al. <lb/>[37] <lb/>Systematic <lb/>review <lb/>EHR safety and <lb/>usability challenges <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>55 <lb/>2010-2016 <lb/>English <lb/>Peer-<lb/>reviewed <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Governance &amp; <lb/>consensus building <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>Governance &amp; <lb/>consensus building <lb/>Training <lb/>Support <lb/>Training <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Cost and resources <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Clinical workflow <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Training <lb/>Usability <lb/>Customization <lb/>Usability testing <lb/>Adaptability <lb/>Customization <lb/>Testing <lb/>Risk assessment <lb/>Usability testing <lb/>Ross et al. <lb/>[62] <lb/>Umbrella <lb/>review <lb/>Implementation of <lb/>e-health <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>44 <lb/>2009-2014 <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Implementation <lb/>climate <lb/>Planning <lb/>Engaging <lb/>Reflecting &amp; <lb/>evaluating <lb/>Leadership <lb/>engagement <lb/>Champions <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>Key stakeholders <lb/>Support <lb/>Training <lb/>Access to <lb/>knowledge &amp; <lb/>information <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Cost <lb/>Available <lb/>resources <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Compatibility <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Knowledge &amp; <lb/>beliefs <lb/>Other personal <lb/>attributes <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Incentives <lb/>Reflecting and <lb/>evaluating <lb/>Perceived changes <lb/>to the healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Knowledge &amp; <lb/>beliefs <lb/>Usability <lb/>Complexity <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Complexity <lb/>Regulations, <lb/>standards and <lb/>policies <lb/>External policy <lb/>Adaptability <lb/>Sligo et al. <lb/>[10] <lb/>Literature <lb/>review with a <lb/>meta-<lb/>narrative <lb/>Large scale HIT <lb/>planning, <lb/>implementation <lb/>and evaluation <lb/>No restriction on <lb/>healthcare setting or <lb/>participants identified <lb/>382 <lb/>n/a <lb/>Governance, <lb/>leadership and <lb/>culture <lb/>Structural/ <lb/>contextual/ <lb/>organizational <lb/>factors <lb/>Technical factors <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>Structural/ <lb/>contextual/ <lb/>organizational <lb/>factors <lb/>Technical factors <lb/>Training <lb/>Human factors <lb/>Support <lb/>Structural/ <lb/>contextual/ <lb/>organizational <lb/>factors <lb/>Resourcing <lb/>Structural/ <lb/>contextual/ <lb/>organizational <lb/>factors <lb/>Human factors <lb/>Workflows <lb/>Human factors <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Human factors <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Technical factors <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Human Factors <lb/>Usability <lb/>Technical factors <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Technical factors <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Technical factors <lb/>Adaptability <lb/>Technical factors <lb/>Testing <lb/>Technical factors <lb/>Strudwick <lb/>and <lb/>Eyasu <lb/>[47] <lb/>Literature <lb/>review <lb/>Experiences with <lb/>EHR <lb/>implementation <lb/>Nurses in mental health <lb/>settings <lb/>7 <lb/>English <lb/>End-user <lb/>involvement <lb/>Skills and <lb/>characteristics <lb/>Characteristics of <lb/>nurses <lb/>Experience and <lb/>Perceived <lb/>benefits and <lb/>incentives <lb/>Perceived benefits <lb/>Perceived <lb/>changes to the <lb/>healthcare <lb/>Usability <lb/>Infrastructure <lb/>Physical space <lb/>Lack of computers <lb/>(continued on next page) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>reviews, reports, books and guidelines identified. Perspectives of a va-<lb/>riety of stakeholders were captured in these reviews including GPs (or <lb/>primary care physicians), other doctors, nurses, health and social care <lb/>professionals (HCPs), patients, policymakers, vendors and IT consultants <lb/>(Table 3). Although many literature reviews encompassed studies from a <lb/>variety of healthcare settings, others were specific to primary care (i.e., <lb/>community) [13,44,45], long term care [46] and mental health settings <lb/>[47] or within specific countries or groups of countries [19,48-51]. <lb/>3.2. Synthesized findings <lb/>Fifteen common factors were identified and classified as organiza-<lb/>tional, human and technological. Each of these factors are discussed in <lb/>detail below as well as how they interact within different contexts. <lb/>3.2.1. Organizational factors <lb/>Factors relating to the processes by which the EHR was introduced <lb/>and incorporated into routine care were categorized as organizational <lb/>[54]. Whilst each of the six factors were important across all contexts, <lb/>the size and type of organization impacted on how each triggered suc-<lb/>cess during the EHR implementation [46,53,61]. <lb/>3.2.1.1. Governance, leadership and culture. The governance of the EHR <lb/>implementation [13,19,37], as well as leaders [7,10,36,44,48,52-54,62, <lb/>63] and organizational culture, were identified as paramount in <lb/>ensuring a successful EHR system [7,10,13,36,45,50-53,56,59,62]. <lb/>Whilst top-down, middle-out and bottom-up governance structures have <lb/>been utilised, ongoing political willingness, national policies and some <lb/>independence at an individual organizational level regarding EHR pro-<lb/>curement, development and design, were recommended to promote <lb/>engagement, usability and interoperability [13,48,51,62]. It was also <lb/>important that executive leaders such as CIOs and project management <lb/>teams establish good and trusting relationships with vendors and <lb/>consulting firms [12,44,52,56,63], and designed the implementation <lb/>strategy with clear measurable objectives [10,50,52], a fitting imple-<lb/>mentation process (e.g., big-bang or phased) [44,46,51,58], and clear <lb/>roles and divisions of labour [10,60]. A shift away from the dominance <lb/>of top and middle management has also been recommended [10,19,36], <lb/>with the appointment of local leaders or champions, and supporting of <lb/>internal and external communication and collaboration [10,11,19,52, <lb/>59], innovation and continual improvement [52], and patient-centred <lb/>care [19]. This also helps to create a favourable [10,36,44,63] and <lb/>flexible [52] culture. <lb/>3.2.1.2. End-user involvement. During each stage of the EHR imple-<lb/>mentation process, end-user involvement was highlighted as important <lb/>[7,10,37,47,48,52,54,56,57,60,62,63], as it helps to ensure that the <lb/>EHR meets end-users&apos; needs and workflows, as well as promoting a sense <lb/>of ownership [37] and acceptance amongst staff [10,37,63]. Engaging <lb/>end-users from each stakeholder group was recommended [36], and this <lb/>has often been done in the form of appointing champions. These leaders <lb/>should be respected amongst their colleagues as well as having the <lb/>relevant knowledge to act as a bridge between the end-users and IT staff <lb/>[60,62,63]. However, champions may sometimes need to be shared be-<lb/>tween organizations [10]. <lb/>3.2.1.3. Training. Basic computer and EHR-specific training were <lb/>identified as key to a successful EHR implementation [7,10,12,13,19,36, <lb/>37,45,46,48,50-53,56,57,60,61,63]. However, the effectiveness and <lb/>resource-efficiency of training depended on the appropriateness of the <lb/>appointed trainers, training content, timing of training (i.e., as close to <lb/>Go Live as possible [36]) and methods of training e.g., classroom based <lb/>versus eLearning [57]. EHR training was also recommended on an <lb/>ongoing basis for new staff, as well as existing staff to optimize their use <lb/>of the system [37,53]. <lb/>3.2.1.4. Support. Expert, technical, executive and external support have <lb/>been critical to successful EHR implementations [7,10-13,19,36,37,44, <lb/>50-53,56-58,60-63]. Expert or peer support, often referred to as <lb/>super-users, reportedly helped end-users to optimize their use of the EHR <lb/>[7,11,12,36,53], whereas technical support staff helped solve IT issues <lb/>[51,62]. During Go Live (often first 3-4 weeks [37]), technical and peer <lb/>support should be available 24/7 seven days a week in hospitals [12,36]. <lb/>However, this may not be feasible or required in primary care centres <lb/>but channels to obtain support during working hours remain important. <lb/>Other crucial support comes from an executive or policy level [19,50,52, <lb/>53,56,57,60,63] and professional networks or external parties [19,53]. <lb/>Although maintenance support for servers and networks was not as <lb/>evidenced in the identified literature [50], the expert panel also deemed <lb/>this as important. <lb/>3.2.1.5. Resourcing. The availability of resources in terms of finance, <lb/>skilled workforce and time was also important [7,10,12,13,36,37, <lb/>44-46,48,49,51-54,56,59-63]. Financial resourcing was often high-<lb/>lighted as a barrier especially by primary care doctors [12,13] and those <lb/>in lower income countries [48], and scope creep of the budget was a <lb/>common occurrence for larger hospitals [10,52,54]. Therefore, a cost <lb/>analysis which encompasses infrastructure, personnel, maintenance and <lb/>ongoing optimization was critical [36,62]. Having a skilled workforce <lb/>in-house who understand the clinical workflows was also recommended <lb/>[53,61] as it can reduce dependence on and cost of vendors [12,36]. <lb/>However, this may not be feasible for smaller organizations, and larger <lb/>organizations also reportedly had issues with IT staff retention [10,13, <lb/>36,48,51]. Adequate time for end-user involvement and habituation to <lb/>the EHR was also vital [7,10,12] to ensure organizational readiness [7, <lb/>13,51,53]. <lb/>3.2.1.6. Workflows. Inability of the EHR system to meet the workflows <lb/>of end-users and organizations was commonly cited as negatively <lb/>impacting on success [7,10-12,36,37,51,52,54,56,62,63], including <lb/>end-user efficiency, productivity, satisfaction and acceptance of the EHR <lb/>[7,11,63]. Although replicating existing paper-based practices may <lb/>minimize disruptions for end-users [7,13,19,62], re-engineering of <lb/>workflows during digitization to make them safer and more efficient was <lb/>recommended [19,62,63]. <lb/>3.2.2. Human factors <lb/>Ability of healthcare organizations to successfully adopt an EHR <lb/>system was largely determined by the individual end-users [10,54], and <lb/>three overarching human factors were identified. <lb/>Table 3 (continued ) <lb/>Author <lb/>(Year) <lb/>Design <lb/>Focus <lb/>Setting/ <lb/>participants <lb/>Studies <lb/>Inclusion <lb/>criteria <lb/>Identified factors <lb/>interest in <lb/>computers <lb/>ecosystem <lb/>Privacy and <lb/>confidentiality <lb/>concerns <lb/>Note: EHR, Electronic health record; LTC, long-term care; HIT, Health Information Technology; OECD, Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development; <lb/>EFTA, European Free Trade Association; HCPs, Health and Social Care Professionals. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.2.2.1. Skills and characteristics. IT skills as well as personal charac-<lb/>teristics of individuals impacted on the success of an EHR implementa-<lb/>tion [10,12,50,51,53,56,58,60,62,13,19,36,37,44,47-49]. Assessing <lb/>computer literacy of end-users enabled provision of basic computer <lb/>training to those requiring it, prior to effective EHR training [36,48]. <lb/>Whilst the research assessing the impact of age, gender and clinical <lb/>experience on acceptance of the EHR reported in the identified reviews <lb/>was inconclusive, personal traits such as being open-to-change and a <lb/>problem-solver appeared to contribute to success [56,62]. However, <lb/>resistance to embracing the EHR could also be attributed to unusable <lb/>technology [10,51]. <lb/>3.2.2.2. Perceived benefits and incentives. Where individual end-users <lb/>perceived the EHR to positively impact on patient care and workload, <lb/>this reportedly facilitated a successful implementation [10,12,50,51,56, <lb/>58,60,13,19,36,37,44,47-49]. However, realistic benefits and time-<lb/>frames specific to the organization should be communicated with <lb/>end-users [44,45,62]. Monetary incentives or penalties have also been <lb/>shown to be important, especially for privately-governed organizations <lb/>[13,45,59]. <lb/>3.2.2.3. Perceived changes to the healthcare ecosystem. End-users&apos; con-<lb/>cerns with changes to data privacy and security, patient-clinician re-<lb/>lationships and their roles and responsibilities, appeared to negatively <lb/>impact on EHR implementations [7,10,51,53,56,58,60-62,12,13,19,36, <lb/>44,47-49]. These concerns may differ depending on the specific setting <lb/>and type of sensitive personal information being collected (e.g., mental <lb/>health) [47]. Therefore, specific concerns and their causes of concerns <lb/>should be identified and addressed as soon as possible to mitigate their <lb/>impact on EHR implementations [19,36]. <lb/>3.2.3. Technological factors <lb/>Six factors relating to the technology aspect of the EHR imple-<lb/>mentation were identified as critical to its success and were intrinsically <lb/>linked to the organizational and human factors. <lb/>3.2.3.1. Usability. EHR usability was deemed important across several <lb/>reviews [7,10,11,13,36,37,44,46,47,49,51,52,54,58,60,62], as it <lb/>impacted on end-user efficiency, patient-facing time [12,13,37,53], <lb/>quality of care [12], patient-clinician relationships [52] and safety [37]. <lb/>However, a simple and intuitive system in one setting may not be <lb/>transferrable to another, and therefore, end-user involvement in devel-<lb/>opment, design [10,37,62] and usability testing were recommended at <lb/>each site [37]. Additionally, enabling personalization of the EHR <lb/>interface [53] and access to legacy paper-based records [50,51] as well <lb/>as consideration of data quality and accuracy [13,44,51] with use of <lb/>health terminologies and classifications [56] was recommended. How-<lb/>ever, usability needs to be balanced with security [44]. <lb/>3.2.3.2. Interoperability. To enable health information exchange both <lb/>within and across healthcare organizations, interoperability was iden-<lb/>tified as critical [7,10-13,19,37,44,45,49-52,54,58,60,62]. Local <lb/>contextual factors within countries such as two tier and fully private <lb/>health systems, lack of employment of national standards [45,53,62], <lb/>inconsistent data capture in incompatible formats [12], have rendered <lb/>the creation of a fully interoperable EHR as difficult. Therefore, tech-<lb/>nical standards and communication between organizations were rec-<lb/>ommended to ensure interoperability was built in from the outset <lb/>including for legacy and existing health IT systems [7]. <lb/>3.2.3.3. Infrastructure. Procurement or enhancement of infrastructure, <lb/>including software (e.g., EHR, anti-viral), hardware (e.g., data-entry <lb/>devices, Wi-Fi, power outlets) and furniture, accounted for a large pro-<lb/>portion of the financial resourcing and were deemed critical for the <lb/>success of the overall EHR implementation [10,12,56,62,63,36,47-53]. <lb/>The existing and new hardware and software must be compatible with <lb/>the specific EHR product 45 , reliable and functional [13,36,44,53,56], <lb/>and enable sufficient accessibility to the EHR for end-users [36,45,52, <lb/>56]. According to the expert panel and additional literature reviewed, <lb/>selection of mobile and stationary data-entry devices also require <lb/>consideration of vendor certification, healthcare setting (e.g., out-<lb/>patients versus isolation rooms), required functions and workflows (e.g., <lb/>checklists versus long narrative notes), and end-user preferences for <lb/>usability. <lb/>3.2.3.4. Regulation, standards and policies. As stated earlier, national <lb/>and international standards as well as regulation and policies were <lb/>critical for interoperability and addressing privacy and security concerns <lb/>[7,13,19,45,46,51,52,56,58,60,62,63]. Therefore, messaging and lan-<lb/>guage standards [45,52,56], as well as robust privacy laws and policies <lb/>[13,44,52,56,62] were recommended. Where healthcare organizations <lb/>were permitted to procure their own EHR product, these standards <lb/>would likely be especially important. <lb/>3.2.3.5. Adaptability. Many of the literature reviews reported that <lb/>adaptability of the software was important to facilitate customization of <lb/>the EHR software to meet the needs of the end-users and organizations <lb/>[10,36,37,50,51,53,54,62]. This reportedly required the software ven-<lb/>dors to be open to sharing code development data and willing to adapt <lb/>their product [36,37,53], and the organization to have access to a skilled <lb/>workforce with the capabilities to adapt the EHR to clinical workflows <lb/>[37]. Where interoperability standards exist, the need for adaptations to <lb/>the software may be reduced [37]. <lb/>3.2.3.6. Testing. Comprehensive testing of the system was critical to <lb/>ensure usability and safety [7,10,37,54], and was more commonly cited <lb/>as important by IT staff and management than by HCPs [7]. This <lb/>rigorous, resource-intensive, multi-step testing process of each EHR <lb/>function needed to be conducted within live environments with actual <lb/>end-users [54] and should not be underestimated. <lb/>4. Discussion <lb/>This umbrella review distilled the large volume of evidence available <lb/>regarding the successful implementation of a national EHR and these <lb/>findings were corroborated by an expert panel as being relevant to the <lb/>Irish healthcare context. Fifteen key organizational, human and tech-<lb/>nological factors were identified as critical and by synthesizing the <lb/>findings from several stakeholder groups and clinical settings, such as <lb/>doctors in primary or secondary care [11,13,45,53,58,61] and nurses in <lb/>a mental health setting [47], this review of reviews identified that each <lb/>of these factors were also relevant and important to EHR and other HIT <lb/>implementations across different healthcare contexts. <lb/>However, between country differences including health service <lb/>management, politics, economics, regulation and socio-culture impact <lb/>on how the identified factors influence success. This was evident in the <lb/>literature reviews which largely focused on studies conducted in the <lb/>predominantly private health service in the USA where return on in-<lb/>vestment and productivity were perceived benefits and incentives of <lb/>EHRs or EMRs [50,51,56]. Additionally whilst the governance approach <lb/>was identified as important, a successful approach in one country cannot <lb/>necessarily be replicated in another, as occurred in the UK where the <lb/>top-down approach successfully employed in the Netherlands resulted in <lb/>disengaged healthcare organizations across the UK [22]. Therefore, <lb/>these factors need to be employed with consideration of the national <lb/>context and in the Republic of Ireland this will also require close <lb/>collaboration and communication across the co-existing public and <lb/>private health sectors [64,65], as well as with those in Northern Ireland <lb/>(UK). Additionally, European Union (EU) citizens may avail of health-<lb/>care from any member state under the Cross-Border Healthcare <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Directive (2011/24/EU) and thus, efficient exchange of health data <lb/>across borders is a major priority [66] and is a pillar of EU4Health <lb/>2021-2027 [67]. Therefore, the EU interoperability policies and <lb/>frameworks [14] as well as standards such as the International Patient <lb/>Summary, the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) and stand-<lb/>ardised terminologies [4] to support these frameworks need to be <lb/>employed. <lb/>Despite the expansion in internationally-recognised standards (e. <lb/>g., HL7 FHIR) and significant regulatory and financial incentives <lb/>created by the HITECH Act and &quot;Meaningful Use&quot; requirements in the <lb/>USA, factors such as Usability and Regulations, standards and policies <lb/>continue to be highlighted as important for success as opposed to <lb/>being assumed components of EHR products. Whilst the inclusion of <lb/>older studies by these reviews perhaps contributed to this, it is also <lb/>likely that standards and requirements alone will not ensure an <lb/>interoperable and usable EHR. In fact, it is the dynamic interaction <lb/>between each of the identified factors which promotes a successful <lb/>EHR [68]. However, placing more emphasis on an individual factor <lb/>can reduce the resources required for others. For example, promoting <lb/>Usability and Standards can respectively reduce the burden of training <lb/>and support, as well as adaptability [37]. Additionally, this may be <lb/>achieved by advances in evidence and technology such as artificial <lb/>intelligence (AI) including automated testing [69], eLearning mod-<lb/>ules [70,71], and personalization of the EHR interface [72]. There-<lb/>fore, it is recommended that those involved in each aspect of the <lb/>implementation process communicate throughout it and review the <lb/>latest evidence regarding technology including peer-reviewed publi-<lb/>cations and white papers. <lb/>At a more local or meso level, the size of the organization, infra-<lb/>structure, organizational readiness and culture, capabilities and be-<lb/>liefs of the workforce, and available finance [36,37], were also <lb/>identified as important when considering the application of the <lb/>identified factors. Certain aspects of the internal context can also be <lb/>enhanced to improve the likelihood of EHR success such as employing <lb/>change management to create a clear and realistic vision of the EHR <lb/>[73] and providing basic computer training [36,48]. However, the <lb/>size of the organization and its workforce will likely remain more <lb/>limited compared to their larger counterparts [10,37]. Therefore, <lb/>sharing of resources such as champions, support staff and trainers <lb/>between larger and smaller hospitals or primary care settings has <lb/>been recommended, with some countries creating networks or <lb/>encouraging collaboration between existing regional groups of <lb/>healthcare organizations [73,74]. <lb/>4.1. Strengths and Limitations <lb/>Undertaking a rapid qualitative evidence synthesis requires accel-<lb/>eration of many of the research processes, is dependent on the reporting <lb/>in the original reviews [32] and could risk losing the context and <lb/>complexity of the original research setting [32,42,75]. Additionally, five <lb/>of the literature reviews were conducted by the same lead author which <lb/>could lead to bias of individual study inclusion. However, the inclusion <lb/>of literature reviews, consideration of the inclusion criteria of each <lb/>literature review and ongoing collaboration with an expert panel [30], <lb/>provided a degree of confidence regarding the coherence, relevance and <lb/>adequacy of the findings and their generalisability across healthcare <lb/>settings [76]. Additionally, actively involving knowledge-users who <lb/>were undertaking HIT implementations led to the concurrent translation <lb/>of this knowledge into practice [77]. <lb/>5. Conclusion <lb/>The key organizational, human and technological factors identified <lb/>in this review provide policy-makers and other key stakeholders with a <lb/>foundation for making evidence-based decisions during the imple-<lb/>mentation of a fully interoperable EHR across primary, secondary and <lb/>long-term care. However, consideration of the specific contextual in-<lb/>fluences is critical to the successful application of these factors. Addi-<lb/>tionally, the end-users, existing technological standards and policies, <lb/>and advances in technology and research in the area, will impact on how <lb/>these factors dynamically interact during the EHR implementation and <lb/>will influence success. <lb/></body>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This work was supported by the Office of the Nursing and Midwifery <lb/>Services Director, Health Service Executive (HSE), Ireland. <lb/></div>

			<<div type="conflict">Declaration of Competing Interest <lb/>The authors report no declarations of interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The panel of experts and knowledge users who gave their time and <lb/>expertise as well as other contributors from the HSE. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Summary points <lb/>What was already known on the topic: <lb/>• Despite recognition of the huge potential for EHRs to improve the delivery of healthcare, huge challenges have been met in implementing a <lb/>fully interoperable EHR across acute and community care. <lb/>• The implementation process of EHRs is critical to their success and needs to be carefully planned and considered across the complex and <lb/>adapting healthcare landscape. <lb/>• A vast amount of literature exists on EHRs which has been relevant to specific stakeholder groups and healthcare contexts. <lb/>What this study adds: <lb/>• A comprehensive and clear overview of factors influencing the success of an EHR implementation across primary, secondary and long term <lb/>care and different stakeholder groups is presented. <lb/>• Validation of these factors for the Irish healthcare context via co-production and transfer of knowledge with key knowledge-users. <lb/>• Generation of key considerations for each of these factors for policy-makers and other knowledge-users. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Search Strategy <lb/>Electronic Health record <lb/>Electronic health record* <lb/>Electronic Healthcare Record* <lb/>Electronic patient record* <lb/>Computeri?ed health record* <lb/>Electronic medical record* <lb/>Online health record* <lb/>Digital health record* <lb/>Computeri?ed medical record* <lb/>Electronic Medical Record <lb/>Automated medical records <lb/>Electronic health record <lb/>Electronic health records <lb/>Electronic medical record <lb/>Computerized medical records <lb/>Automated medical records <lb/>Electronic Record System* <lb/>Clinical Information system* <lb/>Electronic Health Record <lb/>System* <lb/>Medical Information System <lb/>Computerized medical systems <lb/>Computerized medical systems <lb/>Clinical data repositor* <lb/>Health Records System* <lb/>Medical Records System* <lb/>Health information system* <lb/>Hospital information system* <lb/>Health Information Systems <lb/>Medical records system, <lb/>Computerized <lb/>Electronic health record system <lb/>Medical information system <lb/>electronic prescribing <lb/>e-prescri* <lb/>eprescri* <lb/>Electronic pharmaceutical <lb/>record <lb/>Electronic Order Entry <lb/>computerized ordering <lb/>Medical Order Entry System* <lb/>Drug Information System <lb/>Order comm* <lb/>Computeri?ed Physician Order <lb/>Management <lb/>Computeri?ed Provider Order <lb/>Entry <lb/>Computeri?ed Provider Order <lb/>Management <lb/>Computeri?ed Physician Order <lb/>Entry <lb/>Medical Order Entry Systems <lb/>Electronic Order Entry <lb/>Computerized provider order <lb/>entry <lb/>Personal health record* <lb/>Patient health record* <lb/>Electronic patient record* <lb/>Patient portal* <lb/>Shared care record* <lb/>Summary care record* <lb/>Patient data repositor* <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Health Care Information <lb/>Exchange* <lb/>Medical record linkage* <lb/>Health Information Exchange <lb/>Patient Portals <lb/>Health Information <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Data interoperability <lb/>Interoperability <lb/>Health Information Exchange <lb/>Medical Record Linkage EHR <lb/>PHR <lb/>EHCR <lb/>(continued on next page) <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">(continued ) <lb/>EPR <lb/>EMR <lb/>CIS <lb/>EHRS <lb/>DIS <lb/>CPOM <lb/>CPOE <lb/>EPR <lb/>EHRS <lb/>HIE <lb/>Implementation <lb/>Implement* <lb/>Introduc* <lb/>Adopt* <lb/>Develop* <lb/>Establish* <lb/>Process* <lb/>Execut* <lb/>Employ* <lb/>Instigat* <lb/>Launch* <lb/>Re-launch <lb/>Commence* <lb/>Initiat* <lb/>Uptake* <lb/>Configuration* <lb/>Customization* <lb/>Re-optimi* <lb/>Optimi* <lb/>Rollout* <lb/>Evaluat* <lb/>Assess* <lb/>Design <lb/>Facilitate* <lb/>Barrier* <lb/>Challeng* <lb/>Benefit* <lb/>Success <lb/>Failure <lb/>Systems Development <lb/>Systems Implementation <lb/>Literature Review <lb/>Systematic Review <lb/>Scoping Review <lb/>Meta Analysis <lb/>Literature review <lb/>Systematic review <lb/>Scoping review <lb/>Meta-analysis <lb/>Meta-synthesis <lb/>Systematic interpretive review <lb/>Systematic methodological <lb/>review <lb/>Systematic meta-review <lb/>Systematic literature review <lb/>Qualitative synthesis <lb/>Note: *, truncation; ?, wildcard; <lb/>italicised terms, refer to subject <lb/>headings which were exploded in <lb/>the relevant databases. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] eHealth Ireland. Electronic Health Record. https://www.ehealthireland.ie/ <lb/>Strategic-Programmes/Electronic-Health-Record-EHR-/. Published 2019. Accessed <lb/>June 15, 2019. <lb/>[2] Gartner, Healthcare EHR and Digital Care Delivery Optimization Primer for 2019, <lb/>2019. <lb/>[3] E. Williamson, A. Walker, K. Bhaskaran, S Bates Bacon, Caroline E Morton, Helen <lb/>J Curtis, Amir Mehrkar, David Evans, Peter Inglesby, Jonathan Cockburn, Helen <lb/>I Mcdonald, Brian MacKenna, Laurie Tomlinson, I. VOPG, OpenSAFELY: factors <lb/>associated with COVID-19-related hospital death in the linked electronic health <lb/>records of 17 million adult NHS patients, J Chem Inf Model. 53 (9) (2020) <lb/>1689-1699, https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781107415324.004. <lb/>[4] Health Information Quality Authority (HIQA), Developing National EHealth <lb/>Interoperability Standards for Ireland: A Consultation Document, 2011. htt <lb/>ps://www.hiqa.ie/sites/default/files/2017-01/eHealth-Interoperability-Consultati <lb/>on.pdf. <lb/>[5] ISO, International Organization for Standardization ISO/TR 20514:2005, 2005. <lb/>[6] A. Kouroubali, D.G. Katehakis, The new European interoperability framework as a <lb/>facilitator of digital transformation for citizen empowerment, J Biomed Inform 94 <lb/>(2019), 103166, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103166. <lb/>[7] L. Nguyen, E. Bellucci, L.T. Nguyen, Electronic health records implementation: an <lb/>evaluation of information system impact and contingency factors, Int J Med Inform <lb/>83 (11) (2014) 779-796, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2014.06.011. <lb/>[8] H.J. Warraich, R.M. Califf, H.M. Krumholz, The digital transformation of medicine <lb/>can revitalize the patient-clinician relationship, npj Digit Med 1 (1) (2018) 6-8, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41746-018-0060-2. <lb/>[9] J. Carnicero, D. Rojas, Lessons learned from implementation of information and <lb/>communication technologies in Spain&apos;s healthcare services: Issues and <lb/>opportunities, Appl Clin Inform 1 (4) (2010) 363-376, https://doi.org/10.4338/ <lb/>ACI-2010-07-CR-0041. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[10] J. Sligo, R. Gauld, V. Roberts, L. Villa, A literature review for large-scale health <lb/>information system project planning, implementation and evaluation, Int J Med <lb/>Inform 97 (2017) 86-97, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2016.09.007. <lb/>[11] V.H. Castillo, A.I. Martinez-Garcia, J.R.G. Pulido, A knowledge-based taxonomy of <lb/>critical factors for adopting electronic health record systems by physicians: a <lb/>systematic literature review, BMC Med Inform Decis Mak 10 (2010) 60, https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1186/1472-6947-10-60. <lb/>[12] S. Ajami, T. Bagheri-Tadi, Barriers for adopting electronic health records (EHRs) by <lb/>physicians, Acta Inform Medica 21 (2) (2013) 129-134, https://doi.org/10.5455/ <lb/>aim.2013.21.129-134. <lb/>[13] A. O&apos;Donnell, E. Kaner, C. Shaw, C. Haighton, Primary care physicians&apos; attitudes to <lb/>the adoption of electronic medical records: a systematic review and evidence <lb/>synthesis using the clinical adoption framework, BMC Med Inform Decis Mak 18 <lb/>(1) (2018) 101, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12911-018-0703-x. <lb/>[14] eHealth Network, Refined EHealth European Interoperability Framework, 2015, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-137-42617-8_32. <lb/>[15] K. Shah, C. Lo, M. Babich, N.W. Tsao, N.J. Bansback, Bar Code Medication <lb/>Administration Technology: A Systematic Review of Impact on Patient Safety <lb/>When Used with Computerized Prescriber Order Entry and Automated Dispensing <lb/>Devices, Can J Hosp Pharm. 69 (5) (2016) 394-402, https://doi.org/10.4212/cjhp. <lb/>v69i5.1594. <lb/>[16] M. Prgomet, L. Li, Z. Niazkhani, A. Georgiou, J.I. Westbrook, Impact of commercial <lb/>computerized provider order entry (CPOE) and clinical decision support systems <lb/>(CDSSs) on medication errors, length of stay, and mortality in intensive care units: <lb/>a systematic review and meta-analysis, J Am Med Inform Assoc 24 (2) (2017) <lb/>413-422, https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocw145. <lb/>[17] Health Information Quality Authority (HIQA), National Standard on Information <lb/>Requirements for a National Electronic Patient Summary, 2019. <lb/>[18] A. Roehrs, C.A. da Costa, R. Righi R da, K.S.F. de Oliveira, Personal Health Records: <lb/>A Systematic Literature Review, J Med Internet Res 19 (1) (2017) e13, https://doi. <lb/>org/10.2196/jmir.5876. <lb/>[19] M. Lluch, Healthcare professionals&apos; organisational barriers to health information <lb/>technologies-a literature review, Int J Med Inform 80 (12) (2011) 849-862, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2011.09.005. <lb/>[20] E. Deutsch, G. Duftschmid, W. Dorda, Critical areas of national electronic health <lb/>record programs-Is our focus correct? Int J Med Inform 79 (3) (2010) 211-222, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2009.12.002. <lb/>[21] O. Campion-Awwad, A. Hayton, L. Smith, M. Vuaran, The National Programme for <lb/>IT in the NHS: A Case History, 2014 https://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~rja14/Papers/ <lb/>npfit-mpp-2014-case-history.pdf. <lb/>[22] L.L. Fragidis, P.D. Chatzoglou, Implementation of a nationwide electronic health <lb/>record (EHR): The international experience in 13 countries, Int J Health Care Qual <lb/>Assur. 31 (2) (2018) 116-130, https://doi.org/10.1108/IJHCQA-09-2016-0136. <lb/>[23] M.F. Collen, R.A. Miller, in: M.F. Collen, M.J. Ball (Eds.), The Early History of <lb/>Hospital Information Systems for Inpatient Care in the United States BT -The <lb/>History of Medical Informatics in the United States, Springer London, London, <lb/>2015, pp. 339-383, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4471-6732-7_6. <lb/>[24] Department of Health, EHealth Strategy, 2013. <lb/>[25] eHealth Ireland. Lighthouse Projects. https://www.ehealthireland.ie/Lighthouse-<lb/>Projects/. Published 2016. Accessed July 3, 2020. <lb/>[26] Department of Health, Sláintecare Implementation Strategy, 2018. <lb/>[27] K. Keown, D. Van Eerd, E. Irvin, Stakeholder engagement opportunities in <lb/>systematic reviews: Knowledge transfer for policy and practice, J Contin Educ <lb/>Health Prof. 28 (2) (2008). https://journals.lww.com/jcehp/Fulltext/2008/2802 <lb/>0/Stakeholder_engagement_opportunities_in_systematic.3.aspx. <lb/>[28] J.M. Grimshaw, N. Santesso, M. Cumpston, A. Mayhew, J. McGowan, Knowledge <lb/>for knowledge translation: The role of the Cochrane Collaboration, J Contin Educ <lb/>Health Prof. 26 (1) (2006). https://journals.lww.com/jcehp/Fulltext/2006/26 <lb/>010/Knowledge_for_knowledge_translation__The_role_of.7.aspx. <lb/>[29] R. Pawson, T. Greenhalgh, G. Harvey, K. Walshe, Realist review -a new method of <lb/>systematic review designed for complex policy interventions, J Health Serv Res <lb/>Policy 10 (1_suppl) (2005) 21-34, https://doi.org/10.1258/1355819054308530. <lb/>[30] É Ní Shé, S. Morton, V. Lambert, et al., Clarifying the mechanisms and resources <lb/>that enable the reciprocal involvement of seldom heard groups in health and social <lb/>care research: A collaborative rapid realist review process, Health Expect 22 (3) <lb/>(2019) 298-306, https://doi.org/10.1111/hex.12865. <lb/>[31] A. Tricco, E. Langlois, S. Straus, Rapid Reviews to Strengthen Health Policy and <lb/>Systems: A Practical Guide, 2017. https://www.who.int/alliance-hpsr/resources/p <lb/>ublications/rapid-review-guide/en/. <lb/>[32] E. Aromataris, Z. Munn, JBI Reviewer&apos;s Manual, 2020, https://doi.org/10.46658/ <lb/>JBIRM-19-01. <lb/>[33] E. Aromataris, R. Fernandez, C.M. Godfrey, C. Holly, H. Khalil, P. Tungpunkom, <lb/>Summarizing systematic reviews: methodological development, conduct and <lb/>reporting of an umbrella review approach, Int J Evid Based Healthc. 13 (3) (2015). <lb/>https://journals.lww.com/ijebh/Fulltext/2015/09000/Summarizing_systematic_re <lb/>views__methodological.4.aspx. <lb/>[34] HSE, Factors for Success in Electronic Health Record Implementation: Literature <lb/>Review and Key Considerations, 2019. <lb/>[35] ÉN Shé, F. Keogan, E. McAuliffe, et al., Undertaking a Collaborative Rapid Realist <lb/>Review to Investigate What Works in the Successful Implementation of a Frail <lb/>Older Person&apos;s Pathway, Int J Environ Res Public Health 15 (2) (2018) 199, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph15020199. <lb/>[36] A. Boonstra, A. Versluis, J.F.J. Vos, Implementing electronic health records in <lb/>hospitals: a systematic literature review, BMC Health Serv Res 14 (2014) 370, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/1472-6963-14-370. <lb/>[37] R. Ratwani, T. Fairbanks, E. Savage, et al., Mind the Gap. A systematic review to <lb/>identify usability and safety challenges and practices during electronic health <lb/>record implementation, Appl Clin Inform 7 (4) (2016) 1069-1087, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.4338/ACI-2016-06-R-0105. <lb/>[38] D. Ludwick, D. Manca, J. Doucette, Primary care physicians&apos; experiences with <lb/>electronic medical records: implementation experience in community, urban, <lb/>hospital, and academic family medicine, Can Fam Physician 56 (1) (2010) 40-47. <lb/>[39] V.M. Montori, N.L. Wilczynski, D. Morgan, R.B. Haynes, Optimal search strategies <lb/>for retrieving systematic reviews from Medline: analytical survey, BMJ 330 (7482) <lb/>(2005) 68, https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.38336.804167.47. <lb/>[40] B.J. Powell, E.K. Proctor, J.E. Glass, A Systematic Review of Strategies for <lb/>Implementing Empirically Supported Mental Health Interventions, Res Soc Work <lb/>Pract 24 (2) (2014) 192-212, https://doi.org/10.1177/1049731513505778. <lb/>[41] U.H. Graneheim, B. Lundman, Qualitative content analysis in nursing research: <lb/>concepts, procedures and measures to achieve trustworthiness, Nurse Educ Today <lb/>24 (2) (2004) 105-112, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nedt.2003.10.001. <lb/>[42] J. Thomas, A. Harden, Methods for the thematic synthesis of qualitative research in <lb/>systematic reviews, BMC Med Res Methodol 8 (2008) 1-10, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1186/1471-2288-8-45. <lb/>[43] S.S. McMillan, M. King, M.P. Tully, How to use the nominal group and Delphi <lb/>techniques, Int J Clin Pharm 38 (3) (2016) 655-662, https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s11096-016-0257-x. <lb/>[44] M.-P. Gagnon, E.-R. Nsangou, M.-P. Payne-Gagnon, S. Grenier, C. Sicotte, Barriers <lb/>and facilitators to implementing electronic prescription: a systematic review of <lb/>user groups&apos; perceptions, J Am Med Inform Assoc 21 (3) (2014) 535-541, https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1136/amiajnl-2013-002203. <lb/>[45] R.L. Police, T. Foster, K.S. Wong, Adoption and use of health information <lb/>technology in physician practice organisations: systematic review, Inform Prim <lb/>Care 18 (4) (2010) 245-258, https://doi.org/10.14236/jhi.v18i4.780. <lb/>[46] C.S. Kruse, M. Mileski, V. Alaytsev, E. Carol, A. Williams, Adoption factors <lb/>associated with electronic health record among long-term care facilities: a <lb/>systematic review, BMJ Open 5 (1) (2015), e006615, https://doi.org/10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2014-006615. <lb/>[47] G. Strudwick, T. Eyasu, Electronic Health Record Use by Nurses in Mental Health <lb/>Settings: A Literature Review, Arch Psychiatr Nurs 29 (4) (2015) 238-241, https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.apnu.2015.03.007. <lb/>[48] F. Fritz, B. Tilahun, M. Dugas, Success criteria for electronic medical record <lb/>implementations in low-resource settings: a systematic review, J Am Med Inform <lb/>Assoc 22 (2) (2015) 479-488, https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocu038. <lb/>[49] C.A. McGinn, S. Grenier, J. Duplantie, et al., Comparison of user groups&apos; <lb/>perspectives of barriers and facilitators to implementing electronic health records: <lb/>a systematic review, BMC Med 9 (2011) 46, https://doi.org/10.1186/1741-7015-<lb/>9-46. <lb/>[50] C.S. Kruse, K. Kothman, K. Anerobi, L. Abanaka, Adoption Factors of the Electronic <lb/>Health Record: A Systematic Review, JMIR Med informatics 4 (2) (2016) e19, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2196/medinform.5525. <lb/>[51] C.S. Kruse, C. Kristof, B. Jones, E. Mitchell, A. Martinez, Barriers to Electronic <lb/>Health Record Adoption: a Systematic Literature Review, J Med Syst 40 (12) <lb/>(2016) 252, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10916-016-0628-9. <lb/>[52] R. Ben-Zion, N. Pliskin, L. Fink, Critical Success Factors for Adoption of Electronic <lb/>Health Record Systems: Literature Review and Prescriptive Analysis, Inf Syst <lb/>Manag 31 (4) (2014) 296-312, https://doi.org/10.1080/10580530.2014.958024. <lb/>[53] A. Boonstra, M. Broekhuis, Barriers to the acceptance of electronic medical records <lb/>by physicians from systematic review to taxonomy and interventions, BMC Health <lb/>Serv Res 10 (2010) 231, https://doi.org/10.1186/1472-6963-10-231. <lb/>[54] K. Cresswell, A. Sheikh, Organizational issues in the implementation and adoption <lb/>of health information technology innovations: An interpretative review, Int J Med <lb/>Inform 82 (5) (2013) e73-e86, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2012.10.007. <lb/>[55] C. de Grood, A. Raiss, Y. Kwon, M.J. Santana, Adoption of e-health technology by <lb/>physicians: a scoping review, J Multidiscip Healthc 9 (2016) 335-344, https://doi. <lb/>org/10.2147/JMDH.S103881. <lb/>[56] J.M. Gesulga, A. Berjame, K.S. Moquiala, A. Galido, Barriers to Electronic Health <lb/>Record System Implementation and Information Systems Resources: A Structured <lb/>Review, Procedia Comput Sci 124 (2017) 544-551, https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>procs.2017.12.188. <lb/>[57] R. Gill, E.M. Borycki, The Use of Case Studies in Systems Implementations Within <lb/>Health Care Settings: A Scoping Review…ITCH 2017, Stud Heal Technol <lb/>Informatics (234) (2017) 142-149, https://doi.org/10.3233/978-1-61499-742-9-<lb/>142. <lb/>[58] C.S. Kruse, A. Stein, H. Thomas, H. Kaur, The use of Electronic Health Records to <lb/>Support Population Health: A Systematic Review of the Literature, J Med Syst 42 <lb/>(11) (2018) 214, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10916-018-1075-6. <lb/>[59] C. Kruse, J. DeShazo, F. Kim, L. Fulton, Factors associated with adoption of health <lb/>information technology: a conceptual model based on a systematic review, JMIR <lb/>Med Inf 2 (1) (2014) e9. <lb/>[60] F.S. Mair, C. May, C. O&apos;Donnell, T. Finch, F. Sullivan, E. Murray, Factors that <lb/>promote or inhibit the implementation of e-health systems: an explanatory <lb/>systematic review, Bull World Health Organ 90 (5) (2012) 357-364, https://doi. <lb/>org/10.2471/BLT.11.099424. <lb/>[61] C. de Grood, A. Raissi, Y. Kwon, M. Santana, Adoption of e-health technology by <lb/>physicians: A scoping review, J Multidiscip Healthc 9 (2016) 335-344, https://doi. <lb/>org/10.2147/JMDH.S103881 LK. http://search.library.nuigalway.ie/open <lb/>url/353GAL_INST/353GAL_services_page?sid=EMBASE&amp;sid=EMBASE&amp;issn <lb/>=11782390&amp;id=doi:10.2147%2FJMDH.S103881&amp;atitle=Adoption+of+e-health <lb/>+technology+by+physicians%3A+A+scoping+review&amp;stitle=J.+Multidiscip. <lb/>Healthc.&amp;title=Journal+of+Multidisciplinary+Healthcare&amp;volume=9&amp;issue <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. <lb/>International Journal of Medical Informatics 144 (2020) 104281 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>=&amp;spage=335&amp;epage=344&amp;aulast=de+Grood&amp;aufirst=Chloe&amp;auinit=C.&amp; <lb/>aufull=de+Grood+C.&amp;coden=&amp;isbn=&amp;pages=335-344&amp;date=2016&amp;auin <lb/>it1=C&amp;auinitm=. <lb/>[62] J. Ross, F. Stevenson, R. Lau, E. Murray, Factors that influence the implementation <lb/>of e-health: a systematic review of systematic reviews (an update), Implement Sci <lb/>11 (1) (2016) 146, https://doi.org/10.1186/s13012-016-0510-7. <lb/>[63] T.T.H. Nguyen, K. Saranto, T. Tapanainen, D. Ishmatova, A Review of Health <lb/>Information Technology Implementation Success Factors: Importance of <lb/>Regulation and Finance, 2014 47th Hawaii International Conference on System <lb/>Sciences (2014) 2693-2705, https://doi.org/10.1109/HICSS.2014.340. <lb/>[64] D. Capurro, A. Echeverry, R. Figueroa, et al., Chile&apos;s national center for health <lb/>information systems: A public-private partnership to foster health care information <lb/>interoperability, Stud Health Technol Inform 245 (2017) 693-695, https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3233/978-1-61499-830-3-693. <lb/>[65] A. Tubaishat, Evaluation of Electronic Health Record Implementation in Hospitals, <lb/>CIN Comput Informatics, Nurs. 35 (7) (2017). https://journals.lww.com/cinjour <lb/>nal/Fulltext/2017/07000/Evaluation_of_Electronic_Health_Record.8.aspx. <lb/>[66] M. Nalin, I. Baroni, G. Faiella, et al., The European cross-border health data <lb/>exchange roadmap: Case study in the Italian setting, J Biomed Inform 94 (April) <lb/>(2019) 103183, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103183. <lb/>[67] European Commission, EU4Health Programme for a Healthier and Safer Union, <lb/>2020. https://ec.europa.eu/health/sites/health/files/funding/docs/eu4health_fa <lb/>ctsheet_en.pdf. <lb/>[68] T. Greenhalgh, J. Wherton, C. Papoutsi, et al., Beyond adoption: A new framework <lb/>for theorizing and evaluating nonadoption, abandonment, and challenges to the <lb/>scale-up, spread, and sustainability of health and care technologies, J Med Internet <lb/>Res 19 (11) (2017), https://doi.org/10.2196/jmir.8775. <lb/>[69] A. Wright, S. Aaron, D.F. Sittig, Testing electronic health records in the <lb/>&quot;production&quot; environment: an essential step in the journey to a safe and effective <lb/>health care system, J Am Med Inform Assoc 24 (1) (2017) 188-192, https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1093/jamia/ocw039. <lb/>[70] E. Topol, Preparing the healthcare workforce to deliver the digital future The Topol <lb/>Review. An independent report on behalf of the Secretary of State for Health and <lb/>Social Care, Nhs (February) (2019) 102. https://topol.hee.nhs.uk/wp-content/uplo <lb/>ads/HEE-Topol-Review-2019.pdf. <lb/>[71] S.P. Slight, C. Quinn, A.J. Avery, D.W. Bates, A. Sheikh, A qualitative study <lb/>identifying the cost categories associated with electronic health record <lb/>implementation in the UK, J Am Med Informatics Assoc 21 (e2) (2014) e226-e231, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1136/amiajnl-2013-002404. <lb/>[72] KLAS, Improving the EHR Experience Through Personalization: An Arch <lb/>Collaborative Impact Report, 2018. <lb/>[73] Health Information Technology Research Centre (HITRC), Change Management in <lb/>EHR, 2013. https://www.healthit.gov/sites/default/files/tools/nlc_changemanag <lb/>ementprimer.pdf. <lb/>[74] E. Ford, N. Menachemi, T. Huerta, F. Yu, Hospital IT adoption strategies associated <lb/>with implementation success: Implications for achieving meaningful use, J Healthc <lb/>Manag 55 (3) (2010) 175. <lb/>[75] S. Lewin, A. Booth, C. Glenton, et al., Applying GRADE-CERQual to qualitative <lb/>evidence synthesis findings: Introduction to the series, Implement Sci 13 (Suppl 1) <lb/>(2018) 1-10, https://doi.org/10.1186/s13012-017-0688-3. <lb/>[76] C.D. Willis, J.E. Saul, J. Bitz, K. Pompu, A. Best, B. Jackson, Improving <lb/>organizational capacity to address health literacy in public health: a rapid realist <lb/>review, Public Health 128 (6) (2014) 515-524, https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>puhe.2014.01.014. <lb/>[77] World Health Organisation (WHO), Implementation Research Toolkit: Introduction <lb/>and Basic Orientation, 2014. https://www.who.int/tdr/publications/year/2014 <lb/>/participant-workbookintro_030414.pdf?ua=1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">O. Fennelly et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
