<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Article <lb/>Skin exposure to UVB light induces a skin-brain-<lb/>gonad axis and sexual behavior <lb/>Graphical abstract <lb/>Highlights <lb/>d UVB exposure increases circulating sex-steroid levels in mice <lb/>and humans <lb/>d UVB exposure enhances female attractiveness and <lb/>receptiveness toward males <lb/>d UVB exposure increases females&apos; estrus phase, HPG axis <lb/>hormones, and follicle growth <lb/>d Skin p53 regulates UVB-induced sexual behavior and ovarian <lb/>physiological changes <lb/>Authors <lb/>Roma Parikh, Eschar Sorek, <lb/>Shivang Parikh, ..., Ruth Percik, <lb/>Aron Weller, Carmit Levy <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>carmitlevy@post.tau.ac.il <lb/></front>

			<body>In brief <lb/>Parikh et al. find that UVB exposure <lb/>triggers a skin-brain-gonadal axis <lb/>through skin p53 activation. UVB <lb/>exposure increases in female mice sexual <lb/>responsiveness and attractiveness, <lb/>hypothalamus-pituitary-gonadal axis <lb/>hormone levels, ovary size, and estrus <lb/>duration, as well as male-female <lb/>interactions. Solar exposure in humans <lb/>enhances romantic passion and <lb/>positively correlates with male <lb/>testosterone levels. <lb/></body>

			<front>Parikh et al., 2021, Cell Reports 36, 109579 <lb/>August 24, 2021 ª 2021 The Authors. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2021.109579 <lb/>ll <lb/>Article <lb/>Skin exposure to UVB light induces <lb/>a skin-brain-gonad axis and sexual behavior <lb/>Roma Parikh, 1 Eschar Sorek, 1 Shivang Parikh, 1 Keren Michael, 2 Lior Bikovski, 3,4 Sagi Tshori, 5,6 Galit Shefer, 5 <lb/>Shira Mingelgreen, 5 Taiba Zornitzki, 7 Hilla Knobler, 7 Gabriel Chodick, 8,23 Mariya Mardamshina, 1 Arjan Boonman, 9 <lb/>Noga Kronfeld-Schor, 9 Hadas Bar-Joseph, 10 Dalit Ben-Yosef, 11,12 Hadar Amir, 13,14 Mor Pavlovsky, 15 Hagit Matz, 15,16 <lb/>Tom Ben-Dov, 1,17 Tamar Golan, 1 Eran Nizri, 15,16 Daphna Liber, 18 Yair Liel, 19 Ronen Brenner, 20 Yftach Gepner, 21 <lb/>Orit Karnieli-Miller, 22 Rina Hemi, 23 Ruth Shalgi, 24 Tali Kimchi, 25 Ruth Percik, 16,23 Aron Weller, 26 and Carmit Levy 1,27, * <lb/>1 Department of Human Genetics and Biochemistry, Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv 69978, Israel <lb/>2 Department of Human Services, The Max Stern Yezreel Valley Academic College, Jezreel Valley 1930600, Israel <lb/>3 The Myers Neuro-Behavioral Core Facility, Sackler School of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv 69978, Israel <lb/>4 School of Behavioral Sciences, Netanya Academic College, Netanya 4223587, Israel <lb/>5 Research Authority, Kaplan Medical Center, Rehovot, Israel <lb/>6 Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Institute for Medical Research Israel-Canada, The Hebrew University, Jerusalem, Israel <lb/>7 Diabetes, Endocrinology and Metabolic Disease Institute, Kaplan Medical Center, Hadassah School of Medicine, Hebrew University in <lb/>Jerusalem, Rehovot, Israel <lb/>8 Maccabitech, Maccabi Healthcare Services, Tel Aviv, Israel <lb/>9 School of Zoology, Faculty of Life Sciences and the Sagol School of Neuroscience, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv 6997801, Israel <lb/>10 The TMCR Unit, Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv 69978, Israel <lb/>11 IVF Lab &amp; Wolfe PGD-Stem Cell Lab, Fertility Institute, Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center, Tel Aviv, Israel <lb/>12 Department of Cell Biology and Development, Sackler Faculty of Medicine &amp; Sagol School of Neuroscience, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, <lb/>Israel <lb/>13 Fertility Institute, Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center, Tel Aviv, Israel <lb/>14 Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, Israel <lb/>15 Department of Dermatology, Tel Aviv Sourasky (Ichilov) Medical Center, Tel Aviv 6423906, Israel <lb/>16 Sackler School of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv 69978, Israel <lb/>17 Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck surgery, Meir Medical Center, Kfar Saba 4428164, Israel <lb/>18 Faculty of Humanities, Education and Social Sciences, Ono Academic College, Kiryat Ono, Israel <lb/>19 Faculty of Health Sciences, Ben-Gurion University of the Negev, Beer-Sheva, Israel <lb/>20 Institute of Pathology, E. Wolfson Medical Center, Holon 58100, Israel <lb/>21 School of Public Health, Sackler Faculty of Medicine and Sylvan Adams Sports Institute, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv 69978, Israel <lb/>22 Department of Medical Education, Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv 69978, Israel <lb/>23 Institute of Endocrinology, Chaim Sheba Medical Center, Tel-Hashomer, Israel <lb/>24 Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv 69978, Israel <lb/>25 Department of Neurobiology, Weizmann Institute of Science, Rehovot, Israel <lb/>26 Department of Psychology and the Gonda Brain Research Center, Bar-Ilan University, Ramat Gan 5290002, Israel <lb/>27 Lead contact <lb/>*Correspondence: carmitlevy@post.tau.ac.il <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2021.109579 <lb/>SUMMARY <lb/>Ultraviolet (UV) light affects endocrinological and behavioral aspects of sexuality via an unknown mechanism. <lb/>Here we discover that ultraviolet B (UVB) exposure enhances the levels of sex-steroid hormones and sexual <lb/>behavior, which are mediated by the skin. In female mice, UVB exposure increases hypothalamus-pituitary-<lb/>gonadal axis hormone levels, resulting in larger ovaries; extends estrus days; and increases anti-Mullerian <lb/>hormone (AMH) expression. UVB exposure also enhances the sexual responsiveness and attractiveness <lb/>of females and male-female interactions. Conditional knockout of p53 specifically in skin keratinocytes abol-<lb/>ishes the effects of UVB. Thus, UVB triggers a skin-brain-gonadal axis through skin p53 activation. In humans, <lb/>solar exposure enhances romantic passion in both genders and aggressiveness in men, as seen in analysis of <lb/>individual questionaries, and positively correlates with testosterone level. Our findings suggest opportunities <lb/>for treatment of sex-steroid-related dysfunctions. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Exposure to the ultraviolet (UV) component of solar radiation in-<lb/>creases testosterone levels in men (Myerson and Neustadt, <lb/></body>

			<front>1939), estradiol and testosterone levels in fish (Mitchell et al., <lb/>2014), and the attractiveness of hens to cockerels (Jones et al., <lb/>2001). This suggests that exposure to UV plays a major role in <lb/>the regulation of sexuality on both behavioral and endocrinological <lb/>Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 ª 2021 The Authors. 1 <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>levels. The mechanism underlying this effect remains poorly <lb/>understood. <lb/>The reproductive endocrine system includes organs such as <lb/>the hypothalamus, pituitary, thyroid, pineal and adrenal glands, <lb/>ovaries, and testes (Rawindraraj et al., 2019). The system is gov-<lb/>erned by the hypothalamus, which sends signaling mediators <lb/>such as gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) to the pituitary <lb/>gland to induce release of follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and <lb/>luteinizing hormone (LH). In turn, these hormones transmit sig-<lb/>nals to the male and female gonads (Rawindraraj et al., 2019), <lb/>the testicles and the ovaries, respectively, promoting sex-steroid <lb/>production and gametogenesis (Rawindraraj et al., 2019). In fe-<lb/>males, FSH and LH stimulate the production of estrogen and <lb/>progesterone, which regulate ovulation and pregnancy (Barbieri, <lb/>2014; Rosner and Sarao, 2019). In most female mammals, sexual <lb/>activity and receptivity are confined to the preovulatory period <lb/>(Wallner et al., 2019) and the estrus phase (Kim et al., 2016) of <lb/>the menstrual/estrous cycle. These cyclic hormonal changes <lb/>dictate sexual behavior. In humans, it has been shown that <lb/>men respond more favorably to a woman&apos;s scent (Kuukasja ¨rvi <lb/>et al., 2004) or facial appearance (Roberts et al., 2004) during <lb/>the preovulatory phase of the woman&apos;s cycle. <lb/>The skin, consisting of epidermal, dermal, and hypodermal <lb/>layers, is the largest body organ (Golan et al., 2015; Yousef <lb/>et al., 2020). In contrast to the vast literature on the skin as a hor-<lb/>monal target (Slominski and Wortsman, 2000; Zouboulis, 2004), <lb/>its role as a source of hormones is less understood. The skin is <lb/>capable of producing and releasing hormones including vitamin <lb/>D, various peptides derived from proopiomelanocortin (POMC), <lb/>b-endorphin (Fell et al., 2014), and corticotropin-releasing hor-<lb/>mone (CRH) (Skobowiat and Slominski, 2015), resembling the <lb/>central regulatory paradigms of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adre-<lb/>nal axis (Slominski and Wortsman, 2000; Slominski et al., 2015). <lb/>b-endorphin release into the circulation is implicated in sun-<lb/>addiction behavior (Fell et al., 2014). Furthermore, ultraviolet B <lb/>(UVB) exposure is linked to increased expression of the stress-<lb/>response hormone CRH, as well as with components of the hy-<lb/>pothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis, including adrenocorti-<lb/>cotropic hormone (ACTH) and corticosterone, both in the skin <lb/>and in the plasma; stimulation of corticosterone production <lb/>was seen in the absence of pituitary involvement (Skobowiat <lb/>and Slominski, 2015; Skobowiat et al., 2011, 2017; Slominski <lb/>et al., 2013, 2018). These data situate the skin as an important <lb/>component in the regulation of stress-related behaviors and <lb/>sun-addiction behavior. <lb/>Given that the furless human skin contacts the environment in <lb/>general and the sun&apos;s rays in particular, it is conceivable that the <lb/>skin plays a role in hormone-related social, sexual, and reproduc-<lb/>tive behavior, but this assumption has yet to be verified. Solar ra-<lb/>diation (bright light and radiant heat) from the sun includes infrared, <lb/>visible, and UV. UV light is further divided into UVA, UVB, and UVC <lb/>(Ho ¨lzle and Ho ¨nigsmann, 2005). Here, we report, using behavioral <lb/>tests in mice, that UVB treatment significantly enhanced the sex-<lb/>ual responsiveness of females, which in turn increases male sexual <lb/>arousal and behavior. Furthermore, UVB treatment significantly <lb/>enhanced the desire for male-female interaction and female <lb/>attractiveness to males. In terms of physiological changes, we <lb/>found that UVB treatment increased the incidence of estrus days <lb/></front>

			<body>and enhanced ovary size and anti-Mullerian hormone (AMH) <lb/>expression in mice. Mechanistically, we demonstrated that the <lb/>UVB-induced sexual behavior and hormonal changes are medi-<lb/>ated by p53 activation in epidermal keratinocytes through a <lb/>skin-brain-gonadal axis. We also demonstrated, using question-<lb/>naires, that UVB treatment enhanced romantic passion in both <lb/>men and women and aggressiveness in men and is positively <lb/>correlated with testosterone level. This study suggests that UVB <lb/>phototherapy has potential as an ancillary treatment of sex-ste-<lb/>roid-related dysfunctions. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Daily UVB treatment enhances female sexual <lb/>attractiveness and receptiveness <lb/>To investigate the systemic effects of UVB radiation, we exposed <lb/>dorsally shaved mice to a single UVB dose of 800 mJ/cm 2 <lb/>(Svobodova ´et al., 2012) or to 50 mJ/cm 2 daily for 8 weeks, a <lb/>sub-erythemic UVB dose that is equivalent to 20-30 min of <lb/>midday sun (Fell et al., 2014). Blood samples were collected <lb/>24 h after UVB treatment for the acute model and after 8 weeks <lb/>of UVB treatment for chronic models (Figure S1A). As expected <lb/>(Malcov-Brog et al., 2018), skin pigmentation increased in the tails <lb/>of both male and female mice upon chronic exposure compared <lb/>with mock treatment (control) (Figure S1B). Furthermore, we <lb/>found significant positive activation Z score for upstream regula-<lb/>tors b-estradiol, testosterone, and estrogen in male mice (Fig-<lb/>ure 1A, right panel) and for estrogen, androgen, b-estradiol, and <lb/>progesterone in female mice after chronic UVB treatment <lb/>compared with the controls (Figure 1A, right panel). Acute <lb/>exposure of mice did not result in significant activation of sex-ste-<lb/>roid signaling (Figure S1C), suggesting that the chronic dose of <lb/>UVB exposure is a more physiologically relevant model. Sex ste-<lb/>roids released from gonads activate the neuronal pathways <lb/>involved in sexual behavior in zebrafish (Pradhan and Olsson, <lb/>2015), and testosterone injections enhance mounting behavior <lb/>in males by priming the neural tissues mediating the mating <lb/>behavior in guinea pigs (Phoenix et al., 1959). These data suggest <lb/>that UVB treatment enhances sex-steroid signaling in both male <lb/>and female mice and thus might influence mating behavior. <lb/>Mating behavior in rodents consists of several behaviors. At-<lb/>tractivity (Beach, 1976) involves efforts to elicit a response <lb/>from the opposite sex by vocalizations and olfactory and visual <lb/>stimuli (Beach, 1976). Proceptivity includes estrus responsive-<lb/>ness and purposive vocalizations (Beach, 1976), and female <lb/>receptivity involves lordosis behavior that involves readiness to <lb/>be involved in copulation, which culminates in successful intro-<lb/>mission (Beach, 1976). To assess the effect of UVB on reproduc-<lb/>tive behavior, we conducted a mating test (Figure 1B) in which a <lb/>sexually naive female, either UVB treated or mock treated (con-<lb/>trol), was introduced into the home cage of a sexually naive male <lb/>that had been UVB treated or mock treated (control). Sexual <lb/>receptivity in rodents varies with the stage of the female estrous <lb/>cycle (Zinck and Lima, 2013). To exclude the differences in fe-<lb/>male sexual receptivity, we evaluated the estrous cycle of the fe-<lb/>male by vaginal cytology (Caligioni, 2009) and used only females <lb/>in the estrus/proestrus stage for the mating test. During the 1-h <lb/>mating test, we monitored vocalization, sniffing, self-grooming, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>intromission, lordosis, and ejaculation as has been done previ-<lb/>ously (Achiraman et al., 2014; Beach, 1976; Haga et al., 2010; <lb/>Kimchi et al., 2007). <lb/>To determine the effect of UVB exposure on attractivity, we as-<lb/>sessed ultrasonic vocalizations (USVs) (Costantini and D&apos;Amato, <lb/>2006). During a male-female encounter, male mice exclusively <lb/>Figure 1. Daily UVB treatment enhances female sexual attractiveness and receptiveness <lb/>(A) Activation Z scores of predicted upstream regulators of mice upon UVB treatment for 6 weeks. <lb/>(B) Schematic representation of the mating test with male and female mice treated with UVB or control for 6 weeks. <lb/>(C-E) Total number, total time, and mean dominant frequency of USVs by control males in the presence of UVB-or control-treated females. <lb/>(F) Representative photograph of sexual behavior parameters. <lb/>(G) Total number of control male anogenital sniffing events of UVB-or control-treated females. <lb/>(H) Total time self-grooming by control males in the presence of UVB-or control-treated females. <lb/>(I) Latency intromission (left) and total number of intromissions (right) by control males on UVB-or control-treated females. <lb/>(J) UVB-or control-treated females&apos; lordosis quotient upon control male mounting. <lb/>(K) Total number of anogenital sniffing events (left) and total time self-grooming (right) for control females in the presence of UVB-or control-treated males. <lb/>(L) Plasma testosterone levels of males upon 8 weeks of UVB or control treatment. <lb/>(M) Total number of anogenital sniffing events by UVB-or control-treated males on a control-treated female. <lb/>(N) Total time spent self-grooming by UVB-or control-treated males for a control-treated female. <lb/>(O) Latency intromission (left panel), duration of intromission (middle panel), and total number of intromissions (right panel) by a UVB-or control-treated male on a <lb/>control female. <lb/>(P) Total number of anogenital sniffing events (left) and total time self-grooming (right) by UVB-or control-treated females on a control-treated male. <lb/>Data are means ± SEM, n = 3 (A and C-E), n = 7 (G-K and M-P), n = 8 (L). For data analysis, a two-tailed, unpaired Student&apos;s t test was performed. *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; <lb/>0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001; ns, not statistically significant. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 3 <lb/>Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>dominate the calls (frequency of 40-70 kHz), a behavior posi-<lb/>tively related to their level of sexual arousal (Kerchner, 2004). <lb/>We evaluated the effect of UVB treatment on the USVs of control <lb/>males in the presence of a UVB-treated or control female as a <lb/>stimulus. The audio recordings were then extracted into several <lb/>parameters, including total call duration and its mean dominant <lb/>frequency using UltraVox XT 3.1 software. The total number of <lb/>control male calls (Figure 1C; Figure S1D) and their total duration <lb/>(Figure 1D) were significantly higher when males were matched <lb/>with UVB-treated females than with control females. There was <lb/>no difference in frequencies of the calls with the highest energy <lb/>(mean dominant frequency) (Figure 1E), indicating that the dura-<lb/>tion and number of calls changed but the type of call did not. <lb/>These results suggest that UVB treatment of females enhances <lb/>their attractivity as indicated by the relative increase in male <lb/>vocalization parameters. <lb/>Next, we evaluated the effect of UVB treatment on female <lb/>attractiveness by measuring anogenital sniffing behavior (Clarke <lb/>and Trowill, 1971) (Figure 1F; Video S1). Males exhibited similar <lb/>sniffing behavior during the 1-h test session regardless of the <lb/>treatment the female received (Figure 1G). Self-grooming re-<lb/>flects an attraction to the opposite sex (Achiraman et al., 2014; <lb/>Haga et al., 2010), and the total duration of grooming (Figure 1F; <lb/>Videos S2A and S2B) was significantly enhanced for males in the <lb/>presence of UVB-treated females compared with control fe-<lb/>males (Figure 1H). Furthermore, we analyzed intromission, which <lb/>is a measurement of a successful mating event by the male on a <lb/>receptive female (Haga et al., 2010) (Figure 1F; Video S3). The la-<lb/>tency to intromit was significantly shorter for UVB-treated than <lb/>for control females (Figure 1I, left panel). The duration (Fig-<lb/>ure S1E) and total number of successful intromissions (Figure 1I, <lb/>right panel) were significantly greater when males were mated <lb/>with UVB-treated females than with controls. This indicated <lb/>that males are more attracted to and subsequently sexually <lb/>more successful with UVB-treated females. <lb/>During intromission, the receptiveness of the female is <lb/>measured by her lordotic response (Haga et al., 2010) (Figure 1F; <lb/>Video S3). We found a significant increase in the lordosis quo-<lb/>tient of UVB-treated females toward males compared with that <lb/>exhibited by mock-treated females (Figure 1K), suggesting that <lb/>UVB enhances female receptiveness. No change was observed <lb/>in the rearing behavior of females (Figure S1F), indicating no dif-<lb/>ference in forced intromission encounters. <lb/>Finally, male ejaculation did not significantly differ between <lb/>UVB-or mock-treated females (Figure 1F; Figure S1G; Video <lb/>S4). Similar tests were performed using UVB-treated males, <lb/>and differences between the number of ejaculations did not differ <lb/>when females were UVB or mock treated (Figure S1H). This <lb/>demonstrates that UVB treatment significantly enhances the <lb/>attractiveness and responsiveness of female mice, which in <lb/>turn increases the sexual arousal and behavior of males. <lb/>Next, we measured the effect of UVB on male attractiveness <lb/>by testing anogenital sniffing and grooming of a female in the <lb/>presence of UVB-treated or control males. Females exhibited <lb/>significantly more anogenital sniffing events toward UVB-treated <lb/>males compared with control males (Figure 1K, left panel). No <lb/>significant difference was observed in female grooming behavior <lb/>(Figure 1K, right panel). Similar tests were performed using UVB-<lb/>treated females, demonstrating same significant trend toward <lb/>the UVB-treated male compare to control male (Figure S1I), sug-<lb/>gesting an increase in male odor upon UVB exposure. <lb/>Because testosterone is involved in synthesis and secretion of <lb/>pheromones (Asaba et al., 2014), male attractivity (Mitra and <lb/>Sapolsky, 2012; Schellino et al., 2016), and social and emotional <lb/>bonds with females (van der Meij et al., 2012), we found signifi-<lb/>cantly higher plasma total testosterone levels in UVB-than <lb/>mock-treated male mice (Figure 1L). We found no change in <lb/>the level of testosterone in female mice upon UVB exposure <lb/>(Figure S1J). <lb/>Next, we tested the effect of UVB treatment on the social/sex-<lb/>ual behavior of males and females. No significant differences <lb/>were observed in anogenital sniffing, grooming behavior, latency <lb/>to intromit, duration of intromission, and number of intromissions <lb/>by control or UVB-treated male mice mated with control-treated <lb/>females (Figures 1M-1O). However, UVB treatment significantly <lb/>increased female anogenital sniffing and grooming behavior to-<lb/>ward control males (Figure 1P). This suggests that UVB treat-<lb/>ment enhances social/sexual behavior of females. Because <lb/>grooming behavior is also a known characteristic of anxiety in ro-<lb/>dents (Kalueff et al., 2016), we evaluated anxiety in an elevated <lb/>plus maze test, a classic measure of anxiety-related behavior <lb/>(Walf and Frye, 2007). Our results demonstrate that males <lb/>treated with UVB displayed a significant reduction in their anxiety <lb/>level compared with the control males (Figure S1K), as was <lb/>shown previously for male mice (Fell et al., 2014). No difference <lb/>was observed in the anxiety levels of females (Figure S1L). These <lb/>data support our conclusion that an increase in grooming <lb/>behavior might be indicative of attraction to the opposite sex ir-<lb/>respective of anxiety. Altogether, our data demonstrate that UVB <lb/>exposure enhances female attraction, the testosterone level in <lb/>males, and the social/sexual behavior of females. <lb/>UVB treatment enhances male and female sexual <lb/>behavior and female attraction <lb/>Sexual selection is based on the preference for social proximity <lb/>to an attractive partner (Puts, 2010). Given our findings that UVB <lb/>treatment significantly increases the attractiveness of males and <lb/>females, we investigated odor-triggered preferences and mate <lb/>selection through social proximity using the three-chamber test <lb/>(Yang et al., 2011), in which a subject&apos;s preference for one of <lb/>two stimuli is monitored (Figure 2A). The subject was a UVB-<lb/>or mock-treated male or female mouse, and the stimulus was <lb/>a UVB-or mock-treated male, a control female mouse, or a novel <lb/>object. The wire cages in this test setup ensure that the social <lb/>behavioral analysis is limited to the subject mouse (Yang et al., <lb/>2011). This setup allows olfactory, auditory, and visual stimuli. <lb/>All females were in the estrus/proestrus stage. <lb/>We found that when the stimulus was a UVB-treated or a <lb/>mock-treated control female mouse, the males exhibited a clear <lb/>preference for the UVB-treated female (Figure 2B). We analyzed <lb/>our results in terms of the latency of the subject mouse to venture <lb/>into a stimulus compartment, the frequency of visits, and the visit <lb/>duration. Our analysis showed that it took significantly less time <lb/>for the male to move near the wire cage (Figure 2C, left panel) or <lb/>into the zone of the wire cage (Figure S2A, left panel) of a UVB-<lb/>treated female than a mock-treated control female. Furthermore, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">4 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>G <lb/>F <lb/>H <lb/>I <lb/>E <lb/>C <lb/>(legend on next page) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 5 <lb/>Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>the subject males preferred to visit and stay near the wire cage <lb/>(Figure 2C, middle and right panels) and in the zone of the wire <lb/>cage (Figure S2A, middle and right panels) of a UVB-treated fe-<lb/>male rather than a control female. Similar trends of attraction to-<lb/>ward the UVB-treated female were observed when the subject <lb/>was a UVB-treated male (Figures S2B and S2C). These data <lb/>demonstrate a significant male preference for social proximity <lb/>to UVB-treated females, supporting our hypothesis that UVB <lb/>treatment enhances female attractiveness. <lb/>Next, we examined the effect of UVB on male attractiveness. <lb/>The subject female demonstrated no difference in the latency <lb/>to visit, the frequency of visits, or the total time spent near or in <lb/>the zone of a wire cage containing a UVB-treated or a mock-<lb/>treated male stimulus (Figures 2D and 2E; Figure S2D). Similar <lb/>trends were observed when the subject was UVB-treated female <lb/>except in a few parameters (Figures S2E and S2F), which might <lb/>be a result of an interaction between two UVB-treated animals. <lb/>Next, to check the effect of UVB on social behavior, we deter-<lb/>mined the latency to visit, the frequency of visits, and the total <lb/>time spent by UVB-treated or mock-treated males with a <lb/>mock-treated control female. We found a significant decrease <lb/>in the latency to visit and a significant increase in the total time <lb/>spent near the female by the UVB-treated male subjects <lb/>compare to the control male subjects (Figures 2F and 2G). No <lb/>difference was observed in the frequency to visit the female (Fig-<lb/>ure 2G, middle panel). This suggests that UVB treatment en-<lb/>hances male social behavior. Furthermore, we observed a signif-<lb/>icant decrease in the latency to visit and a significant increase in <lb/>the frequency of visits near a wire cage containing a male by the <lb/>UVB-treated female subjects compared with the control female <lb/>subjects (Figures 2H and 2I), although no difference was <lb/>observed in the total time spent next to a male (Figure 2I, right <lb/>panel). This suggests that UVB treatment enhances female so-<lb/>cial behavior. <lb/>To rule out the possibility that the results are due to mice <lb/>pausing in the center of the chamber, we measured the total <lb/>time spent by the subject mouse in the center of the chamber. <lb/>Notably, no difference was found between the two male subject <lb/>groups (Figure S2G) or the two female subject groups (Fig-<lb/>ure S2H). This confirmed that the observed desire for social <lb/>proximity in both male and female mice results from the UVB <lb/>treatment. <lb/>To validate that male preference for a UVB-treated female <lb/>mouse results from sexual signals, we repeated the three-cham-<lb/>ber test with a female subject, a UVB-treated female stimulus, <lb/>and a mock-treated control female stimulus (Figures S2I-S2L). <lb/>No variation in the social preference of the female subject was <lb/>observed (Figures S2I-S2L), supporting our hypothesis that <lb/>UVB treatment induces female sexual attractiveness to males. <lb/>We also performed the test with a female as a subject and a <lb/>male and a novel object (plastic block) as stimuli. The results <lb/>clearly showed that UVB-treated females preferred to visit and <lb/>stay near the male rather than near the novel object (Figures <lb/>S2I and S2M); the mock-treated control female demonstrated <lb/>no such preference (Figures S2M-S2O). These data support <lb/>our hypothesis that UVB treatment increases the social behavior <lb/>of female mice with male mice. Altogether, our observations <lb/>show that UVB treatment significantly enhances the desire for <lb/>male-female interaction and significantly increases the attrac-<lb/>tiveness of female mice. <lb/>UVB treatment induces romantic passion in humans <lb/>To conduct a controlled study of the effect of UVB treatment in <lb/>humans, we assembled a cohort of patients who were undergo-<lb/>ing phototherapy, which provides a documented dose of UVB <lb/>exposure. The patients were asked to fill an adapted Passionate <lb/>Love Scale (PLS) questionnaire (Hatfield and Sprecher, 1986) <lb/>before the first UVB treatment (time point T1) and 1 month there-<lb/>after (time point T2). Dermatosis was not expected to have <lb/>improved at the 1-month time point (Bae et al., 2017; Cameron <lb/>et al., 2002); thus, therapeutic success, or lack thereof, should <lb/>not influence the stress levels of subjects, and there should not <lb/>have been bias in our questionnaire because of therapeutic effi-<lb/>cacy. During this period, patients received a UVB dose (0.1-2.5 <lb/>J/cm) two or three times a week for 10-12 UVB treatments. The <lb/>PLS, developed to measure passionate love in intimate relation-<lb/>ships, focuses on intense longing for union with the other. We <lb/>found that the male participants&apos; scores were significantly higher <lb/>at T2 with respect to obsessive thoughts regarding their loved <lb/>ones, yearning to know everything about her, and endless desire <lb/>for affection from her (Table 1). However, they also reported <lb/>significantly less attraction to that person compared with at T1. <lb/>Female participants at T2 scored significantly higher when it <lb/>came to feeling that the person whom they loved most passion-<lb/>ately is the perfect romantic partner and experiencing a physical <lb/>response when touched by that person. Furthermore, because <lb/>we observed an increase in the level of testosterone following <lb/>UVB treatment in male mice (Figure 1L) and because testos-<lb/>terone is responsible for sexual and aggressive behavior (Muller, <lb/>2017), we asked our human cohort of patients undergoing <lb/>Figure 2. UVB treatment enhances male and female sexual behavior and female attraction <lb/>(A) Schematic representation of the three chamber test for subject and stimulus mice treated for 5 weeks with UVB or control treatment. <lb/>(B) Heatmap paths of a control male subject (n R 10) toward a UVB-or control-treated female stimulus. <lb/>(C) Latency of visit (left), frequency of visits (middle), and total time spent (right) by subject control-treated males toward the wire cage of a UVB-or control-treated <lb/>female stimulus. <lb/>(D) Heatmap paths of a control female subject toward a UVB-or control-treated male stimulus. <lb/>(E) As in (C) but for female subject movement toward a UVB-or control-treated male stimulus. <lb/>(F) Heatmap as in (B), depicting control or UVB-treated subject male movement toward control female stimuli. <lb/>(G) As in (C) but for control or UVB-treated male subject movement toward control female stimuli. <lb/>(H) Heatmap as in (B) but for UVB-or control-treated female subject movement toward control male stimuli. <lb/>(I) As in (C) but for UVB-or control-treated female subject movement toward control male stimuli. <lb/>Data are presented as means ± SEM, n R 10. For data analysis, a two-tailed, unpaired Student&apos;s t test was performed. *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; ns, not statistically <lb/>significant. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">6 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>phototherapy to complete an aggression questionnaire (Buss <lb/>and Perry, 1992) at T1 and T2. Our results indicate that male par-<lb/>ticipants were significantly more verbally aggressive at T2 than at <lb/>T1 (Table S1), whereas women showed no difference. Neither <lb/>men nor women had a significant change in the level of physical <lb/>aggression between T1 and T2. Altogether, our data suggest that <lb/>in humans, UVB treatment enhances passionate love in both <lb/>genders and increases some aspects of aggressiveness in men. <lb/>UVB treatment increases estrus incidence and the <lb/>number of growing follicles <lb/>UVB treatment was found to enhance female sexual/social <lb/>behavior, receptiveness, and attractiveness in mice, so we <lb/>investigated its effect on the estrus phase, because females <lb/>are more sexually receptive and attractive during its estrus stage <lb/>(Kim et al., 2016). To this end, we followed the estrous cycle of <lb/>eight female mice for 45 days using the vaginal smear method <lb/>(Caligioni, 2009) (Figure S3A). We found a significant increase <lb/>in the percentage of estrus days from the total number of 45 <lb/>tested days (Figure 3A) and in the length of the estrus phase (Fig-<lb/>ure 3B) in UVB-treated females. These data suggest that UVB <lb/>treatment modifies the estrus incidence of female mice, <lb/>increasing the number of estrus days in the cycles. <lb/>The estrous cycle is governed by the level of GnRH secretion <lb/>from the hypothalamus, which stimulates the pituitary gland to <lb/>release FSH and LH; these hormones regulate the ovarian cycle, <lb/>resulting in the production of sex-steroid hormones (Smith, <lb/>2009). We measured the levels of GnRH, FSH, and LH in the <lb/>plasma of female mice following 8 weeks of UVB or mock treat-<lb/>ment and found a significant rise in these hormones following <lb/>UVB treatment (Figure 3C). These data demonstrate that UVB <lb/>treatment induces the production of hormones involved in the <lb/>brain-gonadal axis. <lb/>FSH and LH regulate follicle growth in the ovaries, leading to <lb/>ovulation (Smith, 2009). Therefore, we surgically resected the <lb/>ovaries from UVB-treated and mock-treated control female <lb/>mice in their proestrus/estrus stage to assess the effect of the <lb/>UVB treatment on ovarian morphology. Interestingly, we found <lb/>a significant increase in the size and weight of the ovaries of <lb/>UVB-treated compared with mock-treated female mice (Fig-<lb/>ure 3D, left and middle panel), which was reflected in their histol-<lb/>ogy (Figure 3D, right panel). Moreover, there was a significant in-<lb/>crease in the expression of mRNAs encoding the progesterone <lb/>receptor (PGR), androgen receptor (AR), and estrogen receptors <lb/>(ESR1 and ESR2) in ovaries of UVB-treated females compared <lb/>with control females (Figure 3E). We also observed significant <lb/>upregulation in the enzymes involved in sex-steroid biosynthesis <lb/>in UVB-treated females compared with control females (Fig-<lb/>ure S3B). AMH suppresses the cyclic recruitment of primordial <lb/>follicles into the pool of growing follicles and inhibits FSH-depen-<lb/>dent follicle recruitment (Dewailly et al., 2016), thus playing an <lb/>important role in maintaining the ovarian reserve (Visser et al., <lb/>2006). AMH levels are an indicator of a female&apos;s ovarian reserve, <lb/>and the number of oocytes with high AMH levels reflect a pro-<lb/>longed fertility window (Santoro, 2017). Upon UVB treatment, <lb/>we found significant upregulation of the expression of AMH <lb/>and AMHR2, which encode the AMH receptor, in the ovaries of <lb/>female mice (Figure 3F), suggesting an increase in the pool of <lb/>growing follicles. Altogether, our data indicate that UVB treat-<lb/>ment of female mice enhances their estrous cycle, gonadotropin <lb/>secretion, follicle growth, and sex-steroid synthesis. <lb/>p53 modulates UVB-mediated sexual behavior and <lb/>ovarian changes <lb/>Skin interacts with solar/UVB light and has been suggested to <lb/>result in production and release of hormones (Fell et al., 2014; <lb/>Skobowiat and Slominski, 2015). Therefore, we reasoned that <lb/>the skin plays a role in hormone-related social, sexual, and <lb/>reproductive behavior in response to solar/UVB radiation. To <lb/>identify the regulators that drive the sexual behavior and ovarian <lb/>changes induced by UVB, we determined the overlap of the up-<lb/>stream transcription regulators upregulated in mouse plasma <lb/>proteomes upon UVB treatment by Ingenuity pathway analysis <lb/>(IPA) (Table S2), with the top 10 UVB-related transcription factors <lb/>identified by GeneCards and the list of skin regulators involved in <lb/>UVB response identified by GeneCards. The overlap of these <lb/>three lists indicated that p53 is a potential regulator (Figure 4A; <lb/>Table S3). Furthermore, p53 target genes, identified by IPA, <lb/>are significantly enriched in biological processes involved in <lb/>behavior and reproduction (Figure S4A), which is in line with <lb/>Table 1. Within-group differences in passionate love <lb/>Males <lb/>Females <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>Z <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>Z <lb/>Median Range Median Range <lb/>Median Range Median Range <lb/>Obsessive thoughts on __ a <lb/>3 <lb/>1-7 <lb/>5 <lb/>2-7 <lb/>À1.63 b * 2 <lb/>1-8 <lb/>3 <lb/>1-6 <lb/>À0.65 b <lb/>Rather be with __ than anyone else <lb/>8 <lb/>4-9 <lb/>8 <lb/>6-9 <lb/>À0.96 b <lb/>6.5 <lb/>1-9 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>1-9 <lb/>À0.95 b <lb/>Yearn to know everything on __ <lb/>7 <lb/>4-9 <lb/>8 <lb/>6-9 <lb/>À2.06 b * 5 <lb/>1-9 <lb/>5 <lb/>2-9 <lb/>À0.86 b <lb/>Endless appetite for affection from __ <lb/>7 <lb/>3-9 <lb/>8 <lb/>5-9 <lb/>À1.71 b * 4.5 <lb/>1-9 <lb/>5 <lb/>1-9 <lb/>À1.20 b <lb/>__ is the perfect romantic partner <lb/>8 <lb/>4-9 <lb/>8 <lb/>1-9 <lb/>À0.14 b <lb/>7 <lb/>2-9 <lb/>8 <lb/>3-9 <lb/>À2.00 b * <lb/>Sense body responding when __ touches 9 <lb/>3-9 <lb/>8 <lb/>1-9 <lb/>À0.32 b <lb/>7 <lb/>2-9 <lb/>8.5 <lb/>3-9 <lb/>À1.73 b * <lb/>Possess a powerful attraction to __ <lb/>8 <lb/>4-9 <lb/>7 <lb/>1-9 <lb/>À1.89 c * 7 <lb/>2-9 <lb/>7 <lb/>2-9 <lb/>À0.32 b <lb/>*p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01. <lb/>a <lb/>__, name of the person whom the participant loved most passionately. <lb/>b <lb/>Based on negative ranks. <lb/>c <lb/>Based on positive ranks. <lb/>Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 7 <lb/>Article <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>our observations. Therefore, we hypothesized that the skin p53 <lb/>modulates sexual behavior via a skin-brain-gonadal axis. <lb/>To test whether the UVB-induced sexual behavior changes we <lb/>observed are p53 dependent, we crossed mice that express Cre <lb/>specifically in keratinocytes (under the K14 promotor) with p53 <lb/>floxed mice (Marino et al., 2000) to generate a conditional p53 <lb/>knockout in epidermal keratinocytes (p53 flox/flox K14-Cre +/+ ), <lb/>referred to here as p53-KO mice (Fell et al., 2014); wild-type <lb/>p53 littermates (p53 flox/flox K14-Cre À/À ), referred to here as <lb/>p53-WT, were used as controls (Figure S4B). We treated the <lb/>p53-KO and p53-WT mice daily with UVB in a dose of 50 mJ/ <lb/>cm 2 . There was a significant decrease in the levels of p53 in <lb/>the whole skin of mice, as shown at protein level (Figure S4C) <lb/>and at mRNA levels for p53 and its downstream target p21 in <lb/>the skin (Figure S4D). These results validated the efficiency of <lb/>the knockout of p53 in epidermal keratinocytes. Consistent <lb/>with the known role of p53 in the pigmentation response (Mal-<lb/>cov-Brog et al., 2018), there was no increase in skin pigmenta-<lb/>tion in the p53-KO mice after 5 weeks of UVB treatment (Fig-<lb/>ure S4E). There were no differences in body weight between <lb/>these mice before and after treatment (Figure S4F). <lb/>No increases in the circulating levels of GnRH, LH, or FSH <lb/>were detected upon UVB treatment in the p53-KO females (Fig-<lb/>ure 4B). Moreover, no changes in ovary size, weight, or histology <lb/>were noted in UVB-treated p53-KO females compared with <lb/>mock-treated p53-KO females (Figure 4C). Furthermore, there <lb/>were no differences in the levels of mRNAs encoding steroido-<lb/>genic hormone receptors (PGR, AR, ESR1, and ESR2) (Fig-<lb/>ure 4D), in the expression level of the enzymes related to each <lb/>of these receptors in the ovaries (Figure S4G) or in the expression <lb/>of AMH and AMHR (Figure 4E) when UVB-treated and mock-<lb/>treated control p53-KO females were compared. These data <lb/>support our hypothesis that skin p53 drives the changes in <lb/>the ovaries and mediates sex-steroid induction upon UVB <lb/>treatment. <lb/>To evaluate how skin p53 influences sexual behavior, UVB-<lb/>treated and mock-treated control p53-WT and p53-KO mice <lb/>were subjected to the mating test (Figure 1B). All females were <lb/>in the estrus/proestrus stage. We found no difference in the ano-<lb/>genital sniffing behavior of p53-WT and p53-KO males toward <lb/>UVB-treated or mock-treated p53-WT females (Figure 4F, left <lb/>panel). In contrast, the amount of sniffing toward the UVB-<lb/>treated p53-KO females was significantly reduced compared <lb/>with that toward the mock-treated p53-KO females and UVB-<lb/>treated p53-WT females (Figure 4F, left panel). Furthermore, <lb/>we found a significant increase in the sniffing behavior of females <lb/>(both p53-WT and p53-KO) toward UVB-treated p53-WT males <lb/>compared with mock-treated control p53-WT males, but no <lb/>enhancement of sniffing behavior was observed toward the <lb/>UVB-treated p53-KO males (Figure 4F, right panel). This sug-<lb/>gests that UVB treatment induces a male mouse odor cue that <lb/>depends on skin p53. <lb/>Both p53-WT and p53-KO males exhibited significant <lb/>enhancement of facial and genital grooming in the presence of <lb/>a UVB-treated p53-WT female compared with a control p53-<lb/>WT female, whereas this UVB effect did not occur in the pres-<lb/>ence of the p53-KO females (Figure 4G, left panel). Furthermore, <lb/>we noted an increase in the grooming behavior of females (both <lb/>p53-WT and p53-KO) in the presence of UVB-treated p53-WT <lb/>males compared with control p53-WT males, a feature not <lb/>A <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Figure 3. Daily UVB treatment increases estrus incidence and the number of growing follicles <lb/>(A) Percentage total of the proestrus/estrus stage (estrus) and metestrus/diestrus stage (diestrus) of the control or UVB-treated female estrous cycle. <lb/>(B) Length of the estrous cycle in a control or UVB-treated female. <lb/>(C) Plasma levels of GnRH (n = 3), FSH (n = 5), and LH (n = 3) of control or UVB-treated female mice. <lb/>(D) Representative photograph of the ovaries (left), the weight of ovaries in milligrams (middle), and representative H&amp;E staining of female mice ovaries after <lb/>8 weeks of control or UVB treatment (right; scale bar, 500 mm). <lb/>(E) Relative mRNA expression from ovary section genes involved in female steroidogenesis after an 8-week control or UVB treatment. <lb/>(F) Relative expression of AMH and AMHR from an ovary section after an 8-week control or UVB treatment. <lb/>Data are presented as means ± SEM, n = 4 (A, B, E, and F), n = 3 (D). For data analysis, a two-tailed, unpaired Student&apos;s t test was performed. *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; <lb/>***p &lt; 0.001; ns, not statistically significant <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">8 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>A <lb/>C <lb/>F <lb/>H <lb/>I <lb/>J <lb/>G <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 4. p53 modulates UVB treatment-mediated sexual behavior and ovarian changes <lb/>(A) Overlap of predicted upstream regulators from mouse upon UVB treatment of 8 weeks with the top 10 UVB-related transcription factors (GeneCards) and with <lb/>skin regulators involved in UVB response (GeneCards). <lb/>(B) Plasma levels of GnRH (n = 3), FSH (n = 5), and LH (n = 3) in p53-KO females. <lb/>(C) Photograph of representative ovaries (left), weight in milligrams (mg) of ovaries (middle), and representative H&amp;E staining (right; scale bar, 500 mm) from p53-<lb/>KO females ovaries. <lb/>(D) Relative mRNA expression levels of genes involved in steroidogenesis from p53-KO female ovaries. <lb/>(E) Relative mRNA expression levels of AMH and AMHR from p53-KO female ovaries. <lb/>(F) Total number of anogenital sniffing events by males (control-or UVB-treated p53-WT and p53-KO) toward control-or UVB-treated p53-WT or p53-KO females <lb/>(left). Total number of anogenital sniffing events by females (control-or UVB-treated p53-WT and p53-KO) toward control-or UVB-treated p53-WT or p53-KO <lb/>males (right). <lb/>(G) Total time spent self-grooming by males (control-or UVB-treated p53-WT and p53-KO) in the presence of control-or UVB-treated p53-WT or p53-KO females <lb/>(left panel). Total time spent self-grooming by females (control-or UVB-treated p53-WT and p53-KO) in the presence of control-or UVB-treated p53-WT or p53-<lb/>KO males (right panel). <lb/>(H) Total number of intromissions (left) and total duration of intromissions (right) by males (control-or UVB-treated p53-WT and p53-KO) with control-or UVB-<lb/>treated p53-WT or p53-KO females. <lb/>(I) UVB-or control-treated p53-WT or p53-KO females&apos; lordosis quotient with control-and UVB-treated p53-WT or p53-KO males. <lb/>(legend continued on next page) <lb/>Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 9 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>observed in the presence of p53-KO males (Figure 4G, right <lb/>panel). The total number and duration of successful intromis-<lb/>sions by males (both p53-WT and p53-KO) on UVB-treated <lb/>p53-WT females were significantly higher than on control p53-<lb/>WT females, whereas no change was observed toward p53-<lb/>KO females (Figure 4H). <lb/>The lordotic response of a female was significantly higher in <lb/>UVB-treated p53-WT mice than in mock-treated control p53-<lb/>WT mice; there was no difference in p53-KO females (Figure 4I). <lb/>We also found that UVB-treated p53-WT males have signifi-<lb/>cantly higher levels of testosterone in their plasma than do <lb/>mock-treated p53-WT males and that this UVB effect was abol-<lb/>ished in p53-KO males (Figure S4H, left panel). No change was <lb/>observed in female testosterone levels upon UVB treatment (Fig-<lb/>ure S4H, right panel). These observations support our finding <lb/>that testosterone appears to be influenced by UVB-induced <lb/>skin p53. These data indicate that the enhancement of female <lb/>and male attractiveness to the opposite sex induced by UVB <lb/>treatment depends on p53 in the skin. <lb/>To further explore the mechanism by which p53 controls sex-<lb/>ual behavior upon UVB treatment, we overlapped two datasets, <lb/>p53 binding genes (identified using chromatin immunoprecipita-<lb/>tion sequencing [ChIP-seq]) (Nguyen et al., 2018) and UVB-<lb/>affected keratinocyte genes (identified using GeneCards) <lb/>(Figure 4J). To identify the downstream targets of p53 (i.e., <lb/>UVB-induced keratinocyte genes bound by p53), we overlapped <lb/>these genes with genes known to affect the hypothalamus (Kang <lb/>et al., 2000; McCann et al., 2003; Ray et al., 1996; Schmidt et al., <lb/>1995; Slominski et al., 2012), genes known to affect the pituitary <lb/>hypothalamus-pituitary-gonadal (HPG) and HPA axes (Rawin-<lb/>draraj et al., 2019), or genes known to affect the gonadal HPG <lb/>axis (Figure 4J). We found six overlapping genes that affect the <lb/>hypothalamus: IL6, LIF, IL-1b, NOS, Leptin, and LEP-R (Fig-<lb/>ure 4J; Table S4). IL-6 and LIF are known to increase the expres-<lb/>sion of POMC to enhance LH, FSH, and ACTH effects on the <lb/>downstream gonads and adrenal gland (Chida et al., 2005; Ray <lb/>et al., 1996). Interleukin (IL)-1b increases the expression of <lb/>CRH and GnRH from the hypothalamus (Kang et al., 2000; <lb/>Schmidt et al., 1995). NOS increases luteinizing hormone <lb/>releasing hormone (LHRH) levels (McCann et al., 2003), and <lb/>vice versa (Garrel et al., 1998). LHRH controls female lordosis <lb/>and male sexual behavior (McCann et al., 2003). Moreover, we <lb/>found one overlapping gene, CRH, that affects the pituitary. <lb/>The CRH protein is released from the skin upon UVB treatment <lb/>and acts on the local and central HPA axis (Skobowiat and Slo-<lb/>minski, 2015; Skobowiat et al., 2011). <lb/>We observed significant upregulation of IL1B, CRH, and IL6 <lb/>expression in UVB-treated p53-WT males, whereas the expres-<lb/>sion of these genes remained unchanged in the UVB-treated <lb/>p53-KO males (Figure S4I, upper panel). Furthermore, we <lb/>observed significant upregulation of IL1B, IL6, LIF, and CRH, <lb/>as expected based on previous work (Skobowiat and Slominski, <lb/>2015), and of NOS1 in UVB-treated p53-WT females, but not in <lb/>UVB-treated p53-KO females, compared with mock-treated <lb/>controls (Figure S4I, lower panel). Altogether, these findings <lb/>demonstrate that p53 expressed in epidermal keratinocytes reg-<lb/>ulates sexual behavior and ovarian changes through a skin-<lb/>brain-gonadal axis. <lb/>Solar exposure enhances human sex-related steroids <lb/>To examine the relevance of mouse data to humans, we re-<lb/>cruited volunteers (n = 9 men, n = 10 women; age 18-55 years) <lb/>who were asked to avoid sun exposure for 2 days and then <lb/>spend approximately 25 min in the sun on a bright sunny midday; <lb/>this resulted in a dose of approximately 2,000 mJ/cm 2 UV radia-<lb/>tion (measured using a UVX radiometer). Blood samples were <lb/>collected on the day before sun exposure and approximately <lb/>the same time on the day of sun exposure. Similar to the mouse <lb/>proteome data (Figure 1A), we found a significant positive activa-<lb/>tion Z score for upstream regulators b-estradiol, progesterone, <lb/>testosterone, and estrogen in men (Figure 5A, left panel) and <lb/>for estrogen, progesterone, and testosterone in women following <lb/>solar exposure compared with the control day before exposure <lb/>(Figure 5A, right panel). <lb/>Furthermore, we analyzed the testosterone levels of men aged <lb/>21-25 years (n = 13,086) from the Maccabi Health Service (Cho-<lb/>dick et al., 2020) and observed a significant peak in total testos-<lb/>terone level during the summer (July), indicative of testosterone <lb/>seasonal variation (Figure 5B). This is in line with a previous <lb/>report that testosterone levels increase in men following UV radi-<lb/>ation (Myerson and Neustadt, 1939). Finally, to determine how <lb/>pigment phenotype affects these solar responses, we retrieved <lb/>testosterone-level data of men aged 20-50 years from the Clalit <lb/>Health Services data-sharing platform (Israel) and divided them <lb/>into two groups based on the amount of ultraviolet radiation <lb/>(UVR) in their country of origin. Testosterone levels were signifi-<lb/>cantly higher (n = 1,607, p = 0.004) in men originating from coun-<lb/>tries with low UVR (UV &lt; 2,500 J/m 2 ) compared with individuals <lb/>who originated from countries with high UVR (UV R 4,500 J/m 2 ) <lb/>during summer months (May-September) for all body mass in-<lb/>dex values (Figure S5, left panel). No significant differences <lb/>(n = 2,309, p = 0.499) were observed during the winter months <lb/>(October-April) (Figure S5, right panel). Because skin coloration <lb/>is strongly related to levels of UVR in a given country (Chaplin, <lb/>2004), our data support the involvement of the skin reaction to <lb/>UVR in regulation of sexual behavior. Altogether, our data sug-<lb/>gest enhancement of sex steroids upon solar exposure and <lb/>demonstrate a positive correlation between solar exposure and <lb/>testosterone levels in human males. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Fitness is defined by the individual&apos;s reproductive success (Zim-<lb/>mer et al., 2016). Conception must be timed so that offspring are <lb/>born when they have the highest chances of survival and repro-<lb/>duction. This is likely the reason for seasonality in birth rates in <lb/>(J) Overlap between p53 DNA binding-based ChIP-seq (Nguyen et al., 2018), UVB-affected keratinocyte genes (GeneCards), and genes affecting hypothalamic, <lb/>pituitary, and gonad expression (Kang et al., 2000; McCann et al., 2003; Ray et al., 1996; Schmidt et al., 1995; Slominski et al., 2012). <lb/>Data are presented as means ± SEM, n = 4 (C-E), n = 3 (F-I). For data analysis, a two-tailed, unpaired Student&apos;s t test (B-E) or two-way ANOVA (F-I) was <lb/>performed. *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001; ns, not statistically significant. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">10 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>humans. There is a unimodal spring-summer (end of April-May) <lb/>peak in conceptions in most of Europe and a strongly bimodal <lb/>distribution in North America, with peaks in spring and autumn <lb/>(Roenneberg, 2004). Photoperiod and temperature have been <lb/>suggested to be the major environmental factors affecting this <lb/>seasonality (Roenneberg and Aschoff, 1990a, 1990b). Because <lb/>we showed a direct response to UVB, the source is not <lb/>the endogenous circannual clock, which generates seasonal <lb/>changes in physiology and behavior in the absence of environ-<lb/>mental cues (Scanes, 2015). Therefore, UVB may serve as a <lb/>backup mechanism, ensuring optimal reproduction timing and <lb/>direct influence on fitness. It is interesting that industrialization, <lb/>which shifted work from outdoors to indoors with eternal summer <lb/>conditions, characterized by a long photoperiod and mild tem-<lb/>peratures with almost no seasonality (Stevenson et al., 2015), <lb/>happened in parallel to an amplitude reduction in peaks in human <lb/>conceptions observed in today&apos;s industrialized nations (Foster <lb/>and Roenneberg, 2008; Roenneberg, 2004). It is possible that <lb/>the reduced exposure to UVB contributed to this change. <lb/>Our data suggest skin-brain crosstalk, in which the skin acts as a <lb/>dermato-endocrine organ, releasing hormones that affect the hy-<lb/>pothalamus-pituitary-gonadal axis. The mechanism of action may <lb/>be similar to that of b-endorphins (Fell et al., 2014) and CRH (Sko-<lb/>bowiat and Slominski, 2015), which are released from the skin and <lb/>affect the opioid system and axis, respectively, and/or to nerve fi-<lb/>bers, the immune system, or as-yet-unknown regulators. Because <lb/>eyes of mice and of human volunteers were not covered, we <lb/>cannot exclude the possibility that solar/UV radiation to the eye <lb/>affected the observed sexual behavior. UVB exposure via the <lb/>eye activates the hypothalamopituitary proopiomelanocortin sys-<lb/>tem, which is upstream of the HPA and HPG axes (Hiramoto et al., <lb/>2003). However, when we depleted p53 from skin keratinocytes, <lb/>we observed suppression of the UVB-induced sexual behavior <lb/>traits, as well as a significant decrease in the hormones of the <lb/>HPG axis, which favor our hypothesis that in addition to the <lb/>eyes, the skin has an active part in regulating sexuality. <lb/>Vitamin D synthesis is affected by UV absorption, which de-<lb/>pends on the skin tone of the individual (Webb et al., 2018; Ri-<lb/>chard et al., 2017); thus, individuals with the Fitzpatrick V (FST <lb/>V) skin type must receive a greater UV dose per unit time to syn-<lb/>thesize vitamin D compared with individuals with lighter skin <lb/>(Webb et al., 2018). In addition to the seasonality of birth rates, <lb/>conception rates, ovulation, socioeconomic status, and age <lb/>group as fertility effectors (Bobak and Gjonca, 2001; Lam <lb/>et al., 1994; Stolwijk et al., 1996), we propose that pigment <lb/>phenotype might play a role in regulating the skin-brain-gonadal <lb/>axis, thereby regulating sexual behavior. <lb/>All skin layers are innervated by sensory, sympathetic, and <lb/>parasympathetic nerve fibers that relay signals to the brain and <lb/>receive cues from it (Slominski et al., 2012). Sensory signals <lb/>from the skin to the brain include temperature, touch, pain, <lb/>stretch, itch, and vibration; they are sensed by skin receptors <lb/>that transfer the stimuli via nerve fibers directly to the brain <lb/>(Roosterman et al., 2006). Signals from the brain to the skin <lb/>include thermoregulation, sweat-gland function, blood flow, <lb/>adnexal functions (Roosterman et al., 2006), and hair graying <lb/>(Zhang et al., 2020). <lb/>Another mode of skin-brain crosstalk involves the combined <lb/>neural signals from the preoptic hypothalamus and peripheral <lb/>nerves that together trigger eccrine sweat glands (Stowers and <lb/>Liberles, 2016). In a response that is sex dependent (Stowers <lb/>and Liberles, 2016), pheromones are mainly secreted in axillary <lb/>sweat, which contains the odorous 16-androstenes (Verhaeghe <lb/>et al., 2013). Axillary secretions originate from apocrine odor <lb/>glands, eccrine sweat glands, and sebaceous glands located <lb/>in the skin (Verhaeghe et al., 2013). Pheromones are inducers <lb/>of communication and behavioral responses, including sexuality <lb/>and mating (Ferrero et al., 2013; Roberts et al., 2010; Stowers <lb/>and Liberles, 2016; Verhaeghe et al., 2013). Although the neural <lb/>triggers for pheromone synthesis and secretion are poorly un-<lb/>derstood, it has been established that eccrine sweat glands <lb/>are controlled by hypothalamus cues (Stowers and Liberles, <lb/>2016). Therefore, we cannot exclude the possibility that part of <lb/>the observed effect is mediated by pheromones: UVB radiation <lb/>may alter hypothalamus activity or directly affect axillary secre-<lb/>tion. Both possibilities should be further investigated. In line <lb/>with this, knock down of p53 has been shown to trigger the <lb/>DNA damage response in skin keratinocytes that results in <lb/>peeling of these cells (Farmer et al., 1992; Fields and Jang, <lb/>1990; Levine et al., 2006; de Pedro et al., 2018). This by itself <lb/>might be a trigger of attractiveness and should be investigated <lb/>in the future. <lb/>It is worth putting in mind that species differences play an <lb/>essential role in activating mating behavior via the circulating <lb/>sex steroids. For example, female rhesus monkeys continue to <lb/>mate with males for weeks after ovariectomy, wherein there is <lb/>withdrawal of estradiol (Baum et al., 1977). In contrast, ovariec-<lb/>tomized female mice cease to mate within few days of the <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 5. Solar exposure enhances human <lb/>sex-related steroids <lb/>(A) Predicted upstream regulators of the differential <lb/>blood plasma proteins from humans following a <lb/>single solar exposure (2,000 mJ/cm 2 UV) (n = 5 <lb/>humans for each condition). <lb/>(B) Total testosterone levels of men aged 21-25 <lb/>years (n = 13,086). Plot depicts monthly means on <lb/>a cubic spline of calendar month (January-<lb/>December; 2 degrees of freedom). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 11 <lb/>Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>procedure and resume it only upon receiving an injection of <lb/>estradiol benzoate followed by progesterone (Edwards, 1971). <lb/>Likewise, male rhesus monkeys typically continue mating for <lb/>many months after castration (Phoenix et al., 1973), whereas <lb/>most strains of male mice stop mating within 3-4 weeks after <lb/>castration (Thompson et al., 1976). <lb/>Our quantitative questionnaire results show that both sexes <lb/>have a tendency toward higher levels of passion following UV <lb/>treatment. Passion takes two forms, emotional and sexual. <lb/>UVB radiation affected different components of passion in men <lb/>than in women. UVB-treated women scored higher on questions <lb/>about physical arousal that related more to sexual passion and <lb/>idealizing the connection, whereas men scored higher on the <lb/>cognitive dimension of passion, which involves obsessive <lb/>thoughts about the partner and wanting to know more about <lb/>her. The questionnaire we used measured romantic passion, <lb/>rather than physiological/sexual passion, due to institutional re-<lb/>view board (IRB) ethical concerns regarding sensitive sexually <lb/>oriented questions. Future studies on this topic should address <lb/>physiological arousal more directly and should be geared toward <lb/>the precise identification of the different effects of UVB on the <lb/>sexual behavior of men and women. <lb/>STAR+METHODS <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Detailed methods are provided in the online version of this paper <lb/>and include the following: <lb/>d KEY RESOURCES TABLE <lb/>d RESOURCE AVAILABILITY <lb/>B Lead contact <lb/>B Materials availability <lb/>B Data and code availability <lb/>d EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS <lb/>B Mouse models and habituation <lb/>B Human cohort <lb/>B Human cohort testosterone study <lb/>B Human questionnaire <lb/>d METHOD DETAILS <lb/>B UV treatment <lb/>B Melanin intensity quantification <lb/>B Mouse blood draw <lb/>B Human cohort Solar-exposure study <lb/>B Human blood draw <lb/>B Proteolysis and mass spectrometry <lb/>B Proteomic analysis <lb/>B ELISA <lb/>B Mating test <lb/>B Ultrasonic vocalization <lb/>B Elevated plus maze test <lb/>B Three-chamber test <lb/>B Male subject and two female stimuli <lb/>B Female subject and two male stimuli <lb/>B Female subject and two female stimuli <lb/>B Female subject, a male stimulus, and a novel-object <lb/>stimulus <lb/>B Vaginal smears for estrous cycle evaluation <lb/>B RNA purification and qRT-PCT <lb/>B Histology <lb/>B Genotyping <lb/>B Immunoblotting <lb/>d QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS <lb/>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION <lb/>Supplemental information can be found online at https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>celrep.2021.109579. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>The authors thank Prof. Eli Pikarsky (The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, <lb/>Israel) for the gift of the p53-floxed mice and Prof. Itai Ben-Porath for the gift <lb/>of K14 CRE mice (The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Israel). C.L. thanks <lb/>Prof. Yossi Yovel (Department of Zoology, Faculty of Life Sciences, Tel Aviv <lb/>University) for providing the recording instrument and analysis and Prof. Uri <lb/>Alon, Prof. Noam Sobel (Weizmann Institute of Science, Israel) for useful dis-<lb/>cussions, and Yuval and Omer Levy for infinite joy. C.L. acknowledges grant <lb/>support from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European <lb/>Union&apos;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation program (grant 726225) and <lb/>the Israel Science Foundation (ISF) (grant 2017/20). R. Parikh is the recipient <lb/>of a CBRC 2020 travel grant and 3 rd Esther and Zvi Weinstat Graduate Student <lb/>Award, 2021, and would like to thank her family for their love and support. <lb/>Research in A.W.&apos;s lab is supported in part by the ISF (grant 1781/16), Israel <lb/>Ministry of Science and Technology (grants 3-13608 and 84/19), and EPM Inc. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>R. Parikh, conceptualization, methodology, validation, formal analysis, inves-<lb/>tigation, writing -original draft, and visualization. E.S., conceptualization and <lb/>formal analysis. S.P., methodology and validation (human cohort study). <lb/>K.M., D.L., and O.K.-M., formal analysis (human questionnaire). L.B. and <lb/>A.W., methodology and resources. S.T., G.S., S.M., T.Z., H.K., and G.C., <lb/>investigation and formal analysis (human testosterone data). M.M., formal <lb/>analysis (mass spectrometry). A.B., resources (ultrasonic vocalization). <lb/>N.K.-S., writing -review &amp; editing. H.B.-J., formal analysis (ovary cross sec-<lb/>tions). D.B.-Y., H.A., and T.G., writing -review &amp; editing. H.M. and M.P., re-<lb/>sources (human questionnaire data from phototherapy clinic). Y.L., R.B., and <lb/>E.N., visualization. Y.G., formal analysis (human epidemiological data). R.H., <lb/>investigation. R.S., methodology and writing -review &amp; editing (ovarian exper-<lb/>iments). T.K., visualization (sexual behavioral data). R. Percik, investigation <lb/>and writing -review &amp; editing. C.L., conceptualization, methodology, writing -<lb/>original draft, visualization, supervision, project administration, and funding <lb/>acquisition. All authors reviewed the final draft and approved it. <lb/>DECLARATION OF INTERESTS <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: November 9, 2020 <lb/>Revised: May 12, 2021 <lb/>Accepted: July 30, 2021 <lb/>Published: August 24, 2021 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Achiraman, S., SankarGanesh, D., Kannan, S., Kamalakkannan, S., Nirmala, <lb/>N., and Archunan, G. (2014). Response male mice to odours of female <lb/>mice in different stages of oestrous cycle: self-grooming behaviour and the ef-<lb/>fect of castration. Indian J. Exp. Biol. 52, 30-35. <lb/>Ajayi, A.F., and Akhigbe, R.E. (2020). Staging of the estrous cycle and induc-<lb/>tion of estrus in experimental rodents: an update. Fertil. Res. Pract. 6, 5. <lb/>Asaba, A., Hattori, T., Mogi, K., and Kikusui, T. (2014). Sexual attractiveness of <lb/>male chemicals and vocalizations in mice. Front. Neurosci. 8, 231. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">12 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Bae, J.M., Jung, H.M., Hong, B.Y., Lee, J.H., Choi, W.J., Lee, J.H., and Kim, <lb/>G.M. (2017). Phototherapy for vitiligo: A systematic review and meta-analysis. <lb/>JAMA Dermatol. 153, 666-674. <lb/>Barbieri, R.L. (2014). The endocrinology of the menstrual cycle. Methods Mol. <lb/>Biol. 1154, 145-169. <lb/>Baum, M.J., Everitt, B.J., Herbert, J., and Keverne, E.B. (1977). Hormonal ba-<lb/>sis of proceptivity and receptivity in female primates. Arch. Sex. Behav. 6, <lb/>173-192. <lb/>Beach, F.A. (1976). Sexual attractivity, proceptivity, and receptivity in female <lb/>mammals. Horm. Behav. 7, 105-138. <lb/>Bobak, M., and Gjonca, A. (2001). The seasonality of live birth is strongly influ-<lb/>enced by socio-demographic factors. Hum. Reprod. 16, 1512-1517. <lb/>Buss, A.H., and Perry, M. (1992). The aggression questionnaire. J. Pers. Soc. <lb/>Psychol. 63, 452-459. <lb/>Caligioni, C.S. (2009). Assessing reproductive status/stages in mice. Curr. Pro-<lb/>toc. Neurosci. 4 (Appendix), 4I. <lb/>Cameron, H., Dawe, R.S., Yule, S., Murphy, J., Ibbotson, S.H., and Ferguson, <lb/>J. (2002). A randomized, observer-blinded trial of twice vs. three times weekly <lb/>narrowband ultraviolet B phototherapy for chronic plaque psoriasis. Br. J. Der-<lb/>matol. 147, 973-978. <lb/>Chaplin, G. (2004). Geographic distribution of environmental factors influ-<lb/>encing human skin coloration. Am. J. Phys. Anthropol. 125, 292-302. <lb/>Chida, D., Imaki, T., Suda, T., and Iwakura, Y. (2005). Involvement of cortico-<lb/>tropin-releasing hormone-and interleukin (IL)-6-dependent proopiomelano-<lb/>cortin induction in the anterior pituitary during hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal <lb/>axis activation by IL-1a. Endocrinology 146, 5496-5502. <lb/>Chodick, G., Epstein, S., and Shalev, V. (2020). Secular trends in testos-<lb/>terone-findings from a large state-mandate care provider. Reprod. Biol. En-<lb/>docrinol. 18, 19. <lb/>Clarke, S., and Trowill, J.A. (1971). Sniffing and motivated behavior in the rat. <lb/>Physiol. Behav. 6, 49-52. <lb/>Costantini, F., and D&apos;Amato, F. (2006). Ultrasonic vocalizations in mice and <lb/>rats: social contexts and functions. Dong Wu Xue Bao 52, 619-633. <lb/>Cox, J., and Mann, M. (2008). MaxQuant enables high peptide identification <lb/>rates, individualized p.p.b.-range mass accuracies and proteome-wide pro-<lb/>tein quantification. Nat. Biotechnol. 26, 1367-1372. <lb/>de Pedro, I., Alonso-Lecue, P., Sanz-Go ´mez, N., Freije, A., and Gandarillas, A. <lb/>(2018). Sublethal UV irradiation induces squamous differentiation via a p53-in-<lb/>dependent, DNA damage-mitosis checkpoint. Cell Death Dis. 9, 1094. <lb/>Dewailly, D., Robin, G., Peigne, M., Decanter, C., Pigny, P., and Catteau-Jon-<lb/>ard, S. (2016). Interactions between androgens, FSH, anti-M€ ullerian hormone <lb/>and estradiol during folliculogenesis in the human normal and polycystic ovary. <lb/>Hum. Reprod. Update 22, 709-724. <lb/>Dror, S., Sander, L., Schwartz, H., Sheinboim, D., Barzilai, A., Dishon, Y., <lb/>Apcher, S., Golan, T., Greenberger, S., Barshack, I., et al. (2016). Melanoma <lb/>miRNA trafficking controls tumour primary niche formation. Nat. Cell Biol. <lb/>18, 1006-1017. <lb/>Edwards, D.A. (1971). Neonatal administration of androstenedione, testos-<lb/>terone or testosterone propionate: effects on ovulation, sexual receptivity <lb/>and aggressive behavior in female mice. Physiol. Behav. 6, 223-228. <lb/>Farmer, G., Bargonetti, J., Zhu, H., Friedman, P., Prywes, R., and Prives, C. <lb/>(1992). Wild-type p53 activates transcription in vitro. Nature 358, 83-86. <lb/>Fell, G.L., Robinson, K.C., Mao, J., Woolf, C.J., and Fisher, D.E. (2014). Skin <lb/>b-endorphin mediates addiction to UV light. Cell 157, 1527-1534. <lb/>Ferrero, D.M., Moeller, L.M., Osakada, T., Horio, N., Li, Q., Roy, D.S., Cichy, A., <lb/>Spehr, M., Touhara, K., and Liberles, S.D. (2013). A juvenile mouse pheromone <lb/>inhibits sexual behaviour through the vomeronasal system. Nature 502, <lb/>368-371. <lb/>Fields, S., and Jang, S.K. (1990). Presence of a potent transcription activating <lb/>sequence in the p53 protein. Science 249, 1046-1049. <lb/>Foster, R.G., and Roenneberg, T. (2008). Human responses to the geophysical <lb/>daily, annual and lunar cycles. Curr. Biol. 18, R784-R794. <lb/>Garrel, G., Lerrant, Y., Siriostis, C., Be ´rault, A., Magre, S., Bouchaud, C., and <lb/>Counis, R. (1998). Evidence that gonadotropin-releasing hormone stimulates <lb/>gene expression and levels of active nitric oxide synthase type I in pituitary go-<lb/>nadotrophs, a process altered by desensitization and, indirectly, by gonadal <lb/>steroids. Endocrinology 139, 2163-2170. <lb/>Glaich, O., Parikh, S., Bell, R.E., Mekahel, K., Donyo, M., Leader, Y., Shaye-<lb/>vitch, R., Sheinboim, D., Yannai, S., Hollander, D., et al. (2019). DNA methyl-<lb/>ation directs microRNA biogenesis in mammalian cells. Nat. Commun. 10, <lb/>5657. <lb/>Golan, T., Messer, A.R., Amitai-Lange, A., Melamed, Z., Ohana, R., Bell, R.E., <lb/>Kapitansky, O., Lerman, G., Greenberger, S., Khaled, M., et al. (2015). Interac-<lb/>tions of Melanoma Cells with Distal Keratinocytes Trigger Metastasis via Notch <lb/>Signaling Inhibition of MITF. Mol. Cell 59, 664-676. <lb/>Haga, S., Hattori, T., Sato, T., Sato, K., Matsuda, S., Kobayakawa, R., Sakano, <lb/>H., Yoshihara, Y., Kikusui, T., and Touhara, K. (2010). The male mouse phero-<lb/>mone ESP1 enhances female sexual receptive behaviour through a specific <lb/>vomeronasal receptor. Nature 466, 118-122. <lb/>Hatfield, E., and Sprecher, S. (1986). Measuring passionate love in intimate re-<lb/>lationships. J. Adolesc. 9, 383-410. <lb/>Hiramoto, K., Yanagihara, N., Sato, E.F., and Inoue, M. (2003). Ultraviolet B <lb/>irradiation of the eye activates a nitric oxide-dependent hypothalamopituitary <lb/>proopiomelanocortin pathway and modulates functions of a-melanocyte-<lb/>stimulating hormone-responsive cells. J. Invest. Dermatol. 120, 123-127. <lb/>Ho ¨lzle, E., and Ho ¨nigsmann, H. (2005). [UV-radiation-sources, wavelength, <lb/>environment]. J. Dtsch. Dermatol. Ges. 3 (Suppl 2), S3-S10. <lb/>Jones, E.K.M., Prescott, N.B., Cook, P., White, R.P., and Wathes, C.M. (2001). <lb/>Ultraviolet light and mating behaviour in domestic broiler breeders. Br. Poult. <lb/>Sci. 42, 23-32. <lb/>Kalueff, A.V., Stewart, A.M., Song, C., Berridge, K.C., Graybiel, A.M., and Fen-<lb/>tress, J.C. (2016). Neurobiology of rodent self-grooming and its value for trans-<lb/>lational neuroscience. Nat. Rev. Neurosci. 17, 45-59. <lb/>Kang, S.S., Kim, S.R., Leonhardt, S., Jarry, H., Wuttke, W., and Kim, K. (2000). <lb/>Effect of interleukin-1b on gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) and GnRH <lb/>receptor gene expression in castrated male rats. J. Neuroendocrinol. 12, <lb/>421-429. <lb/>Kerchner, M. (2004). Ultrasonic courtship vocalizations of adult male mice: A <lb/>laboratory exercise illustrating comparable activation by either estradiol or <lb/>testosterone. J. Undergrad. Neurosci. Educ. 2, A50-A61. <lb/>Kim, H., Son, J., Yoo, H., Kim, H., Oh, J., Han, D., Hwang, Y., and Kaang, B.K. <lb/>(2016). Effects of the female Estrous cycle on the sexual behaviors and ultra-<lb/>sonic vocalizations of male C57BL/6 and autistic BTBR T+ tf/J Mice. Exp. Neu-<lb/>robiol. 25, 156-162. <lb/>Kimchi, T., Xu, J., and Dulac, C. (2007). A functional circuit underlying male <lb/>sexual behaviour in the female mouse brain. Nature 448, 1009-1014. <lb/>Kuukasja ¨rvi, S., Eriksson, C.J.P., Koskela, E., Mappes, T., Nissinen, K., and <lb/>Rantala, M.J. (2004). Attractiveness of women&apos;s body odors over the men-<lb/>strual cycle: The role of oral contraceptives and receiver sex. Behav. Ecol. <lb/>15, 579-584. <lb/>Lam, D.A., Miron, J.A., and Riley, A. (1994). Modeling seasonality in fecund-<lb/>ability, conceptions, and births. Demography 31, 321-346. <lb/>Levine, A.J., Hu, W., and Feng, Z. (2006). The P53 pathway: what questions <lb/>remain to be explored? Cell Death Differ. 13, 1027-1036. <lb/>Malcov-Brog, H., Alpert, A., Golan, T., Parikh, S., Nordlinger, A., Netti, F., <lb/>Sheinboim, D., Dror, I., Thomas, L., Cosson, C., et al. (2018). UV-Protection <lb/>Timer Controls Linkage between Stress and Pigmentation Skin Protection <lb/>Systems. Mol. Cell 72, 444-456.e7. <lb/>Marino, S., Vooijs, M., van Der Gulden, H., Jonkers, J., and Berns, A. (2000). <lb/>Induction of medulloblastomas in p53-null mutant mice by somatic inactivation <lb/>of Rb in the external granular layer cells of the cerebellum. Genes Dev. 14, 994-<lb/>1004. <lb/>McCann, S., Mastronardi, C., Walczewska, A., Karanth, S., Rettori, V., and Yu, <lb/>W. (2003). The Role of Nitric Oxide (NO) in Control of LHRH Release that <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 13 <lb/>Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Mediates Gonadotropin Release and Sexual Behavior. Curr. Pharm. Des. 9, <lb/>381-390. <lb/>Mitchell, D.L., Fernandez, A.A., Garcia, R., Paniker, L., Lin, K., Hanninen, A., <lb/>Zigelsky, K., May, M., Nuttall, M., Lo, H.H., et al. (2014). Acute exposure to ul-<lb/>traviolet-B radiation modulates sex steroid hormones and receptor expression <lb/>in the skin and may contribute to the sex bias of melanoma in a fish model. <lb/>Pigment Cell Melanoma Res. 27, 408-417. <lb/>Mitra, R., and Sapolsky, R.M. (2012). Short-term enrichment makes male rats <lb/>more attractive, more defensive and alters hypothalamic neurons. PLoS ONE <lb/>7, e36092. <lb/>Muller, M.N. (2017). Testosterone and reproductive effort in male primates. <lb/>Horm. Behav. 91, 36-51. <lb/>Myerson, A., and Neustadt, R. (1939). Influence of ultraviolet irradiation upon <lb/>excretion of sex hormones in the male. Endocrinology 25, 7-12. <lb/>Nghiem, D.X., Kazimi, N., Mitchell, D.L., Vink, A.A., Ananthaswamy, H.N., <lb/>Kripke, M.L., and Ullrich, S.E. (2002). Mechanisms underlying the suppression <lb/>of established immune responses by ultraviolet radiation. J. Invest. Dermatol. <lb/>119, 600-608. <lb/>Nguyen, T.T., Grimm, S.A., Bushel, P.R., Li, J., Li, Y., Bennett, B.D., Lavender, <lb/>C.A., Ward, J.M., Fargo, D.C., Anderson, C.W., et al. (2018). Revealing a hu-<lb/>man p53 universe. Nucleic Acids Res. 46, 8153-8167. <lb/>Perez-Riverol, Y., Csordas, A., Bai, J., Bernal-Llinares, M., Hewapathirana, S., <lb/>Kundu, D.J., Inuganti, A., Griss, J., Mayer, G., Eisenacher, M., et al. (2019). The <lb/>PRIDE database and related tools and resources in 2019: Improving support <lb/>for quantification data. Nucleic Acids Res. 47, D442-D450. <lb/>Phoenix, C.H., Goy, R.W., Gerall, A.A., and Young, W.C. (1959). Organizing ac-<lb/>tion of prenatally administered testosterone propionate on the tissues medi-<lb/>ating mating behavior in the female guinea pig. Endocrinology 65, 369-382. <lb/>Phoenix, C.H., Slob, A.K., and Goy, R.W. (1973). Effects of castration and <lb/>replacement therapy on sexual behavior of adult male rhesuses. J. Comp. <lb/>Physiol. Psychol. 84, 472-481. <lb/>Pradhan, A., and Olsson, P.E. (2015). Zebrafish sexual behavior: role of sex <lb/>steroid hormones and prostaglandins. Behav. Brain Funct. 11, 23. <lb/>Puts, D.A. (2010). Beauty and the beast: Mechanisms of sexual selection in hu-<lb/>mans. Evol. Hum. Behav. 31, 157-175. <lb/>Rawindraraj, A.D., Basit, H., and Jialal, I. (2019). Physiology, Anterior Pituitary <lb/>(StatPearls). <lb/>Ray, D.W., Ren, S.G., and Melmed, S. (1996). Leukemia inhibitory factor (LIF) <lb/>stimulates proopiomelanocortin (POMC) expression in a corticotroph cell line. <lb/>Role of STAT pathway. J. Clin. Invest. 97, 1852-1859. <lb/>Richard, A., Rohrmann, S., and Quack Lo ¨tscher, K.C. (2017). Prevalence of <lb/>vitamin D deficiency and its associations with skin color in pregnant women <lb/>in the first trimester in a sample from Switzerland. Nutrients 9, E260. <lb/>Roberts, S.C., Havlicek, J., Flegr, J., Hruskova, M., Little, A.C., Jones, B.C., <lb/>Perrett, D.I., and Petrie, M. (2004). Female facial attractiveness increases dur-<lb/>ing the fertile phase of the menstrual cycle. Proc. Biol. Sci. 271 (Suppl 5), S270-<lb/>S272. <lb/>Roberts, S.A., Simpson, D.M., Armstrong, S.D., Davidson, A.J., Robertson, <lb/>D.H., McLean, L., Beynon, R.J., and Hurst, J.L. (2010). Darcin: a male phero-<lb/>mone that stimulates female memory and sexual attraction to an individual <lb/>male&apos;s odour. BMC Biol. 8, 75. <lb/>Roenneberg, T., and Aschoff, J. (1990a). Annual rhythm of human reproduc-<lb/>tion: I. Biology, sociology, or both? J. Biol. Rhythms 5, 195-216. <lb/>Roenneberg, T., and Aschoff, J. (1990b). Annual Rhythm of Human Reproduc-<lb/>tion: II. Environmental Correlations. J. Biol. Rhythms 5, 217-239. <lb/>Roenneberg, T. (2004). The decline in human seasonality. J. Biol. Rhythms 19, <lb/>193-195, discussion 196-197. <lb/>Roosterman, D., Goerge, T., Schneider, S.W., Bunnett, N.W., and Steinhoff, M. <lb/>(2006). Neuronal control of skin function: the skin as a neuroimmunoendocrine <lb/>organ. Physiol. Rev. 86, 1309-1379. <lb/>Rosner, J., and Sarao, M.S. (2019). Physiology, Female Reproduction (Stat-<lb/>Pearls). <lb/>Santoro, N. (2017). Using Antim€ ullerian Hormone to Predict Fertility. JAMA <lb/>318, 1333-1334. <lb/>C.G. Scanes, ed. (2015). Sturkie&apos;s Avian Physiology, Sixth Edition (Academic <lb/>Press). <lb/>Schellino, R., Trova, S., Cimino, I., Farinetti, A., Jongbloets, B.C., Pasterkamp, <lb/>R.J., Panzica, G., Giacobini, P., De Marchis, S., and Peretto, P. (2016). Oppo-<lb/>site-sex attraction in male mice requires testosterone-dependent regulation of <lb/>adult olfactory bulb neurogenesis. Sci. Rep. 6, 36063. <lb/>Schmidt, E.D., Janszen, A.W., Wouterlood, F.G., and Tilders, F.J. (1995). Inter-<lb/>leukin-1-induced long-lasting changes in hypothalamic corticotropin-releasing <lb/>hormone (CRH)-neurons and hyperresponsiveness of the hypothalamus-pitu-<lb/>itary-adrenal axis. J. Neurosci. 15, 7417-7426. <lb/>Skobowiat, C., and Slominski, A.T. (2015). UVB Activates Hypothalamic-<lb/>Pituitary-Adrenal Axis in C57BL/6 Mice. J. Invest. Dermatol. 135, 1638-<lb/>1648. <lb/>Skobowiat, C., Dowdy, J.C., Sayre, R.M., Tuckey, R.C., and Slominski, A. <lb/>(2011). Cutaneous hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis homolog: regula-<lb/>tion by ultraviolet radiation. Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab. 301, <lb/>E484-E493. <lb/>Skobowiat, C., Postlethwaite, A.E., and Slominski, A.T. (2017). Skin Exposure <lb/>to Ultraviolet B Rapidly Activates Systemic Neuroendocrine and Immunosup-<lb/>pressive Responses. Photochem. Photobiol. 93, 1008-1015. <lb/>Slominski, A., and Wortsman, J. (2000). Neuroendocrinology of the skin. En-<lb/>docr. Rev. 21, 457-487. <lb/>Slominski, A.T., Zmijewski, M.A., Skobowiat, C., Zbytek, B., Slominski, R.M., <lb/>and Steketee, J.D. (2012). Sensing the environment: regulation of local and <lb/>global homeostasis by the skin&apos;s neuroendocrine system. Adv. Anat. Embryol. <lb/>Cell Biol. 212 (v, vii), 1-115. <lb/>Slominski, A.T., Zmijewski, M.A., Zbytek, B., Tobin, D.J., Theoharides, T.C., <lb/>and Rivier, J. (2013). Key role of CRF in the skin stress response system. En-<lb/>docr. Rev. 34, 827-884. <lb/>Slominski, A.T., Manna, P.R., and Tuckey, R.C. (2015). On the role of skin in the <lb/>regulation of local and systemic steroidogenic activities. Steroids 103, 72-88. <lb/>Slominski, A.T., Zmijewski, M.A., Plonka, P.M., Szaflarski, J.P., and Paus, R. <lb/>(2018). How UV Light Touches the Brain and Endocrine System Through <lb/>Skin, and Why. Endocrinology 159, 1992-2007. <lb/>Smith, M.S. (2009). Estrus and menstrual cycles: Neuroendocrine control. In <lb/>Encyclopedia of Neuroscience, L.R. Squire, ed. (Elsevier), pp. 1-5. <lb/>Stevenson, T.J., Visser, M.E., Arnold, W., Barrett, P., Biello, S., Dawson, A., <lb/>Denlinger, D.L., Dominoni, D., Ebling, F.J., Elton, S., et al. (2015). Disrupted <lb/>seasonal biology impacts health, food security and ecosystems. Proc. Biol. <lb/>Sci. 282, 20151453. <lb/>Stolwijk, A.M., Olsen, J., Schaumburg, I., Jongbloet, P.H., and Zielhuis, G.A. <lb/>(1996). Seasonal variation in the time to pregnancy: a secondary analysis of <lb/>three Danish databases. Eur. J. Epidemiol. 12, 437-441. <lb/>Stowers, L., and Liberles, S.D. (2016). State-dependent responses to sex <lb/>pheromones in mouse. Curr. Opin. Neurobiol. 38, 74-79. <lb/>Svobodova ´, A.R., Galanda ´kova ´, A., Sianska ´, J., Dole zal, D., Lichnovska ´, R., <lb/>Ulrichova ´, J., and Vosta ´lova ´, J. (2012). DNA damage after acute exposure of <lb/>mice skin to physiological doses of UVB and UVA light. Arch. Dermatol. Res. <lb/>304, 407-412. <lb/>Thompson, M.L., McGill, T.E., McIntosh, S.M., and Manning, A. (1976). Effects <lb/>of adrenalectomy on the sexual behaviour of castrated and intact BDF1 mice. <lb/>Anim. Behav. 24, 519-522. <lb/>van der Meij, L., Almela, M., Buunk, A.P., Fawcett, T.W., and Salvador, A. <lb/>(2012). Men with elevated testosterone levels show more affiliative behaviours <lb/>during interactions with women. Proc. Biol. Sci. 279, 202-208. <lb/>Verhaeghe, J., Gheysen, R., and Enzlin, P. (2013). Pheromones and their effect <lb/>on women&apos;s mood and sexuality. Facts Views Vis. ObGyn 5, 189-195. <lb/>Visser, J.A., de Jong, F.H., Laven, J.S.E., and Themmen, A.P.N. (2006). Anti-<lb/>M€ ullerian hormone: a new marker for ovarian function. Reproduction 131, 1-9. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">14 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Walf, A.A., and Frye, C.A. (2007). The use of the elevated plus maze as an <lb/>assay of anxiety-related behavior in rodents. Nat. Protoc. 2, 322-328. <lb/>Wallner, B., Windhager, S., Schaschl, H., Nemeth, M., Pfl€ uger, L.S., Fieder, M., <lb/>Domjani c, J., Millesi, E., and Seidler, H. (2019). Sexual Attractiveness: a <lb/>Comparative Approach to Morphological, Behavioral and Neurophysiological <lb/>Aspects of Sexual Signaling in Women and Nonhuman Primate Females. <lb/>Adapt. Hum. Behav. Physiol. 5, 164-186. <lb/>Webb, A.R., Kazantzidis, A., Kift, R.C., Farrar, M.D., Wilkinson, J., and Rhodes, <lb/>L.E. (2018). Colour counts: Sunlight and skin type as drivers of vitamin D defi-<lb/>ciency at UK latitudes. Nutrients 10, E457. <lb/>Yang, M., Silverman, J.L., and Crawley, J.N. (2011). Automated three-cham-<lb/>bered social approach task for mice. Curr. Protoc. Neurosci. Chapter 8, 26. <lb/>Yousef, H., Alhajj, M., and Sharma, S. (2020). Anatomy, Skin (Integument), <lb/>Epidermis. (StatPearls). <lb/>Zhang, B., Ma, S., Rachmin, I., He, M., Baral, P., Choi, S., Gonc ¸alves, W.A., <lb/>Shwartz, Y., Fast, E.M., Su, Y., et al. (2020). Hyperactivation of sympathetic <lb/>nerves drives depletion of melanocyte stem cells. Nature 577, 676-681. <lb/>Zimmer, C., Emlen, D.J., and Perkins, A.E.H. (2016). Evolution: Making Sense <lb/>of Life (Roberts). <lb/>Zinck, L., and Lima, S.Q. (2013). Mate choice in Mus musculus is relative and <lb/>dependent on the estrous state. PLoS ONE 8, e66064. <lb/>Zouboulis, C.C. (2004). The human skin as a hormone target and an endocrine <lb/>gland. Hormones (Athens) 3, 9-26. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 15 <lb/>Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">STAR+METHODS <lb/>KEY RESOURCES TABLE <lb/>REAGENT or RESOURCE <lb/>SOURCE <lb/>IDENTIFIER <lb/>Antibodies <lb/>Anti-p53 antibody [PAb 240] <lb/>abcam <lb/>Cat #ab26; RRID:AB_303198 <lb/>Anti-mouse IgG, HRP-linked <lb/>Cell Signaling Technology <lb/>Cat #7076; RRID:AB_330924 <lb/>Anti-actin antibody <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>Cat #A2066; RRID:AB_476693 <lb/>Anti-Rabbit IgG, HRP-linked <lb/>abcam <lb/>Cat #ab6721; RRID:AB_955447 <lb/>Biological samples <lb/>Human blood plasma <lb/>Separated from blood samples in our lab <lb/>(This study) <lb/>Approval of Tel Aviv University Ethics <lb/>Committee <lb/>Mouse tissue samples <lb/>Tissues obtained after sacrifice in our lab <lb/>(This study) <lb/>IACUC permit#10-16-078 <lb/>Chemicals <lb/>TRIzol <lb/>Invitrogen <lb/>Cat# 15596026 <lb/>Choloroform <lb/>Bio-Lab <lb/>Cat# 3082301 <lb/>2-Propanol <lb/>Sigma Aldrich <lb/>Cat #278475 <lb/>Methanol <lb/>Bio-Lab <lb/>Cat #136806 <lb/>Paraformaldehyde, 16% <lb/>Electron Microscopy Sciences <lb/>Cat #30525-89-4 <lb/>Difco Skim Milk <lb/>Avantor Sciences <lb/>Cat #90002-594 <lb/>Hematoxylin Solution, Harris Modified <lb/>Sigma-Aldrich <lb/>Cat #HHS16 <lb/>Eosin Y solution <lb/>Sigma-Aldrich <lb/>Cat #HT110232 <lb/>DPX Mountant for histology <lb/>Sigma-Aldrich <lb/>Cat #06522 <lb/>Ketamine hydrochloride <lb/>Bremer Pharma GMBH <lb/>N/A <lb/>SEDAXYLAN <lb/>Eurovet animal health <lb/>N/A <lb/>Isoflurane, USP TerrellTM <lb/>Piramal Critical care, Inc. <lb/>N/A <lb/>Critical commercial assays <lb/>Mouse LH(Luteinizing Hormone) <lb/>Wuhan Fine Biotech Co., Ltd <lb/>Cat # EM1188 <lb/>Mouse GnRH(Gonadotropin Releasing <lb/>Hormone) <lb/>Wuhan Fine Biotech Co., Ltd <lb/>Cat # EM1616-CM <lb/>Mouse FSH(Follicle-stimulating hormone) <lb/>Wuhan Fine Biotech Co., Ltd <lb/>Cat # EM1035 <lb/>Testosterone <lb/>abcam <lb/>Cat # ab108666 <lb/>Deposited data <lb/>Raw Mass Spectrometry Data Files <lb/>This study <lb/>The mass spectrometry proteomics data <lb/>have been deposited to the <lb/>ProteomeXchange Consortium via the <lb/>PRIDE (Perez-Riverol et al., 2019) partner <lb/>repository with the dataset identifier <lb/>Database:PXD025973 <lb/>Experimental models: Organisms/strains <lb/>Mouse: C57BL/6J <lb/>Envigo <lb/>N/A <lb/>Mouse: C57BL/6J-p53flx/flx <lb/>A gift from Dr. Eli Pikarsky, The Hebrew <lb/>University of Jerusalem, Israel <lb/>N/A <lb/>Mouse: C57BL/6J-k14Cre+/À <lb/>A gift from Dr. Ittai Ben-Porath, The Hebrew <lb/>University of Jerusalem, Israel <lb/>N/A <lb/>Mouse: p53flx/flxK14CreÀ/À (Control <lb/>littermates) <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Bred &amp; genotyped in our lab (This study) <lb/>N/A <lb/>Mouse: p53flx/flxK14Cre+/+ (p53-KO <lb/>littermates) <lb/>Bred &amp; genotyped in our lab (This study) <lb/>N/A <lb/>(Continued on next page) <lb/>e1 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">RESOURCE AVAILABILITY <lb/>Lead contact <lb/>Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Carmit <lb/>Levy (carmitlevy@post.tau.ac.il). <lb/>Materials availability <lb/>All in-house generated mouse strains generated for this study are available from the Lead Contact with a completed Materials Trans-<lb/>fer Agreement. <lb/>Data and code availability <lb/>d All original datasets has been deposited at the ProteomeXchange Consortium via the PRIDE (Perez-Riverol et al., 2019) partner <lb/>repository and is publicly available as of the date of publication: Database: PXD025973. <lb/>d This paper does not report original code. <lb/>d Any additional information required to reanalyze the data reported in this paper is available from the lead contact upon request. <lb/>EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS <lb/>Mouse models and habituation <lb/>Unless stated otherwise, we used 5-to 6-week-old C57BL6 male and female mice (Envigo) for experiments. The p53 floxed male and <lb/>female mice were a gift from Dr. Eli Pikarsky (The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Israel). Dr. Ittai Ben-Porath (The Hebrew University <lb/>Continued <lb/>REAGENT or RESOURCE <lb/>SOURCE <lb/>IDENTIFIER <lb/>Oligonucleotides <lb/>See Table S5 for RT-qPCR primers <lb/>Intergrated DNA Technologies (IDT) <lb/>N/A <lb/>See Table S5 for genotyping primers <lb/>Jackson laboratories <lb/>N/A <lb/>Software and algorithms <lb/>EthoVision XT 7 <lb/>Noldus information technology <lb/>https://www.noldus.com/ethovision-xt; <lb/>RRID:SCR_000441 <lb/>UltraVox XT system <lb/>Noldus information technology; version 3.1 <lb/>N/A <lb/>SPSS Statistics <lb/>IBM; version 25.0 <lb/>https://www.ibm.com/uk-en/analytics/ <lb/>spss-statistics-software; <lb/>RRID:SCR_002865 <lb/>Prism <lb/>Graphpad; version 8 <lb/>http://www.graphpad.com/; RRID: <lb/>SCR_002798 <lb/>Ingenuity Pathway Analysis <lb/>QIAGEN <lb/>https://digitalinsights.qiagen.com/; <lb/>RRID:SCR_008653 <lb/>Proteome Discoverer 1.4 <lb/>Thermo Fisher Scientific <lb/>https://www.thermofisher.com/order/ <lb/>catalog/product/ <lb/>IQLAAEGABSFAKJMAUH; <lb/>RRID:SCR_014477 <lb/>MaxQuant <lb/>Cox and Mann, 2008; version 1.5.2.8 <lb/>https://www.biochem.mpg.de/5111795/ <lb/>maxquant/; MaxQuant, RRID:SCR_014485 <lb/>Perseus software <lb/>Cox and Mann, 2008; version 1.6.10.43 <lb/>https://www.biochem.mpg.de/5111810/ <lb/>perseus <lb/>BioMart <lb/>Ensembl <lb/>https://www.ensembl.org/biomart/ <lb/>martview/ <lb/>9b0f3136bd9d6999b66c3a766729a6ae <lb/>Other <lb/>Virusolveâ+ <lb/>Amity International <lb/>N/A <lb/>Veet hair removal cream <lb/>Reckitt <lb/>N/A <lb/>UVB Lamp (Model: XX-15MR Bench Lamp, <lb/>302 nm) <lb/></div>

			<front>Analytik Jena US <lb/>Cat # 95-0042-15 <lb/>UVX radiometer <lb/>Analytik Jena US <lb/>Cat #97-0015-02 <lb/>Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 e2 <lb/>Article <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>of Jerusalem, Israel) provided male and female mice in which the K14 promoter directs expression of Cre recombinase. We <lb/>confirmed the p53 knockout in keratinocytes by genotyping, qRT-PCR, and ear pigmentation analysis. Male and female mice <lb/>were habituated for at least 1 week to their new environment under a standard 12-h light/dark cycle and the conditions of constant <lb/>temperature (24 ± 1 C) and humidity (50 ± 5%) with access to food and water ad libitum prior to experimentation. The guidelines of <lb/>the Tel Aviv University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) (10-16-078) were followed. <lb/>Human cohort <lb/>The human cohort of 9 men and 10 women (18-55 year of age) were recruited through convenience sampling at the Sackler School of <lb/>Medicine (Tel Aviv University, Israel). All provided written consent. The approval of the University&apos;s Ethics Committee was obtained <lb/>prior to the study. <lb/>Human cohort testosterone study <lb/>The human cohort study from Clalit was approved by Kaplan Medical Center Institutional Review Board. Total testosterone data and <lb/>related medical data were retrieved for all males aged 20 to 50 years old in Israel Central and Jerusalem districts from Clalit Health <lb/>Services using Clalit Secure Data Sharing Platform powered by MDClone (https://www.mdclone.com), and subjects with testos-<lb/>terone modifying medical conditions were excluded. Subjects were classified into four groups categorized according to average <lb/>UV radiation (UVR) in their country of origin (https://apps.who.int/gho/data/node.main.164?lang=en) by using WHO map (https:// <lb/>www.who.int/gho/phe/ultraviolet_radiation/exposure/en/). Only men from countries with low UVR (UV &lt; 2500 J/m 2 ) and high UVR <lb/>(UV R 4500 J/m 2 ) were considered for this study. Multivariate analysis of variance models was used to estimate the effect of season-<lb/>ality and country of origin on total testosterone levels. Models were assessed separately for the summer (May-September) and winter <lb/>(October-April) months and were adjusted for age and body mass index. The analysis of human cohort testosterone level data of men <lb/>aged 21-25 years old (n = 13,086) from the Maccabi Health Services, was done as previously described (Chodick et al., 2020). <lb/>Human questionnaire <lb/>For the quantitative longitudinal study, 19 subjects aged 23-73 (mean M = 45.89, SD = 15.22), 47.4% male and 52.6% female, with <lb/>skin conditions including vitiligo, eczema, and psoriasis were recruited by convenience sampling from two Israeli hospitals (Assuta <lb/>Hospital; Helsinki ethical approval 0063-17-ASMC 17 and Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center; Helsinki ethical approval 0151-17-TLV). <lb/>Of all the participants, 11.8% were single, 64.7% were married, and 23.5% were divorced, 35.3% had no children, and 64.7% had 1-<lb/>3 children. Data were collected through self-reported questionnaires at two time points, before exposing the participants to a UVB <lb/>treatment (T1), and approximately a month after the treatment (T2). During this period, patients were given full body (except their gen-<lb/>itals, eyes, and head) narrow band UVB exposure (0.1-2.5 J/cm) (Waldmann UV7002 UVB instrument; UV lamp (UVB) 42 x TL 01 120 <lb/>W) 2-3 times a week, 10-12 UVB exposures in total. The hospitals IRB approved the study, and all participants signed informed con-<lb/>sent forms. <lb/>The PLS (Hatfield and Sprecher, 1986) was developed to measure passionate love in intimate relationships and focuses on an <lb/>intense longing for union with the other. We used a Hebrew translation of the PLS for our study. We used seven items from the short <lb/>version of the PLS relevant to our study: cognitive components of passion (intrusive thinking about the partner, idealization of the <lb/>other and the relationship); emotional components of passion (attraction, longing for reciprocity, and physiological arousal). From <lb/>the short version of the PLS, we excluded items that did not directly examine the person&apos;s passion, such as actions taken to deter-<lb/>mine the other person&apos;s feelings. We included items related to cognitive components of passion (e.g., intrusive thinking about the <lb/>other and idealization of the other and the relationship) and emotional components of passion (e.g., attraction, longing for reciprocity, <lb/>and physiological arousal). Each item was rated on a 9-point Likert-scale (1 = not at all true; 9 = definitely true), with a higher score <lb/>representing more passionate love. <lb/>The aggression questionnaire (Buss and Perry, 1992) was developed to measure four aspects of aggressiveness: physical aggres-<lb/>sion, verbal aggression, anger, and hostility. A questionnaire translated into Hebrew was used to assess two factors relevant to our <lb/>study: physical aggression (nine items; e.g., &apos;I get into fights a little more than the average person&apos;) and verbal aggression (five items; <lb/>e.g., &apos;I can&apos;t help getting into arguments when people disagree with me&apos;). Each factor was rated on a 5-point Likert-scale (1 = <lb/>extremely uncharacteristic of me; 5 = extremely characteristic of me) and calculated by summing the answers (after re-coding <lb/>one item of physical aggression), with higher scores representing more aggression. The reliability of the scale of the original ques-<lb/>tionnaire, measured through Cronbach&apos;s alpha, was 0.85 for physical aggression and 0.72 for verbal aggression. In our study, the <lb/>Cronbach&apos;s Alpha was 0.84 in T1 and 0.77 in T2 for physical aggression (after deleting one item); and 0.81 and 0.79, respectively, <lb/>for verbal aggression. <lb/>METHOD DETAILS <lb/>UV treatment <lb/>Mice were kept in a reverse 12-h dark/light cycle (red light) and were shaved on the dorsal side in an area of approximately $60% of <lb/>the skin, excluding the ears, tail and paw regions, where hair growth is not prevalent, and were treated with depilatory cream (Veet). <lb/>Mice were exposed to daily UVB treatment of 50 mJ/cm 2 in the reverse light setting with a XX-15 stand equipped with 15-W, 302-nm <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">e3 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>UVB bulbs (Ultraviolet Products) at approximately the same time of their day (9:00 -10:00 AM) in a custom transparent plexiglass <lb/>chamber that allowed freedom of movement during the treatment. To exclude the possibility of not crawling on top of each other <lb/>and hindering the UVB skin exposure, one mouse per chamber at a time were UVB exposed (Nghiem et al., 2002). The UV emission <lb/>was measured using a UVX radiometer (Ultraviolet Products, 280 nm -320 nm) equipped with a UVB measuring head. The calibration <lb/>was done for the delivered doses of UVB emission. For the mock (control) treatment, the animals were placed in the chamber but the <lb/>UVB lamp was not turned on, which ensured that the UVB-exposed and control mice experienced the same stress conditions. After <lb/>each treatment, the container was cleaned using Virusolve (Amity International) to avoid cross-contamination of odors. Control and <lb/>UVB exposed mice used for the study were of similar age and underwent similar experimental protocols in order to exclude the pos-<lb/>sibility of hair-cycle differences as well as stress related interferences in the behavioral experiment. <lb/>Melanin intensity quantification <lb/>The reflective colorimetric measurements were performed with a DSM II Color Meter (Cortex Technology), which gives the level of <lb/>pigmentation. A white standard background (provided by the manufacturer) was used for the calibration before every measurement. <lb/>All the measurements were performed on the same background with no UV light. The tail and ear pigmentation were measured at the <lb/>end of the 8-week UVB (50 mJ/cm 2 ) or mock (control) treatment series and at the end of 5-week period for p53-KO and p53-WT an-<lb/>imals, and pigmentation intensity was scored relative to control (UV/Mock -melanin pigmentation intensity). <lb/>Mouse blood draw <lb/>Mice were anesthetized by the intraperitoneal injection of ketamine (100 mg/kg body weight; Bremer Pharma GMBH) and xylazine <lb/>(10 mg/kg body weight; Eurovet Animal Health BV), and blood was drawn from the heart with a 23G needle (KDL) at approximately the <lb/>same time of the day (between 10:00 -13:00 Israel Standard Time) for all samples. The drawn blood was transferred to EDTA-coated <lb/>microvette tubes (BD Mictrotainer) and immediately placed on ice, followed by centrifugation at 448 g for 10 min at 4 C to separate <lb/>the plasma fraction, which was then aliquoted and stored at À80 C until further use. <lb/>Human cohort Solar-exposure study <lb/>All subjects were asked to avoid or minimize their solar exposure during the 2 days prior to the experiment and were requested to <lb/>wear long-sleeved clothes on those days. On the day of the experiment (between 16:00-18:00, Israel standard time), 10 cc of intra-<lb/>venous blood was drawn by a certified physician. On the next day subjects were asked to wear short sleeves/sleeveless shirt and <lb/>shorts and be in a non-shaded area in order to expose themselves to 2000 mJ/cm 2 solar UV radiation, as measured by the UVX radi-<lb/>ometer (Ultraviolet Products, 280 nm -320 nm), between 11:00-13:00, Israel standard time. The second blood sample was then <lb/>drawn later that day, between 16:00-18:00, Israel standard time. <lb/>Human blood draw <lb/>Venous blood was drawn from the forearm, after disinfection with Alcosept (chlorhexidine gluconate 0.5% W/V and alcohol 70% V/V; <lb/>Floris) using a blood-collecting needle set (KDL). Blood was collected in Vacutainerâ tubes (BD Biosciences). The blood was allowed <lb/>to clot at room temperature for 15-30 min followed by centrifugation at 2000 g for 10 min at 4 C to separate the serum fraction, which <lb/>was then aliquoted and stored at À80 C until further use. <lb/>Proteolysis and mass spectrometry <lb/>Proteins from plasma of five human volunteers randomly selected from the cohort and from three mice were precipitated with 90% <lb/>ethanol at 90 C for 10 min, followed by centrifugation at 11,200 g for 5 min. The resulting supernatant was dried and resuspended in <lb/>9 M urea, 400 mM ammonium bicarbonate, reduced with 3 mM DTT (60 C, 30 min), modified with 12 mM iodoacetamide in 400 mM <lb/>ammonium bicarbonate (in the dark, at room temperature, 30 min), and digested in 1 M urea, 50 mM ammonium bicarbonate with modi-<lb/>fied trypsin (Promega) at a 1:50 enzyme-to-substrate ratio at 37 C for 2 h. The tryptic peptides were desalted using C18 tips (Top tip, <lb/>Glygen), dried, and re-suspended in 0.1% formic acid. The peptides were then resolved by reverse-phase chromatography on 0.075 X <lb/>180 mm fused silica capillaries (J&amp;W Pharmalab) packed with Reprosil reversed-phase material (Dr Maisch GmbH). The peptides were <lb/>eluted with a linear 60-min gradient from 5% to 28%, then a 15-min linear gradient from 28% to 95%, followed by 25 min at 95% aceto-<lb/>nitrile with 0.1% formic acid in water, at a flow rate of 0.15 ml/min. Mass spectrometry was performed with a Q Exactive HF mass spec-<lb/>trometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific) in a positive mode, using repetitively full MS scan followed by collision induced dissociation of the 18 <lb/>most dominant ions selected from the first MS scan. The mass spectrometry data from three biological repeats was analyzed using the <lb/>MaxQuant software 1.5.2.8 (Cox and Mann, 2008). The data was quantified by label-free analysis using the same software. Statistical <lb/>analysis of the identification and quantization results was done using Perseus 1.6.10.43 software (Cox and Mann, 2008). <lb/>Proteomic analysis <lb/>The proteomic dataset, which included the UniProt identifiers, were converted to gene symbols using BioMart, Ensembl. The gene sym-<lb/>bols and absolute value of the log 2 -transformed fold-change were subjected to IPA for the core analysis (QIAGEN). Matching with the <lb/>mouse Ingenuity Knowledge Database generated predicted possible upstream and transcription regulators based on the p value and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 e4 <lb/>Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>activation Z-score values, which infers the activation state (increased or decreased). Fisher&apos;s right-tailed exact test was used to deter-<lb/>mine the probability of upstream analysis over-representation in the dataset. The protein network was built using the string output. <lb/>ELISA <lb/>Testosterone, LH, FSH, and GnRH levels in mouse plasma were detected and quantified after 8 weeks of UVB (50 mJ/cm 2 ) or control <lb/>treatment using the Testosterone Elisa Kit (ab108666, Abcam), LH Elisa kit (EM1188, Wuhan Fine Biotech Co., Ltd.), FSH Elisa kit <lb/>(EM1035, Wuhan Fine Biotech Co., Ltd.), and GnRH Elisa Kit (EM1616-CM, Wuhan Fine Biotech Co., Ltd.), according to the manu-<lb/>facturers&apos; instructions. <lb/>Mating test <lb/>Procedure: This test was conducted on sexually naive female and male C57BL6, p53-WT, and p53-KO mice after UVB (50 mJ/cm 2 ) or <lb/>mock treatment. The males were individually housed for 24 h in a new cage with sawdust bedding; food and water were provided ad <lb/>libitum. Before the start of the mating test, the food and water were removed from the cage, and the females were examined for the <lb/>stage of their estrous cycle; they were mated with a male only if they were in the estrus/proestrus stage. In the mating test, a female <lb/>was introduced into the cage of the male, where she spent 1 hour, after which she was immediately returned to her cage. All tests <lb/>were conducted in a 17 3 25 cm transparent plexiglass chamber placed on a table that allowed videotaping in the ventral view with a <lb/>digital camera. The visual data were subsequently analyzed manually for respective behavior parameters. All the experiments took <lb/>place in a reverse 12-h light/dark cycle under dim, red lighting. In the case of the p53-WT and p53-KO mice, the mating test was <lb/>carried out at the end of the light phase of the standard 12-h light/dark cycle under dim, red lighting, as mating behavior was tested <lb/>during the active phase (dark phase) of the mice. <lb/>Analysis parameters and criteria: The following parameters were measured as previously described (Haga et al., 2010): number of <lb/>anogenital sniffs, grooming behavior, latency and total number of male mounting of the female, intromission latency, duration and <lb/>total number of intromissions, female lordosis response, rearing behavior, and number of ejaculations. Anogenital sniffing was <lb/>defined as actively reaching out and sniffing the genital regions of a mouse. Reaching out was defined as a mouse trying to stretch <lb/>out and sniff the other sex&apos;s genitalia. Mouse grooming behavior was scored when the mouse self-groomed its face or body. <lb/>Mounting was defined as a failed attempt of the male to climb with both forepaws on the female&apos;s back in an attempt to mate. Intro-<lb/>mission was defined as a male successfully climbing on the female with its forepaws and making pelvic thrust movements with a <lb/>stable frequency for a minimum duration of 5 s. A female&apos;s lordosis response was defined as the female standing on all four paws <lb/>grounded and elevating the hind region from the floor, creating a lordotic curve of the spine. A female was classified as receptive <lb/>only if she exhibited the lordotic posture upon mounting by a male. The lordosis analysis was performed against the total number <lb/>of mounting with pelvic thrusts by male mouse, which may or may not include penile intromission (Lordosis quotient = Total number <lb/>of female lordosis/total number of male mounts*100) in a single experimental session as previously described (Beach, 1976; Haga <lb/>et al., 2010). Rearing behavior was considered a female assuming a defensive upright posture toward a male, with both forepaws <lb/>in the air and the back straight and stretched. Ejaculation was defined as the end of the intromission period, when the male, after <lb/>ejaculating, would fall on one side and remain in that position for a couple of seconds. <lb/>Ultrasonic vocalization <lb/>Sexually naive male and female mice were subject to the above-described mating test but in a room suited for recording their ultrasonic <lb/>vocalizations. Recordings were obtained using an UltraVox XT system (Noldus Information Technology), which was capable of recording <lb/>the full spectrum of sound with a maximum frequency of 160 kHz. Detector outputs were analyzed with UltraVox XT 3.1 software (Noldus <lb/>Information Technology). The number of vocalizations, mean dominant frequency, duration of the mice vocalizing with each other was <lb/>recorded and scored. A representative spectrogram of the vocalization was extracted using the UltraVox XT 3.1 software. <lb/>Elevated plus maze test <lb/>The elevated plus maze test was performed after 5 weeks of UVB or control treatment with an apparatus measuring 90.0 cm in height <lb/>made of white plexiglass. The maze consisted of four arms in total (two open arms without walls and two enclosed arms with 15.0-cm <lb/>high walls). The mice were habituated for 30 min to the experimental room prior to the start of experiment in order to avoid the stress bias <lb/>of a new environment. Naive mice, who did not undergo any experimental protocols other than the UVB and control treatments were <lb/>used for this study thus giving us the true measure of the test unhindered from the stress due to other behavioral experiments. The con-<lb/>trol or UVB-treated mouse was placed in the center of the maze (intersection of the open and closed arms) facing the open arm and was <lb/>allowed to move for 7 min in the maze. The mouse behavior was recorded in a digital video camera mounted overhead on the ceiling and <lb/>was scored and analyzed using the Ethovision XT software (Noldus Information Technology). The test was conducted in a reverse 12-<lb/>hour light/dark condition under the dim red light setting during their active phase cycle. The females were checked for their estrous cycle <lb/>by vaginal smears prior to the experiment in order to avoid the bias of the state of the cycle influencing the anxiety parameter. Between <lb/>each trial, the maze was cleaned using Virusolve (Amity International) to avoid cross contamination of odors between gender and treat-<lb/>ments. The parameters scored included the total time spent giving the cumulative of the time spent either in the open or closed arm and <lb/>the frequency giving the number of visits by the mouse either in the open or closed arms of the elevated plus-maze. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">e5 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<body>Three-chamber test <lb/>A white, rectangular, plexiglass chamber was divided into three consecutive compartments, with each of the two outer compart-<lb/>ments containing a wire cage. Small openings in the center of the two partitions facilitated movement throughout the chamber, <lb/>except into the wire cages. The wire cage limits movement of the stimulus mouse. To habituate the subject mouse to the test cham-<lb/>ber, it was placed in the center of the middle chamber with freedom of movement on either side of the compartment for 10 min the day <lb/>before the experiment; no stimuli was introduced. On the day of the experiment, the subject and stimulus mice were brought into the <lb/>experimental room and habituated to the room for 20 min. Next, the stimulus mice (or novel objects) were placed in the wire cages, <lb/>one in each cage. The subject mouse was then placed in the center of the middle compartment and allowed to move freely for 15 min. <lb/>The experiments were performed under a reverse 12-h light/dark phase under dim, red lighting. A digital camera mounted overhead <lb/>on the ceiling was used to record the mouse&apos;s behavior throughout the 15-min session, which was scored using EthoVision XT soft-<lb/>ware (Noldus Information Technology). Between each trial, the positions of the stimuli were switched, to avoid a confounding error <lb/>(preferred side of the subject mouse), and the chamber and wire cages were cleaned using Virusolve (Amity International), to avoid <lb/>cross-contamination of the odors from the subject or the stimulus mice. <lb/>The coordinates and time stamps of the subject mouse obtained from a live video feed were translated into a number of parameters <lb/>and further visualized by a heatmap generated with EthoVision XT software (Noldus) to detect the subject mouse&apos;s location and <lb/>movements. We scored the following parameters: latency toward the zone of the cage and near the cage, which are the amounts <lb/>of time taken by the subject mouse to move toward a compartment with a stimulus. The total time spent in the zone of the cage <lb/>and near the cage represents the cumulative time spent in the compartment with a stimulus. The frequency of visits to the zone <lb/>of the cage and near the cage provides the number of times the subject mouse visited a compartment with a stimulus. <lb/>In all the following schemes, mice received UVB (50 mJ/cm 2 ) or control treatment for 5 weeks. All the female mice were examined <lb/>prior to the test session for their estrous cycle stage, with only those in their estrus/proestrus stage used in the test. <lb/>Male subject and two female stimuli <lb/>The same stimulus females (one UVB-treated and one control female) were tested twice, once with a control male mouse subject and <lb/>once with a UVB-treated male mouse subject, on separate days. <lb/>Female subject and two male stimuli <lb/>The same stimulus males (one UVB-treated and one control male) were tested twice, once with a control female subject and once <lb/>with a UVB-treated female subject, on separate days. <lb/>Female subject and two female stimuli <lb/>The same stimulus females (one UVB-treated and one control female) were tested twice, once with a control female subject and once <lb/>with a UVB-treated female subject, on separate days. <lb/>Female subject, a male stimulus, and a novel-object stimulus <lb/>The same stimulus male (one set of experiments with a UVB-treated male and the other with a control male) were tested twice, once <lb/>with a control female mouse subject and once with a UVB-treated female mouse subject, on separate days. The novel object (plastic <lb/>block) was cleaned using Virusolve (Amity International) between each trial. <lb/>Vaginal smears for estrous cycle evaluation <lb/>To examine the estrous cycle, a gentle lavage technique was used to collect vaginal smears from each female mouse daily, approx-<lb/>imately at the same time, for a period of 45 days, starting when the females were 4 weeks old. In the first 2 weeks of smear collection, <lb/>females were not subject to any treatment. In the following 4 weeks, the females were subjected UVB (50 mJ/cm 2 ) or control <lb/>treatment. <lb/>The smear collection involved gently inserting a 200-ml pipette tip containing 30 ml sterile PBS X1 into the vagina to a depth of 3 mm, <lb/>and the lavage was smeared onto a plain glass slide (76 3 26 mm, Bar Naor Ltd.). The smears were then immediately viewed under a <lb/>bright field microscope (Nikon) to assess the stage of estrous cycle, as determined by examining the morphology of the cells present <lb/>in the vaginal smear, as described previously (Caligioni, 2009). The proestrus stage was characterized by the presence of nucleated <lb/>epithelial cells; the estrus stage by enucleated cornified cells; the metestrus stage by leucocytes, cornified cells, and nucleated <lb/>epithelial cells; and the diestrus stage by the predominant presence of leucocytes and lower amounts of nucleated cells. For Fig-<lb/>ure 3B, the proestrus and estrus stage were combined and the diestrus and metestrus stage were combined as previously done (Ajayi <lb/>and Akhigbe, 2020) for the subsequent analysis. <lb/>RNA purification and qRT-PCT <lb/>Flash-frozen tissues were thawed on ice, followed by homogenization with magnetic beads of the desired size (Next Advance) in a <lb/>Bullet Blender (Next Advance). Total RNA was purified using TriZol (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer&apos;s guidelines. RNA was <lb/>quantified by measuring the OD 260 nm /OD 280 nm . For the mRNA analysis, the cDNA was prepared using the qScript cDNA synthesis kit <lb/>(Quantabio) and further subjected to qRT-PCR using PerfeCTa SYBR green FastMix (Quantabio). The data are represented as the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 e6 <lb/>Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>fold changes relative to the control. All experiments were performed at least in triplicates. All the primer sequences used are pre-<lb/>sented in Table S5. <lb/>Histology <lb/>Following UVB or control treatment of female mice, the ovaries were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde and paraffin-embedded, followed <lb/>by staining with hematoxylin (HHS16, Sigma-Aldrich) and eosin (HT110232, Sigma-Aldrich) according to the manufacturer&apos;s instruc-<lb/>tions. Sections of 5 mm were mounted using the DPX mountant (06522, Sigma-Aldrich). The images were obtained with an Aperio <lb/>Slide Scanner microscope (Leica Biosystem, USA), at 3 20 magnification. <lb/>Genotyping <lb/>Genomic DNA was extracted from the tail of a mouse using extraction buffer (25 mM NaOH, 0.2 mM disodium salt EDTA; pH 12) for <lb/>60 min, followed by incubation in neutralization buffer. PCR was performed in a 20-ml volume that included 10 ml GoTaq green master <lb/>mix ( 3 2) (Promega), 0.5 mM Cre primers (with positive control) and 0.5 mM flox primers (Integrated DNA Technologies). Reactions <lb/>were carried out in a PCR cycler (Biometra PCR Cycler) at 95 C for 3 min, followed by 35 cycles at 95 C for 30 s, a cycle at 55 C for <lb/>1 min, and an extension step at 72 C for 5 min. The PCR products were kept at 4 C until electrophoresis in 3% agarose gel. The <lb/>visualization of the PCR product was done based on its size (Cre-recombinase 100 bp, internal positive control 324 bp, flox <lb/>390 bp), and the digital images were captured in a Gel Documentation system (UVITEC Ltd.). <lb/>Immunoblotting <lb/>Whole skin tissues were dissected from mice and snap frozen in liquid nitrogen followed by homogenization in RIPA buffer with pro-<lb/>tease inhibitor (Roche) as previously described (Glaich et al., 2019). This was followed by incubation on ice for 1 hour, then the sam-<lb/>ples were centrifuged at 10,000 g for 15 mins at 4 C. The resulting clear phase protein was stored at À80 C until further use. Samples <lb/>were subjected to western blot analysis as described previously (Dror et al., 2016). Membrane was exposed overnight to antibody <lb/>targeting p53 (ab26, Abcam) and Actin (#A2066, Sigma Aldrich) and proteins were visualized with SuperSignal Chemiluminescent <lb/>Substrates (Pierce) using horseradish peroxidase-conjugated anti-mouse antibody (#7076, Cell Signaling) and horseradish peroxi-<lb/>dase-conjugated anti-Rabbit antibody (#ab6721, abcam). The p53 protein levels in each condition were normalized to actin (Q). <lb/>QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS <lb/>The data are shown by means and standard errors. We performed two-tailed Student&apos;s t tests for two group comparisons and <lb/>ANOVA for multiple group comparisons. For the PLS questionnaire, we used IBM SPSS (version 25.0) and conducted Wilcoxon tests <lb/>to examine within-group differences (ranks of T1 versus T2 for each gender separately). For all the tests, p values &lt; 0.05 were consid-<lb/>ered significant. All the analyses were performed using Excel (Microsoft Corp.), SPSS (version 25.0), and GraphPad PRISM 8 soft-<lb/>ware. The statistics details and the software&apos;s used for all the experiments can be found in the resources tables and figure legends <lb/>and the Human questionnaire statistics details can be found in the STAR Methods section: Human questionnaire. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">e7 Cell Reports 36, 109579, August 24, 2021 <lb/>Article <lb/>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS </note>


	</text>
</tei>
