<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Chlorite-induced porosity evolution in multi-source tight sandstone reservoirs: A case study of the Shaximiao Formation in western Sichuan Basin</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Qingshao</forename>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Chunyu</forename>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-11-03T16:35:06.453095Z">03.11.2025 16:35:06</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1515$1$geo-2022-0732</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Walter de Gruyter GmbH</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1515/geo-2022-0732</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Qingshao Liang, Chunyu Chen. (2024). Chlorite-induced porosity evolution in multi-source tight sandstone reservoirs: A case study of the Shaximiao Formation in western Sichuan Basin. Open Geosciences, 16(1), None. DOI: 10.1515/geo-2022-0732</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-03T16:35:06.453095Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-03T16:35:06.453095Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Ruti Bardenstein* and Mira Ariel <lb/>From location to conjunction, disjunction, <lb/>partition, exemplification and association: <lb/>Hebrew bein constructions <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1515/ling-2022-0115 <lb/>Received July 22, 2022; accepted July 23, 2023; published online April 22, 2024 <lb/>Abstract: Analyzing the diachrony of Hebrew bein, originally a spatial preposition <lb/>&apos;within/among&apos;, this article traces several grammaticization clines associated with bein&apos;s <lb/>gradual evolution into a rich variety of functions within various constructions. While its <lb/>early function is purely locative, bein later participates in an array of constructions and <lb/>sub-constructions, where its syntactic status, its semantic meanings and functions, as <lb/>well as its discourse role, have shifted considerably. Bein may thus be part of a <lb/>conjunctive or a disjunctive construction, but it may also be part of an &apos;in any case&apos; <lb/>adverbial, and later an &apos;anyway&apos; discourse marker. It conveys different locative con-<lb/>struals (&apos;within&apos;, &apos;among&apos; and &apos;between&apos;), but also various abstract symmetric relations, <lb/>such as &apos;difference&apos;, &apos;dispute&apos; and &apos;separation&apos;. Some bein constructions partition a set, <lb/>focusing on a subset of it, while in other cases bein serves as an &apos;all-purpose&apos; preposition. <lb/>Nevertheless, our goal is to show how each grammatical, semantic and discoursal phase <lb/>is well motivated, given the previous phase. Based on written historical corpora, from <lb/>Biblical to contemporary Hebrew, we provide a step-by-step diachronic development <lb/>from earlier to later bein functions. <lb/>Keywords: conjunctions; constructions; disjunctions; grammaticization <lb/></front>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>The topic of this article is the evolution of Hebrew bein &apos;inside, in the middle of, among, <lb/>between&apos; (Ben Jehuda 1908-1959; Brown et al. 1907; Even Shoshan 1982) into a sur-<lb/>prisingly rich variety of meanings and functions it contributes to, among them: loca-<lb/>tion, conjunction, disjunction, partition, exemplification and association. The Biblical <lb/>(1a) shows an early function of bein, as a spatial preposition meaning &apos;among&apos;, but bein <lb/></body>

        <front>*Corresponding author: Ruti Bardenstein, Department of Foreign Literatures and Linguistics, <lb/>Ben-Gurion University of the Negev, Ben-Gurion 1 Boulevard, P.O. Box 653, Beer Sheva, 84105, Israel; and <lb/>English, Shenkar College, Anna Frank 12, Ramat Gan, Israel, E-mail: ruti.bardenstein@gmail.com <lb/>Mira Ariel, Linguistics, Cognitive Studies of Language and Language Use, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, <lb/>Israel, E-mail: mariel@tauex.tau.ac.il. https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2018-6917 <lb/>Linguistics 2024; 62(5): 1301-1338 <lb/>Open Access. © 2024 the author(s), published by De Gruyter. <lb/>This work is licensed under the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. <lb/></front>

        <body>later plays a key role in various nonspatial Goldbergian constructions, only some of <lb/>which are exemplified in Examples (1b)-(1e). The Biblical (1b) contains a bein prepo-<lb/>sitional phrase within a VP, where the initial bein, here &apos;between&apos;, takes a conjunction <lb/>containing a reduplicated (dummy) bein. The Mishnaic (1c) presents an adverbial <lb/>phrase, where the two bein tokens make up a correlative connective. This construction <lb/>introduces an irrealis disjunction akin to the adverbial indifference or construction <lb/>&apos;whether X or Y&apos; (Ariel 2016). In (1d), a sub-construction of (1c), each of the alternatives <lb/>is introduced specifically by a discourse-anaphoric kax &apos;thus&apos;. Finally, (1e), a reduced <lb/>variant of (1d), presents a lexicalized &quot;free-choice&quot; adverbial (&apos;in any case&apos;), which is <lb/>pronounced as a single phonological word. 1 <lb/>(1) a. Hi mithalexet <lb/>bein <lb/>ha-Xayot <lb/>it is.moving.to.and.fro among the-living.creatures <lb/>&apos;It is moving among the animals.&apos; <lb/>(Ezekiel 1: 13) <lb/>b. Va-yešvu <lb/>bein <lb/>bet el u-vein <lb/>ha-ʕai <lb/>and-they.abode between Bethel and-between the-Ai <lb/>&apos;And they abode between Bethel and Ai.&apos; <lb/>(Joshua 8: 9) 2 <lb/>c. Bein <lb/>min <lb/>ha-yorshim u-vein <lb/>še-eino <lb/>min <lb/>whether <lb/>from <lb/>the-heirs <lb/>and-whether that-isn&apos;t from <lb/>ha-yorshim, dvarav <lb/>kayamin. <lb/>the-heirs, <lb/>his.words are.valid <lb/>&apos;Whether (he is) one of the successors or not, his words are valid.&apos; <lb/>(Baba Bathra 8:6, Mishnah) <lb/>d. ʕeved še-nišba <lb/>u-fadauhu, <lb/>im lešum ʕeved, <lb/>slave that-was.captivated and-was.redeemed, if for <lb/>slave <lb/>yištaʕabed, <lb/>im lešum ben-xorin lo <lb/>will.be.subjugated, if for <lb/>free <lb/>not <lb/>yištaabed. <lb/>Raban šimon <lb/>ben <lb/>amlieliel <lb/>will.be.subjugated. Rabbi Shimon son.of Gamliel <lb/>omer <lb/>bein <lb/>kax <lb/>u-vein <lb/>kax <lb/>says <lb/>whether <lb/>like.this <lb/>and-whether <lb/>like.this <lb/>yištaabed <lb/>will.be.subjugated <lb/>&apos;A slave that was captivated and was redeemed for a slave, will be <lb/>subjugated, one redeemed for a free person shall not be subjugated. Rabbi <lb/>Gamliel says be it this way or be it that way he should be subjugated.&apos; <lb/>(Gittin 4:4) <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">1 For lack of space, we only elaborate on these functions when we describe their evolution (see <lb/>Sections 2-6). Our goal here is to impress on the reader how wide-ranging the evolutionary paths <lb/>associated with bein are. <lb/>2 -vein is a phonetically conditioned variant of bein. U-is a phonetically conditioned variant of ve &apos;and&apos;. <lb/></note>

        <page>1302 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>e. Lama le-hitamec? <lb/>Bein <lb/>ko <lb/>ekašel <lb/>why to-make.an.effort whether thus I.will.fail <lb/>&apos;Why make an effort? I will fail anyway.&apos; <lb/>(https://www.nli.org.il › books) <lb/>All the developments exemplified above originate from the complex [bein X u-vein Y] <lb/>&apos;between X and between Y&apos; construction. A separate, additional path of metaphorical <lb/>extensions of the simple locative construction [bein NPs] &apos;among NPs&apos; rendered this <lb/>bein a set partitioner (akin to partitive some), as well as an &apos;all-purpose&apos; associative <lb/>preposition (standing for &apos;by&apos;, &apos;for&apos; etc.) (see Section 4). <lb/>These semantic and syntactic changes, which turned a spatial preposition into a <lb/>partitive or a general associative preposition on the one hand, and to forming part of <lb/>a conjunction, a (limited) disjunction, a conjunction again, an &apos;any circumstance&apos; <lb/>adverbial and finally an &apos;anyway&apos; discourse marker on the other hand, are puzzling. <lb/>We trace here the small linguistic steps that must have gradually led to these rather <lb/>radical changes: We show that they were functionally motivated, and occurred <lb/>within specific Goldbergian constructions (Bybee 2003; Himmelmann 2004; Traugott <lb/>2008). We focus on the innovative bein constructions for each period we discuss <lb/>below but note that practically all older functions persist in later periods as well <lb/>(Hopper 1991), though at different frequencies. <lb/>Briefly, the initial function (1a) is typical of prepositional phrases, where a <lb/>figure (&apos;it&apos;) is located in relation to some ground (&apos;the living creatures&apos;). It presents <lb/>the ground (the locating entity) as a formless, unstructured plurality (or collective) <lb/>of landmarks, and no definite space is delineated for the figure&apos;s location within <lb/>the ground (Talmy 1972). Disjunctions (1c), however, involve an alternativity <lb/>relation, typically between specifically two options (Ariel and Mauri 2019). We <lb/>therefore need to explain the shift into two distinct profiled alternatives in (1c). <lb/>Indeed, with the evolution of the complex prepositional correlative construction <lb/>(1b) the complement of bein profiles the relevant ground as two individuated <lb/>landmarks. <lb/>We will argue that once these landmarks are (i) extended to nonlocative entities, <lb/>(ii) are contextually construed as alternatives to each other and (iii) occur within an <lb/>irrealis context, a (limited) disjunctive reading is made available, free-alternative (or <lb/>&quot;free-choice&quot;) (see Example (4) below). A syntactic detachment of the free-alternative <lb/>construction then gives rise to an adverbial indifference-disjunctive bein construction <lb/>(4c)-(4d). Finally, should the explicit alternatives be deictic markers used merely as <lb/>general placeholders for indefinite reference (Cf. English this and that), rather than as <lb/>pointers to specific entities (ko and kax both meaning &apos;this way, thus&apos;), the two alter-<lb/>natives (&apos;this way or this way&apos;, similar to &apos;one way or another&apos;) are interpreted as a <lb/>higher-level-category &apos;or&apos; construction (Ariel and Mauri 2018). In such cases, a single, <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1303 <lb/></page>

        <body>abstract category is constructed ad hocly, and serves as the speaker-intended message. <lb/>In this collocative variant, the literal &apos;thus or thus&apos; or &apos;one way or another&apos; point to a <lb/>single abstract &apos;any case&apos;. <lb/>We note that with the initiation of the Mishnaic correlative adverbial use (1c), the <lb/>construction was mobilized for argumentative strengthening of the main assertion it <lb/>modifies. This discourse function will be inherited by all of its descendants, as pre-<lb/>dicted by Bardenstein&apos;s (2021) Persistence Principle. Bardenstein&apos;s principle predicts <lb/>the retention of discourse functions associated with specific forms, rather than of <lb/>meanings per se. The claim is that it is the initial inference-based (argumentative) <lb/>motivation for change that persists (and can ultimately lead to a shifted meaning as <lb/>well). Since not all the diachronic changes undergone by bein involved argumenta-<lb/>tive strengthening, not all later functions manifest it. Specifically, the independent <lb/>diachronic path from locative to subset and a general associator are not accompa-<lb/>nied by argumentative strengthening. <lb/>The following sections tell the diachronic story of bein &apos;within, between&apos;, fleshing <lb/>out the details behind its evolution. We analyze the uses of bein in Biblical Hebrew <lb/>(Section 2), in Mishnaic Hebrew (Section 3), in Diaspora Hebrew (Section 4), in <lb/>Revival Hebrew (Section 5) and Contemporary Hebrew (Section 6). 3 Section 7 sum-<lb/>marizes the grammaticization phases involved. <lb/>2 Biblical Hebrew: from locative preposition to <lb/>conjunctive construction <lb/>We extracted all 249 bein &apos;within, between&apos; tokens from the Hebrew Bible, written <lb/>between 1000 B.C. and early A.D. times. Biblical bein occurs in two syntactic <lb/>frames. As part of a simple PP, bein modifies a single NP and often means &apos;within&apos; <lb/>(Section 2.1). As part of a complex conjunctive PP correlative, its complement is a <lb/>conjunction of two NPs, and its meaning is &apos;between&apos; (Section 2.2). Whereas the <lb/>simple construction is predominantly a locative, the complex construction mostly <lb/>profiles a symmetric relation between two reference points. 4 The simple con-<lb/>struction will give rise to innovative uses in Diaspora Hebrew. The complex <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">3 Readers should be aware, however, that the written sources we rely on, Biblical Hebrew, Mishnaic <lb/>Hebrew, Diaspora Hebrew, Revival Hebrew and Contemporary Hebrew do not represent a contin-<lb/>uous history of natural transmission. <lb/>4 A relation between X and Y is symmetric if X bears the same conceptual relation to Y as Y to X. <lb/></note>

        <page>1304 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>construction, which this article focuses on, paved the way for further developments <lb/>already in Mishnaic Hebrew. <lb/>2.1 A simple prepositional phrase <lb/>The simplest syntactic structure found for Biblical bein is where the preposition takes <lb/>a single NP, as in (1a) above. We found 95 such tokens, the morphological and <lb/>syntactic/semantic breakdown of which is shown in Table 1. <lb/>The most basic meaning of bein &apos;within/among/between&apos; shows it as a modifier of <lb/>a complement NP which is either collective or mass (e.g., srefa &apos;burnt.stuff&apos;) (4) 5 or, <lb/>more commonly, plural (54) NPs. Both types of NPs mostly stand for a non-<lb/>individuated ground (58, 61 %). Bearing in mind that bein &apos;within/among (an undif-<lb/>ferentiated ground)&apos; will evolve into &apos;between (two identifiable landmarks)&apos;, it&apos;s <lb/>interesting to examine the frequency of cases where the ground happens to involve <lb/>specifically two reference points (we estimate at least 41, 43.2 %). First, some of the <lb/>plural NPs (e.g., anašim &apos;people&apos; -see (3) below) denote two entities in the specific <lb/>context (at least 6, quite possibly many more). More importantly, many of the <lb/>complement NPs are morphologically dual (37), most of which (35) indeed refer to <lb/>two entities. Most of these are body parts that often come naturally in pairs (e.g., <lb/>&apos;feet&apos;, &apos;eyes&apos;). These cases are crucial because the original &apos;within/among&apos; bein mod-<lb/>ifies a continuous, homogenous ground. But once the ground happens to consist of <lb/>two individuated, noncontiguous, well-defined landmarks, there is no longer a single <lb/>undifferentiated region for the figure to be located in. This is when bein is used as <lb/>&apos;between&apos;, rather than as among. The landmarks are construed as distinct from each <lb/>other, as is the space between them -the space between the eyes/feet is distinct from <lb/>Table : The syntactic and semantic roles of simple bein PPs. <lb/>NP sg <lb/>NP pl <lb/>NP dual <lb/>a <lb/>Total <lb/>Locative adv. <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/>Time adv. <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Copular compl. <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>VP compl. <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Verbal argument <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>VP adjunct <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Total <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/>a Most morphologically dual NPs in Hebrew double up as plural forms. Thus, raglaim &apos;feet/legs.dual&apos; is dual in form, plural <lb/>in meaning, but, often refers to precisely &apos;two feet/legs&apos;. Most of the dual forms found here refer to two entities, but three <lb/>refer to a plurality. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">5 Two of these NPs are proper names, where bein is interpreted as &apos;within/inside.&apos; <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1305 <lb/></page>

        <body>each of the landmarks. Hence, no single homogenous region is profiled. However, if <lb/>the two landmarks are excluded from the total ground, we are indeed left with a <lb/>single continuous region, namely, the space demarcated by the two landmarks, which <lb/>is where the figure is asserted to be located. In this approximately third of the cases <lb/>bein is interpreted as &apos;between&apos;, rather than &apos;within&apos;, and the former will be its sole <lb/>meaning in the complex construction (Section 2.2). Here is a relevant example. <lb/>(2) <lb/>Ve-hayu <lb/>le-totafot <lb/>bein <lb/>ʕenexa. <lb/>that they.may.be as-frontlets between your.eyes <lb/>&apos;And they shall be for frontlets between your eyes.&apos; <lb/>(Deuteronomy 6: 8) <lb/>Table 1 shows that the most frequent function of the simple PPs is as locative adverbs <lb/>(69, 72.6 %). But once it is the space between the two landmarks that is profiled by the <lb/>bein NP complement, this physical space can receive an extended metaphorical <lb/>interpretation (Brown et al. 1907). First, a single collocation (bein ha-ʕarbaim &apos;twi-<lb/>light&apos;) accounts for 11/12 time adverbials. These are metaphorically derived from the <lb/>locative adverbial (physical space &gt; time interval). 6 Thus, locative and time adver-<lb/>bials together account for as much as 84.2 % of the simple bein PPs. <lb/>Next, the (implicit) physical space connecting the two landmarks can be further <lb/>metaphorically extended. It can be construed as an abstract, rather than a physical <lb/>link (or relation) connecting the two entities, which are no longer physical locations. <lb/>Note that just like the space between two landmarks establishes a symmetric relation <lb/>between them, so is the abstract link asserted here reciprocal. At first, this relation <lb/>needs to be explicitly specified. In the following copular complement case in Example <lb/>(3), the specified relation is one of &apos;dispute&apos; (the same is true for the 1 VP complement). <lb/>(3) <lb/>Ki <lb/>yihye <lb/>riv <lb/>bein <lb/>anašim… <lb/>if/when will.be dispute between people… <lb/>&apos;Suppose two persons have a dispute…&apos; <lb/>(Deuteronomy 25: 1, New Revised Standard Version) <lb/>The next phase already leaves the abstract relation implicit. It is contextually <lb/>inferred from the nature of the verb. An examination of the 9 verbal argument cases <lb/>reveals that all the verbs depict an act that executes a separation, typically dis-<lb/>tinguishing between two human entities, based on some abstract criterion (who is <lb/>&apos;just&apos; and who is &apos;unjust&apos; in a dispute between them in Example (4)). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">6 The 12th time adverbial is differently interpreted, as &apos;one in ten days&apos;. <lb/></note>

        <page>1306 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>(4) <lb/>Ve-<lb/>yoxiXu <lb/>bein <lb/>šnenu <lb/>and-<lb/>will.judge <lb/>between <lb/>two.of.us <lb/>&apos;So that they may decide between us two&apos; <lb/>(Genesis 31: 3, New revised standard version) <lb/>All in all, the syntactically simple bein (NP) structure mostly presents an undiffer-<lb/>entiated and non-prominent ground, which can only indicate a vague location (or <lb/>time) for the figure within the ground. The figure and the ground are not physically <lb/>distinguished at this stage. At the same time, a significant minority of the plural/dual <lb/>NPs refer specifically to two individuated, relatively more prominent landmarks. In <lb/>these cases, the ground region no longer subsumes the landmarks. It is limited to the <lb/>continuous space delineated between the landmarks. This is how we get an inferred <lb/>interpretation of bein, originally &apos;within/among (an undifferentiated ground)&apos;, as <lb/>&apos;between (two specific landmarks)&apos;. 7 Finally, a minority of copular, verbal and VP <lb/>complements (12 tokens, 12.6 %) no longer introduce locative landmarks, but rather, <lb/>entities standing in opposition to one another (typically human). <lb/>Biblical Hebrew naturally reflects different diachronic stages. Section 2.1 iden-<lb/>tified two general trends. First, a potential rise in the prominence of the relevant <lb/>discourse entities, from a non-prominent undifferentiated plurality landmark (e.g., <lb/>&apos;living creatures&apos; in (1a)), through individuated (inanimate) landmarks (e.g., &apos;your <lb/>eyes&apos; in (2) to humans standing in some opposition to each other) (&apos;the two of us&apos; in <lb/>(4)). Second, a metaphorical extension of the space between the landmarks has been <lb/>mobilized to express a symmetric interpersonal relation between the prominent <lb/>entities (e.g., &apos;dispute&apos; in (3)). As we see below, this minority discourse profile, where <lb/>two prominent entities are involved in some symmetric relation becomes more <lb/>dominant in the complex bein PP constructions discussed in Section 2.2 and consti-<lb/>tutes a crucial step towards specifically a disjunctive relation (extremely prevalent in <lb/>Mishnaic Hebrew -Section 3). <lb/>2.2 Complex conjunctive PP correlative <lb/>Complex PP constructions are the more frequent structures for Biblical bein (154/249, <lb/>61.8 %). In these constructions the initial preposition bein &apos;between&apos; takes conjoined <lb/>NPs, the second of which is often prefaced by a duplicate of bein, which is non-<lb/>referential, and is a dummy form (122, 79.2 %). See Example (5). 8 <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">7 See Todaka (1996) for this and other differences between the complements of English between and <lb/>among (pertaining to identifiability, separation and competition). <lb/>8 Note that reduplicate (and rarely triple) bein tokens were counted as single occurrences. <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1307 <lb/></page>

        <body>(5) <lb/>[Bein <lb/>(X u-<lb/>vein <lb/>Y)] <lb/>[within/among (X and-within/among Y)] <lb/>&apos;between X and Y&apos; <lb/>Here in Example (6) are two such examples. <lb/>(6) a. Va-yavdel <lb/>elohoim <lb/>bein <lb/>ha-or <lb/>u-<lb/>and-distinguished God <lb/>between the-light and <lb/>vein <lb/>ha-Xošex. <lb/>between <lb/>the-darkness <lb/>&apos;God divided the light from the darkness.&apos; <lb/>(Genesis 1:4) <lb/>b. Ve-šafateti <lb/>bein <lb/>iš <lb/>u-vein <lb/>reʕehu. <lb/>and-I.would.judge between man and-between his.friend <lb/>&apos;And I would judge between one person and another.&apos; <lb/>(Exodus 18:16) <lb/>We propose that this complex construction, which conjoins two individual reference <lb/>points, contributes crucial steps towards the evolution of the later (restricted) disjunctive <lb/>function in Mishnaic Hebrew. First, the minority trends observed above for the simple <lb/>PP construction, namely, the prominence of the entities involved and the abstract <lb/>symmetric relation between them are quite evident for this construction. Second, a new <lb/>relevant factor shows up, the irrealis context (see Mauri [2008] for the crucial role of <lb/>irrealis in evolving disjunctive constructions). Third, the symmetric relation between the <lb/>profiled entities is associated with some opposition between them, which facilitates their <lb/>construal as alternatives to each other. This is accompanied by an implicit need to decide <lb/>or choose between the two alternatives. Finally, as we see below (Section 2.2.3), three <lb/>examples show an interpretation that lies between conjunction and disjunction, quite <lb/>like free-alternative (&quot;free-choice&quot;) or disjunctions (Ariel and Mauri 2018). <lb/>2.2.1 Motivating the correlative bein construction <lb/>The correlative construction in Example (5), literally &apos;among/within X and among/ <lb/>within Y&apos; seems to be rare typologically. We should therefore motivate its syntactic <lb/>evolution, as well as the semantic shift from &apos;within, among (undifferentiated) Xs&apos; <lb/>(with &apos;between two Xs&apos; as an occasional contextual inference) to an explicitly <lb/>encoded &apos;between X and Y&apos;. Now, the initial bein token contributes the spatial <lb/>meaning in the complex construction. The conjunction (here u-) conjoins the two NPs <lb/>comprising the relevant landmark reference points. It is the second, duplicate bein <lb/>that is not transparently compositional, and in need of an explanation. Why did <lb/>speakers evolve this construction, and why with reduplication? Specifically, why not <lb/></body>

        <page>1308 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>directly evolve the more compact conjunction [bein (X ve-Y)] &apos;[between (X and Y)]&apos;, <lb/>which is frequent in Modern Hebrew? 9 <lb/>The key motivation behind the evolved complex construction, we propose, is <lb/>that it is conducive to the function sought by speakers. Specifically, the innovative <lb/>syntactic structure iconically reflects a symmetric relation between separate entities. <lb/>To get a feel for the motivation behind this innovative &quot;redundant&quot; conjunctive <lb/>construction consider the current English conjunctive examples in (7): <lb/>(7) a. The yearlings have great long bare spots in their sides and in their rumps. <lb/>(LSAC) 10 <lb/>b. Reagan and Bush and Clinton all pointed to the growth in employment, <lb/>which happened in the eighties and in the early nineties. <lb/>(LSAC) <lb/>Presumably, the speakers in (7) could have avoided the &quot;superfluous&quot; repetitions, <lb/>opting for the shorter and more compact conjunctions in (8): <lb/>(8) a. ∼The yearlings have great long bare spots in their sides and rumps. 11 <lb/>b. ∼Reagan and Bush and Clinton all pointed to the growth in employment, <lb/>which happened in the eighties and early nineties. <lb/>Note, however, that sides and rumps, and the eighties and early nineties may very well <lb/>be interpreted as referring to grounds denoting single space and time continuities <lb/>(respectively). Avoiding this reading is the motivation behind the longer variants in (7). <lb/>The ground is then construed as consisting of two separate reference points. As a <lb/>result, we are more likely to envision the yearlings as having spots on the sides, which <lb/>are separate from the spots on the rumps (in (8a)). Similarly, the employment growth <lb/>(in (8b)) is construed as comprising two separate intervals of growth, one pointed to by <lb/>the Republican presidents in the 80s and one pointed to by the Democratic president in <lb/>the early nineties. The repeated and here supports a distributive versus a collective <lb/>reading. We note that Chatzikyriakidis and Giorgos 2015 analyze Greek reduplicate <lb/>conjunctive correlatives (ke… ke…lit. &apos;and… and…&apos;, &apos;both…&apos;) as specialized for a <lb/>distributive, rather than a collective reading. The Hebrew bein correlative is partly <lb/>similar to this construction, although it&apos;s not quite distributive. <lb/>We propose that the reduplicate form (for and and for bein) creates a separation <lb/>between the conjoined elements (an iconic motivation). Consider (1b) again in <lb/>Example (9) below. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">9 According to the Hebrew Academy of Language (10 July 2012), the compact structure is a much later <lb/>development, most likely from the Diaspora. The few Mishnaic cases are assumed to be copying <lb/>errors. <lb/>10 LSAC is the Longman Corpus of Spoken American English. <lb/>11 ∼ indicates an unattested example. <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1309 <lb/></page>

        <body>(9) <lb/>Va.yešvu <lb/>bein <lb/>bet el u-vein <lb/>ha-ʕai. <lb/>and they.abode between Bethel and-between the Ai <lb/>&apos;And they abode between Bethel and Ai.&apos; <lb/>(Joshua 8: 9) <lb/>Recall that bein&apos;s original meaning is &apos;within, among&apos;, which introduces a continuous <lb/>region as its complement. If so, [bein (bet el ve-ha-ʕai)] could be interpreted as &apos;within <lb/>a single region covering both places&apos;. But this is precisely what the speakers using <lb/>the complex PP construction wished to avoid. Their intended referent is the space <lb/>between these two places, such that the latter are taken as two separate reference <lb/>points, together delineating that space. <lb/>Now, when the reduplicated form is &apos;and&apos; this separation forces a distributive <lb/>reading (as in Greek and English). When the relevant form is the locative preposition <lb/>bein, as in Hebrew, all we get is a blocking of a single, continuous region. In this way, <lb/>the Hebrew construction maintains the independence of each of the landmarks, but <lb/>in this case, it gave way to a &apos;between (individuated reference points)&apos; interpretation, <lb/>later entrenched as part of the [bein (X u-vein Y)] construction. This continues the <lb/>trend of including prominent landmarks and/or reference points already noted <lb/>for the simple PP construction in Section 2.1. But in the complex construction, all <lb/>the relevant entities are prominent (as compared with about a third in the simple <lb/>construction). This is crucial for the evolution of the complex locative construction <lb/>into a disjunctive construction (see Section 2.2.3). <lb/>2.2.2 The functions of Biblical complex bein &apos;between&apos; constructions <lb/>As mentioned above, [bein X u-vein Y] constitutes the great majority of the complex <lb/>bein PP constructions. The remaining 32 cases (20.8 %) omit the conjunction u, and <lb/>replace bein with a different preposition, le &apos;to&apos;, resulting in a different structure, <lb/>where bein governs a PP, rather than a conjunction (see Example 10). <lb/>(10) <lb/>[ pp bein <lb/>( pp X le-Y)] <lb/>[ pp between ( pp X to-Y)] <lb/>This is a more compact syntactic structure. Note that the syntactic symmetry be-<lb/>tween the landmarks is lost, but the distinctness of X and Y is maintained because <lb/>bein takes two complements (&apos;X to Y&apos; is also not merged into a singular referent). <lb/>Here in Table 2 below is the breakdown of the two variant constructions for the <lb/>construction&apos;s functions. <lb/>A comparison between the simple PP construction in Table 1 and the complex PP <lb/>construction in Table 2 shows remarkably different discourse profiles for the two <lb/>constructions, mainly concerning the prominence of the locative function. We note a <lb/></body>

        <page>1310 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>substantial reduction in locative and time adverbials, a rise in specifying a nonspatial, <lb/>abstract symmetric relation between the NPs, and a rise in irrealis contexts associated <lb/>with choice. These changes motivate bein&apos;s later constructional functions. <lb/>Time adverbials were not found here at all. This is not surprising since 11/12 time <lb/>adverbials in Table 1 were restricted to a single collocation. Locative adverbials remain <lb/>the most frequent function here (31.8 %), but this is a remarkably lower percentage <lb/>than for the simple PP construction (72.6 %). We here first see NP complement cases, <lb/>most of which lack a reduplicated preposition, as in Example (11a): <lb/>(11) a. Ha-Xuqim… <lb/>bein <lb/>iš <lb/>le-išto <lb/>the statutes… <lb/>between <lb/>man <lb/>to-his.wife <lb/>&apos;the statutes… between a husband and his wife.&apos; (Numbers 30:17) <lb/>b. Le-hafer <lb/>et <lb/>ha-aXva <lb/>bein <lb/>yehuda <lb/>to-break <lb/>ACC <lb/>the-brotherhood between Judah <lb/>u-vein <lb/>israel <lb/>and-between Israel <lb/>&apos;to break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel&apos; <lb/>(Zachary 11: 14) <lb/>Copular and NP complement bein constructions, as well as VP adjuncts, all focus on a <lb/>nonphysical relation between the two reference points, which they mention <lb/>explicitly. Here&apos;s a VP adjunct example: <lb/>(12) <lb/>Ve-eva <lb/>ašit <lb/>bein.xa <lb/>u-vein <lb/>ha-iša. <lb/>and-enmity I.will.put between.you and-between the-woman <lb/>&apos;I will put enmity between you and the woman.&apos; <lb/>(Genesis 3: 5). <lb/>These three construction types, where the space between the landmarks is construed <lb/>as some abstract symmetric relation between two referents, constitute 38.9 % of the <lb/>Table : The two variant complex PP bein constructions per each semantic/syntactic function. <lb/>Bein X u-vein Y <lb/>Bein X le-Y <lb/>Total <lb/>Locative <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Copular complement <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Verb argument <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>NP complement <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>VP adjunct <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Sentential adjunct <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Total <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1311 <lb/></page>

        <body>complex bein constructions, as compared with only 3.6 % of the simple constructions. <lb/>As we see immediately, these are not the only constructions where an abstract <lb/>relation between the profiled entities is involved. <lb/>Another function that shows a dramatic rise in frequency is verbal argument <lb/>cases (as in (6) above). This function, which presupposes an abstract relation be-<lb/>tween the entities, was rather marginal for the simple PP construction (9.5 %) but is <lb/>now almost three times as frequent (26.6 %). This is a more advanced stage of <lb/>development in that (i) the relation between the reference points need not be <lb/>explicitly mentioned -it is implied by the verb meaning (e.g., &apos;judge&apos;), and (ii) a <lb/>substantial minority involves the more compact &apos;between X to Y&apos; construction <lb/>(41.5 %). All in all, more than two-thirds of the complex constructions are associated <lb/>with some abstract, nonspatial symmetric relation between prominent referents, as <lb/>opposed to 12.6 % of the simple constructions. <lb/>In addition, a majority of these tokens imply a choice to be made between two <lb/>alternatives (26/41, 63.4 %). An even larger majority (35, 87.8 %) occurs in an irrealis <lb/>context, which is a well-established precursor of disjunctive constructions. The <lb/>disjunctive target construction for the complex construction is restricted to irrealis <lb/>contexts. We must stress, however, that there&apos;s a significant difference between an <lb/>inferred interpretation of &apos;dispute&apos;, &apos;peace&apos;, or any other symmetric relation between <lb/>the reference points (as in Examples (3) and (4)) and an inferred &apos;alternativity&apos; <lb/>relation between the reference points. The former relations are conceptual, but the <lb/>latter is procedural, so it does not contribute to the propositional content. This <lb/>procedural status of &apos;alternativity&apos; is the hallmark of grammaticized disjunctive <lb/>constructions -consider the difference between the explicit alternativity encoded by <lb/>otherwise, alternatively and the implicit alternativity associated with the gramma-<lb/>ticized or (Ariel and Mauri 2019). <lb/>2.2.3 Free-alternative bein constructions <lb/>Three VP adjunct constructions deserve special attention. They combine conjunctive <lb/>and disjunctive components, which is why we propose that they constitute a natural <lb/>bridging context (Evans and Wilkins 2000; Traugott and Dasher 2002) between the <lb/>conjunctive phase above and the Mishnaic adverbial indifference-disjunctive <lb/>construction. 12 We note that these three are not only rare in the Bible, but they also <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">12 Davidson (2013) offers an interesting analysis for juxtaposed phrases in ASL as generally coor-<lb/>dinated components. These are then contextually interpreted either conjunctively or disjunctively. <lb/>But free-alternative &apos;or&apos; constructions, as well as the relevant bein constructions considered below, <lb/>are different in that they actually combine both &apos;additivity&apos; and &apos;alternativity&apos; (in varying degrees of <lb/>prominence). <lb/></note>

        <page>1312 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>have a very restricted dispersal (Gries 2022): all three occur in a single chapter in <lb/>Leviticus, where the verb is compatible with an ensuing choice between alternatives <lb/>(2 tokens of &apos;assess&apos; and 1 of &apos;distinguish&apos;), although the writer is indifferent to which <lb/>choice is made. 13 Here is one such case in Example (13). <lb/>(13) <lb/>Ve-heʕerix <lb/>ha-kohen ota bein <lb/>tov <lb/>and-shall.assess the-priest it <lb/>between/be.it good <lb/>u-vein <lb/>raʕ. Ke-ʕerkexa <lb/>ha-kohen ken <lb/>and-between/be.it bad. as-you.value the-priest so <lb/>yihye. <lb/>will.be <lb/>&apos;And the priest shall value it as either good or bad; as the priest values it, so it <lb/>shall be.&apos; <lb/>(Leviticus 27:12, English Standard Version) <lb/>Importantly, these examples introduce two alternatives (&apos;good&apos; and &apos;bad&apos; in all three <lb/>cases), where the speaker is indifferent to the actual choice to be made between <lb/>them. They are the only Biblical bein examples that are paraphrasable by &apos;or&apos;, as <lb/>shown by the translation. In this respect, they are quite similar to the more familiar <lb/>free-alternative (or &quot;free-choice&quot; in Kamp [1973]) or constructions analyzed by Ariel <lb/>and Mauri (2018) in Example (14), despite the absence of an &apos;or&apos; connective in (13). <lb/>(14) <lb/>RANDY: … But you can wrap em around, <lb/>to one-thirty or one-sixty, (SBC: 022) 14 <lb/>According to Ariel and Mauri (2018), using a free-alternative or construction, (in (15)) <lb/>the speaker. <lb/>(15) <lb/>a. puts on the table multiple nonfactual alternatives. <lb/>b. commits to the possibility of each of the alternatives to be realized. <lb/>c. expects only one alternative to be realized. <lb/>d. is impartial as to which alternative is realized (&apos;any one&apos;). <lb/>The semantically faithful paraphrase proposed by Ariel and Mauri (2018) for such con-<lb/>structions is &apos;any one of X and Y&apos;. Indeed, (13) fits the bill: (a) It presents two alternatives <lb/>(&apos;good&apos; and &apos;bad&apos;) within a deontic (nonfactual) modality -the priest is supposed to be the <lb/>assessor of acceptable (good) and unacceptable (bad) sacrifices; (b) the speaker commits <lb/>to the viability of each of two alternative assessments (&apos;good&apos; and &apos;bad&apos;) -a conjunctive, <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">13 We thank one of our referees for drawing our attention to the role of the specific verbs here. <lb/>14 SBC refers to the Santa Barbara Corpus of Spoken American English (Du Bois et al. 2000-2005), see: <lb/>https://www.linguistics.ucsb.edu/research/santa-barbara-corpus. <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1313 <lb/></page>

        <body>&apos;both&apos; interpretation; 15 at the same time, (c) the speaker expects only one assessment (at a <lb/>time); finally, (d) although one alternative is expected to be chosen per event, the speaker <lb/>is open to any one of them being chosen. Indeed, the priest is free to offer either one of the <lb/>two alternative assessments (per beast inspection), as the continuation makes clear <lb/>&quot;According to the assessment of the priest, so it shall be&quot;. <lb/>In sum, Biblical Hebrew bein X u-vein Y prepared the ground for the next evolutionary <lb/>step, a correlative adverbial indifference-disjunctive construction, in that, unlike the <lb/>simple PP construction, it shows an increase in the number of cases profiling (i) specifically <lb/>two prominent entities, which (ii) are linked to each other by an abstract relation (rather <lb/>than physical space). This relation is, moreover, very often projected on (iii) an irrealis <lb/>state of affairs, where the entities are not only construable as (iv) alternatives to each <lb/>other, but (vi) a choice between them is discourse-relevant, even if it is not foregrounded. <lb/>This is why the constructions are relatively closer to typical disjunctive relations (see Ariel <lb/>and Mauri 2019), so the bein complements are no longer purely conjunctive. The last <lb/>Hebrew example discussed, Example (13), is a bona fide free-alternative construction, <lb/>which is synonymous with a free-alternative &apos;or&apos; construction. The free-alternative bein <lb/>construction in (13), we claim, is the direct source of the adverbial indifference-disjunctive <lb/>use predominant among Mishnaic Hebrew bein constructions. <lb/>3 Mishnaic Hebrew: from conjunctive <lb/>construction to indifference-disjunctive <lb/>adverbial <lb/>Our main challenge is to explain the shift from a clearly conjunctive construction <lb/>(&apos;between Bethel and Ai&apos; -(1b)) to a disjunctive construction (&apos;whether successors <lb/>or not&apos; -1c). We here argue that two factors contributed to this shift: (i) irrealis <lb/>contexts which are characteristic of disjunctions, and (ii) the specific disjunctive <lb/>reading evolved, namely &apos;free-alternative&apos;, which combines conjunctive and <lb/>disjunctive aspects (see Section 3.1 below). <lb/>Mishnaic Hebrew partially overlaps with Late Biblical Hebrew, ending in the <lb/>early part of the 3rd century. The 206 bein examples we coded were extracted <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">15 As befits conjunctive constructions, free-alternative constructions can be falsified on the basis of <lb/>only one false alternative. This is true for (14), as in (a), and equally so for (13), as in (b): <lb/>a. ∼That&apos;s not true. I can&apos;t wrap em around to one-thirty <lb/>b. ∼That&apos;s not true. He shall not assess it as bad. <lb/></note>

        <page>1314 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>from &quot;Ma&apos;agarim&quot;, a historical corpus compiled by the Hebrew Academy of <lb/>language. 16 <lb/>The Mishnaic bein constructions manifest several formal differences from their <lb/>Biblical counterparts, all pointing to greater complexity. The first difference pertains <lb/>to the ratio of simple bein constructions (the modified NP is a single plural NP) and <lb/>complex bein constructions (the modified NP/PP comprises two distinct NPs). The <lb/>number of simple bein constructions is here reduced by half (40/206, 19.4 %, Cf. 38.1 % <lb/>in the Bible), while that of complex constructions increases to a solid majority of <lb/>80.6 % (166/206), as compared with 61.8 % for Biblical Hebrew. The second added <lb/>complexity pertains to bein complements. As befits a preposition, the Biblical bein <lb/>complements virtually all NPs. 17 But Mishnaic Hebrew allows adjectives, adverbs <lb/>and even clauses (only in the adverbial indifference-disjunctive construction). 18 This <lb/>syntactic expansion in complement types, we suggest, testifies to a reanalysis of the <lb/>original preposition bein &apos;within, between&apos; as a connective akin to the conjunctive <lb/>&apos;whether&apos; (but only in the adverbial indifference-disjunctive construction). <lb/>At the same time, grammaticization is often accompanied by formal compactiza-<lb/>tion, i.e., &quot;less form for more meaning&quot; (Hopper and Traugott 2003 [1993]) (see also <lb/>Bardenstein 2016). The price of compactization is reduced semantic transparency, of <lb/>course. Overt conjoining is no longer transparently indicated in the majority of Mish-<lb/>naic bein cases. First, whereas all the Biblical correlative bein constructions involve an <lb/>explicit ve &apos;and&apos;, more than two-thirds of the reference points within the correlative <lb/>Mishnaic constructions (74/108, 68.5 %) now show juxtaposed phrases: [bein X bein Y]. <lb/>Second, as much as a third of the Mishnaic complex constructions (54/166, 32.5 %) show <lb/>le &apos;to&apos; instead of a reduplicated bein: [bein X le-Y], rather than the more complex [bein X <lb/>u-vein Y]. Unlike bein &apos;between&apos;, le &apos;to&apos; does not participate in a syntactically symmetric <lb/>construction. The construction then is less transparent, since a conceptually symmetric <lb/>relation is expressed by a syntactically nonsymmetric structure. <lb/>Third, the proportion of constructions naming the symmetric relation between <lb/>the two reference points (with an overt NP) has dramatically dropped, from 28.9 % in <lb/>Biblical Hebrew to 1.9 % in Mishnaic Hebrew (4/206). No doubt this is so because the <lb/>constructions are no longer necessarily associated with a syntactically symmetric <lb/>structure, so it&apos;s virtually always left to inference. Especially interesting in this <lb/>connection are two sub-constructions where a specific NP that is syntactically and <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">16 https://ma&apos;agarim.hebrew-academy.org.il/Pages/PMain.aspx. An exhaustive search of the <lb/>Mishnah revealed 378 sentences containing 412 bein constructions (some sentences contained mul-<lb/>tiple constructions). <lb/>17 We note that Hebrew adjectives often have nominal forms (as in 13). We analyzed every other bein <lb/>token of 412 cases, totaling 206 instances <lb/>18 Bein-prefaced clauses are introduced by the complementizer she &apos;that&apos; (there were 17 such cases). <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1315 <lb/></page>

        <body>semantically mandated is nonetheless absent. Not surprisingly, in all these cases in <lb/>(16) the &quot;missing NP&quot; is &apos;(the) difference&apos;: <lb/>(16) a. Ma <lb/>bein <lb/>get <lb/>le-mita <lb/>what <lb/>between <lb/>divorce <lb/>to-death <lb/>&apos;What is the difference between divorce and death?&apos; (Gittin 2:7) <lb/>b. Ein <lb/>bein <lb/>cohen <lb/>mešameš <lb/>there.is.no <lb/>between <lb/>Jewish.priest <lb/>serving <lb/>le-cohen <lb/>še-avar <lb/>to-Jewish.priest <lb/>that-passed <lb/>&apos;There is no difference between a serving (Jewish) priest and one that no <lb/>longer serves&apos; <lb/>(Megillah 1: 9) <lb/>So, all in all, Mishnaic Hebrew has a stronger preference for the more complex <lb/>bein constructions, in some of which bein has shifted from a preposition to a <lb/>connective (see below). At the same time, a higher compactization reflects a higher <lb/>degree of grammaticization of these complex constructions. We return to the <lb/>conjunction &gt; juxtaposition shift below. <lb/>What about the functions served by the constructions? The proportion of locative <lb/>and temporal uses has decreased from 47.4 to 34.9 % (72/206). We further note that a <lb/>majority of these are expressed specifically by the simple bein construction (40, 55.5 %). <lb/>Focusing on the 166 complex bein constructions (introducing two distinct NPs), a third <lb/>(58, 34.9 %) concerns some relation between the reference points (physical or temporal <lb/>space, or a distinction drawn between categories according to Jewish law). The <lb/>remaining majority 108 examples are all disjunctive (and discussed below). <lb/>Recall that Biblical Hebrew introduced a variant, more compact [bein X le-Y], &apos;[be-<lb/>tween X to-Y]&apos; form. Mishnaic Hebrew added another variant, a conjunctionless [bein X <lb/>bein Y] &apos;[between X between Y]&apos;. Once these variant constructions are available, Mishnaic <lb/>Hebrew is able to draw a sharp distinction between disjunctive and nondisjunctive bein <lb/>uses. While 100 % of the disjunctive cases contain a reduplicated bein (with or without ve <lb/>&apos;and&apos;) only 4/58 (6.9 %) nondisjunctive complex bein constructions contain a reduplicated <lb/>u-vein. 93.1 % (54 tokens) present the simplified [bein X le-Y] structure, but no disjunctive <lb/>tokens show the le &apos;to&apos; variant. In addition, 40 of the locative/temporal examples are <lb/>expressed by the simple [bein NPs] structure, disjunctive and nondisjunctive functions <lb/>are virtually always formally distinct: 100 % disjunctive uses show a reduplicated bein, as <lb/>compared with 4/98 of the nondisjunctive uses (4.1 %). And no disjunctive uses show a le <lb/>&apos;to&apos; construction, as compared with virtually all nondisjunctive uses (93.1 %). <lb/></body>

        <page>1316 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>3.1 The correlative adverbial indifference-disjunctive bein <lb/>constructions: combining conjunctive and disjunctive <lb/>aspects <lb/>The most frequent function observed in Mishnaic Hebrew (e.g., 1c) (107/206, 51.9 %) is <lb/>one we&apos;re calling correlative adverbial indifference-disjunctive because it is quite <lb/>parallel to the function served by the &apos;or&apos; construction dubbed Indifference adverbial <lb/>or by Ariel (2016), as in (17), where the whether…or adverbial exhaustively lists all <lb/>the alternatives under which &apos;it would still be water&apos; holds true: 19 <lb/>(17) <lb/>PHIL: .. But it would still be water. ((1 LINE OMITTED)) <lb/>(H)… Whether it&apos;s a solid, a liquid, or a gas. <lb/>(SBC: 026) <lb/>Recall that we did find 3 relatively disjunctive bein examples in Biblical Hebrew, <lb/>which we classified as free-alternative bein constructions, namely constructions <lb/>that combine conjunctive and disjunctive elements. We claim that these free-<lb/>alternative constructions hold the key ingredient for the shift from a predomi-<lb/>nantly conjunctive to a predominantly disjunctive construction. But before we <lb/>demonstrate how small the step is that separates indifference-disjunctive adver-<lb/>bials from free-alternative cases we would like to make a more general point. It is <lb/>no accident that some constructions combine the seemingly rather different <lb/>conjunctive and disjunctive relations. This is because states of affairs may simul-<lb/>taneously manifest both conjunctive (&apos;additive&apos;) and disjunctive (&apos;alternativity&apos;) <lb/>aspects. In such cases, the choice between or and and is dictated by the speaker&apos;s <lb/>choice of construal. <lb/>As argued by Ariel and Mauri (2019), overt conjoining does not preclude an <lb/>inferred &apos;alternativity&apos; (hence, disjunctive) relation between the conjuncts. Consider <lb/>Example (18) in which they cite: <lb/>(18) <lb/>Many treatments, including steroids, gabapentin, acupuncture, heat or ice, <lb/>and spinal manipulation, have poor evidence for their use. <lb/>(Wikipedia, 29 Jan 2023) <lb/>The source cited in (18) lists six examples of treatments for sciatica, all claimed to be <lb/>ineffective. However, the speaker did not choose to construe them as a list of six <lb/>parallel alternatives. Instead, five types of treatment are profiled as members of an <lb/>additive list: steroids, gabapentin, acupuncture, spinal manipulation, and crucially, <lb/>some temperature-changing treatment (i.e., heat and ice), the latter two being <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">19 Example (22) discussed below is ambiguous between a free-alternative and an indifference-<lb/>disjunctive adverbial, so was not here counted. <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1317 <lb/></page>

        <body>profiled as alternatives to each other. But the reality behind (18) is that all six <lb/>treatments are both (i) members of an additive list of treatments, and (ii) alternatives <lb/>to each other. Speakers have a choice in such cases whether to present the options as <lb/>conjunctively or as disjunctively conjoined. Example (19) is a famous Biblical quote <lb/>that uses the conjunction ve &apos;and&apos;, but is routinely translated by the disjunctive &apos;or&apos; <lb/>because it is interpreted as a free-alternative disjunction: <lb/>(19) <lb/>U-make <lb/>aviv <lb/>ve-imo <lb/>mot <lb/>and-beater.of his.father and-his.mother to.die <lb/>yumat. <lb/>will.be.killed <lb/>(Exodus 21: 15) <lb/>&apos;And he that smiteth his father, or his mother, shall be surely put to death.&apos; <lb/>(King James Version) <lb/>&apos;Whoever strikes father or mother shall be put to death.&apos; <lb/>(New Revised Standard Version Updated Edition) <lb/>Ariel and Mauri (2018) argued that some or constructions display a &apos;both&apos; interpretation on <lb/>one level, but a mutually exclusive &apos;only one&apos; interpretation on another level. From a bird&apos;s <lb/>eye view, they explained, the speaker commits to all the options mentioned in the free-<lb/>alternative (14) (a conjunctive reading). But from an ant&apos;s point of view, which is limited to <lb/>one event at a time, only one option can be realized (the addressee is expected to choose <lb/>either &apos;one thirty&apos; or &apos;one sixty&apos; in 14). We propose that constructions projecting such Janus-<lb/>faced states of affairs serve as a bridging context from conjunctive to disjunctive readings. <lb/>In (13), a free-alternative complex bein construction on our account, &apos;good&apos; and &apos;bad&apos; <lb/>simultaneously function as members of an additive list of assessments available to the <lb/>priest to choose from, and at the same time, as alternatives that are mutually exclusive to <lb/>each other, since the priest is expected to choose only one assessment at a time. <lb/>The following Mishnaic examples show that indeed, the complex indifference <lb/>bein construction is quite parallel to both &apos;or&apos; and &apos;and&apos; constructions. The speakers <lb/>here shift between bein and o &apos;or&apos; (in a) and between bein and ve &apos;and&apos; (in b), although <lb/>each of the four pairs of entities introduce an &apos;alternativity&apos; relation: <lb/>(20) a. ha-moci <lb/>bein <lb/>bi-ymino, <lb/>bein <lb/>one.who.takes.out whether in-his.right whether <lb/>bi-smolo, betox Xeiko o al ktefo <lb/>his.left <lb/>in <lb/>his.lap or on his.shoulder <lb/>Xayav <lb/>accountable <lb/>&apos;He who takes out (the Holy Ark), whether with his right or his left hand, in <lb/>his lap or on his shoulder, is held accountable&apos; <lb/>(Shabbat 10: 3) <lb/></body>

        <page>1318 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>b. Bein <lb/>gdolim bein <lb/>qtanim, <lb/>whether big.ones whether small.ones, <lb/>le-daʕato <lb/>ve-she-lo <lb/>le-daʕato <lb/>according.to-his.opinion and-that-not according.to-his.opinion <lb/>&apos;Whether big ones or small ones, whether according to his opinion or not&apos; <lb/>(Machshirin 6: 8) <lb/>As mentioned above, the common disjunctive bein construction in Mishnaic Hebrew is <lb/>not a free-alternative construction, but rather, a correlative adverbial indifference-<lb/>disjunctive construction (similar to the &apos;or&apos; construction exemplified in (8)). Indeed, the <lb/>adverbial indifference-disjunctive construction is also about options that can be <lb/>construed either additively, via ve &apos;and&apos;, or as alternatives to each other, via the <lb/>complex bein construction. On our account, a few small and related steps separate the <lb/>Mishnaic (1c), here repeated as (21), from the Biblical free-alternative use in (13): <lb/>(21) <lb/>Bein <lb/>min ha-yorshim u-vein <lb/>še-eino <lb/>min <lb/>whether from the-heirs <lb/>and-whether that-isn&apos;t from <lb/>ha-yorshim, dvarav <lb/>kayamin. <lb/>the-heirs, <lb/>his.words are.valid <lb/>&apos;Whether (he is) one of the successors or not, his words are valid.&apos; <lb/>(Baba Bathra 8: 6) <lb/>First, while both the free-alternative bein construction in (13) and the indifference-<lb/>disjunctive adverbial in (21) are optional adjuncts, the former is governed within <lb/>the VP, but the latter is not VP-governed. Rather, it is a clause-level constituent. <lb/>Second, and not surprisingly, the free-alternative bein construction is an integral <lb/>part of the main assertion, contributing pertinent conceptual propositional con-<lb/>tent, but the indifference-disjunctive adverbial is more loosely integrated with the <lb/>main assertions (&apos;It would still be water&apos; in (17); &apos;His words are valid&apos; in (21)). It is a <lb/>correlative adverbial, hence, syntactically incomplete on its own, and intonation-<lb/>ally set apart from the main assertion. It only plays an auxiliary role to it, elabo-<lb/>rating on the circumstances under which the main assertion holds. 20 Third, a <lb/>speaker using a free-alternative construction (as in 13) indicates that she is equally <lb/>open to any one of the alternatives being realized, but these alternatives may or <lb/>may not (objectively) carry different implications (e.g., &apos;good beasts are sacrifice-<lb/>able&apos;, &apos;bad beasts are not&apos;). Using an indifference-disjunctive adverbial, however, <lb/>the speaker does not only happen to be indifferent as to which alternative should be <lb/>realized, she actively conveys that the alternatives equally fit the bill. In other <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">20 Indeed, unlike the free-alternative construction, the indifference-disjunctive adverbial can be <lb/>omitted without affecting the truth of the main assertion. <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1319 <lb/></page>

        <body>words, a potential &apos;indifference&apos; pragmatic inference comes to be an inherent <lb/>procedural ingredient of the construction. <lb/>The interpretative difference between free-alternative and adverbial indiffer-<lb/>ence-disjunctive cases, we claim, results from the different syntactic attachment of <lb/>the bein construction to the main assertion. This carries semantic and pragmatic <lb/>effects. (22) shows this syntax/interpretation dependence, which is why we analyze it <lb/>as a potential bridge between the two readings. Each reading is explicated in (23): <lb/>(22) <lb/>Rabi yosi <lb/>omer yavor. <lb/>Bein <lb/>Rabbi Joseph says should.separate.out be.it/whether <lb/>mi-min <lb/>eXad, bein <lb/>mi-shnei minin. Rabi <lb/>from-kind one, be.it/whether from-two kinds Rabbi <lb/>shimʕon omer lo <lb/>amru ela <lb/>mi-min <lb/>eXad. <lb/>Simon <lb/>says not said.pl except from-kind one <lb/>&apos;Rabbi Joseph says he shall separate out. Be it one kind, be it two kinds. <lb/>Rabbib Simon says they only said from one kind.&apos; (Kil&apos;ayim 2:1) <lb/>(23) <lb/>a. Free-alternative: &apos;Rabbi Joseph says one should separate out. One kind or <lb/>two kinds. <lb/>b. Indifference-disjunctive adverbial: &apos;Rabbi Joseph says one should separate <lb/>out. Whether it is one kind or two kinds&apos;. <lb/>The fact that yavor &apos;separate out&apos; normally requires an argument (here served by the <lb/>bein construction), as well as Rabbi Simon&apos;s response (&quot;It was only said one kind&quot;) <lb/>support a free-alternative reading (VP attachment). But the full stop dividing (22) into <lb/>two utterances, where the second is an added increment on the first one, inter-<lb/>pretable as a complete main assertion, supports an adverbial indifference-disjunc-<lb/>tive interpretation, which is more loosely connected to the main proposition (S <lb/>attachment). <lb/>Most of the adverbial indifference constructions (73/107, 68.2 %) function as <lb/>conditional adjuncts, which specify further circumstances under which the main <lb/>assertion applies (as in (20), (21), (22)). The rest (34/107, 31.8 %) have a slightly <lb/>different, clarification function, as in: <lb/>(24) <lb/>YocɁa <lb/>iša <lb/>be-xutei <lb/>sear bein <lb/>mi-šela <lb/>goes.out woman in-threads hair whether from-hers <lb/>u-vein <lb/>mi-šel <lb/>xaverta <lb/>u-vein <lb/>mi-šel <lb/>and-whether from-of friend.her and-whether from-of <lb/>behema <lb/>beast <lb/>&apos;A woman comes out with hair-made threads, whether her own or another&apos;s <lb/>or a beast&apos;s&apos; <lb/>(Shabbat 6: 5) <lb/></body>

        <page>1320 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>The category under discussion in (24) is &apos;hair-made threads&apos;. Now, as is well-known, <lb/>the set of contextually adjusted denotations associated with lexical items is often <lb/>narrowed to only a subset of the potential denotations of those expressions (Carston <lb/>2002). The adverbial indifference-disjunctive construction in (24) has a metalinguistic <lb/>function in effect, in that it guides the addressee on how to interpret &apos;hair-made <lb/>threads&apos;: The addressee should avoid narrowing the concept into &apos;hair-made threads <lb/>that are specifically the woman&apos;s own&apos; (for example). The correlative adverbial then <lb/>strengthens the propositional content of the utterance (making sure it applies to more <lb/>states of affairs). We surmise that this metalinguistic use is a later development, just <lb/>because of its metalinguistic flavor, but we have no evidence for this. 21 <lb/>Finally, the set of alternatives in the adverbial indifference-disjunctive con-<lb/>structions is profiled as exhaustive (see Mittwoch et al. 2002). Hence, the main clause <lb/>or category is here asserted to hold/apply under all relevant circumstances <lb/>(regardless of which one of the listed alternatives is realized). The construction then <lb/>establishes the main assertion as a relatively strong statement. This is the first bein <lb/>construction that sets a procedural argumentative strengthening path for its later <lb/>descendants (see Bardenstein 2021 and above on the persistence of argumentative <lb/>direction across diachronic changes). <lb/>On our account, then, the &quot;free-choice&quot; flavor of the free-alternative bein <lb/>u-vein construction (21), where the speaker projects herself as open to any of the <lb/>listed alternatives, becomes a prominent speaker-intended interpretation in the <lb/>adverbial indifference construction, possibly because of the separate intonation <lb/>unit it receives as a correlative adverbial. These constructions encode a message <lb/>that &apos;it doesn&apos;t matter whether X is the case or Y is the case&apos;. The speaker is <lb/>committed to the main assertion (dvarav kayamim &apos;his words are valid&apos;) under <lb/>circumstances that the addressee might have considered as exceptions to the <lb/>claim. We note that the overwhelming majority of these involve antonyms, polar <lb/>or cultural opposites, which if we apply the excluded middle principle, cover all <lb/>relevant options and not only the ones explicitly mentioned. This is how the <lb/>construction must have come to construe the alternatives as contrastive and <lb/>exhaustive. <lb/>Here&apos;s one such example, where widows who are in between rich and poor are <lb/>most likely inferred to be included under the predication: <lb/>(25) <lb/>Almana -bein <lb/>še-hi <lb/>ʕaniya, bein <lb/>še-hi <lb/>Widow -whether that-she poor, whether that-she <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">21 Not surprisingly, quite a few of the examples were hard to classify as &apos;conditional&apos; versus <lb/>&apos;metalinguistic&apos;. <lb/>Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1321 <lb/></page>

        <body>ʕašira -ein memaškenin <lb/>ota. <lb/>rich -not <lb/>take.collateral from.her <lb/>&apos;A widow, whether she is poor or rich, must not be taken collateral from.&apos; <lb/>(Baba Metzia 9: 13) <lb/>Note that the construction in (25) is slightly different from the ones we have so far <lb/>analyzed, in that the two bein phrases are here juxtaposed, rather than conjoined by <lb/>ve &apos;and&apos;. This is the case for 24 of the disjunctive bein constructions. While these only <lb/>constitute 22.2 % of the disjunctive constructions, just like the correlative construc-<lb/>tion, they are restricted to disjunctive uses. We propose that this change is not <lb/>motivated by mere compactization. It also reflects a disconnection from the initial <lb/>conjunctive construal of the complex bein constructions due to their disjunctive <lb/>interpretation. Indeed, we observe the same ve &apos;and&apos; omission for a parallel indif-<lb/>ference-disjunctive adverbial, this one already within Biblical Hebrew: <lb/>(26) <lb/>Metuqa šnat <lb/>ha-ʕeved, im meʕat ve-im <lb/>Sweet <lb/>sleep.of the-slave, if little <lb/>and-if <lb/>harbe yoxal. <lb/>a lot shall.eat <lb/>&apos;The sleep of a slave is sweet, whether he eats a little or a lot.&apos; <lb/>(Ecclesiastes 5:11) <lb/>This construction can occur with or without an explicit ve &apos;and&apos;, although the explicit <lb/>conjunction is much more common. Since this construction evolved in Biblical He-<lb/>brew it shows ve &apos;and&apos; omission in the Bible already, which the (overwhelmingly non-<lb/>disjunctive) Biblical complex bein constructions do not. <lb/>3.2 Bein kax u-vein kax &apos;whether this or that way&apos; constructions <lb/>An interesting and relatively frequent sub-construction of the [bein X u-vein Y] con-<lb/>struction is the [bein kax u-vein kax], &apos;whether thus or thus&apos;/&apos;whether this way or that <lb/>way&apos; sub-construction, which constitutes 13.9 % of the disjunctive constructions (15/ <lb/>108). An exhaustive search for this construction yielded a total of 33 examples, whose <lb/>interpretation is similar to the interpretation of the English (14) and the Mishnaic 1(c)/ <lb/>(21) and (25) in that together, the two kaxs &apos;thus&apos; also exhaust the relevant alternatives <lb/>under which the main assertion holds true. The only difference is that each of the <lb/>alternatives here is represented by the deictic kax &apos;thus&apos; used anaphorically (its <lb/>antecedent has just been mentioned in the discourse), rather than by lexical material: <lb/></body>

        <page>1322 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>(27) <lb/>ŠaXor še-yeš <lb/>bo <lb/>efer <lb/>kotšin <lb/>oto; ve-še-ein <lb/>black that-there.is in.it ashes crush.they it <lb/>and-that-not <lb/>bo <lb/>maniXin oto. ʕecem-bein <lb/>kax <lb/>in.it leave.PL it. <lb/>Bone-whether like.this <lb/>u-vein <lb/>kax, <lb/>haya niktaš. <lb/>and-whether like.this would be.crushed <lb/>&apos;A black patch which contains ashes should be crushed; and one that doesn&apos;t <lb/>is left alone. A bone, be it one way or another, should be crushed.&apos; <lb/>(Parah 3:11) <lb/>Just like the general indifference-disjunctive adverbial, these examples strongly <lb/>implicate that the difference between the alternatives (here, whether the bone con-<lb/>tains or doesn&apos;t contain ashes) does not matter, which is why we&apos;re proposing that the <lb/>[bein kax u-vein kax] sub-construction is associated with a strong &apos;it doesn&apos;t matter&apos; <lb/>implicature. But whereas the specific alternatives mentioned in the general con-<lb/>struction are construed as exclusions a reasonable addressee might entertain against a <lb/>perfectly general application of the rule, the bein kax u-vein kax construction treats it as <lb/>self-evident that the alternatives pointed to fall within the claim. The argumentative <lb/>strengthening here is therefore stronger than in the general cases. Indeed, the [bein <lb/>kax u-vein kax] sub-construction introduces a stronger variant of the (persisting) <lb/>argumentative strengthening initially introduced in the general construction. <lb/>Summing up the developments observed in Mishnaic Hebrew, we see that while <lb/>the locative/temporal, as well as other readings on various relations between the <lb/>reference points are quite common (totaling almost half of the cases), the frequency <lb/>of simple bein constructions is drastically reduced. More dramatically, unlike in <lb/>Biblical Hebrew, the dominant function served by the complex bein constructions in <lb/>Mishnaic Hebrew is the predominantly disjunctive indifference-disjunctive adver-<lb/>bial. This construction has a collocative sub-construction [bein kax u-vein kax], which <lb/>will play a role in Diaspora and Contemporary Hebrew as well. <lb/>4 Diaspora Hebrew: establishing disjunctiveness, <lb/>creating generic and subset readings, and <lb/>shifting towards &apos;anyway&apos; <lb/>Hebrew was not spoken from approx. the 3rd century up to the 19th century. But we have <lb/>written sources for Diaspora Hebrew from 800 to 1800 (the Ma&apos;agarim corpus -see Note 15 <lb/>again). We extracted 46-48 random examples for every 200-year period, 238 tokens in <lb/>total. While there are frequency fluctuations between the 5 periods, these are mostly <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1323 <lb/></page>

        <body>irrelevant to the evolutionary path we are tracing for bein. More generally, Diaspora <lb/>Hebrew bein mostly shows the same Biblical and Mishnaic functions and constructions. <lb/>Surprisingly perhaps, it often seems closer to Biblical Hebrew than to Mishnaic Hebrew. <lb/>4.1 Establishing disjunctiveness <lb/>Recall that Biblical Hebrew had no adverbial indifference-disjunctive cases, but more <lb/>than half of Mishnaic Hebrew bein constructions were of the indifference type. Dias-<lb/>pora Hebrew has 80/238, 33.6 %. As for distinguishing disjunctive and non-disjunctive <lb/>functions, doubly marked cases are still the majority for disjunctive uses (67/80, 83.4 %), <lb/>but adverbial indifference-disjunctive cases are no longer doubly marked as they were <lb/>in Mishnaic Hebrew. <lb/>Still, Diaspora Hebrew does introduce several disjunctive constructions and <lb/>functions, which will also be attested in Revival and Contemporary Hebrew. Like <lb/>Mishnaic Hebrew, Diaspora Hebrew too adds complementizer še &apos;that&apos; when one or <lb/>both disjuncts are sentential, but it also introduces the variant im &apos;if, whether&apos; <lb/>complementizer, which is the dominant pattern in Contemporary Hebrew. <lb/>(28) <lb/>Bein <lb/>im magia u-vein <lb/>lo <lb/>magia <lb/>whether if arrives and-whether not arrives <lb/>&apos;Whether he arrives or not&apos; <lb/>(Sherira ben Hananya Gaon, before 1038) <lb/>Next, we have seen that adverbial indifference-disjunctive bein constructions may be <lb/>used interchangeably with [X o Y] &apos;X or Y&apos; constructions in Mishnaic Hebrew. Dias-<lb/>pora Hebrew supports our suggestion that the complex bein construction has actu-<lb/>ally undergone reanalysis as a disjunctive construction. 8 of the indifference-<lb/>disjunctive adverbials (10 %) show o &apos;or&apos; instead of the duplicate bein, [bein X o Y] <lb/>&apos;whether X or Y&apos;, as in: 22 <lb/>(29) <lb/>Bein <lb/>še-yihyu <lb/>ilanei srak <lb/>o ʕosei <lb/>pri… <lb/>whether that-will.be trees barren or bearing fruit <lb/>&apos;Whether they are barren or fruit-bearing trees…&apos; <lb/>(Abraham ben Mordechai Farissol 1586) <lb/>Note that o &apos;or&apos; invariably replaces the second bein, not the first one (*[O X bein Y]). The <lb/>same is true for the [im X im Y] &apos;if X if Y&apos; construction discussed above, which also has an o <lb/>&apos;or&apos; variant in place of the second im &apos;if&apos;: [im X o Y] &apos;if X or Y&apos;. According to Ariel (2018), <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">22 These cases were counted as doubly marked disjunctive cases above, together with [bein X (u)-vein <lb/>Y] &apos;whether (and) whether Y&apos;. <lb/></note>

        <page>1324 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>the first would-be &apos;alternativity&apos; marker (the initial bein/im here) has a wider scope, over <lb/>the whole conjunction (see the structure in 5), and is reanalyzed as an &apos;irrealis&apos; marker, 23 <lb/>a crucial component of disjunctive constructions in general, and certainly the ones <lb/>discussed in this article (free-alternative and indifference-disjunctive adverbial). It is <lb/>the second occurrence of bein/im, which governs the second option and profiles an <lb/>&apos;alternativity&apos; relation between them, that is potentially reanalyzed as an &apos;or&apos;. Hence only <lb/>the second bein (and im &apos;if&apos;) is replaceable by o &apos;or&apos;. Ironically perhaps, it is this o <lb/>substitution that will trigger the fall of the indifference-disjunctive bein construction <lb/>later on. <lb/>4.1.1 Bein kax &apos;whether thus&apos; sub-constructions <lb/>We already noted that [bein kax u-vein kax] &apos;whether thus and whether thus&apos; was part <lb/>of a specialized sub-construction in Mishnaic Hebrew, used for argumentative <lb/>strengthening. A search for the string bein kax in Diaspora Hebrew yielded 5 formal <lb/>variants. Interestingly, these variants mirror the very same increasing compactization <lb/>of the general complex bein constructions we saw for the three periods above. The only <lb/>difference is that the alternatives here are restricted to the deictic kax (or ko) &apos;thus&apos;, <lb/>and the 5th variant (e) is a reduced construction containing only one kax &apos;thus&apos;: <lb/>(30) <lb/>a. bein kax u-vein kax &apos;whether thus and whether thus&apos; <lb/>b. bein kax le-xax &apos;whether thus to thus&apos; <lb/>c. bein kax ve-xax &apos;whether thus and thus&apos; <lb/>d. bein kax o kax &apos;whether thus or thus&apos; <lb/>e. bein kax &apos;whether thus&apos; <lb/>Analyzing or constructions, Ariel and Mauri (2018) found that an extremely frequent <lb/>function of these constructions is what they called the higher-level-category use. In such <lb/>cases, the distinct alternatives listed by the speaker are taken to point to a single higher-<lb/>level category, and it is this abstract entity that is speaker intended. For example, the <lb/>whale or the polar bear (SBC: 003) refers to the single, higher-level category of &apos;endan-<lb/>gered animals&apos; (in that context). The denotation of this abstract category, often ad hocly <lb/>constructed, is not restricted to the members mentioned explicitly, since the higher-level <lb/>category often includes additional members (&apos;grizzly bears&apos;, for example). <lb/>Now, deictics are often mobilized as indefinite references in dedicated conjunctive <lb/>constructions (e.g., this that and the other thing, this or that). If this denotes &apos;some <lb/>indefinite entity&apos; and that denotes &apos;some other indefinite entity&apos; a higher-level category <lb/>reading yields &apos;an unspecified item of a wide-range, yet context-relevant set&apos;, in other <lb/>words, &apos;any (relevant) entity&apos;. Such an evolution makes sense because indifference-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">23 Of course, im &apos;if&apos; starts out as an irrealis marker. <lb/>Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1325 <lb/></page>

        <body>disjunctive adverbials are mobilized for argumentative strengthening. At first, this is <lb/>achieved by specifying broadened conditions under which the rule applies. Such <lb/>conceptual strengthening then naturally gives way to procedural argumentative <lb/>strengthening, where the individual content of the conditions doesn&apos;t even matter. <lb/>Indeed, we note that, unlike the Mishnaic Hebrew cases, the kaxs here are not <lb/>anaphoric, which is why they can be interpreted as indefinite. We found that the <lb/>nonspecific entity referred to by these kaxs is either &apos;some indefinite time interval&apos; or <lb/>&apos;some indefinite circumstance&apos;. For example, each of the kaxs in the following <lb/>example is interpreted as an &apos;indefinite time&apos;, so the higher-level category extracted <lb/>for bein kax u-vein kax here gives rise to &apos;an indefinite time interval&apos;, &apos;in the <lb/>meantime&apos;: <lb/>(31) <lb/>Bein <lb/>kax u-<lb/>vein <lb/>kax moshe ba. <lb/>between thus and-between thus Moses would.come <lb/>&apos;In the meantime, Moses would arrive.&apos; <lb/>(Rashi, Exodus 32: 5) <lb/>Through compactization, we also find the opaque bein kax &apos;between thus&apos; with the <lb/>same interpretation: <lb/>(32) <lb/>Bein <lb/>kax <lb/>asa <lb/>sXorato <lb/>baʕal <lb/>ha-sfina. <lb/>between thus made his.goods owner the-ship <lb/>&apos;In the meantime, the owner of the ship prepared his goods.&apos; <lb/>(Unknown writer, ∼1050) <lb/>But the indefinite deictics may denote &apos;indefinite cases (circumstances/ways/man-<lb/>ners)&apos;, rather than times, so when occurring in the complex construction, a single <lb/>higher-level &apos;any case&apos; concept is extracted. The context preceding (33) introduces <lb/>three distinct alternatives, so the two kaxs in the construction below cannot each be <lb/>anaphoric to one of these alternatives: <lb/>(33) <lb/>Bein <lb/>kax <lb/>o kax <lb/>haya min harauy še… <lb/>whether like.this or ike.that was from proper that… <lb/>&apos;Either way, it would have been appropriate to…&apos; <lb/>(Pinchas Eliyah Horowitz 1797) <lb/>Instead, kax o kax &apos;thus or thus&apos; denotes any unspecified, but relevant alternative <lb/>circumstances, serving a clear argumentative strengthening function. <lb/>The following example shows a more advanced use, where the kaxs do not <lb/>generalize into &apos;any literal circumstance&apos;. Rather, the construction functions as a <lb/>topic shifter &apos;be that as it may/anyway&apos; utterance-level discourse marker: <lb/></body>

        <page>1326 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>(34) <lb/>Bein <lb/>kax <lb/>o kax <lb/>ašrei <lb/>mi <lb/>še-banav <lb/>zxarim <lb/>whether like.this or like.that happy.is who that-his.sons males <lb/>&apos;Anyway, happy is the man whose children are male.&apos; <lb/>(Pinchas Eliyahu Horowitz 1797) <lb/>Since the preceding text discusses methods to ensure the birth of a male child the <lb/>misogynistic assertion in (34) is a digression from the previous topic and is so marked <lb/>by the discourse marker. Note that in this case, argumentative strengthening applies <lb/>to the discourse status of the modified assertion: Its centrality to the discourse is <lb/>raised, rather than the validity of its propositional content. <lb/>For the sake of completeness, we cite here a not much later Revival period <lb/>example where this &apos;anyway&apos; function has a compact variant (this time with ko &apos;thus&apos;): <lb/>(35) <lb/>Le-zot <lb/>tšuvatxa <lb/>acape <lb/>ve-hineni bein ko <lb/>to-this <lb/>your.answer I.look.forward.to and-I.am anyway <lb/>yedidxa <lb/>beemet <lb/>your.friend truly <lb/>&apos;I shall look forward to your answer and I am your true friend anyway.&apos; <lb/>(Moshe Leib Lilienblum 1876) <lb/>While we cannot know how this compact construction was pronounced then, we do <lb/>know that in Contemporary Hebrew bein ko/kax constitutes a single phonological <lb/>word, which is only appropriate for a grammaticized discourse marker. <lb/>4.2 Simple bein construction evolutions <lb/>The main focus of our article is bein evolutions for the complex (double ground) <lb/>constructions. We therefore only briefly discuss two new functions that evolved in <lb/>Diaspora Hebrew for the simple [bein NPs] construction. Six bein NPs tokens show an <lb/>interesting metaphorical extension of the original locative function. For comparison <lb/>purposes, we here repeat the classical locative case cited as (1a): <lb/>(36) <lb/>Hi mithalexet <lb/>bein <lb/>ha-Xayot <lb/>she is.moving.to.and.fro among the-living.creatures <lb/>&apos;She walks among the living creatures&apos; <lb/>(Ezekiel 1: 13) <lb/>In such cases, the point of the utterance is to assert that the figure (&apos;it&apos;) is physically <lb/>located somewhere among the ground entities (&apos;the living creatures&apos;). In the <lb/>following example, a disease is asserted to metaphorically exist among the ground <lb/>entities: <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1327 <lb/></page>

        <body>(37) <lb/>Zot <lb/>ha-maxala ha-nora&apos;a <lb/>mecuya bein <lb/>this.F the-disease the-terrible is <lb/>among <lb/>bnei <lb/>ha-kfarim <lb/>sons <lb/>the-village <lb/>&apos;This terrible disease is prevalent among the villagers&apos; <lb/>(Menachem Mendel Lapin 1794) <lb/>Note, however, that just like in the English use of among here, the disease doesn&apos;t exist <lb/>in some metaphorical space between the set of villagers, but rather, within each <lb/>villager. In other words, each entity of the ground constitutes an independent ground <lb/>within which an instance of the figure (disease) metaphorically exists. We call this the <lb/>generic function because the ground must be construed as a relevant general category <lb/>with multiple individual members (here, &apos;villagers&apos;), and the predicate then asserts <lb/>that some typical property (here, &apos;having the terrible disease&apos;) is true of the members. <lb/>Although syntactically part of the VP, the bein ground in these cases is topical. <lb/>Note that while the argumentative point in the generic use concerns the whole <lb/>category, realistically, interlocutors do not assume that the property applies to each <lb/>member. More likely, the property is true only of a (representative) subset of the <lb/>category (&apos;a subset of the villagers&apos;). This reasonable inference must have paved the <lb/>way for the next, &apos;subset&apos; function of bein: <lb/>(38) <lb/>Ve-hayu <lb/>bein <lb/>ha-baim <lb/>axareihem be-xol <lb/>and-there.were among the-coming after.them in-every <lb/>dor <lb/>va-dor <lb/>yexidei <lb/>sgula <lb/>yodei <lb/>generation and-generation unique(people).of quality knowers.of <lb/>bina. <lb/>wisdom <lb/>&apos;And there were among the [people] following them in each generation wise <lb/>outstanding [people].&apos; <lb/>&apos;Some of the people in each of the following generations were outstanding <lb/>and wise.&apos; <lb/>(Mordechai Gumpel Schnaber Levison 1771) <lb/>Unlike the locative and the generic uses, where the existence of the figure (&apos;the <lb/>villagers&apos;) is presupposed, the distinct existence of the figure in the subset use (the <lb/>outstanding, wise people) is not presupposed. It is carved out by the bein construc-<lb/>tion. It is the point of the utterance to assert the existence of the figure, which is at the <lb/>outset not distinguishable from the members of the category introduced by the <lb/>ground (people of later generations). The ground is here partitioned by bein for a <lb/>subset of it to become the figure. The predication then applies to the figure alone. The <lb/>following subset example is noteworthy because a descendent of it (exemplification) <lb/>will become quite frequent in Contemporary Hebrew: <lb/></body>

        <page>1328 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>(39) <lb/>Laʕavod eclo <lb/>bein <lb/>šɁar cva <lb/>milxamto <lb/>To.work for.him among rest army his.war <lb/>&apos;To work for him among the rest of his war soldiers&apos; <lb/>(Baruch Linde 1788) <lb/>What is special about this collocative example (bein šɁar &apos;among the rest.of&apos;) is that <lb/>the figure is not only introduced as a subset of some whole. It is at the same time also <lb/>construed as one among multiple subsets of that whole. <lb/>In other words, in the classical locative case, the (specifically locative) predica-<lb/>tion is about the figure. In the generic use, the figure, a property, is predicated as <lb/>typical of the ground, the category as a whole. In the subset use some property (not <lb/>necessarily a typical one) is predicated on a delineated subset of the category, defined <lb/>as a figure by the construction. <lb/>5 Revival Hebrew: bein introducing a &apos;range&apos; and <lb/>an all-purpose preposition <lb/>Revival Hebrew covers a relatively short period (1881-1947). The random sample of <lb/>100 bein examples we coded were extracted from &quot;Ma&apos;agarim&quot; (see Note 18). Once <lb/>again, our discussion ignores the many functions already noted for the earlier <lb/>periods, which are still attested here, and focuses on two new functions. Both are <lb/>further developments of two innovative Diaspora functions. <lb/>Consider the following example. <lb/>(40) <lb/>Ha-xom <lb/>ha-acmi šel <lb/>ha-adam <lb/>hu <lb/>munax <lb/>the-fever the-self <lb/>of <lb/>the-person is <lb/>lie <lb/>tamid <lb/>bein <lb/>36-38 maalot <lb/>celsyus <lb/>always <lb/>between 36-38 degrees <lb/>Celsius <lb/>&apos;A person&apos;s fever always lies between 36-38 degrees Celsius&apos; <lb/>(Aharon Foryes 1876) <lb/>This Range function must have evolved from indifference-disjunctive adverbials <lb/>such as the following Mishnaic example, a more compact, grammaticized variant of <lb/>the Mishnaic (41): <lb/>(41) <lb/>Ziporet kramim <lb/>bein <lb/>xaya bein <lb/>meta kolšehi… <lb/>Tziporet Cramim whether alive whether dead whatever… <lb/>&apos;Tziporet Cramim (a specific bird), whether alive or dead, whatever…&apos; <lb/>(Shabbat 9: 7) <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1329 <lb/></page>

        <body>We can interpret &apos;live or dead&apos; as exhausting all (=two) alternatives. However, we can <lb/>also interpret it as pointing to a higher-level category, including any living status <lb/>(e.g., &apos;sick birds&apos; -see again Section 4.1.1). This is supported by the following &apos;what-<lb/>ever (state)&apos;. But since the two alternatives here are also endpoint values on a salient <lb/>scale, bein X (u-) v/bein Y may be construed as any value on the range. <lb/>Next, recall the generic use exemplified in (41), where the speaker predicated a <lb/>property on each member of a relevant category. Revival Hebrew (42) first shows <lb/>that the category need not be generic (the relevant ground is quite specific here, <lb/>&apos;people about whom some rabbi said something&apos;). More importantly, it seems that <lb/>bein, is used here as a general associative preposition. Whereas in (40) an extended <lb/>metaphorical location is involved, in (42) bein is contextually adjusted to convey &apos;by&apos; <lb/>(in other examples it is interpreted as &apos;according to&apos;, &apos;of&apos; or &apos;for&apos;): <lb/>(42) <lb/>Ve-divreixem <lb/>yihiyu <lb/>muvanim <lb/>ve-nikraim <lb/>and-your.words <lb/>will.be <lb/>understood <lb/>and-readable <lb/>rak <lb/>bein <lb/>mikcat <lb/>anašim <lb/>only <lb/>among <lb/>a.few <lb/>people <lb/>&apos;And your words shall be understood and read only by some people&apos; (Shalom <lb/>Yakov Avramovic 1867) <lb/>In these cases, bein functions as a general associator between some property and the <lb/>referent of its NP complement, but note that this NP must introduce multiple <lb/>individuals that form a specific set. The all-purpose preposition bein is then restricted <lb/>to a specific [bein NPs] construction. <lb/>6 Contemporary Hebrew: marked disjunctives, <lb/>higher-level category, subset and <lb/>exemplification <lb/>We extracted 200 random examples from the heTenTen corpus via Sketch Engine. 24 <lb/>Thirteen noncontemporary examples were removed, so we were left with 187 tokens. <lb/>Once again, we here focus only on notable differences from previous periods. 6.1 <lb/>addresses complex constructions, 6.2 addresses simple constructions. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">24 heTenTen is a big-data internet-based corpus: https://www.sketchengine.eu/hetenten-hebrew-<lb/>corpus/. <lb/></note>

        <page>1330 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>6.1 From disjunctive to conjunctive bein constructions <lb/>A striking fact about Contemporary Hebrew bein is the paucity of disjunctive uses. <lb/>free-alternative, which was always extremely rare, is not attested at all, and the <lb/>indifference-disjunctive adverbial is now quite rare too (9, 4.8 %), and practically <lb/>limited to sentential (rather than phrasal) alternatives. We propose that the decrease <lb/>in adverbial indifference-disjunctive use (ever since the 15th century, in fact) is <lb/>mostly due to genre change -only Mishnaic Hebrew is rule oriented and needs to <lb/>clarify the circumstances under which rules apply. But an additional factor is the <lb/>gradual, partial, and later total replacement of the original bein X u-vein Y con-<lb/>struction by alternative forms. These were motivated by both compactization and <lb/>reanalysis. For example, while 79.2 % of Biblical complex constructions contained a <lb/>reduplicate bein token, only 21.3 % currently do. The many cases where the second <lb/>connective was replaced by o &apos;or&apos; testify to a reanalysis of some of the complex bein <lb/>constructions as (specialized) disjunctive constructions, and these served as impetus <lb/>for a wholesale replacement of the original indifference-disjunctive adverbial. The <lb/>same is true for other substitutions of the second bein: ve &apos;and&apos;, le &apos;to&apos;, a hyphen, and a <lb/>few other prepositions. <lb/>No wonder we can identify a typical discourse profile for the adverbial indif-<lb/>ference-disjunctive construction. First, in all cases, at least one of the alternatives is <lb/>prefaced by im &apos;if&apos; in addition to bein &apos;whether&apos; (9/9). Second, 3/9 involve a specific <lb/>collocation, bein im medubar, literally &apos;whether if spoken&apos;, &apos;whether we&apos;re talking <lb/>about&apos;. Indeed, an additional search for 100 random bein im strings (98 cases here <lb/>included) revealed that medubar is part of the construction in 25 of these, more than a <lb/>quarter. Third, as attested for English (Ariel 2016), in as many as 16.3 % the subse-<lb/>quent alternative is an elliptical im lo/lav &apos;if/or not&apos;. Finally, and most crucially, more <lb/>than a third (34.7 %) introduce the conventional o &apos;or&apos; instead of or in addition to the <lb/>second bein. <lb/>Interestingly, the decrease in disjunctive constructions is accompanied by a rise <lb/>in innovative conjunctive uses. Now, we have seen above that certain conjunctive <lb/>bein constructions were reinterpreted as disjunctive (see Section 3). However, the <lb/>shift between conjunctive and disjunctive constructions is not unidirectional, which <lb/>is why a disjunctive construction can also become conjunctive. Of course, such shifts <lb/>are restricted to cases where the listed items can simultaneously be construed as <lb/>both additive and alternative to each other. Lists are just that. Five examples (2.7 %) <lb/>show a list reading: 25 <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">25 Two additional tokens show no second marker at all. <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1331 <lb/></page>

        <body>(43) <lb/>Bein <lb/>im <lb/>ze <lb/>be-pgišot <lb/>rišonot, nihul <lb/>whether if <lb/>this <lb/>in-meetings initial <lb/>management.of <lb/>tikim <lb/>ve-af <lb/>lesoxeax im <lb/>lakoax <lb/>files <lb/>and-even talk <lb/>with <lb/>client <lb/>&apos;Whether it is initial meetings, file management and even talking to a client&apos; <lb/>(Example 53) <lb/>Next, once some additive or alternative list is interpreted as non-exhaustive, we may <lb/>end up with one of two close readings. A non-exhaustive set of items may give rise to a <lb/>higher-level-category (HLC) disjunctive reading, where an ad hoc abstract category is <lb/>constructed, based on the explicit alternatives (see Ariel and Mauri (2018) and Section <lb/>4.1.1). Here&apos;s such an HLC example, which, unlike 1(d), is not a kax &apos;thus&apos; collocation: <lb/>(44) <lb/>Bein <lb/>im medubar be-dira <lb/>ironit, be-kotej <lb/>kafri, <lb/>whether if <lb/>talk <lb/>of-apartment city <lb/>of-cottage rural <lb/>be-ohel <lb/>o <lb/>be-yaxta. Be-xol <lb/>xalal <lb/>megurim <lb/>of-tent <lb/>or <lb/>of-yacht. in-any <lb/>space <lb/>living <lb/>&apos;Whether we are talking about a city apartment, a rural cottage, a tent or a <lb/>yacht. In any living space.&apos; <lb/>(https://www.haaretz.co.il/literature/2006-05-08/ty-article/0000017f-<lb/>eff9-dc28-a17f-ffffb7ad0000) <lb/>That an HLC reading is here intended is supported by the added assertion, which <lb/>spells out the HLC, &apos;any living space&apos;. Such uses are typical of constructions intro-<lb/>ducing more than two alternatives. The next example specifies the HLC in the <lb/>beginning, but then goes on to introduce an explicitly marked non-exhaustive list of <lb/>potential examples of this general category (note the final &apos;etcetera&apos;): <lb/>(45) <lb/>Le-xol <lb/>mucar <lb/>xašmali bein <lb/>im <lb/>medub <lb/>to-every <lb/>product <lb/>electrical whether if <lb/>talking <lb/>be-mexonit, ofanayim-xašmalyim blender <lb/>radio <lb/>ve-xadome <lb/>in-car, <lb/>bicycle-electric <lb/>blender radio <lb/>and-like.similar <lb/>&apos;Every electrical product, whether we are talking about a car, an electric <lb/>bicycle, a blender, a radio, etc.&apos; <lb/>(Example 150) <lb/>Barotto (2021) proposes that non-exhaustive HLC readings within an irrealis context <lb/>constitute exemplification cases. Indeed, it seems that bein im (medubar) &apos;whether if <lb/>(we&apos;re talking&apos;) strings, which are marked irrealis multiple times, are currently <lb/>specializing as exemplification constructions. <lb/>While not conjunctive, we note that the Range function, previously introduced <lb/>but rarely used, has become quite prevalent (21, 11.2 %). The complex construction <lb/></body>

        <page>1332 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>here uses &apos;to&apos; rather than &apos;and&apos; ([bein X le-Y] &apos;between X to Y&apos;). Even more interest-<lb/>ingly, a related function, not found in our random sample, is worth mentioning too: <lb/>&apos;Intermediate value on a range&apos;, as in: <lb/>(46) <lb/>Bein <lb/>ha-dimyoni <lb/>la-mamaši. <lb/>between <lb/>the-imaginary <lb/>to.the-real <lb/>&apos;In-between the imaginary and the real.&apos; [https://www.eol.co.il/articles/1420] <lb/>The referent here (a dream) does not refer to the whole range, nor to just any value <lb/>on it, but rather, to some unspecified intermediate value on the range, possibly <lb/>combining features from both. <lb/>6.2 Simple bein constructions <lb/>Another function showing an increase (24, 12.8 %) is the subset function. Intriguingly, <lb/>it too has evolved an exemplification sub-construction, out of a collocation initially <lb/>found in Diaspora Hebrew, where the figure is construed as one subset among <lb/>multiple subsets of the whole (see again (39)). Since the nonanaphoric &apos;the rest&apos; in bein <lb/>ha-yeter &apos;among(the)-other (things)&apos; highlights the existence of additional examples <lb/>left implicit, such cases need not even list multiple examples: <lb/>(47) <lb/>Be-kama mekomot <lb/>bodedim ba-arec. <lb/>Bein <lb/>in-several places <lb/>isolated in.the.country. among <lb/>ha-yeter ba-šxuna <lb/>be-yavne <lb/>the-rest <lb/>in.the.neighborhood in-Yavne <lb/>&apos;In several isolated places in the country. Among other (places) in a <lb/>neighborhood in Yavne.&apos; <lb/>(Example 77) <lb/>The exemplification use marks a split of the subset function into two rather different <lb/>functions. The majority (15/24) involves what we&apos;re calling the exemplification bein ha-<lb/>yeter/bein ha-shɁar &apos;among other things&apos; sub-construction, as in (47). The general <lb/>subset construction mostly serves to assert category membership for some entity -a <lb/>hybrid between the generic (37) and the subset (39) functions from Diaspora Hebrew: <lb/>(48) <lb/>Nivxar <lb/>Doli-City bein <lb/>aseret ha-sfarim ha-tovim <lb/>was.chosen Doly-City among ten.of the-books the-good <lb/>beyoter <lb/>most <lb/>&apos;Doly-City&apos; was chosen among the ten best books&apos; <lb/>[https://simania.co.il/bookdetails.php?item_id=2223] <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1333 <lb/></page>

        <body>Within NPmass (Locative PP) <lb/>Bein ha-srefa &apos;within the burnt.stuff&apos; ( §2.1) <lb/>Among NPs (Locative PP) <lb/>Bein ha-Xayot &apos;among the living creatures&apos; (1a) <lb/>Between NPsdual (Locative PP) <lb/>Bein ʕenexem &apos;between your eyes&apos; (2) <lb/>Among NPscategory (nonlocative PP) <lb/>Bein bnei ha-kfarim &apos;Among the <lb/>villagers&apos; (28) <lb/>Between NP1 and NP2 <lb/>(Locative conjunctive PP) <lb/>Bein bet el u-vein ha-ʕai &apos;between Bethel and Ai&apos; (1b) <lb/>Among/Part of Nps (NPcategory) <lb/>Bein ha-baim aXrehem &apos;Among/part <lb/>of those who came after them&apos; (29) <lb/>Between NP1 and NP2 ((Implicit) symmetric relation <lb/>in a conjunctive adjunct or argument PP) <lb/>Bein ha-or u-vein ha-Xoshex &apos;between light and <lb/>darkness&apos;(6a); <lb/>Bein av le-vito &apos;between father and daughter&apos; ( §2.2) <lb/>Among other <lb/>things, for <lb/>example S <lb/>Bein ha-yeter ba-<lb/>šxuna… &apos;For <lb/>example, in the <lb/>neighborhood <lb/>of…&apos; (38) <lb/>General <lb/>associator <lb/>Bein mi.kcat <lb/>anašim še… &apos;by <lb/>some of the <lb/>people that…&apos; <lb/>(33) <lb/>Be it NP1 and be it NP2 (Free Alternative: (nonlocative <lb/>PP) Conditional conjunctive/disjunctive adjunct or <lb/>argument) <lb/>bein tov u-vein raʕ &apos;be it good, be it bad&apos; (4) <lb/>Whether X1 or X2, S (Indifference disjunctive sentence <lb/>adverbial) <lb/>Bein min ha-yorshim u-vein še-eino min ha-yorshim <lb/>&apos;whether a successor or not&apos; (6c); <lb/>Bein…srak… o pri &apos;whether barren or fruit-bearing&apos; (20) <lb/>Whether X1 or X2, S (Higher-level category) <lb/>Bein im (medubar be-) X u-vein im/o Y <lb/>Whether it&apos;s a city apartment… or a yacht (35) <lb/>Whether X or Y, <lb/>for example, S <lb/>Bein im medubar bi-<lb/>mxonit… radyo <lb/>ve-xadome &apos;whether <lb/>we&apos;re talking about a <lb/>car… etc.&apos; (36) <lb/>In any case, S (Free Choice <lb/>sentence Adv. within a lexicalized <lb/>sub-construction) <lb/>Bein kax u-vein/ ve/o kax/ko &apos;in <lb/>any case&apos; <lb/>Bein kax o kax, haya raɁuy &apos;In any <lb/>case, it would have been right&apos; (24) <lb/>Bein ko ekashel <lb/>&apos;I will fail no matter what&apos; (1e) <lb/>Anyway, Ut. (Discourse marker; <lb/>within a sub-construction) <lb/>Bein kax o kax, ašrei mi… <lb/>&apos;Anyway, happy is whoever…&apos; (25) <lb/>Hineni bein ko yedidxa. <lb/>&apos;Anyway, I&apos;m your friend&apos; (26) <lb/>Figure 1: The grammaticization clines of bein &apos;between&apos;. <lb/></body>

        <page>1334 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>Summing up, Contemporary Hebrew mostly reflects a fall in disjunctive complex <lb/>bein constructions in favor of conjunctive functions: list and exemplification. The <lb/>simple construction has also come to be used for exemplification, but it can now also <lb/>serve to assert category membership for specific (rather than generic) entities. See <lb/>Figure 1 for the complete grammaticization clines of Hebrew bein &apos;between&apos;. <lb/>7 Conclusions <lb/>Sections 2-6 provided a detailed description of the evolution of Hebrew bein, from its <lb/>early Biblical use as a preposition meaning &apos;within/among&apos;, up to current Hebrew, where <lb/>it is (among many other things) part of a lexicalized sentence adverbial. The following <lb/>schema summarizes the main phases that the bein constructions went through. The first <lb/>line for each phase specifies the meaning of bein (in large bold English font), followed by <lb/>the complement type it takes. The syntactic/semantic role of the construction is then <lb/>listed in parentheses. The subsequent lines exemplify the specific construction, marking <lb/>in bold the relevant constructional components in the transcription, followed by a free <lb/>gloss. Where more than one constructional variant is attested, two examples are pro-<lb/>vided. If originally cited in the article, we refer to the original citation in parentheses: <lb/>Generalizing over the changes we have analyzed, we see a gradual rise in more <lb/>complex meanings: from location (physical, concrete) to symmetric relation (abstract), <lb/>to Alternativity and to exemplification (the latter two being procedural meanings). We <lb/>have also documented a rise in complex structures: PP to P (conjoined NPs), to <lb/>conjunctive disjunction. For syntactic integration, we have seen shifts for more inte-<lb/>gration (VP-governed adjunct, locative adverb to verbal argument), as well as towards <lb/>less integration (VP-governed adjunct to ungoverned correlative adverbial and to <lb/>discourse marker). We have seen a shift towards opaqueness (due to compactization), <lb/>but also towards transparency (when e.g., the second bein was replaced by o &apos;or&apos; in <lb/>disjunctive constructions). We have observed a shift from a mostly conjunctive con-<lb/>struction to a mostly disjunctive one (to indifference-disjunctive adverbial), but then, <lb/>also back to a more conjunctive one (exemplification). <lb/>For the most part, Hebrew tended to add on bein functions and constructions on <lb/>top of the old ones, which is in the spirit of Hopper&apos;s (1991) Layering proposal. This is <lb/>why most of the functions analyzed for all periods preceding Contemporary Hebrew <lb/>are still currently attested. Occasionally, however, some functions (&apos;among NP mass &apos;, <lb/>free-alternative) or forms (bein she &apos;whether that&apos;) have disappeared. The frequency <lb/>of various functions naturally varies between the different periods but is at least <lb/>partly due to genre differences. We suspect that the dominance of legal rulings is <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1335 <lb/></page>

        <body>responsible for the exceptionally frequent use of indifference-disjunctive adverbials <lb/>in Mishnaic Hebrew. 26 <lb/>The analysis we offered for the diachronic evolution of Hebrew bein considered <lb/>each of its many particular constructional functions, thus demonstrating how small <lb/>interpretative and formal changes can account for how speakers must have shifted <lb/>from one function to another. But we would now like to draw attention to more <lb/>abstract and global trends, which apply to multiple functions but are at least partly <lb/>orthogonal to these functions. First, as already mentioned, once the adverbial <lb/>indifference construction was mobilized for discourse argumentative strengthening <lb/>(in Mishnaic Hebrew), first as an anti-narrowing device, all its descendants, non-<lb/>disjunctive ones included, carry this discourse function too, in line with Barden-<lb/>stein&apos;s Persistence Principle (2021). <lb/>A second global change responsible for the multiple functions we observed relates <lb/>to the entity focused on by bein. In principle, bein constructions may profile (i) pre-<lb/>dominantly the interval between the complement reference points (locative, temporal, <lb/>range), (ii) predominantly the reference points themselves (indifference-disjunctive <lb/>adverbial, subset, exemplification), or (iii) both the reference points and the interval <lb/>(relation, separation). Biblical Hebrew is more or less equally divided between interval <lb/>(52.2 %) (i) and the double interval + reference points foci (46.6 %) (iii), but hardly has <lb/>any reference points foci (1.2 %) (ii). Contemporary Hebrew, on the other hand, has <lb/>many less interval foci (22.5 %) (i), many more reference-points focus (19.8 %) (iii), but <lb/>mostly demonstrates the double foci (ii). It is important to note these different potential <lb/>foci, for they provide the basis for the different functions we analyzed above. Each <lb/>function is associated with its focus. We propose that it is the potential for three distinct <lb/>foci for the bein complement that made the rich variety of functions possible. The <lb/>individual functions can then be distinguished from one another, at least partially, by <lb/>reference to the nature of the reference points, the syntactic status of the construction, <lb/>the nature of the relevant verb, as well as additional constructional and sub-<lb/>constructional features (e.g., double bein versus single bein etc.). <lb/>We end with possible implications for future research. Note that most, if not all, of <lb/>the radically different functions we identified for Hebrew bein and its descendants are <lb/>present in other languages (as witnessed by the free translations of the examples <lb/>above). It would be interesting to look for parallel etymological relations and gram-<lb/>maticizations in other languages. While we noted some parallel developments for the <lb/>simple Hebrew bein NP construction and English among, we suspect that the functions <lb/>encoded by the complex bein constructions are typically not expressed by etymologi-<lb/>cally related lexemes in other languages. We propose that it&apos;s bein&apos;s participation in so <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">26 Indeed, Kuperschmidt (2021) found that the book of Leviticus, which presents Jewish halacha <lb/>(law) abounds with (nonadverbial) or constructions, as compared with the rest of the Old Testament. <lb/></note>

        <page>1336 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel <lb/></note>

        <body>many different Goldbergian constructions that accounts for the rather surprising di-<lb/>versity of diachronic changes it underwent (see again Figure 1). Indeed, we&apos;re not the <lb/>first to underscore the crucial role of specific constructions in language change <lb/>(Traugott and Trousdale 2013). Next, we only briefly touched on the functional moti-<lb/>vations behind (duplicate) correlative constructions, but these intriguing evolutions <lb/>deserve much more empirical and theoretical work. Lastly, we offered a potential <lb/>connection between conjunctive and disjunctive constructions (beyond the fact that <lb/>both are syntactically symmetric). We proposed that conjunctive constructions within <lb/>irrealis contexts may be compatible with an inferred &apos;alternativity&apos; relation between <lb/>the conjuncts and thus lead to a disjunctive construction, and at the same time that <lb/>disjunctive constructions used for exemplification may lead to reanalysis as conjunctive <lb/>constructions. Future research should explore how prevalent such shifts are. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments: The research here reported was supported by grant 1398/20 <lb/>from the Israel Science Foundation awarded to Mira Ariel. We thank Tal Siloni and <lb/>Aya Meltzer-Asscher for their help with the syntactic analyses. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability statement: The data underlying this article are available in the <lb/>Zenodo repository: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10575239. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Ariel, Mira. 2016. Indifference adverbial X or Y. In Alex Reuneker, Ronny Boogaart &amp; Saskia Lensink (eds.), <lb/>Aries netwerk een constructicon, 11-15. Leiden: University of Leiden. <lb/>Ariel, Mira. 2018. Evolving or constructions: In and out of &apos;alternativity&apos;. In Paper presented to the formal <lb/>semantics and grammaticization group. Jerusalem: Hebrew University. <lb/>Ariel, Mira &amp; Caterina Mauri. 2018. Why use or? Linguistics 56. 939-994. <lb/>Ariel, Mira &amp; Caterina Mauri. 2019. An &apos;alternative&apos; core for or. Journal of Pragmatics 149. 40-59. <lb/>Bardenstein, Ruti. 2016. The Hebrew adverbial bixlal. Entrepalavras 6. 10-28. <lb/>Bardenstein, Ruti. 2021. Persistent argumentative discourse markers: The case of Hebrew rectification-<lb/>marker be-ʕecem (&apos;actually&apos;). Journal of Pragmatics 172. 254-269. <lb/>Barotto, Alessandra. 2021. Exemplification and categorization: The case of Japanese. Berlin &amp; Boston: De <lb/>Gruyter Mouton. <lb/>Ben Jehuda, Eliezer. 1908-1959. A complete dictionary of ancient and Modern Hebrew. Jerusalem &amp; Berlin: <lb/>Langenscheidtsche Verlagsbuchandlung. <lb/>Brown, Francis, Samuel Rolles Driver &amp; Charles Augustus Briggs. 1907. A Hebrew and English lexicon of the <lb/>old testament. Oxford: Clarendon Press. <lb/>Bybee, Joan. 2003. Mechanisms of change in grammaticization: The role of repetition. In Richard Janda &amp; <lb/>Brian Joseph (eds.), Handbook of historical linguistics, 602-623. Oxford: Blackwell. <lb/>Carston, Robyn. 2002. Thoughts and utterances: The pragmatics of explicit communication. Oxford: Blackwell. <lb/>Chatzikyriakidis, Stregios &amp; Giorgos Spathas. 2015. Bisyndetic distributive conjunction and additive ke <lb/>under a diachronic perspective. In Paper presented at the 36th annual meeting of the Department of <lb/>Linguistics, 24-25 April. Thessaloniki: AMGL36. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Evolution of Hebrew bein constructions <lb/></note>

        <page>1337 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Davidson, Kathryn. 2013. &apos;And&apos; or &apos;or&apos;: General use coordination in ASL. Semantics &amp; Pragmatics 6. 1-44. <lb/>Du Bois, John, Wallace Chafe, Charles Meyer, Sandra Thompson, Robert Englebretson &amp; Nii Martey. 2000-<lb/>2005. Santa Barbara corpus of spoken American English, parts 1-4. Philadelphia: Linguistic Data <lb/>Consortium. <lb/>Even Shoshan, Avraham. 1982. The new dictionary (Hebrew). Jerusalem: Kiryat Sefer. <lb/>Evans, Nicholas &amp; David Wilkins. 2000. In the mind&apos;s ear: The semantic extensions of perception verbs in <lb/>Australian languages. Language 76. 546-592. <lb/>Gries, Stefan Th. 2022. What do (most of) our dispersion measures measure (most)? Dispersion? Journal of <lb/>Second Language Studies 5. 1-33. <lb/>Himmelmann, Nikolaus. 2004. Lexicalization and grammaticalization: Opposite or orthogonal? In <lb/>Walter Bisang, Nikolaus Himmelmann &amp; Bjorn Wiemer (eds.), What makes grammaticalization? A look <lb/>from its fringes and its components, 21-44. Berlin &amp; New York: Mouton de Gruyter. <lb/>Hopper, Paul. 1991. On some principles of grammaticization. In Elizabeth Closs Traugott &amp; Bernd Heine <lb/>(eds.), Approaches to grammaticalization, 17-35. Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John Benjamins. <lb/>Hopper, Paul &amp; Elizabeth Closs Traugott. 2003 [1993]. Grammaticalization. Cambridge: Cambridge <lb/>University Press. <lb/>Kamp, Hans. 1973. Free choice permission. Proceedings of the Aristotelian Society 74. 57-74. <lb/>Kuperschmidt, Itai. 2021. The relation of alternativity in Biblical Hebrew: A syntactic, semantic and pragmatic <lb/>study. Tel Aviv: Tel Aviv University Dissertation. <lb/>Mauri, Caterina. 2008. The irreality of alternatives: Towards a typology of disjunction. Studies in Language <lb/>32. 22-55. <lb/>Mittwoch, Anita, Rodney Huddleston &amp; Peter Collins. 2002. In Rodney Huddleston &amp; Geoffrey Pullum <lb/>(eds.), The clause: Adjuncts. The Cambridge grammar of the English language, 663-784. Cambridge: <lb/>Cambridge University Press. <lb/>Talmy, Leonard. 1972. The basis for a crosslinguistic typology of motion/location. Working Papers on <lb/>Language Universals 9. 41-116. <lb/>Todaka, Yuichi. 1996. Between and among: A data-based analysis. Word 47(1). 13-40. <lb/>Traugott, Elizabeth Closs. 2008. Grammaticalization, constructions and the incremental development of <lb/>language: Suggestions from the development of degree modifiers in English. In Regine Eckardt, <lb/>Gerhard Jaeger &amp; Tonjes Veenstra (eds.), Variation, selection, development: Probing the evolutionary <lb/>model of language change, 219-250. Berlin &amp; New York: Mouton de Gruyter. <lb/>Traugott, Elizabeth Closs &amp; Richard Dasher. 2002. Regularity in semantic change. Cambridge: Cambridge <lb/>University Press. <lb/>Traugott, Elizabeth Closs &amp; Graeme Trousdale. 2013. Constructionalization and constructional changes. <lb/>Oxford: Oxford University Press. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>1338 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Bardenstein and Ariel </note>


	</text>

</TEI>