<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Broad transcriptional dysregulation of brain and choroid plexus cell types with COVID-19 <lb/>Andrew C. Yang 1,2,3,# , Fabian Kern 4,# , Patricia M. Losada 3 , Christina A. Maat 3 , Georges Schmartz 4 , <lb/>Tobias Fehlmann 4 , Nicholas Schaum 3 , Davis P. Lee 3 , Kruti Calcuttawala 3 , Ryan T. Vest 3 , David Gate 3 , <lb/>Daniela Berdnik 3 , M. Windy McNerney 5 , Divya Channappa 3 , Inma Cobos 3,6 , Nicole Ludwig 7 , <lb/>Walter J. Schulz-Schaeffer 8 , Andreas Keller 3,4,* , Tony Wyss-Coray 2,3,9,10,* <lb/>1 Department of Bioengineering, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, California, USA. <lb/>2 ChEM-H, Stanford University, Stanford, California, USA. <lb/>3 Department of Neurology and Neurological Sciences, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, California, USA. <lb/>4 Chair for Clinical Bioinformatics, Saarland University, 66123 Saarbrucken, SL, Germany. <lb/>5 Department of Psychiatry, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, California, USA. <lb/>6 Department of Pathology, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, California, USA. <lb/>7 Department of Human Genetics, Saarland University, 66421 Homburg/Saar, Germany. <lb/>8 Institute for Neuropathology, Saarland University Hospital and Medical Faculty of Saarland University. <lb/>9 Wu Tsai Neurosciences Institute, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA. <lb/>10 Paul F. Glenn Center for the Biology of Aging, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, California, USA. <lb/># These authors contributed equally <lb/>* Correspondence to andreas.keller@ccb.uni-saarland.de or twc@stanford.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Though SARS-CoV-2 primarily targets the respiratory system, it is increasingly <lb/>appreciated that patients may suffer neurological symptoms of varied severity 1-3 . However, an <lb/>unbiased understanding of the molecular processes across brain cell types that could contribute <lb/>to these symptoms in COVID-19 patients is still missing. Here, we profile 47,678 droplet-based <lb/>single-nucleus transcriptomes from the frontal cortex and choroid plexus across 10 non-viral, 4 <lb/>COVID-19, and 1 influenza patient. We complement transcriptomic data with <lb/>immunohistochemical staining for the presence of SARS-CoV-2. We find that all major cortex <lb/>parenchymal and choroid plexus cell types are affected transcriptionally with COVID-19. This <lb/>arises, in part, from SARS-CoV-2 infection of the cortical brain vasculature, meninges, and <lb/>choroid plexus, stimulating increased inflammatory signaling into the brain. In parallel, <lb/>peripheral immune cells infiltrate the brain, microglia activate programs mediating the <lb/>phagocytosis of live neurons, and astrocytes dysregulate genes involved in neurotransmitter <lb/>homeostasis. Among neurons, layer 2/3 excitatory neurons-evolutionarily expanded in <lb/>humans 4 -show a specific downregulation of genes encoding major SNARE and synaptic <lb/>vesicle components, predicting compromised synaptic transmission. These perturbations are <lb/>not observed in terminal influenza. Many COVID-19 gene expression changes are shared with <lb/>those in chronic brain disorders and reside in genetic variants associated with cognitive <lb/>function, schizophrenia, and depression. Our findings and public dataset provide a molecular <lb/>framework and new opportunities to understand COVID-19 related neurological disease. <lb/></front>

			<body>Main Text <lb/>Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), the etiologic agent <lb/>of the COVID-19 global pandemic, has as of October 2020 infected over 40 million people and <lb/></body>

			<front>. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></front>

			<body>caused over a million deaths worldwide (worldometers.info/coronavirus). Though SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>primarily targets the respiratory system, it is increasingly appreciated that COVID-19 patients <lb/>can suffer neurological and psychiatric symptoms of varied severity, depending on SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>mechanisms as well as other variables, such as co-morbidities and clinical care 1-3,5 . Central <lb/>nervous system (CNS) symptoms range from loss of smell and headache to memory loss, <lb/>encephalitis, stroke, difficulty concentrating, and persistent fatigue 1,6-8 . Symptoms are especially <lb/>frequent and prominent in the over 20% of COVID-19 patients that require hospitalization 1,9-11 . <lb/>With lingering CNS symptoms documented in Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) and <lb/>Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS) survivors 1,12-14 , it remains to be seen whether such <lb/>chronic symptoms will emerge in COVID-19 survivors. <lb/>Cellular and molecular approaches are required to understand the neurological changes <lb/>that may contribute to symptoms reported in COVID-19 patients. Fundamentally, pathology can <lb/>arise from the direct infection of neurons and glia or indirectly from peripheral infection and its <lb/>attendant immune response 15,16 . Viral RNA has been detected in the olfactory mucosa and <lb/>cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) in some cases, but the consequences for brain cells remain unclear 17-<lb/>20 . Several reports using elegant in vitro culture systems, such as neuronal organoids, have <lb/>reached conflicting conclusions regarding the potential for SARS-CoV-2 neuroinvasion 21-26 . The <lb/>physiological relevance of such cultured systems, from the viral titers applied to their fidelity to <lb/>actual patient brains, also remains unclear 23,27,28 . Missing so far is an unbiased view of the <lb/>molecular and cellular perturbations across brain cell types in COVID-19 patients. This is in part <lb/>because high-quality human brain tissue from patients for such studies is largely <lb/>inaccessible 21,23,24 . Furthermore, several brain regions highly relevant to COVID-19, such as the <lb/>choroid plexus 23,24 , have not yet been successfully profiled in humans at single-cell resolution, in <lb/>health or disease 29 . <lb/>Here, we profile 47,678 droplet-based single-nucleus transcriptomes from the frontal <lb/>cortex and choroid plexus across 10 non-viral, 4 COVID-19, and 1 influenza patient (Fig. 1a). <lb/>We complement transcriptomic data with immunohistochemical staining for the presence of <lb/>SARS-CoV-2. These data-which includes the first, to our knowledge, single-cell view of <lb/>neurological changes in COVID-19 and of the human choroid plexus in general-provide a <lb/>molecular framework for how SARS-CoV-2 affects the brain without requiring direct <lb/>neuroinvasion; reveals the major pathways and cell types perturbed; and highlights associations <lb/>with chronic CNS diseases potentially pertinent to COVID-19 survivors. We created an <lb/>interactive data browser (https://twc-stanford.shinyapps.io/scRNA_Brain_COVID19), which will <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>be updated as more patient samples become available, to provide a resource for researchers to <lb/>further dissect the molecular mechanisms of SARS-CoV-2&apos;s impacts on the brain. <lb/>Cell type-specific gene expression changes in the COVID-19 brain <lb/>We aimed to gain insight into the cell type-specific transcriptomic effects of COVID-19 <lb/>on the brain by performing unbiased single-nucleus RNA sequencing (snRNA-seq) of 15 fresh-<lb/>frozen postmortem medial frontal cortex and lateral ventricle choroid plexus samples from 10 <lb/>non-viral, 4 COVID-19, and 1 influenza patient of similar clinical course as the COVID-19 <lb/>patients (Extended Data Table 1). Our sample sizes were similar to those reported in previous <lb/>snRNA-seq studies 30-32 . Samples in the control and COVID-19 groups were between 58 and 91 <lb/>years old and matched for tissue dissection area and RNA quality (Extended Data Fig. 1, <lb/>Extended Data Table 1). Cause of death for COVID-19 and influenza patients was consistently <lb/>interstitial pneumonia after more than two weeks of mechanical ventilation. Two COVID-19 <lb/>patients experienced objective neurological symptoms during care (Extended Data Table 1). <lb/>Samples were not confounded by technical or batch artifacts (Extended Data Fig. 2). <lb/>To begin, we generated 23,626 single-nuclei gene expression profiles from the medial <lb/>frontal cortex (4 non-viral, 4 COVID-19, 1 influenza)-and detected a median of 1,486 genes <lb/>per nucleus, a yield that is in line with recent snRNA-seq studies (Fig. 1b, Extended Data Fig. <lb/>1) 31-34 . We performed unbiased clustering of nuclear profiles to identify and annotate 8 cell <lb/>types, including subtypes of excitatory neurons and interneurons. Each annotated cell type <lb/>expressed previously established marker genes (Extended Data Fig. 3): excitatory neurons <lb/>(e.g., marked by CBLN2 and NRGN), inhibitory neurons (GAD1), astrocytes (AQP4), <lb/>oligodendrocytes (MBP and ST18), microglia (DOCK8), oligodendrocyte progenitor cells <lb/>(VCAN), maturing neurons (DACH1), and endothelial cells (LEPR)-though this latter <lb/>population also contains mixed markers for vascular mural pericytes and smooth muscle cells, <lb/>as in prior reports 32,34,35 . Overall, the cell type identities, markers, and proportions match prior <lb/>snRNA-seq data from adult human cortex (Extended data Fig. 1-4, Extended Data Table 2) 31-34 . <lb/>We compared levels of gene expression in cells isolated from COVID-19 versus non-<lb/>viral control individuals by cell type and identified 2,194 unique differentially expressed genes <lb/>(DEGs) that implicated all major cell types (Extended Data Table 3). As recently reported in <lb/>Alzheimer&apos;s disease (AD) 34 , neurons exhibited a strong signature of repression-73% of DEGs <lb/>in excitatory neurons and 65% in interneurons were downregulated-whereas DEGs in glial <lb/>oligodendrocytes, OPCs, astrocytes, and microglia were more balanced (36-51%, Fig. 1c-d). <lb/>The number of DEGs was greatest for astrocytes, excitatory neurons, and oligodendrocytes, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>partially reflecting increased power in these higher-abundance cell types. The vast majority of <lb/>DEGs were perturbed in only a single cell type (~84%, Fig. 1e-f, Extended Data Fig. 5a), further <lb/>indicating a cell type-specific CNS response to COVID-19. However, the minority of shared <lb/>DEGs clustered into meaningful pathways: for example, commonly downregulated DEGs <lb/>implicated impairments in brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) and interleukin-2 (IL-2) <lb/>signaling (Fig. 1f), both critical for homeostatic neuronal function 36-40 . Overall, these results <lb/>indicate that all major brain parenchymal cell types are affected at the transcriptional level by <lb/>COVID-19, and that single-cell-level resolution is critical because changes in gene expression-<lb/>including directionality-are dependent on cell type. <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 accumulation in barrier cells stimulates inflammatory signaling to the brain <lb/>The observed transcriptional response to COVID-19 in the brain could arise from direct <lb/>neurotropism or indirect damage via peripheral inflammation 15,16 . We thus stained for the SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 spike glycoprotein 20,41 in medial frontal cortex and choroid plexus tissue immediately <lb/>adjacent to tissue used in snRNA-seq. Intriguingly, we detected spike glycoprotein robustly in <lb/>two COVID-19 patients (Fig. 2). Upon closer examination however, spike glycoprotein signal <lb/>resided only within the barrier-forming cortical vasculature, meninges, and choroid plexus. <lb/>Within the choroid plexus, signal appeared within the stromal compartment, though confident <lb/>cell type assignment was not possible (Fig. 2c). Thus, unlike recent reports where SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>was added directly to neuroglial organoids lacking brain-barrier cells 21-25 , we do not observe <lb/>significant virus invasion in cortex parenchymal cells. On the other hand, SARS-CoV-2 infection <lb/>of the CSF-barrier forming choroid plexus and meninges corroborates recent in vitro, in silico, <lb/>CSF, and postmortem case studies suggesting CNS barrier cells can support productive <lb/>infection at relatively low titers 5,23,24,42,43 . We note however that this absence of detectable <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 neuroinvasion does not exclude its possibility. Likewise, it is possible that the <lb/>other two COVID-19 patients sustain SARS-CoV-2 barrier cell infection undetected in the tissue <lb/>sampled. Corroborating a recent study 5 , presence of SARS-CoV-2 in the CNS did not correlate <lb/>with neurological symptoms (Extended Data Table 1). Together, these results suggest that <lb/>brain-barrier cells may be particularly susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection, and that preferential <lb/>accumulation of virus in the barriers may give rise to widespread cortical DEGs. <lb/>Because we detected SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein in the blood-brain and blood-<lb/>CSF-barrier cells, we sought to devise methods to profile these cells and better understand their <lb/>relation to cortical transcriptional perturbations with COVID-19. However, conventional brain <lb/>snRNA-seq preparation methods nearly universally deplete high-quality brain vascular nuclei <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>from endothelial cells, pericytes, smooth muscle cells, and fibroblasts for currently unknown <lb/>reasons 32-35 . At the same time, no snRNA-seq study exists on the human choroid plexus, in <lb/>health or disease. This could, as we discovered, be because enzymatic and dounce <lb/>homogenization techniques successfully used to process mouse tissue 29 resulted in a near <lb/>complete loss of genes in isolated human choroid nuclei. We thus generated a method involving <lb/>successive gentle triturations in mild detergent (Methods), yielding 24,052 nuclei across 7 major <lb/>epithelial, mesenchymal, immune, and glial cell types (6 non-viral, 4 COVID-19, 1 influenza; Fig. <lb/>3a, Extended Data Fig. 4, Extended Data Table 4). <lb/>Epithelial cells accounted for 81% of choroid nuclei profiled, and interestingly, <lb/>subclustered based on expression of the receptor (PRLR) for prolactin-a hormone mediating <lb/>neurogenesis 44,45 -, the glutathione peroxidase GPX3-which protects the CSF from <lb/>hydroperoxides 46 -, and the chloride anion exchanger SLC26A3-which may maintain <lb/>physiologic ion concentrations in the CSF 47 . Similar to brain vascular cells 16,48 , the choroid <lb/>barrier and stromal epithelial, endothelial, mesenchymal, and ependymal cells robustly <lb/>expressed the antiviral defense gene IFITM3. Intriguingly, we observed a broad upregulation of <lb/>IFITM3 across barrier cells in COVID-19 patients, consistent with immunohistochemical <lb/>detection of SARS-CoV-2 infection (Fig. 3b). IFITM3 serves as the first line of defense against <lb/>viral infection 49 and its upregulation is a marker of SARS-CoV-2 infection across publicly <lb/>available datasets 50 . We also observed in the cortex parenchyma a consistent upregulation of <lb/>the newly described viral entry receptor NRP1 41,51,52 (Fig. 3b, Extended Data Fig. 6), which has <lb/>been previously found upregulated in inflamed COVID-19 lung tissue 51,53 . <lb/>Overall, the DEGs detected in choroid epithelial cells, mesenchymal cells, and <lb/>monocytes indicate strong CNS inflammation in COVID-19 (Fig. 3c-e, Extended Data Table 5). <lb/>For example, we observed upregulation of the pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-1β, which has been <lb/>reported sufficient to induce pathologic microglial and astrocyte activation 54,55 . The coincident <lb/>upregulation of IL-1β, CCL2, and CCL4 further suggests a weakened choroid barrier and an <lb/>increasingly permissive environment for immune cell transmigration into the brain <lb/>parenchyma 56-58 . The aged choroid plexus has recently been reported to send inflammatory <lb/>signals to the brain, thereby activating glia and impairing cognitive function 59,60 . To assess if <lb/>similar pro-inflammatory signaling mechanisms occur in COVID-19, we performed cell-cell <lb/>communication analysis 61,62 . We observed a strong increase in choroid-to-cortex signaling <lb/>across key inflammatory pathways, such as the CCL and CXCL family of chemokines (Fig. 3f, <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 5b). Together, these results suggest that SARS-CoV-2 can infect and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>inflame brain-barrier cells, including the choroid plexus; and that this barrier-together with <lb/>peripheral-inflammation is then relayed into the brain parenchyma. <lb/>Immune cell infiltration and activation of neuronal engulfment programs in microglia <lb/>We sought to evaluate the predicted activation of brain microglia and migration of <lb/>peripheral immune cells via enhanced inflammatory signaling from the periphery and brain-<lb/>barrier cells. Intriguingly, we observed in the cortex a COVID-19 enriched subpopulation of <lb/>microglia (Fig. 4a-b, Extended Data Fig. 7-8). This cluster was marked by expression of genes <lb/>implicated in human microglial activation, such as CD74, FTL, and FTH1 (Extended Data Table <lb/>6). These very genes have recently been described as difficult to detect by snRNA-seq 63 , further <lb/>underscoring strong COVID-19 microglial activation. An over-represented fraction of COVID-19 <lb/>microglia cluster marker genes overlap (P &lt; 10 -25 , hypergeometric test) with human Alzheimer&apos;s <lb/>disease microglia cluster markers 34 (Extended Data Fig. 7c). Monocle trajectory analysis 64 found <lb/>that the COVID-19 microglia cluster emerged from the parent homeostatic population-and that <lb/>the expression of activation markers increased along the pseudotime route-, suggesting that <lb/>these microglia emerged in response to an increasingly inflamed CNS environment (Fig. 4c, <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 7a-b), consistent with enhanced brain-barrier inflammatory signaling. Our <lb/>observations suggest that the COVID-19 subpopulation represents a distinct microglial state <lb/>that shares features with, but is ultimately different from, microglial cell states previously <lb/>reported in human neurodegenerative disease. <lb/>We next assessed the predicted increase in peripheral immune cell infiltration. We <lb/>indeed found both an increase in T-cells (marked by CD247 encoding the TCR CD3-zeta <lb/>protein, Fig. 4d, Extended Data Fig. 8e) and an increase in peripheral macrophages (marked by <lb/>F13A1 65,66 , Fig. 4e). Microglial activation and enhanced immune cell infiltration have been <lb/>recently reported by IHC staining in a series of 43 COVID-19 brains, with the degree of <lb/>infiltration and glial activation not clearly correlated with neurological symptoms or the presence <lb/>of detectable virus in the brain 5 . Our results largely corroborate those findings via an orthogonal <lb/>snRNA-seq approach (Fig. 4a-e). Both the formation of a distinct microglial cluster and the <lb/>enhanced infiltration of peripheral T-cells and macrophages did not occur in terminal influenza, <lb/>suggesting a COVID-19 specific-or at least not a pan-viral-CNS response. <lb/>Because we collected sufficient microglia for DEG analysis, we sought a clearer <lb/>understanding of the functional ramifications of their COVID-19 activation. As expected, <lb/>established markers of microglial activation previously linked to pathologic functions such as <lb/>CD74 and MERTK were strongly upregulated 67-74 . We observed a concomitant loss of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>immune checkpoint molecules MEF2C and IRAK3 that restrain runaway inflammation 75-77 . <lb/>Recently, increased microglial phagocytosis of live neurons-termed phagoptosis-has been <lb/>demonstrated to be an important mechanism driving various neurodegenerative diseases 71,78-81 . <lb/>Remarkably, nearly every gene reported 81 to mediate microglial phagocytosis of live neurons is <lb/>strongly upregulated in COVID-19 microglia (Fig. 4g). These include the genes encoding <lb/>complement proteins C3, all three components of C1Q, and the pro-phagocytic receptors <lb/>MERTK and VNR. Together, these data reveal in the COVID-19 brain the infiltration of immune <lb/>cells and strong activation of a pathologic microglial phagocytosis program predicted to <lb/>prematurely engulf and prune live neurons. <lb/>Potential synaptic dysfunction specifically in layer 2/3 excitatory neurons <lb/>The global induction of microglial phagoptosis programs prompted us to look into other <lb/>potential signatures of neuronal compromise. Astrocytes play a dual role in both forming the glia <lb/>limitans barrier 82,83 and supporting homeostatic neuronal function 84-86 (Fig. 5a). Given SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 infection of barrier cells, we thus wondered whether astrocytes would exhibit similar <lb/>hallmarks of inflammation with concomitant consequences for neuronal health. We indeed <lb/>observed hallmarks of astrogliosis 87 and viral defense 50 in upregulated GFAP and IFITM3 <lb/>expression, as well as neurotoxicity in the secreted factor CHI3L1 88-90 (Fig. 3b, Fig. 5a-d). <lb/>Forming a tripartite synapse with neurons, astrocytes finely balance the levels of synaptic <lb/>neurotransmitters like glutamate via the dedicated transporters EEAT1 (SLC1A3) and EEAT2 <lb/>(SLC1A2) 91-93 . Dysregulated glutamate transporter expression causes neuronal dysfunction: <lb/>downregulation results in excess glutamate excitotoxicity 94,95 and extrasynaptic spillover 96,97 ; <lb/>whereas upregulation impairs long-term potentiation (LTP) and synaptic plasticity 98-101 . We <lb/>observed dysregulated overexpression of genes predicting diminished glutamate signaling <lb/>across synapses: for example, the overexpression of both glutamate transporters (SLC1A2 and <lb/>SLC1A3, Fig. 5a, e) as well as the major potassium uptake channel Kir4.1 (KCNJ10), which <lb/>reduces neuronal excitability by lowering extracellular potassium, glutamate, and BDNF 102 . <lb/>We next sought to identify the neuronal subtypes affected in COVID-19. Enrichment <lb/>analysis implicated potential impairments in synaptic transmission specifically in excitatory <lb/>neurons (Extended Data Fig. 9). Among COVID-19 patients, those with objective neurological <lb/>symptoms or detectable virus did not exhibit further deficits in the expression of genes <lb/>mediating synaptic transmission (Extended Data Fig. 9c, Extended Data Table 1). Glutamate <lb/>release at synapses is critical for fast and faithful communication between neurons for <lb/>information processing in sub-second timeframes 103-105 . Glutamate is stored in readily <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>releasable pools of vesicles within presynaptic terminals. During synaptic transmission, SNARE <lb/>proteins play an indispensable role in vesicle docking, priming, fusion, and synchronization of <lb/>glutamate release into the synaptic cleft 103,104 . Downregulation of the mRNA encoding SNARE <lb/>components has been found in various neurological diseases 106-109 , and is sufficient in <lb/>experimental models to impair both vesicle processing and overall neuronal viability 110-114 . We <lb/>observed in COVID-19 excitatory neurons a consistent downregulation of major SNARE <lb/>components (Fig. 5f). For example, genes encoding both v-SNARE synaptobrevins (VAMP1, <lb/>VAMP2) necessary for calcium-dependent glutamate release 115,116 decreased. Likewise, <lb/>expression diminished for the partner t-SNARE proteins syntaxin 1B (STX1B) and SNAP-25, <lb/>also necessary 117,118 for glutamate release. <lb/>The human neocortex is composed of six layers of interconnected excitatory and <lb/>inhibitory neurons, with each layer both highly specialized locally and integrated globally. Of <lb/>these six layers, layers 2 and 3 are disproportionately thickened during the evolution of the <lb/>human brain, playing a key role in higher brain functions such as cognition, learning, memory, <lb/>creativity, and abstraction 4,119,120 . Though we captured neurons from all cortical layers, we found <lb/>that gene expression changes linked to synaptic deficits are specific to only these layer 2/3 <lb/>excitatory neurons (Fig. 5g). L2/3 excitatory neurons already exhibit sparse action potential <lb/>firing to generate a simple and reliable neural code for associative learning 120 . Thus, this <lb/>neuronal population may be particularly sensitive to the predicted deficits in neurotransmission <lb/>with COVID-19. Together, these data suggest potential impairments in L2/3 neuron synaptic <lb/>transmission, plasticity, and LTP in COVID-19, due to the dysregulation of genes mediating <lb/>astrocyte glutamate homeostasis and genes encoding major synaptic vesicle components. <lb/>Associations with chronic CNS disease <lb/>Reports of lingering CNS complications in COVID-19 survivors are emerging 121 . To <lb/>provide a molecular rationale for these complications, we compared COVID-19 cell type-specific <lb/>DEGs with those recently described by snRNA-seq in chronic CNS diseases, including <lb/>Alzheimer&apos;s disease 34 , multiple sclerosis 122 , Huntington&apos;s disease 123 , and autism spectrum <lb/>disorder 33 . Surprisingly, the overlap of DEGs between COVID-19 and these chronic CNS <lb/>diseases was over-represented for each cell type (Fig. 6a, Extended Data Fig. 10, Extended <lb/>Data Table 7). The degree of overlap was particularly high in astrocytes and excitatory neurons. <lb/>For example, genes encoding the SNARE protein SNAP-25 and the neurotrophic factor BDNF <lb/>were commonly downregulated in excitatory neurons in both COVID-19 and Alzheimer&apos;s <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>disease 34 . This over-representation of overlapping DEGs suggests existing CNS disease <lb/>knowledge-and even treatment approaches-may be relevant to COVID-19 neuropathology. <lb/>Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have shed insight into the molecular <lb/>pathways involved in complex traits and diseases 124,125 . GWAS variants suggest an important <lb/>role for a given gene through its loss or gain of function or expression. Thus, differential <lb/>expression of GWAS genes in COVID-19 may signal a re-emergence of these trait and disease <lb/>pathways 32 . To determine the enrichment of COVID-19 DEGs within genetic variants associated <lb/>with complex traits and diseases in a cell type-specific fashion, we obtained GWAS summary <lb/>statistics for neurological and psychiatric disorders and neurobehavior traits (Extended Data <lb/>Table 8) 125-127 . We found a strong enrichment of DEGs residing within GWAS hits of various <lb/>disorders and traits, especially in cognition, schizophrenia, and depression (Fig. 6b). These <lb/>particular disorders have been associated with dysfunction in L2/3 neurons and astrocytes 128-<lb/>135 . Together, these data suggest that COVID-19 may partially recapitulate established <lb/>pathological processes in the brain and provide molecular hypotheses for emerging neurological <lb/>complaints in COVID-19 survivors. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Recent snRNA-seq studies have elucidated the cell type-specific processes involved in <lb/>several CNS diseases 32-35,122,123 . Here, by combining sequencing of 47,678 nuclei in both frontal <lb/>cortex and choroid plexus along with IHC detection of SARS-CoV-2 in brain-barrier cells, we <lb/>reveal several major neuropathological mechanisms in severe COVID-19. Based on gene <lb/>expression patterns uncovered in this study, we propose a model where SARS-CoV-2 infected <lb/>brain-barrier cells can relay and permit inflammatory signaling into the cortex parenchyma. In <lb/>this inflammatory milieu, peripheral immune cells infiltrate the brain, microglia activate neuronal <lb/>phagocytosis programs, and astrocyte homeostatic properties become dysregulated. Microglial <lb/>activation is sufficient to induce a COVID-19 specific subpopulation. Together, these <lb/>perturbations may converge on impaired neuronal function, with L2/3 excitatory neurons in <lb/>particular exhibiting a transcriptomic signature of compromised glutamate transmission and <lb/>information processing 4,119,120 . <lb/>There are, however, limitations to consider given the unique logistical circumstances of a <lb/>pandemic. With most postmortem COVID-19 brain tissue immediately fixed 42 or not handled <lb/>with snRNA-seq studies in mind for safety and regulatory reasons, there is a lack of the high-<lb/>quality tissue necessary for such studies 21,23,24 . This has precluded larger study cohorts that <lb/>could be more representative of COVID-19 patients as a whole. For example, while we and a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>recent IHC-based study of 43 patient brains 5 (the largest to date) do not find a clear correlation <lb/>between detectable brain SARS-CoV-2 and glial inflammation or neurological symptoms, this <lb/>may not be representative of all patients, especially those without pre-existing co-morbidities or <lb/>who do not require ventilation 136 . Furthermore, the associations with chronic CNS disease may <lb/>not be relevant in mild COVID-19 disease and may change over time in severe COVID-19 <lb/>survivors. Long-term postmortem studies of survivors after the acute phase of disease are not <lb/>currently possible to assess this. However, there is precedent for acute viral infections causing <lb/>long-term inflammation and dysfunction predisposing neurodegenerative disease 137-140 . <lb/>Understanding the underlying mechanisms of how SARS-CoV-2 affects the brain may <lb/>inform therapeutic approaches 121 . Most molecular studies to date on SARS-CoV-2 neurotropism <lb/>have made powerful use of cultured organoids, though they have reached conflicting <lb/>conclusions 21-26 . Here, in postmortem COVID-19 patient tissue, we find that the blood-brain and <lb/>blood-CSF barrier cells typically lacking in organoid models are of high physiologic relevance in <lb/>informing questions of neurotropism. By combining IHC with a new method to process human <lb/>choroid plexi tissue for snRNA-seq, we propose that infection of brain-barrier cells can generate <lb/>a depot of strong antiviral inflammation and compromise barrier function, combining to inflame <lb/>the brain parenchyma. Such brain-barrier relay and permeability mechanisms have been found <lb/>important in brain aging 59,141-144 . Thus, COVID-19&apos;s impact on the brain, like many of its other <lb/>properties, may follow a nuanced-but potentially therapeutically targetable-mechanism of <lb/>action. We propose that the development of new techniques to study human brain-barrier cells <lb/>will further help elucidate disease processes in COVID-19 and beyond. <lb/>The scale of the COVID-19 pandemic means thousands of people may suffer <lb/>neurological symptoms, with some facing lifelong problems as a result. Our results nominate <lb/>COVID-19 pathologic processes in microglia, astrocytes, and neurons not seen in a patient <lb/>suffering terminal influenza infection. The particular vulnerability of layer 2/3 excitatory neurons <lb/>in COVID-19 provides a consistent molecular hypothesis for emerging neurological complaints, <lb/>from &quot;brain fog&quot; to memory loss to difficulty concentrating 11,145,146 . Several COVID-19 <lb/>perturbations revealed here may be addressable with existing medications 147 . However, as is <lb/>the case for recent human transcriptomic studies, additional research will be required to link the <lb/>observed cell type-specific gene expression changes with neurological symptoms 32,33,35,122,123 . <lb/>Nevertheless, these studies have served as important resources for understanding the <lb/>molecular and cellular basis of disease and for formulating new lines of investigation. In <lb/>summary, this work sheds insight into and provides new opportunities to explore the acute and <lb/>lasting neurological consequences of COVID-19. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank N. Khoury, T. Iram, E. Tapp, O. Hahn, and other members of the Wyss-Coray and <lb/>Keller labs for feedback and support, and H. Zhang and K. Dickey for laboratory management. <lb/>This work was funded by the NOMIS Foundation (T.W.-C.), the National Institute on Aging (T32-<lb/>AG0047126 to A.C.Y., 1RF1AG059694 to T.W.-C), Nan Fung Life Sciences (T.W.-C.), the <lb/>Bertarelli Brain Rejuvenation Sequencing Cluster (an initiative of the Stanford Wu Tsai <lb/>Neurosciences Institute), and the Stanford Alzheimer&apos;s Disease Research Center (P30 <lb/>AG066515). A.C.Y was supported by a Siebel Scholarship. F.K., G.S., T.F., W.S.-S., and A.K., <lb/>are a part of the CORSAAR study supported by the State of Saarland, the Saarland University, <lb/>and the Rolf M. Schwiete Stiftung. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>A.C.Y., F.K., A.K. and T.W.-C. conceptualized the study. M.W.M., N.L., I.C., W.S.-S., N.S., D.C., <lb/>D.B., and A.C.Y. provided and organized tissue samples. A.C.Y. performed tissue dissociations. <lb/>A.C.Y., N.S., D.P.L., R.T.V., D.G., and K.C. prepared libraries for sequencing. F.K., G.S., T.F., <lb/>and A.C.Y. performed computational analysis, with F.K. leading advanced analysis and data <lb/>management. P.M.L. developed the searchable web interface (Shiny app). W.S.-S. performed <lb/>immunohistochemical stains. A.C.Y. and C.A.M. assembled figures. A.C.Y. wrote the <lb/>manuscript with input from all authors. T.W.-C. and A.K. supervised the study. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>T.W.-C. is a founder and scientific advisor of Alkahest Inc. <lb/></div>

			<front>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to A.K. or T.W.-C. <lb/>(andreas.keller@ccb.uni-saarland.de, twc@stanford.edu). <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figures <lb/>Figure 1. Cell type-specific gene expression changes in the brain of COVID-19 patients. <lb/>a, Study design. Colored triangles denote brain regions studied for each patient. <lb/>b, Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) of 23,626 nuclei captured from the human <lb/>medial frontal cortex, colored by cell type and labeled with percent of total nuclei. Note, that as in prior <lb/>reports 32,34,35 , the &apos;Endothelial&apos; cluster also exhibits vascular mural cell markers. <lb/>c, Differentially expressed gene (DEG) counts for each cell type (MAST with default thresholds, FDR &lt; <lb/>0.05, Log (fold change) &gt; 0.25 (absolute value)). The intensity of the blue color and the size of the <lb/>squares are proportional to entry values. <lb/>d, Example differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in COVID-19: excitatory (Ex N) and inhibitory (In N) <lb/>neurons, astrocytes (Ast), oligodendrocytes (Oli), oligodendrocyte precursor cells (OPC), and microglia <lb/>(Mic). <lb/>e, Matrix layout for intersections of DEGs shared across and specific to each cell type. Circles in the <lb/>matrix indicate sets that are part of the intersection, showing that most DEGs are cell type-specific. <lb/>f, Fraction of total up-and downregulated genes (y-axis) as a function of the total number of cell types in <lb/>which the differential expression occurs. Biological pathways associated with genes downregulated in <lb/>COVID-19 that are common to ≥2 cell types are shown (n = 161 genes, hypergeometric test, FDR <lb/>correction). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1. Cell type-specific gene expression changes in the brain of COVID-19 patients. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2. SARS-CoV-2 infection of blood-brain and -CSF barrier cells. <lb/>a, SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein (brown) detection in the frontal medial cortex of two COVID-19 <lb/>patients in tissue immediately adjacent to that used for snRNA-seq. Hematoxylin counterstain (blue). <lb/>Scale bar = 20 microns. <lb/>b, As in (a) but for the meninges in Patient 2. Scale bar = 20 microns. <lb/>c, As in (a) but for the choroid plexi immediately adjacent to tissue used for snRNA-seq, in Patient 1. <lb/>Scale bar = 20 microns. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2. SARS-CoV-2 infection of blood-brain and -CSF barrier cells. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 3. Viral defense and inflammatory signaling in blood-CSF barrier cells. <lb/>a, UMAP of 24,052 nuclei captured from the human lateral choroid plexus, colored by cell type and <lb/>labeled with percent of total nuclei. <lb/>b, Expression profiles (CPM, circle size) and differential expression in COVID-19 patients (Log (fold <lb/>change), color) for genes relevant to SARS-CoV-2 brain entry 16 . Grey indicates genes consistently <lb/>upregulated in either brain-barrier cells (IFITM3) or cortex (NRP1). <lb/>c, DEG counts for each cell type (MAST, FDR &lt; 0.05, Log (fold change) &gt; 0.25 (absolute value)). The <lb/>intensity of the blue color and the size of the squares are proportional to entry values. <lb/>d, Example DEGs in COVID-19 choroid plexus. <lb/>e, Matrix layout for intersections of DEGs shared across and specific to each cell type. <lb/>f, Circle plot showing the number of statistically significant intercellular signaling interactions for the CCL <lb/>and CXCL family of molecules in controls (non-viral and influenza) compared to COVID-19 patients <lb/>(permutation test, CellChat 61 ). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 3. Viral defense and inflammatory signaling in blood-CSF barrier cells. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 4. Immune cell infiltration and activation of microglial phagocytosis programs in COVID-19 <lb/>brains. <lb/>a, UMAP of 1,154 immune cells captured in the human frontal cortex, split by non-viral controls, influenza, <lb/>and COVID-19 patients. Cells are colored by cell type subcluster. Example genes upregulated in <lb/>Microglia cluster 2 are shown. <lb/>b, Quantification of Microglia 2 population as a proportion of total immune cells (n = 5 controls, including <lb/>influenza; n = 4 COVID-19, two-sided t-test; mean +/-s.e.m.). <lb/>c, Monocle 64 pseudotime trajectory plotting the emergence of Microglia cluster 2. Pseudotime is indicated <lb/>in graded purple (high) to yellow (high). Numbers indicate Microglial cluster from (a). <lb/>d, Quantification of the T-cell population as a proportion of total immune cells (n = 5 controls, including <lb/>influenza; n = 4 COVID-19, two-sided t-test; mean +/-s.e.m.). <lb/>e, Expression of the established peripheral macrophage-specific marker F13A1 65,66 . Expression (logCPM) <lb/>is indicated in graded purple (left). Quantification of the peripheral macrophage population as a proportion <lb/>of total immune cells (n = 5 controls, including influenza; n = 4 COVID-19, two-sided t-test; mean +/-<lb/>s.e.m., right). <lb/>f, Expression of established microglial activation 67-74 and inflammation checkpoint 75-77 molecules. Violin <lb/>plots are centered around the median, with their shape representing cell distribution (***P &lt; 0.001, ****P &lt; <lb/>0.00001, MAST). <lb/>g, Upregulation of genes mediating the microglial phagocytosis of live neurons 81 . Bold indicates <lb/>upregulated genes in COVID-19, grey not detected. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 4. Immune cell infiltration and activation of microglial phagocytosis programs in COVID-19 brains. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 5. Impaired astrocytic support and excitatory neurotransmission in COVID-19 cortex. <lb/>a, Upregulation of inflammatory and dysregulation of homeostatic genes in COVID-19 astrocytes (n = <lb/>3,967). <lb/>b, Enriched biological pathways (Elsevier Pathway Collection, Enrichr) amongst upregulated genes in <lb/>COVID-19 astrocytes. Enrichment is based on FDR-corrected cumulative hypergeometric P values, with a <lb/>P value-thresholded DEG gene-marker list (Log (fold change) &gt; 0.25 (absolute value), adjusted P value <lb/>(Bonferroni correction) &lt; 0.05, MAST). <lb/>c, UMAP of 3,967 astrocytes captured in the human frontal cortex, split by non-viral controls, influenza, <lb/>and COVID-19 patients. Cells are colored by cell type subcluster. Example genes upregulated in <lb/>Astrocyte cluster 3 are shown. <lb/>d, Quantification of Astrocyte 3 population as a proportion of all astrocytes (n = 5 controls, including <lb/>influenza; n = 4 COVID-19, two-sided t-test excluding influenza patient; mean +/-s.e.m.). <lb/>e, Expression of homeostatic astrocyte glutamate transporter genes encoding EEAT2 (SLC1A2) and <lb/>EEAT1 (SLC1A3). Violin plots are centered around the median, with their shape representing cell <lb/>distribution (****P &lt; 0.0001, MAST). <lb/>f, Downregulation of major SNARE components in COVID-19 excitatory neurons (n = 7,680 excitatory <lb/>neurons). <lb/>g, Heatmap showing downregulation of synaptic vesicle components specifically in COVID-19 L2/3 <lb/>excitatory neurons (n = 7,680 excitatory neurons; n = 4,948 L2/3 excitatory neurons, Log (fold change) &gt; <lb/>0.25 (absolute value), adjusted P value (Bonferroni correction) &lt; 0.05, MAST). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 5. Impaired astrocytic support and excitatory neurotransmission in COVID-19 cortex. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 6. Association of COVID-19 gene expression changes with chronic CNS disease. <lb/>a, Proportion of COVID-19 DEGs across cell types that are also DEGs in chronic CNS diseases, as <lb/>published for Alzheimer&apos;s Disease (AD) 34 , Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) 33 , Huntington&apos;s disease <lb/>(HD) 123 , and Multiple sclerosis (MS) 122 . Bars labeled with percent overlapping and over-representation P <lb/>values (cumulative hypergeometric test). <lb/>b, Heatmap showing the number of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) per cell type that are also <lb/>GWAS risk variants across psychiatric and neurological diseases and traits from the GWAS catalog <lb/>(NHGRI-EBI) 126 . Significance is based on FDR-corrected cumulative hypergeometric P values, with a P <lb/>value-thresholded DEG list (Log (fold change) &gt; 0.25 (absolute value), adjusted P value (Bonferroni <lb/>correction) &lt; 0.05, MAST). ALS: Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, MSA: Multiple system atrophy, ADHD: <lb/>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, and PTSD: Post-traumatic stress disorder. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 6. Association of COVID-19 gene expression changes with chronic CNS disease. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Methods <lb/>Isolation of nuclei from frozen post-mortem medial frontal gyrus <lb/>Frozen medial frontal cortex tissue from post-mortem control and COVID-19 patients were <lb/>obtained from the Stanford/ VA/ NIA Aging Clinical Research Center (ACRC) and the Saarland <lb/>University Hospital Institute for Neuropathology, with approval from local ethics committees. <lb/>Group characteristics are presented in Supplementary Table 1. The protocol for the isolation of <lb/>nuclei was adapted from previous studies 32,34,35,148,149 , and performed in a BSL2+ Biosafety <lb/>Cabinet wearing PPE. All procedures were carried out on ice or at 4°C. Briefly, 50 mg of post-<lb/>mortem brain tissue was dounce homogenized in 2 ml of Nuclei EZ Prep Lysis Buffer (Sigma, <lb/>NUC101) spiked with 0.2 U μl −1 RNase inhibitor (Takara, 2313A) and EDTA-free Protease <lb/>Inhibitor Cocktail (Roche, 11873580001) before incubating on ice for 5 min in a final volume of 5 <lb/>ml. Homogenized tissue was filtered through a 100-μm cell strainer (Falcon, 352360), mixed <lb/>with an equal volume of 50% iodixanol density gradient medium in PBS (OptiPrep, Sigma-<lb/>Aldrich, D1556) to make a final concentration of 25% iodixanol. 30% iodixanol was layered <lb/>underneath the 25% mixture. Similarly, 40% iodixanol was layered underneath the 30% <lb/>iodixanol. In a swinging-bucket centrifuge, nuclei were centrifuged for 20 min at 3,000 r.c.f. After <lb/>centrifugation, the nuclei were present at the interface of the 30% and 40% iodixanol solutions. <lb/>Isolated nuclei were resuspended in 1% BSA with 0.2 U μl −1 RNase inhibitor, filtered twice <lb/>through a 40 μm strainer (Flowmi), and counted on an TC20 automated cell counter (Bio-Rad) <lb/>after the addition of Trypan Blue. We did not use statistical methods to pre-determine sample <lb/>sizes, but our sample sizes are similar to those reported in previous publications 30-32 . <lb/>Isolation of nuclei from frozen post-mortem choroid plexus <lb/>Frozen choroid plexus tissue was extracted from the lateral ventricles of post-mortem tissue <lb/>obtained from the Stanford University Pathology department and the Saarland University <lb/>Hospital Institute for Neuropathology, with approval from local ethics committees. Group <lb/>characteristics are presented in Supplementary Table 1. All procedures were carried out on ice <lb/>or at 4°C, and in a BSL2+ Biosafety Cabinet wearing PPE. Dounce homogenization or <lb/>enzymatic dissociation successfully used for mice choroid plexi 29 resulted in loss of nuclei <lb/>integrity and low nuclei complexity (&lt;50 median genes/ nuclei). We hypothesized that like <lb/>shaking an apple tree, gentle pipetting of choroid plexi tissue in lysis buffer could liberate nuclei <lb/>without needing to physically disintegrate the fibrous choroid matrix-and thus avoid collateral <lb/>physical damage to nuclei. Specifically, 40 mg of choroid plexus tissue was thawed in 250 μl of <lb/>1% BSA with 0.2 U μl −1 RNase inhibitor until the tissue settled. 5 ml of lysis buffer (10 mM Tris, <lb/>10 mM NaCl, 3 mM MgCl2, 0.1% Nonidet P40 substitute (Roche/ Sigma, 11754599001), 0.2 U <lb/>μl −1 RNase inhibitor, and protease inhibitor) was added and tissue incubated on ice for 10 <lb/>minutes with gentle swirling every 2 minutes. 5 ml of 1% BSA was added and the tissue <lb/>triturated 10 times with a 5 ml serological pipette. After centrifugation (500g, 5 min), pelleted <lb/>nuclei were resuspended in 1% BSA with 0.2 U μl −1 RNase inhibitor; gently triturated 10 times <lb/>with a 1 ml regular-bore pipette tip; and filtered twice through a 70 μm and then a 40 μm strainer <lb/>(Flowmi). Debris was inspected on a brightfield microscope and nuclei were counted on an <lb/>TC20 automated cell counter (Bio-Rad) after the addition of Trypan Blue. <lb/>Droplet-based snRNA-sequencing <lb/>For droplet-based snRNA-seq, libraries were prepared using the Chromium Next GEM Single <lb/>Cell 3ʹ v3.1 according to the manufacturer&apos;s protocol (10x Genomics), targeting 10,000 nuclei <lb/>per sample after counting with a TC20 Automated Cell Counter (Bio-Rad). 13 cycles were <lb/>applied to brain parenchyma samples to generate cDNA, and 15 for choroid plexus samples. All <lb/>samples underwent 15-16 cycles for final library generation. Generated snRNA-seq libraries <lb/>were sequenced across two S4 lanes on a NovaSeq 6000 (150 cycles, Novogene). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>snRNA-seq quality control <lb/>Gene counts were obtained by aligning reads to the hg38 genome (refdata-gex-GRCh38-2020-<lb/>A) using CellRanger software (v.4.0.0) (10x Genomics). To account for unspliced nuclear <lb/>transcripts, reads mapping to pre-mRNA were counted. As previously published, a cut-off value <lb/>of 200 unique molecular identifiers (UMIs) was used to select single nuclei for further analysis 34 . <lb/>As initial reference, the entire dataset was projected onto two-dimensional space using Uniform <lb/>Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) on the top 20 principal components 150 . Three <lb/>approaches were combined for quality control: (1) ambient cell free mRNA contamination was <lb/>removed using SoupX 151 for each individual sample; (2) outliers with a high ratio of <lb/>mitochondrial (&gt;5%, &lt;200 features) relative to endogenous RNAs and homotypic doublets (&gt; <lb/>5000 features) were removed in Seurat 152 ; and (3) after scTransform normalization and <lb/>integration, doublets and multiplets were filtered out using DoubletFinder with subsequent <lb/>manual inspection and filtering based on cell type-specific marker genes 153 . Genes detected in <lb/>fewer than 4 cells were excluded. After applying these filtering steps, the dataset contained <lb/>47,678 high-quality nuclei. <lb/>Cell annotations <lb/>Seurat&apos;s Integration function was used to align data with default settings. Genes were projected <lb/>into principal component (PC) space using the principal component analysis (RunPCA). The <lb/>first 80 (for global object), 30 (choroid plexus), or 25 (specific cell types) dimensions were used <lb/>as inputs into Seurat&apos;s FindNeighbors, FindClusters (at 0.2 resolution) and RunUMAP functions. <lb/>Briefly, a shared-nearest-neighbor graph was constructed based on the Euclidean distance <lb/>metric in PC space, and cells were clustered using the Louvain method. RunUMAP functions <lb/>with default settings was used to calculate 2-dimensional UMAP coordinates and search for <lb/>distinct cell populations. Positive differential expression of each cluster against all other clusters <lb/>(MAST) was used to identify marker genes for each cluster 154 . We annotated cell-types using <lb/>previously published marker genes 31,33-35 . <lb/>Differential gene expression and sub-cluster analysis <lb/>Differential gene expression of genes comparing controls, COVID-19, and influenza samples-<lb/>or comparing cell type sub-cluster markers-was done using the MAST 154 algorithm, which <lb/>implements a two-part hurdle model. Seurat default Log (fold change) &gt; 0.25 (absolute value), <lb/>adjusted P value (Bonferroni correction) &lt; 0.05, and expression in greater than 10% of cells <lb/>were required to consider a gene differentially expressed. Biological pathway and gene ontology <lb/>enrichment analysis was performed using Enrichr 155 , Metascape 156 , or GeneTrail 3 157 with input <lb/>species set to Homo sapiens 156 and using standard parameters. Docking, processing, and viral <lb/>defense genes relevant to SARS-CoV-2 were chosen based on Iadecola, et al 16 . To identify <lb/>microglia sub-cluster markers, differential expression analysis of cells grouped in each sub-<lb/>cluster was performed against the remaining cells within the given cell-type. Markers were <lb/>defined based on the MAST algorithm using only positive values with Log (fold change) &gt; 0.25 <lb/>(absolute value), adjusted P value (Bonferroni correction) &lt; 0.01. Enrichment/ over-<lb/>representation of the overlap between markers defining the COVID-19 microglia 2 cluster and <lb/>the Mathys 34 Alzheimer&apos;s disease Mic1 cluster followed the hypergeometric probability, using <lb/>the set of 17,926 protein-coding genes as background. <lb/>Monocle trajectory analysis <lb/>Monocle3 (v.0.2.1.) was used to generate the pseudotime trajectory analysis in microglia 64 . <lb/>Cells were re-clustered as above and used as input into Monocle to infer cluster and lineage <lb/>relationships within a given cell type. Specifically, UMAP embeddings and cell sub-clusters <lb/>generated from Seurat were converted to a cell_data_set object using SeuratWrappers (v.0.2.0) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>and then used as input to perform trajectory graph learning and pseudo-time measurement <lb/>through reversed graph embedding with Monocle. <lb/>Viral transcripts <lb/>To search for SARS-CoV-2 reads, raw fastq files were subjected to read alignment via Viral-<lb/>Track 158 or centrifuge 159 using the human (GRCh38) genome reference. For Viral-Track both a <lb/>collection of 12,163 consensus virus sequences from Virusite 160 (release 2020.3) and 17,133 <lb/>curated SARS-CoV-2 genomes from NCBI (downloaded on 29-09-2020) were used. For <lb/>centrifuge, a preprocessed virus index compiled by genexa containing among other viruses 138 <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 genomes was used. We also adopted a complementary approach 161 focusing on <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 reads, whereby barcoded but unmapped BAM reads were aligned using STAR to <lb/>the SARS-CoV-2 reference genome, with a less stringent mapping parameter <lb/>(outFilterMatchNmin 25-30) than the original Viral-Track pipeline. <lb/>Cell-cell communication <lb/>Cell-cell interactions based on the expression of known ligand-receptor pairs in different cell <lb/>types were inferred using CellChatDB 61 (v.0.02). To identify potential cell-cell communication <lb/>networks perturbed or induced in COVID-19 patient brains, we focused on differentially <lb/>expressed ligands in choroid plexus epithelium, microglia, and astrocytes; and differentially <lb/>expressed receptor pairs in excitatory and inhibitory neurons. Briefly, we followed the official <lb/>workflow and loaded the normalized counts into CellChat and applied the preprocessing <lb/>functions identifyOverExpressedGenes, identifyOverExpressedInteractions, and projectData <lb/>with standard parameters set. As database we selected the Secreted Signaling pathways and <lb/>used the pre-compiled human Protein-Protein-Interactions as a priori network information. For <lb/>the main analyses the core functions computeCommunProb, computeCommunProbPathway, <lb/>and aggregateNet were applied using standard parameters and fixed randomization seeds. <lb/>Finally, to determine the senders and receivers in the network the function <lb/>netAnalysis_signalingRole was applied on the netP data slot. <lb/>GWAS <lb/>From the GWAS catalog 126 , we obtained GWAS risk genes for neurological disorders <lb/>[Alzheimer&apos;s disease (AD), amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS), brain aging, multiple system <lb/>atrophy (MSA), multiple sclerosis (MS), Parkinson&apos;s disease (PD), and narcolepsy], psychiatric <lb/>disorders [Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), autism, bipolar disorder, depression, <lb/>psychosis, post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), and schizophrenia], and neurobehavior traits <lb/>[Anxiety, suicidality, insomnia, neuroticism, risk behavior, intelligence, and cognitive function]. <lb/>We removed gene duplicates and GWAS loci either not reported or in intergenic regions and <lb/>used a P &lt; 9 × 10 −6 to identify significant associations 32 . Then, since GWAS signals can point to <lb/>multiple candidate genes within the same locus, we focused on the &apos;Reported Gene(s)&apos; (genes <lb/>reported as associated by the authors of each GWAS study). Disorders and traits exhibiting a <lb/>significant number of genes also perturbed in COVID-19 patients are highlighted. Following <lb/>gene symbol extraction, we curated the gene set by (1) removing unknown or outdated gene <lb/>names using the HGNChelper package (v.0.8.6), (2) converting remaining Ensembl gene IDs to <lb/>actual gene names using the packages ensembldb (v.2.10.0) and EnsDb.Hsapiens.v86 <lb/>(v.2.99.0), and (3) removing any remaining duplicates. We then calculated the overlap between <lb/>each set of GWAS genes with the cell type-specific DEGs. Finally, a statistical enrichment of <lb/>each overlap against background was calculated using a hypergeometric test with the total <lb/>background size set equal to the number of unique RNAs mapped in our data set (29,431). <lb/>Comparison of DEGs in chronic CNS disease <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>We compiled cell type-specific differentially expressed genes (DEGs) reported in published <lb/>datasets for Alzheimer&apos;s Disease (AD) 34 , Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) 33 , Huntington&apos;s <lb/>disease (HD) 123 , and Multiple sclerosis (MS) 122 . Lists of gene symbols were curated using the <lb/>aforementioned approach. COVID-19 DEGs that overlap with those found across the selected <lb/>CNS diseases were called shared, whereas those not previously reported were called unique to <lb/>COVID-19. Statistical significance calculations of over-representation in DEG overlaps are <lb/>based on cumulative hypergeometric P values analogous to the procedure described above. <lb/>PVCA and PCA analysis <lb/>Briefly, to conduct the Principal Variance Component Analysis (PVCA), we aggregated the <lb/>SoupX corrected raw counts for each gene and each biological sample using the aggregateData <lb/>function of the muscat package (v.1.2.1). The resulting matrix was normalized by dividing each <lb/>feature of a sample by the total counts from that sample, multiplied by a scaling factor of <lb/>100,000 and scaling the result using the function log(x+1). As variables we considered the <lb/>sample annotation fields &quot;Sample-ID&quot;, &quot;Patient-ID&quot;, &quot;Sex&quot;, &quot;Brain-region&quot;, &quot;Disease&quot;, &quot;ageBin&quot;, <lb/>and &quot;nNucleiBin&quot;. Since the number of nuclei and age are numeric variables but PVCA is <lb/>designed to support factors, we assigned the values into ordered bins, more specifically, into <lb/>five half-open (left-closed) intervals of size 1,000 starting at 2,000 for the number of nuclei and <lb/>five similarly defined intervals of size 10 starting at 51 for the age. We set the algorithm cut-off <lb/>for the minimal variance out of the total variance being explained to be 95%. For each single <lb/>annotation variable, or first higher-order combinations of such, at cut-off of 0.005 was applied to <lb/>consider them explanatory. All variables (or combinations of such) not passing the threshold <lb/>were summarized as Other in the analysis. The residual is then defined as the remaining <lb/>proportion of variance not being associated with any of the variables that are explanatory nor <lb/>informative to a minor proportion. To conduct Principal Components Analysis (PCA) we <lb/>aggregated the log-normalized cell counts from Seurat for each gene and sample using the <lb/>aggregateData function from muscat and centered the gene expression vectors before <lb/>computing eigenvectors. <lb/>Overall in-silico analysis <lb/>Analysis and dissection of the data was performed using the statistical programming language <lb/>R (v.3.6.3) using the following general-purpose package for loading, saving, and manipulating <lb/>data, as well as generating plots, and fitting statistical models: dplyr (v.1.0.0), ggplot2 (v.3.2.2.), <lb/>patchwork (v.1.0.1), openxlsx (v.4.1.5), bioconductor-scater (v.1.14.6), bioconductor-dropletutils <lb/>(v1.6.1), bioconductor-complexheatmap (v.2.2.0), tidyverse (v.1.3.0), and lsa (v.0.73.2). All <lb/>other tasks were performed on an x86_64-based Ubuntu (4.15.0-55-generic kernel) server <lb/>cluster. <lb/>Immunohistochemistry <lb/>Paraffin-embedded human brain tissue (medial frontal cortex, meninges, and choroid plexus) <lb/>adjacent to tissue processed for snRNA-seq was subjected to immunohistochemistry (IHC). <lb/>After deparaffinization and rehydration of 1-3 µm sections, peroxidases were blocked by <lb/>incubation in 1% H2O2 for 15 minutes at room temperature. Heat antigen retrieval was <lb/>performed by steaming at 98°C in target retrieval solution pH 6.1 (Dako, Carpinteira, CA, USA <lb/>#S1699) for 30 minutes. Sections were allowed to cool down at room temperature. Following <lb/>antigen retrieval, sections were incubated for 45 minutes at room temperature with the anti-<lb/>SARS spike glycoprotein antibody 3A2 (rabbit, Abcam ab272420 1:100 diluted in Dako REAL <lb/>antibody diluent #S2022), which has been validated in previous publications 20,41 . After three <lb/>washes with wash buffer (Dako #S3006), the Dako REAL EnVision HRP kit (#K5007) was used <lb/>for the visualization of the antibody reaction according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. <lb/>Sections were counterstained with Mayer&apos;s hemalum (Sigma-Aldrich #1.09249). After <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>dehydration, coverslips were mounted with Entellan (Merck #1.07961). Images were acquired <lb/>with an Olympus BX 40 microscope, equipped with an Olympus SC30 digital microscope <lb/>camera using the Olympus cellSens software. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data Availability. Raw sequencing data is deposited under NCBI GEO: GSE159812. <lb/>Normalized counts data also available for download at: <lb/>https://twc-stanford.shinyapps.io/scRNA_Brain_COVID19. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figures <lb/>Extended Data Figure 1. Characterization of human cortical and choroid plexi nuclei sequenced. <lb/>a, Total number of nuclei and median number of genes of each human sample sequenced in medial <lb/>frontal cortex and choroid plexus. <lb/>b, Quantification of the median number of genes detected per nuclei in controls (non-viral and influenza) <lb/>and COVID-19 samples in medial frontal cortex and choroid plexus (n=5-7 controls and n=4 COVID-19, <lb/>two-sided t-test; mean +/-s.e.m.). <lb/>c, d, Bar graph presenting frequency of nuclei for non-viral controls, influenza, and COVID-19 medial <lb/>frontal cortex (c) and choroid plexus (d) sample groups. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 1. Characterization of human cortical and choroid plexi nuclei sequenced. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 2. Gene expression variance analysis. <lb/>a, Principal variance component analysis, displaying the gene expression variance explained by residuals <lb/>(biological and technical noise) or experimental factors such as brain region, age, sex, and respective <lb/>combinations. n = 15 samples. <lb/>b, Principal component analysis (PCA) visualization of all samples, based on unscaled counts. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 2. Gene expression variance analysis. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 3. Markers for annotating parenchymal cells in the human frontal medial <lb/>cortex. <lb/>a, Discovery of the top cell type-specific genes across the 12 classes of cells captured in the human <lb/>cortex. The color bar indicates gene expression from low (blue) to high (yellow). <lb/>b, Validation of cell type annotations using established cell type-specific markers. Violin plots are <lb/>centered around the median, with their shape representing cell distribution. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 3. Markers for annotating parenchymal cells in the human frontal medial cortex. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 4. Markers for annotating parenchymal cells in the human choroid plexus. <lb/>Validation of cell type annotations using established cell type-specific markers. Subsets of epithelial cells <lb/>are marked by high expression of specific markers not previously described in mice. Violin plots are <lb/>centered around the median, with their shape representing cell distribution. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 4. Markers for annotating parenchymal cells in the human choroid plexus. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 5. Cell-type specific changes in gene expression and intercellular signaling <lb/>in the COVID-19 brain. <lb/>a, Heatmap displaying the number of significant biological pathways among the set of differentially <lb/>expressed genes in each cell type (FDR &lt; 0.05, Fisher&apos;s exact test with Benjamini-Hochberg correction). <lb/>Number of significant pathways is indicated in graded black (high) to yellow (high). <lb/>b, Circle plot showing the total inferred intercellular signaling network, aggregating across the signaling <lb/>molecule interaction (i.e., ligand-receptor) CellChatDB database 61 . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 5. Cell-type specific changes in gene expression and intercellular signaling in the COVID-19 brain. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 6. Expression of SARS-CoV-2 virus entry genes across cell types. <lb/>a, b, Expression of SARS-CoV-2 entry receptors, established and putative, across cell types in the <lb/>human medial frontal cortex (a) and choroid plexus (b). Violin plots are centered around the median, with <lb/>their shape representing cell distribution. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 6. Expression of SARS-CoV-2 virus entry genes across cell types. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 7. Evolution and properties of the COVID-19 enriched microglia cluster. <lb/>a, b, Expression of established microglia activation markers (b) and SARS-CoV-2 entry receptors (c) <lb/>along the pseudotime route in (a). Pseudotime is indicated in graded purple (high) to yellow (high). <lb/>c, Overlap (hypergeometric test) between Alzheimer&apos;s disease human activated microglia Mic1 marker <lb/>genes 34 and genes upregulated in the COVID-19 enriched Microglia 2 subcluster. <lb/>d, Enriched biological pathways amongst Microglia 2 marker genes. Enrichment is based on FDR-<lb/>corrected cumulative hypergeometric P values, with a P value-ranked gene-marker list (FDR &lt; 0.01, <lb/>log2(mean gene expression across Microglia 2/ mean gene expression across all microglia) &gt; 0.25, <lb/>MAST). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 7. Evolution and properties of the COVID-19 enriched microglia cluster. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 8. Evaluation of COVID-19 enriched subpopulations in other parenchymal <lb/>glia. <lb/>a, UMAP projection of oligodendrocyte progenitor cells (OPCs, n = 1,634 from 4 non-viral controls, 1 <lb/>influenza and 4 COVID-19 individuals) and the emergence of COVID-19 enriched subcluster. <lb/>b, Quantification of the frequency of the COVID-19 enriched OPC subcluster as a proportion of all OPCs <lb/>(n=5 controls and n=4 COVID-19, two-sided t-test; mean +/-s.e.m.). <lb/>c, d, As in (a-b) but for oligodendrocytes. <lb/>e, Expression of the established T-cell marker CD247 (encoding TCR CD3 zeta chain) among immune <lb/>cells captured in human medial frontal cortex. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 8. Evaluation of COVID-19 enriched subpopulations in other parenchymal glia <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 9. Processes downregulated in excitatory neurons in COVID-19. <lb/>a, Enriched biological pathways amongst downregulated genes in COVID-19 excitatory neurons (n = <lb/>7,680 from 4 non-viral controls, 1 influenza and 4 COVID-19 individuals). Enrichment is based on FDR-<lb/>corrected cumulative hypergeometric P values, with a P value-ranked gene-marker list (Log (fold change) <lb/>&gt; 0.25 (absolute value), adjusted P value (Bonferroni correction) &lt; 0.05, MAST). <lb/>b, As in (a) but for Gene Ontology cellular components. <lb/>c, As in (a) but comparing COVID-19 patients with neurological symptoms versus those without. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 9. Processes downregulated in excitatory neurons in COVID-19. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 10. Comparison of cell type-specific changes in COVID-19 with chronic CNS <lb/>diseases. <lb/>Upset matrix plots comparing the cell type-specific genes expression changes in COVID-19 frontal cortex <lb/>with those previously published for Alzheimer&apos;s Disease (AD) 34 , Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) 33 , <lb/>Huntington&apos;s disease (HD) 123 , and Multiple sclerosis (MS) 122 . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Figure 10. Comparison of cell type-specific changes in COVID-19 with chronic CNS diseases. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Mao, L. et al. Neurologic Manifestations of Hospitalized Patients with Coronavirus Disease 2019 in <lb/>Wuhan, China. JAMA Neurol. (2020). doi:10.1001/jamaneurol.2020.1127 <lb/>2. <lb/>Yang, X. et al. Clinical course and outcomes of critically ill patients with SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia <lb/>in Wuhan, China: a single-centered, retrospective, observational study. Lancet Respir. Med. <lb/>(2020). doi:10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30079-5 <lb/>3. <lb/>Helms, J. et al. Neurologic features in severe SARS-COV-2 infection. New England Journal of <lb/>Medicine (2020). doi:10.1056/NEJMc2008597 <lb/>4. <lb/>Gidon, A. et al. Dendritic action potentials and computation in human layer 2/3 cortical neurons. <lb/>Science (80-. ). (2020). doi:10.1126/science.aax6239 <lb/>5. <lb/>Matschke, J. et al. Neuropathology of patients with COVID-19 in Germany: a post-mortem case <lb/>series. Lancet Neurol. (2020). <lb/>6. <lb/>Varatharaj, A. et al. Neurological and neuropsychiatric complications of COVID-19 in 153 patients: <lb/>a UK-wide surveillance study. The Lancet Psychiatry (2020). doi:10.1016/S2215-0366(20)30287-X <lb/>7. <lb/>Montalvan, V., Lee, J., Bueso, T., De Toledo, J. &amp; Rivas, K. Neurological manifestations of <lb/>COVID-19 and other coronavirus infections: A systematic review. Clinical Neurology and <lb/>Neurosurgery (2020). doi:10.1016/j.clineuro.2020.105921 <lb/>8. <lb/>Wu, Y. et al. Nervous system involvement after infection with COVID-19 and other coronaviruses. <lb/>Brain, Behavior, and Immunity (2020). doi:10.1016/j.bbi.2020.03.031 <lb/>9. <lb/>Bialek, S. et al. Severe Outcomes Among Patients with Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) -<lb/>United States, February 12-March 16, 2020. MMWR. Morb. Mortal. Wkly. Rep. (2020). <lb/>doi:10.15585/mmwr.mm6912e2 <lb/>10. <lb/>Romero-Sánchez, C. M. et al. Neurologic manifestations in hospitalized patients with COVID-19: <lb/>The ALBACOVID registry. Neurology (2020). doi:10.1212/WNL.0000000000009937 <lb/>11. <lb/>Liotta, E. M. et al. Frequent neurologic manifestations and encephalopathy-associated morbidity in <lb/>Covid-19 patients. Ann. Clin. Transl. Neurol. (2020). <lb/>12. <lb/>Rogers, J. P. et al. Psychiatric and neuropsychiatric presentations associated with severe <lb/>coronavirus infections: a systematic review and meta-analysis with comparison to the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic. The Lancet Psychiatry (2020). doi:10.1016/S2215-0366(20)30203-0 <lb/>13. <lb/>Cheng, S. K. W., Wong, C. W., Tsang, J. &amp; Wong, K. C. Psychological distress and negative <lb/>appraisals in survivors of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS). Psychol. Med. (2004). <lb/>doi:10.1017/S0033291704002272 <lb/>14. <lb/>Lam, M. H. B. et al. Mental morbidities and chronic fatigue in severe acute respiratory syndrome <lb/>survivors long-term follow-up. Arch. Intern. Med. (2009). doi:10.1001/archinternmed.2009.384 <lb/>15. <lb/>Ellul, M. A. et al. Neurological associations of COVID-19. The Lancet Neurology (2020). <lb/>doi:10.1016/S1474-4422(20)30221-0 <lb/>16. <lb/>Iadecola, C., Anrather, J. &amp; Kamel, H. Effects of COVID-19 on the Nervous System. Cell (2020). <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.cell.2020.08.028 <lb/>17. <lb/>Puelles, V. G. et al. Multiorgan and Renal Tropism of SARS-CoV-2. The New England journal of <lb/>medicine (2020). doi:10.1056/NEJMc2011400 <lb/>18. <lb/>Solomon, I. H. et al. Neuropathological Features of Covid-19. The New England journal of <lb/>medicine (2020). doi:10.1056/NEJMc2019373 <lb/>19. <lb/>Moriguchi, T. et al. A first case of meningitis/encephalitis associated with SARS-Coronavirus-2. Int. <lb/>J. Infect. Dis. (2020). doi:10.1016/j.ijid.2020.03.062 <lb/>20. <lb/>Meinhardt, J. et al. Olfactory transmucosal SARS-CoV-2 invasion as port of Central Nervous <lb/>System entry in COVID-19 patients. bioRxiv (2020). <lb/>21. <lb/>Song, E. et al. Neuroinvasive potential of SARS-CoV-2 revealed in a human brain organoid model. <lb/>bioRxiv (2020). doi:10.1101/2020.06.25.169946 <lb/>22. <lb/>Ramani, A. et al. SARS-CoV-2 targets cortical neurons of 3D human brain organoids and shows <lb/>neurodegeneration-like effects. bioRxiv (Preprint) (2020). doi:10.1101/2020.05.20.106575 <lb/>23. <lb/>Pellegrini, L. et al. SARS-CoV-2 infects brain choroid plexus and disrupts the blood-CSF-barrier. <lb/>bioRxiv (2020). doi:10.1101/2020.08.20.259937 <lb/>24. <lb/>Jacob, F. et al. Human Pluripotent Stem Cell-Derived Neural Cells and Brain Organoids Reveal <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 Neurotropism. bioRxiv (2020). doi:10.1101/2020.07.28.225151 <lb/>25. <lb/>Zhang, B. Z. et al. SARS-CoV-2 infects human neural progenitor cells and brain organoids. Cell <lb/>Research (2020). doi:10.1038/s41422-020-0390-x <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>26. <lb/>Mesci, P. et al. Sofosbuvir protects human brain organoids against SARS-CoV-2. (2020). <lb/>doi:10.1101/2020.05.30.125856 <lb/>27. <lb/>Bhaduri, A. et al. Cell stress in cortical organoids impairs molecular subtype specification. Nature <lb/>(2020). doi:10.1038/s41586-020-1962-0 <lb/>28. <lb/>Huch, M., Knoblich, J. A., Lutolf, M. P. &amp; Martinez-Arias, A. The hope and the hype of organoid <lb/>research. Dev. (2017). doi:10.1242/dev.150201 <lb/>29. <lb/>Dani, N. et al. A cellular and spatial map of the choroid plexus across brain ventricles and ages. <lb/>bioRxiv (2019). doi:10.1101/627539 <lb/>30. <lb/>Zhong, S. et al. A single-cell RNA-seq survey of the developmental landscape of the human <lb/>prefrontal cortex. Nature (2018). doi:10.1038/nature25980 <lb/>31. <lb/>Lake, B. B. et al. Integrative single-cell analysis of transcriptional and epigenetic states in the <lb/>human adult brain. Nat. Biotechnol. (2018). doi:10.1038/nbt.4038 <lb/>32. <lb/>Grubman, A. et al. A single-cell atlas of entorhinal cortex from individuals with Alzheimer&apos;s disease <lb/>reveals cell-type-specific gene expression regulation. Nat. Neurosci. (2019). doi:10.1038/s41593-<lb/>019-0539-4 <lb/>33. <lb/>Velmeshev, D. et al. Single-cell genomics identifies cell type-specific molecular changes in <lb/>autism. Science (80-. ). (2019). doi:10.1126/science.aav8130 <lb/>34. <lb/>Mathys, H. et al. Single-cell transcriptomic analysis of Alzheimer&apos;s disease. Nature (2019). <lb/>doi:10.1038/s41586-019-1195-2 <lb/>35. <lb/>Zhou, Y. et al. Human and mouse single-nucleus transcriptomics reveal TREM2-dependent and <lb/>TREM2-independent cellular responses in Alzheimer&apos;s disease. Nat. Med. (2020). <lb/>doi:10.1038/s41591-019-0695-9 <lb/>36. <lb/>Cohen-Cory, S., Kidane, A. H., Shirkey, N. J. &amp; Marshak, S. Brain-derived neurotrophic factor and <lb/>the development of structural neuronal connectivity. Developmental Neurobiology (2010). <lb/>doi:10.1002/dneu.20774 <lb/>37. <lb/>Bathina, S. &amp; Das, U. N. Brain-derived neurotrophic factor and its clinical Implications. Archives of <lb/>Medical Science (2015). doi:10.5114/aoms.2015.56342 <lb/>38. <lb/>Prinz, M., Rossum, D. Van &amp; Hanisch, U. K. Interleukin-2 as a Neuroregulatory Cytokine. <lb/>NeuroImmune Biology (2008). doi:10.1016/S1567-7443(07)10008-9 <lb/>39. <lb/>Sarder, M., Saito, H. &amp; Abe, K. Interleukin-2 promotes survival and neurite extension of cultured <lb/>neurons from fetal rat brain. Brain Res. (1993). doi:10.1016/0006-8993(93)91080-C <lb/>40. <lb/>Awatsuji, H., Furukawa, Y., Nakajima, M., Furukawa, S. &amp; Hayashi, K. Interleukin-2 as a <lb/>neurotrophic factor for supporting the survival of neurons cultured from various regions of fetal rat <lb/>brain. J. Neurosci. Res. (1993). doi:10.1002/jnr.490350310 <lb/>41. <lb/>Cantuti-Castelvetri, L. et al. Neuropilin-1 facilitates SARS-CoV-2 cell entry and provides a possible <lb/>pathway into the central nervous system. 1-36 (2020). doi:10.1101/2020.06.07.137802 <lb/>42. <lb/>Bryce, C. et al. Pathophysiology of SARS-CoV-2: targeting of endothelial cells renders a complex <lb/>disease with thrombotic microangiopathy and aberrant immune response. The Mount Sinai <lb/>COVID-19 autopsy experience. medRxiv (2020). <lb/>43. <lb/>He, L. et al. Pericyte-specific vascular expression of SARS-CoV-2 receptor ACE2 -implications <lb/>for microvascular inflammation and hypercoagulopathy in COVID-19 patients. bioRxiv (2020). <lb/>44. <lb/>Shingo, T. et al. Pregnancy-stimulated neurogenesis in the adult female forebrain mediated by <lb/>prolactin. Science (80-. ). (2003). doi:10.1126/science.1076647 <lb/>45. <lb/>Larsen, C. M. &amp; Grattan, D. R. Prolactin, neurogenesis, and maternal behaviors. Brain, Behavior, <lb/>and Immunity (2012). doi:10.1016/j.bbi.2011.07.233 <lb/>46. <lb/>Saudrais, E., Strazielle, N. &amp; Ghersi-Egea, J. F. Choroid plexus glutathione peroxidases are <lb/>instrumental in protecting the brain fluid environment from hydroperoxides during postnatal <lb/>development. Am. J. Physiol. -Cell Physiol. (2018). doi:10.1152/ajpcell.00094.2018 <lb/>47. <lb/>Saunders, N. R. et al. Influx mechanisms in the embryonic and adult rat choroid plexus: A <lb/>transcriptome study. Front. Neurosci. (2015). doi:10.3389/fnins.2015.00123 <lb/>48. <lb/>Hodge, R. D. et al. Conserved cell types with divergent features in human versus mouse cortex. <lb/>Nature (2019). doi:10.1038/s41586-019-1506-7 <lb/>49. <lb/>Bailey, C. C., Zhong, G., Huang, I. C. &amp; Farzan, M. IFITM-family proteins: The cell&apos;s first line of <lb/>antiviral defense. Annu. Rev. Virol. (2014). doi:10.1146/annurev-virology-031413-085537 <lb/>50. <lb/>Hachim, M. Y. et al. Interferon-Induced Transmembrane Protein (IFITM3) Is Upregulated Explicitly <lb/>in SARS-CoV-2 Infected Lung Epithelial Cells. Front. Immunol. (2020). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>doi:10.3389/fimmu.2020.01372 <lb/>51. <lb/>Daly, J. L. et al. Neuropilin-1 is a host factor for SARS-CoV-2 infection. bioRxiv (2020). <lb/>52. <lb/>Moutal, A. et al. SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein co-opts VEGF-A/Neuropilin-1 receptor signaling to <lb/>induce analgesia. Pain (2020). doi:10.1097/j.pain.0000000000002097 <lb/>53. <lb/>Ackermann, M. et al. Pulmonary vascular endothelialitis, thrombosis, and angiogenesis in Covid-<lb/>19. N. Engl. J. Med. (2020). doi:10.1056/NEJMoa2015432 <lb/>54. <lb/>Shaftel, S. S. et al. Sustained hippocampal IL-1β overexpression mediates chronic <lb/>neuroinflammation and ameliorates Alzheimer plaque pathology. J. Clin. Invest. (2007). <lb/>doi:10.1172/JCI31450 <lb/>55. <lb/>Shaftel, S. S. et al. Chronic interleukin-1β expression in mouse brain leads to leukocyte infiltration <lb/>and neutrophil-independent blood-brain barrier permeability without overt neurodegeneration. J. <lb/>Neurosci. (2007). doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1418-07.2007 <lb/>56. <lb/>Mahad, D. et al. Modulating CCR2 and CCL2 at the blood-brain barrier: Relevance for multiple <lb/>sclerosis pathogenesis. Brain (2006). doi:10.1093/brain/awh655 <lb/>57. <lb/>Guedes, J. R., Lao, T., Cardoso, A. L. &amp; El Khoury, J. Roles of microglial and monocyte <lb/>chemokines and their receptors in regulating Alzheimer&apos;s disease-associated amyloid-β and tau <lb/>pathologies. Frontiers in Neurology (2018). doi:10.3389/fneur.2018.00549 <lb/>58. <lb/>Cui, J. et al. Inflammation of the embryonic blood-cerebrospinal fluid barrier following maternal <lb/>immune activation. Submitt. to Dev Cell 1-12 (2020). doi:10.1016/j.devcel.2020.09.020 <lb/>59. <lb/>Baruch, K. et al. Aging-induced type I interferon response at the choroid plexus negatively affects <lb/>brain function. Science (80-. ). (2014). doi:10.1126/science.1252945 <lb/>60. <lb/>Baruch, K. et al. CNS-specific immunity at the choroid plexus shifts toward destructive Th2 <lb/>inflammation in brain aging. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. (2013). doi:10.1073/pnas.1211270110 <lb/>61. <lb/>Jin, S., Guerrero-juarez, C. F., Zhang, L., Chang, I. &amp; Myung, P. Inference and analysis of cell-cell <lb/>communication using CellChat. bioRxiv (2020). <lb/>62. <lb/>Efremova, M., Vento-Tormo, M., Teichmann, S. A. &amp; Vento-Tormo, R. CellPhoneDB: inferring <lb/>cell-cell communication from combined expression of multi-subunit ligand-receptor complexes. <lb/>Nat. Protoc. (2020). doi:10.1038/s41596-020-0292-x <lb/>63. <lb/>Thrupp, N. et al. Single-Nucleus RNA-Seq Is Not Suitable for Detection of Microglial Activation <lb/>Genes in Humans. Cell Rep. (2020). doi:10.1016/j.celrep.2020.108189 <lb/>64. <lb/>Trapnell, C. et al. The dynamics and regulators of cell fate decisions are revealed by <lb/>pseudotemporal ordering of single cells. Nat. Biotechnol. (2014). doi:10.1038/nbt.2859 <lb/>65. <lb/>Hammond, T. R. et al. Single-Cell RNA Sequencing of Microglia throughout the Mouse Lifespan <lb/>and in the Injured Brain Reveals Complex Cell-State Changes. Immunity (2019). <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.immuni.2018.11.004 <lb/>66. <lb/>Cochain, C. et al. Single-cell RNA-seq reveals the transcriptional landscape and heterogeneity of <lb/>aortic macrophages in murine atherosclerosis. Circ. Res. (2018). <lb/>doi:10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.117.312509 <lb/>67. <lb/>Bryan, K. J. et al. Expression of CD74 is increased in neurofibrillary tangles in Alzheimer&apos;s <lb/>disease. Mol. Neurodegener. (2008). doi:10.1186/1750-1326-3-13 <lb/>68. <lb/>Borghese, F. &amp; Clanchy, F. Il. CD74: An emerging opportunity as a therapeutic target in cancer <lb/>and autoimmune disease. Expert Opinion on Therapeutic Targets (2011). <lb/>doi:10.1517/14728222.2011.550879 <lb/>69. <lb/>Mathys, H. et al. Temporal Tracking of Microglia Activation in Neurodegeneration at Single-Cell <lb/>Resolution. Cell Rep. (2017). doi:10.1016/j.celrep.2017.09.039 <lb/>70. <lb/>Hopperton, K. E., Mohammad, D., Trépanier, M. O., Giuliano, V. &amp; Bazinet, R. P. Markers of <lb/>microglia in post-mortem brain samples from patients with Alzheimer&apos;s disease: A systematic <lb/>review. Molecular Psychiatry (2018). doi:10.1038/mp.2017.246 <lb/>71. <lb/>Nomura, K., Vilalta, A., Allendorf, D. H., Hornik, T. C. &amp; Brown, G. C. Activated Microglia <lb/>Desialylate and Phagocytose Cells via Neuraminidase, Galectin-3, and Mer Tyrosine Kinase. J. <lb/>Immunol. (2017). doi:10.4049/jimmunol.1502532 <lb/>72. <lb/>Healy, L. M. et al. MerTK Is a Functional Regulator of Myelin Phagocytosis by Human Myeloid <lb/>Cells. J. Immunol. (2016). doi:10.4049/jimmunol.1502562 <lb/>73. <lb/>Lew, D. S., Mazzoni, F. &amp; Finnemann, S. C. Microglia Inhibition Delays Retinal Degeneration Due <lb/>to MerTK Phagocytosis Receptor Deficiency. Front. Immunol. (2020). <lb/>doi:10.3389/fimmu.2020.01463 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>74. <lb/>Tondo, G., Perani, D. &amp; Comi, C. TAM receptor pathways at the crossroads of neuroinflammation <lb/>and neurodegeneration. Disease Markers (2019). doi:10.1155/2019/2387614 <lb/>75. <lb/>Kobayashi, K. et al. IRAK-M is a negative regulator of Toll-like receptor signaling. Cell (2002). <lb/>doi:10.1016/S0092-8674(02)00827-9 <lb/>76. <lb/>Lyu, C. et al. IRAK-M deficiency exacerbates ischemic neurovascular injuries in experimental <lb/>stroke mice. Front. Cell. Neurosci. (2018). doi:10.3389/fncel.2018.00504 <lb/>77. <lb/>Deczkowska, A. et al. Mef2C restrains microglial inflammatory response and is lost in brain ageing <lb/>in an IFN-I-dependent manner. Nat. Commun. (2017). doi:10.1038/s41467-017-00769-0 <lb/>78. <lb/>Hong, S. et al. Complement and microglia mediate early synapse loss in Alzheimer mouse <lb/>models. Science (80-. ). (2016). doi:10.1126/science.aad8373 <lb/>79. <lb/>Stevens, B. et al. The Classical Complement Cascade Mediates CNS Synapse Elimination. Cell <lb/>(2007). doi:10.1016/j.cell.2007.10.036 <lb/>80. <lb/>Lehrman, E. K. et al. CD47 Protects Synapses from Excess Microglia-Mediated Pruning during <lb/>Development. Neuron (2018). doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2018.09.017 <lb/>81. <lb/>Brown, G. C. &amp; Neher, J. J. Microglial phagocytosis of live neurons. Nat. Rev. Neurosci. (2014). <lb/>doi:10.1038/nrn3710 <lb/>82. <lb/>Sofroniew, M. V. Astrocyte barriers to neurotoxic inflammation. Nature Reviews Neuroscience <lb/>(2015). doi:10.1038/nrn3898 <lb/>83. <lb/>Owens, T., Bechmann, I. &amp; Engelhardt, B. Perivascular spaces and the two steps to <lb/>neuroinflammation. Journal of Neuropathology and Experimental Neurology (2008). <lb/>doi:10.1097/NEN.0b013e31818f9ca8 <lb/>84. <lb/>Allen, N. J. &amp; Eroglu, C. Cell Biology of Astrocyte-Synapse Interactions. Neuron (2017). <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2017.09.056 <lb/>85. <lb/>Chung, W. S., Allen, N. J. &amp; Eroglu, C. Astrocytes control synapse formation, function, and <lb/>elimination. Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Biol. (2015). doi:10.1101/cshperspect.a020370 <lb/>86. <lb/>Perea, G., Navarrete, M. &amp; Araque, A. Tripartite synapses: astrocytes process and control <lb/>synaptic information. Trends in Neurosciences (2009). doi:10.1016/j.tins.2009.05.001 <lb/>87. <lb/>Eng, L. F. &amp; Ghirnikar, R. S. GFAP and Astrogliosis. in Brain Pathology (1994). <lb/>doi:10.1111/j.1750-3639.1994.tb00838.x <lb/>88. <lb/>Llorens, F. et al. YKL-40 in the brain and cerebrospinal fluid of neurodegenerative dementias. Mol. <lb/>Neurodegener. (2017). doi:10.1186/s13024-017-0226-4 <lb/>89. <lb/>Matute-Blanch, C. et al. Chitinase 3-like 1 is neurotoxic in primary cultured neurons. Sci. Rep. <lb/>(2020). doi:10.1038/s41598-020-64093-2 <lb/>90. <lb/>Moreno-Rodriguez, M., Perez, S. E., Nadeem, M., Malek-Ahmadi, M. &amp; Mufson, E. J. Frontal <lb/>cortex chitinase and pentraxin neuroinflammatory alterations during the progression of Alzheimer&apos;s <lb/>disease. J. Neuroinflammation (2020). doi:10.1186/s12974-020-1723-x <lb/>91. <lb/>Kim, K. et al. Role of Excitatory Amino Acid Transporter-2 (EAAT2) and glutamate in <lb/>neurodegeneration: Opportunities for developing novel therapeutics. Journal of Cellular Physiology <lb/>(2011). doi:10.1002/jcp.22609 <lb/>92. <lb/>Su, Z. zhong et al. Insights into glutamate transport regulation in human astrocytes: Cloning of the <lb/>promoter for excitatory amino acid transporter 2 (EAAT2). Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. (2003). <lb/>doi:10.1073/pnas.0136555100 <lb/>93. <lb/>Maragakis, N. J., Dykes-Hoberg, M. &amp; Rothstein, J. D. Altered Expression of the Glutamate <lb/>Transporter EAAT2b in Neurological Disease. Ann. Neurol. (2004). doi:10.1002/ana.20003 <lb/>94. <lb/>Lewerenz, J. &amp; Maher, P. Chronic glutamate toxicity in neurodegenerative diseases-What is the <lb/>evidence? Frontiers in Neuroscience (2015). doi:10.3389/fnins.2015.00469 <lb/>95. <lb/>Dong, X. X., Wang, Y. &amp; Qin, Z. H. Molecular mechanisms of excitotoxicity and their relevance to <lb/>pathogenesis of neurodegenerative diseases. Acta Pharmacologica Sinica (2009). <lb/>doi:10.1038/aps.2009.24 <lb/>96. <lb/>Kullmann, D. M. &amp; Asztely, F. Extrasynaptic glutamate spillover in the hippocampus: Evidence and <lb/>implications. Trends Neurosci. (1998). doi:10.1016/S0166-2236(97)01150-8 <lb/>97. <lb/>Diamond, J. S. A broad view of glutamate spillover. Nature Neuroscience (2002). <lb/>doi:10.1038/nn0402-291 <lb/>98. <lb/>Rose, C. R. et al. Astroglial glutamate signaling and uptake in the hippocampus. Frontiers in <lb/>Molecular Neuroscience (2018). doi:10.3389/fnmol.2017.00451 <lb/>99. <lb/>Filosa, A. et al. Neuron-glia communication via EphA4/ephrin-A3 modulates LTP through glial <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>glutamate transport. Nat. Neurosci. (2009). doi:10.1038/nn.2394 <lb/>100. Robinson, M. B. &amp; Jackson, J. G. Astroglial glutamate transporters coordinate excitatory signaling <lb/>and brain energetics. Neurochemistry International (2016). doi:10.1016/j.neuint.2016.03.014 <lb/>101. Carmona, M. A., Murai, K. K., Wang, L., Roberts, A. J. &amp; Pasqualea, E. B. Glial ephrin-A3 <lb/>regulates hippocampal dendritic spine morphology and glutamate transport. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. <lb/>U. S. A. (2009). doi:10.1073/pnas.0903328106 <lb/>102. Ohno, Y., Kinboshi, M. &amp; Shimizu, S. Inwardly rectifying potassium channel kir4.1 as a novel <lb/>modulator of BDNF expression in astrocytes. International Journal of Molecular Sciences (2018). <lb/>doi:10.3390/ijms19113313 <lb/>103. Ramakrishnan, N. A., Drescher, M. J. &amp; Drescher, D. G. The SNARE complex in neuronal and <lb/>sensory cells. Molecular and Cellular Neuroscience (2012). doi:10.1016/j.mcn.2012.03.009 <lb/>104. Südhof, T. C. &amp; Malenka, R. C. Understanding Synapses: Past, Present, and Future. Neuron <lb/>(2008). doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2008.10.011 <lb/>105. Davison, A. Basic Neurochemistry: Molecular, Cellular, and Medical Aspects. J. Neurol. <lb/>Neurosurg. Psychiatry (1989). doi:10.1136/jnnp.52.8.1021-a <lb/>106. Hess, E. J., Jinnah, H. A., Kozak, C. A. &amp; Wilson, M. C. Spontaneous locomotor hyperactivity in a <lb/>mouse mutant with a deletion including the Snap gene on chromosome 2. J. Neurosci. (1992). <lb/>doi:10.1523/jneurosci.12-07-02865.1992 <lb/>107. Thompson, P. M., Sower, A. C. &amp; Perrone-Bizzozero, N. I. Altered levels of the synaptosomal <lb/>associated protein SNAP-25 in schizophrenia. Biol. Psychiatry (1998). doi:10.1016/S0006-<lb/>3223(97)00204-7 <lb/>108. Gabriel, S. M. et al. Increased concentrations of presynaptic proteins in the cingulate cortex of <lb/>subjects with schizophrenia. Arch. Gen. Psychiatry (1997). <lb/>doi:10.1001/archpsyc.1997.01830180077010 <lb/>109. Berchtold, N. C. et al. Synaptic genes are extensively downregulated across multiple brain regions <lb/>in normal human aging and Alzheimer&apos;s disease. Neurobiol. Aging (2013). <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2012.11.024 <lb/>110. Vardar, G. et al. Distinct functions of syntaxin-1 in neuronal maintenance, synaptic vesicle <lb/>docking, and fusion in mouse neurons. J. Neurosci. (2016). doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1314-<lb/>16.2016 <lb/>111. Arancillo, M. et al. Titration of Syntaxin1 in mammalian synapses reveals multiple roles in vesicle <lb/>docking, priming, and release probability. J. Neurosci. (2013). doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0187-<lb/>13.2013 <lb/>112. Yang, H. et al. Brain-Specific SNAP-25 Deletion Leads to Elevated Extracellular Glutamate Level <lb/>and Schizophrenia-Like Behavior in Mice. Neural Plast. (2017). doi:10.1155/2017/4526417 <lb/>113. Sharma, M. et al. CSPα knockout causes neurodegeneration by impairing SNAP-25 function. <lb/>EMBO J. (2012). doi:10.1038/emboj.2011.467 <lb/>114. Vuong, C. K. et al. Rbfox1 Regulates Synaptic Transmission through the Inhibitory Neuron-<lb/>Specific vSNARE Vamp1. Neuron (2018). doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2018.03.008 <lb/>115. Schoch, S. et al. SNARE function analyzed in synaptobrevin/VAMP knockout mice. Science (80-. <lb/>). (2001). doi:10.1126/science.1064335 <lb/>116. Blasi, J. et al. Inhibition of neurotransmitter release by clostridial neurotoxins correlates with <lb/>specific proteolysis of synaptosomal proteins. J. Physiol. -Paris (1994). doi:10.1016/0928-<lb/>4257(94)90086-8 <lb/>117. Wang, D. et al. Syntaxin requirement for Ca2+-triggered exocytosis in neurons and endocrine cells <lb/>demonstrated with an engineered neurotoxin. Biochemistry (2011). doi:10.1021/bi200290p <lb/>118. Washbourne, P. et al. Genetic ablation of the t-SNARE SNAP-25 distinguishes mechanisms of <lb/>neuroexocytosis. Nat. Neurosci. (2002). doi:10.1038/nn783 <lb/>119. Feldmeyer, D. Excitatory neuronal connectivity in the barrel cortex. Front. Neuroanat. (2012). <lb/>doi:10.3389/fnana.2012.00024 <lb/>120. Petersen, C. C. H. &amp; Crochet, S. Synaptic Computation and Sensory Processing in Neocortical <lb/>Layer 2/3. Neuron (2013). doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2013.03.020 <lb/>121. Marshall, M. How COVID-19 can damage the brain. Nature (2020). doi:10.1038/d41586-020-<lb/>02599-5 <lb/>122. Jäkel, S. et al. Altered human oligodendrocyte heterogeneity in multiple sclerosis. Nature (2019). <lb/>doi:10.1038/s41586-019-0903-2 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>123. Al-Dalahmah, O. et al. Single-nucleus RNA-seq identifies Huntington disease astrocyte states. <lb/>Acta Neuropathol. Commun. (2020). doi:10.1186/s40478-020-0880-6 <lb/>124. Maurano, M. T. et al. Systematic localization of common disease-associated variation in regulatory <lb/>DNA. Science (80-. ). (2012). doi:10.1126/science.1222794 <lb/>125. Nott, A. et al. Brain cell type-specific enhancer-promoter interactome maps and disease-risk <lb/>association. Science (80-. ). (2019). doi:10.1126/science.aay0793 <lb/>126. Buniello, A. et al. The NHGRI-EBI GWAS Catalog of published genome-wide association studies, <lb/>targeted arrays and summary statistics 2019. Nucleic Acids Res. (2019). doi:10.1093/nar/gky1120 <lb/>127. Wang, D. et al. Comprehensive functional genomic resource and integrative model for the human <lb/>brain. Science (80-. ). (2018). doi:10.1126/science.aat8464 <lb/>128. Lewis, D. A. The chandelier neuron in schizophrenia. Dev. Neurobiol. (2011). <lb/>doi:10.1002/dneu.20825 <lb/>129. Pierri, J. N., Volk, C. L. E., Auh, S., Sampson, A. &amp; Lewis, D. A. Decreased somal size of deep <lb/>layer 3 pyramidal neurons in the prefrontal cortex of subjects with schizophrenia. Arch. Gen. <lb/>Psychiatry (2001). doi:10.1001/archpsyc.58.5.466 <lb/>130. Garey, L. When cortical development goes wrong: Schizophrenia as a neurodevelopmental <lb/>disease of microcircuits. J. Anat. (2010). doi:10.1111/j.1469-7580.2010.01231.x <lb/>131. Shrestha, P., Mousa, A. &amp; Heintz, N. Layer 2/3 pyramidal cells in the medial prefrontal cortex <lb/>moderate stress induced depressive behaviors. Elife (2015). doi:10.7554/eLife.08752 <lb/>132. Granato, A. &amp; De Giorgio, A. Alterations of neocortical pyramidal neurons: Turning points in the <lb/>genesis of mental retardation. Frontiers in Pediatrics (2014). doi:10.3389/fped.2014.00086 <lb/>133. Zhou, X. et al. Astrocyte, a promising target for mood disorder interventions. Frontiers in Molecular <lb/>Neuroscience (2019). doi:10.3389/fnmol.2019.00136 <lb/>134. Rajkowska, G. &amp; Stockmeier, C. Astrocyte Pathology in Major Depressive Disorder: Insights from <lb/>Human Postmortem Brain Tissue. Curr. Drug Targets (2013). <lb/>doi:10.2174/13894501113149990156 <lb/>135. Tarasov, V. V. et al. Alterations of astrocytes in the context of schizophrenic dementia. Frontiers in <lb/>Pharmacology (2020). doi:10.3389/fphar.2019.01612 <lb/>136. Swain, A., Bhagat, H., Sahni, N. &amp; Salunke, P. Mechanical ventilation in neurological and <lb/>neurosurgical patients. Neurol. India (2016). doi:10.4103/0028-3886.181585 <lb/>137. Hosseini, S. et al. Long-term neuroinflammation induced by influenza a virus infection and the <lb/>impact on hippocampal neuron morphology and function. J. Neurosci. (2018). <lb/>doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1740-17.2018 <lb/>138. Casals, J., Elizan, T. S. &amp; Yahr, M. D. Postencephalitic parkinsonism -A review. Journal of Neural <lb/>Transmission (1998). doi:10.1007/s007020050086 <lb/>139. Readhead, B. et al. Multiscale Analysis of Independent Alzheimer&apos;s Cohorts Finds Disruption of <lb/>Molecular, Genetic, and Clinical Networks by Human Herpesvirus. Neuron (2018). <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2018.05.023 <lb/>140. Deleidi, M. &amp; Isacson, O. Viral and inflammatory triggers of neurodegenerative diseases. Science <lb/>Translational Medicine (2012). doi:10.1126/scitranslmed.3003492 <lb/>141. Yousef, H. et al. Aged blood impairs hippocampal neural precursor activity and activates microglia <lb/>via brain endothelial cell VCAM1. Nat. Med. (2019). doi:10.1038/s41591-019-0440-4 <lb/>142. Chen, M. B. et al. Brain Endothelial Cells Are Exquisite Sensors of Age-Related Circulatory Cues. <lb/>Cell Rep. (2020). doi:10.1016/j.celrep.2020.03.012 <lb/>143. Petersen, M. A., Ryu, J. K. &amp; Akassoglou, K. Fibrinogen in neurological diseases: Mechanisms, <lb/>imaging and therapeutics. Nature Reviews Neuroscience (2018). doi:10.1038/nrn.2018.13 <lb/>144. Yang, A. C. et al. Physiological blood-brain transport is impaired with age by a shift in <lb/>transcytosis. Nature (2020). doi:10.1038/s41586-020-2453-z <lb/>145. Garrigues, E. et al. Post-discharge persistent symptoms and health-related quality of life after <lb/>hospitalization for COVID-19. Journal of Infection (2020). doi:10.1016/j.jinf.2020.08.029 <lb/>146. Kaseda, E. T. &amp; Levine, A. J. Post-traumatic stress disorder: a differential diagnostic consideration <lb/>for COVID-19 survivors. Clinical Neuropsychologist (2020). doi:10.1080/13854046.2020.1811894 <lb/>147. Vallejo-Illarramendi, A., Torres-Ramos, M., Melone, M., Conti, F. &amp; Matute, C. Clozapine reduces <lb/>GLT-1 expression and glutamate uptake in astrocyte cultures. Glia (2005). doi:10.1002/glia.20172 <lb/>148. Swiech, L. et al. In vivo interrogation of gene function in the mammalian brain using CRISPR-<lb/>Cas9. Nat. Biotechnol. (2015). doi:10.1038/nbt.3055 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>149. Corces, M. R. et al. An improved ATAC-seq protocol reduces background and enables <lb/>interrogation of frozen tissues. Nat. Methods (2017). doi:10.1038/nmeth.4396 <lb/>150. McInnes, L., Healy, J., Saul, N. &amp; Großberger, L. UMAP: Uniform Manifold Approximation and <lb/>Projection. J. Open Source Softw. (2018). doi:10.21105/joss.00861 <lb/>151. Young, M. &amp; Behjati, S. SoupX removes ambient RNA contamination from droplet based single-<lb/>cell RNA sequencing data. bioRxiv (2018). doi:10.1101/303727 <lb/>152. Satija, R., Farrell, J. A., Gennert, D., Schier, A. F. &amp; Regev, A. Spatial reconstruction of single-cell <lb/>gene expression data. Nat. Biotechnol. (2015). doi:10.1038/nbt.3192 <lb/>153. McGinnis, C. S., Murrow, L. M. &amp; Gartner, Z. J. DoubletFinder: Doublet Detection in Single-Cell <lb/>RNA Sequencing Data Using Artificial Nearest Neighbors. Cell Syst. (2019). <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.cels.2019.03.003 <lb/>154. Finak, G. et al. MAST: A flexible statistical framework for assessing transcriptional changes and <lb/>characterizing heterogeneity in single-cell RNA sequencing data. Genome Biol. (2015). <lb/>doi:10.1186/s13059-015-0844-5 <lb/>155. Chen, E. Y. et al. Enrichr: Interactive and collaborative HTML5 gene list enrichment analysis tool. <lb/>BMC Bioinformatics (2013). doi:10.1186/1471-2105-14-128 <lb/>156. Zhou, Y. et al. Metascape provides a biologist-oriented resource for the analysis of systems-level <lb/>datasets. Nat. Commun. (2019). doi:10.1038/s41467-019-09234-6 <lb/>157. Gerstner, N. et al. GeneTrail 3: advanced high-throughput enrichment analysis. Nucleic Acids Res. <lb/>(2020). doi:10.1093/nar/gkaa306 <lb/>158. Bost, P. et al. Host-Viral Infection Maps Reveal Signatures of Severe COVID-19 Patients. Cell <lb/>(2020). doi:10.1016/j.cell.2020.05.006 <lb/>159. Kim, D., Song, L., Breitwieser, F. P. &amp; Salzberg, S. L. Centrifuge: Rapid and sensitive <lb/>classification of metagenomic sequences. Genome Res. (2016). doi:10.1101/gr.210641.116 <lb/>160. Stano, M., Beke, G. &amp; Klucar, L. ViruSITE -Integrated database for viral genomics. Database <lb/>(2016). doi:10.1093/database/baw162 <lb/>161. Wauters, E. et al. Discriminating Mild from Critical COVID-19 by Innate and Adaptive Immune <lb/>Single-cell Profiling of Bronchoalveolar Lavages. (2020). doi:10.1101/2020.07.09.196519 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted October 22, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.10.22.349415 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint </note>


	</text>
</tei>
