<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>Mapping hydrologic alteration and <lb/>ecological consequences in stream <lb/>reaches of the conterminous United <lb/>States <lb/>Ryan a. McManamay 1 ✉ , Rob George 2 , Ryan R. Morrison 3 &amp; Benjamin L. Ruddell 2 <lb/>Environmental flows are critical for balancing societal water needs with that of riverine ecosystems; <lb/>however, data limitations often hinder the development of predictive relationships between <lb/>anthropogenic modifications to streamflow regimes and ecological responses -these relationships <lb/>are the basis for setting regional water policy standards for rivers. Herein, we present and describe a <lb/>comprehensive dataset of modeled hydrologic alteration and consequences for native fish biodiversity, <lb/>both mapped at the stream-reach resolution for the conterminous U.S. Using empirical observations <lb/>of reference conditions and anthropogenically altered streamflow at over 7000 stream gauges, we <lb/>developed a predictive model of hydrologic alteration, which was extended to &gt;2.6 million stream <lb/>reaches. We then used a previous nationwide assessment of ecological responses to hydrologic <lb/>alteration to predict fish biodiversity loss in stream reaches resulting from streamflow modification. <lb/>Validation efforts suggested hydrologic alteration models had satisfactory performance, whereas <lb/>modeled ecological responses were susceptible to compounded errors. The dataset could ameliorate <lb/>regional data deficits for setting environmental flow standards while providing tools for prioritizing <lb/>streamflow protection or restoration. <lb/></front>

			<body>Background &amp; Summary <lb/>Freshwater ecosystems are facing a global biodiversity crisis 1 . Despite only 0.01% of the Earth&apos;s surface water <lb/>occurring as freshwater ecosystems, these systems harbor 7% of the world&apos;s described species and one third of all <lb/>vertebrates 2,3 . Yet these same ecosystems are facing alarming rates of habitat and biodiversity loss. Even among <lb/>freshwater ecosystems, rivers and streams are considered numerically rare despite providing disproportionate <lb/>services to society, ultimately leading to their over-exploitation 4 . Much of the exploitation of lotic systems is <lb/>directly related to the manipulation of natural streaflow variability. For instance, roughly 50% of rivers and <lb/>streams across the world are hydrologically altered from their natural state 5,6 , with as much as 80% of streams <lb/>in Canada 7 and 80% of streams in the conterminous US 8 displaying signs of alteration in streamflow regimes. <lb/>By 2050, climate change is expected to have altered streamflow regimes in as much as 80% of the global terres-<lb/>trial land surface aside from that already altered from human infrastructures 9,10 -only exacerbating decades of <lb/>declines in freshwater fauna populations 11 . The monumental challenge faced by modern society is &quot;bending the <lb/>curve&quot; of freshwater biodiversity loss, all while addressing climate change mitigation and human population <lb/>growth 1 . <lb/>In their Emergency Recovery Plan for dampening or reversing declines in freshwater biodiversity, Tickner <lb/>et al. 1 lay out several major actions, the first being the widespread implementation of environmental flows, i.e., <lb/>the quantity and timing of streamflow volumes required to sustain the ecological integrity of river systems. With <lb/>competing demands for limited water quantities, the inevitable question that follows is &quot;How much water do <lb/>river [ecosystems] need?&quot; 12,13 . Prescribing environmental flows for rivers requires understanding dependen-<lb/>cies or linkages between essential stream flow components (e.g., magnitude, duration, frequency of flows) and <lb/>ecological processes. Even more critical is understanding ecological responses to human-induced alterations <lb/></body>

			<front>1 <lb/>Department of Environmental Science, Baylor University, Waco, TX, 76798, USA. 2 School of informatics, computing <lb/>and Cyber Systems, Northern Arizona University, Flagstaff, AZ, 86011, USA. 3 Department of civil and environmental <lb/>Engineering, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO, 80523, USA. ✉ e-mail: Ryan_McManamay@baylor.edu <lb/>Data DeScRiptoR <lb/>opeN <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>to naturally variant streamflow regimes -generally termed &quot;flow-ecology relationships&quot; 14 . At a regional level, <lb/>flow-ecology relationships, especially thresholds or tipping points of streamflow alteration, can be used as gen-<lb/>eral guidelines for environmental flow implementation and preventatives for over-extraction -this general pro-<lb/>cess has been formalized as the Ecological Limits of Hydrologic Alteration (ELOHA) framework 15 . The ELOHA <lb/>framework has been implemented in at least 20 US states and several countries 16 ; however, a practical demand of <lb/>developing empirical flow-ecology relationships include identifying datasets with sufficient empirical observa-<lb/>tions. A commonly reported shortcoming of regional ELOHA studies is the limited availability of information to <lb/>support the development of flow-ecology relationships, either from the scientific literature 14 or from pre-existing <lb/>inventories of biological surveys and hydrologic records 17 . <lb/>Imposing restrictive criteria on observation datasets dramatically reduces sample sizes and generalizations <lb/>that can be drawn from the data. For example, in a nationwide study evaluating flow-ecology relationships, only <lb/>237 (3%) of 7,000 US Geological Survey gaging locations had co-occurring macroinvertebrate or fish sampling <lb/>surveys 8 . One solution to ameliorate the data-shortage issue is to increase the volume and density of systematic <lb/>biological surveys; however, US federal and state-funded systematic biological surveys are already considered <lb/>regionally comprehensive (&gt;1.5 million sampling events) yet provide high-quality survey data for only 13% <lb/>of US streams 18 . Even marginal increases in the percentage of surveyed streams would come at great cost to <lb/>resources. A more economical solution is to model expected hydrologic and ecological conditions in ungauged <lb/>stream reaches to fully leverage the wealth of existing hydrologic and biological data 19 . For instance, George et <lb/>al. 17 used modeled estimates of hydrologic conditions in streams to yield a nationwide flow-ecology dataset of <lb/>6,452 observations -a value almost 9 times the observations reported in a comparable study relying on overlap-<lb/>ping biological surveys and hydrological data 20 . Obviously, a limitation of such an approach is the uncertainty <lb/>of modeled versus observed hydrologic conditions and subsequent error propagation that arises in developing <lb/>flow-ecology relationships 19 . <lb/>Given the importance of ensuring region-wide extensions of the ELOHA framework, especially in <lb/>data-limited regions, a comprehensive dataset of modeled hydrologic conditions or hydrologic alteration val-<lb/>ues and ecological consequences, mapped to the stream-reach resolution, would be valuable to the research <lb/>and practitioner community. Not only could such a dataset address limitations of contemporary flow-ecology <lb/>relationship development, but it expedites the entire 4-step scientific components embodied within the ELOHA <lb/>process and provides substantial time-savings for researchers and managers. Herein, we present a dataset of <lb/>modeled hydrologic (streamflow) alteration, summarized in 43 metrics, and resulting estimates of losses in fish <lb/>species richness for 2.6 million stream reaches within the conterminous US. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Overview of hydrologic and ecological mapping protocol. Mapping hydrologic and ecological alter-<lb/>ation at the stream reach level followed a 7-step process that builds upon several previously published methods <lb/>(Fig. 1). The steps include: (1) compiling a nationwide dataset of streamflow gauges from the US Geological <lb/>Survey (USGS) and distinguishing reference and non-reference gages and associated records 21-23 , (2) assembling <lb/>stream flow records and calculating hydrologic indices 23 , (3) quantifying hydrologic alteration for stream gages 22 , <lb/>(4) developing models to predict hydrologic alteration from human disturbance variables 24 , (5) using models to <lb/>Reference <lb/>Non-Reference <lb/>Hydrologic <lb/>alteration <lb/>Hydrologic <lb/>metric <lb/>Observed <lb/>Expected <lb/>Hydrologic <lb/>Alteration <lb/>Models <lb/>Human <lb/>Infrastructures <lb/>Land Cover <lb/>Change <lb/>Mapping Hydrologic Alteration <lb/>in Stream Reaches <lb/>Fish <lb/>Richness <lb/>Residual <lb/>Fish community <lb/>sampling <lb/>Fish <lb/>Richness <lb/>Drainage <lb/>Area <lb/>Hydrologic <lb/>Alteration <lb/>Threshold <lb/>Hydrologic <lb/>alteration <lb/>Fish Richness <lb/>Residuals <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>0 <lb/>Step 1 <lb/>Step 2 <lb/>Step 3 <lb/>Step 4 <lb/>Step 6 <lb/>Step 5 <lb/>Step 7 <lb/>Fish Richness <lb/>Response <lb/>Fig. 1 Overview of the 7-step approach used to map hydrologic alteration and ecological consequences in <lb/>stream reaches of the conterminous US. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>extrapolate hydrologic alteration to ungauged stream reaches 24 , (6) developing empirical models of fish species <lb/>richness responses to hydrologic alteration 17 , and (7) mapping fish richness responses to ungauged stream reaches <lb/>based on modeled estimates of hydrologic alteration. Methodological details are provided in each of the publi-<lb/>cations cited above; however, an overview of the steps is provided here. We elaborate more fully on the detailed <lb/>methodology starting at step 3, as this reflects more of the focus of the technical validation of the dataset (Fig. 1). <lb/>Step 1 -Compiling a nationwide streamflow dataset. We assembled streamflow information for 7,088 USGS <lb/>stream gages with at least 15 years of daily discharge data as of 2010. We only included gages with at least 15 <lb/>years of complete annual records (i.e., those with &lt;= 30 days of missing daily data). The influence of climate <lb/>variability on hydrologic statistic values dampens as periods of records increase, and typically, at least 15 years <lb/>of record are required to stabilize variation in indices, at least to acceptable levels for spatial analyses 25 . However, <lb/>a noted limitation of our analysis is that we did not formally control for climate variation in the calculation of <lb/>hydrologic statistics from stream records varying in length and duration, as compared to Eng et al. 26 . However, <lb/>Eng et al. 26 found that climate variability had minimal influence on hydrologic alteration at stream gages relative <lb/>to human land and water management. <lb/>Gages were partitioned into reference (n = 2,249) and non-reference (n = 4,839) condition based on geo-<lb/>graphical evaluations of human disturbance regimes in basins upstream of each gage, reviews of USGS water <lb/>reports, and visually inspecting flow duration curves 21,22 . For ease of terminology, we use the term &quot;reference&quot; to <lb/>indicate the &quot;least disturbance&quot; condition for a region, as defined by Stoddard et al. 27 . For streams currently reg-<lb/>ulated by dams and with at least 15-yr records extending prior to dam regulation (n = 250), streamflow records <lb/>were partitioned into pre-and post-dam construction time periods 22 . Except for pre-dam construction records, <lb/>periods of record for reference conditions displayed considerable temporal overlap (at least 50% of overlap in <lb/>records) 23 , as did periods of record for non-reference conditions 22 . <lb/>Step 2-Assembling streamflow records and calculating hydrologic statistics. Daily streamflow records were <lb/>obtained from the USGS National Water Information System (NWIS) website (https://waterdata.usgs.gov/ <lb/>nwis). For reference streams, the entire period of record was used for calculating hydrologic statistics, whereas <lb/>for non-reference gages, only periods overlapping with contemporary human disturbance regimes were used <lb/>(1980-2010) due to the temporal limitations of anthropogenic disturbance variables used to predict hydro-<lb/>logic alteration. The National Hydrologic Assessment Tool (www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5387735ee-<lb/>4b0aa26cd7b5461) was used to calculate 110 hydrologic statistics summarizing the magnitude, frequency, <lb/>duration, timing, and rate of change in flow for all reference and non-reference stream flow records 23 . <lb/>Step 3-Calculating hydrologic alteration indices at gages. Calculating hydrologic alteration at non-reference <lb/>gages first required estimating reference or natural hydrologic conditions as a baseline from which the degree of <lb/>alteration could be assessed. Of the 110 hydrologic statistics above, we selected 41 indices that adequately rep-<lb/>resent the multi-dimensional nature of regional variation in hydrologic across the US 23 and have been used in <lb/>previous assessments of hydrologic alteration 22 (Table 1). These 41 indices include the Indicators of Hydrologic <lb/>Alteration 12 , a series of non-redundant metrics representing the predominant variation embodied by almost 200 <lb/>hydrologic variables 28 . Since the 41 indices are univariate summaries of hydrologic conditions, two additional <lb/>indices, a hydrologic alteration index and a seasonality alteration index, were calculated to represent multivar-<lb/>iate impacts to overall variation among hydrologic metrics and the distribution of monthly flows, respectively <lb/>(more details provided in Step 3 expanded). <lb/>Generally, reference condition values of hydrologic indices were estimated for non-reference gages using ran-<lb/>dom forest statistical models constructed from reference gauges or gauges with pre-dam hydrologic records 22 . <lb/>Random forest model performance was high with a median variance explained of 91% among all hydrologic <lb/>indices and median normalized RMSE of 0.513 22 (normalized RMSE by range of values). In cases where statis-<lb/>tical models were unreliable (i.e., indices depicting timing of low and high flows), non-reference stream gages <lb/>were assigned to a hydrologic class representing a range of reference condition index values 22 . In these situa-<lb/>tions, the 90 th percent confidence interval of hydrologic index values represented by all reference gauges within <lb/>a hydrologic class was used to represent the reference flow condition. Observed hydrologic indices were then <lb/>compared to estimated reference conditions to calculate hydrologic alteration indices, characterizing the degree <lb/>of changes in stream flow due to human influence (see next section). <lb/>Step 4 and 5 -Predicting hydrologic alteration and mapping to U.S. streams. Random forest models were con-<lb/>structed to predict each hydrologic alteration index at stream gages using an ensemble of human disturbance <lb/>variables summarized in the upstream basins contributing to each gage. Predictor variables included landcover, <lb/>dam storage, infrastructure, and water withdrawals (Supplementary Table 1). Random forest models were devel-<lb/>oped for the entire US and for each of 29 ecohydrologic regions (Fig. 2), which represent unique combinations <lb/>of Freshwater Ecoregions 29 and two-digit hydrologic unit codes (i.e., major river basins). The same human dis-<lb/>turbance variables were compiled in the networks upstream of all NHDplus V1 stream reaches (https://nhd-<lb/>plus.com/NHDPlus/NHDPlusV1_home.php) and models were then applied to predict hydrologic alteration <lb/>in those reaches. Values were then extended to NHDplus V2 stream reaches (https://www.epa.gov/waterdata/ <lb/>get-nhdplus-national-hydrography-dataset-plus-data) using crosswalk tables. <lb/>Step 6 and 7 -Predicting and mapping ecological responses to hydrologic alteration in stream <lb/>reaches. Comprehensive maps of hydrologic alteration in stream reaches provide a foundation for subsequent <lb/>modeling efforts, such as evaluating ecological responses to altered streamflow. Once these flow-ecology rela-<lb/>tionships are developed for multiple regions, ecological conditions, similar to hydrologic conditions, can be <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>extrapolated to stream reaches. Recently, George et al. 17 used the same hydrologic alteration indices reported <lb/>in this study to develop regionally explicit nationwide flow-alteration-ecological-response relationships. These <lb/>models were used to extrapolate ecological conditions (i.e., losses in fish species richness) to the stream reach <lb/>resolution based on modeled hydrologic alteration values. <lb/>Step 3 expanded: Calculating hydrologic alteration indices for stream gages. We elaborate on the <lb/>above methodology, starting here with step 3. We used two approaches for calculating hydrologic alteration for <lb/>non-reference stream gages 24 . For the majority of indices (Table 1), we calculated hydrologic alteration as propor-<lb/>tional changes of observed (O) index values (i.e., human-altered conditions), versus expected (E) index values (i.e., <lb/>reference conditions) in the equation: (O -E)/E 30 . Hence, indices ranged from −1 to values» 1. Performance, as <lb/>measured by area-under-the-curve (AUC), of preliminary models using these raw values were lower than desired <lb/>(AUC &lt; 0.7). Hence, following Eng et al. 30 , we scaled values from 0 to 1 to represent a likelihood of hydrologic <lb/>alteration in the following fashion. For indices &lt; = 1, we used the absolute value of (O -E)/E, whereas indices &gt;1 <lb/>were assigned maximum values of 1. For reference gages, hydrologic alteration values were set to 0 for each metric. <lb/>While the above measures are informative for individual flow components, indices that summarize the <lb/>multi-dimensional nature of stream flow alterations provide convenient single measures of alteration. We calcu-<lb/>lated a seasonality index, analogous to Zaerpour et al. 7 , representing shifts in the monthly flow magnitudes, as <lb/>cumulative differences in observed (O) and expected (E) values for all mean monthly flows using the following <lb/>equation: <lb/>O <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>(1) <lb/>m i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>12 <lb/>∑ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>   <lb/>− <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>= <lb/>Index <lb/>Definition <lb/>Magnitude of flow events <lb/>MA1 <lb/>Mean Daily Flow <lb/>MA2 <lb/>Median Daily flow <lb/>MA3 <lb/>Variability in daily flows <lb/>MA12-23 <lb/>Mean monthly flow for all months, January (12) through December (23) <lb/>MA41 <lb/>Mean annual runoff <lb/>ML17 <lb/>Baseflow 1. Seven-day minimum flow divided by mean annual daily flows averaged across all years. <lb/>ML19 <lb/>Baseflow 2. Mean of ratio of the lowest annual daily flow to the mean annual daily flow times 100 averaged <lb/>across all years <lb/>MH20 <lb/>Mean annual maximum flows divided by catchment area <lb/>Duration of flow events <lb/>DL1-5 <lb/>Magnitude of minimum annual flow for 1-/3-/7-/30-/90-day means <lb/>DL16 <lb/>Low flow pulse duration <lb/>DL18 <lb/>Number of zero-flow days <lb/>DH1-5 <lb/>Annual maxima of 1-/3-/7-/30-/90-day means of daily discharge <lb/>DH15 <lb/>High flow pulse duration <lb/>Frequency of flow events <lb/>FL1 <lb/>Low flow pulse count. Number of annual occurrences during which the magnitude of flow remains below a <lb/>lower threshold. <lb/>FH1 <lb/>High flood pulse count. See FL1. <lb/>FH6 <lb/>Flood frequency. Mean number of high flow events per year using 3 times median annual flow <lb/>FH7 <lb/>Flood frequency. Mean number of high flow events per year using 7 times median annual flow <lb/>Timing of Flow Events <lb/>TA1 <lb/>Constancy <lb/>TA2 <lb/>Predictability of flow <lb/>Rate of Change of flow events <lb/>RA1 <lb/>Rise rate. Mean rate of positive changes in flow from one day to the next. <lb/>RA3 <lb/>Fall Rate. Mean rate of negative changes in flow from one day to next. <lb/>RA8 <lb/>Reversals. Number of positive and negative changes in water conditions from one day to the next. <lb/>Cumulative measures <lb/>HAI <lb/>Hydrologic Alteration Index. A measure of cumulative hydrologic change of the most important dimensions <lb/>of the flow regime. See Methods. <lb/>Seasonality <lb/>Seasonality alteration. A cumulative measure of departures in mean monthly flows for all months. See <lb/>Methods. <lb/>Table 1. Hydrologic indices used in the study and their description. Table taken directly from George et al. 17 . <lb/>With the exception of cumulative indices, index codes are taken from Olden et al. 28 . <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>As a second multidimensional measure, we calculated a cumulative hydrologic alteration index (HAI), which <lb/>evaluates the degree of separation between the flow regime of non-reference streams&apos; and that of reference <lb/>streams within the same hydrologic class. Hydrologic classes represent groups of streams that share similar <lb/>natural hydrologic patterns. McManamay et al. 23 developed a hydrologic classification of reference streams in <lb/>the US, and subsequently, non-reference gages were assigned to those hydrologic classes using models 22 . To <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>Daily CV Flow (MA3) <lb/>Annual Max (MH20) <lb/>90-day Low Flow <lb/>(DL5) <lb/>Rise Rate (RA1) <lb/>f <lb/>High Flow Pulse Count <lb/>(FH1) <lb/>Fig. 2 Six examples of hydrologic alteration indices mapped to stream reaches. (a) Hydrologic alteration index <lb/>(HAI), (b) Daily CV Flow (MA3), (c) Annual Max divided by catchment area (km2) (MH20), (d) 90-day Low <lb/>Flow (DL5), (e) Rise Rate (RA1), and (f) High Flow Pulse Count (FH1). See Table 1 for details on hydrologic <lb/>index descriptions. Regional boundaries represent ecohydrologic regions. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>calculate the HAI, all 110 hydrologic metrics (step 2 above) for reference and non-reference gages were cen-<lb/>tered, scaled from 0 to 1, and assessed in a principal components analysis (PCA) 24 . Thirteen of the components <lb/>were significant according to the broken-stick method 31 . We partitioned the 13 principal component scores by <lb/>hydrologic class membership and calculated 90 th percentile confidence intervals for only reference streams. The <lb/>confidence interval (a…b) for significant PC scores (S) is represented by the lower (a) and upper (b) bounds. For <lb/>each non-reference gage and each significant PC, we calculated a rank (r) value using the following: <lb/>≤ ≤ <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>a <lb/>S <lb/>b <lb/>r <lb/>r <lb/>V <lb/>If <lb/>is true then <lb/>0, otherwise <lb/>, <lb/>(2) <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>Where V i is the eigenvalue for the i th significant PC. The HAI was then calculated for each non-reference <lb/>gage using: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>S <lb/>a <lb/>r <lb/>S <lb/>a <lb/>S <lb/>b <lb/>r <lb/>S <lb/>b <lb/>for <lb/>,and <lb/>f or <lb/>(3) <lb/>i <lb/>n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>∑ <lb/>∑ <lb/>− <lb/> * <lb/>&lt; <lb/>− <lb/> * <lb/>&gt; <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>The formula accounts for both the degree of alteration of the PC (i.e., S i -a i or S i -b i ) as well as the importance <lb/>of each PC to overall variability in hydrologic regimes (i.e., eigenvalue, V i ). <lb/>To ensure all metrics were on a similar scale, both the seasonality index and HAI were scaled from 0 to 1 for <lb/>each ecohydrologic region based on: <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>min( ) <lb/>max( ) <lb/>min( ) <lb/>(4) <lb/>i <lb/>Step 4 and 5 expanded: Hydrologic alteration models and mapping. Random forests 32 were <lb/>constructed to model all hydrologic alteration indices as binomial distributions using 50 predictor variables <lb/>summarizing natural characteristics and human disturbances, such as landscape alteration and infrastructures <lb/>(Supplementary Table 1, see 24 ). Random forests are a form of machine learning where large numbers of decision <lb/>trees are constructed in an iterative fashion using a bootstrapped subsample of observations and subsets of vari-<lb/>ables 32 . The remaining observations are termed the out-of-bag (OOB) sample, which is used in cross-validation <lb/>measurements of variance explained, error, and variable importance. Each tree is constructed from training data <lb/>and then predictions are combined among all trees. We used the randomForest package 33 in the R programming <lb/>environment to develop tree-based models for the entire US (all gauges) and separately for each ecohydrologic <lb/>region. Hence, with 43 hydrologic indices and 29 regions, over 1,000 forest models were generated. Predictor <lb/>variables used in models are classified into 8 groups (number of variables in parentheses): urbanization (14), <lb/>agriculture (10), dams and reservoirs (6), power generation (6), dischargers and flow modifiers (5), human dis-<lb/>turbance indices (3), basin size, stream size, and climate (3), and natural land cover (3) (Supplementary Table 1). <lb/>Predictor variables were obtained from multiple sources or our own geospatial analysis and were summarized for <lb/>both the local catchment surrounding each stream reach containing the stream gauge or were accumulated for the <lb/>entire catchment contributing to each gauge (Supplementary Table 1). Similarly, the same predictor variables were <lb/>compiled for all 2.6 million NHDPlus V1 stream reaches, both for local catchments and entire stream networks <lb/>upstream of each reach. Following construction and calibration, random forest models were used to extrapolate <lb/>hydrologic alteration values to all 2.6 million NHDPlus V1 stream reaches in the CONUS (Fig. 2). Using cross-<lb/>walks between NHDPlus V1 and V2, we extended hydrologic alteration values to NHD Plus V2 stream reaches. <lb/>Step 6 and 7 expanded: Ecological alteration models and mapping. To develop flow-alteration-<lb/>ecological response relationships, George et al. 17 developed a comprehensive dataset of overlapping hydrologic <lb/>and ecological data for 6,452 stream reach locations. At each location, measures of hydrologic alteration and <lb/>ecological alteration were compiled, where ecological alteration was measured as the deviation in observed native <lb/>fish richness from expected natural conditions 17 . Flow-alteration-ecological-response relationships typically <lb/>adopt a &quot;wedge-shaped&quot; distribution well-suited for quantile regression 34 . Hence, George et al. generated quantile <lb/>regression models predicting 50 th , 75 th , and 95 th percentile alterations in fish richness from hydrologic alteration <lb/>values for all hydrologic metrics, except HAI, within each 4-digit hydrologic unit code (HUC-4), except water-<lb/>sheds where limited sample size prohibited model development (12% of watersheds). <lb/>Quantile regression model coefficients for each hydrologic metric within each HUC4 were used to predict <lb/>alterations in native fish richness at the stream reach resolution based on modeled estimates of hydrologic alter-<lb/>ation. In situations where coefficients were unavailable for HUC-4s, average model coefficients for entire ecohy-<lb/>drologic regions were used. Residuals in fish richness were calculated for each hydrologic alteration metric (e.g., <lb/>Fig. 3a). Flow thresholds or tipping points represent hydrologic alteration values beyond which ecological deg-<lb/>radation is expected 13 or can be deemed socially unacceptable 15 . Presuming that loss of any native fish species is <lb/>unacceptable, the hydrologic alteration value at which residuals in fish richness &lt;0 is considered the threshold <lb/>or limit. Based on the quantile regression models 17 , thresholds were identified and applied to all stream reaches <lb/>based on HUC-4 or ecohydrologic region. Modeled hydrologic alteration values for each metric were compared <lb/>to each respective threshold in each stream reach to yield a binary response where losses in fish biodiversity are <lb/>expected (1) or not (0), depending on if the hydrologic threshold was exceeded. The mean value among these <lb/>responses for all hydrologic alteration metrics yields a probability of fish biodiversity loss (Fig. 3b), ranging from <lb/>0 to 1, based on all components of the flow regime. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Data Records <lb/>All data records available and their file structure are described in Table 2. Modeled estimates of hydrologic <lb/>alteration for all 43 metrics and estimates of fish biodiversity loss in response to each metric (except HAI) are <lb/>provided at the NHDPlus stream-reach resolution in .csv or .txt files. Each row entry includes the corresponding <lb/>stream reach identifiers (i.e., COMIDs) for both NHDPlus V1 and V2 versions. Given that fish species richness <lb/>responses were modeled for many hydrologic alteration metrics, the median and extreme fish biodiversity loss <lb/>values across all metrics, in addition to binary and probability measures of fish biodiversity loss, are also pro-<lb/>vided for each stream reach. Estimates of hydrologic alteration are provided separately for different modeled <lb/>outcomes, including the random forests developed for all gauges in the US and the aggregated results from all <lb/>forests developed for each ecohydrologic region. Likewise, the fish species richness response data are provided in <lb/>two datasets for reach set of responses, one for the entire US and one for the aggregated regional results. The data <lb/>are generally split into two or four regional sub-datasets for the entire CONUS. Random forest model perfor-<lb/>mance measures, including AUC values and relative importance of predictor variables are also provided in .csv <lb/>files, both for the entire-US model and for each ecohydrologic region model. Data records are freely and openly <lb/>accessible under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license on Zenodo 35 . <lb/>technical Validation <lb/>We evaluated hydrologic alteration model performance using area-under-the-curve (AUC) measures for all <lb/>models. AUC values represent cross-validation measures, as predictions from model trees are taken from the <lb/>out-of-bag (OOB) sample, representing roughly 33% of observations, modeled in that forest. AUC values are <lb/>appropriate for evaluating the performance of hydrologic alteration models as the indices range from 0 to 1; <lb/>however, AUC evaluation requires a binary classifier as the control from which to measure performance. In this <lb/>case, we used two binary control measures to calculate AUC values: a binary categorization of reference and <lb/>non-reference gages (measure 1), and a categorization of high (index &gt; 0.5) and low (index &lt; = 0.5) hydrologic <lb/>alteration values in the empirical observations (measure 2). Relative importance (RI) of variables in predicting <lb/>hydrologic alteration indices was also measured from the OOB sample as the average decrease in mean squared <lb/>error (MSE) rates across all permutations of a given variable among all trees. Because RI can vary with MSE <lb/>values, we scaled all RI values from 0 to 1 using the Eq. 4 to support comparison among hydrologic alteration <lb/>0 <lb/>1 ,000 <lb/>2,000 <lb/>km <lb/>Probability <lb/>0.00 -0.05 <lb/>0.06 -0.10 <lb/>0.11 -0.25 <lb/>0.26 -0.50 <lb/>0.51 -0.75 <lb/>0.76 -1.00 <lb/>Residual (Species Loss) <lb/>-1.28 --1.00 <lb/>-0.99 --0.75 <lb/>-0.74 --0.50 <lb/>-0.49 --0.25 <lb/>-0.24 --0.10 <lb/>-0.09 -0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Cumulative Proportion <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Probability of Biodiversity Loss <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>95 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>of Biodiversity Loss <lb/>Percentile <lb/>1-day Low Flow (DL1) <lb/>Fig. 3 Modeled fish biodiversity responses to hydrologic alteration and assessment of uncertainty. (a) Losses in <lb/>fish species richness (measured as residuals) estimated in response to alterations in 1-day low flows (DL1). Fish <lb/>residuals were estimated using the 95 th quantile regression. (b) Probability of fish biodiversity loss estimated <lb/>from fish richness responses to 42 hydrologic alteration metrics. Fish biodiversity losses were estimated using <lb/>the 95 th quantile regressions for all metrics. (c-e) Cumulative proportions of stream reaches exceeding a given <lb/>probability of fish biodiversity loss based on (c) 50 th , (d) 75 th , and (e) and 95 th quantile regressions. Ranges for <lb/>each cumulative distribution represent compounded uncertainty arising from error in hydrologic alteration <lb/>models and quantile regressions. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>indices, groups of predictor variables, and regions. MSE values for all random forest models are provided in <lb/>Supplementary Material 1. <lb/>AUC values for models developed for the entire US averaged 0.87 and ranged from 0.72 to 0.91 for measure <lb/>1, whereas for measure 2, AUC values averaged 0.82 and ranged from 0.78 to 0.88 (Fig. 4, results also available <lb/>via 35 ). Performance for models developed for individual ecohydrologic regions varied considerably. For meas-<lb/>ure 1, AUC values averaged 0.87 and ranged from 0.5 to 0.998 depending on the hydrologic index (Fig. 4a) and <lb/>region (Fig. 4b). For measure 2, AUC values averaged 0.81 and ranged from 0.53 to 0.995 (Fig. 4c,d). Variation <lb/>in model performance seemed to be related to intrinsic properties of each region and less influenced by different <lb/>hydrologic indices. Differences in model performance was not influenced by the gauges available for model <lb/>construction. For instance, there was no relationship between the number of observations (number of gauges) <lb/>and average variation explained in hydrologic indices for each ecohydrologic region. <lb/>The relative importance of predictor variables in explaining variation in hydrologic indices was also explored. <lb/>Climate and natural basin characteristics, such as drainage area and precipitation, were the most important pre-<lb/>dictor variables, followed by variables characterizing dams (e.g., dam storage, degree of regulation). Landcover <lb/>variables were of moderate importance, whereas energy infrastructure and water discharges (unrelated to dam <lb/>regulation) were of minor importance (Fig. 5a). With a few exceptions, variation in importance among models <lb/>within a region generally mirrored the overall importance of variables, where basin and climate variables had <lb/>higher variation in importance, followed by dam-related variables (Fig. 5b). <lb/>As a second and coarse validation of hydrologic alteration, we compared our nationwide rates of hydro-<lb/>logic alteration from our assessment to three other nationwide assessments of hydrologic alteration, conducted <lb/>at either the stream-gage or stream-reach level 8,26,36 . Comparing rates of alteration among different assess-<lb/>ments requires establishing common hydrologic alteration thresholds, which, in the case of Carlisle et al. 8 , was <lb/>&gt; = 10% change in hydrologic indices from reference conditions. Carlisle et al. found that 86% of stream gages <lb/>showed signs of at least 10% deflated mean annual minima and maxima values. Based on our assessment, 93% <lb/>of stream gages had alteration values of &gt; = 0.1 for DL1 (1-day annual minimum), 66% of gages with &gt; = 0.1 for <lb/>DH1 (1-day annual maximum), and 96% of gages considering both DL1 and DH1. In contrast to Carlisle et al., <lb/>our analysis considers both decreases and increases to hydrologic metrics as a measure of alteration. Extending <lb/>the comparison to stream reaches, approximately 74% of U.S. stream mileage, on average (79% median), across <lb/>all hydrologic indices had hydrologic alternation values equal or exceeding 10%. According to the hydrologic <lb/>alteration index (HAI), 79% of streams were hydrologically altered, whereas the mean daily flow index (MA1) <lb/>indicated 81% of streams were altered. <lb/>Eng et al. 26 conducted a thorough study of hydrologic alteration at stream gages and reported percentages <lb/>of non-reference gages displaying alteration for twelve hydrologic metrics, some of which were compatible <lb/>with those used in our study, although none were identical (Supplementary Material 2, Table S1). Aside from <lb/>differences in the metrics used, the scale of values used in Eng et al. &apos;s approach to measure degrees of hydro-<lb/>logic alteration differed from our approach and required some adjustment to be compatible for comparison <lb/>(Supplementary Material 2, Table S2). Generally, the frequency of non-reference stream gages displaying degrees <lb/>of alteration for various flow components in our study agreed relatively well with that of Eng et al. (Fig. 6). <lb/>Carlisle et al. 36 used machine learning models to extend Eng et al. &apos;s stream gage assessment to the stream reach <lb/>level and reports that 1.2 million km, or roughly 38% of streams have &quot;modified flows&quot;. Carlisle et. al. does not <lb/>report what threshold was used to generate this result; however, if we assume that a 20% presumptive standard <lb/>File(s) <lb/>Description <lb/>Ecohydrologic_Regions <lb/>ESRI shapefile of regions used for separate hydrologic alteration model development <lb/>Hydrologic_alteration.zip <lb/>Predicted values of hydrologic alteration in 43 metrics at the stream reach resolution. <lb/>Predicted values were estimated using regional models or models developed for the entire <lb/>US. Stream reach identifiers are provided for NHDPlus V1 and V2 stream reaches. <lb/>Model_peformance_AUC.zip <lb/>Performance, as measured by Area-under-the-curve (AUC), of regional models and US-<lb/>wide models in predicting hydrologic alteration values. Two measures of performance were <lb/>used: 1) the ability of the model to differentiate hydrologic alteration between reference <lb/>and non-reference streams and 2) the ability of the model to predict hydrologic alterations <lb/>greater than and less than 0.5. <lb/>Variable_importance_RF.zip <lb/>The importance of variables used as predictors of hydrologic alteration across all hydrologic <lb/>metrics and models. Variable importance is provided for each regional model and for the <lb/>entire US model for all metrics. <lb/>Fishresponses_allmetrics.zip <lb/>Estimates of fish richness responses to hydrologic alteration for 43 hydrologic metrics. <lb/>Values are provided for each hydrologic metric and each stream reach. Responses are <lb/>modeled using 50th, 75th, and 95th quantile regression models. Hydrologic alteration <lb/>values were generated for both regional models and US models. <lb/>Fish_Responses_biodiversity_loss_prob.zip <lb/>Probabilities of fish biodiversity loss in each stream reach based on 50th, 75th, and 95th <lb/>quantile regression models (mean, minimum and maximum values) for all hydrologic <lb/>alteration metrics. Two files are provided, one based on probabilities of biodiversity loss <lb/>using predicted hydrologic alteration values from region-specific models (ecohydrologic <lb/>regions) and for models developed for the entire US. <lb/>Fish_Responses_min_median_rich_delta.zip <lb/>Estimated minimum and median changes in fish richness (or delta fish richness) in each <lb/>stream reach in response to hydrologic alteration across all 43 hydrologic metrics. Separate <lb/>fish responses were developed for 50th, 75th, and 95th quantile models evaluating fish <lb/>species response to hydrologic alteration. Additionally, separate analyses were conducted <lb/>from region-specific hydrologic alteration models and models developed for the entire US. <lb/>Table 2. Description of files in the Data Record openly accessible through Zenodo 35 . <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>threshold 13 was used, then our dataset suggests 57% of streams are hydrologically altered based on HAI values <lb/>&gt; = 0.2 (note: HAI is a more comprehensive measure of 110 hydrologic metrics, compared to the 12 reported <lb/>in Eng et al.). Collectively, despite inconsistencies in approaches, these comparisons suggest that our hydrologic <lb/>alteration assessment is within reasonable estimates of other nationwide assessments. <lb/>Validation of the ecological alteration data required consideration of compounding error arising from both <lb/>the hydrologic alteration models and quantile regression models. Hence, cumulative uncertainty in fish biodi-<lb/>versity loss can stem from error in the quantification of hydrologic alteration thresholds, as well as estimation of <lb/>hydrologic alteration. Using mean-square error (MSE) rates for each random forest model, modeled hydrologic <lb/>alteration estimates HA <lb/>( ) were adjusted for each stream reach by subtracting or adding MSE values (from ran-<lb/>dom forest models), yielding minimum HA <lb/>( ) and maximum HA <lb/>( ) values, respectively, for each hydrologic met-<lb/>ric. For quantile regression models, standard error values for slope coefficients were used to vary slopes to yield <lb/>minima T <lb/>( ) and maxima T <lb/>( ) threshold values for each hydrologic metric. Subsequently, fish biodiversity loss <lb/>(R) was modeled as a binary outcome of surpassed thresholds for the h th hydrologic metric at the i th stream <lb/>reach, where <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 .6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0 .8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 .0 <lb/>Index <lb/>HAI <lb/>MA1 <lb/>MA2 <lb/>MA3 <lb/>MA12 <lb/>MA13 <lb/>MA14 <lb/>MA15 <lb/>MA16 <lb/>MA17 <lb/>MA18 <lb/>MA19 <lb/>MA20 <lb/>MA21 <lb/>MA22 <lb/>MA23 <lb/>MA41 <lb/>ML17 <lb/>ML19 <lb/>MH20 <lb/>FL1 <lb/>FH1 <lb/>FH6 <lb/>FH7 <lb/>DL1 <lb/>DL2 <lb/>DL3 <lb/>DL4 <lb/>DL5 <lb/>DL16 <lb/>DL18 <lb/>DH1 <lb/>DH2 <lb/>DH3 <lb/>DH4 <lb/>DH5 <lb/>DH15 <lb/>TA1 <lb/>TA2 <lb/>TL1 <lb/>TH1 <lb/>RA1 <lb/>RA3 <lb/>RA8 <lb/>Seas <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 .6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0 .8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 .0 <lb/>Region <lb/>1019 <lb/>1020 <lb/>1021 <lb/>1115 <lb/>1212_1312 <lb/>140 <lb/>1417 <lb/>157_158 <lb/>166 <lb/>171 <lb/>175 <lb/>182_183 <lb/>184 <lb/>20 <lb/>240 <lb/>316 <lb/>331 <lb/>332 <lb/>40 <lb/>526 <lb/>616 <lb/>724 <lb/>80_1125 <lb/>922_1018 <lb/>US <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0 .7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0 .9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0 .7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0 .9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Index <lb/>HAI <lb/>MA1 <lb/>MA2 <lb/>MA3 <lb/>MA12 <lb/>MA13 <lb/>MA14 <lb/>MA15 <lb/>MA16 <lb/>MA17 <lb/>MA18 <lb/>MA19 <lb/>MA20 <lb/>MA21 <lb/>MA22 <lb/>MA23 <lb/>MA41 <lb/>ML17 <lb/>ML19 <lb/>MH20 <lb/>FL1 <lb/>FH1 <lb/>FH6 <lb/>FH7 <lb/>DL1 <lb/>DL2 <lb/>DL3 <lb/>DL4 <lb/>DL5 <lb/>DL16 <lb/>DL18 <lb/>DH1 <lb/>DH2 <lb/>DH3 <lb/>DH4 <lb/>DH5 <lb/>DH15 <lb/>TA1 <lb/>TA2 <lb/>RA1 <lb/>RA3 <lb/>RA8 <lb/>Seasonality <lb/>Region <lb/>1019 <lb/>1020 <lb/>1021 <lb/>1115 <lb/>1212_1312 <lb/>140 <lb/>1417 <lb/>157_158 <lb/>166 <lb/>171 <lb/>175 <lb/>182_183 <lb/>184 <lb/>20 <lb/>240 <lb/>316 <lb/>331 <lb/>332 <lb/>40 <lb/>526 <lb/>616 <lb/>724 <lb/>80_1125 <lb/>922_1018 <lb/>US <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>Density <lb/>Area Under Curve (AUC) <lb/>Fig. 4 Area Under the Curve (AUC) values assessment random forest model performance using two measures. <lb/>Density plots display the frequency of AUC values measuring model performance for distinguishing (a) <lb/>reference and non-reference gauges (measure 1) for all hydrologic indices, and for (b) all ecohydrologic regions, <lb/>and distinguishing observed hydrologic alteration values &gt; or &lt;0.5 (measure 2) for (c) all hydrologic indices, <lb/>and (d) all ecohydrologic regions. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>∈ <lb/>. <lb/>R <lb/>h <lb/>i <lb/>{0, 1}for all and <lb/>(5) <lb/>h i <lb/>, <lb/>Lower limits (R h i <lb/>, ) and upper limits R <lb/>( ) <lb/>h i <lb/>, of fish biodiversity loss were subject to the following constraint: <lb/>≥ <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>T <lb/>HA <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>If <lb/>, then <lb/>1 , else <lb/>0 , <lb/>(6) <lb/>h <lb/>h i <lb/>h i <lb/>h i <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>80 <lb/>140 <lb/>157 <lb/>158 <lb/>166 <lb/>171 <lb/>175 <lb/>182 <lb/>183 <lb/>184 <lb/>240 <lb/>316 <lb/>331 <lb/>332 <lb/>526 <lb/>616 <lb/>724 <lb/>922 <lb/>1018 <lb/>1019 <lb/>1020 <lb/>1021 <lb/>1115 <lb/>1125 <lb/>1212 <lb/>1312 <lb/>1417 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Relative Importance <lb/>Ecohydrologic Regions <lb/>variable <lb/>Basin_Clim <lb/>Dams <lb/>Natural_LC <lb/>Urban <lb/>Agr <lb/>Discharges <lb/>Disturb_Ind <lb/>Energy <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>80 <lb/>140 <lb/>157 <lb/>158 <lb/>166 <lb/>171 <lb/>175 <lb/>182 <lb/>183 <lb/>184 <lb/>240 <lb/>316 <lb/>331 <lb/>332 <lb/>526 <lb/>616 <lb/>724 <lb/>922 <lb/>1018 <lb/>1019 <lb/>1020 <lb/>1021 <lb/>1115 <lb/>1125 <lb/>1212 <lb/>1312 <lb/>1417 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0 .4 <lb/>Standard Error <lb/>Ecohydrologic Regions <lb/>variable <lb/>Basin_Clim <lb/>Dams <lb/>Natural_LC <lb/>Urban <lb/>Agr <lb/>Discharges <lb/>Disturb_Ind <lb/>Energy <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>Fig. 5 Relative importance of variables in hydrologic alteration models. (a) Relative importance values for <lb/>predictors were grouped within variable types (e.g., basin, dams) and then averaged with the group and across <lb/>all models within a region. (b) standard error in relative importance values within a group and region. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

            <note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>and <lb/>T <lb/>HA <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>If <lb/>, then <lb/>1 , else <lb/>0 <lb/>(7) <lb/>h <lb/>h i <lb/>h i <lb/>h i <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>≥ <lb/>= <lb/>= . <lb/>Lower and upper limits to the probability of fish biodiversity loss for each stream reach were then calculated <lb/>as: <lb/>∑ R <lb/>n <lb/>(8) <lb/>h <lb/>n <lb/>h i <lb/>, <lb/>and <lb/>∑ R <lb/>n <lb/>(9) <lb/>h <lb/>n <lb/>h i <lb/>, <lb/>Where n is the number of hydrologic metrics. Lower and upper limits of probability of fish biodiversity loss <lb/>were calculated separately for 50 th , 75 th , and 95 th quantile model results, each of which had different hydrologic <lb/>threshold values corresponding to each hydrologic alteration metric. <lb/>Cumulative frequency distributions were used to examine the variability and uncertainty in the probability of <lb/>fish biodiversity loss in stream reaches according to different quantile models. The distribution of fish biodiver-<lb/>sity loss probability varied widely among different quantiles (Fig. 3c-e). Uncertainty was considerable, indicating <lb/>high amounts of compounding error arose from both hydrologic alteration models and quantile models predict-<lb/>ing fish biodiversity loss (Fig. 3c-e); however, total uncertainty was lower for the 95 th percentile models (Fig. 3e). <lb/>Usage Notes <lb/>Mapping hydrologic alteration indices and associated measures of ecological responses in stream reaches pro-<lb/>vides a rich dataset for environmental flow applications, especially in data-poor regions. The dataset provides <lb/>general &quot;rules of thumb&quot; for environmental flow guidelines, specifically which hydrologic indices are important <lb/>to ecology, and hence, management. Maps at the stream-reach resolution can be used to explore hydrologic <lb/>indices with the highest rates of alteration, as well as the risk of stream habitat alteration and biodiversity loss. As <lb/>such, the data can be useful for exploring the frequency of alteration in the landscape according to hydrologic <lb/>or biologically meaningful spatial units (e.g., species ranges), and can support aquatic species GAP analyses or <lb/>prioritization for areas of flow restoration. Data are provided in accessible .csv formats and summarized at the <lb/>NHDplus stream-reach scale. Hence, the data provide inherent interoperability with other NHDplus-derived <lb/>products with associated COMID identifiers. The full functionality of the NHDplus framework, including topo-<lb/>logical connections and stream routing, can be leveraged with the hydrologic alteration dataset. <lb/>Users of the dataset should be aware of its limitations. The modeled hydrologic alteration and ecological <lb/>alteration values are not meant to replace site-specific environmental assessments and are most appropriately <lb/>used as information building blocks for regional environmental flow applications. As indicated in the valida-<lb/>tion section, random forest models of hydrologic alteration had variable error rates. While model performance <lb/>is satisfactory for most hydrologic metrics, uncertainty would have likely reduced had we controlled for cli-<lb/>mate variation among reference and non-reference gages 26 . Although 15 years of hydrologic data records is <lb/>considered sufficient for calculating hydrologic statistics 25 , a formal control of climate shifts would have likely <lb/>Fig. 6 Comparison of hydrologic alteration assessments of stream gauges conducted by Eng et al. (2019) (E) <lb/>and that of the current study (C). Percentages of stream gages having various degrees of hydrologic alteration <lb/>(colors) are compared between the two studies. Analogous hydrologic statistics were selected for comparison in <lb/>each category (e.g., Low-flows magnitude); however, no statistics were exactly the same between the two studies <lb/>and likely contributed to differences. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>improved model performance. Furthermore, compounded uncertainties were significant when predicting fish <lb/>biodiversity responses to alteration. An important consideration is the interpretation of hydrologic alteration <lb/>values, which have been standardized from 0 to 1. As such, these are not directly translatable as measures of <lb/>hydrologic alteration. Although values were generally derived from ratios of alteration and intended to represent <lb/>a probability of alteration, interpreting the values as measures of risk and indicators of alteration is more appro-<lb/>priate than in a strict probabilistic sense. Finally, random forest models developed for each ecohydrologic region <lb/>were influenced by the range of hydrologic alteration values and frequency of altered streams in those regions. <lb/>Additionally, values were standardized based on minima and maxima within each ecohydrologic region; there-<lb/>fore, hydrologic alteration values derived from regional models will display slight regional biases in values. <lb/>Therefore, users desiring US-wide applications should perhaps use values from US-wide models. <lb/></body>
			
			<div type="availability">code availability <lb/>Data processing, visualization, and random forest development were conducted using pre-existing libraries, <lb/>particularly the randomForest package 33 and ggplot2 package 37 (for density plots and stacked bar plots) in the <lb/>R programming environment, whereas spatial mapping was conducted in ArcMap 10.7.1, as indicated in the <lb/>methods and validation. Therefore, no custom code was used for this study. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 8 February 2022; Accepted: 13 July 2022; <lb/>Published: xx xx xxxx <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Tickner, D. et al. Bending the curve of global freshwater biodiversity loss: an emergency recovery plan. BioScience 70(4), 330-342 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>2. Dudgeon, D. et al. Freshwater biodiversity: importance, threats, status and conservation challenges. Biological reviews 81(2), <lb/>163-182 (2006). <lb/>3. Balain, E. V., Segers, H., Lévèque, C. &amp; Martens, K. The Freshwater Animal Diversity Assessment: An overview of the results. <lb/>Hydrobiologia 595, 627-637 (2008). <lb/>4. McManamay, R. A. &amp; Jager, H. I. Stream Biomes of the World in Encyclopedia of the World&apos;s Biomes (ed. Goldstein, M. I. &amp; DellaSala, <lb/>D. A.) https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-409548-9.12047-0 (Elsevier, 2020). <lb/>5. Grill, G. et al. An index-based framework for assessing patterns and trends in river fragmentation and flow regulation by global <lb/>dams at multiple scales. Environ. Res. Lett. 10(1), 015001 (2015). <lb/>6. Virkki, V. et al. Environmental flow envelopes: quantifying global, ecosystem-threatening streamflow alterations. Hydrol. Earth Syst. <lb/>Sci. https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-2021-260 (2021) <lb/>7. Zaerpour, M., Hatami, S., Sadri, J. &amp; Nazemi, A. A global algorithm for identifying changing streamflow regimes: application to <lb/>Canadian natural streams (1966-2010). Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci. 25(9), 5193-5217 (2021). <lb/>8. Carlisle, D. M., Wolock, D. M. &amp; Meador, M. R. Alteration of streamflow magnitudes and potential ecological consequences: a <lb/>multiregional assessment. Front. Ecol. Environ. 9(5), 264-270 (2011). <lb/>9. Döll, P. &amp; Zhang, J. Impact of climate change on freshwater ecosystems: a global-scale analysis of ecologically relevant river flow <lb/>alterations. Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci. 14(5), 783-799 (2010). <lb/>10. Asadieh, B. &amp; Krakauer, N. Y. Global change in streamflow extremes under climate change over the 21 st century. Hydrol. Earth Syst. <lb/>Sci. 21, 5863-5874 (2017). <lb/>11. Grooten, M. &amp; Almond, R. E. A. Living Planet Report -2018: Aiming Higher. https://www.worldwildlife.org/pages/living-planet-<lb/>report-2018 (World Wildlife Fund, 2018) <lb/>12. Richter, B. D., Baumgartner, J. V., Powell, J. &amp; Braun, D. P. A method for assessing hydrologic alteration within ecosystems. Conserv. <lb/>Biol. 10(4), 1163-1174 (1996). <lb/>13. Richter, B. D., Davis, M., Apse, C. &amp; Konrad, C. A presumptive standard for environmental flow protection. River Research and <lb/>Applications 28(2012), 1312-1321 (2012). <lb/>14. Poff, N. L. &amp; Zimmerman, J. K. Ecological responses to altered flow regimes: a literature review to inform the science and <lb/>management of environmental flows. Freshw. Biol. 55(1), 194-205 (2010). <lb/>15. Poff, N. L. et al. The ecological limits of hydrologic alteration (ELOHA): a new framework for developing regional environmental <lb/>flow standards. Freshwater biology 55(1), 147-170 (2010). <lb/>16. TNC (The Nature Conservancy). ELOHA Case Studies. https://www.conservationgateway.org/ConservationPractices/Freshwater/ <lb/>EnvironmentalFlows/MethodsandTools/ELOHA/Pages/Case-Studies.aspx (2018) <lb/>17. George, R., McManamay, R., Perry, D., Sabo, J. &amp; Ruddell, B. L. Indicators of hydro-ecological alteration for the rivers of the United <lb/>States. Ecological Indicators 120, 106908 (2021). <lb/>18. Troia, M. J. &amp; McManamay, R. A. Completeness and coverage of open-access freshwater fish distribution data in the United States. <lb/>Diversity and Distributions 23, 1482-1498, https://doi.org/10.1111/ddi.12637 (2017). <lb/>19. Irving, K. et al. A high-resolution streamflow and hydrological metrics dataset for ecological modeling using a regression model. <lb/>Scientific data 5(1), 1-14 (2018). <lb/>20. Carlisle, D. M., Grantham, T. E., Eng, K. &amp; Wolock, D. M. Biological relevance of streamflow metrics: regional and national <lb/>perspectives. Freshwater Sci. 36(4), 927-940 (2017). <lb/>21. Falcone, J. A. GAGES-II: Geospatial Attributes of Gages for Evaluating Streamflow. U.S. Geological Survey https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3133/70046617 (2011). <lb/>22. McManamay, R. A. Quantifying and generalizing hydrologic responses to dam regulation using a statistical modeling approach. J. <lb/>Hydrol. 519, 1278-1296 (2014). <lb/>23. McManamay, R. A., Bevelhimer, M. S. &amp; Kao, S. C. Updating the US hydrologic classification: an approach to clustering and <lb/>stratifying ecohydrologic data. Ecohydrology 7(3), 903-926 (2014). <lb/>24. McManamay, R. A. et al. US cities can manage national hydrology and biodiversity using local infrastructure policy. Proceedings of <lb/>the National Academy of Sciences 114(36), 9581-9586 (2017). <lb/>25. Kennard, M. J., Mackay, S. J., Pusey, B. J., Olden, J. D. &amp; Marsh, N. Quantifying uncertainty in estimation of hydrologic metrics for <lb/>ecohydrological studies. River Res. Applic. 26, 137-156, https://doi.org/10.1002/rra.1249 (2010). <lb/>26. Eng, K., Carlisle, D. M., Grantham, T. E., Wolock, D. M. &amp; Eng, R. L. Severity and extent of alterations to natural streamflow regimes <lb/>based on hydrologic metrics in the conterminous United States, 1980-2014: U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Report <lb/>2019-5001, 25 p., https://doi.org/10.3133/sir20195001 (2019) <lb/>27. Stoddard, J. L., Larse, D. P., Hawkins, C. P., Jonson, R. K. &amp; Norris, R. H. Setting expectations for the ecological conditions of streams: <lb/>the concept of reference condition. Ecological Applications 16, 1267-1276 (2006). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:450 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>28. Olden, J. D. &amp; Poff, N. L. Redundancy and the choice of hydrologic indices for characterizing streamflow regimes. River Res. Appl. <lb/>19(2), 101-121 (2003). <lb/>29. Abell, R. et al. Freshwater Ecoregions of the World: A new map of biogeographic units for freshwater biodiversity conservation. <lb/>BioScience 58, 403-414, https://doi.org/10.1641/B580507 (2008). <lb/>30. Eng, K., Carlisle, D. M., Wolock, D. M. &amp; Falcone, J. A. Predicting the likelihood of altered streamflows at ungauged rivers across the <lb/>conterminous United States. River Res. Appl. 29(6), 781-791 (2013). <lb/>31. Jackson, D. A. Stopping rules in principal components analysis: a comparison of heuristical and statistical approaches. Ecology 74, <lb/>2204-2214 (1993). <lb/>32. Breiman, L. Random forests. Mach Learn 45, 5-32 (2001). <lb/>33. Liaw, A. &amp; Wiener, M. Classification and Regression by randomForest. R News, 2(3), 18-22, https://CRAN.R-project.org/doc/ <lb/>Rnews/ (2002). <lb/>34. Knight, R. R., Murphy, J. C., Wolfe, W. J., Saylor, C. F. &amp; Wales, A. K. Ecological limit functions relating fish community response to <lb/>hydrologic departures of the ecological flow regime in the Tennessee River basin, United States. Ecohydrology 7(5), 1262-1280 <lb/>(2014). <lb/>35. McManamay, R. A., George, R., Morrison, R. A. &amp; Ruddell, B. L. A dataset of modeled hydrologic alteration and ecological <lb/>consequences in stream reaches of the conterminous United States, Zenodo https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5839011 (2022). <lb/>36. Carlisle, D. M. et al. Flow modification in the Nation&apos;s streams and rivers: U.S. Geological Survey Circular 1461, 75 p., https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3133/cir1461 (2019) <lb/>37. Wickham, H. ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis. Springer-Verlag New York. ISBN 978-3-319-24277-4, https://ggplot2. <lb/>tidyverse.org (2016) <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This research was partially funded through the US Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS), Grant TX T-234-R-1, <lb/>F21AF02689-00 under the authority of the State Wildlife Grant Program (CFDA #15.634) issued by Texas Parks <lb/>and Wildlife Department. We thank two anonymous reviewers for providing comments that improved previous <lb/>version of this manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">author contributions <lb/>R.A.M. conceived the idea of the data, constructed the dataset, and drafted the manuscript. R.G. built the <lb/>ecological thresholds and helped with dataset integration. R.R.M. assisted in writing and editing the manuscript. <lb/>B.L.R. co-conceived the data and edited the draft. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>additional information <lb/>Supplementary information The online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/s41597-022-01566-1. <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to R.A.M. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/>

			Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2022 </front>

	</text>
</tei>
