<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448 <lb/>Available online 1 March 2024 <lb/>2405-8440/© 2024 The Authors. <lb/>Published by Elsevier Ltd. <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Research article <lb/>Propionyl-L-carnitine mitigates ischemia-reperfusion injury in rat <lb/>epigastric island flaps <lb/>Atilla Adnan Eyuboglu a , Ovunc Akdemir b, * , Oytun Erbas c , Mustafa Tonguc Isken d , <lb/>Feng Zhang e , William C. Lineaweaver f <lb/>a Arel University, Department of Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>b Aydin University, Department of Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>c Bilim University, Department of Physiopathology, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>d Bahcesehir Medical University, Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>e PhD University of Mississippi Medical Center, Division of Plastic Surgery, Microsurgery, 2500 North State Street, Jackson, MS 39216, USA <lb/>f Vanderbilt Bill Wilkerson Center for Otolaryngology and Communication Sciences, Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery, Nashville, TN, <lb/>USA <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Carnitine <lb/>Flap survival <lb/>Inflammation <lb/>Ischemia-reperfusion injury <lb/>Necrosis <lb/>Oxidative stress <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>Background: Ischemia-reperfusion injury presents a substantial concern in various medical sce-<lb/>narios, notably in reconstructive surgery involving tissue flaps. Despite reports on the protective <lb/>benefits of Propionyl-L-carnitine against ischemia-reperfusion injury, a thorough assessment of its <lb/>efficacy in epigastric island flap models is currently lacking. <lb/>Methods: Sixteen male Sprague-Dawley rats underwent epigastric island flap surgery and were <lb/>divided into two groups: a Propionyl-L-carnitine group that received intraperitoneal Propionyl-L-<lb/>carnitine prior to ischemia induction and a sham group that received saline treatment. A <lb/>comprehensive evaluation was performed including macroscopic, biochemical and histological <lb/>assessments encompassing measurements of flap survival areas, lipid peroxidation (malondial-<lb/>dehyde), glutathione, myeloperoxidase, nitric oxide and peripheral neutrophil counts. <lb/>Results: The Propionyl-L-carnitine group demonstrated significantly increased flap survival areas <lb/>when compared to the sham group. Administration of Propionyl-L-carnitine led to reduced <lb/>malondialdehyde levels and elevated glutathione levels indicating a reduction in oxidative stress. <lb/>Furthermore, the Propionyl-L-carnitine group exhibited lower myeloperoxidase levels, higher <lb/>nitric oxide levels and reduced peripheral neutrophil counts, suggesting a decrease in the in-<lb/>flammatory response. Histopathological analysis revealed decreased levels of inflammation, ne-<lb/>crosis, polymorphonuclear leukocyte infiltration and edema in the Propionyl-L-carnitine group. <lb/>Additionally, vascularity was enhanced in the Propionyl-L-carnitine group. <lb/>Conclusion: This study provides compelling evidence that Propionyl-L-carnitine administration <lb/>effectively mitigates the deleterious effects of ischemia-reperfusion injury in epigastric island <lb/>flaps. This is substantiated by the improved flap survival, diminished oxidative stress and <lb/>inflammation, as well as the enhanced vascularity observed. Propionyl-L-carnitine emerges as a <lb/>promising therapeutic intervention to enhance tissue flap survival in reconstructive surgery, <lb/>warranting further exploration through larger-scale investigations. <lb/>* Corresponding author. Aydin University, Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery, Istanbul, Turkey. <lb/>E-mail addresses: atillaeyuboglu@yahoo.com (A.A. Eyuboglu), ovuncakdemir@gmail.com (O. Akdemir), oytunerbas2012@gmail.com <lb/>(O. Erbas), tongucisken@yahoo.com (M.T. Isken), feng.zhang@jmsburncenters.com (F. Zhang), william.c.lineaweaver@vumc.org <lb/>(W.C. Lineaweaver). <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Heliyon <lb/>journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e27448 <lb/>Received 8 November 2023; Received in revised form 30 January 2024; Accepted 28 February 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Ischemia-reperfusion injury in skin/muscle flaps can lead to partial or complete flap loss without an apparent cause. This injury is a <lb/>multifaceted problem involving apoptosis, the generation of oxygen radicals, platelet aggregation and interactions between leukocytes <lb/>and endothelium. It arises from the acute interruption of blood flow within the microvasculature. Recent attention has centered on the <lb/>interplay between neutrophils and endothelial cells in the context of ischemia-reperfusion injury (I/R) [1]. Ischemia-reperfusion injury <lb/>plays a pivotal role in a wide range of diseases and can lead to exacerbated damage during surgical procedures. While considerable <lb/>research efforts have been dedicated to alleviating its effects on brain, liver, kidney and cardiac tissues, the examination of its im-<lb/>plications in the context of skeletal muscle has not received commensurate attention [2]. Ischemia-reperfusion injury following <lb/>revascularization is an inherent pathophysiological process that occurs regardless of a surgeon&apos;s level of expertise [3]. <lb/>Propionyl-L-carnitine (PLC), alternatively known as β-trimethylamino-β-hydroxybutyrate, is a naturally occurring compound <lb/>present in its unesterified form within mammalian cells. It exists in various derivatives such as acetyl-L-carnitine, propionyl-L-carnitine <lb/>and palmitoyl-L-carnitine. These derivatives are sourced from dietary components primarily found in meat and dairy products and are <lb/>also synthesized endogenously, particularly within the liver and kidney [4]. Propionyl-L-carnitine&apos;s primary function is to serve as a <lb/>co-transporter aiding in the translocation of long-chain free fatty acids from the cytosol into the mitochondria. Inside the mito-<lb/>chondria, these fatty acids are harnessed for β-oxidation leading to the production of acetyl coenzyme A as part of the tricarboxylic acid <lb/>cycle. This metabolic process culminates in the generation of Adenosine Triphosphate (ATP) through the electron transport chain and <lb/>oxidative phosphorylation. However, it should be noted that this process consumes a substantial amount of oxygen. In the end, oxygen <lb/>is converted to water and the formation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) is curtailed [5]. Moreover, propionyl-L-carnitine demon-<lb/>strates its antioxidant characteristics by boosting the function of key antioxidant enzymes including glutathione peroxidase (GSH), <lb/>catalase and superoxide dismutase (SOD). It also has the capacity to bind to metal ions that play a role in generating ROS, such as <lb/>ferrous ions. In the realm of antioxidant activity, propionyl-L-carnitine shares similarities with renowned antioxidants like <lb/>alpha-tocopherol [6]. Although the precise mechanisms and advantages of PLC and its derivatives in the human body remain partially <lb/>elucidated, it is established that tissues with elevated energy requirements such as skeletal and cardiac muscles, possess a notable <lb/>presence of PLC. The protective attributes of PLC and its derivatives against I/R are predominantly attributed to their antioxidant <lb/>properties. By restraining the generation of ROS during aerobic metabolism, they can ameliorate the harm resulting from I/R injury <lb/>[7]. <lb/>To contribute to the understanding of this subject, we utilized PLC in an ischemia-reperfusion injury model employing epigastric <lb/>island flaps in rats, similar to our previous investigation into the effects of Trimetazidine on reperfusion injury [8]. In the light of <lb/>aforementioned information from the literature, We have examined the effects of PLC on reperfusion damages using the skin flap <lb/>model in rats. <lb/>2. Materials and methods <lb/>The biostatistics department determined the number of subjects, aiming to minimize the required number of animal groups while <lb/>ensuring statistical significance. Sixteen male Sprague-Dawley rats, weighing between 230 and 280 g, were enrolled in this study. The <lb/>experimental procedures followed the ethical guidelines set forth by the National Research Council for the care and utilization of <lb/>laboratory animals. The reduction of the upper and lower incisor teeth was executed using a motor tool (Electric Variable Speed Motor <lb/>Tool, Model 380-5, Dremel Co. Racine, WI, lowest speed) equipped with an abrasive cutting disc following the surgical procedure, as a <lb/>preventative measure against auto cannibalism. <lb/>3. Experimental protocol <lb/>3.1. The characteristics of the experimental protocol were as follows <lb/>• The animals were divided into two groups, each comprising eight rats. <lb/>• In the PLC group, the flap was elevated following intraperitoneal administration of Propionyl-L-carnitine, after which ischemia was <lb/>induced. <lb/>• In the sham group, the flap was elevated after intraperitoneal application of saline, and ischemia was subsequently induced. <lb/>• Biochemical samples were collected 24 h after reperfusion for analysis. <lb/>• On the 10th postoperative day, the rats were euthanized, and the flaps were photographed to assess flap survival. Additionally, <lb/>tissue samples were collected for histopathological examination. <lb/>3.2. Surgical procedures <lb/>All surgical procedures were conducted by the same surgeon (OA). Following intramuscular administration of xylazine (15 mg/kg; <lb/>Alfazyne®, Alfasan International BV, Netherlands) and ketamine (50 mg/kg; Ketalar®, Pfizer Warner-Lambert, Turkey). The <lb/>abdominal and inguinal regions of the rats were carefully shaved. Aseptic conditions were maintained using cetrimide and chlor-<lb/>hexidine gluconate (Savlon®, GlaxoSmithKline, Brentford, UK). Subsequently, the animals were positioned in the supine posture on <lb/>the operating table. A 6 × 4 cm 2 epigastric flap was meticulously marked and delineated using a skin marker as described on our <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A.A. Eyuboglu et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>previous studies [8,9]. In the PLC group (group 2), intraperitoneal administration of PLC (100 mg/kg body weight in 0.5 mL of saline) <lb/>from Sigma Tau Co., Pomezia (Italy) was carried out. Approximately 30 min following the PLC injection, the flap, encompassing the <lb/>subcutaneous and superficial fascia at the distal section of the inguinal ligament was raised in a craniocaudal direction. Subsequently, <lb/>the epigastric artery and vein were meticulously identified and separated from the surrounding tissue. To secure the pedicle, an Acland <lb/>V2 micro clamp was applied for a duration of 10 h (Fig. 1). (see <lb/>Following a 10-h period, the clamp was removed, and arterial-venous flow was reestablished using peristalsis. The flap exhibited an <lb/>increase in temperature and a change in color before being repositioned and sutured with 4-0 polypropylene sutures. In the sham <lb/>group (group 1), only 0.5 mL of physiological serum was injected 30 min prior to reperfusion via the saphenous vein. The flap in this <lb/>group remained untreated. Under general anesthesia and with intramuscular ketamine and xylazine for analgesia, 1 × 1 cm 2 tissue <lb/>samples were obtained from the same sides of all flaps 24 h after reperfusion for subsequent biochemical analysis. After a period of 10 <lb/>days, the rats were euthanized using a lethal dose of ketamine and images were captured to quantify the surviving area of the flap. To <lb/>ensure the integrity of the necrotic region, 1 × 1 cm 2 samples were extracted from the same sides of all flaps after the 10th-day images <lb/>were taken for histological assessments. <lb/>3.3. Macroscopic measurement of the surviving flap area <lb/>Seven days after the operation, photographs of the flaps were taken using a Canon EOS 600 d camera positioned at a 25 cm distance. <lb/>The surviving flap area was subsequently computed using the Image-Pro Express program (Version 6.0, Media Cybernetics, USA). To <lb/>obtain this value, the necrotic area was deducted from the overall flap area [ [9]]. <lb/>3.4. Histopathological and biochemical analysis <lb/>Lipid peroxidation, tissue glutathione, nitric oxide, myeloperoxidase levels and peripheral neutrophil counts were analyzed. <lb/>3.5. Measurement of tissues lipid peroxidation (MDA) <lb/>Lipid peroxidation was assessed in tissue specimens, each weighing approximately 100 mg, through the measurement of MDA <lb/>levels as thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS). In brief, trichloroacetic acid and the TBARS reagent were introduced to the <lb/>tissue samples, creating a mixture that was subsequently incubated at 100 • C for a duration of 60 min. After a period of cooling in an ice <lb/>bath, the samples underwent centrifugation at 3000 rpm for 20 min and the absorbance of the resulting supernatant was recorded at <lb/>535 nm. MDA levels were quantified using a standard calibration curve generated with tetraethoxypropane and the values were <lb/>expressed in nanomoles per gram of protein [10]. <lb/>3.6. Measurement of tissue glutathione (GSH) level <lb/>The determination of the GSH content in tissue samples, each weighing approximately 100 mg was accomplished <lb/>Fig. 1. The surviving flap area was determined using Image-Pro Express program (Version 6.0, Media Cybernetics, USA). (a) Represents the Sham <lb/>group, and (b) the Carnitine group. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A.A. Eyuboglu et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>spectrophotometrically employing Ellman&apos;s method. In this assay, thiols within the samples reacted with 5,5′-dithiobis-(2-nitrobenzoic <lb/>acid) (DTNB), resulting in the formation of a colored anion with a maximum peak absorbance at 412 nm. The GSH levels were <lb/>quantified via a standard calibration curve and reported in units of nanomoles per milligram of protein [11]. <lb/>Fig. 2. Histopathological examination of two experimental groups. (A) Displays the histopathological view of the Sham group with hematoxylin and <lb/>eosin (HE) staining, original magnification × 10. (Black arrow indicates discolored collagen bundles; brown arrow indicates polymorphonuclear <lb/>leukocyte [PMNL] infiltration; blue arrow indicates edema.) (B) Shows the Sham group histopathological view with Mallory Azan (MA) staining, <lb/>original magnification × 10. (Yellow arrow points to discolored collagen bundles, and &apos;Hf&apos; indicates degenerated hair follicle.) (C) Depicts the <lb/>Carnitine group histopathological view with HE staining, original magnification × 10. (Black arrow signifies a significant difference from the sham <lb/>group in collagen structure, while the brown arrow indicates significantly reduced PMNL infiltration compared to the sham group.) (D) Presents the <lb/>Carnitine group histopathological view with MA staining, original magnification × 10. (Yellow arrow signifies a significant difference from the sham <lb/>group in collagen structure, and &apos;Hf&apos; represents a significant difference from the sham group in hair follicle degeneration.) (E) Shows anti-inducible <lb/>nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) staining in the Sham group, original magnification × 40. (Red arrow points to anti-iNOS [+] endothelial cells.) (F) <lb/>Displays anti-iNOS staining in the Carnitine group, original magnification × 40. (Red arrow again indicates anti-iNOS [+] endothelial cells.). (For <lb/>interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A.A. Eyuboglu et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.7. Nitric Oxide Assay (NO) <lb/>Tissue samples, weighing approximately 100 mg, were collected from the distal portion of the muscle and skin paddle at the 24-h <lb/>mark. The measurement of tissue nitric oxide levels was conducted using the Nitric Oxide Assay kit from Abcam, which relies on the <lb/>Greiss reagent method. The absorbance was recorded spectrophotometrically at a wavelength of 540 nm, and the tissue&apos;s nitric oxide <lb/>content was quantified and reported in micromoles per milligram of tissue [9]. <lb/>3.8. Myeloperoxidase level (MPO) <lb/>Tissue-associated MPO level was determined using a method like that described by Hillegas et al. [12] Tissue samples were ho-<lb/>mogenized in 50 mM potassium phosphate buffer (PB; pH 6.0) and then centrifuged at 41,400 g for 10 min. The resulting pellets were <lb/>reconstituted in 50 mM PB containing 0.5% hexadecyltrimethylammonium bromide. After subjecting the samples to three freeze-thaw <lb/>cycles with sonication between cycles, they were once again centrifuged at 41,400 g for 10 min. Subsequently, 0.3 mL aliquots of the <lb/>prepared samples were combined with a 2.3 mL reaction mixture composed of 50 mM PB, o-dianisidine, and a 20 mM H 2 O 2 solution. <lb/>One unit of enzyme level was defined as the quantity of MPO that brought about a change in absorbance, measured at 460 nm, over a <lb/>period of 3 min. MPO level was reported in units per gram of tissue (U/g tissue). <lb/>3.9. Peripheral neutrophil count <lb/>Peripheral blood was collected at the 24-h mark to prepare smears, which were subsequently stained with Wright-Giemsa stain for <lb/>assessing circulating neutrophils. On each slide, five fields were randomly chosen at high-power-field (200x) magnification, and <lb/>neutrophil counts were manually conducted. The circulating neutrophil count was computed as 1000 times the average value obtained <lb/>from these counts [9]. <lb/>3.10. Histopathological analysis <lb/>Histopathological analyses were conducted following the methodology as outlined by Ersel et al. [13] Following the fixation of skin <lb/>biopsy samples in 10% buffered formalin for 24 h, standard paraffin wax embedding procedures were employed and the specimens <lb/>were sectioned. Sections of approximately 5 μm thickness were obtained using a Leica RM2145 microtome from Germany. These <lb/>sections were subsequently subjected to staining with both hematoxylin and eosin, as well as Mallory Azan stains. The evaluation of the <lb/>hematoxylin and eosin-and Mallory Azan-stained sections involved the use of a light microscope (Olympus BX-51 light microscope, <lb/>Olympus C-5050 digital camera) to assess features such as necrosis, edema, polymorphonuclear leukocyte (PMNL) infiltration and <lb/>vascularization, employing a modified Verhofstad scoring system [9]. (Table 1). For the immunohistochemical analysis of inducible <lb/>nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) expression, paraffin sections underwent deparaffinization in xylene overnight to quench endogenous <lb/>peroxidase activity. Following this, they were immersed in a solution containing 3% H2O2 in methanol. To retrieve antigenicity, the <lb/>sections were subjected to heat-induced epitope retrieval in a sodium citrate solution within a microwave oven, initially at 90 W for 5 <lb/>min, followed by 360 W for 15 min. Next, the sections were incubated with the primary antibody (anti-iNOS, 1/100 dilution) for 24 h <lb/>at 4 • C. Detection of the antibody was accomplished using the Histostain-Plus Bulk Kit from Bioss, Inc., with a secondary antibody <lb/>specific for rabbit immunoglobulin G. The visualization of the immunoreaction was achieved using 3,3′-diaminobenzidine. The <lb/>evaluation of immunoreactivity was performed under light microscopy at both ×10 and ×40 magnifications using an Olympus BX-51 <lb/>light microscope coupled with an Olympus C-5050 digital camera. <lb/>4. Statistical analysis <lb/>Statistical analysis was conducted using Student&apos;s T-test to compare two groups. Differences among groups with respect to pa-<lb/>rameters such as flap survival areas, modified Verhofstad scores, NO, GSH, MPO, MDA levels and tissue neutrophil counts were <lb/>assessed through one-way ANOVA. In cases where the p-value from the variance analysis indicated statistical significance, post hoc <lb/>Tukey tests were employed for further comparisons. Results are presented as mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM), and statistical <lb/>significance was defined as p &lt; 0.05. <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Histopathological scoring system, modified Verhofstad Scoring. <lb/>Score <lb/>Necrosis <lb/>Edema <lb/>PMNL a <lb/>Vascularization <lb/>0 <lb/>None <lb/>None <lb/>Normal <lb/>None <lb/>1 <lb/>Superficial <lb/>Light <lb/>Light <lb/>Light <lb/>2 <lb/>Pronounced <lb/>Pronounced <lb/>Pronounced <lb/>Pronounced <lb/>3 <lb/>Massive <lb/>Dense <lb/>Massive <lb/>Dense <lb/>a PMNL -polymorph nuclear leukocytes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A.A. Eyuboglu et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>5. Results <lb/>Throughout the study, no fatalities among the rats were recorded, and no complications were observed. <lb/>5.1. Flap survival area <lb/>The flap survival area (23.47 cm 2 ) was calculated by subtracting the necrotic region from the total flap area. In the sham group, the <lb/>mean survival area measured 8.98 ± 1.6 cm 2 , while in the PLC group, it was notably larger at 16.2 ± 2.3 cm 2 . This disparity between <lb/>the results was found to be statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05). <lb/>5.2. Biochemical assessments <lb/>In the sham group, the mean MDA level was 146.2 ± 12.7 nmol/g, GSH level was 1.4 ± 0.9 nmol/g, MPO was 30.8 ± 5.1 U/g, and <lb/>NO level was 21.5 ± 6.05 μM/mg of tissue. Conversely, in the PLC group, the mean MDA level was 118.6 ± 11.2 nmol/g, GSH level <lb/>was 2.3 ± 0.1 nmol/g, MPO was 23.2 ± 4.8 U/g, and NO level was 29.2 ± 9.7 μM/mg of tissue. Notably, statistically significant <lb/>differences were observed between the two groups across all of these parameters (Table 2). <lb/>5.3. Peripheral neutrophil count assessment <lb/>In the sham group, the peripheral neutrophil count averaged 23,643 ± 1780 cells/μL, while in the PLC group, it measured 20,425 <lb/>± 1355 cells/μL. Significantly, the disparity between these findings was supported by a p-value of &lt;0.05. <lb/>5.4. Histopathological examination <lb/>In an examination of necrosis, edema, PMNL infiltration and vascularization in samples collected from 16 subjects, with eight in <lb/>each group (PLC and sham), it became evident that the scores for these parameters were in proximity. The average necrosis values for <lb/>the 16 subjects ranged from 0 to 3, with readings of 2 ± 0.5 for the PLC group and 3.75 ± 0.4 for the sham group. In the sham group, <lb/>the scores for edema, PMNL and vascularization were 3.62 ± 0.5, 3.1 ± 0.8 and 1 ± 0.9 respectively. On the other hand, the PLC group <lb/>exhibited mean scores of 1.75 ± 0.4 for edema, 1.87 ± 0.5 for PMNL infiltration, and 2.37 ± 0.7 for vascularization. Consequently, it is <lb/>apparent that statistically significant differences were identified for all these parameters between the sham and PLC groups (p &lt; 0.05) <lb/>(Table 3; Fig. 2). <lb/>6. Discussion <lb/>The success rate of free tissue applications, a commonly practiced procedure in recent years, typically ranges between 97% and <lb/>87%. However, it is noteworthy that partial or complete flap losses in pedicle flaps, along with associated complications can occur at <lb/>rates as high as 25%. These outcomes are primarily attributed to insufficient perfusion and ischemic damage that can trigger various <lb/>tissue and vascular alterations which ultimately results flap necrosis [14]. <lb/>Ischemia/reperfusion injury stands as a pivotal factor significantly influencing flap survival. This intricate process gives rise to the <lb/>generation of ROS and various harmful substances which in turn trigger processes like apoptosis or necroptosis, leading to cellular <lb/>damage or demise. A decrease in microcirculation can ultimately result in partial or complete flap necrosis. Antioxidant agents play a <lb/>crucial role in mitigating the impact of ROS. This includes their ability to counteract oxygen ions, peroxides, free radicals and other <lb/>byproducts, which tend to exacerbate complement activation, leukocyte-endothelial cell adhesion, platelet-leukocyte aggregation and <lb/>microvascular permeability during reperfusion following an ischemic period [ [15]. Modern research efforts have delved extensively <lb/>into the exploration of endogenous and exogenous agents capable of alleviating or diminishing the oxidative damage inflicted by free <lb/>radicals on crucial cellular components. These components include DNA, proteins, lipids and various other vital constituents [16-19]. <lb/>L-carnitine plays several vital metabolic roles within the body, with one of the most extensively studied being its function in <lb/>transporting long-chain fatty acids into the mitochondria&apos;s inner compartment. This process is crucial for the β-oxidation reaction and <lb/>subsequent energy production. Early reports suggest that propionyl-L-carnitine may act by improving myocardial energy metabolism, <lb/>reducing oxidative stress and enhancing endothelial function. One study found that propionyl-L-carnitine improved glucose oxidation <lb/>and reduced the intramitochondrial ratio of acetyl-CoA to free CoA, which stimulated the activity of pyruvate dehydrogenase and <lb/>increased the oxidation of pyruvate [20]. Another study found that propionyl-L-carnitine reduced myocardial injury by counteracting <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Biochemical assesment of mean malondialdehyde (MDA) levels, tissue glutathione (GSH) levels, myeloperoxidase level (MPO) and nitric oxide (NO) <lb/>of sham and Propionyl-L-carnitine (PLC) group. <lb/>Biochemical Parameters <lb/>Mean MDA (nmol/g) <lb/>GSH level (nmol/g) <lb/>MPO level (U/g) <lb/>NO level (μM/mg) <lb/>Sham group <lb/>146.2 ± 12.7 <lb/>1.4 ± 0.9 <lb/>30.8 ± 5.1 <lb/>21.5 ± 6.05 <lb/>PLC group <lb/>*118.6 ± 11.2 <lb/>*2.3 ± 0.1 <lb/>*23.2 ± 4.8 <lb/>*29.2 ± 9.7 <lb/>*p &lt; 0.05. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A.A. Eyuboglu et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>the toxic effect of high levels of free fatty acids, which occur in ischemia, and by improving carbohydrate metabolism [21]. Propio-<lb/>nyl-L-carnitine also exerts beneficial effects on fatty acid turnover. It has been observed that the peroxidation of fatty acids in ischemic <lb/>tissue can lead to the generation of free oxygen radicals, which directly contribute to oxidative damage to cellular macromolecules, <lb/>including nucleic acids, proteins and lipids. In the 20th century, a notable interest arose in assessing the potential effects of PLC in <lb/>preventing I/R injuries. Numerous studies in clinical and experimental settings have explored the protective effects of PLC against <lb/>I/R-induced heart injuries and these investigations have often encompassed other organs as well [4,20,21]. <lb/>This study aimed to evaluate the impact of PLC on ischemia-reperfusion injury within rat epigastric island flaps, encompassing <lb/>various macroscopic, biochemical and histopathological parameters. The investigation provides empirical support for the hypothesis <lb/>that pre-ischemic administration of L-carnitine reduces I/R injury in rat epigastric flaps. To achieve this, we surgically raised 6 × 4 cm <lb/>epigastric flaps in rats and conducted a comprehensive assessment that included biochemical, histopathological and macroscopic <lb/>evaluations following a 10-h period of ischemia, consistent with the methodology applied in our prior studies [8,9,14,15]. <lb/>The designated global ischemia duration for the skin flap was established as 10 h and accordingly, a 10-h ischemic period was <lb/>implemented in our experimental design. Commencing 24 h post-reperfusion, biochemical analyses were initiated due to the recog-<lb/>nition that the levels of oxidant products or end products attain their zenith during the 24-h reperfusion period. Histopathological <lb/>changes, encompassing angiogenesis, inflammation and edema commenced on the 5th day of the experimental timeline. Conse-<lb/>quently, a histopathological assessment was conducted on the 10 t h day to systematically evaluate the temporal progression of <lb/>observed physiological alterations [3,5,9,14,15]. Biochemical measurements were taken from the right side of the flaps 24 h after <lb/>reperfusion, while the evaluation of necrotic areas on the left side of the flaps was carried out prior to obtaining samples for histo-<lb/>chemical analysis on the tenth postoperative day. This method was employed to enhance the objectivity in quantifying flap necrotic <lb/>areas. The macroscopic assessment of flap survival areas was performed using the Image-pro express program (Version 6.0, Media <lb/>Cybernetics, USA). The results showed statistically significant differences in flap survival areas between the PLC group and the sham <lb/>group. <lb/>Detecting the presence of free oxygen radicals has been a challenging task owing to their short half-lives. To address this, we turned <lb/>to the measurement of MDA, which serves as an indicator of the product of lipid peroxidation within cells. Malondialdehyde levels are <lb/>known to increase in tandem with the presence of free oxygen radicals in I/R injury. Thus, we utilized MDA measurements as a method <lb/>to evaluate reperfusion injury [8,15]. Significantly, the PLC group demonstrated a notably lower MDA level in comparison to the sham <lb/>group. It is important to highlight that glutathione (GSH) plays a critical role as an intracellular antioxidant, effectively countering free <lb/>radicals and oxygen-derived products [22]. In accordance with consistency, Kurt et al. [23] reported elevated lipid peroxidation and <lb/>diminished tissue GSH levels in animals subjected to I/R injury. <lb/>In the context of this study, it is noteworthy that GSH levels exhibited a significant increase in the PLC group compared to the sham <lb/>group. Myeloperoxidase is typically found within azurophilic granules in neutrophils and lysosomes in monocytes. The release of MPO <lb/>from neutrophils during episodes of inflammation can have detrimental effects on cells. MPO has been utilized in certain investigations <lb/>as a marker for ischemia-reperfusion injury. For instance, Matthijsen et al. [24] established a positive correlation between I/R injury in <lb/>rats and MPO levels, underscoring its significance in assessing such injuries. Gorur et al. [25] have presented an extensive overview of <lb/>the results from their experimental study, which focused on the effects of PLC preconditioning on renal ischemia-reperfusion injury in <lb/>rats. Their research has demonstrated a notable reduction in tissue malondialdehyde, myeloperoxidase and nitric oxide levels in <lb/>animals that underwent L-carnitine pretreatment before the induction of renal ischemia-reperfusion injury, as compared to the control <lb/>group. <lb/>Nitric oxide plays a vital role by exerting antioxidative properties through the inhibition of leukocyte activation and by enhancing <lb/>superoxide anion production [26]. It is important to note that ROS are recognized for their ability to reduce NO levels [8]. In a study <lb/>conducted by Lille et al. [27], a reduction in muscle-flap ischemia-reperfusion injury was observed, accompanied by an elevation in <lb/>cyclic adenosine monophosphate and NO levels. Additionally, Khiabani et al. [28] reported a positive correlation between the survival <lb/>of random skin flaps and NO levels. In the present study, the PLC group demonstrated higher NO levels in comparison to the sham <lb/>group. <lb/>Histopathological assessment revealed a substantial increase in inflammation and reperfusion injury parameters, including ne-<lb/>crosis, polymorphonuclear leukocyte (PMNL) infiltration, and edema, within the Sham group. Conversely, the PLC group displayed <lb/>reduced scores across these categories, indicating the robust ability of PLC to prevent reperfusion injury through its anti-inflammatory <lb/>effects. Notably, the PLC group also exhibited an evident enhancement in vascularity, suggesting that PLC promotes increased blood <lb/>supply, thereby ameliorating the effects of ischemia. Neutrophils play a role in impeding tissue perfusion due to capillary obstruction <lb/>and an elevated neutrophil count is a common characteristic of ischemia-reperfusion injury [ [8,9]]. The reduction in neutrophil count <lb/>observed in the PLC group signifies a beneficial impact on I/R injury. This reduction in neutrophil count is indicative of a favorable <lb/>outcome, suggesting that PLC exerts a protective effect against I/R injury by modulating the neutrophil response. <lb/>Table 3 <lb/>Histopatological examination of sham and Propionyl-L-carnitine (PLC) group involving necrosis, edema, polymorphonuclear leukocyte (PMNL) <lb/>infiltration, vascularization. <lb/>Histopatological examination <lb/>Necrosis <lb/>Edema <lb/>PMNL <lb/>Vascularization <lb/>Sham group <lb/>3.75 ± 0.4 <lb/>3.62 ± 0.5 <lb/>3.1 ± 0.8 <lb/>1 ± 0.9 <lb/>PLC group <lb/>*2 ± 0.5 <lb/>*1.75 ± 0.4 <lb/>*1.87 ± 0.5 <lb/>*2.37 ± 0.7 <lb/>*p &lt; 0.05. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A.A. Eyuboglu et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>While multiple prior studies have indeed highlighted the impact of PLC on I/R damage, it is worth noting that, to the best of our <lb/>knowledge, this study represents the first all-encompassing examination of its effectiveness at macroscopic, biochemical, and histo-<lb/>logical levels. However, it is important to acknowledge certain limitations within the current investigation. Firstly, the sample size was <lb/>relatively small. Secondly, the assessment was confined to macroscopic necrotic areas and the evaluation of histological and <lb/>biochemical markers. Subsequent research is imperative to provide further validation of the innovative therapeutic potential of PLC in <lb/>the realm of I/R injuries. <lb/>7. Conclusion <lb/>In summary, this study underscores the prospective clinical utility of Propionyl-L-carnitine in mitigating the adverse consequences <lb/>of I/R injury. This application is especially pertinent in the realm of reconstructive surgery, where tissue flaps are frequently employed. <lb/>Ethical approval <lb/>This study is approved by Demiroglu Science University Ethical Committee as study number #1217015402. All procedures per-<lb/>formed in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional and/or national research committee. <lb/></body>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>No funding was received. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Additional information <lb/>No additional information is available for this paper. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">8. Data availability statement <lb/>There is no research related data stored in publicly available repositories, and the data will be made available on request. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>Atilla Adnan Eyuboglu: Writing -review &amp; editing, Writing -original draft, Visualization, Validation, Supervision, Methodology, <lb/>Investigation, Funding acquisition. Ovunc Akdemir: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Validation, Software, Resources, Project <lb/>administration, Methodology, Investigation, Funding acquisition, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. Oytun Erbas: <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing, Visualization, Software, Methodology. Mustafa Tonguc Isken: Writing -review &amp; editing, Visualization, <lb/>Supervision. Feng Zhang: Supervision, Software, Investigation, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. William C. Lin-<lb/>eaweaver: Visualization, Project administration, Methodology, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to <lb/>influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

            <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>Not available. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] W.A. Zamboni, A.C. Roth, R.C. Russel, B. Graham, H. Suchy, J.O. Kucan, Morphologic analysis of the microcirculation during reperfusion of ischemic skeletal <lb/>muscle and the effect of hyperbaric oxygen, Plast. Reconstr. Surg. 91 (1993) 1110. <lb/>[2] C. Wallner, M. Drysch, M. Becerikli, S.V. Schmidt, S. Hahn, J.M. Wagner, F. Reinkemeier, M. Dadras, A. Sogorski, M. von Glinski, M. Lehnhardt, B. Behr, <lb/>Deficiency of myostatin protects skeletal muscle cells from ischemia reperfusion injury, Sci. Rep. 11 (1) (2021) 12572, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-<lb/>92159-2. <lb/>[3] G. Zhao, X. Zhang, P. Xu, J.-Y. Mi, Y.-J. Rui, The protective effect of irisin against ischemia-reperfusion injury after perforator flap grafting in rats, Injury 49 (12) <lb/>(2018) 2147-2153. <lb/>[4] A. Moghaddas, S. Dashti-Khavidaki, L-Carnitine and potential protective effects against ischemia-reperfusion injury in noncardiac organs: from experimental <lb/>data to potential clinical applications, J. Diet. Suppl. 15 (5) (2018) 740-756, https://doi.org/10.1080/19390211.2017.1359221. <lb/>[5] Mayes PA. Lipids of physiologic significance. In: Murray RK, Granner DK, Mayes PA, Rodwell VW (Eds), Harper&apos;s Biochemistry. 25th edn. Appleton and Lange, <lb/>Stanford; pp. 160e171.. <lb/>[6] I. Gulcin, Antioxidant and antiradical activities of L-carnitine, Life Sci. 78 (8) (2006) 803-811, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lfs.2005.05.103. <lb/>[7] A. Moghaddas, S. Dashti-Khavidaki, Potential protective effects of l-carnitine against neuromuscular ischemia-reperfusion injury: from experimental data to <lb/>potential clinical applications, Clin. Nutr. 35 (4) (2016) 783-790, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clnu.2015.07.001. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">A.A. Eyuboglu et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27448 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[8] O. Akdemir, B.E. Tatar, A. Gokhan, et al., Preventive effect of trimetazidine against ischemia-reperfusion injury in rat epigastric island flaps: an experimental <lb/>study, Eur. J. Plast. Surg. 44 (2019) 177-188. <lb/>[9] O. Akdemir, B.E. Tatar, Y. Uyanikgil, et al., Preventive effect of edaravone against ischemia-reperfusion injury in rat epigastric island flaps: an experimental <lb/>study, Genel Tıp Derg. 33 (2) (2020) 117-122. <lb/>[10] C. Demougeot, C. Marie, A. Beley, Importance of iron location in iron-induced hydroxyl radical production by brain slices, Life Sci. 67 (2000) 399-410. <lb/>[11] G.L. Ellman, Tissue sulfhydryl groups, Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 82 (1959) 70-77. <lb/>[12] L.M. Hillegass, D.E. Griswold, B. Brickson, C. Albrightson-Winslow, Assessment of myeloperoxidase activity in whole rat kidney, J. Pharmacol. Methods 24 <lb/>(1990) 285-295. <lb/>[13] M. Ersel, Y. Uyanikgil, F.K. Akarca, E. Ozcete, Y.A. Altunci, F. Karabey, et al., Effects of silk sericin on incision wound healing in a dorsal skin flap wound healing <lb/>rat model, Med. Sci. Mon. Int. Med. J. Exp. Clin. Res. 22 (2016) 1064-1078. <lb/>[14] O. Akdemir, H. Yan, F. Zhang, W.C. Lineaweaver, The effect of taurine on reperfusion injury, J. Plast. Reconstr. Aesthetic Surg. 64 (7) (2011) 921-928. <lb/>[15] M. Seyid, Y. Tiftikcioglu, M. Erdem, O. Akdemir, B.E. Tatar, Y. Uyanikgil, G. Ercan, The effect of ceruloplasmin against ischemia-reperfusion injury in epigastric <lb/>island flap in rats, J. Surg. Res. 267 (2021) 627-635. <lb/>[16] M.F. Angel, S.S. Ramasastry, W.M. Swartz, et al., Augmentation of skin flap with allopurinol, Ann. Plast. Surg. 18 (1987) 494-498. <lb/>[17] C.J. Green, L. Dhami, S. Prasad, G. Healing, C. Shurey, The effect of desferrioxamine on lipid peroxidation and survival of ischemic island skin flaps in rats, Br. J. <lb/>Plast. Surg. 42 (1989) 565-569. <lb/>[18] E.G. Wilkins, R.S. Rees, B. Cashmer, et al., Identification of xanthine oxidase activity following reperfusion in human tissue, Ann. Plast. Surg. 31 (1) (1993; Jul) <lb/>60-65. <lb/>[19] H. Yan, F. Zhang, A.J. Kochevar, O. Akdemir, W. Gao, M. Angel, The effect of postconditioning on the muscle flap survival after ischemia-reperfusion injury in <lb/>rats, J. Invest. Surg. 23 (5) (2010) 249-256. <lb/>[20] R. Ferrari, E. Merli, G. Cicchitelli, D. Mele, A. Fucili, C. Ceconi, Therapeutic effects of L-carnitine and PLC on cardiovascular diseases: a review, Ann. N. Y. Acad. <lb/>Sci. 1033 (1) (2004) 79-91. <lb/>[21] M. Najafi, Effects of postconditioning, preconditioning and perfusion of L-carnitine during whole period of ischemia/reperfusion on cardiac hemodynamic <lb/>functions and myocardial infarction size in isolated rat heart, Iran J Basic Med Sci 16 (4) (2013) 640. <lb/>[22] Y.K. Coban, Y. Ergun, H. Ciralik, Depletion of glutathione by buthionine sulfoximine decreases random-pattern skin flap viability in rats, J. Surg. Res. 143 (2) <lb/>(2007) 247-252. <lb/>[23] G. Kurt, E. Ergun, B. Cemil, A.O. Borcek, P. Borcek, O. Gulbahar, N. Ceviker, Neuroprotective effects of infliximab in experimental spinal cord injury, Surg. <lb/>Neurol. 71 (3) (2009) 332-336. <lb/>[24] R.A. Matthijsen, D. Huugen, N.T. Hoebers, B. De Vries, C.J. Peutz-Kootstra, Y. Aratani, M.R. Daha, J.W.C. Tervaert, W.A. Buurman, P. Heeringa, <lb/>Myeloperoxidase is critically involved in the induction of organ damage after renal ischemia reperfusion, Am. J. Pathol. 171 (6) (2007) 1743-1752. <lb/>[25] S. Gorur, O.T. Bagdatoglu, G. Polat, Protective effect of L-carnitine on renal ischemia-reperfusion injury in the rat, Cell Biochem. Funct. 23 (3) (2005 May-Jun) <lb/>151-155. <lb/>[26] R. Schulz, M. Kelm, G. Heusch, Nitric oxide in myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury, Cardiovasc. Res. 61 (3) (2004) 402-413. <lb/>[27] S. Lille, E.M. Boyle, T. Schoeller, H. Suchy, R.C. Russell, Augmentation of cAMP improves muscle-flap survival and tissue inflammation in response to ischemia/ <lb/>reperfusion injury, J. Reconstr. Microsurg. 15 (1) (1999) 37-45. <lb/>[28] K.T. Khiabani, C.L. Kerrigan, Presence and activity of nitric oxide synthase isoforms in ischemia-reperfusion-injured flaps, Plast. Reconstr. Surg. 109 (5) (2002) <lb/>1638-1645. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">A.A. Eyuboglu et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
