<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Imported malaria in the UK, 2005 to 2016: <lb/>Estimates from primary care electronic <lb/>health records <lb/>Hamad Bastaki ID <lb/>1 <lb/>*, Louise Marston 1 , Jackie Cassell 2 , Greta Rait 1 <lb/>1 Research Department of Primary Care and Population Health, University College London, London, United <lb/>Kingdom, 2 Division of Primary Care and Public Health, Brighton and Sussex Medical School, University of <lb/>Brighton, Brighton, United Kingdom <lb/>* h.bastaki@ucl.ac.uk <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Objective <lb/>To investigate trends in the incidence of imported malaria in the UK between 2005 and 2016. <lb/>Design <lb/>Analysis of longitudinal electronic health records (EHRs) in The Health Improvement Net-<lb/>work (THIN) primary care database. <lb/>Setting <lb/>UK primary care <lb/>Participants <lb/>In total, we examined 12,349,003 individuals aged 0 to 99 years. <lb/>Outcome measure <lb/>The rate of malaria recordings in THIN was calculated per year between 2005 and 2016. <lb/>Rate ratios exploring differences by age, sex, location of general practice, socioeconomic <lb/>status and ethnicity were estimated using multivariable Poisson regression. <lb/>Results <lb/>A total of 1,474 individuals with a first diagnosis of malaria were identified in THIN between <lb/>2005 and 2016. The incidence of recorded malaria followed a decreasing trend dropping <lb/>from a rate of 3.33 in 2005 to 1.36 cases per 100,000 person years at risk in 2016. Multivari-<lb/>able Poisson regression showed that adults of working age (20 to 69 years), men, those reg-<lb/>istered with a general practice in London, higher social deprivation and non-white ethnicity <lb/>were associated with higher rates of malaria recordings. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>There has been a decrease in the number of malaria recordings in UK primary care over the <lb/>past decade. This decrease exceeds the rate of decline reported in national surveillance <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/>1 / 14 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Bastaki H, Marston L, Cassell J, Rait G <lb/>(2018) Imported malaria in the UK, 2005 to 2016: <lb/>Estimates from primary care electronic <lb/>health records. PLoS ONE 13(12): e0210040. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 <lb/>Editor: Sreeram V. Ramagopalan, University of <lb/>Oxford, UNITED KINGDOM <lb/>Received: November 5, 2018 <lb/>Accepted: December 14, 2018 <lb/>Published: December 31, 2018 <lb/>Copyright: © 2018 Bastaki et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: The authors have <lb/>obtained the data for this study from IQVIA through <lb/>a research license and do not own the dataset used <lb/>and do not have permission to share the data. <lb/>Access to THIN can be obtained through IQVIA by <lb/>applying for a research license. More information <lb/>on the availability of THIN data is available in the <lb/>following URL https://www.iqvia.com/locations/uk-<lb/>and-ireland/thin and permissions for data access <lb/>can be obtained through https://www.iqvia.com/ <lb/>contact/general. The authors accessed the data in <lb/>the same manner and had no special privileges to <lb/>the data. <lb/>data; however there are similar associations with age, sex and deprivation. Improved geo-<lb/>graphic information on the distribution of cases and the potential for automation of case <lb/>identification suggests that EHRs could provide a complementary role for investigating <lb/>malaria trends over time. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Globally, malaria affected 216 million individuals in 2016 and resulted in 445,000 deaths [1]. <lb/>Amongst non-endemic countries, the UK has one of the highest numbers of imported malaria <lb/>in Europe with around 1500 cases a year [2]. Despite a decreasing trend in the overall global <lb/>number of cases, it remains the most common imported infection in returning ill travellers in <lb/>Europe [3]. <lb/>In the UK, malaria is a notifiable disease and information on trends over time is usually <lb/>obtained from passive surveillance data on imported cases from the Malaria Reference Labora-<lb/>tory (MRL), supplemented more recently with cases reported to the Public Health England <lb/>(PHE) case management database (HPzone) [2, 4]. Reports on cases are completed by clini-<lb/>cians and laboratory staff with information on patient demographics, reason for travel, area <lb/>and duration of travel, and chemoprophylaxis use [5]. This surveillance method is associated <lb/>with underreporting since not all cases who seek healthcare are notified. A capture recapture <lb/>study estimated that only 56% of cases were captured by the MRL surveillance system [6], <lb/>with similar levels of underreporting in other European notification based surveillance systems <lb/>[7-9]. <lb/>Use of electronic health records (EHRs) may provide a complementary method of explor-<lb/>ing trends in malaria diagnoses over time. Although they have limitations, EHRs have been <lb/>widely used for observational research and several studies have used them for exploring trends <lb/>in the incidence of illnesses over time [10-13]. Data collection at the time of recording a <lb/>malaria diagnosis in primary care can result in the inclusion of unreported cases in the analysis <lb/>as it forgoes the added step of notification. Furthermore, it can provide insight into the num-<lb/>ber of cases seen in this setting. <lb/>Our aims were to investigate the incidence of imported malaria in the UK between 2005 <lb/>and 2016 using The Health Improvement Network (THIN) Primary care database; to explore <lb/>the variation in incidence by age, sex, UK region, socioeconomic status and ethnicity; and to <lb/>compare the characteristics of cases identified in THIN to those identified through passive <lb/>surveillance. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Data source <lb/>Relevant data were extracted from THIN. THIN contains anonymised EHRs of around 12 mil-<lb/>lion patients attending 693 general practices participating in the network [14]. It has coverage <lb/>of around 6% of the UK population and has been shown to be broadly representative of the <lb/>UK population in terms of demographics and prevalence of major conditions [15]. Data in <lb/>THIN are collected routinely from consultations in general practice and consist of information <lb/>on individual patient characteristics, medical information such as symptoms and diagnoses of <lb/>disease, investigations ordered and medication prescribed. Data are coded using Read codes, a <lb/>standard vocabulary list clinician&apos;s use to record medical information; and drug codes, based <lb/>on the British National Formulary classifications for medication. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<front>Funding: The authors received no specific funding <lb/>for this work. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>Study population <lb/>General practices that contributed data to THIN between January 2005 and December 2016 <lb/>were used for this study. The quality of the data included was assessed using the acceptable <lb/>computer usage (ACU) dates [16] and the acceptable mortality recording (AMR) dates [17]. <lb/>The ACU date refers to the date when general practices use their computer systems adequately <lb/>for recording clinical data. In THIN, this was defined as the date where at least one medical <lb/>record, one additional health data (AHD) record and two therapy records are consistently <lb/>recorded per patient per year[16]. The AMR date refers to the date from which the mortality <lb/>recordings of a general practice are deemed complete. In THIN, this was defined as the date <lb/>the mortality recordings within the general practice was similar to what the expected mortality <lb/>would be in the general population using the Office for National Statistics data, taking into <lb/>account the characteristics of the patients within that practice [17]. Practices were included <lb/>after the latter of the ACU and AMR date. Additionally, information on postcode linked socio-<lb/>economic indices (Townsend Score) was not available for 17 practices and they were excluded <lb/>from the analysis. <lb/>Participants <lb/>All individuals aged 0-99 years that were registered with a general practice contributing data <lb/>between 2005 and 2016 were included in the analysis. <lb/>Case definition. Cases of malaria in primary care may be indicated by diagnostic codes, <lb/>or a combination of investigation and treatment codes. An algorithm was developed to identify <lb/>individuals diagnosed with malaria within THIN based on having any of the following records <lb/>(Fig 1): <lb/>• A diagnostic Read code for malaria: <lb/>A Read code list indicating a diagnosis of malaria was developed (S1 Table). Those with a <lb/>malaria diagnostic Read code within their medical records were considered to have a diagno-<lb/>sis of malaria. The date that malaria was first recorded was considered the index date of <lb/>diagnosis. <lb/>• A code for malaria investigation followed by treatment for malaria within 60 days: <lb/>In order to capture potential cases that did not have a diagnostic Read code for malaria, <lb/>those with an AHD code or Read code for malaria specific investigations were identified <lb/>(S1 Table). In records where a laboratory test is ordered with no result reported in THIN, it <lb/>was assumed that the individual had a diagnosis of malaria if an antimalarial was prescribed <lb/>within two months after the date the test was ordered. The antimalarials prescribed were <lb/>identified using a drug code list developed based on chapter 5.4.1 of the British National For-<lb/>mulary (BNF) (S1 Table) [18]. Although some of these medications can be used for prophy-<lb/>laxis, the preceding indication for ordering the malaria specific investigation makes this <lb/>unlikely. The date the antimalarial was prescribed was considered the index date of diagnosis <lb/>in those who were investigated for malaria. <lb/>• A prescription for artemesinin-based combination therapy (ACT). <lb/>Artemesinin-based combination therapy is the recommended treatment for those with P. <lb/>falciparum infection and for non-falciparum malaria if the area of infection is known to have <lb/>chloroquine resistance [19]. The drug codes in THIN were searched to identify all ACTs <lb/>recorded in the database and only artemether-lumefantrine was identified. Artemether-<lb/>lumefantrine is the drug of choice for treating uncomplicated P. falciparum and is licensed <lb/>solely for the treatment of malaria [18]. It was assumed that the individual had a diagnosis of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>malaria if they received a prescription for artemether-lumefantrine. The date this was pre-<lb/>scribed was considered to be the index date of diagnosis. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>The overall crude incidence of malaria was estimated per 100,000 person years at risk (PYAR). <lb/>This was determined by totalling the number of patients with a first recording of malaria <lb/>between 2005 and 2016, and then dividing this number by the total person years of follow-up <lb/>for all patient records for this period. The start date used to calculate the total PYAR for each <lb/>participant was the latest of: <lb/>• The date the individual registered with their current general practice <lb/>• The date the practice reached AMR <lb/>• The date the practice reached ACU <lb/>• The 1 st of January 2005 <lb/>The end date used to calculate the total PYAR for each participant was the earliest of: <lb/>• The date the individual transferred to a different practice to the one included in the analysis. <lb/>• The date of death recorded in the practice. <lb/>Fig 1. An algorithm summarising how malaria cases were identified within THIN database. THIN: The Health Improvement Network, ACT: <lb/>Artemesinin-based combination therapy. To minimise the effect of miscoding a diagnosis of malaria for a pre-travel malaria advice consultation, those <lb/>with a prescription for a travel vaccination issued on the same day as a malaria recording were excluded (S1 Table). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>• The last date the practice contributed data to THIN. <lb/>• The index date of diagnosis in those who have malaria <lb/>• The 31 st of December 2016 <lb/>Crude incidence rates by calendar year, age group (&lt;10, 10-19, 20-29, 30-39, 40-49, 50-<lb/>59, 60-69, 70-79, 80-89 and &gt;90 years), sex (male and female), level of social deprivation <lb/>(Townsend Score; a measure which incorporates unemployment, car ownership, home owner-<lb/>ship and household overcrowding to calculate area-level deprivation. The score ranges from 1 <lb/>to 5 with 1 being the least deprived and 5 indicating the greatest degree of deprivation) region <lb/>(based on former strategic health authority location; London, East Midlands, East of England, <lb/>North East, North West, Northern Ireland, Scotland, South Central, South East Coast, South <lb/>West, Wales, West Midlands and Yorkshire and Humber) and ethnicity (Grouped into the <lb/>2001 UK census 5 category classification: White, Black, Asian, Other and Mixed) were also <lb/>estimated by restricting the person years of follow-up to the respective category in question. <lb/>Multivariable Poisson regression analysis was carried out to explore the change in incidence <lb/>by calendar year, age group, sex, region and Townsend score mutually adjusting for the other <lb/>variables included in this model. Ethnicity was not included in the model as the data quality <lb/>was poor with missing data in 40% of cases. To fit the Poisson model to calculate a rate ratio, <lb/>the coefficients were exponentiated with person-time specified as the exposure. <lb/>Additionally a sensitivity analysis was conducted to take into account multiple episodes of <lb/>malaria in the same individual. It was considered an individual had an additional episode of <lb/>malaria if they had a diagnostic Read code for malaria at least three months after the previous <lb/>recording. In these individuals, the start date used to calculate PYAR commenced three <lb/>months after the date of the previous event as they were not considered to be at risk during <lb/>that three month period. <lb/>All statistical analyses were carried out using Stata version 14 [20]. <lb/>Comparison with national surveillance data <lb/>Data on the number of malaria cases imported to the United Kingdom from 2005 to 2016 by <lb/>UK region was obtained from the PHE Travel and Migrant section. In the absence of an equiv-<lb/>alent denominator for PYAR to estimate incidence for PHE data, we compared the number of <lb/>cases by year and UK region as a proportion of the total number of cases for each dataset from <lb/>2005 to 2016 to describe the variation in the number of cases identified over time, and their <lb/>geographical spread in THIN compared to those notified to PHE. <lb/>Ethics <lb/>THIN data collection has been approved by the South East NHS Multicentre Research Ethics <lb/>Committee. Scientific approval for this study was obtained from the IMS Heath Scientific <lb/>review committee in 2016 (ref: SRC 16THIN056). <lb/>Results <lb/>A total of 1,806 individuals with a first diagnosis of malaria were identified in THIN between <lb/>2005 and 2016, with 1,474 cases included in the final analysis after excluding those with a code <lb/>for a travel vaccination on the index date of diagnosis or were missing sociodemographic data. <lb/>A summary of the number of cases identified at each stage of the algorithm is shown in (Fig 2). <lb/>The incidence of recorded malaria followed a decreasing trend dropping from a rate of 3.33 <lb/>in 2005 to 1.36 cases per 100,000 person years at risk in 2016 (Fig 3). The incidence was higher <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>in those aged 20 to 69 compared to those less than 20 years or more than 70 years of age <lb/>(Table 1). Men experienced a higher rate of recorded malaria than women (IRR: 0.72 (95% CI <lb/>0.65-0.80), incidence per 100,000 PYAR; men 2.57, women 1.81). General Practices in London <lb/>and the East of England had the highest incidence (6.15 and 2.51 per 100,000 PYAR respec-<lb/>tively), while practices in Northern Ireland were 89% less likely to have a recording of malaria <lb/>compared to London (IRR: 0.11 (95% CI 0.07-0.18), incidence per 100,000 PYAR: 0.63) <lb/>(Table 1, S1 Fig). Greater deprivation was associated with a higher recording of malaria com-<lb/>pared to those who were less deprived (IRR: 1.86 (95% CI 1.54-2.25), incidence per 100,000 <lb/>PYAR; most deprived: 3.29, least deprived: 1.48). <lb/>Ethnicity was poorly recorded in THIN with missing data on 40% of the cases included in <lb/>the analysis (Table 1). Amongst those with a recording of ethnicity, those who identify as black <lb/>had the highest incidence while those who identified as white had the lowest (56.14 and 1.40 <lb/>per 100,000 PYAR respectively). Those with unrecorded ethnicity data had a similar rate as <lb/>those who identified as white (1.38 vs 1.40 per 100,000 PYAR). <lb/>Fig 2. Number of cases identified in THIN from 2005 to 2016. THIN: The Health Improvement Network, ACT: Artemesinin-<lb/>based combination therapy. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>The sensitivity analysis looking at multiple episodes within the same individual identified <lb/>nine individuals with two episodes and one individual with more than two episodes of <lb/>recorded malaria within the study period. Including these episodes in the analysis had no sig-<lb/>nificant effect on the results. <lb/>Comparison with national surveillance data <lb/>There were a total of 18,833 cases of malaria identified by PHE through the MRL and HPZone <lb/>between 2005 and 2016. Comparing the proportion of cases identified by each dataset per year, <lb/>there was a proportionately larger number of cases identified in THIN between 2005 and 2009 <lb/>compared to PHE and a proportionately smaller number of cases in THIN for more recent <lb/>years (2014 to 2016) (Fig 4A). In terms of region, there was a larger representation of cases <lb/>from London in PHE (57%) compared to THIN (32%) (Fig 4B). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This study showed that the incidence of malaria recordings in primary care significantly <lb/>decreased between 2005 and 2016. Adults of working age were three times as likely to have a <lb/>diagnosis of malaria compared to children and older adults. Men were 28% more likely to have <lb/>a diagnosis of malaria compared to women. London had the highest incidence of malaria in <lb/>the UK and those who were most deprived were 86% more likely to be diagnosed with malaria <lb/>compared to those who were least deprived. <lb/>Findings of this study were similar to other data from the UK [2, 21], however the rate of <lb/>decline in the number of cases was more pronounced compared to data from the national <lb/>review for malaria, where annual case numbers have remained stable over the last 10 years [2]. <lb/>Fig 3. Malaria incidence in THIN, 2005 to 2016. THIN: The Health Improvement Network, PYAR: Person Years at Risk. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Incidence of malaria recordings in THIN by calendar year, age, sex, region, Townsend score and ethnicity. <lb/>Number of cases <lb/>PYAR <lb/>(100,000) <lb/>Incidence <lb/>Unadjusted IRR <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>Adjusted † IRR <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>Year <lb/>2005 <lb/>175 <lb/>52.50 <lb/>3.33 <lb/>Baseline <lb/>2006 <lb/>178 <lb/>54.81 <lb/>3.25 <lb/>0.97 (0.79-1.20) <lb/>0.97 (0.79-1.19) <lb/>2007 <lb/>155 <lb/>57.14 <lb/>2.71 <lb/>0.81 (0.66-1.01) <lb/>0.81 (0.65-1.01) <lb/>2008 <lb/>151 <lb/>58.95 <lb/>2.56 <lb/>0.77 (0.62-0.96) <lb/>0.77 (0.62-0.95) <lb/>2009 <lb/>130 <lb/>59.80 <lb/>2.17 <lb/>0.65 (0.52-0.82) <lb/>0.65 (0.51-0.81) <lb/>2010 <lb/>127 <lb/>59.59 <lb/>2.13 <lb/>0.64 (0.51-0.80) <lb/>0.62 (0.50-0.78) <lb/>2011 <lb/>134 <lb/>61.20 <lb/>2.19 <lb/>0.66 (0.52-0.82) <lb/>0.64 (0.51-0.80) <lb/>2012 <lb/>83 <lb/>62.42 <lb/>1.33 <lb/>0.40 (0.31-0.52) <lb/>0.39 (0.30-0.51) <lb/>2013 <lb/>124 <lb/>61.10 <lb/>2.03 <lb/>0.61 (0.48-0.77) <lb/>0.59 (0.47-0.74) <lb/>2014 <lb/>93 <lb/>57.68 <lb/>1.61 <lb/>0.48 (0.38-0.62) <lb/>0.48 (0.38-0.62) <lb/>2015 <lb/>68 <lb/>49.97 <lb/>1.36 <lb/>0.41 (0.31-0.54) <lb/>0.43 (0.33-0.57) <lb/>2016 <lb/>56 <lb/>41.27 <lb/>1.36 <lb/>0.41 (0.30-0.55) <lb/>0.44 (0.32-0.60) <lb/>Total <lb/>1,474 <lb/>676.43 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>Age <lb/>Less than 10 years <lb/>79 <lb/>70.44 <lb/>1.12 <lb/>Baseline <lb/>10 to 19 years <lb/>104 <lb/>73.08 <lb/>1.42 <lb/>1.27 (0.95-1.70) <lb/>1.32 (0.98-1.77) <lb/>20 to 29 years <lb/>249 <lb/>87.46 <lb/>2.85 <lb/>2.54 (1.97-3.27) <lb/>2.50 (1.94-3.22) <lb/>30 to 39 years <lb/>323 <lb/>96.89 <lb/>3.33 <lb/>2.97 (2.32-3.80) <lb/>2.81 (2.20-3.60) <lb/>40 to 49 years <lb/>326 <lb/>101.02 <lb/>3.23 <lb/>2.88 (2.25-3.68) <lb/>2.92 (2.28-3.74) <lb/>50 to 59 years <lb/>213 <lb/>84.06 <lb/>2.53 <lb/>2.26 (1.75-2.92) <lb/>2.43 (1.88-3.15) <lb/>60 to 69 years <lb/>120 <lb/>71.45 <lb/>1.68 <lb/>1.50 (1.13-1.99) <lb/>1.69 (1.27-2.25) <lb/>70 to 79 years <lb/>46 <lb/>50.66 <lb/>0.91 <lb/>0.81 (0.56-1.16) <lb/>0.91 (0.64-1.31) <lb/>80 to 89 years <lb/>9 <lb/>30.53 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.26 (0.13-0.52) <lb/>0.30 (0.15-0.60) <lb/>90 years and older <lb/>5 <lb/>10.85 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>0.41 (0.17-1.01) <lb/>0.51 (0.21-1.25) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Male <lb/>846 <lb/>329.05 <lb/>2.57 <lb/>Baseline <lb/>Female <lb/>628 <lb/>347.37 <lb/>1.81 <lb/>0.70 (0.63-0.78) <lb/>0.72 (0.65-0.80) <lb/>Region <lb/>London <lb/>474 <lb/>77.10 <lb/>6.15 <lb/>Baseline <lb/>East Midlands <lb/>25 <lb/>13.74 <lb/>1.82 <lb/>0.30 (0.20-0.44) <lb/>0.29 (0.20-0.44) <lb/>East of England <lb/>95 <lb/>37.80 <lb/>2.51 <lb/>0.41 (0.33-0.51) <lb/>0.45 (0.36-0.56) <lb/>North East <lb/>27 <lb/>13.62 <lb/>1.98 <lb/>0.32 (0.22-0.48) <lb/>0.32 (0.22-0.48) <lb/>North West <lb/>80 <lb/>59.40 <lb/>1.35 <lb/>0.22 (0.17-0.28) <lb/>0.24 (0.19-0.30) <lb/>Northern Ireland <lb/>17 <lb/>27.14 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>0.10 (0.06-0.17) <lb/>0.11 (0.07-0.18) <lb/>Scotland <lb/>164 <lb/>97.51 <lb/>1.68 <lb/>0.27 (0.23-0.33) <lb/>0.30 (0.25-0.36) <lb/>South Central <lb/>169 <lb/>79.79 <lb/>2.12 <lb/>0.34 (0.29-0.41) <lb/>0.41 (0.34-0.49) <lb/>South East Coast <lb/>140 <lb/>74.18 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>0.31 (0.25-0.37) <lb/>0.37 (0.31-0.45) <lb/>South West <lb/>73 <lb/>60.50 <lb/>1.21 <lb/>0.20 (0.15-0.25) <lb/>0.23 (0.18-0.29) <lb/>Wales <lb/>71 <lb/>68.32 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>0.17 (0.13-0.22) <lb/>0.20 (0.15-0.25) <lb/>West Midlands <lb/>126 <lb/>54.58 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>0.38 (0.31-0.46) <lb/>0.42 (0.34-0.51) <lb/>Yorkshire &amp; Humber <lb/>13 <lb/>12.75 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>0.17 (0.10-0.29) <lb/>0.17 (0.10-0.29) <lb/>Townsend Score <lb/>(Least Deprived) 1 <lb/>218 <lb/>147.02 <lb/>1.48 <lb/>Baseline <lb/>2 <lb/>204 <lb/>132.21 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>1.04 (0.86-1.26) <lb/>1.03 (0.85-1.25) <lb/>3 <lb/>290 <lb/>127.94 <lb/>2.27 <lb/>1.53 (1.28-1.82) <lb/>1.39 (1.16-1.66) <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>The lack of a denominator in our comparison of THIN and PHE data meant that variations <lb/>over time could either reflect changes in the number of cases identified; or changes in the <lb/>number of individuals where the cases derived from. Therefore the more pronounced decline <lb/>in THIN could partly be due to the improvement in data quality with regards to the complete-<lb/>ness of PHE data. Since 2013, cases reported to the PHE case management database (HPZone) <lb/>supplemented the cases identified in the MRL dataset. In addition, the number of cases identi-<lb/>fied in THIN may be underestimated for 2016 since not all practices contributed data for that <lb/>year, further contributing to the declining trend. Despite this, it is likely that our findings <lb/>reflect a true decline in the number of cases since 2005. Decreasing global malaria incidence <lb/>[1], decreased transmission of malaria in West Africa, where most cases in the UK are acquired <lb/>and changing chemoprophylaxis usage have been suggested as possible factors contributing to <lb/>the decline [22, 23]. <lb/>Similar to data from national and European surveillance [2, 24], men were more likely to <lb/>present with malaria than women. Previous studies have suggested that gender differences in <lb/>attitudes towards seeking pre-travel health advice [25], poorer adherence to malaria chemo-<lb/>prophylaxis [26], increased risk taking behaviour and travel to more remote areas where the <lb/>risk of contracting malaria is higher may account for the male predominance in the number of <lb/>malaria cases [27]. On the other hand, other studies have shown no gender differences in che-<lb/>moprophylaxis uptake and adherence [28] and suggest that host factor differences resulting in <lb/>increased attractiveness to mosquitoes may be responsible for the higher rate of malaria in <lb/>men [26]. Although both, behavioural and biological host factors may be contributory, the <lb/>main reason for the difference is likely due to the number of individuals who travel as between <lb/>2014 and 2016, 17% more men travelled to malaria endemic areas from the UK than women <lb/>[29]. Similarly, age differences in malaria rates may also reflect UK travel patterns [29]. <lb/>Although we were unable to adjust for ethnicity in our analysis due to a large amount of <lb/>missing data, the trends in the rates of recordings where data were available was comparable <lb/>with other UK data, showing higher rates in ethnic minorities (Black, mixed, Asian and other, <lb/>respectively) compared to those who were White[2, 21]. Additionally, those with missing eth-<lb/>nicity data had a similar rate of malaria recording in THIN as those who were white suggesting <lb/>Table 1. (Continued) <lb/>Number of cases <lb/>PYAR <lb/>(100,000) <lb/>Incidence <lb/>Unadjusted IRR <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>Adjusted † IRR <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>4 <lb/>344 <lb/>111.25 <lb/>3.09 <lb/>2.09 (1.76-2.47) <lb/>1.82 (1.53-2.16) <lb/>(Most deprived) 5 <lb/>248 <lb/>75.40 <lb/>3.29 <lb/>2.22 (1.85-2.66) <lb/>1.86 (1.54-2.25) <lb/>Missing <lb/>170 <lb/>82.61 <lb/>2.06 <lb/>1.39 (1.14-1.70) <lb/>1.15 (0.94-1.42) <lb/>Ethnicity <lb/>Black <lb/>432 <lb/>7.70 <lb/>56.14 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>White <lb/>312 <lb/>220.00 <lb/>1.40 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Asian <lb/>114 <lb/>13.00 <lb/>8.86 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Other <lb/>13 <lb/>4.60 <lb/>2.83 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Mixed <lb/>20 <lb/>2.40 <lb/>8.51 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Missing <lb/>592 <lb/>430.00 <lb/>1.38 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Total <lb/>1,483ⁱ <lb/>677.70 <lb/>2.19 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>THIN, The Health Improvement Network; PYAR, Person Years at Risk; CI, Confidence Interval; IRR, Incidence rate ratio. <lb/> † IRR adjusted for year, age, sex, region and Townsend score. IRR was not adjusted for ethnicity due to a large amount of missing data (40% missing). <lb/>ⁱ <lb/>The total includes the 9 cases with missing demographic information. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>that the majority of those with missing data were white. Furthermore, those diagnosed with <lb/>malaria could be more likely to have their ethnicity recorded compared to those who are not, <lb/>resulting in an inflated value for the incidence rate amongst ethnic minorities. Also, given that <lb/>ethnic minority populations are more likely to be found in London and are more likely to <lb/>experience deprivation [30, 31], ethnicity may account for the higher incidence of malaria in <lb/>London and in those who were most deprived. <lb/>Fig 4. Comparison of the proportion of total malaria cases identified by PHE and THIN from 2005 to 2016. (A) Per year, and (B) by <lb/>UK region. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Use of EHRs for malaria research could provide a complementary role to data obtained <lb/>through passive surveillance. The characteristics of each data source and their respective <lb/>strengths and limitations are summarised in (Table 2). For THIN, the large number of individ-<lb/>uals included in the analysis allowed us to accurately compare primary care incidence esti-<lb/>mates by age, sex, gender, region, socioeconomic status and calendar year. Additionally, the <lb/>use of routinely collected prospective data to estimate incidence potentially captured cases not <lb/>reported in surveillance based incidence estimates, since it relies on clinicians recording a <lb/>diagnosis of malaria regardless of whether it had been notified to Public Health England or <lb/>MRL. It also resulted in a more accurate estimation of the geographic distribution of cases <lb/>since the centralised reporting site for MRL make it less sensitive to cases resident outside of <lb/>London [6]. On the other hand, relying on clinician recording of the diagnosis also meant that <lb/>it was difficult to look at the incidence of malaria by parasite species since the species of <lb/>malaria were rarely recorded. Moreover, although our algorithm captured cases without a <lb/>diagnostic code for malaria by looking at other variables such as treatment and investigations <lb/>and excluded those with a code for a travel related vaccination, there still remains a risk of <lb/>some misclassification if a diagnosis of malaria was not considered. Furthermore, our use of <lb/>GP records for the analysis of incidence meant that our findings are restricted to those <lb/>Table 2. summarising the characteristics, strengths and limitations of using PHE data and primary care EHR (THIN) data. <lb/>PHE <lb/>THIN <lb/>Data source <lb/>Passive surveillance through MRL (supplemented by HPZone <lb/>since 2013) [2] <lb/>Primary care electronic health records <lb/>Case definition for <lb/>malaria case <lb/>Parasitological confirmation of diagnosis by blood film or tissue <lb/>histology. Cases treated presumptively or diagnosed by other <lb/>methods (e.g. antigen based) are not included [34]. <lb/>Indicated by diagnostic codes for malaria, or a combination of <lb/>investigation and treatment codes <lb/>Coverage and <lb/>representativeness of <lb/>sample <lb/>UK population [2] <lb/>Coverage of around 6% of the UK population and has been shown <lb/>to be broadly representative of the UK population [15] <lb/>Data quality and type of <lb/>data available <lb/>Data collected solely for malaria surveillance capturing important <lb/>variables related to malaria e.g. parasite species, ethnicity, travel <lb/>history, chemoprophylaxis and treatment. <lb/>Primary use of EHR&apos;s is patient management and data will reflect <lb/>only those relevant to patient care. <lb/>Good quality of recordings for investigations and prescriptions. <lb/>Poor quality of data on parasite species, ethnicity and travel history. <lb/>Timeliness of annual <lb/>reporting <lb/>Annual data is published six months after the end of the year (e.g. <lb/>Annual report for 2016 available online August 2017) <lb/>Data is collected from participating general practices every three <lb/>months by the data provider (IMS health/IQVIA), who then provide <lb/>access to the data for researchers through a license. <lb/>Strengths <lb/>• Most complete source of information about malaria in the UK <lb/>• Data is collected in a standardised way <lb/>• High specificity for identifying malaria cases <lb/>• Does not rely on notification of cases. <lb/>• Availability of data on malaria investigation and treatment allows <lb/>cases to be identified even when a diagnosis is not coded. <lb/>• Data is available on the sequence of care prior to a diagnosis of <lb/>malaria, allowing investigation into potential missed <lb/>opportunities for diagnosis and treatment. <lb/>• More accurate estimation of geographical distribution of cases <lb/>• Can explore associations for contracting malaria in variables not <lb/>captured by the PHE malaria form <lb/>Limitations <lb/>• Relies on notification-only 56% of cases captured by <lb/>surveillance system <lb/>• Data available is restricted to what is collected in the Patient <lb/>report/referral form <lb/>• Centralised reporting site-More sensitive to cases resident in <lb/>London [6] <lb/>• Miscoding, misclassification and misdiagnosis-These can be <lb/>minimised by using recorded data from a consultation to exclude <lb/>common coding errors (e.g. Miscoding malaria for malaria <lb/>prophylaxis can be excluded by identifying prescriptions which <lb/>are prescribed prior to travel) <lb/>• Does not capture those not registered with a GP <lb/>• Relies on practices using a specific IT system (INPS vision). <lb/>Regional variation in the transition of practices to other IT <lb/>systems can affect the representativeness of the sample over time. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>registered with a general practitioner. Using an additional data source from secondary care <lb/>(Hospital Episode Statistics, HES) could have resulted in additional information on parasite <lb/>species and identified further cases not recorded in THIN [32]. However, the limited number <lb/>of practices in THIN with linkage to HES (23% of practices) and the lack of HES-linked data <lb/>for practices outside England would have restricted the number of individuals included in the <lb/>study [33]. Despite this, future research on the subset of individuals with HES linked data <lb/>could provide insight into the levels of recording in both settings. Finally, the number of <lb/>malaria recordings is not a true reflection of incidence since only those who travel are at risk of <lb/>contracting malaria, however, in the absence of reliable data regarding travel in THIN, includ-<lb/>ing all individuals when looking at the rate of malaria recordings allows us to explore trends <lb/>over time and compare with surveillance data which also uses population data [2, 24]. <lb/>This is the first study, to the best of our knowledge, which has explored malaria recordings <lb/>over time using UK primary care data. The comparability of our findings to that from other <lb/>UK data sources supports the use of this routinely collected data source for further research. <lb/>Since the majority of previous malaria related research is retrospective [35], the routine <lb/>recording in primary care datasets can allow prospective evaluation of the sequence of care <lb/>prior to a diagnosis amongst the cases identified in this study. Given that prompt diagnosis <lb/>and treatment of malaria remains a challenge in primary care [36], future research can use pri-<lb/>mary care data to identify missed opportunities for diagnosis and explore factors associated <lb/>with it. Additionally, the improved geographic information on the distribution of cases can <lb/>help with resource allocation and delivery of malaria prevention and treatment services. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>There has been a decrease in the number of malaria recordings in UK primary care over the <lb/>past decade. This decrease exceeds the rate of decline reported in national surveillance data; <lb/>however there are similar associations with age, sex and deprivation. Improved geographic <lb/>information on the distribution of cases and the potential for automation of case identification <lb/>suggests that EHRs could provide a complementary role for investigating malaria trends over <lb/>time. <lb/>Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Incidence of malaria recording by UK region in THIN. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S1 Table. Read code lists used in this study. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Hamad Bastaki, Louise Marston, Jackie Cassell, Greta Rait. <lb/>Data curation: Hamad Bastaki. <lb/>Formal analysis: Hamad Bastaki, Louise Marston, Greta Rait. <lb/>Investigation: Hamad Bastaki, Louise Marston, Jackie Cassell, Greta Rait. <lb/>Methodology: Hamad Bastaki, Louise Marston, Jackie Cassell, Greta Rait. <lb/>Software: Hamad Bastaki. <lb/>Supervision: Louise Marston, Jackie Cassell, Greta Rait. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Validation: Hamad Bastaki, Louise Marston. <lb/>Visualization: Hamad Bastaki, Greta Rait. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Hamad Bastaki. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Hamad Bastaki, Louise Marston, Jackie Cassell, Greta Rait. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. WHO. World Malaria Report 2017. World Health Organization Geneva; 2017. <lb/>2. PHE. Malaria imported into the UK 2016: implications for those advising travellers United Kingdom: <lb/>Public Health England; 2017 [https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/malaria-in-the-uk-annual-<lb/>report. <lb/>3. Schlagenhauf P, Weld L, Goorhuis A, Gautret P, Weber R, von Sonnenburg F, et al. Travel-associated <lb/>infection presenting in Europe (2008-12): an analysis of EuroTravNet longitudinal, surveillance data, <lb/>and evaluation of the effect of the pre-travel consultation. The Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2015; <lb/>15(1):55-64. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-3099(14)71000-X PMID: 25477022 <lb/>4. MRL. Malaria Reference Laboratory: reference, diagnostic and advisory services: Public Health <lb/>England; 2007 [https://www.gov.uk/guidance/mrl-reference-diagnostic-and-advisory-services. <lb/>5. MRL. Malaria Reference Laboratory: Malaria Report form. In: England PH, editor. 2017. <lb/>6. Cathcart S, Lawrence J, Grant A, Quinn D, Whitty C, Jones J, et al. Estimating unreported malaria <lb/>cases in England: a capture-recapture study. Epidemiology &amp; Infection. 2010; 138(7):1052-8. <lb/>7. Van Hest N, Smit F, Verhave J. Underreporting of malaria incidence in The Netherlands: results from a <lb/>capture-recapture study. Epidemiology &amp; Infection. 2002; 129(2):371-7. <lb/>8. Legros F, Pichard E, Danis M. Formes graves du paludisme d&apos;importation: donne ´es e ´pide ´miologiques <lb/>en France 1999-2001. Me ´decine et maladies infectieuses. 2003; 33:3-5. <lb/>9. Fonseca AG, Simões Dias S, Baptista JL, Torgal J. Surveillance of imported hospital requiring malaria <lb/>in Portugal: can it be improved? The European Journal of Public Health. 2016; 26(3):403-6. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1093/eurpub/ckw052 PMID: 27069002 <lb/>10. Cowie MR, Blomster JI, Curtis LH, Duclaux S, Ford I, Fritz F, et al. Electronic health records to facilitate <lb/>clinical research. Clinical Research in Cardiology. 2017; 106(1):1-9. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00392-<lb/>016-1025-6 PMID: 27557678 <lb/>11. Basatemur E, Horsfall L, Marston L, Rait G, Sutcliffe A. Trends in the Diagnosis of Vitamin D Deficiency. <lb/>Pediatrics. 2017; 139(3):e20162748. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2016-2748 PMID: 28159871 <lb/>12. Sharma M, Nazareth I, Petersen I. Trends in incidence, prevalence and prescribing in type 2 diabetes <lb/>mellitus between 2000 and 2013 in primary care: a retrospective cohort study. BMJ open. 2016; 6(1): <lb/>e010210. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010210 PMID: 26769791 <lb/>13. Shallcross LJ, Hayward AC, Johnson AM, Petersen I. Incidence and recurrence of boils and abscesses <lb/>within the first year: a cohort study in UK primary care. Br J Gen Pract. 2015; 65(639):e668-e76. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.3399/bjgp15X686929 PMID: 26412844 <lb/>14. UCL. THIN database-Data structure University College London2017 [https://www.ucl.ac.uk/pcph/ <lb/>research-groups-themes/thin-pub/database. <lb/>15. Blak B, Thompson M, Dattani H, Bourke A. Generalisability of The Health Improvement Network (THIN) <lb/>database: demographics, chronic disease prevalence and mortality rates. Journal of Innovation in <lb/>Health Informatics. 2011; 19(4):251-5. <lb/>16. Horsfall L, Walters K, Petersen I. Identifying periods of acceptable computer usage in primary care <lb/>research databases. Pharmacoepidemiology and drug safety. 2013; 22(1):64-9. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1002/pds.3368 PMID: 23124958 <lb/>17. Maguire A, Blak BT, Thompson M. The importance of defining periods of complete mortality reporting <lb/>for research using automated data from primary care. Pharmacoepidemiology and drug safety. 2009; <lb/>18(1):76-83. https://doi.org/10.1002/pds.1688 PMID: 19065600 <lb/>18. Association BM. British National Formulary, 69th edn. In: Society RP, editor. Pharmaceutical Press, <lb/>London: BMJ group; 2015. <lb/>19. Lalloo DG, Shingadia D, Bell DJ, Beeching NJ, Whitty CJ, Chiodini PL. UK malaria treatment guidelines <lb/>2016. The Journal of infection. 2016; 72(6):635-49. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinf.2016.02.001 PMID: <lb/>26880088 <lb/>20. StataCorp. Stata Statistical Software: Release 14. Texas USA: StataCorp LP. 2015. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 14 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>21. Rees E, Saavedra-Campos M, Usdin M, Anderson C, Freedman J, De Burgh J, et al. Trend analysis of <lb/>imported malaria in London; observational study 2000 to 2014. Travel medicine and infectious disease. <lb/>2017. <lb/>22. Behrens RH, Carroll B, Smith V, Alexander N. Declining incidence of malaria imported into the UK from <lb/>West Africa. Malaria Journal. 2008; 7(1):235. <lb/>23. Zuckerman JN, Batty AJ, Jones ME. Effectiveness of malaria chemoprophylaxis against Plasmodium <lb/>falciparum infection in UK travellers: retrospective observational data. Travel medicine and infectious <lb/>disease. 2009; 7(6):329-36. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tmaid.2009.10.002 PMID: 19945009 <lb/>24. ECDC. Malaria-Annual Epidemiological Report 2016 European Centre for Disease Prevention and <lb/>Control; 2017 [Surveillance Report]. https://ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/malaria-annual-<lb/>epidemiological-report-2016-2014-data. <lb/>25. Pavli A, Silvestros C, Patrinos S, Maltezou HC. Vaccination and malaria prophylaxis among Greek inter-<lb/>national travelers to Asian destinations. Journal of infection and public health. 2015; 8(1):47-54. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.jiph.2014.07.002 PMID: 25129447 <lb/>26. Schlagenhauf P, Chen LH, Wilson ME, Freedman DO, Tcheng D, Schwartz E, et al. Sex and gender dif-<lb/>ferences in travel-associated disease. Clinical infectious diseases. 2010; 50(6):826-32. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1086/650575 PMID: 20156059 <lb/>27. Stienlauf S, Segal G, Sidi Y, Schwartz E. Epidemiology of travel-related hospitalization. Journal of travel <lb/>medicine. 2005; 12(3):136-41. PMID: 15996442 <lb/>28. Stoney RJ, Chen LH, Jentes ES, Wilson ME, Han PV, Benoit CM, et al. Malaria prevention strategies: <lb/>adherence among Boston area travelers visiting malaria-endemic countries. The American journal of <lb/>tropical medicine and hygiene. 2016; 94(1):136-42. https://doi.org/10.4269/ajtmh.15-0565 PMID: <lb/>26483125 <lb/>29. ONS. UK Residents Visits Abroad. In: Statistics OfN, editor. United Kingdom2016. <lb/>30. ONS. Ethnicity facts and figures: Regional ethnic diversity United Kingdom2018 [https://www.ethnicity-<lb/>facts-figures.service.gov.uk/british-population/national-and-regional-populations/regional-ethnic-<lb/>diversity/latest. <lb/>31. ONS. Ethnicity facts and figures: Socioeconomic status United Kingdom: Office for National Statistics; <lb/>2018 [https://www.ethnicity-facts-figures.service.gov.uk/british-population/demographics/ <lb/>socioeconomic-status/latest. <lb/>32. NHS Digital. Hospital Episode statistics (HES); About the HES database Unnited Kingdom2018 [https:// <lb/>digital.nhs.uk/data-and-information/data-tools-and-services/data-services/hospital-episode-<lb/>statistics#about-the-hes-database. <lb/>33. IQVIA. THIN-HES Data Linkage 2018 [https://www.iqvia.com/locations/uk-and-ireland/thin-hes-data. <lb/>34. Smith AD, Bradley DJ, Smith V, Blaze M, Behrens RH, Chiodini PL, et al. Imported malaria and high risk <lb/>groups: observational study using UK surveillance data 1987-2006. Bmj. 2008; 337:a120. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1136/bmj.a120 PMID: 18599471 <lb/>35. Bastaki H, Carter J, Marston L, Cassell J, Rait G. Time delays in the diagnosis and treatment of malaria <lb/>in non-endemic countries: A systematic review. Travel medicine and infectious disease. 2017. <lb/>36. Willcox ML, Mant J, O&apos;dempsey T. Imported malaria. BMJ: British Medical Journal. 2013; 346. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Imported malaria in the UK <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210040 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 14 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
