<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Constructing and applying a neural-network-based architectural landscape evaluation model</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Weiwei</forename>
          <surname>Yang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Chunyan</forename>
          <surname>Yan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Yifan</forename>
          <surname>Wei</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-04T08:54:50.307Z">11/4/2025 8:54:50 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Emerald</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1680/jsmic.23.00085</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Weiwei Yang, Chunyan Yan, Yifan Wei. (2024). Constructing and applying a neural-network-based architectural landscape evaluation model. Proceedings of the Institution of Civil Engineers - Smart Infrastructure and Construction, 177(4), 236-245. DOI: 10.1680/jsmic.23.00085</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-04T08:54:35.025546Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-04T08:54:35.025546Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Evaluation of innovation efficiency <lb/>of high-tech enterprise based on <lb/>DEA and Malmquist index <lb/>under the background of <lb/>sustainable development <lb/>Liwei Wang <lb/>Shanghai Information Center for Life Sciences, <lb/>Shanghai Institute of Nutrition and Health Chinese Academy of Sciences, <lb/>Shanghai, China, and <lb/>Tianbo Tang <lb/>Shanghai Institute for Science of Science, Shanghai, China <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Purpose -This paper aims to promote the higher quality development of high-tech enterprises in China. <lb/>While science and technology have greatly promoted human civilization, resources have been excessively <lb/>consumed and the environment has been sharply polluted. Therefore, it is particularly important for current <lb/>enterprises to make use of scientific and technological innovation to maximize the benefits of mankind, <lb/>minimize the loss of nature, and promote the sustainable development of our country. <lb/>Design/methodology/approach -By using DEA-Banker-Charnes-Cooper (BCC) model and DEA-<lb/>Malmquist model, this paper comprehensively examines the innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises <lb/>from both static and dynamic perspectives, and conducts a provincial comparative study with the panel data <lb/>of ten representative provinces from 2011 to 2020. <lb/>Findings -The research findings are as follows: the rapid number increase of high-tech enterprises in most <lb/>provinces (cities) is accompanied by an ineffective input-output efficiency; the quality of high-tech enterprises <lb/>needs to comprehensively examine both input-output efficiency and total factor productivity; and there is not <lb/>a positive correlation between element investment and innovation performance. <lb/>Research limitations/implications -Because the DEA model used in this paper assumes that the <lb/>improvement direction of invalid units is to ensure that the input ratio of various production factors remains <lb/>unchanged but sometimes the proportion of scientific and technological activities personnel and the total <lb/>research and development investment is not constant. In the future, the nonradial DEA model can be <lb/>considered for further research. Due to historical data statistics, more provinces, cities and longer panel data <lb/>are difficult to obtain. The samples studied in this paper mainly refer to the provinces and cities that ranked <lb/>first in the number of national high-tech enterprises in 2020. Limited by the number of samples, DEA analysis <lb/>© Liwei Wang and Tianbo Tang. Published in Asia Pacific Journal of Innovation and <lb/>Entrepreneurship. Published by Emerald Publishing Limited. This article is published under the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY 4.0) licence. Anyone may reproduce, distribute, translate and <lb/>create derivative works of this article (for both commercial and non-commercial purposes), subject to <lb/>full attribution to the original publication and authors. The full terms of this licence may be seen at <lb/>http://creativecommons.org/licences/by/4.0/legalcode <lb/>Data availability: The data set is available from the corresponding author upon request. <lb/>Conflicts of interest: There are no conflicts of interest regarding the publication of this article. <lb/>APJIE <lb/>18,4 <lb/>340 <lb/>Received 9 October 2023 <lb/>Revised 7 December 2023 <lb/>Accepted 26 February 2024 <lb/>Asia Pacific Journal of Innovation <lb/>and Entrepreneurship <lb/>Vol. 18 No. 4, 2024 <lb/>pp. 340-354 <lb/>Emerald Publishing Limited <lb/>e-ISSN: 2398-7812 <lb/>p-ISSN: 2071-1395 <lb/>DOI 10.1108/APJIE-10-2023-0190 <lb/>The current issue and full text archive of this journal is available on Emerald Insight at: <lb/>https://www.emerald.com/insight/2398-7812.htm <lb/>Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/>failed to select more input and output indicators. In the future, with the accumulation of statistical data, the <lb/>existing efficiency analysis will be further optimized. <lb/>Originality/value -Aiming at the misunderstanding of emphasizing quantity and neglecting quality in <lb/>the cultivation of high-tech enterprises, this paper comprehensively uses DEA-BCC model and DEA <lb/>Malmquist index decomposition method to make a comprehensive comparative study on the development of <lb/>high-tech enterprises in ten representative provinces (cities) from two aspects of static efficiency evaluation <lb/>and dynamic efficiency evaluation. <lb/>Keywords Sustainable development, Innovation efficiency, DEA-BCC model, <lb/>DEA-Malmquist model, High-tech enterprise <lb/>Paper type Research paper <lb/></front>

        <body>1. Introduction <lb/>These years, the Chinese economy is experiencing exponential growth and China has <lb/>become the second largest economy in the world, but the accompanying ecological <lb/>environment problems are also becoming more and more serious. Ecological <lb/>deterioration and other issues are important factors affecting economic and social <lb/>development. The Chinese Government places great importance to sustainable <lb/>development issues such as the ecological environment and has made a series of efforts. <lb/>Under the conditions of economic slowdown and tighter resource constraints, <lb/>environmental protection efforts have not been relaxed. China&apos;s sustainable development <lb/>level has been rising in recent years. In addition, as a responsible big country, China has <lb/>set the goals of &quot;carbon peak&quot; in 2030 and &quot;carbon neutrality&quot; in 2060, which raises the <lb/>bar for China&apos;s sustainable development level. Facing the pressure of ecological <lb/>environment and the complex international economic situation, China urgently needs to <lb/>turn its attention to improving the efficiency of sustainable development and explore a <lb/>high-quality path of sustainable development. Among them, Sci-Tech innovation, as an <lb/>important foundation and key means of sustainable development (Wang and Fan, 2022), <lb/>is the best choice to promote sustainable development when the constraints of natural <lb/>resources and ecological environment are increasingly tight. <lb/>As a knowledge and technology intensive economic unit that continuously carries out <lb/>research and development (R&amp;D) and technology transformation, high-tech enterprise is an <lb/>important carrier of Sci-Tech innovation, the core force of the development of national high-<lb/>tech industries and the new force of regional innovation (Zhang and Lv, 2013). The outbreak <lb/>of COVID-19 has not only exerted great influence on China&apos;s economy and people&apos;s lives, but <lb/>also brought challenges and opportunities to high-tech enterprises. During the epidemic <lb/>prevention and control period, all kinds of high-tech enterprises actively applied their Sci-<lb/>Tech innovation achievements to the new scene of epidemic prevention and control, such as <lb/>the intelligent analysis system for the detection and quantification of COVID-19, mobile <lb/>disinfection and sterilization robots, mobile nucleic acid detection vehicles, wearable <lb/>wireless thermometers and unmanned logistics robots, which not only provided important <lb/>support for the epidemic prevention and control work but also further established the <lb/>important position of high-tech enterprises in the development of China&apos;s economy and <lb/>society. <lb/>With the in-depth promotion of the strategy of strengthening the country through <lb/>science and technology, relevant ministries and commissions such as the Ministry of <lb/>science and technology and provincial (municipal) local governments have issued many <lb/>policies and measures to vigorously promote the cultivation and identification of high-<lb/>tech enterprises. As the number of high-tech enterprises in China increases rapidly, a <lb/>competition for cultivating and developing the high-tech enterprises have been quietly <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">DEA and <lb/>Malmquist <lb/>index <lb/></note>

        <page>341 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>launched across the country. The number of high-tech enterprises has become a major <lb/>assessment indicator for many local science and technology departments, and even one of <lb/>the indicators to assess the efficiency of regional high-quality development. Some studies <lb/>have found that the number of enterprises has an insignificant negative impact on <lb/>innovation efficiency (Han, 2010), and the more enterprises in a region, the less conducive <lb/>it is for them to improve technological innovation efficiency (Guo et al., 2020). Which <lb/>means that the efficiency of regional innovation is not closely linked to the number of <lb/>enterprises. In particular, for the transformation of China&apos;s economy from high-speed <lb/>growth to high-quality development, improving development efficiency and quality is a <lb/>more important goal. Therefore, carrying out the evaluation of innovation efficiency of <lb/>high-tech enterprises and establishing a correct development orientation of high-tech <lb/>enterprises are significant to the rational allocation of scientific and technological <lb/>resources, the optimization of economic and industrial structure, and the realization of <lb/>high-quality development. This paper comprehensively inspects the innovation <lb/>efficiency of high-tech enterprises by using the DEA-Banker-Charnes-Cooper (BCC) <lb/>model and the DEA-Malmquist model, then proposes three suggestions to push the <lb/>higher quality development of Chinese high-tech enterprises based on the findings. <lb/>2. Literature review <lb/>On the research about high-tech enterprises, a growing number of scholars begin to show <lb/>interest in the sustainable development and innovation ability of high-tech enterprises. <lb/>About the evaluation of innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises, the existing literature <lb/>mainly focuses on two aspects, multilevel efficiency analysis and influencing factor <lb/>evaluation. Among them, the former mainly includes three levels: region, industry and <lb/>enterprise; The latter mainly determines the influencing factors through the evaluation of <lb/>the innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises, then puts forward the path to optimize the <lb/>innovation efficiency. In addition, this paper will also review and discuss the evaluation <lb/>methods of enterprise innovation efficiency. <lb/>2.1 Sustainable development of high-tech enterprises <lb/>In terms of the sustainable development of high-tech enterprises, Pylaeva et al. (2022) <lb/>proposed a new method to identify sustainable high-tech enterprises; Cochran and <lb/>Rauch (2020) better solved the problems of sustainability and industry 4.0 from the <lb/>view of enterprise sustainable development. Yang and Wang (2020) proposed to <lb/>establish an ecosystem of marine high-tech enterprises from the view of sustainable <lb/>development; Law and Gunasekaran (2012) studied the key factors that promote Hong <lb/>Kong&apos;s high-tech enterprises to adopt and implement sustainable development <lb/>strategies; Du et al. (2022) evaluated the effect of high-tech industries and renewable <lb/>energy on consumption-based carbon emissions in Middle Eastern and Northern Africa <lb/>countries. Liu et al. (2020) used the lasso regression method to find out the factors that <lb/>affect the efficiency of green technology innovation in high-tech industries within each <lb/>cluster area; Chen et al. (2021) based on the three-stage ultra-efficient data envelopment <lb/>analysis (DEA) model of cooperative game, studied its application in the R&amp;D of green <lb/>innovation in China&apos;s high-tech industry. <lb/>In accordance with innovation of high-tech enterprises, Ye et al. (2022) researched on the <lb/>impact of R&amp;D agglomeration and economic policy uncertainty on innovation of high-tech <lb/>enterprises in China. (Li and Zhang, 2021) studied the independent innovation ability of <lb/>high-tech enterprises based on field programmable gata array processors and dynamic <lb/>reconfiguration technology. Based on the insight into internal and external governance, Lin <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">APJIE <lb/>18,4 <lb/></note>

        <page>342 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>et al. (2020) discussed how management power and network centrality affect the innovation <lb/>performance of high-tech enterprises in the big data environment. Ghazinoory and Hashemi <lb/>(2021) studied whether tax incentives and direct funds can improve the innovation input and <lb/>output of high-tech enterprises; Wang et al. (2020) constructed an industrial evaluation <lb/>framework for high-tech industrialization based on two-stage network DEA to evaluate the <lb/>technological innovation efficiency of China&apos;s high-tech industry. <lb/>2.2 Multilevel efficiency evaluation <lb/>At the regional level, Simonen et al. (2015) discussed the economic performance of high-<lb/>tech enterprises in Finland; Raab and Kotamraju (2006) used DEA to assess the <lb/>innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises in 50 states of the USA; Li et al. (2020) used <lb/>the DEA method to evaluate the innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises in the <lb/>Beijing Tianjin Hebei region and found that the three places in Beijing Tianjin Hebei have <lb/>shortcomings such as unreasonable resource allocation and an imperfect coordination <lb/>mechanism and put forward suggestions such as strengthening the linkage and <lb/>integration of the three places, providing independent innovation ability and increasing <lb/>government investment. <lb/>At the industrial level, for example, Chen and Yeh (2005) used DEA to analyze the <lb/>development efficiency of six high-tech industries; Guo et al. (2018) studied from the <lb/>perspective of industrial development, used DEA method to evaluate the input-output <lb/>efficiency of high-tech enterprises in different technology fields and concluded that there are <lb/>certain differences in the input-output efficiency between high-tech enterprises in different <lb/>technology fields; LV et al. (2017) used DEA to evaluate the innovation efficiency with high-<lb/>tech enterprises and individual enterprises in different technology fields as decision-making <lb/>units, and concluded that the innovation efficiency of technology enterprises in the four <lb/>technology fields of electronic information, new materials, new energy and resources in the <lb/>environment is high. <lb/>From the perspective of enterprise, Chen et al. (2014) used the random effect model to test <lb/>the data of China&apos;s listed companies from 2004 to 2006 and drew a conclusion that the <lb/>innovation efficiency of non-state-owned holding enterprises was remarkably better than <lb/>that of state-owned holding enterprises; Based on the two-stage value chain theory, Xiao <lb/>et al. (2015) concluded that the innovation efficiency of Chinese domestic funded enterprises, <lb/>Hong Kong, Macao, Taiwan-funded enterprises and foreign-funded enterprises increased <lb/>successively, and the efficiency difference was obvious. <lb/>Through the above literature review, which can be found that the research on the <lb/>evaluation of innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises has attracted the attention of <lb/>a host of scholars, and the existing research has also been comprehensively analyzed <lb/>from macro to micro, which has laid the foundation for this paper. However, with the <lb/>development of the identification of high-tech enterprises, the quantity of high-tech <lb/>enterprises in various regions has expanded rapidly. The relationship between the <lb/>quantity of high-tech enterprises and the innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises is <lb/>also a matter of concern. Therefore, this paper evaluates the innovation efficiency of <lb/>China&apos;s high-tech enterprises from the perspective of the number of high-tech enterprises <lb/>in each region. <lb/>2.3 Evaluation of influencing factors <lb/>In terms of independent innovation ability, Hu and Zhou, (2018) used the DEA and <lb/>Malmquist index methods to calculate the innovation efficiency of high-tech industries in <lb/>the Yangtze River economic belt. Studies have found enterprise-independent innovation and <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">DEA and <lb/>Malmquist <lb/>index <lb/></note>

        <page>343 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>government support are the main influencing power in improving the innovation efficiency <lb/>of high-tech industries. Based on the panel data of high-tech industries in the Beijing Tianjin <lb/>Hebei region from 2010 to 2017, Li et al. (2020) used DEA to evaluate the innovation <lb/>efficiency of high-tech enterprises in Beijing Tianjin Hebei region, and believed that <lb/>improving the independent innovation ability of enterprises would raise the innovation <lb/>efficiency of enterprises. <lb/>In terms of government support, such as Dou et al. (2020) used the three-stage DEA <lb/>model to evaluate the innovation efficiency of the sample enterprises, and through the <lb/>counterfactual estimation and intermediary effect model, it was explored the identification <lb/>policy of high-tech enterprises can raise the innovation efficiency in the technology research <lb/>and development stage. Bronzini and Piselli, (2016) believed that the government R&amp;D <lb/>subsidy policy had a positive impact on the quantity of patent applications of the company. <lb/>In terms of the quality of workers, Burton et al. (2009) believe that employees with high <lb/>job embeddedness can take the initiative to work and improve job performance; Mumford <lb/>(2000) believes that the knowledge discovery and working atmosphere of R&amp;D personnel <lb/>will also affect innovation performance. Li et al. (2015) studied the relationship between <lb/>R&amp;D personnel&apos;s self-efficacy, job embeddedness and innovation efficiency by using <lb/>structural equation model and proposed that the innovation efficiency of high-tech <lb/>enterprises can be improved by improving R&amp;D personnel&apos;s self-efficacy and job <lb/>embeddedness. <lb/>From the above analysis, we can see that the innovation efficiency of enterprises is <lb/>relevant to government support, independent innovation ability of enterprises and various <lb/>factors of enterprise employees. By analyzing the influencing factors of enterprise <lb/>innovation efficiency, we can provide reference for the improvement of enterprise innovation <lb/>efficiency, which has guiding significance for reality. Through the evaluation of the <lb/>innovation efficiency of enterprises in the top ten provinces (cities) with the number of high-<lb/>tech enterprises, this paper explores the relationship between the number of enterprises and <lb/>the innovation efficiency of enterprises, and provides reference for the relevant policies to <lb/>improve the innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises. <lb/>2.4 Relevant evaluation methods <lb/>Among the existing evaluation methods of enterprise innovation efficiency, factor analysis, <lb/>grey evaluation, stochastic frontier analysis and DEA are commonly used. <lb/>Because DEA does not need dimensionless processing of indicators, it can directly <lb/>analyze technical efficiency and scale efficiency without defining a special function form, so <lb/>it has a wider range of applications. For example, Fang et al. (2020) applied the Charnes-<lb/>Cooper-Rhodes and BCC models in DEA to analyze the technological innovation efficiency <lb/>of 23 Chinese new energy vehicle listed enterprises from 2013 to 2018; Lee and Parka, (2009) <lb/>used DEA to evaluate the technological innovation efficiency of equipment manufacturing <lb/>industry in many Asian countries; Kortelainen (2008) applied DEA to evaluate the <lb/>innovation efficiency of 20 EU Member States. <lb/>Furthermore, Fare et al. (1994) combined the Malmquist index used to study the <lb/>indifference curve with DEA so as to measure the change of efficiency in different periods <lb/>and proposed the DEA Malmquist model to analyze the dynamic change of total factor <lb/>productivity, which has been widely used by many scholars. For example, Sha and Wang <lb/>(2022) used DEA and Malmquist index models to calculate the innovation efficiency of nine <lb/>provinces and regions in the Yellow River Basin. <lb/>It can be seen that the traditional DEA model takes no account of the impact of <lb/>environmental factors and random errors on the efficiency evaluation of the decision-<lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">APJIE <lb/>18,4 <lb/></note>

        <page>344 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>making unit (DMU) and can eliminate management inefficiency, environmental factors and <lb/>random errors, which can obviously reflect the efficiency of DMU itself. The DEA <lb/>Malmquist model, which combines the Malmquist index with DEA, can overcome the <lb/>disadvantage that the traditional DEA model can only do static efficiency analysis so as to <lb/>better solve the dynamic efficiency and total factor efficiency. Therefore, the research based <lb/>on the DEA model or model variant is quite mature, and it is very consistent with the <lb/>research theme of this paper. This paper will use the traditional DEA model and the DEA <lb/>Malmquist model to measure the innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises, respectively. <lb/>3. Static efficiency evaluation based on DEA-BCC model <lb/>Referring to the literature related to the input-output efficiency of high-tech industries (Guo <lb/>et al., 2018; Si and Li, 2017), and considering the continuity and availability of data, this <lb/>paper selects the internal expenditure of scientific and technological activities personnel and <lb/>R&amp;D funds as input indicators, and the total income and export foreign exchange earnings <lb/>as output indicators. At the same time, considering the impact of scale efficiency on the <lb/>measurement results, this section adopts the scale income and input-oriented DEA-BCC <lb/>model to make a horizontal comparison of input-output efficiency of different provinces <lb/>(cities) through the average data from 2011 to 2020 and the time point data in 2020 (Guo <lb/>et al., 2018). <lb/>3.1 Horizontal comparison of average input-output efficiency from 2011 to 2020 <lb/>As shown in Table 1, from the angle of comprehensive technical efficiency, only the average <lb/>input-output efficiency of Shandong from 2011 to 2020 is effective, and the invalidity of the <lb/>comprehensive efficiency of other provinces (cities) is due to the invalidity of technical <lb/>efficiency and scale efficiency. Among them, Jiangsu ranks second among the ten provinces <lb/>(cities) in terms of pure technical efficiency and scale efficiency. The ranking of pure <lb/>technical efficiency in Zhejiang, Shanghai, Beijing, Hubei and Anhui lags behind their scale <lb/>efficiency, and the ineffectiveness of their comprehensive technical efficiency is due to the <lb/>ineffectiveness of pure technical efficiency to a greater extent. The pure technical efficiency <lb/>of Guangdong, Tianjin and Sichuan is ahead of their scale efficiency, and the inefficiency of <lb/>their comprehensive technical efficiency is caused by the inefficiency of scale efficiency to a <lb/>greater extent. <lb/>Table 1. <lb/>Calculation results of <lb/>average input-<lb/>output relative <lb/>efficiency of ten <lb/>representative <lb/>provinces (cities) <lb/>from 2011 to 2020 <lb/>Province (city) <lb/>Crste <lb/>Ranking <lb/>Vrste <lb/>Ranking <lb/>Scale <lb/>Ranking <lb/>Beijing <lb/>0.8338 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.9132 <lb/>8 <lb/>0.9131 <lb/>7 <lb/>Guangdong <lb/>0.8907 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.9812 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.909 <lb/>8 <lb/>Jiangsu <lb/>0.9995 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.9997 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.9998 <lb/>2 <lb/>Zhejiang <lb/>0.8902 <lb/>7 <lb/>0.8995 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.9896 <lb/>3 <lb/>Shanghai <lb/>0.8815 <lb/>8 <lb/>0.9052 <lb/>9 <lb/>0.9742 <lb/>5 <lb/>Shandong <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Hubei <lb/>0.955 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.9763 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.9773 <lb/>4 <lb/>Anhui <lb/>0.8995 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.9726 <lb/>7 <lb/>0.9243 <lb/>6 <lb/>Sichuan <lb/>0.876 <lb/>9 <lb/>0.9967 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.8789 <lb/>10 <lb/>Tianjin <lb/>0.892 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.989 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.9028 <lb/>9 <lb/>Notes: &quot;Crste&quot; represents the comprehensive technical efficiency level, &quot;Vrste&quot; represents the pure <lb/>technical efficiency level, &quot;Scale&quot; represents the scale efficiency level. The same below <lb/>Source: Table by authors <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">DEA and <lb/>Malmquist <lb/>index <lb/></note>

        <page>345 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>3.2 Horizontal comparison of input-output efficiency in 2020 <lb/>As shown in Table 2, from the perspective of comprehensive technical efficiency, the <lb/>average efficiency of ten representative provinces (cities) is 0.9561, less than 1, which means <lb/>that there are provinces (cities) with insufficient input-output efficiency. Specifically, the <lb/>comprehensive technical efficiency of Guangdong, Zhejiang, Shanghai and Shandong is <lb/>effective, which shows that the input-output of these four provinces (cities) is relatively <lb/>balanced in 2020, and the output is maximized under certain input. <lb/>From the perspective of pure technical efficiency, the pure technical efficiency of Beijing, <lb/>Guangdong, Zhejiang, Shanghai, Shandong, Hubei, Sichuan and Tianjin is effective, <lb/>indicating that under the existing industrial scale, the technical level of these eight provinces <lb/>(cities) in 2020 is advanced, their input and output levels are high, and there is no input <lb/>redundancy or insufficient output. Whereas, the pure technical efficiency of Jiangsu and <lb/>Anhui is less than 1, indicating that under the existing industrial scale, the technical level of <lb/>the two places needs to be improved, and there is currently input redundancy or insufficient <lb/>output. <lb/>Based on the analysis of the average input-output efficiency of ten provinces (cities) from <lb/>2011 to 2020 and the input-output efficiency of 2020, the findings are below: <lb/>Shandong: The average input-output efficiency from 2011 to 2020 and the time <lb/>point input-output efficiency in 2020 are both effective, which shows that the <lb/>comprehensive technological development level of Shandong Province determines <lb/>the shape of the production frontier of China&apos;s high-tech enterprises at present. <lb/>From now on, we should take the lead in improving technical standards and <lb/>promoting Pareto improvement of the production frontier, so as to push for the <lb/>development of the whole industry. <lb/>Guangdong, Zhejiang and Shanghai: The average input-output efficiency from <lb/>2011 to 2020 is less than 1, but the input-output efficiency at the time points of 2020 <lb/>is effective, indicating that the input scale of the three provinces (cities) is becoming <lb/>more reasonable. In the future, it is suggested to continue to develop according to <lb/>the current production and operation modes. <lb/>Hubei, Sichuan and Tianjin: The average input-output efficiency from 2011 to 2020 <lb/>and the time point input-output efficiency in 2020 are less than 1, due to the <lb/>Table 2. <lb/>Calculation results of <lb/>input-output relative <lb/>efficiency of high-<lb/>tech industries in ten <lb/>representative <lb/>provinces (cities) in <lb/>2020 <lb/>Province (city) <lb/>Crste <lb/>Vrste <lb/>Scale <lb/>Scale effectiveness <lb/>Beijing <lb/>0.826 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.826 <lb/>drs <lb/>Guangdong <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>Jiangsu <lb/>0.995 <lb/>0.997 <lb/>0.998 <lb/>irs <lb/>Zhejiang <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>Shanghai <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>Shandong <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>Hubei <lb/>0.996 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.996 <lb/>irs <lb/>Anhui <lb/>0.876 <lb/>0.989 <lb/>0.886 <lb/>irs <lb/>Sichuan <lb/>0.902 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.902 <lb/>irs <lb/>Tianjin <lb/>0.966 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.966 <lb/>irs <lb/>Average <lb/>0.9561 <lb/>0.9986 <lb/>0.9574 <lb/>Note: &quot;drs&quot; stands for diminishing returns to scale, &quot;irs&quot; stands for increasing returns to scale and &quot;-&quot; <lb/>stands for constant returns to scale <lb/>Source: Table by authors <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">APJIE <lb/>18,4 <lb/></note>

        <page>346 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>inefficiency of scale efficiency during the phase of increasing returns to scale. In the <lb/>future, it is suggested to expand the input scale of production factors. <lb/>Beijing: The average input-output efficiency from 2011 to 2020 and the time point <lb/>input-output efficiency in 2020 are less than 1, due to the inefficiency of scale <lb/>efficiency during the phase of diminishing returns to scale. In the future, it is <lb/>suggested to appropriately reduce the input of production factors, optimize the <lb/>structure of production input and strengthen internal supervision. <lb/>Jiangsu and Anhui: The average input-output efficiency from 2011 to 2020 and the <lb/>time point input-output efficiency in 2020 are less than 1, which is caused by the <lb/>ineffectiveness of technical efficiency and scale efficiency during the phase of <lb/>increasing returns to scale. In the future, it is suggested to expand the input of <lb/>production factors and improve the management level. <lb/>4. Dynamic efficiency evaluation based on data envelopment <lb/>analysis -Malmquist model <lb/>This section considers to reflect the changes in the relative efficiency of input and output of high-<lb/>tech enterprises in different provinces (cities), and adopts the DEA Malmquist model to conduct a <lb/>vertical comparison of input-output efficiency through the decomposition of the average <lb/>Malmquist index and the changes in total factor productivity from 2011 to 2020 (Yu et al., 2018). <lb/>4.1 Average Malmquist index and its decomposition of ten representative provinces (cities) <lb/>from 2011 to 2020 <lb/>Table 3 shows that, on average, the total factor productivity of high-tech enterprises in ten <lb/>representative provinces (cities) increased by 6.28% from 2011 to 2020. Among them, the <lb/>pure technical efficiency increased by 0.6%, the scale efficiency increased by 0.03% and the <lb/>technological progress index increased by 5.59%. <lb/>In terms of provinces (cities), the total factor productivity of high-tech enterprises in the <lb/>ten representative provinces (cities) from 2011 to 2020 was greater than 1. Among them, the <lb/>Table 3. <lb/>Average Malmquist <lb/>index and its <lb/>decomposition of ten <lb/>representative <lb/>provinces (cities) <lb/>from 2011 to 2020 <lb/>Province (city) <lb/>Effch <lb/>Techch <lb/>Pech <lb/>Sech <lb/>Tfpch <lb/>Beijing <lb/>1.012 <lb/>1.004 <lb/>1.011 <lb/>1.001 <lb/>1.017 <lb/>Guangdong <lb/>1.01 <lb/>1.075 <lb/>1.009 <lb/>1.001 <lb/>1.086 <lb/>Jiangsu <lb/>1 <lb/>1.054 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.054 <lb/>Zhejiang <lb/>1.037 <lb/>1.078 <lb/>1.033 <lb/>1.004 <lb/>1.118 <lb/>Shanghai <lb/>1 <lb/>1.063 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.063 <lb/>Shandong <lb/>1 <lb/>1.086 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.086 <lb/>Hubei <lb/>0.999 <lb/>1.027 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.999 <lb/>1.026 <lb/>Anhui <lb/>0.987 <lb/>1.057 <lb/>0.998 <lb/>0.989 <lb/>1.043 <lb/>Sichuan <lb/>1.013 <lb/>1.038 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.013 <lb/>1.052 <lb/>Tianjin <lb/>1.005 <lb/>1.077 <lb/>1.009 <lb/>0.996 <lb/>1.083 <lb/>Average <lb/>1.0063 <lb/>1.0559 <lb/>1.006 <lb/>1.0003 <lb/>1.0628 <lb/>Notes: &quot;Effch&quot; refers to the change of comprehensive technical efficiency, &quot;Techch&quot; refers to the change of <lb/>technology, &quot;Pech&quot; refers to the change of pure technical efficiency, &quot;Sech&quot; refers to the change of scale <lb/>efficiency and &quot;Tfpch&quot; refers to total factor productivity. Where, Tfpch ¼ Effch Â Techch, Effch ¼ Pech Â <lb/>Sech <lb/>Source: Table by authors <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">DEA and <lb/>Malmquist <lb/>index <lb/></note>

        <page>347 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>comprehensive technical efficiency of Jiangsu, Shanghai and Shandong provinces (cities) <lb/>remains unchanged, all thanks to the rise of the technological progress index. The <lb/>advancement of total factor productivity in other provinces (cities) comes from the mixed <lb/>effect of comprehensive technical efficiency and the technological progress index. <lb/>Specifically, Hubei and Anhui are affected by the decline of scale efficiency, which causes <lb/>the decline of comprehensive technical efficiency. The advancement of total factor <lb/>production efficiency is mainly because of the greater advancement of the technological <lb/>progress index. The comprehensive technical efficiency and technological progress index of <lb/>Beijing, Guangdong, Zhejiang, Sichuan and Tianjin have increased to varying degrees, <lb/>which together contributed to the advancement of total factor productivity, but the scale <lb/>efficiency of Tianjin has decreased and the scale efficiency of Sichuan has increased. <lb/>4.2 Annual total factor productivity changes in ten representative provinces (cities) from <lb/>2011 to 2020 <lb/>From 2011 to 2020, the annual total factor productivity of high-tech enterprises in ten <lb/>representative provinces (cities) showed a fluctuating trend of rising first and then declining, <lb/>reaching a peak between 2015 and 2016. According to the overall changes of the start and <lb/>end years, it can be divided into three types, as shown in Figure 1: <lb/>(1) Total factor productivity rise: Beijing, Guangdong, Hubei, Anhui and Tianjin <lb/>belong to this type. The initial annual total factor productivity is less than 1. After <lb/>slow changes and fluctuations, the total factor productivity from 2019 to 2020 has <lb/>achieved a breakthrough of more than 1, showing a good development trend. <lb/>(2) Total factor productivity increased, but the growth rate became smaller. Sichuan <lb/>belongs to this type, and the total factor productivity in the initial year and 2019-<lb/>Figure 1. <lb/>Changes in total <lb/>factor productivity in <lb/>ten representative <lb/>provinces (cities) <lb/>from 2011 to 2020 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>2011-2012 2012-2013 2013-2014 2014-2015 2015-2016 2016-2017 2017-2018 2018-2019 2019-2020 <lb/>Beijing <lb/>Guangdong <lb/>Jiangsu <lb/>Zhejiang <lb/>Shanghai <lb/>Shandong <lb/>Hubei <lb/>Anhui <lb/>Sichuan <lb/>Tianjin <lb/>Source: Figure by authors <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">APJIE <lb/>18,4 <lb/></note>

        <page>348 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>2020 was greater than 1, but the total factor productivity in 2019-2020 was <lb/>significantly less than that in the initial year, showing a trend of slowing down. <lb/>(3) Total factor productivity decreased, but the decline became smaller. Jiangsu, <lb/>Zhejiang, Shanghai and Shandong belong to this type. The total factor <lb/>productivity in the initial year and 2019-2020 is less than 1, but the total factor <lb/>productivity in 2019-2020 is remarkably better than that in the initial year, <lb/>showing a positive trend of increasing growth. <lb/>In addition, the total factor productivity of five provinces and cities, including Guangdong, <lb/>Zhejiang, Shanghai, Jiangsu and Shandong, exceeded 2 from 2015 to 2016, which was <lb/>mainly affected by the output index of &quot;export foreign exchange earning.&quot; For example, we <lb/>chose the province with the lowest total factor productivity in 2016 (Hubei: 1.456) and the <lb/>province with the highest total factor productivity (Zhejiang: 2.694) for comparison, as <lb/>shown in Figure 2. The four subcharts in Figure 2 show the change trends of the four <lb/>indicators of total income, export foreign exchange earnings, scientific and technological <lb/>activity personnel and internal expenditure of R&amp;D funds in Zhejiang and Hubei, <lb/>respectively. It can be concluded that the total factor productivity of these two provinces is <lb/>greatly affected by the output index of &quot;export foreign exchange earnings.&quot; Hubei Province&apos;s <lb/>Figure 2. <lb/>Change trend of four <lb/>indicators in Zhejiang <lb/>and Hubei from 2011 <lb/>to 2020 <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">DEA and <lb/>Malmquist <lb/>index <lb/></note>

        <page>349 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>export foreign exchange earnings showed steady linear growth from 2015 to 2016, and its <lb/>growth trend is almost the same as that of other years; Zhejiang Province showed linear <lb/>growth before 2015 and exponential growth from 2015 to 2019. This growth trend was <lb/>particularly obvious from 2015 to 2016. <lb/>5. Conclusions and suggestions <lb/>Aiming at the misunderstanding of emphasizing quantity and neglecting quality in the <lb/>cultivation of high-tech enterprises, this paper comprehensively uses the DEA-BCC model <lb/>and the DEA Malmquist index decomposition method to conduct a comprehensive <lb/>comparative study of the development of high-tech enterprises in ten representative <lb/>provinces (cities) from two aspects of static efficiency evaluation and dynamic efficiency <lb/>evaluation. <lb/>5.1 Research conclusion <lb/>To estimate the cultivation and development level of high-tech enterprises, we cannot rely <lb/>solely on the quantitative indicators of high-tech enterprises. Only in terms of input-output <lb/>efficiency and total factor productivity can we more objectively evaluate the development <lb/>quality of high-tech enterprises in different regions: <lb/>The rapid increase in the quantity of high-tech enterprises in most provinces (cities) <lb/>is accompanied by invalid input-output efficiency. In terms of average input-output <lb/>efficiency from 2011 to 2020, except that Shandong is DEA effective, the other nine <lb/>provinces (cities) have invalid scale efficiency, technical efficiency or both. In terms <lb/>of input-output efficiency at the time point of 2020, except that Shandong, <lb/>Guangdong, Zhejiang and Shanghai are DEA effective, the other six provinces <lb/>(cities) need to make efforts in changing the scale of factor input and improving the <lb/>management level. <lb/>The quality of high-tech enterprises needs to comprehensively examine input-<lb/>output efficiency and total factor productivity. Not the more input factors that affect <lb/>innovation performance, the better. Shanghai has the problem of redundant input or <lb/>insufficient output, and its total factor productivity is lower than that of most other <lb/>provinces (cities), which is worthy of vigilance. At present, the input-output <lb/>efficiency of Hubei, Anhui, Sichuan and Tianjin is relatively insufficient, but the <lb/>total factor productivity is relatively high, and the prospect is promising. <lb/>5.2 Enlightenment suggestions <lb/>In an effort to further improve the innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprises in all <lb/>provinces (cities) and promote the development of high-tech industries, the following <lb/>suggestions are put forward: <lb/>The national level should strengthen guidance to ensure that the policies of high-<lb/>tech enterprises are in line with the goals of developing high-tech industries. <lb/>Developing high-tech industries is a key measure to promote economy growth and <lb/>structure of industry upgrade. Cultivating high-tech enterprises gets a head start for <lb/>improving the innovation level of enterprises and promoting the development of <lb/>high-tech industries. In essence, the policy of high-tech enterprises is a policy <lb/>measure based on the enterprise level and oriented to industrial development. It is <lb/>suggested that the state strengthen the evaluation of the development quality of <lb/>high-tech enterprises and the driving role of high-tech enterprises in their <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">APJIE <lb/>18,4 <lb/></note>

        <page>350 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>industries/fields according to the &quot;high tech fields supported by the state,&quot; and <lb/>include it in the assessment standards for the identification of high-tech enterprises <lb/>organized by all provinces (cities). <lb/>Different provinces (cities) take differentiated measures to effectively promote the <lb/>development of high-tech enterprises in light of local conditions. The input-output <lb/>efficiency of Shandong, Guangdong, Zhejiang and Shanghai is relatively reasonable, <lb/>and the total factor productivity is increasing. It is suggested to continue to develop <lb/>according to the current production and operation modes in the future. The input-<lb/>output efficiency of Hubei, Sichuan, Tianjin, Jiangsu and Anhui is relatively <lb/>insufficient, and it is in the stage of increasing returns to scale, and the average <lb/>value of total factor productivity is greater than 1. In the future, it is suggested to <lb/>expand the input of production factors and vigorously develop them according to <lb/>the current mode of production and operation. The input-output efficiency of <lb/>Beijing is relatively insufficient during the phase of diminishing returns to scale, <lb/>and the average total factor productivity is greater than 1. From now on, it is <lb/>suggested to appropriately reduce the input of production factors and continue to <lb/>develop in accordance with the current mode of production and operation. <lb/>Build an exchange and cooperation platform to accelerate the linkage and <lb/>interoperability development of high-tech enterprises in different provinces (cities). <lb/>As the main force of innovation, high-tech enterprises should take the lead in <lb/>growing into industry benchmarks and field leaders. It is suggested to bring into <lb/>full play the role of industry associations/industrial alliances, build exchange and <lb/>cooperation platforms for high-tech enterprises in different industries, break <lb/>administrative boundaries and even market barriers between different provinces <lb/>(cities), support knowledge sharing, resource exchange and business docking <lb/>among high-quality high-tech enterprises, promote common progress and <lb/>collaborative development of high-quality high-tech enterprises and expand the <lb/>circle of friends of high-tech enterprises. Furthermore, by strengthening the <lb/>communication and cooperation platform of high-tech enterprises and the publicity <lb/>of high-quality high-tech enterprises, we will attract more scientific and <lb/>technological enterprises to actively find benchmarks, gaps and developments so as <lb/>to cultivate more high-tech enterprises with higher quality. <lb/>5.3 Research limitations <lb/>Because the DEA model used in this paper assumes that the improvement direction <lb/>of invalid units is to ensure that the input ratio of various production factors <lb/>remains unchanged, sometimes the proportion of scientific and technological <lb/>activity personnel and the total R&amp;D investment is not constant. In the future, the <lb/>nonradial DEA model can be considered for further research. <lb/>Due to historical data statistics, more provinces (cities) and longer panel data are <lb/>difficult to obtain. The samples studied in this paper mainly refer to the provinces <lb/>(cities) that ranked first in the number of national high-tech enterprises in 2020. <lb/>Limited by sample size, DEA analysis failed to select more input and output <lb/>indicators. In the future, with the accumulation of statistical data, the existing <lb/>efficiency analysis will be further optimized. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">DEA and <lb/>Malmquist <lb/>index <lb/></note>

        <page>351 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Bronzini, R. and Piselli, P. (2016), &quot;The impact of R&amp;D subsidies on firm innovation&quot;, Research Policy, <lb/>Vol. 45 No. 2, pp. 442-457. <lb/>Burton, J.P., Holtom, B.C., Sablynski, C.J., et al. (2009), &quot;The buffering effects of job embeddedness on <lb/>negative shocks&quot;, Journal of Vocational Behavior, Vol. 76 No. 1, pp. 42-51. <lb/>Chen, C.J. and Yeh, Q.J. (2005), &quot;A comparative performance evaluation of Taiwan&apos;s high-tech <lb/>industries&quot;, International Journal of Business Performance Management, Vol. 7 No. 1, <lb/>pp. 16-33. <lb/>Chen, X., Liu, X., Gong, Z., et al. (2021), &quot;Three-stage super-efficiency DEA models based on the <lb/>cooperative game and its application on the R&amp;D green innovation of the Chinese high-tech <lb/>industry&quot;, Computers and Industrial Engineering, Vol. 156, p. 107234. <lb/>Chen, V.Z., Zhang, X., Li, J., et al. (2014), &quot;Ownership structure and innovation performance: an <lb/>emerging market perspective&quot;, Asia Pacific Journal of Management, Vol. 31 No. 1, pp. 1-24. <lb/>Cochran, D.S. and Rauch, E. (2020), &quot;Sustainable enterprise design 4.0: addressing Industry 4.0 <lb/>technologies from the perspective of sustainability&quot;, Procedia Manufacturing, Vol. 51, <lb/>pp. 1237-1244. <lb/>Dou, Q., Sun, M., Wang, F., et al. (2020), &quot;High-tech enterprise identification and enterprise innovation <lb/>efficiency: promotion or inhibit--counterfactual estimation based on Chinese listed <lb/>companies&quot;, Science and Technology Progress and Policy, Vol. 37 No. 19, pp. 123-132. <lb/>Du, L., Jiang, H., Adebayo, T.S., et al. (2022), &quot;Asymmetric effects of high-tech industry and renewable <lb/>energy on consumption-based carbon emissions in MENA countries&quot;, Renewable Energy, <lb/>Vol. 196. <lb/>Fang, S., Xue, X., Yin, G., et al. (2020), &quot;Evaluation and improvement of technological innovation <lb/>efficiency of new energy vehicle enterprises in China based on DEA-Tobit model&quot;, Sustainability, <lb/>Vol. 12 No. 18, p. 7509. <lb/>Fare, R., Grosskopf, S. and Norris, M. (1994), &quot;Productivity growth, technical progress, and efficiency <lb/>change in industrialized countries&quot;, American Economic Review, Vol. 84 No. 5, pp. 1040-1044. <lb/>Ghazinoory, S. and Hashemi, Z. (2021), &quot;Do tax incentives and direct funding enhance innovation input <lb/>and output in high-tech firms?&quot;, The Journal of High Technology Management Research, Vol. 32 <lb/>No. 1, p. 100394. <lb/>Guo, J., Chang, J. and Huang, H. (2018), &quot;Efficiency evaluation of hi-tech enterprises from the <lb/>perspective of industrial development: empirical research based on DEA model&quot;, Science and <lb/>Technology Management Research, Vol. 38 No. 12, pp. 67-72. <lb/>Guo, Y., Zhu, Y. and Zhang, Y. (2020), &quot;Unbalanced development of urban logistics and its external <lb/>effects: take the sample of Shaanxi province as an example&quot;, Technology Economics, Vol. 39 <lb/>No. 7, pp. 128-139. <lb/>Han, J. (2010), &quot;An empirical analysis on China&apos;s high-technology industry innovation efficiency based <lb/>on SFA&quot;, Studies in Science of Science, Vol. 28 No. 3, pp. 467-472. <lb/>Hu, Y. and Zhou, L. (2018), &quot;Research on the innovation efficiency and influencing factors of high-tech <lb/>industry in the Yangtze river economic belt&quot;, Journal of Industrial Technological Economics, <lb/>Vol. 37 No. 6, pp. 71-77. <lb/>Kortelainen, M. (2008), &quot;Dynamic environmental performance analysis: a Malmquist index approach&quot;, <lb/>Ecological Economics, Vol. 64 No. 4, pp. 701-715. <lb/>Law, K.M.Y. and Gunasekaran, A. (2012), &quot;Sustainability development in high-tech manufacturing <lb/>firms in Hong Kong: motivators and readiness&quot;, International Journal of Production Economics, <lb/>Vol. 137 No. 1, pp. 116-125. <lb/>Lee, H. and Parka, Y. (2009), &quot;Comparative evaluation of performance of national R&amp;D programs with <lb/>heterogeneous objectives: a DEA approach&quot;, European Journal of Operational Research, Vol. 196 <lb/>No. 3, pp. 847-855. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">APJIE <lb/>18,4 <lb/></note>

        <page>352 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Li, W. and Zhang, D. (2021), &quot;Independent innovation capability of high-tech enterprises based on <lb/>FPGA processor and dynamic reconfigurable technology&quot;, Microprocessors and Microsystems, <lb/>Vol. 81, p. 103799. <lb/>Li, Y., Wang, Y. and Yang, J. (2015), &quot;Research on influencing of self-efficacy, job involvement on job <lb/>performance of high-tech enterprise&apos; R&amp;D staff&quot;, Science of Science and Management of S. and <lb/>T, Vol. 36 No. 2, pp. 173-180. <lb/>Li, J., Zahng, J. and Xu, Q. (2020), &quot;Evaluation and improvement path on innovation efficiency of high-<lb/>tech enterprises in Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei region&quot;, Science and Technology Management <lb/>Research, Vol. 40 No. 12, pp. 64-69. <lb/>Lin, R., Xie, Z., Hao, Y., et al. (2020), &quot;Improving high-tech enterprise innovation in big data <lb/>environment: a combinative view of internal and external governance&quot;, International Journal of <lb/>Information Management, Vol. 50, pp. 575-585. <lb/>Liu, C., Gao, X., Ma, W., et al. (2020), &quot;Research on regional differences and influencing factors of green <lb/>technology innovation efficiency of China&apos;s high-tech industry&quot;, Journal of Computational and <lb/>Applied Mathematics, Vol. 369, p. 112597. <lb/>Lv, Y., Gong, L., Hu, J., et al. (2017), &quot;Research on innovation status survey and innovation efficiency <lb/>evaluation of high-tech enterprises--case of national high-tech enterprises in Hangzhou&quot;, <lb/>Bulletin of Science and Technology, Vol. 33 No. 3, pp. 242-247. <lb/>Mumford, M.D. (2000), &quot;Managing creative people: strategies and tactics for innovation&quot;, Human <lb/>Resource Management Review, Vol. 10 No. 3, pp. 313-351. <lb/>Pylaeva, I.S., Podshivalova, M.V., Alola, A.A., Podshivalov, D.V. and Demin, A.A. (2022), &quot;A new <lb/>approach to identifying high-tech manufacturing SMEs with sustainable technological <lb/>development: empirical evidence&quot;, Journal of Cleaner Production, Vol. 363, p. 132322. <lb/>Raab, R.A. and Kotamraju, P. (2006), &quot;The efficiency of the high-tech economy: conventional development <lb/>indexes versus a performance index&quot;, Journal of Regional Science, Vol. 46 No. 3, pp. 545-562. <lb/>Sha, D. and Wang, M. (2022), &quot;Evaluation on innovation efficiency of nine provinces and autonomous <lb/>regions in the Yellow River basin&quot;, Science and Technology Management Research, Vol. 42 No. 6, <lb/>pp. 43-50. <lb/>Si, Y. and Li, Y. (2017), &quot;A study of venture capital on high-tech industry technology innovation based <lb/>on empirical analysis on DEA model&quot;, Science and Technology Management Research, Vol. 37 <lb/>No. 12, pp. 167-171. <lb/>Simonen, J., Svento, R. and Juutinen, A. (2015), &quot;Specialization and diversity as drivers of economic <lb/>growth: evidence from high-tech industries&quot;, Papers in Regional Science, Vol. 94 No. 2, <lb/>pp. 229-247. <lb/>Wang, S. and Fan, F. (2022), &quot;The impact of China&apos;s sustainable development efficiency on its scientific <lb/>and technological innovation&quot;, Journal of Dalian University of Technology (Social Sciences), <lb/>Vol. 43 No. 3, pp. 41-50. <lb/>Wang, Y., Pan, J., Pei, R., et al. (2020), &quot;Assessing the technological innovation efficiency of China&apos;s <lb/>high-tech industries with a two-stage network DEA approach&quot;, Socio-Economic Planning <lb/>Sciences, Vol. 71, p. 100810. <lb/>Xiao, R.Q., Wang, C.J. and Qian, L. (2015), &quot;Research on Chinese enterprise&apos;s technology innovation <lb/>efficiency and its influencing factors in different property based on the angle of value chain in <lb/>the two stages&quot;, Journal of Industrial Engineering/Engineering Management, Vol. 29 No. 2, <lb/>pp. 190-201. <lb/>Yang, M. and Wang, J. (2020), &quot;Marine high-tech enterprise ecosystem based on sustainable <lb/>development&quot;, Sustainable Computing: Informatics and Systems, Vol. 28, p. 100399. <lb/>Ye, J., Wan, Q., Li, R., et al. (2022), &quot;How do R&amp;D agglomeration and economic policy uncertainty affect <lb/>the innovative performance of Chinese high-tech industry?&quot;, Technology in Society, Vol. 69, <lb/>p. 101957. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">DEA and <lb/>Malmquist <lb/>index <lb/></note>

        <page>353 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Yu, L., Zhang, M. and Wang, Z. (2018), &quot;The study of the performance evaluation of regional hi-tech <lb/>industrial policies and the influencing factors&quot;, Studies in Science of Science, Vol. 36 No. 1, <lb/>pp. 28-36. <lb/>Zhang, Y. and Lv, X. (2013), &quot;A study of high-tech firms&apos; innovation performance and its determinants&quot;, <lb/>Science Research Management, Vol. 34 No. 12, pp. 58-65. <lb/></listBibl>

        <front>Corresponding author <lb/>Tianbo Tang can be contacted at: timbert@163.com <lb/></front>

        <div type="annex">For instructions on how to order reprints of this article, please visit our website: <lb/>www.emeraldgrouppublishing.com/licensing/reprints.htm <lb/>Or contact us for further details: permissions@emeraldinsight.com <lb/></div>

        <note place="headnote">APJIE <lb/>18,4 <lb/></note>

        <page>354 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/apjie/article-pdf/18/4/340/9469426/apjie-10-2023-0190.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>