<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Identification of transthyretin as a novel <lb/>interacting partner for the δ subunit of GABA A <lb/>receptors <lb/>Li Zhou ID <lb/>1 <lb/>*, Xin Tang 1 , Xinyi Li 2 , Yuting Bai 1 , Joel N. Buxbaum 2 , Gong Chen 1 * <lb/>1 Department of Biology, Huck Institutes of Life Sciences, The Pennsylvania State University, University <lb/>Park, PA, United States of America, 2 Department of Molecular and Experimental Medicine, The Scripps <lb/>Research Institute, La Jolla, CA, United States of America <lb/>* li.zhou.sci@gmail.com (LZ); gongchen@psu.edu(GC) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>GABA A receptors (GABA A -Rs) play critical roles in brain development and synchronization of <lb/>neural network activity. While synaptic GABA A -Rs can exert rapid inhibition, the extrasynaptic <lb/>GABA A -Rs can tonically inhibit neuronal activity due to constant activation by ambient GABA. <lb/>The δ subunit-containing GABA A -Rs are expressed abundantly in the cerebellum, hippocam-<lb/>pus and thalamus to mediate the major tonic inhibition in the brain. While electrophysiological <lb/>and pharmacological properties of the δ-GABA A -Rs have been well characterized, the molec-<lb/>ular interacting partners of the δ-GABA A -Rs are not clearly defined. Here, using a yeast two-<lb/>hybrid screening assay, we identified transthyretin (TTR) as a novel regulatory molecule for <lb/>the δ-GABA A -Rs. Knockdown of TTR in cultured cerebellar granule neurons significantly <lb/>decreased the δ receptor expression; whereas overexpressing TTR in cortical neurons <lb/>increased the δ receptor expression. Electrophysiological analysis confirmed that knockdown <lb/>or overexpression of TTR in cultured neurons resulted in a corresponding decrease or <lb/>increase of tonic currents. Furthermore, in vivo analysis of TTR-/-mice revealed a significant <lb/>decrease of the surface expression of the δ-GABA A -Rs in cerebellar granule neurons. <lb/>Together, our studies identified TTR as a novel regulator of the δ-GABA A -Rs. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>GABA (γ-aminobutyric acid) activates GABA A and GABA B receptors to mediate the majority <lb/>of inhibition in the brain [1, 2]. GABA A receptors (GABA A -Rs) are located on both synaptic <lb/>and extrasynaptic membranes to mediate phasic and tonic inhibition. We have recently dem-<lb/>onstrated that synaptic and extrasynaptic GABA A -Rs compete with each other to regulate the <lb/>homeostasis of inhibition [3]. Deficits in GABA A -R-mediated neurotransmission are involved <lb/>in epilepsy, anxiety, depression, schizophrenia, and autism [4-8]. Extrasynaptic GABA A -Rs <lb/>are sensitive to steroid and alcohol regulation, and play important roles in sleep, stress, <lb/>puberty, learning, and pregnancy-related mood disorders [9-11]. The δ subunit-containing <lb/>GABA A -Rs (δ-GABA A -Rs) are one of the major subtypes of extrasynaptic GABA A -Rs, localiz-<lb/>ing in the cerebellum (α6βδ), hippocampus and thalamus (α4βδ) [9, 12-14]. Although it is <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/>1 / 17 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Zhou L, Tang X, Li X, Bai Y, Buxbaum JN, <lb/>Chen G (2019) Identification of transthyretin as a <lb/>novel interacting partner for the δ subunit of GABA A <lb/>receptors. PLoS ONE 14(1): e0210094. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 <lb/>Editor: Alexander G. Obukhov, Indiana University <lb/>School of Medicine, UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: June 14, 2018 <lb/>Accepted: December 17, 2018 <lb/>Published: January 7, 2019 <lb/>Copyright: © 2019 Zhou et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>included in our paper. <lb/>Funding: This work was supported by grants from <lb/>National Institutes of Health (MH083911 and <lb/>AG045656) and an Endowment Fund from <lb/>Pennsylvania State University to G.C. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>well known that δ-GABA A -Rs mediate tonic inhibition of neuronal activity in the brain [9, 14, <lb/>15], the molecular partners that interact with the δ-GABA A -Rs have not yet been identified. <lb/>Here, we employed a yeast two-hybridization system to screen for δ-subunit interacting <lb/>proteins from a mouse cerebellar cDNA library, a brain region in which the δ-subunit is highly <lb/>expressed. We indentified transthyretin (TTR) as a novel interacting partner for the δ-subunit. <lb/>Transthyretin (TTR) is a transporter for thyroxine and retinol-binding protein bound to reti-<lb/>nol in the blood and cerebral spinal fluid [16, 17]. Plasma TTR is mainly produced by liver, <lb/>while TTR in the brain is predominantly synthesized by choroid plexus [18] and by neurons <lb/>under stress [19]. TTR interacts with the β-amyloid peptide (Aβ) oligomers and fibrils and <lb/>may play a neuroprotective role in Alzheimer&apos;s disease [20-23]. <lb/>Our current study demonstrates that TTR interacts with δ-GABA A -Rs and regulates their <lb/>expression and function. We found that TTR co-immunoprecipitates with the δ subunit in <lb/>brain lysates. Knockdown of TTR expression in cultured cerebellar granule cells significantly <lb/>reduced the surface δ expression level as well as the corresponding tonic current. Conversely, <lb/>overexpressing TTR in cortical neurons, which typically have low levels of δ expression, signifi-<lb/>cantly increased the surface expression level of the δ subunit and the tonic current as well. <lb/>Interestingly, external application of recombinant human TTR (hTTR), but not mutant mono-<lb/>meric hTTR, significantly increased the surface δ receptors in cultured cerebellar granule cells. <lb/>We further investigated TTR regulation of the δ receptors in TTR knockout mice, and <lb/>observed a significant decrease of the δ surface staining in cerebellar granule layer compared <lb/>to the wild type (WT) mice. In conclusion, we discovered that TTR is a novel interacting part-<lb/>ner for the δ-GABA A -Rs. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Yeast two-hybrid assay <lb/>Mouse cerebellar RNA was extracted using Neuron spin RNA II kit (Clontech). Make Your <lb/>Own &quot;Mate &amp; Plate™&quot; Library (Clontech) was used to establish the mouse cDNA library from <lb/>the cerebellar RNA according to the manual. Matchmaker™ Gold Yeast Two-Hybrid System <lb/>(Clontech) and the established cDNA library were used in the interacting screen according to <lb/>the manual. The interaction of pray (pGADT7) and bait (pGBKT7) fusion proteins were <lb/>assayed by the AUR1-C, ADE2, HIS3, and MEL1 reporters. Plasmid DNA of positive clones <lb/>was recovered and inserts were analyzed by sequencing. <lb/>Plasmid constructs and transfection <lb/>The extracellular domain of the δ subunit of GABA A receptor was subcloned into pGBKT7-DNA <lb/>BD vector (Clontech). The full-length TTR cDNA was amplified from mouse cerebellar RNA <lb/>and was cloned as BGII and EcoR fragment into pN3HA plasmid in which the GFP sequence of <lb/>pEGFPC1 was replaced by triple HA (a kind gift from Dr. Yingwei Mao) or PEGFPC1 vector. <lb/>The plasmid pLenti-GIII-CMV encoding the full length human TTR with RFP reporter driven <lb/>by the independent promoter was purchased from Applied Biological Materials (Richmond, <lb/>Canada). The GIPZ mouse TTR shRNA vector was purchased from Open Biosystem. The vec-<lb/>tors of GABA A receptor δ, α6, β3 subunits were described preciously in our publications [3, 24]. <lb/>The purified proteins of human TTR and mutated monomeric hTTR are from Dr. Buxbaum&apos; <lb/>Lab (Scripps Research Institute). Primary cultured neurons were transfected using calcium-phos-<lb/>hphate transfection protocol as described [25]. For HEK 293T cell transfection, polyethylenimine <lb/>(PEI, Polyscience) was used. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Mice and primary neuron culture <lb/>C57BL/6 [WT (B6)] and mttr-/-(mouse ttr knockout) mice were used similar to that described <lb/>before [19]. C57BL/6 were purchased from Jackson Lab. Mice of mttr-/-were from Dr. Bux-<lb/>baum&apos; Lab(Scripps Institutes). Mice of either sex were used in the experiments. Primary cere-<lb/>bellar and cortical tissues were dissected out from C57BL/6 mouse pups (newborn for cortical <lb/>culture and postnatal 5-7 days for cerebellar culture) as described previously [3, 26, 27]. All <lb/>the animal procedures were reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use <lb/>Committee at Penn State University (IACUC# 43379). Briefly, cerebellar or cortical cells were <lb/>dissociated with 0.25% Trypsin-EDTA containing 50 units/ml DNase I and then plated on a <lb/>monolayer of cortical astrocytes at a density of 8,000-12,000 cells/cm 2 . The cerebellar neuron <lb/>culture medium contained 500 ml MEM (Invitrogen, Eugene, OR), 10% fetal bovine serum <lb/>(HyClone, Logan, UT), 10 ml B-27 supplement (Invitrogen), 100 mg NaHCO3, 20 mM KCl, <lb/>0.5 mM L-glutamine, 25 unit/ml penicillin/streptomycin, and 4 μM AraC to suppress the <lb/>excessive proliferation of astrocytes. Neurons were maintained at 37˚C in a 5% CO 2 -humidi-<lb/>fied incubator for 2-3 weeks. All data presented as mean ± SE. Student&apos;s t test or one-way <lb/>ANOVA followed with Bonferroni correction were used for statistical analyses. <lb/>Co-immunoprecipitation and Western blot <lb/>The cerebellum tissue of adult mice was dissected out and homogenized in cold IP lysis buffer <lb/>containing 25 mM Tris/HCl (pH 7.4), 150 mM NaCl, 1% NP-40, 1 mM EDTA, 5% glycerol <lb/>(Thermo Scientific, Rockford, USA) with protease inhibitors and phosphatase inhibitors <lb/>(Sigma), followed by incubation at 4˚C for 30 min and sonication twice for 30 s each. The <lb/>supernatant of brain extracts was harvested by centrifugation (12,000 g, 10 min). Protein con-<lb/>tent was measured by Bradford protein assay (Thermo Scientific). For Co-IP assay, the cerebel-<lb/>lum extracts or the overexpressed HEK cell lysates were first pre-cleaned by incubation with <lb/>Dynabeads M-280 IgG (Invitrogen) for 2 hr at 4˚C. 2 μg primary antibodies of rabbit anti-<lb/>TTR (DAKO), mouse anti-HA (Santacruz), or rabbit anti-myc (cell signal Tech) were added <lb/>into the protein lysate and incubated overnight at 4˚C, followed by adding 30 μl Dynabead M-<lb/>280 anti-mouse or anti-rabbit IgG (Invitrogen) and incubating for another 4 hr at 4˚C. After <lb/>washing with PBS, the immunoprecipitated proteins were eluted and boiled for 10 min in <lb/>NuPAGE LDS sample buffer (Invitrogen). The precipitated protein was then separated by <lb/>SDS-PAGE gel and transferred to PVDF membrane. The primary antibodies used in this <lb/>study included mouse anti-HA, rabbit anti-Myc, rabbit anti-GABA A -R δ subunit (PhosphoSo-<lb/>lution, Aurora, USA), and mouse anti-actin (BD). Immunoblot band intensities were quanti-<lb/>fied using Image J software. All experiments were repeated at least three times independently. <lb/>Immunocytochemistry <lb/>For live cell staining, cultured cerebellar or cotical neurons (9-12 days in vitro) were incubated <lb/>in bath solution (128 mM NaCl, 30 mM glucose, 25 mM HEPES, 2 mM KCl, 2 mM CaCl 2 and <lb/>1 mM MgCl 2 (320 mOsm, pH 7.4) with primary anti-GABA A -R δ subunit or anti-transthyre-<lb/>tin antibodies (Abcam) at 4˚C for 1 hr, followed by washing with phosphate-buffered saline <lb/>(PBS) and fixed for 15 min in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA). After fixation, neurons were <lb/>blocked with 5% BSA in PBS for 1 hr, followed by incubation with Dylight-conjugated anti-<lb/>rabbit 546 (1:500, Jackson ImmunoResearch) or Alexa flour 488 (1:500, Molecular probes) for <lb/>2 hr under non-permeabilized condition. <lb/>For total protein staining, neurons were washed with bath solution, fixed by 4% PFA for 12 <lb/>min, and followed by three times washing with PBS. Then, neurons were permeabilized with <lb/>0.2% triton in PBS for 8 min, and changed into 5% NDS + 0.1% triton in PBS for 30 min before <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>incubating with primary antibodies in blocking buffer overnight at 4˚C. After extensive wash-<lb/>ing with PBS, the coverslips with neurons were incubated with appropriate secondary antibod-<lb/>ies for 1 hr at room temperature, and then rinsed with PBS four times. The coverslips were <lb/>finally mounted with anti-fading mounting solution containing DAPI (Invitrogen). The <lb/>images were taken by an epifluorescent microscope (Nikon TE 2000-S) or a confocal micro-<lb/>scope (Olympus FV1000) and analyzed by Image J software. <lb/>For mouse brain section staining, 7-8 months old mice were anesthetized with 2.5% Aver-<lb/>tin and then perfused with cold saline solution (0.9% NaCl) for 2 min. The whole brain was <lb/>immediately taken out and cut into half and fixed in 4% PFA overnight at 4˚C. The brain tissue <lb/>was then cut into 45 μm slices with a vibratome (Lecia). The brain slices were washed with PBS <lb/>and pretreated with 0.3% triton for 2 hr and then incubated with 5% NDS and 0.1% triton in <lb/>PBS for 2 hr. The primary antibodies in blocking solution were applied to brain slices at 4˚C <lb/>overnight. The next day, the cells were washed with PBS and incubated with proper fluoro-<lb/>phore-conjucated secondary antibodies for 1 hr at room temperature. After the secondary <lb/>antibody incubation, the excessive antibodies were washed off with PBS and the coverslips or <lb/>brain slices were mounted in anti-fading mounting solution with DAPI (Invitrogen). The <lb/>images were collected on an Olympus FV1000 confocal microscope. For quantification of <lb/>GABA A -R δ subunit signal, the mean intensity of neuronal soma was analyzed by Image J soft-<lb/>ware. The colocalization was analyzed with the Intensity Correlation analysis plug-in in ImageJ <lb/>(National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD) [28]. All experiments were repeated at least <lb/>three times independently. <lb/>Electrophysiology <lb/>TTR and TTR shRNA plasmids were transfected at 4 days in vitro (DIV) with Ca 2+ -phosphate <lb/>methods described before [25]. Cover glasses with cultured cells were transferred to a record-<lb/>ing chamber with continuous perfusion of the bath Tyrode&apos;s solution that contains (in mM) <lb/>128 NaCl, 30 glucose, 25 HEPES, 5 KCl, 2 CaCl 2 , and 1 MgCl 2 , pH 7.3, ~320 Osm. Fire-pol-<lb/>ished borosilicate glass pipettes with resistance of 3-5 MO were used for recording. The inter-<lb/>nal pipette solution contained (in mM) 135 KCl, 10 HEPES, 2 EGTA, 10 Tris-<lb/>phosphocreatine, 4 MgATP, and 0.5 Na 2 GTP (pH 7.3, ~300 Osm). Whole-cell recordings of <lb/>THIP-induced currents were performed at room temperature in voltage-clamp mode using <lb/>Multiclamp 700A amplifier (Molecular Devices, Palo Alto, CA), similar to previously <lb/>described [24]. The membrane potential was held at -70 mV. Data were acquired using <lb/>pClamp 9 software (Molecular Devices), sampled at 5 kHz, and filtered at 1 kHz. Cerebellar <lb/>cultures were recorded around DIV 8, whereas cortical cultures were recorded around DIV <lb/>14. To examine THIP-induced currents, neurons were perfused with bath solution that con-<lb/>tains TTX (0.5 μM) and CNQX (10 μΜ) to block voltage-gated sodium channels and AMPA/ <lb/>kainate receptor currents. THIP (2 μM) was then applied for 10 s through a valve-controlled <lb/>drug delivery system VC-6 (Warner Instruments, Hamden, CT) to elicit stable inward current. <lb/>All experiments were repeated at least three times independently. <lb/>Results <lb/>Transthyretin identified as the interacting partner for GABA A receptor δ <lb/>subunit <lb/>The structure of GABA A -R δ subunit includes one extracellular domain (extra-δ), one cyto-<lb/>plasmic domain and four transmembrane domains. The N-terminus of GABA A -R subunit is <lb/>responsible for oligomerization and receptor assembly [1]. While δ-GABA A -Rs have been <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>extensively studied in terms of function and subcellular localization, the molecular partners <lb/>interacting with δ-GABA A -Rs have not yet been identified. To understand the molecular <lb/>mechanism of δ-receptor regulation, we used the extracellular domain of the δ subunit (amino <lb/>acid 17-248) as the bait in a yeast two-hybrid screen to identify interacting proteins. Since the <lb/>cerebellum has a high level of δ subunit expression, we made the cDNA library from adult <lb/>mouse cerebellum. From this library, one of the positive clones encoding amino acid 73-147 <lb/>of transthyretin (TTR) was isolated (Fig 1A). To confirm the interaction between TTR and the <lb/>extra-δ in mammalian systems, HA-tagged full length TTR and Myc-tagged extra-δ were co-<lb/>expressed in HEK cells, and the lysate was immunoprecipitated with HA or myc antibodies. <lb/>Both HA-TTR and myc-extra-δ were co-precipitated with each other (Fig 1B and 1C). Consis-<lb/>tently, confocal images showed that TTR was co-localized with α6β3δ receptors when co-<lb/>expressed in HEK cells (Fig 1D). The co-localozation of the transfected TTR and α6β3δ recep-<lb/>tors was analyzed using intensity correlation analysis. The mean intensity correlation quotient <lb/>(ICQ) number of the co-localozation of the transfected TTR and delta subunits is 0.333±0.108 <lb/>(Fig 1E), which means that the staining of TTR and α6β3δ receptors are dependent staining. <lb/>Therefore, our results identified TTR as a novel interacting protein with the δ subunit of <lb/>GABA A receptors. <lb/>Endogenous transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors in the <lb/>cerebellum <lb/>It is well know that δ-subunit-containing GABAA receptors mediate tonic inhibition in cere-<lb/>bellar granule cells [29], the dentate gyrus granule cells [29], alamic neurons [30], and in pyra-<lb/>midal neurons[31]. And recently, α1δ-subunit assemblies were shown to be present in the <lb/>hippocampal interneurons [32]. These inspire us to examine the interaction between TTR and <lb/>the δ subunit of GABA A -Rs in primary neuronal cultures. We started with an investigation of <lb/>the endogenous signal of TTR and the δ subunit in cerebellar granule cells in primary cultures. <lb/>After fixation and membrane permeabilization, we found that TTR and the δ subunit partially <lb/>co-localized in granule cells (Fig 2A). We further performed live cell staining without mem-<lb/>brane permeabilization and demonstrated that TTR and the δ subunit also partially co-local-<lb/>ized on cell surface (Fig 2B). We next overexpressed human TTR (hTTR) and the rat δ subunit <lb/>in cultured cortical neurons, which usually lack endogenous δ subunit, and performed live cell <lb/>staining. Again, the expressed hTTR and the δ subunit were found partially co-localized in cor-<lb/>tical neurons (Fig 2C). The quantification of both total staining and surface staining of TTR <lb/>and δ-GABA A -Rs in cerebellar neurons was analyzed by the intensity correlation analysis. The <lb/>mean intensity correlation quotient (ICQ) of total staining is 0.242±0.043, and the mean ICQ <lb/>of surface staining is 0.318±0.048 (Fig 2E). The number of ICQ between 0 and +0.5 indicates <lb/>that they are dependent staining. To further understand whether TTR interacts with the δ-<lb/>GABA A -Rs in mouse brain in vivo, we used TTR antibodies to immunoprecipitate TTR from <lb/>cerebellum lysate, which is known to contain a high level of the δ-GABA A -Rs [33]. Immuno-<lb/>blotting with the δ-specific antibodies clearly showed that TTR and the δ-GABA A -Rs were co-<lb/>immunoprecipitated with each other in the cerebellum tissue (Fig 2D). Therefore, TTR can <lb/>interact with the δ-GABA A -Rs in the brain in vivo. <lb/>TTR regulates the expression of δ-GABA A receptors <lb/>To investigate whether TTR directly regulates the δ-GABA A -R expression in neuronal cells, we <lb/>knocked down TTR expression with mouse-specific shRNAs in cultured cerebellar granule <lb/>cells. As shown in Fig 3A, knockdown of TTR resulted in a significant reduction of the surface <lb/>δ expression level. Importantly, human TTR, which is resistant to the mouse shRNAs (see <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>sequence alignment in Fig 3C), could rescue the deficit of the surface δ staining (Fig 3B; Con-<lb/>trol, 1 ± 0.08, n = 22; TTR shRNA, 0.52 ± 0.093, n = 34; TTR shRNA + hTTR, 0.92 ± 0.12, <lb/>n = 19). The knockdown efficiency of TTR shRNA on mouse TTR was demonstrated in Fig <lb/>3D (75% reduction in the presence of shRNA; p &lt; 0.03). We also demonstrated that TTR <lb/>shRNA had no off-target effect on the δ subunit (Fig 3E). <lb/>Fig 1. Identification of TTR as a novel interacting protein for the GABA A receptor δ subunit. (A) Alignment of the <lb/>amino-acid sequence of full length mouse transthyretin (NP_038725) with the sequence of the positive clone obtained <lb/>from our yeast two-hybrid screening. (B-C) Co-immunoprecipitation of the HA-tagged TTR and the myc-tagged <lb/>extracellular domain of the δ-subunit (extra-δ) after co-expression in HEK cells. (D) Confocal images showing the co-<lb/>localization of the α6β3δ-receptors (green) and TTR (red) after co-expressed in HEK cells. The arrows show the <lb/>coloclization sites. Scale bar, 10 μm. (E) The quantification of colocalization of the transfected TTR and α6β3δ <lb/>receptors in HEK cell by intensity correlation analysis in Image J. The mean intensity correlation quotient(ICQ) is <lb/>between 0 and +05, which means they are dependent staining. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 2. TTR interacts with the GABA A receptor δ subunit in vivo. (A) Total staining of endogenous GABA A receptor <lb/>δ subunit (red) and TTR (green) in cerebellar granule cells in culture. Boxed areas were enlarged for better view of the <lb/>colocalization. The arrows point the coloclization sites. Scale bar: 5 μm. (B) Live cell staining of the endogenous surface <lb/>level of TTR (green) and the GABA A receptor δ subunit (red) in cultured cerebellar granule cells. The arrows point the <lb/>coloclization sites. Scale bar: 5 μm. (C) Live cell staining of cortical neurons overexpressed with hTTR (green) and rat δ <lb/>subunit (red), revealing partial colocalization of the two signals. The arrows point the coloclization sites. Scale bar: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>To further understand the functional regulation of TTR on the extrasynaptic δ-GABA A -Rs, <lb/>we employed electrophysiological recordings to measure δ-GABA A -R mediated tonic currents <lb/>in cerebellar granule cell cultures. Low concentration of THIP is a relatively specific agonist <lb/>for δ-GABA A -Rs [13]. We found that application of THIP (2 μM) induced a significant tonic <lb/>current in cerebellar granule cells (Fig 3F), indicating the presence of δ-GABA A -Rs as revealed <lb/>by surface immunostaining. Importantly, the tonic current was significantly reduced after <lb/>knocking down TTR in cerebellar granule neurons, consistent with the reduction of surface δ-<lb/>staining induced by TTR shRNA (Fig 3G). Quantification indicated that both the THIP cur-<lb/>rent amplitude and the current density were significantly reduced in TTR knockdown cells <lb/>(Fig 3H and 3I; p &lt; 0.05), whereas the capacitance of cells, a measure of cell size was not <lb/>changed (Fig 3J). <lb/>We next examined whether increasing intracellular synthesis of TTR will affect the expres-<lb/>sion of the δ-GABA A -Rs. For this purpose, we tested in cultured cortical neurons, which nor-<lb/>mally do not express δ-GABA A -Rs. As shown in the control cortical neurons expressing <lb/>mCherry alone, the immunostaining of the δ subunit was essentially absent (Fig 4A, top row). <lb/>In contrast, when cortical neurons were transfected with human TTR, the δ immunostaining <lb/>signal was readily detected (Fig 4A, bottom row). Quantitative data showed a remarkable <lb/>increase of the δ expression level after overexpressing hTTR in cortical neurons (Fig 4B; <lb/>p &lt; 0.05). These immunostaining results were further confirmed with electrophysiological <lb/>analyses. To assess the level of the δ-GABA A -Rs in cortical neurons, we applied their specific <lb/>agonist THIP (2 μM) to examine the activated tonic current. We found that THIP-induced <lb/>tonic current was significantly increased in cortical neurons after overexpressing hTTR (Fig <lb/>4C-4G; p &lt; 0.05). Together, our results demonstrated that TTR is a potent regulator of the δ-<lb/>GABA A -Rs. <lb/>Monomeric TTR not effective in regulating δ-GABA A -Rs <lb/>TTR is mostly synthesized in the liver and in choroid plexus in the brain[18]. Therefore, neu-<lb/>rons are often exposed to TTR in the extracellular space. TTR normally circulates as a non-<lb/>covalently bound homo-tetramer [34]. A mutant TTR has been engineered that cannot form <lb/>tetramers and exists as a monomer [35]. To investigate which type of TTR, tetramer or mono-<lb/>mer, regulates the δ-GABA A -Rs, we added either normal purified human TTR (hTTR) protein <lb/>or purified monomeric hTTR (M-hTTR; both at 14 ug/ml) protein into the culture medium <lb/>for 24 hrs before analyzing the surface level of δ-GABA A -Rs in cerebellar granule neurons. <lb/>Both types of hTTR contain no tags. We found that normal hTTR protein significantly <lb/>increased the expression level of δ-GABA A -Rs as expected, but monomeric hTTR had no effect <lb/>on the δ-GABA A -Rs (Fig 5A). Quantitative analysis demonstrated that normal hTTR, but not <lb/>monomeric hTTR, increased the surface expression of δ-GABA A -Rs in both soma and den-<lb/>drites (Fig 5B; p &lt; 0.01). <lb/>In vivo analysis of TTR effect on δ-GABA A receptors <lb/>After in vitro analysis of TTR regulation of δ-GABA A -Rs in cell cultures, we further investi-<lb/>gated TTR effect in mouse brain in vivo by using TTR knockout mice (TTR-/-) [36]. It is <lb/>10 μm. (D) Co-immunoprecipitation of TTR and δ-receptors from mouse cerebellum extract. Brain lysate was <lb/>immunoprecipitated with sheep anti-TTR antibody or normal sheep IgG as a control, and then immunoblotted with <lb/>rabbit anti-δ antibody. (E) The quantification ofcolocalization of the TTR and δ-α6β3δ receptors in cerebellar neurons <lb/>by intensity correlation analysis. The intensity correlation quotient(IQC) was shown for both total staining (TS) and <lb/>live cell staining(LCS). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 3. TTR regulates the surface expression of δ-receptors in cultured cerebellar neurons. (A) Knockdown TTR with mouse-specific shRNAs reduced the <lb/>surface δ-staining (red), which was rescued by co-transection with human TTR (RFP-tagged, purple in the insert) that was resistant to mouse TTR shRNAs. <lb/>Arrows point to the transfected cells. Scale bar, 10 μm. (B) Quantification of the surface δ staining signal shown in (A). � P &lt; 0.05; �� P &lt; 0.01. (C) <lb/>Nucleotide sequence alignment showing the specificity of the TTR shRNA designed for mouse TTR, but not for human TTR. (D) Knockdown efficiency of <lb/>the TTR shRNAs evaluated by cotransfecting mouse HA-TTR with control plasmid or with TTR specific shRNAs in HEK cells. TTR shRNAs significantly <lb/>downregulated the expression level of mouse HA-TTR. (E) TTR shRNAs had no off-target effect directly on δ-GABA A -Rs when coexpressed in HEK cells. <lb/>(F-G) Representative traces of THIP current recorded from cultured cerebellar granule cells either transfected with GFP as a control (F) or with TTR shRNA <lb/>(G). (H-J) Summarized bar graphs showing the THIP current amplitude (H; Control: 107 ± 25 pA, n = 18; TTR shRNA: 55 ± 12 pA, n = 22; P &lt; 0.05, <lb/>Students&apos; t-test.), THIP current density (I; Control: 7.2 ± 1.7 pA/pF, n = 18; TTR shRNA: 2.9 ± 0.6 pA/pF, n = 22; P &lt; 0.05), and membrane capacitance (J; <lb/>Control: 17.4 ± 4.1 pF, n = 18; TTR shRNA: 19.8 ± 4.2 pF, n = 22; P &gt; 0.2) changes after transfection of TTR shRNAs in cultured cerebellar granule cells. � <lb/>P &lt; 0.05. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>known that δ-subunit-containing GABAA receptors are expressed in cerebellar granule cells <lb/>[29], so we immunostained the δ receptors in the cerebellum to examine TTR effect. We found <lb/>that the δ signal was significantly reduced in the granule layer of TTR-/-mice (Fig 6A and 6B; <lb/>p &lt; 0.001). We further performed Western blot analysis for the total and surface δ receptors <lb/>(biotinylated) in the cerebellar tissue. While the total δ receptor signal did not change, the sur-<lb/>face δ receptor signal significantly reduced in the cerebellar granule layer of TTR-/-mice (Fig <lb/>6C-6E; p &lt; 0.01). In contrast, no differences were found in both total and surface γ2 receptors <lb/>between WT and TTR-/-mice (Fig 6C). Furthermore, we cultured cerebellar granule neurons <lb/>from WT and TTR-/-mice and confirmed the surface staining of δ receptors significantly <lb/>Fig 4. Overexpression of TTR in cultured cortical neurons increased the surface δ expression and tonic current. <lb/>(A) Overexpression of human TTR increased the surface δ signal in cortical neurons. Arrows point to the cells <lb/>transfected with mCherry (control) or TTR. Scale bar, 10 μm. (B) Quantification of the surface δ signal intensity in <lb/>control and TTR-overexpressing cells. � P &lt; 0.04. (C-D) Representative traces of THIP currents recorded from cortical <lb/>neurons transfected with mCherry (C, control) or human TTR (D). (E-G) Summary bar graphs for THIP current <lb/>amplitude (E; Control: 22 ± 3 pA, n = 17; TTR: 33 ± 3 pA, n = 17; � P &lt; 0.05, Student&apos;s t-test), THIP current density (F; <lb/>Control: 0.52 ± 0.08 pA/pF, n = 17; TTR: 0.79 ± 0.09 pA/pF, n = 17; � P &lt; 0.05), and cell membrane capacitance (G; <lb/>Control: 47 ± 5 pF, n = 17; TTR: 47 ± 4 pF, n = 17; P &gt; 0.9). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 5. Effects of wide type human TTR peptides or engineered monomeric human TTR (M-hTTR) on δ-GABA A -<lb/>Rs in cerebellar granule cells. (A) Immunostaining of surface δ subunit (green) in cerebellar granule neurons after <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>treatment with 14 ug/ml hTTR or M-hTTR for 1 day. Scale bar, 5 μm and 2.5 μm. (B-C) Quantification of the surface δ <lb/>signal on soma (B) or dendrites (C). ��� P &lt; 0.001, �� P &lt; 0.01. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094.g005 <lb/>Fig 6. In vivo analysis of the δ-GABA A -Rs in the cerebellar granule layer in WT and TTR-/-mice. (A) <lb/>Immunostaining of the surface δ receptors in cerebellar slices from WT and TTR-/-mice (7-8 months old). Top row, <lb/>low power image of the δ signal in cerebellar granule layer. Scale bar, 50 μm. Bottom row, high power image of the δ <lb/>signal. Scale bar, 20 μm. (B) Quantification of the relative surface δ signal density in WT and TTR-/-mice (low power <lb/>image). (C) Western blot analysis of the total and surface δ receptors in WT and TTR-/-cerebellar tissue. The total δ <lb/>protein level showed no difference, while the biotinylated surface δ protein level decreased significantly in TTR-/-<lb/>mice. Both total and the surface γ2 GABA A -Rs have no difference between WT and TTR-/-mice. (D-E) Quantification <lb/>of the relative total and surface δ intensity from the Western blot analysis. (F-G) Surface δ staining and quantification <lb/>in primary cerebellar neuronal cultures from WT or TTR-/-mice. Bar, 5μm. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>reduced in TTR-/-neurons (Fig 6F and 6G; p &lt; 0.001). Thus, our in vivo analysis further dem-<lb/>onstrated that TTR plays an important role in regulating the δ-GABA A -Rs. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The current study identified TTR as a novel interacting partner for the extrasynaptic δ sub-<lb/>unit-containing GABA A -Rs. This was achieved by yeast two-hybrid screening of a mouse cere-<lb/>bellum cDNA library where the δ transcript is enriched. We demonstrated that TTR and the <lb/>δ-GABA A -Rs can co-immunoprecipitate when coexpressed in HEK cells or directly lysed from <lb/>mouse cerebellar tissue. Overexpression and knockdown experiments in cultured neurons <lb/>suggest that TTR can potently regulate the expression level of the δ-GABA A -Rs. External appli-<lb/>cation of normal TTR, which typically forms tetramers, or mutant monomeric TTR revealed <lb/>that tetrameric TTR can regulate surface expression of δ-GABA A -Rs. In TTR-/-mice, we also <lb/>observed a reduction of the δ-GABA A -R expression level in the cerebellar granule layer. Func-<lb/>tionally, TTR regulates the tonic currents mediated by the δ-GABA A -Rs. Together our studies <lb/>suggest that TTR is a critical regulator of the δ-GABA A -Rs. <lb/>Identification of TTR as an interacting partner for the GABA A -R δ subunit <lb/>Using an unbiased yeast two-hybrid screening assay, we identified TTR as an interacting pro-<lb/>tein for the extracellular domain of the δ subunit of GABA A -Rs. We confirmed their interac-<lb/>tion in HEK 293T cells through co-immunoprecipitation and co-localization experiments. Co-<lb/>immunoprecipitation experiments from brain tissue lysates further demonstrated that TTR <lb/>and the δ-GABA A -Rs interact with each other in vivo. In the brain, TTR is mainly secreted by <lb/>choroid plexus into the cerebrospinal fluid [29]. Interestingly, cerebellum is in close proximity <lb/>of one of the choroid plexuses in the brain, and thus may be under the influence of TTR <lb/>secreted by the nearby choroid plexus. A recent study reported that sleep increases the <lb/>exchange of cerebrospinal fluid with interstitial fluid in the brain [37]. Previous studies have <lb/>already found that the δ-GABA A -Rs may play a role in sleep [38, 39]. Thus, our studies raised a <lb/>possibility that TTR might be related to sleep by influencing the δ-GABA A -Rs. <lb/>Regulation of δ-GABA A -Rs by TTR <lb/>Our intracellular manipulation of TTR expression in cultured neurons suggests that TTR is a <lb/>potent regulator of δ-GABA A -Rs. We demonstrated that overexpression of TTR in cortical <lb/>neurons, which typically have low expression of δ-GABA A -Rs, significantly increases the <lb/>expression of δ-GABA A -Rs. Conversely, knockdown of TTR in cerebellar granule cells signifi-<lb/>cantly downregulates the normally high expression level of δ-GABA A -Rs. The δ-GABA A -Rs <lb/>are the major subtype of extrasynaptic GABA A -Rs and play an important role of tonic inhibi-<lb/>tion to regulate neuronal excitability in the brain [9]. Our recent work demonstrated that <lb/>increasing extrasynaptic δ-GABA A -Rs in cortical neurons will result in a significant decrease <lb/>of synaptic GABA transmission, suggesting a homeostatic competition between tonic and pha-<lb/>sic GABA inhibition [3]. The potent regulation of TTR on the δ-GABA A -Rs suggests that TTR <lb/>may play a role in modulating the tonic inhibition and thus tilting the balance between tonic <lb/>and phasic inhibition. Indeed, we have demonstrated that overexpression of TTR can signifi-<lb/>cantly increase tonic current, whereas knockdown of TTR can significantly decrease tonic cur-<lb/>rent. Thus, besides its normal function of transporting thyroid hormone and retinol, our <lb/>studies suggest that TTR may have a completely different function in regulating GABA inhibi-<lb/>tion in the brain. <lb/>Previous studies have reported that TTR also binds to amyloid β peptide (Aβ) and thus may <lb/>play a role in Aβ clearance in Alzheimer&apos;s disease brain [21, 22]. On the other hand, TTR itself <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>may form aggregates and lead to systemic amyloidosis [40, 41]. Recent biochemical analysis <lb/>suggested that in vivo it is likely the tetrameric TTR that binds to Aβ monomers and inhibits <lb/>Aβ aggregation [22, 42]. This is consistent with our finding that TTR tetramer, not monomer, <lb/>regulates the expression level of the δ-GABA A -Rs. Interestingly, TTR has been reported to be <lb/>involved in cognition during aging [43] and associated with depression [44]. GABA A -Rs are <lb/>known to play an important role in cognitive functions and are involved in mood disorders [7, <lb/>9, 45]. Whether the function of TTR in cognition and depression is mediated by the regulation <lb/>of the δ-GABA A -Rs reported here will be an interesting topic to explore in future studies. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We would like to thank all Chen Lab members for vigorous discussion throughout the prog-<lb/>ress of this project. This work was supported by grants from National Institutes of Health <lb/>(MH083911 and AG045656) and an Endowment Fund from Pennsylvania State University to <lb/>G.C. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Li Zhou, Gong Chen. <lb/>Data curation: Li Zhou, Xin Tang, Xinyi Li, Yuting Bai. <lb/>Formal analysis: Li Zhou, Xin Tang, Xinyi Li. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Gong Chen. <lb/>Investigation: Li Zhou, Xinyi Li, Yuting Bai, Gong Chen. <lb/>Methodology: Li Zhou, Xin Tang, Yuting Bai. <lb/>Project administration: Li Zhou, Gong Chen. <lb/>Resources: Li Zhou, Xinyi Li, Joel N. Buxbaum, Gong Chen. <lb/>Software: Li Zhou, Gong Chen. <lb/>Supervision: Gong Chen. <lb/>Validation: Li Zhou, Gong Chen. <lb/>Visualization: Li Zhou, Joel N. Buxbaum. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Li Zhou, Gong Chen. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Gong Chen. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Jacob TC, Moss SJ, Jurd R. GABA(A) receptor trafficking and its role in the dynamic modulation of neu-<lb/>ronal inhibition. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2008; 9(5):331-43. Epub 2008/04/03. doi: nrn2370 [pii] https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/nrn2370 PMID: 18382465; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2709246. <lb/>2. Luscher B, Fuchs T, Kilpatrick CL. GABAA receptor trafficking-mediated plasticity of inhibitory synap-<lb/>ses. Neuron. 2011; 70(3):385-409. Epub 2011/05/11. doi: S0896-6273(11)00300-X [pii] https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.neuron.2011.03.024 PMID: 21555068; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3093971. <lb/>3. Wu X, Huang L, Wu Z, Zhang C, Jiang D, Bai Y, et al. Homeostatic Competition between phasic and <lb/>tonic inhibition. J Biol Chem. 2013; 288:25053-65. Epub 2013/07/11. doi: M113.491464 [pii] https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1074/jbc.M113.491464 PMID: 23839941. <lb/>4. Coghlan S, Horder J, Inkster B, Mendez MA, Murphy DG, Nutt DJ. GABA system dysfunction in autism <lb/>and related disorders: from synapse to symptoms. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2012; 36(9):2044-55. Epub <lb/>2012/07/31. doi: S0149-7634(12)00118-2 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2012.07.005 PMID: <lb/>22841562. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>5. Fritschy JM. Epilepsy, E/I Balance and GABA(A) Receptor Plasticity. Front Mol Neurosci. 2008; 1:5. <lb/>Epub 2008/10/24. https://doi.org/10.3389/neuro.02.005.2008 PMID: 18946538; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC2525999. <lb/>6. Lydiard RB. The role of GABA in anxiety disorders. J Clin Psychiatry. 2003; 64 Suppl 3:21-7. Epub <lb/>2003/03/29. PMID: 12662130. <lb/>7. Luscher B, Shen Q, Sahir N. The GABAergic deficit hypothesis of major depressive disorder. Mol Psy-<lb/>chiatry. 2011; 16(4):383-406. Epub 2010/11/17. doi: mp2010120 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1038/mp.2010. <lb/>120 PMID: 21079608. <lb/>8. Lewis DA, Fish KN, Arion D, Gonzalez-Burgos G. Perisomatic inhibition and cortical circuit dysfunction <lb/>in schizophrenia. Curr Opin Neurobiol. 2011; 21(6):866-72. Epub 2011/06/18. doi: S0959-4388(11) <lb/>00081-X [pii] https://doi.org/10.1016/j.conb.2011.05.013 PMID: 21680173; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC3183273. <lb/>9. Brickley SG, Mody I. Extrasynaptic GABA(A) receptors: their function in the CNS and implications for <lb/>disease. Neuron. 2012; 73(1):23-34. Epub 2012/01/17. doi: S0896-6273(11)01093-2 [pii] https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.neuron.2011.12.012 PMID: 22243744. <lb/>10. Shen H, Sabaliauskas N, Sherpa A, Fenton AA, Stelzer A, Aoki C, et al. A critical role for alpha4betadelta <lb/>GABAA receptors in shaping learning deficits at puberty in mice. Science. 2010; 327(5972):1515-8. <lb/>Epub 2010/03/20. doi: 327/5972/1515 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1184245 PMID: 20299596; <lb/>PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2887350. <lb/>11. Maguire J, Mody I. GABA(A)R plasticity during pregnancy: relevance to postpartum depression. Neu-<lb/>ron. 2008; 59(2):207-13. Epub 2008/08/01. doi: S0896-6273(08)00537-0 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>neuron.2008.06.019 PMID: 18667149. <lb/>12. Nusser Z, Sieghart W, Somogyi P. Segregation of different GABAA receptors to synaptic and extrasy-<lb/>naptic membranes of cerebellar granule cells. J Neurosci. 1998; 18(5):1693-703. PMID: 9464994. <lb/>13. Jia F, Pignataro L, Schofield CM, Yue M, Harrison NL, Goldstein PA. An extrasynaptic GABAA receptor <lb/>mediates tonic inhibition in thalamic VB neurons. J Neurophysiol. 2005; 94(6):4491-501. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1152/jn.00421.2005 PMID: 16162835. <lb/>14. Smith SS, Shen H, Gong QH, Zhou X. Neurosteroid regulation of GABA(A) receptors: Focus on the <lb/>alpha4 and delta subunits. Pharmacol Ther. 2007; 116(1):58-76. Epub 2007/05/22. doi: S0163-7258 <lb/>(07)00070-8 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pharmthera.2007.03.008 PMID: 17512983; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC2657726. <lb/>15. Farrant M, Nusser Z. Variations on an inhibitory theme: phasic and tonic activation of GABA(A) recep-<lb/>tors. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2005; 6(3):215-29. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn1625 PMID: 15738957. <lb/>16. Hamilton JA, Benson MD. Transthyretin: a review from a structural perspective. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2001; <lb/>58(10):1491-521. https://doi.org/10.1007/PL00000791 PMID: 11693529. <lb/>17. Buxbaum JN, Reixach N. Transthyretin: the servant of many masters. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2009; 66 <lb/>(19):3095-101. Epub 2009/08/01. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00018-009-0109-0 PMID: 19644733. <lb/>18. Soprano DR, Herbert J, Soprano KJ, Schon EA, Goodman DS. Demonstration of transthyretin mRNA in <lb/>the brain and other extrahepatic tissues in the rat. J Biol Chem. 1985; 260(21):11793-8. PMID: 4044580. <lb/>19. Li X, Masliah E, Reixach N, Buxbaum JN. Neuronal production of transthyretin in human and murine <lb/>Alzheimer&apos;s disease: is it protective? J Neurosci. 2011; 31(35):12483-90. Epub 2011/09/02. doi: 31/35/ <lb/>12483 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2417-11.2011 PMID: 21880910; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC3172869. <lb/>20. Li X, Buxbaum JN. Transthyretin and the brain re-visited: is neuronal synthesis of transthyretin protec-<lb/>tive in Alzheimer&apos;s disease? Mol Neurodegener. 2011; 6:79. Epub 2011/11/25. doi: 1750-1326-6-79 [pii] <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/1750-1326-6-79 PMID: 22112803; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3267701. <lb/>21. Buxbaum JN, Ye Z, Reixach N, Friske L, Levy C, Das P, et al. Transthyretin protects Alzheimer&apos;s mice <lb/>from the behavioral and biochemical effects of Abeta toxicity. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2008; 105 <lb/>(7):2681-6. Epub 2008/02/15. doi: 0712197105 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0712197105 PMID: <lb/>18272491; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2268196. <lb/>22. Li X, Zhang X, Ladiwala AR, Du D, Yadav JK, Tessier PM, et al. Mechanisms of transthyretin inhibition <lb/>of beta-amyloid aggregation in vitro. J Neurosci. 2013; 33(50):19423-33. Epub 2013/12/18. doi: 33/50/ <lb/>19423 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2561-13.2013 PMID: 24336709; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMC3858619. <lb/>23. Silva CS, Eira J, Ribeiro CA, Oliveira A, Sousa MM, Cardoso I, et al. Transthyretin neuroprotection in <lb/>Alzheimer&apos;s disease is dependent on proteolysis. Neurobiol Aging. 2017; 59:10-4. Epub 2017/08/07. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2017.07.002 PMID: 28780366. <lb/>24. Wu X, Wu Z, Ning G, Guo Y, Ali R, Macdonald RL, et al. gamma-Aminobutyric Acid Type A (GABAA) <lb/>Receptor alpha Subunits Play a Direct Role in Synaptic Versus Extrasynaptic Targeting. J Biol Chem. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>2012; 287(33):27417-30. Epub 2012/06/20. doi: M112.360461 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M112. <lb/>360461 PMID: 22711532. <lb/>25. Jiang M, Chen G. High Ca2+-phosphate transfection efficiency in low-density neuronal cultures. Nature <lb/>Protocols. 2006; 1(2):695-700. https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2006.86 PMID: 17406298 <lb/>26. Deng L, Yao J, Fang C, Dong N, Luscher B, Chen G. Sequential postsynaptic maturation governs the <lb/>temporal order of GABAergic and glutamatergic synaptogenesis in rat embryonic cultures. J Neurosci. <lb/>2007; 27(40):10860-9. Epub 2007/10/05. doi: 27/40/10860 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI. <lb/>2744-07.2007 PMID: 17913919. <lb/>27. Sun C, Zhang L, Chen G. An unexpected role of neuroligin-2 in regulating KCC2 and GABA functional <lb/>switch. Mol Brain. 2013; 6:23. Epub 2013/05/15. https://doi.org/10.1186/1756-6606-6-23 PMID: <lb/>23663753; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3661362. <lb/>28. Kilpatrick CL, Murakami S, Feng M, Wu X, Lal R, Chen G, et al. Dissociation of Golgi-associated <lb/>DHHC-type Zinc Finger Protein (GODZ)-and Sertoli Cell Gene with a Zinc Finger Domain-beta (SERZ-<lb/>beta)-mediated Palmitoylation by Loss of Function Analyses in Knock-out Mice. J Biol Chem. 2016; 291 <lb/>(53):27371-86. Epub 2016/11/23. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M116.732768 PMID: 27875292; PubMed <lb/>Central PMCID: PMCPMC5207163. <lb/>29. Schreiber G, Aldred AR, Jaworowski A, Nilsson C, Achen MG, Segal MB. Thyroxine transport from <lb/>blood to brain via transthyretin synthesis in choroid plexus. Am J Physiol. 1990; 258(2 Pt 2):R338-45. <lb/>Epub 1990/02/01. https://doi.org/10.1152/ajpregu.1990.258.2.R338 PMID: 2309926. <lb/>30. Cope DW, Hughes SW, Crunelli V. GABAA receptor-mediated tonic inhibition in thalamic neurons. J <lb/>Neurosci. 2005; 25(50):11553-63. Epub 2005/12/16. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3362-05. <lb/>2005 PMID: 16354913. <lb/>31. Scimemi A, Andersson A, Heeroma JH, Strandberg J, Rydenhag B, McEvoy AW, et al. Tonic GABA(A) <lb/>receptor-mediated currents in human brain. Eur J Neurosci. 2006; 24(4):1157-60. Epub 2006/08/26. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1460-9568.2006.04989.x PMID: 16930441. <lb/>32. Glykys J, Peng Z, Chandra D, Homanics GE, Houser CR, Mody I. A new naturally occurring GABA(A) <lb/>receptor subunit partnership with high sensitivity to ethanol. Nat Neurosci. 2007; 10(1):40-8. Epub <lb/>2006/12/13. https://doi.org/10.1038/nn1813 PMID: 17159992. <lb/>33. Stell BM, Brickley SG, Tang CY, Farrant M, Mody I. Neuroactive steroids reduce neuronal excitability by <lb/>selectively enhancing tonic inhibition mediated by delta subunit-containing GABAA receptors. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A. 2003; 100(24):14439-44. Epub 2003/11/19. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2435457100 <lb/>PMID: 14623958; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC283610. <lb/>34. Blake CC, Geisow MJ, Oatley SJ, Rerat B, Rerat C. Structure of prealbumin: secondary, tertiary and <lb/>quaternary interactions determined by Fourier refinement at 1.8 A. J Mol Biol. 1978; 121(3):339-56. <lb/>Epub 1978/05/25. PMID: 671542. <lb/>35. Jiang X, Smith CS, Petrassi HM, Hammarstrom P, White JT, Sacchettini JC, et al. An engineered trans-<lb/>thyretin monomer that is nonamyloidogenic, unless it is partially denatured. Biochemistry. 2001; 40 <lb/>(38):11442-52. Epub 2001/09/19. PMID: 11560492. <lb/>36. Episkopou V, Maeda S, Nishiguchi S, Shimada K, Gaitanaris GA, Gottesman ME, et al. Disruption of <lb/>the transthyretin gene results in mice with depressed levels of plasma retinol and thyroid hormone. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1993; 90(6):2375-9. Epub 1993/03/15. PMID: 8384721; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC46089. <lb/>37. Xie L, Kang H, Xu Q, Chen MJ, Liao Y, Thiyagarajan M, et al. Sleep drives metabolite clearance from <lb/>the adult brain. Science. 2013; 342(6156):373-7. Epub 2013/10/19. doi: 342/6156/373 [pii] https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1126/science.1241224 PMID: 24136970; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3880190. <lb/>38. Faulhaber J, Steiger A, Lancel M. The GABAA agonist THIP produces slow wave sleep and reduces <lb/>spindling activity in NREM sleep in humans. Psychopharmacology (Berl). 1997; 130(3):285-91. Epub <lb/>1997/04/01. PMID: 9151364. <lb/>39. Winsky-Sommerer R, Vyazovskiy VV, Homanics GE, Tobler I. The EEG effects of THIP (Gaboxadol) <lb/>on sleep and waking are mediated by the GABA(A)delta-subunit-containing receptors. Eur J Neurosci. <lb/>2007; 25(6):1893-9. Epub 2007/04/06. doi: EJN5455 [pii] https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1460-9568.2007. <lb/>05455.x PMID: 17408425. <lb/>40. Buxbaum J, Tagoe C, Gallo G, Reixach N, French D. The pathogenesis of transthyretin tissue deposi-<lb/>tion: lessons from transgenic mice. Amyloid. 2003; 10 Suppl 1:2-6. Epub 2003/12/03. PMID: 14640034. <lb/>41. Zhao L, Buxbaum JN, Reixach N. Age-related oxidative modifications of transthyretin modulate its amy-<lb/>loidogenicity. Biochemistry. 2013; 52(11):1913-26. Epub 2013/02/19. https://doi.org/10.1021/ <lb/>bi301313b PMID: 23414091; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3604100. <lb/>42. Cascella R, Conti S, Mannini B, Li X, Buxbaum JN, Tiribilli B, et al. Transthyretin suppresses the toxicity <lb/>of oligomers formed by misfolded proteins in vitro. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2013; 1832(12):2302-14. <lb/>Epub 2013/10/01. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbadis.2013.09.011 PMID: 24075940. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>43. Brouillette J, Quirion R. Transthyretin: a key gene involved in the maintenance of memory capacities <lb/>during aging. Neurobiol Aging. 2008; 29(11):1721-32. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2007. <lb/>04.007 PMID: 17512093. <lb/>44. Sousa JC, Grandela C, Fernandez-Ruiz J, de Miguel R, de Sousa L, Magalhaes AI, et al. Transthyretin <lb/>is involved in depression-like behaviour and exploratory activity. J Neurochem. 2004; 88(5):1052-8. <lb/>PMID: 15009661. <lb/>45. Braudeau J, Delatour B, Duchon A, Pereira PL, Dauphinot L, de Chaumont F, et al. Specific targeting of <lb/>the GABA-A receptor alpha5 subtype by a selective inverse agonist restores cognitive deficits in Down <lb/>syndrome mice. J Psychopharmacol. 2011; 25(8):1030-42. Epub 2011/06/23. doi: 0269881111405366 <lb/>[pii] https://doi.org/10.1177/0269881111405366 PMID: 21693554; PubMed Central PMCID: <lb/>PMC3160204. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Transthyretin interacts with δ-GABA A receptors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210094 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 17 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
