<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E <lb/>Open Access <lb/>TrkB expression and dependence divides <lb/>gustatory neurons into three <lb/>subpopulations <lb/>Jennifer Rios-Pilier and Robin F. Krimm * <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: During development, gustatory (taste) neurons likely undergo numerous changes in morphology and <lb/>expression prior to differentiation into maturity, but little is known this process or the factors that regulate it. Neuron <lb/>differentiation is likely regulated by a combination of transcription and growth factors. Embryonically, most geniculate <lb/>neuron development is regulated by the growth factor brain derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF). Postnatally, however, <lb/>BDNF expression becomes restricted to subpopulations of taste receptor cells with specific functions. We hypothesized <lb/>that during development, the receptor for BDNF, tropomyosin kinase B receptor (TrkB), may also become developmentally <lb/>restricted to a subset of taste neurons and could be one factor that is differentially expressed across taste neuron subsets. <lb/>Methods: We used transgenic mouse models to label both geniculate neurons innervating the oral cavity (Phox2b+), <lb/>which are primarily taste, from those projecting to the outer ear (auricular neurons) to label TrkB expressing neurons <lb/>(TrkB GFP ). We also compared neuron number, taste bud number, and taste receptor cell types in wild-type animals and <lb/>conditional TrkB knockouts. <lb/>Results: Between E15.5-E17.5, TrkB receptor expression becomes restricted to half of the Phox2b + neurons. This TrkB <lb/>downregulation was specific to oral cavity projecting neurons, since TrkB expression remained constant throughout <lb/>development in the auricular geniculate neurons (Phox2b-). Conditional TrkB removal from oral sensory neurons (Phox2b+) <lb/>reduced this population to 92% of control levels, indicating that only 8% of these neurons do not depend on TrkB for <lb/>survival during development. The remaining neurons failed to innervate any remaining taste buds, 14% of which remained <lb/>despite the complete loss of innervation. Finally, some types of taste receptor cells (Car4+) were more dependent on <lb/>innervation than others (PLCβ2+). <lb/>Conclusions: Together, these findings indicate that TrkB expression and dependence divides gustatory neurons into three <lb/>subpopulations: 1) neurons that always express TrkB and are TrkB-dependent during development (50%), 2) neurons <lb/>dependent on TrkB during development but that downregulate TrkB expression between E15.5 and E17.5 (41%), and 3) <lb/>neurons that never express or depend on TrkB (9%). These TrkB-independent neurons are likely non-gustatory, as they do <lb/>not innervate taste buds. <lb/>Keywords: BDNF, TrkB, Neurotrophin, Taste, Geniculate ganglion, Taste buds, Innervation, Neuron development, Gustatory <lb/>* Correspondence: rfkrim01@louisville.edu <lb/>Department of Anatomical Sciences and Neurobiology, University of <lb/>Louisville School of Medicine, 511 S. Floyd St., MDR Building Room 111, <lb/>Louisville, KY 40202, USA <lb/>© The Author(s). 2019 Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 <lb/>International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to <lb/>the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated. <lb/>Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13064-019-0127-z <lb/></front>

			<body>Background <lb/>The geniculate ganglion primarily contains two neuron <lb/>subpopulations: 1) neurons that carry mostly taste, but <lb/>some somatosensory information from the anterior <lb/>two-thirds of the tongue and the palate to the brain (oral <lb/>sensory), and 2) those that innervate the outer ear through <lb/>the auricular nerve (auricular neurons). Development of <lb/>most of these neurons is regulated by the neurotrophin <lb/>brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF). BDNF binds <lb/>with high affinity to the tropomyosin kinase B receptor <lb/>(TrkB) [1, 2] and critically regulates the survival of taste <lb/>neurons [3, 4]. Early in development, BDNF expression in <lb/>taste buds acts as a cue for TrkB+ fibers to innervate taste <lb/>organs [5-12]. Both this target innervation process and <lb/>neuron survival occur during a critical developmental <lb/>period [8, 10]. After this critical period, BDNF is downreg-<lb/>ulated in the taste bud, but continues to be expressed in a <lb/>subpopulation of taste receptor cells [13, 14]. This expres-<lb/>sion change suggests that BDNF may play a different role/ <lb/>s in later developmental stages and adulthood. <lb/>Most geniculate ganglion neurons express the BDNF <lb/>receptor TrkB [15-17] early in development and depend <lb/>on TrkB signaling for their survival [15, 18, 19]. How-<lb/>ever, in TrkB knockout animals, many innervated taste <lb/>buds remain at birth despite profound geniculate neuron <lb/>loss by E13.5 [15, 18]. One possible explanation is that <lb/>gustatory neurons lacking the TrkB receptor could mi-<lb/>grate into the geniculate ganglion after E13.5. Consist-<lb/>ently, in chick embryos, geniculate neurons continue to <lb/>delaminate from the epibranchial placodes and migrate <lb/>into the geniculate ganglion throughout embryonic de-<lb/>velopment [20]. How many gustatory neurons remain <lb/>after E13.5 in TrkB knockouts is unclear, particularly be-<lb/>cause earlier studies lacked markers for taste neurons <lb/>and did not quantify geniculate neurons after E13.5 [15, <lb/>18]. Therefore, a subset of TrkB-independent taste neu-<lb/>rons of unknown size likely exists. <lb/>By adulthood, only a subset of taste neurons appears <lb/>to be regulated by BDNF, as adult BDNF removal only <lb/>reduces taste bud innervation by 40% [21, 22]. There-<lb/>fore, in adulthood, many gustatory neurons likely lack <lb/>the TrkB receptor. Yet, it remains unknown if, when, or <lb/>how, during development or adulthood, TrkB expression <lb/>decreases in the neurons that innervate the oral cavity. <lb/>Here, our primary goals were to determine 1) how many <lb/>neurons express TrkB in adulthood, and 2) when and <lb/>how TrkB expression decreases during development. <lb/>Previous studies examining TrkB expression in adult-<lb/>hood lacked markers for distinguishing the roughly 50% <lb/>of geniculate ganglion neurons that are oral sensory <lb/>from the auricular neurons innervating the outer ear. <lb/>The transcription factor Phox2b was recently established <lb/>as a marker that distinguishes geniculate ganglion neu-<lb/>rons innervating the oral cavity (Phox2b+) from <lb/>auricular neurons (Phox2b-) [23, 24]. Using Phox2b as a <lb/>marker for geniculate oral sensory neurons, we deter-<lb/>mined that developmental reduction of TrkB-expression <lb/>and differential dependence on TrkB for survival divide <lb/>oral sensory neurons of the geniculate into three subsets. <lb/>These subpopulations were: 1) neurons that depend on <lb/>TrkB expression during development and continue to <lb/>express TrkB receptors in adulthood (50%), 2) neurons <lb/>that depend on TrkB during development but downreg-<lb/>ulate it between E15.5 and birth (41%), and 3) neurons <lb/>that never express or depend on TrkB and do not in-<lb/>nervate taste buds (9%). Therefore, adult roles of <lb/>TrkB-signaling are likely restricted to a subset of oral <lb/>cavity projecting neurons. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Animals <lb/>All mice were housed in a central facility and maintained <lb/>under controlled conditions of normal humidity and <lb/>temperature, with standard alternating 12-h periods of <lb/>light/dark and free access to water and food. Animals <lb/>were cared for and used in accordance with guidelines of <lb/>the U.S. Public Health Service Policy on Humane Care <lb/>and Use of Laboratory Animals and NIH Guide for the <lb/>Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. <lb/>To visualize TrkB expression in Phox2b-expressing neu-<lb/>rons, Phox2b-Cre (Tg [Phox2b-cre]NP91Gsat/Mmucd, <lb/>Stock No. 034613-UCD [23]) with tdTomato (Ai14, Jax <lb/>Stock No. 007914) mice were bred with TrkB GFP/+ <lb/>(B6.129S6[Cg]-Ntrk2 tm2.1Ddg /J, Jax Stock No. 023046) mice <lb/>[25, 26]. In Phox2b-Cre mice, gene recombination occurs <lb/>in any neuron that has ever expressed Phox2b. In the gen-<lb/>iculate ganglion, this is specific to oral sensory neurons <lb/>and excludes the somatosensory neurons that innervate <lb/>the outer ear via the auricular nerve [23]. These oral sen-<lb/>sory neurons are mostly gustatory, but also include som-<lb/>atosensory fibers [24, 27-29]. However, most of the <lb/>somatosensory neurons innervating the tongue arise from <lb/>the trigeminal ganglion. In TrkB GFP/+ mice, GFP had been <lb/>shown to be expressed in the same geniculate neurons <lb/>that labeled with an anti-TrkB antibody ([27], supplemen-<lb/>tary Fig. 3), making it an appropriate marker for <lb/>TrkB-expressing neurons. <lb/>Embryo heads from mice aged E13.5 (n = 2), E15.5 (n = <lb/>3), E17.5 (n = 4), and P0 (n = 3) were collected for immuno-<lb/>histochemistry. The day that a vaginal plug was observed <lb/>was designated E0.5. Geniculate ganglia from adult mice <lb/>(P60) were also collected for whole mount and serial sec-<lb/>tions. To conditionally remove the TrkB receptor from oral <lb/>cavity neurons, we bred Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ <lb/>mice with a mouse line in which the coding region of the <lb/>TrkB gene was surrounded by loxP sites (Ntrk2 tm1Ddg /J <lb/>mouse, Jax Stock No. 022363) [30]. These conditional TrkB <lb/>knockout mice do not live to adulthood and instead die at <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>different postnatal ages [15, 31], so we collected geniculate <lb/>ganglia and tongues from Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/ <lb/>loxP (n = 8) and Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ (n = 5) <lb/>P20. These geniculate ganglia were processed to determine <lb/>how many oral sensory neurons depended on TrkB signal-<lb/>ing during development. <lb/>Immunohistochemistry <lb/>Embryos aged E13.5 were fixed by immersion in 4% <lb/>paraformaldehyde (PFA). Embryos aged E15.5 and older, <lb/>young (P20) mice, and adult (P60) mice were all sacri-<lb/>ficed with an overdose (1 ml, i.p.) of 2.5% tribromoetha-<lb/>nol (Avertin) and then were trans-cardially perfused <lb/>with 4% PFA. Geniculate ganglia were dissected under a <lb/>microscope and then embryo and newborn heads or <lb/>geniculate ganglia from adult mice were post-fixed in 4% <lb/>PFA overnight at 4 °C. Tissue was then transferred to <lb/>30% sucrose/phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for cryo-<lb/>protection at 4 °C overnight. The following day, tissue <lb/>was frozen on dry ice in OCT (Sakura Tek) embedding <lb/>medium and stored at − 80 °C until processed for <lb/>immunohistochemistry. <lb/>To visualize oral cavity neurons in adult mice, entire gen-<lb/>iculate ganglia were rinsed in 0.1 M PB four times and <lb/>blocked overnight with 3% donkey serum in 0.1 M PBS <lb/>containing 0.5% Triton X-100 (PBST). Ganglia were then <lb/>incubated with the following primary antibodies for 5 d at <lb/>4 °C: goat anti-GFP (1:400; Novus, AB Registry ID: <lb/>AB_10128178, Cat No. NB100-1700, Littleton, CO) and <lb/>rabbit polyclonal anti-dsRed (1:500, Clontech Laboratories, <lb/>Inc., Cat No. 632496, Mountain View, CA) and for some <lb/>ganglia anti-calbindin (1:1000; Neuromics, Edina, MD). <lb/>After incubation in primary antibodies and four rinses with <lb/>0.1 M phosphate buffer (PB), tissues were incubated for 2 d <lb/>in the following secondary antibodies: anti-goat Alexa Fluor <lb/>488 (1:500; Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, West <lb/>Grove, PA) and anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor 555 (1:500; Jackson <lb/>ImmunoResearch Laboratories) and for some ganglia <lb/>anti-chicken Alexa 647 (1:500; Jackson ImmunoResearch <lb/>Laboratories). The tissue was then washed four times in <lb/>0.1 M PB, mounted onto slides, and cover-slipped using <lb/>aqueous mounting medium (Fluoromount-G, SouthernBio-<lb/>tech, Birmingham, AL). <lb/>Alternatively, serial transverse sections (20 μm) were cut <lb/>using a cryostat. Sections were left to air-dry on a slide <lb/>warmer overnight. The next day, sections were post-fixed <lb/>in 4% PFA for 15 min at 4 °C. After four rinses with PBST, <lb/>sections were blocked for 1 h at room temperature with <lb/>5% normal goat serum in PBST. Then, the tissue was in-<lb/>cubated overnight at 4 °C with the following primary anti-<lb/>bodies: chicken anti-GFP (1:1000; Thermo Fisher, Cat No. <lb/>A10262, Carlsbad, CA) and rabbit anti-P2X3 (1:500; Milli-<lb/>pore, AB Registry ID: AB_11212062, Cat No. AB58950, <lb/>Billerica, MA). After incubation in primary antibodies and <lb/>four rinses in PBST, sections were incubated for 1 h at <lb/>room temperature in the following secondary antibodies: <lb/>goat anti-chicken Alexa Fluor 488 (1:500; Jackson Immu-<lb/>noResearch Laboratories) and goat anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor <lb/>647 (1:500; Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories). The <lb/>tissue was then washed four times in 0.1 M PBS, mounted <lb/>onto slides, and cover-slipped using aqueous mounting <lb/>medium (Fluoromount-G). <lb/>To visualize fungiform papillae and innervated taste buds, <lb/>anterior tongue-halves from Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::Trk <lb/>B GFP/loxP and Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ mice were <lb/>collected at P20 using the same procedures as described for <lb/>geniculate ganglia. To examine taste bud innervation and <lb/>Car4-positive taste receptor cells, thick sagittal sections <lb/>(70 μm) of one half tongue from each animal were cut <lb/>using a cryostat and rinsed in 0.1 M PB four times for 15 <lb/>min. After blocking with 3% normal donkey serum in 0.1 <lb/>M PB containing 0.5% Triton X-100 overnight at 4 °C, tis-<lb/>sues were incubated for 5 d in the following primary anti-<lb/>bodies: rat anti-cytokeratin-8 (K8, 1:50, Cat No. Troma-1-s, <lb/>Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, Iowa City, IA), <lb/>rabbit polyclonal anti-dsRed (1:500, Clontech Laboratories, <lb/>Inc., Cat No. 632496), and either goat anti-Car4 (1:500, Cat <lb/>No. AF2414, R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN). Floating <lb/>sections were rinsed in 0.1 M PB four times for 15 min and <lb/>incubated for 2 d in the following secondary antibodies <lb/>(Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories): donkey anti-rat <lb/>Alexa Fluor 488, donkey anti-rabbit Cy3, and donkey <lb/>anti-goat Alexa 647. To examine taste bud innervation and <lb/>PLCβ2-positive taste receptor cells, the other half of the <lb/>tongue for each animal was incubated for 5 d in rabbit <lb/>anti-PLCβ2 (1:500, Cat No. SC-206, Santa Cruz Biotechnol-<lb/>ogy, Dallas, TX). Floating sections were rinsed in 0.1 M PB <lb/>four times for 15 min and incubated for 2 d in donkey <lb/>anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor 647. Then, sections were rinsed in <lb/>0.1 M PB four times for 15 min and blocked for 2 d with <lb/>donkey anti-rabbit (1:100, Cat No. 007-003-007, Jackson <lb/>ImmunoResearch, Laboratories). After four rinses in 0.1 M <lb/>PB for 15 min, sections were incubated for 5 d in the fol-<lb/>lowing primary antibodies: rat anti-K8 (1:50, Cat No. <lb/>Troma-1-s, Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, Iowa <lb/>City, IA), and rabbit polyclonal anti-dsRed (1:500, Clontech <lb/>Laboratories, Inc., Cat No. 632496). Floating sections <lb/>were rinsed in 0.1 M PB four times for 15 min and <lb/>incubated for 2 d in the following secondary <lb/>antibodies (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories): <lb/>donkey anti-rat Alexa 488, donkey anti-goat Alexa <lb/>Fluor 488, and donkey anti-rabbit Cy3. To quantify <lb/>fungiform papillae, all tissues were then rinsed in 0.1 <lb/>M PB and stained with DAPI (2 μL in 50 mL of <lb/>double distilled H20, Life Technologies, Foster City, <lb/>CA) for 45 min. After four rinses in 0.1 M PB, tissues <lb/>were cover-slipped using aqueous mounting medium <lb/>(Fluoromount-G). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Neuron quantification of whole mounts at P20 and in <lb/>adulthood <lb/>Images of whole ganglia were captured using a 40× oil <lb/>immersion lens (FV1200, Olympus) with a step size of <lb/>0.47 μm. Confocal images were obtained by stitching <lb/>multiple fields to create a high-resolution image of the <lb/>entire ganglia in a single Z-stack. Each labeled channel <lb/>was collected individually using single-wavelength exci-<lb/>tation. Images of each optical section through the whole <lb/>ganglia were then analyzed using Neurolucida 360 (MBF <lb/>Bioscience, Williston, VT). Brightness and contrast were <lb/>adjusted for background standardization in all images. <lb/>Each labeled neuron was followed through the optical <lb/>sections so that each neuron was only counted once. <lb/>The absolute number of single-(anti-dsRed) and <lb/>double-labeled (anti-dsRed and anti-GFP) neurons were <lb/>counted by examining each cell through the Z-stack. <lb/>Neuron size was measured by measuring the area of the <lb/>neurons from the optical section where the neuron ap-<lb/>pears to be its largest size; diameters were then calcu-<lb/>lated from areas. <lb/>Neuron quantification of sections during development <lb/>Serial sections of embedded embryo and newborn heads <lb/>and adult geniculate ganglia were captured using a 40× <lb/>oil immersion lens (FV1200, Olympus). Confocal images <lb/>were collected using single-wavelength excitation taken <lb/>with a step size of 1.0 μm. Alternating images from serial <lb/>sections containing ganglia were then analyzed using <lb/>Neurolucida 360 (MBF Bioscience). The number of sin-<lb/>gle-(anti-dsRed) and double-labeled (anti-dsRed and <lb/>anti-GFP) neurons were counted in alternating sections <lb/>by following each cell through the Z-stack so that each <lb/>neuron was only counted once. The percentage of oral <lb/>cavity neurons (tdTomato+) expressing TrkB (GFP+) <lb/>was calculated for each section and averaged for each <lb/>animal per age group and then compared to tdTomato <lb/>single-positive neurons. To quantify TrkB expression in <lb/>non-taste neurons, the percentage of neurons that <lb/>expressed both TrkB (GFP) and P2X3 but not Phox2b <lb/>was examined across ages. <lb/>Quantification of fungiform papillae and taste bud <lb/>number after conditional removal of TrkB from oral <lb/>sensory neurons <lb/>Images of taste buds were captured from thick sections <lb/>of tongue-halves using a 60× oil immersion lens with a <lb/>step size of 1.0 μm. Images were collected using <lb/>single-wavelength excitation and projected along the <lb/>Z-axis. To determine how TrkB removal affected taste <lb/>bud number, we counted taste buds in fungiform papil-<lb/>lae using DAPI staining with a fluorescence microscope <lb/>and a 20× objective lens. We examined all sections for <lb/>one-half of a mouse tongue. Anti-K8 labeling indicated <lb/>the presence of a taste bud in each fungiform papilla. <lb/>We examined all the taste buds labeled with anti-K8 on <lb/>each half tongue and quantified the number of taste <lb/>buds containing Car4+ or PLCβ2+ labeled cells. The <lb/>percentage of taste buds containing Car4+ and PLCβ2+ <lb/>taste receptor cells was calculated by dividing the num-<lb/>ber of taste buds containing labeled cells by the total <lb/>number of taste buds for each one-half of tongue <lb/>(anti-K8, n = 3/genotype). <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>A student&apos;s t-test was used to compare the number of <lb/>double-labeled vs. single-labeled neurons in Phox2b-<lb/>Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/lox mice in adulthood (n = 3). A <lb/>Chi-squared (X 2 ) test was used to analyze the percentage of <lb/>Phox2b neurons that express TrkB in geniculate ganglion <lb/>sections in E15.5 (n = 3), compared to E17.5 (n = 4), P0 (n <lb/>= 3) and adult (n = 3). Because this is 3 statistical tests, type <lb/>one error was controlled using a Bonferroni correction, and <lb/>so a p-value of p &lt; 0.0167 was established before analysis. A <lb/>Chi-squared (χ 2 ) test was also used to analyze TrkB expres-<lb/>sion in Phox2b-negative neurons across different ages <lb/>(E13.5 (n = 2), P0 (n = 3), and adult (n = 3)) and Bonferroni <lb/>correction was used for a p-value of p &lt; 0.025. A students <lb/>t-test was used to compare the number of remaining <lb/>neurons at P20 in conditional TrkB knockouts (Phox2b--<lb/>Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/lox , n = 8) compared with controls <lb/>(Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ , controls, n = 5). A <lb/>student&apos;s t-test was used to compare the number of taste <lb/>buds between controls (Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ , <lb/>n = 5) and conditional knockouts (Phox2b-Cre::tdToma-<lb/>to::TrkB GFP/lox n = 5). Chi-squared (χ 2 ) test was used to <lb/>compare the percentage of taste buds with PLCβ2+ and <lb/>Car4+ cells between (Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/lox , <lb/>conditional knockouts, n = 3) and controls (Phox2b-Cre::td-<lb/>Tomato::TrkB GFP/+ , controls, n=3). Except where <lb/>otherwise specified, a significance for all tests was estab-<lb/>lished as p &lt; 0.05 before analysis; however, actual p-values <lb/>are reported. <lb/>Results <lb/>Only half of the oral sensory neurons in the geniculate <lb/>ganglion express TrkB in adulthood <lb/>Early in development, approximately 90% of geniculate <lb/>neurons express TrkB and depend on TrkB for their sur-<lb/>vival [15, 18]. We hypothesized that following this critical <lb/>period for neuron survival, only a subset of the neurons <lb/>projecting to the anterior two-thirds of the tongue would <lb/>continue to express TrkB in adulthood. This would be <lb/>consistent with the finding that not all adult gustatory <lb/>nerve fibers appear to express TrkB in adulthood [22]. <lb/>Recently, Phox2b expression has been used to distin-<lb/>guish oral sensory neurons (Phox2b+) from those innerv-<lb/>ating the outer ear (auricular neurons; Phox2b-) [23, 24]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Trigeminal neurons innervating the tongue are also <lb/>Phox2b-. Thus, in the geniculate ganglion, Phox2b expres-<lb/>sion is fairly specific to taste neurons, plus a few general <lb/>oral sensory neurons. To visualize TrkB expression in oral <lb/>sensory neurons, we crossed Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato mice <lb/>with TrkB GFP/+ mice to visualize TrkB receptor expression <lb/>(GFP+: green) in oral sensory neurons (dsRed+, red; <lb/>Fig. 1a). We quantified neurons from Z-stacks of adult <lb/>(P60) whole mount geniculate ganglia. In adulthood, not <lb/>all geniculate ganglion neurons expressed the TrkB recep-<lb/>tor (Fig. 1a, b). Specifically, while GFP labeling was distrib-<lb/>uted throughout the ganglion, tdTomato+ neurons were <lb/>located more medially and closer to the greater superficial <lb/>petrosal nerve (Fig. 1a). This suggests that oral <lb/>cavity-projecting neurons are primarily localized to one <lb/>part of the ganglion. <lb/>We then quantified the numbers of single-labeled (TrkB-, <lb/>tdTomato only) and double-labeled (TrkB+, red and green) <lb/>oral cavity-projecting neurons in whole mount P60 genicu-<lb/>late ganglia (Fig. 1b). An average of 354 ± 33 neurons were <lb/>Phox2b+. Of those, 185 ± 21 neurons co-labeled with GFP, <lb/>while 169 ± 0 neurons expressed tdTomato alone (**p &lt; <lb/>0.01; Fig. 1b). Thus, roughly 52% of oral cavity-projecting <lb/>neurons express TrkB in adulthood. Although different in <lb/>terms of TrkB expression these two populations were not <lb/>different in terms of diameter (Phox2b-only (17.8 ± 0.2) vs <lb/>Phox2b/TrkB (17.7 ± 0.2), p = 0.21). <lb/>TrkB expression declines between E15.5 and E17.5 <lb/>Although approximately half of oral cavity-projecting neu-<lb/>rons express TrkB in adulthood (Fig. 1), approximately 90% <lb/>of geniculate neurons express TrkB between E11.5 and <lb/>E13.5 [15-17, 32]. We next sought to determine at what <lb/>period during development TrkB expression decreases. <lb/>Using Phox2b-tdTomato to identify oral cavity-projecting <lb/>neurons, we quantified the number of tdTomato+ neurons <lb/>expressing TrkB-GFP at ages E13.5, E15.5, E17.5, at birth <lb/>(P0), and adulthood (P60) from serial transverse sections <lb/>using immunohistochemistry. Consistent with previous <lb/>findings [15, 17], we observed TrkB GFP labeling throughout <lb/>most of the geniculate ganglion at E13.5. TrkB GFP labeling <lb/>was also observed outside of the geniculate ganglion (Top <lb/>panel, Fig. 2a-e). Across all ages examined, Phox2b-tdTo-<lb/>mato labeling (red) was more prevalent in the medial por-<lb/>tion of the geniculate ganglion (Middle panel, Fig. 2a-e). At <lb/>E13.5 and E15.5, TrkB GFP labeling appeared uniformly dis-<lb/>tributed throughout the geniculate ganglion. After E17.5, <lb/>TrkB labeling appeared to be more strongly expressed <lb/>tdTomato-(non-taste) neurons, and this pattern persisted <lb/>through adulthood (bottom panel, Fig. 2a-e). <lb/>Understanding the temporal dynamics of TrkB ex-<lb/>pression might provide insight into the mechanism <lb/>underlying decreased TrkB expression in adulthood. <lb/>To determine when during development TrkB expres-<lb/>sion begins to decrease in oral sensory neurons, the <lb/>Fig. 1 Half of adult taste neurons express the TrkB receptor. a) Representative image of the entire z-stack of a whole mount adult geniculate <lb/>ganglion from a Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ mouse labeled for both tdTomato (oral cavity-projecting, red) and GFP (TrkB, green). b) <lb/>Quantification of the total number of neurons (n = 3) projecting to the oral cavity (red only) and oral cavity-projecting neurons that express <lb/>TrkB GFP (double-labeled). c-e) Magnified images of a single optical section illustrate the criteria used to identify and count single-labeled <lb/>(arrowhead) and double-labeled (arrow) oral cavity-projecting neurons. Scale bar = 50 μm (a) and 10 μm (c-e). ***p &lt; 0.001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>percentage of Phox2b + neurons co-labeled with GFP <lb/>was quantified E13.5-P60 (Fig. 2f ). At E13.5, most <lb/>(95%) tdTomato+ neurons expressed TrkB. The <lb/>remaining 5% of tdTomato+ neurons likely consisted <lb/>of the small subpopulation of TrkB-independent gen-<lb/>iculate ganglion taste neurons [15]. TrkB expression <lb/>in oral cavity-projecting neurons did not differ be-<lb/>tween ages E13.5 and E15.5 (91%; p = 0.151). How-<lb/>ever, by E17.7, TrkB expression was significantly <lb/>reduced to only 63% (***p &lt; 0.001) and remained re-<lb/>duced at birth (57%; ***p &lt; 0.001). By adulthood, only <lb/>50% of tdTomato+ neurons expressed GFP. These <lb/>data replicate our findings regarding TrkB expression <lb/>in whole mount ganglia (Fig. 1). Thus, TrkB expres-<lb/>sion is significantly reduced to approximately 50% of <lb/>oral cavity-projecting neurons between E15.5 and <lb/>E17.5 and remains reduced into adulthood. <lb/>Decreased TrkB expression is specific to Phox2b + oral <lb/>sensory neurons <lb/>Because TrkB expression is reduced in tdTomato+ neu-<lb/>rons, we next wanted to determine if this decrease was <lb/>specific to oral sensory neurons, or if it also occurred in <lb/>the auricular neurons of the geniculate ganglion. To de-<lb/>termine if TrkB expression was also reduced in these <lb/>auricular neurons during development, we examined <lb/>TrkB expression in tdTomato-neurons. We used P2X3 <lb/>(Fig. 3: blue) as a general marker of geniculate ganglion <lb/>neurons [15, 33, 34]. Contrary to previous reports [33], <lb/>P2X3 did not label all tdTomato-neurons (Fig. 3). P2X3 <lb/>labeling was observed in many sensory neurons within <lb/>the geniculate ganglion, including some Phox2b-cells. <lb/>TrkB GFP labeling was brighter in some regions of the <lb/>geniculate ganglion, especially near Phox2b-neurons. <lb/>This pattern continued into birth and adulthood. We <lb/>Fig. 2 TrkB expression decreases before birth in oral cavity-projecting neurons and remains reduced through adulthood. a) Representative Z-stack <lb/>images of TrkB-GFP (green, top) and Phox2b-tdTomato (red, middle) from geniculate ganglion sections across ages E13.5 (n = 2), E15.5 (n = 3), <lb/>E17.5 (n = 4), P0 (n = 3), and P60 (n = 3). Dashed lines illustrate the boundaries of the geniculate ganglion. b) Mean percentage ± SEM of Phox2b-<lb/>positive neurons that express TrkB receptor during development and adulthood. ***p &lt; 0.001, Scale bar = 50 μm <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>counted the number of P2X3+/tdTomato-(non-taste neu-<lb/>rons) with and without GFP (TrkB). Early in development <lb/>(E13.5), most (92.9%) P2X3+ neurons also express <lb/>TrkB GFP . Importantly, the percentage of P2X3+/tdTo-<lb/>mato-neurons expressing TrkB did not significantly differ <lb/>at birth (86.4%; p &gt; 0.05) or adulthood (94.7%; p &gt; 0.05). <lb/>Thus, in somatosensory (non-taste) geniculate ganglion <lb/>neurons, TrkB receptor expression remains consistent <lb/>across development. We conclude that decreased TrkB <lb/>expression during development is specific to a subset of <lb/>neurons that carry oral sensory (primarily taste) informa-<lb/>tion from the tongue and soft palate to the brain. TrkB re-<lb/>duction is likely part of the differentiation program for <lb/>this specific subset of taste neurons. <lb/>A small population of Phox2b + oral sensory neurons is <lb/>TrkB-independent during development <lb/>When TrkB expression is eliminated during development, <lb/>most geniculate ganglion neurons (94%) are lost by E13.5. <lb/>However, 33% of the taste buds remain and most of these <lb/>are innervated at birth [15], which seemed a surprising <lb/>amount of innervation considering the large total genicu-<lb/>late neuron loss. Because neurons continue to migrate <lb/>into the geniculate ganglion over a long period of <lb/>embryonic development [20], we speculated that at least <lb/>some of the decreased TrkB+ expression observed at <lb/>E17.5 resulted from the migration of TrkB-neurons into <lb/>the geniculate ganglion after E15.5. If this were the case, <lb/>these TrkB+ tdTomato+ neurons would be present in the <lb/>geniculate ganglion at later stages of development when <lb/>TrkB is conditionally removed. Alternatively, TrkB expres-<lb/>sion may be downregulated after the critical developmen-<lb/>tal period for either geniculate neuron targeting or <lb/>survival [8, 10, 21, 35]. In this case, most geniculate neu-<lb/>rons would be lost in conditional TrkB knockouts. To <lb/>evaluate these possibilities, we quantified the number of <lb/>tdTomato+ neurons remaining in the geniculate ganglion <lb/>at P20 in conditional TrkB knockout mice (Phox2b--<lb/>Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP ) compared to controls <lb/>(Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ ). <lb/>As shown in adulthood (Fig. 1), TrkB expression was <lb/>not homogenous across the geniculate ganglion at P20 <lb/>(Fig. 4a, green). tdTomato expression was restricted to a <lb/>subset of neurons, confirming that not all geniculate <lb/>ganglion neurons express Phox2b (Fig. 4a, red). The gen-<lb/>iculate ganglia from Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato:: TrkB GFP/ <lb/>loxP mice were smaller and contained fewer tdTomato+ <lb/>neurons relative to controls. Interestingly, an average of <lb/>Fig. 3 TrkB expression is consistent across ages in non-taste neurons. a) Representative image of geniculate ganglion sections labeled with <lb/>TrkB GFP (green), P2X3 (blue) and Phox2b-tdTomato (red) across ages (E13.5 (n = 2), P0 (n = 3), adult (n = 3)). Dashed lines illustrate the boundaries <lb/>of the geniculate ganglion. b) Mean percentage ± SEM of non-taste neurons (Phox2b-, P2X3+) that express TrkB during development and <lb/>adulthood. Scale bar = 50 μm <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>25 ± 5.3 (n = 8) tdTomato+ neurons remained in the <lb/>geniculate ganglion after TrkB removal compared to <lb/>349.8 ± 44.6 (n = 5) in control mice (Phox2b-Cre::tdToma-<lb/>to::TrkB GFP/+ ; Fig. 4c; ***p &lt; 0.001). Of the 156 remaining <lb/>Phox2b neurons in mice where GFP was quantifiable (n = <lb/>7) only one also appeared to be labeled with GFP (fewer <lb/>than 1%). Therefore, the TrkB-independent population <lb/>does not express either the full-length or the truncated <lb/>TrkB receptor. This remaining 8% of tdTomato+ neurons <lb/>represent a small subset of Phox2b-positive gustatory neu-<lb/>rons. This proportion is equivalent to the percentage of <lb/>tdTomato+/TrkB-neurons in the geniculate ganglion at <lb/>E13.5 (5%). Therefore, new TrkB-independent taste neu-<lb/>rons do not migrate into the geniculate ganglion after <lb/>E13.5. These results support the conclusion that 92% of <lb/>taste neurons express and depend on TrkB during devel-<lb/>opment (E13.5 and earlier), and that TrkB is downregu-<lb/>lated in a subset of these neurons between E15.5 and <lb/>E17.5. <lb/>A recent study defined three subpopulations of gustatory <lb/>neurons based on expression [24]. To test the relationship <lb/>between one of these subpopulations and differential TrkB <lb/>Fig. 4 A small subpopulation of taste neurons (Phox2b-positive) do not depend on TrkB expression during development. a) A Z-stack composite <lb/>image of a whole mount geniculate ganglion at P20 from Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ (control). A higher magnification image of a single <lb/>optical section from this ganglion illustrates that some tdTomato positive neurons also express GFP (arrows), while others do not (asterisks). b) Far <lb/>fewer tdTomato-positive neurons can be observed in the whole mount of a geniculate ganglion at P20 from a Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP <lb/>(conditional knockout) mouse. A higher magnification image of a single optical section illustrates that tdTomato-positive neurons do not express <lb/>GFP (asterisks). c) Mean ± SEM of Phox2b + neurons remaining after TrkB removal from oral cavity-projecting neurons (control, n = 5; conditional <lb/>knockout, n = 8 conditional knockout). d) In control mice (Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ ), a small number of brightly labeled calbindin positive <lb/>neurons that also express tdTomato are present in the ganglion. Triple labeling with GFP (green), tdTomato (red) and calbindin (white) reveals <lb/>that neurons double-labeled for both tdTomato and calbindin are not GFP positive (D, top arrows). Removal of TrkB from Phox2b positive <lb/>neurons (Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP ) results in a complete loss of this neuron population. Remaining tdTomato positive neurons do not <lb/>express either calbindin or GFP (D, bottom, arrows). Scale bars in A and B = 100 μm, the scale bar in D = 50 μm and applies to all high <lb/>magnification images. ***p &lt; 0.001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>expression we labeled TrkB conditional knockout ganglion <lb/>(Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP n = 2) and control <lb/>ganglia (Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ n = 3) with cal-<lb/>bindin, a marker for one of these subpopulations (Fig. 4d). <lb/>Control ganglia (Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ ) had 40 <lb/>neurons double-labeled with calbindin and tdTomato <lb/>(Phox2b), which represent 5% of the total population (Fig. <lb/>4e, top, arrows). None of these neurons expressed <lb/>TrkB-GFP (Fig. 4e, top middle, arrows). There were no <lb/>remaining neurons double-labeled with calbindin and <lb/>tdTomato (Phox2b) in ganglia from conditional knockout <lb/>mice (Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP , Fig. 4e, bottom, <lb/>arrows). Consistent with a previous report [24], some of the <lb/>Phox2b-negative neurons showed weak calbindin expres-<lb/>sion (Fig. 4d, bottom). Therefore, this small population of <lb/>calbindin-positive oral cavity projecting neurons is a subset <lb/>of the neurons that are TrkB-dependent during develop-<lb/>ment, but lose their TrkB expression by adulthood. <lb/>Remaining neurons innervate fungiform papillae but not <lb/>taste buds, resulting in a substantial taste bud loss by P20 <lb/>A small group of Phox2b + geniculate neurons do not de-<lb/>pend on the TrkB receptor during development. These oral <lb/>sensory neurons are primarily gustatory, but also include a <lb/>small population of somatosensory neurons [24, 36]. <lb/>Therefore, whether the remaining neurons in conditional <lb/>TrkB knockouts innervated taste buds was unclear. To <lb/>examine the location of innervation for these remaining <lb/>oral sensory neurons, we examined the entire tongue for <lb/>dsRed positive nerve fibers in control (Phox2b-Cre::tdTo-<lb/>mato::TrkB GFP/+ ; Fig. 5a) and conditional TrkB knockout <lb/>(Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP ; Fig. 5b, c) mice. <lb/>Conditional TrkB removal reduced taste bud size and com-<lb/>pletely eliminated tdTomato innervation within taste buds <lb/>(Fig. 5b). We found only a few tdTomato+ fibers innervat-<lb/>ing the lingual epithelium. These fibers innervated fungi-<lb/>form papillae, but these papillae lacked taste buds (Fig. 5c). <lb/>The few neurons remaining following TrkB removal might <lb/>belong to a somatosensory neuron population, since they <lb/>innervated fungiform epithelium and not taste buds. <lb/>TrkB is required for the survival of 92% of oral sensory <lb/>neurons in the geniculate ganglion; gustatory neurons <lb/>are required to maintain taste buds [37-40]. So, next we <lb/>quantified the number of taste buds that developed in <lb/>the absence of TrkB fibers. Consistent with previous <lb/>findings, TrkB removal significantly reduced the number <lb/>of taste buds (Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ : 63.8 ± <lb/>4.9 vs. Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP : 8.9 ± 1.5, <lb/>**p &lt; 0.01, Fig. 5d). TrkB removal from Phox2b + <lb/>neurons reduced taste buds by 86%, suggesting that <lb/>TrkB-dependent neurons support most taste buds <lb/>during development. <lb/>Fig. 5 In conditional TrkB knockouts, remaining neurons innervate fungiform papillae, but not taste buds, resulting in substantial taste bud loss <lb/>by P20. a) Representative image of a taste bud (keratin-8) with Phox2b + fibers (tdTomato) from Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ mice. b) <lb/>Representative image of a taste bud from Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP lacking Phox2b-fibers. c) Phox2b + nerve fiber innervating a <lb/>fungiform papillae (DAPI). D) Quantification of the number of taste buds remaining after TrkB removal from taste neurons (control, n = 3; <lb/>conditional knockout, n = 5). e, g) Representative image of Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ taste bud (keratin-8) with innervation (red) from <lb/>Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ mice, f, g) Car4+ (green) and PLCβ2+ taste receptor cells. H-J) Representative image of Phox2b-<lb/>Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP taste bud (keratin-8) with no innervation from Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ mice and I) PLCβ2+ taste receptor cells <lb/>K) Quantification of percentage of taste buds with PLCβ2+ cells and Car4+ cells. Data represent the mean of percentage ± SEM. Scale bar = <lb/>10 μm. Scale bar on E applies to F and G. Scale bar on H applies to I and J. **p &lt; 0.01 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Because the remaining taste buds completely lacked in-<lb/>nervation, we also wanted to determine if nerve fibers pref-<lb/>erentially supported specific subtypes of taste receptor cells. <lb/>Taste buds from Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ (Fig. 5a, <lb/>e-g) and Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/loxP (Fig. 5b, h-j) <lb/>mice were labeled for PLCβ2, a marker for Type II taste re-<lb/>ceptor cells that transduce bitter, sweet, umami [41], and <lb/>for Car4, a marker of Type III cells that transduce sour <lb/>[42]. We quantified the percentages of taste buds with <lb/>PLCβ2+ and Car4+ cells for both genotypes. All taste buds <lb/>from Phox2b-Cre::tdTomato::TrkB GFP/+ mice contained <lb/>both Car4+ and PLCβ2+ taste receptor cells (Fig. 5f and g). <lb/>In contrast, taste buds from conditional knockouts typically <lb/>lacked Car4+ cells (Fig. 5i and j), while PLCβ2+ cells were <lb/>present in 100% of taste buds examined from both geno-<lb/>types (Fig. 5k). Conditional TrkB knockout mice had sig-<lb/>nificantly fewer Car4+ cells in the remaining taste buds to <lb/>~21.3 ± 2.5% compared to controls (Phox2b-Cre::tdToma-<lb/>to::TrkB GFP/+ : 85.3 ± 1.8%, **p &lt; 0.01, Fig. 5k). These data <lb/>suggest that the loss of innervation caused by TrkB removal <lb/>markedly reduces the number of taste buds and Type III <lb/>taste receptor cells by P20. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>During development, the neurotrophin BDNF and its re-<lb/>ceptor TrkB play vital roles in the development of gen-<lb/>iculate ganglion neurons [8, 43]. Specifically, BDNF and <lb/>NT4 regulate apoptotic developmental cell death and <lb/>targeting via TrkB [3, 8, 15, 44, 45]. Most geniculate <lb/>neurons express TrkB in early development (E13.5 [15, <lb/>17]). By adulthood, however, the ligand for TrkB, BDNF, <lb/>is expressed in a subset of taste receptor cells, and <lb/>BDNF removal reduces some but not all of the nerve fi-<lb/>bers innervating taste buds [21, 22]. These findings sug-<lb/>gest that by adulthood, TrkB expression may be limited <lb/>to a subset of taste neurons and BDNF-TrkB signaling <lb/>functions to maintain innervation of this subset, but not <lb/>others [21, 22]. Consistent with these findings, we found <lb/>that not all adult Phox2b + (taste) neurons expressed <lb/>TrkB. Furthermore, TrkB expression decreased in these <lb/>neurons between E15.5 and E17.5 such that it was <lb/>expressed in half the taste neurons by adulthood. This <lb/>reduction likely signifies a changing role for TrkB during <lb/>development. <lb/>There were two potential explanations for how this de-<lb/>velopmental reduction in TrkB expression occurred. <lb/>One possibility was that TrkB receptors were downregu-<lb/>lated and became restricted to a subset of geniculate <lb/>neurons. Alternatively, TrkB expression could have de-<lb/>creased because TrkB-neurons migrate into the genicu-<lb/>late ganglion after E13.5 [20], an age when most <lb/>geniculate neurons both express and depend on TrkB <lb/>[15]. We found that TrkB-neurons do not migrate into <lb/>the geniculate ganglion at later embryonic ages, and <lb/>instead the TrkB receptor is downregulated. Specifically, <lb/>TrkB expression did not decrease until after E15.5, <lb/>which is later than might be expected if new TrkB-ex-<lb/>pressing neurons continue to migrate into the geniculate <lb/>ganglion. Furthermore, the small number of TrkB-ex-<lb/>pressing oral cavity neurons present in the E13.5 genicu-<lb/>late ganglion (approximate 5%) accounted for most of <lb/>the remaining neurons in the conditional TrkB knockout <lb/>at P20 (approximately 9%). We conclude that most <lb/>(91%) of the oral cavity neurons initially express and <lb/>depend on the TrkB receptor and then 41% of these <lb/>neurons downregulate TrkB between E15.5 and E17.5. <lb/>The timing of TrkB downregulation in the oral <lb/>cavity-projecting neurons corresponds with the timing of <lb/>decreased BDNF expression in the taste bud [32]. Around <lb/>E14.5, geniculate neurons depend on BDNF expression in <lb/>the lingual epithelium to properly innervate their targets <lb/>[8, 11]. By E15.5, geniculate neurons have already reached <lb/>their targets, so BDNF should no longer be needed in the <lb/>tongue at such high levels. Also, at these later stages, gen-<lb/>iculate neurons no longer depend on BDNF for survival <lb/>[10]. Thus, the timing of decreased TrkB expression cor-<lb/>responds with changing roles of BDNF-TrkB signaling <lb/>during development. Another example in these same neu-<lb/>rons of a developmentally critical gene changing roles dur-<lb/>ing development, is the growth factor receptor, Ret (27). <lb/>Ret regulates expression of the transcription factor, <lb/>Phox2b, embryonically, but later identifies a subset of <lb/>adult Ret expressing neurons that are likely somatosensory <lb/>in function [27]. The role of TrkB in adulthood may be to <lb/>regulate plasticity and branching characteristics for a sub-<lb/>set of oral sensory geniculate neurons (TrkB-expressing <lb/>[22]), but could also regulate taste function in this same <lb/>neuron subset [14]. <lb/>In the dorsal root ganglion, a series of developmentally <lb/>expressed transcription factors and growth factor recep-<lb/>tors orchestrate neuron subtype development [46]. How-<lb/>ever, our current understanding of neuron subtypes and <lb/>how they differentiate within the geniculate ganglion is <lb/>still emergent. The transcription factor Phox2b plays a <lb/>role in the differentiation of neurons that control <lb/>viscero-sensory functions [47-49] and so likely specifies <lb/>oral sensory from auricular neurons in the geniculate gan-<lb/>glion [23, 24]. We found that the TrkB expression is <lb/>downregulated specifically in this subset of geniculate <lb/>neurons (Phox2b + oral sensory neurons), but not in the <lb/>auricular neurons. A finding consistent with a higher level <lb/>of TrkB expression in auricular neurons than oral sensory <lb/>neurons by adulthood [24]. Therefore, Phox2b-regulated <lb/>differentiation into an oral sensory neuron subtype is <lb/>likely required for this decrease in TrkB expression. How-<lb/>ever, this decrease only occurs in half of the Phox2b + <lb/>neurons. Given that Phox2b expression first occurs at E9-<lb/>9.5 [49, 50], which is days before the downregulation of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 10 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>TrkB, Phox2b likely initiates a cascade of events orches-<lb/>trating the differentiation of taste neurons followed by <lb/>differentiation of neuron subtypes. A complex series of <lb/>events such that combinations of these factors work <lb/>together to orchestrate adult expression patterns (24) <lb/>seems likely. For example, the growth factor receptor, Ret, <lb/>is expressed in both TrkB+ and TrkB-neurons, which fur-<lb/>ther divides oral sensory neurons into Ret+TrkB+,Ret <lb/>+TrkB-,Ret-TrkB+, etc. [27]. Using a combination of fac-<lb/>tors to specify neuron subtypes permits a smaller number <lb/>of factors to orchestrate the development of a larger num-<lb/>ber of neuron subtypes (i.e. two factors can specify four <lb/>types, etc). It is now clear that multiple molecular <lb/>subtypes of oral sensory neurons are present in the <lb/>geniculate ganglion [24], although precisely how many is <lb/>still unclear. <lb/>Interestingly, a recently defined subpopulation of taste <lb/>neurons that express calbindin [24], are a subset of the <lb/>neurons that depend on TrkB during development but <lb/>lose TrkB-expression by adulthood. This finding is con-<lb/>sistent with the idea that adult TrkB+ and TrkB-neu-<lb/>rons are too large to be a single pure neuronal subset. <lb/>However, it is also consistent with the idea that pure <lb/>neuronal subsets do not contain both TrkB+ and TrkB-<lb/>neurons in adulthood. Instead, the calbindin+ subpopu-<lb/>lation is one of multiple gustatory neuron subpopula-<lb/>tions whose adult innervation patterns are not likely to <lb/>be regulated by BDNF [21, 22]. <lb/>While much of gustatory neuron differentiation may be <lb/>regulated by a cascade of intrinsically expressed molecular <lb/>factors, the target also likely regulates gustatory neuron dif-<lb/>ferentiation. Once taste neurons innervate their targets <lb/>BDNF from the taste bud could maintain TrkB expression <lb/>in gustatory neurons, such that those innervating BDNF-<lb/>expressing taste receptor cells retain the higher TrkB levels. <lb/>Because BDNF is preferentially expressed in the taste <lb/>receptor cells that express the neurotransmitter serotonin <lb/>[14], TrkB might be preferentially expressed in neurons that <lb/>have the serotonin receptor, Htr3a, which mediates the <lb/>neuronal serotonin response [51]. Consistently, mean TrkB <lb/>expression is higher in the Phox2b + neurons that express <lb/>Htr3a relative to those that do not [24]. <lb/>When TrkB was conditionally removed from Phox2b <lb/>+ neurons during early development, a few remaining <lb/>neurons innervated the oral cavity. This is consistent <lb/>with studies using full TrkB knockouts reporting that <lb/>TrkB removal substantially reduces the number of gen-<lb/>iculate ganglion neurons [15, 18]. However, these previ-<lb/>ous studies could not examine innervation patterns of <lb/>these remaining neurons, as they lacked appropriate <lb/>genetic markers. Here, we found a few tdTomato+ fibers <lb/>innervating the epithelium in a fungiform papilla and no <lb/>labeled innervation in remaining taste buds. There are <lb/>several possible sources of these remaining fibers. These <lb/>few remaining nerve fibers might have originally inner-<lb/>vated locations previously occupied by a taste bud and <lb/>remain when taste buds are lost. Alternatively, these <lb/>remaining neurons may be non-taste, and could belong <lb/>instead to a small somatosensory population in the gen-<lb/>iculate ganglion that innervate the oral cavity [27, 36, <lb/>52]. We found this neuron population to be surprisingly <lb/>small (only 4 neurons in some individuals); therefore, it <lb/>may not be a large enough population to have been <lb/>identified in recent expression studies [24]. <lb/>Consistent with the neuronal loss, conditional TrkB <lb/>knockout mouse tongues had fewer taste buds. Previous <lb/>reports of full TrkB knockouts indicate that 37% of the <lb/>taste buds remained [15], compared to only 14% in the <lb/>current study. Furthermore, in one of these earlier stud-<lb/>ies, 58% of the remaining taste buds were innervated in <lb/>full TrkB knockout mice [15], while we observed no <lb/>remaining taste bud innervation. One explanation for <lb/>these discrepancies is that P2X3 was previously used as <lb/>marker for taste bud innervation [15]. P2X3 is expressed <lb/>in some somatosensory neurons [53]; therefore, <lb/>non-taste P2X3+ fibers may innervate some of the <lb/>remaining taste buds. More likely, these two studies ex-<lb/>amined different postnatal ages; therefore, the remaining <lb/>Phox2b + neurons in the geniculate ganglion might ini-<lb/>tially innervate taste buds at birth but retract by P20, <lb/>resulting in an additional postnatal taste bud loss. <lb/>Taste buds require innervation to retain their normal <lb/>size and integrity [40, 54, 55]. Because some taste buds <lb/>remained despite complete innervation loss by P20, we in-<lb/>vestigated whether developmental denervation influences <lb/>some taste cell types more than others. We found that <lb/>Car4+ taste receptor cells, known to express SNAP25 and <lb/>have synapses [56, 57], were absent from most remaining <lb/>taste buds. Alternatively, all remaining taste buds still con-<lb/>tained PLCβ2+ taste receptor cells. Therefore, Car4+ taste <lb/>receptor cells may depend on innervation more than <lb/>PLCβ2+ receptor cells. Innervation likely supports taste <lb/>buds at least in part by releasing sonic hedgehog [58, 59]. <lb/>However, in the absence of innervation, the few remaining <lb/>taste buds could be supported by epithelial-derived sonic <lb/>hedgehog [28, 58, 60-62]. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Taken together, these data show that TrkB expression <lb/>and dependence divides taste neurons into subpopula-<lb/>tions. We suggest that BDNF expression initially guides <lb/>TrkB+ fibers to innervate taste buds during a critical de-<lb/>velopmental period [8]. During this time, all taste neu-<lb/>rons express and depend on TrkB, while the 9% of oral <lb/>cavity-projecting neurons that are TrkB-independent are <lb/>oral somatosensory. After this critical period, TrkB ex-<lb/>pression in Phox2b + neurons is downregulated, dividing <lb/>these neurons into a TrkB+ and TrkB-subpopulations. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 11 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the adult taste system, BDNF likely maintains TrkB <lb/>expression and taste bud innervation of the TrkB+ but <lb/>not the TrkB-taste fibers [22]. These TrkB+ taste neu-<lb/>rons may play a different functional role than TrkB-<lb/>neurons in adulthood. Because taste neuron subclasses <lb/>are likely defined by combinations of differential gene <lb/>expression, TrkB likely joins with other factors [24, 27, <lb/>63, 64] to separate taste neurons into types and influ-<lb/>ence their ability to innervate subclasses of taste recep-<lb/>tor cells. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Abbreviations <lb/>BDNF: brain derived neurotrophic factor; DAPI: 4,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole <lb/>dihydrochloride; K8: cytokeratin-8; PB: phosphate buffer; PBS: phosphate-<lb/>buffered saline.; PBST: PBS containing 0.5% Triton X-100; <lb/>PFA: paraformaldehyde; SEM: standard error of the mean; TrkB: tropomyosin <lb/>kinase B receptor <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This work was supported by NIH grants: DC007176 and DC015400. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Availability of data and materials <lb/>All data generated of analyzed during the current study are included in this <lb/>published article. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>JR-P collected and analyzed all the data, and wrote the first draft of the <lb/>manuscript, RFK directed the project and revised the manuscript for <lb/>publication. All authors read and approved the final manuscript. <lb/>Ethics approval and consent to participate <lb/>This manuscript does not include data from human subjects. Animal studies <lb/>were approved by the Institutional (University of Louisville) Animal Care and <lb/>Use Committee. Approval number 16479, dated 8/3/2016-8/3/2019. <lb/>Consent for publication <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s Note <lb/>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in <lb/>published maps and institutional affiliations. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 17 October 2018 Accepted: 7 January 2019 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Barbacid M. Structural and functional properties of the TRK family of <lb/>neurotrophin receptors. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 1995;766:442-58. <lb/>2. Huang EJ, Reichardt LF. Trk receptors: roles in neuronal signal transduction. <lb/>Annu Rev Biochem. 2003;72:609-42. <lb/>3. Patel AV, Krimm RF. BDNF is required for the survival of differentiated <lb/>geniculate ganglion neurons. Dev Biol. 2010;340:419-29. <lb/>4. Patel AV, Huang T, Krimm RF. Lingual and palatal gustatory afferents each <lb/>depend on both BDNF and NT-4, but the dependence is greater for lingual <lb/>than palatal afferents. J Comp Neurol. 2010;518:3290-301. <lb/>5. Nosrat CA, Ebendal T, Olson L. Differential expression of brain-derived <lb/>neurotrophic factor and neurotrophin 3 mRNA in lingual papillae and taste <lb/>buds indicates roles in gustatory and somatosensory innervation. J Comp <lb/>Neurol. 1996;376:587-602. <lb/>6. Nosrat CA, Olson L. Brain-derived neurotrophic factor mRNA is expressed in <lb/>the developing taste bud-bearing tongue papillae of rat. J Comp Neurol. <lb/>1995;360:698-704. <lb/>7. Rochlin MW, O&apos;Connor R, Giger RJ, Verhaagen J, Farbman AI. Comparison of <lb/>neurotrophin and repellent sensitivities of early embryonic geniculate and <lb/>trigeminal axons. J Comp Neurol. 2000;422:579-93. <lb/>8. Ma L, Lopez GF, Krimm RF. Epithelial-derived brain-derived neurotrophic <lb/>factor is required for gustatory neuron targeting during a critical <lb/>developmental period. J Neurosci. 2009;29:3354-64. <lb/>9. Krimm RF, Miller KK, Kitzman PH, Davis BM, Albers KM. Epithelial <lb/>overexpression of BDNF or NT4 disrupts targeting of taste neurons that <lb/>innervate the anterior tongue. Dev Biol. 2001;232:508-21. <lb/>10. Hoshino N, Vatterott P, Egwiekhor A, Rochlin MW. Brain-derived <lb/>neurotrophic factor attracts geniculate ganglion neurites during embryonic <lb/>targeting. Dev Neurosci. 2010;32:184-96. <lb/>11. Lopez GF, Krimm RF. Epithelial overexpression of BDNF and NT4 produces <lb/>distinct gustatory axon morphologies that disrupt initial targeting. Dev Biol. <lb/>2006;292:457-68. <lb/>12. Ringstedt T, Ibanez CF, Nosrat CA. Role of brain-derived neurotrophic factor <lb/>in target invasion in the gustatory system. J Neurosci. 1999;19:3507-18. <lb/>13. Huang T, Ma L, Krimm RF. Postnatal reduction of BDNF regulates the <lb/>developmental remodeling of taste bud innervation. Dev Biol. 2015;405: <lb/>225-36. <lb/>14. Yee CL, Jones KR, Finger TE. Brain-derived neurotrophic factor is present in <lb/>adult mouse taste cells with synapses. J Comp Neurol. 2003;459:15-24. <lb/>15. Fei D, Krimm RF. Taste neurons consist of both a large TrkB-receptor-<lb/>dependent and a small TrkB-receptor-independent subpopulation. PLoS <lb/>One. 2013;8:e83460. <lb/>16. Farbman AI, Brann JH, Rozenblat A, Rochlin MW, Weiler E, Bhattacharyya M. <lb/>Developmental expression of neurotrophin receptor genes in rat geniculate <lb/>ganglion neurons. J Neurocytol. 2004;33:331-43. <lb/>17. Yamout A, Spec A, Cosmano J, Kashyap M, Rochlin MW. Neurotrophic factor <lb/>receptor expression and in vitro nerve growth of geniculate ganglion <lb/>neurons that supply divergent nerves. Dev Neurosci. 2005;27:288-98. <lb/>18. Fritzsch B, Sarai PA, Barbacid M, Silos-Santiago I. Mice with a targeted <lb/>disruption of the neurotrophin receptor trkB lose their gustatory ganglion <lb/>cells early but do develop taste buds. Int J Dev Neurosci. 1997;15:563-76. <lb/>19. Nosrat CA. Neurotrophic factors in the tongue: expression patterns, <lb/>biological activity, relation to innervation and studies of neurotrophin <lb/>knockout mice. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 1998;855:28-49. <lb/>20. Blentic A, Chambers D, Skinner A, Begbie J, Graham A. The formation of the <lb/>cranial ganglia by placodally-derived sensory neuronal precursors. Mol Cell <lb/>Neurosci. 2011;46:452-9. <lb/>21. Meng L, Ohman-Gault L, Ma L, Krimm RF. Taste bud-derived BDNF is required to <lb/>maintain Normal amounts of innervation to adult taste buds. eNeuro. 2015;2. <lb/>22. Tang T, Rios-Pilier J, Krimm R. Taste bud-derived BDNF maintains <lb/>innervation of a subset of TrkB-expressing gustatory nerve fibers. Mol Cell <lb/>Neurosci. 2017;82:195-203. <lb/>23. Ohman-Gault L, Huang T, Krimm R. The transcription factor Phox2b <lb/>distinguishes between oral and non-oral sensory neurons in the geniculate <lb/>ganglion. J Comp Neurol. 2017;525:3935-50. <lb/>24. Dvoryanchikov G, Hernandez D, Roebber JK, Hill DL, Roper SD, Chaudhari N. <lb/>Transcriptomes and neurotransmitter profiles of classes of gustatory and <lb/>somatosensory neurons in the geniculate ganglion. Nat Commun. 2017;8:760. <lb/>25. Li L, Rutlin M, Abraira VE, Cassidy C, Kus L, Gong S, Jankowski MP, Luo W, <lb/>Heintz N, Koerber HR, et al. The functional organization of cutaneous low-<lb/>threshold mechanosensory neurons. Cell. 2011;147:1615-27. <lb/>26. Madisen L, Zwingman TA, Sunkin SM, Oh SW, Zariwala HA, Gu H, Ng LL, <lb/>Palmiter RD, Hawrylycz MJ, Jones AR, et al. A robust and high-throughput <lb/>Cre reporting and characterization system for the whole mouse brain. Nat <lb/>Neurosci. 2010;13:133-40. <lb/>27. Donnelly CR, Shah AA, Mistretta CM, Bradley RM, Pierchala BA. Biphasic functions <lb/>for the GDNF-ret signaling pathway in chemosensory neuron development and <lb/>diversification. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2018;115:E516-e525. <lb/>28. Kumari A, Ermilov AN, Allen BL, Bradley RM, Dlugosz AA, Mistretta CM. <lb/>Hedgehog pathway blockade with the cancer drug LDE225 disrupts taste <lb/>organs and taste sensation. J Neurophysiol. 2015;113:1034-40. <lb/>29. Kumari A, Ermilov AN, Grachtchouk M, Dlugosz AA, Allen BL, Bradley RM, <lb/>Mistretta CM. Recovery of taste organs and sensory function after severe <lb/>loss from hedgehog/smoothened inhibition with cancer drug sonidegib. <lb/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2017;114:E10369-e10378. <lb/>30. Chen X, Ye H, Kuruvilla R, Ramanan N, Scangos KW, Zhang C, Johnson NM, <lb/>England PM, Shokat KM, Ginty DD. A chemical-genetic approach to <lb/>studying neurotrophin signaling. Neuron. 2005;46:13-21. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rios-Pilier and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 12 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>31. Ozek C, Zimmer DJ, De Jonghe BC, Kalb RG, Bence KK. Ablation of intact <lb/>hypothalamic and/or hindbrain TrkB signaling leads to perturbations in <lb/>energy balance. Mol Metab. 2015;4:867-80. <lb/>32. Huang T, Krimm RF. Developmental expression of Bdnf, Ntf4/5, and TrkB in <lb/>the mouse peripheral taste system. Dev Dyn. 2010;239:2637-46. <lb/>33. Ishida Y, Ugawa S, Ueda T, Yamada T, Shibata Y, Hondoh A, Inoue K, Yu Y, <lb/>Shimada S. P2X(2)-and P2X(3)-positive fibers in fungiform papillae originate <lb/>from the chorda tympani but not the trigeminal nerve in rats and mice. J <lb/>Comp Neurol. 2009;514:131-44. <lb/>34. Vandenbeuch A, Larson ED, Anderson CB, Smith SA, Ford AP, Finger TE, <lb/>Kinnamon SC. Postsynaptic P2X3-containing receptors in gustatory nerve fibres <lb/>mediate responses to all taste qualities in mice. J Physiol. 2015;593:1113-25. <lb/>35. Runge EM, Hoshino N, Biehl MJ, Ton S, Rochlin MW. Neurotrophin-4 is more <lb/>potent than brain-derived neurotrophic factor in promoting, attracting and <lb/>suppressing geniculate ganglion neurite outgrowth. Dev Neurosci. 2012;34: <lb/>389-401. <lb/>36. Yokota Y, Bradley RM. Receptive field size, chemical and thermal responses, <lb/>and fiber conduction velocity of rat chorda tympani geniculate ganglion <lb/>neurons. J Neurophysiol. 2016;115:3062-72. <lb/>37. Fei D, Huang T, Krimm RF. The neurotrophin receptor p75 regulates <lb/>gustatory axon branching and promotes innervation of the tongue during <lb/>development. Neural Dev. 2014;9:15. <lb/>38. Ito A, Nosrat CA. Gustatory papillae and taste bud development and <lb/>maintenance in the absence of TrkB ligands BDNF and NT-4. Cell Tissue Res. <lb/>2009;337:349-59. <lb/>39. Nosrat IV, Agerman K, Marinescu A, Ernfors P, Nosrat CA. Lingual deficits in <lb/>neurotrophin double knockout mice. J Neurocytol. 2004;33:607-15. <lb/>40. Oakley B, Lawton A, Riddle DR, Wu LH. Morphometric and <lb/>immunocytochemical assessment of fungiform taste buds after interruption <lb/>of the chorda-lingual nerve. Microsc Res Tech. 1993;26:187-95. <lb/>41. DeFazio RA, Dvoryanchikov G, Maruyama Y, Kim JW, Pereira E, Roper SD, <lb/>Chaudhari N. Separate populations of receptor cells and presynaptic cells in <lb/>mouse taste buds. J Neurosci. 2006;26:3971-80. <lb/>42. Chandrashekar J, Hoon MA, Ryba NJ, Zuker CS. The receptors and cells for <lb/>mammalian taste. Nature. 2006;444:288-94. <lb/>43. Jones KR, Farinas I, Backus C, Reichardt LF. Targeted disruption of the BDNF <lb/>gene perturbs brain and sensory neuron development but not motor <lb/>neuron development. Cell. 1994;76:989-99. <lb/>44. Huang T, Krimm RF. BDNF and NT4 play interchangeable roles in gustatory <lb/>development. Dev Biol. 2014;386:308-20. <lb/>45. Patel AV, Krimm RF. Neurotrophin-4 regulates the survival of gustatory <lb/>neurons earlier in development using a different mechanism than brain-<lb/>derived neurotrophic factor. Dev Biol. 2012;365:50-60. <lb/>46. Lallemend F, Ernfors P. Molecular interactions underlying the specification <lb/>of sensory neurons. Trends Neurosci. 2012;35:373-81. <lb/>47. Dauger S, Pattyn A, Lofaso F, Gaultier C, Goridis C, Gallego J, Brunet JF. <lb/>Phox2b controls the development of peripheral chemoreceptors and <lb/>afferent visceral pathways. Development. 2003;130:6635-42. <lb/>48. D&apos;Autreaux F, Coppola E, Hirsch MR, Birchmeier C, Brunet JF. Homeoprotein <lb/>Phox2b commands a somatic-to-visceral switch in cranial sensory pathways. <lb/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2011;108:20018-23. <lb/>49. Pattyn A, Morin X, Cremer H, Goridis C, Brunet JF. Expression and <lb/>interactions of the two closely related homeobox genes Phox2a and <lb/>Phox2b during neurogenesis. Development. 1997;124:4065-75. <lb/>50. Pla P, Hirsch MR, Le Crom S, Reiprich S, Harley VR, Goridis C. Identification of <lb/>Phox2b-regulated genes by expression profiling of cranial motoneuron <lb/>precursors. Neural Dev. 2008;3:14. <lb/>51. Larson ED, Vandenbeuch A, Voigt A, Meyerhof W, Kinnamon SC, Finger TE. <lb/>The role of 5-HT3 receptors in signaling from taste buds to nerves. J <lb/>Neurosci. 2015;35:15984-95. <lb/>52. Yokota Y, Bradley RM. Geniculate ganglion neurons are multimodal and <lb/>variable in receptive field characteristics. Neuroscience. 2017;367:147-58. <lb/>53. Staikopoulos V, Sessle BJ, Furness JB, Jennings EA. Localization of P2X2 and P2X3 <lb/>receptors in rat trigeminal ganglion neurons. Neuroscience. 2007;144:208-16. <lb/>54. Guth L. The effects of glossopharyngeal nerve transection on the <lb/>circumvallate papilla of the rat. Anat Rec. 1957;128:715-31. <lb/>55. Sun H, Oakley B. Development of anterior gustatory epithelia in the palate and <lb/>tongue requires epidermal growth factor receptor. Dev Biol. 2002;242:31-43. <lb/>56. Lossow K, Hermans-Borgmeyer I, Behrens M, Meyerhof W. Genetic labeling <lb/>of Car4-expressing cells reveals subpopulations of type III taste cells. Chem <lb/>Senses. 2017;42:747-58. <lb/>57. Yang R, Crowley HH, Rock ME, Kinnamon JC. Taste cells with synapses in rat <lb/>circumvallate papillae display SNAP-25-like immunoreactivity. J Comp <lb/>Neurol. 2000;424:205-15. <lb/>58. Castillo-Azofeifa D, Losacco JT, Salcedo E, Golden EJ, Finger TE, Barlow LA. <lb/>Sonic hedgehog from both nerves and epithelium is a key trophic factor for <lb/>taste bud maintenance. Development. 2017;144:3054-65. <lb/>59. Lu WJ, Mann RK, Nguyen A, Bi T, Silverstein M, Tang JY, Chen X, Beachy PA. <lb/>Neuronal delivery of hedgehog directs spatial patterning of taste organ <lb/>regeneration. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2018;115:E200-9. <lb/>60. Liu HX, Maccallum DK, Edwards C, Gaffield W, Mistretta CM. Sonic <lb/>hedgehog exerts distinct, stage-specific effects on tongue and taste papilla <lb/>development. Dev Biol. 2004;276:280-300. <lb/>61. Miura H, Kusakabe Y, Sugiyama C, Kawamatsu M, Ninomiya Y, Motoyama J, <lb/>Hino A. Shh and Ptc are associated with taste bud maintenance in the adult <lb/>mouse. Mech Dev. 2001;106:143-5. <lb/>62. Miura H, Scott JK, Harada S, Barlow LA. Sonic hedgehog-expressing basal <lb/>cells are general post-mitotic precursors of functional taste receptor cells. <lb/>Dev Dyn. 2014;243:1286-97. <lb/>63. Abraira VE, Ginty DD. The sensory neurons of touch. Neuron. 2013;79:618-<lb/>39. <lb/>64. Lee H, Macpherson LJ, Parada CA, Zuker CS, Ryba NJP. Rewiring the taste <lb/>system. Nature. 2017;548:330-3. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">and Krimm Neural Development <lb/>(2019) 14:3 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 13 13 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
