<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>the role of plant functional groups <lb/>mediating climate impacts on <lb/>carbon and biodiversity of alpine <lb/>grasslands <lb/>Vigdis Vandvik 1,2 ✉ , Inge H. J. Althuizen 1,2,3 , Francesca Jaroszynska 1,4 , Linn C. Krüger 1 , <lb/>Hanna Lee 2,3,5 , Deborah E. Goldberg 6 , Kari Klanderud 7 , Siri L. Olsen 7,8 , Richard J. Telford 1,2 , <lb/>Silje A. H. Östman 1 , Sara Busca 1 , Ingrid J. Dahle 1 , Dagmar D. Egelkraut 1,2 , Sonya R. Geange 1,2 , <lb/>Ragnhild Gya 1,2 , Josh S. Lynn 1,2 , Eric Meineri 1,9 , Sherry Young 10 &amp; Aud H. Halbritter 1,2 <lb/>Plant removal experiments allow assessment of the role of biotic interactions among species or <lb/>functional groups in community assembly and ecosystem functioning. When replicated along climate <lb/>gradients, they can assess changes in interactions among species or functional groups with climate. <lb/>Across twelve sites in the Vestland Climate Grid (VCG) spanning 4 °C in growing season temperature <lb/>and 2000 mm in mean annual precipitation across boreal and alpine regions of Western Norway, we <lb/>conducted a fully factorial plant functional group removal experiment (graminoids, forbs, bryophytes). <lb/>Over six years, we recorded biomass removed, soil microclimate, plant community composition <lb/>and structure, seedling recruitment, ecosystem carbon fluxes, and reflectance in 384 experimental <lb/>and control plots. The dataset consists of 5,412 biomass records, 360 species-level biomass records, <lb/>1,084,970 soil temperature records, 4,771 soil moisture records, 17,181 plant records covering 206 <lb/>taxa, 16,656 seedling records, 3,696 ecosystem carbon flux measurements, and 1,244 reflectance <lb/>measurements. The data can be combined with longer-term climate data and plant population, <lb/>community, ecosystem, and functional trait data collected within the VCG. <lb/></front>
			
			<body>Background &amp; Summary <lb/>Climate change poses a threat to biodiversity and ecosystem functioning of alpine ecosystems by altering plant, <lb/>animal and microbial distributions 1,2 , community composition 3 , and food webs 4 ; as well as affecting biotic inter-<lb/>actions between organisms and functional groups 5-8 . These impacts operate through both direct and indirect <lb/>pathways. Individual organism&apos;s physiological rates such as photosynthesis and respiration are directly regu-<lb/>lated by climatic factors such as temperature and precipitation 9,10 . In turn, these impacts will aggregate to affect <lb/>ecosystem-level processes such as productivity, decomposition, and carbon and nutrient fluxes in response <lb/>to climate change 11,12 . Because biodiversity and ecosystem functioning are linked through biotic interactions <lb/>within and among trophic levels and functional groups 5,13 , indirect impacts of climate, operating on and via <lb/>these interactions, are also of critical importance. Disentangling the direct and indirect consequences of climate <lb/>on ecosystems is key to understanding and predicting the full spectrum of biodiversity and functional responses <lb/>to a changing climate. <lb/>Plants are key players in ecosystems: they make up the majority of terrestrial biomass globally, are the main <lb/>source of photosynthetically fixed carbon, and serve as habitat, food sources, and hosts for other organismal <lb/></body>
			
			<front>1 Department of Biological Sciences, University of Bergen, Bergen, norway. 2 Bjerknes centre for climate Research, <lb/>University of Bergen, Bergen, norway. 3 norwegian Research centre, Bjerknes centre for climate Research, Bergen, <lb/>norway. 4 Office Français de la Biodiversité, Pérols, France. 5 Department of Biology, norwegian University of Science <lb/>and technology, trondheim, norway. 6 Department of ecology and evolutionary Biology, University of Michigan, Ann <lb/>Arbor, Mi, USA. 7 faculty of environmental Sciences and natural Resource Management, norwegian University of Life <lb/>Sciences, Ås, norway. 8 norwegian institute for nature Research, Oslo, norway. 9 Aix Marseille Univ, Avignon Univ, <lb/>cnRS, iRD, iMBe, Marseille, france. 10 Simon fraser University, Vancouver, canada. ✉ e-mail: vigdis.vandvik@uib.no <lb/>DATA DESCRI TOR <lb/>O EN <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>groups, while also competing with them for resources 13-15 . A changing climate will drive predictable shifts in <lb/>plant species composition; warmer and wetter climates generally favour taller plants, more resource-acquisitive <lb/>traits, and species that are better competitors for light and nutrients 16 . Previous experiments and observational <lb/>studies from arctic and alpine systems show that plant functional groups encapsulate much of this variation, and <lb/>also respond differently to climate and climate change, with graminoids and shrubs typically increasing 17-19 , and <lb/>bryophytes and lichens decreasing in response to warming 17,18,20,21 . These shifts have knock-on effects on ecosys-<lb/>tem productivity, moisture availability, mineralization, and decomposition processes 22,23 . <lb/>Removal experiments are a &apos;gold standard&apos; approach for disentangling the roles, interactions, and effects of <lb/>co-occurring (groups of) plants (see 13,24 ). Here we report on a fully factorial removal experiment to assess the roles <lb/>of and interactions between the major different plant functional groups in alpine grasslands -graminoids, forbs, and <lb/>bryophytes -in controlling alpine biodiversity, microclimate, and ecosystem functioning. Our semi-natural alpine <lb/>grassland study system is of high biodiversity and conservation value 25 , yet structurally simple and fine-scaled enough <lb/>to allow whole-ecosystem (plants and soil community) experimental manipulation. Our experiment was replicated <lb/>across broad-scale temperature and precipitation gradients in Western Norway in a &apos;climate grid&apos; design that allows <lb/>disentangling effects of temperature and precipitation change. This is useful, as temperature and precipitation are <lb/>often confounded, both along elevational gradients and in warming experiments (changes in moisture availability <lb/>are a side-effect of standard experimental warming approaches, see 26 ). We use this study design to disentangle the <lb/>direct and indirect effects of climate on plant taxonomic and functional diversity, microclimate, and carbon dynamics <lb/>of alpine grasslands by comparing treatments with plant functional groups removed (direct effects of climate) with <lb/>treatments with one or more functional groups present (net of direct and indirect climate effects) across sites. <lb/>Our experiment is replicated across a macroecological context of twelve calcareous semi-natural grassland <lb/>sites in south-western Norway (Fig. 1a). The fjords of western Norway offer large variation in temperature and <lb/>precipitation, and we used this variability to select sites in a &apos;climate grid&apos; where three temperature levels are <lb/>crossed with four precipitation levels (Fig. 1b). The Vestland Climate Grid (VCG), was established in 2008, and <lb/>a host of biotic and abiotic data are available from previous research, as detailed below. Within each VCG site, <lb/>we established the FunCaB plant functional group removal experiment from which we measured carbon and <lb/>biodiversity responses over 7 years (Fig. 1c). Below, we first describe the site selection and provide basic site <lb/>information, then outline the experimental design and setup, before we detail variables related to (i) functional <lb/>group biomass and the removal treatments, (ii) species-level biomass, (iii-iv) soil microclimate, (v) plant com-<lb/>munity composition, (vi) seedling recruitment, (vii) ecosystem carbon fluxes, and (viii) ecosystem reflectance <lb/>(Table 1). Note that these data vary in spatial and temporal coverage, as described below. We provide raw and <lb/>clean datasets with consistent structure and variable naming 27 , and associated code for cleaning and combining <lb/>data 28 . By documenting and communicating data structures and qualities we aim to facilitate data reuse and <lb/>combination for new applications in the future. <lb/>Fig. 1 Study area, site selection, experimental design, and field sampling overview for the FunCaB plant <lb/>functional group experiment. (a) Location of the study area and the 12 study sites in Vestland county, <lb/>Western Norway. (b) The Vestland Climate Grid is established across independent broad-scale biogeographic <lb/>gradients in summer temperature (mean of four warmest months, °C), and annual precipitation (mean annual <lb/>precipitation, mm). Temperature levels are given as boreal, sub-alpine, and alpine; precipitation levels range <lb/>from 1 (dry) to 4 (wet). (c) Experimental design, with the timeline (species composition recordings [dataset v], <lb/>seedling recruitment monitoring [vi], ecosystem carbon flux monitoring [vii], and functional group removals <lb/>[i] indicated, see legend for dataset symbols, for other datasets see text), an overview of the eight factorial <lb/>removal treatments, and plot layout with subplots used for the community and seedling recording. The removal <lb/>treatments are described by the functional groups removed from the respective plots, note that in the figure the <lb/>&apos;Intact&apos; plot refers to the no removal controls whereas the &apos;Gap&apos; are plots with all functional groups removed. For <lb/>detailed description of treatments and their abbreviations as used in the datasets, see text. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Methods <lb/>Data management and workflows. We adopt best-practice approaches for open and reproducible <lb/>research planning, execution, reporting, and management throughout the project (see e.g. 29-32 ). Specifically, we <lb/>use community-approved standards for experimental design and data collection 29 , and clean and manage the data <lb/>using a fully scripted and reproducible data workflow, with data and code deposited at open repositories (Fig. 2). <lb/>Research site selection and basic information, and general study setup. Site selection. Our study <lb/>is conducted across the twelve calcareous grassland experimental sites in the Vestland Climate Grid (VCG), in <lb/>south-western Norway (Fig. 1a). The VCG sites were chosen to fit within a climate grid reflecting a fully factorial <lb/>design encompassing the major bioclimatic variation in Norway. Potential sites were identified using a combi-<lb/>nation of topographic maps, geological maps (NGU) and interpolated maps of summer temperature and annual <lb/>precipitation using the 1960-1990 climate normal (100 m resolution gridded data, met.no; see 33 and references <lb/>therein). The three temperature levels (alpine, sub-alpine, boreal) and four levels of precipitation in the climate <lb/>grid (Fig. 1b) were selected to reflect a difference in mean growing season temperature of ca. 2 °C between three <lb/>temperature levels (alpine = 6.5 °C, sub-alpine = 8.5 °C, boreal = 10.5 °C mean temperature of the four warmest <lb/>months of the year) and a difference in mean annual precipitation of 700 mm between four precipitation levels <lb/>(precipitation levels 1 -4 representing 700 mm, 1400 mm, 2100 mm, and 2800 mm, respectively). Climate data <lb/>for the site selection was based on 100-m resolution downscaled data using the 1960-1990 climate normal from <lb/>met.no. The final sites were selected from approximately 200 potential sites visited and surveyed in the sum-<lb/>mer of 2008, with selection criteria set to ensure that other factors such as grazing regime and history, bedrock, <lb/>vegetation type and structure, slope and exposure were kept as constant as possible among the selected sites 34 . <lb/>Geographical distance between sites is on average 15 km and ranges from 175 km to 650 m. <lb/>Dataset <lb/>Response variable <lb/>Number of observations <lb/>Temporal range <lb/>Citation information for raw <lb/>data, clean data, and code <lb/>i <lb/>Functional group removal <lb/>5,412 <lb/>2015 -2021 <lb/>Raw data 27 , clean data 27 , code 28 <lb/>ii <lb/>Species-level biomass <lb/>360 <lb/>2016 <lb/>Raw data 27 , clean data 27 , code 28 <lb/>iii <lb/>Soil temperature <lb/>1,084,970 <lb/>2015 -2016 <lb/>Raw data 27 , clean data 27 , code 28 <lb/>iv <lb/>Soil moisture <lb/>4,771 <lb/>2015 -2019 <lb/>Raw data 27 , clean data 27 , code 28 <lb/>v <lb/>Plant community composition <lb/>plant records: 17,181; plant <lb/>taxa: 206 <lb/>2015 -2019 <lb/>Raw data 27 , clean data 27 , code 28 <lb/>vi <lb/>Seedling recruitment <lb/>16,656 <lb/>2018 -2019 <lb/>Raw data 27 , clean data 27 , code 28 <lb/>vii <lb/>Ecosystem carbon fluxes <lb/>3,696 <lb/>2015 -2017 <lb/>Raw data 27 , clean data 27 , code 28 <lb/>viii <lb/>Reflectance <lb/>1,244 <lb/>2019, 2021 <lb/>Raw data 27 , clean data 27 , code 28 <lb/> Table 1. Description and location of the datasets in the FunCaB plant functional group experiment. This table <lb/>summarises information on dataset number, response variable(s), number of observations, temporal range of <lb/>the data, and location of the primary data, the final published data, and the code for extracting and cleaning <lb/>data from the primary data. <lb/>Fig. 2 The data collection and management workflow of the FunCaB project. Reproducibility throughout the <lb/>research process is assured as follows: Experimental design and data collection was based on best-practice <lb/>community methods and protocols, adapted for the projects&apos; needs. Measurements were digitalized and the <lb/>raw data stored in the project Open Science Foundation (OSF) repository before the raw data were cleaned and <lb/>managed through code-based data curation, with version control secured via GitHub. The clean data are stored <lb/>at the OSF repository, and a time-stamped version of the code to retrieve and clean data is provided through <lb/>Zenodo. This data paper describes and documents the data collection and workflow, and describes how to <lb/>access and use clean data, raw data, and code. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>
			
			<body>Study system and experimental area selection within sites. At each site, we selected an experimental area of ca. <lb/>75 -200 m 2 , targeting a homogeneous and representative part of the target grassland vegetation at large at that <lb/>site. The experimental areas were placed on southerly-facing slopes, avoiding depressions and concave areas <lb/>in the landscape and other features such as big rocks or formations that may affect light conditions, hydrol-<lb/>ogy and/or snowdrift. The target vegetation type was forb-rich semi-natural upland grassland vegetation 34,35 , <lb/>within the plant sociological association Potentillo-Festucetum ovinae tending towards Potentillo-Poligonium <lb/>vivipara in the alpine sites and Nardo-Agrostion tenuis in some lowland sites 36 . The most common vascular <lb/>plants across sites, based on sum of covers, are the graminoids Agrostis capillaris, Festuca rubra, Avenella flex-<lb/>uosa, Anthoxanthum odoratum, and Nardus stricta and the forbs Leucantemum vulgare, Hypericum macula-<lb/>tum, Silene acaulis, Alchemilla alpina, and Lotus corniculatus. Common bryophytes are Pleurotium schreberi, <lb/>Hylocomium splendens, Polythricum spp, Racomitrium lanuginosum, R. fasciculare, and Dicranum spp. All sites <lb/>were moderately grazed prior to the study by sheep, cattle, goats, reindeer, deer, moose, and/or horses; and the <lb/>experimental areas were fenced for the duration of the study to prevent animal and human disturbance of the <lb/>experimental infrastructure. The fenced area was lightly mowed at the end of each growing season to mimic <lb/>past grazing pressure and minimize fence effects. For further description of the sites, see 34 and for access to and <lb/>further description of site-level data, see 35 . <lb/>Block and experimental plot setup. Within these study areas we established four blocks, with a distance between <lb/>the blocks ranging from one up to (in rare cases) 50 meters. Blocks were selectively placed in homogenous <lb/>grassland vegetation, avoiding rocks, depressions, and other features as described above. Each block accom-<lb/>modates eight 25 × 25 cm plots, with at least 25 cm between adjacent plots. If a plot contained more than 10% <lb/>bare rock, shrubs, or other non-grassland features, they were rejected or moved slightly to avoid these features. <lb/>The plots were permanently marked with four aluminium 10-cm long pipes in the soil in the outer corners <lb/>of all the 25 × 25 cm treatment plots, ensuring the pipes to fit the corners of a standardized vegetation anal-<lb/>ysis frame (aluminium frame demarking a 25 × 25 cm inner area, with poles fixed in the corners that fit into <lb/>the aluminium tubes used for plot demarcation in the field). The upslope left corner tube was marked with a <lb/>colour-coded waterproof tape. Note that in 31 out of 48 cases (12 sites × 4 blocks), the blocks were located within <lb/>larger experimental blocks in the VCG sites, and control plots and various block-level data are then shared with <lb/>other experiments in these larger blocks. Linking keys are described in the FunCaB data dictionaries below (see <lb/>Fig. 3 and data records iii-vii below). For some datasets, additional plots within blocks were needed. These are <lb/>described as needed below. <lb/>Variable name <lb/>Description <lb/>Variable type Variable range or levels <lb/>Units <lb/>How <lb/>measured <lb/>year <lb/>Year of sampling <lb/>numeric <lb/>2015 -2021 <lb/>yyyy <lb/>defined <lb/>date <lb/>Date of sampling <lb/>date <lb/>2015-07-22 -2021-07-30 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd <lb/>defined <lb/>round <lb/>Round of sampling <lb/>numeric <lb/>1 -2 <lb/>count <lb/>defined <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alrust-Vikesland <lb/>defined <lb/>temperature_level <lb/>Temperature level with the climate <lb/>grid <lb/>categorical <lb/>boreal, sub-alpine, alpine <lb/>defined <lb/>precipitation_level <lb/>Precipitation level within the <lb/>climate grid (low to high) <lb/>categorical <lb/>1, 2, 3, 4 <lb/>defined <lb/>blockID <lb/>Unique block ID a combination of <lb/>site and block <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1 -Vik5 <lb/>defined <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a combination <lb/>of site, block and treatment <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1B -Vik5GF <lb/>defined <lb/>treatment <lb/>Plant functional groups removed, <lb/>where F = forbs, G = graminoids, <lb/>B = bryophytes, C = control and <lb/>XC = extra control <lb/>categorical <lb/>FGB, FG, FB, GB, G, F, B, C, XC <lb/>defined <lb/>removed_fg <lb/>Removed functional group, <lb/>where F = forbs, B = bryophytes, <lb/>G = graminoids. For extra controls <lb/>also L = litter, P = pteridophytes, <lb/>LI = lichens, and C = cryptograms <lb/>categorical <lb/>For experimental plots: F, G, <lb/>B,For extra controls: F, G, B, L, <lb/>P, LI, C <lb/>defined <lb/>functional_group <lb/>Removed functional group, <lb/>including forbs, bryophytes, <lb/>graminoids. For extra controls <lb/>also litter, pteridophytes, lichens, <lb/>and cryptograms <lb/>categorical <lb/>bryophytes-pteridophytes <lb/>defined <lb/>biomass <lb/>Dry weight of removed <lb/>functional_group <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -41.31 <lb/>g <lb/>measured <lb/>name <lb/>Name of data collector <lb/>categorical <lb/>AB -William <lb/>recorded <lb/>remark <lb/>Remarks <lb/>categorical <lb/>Table 2. Data dictionary for the FunCaB functional group-level biomass (dataset i). Data dictionary with <lb/>column descriptions for dataset i -the biomass removed from 384 25 × 25 cm experimental plant functional <lb/>group removal plots from 2015 -2021, and total biomass in 48 extra controls in 2016, at twelve sites in the <lb/>Vestland Climate Grid, Vestland County, Norway. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Background abiotic and biotic data from the Vestland Climate Grid. The Vestland Climate Grid <lb/>field sites were established in 2008, and from a series of research projects within the grid over the years we have <lb/>collected a broad range of datasets on the climate and environment, soils, land-use and environment, vegetation, <lb/>and ecosystems, along with basic descriptive data of the 12 sites, as described in 34 . All these datasets are available <lb/>from the previous projects through the VCG OSF (Open Science Framework) repository 35 , and the results are <lb/>presented in associated papers, see for example 34,37-45 . The overall data structure, and the most relevant datasets <lb/>from the VCG for the FunCaB project is laid out in Fig. 3, and briefly described below. Code to download and <lb/>link these data to the FunCaB experimental data and sites are provided in the FunCaB github repository 28 (see R/ <lb/>download_VCG_data). <lb/>A new research project, &apos;FUNDER -Direct and indirect climate impacts on the biodiversity and FUNctioning <lb/>of the UNDERground ecosystem&apos; funded by the Norwegian Research Council KLIMAFORSK programme (pro-<lb/>ject number 315249, 2021 -2025) will augment the FunCaB experiment with data on the belowground compo-<lb/>nents of the plant-soil ecosystem, including roots, mesofauna, fungi and microbes. These upcoming data will all <lb/>link with the FunCaB and VCG project based on the given experimental, site and organismal keys, as indicated <lb/>in Fig. 3. <lb/>VCG Basic site-level attributes. Basic descriptive data on the 12 sites include latitude, longitude, elevation, <lb/>geology, land-use, soils, and their position within the climate grid (precipitation and temperature levels). These <lb/>data are described in 34,40 , provided in 35 , and can be downloaded using 28 (see R/download_VCG_data). For con-<lb/>venience, the climate grid information is also provided in the biomass dataset (see below). <lb/>VCG Site-level climate data. Temperature was measured continuously at each of the 12 VCG sites at four <lb/>heights (2 m and 30 cm above ground, at ground level, and 5 cm below ground), soil moisture was measured <lb/>continuously with two replicate loggers ca. 5 cm below ground, and precipitation was measured at each site dur-<lb/>ing the snow-free season. For these measurements, we used Delta T GP1 loggers (Delta T devices, Cambridge, <lb/>UK) equipped with two temperature probes, two SM200 moisture sensors which were later replaced as necessary <lb/>with SM300 and SM150T loggers, and an ARG 100 tipping bucket (EML LTD, North Shields, UK) from 2009 <lb/>onwards. UTL-3 version 3.0 temperature loggers (GEOTEST AG, Zollikofen, Switzerland) were used for meas-<lb/>uring the 2 m and 30 cm temperatures. Soil moisture was measured as the mean of four measurements taken <lb/>along each side of the turf, several times during the growing season using a Delta T HH2 version 2.3 Moisture <lb/>Meter with the same probes as for the GP1 logger (SM200, SM150T). These data are described in 34,40 , provided <lb/>in 35 , and can be downloaded using 28 (see folder R/download_VCG_data). <lb/>VCG Soil chemical and structural data. Over the years, various soil chemical variables have been measured at <lb/>the block level within each of the 12 VCG sites, including soil pH (2009) and % Loss-On-Ignition (2009, 2013), <lb/>and available N, as sum of N available as NH4-N and NO 3 -N (available N per deployment period, 2010 &amp; 2012). <lb/>Soil pH was measured after adding 50 ml distilled water to 25 g soil and mixing for two hours. Loss-on-ignition <lb/>(LOI), was measured by weighing dry soil (105 °C for 24, one hour in a desiccator), and burnt soil (six hours <lb/>at 550 °C, one hour in the desiccator) and calculating LOI as the (burnt soil mass/dry soil mass) × 100. NH4-N <lb/>and NO 3 -N were measured using in-situ ion exchange resin bags (IERBs) were used to measure the amount of <lb/>plant-available nutrients in the soil. These data are partially described in 34,40 , and the full data are provided in 35 . <lb/>VCG Litter decomposition data. Decomposition has been assessed at each of the 12 VCG sites using local plant <lb/>litter and the Tea Bag Index method (Keuskamp et al., 2013). Local litter (dead leaves detached from live plants) <lb/>was collected at each site in 2013 or 2014, with the specific timing of the collections at each site tuned to ensure that <lb/>litter was present, not covered by snow, and not decomposed. In practice, this necessitated litter collection after <lb/>snowmelt in spring in many sites. The litter was washed, dried, and stored in dark, dry, cool conditions. In 2016, <lb/>Variable name <lb/>Description <lb/>Variable type Variable range or levels Units How measured <lb/>year <lb/>Year of sampling <lb/>numeric <lb/>2016 -2016 <lb/>yyyy <lb/>defined <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alrust -Vikesland <lb/>defined <lb/>blockID <lb/>Unique block ID a combination of site and block categorical <lb/>Alr1 -Vik4 <lb/>defined <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a combination of site, block <lb/>and treatment <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1XC -Vik4XC <lb/>defined <lb/>treatment <lb/>Plant functional groups removed, where <lb/>F = forbs, G = graminoids, B = bryophytes and <lb/>C = control, and XC = extra control <lb/>categorical <lb/>XC -XC <lb/>defined <lb/>functional_group <lb/>Removed functional group, including forbs, <lb/>bryophytes, graminoids, litter, pteridophytes, <lb/>lichens, and cryptograms <lb/>categorical <lb/>forb -forb <lb/>defined <lb/>species <lb/>Species abbreviation <lb/>categorical <lb/>Ach.mil -Vio.sp <lb/>defined <lb/>biomass <lb/>Dry weight of removed functional group <lb/>numeric <lb/>0.01 -12.95 <lb/>g <lb/>measured <lb/>sorted_by <lb/>Person that sorted the biomass <lb/>categorical <lb/>AP -PP <lb/>recorded <lb/>Table 3. Data dictionary for the FunCaB species-level biomass (dataset ii). Data dictionary with column <lb/>descriptions for dataset ii -the total forb biomass per species in the 48 extra controls in 2016 at twelve sites in <lb/>the Vestland Climate Grid, Vestland county, Norway. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>five replicate litter bags containing 1 g of graminoid litter were buried at each site, and collected at four points in <lb/>time after burial (1, 2, 3 and 12 months). Harvested litter bags were cleaned (soil and roots removed), dried for 48 h <lb/>at 60 °C and weighed. The Tea Bag Index method 46 was used in 2014, 2015 and 2016 to measure decomposition at <lb/>all sites of the climate grid. At each site, 10 replicates of each tea type were buried pair-wise, 8 cm below ground and <lb/>with at least 10 cm between the tea bags. For a couple of sites, the number of replicate tea bag pairs was higher in <lb/>2015 (12 replicates at the site Gudmedalen and 16 replicates at Låvisdalen). After collection, adhering soil particles <lb/>and roots were removed and the tea bags were dried (48 h at 60 °C) and weighed. These data are partially described <lb/>in 47 , and the full data are provided in 35 and can be downloaded using 28 (see folder R/download_VCG_data). <lb/>VCG Species-level cover, biomass, and performance data. A variety of plant species and community composi-<lb/>tion, cover, biomass, fitness, and reproductive data exists for the sites and blocks in the VCG from 2008 to 2021. <lb/>These data are described in e.g 34,37,38,41,43-45,48-50 , and provided in 35 . <lb/>VCG Site-level plant functional traits. In 2016 and 2017, we measured 11 leaf functional traits that are related to <lb/>potential physiological growth rates and environmental tolerance of plants, following the standardized protocols <lb/>in Pérez-Harguindeguy et al. 51 : leaf area (LA, cm 2 ), leaf thickness (LT, mm), leaf dry matter content (LDMC, g/g), <lb/>specific leaf area (SLA, cm 2 /g), carbon (C, %), nitrogen (N, %), phosphorus (P, %), carbon nitrogen ratio (C:N), <lb/>nitrogen phosphorus ratio (N:P), carbon13 isotope ratio (δ13C, ‰), and nitrogen15 isotope ratio (δ15N, ‰). <lb/>Trait data are available at the site level for species making up at least 80% of the vegetation cover in the control <lb/>plots at each of the 12 VCG sites. The plants were collected outside of the experimental plots and within a 50 m <lb/>perimeter from the blocks, and we aimed to collect up to five individuals from each species in each site. To avoid <lb/>repeated sampling from a single clone, we selected individuals that were visibly separated from other ramets of <lb/>that species. The sampled plant individuals were labelled, put in plastic bags with moist paper towels, and stored <lb/>in darkness at 4 °C until processing, which was done as soon as possible and always within 4 days. These data are <lb/>described in 52 , provided in 35 , and can be downloaded using 28 (see folder R/download_VCG_data). <lb/> Experimental design. The functional group removal experiment was designed to examine the impact of <lb/>aboveground interactions among the major plant functional groups -graminoids, forbs and bryophytes -on <lb/>the performance and functioning of other components of the vegetation and ecosystem. The experiment con-<lb/>sists of eight 25 × 25 cm plots per site and block, with a fully factorial combination of removals of three plant <lb/>functional groups, with treatments randomized within each block. The general experimental design, with the <lb/>different removal treatments detailed, are provided as an insert to the timeline in Fig. 1c. The functional groups <lb/>are delineated and abbreviated in the various datasets as follows: G = graminoids (including grasses, sedges and <lb/>rushes), F = forbs (including herbaceous forbs, pteridophytes, dwarf-shrubs, and small individuals of trees and <lb/>shrubs), B = Bryophytes (including mosses, liverworts, and hornworts). Note that all species are also coded by <lb/>their respective functional group into which they were classified in the FunCaB taxon table. The experimental <lb/>treatments are coded by functional group removed so that FGB = bare-ground gaps with all plants removed, <lb/>FB = only graminoids remaining, GB = only forbs remaining, GF = only bryophytes remaining, B = graminoids <lb/>and forbs remaining, F = bryophytes and graminoids remaining, G = bryophytes and forbs remaining, and <lb/>C = intact vegetation controls with no vegetation removed. In 2016, four extra control (XC) plots were marked <lb/>per site for aboveground biomass harvest and ecosystem carbon flux measurements. This sampling regime gave a <lb/>total of 384 plots in the core FunCaB experiment, plus the additional 48 controls in 2016. <lb/>Functional group removals were done once in 2015 (at peak growing season due to late snowmelt), twice per <lb/>year in 2016 and 2017 (after the spring growth and at peak growing season) and annually from 2018 to 2021 (at <lb/>Variable name Description <lb/>Variable type Variable range or levels <lb/>Units <lb/>How <lb/>measured <lb/>year <lb/>Year of sampling <lb/>numeric <lb/>2015 -2016 <lb/>yyyy <lb/>defined <lb/>date_time <lb/>Date and time of sampling (UTC + 2) <lb/>date_time <lb/>2015-07-12 17:58:01 -<lb/>2016-06-27 23:05:01 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ss defined <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alrust -Vikesland <lb/>defined <lb/>blockID <lb/>Unique block ID a combination of site and block categorical <lb/>Alr1 -Vik5 <lb/>defined <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a combination of site, block and <lb/>treatment <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1B -Vik5GF <lb/>defined <lb/>iButtonID <lb/>Unique iButton ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>003E3B5C41_2016 -<lb/>F83E3E2A41_2016 <lb/>defined <lb/>treatment <lb/>Plant functional groups removed, where <lb/>F = forbs, G = graminoids, B = bryophytes, and <lb/>C = control <lb/>categorical <lb/>FGB, FG, FB, GB, G, <lb/>F, B, C <lb/>defined <lb/>soiltemperature Soil temperature measurement per plot <lb/>numeric <lb/>−8.75 -32.8 <lb/>°C <lb/>recorded <lb/>comments <lb/>Additional comments <lb/>categorical <lb/>turfID <lb/>Unique turf ID from SeedClim transplant <lb/>experiment <lb/>categorical <lb/>101 TTC -73 TTC <lb/>defined <lb/>Table 4. Data dictionary for the FunCaB soil temperatures (dataset ii). Data dictionary with column <lb/>descriptions for dataset iii -soil temperature from 384 25 × 25 cm experimental plant functional group removal <lb/>plots from 2015 -2016 at twelve sites in the Vestland Climate Grid, Vestland county, Norway. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>peak growing season) as regrowth had declined (see below) and biannual removals were no longer necessary. <lb/>At each sampling, all above-ground biomass of the relevant plant functional group was removed from each plot <lb/>as follows: for each plot, all the above-ground parts of the relevant functional group(s) were removed using <lb/>scissors and tweezers to cut the plants at the ground layer (i.e., the soil-vegetation interface). Roots and other <lb/>below-ground parts were not removed, and non-target plant functional groups and litter were left intact. <lb/>Species identification, taxonomy, and flora. All vascular plant species were identified to the species <lb/>level in the field, with nomenclature following Lid and Lid 53 . Exceptions are sterile specimens of species that <lb/>are not possible to identify without reproductive parts, and where flowers are either too rare or individuals too <lb/>short-lived for comparisons of the position of individuals within the plots over years to be used to ascertain <lb/>identifications (For example, Alchemilla spp. excluding A. alpina, and the annual Euphrasia spp.). Species iden-<lb/>tifications were confirmed by comparing records over time as described below. All unidentified specimens are <lb/>included and flagged in the dataset, as described in Data Records below. The full taxon names are provided in the <lb/>taxon table on OSF (Fig. 3). <lb/>Dataset collection methods. Datasets (i-ii): Biomass and functional group removal. As described above, <lb/>functional group removals were done once in 2015 at peak growing season, and twice per year in 2016 and 2017 <lb/>(after the spring growth; at peak growing season) and annually at peak growing season from 2018 to 2021. For <lb/>each removal plot and occasion, a picture was taken of the plot pre-removal, the biomass to be removed was <lb/>collected in separate pre-marked paper bags for each functional group (graminoids, forbs and bryophytes), and <lb/>a picture was taken post-removal. The collected biomass was then dried at 60 °C for 48 hours and weighed to the <lb/>nearest 0.01 g (Model LPG-1002, VWR). From the four extra control (XC) plots in 2016, total above-ground <lb/>biomass as well as litter (defined as dead biomass detached from live plants, see 28 ) was collected at peak growing <lb/>season. From these plots, biomass was sorted into functional groups as described above, except the forb func-<lb/>tional group, which was sorted into species. The graminoid and bryophyte functional groups, each forb species, <lb/>and litter were individually dried and weighed as described above. The data is available as (i) a biomass dataset, <lb/>consisting of the removed biomass per plot, date, removal treatment, and functional group for all treatment plots, <lb/>and the total biomass per functional group plus litter for the extra control plots in 2016, and (ii) a species-level <lb/>forb biomass dataset from the extra control plots in 2016 (Fig. 3, Table 1). <lb/>Datasets (iii-iv) -Soil microclimate. We measured soil temperature 3-5 cm below the soil surface for each plot <lb/>using iButton temperature sensors (DS1922L, Manufacturer reports temperature accuracy of ±0.5 °C, Maxim <lb/>Integrated INC., San Jose, CA, USA). The data are reported with a resolution of 0.0625 at 140 min intervals from <lb/>June 2015 to July 2016. We measured soil moisture as volumetric soil moisture; expressed as % water volume per <lb/>soil volume ((m 3 water /m 3 soil) × 100). These measurements were done c. 3-5 times during the growing seasons <lb/>from 2015-2019, usually in connection with the flux and vegetation measurements, by taking the average of four <lb/>measurements, one at each side of each plot (SM300, Manufacturer reports accuracy ±2.5% vol over 0 to 50% <lb/>vol and 0-60 °C, Delta-T Devices, Cambridge, UK). The data is available as (iii) temperature and (iv) volumetric <lb/>soil moisture % per plot and time point (temperature) or date (moisture) (Fig. 3, Table 1). <lb/>Dataset (v): Vascular plant community composition and vegetation structure. We recorded the full vascular <lb/>plant species composition of all experimental plots in 2015 (pre treatment), and the control plots plus the extra <lb/>control plots in 2016. In 2017, 2018, and 2019, we recorded the community composition in controls and in <lb/>the functional groups that remained in the experimental plots according to the plot&apos;s treatment. At each anal-<lb/>ysis, each plot was sub-divided into 25 5 × 5 cm subplots, using a subplot overlay. We first recorded all species <lb/>of vascular plants in the central five subplots, (i.e., the central + shaped area of each plot, Fig. 1c) noting the <lb/>subplot cover of each species present in each of the five subplots (1 -25% = 1, 26 -50% = 2, 51 -75% = 3, <lb/>&gt;76% = 4). Additionally, we noted if the individual was fertile (records circled if buds, flowers, or fruits were <lb/>present). The five subplots were recorded and numbered (1-5) by row, and from left to right, starting from the <lb/>Variable name Description <lb/>Variable type Variable range or levels <lb/>Units <lb/>How measured <lb/>date <lb/>Date of sampling <lb/>date <lb/>2015-06-02 -2019-08-09 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd <lb/>defined <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alrust -Vikesland <lb/>defined <lb/>blockID <lb/>Unique block ID a combination of site and block <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr -Vik5 <lb/>defined <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a combination of site, block and treatment <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1B -Vik5GF <lb/>defined <lb/>treatment <lb/>Plant functional groups removed, where F = forbs, <lb/>G = graminoids, B = bryophytes, and C = control <lb/>categorical <lb/>FGB, FG, FB, GB, G, F, B, C <lb/>defined <lb/>soilmoisture <lb/>Soil moisture measurement per plot <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -100 <lb/>(m 3 water × m −3 <lb/>soil) × 100 <lb/>recorded <lb/>weather <lb/>Weather conditions during data collection <lb/>categorical <lb/>Blue sky -windy, cloudy <lb/>recorded <lb/>recorder <lb/>Data collector <lb/>categorical <lb/>? -Vojta <lb/>recorded <lb/>turfID <lb/>Unique turf ID from SeedClim transplant experiment <lb/>categorical <lb/>101 TTC -TTC 281 <lb/>defined <lb/>Table 5. Data dictionary for the FunCaB soil moisture (dataset iv). Data dictionary with column descriptions <lb/>for dataset iv -soil moisture from 384 25 × 25 cm experimental plant functional group removal plots from <lb/>2015 -2016 at twelve sites in the Vestland Climate Grid, Vestland county, Norway. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>top up-slope subplot. For the entire 25 × 25 cm plot, any additional species not present in one of the central sub-<lb/>plots were recorded and their fertility noted. We then visually estimated the percentage cover of each vascular <lb/>plant species in the whole plot to the nearest 1% and measured vegetation height in mm at four points within <lb/>the plot. Note that the total coverage in each plot can exceed 100% due to layering of the vegetation. The vascular <lb/>plant vegetation data is available as percentage cover and fertility status (sterile or fertile) per species per subplot <lb/>and plot per sampling date, and vegetation height in mm per plot per sampling date (Fig. 3, Table 1). <lb/>Climate <lb/>i) biomass <lb/>date <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>treatment <lb/>plotID <lb/>removed_fg <lb/>Vegetation <lb/>v) community <lb/>year <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>treatment <lb/>plotID <lb/>total_fg_cover <lb/>height <lb/>species <lb/>cover <lb/>turfID <lb/>vi) seedling <lb/>year <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>treatment <lb/>plotID <lb/>species <lb/>presence <lb/>turfID <lb/>Keys to join FunCaB/FUNDER datasets <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>Vikesland <lb/>blockID Unique block ID a combination Vik1 <lb/>of site and block <lb/>treatment Plant functional groups <lb/>FGB <lb/>removed (F = forbs, G = <lb/>graminoids, B = bryophytes <lb/>and C = controls) <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a <lb/>Vik1FGB <lb/>combination of site, block <lb/>and treatment <lb/>species Species abbreviation <lb/>Ach.mill <lb/>ii) biomass -species <lb/>year <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>treatment <lb/>plotID <lb/>removed_fg <lb/>species <lb/>biomass <lb/>v) taxon <lb/>species <lb/>species_name <lb/>family <lb/>functional_group <lb/>iii) soil temperature <lb/>date_time <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>treatment <lb/>plotID <lb/>soiltemperature <lb/>turfID <lb/>iv) soil moisture <lb/>date <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>treatment <lb/>plotID <lb/>soilmoisture <lb/>turfID <lb/>viii) re ectance <lb/>date <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>treatment <lb/>plotID <lb/>pre_post_cut <lb/>ndvi <lb/>turfID <lb/>vii) carbon uxes <lb/>date <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>treatment <lb/>plotID <lb/>nee <lb/>gpp <lb/>Reco <lb/>Ecosystem <lb/>Keys to join VCG and FunCaB <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>Vikesland <lb/>blockID Unique block ID a combination Vik1 <lb/>of site and block <lb/>species Species abbreviation <lb/>Ach.mill <lb/>turfID <lb/>Unique turf ID from SeedClim TTC 101 <lb/>transplant experiment <lb/>Vestland Climate Grid: 12 sites along <lb/>climate gradients <lb/>Functional group removal experiment within VCG <lb/>VCG data <lb/>site <lb/>siteID <lb/>latitude <lb/>longitude <lb/>elevation <lb/>site_attributes <lb/>siteID <lb/>landuse <lb/>geology <lb/>slope <lb/>aspect <lb/>other datasets* <lb/>date <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>species <lb/>other response <lb/>turfID <lb/>FunCaB data <lb/>FUNDER data <lb/>datasets* <lb/>date <lb/>siteID <lb/>blockID <lb/>treatment <lb/>response <lb/>turfID <lb/>Belowground responses of <lb/>FunCaB experiment within <lb/>VCG <lb/>Fig. 3 Data structure for the FunCaB functional group removal experiment and associated Vestland Climate <lb/>Grid (VCG) and FUNDER project data. Within each of the three projects, boxes represent data tables. The <lb/>FunCaB project data tables include biomass of functional groups removed and forb species-level biomass <lb/>(datasets i, ii), soil temperature and moisture (datasets iii, iv) plant community composition and the associated <lb/>taxon table (dataset v), seedling recruitment (dataset vi), ecosystem carbon fluxes (dataset vii) and reflectance <lb/>(dataset viii). Names of individual data tables are given in the coloured title area, and a selection of the main <lb/>variables available within tables in the internal lists. For full sets of variables for each FunCaB dataset, see <lb/>Tables 3-9. The lines linking three of the boxes exemplify links using species as keys across tables, note that <lb/>all bold variables are shared between several tables and can be used as keys to join them. Keys can also be <lb/>used to link to/from data from other projects in the VCG (for general VCG project keys, see top right hatched <lb/>outline box, for keys between the FunCaB and FUNDER projects see the bottom right hatched outline box <lb/>(both including an example value for each variable on the right). The (other) datasets* boxes refer to extensive <lb/>datasets on plant community composition, cover, biomass, fitness, and reproduction available from previous <lb/>projects in the VCG 27 and upcoming datasets in the FUNDER project. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Other variables that were measured were percentage cover of bryophytes, litter, bare ground, and rock (meas-<lb/>ured per plot and per subplot) and moss layer depth in mm (mean of 4 measurements/plot), date of analysis, <lb/>recorder/scribe (if any), and free-text comments. These data are available as % cover, depth in mm, date (year. <lb/>month.day) and text strings per subplot and /or plot per sampling date (Fig. 3, Table 1). <lb/>Dataset (vi): Seedling recruitment. The total number of forb seedlings that emerged in the plots was recorded <lb/>in 2018 and 2019. At peak growing season in 2018 (round 1, July-August, depending on site), all dicotyledon-<lb/>ous seedlings were marked with wooden toothpicks and their x and y coordinates in the plot (mm, recorded <lb/>from the bottom left hand-corner of the plot, Fig. 1c) and tentative species identity noted. Toward the end of <lb/>the growing season (round 2, August-September, depending on site), each plot was revisited, seedling survival <lb/>established, and any further seedlings marked. Survival (recorded when a seedling was present in subsequent <lb/>surveys; recorded as mortality if absent) and new seedling emergence were followed up in the same manner <lb/>in 2019 (rounds 3 and 4, respectively). Species identification was (re)assessed at all censuses and corrected if <lb/>needed as the seedlings grew and identification uncertainty decreased. New seedlings were differentiated from <lb/>emergent clonal ramets by looking for cotyledons or signs of above-or below-ground ramet connections. These <lb/>data are available as talleys of seedlings, each with a status (dead or alive) and species identity (or NA when not <lb/>identifiable), per subplot and /or plot per sampling round (Fig. 3, Table 1). <lb/>Dataset (vii): Ecosystem carbon flux data and flux calculations. Carbon flux measurements. Ecosystem CO 2 <lb/>fluxes were measured to estimate net ecosystem exchange (NEE), ecosystem respiration (Reco) and gross pri-<lb/>mary production (GPP). The dataset covers the years 2015, 2016 and 2017, and individual plots have multiple <lb/>measurements for ecosystem carbon flux per year as detailed below. At peak growing season in 2015, a median <lb/>of 2 sets of paired carbon flux measurements were measured pre-removal for all plots, where a paired set consist <lb/>of a light and a dark flux measurement of an individual plot. In 2016, a median of 8 sets of paired measurements <lb/>were made for all control plots, and a median of 7 for the 4 extra controls (see experimental design above). In <lb/>the data files, some additional measurements exist for other experiments in the VCG sites (a median of 7 paired <lb/>sets of measurements for controls (TTC) and graminoid removal plots (RTC), see 42 for a presentation of this <lb/>experiment and 35 for technical details). In 2017, a median of 5 paired sets of measurements were made for all <lb/>treated plots in nine of the sites, excluding the second wettest precipitation level (sites Gudmedalen, Rambera, <lb/>Variable name <lb/>Description <lb/>Variable type <lb/>Variable range or levels Units <lb/>How measured <lb/>year <lb/>Year of sampling <lb/>numeric <lb/>2015 -2019 <lb/>yyyy <lb/>defined <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alrust -Vikesland <lb/>defined <lb/>blockID <lb/>Unique block ID a combination of site <lb/>and block <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1 -Vik5 <lb/>defined <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a combination of site, <lb/>block and treatment <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1B -Vik5GF <lb/>defined <lb/>removal <lb/>Pre (2015) or post ( &gt;2015) removal <lb/>treatment. Pre removal is related to the <lb/>start of the experiment. <lb/>categorical <lb/>post -pre <lb/>defined <lb/>treatment <lb/>Plant functional groups removed, <lb/>where F = forbs, G = Graminoids, and <lb/>B = Bryophytes. C = Controls and <lb/>XC = extra controls <lb/>categorical <lb/>FGB, FG, FB, GB, G, F, <lb/>B, C, XC <lb/>defined <lb/>total_graminoids <lb/>Cover of graminoids <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -100 <lb/>percentage recorded <lb/>total_forbs <lb/>Cover of forbs <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -100 <lb/>percentage recorded <lb/>total_bryophytes <lb/>Cover of bryophytes <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -120 <lb/>percentage recorded <lb/>vegetation_height Height of vegetation <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -350 <lb/>mm <lb/>measured <lb/>moss_height <lb/>Height of bryophytes <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -120 <lb/>mm <lb/>measured <lb/>litter <lb/>Cover of litter <lb/>numeric <lb/>1 -100 <lb/>recorded <lb/>species <lb/>Species abbreviation <lb/>categorical <lb/>Ach.mil -Vio.tri or NA <lb/>defined <lb/>cover <lb/>Individual species cover <lb/>numeric <lb/>1 -98 <lb/>percentage recorded <lb/>functional_group <lb/>Removed functional group, including <lb/>forbs, bryophytes, graminoids. For <lb/>extra controls also litter, pteridophytes, <lb/>lichens, and cryptograms <lb/>categorical <lb/>forb -graminoid <lb/>defined <lb/>sumcover <lb/>Total sum of species cover <lb/>numeric <lb/>1 -176 <lb/>percentage recorded <lb/>recorder <lb/>Data collector <lb/>categorical <lb/>Aud -W <lb/>recorded <lb/>turfID <lb/>Unique turf ID from SeedClim <lb/>transplant experiment <lb/>categorical <lb/>101 TTC -73 TTC <lb/>defined <lb/>Table 6. Data dictionary for the FunCaB plant community composition (dataset v). Data dictionary with <lb/>column descriptions for dataset v -the plant community composition of 384 25 × 25 cm experimental plant <lb/>functional group removal plots from 2015 -2019, and in 48 extra controls in 2016, at twelve sites in the Vestland <lb/>Climate Grid, Vestland County, Norway. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>and Arhelleren). These measurements were made ca. 1 week after the first round of plant functional group <lb/>removals in that season. <lb/>At each sampling occasion, a clear chamber (25 × 25 × 40 cm) equipped with two fans for air circulation and <lb/>connected to an infrared gas analyzer (Li-840; Manufacturer reports accuracy within 1.5% of the reading value; <lb/>LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, NE, USA) was used to measure CO 2 fluxes at all plots. To prevent cutting of roots <lb/>and disruption of water flow in the plots by installing collars, we instead attached a windshield to the bottom of <lb/>the chamber and weighed it down on the ground by a heavy chain to prevent wind-air mixing. At each sampling <lb/>occasion we made paired measurements of fluxes under light and dark conditions, covering the chamber with a <lb/>fitted light-excluding cover for the dark measurements. <lb/>NEE was estimated from measurements of CO 2 flux under ambient light and dark conditions: <lb/>NEElight = GPP -Reco, NEEdark = (-) Reco. We define NEE such that negative values reflect CO 2 uptake in <lb/>the ecosystem, and positive values reflect CO 2 release from the ecosystem to the atmosphere. For each measure-<lb/>ment, CO 2 concentration was recorded at 5 s intervals over a period of 90-120 s. NEE was calculated from the <lb/>temporal change of CO 2 concentration within the closed chamber according to the following formula: <lb/>NEE <lb/>CO <lb/>t <lb/>PV <lb/>R A <lb/>T <lb/>( <lb/>273 15) <lb/>2 <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>= <lb/>× <lb/>× × <lb/>+ <lb/>. <lb/>where δ δ <lb/>CO <lb/>t <lb/>2 is the slope of the CO 2 concentration against time (µmol mol −1 s −1 ), P is the atmospheric pressure <lb/>(kPa), R is the gasconstante (8.314 kPa m3 K −1 mol −1 ), T is the air temperature inside the chamber (°C), V is the <lb/>chamber volume (m 3 ) and A is the surface area (m 2 ). <lb/>Light intensity was measured as photosynthetically active radiation (PAR, µmol m −2 s −1 ) using a quantum <lb/>sensor (Li-190; Manufacturer reports absolute calibration accuracy of ±5%; LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, NE, <lb/>USA) placed inside the chamber. Temperature inside the chamber was measured using an iButton temper-<lb/>ature logger (DS1922L, Manufacturer reports temperature accuracy of ±0.5 °C, Maxim Integrated, San Jose, <lb/>CA, USA). Volumetric soil moisture content (m 3 water/m 3 soil) × 100 was measured by calculating the average <lb/>of four measurements with a soil moisture sensor (SM300, Manufacturer reports moisture accuracy of ±2.5%, <lb/>Delta-T Devices, Cambridge, UK), taken at each side of a plot. <lb/>Data management and calculations. Data from the LiCOR data logger and iButton was downloaded in the field <lb/>and stored. The information from the field data sheets (metadata of CO 2 measurements and plot soil moisture) <lb/>was manually entered into digital worksheets, manually proof-read and stored. Data from the data logger (PAR <lb/>Variable name <lb/>Description <lb/>Variable type Variable range or levels <lb/>Units <lb/>How <lb/>measured <lb/>year <lb/>Year of sampling <lb/>numeric <lb/>2018 -2019 <lb/>yyyy <lb/>defined <lb/>date <lb/>Date of sampling <lb/>date <lb/>2018-07-01 -2019-08-15 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd <lb/>defined <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alrust -Vikesland <lb/>defined <lb/>blockID <lb/>Unique block ID a combination of <lb/>site and block <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1 -Vik5 <lb/>defined <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a combination of <lb/>site, block and treatment <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1B -Vik5GF <lb/>defined <lb/>treatment <lb/>Plant functional groups removed, <lb/>where F = forbs, G = graminoids, <lb/>B = bryophytes and C = control, and <lb/>XC = extra control <lb/>categorical <lb/>B -GF <lb/>defined <lb/>seedID <lb/>Unique seedling ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>1_Alr3B -z_Ves3GB <lb/>round <lb/>Round of sampling <lb/>numeric <lb/>1 -4 <lb/>count <lb/>defined <lb/>species <lb/>Species abbreviation <lb/>categorical <lb/>Ach.mil -Vio.sp <lb/>defined <lb/>presence <lb/>Presence (1) or absence (0) of a <lb/>seedling per census <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -1 <lb/>recorded <lb/>x <lb/>x coordinate in the plot <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -250 <lb/>mm <lb/>recorded <lb/>y <lb/>y coordinate in the plot <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -250 <lb/>mm <lb/>recorded <lb/>comment <lb/>Comment on measurement <lb/>categorical <lb/>? -x220, y113 <lb/>turfID <lb/>Unique turf ID from SeedClim <lb/>transplant experiment <lb/>categorical <lb/>11 TTC -73 TTC <lb/>defined <lb/>functional_group <lb/>Removed functional group, <lb/>including forbs, bryophytes, <lb/>graminoids, litterm pteridophytes, <lb/>lichens, and cryptograms <lb/>categorical <lb/>forb -forb <lb/>defined <lb/>round <lb/>Round of sampling; round 1-2 <lb/>correspond to 2018, and round 3-4 <lb/>to 2019 <lb/>numeric <lb/>1 -4 <lb/>defined <lb/>Table 7. Data dictionary for the FunCaB seedling recruitment (dataset v). Data dictionary with column <lb/>descriptions for dataset v -the plant community composition of 384 25 × 25 cm experimental plant functional <lb/>group removal plots from 2015 -2019, and in 48 extra controls in 2016, at twelve sites in the Vestland Climate <lb/>Grid, Vestland County, Norway. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>and CO 2 ) and the iButton temperature logger were linked based on information from the field data sheets. All <lb/>measurements were first visually evaluated for quality and only measurements that showed a consistent linear <lb/>relationship between CO 2 over a time for a period of at least 60 s were used for NEE calculations. A second <lb/>inclusion criterion was that this relationship had R 2 ≤ 0.2 or R 2 ≥ 0.8 for NEE measurement in light conditions <lb/>and R 2 ≥ 0.8 for NEE dark measurements (R eco ). Measurements of NEE in light conditions with R 2 ≤ 0.2 ensures <lb/>representation of measurements with equal rates for R eco and GPP. Third, paired measurements that were more <lb/>than 2 h apart were excluded. These data are available as raw fluxes and as GPP and R eco per plot per measurement <lb/>(Fig. 3, Table 1). <lb/>Dataset (vi): Reflectance. Reflectance measures of Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) were taken <lb/>for each plot during the 2019 (post functional group removal) and 2021 (pre and post removal) field seasons <lb/>(July-August), using a Trimble Greenseeker Handheld Crop Sensor (Trimble Inc., Sunnydale, CA, USA). As <lb/>the sensor measures an elliptical plane, two measures perpendicular to each other were taken for each sub-<lb/>plot (25 × 25 cm plot), with the centre of each ellipse being the centre of the subplot. Care was taken to ensure <lb/>that sampling quadrat frames were not within the sensor range when conducting measurements (see methods <lb/>Dataset ii). Measures of NDVI were taken at 60 cm above the surface where possible. Height was measured <lb/>perpendicular to the sampled ground surface. These data are available as reflectance per plot per sampling date <lb/>(Fig. 3, Table 1). <lb/>Data Records <lb/>This paper reports on data from a plant functional group removal experiment replicated across the twelve sites <lb/>in the Vestland Climate Grid along broad-scale bioclimatic gradients in boreal and alpine grasslands in western <lb/>Norway, conducted from the 2015 growing season onwards. The datasets include the treatment variable, biomass <lb/>removed, and a number of response variables reflecting microclimate, plant community composition, seedling <lb/>recruitment, ecosystem carbon fluxes, and vegetation reflectance collected from 2015 (the pre-treatment year) <lb/>through 2021, with variable number of years of data and temporal resolution between datasets (Fig. 1c, Table 1). <lb/>Additional information and covariables reflecting site climate and environment, soils, litter decomposition, and <lb/>plant functional traits in the Vestland Climate Grid can be obtained from the VCG data descriptor 35 and linked <lb/>Variable name Description <lb/>Variable type Variable range or levels <lb/>Units <lb/>How <lb/>measured <lb/>year <lb/>Year of sampling <lb/>numeric <lb/>2015 -2017 <lb/>yyyy <lb/>defined <lb/>date <lb/>Date of sampling <lb/>date <lb/>2015-06-30 -2017-08-01 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd <lb/>defined <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alrust -Vikesland <lb/>defined <lb/>blockID <lb/>Unique block ID a combination of site and block <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1 -Vik5 <lb/>defined <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a combination of site, block and treatment <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1B -Vik5RTC <lb/>defined <lb/>treatment <lb/>Plant functional groups removed, where F = forbs, <lb/>G = graminoids, B = bryophytes, C = control, XC = extra <lb/>control, RTC = VCG graminoid removal <lb/>categorical <lb/>FGB, FG, FB, GB, G, F, B, C, <lb/>XC, RTC <lb/>defined <lb/>starttime <lb/>Start time of light measurement (UTC + 2) <lb/>date_time <lb/>2015-06-30 08:10:30 -2017-<lb/>08-01 14:17:10 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ss <lb/>recorded <lb/>stoptime <lb/>End time of light measurement (UTC + 2) <lb/>date_time <lb/>2015-06-30 08:12:30 -2017-<lb/>08-01 14:19:10 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ss <lb/>recorded <lb/>PAR <lb/>PAR value of light measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>4.659 -2555 <lb/>µmol m-2 s-1 <lb/>recorded <lb/>soiltemp <lb/>Soil temperature value of light measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>3 -23.2 <lb/>°C <lb/>recorded <lb/>soilmoisture <lb/>Soil moisture measurement per plot <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -76.775 <lb/>m3 water×m-3 soil×100 <lb/>recorded <lb/>tempK <lb/>Air temperature in the chamber during light measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>279.225 -312.784 <lb/>Kelvin <lb/>recorded <lb/>vegHeight <lb/>Vegetation height <lb/>numeric <lb/>0.01 -27 <lb/>mm <lb/>measured <lb/>nee <lb/>Net ecosystem exchange <lb/>numeric <lb/>−15.392 -17.885 <lb/>µmol m −2 s −1 <lb/>calculated <lb/>rsqd <lb/>R squared of slope of linear regression fitting the CO2 <lb/>concentration versus time <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -1 <lb/>calculated <lb/>chamber <lb/>Carbon flux chamber <lb/>numeric <lb/>1 -2 <lb/>defined <lb/>removal <lb/>Pre (2015) or post (&gt;2015) removal treatment. Pre removal is <lb/>related to the start of the experiment. <lb/>categorical <lb/>post -pre <lb/>defined <lb/>weather <lb/>Weather conditions during data collection <lb/>categorical <lb/>cloud -Windy <lb/>recorded <lb/>flag <lb/>Flag for data quality (x or DROP) <lb/>categorical <lb/>comment <lb/>Comment on measurement <lb/>categorical <lb/>time <lb/>Time in seconds for light measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -195 <lb/>second <lb/>recorded <lb/>Table 8. Data dictionary for the FunCaB ecosystem light measurement carbon fluxes (dataset vii). Data <lb/>dictionary with column descriptions for dataset vii -the ecosystem light measurement carbon fluxes from 384 <lb/>25 × 25 cm experimental plant functional group removal plots from 2015 -2017, and in 48 extra controls in <lb/>2016, at twelve sites in the Vestland Climate Grid, Vestland County, Norway. Note that the dataset also contains <lb/>additional measurements from another graminoid removal experiment in the VCD and the corresponding dark <lb/>measurements for each plot and measurement time (Table 9). <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>to the FunCaB data using shared site, block, plot, treatment and taxonomic variables as keys (Fig. 3). Code to <lb/>download and link selected VCG data to the FunCaB experiment is provided in the open FunCaB GitHub repos-<lb/>itory, and in a time-stamped version on Zenodo 28 . <lb/>Data outputs consist of 6 datasets, (i) the functional group biomass removed from all treatment plots from <lb/>2015 through 2021, (ii) species-level forb biomass from the extra control plots in 2016, (iii) soil temperature in <lb/>2015 and 2016, (iv) soil moisture from 2015 through 2019, (v) species composition and structure of the exper-<lb/>imental plots from 2015 thorugh 2019, (vi) seedling recruitment in 2018 and 2019, (vii) ecosystem fluxes from <lb/>2015 through 2017, and (viii) reflectance in 2019 and 2021 (Table 1). The structure and relationship between <lb/>datasets are described in Fig. 3. These data were checked and cleaned according to the procedures described in <lb/>Fig. 2, see Technical Validation for details, before final data files and associated metadata were produced. <lb/>The final data files (see Table 1 for an overview) and all raw data, including raw flux measurements and <lb/>pictures of the plots pre-and post-removals, are available at the FunCaB Open Science Framework (OSF) data <lb/>repository 27 . To ensure reproducibility and open workflows, the code necessary to access the raw data and pro-<lb/>duce cleaned datasets, along with explanations of the various data cleaning steps, issues, and outcomes, are <lb/>available in the open FunCaB GitHub code repository, in the file R/data_dic/download_clean_data.R, with a <lb/>Variable name <lb/>Description <lb/>Variable type <lb/>Variable range or <lb/>levels <lb/>Units <lb/>How <lb/>measured <lb/>year <lb/>Year of sampling <lb/>numeric <lb/>2015 -2017 <lb/>yyyy <lb/>defined <lb/>date <lb/>Date of sampling <lb/>date <lb/>2015-06-30 -<lb/>2017 -08-01 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd <lb/>defined <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alrust -Vikesland <lb/>defined <lb/>blockID <lb/>Unique block ID a combination of <lb/>site and block <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1 -Vik5 <lb/>defined <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a combination of <lb/>site, block and treatment <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1B -Vik5RTC <lb/>defined <lb/>treatment <lb/>Plant functional groups removed, <lb/>where F = forbs, G = graminoids, <lb/>B = bryophytes, C = control, <lb/>XC = extra control, RTC = VCG <lb/>graminoid removal <lb/>categorical <lb/>FGB, FG, FB, GB, G, F, <lb/>B, C, XC, RTC <lb/>defined <lb/>vegHeight <lb/>Vegetation height <lb/>numeric <lb/>0.01 -27 <lb/>mm <lb/>measured <lb/>gpp <lb/>Gross primary production <lb/>calculated from nee -Reco <lb/>numeric <lb/>−24.342 -−0.004 <lb/>µmol m −2 s −1 <lb/>calculated <lb/>starttime_Reco <lb/>Start time of dark measurement <lb/>(UTC + 2) <lb/>date_time <lb/>2015-06-30 08:14:30 -<lb/>2017-08-01 14:19:55 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ss <lb/>recorded <lb/>stoptime_Reco <lb/>End time of dark measurement <lb/>(UTC + 2) <lb/>date_time <lb/>2015-06-30 08:16:00 -<lb/>2017-08-01 14:21:55 <lb/>yyyy-mm-dd hh:mm:ss <lb/>recorded <lb/>time_Reco <lb/>Time in seconds for dark <lb/>measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>5 -180 <lb/>second <lb/>recorded <lb/>PAR_Reco <lb/>PAR value of dark measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -140.131 <lb/>µmol m −2 s −1 <lb/>recorded <lb/>soiltemp_Reco <lb/>Soil temperature value of dark <lb/>measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>3 -23.2 <lb/>°C <lb/>recorded <lb/>tempK_Reco <lb/>Air temperature in the chamber <lb/>during dark measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>279.225 -311.977 <lb/>Kelvin <lb/>recorded <lb/>Reco <lb/>Ecosystem respiration <lb/>numeric <lb/>0.549 -30.354 <lb/>µmol m −2 s −1 <lb/>recorded <lb/>rsqd_Reco <lb/>R squared of slope of linear <lb/>regression fitting the CO2 <lb/>concentration versus time <lb/>numeric <lb/>0.8 -1 <lb/>calculated <lb/>chamber_Reco <lb/>Carbon flux chamber <lb/>numeric <lb/>1 -3 <lb/>defined <lb/>delta <lb/>Time difference between dark and <lb/>light measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>65 -7050 <lb/>second <lb/>calculated <lb/>removal <lb/>Pre (2015) or post (&gt;2015) removal <lb/>treatment. Pre removal is related to <lb/>the start of the experiment. <lb/>categorical <lb/>post -pre <lb/>defined <lb/>weather <lb/>Weather conditions during data <lb/>collection <lb/>categorical <lb/>cloud -Windy <lb/>recorded <lb/>flag <lb/>Flag for data quality (x or DROP) <lb/>categorical <lb/>comment <lb/>Comment on measurement <lb/>categorical <lb/>time <lb/>Time in seconds for light <lb/>measurement <lb/>numeric <lb/>0 -195 <lb/>second <lb/>recorded <lb/>Table 9. Data dictionary for the FunCaB ecosystem dark measurement carbon fluxes (dataset vii). Data <lb/>dictionary with column descriptions for dataset vii -the ecosystem dark measurement carbon fluxes from 384 <lb/>25 × 25 cm experimental plant functional group removal plots from 2015 -2017, and in 48 extra controls in <lb/>2016, at twelve sites in the Vestland Climate Grid, Vestland County, Norway. Note that the dataset also contains <lb/>additional measurements from another graminoid removal experiment in the VCD and the corresponding light <lb/>measurements for each plot and measurement time (Table 8). The light measurement data are used to calculate <lb/>gpp (gross primary production) and delta (time difference between light and dark measurements). <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>time-stamped versioned copy archived in Zenodo 28 . The reader is referred to the code and the detailed cod-<lb/>ing, data cleaning, and data accuracy comments and the associated raw and cleaned data and metadata tables <lb/>available in these repositories for detailed information about the data cleaning process. Figure 2 and the Usage <lb/>Notes section in this paper summarises the data accuracy and data cleaning procedures, see the latter for caveats <lb/>regarding data quality and our advice on &apos;best practice&apos; data usage. <lb/>Dataset (i): lant functional group removed and total biomass. This dataset contains the biomass <lb/>removed per experimental plot and functional group per year, and the total biomass in the extra controls in 2016 <lb/>(Tables 1, 2, Fig. 4). For convenience, this dataset also contains basic information on the temperature and precipi-<lb/>tation levels in the VCG climate grid (more details available in 35 and 28 ). From the experimental plots we removed <lb/>a total of 17,839 g biomass over the project period; 5,881 g graminoids, 6,039 g forbs, and 5,918 g bryophytes. <lb/>Biomass removed decreased over time, 3,742 g, 6,396 g, 1,956 g, 1,095 g, 1,701 g, 1,502 g, and 1,446 g per year from <lb/>2015 through 2021, suggesting that the removed functional groups were not able to recover from treatments and <lb/>gradually were excluded from the treated plots as the experiment progressed. The lowest biomass was removed <lb/>in 2018, a drought year. <lb/>The extra control plots in 2016 contained a total of 1,495 g total above-ground biomass; 357.0 g grasses, <lb/>300.0 g forbs, 322.0 g bryophytes, 7.9 g lichens, 0.9 g ferns, 1.9 g cryptogams, and 506.0 g litter. This corresponds <lb/>to overall average biomass across the twelve sites of 119.0, 100.0, 107.3 and 168.7 g/m 2 for the three functional <lb/>groups and litter, respectively. For an overview over the clean dataset see Table 2. The raw data is provided on the <lb/>FunCaB OSF 27 , the code to download and clean the data can be found in the FunCaB GitHub repository 28 in the <lb/>file R/biomass/read_biomass.R. <lb/>Dataset (ii): Species-level biomass in extra controls in 2016. This dataset contains the biomass <lb/>removed per plot and species for forbs in the 48 extra control plots in 2016 (Tables 1, 3). Species-level biomass was <lb/>recorded for 79 forb species, of which Potentilla erecta (24.3 g), Achillea millefolium (16.6 g), and Alchemilla alpina <lb/>(16.3 g) were the most abundant overall. Abundances varied across sites, in the alpine Alchemilla alpina (12.9 g), <lb/>Alchemilla sp. (10.0 g), and Salix herbacea (5.97 g) were the most abundant species, whereas in boreal sites Achillea <lb/>millefolium (10.2 g), Potentilla erecta (6.88 g), and Hieracium pilosella (5.51 g), dominated. For an overview over <lb/>the clean dataset see Table 3. The final cleaned data together with a data dictionary is provided on the FunCaB <lb/>OSF 27 , and the code to download the final cleaned data can be found in the FunCaB GitHub repository 28 in the <lb/>file R/data_dic/download_clean_data.R. <lb/>Dataset (iii): Soil temperature. The iButton dataset contains soil temperature data per plot from July <lb/>2015 to July 2016 (Tables 1, 4). This dataset has data from 322 loggers with a total of 1,084,970 observations. <lb/>Soil temperatures ranged from −8.25 to 32.8 °C. During the growing season months, May through August, the <lb/>average daily mean temperature was lowest in plots where only forbs were present, 9.47 ± 0.16 °C (GB treatment) <lb/>and highest in the bare ground plots 10.40 ± 0.14 °C (FGB treatment). During the same period, the daily max <lb/>temperatures were also lowest where only forbs were present, 17.80 ± 0.16 °C (GB treatment) and highest in the <lb/>bare ground plots 20.40 ± 0.14 °C (FGB treatment). For an overview over the clean dataset see Table 4. The final <lb/>cleaned data together with a data dictionary is provided on the FunCaB OSF 27 , and the code to download the final <lb/>cleaned data can be found in the FunCaB GitHub repository 28 in the file R/data_dic/download_clean_data.R. <lb/>Dataset (iv): Soil moisture. The soil moisture dataset contains volumetric soil moisture data per plot <lb/>from June 2015 to August 2018 (Tables 1, 5). The database contains 4,771 soil moisture measurements from <lb/>Variable name Description <lb/>Variable type Variable range or levels Units <lb/>How measured <lb/>date <lb/>Date of sampling <lb/>date <lb/>2019-07-19 -2021-07-30 yyyy-mm-dd defined <lb/>siteID <lb/>Unique site ID <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alrust -Vikesland <lb/>defined <lb/>blockID <lb/>Unique block ID a combination of site and <lb/>block <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1 -Vik5 <lb/>defined <lb/>plotID <lb/>Unique plot ID is a combination of site, block <lb/>and treatment <lb/>categorical <lb/>Alr1B -Vik5GF <lb/>defined <lb/>treatment <lb/>Plant functional groups removed, where <lb/>F = forbs, G = graminoids, B = bryophytes <lb/>and C = control, extra controls <lb/>categorical <lb/>FGB, FG, FB, GB, G, F, <lb/>B, C, XC <lb/>defined <lb/>pre_post_cut <lb/>Measurement was taken before or after the cut categorical <lb/>post -pre <lb/>recorded <lb/>ndvi <lb/>NDVI value <lb/>numeric <lb/>0.315 -4.265 <lb/>percentage <lb/>measured <lb/>notes <lb/>Notes <lb/>categorical <lb/>turfID <lb/>Unique turf ID from SeedClim transplant <lb/>experiment <lb/>categorical <lb/>TTC 101 -TTC 69 <lb/>defined <lb/>weather <lb/>Weather conditions during data collection <lb/>categorical <lb/>Cloudy -Sunny <lb/>recorded <lb/>time <lb/>Time of sampling (UTC + 2) <lb/>time <lb/>08:00 -19:55 <lb/>hh:mm <lb/>defined <lb/>Table 10. Data dictionary for the FunCaB vegetation reflectance (dataset viii). Data dictionary with column <lb/>descriptions for dataset vii -the vegetation reflectance from 384 25 × 25 cm experimental plant functional <lb/>group removal plots from 2019 and 2021, at twelve sites in the Vestland Climate Grid, Vestland County, Norway. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>2015 to 2019, with the median number of measurements per plot per year ranging from 3 -5, except in 2018 <lb/>where the median was one measurement per plot. Average soil moisture was 20.2 ± 0.4% in 2015, 26.1 ± 0.5% <lb/>in 2016, 29.6 ± 0.6% in 2017, 19.0 ± 0.9% in 2018, and 13.7 ± 0.5% in 2019, which was a drought year. Plots with <lb/>forbs only and all functional groups removed were the driest, with an average soil moisture of 21.8 ± 0.7% (F) and <lb/>22.1 ± 0.7 (FGB) whereas the intact control plots were the wettest with 24.1 ± 0.6% (C). For an overview over the <lb/>clean dataset see Table 5. The final cleaned data together with a data dictionary is provided on the FunCaB OSF 27 , <lb/>and the code to download the final cleaned data can be found in the FunCaB GitHub repository 28 in the file R/ <lb/>data_dic/download_clean_data.R. <lb/>Dataset (v): Vascular plant community composition and structure. The plot-level plant commu-<lb/>nity dataset contains a total of 206 taxa and 17,181 observations (taxa × plots × years) (Tables 2, 6). Overall, <lb/>299 observations (1.74%) were not identified to taxon. In 2015, the pre-treatment vegetation had an average <lb/>species richness of 5.9 graminoids (ranging from 3.2 to 9.3 across sites) and 10.8 forbs (ranging from 3.8 to 14.9 <lb/>across sites) per plot. The highest species richness was found in alpine sites. Sum of covers of the non-removed <lb/>functional groups varied over sites and years (Fig. 5). In many cases, biomass of the remaining functional group <lb/>increases over time in plots where other functional groups were removed, relative to controls, suggesting release <lb/>from competitive interactions may be occurring. However, in some cases, notably forbs in colder and wetter sites, <lb/>responses are neutral to negative, which is consistent with earlier work in the system suggesting that competitive <lb/>plant-plant interactions are less important and facilitative interactions more important under these conditions 42 . <lb/>Similarly, there were generally lower abundances and also lower relative biomass gains in removals in 2018, which <lb/>was a drought year, suggesting competitive release was less important under this climate extreme event (Fig. 5). <lb/>Note that some of the recorded data (e.g., sub-plot level presence data, life-history stage/fertility data, acrocarp/ <lb/>pleurocarp bryophyte cover data) are available in the raw data tables, but these are not processed or presented in <lb/>the final data table. For an overview over the clean dataset see Table 6. The final cleaned data together with a data <lb/>dictionary is provided on the FunCaB OSF 27 , and the code to download the final cleaned data and the taxon table <lb/>can be found in the FunCaB GitHub repository 28 in the file R/data_dic/download_clean_data.R. <lb/>Dataset (vi): Seedling recruitment. The seedling recruitment dataset has data on a total of 16,656 seed-<lb/>lings of 44 species (Tables 2, 7). Overall, 61.2% of the seedlings were identified to species, the remaining 38.8% <lb/>were either unidentifiable for the duration of the study or they died before they could be identified. Seedling den-<lb/>sities were highest in the bare soil and forb only plots (FGB and GB treatments) with 1,297 and 1,451 seedlings <lb/>m −2 , respectively, and lowest in the graminoid and bryophyte and graminoid only plots (F and FB treatments) <lb/>with 228 and 224 seedlings m −2 , respectively. The intact vegetation controls (C) had intermediate seedling den-<lb/>sities, with 764 seedlings m −2 . Seedling emergence differed between the two study years, with 5,888 seedlings <lb/>recorded in the drought year 2018 compared to 10,768 in 2019. Overall, 5,870 seedlings survived till the last <lb/>census. For an overview over the clean dataset see Table 7. The final cleaned data together with a data dictionary <lb/>Fig. 4 Biomass over time in the FunCaB plant functional group removal experiment. Biomass removed per <lb/>site, treatment, and plant functional group over time from 384 25 × 25 cm experimental plant functional group <lb/>removal plots from 2015-2021, and total biomass from 48 extra controls in 2016, at twelve sites in the Vestland <lb/>Climate Grid, Vestland County, Norway. Sites are coded by vegetation zone (boreal, sub-alpine, alpine) and <lb/>precipitation level (low = 1 to high = 4). B = bryophytes, F = forbs, G = graminoids. Removal treatments are <lb/>coded by the plant functional group removed (i.e., in the B treatments, F and G are not removed). <lb/>boreal1 <lb/>boreal2 <lb/>boreal3 <lb/>boreal4 <lb/>sub.alpine1 <lb/>sub.alpine2 <lb/>sub.alpine3 <lb/>sub.alpine4 <lb/>alpine1 <lb/>alpine2 <lb/>alpine3 <lb/>alpine4 <lb/>2021 <lb/>2020 <lb/> 2019 <lb/>2018 <lb/>2017 <lb/>2016 <lb/>2015 <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>FB <lb/>GB <lb/>GF <lb/>FGB <lb/>XC <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/> 100 <lb/> 150 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>Removal treatment <lb/>Removed functional group biomass in g <lb/>Functional group <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>is provided on the FunCaB OSF 27 , and the code to download the final cleaned data can be found in the FunCaB <lb/>GitHub repository 28 in the file R/data_dic/download_clean_data.R. <lb/>Dataset (vii)-Ecosystem carbon fluxes. The plot-level ecosystem carbon flux dataset has a total of 3,696 <lb/>paired light (GPP) and dark (Reco) measurements between 2015 and 2017 (Tables 1, 8, 9). A total of 926 paired <lb/>fluxes were recorded in 2015, 1,286 in 2016 and 1,484 in 2017. The median number of measurements per plot <lb/>and year 2 in 2015, 8 in 2016 (when we measured control plots only) and 5 in 2017. The GPP values ranged <lb/>from −24.30 ± 0.06 to −0.01 ± 0.06 µmol mol −1 s −1 CO 2 , the PAR between 4.66 ± 8.46 and 2555.00 ± 8.46 (µmol <lb/>m −2 s −1 ), the soil moisture between 0 ± 0.28 and 76.78 ± 0.28 and the air temperature within the chamber var-<lb/>ied between 6.08 ± 0.10 and 39.63 ± 0.10 °C. The respiration measurements (R eco ) ranged from 0.55 ± 0.05 to <lb/>30.35 ± 0.05 µmol mol −1 s −1 CO 2 , the soil moisture between 0 ± 0.28 and 76.78 ± 0.28 and the associated air <lb/>temperature varied within the chamber measurements between 6.08 ± 0.10 and 38.83 ± 0.10 °C. Note that light <lb/>and dark measurements have very similar soil moisture and air temperature, as would be expected given that <lb/>they are both measured on the same plots within a short period. Average GPP varied among treatments, and on <lb/>average, the highest CO 2 uptake was found in intact vegetation (C; −8.28 ± 0.19 µmol mol −1 s −1 CO 2 ) while the <lb/>lowest uptake was found in bare ground plots (FGB treatment; −4.95 ± 0.27 µmol mol −1 s −1 CO 2 ). Respiration <lb/>did not vary much across treatments, but for GPP, the highest value 6.63 ± 0.15µmol mol −1 s −1 CO 2 was again <lb/>found in the intact vegetation (C) and the lowest value 5.04 ± 0.17 µmol mol −1 s −1 CO 2 in the bare ground plots <lb/>(FGB treatment). For an overview over the clean dataset see Tables 8, 9. The final cleaned data together with a data <lb/>dictionary is provided on the FunCaB OSF 27 , and the code to download the final cleaned data can be found in the <lb/>FunCaB GitHub repository 28 in the file R/data_dic/download_clean_data.R. <lb/>Dataset (xi) -Reflectance. The plot-level community reflectance dataset has a total of 1,244 observations. <lb/>In 2019 we made 480 post-treatment measurements, and in 2021 we made 382 pre-treatment measurements <lb/>and 382 post-treatment measurements (Tables 2, 10). Average reflectance post-treatment was 0.634 ± 0.004 <lb/>(mean ± SE) in 2019 and 0.679 ± 0.006 in 2021, whereas the reflectance pre-treatment in 2021 was 0.760 ± 0.010. <lb/>In both years, the highest reflectance post cut was found in the intact vegetation (C), 0.695 ± 0.007 in 2019 and <lb/>0.774 ± 0.009 in 2021, whereas the lowest reflectance was found in the bare ground treatment (FGB) 0.524 ± 0.008 <lb/>in 2019 and 0.507 ± 0.015 in 2021. For an overview over the clean dataset see Table 10. The final cleaned data <lb/>together with a data dictionary is provided on the FunCaB OSF 27 , and the code to download the final cleaned data <lb/>can be found in the FunCaB GitHub repository 28 in the file R/data_dic/download_clean_data.R. <lb/>technical Validation <lb/>Experimental validation. The plant functional group experiments and field measurements (before-after <lb/>treatment photographs, soil moisture measurements, site-level VCD climate data) were maintained over seven <lb/>years under the oversight of LCK, supported by IHJA and SAHÖ in some years and field campaigns. Consistent <lb/>leadership of the campaigns ensured consistency in experimental treatments and data collection, which was crit-<lb/>ical as a large number of students, technicians and interns were involved in the plant functional group removal <lb/>work, typically 4 -6 people each year (see Acknowledgements). Errors made during field work are noted in the <lb/>data sheets and entered as comments in the plant functional group removal biomass data tables. The photographs <lb/>of each plot pre-and post-removal for each field campaign (with some gaps, and photos are lacking from 2020) <lb/>can be used for further documentation and validation 27 . Biomass removed decreased over time, especially after <lb/>the second year (Fig. 5, suggesting the communities stabilised in the experimentally defined functional group <lb/>composition, with relatively little regrowth of the removed functional group after this point. <lb/>Taxonomic validation. During the 7-year data collection period a number of people were involved in com-<lb/>munity and seedling data collection (see notes in dataset for recorder information), which introduces a risk of <lb/>observer errors. In particular, species can be misidentified (e.g., sterile graminoids) or might be overlooked in <lb/>one of the community censuses. Such errors, if uncorrected, generate pseudo-turnover in the plant community <lb/>and seedling data. To detect and correct errors in the community data, we compared each recorded species in <lb/>each plot or subplot over the time-series. We used these comparisons to assign unidentified or missing species <lb/>to an existing identified species in that plot if it was likely that this could be the correct ID, and if there was a <lb/>record of that species in the plot in the previous and following year. Further, we imputed species covers in cases <lb/>where cover was either missing or clearly too low or high to be realistic when comparing with the total sum of <lb/>covers and covers of the same species in adjacent years in the time-series, replacing such erroneous values with <lb/>the mean cover from the previous and following year. We further checked and corrected &apos;botanist effects&apos; in cover <lb/>estimation between observers, in height estimations (using cm vs mm), and ensured taxonomic consistency. The <lb/>data-checking code and outcomes for these various procedures is documented in 28 . In addition, 23 forbs and six <lb/>graminoid taxa are identified to the genus level in the community dataset and one graminoid, two forbs and seven <lb/>seedling observations are unidentified (these are named NID.herb, NID.gram, and NID.seedling in the datasets) <lb/>(datasets v, vi). A full species list of all identified taxa across datasets is also available in the taxon table in the <lb/>OSF repository (see Table 2). This table also includes the functional group (F, G, or B) to which each taxon was <lb/>assigned in the experimental treatments. Note that the sub-plot-level presences and life-history stage/fertility data <lb/>are available in the OSF, but these data have not been processed or cleaned. <lb/>Ecosystem C flux validation. All measurements were first visually evaluated for data quality. If there were <lb/>clear outliers (values far outside the normal range of CO 2 concentrations within a measurement), these values <lb/>were flagged and removed before flux calculation. The timeframes of measurements were adjusted if the linear <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>relationship over time was affected by either change in cloud cover or there was indication of chamber leakage <lb/>(CO 2 increase/decrease levelling off after steady linear relationship). Resulting fluxes were only included if they <lb/>showed a consistent linear relationship between CO 2 and time for a period of at least 60 seconds. Measurements <lb/>of poor quality due to erratic CO 2 concentrations over time were flagged and removed. An additional criterion <lb/>was that this relationship had R 2 ≤ 0.2 or R 2 ≥ 0.8 for NEE measurement in light conditions and R 2 ≥ 0.8 for <lb/>NEE dark measurements (R eco ; 52, 150 and 466 measurements removed in 2015, 2016 and 2017, respectively). <lb/>Measurements of NEE in light conditions with R 2 ≤ 0.2 ensure inclusion of measurements with equal rates for R eco <lb/>and GPP. Dark measurements with resulting NEE &lt; 0 were removed, as they would indicate uptake CO 2 uptake <lb/>(49 measurements removed in 2017). Sets of L and D measurement per plot were then matched together based <lb/>on date and time of day for calculation of GPP but were not paired if they were more than 2 hours apart from each <lb/>other. Finally, GPP fluxes with values &gt; 0 were removed, as they would represent CO 2 release, not uptake/primary <lb/>productivity (0 measurements were thus removed in 2015, 18 in 2016, and 191 in 2017). The PAR sensor for one <lb/>of the chambers was malfunctioning between 03 July 2017 and 6 July 2017. PAR values for these measurements <lb/>were corrected by using an estimated value based on recorded PAR values in the metadata from the other par <lb/>sensor. <lb/>Usage Notes <lb/>Data use best practice. We suggest that all FunCaB project data presented here and available in the FunCaB <lb/>OSF 27 be cited to this data paper. Other VCG data available through the VCG OSF 35 should be cited to the rele-<lb/>vant publications, specifically, the general description of the climate and environment, soils, land-use and envi-<lb/>ronment, vegetation, and ecosystems along with basic descriptive data of the 12 sites are presented in 34 , whereas <lb/>specific biotic and abiotic response data are presented in e.g. 37-48 ,. Note that major VCG datasets will be made <lb/>700 mm <lb/>1400 mm <lb/>2100 mm <lb/>2800 mm <lb/>alpine <lb/>sub.alpine <lb/>boreal <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>19 15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>19 15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>19 15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>19 <lb/>−25 <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>−25 <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>−25 <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>year <lb/>...cover (treatment − control) <lb/>Functional group <lb/>Graminoids <lb/>Forbs <lb/>B ryophytes <lb/>Fig. 5 Functional group cover in response to removal treatments in the FunCaB plant functional group <lb/>experiment. Difference from unmanipulated control plots (C treatment) over time in the sum of covers of <lb/>graminoids, forbs, and bryophytes in plots where this functional group grows alone (i.e., the FB, GB, and GF <lb/>removal treatments, respectively, see Table 6 for abbreviations). Data from 192 25 × 25 cm experimental plant <lb/>functional group removal plots from 2015 -2019 at twelve sites in the Vestland Climate Grid, Vestland County, <lb/>Norway. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>available in a forthcoming data paper, and they can henceforth be cited to that paper. See Fig. 3 for a description <lb/>of the interrelations and linkage keys among datasets. <lb/>The data are available for use under a CC-BY licence. We appreciate being contacted for advice or collab-<lb/>oration, if relevant, by users of our data. In cases where our data make up &gt;10% of the data used in a down-<lb/>stream publication, we expect that appropriately acknowledging our contributions would require an invitation <lb/>for collaboration. <lb/>Combination and augmentation with existing and new data from the VCG. We note that for plant <lb/>functional group removal biomass (dataset i), soil moisture (dataset iv), plant community (dataset v), carbon flux <lb/>(dataset vii) and reflectance (dataset viii), a final census planned for 2022. These data will be added to 27 and 28 . <lb/>The data presented here relates to a large amount site and block level data from the same sites 35 , the most <lb/>relevant of which are briefly explained under &apos;Background abiotic and biotic data from the Vestland Climate <lb/>Grid&apos; above. Code is provided for linking and downloading the most relevant datasets in the FunCaB github <lb/>repository, with a time-stamper version on Zenodo 28 . See Fig. 2 for a conceptual representation of how these <lb/>datasets are linked via shared variables/keys. <lb/>In connection with a new project, FUNDER (Norwegian Research Council project number 315249, <lb/>2021 -2025), the FunCaB experiment will be augmented with data on the belowground components of the <lb/>plant-soil ecosystem, including roots, mesofauna, fungi and microbes. Plot-level slope, aspect, and soil depth <lb/>will also be measured. These data will link with the FunCaB and VCG project based on the given experimental, <lb/>site and organismal keys, as indicated in Fig. 3. <lb/>The VCG and FUNDER data will be made available in forthcoming data papers. <lb/>Data quality comments and options. The procedures and consequences for data collection, manage-<lb/>ment, and cleaning are detailed in this paper, and the associated code 28 . The code 28 describes and implements <lb/>our suggested data cleaning and checking procedures that result in producing what we consider the clean and <lb/>&apos;best practice&apos; final datasets 27 and the various &apos;flag&apos; , &apos;comment&apos; or&apos;notes&apos; columns in the different dataset tables <lb/>(Tables 2-9) that indicate additional specific data points that could be removed to create even more robust data-<lb/>sets. Users who might prefer stricter or more inclusive data handling strategies should check the flags in the raw <lb/>data sets and adjust the data cleaning accordingly. <lb/>Note that unidentified taxa are not harmonized across datasets (relevant for datasets ii, v, vi; Table 1). <lb/>Also note that dataset ii species-level forb biomass has some blocks where data at the species level is lacking <lb/>(11 cases, out of 48). For these blocks, the forb biomass is provided at the functional group level. <lb/>Dataset vi, seedling recruitment, does not contain any information on the plots that did not have any seed-<lb/>lings. If the user wants a complete dataset with all plots per site, for example for calculating overall seedling <lb/>densities per treatment or site, these missing plots need to be extracted from another dataset, e.g. dataset v, plant <lb/>community composition. <lb/>For dataset vii, ecosystem carbon fluxes, users might want to set more or less restrictive data exclusion thresh-<lb/>olds regarding linear fits of fluxes to include in analysis, and can do so by altering the cleaning code. For example, <lb/>many paired light-dark measurements were deleted due to the quality control of the light measurements. Users <lb/>who are interested in dark measurements only might be interested in accessing the full dark measurements <lb/>dataset available from the raw data available in 27 . If users want to visually inspect individual measurements and <lb/>set their own timeframes the code for running through individual combinations of metadata, logger data and <lb/>temperature data are provided in the OSF. Note that in 2016, some control plots shared with another experiment <lb/>(treatment = TTC) and other graminoid removal plots (treatment = RTC) from another project 35 , see also 42 , <lb/>were also measured. These measurements are found in the FunCaB flux dataset. <lb/></body>
			
			<div type="availability">Code availability <lb/>The code used for checking, cleaning and analysing the data is available in the open GitHub repository https:// <lb/>github.com/Between-the-Fjords/funcab_data, of which a versioned copy is available at Zenodo 54 . <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 21 December 2021; Accepted: 12 July 2022; <lb/>Published: xx xx xxxx <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Steinbauer, M. J. et al. Accelerated increase in plant species richness on mountain summits is linked to warming. Nature 556, <lb/>231-234 (2018). <lb/>2. Walther, G.-R. et al. Ecological responses to recent climate change. Nature 416, 389-395 (2002). <lb/>3. Elmendorf, S. C. et al. Experiment, monitoring, and gradient methods used to infer climate change effects on plant communities <lb/>yield consistent patterns. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 112, 448-452 (2015). <lb/>4. Bardgett, R. D. &amp; Wardle, D. A. Aboveground-belowground linkages: biotic interactions, ecosystem processes, and global change. <lb/>(Oxford University Press, 2010). <lb/>5. Tylianakis, J. M., Didham, R. K., Bascompte, J. &amp; Wardle, D. A. Global change and species interactions in terrestrial ecosystems. Ecol. <lb/>Lett. 11, 1351-1363 (2008). <lb/>6. Berg, M. P. et al. Adapt or disperse: understanding species persistence in a changing world. Global Change Biology 16, 587-598 <lb/>(2010). <lb/>7. Roslin, T. et al. Higher predation risk for insect prey at low latitudes and elevations. Science 356, 742-744 (2017). <lb/>8. Alexander, J. M., Diez, J. M. &amp; Levine, J. M. Novel competitors shape species&apos; responses to climate change. Nature 525, 515-518 <lb/>(2015). <lb/>9. Scafaro, A. P. et al. Responses of leaf respiration to heatwaves. Plant Cell Environ. 44, 2090-2101 (2021). <lb/>10. Lin, Y.-S., Medlyn, B. E. &amp; Ellsworth, D. S. Temperature responses of leaf net photosynthesis: the role of component processes. Tree <lb/>Physiol. 32, 219-231 (2012). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<node place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></node>

			<listBibl>11. Wu, Z., Dijkstra, P., Koch, G. W., Peñuelas, J. &amp; Hungate, B. A. Responses of terrestrial ecosystems to temperature and precipitation <lb/>change: a meta-analysis of experimental manipulation. Glob. Chang. Biol. 17, 927-942 (2011). <lb/>12. Sundqvist, M. K. et al. Responses of tundra plant community carbon flux to experimental warming, dominant species removal and <lb/>elevation. Funct. Ecol. 34, 1497-1506 (2020). <lb/>13. Fanin, N. et al. Effects of plant functional group removal on structure and function of soil communities across contrasting <lb/>ecosystems. Ecology Letters Volume 22, 1095-1103 (2019). <lb/>14. Bar-On, Y. M., Phillips, R. &amp; Milo, R. The biomass distribution on Earth. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 115, 6506-6511 (2018). <lb/>15. Beerling, D. The Emerald Planet: How Plants Changed Earth&apos;s History. (Oxford University Press, 2017). <lb/>16. Bjorkman, A. D. et al. Plant functional trait change across a warming tundra biome. Nature 562, 57-62 (2018). <lb/>17. Elmendorf, S. C. et al. Global assessment of experimental climate warming on tundra vegetation: heterogeneity over space and time. <lb/>Ecol. Lett. 15, 164-175 (2012). <lb/>18. Elmendorf, S. C. et al. Plot-scale evidence of tundra vegetation change and links to recent summer warming. Nat. Clim. Chang. 2, <lb/>453-457 (2012). <lb/>19. Ross, L. C., Woodin, S. J., Hester, A. J., Thompson, D. B. A. &amp; Birks, H. J. B. Biotic homogenization of upland vegetation: patterns and <lb/>drivers at multiple spatial scales over five decades. Journal of Vegetation Science 23, 755-770 (2010). <lb/>20. Klanderud, K. &amp; Totland, Ø. Simulated climate change altered dominance hierarchies and diversity of an alpine biodiversity hotspot. <lb/>Ecology 86, 2047-2054 (2005). <lb/>21. Michel, P., Burritt, D. J. &amp; Lee, W. G. Bryophytes display allelopathic interactions with tree species in native forest ecosystems. Oikos <lb/>120, 1272-1280 (2011). <lb/>22. Soudzilovskaia, N. A. et al. How do bryophytes govern generative recruitment of vascular plants? New Phytol. 190, 1019-1031 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>23. Wardle, D. A. et al. Linking vegetation change, carbon sequestration and biodiversity: insights from island ecosystems in a long-term <lb/>natural experiment. J. Ecol. 100, 16-30 (2012). <lb/>24. Guido, A. &amp; Pillar, V. D. Are removal experiments effective tools for assessing plant community resistance and recovery from <lb/>invasion? J. Veg. Sci. 26, 608-613 (2015). <lb/>25. Artsdatabanken. Norsk rødliste for naturtyper. https://www.artsdatabanken.no/rodlistefornaturtyper (2018). <lb/>26. Bokhorst, S. et al. Variable temperature effects of Open Top Chambers at polar and alpine sites explained by irradiance and snow <lb/>depth. Global Change Biology 19, 64-74 (2013). <lb/>27. Vandvik, V. &amp; the FunCaB Project Team. FunCaB -The role of functional group interactions in mediating climate change impacts <lb/>on the Carbon dynamics and biodiversity of alpine ecosystems, Open Science Framework, https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/4C5V2 <lb/>(2022). <lb/>28. Halbritter A. H. and the FunCaB Data Team. GitHub repository for FunCaB -The role of functional group interactions in mediating <lb/>climate change impacts on the Carbon dynamics and biodiversity of alpine ecosystems. Version 2.1. Available at: github.com. <lb/>29. Halbritter, A. H. et al. The handbook for standardized field and laboratory measurements in terrestrial climate change experiments <lb/>and observational studies (ClimEx). Methods Ecol. Evol. 11, 22-37 (2019). <lb/>30. Wilkinson, M. D. et al. The FAIR Guiding Principles for scientific data management and stewardship. Sci Data 3, 160018 (2016). <lb/>31. Alston, J. M. &amp; Rick, J. A. A beginner&apos;s guide to conducting reproducible research. Bull. Ecol. Soc. Am. 102(2), e01801 (2021). <lb/>32. Hampton, S. E. et al. The Tao of open science for ecology. Ecosphere 6, art120 (2015). <lb/>33. Tveito, O. E., Bjørdal, I., Skjelvåg, A. O. &amp; Aune, B. A GIS-based agro-ecological decision system based on gridded climatology. <lb/>Meteorol. Appl. 12, 57-68 (2005). <lb/>34. Klanderud, K., Vandvik, V. &amp; Goldberg, D. The Importance of Biotic vs. Abiotic Drivers of Local Plant Community Composition <lb/>Along Regional Bioclimatic Gradients. PLoS One 10, e0130205 (2015). <lb/>35. Vandvik, V. &amp; The Vestland Climate Grid and SeedClim Project Teams. Vestland Climate Grid (VCG). Open Science Framework <lb/>https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/NPFA9 (2022). <lb/>36. Fremstad, E. Vegetasjonstyper i Norge. (NINA, Norsk Institutt for Naturforskning, 1998). <lb/>37. Klanderud, K. et al. Vital rates in early life history underlie shifts in biotic interactions along bioclimatic gradients: An experimental <lb/>test of the Stress Gradient Hypothesis. J. Veg. Sci. 32, e13006 (2021). <lb/>38. Vandvik, V., Klanderud, K., Meineri, E., Måren, I. E. &amp; Töpper, J. Seed banks are biodiversity reservoirs: species-area relationships <lb/>above versus below ground. Oikos 125, 218-228 (2016). <lb/>39. Lynn, J. S., Klanderud, K., Telford, R. J., Goldberg, D. &amp; Vandvik, V. Macroecological context predicts species&apos; responses to climate <lb/>warming. Glob. Chang. Biol. 27, 2088-2101 (2021). <lb/>40. Vandvik, V. et al. Biotic rescaling reveals importance of species interactions for variation in biodiversity responses to climate change. <lb/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA (2020). <lb/>41. Guittar, J. et al. Quantifying the roles of seed dispersal, filtering, and climate on regional patterns of grassland biodiversity. Ecology <lb/>e03061 (2020). <lb/>42. Olsen, S. L., Töpper, J. P. &amp; Skarpaas, O. From facilitation to competition: temperature-driven shift in dominant plant interactions <lb/>affects population dynamics in seminatural grasslands. Glob. Chang. Biol. 22, 1915-1926 (2016). <lb/>43. Klanderud, K., Meineri, E., Töpper, J., Michel, P. &amp; Vandvik, V. Biotic interaction effects on seedling recruitment along bioclimatic <lb/>gradients: testing the stress-gradient hypothesis. J. Veg. Sci. 28, 347-356 (2017). <lb/>44. Töpper, J. P. et al. The devil is in the detail: Nonadditive and context-dependent plant population responses to increasing temperature <lb/>and precipitation. Glob. Chang. Biol. 24, 4657-4666 (2018). <lb/>45. Meineri, E., Klanderud, K., Guittar, J., Goldberg, D. E. &amp; Vandvik, V. Functional traits, not productivity, predict alpine plant <lb/>community openness to seedling recruitment under climatic warming. Oikos 129, 13-23 (2019). <lb/>46. Keuskamp, J. A., Dingemans, B. J. J., Lehtinen, T., Sarneel, J. M. &amp; Hefting, M. M. Tea Bag Index: a novel approach to collect uniform <lb/>decomposition data across ecosystems. Methods Ecol. Evol. 4, 1070-1075 (2013). <lb/>47. Althuizen, I. H. J., Lee, H., Sarneel, J. M. &amp; Vandvik, V. Long-Term Climate Regime Modulates the Impact of Short-Term Climate <lb/>Variability on Decomposition in Alpine Grassland Soils. Ecosystems 21, 1580-1592 (2018). <lb/>48. Skarpaas, O., Meineri, E., Bargmann, T. &amp; Pötsch, C. Biomass partitioning in grassland plants along independent gradients in <lb/>temperature and precipitation. Perspect. Plant Ecol. Evol. Syst. 19, 1-11 (2016). <lb/>49. Meineri, E., Skarpaas, O. &amp; Spindelböck, J. Direct and size-dependent effects of climate on flowering performance in alpine and <lb/>lowland herbaceous species. J. Veg. Sci. 25, 275-286 (2014). <lb/>50. Meineri, E., Spindelböck, J. &amp; Vandvik, V. Seedling emergence responds to both seed source and recruitment site climates: a climate <lb/>change experiment combining transplant and gradient approaches. Plant Ecol. 214, 607-619 (2013). <lb/>51. Pérez-Harguindeguy, N. et al. New handbook for standardised measurement of plant functional traits worldwide. Aust. J. Bot. 61, <lb/>167-234 (2013). <lb/>52. Gya, R. The role of intraspecific variability in driving community trait shifts along temperature and precipitation gradients in alpine <lb/>and boreal semi-natural grasslands. (The University of Bergen, 2017). <lb/>53. Lid, J. &amp; Lid, D. T. Norsk flora (Norwegian flora). Oslo: Samlaget (2005). <lb/>54. Halbritter, A. H. &amp; The FunCaB Project Team. Between-the-Fjords/funcab_data: Publish FunCaB data paper, Zenodo https://doi. <lb/>org/10.5281/zenodo.6752847 (2022). <lb/>55. CRediT -Contributor Roles Taxonomy. https://casrai.org/credit/ (2019). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:451 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01559-0 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">acknowledgements <lb/>This research was conducted in the 12 sites of the Vestland Climate Grid, and we would like to thank the <lb/>landowners for permission to established and maintain the experiments on their lands. The FunCaB project <lb/>&apos;The role of Functional group interactions in mediating climate change impacts on the Carbon dynamics and <lb/>Biodiversity of alpine ecosystems&apos; was funded by the Research Council of Norway KLIMAFORSK program, <lb/>project number 244525 (2015 -2019). The research sites and VCG data collection has been funded by the <lb/>Research Council of Norway under the projects SEEDCLIM: NORKLIMA project number 184912 (2008 -2015), <lb/>INCLINE FRIMEDBIO project number 274712 (2018 -2022), and EMERALD: KLIMAFORSK project number <lb/>294948 (2019 -2022). Student internships were funded under the Research Council of Norway projects RECITE <lb/>INTPART project number 274831 (2018 -2021), ExperTS: INTPART project number 287784 (2019 -2022), <lb/>and the Centre for Internationalisation in Education (SIU) project TraitTrain: SIU project HNP-2015/10037 <lb/>(2016 -2018). We acknowledge a covid-19 infection (v. Delta) affecting VV and thereby providing the isolated <lb/>time necessary to write this manuscript, in lieu of the otherwise required long-distance flight. The following <lb/>people assisted with field and lab work: Terezie Novakova, Vojtěch Škara, Tabea Galusser, Alba Tousfandos, Linn <lb/>Vassvik, Kari Elva Aarvik, Dan from America, Amund Skogrand, Maja Ugrin, Emilia Meneses-Reyes, Aynhoa <lb/>Gomez, Arild Breistøl, Olav V. Skogrand, Ingrid Toresen, Ardian Høgøy Abaz, Nataniel Nesse, Frida Klubb, <lb/>Kristina Svare Toby Santamaria, Peter Petrik, David Escobar Cruz, Anja Petek, Loushu He, Elisabeth Bergman, <lb/>William Erazo Garcia, Jesslyn Tjendra, Lucely Vilca Bustamante, Sára Nagy, Kengo Mieda, Betsabe Kuan, Daiki <lb/>Koga, Vincent Zimmermann, Philippine Surer, Eira Rønneberg, Alexander Vågenes, Leire Campos, Emma Little, <lb/>Maryam Kazemi, Morgane Demeaux, Regine Gulbrandsen, Eliska Suchoparova, Julie Eriksen, and Jana Rüthers. <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="annex">author contributions <lb/>We follow the CreDiT taxonomy 55 , and recognize the following author contributions, Conceptualization (co), <lb/>Data curation (da), Formal analysis (fo), Funding acquisition (fu), Investigation (in), Methodology (me), Project <lb/>administration (pr), Resources (re), Software (so), Supervision (su), Validation (va), Visualization (vi), Writing <lb/>-original draft (wo), and Writing -review &amp; editing (wr), as follows: V.V. (co, fu, in, me, pr, re, su, wo), F.J. and <lb/>I.H.J.A. (da, fo, in, me, va, vi, wr), D.E.G., H.L., K.K. and S.L.O. (co, fu, me, re, su, wr), R.J.T. (da, fo, me, re, su, va, <lb/>wr), L.C.K. (in, pr, va, wr), S.R.G. (da, in, me, wr), D.D.E. and S.A.H.Ö. (in, pr, wr), E.M., I.D., J.S.L., R.G., S.B. and <lb/>S.Y. (in, wr), and A.H.H. (da, fo, me, pr, re, su, va, vi, wo). <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>Open access funding provided by University of Bergen. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>additional information <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to V.V. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/>

			Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2022 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
