<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Helicobacter pylori infection and increased <lb/>diabetes prevalence were the risks of colorectal <lb/>adenoma for adults <lb/>A systematic review and meta-analysis (PRISMA-compliant <lb/>article) <lb/>Hung-Ju Ko, Ms a,b , Ying-Chun Lin, MD c,d , Chieh-Chang Chen, MD e , Ming-Jen Chen, MD b,f , <lb/>Ming-Shiang Wu, MD, PhD e , Chun-Jen Liu, MD, PhD e , Chun-Ta Huang, MD g , Horng-Woei Yang, PhD h , <lb/>Shou-Chuan Shih, MD a,b,f,i , Lo-Yip Yu, MD a,b,f , Yang-Che Kuo a,b,f , Horng-Yuan Wang, MD b,f , <lb/>Kuang-Chun Hu, MD, PhD a,b,f,i, * <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: Helicobacter pylori infection and hyperglycemia are associated with an increased risk of colorectal neoplasm, and <lb/>may have a synergistic effect in combination. However, these 2 factors that affect colorectal neoplasm remain controversial. We <lb/>aimed to carry out a meta-analysis to evaluate the study population diabetes prevalence rate and H pylori infection rate with colorectal <lb/>adenoma risk for adults. <lb/>Methods: We conducted systemic research through English databases for medical reports. We also recorded the diabetes <lb/>prevalence and H pylori infection prevalence in each study. We classified these studies into 4 subgroups as their background <lb/>population diabetes prevalence &lt;6% (Group 1); between 6% and 8% (Group 2); between 8% and 10% (Group 3), and more than <lb/>10% (Group 4). The random-effects model had used to calculate pooled prevalence estimates with 95% confidence interval (CI). <lb/>Results: Twenty-seven studies were finally eligible for meta-analysis. The random-effects model of the meta-analysis was chosen, <lb/>showing pooled odds ratio (OR) equal to 1.51 (95% CI 1.39-1.63). The subgroup meta-analyses showed in Group 1 the H pylori <lb/>infection associated colorectal adenoma risk OR was 1.24 (95% CI 0.86-1.78). As the diabetes rate exceed 6%, the H pylori infection <lb/>became the more significant increased risk of colorectal adenoma (Group 2: OR 2.16 (95% CI 1.61-2.91); Group 3: OR 1.40 (95% CI <lb/>1.24-1.57); and Group 4: OR 1.52 (95% CI 1.46-1.57)). <lb/>Conclusions: The results of this meta-analysis showed elevated diabetes prevalence combined H pylori infection increasing the <lb/>risks of colorectal adenoma in the adult population. <lb/>Editor: Maya Saranathan. <lb/>The authors have read the PRISMA 2009 Checklist, and the manuscript was prepared and revised according to the PRISMA 2009 Checklist. The registration number: <lb/>CRD42020199442. <lb/>MMH-110-34. The funding was provided by Department of Medical Research, Mackay Memorial Hospital and MOST-109-2314-B-195-007 from the Ministry of <lb/>Science and Technology, for encouraging members to carry out clinical studies. After reviewing the proposals and approving the promising studies, the funding body <lb/>will not intervene in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing the manuscript in any way. <lb/>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. <lb/>The data supporting this systematic review and meta-analysis are from previously reported studies and datasets, which have been cited. The processed data are <lb/>available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request. The protocol of this meta-analysis has been registered with PROSPERO (no. CRD42020199442). <lb/>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article [and its supplementary information files]. The datasets generated during and/or <lb/>analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. Data sharing not applicable to this article as no datasets were <lb/>generated or analyzed during the current study. <lb/>a Healthy Evaluation Center, MacKay Memorial Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan, b MacKay Junior College of Medicine, Nursing, and Management, Taipei, Taiwan, c Department <lb/>of Anesthesia, MacKay Memorial Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan, d Institute of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine, College of Public Health, National Taiwan University, <lb/>e Department of Internal Medicine, National Taiwan University Hospital, National Taiwan University College of Medicine, Taipei, Taiwan, f Division of Gastroenterology, <lb/>Department of Internal Medicine, MacKay Memorial Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan Healthy, g Division of Endocrine, Department of Internal Medicine, DM Center, MacKay <lb/>Memorial Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan, h Departments of Medical Research, MacKay Memorial Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan, i MacKay Medical College, Taipei, Taiwan. <lb/> * <lb/>Correspondence: Kuang-Chun Hu, Division of Gastroenterology, Department of Internal Medicine, Healthy Evaluation Center, MacKay Memorial Hospital, No. 92, Sec. <lb/>2, Chung-Shan North Road, Taipei, Taiwan (e-mail: mimiandbear2001@yahoo.com.tw). <lb/>Copyright © 2021 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. <lb/>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC), where it is permissible to <lb/>download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission from the journal. <lb/>How to cite this article: Ko HJ, Lin YC, Chen CC, Chen MJ, Wu MS, Liu CJ, Huang CT, Yang HW, Shih SC, Yu LY, Kuo YC, Wang HY, Hu KC. Helicobacter pylori <lb/>infection and increased diabetes prevalence were the risks of colorectal adenoma for adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis (PRISMA-compliant article). <lb/>Medicine 2021;100:50(e28156). <lb/>Received: 22 October 2020 / Received in final form: 15 November 2021 / Accepted: 18 November 2021 <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000028156 <lb/>Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis <lb/>Medicine ® <lb/>OPEN <lb/>1 <lb/>Abbreviations: CIs = confidence intervals, CLO = Campylobacter-like organism test, CRC = colorectal carcinoma, DM = <lb/>diabetes mellitus, H pylori = Helicobacter pylori, HbA 1c = glycosylated hemoglobin, IL = interleukin, OR = odds ratio, UBT = urea <lb/>breath test. <lb/>Keywords: colorectal adenoma, diabetes prevalence, Helicobacter pylori <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Helicobacter pylori is a Gram-negative bacterium that has <lb/>infected almost 50% of the world&apos;s population. [1] Since 1994, H <lb/>pylori has been recognized as a human carcinogen by the <lb/>International Agency for Research on Cancer due to its strong <lb/>correlation with gastric cancer. [2] Except for intragastric <lb/>malignancy disease, many scientists have noted that this <lb/>bacterium is also related to colon neoplasms and colorectal <lb/>carcinoma (CRC) formation and have shown that infection with <lb/>H pylori confers a 1.3-to 1.97-fold increased risk of colon <lb/>adenoma or adenoma with high-grade dysplasia in the past 2 <lb/>decades. [3-5] However, some Asian studies did not show <lb/>consistent results. Early studies showed that H pylori infection <lb/>may have a trend of increased colon adenoma but no significant <lb/>difference. [6,7] Recent studies have demonstrated a positive <lb/>association between H pylori infection and colon adenoma <lb/>formation. [8,9] In these studies, Sonnenberg and Genta [3] <lb/>established the largest study, which included 156,000 patients, <lb/>and showed that H pylori gastritis was positively associated with <lb/>colon adenomas (odds ratio [OR] = 1.52). Even with this <lb/>impressive study result, Plummer also commented and queried <lb/>several key points. [10] The most important question that needs to <lb/>be answered is how to explain why some areas had a high <lb/>prevalence of H pylori infection but a low CRC risk. Several <lb/>meta-analysis studies have shown that H pylori infection <lb/>increases the risk of colorectal neoplasm formation. [11-13] <lb/>However, these studies did not address Plummer query. <lb/>Diabetes mellitus type 2 (DM) is one of the most common <lb/>metabolic disorders in the world, and the prevalence of DM has <lb/>been increasing quickly in recent decades. [14] The prevalence of <lb/>DM also has significant regional variability. According to the <lb/>latest report, the highest prevalence of DM was found in North <lb/>America and the Caribbean region, and the prevalence in this <lb/>region was approximately 11.0%. The Western Pacific region <lb/>(including Australia, China, Indonesia, Japan, Taiwan, Korea, <lb/>and Vietnam) has a DM prevalence of approximately 8.1%. [15] <lb/>However, as socioeconomic growth and industrialization are <lb/>rapidly occurring in this area, the increasing prevalence of <lb/>diabetes was also noted in these countries. [16] DM is also <lb/>considered a risk factor for colon adenoma and carcinoma. <lb/>Several studies have shown that subjects with DM had an OR of <lb/>1.45 for colon adenoma and a relative risk of 1.38 for colorectal <lb/>adenocarcinoma. [17,18] Our previous study demonstrated that <lb/>combined hyperglycemia and H pylori infection was involved in <lb/>colon adenoma formation and had a synergistic effect. [19] The <lb/>risk of colorectal adenoma might decrease after H pylori is <lb/>successfully eradicated. [20] This means that hyperglycemia and <lb/>H pylori infection might interact and affect colorectal adenoma <lb/>formation. <lb/>Therefore, we carried out a systematic review and meta-<lb/>analysis of published studies to evaluate the association between <lb/>H pylori infection and colorectal adenoma formation. Further-<lb/>more, we surveyed the DM prevalence in each published study as <lb/>a subgroup analysis and tried to determine the relationship <lb/>between H pylori infection and DM prevalence in the risk of <lb/>colon adenoma formation. We tried to use different DM <lb/>prevalence rates to classify subgroups of these studies to answer <lb/>Plummer question and discuss the relationship between the DM <lb/>prevalence rate and H pylori infection involvement in colorectal <lb/>adenoma formation. <lb/>2. Materials and methods <lb/>2.1. Data sources and searches <lb/>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-<lb/>analyses statement guidelines were followed for conducting and <lb/>reporting meta-analysis data. The participants, intervnetions, <lb/>comparison, outcomes, and study design scheme was followed <lb/>for reporting inclusion criteria. A systematic search was <lb/>conducted using PubMed/MEDLINE, EMBASE, and the <lb/>Cochrane Library for medical reports published until the end <lb/>of August 2020 without language or date restrictions. The <lb/>following search terms were used: &quot;Helicobacter pylori&quot; AND <lb/>(&quot;colorectal OR &quot;colonic&quot; OR &quot;colon&quot; OR &quot;large intestine&quot;) <lb/>AND (&quot;neoplasms&quot; OR &quot;polyp&quot; OR &quot;adenoma&quot; OR &quot;cancer&quot;). <lb/>Abstracts of articles from the literature search were individually <lb/>evaluated independently for possible inclusion by the 3 authors <lb/>(CMJ, WMS, and YHW). For all databases, the last search was <lb/>run on 3 September 2020. The study protocol was registered in <lb/>PROSPERO (CRD42020199442). <lb/>2.2. Study selection <lb/>The eligible studies enrolled in the meta-analysis satisfied the <lb/>following criteria: (i) English-language abstract; (ii) full manu-<lb/>script publication; (iii) study design: clinical trials including <lb/>cohort studies, cross-sectional studies, and case-control studies; <lb/>(iv) reported OR estimates with corresponding 95% confidence <lb/>intervals (CIs) for the relationship between H pylori and <lb/>colorectal adenoma or provided sufficient raw data to calculate <lb/>crude ORs and 95% CIs; and (v) results: the prevalence of <lb/>patients with colorectal adenoma due to H pylori infection or the <lb/>risk of colorectal adenoma in H pylori infection. Studies were <lb/>excluded if they (i) reported duplicate results that were published <lb/>in other articles, (ii) investigated only the gastrin level or the <lb/>recurrence of colorectal neoplasia, or (iii) included a pediatric <lb/>population. <lb/>2.3. Data extraction <lb/>Three reviewers (CCC, LCJ, and SSC) independently extracted <lb/>data using a predefined form, and disagreements were resolved by <lb/>discussion and consensus. Information was collected in each <lb/>selected study as possible, concerning first author, publication <lb/>year, research type, publication type, the number of subjects, the <lb/>country of origin, the prevalence of DM rate of origin, the <lb/>matching variables, the location of neoplasia, the H pylori <lb/>detection method, the sample characteristics (age and sex), the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ko et al. Medicine (2021) 100:50 <lb/>Medicine <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>reported OR for colorectal adenoma with 95% CIs, and the <lb/>covariates adjusted for in the analysis. <lb/>2.4. Statistical analysis <lb/>Three reviewers (LYC, YLY, and KHJ) independently assessed <lb/>the quality of all eligible studies using the risk of bias in non-<lb/>randomized studies of interventions scale. The ORs were <lb/>collected for analysis. Heterogeneity between studies was <lb/>assessed using both the x 2 test with a P value &lt;.10 and <lb/>inconsistency index (I 2 ) with a cutoff of 50%. Pooled effects with <lb/>95% CIs were derived using a fixed-effect model unless <lb/>significant heterogeneity was present, in which case a random-<lb/>effects model was applied. When a study provided different OR <lb/>estimates based on hospital-based controls and population-based <lb/>controls, the latter estimates were selected for the combined <lb/>analysis. We also calculated and presented a summary of the <lb/>adjusted ORs for the studies that provided adjusted results. <lb/>Publication bias was evaluated with a funnel plot and Egger test. <lb/>We examined the roles of several potential sources of <lb/>heterogeneity using restricted maximum likelihood-based ran-<lb/>dom-effects meta-regression analysis and subgroup analyses <lb/>according to geographic location, prevalence of diabetes (DM) <lb/>rate, the prevalence of H pylori infection rate, study design, the <lb/>sample size for the cases, subsite of the neoplasia, H pylori <lb/>detection method and sex. The estimated DM prevalence rate of <lb/>each study was referenced from the International Diabetes <lb/>Federation Atlas and local country government data or study <lb/>results (by WHY and HCT). We used the mean year of study <lb/>duration as the DM prevalence rate. According to the diabetes <lb/>prevalence rate of the study population, we classified the studies <lb/>into 4 groups: Group 1: DM prevalence &lt;6%; Group 2: DM <lb/>prevalence from 6% to 8%, Group 3: DM prevalence from 8% to <lb/>10%; and Group 4: DM prevalence &gt;10%. Statistical analyses <lb/>were performed by STATA version 11.0 (STATA Corporation, <lb/>College Station, TX, USA) and RevMan version 5.3 (The <lb/>Cochrane Collaboration, Oxford, UK). <lb/>2.5. Ethical statements <lb/>No ethical approval is required since this is a literature-based <lb/>study. <lb/>3. Results <lb/>3.1. Search results and study characteristics <lb/>After initial screening, the full text of 281 potentially eligible <lb/>articles was retrieved for detailed assessment, and 27 studies were <lb/>eligible for analysis. [3,6,8,9,19,21-42] All of the eligible studies <lb/>presented OR for colorectal adenoma related to H pylori <lb/>infection. [3,6,8,9,19,21-42] Nineteen of them are cross-sectional <lb/>studies, [3,6,8,19,21-24,25-28,30,31,35,37-40] and the remaining 8 are <lb/>case-control studies. [9,29,32-34,36,41,42] Serology was utilized as <lb/>the detection method for H pylori in 14 studies, [8,9,21,23,25-27,31-<lb/>35,38,39] pathology in 4, [3,22,40,42] urea breath test (UBT) in 4, [6,37] <lb/>Campylobacter-like organism test (CLO) in 6, [19,24,30,36] and <lb/>combining UBT and CLO in 2. [28,29] Gender and age are reported <lb/>in 22 [3,6,8,9,19,21-30,34-40] and 27 [3,6,8,9,19,21-35,37-39,41,42] studies, <lb/>respectively. Most studies were carried out in Asia (7 in Korea, 3 <lb/>in Taiwan, 3 in Japan, 1 in Thailand, and 1 in China) and the <lb/>remaining in the Americas (5 in the United States of America and <lb/>1 in Brazil) and in Europe (2 in Germany, 1 in Turkey, 1 in <lb/>Greece, and 1 in Israel). All included studies had assessed the <lb/>quality of all eligible studies using the risk of bias in non-<lb/>randomized studies of interventions scale and no serious risk of <lb/>bias after survey (in Appendix). <lb/>A flow chart describing the process of study selection is <lb/>shown in Figure 1. For the meta-analysis, data were extracted <lb/>from 27 studies with a total of 68,410 patients, and the pooled <lb/>OR for colorectal adenoma related to H pylori infection was <lb/>1.51 (95% CI 1.39-1.63), although there was significant <lb/>heterogeneity (P &lt; .001) (Table 1 and Fig. 2). Because of <lb/>geographic and time differences in DM prevalence rate, [14,43-51] <lb/>subgroup analysis for the studies was performed by classifying <lb/>them into 4 groups: Group 1: DM prevalence &lt;6%; Group 2: <lb/>DM prevalence from 6% to 8%, Group 3: DM prevalence from <lb/>8% to 10%, and Group 4: DM prevalence &gt;10% (Table 1 and <lb/>Fig. 2). <lb/>In the subgroup analysis, the background population DM <lb/>prevalence &lt;6% studies had 3 studies with a total of 886 <lb/>patients. Meta-analysis of these studies revealed that the H pylori-<lb/>infected patients have an increased risk of having colorectal <lb/>adenoma with a pooled OR of 1.24 (95% CI 0.86-1.78) but no <lb/>significant difference. There was no significant heterogeneity <lb/>in Group 1 studies (P = .279). Since the study background <lb/>population DM prevalence increased more than 6%, the <lb/>H pylori-infected patients have a significantly increased risk of <lb/>having colorectal adenoma. This upturn was more significant <lb/>when the background population DM prevalence was approxi-<lb/>mately 6% to 8%. After a meta-analysis of these studies, the <lb/>H pylori-infected people had a higher risk of colorectal adenoma <lb/>than noninfected people. The pooled OR was 2.16 (95% CI <lb/>1.61-2.91), and a total of 11,655 patients were included. In these <lb/>studies, Lin study noted the DM prevalence in his study <lb/>participants, and males had an 8.1% prevalence of DM, and <lb/>females had a 6.1% prevalence of DM. Due to Lin study <lb/>population, 6.94% of patients had DM and were thus classified <lb/>into Group 2 for subgroup analysis. There was significant <lb/>heterogeneity in the Group 2 studies (P &lt; .01) <lb/>In Groups 3 and 4, similar results were observed. Compared to <lb/>that of Group 2 studies, the pooled OR of Groups 3 and 4 was <lb/>mildly decreased but still had a significantly elevated risk of <lb/>colorectal adenoma in H pylori-infected patients. For the <lb/>H pylori-infected patients, the risk of colorectal adenoma in <lb/>Group 3 was 1.40 (95% CI 1.24-1.57), and the Group 4 OR <lb/>was 1.52 (95% CI 1.46-1.57). The Group 3 studies included <lb/>28,431 patients, and the heterogeneity across studies was <lb/>marginal (I 2 = 58.6%, P = .013). There were 27,438 participants <lb/>included in Group 4 studies, and there was no significant <lb/>heterogeneity (I 2 = 0.0%, P = .704). We also checked other <lb/>variables, including gender, detection methods of H pylori <lb/>infection, and study designs, and there was no evidence of <lb/>statistical relevance to OR for adenoma with H pylori infection. <lb/>3.2. Test of heterogeneity and publication bias <lb/>Heterogeneity was assessed by chi-square and I-square for the <lb/>included studies. The value of x 2 was &lt;0.01, and the I 2 was <lb/>61.9%. Due to the heterogeneity noted in our analysis, a random-<lb/>effects model was used. The shape of the funnel plots for studies <lb/>on the association between H pylori infection and the risk of <lb/>colorectal adenoma appeared asymmetrical (Fig. 3A), which <lb/>indicated that studies with positive correlation are reported more <lb/>often. The P-value for Egger linear regression method (P &lt; .01) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ko et al. Medicine (2021) 100:50 <lb/>www.md-journal.com <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>suggested that there was statistical evidence of publication bias <lb/>(Fig. 3B). <lb/>4. Discussion <lb/>Since the discovery of H pylori as a cause of peptic ulcer disease <lb/>in 1983, this bacterial infection continues to be a major public <lb/>health issue worldwide. The prevalence of H pylori infection <lb/>varies by geographic area, age, ethnicity, and socioeconomic <lb/>status; in fact, the prevalence is higher in developing countries <lb/>and in those in poor socioeconomic conditions. [52] Traditionally, <lb/>Western and Eastern countries have different H pylori infection <lb/>rates in their general populations. The prevalence is highest in <lb/>Africa (79.1%), Latin America, and Asia (54.7%). On the other <lb/>hand, the H pylori infection rate is lowest in Northern America <lb/>(37.1%) and Oceania (24.4%). [53,54] <lb/>As an infectious disease, H pylori can be cured with a course of <lb/>antibiotics and its infection rate decreased due to public health <lb/>improvement in developed countries and some developing <lb/>countries. However, as the prevalence rate of H pylori infection <lb/>remains high in most developing countries and is generally related <lb/>to socioeconomic status, it remains one of the most important <lb/>diseases in these areas. [54] Hong et al. published a meta-analysis <lb/>of H pylori infection and increased the risk of colorectal adenoma <lb/>formation. In this study, he focused on Eastern or Western studies <lb/>for subgroup analysis and found that the ORs of these 2 groups <lb/>were similar. [25] This means that even the H pylori infection <lb/>prevalence was different in Eastern and Western countries, and <lb/>this bacterial infection still increased colorectal adenoma <lb/>formation. Although the detailed mechanism of the relation <lb/>between H pylori infection and colorectal adenoma formation <lb/>was not clear. Butt and Epplein stated H pylori infection might <lb/>contribute to colorectal carcinogenesis by direct or indirect effect. <lb/>In direct effect, H pylori might secrete toxins and present in the <lb/>respective colorectal tissue. On the other hand, the indirect effect <lb/>included several hypotheses. First, H pylori infection could lead <lb/>to changes in the colonization of the gut with other bacteria and <lb/>then could induce colorectal carcinogenesis. Second, the gastrin <lb/>level might increase after H pylori infection and gastrin might act <lb/>as a mitogen. Third, H pylori was found to be associated with <lb/>metabolic diseases that are associated with CRC risk. [55] It also <lb/>hints at a link between H pylori infection and colorectal adenoma <lb/>formation, which may be due to the third factor in this <lb/>connection. <lb/>Records idenƟfied through <lb/>database searching <lb/>(n = 349) <lb/>Screening <lb/>Included <lb/>Eligibility <lb/>IdenƟficaƟon <lb/>AddiƟonal records idenƟfied <lb/>through other sources <lb/>(n = 59) <lb/>Records aŌer duplicates removed <lb/>(n = 241) <lb/>Records screened <lb/>(n = 241) <lb/>Records excluded (n = 157) <lb/>Not targeted arƟcle types (n = 45) <lb/>Topic unrelated to our study (n = 95) <lb/>Animal studies (n = 7) <lb/>No English or Chinese abstract (n = 10) <lb/>Full-text arƟcles assessed <lb/>for eligibility <lb/>(n = 119) <lb/>Full-text arƟcles excluded, with reasons (n = 92) <lb/>Not targeted arƟcle types (n = 7) <lb/>Topic unrelated to our study (n = 43) <lb/>Included pediatric paƟents (n = 3) <lb/>Duplicate reports on the same study populaƟon (n = 4) <lb/>Focus on malignancy (n = 22) <lb/>Focus on gastrin level (n = 5) <lb/>Focus on paƟents with specific genotype (n = 1) <lb/>Study recurrence colorectal adenomas (n = 1) <lb/>Full-text not available (n = 3) <lb/>Duplicate studies (n = 2) <lb/>Unable to retrieve data (n = 1) <lb/>Studies included in <lb/>qualitaƟve synthesis <lb/>(n = 27) <lb/>Studies included in <lb/>quanƟtaƟve synthesis <lb/>(meta-analysis) <lb/>(n = 27) <lb/>Figure 1. Flow diagram of the studies identified in this meta-analysis. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ko et al. Medicine (2021) 100:50 <lb/>Medicine <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Unlike H pylori infection disease, the prevalence of DM in the <lb/>global world has persisted. The age-standardized DM prevalence <lb/>increased from 4.3% in 1980 to 9.0% in 2014 in men and from <lb/>5.0% to 7.9% in women. [56] The rise in prevalence might be due <lb/>to population growth and aging, as the number of adults with <lb/>diabetes has increased nearly 4-fold over the past 35 years. The <lb/>prevalence and number of adults with diabetes both increased <lb/>and doubled in men and increased by 60% in women worldwide, <lb/>shifting from an excess prevalence in women in 1980 to a higher <lb/>male prevalence in 2014. [57] Persistent high blood sugar <lb/>concentrations lead to damage to the blood vessels and peripheral <lb/>nerves. This situation might result in an increased risk of <lb/>cardiovascular diseases, such as heart attack and stroke, kidney <lb/>disease, diabetic retinopathy, and foot amputations. [58] DM is <lb/>also considered an increased risk factor for colon adenoma and <lb/>carcinoma. [59] These DM-related complications lead to higher <lb/>costs for the health care system, [60] as well as lower quality of life <lb/>and reduced life expectancy. [61] <lb/>Although, a past study showed that DM prevalence was low in <lb/>much of Asia and sub-Saharan Africa in the 1980s and 1990s, [62] <lb/>recent reports have demonstrated an increase in China, India, <lb/>Turkey, and Saudi Arabia. [63-66] Some high-income English-<lb/>speaking countries, such as the USA and the United King-<lb/>dom, [44,67] also reported increased DM prevalence. On the other <lb/>hand, DM prevalence did not increase in Western Europe, like <lb/>Sweden, Germany, and Switzerland. [68,69] In accordance with a <lb/>previous statement and based on geographical distribution, the <lb/>prevalence of H pylori infection and DM seems to be inversely <lb/>related. In our study, when the background population DM <lb/>prevalence was below 6%, H pylori infection did not significantly <lb/>increase the risk of colorectal adenoma formation (Group 1). <lb/>This association became significant when the study population <lb/>DM prevalence was over 6% (Groups 2-4). The odds ratio of <lb/>H pylori infection-related colorectal formation was 2.16 (95% CI <lb/>1.61-2.91); it was the highest when the population DM <lb/>prevalence was from 6% to 8% (Group 2). However, when <lb/>the DM prevalence rate was elevated to 8% to 10% or more than <lb/>10% (Groups 3 and 4), the OR was mildly decreased to 1.40 <lb/>(95% CI 1.24-1.57) and 1.52 (95% CI 1.46-1.57). H pylori <lb/>infection still significantly increased colorectal adenoma but was <lb/>not distinct from Group 2 (DM prevalence between 6% and 8%). <lb/>However, when DM prevalence increased, H pylori infection <lb/>might increase the risk of colorectal adenoma formation. <lb/>The cause of this condition may be related to the study period <lb/>and location. Most studies in Group 2 were carried out from <lb/>1996 to 2000, and Group 3 studies were carried out from 2000 to <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Demographics and outcome characteristics of included Groups 1 to 4 studies. <lb/>First author <lb/>Study <lb/>duration <lb/>Study <lb/>location <lb/>Study <lb/>design <lb/>H. pylori <lb/>detection <lb/>Sample <lb/>size <lb/>Mean age <lb/>(years) <lb/> * <lb/>Gender <lb/>(% male) <lb/>Odds <lb/>ratio † 95% CI <lb/>H pylori <lb/>infection <lb/>rate (%) <lb/>Estimate DM <lb/>prevalence <lb/>(%) ‡ <lb/>DM <lb/>prevalence <lb/>Reference Reference <lb/>Group 1 (DM prevalence &lt; 6%) <lb/>Siddheshwar RK <lb/>1997-1999 UK <lb/>Cross-section <lb/>Serology <lb/>236 <lb/>62.21 (10-94) <lb/>44.92 <lb/>1.08 0.58-1.99 35.5 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>49 <lb/>27 <lb/>Liou JM <lb/>2005 <lb/>Taiwan <lb/>Cross-section UBT(C13) <lb/>462 <lb/>49.97 0.74 <lb/>57.79 <lb/>1.06 0.69-1.62 53.9 <lb/>5.56 <lb/>46 <lb/>6 <lb/>Buso AG <lb/>2005-2007 Brazil <lb/>Case-control Serology <lb/>188 <lb/>59.79 12.25 <lb/>46.88 <lb/>1.98 0.82-3.15 71.2 <lb/>5.8 <lb/>45 <lb/>34 <lb/>Group 2 (DM prevalence: 6%-8%) <lb/>Lin YL <lb/>2004-2006 Taiwan <lb/>Cross-section CLO test <lb/>9311 <lb/>52.84 x <lb/>41.95 1.366 1.23-1.517 <lb/>53.9 <lb/>6.94 <lb/>24 <lb/>24 <lb/>Georgopoulos S. D 2000-2001 Greece <lb/>Case-control Serology <lb/>156 <lb/>64.25 (37-80) <lb/>NA <lb/>1.83 0.88-3.78 <lb/>52.1 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>51 <lb/>33 <lb/>Fujimori S <lb/>1996-2003 Japan <lb/>Cross-section UBT and CLO <lb/>669 <lb/>61.08 9.57 <lb/>70.25 1.6 <lb/>1.18-2.12 <lb/>51.7 <lb/>7.07 <lb/>50 <lb/>28 <lb/>Inoue <lb/>1996-2004 Japan <lb/>Case-control Serology <lb/>478 <lb/>49.7 4.11 <lb/>100 <lb/>2.26 1.44-3.55 <lb/>51.7 <lb/>7.07 <lb/>50 <lb/>9 <lb/>Shmuely, H <lb/>2008-2010 Israel <lb/>Cross-section Serology <lb/>273 <lb/>64.5 12.30 <lb/>NA <lb/>4.07 2.26-7.35 <lb/>68.9 <lb/>7.1 <lb/>47 <lb/>31 <lb/>Aydin A <lb/>1996-1997 Turkey <lb/>Cross-section Serology <lb/>267 <lb/>49.13 22.61 <lb/>45.32 2.63 1.26-5.48 <lb/>77.2 <lb/>7.2 <lb/>48 <lb/>26 <lb/>Breuer-Katschinski 1993-1996 Germany Case-control Serology <lb/>196 <lb/>62.4 9.08 <lb/>NA <lb/>2.1 <lb/>1.1-3.9 <lb/>35.3 <lb/>7.2 <lb/>52 <lb/>32 <lb/>Mizuno <lb/>2005 <lb/>Japan <lb/>Cross-section Serology <lb/>305 <lb/>59.8 2.26 <lb/>57.33 3.4 <lb/>1.9-6.08 <lb/>51.7 <lb/>7.45 <lb/>43 <lb/>21 <lb/>Group 3 (DM prevalence: 8% -10%) <lb/>Tongtawee T <lb/>2014-2015 Thailand Cross-section Pathology <lb/>303 <lb/>NA <lb/>38.28 7.29 2.74-19.36 <lb/>43.6 <lb/>8 <lb/>52 <lb/>40 <lb/>Bae RC <lb/>2005-2008 Korea <lb/>Case-control UBT and CLO <lb/>346 <lb/>54.1 10.50 <lb/>74.57 1.037 0.67-1.59 <lb/>54.0 <lb/>8.6 <lb/>45 <lb/>29 <lb/>Kim TJ <lb/>2002-2010 Korea <lb/>Cross-section Serology <lb/>8916 <lb/>51.6 7.9 <lb/>100.00 1.37 1.18-1.58 <lb/>54.0 <lb/>8.6 <lb/>45 <lb/>35 <lb/>Nam JH <lb/>2007-2009 Korea <lb/>Case-control CLO <lb/>4466 <lb/>NA <lb/>53.63 1.28 1.11 -1.47 <lb/>54.0 <lb/>8.6 <lb/>45 <lb/>36 <lb/>Lee JY <lb/>2012-2013 Korea <lb/>Cross-section Serology <lb/>6351 <lb/>51.7 8.1 <lb/>52.79 1.28 1.09-1.36 <lb/>54.0 <lb/>8.9 <lb/>45 <lb/>39 <lb/>Hong SN <lb/>2010 <lb/>Korea <lb/>Cross-section Serology <lb/>2195 <lb/>49.23 10.34 <lb/>62.00 1.36 1.1-1.68 <lb/>54.0 <lb/>9 <lb/>47 <lb/>25 <lb/>Park YM <lb/>2008-2012 Korea <lb/>Cross-section Serology <lb/>2781 <lb/>44.8 2.8 <lb/>58.72 2.26 1.11-4.62 <lb/>54.0 <lb/>9.0 <lb/>47 <lb/>38 <lb/>Nam KW <lb/>2004-2005 Korea <lb/>Cross-section Serology <lb/>598 <lb/>56.33 10.34 <lb/>65.38 1.93 1.24-3.01 <lb/>54.0 <lb/>8.8 <lb/>45 <lb/>8 <lb/>Hu KC <lb/>2006-2015 Taiwan <lb/>Cross-section CLO <lb/>2475 <lb/>52.90 8.25 <lb/>66.91 1.44 1.20-1.73 <lb/>53.9 <lb/>9.59 <lb/>19 <lb/>19 <lb/>Group 4 (DM prevalence: &gt;10%) <lb/>Yan Ye <lb/>2014-2016 China <lb/>Cross-section UBT <lb/>1641 <lb/>50.73 8.26 <lb/>66.24 1.535 1.04-1.75 <lb/>55.8 <lb/>10.6 <lb/>52 <lb/>37 <lb/>Brim H <lb/>2005-2009 USA <lb/>Cross-section pathology <lb/>1256 57 9.6 <lb/>34.00 1.5 <lb/>1.2-2.2 <lb/>35.6 <lb/>10.7 <lb/>44 <lb/>22 <lb/>Selgrad M <lb/>2008-2013 Germany Cross-section Serology <lb/>377 <lb/>66.38 9.82 <lb/>50.13 1.85 1.14-2.99 <lb/>35.3 <lb/>11.9 <lb/>47 <lb/>23 <lb/>Sonnenberg <lb/>2008-2011 USA <lb/>Cross-section pathology <lb/>22231 <lb/>57.88 15.21 <lb/>41.00 1.52 1.46 -1.57 <lb/>35.6 <lb/>12.1 <lb/>44 <lb/>3 <lb/>Abbass K <lb/>2008-2009 USA <lb/>Cross-section CLO <lb/>192 <lb/>59.1 12.82 <lb/>38.02 1.29 0.69-2.42 <lb/>35.6 <lb/>12.1 <lb/>44 <lb/>30 <lb/>Patel S <lb/>2009-2011 USA <lb/>Case-control Pathology <lb/>798 <lb/>54.83 11.51 <lb/>NA <lb/>1.04 0.67-1.61 <lb/>35.6 <lb/>12.1 <lb/>44 <lb/>42 <lb/>Zuniga R <lb/>2010-2012 USA <lb/>Case-control NA <lb/>943 <lb/>57 jj <lb/>NA <lb/>1.55 1.13-2.12 <lb/>35.6 <lb/>12.3 <lb/>44 <lb/>41 <lb/>Siddheshwar RK study only included colon polyp population; Nam JH, Tongtawee T studies only demonstrated aging disturbance. <lb/>Park YM focus age 40-49 subjects; Sonnenberg only included subjects who had H pylori pathology report. <lb/>CI = confidence interval, CLO = Campylobacter-like organism test, DM = diabetes mellitus, H pylori = Helicobacter pylori, UBT = urea breath test, UK = the United Kingdom. <lb/> * <lb/>SD (standard deviation) or (range). <lb/> † Odds ratio: for colorectal adenoma. <lb/> ‡ From Ref. 57. <lb/>x Did not specify the reported data as range or interquartile range. <lb/>jj No standard deviation, standard error, or range reported in the study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ko et al. Medicine (2021) 100:50 <lb/>www.md-journal.com <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>2010. The study&apos;s location may also affect this result. Most of the <lb/>Group 3 studies were from Korea, and Group 4 studies were from <lb/>the USA. The Group 2 studies were more heterogeneous in <lb/>location, including Japan, Taiwan, Turkey, Israel, and Germany. <lb/>The H pylori infection rate of the study population was also <lb/>collected and is shown in Table 1. There was no significant <lb/>difference in the ORs of H pylori infection-associated colorectal <lb/>adenoma between the lower infection rate area (USA or <lb/>Germany, 35.3%-35.6%) and the middle infection rate area <lb/>(Japan, Korea, China, Taiwan; approximately 51.7%-55.8%). <lb/>Further evaluation for the other reason that Group 2 studies <lb/>revealed higher ORs in H pylori infection-associated colorectal <lb/>adenoma is necessary. In addition, our study might partially <lb/>answer Plummer query &quot;How to explain that some areas had a <lb/>high prevalence of H pylori infection but low CRC risk?&quot; [10] <lb/>According to our study, we could see that Brazil et al. had a <lb/>Figure 2. Forest plot showing individual and pooled odds ratio (95% CIs) of all studies included with subgroups of the prevalence of DM. Each study is labeled with <lb/>the authors&apos; name. CIs = confidence intervals, DM = diabetes mellitus. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ko et al. Medicine (2021) 100:50 <lb/>Medicine <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>higher H pylori infection prevalence (71.2%) but a lower DM <lb/>prevalence rate (5.8%). (Table 1) Buso study demonstrated that <lb/>the H pylori infection proportion did not significantly increase <lb/>colorectal adenoma risk (OR: 1.98, 95% CI 0.82-3.15). [34] <lb/>However, when the DM prevalence was higher (&gt;10%), even <lb/>when the H pylori infection rate was lower (35.6%), the OR of <lb/>colorectal adenoma with H pylori infection was significantly <lb/>increased (Group 4: OR: 1.52, 95% CI 1.46-1.57). This means <lb/>that the DM prevalence rate might be the key factor of increased <lb/>colorectal adenoma risk with H pylori infection. <lb/>Our previous study demonstrated the interaction of hypergly-<lb/>cemia and H pylori infection in colon adenoma formation. We <lb/>found that the OR for adenoma was 1.437 (95% CI 1.197-<lb/>1.726) if H pylori was present or 1.629 (95% CI 1.239-2.14) if <lb/>HbA 1c ≥6.5. When combining these 2 factors, the OR was <lb/>elevated to 4.712 (95% CI 3.189-6.963), suggesting that these 2 <lb/>factors may have a synergistic effect in colorectal adenoma. [19] <lb/>The likely reason for the synergistic effect may involve several <lb/>processes. First, hyperglycemia status affected gastrointestinal <lb/>morphology and function and resulted in gut barrier loss and <lb/>changes in intestinal mucosa permeability. Second, high-fat and <lb/>high-caloric diets also increase gut permeability, and this <lb/>situation was more significant in DM patients. [70] Third, some <lb/>intestinal microorganism-related products, such as lipopolysac-<lb/>charides, would more efficiently pass through the gut barrier and <lb/>stimulate the Toll-like receptors in the mucosa. This would <lb/>trigger a serious inflammatory process, and finally, IL(interleu-<lb/>kin)-17 and IL-6 will increase. IL-17 activates the signal <lb/>transducer and activator of the transcription 3 pathway, <lb/>promoting cell proliferation and survival and finally inducing <lb/>tumorigenesis. [71] <lb/>These animal models and individualized study results support <lb/>this study finding that states that an elevated DM prevalence rate <lb/>enhances the risk of colorectal adenoma in H pylori-infected <lb/>populations. Our study still had several limitations. First, in our <lb/>subgroup analysis, we found that the Group 2 studies had more <lb/>heterogeneity. The reason for this condition may be related to <lb/>population studies with differences in study location, population, <lb/>aging, and gender. Despite this heterogeneity, H pylori infection <lb/>also increased the risk of colorectal adenoma. Second, the <lb/>asymmetry of the results of Egger test and funnel plots suggested <lb/>the possibility of publication bias. However, because most of our <lb/>included studies [3,6,8,9,19,21-42] had statistically significant results, <lb/>Egger test and funnel plots would show asymmetry. Third, the <lb/>population DM prevalence rate might not completely represent <lb/>our included studies participant&apos;s diabetes condition. Only Lin <lb/>et al. [24] and Hu et al. [19] included the DM prevalence rate in their <lb/>studies. To the best of our knowledge, we tried to estimate the <lb/>diabetes rate of each study as accurately as possible. <lb/>5. Conclusion <lb/>In conclusion, our study demonstrated that population DM <lb/>prevalence affects the risk of colorectal adenoma with H pylori <lb/>infection. Since diabetes prevalence was over 6% in the <lb/>background study population, H pylori infection became a more <lb/>significant factor in inducing colorectal adenoma formation. <lb/>Given the increasing prevalence of diabetes in the world, H pylori <lb/>eradication and hyperglycemia control might have an impact on <lb/>the prevention of colorectal neoplasm formation. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We acknowledge the funding of the Department of Medical <lb/>Research, Mackay Memorial Hospital, grant number MMH-<lb/>110-34 and MOST-109-2314-B-195-007 from the Ministry of <lb/>Science and Technology, who had no role in the design of the <lb/>study; in the collection, analyses, or interpretation of data; in the <lb/>writing of the manuscript, or in the decision to publish the results. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>MJC, MSW, and HWY acquisition of data; CCC, CJL, and SCS <lb/>analysis and interpretation of data; YCL, LYY, and HJK <lb/>interpretation and analysis of data, revising the article; CTH and <lb/>HYW for the prevalence of diabetes survey and interpretation of <lb/>data, revising the article; KCH conception and design of the <lb/>study, critical revision, and final approval. All authors read and <lb/>approved the final manuscript. <lb/>Conceptualization: Ying-Chun Lin. <lb/>Data curation: Chieh-Chang Chen, Ming-Jen Chen, Chun-Ta <lb/>Huang, Lo-Yip Lu, Yang-Che Kuo, Horng-Yuan Wang. <lb/>Formal analysis: Ying-Chun Lin, Chieh-Chang Chen, Horng-<lb/>Woei Yang, Lo-Yip Lu. <lb/></div>

			<body>Figure 3. (A) Funnel plot of all studies included examining the relation between Helicobacter pylori infection and colon adenoma. (B) Egger regression test of all <lb/>studies including the relation between Helicobacter pylori infection and colon adenoma. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ko et al. Medicine (2021) 100:50 <lb/>www.md-journal.com <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Investigation: Ming-Jen Chen, Chun-Ta Huang, Shou-Chuan <lb/>Shih. <lb/>Methodology: Chun-Jen Liu, Shou-Chuan Shih. <lb/>Project administration: Ming-Shiang Wu. <lb/>Visualization: Ming-Shiang Wu, Chun-Jen Liu. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Hung-Ju Ko. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Kuang-Chun Hu. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Muhammad JS, Zaidi SF, Sugiyama T. Epidemiological ins and outs of <lb/>helicobacter pylori: a review. J Pak Med Assoc 2012;62:955-9. [PMID: <lb/>23139983]. <lb/>[2] Infection with Helicobacter pylori. IARC Monogr Eval Carcinog Risks <lb/>Hum 1994;61:177-240. [PMID: 7715070]. <lb/>[3] Sonnenberg A, Genta RM. Helicobacter pylori is a risk factor for colonic <lb/>neoplasms. Am J Gasteroenterol 2013;108:208-15. [PMID: 23208272 <lb/>DOI: 10.1038/ajg.2010.407]:. <lb/>[4] Rokkas T, Sechopoulos P, Pistiolas D, Kothonas F, Margantinis G, <lb/>Kouklulis G. The relationship of Helicobacter pylori infection and colon <lb/>neoplasia, on the basis of meta-analysis. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol <lb/>2013;25:1286-94. [PMID: 23820245]. <lb/>[5] Kapetanakis N, Kountouras J, Zayos C, et al. Helicobacter pylori <lb/>infection and colorectal cancer risk: evidence from a large population-<lb/>based case-control study in Germany. Am J Epidemiol 2012;176:566-7. <lb/>[PMID: 22908208 DOI: 10.1093/aje/kws302]. <lb/>[6] Liou JM, Lin JW, Huang SP, Lin JT, Wu MS. Helicobacter pylori <lb/>infection is not associated with increased risk of colorectal polyps in <lb/>Taiwanese. Int J Cancer 2006;119:1999-2000. [PMID: 16708392 DOI: <lb/>10.1002/ijc.22050]. <lb/>[7] Machida-Montani A, Sasazuki S, Inoue M, et al. Atrophic gastritis, <lb/>Helicobacter pylori, and colorectal cancer risk: a case-control study. <lb/>Helicobacter 2007;12:328-32. [PMID: 17669106]. <lb/>[8] Nam KW, Baeg MK, Kwon JH, Cho SH, Na SJ, Choi MG. Helicobacter <lb/>pylori seropositivity is positively associated with colorectal neoplasms. <lb/>Korean J Gastroenterol 2013;61:259-64. [PMID: 23756667]. <lb/>[9] Inoue I, Mukoubayashi C, Yoshimura N, et al. Elevated risk of colorectal <lb/>adenoma with Helicobacter pylori-related chronic gastritis: a popula-<lb/>tion-based case-control study. Int J Cancer 2011;129:2704-11. [PMID: <lb/>21225622 DOI: 10.1002/ijc.25931]. <lb/>[10] Plummer M. Helicobacter pylori and colonic neoplasms. Am J <lb/>Gasteroenterol 2013;108:216-7. [PMID:23381070 DOI: 10.1038/ <lb/>ajg.2012.409]. <lb/>[11] Chen YS, Xu SX, Ding YB, Huang XE, Deng B. Helicobacter pylori <lb/>infection and the risk of colorectal adenoma and adenocarcinoma: an <lb/>updated meta-analysis of different testing methods. Asian Pac J Cancer <lb/>Prev 2013;14:7613-9. [PMID: 24460342]. <lb/>[12] Wu Q, Yang ZP, Xu P, Gao LC, Fan DM. Association between <lb/>Helicobacter pylori infection and the risk of colorectal neoplasia: a <lb/>systematic review and meta-analysis. Colorectal Dis 2013;15:e352-64. <lb/>[PMID: 23672575 DOI: 10.1111/codi.12284]. <lb/>[13] Rokkas T, Sechopoulos P, Pistiolas D, Kothonas F, Margantinis G, <lb/>Koukoulis G. The relationship of Helicobacter pylori infection and colon <lb/>neoplasia, on the basis of meta-analysis. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol <lb/>2013;25:1286-94. [PMID: 23820245]. <lb/>[14] Guariguata L, Whiting DR, Hambleton I, Beagley J, Linnenkamp U, <lb/>Shaw JE. Global estimates of diabetes prevalence for 2013 and <lb/>projections for 2035. Diabetes Res Clin Pract 2014;103:137-49. [PMID: <lb/>24630390]. <lb/>[15] American Diabetes AssociationDiagnosis and classification of diabetes <lb/>mellitus. Diabetes Care 2010;33:S62-9. <lb/>[16] Ramachandran A, Snehalatha C, Shetty AS, Nanditha A. Trends in <lb/>prevalence of diabetes in Asian countries. World J Diabetes 2012;3:110-<lb/>7. [PMID: 22737281 DOI: 10.4239/wjd.v3.i6.110]. <lb/>[17] Eddi R, Karki A, Shah A, DeBari VA, DePasquale JR. Association of type <lb/>2 diabetes and colon adenomas. J Gastrointest Cancer 2012;43:87-92. <lb/>[PMID: 21894459]. <lb/>[18] Yuhara H, Steinmaus C, Cohen SE, Corley DA, Tei Y, Buffler PA. Is <lb/>diabetes mellitus an independent risk factor for colon cancer and rectal <lb/>cancer? Am J Gastroenterol 2011;106:1911-21. [PMID: 21912438 <lb/>DOI: 10.1038/ajg.2011.301]. <lb/>[19] Hu KC, Wu MS, Chu CH, et al. Synergistic effect of hyperglycemia and <lb/>Helicobacter pylori infection status on colorectal adenoma risk. J Clin <lb/>Endocrinol Metab 2017;102:2017-257. [PMID: 28475740 DOI: <lb/>10.1210/jc.2017-00257]. <lb/>[20] Hu KC, Wu MS, Chu CH, et al. Decreased colorectal adenoma risk after <lb/>Helicobacter pylori eradication: a retrospective cohort study. Clin Infect <lb/>Dis 2019;68:2105-13. [PMID: 30566695 DOI: 10.1093/cid/ciy591]. <lb/>[21] Mizuno S, Morita Y, Inui T, et al. Helicobacter pylori infection is <lb/>associated with colon adenomatous polyps detected by high-resolution <lb/>colonoscopy. Int J Cancer 2005;117:1058-9. [PMID: 15986436 DOI: <lb/>10.1002/ijc.21280]. <lb/>[22] Brim H, Zahaf M, Laiyemo AO, et al. Gastric Helicobacter pylori <lb/>infection associates with an increased risk of colorectal polyps in African <lb/>Americans. BMC Cancer 2014;14:296[PMID: 24774100]. <lb/>[23] Selgrad M, Bornschein J, Kandulski A, et al. Helicobacter pylori but not <lb/>gastrin is associated with the development of colonic neoplasms. Int J <lb/>Cancer 2014;135:1127-31. [PMID: 24496701 DOI: 10.1002/ <lb/>ijc.28758]. <lb/>[24] Lin YL, Chiang JK, Lin SM, Tseng CE. Helicobacter pylori infection <lb/>concomitant with metabolic syndrome further increase risk of colorectal <lb/>adenomas. World J Gastroenterol 2010;16:3841-6. [PMID: 20698048]. <lb/>[25] Hong SN, Lee SM, Kim JH, et al. Helicobacter pylori infection increases <lb/>the risk of colorectal adenomas: cross-sectional study and meta-analysis. <lb/>Dig Dis Sci 2012;57:2184-94. [PMID: 22669208]. <lb/>[26] Aydin A, Karasu Z, Zeytinoglu A, Kumanlioglu K, Özacar T. Colorectal <lb/>adenomateous polyps and Helicobacter pylori infection. Am J Gastro-<lb/>enterol 1999;94:1121-2. [PMID: 10201512]. <lb/>[27] Siddheshwar RK, Muhammad KB, Gray JC, Kelly SB. Seroprevalence of <lb/>Helicobacter pylori in patients with colorectal polyps and colorectal <lb/>carcinoma. Am J Gastroenterol 2001;96:84-8. [PMID: 11197293]. <lb/>[28] Fujimori S, Kishida T, Kobayashi T, et al. Helicobacter pylori infection <lb/>increases the risk of colorectal adenoma and adenocarcinoma, especially <lb/>in women. J Gastroenterol 2005;40:887-93. [PMID:16211345]. <lb/>[29] Bae RC, Jeon SW, Cho HJ, Jung MK, Kweon YO, Kim SK. Gastric <lb/>dysplasia may be an independent risk factor of an advanced colorectal <lb/>neoplasm. World J Gastroenterol 2009;15:5722-6. [PMID: 19960571]. <lb/>[30] Abbass K, Gul W, Beck G, Markert R, Akram S. Association of <lb/>Helicobacter pylori infection with the development of colorectal polyps and <lb/>colorectal carcinoma. South Med J 2011;104:473-6. [PMID: 21886044]. <lb/>[31] Shmuely H, Melzer E, Braverman M, Domniz N, Yahav J. Helicobacter <lb/>pylori infection is associated with advanced colorectal neoplasia. Scand J <lb/>Gastroenterol 2014;49:35-42. [PMID: 24490722]. <lb/>[32] Breuer-Katschinski B, Nemes K, Marr A, et al. Helicobacter pylori and <lb/>the risk of colonic adenomas. Digestion 1999;60:210-5. [PMID: <lb/>10343134 DOI: 10.1159/000007661]. <lb/>[33] Georgopoulos SD, Polymeros D, Triantafyllou K, et al. Hypergastrine-<lb/>mia is associated with increased risk of distal colon adenomas. Digestion <lb/>2006;74:42-6. [PMID:17068397]. <lb/>[34] Buso AG, Rocha HLOG, Diogo DM, Diogo PM, Diogo-Filho A. <lb/>Seroprevalence of Helicobacter pylori in patients with colon adenomas in <lb/>a Brazilian university hospital. Arq Gastroenterol 2009;46:97-101. <lb/>[PMID: 19578608]. <lb/>[35] Kim TJ, Kim ER, Chang DK, et al. Helicobacter pylori infection is an <lb/>independent risk factor of early and advanced colorectal neoplasm. <lb/>Helicobacter 2017;22[PMID: 28124492 DOI: 10.1111/hel.12377]. <lb/>[36] Nam JH, Hong CW, Kim BC, et al. Helicobacter pylori infection is an <lb/>independent risk factor for colonic adenomatous neoplasms. Cancer <lb/>Causes Control 2017;28:107-15. [PMID: 28025763]. <lb/>[37] Yan Ye, Chen YN, Zhao Q, et al. Helicobacter pylori infection with <lb/>intestinal metaplasia: an independent risk factor for colorectal adeno-<lb/>mas. World J Gastroenterol 2017;23:1443-9. [PMID: 28293091]. <lb/>[38] Park YM, Kim HS, Park JJ, et al. A simple scoring model for advanced <lb/>colorectal neoplasm in asymptomatic subjects aged 40-49 years. BMC <lb/>Gastroenterol 2017;17[PMID: 28068908 DOI: 10.1186/s12876-016-<lb/>0562-9]. <lb/>[39] Lee JY, Park HW, Choi JY, et al. Helicobacter pylori infection with <lb/>atrophic gastritis is an independent risk factor for advanced colonic <lb/>neoplasm. Gut Liver 2016;10:902-9. [PMID: 27458180 DOI: 10.5009/ <lb/>gnl15340]. <lb/>[40] Tongtawee T, Kaewpitoon S, Kaewpitoon N, et al. Helicobacter pylori <lb/>associated gastritis increases risk of colorectal polyps: a hospital based-<lb/>cross-sectional study in Nakhon Ratchasima Province, Northeastern <lb/>Thailand. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev 2016;17:341-5. [PMID: 26838234]. <lb/>[41] Zuniga R, Bautista J, Sapra K, Westerfield K, Williams S, Sy AM. <lb/>Combination of triple therapy and chronic PPI use may decrease risk of <lb/>colonic adenomatous polyps in Helicobacter pylori infection. Gastro-<lb/>enterol Res Pract 2015;2015:638547[PMID: 26064095]. <lb/>Ko et al. Medicine (2021) 100:50 <lb/>Medicine <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[42] Patel S, Lipka S, Shen H, et al. The association of H. pylori and colorectal <lb/>adenoma: does it exist in the US Hispanic population? J Gastrointest <lb/>Oncol 2014;5:463-8. [PMID: 25436126]. <lb/>[43] Charvat H, Goto A, Goto M, et al. Impact of population aging on trends <lb/>in diabetes prevalence: a meta-regression analysis of 160,000 Japanese <lb/>adults. J Diabetes Investing 2015;6:533-42. [PMID: 26417410 DOI: <lb/>10.1111/jdi.12333]. <lb/>[44] Menke A, Casagrande S, Geiss L, Cowie CC. Prevalence of and trends in <lb/>diabetes among adults in the United States, 1988-2012. JAMA <lb/>2015;314:1021-9. [PMID: 26348752]. <lb/>[45] Whiting DR, Guariguata L, Weil C, Shaw J. IDF diabetes atlas: global <lb/>estimates of the prevalence of diabetes for 2011 and 2030. Diabetes Res <lb/>Clin Pract 2011;94:311-21. [PMID: 22079683]. <lb/>[46] Jiang YD, Chang CH, Tai TY, Chen JF, Chuang LM. Incidence and <lb/>prevalence rates of diabetes mellitus in Taiwan: analysis of the 2000-<lb/>2009 Nationwide Health Insurance database. J Formos Med Assoc <lb/>2012;111:599-604. [PMID: 23217595]. <lb/>[47] Satman I, Yilmaz T, Sengül A, et al. Population-based study of diabetes <lb/>and risk characteristics in Turkey: results of the Turkish diabetes <lb/>epidemiology study (TURDEP). Diabetes Care 2002;25:1551-6. [PMID: <lb/>12196426]. <lb/>[48] Imkampe AK, Gulliford MC. Increasing socio-economic inequality <lb/>in type 2 diabetes prevalence-repeated cross-sectional surveys in <lb/>England 1994-2006. Eur J Public Health 2010;21:484-90. [PMID: <lb/>20685812]. <lb/>[49] Panagiotakos DB, Pitsavos C, Chrysohoou C, Stefanadis C. The <lb/>epidemiology of Type 2 diabetes mellitus in Greek adults: the ATTICA <lb/>study. Diabetic Med 2005;22:1581-8. [PMID: 16241925]. <lb/>[50] International Diabetes Federation. IDF Diabetes Atlas. 7th Edition. <lb/>2015. International Diabetes Federation, Brussels. http://www.idf.org/ <lb/>diabetesatlas/. Accessed November 6, 2015. <lb/>[51] Frese T, Sandholzer H, Voigt S, Voigt R. Epidemiology of diabetes <lb/>mellitus in German general practitioners&apos; consultation-results of the <lb/>SESAM 2-study. Exp Clin Endocrinol Diabetes 2008;116:326-8. <lb/>[PMID: 18700277]. <lb/>[52] Go MF. Review article: natural history and epidemiology of Helicobacter <lb/>pylori infection. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2002;16(Suppl 1):3-15. <lb/>[PMID: 11849122 DOI: 10.1046/j.1365-2036.2002.0160s1003.x]. <lb/>[53] Marshall BJ, Warren JR. Unidentified curved bacilli in the stomach of <lb/>patients with gastritis and peptic ulceration. Lancet 1984;1:1311-5. <lb/>[PMID:6145023]. <lb/>[54] Hooi JK, Lai WY, Ng WK, et al. Global prevalence of Helicobacter pylori <lb/>infection: systematic review and meta-analysis. Gastroenterology <lb/>2017;153:420-9. [PMID: 28456631]. <lb/>[55] Butt J, Epplein M. Helicobacter pylori and colorectal cancer-a <lb/>bacterium going abroad? PLoS Pathog 2019;15:e1007861[PMID: <lb/>31393968; DOI: 10.1371/journal.ppat.1007861]. <lb/>[56] NCD Risk Factor CollaborationWorldwide trends in diabetes since <lb/>1980: a pooled analysis of 751 population-based studies with 4.4 million <lb/>participants. Lancet 2016;387:1513-30. [DOI: 10.1016/S0140-6736 <lb/>(16)00618-8]. <lb/>[57] Wandell PE, Carlsson AC. Gender differences and time trends in <lb/>incidence and prevalence of type 2 diabetes in Sweden -a model <lb/>explaining the diabetes epidemic worldwide today? Diabetes Res Clin <lb/>Pract 2014;106:e90-92. [PMID: 25451899]. <lb/>[58] American Diabetes AssociationDiagnosis and classification of diabetes <lb/>mellitus. Diabetes Care 2012;35(Suppl 1):64-71. [PMID:]. <lb/>[59] Yuhara H, Steinmaus C, Cohen SE, Corley DA, Tei Y, Buffler PA. Is <lb/>diabetes mellitus an independent risk factor for colon cancer and rectal <lb/>cancer? Am J Gastroenterol 2011;106:1911-21. [PMID: 21912438]. <lb/>[60] Koster I, Schubert I, Huppertz E. Follow up of the CoDiM-Study: cost of <lb/>diabetes mellitus 2000-2009. Dtsch Med Wochenschr 2012;137:1013-<lb/>6. [PMID: 22549261]. <lb/>[61] Schunk M, Reitmeir P, Schipf S, et al. Health-related quality of life in <lb/>subjects with and without Type 2 diabetes: pooled analysis of five <lb/>population-based surveys in Germany. Diabet Med 2012;29:646-53. <lb/>[PMID: 21978176]. <lb/>[62] Hwang CK, Han PV, Zabetian A, Ali MK, Narayan KM. Rural diabetes <lb/>prevalence quintuples over twenty-five years in low-and middle-income <lb/>countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Diabetes Res Clin Pract <lb/>2012;96:271-85. [PMID: 22261096]. <lb/>[63] Zuo H, Shi Z, Hussain A. Prevalence, trends and risk factors for the <lb/>diabetes epidemic in China: a systematic review and meta-analysis. <lb/>Diabetes Res Clin Pract 2014;104:63-72. [PMID: 24468097 DOI: <lb/>10.1016/j.diabres.2014.01.002]. <lb/>[64] Jayawardena R, Ranasinghe P, Byrne NM, Soares MJ, Katulanda P, Hills <lb/>AP. Prevalence and trends of the diabetes epidemic in South Asia: a <lb/>systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Public Health 2012;12:380 <lb/>[PMID: 22630043]. <lb/>[65] Satman I, Omer B, Tutuncu Y, et al. Twelve-year trends in the prevalence <lb/>and risk factors of diabetes and prediabetes in Turkish adults. Eur J <lb/>Epidemiol 2013;28:169-80. [PMID: 23407904]. <lb/>[66] Alharbi NS, Almutari R, Jones S, Al-Daghri N, Khunti K, de Lusignan S. <lb/>Trends in the prevalence of type 2 diabetes mellitus and obesity in the <lb/>Arabian Gulf States: systematic review and meta-analysis. Diabetes Res <lb/>Clin Pract 2014;106:e30-33. [PMID: 25241351]. <lb/>[67] Imkampe AK, Gulliford MC. Increasing socio-economic inequality in <lb/>type 2 diabetes prevalence-repeated cross-sectional surveys in England <lb/>1994-2006. Eur J Public Health 2011;21:484-90. [PMID: 20685812 <lb/>DOI: 10.1093/eurpub/ckq 106]. <lb/>[68] Icks A, Moebus S, Feuersenger A, Haastert B, Jockel KH, Giani G. <lb/>Diabetes prevalence and association with social status-widening of a <lb/>social gradient? German national health surveys 1990-1992 and 1998. <lb/>Diabetes Res Clin Pract 2007;78:293-7. [PMID: 17532522]. <lb/>[69] Teuscher AU, Diem P, Thomas W, Janett J, Teuscher A. Incidence of insulin-<lb/>dependent diabetes mellitus in Switzerland (1972-1993) in 19-year-old <lb/>men. Schweiz Med Wochenschr 1995;125:1041-5. [PMID: 7770760]. <lb/>[70] De Kort S, Keszthelyi D, Masclee AAM. Leaky gut and diabetes mellitus: <lb/>what is the link? Obes Rev 2011;12:449-58. [PMID: 21382153]. <lb/>[71] Gallimore AM, Godkin A. Epithelial barriers, microbiota, and colorectal <lb/>cancer. N Engl J Med 2013;368:282-4. [PMID: 23323906 DOI: <lb/>10.1056/NEJMcibr121234]. <lb/>Ko et al. Medicine (2021) 100:50 <lb/>www.md-journal.com <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
