<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Did relaxing clinical trial regulation enhance <lb/>the stock of scientific knowledge in India? Not <lb/>necessarily <lb/>Bastian Rake ID <lb/>1 <lb/>*, Carolin Haeussler ID <lb/>2 <lb/>1 School of Business, Maynooth University, Maynooth, Co Kildare, Ireland, 2 Chair of Organisation, <lb/>Technology Management and Entrepreneurship, University of Passau, Passau, Germany <lb/>* bastian.rake@mu.ie <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The increasing amount of clinical research conducted outside the &quot;traditional&quot; countries <lb/>raises questions about the benefits of hosting offshored clinical research. The extent to <lb/>which trials contribute to the scientific knowledge base and, in particular, whether there are <lb/>differences between different types of trials remain open questions. By examining a change <lb/>in clinical trial regulations in India, a country often viewed as a first-choice offshoring loca-<lb/>tion, we study how the relaxation of clinical trial regulations affects the number and the type <lb/>of clinical trials as well as the domestic scientific knowledge base. Based on trial data from <lb/>ClinicalTrials.gov and data on associated publication activities, our empirical analysis sug-<lb/>gests that, despite an initial increase in the number of clinical trials, relaxing clinical trial reg-<lb/>ulations has a limited impact on the domestic scientific knowledge base. More specifically, <lb/>the number of Indian researchers involved in the production of trial-related scientific knowl-<lb/>edge remains modest. Furthermore, the potential to learn from the additional trials appears <lb/>to be limited: the influx of phase 3 trials-mainly sponsored by Western-pharmaceutical <lb/>firms-is accompanied by a lower likelihood that the trial results will be used in Indian <lb/>researchers&apos; subsequent research activities when compared to phase 3 trials with preceding <lb/>phase 2 trials, as was required before the regulatory change. Overall, our results contradict <lb/>expectations that relaxing the regulatory requirements for conducting late-stage clinical tri-<lb/>als is an appropriate means of supporting the development of the domestic scientific knowl-<lb/>edge base. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The geographical distribution of clinical research has changed considerably over time, such <lb/>that clinical trials are increasingly conducted outside the &quot;traditional&quot; research centers in <lb/>North America, Western Europe, and selected locations in the Asia-Pacific region. Non-tradi-<lb/>tional countries, particularly emerging economies in East Asia, Southeast Asia, and Latin <lb/>America, have gained importance as locations for conducting clinical trials [1-4]. This rising <lb/>importance of non-traditional countries coincides with an increase in intercontinental <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/>1 / 15 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Rake B, Haeussler C (2019) Did relaxing <lb/>clinical trial regulation enhance the stock of <lb/>scientific knowledge in India? Not necessarily. <lb/>PLoS ONE 14(1): e0210163. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 <lb/>Editor: Joel Lexchin, York University, CANADA <lb/>Received: April 13, 2018 <lb/>Accepted: December 18, 2018 <lb/>Published: January 3, 2019 <lb/>Copyright: © 2019 Rake, Haeussler. This is an <lb/>open access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Data on clinical trials <lb/>conducted in India obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov <lb/>is made available in the corresponding Supporting <lb/>Information file. Other authors can also access this <lb/>information through ClinicalTrials.gov. We obtained <lb/>publication data from the Scopus database which <lb/>is a proprietary database (www.scopus.com). <lb/>Researchers interested in replicating our study can <lb/>access data on trial-related publications following <lb/>the search procedure described in the paper. <lb/>Researchers do not need special privileges to <lb/>access the Scopus database, however, a <lb/>subscription may be required. The authors did not <lb/>have special access privileges to the data. <lb/></front>

			<body>industry-sponsored trials [5]. Given pharmaceutical firms&apos; interest in outsourcing clinical tri-<lb/>als to emerging economies, national governments face the complex decision of whether to <lb/>hamper or support this development through, for example, policy decisions, public invest-<lb/>ments in research infrastructure, or regulatory changes [6,7]. Arguments for restricting (off-<lb/>shored) clinical trials include the crowding out of domestic research, and concerns about <lb/>patient safety, access to information about the research, and the possibility of a lack of access <lb/>to medications after a trial has been completed when those medications have been tested on <lb/>the country&apos;s population [2,8,9]. In addition, researchers have suggested that offshored clinical <lb/>trials often focus on diseases that are predominantly prevalent in high-income countries, while <lb/>they largely ignore diseases common in low-income countries [10,11]. In contrast, arguments <lb/>for attracting clinical trials include the enhanced availability of new medications that corre-<lb/>spond to local needs, the support of domestic health systems, and opportunities for knowledge <lb/>transfer and learning [9,2]. <lb/>Although knowledge-transfer arguments are highlighted in policy discussions and reports, <lb/>the extent to which countries&apos; scientific knowledge bases truly benefit from attracting clinical <lb/>research sponsored by Western organizations is still an open question. Anecdotal evidence <lb/>suggests that an influx of trials strengthens the host country&apos;s scientific capabilities, but there <lb/>is a lack of corresponding quantitative analyses. To address this gap, we study how relaxing <lb/>clinical trial regulations affects the number of clinical trials as well as the domestic scientific <lb/>knowledge base in a country by measuring scientific publications and forward citations. More <lb/>specifically, we analyze whether a policy change aimed at increasing late-stage clinical trials in <lb/>an emerging economy fosters the involvement of domestic researchers in the production of <lb/>scientific knowledge. In particular, we investigate the change in trial-related publication output <lb/>as well as the dissemination of trial-related knowledge based on forward citations by domestic <lb/>authors. Since a thorough evaluation of the policy change would require including a large <lb/>number of aspects ranging from patient safety to market aspects and is beyond the scope of a <lb/>single paper, we focus on how the production of scientific knowledge in terms of publications <lb/>and their use by domestic researchers through forward citations may be affected. <lb/>Our study&apos;s context is a country that has long been a first-choice offshoring location [12-<lb/>15]: India. To increase its attractiveness for (offshored) clinical trials, India repealed its so-<lb/>called &quot;phase lag&quot; regulation, which applied to compounds not discovered in India, in January <lb/>2005 [16,8]. According to the pre-2005 regulation, clinical trials in India had to be conducted <lb/>in an earlier drug-development phase than the phase of trials being undertaken in other coun-<lb/>tries for the same drug. If, for example, a new drug was being tested in a phase 3 study in the <lb/>United States, the same drug could only be tested in a phase 2 study in India. Table 1 provides <lb/>an overview of the key change in India&apos;s regulatory framework in 2005. In order to assess the <lb/>consequences of this regulatory change, it is important to take a closer look at the context in <lb/>which it took place. <lb/>Table 1. Overview of key change in India&apos;s clinical trial regulations. <lb/>Clinical Trial Regulations Prior to January 2005 <lb/>Clinical Trial Regulations Since January 2005 <lb/>• Phase 1 trials of compounds not discovered in <lb/>India were generally not allowed. <lb/>• Trials in later phases for compounds not <lb/>discovered in India needed to be initiated with a <lb/>&quot;phase lag.&quot; <lb/>• Phase 1 trials of compounds not discovered in India are <lb/>generally not allowed. <lb/>• Trials in later phases for compounds not discovered in <lb/>India can be initiated at the same time as in other <lb/>countries. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<front>Funding: The authors received no specific funding <lb/>for this work. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>After its independence in 1947, India adopted a self-reliance policy based on price controls <lb/>and other regulations aimed at supporting its domestic pharmaceutical industry. The policy <lb/>included high tariffs and foreign ownership restrictions, which limited dependence on West-<lb/>ern pharmaceutical companies with respect to drug development and the supply of pharma-<lb/>ceuticals [17]. Furthermore, starting in the early 1970s, product patents for pharmaceuticals <lb/>could no longer be filed, and patents for pharmaceutical production processes expired seven <lb/>years from the application date or five years after they were granted [18,19]. In addition, <lb/>India&apos;s regulatory framework for clinical trials was designed to protect the domestic popula-<lb/>tion from being abused as experimental subjects for untested and possibly unsafe drugs devel-<lb/>oped by foreign companies, especially those of Western origin [8]. Consequently, phase 1 trials <lb/>of compounds not discovered in India were generally not allowed and trials in other stages <lb/>needed to be initiated after a &quot;phase lag.&quot; <lb/>This combination of regulations enabled Indian companies to improve their position in <lb/>both the domestic market and overseas, primarily based on the development of generic varie-<lb/>ties of medications originally developed and patented by Western companies [20]. However, <lb/>this imitation-based business model came into question in the 1990s when India became a <lb/>member of the World Trade Organization and was required to comply with the TRIPS agree-<lb/>ment. As a consequence, the country had to introduce product patents by 2005 [21-23]. Con-<lb/>sequently, the industry had to adapt its business model. Alternatives in this regard included <lb/>imitating off-patent drugs or developing new drugs based on India&apos;s own R&amp;D activities. Fur-<lb/>thermore, the Indian pharmaceutical industry was challenged to build up the biotechnology <lb/>skills needed to develop innovative drugs [24,25]. <lb/>The Indian Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development Committee [26] arrived at the <lb/>conclusion that changes in clinical trial regulations could turn India into a worldwide leading <lb/>location for clinical trials. This potential for clinical research was expected to support the trans-<lb/>formation of the domestic pharmaceutical industry from a&quot;late follower to an innovative <lb/>leader&quot; by encouraging the return of Indian scientists from abroad, the establishment of <lb/>knowledge-intensive R&amp;D service companies, and to increase foreign direct investment (FDI) <lb/>by multi-national pharmaceutical companies. In January 2005, the Indian government finally <lb/>amended its Drug and Cosmetic Rules and repealed the&quot;phase lag&quot; for compounds not discov-<lb/>ered in India [16,8]. Indian companies reacted favorably to these changes based on the expec-<lb/>tation that the changes would strengthen the country&apos;s scientific and innovation capacity, and <lb/>increase profits by enabling Indian companies to provide services to the Western pharmaceuti-<lb/>cal firms expected to offshore trials to India [27]. In contrast to the positive expectations of the <lb/>Indian government and domestic companies, the national media stressed the potential risks <lb/>for Indian trial subjects, who might be abused as &quot;guinea pigs&quot; by multinational companies <lb/>[28,29]. <lb/>Against this background, Reid and Ramani [30] point out that conducting clinical research <lb/>has been viewed as key for India&apos;s ability to catch up to the international knowledge frontier. <lb/>However, whether the changes resulted in the expected catch-up effect is unknown. It may <lb/>well be that clinical research has not enabled India to develop the scientific capabilities that are <lb/>required for pre-clinical or upstream research. As such, activities linked to drug discovery may <lb/>still only be conducted in R&amp;D labs outside of India. <lb/>In this paper, we provide a thorough analysis of the consequences of the regulatory changes <lb/>for India&apos;s domestic scientific knowledge base. To do so, we investigate the relation between <lb/>trials of new medications that correspond to international demands and changes in India&apos;s sci-<lb/>entific knowledge base. In line with prior studies, we build our analysis on measurements of <lb/>scientific publications and forward citations to account for the scientific knowledge base [31]. <lb/>Scientific publications document scientific discoveries and the creation of new knowledge that <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<body>advances the existing knowledge base in a specific area of research. Forward citations reflect <lb/>the use of a published piece of knowledge by other researchers in their own attempts to con-<lb/>tribute to the scientific knowledge base [32]. Against this background, we investigate the extent <lb/>to which the repeal of the phase lag strengthened the involvement of Indian researchers in <lb/>publications related to clinical trials and the extent to which Indian researchers have been able <lb/>to build on trial-related publications. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Clinical trials and publication data <lb/>Our empirical analysis, which explores the consequences of the repeal of the &quot;phase lag&quot; for <lb/>India&apos;s domestic scientific knowledge base, is based on clinical trial data obtained from Clini-<lb/>calTrials.gov. That dataset contains detailed information about clinical trials conducted in the <lb/>US and 179 other countries, including India and many other non-traditional countries. <lb/>Haeussler and Rake [1] provide a detailed overview of the database&apos;s characteristics, the types <lb/>of clinical trials registered in ClinicalTrials.gov, and the regulatory requirements for registra-<lb/>tion. As we focus on India, our dataset encompasses 725 phase 3 clinical trials. Phase 3 trials <lb/>use comparatively large samples of trial subjects to evaluate the safety and efficacy of various <lb/>doses of drugs or biological products for different populations. The trials covered in our data-<lb/>set were launched between January 2002 and December 2012, and were conducted in at least <lb/>one facility located in India, usually hospitals or other medical-care institutions. Of the 725 <lb/>phase 3 trials, 722 started after the repeal of the phase lag requirement (i.e., between January <lb/>2005 and December 2012). <lb/>We identified whether a phase 3 trial was preceded by a phase 2 trial in India. Phase 2 trials <lb/>test drug candidates in humans who are affected by specific diseases or conditions. The objec-<lb/>tive is to obtain preliminary data on effectiveness and adverse events that occur in the short <lb/>term. As ClinicalTrials.gov does not provide unique identifiers for each drug under develop-<lb/>ment, we relied on the work of six experts in biology and medicine to create drug synonym <lb/>groups. Drug synonym groups uniquely identify drugs that are under development, as they are <lb/>labeled differently during the different phases of their development. Put differently, drug syno-<lb/>nym groups enable us to identify whether the same drug had been tested in different trials <lb/>using different names or labels. By matching each clinical trial with the corresponding drug <lb/>synonym group, we identified whether a phase 3 trial was preceded by a phase 2 trial of the <lb/>same compound in India. <lb/>ClinicalTrials.gov provides information about the type of (lead) sponsor of each clinical <lb/>trial. This information allowed us to distinguish clinical trials that are sponsored by biotech-<lb/>nology and pharmaceutical companies from those that are sponsored by academic institutions <lb/>or other organizations. <lb/>In order to account for the involvement of researchers with Indian affiliations in publica-<lb/>tions related to clinical trials, we followed Hoekman et al. [33] and searched the trial registra-<lb/>tion numbers in MEDLINE via PubMed (see Fig 1). MEDLINE indexes more than 5,500 <lb/>journals, including the leading life-science and biomedical scientific journals as well as <lb/>domestic scientific journals from India and other countries. As MEDLINE does not provide <lb/>information on all author affiliations, we complemented the data with information on author <lb/>affiliations from Scopus, one of the world&apos;s largest abstract and citation databases covering <lb/>peer-reviewed research. We found 549 articles that list a trial-registration number referring to <lb/>a phase 3 trial conducted in India. Of these, 104 had at least one author with an Indian affilia-<lb/>tion. These articles either report the intermediate or final results of a particular clinical trial, or <lb/>describe trial protocols and the research methods used in a clinical trial. Scopus can also be <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<body>used to obtain detailed information concerning scientific articles that cite trial-related publica-<lb/>tions. In this regard, we found 40,655 citations referring to the trial-related publications in <lb/>our sample. 735 of these 40,655 citations had at least one author affiliated with an Indian <lb/>institution. <lb/>In order to obtain information on the type of trial-related publications and the citing <lb/>publications related to the clinical trials in our sample, we use the CHI journal-classification <lb/>system [34]. The CHI system assigns scientific journals to one of four categories depending on <lb/>whether the articles in those journals can be described as predominantly focused on basic <lb/>research or clinical research. Hence, the CHI journal-classification system enables us to obtain <lb/>an indicator of whether a trial-related publication has been published in a journal that is pre-<lb/>dominantly focused on basic or clinical research; this may impact how often a publication is <lb/>cited. <lb/>Analyses <lb/>We use descriptive analyses to investigate developments in the number of phase 3 trials con-<lb/>ducted in India with and without preceding phase 2 trials as well as the number of publications <lb/>related to those trials and their forward citations. In addition, we use regression analysis to <lb/>examine the consequences of the repeal of the phase lag requirement on the Indian scientific <lb/>knowledge base. Our regression analysis is based on a sample of 385 publications related to <lb/>Fig 1. Search strategy for publication data. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<body>phase 3 trials conducted in India that started between the enactment of the regulatory changes <lb/>in January 2005 and December 2012. Note that we lost observations because publications <lb/>could not be matched to the CHI classification system or there was no information about the <lb/>length of the publication available. As a dependent variable, we used how often a trial-related <lb/>publication was cited in subsequent publications that listed at least one author with an Indian <lb/>affiliation. This measure allows us to examine the impact of trial-related publications within <lb/>the Indian science system, as shown in Models 1, 2, and 3. In Models 4, 5, and 6, we included <lb/>only those forward citations associated with at least one author from India that were made in <lb/>the first three years following the publication of the focal phase 3 trial-related publication. The <lb/>dependent variable is a count variable, i.e., a variable which can take only non-negative integer <lb/>values including zero. Therefore, we use negative binomial regressions with Huber-White <lb/>robust standard errors, which is a standard model for analyzing count data. All regressions <lb/>include several publication-and trial-related control variables. An overview of the variables <lb/>can be found in Table 2. <lb/>In Models 7, 8, and 9 we use a weighted count of forward citations found in publications <lb/>with at least one author affiliated with India as the dependent variable. More specifically, we <lb/>weighted each publication by the number of countries listed in the authors&apos; affiliations in <lb/>order to account for the contribution of Indian authors to each forward citation. Conse-<lb/>quently, a forward citation that lists India and two other countries in the author affiliations <lb/>would contribute 1/3 to India&apos;s weighted citation count. In Models 10, 11, and 12, we include <lb/>only weighted forward citations that were made in the first three years after publication of the <lb/>focal article. We analyzed the models using weighted citations as the dependent variable, and <lb/>we relied on Tobit regression models with Huber-White robust standard errors. These models <lb/>are suitable when data entries for a considerable number of cases are equal to zero and when <lb/>Table 2. Description of variables and summary statistics. <lb/>Variable <lb/>Description <lb/>N Mean SD Min. Max. <lb/>Citations by Indian authors <lb/>Number of forward citations reporting at least one author affiliation in India <lb/>385 1.60 3.90 <lb/>0 <lb/>41 <lb/>Citations by Indian authors in the first <lb/>three years after publication <lb/>Number of forward citations reporting at least one author affiliation in India in the <lb/>first three years after publication of the focal publication <lb/>385 1.21 2.63 <lb/>0 <lb/>26 <lb/>Weighted citations by Indian authors <lb/>Weighted number of forward citations reporting at least one author affiliation in <lb/>India <lb/>385 1.05 2.77 <lb/>0 <lb/>29.62 <lb/>Weighted citations by Indian authors in the <lb/>first three years after publication <lb/>Weighted number of forward citations reporting at least one author affiliation in <lb/>India in the first three years after publication of the focal publication <lb/>385 0.78 1.89 <lb/>0 <lb/>19 <lb/>Indian author <lb/>Dummy variable indicating the presence or lack of at least one author affiliation in <lb/>India <lb/>385 0.18 0.38 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>No preceding phase 2 <lb/>Dummy variable indicating whether the phase 3 trial had no preceding phase 2 trial <lb/>conducted in India <lb/>385 0.86 0.35 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Basic research journal <lb/>Dummy variable indicating whether the publication appeared in a journal classified as <lb/>&quot;basic biomedical research&quot; or &quot;clinical investigation&quot; according to the CHI journal <lb/>classification <lb/>385 0.11 0.31 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Number of authors <lb/>Number of authors of the article <lb/>385 12.95 20.77 <lb/>1 <lb/>373 <lb/>Page count <lb/>Number of pages in the article <lb/>385 8.20 2.36 <lb/>1 <lb/>23 <lb/>Number of countries (publication) <lb/>Number of countries involved in the publication according to author affiliations <lb/>385 5.26 4.44 <lb/>1 <lb/>40 <lb/>Traditional country co-author <lb/>Dummy variable indicating whether at least one author affiliation is in a traditional <lb/>clinical trial country <lb/>385 0.96 0.20 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Life-threatening disease <lb/>Clinical trial addresses a life-threatening disease according to FDA regulations <lb/>385 0.50 0.50 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Industry sponsor <lb/>Clinical trial sponsored by a company <lb/>385 0.91 0.29 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Number of countries (trial) <lb/>Number of countries in which the clinical trial is conducted <lb/>385 20.23 10.74 <lb/>1 <lb/>46 <lb/>Domestic sponsor <lb/>Clinical trial sponsored by an organization based in India <lb/>385 0.05 0.22 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<body>the data are roughly continuously distributed over positive values. We use ordinary least <lb/>squares regressions as an alternative method to assess the robustness of our findings for <lb/>weighted citation counts. In addition, we use an auxiliary analysis to ensure that our results are <lb/>not driven by clinical trials testing generic drugs or biosimilars. To carry out this analysis, we <lb/>add a control variable to our analysis that indicates whether a clinical trial is sponsored by <lb/>companies that exclusively produce generics and biosimilars or indicates the evaluation of <lb/>generics or biosimilars in its official title or description. <lb/>Our aim is to investigate whether Indian authors cite publications related to phase 3 trials <lb/>with or without preceding phase 2 trials more often. <lb/>Results <lb/>Clinical trials in India <lb/>With respect to the changes in phase 3 clinical trials over time, visual inspection of Fig 2 sug-<lb/>gests that the repeal of the phase lag requirement enabled Indian researchers to conduct phase <lb/>3 trials without having to carry out a preceding phase 2 trials from 2005 on. In subsequent <lb/>years, the number of phase 3 trials without preceding phase 2 trials increased considerably <lb/>until 2008. <lb/>The vast majority of phase 3 clinical trials without preceding phase 2 trials that started after <lb/>2005 were sponsored by biotechnology and pharmaceutical companies, while a minority were <lb/>sponsored by universities and research institutes (see Fig 3). Importantly, most phase 3 trials <lb/>were sponsored by companies and other organizations headquartered in traditional clinical <lb/>research countries. <lb/>Fig 2. Phase 3 trials conducted in India. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163.g002 <lb/>Fig 3. Sponsors of phase 3 trials conducted in India without preceding phase 2 trials. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Relaxing trial regulation and the Indian scientific knowledge base-Descriptive <lb/>results. We find that the absolute number of trial-related publications and the absolute num-<lb/>ber of citations of publications related to those trials increased over time (see Table 3). How-<lb/>ever, the involvement of Indian-based researchers in trial-related publication activities <lb/>remained modest following the repeal of the phase lag. In order to account for the countries <lb/>involved, we computed weighted publication and citations counts in which each publication <lb/>or citation was weighted by the number of countries involved. The average number of <lb/>weighted trial-related publications by Indian authors is slightly (but not significantly) higher <lb/>for phase 3 trials that were not preceded by a phase 2 trial in India (0.053) (i.e., trials that were <lb/>affected by the regulatory change) than for phase 3 trials that were preceded by a phase 2 trial <lb/>(0.045). In contrast, the z-test indicates that, on average, India-based researchers refer in their <lb/>follow-on work significantly more to phase 3 trial-related publications with preceding phase 2 <lb/>trials conducted in India than to phase 3 trial-related publications without preceding phase 2 <lb/>trials. <lb/>Table 3 indicates that the engagement of Indian researchers in trial-related publications is <lb/>generally lower for industry-sponsored trials (i.e., trials predominantly sponsored by Western <lb/>multinational companies). In contrast to our findings for the entire sample, we find that for <lb/>Table 3. Number of phase 3 trials, publications, and citations. <lb/>Phase 3 trials with <lb/>preceding phase 2 <lb/>trials <lb/>Phase 3 trials with <lb/>preceding phase 2 <lb/>trials <lb/>Phase 3 Trials <lb/>without preceding <lb/>phase 2 trials <lb/>Industry-sponsored <lb/>phase 3 trials with <lb/>preceding phase 2 trials <lb/>Industry-sponsored <lb/>phase 3 trials without <lb/>preceding phase 2 trials <lb/>Trial start years <lb/>2002-2004 <lb/>2005-2012 <lb/>2005-2012 <lb/>2005-2012 <lb/>2005-2012 <lb/>Number of trials <lb/>3 <lb/>100 <lb/>622 <lb/>91 <lb/>551 <lb/>Number of publications <lb/>7 <lb/>71 <lb/>471 <lb/>67 <lb/>423 <lb/>Number of publications by Indian authors <lb/>1 <lb/>14 <lb/>89 <lb/>11 <lb/>49 <lb/>Number of weighted publications by Indian <lb/>authors <lb/>0.143 <lb/>4.474 <lb/>33.252 <lb/>2.640 <lb/>12.012 <lb/>Average number of publications per trial <lb/>(Number of trial-related publications / Number <lb/>of trials) <lb/>2.333 <lb/>0.710 <lb/>0.757 <lb/>0.736 <lb/>0.768 <lb/>Average number of publications by Indian <lb/>authors per trial (Number of trial-related <lb/>publications by Indian authors / Number of <lb/>trials) <lb/>0.333 <lb/>0.140 <lb/>0.143 <lb/>0.121 <lb/>0.089 <lb/>Average number of weighted publications by <lb/>Indian authors per trial (Number of weighted <lb/>trial-related publications by Indian authors / <lb/>Number of trials) <lb/>0.048 <lb/>0.045 <lb/>0.053 <lb/>0.029 <lb/>0.022 <lb/>Number of citations <lb/>223 <lb/>5,968 <lb/>34,464 <lb/>5,680 <lb/>33,210 <lb/>Number of citations by Indian authors <lb/>3 <lb/>140 <lb/>592 <lb/>67 <lb/>443 <lb/>Number of weighted citations by Indian authors <lb/>0.411 <lb/>97.565 <lb/>366.820 <lb/>42.449 <lb/>281.478 <lb/>Average number of citations per trial (Number <lb/>of citations to trial-related publications / <lb/>Number of trials) <lb/>74.333 <lb/>59.680 <lb/>55.408 <lb/>62.418 <lb/>60.272 <lb/>Average number of citations by Indian authors <lb/>per trial (Number of citations to trial-related <lb/>publications by Indian authors / Number of <lb/>trials) <lb/>1.000 <lb/>1.400 <lb/>0.952 <lb/>0.736 <lb/>0.804 <lb/>Average number of weighted citations by Indian <lb/>authors per trial (Number of weighted citations <lb/>to trial-related publications by Indian authors / <lb/>Number of trials) <lb/>0.137 <lb/>0.976 <lb/>0.590 <lb/>0.466 <lb/>0.511 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<body>industry-sponsored trials, the average number of (weighted) publications by Indian authors <lb/>for phase 3 trials without preceding phase 2 trials is lower than for trials with preceding phase <lb/>2 trials. <lb/>Relaxing trial regulation and the Indian scientific knowledge base-<lb/>Multivariate analysis <lb/>Our regression results, which are presented in Table 4, suggest that the number of citations by <lb/>Indian authors increases when an author working for an Indian organization was involved in <lb/>the publication related to a phase 3 clinical trial conducted in India. In the negative binomial <lb/>regressions, we do not find significant associations between the absence of a preceding phase 2 <lb/>study conducted in India and the number of citations by Indian researchers. However, we find <lb/>a significant negative interaction between Indian Author and No Preceding Phase 2 in Model 3, <lb/>indicating that Indian authors cite trial-related publications less frequently when the corre-<lb/>sponding phase 3 clinical trial did not have a phase 2 study conducted in India. However, this <lb/>negative interaction disappears when we restrict the number of citations to forward citations <lb/>made in the first three years after the publication of a trial-related study. <lb/>As in the case of unweighted forward citations, our results for weighted forward citations <lb/>suggest that Indian researchers are more likely to refer to phase 3 clinical trial-related publica-<lb/>tions that have been authored by Indian researchers than to those without Indian authors. <lb/>When comparing trials with and without preceding phase 2 trials, we find significant differ-<lb/>ences in terms of the number of citations when we weight the number of subsequent citations <lb/>by the number of countries involved (Models 8 and 11). However, the coefficient for No Pre-<lb/>ceding Phase 2 loses significance when we introduce the interaction between Indian Author <lb/>and No Preceding Phase 2 to the analysis. Negative coefficients in Models 9 and 12 indicate <lb/>that publications associated with phase 3 clinical trials without preceding phase 2 trials receive <lb/>fewer citations by Indian authors. The results for the weighted citations counts remain qualita-<lb/>tively similar if ordinary least squares regressions are used to analyze weighted citation counts. <lb/>Notably, our results are not driven by clinical trials of generic drugs or biosimilars as demon-<lb/>strated by the auxiliary analysis described in the Methods section. <lb/>With respect to the control variables, we find a robust positive association between the pres-<lb/>ence of co-authors working for organizations from traditional clinical research countries (i.e., <lb/>countries in North America, Western Europe, and selected Asia-Pacific locations) and cita-<lb/>tions by Indian authors. <lb/>Moreover, we find that phase 3 trials sponsored by biotechnology or pharmaceutical com-<lb/>panies are cited less by Indian authors than trials sponsored by academic, healthcare, or phil-<lb/>anthropic organizations. We also find that Indian authors more frequently cite trial-related <lb/>publications that refer to trials sponsored by domestic companies. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This paper&apos;s objective is to improve our understanding of how policy changes related to clini-<lb/>cal trials affect the scientific knowledge base. An understanding of the complex dynamics in <lb/>this context is important for effective regulation and, in our case, for understanding the conse-<lb/>quences of relaxing clinical trial regulations. India serves as the context of our study, as the <lb/>country has been a first-choice location for the offshoring of clinical trials and as it changed its <lb/>clinical trial regulations in order to attract more late-stage (offshored) clinical trials. <lb/>The results of our empirical analyses suggest that the regulatory change (i.e., allowing phase <lb/>3 trials to be carried out even if they were not preceded by a phase 2 trial in the country) was <lb/>followed by an initial increase in the number of phase 3 trials without preceding phase 2 trials, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">especially trials sponsored by Western pharmaceutical companies. However, the benefits for <lb/>India&apos;s domestic scientific knowledge base have been limited, as the involvement of India-<lb/>based researchers in trial-related publication activities remained modest after the repeal of the <lb/>phase lag requirement. In addition, the potential for learning from the additional trials appears <lb/>to be limited, as publications referring to phase 3 trials without preceding phase 2 trials are less <lb/>Table 4. Regression analysis of citations of trial-related publications by Indian authors. <lb/>(1) <lb/>(2) <lb/>(3) <lb/>(4) <lb/>(5) <lb/>(6) <lb/>(7) <lb/>(8) <lb/>(9) <lb/>(10) <lb/>(11) <lb/>(12) <lb/>Regression model: <lb/>Negative binomial <lb/>Tobit <lb/>Dependent variable: <lb/>Citations to trial-related <lb/>publications by Indian <lb/>authors <lb/>Citations by Indian authors <lb/>in the first three years after <lb/>publication <lb/>Weighted citations by Indian <lb/>authors <lb/>Weighted citations by Indian <lb/>authors in the first three <lb/>years after publication <lb/></div>

			<body>Indian author <lb/>0.63 ��� 0.62 ��� 1.19 ��� <lb/>0.59 �� <lb/>0.58 �� <lb/>1.12 ��� <lb/>1.86 �� <lb/>1.88 �� <lb/>6.52 ��� <lb/>1.24 � <lb/>1.25 � <lb/>4.85 ��� <lb/>(0.23) <lb/>(0.23) <lb/>(0.37) <lb/>(0.24) <lb/>(0.23) <lb/>(0.38) <lb/>(0.92) <lb/>(0.91) <lb/>(2.14) <lb/>(0.68) <lb/>(0.66) <lb/>(1.72) <lb/>No preceding phase 2 <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>-0.22 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-1.78 � <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>-1.38 � <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>(0.21) <lb/>(0.27) <lb/>(0.22) <lb/>(0.27) <lb/>(0.93) <lb/>(0.65) <lb/>(0.72) <lb/>(0.53) <lb/>Indian author � No preceding phase 2 <lb/>-0.73 � <lb/>-0.71 <lb/>-5.83 �� <lb/>-4.55 �� <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>(0.43) <lb/>(2.35) <lb/>(1.80) <lb/>Basic research journal <lb/>-0.17 <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>-0.09 <lb/>-0.29 <lb/>-0.27 <lb/>-0.20 <lb/>-0.86 <lb/>-0.64 <lb/>-0.34 <lb/>-0.92 <lb/>-0.74 <lb/>-0.48 <lb/>(0.27) <lb/>(0.27) <lb/>(0.27) <lb/>(0.32) <lb/>(0.32) <lb/>(0.32) <lb/>(0.91) <lb/>(0.88) <lb/>(0.84) <lb/>(0.77) <lb/>(0.74) <lb/>(0.69) <lb/>Number of authors <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.03) <lb/>(0.03) <lb/>(0.01) <lb/>Page count <lb/>0.09 �� <lb/>0.09 �� <lb/>0.09 �� <lb/>0.09 �� <lb/>0.09 �� <lb/>0.09 �� <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>Number of countries (publication) <lb/>0.05 �� <lb/>0.05 �� <lb/>0.06 ��� <lb/>0.05 �� <lb/>0.05 �� <lb/>0.06 �� <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>Traditional country co-author <lb/>1.18 �� <lb/>1.19 �� <lb/>1.08 � <lb/>1.60 ��� 1.60 ��� 1.49 ��� <lb/>6.90 �� <lb/>6.88 �� <lb/>6.22 �� <lb/>4.74 �� <lb/>4.77 �� <lb/>4.21 ��� <lb/>(0.56) <lb/>(0.57) <lb/>(0.57) <lb/>(0.52) <lb/>(0.53) <lb/>(0.55) <lb/>(3.38) <lb/>(3.05) <lb/>(2.62) <lb/>(2.08) <lb/>(1.87) <lb/>(1.58) <lb/>Life-threatening disease <lb/>0.42 ��� 0.41 ��� 0.42 ��� <lb/>0.40 �� <lb/>0.38 �� <lb/>0.39 �� <lb/>0.85 � <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0.74 <lb/>0.68 � <lb/>0.58 <lb/>0.59 � <lb/>(0.15) <lb/>(0.15) <lb/>(0.15) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.46) <lb/>(0.47) <lb/>(0.46) <lb/>(0.36) <lb/>(0.36) <lb/>(0.35) <lb/>Industry sponsor <lb/>-1.13 ��� -1.13 ��� -1.10 ��� -1.14 ��� -1.14 ��� -1.11 ��� <lb/>-3.34 �� <lb/>-3.63 �� <lb/>-3.58 �� <lb/>-2.34 � <lb/>-2.56 � <lb/>-2.59 �� <lb/>(0.38) <lb/>(0.38) <lb/>(0.37) <lb/>(0.40) <lb/>(0.40) <lb/>(0.39) <lb/>(1.54) <lb/>(1.58) <lb/>(1.44) <lb/>(1.30) <lb/>(1.32) <lb/>(1.24) <lb/>Number of countries (trial) <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>(0.01) <lb/>(0.01) <lb/>(0.01) <lb/>(0.01) <lb/>(0.01) <lb/>(0.01) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.03) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>Domestic sponsor <lb/>1.12 �� <lb/>1.15 �� <lb/>1.21 �� <lb/>1.52 ��� 1.56 ��� 1.61 ��� <lb/>4.95 <lb/>4.78 � <lb/>4.63 � <lb/>3.98 �� <lb/>3.86 �� <lb/>3.71 �� <lb/>(0.50) <lb/>(0.50) <lb/>(0.50) <lb/>(0.45) <lb/>(0.45) <lb/>(0.47) <lb/>(3.06) <lb/>(2.77) <lb/>(2.37) <lb/>(1.97) <lb/>(1.80) <lb/>(1.54) <lb/>Trial start years <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Publication years <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Yes <lb/>Constant <lb/>-4.19 ��� -4.06 ��� -4.21 ��� -4.61 ��� -4.43 ��� -4.56 ��� -11.23 ��� -9.43 ��� -10.02 ��� -8.41 ��� -7.05 ��� -7.35 ��� <lb/>(1.46) <lb/>(1.47) <lb/>(1.47) <lb/>(1.44) <lb/>(1.46) <lb/>(1.47) <lb/>(3.82) <lb/>(3.26) <lb/>(3.03) <lb/>(2.54) <lb/>(2.22) <lb/>(2.02) <lb/>Sigma <lb/>3.55 ��� <lb/>3.48 ��� <lb/>3.33 ��� <lb/>2.76 ��� 2.69 ��� 2.56 ��� <lb/>(0.45) <lb/>(0.41) <lb/>(0.35) <lb/>(0.36) <lb/>(0.31) <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>N <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>385 <lb/>AIC <lb/>1019.31 1020.87 1021.04 950.13 <lb/>951.39 <lb/>951.74 <lb/>1074.18 1069.88 1056.94 <lb/>954.86 <lb/>950.53 <lb/>937.09 <lb/>BIC <lb/>1118.14 1123.65 1127.77 1048.96 1054.18 1058.47 1176.96 1176.62 1167.63 1057.64 1057.26 1047.78 <lb/>Robust standard errors in parentheses <lb/>� p&lt;0.10, <lb/>�� p&lt;0.05, <lb/>��� p&lt;0.01 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<body>frequently used in Indian researchers&apos; subsequent research activities than publications related <lb/>to phase 3 trials with preceding phase 2 trials. Overall, our findings contradict the expectation <lb/>that the changes to the Indian clinical trial regulations enacted in January 2005 would effec-<lb/>tively support knowledge transfer, the advancement of the domestic scientific knowledge base, <lb/>and the development of new, innovative drugs by domestic companies. The increasing number <lb/>of phase 3 trials without preceding phase 2 trials can be seen as a reflection of India&apos;s growing <lb/>attractiveness as a host country for clinical trials after the repeal of the phase lag requirement. <lb/>India has been able to attract phase 3 trials sponsored primarily by foreign (i.e., predominantly <lb/>Western) companies, especially in the years immediately after the repeal of the phase lag. The <lb/>decreasing number of phase 3 clinical trials without preceding phase 2 trials in more recent <lb/>years may be caused by dissatisfaction among trial sponsors and contract research organiza-<lb/>tions with India&apos;s administrative and institutional environment as well as the perceived loss of <lb/>credibility due to cases of fraud and poorly conducted trials [35]. <lb/>The regulatory amendments provided only limited benefits to India&apos;s science system. More <lb/>specifically, the involvement of Indian researchers in trial-related scientific publications <lb/>remains quite modest and knowledge generated by phase 3 trials without preceding phase 2 <lb/>trials has a limited impact among domestic researchers compared to phase 3 trials with preced-<lb/>ing phase 2 trials. In this regard, our results reveal that the benefits of offshored late-stage clini-<lb/>cal trials for the domestic scientific knowledge base seem to be limited, as Indian researchers <lb/>are still only involved in trial-related publication activities to a minor extent. One potential <lb/>explanation for this finding is that Indian researchers&apos; access to clinical trial data and, hence, <lb/>the opportunities they have to contribute to data analysis and publication activities may be <lb/>considerably restricted for industry-sponsored trials, which represent the vast majority of <lb/>phase 3 trials without a preceding phase 2 trials [36]. An additional explanation for the limited <lb/>involvement of Indian researchers in trial-related publications is the, until recently, rather lim-<lb/>ited emphasis many Indian medical institutions put on publication activities. A recent study <lb/>analyzing the publications of Indian medical institutions between 2005-2014 using Scopus, <lb/>revealed that nearly 60% of Indian medical institutions had no single peer-reviewed publica-<lb/>tion in a decade [37]. While policy makers aim to increase publication rates, e.g., by increasing <lb/>the minimum number of research publications that is required for promotion to the associate <lb/>or full professor level [38], it takes time to establish an academic culture that emphasizes the <lb/>importance of publications in (international) journals. In addition, Indian researchers may <lb/>need to be acquainted with knowledge about habits and informal rules which spur successful <lb/>publishing in international journals. <lb/>Our finding corresponds to earlier contributions stressing the limited involvement of <lb/>researchers from non-traditional clinical trial countries in trial-related publication activities as <lb/>well as the low number of publications by industry scientists working in R&amp;D labs in non-tra-<lb/>ditional countries when compared to publications by their counterparts in Europe and North <lb/>America [33,39]. Moreover, Phase 3 trials sponsored by biotechnology or pharmaceutical com-<lb/>panies are associated with fewer citations by Indian authors than trials sponsored by academic, <lb/>healthcare, or philanthropic organizations. This finding may be driven by concerns related to <lb/>the influence of industry sponsors on the outcomes of clinical trials, the restricted dissemina-<lb/>tion of results in scientific publications, and scientific and ethical misbehavior among Indian <lb/>companies conducting clinical trials [35,40]. <lb/>In addition, we find that the number of forward citations made by Indian authors is lower <lb/>for publications related to phase 3 trials that are not associated with a preceding phase 2 trials <lb/>when all trials in our sample are considered. This indicates that the knowledge produced in <lb/>offshored, late-stage clinical trials is only used by domestic researchers to a limited extent, as <lb/>also expressed in the rather low number of forward citations of trial-related publications and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<body>the particularly low number of forward citations of publications associated with industry-<lb/>sponsored trials. <lb/>However, the presence of co-authors working for organizations from traditional clinical <lb/>research countries increases citations by Indian authors. This positive relationship might be <lb/>driven by several factors. For example, researchers from traditional countries may have more <lb/>experience in analyzing clinical trial data and in writing contributions for scientific journals <lb/>that communicate trial results to the international scientific community. This experience may <lb/>increase the quality of trial-related articles and, hence, the number of forward citations, includ-<lb/>ing citations by Indian authors. In addition, researchers from traditional countries may self-<lb/>select into clinical research projects that have a higher probability of success, a higher degree of <lb/>novelty, and higher scientific quality. Moreover, these authors may share their publications <lb/>within their professional networks which may increase the attention paid to those publications <lb/>within the scientific community and, hence, increase the number of citations, including the <lb/>number of citations by Indian authors. <lb/>Clinical trials sponsored by Indian organizations are likely to focus on disease areas that <lb/>predominantly address health problems prevalent in India, which increases their relevance for <lb/>domestic researchers and authors and, consequently, the number of citations by Indian <lb/>researchers. <lb/>Taken together, our findings suggest that abolishing the phase lag reduces the ability of <lb/>Indian researchers to learn from trials if the outsourced trial only focuses on Phase 3 and does <lb/>not include Phase 2. A potential explanation for this seemingly limited knowledge transfer can <lb/>be found in the nature of clinical trials. While clinical trials through phase 2 can be described <lb/>as highly knowledge-intensive [41] trials that may offer opportunities for knowledge transfer <lb/>to Indian researchers, late-stage trials focused on data generation provide fewer opportunities <lb/>for knowledge transfer. Consequently, it seems much more difficult for Indian researchers to <lb/>learn from offshored phase 3 trials that are not accompanied by preceding phase 2 trials. As a <lb/>consequence, Indian researchers cite publications that refer to phase 3 trials that are not associ-<lb/>ated with preceding phase 2 trials less frequently than trials with preceding phase 2 trials. In <lb/>addition, the limited involvement of Indian researchers in publication activities related to late-<lb/>stage clinical trials may further increase the complexity of knowledge transfers and complicate <lb/>the application of trial-related knowledge in their own clinical research projects. The conse-<lb/>quences of this limited involvement may reach beyond the individual researcher, as they also <lb/>may make the dissemination of knowledge embodied in trial-related publications through <lb/>Indian researchers&apos; professional networks less likely and less effective. <lb/>Based on these results and interpretations, the Indian case does not suggest that lower regu-<lb/>latory hurdles for late-stage clinical trials provide the expected benefits. Consequently, the <lb/>Indian case may not be the best role model for other non-traditional countries wishing to sup-<lb/>port the development of their domestic scientific knowledge bases through clinical research. <lb/>Instead, our results suggest that governments need to search for alternative ways of promoting <lb/>knowledge transfers and the development of the domestic scientific knowledge base, such as <lb/>investments in domestic scientific and technological capabilities to strengthen the country&apos;s <lb/>absorptive capacity or to attract multinational companies&apos; R&amp;D labs. <lb/>Limitations <lb/>It is important to emphasize that our analyses focus on the consequences of the repeal of the <lb/>phase lag requirement for India&apos;s domestic scientific knowledge base in terms of scientific pub-<lb/>lications and forward citations. Future research may address the impact of this regulatory <lb/>change on India&apos;s abilities to attract talent and to encourage Indian scientists to return from <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<body>abroad, as well as its impact on the establishment of knowledge-intensive R&amp;D service compa-<lb/>nies, FDI, and the direction of domestic research activities. Along similar lines, future research <lb/>may study the consequences of regulatory changes on other dimensions of the domestic <lb/>scientific knowledge base such as the number of domestic researchers in disciplines that are <lb/>relevant for clinical research, their training and education, their involvement in clinical trials, <lb/>or changes in domestic R&amp;D investments that have not been the focus of this study. Another <lb/>area of research might be the consequences of this repeal for the availability of new pharma-<lb/>ceuticals to the domestic population. <lb/>Our empirical analyses build on data covering clinical trials and trial-related publications <lb/>that are listed in international databases. This data may not fully account for trial-related publi-<lb/>cations by Indian authors in domestic journals. Future research may assess whether the conse-<lb/>quences of changing clinical trial regulations differ when domestic databases are considered. <lb/>Moreover, our data do not allow us to assess the role Indian researchers play in trial-related <lb/>publications (i.e., whether they are involved in different scholarly activities and whether they <lb/>solely contribute data) or the extent to which clinical trial sponsors restrict domestic researcher <lb/>from accessing data and publishing trial results. Future research may also assess the conse-<lb/>quences of outsourcing trial-management tasks to contract research organizations for the <lb/>domestic scientific knowledge base. <lb/>ClinicalTrials.gov provides a comprehensive registry for clinical trials. However, there <lb/>might be trials that have been affected by India&apos;s regulatory change but have not been regis-<lb/>tered in ClinicalTrials.gov. Instead these trials may have been registered in other registries as <lb/>the compounds tested in these trials did not meet the requirements for mandatory registration <lb/>in ClinicalTrials.gov or the trial sponsor did not intend to market the compound in the United <lb/>States once clinical testing had been completed. Since India&apos;s domestic registry for clinical tri-<lb/>als had not been established yet around the time of the regulatory change studied in this paper, <lb/>we could not supplement the data obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov with data on trials that <lb/>were only registered domestically. <lb/>ClinicalTrials.gov employs automated and manual reviews to identify possible errors, defi-<lb/>ciencies, or inconsistencies in the information provided by trial sponsors or investigators. <lb/>There are considerably penalties for noncompliance with the rules of clinical trial registration <lb/>[42]. Nevertheless, not all trials are subject to manual reviews and checks and our study has to <lb/>rely on the accuracy of the information that trial sponsors and investigators report to the data-<lb/>base. While the ClinicalTrials.gov provides a list of facilities that the trial is conducted in, it <lb/>does not contain information concerning the recruitment of subjects on the facility level. <lb/>Hence, it is not possible to verify whether trial subjects have been recruited in a particular facil-<lb/>ity or how important a specific location was for recruiting subjects. <lb/>Given the above discussion, our analysis serves as a starting point for a debate on how <lb/>non-traditional countries&apos; science systems can benefit from the internationalization of clinical <lb/>trials. As part of this debate, researchers need to carefully evaluate whether offshored clinical <lb/>research provides other benefits for non-traditional countries&apos; science and health-care <lb/>systems. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Table. Correlations among independent variables. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/>S2 Table. Data on phase 3 clinical trials conducted in India. <lb/>(TXT) <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank Anne Assmus, Saradindu Bhaduri, Henry Sauermann, and the participants at the <lb/>Workshop on Medical Innovation 2016 in Brighton for stimulating discussions and valuable <lb/>suggestions. Manuel Donaubauer provided competent research assistance. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Bastian Rake, Carolin Haeussler. <lb/>Data curation: Bastian Rake. <lb/>Formal analysis: Bastian Rake. <lb/>Investigation: Bastian Rake, Carolin Haeussler. <lb/>Methodology: Bastian Rake, Carolin Haeussler. <lb/>Resources: Carolin Haeussler. <lb/>Validation: Bastian Rake, Carolin Haeussler. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Bastian Rake, Carolin Haeussler. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Bastian Rake, Carolin Haeussler. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Haeussler C, Rake B (2017) The Changing Geography of Clinical Research: A Critical Analysis of its <lb/>Drivers. Industrial and Corporate Change 26 (2): 285-310. <lb/>2. Glickman SW, McHutchison JG, Peterson ED, Cairns CB, Harrington RA, Califf RM et al. (2009) Ethical <lb/>and Scientific Implications of the Globalization of Clinical Research. New England Journal of Medicine <lb/>360 (8): 816-823. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMsb0803929 PMID: 19228627 <lb/>3. Thiers FA, Sinskey AJ, Berndt ER (2008) Trends in the Globalization of Clinical Trials. Nature Reviews <lb/>Drug Discovery 7 (1): 13-14. <lb/>4. Drain PK, Parker RA, Robine M, Holmes KK (2018) Global migration of clinical research during the era <lb/>of trial registration. PLoS ONE 13 (2): e0192413. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0192413 PMID: <lb/>29489839 <lb/>5. Atal I, Trinquart L, Porcher R, Ravaud P (2015) Differential Globalization of Industry-and Non-Industry-<lb/>Sponsored Clinical Trials. PLoS ONE 10 (12): e0145122. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0145122 PMID: 26658791 <lb/>6. Jommi C, Paruzzolo S (2007) Public administration and R&amp;D localisation by pharmaceutical and bio-<lb/>tech companies: A theoretical framework and the Italian case-study. Health Policy 81 (1): 117-130. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.healthpol.2006.05.010 PMID: 16824641 <lb/>7. Lockhart M, Babar Z, Garg S (2010) Evaluation of policies to support drug development in New Zea-<lb/>land. Health Policy 96 (2): 108-117. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.healthpol.2010.01.012 PMID: 20170976 <lb/>8. Nundy S, Gulhati CM (2005) A New Colonialism?-Conducting Clinical Trials in India. New England <lb/>Journal of Medicine 352 (16): 1633-1636. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMp048361 PMID: 15843665 <lb/>9. Lang T, Siribaddana S (2012) Clinical Trials Have Gone Global: Is This a Good Thing. PLoS Medicine <lb/>9 (6): e1001228. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001228 PMID: 22719228 <lb/>10. Kamat VR (2014) Fast, Cheap, and Out of Control? Speculations and Ethical Concerns in the Conduct <lb/>of Outsourced Clinical Trials in India. Social Science &amp; Medicine 104: 48-55. <lb/>11. Fisher JA, Cottingham MD, Kalbaugh CA (2015) Peering into the pharmaceutical &quot;pipeline&quot;: Investiga-<lb/>tional drugs, clinical trials, and industry priorities. Social Science &amp; Medicine 131: 322-330. <lb/>12. Haakonsson SJ, Jensen PDO, Mudambi SM (2013) A Co-evolutionary Perspective on the Drivers of Inter-<lb/>national Sourcing of Pharmaceutical R&amp;D to India. Journal of Economic Geography 13 (4): 677-700. <lb/>13. Unni VK (2012) Indian Patent Law and TRIPS: Redrawing the Flexibility Framework in the Context of <lb/>Public Policy and Health. Pacific McGeorge Global Business &amp; Development Law Journal 25: 323-447. <lb/>14. Maiti R, Raghavendra M (2007) Clinical Trials in India. Pharmacological Research 56 (1): 1-10. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.phrs.2007.02.004 PMID: 17391981 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 15 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>15. Sariola S, Ravindran D, Kumar A, Jeffery R (2015) Big-pharmaceuticalisation: Clinical Trials and Con-<lb/>tract Research Organisations in India. Social Science &amp; Medicine 131: 239-246. <lb/>16. Ministry of Health Family Welfare (2005) Drugs and Cosmetics (2nd amendment) Rules, 2005-<lb/>Notification. <lb/>17. Chaudhuri S (2005) The WTO and India&apos;s Pharmaceuticals Industry: Patent Protection TRIPS and <lb/>Developing Countries. New Delhi: Oxford University Press. <lb/>18. Lanjouw JO (1998) The Introduction of Pharmaceutical Product Patents in India: &quot;Heartless Exploitation <lb/>of the Poor and Suffering&quot;. NBER Working Paper 6366. <lb/>19. Iyer VRK, Reddy OC, Desai DA, Sanchar R (1996) Peoples&apos; Commission on GATT: Report on the Con-<lb/>stitutional Implications of the Final Act Embodying the Results of the Uruguay Round of Multinational <lb/>Trade Negotiations: Centre for Study of Global Trade System Development, New Delhi. <lb/>20. Ramani SV (2002) Who is Interested in Biotech? R&amp;D Strategies, Knowledge Base and Market Sales <lb/>of Indian Biopharmaceutical Firms. Research Policy 31 (3): 381-398. <lb/>21. Guennif S, Ramani SV (2012) Explaining Divergence in Catching-up in Pharma Between India and Bra-<lb/>zil Using the NSI Framework. Research Policy 41 (2): 430-441. <lb/>22. Haley GT, Haley UCV (2012) The Effects of Patent-law Changes on Innovation: The Case of India&apos;s <lb/>Pharmaceutical Industry. Technological Forecasting and Social Change 79 (4): 607-619. <lb/>23. Athreye S, Kale D, Ramani SV (2009) Experimentation with Strategy and the Evolution of Dynamic <lb/>Capability in the Indian Pharmaceutical Sector. Industrial and Corporate Change 18 (4): 729-759. <lb/>24. Kneller R (2010) The Importance of New Companies for Drug Discovery: Origins of a Decade of New <lb/>Drugs. Nature Reviews Drug Discovery 9 (11): 867-882. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrd3251 PMID: <lb/>21031002 <lb/>25. Ramani SV, Maria A (2005) TRIPS: Its Possible Impact on Biotech Segment of the Indian Pharmaceuti-<lb/>cal Industry. Economic and Political Weekly 40 (7): 675-683. <lb/>26. Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development Committee (1999) Transforming India Into a Knowledge Power. <lb/>27. Sharma DC (2004) India pressed to relax rules on clinical trials. The Lancet 363 (9420): 1528-1529. <lb/>28. (2004) Guinea Pigs. The Financial Express. https://www.financialexpress.com/archive/guinea-pigs/ <lb/>117217/. Accessed 10 July 2018. <lb/>29. (2006) Clinical trials: concern over liberal permission. The Hindu. https://www.thehindu.com/todays-<lb/>paper/tp-national/clinical-trials-concern-over-liberal-permission/article3234692.ece. Accessed 10 July <lb/>2018. <lb/>30. Reid S, Ramani SV (2012) The Harnessing of Biotechnology in India: Which Roads to Travel. Techno-<lb/>logical Forecasting and Social Change 79 (4): 648-664. <lb/>31. Brusoni S, Geuna A (2003) An international comparison of sectoral knowledge bases. Persistence and <lb/>integration in the pharmaceutical industry. Research Policy 32 (10): 1897-1912. <lb/>32. Stephan PE (1996) The Economics of Science. Journal of Economic Literature 34 (3): 1199-1235. <lb/>33. Hoekman J, Frenken K, de Zeeuw D, Lambers Heerspink H (2012) The Geographical Distribution of <lb/>Leadership in Globalized Clinical Trials. PLoS ONE 7 (10): e45984. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0045984 PMID: 23071532 <lb/>34. Hamilton KS (2003) Subfield and Level Classification of Journals. CHI Research Inc CHI No. 2012-R. <lb/>35. Rohatgi P, Chabbra S, Gogia A, Kakar A (2016) Clinical Research: What Potential Investigators Should <lb/>Know. Current Medicine Research and Practice 6 (1): 30-34. <lb/>36. Gøtzsche P, Hro ´bjartsson A, Johansen H, Haahr M, Altman D, Chan AW(2006) Constraints on Publica-<lb/>tion Rights in Industry-Initiated Clinical Trials. JAMA 295 (14): 1641-1646. <lb/>37. Ray S, Shah I, Nundy S (2016) The research output from Indian medical institutions between 2005 and <lb/>2014. Current Medicine Research and Practice 6 (2): 49-58. <lb/>38. Aulakh R (2016) Mandatory publication in India. Setting quotas for research output could encourage sci-<lb/>entific fraud. BMJ 354. <lb/>39. Rafols I, Hopkins MM, Hoekman J, Siepel J, O&apos;Hare A, Perianes-Rodrı ´guez A et al. (2014) Big Pharma, <lb/>Little Science?: A Bibliometric Perspective on Big Pharma&apos;s R&amp;D Decline. Technological Forecasting <lb/>and Social Change 81: 22-38. <lb/>40. Lundh A, Lexchin J, Mintzes B, Schroll JB, Bero L (2017) Industry sponsorship and research outcome. <lb/>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews (2): MR000033. <lb/>41. Azoulay P (2004) Capturing Knowledge within and across Firm Boundaries: Evidence from Clinical <lb/>Development. The American Economic Review 94 (5): 1591-1612. <lb/>42. US Public Law 110-85 (2007) Food and Drug Administration Amendments Act of 2007. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Clinical trial regulation and pharmaceutical knowledge stock in India <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210163 January 3, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 15 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
