<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
        <front>Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences, 9(1) (2024) 1-17 <lb/>Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences <lb/>https://www.sciendo.com <lb/> †Corresponding author. <lb/>Email address: lihaod@suntien.com <lb/>ISSN 2444-8656 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2478/amns-2024-0638 <lb/>© 2023 Xin Cao, Jianxin Tan, Hao Li, Rui Li, Yifan Wang and Junfeng Zhang, published by Sciendo. <lb/>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution alone 4.0 License. <lb/>Research on Intelligent Management System of Gas Pipeline with Multi-source Data <lb/>Fusion <lb/>Xin Cao 1, † , Jianxin Tan 2 , Hao Li 3 , Rui Li 2 , Yifan Wang 3 , Junfeng Zhang 3 <lb/>1. Hebei Construction&amp;Investment Group Co., Ltd Shijiazhuang, Hebei, 050051, China. <lb/>2. China Suntien Green Energy Co., Ltd Shijiazhuang, Hebei, 050051, China. <lb/>3. Hebei Gas Co., Ltd., Shijiazhuang, Hebei, 050051, China. <lb/>Submission Info <lb/>Communicated by Z. Sabir <lb/>Received January 15, 2024 <lb/>Accepted January 21, 2024 <lb/>Available online February 26, 2024 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Aiming at the current challenges of enormous scale, complex structure, difficult control and frequent accidents of city gas <lb/>high-pressure pipeline network, there are still three aspects of difficulties in the risk monitoring and control of China&apos;s <lb/>city gas high-pressure pipeline network, namely, rough data, shallow assessment, and lack of power. This paper proposes <lb/>an intelligent management system for gas pipelines based on C/S model and J2EE enterprise-level framework, in which <lb/>the failure warning models of gas leakage, Gaussian plume diffusion, and fire and explosion are established. And the <lb/>Kalman filter algorithm improved by DS evidence theory is used for intelligent fusion of Multi-source data, analyzing <lb/>and screening the unified adequate information on data types, extracting state characteristics, classifying warning levels, <lb/>and developing an integrated and visualized pipeline remote diagnosis and warning platform. In the simulation of the <lb/>intelligent management system of gas pipeline, when the wind speed is 1.5m/s in winter, the ground surface is a safe area <lb/>within 12.15m of the gas pipeline. When the maximum wind speed is 10m/s, the upper limit distance of the gas leading <lb/>to fire and explosion is only 2.43m, and the hazardous range of the gas pipeline jet fire is within 12.69m. Relying on the <lb/>gas high-pressure pipeline network in L city for practical experiments and applications, it provides technical support and <lb/>decision-making basis for the construction of intelligent pipeline network, comprehensively improves the risk control <lb/>capability of city gas high-pressure pipeline network, and has reference significance for the risk control of national city <lb/>gas high-pressure pipeline network. <lb/>Keywords: Gas leakage model; Gaussian plume model; DS evidence theory; Kalman filter algorithm; Multi-source <lb/>data fusion; Gas pipeline. <lb/>AMS 2010 codes: 05C82 <lb/></front>

        <note place="headnote">Xin Cao, Jianxin Tan, Hao Li, Rui Li and Yifan Wang and Junfeng Zhang. Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences, <lb/>9(1) (2024) 1-17 <lb/></note>

        <page>2 <lb/></page>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>With the acceleration of urbanization, the safe and efficient operation of gas pipelines, as an important <lb/>part of urban infrastructure, is crucial [1]. Traditional gas pipeline management methods have <lb/>limitations in data processing and risk prediction. Therefore, it is particularly important to research <lb/>and develop an intelligent management system for gas pipelines based on Multi-source data fusion <lb/>[2-3]. The system aims to improve the efficiency and safety of pipeline management by integrating <lb/>and analyzing various data sources. <lb/>There are various data sources involved in gas pipeline management, including but not limited to <lb/>pipeline pressure, flow, and temperature data, geographic information system (GIS) data, and real-<lb/>time monitoring data from sensors [4-6]. The fusion of data from multiple sources can provide a more <lb/>comprehensive view of the system and help assess the operational status and potential risks of <lb/>pipelines more accurately [7]. An efficient, intelligent gas pipeline management system usually <lb/>includes several key components, including data collection, data storage, data analysis, and decision <lb/>support [8-10]. The system should be able to collect and process data from various sensors and <lb/>databases in real-time, utilize advanced data analysis techniques (e.g., machine learning and artificial <lb/>intelligence) to perform risk assessment and prediction, and provide effective decision support [11]. <lb/>Intelligent management systems for gas pipelines with Multi-source data fusion are of great <lb/>significance in improving the safety of city gas supply, optimizing resource allocation, and reducing <lb/>operation and maintenance costs [12-13]. With the further development of technology, such systems <lb/>are expected to be more intelligent and able to provide more accurate risk assessment and more <lb/>effective O&amp;M decision support. The research and development of an intelligent management system <lb/>of gas pipelines with Multi-source data fusion is of great practical significance for improving the <lb/>safety and operational efficiency of urban gas pipelines [14-16]. With the continuous development <lb/>and improvement of related technologies, such systems will play an increasingly important role in <lb/>the field of intelligent management of gas pipelines [17-18]. <lb/>This paper adopts the C/S network architecture and J2EE enterprise application development <lb/>framework based on the basic application modules such as process, user, and authority management <lb/>to establish an intelligent management system for gas pipelines and establish the Database of the <lb/>intelligent management system in order to realize a good integration and sharing with other <lb/>information systems. In the system, relevant prediction and warning models of gas pipeline failure <lb/>are established, i.e., warning models of gas leakage, diffusion, fire and explosion, etc. By means of <lb/>the correlation mathematical model of Multi-source data fusion, the Kalman filter algorithm is <lb/>improved by the introduction of DS evidence theory, and the data of multiple features are fused. For <lb/>the gas pipeline intelligent management system established in this paper, simulation and example <lb/>analysis is carried out from multiple perspectives, such as gas pipeline leakage and diffusion hazard <lb/>range, jet fire hazard range, explosion consequences in hazardous areas, and prediction and warning <lb/>algorithms, respectively. <lb/>2 Gas pipeline intelligent management system architecture <lb/>In order to strengthen the comprehensive ability to deal with potential accidents in gas pipeline <lb/>operation and to establish an emergency response mechanism to quickly and effectively organize <lb/>accident rescue and relief in case of emergency, it is important to clarify the responsibilities and <lb/>obligations of all levels of personnel in the emergency response. To clarify the responsibilities and <lb/>obligations of personnel at all levels in accident emergency response, to protect the lives of employees <lb/>and the public, to protect the environment and the company&apos;s property, to safeguard public order and <lb/>social stability, combined with the actual situation of pipeline operation, the establishment of an <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Research on Intelligent Management System of Gas Pipeline with Multi-source Data Fusion <lb/></note>

        <page>3 <lb/></page>

        <body>intelligent management system applicable to urban gas pipeline is an inevitable choice. This chapter <lb/>establishes the general framework of the intelligent management system of gas pipelines based on <lb/>related technology, which provides support for further realizing the intelligent management of urban <lb/>gas pipelines. <lb/>2.1 Framework of Intelligent Management System for Gas Pipelines <lb/>2.1.1 C/S model architecture <lb/>C / S pattern architecture appeared in the 1980s; the most typical and popular is a two-tier structure, <lb/>one for the client layer, the application program installed in the user&apos;s client, and a centralized user <lb/>interface with a variety of business logic and processing functions. The second layer is the service <lb/>layer; the client user application is connected to the database server through the network. In the C/S <lb/>two-tier structure, the client maintains the application program and accesses the Database directly, <lb/>the server-side holds all the data, and each client maintains a task connection with the Database. The <lb/>client sends a request to the data server through the application program, and the data server responds <lb/>to the request to manipulate the data and returns the result to the client. Utilizing C/S mode to carry <lb/>out data exchange can quickly realize the data response, making the data operation process more <lb/>efficient and faster and providing reliable support for massive data interaction. <lb/>2.1.2 General Architecture of Intelligent Management System <lb/>City gas pipeline intelligent management system should be based on the unified pipeline professional <lb/>database and basic geographic Database as the information source, with enterprise safety production <lb/>related standards and norms system as the policy support, using C/S network architecture and J2EE <lb/>enterprise-level application development framework, based on the process, the user, rights <lb/>management and other basic application modules, to reach the gas pipeline intelligent management <lb/>business required for the various functional applications, and Can form a good integration and sharing <lb/>with other information systems of the enterprise. As a result, this paper establishes the overall <lb/>framework of the city gas pipeline intelligent relationship system, as shown in Figure 1; the overall <lb/>structure of the platform consists of five layers, three support systems, and a management system. <lb/>The five layers are divided from bottom to top as the basic support layer, application support layer, <lb/>business operation layer, decision analysis layer, and strategic target layer, and the three systems <lb/>include information security management system, standardization system, and IT control system. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Xin Cao, Jianxin Tan, Hao Li, Rui Li and Yifan Wang and Junfeng Zhang. Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences, <lb/>9(1) (2024) 1-17 <lb/></note>

        <page>4 <lb/></page>

        <body>SOA Architecture <lb/>Support Platform <lb/>Network Architecture <lb/>Data Sharing Center <lb/>server-side hardware and <lb/>software environment <lb/>Deep Combustion Pipeline Integrity Management Data Model <lb/>Pipeline business data <lb/>Neighborhood <lb/>Information <lb/>Corrosion <lb/>protection <lb/>Pipeline <lb/>protection <lb/>Pipeline <lb/>Inspection Data <lb/>Risk <lb/>evaluation <lb/>Engineering <lb/>data <lb/>Spatial data <lb/>Basic geographic <lb/>information <lb/>database <lb/>Pipeline <lb/>thematic base <lb/>database <lb/>Pipe Alignment Diagram <lb/>Remote Industrial <lb/>Control System <lb/>Pipeline spatial data-<lb/>sharing platform <lb/>Technical standards <lb/>Integrity data <lb/>management <lb/>Party Integrity <lb/>Knowledge Base <lb/>Integrity Business <lb/>Infrastructure Platform <lb/>Management System <lb/>Pipeline protection <lb/>Disaster prevention and control <lb/>Ontology Defect Management <lb/>Corrosion protection <lb/>Emergency management <lb/>Repair and maintenance <lb/>Unit identification and analysis <lb/>Risk evaluation <lb/>Integrity Management Program <lb/>Program management <lb/>Integrity Management Strategy <lb/>Evaluation of integrity management effectiveness <lb/>Decision <lb/>analysis layer <lb/>Business <lb/>Operations <lb/>Layer <lb/>Application <lb/>support layer <lb/>Data Support <lb/>Layer <lb/>Foundation <lb/>support layer <lb/>Risks are pre-empted and accidents are controlled <lb/>Strategic <lb/>Objective <lb/>Level <lb/>IT <lb/>Control <lb/>System Information <lb/>Security <lb/>Management <lb/>System <lb/>Demand <lb/>and <lb/>drive <lb/>Support <lb/>and <lb/>Realization <lb/>Figure 1. Intelligent management system of urban gas pipeline <lb/>The business application architecture is generally divided into three levels, i.e., the management <lb/>support layer, business operation layer, and decision analysis layer. Designing the system in a <lb/>business-driven way is conducive to the full integration of pipeline integrity management methods, <lb/>processes, and technologies into IT applications, on the one hand, standardizing the management <lb/>process and data through a process-oriented approach, and, on the other hand, progressively opening <lb/>up various links to gradually realize the integrity management of the data and business closure, thus <lb/>truly reflecting the idea of the intelligent management of gas pipelines. <lb/>2.2 Construction of Intelligent Management System Database <lb/>2.2.1 Database logical model design <lb/>The logical model of a database is transformed from the conceptual model of a database, which is <lb/>mainly a concrete description of the data structure and content. The logical model of the Database is <lb/>transformed by the conceptual model of the Database, which is mainly a concrete description of the <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Research on Intelligent Management System of Gas Pipeline with Multi-source Data Fusion <lb/></note>

        <page>5 <lb/></page>

        <body>data structure and content. The purpose is that it can be adapted to the database management system <lb/>to meet the needs of users according to the problems encountered in the model, using object-oriented <lb/>technology to decompose it into each specific data model. The data model of each object has attributes, <lb/>behavior, etc., which are one-to-one correspondence, and there is a certain relationship to achieve a <lb/>unified storage of spatial and attribute data. <lb/>Database design is the actual application environment for the construction of the model, and the <lb/>database model is based on the actual user to design and meet the needs of the actual user. Database <lb/>design is divided into two stages of conversion, first from the real world to the conceptual world of <lb/>conversion and then from the conceptual world to the computer information world. <lb/>2.2.2 Database construction process <lb/>Problems of data storage, classification, sharing, retrieval methods, and security can be solved by <lb/>establishing an intelligent management database for urban gas pipelines. In order to make convenient <lb/>and efficient use of these data and reduce duplication of development, the data resources required by <lb/>each subsystem can be uniformly organized through the application subsystem platform. At the same <lb/>time, a unified data access method is designed and provided for use by each subsystem as well as <lb/>other external systems. <lb/>In the work of database construction, these two types of data should be collected, organized, processed, <lb/>and other operations so that they meet the design requirements of the Database, and at the same time, <lb/>the spatial data and attribute data should be associated to form data integrating spatial information <lb/>and attribute information. Then, the data are processed, unified, and standardized according to the <lb/>design requirements and converted into data that can be recognized by the system. The collection and <lb/>organization of the underlying data are shown in Figure 2, and after the data processing is qualified, <lb/>the data is entered into the Database and stored in the database management system DBMS. <lb/>Establishment of the gas network database in addition to the basic management of data operations, <lb/>more importantly, pipe network analysis, including pipe burst analysis, flow analysis, emergency <lb/>rescue, and other functions, which requires the establishment of topological relationships on the <lb/>Database to build the gas network relationships. <lb/>Topographic <lb/>maps <lb/>Pipe <lb/>network <lb/>equipment <lb/>Road <lb/>data <lb/>Pipe <lb/>network <lb/>appurtenances <lb/>User <lb/>Profile <lb/>Pipe <lb/>network <lb/>equipment <lb/>properties <lb/>Station <lb/>data <lb/>Pipe <lb/>network <lb/>appurtenances <lb/>Station <lb/>data <lb/>Sensor <lb/>data <lb/>Spatial <lb/>database <lb/>Attribute <lb/>Database <lb/>Real-time <lb/>data <lb/>Urban Gas Network Information System Database <lb/>ADO.NET <lb/>ArcGIS SDE <lb/>Figure 2. Collection of the database data <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Xin Cao, Jianxin Tan, Hao Li, Rui Li and Yifan Wang and Junfeng Zhang. Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences, <lb/>9(1) (2024) 1-17 <lb/></note>

        <page>6 <lb/></page>

        <body>3 Gas pipeline Multi-source data fusion technology <lb/>Since the 21st century, the risk-based gas pipeline management model has achieved remarkable <lb/>results in safeguarding the intrinsic safety of oil and gas long-distance pipelines and has been widely <lb/>recognized internationally. However, in comparison, the city gas pipeline network has many pressure <lb/>levels, complex topology, a large number of pipelines, large differences in pipe age, material type, <lb/>wide distribution area, complex service environment, and other significant features, its intelligent <lb/>management in many aspects of long-distance pipeline and oil and gas pipeline has obvious <lb/>differences, can not be copied and transplanted. In the city, gas pipelines contain a variety of different <lb/>sources of related data; normalizing these data and achieving database storage are problems that must <lb/>be solved. This chapter proposes a Multi-source data fusion method for gas pipeline data and provides <lb/>a variety of gas pipeline diagnoses and early warning models to provide technical support for the <lb/>realization of intelligent management of gas pipelines. <lb/>3.1 Predictive Early Warning Models for Gas Pipe Failure <lb/>3.1.1 Gas Leakage Failure Early Warning Models <lb/>The gas pipeline leakage model is mainly divided into three kinds, namely, perforation leakage, <lb/>cracking leakage, and infiltration leakage. Considering that the pressure level of the urban gas <lb/>pipeline network is relatively low, according to the size of the pipeline leakage caliber, the pipeline <lb/>leakage model is selected, which can basically satisfy the actual needs. <lb/>The pipeline leakage model is suitable for cracking leakage, which is often caused by external <lb/>interference, overpressure rupture, or geological subsidence. The leakage is characterized by the <lb/>direct truncation of the pipeline, 80%~100% of the pipeline cross-sectional area leakage, and <lb/>instantaneous leakage of a large amount of pressure is significantly reduced. Since the gas pressure <lb/>at the leakage port and the pressure of the surrounding environment do not differ much, the following <lb/>equations can be established using the conservation of energy and the conservation of momentum. <lb/>Namely: <lb/>0 <lb/>dp <lb/>udu <lb/>F <lb/> <lb/>+ <lb/>+ = <lb/>(1) <lb/>0 <lb/>dH udu <lb/>+= <lb/>(2) <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>dL <lb/>F <lb/>D <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/>(3) <lb/>Where u is the flow rate of gas leakage, P is the absolute pressure of the gas,  is the gas <lb/>density, F is the friction, H is the enthalpy of the gas,  is the kinetic viscosity of the gas, L <lb/>is the distance of the leakage point from the beginning, D is the inner diameter of the pipeline. <lb/>The formula (1), (2), (3) can be obtained by organizing the formula (4) pipeline leakage model of the <lb/>leakage strength formula: <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Research on Intelligent Management System of Gas Pipeline with Multi-source Data Fusion <lb/></note>

        <page>7 <lb/></page>

        <body>34 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>43 <lb/>2 ** <lb/>1 <lb/>mp <lb/>TT <lb/>MK <lb/>q C A <lb/>ZR K <lb/>T <lb/>T <lb/>pp <lb/>-<lb/>= <lb/>-<lb/> <lb/> - <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>(4) <lb/>Where m <lb/>q is the leakage intensity, A is the area of the leakage port, K is the isentropic index of <lb/>gas, M is the molar mass of gas, Z is the compression factor, R is the molar gas constant, p <lb/>C <lb/>is the leakage coefficient of the pipeline, according to the leakage situation can be g <lb/>C , I <lb/>C , and d <lb/>C , <lb/>respectively, 3 <lb/>T , 4 <lb/>T for the leakage point, leakage upstream of the point of the pipeline at L the <lb/>temperature of the gas, 3 <lb/>p , 4 <lb/>p for the leakage point, leakage upstream of the point of the pipeline <lb/>at L the absolute pressure of gas. The absolute pressure of gas in the pipeline at the leakage point <lb/>and 16 upstream of the leakage point. <lb/>3.1.2 Gas diffusion failure early warning models <lb/>Gas leakage essentially consists of two processes: jetting and expansion. The diffusion of a gas is <lb/>affected by a variety of uncontrollable factors such as gas leakage conditions, gravity, and its <lb/>buoyancy, wind speed, wind direction, atmospheric stability, atmospheric humidity, surface <lb/>temperature, etc., which are generally categorized into Gaussian plume diffusion model, Gaussian <lb/>smoke plume diffusion model, and atmospheric diffusion model under special meteorological <lb/>conditions. <lb/>When the pipeline gas release time is not less than the diffusion time, the Gaussian plume diffusion <lb/>model can be used for Calculation. The use of the Gaussian plume diffusion model is required to have <lb/>the following conditions: <lb/>1) The range of gas diffusion should be over the flat, unobstructed ground. <lb/>2) There is no chemical or other reaction between the gas and the outside world in the process of <lb/>diffusion, and there is no phenomenon such as droplet deposition. <lb/>3) The rate of gas leakage is assumed to be a constant that does not change. <lb/>4) The wind direction is horizontal, and the wind speed is uniform. The center of the cloud moves <lb/>at the same speed as the outside wind speed. <lb/>5) There is no heat exchange between the gas and the outside air. <lb/>6) The variation of some parameters within the cloud or in the cross-section of the cloud plume <lb/>conforms to a normal distribution model. <lb/>The schematic diagram of the Gaussian plume diffusion model is shown in Fig. 3. In the figure, the <lb/>X -axis indicates the downwind direction; the Y -axis indicates the crosswind direction; the Z -axis <lb/>indicates the vertical height, and the concentration at point ( , , ) <lb/>x y z in the schematic is: <lb/>2 <lb/>22 <lb/>2 <lb/>22 <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>22 <lb/>( , , , ) <lb/>2 <lb/>y <lb/>zz <lb/>y <lb/>z H <lb/>z H <lb/>yz <lb/>Q <lb/>C x y z H <lb/>e <lb/>e <lb/>e <lb/>u <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>-+ <lb/>  <lb/>--<lb/>-<lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/>+ <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/>(5) <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Xin Cao, Jianxin Tan, Hao Li, Rui Li and Yifan Wang and Junfeng Zhang. Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences, <lb/>9(1) (2024) 1-17 <lb/></note>

        <page>8 <lb/></page>

        <body>Where Q is the intensity of the leakage source, u is the wind speed, x <lb/> , y <lb/> , z <lb/> are the <lb/>diffusion coefficients for downwind, sidewind, and vertical wind direction, x , y , and z are the <lb/>distances from the leakage source, and H is the effective source height, which is the sum of the <lb/>height of the leakage source and the height of the lift. <lb/>Cloud <lb/>Centerline <lb/>Downwind distance <lb/>Wind <lb/>speed <lb/>Vertical <lb/>height <lb/>Lifting <lb/>height <lb/>Release <lb/>height <lb/>Crosswind <lb/>distance <lb/>Figure 3. Schematic diagram of Gauss model <lb/>The diffusion coefficient is related to wind speed, height above ground, and other factors and can be <lb/>determined by atmospheric stability. <lb/>3.1.3 Early warning models for fire and explosion failures <lb/>1) Fire failure warning model <lb/>The damage caused by urban gas pipeline leakage fire accidents is mainly manifested as casualties <lb/>and losses of structures and other property, and the damage mainly comes from the toxic smoke and <lb/>high-temperature radiation generated by gas combustion. Fire accidents may occur when the gas <lb/>pipeline leaks and encounters an ignition source. According to the surrounding environment of the <lb/>leak and the characteristics of the ignition, the fire accidents that may occur include jet fires, gas cloud <lb/>combustion, and other types of fires. <lb/>Jet fire leaks gas at the orifice and is immediately ignited, while a steady stream of gas is provided <lb/>from the pipeline, the trip steady-state flame, belonging to the phenomenon of constant diffusion <lb/>combustion. Gas pipeline leakage can be based on the shape of the flame to determine whether the <lb/>jet fire, the heat flux of thermal radiation in different places can be expressed as: <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>a h c <lb/>QH <lb/>I <lb/>r <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/>= <lb/>(6) <lb/>where I is the radiant heat flux at a given location,  is the ratio of radiant heat to heat released <lb/>from the fire, which is 0.2 for methane, a <lb/> is the atmospheric transmittance, h <lb/>Q is the gas leakage <lb/>flow rate at the hole, <lb/>c <lb/>H is the heat of combustion, which is for natural gas, and <lb/>5.56 104kJ/kg <lb/>c <lb/>H = <lb/>, r is the axial distance from the center of the flame to the given location. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Research on Intelligent Management System of Gas Pipeline with Multi-source Data Fusion <lb/></note>

        <page>9 <lb/></page>

        <body>Comparison of the calculated heat fluxes with the known radiant heat flux damage criterion gives the <lb/>damage to the object target. Also, with the knowledge of the target heat radiation flux threshold, the <lb/>safe distance radius can be found. Namely: <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>24 <lb/>5 <lb/>r r <lb/>Q <lb/>=  + <lb/>(7) <lb/>If a gas leak is ignited immediately to form a jet-spreading flame, in general, the height of the jet <lb/>flame is proportional to the square root of the gas leak flow rate. Bringing in equation (7) gives the <lb/>radius of injury, then: <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>24 <lb/>45 <lb/>a h c <lb/>h <lb/>QH <lb/>rQ <lb/>I <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>=+ <lb/>(8) <lb/>2) Explosion failure warning model <lb/>Gas pipeline leakage is a large amount of gas in the air that forms a gas cloud. If the gas cloud <lb/>concentration reaches the explosion limit, the surrounding ignition source will detonate the leakage <lb/>of the gas cloud so that an explosion occurs. Gas explosions mainly through the explosion shock <lb/>wave, high-temperature flame formed by the hot gas, and toxic and harmful gas flow on the human <lb/>body to cause comprehensive damage. City gas explosion has a strong roll suction effect, while high-<lb/>temperature flame and explosion pressure wave coupled with each other, the explosion shock wave <lb/>can drive the propagation path of the gas together with the movement, resulting in a gradual increase <lb/>in the range of high-temperature and high-pressure gas impact. <lb/>Gas cloud explosion impact in accordance with the TNT equivalent method of Calculation, that is, <lb/>the TNT equivalent to express the effective power of the gas cloud explosion and the actual <lb/>contribution of the value of the TNT equivalent method of explosion estimation model is as follows: <lb/>ff <lb/>TNT <lb/>TNT <lb/>A M H <lb/>M <lb/>Q <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/>(9) <lb/>TNT <lb/>M <lb/>is the TNT equivalent of the gas cloud,  is the ground blast coefficient, and  is the <lb/>equivalence factor, which ranges from 0.02% to 14.9%. The median value of this range is 3% to 4%, <lb/>f <lb/>M is the total mass of fuel in the gas cloud, <lb/>f <lb/>H is the heat of combustion of the fuel, and TNT <lb/>Q <lb/>is the heat of detonation of TNT. <lb/>3.2 Correlation mathematical model for Multi-source data fusion <lb/>3.2.1 Fundamentals of multi-sensor information fusion <lb/>In sensor systems, relying on a single sensor often does not satisfy the accurate detection of a target, <lb/>which may lead to large errors or even mistakes, so multiple sensors are needed. If each sensor makes <lb/>independent decisions without considering the connection existing between the detection information <lb/>of each sensor, not only will the key information be lost, resulting in the waste of massive data <lb/>resources, but it will also lead to a drastic increase in the workload of data processing. Therefore, data <lb/>from multiple sensors need to be processed and analyzed comprehensively, which is the essence of <lb/>multi-sensor information fusion. Multi-sensor information fusion can enhance the discriminative <lb/>ability of the system and improve its robustness and reliability. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Xin Cao, Jianxin Tan, Hao Li, Rui Li and Yifan Wang and Junfeng Zhang. Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences, <lb/>9(1) (2024) 1-17 <lb/></note>

        <page>10 <lb/></page>

        <body>In the multi-sensor system, redundant information, complementary information, and synergistic <lb/>information ensure the quality of the data, on the basis of which the advantages of multi-sensors are <lb/>fully utilized to process the data comprehensively and improve the stability and reliability of the <lb/>system. <lb/>3.2.2 Mathematical model of information fusion association <lb/>System engineering is a complex, non-linear open system, which, in its implementation, requires <lb/>continuous exchange of resources both inside and outside the system and is simultaneously affected <lb/>by various factors from both inside and outside the system. In this regard, system science and control <lb/>theory believe that the state of the system and its characteristics are the result of the combined effect <lb/>of factors inside and outside the system. <lb/>If () <lb/>Xt is set to be a set of sets characterizing the behavior of multiparameter fusion related to the <lb/>state of the system and its results at a certain time, then the state equation of the system can be <lb/>expressed as <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>X t Ax t <lb/>= <lb/>if and only if there are no disturbances coming from outside the system, <lb/>where A is the parameter matrix of the endogenous system variables () <lb/>xt . If the dimension of <lb/>() <lb/>xt is N , then the system variables can be expressed as a function of time for an engineering <lb/>system that satisfies the Markov characteristic, i.e., <lb/>21 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>n 1 <lb/>() <lb/>n <lb/>x t a a t a t <lb/>a t -<lb/>-<lb/>= + + <lb/>+ + <lb/>. where, a is <lb/>a N -dimensional column vector. If () <lb/>xt is substituted into the system state equation, then: <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>( ) <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>nn <lb/>nn <lb/>X t <lb/>A a a t a t <lb/>a t <lb/>a <lb/>a t a t <lb/>na t <lb/>--<lb/>-<lb/>= <lb/>+ + <lb/>+ + <lb/>= + <lb/>+ <lb/>+ + <lb/>(10) <lb/>Among them: <lb/>21 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>11 <lb/>,, <lb/>2! <lb/>( 1)! <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>a Aa a <lb/>A a a <lb/>A a <lb/>n <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>-<lb/>(11) <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>11 <lb/>() <lb/>2! <lb/>( 1)! <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>x t a a t a t <lb/>a t <lb/>a I At <lb/>A t <lb/>A t <lb/>n <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/> <lb/>= + + <lb/>+ + <lb/>= <lb/>+ + <lb/>+ + <lb/> <lb/>-<lb/> <lb/>(12) <lb/>At this point, the multinomial series sum in parentheses is denoted as the exponential function At <lb/>e <lb/>then <lb/>0 <lb/>() <lb/>At <lb/>x t e a <lb/>= <lb/>. At the initial time of the system, <lb/>0 <lb/>(0) <lb/>xa = , the system is in a steady state. If we <lb/>want to know the multi-parameter fusion response of the system over time t , the change in state of <lb/>the system at any moment t is: <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) ( ) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>() <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>x t x t <lb/>A t x t dt <lb/>-<lb/>= <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/>(13) <lb/>3.2.3 Improved Kalman filter data fusion <lb/>Aiming at the Multi-source data such as gas pipeline leakage, diffusion, fire, explosion, etc., in the <lb/>intelligent management system of urban gas pipelines, this paper introduces the DS evidence theory <lb/>to improve the Kalman filtering algorithm, relying on the algorithms of DS evidence theory in the <lb/>allocation of the weights to the system sensors for the fusion of the measurement information received <lb/>by the fusion process. The improved Multi-source data fusion framework of multi-sensor Kalman <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Research on Intelligent Management System of Gas Pipeline with Multi-source Data Fusion <lb/></note>

        <page>11 <lb/></page>

        <body>filtering is shown in Fig. 4, relying on different sensors to collect different data, filtering the <lb/>information through multiple filters, and then fusing them with DS evidence theory. <lb/>Sensor 1 <lb/>Z 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Ẑ <lb/>Sensor 2 <lb/>Z 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>Ẑ <lb/>Sensor N <lb/>Z N <lb/>ˆN <lb/>Z <lb/>DS combination rules <lb/>Subfilter 1 <lb/>Subfilter 2 <lb/>Subfilter N <lb/>Data fusion <lb/>Filtering algorithms <lb/>X <lb/>Y <lb/>X <lb/>Figure 4. Improved Kalman filtering for data fusion <lb/>The measurement information received by different sensors and the filtered information through the <lb/>sub-filter is taken as evidence of the received information. Then: <lb/>, <lb/>1, 2, <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>m <lb/>Z Z i <lb/>N <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>(14) <lb/>The evidence will be calculated according to the DS evidence theory improvement algorithm, and the <lb/>proportion of weights occupied by the information received by the sensors at different moments can <lb/>be obtained as: <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>12 ,, <lb/>k <lb/>k <lb/>k <lb/>Nk <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/>(15) <lb/>Where k denotes the moment and i denotes the number of sensors. <lb/>The information is data fused to obtain a new sequence of information as: <lb/>1 <lb/>N <lb/>T <lb/>ik <lb/>i <lb/>YZ  <lb/>= <lb/>=  <lb/>(16) <lb/>T Denotes the transpose. The new sequence is passed through the Kalman filter, and finally, a more <lb/>desirable filter is obtained. <lb/>4 Test and Analysis of Intelligent Management System for Urban Gas Pipelines <lb/>The urban gas pipeline is an important hub for supplying living gas, enterprise heat sources, and raw <lb/>chemical materials to urban areas. Any accident that occurs in the pipeline may seriously affect <lb/>people&apos;s production and life and even cause great losses, so it is of great practical significance to carry <lb/>out effective, intelligent management of urban gas pipelines. The purpose of studying the intelligent <lb/>management of gas pipelines is to provide relevant decision-support information for people to analyze, <lb/>judge, prevent, and make decisions for reference and ultimately to minimize the risk. In this chapter, <lb/>the simulation test is carried out for the intelligent management system of urban gas pipelines <lb/>established in the previous chapter to explore the effectiveness of its application practice. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Xin Cao, Jianxin Tan, Hao Li, Rui Li and Yifan Wang and Junfeng Zhang. Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences, <lb/>9(1) (2024) 1-17 <lb/></note>

        <page>12 <lb/></page>

        <body>4.1 Consequences of gas pipeline failures <lb/>4.1.1 Scope of spreading hazards of gas pipeline leakage <lb/>In order to verify the effectiveness of the gas pipeline intelligent management system given in this <lb/>paper in analyzing the hazards of urban gas pipeline leakage and diffusion, MATLAB software is <lb/>used to simulate and test the gas pipeline intelligent management system. Due to the different <lb/>environmental parameters having different impacts on gas pipeline leakage and diffusion, this paper <lb/>chooses the environmental parameters of different times in summer and winter for simulation. <lb/>After the rupture of the gas pipeline, if there is no ignition source when the natural gas with pressure <lb/>leaks out from the pipeline into the atmosphere, the gas phase diffusion mixes with the air to form <lb/>vapor cloud diffusion. The range of vapor cloud diffusion after gas pipeline rupture is shown in Table <lb/>1 and the curve of the influence range of vapor cloud diffusion is shown in Fig. 5, of which Fig. 5(a) <lb/>and (b) are the centerline concentration and distance, and the top view of the cloud, respectively. <lb/>Since the season has a large impact on the environmental parameters of air temperature, temperature, <lb/>and humidity, the simulation is carried out for summer, winter, annual average, and working <lb/>conditions, respectively. <lb/>From the chart, it can be seen that in the winter wind speed of 1.5m/s and atmospheric stability of D, <lb/>the surface from the gas pipeline outside the range of 12.15m belongs to a safe area, not easy to fire <lb/>and explosion, while the surface from the gas pipeline 2.87 ~ 12.15m belongs to the flammable and <lb/>explosive explosion area, the site strictly eliminate any ignition sources and factors causing <lb/>explosions, and the surface from the pipeline within the range of 2.87m belong to the High-risk areas, <lb/>open fire and people are strictly prohibited. In the summer wind speed of 2.5m / s and atmospheric <lb/>stability of D, the upper limit of the explosion and the lower limit of the explosion compared to the <lb/>winter were increased by 8.71% and decreased by 15.56%, indicating that the summer in the gas <lb/>pipeline leakage is more likely to occur when the fire and explosion. When the maximum wind speed <lb/>is 10m/s, the upper limit of fire and explosion caused by gas pipeline rupture is only 2.43 m. The <lb/>system designed in this paper can fully obtain the possible failures caused by the rupture of urban gas <lb/>pipelines at different points in time and provide a reference to improve disaster prevention and early <lb/>warning of urban gas pipelines further. <lb/>(a) Centerline concentration versus distance <lb/>(b) Cloud group overlooking the circle <lb/>Figure 5. Steam cloud diffusion influence range curve <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Research on Intelligent Management System of Gas Pipeline with Multi-source Data Fusion <lb/></note>

        <page>13 <lb/></page>

        <body>Table 1. The influence of rupture diffusion of urban gas pipeline <lb/>Accident <lb/>situation <lb/>Meteorologic <lb/>condition <lb/>The most diffusion out from the surface (m) <lb/>Upper explosive <lb/>limit <lb/>low explosive <lb/>limit <lb/>The 50% explosion lower <lb/>limit <lb/>The pipe rupture <lb/>1.5/D in winter <lb/>2.87 <lb/>12.15 <lb/>23.46 <lb/>2.5/D in the summer <lb/>3.12 <lb/>10.69 <lb/>24.85 <lb/>1.9/D annual average <lb/>3.04 <lb/>1.63 <lb/>21.99 <lb/>Maximum wind speed <lb/>2.43 <lb/>6.52 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>4.1.2 Scope of Gas Pipe Jet Fire Hazards <lb/>Pressurized natural gas forms a jet when it leaks, and if ignited at the leak opening, a jet fire can form. <lb/>When the intensity of the heat radiation from the fire is sufficiently high, it can cause surrounding <lb/>objects to burn or deform, and the intense heat radiation may cause equipment to burn or even injuries. <lb/>The hazardousness of a gas pipeline jet fire is mainly characterized by the flame extent and the radius <lb/>of injury caused by thermal radiation. The variation curve of radiation intensity with distance for gas <lb/>pipeline jet fire is shown in Figure 6, and the statistics of the range of influence of thermal radiation <lb/>from jet fire are shown in Table 2. <lb/>In the curve of jet fire occurring during gas pipeline rupture, the overall trend of thermal radiation <lb/>energy of jet fire in winter shows a parabola, and the following conclusions can be drawn when the <lb/>wind speed is 1m/s and atmospheric stability is D: <lb/>1) In the range of 12.69~18.67m from the leakage point, the intensity of thermal radiation is <lb/>more than 5kW/m 2. T here is no special requirement for the equipment in this radiation intensity, <lb/>but it will cause harm to the personnel, so the staff who are active in this area need to wear <lb/>professional radiation protective clothing. <lb/>2) from the leakage point 0 ~ 12.69m, the intensity of thermal radiation exceeding 13.5kW/m 2 <lb/>the radiation intensity should be avoided within the wooden equipment; radiation to personnel <lb/>more than 20 will cause human burns and need close attention. <lb/>3) The intensity of thermal radiation of jet fire caused by the rupture of the city gas pipeline will <lb/>not exceed 39.55kW/m 2 . <lb/>Based on the above results, it is clear that the overall winter gas pipeline rupture failure accidents are <lb/>caused by losses compared to the summer, and the maximum wind speed is low, the focus of the gas <lb/>pipeline needs to be carried out in the summer for timely maintenance, as a way to better avoid gas <lb/>pipeline rupture accidents that may occur in the summer. <lb/>Figure 6. Curve of radiation intensity with distance <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Xin Cao, Jianxin Tan, Hao Li, Rui Li and Yifan Wang and Junfeng Zhang. Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences, <lb/>9(1) (2024) 1-17 <lb/></note>

        <page>14 <lb/></page>

        <body>Table 2. Impact range of jet hot radiation <lb/>Accident <lb/>situation <lb/>Meteorologic condition <lb/>Length of flame <lb/>(m) <lb/>Heat radiation intensity(kW/m 2 ) <lb/>5 <lb/>13.5 <lb/>39.5 <lb/>Irradiation loop (m) <lb/>The pipe <lb/>rupture <lb/>1.5/D in winter <lb/>12.03 <lb/>18.67 <lb/>12.69 <lb/>23.46 <lb/>2.5/D in the summer <lb/>14.27 <lb/>19.85 <lb/>15.76 <lb/>--<lb/>1.9/D annual average <lb/>13.38 <lb/>18.92 <lb/>14.38 <lb/>--<lb/>Maximum wind speed <lb/>19.59 <lb/>20.76 <lb/>18.72 <lb/>--<lb/>4.2 Explosions and Early Warning in Gas Pipeline Hazardous Areas <lb/>4.2.1 Calculation and analysis of the consequences of explosions in hazardous areas <lb/>In order to further clarify the role of the gas pipeline intelligent management system established in <lb/>this paper in the monitoring of gas leakage, this paper further simulates the leakage caused by the <lb/>negligence of personnel who forget to close the gas valve. Calculate the TNT equivalent under <lb/>different leakage times so as to clarify the possible explosion risk, the shock wave generated after the <lb/>explosion overpressure, and the hazardous radius area division. Table 3 shows the variation of each <lb/>parameter under different leakage events of the gas valve. <lb/>As can be seen from the table, as the gas leakage time continues to increase, the TNT equivalent <lb/>generated in the explosion is also greater; when the gas leakage event from 10s to 5000s, the TNT <lb/>equivalent increased from 0.005kg to 0.6285kg, the increase has reached 1256 times. The increase in <lb/>leakage time due to the gas explosion and the shock wave generated by the overpressure from <lb/>13.76Kpa to 815.92Kpa in the same location, under the different leakage times generated by the shock <lb/>wave, is growing. The longer the gas leakage time, the greater the shock wave overpressure, which <lb/>reflects the earlier the gas pipeline leakage can be found to minimize the losses generated by the <lb/>explosion, which reflects the benefits of an intelligent management system for gas pipelines. At the <lb/>same time, as the gas pipeline leakage time increases, the radius of the hazardous area has become <lb/>larger and larger; some of the original Scope of the no longer dead zone has gradually become a dead <lb/>zone, and the hazardous area is further expanding. Based on the above analysis, it is clear that timely <lb/>detection of gas pipeline leakage can effectively avoid the losses caused by the explosion; relying on <lb/>the gas pipeline intelligent management system established in this paper can fully access the operation <lb/>of the gas pipeline so that the gas pipeline in the early stage of leakage can be effectively controlled. <lb/>Table 3. TNT equivalent, shock wave overpressure and hazard radius area division <lb/>Leak <lb/>time (s) <lb/>Leakage <lb/>gas mass <lb/>(kg) <lb/>TNT <lb/>Equivalent (kg) <lb/>Shock-wave <lb/>overpressure <lb/>(KPa) <lb/>Radius of dangerous area(m) <lb/>Death area <lb/>Serious injury <lb/>area <lb/>Minor injury <lb/>area <lb/>10 <lb/>0.0012 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>13.76 <lb/>0.0578 <lb/>0.3368 <lb/>0.6842 <lb/>50 <lb/>0.0153 <lb/>0.0079 <lb/>22.45 <lb/>0.1243 <lb/>0.4152 <lb/>0.9117 <lb/>100 <lb/>0.0527 <lb/>0.0237 <lb/>24.68 <lb/>0.2561 <lb/>0.5379 <lb/>1.4521 <lb/>200 <lb/>0.0746 <lb/>0.0316 <lb/>27.12 <lb/>0.3319 <lb/>0.7835 <lb/>2.0346 <lb/>300 <lb/>0.0951 <lb/>0.0482 <lb/>35.47 <lb/>0.3854 <lb/>0.9461 <lb/>2.4479 <lb/>500 <lb/>0.1148 <lb/>0.0541 <lb/>62.59 <lb/>0.4252 <lb/>1.1103 <lb/>2.6153 <lb/>800 <lb/>0.1576 <lb/>0.0763 <lb/>136.81 <lb/>0.4846 <lb/>1.3568 <lb/>2.9982 <lb/>1200 <lb/>0.3345 <lb/>0.1432 <lb/>206.34 <lb/>0.5327 <lb/>2.4305 <lb/>3.8764 <lb/>3000 <lb/>0.6859 <lb/>0.3001 <lb/>463.57 <lb/>0.6876 <lb/>2.8258 <lb/>4.6605 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1.2643 <lb/>0.6285 <lb/>815.92 <lb/>0.8847 <lb/>3.6617 <lb/>5.9843 <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Research on Intelligent Management System of Gas Pipeline with Multi-source Data Fusion <lb/></note>

        <page>15 <lb/></page>

        <body>4.2.2 Example analysis of gas pipeline forecasting and warning algorithms <lb/>For the gas pipeline leakage and proliferation of fire and explosion that may be triggered by the two <lb/>consequences, this paper proposes the casualty area and building damage area of the two indicators, <lb/>respectively, for the prediction of the consequences of the accident early warning estimates, early <lb/>warning of the alarm level of red, orange, yellow, blue four levels, the establishment of prediction <lb/>and warning model, namely: <lb/>2 <lb/>SR  <lb/>= <lb/>(17) <lb/>DeathNum S D <lb/>= <lb/>(18) <lb/>Where D is the population density. <lb/>In this paper, the city of L is selected as the research object of early warning analysis, with a <lb/>population density of 40,512 people/square kilometer, and its population density data is derived from <lb/>the statistical data of P city. Using the relevant calculation steps, the casualty prediction area, the <lb/>number of casualties and the corresponding alert level of fire and explosion accident prediction are <lb/>obtained as shown in Table 4, respectively. <lb/>From the data in the table, when the gas pipeline rupture leakage flow is 0.0148kg/s and pressure is <lb/>0.002MPa when the casualty prediction area is only 7.1542m 2 , at this time, the warning level of the <lb/>blue warning, even if it is the medium pressure B for 0.12MPa when its warning level is also blue. <lb/>When the gas pipeline leakage pressure reaches A0.35MPa, the gas leakage flow rate reaches <lb/>27.6976kg/s; at this time, the casualty prediction area has reached 9939.0851m 2 , the casualty <lb/>prediction number is up to 384.1147 people, the warning level of red warning. From this, it can be <lb/>clear that when the rupture size of the gas pipeline reaches more than 40mm, and the pressure of the <lb/>gas pipeline exceeds 0.35MPa, it will trigger the red warning of the gas pipeline. Using the gas <lb/>pipeline intelligent management system given in this paper can clarify the current warning level of <lb/>gas leakage, which can help the emergency management department to better use the corresponding <lb/>emergency plan to realize the minimum loss. <lb/>Table 4. Fire early warning and forecast query <lb/>Pressure (MPa) <lb/>Pipe diameter <lb/>rupture size (mm) <lb/>Leakage flow <lb/>rate (kg/s) <lb/>Forecast area of <lb/>casualties (m 2 ) <lb/>Number of <lb/>casualties predicted <lb/>Warning <lb/>level <lb/>Low pressure <lb/>25 <lb/>0.0148 <lb/>7.1542 <lb/>0.2218 <lb/>Blue <lb/>0.002 <lb/>120 <lb/>0.5051 <lb/>178.2541 <lb/>6.9602 <lb/>Blue <lb/>Medium voltage B <lb/>50 <lb/>0.5543 <lb/>193.5429 <lb/>7.9254 <lb/>Blue <lb/>0.12 <lb/>250 <lb/>1.5124 <lb/>495.1472 <lb/>18.0658 <lb/>Blue <lb/>Medium voltage A <lb/>50 <lb/>1.0879 <lb/>393.5527 <lb/>15.6652 <lb/>Blue <lb/>0.35 <lb/>200 <lb/>27.6976 <lb/>9939.0851 <lb/>384.1147 <lb/>Red <lb/>High voltage B <lb/>120 <lb/>13.1525 <lb/>4349.6185 <lb/>165.6524 <lb/>Red <lb/>0.9 <lb/>600 <lb/>300.5241 <lb/>101241.52 <lb/>4233.142 <lb/>Red <lb/>High voltage A <lb/>120 <lb/>23.7867 <lb/>8548.3581 <lb/>339.8398 <lb/>Red <lb/>1.5 <lb/>600 <lb/>569.4523 <lb/>221747.54 <lb/>8020.541 <lb/>Red <lb/>Ultrahigh voltage B <lb/>120 <lb/>35.4992 <lb/>13442.589 <lb/>493.1143 <lb/>Red <lb/>3.0 <lb/>600 <lb/>887.4981 <lb/>335795.63 <lb/>12523.47 <lb/>Red <lb/>Ultrahigh voltage A <lb/>120 <lb/>55.7419 <lb/>21005.647 <lb/>777.1268 <lb/>Red <lb/>4.5 <lb/>600 <lb/>1388.7942 <lb/>523541.78 <lb/>19584.45 <lb/>Red <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Xin Cao, Jianxin Tan, Hao Li, Rui Li and Yifan Wang and Junfeng Zhang. Applied Mathematics and Nonlinear Sciences, <lb/>9(1) (2024) 1-17 <lb/></note>

        <page>16 <lb/></page>

        <body>5 Conclusion <lb/>In this paper, the C/S network architecture and J2EE enterprise-level application development <lb/>framework are used to establish an intelligent management system for gas pipelines, and the data of <lb/>the prediction and warning model related to the failure of gas pipelines are fused by Multi-source data <lb/>fusion technology, and the system is simulated and empirically analyzed. The conclusions are as <lb/>follows: <lb/>1) in the simulation of a gas pipeline failure accident, a winter wind speed of 1.5m/s at the surface <lb/>from the gas pipeline outside the range of 12.15m belongs to the safe area, and when the <lb/>maximum wind speed of 10m/s, the upper limit distance of fire and explosion caused by the <lb/>rupture of the gas pipeline is only 2.43m, and the hazardous range of the gas pipeline jet fire <lb/>is within the range of 12.69m. Using the gas pipeline intelligent management system <lb/>established in this paper can clarify the parameters related to gas pipeline failure accidents and <lb/>help emergency management personnel visualize the data before the development of the <lb/>appropriate emergency plan to reduce the losses due to gas pipeline leakage fully. <lb/>2) with the gas leakage time increases, the TNT equivalent generated in the explosion, shock <lb/>wave overpressure, and the radius of the hazardous area is also larger; when the gas leakage <lb/>time is more than 3,000s, the shock wave overpressure of up to 815.92KPa, the radius of the <lb/>area of serious injuries has reached 3.66 m. Relying on this paper&apos;s system can give a better <lb/>understanding of the operation of the gas pipeline in the gas pipeline leakage. In the early <lb/>stage of the gas pipeline leakage, timely measures to repair to better ensure the safety of <lb/>people&apos;s lives and property. <lb/>3) Combined with Multi-source data obtained from the visualization of the chart can be clear gas <lb/>pipeline prediction and early warning, the face of different degrees of gas pipeline leakage <lb/>will lead to different results in the prediction of the early warning to provide emergency <lb/>management personnel with more response time, but also in the end of the accident in a timely <lb/>manner to understand the pipeline occurred in the specific problem, in order to further <lb/>optimize the quality of pipeline construction. <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Liu, B., He, L. Y., Zhang, H., Cao, Y., &amp; Fernandes, H. (2017). The axial crack testing model for long <lb/>distance oil -gas pipeline based on magnetic flux leakage internal inspection method. Measurement, 103, <lb/>275-282. <lb/>[2] Bai, L., Li, F., Jiang, T., &amp; Jia, H. (2017). Robust scheduling for wind integrated energy systems <lb/>considering gas pipeline and power transmission n-1 contingencies. IEEE Transactions on Power Systems, <lb/>PP(2), 1-1. <lb/>[3] Li, J., Yan, M., &amp; Yu, J. (2018). Evaluation on gas supply reliability of urban gas pipeline network. <lb/>Eksploatacja i Niezawodnosc -Maintenance and Reliability, 20(3), 471-477. <lb/>[4] Tchórzewska-Cie?lak Barbara, Katarzyna, P. U., Marek, U., &amp; Janusz, R. (2018). Approaches for safety <lb/>analysis of gas-pipeline functionality in terms of failure occurrence: a case study. Energies, 11(6), 1589-. <lb/>[5] Xie, Y., Gao, C., Wang, P., Qu, X., &amp; Cui, H. (2023). Research on vibration fatigue damage identification <lb/>of oil and gas pipeline under the condition of measured noise injection. Applied Ocean Research. <lb/>[6] Liu, E., Peng, Y., Ji, Y., Azimi, M., &amp; Shi, L. (2023). Energy consumption optimization model of large <lb/>parallel natural gas pipeline network: using compressors with multiple operating modes. Energy And <lb/>Fuels, 37(1), 774-784. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Research on Intelligent Management System of Gas Pipeline with Multi-source Data Fusion <lb/></note>

        <page>17 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>[7] Song, R., Xia, Y., Chen, Y., Du, S., Strunz, K., &amp; Song, Y., et al. (2023). Efficient modelling of natural <lb/>gas pipeline on electromagnetic transient simulation programs. IET renewable power generation. <lb/>[8] Vandrangi, S. K., Mujtaba, S. M., &amp; Lemma, T. A. (2022). Gas pipeline safety management system based <lb/>on neural network. Process Safety Progress, 41, S59-S67. <lb/>[9] Hao, YongmeiWu, YujiaJiang, JunchengXing, ZhixiangYang, KeWang, ShuliXu, NingRao, Yongchao. <lb/>(2021). The method for leakage detection of urban natural gas pipeline based on the improved ita and alo. <lb/>Journal of loss prevention in the process industries, 71(1). <lb/>[10] Yuan, Y., Dehghanpour, K., Wang, Z., &amp; Bu, F. (2022). Multi-source data fusion outage location in <lb/>distribution systems via probabilistic graphical models. IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid, 13, 1357-1371. <lb/>[11] Zhang, C., Lv, A., Jia, S., &amp; Qi, S. (2022). Longterm Multi-source satellite data fusion reveals dynamic <lb/>expansion of lake water area and storage in a hyperarid basin of china. Journal of Hydrology. <lb/>[12] Cao, X., Shi, Y., &amp; Zhou, L. (2021). Research on urban carrying capacity based on Multi-source data <lb/>fusion-a case study of shanghai. Remote Sensing, 13(14), 2695. <lb/>[13] Hoschke, J., Chowdhury, M. F. W., Venezuela, J., &amp; Atrens, A. (2023). A review of hydrogen <lb/>embrittlement in gas transmission pipeline steels. Corrosion Reviews, 41, 277 -317. <lb/>[14] Yan, Y., Liu, D., Gao, B., Tian, G. Y., &amp; Cai, Z. C. (2020). A deep learning-based ultrasonic pattern <lb/>recognition method for inspecting girth weld cracking of gas pipeline. IEEE Sensors Journal, PP(99), 1-<lb/>1. <lb/>[15] Ma, Y., Huang, Z., Lian, Z., Chang, W., &amp; Tan, H. (2019). Effects of a new drag reduction agent on <lb/>natural gas pipeline transportation. Advances in Mechanical Engineering(10). <lb/>[16] Wang, C., Liu, M., Aidong, X. U., &amp; Zhang, J. (2017). The application of plc control system in oil and <lb/>gas pipeline transportation. Molecular Cancer Therapeutics, 8(Supplement 1), C133-C133. <lb/>[17] Javadi, Yashar, Goldak, John, A., &amp; Fooladi, et al. (2018). Using ultrasonic and finite element for residual <lb/>stress evaluation of a gas transmission pipeline. Materials Evaluation. <lb/>[18] Shi, M., Zhao, H., Huang, Z., &amp; Jiang, L. (2018). Study on detection methods of residual wall thickness <lb/>for process pipeline corrosion in oil and gas gathering and transportation station. Journal of Magnetics, <lb/>23. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
