<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/>reveal distinct and complex ecosystems <lb/>C. C. LymanID 1☯ *, G. R. Holyoak 1☯ , K. Meinkoth 1☯ , X. Wieneke 2 , K. A. Chillemi 1 , <lb/>U. DeSilvaID 2☯ <lb/>1 Department of Veterinary Clinical Sciences, Center for Veterinary Health Sciences, Oklahoma State <lb/>University, Stillwater, Oklahoma, United States of America, 2 Department of Animal Science, Oklahoma <lb/>State University, Stillwater, Oklahoma, United States Of America <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* candace.lyman@okstate.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The objective of this study was to characterize the normal microbiome of healthy canine <lb/>vagina and endometrium and to determine the effect of the stage of estrous, on the resident <lb/>microbiome. Cranial vaginal swabs and uterine biopsy samples were collected from twenty-<lb/>five bitches in five different stages of estrous at elective ovariohysterectomy (OVH). Over 4 <lb/>million reads of the V4 region of 16S rDNA gene were obtained and used for further analy-<lb/>ses. A total of 317 genera belonging to 24 known phyla were identified. The endometrium <lb/>was higher in bacterial diversity while the vagina was higher in richness. Proteobacteria, <lb/>Bacteroidetes and Firmicutes were the most abundant phyla observed across all samples. <lb/>Hydrotalea, Ralstonia, and Fusobacterium accounted for nearly 60% of the OTUs identified <lb/>in the vagina while organisms identified in the endometrium were more evenly distributed. <lb/>Pseudomonas, Staphylococcus, and Corynebacterium were the prominent genera in the <lb/>endometrium. The microbiome of the endometrium was distinctly different from that of the <lb/>vagina. There was large animal-to-animal variation. Other than the vaginal microbiome of <lb/>bitches in estrus (i.e. in heat), there were no distinct clustering of the organisms based on <lb/>the stage of estrous. These findings establish the presence of a resident microbiome of the <lb/>endometrium throughout all stages of estrous cycle. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>While it is established that the cranial vagina of mammals harbor a thriving microbial ecosys-<lb/>tem, the uterus was long considered a sterile environment in order to sustain a successful preg-<lb/>nancy. This paradigm was recently challenged by the observation that the human placenta <lb/>harbors a diverse microbiome [1, 2]. There is little information available on canine reproduc-<lb/>tive tract microbiota and all available data has been obtained using culture-based techniques <lb/>[3-7]. It has been established that standard culture-based techniques fail to detect &gt;90% of res-<lb/>ident microflora [8], underestimate diversity [9], and overestimate the role of culturable bacte-<lb/>ria [10]. <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/>1 / 17 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Lyman CC, Holyoak GR, Meinkoth K, <lb/>Wieneke X, Chillemi KA, DeSilva U (2019) Canine <lb/>endometrial and vaginal microbiomes reveal <lb/>distinct and complex ecosystems. PLoS ONE 14 <lb/>(1): e0210157. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0210157 <lb/>Editor: Claire Wade, University of Sydney Faculty of <lb/>Veterinary Science, AUSTRALIA <lb/>Received: March 7, 2018 <lb/>Accepted: December 18, 2018 <lb/>Published: January 7, 2019 <lb/>Copyright: © 2019 Lyman et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Data are available at <lb/>NCBI Sequence Read Archive (https://www.ncbi. <lb/>nlm.nih.gov/sra) under SRP115220. <lb/>Funding: This study was supported by the Center <lb/>for Veterinary Health Sciences, Oklahoma State <lb/>University, to CCL; and Oklahoma Agricultural <lb/>Experiment Station, to UD. The funders had no role <lb/>in study design, data collection and analysis, <lb/>decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></front>

			<body>A recent study utilizing culture-independent 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA) sequence analysis <lb/>of the bovine and ovine vaginal microbiota from ectocervicovaginal lavages revealed that cow <lb/>and ewe vaginal microbiota are unique from previously described vaginal microbial ecosys-<lb/>tems [11]. Similarly other studies specifically investigating the bovine uterine bacterial micro-<lb/>biota in healthy and metritic postpartum dairy cows found a significant diversity in the <lb/>type and succession of bacterial communities related to clinical signs and in time progression <lb/>[12-15]. <lb/>Although the presence of commensal microorganisms in the uterine lumen is generally <lb/>accepted in human medicine [2, 16, 17], the general consensus in canine medicine still is that <lb/>the normal uterus is a sterile environment [18]. Many microbes are implicated in infertility <lb/>and pregnancy loss [19, 20]. Culture of uterine swabs are performed routinely in bitches that <lb/>fail to get pregnant with normal breed/cycle management and presence of any growth calls for <lb/>antibiotic intervention [21]. As far as we are aware, this is the first comprehensive study of <lb/>uterine and vaginal microbiota of normal, healthy bitches using a culture-independent tech-<lb/>nique. We provide essential and compelling evidence, that the canine uterus has a thriving <lb/>microbial ecosystem and that treating a breeding bitch with antibiotics in the absence of <lb/>abnormal diagnostic findings is counterproductive. <lb/>Here we describe a culture-independent approach to evaluate bacterial population structure <lb/>and diversity of the cranial vagina and the endometrium of 25 clinically healthy bitches at vari-<lb/>ous stages of estrous. We present a comparative analysis of the microbiomes of the vagina and <lb/>the endometrium, organisms identified in both environments at both phylum and genus lev-<lb/>els, and differences observed at different stages of estrous. <lb/>Material and methods <lb/>Animals <lb/>Fifty young, healthy bitches presented to Oklahoma State University, Boren Veterinary Medi-<lb/>cal Hospital for elective ovariohysterectomy (OVH) were utilized in sample collection. Dogs <lb/>with clinical signs of estrus (i.e. in heat) were noted. None of the animals had recent antibiotic <lb/>exposure. Bitches were induced and anesthetized using an accepted shelter protocol: Telazol-<lb/>Torbugesic-Dexdomitor (Pfizer Animal Health, Parsippany, NJ) [22]. Once a level surgical <lb/>plane of anesthesia was obtained, each patient had blood samples collected for hormonal <lb/>assays. Samples for vaginal culture and cytology were collected using a standard technique <lb/>[21]. Briefly, after placing a sterile otoscope cone beyond the vaginal vestibule, a sterile cultur-<lb/>ette swab (Becton Dickinson, Franklin Lakes, NJ) was passed through the speculum to contact <lb/>the anterior vagina. The swab was placed inside of a sterile Eppendorf tube or sterile cryovial <lb/>tube for transport to the lab. Vaginal epithelial cell samples were obtained by passing a vaginal <lb/>cytologic brush through a vaginal speculum. A vaginal smear was prepared immediately and <lb/>processed in Diff-Quick stain (Cole-Palmer, Vernon Hills, IL). The slides were evaluated to <lb/>assist in classification of stages of estrous. Patients were then moved to the surgical suite for <lb/>ovariohysterectomy. The reproductive tract was removed using sterile surgical technique. The <lb/>uterine body was clamped and ligated proximal to the cervix. Two sections of uterine endome-<lb/>trial samples (1cm X1cm) were obtained using sterile Metzenbaum scissors and stored in indi-<lb/>vidual sterile Eppendorf tubes or sterile cryovial tubes appropriate for liquid nitrogen <lb/>cryopreservation of the endometrium until DNA extraction. Blood samples were evaluated <lb/>using ELISA progesterone assay. Animal use and procedures were approved by the Oklahoma <lb/>State University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC VM-14-42). All ani-<lb/>mals used in this study belonged to the Humane Society of Stillwater and were undergoing <lb/>mandatory ovariohysterectomy prior to being offered for adoption. The director of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<front>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>Humane Society approved of the collection of samples for the research described in this <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Estrous cycle based group designation <lb/>Of the fifty animals that were utilized in sample collection, five animals whose samples clearly <lb/>demarcated the stage of cycle were assigned to one of five groups based on the stage of the <lb/>estrous cycle: pre-pubertal, anestrus, pro-estrus, estrus or diestrus (n = 5 per group) giving a <lb/>total of twenty-five animals. Staging of the cycle was accomplished retrospectively via serum <lb/>progesterone analysis and by interpretation of vaginal cytology (superficial cornification, or <lb/>lack thereof) obtained immediately prior to the time of surgery, after which the samples were <lb/>allocated to their respective groups. Pre-pubertal group was determined by age. <lb/>DNA Isolation <lb/>Paired vaginal swab and endometrial biopsy samples from each animal were obtained for <lb/>DNA extraction. 0.4g of tissue was ground up in liquid N 2 and total DNA was extracted from <lb/>individual samples using QiAamp DNA mini kit (Qiagen, Germantown, MD) and following <lb/>manufacturer&apos;s instructions. A 0.8% (wt/vol) low melting point agarose gel was used to mea-<lb/>sure DNA quality. DNA was purified by using the Agarose Gel DNA Purification Kit (TaKaRa <lb/>Bio USA Inc., Mountainview, CA, USA). Purified DNA was quantified using a NanoDrop <lb/>ND-1000 spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, DE, USA). We obtained <lb/>161-605 ng/μl DNA from endometrial biopsies and 58-128 ng/μl DNA from vaginal swabs. <lb/>Each batch of DNA extractions and each new QiAamp DNA mini kit used were accompanied <lb/>by a negative control consisting of H 2 O roughly at the same volume as the samples analyzed. <lb/>Negative controls yielded 2-10 ng/μl DNA which was around the published minimal detection <lb/>level of the NanoDrop instrument that was used for quantifying DNA. All DNA extractions <lb/>were subjected to PCR amplification using 515F and 806R primer pair described below. All <lb/>biopsy and swabs samples showed robust amplification of microbial DNA while the negative <lb/>controls did not have a visible band after 35 cycles of amplification. Samples were stored at <lb/>-20˚C. Frozen DNA samples were sent to Molecular Research LLC for sequence analysis. Neg-<lb/>ative controls were not sequence analyzed as their concentration and quality was far below the <lb/>threshold acceptable to the sequence provider. <lb/>PCR amplification and DNA sequencing <lb/>A ~250 bp fragment from ribosomal v4 region was PCR-amplified from resulting DNA. PCR <lb/>amplification and amplicon sequencing was performed by Molecular Research LLC (Mr. <lb/>DNA), Shallowater, TX using their established protocols [23]. Briefly, an aliquot of 50 ng DNA <lb/>was used as template for PCR amplification. The V4 region of 16S rRNA gene was amplified <lb/>using the primer pair 515F (5&apos;-GTGCCAGCMGCCGCGGTAA-3&apos;) and 806R (5&apos;-GGAC <lb/>TACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3&apos;) with added barcodes on the forward primer. DNA was amplified <lb/>in a 28-cycle PCR using HotStarTaqPlus Master Mix Kit (Qiagen, USA) under the following <lb/>conditions: 94˚C for 3 minutes, followed by 28 cycles of 94˚C for 30 seconds, 53˚C for 40 sec-<lb/>onds, and 72˚C for 1 minute. Afterward, a final elongation step of 72˚C for 5 minutes was <lb/>performed. <lb/>A 2% agarose gel was used to determine the success of PCR amplification. DNA was puri-<lb/>fied using Qiagen Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen, USA). Multiple barcoded samples were pooled <lb/>in equal proportions based on their molecular weight and DNA concentrations. Pooled sam-<lb/>ples were purified with calibrated Ampure XP beads. The resulting pooled and purified PCR <lb/>product was used to prepare Illumina sequencing library. The library was constructed using <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>TruSeq DNA PCR-free sample preparation kit (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA) following <lb/>instructions and index codes were added. The library was quality tested on a Qubit 3.0 fluo-<lb/>rometer (ThermoScientific, Waltham, MA) and an Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 system (Agilent <lb/>Technologies, Santa Clara, CA). The library was sequenced on Illumina HiSeq2500 platform <lb/>(Illumina) and 250bp paired-end raw reads were generated. <lb/>Bioinformatic analysis <lb/>Mothur 1.37 was used for data mining following the MiSeq standard operating procedure <lb/>(SOP) [24]. Briefly, paired-end reads were assembled and assigned to each sample based on <lb/>their unique barcode and then truncated by removing barcodes and primer sequences. <lb/>Sequence reads that were over 273 bp in length, those that contained homoploymeric tracts of <lb/>longer than 8 bp in length, those that had more than one mismatch against primer sequences, <lb/>contained undetermined bases, ambiguities, or did not align to V4 hypervariable region were <lb/>removed from the analysis. Qualified contigs were further processed with commands &apos;trim. <lb/>seqs&apos; and &apos;pre.cluster&apos;. Uchime was used to remove chimeric sequences [25]. Alignment of V4 <lb/>region against SILVA rRNA ref nr123 [26] was performed using mothur (Needleman-Wunsch <lb/>algorithm). Qualified sequences were classified into operational taxonomic units (OTUs) <lb/>based on at least 97% similarity (OTU 0.03 ). All sequences of OTU 0.03 were assigned into taxo-<lb/>nomic groups at the bootstrap threshold of 80%. Samples were randomly normalized to the <lb/>sample with the least amount of sequencing reads to avoid sequencing bias. Alpha diversity <lb/>was calculated using command &apos;summary.single&apos; in mothur. Beta diversity was measured <lb/>using Unifrac-based metrics generated with command &apos;unifrac.weighted&apos; [27]. Raw sequenc-<lb/>ing data was submitted to Sequence Read Archive (SRA) at NCBI (access number SRP <lb/>115220). <lb/>Statistical analyses <lb/>R 3.3.2 statistical analysis software [28] was used to perform one-way analyses of variance <lb/>(one-way ANOVA), t-test, and Tukey&apos;s honest significant difference (HSD) test. Differences <lb/>were labeled as significant when the P value was &lt;0.05. The unweighted pair group method <lb/>with arithmetic mean(UPGMA) algorithm was performed using phangorn package in R [29]. <lb/>The UPGMA tree was used to reveal the similarity of bacterial community composition. <lb/>Linear discriminant analysis (LDA) Effect Size (LEfSe) was used to determine the change in <lb/>relative abundance of the bacterial community [30]. The non-parametric factorial Kruksal-<lb/>Wallis (KW) sum-rank test was first used to determine taxa with significant abundant differ-<lb/>ences (P&lt;0.05). The unpaired Wilcoxon rank-sum test was used to compare the significant <lb/>abundant differences among taxa (P&lt;0.05). Linear Discriminant Analysis was applied to cal-<lb/>culate effective size of abundant differences. Neighbor-joining trees were generated using <lb/>MEGAN Community Edition [31]. The Shannon diversity index was calculated using mothur <lb/>and principal coordinate analyses (PCoA) was calculated based on the distance matrix. <lb/>Results <lb/>16S rDNA sequencing resulted in 4,134,024 paired-end reads. After removal of ambiguous <lb/>and low-quality reads, 3,527,169 reads remained resulting in 70,543±51,247 reads per sample. <lb/>A taxonomy rarefaction curve (data not shown) indicated that the utilized sequencing depth <lb/>was sufficient to saturate the bacterial diversity in canine endometrium and vagina. Next-gen-<lb/>eration sequencing with barcoded and pooled amplicons generates large variations in reads <lb/>among samples. To eliminate sample size bias in downstream comparative analyses, we sub-<lb/>sampled every animal/tissue to normalize the reads to that with the lowest number of reads <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>[24, 32, 33]. After this process, 572,100 reads were selected for OTU classification. Of these, <lb/>562,971 reads were assigned to 24 known phyla and 384,974 sequence reads were classified <lb/>into 317 known genera. Phylum Proteobacteria had the highest diversity with 120 OTUs, fol-<lb/>lowed by Firmicutes (74 OTUs), Actinobacteria (46 OTUs), Bacteroidetes (38 OTUs), and <lb/>Fusobacteria (5 OTUs). Proteobacteria was also the most abundant phylum at 24.23% followed <lb/>by Bacteroidetes (17.32%), Firmicutes (14.4%), Actinobacteria (8.06%) Tenericutes (6.22%) <lb/>and Fusobacteria (3.27%). Proteobacteria, Bacteroidetes, and Firmicutes, the three dominant <lb/>phyla, accounted for 55.99% of the total bacterial community. Only three phyla, Proteobac-<lb/>teria, Bacteroidetes and Fusobacteria, were found in all 50 samples while Actinobacteria, Fir-<lb/>micutes and Tenericutes were observed in at least 47 samples. Bacteroidetes (34.3%), <lb/>Proteobacteria (26.2%), Tenericutes (15%), and Firmicutes (12.9%) were the most prevalent <lb/>phyla in the vagina while Proteobacteria (38.8%), Firmicutes (26.2%), Actinobacteria (18.2%), <lb/>and Bacteroidetes (9.4%) were the most prevalent phyla in the uterus (Fig 1, Table 1). Of the <lb/>24 phyla identified in this study, Cyanobacteria, Elusimicrobia, Gemmatimonadetes, Lenti-<lb/>sphaerae, and Thermotogae were only found in the vagina while Armatimonadetes, Chlamyd-<lb/>iae, and Deferribacteres, were only identified in the uterus. Chloroflexi, Deinococcus-<lb/>Thermus, Planctomycetes, Spirochaetes, Synergistetes, and Verrucomicrobia were extremely <lb/>rare in the vagina (&lt;5%). Firmicutes:Bacteroidetes ratio was lower in vagina compared to the <lb/>uterus (0.38 and 1.61 respectively). <lb/>At genus level (Fig 2 and S1 Table), 317 genera were identified in the endometrium and <lb/>vagina (248 in the endometrium and 254 in the vagina); Hydrotalea, Ralstonia, and Myco-<lb/>plasma accounted for 59.4% of the organisms identified in the vagina while the endometrium <lb/>had a more evenly distributed microbiome. Microbiome of the endometrium was also more <lb/>diverse than that of the vagina. Hydrotalea, Ralstonia, Mycoplasma, Fusobacterium and Strep-<lb/>tococcus were the predominant species in the vagina; whereas Pseudomonas, Staphylococcus, <lb/>and Corynebacterium were the predominant species in the uterus. Four genera, Hydrotalea, <lb/>Fig 1. Bacterial community composition in canine endometrium and vagina. Community composition at phylum level. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Ralstonia, Pseudomonas, and Fusobacterium existed ubiquitously across all samples accounting <lb/>for 33.24% of the community while 92 (28.93%) genera were present only in single samples. <lb/>Those represented 0.24% of the population. At genus level, we found the bacterial community <lb/>in the vagina to be higher in richness and the uterus was more diverse (Table 2). The difference <lb/>Table 1. Bacterial phyla identified in the endometrium and vagina. The numbers represent OTUs that could be <lb/>classified into a known genus after subsampling (384,974 reads). Phyla ordered alphabetically. E = endometrium, <lb/>V = vagina. <lb/>Phylum (n = 24) <lb/>E (n = 19) <lb/>V (n = 20) <lb/>Acidobacteria <lb/>54 <lb/>Actinobacteria <lb/>32269 <lb/>Aquificae &lt;phylum&gt; <lb/>16 <lb/>Armatimonadetes <lb/>50 <lb/>Bacteroidetes <lb/>16706 <lb/>Chlamydiae <lb/>45 <lb/>Chlorobi <lb/>1 <lb/>Chloroflexi <lb/>319 <lb/>Cyanobacteria <lb/>0 <lb/>Deferribacteres &lt;phylum&gt; <lb/>5 <lb/>Deinococcus-Thermus <lb/>7037 <lb/>Elusimicrobia <lb/>0 <lb/>Firmicutes <lb/>46560 <lb/>Fusobacteria <lb/>1806 <lb/>Gemmatimonadetes <lb/>0 <lb/>Lentisphaerae <lb/>0 <lb/>Nitrospirae <lb/>1 <lb/>Planctomycetes <lb/>647 <lb/>Proteobacteria <lb/>68861 <lb/>Spirochaetes <lb/>1725 <lb/>Synergistetes <lb/>96 <lb/>Tenericutes <lb/>357 <lb/>Thermotogae &lt;phylum&gt; <lb/>0 <lb/>Verrucomicrobia <lb/>909 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157.t001 <lb/>Fig 2. Bacterial community composition in canine endometrium and vagina. Community composition at genus <lb/>level. Only the top 25 genera are depicted in the key for clarity. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>was not statistically significant in diversity, although richness between endometrial and vaginal <lb/>microbiomes was significantly different (P = 0.0051). <lb/>We did not find significant differences in diversity (Shannon) and richness (Ace) among <lb/>endometrial and vaginal samples between different stages of estrous in one-way ANOVA. <lb/>However, Tukey&apos;s HSD analysis shows a significant difference in diversity among vaginal <lb/>microbiomes of animals in estrus (i.e. in heat) and those pre-pubertal (P&lt;0.05). There was a <lb/>significant difference in richness among endometrial samples at estrus and pro-estrus as well <lb/>as vaginal samples in animals in estrus and those in pre-pubertal stage (Fig 3). Endometrium <lb/>at estrus was the lowest in richness while the vagina at estrus and pro-estrus stages had the <lb/>highest richness (Table 3). <lb/>We evaluated the similarities between reproductive tract microbiota in bitches using the <lb/>neighbor-joining tree approach of MEGAN [31] at genus level (Fig 4). As expected, there was <lb/>a reasonably high inter-sample variability among samples. Vaginal samples clustered <lb/>Table 2. Diversity and Richness estimates of the endometrium and vagina at genus level. <lb/>DIVERSITY <lb/>RICHNESS <lb/>ENDOMETRIUM <lb/>3.06 ± 0.65 <lb/>7565.72 ± 2941.09 <lb/>VAGINA <lb/>2.75 ± 0.512 <lb/>10640.37 ± 2756.26 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157.t002 <lb/>Fig 3. Variation in diversity (Shannon index) and richness (Ace) in endometrium (E) and vagina (V) at different stages of estrous cycle. Anestrus (ae) is depicted <lb/>in red, diestrus (de) in green, estrus (e) in yellow, pro-estrus (pe) in purple, and pre-pubertal (pp) in dark beige. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3. Diversity and richness estimations of endometrial and vaginal samples at different stages of estrous. (AE = anestrus, DE = diestrus, E = estrus, PE = pro-<lb/>estrus and PP = pre-pubertal). <lb/>DIVERISTY <lb/>RICHNESS <lb/>Endometrium <lb/>Vagina <lb/>Endometrium <lb/>Vagina <lb/>AE <lb/>2.81 ± 1.12 <lb/>2.74 ± 0.61 <lb/>7202.88 ± 5676.79 <lb/>8598.18 ± 4667.98 <lb/>DE <lb/>3.01 ± 0.76 <lb/>2.65 ± 0.36 <lb/>8210.13 ± 2819.41 <lb/>9596.02 ± 878.71 <lb/>E <lb/>2.97 ± 0.28 <lb/>3.61 ± 0.42 <lb/>4724.86 ± 1235.92 <lb/>14495.97 ± 2126.36 <lb/>PE <lb/>3.28 ± 0.59 <lb/>2.46 ± 0.83 <lb/>9618.37 ± 2299.23 <lb/>12062.65 ± 3159.39 <lb/>PP <lb/>3.22 ± 0.5 <lb/>2.29 ± 0.34 <lb/>8072.34 ± 2674.12 <lb/>8449.01 ± 2948.87 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157.t003 <lb/>Fig 4. Neighbor-joining tree drawn at genus level. Circles represent endometrial samples while triangles are vaginal samples. Stages of estrous are color-coded. <lb/>Anestrus (ae)-yellow, estrus (e)-green, diestrus (de)-green, pro-estrus (pe)-red, and pre-pubertal (pp)-gray. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>independent of the endometrial samples at all stages of estrous. The same was observed in <lb/>Principal Coordinates Analysis (PCoA) (Fig 5). Other than vaginal samples from animals in <lb/>estrus, there was little correlation between microbiomes and the stage of estrous. Vaginal sam-<lb/>ples at estrus were high in similarity and clustered strongly together. We did not observe simi-<lb/>lar clustering in any of the other stages of estrous in either tissue. <lb/>We further confirmed the differentially abundant taxa by LEfSe, an algorithm for bio-<lb/>marker discovery that uses LDA to estimate the effect size of different taxa differentially repre-<lb/>sented in different environments (Fig 6). We used a cutoff LDA score of �2.0 for further <lb/>analysis. Ralstonia was the most common differentially abundant species in the vagina scoring <lb/>LDA scores &gt;5.0 in all stages of estrous. Vagina at estrus had the largest number of genera <lb/>(n = 24) that had LDA scores &gt;2.0. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Although the mammalian vagina was known to harbor a rich microbial ecosystem, other than <lb/>the well-described work done on the human reproductive tract [34-40], only a few non-<lb/>human vaginal microbiomes have been described to date [11, 41-43]. The endometrium on <lb/>the other hand, was considered a sterile environment [44, 45] until a few years ago when that <lb/>Fig 5. Principal Coordinates Analysis (PCoA). Distribution of bacterial communities based on the tissue and stage of estrous cycle. Community composition is <lb/>measured using a UniFrac-weighted matrix. Vaginal samples are in blue and endometrial samples are in red. Anestrus-(ae), estrus-(e), diestrus-(de), pro-estrus-(pe) <lb/>and pre-pubertal-(pp). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>paradigm was challenged by the observation that the human placenta possesses a small but <lb/>diverse microbiome [1, 44]. Although the presence of a placental microbiome has been ques-<lb/>tioned recently due to the possibility of contamination [46, 47], the presence of a rich micro-<lb/>biome in the mammalian endometrium was established in several species [48-51]. A few <lb/>studies have been performed exploring the microbiome of the canine reproductive tract [3, 6, <lb/>52-56], however these were all performed based on culture-based techniques that fail to iden-<lb/>tify a majority of organisms that inhabit a given ecosystem. <lb/>In this study, we sought to establish the vaginal and endometrial microbiomes of healthy <lb/>bitches. Samples were collected from 50 bitches and the stage of estrous cycle was determined <lb/>by serum progesterone analysis and vaginal cytology. Five animals were picked from each of <lb/>the five stages of estrous for sequence analysis. All animals used in this study were stray or <lb/>abandoned animals presented to a local animal shelter and, as such, we had no information on <lb/>their exact age or breed. Most animals looked cross-bred. Although estimated age and the <lb/>most probable breed composition of the animal was recorded, we did not select animals based <lb/>on those two criteria. We were able to amplify 16S rDNA fragments from each sample. How-<lb/>ever, our methodology does not allow us to estimate the total amount of rDNA fragments <lb/>amplified from each sample and as such, we cannot infer the density of microorganisms in any <lb/>one of the samples. We found the vagina to be much higher in richness (number of different <lb/>species) but lower in diversity (number of species and abundance of each species) compared to <lb/>Fig 6. Linear discriminant analysis (LDA) effect size (LEfSe) analysis of endometrial (e) vs. vaginal (v) samples at different stages of estrous cycle. LefSe analysis <lb/>identifies genera that differ significantly between the endometrium (e) and vagina (v). Relative abundance was considered significant when P&lt;0.05 and LDA Score <lb/>�2.0. Anestrus-(ae), estrus-(e), diestrus-(de), pro-estrus-(pe), and pre-pubertal-(pp). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>the endometrium (Table 2). The lower diversity is because 59.4% of the OTUs identified in the <lb/>vagina belonged to three genera, Ralstonia, Hydrotalea, and Mycoplasma (S1 Table). The <lb/>vagina at estrus (i.e. in heat) was the most diverse as well as the highest in richness (Table 3). <lb/>The differences however were not statistically significant except between estrus and pre-puber-<lb/>tal stage (Fig 3). The lack of significant differences among vaginal microbiomes at main stages <lb/>of estrous cycle is consistent with that seen in Go ¨ttingen minipigs [57]. Organisms identified <lb/>as major occupants of the vaginal microbiome in this study are different from other published <lb/>studies on canine vaginal microbiome. The most commonly isolated organisms in studies that <lb/>are older than 10 years include; Escherichia coli, Streptococcus canis, Pasteurella multocida, <lb/>Staphylococcus aureus and Staphylococcus pseudintermedius [3, 4, 58]. Of more recent studies, <lb/>Maksimovic&apos; et al. [6] found Staphylococcus spp, Streptococcus spp, Escherichia coli, and Proteus <lb/>spp. to be the most prevalent species and Hutchins et al. [7] found Staphylococcus pseudinter-<lb/>medius, Streptococcus, Enterococcus, and Escherichia coli to be the most prevalent species. <lb/>Although we detected 9184 OTUs of Streptococcus spp they only represented 4.4% of the popu-<lb/>lation (S1 Table). Staphylococcus represented 1.5% of the population, Enterococcus represented <lb/>.006% of the population, and we only detected Proteus in the endometrium. Surprisingly, we <lb/>did not detect any members of the genus Escherichia in our study. As noted before, all previous <lb/>studies have been conducted using culture-based technologies making a direct comparison dif-<lb/>ficult. Culture-based technologies are biased towards organisms that grow well in culture <lb/>media, aerobic organisms, and those that have a faster growth time. Lactobacilli is the most <lb/>common organism identified in humans ranging from 70-100% of human vaginal microbiota <lb/>[59-61]. We observed 76 OTUs representing Lactobacillus spp in the vagina and 25 OTUs in <lb/>the endometrium. Lactobacilli in the canine vagina represented 0.03% of the population. The <lb/>low abundance of Lactobacilli is consistent with what is observed in the cow and ewe repro-<lb/>ductive tracts [11] and could be attributable to the near neutral to alkaline pH [62] of the <lb/>canine vagina. Hydrotalea was the most prevalent genus in the vagina and accounted for over <lb/>25% of the organisms identified in the canine vagina. Hydrotalea belong to the family Bacteroi-<lb/>detes and is generally known as an aquatic species [63]. To our knowledge, other than low-<lb/>level presence in a single study on antibiotic-induced changes in rat gut [64], Hydrotalea has <lb/>never been reported in microbiomes of land-dwelling animals. Ralstonia accounted for 20.8% <lb/>of organisms detected in the vagina. Ralstonia belongs to the phylum Proteobacteria and is not <lb/>commonly associated with animals and no members of the genus is known to be pathogenic. <lb/>It has never been reported in a healthy mammalian vagina although it has been reported in <lb/>low concentrations in women that had levonorgestrel containing intrauterine devices placed <lb/>in them (0.8% in vagina, 7.8% in uterus) [65] and in one study of women diagnosed with clini-<lb/>cal vaginosis (0.8%) [66]. Mycoplasma (13.2%) was the third most abundant species. Although <lb/>Mycoplasma was present in all 25 samples we tested, it is not considered a major organism in <lb/>normal, healthy, vaginal flora of humans or animals [67]. However, it has been reported in <lb/>bacterial vaginosis and other disease statuses in humans for decades [66, 68]. Watts et al., failed <lb/>to culture mycoplasma from the reproductive tract of bitches at different stages of reproductive <lb/>cycle [56], while it was isolated from bitches treated with ampicillin and trimethoprim-sulfa-<lb/>methoxazole [69]. We found high numbers of Mycoplasma ubiquitously present in all the sam-<lb/>ples we tested from the vagina and they were detected at much lower concentration (0.18%) in <lb/>the endometrium suggesting that it is a commensal organism in the healthy canine reproduc-<lb/>tive tract. <lb/>In contrast to the vagina, we found the microbiome of the endometrium more evenly dis-<lb/>tributed. Although the phyla Proteobacteria, Firmicutes, Actinobacteria, and Bacteroidetes <lb/>accounted for 92.6% of the 19 phyla identified in the endometrium (Table 1, Fig 1), the distri-<lb/>bution of the organisms at genus level was more even (S1 Table, Fig 2). Pseudomonas (9.9%), <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Staphylococcus (6.5%) and Campylobacter (5.8%) were the most prevalent genera. Unlike in <lb/>the vagina, no organism represented more than 10% of the population. This distribution is in <lb/>stark contrast to endometrial microbiomes found in other species. In different human studies, <lb/>endometrial microbiomes ranged from Bacteroides predominance [51], Prevotella, Fusobacter-<lb/>ium, and Jonquetella Predominance [44, 70], to Flavobacterium and Lactobacillus predomi-<lb/>nance [49]. We found all these organisms with the exception of Jonquetella among our <lb/>samples. However, they were present in very low abundance (S1 Table). In dairy cattle, most <lb/>abundant genera were Fusobacterium, Bacteroides, Coxiella, Porphyromonas, and class Gam-<lb/>maproteobacteria [71, 72]. We did not observe any Coxiella in bitches. We observed similar <lb/>differences in vaginal microbiomes as well suggesting that core endometrial and vaginal <lb/>microbiomes tend to be species-specific. A few attempts have been made at isolating microbes <lb/>from the canine endometrium using culture-based techniques [3-6]. The success rate at isolat-<lb/>ing bacteria ranged from 3.8% [4] to 62.5% [6] proving that most endometrial microbes are <lb/>not amenable to culture using standard techniques. Most prevalent organisms isolated in these <lb/>studies were Staphylococcus, Mycoplasma and in one study Streptococcus [4]. Staphylococcus <lb/>was the second-most abundant organism in our study whereas Mycoplasma and Streptococcus <lb/>were much rarer. Staphylococcus and Streptococcus are also easily cultured under standard <lb/>technology explaining their abundance in culture-based studies. <lb/>Intriguingly, the most abundant organisms in the canine endometrium belonged to the <lb/>genus Pseudomonas and was identified in all endometrial samples. Pseudomonas spp is often <lb/>associated with pyometra in bitches [73] but has not been reported in a healthy endometrium. <lb/>The SILVA database [26] was used to classify OTUs and does not allow taxonomic classifica-<lb/>tion at species level. Although indirect evidence suggests that the genus Pseudomonas in the <lb/>canine endometrium consists of several species, the exact identity of the organisms remain <lb/>unknown. Staphylococcus, the genus with second highest abundance in the endometrium has <lb/>been isolated from the canine endometrium in previous studies [3, 5, 6]. Campylobacter repre-<lb/>sented 5.8% of organisms identified in the endometrium and seems to be a major representa-<lb/>tive of the canine endometrial microbiome. Although Campylobacter associated reproductive <lb/>tract pathology has not been reported in bitches, different species of Campylobacter has been <lb/>implicated in abortions in cattle and sheep [74, 75]. <lb/>The prevalent explanation for the presence of microbes in the uterus was that they always <lb/>are introduced as an ascending infection from the vagina through an open cervix during pro-<lb/>estrus and estrus. To test this hypothesis, we compared the vaginal and uterine microbiomes of <lb/>the five bitches in estrus (Fig 6). Contrary to the prevailing notion, we did not find a correla-<lb/>tion between the vaginal and uterine microbiomes of any of the bitches suggesting that the <lb/>endometrium has its own resident microbiome and it was not established as an ascending <lb/>infection from the vagina [76, 77]. <lb/>Since the focus of this study was to ascertain the presence of an endometrial microbiome of <lb/>healthy bitches and to compare the microbiome across different stages of estrous, we did not <lb/>analyze the effect of breed and age of the animal (other than pre-pubertal animals). The source <lb/>of our experimental animals (local humane society) would have made reliable age and breed <lb/>estimates difficult. Although it is possible for breed differences in reproductive tract micro-<lb/>biomes to exist, many studies have found no differences in resident microbiomes of animals of <lb/>different breeds housed in similar conditions [78-80]. We found the diversity and richness of <lb/>microbiomes of pre-pubertal animals to be significantly different from older animals (Fig 3). <lb/>Both breeds and ages were rough phenotypic estimates as all of these animals were obtained <lb/>from a local Humane Society and most looked crossbred. We were intrigued to find a rich, <lb/>diverse uterine microbiome even in the youngest pre-pubertal animals used in the study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Conclusions <lb/>From this study, we conclude that both the endometrium and the vagina have rich microbial <lb/>ecosystems. The endometrium is much more diverse than the vagina. The endometrial micro-<lb/>biome does not change with the stage of the estrous cycle. Whereas the vaginal environment in <lb/>estrus (i.e. in heat) is significantly different from other stages of estrous. There is no age or <lb/>breed effect, while significant animal-to-animal variation in endometrial and vaginal micro-<lb/>biome does exist. We conclude from our results as well as past studies that culture-based sys-<lb/>tems miss the great diversity present in both diseased and healthy reproductive tracts. Given <lb/>this diversity, there is much to be studied relative to the intra-microbiota interactions and spe-<lb/>cies-intrinsic factors that may be more relevant to maintaining a state of balance and health <lb/>and that an imbalance of these factors maybe more important in the development of uterine <lb/>disease than the abundance of any given bacterial species. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Table. Bacterial genera identified in canine endometrium and vagina. Column A is <lb/>sorted by prevalence in the vagina and Column B is sorted by prevalence in the endometrium. <lb/>317 known genera were identified among the samples. 254 genera were present in the vagina <lb/>and 248 were present in the endometrium. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>Center for Veterinary Health Sciences, Oklahoma State University (to CCL) and Oklahoma <lb/>Agricultural Experiment Station (to UD). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: G. R. Holyoak. <lb/>Data curation: C. C. Lyman, X. Wieneke, U. DeSilva. <lb/>Formal analysis: C. C. Lyman, U. DeSilva. <lb/>Investigation: C. C. Lyman, G. R. Holyoak, K. Meinkoth, K. A. Chillemi, U. DeSilva. <lb/>Methodology: C. C. Lyman, G. R. Holyoak. <lb/>Resources: K. Meinkoth. <lb/>Supervision: G. R. Holyoak, U. DeSilva. <lb/>Writing -original draft: C. C. Lyman, U. DeSilva. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: C. C. Lyman, G. R. Holyoak, K. Meinkoth, U. DeSilva. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Aagaard K, Ma J, Antony KM, Ganu R, Petrosino J, Versalovic J. The Placenta Harbors a Unique Micro-<lb/>biome. Science Translational Medicine. 2014; 6(237). https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.3008599 <lb/>PMID: 24848255 <lb/>2. Wassenaar TM, Panigrahi P. Is a foetus developing in a sterile environment? Letters in Applied Microbi-<lb/>ology. 2014; 59(6):572-9. https://doi.org/10.1111/lam.12334 PMID: 25273890 <lb/>3. Baba E, Hata H, Fukata T, Arakawa A. Vaginal and Uterine Microflora of Adult Dogs. American Journal <lb/>of Veterinary Research. 1983; 44(4):606-9. PMID: 6683475 <lb/>4. Olson PNS, Mather EC. CANINE VAGINAL AND UTERINE BACTERIAL-FLORA. Journal of the Ameri-<lb/>can Veterinary Medical Association. 1978; 172(6):708-11. PMID: 640936 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>5. Schultheiss PC, Jones RL, Kesel ML, Olson PN. Normal bacterial flora in canine and feline uteri. Journal <lb/>of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation. 1999; 11(6):560-2. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>104063879901100618 PMID: 12968746 <lb/>6. Maksimovic A, Maksimovic Z, Filipovic S, Besirovic H, Rifatbegovic M. Vaginal and uterine bacteria of <lb/>healthy bitches during different stages of their reproductive cycle. Veterinary Record. 2012; 171 <lb/>(15):375-+. https://doi.org/10.1136/vr.100886 PMID: 22903902 <lb/>7. Hutchins RG, Vaden SL, Jacob ME, Harris TL, Bowles KD, Wood MW, et al. Vaginal Microbiota of <lb/>Spayed Dogs with or without Recurrent Urinary Tract Infections. Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine. <lb/>2014; 28(2):300-4. https://doi.org/10.1111/jvim.12299 PMID: 24467326 <lb/>8. Theron J, Cloete TE. Molecular techniques for determining microbial diversity and community structure <lb/>in natural environments. Critical Reviews in Microbiology. 2000; 26(1):37-57. https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>10408410091154174 PMID: 10782339 <lb/>9. Whitman WB, Coleman DC, Wiebe WJ. Prokaryotes: The unseen majority. Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 1998; 95(12):6578-83. https://doi.org/10.1073/ <lb/>pnas.95.12.6578 PMID: 9618454 <lb/>10. Shade A, Hogan CS, Klimowicz AK, Linske M, McManus PS, Handelsman J. Culturing captures mem-<lb/>bers of the soil rare biosphere. Environmental Microbiology. 2012; 14(9):2247-52. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1111/j.1462-2920.2012.02817.x PMID: 22788977 <lb/>11. Swartz JD, Lachman M, Westveer K, O&apos;Neill T, Geary T, Kott RW, et al. Characterization of the Vaginal <lb/>Microbiota of Ewes and Cows Reveals a Unique Microbiota with Low Levels of Lactobacilli and Near-<lb/>Neutral pH. Frontiers in veterinary science. 2014; 1:19. Epub 2014/01/01. https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets. <lb/>2014.00019 PMID: 26664918. <lb/>12. Santos T, Gilbert R, Bicalho R. Metagenomic analysis of the uterine bacterial microbiota in healthy and <lb/>metritic postpartum dairy cows. Journal of Dairy Science. 2011; 94(1):291-302. https://doi.org/10.3168/ <lb/>jds.2010-3668 PMID: 21183039 <lb/>13. Peng Y, Wang YH, Hang SQ, Zhu WY. Microbial diversity in uterus of healthy and metritic postpartum <lb/>Holstein dairy cows. Folia Microbiologica. 2013; 58(6):593-600. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12223-013-<lb/>0238-6 PMID: 23585284 <lb/>14. Santos TMA, Bicalho RC. Diversity and Succession of Bacterial Communities in the Uterine Fluid of <lb/>Postpartum Metritic, Endometritic and Healthy Dairy Cows. Plos One. 2012; 7(12). https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1371/journal.pone.0053048 PMID: 23300859 <lb/>15. Machado V, Oikonomou G, Bicalho M, Knauer W, Gilbert R, Bicalho R. Investigation of postpartum <lb/>dairy cows&apos; uterine microbial diversity using metagenomic pyrosequencing of the 16S rRNA gene. Vet-<lb/>erinary Microbiology. 2012; 159(3-4):460-9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vetmic.2012.04.033 PMID: <lb/>22595139 <lb/>16. Perez-Munoz ME, Arrieta MC, Ramer-Tait AE, Walter J. A critical assessment of the &quot;sterile womb&quot; and <lb/>&quot;in utero colonization&quot; hypotheses: implications for research on the pioneer infant microbiome. Micro-<lb/>biome. 2017; 5. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40168-017-0268-4 PMID: 28454555 <lb/>17. Moreno I, Franasiak JM. Endometrial microbiota-new player in town. Fertility and Sterility. 2017; 108 <lb/>(1):32-9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fertnstert.2017.05.034 PMID: 28602480 <lb/>18. Threlfall W. Canine: Breeding soundness examination of the bitch Kansas City: CVC; 2008 [cited 2018 <lb/>7/21/2018]. http://veterinarycalendar.dvm360.com/canine-breeding-soundness-examination-bitch-<lb/>proceedings. <lb/>19. Graham EM, Taylor DJ. Bacterial Reproductive Pathogens of Cats and Dogs. Vet Clin North Am Small <lb/>Anim Pract. 2012; 42(3):561-82. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cvsm.2012.01.013 PMID: 22482819 <lb/>20. Pretzer SD. Bacterial and protozoal causes of pregnancy loss in the bitch and queen. Theriogenology. <lb/>2008; 70(3):320-6. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.theriogenology.2008.04.035 PMID: 18495236 <lb/>21. Kustritz MVR. Collection of tissue and culture samples from the canine reproductive tract. Theriogenol-<lb/>ogy. 2006; 66(3 SPEC. ISS.):567-74. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.theriogenology.2006.05.003 PMID: <lb/>16750845 <lb/>22. Ko JC, Berman AG. Anesthesia in shelter medicine. Topics in Companion Animal Medicine. 2010; 25 <lb/>(2):92-7. https://doi.org/10.1053/j.tcam.2010.03.001 PMID: 20515672 <lb/>23. Dowd SE, Sun Y, Wolcott RD, Domingo A, Carroll JA. Bacterial tag-encoded FLX amplicon pyrose-<lb/>quencing (bTEFAP) for microbiome studies: Bacterial diversity in the ileum of newly weaned Salmo-<lb/>nella-infected pigs. Foodborne Pathogens and Disease. 2008; 5(4):459-72. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd. <lb/>2008.0107 PMID: 18713063 <lb/>24. Schloss PD, Westcott SL, Ryabin T, Hall JR, Hartmann M, Hollister EB, et al. Introducing mothur: <lb/>Open-Source, Platform-Independent, Community-Supported Software for Describing and Comparing <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Microbial Communities. Applied and Environmental Microbiology. 2009; 75(23):7537-41. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1128/AEM.01541-09 PMID: 19801464 <lb/>25. Edgar RC, Haas BJ, Clemente JC, Quince C, Knight R. UCHIME improves sensitivity and speed of chi-<lb/>mera detection. Bioinformatics. 2011; 27(16):2194-200. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btr381 <lb/>PMID: 21700674 <lb/>26. Quast C, Pruesse E, Yilmaz P, Gerken J, Schweer T, Yarza P, et al. The SILVA ribosomal RNA gene <lb/>database project: improved data processing and web-based tools. Nucleic Acids Research. 2013; 41 <lb/>(D1):D590-D6. <lb/>27. Lozupone C, Lladser ME, Knights D, Stombaugh J, Knight R. UniFrac: An effective distance metric for <lb/>microbial community comparison. ISME Journal. 2011; 5(2):169-72. https://doi.org/10.1038/ismej. <lb/>2010.133 PMID: 20827291 <lb/>28. Team RC. R: A language and environment for statistical computing Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for <lb/>Statistical Computing; 2013 [cited 2018 04/07]. http://www.R-project.org/. <lb/>29. Schliep KP. phangorn: Phylogenetic analysis in R. Bioinformatics. 2011; 27(4):592-3. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1093/bioinformatics/btq706 PMID: 21169378 <lb/>30. Segata N, Izard J, Waldron L, Gevers D, Miropolsky L, Garrett WS, et al. Metagenomic biomarker dis-<lb/>covery and explanation. Genome Biology. 2011; 12(6). <lb/>31. Huson DH, Beier S, Flade I, Gorska A, El-Hadidi M, Mitra S, et al. MEGAN Community Edition-<lb/>Interactive Exploration and Analysis of Large-Scale Microbiome Sequencing Data. PLoS Comput Biol. <lb/>2016; 12(6):e1004957. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004957 PMID: 27327495. <lb/>32. Ding T, Schloss PD. Dynamics and associations of microbial community types across the human body. <lb/>Nature. 2014; 509(7500):357-+. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature13178 PMID: 24739969 <lb/>33. Metzler-Zebeli BU, Schmitz-Esser S, Mann E, Grull D, Molnar T, Zebeli Q. Adaptation of the Cecal Bac-<lb/>terial Microbiome of Growing Pigs in Response to Resistant Starch Type 4. Applied and Environmental <lb/>Microbiology. 2015; 81(24):8489-99. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.02756-15 PMID: 26431973 <lb/>34. Sirota I, Zarek SM, Segars JH. Potential Influence of the Microbiome on Infertility and Assisted Repro-<lb/>ductive Technology. Seminars in Reproductive Medicine. 2014; 32(1):35-42. https://doi.org/10.1055/s-<lb/>0033-1361821 PMID: 24390919 <lb/>35. Braundmeier AG, Lenz KM, Inman KS, Chia N, Jeraldo P, Walther-Antonio MRS, et al. Individualized <lb/>medicine and the microbiome in reproductive tract. Frontiers in Physiology. 2015; 6. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>3389/fphys.2015.00097 PMID: 25883569 <lb/>36. Martin DH, Marrazzo JM. The Vaginal Microbiome: Current Understanding and Future Directions. Jour-<lb/>nal of Infectious Diseases. 2016; 214:S36-S41. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiw184 PMID: 27449871 <lb/>37. Zhou X, Brown CJ, Abdo Z, Davis CC, Hansmann MA, Joyce P, et al. Differences in the composition of <lb/>vaginal microbial communities found in healthy Caucasian and black women. Isme Journal. 2007; 1 <lb/>(2):121-33. https://doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2007.12 PMID: 18043622 <lb/>38. Srinivasan S, Hoffman NG, Morgan MT, Matsen FA, Fiedler TL, Hall RW, et al. Bacterial Communities <lb/>in Women with Bacterial Vaginosis: High Resolution Phylogenetic Analyses Reveal Relationships of <lb/>Microbiota to Clinical Criteria. Plos One. 2012; 7(6). https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0037818 <lb/>PMID: 22719852 <lb/>39. Srinivasan S, Liu CZ, Mitchell CM, Fiedler TL, Thomas KK, Agnew KJ, et al. Temporal Variability of <lb/>Human Vaginal Bacteria and Relationship with Bacterial Vaginosis. Plos One. 2010; 5(4). https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1371/journal.pone.0010197 PMID: 20419168 <lb/>40. Marrazzo JM. Vaginal Biofilms and Bacterial Vaginosis: Of Mice and Women. Journal of Infectious Dis-<lb/>eases. 2013; 207(10):1481-3. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jit050 PMID: 23431034 <lb/>41. Barfod KK, Roggenbuck M, Hansen LH, Schjorring S, Larsen ST, Sorensen SJ, et al. The murine lung <lb/>microbiome in relation to the intestinal and vaginal bacterial communities. Bmc Microbiology. 2013; 13. <lb/>42. Yildirim S, Yeoman CJ, Janga SC, Thomas SM, Ho MF, Leigh SR, et al. Primate vaginal microbiomes <lb/>exhibit species specificity without universal Lactobacillus dominance. Isme Journal. 2014; 8(12):2431-<lb/>44. https://doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.90 PMID: 25036926 <lb/>43. Yang X, Yang J, Wang HN, Li CW, He YG, Jin SY, et al. Normal vaginal bacterial flora of giant pandas <lb/>(Ailuropoda melanoleuca) and the antimicrobial susceptibility patterns of the isolates. Journal of Zoo <lb/>and Wildlife Medicine. 2016; 47(2):671-5. <lb/>44. Giudice LC. Challenging dogma: the endometrium has a microbiome with functional consequences! <lb/>American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology. 2016; 215(6):682-3. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajog. <lb/>2016.09.085 PMID: 27725136 <lb/>45. Ansbacher R, Boyson WA, Morris JA. Sterility of the uterine cavity. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1967; <lb/>99:394-6. PMID: 4962972 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>46. Lauder AP, Roche AM, Sherrill-Mix S, Bailey A, Laughlin AL, Bittinger K, et al. Comparison of placenta <lb/>samples with contamination controls does not provide evidence for a distinct placenta microbiota. <lb/>Microbiome. 2016; 4. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40168-016-0172-3 PMID: 27338728 <lb/>47. Willyard C. Baby&apos;s first bacteria THE WOMB WAS THOUGHT TO BE STERILE. SOME SCIENTISTS <lb/>ARGUE IT&apos;S WHERE THE MICROBIOME BEGINS. Nature. 2018; 553(7688):264-6. <lb/>48. Karstrup CC, Agerholm JS, Jensen TK, Swaro LRV, Klitgaard K, Rasmussen EL, et al. Presence and <lb/>localization of bacteria in the bovine endometrium postpartum using fluorescence in situ hybridization. <lb/>Theriogenology. 2017; 92:167-75. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.theriogenology.2017.01.026 PMID: <lb/>28237333 <lb/>49. Franasiak JM, Werner MD, Juneau CR, Tao X, Landis J, Zhan Y, et al. Endometrial microbiome at the <lb/>time of embryo transfer: next-generation sequencing of the 16S ribosomal subunit. Journal of Assisted <lb/>Reproduction and Genetics. 2016; 33(1):129-36. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10815-015-0614-z PMID: <lb/>26547201 <lb/>50. Moore SG, Ericsson AC, Poock SE, Melendez P, Lucy MC. 16S rRNA gene sequencing reveals the <lb/>microbiome of the virgin and pregnant bovine uterus. Journal of Dairy Science. 2017; 100(6):4953-60. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3168/jds.2017-12592 PMID: 28434745 <lb/>51. Verstraelen H, Vilchez-Vargas R, Desimpel F, Jauregui R, Vankeirsbilck N, Weyers S, et al. Characteri-<lb/>sation of the human uterine microbiome in non-pregnant women through deep sequencing of the V1-2 <lb/>region of the 16S rRNA gene. Peerj. 2016; 4. https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.1602 PMID: 26823997 <lb/>52. Groppetti D, Pecile A, Barbero C, Martino PA. Vaginal bacterial flora and cytology in proestrous bitches: <lb/>Role on fertility. Theriogenology. 2012; 77(8):1549-56. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.theriogenology.2011. <lb/>11.022 PMID: 22289216 <lb/>53. Gunay U, Onat K, Gunay A, Ulgen M. Vaginal, Cervical and Uterine Bacterial Flora at the Different <lb/>Stages of the Reproductive Cycle in Ovariohysterectomized Bitches. Journal of Animal and Veterinary <lb/>Advances. 2010; 9(3):478-81. <lb/>54. Laurusevicius SA, Siugzdaite J, Zilinskas H. Correlation between different sexual cycle stages and vagi-<lb/>nal bacterial flora in bitches of different breeds. Veterinarija Ir Zootechnika. 2008; 41(63):76-9. <lb/>55. Zheng H, Zheng X, Gen J, Zhang W, He C, Li M, et al. Microbial flora in vagina and uterus of bitches. <lb/>Chinese Journal of Veterinary Medicine. 2000; 26(9):47-8. CABI:20013168214. <lb/>56. Watts JR, Wright PJ, Whithear KC. Uterine, cervical and vaginal microflora of the normal bitch through-<lb/>out the reproductive cycle. Journal of Small Animal Practice. 1996; 37(2):54-60. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1111/j.1748-5827.1996.tb01936.x PMID: 8656593 <lb/>57. Lorenzen E, Kudirkiene E, Gutman N, Grossi AB, Agerholm JS, Erneholm K, et al. The vaginal micro-<lb/>biome is stable in prepubertal and sexually mature Ellegaard Gottingen Minipigs throughout an estrous <lb/>cycle. Veterinary Research. 2015; 46. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13567-015-0274-0 PMID: 26510418 <lb/>58. Allen WE, Dagnall GJR. Some observations on the aerobic bacterial-flora of the genital-tract of the dog <lb/>and bitch. Journal of Small Animal Practice. 1982; 23(6):325-35. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1748-5827. <lb/>1982.tb01674.x <lb/>59. Franasiak JM, Scott RT. Introduction: Microbiome in human reproduction. Fertility and Sterility. 2015; <lb/>104(6):1341-3. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fertnstert.2015.10.021 PMID: 26515381 <lb/>60. MacIntyre DA, Chandiramani M, Lee YS, Kindinger L, Smith A, Angelopoulos N, et al. The vaginal <lb/>microbiome during pregnancy and the postpartum period in a European population. Scientific Reports. <lb/>2015; 5:1-9. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep08988 PMID: 25758319 <lb/>61. Huttenhower C, Gevers D, Knight R, Abubucker S, Badger JH, Chinwalla AT, et al. Structure, function <lb/>and diversity of the healthy human microbiome. Nature. 2012; 486(7402):207-14. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1038/nature11234 PMID: 22699609 <lb/>62. Delucchi L, Fraga M, Perelmuter K, Cidade E, Zunino P. Vaginal lactic acid bacteria in healthy and ill <lb/>bitches and evaluation of in vitro probiotic activity of selected isolates. Canadian Veterinary Journal-<lb/>Revue Veterinaire Canadienne. 2008; 49(10):991-4. <lb/>63. Kampfer P, Lodders N, Falsen E. Hydrotalea flava gen. nov., sp. nov., a new member of the phylum <lb/>Bacteroidetes and allocation of the genera Chitinophaga, Sediminibacterium, Lacibacter, Flavihumibac-<lb/>ter, Flavisolibacter, Niabella, Niastella, Segetibacter, Parasegetibacter, Terrimonas, Ferruginibacter, <lb/>Filimonas and Hydrotalea to the family Chitinophagaceae fam. nov. International Journal of Systematic <lb/>and Evolutionary Microbiology. 2011; 61:518-23. https://doi.org/10.1099/ijs.0.023002-0 PMID: <lb/>20382796 <lb/>64. Khan I, Azhar EI, Abbas AT, Kumosani T, Barbour EK, Raoult D, et al. Metagenomic Analysis of Antibi-<lb/>otic-Induced Changes in Gut Microbiota in a Pregnant Rat Model. Frontiers in Pharmacology. 2016; <lb/>7:104. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2016.00104 PMID: 27199748 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>65. Jacobson JC, Turok DK, Dermish AI, Nygaard IE, Settles ML. Vaginal microbiome changes with levo-<lb/>norgestrel intrauterine system placement. Contraception. 2014; 90(2):130-5. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>contraception.2014.04.006 PMID: 24835828 <lb/>66. Xia Q, Cheng LJ, Zhang H, Sun SW, Liu F, Li H, et al. Identification of vaginal bacteria diversity and it&apos;s <lb/>association with clinically diagnosed bacterial vaginosis by denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis and <lb/>correspondence analysis. Infection Genetics and Evolution. 2016; 44:479-86. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>meegid.2016.08.001 PMID: 27503595 <lb/>67. Ljubin-Sternak S, Mestrovic T. Chlamydia trachomatis and Genital Mycoplasmas: Pathogens with an <lb/>Impact on Human Reproductive Health. Journal of Pathogens. 2014; 2014:15. https://doi.org/10.1155/ <lb/>2014/183167 PMID: 25614838 <lb/>68. Waites KB, Katz B, Schelonka RL. Mycoplasmas and ureaplasmas as neonatal pathogens. Clinical <lb/>Microbiology Reviews. 2005; 18(4):757-+. https://doi.org/10.1128/CMR.18.4.757-789.2005 PMID: <lb/>16223956 <lb/>69. Stro ¨m B, Linde-Forsberg C. Effects of ampicillin and trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole on the vaginal bac-<lb/>terial flora of bitches. American journal of veterinary research. 1993; 54(6):891-6. PMID: 8323058. <lb/>70. Pelzer E, Willner D, Huygens F, Buttini M. IS DIVERSIFICATION OF THE ENDOMETRIAL MICRO-<lb/>BIOME SIGNIFICANT FOR REPRODUCTIVE SUCCESS? Placenta. 2015; 36(9):A23-A. <lb/>71. Santos TMA, Gilbert RO, Bicalho RC. Metagenomic analysis of the uterine bacterial microbiota in <lb/>healthy and metritic postpartum dairy cows. Journal of Dairy Science. 2011; 94(1):291-302. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3168/jds.2010-3668 PMID: 21183039 <lb/>72. Jeon SJ, Vieira-Neto A, Gobikrushanth M, Daetz R, Mingoti RD, Parize ACB, et al. Uterine Microbiota <lb/>Progression from Calving until Establishment of Metritis in Dairy Cows. Applied and Environmental <lb/>Microbiology. 2015; 81(18):6324-32. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.01753-15 PMID: 26150453 <lb/>73. Vandeplassche M, Coryn M, Deschepper J. Pyometra in the Bitch-Cytological, Bacterial, Histological <lb/>and Endocrinologic Characteristics. Vlaams Diergeneeskundig Tijdschrift. 1991; 60(6):207-11. <lb/>74. Hedstrom OR, Sonn RJ, Lassen ED, Hultgren BD, Crisman RO, Smith BB, et al. Pathology of Campylo-<lb/>bacter-Jejuni Abortion in Sheep. Veterinary Pathology. 1987; 24(5):419-26. https://doi.org/10.1177/ <lb/>030098588702400509 PMID: 3672807 <lb/>75. Gilbert GL, Davoren RA, Cole ME, Radford NJ. Midtrimester-Abortion Associated with Septicemia <lb/>Caused by Campylobacter-Jejuni. Medical Journal of Australia. 1981; 1(11):585-6. PMID: 7254038 <lb/>76. Hadley JC. The development of cystic endometrial hyperplasia in the bitch following serial uterine biop-<lb/>sies. Journal of Small Animal Practice. 1975; 16(1-12):249-57. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1748-5827. <lb/>1975.tb05741.x <lb/>77. Schlafer DH, Gifford AT. Cystic endometrial hyperplasia, pseudo-placentational endometrial hyperpla-<lb/>sia, and other cystic conditions of the canine and feline uterus. Theriogenology. 2008; 70(3):349-58. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.theriogenology.2008.04.041 PMID: 18550158 <lb/>78. Bian G, Ma S, Zhu Z, Su Y, Zoetendal EG, Mackie R, et al. Age, introduction of solid feed and weaning <lb/>are more important determinants of gut bacterial succession in piglets than breed and nursing mother <lb/>as revealed by a reciprocal cross-fostering model. Environmental Microbiology. 2016; 18(5):1566-77. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/1462-2920.13272 PMID: 26940746 <lb/>79. Ding J, Dai R, Yang L, He C, Xu K, Liu S, et al. Inheritance and establishment of gut microbiota in chick-<lb/>ens. Frontiers in Microbiology. 2017; 8(OCT). https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01967 PMID: <lb/>29067020 <lb/>80. Li Q, Lauber CL, Czarnecki-Maulden G, Pan Y, Hannah SS. Effects of the dietary protein and carbohy-<lb/>drate ratio on gut microbiomes in dogs of different body conditions. mBio. 2017; 8(1). https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1128/mBio.01703-16 PMID: 28119466 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Canine endometrial and vaginal microbiomes <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210157 January 7, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 17 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
