<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Apache is a neuronal player in autophagy required for retrograde axonal transport of autophagosomes</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Barbara</forename>
            <surname>Parisi</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Alessandro</forename>
            <surname>Esposito</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Enrico</forename>
            <surname>Castroflorio</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Mattia</forename>
            <surname>Bramini</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Sara</forename>
            <surname>Pepe</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Antonella</forename>
            <surname>Marte</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Fabrizia C.</forename>
            <surname>Guarnieri</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Flavia</forename>
            <surname>Valtorta</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Pietro</forename>
            <surname>Baldelli</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Fabio</forename>
            <surname>Benfenati</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Anna</forename>
            <surname>Fassio</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Silvia</forename>
            <surname>Giovedì</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-27T09:36:32.893074Z">27.10.2025 09:36:32</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1007$1$s00018-024-05441-7</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00018-024-05441-7</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Barbara Parisi, Alessandro Esposito, Enrico Castroflorio, Mattia Bramini, Sara Pepe, Antonella Marte, Fabrizia C. Guarnieri, Flavia Valtorta, Pietro Baldelli, Fabio Benfenati, Anna Fassio, Silvia Giovedì. (2024). Apache is a neuronal player in autophagy required for retrograde axonal transport of autophagosomes. Cellular and Molecular Life Sciences, 81(1), None. DOI: 10.1007/s00018-024-05441-7</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-27T09:36:32.893074Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-27T09:36:32.893074Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s40121-024-01022-0 <lb/>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Pediatric Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine <lb/>and Dosing Schedule Perceptions Among Health Care <lb/>Providers and Caregivers in Germany, France, Spain, <lb/>and Greece <lb/>Johnna E. Perdrizet • Mark H. Rozenbaum • Matthew J. Heffler <lb/>Received: May 22, 2024 / Accepted: July 12, 2024 / Published online: July 26, 2024 <lb/>© The Author(s) 2024 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Introduction: Most European infant national <lb/>immunization programs (NIPs) recommend <lb/>pneumococcal conjugate vaccines (PCVs), which <lb/>currently cover 10-15 serotypes administered <lb/>in a three-dose schedule (two primary plus one <lb/>booster). Recently, a PCV covering 20 serotypes <lb/>that is administered in a four-dose schedule <lb/>(three primary plus one booster) was licensed. <lb/>Methods: An online survey was administered <lb/>to collect data from health care providers (HCPs) <lb/>and caregivers of children aged 0-5 (including <lb/>expectant mothers) in four European countries <lb/>(Germany, France, Spain, and Greece). All car-<lb/>egiver respondents had a shared or full respon-<lb/>sibility to make health decisions for their child. <lb/>Data on opinions, perceptions, and openness to <lb/>a change in childhood vaccination dosing sched-<lb/>ules were collected, along with demographic <lb/>information for HCPs as well as caregivers. <lb/>Results: A total of 601 HCPs and 1954 car-<lb/>egivers were recruited across the four countries. <lb/>Nearly all HCPs (93%) agreed that broader sero-<lb/>type coverage against pneumococcal disease for <lb/>children is a significant unmet need, and 92% <lb/>had a &quot;sense of urgency&quot; to vaccinate children. <lb/>Both HCPs and caregivers were supportive of an <lb/>additional PCV dose and doctor visit, assuming <lb/>it provided at least 20% more serotype cover-<lb/>age than what is currently available. Caregivers <lb/>strongly agreed on the importance of full vac-<lb/>cination for pneumococcal disease, even if an <lb/>extra dose and visit to the doctor was required. <lb/>Conclusions: HCPs and caregivers were virtu-<lb/>ally unanimous in their support for a PCV with <lb/>broader serotype coverage and showed a sub-<lb/>sequent willingness to include an extra infant <lb/>dose/visit. These results can help guide broader <lb/>discussions regarding public health policy and <lb/>vaccine administration in the context of impor-<lb/>tant efforts to reduce the global disease burden <lb/>associated with pneumococcal disease. <lb/>Keywords: Pneumococcal vaccine; Caregiver <lb/>perceptions; Health care provider perceptions <lb/>Supplementary Information The online version <lb/>contains supplementary material available at <lb/>https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s40121-024-01022-0. <lb/>J. E. Perdrizet (*) <lb/>Global Value and Evidence, Pfizer Canada, Kirkland, <lb/>QC, Canada <lb/>e-mail: Johnna.Perdrizet@pfizer.com <lb/>M. H. Rozenbaum <lb/>Global Value and Evidence, Pfizer B.V., Rotterdam, <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>M. J. Heffler <lb/>Ipsos Insight LLC, Norwalk, CT, USA <lb/>2018 <lb/>Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/>Key Summary Points <lb/>Why carry out the study? <lb/>Current European infant national immuniza-<lb/>tion programs (NIPs) recommend pneumo-<lb/>coccal conjugate vaccines (PCVs) that cover <lb/>10 to 15 serotypes and are administered in <lb/>a three-dose schedule (two primary plus one <lb/>booster). Recently, a PCV that offers broader <lb/>serotype coverage (it protects against 20 sero-<lb/>types) was licensed in a four-dose schedule <lb/>(three primary plus one booster); however, the <lb/>attitudes of health care providers (HCPs) and <lb/>caregivers towards the PCV serotype cover-<lb/>age and dosing schedule in Europe remain <lb/>unknown. <lb/>A total of 601 HCPs and 1,954 caregivers <lb/>from four European countries (Germany, <lb/>France, Spain, and Greece) completed an <lb/>online survey concerning preferences for <lb/>PCVs. <lb/>What was learned from the study? <lb/>Nearly all HCPs (93%) agreed that broader <lb/>serotype coverage against pneumococcal dis-<lb/>ease for children is a significant unmet need, <lb/>and 92% had a &quot;sense of urgency&quot; to vacci-<lb/>nate children. <lb/>Both HCPs and caregivers were supportive of <lb/>an additional PCV dose and doctor visit in a <lb/>situation where it would provide at least 20% <lb/>more serotype coverage than what is cur-<lb/>rently available. <lb/>These results can help guide broader discus-<lb/>sions regarding public health policy and <lb/>vaccine administration in the context of <lb/>important efforts to reduce the global dis-<lb/>ease burden associated with pneumococcal <lb/>disease. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Pneumococcal disease is associated with signifi-<lb/>cant global morbidity and mortality [1, 2]. These <lb/>infections are caused by Streptococcus pneumoniae <lb/>(Spn) bacteria, of which there are more than 100 <lb/>different strains or serotypes, some of which can <lb/>cause serious infections (such as meningitis, bac-<lb/>teremia, and septicemia) as well as non-invasive <lb/>disease (such as non-bacteremic pneumonia and <lb/>acute otitis media) [3]. Pneumococcal disease <lb/>can lead to serious complications, especially <lb/>among children under the age of two, those with <lb/>specific underlying conditions, and the elderly <lb/>[3-5], with the World Health Organization <lb/>(WHO) estimating that Spn bacteria are respon-<lb/>sible for more than 300,000 deaths among chil-<lb/>dren under 5 years old annually [6, 7]. <lb/>The high burden of disease associated with <lb/>pneumococcal infections has led to the devel-<lb/>opment of pneumococcal conjugate vaccines <lb/>(PCVs) for children and adults. The WHO has <lb/>recommended routine immunization with the <lb/>pneumococcal conjugate vaccine globally since <lb/>2007. Importantly, evidence suggests that vac-<lb/>cine adoption, which now includes more than <lb/>148 of the 194 WHO member states, is associ-<lb/>ated with significant reductions in severe pneu-<lb/>mococcal disease and pneumonia [4, 5, 7, 8]. <lb/>The current standard of care for childhood <lb/>vaccination against pneumococcal disease in <lb/>Europe covers 10-15 of the leading serotypes <lb/>and is generally given in a three-dose schedule <lb/>(two primary plus one booster: &quot;2 + 1&quot;), with <lb/>the first dose given at 2 months of age, the <lb/>second dose at 4 months of age, and the third <lb/>dose at 11-14 months of age in most European <lb/>countries [9]. Recently, a PCV that has broader <lb/>serotype coverage (it covers 20 serotypes), <lb/>PCV20, was licensed in a four-dose schedule <lb/>(three primary plus one booster: &quot;3 + 1&quot;) (Fig. 1) <lb/>[10-13]. <lb/>In Europe, the recommendation of an infant <lb/>PCV program is often issued for the population <lb/>by national immunization technical advisory <lb/>groups (NITAGs) and/or health technology <lb/>assessment (HTA) agencies. With the recent <lb/>market authorization of PCV20, these deci-<lb/>sion bodies will be required to evaluate PCVs <lb/>in their national immunization programs and <lb/>may choose to give a non-preferential recom-<lb/>mendation, meaning that more than one PCV <lb/>may be offered, potentially under different dos-<lb/>ing schedules. In some countries, it will be at <lb/>the discretion of health care providers (HCPs) <lb/></body>

			<page>2019 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>along with caregivers to choose the PCV for <lb/>their practice or child, respectively. <lb/>Thus, with multiple PCV options and sched-<lb/>ules recommended in a single European coun-<lb/>try, it will become progressively more impor-<lb/>tant to understand both the HCPs and the <lb/>caregivers&apos; current knowledge of and support <lb/>for adding PCVs with different characteristics <lb/>to the current childhood immunization sched-<lb/>ule. Given the significant burden pneumococ-<lb/>cal disease exerts in Europe and the potential <lb/>far-reaching implications of implementing a <lb/>PCV with more disease coverage ith an alter-<lb/>native dosing schedule compared with current <lb/>recommendations, there remains a gap regard-<lb/>ing HCP and caregiver understanding and <lb/>perceptions of adopting this change in dosing <lb/>schedule for additional serotype coverage com-<lb/>pared withthe current standard of care. <lb/>This study seeks to gain novel insight into <lb/>vaccine perceptions relating to protection <lb/>against pneumococcal disease in the setting of <lb/>different dosing schedules and varying degrees <lb/>of protection among HCPs and caregivers in <lb/>Germany, France, Spain, and Greece. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Caregivers and HCPs who met the study inclu-<lb/>sion criteria were recruited from pre-existing <lb/>internet market research panels to participate in <lb/>a cross-sectional online survey. The markets of <lb/>Germany, France, Spain, and Greece were cho-<lb/>sen to represent a diverse sample of countries <lb/>within the European Union in lieu of the ability <lb/>to conduct the study in every country. This is a <lb/>descriptive study only, and no a priori hypoth-<lb/>esis was defined. Therefore, no formal sample <lb/>size or power calculations were conducted for the <lb/>study. All eligible participants that met the study <lb/>inclusion criteria were included in the research <lb/>and analysis. The target sample size was deemed <lb/>robust and representative within funding con-<lb/>straints. The request to participate in research was <lb/>sent via email to members of the panels who had <lb/>expressed a willingness to participate in research <lb/>studies. The interview request included a state-<lb/>ment of informed consent and the set of screen-<lb/>ing questions to determine eligibility. <lb/>Caregivers and HCPs who expressed interest <lb/>and were eligible to participate were directed to <lb/>complete a 10-min online survey. The respond-<lb/>ent could choose to quit the survey at any point <lb/>without penalty. Upon completion of the survey, <lb/>participants were compensated through their <lb/>panel with a modest honorarium in line with <lb/>current fair market values as determined by the <lb/>study sponsor. Respondents remained blinded to <lb/>the study sponsor until all questions had been <lb/>answered, at which time participants were able to <lb/>request details on the study sponsor, in line with <lb/>local regulations. <lb/>The study (protocol # 2023-0381) was approved <lb/>by Pearl Institutional Review Board (IRB) of Indi-<lb/>anapolis, Indiana, on October 27, 2023. Informed <lb/>consent was obtained from all participants prior <lb/>to participating in the study. This article is based <lb/>on primary data collected from human partici-<lb/>pants who consented to the study. <lb/>Fig. 1 This figure shows the incremental serotype cover-<lb/>age by available PCVs in four European countries [10-13]. <lb/>PCV pneumococcal conjugate vaccine, PCV10-type refers <lb/>to serotypes that are unique to the 10-valent PCV, PCV13-<lb/>type refers to serotypes that are unique to the 13-valent <lb/>PCV, PCV15-type refers to serotypes that are unique to the <lb/>15-valent PCV, and PCV20-type refers to serotypes that are <lb/>unique to the 20-valent PCV. *PCV10/PCV13 is recom-<lb/>mended in Germany, but PCV13 accounts for &gt; 90% of the <lb/>uptake. All other countries recommend PCV13 in national <lb/>immunization programs (NIPs). Data from France are <lb/>from 2019 and for children &lt; 2 years of age. Data from <lb/>Germany are from 2017-2018 and for children &lt; 2 years <lb/>of age. Data from Greece are from 2010-2020 and for chil-<lb/>dren 0-14 years of age. Data from Spain are from 2019 and <lb/>for children &lt; 2 years of age <lb/></body>

			<page>2020 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>Study Population <lb/>Health Care Providers <lb/>Pediatricians in all countries, primary care phy-<lb/>sicians (PCPs) in France, and nurses in Greece <lb/>involved in the recommendation and/or admin-<lb/>istration of vaccines to children aged 0-5 were <lb/>recruited to participate in the study. PCPs were <lb/>included in France and nurses in Greece due to <lb/>their greater involvement in pediatric vaccination <lb/>in these countries compared to other countries <lb/>included in the study. <lb/>Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria <lb/>The inclusion criteria for HCPs included: (1) a <lb/>practicing pediatrician (in all markets) or PCP <lb/>(in France) or nurse (in Greece); (2) in practice <lb/>for 3-30 years in an office-based practice; and <lb/>(3) administered or recommended vaccines to <lb/>patients. <lb/>Exclusion criteria included: (1) unwilling to <lb/>provide informed consent or to have poten-<lb/>tial adverse events reported anonymously; (2) <lb/>required consent from an employer, organiza-<lb/>tion, or professional association to participate in <lb/>this research, which they had not yet obtained; <lb/>(3) practiced in a hospital or private clinic; (4) <lb/>spent less than 75% of their professional time in <lb/>direct patient care; (5) saw less than 300 pediat-<lb/>ric patients per month as a pediatrician or less <lb/>than 200 pediatric patients per month as a PCP; <lb/>(6) patients aged 0-5 made up less than 20% of <lb/>their patient population as a pediatrician or less <lb/>than 10% of their patient population as a PCP; (7) <lb/>they had not prescribed or recommended specific <lb/>pneumococcal vaccines; and (8) they were affili-<lb/>ated with any pharmaceutical company or health-<lb/>care manufacturer, serving as a clinical investi-<lb/>gator, conducting clinical research, or providing <lb/>consulting services in any capacity. <lb/>Caregivers <lb/>Caregivers of children aged 0-5 and expectant <lb/>mothers were recruited across the four European <lb/>countries, as per the criteria outlined below. <lb/>Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria <lb/>The inclusion criteria for caregivers were (1) <lb/>aged 18 to 55 years old; (2) residing in Ger-<lb/>many, Spain, France, or Greece; (3) parent or <lb/>legal guardian of at least one child aged 0-5 or a <lb/>female currently in the third trimester of preg-<lb/>nancy; and (4) responsible (or shared respon-<lb/>sibility) for making decisions concerning the <lb/>health of their child. Of note, 80% of the partici-<lb/>pants were required to be aware of the existence <lb/>of pneumococcal disease (e.g., pneumonia, ear <lb/>infection, etc.). <lb/>Exclusion criteria for caregivers included: (1) <lb/>unwilling to provide informed consent or to <lb/>have potential adverse events reported anony-<lb/>mously; (2) consider themselves not at all sup-<lb/>portive of vaccines (excluded because questions <lb/>would not be relevant for these respondents); <lb/>and (3) currently employed in the advertising/ <lb/>market research, public relations, pharmaceuti-<lb/>cal, or medical industry. <lb/>Study Measures <lb/>The following measures were collected from <lb/>study participants and are included as supple-<lb/>mentary material. Survey instruments were <lb/>translated into local languages, and all respond-<lb/>ents completed the survey in their local lan-<lb/>guage. Whereas both HCPs and caregivers <lb/>responded to the same schedule statements, <lb/>each group then responded to questions tailored <lb/>to their role. <lb/>Health Care Providers <lb/>HCPs provided basic demographic information, <lb/>including specialty, involvement in the adminis-<lb/>tration of the vaccination, regional location and <lb/>setting of practice, gender, years in practice, and <lb/>monthly patient volume. <lb/>HCPs were surveyed concerning the per-<lb/>ceived importance of protection from pneu-<lb/>mococcal diseases, the level of agreement with <lb/>pneumococcal disease vaccination, the impor-<lb/>tance of attributes when considering the PCV <lb/>dosing schedule, their opinion and perceptions <lb/></body>

			<page>2021 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>of a 3 + 1 PCV dosing schedule, their likelihood <lb/>of supporting a 3 + 1 PCV dosing schedule as a <lb/>national recommendation, their opinion of par-<lb/>ent support of a 3 + 1 PCV dosing schedule, the <lb/>perceived level of burden induced by an extra <lb/>dose/doctor visit for pneumococcal disease vac-<lb/>cination, and the sources typically relied on for <lb/>childhood vaccine information. <lb/>In the HCP survey, a four-point Likert scale <lb/>was used to force respondents to have positive <lb/>or negative opinions. As the HCPs in this survey <lb/>had all prescribed pneumococcal vaccines, they <lb/>were familiar with the subject matter, and there-<lb/>fore a neutral option was deemed unnecessary. <lb/>Caregivers <lb/>Caregivers provided basic demographic infor-<lb/>mation, including gender, type of area in which <lb/>their primary residence is located (urbanicity), <lb/>educational attainment, current employment <lb/>status, household income, and age. <lb/>Caregivers responded to survey questions <lb/>regarding the perceived seriousness of pneu-<lb/>mococcal diseases, the importance of vaccina-<lb/>tion, their agreement on aided statements about <lb/>pneumococcal diseases, their opinion on PCV <lb/>schedules that include an additional dose/doctor <lb/>visit, and their overall agreement with and per-<lb/>ceptions on childhood vaccinations and sources <lb/>typically relied on for childhood vaccine infor-<lb/>mation. In the caregivers survey, a five-point <lb/>scale was used when measuring to allow a neu-<lb/>tral option. As such, direct comparisons between <lb/>the HCP survey and caregiver survey should be <lb/>viewed with caution, as the presence or absence <lb/>of a midpoint option may impact the overall <lb/>percentage of positive or negative responses. <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>This study primarily utilized Likert scales to <lb/>assess respondent agreement with and support <lb/>for the questions and statements posed. Data for <lb/>these questions are reported as the percentage <lb/>(%) of respondents who somewhat or strongly <lb/>agree with/support the question/statement. <lb/>Descriptive statistics are presented for study <lb/>respondents. Data for continuous variables (e.g., <lb/>age) include the mean and standard deviation <lb/>(SD). For categorical variables (e.g., gender and <lb/>employment status), frequencies and percent-<lb/>ages are presented. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Health Care Providers <lb/>A total of 601 HCPs were recruited across the <lb/>four European countries (Germany, France, <lb/>Spain, and Greece). The sample distribution is <lb/>summarized in Table 1. The majority of HCP <lb/>respondents were pediatric providers (67%). <lb/>Most (76-100%) were directly involved in the <lb/>administration of vaccines to the patients in an <lb/>urban (78%), office-based (75%) practice. The <lb/>majority (56%) of respondents were female and <lb/>had been in practice for an average of 15 years. <lb/>Nearly all HCPs (93%) agreed that broader <lb/>serotype coverage against pneumococcal dis-<lb/>ease for children is a significant unmet need, <lb/>and 92% have a &quot;sense of urgency&quot; to vaccinate <lb/>children. Across the countries surveyed, 92% of <lb/>HCPs agreed that they would go out of their way <lb/>to recommend a vaccine that required an addi-<lb/>tional dose if it meant more protection, and 93% <lb/>would accept the time and effort needed from <lb/>them and their practice to educate caregivers <lb/>about the extra dose. Similarly, 94% of respond-<lb/>ents also agreed that having a vaccination sched-<lb/>ule that is the same for full-term and pre-term <lb/>infants would be very beneficial. <lb/>HCPs were highly supportive of a new dos-<lb/>ing schedule, assuming it garnered at least 20% <lb/>more coverage than what is currently available. <lb/>Across the countries surveyed, at least 91% of <lb/>the HCPs would support an additional dose if (1) <lb/>20% incremental protection was provided, (2) <lb/>children were protected against more medically <lb/>significant strains of disease, and (3) more lives <lb/>were saved or more severe disease was averted. <lb/>Among HCPs, support for an additional dose or <lb/>doctor visit was generally strongest among those <lb/>in Spain and Greece. Findings were similar when <lb/>survey results were analyzed by HCP specialty. <lb/>Results are summarized in Tables 2 and 3. <lb/></body>

			<page>2022 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1 Healthcare provider demographics <lb/>* Percentages may not sum exactly to 100% due to rounding to the nearest full percentage point <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 601) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 201) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 200) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>Specialty <lb/>Primary care provider <lb/>101 <lb/>17% -<lb/>101 <lb/>50% -<lb/>-<lb/>Pediatrician <lb/>400 <lb/>67% 100 <lb/>100% 100 <lb/>50% 100 <lb/>50% 100 100% <lb/>Nurse <lb/>100 <lb/>17% -<lb/>-<lb/>100 <lb/>50% -<lb/>Involvement in vaccines <lb/>Directly involved w/ administration <lb/>549 <lb/>91% 96 <lb/>96% 201 <lb/>100% 152 <lb/>76% 100 100% <lb/>Prescribe/recommend only <lb/>52 <lb/>9% <lb/>4 <lb/>4% <lb/>-<lb/>48 <lb/>24% -<lb/>Practice location <lb/>Urban <lb/>466 <lb/>78% 74 <lb/>74% 154 <lb/>77% 161 <lb/>81% 77 77% <lb/>Suburban <lb/>99 <lb/>16% 19 <lb/>19% 27 <lb/>13% 32 <lb/>16% 21 21% <lb/>Rural <lb/>36 <lb/>6% <lb/>7 <lb/>7% <lb/>20 <lb/>10% 7 <lb/>4% 2 <lb/>2% <lb/>Practice setting <lb/>Office-based <lb/>453 <lb/>75% 100 <lb/>100% 122 <lb/>61% 165 <lb/>83% 66 66% <lb/>Private clinic <lb/>62 <lb/>10% -<lb/>28 <lb/>14% -<lb/>34 34% <lb/>Academic, university, or teaching hospital 46 <lb/>8% <lb/>-<lb/>46 <lb/>23% -<lb/>-<lb/>Outpatient clinic <lb/>40 <lb/>7% <lb/>-<lb/>5 <lb/>2% <lb/>35 <lb/>18% -<lb/>Gender <lb/>Male <lb/>251 <lb/>42% 46 <lb/>46% 104 <lb/>52% 70 <lb/>35% 31 31% <lb/>Female <lb/>334 <lb/>56% 50 <lb/>50% 96 <lb/>48% 119 <lb/>60% 69 69% <lb/>Prefer not to answer <lb/>16 <lb/>3% <lb/>4 <lb/>4% <lb/>1 <lb/>0% <lb/>11 <lb/>6% -<lb/>Years in practice <lb/>Mean SD <lb/>Mean SD <lb/>Mean SD <lb/>Mean SD Mean SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>15.0 <lb/>7.0 16.8 <lb/>6.2 <lb/>16.2 <lb/>8.2 13.2 <lb/>5.3 14.2 <lb/>7.2 <lb/>Monthly patient volume <lb/>Age 0-2 <lb/>85.1 <lb/>53.3 120.9 84.3 <lb/>72.6 44.4 78.8 42.8 87.0 26.6 <lb/>Age 3-5 <lb/>80.8 <lb/>45.6 118.5 70.0 <lb/>69.0 35.0 73.7 37.5 80.8 24.1 <lb/>Age 6-10 <lb/>73.6 <lb/>43.4 101.8 72.3 <lb/>59.1 30.2 68.1 35.2 85.6 20.2 <lb/>Age 11-17 <lb/>63.2 <lb/>35.9 76.7 55.4 <lb/>57.6 32.4 52.9 23.9 81.6 25.4 <lb/>Age 18 + <lb/>57.3 107.8 <lb/>7.9 12.7 132.3 159.1 16.0 19.1 38.5 25.2 <lb/></body>

			<page>2023 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 2 Healthcare provider survey responses-agreement with provided statements <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 601) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 201) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 200) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>Broader serotype coverage is a significant unmet need when it comes to vaccination against pneumococcal disease in children <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>306 <lb/>51% <lb/>44 <lb/>44% <lb/>92 <lb/>46% <lb/>99 <lb/>50% <lb/>71 <lb/>71% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>251 <lb/>42% <lb/>50 <lb/>50% <lb/>87 <lb/>43% <lb/>85 <lb/>43% <lb/>29 <lb/>29% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>42 <lb/>7% <lb/>6 <lb/>6% <lb/>21 <lb/>10% <lb/>15 <lb/>8% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>2 <lb/>0% <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>0% <lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>My practice has a sense of urgency to vaccinate children against pneumococcal disease <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>304 <lb/>51% <lb/>55 <lb/>55% <lb/>80 <lb/>40% <lb/>105 <lb/>53% <lb/>64 <lb/>64% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>249 <lb/>41% <lb/>41 <lb/>41% <lb/>91 <lb/>45% <lb/>81 <lb/>41% <lb/>36 <lb/>36% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>46 <lb/>8% <lb/>4 <lb/>4% <lb/>28 <lb/>14% <lb/>14 <lb/>7% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>2 <lb/>0% <lb/>-<lb/>2 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>I would go out of my way to recommend a childhood pneumococcal vaccine that requires an extra dose if it means more disease <lb/>coverage for the child <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>298 <lb/>50% <lb/>52 <lb/>52% <lb/>91 <lb/>45% <lb/>103 <lb/>52% <lb/>52 <lb/>52% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>256 <lb/>43% <lb/>32 <lb/>32% <lb/>100 <lb/>50% <lb/>76 <lb/>38% <lb/>48 <lb/>48% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>42 <lb/>7% <lb/>12 <lb/>12% <lb/>9 <lb/>4% <lb/>21 <lb/>11% <lb/>-<lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>4 <lb/>4% <lb/>1 <lb/>0% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>I would accept the extra effort needed of my practice to offer a pneumococcal vaccine that requires an additional doctor visit if it <lb/>means more disease coverage for children <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>307 <lb/>51% <lb/>40 <lb/>40% <lb/>98 <lb/>49% <lb/>104 <lb/>52% <lb/>65 <lb/>65% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>252 <lb/>42% <lb/>48 <lb/>48% <lb/>93 <lb/>46% <lb/>77 <lb/>39% <lb/>34 <lb/>34% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>37 <lb/>6% <lb/>11 <lb/>11% <lb/>7 <lb/>3% <lb/>18 <lb/>9% <lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>3 <lb/>1% <lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>It is worth the time and effort it will take to educate parents about a new pneumococcal vaccine if it means children will get the <lb/>broadest protection available <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>263 <lb/>44% <lb/>35 <lb/>35% <lb/>85 <lb/>42% <lb/>97 <lb/>49% <lb/>46 <lb/>46% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>297 <lb/>49% <lb/>53 <lb/>53% <lb/>103 <lb/>51% <lb/>89 <lb/>45% <lb/>52 <lb/>52% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>39 <lb/>6% <lb/>11 <lb/>11% <lb/>12 <lb/>6% <lb/>14 <lb/>7% <lb/>2 <lb/>2% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>2 <lb/>0% <lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>1 <lb/>0% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Having a vaccination schedule for pneumococcal disease that was the same for full-term and pre-term infants would be very <lb/>beneficial <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>278 <lb/>46% <lb/>47 <lb/>47% <lb/>79 <lb/>39% <lb/>93 <lb/>47% <lb/>59 <lb/>59% <lb/></body>

			<page>2024 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>Caregivers <lb/>A total of 1954 caregivers were recruited across <lb/>the four European countries surveyed. The <lb/>sample distribution is summarized in Table 4. <lb/>The average age of respondents was 34 years, <lb/>with the majority being married or living with <lb/>a partner and reporting being a college grad or <lb/>higher. Overall, the majority of respondents <lb/>lived in urban areas (68%) and were female <lb/>(74%). <lb/>Caregivers strongly agreed on the impor-<lb/>tance of full vaccination for pneumococ-<lb/>cal disease, even if it was associated with an <lb/>additional dose and doctor visit. Doctors were <lb/>highly trusted by survey respondents, with a <lb/>recommendation of an extra dose deemed a <lb/>strong influence on caregiver acceptance. In <lb/>France and Greece, 75% of respondents were <lb/>willing to pay more if it meant additional sero-<lb/>type coverage for their child. Caregivers were <lb/>broadly supportive and willing to accept an <lb/>additional dose/visit, assuming it garnered <lb/>at least 20% more serotype coverage. Across <lb/>the countries surveyed, at least 74% would <lb/>support an additional dose if it provided sig-<lb/>nificant incremental coverage, their child was <lb/>protected against more medically significant <lb/>strains of pneumococcal disease, or more lives <lb/>were saved or more severe disease averted. <lb/>Results are summarized in Tables 5 and 6. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Pneumococcal disease is associated with signifi-<lb/>cant morbidity, mortality, and economic bur-<lb/>den in children [14, 15]. This burden has been <lb/>reduced significantly in the era of PCVs; how-<lb/>ever, challenges remain in the development of <lb/>vaccines that maximize the coverage of disease <lb/>serotypes and vaccine schedules that are deemed <lb/>feasible by both HCPs and caregivers. <lb/>The current study provides important and <lb/>novel insight into the vaccine preferences of <lb/>both HCPs and caregivers across Europe. Overall, <lb/>there was unanimous agreement among HCPs <lb/>and caregivers that a pneumococcal vaccine <lb/>with broader serotype coverage would be desira-<lb/>ble, and they expressed a subsequent willingness <lb/>to include an extra infant dose/visit to provide <lb/>added protection against pneumococcal disease. <lb/>This finding is in line with similar research con-<lb/>cerning meningitis vaccines, in which HCPs and <lb/>caregivers were open to adding new vaccines to <lb/>the immunization schedule, even if it required <lb/>co-administration with current vaccines or the <lb/>introduction of a new office visit [16]. <lb/>The serotypes covered by available PCVs in <lb/>the countries surveyed demonstrate that the <lb/>additional incremental coverage for PCV20-<lb/>unique serotypes ranges from 24 to 31% com-<lb/>pared with PCV15 serotype coverage, ranges <lb/>from 28 to 43% compared with PCV13 serotype <lb/>coverage, and is 42% compared with PCV10 <lb/>serotype coverage (only reported for Germany, <lb/>Table 2 continued <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 601) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 201) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 200) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>286 <lb/>48% <lb/>42 <lb/>42% <lb/>110 <lb/>55% <lb/>93 <lb/>47% <lb/>41 <lb/>41% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>34 <lb/>6% <lb/>10 <lb/>10% <lb/>10 <lb/>5% <lb/>14 <lb/>7% <lb/>-<lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>3 <lb/>0% <lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>2 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>* Percentages may not sum exactly to 100% due to rounding to the nearest full percentage point <lb/></body>

			<page>2025 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 3 Healthcare provider survey responses-extent to which respondents would support or oppose an additional dose or <lb/>doctor visit <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 601) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 201) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 200) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>If the vaccine provides strong incremental coverage compared to other licensed vaccines <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>299 <lb/>50% <lb/>48 <lb/>48% <lb/>102 <lb/>51% <lb/>90 <lb/>45% <lb/>59 <lb/>59% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>261 <lb/>43% <lb/>40 <lb/>40% <lb/>84 <lb/>42% <lb/>96 <lb/>48% <lb/>41 <lb/>41% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>40 <lb/>7% <lb/>12 <lb/>12% <lb/>15 <lb/>7% <lb/>13 <lb/>7% <lb/>-<lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>1 <lb/>0% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>Protects against more medically significant and high-disease-potential serotypes <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>322 <lb/>54% <lb/>41 <lb/>41% <lb/>110 <lb/>55% <lb/>96 <lb/>48% <lb/>75 <lb/>75% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>250 <lb/>42% <lb/>49 <lb/>49% <lb/>86 <lb/>43% <lb/>90 <lb/>45% <lb/>25 <lb/>25% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>28 <lb/>5% <lb/>10 <lb/>10% <lb/>5 <lb/>2% <lb/>13 <lb/>7% <lb/>-<lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>1 <lb/>0% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>Could result in more lives being saved or more severe disease being averted <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>372 <lb/>62% <lb/>49 <lb/>49% <lb/>125 <lb/>62% <lb/>117 <lb/>59% <lb/>81 <lb/>81% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>197 <lb/>33% <lb/>41 <lb/>41% <lb/>68 <lb/>34% <lb/>69 <lb/>35% <lb/>19 <lb/>19% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>32 <lb/>5% <lb/>10 <lb/>10% <lb/>8 <lb/>4% <lb/>14 <lb/>7% <lb/>-<lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Has 10% additional coverage vs. the highest-valent pediatric pneumococcal vaccine that is currently available <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>127 <lb/>21% <lb/>20 <lb/>20% <lb/>45 <lb/>22% <lb/>57 <lb/>29% <lb/>5 <lb/>5% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>319 <lb/>53% <lb/>50 <lb/>50% <lb/>107 <lb/>53% <lb/>101 <lb/>51% <lb/>61 <lb/>61% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>153 <lb/>25% <lb/>30 <lb/>30% <lb/>48 <lb/>24% <lb/>42 <lb/>21% <lb/>33 <lb/>33% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>2 <lb/>0% <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>0% <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>Has 20% additional coverage vs. the highest-valent pediatric pneumococcal vaccine that is currently available <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>169 <lb/>28% <lb/>28 <lb/>28% <lb/>70 <lb/>35% <lb/>58 <lb/>29% <lb/>13 <lb/>13% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>376 <lb/>63% <lb/>58 <lb/>58% <lb/>116 <lb/>58% <lb/>120 <lb/>60% <lb/>82 <lb/>82% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>56 <lb/>9% <lb/>14 <lb/>14% <lb/>15 <lb/>7% <lb/>22 <lb/>11% <lb/>5 <lb/>5% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Has 40% additional coverage vs. the highest-valent pediatric pneumococcal vaccine that is currently available <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>381 <lb/>63% <lb/>50 <lb/>50% <lb/>122 <lb/>61% <lb/>122 <lb/>61% <lb/>87 <lb/>87% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>195 <lb/>32% <lb/>47 <lb/>47% <lb/>70 <lb/>35% <lb/>65 <lb/>33% <lb/>13 <lb/>13% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>25 <lb/>4% <lb/>3 <lb/>3% <lb/>9 <lb/>4% <lb/>13 <lb/>7% <lb/>-<lb/></body>

			<page>2026 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>as it is the only country to include PCV10 as an <lb/>option in the national immunization programs <lb/>(NIPs)) (Fig. 1) [10-13]. This additional incre-<lb/>mental serotype coverage suggests that PCV20 <lb/>could potentially protect against significantly <lb/>more pneumococcal disease and, as demon-<lb/>strated in this research, plays a critical role for <lb/>guiding HCPs and caregivers perceptions on the <lb/>benefit of PCVs and care decisions. Importantly, <lb/>European NITAGs and HTA recommending bod-<lb/>ies may ultimately give a non-preferential rec-<lb/>ommendation for PCVs in their infant NIPs, <lb/>leaving HCPs and caregivers to choose the PCV <lb/>for their practice or child. Therefore, this study <lb/>provides new insights into the increasing impor-<lb/>tance of HCPs and caregiver perceptions, as they <lb/>may have to decide which PCV and schedule is <lb/>administered to their patient/child. <lb/>The vast majority of HCPs noted a degree <lb/>of urgency in developing and implementing <lb/>PCVs that provide broader serotype cover-<lb/>age, even if this meant an additional dose for <lb/>infants, and nearly all expressed a willingness <lb/>to endorse a revised PCV schedule. These find-<lb/>ings underscore the burden of pneumococcal <lb/>disease on a societal scale as well as the impor-<lb/>tance of understanding the views of HCPs to <lb/>help further the mission of combatting pneu-<lb/>mococcal disease. In a study of HCP prefer-<lb/>ences for PCVs in the United States (US), the <lb/>authors found that the top two attributes for a <lb/>PCV are (1) the ability of the vaccine to elicit a <lb/>robust immune response against vaccine sero-<lb/>types and (2) the overall serotype coverage the <lb/>vaccine offers against invasive pneumococcal <lb/>disease [17]. PCV20 has both attributes. PCV20 <lb/>elicits a robust immune response against all <lb/>20 serotypes, meeting noninferiority for at <lb/>least one co-primary endpoint as measured <lb/>by IgG concentrations for PCV20 under a 3 + 1 <lb/>schedule [18] and meeting noninferiority for <lb/>at least one primary endpoint as measured by <lb/>IgG concentrations under a 2 + 1 schedule for <lb/>19 of 20 serotypes [19]. Moreover, PCV20 has <lb/>incremental serotype coverage compared to <lb/>lower-valent PCVs, offering the broadest cov-<lb/>erage of any available PCV in infants to date <lb/>(Fig. 1) [10-13]. <lb/>Among caregivers, there was a high level of <lb/>vaccine acceptance if a doctor recommended <lb/>it. This is similar to findings from the Well-<lb/>come Global Monitor survey of over 140,000 <lb/>individuals globally (90% of whom were in <lb/>northern and southern Europe), which noted <lb/>those surveyed would trust an HCP more <lb/>than several other possible sources of health <lb/>advice [20]. Further notable findings from our <lb/>research included a broad willingness, regard-<lb/>less of country of origin, to undertake any <lb/>extra steps to achieve effective protection of <lb/>their children from pneumococcal disease. <lb/>Given there was still a significant amount of <lb/>Table 3 continued <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 601) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 201) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 200) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 100) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Is from a manufacturer that has over 20 years of experience in helping protect against childhood pneumococcal disease <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>208 <lb/>35% <lb/>22 <lb/>22% <lb/>68 <lb/>34% <lb/>74 <lb/>37% <lb/>44 <lb/>44% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>321 <lb/>53% <lb/>60 <lb/>60% <lb/>102 <lb/>51% <lb/>106 <lb/>53% <lb/>53 <lb/>53% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>70 <lb/>12% <lb/>17 <lb/>17% <lb/>30 <lb/>15% <lb/>20 <lb/>10% <lb/>3 <lb/>3% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>2 <lb/>0% <lb/>1 <lb/>1% <lb/>1 <lb/>0% <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>* Percentages may not sum exactly to 100% due to rounding to the nearest full percentage point <lb/></body>

			<page>2027 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 4 Caregiver demographics <lb/>* Percentages may not sum exactly to 100% due to rounding to the nearest full percentage point <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 1954) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 459) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 497) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 498) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 500) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>Gender <lb/>Male <lb/>509 <lb/>26% <lb/>116 <lb/>25% <lb/>127 <lb/>26% <lb/>151 <lb/>30% <lb/>115 <lb/>23% <lb/>Female <lb/>1445 <lb/>74% <lb/>343 <lb/>75% <lb/>370 <lb/>74% <lb/>347 <lb/>70% <lb/>385 <lb/>77% <lb/>Urbanicity <lb/>Urban <lb/>1322 <lb/>68% <lb/>268 <lb/>58% <lb/>260 <lb/>52% <lb/>403 <lb/>81% <lb/>391 <lb/>78% <lb/>Suburban <lb/>310 <lb/>16% <lb/>100 <lb/>22% <lb/>82 <lb/>16% <lb/>51 <lb/>10% <lb/>77 <lb/>15% <lb/>Rural <lb/>322 <lb/>16% <lb/>91 <lb/>20% <lb/>155 <lb/>31% <lb/>44 <lb/>9% <lb/>32 <lb/>6% <lb/>Educational attainment <lb/>High school or less <lb/>401 <lb/>21% <lb/>44 <lb/>10% <lb/>185 <lb/>37% <lb/>100 <lb/>20% <lb/>72 <lb/>14% <lb/>2 years of college or technical/ <lb/>vocational <lb/>384 <lb/>20% <lb/>158 <lb/>34% <lb/>101 <lb/>20% <lb/>67 <lb/>13% <lb/>58 <lb/>12% <lb/>4 years of college <lb/>692 <lb/>35% <lb/>171 <lb/>37% <lb/>106 <lb/>21% <lb/>218 <lb/>44% <lb/>197 <lb/>39% <lb/>Some postgraduate work <lb/>147 <lb/>8% <lb/>20 <lb/>4% <lb/>40 <lb/>8% <lb/>38 <lb/>8% <lb/>49 <lb/>10% <lb/>Postgraduate degree <lb/>319 <lb/>16% <lb/>64 <lb/>14% <lb/>60 <lb/>12% <lb/>71 <lb/>14% <lb/>124 <lb/>25% <lb/>Prefer not to answer <lb/>11 <lb/>1% <lb/>2 <lb/>0% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>4 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>0% <lb/>Employment status <lb/>Employed full-time <lb/>1365 <lb/>70% <lb/>305 <lb/>66% <lb/>334 <lb/>67% <lb/>339 <lb/>68% <lb/>387 <lb/>77% <lb/>Employed part-time <lb/>223 <lb/>11% <lb/>79 <lb/>17% <lb/>40 <lb/>8% <lb/>73 <lb/>15% <lb/>31 <lb/>6% <lb/>Not employed <lb/>346 <lb/>18% <lb/>75 <lb/>16% <lb/>114 <lb/>23% <lb/>78 <lb/>16% <lb/>79 <lb/>16% <lb/>Prefer not to answer <lb/>20 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>9 <lb/>2% <lb/>8 <lb/>2% <lb/>3 <lb/>1% <lb/>Household income <lb/>Less than €29,999 <lb/>652 <lb/>33% <lb/>62 <lb/>13% <lb/>159 <lb/>32% <lb/>154 <lb/>31% <lb/>277 <lb/>55% <lb/>€30,000-€49,999 <lb/>476 <lb/>24% <lb/>138 <lb/>30% <lb/>151 <lb/>30% <lb/>138 <lb/>28% <lb/>49 <lb/>10% <lb/>€50,000-€74,999 <lb/>400 <lb/>20% <lb/>179 <lb/>39% <lb/>77 <lb/>15% <lb/>114 <lb/>23% <lb/>30 <lb/>6% <lb/>€75,000-€99,999 <lb/>196 <lb/>10% <lb/>13 <lb/>3% <lb/>55 <lb/>11% <lb/>45 <lb/>9% <lb/>83 <lb/>17% <lb/>More than €100,000 <lb/>161 <lb/>8% <lb/>63 <lb/>14% <lb/>37 <lb/>7% <lb/>29 <lb/>6% <lb/>32 <lb/>6% <lb/>Age <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>34.0 <lb/>5.4 <lb/>33.2 <lb/>5.4 <lb/>33.6 <lb/>5.8 <lb/>34.1 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>35.1 <lb/>4.7 <lb/></body>

			<page>2028 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 5 Caregiver survey responses-agreement with provided statements <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 1954) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 459) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 497) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 498) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 500) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>The number of vaccine doses required does not impact my decision to vaccinate my child against pneumococcal disease <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>735 <lb/>38% <lb/>130 <lb/>28% <lb/>127 <lb/>26% <lb/>249 <lb/>50% <lb/>229 46% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>847 <lb/>43% <lb/>229 <lb/>50% <lb/>238 <lb/>48% <lb/>178 <lb/>36% <lb/>202 40% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>314 <lb/>16% <lb/>94 <lb/>20% <lb/>103 <lb/>21% <lb/>64 <lb/>13% <lb/>53 <lb/>11% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>58 <lb/>3% <lb/>6 <lb/>1% <lb/>29 <lb/>6% <lb/>7 <lb/>1% <lb/>16 <lb/>3% <lb/>The number of doctor visits required does not impact my decision to vaccinate my child against pneumococcal disease <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>838 <lb/>43% <lb/>177 <lb/>39% <lb/>168 <lb/>34% <lb/>242 <lb/>49% <lb/>251 50% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>855 <lb/>44% <lb/>219 <lb/>48% <lb/>247 <lb/>50% <lb/>201 <lb/>40% <lb/>188 38% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>207 <lb/>11% <lb/>47 <lb/>10% <lb/>67 <lb/>13% <lb/>46 <lb/>9% <lb/>47 <lb/>9% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>53 <lb/>3% <lb/>15 <lb/>3% <lb/>15 <lb/>3% <lb/>9 <lb/>2% <lb/>14 <lb/>3% <lb/>When it comes to vaccines for pneumococcal disease, I trust the specific recommendation from my child&apos;s doctor <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>851 <lb/>44% <lb/>147 <lb/>32% <lb/>163 <lb/>33% <lb/>283 <lb/>57% <lb/>258 52% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>937 <lb/>48% <lb/>274 <lb/>60% <lb/>269 <lb/>54% <lb/>189 <lb/>38% <lb/>205 41% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>139 <lb/>7% <lb/>34 <lb/>7% <lb/>49 <lb/>10% <lb/>24 <lb/>5% <lb/>32 <lb/>6% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>28 <lb/>1% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>16 <lb/>3% <lb/>2 <lb/>0% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>I would accept an extra dose of a pneumococcal vaccine if my child&apos;s doctor recommended it <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>833 <lb/>43% <lb/>151 <lb/>33% <lb/>149 <lb/>30% <lb/>275 <lb/>55% <lb/>258 52% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>880 <lb/>45% <lb/>244 <lb/>53% <lb/>262 <lb/>53% <lb/>185 <lb/>37% <lb/>189 38% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>203 <lb/>10% <lb/>59 <lb/>13% <lb/>66 <lb/>13% <lb/>33 <lb/>7% <lb/>45 <lb/>9% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>38 <lb/>2% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>20 <lb/>4% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>8 <lb/>2% <lb/>You must receive all recommended doses of the pneumococcal vaccine to get full disease coverage <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>838 <lb/>43% <lb/>147 <lb/>32% <lb/>132 <lb/>27% <lb/>291 <lb/>58% <lb/>268 54% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>898 <lb/>46% <lb/>251 <lb/>55% <lb/>277 <lb/>56% <lb/>170 <lb/>34% <lb/>200 40% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>186 <lb/>9% <lb/>52 <lb/>11% <lb/>76 <lb/>15% <lb/>32 <lb/>6% <lb/>26 <lb/>5% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>32 <lb/>2% <lb/>9 <lb/>2% <lb/>12 <lb/>2% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>6 <lb/>1% <lb/>I would go out of my way for an extra dose of a pneumococcal vaccine if it means more disease coverage for my child <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>705 <lb/>36% <lb/>151 <lb/>33% <lb/>143 <lb/>29% <lb/>234 <lb/>47% <lb/>177 35% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>920 <lb/>47% <lb/>213 <lb/>46% <lb/>270 <lb/>54% <lb/>198 <lb/>40% <lb/>239 48% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>251 <lb/>13% <lb/>66 <lb/>14% <lb/>64 <lb/>13% <lb/>63 <lb/>13% <lb/>58 <lb/>12% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>77 <lb/>4% <lb/>28 <lb/>6% <lb/>20 <lb/>4% <lb/>3 <lb/>1% <lb/>26 <lb/>5% <lb/></body>

			<page>2029 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>*Percentages may not sum exactly to 100% due to rounding to the nearest full percentage point <lb/>**Question not asked in Germany and Spain <lb/>Table 5 continued <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 1954) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 459) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 497) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 498) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 500) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>I would accept the inconvenience of an extra doctor visit if it means my child gets added coverage against pneumococcal disease <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>905 <lb/>46% <lb/>176 <lb/>38% <lb/>181 <lb/>36% <lb/>278 <lb/>56% <lb/>270 54% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>853 <lb/>44% <lb/>235 <lb/>51% <lb/>251 <lb/>51% <lb/>179 <lb/>36% <lb/>188 38% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>164 <lb/>8% <lb/>43 <lb/>9% <lb/>53 <lb/>11% <lb/>37 <lb/>7% <lb/>31 <lb/>6% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>32 <lb/>2% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>12 <lb/>2% <lb/>4 <lb/>1% <lb/>11 <lb/>2% <lb/>Getting a vaccine with greater coverage against pneumococcal disease far outweighs the inconvenience of an extra doctor visit <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>758 <lb/>39% <lb/>151 <lb/>33% <lb/>173 <lb/>35% <lb/>247 <lb/>50% <lb/>187 37% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>901 <lb/>46% <lb/>231 <lb/>50% <lb/>254 <lb/>51% <lb/>202 <lb/>41% <lb/>214 43% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>233 <lb/>12% <lb/>68 <lb/>15% <lb/>55 <lb/>11% <lb/>42 <lb/>8% <lb/>68 <lb/>14% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>62 <lb/>3% <lb/>9 <lb/>2% <lb/>15 <lb/>3% <lb/>7 <lb/>1% <lb/>31 <lb/>6% <lb/>Getting a vaccine with greater coverage against pneumococcal disease far outweighs the discomfort an additional dose may pose <lb/>for my child <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>677 <lb/>35% <lb/>117 <lb/>26% <lb/>133 <lb/>27% <lb/>244 <lb/>49% <lb/>183 37% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>915 <lb/>47% <lb/>238 <lb/>52% <lb/>255 <lb/>51% <lb/>197 <lb/>40% <lb/>225 45% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>305 <lb/>16% <lb/>90 <lb/>20% <lb/>92 <lb/>19% <lb/>49 <lb/>10% <lb/>74 <lb/>15% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>57 <lb/>3% <lb/>14 <lb/>3% <lb/>17 <lb/>3% <lb/>8 <lb/>2% <lb/>18 <lb/>4% <lb/>Taking my child for an extra doctor visit to get an additional dose of a vaccine would be a huge inconvenience for me <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>267 <lb/>14% <lb/>49 <lb/>11% <lb/>43 <lb/>9% <lb/>110 <lb/>22% <lb/>65 <lb/>13% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>560 <lb/>29% <lb/>168 <lb/>37% <lb/>133 <lb/>27% <lb/>139 <lb/>28% <lb/>120 24% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>494 <lb/>25% <lb/>128 <lb/>28% <lb/>179 <lb/>36% <lb/>107 <lb/>21% <lb/>80 <lb/>16% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>632 <lb/>32% <lb/>113 <lb/>25% <lb/>142 <lb/>29% <lb/>142 <lb/>29% <lb/>235 47% <lb/>I would pay more for an additional dose of the pneumococcal vaccine to ensure my child gets more/extended disease coverage** <lb/>Strongly agree <lb/>273 <lb/>27% <lb/>-<lb/>102 <lb/>21% <lb/>-<lb/>171 34% <lb/>Somewhat agree <lb/>472 <lb/>47% <lb/>-<lb/>244 <lb/>49% <lb/>-<lb/>228 46% <lb/>Somewhat disagree <lb/>170 <lb/>17% <lb/>-<lb/>101 <lb/>20% <lb/>-<lb/>69 <lb/>14% <lb/>Strongly disagree <lb/>82 <lb/>8% <lb/>-<lb/>50 <lb/>10% <lb/>-<lb/>32 <lb/>6% <lb/></body>

			<page>2030 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 6 Caregiver survey responses-extent to which respondents would support or oppose an additional dose or doctor <lb/>visit <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 1954) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 459) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 497) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 498) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 500) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>If the vaccine provides strong incremental coverage compared to other licensed vaccines <lb/>Strongly support <lb/>688 <lb/>35% <lb/>118 <lb/>26% <lb/>122 <lb/>25% <lb/>229 <lb/>46% <lb/>219 44% <lb/>Somewhat support <lb/>876 <lb/>45% <lb/>243 <lb/>53% <lb/>243 <lb/>49% <lb/>194 <lb/>39% <lb/>196 39% <lb/>No feelings either way <lb/>328 <lb/>17% <lb/>92 <lb/>20% <lb/>107 <lb/>22% <lb/>67 <lb/>13% <lb/>62 <lb/>12% <lb/>Somewhat oppose <lb/>49 <lb/>3% <lb/>6 <lb/>1% <lb/>21 <lb/>4% <lb/>6 <lb/>1% <lb/>16 <lb/>3% <lb/>Strongly oppose <lb/>13 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>4 <lb/>1% <lb/>2 <lb/>&lt; 1% <lb/>7 <lb/>1% <lb/>The vaccine protects my child against more medically significant pneumococcal strains that cause serious infections <lb/>Strongly support <lb/>808 <lb/>41% <lb/>131 <lb/>29% <lb/>151 <lb/>30% <lb/>277 <lb/>56% <lb/>249 50% <lb/>Somewhat support <lb/>834 <lb/>43% <lb/>228 <lb/>50% <lb/>237 <lb/>48% <lb/>167 <lb/>34% <lb/>202 40% <lb/>No feelings either way <lb/>242 <lb/>12% <lb/>74 <lb/>16% <lb/>85 <lb/>17% <lb/>48 <lb/>10% <lb/>35 <lb/>7% <lb/>Somewhat oppose <lb/>56 <lb/>3% <lb/>22 <lb/>5% <lb/>22 <lb/>4% <lb/>3 <lb/>1% <lb/>9 <lb/>2% <lb/>Strongly oppose <lb/>12 <lb/>1% <lb/>2 <lb/>&lt; 1% <lb/>2 <lb/>&lt; 1% <lb/>3 <lb/>1% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>The vaccine could result in more lives being saved or more severe disease being averted <lb/>Strongly support <lb/>858 <lb/>44% <lb/>194 <lb/>42% <lb/>164 <lb/>33% <lb/>286 <lb/>57% <lb/>214 43% <lb/>Somewhat support <lb/>765 <lb/>39% <lb/>198 <lb/>43% <lb/>231 <lb/>46% <lb/>146 <lb/>29% <lb/>190 38% <lb/>No feelings either way <lb/>281 <lb/>14% <lb/>64 <lb/>14% <lb/>85 <lb/>17% <lb/>57 <lb/>11% <lb/>75 <lb/>15% <lb/>Somewhat oppose <lb/>38 <lb/>2% <lb/>3 <lb/>1% <lb/>14 <lb/>3% <lb/>6 <lb/>1% <lb/>15 <lb/>3% <lb/>Strongly oppose <lb/>12 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>1% <lb/>3 <lb/>1% <lb/>6 <lb/>1% <lb/>It means 10% more coverage for my child against contracting pneumococcal disease vs. current immunization schedule <lb/>Strongly support <lb/>480 <lb/>25% <lb/>64 <lb/>14% <lb/>69 <lb/>14% <lb/>170 <lb/>34% <lb/>177 35% <lb/>Somewhat support <lb/>794 <lb/>41% <lb/>189 <lb/>41% <lb/>196 <lb/>39% <lb/>203 <lb/>41% <lb/>206 41% <lb/>No feelings either way <lb/>512 <lb/>26% <lb/>158 <lb/>34% <lb/>175 <lb/>35% <lb/>98 <lb/>20% <lb/>81 <lb/>16% <lb/>Somewhat oppose <lb/>132 <lb/>7% <lb/>33 <lb/>7% <lb/>48 <lb/>10% <lb/>23 <lb/>5% <lb/>28 <lb/>6% <lb/>Strongly oppose <lb/>36 <lb/>2% <lb/>15 <lb/>3% <lb/>9 <lb/>2% <lb/>4 <lb/>1% <lb/>8 <lb/>2% <lb/>It means 20% more coverage for my child against contracting pneumococcal disease vs. current immunization schedule <lb/>Strongly support <lb/>569 <lb/>29% <lb/>106 <lb/>23% <lb/>77 <lb/>15% <lb/>197 <lb/>40% <lb/>189 38% <lb/>Somewhat support <lb/>856 <lb/>44% <lb/>220 <lb/>48% <lb/>226 <lb/>45% <lb/>196 <lb/>39% <lb/>214 43% <lb/>No feelings either way <lb/>423 <lb/>22% <lb/>110 <lb/>24% <lb/>149 <lb/>30% <lb/>94 <lb/>19% <lb/>70 <lb/>14% <lb/>Somewhat oppose <lb/>86 <lb/>4% <lb/>18 <lb/>4% <lb/>37 <lb/>7% <lb/>11 <lb/>2% <lb/>20 <lb/>4% <lb/></body>

			<page>2031 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>caregivers who were not fully aware of pneu-<lb/>mococcal disease, there is the potential for <lb/>more education on how the disease is spread. <lb/>Comprehensive waiting-room material and <lb/>online disease awareness campaigns could aid <lb/>with improving knowledge among caregivers. <lb/>In addition, some recent evidence from a Ger-<lb/>man study suggests that there is little differ-<lb/>ence in the rate of vaccination achieved with <lb/>a 3 + 1 versus a 2 + 1 schedule [21], and thus <lb/>characteristics of the vaccine, such as the vac-<lb/>cine effectiveness or serotype coverage, may <lb/>take priority over caregiver preferences. <lb/>National-level recommendations for PCVs <lb/>and dosing schedules may soon vary by coun-<lb/>try and/or region, thus underscoring the impor-<lb/>tance of studies, such as this one, that provide <lb/>insight into HCP and caregiver knowledge levels <lb/>and opinions. Similar results from our survey <lb/>of HCPs were reported in another separate and <lb/>recent US-based study, with 93% of the HCPs <lb/>surveyed reporting a preference for PCV20 over <lb/>PCV15 for children ≤ 18 years. Among those <lb/>who preferred PCV20, more than 80% based <lb/>their decision primarily on serotype coverage <lb/>[22]. It is important to note that in the US, the <lb/>Centers for Disease Control&apos;s Advisory Com-<lb/>mittee on Immunization Practices (ACIP) cur-<lb/>rently non-preferentially recommend PCV15 <lb/>or PCV20 under a 3 + 1 schedule [23], thus rein-<lb/>forcing the need to investigate vaccine prefer-<lb/>ences in Europe, especially with the option of <lb/>PCVs under different schedules. Findings from <lb/>our study are important in the context of an <lb/>ongoing debate as to whether societal opinions <lb/>regarding childhood vaccination should be con-<lb/>sidered when formulating disease control poli-<lb/>cies, and these survey results can add to that <lb/>discussion. <lb/>*Percentages may not sum exactly to 100% due to rounding to the nearest full percentage point <lb/>Table 6 continued <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 1954) <lb/>Germany <lb/>(n = 459) <lb/>France <lb/>(n = 497) <lb/>Spain <lb/>(n = 498) <lb/>Greece <lb/>(n = 500) <lb/>N <lb/>%* <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>Strongly oppose <lb/>19 <lb/>1% <lb/>4 <lb/>1% <lb/>8 <lb/>2% <lb/>-<lb/>7 <lb/>1% <lb/>It means 40% more coverage for my child against contracting pneumococcal disease vs. current immunization schedule <lb/>Strongly support <lb/>762 <lb/>39% <lb/>176 <lb/>38% <lb/>114 <lb/>23% <lb/>234 <lb/>47% <lb/>238 48% <lb/>Somewhat support <lb/>802 <lb/>41% <lb/>211 <lb/>46% <lb/>228 <lb/>46% <lb/>169 <lb/>34% <lb/>194 39% <lb/>No feelings either way <lb/>335 <lb/>17% <lb/>65 <lb/>14% <lb/>128 <lb/>26% <lb/>88 <lb/>18% <lb/>54 <lb/>11% <lb/>Somewhat oppose <lb/>42 <lb/>2% <lb/>6 <lb/>1% <lb/>23 <lb/>5% <lb/>7 <lb/>1% <lb/>6 <lb/>1% <lb/>Strongly oppose <lb/>12 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>4 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>8 <lb/>2% <lb/>The vaccine manufacturer has over 20 years of experience in helping protect against childhood pneumococcal disease <lb/>Strongly support <lb/>669 <lb/>34% <lb/>149 <lb/>33% <lb/>95 <lb/>19% <lb/>232 <lb/>47% <lb/>193 39% <lb/>Somewhat support <lb/>852 <lb/>44% <lb/>234 <lb/>51% <lb/>234 <lb/>47% <lb/>172 <lb/>35% <lb/>212 42% <lb/>No feelings either way <lb/>371 <lb/>19% <lb/>70 <lb/>15% <lb/>140 <lb/>28% <lb/>82 <lb/>16% <lb/>79 <lb/>16% <lb/>Somewhat oppose <lb/>48 <lb/>2% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>23 <lb/>5% <lb/>9 <lb/>2% <lb/>11 <lb/>2% <lb/>Strongly oppose <lb/>13 <lb/>1% <lb/>-<lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/>3 <lb/>1% <lb/>5 <lb/>1% <lb/></body>

			<page>2032 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<body>Strengths and Limitations <lb/>Strengths of the current study include the sur-<lb/>veying of respondents across several European <lb/>countries, the inclusion of both HCPs and car-<lb/>egivers, and the relevance and potential impli-<lb/>cations of the study question for societal public <lb/>health. Further, the results of this survey broadly <lb/>aligned with existing studies that have exam-<lb/>ined similar topics, suggesting that the questions <lb/>were appropriate and the data garnered were <lb/>meaningful. <lb/>Despite these strengths, it is important to <lb/>acknowledge that the method and the nature <lb/>of self-report surveys rely on the willingness of <lb/>respondents to be involved in a research panel, <lb/>which invites the possibility of selection bias. <lb/>Further, as with any research that relies on con-<lb/>venience sampling, it is possible that certain <lb/>types of participants may be over-represented <lb/>and that the results may not generalize to the <lb/>entire population. Finally, surveys regarding <lb/>hypothetical scenarios, such as a willingness <lb/>to pay for or schedule an additional medical <lb/>visit, are not 100% reliable indicators of future <lb/>behavior. Further, different Likert scales were <lb/>used for HCPs and caregivers surveyed in the <lb/>study, and thus caution is warranted in drawing <lb/>comparisons. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>The current study provides critical insight into <lb/>pneumococcal vaccine opinions and percep-<lb/>tions in Europe. HCPs and caregivers were vir-<lb/>tually unanimous in their support for a PCV <lb/>with broader serotype coverage and expressed <lb/>a subsequent willingness to include an extra <lb/>infant dose/visit. These results can help guide <lb/>broader discussions regarding public health <lb/>policy and vaccine administration in the con-<lb/>text of important efforts to reduce the global <lb/>disease burden associated with pneumococcal <lb/>disease. There is ongoing debate as to whether <lb/>societal preferences for childhood vaccina-<lb/>tion should be considered when formulating <lb/>national immunization policies, and these sur-<lb/>vey results can add to that discussion. <lb/></body>
    
            <div type="annex">Medical Writing and Editorial Assis-<lb/>tance. Writing support was provided by Errol <lb/>J. Philip, MD, and was funded by Pfizer. <lb/>Authorship. All named authors meet the <lb/>International Committee of Medical Journal <lb/>Editors (ICMJE) criteria for authorship for this <lb/>article, take responsibility for the integrity of the <lb/>work as a whole, and have given their approval <lb/>for this version to be published. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="contribution">Author Contributions. Johnna Perdrizet <lb/>and Mark Rozenbaum participated in study con-<lb/>ception. Matthew Heffler performed all descrip-<lb/>tive and statistical analyses. All authors helped <lb/>to draft the manuscript and read and approved <lb/>the final manuscript. <lb/></div>
      
            <div type="funding">Funding. This study, manuscript, and rapid <lb/>service fees were funded by Pfizer Inc. <lb/></div>
        
            <div type="availability">Data Availability. The datasets generated <lb/>during and/or analyzed during the current study <lb/>are available from the corresponding author on <lb/>reasonable request. <lb/></div>
          
            <div type="annex">Declarations <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="conflict">Conflict of Interest. Johnna Perdrizet and <lb/>Mark Rozenbaum are employees of Pfizer Inc., <lb/>manufacturer of the PCV20 vaccine. Matthew <lb/>Heffler is an employee of Ipsos Insight LLC, <lb/>which was a paid consultant to Pfizer in connec-<lb/>tion with the development of this manuscript <lb/>and conducting this research study. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="annex">Ethical Approval. This study was con-<lb/>ducted in full conformance with the guidelines <lb/>for good pharmacoepidemiology practice (GPP) <lb/>published by the International Society of Phar-<lb/>macoepidemiology (ISPE), the Helsinki Declara-<lb/>tion of 1964, and the laws and regulations of <lb/>the countries in which the research was con-<lb/>ducted. Informed consent was collected from all <lb/>participants prior to participating in the study. <lb/>No identifiable data were collected during the <lb/>course of this research or are included in this <lb/>manuscript. The study (protocol # 2023-0381) <lb/>was approved by Pearl Institutional Review <lb/></div>

			<page>2033 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Board (IRB) of Indianapolis, Indiana, on October <lb/>27, 2023. This article is based on primary data <lb/>collected in human participants who consented <lb/>to the study. <lb/></div>
              
            <front>Open Access. This article is licensed under a <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial <lb/>4.0 International License, which permits any <lb/>non-commercial use, sharing, adaptation, distri-<lb/>bution and reproduction in any medium or for-<lb/>mat, as long as you give appropriate credit to the <lb/>original author(s) and the source, provide a link <lb/>to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate <lb/>if changes were made. The images or other third <lb/>party material in this article are included in the <lb/>article&apos;s Creative Commons licence, unless indi-<lb/>cated otherwise in a credit line to the material. <lb/>If material is not included in the article&apos;s Crea-<lb/>tive Commons licence and your intended use is <lb/>not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds <lb/>the permitted use, you will need to obtain per-<lb/>mission directly from the copyright holder. To <lb/>view a copy of this licence, visit http:// creat iveco <lb/>mmons. org/ licen ses/ by-nc/4. 0/. <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. O&apos;Reilly R, Yokoyama S, Boyle J, et al. The impact <lb/>of acute pneumococcal disease on health state <lb/>utility values: a systematic review. Qual Life Res. <lb/>2022;31(2):375-88. <lb/>2. Estimates of the global. regional, and national <lb/>morbidity, mortality, and aetiologies of lower <lb/>respiratory infections in 195 countries, 1990-<lb/>2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Bur-<lb/>den of Disease Study 2016. Lancet Infect Dis. <lb/>2018;18(11):1191-210. <lb/>3. Scelfo C, Menzella F, Fontana M, Ghidoni G, Gale-<lb/>one C, Facciolongo NC. Pneumonia and invasive <lb/>pneumococcal diseases: the role of pneumococcal <lb/>conjugate vaccine in the era of multi-drug resist-<lb/>ance. Vaccines. 2021;9(5):420. <lb/>4. Jimbo Sotomayor R, Toscano CM, Sánchez Choez <lb/>X, et al. Impact of pneumococcal conjugate vac-<lb/>cine on pneumonia hospitalization and mortal-<lb/>ity in children and elderly in Ecuador: time series <lb/>analyses. Vaccine. 2020;38(45):7033-9. <lb/>5. Mohanty S, Podmore B, Cuñado Moral A, et al. <lb/>Incidence of pneumococcal disease from 2003 to <lb/>2019 in children ≤17 years in England. Pneumonia <lb/>(Nathan). 2023;15(1):2. <lb/>6. Muhoza P, Danovaro-Holliday M, Diallo <lb/>M. Routine vaccination coverage-world-<lb/>wide, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. <lb/>2021;70:1495-500. <lb/>7. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. <lb/>Global pneumococcal disease and vaccination. <lb/>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Avail-<lb/>able from: https:// www. cdc. gov/ pneum ococc al/. <lb/>8. Grant LR, Slack MPE, Theilacker C, et al. Distribu-<lb/>tion of serotypes causing invasive pneumococcal <lb/>disease in children from high-income countries <lb/>and the impact of pediatric pneumococcal vacci-<lb/>nation. Clin Infect Dis. 2023;76(3):e1062-70. <lb/>9. European Centre for Disease Control and Preven-<lb/>tion. Pneumococcal disease: Recommended vacci-<lb/>nations. Available from: https:// vacci ne-sched ule. <lb/>ecdc. europa. eu/ Sched uler/ ByDis ease? Selec tedDi <lb/>sease Id= 25&amp; Selec tedCo untry IdByD iseas e=-1. <lb/>10. van der Linden M, Imöhl M, Perniciaro S. Limited <lb/>indirect effects of an infant pneumococcal vacci-<lb/>nation program in an aging population. PLoS One. <lb/>2019;14(8): e0220453. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1371/ <lb/>journ al. pone. 02204 53. (Erratum in: PLoS One. <lb/>2020 Jan 16;15(1):e0228126). <lb/>11. Centre National de Référence des Pneumocoques <lb/>(CNRP). Rapport d&apos;activitie 2020, epidemiologie <lb/>2019 (Activity report 2020, epidemiology 2018-<lb/>2020). Créteil: CNRP; 2020. <lb/>12. De Miguel S, Domenech M, González-Camacho <lb/>F, et al. Nationwide trends of invasive pneu-<lb/>mococcal disease in Spain from 2009 through <lb/>2019 in children and adults during the pneu-<lb/>mococcal conjugate vaccine era. Clin Infect Dis. <lb/>2009;73(11):e3778-87. <lb/>13. Xirogianni A, Marmaras N, Georgakopoulou <lb/>T, et al. Pneumococcal meningitis in Greece: <lb/>a retrospective serotype surveillance study <lb/>in the post-PCV13 era (2010-2020). Vaccine. <lb/>2022;40(34):5079-87. <lb/>14. Li X, Warren S, Rozenbaum MH, Perdrizet J. Rea-<lb/>nalysis of the clinical and economic burden of <lb/>pneumococcal disease due to serotypes contained <lb/>in current and investigational pneumococcal con-<lb/>jugate vaccines in children &lt; 5 age: a societal per-<lb/>spective. Infect Dis Ther. 2023;12(3):997-1006. <lb/>15. Wasserman MD, Perdrizet J, Grant L, et al. Clini-<lb/>cal and economic burden of pneumococcal dis-<lb/>ease due to serotypes contained in current and <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2034 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:2017-2034 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>investigational pneumococcal conjugate vaccines <lb/>in children under five years of age. Infect Dis Ther. <lb/>2021;10(4):2701-20. <lb/>16. Bakhache P, Rodrigo C, Davie S, et al. Health care <lb/>providers&apos; and parents&apos; attitudes toward adminis-<lb/>tration of new infant vaccines-a multinational <lb/>survey. Eur J Pediatr. 2013;172(4):485-92. <lb/>17. Mohanty S, Tsai JH, Ning N, et al. Understand-<lb/>ing healthcare providers&apos; preferred attributes <lb/>of pediatric pneumococcal conjugate vaccines <lb/>in the United States. Hum Vaccin Immunother. <lb/>2024;20(1):2325745. <lb/>18. Senders S, Klein NP, Tamimi N, et al. A phase three <lb/>study of the safety and immunogenicity of a four-<lb/>dose series of 20-valent pneumococcal conjugate <lb/>vaccine in healthy infants. Pediatr Infect Dis J. <lb/>2024. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1097/ INF. 00000 00000 <lb/>004334. <lb/>19. Korbal P, Wysocki J, Jackowska T, et al. Phase 3 <lb/>safety and immunogenicity study of a three-dose <lb/>series of twenty-valent pneumococcal conjugate <lb/>vaccine in healthy infants and toddlers. Pediatr <lb/>Infect Dis J. 2024. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1097/ INF. <lb/>00000 00000 004300. <lb/>20. Gallup. Wellcome Global Monitor-first wave find-<lb/>ings. London: Wellcome Trust; 2019. <lb/>21. Laurenz M, von Eiff C, Borchert K, Jacob C, Seidel <lb/>K, Schley K. Vaccination rates and adherence in <lb/>pneumococcal conjugate vaccination in mature <lb/>born infants before and after vaccination sched-<lb/>ule change-a claims database analysis. Vaccine. <lb/>2021;39(24):3287-95. <lb/>22. Vietri JT, Myers KH, Huang L, et al. 1740. Health-<lb/>care providers&apos; preferences for pediatric pneu-<lb/>mococcal vaccination recommendations in the <lb/>United States. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2023. <lb/>https:// doi. org/ 10. 1093/ ofid/ ofad5 00. 1571. <lb/>23. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Pneu-<lb/>mococcal vaccine recommendations 2023. Avail-<lb/>able from: https:// www. cdc. gov/ vacci nes/ vpd/ <lb/>pneumo/ hcp/ recom menda tions. html. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s Note Springer Nature remains neutral with <lb/>regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. </div>


	</text>

</TEI>