<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Kidney function in newly diagnosed myeloma patients: factors associated with kidney impairment and recovery</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Bruno Nogueira</forename>
            <surname>Cesar</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Walter Moises Tobias</forename>
            <surname>Braga</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Nelson</forename>
            <surname>Hamerschlak</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Marcelino de Souza Durão</forename>
            <surname>Junior</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-31T12:03:09.382828Z">31.10.2025 12:03:09</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1186$1$s12882-024-03717-5</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12882-024-03717-5</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Bruno Nogueira Cesar, Walter Moises Tobias Braga, Nelson Hamerschlak, Marcelino de Souza Durão Junior. (2024). Kidney function in newly diagnosed myeloma patients: factors associated with kidney impairment and recovery. BMC Nephrology, 25(1), None. DOI: 10.1186/s12882-024-03717-5</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-31T12:03:09.382828Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-31T12:03:09.382828Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Clinical Efficacy and Safety of Colistin Sulfate <lb/>in the Treatment of Carbapenem-Resistant Organism <lb/>Infections in Patients with Hematological Diseases <lb/>Yuanbing Wu . Shanshan Jiang . Dongyang Li . Yaxue Wu . <lb/>Qian Li . Xing Wang . Bin Liu . Haiyan Bao . Depei Wu . <lb/>Xiaohui Hu <lb/>Received: October 6, 2023 / Accepted: December 15, 2023 / Published online: January 11, 2024 <lb/>Ó The Author(s) 2024 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Introduction: Carbapenem-resistant organisms <lb/>(CRO) have emerged as a significant worldwide <lb/>issue. However, the availability of efficacious <lb/>antibiotics for treating CRO infections remains <lb/>limited. Polymyxins, including colistin sulfate, <lb/>represent the last-line therapeutic option <lb/>against CRO infections. This study aims to ret-<lb/>rospectively evaluate the clinical effectiveness <lb/>and safety of colistin sulfate in managing CRO <lb/>infections among patients with hematological <lb/>diseases. <lb/>Methods: Between April 2022 and January <lb/>2023, a total of 118 hematological patients <lb/>diagnosed with CRO infection were treated with <lb/>colistin sulfate at Suzhou Hongci Hospital of <lb/>Hematology. The assessment encompassed the <lb/>clinical efficacy, bacterial clearance rate, adverse <lb/>reactions, and 30-day all-cause mortality. <lb/>Results: The study found that the total effec-<lb/>tive rate of colistin sulfate in the treatment of <lb/>CRO infection was 74.6%, with a bacterial <lb/>clearance rate of 72.6%. Throughout the treat-<lb/>ment, nephrotoxicity occurred in 7.6% of cases, <lb/>neurotoxicity in 2.5% of cases, and the 30-day <lb/>all-cause mortality rate was 22.9%. Multivariate <lb/>logistic analysis revealed that the treatment <lb/>course and combination medication with other <lb/>antimicrobials were independent factors affect-<lb/>ing the clinical efficacy of colistin sulfate. <lb/>Conclusion: Our study demonstrates that the <lb/>treatment of colistin sulfate can achieve high <lb/>clinical efficacy and microbial responses, with a <lb/>low risk of nephrotoxicity. This study provides <lb/>evidence of the positive clinical efficacy and <lb/>safety of colistin sulfate treatment in these <lb/>patients. High-quality randomized controlled <lb/>trials are still needed to further confirm the <lb/>beneficial role of colistin sulfate. <lb/>Keywords: Polymyxins; <lb/>Colistin; <lb/>Hematological diseases; Carbapenem-resistant <lb/>organisms; Infections <lb/>Yuanbing Wu, Shanshan Jiang and Dongyang Li <lb/>contributed equally to this work. <lb/>Y. Wu Á S. Jiang Á D. Li Á Y. Wu Á Q. Li Á X. Wang Á <lb/>B. Liu <lb/>Department of Hematology, The Hospital of Suzhou <lb/>Hongci Hematology, Suzhou 215000, Jiangsu, <lb/>China <lb/>H. Bao Á D. Wu (&amp;) Á X. Hu (&amp;) <lb/>Department of Hematology, National Clinical <lb/>Research Center for Hematologic Diseases, The First <lb/>Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University, Suzhou <lb/>215000, Jiangsu, China <lb/>e-mail: wudepei@suda.edu.cn <lb/>X. Hu <lb/>e-mail: huxiaohui@suda.edu.cn <lb/>Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s40121-023-00909-8 <lb/>Key Summary Points <lb/>Why carry out this study? <lb/>Colistin sulfate has been only clinically <lb/>available in China, and there is an unmet <lb/>need to clarify the efficacy and safety of <lb/>colistin sulfate in hematological patients <lb/>with carbapenem-resistant organisms <lb/>(CRO) infections. <lb/>We retrospectively evaluated the efficacy, <lb/>microbial response, 30-day all-cause <lb/>mortality, and incidence of adverse events <lb/>at discontinuation. <lb/>What was learned from the study <lb/>Colistin sulfate can achieve high clinical <lb/>efficacy and microbial responses, with a <lb/>low risk of nephrotoxicity in CRO <lb/>infections. The treatment course and <lb/>combination medication with other <lb/>antimicrobials were independent factors <lb/>affecting the clinical efficacy of colistin <lb/>sulfate. <lb/>Prospective, multicenter, randomized <lb/>controlled, and well-designed trials are <lb/>needed to better evaluate the efficacy and <lb/>safety of colistin sulfate in the future. <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>In recent years, with the widespread clinical use <lb/>of broad-spectrum antibiotics, drug-resistant <lb/>bacteria have increased remarkably, which may <lb/>delay targeted therapies and affect public <lb/>health. Among these, carbapenem-resistant <lb/>organisms (CRO), especially carbapenem-resis-<lb/>tant Enterobacteriaceae (CRE), carbapenem-resis-<lb/>tant Acinetobacter baumannii (CRAB), and <lb/>carbapenem-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>(CRPA), are critical well-known contributors to <lb/>infection-associated morbidity and mortality <lb/>worldwide and have been identified by the <lb/>World Health Organization (WHO) as the <lb/>priority pathogens that critically threaten pub-<lb/>lic health [1, 2]. <lb/>Patients with hematological malignancies <lb/>are at high risk for CRO infections [3, 4]. These <lb/>patients have a higher incidence of CRO infec-<lb/>tions and mortality than patients in other <lb/>clinical departments due to primary immun-<lb/>odeficiencies and therapeutic interventions <lb/>such as chemotherapy, radiotherapy, and <lb/>hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) <lb/>resulting in neutropenia [1, 5, 6]. Studies <lb/>revealed that the mortality caused by CRE <lb/>infections in patients with hematological <lb/>malignancies ranges from 45.6% to 100% [7-9]. <lb/>Unfortunately, the current availability of <lb/>antimicrobials for CRO infections is very lim-<lb/>ited. Polymyxins, the &apos;&apos;old&apos;&apos; antibiotics that are <lb/>effective against almost all CRO infections, have <lb/>returned to clinical practice as the last line of <lb/>defense [10, 11]. <lb/>Currently, only three forms of polymyxins <lb/>are available clinically, i.e., polymyxin B sulfate <lb/>(PMB), colistin sulfate, and colistimethate <lb/>sodium (CMS) [12]. Numerous published stud-<lb/>ies have shown very positive evidence for CMS <lb/>and PMB in the treatment of CRO infections <lb/>[13-17]. However, the most common side <lb/>effects of polymyxins, especially nephrotoxic-<lb/>ity, must be considered regarding clinical use <lb/>[18]. Nephrotoxicity has been reported to occur <lb/>in up to 50% to 60% of patients treated with <lb/>CMS or PMB [19]. Moreover, PMB-induced skin <lb/>hyperpigmentation remains a major quality-of-<lb/>life concern for patients [20]. These adverse <lb/>events have somewhat limited the clinical use <lb/>of PMB and CMS. <lb/>As one of the polymyxins, colistin sulfate has <lb/>been shown in recent studies to have a high <lb/>clinical and microbiological response but a low <lb/>nephrotoxicity incidence during the treatment <lb/>of CRO infections [21-23]. However, limited <lb/>studies have been reported on its efficacy and <lb/>safety in infections in patients with hemato-<lb/>logical diseases. Therefore, we conducted this <lb/>real-world retrospective study of the efficacy <lb/>and safety of colistin sulfate in these patients, <lb/>with the aim of providing a reference for the <lb/>clinical use of this drug. <lb/></body>

        <page>142 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <body>METHODS <lb/>Study Design <lb/>This observational, retrospective, single-center <lb/>clinical study was performed at the Hospital of <lb/>Suzhou Hongci Hematology, Suzhou, Jiangsu <lb/>Province, China. Data concerning patients <lb/>treated with colistin sulfate in our hospital <lb/>between April 2022 and January 2023 were <lb/>reviewed. This study was approved by the Ethics <lb/>Committee of the Hospital of Suzhou Hongci <lb/>Hematology and was exempt from informed <lb/>consent because of its observational nature. <lb/>Furthermore, the study was implemented in <lb/>accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki (as <lb/>revised in 2013). <lb/>The primary outcomes of the study were <lb/>clinical efficacy, microbial response, 30-day all-<lb/>cause mortality, and the incidence of adverse <lb/>events at discontinuation. Secondary outcomes <lb/>were factors associated with the therapeutic <lb/>efficacy of colistin sulfate. <lb/>Patients <lb/>Adult patients were considered eligible if they: <lb/>(1) were diagnosed with a hematological disease <lb/>(including malignant hematology and aplastic <lb/>anemia); (2) had a positive culture for CRO or <lb/>high suspicion of CRO infection. The diagnosis <lb/>of CRO infection was made by two clinicians <lb/>based on culture of CRO from sterile or eligible <lb/>specimens and high suspicion of CRO infection <lb/>based on the patient&apos;s clinical symptoms, signs, <lb/>and laboratory findings, such as fever pattern <lb/>and inflammatory indicators, despite the <lb/>absence of positive pathogenic bacterial culture <lb/>results; (3) had completed clinical data; (4) had <lb/>received colistin sulfate treatment for C 72 h, <lb/>either alone or in combination with other <lb/>antimicrobials. Patients were excluded if they <lb/>were: (1) under 18 years of age; (2) allergic to the <lb/>study drug; (3) co-infected with any gram-posi-<lb/>tive bacteria; (4) died within 48 h after treat-<lb/>ment; (5) had incomplete clinical data; (6) had <lb/>severe organ damage (renal and/or hepatic <lb/>dysfunction grade [ 2 according to the <lb/>Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse <lb/>Events [version 5.0]). <lb/>Data Collection and Definitions <lb/>Patient data collection was based on the elec-<lb/>tronic medical record system of our hospital. It <lb/>mainly includes basic demographic character-<lb/>istics: age, gender, type of hematological dis-<lb/>ease, hematopoietic stem cell transplantation <lb/>status, site of infection, distribution of patho-<lb/>gens, infection index, exposure to antimicrobial <lb/>therapy, clinical and microbiological responses, <lb/>adverse reactions, and survival status, etc. <lb/>All patients in this study were treated with <lb/>intravenous colistin sulfate (colistin sulfate for <lb/>injection, Shanghai SPH New Asia Pharmaceu-<lb/>tical Co. Ltd., Shanghai, China) for C 72 h at a <lb/>dose of 1.0-1.5 million IU per day, divided into <lb/>2-3 intravenous doses. Clinicians administered <lb/>colistin sulfate in accordance with the drug <lb/>package insert, the national consensus on the <lb/>optimal clinical use of the polymyxins in China <lb/>[24], as well as adverse reactions and in the <lb/>context of the patient&apos;s disease progression. <lb/>The clinical effectiveness of colistin sulfate <lb/>treatment was evaluated by clinical and micro-<lb/>biological criteria at the time of drug discon-<lb/>tinuation. Patients received multiple courses of <lb/>colistin sulfate treatment, whereas only the first <lb/>course of therapy was evaluated. Clinical effi-<lb/>cacy was defined as the recovery from symp-<lb/>toms and signs at the end of colistin sulfate <lb/>treatment, while clinical failure was defined as <lb/>the aggravation or persistence of symptoms and <lb/>signs during treatment. <lb/>CRO strains were isolated from body fluid <lb/>specimens of enrolled patients, including spu-<lb/>tum, alveolar lavage fluid, and blood. The <lb/>pathogenic bacteria were extracted and identi-<lb/>fied through matrix-assisted laser desorption/ <lb/>ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry. In <lb/>addition, when there was clinical suspicion of <lb/>infection in a critically or seriously ill patient, or <lb/>when empirical treatment had not been effec-<lb/>tive for 3 days, pathogen metagenomic next-<lb/>generation sequencing (mNGS) was used for <lb/>bacterial identification and detection of drug <lb/>resistance genes in pathogens [25]. In vitro <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <page>143 <lb/></page>

        <body>antimicrobial susceptibility testing was per-<lb/>formed according to the Clinical and Labora-<lb/>tory Standards Institute (CLSI) guidelines <lb/>(M100), using the micro-broth dilution <lb/>method. The results for carbapenems, amino-<lb/>glycosides, quinolones, fosfomycin, tigecycline, <lb/>and aztreonam were interpreted according to <lb/>CLSI breakpoints. Clinical breakpoint reference <lb/>for colistin susceptibility testing was according <lb/>to the United States Committee on Antimicro-<lb/>bial Susceptibility Testing (USCAST) (S B 2 mg/ <lb/>l, R C 4 mg/l) [26, 27]. Bacterial clearance was <lb/>considered a clinically favorable outcome. <lb/>However, the absence of the above microbio-<lb/>logical responses or persistent detection of the <lb/>same causative pathogens was defined as <lb/>invalid. <lb/>Adverse events associated with colistin sul-<lb/>fate were closely monitored, including nephro-<lb/>toxicity, hepatotoxicity, and neurotoxicity. The <lb/>renal and liver functions were evaluated on the <lb/>day before and after treatment with colistin <lb/>sulfate. Increased creatinine (Cr) was calculated <lb/>by subtracting the creatinine level prior to the <lb/>commencement of colistin sulfate treatment <lb/>from the post-treatment creatinine level. Renal <lb/>impairment was assessed according to the Kid-<lb/>ney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes <lb/>(KDIGO) criteria [28]. Neurotoxicity was evalu-<lb/>ated according to CTCAE (version 5.0). <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>SPSS22.0 software was used for statistical anal-<lb/>yses (IBM Corp. in Armonk, NY, USA). Data are <lb/>presented as n (%), mean ± SD, or median <lb/>(range). Student&apos;s t-tests were performed for <lb/>continuous variables between groups. The v 2 or <lb/>Fisher&apos;s exact tests were performed for categor-<lb/>ical variables. Variables with a p-value \ 0.05 in <lb/>the univariate analysis were enrolled in the <lb/>multivariate logistic regression model for fur-<lb/>ther analysis. The Kaplan-Meier curve was used <lb/>to demonstrate the survival probability. A two-<lb/>tailed p-value \ 0.05 indicates a significant <lb/>difference. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Patient Demographic and Clinical <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Patients who received colistin sulfate treatment <lb/>between April 2022 and January 2023 were <lb/>enrolled. Of 193 patients screened for eligibility, <lb/>118 were included in the final analysis based on <lb/>the inclusion and exclusion criteria (Fig. 1). We <lb/>summarized the patient demographic and clin-<lb/>ical characteristics to describe the overall pop-<lb/>ulation. The mean age of these patients was <lb/>43.92 ± 15.82 years, including 52 (44.1%) <lb/>females and 66 (55.9%) males. The most com-<lb/>mon hematological disease was acute myeloid <lb/>leukemia (49.2%), followed by acute lym-<lb/>phoblastic leukemia (22.0%), myelodysplastic <lb/>syndrome (18.6%), and aplastic anemia <lb/>(10.2%). Among them, 81 (68.6%) patients <lb/>received allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell <lb/>transplantation, and 37 (31.4%) received <lb/>chemotherapy. <lb/>All patients were diagnosed with CRO <lb/>infections, and the most common site of infec-<lb/>tion was the lung (58.5%), followed by blood-<lb/>stream (39.8%) and intestinal tract (15.3%). <lb/>Among them, multiple sites of infection were <lb/>seen in 21 (17.8%) of the patients. CRKP (28%) <lb/>was the most commonly monitored CRO in <lb/>sterile specimens, followed by CRAB (25.4%) <lb/>and CRPA (20.3%). In addition, there were <lb/>other CRE (33.1%) infections such as Enter-<lb/>obacter cloacae and Escherichia coli. Of the 118 <lb/>patients, 33.1% were infected with more than <lb/>one CRO pathogens. <lb/>Colistin Sulfate Administration <lb/>Overall, 118 patients received colistin sulfate at <lb/>doses of 1.0-1.5 million IU/day for a mean <lb/>treatment duration of 12.75 ± 5.91 (range 4--<lb/>30) days. The total mean cumulative dose was <lb/>17.58 ± 8.70 million IU. Only nine (7.6%) <lb/>patients were treated with a loading dosage of <lb/>colistin sulfate at 1.5 million IU. Twenty-one <lb/>(17.8%) patients received colistin sulfate treat-<lb/>ment for no more than 7 days, 61 (51.7%) for <lb/>8-14 days, and 36 (30.5%) for [ 14 days. Only <lb/></body>

        <page>144 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <body>nine (7.6%) patients received colistin sulfate <lb/>monotherapy. Forty (33.9%) patients received <lb/>colistin sulfate combined with one other <lb/>antibacterial agent, 55 patients (46.6%) with 2, <lb/>and 14 patients (11.9%) with 3 or more other <lb/>antibacterial agents. Antibacterial agents used <lb/>in combination with colistin sulfate included <lb/>carbapenems, aminoglycosides, quinolones, <lb/>fosfomycin, <lb/>tigecycline, <lb/>aztreonam, <lb/>etc. <lb/>(Table 1). <lb/>Clinical and Microbiological Outcomes <lb/>Based on the clinical response outcomes after <lb/>colistin sulfate treatment, all patients and rele-<lb/>vant variables were categorized into clinically <lb/>effective and ineffective groups. The key <lb/>demographic and clinical characteristics and <lb/>clinical outcomes of these patients are pre-<lb/>sented below in Table 1. Overall, clinical <lb/>response was achieved by 88 (74.6%) patients, <lb/>and 30 (25.4%) patients were considered treat-<lb/>ment failure. There were no significant differ-<lb/>ences between the clinically effective and <lb/>ineffective groups (all p [ 0.05) in terms of age, <lb/>weight, gender, hematopoietic disease type, <lb/>hematopoietic stem cell transplantation status, <lb/>infection sites, and CRO types. Compared to the <lb/>ineffective group, patients in the clinically <lb/>effective group had a significantly longer course <lb/>of treatment (13.73 vs. 9.90 days; p = 0.005) and <lb/>received a higher cumulative dose of colistin <lb/>sulfate (18.58 ± 7.89 vs. 14.67 ± 10.35 million <lb/>IU, p = 0.033). A daily dose of 1.5 million <lb/>IU/day was significantly more likely with <lb/>favorable efficacy than that of 1.0 million <lb/>IU/day (60.2% vs. 39.8%, p = 0.029). Compared <lb/>to those treated for B 7 days, a longer duration <lb/>of [ 7 days had a significantly higher efficacy <lb/>rate (88.4% vs. 11.4, p <lb/>= 0.002). Multiple <lb/>comparisons of subgroups with different treat-<lb/>ment durations showed that a treatment dura-<lb/>tion of 8-14 days or [ 14 days was more <lb/>advantageous in efficacy than that of a treat-<lb/>ment duration of [ 7 days (all p \ 0.05). How-<lb/>ever, there was no significant difference in <lb/>efficacy between treatments with a duration of <lb/>8-14 days and [ 14 days (Fig. 2A). Compared <lb/>with the clinically ineffective group, patients in <lb/>the clinically effective group who were treated <lb/>with colistin sulfate in combination with other <lb/>antibiotics had a significantly higher clinical <lb/>response rate than that of monotherapy <lb/>(p = 0.016). Multiple comparisons of subgroups <lb/>Fig. 1 Flowchart of the patient selection process. CRO Carbapenem-resistant organisms <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <page>145 <lb/></page>

        <body>Table 1 Demographic and clinical characteristics and clinical outcomes of 118 patients receiving colistin sulfate treatment <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Effective group <lb/>(n = 88) <lb/>Ineffective group <lb/>(n = 30) <lb/>Total <lb/>(N = 118) <lb/>t/v 2 <lb/>value <lb/>p-value <lb/>Age, years (mean ± SD) <lb/>42.81 ± 15.59 <lb/>47.20 ± 16.29 <lb/>43.92 ± 15.82 1.31 <lb/>0.190 <lb/>Weight, kg (mean ± SD) <lb/>59.30 ± 10.79 <lb/>54.78 ± 11.27 <lb/>57.90 ± 11.04 1.46 <lb/>0.151 <lb/>Gender, n (%) <lb/>Female <lb/>35 (39.8%) <lb/>17 (56.7%) <lb/>52 (44.1%) <lb/>2.59 <lb/>0.107 <lb/>Male <lb/>53 (60.2%) <lb/>13 (43.3%) <lb/>66 (55.9%) <lb/>Type of hematological diseases, n (%) <lb/>Acute myeloid leukemia <lb/>45 (51.1%) <lb/>13 (43.3%) <lb/>58 (49.2%) <lb/>2.95 <lb/>0.400 <lb/>Acute lymphoblastic leukemia <lb/>18 (20.5%) <lb/>8 (26.7%) <lb/>26 (22.0%) <lb/>Aplastic anemia <lb/>7 (8.0%) <lb/>5 (16.7%) <lb/>12 (10.2%) <lb/>Myelodysplastic syndrome <lb/>18 (20.5%) <lb/>4 (13.3%) <lb/>22 (18.6%) <lb/>Transplant status, n (%) <lb/>Pre-transplant <lb/>27 (30.7%) <lb/>10 (33.3%) <lb/>37 (31.4%) <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.822 <lb/>Post-transplant <lb/>61 (69.3%) <lb/>20 (66.5%) <lb/>81 (68.6%) <lb/>Infection sites, n (%) <lb/>Pulmonary <lb/>51 (58.0%) <lb/>18 (60.0%) <lb/>69 (58.5%) <lb/>1.15 <lb/>0.764 <lb/>Bloodstream <lb/>33 (37.5%) <lb/>14 (46.7%) <lb/>47 (39.8%) <lb/>Intestinal <lb/>13 (14.8%) <lb/>5 (16.7%) <lb/>18 (15.3%) <lb/>C 2 Infection sites <lb/>13 (14.8%) <lb/>8 (33.3%) <lb/>21 (17.8%) <lb/>CROs, n (%) <lb/>CRKP <lb/>21 (23.9%) <lb/>12 (40.0%) <lb/>33 (28.0%) <lb/>2.96 <lb/>0.085 <lb/>CRAB <lb/>23 (26.1%) <lb/>7 (23.3%) <lb/>30 (25.4%) <lb/>CRPA <lb/>21 (23.9%) <lb/>3 (10.0%) <lb/>24 (20.3%) <lb/>Other CREs <lb/>31 (35.2%) <lb/>8 (26.7%) <lb/>39 (33.1%) <lb/>C 2 Types of CRO <lb/>34 (38.6%) <lb/>5 (16.7%) <lb/>39 (33.1%) <lb/>Highly suspected CRO <lb/>7 (8.0%) <lb/>5 (16.7%) <lb/>12 (10.2%) <lb/>Colistin sulfate administration <lb/>Loading dose, n (%) <lb/>5 (5.7%) <lb/>4 (13.3%) <lb/>9 (7.6%) <lb/>0.229 <lb/>Daily dose, n (%) <lb/>1.0 million IU/day <lb/>30 (34.1%) <lb/>17 (56.7%) <lb/>47(39.8%) <lb/>4.76 <lb/>0.029 <lb/>1.5 million IU/day <lb/>58 (65.9%) <lb/>13 (43.3%) <lb/>71 (60.2%) <lb/>Cumulative dose, million IU <lb/>(mean ± SD) <lb/>18.58 ± 7.89 <lb/>14.67 ± 10.35 <lb/>17.58 ± 8.70 <lb/>2.160 <lb/>0.033 <lb/></body>

        <page>146 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <body>with different medications showed that the <lb/>efficacy of colistin sulfate in combination with <lb/>one or two antibacterial agents was superior to <lb/>that of colistin sulfate monotherapy, but it was <lb/>not when combined with three antibacterial <lb/>agents (Fig. 2B). <lb/>Of the 106 patients with bacterial culture <lb/>results, 77 (72.6%) achieved eradication of the <lb/>causative microorganism, including 72 (88.9%) <lb/>in the effective group and 5 (20.0%) in the <lb/>ineffective group. Compared to the ineffective <lb/>group, patients in the clinically effective group <lb/>had a significantly higher microbial response <lb/>rate (p \ 0.001). <lb/>Analysis of Infection Indicators <lb/>The changes in clinical parameters were evalu-<lb/>ated before and after colistin sulfate treatment. <lb/>Overall, all monitored clinical infection-associ-<lb/>ated indicators were improved after colistin <lb/>sulfate treatment, with neutrophil counts and <lb/>platelet levels significantly increased (p \ 0.05), <lb/>and C-reaction protein (CRP) and procalcitonin <lb/>(PCT) levels significantly decreased (p \ 0.05). <lb/>Table 1 continued <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Effective group <lb/>(n = 88) <lb/>Ineffective group <lb/>(n = 30) <lb/>Total <lb/>(N = 118) <lb/>t/v 2 <lb/>value <lb/>p-value <lb/>Treatment duration, days <lb/>(mean ± SD) <lb/>13.73 ± 6.14 <lb/>9.90 ± 4.05 <lb/>12.75 ± 5.91 <lb/>3.18 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Treatment course, n (%) <lb/>B 7 days <lb/>10 (11.4%) <lb/>11 (36.7%) <lb/>21 (17.8%) <lb/>10.77 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>8-14 days <lb/>47 (53.4%) <lb/>14 (46.7%) <lb/>61 (51.7%) <lb/>[ 14 days <lb/>31 (35.2%) <lb/>5 (16.7%) <lb/>36 (30.5%) <lb/>Antibacterial combination therapy, n (%)* <lb/>Colistin sulfate monotherapy <lb/>3 (3.4%) <lb/>6 (20.0%) <lb/>9 (7.6%) <lb/>10.33 <lb/>0.016 <lb/>Combined one antibacterial agent 32 (36.4%) <lb/>8 (26.7%) <lb/>40 (33.9%) <lb/>Combined 2 antibacterial agents <lb/>44 (50%) <lb/>11 (36.7%) <lb/>55 (46.6%) <lb/>Combined C 3 antibacterial <lb/>agents <lb/>9 (10.2%) <lb/>5 (16.6%) <lb/>14 (11.9%) <lb/>Outcome <lb/>Bacteria eradication <lb/>72 (88.9%) <lb/>5 (20.0%) <lb/>77 (72.6%) à <lb/>41.89 <lb/>\ 0.001 <lb/>Nephrotoxicity <lb/>5 (5.7%) <lb/>4 (13.3%) <lb/>9 (7.6%) <lb/>0.221 <lb/>Neurotoxicity <lb/>1 (1.1%) <lb/>2 (6.7%) <lb/>3 (2.5%) <lb/>0.159 <lb/>SD Standard deviation; CRO carbapenem-resistant organisms; CRAB carbapenem-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii; CRKP <lb/>carbapenem-resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae; CRPA carbapenem-resistant Pseudomonas asaeruginosa; CRE carbapenem-<lb/>resistant Enterobacteriaceae; IU international units <lb/>*Antibacterial agents used in combination with colistin sulfate included carbapenems, aminoglycosides, quinolones, fos-<lb/>fomycin, tigecycline, aztreonam, etc. <lb/>v 2 -value <lb/>à Twelve patients who received empirical treatment were excluded because of lack of bacterial culture results <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <page>147 <lb/></page>

        <body>Compared to baseline, an increase in creatinine <lb/>(Cr) was observed after colistin sulfate admin-<lb/>istration, suggesting that colistin sulfate treat-<lb/>ment might impair renal function. However, <lb/>the level of alanine aminotransferase (ALT), <lb/>aspartate aminotransferase (AST), and total <lb/>bilirubin (TBIL) did not change significantly, <lb/>suggesting that colistin sulfate did not affect <lb/>liver function (p [ 0.1) (Fig. 3). <lb/>Factors Associated with Clinical Efficacy <lb/>Multivariate logistic regression was used to <lb/>analyze all above variables that showed signifi-<lb/>cant differences and potentially affected the <lb/>colistin treatment efficacy. The treatment <lb/>course (p = 0.031; OR = 2.980; 95% CI <lb/>1.107-8.019) and combination with other <lb/>antibacterial agents (p = 0.012; OR = 3.009; <lb/>95% CI 1.276-7.095) were identified factors that <lb/>were significantly associated with the treatment <lb/>effectiveness of colistin sulfate. These suggest <lb/>that the treatment duration of colistin sulfate <lb/>and co-medication with other antibacterial <lb/>agents, rather than the daily dose of colistin <lb/>sulfate and transplant status, might affect the <lb/>curative effect (Fig. 4). <lb/>Mortality Analysis <lb/>Twenty-seven patients died within 30 days, <lb/>with an overall 30-day all-cause mortality of <lb/>22.9%. Compared to the ineffective group, <lb/>patients in the clinically effective group had <lb/>significantly lower 30-day mortality (8.0% vs. <lb/>66.7%, v 2 = 43.71, p \ 0.001) (Fig. 5). <lb/>Safety Evaluation <lb/>Overall, nephrotoxicity was observed in nine <lb/>(7.6%) cases and neurotoxicity in three cases <lb/>(2.5%). The incidence of these adverse events <lb/>was comparable between the clinically effective <lb/>and ineffective groups, with incidences of <lb/>nephrotoxicity of 5.7% and 13.3% (p = 0.221) <lb/>and neurotoxicity of 5.7% and 13.3% <lb/>(p = 0.159), respectively (Table 1). These nine <lb/>patients developed renal impairment within <lb/>4-7 days after drug administration, of which <lb/>seven patients experienced a gradual decrease in <lb/>creatinine after discontinuation of colistin <lb/>Fig. 2 A Compared with the efficacy of colistin sulfate at <lb/>different treatment durations. B Compared with the <lb/>efficacy of colistin sulfate at different antimicrobial <lb/>combinations. Antibacterial agents used in combination <lb/>with colistin sulfate included carbapenems, aminoglyco-<lb/>sides, quinolones, fosfomycin, tigecycline, aztreonam, etc. <lb/>*p \ 0.05; **p \ 0.001; NS not statistically significant <lb/></body>

        <page>148 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <body>sulfate and two died the next day of acute renal <lb/>failure caused by septic shock. Three patients <lb/>with neurotoxicity were relieved 2 days after <lb/>discontinuation of colistin sulfate (not shown <lb/>in Table 1). Treatment with colistin sulfate was <lb/>safe and well tolerated. <lb/>Fig. 3 Comparison of patient clinical parameters at <lb/>baseline and after therapy. Pre: indicates the baseline level <lb/>before colistin sulfate treatment; post: indicates the level <lb/>after colistin sulfate treatment; SD standard deviation; <lb/>ALT <lb/>alanine <lb/>aminotransferase; AST <lb/>aspartate <lb/>aminotransferase; Cr creatinine; CRP C-reaction protein; <lb/>PLT platelet; PCT procalcitonin; TBIL total bilirubin. <lb/>Data were expressed as mean ± SD. *p \ 0.05; <lb/>**p \ 0.001; NS not statistically significant <lb/>Fig. 4 Multivariate logistic regression analysis of the factors affecting the efficacy of colistin sulfate treatment <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <page>149 <lb/></page>

        <body>DISCUSSION <lb/>In this study, the clinical data of 118 patients <lb/>with CRO infections treated with colistin sulfate <lb/>were retrospectively analyzed. Based on the <lb/>product sheet&apos;s recommended dose of 1.0-1.5 <lb/>million IU per day, clinical response and bac-<lb/>terial clearance was achieved in 74.6% and <lb/>65.3%, respectively, showing superior effec-<lb/>tiveness over that previously published retro-<lb/>spective studies by Jin et al. (58% and 40%, <lb/>respectively) and Lu et al. (53.8% and 49.1%, <lb/>respectively) [29]. Notably, in the current study <lb/>population, approximately six in ten patients <lb/>had pulmonary infections, while none of these <lb/>patients received nebulized antibiotic therapy. <lb/>Effective antibiotic therapy for pulmonary <lb/>infections requires the drug concentration at <lb/>the infection site to be sufficient to meet or <lb/>exceed the minimal inhibitory concentration <lb/>(MIC) to inhibit or kill a particular bacterial <lb/>strain. Although lung tissue penetration of col-<lb/>istin sulfate after intravenous infusion is <lb/>unknown, and how this may affect the clinical <lb/>efficacy in our studied population remains <lb/>unclear, it is reasonable to assume a higher <lb/>efficacy when using nebulized along with <lb/>intravenous infusion of colistin sulfate consid-<lb/>ering that polymyxins do not efficiently diffuse <lb/>into tissues and generally have poor penetration <lb/>into the lung tissue [30]. <lb/>In addition, a study of polymyxin B in <lb/>patients with CRO infections showed that <lb/>treatment with a duration of 8-14 days <lb/>or [ 14 days had significantly greater efficacy <lb/>than those with a duration of 3-7 days (all <lb/>p \ 0.05); however, extending the treatment <lb/>duration to [ 14 days did not show a significant <lb/>increase in efficacy compared to that treatment <lb/>for 8-14 days (p [ 0.05) [15]. The results of our <lb/>study are consistent with those of polymyxin B. <lb/>Extending the treatment duration of colistin <lb/>sulfate to 8-14 days can result in better clinical <lb/>efficacy than that not exceeding 7 days. <lb/>Although a treatment duration of[14 days also <lb/>showed better efficacy, it seems this treatment <lb/>duration confers no additional significant ben-<lb/>efit compared with that of 8-14 days. However, <lb/>prior studies examining the impact of the <lb/>polymyxin treatment duration on hematologi-<lb/>cal patients with CRO infection remain limited. <lb/>Therefore, the optimal treatment course for <lb/>colistin sulfate for patients with hematological <lb/>diseases remains uncertain and needs to be <lb/>further investigated. <lb/>Heterogeneous resistance against polymyx-<lb/>ins has been often observed during the treat-<lb/>ment of CRE, CRPA, and CRAB infections [31]. <lb/>However, the risk of heterogeneous resistance <lb/>can be improved or decreased by using a com-<lb/>bination of polymyxins and other antimicro-<lb/>bials [32-34]. In our study, 80.5% of patients <lb/>were treated with colistin sulfate combined <lb/>with one or two other antimicrobials, and <lb/>clinical response was achieved by 80.0% of <lb/>these patients. This is considered comparable to <lb/>the results of other studies on polymyxin com-<lb/>bination therapy versus polymyxin monother-<lb/>apy [35-37]. Notably, in our current study, only <lb/>a small fraction of patients (9/118) received <lb/>colistin sulfate monotherapy, and the corre-<lb/>sponding results are based on a small sample <lb/>size, which may cause statistical errors. <lb/>In the univariate study, increasing the daily <lb/>dose of colistin sulfate could improve the effi-<lb/>cacy, but further multivariate logistic analysis <lb/>showed that the daily dose was not a factor <lb/>affecting the efficacy, which might be disturbed <lb/>by the interaction of combination drugs. <lb/>High post-treatment CRP and PCT levels <lb/>indicated poor therapeutic effects of antibiotics. <lb/>CRP and PCT are reliable biomarkers for differ-<lb/>entiating bacterial infections in monitoring <lb/>Fig. 5 Kaplan-Meier survival analysis curve at 30 days <lb/>following treatment with colistin sulfate <lb/></body>

        <page>150 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <body>inflammation and infection courses [38-40]. <lb/>The present study demonstrated a significant <lb/>decrease in the levels of CRP and PCT after <lb/>treatment with colistin sulfate. Due to the lack <lb/>of therapeutic drug monitoring (TDM), post-<lb/>treatment CRP and PCT levels were used to <lb/>assess the response of patients to colistin sulfate <lb/>therapy and to determine whether to continue <lb/>therapy. In addition, the neutrophil and plate-<lb/>let counts were significantly increased in <lb/>patients with hematological diseases. In turn, <lb/>the increase of neutrophils after colistin sulfate <lb/>treatment contributes to anti-infective therapy. <lb/>In terms of adverse events, the overall inci-<lb/>dence of adverse events to colistin sulfate is low. <lb/>In this study, only 7.6% of the patients had <lb/>mild nephrotoxicity, 2.5% had neurotoxicity, <lb/>and no patients had hepatic dysfunction. <lb/>Studies have shown that nephrotoxicity is dose <lb/>limiting for polymyxins [19, 41, 42]. Two recent <lb/>meta-analyses showed that the overall inci-<lb/>dences of CMS-and PMB-induced nephrotoxi-<lb/>city were 34.8% and 45%, respectively [43, 44]. <lb/>Compared with those of CMS and polymyxin B, <lb/>the event of renal impairment associated with <lb/>colistin sulfate was considerably lower (up to <lb/>9.2%) [21, 45]. Furthermore, unlike polymyxin <lb/>B, we did not find any skin hyperpigmentation <lb/>in the current study [15]. Considering these <lb/>findings, we suggest that the rational use of <lb/>colistin sulfate in the clinic is effective and safe. <lb/>However, this study has several limitations. <lb/>First, this is a single-center retrospective study <lb/>with limited sample size. Second, the drug <lb/>concentrations of colistin sulfate were not <lb/>monitored during the treatment, and PK/PD <lb/>analysis was lacking. Clinicians made clinical <lb/>decisions about dosage, administration, and <lb/>duration based on guidelines and personal <lb/>clinical experience, which made it difficult to <lb/>identify the optimal therapeutic concentra-<lb/>tions. Third, the majority of patients were <lb/>treated with colistin sulfate in conjunction with <lb/>other drugs, and colistin sulfate might be not <lb/>solely responsible for the ultimate effectiveness. <lb/>Moreover, in the current study, a significant <lb/>fraction of patients (58.5%) had lung infections <lb/>but did not receive any nebulized antibiotic <lb/>therapy, which may affect the possible antimi-<lb/>crobial treatment and outcomes. Therefore, <lb/>prospective, multicenter, randomized con-<lb/>trolled, and well-designed trials are needed to <lb/>better evaluate the efficacy and safety of colistin <lb/>sulfate in the future. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>As one of the polymyxins, colistin sulfate has <lb/>been marketed in China in 2018 and has played <lb/>an increasingly important role in the treatment <lb/>of CRO infections. There is an unmet need to <lb/>clarify the efficacy and safety of colistin sulfate <lb/>in hematological patients with CRO infections, <lb/>and such a real-world study fills the gap in the <lb/>current literature and provides a valuable refer-<lb/>ence for the clinical use of colistin sulfate. As <lb/>the study had shown, colistin sulfate is an <lb/>effective antimicrobial drug against CRO infec-<lb/>tions. Furthermore, the study found that the <lb/>treatment course of colistin sulfate and its <lb/>combination with other antimicrobial agents <lb/>were the factors affecting the clinical efficacy of <lb/>colistin sulfate. Colistin sulfate has a low inci-<lb/>dence of nephrotoxicity and neurotoxicity, <lb/>which provides a reference value for the rational <lb/>use of colistin sulfate in clinical practice. <lb/></body>

        <div type="contribution">Author Contribution. Yuanbing Wu and <lb/>Xiaohui Hu designed the study; Depei Wu pro-<lb/>vided administrative support; Xiaohui Hu pro-<lb/>vided the study materials and patients; <lb/>Shanshan Jiang, Dongyang Li, Yaxue Wu, Qian <lb/>Li, Xing Wang, Bin Liu, Haiyan Bao collected <lb/>the data; Shanshan Jiang and Dongyang Li <lb/>performed the data analyses and interpretation; <lb/>Yuanbing Wu wrote the manuscript. All authors <lb/>reviewed the manuscript and approved the final <lb/>version. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Funding. The work was supported by <lb/>grants from the Su Zhou Industrial Park He He <lb/>Yuan Da Blood Innovation Research Institute <lb/>(H221084); Innovative and Applied Scientific <lb/>Research Project of Professional Ability of Clin-<lb/>ical Specialists (RCLX2315016). The journal&apos;s <lb/>Rapid Service Fee was sponsored by The Hospi-<lb/>tal of Suzhou Hongci Hematology. <lb/></div>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <page>151 <lb/></page>

        <div type="availability">Data Availability. The datasets generated <lb/>during and/or analyzed during the current <lb/>study are available from the corresponding <lb/>author on reasonable request. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Declarations <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Conflict of Interest. Yuanbing Wu, Shan-<lb/>shan Jiang, Dongyang Li, Yaxue Wu, Qian Li, <lb/>Xing Wang, Bin Liu, Haiyan Bao, Depei Wu, <lb/>and Xiaohui Hu declared no competing <lb/>interests. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Ethical Approval. This retrospective study <lb/>was performed at the Hospital of Suzhou Hon-<lb/>gci Hematology, Suzhou, Jiangsu Province, <lb/>China. This study was approved by the Ethics <lb/>Committee of the Hospital of Suzhou Hongci <lb/>Hematology and was exempt from informed <lb/>consent because of its observational nature. <lb/>Furthermore, the study was implemented in <lb/>accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki (as <lb/>revised in 2013). <lb/></div>

        <front>Open Access. This article is licensed under a <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommer-<lb/>cial 4.0 International License, which permits <lb/>any non-commercial use, sharing, adaptation, <lb/>distribution and reproduction in any medium <lb/>or format, as long as you give appropriate credit <lb/>to the original author(s) and the source, provide <lb/>a link to the Creative Commons licence, and <lb/>indicate if changes were made. The images or <lb/>other third party material in this article are <lb/>included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons <lb/>licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit <lb/>line to the material. If material is not included <lb/>in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and <lb/>your intended use is not permitted by statutory <lb/>regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you <lb/>will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, <lb/>visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-<lb/>nc/4.0/. <lb/></front>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Averbuch D, Tridello G, Hoek J, et al. Antimicrobial <lb/>resistance in Gram-negative rods causing bac-<lb/>teremia in hematopoietic stem cell transplant <lb/>recipients: intercontinental prospective study of the <lb/>infectious diseases working party of the european <lb/>bone marrow transplantation group. Clin Infect <lb/>Dis. 2017;65(11):1819-28. <lb/>2. Zeng M, Xia J, Zong Z, et al. Guidelines for the <lb/>diagnosis, treatment, prevention and control of <lb/>infections caused by carbapenem-resistant gram-<lb/>negative bacilli. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. <lb/>2023;S1684-1182(23):00036-41. <lb/>3. Loon KV, Voor in &apos;T Holt AF, Vos MC. A systematic <lb/>review and meta-analyses of the clinical epidemi-<lb/>ology of carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae. <lb/>Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2018;62(1):e01730-<lb/>e11717. <lb/>4. Micozzi A, Gentile G, Minotti C, et al. Carbapenem-<lb/>resistant Klebsiella pneumoniae in high-risk haema-<lb/>tological patients: factors favouring spread, risk <lb/>factors and outcome of carbapenem-resistant Kleb-<lb/>siella pneumoniae bacteremias. BMC Infect Dis. <lb/>2017;17(1):203. <lb/>5. Satlin MJ, Jenkins SG, Walsh TJ. The global chal-<lb/>lenge of carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae <lb/>in transplant recipients and patients with hemato-<lb/>logic malignancies. Clin Infect Dis. 2014;58(9): <lb/>1274-83. <lb/>6. Satlin MJ, Cohen N, Ma KC, et al. Bacteremia due to <lb/>carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae in neu-<lb/>tropenic patients with hematologic malignancies. <lb/>J Infect. 2016;73(4):336-45. <lb/>7. Andria N, Henig O, Kotler O, et al. Mortality burden <lb/>related to infection with carbapenem-resistant <lb/>Gram-negative bacteria among haematological <lb/>cancer patients: a retrospective cohort study. <lb/>J Antimicrob Chemother. 2015;70(11):3146-53. <lb/>8. Lalaoui R, Javelle E, Bakour S, et al. Infections due <lb/>to carbapenem-resistant bacteria in patients with <lb/>hematologic malignancies. Front Microbiol. <lb/>2020;11:1422. <lb/>9. Jaiswal SR, Gupta S, Kumar RS, et al. Gut coloniza-<lb/>tion with carbapenem-resistant enterobacteriaceae <lb/>adversely impacts the outcome in patients with <lb/>hematological malignancies: results of a prospec-<lb/>tive surveillance study. Mediterr J Hematol Infect <lb/>Dis. 2018;10(1): e2018025. <lb/>10. Adukauskiene D, Ciginskiene A, Adukauskaite A, <lb/>et al. Clinical features and outcomes of monobac-<lb/>terial and polybacterial episodes of ventilator-<lb/></listBibl>

        <page>152 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>associated pneumonia due to multidrug-resistant <lb/>Acinetobacter <lb/>baumannii. <lb/>Antibiotics <lb/>(Basel). <lb/>2022;11(7):892. <lb/>11. Tsuji BT, Pogue JM, Zavascki AP, et al. International <lb/>consensus guidelines for the optimal use of the <lb/>polymyxins: endorsed by the American college of <lb/>clinical pharmacy (ACCP), European society of <lb/>clinical microbiology and infectious diseases (ESC-<lb/>MID), infectious diseases society of America (IDSA), <lb/>international society for anti-infective pharmacol-<lb/>ogy (ISAP), society of critical care medicine (SCCM), <lb/>and society of infectious diseases pharmacists <lb/>(SIDP). Pharmacotherapy. 2019;39(1):10-39. <lb/>12. El-Sayed Ahmed MAE, Zhong LL, Shen C, et al. <lb/>Colistin and its role in the Era of antibiotic resis-<lb/>tance: an extended review (2000-2019). Emerg <lb/>Microbes Infect. 2020;9(1):868-85. <lb/>13. Sirijatuphat R, Thawornkaew S, Ruangkriengsin D, <lb/>et al. Colistin monotherapy versus colistin plus <lb/>sitafloxacin for therapy of carbapenem-resistant <lb/>acinetobacter baumannii infections: a preliminary <lb/>study. Antibiotics (Basel). 2022;11(12):1707. <lb/>14. Zheng G, Cai J, Zhang L, et al. Ceftazidime/av-<lb/>ibactam-based versus polymyxin B-based therapeu-<lb/>tic regimens for the treatment of carbapenem-<lb/>resistant klebsiella pneumoniae infection in criti-<lb/>cally ill patients: a retrospective cohort study. Infect <lb/>Dis Ther. 2022;11(5):1917-34. <lb/>15. Xia GL, Jiang RL. Efficacy and safety of polymyxin B <lb/>in carbapenem-resistant gram-negative organisms <lb/>infections. BMC Infect Dis. 2021;21(1):1034. <lb/>16. Zhang X, Qi S, Duan X, et al. Clinical outcomes and <lb/>safety of polymyxin B in the treatment of car-<lb/>bapenem-resistant Gram-negative bacterial infec-<lb/>tions: a real-world multicenter study. J Transl Med. <lb/>2021;19:431. <lb/>17. Yu Z, Liu X, Du X, et al. Pharmacokinetics/phar-<lb/>macodynamics of polymyxin B in patients with <lb/>bloodstream infection caused by carbapenem-re-<lb/>sistant Klebsiella pneumoniae. Front Pharmacol. <lb/>2022;13: 975066. <lb/>18. Wagenlehner F, Lucenteforte E, Pea F, et al. Sys-<lb/>tematic review on estimated rates of nephrotoxicity <lb/>and neurotoxicity in patients treated with <lb/>polymyxins. <lb/>Clin <lb/>Microbiol <lb/>Infect. <lb/>2021;S1198-743X(20):30764-73. <lb/>19. Zavascki AP, Nation RL. Nephrotoxicity of <lb/>polymyxins: is there any difference between colis-<lb/>timethate and polymyxin B? Antimicrob Agents <lb/>Chemother. 2017;61(3):e02319-e2416. <lb/>20. Mattos KPH, Cintra ML, Gouve ˆa IR, et al. Skin <lb/>hyperpigmentation <lb/>following <lb/>intravenous <lb/>polymyxin B treatment associated with melanocyte <lb/>activation and inflammatory process. J Clin Pharm <lb/>Ther. 2017;42(5):573-8. <lb/>21. Xie YL, Jin X, Yan SS, et al. Population pharma-<lb/>cokinetics of intravenous colistin sulfate and <lb/>dosage optimization in critically ill patients. Front <lb/>Pharmacol. 2022;13: 967412. <lb/>22. Peng D, Zhang F, Chen Y, et al. Efficacy and safety <lb/>of colistin sulfate in the treatment of infections <lb/>caused by carbapenem-resistant organisms: a mul-<lb/>ticenter retrospective cohort study. J Thorac Dis. <lb/>2023;15(4):1794-804. <lb/>23. Jin J, Zhu J, Zhu Z, et al. Clinical efficacy and <lb/>nephrotoxicity of intravenous colistin sulfate in the <lb/>treatment of carbapenem-resistant gram-negative <lb/>bacterial infections: a retrospective cohort study. <lb/>Ann Transl Med. 2022;10(20):1137. <lb/>24. Infectious Diseases Society of China, Chinese Tho-<lb/>racic Society, Chinese Society of Critical Care <lb/>Medicine, et al. [Multi-disciplinary expert consen-<lb/>sus on the optimal clinical use of the polymyxins in <lb/>China]. Zhonghua Jie He He Hu Xi Za Zhi. 2021, <lb/>44(4):292-310 <lb/>25. Editorial Board of Chinese Journal of Infectious <lb/>Diseases. Clinical practice expert consensus for the <lb/>application of metagenomic next generation <lb/>sequencing (In Chinese). Chin J Infect Dis. <lb/>2020;38(11):681-9. <lb/>26. Yang QW, Ma XL, Hu FP, et al. Expert consensus on <lb/>polymyxin antimicrobial susceptibility testing and <lb/>clinical interpretation. Chin Med Sci J. 2021;36(1): <lb/>1-16. <lb/>27. Pogue JM, Jones RN, Bradley JS, et al. Polymyxin <lb/>susceptibility testing and interpretive breakpoints: <lb/>recommendations from the United States commit-<lb/>tee on antimicrobial susceptibility testing <lb/>(USCAST). <lb/>Antimicrob <lb/>Agents <lb/>Chemother. <lb/>2020;64(2):e01495-e1519. <lb/>28. Khwaja A. KDIGO clinical practice guidelines for <lb/>acute kidney injury. Nephron Clin Pract. <lb/>2012;120(4):c179-184. <lb/>29. Lu X, Zhong C, Liu Y, Ye H, Qu J, Zong Z, Lv X. <lb/>Efficacy and safety of polymyxin E sulfate in the <lb/>treatment of critically ill patients with carbapenem-<lb/>resistant organism infections. Front Med (Lau-<lb/>sanne). 2022;9:1067548. <lb/>30. Ayoub MC. Polymyxins and bacterial membranes: a <lb/>review of antibacterial activity and mechanisms of <lb/>resistance. Membranes (Basel). 2020;10(8):181. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 <lb/></note>

        <page>153 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>31. Stefaniuk EM, Tyski S. Colistin resistance in enter-<lb/>obacterales strains -a current view. Pol J Microbiol. <lb/>2019;68(4):417-27. <lb/>32. Rodriguez CH, De Ambrosio A, Bajuk M, et al. <lb/>In vitro antimicrobials activity against endemic <lb/>Acinetobacter baumannii multiresistant clones. <lb/>J Infect Dev Ctries. 2010;4(3):164-7. <lb/>33. Pankuch GA, Lin G, Seifert H, et al. Activity of <lb/>meropenem with and without ciprofloxacin and <lb/>colistin against Pseudomonas aeruginosa and Acine-<lb/>tobacter baumannii. Antimicrob Agents Che-<lb/>mother. 2008;52(1):333-6. <lb/>34. Gordon NC, Png K, Wareham DW. Potent synergy <lb/>and sustained bactericidal activity of a vancomycin-<lb/>colistin combination versus multidrug-resistant <lb/>strains of Acinetobacter baumannii. Antimicrob <lb/>Agents Chemother. 2010;54(12):5316-22. <lb/>35. Zusman O, Altunin S, Koppel F, et al. Polymyxin <lb/>monotherapy or in combination against car-<lb/>bapenem-resistant bacteria: systematic review and <lb/>meta-analysis. <lb/>J <lb/>Antimicrob <lb/>Chemother. <lb/>2017;72(1):29-39. <lb/>36. Nutman A, Lellouche J, Temkin E, et al. Colistin <lb/>plus meropenem for carbapenem-resistant Gram-<lb/>negative infections: in vitro synergism is not asso-<lb/>ciated with better clinical outcomes. Clin Microbiol <lb/>Infect. 2020;26(9):1185-91. <lb/>37. Saelim W, Changpradub D, Thunyaharn S, et al. <lb/>Colistin plus sulbactam or fosfomycin against car-<lb/>bapenem-resistant <lb/>acinetobacter <lb/>baumannii: <lb/>improved efficacy or decreased risk of nephrotoxi-<lb/>city? Infect Chemother. 2021;53(1):128-40. <lb/>38. Covington EW, Roberts MZ, Dong J. Procalcitonin <lb/>monitoring as a guide for antimicrobial therapy: a <lb/>review of current literature. Pharmacotherapy. <lb/>2018;38(5):569-81. <lb/>39. Dias RF, de Paula ACRB, Hasparyk UG, et al. Use of <lb/>C-reactive protein to guide the antibiotic therapy in <lb/>hospitalized patients: a systematic review and meta-<lb/>analysis. BMC Infect Dis. 2023;23(1):276. <lb/>40. Henriquez-Camacho C, Losa J. Biomarkers for sep-<lb/>sis. Biomed Res Int. 2014;2014: 547818. <lb/>41. Pogue JM, Ortwine JK, Kaye KS. Are there any ways <lb/>around the exposure-limiting nephrotoxicity of the <lb/>polymyxins? Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2016;48(6): <lb/>622-6. <lb/>42. Azad MAK, Nation RL, Velkov T, et al. Mechanisms <lb/>of polymyxin-induced nephrotoxicity. Adv Exp <lb/>Med Biol. 2019;1145:305-19. <lb/>43. Wang JL, Xiang BX, Song XL, et al. Prevalence of <lb/>polymyxin-induced nephrotoxicity and its predic-<lb/>tors in critically ill adult patients: a meta-analysis. <lb/>World J Clin Cases. 2022;10(31):11466-85. <lb/>44. Sisay M, Hagos B, Edessa D, et al. Polymyxin-in-<lb/>duced nephrotoxicity and its predictors: a system-<lb/>atic review and meta-analysis of studies conducted <lb/>using RIFLE criteria of acute kidney injury. Phar-<lb/>macol Res. 2021;163: 105328. <lb/>45. Hao M, Yang Y, Guo Y, et al. Combination regi-<lb/>mens with colistin sulfate versus colistin sulfate <lb/>monotherapy in the treatment of infections caused <lb/>by carbapenem-resistant gram-negative bacilli. <lb/>Antibiotics (Basel). 2022;11(10):1440. <lb/></listBibl>

        <div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s Note <lb/>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdic-<lb/>tional claims in published maps and institutional <lb/>affiliations. <lb/></div>

        <page>154 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Infect Dis Ther (2024) 13:141-154 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>