<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Exploring Drivers of Historic Mercury Trends in Beluga Whales Using an Ecosystem Modeling Approach</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Emma J.</forename>
            <surname>Gillies</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Mi-Ling</forename>
            <surname>Li</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Villy</forename>
            <surname>Christensen</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Carie</forename>
            <surname>Hoover</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Kristen J.</forename>
            <surname>Sora</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Lisa L.</forename>
            <surname>Loseto</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>William W. L.</forename>
            <surname>Cheung</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Hélène</forename>
            <surname>Angot</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Amanda</forename>
            <surname>Giang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-27T11:27:51.309320Z">27.10.2025 11:27:51</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1021$1$acsenvironau.3c00072</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>American Chemical Society (ACS)</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1021/acsenvironau.3c00072</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Emma J. Gillies, Mi-Ling Li, Villy Christensen, Carie Hoover, Kristen J. Sora, Lisa L. Loseto, William W. L. Cheung, Hélène Angot, Amanda Giang. (2024). Exploring Drivers of Historic Mercury Trends in Beluga Whales Using an Ecosystem Modeling Approach. ACS Environmental Au, 4(5), 219-235. DOI: 10.1021/acsenvironau.3c00072</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-27T11:27:51.309320Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-27T11:27:51.309320Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Electrical Properties of Laser Patterned Schottky Diode with ALD-<lb/>Grown TiO 2 Interlayer <lb/>Elanur Dikiciogľu,* M. Burcu Balı, Semran Sagľam, Halil Berberogľu, Ihor Pavlov, Arian Goodarzi, <lb/>and Elif Orhan* <lb/>Cite This: ACS Omega 2024, 9, 21346-21352 <lb/>Read Online <lb/>ACCESS <lb/>Metrics &amp; More <lb/>Article Recommendations <lb/>ABSTRACT: Heterojunction formation is the key to adjusting <lb/>the electronic and optoelectronic properties of various semi-<lb/>conductor devices. There have been various reports on the <lb/>formation and importance of semiconducting heterojunction <lb/>devices based on metal oxides. Titanium dioxide (TiO 2 ) is one <lb/>of the metal oxides that has many unique properties. TiO 2 &apos;s <lb/>importance is due to its physical and chemical properties such as <lb/>large band gap, large permittivity, stability, and low leakage current <lb/>density. In this context, we present the electrical properties of the <lb/>metal-insulator-semiconductor (MIS) type-TiO 2 -based Schottky barrier diode (SBD) in the study. To create a thin layer of TiO 2 <lb/>on p-type silicon (p-type Si) patterned partially by the laser-induced periodic surface structure (LIPSS) technique, an atomic layer <lb/>deposition (ALD) technique was used in the study. For comparison, the current-voltage (I-V) characteristics of the TiO 2 -based <lb/>laser-patterned (LP) and nonlaser-patterned (non-LP) diodes were measured at 300 K and in the dark at ±5 V. Classical thermionic <lb/>emission (TE) theory and Cheung functions were used to investigate the critical diode parameters of the diodes, including ideality <lb/>factor (n), series resistance (R s ), and barrier height (Φ b ). The n values were obtained as 4.10 and 3.68 from the TE method and <lb/>Cheung functions for the LP diode, respectively. The Φ b values were found as 0.68 and 0.69 eV from the TE method and Cheung <lb/>functions, respectively. According to experimental results, the laser patterning resulted in an increase in the Φ b values and a decrease <lb/>in the n values. After laser patterning, it was observed that the device worked effectively, and the ideality factor and barrier height <lb/>values were improved. This study provides insight into the fabrication and electrical properties of TiO 2 -based heterojunction devices. <lb/></front>

        <body>1. INTRODUCTION <lb/>A semiconductor device called a Schottky diode is created <lb/>when a metal and a semiconductor come together. This diode <lb/>generates an energy barrier using a metal-semiconductor <lb/>junction. Schottky diodes are dependent on the energy barrier <lb/>that develops at the interface between a semiconductor and a <lb/>metal. Because of their quick switching speed and limited <lb/>reverse voltage tolerance, diodes are frequently used in high-<lb/>frequency applications. They also display nonlinear voltage-<lb/>current characteristics. Metals, insulators, and semiconductors <lb/>are all combined to form metal-insulator-semiconductor <lb/>(MIS) structures. By adjusting the electric field, this arrange-<lb/>ment may regulate the carrier density on the semiconductor <lb/>surface. MIS structures are frequently seen as components with <lb/>a capacitance. The semiconductor surface is connected to the <lb/>insulator that sits between the metal electrode and the <lb/>semiconductor. Applying an electric field has an impact on <lb/>the carriers in semiconductors. MIS structure is frequently seen <lb/>in capacitive devices and semiconductor memory devices, and <lb/>it is utilized as an isolation layer in transistors and integrated <lb/>circuits. The insulator layer in the metal-insulator sandwich <lb/>structures is usually bonded directly to a semiconductor <lb/>surface and can be made of several materials, not just oxide. An <lb/>oxide material such as SiO 2 , Al 2 O 3 , ZnO, or TiO 2 is commonly <lb/>employed as the insulator layer in metal-oxide-semi-<lb/>conductor (MOS) systems. 1,2 Particularly in MOS transistors <lb/>and integrated circuits, these structures are commonly used. <lb/>The formation of heterojunctions is the key to tuning the <lb/>electronic and optoelectronic properties of various semi-<lb/>conductor devices. The formation and importance of semi-<lb/>conducting heterojunction devices based on metal oxides have <lb/>been widely reported. 3-5 TiO 2 is a high-dielectric, high-<lb/>refractive, big band gap material that is widely employed in <lb/>many different electronic devices, especially in the memory, <lb/>photovoltaic, and optical coatings industries. 6,7 It is being <lb/>investigated in several papers for application at the MS <lb/>interface to provide barrier modification in addition to the <lb/></body>

        <front>Received: February 19, 2024 <lb/>Revised: April 17, 2024 <lb/>Accepted: April 23, 2024 <lb/>Published: May 2, 2024 <lb/>Article <lb/>http://pubs.acs.org/journal/acsodf <lb/>© 2024 The Authors. Published by <lb/>American Chemical Society <lb/>21346 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.4c01585 <lb/>ACS Omega 2024, 9, 21346-21352 <lb/>This article is licensed under CC-BY 4.0 <lb/>Downloaded via 87.196.73.201 on September 10, 2025 at 13:43:25 (UTC). <lb/>See https://pubs.acs.org/sharingguidelines for options on how to legitimately share published articles. <lb/></front>

        <body>semiconductor layer&apos;s surface passivation. Before Schottky <lb/>metallization, a TiO 2 thin-film layer deposition provides several <lb/>technological benefits, including enhanced device impedance <lb/>characteristics and shielding the semiconductor surface from <lb/>defective interfacial compounds. 8,9 In other words, because of <lb/>potential interfacial reactions resulting from the deposition of a <lb/>rectifying metal contact, TiO 2 can be added to the MS <lb/>interface to control the defective states. Consequently, efforts <lb/>are focused on improving the rectification capabilities and <lb/>increasing the junction barrier in these kinds of diodes. 10,11 <lb/>Atomic layer deposition (ALD) is one of the most viable <lb/>ways to successfully create TiO 2 in diode applications, even if <lb/>there are other methods used to deposit TiO 2 thin-film layer at <lb/>the MS interface, such as vapor deposition and solution-based <lb/>techniques. 12-17 It can produce dense, smooth films with fewer <lb/>flaws and controllability over the film thickness when utilized <lb/>in the deposition of TiO 2 layers. Aydın et al. 18 investigated the <lb/>electrical analysis of the Al/p-Si Schottky diode with TiO 2 thin <lb/>film performed at room temperature. They concluded that the <lb/>Schottky effect was found to be dominant in the reverse <lb/>direction. A researcher 19 studied the diode parameters of the <lb/>Al/TiO 2 /p-Si Schottky diode at a wide temperature range and <lb/>different illuminance intensities. With the increasing temper-<lb/>ature, the ideality factor value of the device decreases from <lb/>4.878 to 2.305 and the barrier height increases from 0.287 to <lb/>0.714 eV. The electrical characterization of the Al/ALD-grown <lb/>TiO 2 /p-Si structure was investigated by Karabulut et al. 20 The <lb/>optoelectronic properties of Li:TiO 2 -based photodiodes were <lb/>investigated. 21 It was concluded that the lowest n value of 5.92 <lb/>is obtained for a 2% Li-doped diode. The I-V measurements <lb/>of Al/TiO 2 /n-Si were taken in the temperature range of 50 K-<lb/>400 K. 22 The results showed that the currents of the devices <lb/>are a strong function of the temperature. Yıldız et al. fabricated <lb/>the Al/TiO 2 /p-Si Schottky-type by atomic layer deposition <lb/>(ALD) for a thin layer and investigated I-V-T properties. 23 <lb/>Boutelala et al. 24 obtained the characteristic parameters of Al/ <lb/>TiO 2 /p-Si/Al from I-V measurement. It was concluded that <lb/>the diode exhibits perfect photosensitivity and high photo-<lb/>response properties. Additionally, TiO 2 is typically utilized in <lb/>the UV light detection spectrum. TiO 2 nanorods were <lb/>produced using the hydrothermal technique by Gao et al. 25 <lb/>Nicolaescu et al. 26 created a heterostructured p-n type <lb/>photodetector with high responsivity performance by thermal <lb/>oxidation of n-TiO 2 and using p-CuMnO 2 to get n-TiO 2 /p-<lb/>CuMnO 2 thin film. TiO 2 is occasionally employed as an <lb/>interfacial layer to improve the photodetection capabilities of <lb/>Schottky-type photodetectors in the presence of sunlight. 27-30 <lb/>The device performed well in the UV and visible ranges if TiO 2 <lb/>is placed on the Si substrate to create a photodetector. 31 The <lb/>effect of laser patterning (LP) on Schottky diode properties <lb/>and graphene film quality was investigated by Orhan et al. 32 <lb/>They showed that laser patterning reduces reverse-biased <lb/>leakage currents and increases the Schottky barrier height. In <lb/>particular, they have seen how the laser patterning process <lb/>affects 3D graphene nanosheets, resulting in the formation of <lb/>new structures over the entire surface of the p-type substrate. <lb/>These structures were in the form of nanospheres and <lb/>nanoroses. According to their results, it is expected that the <lb/>ideality factor and the barrier height will be improved after the <lb/>laser patterning structuring and that the device will work <lb/>effectively. <lb/>Figure 1. SEM images of laser-patterned p-type Si wafer. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>http://pubs.acs.org/journal/acsodf <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.4c01585 <lb/>ACS Omega 2024, 9, 21346-21352 <lb/></note>

        <page>21347 <lb/></page>

        <body>This study is focused on investigating the effect of the LP <lb/>process on the diode properties of ALD-grown TiO 2 /p-type Si <lb/>Schottky structures. By comparison of two diodes consisting of <lb/>oxide (TiO 2 ) junctions with an LP diode and a non-LP diode <lb/>at 300 K in the dark, the effect of LP on the TiO 2 -p-type Si <lb/>interface was evaluated. In this study, only the central region of <lb/>the p-type Si wafer was patterned by LIPSS. The TiO 2 layer <lb/>was deposited directly on p-type Si with patterned and <lb/>nonpatterned regions by the ALD technique for the fabrication <lb/>of Al/ALD-grown TiO 2 /p-type Si Schottky diodes. Current-<lb/>voltage (I-V) characteristics were measured in the dark at 300 <lb/>K at ±5 V. Using the methods of Cheung and the standard TE <lb/>theory, the ideality factor (n), the barrier height (ϕ b ), and the <lb/>series resistance (R s ) of the fabricated diodes were extracted. <lb/>2. EXPERIMENTAL SECTION <lb/>In this work, we employed a p-type Si (100) wafer with a <lb/>resistivity of 1-10 Ω•cm and a thickness of 380 μm. The p-type <lb/>Si wafer was cleaned using Radio Corporation of America <lb/>(RCA) techniques to get rid of any organic residues before <lb/>processing. 33 The central region of p-type Si was patterned by <lb/>using a femtosecond laser source. A central region of p-type Si <lb/>was patterned by only the LIPSS technique, but the whole <lb/>wafer was coated with a TiO 2 layer by the ALD technique. The <lb/>source (up to 2 μJ pulse energy; ∼300 fs pulse duration) <lb/>was a homemade fs-fiber laser with a 1 MHz rep rate at 1030 <lb/>nm. After the laser was focused on the Si substrate, a Galvo <lb/>scanner was used to raster-scan the area, which measured 8 × 8 <lb/>mm 2 . On Si, the beam diameter was about ∼9 μm. The overlap <lb/>factor was 5-6 pulses per spot, and the surface pulse energy <lb/>was 400 nJ. A scanning electron microscopy (SEM) images of <lb/>the laser patterned p-type Si wafer are shown in Figure 1. As <lb/>can be seen in Figure 1, this results in a regular periodic path. <lb/>In this study, two diodes with TiO 2 layer laser pattern (LP) <lb/>and nonlaser pattern (non-LP) were created. The I-V <lb/>characteristics of the two diodes were measured in the ±5 V <lb/>range at 300 K and in the dark. Using sputtering systems <lb/>operating at 500 °C and 4.7 × 10 -6 Torr pressure, 128 nm <lb/>thick Al (99.999%) metal was formed to create an ohmic <lb/>contact on the unpolished back surface of the plate. An ALD <lb/>device (Okyay Nanotech) was used to deposit a TiO 2 layer as <lb/>a 16 nm thin film on the entire surface of the p-type Si wafer, <lb/>including both laser-patterned and nonlaser-patterned regions. <lb/>This was carried out at 170 °C, a low substrate temperature. <lb/>To reach a layer thickness of 16 nm at a growth rate of 1.29 Å/ <lb/>cycle, 125 cycles of TiO 2 deposition were carried out. Tetrakis <lb/>(dimethylamido) titanium(IV) (TDMAT) and H 2 O were used <lb/>as precursor materials of TiO 2 . To separate precursor cycles, <lb/>nitrogen (%99.999) was employed as a cleaning gas and carrier <lb/>at a flow rate of 7 sscm. The percussive temperature is 150 °C; <lb/>the circle inner temperature is 170 °C, and the system pressure <lb/>is 2.72 × 10 -1 Torr. A 100 ms TDMAT pulse, a 20 s N 2 purge, <lb/>a 15 ms H 2 O pulse, and a 10 s N 2 purge make up a single TiO 2 <lb/>ALD cycle. Subsequently, using a mask shaped like 1.5 mm <lb/>circular dots, 128 nm thick Al (∼99.999%) rectifier contacts <lb/>were formed on the TiO 2 layer using the sputtering process at <lb/>7.06 × 10 -6 Torr. <lb/>Figure 2 displays the measurement setup and schematic <lb/>cross-section of the Al/ALD-grown TiO 2 /p-type Si diode. <lb/>Keithley 2400 programmable constant current source was used <lb/>for current-voltage (I-V) measurements. All of these <lb/>measurements were carried out by controlling the device <lb/>with the help of an IEEE-488 AC/DC converter card plugged <lb/>into the computer. All of the electrical data presented in the <lb/>study was collected from both the LP diode and the non-LP <lb/>diode. In this study, only the central region of the p-type Si <lb/>wafer was patterned by LIPSS. The TiO 2 layer was deposited <lb/>directly over the entire region, including patterned and <lb/>nonpatterned regions, using the ALD technique to fabricate <lb/>Al/ALD-grown TiO 2/ p-type Si Schottky diodes on p-type Si. <lb/>Figure 3 shows the energy band diagram for the Al/TiO 2 /p-<lb/>type Si diode. The electron affinities of p-Si, anatase phase <lb/>TiO 2 , and l metal have been reported to be approximately <lb/>4.05, 34 4.2, 18,35 and 4.3 eV, 36 respectively. <lb/>3. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>First, the TE theory has been used to analyze the electrical <lb/>properties of the Al/ALD-grown TiO 2 /p-type Si diode. The <lb/>relationship between the current flowing through a Schottky <lb/>diode and the forward bias voltage (V &gt; 3kT/q) is as follows, <lb/>for the TE theory. 37 <lb/>i <lb/>k <lb/>j j j <lb/>y <lb/>{ <lb/>z z z <lb/>Ä <lb/>Ç <lb/>Å Å Å Å Å Å Å Å <lb/>i <lb/>k <lb/>j j j <lb/>y <lb/>{ <lb/>z z z <lb/>É <lb/>Ö <lb/>Ñ Ñ Ñ Ñ Ñ Ñ Ñ Ñ Ñ <lb/>I I <lb/>qV <lb/>nkT <lb/>qV <lb/>kT <lb/>exp <lb/>1 exp <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>(1) <lb/>i <lb/>k <lb/>j j j j <lb/>y <lb/>{ <lb/>z z z z <lb/>I <lb/>AA T <lb/>q <lb/>kT <lb/>exp <lb/>b <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>= * <lb/>(2) <lb/>where I 0 is the saturation current found at V = 0 at the (ln I)-<lb/>V plot&apos;s straight-line intercept. A* is Richardson&apos;s constant (32 <lb/>A/(cm 2 K 2 ) for p-type Si). The electron charge, Boltzmann&apos;s <lb/>constant, and temperature in Kelvin are denoted by the letters <lb/>Figure 2. (a) Measurement setup. (b) Schematic sections of Al/ALD-grown TiO 2 /p-type Si for LP (central region) and non-LP diode (edge <lb/>region). <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>http://pubs.acs.org/journal/acsodf <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.4c01585 <lb/>ACS Omega 2024, 9, 21346-21352 <lb/></note>

        <page>21348 <lb/></page>

        <body>q, k, and T. The diode area, effective barrier height, and applied <lb/>voltage are denoted by the letters A, ϕ b , and V, respectively. <lb/>Using eq 3, the slope of the semilogarithmic I-V plots for <lb/>the linear region was used to get the values of n. 37 <lb/>n <lb/>q <lb/>kT <lb/>V <lb/>I <lb/>d <lb/>d(ln ) <lb/>= <lb/>(3) <lb/>ϕ b can be derived from eq 4 as given by <lb/>i <lb/>k <lb/>j j j j j <lb/>y <lb/>{ <lb/>z z z z z <lb/>kT <lb/>q <lb/>AA T <lb/>I <lb/>ln <lb/>b <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>* <lb/>(4) <lb/>Figure 4 shows the (ln I)-V characteristics of an Al/ALD-<lb/>grown TiO 2 /p-type Si diode at ±5 V and 300 K. The diode&apos;s I-<lb/>V curve is displayed in the embedded graph in Figure 4. ϕ b <lb/>values were calculated from the intercepts of the forward bias <lb/>(ln I)-V plot at 300 K. <lb/>Figure 4 makes it clear that despite low leakage, the I-V <lb/>characteristics of the Al/ALD-grown TiO 2 /p-type Si structure <lb/>exhibit rectifying behavior. The diode&apos;s rectification ratio (RR) <lb/>was found to be 9.5 × 10 3 . In the linear region, which is the <lb/>forward bias I-V characteristic downward curvature, R s is <lb/>considerable. But in both the nonlinear and linear regions of <lb/>I-V characteristics, the other two factors, n and ϕ b , are <lb/>important. A method created by S.K. Cheung and N.W. <lb/>Cheung was used to calculate the values of n, ϕ b , and R s . 37 For <lb/>a nonlinear high-voltage region of the forward bias of I-V <lb/>plots, Cheung&apos;s model is implemented. 38 According to this <lb/>method, n, ϕ b , R s , and H(I) can be written as <lb/>V <lb/>I <lb/>n <lb/>kT <lb/>q <lb/>IR <lb/>d <lb/>d(ln ) <lb/>s <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>(5) <lb/>i <lb/>k <lb/>j j j <lb/>y <lb/>{ <lb/>z z z <lb/>H I <lb/>V <lb/>nkT <lb/>q <lb/>I <lb/>AA T <lb/>( ) <lb/>ln <lb/>2 <lb/>= <lb/>* <lb/>(6) <lb/>H I <lb/>n <lb/>IR <lb/>( ) <lb/>b <lb/>s <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>(7) <lb/>The ϕ b obtained from the linear region in the forward bias <lb/>I-V characteristics. In Figure 5, the dV/d ln I vs I and H(I) vs <lb/>I plots are presented for an Al/ALD-grown TiO 2 /p-type Si <lb/>diode at 300 K, respectively. <lb/>The slope of the dV/d(ln I) vs I curve yields the value of R s , <lb/>while the curve&apos;s cut-point yields the value of n. Using the n <lb/>value in eq 5, R s is obtained from the slope of the H(I) vs I <lb/>curve and ϕ b values are obtained from the intersection point of <lb/>the curve in eq 7. The values of n, ϕ b , and R s for the Schottky <lb/>diode are computed, as shown in Table 1. For Al/ALD-grown <lb/>TiO 2 /p-type Si, the diode parameters for the LP and non-LP <lb/>regions are given in Table 1. <lb/>It was found that the n values were obtained as 4.10 and 3.68 <lb/>from the TE method and Cheung functions for the LP diode, <lb/>respectively. The Φ b values were found as 0.68 and 0.69 eV <lb/>from the TE method and Cheung functions, respectively. For <lb/>the non-LP diode, the n values were obtained as 8.13 and 4.97 <lb/>from the TE method and Cheung functions, respectively. The <lb/>Φ b values were found as 0.51 and 0.38 eV from the TE method <lb/>and Cheung functions for the non-LP region, respectively. The <lb/>results in Table 1 show a good agreement (1% discrepancy) <lb/>between the barrier height (Φ b ) values obtained by the TE and <lb/>Cheung methods. This confirms the effectiveness of these <lb/>techniques. However, there is a discrepancy of about 10% <lb/>between the nanovalues obtained by the two methods for the <lb/>Figure 3. Energy band diagram of Al/ALD-grown TiO 2 /p-type Si <lb/>diode. <lb/>Figure 4. Semilogarithmic I-V characteristics of the Al/ ALD-grown <lb/>TiO 2 /p-type Si diode. <lb/>Figure 5. dV/d(ln I) vs I and H(I) vs I characteristics of Al ALD-<lb/>grown TiO 2 /p-type Si diode. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>http://pubs.acs.org/journal/acsodf <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.4c01585 <lb/>ACS Omega 2024, 9, 21346-21352 <lb/></note>

        <page>21349 <lb/></page>

        <body>LP region. An increase in R s values for the LP region is <lb/>attributed to the defects and surface roughness created on p-<lb/>type Si by laser patterning. The nonideal behavior (n &gt; 1) of <lb/>the diode confirmed the presence of interfacial states. The Φ b <lb/>values for all two methods are in agreement with each other for <lb/>the LP-diode. <lb/>The periodicity of LIPSS on silicon for the laser used (1030 <lb/>nm) is around 850-900 nm. Therefore, this periodicity is <lb/>greater than the thickness of the TiO 2 layer (16 nm) and the <lb/>metal contact (128 nm) and it can be said that the layers will <lb/>take the shape of the pattern during deposition. As a result, the <lb/>effective contact surface of metal contacts is expected to <lb/>increase compared with the flat surface. Laser patterning <lb/>resulted in an increase in the Φ b values and a decrease in the n <lb/>values. After laser patterning, it was observed that the device <lb/>worked effectively and the ideality factor and barrier height <lb/>values were improved. Therefore, this effect may confirm an <lb/>improvement in the functioning of the device. For comparison <lb/>with our work, we have presented the diode parameters of <lb/>various Schottky diodes with TiO 2 interlayers of different <lb/>thicknesses fabricated by some researchers 18-24 at 300 K in the <lb/>literature in Table 2. <lb/>As can be seen from Table 2, thickness of the interlayer <lb/>and the difference in the method used to create the <lb/>measurements affected the n and Φ b values. When the basic <lb/>diode parameters of the device created in this study were <lb/>compared with other studies, especially ALD-grown structures <lb/>[refs 18, 20, and 23], we found a high n value (8.13) for the <lb/>non-LP diode as in ref 23 (see Table 1). The height of the <lb/>barrier was found to be compatible with the study mentioned <lb/>above at 6%. 23 After laser pattering, the n value (calculated by <lb/>the TE method) of the LP diode decreased by a factor of 50%. <lb/>Compared to the structure grown by ALD by the <lb/>researchers, 20 the n values for the LP diode are higher than <lb/>that of the work. As no RR data exist for the ALD-grown TiO 2 <lb/>structure, it could not be compared. The RR was higher than <lb/>those of thermally evaporated 19 and sol-gel spin-coated 21 <lb/>structures. A high RR value was obtained for the spin-coated <lb/>bilayer TiO 2 structure 22 as shown in Table 2. <lb/>4. CONCLUSION <lb/>In this study, the electrical properties of the Al/ALD-grown <lb/>TiO 2 /p-type Si Schottky barrier diode fabricated in the form of <lb/>a heterojunction were examined in the dark and at 300 K using <lb/>TE theory and Cheung methods. To create a thin layer of TiO 2 <lb/>on both the LP region and the non-LP region on the p-type Si <lb/>substrate, the ALD technique was used in the study. The I-V <lb/>characteristics of the diode were investigated. The presence of <lb/>interfacial states was confirmed by the nonideal behavior (n &gt; <lb/>1) of the measured values. It can be said that the layers will <lb/>take the shape of the pattern during deposition. Thus, laser <lb/>patterning increased the effective contact surface of metal <lb/>contacts compared to the flat surface, causing an increase in <lb/>the Φ b values and a decrease in the n values. After laser <lb/>patterning, it was observed that the device worked effectively <lb/>and the ideality factor and barrier height values were improved. <lb/>Therefore, this effect may confirm the improvement in the <lb/>functioning of the device. This study provides insight into the <lb/>fabrication and the electrical properties of heterojunction <lb/>devices based on TiO 2 . <lb/></body>

        <div type="annex">■ ASSOCIATED CONTENT <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data Availability Statement <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study are available <lb/>from the corresponding author, [E.O.], upon reasonable <lb/>request as it is unpublished data for another study. <lb/></div>

        <front>■ AUTHOR INFORMATION <lb/>Corresponding Authors <lb/>Elanur Dikiciogľu -Vocational School of Health Services, <lb/>Yuksek I ̇htisas University, 06291 Ankara, Turkey; <lb/>orcid.org/0000-0002-8984-1054; <lb/>Email: elanurdikicioglu@yiu.edu.tr <lb/>Elif Orhan -Faculty of Science, Department of Physics, Gazi <lb/>University, 06500 Ankara, Turkey; orcid.org/0000-0002-<lb/>3949-6141; Email: eliforhan@gazi.edu.tr <lb/></front>

        <body>Table 1. Diode Parameters for the LP Diode and the Non-LP Diode <lb/>LP diode <lb/>Non-LP diode <lb/>Methods <lb/>n <lb/>Φ b (eV) <lb/>R s (kΩ) <lb/>n <lb/>Φ b (eV) <lb/>R s (kΩ) <lb/>TE <lb/>4.10 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>-<lb/>8.13 <lb/>0.51 <lb/>Cheung <lb/>dV/d ln I vs I <lb/>3.68 <lb/>-<lb/>2.99 <lb/>4.97 <lb/>-<lb/>0.80 <lb/>H(I) vs I <lb/>-<lb/>0.69 <lb/>1.93 <lb/>-<lb/>0.38 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>Table 2. Comparison of Diode Parameters for Various Types of Schottky Diodes with TiO 2 Interlayer <lb/>Diodes <lb/>Interlayer Coating Methods <lb/>n (LP diode <lb/>Φ b (eV) <lb/>RR <lb/>References <lb/>Al/TiO 2 (16 nm)/laser-patterned p-Si <lb/>ALD <lb/>4.10 (TE) <lb/>0.68 <lb/>9.5 × 10 3 <lb/>Present work <lb/>3.68 (Cheung) <lb/>0.69 <lb/>Al/TiO 2 (200 nm)/p-Si <lb/>ALD <lb/>2.96 (TE) <lb/>0.66 <lb/>-<lb/>18 <lb/>2.55 (Cheung) <lb/>0.76 <lb/>Al/TiO 2 (20.4 nm)/p-Si <lb/>Thermal evaporation <lb/>2.437 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>1.77 × 10 3 <lb/>19 <lb/>Al/TiO 2 (10 nm)/p-Si <lb/>ALD <lb/>1.04 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>-<lb/>20 <lb/>Al/TiO 2 /p-Si <lb/>Sol-gel spin coating <lb/>9.41 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>4.75 × 10 3 <lb/>21 <lb/>Al/TiO 2 (200 nm)/n-Si <lb/>Spin coating <lb/>1.93 (TE) <lb/>0.93 <lb/>2.49 × 10 4 <lb/>22 <lb/>2.26 (Cheung) <lb/>0.84 <lb/>Al/TiO 2 (4 nm)/p-Si <lb/>ALD <lb/>12.71 (TE) <lb/>0.64 <lb/>-<lb/>23 <lb/>12.73 (Cheung) <lb/>0.68 <lb/>Al/bilayer TiO 2 (226.92 nm ) /p-Si <lb/>Spin coating <lb/>1.91 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>3 × 10 4 <lb/>24 <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>http://pubs.acs.org/journal/acsodf <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.4c01585 <lb/>ACS Omega 2024, 9, 21346-21352 <lb/></note>

        <page>21350 <lb/></page>

        <front>Authors <lb/>M. Burcu Balı -Faculty of Science, Department of Physics, <lb/>Gazi University, 06500 Ankara, Turkey; orcid.org/0000-<lb/>0002-3664-0507 <lb/>Semran Sagľam -Faculty of Science, Department of Physics, <lb/>Gazi University, 06500 Ankara, Turkey; orcid.org/0000-<lb/>0002-5837-6540 <lb/>Halil Berberogľu -Physics, Ankara Hacı Bayram Veli <lb/>University, 06570 Ankara, Turkey; orcid.org/0000-0002-<lb/>2435-3631 <lb/>Ihor Pavlov -Department of Physics, Middle East Technical <lb/>University, 06800 Ankara, Turkey; ODTU-GUNAM, Center <lb/>for solar energy research and application, 06800 Ankara, <lb/>Turkey; orcid.org/0000-0001-9494-4149 <lb/>Arian Goodarzi -ODTU-GUNAM, Center for solar energy <lb/>research and application, 06800 Ankara, Turkey; <lb/>orcid.org/0000-0003-0153-3602 <lb/>Complete contact information is available at: <lb/>https://pubs.acs.org/10.1021/acsomega.4c01585 <lb/></front>

        <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This study was funded by the Scientific Research Council of <lb/>Gazi University (BAP) Grant Number FGA-2022-8252. Open <lb/>access is funded by The Anatolian University Libraries <lb/>Consortium (ANKOS) in Turkiye. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Notes <lb/>The authors declare no competing financial interest. <lb/></div>

        <div type="acknowledgment">■ ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>The authors are grateful to Gazi University Scientific Research <lb/>Council (BAP) for the financial support of this research under <lb/>Project Number FGA-2022-8252 (E.O.). <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>■ REFERENCES <lb/>(1) Efil, E.; Kaymak, N.; Seven, E.; Orhan, E. O.; Bayram, O.; Ocak, <lb/>S. B.; Tataroglu, A. Current-voltage analyses of Graphene-based <lb/>structure onto Al 2 O 3 /p-Si using various methods. Vacuum 2020, 181, <lb/>109654. <lb/>(2) Kaymak, N.; Efil, E.; Seven, E.; Tatarogľu, A.; Bilge, S.; Orhan, E. <lb/>O ̈. Electrical characteristics analyses of zinc-oxide based MIS structure <lb/>grown by atomic layer deposition. Materials Research Express 2019, 6 <lb/>(2), 026309. <lb/>(3) Wang, J.; Bi, J.; Xu, Y.; Niu, G.; Liu, M.; Stempitsky, V. Effects of <lb/>charge trapping on memory characteristics for HfO 2 -based ferro-<lb/>electric field effect transistors. Nanomaterials 2023, 13 (4), 638. <lb/>(4) Akay, D.; Seven, E.; Gökmen, U.; Bi ̇lge Ocak, S. Semiconducting <lb/>Double-Layer Lead Monoxide Tin Oxide Nanostructures for <lb/>Photodetectors. ACS Applied Nano Materials 2023, 6 (19), 17482-<lb/>17490. <lb/>(5) Seven, E.; Akay, D.; Ocak, S. B.; Orhan, E. O ̈. Characterization <lb/>of electrical parameters in PbO/SnO2 double layer semiconductor <lb/>(DLS) diodes. Materials Science in Semiconductor Processing 2024, 169, <lb/>107913. <lb/>(6) Turk, Ç. G.; Tan, S. O.; Altındal, S.; I ̇nem, B. Frequency and <lb/>voltage dependence of barrier height, surface states, and series <lb/>resistance in Al/Al 2 O 3 /p-Si structures in wide range frequency and <lb/>voltage. Physica B: Condensed Matter 2020, 582, 411979. <lb/>(7) Yıldırım, M. Characterization of the framework of Cu doped <lb/>TiO 2 layers: An insight into optical, electrical and photodiode <lb/>parameters. J. Alloys Compd. 2019, 773, 890-904. <lb/>(8) Arslan, E.; Buẗun, S.; Ozbay, E. Leakage current by Frenkel-<lb/>Poole emission in Ni/Au schottky contacts on Al 0.83 In 0.17 N/AlN/GaN <lb/>heterostructures. Appl. Phys. Lett. 2009, 94 (14), 142106. <lb/>(9) Yildirim, M.; Kocyigit, A. A Systematıc study on the dıelectrıc <lb/>relaxatıon, electrıc modulus and electrıcal conductıvıty of Al/ <lb/>Cu:TiO2/n-Si (MOS) structures/capacıtors. Surf. Rev. Lett. 2020, <lb/>27 (10), 1950217. <lb/>(10) Aydin, S. B.; Yildiz, D. E.; Çavus, H. K.; Sahingöz, R. ALD TiO 2 <lb/>thin film as dielectric for Al/p-Si Schottky diode. Bulletin of Materials <lb/>Science 2014, 37, 1563-1568. <lb/>(11) Alialy, S.; Altındal, S.; Tanrıkulu, E.; Yıldız, D. E. Analysis of <lb/>temperature dependent current-conduction mechanisms in Au/TiO 2 / <lb/>n-4H-SiC (metal/insulator/semiconductor) type Schottky barrier <lb/>diodes. J. Appl. Phys. 2014, 116 (8), 083709. <lb/>(12) Kınacı, B.; O ̈zcȩlik, S. Analysis of the temperature dependence <lb/>of the capacitance-voltage and conductance-voltage characteristics of <lb/>Au/TiO 2 (rutile)/n-Si structures. Journal of electronic materials 2013, <lb/>42, 1108-1113. <lb/>(13) Pakma, O.; Serin, N.; Serin, T.; Altındal, S. On the energy <lb/>distribution profile of interface states obtained by taking into account <lb/>of series resistance in Al/TiO 2 /p-Si (MIS) structures. Physica B: <lb/>Condensed Matter 2011, 406 (4), 771-776. <lb/>(14) Bengi, A.; Aydemir, U.; Altındal, S.; O ̈zen, Y.; O ̈zcȩlik, S. A. <lb/>comparative study on the electrical characteristics of Au/n-Si <lb/>structures with anatase and rutile phase TiO 2 interfacial insulator <lb/>layer. J. Alloys Compd. 2010, 505 (2), 628-633. <lb/>(15) Bonkerud, J.; Zimmermann, C.; Weiser, P. M.; Aarholt, T.; <lb/>Verhoeven, E. F.; Vines, L.; Monakhov, E. V.; Herklotz, F. Fabrication <lb/>and characterization of Schottky barrier diodes on rutile TiO 2 . <lb/>Materials Research Express 2020, 7 (6), 065903. <lb/>(16) Seven, E.; Orhan, E. O ̈.; Di Bartolomeo, A.; Ertugřul, M.; <lb/>Tasţekin, N. A. Graphene/Al 2 O 3 /Si Schottky diode with integrated <lb/>waveguide on a silicon-on-insulator wafer. Indian Journal of Physics <lb/>2024, DOI: 10.1007/s12648-023-03062-7. <lb/>(17) Candan, I ̇.; O ̈zen, Y. Comparison of TiO 2 and ZnO electron <lb/>selective layers on the inverted-type polymer solar cells. Polym. Bull. <lb/>2021, 78, 3117-3129. <lb/>(18) Aydin, S. B.; Yildiz, D. E.; Çavus, H. K.; Sahingöz, R. ALD TiO 2 <lb/>thin film as dielectric for Al/p-Si Schottky diode. Bulletin of Materials <lb/>Science 2014, 37, 1563-1568. <lb/>(19) Sevgili, O ̈. Termal Buharlasţırma Yontemiyle Hazırlanan Al/ <lb/>TiO 2 /p-Si Schottky Diyotun Elektriksel O ̈zelliklerinin Sıcaklık ve <lb/>Aydınlanma Siddetine Bagľı I ̇ncelenmesi. Turk Dogǎ ve Fen Dergisi <lb/>2021, 10 (1), 275-283. <lb/>(20) Karabulut, A.; Orak, I ̇.; Turuẗ, A. The photovoltaic impact of <lb/>atomic layer deposited TiO 2 interfacial layer on Si-based photodiodes. <lb/>Solid-State Electron. 2018, 144, 39-48. <lb/>(21) Ruzgar, S. The Optoelectrical Properties of Li: TiO 2 /p-Si <lb/>Photodiodes for Various Li Doping. physica status solidi (a) 2020, 217 <lb/>(23), 2000481. <lb/>(22) Erdal, M. O.; Kocyigit, A.; Yıldırım, M. Temperature <lb/>dependent current-voltage characteristics of Al/TiO 2 /n-Si and Al/ <lb/>Cu: TiO 2 /n-Si devices. Materials Science in Semiconductor Processing <lb/>2019, 103, 104620. <lb/>(23) Yıldız, D. E.; Kocyigit, A.; Yıldırım, M. Comparison of Al/ <lb/>TiO 2 /p-Si and Al/ZnO/p-Si photodetectors. Opt. Mater. 2023, 145, <lb/>114371. <lb/>(24) Boutelala, A.; Bourfa, F.; Mahtali, M. Effect of light on electrical <lb/>and photoelectrical characteristics of Al/TiO 2 /p-Si Schottky diode. <lb/>Journal of Materials Science: Materials in Electronics 2020, 31 (14), <lb/>11379-11389. <lb/>(25) Gao, Y.; Xu, J.; Shi, S.; Dong, H.; Cheng, Y.; Wei, C.; Zhang, <lb/>X.; Yin, S.; Li, L. TiO 2 nanorod arrays based self-powered UV <lb/>photodetector: heterojunction with NiO nanoflakes and enhanced <lb/>UV photoresponse. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2018, 10 (13), <lb/>11269-11279. <lb/>(26) Nicolaescu, M.; Bandas, C.; Orha, C.; Sȩrban, V.; Lazaǔ, C.; <lb/>Caprařescu, S. Fabrication of a UV photodetector based on n-TiO 2 /p-<lb/>CuMnO 2 heterostructures. Coatings 2021, 11 (11), 1380. <lb/>(27) Orak, I.; Kocyigit, A.; Turut, A. The surface morphology <lb/>properties and respond illumination impact of ZnO/n-Si photodiode <lb/>by prepared atomic layer deposition technique. J. Alloys Compd. 2017, <lb/>691, 873-879. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>http://pubs.acs.org/journal/acsodf <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.4c01585 <lb/>ACS Omega 2024, 9, 21346-21352 <lb/></note>

        <page>21351 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>(28) Yıldırım, M.; Kocyigit, A. Characterization of Al/In: ZnO/p-Si <lb/>photodiodes for various In doped level to ZnO interfacial layers. J. <lb/>Alloys Compd. 2018, 768, 1064-1075. <lb/>(29) Erdal, M. O.; Yıldırım, M.; Kocyigit, A. A comparison of the <lb/>electrical characteristics of TiO 2 /p-Si/Ag, GNR-TiO 2 /p-Si/Ag and <lb/>MWCNT-TiO 2 /p-Si/Ag photodiodes. Journal of Materials Science: <lb/>Materials in Electronics 2019, 30, 13617-13626. <lb/>(30) Banerjee, D.; Asuo, I. M.; Pignolet, A.; Cloutier, S. G. Low-cost <lb/>photodetector architectures fabricated at room-temperature using <lb/>nano-engineered silicon wafer and sol-gel TiO 2 -based heterostruc-<lb/>tures. Sci. Rep. 2019, 9 (1), 17994. <lb/>(31) Chatzigiannakis, G.; Jaros, A.; Leturcq, R.; Jungclaus, J.; Voss, <lb/>T.; Gardelis, S.; Kandyla, M. Laser-microstructured ZnO/p-Si <lb/>photodetector with enhanced and broadband responsivity across the <lb/>ultraviolet-visible-near-infrared range. ACS Applied Electronic Materials <lb/>2020, 2 (9), 2819-2828. <lb/>(32) Orhan, E. O.; Efil, E.; Bayram, O.; Kaymak, N.; Berberogľu, H.; <lb/>Candemir, O.; Pavlov, I.; Ocak, S. B. 3D-graphene-laser patterned p-<lb/>type silicon Schottky diode. Materials Science in Semiconductor <lb/>Processing 2021, 121, 105454. <lb/>(33) Bilge Ocak, S.; Selcuk, A. B.; Aras, G.; Orhan, E. Electrical <lb/>analysis of Al/ZnO/p-Si, Al/PMMA/p-Si and Al/PMMA/ZnO/p-Si <lb/>structures: comparison study. Materials Science in Semiconductor <lb/>Processing 2015, 38, 249-256. <lb/>(34) Sze, S. M.; Li, Y.; Ng, K. K. Physics of semiconductor devices; <lb/>John Wiley &amp; Sons: 2021. <lb/>(35) Cai, X.; Zhang, P.; Wei, S.-H. Revisit of the band gaps of rutile <lb/>SnO 2 and TiO 2 : A first-principles study. Journal of Semiconductors <lb/>2019, 40 (9), 092101. <lb/>(36) Gullu, H. H.; Yildiz, D. E. Capacitance, conductance, and <lb/>dielectric characteristics of Al/TiO 2 /Si diode. J. Mater. Sci: Mater. <lb/>Electron 2021, 32, 13549-1356. <lb/>(37) Wang, Z. L. Zinc oxide nanostructures: growth, properties and <lb/>applications. J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 2004, 16 (25), R829. <lb/>(38) Cheung, S.; Cheung, N. Extraction of Schottky diode <lb/>parameters from forward current-voltage characteristics. Applied <lb/>physics letters 1986, 49, 85-87. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>http://pubs.acs.org/journal/acsodf <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.4c01585 <lb/>ACS Omega 2024, 9, 21346-21352 <lb/></note>

        <page>21352 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>