<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Do current maternal health staffing and bed occupancy benchmarks work in practice? Results from a simulation model</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Rebecca F</forename>
            <surname>Baggaley</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Giorgia</forename>
            <surname>Gon</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Said</forename>
            <surname>Mohammed Ali</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Salma</forename>
            <surname>Abdi Mahmoud</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Farhat</forename>
            <surname>Jowhar</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Carolin</forename>
            <surname>Vegvari</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-29T10:43:27.046221Z">29.10.2025 10:43:27</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1136$1$bmjph-2023-000212</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>BMJ</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjph-2023-000212</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Rebecca F Baggaley, Giorgia Gon, Said Mohammed Ali, Salma Abdi Mahmoud, Farhat Jowhar, Carolin Vegvari. (2024). Do current maternal health staffing and bed occupancy benchmarks work in practice? Results from a simulation model. BMJ Public Health, 2(1), e000212. DOI: 10.1136/bmjph-2023-000212</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T10:43:27.046221Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-29T10:43:27.046221Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>1 <lb/>Sakai R, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Increased risk of cardiovascular events <lb/>under the treatments with Janus kinase <lb/>inhibitors versus biological disease-<lb/>modifying antirheumatic drugs in <lb/>patients with rheumatoid arthritis: a <lb/>retrospective longitudinal population-<lb/>based study using the Japanese health <lb/>insurance database <lb/>Ryoko Sakai <lb/>, 1,2 Eiichi Tanaka, 2,3 Eisuke Inoue, 4 Masayoshi Harigai <lb/>2,3 <lb/>To cite: Sakai R, Tanaka E, <lb/>Inoue E, et al. Increased risk <lb/>of cardiovascular events <lb/>under the treatments with <lb/>Janus kinase inhibitors versus <lb/>biological disease-modifying <lb/>antirheumatic drugs in patients <lb/>with rheumatoid arthritis: a <lb/>retrospective longitudinal <lb/>population-based study <lb/>using the Japanese health <lb/>insurance database. RMD Open <lb/>2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/ <lb/>rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/>► Additional supplemental <lb/>material is published online only. <lb/>To view, please visit the journal <lb/>online (https:// doi. org/ 10. 1136/ <lb/>rmdopen-2023-003885). <lb/>Received 18 December 2023 <lb/>Accepted 31 May 2024 <lb/>For numbered affiliations see <lb/>end of article. <lb/>Correspondence to <lb/>Dr Masayoshi Harigai; <lb/>harigai. masayoshi@ twmu. ac. jp <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>© Author(s) (or their <lb/>employer(s)) 2024. Re-use <lb/>permitted under CC BY-NC. No <lb/>commercial re-use. See rights <lb/>and permissions. Published <lb/>by BMJ. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Objectives To compare the risk of cardiovascular events <lb/>among Janus kinase inhibitors (JAKIs), biological disease-<lb/>modifying antirheumatic drugs (bDMARDs) (tumour necrosis <lb/>factor inhibitors (TNFIs) and non-TNFIs) and methotrexate <lb/>(MTX) in Japanese patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA). <lb/>Methods Using Japanese claims data, patients with RA <lb/>were enrolled in this study if they had at least one ICD-10 <lb/>code (M05 or M06), were new users of JAKIs, bDMARDs or <lb/>MTX between July 2013 and July 2020 and being 18 years <lb/>old or older. The incidence rate (IR), IR ratio and adjusted <lb/>hazard ratio (aHR (95% CI)) of cardiovascular events <lb/>including venous thromboembolism, arterial thrombosis, <lb/>acute myocardial infarction and stroke were calculated. A <lb/>time-dependent Cox regression model adjusted for patient <lb/>characteristics at baseline was used to calculate aHR. <lb/>Results In 53 448 cases, IRs/1000 patient-years of the <lb/>overall cardiovascular events were 10.1, 6.8, 5.4, 9.1 and <lb/>11.3 under the treatments with JAKIs, bDMARDs, TNFIs, <lb/>non-TNFIs and MTX, respectively. The adjusted HRs of JAKIs <lb/>for overall cardiovascular events were 1.7 (1.1 to 2.5) versus <lb/>TNFIs without MTX and 1.7 (1.1 to 2.7) versus TNFIs with <lb/>MTX. <lb/>Conclusions Among patients with RA, individuals <lb/>using JAKIs had a significantly higher risk of overall <lb/>cardiovascular events than TNFIs users, which was <lb/>attributed to the difference in the risk between JAKIs and <lb/>TNFIs versus MTX. These data should be interpreted with <lb/>caution because of the limitations associated with the <lb/>claims database. <lb/></front>
        
        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Many medications for rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>(RA) have become available over the past <lb/>20 years and have enabled better control of <lb/>disease activity in large number of patients. 1 <lb/>Of these, Janus kinase inhibitors (JAKIs) are <lb/>new treatment options, 2 3 and five agents have <lb/>been approved for RA in Japan (tofacitinib <lb/>was approved in 2013, baricitinib in 2017, <lb/>peficitinib in 2019 and filgotinib and upad-<lb/>acitinib in 2020). Clinical trials and observa-<lb/>tional studies have shown clinical efficacy and <lb/>effectiveness in patients with RA, whereas, <lb/>concerns about safety has increased. 4 Current <lb/></body>
        
        <front>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC <lb/>⇒ In patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA), reports <lb/>of the association between Janus kinase inhibitors <lb/>(JAKIs) and the risk of cardiovascular events has not <lb/>been consistent. <lb/>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS <lb/>⇒ This study showed a significantly higher risk of <lb/>overall cardiovascular events in JAKIs users than <lb/>in tumour necrosis factor inhibitors (TNFIs) users <lb/>irrespective of concomitant MTX, and a significantly <lb/>lower risk in TNFIs users than in MTX users using a <lb/>large Japanese claims database. <lb/>⇒ JAKIs users without MTX also showed a significant-<lb/>ly higher cardiovascular risk than non-TNFIs users <lb/>without MTX. <lb/>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, <lb/>PRACTICE, OR POLICY <lb/>⇒ The results of this study suggest the need for ap-<lb/>propriate risk management of cardiovascular events <lb/>among patients with RA, especially, those treated <lb/>with JAKIs. <lb/></front>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 on 17 June 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
        
        <page>2 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Sakai R, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>
        
        <body>clinical practice guidelines of the Japan College of Rheu-<lb/>matology 5 and recommendations from the European <lb/>Alliance for Associations for Rheumatology 6 call for a <lb/>careful approach to the use of JAKIs. <lb/>Among safety issues under the treatment of JAKIs, <lb/>the risk of cardiovascular events such as venous throm-<lb/>boembolism (VTE), arterial thromboembolism (ATE), <lb/>acute myocardial infarction (AMI) and stroke is clini-<lb/>cally important. It has been reported that patients with <lb/>RA have a 60%-140% increased risk of VTE compared <lb/>with the general population, 7-9 and the incidence rate <lb/>(IR) of VTE in patients treated with biological disease-<lb/>modifying antirheumatic drugs (bDMARDs) or conven-<lb/>tional synthetic DMARDs is estimated to be 0.4-0.8/100 <lb/>patient-years (PYs). 10 11 Additionally, patients with RA <lb/>have a higher risk of ATE, AMI and stroke than that of <lb/>the general population. 12 13 A meta-analysis showed that <lb/>use of TNFI reduced the risk of myocardial infarction <lb/>(pooled adjusted relative risk 0.81 (0.68 to 0.96)) and <lb/>cerebrovascular accident (RR: 0.69 (0.53 to 0.89)). 14 <lb/>German cohort study revealed that better physical func-<lb/>tion decreased the risk of stroke significantly (adjusted <lb/>HR: 0.9 (0.8 to 0.96), 15 indicating better disease control <lb/>by biologics could lead to lower risk of stroke. To opti-<lb/>mise the treatment of RA, it is necessary to determine <lb/>the differences in the risk of these cardiovascular events <lb/>in patients with RA receiving different categories of <lb/>DMARDs. <lb/>The association between JAKIs and cardiovascular <lb/>events requires further investigation. A case report and <lb/>review of the literature of JAKIs showed a numerically <lb/>higher IR of VTE than placebo 16 ; however, a meta-analyses <lb/>of randomised clinical trials did not show significantly <lb/>elevated risks of VTE, pulmonary embolism (PE) and <lb/>deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in patients with autoim-<lb/>mune diseases who were treated with JAKI. 17 A review <lb/>of observational studies have also shown similar risks of <lb/>major adverse cardiovascular events (MACEs) and VTE <lb/>between bDMARDs and JAKIs, 18 except for one study on <lb/>VTE. 19 However, tofacitinib did not show non-inferiority <lb/>to tumour necrosis factor inhibitors (TNFIs) in MACE <lb/>and malignancy in the ORAL Surveillance, a controlled, <lb/>prospective, clinical trial, 20 and safety warnings from the <lb/>US Food and Drug Administration, 21 and the European <lb/>Medicines Agency 22 also were announced. The Pharma-<lb/>ceuticals and Medical Devices Agency in Japan updated <lb/>the package inserts of all JAKIs, despite the small propor-<lb/>tion of Asian patients enrolled in the ORAL Surveillance. <lb/>Ethnic differences in the risk of cardiovascular events <lb/>have been reported, with Japanese patients with RA <lb/>having a lower risk of cardiovascular events than those <lb/>in Western countries. 23 Therefore, it is essential to clarify <lb/>the risk of cardiovascular events in Japanese patients <lb/>undergoing treatment with JAKI in the clinical setting. <lb/>Investigating rare cardiovascular events during treat-<lb/>ment of RA with a particular drug or a class of drugs <lb/>requires a large number of patients, which can be imple-<lb/>mented by a large randomised controlled trial or by <lb/>using a large registry of the disease or a claims database. <lb/>A claims database usually contains a larger number of <lb/>patients than the others, but major drawbacks are it has <lb/>no or does not have enough information about previ-<lb/>ously reported risk factors such as body mass index, <lb/>smoking status, disease activity of RA and history and <lb/>family history of cardiovascular disease. <lb/>This study aimed to estimate and compare the risk <lb/>of new cardiovascular events among patients with RA <lb/>treated with JAKIs, bDMARDs (ie, TNFIs or non-TNFIs) <lb/>and methotrexate (MTX) using a large Japanese health <lb/>insurance database. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Data source <lb/>This retrospective, longitudinal, population-based study <lb/>was conducted using nationwide hospital-based claims <lb/>data provided by Medical Data Vision (MDV) Co (Tokyo, <lb/>Japan). Previous studies have used the MDV database. 24 <lb/>Briefly, the MDV database covers 37.4 million patients <lb/>from more than 450 hospitals that participate in the <lb/>Diagnostic Procedure Combination/per diem payment <lb/>system (DPC/PDPS) in Japan (as of July 2021), which <lb/>corresponds to 26% of the hospitals that participate in <lb/>the DPC/PDPS. The data in the MDV database included <lb/>patient age, sex, diagnoses, drug prescriptions, medical <lb/>procedures and reimbursement costs for inpatients and <lb/>outpatients. No personal identifiable information such as <lb/>patient name, residence, employment or economic status <lb/>was included in the MDV database. In addition, linkage <lb/>of databases with other databases or patient medical <lb/>records has not been allowed in Japan to date. <lb/>Study population <lb/>This study included new users of JAKIs, bDMARDs and <lb/>MTX users. We defined the patients who met all the <lb/>following criteria as new users: (1) having at least one <lb/>ICD-10 code for RA (M05 or M06); (2) having at least <lb/>one prescription of JAKI (tofacitinib, baricitinib, pefi-<lb/>citinib, upadacitinib or filgotinib), bDMARDs (listed <lb/>in online supplemental table 1) or oral MTX between <lb/>July 2013 and July 2020 (subcutaneous (sc) MTX was <lb/>not yet approved in Japan during these calendar years); <lb/>(3) being 18 years old or over; and (4) having prescrip-<lb/>tion of neither JAKIs, bDMARDs or MTX in 6 months <lb/>prior to the index month for MTX new users; having no <lb/>prescription of bDMARDs irrespective of MTX or JAKIs <lb/>in 6 months prior to the index month for bDMARDs new <lb/>users; having no prescription of JAKIs irrespective of <lb/>MTX or bDMARDs for JAKIs new users. The index month <lb/>was defined as the first month in which patients met all <lb/>the above criteria: (1), (2) and (3). To identify new cardi-<lb/>ovascular events, patients were excluded from the study <lb/>if they had a diagnosis of cardiovascular events 6 months <lb/>prior to the index month. The definitions of cardiovas-<lb/>cular events are described in the &apos;Definition of cardio-<lb/>vascular events&apos; section. If MTX+JAKI or MTX+bDMARD <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 on 17 June 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
        
        <page>3 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Sakai R, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/></note>
        
        <body>was prescribed in the index month, the patient was classi-<lb/>fied as a new JAKI or bDMARD user. <lb/>Follow-up <lb/>Patients were followed-up from the index month until <lb/>the last exposure to JAKIs, bDMARDs, MTX, date of loss <lb/>to follow-up or the end of follow-up (July 2021), which-<lb/>ever came first. The last day of exposure to MTX, JAKI or <lb/>bDMARDs for sc injection was defined as the last day of <lb/>prescription of these drugs plus supply days and 30 days <lb/>as a grace period. The last day of exposure to bDMARDs <lb/>for intravenous injection was defined as the last day of <lb/>bDMARD prescription plus the interval in days of each <lb/>agent. 25 The observation was continued even after <lb/>changing the drugs to JAKIs or bDMARDs. We imple-<lb/>mented an on-drug analysis of the events, considering <lb/>that the patients were censored at the end of exposure <lb/>to MTX, bDMARDs or JAKIs, with or without a 30-day <lb/>grace period, as described above (online supplemental <lb/>figure 1). <lb/>Definition of cardiovascular events <lb/>Cardiovascular events, including VTE, DVT, PE, arterial <lb/>thrombosis, AMI and stroke, were defined as instances <lb/>where at least one ICD-10 code and medication or medical <lb/>practice for each disease were recorded during hospital-<lb/>isation (online supplemental table 2), considering the <lb/>clinical setting in Japan. Cardiovascular death, typically <lb/>included in MACE, was not defined as an outcome in this <lb/>study because it was impossible to define it accurately, due <lb/>to a lack of data regarding the certification of death and <lb/>clinical information. In this study, we performed on-drug <lb/>analysis (online supplemental figure 1). If a cardiovas-<lb/>cular event developed during MTX, bDMARD or JAKI <lb/>monotherapy, it was attributed to the respective drug. If a <lb/>cardiovascular event occurred during MTX+bDMARD or <lb/>MTX+JAKI treatment, it was attributed to bDMARD or <lb/>JAKI. None of the patients received JAKI or bDMARD <lb/>simultaneously. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>We described the patients&apos; comorbidities reported <lb/>6 months before the index month (baseline period). <lb/>Diabetes mellitus (DM), hypertension (HT), dyslipi-<lb/>daemia (DL), antiphospholipid syndrome (APS) and <lb/>atrial fibrillation (AF) were defined by having at least <lb/>one ICD-10 code and at least one prescription for each <lb/>disease (online supplemental table 3). Malignancy was <lb/>defined using ICD-10 codes (C.x, D.x except for D10.x--<lb/>D36.x (benign tumour)) and medical procedures <lb/>(chemotherapy, surgery and radiation) for malignancy <lb/>or cancer management. Hip fracture was defined as the <lb/>presence of ICD-10 code S72.x and surgery for hip frac-<lb/>ture with hospitalisation. Chronic kidney disease (CKD), <lb/>congestive heart failure and liver disease were defined <lb/>using ICD-10 codes according to a previous report. 26 A <lb/>history of hormone replacement treatment was defined <lb/>as at least one prescription of oestrogen, progestogen or <lb/>these compounds during the baseline period. Age, sex <lb/>and medications for RA were defined as index months. <lb/>Body mass index, smoking status, disease activity of RA, <lb/>and family history of cardiovascular disease were not <lb/>included in the database. <lb/>Descriptive patient characteristics at baseline, such as <lb/>age, sex, comorbidities and RA medications, were anal-<lb/>ysed for the new users of each medication. The IR per <lb/>1000 patient-years (PY) and crude IR ratio (IRR) (JAKIs <lb/>vs bDMARDs, JAKIs vs TNFIs, JAKIs vs non-TNFIs (inter-<lb/>leukin-6 (IL-6) inhibitors and abatacept (ABT)) and <lb/>JAKIs vs MTX) of cardiovascular events were calculated. <lb/>Time-dependent Cox regression models were employed <lb/>to calculate the HRs of JAKIs versus bDMARDs, JAKIs <lb/>versus MTX, bDMARDs versus MTX after adjusting for <lb/>age, sex, comorbidities including HT, DM, DL, APS, <lb/>liver disease, CKD, AF and CHF as baseline covariates, <lb/>and JAKI use, bDMARD use, MTX use, history of malig-<lb/>nancy, prescription of hormone replacement treatment, <lb/>NSAIDs use and categorical doses of oral glucocorti-<lb/>coids (GCs, prednisolone-equivalent dose) (0 mg/day, <lb/>0&lt;GC≤5 mg/day, 5&lt;GC≤10 mg/day, GC&gt;10 mg/day) as <lb/>time-dependent covariates. We calculated adjusted HRs <lb/>of JAKIs (vs TNFIs, non-TNFIs and MTX), TNFIs (vs <lb/>MTX), non-TNFIs (vs MTX) with or without MTX sepa-<lb/>rately. We also calculated adjusted HRs of venous events <lb/>(VTE) and arterial events (ATEA, AMI and stroke) sepa-<lb/>rately. Analysis were performed using R V.4.1. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Study population <lb/>The number of the study population was 53 448 and <lb/>that of JAKIs, bDMARDs and MTX new users were <lb/>4416, 20 964 and 37 926, respectively (figure 1). Table 1 <lb/>presents the baseline patient characteristics. The median <lb/>(interquartile) and mean±SD observation period were <lb/>26 (12-43), 31.7±24.9 months in JAKIs new users, 31 <lb/>(15-57), 39.1±30.4 months for bDMARD new users and <lb/>24 (6-51), 33.4±31.0 months for MTX new users. The <lb/>median age was late 60s and the most frequent comor-<lb/>bidity in all three groups was HT, followed by DL. Among <lb/>JAKI new users, most patients started baricitinib (45.9%) <lb/>or tofacitinib (43.1%). Among the bDMARDs new users, <lb/>58.8% started a TNF inhibitor and the remaining patients <lb/>started a non-TNF inhibitor. Among the patients who <lb/>started a non-TNF inhibitor, approximately half started <lb/>tocilizumab treatment. <lb/>Occurrence of cardiovascular events <lb/>The IRs (per 1000 PY) with a 95% CI of the total and <lb/>each cardiovascular event by medication are shown in <lb/>table 2. The IR of total cardiovascular events was 10.1 <lb/>(7.9 to 12.9) for JAKIs, 6.8 (6.2 to 7.5) for bDMARDs <lb/>and 11.3 (10.6 to 12.0) for MTX. When bDMARDs were <lb/>divided into TNFIs and non-TNFIs, the IR of total cardio-<lb/>vascular events was 5.4 (4.7 to 6.1) for TNFIs and 9.1 (8.0 <lb/>to 10.3) for non-TNFIs. VTE accounted for the majority <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 on 17 June 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
        
        <page>4 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Sakai R, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>
        
        <body>of cardiovascular events, except in MTX users. The IRR <lb/>(95% CI) for total cardiovascular events comparing to <lb/>JAKIs with TNFIs was elevated (1.9 (1.4 to 2.5)), whereas <lb/>the IRRs comparing JAKIs with non-TNFIs or MTX were <lb/>not (1.1 (0.9 to 1.5), 0.9 (0.7 to 1.2)) (table 3). <lb/>Comparison of the risk of total cardiovascular events among <lb/>therapies <lb/>In a time-dependent Cox regression model, JAKIs with <lb/>and without MTX showed a significantly higher risk for <lb/>overall cardiovascular events compared with TNFIs with <lb/>(1.7 (1.1 to 2.7)) and without MTX (1.7 (1.1 to 2.5)), <lb/>respectively. HR for JAKIs without MTX versus non-TNFIs <lb/>without MTX was also significantly elevated (1.7 (1.1 to <lb/>2.5)), but HR for JAKIs with MTX versus non-TNFIs with <lb/>MTX was not (1.0 (0.6 to 1.5)) (table 4, online supple-<lb/>mental figure 2). When venous events (VTE) and arterial <lb/>events (ATE, AMI and stroke) were separately analysed, <lb/>JAKIs with and without MTX had a significantly higher <lb/>risk of venous events than TNFIs with and without MTX, <lb/>respectively, but did not for that of arterial events. JAKIs <lb/>without MTX showed a significantly higher risk of venous <lb/>events than non-TNFIs without MTX as well, but not that <lb/>of arterial events (online supplemental table 4 and 5). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Using a large claims database, this study demonstrated <lb/>incidence rates of cardiovascular events in patients with <lb/>RA using MTX, JAKIs, bDMARDs, TNFIs, non-TNFIs in <lb/>the real world, and that (1) JAKIs+/-MTX were asso-<lb/>ciated with an increased risk of cardiovascular events <lb/>versus TNFIs+/-MTX, which derived from numeri-<lb/>cally increased risk of JAKIs+/-MTX versus MTX and <lb/>Figure 1 Patients selection flowchart. Figure shows the selection process of the study population. *Prescription of either <lb/>JAKIs, bDMARDs nor MTX 6 months prior to the index month for MTX new users; no prescription of bDMARDs irrespective <lb/>of MTX or JAKIs 6 months prior to the index month for bDMARDs new users; no prescription of JAKIs irrespective of MTX <lb/>or bDMARDs for new users of JAKIs. bDMARDs, biological disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs; JAKIs, Janus kinase <lb/>inhibitors; MTX, methotrexate; RA, rheumatoid arthritis. <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 on 17 June 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
        
        <page>5 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Sakai R, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/></note>
        
        <body>Table 1 Patients&apos; characteristics at baseline <lb/>JAKIs, new <lb/>user (n=4416) <lb/>bDMARDs, <lb/>new user <lb/>(n=20 964) <lb/>MTX, <lb/>new user <lb/>(n=37 926) <lb/>Median age (IQR) <lb/>68 (56, 76) <lb/>66 (54, 75) <lb/>67 (57, 75) <lb/>Mean age±SD <lb/>65.3±13.6 <lb/>63.4±15.0 <lb/>65.2±13.7 <lb/>Female, % <lb/>77.3 <lb/>74.9 <lb/>72.4 <lb/>Comorbidity,* % <lb/>Hypertension <lb/>20.8 <lb/>19.0 <lb/>16.3 <lb/>Diabetes mellitus <lb/>7.6 <lb/>8.4 <lb/>7.1 <lb/>Dyslipidaemia <lb/>14.9 <lb/>12.2 <lb/>10.8 <lb/>Chronic heart failure <lb/>9.8 <lb/>9.4 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>Atrial fibrillation <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>Liver disease <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Chronic kidney disease <lb/>3.9 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>Antiphospholipid <lb/>syndrome <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>History of malignancy <lb/>4.4 <lb/>4.9 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>History of hip fracture <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>History of hormone <lb/>replacement treatment † <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>Mediations for RA ‡, % <lb/>csDMARDs <lb/>MTX <lb/>70.1 <lb/>67.6 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Salazosulfapyridine <lb/>11.1 <lb/>11.0 <lb/>16.1 <lb/>Bucillamine <lb/>4.6 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>6.6 <lb/>Iguratimod <lb/>4.3 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>4.1 <lb/>Tacrolimus <lb/>4.9 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>bDMARDs <lb/>6.7 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>8.9 <lb/>TNFIs <lb/>3.4 <lb/>58.8 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>Infliximab <lb/>0.3 <lb/>8.1 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>Etanercept <lb/>0.8 <lb/>19.8 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>Adalimumab <lb/>0.4 <lb/>11.7 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>Golimumab <lb/>1.1 <lb/>15.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Certolizumab pegol <lb/>0.7 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Non-TNFIs <lb/>3.3 <lb/>41.2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>Tocilizumab <lb/>2.0 <lb/>20.2 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>Sarilumab <lb/>0.4 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>Abatacept <lb/>1.0 <lb/>19.6 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>JAKIs <lb/>100.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Tofacitinib <lb/>43.1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>Baricitinib <lb/>45.9 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>Peficitinib <lb/>6.2 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>Upadacitinib <lb/>4.8 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>Filgotinib <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Oral GCs <lb/>33.9 <lb/>30.1 <lb/>45.6 <lb/>NSAIDs <lb/>46.3 <lb/>44.6 <lb/>46.8 <lb/>*Comorbidity was defined 6 months before the index month. <lb/> †Hormone replacement treatment includes oestrogen, progestogen and these <lb/>compounds. <lb/> ‡Uses of JAKIs in JAKI new users, bDMARDs in bDMARD new users and MTX in <lb/>MTX new users were defined in the index month of each patient. The use of other <lb/>medications for RA was defined as 6 months prior to the index month. <lb/>.bDMARDs, biological disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs; csDMARDs, <lb/>conventional synthetic disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs; JAKIs, Janus kinase <lb/>inhibitors; MTX, methotrexate; RA, rheumatoid arthritis; TNFIs, tumour necrosis <lb/>inhibitors. <lb/>Table 2 IR of cardiovascular events per 1000 patient-years <lb/>JAKIs <lb/>bDMARDs <lb/>TNFIs <lb/>Non-TNFIs <lb/>MTX <lb/>N <lb/>IR <lb/>N <lb/>IR <lb/>N <lb/>IR <lb/>N <lb/>IR <lb/>N <lb/>IR <lb/>Total* <lb/>63 <lb/>10.12 (7.85 to 12.86) <lb/>449 <lb/>6.81 (6.20 to 7.46) <lb/>208 <lb/>5.36 (4.67 to 6.13) <lb/>246 <lb/>9.07 (7.99 to 10.26) <lb/>994 <lb/>11.29 (10.61 to <lb/>12.01) <lb/>VTE † <lb/>43 <lb/>6.91 (5.07 to 9.21) <lb/>267 <lb/>4.05 (3.59 to 4.56) <lb/>129 <lb/>3.32 (2.79 to 3.94) <lb/>141 <lb/>5.20 (4.39 to 6.11) <lb/>480 <lb/>5.45 (4.98 to 5.96) <lb/>DVT <lb/>36 <lb/>5.78 (4.11 to 7.92) <lb/>223 <lb/>3.38 (2.96 to 3.84) <lb/>107 <lb/>2.76 (2.27 to 3.32) <lb/>118 <lb/>4.35 (3.62 to 5.19) <lb/>418 <lb/>4.75 (4.31 to 5.22) <lb/>PE <lb/>7 <lb/>1.12 (0.50 to 2.21) <lb/>56 <lb/>0.85 (0.65 to 1.09) <lb/>27 <lb/>0.70 (0.47 to 1.00) <lb/>30 <lb/>1.11 (0.76 to 1.56) <lb/>87 <lb/>0.99 (0.80 to 1.21) <lb/>ATE <lb/>7 <lb/>1.12 (0.50 to 2.21) <lb/>44 <lb/>0.67 (0.49 to 0.89) <lb/>18 <lb/>0.46 (0.28 to 0.72) <lb/>27 <lb/>1.00 (0.67 to 1.43) <lb/>93 <lb/>1.06 (0.86 to 1.29) <lb/>AMI <lb/>6 <lb/>0.96 (0.40 to 1.99) <lb/>46 <lb/>0.70 (0.52 to 0.92) <lb/>28 <lb/>0.72 (0.49 to 1.03) <lb/>19 <lb/>0.70 (0.44 to 1.07) <lb/>135 <lb/>1.53 (1.29 to 1.81) <lb/>Stroke <lb/>7 <lb/>1.12 (0.50 to 2.21) <lb/>80 <lb/>1.21 (0.97 to 1.50) <lb/>28 <lb/>0.72 (0.49 to 1.03) <lb/>52 <lb/>1.92 (1.45 to 2.49) <lb/>261 <lb/>2.96 (2.62 to 3.34) <lb/>Data are presented as IR (95% CI). <lb/>N indicates the number of the event. <lb/>*The total number of events was the sum of DVT, PE, ATE, AMI and stroke. <lb/> †Number of VTE is not equal to the sum of DVT and PE. When a patient developed both diseases, only one event was considered DVT. <lb/>AMI, acute myocardial infarction; ATE, arterial thromboembolism; bDMARDs, biological disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs; DVT, deep vein thrombosis; IR, incidence rate; JAKIs, Janus <lb/>kinase inhibitors; MTX, methotrexate; TNFIs, tumour necrosis inhibitor; PE, pulmonary embolism; VTE, venous thromboembolism. <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 on 17 June 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
        
        <page>6 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Sakai R, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>
        
        <body>significantly decreased risk of TNFIs+/-MTX versus <lb/>MTX; and (2) similar relationships were observed when <lb/>JAKIs without MTX, non-TNFIs without MTX, and MTX <lb/>were compared. <lb/>In this study, the IR of DVT (0.6/100PY), PE <lb/>(0.1/100PY) or ATE (0.1/100PY) in patients treated with <lb/>JAKIs was similar to the results of previous studies, 27 28 <lb/>although this study population was relatively older than <lb/>previous studies from western countries. 19 29 In patients <lb/>with RA treated with 5 mg or 10 mg of tofacitinib, the IRs <lb/>(95% CI) of DVT and PE were 0.2/100 PYs (0.1 to 0.3) <lb/>and 0.1/100 PYs (0.1 to 0.2) for both doses, and those <lb/>of ATE were 0.3/100 PYs (0.2 to 0.5) for 5 mg twice a day <lb/>and 0.4/100 PYs (0.3 to 0.5) for 10 mg twice a day. 28 In <lb/>the placebo-controlled period of a clinical trial of baric-<lb/>itinib, five DVT/PE cases, including two serious cases, <lb/>were reported in the 4 mg baricitinib group and none <lb/>in the placebo group. 30 The incidence rates of overall <lb/>and serious DVT/PE were 0.5 and 0.3 per 100 PYs in <lb/>the combined dataset of the clinical trials and long-term <lb/>extension study of baricitinib, respectively. 31 In addition, <lb/>in phase II and III clinical trials of baricitinib in Japanese <lb/>patients with RA, the incidence of DVT/PE was 0.5 per <lb/>100 PY. 27 An observational study of tofacitinib in Canada <lb/>reported an IR for VTE of 0.3/100 PY. 32 In this study, <lb/>more than half of events were VTE (table 2). This can be <lb/>explained by recent increase of VTE risk in Asian coun-<lb/>tries including Japan. Although the incidence rates of <lb/>VTE are supposed to be lower in Asian population than <lb/>others, 33 VTE is becoming more common in Asian coun-<lb/>tries including Japan. 34 In addition, recently direct oral <lb/>anticoagulants have been used commonly. These results <lb/>and recent management strategies for DVT indicate that <lb/>treatments for DVT to prevent occurrence of PE during <lb/>the hospitalisation may be implemented more frequently <lb/>than before. <lb/>A meta-analysis comparing baricitinib and TNFIs using <lb/>several claims and registry databases showed an IRR of <lb/>1.51 (95% CI: 1.10 to 2.08) for VTE and 1.54 (0.93 to <lb/>2.54) for MACE, 35 which is similar to the results of the <lb/>present study. Swedish population-based study 19 also <lb/>showed the significantly higher risk of VTE in JAKI users <lb/>compared with TNFI users. However, several real-world <lb/>studies have reported a similar risk of VTE and MACE <lb/>between JAKIs and TNFIs in patients with RA. Analysis of <lb/>French national health data system revealed that risk of <lb/>MACEs and VTE for the JAKIs (tofacitinib or baricitinib)-<lb/>exposed versus adalimumab-exposed group was not <lb/>significantly different: weighted HR was 1.0 (95% CI: 0.7 <lb/>to 1.5) (p=0.99) for MACE and 1.1 (0.7 to 1.6) (p=0.63) <lb/>for VTE. 36 The United States Corrona RA registry also <lb/>reported unincreased risk of MACE in tofacitinib users <lb/>compared with bDMARD users. The pooled weighted <lb/>HR (95% CI) comparing tofacitinib with TNFIs was 1.01 <lb/>(0.83 to 1.23) in a cohort created from claims databases <lb/>and 1.24 (0.90 to 1.69) in ORAL-surveillance-duplicate <lb/>cohort. 37 In addition, Swedish and German observational <lb/>cohort studies also reported that there were not signifi-<lb/>cant differences in the risk of MACE between JAKIs and <lb/>TNFIs. 29 38 These data indicate that the risk of cardiovas-<lb/>cular events may be increased in patients with RA treated <lb/>with JAKIs. However, it should be noted that the absolute <lb/>risk differences in these studies were quite small, and the <lb/>number needed to harm was large. <lb/>Table 3 Crude incidence rate ratio of cardiovascular <lb/>events <lb/>JAKIs vs TNFIs <lb/>JAKIs vs non-<lb/>TNFIs <lb/>JAKIs vs MTX <lb/>Total <lb/>1.89 (1.42 to 2.50) 1.12 (0.85 to 1.47) 0.90 (0.70 to 1.16) <lb/>VTE <lb/>2.08 (1.47 to 2.93) 1.33 (0.94 to 1.87) 1.27 (0.93 to 1.73) <lb/>DVT <lb/>2.10 (1.44 to 3.06) 1.33 (0.92 to 1.93) 1.22 (0.87 to 1.71) <lb/>PE <lb/>1.62 (0.70 to 3.71) 1.02 (0.45 to 2.32) 1.14 (0.53 to 2.46) <lb/>ATE <lb/>2.42 (1.01 to 5.80) 1.13 (0.49 to 2.59) 1.06 (0.49 to 2.30) <lb/>AMI <lb/>1.34 (0.55 to 3.23) 1.38 (0.55 to 3.45) 0.63 (0.28 to 1.42) <lb/>Stroke 1.56 (0.68 to 3.57) 0.59 (0.27 to 1.29) 0.38 (0.18 to 0.80) <lb/>Data are presented as incidence rate ratios (95% CIs). <lb/>AMI, acute myocardial infarction; ATE, arterial thromboembolic <lb/>event; bDMARDs, biological disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs; <lb/>DVT, deep vein thrombosis; JAKIs, Janus kinase inhibitors; MTX, <lb/>methotrexate; PE, pulmonary embolism; TNFIs, tumour necrosis <lb/>factor inhibitors; VTE, venous thromboembolic event. <lb/>Table 4 Adjusted HRs of total cardiovascular events <lb/>Variable <lb/>Adjusted HR <lb/>P value <lb/>JAKIs without MTX (vs TNFIs <lb/>without MTX) <lb/>1.66 (1.11 to 2.49) 0.013 <lb/>JAKI without MTX (vs MTX) <lb/>1.19 (0.83 to 1.71) 0.34 <lb/>TNFIs without MTX (vs MTX) 0.72 (0.59 to 0.88) 0.001 <lb/>JAKIs with MTX (vs TNFIs <lb/>with MTX) <lb/>1.72 (1.11 to 2.66) 0.015 <lb/>JAKI with MTX (vs MTX) <lb/>1.24 (0.83 to 1.84) 0.29 <lb/>TNFIs with MTX (vs MTX) <lb/>0.72 (0.58 to 0.90) 0.004 <lb/>JAKIs without MTX (vs non-<lb/>TNFIs without MTX) <lb/>1.67 (1.13 to 2.48) 0.010 <lb/>Non-TNFIs without MTX (vs <lb/>MTX) <lb/>0.71 (0.59 to 0.87) &lt;0.001 <lb/>JAKIs with MTX (vs non-<lb/>TNFIs with MTX) <lb/>0.97 (0.63 to 1.50) 0.880 <lb/>Non-TNFIs with MTX (vs <lb/>MTX) <lb/>1.28 (1.03 to 1.60) 0.029 <lb/>A time-dependent Cox regression model was used to calculate <lb/>the HRs of JAKIs versus TNFIs, non-TNFIs or MTX after adjusting <lb/>for age, sex and comorbidities, including HT, DM, DL, APS, <lb/>liver disease, CKD, AF, CHF at baseline, history of malignancy, <lb/>prescription of hormone replacement treatment, NSAIDs use and <lb/>categorical doses of oral GCs (prednisolone-equivalent dose) <lb/>(0 mg/day, 0&lt;GC≤5 mg/day, 5&lt;GC≤10 mg/day, GC&gt;10 mg/day). <lb/>AF, atrial fibrillation; APS, antiphospholipid syndrome; CKD, <lb/>chronic kidney disease; DL, dyslipidaemia; DM, diabetes mellitus; <lb/>GCs, glucocorticoids; HT, hypertension; JAKIs, Janus kinase <lb/>inhibitors; MTX, methotrexate; non-TNFIs, non-tumour necrosis <lb/>factors inhibitors; TNFIs, tumour necrosis factors inhibitors. <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 on 17 June 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
        
        <page>7 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Sakai R, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/></note>
        
        <body>In this study, JAKIs had a 1.5-fold increased risk of <lb/>cardiovascular events compared with bDMARDs. Previous <lb/>meta-analyses have shown that bDMARDs are associated <lb/>with a significantly lower risk of MACE and stroke than <lb/>csDMARDs. 39 40 Another observational study conducted <lb/>in the USA also reported that TNFIs decreased the risk of <lb/>cardiovascular diseases compared with csDMARDs. 40 The <lb/>IR of cardiovascular events in this study was also decreased <lb/>for bDMARDs compared with MTX. The same reduction <lb/>was observed for TNFIs without MTX, TNFIs with MTX <lb/>and non-TNFIs without MTX. This decreased risk could <lb/>be explained by the reduction in vascular inflammation <lb/>by bDMARDs. 41 bDMARDs have been reported to be <lb/>associated with protective calcification of non-calcified <lb/>lesions in coronary atherosclerosis. 41 Additionally, TNFIs <lb/>improve endothelial function in patients with inflamma-<lb/>tory arthritis. 42 However, the detailed mechanism has <lb/>not been elucidated to date. Due to the nature of obser-<lb/>vational studies, it is not possible to determine whether <lb/>bDMARDs decreased the risk of cardiovascular events, <lb/>JAKI increased it, or both. 43 <lb/>To the best of our knowledge, the possible differences <lb/>in cardiovascular disease risk due to JAK selectivity have <lb/>not yet been proven. Integrated safety analyses of clinical <lb/>trials showed that risk of MACEs and VTE for upadac-<lb/>itinib was 0.6-1.0/100 PY and 0.3-0.6/100 PY, respec-<lb/>tively, 44 risk of MACEs for filgotinib was 0.4-0.6/100 PY, 45 <lb/>and risk of VTE in Asian patients treated with peficitinib <lb/>was 0.1/100 PY. 46 As approximately 90% of the patients <lb/>with JAKIs were administered tofacitinib or baricitinib, a <lb/>similar analysis enrolling more patients using other JAKIs <lb/>is necessary to determine whether the increased risk of <lb/>vascular events is a class effect of JAKI. <lb/>This study has multiple and significant limitations. <lb/>First, selection bias may have influenced the results <lb/>because the MDV database included data from only <lb/>26% of the hospitals that participated in the DPC/PDPS <lb/>system. Second, we could not analyse the clinical and <lb/>laboratory data owing to a lack of data, especially for <lb/>previously reported risk factors of cardiovascular events <lb/>including body mass index, smoking status, disease <lb/>activity of RA 47 and history and family history of cardio-<lb/>vascular disease. In addition, there are possibilities that <lb/>patients treated with JAKIs had longer RA disease dura-<lb/>tion than others, but we could not include the data in this <lb/>analysis because it was impossible to identify the disease <lb/>duration precisely in a claims data. However, we adjusted <lb/>for other classical risk factors such as DM, HT and HL, <lb/>and excluded patients with a diagnosis of cardiovascular <lb/>events 6 months prior to the index month to identify <lb/>new cardiovascular events as described in the &apos;Methods&apos; <lb/>section. Third, the definition of cardiovascular events <lb/>has not yet been validated in the Japanese claims data. <lb/>Fourth, cardiovascular death was not included among <lb/>the cardiovascular events in this study, which might have <lb/>decreased the IRs of total cardiovascular events. Fifth, <lb/>we could not compare the risk of vascular events among <lb/>agents because the numbers of patients using each drug <lb/>and numbers of cases with events became too small to <lb/>adjust for covariates. It is needed to analyse it in the <lb/>larger number of patients using the latest database. <lb/>Lastly, although the definition of patients with RA has <lb/>been already validated in Japan, 48 there were possibilities <lb/>to include patients with other rheumatic diseases such as <lb/>psoriatic arthritis. <lb/>In conclusion, the total number of the vascular events <lb/>were lower in bDMARD users, especially in TNFI users, <lb/>and users of JAKIs versus TNFIs irrespective of concom-<lb/>itant MTX and users of JAKIs without MTX versus <lb/>non-TNFI without MTX had a significantly higher cardio-<lb/>vascular risk. The increased risks of JAKIs versus TNFIs, <lb/>and non-TNFIs were attributed to the differences in <lb/>the risk between JAKIs (vs MTX) and these bDMARDs <lb/>(vs MTX). The increased cardiovascular risk in JAKIs <lb/>users was mainly derived from venous events. These data <lb/>should be interpreted with caution because of the limita-<lb/>tions associated with claims databases in general. <lb/></body>
        
        <front>Author affiliations <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Publich Health and Epidemiology, Meiji Pharmaceutical University, <lb/>Kiyose, Tokyo, Japan <lb/>2 <lb/>Division of Rheumatology, Department of Internal Medicine, Tokyo Women&apos;s <lb/>Medical University School of Medicine, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo, Japan <lb/>3 <lb/>Institute of Rheumatology, Tokyo Women&apos;s Medical University Hospital, Shinjuku-<lb/>ku, Tokyo, Japan <lb/>4 <lb/>Showa University Research Administration Center, Showa University, Shinagawa-<lb/>ku, Tokyo, Japan <lb/></front>
        
        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements We would like to thank Editage (www.editage.jp) for <lb/>English language editing. The abstract of this work has been presented at the ACR <lb/>Congress 2022. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="contribution">Contributors All authors contributed to the study conception and/or design, data <lb/>analysis and interpretation of data; critically revised the manuscript; and agreed to <lb/>its submission. MH takes responsibility for the overall contents as guarantor. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="funding">Funding This work was supported by Pfizer general research grant (Grant number <lb/>#60447919) and JSPS KAKENHI Grant number 20K10480 and the Ministry of <lb/>Health, Labour, and Welfare (Grant number 22FE1002). <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="conflict">Competing interests Ryoko Sakai has nothing to declare. Eiichi Tanaka has <lb/>received research funding from Pfizer Inc., UCB Japan Co. Ltd, and has received <lb/>lecture fees or consulting fees from AbbVie, Asahi Kasei Pharma Co., Astellas <lb/>Pharmaceutical, Ayumi Pharmaceutical, Boehringer Ingelheim Japan, Inc., Bristol <lb/>Myers Squibb Co., Ltd., Chugai Pharmaceutical, Daiichi-Sankyo, Inc., Eisai <lb/>Pharmaceutical, Eli Lilly Japan K.K., Gilead Sciences, Inc., GlaxoSmithKline K.K., <lb/>Kyowa Pharma Chemical Co., Ltd., Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K., Mitsubishi <lb/>Tanabe Pharma Co., Mochida Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd., Nippon Kayaku Co., Ltd., <lb/>Pfizer Japan Inc., Takeda Pharmaceutical, and Teijin Pharma Ltd., and Viatris <lb/>Japan. Eisuke Inoue has received lecture fees or consulting fees from Nippn tect <lb/>systems Co., Ltd., Cyberdine Inc., Bristol-Myers Squibb, Eisai Co., Ltd., and Chugai <lb/>Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. Masayoshi Harigai has received grants or contacts from <lb/>AbbVie Japan GK, Asahi Kasei Corp., Boehringer Ingelheim Japan, Inc., Eli Lilly <lb/>Japan K.K., Kaken Pharmaceutical Co., Mitsubishi 16 Tanabe Pharma Co., Mochida <lb/>Pharmaceutical Co., Nippon Shinyaku Co., Ltd., Taisho Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd., <lb/>Teijin Pharma Ltd., UCB Japan Co., Ltd., and Viatris Japan, and has received lecture <lb/>fees or consulting fees from Bristol Myers Squibb Co., Ltd., Ono Pharmaceutical <lb/>Co., Ltd., Eli Lilly Japan K.K., AbbVie Japan GK, AbbVie Japan GK, Asahi Kasei Corp., <lb/>Ayumi Pharmaceutical Co., Bristol Myers Squibb Co., Ltd., Chugai Pharmaceutical <lb/>Co., Ltd., Eisai Co., Ltd., Gilead Sciences Inc., Janssen Pharmaceutical K.K., <lb/>Mitsubishi Tanabe Pharma Co., Taisho Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd., Teijin Pharma Ltd <lb/>and UCB Japan. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="annex">Patient consent for publication Not applicable. <lb/>Ethics approval This study was approved by the ethics committee of Meiji <lb/>Pharmaceutical University (approval number 202123) and Tokyo Women&apos;s Medical <lb/>University (approval number 4910). <lb/>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. <lb/>RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 on 17 June 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></div>
        
        <page>8 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Sakai R, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>
        
        <div type="availability">Data availability statement No data are available. No data are available due to <lb/>the regulation of Medical Data Vision (MDV) Co., Ltd. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="annex">Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has <lb/>not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been <lb/>peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those <lb/>of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and <lb/>responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content <lb/>includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability <lb/>of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, <lb/>terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error <lb/>and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise. <lb/></div>
        
        <front>Open access This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which <lb/>permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, <lb/>and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the <lb/>use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/. <lb/>ORCID iDs <lb/>Ryoko Sakai http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1640-1373 <lb/>Masayoshi Harigai http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6418-2603 <lb/></front>
        
        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 Yamanaka H, Tanaka E, Nakajima A, et al. A large observational <lb/>cohort study of rheumatoid arthritis, IORRA: providing context for <lb/>today&apos;s treatment options. Mod Rheumatol 2020;30:1-6. <lb/>2 Harigai M, Honda S. Selectivity of Janus kinase inhibitors in <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis and other immune-mediated inflammatory <lb/>diseases: is expectation the root of all headache Drugs <lb/>2020;80:1183-201. <lb/>3 McLornan DP, Pope JE, Gotlib J, et al. Current and future status of <lb/>JAK inhibitors. Lancet 2021;398:803-16. <lb/>4 Nash P, Kerschbaumer A, Dörner T, et al. Points to consider for <lb/>the treatment of immune-mediated inflammatory diseases with <lb/>Janus kinase inhibitors: a consensus statement. Ann Rheum Dis <lb/>2021;80:71-87. <lb/>5 Kawahito Y, Morinobu A, Kaneko Y, et al. Drug treatment algorithm <lb/>and recommendations from the 2020 update of the Japan college <lb/>of rheumatology clinical practice guidelines for the management <lb/>of rheumatoid arthritis-secondary publication. Mod Rheumatol <lb/>2023;33:21-35. <lb/>6 Smolen JS, Landewé RBM, Bergstra SA, et al. EULAR <lb/>recommendations for the management of rheumatoid arthritis with <lb/>synthetic and biological disease-modifying Antirheumatic drugs: <lb/>2022 update. Ann Rheum Dis 2023;82:3-18. <lb/>7 Schieir O, Tosevski C, Glazier RH, et al. Incident myocardial <lb/>infarction associated with major types of arthritis in the general <lb/>population: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Ann Rheum Dis <lb/>2017;76:1396-404. <lb/>8 Kim SC, Schneeweiss S, Liu J, et al. Risk of venous <lb/>thromboembolism in patients with rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis Care <lb/>&amp; Research 2013;65:1600-7. <lb/>9 Choi HK, Rho Y-H, Zhu Y, et al. The risk of pulmonary embolism and <lb/>deep vein thrombosis in rheumatoid arthritis: a UK population-based <lb/>outpatient cohort study. Ann Rheum Dis 2013;72:1182-7. <lb/>10 Kim SC, Solomon DH, Liu J, et al. Risk of venous thromboembolism <lb/>in patients with rheumatoid arthritis: initiating disease-modifying <lb/>Antirheumatic drugs. Am J Med 2015;128:539. <lb/>11 Liang H, Danwada R, Guo D, et al. Incidence of inpatient venous <lb/>thromboembolism in treated patients with rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>and the association with switching biologic or targeted synthetic <lb/>disease-modifying Antirheumatic drugs (Dmards) in the real-world <lb/>setting. RMD Open 2019;5:e001013. <lb/>12 Kasai S, Sakai R, Koike R, et al. Higher risk of hospitalized infection, <lb/>cardiovascular disease, and fracture in patients with rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis determined using the Japanese health insurance database. <lb/>Mod Rheumatol 2019;29:788-94. <lb/>13 Blum A, Adawi M. Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) and cardiovascular <lb/>disease. Autoimmun Rev 2019;18:679-90. <lb/>14 Barnabe C, Martin BJ, Ghali WA. Systematic review and meta-<lb/>analysis: anti-tumor necrosis factor Α therapy and cardiovascular <lb/>events in rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis Care &amp; Research <lb/>2011;63:522-9. <lb/>15 Meissner Y, Richter A, Manger B, et al. Serious adverse events and <lb/>the risk of stroke in patients with rheumatoid arthritis: results from <lb/>the German RABBIT cohort. Ann Rheum Dis 2017;76:1583-90. <lb/>16 Mori S, Ogata F, Tsunoda R. Risk of venous thromboembolism <lb/>associated with Janus kinase inhibitors for rheumatoid arthritis: case <lb/>presentation and literature review. Clin Rheumatol 2021;40:4457-71. <lb/>17 Yates M, Mootoo A, Adas M, et al. Venous thromboembolism <lb/>risk with JAK inhibitors: a meta-analysis. Arthritis Rheumatol <lb/>2021;73:779-88. <lb/>18 Sepriano A, Kerschbaumer A, Bergstra SA, et al. Safety of synthetic <lb/>and biological Dmards: a systematic literature review informing the <lb/>2022 update of the EULAR recommendations for the management <lb/>of rheumatoid arthritis. Ann Rheum Dis 2023;82:107-18. <lb/>19 Molander V, Bower H, Frisell T, et al. Venous thromboembolism with <lb/>JAK inhibitors and other immune-modulatory drugs: a Swedish <lb/>comparative safety study among patients with rheumatoid arthritis. <lb/>Ann Rheum Dis 2023;82:189-97. <lb/>20 Ytterberg SR, Bhatt DL, Mikuls TR, et al. Cardiovascular and <lb/>cancer risk with tofacitinib in rheumatoid arthritis. N Engl J Med <lb/>2022;386:316-26. <lb/>21 FDA Drug Safety Communication, Available: https://www.fda.gov/ <lb/>media/151936/download <lb/>22 Direct healthcare profesional communication:Xeljanz (tofacitinib): <lb/>increased risk of major adverse cardiovascular events and <lb/>malignancies with use of tofacitinib relative to TNF-alpha inhibitors, <lb/>Available: https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/medicines/dhpc/xeljanz-<lb/>tofacitinib-increased-risk-major-adverse-cardiovascular-events-<lb/>malignancies-use-tofacitinib <lb/>23 Michaud K, Berglind N, Franzén S, et al. Can rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>(RA) registries provide contextual safety data for modern RA clinical <lb/>trials? the case for mortality and cardiovascular disease. Ann Rheum <lb/>Dis 2016;75:1797-805. <lb/>24 Sakai R, Honda S, Tanaka E, et al. The risk of hospitalized infection <lb/>in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus treated with <lb/>hydroxychloroquine. Lupus 2020;29:1712-8. <lb/>25 Yun H, Xie F, Delzell E, et al. Comparative risk of hospitalized <lb/>infection associated with biologic agents in rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis patients enrolled in Medicare. Arthritis &amp; Rheumatology <lb/>2016;68:56-66. <lb/>26 Quan H, Sundararajan V, Halfon P, et al. Coding Algorithms for <lb/>defining comorbidities in ICD-9-CM and ICD-10 administrative data. <lb/>Med Care 2005;43:1130-9. <lb/>27 Harigai M, Takeuchi T, Smolen JS, et al. Safety profile of Baricitinib <lb/>in Japanese patients with active rheumatoid arthritis with over 1.6 <lb/>years median time in treatment: an integrated analysis of phases 2 <lb/>and 3 trials. Mod Rheumatol 2020;30:36-43. <lb/>28 Mease P, Charles-Schoeman C, Cohen S, et al. Incidence of <lb/>venous and arterial thromboembolic events reported in the <lb/>tofacitinib rheumatoid arthritis, psoriasis and Psoriatic arthritis <lb/>development programmes and from real-world data. Ann Rheum Dis <lb/>2020;79:1400-13. <lb/>29 Meissner Y, Schäfer M, Albrecht K, et al. Risk of major adverse <lb/>cardiovascular events in patients with rheumatoid arthritis treated <lb/>with conventional synthetic, biologic and targeted synthetic disease-<lb/>modifying Antirheumatic drugs: observational data from the German <lb/>RABBIT register. RMD Open 2023;9:e003489. <lb/>30 Taylor PC, Weinblatt ME, Burmester GR, et al. Cardiovascular safety <lb/>during treatment with baricitinib in rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis <lb/>Rheumatol 2019;71:1042-55. <lb/>31 Harigai M. Growing evidence of the safety of JAK inhibitors <lb/>in patients with rheumatoid arthritis. Rheumatology (Oxford) <lb/>2019;58:i34-42. <lb/>32 Haraoui B, Khraishi M, Choquette D, et al. Effectiveness and safety <lb/>of tofacitinib in Canadian patients with rheumatoid arthritis: primary <lb/>results from a prospective observational study. Arthritis Care &amp; <lb/>Research 2023;75:240-51. <lb/>33 Heit JA. Epidemiology of venous thromboembolism. Nat Rev Cardiol <lb/>2015;12:464-74. <lb/>34 Yamashita Y, Morimoto T, Amano H, et al. Anticoagulation therapy <lb/>for venous thromboembolism in the real world -from the COMMAND <lb/>VTE registry. Circ J 2018;82:1262-70. <lb/>35 Salinas CA, Louder A, Polinski J, et al. Evaluation of VTE, MACE, <lb/>and serious infections among patients with RA treated with <lb/>Baricitinib compared to Tnfi: a multi-database study of patients <lb/>in routine care using disease registries and claims databases. <lb/>Rheumatol Ther 2023;10:201-23. <lb/>36 Hoisnard L, Pina Vegas L, Dray-Spira R, et al. Risk of major adverse <lb/>cardiovascular and venous thromboembolism events in patients with <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis exposed to JAK inhibitors versus adalimumab: a <lb/>nationwide cohort study. Ann Rheum Dis 2023;82:182-8. <lb/>37 Khosrow-Khavar F, Kim SC, Lee H, et al. Tofacitinib and risk of <lb/>cardiovascular outcomes: results from the safety of tofacitinib in <lb/>routine care patients with rheumatoid arthritis (STAR-RA) study. Ann <lb/>Rheum Dis 2022;81:798-804. <lb/></listBibl>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 on 17 June 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
        
        <page>9 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Sakai R, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003885. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 <lb/></note>
        
        <listBibl>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>38 Frisell T, Bower H, Morin M, et al. Safety of biological and targeted <lb/>synthetic disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs for rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis as used in clinical practice: results from the ARTIS <lb/>programme. Ann Rheum Dis 2023;82:601-10. <lb/>39 Singh S, Fumery M, Singh AG, et al. Comparative risk of <lb/>cardiovascular events with biologic and synthetic disease-modifying <lb/>Antirheumatic drugs in patients with rheumatoid arthritis: A <lb/>systematic review and meta-analysis. Arthritis Care &amp; Research <lb/>2020;72:561-76. <lb/>40 Ozen G, Pedro S, Michaud K. The risk of cardiovascular events <lb/>associated with disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs in <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis. J Rheumatol 2021;48:648-55. <lb/>41 Karpouzas GA, Ormseth SR, Hernandez E, et al. Biologics may <lb/>prevent cardiovascular events in rheumatoid arthritis by inhibiting <lb/>coronary plaque formation and stabilizing high-risk lesions. Arthritis <lb/>&amp; Rheumatology 2020;72:1467-75. <lb/>42 Deyab G, Hokstad I, Whist JE, et al. Methotrexate and anti-tumor <lb/>necrosis factor treatment improves endothelial function in patients <lb/>with inflammatory arthritis. Arthritis Res Ther 2017;19:232. <lb/>43 Singh JA. Risks and benefits of janus kinase inhibitors in rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis -past, present, and future. N Engl J Med 2022;386:387-9. <lb/>44 Cohen SB, van Vollenhoven RF, Winthrop KL, et al. Safety profile <lb/>of upadacitinib in rheumatoid arthritis: integrated analysis from <lb/>the SELECT phase III clinical programme. Ann Rheum Dis <lb/>2021;80:304-11. <lb/>45 Winthrop KL, Tanaka Y, Takeuchi T, et al. Integrated safety analysis <lb/>of filgotinib in patients with moderately to severely active rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis receiving treatment over a median of 1.6 years. Ann Rheum <lb/>Dis 2022;81:184-92. <lb/>46 Takeuchi T, Tanaka Y, Rokuda M, et al. A pooled safety analysis <lb/>of Peficitinib (Asp015K) in Asian patients with rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>treated over a median of 2 years. Mod Rheumatol 2021;31:543-55. <lb/>47 England BR, Thiele GM, Anderson DR, et al. Increased <lb/>cardiovascular risk in rheumatoid arthritis: mechanisms and <lb/>implications. BMJ 2018;361:k1036. <lb/>48 Kubota K, Yoshizawa M, Takahashi S, et al. The validity of the <lb/>claims-based definition of rheumatoid arthritis evaluated in 64 <lb/>hospitals in Japan. BMC Musculoskelet Disord 2021;22:373. <lb/></listBibl>
        
        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003885 on 17 June 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. </note>


    </text>

</TEI>