<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Expression on <lb/>Glycosphingolipids, N-, and O-Glycans in Colorectal <lb/>Cancer Cell Lines is Linked to a Colon-Like <lb/>Differentiation Program <lb/>Authors <lb/>Di Wang, Katarina Maduni ć, Oleg A. Mayboroda, Guinevere S. M. Lageveen-Kammeijer, and <lb/>Manfred Wuhrer <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>Graphical Abstract <lb/>m.wuhrer@lumc.nl <lb/>In Brief <lb/>An integrated analysis of <lb/>glycosylation features including <lb/>(sialyl)Lewis structure and blood <lb/>group antigens was performed <lb/>across N-, O-glycans, and <lb/>glycosphingolipid glycans. <lb/>Colon-like lines exhibited <lb/>abundant (sialyl)Lewis antigens, <lb/>while undifferentiated lines <lb/>expressed H blood group <lb/>antigens and α2-3/6 sialylation. <lb/>The observed associations <lb/>across glycan classes along with <lb/>correlations with <lb/>glycosyltransferases and <lb/>transcription factors suggest that <lb/>certain transcription factors like <lb/>CDX1 contribute to the <lb/>upregulation of (sialyl)Lewis <lb/>antigens on all three glycan <lb/>classes via regulation of <lb/>glycosyltransferases FUT3/4. <lb/>2024, Mol Cell Proteomics 23(6), 100776 <lb/>© 2024 THE AUTHORS. Published by Elsevier Inc on behalf of American Society for Biochemistry and <lb/>Molecular Biology. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/ <lb/>licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mcpro.2024.100776 <lb/>RESEARCH <lb/>Highlights <lb/>• Glycosylation motifs are compared for a set of 22 colorectal cancer cell lines. <lb/>• For (sialyl)Lewis and H blood group antigens significant associations are found across the three <lb/>glycan classes. <lb/>• Colon-like cell lines present high abundance of (sialyl)Lewis antigens. <lb/>• High expression of (sialyl)Lewis antigens might result from the regulation of FUT3. <lb/>RESEARCH <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Expression on <lb/>Glycosphingolipids, N-, and O-Glycans in <lb/>Colorectal Cancer Cell Lines is Linked to a <lb/>Colon-Like Differentiation Program <lb/>Di Wang 1 , Katarina Maduni ć1,2 , Oleg A. Mayboroda 1 , <lb/>Guinevere S. M. Lageveen-Kammeijer 1,3 , and Manfred Wuhrer 1,* <lb/>Alterations in the glycomic profile are a hallmark of can-<lb/>cer, including colorectal cancer (CRC). While, the glyco-<lb/>sylation of glycoproteins and glycolipids has been widely <lb/>studied for CRC cell lines and tissues, a comprehensive <lb/>overview of CRC glycomics is still lacking due to the usage <lb/>of different samples and analytical methods. In this study, <lb/>we compared glycosylation features of N-, O-glycans, and <lb/>glycosphingolipid glycans for a set of 22 CRC cell lines, all <lb/>measured by porous graphitized carbon nano-liquid <lb/>chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry. An overall, <lb/>high abundance of (sialyl)Lewis antigens for colon-like cell <lb/>lines was found, while undifferentiated cell lines showed <lb/>high expression of H blood group antigens and α2-3/6 <lb/>sialylation. Moreover, significant associations of glyco-<lb/>sylation features were found between the three classes of <lb/>glycans, such as (sialyl)Lewis and H blood group antigens. <lb/>Integration of the datasets with transcriptomics data <lb/>revealed positive correlations between (sialyl)Lewis anti-<lb/>gens, the corresponding glycosyltransferase FUT3 and <lb/>transcription factors CDX1, ETS, HNF1/4A, MECOM, and <lb/>MYB. This indicates a possible role of these transcription <lb/>factors in the upregulation of (sialyl)Lewis antigens, <lb/>particularly on glycosphingolipid glycans, via FUT3/4 <lb/>expression in colon-like cell lines. In conclusion, our study <lb/>provides insights into the possible regulation of glycans in <lb/>CRC and can serve as a guide for the development of <lb/>diagnostic and therapeutic biomarkers. <lb/></front>

			<body>Based on the data from Global Cancer Statistics 2020, <lb/>colorectal cancer (CRC) has become the third most commonly <lb/>diagnosed cancer (10.0%) and the second leading cause of <lb/>cancer death (9.4%) worldwide (1). Traditional treatments for <lb/>cancer include chemotherapy, radiation, and surgery. Specific <lb/>molecular targeting methods are increasingly implemented in <lb/>clinical practice, including specific inhibitors (2) and <lb/>monoclonal antibodies (3). Unfortunately, for a large part of the <lb/>cases, these treatments turn out not to be effective due to <lb/>tumor heterogeneity and detection at an advanced stage (4). <lb/>Hence, new treatment strategies are urgently needed. <lb/>Glycosylation has shown to be a promising field for finding <lb/>new biomarkers in diagnosis and specific targets for therapy, <lb/>as an altered glycosylation profile has been related to the <lb/>development and progression of cancer, such as tumor <lb/>angiogenesis, invasion, and metastasis (5).Several factors <lb/>contribute to the abnormal expression of glycosylation <lb/>including (i) altered expression of glycosyltransferases (GTs) <lb/>(6-9), (ii) the changes in the activity of GTs (5), (iii) the mis-<lb/>localization of GTs in the ER and Golgi apparatus (10, 11), and <lb/>(iv) the availability and abundance of sugar donors (12). <lb/>Common cancer-associated glycosylation features include <lb/>alterations in the level of fucosylation and sialylation (5, 13). Of <lb/>which, the latter is involved in cell recognition, adhesion, and <lb/>signaling (5). The upregulation of sialyl transferase ST6GAL1 <lb/>results in overexpression of α2-6 sialylation and has been <lb/>linked to changes in the adhesion of cancer cells to the <lb/>extracellular matrix proteins like collagen, fibronectin, and <lb/>laminin in colon cancer which contribute to metastasis and <lb/>poor survival of CRC patients (14). A well-known sialylation <lb/>feature is the Sialyl-Lewis X (sLe X ) antigen [tetrasaccharide <lb/>composed of a sialic acid (α2-3 linked), galactose (β1-4 <lb/>linked), fucose (α1-3 linked), and an N-acetyllactosamine] <lb/>which is a ligand for selectins which are vascular cell adhesion <lb/>molecules involved in extravasation of cancer cells leading to <lb/>formation of metastasis in secondary sites. Elevated expres-<lb/>sion of sLe X was found to be associated with poor survival of <lb/>CRC patients (15). Some well-established serological bio-<lb/>markers for cancer detection, monitoring, and prognosis are <lb/>carbohydrate antigens (CA) or glycoproteins such as sLe A <lb/></body>

			<front>Form the 1 Center for Proteomics and Metabolomics, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden, The Netherlands; 2 Department of Cellular and <lb/>Molecular Medicine, Copenhagen Center for Glycomics, University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark; 3 Division of Analytical <lb/>Biochemistry, Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy, University of Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands <lb/>* For correspondence: Manfred Wuhrer, m.wuhrer@lumc.nl. <lb/>RESEARCH <lb/>Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 1 <lb/>© 2024 THE AUTHORS. Published by Elsevier Inc on behalf of American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology. <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mcpro.2024.100776 <lb/></front>

			<body>(also known as CA 19-9 and differs from sLe X as the galactose <lb/>is β1-3 linked and the fucose α1-4 linked) (16) and carci-<lb/>noembryonic antigen (17, 18). However, the specificity of <lb/>these biomarkers is limited as they are not only expressed in <lb/>cancer cells but also in nonneoplastic and inflammatory dis-<lb/>eases (19). <lb/>Many glycosylation features are shared between glycopro-<lb/>teins and glycolipids, and to gain better insights into the <lb/>common features and GT isoenzyme specificities, a deeper <lb/>exploration should be performed to investigate which of these <lb/>shared features are correlated to CRC. Eventually this <lb/>knowledge will aid to the discovery of specific tumor-<lb/>associated glycans for diagnosis and targeted treatment of <lb/>CRC. <lb/>On the basis of analysis of mutations and RNA and protein <lb/>expression, CRC cell lines have been classified into two <lb/>groups, which are colon-like cell lines with expression of <lb/>gastrointestinal differentiation markers and undifferentiated <lb/>cell lines characterized by upregulation of genes linked to <lb/>epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) (20). Mass spec-<lb/>trometry (MS) is a powerful tool to perform in-depth charac-<lb/>terization of glycomic profiles and has been widely used to <lb/>study the role of glycosylation in cancer, including CRC <lb/>(21-23). Just recently, we examined the protein N-and O-<lb/>glycosylation (22, 23) as well as glycosphingolipids (GSLs) <lb/>glycosylation profiles (21) of CRC cell lines, using porous <lb/>graphitized carbon nanoliquid chromatography-MS/MS. <lb/>Striking differences were found between colon-like and un-<lb/>differentiated cell lines for all three glycan classes. With regard <lb/>to O-glycosylation, colon-like cell lines showed high expres-<lb/>sion of I-branched and sLe A/X epitope-carrying glycans, while <lb/>undifferentiated cell lines were characterized by high preva-<lb/>lence of truncated α2-6 core sialylated glycans, and some <lb/>undifferentiated cell lines expressed high abundances of gly-<lb/>cans with blood group antigens (A, B, and H) (23). As for N-<lb/>glycans, colon-like cell lines presented a high expression of <lb/>sulfation, (s)Le A/X , Le B/Y , antenna fucosylation, oligomannosi-<lb/>dic, and hybrid-type N-glycans, while undifferentiated cell <lb/>lines highly expressed phosphorylation, bisection, and α2-3 <lb/>sialylation, as well as paucimannosidic N-glycans and N-gly-<lb/>cans carrying (fucosylated) LacdiNAc (GalNAcβ1-4GlcNAc) <lb/>(22). When it comes to GSL glycans, high expression of (s)Le A/ <lb/>X and Le B/Y antigens was found for colon-like cell lines while <lb/>undifferentiated cell lines showed higher abundances of gly-<lb/>cans with all blood group antigens (A, B, and H) (21). <lb/>In regard to GTs, ST6GALNAC1-4 has been reported to add <lb/>sialic acid to N-acetylgalactosamine (GalNAc) of O-glycans <lb/>(24), while ST6GALNAC5/6 seems to be involved in the sia-<lb/>lylation of GSL glycans (25, 26). Regarding fucosylated gly-<lb/>cans synthesized by a range of fucosyltransferases (FUT1-<lb/>FUT11), previous studies have found that the expression of <lb/>sLe X is mainly regulated by FUT6 in breast cancer, while FUT7 <lb/>plays an essential role in the upregulation of sLe X in adult T <lb/>cell leukemia cells (27, 28). However, it remains unclear which <lb/>fucosyltransferase(s) contribute to the expression of Le anti-<lb/>gens in CRC and to which extent the biosynthetic programs <lb/>are shared between the three glycan classes. <lb/>In the present study, we performed an integrated analysis of <lb/>commonalities and discrepancies in the expression of differ-<lb/>entiation-and cancer-associated glycosylation features of <lb/>CRC cell lines. Subsequently, we explored the association of <lb/>CRC cell line glycosylation features with relevant GTs and <lb/>transcription factors (TFs). Overall, our study provides novel <lb/>insights into the potential (dys-)regulation of glycosylation in <lb/>CRC across glycan classes, revealing glycosylation markers <lb/>with potential diagnostic and therapeutic potential. <lb/>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Our recent studies provided in-depth comprehensive glycomic <lb/>profiling (N-, O-glycans, and GSL glycans) of CRC cell lines (21-23). <lb/>Glycomics data for CRC cell lines were retrieved from GlycoPOST (29): <lb/>GPST000239 (GSL glycans) (21), GPST000035 (O-glycan) (23), and <lb/>GPST000302 (N-glycan) (22). An overview of the included CRC cell <lb/>lines is provided in supplemental Table S1. Taking advantage of the <lb/>available data, glycans were assigned to different glycosylation fea-<lb/>tures as indicated in supplemental Tables S2-S5 for N-, O-glycans, <lb/>and GSL glycans, respectively. Only the CRC cell lines that had gly-<lb/>comics data for all classes available (N-, O-glycosylation, and GSLs <lb/>glycosylation) were taken along. Multi-omics (DNA, RNA, and protein) <lb/>datasets of CRC cell lines have been investigated and applied for CRC <lb/>cell lines classifications. The transcriptomics data of CRC cell lines <lb/>were retrieved from the Gene Expression Omnibus GSE97023 (20). <lb/>Colon-like cell lines were characterized by the expression of gastro-<lb/>intestinal differentiation markers, and undifferentiated cell lines <lb/>exhibited an upregulation of EMT pathway and transforming growth <lb/>factor β signaling (20). Data analysis and visualization were conducted <lb/>in &quot;R&quot; (version 4.2.1) with packages &quot;tidyverse&quot;, &quot;Rcpm&quot;, &quot;pcaMe-<lb/>thods&quot;, &quot;stringi&quot;, &quot;readxl&quot;, &quot;ggplot2&quot;, &quot;ggrepel&quot;, &quot;reshape2&quot;, &quot;tidy-<lb/>Heatmap&quot;, and &quot;corrplot&quot;. <lb/>Experimental Design and Statistical Rationale <lb/>We combined the N-, O-glycomic, and GSL glycomic data which all <lb/>have been measured by porous graphitized carbon nanoliquid <lb/>chromatography-MS/MS for the same set of CRC cell lines (21-23). <lb/>More information about glycomic data can be found in supplemental <lb/>Tables S2-S5. For integration, glycosylation traits and motifs deter-<lb/>mined within N-, O-glycomic, and GSL glycomic datasets were <lb/>summed, thereby generating composite, integrated glycosylation <lb/>traits. The transcriptomics data of CRC cell lines were obtained from <lb/>Gene Expression Omnibus GSE97023 (20). For principal component <lb/>analysis, a minimum positive number (0.00001) was used in case of <lb/>missing data. Spearman correlations were conducted between <lb/>glycosylation features of the three glycan classes as well as between <lb/>glycosylation features with corresponding GTs and selected TFs. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Integrated glycosylation features of CRC cell lines reflect <lb/>the differentiation status, and CRC cell lines recapitulate the <lb/>molecular alteration and pharmacogenomics of primary tu-<lb/>mors and are therefore often used as preclinical models of <lb/>CRC (20, 30, 31). To gain a comprehensive landscape of <lb/>glycosylation of CRC cell lines and to explore the <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/>Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 2 <lb/>tumor-associated glycosylation features, the glycosylation <lb/>features on N-, O-glycan, and GSL glycan were utilized and <lb/>integrated based on relative quantification in each individual <lb/>study (supplemental Table S6). Classifications of the CRC cell <lb/>lines were demonstrated by principal component analysis <lb/>(Fig. 1A) driven by the glycan class and specific glycosylation <lb/>features (Fig. 1B). <lb/>Colon-like cell lines (LS180, LS174T, SW1116, WiDr, <lb/>SW948, and HT29) clustered due to the expression of (s)Le A/X <lb/>and Le B/Y (N-, O-glycan, and GSL glycans), sulfo Le A/X (O-<lb/>glycan), and (sialyl) dimeric Le A/X (O-glycan) (Fig. 1). The <lb/>highest abundance of Le A/X on N-, O-glycan, and GSL glycans <lb/>was found for cell line LS180 (6%, 4%, and 36%, respectively) <lb/>and LS174T (5%, 5%, and 49%, respectively) (supplemental <lb/>Fig. S2 and Table S6). Similar to Le A/X , the highest abun-<lb/>dance of sLe A/X structures was observed for LS180 and <lb/>LS174T for all three glycan classes (supplemental Fig. S2 and <lb/>Table S6). Notably, Le B/Y epitopes on O-glycans were only <lb/>expressed in cell lines LS180 and LS174T with relative <lb/>quantification of 1.53% and 1.47%, while 0.38% and 0.22% <lb/>of relative quantification of Le B/Y epitopes on N-glycans in cell <lb/>lines LS180 and LS174T was detected. The highest expres-<lb/>sion of Le B/Y epitope on N-glycans was found in cell line HCT8 <lb/>(unassigned). The highest abundance of (A/B) Le B/Y (with the <lb/>structure <lb/>GalNAcα1-3(Fucα1-2) <lb/>Galβ1-3/4(Fucα1-4/3) <lb/>GlcNAc-R for A Le B/Y and Galα1-3(Fucα1-2) Galβ1-3/4(Fucα1-<lb/>4/3) GlcNAc-R for B Le B/Y ) on GSL glycans was detected in <lb/>the well-differentiated cell line SW1463 (supplemental Fig. S2 <lb/>and Table S6). <lb/>In regard to sialylation, α2-3/6 sialylation was found on all <lb/>three glycan classes and contributed to the grouping of un-<lb/>differentiated cell lines HCT116, DLD-1, RKO, and SW620 as <lb/>well as most unassigned cell lines Colo320, C10, LS411N, and <lb/>SW1398 (Fig. 1). Colon-like cell line SW1463 revealed the <lb/>highest α2-3 sialylation expression in the N-glycan class. <lb/>HCT8 (unassigned regarding its differentiation status) clus-<lb/>tered together with the undifferentiated cell lines SW48, <lb/>LOVO, HCT15, Caco-2, and SW480 driven by the expression <lb/>FIG. 1. Principle component analysis (PCA) of glycosylation features on N-, O-glycans, and GSL glycans in CRC cell lines. A and B, the <lb/>score plot depicts the distribution of CRC cell lines colored by CRC cell line classifications (A), driven by the glycosylation features on N-, O-<lb/>glycans, and GSL glycans displayed in the loading plot (B). Relative quantification of glycosylation features was used for PCA analysis. The top <lb/>two principal components explain 48% of the variation within the data. Together with the third and fourth principal components, a variance of <lb/>69% was covered (supplemental Fig. S1). CRC, colorectal cancer; GSL, glycosphingolipid. <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/>3 Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 <lb/>of blood group antigens on N-, O-glycan, and GSL glycans <lb/>(Fig. 1). HCT8 was found to highly express blood group anti-<lb/>gens on N-glycans with a relative abundance of 2%, and the <lb/>highest expression of blood group antigens on O-glycans was <lb/>found in the Caco-2 cell line (62%) (supplemental Fig. S2 and <lb/>Table S6). In regard to the blood group antigens on GSL <lb/>glycans, the highest abundance was detected in undifferen-<lb/>tiated cell line LOVO (64%). <lb/>Correlation of Glycosylation Features Between Glycan <lb/>Classes <lb/>Next, the correlation of glycosylation features between the <lb/>three glycan classes was explored. No significant correlations <lb/>were observed for α2-3 and α2-6 sialylation among the three <lb/>glycans classes (Fig. 2A). Significant correlations were <lb/>revealed between all glycan classes for H blood group anti-<lb/>gens as well as sLe A/X antigens (Fig. 2A). Subsequently, we <lb/>explored the glycosylation features for the different CRC cell <lb/>line classifications (Fig. 2B). A rather high abundance of (s)Le A/ <lb/>X and (A/B) Le B/Y was observed for all three glycan classes in <lb/>colon-like cell lines. Likewise, these cell lines showed high α2-<lb/>3/6 sialylation on O-glycans and α2-3 sialylation on N-glycans. <lb/>In contrast, blood group antigens on O-glycans and GSL <lb/>glycans were highly expressed in undifferentiated cell lines <lb/>(supplemental Table S7 and Fig. 2B). <lb/>Correlation of Glycosylation Features and GTs in CRC Cell <lb/>Lines <lb/>To explore the underlying pathways that regulate the <lb/>glycosylation features of glycans in CRC, correlations be-<lb/>tween glycosylation features and expression of GTs were <lb/>explored by Spearman correlation (supplemental Table S8). <lb/>GT FUT2, encoded by the gene fucosyltransferase 2 and <lb/>catalyzing the transfer of L-fucose to the terminal galactose of <lb/>both N-and O-glycan and GSL glycans via α1-2 linkage (32, <lb/>33), significantly correlated with (A/B) Le B/Y on GSL glycans <lb/>and integrated (A/B) Le B/Y (which was calculated by summing <lb/>the (A/B) Le B/Y glycosylation traits of N-, O-glycan, and GSL <lb/>glycans) (Fig. 3A). Surprisingly, positive correlation was also <lb/>found between FUT2 and Le A/X on GSL glycans which was <lb/>unexpected as FUT2 does not catalyze the biosynthesis of <lb/>Le A/X structures. GT FUT3, responsible for catalyzing the <lb/>transfer of L-fucose to Galβ1-4/3GlcNAc of glycans via α1-3/4 <lb/>linkage to form Le A/X/B/Y antigens and sLe A and disialyl Le A <lb/>structures (25, 34-36), positively correlated with Le A/X on O-<lb/>glycan, GSL, and integrated glycans, sLe A/X on N-glycans, <lb/>GSL, and integrated glycans, (s)dimeric Le A/X and sulfo Le A/X <lb/>on O-glycans as well as (A/B) Le B/Y on GSL glycans and in-<lb/>tegrated glycans (Fig. 3A). GT FUT4, involved in the biosyn-<lb/>thesis of (s)Le X antigens by transferring L-fucose to GlcNAc of <lb/>type 2 N-acetyllactosamine in α1-3 linkage (37-39), positively <lb/>correlated with (s)Le A/X antigen on GSL glycans (Fig. 3A). GT <lb/>FUT5, also reported to be responsible for the synthesis of (s) <lb/>Le X antigens (40-42), showed no significant correlation with (s) <lb/>Le X antigens (Fig. 3A). Expression of GT FUT6 participating in <lb/>the formation of (sialyl) Lewis antigens (43, 44) positively <lb/>correlated with Le A/X and (sialyl) dimeric Le A/X on O-glycans as <lb/>well as sLe A/X on N-glycans. Expectedly, FUT8, which cata-<lb/>lyzes the addition of fucose to first GlcNAc of N-glycans via <lb/>α1-6 linkage (45), correlated with core fucosylation on N-gly-<lb/>cans (Fig. 3A). <lb/>ST3GAL1, participating in the biosynthesis of terminal sia-<lb/>lylation of glycoproteins and glycolipids in α2-3 linkage (46), <lb/>positively correlated with α2-3 sialylation on O-glycans and <lb/>integrated α2-3 sialylation (Fig. 3B). In contrast, no positive <lb/>correlation was found between ST3GAL3/4/6 and α2-3 sialy-<lb/>lation in all three glycan classes (Fig. 3B), which was some-<lb/>what unexpected as these enzymes have been reported to be <lb/>involved in the synthesis of α2-3 sialylation on glycoprotein <lb/>and glycolipids (47, 48). ST3GAL2, which has been reported to <lb/>be primarily involved in the α2-3 sialylation of ganglio and <lb/>globo series glycolipids (49, 50), showed no significant cor-<lb/>relation with α2-3 sialylation of GSL glycans but unexpectedly <lb/>showed a positive correlation with α2-6 sialylation on O-gly-<lb/>cans (Fig. 3B). Expectedly, ST3GAL5 responsible for the <lb/>addition of sialic acid to lactosyl ceramide forming ganglio-<lb/>sides (51) was found to be positively correlated to α2-3 sia-<lb/>lylation on GSL glycans (Fig. 3B). <lb/>ST6GALNAC1-4 is responsible for adding sialic acid to <lb/>GalNAc of O-glycans (24) yet showed no significant correlation <lb/>with α2-6 sialylation on O-glycans. ST6GALNAC5/6 are known <lb/>to transfer sialic acid to glycolipids forming α2-6 linkage (25, <lb/>26), and also here, no positive correlation was found with α2-6 <lb/>sialylation on GSL glycans (Fig. 3B). ST6GAL1, responsible for <lb/>transferring a sialic acid to galactose-containing acceptor <lb/>substrates mainly on N-glycans and GSL glycans (52, 53), <lb/>showed no positive correlation with α2-6-sialylation on N-gly-<lb/>cans and GSL glycans individually but significantly correlated <lb/>with integrated α2-6 sialylation (Fig. 3B). <lb/>Association of Transcription Factors With GTs and <lb/>Glycosylation Features in CRC Cell Lines <lb/>To obtain insights into the potential regulation of the <lb/>expression of glycosylation features, the TFs with the highest <lb/>difference in expression between colon-like and undifferenti-<lb/>ated cell lines were probed for association with glycans and <lb/>GTs (23). Elevated expression of TFs CDX1, ETS2, HNF1A, <lb/>HNF4A, MECOM, and MYB has been found for colon-like cell <lb/>lines whereas the increased expression of TFs MLLT10, <lb/>MSX1, SIX4, ZNF286A, and ZNF286B have been observed in <lb/>undifferentiated cell lines (23). Correlations between TFs, GTs, <lb/>and corresponding glycosylation features were assessed with <lb/>the Spearman method (supplemental Table S9). <lb/>The correlation heatmap illustrates that FUT3 correlates <lb/>with TFs CDX1, ETS2, HNF1A, HNF4A, and MYB which in turn <lb/>correlated with (A/B) Le B/Y (GSL glycans) and integrated (A/B) <lb/>Le B/Y (Fig. 4A). Next to FUT3, also FUT6 positively correlated <lb/>with TF CDX1. FUT4 exhibited significantly positive <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/>Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 4 <lb/>correlations with HNF4A and MYB. Interestingly, Le A/X on GSL <lb/>glycans and integrated Le A/X showed distinct positive cor-<lb/>rections with ETS2, HNF1A, HNF4A, MECOM, and MYB but <lb/>negative correlations with MLLT10, MSX1, SIX4, ZNF286A, <lb/>and ZNF286B which, as previously mentioned, was highly <lb/>expressed in undifferentiated cell lines. TF MECOM showed <lb/>positive correlation with Le A/X on N-glycans (Fig. 4A). Addi-<lb/>tionally, ETS2, MECOM, and MYB show significant correla-<lb/>tions with sLe A/X (O-glycan, GSL, and integrated glycans) <lb/>which negatively correlated with MLLT10, ZNF286A, and <lb/>ZNF286B (Fig. 4A). CDX1 exhibited significant negative cor-<lb/>relation with integrated H blood group antigens (Fig. 4A). <lb/>Regarding the association of sialyltransferases with TFs, <lb/>ST6GALNAC1 positively correlated with TF ETS2, HNF4A, <lb/>and MECOM, whereas negative correlations were found be-<lb/>tween ST6GALNAC6 and ETS2, HNF4A, and MYB (Fig. 4B). <lb/>TFs MSX1, ZNF286A, and ZNF286B showed negative corre-<lb/>lations with α2-6 sialylation on O-glycans and accordingly with <lb/>ST6GALNAC1, while these TFs showed a positive correlation <lb/>with ST6GALNAC6 (Fig. 4B). <lb/>FIG. 2. Correlation of glycosylation features between three classes of glycans and distribution of glycosylation features on N-, O-<lb/>glycans, and GSL glycans (bottom) in three CRC cell line classifications (right). A, Spearman correlations between glycosylation features of <lb/>three glycan classes are visualized. Significant value is marked with * (p ≤ 0.05), ** (p ≤ 0.01), and *** (p ≤ 0.001). B, glycosylation features of <lb/>three classifications of CRC cell lines are compared. Relative abundances of each glycosylation feature on N-, O-glycans, and GSL glycans were <lb/>used as input. For standardization, the mean was equaled to zero, and the standard deviation was equaled to 1. CRC, colorectal cancer; GSL, <lb/>glycosphingolipid. <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/>5 Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 <lb/>FIG. 3. Correlation of N-, O-glycans, and GSL glycan features with corresponding GT expression. A, correlation of fucosyltransferases <lb/>with (s)Le and H blood group antigens. B, correlation of sialylation with corresponding GTs. The correlation analysis was performed on the basis <lb/>of the relative quantification of glycosylation features and expression of relevant GTs with the Spearman method. Significant values are marked <lb/>with * (p ≤ 0.05), ** (p ≤ 0.01), and *** (p ≤ 0.001). GSL, glycosphingolipid; GT, glycosyltransferase. <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/>Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 6 <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>We recently performed an in-depth N-, O-glycomic, and <lb/>GSL glycomic analyses of different CRC cell lines revealing <lb/>commonalities as well as striking diversities of glycosylation <lb/>(20, 21, 23). To reveal commonalities and discrepancies of <lb/>expression patterns of glycosylation features shared between <lb/>the three glycomics layers of CRC cell lines and to explore <lb/>FIG. 4. Correlation of glycosylation features of N-, O-glycans, and GSL glycans with the transcriptomics of selected TFs in CRC cell <lb/>lines. A, correlation of TFs with fucosyltransferase, (s)Le, and H blood group antigens. B, correlation of TFs with sialylation and corresponding <lb/>GTs. The Spearman method was applied for the correlation analysis between the expression of TFs and glycosylation features. Significant <lb/>values are marked with * (p ≤ 0.05), ** (p ≤ 0.01), *** (p ≤ 0.001) and **** (p ≤ 0.0001). CRC, colorectal cancer; GSL, glycosphingolipid; GT, <lb/>glycosyltransferase; TF, transcription factor. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/></note>

			<page>7 Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 <lb/></page>

			<body>how these glycosylation features contribute to the molecular <lb/>differentiation pattern of CRC cell lines, we integrated the <lb/>available data and assigned them to the different glycosylation <lb/>features (supplemental Tables S2-S5). A clear separation of <lb/>CRC classifications was revealed driven by the glycosylation <lb/>features across the three glycan layers with high abundance of <lb/>(s)Le A/X antigens in colon-like cell lines (Fig. 1), especially for <lb/>cell line LS174T and its parent cell line LS180 (54). A previous <lb/>study suggested that two clonal cell lines, LSB expressing <lb/>only the truncated CA Tn (GalNAcα-Ser/Thr) and sialyl-Tn on <lb/>their mucin molecules and LSC with elongated oligosaccha-<lb/>ride chains, derived from LS174T cell line (55), which might <lb/>result from the genetic variation and differences in epigenetic <lb/>signatures. Due to its natural heterogeneity, cell line LS174T <lb/>might be considered as representative model of primary CRC <lb/>tumor. <lb/>The sLe A/X antigens in glycoproteins and glycolipids are <lb/>typical tumor-associated CAs and are involved in tumor pro-<lb/>gression (4, 5, 56, 57). Interestingly, particularly high expres-<lb/>sion of (s)Le A/X antigens was found in cell line SW1116 in <lb/>which sLe A , also known as CA19-9, was first discovered with <lb/>a mouse monoclonal antibody (1116-NS-19-9) (58-61). <lb/>Nowadays, CA19-9 is used as serum diagnostic biomarker for <lb/>CRC and treatment monitoring and associates with poor <lb/>prognosis (16-18). Moreover, the expression level of sLe A <lb/>shows associations with CRC prognosis, specifically the <lb/>incidence of recurrence and the survival time (62-64). Elevated <lb/>levels of sLe A have been reported for N-, O-glycans, and GSL <lb/>glycans in CRC (65-67) which is in line with our results for <lb/>colon-like cell lines that showed consistent high expression of <lb/>(s)Le A/X antigen across the three glycan classes (Fig. 2). Tak-<lb/>ing the previous findings and current results into account, the <lb/>sLe A/X antigens might be potential targets for treatment of well <lb/>differentiated CRC. A limitation of the current study is its <lb/>inability to fully define Le antigens due to the lack of or low <lb/>abundance of diagnostic ions in tandem MS. Full definition of <lb/>Le antigens may be achieved by implementing orthogonal <lb/>approaches such as ion mobility MS. In addition, Tn antigen <lb/>and other small O-glycans were insufficiently covered in our <lb/>analysis due to the partial loss of small glycans during solid-<lb/>phase extraction cleanup using PGC self-packed columns. To <lb/>address this limitation, additional material needed to be <lb/>investigated for improving solid-phase extraction cleanup. <lb/>More than 3 decades ago, the overexpression of Le Y anti-<lb/>gen was reported in CRC with detection of monoclonal anti-<lb/>body AH6 and considered to be a diagnostic marker of CRC <lb/>(68), and the upregulation of Le B/Y antigens has been attrib-<lb/>uted to poor prognosis of CRC (69). In this study, Le B/Y anti-<lb/>gens were detected across the three glycan classes with no <lb/>significant association between the classes (Fig. 2A). Another <lb/>study demonstrated that transfection of rat CRC cells with <lb/>cDNA encoding for α1-2 fucosyltransferase promoted the <lb/>tumorigenicity and enhances cell motility by increased <lb/>expression of Le B/Y and H blood group antigens (70). Previous <lb/>research reported that increased expression of FUT4 might be <lb/>related to upregulation of Le Y in CRC tissues (71); however, <lb/>according associations were not observed in this study. <lb/>Interestingly, FUT2/3 showed a positive correlation with (A/B) <lb/>Le B/Y antigens on GSL glycans, whereas no correlations were <lb/>observed between FUT2/3 and Le B/Y antigens on N-and O-<lb/>glycans (Fig. 3A), which might suggest GSLs as major sub-<lb/>strates of GTs FUT2/3 for biosynthesis of Le B/Y antigens in <lb/>CRC cell line. FUTs are involved in biosynthesis of Le antigens <lb/>(25, 34, 35, 39, 72, 73). Regarding FUT3, it not only catalyzes <lb/>the synthesis of Le A/X/B/Y , preferring to type chain 1 over type <lb/>chain 2 (72), but also participates in the formation of sLe A and <lb/>disialyl Le A 25, 34-36 . Significant correlations were discovered <lb/>between Le A/X/B/Y , sLe A/X , and (s)dimeric Le A/X with FUT3 <lb/>(Fig. 3A) which suggests associations with the carcinogenesis <lb/>of CRC (74). Besides, upregulation of FUT3 is a marker of <lb/>lower overall survival of breast cancer (75), and knockdown of <lb/>FUT3 inhibits the proliferation, migration, tumorigenesis, and <lb/>TGF-β induced EMT in pancreatic cancer (76). FUT4 contrib-<lb/>utes to the biosynthesis of (s)Le X (37-39) which was observed <lb/>to be positively correlated with (s)Le A/X on GSL glycans but, <lb/>interestingly, not with N-and O-glycans (Fig. 3A). This is not in <lb/>line with literature reporting sLe X to be mainly regulated by <lb/>FUT6 in CRC as well as breast cancer (27, 77). Interestingly, in <lb/>AML cell lines, we found that (s)Le A/X antigen expression was <lb/>positively correlated with FUT7 instead of FUT3/4 (78). We <lb/>hypothesize that the biosynthesis of glycans might be regu-<lb/>lated by different GTs in a disease-and tissue-specific <lb/>manner. FUT6 participates in the formation of (s)Le X antigen <lb/>(43, 44), which positively correlated with Le A/X and (s)dimeric <lb/>Le A/X on O-glycans as well as sLe A/X on N-glycans (Fig. 3A). <lb/>Thus, except for the glycosylation features, the corresponding <lb/>GTs such as FUT3/4/6 might also be promising targets to <lb/>study the underlying mechanism in the development of CRC. <lb/>In addition, the upregulation of H blood group antigens <lb/>(especially on O-glycans and GSL glycans) was found in un-<lb/>differentiated cell lines (Fig. 2B). A previous study demon-<lb/>strated that H blood group antigens modulate the <lb/>tumorigenicity of CRC and contributed to the CRC tumor <lb/>progression (79). Overexpression of H blood group antigen <lb/>caused by upregulation of α1-2 fucosyltransferase has been <lb/>shown to associate with poor prognosis in CRC and promote <lb/>cancer cell mobility (69, 70). Another study indicated α1-2 <lb/>fucosylation as a predictor of postoperative poor prognosis of <lb/>CRC (80). Similarly, ABO (H) blood group expression has po-<lb/>tential as a prognostic factor for recurrence in ovarian and <lb/>vulvar cancer (81). In contrast, in bladder tumor, the lack of <lb/>ABO (H) antigen is a well-documented event and was asso-<lb/>ciated with tumor progression and recurrent disease which are <lb/>attributed to the loss of relevant GT activities due to down-<lb/>regulation of ABO (H) mRNA transcripts (82-84). In the present <lb/>study, although significant correlations were revealed for H <lb/>blood group antigen between three classes of glycans (N-, O-<lb/>glycans, and GSL glycans; Fig. 2A), no significant association <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/>Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 8 <lb/>was observed between H blood group antigen and α1-2 <lb/>fucosyltransferase FUT1 and FUT2 (Fig. 3A). FUT2 rather <lb/>showed positive correlations with (A/B) Le B/Y on GSL glycans <lb/>and integrated (A/B) Le B/Y antigens (Fig. 3A) which have been <lb/>reported to be involved in the poor prognosis of CRC (69). In <lb/>breast cancer, FUT1 and FUT2 have been involved in regu-<lb/>lating growth, adhesion, and migration of breast cancer and <lb/>might serve as a therapeutic target (85). For CRC with undif-<lb/>ferentiated stage, the H blood group antigens and relevant <lb/>GTs may be considered as potential treatment targets. <lb/>CDX1 as a colon-specific TF involved in cell differentiation <lb/>has been associated with different glycosylation features (86). <lb/>In our previous study, we discovered that differentiated cell <lb/>lines expressing CDX1 featured high multifucosylation and <lb/>showed a less invasive and less aggressive phenotype (87). <lb/>The correlation of fucosylation with CDX1 was revealed in <lb/>CRC (87, 88), which presents positive correlations with (A/B) <lb/>Le B/Y on GSL glycans and integrated (A/B)Le B/Y as well as with <lb/>corresponding GTs FUT3 and FUT6 (Fig. 4A). Moreover, we <lb/>found that TF ETS2 upregulated in colon-like cell lines <lb/>significantly correlated with GSL glycans carrying (s)Le A/X and <lb/>(A/B) Le B/Y . ETS2 has been reported to play critical roles <lb/>throughout all stages of tumorigenesis and was demonstrated <lb/>to promote angiogenesis in breast cancer (89, 90). Besides, <lb/>other TFs like HNF1A and HNF4A were found to participate in <lb/>the regulation of antenna fucosylation on N-glycans (86) for <lb/>which no correlation was found in this study. However, posi-<lb/>tive correlations were found for Le A/X and (A/B) Le B/Y antigens <lb/>on GSL glycans with HNF1A and HNF4A as well as with FUT3. <lb/>When exploring the correlation of TF MYB with expression of <lb/>glycosylation features, we found that MYB positively associ-<lb/>ated with (s)Le A/X , (A/B) Le B/Y on GSL glycans, sialyl/sulfo <lb/>Le A/X on O-glycans, and their relevant GTs FUT3/4 (Fig. 4A). <lb/>Upregulation of MYB has been found to be a predictor for poor <lb/>prognosis of CRC (91-93). Taken together, we hypothesize <lb/>that high expression of TFs (CDX1, ETS1, HNF1/4A, MECOM, <lb/>and MYB) might have influence on the overexpression of (s)Le <lb/>antigens in colon-like cell lines by regulation of their corre-<lb/>sponding GT FUT3/4. To prove our hypothesis, more biolog-<lb/>ical experiments are required. In this study, transcriptomic <lb/>expression of TFs was correlated with MS glycomic data to <lb/>obtain insights into the potential regulation of glycan expres-<lb/>sion. The protein expression and activity of these TFs might, <lb/>however, only poorly correlate with transcript expression. <lb/>More experiments such as chip-seq data examining the <lb/>binding of the TFs to the relevant loci need to be conducted in <lb/>future studies. <lb/>In conclusion, the glycosylation patterns across three <lb/>glycan classes were assessed for CRC cell lines. We <lb/>revealed overexpression of (s)Le antigens in colon-like cell <lb/>lines on all three glycan classes and high abundance of H <lb/>blood group antigens or sialylation in undifferentiated cell <lb/>lines. The significate correlations observed between (s)Le <lb/>antigens on three glycan classes with FUT3, partly with <lb/>FUT4/6, instead of other FUTs indicated that FUT3 may be <lb/>the main contributor to the biosynthesis of (s)Le antigens in <lb/>CRC. In addition, FUT3/4 showed stronger correlations with <lb/>(s)Le antigens on GSL glycans compared to that on N-and <lb/>O-glycans, indicating that FUT3/4 might preference for <lb/>expression of (s)Le antigens on three class glycans. The <lb/>discovered relationship between upstream TFs with (s)Le <lb/>antigens and FUT3 indicates that these upstream TFs might <lb/>contribute to the upregulation of (s)Le antigens via regulation <lb/>of FUT3. <lb/></body>

            <div type="availability">DATA AVAILABILITY <lb/>Glycomics data for CRC cell lines were obtained from Gly-<lb/>coPOST: GPST000239 (GSL glycans), GPST000035 (O-<lb/>glycan), and GPST000302 (N-glycan). The transcriptomics <lb/>data of CRC cell lines were retrieved from the Gene Expres-<lb/>sion Omnibus GSE97023. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Supplemental Data -This article contains supplemental <lb/>data (20-23,94) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments -We kindly thank Noortje de Haan and <lb/>Constantin Blöchl for fruitful discussions and suggestions. <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">Funding and additional information -D. W. is supported by <lb/>the China Scholarship Council with File No. 201806220100. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Author contributions -D. W., K. M., G. S. M. L.-K., and M. <lb/>W. conceptualization; D. W. methodology; D. W. and O. A. M. <lb/>software; D. W. validation; D. W. investigation; D. W. and K. M. <lb/>resources; D. W. data curation; D. W. writing-original draft; D. <lb/>W., K. M., O. A. M., G. S. M. L.-K., and M. W. writing-review &amp; <lb/>editing; D. W., K. M., O. A. M., G. S. M. L.-K., and M. W. <lb/>visualization; M. W. supervision. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Conflict of interest -The authors declare no competing <lb/>interests. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Abbreviations -The abbreviations used are: CA, carbohy-<lb/>drate antigen; CRC, colorectal cancer; ECM, extracellular <lb/>matrix; EMT, epithelial-mesenchymal transition; GalNAc, N-<lb/>acetylgalactosamine; GSL, glycosphingolipid; GT, glycosyl-<lb/>transferase; sLe X , Sialyl Lewis X; TF, transcription factor. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received November 3, 2023, and in revised form, April 3, 2024 <lb/>Published, MCPRO Papers in Press, April 25, 2024, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.mcpro.2024.100776 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Sung, H., Ferlay, J., Siegel, R. L., Laversanne, M., Soerjomataram, I., Jemal, <lb/>A., et al. (2021) Global cancer statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN estimates of <lb/>incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. CA <lb/>Cancer J. Clin. 71, 209-249 <lb/>2. Lavanya, V., Adil, M., Ahmed, N., Rishi, A., and Jamal, S. (2014) Small <lb/>molecule inhibitors as emerging cancer therapeutics. Integr. Cancer Sci. <lb/>Ther. 1, 39-46 <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/>9 Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 <lb/>3. Sharkey, R. M., and Goldenberg, D. M. (2006) Targeted therapy of cancer: <lb/>new prospects for antibodies and immunoconjugates. CA Cancer J. Clin. <lb/>56, 226-243 <lb/>4. Costa, A. F., Campos, D., Reis, C. A., and Gomes, C. (2020) Targeting <lb/>glycosylation: a new road for cancer drug discovery. Trends Cancer 6, <lb/>757-766 <lb/>5. Pinho, S. S., and Reis, C. A. (2015) Glycosylation in cancer: mechanisms <lb/>and clinical implications. Nat. Rev. Cancer 15, 540-555 <lb/>6. Bastian, K., Scott, E., Elliott, D. J., and Munkley, J. (2021) FUT8 alpha-(1,6)-<lb/>fucosyltransferase in cancer. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 22, 455 <lb/>7. Groux-Degroote, S., Vicogne, D., Cogez, V., Schulz, C., and Harduin-<lb/>Lepers, A. (2021) B4GALNT2 controls sd(a) and SLe(x) antigen biosyn-<lb/>thesis in healthy and cancer human colon. Chembiochem 22, 3381-3390 <lb/>8. Deschuyter, M., Leger, D. Y., Verboom, A., Chaunavel, A., Maftah, A., and <lb/>Petit, J. M. (2022) ST3GAL2 knock-down decreases tumoral character of <lb/>colorectal cancer cells in vitro and in vivo. Am. J. Cancer Res. 12, 280-302 <lb/>9. Venturi, G., Gomes Ferreira, I., Pucci, M., Ferracin, M., Malagolini, N., <lb/>Chiricolo, M., et al. (2019) Impact of sialyltransferase ST6GAL1 over-<lb/>expression on different colon cancer cell types. Glycobiology 29, 684-<lb/>695 <lb/>10. Kellokumpu, S., Sormunen, R., and Kellokumpu, I. (2002) Abnormal glyco-<lb/>sylation and altered Golgi structure in colorectal cancer: dependence on <lb/>intra-Golgi pH. FEBS Lett. 516, 217-224 <lb/>11. Gill, D. J., Chia, J., Senewiratne, J., and Bard, F. (2010) Regulation of O-<lb/>glycosylation through Golgi-to-ER relocation of initiation enzymes. J. Cell <lb/>Biol. 189, 843-858 <lb/>12. Kumamoto, K., Goto, Y., Sekikawa, K., Takenoshita, S., Ishida, N., Kawa-<lb/>kita, M., et al. (2001) Increased expression of UDP-galactose transporter <lb/>messenger RNA in human colon cancer tissues and its implication in <lb/>synthesis of Thomsen-Friedenreich antigen and sialyl Lewis A/X de-<lb/>terminants. Cancer Res. 61, 4620-4627 <lb/>13. Hakomori, S. (2002) Glycosylation defining cancer malignancy: new wine in <lb/>an old bottle. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 99, 10231-10233 <lb/>14. Seales, E. C., Jurado, G. A., Brunson, B. A., Wakefield, J. K., Frost, A. R., <lb/>and Bellis, S. L. (2005) Hypersialylation of β1 integrins, observed in colon <lb/>adenocarcinoma, may contribute to cancer progression by up-regulating <lb/>cell motility. Cancer Res. 65, 4645-4652 <lb/>15. Nakamori, S., Kameyama, M., Imaoka, S., Furukawa, H., Ishikawa, O., <lb/>Sasaki, Y., et al. (1993) Increased expression of sialyl Lewisx antigen <lb/>correlates with poor survival in patients with colorectal carcinoma: clini-<lb/>copathological and immunohistochemical study. Cancer Res. 53, 3632-<lb/>3637 <lb/>16. Wang, W.-S., Lin, J.-K., Chiou, T.-J., Liu, J.-H., Fan, F. S., Yen, C.-C., et al. <lb/>(2002) CA19-9 as the most significant prognostic indicator of metastatic <lb/>colorectal cancer. Hepatogastroenterology 49, 160-164 <lb/>17. Singh, S., Kumar, R., Kumar, U., and Kumari, R. (2020) Clinical significance <lb/>and role of TK1, CEA, CA 19-9 and CA 72-4 levels in diagnosis of <lb/>colorectal cancers. Asian Pac. J. Cancer Prev. 21, 3133-3136 <lb/>18. Wu, T., Mo, Y., and Wu, C. (2020) Prognostic values of CEA, CA19-9, and <lb/>CA72-4 in patients with stages I-III colorectal cancer. Int. J. Clin. Exp. <lb/>Pathol. 13, 1608-1614 <lb/>19. Reis, C. A., Osorio, H., Silva, L., Gomes, C., and David, L. (2010) Alterations <lb/>in glycosylation as biomarkers for cancer detection. J. Clin. Pathol. 63, <lb/>322-329 <lb/>20. Berg, K. C. G., Eide, P. W., Eilertsen, I. A., Johannessen, B., Bruun, J., <lb/>Danielsen, S. A., et al. (2017) Multi-omics of 34 colorectal cancer cell lines <lb/>-a resource for biomedical studies. Mol. Cancer 16, 116 <lb/>21. Wang, D., Madunic, K., Zhang, T., Mayboroda, O. A., Lageveen-Kammeijer, <lb/>G. S. M., and Wuhrer, M. (2022) High diversity of glycosphingolipid gly-<lb/>cans of colorectal cancer cell lines reflects the cellular differentiation <lb/>phenotype. Mol. Cell. Proteomics 21, 100239 <lb/>22. Wang, D., Kuzyk, V., Madunic, K., Zhang, T., Mayboroda, O. A., Wuhrer, M., <lb/>et al. (2023) In-depth analysis of the N-glycome of colorectal cancer cell <lb/>lines. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 24, 4842 <lb/>23. Madunic, K., Zhang, T., Mayboroda, O. A., Holst, S., Stavenhagen, K., Jin, <lb/>C., et al. (2021) Colorectal cancer cell lines show striking diversity of their <lb/>O-glycome reflecting the cellular differentiation phenotype. Cell. Mol. Life <lb/>Sci. 78, 337-350 <lb/>24. Brockhausen, I., Wandall, H. H., Ten Hagen, K. G., and Stanley, P. (2022) <lb/>O-GalNAc glycans. In: Essentials of Glycobiology, 4th Ed, Cold Spring <lb/>Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold Spring Harbor, NY <lb/>25. Tsuchida, A., Okajima, T., Furukawa, K., Ando, T., Ishida, H., Yoshida, A., <lb/>et al. (2003) Synthesis of disialyl Lewis a (Le(a)) structure in colon cancer <lb/>cell lines by a sialyltransferase, ST6GalNAc VI, responsible for the syn-<lb/>thesis of alpha-series gangliosides. J. Biol. Chem. 278, 22787-22794 <lb/>26. Senda, M., Ito, A., Tsuchida, A., Hagiwara, T., Kaneda, T., Nakamura, Y., <lb/>et al. (2007) Identification and expression of a sialyltransferase respon-<lb/>sible for the synthesis of disialylgalactosylgloboside in normal and ma-<lb/>lignant kidney cells: downregulation of ST6GalNAc VI in renal cancers. <lb/>Biochem. J. 402, 459-470 <lb/>27. Matsuura, N., Narita, T., Hiraiwa, N., Hiraiwa, M., Murai, H., Iwase, T., et al. <lb/>(1998) Gene expression of fucosyl-and sialyl-transferases which syn-<lb/>thesize sialyl Lewisx, the carbohydrate ligands for E-selectin, in human <lb/>breast cancer. Int. J. Oncol. 12, 1157-1164 <lb/>28. Hiraiwa, N., Yabuta, T., Yoritomi, K., Hiraiwa, M., Tanaka, Y., Suzuki, T., <lb/>et al. (2003) Transactivation of the fucosyltransferase VII gene by human <lb/>T-cell leukemia virus type 1 Tax through a variant cAMP-responsive <lb/>element. Blood 101, 3615-3621 <lb/>29. Watanabe, Y., Aoki-Kinoshita, K. F., Ishihama, Y., and Okuda, S. (2021) <lb/>GlycoPOST realizes FAIR principles for glycomics mass spectrometry <lb/>data. Nucleic Acids Res. 49, D1523-D1528 <lb/>30. Mouradov, D., Sloggett, C., Jorissen, R. N., Love, C. G., Li, S., Burgess, A. <lb/>W., et al. (2014) Colorectal cancer cell lines are representative models of <lb/>the main molecular subtypes of primary cancer. Cancer Res. 74, 3238-<lb/>3247 <lb/>31. Ahmed, D., Eide, P. W., Eilertsen, I. A., Danielsen, S. A., Eknaes, M., Hek-<lb/>toen, M., et al. (2013) Epigenetic and genetic features of 24 colon cancer <lb/>cell lines. Oncogenesis 2, e71 <lb/>32. Kelly, R. J., Rouquier, S., Giorgi, D., Lennon, G. G., and Lowe, J. B. (1995) <lb/>Sequence and expression of a candidate for the human secretor blood <lb/>group alpha(1,2)fucosyltransferase gene (FUT2). Homozygosity for an <lb/>enzyme-inactivating nonsense mutation commonly correlates with the <lb/>non-secretor phenotype. J. Biol. Chem. 270, 4640-4649 <lb/>33. Boren, T., Falk, P., Roth, K. A., Larson, G., and Normark, S. (1993) <lb/>Attachment of Helicobacter pylori to human gastric epithelium mediated <lb/>by blood group antigens. Science 262, 1892-1895 <lb/>34. Kukowska-Latallo, J. F., Larsen, R. D., Nair, R. P., and Lowe, J. B. (1990) <lb/>A cloned human cDNA determines expression of a mouse stage-specific <lb/>embryonic antigen and the Lewis blood group alpha(1,3/1,4)fucosyl-<lb/>transferase. Genes Dev. 4, 1288-1303 <lb/>35. Aubert, M., Panicot-Dubois, L., Crotte, C., Sbarra, V., Lombardo, D., <lb/>Sadoulet, M. O., et al. (2000) Peritoneal colonization by human pancreatic <lb/>cancer cells is inhibited by antisense FUT3 sequence. Int. J. Cancer 88, <lb/>558-565 <lb/>36. Cai, Y. J., Zheng, X. F., Lu, C. H., Jiang, Q., Liu, Q., and Xin, Y. H. (2016) <lb/>Effect of FUT3 gene silencing with miRNA on proliferation, invasion and <lb/>migration abilities of human KATO-III gastric cancer cell line. Cell. Mol. <lb/>Biol. (Noisy-le-grand) 62, 15-20 <lb/>37. Goelz, S. E., Hession, C., Goff, D., Griffiths, B., Tizard, R., Newman, B., et al. <lb/>(1990) ELFT: a gene that directs the expression of an ELAM-1 ligand. Cell <lb/>63, 1349-1356 <lb/>38. Lowe, J. B., Kukowska-Latallo, J. F., Nair, R. P., Larsen, R. D., Marks, R. M., <lb/>Macher, B. A., et al. (1991) Molecular cloning of a human fucosyl-<lb/>transferase gene that determines expression of the Lewis x and VIM-2 <lb/>epitopes but not ELAM-1-dependent cell adhesion. J. Biol. Chem. 266, <lb/>17467-17477 <lb/>39. Mondal, N., Dykstra, B., Lee, J., Ashline, D. J., Reinhold, V. N., Rossi, D. J., <lb/>et al. (2018) Distinct human alpha(1,3)-fucosyltransferases drive Lewis-X/ <lb/>sialyl Lewis-X assembly in human cells. J. Biol. Chem. 293, 7300-7314 <lb/>40. Dupuy, F., Germot, A., Julien, R., and Maftah, A. (2004) Structure/function <lb/>study of Lewis alpha3-and alpha3/4-fucosyltransferases: the alpha1,4 <lb/>fucosylation requires an aromatic residue in the acceptor-binding <lb/>domain. Glycobiology 14, 347-356 <lb/>41. Nguyen, A. T., Holmes, E. H., Whitaker, J. M., Ho, S., Shetterly, S., and <lb/>Macher, B. A. (1998) Human alpha1,3/4-fucosyltransferases. I. Identifi-<lb/>cation of amino acids involved in acceptor substrate binding by site-<lb/>directed mutagenesis. J. Biol. Chem. 273, 25244-25249 <lb/>42. Shetterly, S., Jost, F., Watson, S. R., Knegtel, R., Macher, B. A., and <lb/>Holmes, E. H. (2007) Site-specific fucosylation of sialylated polylactos-<lb/>amines by alpha1,3/4-fucosyltransferases-V and -VI Is defined by amino <lb/>acids near the N terminus of the catalytic domain. J. Biol. Chem. 282, <lb/>24882-24892 <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/>Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 10 <lb/>43. Koszdin, K. L., and Bowen, B. R. (1992) The cloning and expression of a <lb/>human alpha-1,3 fucosyltransferase capable of forming the E-selectin <lb/>ligand. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 187, 152-157 <lb/>44. Weston, B. W., Smith, P. L., Kelly, R. J., and Lowe, J. B. (1992) Molecular <lb/>cloning of a fourth member of a human alpha (1,3)fucosyltransferase gene <lb/>family. Multiple homologous sequences that determine expression of the <lb/>Lewis x, sialyl Lewis x, and difucosyl sialyl Lewis x epitopes. J. Biol. <lb/>Chem. 267, 24575-24584 <lb/>45. Ihara, H., Ikeda, Y., Toma, S., Wang, X., Suzuki, T., Gu, J., et al. (2007) <lb/>Crystal structure of mammalian alpha1,6-fucosyltransferase, FUT8. Gly-<lb/>cobiology 17, 455-466 <lb/>46. Ortiz-Soto, M. E., Reising, S., Schlosser, A., and Seibel, J. (2019) Structural <lb/>and functional role of disulphide bonds and substrate binding residues of <lb/>the human beta-galactoside alpha-2,3-sialyltransferase 1 (hST3Gal1). <lb/>Sci. Rep. 9, 17993 <lb/>47. Kitagawa, H., and Paulson, J. C. (1994) Cloning of a novel alpha 2,3-<lb/>sialyltransferase that sialylates glycoprotein and glycolipid carbohydrate <lb/>groups. J. Biol. Chem. 269, 1394-1401 <lb/>48. Basu, S. S., Basu, M., Li, Z., and Basu, S. (1996) Characterization of two <lb/>glycolipid:α2-3sialyltransferases, SAT-3 (CMP-NeuAc:nLcOse4Cer α2-<lb/>3sialyltransferase) and SAT-4 (CMP-NeuAc:GgOse4Cer α2-3sialyl-<lb/>transferase), from human colon carcinoma (Colo 205) cell line. <lb/>Biochemistry 35, 5166-5174 <lb/>49. Kim, Y.-J., Kim, K.-S., Kim, S.-H., Kim, C.-H., Ko, J. H., Choe, I.-S., et al. <lb/>(1996) Molecular cloning and expression of human Galβ1,3GalNAc α2,3-<lb/>sialyltransferase (hST3Gal II). Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 228, <lb/>324-327 <lb/>50. Giordanengo, V., Bannwarth, S., Laffont, C., Van Miegem, V., Harduin-<lb/>Lepers, A., Delannoy, P., et al. (1997) Cloning and expression of cDNA for <lb/>a human Gal(beta1-3)GalNAc alpha2,3-sialyltransferase from the CEM T-<lb/>cell line. Eur. J. Biochem. 247, 558-566 <lb/>51. Ishii, A., Ohta, M., Watanabe, Y., Matsuda, K., Ishiyama, K., Sakoe, K., et al. <lb/>(1998) Expression cloning and functional characterization of human cDNA <lb/>for ganglioside GM3 synthase. J. Biol. Chem. 273, 31652-31655 <lb/>52. Wu, Z. L., Ethen, C. M., Prather, B., Machacek, M., and Jiang, W. (2011) <lb/>Universal phosphatase-coupled glycosyltransferase assay. Glycobiology <lb/>21, 727-733 <lb/>53. Kuhn, B., Benz, J., Greif, M., Engel, A. M., Sobek, H., and Rudolph, M. G. <lb/>(2013) The structure of human alpha-2,6-sialyltransferase reveals the <lb/>binding mode of complex glycans. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr. <lb/>69, 1826-1838 <lb/>54. Tom, B. H., Rutzky, L. P., Jakstys, M. M., Oyasu, R., Kaye, C. I., and Kahan, <lb/>B. D. (1976) Human colonic adenocarcinoma cells. I. Establishment and <lb/>description of a new line. In Vitro 12, 180-191 <lb/>55. Brockhausen, I., Yang, J., Dickinson, N., Ogata, S., and Itzkowitz, S. H. <lb/>(1998) Enzymatic basis for sialyl-Tn expression in human colon cancer <lb/>cells. Glycoconj J. 15, 595-603 <lb/>56. Gomes, C., Almeida, A., Barreira, A., Calheiros, J., Pinto, F., Abrantes, R., <lb/>et al. (2019) Carcinoembryonic antigen carrying SLe(X) as a new <lb/>biomarker of more aggressive gastric carcinomas. Theranostics 9, 7431-<lb/>7446 <lb/>57. Ugorski, M., and Laskowska, A. (2002) Sialyl Lewis(a): a tumor-associated <lb/>carbohydrate antigen involved in adhesion and metastatic potential of <lb/>cancer cells. Acta Biochim. Pol. 49, 303-311 <lb/>58. Koprowski, H., Steplewski, Z., Mitchell, K., Herlyn, M., Herlyn, D., and <lb/>Fuhrer, P. (1979) Colorectal carcinoma antigens detected by hybridoma <lb/>antibodies. Somatic Cell Genet. 5, 957-971 <lb/>59. Lee, T., Teng, T. Z. J., and Shelat, V. G. (2020) Carbohydrate antigen 19-9 -<lb/>tumor marker: past, present, and future. World J. Gastrointest. Surg. 12, <lb/>468-490 <lb/>60. Scar à, S., Bottoni, P., and Scatena, R. (2015) CA 19-9: biochemical and <lb/>clinical aspects. In: Scatena, R., ed. Advances in Cancer Biomarkers: <lb/>From Biochemistry to Clinic for a Critical Revision, Springer, Dordrecht, <lb/>SH: 247-260 <lb/>61. Klug, T. L., LeDonne, N. C., Greber, T. F., and Zurawski, V. R., Jr. (1988) <lb/>Purification and composition of a novel gastrointestinal tumor-associated <lb/>glycoprotein expressing sialylated lacto-N-fucopentaose II (CA 19-9). <lb/>Cancer Res. 48, 1505-1511 <lb/>62. Shimono, R., Mori, M., Akazawa, K., Adachi, Y., and Sgimachi, K. (1994) <lb/>Immunohistochemical expression of carbohydrate antigen 19-9 in colo-<lb/>rectal carcinoma. Am. J. Gastroenterol. 89, 101-105 <lb/>63. Nakayama, T., Watanabe, M., Katsumata, T., Teramoto, T., and Kitajima, M. <lb/>(1995) Expression of Sialyl Lewisa as a new prognostic factor for patients <lb/>with advanced colorectal carcinoma. Cancer 75, 2051-2056 <lb/>64. Yamada, N., Chung, Y. S., Takatsuka, S., Arimoto, Y., Sawada, T., Dohi, T., <lb/>et al. (1997) Increased sialyl Lewis A expression and fucosyltransferase <lb/>activity with acquisition of a high metastatic capacity in a colon cancer <lb/>cell line. Br. J. Cancer 76, 582-587 <lb/>65. Magnani, J. L., Nilsson, B., Brockhaus, M., Zopf, D., Steplewski, Z., <lb/>Koprowski, H., et al. (1982) A monoclonal antibody-defined antigen <lb/>associated with gastrointestinal cancer is a ganglioside containing sia-<lb/>lylated lacto-N-fucopentaose II. J. Biol. Chem. 257, 14365-14369 <lb/>66. Baeckström, D., Hansson, G. C., Nilsson, O., Johansson, C., Gendler, S. J., <lb/>and Lindholm, L. (1991) Purification and characterization of a membrane-<lb/>bound and a secreted mucin-type glycoprotein carrying the carcinoma-<lb/>associated sialyl-Lea epitope on distinct core proteins. J. Biol. Chem. <lb/>266, 21537-21547 <lb/>67. Sawada, R., Lowe, J. B., and Fukuda, M. (1993) E-selectin-dependent <lb/>adhesion efficiency of colonic carcinoma cells is increased by genetic <lb/>manipulation of their cell surface lysosomal membrane glycoprotein-1 <lb/>expression levels. J. Biol. Chem. 268, 12675-12681 <lb/>68. Abe, K., Hakomori, S.-I., and Ohshiba, S. (1986) Differential expression <lb/>of difucosyl type 2 chain (LeY) defined by monoclonal antibody AH6 <lb/>in different locations of colonic epithelia, various histological types <lb/>of colonic polyps, and Adenocarcinomas1. Cancer Res. 46, 2639-<lb/>2644 <lb/>69. Naitoh, H., Nakajima, T., Nagamachi, Y., and Yazawa, S. (1994) <lb/>A clinicopathological evaluation of anti-fucosylated antigens antibody <lb/>(YB-2) in colorectal carcinoma. Glycosylation Dis. 1, 31-36 <lb/>70. Goupille, C., Hallouin, F., Meflah, K., and Le Pendu, J. (1997) Increase of rat <lb/>colon carcinoma cells tumorigenicity by alpha(1-2) fucosyltransferase <lb/>gene transfection. Glycobiology 7, 221-229 <lb/>71. Ito, H., Hiraiwa, N., Sawada-Kasugai, M., Akamatsu, S., Tachikawa, T., <lb/>Kasai, Y., et al. (1997) Altered mRNA expression of specific molecular <lb/>species of fucosyl-and sialyl-transferases in human colorectal cancer <lb/>tissues. Int. J. Cancer 71, 556-564 <lb/>72. de Vries, T., Srnka, C. A., Palcic, M. M., Swiedler, S. J., van den Eijnden, D. <lb/>H., and Macher, B. A. (1995) Acceptor specificity of different length <lb/>constructs of human recombinant alpha 1,3/4-fucosyltransferases. <lb/>Replacement of the stem region and the transmembrane domain of <lb/>fucosyltransferase V by protein A results in an enzyme with GDP-fucose <lb/>hydrolyzing activity. J. Biol. Chem. 270, 8712-8722 <lb/>73. Weston, B. W., Nair, R. P., Larsen, R. D., and Lowe, J. B. (1992) Isolation of <lb/>a novel human alpha (1,3)fucosyltransferase gene and molecular com-<lb/>parison to the human Lewis blood group alpha (1,3/1,4)fucosyltransferase <lb/>gene. Syntenic, homologous, nonallelic genes encoding enzymes with <lb/>distinct acceptor substrate specificities. J. Biol. Chem. 267, 4152-4160 <lb/>74. Hu, X., Chen, F., Ji, W., and Wang, Y. (2022) Correlations of FUT3 gene <lb/>polymorphisms with colon polyps. Cell Cycle 21, 117-125 <lb/>75. do Nascimento, J. C. F., Beltrao, E. I. C., and Rocha, C. R. C. (2020) High <lb/>FUT3 expression is a marker of lower overall survival of breast cancer <lb/>patients. Glycoconj J. 37, 263-275 <lb/>76. Zhan, L., Chen, L., and Chen, Z. (2018) Knockdown of FUT3 disrupts the <lb/>proliferation, migration, tumorigenesis and TGF-beta induced EMT in <lb/>pancreatic cancer cells. Oncol. Lett. 16, 924-930 <lb/>77. Trinchera, M., Malagolini, N., Chiricolo, M., Santini, D., Minni, F., Caretti, A., <lb/>et al. (2011) The biosynthesis of the selectin-ligand sialyl Lewis x in <lb/>colorectal cancer tissues is regulated by fucosyltransferase VI and can be <lb/>inhibited by an RNA interference-based approach. Int. J. Biochem. Cell <lb/>Biol. 43, 130-139 <lb/>78. Blochl, C., Wang, D., Mayboroda, O. A., Lageveen-Kammeijer, G. S. M., and <lb/>Wuhrer, M. (2023) Transcriptionally imprinted glycomic signatures of <lb/>acute myeloid leukemia. Cell Biosci. 13, 31 <lb/>79. Labarri ère, N., Piau, J. P., Otry, C., Denis, M., Lustenberger, P., Meflah, <lb/>K., et al. (1994) H blood group antigen carried by CD44V modulates <lb/>tumorigenicity of rat colon carcinoma cells. Cancer Res. 54, 6275-<lb/>6281 <lb/>80. Tsuboi, K., Asao, T., Ide, M., Hashimoto, S., Noguchi, K., Kominato, Y., et al. <lb/>(2007) Alpha1,2fucosylation is a superior predictor of postoperative <lb/>prognosis for colorectal cancer compared with blood group A, B, or sialyl <lb/>Lewis X antigen generated within colorectal tumor tissues. Ann. Surg. <lb/>Oncol. 14, 1880-1889 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/></note>

			<page>11 Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>81. Montavon Sartorius, C., Schoetzau, A., Kettelhack, H., Fink, D., <lb/>Hacker, N. F., Fedier, A., et al. (2018) ABO blood groups as a <lb/>prognostic factor for recurrence in ovarian and vulvar cancer. PLoS <lb/>One 13, e0195213 <lb/>82. Orlow, I., Lacombe, L., Pellicer, I., Rabbani, F., Delgado, R., Zhang, Z. <lb/>F., et al. (1998) Genotypic and phenotypic characterization of the <lb/>histoblood group ABO(H) in primary bladder tumors. Int. J. Cancer <lb/>75, 819-824 <lb/>83. Decenzo, J. M., Howard, P., and Irish, C. E. (1975) Antigenic deletion and <lb/>prognosis of patients with stage A transitional cell bladder carcinoma. J. <lb/>Urol. 114, 874-878 <lb/>84. Mandel, U., Langkilde, N. C., Orntoft, T. F., Therkildsen, M. H., Kar-<lb/>kov, J., Reibel, J., et al. (1992) Expression of histo-blood-group-A/ <lb/>B-gene-defined glycosyltransferases in normal and malignant <lb/>epithelia: correlation with A/B-carbohydrate expression. Int. J. <lb/>Cancer 52, 7-12 <lb/>85. Lai, T. Y., Chen, I. J., Lin, R. J., Liao, G. S., Yeo, H. L., Ho, C. L., et al. (2019) <lb/>Fucosyltransferase 1 and 2 play pivotal roles in breast cancer cells. Cell <lb/>Death Discov. 5, 74 <lb/>86. Holst, S., Wilding, J. L., Koprowska, K., Rombouts, Y., and Wuhrer, M. <lb/>(2019) N-Glycomic and transcriptomic changes associated with CDX1 <lb/>mRNA expression in colorectal cancer cell lines. Cells 8, 273 <lb/>87. Holst, S., Deuss, A. J., van Pelt, G. W., van Vliet, S. J., Garcia-Vallejo, J. J., <lb/>Koeleman, C. A., et al. (2016) N-Glycosylation profiling of colorectal <lb/>cancer cell lines reveals association of fucosylation with differentiation <lb/>and caudal type homebox 1 (CDX1)/Villin mRNA expression. Mol. Cell. <lb/>Proteomics 15, 124-140 <lb/>88. Jones, M. F., Hara, T., Francis, P., Li, X. L., Bilke, S., Zhu, Y., et al. <lb/>(2015) The CDX1-microRNA-215 axis regulates colorectal cancer <lb/>stem cell differentiation. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 112, E1550-<lb/>E1558 <lb/>89. Sizemore, G. M., Pitarresi, J. R., Balakrishnan, S., and Ostrowski, M. C. <lb/>(2017) The ETS family of oncogenic transcription factors in solid tumours. <lb/>Nat. Rev. Cancer 17, 337-351 <lb/>90. Wallace, J. A., Li, F., Balakrishnan, S., Cantemir-Stone, C. Z., Pecot, T., <lb/>Martin, C., et al. (2013) Ets2 in tumor fibroblasts promotes angiogenesis <lb/>in breast cancer. PLoS One 8, e71533 <lb/>91. Biroccio, A., Benassi, B., D&apos;Agnano, I., D&apos;Angelo, C., Buglioni, S., Motto-<lb/>lese, M., et al. (2001) c-Myb and Bcl-x overexpression predicts poor <lb/>prognosis in colorectal cancer: clinical and experimental findings. Am. J. <lb/>Pathol. 158, 1289-1299 <lb/>92. Stenman, G., Andersson, M. K., and Andren, Y. (2010) New tricks from an <lb/>old oncogene: gene fusion and copy number alterations of MYB in human <lb/>cancer. Cell Cycle 9, 2986-2995 <lb/>93. Fry, E. A., and Inoue, K. (2019) c-MYB and DMTF1 in Cancer. Cancer Invest. <lb/>37, 46-65 <lb/>94. Sveen, A., Bruun, J., Eide, P. W., Eilertsen, I. A., Ramirez, L., Murumagi, A., <lb/>et al. (2018) Colorectal cancer consensus molecular subtypes translated <lb/>to preclinical models uncover potentially targetable cancer cell de-<lb/>pendencies. Clin Cancer Res 24, 794-806 <lb/>(Sialyl)Lewis Antigen Significantly Involved With Colon-Like Differentiation <lb/>Mol Cell Proteomics (2024) 23(6) 100776 12 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
