<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">The Impact of a City’s Healthcare Resources on Immigrants’ Employment Quality</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Ping</forename>
            <surname>Li</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Ziqi</forename>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Liting</forename>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-31T11:09:43.487201Z">31.10.2025 11:09:43</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1177$1$21582440241268520</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1177/21582440241268520</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Ping Li, Ziqi Wang, Liting Zhao. (2024). The Impact of a City’s Healthcare Resources on Immigrants’ Employment Quality. Sage Open, 14(3), None. DOI: 10.1177/21582440241268520</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-31T11:09:43.487201Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-31T11:09:43.487201Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>278 <lb/>Apollo Medicine Volume 21 Issue 3 September 2024 <lb/>Apollo Medicine <lb/>21(3) 278-280, 2024 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s) <lb/>Article reuse guidelines: <lb/>in.sagepub.com/journals-permissions-india <lb/>DOI: 10.1177/09760016241240000 <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/home/aom <lb/>Creative Commons Non Commercial CC BY-NC: This article is distributed <lb/>under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial <lb/>4.0 License (http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits non-<lb/>Commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission <lb/>provided the original work is attributed as specified on the Sage and Open Access pages <lb/>(https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage). <lb/>Submitted: 14-Aug-2023 <lb/>Revised: 15-Nov-2023 <lb/>Accepted: 27-Nov-2023 <lb/>Published: 30-Mar-2024 <lb/>How to cite this article: Kumar M, Singh P, Kumari P, Kumar S. Is it air <lb/>or fat? Chyluria as the lesser known cause of dark fluid levels within the <lb/>urinary system -A case report. Apollo Med 2024;21:278-280. <lb/>Case Report <lb/>Is It Air or Fat? Chyluria as the Lesser Known Cause of <lb/>Dark Fluid Levels within the Urinary System <lb/>Manish Kumar 1,2 , Priya Singh 2 , Priti Kumari 3 , Shashikant Kumar 4 <lb/>1,4 Department of Radiodiagnosis, AIIMS, Raipur, Chhattisgarh, 2 Department of Radiodiagnosis, KNS Institute of Medical Science, <lb/>Barabanki, UP, 3 BPS Goverment Medical College for Women, Sonipat, Haryana, India <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Chyluria is caused by the development of the reno-lymphatic fistula leading to reflux of chyle in urine. The most common cause of chyluria <lb/>is a parasitic infection, especially lymphatic filariasis; however, rarely chronic renal infections like tuberculosis can also cause chyluria. The <lb/>presence of fat fluid level in the pelvicalyceal system, perinephric, retroperitoneal collections and in the urinary bladder on CT scan in a case <lb/>of chronic pyelonephritis is an important indicator of the presence of the reno-lymphatic fistula. We describe clinical picture and CT images <lb/>of a patient with chyluria showing fat fluid in abdominal collections. <lb/>Keywords: Chylous retroperitoneal collections, chyluria, computed tomography <lb/>Address for correspondence: Dr. Manish Kumar, <lb/>AIIMS, Raipur, Chhattisgarh, India. <lb/>E-mail: manish2k4@gmail.com <lb/></front>

    <body>IntroductIon <lb/>Dark fluid levels within the urinary system are commonly <lb/>encountered in radiology practice, and its most common <lb/>cause is an air-fluid level due to emphysematous infections. <lb/>Rarely, a dark-fluid level may be caused by fat-fluid level <lb/>occurring in the setting of chyluria. Chyluria is caused by the <lb/>development of the reno-lymphatic fistula, leading to reflux <lb/>of chyle in urine. The most common cause of chyluria is a <lb/>parasitic infection, especially lymphatic filariasis, but rarely <lb/>chronic renal infections such as tuberculosis can also cause <lb/>chyluria. The presence of fat-fluid level in the pelvicalyceal <lb/>system, perinephric, retroperitoneal collections, and in the <lb/>urinary bladder on computed tomography (CT) scan in a case <lb/>of chronic pyelonephritis is an important indicator of the <lb/>presence of the reno-lymphatic fistula. Due to its rarity, it <lb/>may be mistaken for the more common air-fluid level within <lb/>the urinary system seen in emphysematous infections. Due to <lb/>its rarity, imaging diagnosis of chyluria is often overlooked <lb/>and confused with the more common air-fluid level in the <lb/>pelvicalyceal system and urinary bladder. A measurement of <lb/>the Hounsfield unit (HU) value of the hypodense component <lb/>in any dark-fluid level with the urinary bladder is needed for <lb/>a prompt radiological diagnosis. We describe clinical pictures <lb/>and CT images of a patient with chyluria showing fat-fluid in <lb/>abdominal collections. <lb/>case report <lb/>A 35-year-old female presented with fever, abdominal <lb/>distension, white-colored urine, and left lumbar pain for <lb/>15 days. She was previously diagnosed with Staghorn <lb/>calculus with moderate hydronephrosis in the left kidney and <lb/>treated with percutaneous nephrolithotomy about 1.5 years <lb/>back. About 6 months later, she again presented with <lb/>pyonephrosis and multiple renal calculi, for which she <lb/>underwent D-J stenting and had gradually improved. <lb/></body>

    <page>279 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Apollo Medicine Volume 21 Issue 3 September 2024 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Kumar, et al.: Is it air or fat? Chyluria as the lesser known cause of dark fluid levels within the urinary system <lb/></note>

    <body>Investigations <lb/>The present routine blood investigations revealed raised total <lb/>leukocyte count (18,000 cells/mm 3 ) with increased neutrophil <lb/>counts. The rest of the blood parameters were unremarkable <lb/>including the blood lipid profile. Urine examination revealed <lb/>the presence of chyle in urine with raised triglyceride levels <lb/>and multiple pus cells. Urine culture was negative. <lb/>Ultrasonography revealed a small left kidney with mild <lb/>hydronephrosis, mildly thinned renal parenchyma, few renal <lb/>calculi, and perinephric and capsular calcifications. Associated <lb/>multiple loculated retroperitoneal collections were seen. <lb/>Contrast-enhanced CT with CT urography was done, and it <lb/>revealed [Figure 1] a small left kidney (7.5 cm × 3.8 cm) with <lb/>a distorted outline, focal areas of cortical thinning associated <lb/>with mild hydronephrosis, 2 calculi, and DJ stent in situ. <lb/>Compensatory hypertrophy was seen along the lateral cortex. <lb/>Extensive calcification was seen in the perinephric space <lb/>around the upper pole of the left kidney extending along with <lb/>the renal capsule with minimal perinephric fluid and <lb/>perinephric fat stranding. Fat-fluid level was noted in the <lb/>dilated upper polar and interpolar calyces of the left kidney. <lb/>Mild heterogeneous hypoenhancement and minimal contrast <lb/>excretion were seen through the left kidney. An ill-defined <lb/>retroperitoneal fluid collection was seen on the left side, <lb/>measuring approximately 24.2 cm × 7.7 cm × 6.9 cm and <lb/>extending into the left perinephric space. There was evidence <lb/>of significant cortical thinning and a suspicious breach at the <lb/>lower pole of the left kidney through which the collection <lb/>was communicating with the pelvicalyceal system of the left <lb/>kidney. Fatty attenuation was noted within the collection with <lb/>evidence of fat-fluid levels (HU value ~ -98 to -115). The <lb/>collection was seen to extend into the anterior abdominal <lb/>wall and left psoas and quadratus lumborum muscles. <lb/>Multiple calculi were noted within the collection in the psoas <lb/>and quadratus lumborum muscles. Fat-fluid level was noted <lb/>within the urinary bladder. Multiple subcentimetric-sized <lb/>paraaortic lymph nodes were seen. Small nonobstructive <lb/>calculus was seen in the right kidney also. <lb/>All these CT findings of small and poorly excreting kidney <lb/>with capsular and perinephric renal calcifications, renal calculi, <lb/>mild hydronephrosis, and perinephric collections suggest <lb/>the presence of chronic left pyelonephritis. The presence of <lb/>calculi in retroperitoneal and abdominal wall collections <lb/>suggests communication of calyces with collections. Moreover, <lb/>chyluria, fat-fluid levels in the left pelvicalyceal system <lb/>and retroperitoneal collections suggest the development of <lb/>renolymphatic fistula which can either be due to chronic <lb/>infection or injury to renal parenchyma during prior surgery. <lb/>The patient was initially treated with percutaneous drainage of <lb/>retroperitoneal collections and broad-spectrum antibiotics. Her <lb/>pus culture, later on, came positive for the tubercular organism, <lb/>following which she was kept on antitubercular treatment. <lb/>dIscussIon <lb/>Chyle is a mixture of emulsified fat, albumin, and fibrin, and <lb/>chyluria is a passage of chyle in the urine. The patient mostly <lb/>presents with milky urine, more pronounciated in the <lb/>postprandial period, which may not be associated with other <lb/>symptoms (mild) or may be associated with other symptoms <lb/>such as colicky pain (moderate) or hematochyluria or weight <lb/>Figure 1: Non contrast Computed Tomography (NCCT) coronal (a) and axial (b) images show a small left kidney, dense calcification in the perinephric <lb/>space, and renal capsule at the upper pole (blue arrows) and two calculi in lower pole calyx (white arrow). Contrast-enhanced computed tomography <lb/>images in axial (c, e and f) and coronal planes (d)mild hydronephrosis with the fat-fluid level in pelvi-calyceal system (PCS) (white arrow with black <lb/>outline), surrounding collections with fat-fluid level (yellow arrow) and calculi (white arrow in e), and fat-fluid level in the urinary bladder (red arrow) <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Kumar, et al.: Is it air or fat? Chyluria as the lesser known cause of dark fluid levels within the urinary system <lb/></note>

    <page>280 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Apollo Medicine Volume 21 Issue 3 September 2024 <lb/></note>

    <body>with persistent chyluria, sclerotherapy, or surgical treatment <lb/>is required [3] which may include stripping and ligation of all <lb/>the lymphatic vessels to the kidney and pelvis, development <lb/>of a lymphovenous anastomosis, autotransplantation of the <lb/>kidney, and nephrectomy as a last resort. <lb/>conclusIon <lb/>Imaging diagnosis of chyluria requires demonstration of fat-<lb/>fluid levels in the urinary bladder and pelvicalyceal system of <lb/>the kidney. Depending on severity, the fatty components may <lb/>also be seen in the perinephric and retroperitoneal collections. <lb/>The fat-fluid level in the urinary bladder and pelvicalyceal <lb/>may be mistaken for the more commonly seen air-fluid level <lb/>which is seen in emphysematous infections, and we advocate <lb/>measurement of the HU value of the hypodense component <lb/>in the dark fluid level for correct diagnosis. <lb/></body>

    <div type="acknowledgment">acknowledgement <lb/>None <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">declaratIon of conflIctIng Interests <lb/>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the <lb/>research, authorship and/or publication of this article. <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">fundIng <lb/>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/ <lb/>or publication of this article. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">declaratIon of patIent consent <lb/>The authors certify that he has obtained all appropriate patient consent <lb/>forms. In the form, the patient has given his consent for his images and other <lb/>clinical information to be reported in the journal. The patient understands <lb/>that his name and initials will not be published, and due efforts will be made <lb/>to conceal their identity, but anonymity cannot be guaranteed. <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">credIt author statement <lb/>All authors contributed equally to the final version of manuscript. <lb/></div>

    <div type="availability">data avaIlabIlIty <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study are available on request from <lb/>the corresponding author, [MK]. The data are not publicly available as it can <lb/>compromise the privacy and confidentiality of the patient. <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">use of artIfIcIal IntellIgence <lb/>No use of AI. <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>references <lb/>1. Stainer V, Jones P, Juliebø SØ, Beck R, Hawary A. Chyluria: What does <lb/>the clinician need to know? Ther Adv Urol 2020;12:1756287220940899. <lb/>2. Merchant S, Bharati A, Merchant N. Tuberculosis of the genitourinary <lb/>system-urinary tract tuberculosis: Renal tuberculosis-part I. Indian <lb/>J Radiol Imaging 2013;23:46-63. <lb/>3. Chen KC. Lymphatic abnormalities in patients with chyluria. J Urol <lb/>1971;106:111-4. <lb/>4. Yu NC, Raman SS, Patel M, Barbaric Z. Fistulas of the genitourinary <lb/>tract: A radiologic review. Radiographics 2004;24:1331-52. <lb/></listBibl>

    <body>loss (severe) which increases the severity and requires <lb/>additional treatment. Urinalysis shows the presence of <lb/>chylomicrons and triglycerides in the supernatant fluid. <lb/>Chyluria develops due to abnormal connections between the <lb/>lymphatic and urinary systems. Milky urine is the most <lb/>common presenting finding, and its biochemical demonstration <lb/>is required for clinical diagnosis. There are two theories <lb/>proposed for the formation of chyluria: (1) regurgitation of <lb/>chyle into the renal excretory system and (2) obstruction by <lb/>parasitic worms, leading to fistula formation. <lb/>Ultrasonography and CT can be used to diagnose chyluria which <lb/>shows fat-fluid levels in renal, perirenal regions, or the urinary <lb/>bladder. Magnetic resonance imaging is useful to anatomically <lb/>delineate any fistulous communication between the lymphatic <lb/>and renal excretory system. Although invasive and technically <lb/>challenging, lymphangiography can be used as a preoperative <lb/>tool to assess the size, site, and number of fistulous <lb/>communications. Lymphangioscintigraphy is a noninvasive <lb/>way to visualize the transport and drainage of lymphatic system <lb/>which can be used to identify the site of the fistula. For grading, <lb/>retrograde pyelography can be used to assess the severity of the <lb/>disease depending on the number of calyces involved (one = <lb/>mild/moderate depending on the clinical condition, &gt;1 = severe) <lb/>and to manage the case accordingly. <lb/>The etiology of chyluria includes parasitic, trauma, surgery, <lb/>malignancy, radiation, lymphatic malformation, and rarely <lb/>chronic infections such as tubercular infections. Most of the <lb/>cases described in the literature are caused by parasitic <lb/>infection, especially lymphatic filariasis due to Wuchereria <lb/>bancrofti. [1] Chronic pyelonephritis and renal tuberculosis <lb/>can rarely cause chyluria due to perirenal lymphatic <lb/>blockage, chronic inflammation, and rupture of the fragile <lb/>fornix. [2] In our case, the etiology may be either prior surgery <lb/>(nephrolithotomy) or chronic tubercular infection, or a <lb/>combination of both. On lymphangiography, fistulae between <lb/>the renal collecting system at the fornix and the relatively <lb/>abundant lymphatic drainage have been described. [3] These <lb/>eventually communicate with the retroperitoneal lymphatic <lb/>system through the peripelvic system, leading to chyluria. [4] <lb/>Dark fluid levels within the urinary system may be due <lb/>to fat-fluid level or the more common air-fluid level. <lb/>Subjectively, both of these look similar fat-fluid levels within <lb/>the urinary system may be erroneously labeled as the air-fluid <lb/>level as the latter is fairly common. Air-fluid levels within the <lb/>renal pelvis are seen in emphysematous pyelonephritis. Within <lb/>the urinary bladder, air-fluid levels are extremely common in <lb/>catheterized patients. The presence of air-fluid levels in the <lb/>abdominal collections represents either infection by gas-<lb/>forming organisms, fistulous communication with the bowel, <lb/>or postintervention changes. These potential pitfalls must be <lb/>properly addressed before making a radiological diagnosis. <lb/>Patients with chronic chyluria may have hypoproteinemia, <lb/>hypolipidemia, and mild variable immunodeficiency. <lb/>Treatment of chyluria is conservative with the management <lb/>of underlying etiology. However, in nonresponsive cases </body>


	</text>

</TEI>