<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/>Available online 13 June 2024 <lb/>2405-8440/© 2024 The Authors. <lb/>Published by Elsevier Ltd. <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Research article <lb/>Farmers&apos; perceptions and management of citrus fungal diseases <lb/>in Benin <lb/>Goudjo Habib Toessi a, b, c, * , Rachidatou Sikirou c , Elisée Georges Dadé Ler-<lb/>N&apos;ogn Amari a, b , Esaïe Gandonou d , Afio Zannou d , Daouda Koné a, b <lb/>a African Excellence Center on Climate Change, Biodiversity and Sustainable Agriculture (CEA-CCBAD), Félix Houphouët-Boigny University, 22 BP <lb/>582, Abidjan, Cote d&apos;Ivoire <lb/>b Laboratory of Biotechnology, Agriculture and Valorization of Biological Resources, UFR Biosciences, Félix Houphouët-Boigny University, 22 BP <lb/>582, Abidjan, Cote d&apos;Ivoire <lb/>c Laboratory of Crop Protection (LDC), National Institute of Agricultural Research of Benin (INRAB), 01 BP 884, Cotonou, Benin <lb/>d Laboratory of Agroeconomics and Agribusiness (LAGEC-B), University of Abomey-Calavi, 01 BP 526, Cotonou, Benin <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Citrus <lb/>Fungal diseases <lb/>Farmers&apos; perceptions <lb/>Benin <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/></front>

			<body>Background and aim: Citrus production represents an important activity for the national economy <lb/>and a source of income for farmers in Benin. However, fungal diseases are a major constraint to <lb/>production intensification. The aim of this study is to assess farmers&apos; perceptions on citrus fungal <lb/>diseases in production areas in Benin. <lb/>Methods: A survey was conducted among 417 farmers between July and December 2021 in four <lb/>major citrus-producing agro-ecological zones (zones V, VI, VII and VIII) to collect their percep-<lb/>tions, knowledge and management practices of citrus fungal diseases. <lb/>Results: Farmers reported that fungal diseases are one of the main constraints to citrus production, <lb/>including black spot, anthracnose, brown rot, sooty mold and fruit rot. Among them, black spot <lb/>disease is the most severe, causing damage to production. According to farmers, symptoms appear <lb/>on fruit after fruit set, with a very remarkable presence and high incidence at maturity. Although <lb/>farmers are most of times aware of the damage caused by fungal diseases with adverse conse-<lb/>quences on their income, they have a poor knowledge of appropriate phytosanitary products to <lb/>manage these diseases. Indeed, the majority of farmers (&gt;60 %) use chemical insecticides, which <lb/>they reported to be ineffective against citrus fungal diseases. Although chemical insecticides are <lb/>their only recourse, almost 40 % use nothing to control these diseases. Farmers stated that cli-<lb/>matic variability is a factor favoring the development of diseases, leading to reduced production. <lb/>Conclusions: Among the several citrus fungal diseases, black spot is perceived as the most <lb/>damaging, causing greater yield losses under favorable conditions, coupled with an almost total <lb/>absence of appropriate control methods. This study contributes to the reorganization of the citrus <lb/>industry and to decision-making on capacity building for farmers in terms of orchard pest pro-<lb/>tection, in order to guarantee better production of marketable and exportable fruit. <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. African Excellence Center on Climate Change, Biodiversity and Sustainable Agriculture (CEA-CCBAD), Félix Houphouët-<lb/>Boigny University, 22 BP 582, Abidjan, Cote d&apos;Ivoire. <lb/>E-mail address: habib.toessi@yahoo.com (G.H. Toessi). <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Heliyon <lb/>journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e32775 <lb/>Received 23 September 2023; Received in revised form 7 June 2024; Accepted 9 June 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Citrus fruits originate from Southeast Asia and are an economically important fruit crop worldwide [1]. They are currently grown in <lb/>over 140 countries, and the main commercial species are oranges (Citrus sinensis L. Osbeck), mandarins (Citrus reticulata), lemons <lb/>(Citrus limon), limes (Citrus aurantiifolia) and grapefruits (Citrus x paradisi), belonging to the Citrus genus of the Rutaceae family. <lb/>Subtropical regions are the main areas of commercial production, where the best quality citrus fruits are grown [1,2]. Global citrus <lb/>production is estimated at over 158 million tons in 2020 [3]. In tropical Africa, citrus is grown largely by small-scale farmers for local <lb/>consumption and export [4]. On this continent, an annual production of over 20 million tons was harvested in 2018 from an area of <lb/>more than 3.3 million hectares of citrus [3]. From a nutritional point of view, citrus fruits are rich in essential nutrients and energy, <lb/>which are beneficial to human health [5]. They contain a variety of secondary metabolites and bioactive compounds, such as cou-<lb/>marins, alkaloids, carotenoids, limonoids, phenolic acids, flavonoids and essential oils, which have functional health benefits [6-8]. <lb/>Citrus fruits are also rich in vitamins C, A and E, minerals, pectins and other beneficial phytochemicals, making them an important <lb/>basis for a balanced diet [9]. <lb/>Among the various sectors, the citrus industry has been considered by political leaders for several years as an option for achieving <lb/>food and nutritional security in Benin. Citrus production represents an important activity in the national economy and is a source of <lb/>income for farmers [10]. In Benin nearly 15500 tons of citrus fruit were produced with an area of 5542 ha in 2020 [3]. Despite <lb/>favorable climatic conditions, farmers are faced with a number of phytosanitary problems, including diseases and insect pests. Dis-<lb/>eases, especially fungal ones (black spot, anthracnose, fruit rot, etc.), are currently making their appearance in citrus orchards and are a <lb/>major constraint on the development of the citrus industry in Benin. Their damage to fruit affects yield and consequently farmers&apos; <lb/>income with low value on local and international markets [11,12]. Citrus black spot disease caused by Phyllosticta, is now a serious <lb/>threat to citrus production worldwide [13]. In Ghana, brentu et al. [13] reported that this disease caused around 80 % of yield losses. In <lb/>South Africa, the majority of attacked fruit from trees not protected against black spot disease were declared unfit for export, causing <lb/>over 80 % of economic loss [14]. Furthermore, the control of these pests in general and fungal diseases in particular is essentially based <lb/>on the use of chemical products. In addition to being very costly for small citrus farmers and detrimental to health and income, these <lb/>chemicals contribute significantly to greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions. Excessive pesticide use increases the production of nitrous <lb/>oxide in soils. Many pesticides produce ground-level ozone, a greenhouse gas harmful to humans and plants [15]. <lb/>Fig. 1. Geographical location of study areas. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>In addition, the influence of climate variability is a very important aspect in pest management. Indeed, climatic variability, re-<lb/>flected by changes in average temperatures, reduced annual rainfall, irregular rainfall distribution and prolonged periods of drought, <lb/>can affect the productive quality of plants and potentially cause their death [16]. It creates favorable conditions for the emergence and <lb/>aggressiveness of disease-causing pathogens, thus increasing their level of damage. Deberdt et al. [17] reported that climatic factors <lb/>can change the nature of microorganisms, transforming them into opportunistic pathogens. Previous work on pathogenic microor-<lb/>ganisms has shown that plants weakened or stressed by environmental factors, become more vulnerable to microorganisms [18,19]. In <lb/>order to be informed to help policies in decision-making, it is important to document farmers&apos; knowledge of the pests affecting citrus in <lb/>the different agro-ecological zones (AEZ) of citrus production, the extent of their damage on production and their incomes. The aim of <lb/>this study is to assess farmers&apos; perceptions and practices in the management of citrus-infected fungal diseases in production areas in <lb/>Benin. <lb/>2. Materials and methods <lb/>2.1. Study areas <lb/>The present study was carried out in the citrus-growing area of Benin. It covered four agro-ecological zones (AEZs), namely the <lb/>cotton-growing zone of central Benin (AEZ V), the barre land zone (AEZ VI), the depression zone (AEZ VII) and the fishing zone (AEZ <lb/>VIII) (Fig. 1). Predilection of citrus production, agro-climatic characteristics and accessibility were the main criteria for study site <lb/>selection (Table 1). <lb/>2.2. Sample size <lb/>An exploratory study was carried out in the study areas prior the real survey, in order to determine the sample size to be considered, <lb/>using a normal approximation to the binomial distribution proposed by Dagnelie [20]. <lb/>N = <lb/>[( <lb/>U 1-α/2 <lb/>) 2 × P (1 -p) <lb/>] <lb/>d 2 <lb/>U ¼ value of the normal random variable for the probability value of 1-α/2; <lb/>P ¼ probability of 1-α/2, α ¼ risk of error, d = margin of estimation error. <lb/>For α ¼ 5 %, probability p ¼ 1-α/2 = 0.975 and U 1 -α/2 ¼ 1.96. <lb/>p is the proportion of people engaged in citrus production in the study area and d the margin of estimation error, retained at 8 % in <lb/>this study [21]. Based on the p-values derived from the results of the exploratory phase of the study, 417 farmers were surveyed in the <lb/>four AEZs: 55 for AEZ V, 236 for AEZ VI, 72 for AEZ VII and 54 for AEZ VIII. Importance of citrus area sown was the selection criteria <lb/>for farmers. <lb/>2.3. Data collection <lb/>The study was conducted from June 2021 to December 2021. As the majority of farmers are illiterate, appropriate approaches were <lb/>developed to ensure better understanding and effective participation. Data were collected using a semi-structured questionnaire that <lb/>was directly and orally administered to individual citrus farmers in the four AEZs. The interviewers asked the farmers questions in local <lb/>languages and recorded their responses. Information collected covered farmer&apos;s demography and socio-economic characteristic (age, <lb/>education level, gender, marital status, ethnic group, mode of access to land and membership of an association, other activities, family <lb/>size), citrus orchards characteristics (area, density and age of orchards, citrus species), expression of fungal diseases, periods and stages <lb/>of fungal disease appearance, for how long (year) they have recorded the presence of fungal diseases, disease management methods, <lb/>farmers&apos; perception of climatic variability (temperature, relative humidity and rainfall). Farmers were also asked to determine, <lb/>through the questionnaire, at what time (month) of the year they generally notice an attack of fungal diseases affecting more than 50 <lb/>%, less than 50 %, or no attack at all on their citrus plants. To avoid confusion between the symptoms of fungal diseases and insect pest, <lb/>photos of symptoms of different citrus fungal diseases were attached to the questionnaire and presented to the farmers. This allowed <lb/>farmers to indicate their responses by pointing to the corresponding photos. <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Characteristics of agro-ecological zones. <lb/>AEZ <lb/>Definition <lb/>Climate <lb/>areas (km 2 ) <lb/>rainfall (mm) <lb/>Annual temperature ( • C) (SD) <lb/>V <lb/>Central Benin cotton zone <lb/>Sudano-Guinean climate <lb/>31722 <lb/>1100 <lb/>14-29 <lb/>VI <lb/>Bar land zone <lb/>Sudano-Guinean or sub-equatorial climate <lb/>6373 <lb/>800-1400 <lb/>25,3-29,7 <lb/>VII <lb/>Depression zone <lb/>Sub-equatorial climate <lb/>2564 <lb/>800-1300 <lb/>27-31 <lb/>VIII <lb/>Fishing zone <lb/>Sub-equatorial climate <lb/>3151 <lb/>1000-1400 <lb/>25-30 <lb/>SD= Standard Deviation. <lb/>G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.4. Statistical analysis <lb/>Data were analyzed using R software version 4.0.2 [22]. The socio-economic characteristics of the farmers were summarized using <lb/>cross-tabulations. The Chi-square test was used to test the association between socio-economic characteristics and agro-ecological <lb/>zones. Descriptive statistics (mean ± standard error) were used to summarize orchard age, area and density by AEZ and variety. <lb/>The general linear model (GLM) and analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey&apos;s post hoc test, as performed in the &apos;multcomp&apos; <lb/>package [23], were used to test the difference in age and area between zones and between species. The Kruskal-Wallis test was used to <lb/>determine disease occurrence year numbers. Bar charts and heat maps were used to highlight the periods and stages of appearance of <lb/>each disease inventoried by zone and specie. Cross-tabulations, proportions and graphs were produced to summarize farmers&apos; per-<lb/>ceptions of the effect of climatic variability on citrus production and disease development. <lb/>3. Results <lb/>3.1. Characteristics of citrus farmers in Benin <lb/>Data analysis showed that 17.7 % of farmers were less than 40 years old and 82.3 % were over 40. The distribution of farmers by <lb/>gender revealed that men, with a proportion of 92.8 %, were predominant in the citrus sector. 42.8 % of farmers were illiterate, 34 % <lb/>with primary education, 21.1 % with secondary education and only 2.2 % with higher studies. The &quot;purchase&quot; mode of land acquisition <lb/>was the most dominant (63.9 % of farmers), followed by &quot;inheritance&quot; (30.6 %). In terms of matrimonial status, over 99 % of farmers <lb/>were married. The majority of farmers surveyed (85.4 %) belonged to no agricultural association (Table 2). <lb/>3.2. Distribution of orchards by age class and area according to agro-ecological zone <lb/>Irrespective of agro-ecological zone or citrus species, the age of plantations ranged from 4 to 30 years, with an average of 10.33 ± <lb/>0.22 years. The distribution of orchards by age class revealed that over 85 % of orchards were over 15 years old (Fig. 2a and b). Overall, <lb/>more than 50 % of farmers have an area of less than 1 ha (Fig. 2c and d). Furthermore, in all the AEZs inspected, orchards exceeding 2 <lb/>ha were only Pineapple and Valencia varieties, while over 70 % of tangelo orchards did not exceed 1 ha. Analysis of the data relative to <lb/>citrus orchard age and area showed that there was a significant difference between orchard age (p &lt; 0.001) and area (p = 0.05) <lb/>depending on the AEZs (Table 3). <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Socio-economic characteristics of farmers. <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Agroecological zone <lb/>Overall <lb/>Percentage (%) <lb/>p-value <lb/>V <lb/>VI <lb/>VII <lb/>VIII <lb/>Gender <lb/>Male <lb/>47 <lb/>237 <lb/>63 <lb/>41 <lb/>388 <lb/>92,8 <lb/>0.066 <lb/>Female <lb/>1 <lb/>25 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>30 <lb/>7,2 <lb/>Age <lb/>&lt;40 years <lb/>8 <lb/>39 <lb/>19 <lb/>8 <lb/>74 <lb/>17,7 <lb/>0.089 <lb/>40-50 years <lb/>21 <lb/>95 <lb/>19 <lb/>20 <lb/>155 <lb/>37,1 <lb/>&gt;50 years <lb/>19 <lb/>128 <lb/>26 <lb/>16 <lb/>189 <lb/>45,2 <lb/>Marital status <lb/>Married <lb/>47 <lb/>261 <lb/>64 <lb/>44 <lb/>416 <lb/>99,5 <lb/>0.415 <lb/>Widowed <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>0,5 <lb/>Ethnic group <lb/>Adja <lb/>21 <lb/>49 <lb/>24 <lb/>9 <lb/>103 <lb/>24,6 <lb/>&lt; 0.001 <lb/>Fon <lb/>17 <lb/>158 <lb/>17 <lb/>2 <lb/>194 <lb/>46,4 <lb/>Sahouè <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>19 <lb/>19 <lb/>4,5 <lb/>Yoruba <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0,2 <lb/>Tori <lb/>0 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>15 <lb/>3,6 <lb/>Kotafon <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>17 <lb/>14 <lb/>34 <lb/>8,1 <lb/>Others <lb/>10 <lb/>36 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>52 <lb/>12,4 <lb/>Position in the household <lb/>Head of household <lb/>47 <lb/>235 <lb/>62 <lb/>41 <lb/>385 <lb/>92,1 <lb/>0.573 <lb/>Spouse <lb/>1 <lb/>20 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>25 <lb/>6,0 <lb/>Son/Daughter <lb/>0 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>7 <lb/>1,7 <lb/>Related <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0,2 <lb/>Educational level <lb/>None <lb/>23 <lb/>118 <lb/>30 <lb/>8 <lb/>179 <lb/>42,8 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Primary school <lb/>13 <lb/>90 <lb/>20 <lb/>19 <lb/>142 <lb/>34,0 <lb/>Secondary school <lb/>11 <lb/>53 <lb/>11 <lb/>13 <lb/>88 <lb/>21,1 <lb/>University <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>9 <lb/>2,2 <lb/>Land access mode <lb/>Purchase <lb/>24 <lb/>167 <lb/>39 <lb/>37 <lb/>267 <lb/>63,9 <lb/>0.141 <lb/>Donation <lb/>2 <lb/>13 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>19 <lb/>4,5 <lb/>Legacy <lb/>22 <lb/>78 <lb/>22 <lb/>6 <lb/>128 <lb/>30,6 <lb/>Renting <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>0,7 <lb/>Other <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0,2 <lb/>Member of an association <lb/>No <lb/>42 <lb/>218 <lb/>49 <lb/>42 <lb/>351 <lb/>84,0 <lb/>0.048 <lb/>Yes <lb/>6 <lb/>44 <lb/>15 <lb/>2 <lb/>67 <lb/>16,0 <lb/>Member of an association of citrus producers <lb/>No <lb/>47 <lb/>205 <lb/>61 <lb/>44 <lb/>357 <lb/>85,4 <lb/>&lt; 0.001 <lb/>Yes <lb/>1 <lb/>57 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>61 <lb/>14,6 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.3. Citrus species grown per agro-ecological zone <lb/>All the citrus orchards of the farmers surveyed were dominated by the Pineapple and Valencia orange varieties. Pineapple was the <lb/>most widely grown variety in all the AEZs except AEZ VIII, where Valencia was grown in over 50 % of the orchards (Fig. 3). Tangelo <lb/>was also produced in all agro-ecological zones, but in very small proportions. Fisher&apos;s exact test revealed a significant association <lb/>between varieties grown and AEZs (p = 0.04). <lb/>3.4. Determination of orchard density per agro-ecological zone <lb/>Average orchard density was around 203 plants/ha, and varied significantly not only between AEZs but also within each AEZ (p &lt; <lb/>0.001) (Fig. 4). AEZs V and VI had heterogeneous densities, while densities were more or less homogeneous in AEZs VII and VIII. <lb/>Density was high, at around 247.32 plants/ha in AEZ VI, and lower, at around 113.37 plants/ha in AEZ VIII. <lb/>Fig. 2. Distribution by orchard age (a, b) and area (c, d) across agro-ecological zones and citrus species. <lb/>Table 3 <lb/>Orchard characteristics (age and size) by agro-ecological zone and citrus species. <lb/>Orchard age (year) <lb/>Area of orchard (ha) <lb/>Range <lb/>mean ± SE <lb/>p <lb/>Range <lb/>mean ± SE <lb/>p <lb/>Agroecological zones <lb/>Zone V <lb/>5-15 <lb/>9.71 ± 0.42 b <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>0.12-10.00 <lb/>2.25 ± 0.42 a <lb/>0.05 <lb/>Zone VI <lb/>4-30 <lb/>11.24 ± 0.30 a <lb/>0.03-19.00 <lb/>1.42 ± 0.13 b <lb/>Zone VII <lb/>5-20 <lb/>9.23 ± 0.41 b <lb/>0.20-5.00 <lb/>1.14 ± 0.13 b <lb/>Zone VIII <lb/>4-15 <lb/>7.18 ± 0.39 c <lb/>0.28-8.00 <lb/>1.47 ± 0.24 ab <lb/>Overall <lb/>4-30 <lb/>10.33 ± 0.22 <lb/>0.03-19.00 <lb/>1.47 ± 0.10 <lb/>Citrus varieties <lb/>Pineapple <lb/>4-25 <lb/>10.62 ± 0.30 a <lb/>0.342 <lb/>0.06-14.00 <lb/>1.63 ± 0.15 a <lb/>0.11 <lb/>Valencia <lb/>4-30 <lb/>10.02 ± 0.34 a <lb/>0.03-19.00 <lb/>1.33 ± 0.14 a <lb/>Tangelo <lb/>6-16 <lb/>10.67 ± 0.93 a <lb/>0.06-2.00 <lb/>0.76 ± 0.27 a <lb/>Overall <lb/>4-30 <lb/>10.33 ± 0.22 <lb/>0.03-19.00 <lb/>1.47 ± 0.10 <lb/>p = p-value, SE = standard error. <lb/>Means with the same letters in subscript are not statistically different at 5 % probability level. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 3. Distribution of citrus species across agro-ecological zones. <lb/>Fig. 4. Citrus orchard density by agro-ecological zone. <lb/>Fig. 5. Proportion of respondents reporting biotic constraints linked to citrus production by agro-ecological zone. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.5. Farmers&apos; perceptions of orchard phytosanitary problems and pest management <lb/>For 50-58.1 % of farmers in most AEZs, diseases were a major constraint to citrus production. As for insect pests, 42-50 % of <lb/>farmers were aware that they were also constraints to citrus production (Fig. 5). The occurrence of diseases or insect pests did not <lb/>depend on the AEZ (p = 0.665). <lb/>3.6. Farmers&apos; perception of citrus fungal diseases <lb/>Referring to the fungal disease identification guides they have been given, the farmers identified fourcitrus fungal diseases mainly <lb/>black spot, anthracnose, brown rot, sooty mold and fruit rot (Fig. 6). Of these diseases, more than half the farmers interviewed <lb/>admitted that only black spot disease was most frequently observed in the orchards, and this was the case for all species. The number of <lb/>years of disease appearance varied significantly from one disease to another (p = 0.05), and ranged from 1 to 20 years (Table 4). <lb/>The period of fungal disease appearance varied throughout the year, in January, February, July and/or August (Figs. 7 and 8). <lb/>Analyses of farmers&apos; perceptions revealed that, irrespective of zone and species, most diseases appeared from the fruit set stage through <lb/>to ripening (Figs. 9 and 10). Periods of high and low attack did not depend on AEZ (p &gt; 0.05), unlike periods without attack (p &lt; <lb/>0.001). High attacks of citrus fungal diseases were observed in June, July, August and December, while low attacks were observed in <lb/>May and November. During March, April and September, farmers did not encounter any attacks (Fig. 11). <lb/>3.7. Farmers&apos; perceptions of fungal disease control methods <lb/>To control the diseases reported by farmers, 60 % of those interviewed had adopted chemical control. This control method did not <lb/>vary from one AEZ to another (p = 0.727). Although these methods were their only recourse, almost 40 % of them used no method to <lb/>control the diseases (Fig. 12). <lb/>In the management of citrus fungal diseases, farmers used various phytosanitary products, including Acarius 018 EC (Abamectin <lb/>18 g/L), DD Force (Dichlorvos 1000 g/L EC), Lambda Super 2.5 EC (Lambda-Cyhalothrin 25 g/L), Pacha 25 EC (Lambda-Cyhalothrin <lb/>15 g/L + Acetamiprid 10 g/L), Pyro FTE 672 EC (Cypermethrin 72 g/L + Chlorpyrifos-ethyl 600 g/L), etc. (Fig. 13). Among these <lb/>products, 41.93-76.19 % of farmers reported &quot;Pacha&quot; as the chemical most used to control citrus fungal diseases in all AEZs. Pacha was <lb/>followed by &quot;Lambda Super&quot;, which was also well used in AEZ VII, by 38.71 % of farmers. According to the farmers, all the chemicals <lb/>used were significantly ineffective against citrus fungal diseases (Table 5). <lb/>3.8. Farmers&apos; perception of the relationship between climate variability and fungal diseases <lb/>Indeed, the majority (92.2 %) of farmers reported a reduction in production due to rising temperatures and rare and variable <lb/>rainfall periods (Fig. 14a). Similarly, 81 % of farmers indicated that this latter causes a significant increase in fungal disease outbreaks <lb/>(Fig. 14b). <lb/>Fig. 6. Proportion of farmers having observed the different fungal diseases in Pineapple, Tangelo, and Valencia orchards. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>4. Discussion <lb/>Analysis of socio-economic characteristics indicates that the farmer community is dominated by older people. The great interest <lb/>shown by older farmers can be explained by the fact that orchards represent, for them, a savings source for their retirement or period of <lb/>inactivity. The average age of most orchards (around 86 %), regardless of agro-ecological zone or species, is greater than or equal to 15 <lb/>years. This shows that Benin&apos;s citrus orchards are dominated by older plants, which will mostly enter the ageing phase in coming years. <lb/>De Souza et al. [24] also reported that the average age of citrus orchards in Benin was greater than or equal to 10 years. <lb/>Perhaps, the high illiteracy in this sector also portrays the status of education in the country. For instance, in Morocco and Ghana, <lb/>where the literacy level is high with citrus production far higher than ours, Lahlali et al. [25] and Boakye et al. [26] reported that 17 % <lb/>and 26 % respectively of citrus farmers are not literate. This shows that education is a determinant factor of agricultural productivity as <lb/>it allows farmers to easily unpackage information related to farming technologies and apply them. Hence, efforts to provide agri-<lb/>cultural information to citrus farmers should take into account the high illiteracy rate in this sector in Benin to develop materials in the <lb/>local languages for technologies diffusion while promoting actions to improve the literacy rate. <lb/>Our results showed a wide variation in orchard density between and within the AEZs, ranging from 113.37 to 247.32 plants/ha. <lb/>This could be explained by the low educational level and lack of technical support of the farmers. These results are similar to those of <lb/>Gnimadi [27], who observed a trend from 160 to 360 plants/ha. AEZ VI recorded the highest average density. These results are in line <lb/>with those of Akohoue et al. [28], who also recorded high densities of 260-271 plants/ha in two localities of the same AEZ. However, <lb/>the high planting density combined with the absence of pruning practices hinders tree development, increases competition for sunlight <lb/>and leads to low yields with small-sized fruit [29]. According to Afloukou et al. [30], the appropriate density range for citrus orchards <lb/>in hot, humid regions like Benin is between 156 and 204 plants/ha. Bénaouf [31], pointed out in his report on organic citrus production <lb/>Table 4 <lb/>Observation year for citrus fungal diseases. <lb/>Diseases <lb/>Mean ± S.E <lb/>observation period (year) <lb/>Black spot <lb/>5.62 ± 0.22 a <lb/>1-20 <lb/>Anthracnose <lb/>5.50 ± 0.20 a <lb/>1-18 <lb/>Curvulariose <lb/>6.26 ± 0.37 b <lb/>1-20 <lb/>Fruit rot <lb/>6.41 ± 0.44 b <lb/>2-20 <lb/>Fumagin <lb/>5.25 ± 0.90 a <lb/>1-20 <lb/>SE = standard error. <lb/>Means with the same letters in subscript are not statistically different at 5 % probability level. <lb/>Fig. 7. Periods when the farmers recorded the presence of fungal diseases according to agro-ecological zones. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>that in tropical Africa, the normal orchard density is 202 plants/ha. This density, which is lower than that practiced by farmers, is <lb/>linked to non-compliance with popularized densities. According to Kadir et al. [32], high crop densities contribute to the development <lb/>and severity of phytopathogenic diseases. In orchards, they generate high humidity and less light under the canopy, which are <lb/>favorable conditions for fungal or bacterial citrus disease development. Insect pest pressure is also high in crops at high densities. <lb/>The assessment of farmers&apos; perceptions and knowledge showed that insect pests and diseases are the main constraints to citrus <lb/>production in Benin. However, they have difficulty in identifying and differentiating insect and disease symptoms. In most cases, <lb/>farmers acknowledge having observed the symptoms and damage caused by citrus fungal diseases in their orchards after seeing <lb/>symptom photographs. These results confirm those of Lokossou et al. [10], who identified insect pests and diseases as major constraints <lb/>to citrus orchard production in Benin, and expressed the need to build farmers&apos; capacity for early detection and disease management. <lb/>Using the pest guide, farmers were able to recognize the symptoms of anthracnose, black spot, brown rot, sooty mold and fruit rot <lb/>Fig. 8. Periods when the farmers recorded the presence of fungal diseases according to citrus species. <lb/>Fig. 9. Appearance stages of fungal diseases across agro-ecological zones. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>that they encountered in their orchards. According to the farmers, these diseases had been observed for almost 20 years, but had <lb/>become more remarkable in the last 5-6 years. Some 60 % of farmers confirmed the presence of black spot in their orchards, regardless <lb/>of species. This disease causes enormous damage, attracting more attention from farmers than other diseases (anthracnose, brown rot, <lb/>sooty mold and fruit rot), which are rarely observed in orchards. Although these fungal diseases are observed in orchards, farmers do <lb/>not have a perfect understanding of when they appear. Nevertheless, 8-60 % of farmers, depending on the agro-ecological zone and the <lb/>citrus species, report that these diseases are visible from the fruit enlargement stage until the fruit ripens (January to February and July <lb/>to August), with major attacks in June, July, August and December. Low levels of attack were observed in May and November, ac-<lb/>cording to the farmers. These results are consistent with those of Baldassari et al. [33], Lanza et al. [34] and Fialho et al. [14], who <lb/>indicate that the first symptoms on fruit appear after fruit set until the ripening stages. The period of March, April and September <lb/>mentioned by farmers corresponds to the months of flowering and fruit set for the major and minor crop [35]. <lb/>Fig. 10. Appearance stages of fungal diseases according to citrus species. <lb/>Fig. 11. Different attack levels per period during the year according to farmers in agro-ecological zones. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Chemical control is the most common management method used by farmers. Several studies have reported that chemical control is <lb/>the priority control method used by commercial farmers [36,37]. Various chemical products are used by citrus farmers in the areas <lb/>studied, namely Acarius 018 EC (Abamectin 18 g/L), DD Force (Dichlorvos 1000 g/L EC), Lambda Super 2.5 EC (Lambda-Cyhalothrin <lb/>25 g/L), Pacha 25 EC (Lambda-Cyhalothrin 15 g/L + Acetamiprid 10 g/L), Pyro FTE 672 EC (Cypermethrin 72 g/L + Chlorpyr-<lb/>ifos-Ethyl 600 g/L). Among these products, Pacha 25 EC is the most widely used by farmers. Pacha 25 EC is a chemical insecticide <lb/>registered in Benin to manage defoliating and sucking pests of several crops such as cowpeas, cotton and vegetable crops. All the <lb/>products cited by farmers to manage diseases are only insecticides, which they applied instead of fungicides. This justifies the farmers&apos; <lb/>Fig. 12. Proportion of farmers using methods (chemicals, endogenous, and nothing) to control fungal diseases by agro-ecological zone. <lb/>Fig. 13. Distribution of chemical products frequently used to control citrus fungal diseases according to farmers in the 4 agro-ecological zones (Zone <lb/>I, II, III, IV, and V) and overall. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>statements that the chemical products applied are ineffective against the citrus fungal diseases reported. These results show that <lb/>farmers do not differentiate between pesticide categories. The dominance of insecticides among the pesticides cited by farmers is <lb/>indicative of the non-availability of fungicides and of farmers&apos; poor knowledge of citrus diseases. To effectively manage citrus fungal <lb/>diseases, capacity-building for farmers in citrus disease recognition and management is needed. Citrus-specific pesticide registration is <lb/>also necessary. <lb/>The majority of farmers indicated that climatic variability also affects the citrus sector, contributing to lower production and <lb/>increased disease development. These results could be explained by the rarity and staggering of rainfall, the variation and high level of <lb/>temperature and wind speed seen in the country today. The colonization of previously disease-free areas could also explain the <lb/>development of these diseases and the losses recorded. However, the diseases could spread due to water stress and rising temperatures, <lb/>which weaken the plant and predispose it to infection [12]. This could lead to yield losses and a decline in fruit quality, creating <lb/>marketing and export constraints. <lb/>5. Conclusions <lb/>Several fungal diseases are associated with citrus in production zones (AEZ, V, VI, VII and VIII) in Benin. Among these diseases, <lb/>black spot is perceived as the most damaging, causing greater yield losses under favorable conditions, coupled with an almost total <lb/>absence of appropriate control methods. In addition, farmers need knowledge of good agronomic management and phytosanitary <lb/>practices, in relation with climatic constraints prevailing in production zones. Workshops or training sessions specifically focused on <lb/>citrus black spot are necessary for growers to better understand and manage the disease. These sessions will cover topics such as disease <lb/>identification, symptoms, the life cycle of the pathogen and effective management strategies, which will be developed in the form of <lb/>pamphlets, brochures, posters and videos. To ensure the success of this sector, capacity building for farmers is necessary, while taking <lb/>into account the socio-economic impact of diseases. <lb/></body>

            <div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The datasets used in this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>Goudjo Habib Toessi: Writing -original draft, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <lb/>Rachidatou Sikirou: Supervision, Conceptualization. Elisée Georges Dadé Ler-N&apos;ogn Amari: Supervision, Conceptualization. Esaïe <lb/>Gandonou: Software, Methodology, Formal analysis. Afio Zannou: Software, Methodology, Formal analysis. Daouda Koné: <lb/></div>

            <body>Table 5 <lb/>Efficiency (%) of phytosanitary products used by farmers. <lb/>Phytosanitary products <lb/>High efficiency <lb/>Moderately efficient <lb/>Low efficiency <lb/>Ineffective <lb/>Pacha 25 EC (Lambda-Cyhalothrin 15 g/L + Acetamiprid 10 g/L) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>17,92 <lb/>82,08 <lb/>Lambda Super 2,5 EC (Lambda-Cyhalothrin 25 g/L) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>8,33 <lb/>91,67 <lb/>Pyro FTE 672 EC (Cyperméthrine 72 g/L + Chlorpyrifos-éthyl 600 g/L) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>Pestoff <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>DD Force (Dichlorvos 1000 g/L EC) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>Acarius 018 EC (Abamectine 18 g/L) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>Fig. 14. Climatic variability effect on citrus production (a) and fungal diseases development (b). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

            <div type="annex">Supervision. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to <lb/>influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors thank the Partnership for Skills in Applied Sciences, Engineering and Technology (PASET) and Regional Scholarship <lb/>and Innovation Funds (RSIF) programme, the Université Félix Houphouët-Boigny of Côte d&apos;Ivoire, the Institut National des Recherches <lb/>Agricoles du Bénin (INRAB) and the African Centre of Excellence of Climate Change, Biodiversity and Sustainable Agriculture (CEA-<lb/>CCBAD/Côte d&apos;Ivoire) for financial and technical support and providing working facility of the research study. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Supplementary data <lb/>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e32775. <lb/>References <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] G. Zhong, E. Nicolosi, Citrus origin, diffusion, and economic importance, The citrus genome (2020) 5-21, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-15308-3_2. <lb/>[2] Y. Liu, E. Heying, S.A. Tanumihardjo, History, global distribution, and nutritional importance of citrus fruits, Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 11 (6) (2012) <lb/>530-545, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1541-4337.2012.00201.x. <lb/>[3] F.E. Hounnou, H. Dedehouanou, A. Zannou, S. Bakary, E.F. Mahoussi, Influence of climate change on food crop yield in Benin republic, J. Agric. Sci. 11 (5) <lb/>(2019) 281-295, https://doi.org/10.5539/jas.v11n5p281. <lb/>[4] M. Yesuf, Distribution and management of Phaeoramularia leaf and fruit spot disease of citrus in Ethiopia, Fruits 62 (2) (2007) 99-106, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1051/fruits:2007003. <lb/>[5] Z. Maqbool, W. Khalid, H.T. Atiq, H. Koraqi, Z. Javaid, S.K. Alhag, L.A. Al-Shuraym, D.M.D. Bader, M. Almarzuq, M. Afifi, A. AL-Farga, Citrus waste as source of <lb/>bioactive compounds: Extraction and utilization in health and food industry, Molecules 28 (4) (2023) 1636, https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules28041636. <lb/>[6] A. Abirami, G. Nagarani, P. Siddhuraju, The medicinal and nutritional role of underutilized citrus fruit Citrus hystrix (Kaffir lime): a review, Drug Invent 6.1 <lb/>(2014) 1-5. ISSN: 0975-7619. <lb/>[7] D.E. Okwu, Citrus fruits: a rich source of phytochemicals and their roles in human health, Int. J. Chem. Sci. 6 (2) (2008) 451-471. <lb/>[8] X. Lv, S. Zhao, Z. Ning, H. Zeng, Y. Shu, O. Tao, Y. Liu, Citrus fruits as a treasure trove of active natural metabolites that potentially provide benefits for human <lb/>health, Chem. Cent. J. 9 (2015) 1-14, https://doi.org/10.1186/s13065-015-0145-9. <lb/>[9] R.K. Saini, A. Ranjit, K. Sharma, P. Prasad, X. Shang, K.G.M. Gowda, Y.S. Keum, Bioactive compounds of citrus fruits: a review of Composition and health <lb/>benefits of carotenoids, flavonoids, limonoids, and Terpenes, Antioxidants 11 (2) (2022) 239, https://doi.org/10.3390/antiox11020239. <lb/>[10] B. Lokossou, C. Tossou, C. Vernière, P. Ollitrault, Mission d&apos;évaluation de l&apos;agrumiculture au Bénin: du 28 septembre au 9 octobre 2009 (2009) 1-51. https:// <lb/>agritrop.cirad.fr/554824/1/document_554824.pdf. <lb/>[11] K. Khanchouch, A. Pane, A. Chriki, S.O. Cacciola, Major and emerging fungal diseases of citrus in the Mediterranean Region, Citrus Pathology 1.10.5772 (2017) <lb/>66943, https://doi.org/10.5772/66943. <lb/>[12] M. Jaouad, A. Moinina, S. Ezrari, R. Lahlali, Key pests and diseases of citrus trees with emphasis on root rot diseases: an overview, Moroccan Journal of <lb/>Agricultural Sciences 1 (3) (2020) 149-160. <lb/>[13] F.C. Brentu, K.A. Oduro, S.K. Offei, G.T. Odamtten, A. Vicent, N.A. Peres, L.W. Timmer, Crop loss, aetiology, and epidemiology of citrus black spot in Ghana, <lb/>Eur. J. Plant Pathol. 133 (2012) 657-670, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10658-012-9944-1. <lb/>[14] R.O. Fialho, P. Moyo, P.H. Fourie, F.E. Lanza, F.J. Machado, L. Amorim, G.J. Silva-Junior, Citrus black spot intensity and yield losses on sweet orange are <lb/>affected by Phyllosticta citricarpa inoculum concentration and fruit developmental stage, Plant Pathol. 71 (7) (2022) 1606-1618, https://doi.org/10.1111/ <lb/>ppa.13586. <lb/>[15] R. Cech, F. Leisch, J.G. Zaller, Pesticide use and associated greenhouse gas emissions in sugar beet, apples, and viticulture in Austria from 2000 to 2019, <lb/>Agriculture 12 (6) (2022) 879, https://doi.org/10.3390/agriculture12060879. <lb/>[16] C.K. Besson, R. Lobo-do-Vale, M.L. Rodrigues, P. Almeida, A. Herd, O.M. Grant, T.S. David, M. Schmidt, D. Otieno, T.F. Keenan, C. Gouveia, C. Mériaux, M. <lb/>M. Chaves, J.S. Pereira, Cork oak physiological responses to manipulated water availability in a Mediterranean woodland, Agric. For. Meteorol. 184 (2014) <lb/>230-242, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agrformet.2013.10.004. <lb/>[17] P. Deberdt, J. Guyot, R. Coranson-Beaudu, J. Launay, M. Noreskal, P. Rivière, F. Vigné, D. Laplace, L. Lebreton, E. Wicker, Diversity of Ralstonia solanacearum <lb/>in French Guiana expands knowledge of the &quot;emerging ecotype&quot;, Phytopathology 104 (6) (2014) 586-596, https://doi.org/10.1094/PHYTO-09-13-0264-R. <lb/>[18] C.D. Allen, A.K. Macalady, H. Chenchouni, D. Bachelet, N. McDowell, M. Vennetier, T. Kitzberger, A. Rigling, D.D. Breshears, E.H. Hogg, P. Gonzalez, <lb/>R. Fensham, Z. Zhang, J. Castro, N. Demidova, J.H. Lim, G. Allard, S.W. Running, A. Semerci, N. Cobb, A global overview of drought and heat-induced tree <lb/>mortality reveals emerging climate change risks for forests, For. Ecol. Manag. 259 (4) (2010) 660-684, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2009.09.00. <lb/>[19] S. Moricca, B.T. Linaldeddu, B. Ginetti, B. Scanu, A. Franceschini, A. Ragazzi, Endemic and emerging pathogens Threatening Cork oak trees: management <lb/>options for Conserving a Unique forest Ecosystem, Plant Dis. 100 (11) (2016) 2184-2193, https://doi.org/10.1094/PDIS-03-16-0408-FE. <lb/>[20] P. Dagnelie, Statistique théorique et appliquée: Statistique descriptive et bases de l&apos;inférence statistique, vol. 1, De Boeck Supérieur, 1998, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1111/j.1467-985x.2007.00506_6.x. <lb/>[21] A.E. Assogbadjo, R.G. Kakaï, S. Edon, T. Kyndt, B. Sinsin, Natural variation in fruit characteristics, seed germination and seedling growth of Adansonia digitata <lb/>L. in Benin, N. For. 41 (2011) 113-125, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11056-010-9214-z. <lb/>[22] R.C. Team, R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing, R Foundation for Statistical Computing, 2022 (No Title). <lb/>[23] T. Hothorn, F. Bretz, P. Westfall, Simultaneous inference in general parametric models. Biometrical Journal, Journal of Mathematical Methods in Biosciences 50 <lb/>(3) (2008) 346-363, https://doi.org/10.1002/bimj.200810425. <lb/>[24] E.O. De de Souza, F.M. Anato, A.H. Bokonon-Ganta, E.B. Bokonon-Ganta, Contraintes à l&apos;adoption de la méthode de l&apos;hygiène sanitaire des vergers pour la lutte <lb/>contre les mouches nuisibles aux fruits (Diptera, Tephritidae) par les producteurs de mangues et d&apos;agrumes au Bénin, Agron. Afr. 28 (1) (2016) 60-69. <lb/>[25] R. Lahlali, M. Jaouad, A. Moinina, F. Mokrini, Z. Belabess, Farmers&apos; knowledge, perceptions, and farm-level management practices of citrus pests and diseases in <lb/>Morocco, J. Plant Dis. Prot. 128 (5) (2021) 1213-1226, https://doi.org/10.1007/s41348-021-00479-2. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32775 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[26] D.A. Boakye, P.Y. Kwoseh, P.Y. Adjei, Citrus Pre-harvest fruit Drop: farmers&apos; perception on the causes and their management practices in Ashanti region, Ghana, <lb/>Agric. Biol. jounal north Am. 8 (2) (2017) 58-66. <lb/>[27] A. Gnimadi, Etude pour l&apos;identification des filières agroindustrielles prioritaires (Bénin), Programme de Restructuration et de mise à Niveau de l&apos;Industrie des <lb/>Etats membres de l&apos;UEMOA (PRMN), UEMOA-ONUDI (2008) 118. <lb/>[28] F. Akohoue, A.C. Segnon, E.G. Achigan-Dako, Diversity in smallholder citrus orchards and cultivation bottlenecks: Research avenues for improved production in <lb/>Benin, West Africa, Exp. Agric. 54 (5) (2018) 641-654, https://doi.org/10.1017/S001447971700028X. <lb/>[29] M. Agusti, C. Mesejo, C. Reig, A. Martinez-Fuentes, Citrus production. Horticulture: plants for people and places, production horticulture ume 1 (2014) 159-195, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-017-8578-5_6. <lb/>[30] F. Afloukou, V. Zinsou, N. Onelge, Citrus in Benin Republic: past, present, and future challenge, Citrus Research &amp; Technology 41 (2020) 1-12, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.4322/crt.20820. <lb/>[31] G. Bénaouf, Produire des agrumes en agriculture biologique. Institut technique de l&apos;agriculture biologique (ITAB), CIVAM BIO CORSE 2005, 2005, p. 4p. <lb/>[32] N.A. Kadir, L. Naher, N. Sidek, Economical important phytopathogenic diseases in Vanilla planifolia: a review paper, Journal of Tropical Resources and <lb/>Sustainable Science (JTRSS) 7 (2) (2019) 77-82, https://doi.org/10.47253/jtrss.v7i2.513. <lb/>[33] R.B. Baldassari, R.F. Reis, A. De Goes, Susceptibility of fruits of the &quot;Valência&quot; and &quot;Natal&quot; sweet orange varieties to Guignardia citricarpa and the influence of the <lb/>coexistence of healthy and symptomatic fruits, Fitopatol. Bras. 31 (2006) 337-341, https://doi.org/10.1590/S0100-41582006000400002. <lb/>[34] F.E. Lanza, T.G. Metzker, T. Vinhas, F. Behlau, G.J. Silva Junior, Critical fungicide spray period for citrus black spot control in São Paulo state, Brazil, Plant Dis. <lb/>102 (2) (2018) 334-340, https://doi.org/10.1094/PDIS-04-17-0537-RE. <lb/>[35] O. Orhan, Land suitability determination for citrus cultivation using a GIS-based multi-criteria analysis in Mersin, Turkey, Comput. Electron. Agric. 190 (2021) <lb/>106433, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compag.2021.106433. <lb/>[36] C. Vincent, B. Panneton, Les méthodes de lutte physique comme alternatives aux pesticides, VertigO-la revue électronique en sciences de l&apos;environnement 2.2 <lb/>(2001), https://doi.org/10.4000/vertigo.4093. <lb/>[37] P. Leroux, Modes d&apos;action des produits phytosanitaires sur les organismes pathogènes des plantes, Comptes Rendus Biol. 326 (1) (2003) 9-21, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/S1631-0691(03)00005-2. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">G.H. Toessi et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
