<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/>Available online 5 February 2024 <lb/>2405-8440/Â© 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Research article <lb/>Effect of fluorine tin oxide substrate on the deposited SnO 2 : Ni thin <lb/>films properties for gas sensing <lb/>Khamael Ibrahim Abdulwahid a , Chiheb Chaker b, * , Hanen Chaker c <lb/>a Department of Physics, College of Sciences, University of Misan, Maysan, Iraq <lb/>b Laboratory of Multifunctional Materials and Applications (LaMMA), LR16ES18, University of Sfax, Faculty of Sciences of Sfax, Sfax, Tunisia <lb/>c Laboratory of Materials and Environment for Sustainable Development (LR18ES10), University of Tunis El Manar, ISSBAT, Tunis, Tunisia <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Gas sensor <lb/>Ni-doped SnO 2 <lb/>FTO substrates <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>This study explores the deposition of Tin Oxide and Ni-doped SnO 2 thin films (NSO) via spray <lb/>pyrolysis from aqueous solutions. The deposition process was conducted under uniform condi-<lb/>tions on two substrates, namely glass and fluorine tin oxide (FTO), with varying Ni percentages. <lb/>The aim was to evaluate their potential for gas sensing applications. The as-deposited thin films <lb/>exhibit diverse properties influenced by both Ni content and substrate type. X-Ray Diffraction <lb/>(XRD) measurements reveal polycrystalline structures characterized by broad SnO 2 diffraction <lb/>lines, with the emergence of a NiO phase, particularly evident at higher Ni content. Notably, thin <lb/>films deposited on FTO show the appearance of a secondary phase of SnO and enhanced crys-<lb/>tallinity. Furthermore, lattice parameters and crystallite size decrease with increasing Ni per-<lb/>centage. The Field Emission Scanning Electron Microscopy (FE-SEM) analysis highlights <lb/>significant alterations in surface nanostructures based on nickel content and substrate type. <lb/>Higher nickel concentrations result in the formation of cauliflower-like structures, varying in size <lb/>and density. This structural divergence significantly impacts the sensitivity of NSO-based NO 2 gas <lb/>sensors. Particularly, thin films with 20 % Ni, especially those deposited on FTO, exhibit optimal <lb/>configurations for gas sensor applications, display sensitivity of 501 % at 100 ppm for nano-<lb/>crystalline NSO/FTO compared to 436 % for glass-deposited samples. Our findings highlight the <lb/>crucial role of Ni content and substrate type in modifying the structural and sensing properties of <lb/>NSO thin films, for enhanced gas sensing applications. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Over the last decade, there has been a demand for the creation of extremely sensitive, low-temperature, compact, user-friendly, and <lb/>stable gas sensors to monitor the environment for hazardous gases [1]. Metal oxides are among the most stable natural materials that <lb/>can be used as sensitizers for a variety of hazardous gases, which are basic electronic circuits that can easily integrate [2]. Due to their <lb/>advantages of being inexpensive, easy to build, and compact, metal oxide-based gas sensors are widely employed [3]. Due to their high <lb/>stability, several metal oxides are generally used in gas sensors. SnO 2 is the most commonly used material in gas sensing applications <lb/>[4]. <lb/>Tin oxide thin films (SnO 2 ) have remarkable properties, making them suitable for various applications such as transparent <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail address: chakerchiheb@yahoo.fr (C. Chaker). <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Heliyon <lb/>journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e25585 <lb/>Received 6 November 2023; Received in revised form 27 January 2024; Accepted 30 January 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>conductive coatings in optoelectronic devices [5], solar cells [6] and gas sensors [7]. The undoped Tin oxide films exhibit excellent <lb/>transparency and electrical conductivity [8], translation them crucial in developing technologies. Furthermore, the introduction of <lb/>dopants into SnO 2 thin films enhances their performance and extends their range of applications [9]. Doping with elements such as <lb/>fluorine, indium, or antimony can further improve electrical conductivity, optical properties, and stability. This expand its use in <lb/>advanced electronic devices, flexible electronics and energy storage systems [9]. Recently, there has been a high level of attention on <lb/>the development of SnO 2 nanostructures to enhance the performance of gas sensors [10]. <lb/>Many studies are concentrated on pure and doped SnO 2 for gas sensing due to its high stability, presence of native oxygen va-<lb/>cancies, and high charge carrier density [11]. Numerous studies have investigated various factors influencing the properties of SnO 2 to <lb/>achieve high-performance gas sensors, including elemental modification with many different and doped materials such as zinc [12], <lb/>cobalt [13], etc., methods of preparation and nanostructure modification [14]. The composites usually exhibit improved performances <lb/>compared to pure SnO 2 in terms of gas sensitivity and response time. Nanostructure modification can be achieved by varying the <lb/>substrate type and nature due to variations in the growth mechanism [15]. <lb/>Bera et al. (2020) [16] synthesized oriented rutile SnO 2 nanowires through atomic layer deposition seeding. Seeded growth <lb/>controls the nucleation of nanowires and the crystallographic properties of seeds are key parameters for tuning the properties of <lb/>nanowires. The prepared nanowires show efficient electrochemical CO 2 reduction. Masuda (2020) [17] regulated the growth of SnO 2 <lb/>in aqueous solutions as nanosheets oriented along the (101) direction on FTO substrate for chemical sensors, without a seed layer. The <lb/>(101) facet&apos;s broad, flat surface proved to be metastable. The constructed SnO 2 nanosheet film had an approximate thickness of 800 nm <lb/>and a gradient structure with several connections. By changing the etching condition, the metastable (101) facet can be used to in-<lb/>fluence the pace of crystal formation. <lb/>Our previous study (2023) [18] on SnO 2 and NSO for gas sensing confirmed the tetragonal structure of pure SnO 2 and NSO films. <lb/>The lattice parameters decreased with an increasing Ni ratio. FE-SEM analysis revealed the emergence of cauliflower like aggregation <lb/>structures with an approximate diameter of 100 nm attributed to the increasing Nickel content. Furthermore, these structures dis-<lb/>played a heightened density with higher percentage of Ni content. Raman spectroscopy indicates the formation of SnO 2 nanostructures <lb/>and an increase in defects and vacancies with increasing Ni contents. The NO 2 gas sensors based on the NSO nanostructure showed <lb/>enhanced performance toward NO 2 at 100 • C, with the optimal Ni ratio of 20 mol %. <lb/>The objective of this study is to develop cost-effective, highly sensitive, low-temperature, and stable gas-sensing sensors for <lb/>monitoring hazardous gases. The primary focus is on enhancing the performance of SnO 2 thin film gas sensors through nanostructure <lb/>modifications. The investigation encompasses the introduction of Ni dopants to enhance the properties of SnO 2 thin films. Addi-<lb/>tionally, the study explores the impact of substrate type (glass or FTO) on the characteristics of deposited SnO 2 thin films. The <lb/>deposition technique employed is a simple one-step process using spray pyrolysis. A specific importance is placed on evaluating the <lb/>applicability of these thin films in NO 2 gas sensing applications. <lb/>2. Experimental <lb/>The flow chart for experimental work is shown below. <lb/>2.1. Synthesis <lb/>The starting materials that were used are: Sn Cl 2 .2H 2 O -99.995 • % purity, Merck Co. and NiCl 2 .6H 2 O -99.9 • % purity, Sigma-<lb/>Aldrich. SnO 2 : Ni composite thin films were prepared at same deposition parameters on both glass and fluorine-tin oxide (FTO) <lb/>substrates by spray pyrolysis from aqueous solution at 400 • C substrate temperature. Thin films were prepared at two Ni atomic ratios <lb/>of 0.1 and 0.2. The atomizer was installed 30 cm above the substrates to spray the solution at 1.5 ml/min using 5 bars compressed air. <lb/>2.2. Characterization <lb/>The structural properties of SnO 2 and NSO thin film were characterized using an X-Ray Diffraction system (Shimadzu XRD 6000) <lb/>from 10 to 70 • diffraction angle at 5 • /min scanning speed. The surface morphology for the prepared samples was examined by FE-SEM <lb/>(JSM-7600F by JEOL Ltd).The thicknesses of the thin films were measured using a reflectance probe (SR300 Å Sun Technologies). The <lb/>dedicated software provided with the reflectometer device was utilized to determine the thickness, which was for all samples in the <lb/>range of 310 ± 10 nm. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 1. Schematic diagram for gas sensor structure on glass substrate (A) and on FTO (B). <lb/>Fig. 2. Image of the system for gas sensing testing. <lb/>Fig. 3. XRD for the SnO 2 and NSO films at 10 and 20 % Ni ratios on FTO substrates. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.3. Fabrication of gas sensors <lb/>Gas sensor devices were fabricated by depositing comb-like aluminum electrodes with a thickness of 200 nm onto the coating <lb/>surfaces. For the samples deposited on glass and FTO substrates, a thermal evaporation technique was employed under a vacuum of <lb/>10 -5 Torr using the Edwards coating system. The electrodes were connected by fine wires using silver paste. The schematic diagram of <lb/>the gas sensor structure for the two configurations is illustrated in Fig. 1(A and B). <lb/>Gas sensitivity for the SnO 2 and NSO samples deposited on glass and FTO substrates were tested at a controlled temperature in a <lb/>closed chamber vacuumed by a rotary pump. Electrically, the sample was connected through a multi-pin feed-through to a multimeter <lb/>(Uni-T UT803 Benchtop Digital Multimeter) for resistance measurement connected to a computer during the examination. The Ni-<lb/>trogen dioxide gas (NO 2 ) was mixed with air and flowed into the chamber through two flow meters and electric valves opened-closed <lb/>for specific periods. Fig. 2 illustrates the image of testing system for gas sensing. <lb/>3. Results and discussions <lb/>3.1. Structural analysis <lb/>The XRD patterns of as-deposited SnO 2 and NSO composite thin films at 10 and 20 Ni at % on FTO substrates were shown in Fig. 3. A <lb/>polycrystalline structure appeared for all samples. The dominant phase is the tetragonal SnO 2 , matched with the JCPDS Card No. 96-<lb/>900-9083. Broad diffraction lines corresponding to (110), (101) and (211) for SnO 2 were observed. The broad features of the <lb/>diffraction lines indicated their nanostructure. The peaks are slightly shifted to higher diffraction angles with increasing NiO content, <lb/>indicating the substitution doping of some Ni ions. Increasing the NiO ratio caused the presence of a separated NiO phase as a result of <lb/>an increase in the Ni ion concentration beyond its solubility into the SnO 2 lattice [19]. The samples deposited on the FTO exhibited <lb/>higher crystallinity, and additional peaks corresponding to the SnO phase appeared according to JCPDS 96-901-2141, indicating the <lb/>(101) and (112) planes at diffraction angles around 30 • and 51 • , respectively [20]. <lb/>The following reactions (1) and (2) take place for SnCl 2 in air: <lb/>SnCl 2 + H 2 O → SnO + 2HCl <lb/>(1) <lb/>SnO + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>O 2 →SnO 2 <lb/>(2) <lb/>The reaction of SnCl 2 forms intermediate molecules. Though Sn Cl 2 ⋅2H 2 O can partly ionize into Sn +2 forming SnO structure. <lb/>Full width at half maximum increases with increasing Ni content, indicating a decrease in crystallinity, especially for thin films <lb/>deposited on FTO substrates, suggesting a reduction in crystallite size. In general, replacing the glass substrate with FTO enhances <lb/>crystalline growth, where the substrate of high crystallinity catalyzes the growth in a specific manner. <lb/>The separation distances between atomic planes (d hkl ) were calculated from the angles of diffraction (θ) using Bragg&apos;s law (3) [21]: <lb/>2d hkl sin θ = nλ <lb/>(3) <lb/>where λ = 1.5406 Å is the used X-ray wavelength for Cu-K α , and n is the diffraction order. For the two types: on Glass and FTO <lb/>substrates, the lattice parameters (a and c), for tetragonal SnO 2 prepared at different Ni contents, were determined using equation (4) <lb/>[21]. <lb/>1 <lb/>d 2 <lb/>hkl <lb/>= <lb/>h 2 + k 2 <lb/>a 2 + <lb/>l 2 <lb/>c 2 <lb/>(4) <lb/>While, using Scherrer formula [22], the crystallite size (D) was calculated with equation (5): <lb/>D = <lb/>0.94 λ <lb/>β Cosθ <lb/>(5) <lb/>Here, β represents the broadening of diffraction lines, determined through Lorentzian fitting using Match software. <lb/>While the micro-strain (ε) calculated according to the relation (6) [23]: <lb/>ε = <lb/>β <lb/>4 tan θ <lb/>(6) <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>The lattice constants and the crystallite size (D) for the Ni-SnO 2 on glass and on FTO. <lb/>NiO % <lb/>On glass <lb/>On FTO <lb/>a (Å) <lb/>c (Å) <lb/>D (nm) <lb/>ε × 10 -2 <lb/>a (Å) <lb/>c (Å) <lb/>D (nm) <lb/>ε × 10 -2 <lb/>0 <lb/>4.73445 <lb/>3.18204 <lb/>8.2 <lb/>1.92 <lb/>4.76186 <lb/>3.21788 <lb/>15.2 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>10 <lb/>4.70292 <lb/>3.17320 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>2.10 <lb/>4.74411 <lb/>3.16997 <lb/>9.5 <lb/>1.66 <lb/>20 <lb/>4.69660 <lb/>3.15660 <lb/>6.4 <lb/>2.46 <lb/>4.73320 <lb/>3.15808 <lb/>8.6 <lb/>1.83 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 4. FE-SEM images for SnO 2 on glass (a), SnO 2 on FTO (b), NSO at 10 % Ni on glass (c), NSO at 10 % Ni on FTO (d), NSO at 20 % Ni on glass (e) <lb/>and NSO at 20 % Ni on FTO (f). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 listed the calculated lattice constants, crystallite size, and lattice strain for the SnO 2 films with the content of Nickel on glass <lb/>and FTO substrates. The crystallite size exhibits a decreasing trend with increasing Ni content, attributed to the substitutional doping <lb/>with a lower radius ion, resulting in a reduction in lattice constants. Alongside, the lattice strain experiences an increment with higher <lb/>Ni contents. Conversely, all samples deposited on glass substrates exhibit greater micro strain compared to those on FTO substrates, <lb/>indicating a superior alignment of growth films on FTO due to its lower mismatch with the deposited lattice structure, as opposed to the <lb/>randomly oriented atoms on the glass substrate. <lb/>3.2. Morphological analysis <lb/>The efficacy of gas sensing hinges significantly upon the surface morphology of the active layer, wherein the dimensions of <lb/>nanostructures, porosity, and the inter-cluster connections&apos; behavior play pivotal roles in gas sensing efficiency [24]. Illustrated in <lb/>Fig. 4 are FE-SEM images portraying the as-deposited SnO 2 and the NSO composite thin films with 10 % and 20 % Ni concentrations on <lb/>both glass and FTO substrates. The samples deposited onto glass substrates (Fig. 4-a, c and e) exhibited irregular and non-uniformly <lb/>distributed structures. The pure sample presented itself as a massive surface with small, irregularly dispersed fragments attached. In <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Hall effect parameters for the SnO 2 and NSO films at 10 and 20 % Ni ratios on FTO substrates. <lb/>NiO % <lb/>σ (Ωcm) -1 x10 -5 <lb/>N H cm -3 × 10 14 <lb/>μ H cm 2 /Vs <lb/>0 <lb/>5.82 <lb/>0.759 <lb/>6.77 <lb/>10 <lb/>6.76 <lb/>1.093 <lb/>3.87 <lb/>20 <lb/>8.23 <lb/>1.517 <lb/>2.40 <lb/>Fig. 5. Resistance variation for the SnO 2 and SnO 2 :Ni composite sensor at 100 • C operating temperature against 100 ppm NO 2 on glass (A) and on <lb/>FTO (B). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>contrast, films deposited onto FTO substrates (Fig. 4-b, d and f) demonstrated thorough coverage of the substrate surface. Increasing <lb/>the Ni content to 10 % induced the formation of cauliflower aggregation structures approximately 100 nm in diameter on the surface <lb/>for both substrate types. These aggregations in the glass-deposited sample (Fig. 4-c) exhibited larger separations, while on FTO, they <lb/>were denser and lacked any visible cracks or separations between adjacent nanostructures (Fig. 4-d). Subsequent increments in Ni <lb/>concentration to 20 % led to a heightened density of these nanostructures, appearing interconnected without discernible separations. <lb/>Consequently, samples deposited onto FTO substrates displayed a more regular pattern, with better-distributed nanostructures <lb/>compared to those deposited onto glass. Additionally, the density of surface nanostructures increased with rising Ni concentration. <lb/>Notably, the 10 % Ni concentration resulted in enhanced connectivity between structures, potentially facilitating improved mobility of <lb/>charge carriers across grain boundaries and, consequently, enhancing efficiency in gas sensing applications [25]. The dopant type and <lb/>substrate nature distinctly influence the microstructure governed by thin film nucleation and growth. Moreover, lattice disparities, <lb/>particularly near the contact interface, contribute to increased stress in deposited films, affecting their physical properties, with thin <lb/>films being more susceptible to such influences [26]. <lb/>The measurement of Hall Effect was used to determine the electrical mobility, carrier concentration, conductivity and majority of <lb/>charge carrier&apos;s types for the deposited SnO 2 and NSO films at 10 and 20 % Ni ratios on FTO substrates as listed in Table 2. All films <lb/>were n-type due to oxygen vacancies in metal oxide thin films. N-type semiconductors may play an important role in their electrical <lb/>transport properties by forming an impurity level to release free electrons to the conduction band. The charge carrier mobility <lb/>decreased from 6.77 to 2.40 cm 2 /Vs due to the creation of new grain boundaries against the charge carriers with the reducing the <lb/>nanocrystalline structures, as shown in the FE-SEM test, with increasing the Ni percent from 0 to 20 %. The charge carrier concen-<lb/>tration increased from 0.759 × 10 14 to 1.517 × 10 14 cm -3 for the same samples, which may be due to the formation of lattice defects by <lb/>introducing the dopant, which is the source of charge carriers. The lowest mobility may enhance gas sensitivity, as shown by Li et al. <lb/>[27], so the sample with 20 % Ni suggested has the best gas sensitivity. The final conductivity increased with the Ni dopant. This <lb/>increment may be related to the lattice constant, which can be explained as follows: an increase in the lattice constant means that the <lb/>electrons are less bound to the atom and can, therefore, be more easily removed, leading to a decrease in the band gap. Hence, the <lb/>conductivity increases. <lb/>3.3. Gas sensor measurements <lb/>The gas sensor devices, fabricated on both glass and FTO substrates, underwent testing against NO 2 gas. In Fig. 5(A and B), the <lb/>resistance variation over time is illustrated at an operating temperature of 100 • C with 100 ppm NO 2 for NSO/glass and NSO/FTO, <lb/>featuring different Ni contents (0 %, 10 % and 20 %). In response to the reducing gas NO 2 , all samples demonstrated an increase in <lb/>resistance. As anticipated, the samples exhibited n-type behavior attributed to the presence of oxygen vacancies, where the oxygen <lb/>content falls below its stoichiometric ratio in the SnO 2 structure [28]. <lb/>Previously, ionized oxygen atoms and molecules from the atmosphere gained electrons from the conduction band of the sample, <lb/>creating a depletion area whose effect depends on the size of the nanoparticles, which have a relatively large surface area. When <lb/>oxidizing gas molecules pass, they interact with the surface atoms, leading to an increase in the thickness of the depletion layer. This, in <lb/>turn, results in a decrease in the electrical conductivity of the sample relative to the gas concentration [25]. The decline in conductivity <lb/>occurs through two primary mechanisms: a reduction in carrier concentration close to the surface of nanoparticles or a decrease in <lb/>mobility across grain boundaries [24,29]. Specifically, in the matter of nanoparticles, the predominant impact stems from the alter-<lb/>ation in mobility, attributed to the escalating barrier height across grain boundaries in tandem with an increase in depletion layer <lb/>thickness [30]. <lb/>Gas sensitivity was quantified using equation (7) [25]: <lb/>S% = <lb/>R gas -R air <lb/>R air <lb/>× 100% [Oxidizing gas] <lb/>(7) <lb/>where R air and R gas represent the sensor resistance in clean-air and gas air mixture, respectively. <lb/>The sample blended with 20 % NiO demonstrated the highest sensitivity among all compounds. Across all samples, the recovery <lb/>time consistently outpaced the response time, a characteristic attributed to the prolonged duration required for desorption reactions as <lb/>listed in Table 3. The sensitivity exhibited a pronounced dependence on the nanoparticle structure&apos;s composition, with the 20 % Ni <lb/>sample showing the highest sensitivity. Notably, samples deposited on FTO outperformed those on glass substrates. This superiority is <lb/>attributed to the enhanced surface morphology of the FTO-deposited sample, where the grain boundaries play a pivotal role in <lb/>modulating charge carriers by altering their potential barrier [31]. This nuanced variation in surface morphology contributes to the <lb/>Table 3 <lb/>Sensitivity, response time and recovery for the 20 % Ni-doped SnO 2 sensor for sample deposited on glass and FTO against 100 ppm NO 2 concentration. <lb/>Ni (%) <lb/>On glass <lb/>On FTO <lb/>Sensitivity (%) <lb/>Response time (s) <lb/>Recovery time (s) <lb/>Sensitivity (%) <lb/>Response time (s) <lb/>Recovery time (s) <lb/>0 <lb/>79.1 <lb/>18.0 <lb/>25.0 <lb/>89.0 <lb/>22.0 <lb/>24.0 <lb/>10 <lb/>62.8 <lb/>25.0 <lb/>60.0 <lb/>112.3 <lb/>20.0 <lb/>40.0 <lb/>20 <lb/>436.0 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>45.0 <lb/>501.4 <lb/>17.6 <lb/>36.0 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>heightened sensitivity observed in this particular sample. <lb/>The optimized sensor based on NSO at 20 % Ni on FTO was tested against NO 2 gas at different concentrations from 10 to 50 ppm, at <lb/>100 • C operating temperature. Fig. 6 illustrates the variation of responsivity (the resistance in gas over the resistance in the air) with <lb/>gas. The gas sensitivity trend increased exponentially (as the best fit) with gas concentration as shown in Fig. 7 according to the re-<lb/>lations (8): <lb/>S% = 2.1038 × (NO 2 Con.[ppm]) 0.9048 [R 2 = 0.9893] <lb/>(8) <lb/>Long-term stability is a crucial factor to sensors [32]. Fig. 8 (a,b) shows the long-term stability of the NSO/FTO sensor with same <lb/>NO 2 gas concentration of 50 ppm conducted at optimum operating temperature of 100 • C. It seems the high stability of the prepared <lb/>sensor. The relative deviation of the gas response along 12 days is estimated to be 1.76 % and the average response value was <lb/>calculated to be 1.68. The results indicate that the NSO/FTO sensor displays a good stability. <lb/>Table 4 illustrates a comparison between the specification of some previous gas sensors based on nanostructures of pure and doped <lb/>SnO 2 prepared by different techniques against different gasses with the current study. Although the sensitivity is lower than that <lb/>previously reported, but the optimum working temperature at a lower temperature, in addition, operates at a wide range of detection <lb/>than the compared studies. <lb/>4. Conclusions <lb/>A low-cost chemo-resistance gas sensor based on NSO layers with different proportions of Ni was synthesized by spray pyrolysis <lb/>Fig. 6. Responsivity variation at 100 • C for the 20 % Ni-doped SnO 2 deposited on FTO against different NO 2 concentrations. <lb/>Fig. 7. Sensitivity curve fit against the gas concentration at 100 • C for the 20 % Ni-doped SnO 2 deposited on FTO. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

        <body>technique on glass, and FTO substrates to investigate the effect of substrate structure on the deposited nano-film configuration and its <lb/>effect on gas sensing performance. FE-SEM images test indicates the homogeneous NSO thin films with distinct nanostructure at a high <lb/>Ni content. The XRD measurements show a nanocrystalline structure. The lattice parameters reduced with increasing the Ni compose <lb/>ratio. The deposition on FTO substrate instead of glass substrates highly affects the structural and surface morphology. Concerning <lb/>nanoparticles, a significant impact arises from the fluctuation in barrier height along the grain boundaries, influencing the behavior of <lb/>charge carriers as the depletion layer thickness increases. Hence, the sample resistance is highly sensitive to low concentrations of a <lb/>target gas by the mechanism of adsorption-desorption of gas molecules. The optimum sample was the NSO with 20 % Ni deposited on <lb/>FTO. The proposed equation for sensitivity with gas concentration was achieved with a high R 2 value. By comparing the results with <lb/>those in previous research, despite the simplicity of manufacturing, a sensor was obtained that operates at a lower operating tem-<lb/>perature compared to previous studies, with acceptable sensitivity specifications. Our findings not only contribute to the fundamental <lb/>understanding of NSO thin films but also underscore the critical role played by Ni content and substrate type in modifying both <lb/>structural and sensing properties. This study contributes in advancement of gas sensing applications through enhanced configurations <lb/>of NSO thin films. <lb/></body>

        <div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>Data will be made available on request. <lb/></div>

        <body>Fig. 8. Long-term stability of Ni-doped SnO 2 /FTO sensor at 100 • C against 50 ppm NO 2 gas: (a) time variation of gas response, and (b) maximum <lb/>gas response. <lb/>Table 4 <lb/>Comparison between the specification of previous SnO 2 -based gas sensors prepared by different techniques with the current study. <lb/>Sensor <lb/>Deposition technique <lb/>Target <lb/>gas <lb/>Optimum operating <lb/>Temp. ( • C) <lb/>Detection range <lb/>(ppm) <lb/>Sensitivity or <lb/>response <lb/>Ref. <lb/>Ni-Doped SnO2 <lb/>hydrothermal <lb/>HCHO <lb/>200 <lb/>1-50 <lb/>R = 68 at 50 ppm <lb/>[33] <lb/>Ni-Doped SnO 2 <lb/>Microwave-assisted wet <lb/>chemical <lb/>CO 2 <lb/>275 <lb/>10-200 <lb/>S = 73 % <lb/>[34] <lb/>SnO 2 nanofibers <lb/>Electrospinning <lb/>H 2 S <lb/>350 <lb/>0.1-1 <lb/>R = 15.2 at 1 ppm <lb/>[35] <lb/>SnO 2 nanowires <lb/>Hydrothermal <lb/>H 2 <lb/>250 <lb/>1-50 <lb/>R = 13 at 40 ppm <lb/>[36] <lb/>Ni-doped SnO 2 microstructures <lb/>Facile chemical solution <lb/>ethanol <lb/>260 <lb/>1-100 <lb/>R = 40 at 25 ppm <lb/>[37] <lb/>Ni-doped SnO 2 thick films <lb/>Screen printing <lb/>LPG <lb/>300 <lb/>600 <lb/>S = 92 % at 600 <lb/>ppm <lb/>[38] <lb/>Ni-doped SnO 2 hollow spheres <lb/>Carbon microsphere <lb/>template method <lb/>butanol <lb/>300 <lb/>5-1500 <lb/>R = 5.3 at 5 ppm <lb/>[39] <lb/>SnO 2 : In 2 O 3 <lb/>PLD <lb/>NO 2 <lb/>200 <lb/>10-400 <lb/>S = 300 % at 100 <lb/>ppm <lb/>[40] <lb/>Nanocrystalline Ni-doped SnO 2 <lb/>thin films/glass <lb/>Spray pyrolysis <lb/>NO 2 <lb/>100 <lb/>10-100 <lb/>S = 436 % or R = <lb/>5.36 <lb/>at 100 ppm <lb/>Current <lb/>work <lb/>Nanocrystalline Ni-doped SnO 2 <lb/>thin films/FTO <lb/>Spray pyrolysis <lb/>NO 2 <lb/>100 <lb/>10-100 <lb/>S = 501 % or R = <lb/>6.01 <lb/>at 100 ppm <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

            <div type="contribution">CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>Khamael Ibrahim Abdulwahid: Writing -original draft. Chiheb Chaker: Supervision. Hanen Chaker: Formal analysis. <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to <lb/>influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We extend our sincere respect, appreciation, and gratitude to the Center of Applied Physics, Ministry of Science and Technology, <lb/>Baghdad, Iraq, for their invaluable support. Additionally, we express our heartfelt thanks to the Laboratory of Multifunctional Ma-<lb/>terials and Applications (LaMMA), Faculty of Sciences of Sfax, University of Sfax, Tunisia, for their collaboration and contributions to <lb/>our research endeavors. Their unwavering support has been instrumental in the success of our work. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] K. H. V, R. Thejas, C.S. Naveen, M.I. Khan, G.D. Prasanna, S. Reddy, M. Oreijah, K. Guedri, O.T. Bafakeeh, M. Jameel, A Review on Electrical and Gas-Sensing <lb/>Properties of Reduced Graphene Oxide-Metal Oxide Nanocomposites, Biomass Conversion and Biorefinery, 2022. <lb/>[2] D. Zhang, Z. Yang, S. Yu, Q. Mi, Q. Pan, Diversiform metal oxide-based hybrid nanostructures for gas sensing with versatile prospects, Coord. Chem. Rev. 413 <lb/>(2020) 213272. <lb/>[3] Z. Feng, A. Gaiardo, S. Krik, V. Guidi, G. Pepponi, C. Malagù, P. Bellutti, B. Fabbri, M. Valt, S. Caramori, Gas sensing properties comparison between SnO 2 and <lb/>highly antimony-doped SnO 2 materials, ECS Meeting Abstracts (56) (2021) 1435. MA2021-01. <lb/>[4] J.M. Rzaij, S.O. Nawaf, A.K. Ibrahim, A review on tin dioxide gas sensor: the role of the metal oxide doping, nanoparticles, and operating temperatures, World <lb/>Journal of Advanced Research and Reviews 14 (1) (2022) 51-62. <lb/>[5] X. Kang, N. Deng, Z. Yan, Y. Pan, W. Sun, Y. Zhang, Resistive-type VOCs and pollution gases sensor based on SnO 2 : a review, Mater. Sci. Semicond. Process. 138 <lb/>(2022) 106246. <lb/>[6] M. Ajili, N.T. Kamoun, Structural and optoelectronic studies of CuO, In 2-x Al x S 3 and SnO 2 :F sprayed thin films for solar cell application: Au/CuO (p)/In 2-x Al x S 3 <lb/>(n), SnO 2 :F, Optik 229 (2021) 166222. <lb/>[7] S. Lu, Y. Zhang, J. Liu, H.-Y. Li, Z. Hu, X. Luo, N. Gao, B. Zhang, J. Jiang, A. Zhong, J. Luo, H. Liu, Sensitive H 2 gas sensors based on SnO 2 nanowires, Sensor. <lb/>Actuator. B Chem. 345 (2021) 130334. <lb/>[8] P. Senthilkumar, S. Raja, R. Ramesh Babu, G. Vasuki, Enhanced electrical and optoelectronic properties of W doped SnO 2 thin films, Opt. Mater. 126 (2022) <lb/>112234. <lb/>[9] R. Ramarajan, M. Kovendhan, K. Thangaraju, D.P. Joseph, R.R. Babu, V. Elumalai, Enhanced optical transparency and electrical conductivity of Ba and Sb co-<lb/>doped SnO 2 thin films, J. Alloys Compd. 823 (2020) 153709. <lb/>[10] Y. Masuda, Recent advances in SnO 2 nanostructure based gas sensors, Sensor. Actuator. B Chem. 364 (2022) 131876. <lb/>[11] Z. Feng, A. Gaiardo, M. Valt, B. Fabbri, D. Casotti, S. Krik, L. Vanzetti, M. Della Ciana, S. Fioravanti, S. Caramori, A. Rota, V. Guidi, Investigation on sensing <lb/>performance of highly doped Sb/SnO 2 , Sensors 22 (3) (2022) 1-18. <lb/>[12] W. Wang, Y. Liu, S. Liu, SnO 2 nanostructure with well-engineered crystal facets by Zn doping for chemical sensing applications, Cryst. Growth Des. 20 (4) (2020) <lb/>2742-2752. <lb/>[13] T. Zima, N. Bulina, Enhanced room-temperature ferromagnetism of Co-doped SnO 2 nanostructures produced by the hydrothermal method, Mater. Res. Bull. 117 <lb/>(2019) 48-55. <lb/>[14] N. Kaur, M. Singh, E. Comini, One-dimensional nanostructured oxide chemoresistive sensors, Langmuir 36 (23) (2020) 6326-6344. <lb/>[15] C.W. Ji, J.H. Kim, H.G. Kim, H.N. Lee, H.J. Kim, H. Lee, H.C. Lee, Preparation and characterization of flexible gas sensors with nanostructured NiO-doped SnO 2 <lb/>thick films, Nanosci. Nanotechnol. Lett. 10 (9) (2018) 1262-1266. <lb/>[16] S. Bera, S.A. Lee, W.-J. Lee, M. Ilka, J.-H. Kim, C.-M. Kim, H. Khan, H.W. Jang, S.-H. Kwon, Atomic layer deposition seeded growth of rutile SnO 2 nanowires on <lb/>versatile conducting substrates, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 12 (43) (2020) 48486-48494. <lb/>[17] Y. Masuda, Facet controlled growth mechanism of SnO 2 (101) nanosheet assembled film via cold crystallization, Sci. Rep. 11 (1) (2021) 11304. <lb/>[18] K.I. Abdulwahid, C. Chaker, H. Chaker, Ni-doped SnO 2 thin films for NO 2 gas sensing application, Sensor Actuator Phys. 360 (2023) 114498. <lb/>[19] R. Higler, J. Sprakel, Doping colloidal bcc crystals -interstitial solids and meta-stable clusters, Sci. Rep. 7 (1) (2017) 12634. <lb/>[20] N. Memarian, S.M. Rozati, E. Elamurugu, E. Fortunato, Characterization of SnO 2 :F thin films deposited by an economic spray pyrolysis technique, Phys. Status <lb/>Solidi C 7 (9) (2010) 2277-2281. <lb/>[21] L.K. Dintle, P.V.C. Luhanga, C. Moditswe, C.M. Muiva, Compositional dependence of optical and electrical properties of indium doped zinc oxide (IZO) thin films <lb/>deposited by chemical spray pyrolysis, Phys. E Low-dimens. Syst. Nanostruct. 99 (2018) 91-97. <lb/>[22] A.S. Hassanien, I.M. El Radaf, Effect of fluorine doping on the structural, optical, and electrical properties of spray deposited Sb 2 O 3 thin films, Mater. Sci. <lb/>Semicond. Process. 160 (2023) 107405. <lb/>[23] A.A. Akl, A.S. Hassanien, Microstructure and crystal imperfections of nanosized CdS Se1-thermally evaporated thin films, Superlattice. Microst. 85 (2015) <lb/>67-81. <lb/>[24] M.A. Kadhim, A.A. Ramadhan, M.O.S. Al-Gburi, G.J. Habi, N.J. Hentawe, Effect of mixing ratio of (SnO 2 ) 1-x (In 2 O 3 ) x thin film on gas sensitivity, Karbala <lb/>International Journal of Modern Science 6 (1) (2020) 83-92. <lb/>[25] M.A. Kadhim, A.A. Ramadhan, M.O.S. Al-Gburi, Effect of PEG addition on an SnO 2 gas sensor fabricated using spin coating, Karbala International Journal of <lb/>Modern Science 7 (1) (2021). <lb/>[26] A.A. Abuelwafa, M.S.A. El-sadek, S. Elnobi, T. Soga, Effect of transparent conducting substrates on the structure and optical properties of tin (II) oxide (SnO) thin <lb/>films: comparative study, Ceram. Int. 47 (10) (2021) 13510-13518. <lb/>[27] R. Li, Y. Zhou, M. Sun, Z. Gong, Y. Guo, F. Wu, W. Li, W. Ding, Influence of charge carriers concentration and mobility on the gas sensing behavior of tin dioxide <lb/>thin films, Coatings 9 (9) (2019) 1-12, 591. <lb/>[28] Q. Zeng, Y. Cui, L. Zhu, Y. Yao, Increasing oxygen vacancies at room temperature in SnO 2 for enhancing ethanol gas sensing, Mater. Sci. Semicond. Process. 111 <lb/>(2020) 104962. <lb/>[29] J. Liu, J. Lv, H. Xiong, Y. Wang, G. Jin, Z. Zhai, C. Fu, Q. Zhang, Size effect and comprehensive mathematical model for gas-sensing mechanism of SnO 2 thin film <lb/>gas sensors, J. Alloys Compd. 898 (2022) 162875. <lb/>[30] Y. Xu, W. Zheng, X. Liu, L. Zhang, L. Zheng, C. Yang, N. Pinna, J. Zhang, Platinum single atoms on tin oxide ultrathin films for extremely sensitive gas detection, <lb/>Mater. Horiz. 7 (6) (2020) 1519-1527. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e25585 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[31] P.H. Phuoc, C.M. Hung, N. Van Toan, N. Van Duy, N.D. Hoa, N. Van Hieu, One-step fabrication of SnO 2 porous nanofiber gas sensors for sub-ppm H 2 S detection, <lb/>Sensor Actuator Phys. 303 (2020) 111722. <lb/>[32] J. Li, M. Zheng, M. Yang, X. Zhang, X. Cheng, X. Zhou, S. Gao, Y. Xu, L. Huo, Three-in-one Ni doped porous SnO 2 nanorods sensor: controllable oxygen vacancies <lb/>content, surface site activation and low power consumption for highly selective NO 2 monitoring, Sensor. Actuator. B Chem. 382 (2023) 133550. <lb/>[33] Z. Yang, W. Cao, C. Peng, T. Wang, B. Li, H. Ma, Y. Su, Z. Zhou, J. Yang, M. Zeng, Construction, application and verification of a novel formaldehyde gas sensor <lb/>system based on Ni-doped SnO 2 nanoparticles, IEEE Sensor. J. 21 (9) (2021) 11023-11030. <lb/>[34] V. Manikandan, I. Petrila, S. Vigneselvan, R.S. Mane, B. Vasile, R. Dharmavarapu, S. Lundgaard, S. Juodkazis, J. Chandrasekaran, A reliable chemiresistive <lb/>sensor of nickel-doped tin oxide (Ni-SnO 2 ) for sensing carbon dioxide gas and humidity, RSC Adv. 10 (7) (2020) 3796-3804. <lb/>[35] W. Maziarz, TiO 2 /SnO 2 and TiO 2 /CuO thin film nano-heterostructures as gas sensors, Appl. Surf. Sci. 480 (2019) 361-370. <lb/>[36] S. Lu, Y. Zhang, J. Liu, H.-Y. Li, Z. Hu, X. Luo, N. Gao, B. Zhang, J. Jiang, A. Zhong, J. Luo, H. Liu, Sensitive H 2 gas sensors based on SnO 2 nanowires, Sensor. <lb/>Actuator. B Chem. 345 (2021) 130334. <lb/>[37] C. Gu, W. Guan, X. Liu, L. Gao, L. Wang, J.J. Shim, J. Huang, Controlled synthesis of porous Ni-doped SnO 2 microstructures and their enhanced gas sensing <lb/>properties, J. Alloys Compd. 692 (2017) 855-864. <lb/>[38] K. Jain, R.P. Pant, S.T. Lakshmikumar, Effect of Ni doping on thick film SnO 2 gas sensor, Sens. Actuators, B 113 (2) (2006) 823-829. <lb/>[39] X. Liu, J. Zhang, X. Guo, S. Wu, S. Wang, Enhanced sensor response of Ni-doped SnO 2 hollow spheres, Sens. Actuators, B 152 (2) (2011) 162-167. <lb/>[40] M.A. Kadhim, A.A. Ramadhan, M.O.S. Al-Gburi, G.J. Habi, N.J. Hentawe, Effect of mixing ratio of (SnO 2 ) 1-x (In 2 O 3 ) x thin film on gas sensitivity, Karbala <lb/>International Journal of Modern Science 6 (1) (2020). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">K.I. Abdulwahid et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
