<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Mixed messages, broken trust, avoidable deaths: A critical appraisal of the UK government’s response to the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Alessandro</forename>
          <surname>Siani</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Luca</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-03T17:56:11.313Z">11/3/2025 5:56:11 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Walter de Gruyter GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1515/ohe-2023-0016</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Alessandro Siani. (2024). Mixed messages, broken trust, avoidable deaths: A critical appraisal of the UK government’s response to the COVID-19 pandemic. Open Health, 5(1), None. DOI: 10.1515/ohe-2023-0016</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-03T17:55:59.372240Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-03T17:55:59.372240Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Research Article <lb/>Marina S. Ascunce*, Katherine Casey Carroll, Joe Aufmuth, Lauren Justice, Patricia Perez, <lb/>Andrew Nisip, Jenny M. Gavilanez-Slone, Jawwad A. Qureshi, Sanford Porter and Andrea Lucky <lb/>Ant community composition in a citrus grove <lb/>reveals eastern expansion in Florida of the South <lb/>American big-headed ant (Hymenoptera: <lb/>Formicidae) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1515/flaent-2024-0011 <lb/>Received February 28, 2024; accepted February 29, 2024; <lb/>published online March 29, 2024 <lb/>Abstract: Florida has become a worldwide hotspot for <lb/>introduced and invasive ants (Hymenoptera: Formicidae). <lb/>Furthermore, studies have shown that non-native ants <lb/>support other invasive insects in Florida, such as the Asian <lb/>citrus psyllid, Diaphorina citri Kuwayama (Hemiptera: <lb/>Liviidae), which is the vector of Candidatus Liberibacter <lb/>asiaticus, the causal pathogen of citrus greening, the worst <lb/>citrus disease in the world. The Asian citrus psyllid estab-<lb/>lishes beneficial interactions with invasive, introduced, and <lb/>native ants. In this study, we described the ant diversity in a <lb/>citrus grove in south Florida as a first step to assess ant-Asian <lb/>citrus psyllid interactions for future studies. During the <lb/>summer of 2018, 25 pitfall traps were set in a citrus grove. <lb/>The red imported fire ant, Solenopsis invicta (Buren), was <lb/>present in all the traps (100 %), and 19 traps (76 %) had <lb/>Dorymyrmex bureni (Trager), the pyramid ant, which is <lb/>native to the southeast United States. Two introduced ants, <lb/>Cardiocondyla emeryi (Forel) and Brachymyrmex obscurior <lb/>(Forel), were found in 15 (60 %) and 11 (44 %) traps, respec-<lb/>tively. The South American big-headed ant, Pheidole <lb/>obscurithorax (Naves), was found in 14 traps (56 %). This <lb/>introduced ant has been found to co-exist with S. invicta, and <lb/>to our knowledge, this is the first report of the species in this <lb/>eastern part of peninsular Florida. Finally, Cardiocondyla <lb/>venustula (Wheeler), an introduced ant from Africa, was <lb/>found in one of the traps. Although, this ant is found in south <lb/>Florida, it seems uncommon, and this is its first report in this <lb/>county. Our study highlights the continued spread of intro-<lb/>duced and invasive ants in Florida. <lb/>Keywords: invasive ants; fire ants; Pheidole obscurithorax; <lb/>pitfall traps; Asian citrus psyllid; citrus greening <lb/>Sumario: Florida se ha convertido en un &quot;hot-spot&quot; para <lb/>especies introducidas e invasoras de hormigas <lb/>Current address: Katherine Casey Carroll, Department of Ecology and <lb/>Evolutionary Biology, University of Colorado at Boulder, Boulder, CO 80309, <lb/>USA, E-mail: Casey.Carroll@colorado.edu. <lb/>Current address: Patricia Perez, Florida Department of Agriculture and <lb/>Consumer Services, Department of Plant Industry, Gainesville, FL 32608, <lb/>USA, E-mail: patricia.perez@fdacs.gov. <lb/>Current address: Andrew Nisip, Department of Biology, University of <lb/>Louisville, Louisville, KY 40292, USA; E-mail: andrew.nisip@louisville.edu. <lb/>Current address: Jenny M. Gavilanez-Slone, Entomology Laboratory, <lb/>Faculty of Natural Resources, Escuela Superior Politécnica de Chimborazo <lb/>(ESPOCH), Riobamba, Ecuador; E-mail: jenny.gavilanez@espoch.edu.ec. <lb/>*Corresponding author: Marina S. Ascunce, USDA-ARS Center for <lb/>Medical, Agricultural, and Veterinary Entomology, Gainesville, FL 32608, <lb/>USA; and Emergency Pathogens Institute, Department of Plant <lb/>Pathology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA, <lb/>E-mail: marina.ascunce@usda.gov. https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5239-<lb/>3585 <lb/>Katherine Casey Carroll, Patricia Perez and Jenny M. Gavilanez-Slone, <lb/>Emergency Pathogens Institute, Department of Plant Pathology, University <lb/>of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32610, USA <lb/>Joe Aufmuth, George A. Smathers Libraries, University of Florida, <lb/>Gainesville, FL 32611, USA, E-mail: mapper@uflib.ufl.edu <lb/>Lauren Justice and Sanford Porter, USDA-ARS Center for Medical, <lb/>Agricultural, and Veterinary Entomology, Gainesville, FL 32608, USA, <lb/>E-mail: lauren.justice@usda.gov (L. Justice), sdporter22@gmail.com <lb/>(S. Porter) <lb/>Andrew Nisip, USDA-ARS Center for Medical, Agricultural, and Veterinary <lb/>Entomology, Gainesville, FL 32608, USA; and Emergency Pathogens <lb/>Institute, Department of Plant Pathology, University of Florida, Gainesville, <lb/>FL 32610, USA <lb/>Jawwad A. Qureshi, Entomology and Nematology Department, Southwest <lb/>Florida Research and Education Center (SWFREC), University of Florida, <lb/>Immokalee, FL 34142, USA, E-mail: jawwadq@ufl.edu <lb/>Andrea Lucky, Entomology and Nematology Department, University of <lb/>Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA, E-mail: alucky@ufl.edu <lb/>Fla. Entomol. 2024; 107(1): 20240011 <lb/>Open Access. © 2024 the author(s), published by De Gruyter on behalf of the Florida Entomological Society. <lb/>This work is licensed under the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. <lb/>(Himenóptera: Formicidae). A su vez, estudios han mos-<lb/>trado que las hormigas no-nativas ayudan a otras especies <lb/>invasoras en Florida como el psílido asiático de los cítricos, <lb/>Diaphorina citri Kuwayama (Hemíptera: Liviidae), el cual <lb/>es vector de Candidatus Liberibacter asiaticus, el agente <lb/>causal de la enfermedad del &quot;enverdecimiento&quot; de los <lb/>cítricos, la peor enfermedad de los cítricos a nivel mundial. <lb/>El psílido asiático de los cítricos establece relaciones <lb/>beneficiosas con hormigas invasoras, introducidas y nati-<lb/>vas. En este estudio, describimos la diversidad de hormigas <lb/>en una huerta de cítricos en el sur de la Florida, como un <lb/>primer paso para evaluar las interacciones entre las hor-<lb/>migas y el psílido asiático de los cítricos en estudios futu-<lb/>ros. En el verano del 2018 se pusieron 25 trampas de caída <lb/>en una huerta de cítricos. La hormiga invasora roja de <lb/>fuego, Solenopsis invicta (Buren), estuvo presente en todas <lb/>las trampas (100 %), mientras que 19 trampas (76 %) tenían <lb/>Dorymyrmex bureni (Trager), la hormiga piramidal, la cual <lb/>es nativa del sureste de los Estados Unidos. Dos hormigas <lb/>introducidas: Cardiocondyla emeryi (Forel) y Brachymyr-<lb/>mex obscurior (Forel) se encontraron en 15 (60 %) y 11 <lb/>(44 %) de las trampas, respectivamente. La hormiga Sud-<lb/>americana de cabeza grande, Pheidole obscurithorax <lb/>(Naves), fue hallada en 14 trampas (56 %). Esta hormiga <lb/>introducida ha sido hallada coexistiendo con S. invicta y a <lb/>nuestro entender, este sería el primer reporte de esta <lb/>hormiga en el este de la península de Florida. Finalmente, <lb/>Cardiocondyla venustula (Wheeler), una hormiga intro-<lb/>ducida del Viejo Mundo fue hallada en una de las trampas. <lb/>A pesar de que esta hormiga se encuentra en el sur de la <lb/>Florida, es menos común, y este sería el primer reporte de <lb/>esta hormiga en este condado. Nuestro estudio remarca la <lb/>continua expansión de las hormigas introducidas e inva-<lb/>soras en Florida. <lb/>Palabras Claves: hormigas invasoras; hormigas de fuego; <lb/>Pheidole obscurithorax; trampas de caída; psílido asiático de <lb/>los cítricos; enverdecimiento de los cítricos <lb/></front>

        <body>More than 520 ant species (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) have <lb/>been transported outside their native range and established <lb/>in new areas worldwide (Bertelsmeier et al. 2018; Lach et al. <lb/>2010; Wong et al. 2023). Five of them are among the 100 most <lb/>concerning invasive species including the red imported fire <lb/>ant, Solenopsis invicta (Buren), the Argentine ant, Line-<lb/>pithema humile (Mayr), the African big-headed ant, Pheidole <lb/>megacephala (Fabricius), the little fire ant, Wasmannia <lb/>auropunctata (Roger), and the longlegged ant, Anoplolepis <lb/>gracilipes (Smith) (ISSG 2015). All these five ants are in the <lb/>United States, and all but A. gracilipes are in Florida (Deyrup <lb/>2003; King and Porter 2007; Ohyama et al. 2020). The total ant <lb/>fauna in Florida encompasses 218 ant species, with 52 being <lb/>introduced or invasive (Deyrup 2003; Deyrup et al. 2000). <lb/>This non-native ant fauna is the largest among any of the <lb/>states in the United States (Deyrup 2003) and the largest <lb/>regional non-native ant fauna in the world (King and Porter <lb/>2007), making Florida a hot spot for introduced and invasive <lb/>ants. Even though non-native ant species are known in <lb/>Florida, the understanding of ant community composition <lb/>has not received enough attention, and the knowledge of the <lb/>distributions of even well-established species is limited. A <lb/>clear understanding of how these non-native ants get <lb/>established in Florida may eventually allow formal meta-<lb/>analyses of invasion impacts, which could help pinpoint <lb/>problematic taxa and prioritize early responses. Mapping <lb/>the new reports of invasive species is central to reporting <lb/>expansions of invasive species, guiding effective early re-<lb/>sponses to limit their further geographical expansion, and <lb/>determining if control efforts are working (Elith and <lb/>Leathwick 2009). This study aimed to characterize the ant <lb/>fauna at one agricultural site in Florida, particularly at a <lb/>citrus grove, due to its importance in Florida agriculture. <lb/>In Florida, citrus is a major part of the agricultural <lb/>landscape and a high-value crop of USD $438 million <lb/>(USDA-NASS 2022). In 1998, a serious pest of citrus, the Asian <lb/>citrus psyllid, Diaphorina citri Kuwayama (Hemiptera: Livii-<lb/>dae), was discovered in Florida (Halbert 1998). This invasive <lb/>psyllid is the vector of Candidatus Liberibacter asiaticus, a <lb/>phloem-limited α-proteobacterium, that is the cause of <lb/>the devastating citrus disease Huanglongbing or citrus <lb/>greening. About seven years after D. citri arrived in Florida, <lb/>Huanglongbing was detected in 2005 (Bové 2006) and since <lb/>this date has spread throughout Florida. Currently, 100 % of <lb/>the citrus groves in Florida are positive for Huanglongbing <lb/>(Graham et al. 2020). Because no cure is available, infected <lb/>trees die within a few years, resulting in an 85 % reduction in <lb/>citrus production since the onset of Huanglongbing in the <lb/>state (Singerman and Rogers 2020; USDA-NASS 2022). Man-<lb/>agement of Huanglongbing with antimicrobial agents and <lb/>nutritional treatments has not prevented major production <lb/>losses in Florida (Blaustein et al. 2018; Wang et al. 2017). <lb/>Classical biological control of D. citri using a parasitic wasp, <lb/>Tamarixia radiata (Waterston) (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae) <lb/>(Hoy et al. 1999) has not been effective in controlling the <lb/>psyllid presumably due to its sensitivity to insecticides and <lb/>low temperatures during winter (Chong et al. 2010; Qureshi <lb/>et al. 2009). The limited effect of biological control agents gets <lb/>exacerbated by ants in citrus groves, as ants help D. citri by <lb/>protecting them against natural enemies (predators and <lb/>parasitoids) in return for the psyllid&apos;s sugary excretions <lb/>(i.e., honeydew) as their food. Ants do this by physically <lb/>attacking predators and parasitoids and driving them away <lb/></body>

        <page>2 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M.S. Ascunce et al.: Ant community composition in a citrus grove in Florida <lb/></note>

        <body>from D. citri (Michaud 2004; Navarrete et al. 2013; Oliver et al. <lb/>2008; Shrestha et al. 2022; Vanek and Potter 2010; Yoo et al. <lb/>2013). In Florida citrus groves, invasive and introduced ants, <lb/>including the red imported fire ant, the African big-headed <lb/>ant, the rover ant, Brachymyrmex obscurior (Forel), as well as <lb/>the native pyramid ant, Dorymyrmex bureni (Trager) have <lb/>been observed tending and protecting D. citri (Michaud 2004; <lb/>Navarrete et al. 2013; Shrestha et al. 2022). This study focused <lb/>on ant species diversity in a Florida citrus grove as a first step <lb/>to gain insights into the different ant species that can poten-<lb/>tially provide protection for D. citri against its predators. <lb/>On 5 July 2018, we surveyed a citrus grove at the Uni-<lb/>versity of Florida Indian River Research and Education <lb/>Center (IRREC) in Fort Pierce (27.43 °N, 80.41 °W). Ants were <lb/>collected using pitfall traps with ethanol (70 %), as described <lb/>in Laub et al. (2009). A &quot;mini-roof&quot; was designed to protect <lb/>the traps from rain and reduce evaporation (Supplementary <lb/>Material 1). Traps were placed along three transects sepa-<lb/>rated by 25 m. Along each transect, 7-10 pitfall traps were <lb/>placed at about 5 m intervals for a total of 25 traps. Traps <lb/>were collected after 48 h. Ants were sorted, transferred <lb/>into vials with 95 % ethanol, and identified under a stereo-<lb/>microscope using taxonomic keys from Deyrup (2003, 2016) <lb/>and MacGown (2022). <lb/>After taxonomic identification, the presence of each ant <lb/>species per pitfall was summarized in Table 1. All 25 traps <lb/>(100 %) contained specimens of red imported fire ant, and 19 <lb/>(76 %) contained D. bureni. Cardiocondyla emeryi (Forel) and <lb/>B. obscurior were found in 15 (60 %) and 11 (44 %) traps, <lb/>respectively. The South American big-headed ant, Pheidole <lb/>obscurithorax (Naves), was found in 14 traps (56 %). Finally, <lb/>Cardiocondyla venustula (Wheeler) was found in one pitfall <lb/>(4 %). <lb/>A map was created to show the co-distribution of red <lb/>imported fire ant and D. bureni, as well as P. obscurithorax <lb/>and C. venustula (Figure 1). We used the Global Biodiversity <lb/>Information Facility (GBIF) to create this map. Detailed in-<lb/>formation on the process used to create this map is in Sup-<lb/>plementary Material 2. Presence-only data for each species <lb/>was downloaded individually, combined and evaluated for <lb/>occurrences and duplications. The species records outside of <lb/>Florida were removed. A final presence or absence matrix <lb/>Table : Presence of ant species per pitfall: Solenopsis invicta, Dorymyrmex bureni, Cardiocondyla emeryi, Pheidole obscurithorax, Brachymyrmex obscurior, <lb/>and Cardiocondyla venustula. <lb/>Pitfall <lb/>S. invicta <lb/>D. bureni <lb/>C. emeryi <lb/>P. obscurithorax <lb/>B. obscurior <lb/>C. venustula <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/># Positive pitfalls <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Prevalence <lb/> % <lb/> % <lb/> % <lb/> % <lb/> % <lb/> % <lb/>Status <lb/>Inv <lb/>N <lb/>Int <lb/>Int <lb/>Int <lb/>Int <lb/>Status: Inv: invasive; Int: introduced; N: native. <lb/>M.S. Ascunce et al.: Ant community composition in a citrus grove in Florida <lb/></body>

        <page>3 <lb/></page>

        <body>based on latitude, longitude, and species was imported into <lb/>ArcGIS Pro v2.2 (Esri, Redlands, California), where separate <lb/>layers were created for each species. <lb/>Most agricultural lands are highly disturbed, facilitating <lb/>the establishment of invasive species that outcompete and <lb/>exclude native species (Mooney and Cleland 2001). This could <lb/>be the case in this citrus grove, in which five out of the six <lb/>species collected were non-native (Table 1). However, long-<lb/>term studies need to be done to confirm this hypothesis. It <lb/>was not surprising to find red imported fire ant in 100 % of <lb/>the traps (Table 1). This invasive ant from South America was <lb/>first detected in Mobile, Alabama, in the late 1930s. Since <lb/>then, it has rapidly spread throughout the southeast US as <lb/>well as other countries, becoming a global invasive species in <lb/>the 2000s (Ascunce et al. 2011). Several features make the red <lb/>imported fire ant a successful invader, including high <lb/>reproducibility, ability to outcompete native ants for re-<lb/>sources, and social structure (Arnan et al. 2018; Bertelsmeier <lb/>et al. 2017; Holway et al. 2002; Passera 1994). Despite the red <lb/>imported fire ant&apos;s ability to outcompete native ants in <lb/>general, the native Dorymyrmex are able to coexist with <lb/>S. invicta (Helms and Vinson 2001; LeBrun et al. 2012; Stuble <lb/>et al. 2010), and in this study, D. bureni was in fact found in <lb/>70 % of the traps. Both species have been found to tend to <lb/>D. citri; however, S. invicta provides greater protection to the <lb/>psyllid against its natural enemies, resulting in a larger <lb/>economic cost to citrus growers in Florida (Shrestha et al. <lb/>2022). <lb/>Cardiocondyla are native to Africa and Asia, but some <lb/>Cardiocondyla species have become common cosmopolitan <lb/>introduced ants, including C. emeryi. In the case of C. venus-<lb/>tula, this ant has been recently introduced to the Caribbean, <lb/>Florida and Hawaii and its distribution seems to be <lb/>expanding (Seifert 2002; Starr et al. 2007), with this study <lb/>being its first report in this county (Table 1, Figure 1). For B. <lb/>obscurior, a native ant from the Neotropics, the nature of its <lb/>presence in Florida as introduced or native species is not <lb/>clear (Deyrup et al. 2000). Finally, P. obscurithorax, an ant <lb/>native to South America, was first found in Mobile, Alabama <lb/>in 1949, and then spread to other parts of the southeast US <lb/>(Naves 1985). Its current distribution in the US extends from <lb/>Texas to Florida, where it co-exists with the red imported fire <lb/>ant. It reached the panhandle of Florida in the late 1990s <lb/>(Storz and Tschinkel 2004; Wetterer et al. 2015; Wilson 2003). <lb/>This study is the first report of this species in the eastern part <lb/>of peninsular Florida and in a citrus grove. Although the <lb/>negative impact of its introduction is unclear, it continues to <lb/>spread through Florida and is expected to eventually occupy <lb/>a range similar to the red imported fire ant (King and <lb/>Tschinkel 2007). Our study highlights the continued spread <lb/>Figure 1: Distribution of S. invicta, D. bureni, <lb/>P. obscurithorax, and C. venustula in Florida. <lb/>S. invicta (shaded light red, data from <lb/>USDA-APHIS-PPQ https://www.aphis.usda. <lb/>gov/plant_health/plant_pest_info/fireants/ <lb/>downloads/federal-imported-fire-ant-<lb/>quarantine.pdf), D. bureni (gray stripes, data <lb/>from Deyrup (2016)), P. obscurithorax (filled <lb/>circles, data from GBIF https://doi.org/10. <lb/>15468/dl.bc4w7h) and C. venustula (open cir-<lb/>cles, data from GBIF https://doi.org/10.15468/ <lb/>dl.npp4zj). The black star shows the location of <lb/>the collection site for this study. The distribu-<lb/>tion of the introduced ants, C. emeryi and B. <lb/>obscurior is in Supplementary Material 2. <lb/></body>

        <page>4 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M.S. Ascunce et al.: Ant community composition in a citrus grove in Florida <lb/></note>

        <body>of introduced and invasive ants in Florida. The erosion of <lb/>native ant diversity in this citrus grove may likely be the <lb/>result of &quot;invasional meltdown&quot;, which was defined as: &quot;the <lb/>process by which a group of [introduced] species facilitate <lb/>one another&apos;s invasion in various ways, increasing the <lb/>likelihood of survival and/or of ecological impact, and <lb/>possibly the magnitude of impact&quot; (Simberloff and Von Holle <lb/>1999, p 22). However, to test this hypothesis, long-term <lb/>studies are needed. In addition, management practices <lb/>directed to control the Asian citrus psyllid and other citrus <lb/>insect pests could also affect native ant diversity. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments: We thank the University of Florida, IFAS <lb/>Seed Grant on Interdisciplinary Research on Invasive Spe-<lb/>cies (IRIS) for initial funding of this project, Erica Goss <lb/>(University of Florida, Plant Pathology Department) for her <lb/>encouragement about the project and comments on early <lb/>versions of this manuscript, Rachel Atchison (USDA-ARS-<lb/>CMAVE) for help with taxonomic identification and Sara <lb/>Alvarez (Education and Volunteer Specialist for Manatee <lb/>County, Florida) who assisted with the ant collection. We <lb/>would like to thank two anonymous reviewers and the editor <lb/>for their valuable comments on this manuscript. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Research ethics: Not applicable. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Author contributions: The authors have accepted <lb/>responsibility for the entire content of this manuscript and <lb/>approved its submission. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests: The authors state no conflict of <lb/>interest. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Research funding: This research work was supported by <lb/>IFAS Seed Grant on Interdisciplinary Research on Invasive <lb/>Species (IRIS) and partial funding was obtained from USDA-<lb/>ARS-CMAVE-Fire Ant Unit based funds. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability: The raw data is provided in the manuscript. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Arnan, X., Andersen, A.N., Gibb, H., Parr, C.L., Sanders, N.J., Dunn, R.R., <lb/>Angulo, E., Baccaro, F.B., Bishop, T.R., Boulay, R., et al. (2018). <lb/>Dominance-diversity relationships in ant communities differ with <lb/>invasion. Glob. Change Biol. 24: 4614-4625. <lb/>Ascunce, M.S., Yang, C.-C., Oakey, J., Calcaterra, L., Wu, W.-J., Shih, C.-J., <lb/>Goudet, J., Ross, K.G., and Shoemaker, D. (2011). Global invasion <lb/>history of the fire ant Solenopsis invicta. Science 331: 1066-1068. <lb/>Bertelsmeier, C., Ollier, S., Liebhold, A., and Keller, L. (2017). Recent human <lb/>history governs global ant invasion dynamics. Nat. Ecol. Evol. 1: 0184. <lb/>Bertelsmeier, C., Ollier, S., Liebhold, A.M., Brockerhoff, E.G., Ward, D., and <lb/>Keller, L. (2018). Recurrent bridgehead effects accelerate global alien <lb/>ant spread. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 115: 5486-5491. <lb/>Blaustein, R.A., Lorca, G.L., and Teplitski, M. (2018). Challenges for <lb/>managing Candidatus Liberibacter spp. (Huanglongbing disease <lb/>pathogen): current control measures and future directions. <lb/>Phytopathology 108: 424-435. <lb/>Bové, J.M. (2006). Huanglongbing: a destructive, newly-emerging, century-<lb/>old disease of citrus. J. Plant Pathol. 88: 7-37. <lb/>Chong, J.-H., Roda, A.L., and Mannion, C.M. (2010). Density and natural <lb/>enemies of the Asian citrus psyllid, Diaphorina citri (Hemiptera: <lb/>Psyllidae), in the residential landscape of southern Florida. J. Agric. <lb/>Urban Entomol. 27: 33-49. <lb/>Deyrup, M. (2003). An updated list of Florida ants (Hymenoptera: <lb/>Formicidae). Fla. Entomol 86: 43-48. <lb/>Deyrup, M. (2016). Ants of Florida: identification and natural history. CRC <lb/>Press, Boca Raton, Florida, USA. <lb/>Deyrup, M., Davis, L., and Cover, S. (2000). Exotic ants in Florida. Trans. Am. <lb/>Entomol. Soc. 126: 293-326. <lb/>Elith, J. and Leathwick, J.R. (2009). Species distribution models: ecological <lb/>explanation and prediction across space and time. Annu. Rev. Ecol. Evol. <lb/>Syst. 40: 677-697. <lb/>Graham, J., Gottwald, T., and Setamou, M. (2020). Status of Huanglongbing <lb/>(HLB) outbreaks in Florida, California and Texas. Trop. Plant Pathol. 45: <lb/>265-278. <lb/>Halbert, S.E. (1998) Entomology section. In: Anderson, P.J., and Hodges, G.S. <lb/>(Eds.). Tri-ology, Vol. 37. Division of Plant Industry, Gainesville, Florida, <lb/>pp. 5-9. <lb/>Helms, K.R. and Vinson, S.B. (2001). Coexistence of native ants with the red <lb/>imported fire ant, Solenopsis invicta. Southwest. Nat 46: 396-400. <lb/>Holway, D.A., Lach, L., Suarez, A.V., Tsutsui, N.D., and Case, T.J. (2002). The <lb/>causes and consequences of ant invasions. Annu. Rev. Ecol. Systemat. <lb/>33: 181-233. <lb/>Hoy, M.A., Nguyen, R., and Jeyaprakash, A. (1999). Classical biological <lb/>control of Asian citrus psylla. Citrus Ind. 1: 20-22. <lb/>ISSG (Invasive Species Specialist Group) (2015). The global invasive species <lb/>database, Version 2015.1. Available at: http://iucngisd.org/gisd/ <lb/>search.php. [Accessed 2 July 2023]. <lb/>King, J.R. and Porter, S.D. (2007). Body size, colony size, abundance, and <lb/>ecological impact of exotic ants in Florida&apos;s upland ecosystems. Evol. <lb/>Ecol. Res. 9: 757-774. <lb/>King, J.R. and Tschinkel, W.R. (2007). Range expansion and local <lb/>population increase of the exotic ant, Pheidole obscurithorax, in <lb/>the southeastern United States (Hymenoptera: Formicidae). Fla. <lb/>Entomol. 90: 435-439. <lb/>Lach, L., Parr, C.L., and Abbott, K.L. (Eds.) (2010). Ant ecology. Oxford <lb/>University Press, New York, USA. <lb/>Laub, C., Youngman, R.R., Love, K., and Mize, T. (2009). Using pitfall traps to <lb/>monitor insect activity. Virginia Cooperative Extension Publication. <lb/>Virginia Cooperative Extension, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Virginia, <lb/>pp. 444-416. <lb/>LeBrun, E.G., Plowes, R.M., and Gilbert, L.E. (2012). Imported fire ants near <lb/>the edge of their range: disturbance and moisture determine <lb/>prevalence and impact of an invasive social insect: habitat determines <lb/>imported fire ant impacts. J. Anim. Ecol. 81: 884-895. <lb/>MacGown, J.A. (2022). Identification keys. ants (Formicidae) of the <lb/>southeastern United States. Uploaded on 6 March 2003, last updated on 7 <lb/>February 2022. Available at: https:// <lb/>mississippientomologicalmuseum.org.msstate.edu/ <lb/>Researchtaxapages/Formicidaepages/Identification.Keys.htm. <lb/>[Accessed 1 February 2019]. <lb/>Michaud, J.P. (2004). Natural mortality of Asian citrus psyllid (Homoptera: <lb/>Psyllidae) in central Florida. Biol. Control 29: 260-269. <lb/>Mooney, H.A. and Cleland, E.E. (2001). The evolutionary impact of invasive <lb/>species. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 98: 5446-5451. <lb/>Navarrete, B., McAuslane, H., Deyrup, M., and Peña, J.E. (2013). Ants <lb/>(Hymenoptera: Formicidae) associated with Diaphorina citri <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">M.S. Ascunce et al.: Ant community composition in a citrus grove in Florida <lb/></note>

        <page>5 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>(Hemiptera: Liviidae) and their role in its biological control. Fla. <lb/>Entomol. 96: 590-597. <lb/>Naves, M.A. (1985). A monograph of the genus Pheidole in Florida <lb/>(Hymenoptera: Formicidae). Insecta Mundi 1: 53-90. <lb/>Ohyama, L., King, J.R., and Gochnour, B.M. (2020). Changes in an invaded <lb/>Florida ant (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) community over 25 years. Fla. <lb/>Entomol. 103: 180-190. <lb/>Oliver, T.H., Jones, I.A.N., Cook, J.M., and Leather, S.R. (2008). Avoidance <lb/>responses of an aphidophagous ladybird, Adalia bipunctata, to aphid-<lb/>tending ants. Ecol. Entomol. 33: 523-528. <lb/>Passera, L. (1994) Characteristics of tramp species. In: Williams, D.F. (Ed.). <lb/>Exotic ants: biology, impact, and control of introduced species. Westview <lb/>Press, Boulder, Colorado, USA, pp. 23-43. <lb/>Qureshi, J.A., Rogers, M.E., Hall, D.G., and Stansly, P.A. (2009). Incidence of <lb/>invasive Diaphorina citri (Hemiptera: Psyllidae) and its introduced <lb/>parasitoid Tamarixia radiata (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae) in Florida <lb/>citrus. J. Econ. Entomol. 102: 247-256. <lb/>Seifert, B. (2002). The ant genus Cardiocondyla (Insecta: Hymenoptera: <lb/>Formicidae) -a taxonomic revision of the C. elegans, C. bulgarica, C. <lb/>batesii, C. nuda, C. shuckardi, C. stambuloffii, C. wroughtonii, C. emeryi, <lb/>and C. minutior species groups. Ann. Naturhist. Mus. Wien, B Bot. Zool. <lb/>104: 203-338. <lb/>Shrestha, B., Hoyte, A., and Stelinski, L.L. (2022). Ant-psyllid mutualism <lb/>affects predation of Diaphorina citri by lady beetle larvae and <lb/>abundance of psyllid natural enemies. BioControl 67: 407-417. <lb/>Simberloff, D. and Von Holle, B. (1999). Positive interactions of <lb/>nonindigenous species: invasional meltdown? Biol. Invasions 1: 21-32. <lb/>Singerman, A. and Rogers, M.E. (2020). The economic challenges of dealing <lb/>with citrus greening: the case of Florida. J. Integr. Pest Manag. 11: 3. <lb/>Starr, F., Starr, K., and Loope, L.L. (2007). Survey for little fire ant (Wasmannia <lb/>auropunctata) on the island of Maui, Hawaii. United States Fish and <lb/>Wildlife Service. Puunene, Hawaii, USA, pp. 35. <lb/>Storz, S.R. and Tschinkel, W.R. (2004). Distribution, spread, and ecological <lb/>associations of the introduced ant Pheidole obscurithorax in the <lb/>southeastern United States. J. Insect Sci. 4: 12. <lb/>Stuble, K.L., Kirkman, L.K., and Carroll, C.R. (2010). Are red imported fire <lb/>ants facilitators of native seed dispersal? Biol. Invasions 12: <lb/>1661-1669. <lb/>USDA-NASS (United Stated Department of Agriculture, National Agricultural <lb/>Statistics Service) (2022). United States Department of Agriculture. <lb/>2021-2022 citrus summary production, price and value production by <lb/>county and per tree. USDA, National Agricultural Statistics Service, <lb/>Washington D.C., pp. 1-25. <lb/>Vanek, S.J. and Potter, D.A. (2010). Ant-exclusion to promote biological <lb/>control of soft scales (Hemiptera: Coccidae) on woody landscape <lb/>plants. Environ. Entomol. 39: 1829-1837. <lb/>Wang, N., Pierson, E.A., Setubal, J.C., Xu, J., Levy, J.G., Zhang, Y., Li, J., Rangel, <lb/>L.T., and Martins, J. (2017). The Candidatus Liberibacter -host interface: <lb/>insights into pathogenesis mechanisms and disease control. Annu. <lb/>Rev. Phytopathol. 55: 451-482. <lb/>Wetterer, J.K., MacGown, J.A., and Calcaterra, L.A. (2015). Geographic spread <lb/>of Pheidole obscurithorax (Hymenoptera: Formicidae). Trans. Am. <lb/>Entomol. Soc. 141: 222-231. <lb/>Wilson, E.O. (2003). Pheidole in the New World: a dominant, hyperdiverse <lb/>ant genus, Vol. 1. Harvard University Press, Cambridge. <lb/>Wong, M.K., Economo, E.P., and Guénard, B. (2023). The global spread and <lb/>invasion capacities of alien ants. Curr. Biol. 33: 1-6. <lb/>Yoo, H.J.S., Kizner, M.C., and Holway, D.A. (2013). Ecological effects of multi-<lb/>species, ant-hemipteran mutualisms in citrus: ecological effects of a <lb/>multi-species mutualism. Ecol. Entomol. 38: 505-514. <lb/></listBibl>

        <div type="annex">Supplementary Material: This article contains supplementary material <lb/>(https://doi.org/10.1515/flaent-2024-0011). <lb/></div>

        <page>6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M.S. Ascunce et al.: Ant community composition in a citrus grove in Florida </note>


	</text>

</TEI>