<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Associations between adverse childhood experiences and trust in health and other information from public services, professionals and wider sources: national cross sectional survey</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Mark A</forename>
            <surname>Bellis</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Karen</forename>
            <surname>Hughes</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Kat</forename>
            <surname>Ford</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Catherine</forename>
            <surname>Sharp</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Rebecca</forename>
            <surname>Hill</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-29T10:54:31.312537Z">29.10.2025 10:54:31</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1136$1$bmjph-2023-000868</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>BMJ</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjph-2023-000868</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Mark A Bellis, Karen Hughes, Kat Ford, Catherine Sharp, Rebecca Hill. (2024). Associations between adverse childhood experiences and trust in health and other information from public services, professionals and wider sources: national cross sectional survey. BMJ Public Health, 2(1), e000868. DOI: 10.1136/bmjph-2023-000868</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T10:54:31.312537Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-29T10:54:31.312537Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>1 <lb/>Ferrari A, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e084034. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/>Open access <lb/>Determinants of women&apos;s preferences <lb/>for surgical versus conservative <lb/>management for pelvic organ prolapse: <lb/>a survey-based study from Italy <lb/>Amerigo Ferrari <lb/>, 1,2 Nicola Bellè, 1 Andrea Giannini, 2 Tommaso Simoncini, 2 <lb/>Milena Vainieri <lb/>1 <lb/>To cite: Ferrari A, Bellè N, <lb/>Giannini A, et al. Determinants <lb/>of women&apos;s preferences for <lb/>surgical versus conservative <lb/>management for pelvic organ <lb/>prolapse: a survey-based <lb/>study from Italy. BMJ Open <lb/>2024;14:e084034. doi:10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/>► Prepublication history <lb/>and additional supplemental <lb/>material for this paper are <lb/>available online. To view these <lb/>files, please visit the journal <lb/>online (https://doi.org/10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2024-084034). <lb/>Received 06 January 2024 <lb/>Accepted 05 July 2024 <lb/>1 <lb/>Institute of Management, MeS <lb/>(Management and Health) <lb/>Laboratory, Scuola Superiore <lb/>Sant&apos;Anna, Pisa, Italy <lb/>2 <lb/>Department of Clinical and <lb/>Experimental Medicine, Division <lb/>of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, <lb/>University of Pisa, Pisa, Italy <lb/>Correspondence to <lb/>Dr Amerigo Ferrari; <lb/>amerigo. ferrari@ santannapisa. it <lb/>Original research <lb/>© Author(s) (or their <lb/>employer(s)) 2024. Re-use <lb/>permitted under CC BY-NC. No <lb/>commercial re-use. See rights <lb/>and permissions. Published by <lb/>BMJ. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Background and objective Pelvic organ prolapse (POP) <lb/>affects 40% of women, with a 12%-19% lifetime surgical <lb/>risk. Italy showed high practice variation in POP surgery, <lb/>possibly impacting equity of access to healthcare services, <lb/>a central goal of Beveridge-like health systems. According <lb/>to the literature, unwarranted variation, influenced by <lb/>physician attitudes or resource allocation, must be <lb/>reduced. We aimed to identify determinants influencing <lb/>women&apos;s choice when asked whether they prefer surgical <lb/>or conservative POP management. <lb/>Design, setting and population In this nationwide <lb/>prospective study, we distributed a Qualtrics questionnaire <lb/>via social media to any Italian women over 18 years old <lb/>who voluntarily decided to participate in the survey. <lb/>Intervention A grade 3 POP scenario was presented. <lb/>Women were asked how likely they would have surgery. <lb/>Each woman randomly received only 1 question out of <lb/>11: 1 question was the reference question (&apos;How likely <lb/>would you have surgery?&apos;) while 10 questions contained <lb/>a potential determinant influencing woman&apos;s choice (&apos;How <lb/>likely would you have surgery if…?&apos;). <lb/>Outcome The outcome was the chance of choosing <lb/>surgery expressed as a percentage. We analysed the effect <lb/>of each factor on the outcome by using adjusted beta <lb/>regression models. <lb/>Results Respondents (n=222) opted for surgery with <lb/>a median probability of 61.5%. Factors significantly <lb/>increasing the chance of choosing surgery were advice <lb/>from physicians, the presence of a trusted physician <lb/>during hospitalisation, surgical approach with low <lb/>complication rates, uterine-sparing surgery, the absence of <lb/>postoperative abdominal scars and nearby hospital. <lb/>Conclusions Our findings provide health managers and <lb/>policy-makers with new evidence to better understand <lb/>women&apos;s decision-making and partly capture the <lb/>determinants of unwarranted variation. These inputs may <lb/>also be used as attributes for a future discrete choice <lb/>experiment. <lb/></front>

    <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Pelvic floor dysfunctions are very common <lb/>among elderly women, with a continuously <lb/>increasing incidence related to the growing <lb/>life expectancy. These conditions deteriorate <lb/>from the menopause due to the related endo-<lb/>crine modifications and the ageing process, <lb/>leading to negative consequences on quality <lb/>of life, daily functionality and social interac-<lb/>tions. Pelvic organ prolapse (POP), defined <lb/>as the downward descent of pelvic organs <lb/>towards the vagina, affects up to 40% of <lb/>women, with a 12%-19% lifetime surgical <lb/>risk. 1 2 POP is not a life-threatening disease <lb/>but has no self-limited course, so often the <lb/>decision for surgery depends on women&apos;s <lb/>choices, preferences, needs and symptoms. 3 4 <lb/>Conservative management strategies for <lb/>POP offer non-surgical alternatives aimed <lb/>at alleviating symptoms and enhancing the <lb/>well-being of affected individuals. These <lb/>approaches include the use of pessaries to <lb/></body>
    
    <front>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY <lb/>⇒ This study explores women&apos;s preferences in pelvic <lb/>organ prolapse (POP) management in Italy by using <lb/>data from an online survey developed with expert <lb/>physicians, validated through a convenient pilot <lb/>sample and administered to the general population <lb/>of women. <lb/>⇒ The findings of this study rely on a strong method-<lb/>ology, based on a randomisation technique for the <lb/>initial question that allowed for providing a founda-<lb/>tion for drawing hypotheses and potential testing <lb/>through subsequent survey studies. <lb/>⇒ Results rely on strong statistical methods such as <lb/>adjusted regression models and multiple imputation <lb/>tools. <lb/>⇒ However, the study is prone to a self-selection bias <lb/>since women voluntarily joined the survey, thus re-<lb/>sulting in participants who were younger, more ed-<lb/>ucated and of higher socioeconomic status than the <lb/>typical POP-affected population. <lb/>⇒ Finally, there might have been additional factors po-<lb/>tentially influencing the women&apos;s choice for surgery <lb/>that we have not considered, such as the impact <lb/>on sexual function or the role of minimally invasive <lb/>surgery. <lb/></front>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>24 July 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

    <page>2 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Ferrari A, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e084034. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>support the prolapsed organs, lifestyle modifications such <lb/>as weight management and dietary adjustments, patient <lb/>education and support groups. 5 Despite the benefits <lb/>of conservative treatment, 30% of women will undergo <lb/>surgery within 1-2 years. 6 On the other hand, POP <lb/>surgery consists of various surgical procedures designed <lb/>to anatomically repair and restore pelvic organ support, <lb/>thus providing long-term relief from POP-related symp-<lb/>toms and renewing the structural integrity of the pelvic <lb/>floor. 7 <lb/>POP surgery is one of the most frequent elective <lb/>surgical procedures in Western Countries: in the UK, 20% <lb/>of women on the waiting lists for major gynaecological <lb/>surgery suffer from POP. 8 POP surgery is subject to prac-<lb/>tise variation since there are no clear and uniform indica-<lb/>tions for surgical treatment. In fact, a survey-based study <lb/>on members of the International Urogynecological Asso-<lb/>ciation showed that much of the practice patterns in the <lb/>treatment of POP depended on academic affiliation and <lb/>geographic location. 9 In addition, the spread of new tech-<lb/>nologies-such as robotic surgery-may exacerbate prac-<lb/>tice variation, as it may precede a robust cost-effectiveness <lb/>evaluation, thus providing surgical options that are not <lb/>consistently embraced by physicians. 10 As a matter of <lb/>fact, high regional variation in POP surgical practice has <lb/>been documented in Tuscany, Italy (figure 1). However, <lb/>between-hospital differences could explain only part of <lb/>such variation. 11 <lb/>According to JE Wennberg, variation in elective <lb/>surgery is mainly due to supply-sensitive factors (use <lb/>influenced by the resource allocation) and preference-<lb/>sensitive factors (choice determined by patient&apos;s and/ <lb/>or physician&apos;s preferences). 12 Variation is considered as <lb/>unwarranted when it is not justified by real differences <lb/>in patients&apos; needs, but rather by physicians&apos; attitudes <lb/>and prescribing behaviour or different resource allo-<lb/>cation. Unwarranted variation should be reduced, as it <lb/>conflicts with the increasingly emerging patient-centred <lb/>medical approach and the three pillars of public health <lb/>systems pursuing universal coverage: quality, equity and <lb/>sustainability. 13 <lb/>However, to define variation as unwarranted, a more <lb/>comprehensive understanding of women&apos;s decision-<lb/>making process is needed. 12 Since very little evidence <lb/>is available from the literature about this topic, in this <lb/>article, we aimed to explore the main determinants <lb/>of practice variation at the woman&apos;s level when asked <lb/>whether she potentially prefers surgical or conservative <lb/>management of POP. This may help policy-makers, health <lb/>managers and researchers intercept patients&apos; opinions, <lb/>choices and preferences, thereby providing new insights <lb/>into the potential causes of unwarranted variation and <lb/>guiding resource allocation to align health goals with <lb/>women&apos;s needs. 14 <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Study design and setting <lb/>This was a survey-based prospective study which was <lb/>carried out in Italy. The Italian National Health Service <lb/>represents a Beveridge-style healthcare framework char-<lb/>acterised by the provision of comprehensive and cost-free <lb/>healthcare coverage to all citizens. This system adheres <lb/>to a decentralised paradigm, whereby the central govern-<lb/>ment assumes responsibility for establishing overarching <lb/>financial prerequisites and objectives, as well as guaran-<lb/>teeing the equitable distribution of healthcare services <lb/>throughout the nation. In contrast, individual regions are <lb/>entrusted with the organisation and delivery of healthcare <lb/>services within their respective jurisdictions, enjoying a <lb/>substantial degree of administrative, political, legislative <lb/>and fiscal self-governance. <lb/>Figure 1 Variation in POP treatment rates across the 26 health districts of the Tuscany Region, Italy, with a 5.4-fold difference <lb/>between the health districts with highest and the lowest treatment rates (Ferrari et al 32 ). POP, pelvic organ prolapse. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>24 July 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

    <page>3 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Ferrari A, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e084034. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>Participants and data source <lb/>In this survey-based prospective study, we implemented <lb/>an online questionnaire using the Qualtrics Survey Tool <lb/>(Qualtrics, Provo, Utah, USA). Participants from the <lb/>general population were invited via social media with an <lb/>electronic link to access the online survey. The link was <lb/>disseminated through social channels and participants <lb/>were kindly asked to forward the link in turn. Embedded <lb/>in the link was a message explicitly stating that the ques-<lb/>tionnaire addressed any woman over 18 years old. By <lb/>clicking the link, participants accessed the first page <lb/>that described the purpose of the study, disclosed the <lb/>authors&apos; affiliation and informed women of the complete <lb/>anonymity of the data collected and the possibility of not <lb/>answering questions and dropping out of the survey at any <lb/>time. By clicking the &apos;forward&apos; button, women provided <lb/>their implicit consent to participate. At the end of the <lb/>survey, a link to a Google Forms survey was provided to <lb/>collect the email address to which the participant could <lb/>be recontacted, without the email address being associ-<lb/>ated with the Qualtrics survey response. <lb/>We intentionally chose to enrol women from the <lb/>general population rather than women at higher risk <lb/>of or suffering from POP. This decision allowed us to <lb/>identify factors influencing women&apos;s choices at an early <lb/>stage of the decision-making process before the disease <lb/>manifested leading to medical consultation. By that time, <lb/>a doctor might have already provided some input or <lb/>guidance that could have somehow biased the decision-<lb/>making process. As our specific research objective was to <lb/>explore how determinants influencing women&apos;s choices <lb/>affected practice variations, we necessarily had to select <lb/>this study population to answer our research question. <lb/>The questionnaire <lb/>The questionnaire presented women with a clinical <lb/>scenario of grade 3 POP (with uterus protruding out of <lb/>the vagina). The two therapeutic alternatives (surgery <lb/>or conservative management) were offered. Also, their <lb/>advantages and disadvantages were detailed, for instance, <lb/>the questionnaire explained how conservative manage-<lb/>ment allows for symptom alleviation or resolution in a <lb/>good percentage of cases, but-unlike surgery-cannot <lb/>guarantee correction of the anatomical defect. Women <lb/>were then asked how likely from 1 to 99 they would decide <lb/>to undergo surgery. Each woman received only 1 question <lb/>out of 11 in a randomised manner and then received the <lb/>other 10 questions without randomisation on a different <lb/>webpage. Out of the 11 questions, 1 was the reference <lb/>question containing no additional factors (&apos;How likely <lb/>would you choose surgery?&apos;) while the other 10 ques-<lb/>tions contained a factor possibly influencing the woman&apos;s <lb/>choice for surgery (&apos;How likely would you choose surgery <lb/>if…?&apos;). We also included as a control question &apos;Would <lb/>you use epidural analgesia during childbirth?&apos; to assess <lb/>survey&apos;s reliability (online supplemental table S1). <lb/>The 10 factors were advice from the gynaecologist, <lb/>advice from the general practitioner (GP), advice from two <lb/>physicians, presence of the trusted gynaecologist during <lb/>hospitalisation, advice from friends or relatives, short <lb/>postoperative recovery time, low risk of complications, <lb/>uterine-sparing surgery, no abdominal scarring and short <lb/>travel times. The first question was always randomised to <lb/>avoid response bias, related to the inevitable influence <lb/>of the answer to the first question on the answer to the <lb/>following questions. However, women further received <lb/>the other 10 questions in a non-randomised manner. At <lb/>the end of the questionnaire, sociodemographic data of <lb/>women were also collected. <lb/>The survey content (eg, specification of the clinical <lb/>scenario, factors or determinants of choice, description of <lb/>the two treatment alternatives) was developed through an <lb/>extensive literature review which was performed through <lb/>computerised databases including PubMed, Embase, <lb/>Google Scholar and the Cochrane Library. However, <lb/>there was very little, evidence on this specific topic, so <lb/>we had to draw this information from previous articles <lb/>addressing different clinical scenarios, diseases or treat-<lb/>ments. To consolidate our choices, we further carried out <lb/>a focus group with a team of gynaecologists from the Divi-<lb/>sion of Obstetrics and Gynaecology at the University of <lb/>Pisa, a leading centre in Italy for pelvic floor surgery. The <lb/>focus group was conducted in the presence of five gynae-<lb/>cologists by two authors who acted as moderator and assis-<lb/>tant moderator. For the focus group, researchers created <lb/>a script with the topics to be addressed and the questions <lb/>to be asked. Following this script, the moderator asked <lb/>the gynaecologists to comment on the survey content and <lb/>all the factors that had been selected, choosing the most <lb/>relevant ones and discarding the less important ones. We <lb/>also asked them if any descriptive detail or additional <lb/>factors to be considered had been left out. The interviews <lb/>were recorded, and the focus group data were analysed <lb/>with content analysis. <lb/>Before disseminating the study, we sent via Google <lb/>Form a preview of the questionnaire to a convenient <lb/>sample of 33 women to validate it by determining whether <lb/>the questionnaire was simple and easily understandable <lb/>on a 1-5 scale. 97% of the women responded that the <lb/>questionnaire was either well understandable (4 out of <lb/>5) or totally understandable (5 out of 5). We also asked <lb/>women to indicate the most difficult parts of the text <lb/>to be interpreted. Finally, we asked them whether they <lb/>thought any of the determinants of choice we proposed <lb/>were unnecessary, and whether they would propose other <lb/>factors or determinants of choice that we had not consid-<lb/>ered. For instance, the factor &apos;advice from two physicians&apos; <lb/>was added following women&apos;s advice. <lb/>Outcome and statistical analyses <lb/>The outcome of our study was the response to the <lb/>first randomised question, which was expressed as a <lb/>percentage from 1% to 99% (converted to a 0.01-0.99 <lb/>scale). To explore the effect of each factor on the proba-<lb/>bility of choosing surgery compared with the situation in <lb/>which woman receive no additional input, we modelled <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>24 July 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

    <page>4 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Ferrari A, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e084034. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>unadjusted and adjusted beta regression models. We <lb/>used the probability of choice as the dependent variable, <lb/>and the first randomised factor as the main independent <lb/>variable. <lb/>Adjustment was performed using all the available <lb/>sociodemographic data, and missing data were handled <lb/>through chained equation multiple imputation, gener-<lb/>ating 10 imputed data sets (see table 1 and online supple-<lb/>mental table S2 for further information). As a subanalysis <lb/>of the study, we also ran multilevel beta regression models <lb/>for repeated measures to investigate the effect of each <lb/>factor on the probability of choice within each single <lb/>respondent, using the woman&apos;s anonymous identifier <lb/>as the higher-level grouping variable. Statistical analyses <lb/>were carried out on Stata Software V.17.0 (StataCorp). <lb/>Statistical significance was set at a p&lt;0.05. <lb/>Patient and public involvement <lb/>As described above, the public was involved in the pilot <lb/>phase of the study (convenient sample). The pilot phase <lb/>served (1) to check the clarity of the text (particularly, <lb/>of the clinical scenario and treatment options); (2) to <lb/>modify the text according to the women&apos;s suggestions <lb/>and (3) to confirm the determinants of choice selected <lb/>through literature review and expert focus group and <lb/>possibly suggest additional factors to be considered. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Characteristics of respondents <lb/>As shown in table 1, we obtained 222 participants, with a <lb/>response rate of 89% (250 women opened the link). The <lb/>region of residence of our respondents is shown in online <lb/>supplemental table S3. The median age of our study popu-<lb/>lation was 44.5 years, and the median perceived health <lb/>status was 4.0 (out of 5.0). More than half of women <lb/>had a university degree and were employed. About 36% <lb/>of women had no children while 64% had at least one <lb/>child, and 80% of women lived with a partner. Half of our <lb/>respondents reported that they did physical activity only <lb/>occasionally and that they could receive excellent family <lb/>support when needed. Around 70% of women had no <lb/>chronic comorbidities. Finally, 85%-90% of respondents <lb/>were aware of urinary incontinence and POP despite not <lb/>suffering from it. <lb/>As shown in table 2, each of the 11 questions appeared <lb/>as the first randomised factor for about 8%-10% of the <lb/>women. In the overall population (n=222), the median <lb/>probability of choosing surgical treatment was 61.5%, <lb/>regardless of which of the 11 questions was asked first. <lb/>However, women who had received the reference ques-<lb/>tion without any factor (n=20) responded that they would <lb/>have surgery with a median probability of 39% (online <lb/>supplemental figure S1). This percentage rose to about <lb/>80% when women received, as input, advice for surgery <lb/>from two physicians (n=18) or the presence of a referral <lb/>hospital for POP surgery within a 20 min drive (n=17). A <lb/>slightly lower probability (70%-75%) of choosing surgery <lb/>Table 1 Baseline characteristics of respondents (n=222) <lb/>Age, median (IQR) <lb/>44.5 (31.0-55.0) <lb/>Perceived health status, median <lb/>(IQR) <lb/>4.0 (4.0-4.0) <lb/>Education level, n (%) <lb/>Elementary/middle school <lb/>7 (3.3) <lb/>High school <lb/>86 (41.1) <lb/>University <lb/>116 (55.5) <lb/>Work condition, n (%) <lb/>Employed <lb/>117 (56.3) <lb/>Unemployed <lb/>22 (10.6) <lb/>Student <lb/>9 (4.3) <lb/>Health worker <lb/>60 (28.8) <lb/>Children, n (%) <lb/>No one <lb/>76 (36.4) <lb/>Just one <lb/>76 (36.4) <lb/>Two or more <lb/>57 (27.3) <lb/>Physical activity, n (%) <lb/>Never <lb/>33 (15.9) <lb/>Sometimes <lb/>111 (53.4) <lb/>Often <lb/>64 (30.8) <lb/>Civil status, n (%) <lb/>With partner <lb/>172 (82.7) <lb/>Without partner <lb/>36 (17.3) <lb/>Assumed family support, n (%) <lb/>Excellent <lb/>113 (54.1) <lb/>Good <lb/>76 (36.4) <lb/>Poor <lb/>20 (9.6) <lb/>Chronic diseases, n (%) <lb/>No one <lb/>148 (70.8) <lb/>Just one <lb/>50 (23.9) <lb/>Two or more <lb/>11 (5.3) <lb/>Urinary incontinence knowledge, <lb/>n (%) <lb/>No <lb/>5 (2.4) <lb/>Yes <lb/>190 (90.9) <lb/>Yes: affected <lb/>14 (6.7) <lb/>Pelvic organ prolapse knowledge, <lb/>n (%) <lb/>No <lb/>21 (10.0) <lb/>Yes <lb/>179 (85.6) <lb/>Yes: affected <lb/>9 (4.3) <lb/>Missing data were handled by using chained equation multiple <lb/>imputation, generating 10 imputed data sets. Multiple imputation <lb/>is an iterative form of stochastic imputation that-instead of filling <lb/>in a single value-uses the distribution of the observed data to <lb/>estimate multiple values that reflect the uncertainty around the true <lb/>(missing) value. We included in the multiple imputation model the <lb/>dependent and independent variables of the regression models, <lb/>and all women&apos;s sociodemographic data. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>24 July 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

    <page>5 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Ferrari A, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e084034. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>was observed in women who were told that the interven-<lb/>tion was recommended by their gynaecologist (n=18) and <lb/>that the surgery ensured the lowest possible complication <lb/>rates (n=23). <lb/>Women who answered the control question (n=203) <lb/>stating that they would choose to use epidural analgesia <lb/>during childbirth numbered 71 (32.0%), consistently with <lb/>data provided by the 2022 regional reports of Tuscany <lb/>(31.3%) and Emilia-Romagna (31.4%). 15 16 <lb/>Primary outcome <lb/>Both unadjusted and adjusted beta regression models <lb/>(figure 2, online supplemental figure S2 and table S4) <lb/>revealed that compared with the reference question in <lb/>which women were given no further indication than <lb/>those described in the scenario, all factors-except <lb/>&apos;advice from friends or relatives&apos; and &apos;short postoperative <lb/>recovery time&apos;-significantly increased the likelihood of <lb/>choosing surgical treatment. In the adjusted model, the <lb/>highest OR (&gt;3.0) was observed for the following factors: <lb/>&apos;surgery with the lowest possible complication rate&apos; and <lb/>&apos;uterine-sparing surgery&apos;. Furthermore, the OR was <lb/>significant also for the factors &apos;presence of the trusted <lb/>physician during hospitalisation for surgery&apos;, &apos;advice from <lb/>gynaecologist&apos;, &apos;advice from two physicians&apos; and &apos;absence <lb/>of postoperative abdominal scars&apos;. Finally, the factors <lb/>&apos;advice from general practitioner&apos; and &apos;nearby referral <lb/>hospital&apos;, although significant, had the lowest effect. <lb/>Subanalysis <lb/>Multilevel models for repeated measures (online supple-<lb/>mental figure S3) showed that, within the same subject, <lb/>the factors that most increased the likelihood of choosing <lb/>surgery were &apos;advice from gynaecologist/two physicians&apos;, <lb/>&apos;presence of trusted physician during hospitalisation&apos;, <lb/>&apos;lowest possible complication rate&apos; and &apos;uterine-sparing <lb/>surgery&apos;. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Main findings <lb/>In this study, we presented a clinical scenario of grade <lb/>3 POP to women from the general population, with two <lb/>different treatment alternatives (surgery or conservative <lb/>management), and we asked them to express by what <lb/>percentage they would decide to undergo surgery. We <lb/>documented that the median probability of choosing <lb/>surgery in our study population (n=222) was 61.5%. <lb/>However, when receiving no further input than those <lb/>given in the clinical scenario, women decided to have <lb/>surgery with a 39% median probability. This percentage <lb/>increased to ≈80% when the woman received specific <lb/>inputs, such as the advice from two physicians and the <lb/>presence of a nearby referral hospital. Previous clinical <lb/>studies showed that the choice rate for POP surgery <lb/>versus conservative management was slightly lower than <lb/>in our study (from 33% to 44%) 17 18 while a survey-based <lb/>study reported a choice rate of 48%. 19 Also, women who <lb/>had a heavier symptom burden were found to be more <lb/>likely to opt for surgery. 20 <lb/>Regression models showed that, compared with the <lb/>situation in which the woman received no input, all the <lb/>Table 2 All randomised factors and median probability of <lb/>choosing surgery for each factor <lb/>Randomised factor N (%) <lb/>Response to the first <lb/>answer, median (IQR) <lb/>Any factor (all <lb/>respondents) <lb/>222 (100) <lb/>61.5 (42.0-84.0) <lb/>Reference <lb/>20 (9.0) <lb/>39.0 (6.5-69.0) <lb/>Gynaecologist&apos;s <lb/>advice <lb/>18 (8.1) <lb/>75.5 (60.0-90.0) <lb/>General practitioner&apos;s <lb/>advice <lb/>20 (9.0) <lb/>60.0 (49.5-82.0) <lb/>Two physicians&apos; <lb/>advice <lb/>18 (8.1) <lb/>79.5 (61.0-84.0) <lb/>Trusted physician&apos;s <lb/>presence <lb/>20 (9.0) <lb/>61.0 (50.0-75.5) <lb/>Friends/relatives&apos; <lb/>advice <lb/>23 (10.4) <lb/>50.0 (28.0-52.0) <lb/>Short postsurgical <lb/>recovery <lb/>23 (10.4) <lb/>61.0 (30.0-80.0) <lb/>Low complication <lb/>rates <lb/>23 (10.4) <lb/>71.0 (60.0-90.0) <lb/>Uterine sparing <lb/>surgery <lb/>23 (10.4) <lb/>62.0 (28.0-100.0) <lb/>No abdominal scars <lb/>17 (7.7) <lb/>65.0 (51.0-84.0) <lb/>Nearby hospital <lb/>17 (7.7) <lb/>80.0 (50.0-97.0) <lb/>Figure 2 Adjusted beta regression model for the primary <lb/>outcome. The coefficients of the model are expressed in <lb/>exponential form as ORs (and 95% CI). Please, see online <lb/>supplemental table S4 for non-exponential coefficients. GP, <lb/>general practitioner. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>24 July 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

    <page>6 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Ferrari A, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e084034. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

    <body>factors or determinants of choice considered (except <lb/>two) resulted in a significant increase in the probability <lb/>of choosing surgery. By far, the strongest effect, both in <lb/>the overall population and within the same respondent, <lb/>was observed for the following four factors: &apos;advice from <lb/>gynaecologist&apos;, &apos;presence of trusted physician during <lb/>hospitalisation&apos;, &apos;surgery with lowest possible complica-<lb/>tion rate&apos; and &apos;uterine-sparing surgery&apos;. <lb/>Although there is little evidence from the litera-<lb/>ture on the same topic, our findings are consistent <lb/>with previous articles that have explored the deter-<lb/>minants influencing women&apos;s preferences towards <lb/>specific treatment options for gynaecological diseases. <lb/>First, we showed that the role of the gynaecologist is <lb/>crucial in guiding women&apos;s decision-making. Similarly, <lb/>Lyatoshinskaya et al reported that women from Vienna <lb/>and Moscow would prefer to obtain information about <lb/>POP from medical specialists. 21 Also, women choosing <lb/>between levonorgestrel intrauterine system and endo-<lb/>metrial ablation for heavy menstrual bleeding preferred <lb/>to be treated by a gynaecologist rather than the GP. 22 <lb/>Finally, Janda et al found that gynaecologists were the <lb/>most influential source for women seeking information <lb/>about hysterectomy. 23 <lb/>In line with our findings, uterus preservation has been <lb/>reported to be a key determinant influencing women&apos;s <lb/>choices, but its influence depends greatly on how the <lb/>anatomic success rate is communicated compared <lb/>with hysterectomy-based surgery. 24 For instance, van <lb/>IJsselmuiden et al found that Dutch women were more <lb/>likely in favour of uterus preservation over hysterec-<lb/>tomy when assuming similar functional and anatomical <lb/>outcomes for both procedures. 25 Differently, a survey-<lb/>based study by Urdzík et al showed that female gynaecol-<lb/>ogists from Czech Republic, Slovenia and Slovakia, would <lb/>opt for hysterectomy as a treatment option when they <lb/>were told that hysterectomy provided more satisfactory <lb/>anatomical outcomes. 26 <lb/>We also found that surgery with a low risk of postop-<lb/>erative complications may drive women&apos;s choice. This <lb/>finding is coherent with previous articles, which however <lb/>explored patient&apos;s preferences between two different <lb/>surgical techniques for POP rather than between surgical <lb/>and conservative management. 27 Consistently, for women <lb/>seeking treatment for symptomatic uterine fibroids, <lb/>repeat treatment and complications were found to be the <lb/>leading factors in fostering surgical treatment options. 28 <lb/>We also showed that other factors such as the absence <lb/>of postsurgical abdominal scars may increase the chance <lb/>of choosing surgery. Similarly, a previous study showed <lb/>that women would favour the laparoscopic approach <lb/>for POP surgery due to the cosmetic appearance of the <lb/>skin incision. 29 The evidence that a favourable cosmetic <lb/>outcome can influence women&apos;s choices may foster, in <lb/>the future, a wider diffusion of surgical techniques such <lb/>as transvaginal natural orifice transluminal endoscopic <lb/>surgery, which provide both anatomically and cosmeti-<lb/>cally satisfactory outcomes. 30 <lb/>As for travel times, there is a large body of previous <lb/>literature demonstrating the influence of travel distances <lb/>on the likelihood of receiving treatment. 31 32 Similarly, we <lb/>found that women, when told that a referral hospital for <lb/>POP surgery was within a maximum of a 20 min car ride <lb/>away, were more likely to choose surgery. <lb/>Limitations and strengths <lb/>This study presents some limitations. First, the study <lb/>sample was selected from the general population using <lb/>a link forwarded via social media, so the recruitment of <lb/>participants was subject to a self-selection bias, whereby <lb/>women who decided to participate had a lower average <lb/>age than women who normally suffer from POP and <lb/>had a higher educational level and socioeconomic status <lb/>than the general population. Thus, our sample was not <lb/>representative of the general population. In addition, the <lb/>study was only in Italian so it was not possible to recruit <lb/>women who were not proficient in the language. Also, <lb/>we did not quantitatively investigate the readability of <lb/>the text, 33 but only asked qualitatively whether the clin-<lb/>ical scenario was easily understandable, so some women <lb/>may have responded without fully grasping the content <lb/>of the study. Furthermore, there was no clear distinction <lb/>between reconstructive and obliterative surgery among <lb/>the determinants of choice, although there was a specific <lb/>question about vaginal versus abdominal surgery. Finally, <lb/>there may be additional determinants influencing the <lb/>choice of the individual women that we have not consid-<lb/>ered, such as the impact on sexual function or the role of <lb/>minimally invasive surgery. <lb/>However, despite its limitations, this study has multiple <lb/>strengths. First, to the best of our knowledge, it was the <lb/>first study to investigate women&apos;s preferences for POP <lb/>management while also trying to identify the factors that <lb/>most influenced such preferences. These factors can thus <lb/>be used for further investigations, for example, as attri-<lb/>butes for a future discrete choice experiment (DCE). <lb/>While the choice to include women from the general <lb/>population instead of women at higher risk of or suffering <lb/>from POP might seem to be a limitation of this study, it <lb/>is instead justified by the rationale of our study. In fact, <lb/>this allowed us to identify the determinants influencing <lb/>women&apos;s choices at an early stage before the condition <lb/>occurred and the women had visited a health professional. <lb/>By that time, the woman may have already received input <lb/>that in some way may influence her choice of treatment. <lb/>Since our main purpose was to investigate the effect of <lb/>determinants influencing women&apos;s choice on practice <lb/>variation, we inevitably had to choose this type of popula-<lb/>tion to answer the research question. Moreover, the study <lb/>applied a robust methodology related to the randomisa-<lb/>tion of the first question (and the first factor) that allowed <lb/>us to draw hypotheses on women preferences that could <lb/>be tested through other survey studies. Finally, it was the <lb/>first study to suggest a link between unwarranted prac-<lb/>tice variation in POP surgery and some determinants of <lb/>choice at the individual level. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>24 July 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

    <page>7 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Ferrari A, et al. BMJ Open doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>Implications <lb/>This study provides implications at different levels. <lb/>At the clinical level, the results from this study suggest <lb/>that variation in POP surgery is strictly related to the <lb/>physician advice. We found that less than half of women <lb/>(around 40%) would choose to have surgery if no addi-<lb/>tional prompting or advice was provided. This percentage <lb/>doubles (OR around 2.9-3.0) when external factors that <lb/>influence a woman&apos;s choice intervene. <lb/>This increase hinges on two core components related <lb/>to the clinical dimension: the advice from gynaecologists <lb/>and a proper information on clinical outcomes (compli-<lb/>cations, uterine sparing and abdominal scars). Thus, <lb/>the influence of physicians&apos; attitudes and prescriptive <lb/>behaviours, which are highly dependent on the surgical <lb/>training and the affiliation, may have a great influence on <lb/>women&apos;s choice and, ultimately, on variation in treatment <lb/>rates. For example, an excessive tendency to recommend <lb/>surgery even when unnecessary could lead to unwar-<lb/>ranted variation in terms of overuse. Hence, the need to <lb/>establish more uniform international and national guide-<lb/>lines and recommendations, and to standardise care <lb/>across different providers by developing defined care <lb/>pathways. 34 <lb/>From an organisational point of view, our study <lb/>revealed that, when women are aware of beneficial clin-<lb/>ical outcomes (low complication rates, uterine-sparing <lb/>surgery, favourable cosmetic outcomes), they are more <lb/>likely to choose surgery. Therefore, to avoid non-justified <lb/>underuse of surgery, a robust doctor-patient communica-<lb/>tion and a well-informed shared decision-making (SDM) <lb/>process should be fostered. As a result, women would be <lb/>equipped with comprehensive information about the <lb/>spectrum of available treatment options to make choices <lb/>aligned with their preferences and needs. <lb/>Indeed, previous literature has shown the positive <lb/>effect of SDM, defined as the process of interacting with <lb/>patients to reach informed and value-based choices, in <lb/>reducing practice variations, improving the quality of <lb/>decisions and preventing treatment overuse that patients <lb/>may not welcome. 35 36 Some authors have suggested that a <lb/>tipping point is needed to truly put patients at the centre <lb/>of healthcare as the norm of medical practice, although <lb/>some issues remain unresolved, with a perception-reality <lb/>gap. 37 For example, SDM is a process that applies more <lb/>to women with higher socioeconomic status, coming <lb/>from high-income countries and having higher levels of <lb/>literacy. <lb/>Also, SDM could be a process involving not only the <lb/>doctor-patient relationship, but also family members, <lb/>friends and social context. 38 This is why, for instance, some <lb/>authors might have not observed a significant decrease in <lb/>the level of decision conflict with the addition of a deci-<lb/>sion aid to standard counselling for the management <lb/>of POP. 39 In any case, empirical studies have shown that <lb/>decision aid, active support from nurses and the offer of <lb/>reimbursement could both reduce unwarranted variation <lb/>between hospitals and change variation patterns within <lb/>hospitals, 37 40 contributing to the &apos;physiological&apos; variation <lb/>rate that depends on patient preferences and should be <lb/>valued. This has also recently been described for female <lb/>pelvic floor reconstructive medicine and surgery. 41 <lb/>At the policy level, significant factor influencing <lb/>women&apos;s decisions regarding POP management is the <lb/>proximity of a referral hospital. Travel times play a pivotal <lb/>role, as women are more inclined to opt for surgery when <lb/>such facilities are within a short car ride. In other words, <lb/>the closer the hospital, the higher the probability of <lb/>choosing POP surgery by women. This shows that even <lb/>this surgical intervention is sensitive to the supply, thus <lb/>highlighting the critical role of healthcare infrastruc-<lb/>ture and accessibility in shaping patient choices to avoid <lb/>underuse of surgery. Policy-makers should consider this <lb/>evidence when designing healthcare services and facilities. <lb/>It should be valued if and why these women are forgoing <lb/>the surgery. If it is for a settlement reason, other solutions <lb/>have to be found in order to reduce the dreadful trade-off <lb/>between access to care and financial sustainability. <lb/>Finally, at the academic level, this study paves the <lb/>way for future investigations into patient preferences <lb/>and decision-making processes. Findings of this paper <lb/>provided essential preliminary knowledge to accurately <lb/>specify the factors required for further advanced statistical <lb/>analyses. For instance, the attributes analysed in this study <lb/>may be used to design DCEs which are quasi-experimental <lb/>survey acknowledged for their ability to elicit preferences <lb/>and choices among alternative scenarios, making them a <lb/>powerful tool in various fields. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In summary, this work provided valuable insights into the <lb/>determinants influencing the individual women&apos;s choice <lb/>for surgical management of POP. If a woman who receives <lb/>no input would have surgery in 40% of cases, but when <lb/>receiving specific inputs (such as the determinants of <lb/>choice analysed in this article) she would have surgery <lb/>in 80% of cases, then this difference could explain some <lb/>of the observed variation. The potential causes of such <lb/>a variation have been explored at the user level, and <lb/>they emerged to be mainly related to physicians&apos; advice, <lb/>surgical outcomes and logistic factors such as travel <lb/>distances. Health managers and policy-makers should <lb/>consider these findings to better understand women&apos;s <lb/>decision-making and partly capture the determinants of <lb/>unwarranted variation in terms of underuse or overuse, <lb/>eventually ensuring that patients receive care aligned with <lb/>their individual needs and preferences, regardless of their <lb/>geographical location. The development of standardised <lb/>guidelines and clinical pathways for pelvic prolapse may <lb/>help tackle unwarranted practice variation to advance the <lb/>cause of patient-centred, equitable, sustainable and effec-<lb/>tive healthcare services for women. <lb/></body>
    
    <div type="contribution">Contributors AF contributed to conceptualising and designing the study; collecting <lb/>and managing data and performing statistical analyses; writing the first draft of <lb/>the manuscript; reading, reviewing and editing the manuscript. NB participated <lb/>in conceptualising and designing the study; collecting and managing data and <lb/></div>
      
    <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>24 July 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

    <page>8 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Ferrari A, et al. BMJ Open doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/></note>

    <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <div type="contribution">performing statistical analyses; reading, reviewing and editing the manuscript. <lb/>AG contributed to writing the first draft of the manuscript; reading, reviewing and <lb/>editing the manuscript. TS gave his contribution in reading, reviewing and editing <lb/>the manuscript; approving the final version of the manuscript for initial submission; <lb/>supervising the work by coordinating the collaboration between the two research <lb/>groups. MV contributed to conceptualising and designing the study; reading, <lb/>reviewing and editing the manuscript; approving the final version of the manuscript <lb/>for initial submission; supervising the work by coordinating the collaboration <lb/>between the two research groups; she was also responsible for the overall content <lb/>as guarantor. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="funding">Funding The data sources and the publication charges were funded as part of the <lb/>research activities of the Sant&apos;Anna School of Advanced Studies. Such activities <lb/>were funded by the Regional Health Authority of Tuscany under a collaboration <lb/>agreement with Sant&apos;Anna School. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="annex">Disclaimer The Tuscany Region had no role in research question development, <lb/>study design, data collection and analysis or writing and submitting the article for <lb/>publication. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Competing interests None declared. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="annex">Patient and public involvement Patients and/or the public were not involved in <lb/>the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. <lb/>Patient consent for publication Not applicable. <lb/>Ethics approval Participation in the survey was voluntary, and women gave <lb/>informed consent before answering the questionnaire. They also provided consent <lb/>to be recontacted for possible further questions. The study was exempt from ethics <lb/>committee approval by the Institutional Review Board of Sant&apos;Anna School of <lb/>Advanced Studies since data were totally anonymous and voluntarily provided by <lb/>the participants. <lb/>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="availability">Data availability statement Data are available on reasonable request. The <lb/>datasets used and/or analysed during the current study and the Stata scripts are <lb/>available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="annex">Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has <lb/>not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been <lb/>peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those <lb/>of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and <lb/>responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content <lb/>includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability <lb/>of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, <lb/>terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error <lb/>and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise. <lb/></div>
    
    <front>Open access This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which <lb/>permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, <lb/>and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use <lb/>is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/. <lb/>ORCID iDs <lb/>Amerigo Ferrari http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5309-2813 <lb/>Milena Vainieri http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0914-4487 <lb/></front>

    <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 Smith FJ, Holman CDJ, Moorin RE, et al. Lifetime risk of <lb/>undergoing surgery for pelvic organ prolapse. Obstet Gynecol <lb/>2010;116:1096-100. <lb/>2 Collins SA, O&apos;Shea M, Dykes N, et al. International urogynecological <lb/>consultation: clinical definition of pelvic organ prolapse. Int <lb/>Urogynecol J 2021;32:2011-9. <lb/>3 Mannella P, Giannini A, Russo E, et al. Personalizing pelvic floor <lb/>reconstructive surgery in aging women. Maturitas 2015;82:109-15. <lb/>4 Jelovsek JE, Maher C, Barber MD. Pelvic organ prolapse. Lancet <lb/>2007;369:1027-38. <lb/>5 Hagen S, Thakar R. Conservative management of pelvic organ <lb/>prolapse. Obstet Gynaecol Reprod Med 2012;22:118-22. <lb/>6 Patnam R, Sripad AA, Dengler E, et al. Moving on: how many women <lb/>opt for surgery after pessary use for prolapse? Female Pelvic Med <lb/>Reconstr Surg 2020;26:387-90. <lb/>7 Hudson CO, Northington GM, Lyles RH, et al. Outcomes of robotic <lb/>sacrocolpopexy: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Female <lb/>Pelvic Med Reconstr Surg 2014;20:252-60. <lb/>8 Ryan GA, Purandare NC, Ganeriwal SA, et al. Conservative <lb/>management of pelvic organ prolapse: indian contribution. J Obstet <lb/>Gynaecol India 2021;71:3-10. <lb/>9 Kammerer-Doak D, Svabik K, Bazi T. Variability in practice patterns in <lb/>stress urinary incontinence and pelvic organ prolapse: results of an <lb/>IUGA survey. Int Urogynecol J 2017;28:735-44. <lb/>10 Birkmeyer JD, Reames BN, McCulloch P, et al. Understanding of <lb/>regional variation in the use of surgery. Lancet 2013;382:1121-9. <lb/>11 Ferrari A, Giannini A, Seghieri C, et al. Regional practice variation <lb/>in pelvic organ prolapse surgery in tuscany, italy: a retrospective <lb/>cohort study on administrative health data. BMJ Open <lb/>2023;13:e068145. <lb/>12 Wennberg JE. Time to tackle unwarranted variations in practice. BMJ <lb/>2011;342:bmj.d1513. <lb/>13 Lungu DA, Grillo Ruggieri T, Nuti S. Decision making tools for <lb/>managing waiting times and treatment rates in elective surgery. BMC <lb/>Health Serv Res 2019;19:369. <lb/>14 Nuti S, De Rosis S, Bonciani M, et al. Rethinking healthcare <lb/>performance evaluation systems towards the people-centredness <lb/>approach: their pathways, their experience, their evaluation. Healthc <lb/>Pap 2017;17:56-64. <lb/>15 Puglia M, Pacifici M, Voller F, et al. Gravidanza e parto in Toscana, <lb/>2022. Available: https://www.epicentro.iss.it/territorio/toscana/pdf/ <lb/>Incifre_20_Gravidanza_parto_2022_rev_22_dic.pdf <lb/>16 Perrone E, Formisano D, Gargano G, et al. La nascita in Emilia-<lb/>Romagna: 20° Rapporto sui dati del Certificato di Assistenza al Parto <lb/>(CedAP), 2022. Available: https://salute.regione.emilia-romagna.it/ <lb/>siseps/sanita/cedap/files/la-nascita-in-emilia-romagna_rapporto-<lb/>cedap-dati-anno-2022.pdf/@@download/file/La <lb/>17 Sullivan SA, Davidson ERW, Bretschneider CE, et al. Patient <lb/>characteristics associated with treatment choice for pelvic organ <lb/>prolapse and urinary incontinence. Int Urogynecol J 2016;27:811-6. <lb/>18 Kapoor DS, Thakar R, Sultan AH, et al. Conservative versus <lb/>surgical management of prolapse: what dictates patient choice? Int <lb/>Urogynecol J 2009;20:1157-61. <lb/>19 Thys SD, Roovers JP, Geomini PM, et al. Do patients prefer a pessary <lb/>or surgery as primary treatment for pelvic organ prolapse. Gynecol <lb/>Obstet Invest 2012;74:6-12. <lb/>20 Chan SSC, Cheung RYK, Yiu KW, et al. Symptoms, quality of life, <lb/>and factors affecting women&apos;s treatment decisions regarding pelvic <lb/>organ prolapse. Int Urogynecol J 2012;23:1027-33. <lb/>21 Lyatoshinskaya P, Gumina D, Popov A, et al. Knowledge of pelvic <lb/>organ prolapse in patients and their information-seeking preferences: <lb/>comparing vienna and moscow. Int Urogynecol J 2016;27:1673-80. <lb/>22 van den Brink MJ, Beelen P, Herman MC, et al. Women&apos;s preferences <lb/>for the levonorgestrel intrauterine system versus endometrial ablation <lb/>for heavy menstrual bleeding. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol <lb/>2018;228:143-7. <lb/>23 Janda M, Armfield NR, Page K, et al. Factors influencing <lb/>women&apos;s decision making in hysterectomy. Patient Educ Couns <lb/>2018;101:504-10. <lb/>24 Korbly NB, Kassis NC, Good MM, et al. Patient preferences for <lb/>uterine preservation and hysterectomy in women with pelvic organ <lb/>prolapse. Am J Obstet Gynecol 2013;209:S0002-9378(13)00821-1. <lb/>25 van IJsselmuiden MN, Detollenaere RJ, Gerritse MBE, et al. Dutch <lb/>women&apos;s attitudes towards hysterectomy and uterus preservation <lb/>in surgical treatment of pelvic organ prolapse. Eur J Obstet Gynecol <lb/>Reprod Biol 2018;220:79-83. <lb/>26 Urdzík P, Kalis V, Blaganje M, et al. Pelvic organ prolapse and uterine <lb/>preservation: a survey of female gynecologists (POP-UP survey). <lb/>BMC Womens Health 2020;20::241. <lb/>27 Schulten SFM, Essers B, Notten KJB, et al. Patient&apos;s preference <lb/>for sacrospinous hysteropexy or modified manchester operation: A <lb/>discrete choice experiment. BJOG 2023;130:99-106. <lb/>28 Babalola O, Gebben D, Tarver ME, et al. Patient preferences <lb/>regarding surgical treatment methods for symptomatic uterine <lb/>fibroids. Ther Innov Regul Sci 2023;57:976-86. <lb/>29 Noor N, Rahimi S, Pereira E, et al. Patient preferences for abdominal <lb/>incisions used for pelvic organ prolapse surgery. Female Pelvic Med <lb/>Reconstr Surg 2015;21:348-54. <lb/>30 Interdonato ML, Scollo P, Bignardi T, et al. Hysterectomy <lb/>by transvaginal natural orifice transluminal endoscopic <lb/>surgery: an italian initial experience. Front Med (Lausanne) <lb/>2022;9:1018232:1018232:. <lb/>31 Dunivan GC, Fairchild PS, Cichowski SB, et al. The association <lb/>between distances traveled for care and treatment choices for pelvic <lb/>floor disorders in a rural southwestern population. J Health Dispar <lb/>Res Pract 2014;7:23-32. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>24 July 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

    <page>9 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">Ferrari A, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e084034. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

    <listBibl>32 Ferrari Seghieri C, Giannini A, et al. Driving time drives the hospital <lb/>choice: choice models for pelvic organ prolapse surgery in italy. Eur J <lb/>Health Econ 2023;24:1575-86. <lb/>33 Ferrari A, Pirrotta L, Bonciani M, et al. Higher readability of <lb/>institutional websites drives the correct fruition of the abortion <lb/>pathway: A cross-sectional study. PLoS One 2022;17:e0277342. <lb/>34 Caldwell L, Papermaster AE, Halder GE, et al. Evidence-based <lb/>pelvic floor disorder care pathways optimize shared decision <lb/>making between patients and surgeons. Int Urogynecol J <lb/>2022;33:2841-7. <lb/>35 O&apos;Connor AM, Llewellyn-Thomas HA, Flood AB. Modifying <lb/>unwarranted variations in health care: shared decision making using <lb/>patient decision aids. Health Aff (Millwood) 2004;23:VAR-63. <lb/>36 O&apos;Connor AM, Wennberg JE, Legare F, et al. Toward the &apos;tipping <lb/>point&apos;: decision aids and informed patient choice. Health Aff <lb/>(Millwood) 2007;26:716-25. <lb/>37 Stiggelbout AM, Van der Weijden T, De Wit MPT, et al. Shared <lb/>decision making: really putting patients at the centre of healthcare. <lb/>BMJ 2012;344:bmj.e256. <lb/>38 Greer AL, Goodwin JS, Freeman JL, et al. Bringing the patient back <lb/>in. guidelines, practice variations, and the social context of medical <lb/>practice. Int J Technol Assess Health Care 2002;18:747-61. <lb/>39 Brazell HD, O&apos;Sullivan DM, Forrest A, et al. Effect of a decision aid on <lb/>decision making for the treatment of pelvic organ prolapse. Female <lb/>Pelvic Med Reconstr Surg 2015;21:231-5. <lb/>40 Brabers AEM, van Dijk L, Groenewegen PP, et al. Does A strategy to <lb/>promote shared decision-making reduce medical practice variation <lb/>in the choice of either single or double embryo transfer after in vitro <lb/>fertilisation? A secondary analysis of A randomised controlled trial. <lb/>BMJ Open 2016;6:e010894. <lb/>41 Ossin DA, Carter EC, Cartwright R, et al. Shared decision-making in <lb/>urology and female pelvic floor medicine and reconstructive surgery. <lb/>Nat Rev Urol 2022;19:161-70. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>24 July 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2024-084034 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as </note>


	</text>

</TEI>