<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">How do they become globally high achieving? Trajectories, struggles, and achievements of ethnic Chinese humanities and social sciences scholars</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Lili</forename>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-27T16:19:09.354505Z">27.10.2025 16:19:09</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1057$1$s41599-024-02651-z</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1057/s41599-024-02651-z</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Lili Yang. (2024). How do they become globally high achieving? Trajectories, struggles, and achievements of ethnic Chinese humanities and social sciences scholars. Humanities and Social Sciences Communications, 11(1), None. DOI: 10.1057/s41599-024-02651-z</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-27T16:19:09.354505Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-27T16:19:09.354505Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Accuracy of Ten Intraocular Lens Formulas <lb/>in Spherical Equivalent of Toric Intraocular Lens <lb/>Power Calculation <lb/>Jingyi Shi . Zehui Zhu . Bin Hu . Shuyi Qian . Yalan Wang . <lb/>Pingjun Chang . Yun-e Zhao <lb/>Received: February 14, 2024 / Accepted: February 29, 2024 / Published online: March 20, 2024 <lb/>Ó The Author(s) 2024 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Introduction: The aim of this work is to eval-<lb/>uate the accuracy of the Barrett Universal II (BU <lb/>II), Emmetropia verifying optical (EVO) 2.0, <lb/>Haigis, Hoffer Q, Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni) <lb/>(HQST), Holladay 1, Kane, Ladas Super, San-<lb/>ders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretical (SRK/T), and T2 <lb/>intraocular lens (IOL) power formulas for cal-<lb/>culating spherical equivalent (SE) of toric IOL. <lb/>Methods: This study enrolled consecutive <lb/>patients who underwent phacoemulsification <lb/>and toric IOL implantation at the Eye Hospital <lb/>of Wenzhou Medical University in Hangzhou <lb/>from 2015 to 2022. We compared the new-<lb/>generation formulas with Gaussian optics-based <lb/>standard formulas, and calculated the mean <lb/>absolute error (MAE), median absolute error <lb/>(MedAE), and percentage of eyes within ± 0.25 <lb/>diopter (D), ± 0.50 D, ± 0.75 D and ± 1.00 D <lb/>of the target refraction. Subgroup analyses were <lb/>conducted based on the anterior chamber depth <lb/>(ACD), keratometry (K), and toricity (T). <lb/>Results: A total of 207 eyes of 207 patients were <lb/>included in this study. Overall, the Kane and <lb/>EVO2.0 formulas demonstrated the lowest <lb/>MedAEs. The EVO2.0 formula exhibited the <lb/>highest <lb/>percentage <lb/>of <lb/>eyes <lb/>Pingjun Chang and Yun-e Zhao contributed equally as <lb/>co-corresponding authors. <lb/>J. Shi Á Z. Zhu Á B. Hu Á S. Qian Á Y. Wang Á <lb/>P. Chang (&amp;) Á Y. Zhao (&amp;) <lb/>Eye Hospital and School of Ophthalmology and <lb/>Optometry, Wenzhou Medical University, <lb/>Wenzhou 325000, Zhejiang, China <lb/>e-mail: zyehzeye@126.comY. Zhao <lb/>e-mail: cpj@eye.ac.cn <lb/>J. Shi Á Z. Zhu Á B. Hu Á S. Qian Á Y. Wang Á <lb/>P. Chang Á Y. Zhao <lb/>National Clinical Research Center for Ocular <lb/>Diseases, Wenzhou 325000, Zhejiang, China <lb/>J. Shi Á Z. Zhu Á B. Hu Á S. Qian Á Y. Wang Á <lb/>P. Chang Á Y. Zhao <lb/>Eye Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University <lb/>Hangzhou Branch, 618 Fengqi Road, Hangzhou <lb/>310000, Zhejiang, China <lb/>B. Hu <lb/>Shaoxing People&apos;s Hospital, Shaoxing 312000, <lb/>Zhejiang, China <lb/>S. Qian <lb/>The First Affiliated Hospital of Ningbo University, <lb/>Ningbo 315010, Zhejiang, China <lb/>Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s40123-024-00926-x <lb/>within ± 0.50 D, ± 0.75 D, ± 1.00 D. <lb/>More-<lb/>over, the EVO2.0 formula showed the lowest <lb/>MedAE for flat K subgroup, the highest per-<lb/>centage of eyes within ± 0.50 D, ± 1.00 D for <lb/>shallow ACD subgroup, the highest percentage <lb/>of eyes within ± 0.75 D for regular ACD, flat K, <lb/>T2-T3, T4-T5 subgroups. The Kane and formula <lb/>performed the lowest MedAE in the T4-T5 <lb/>subgroup. <lb/>Conclusions: Application of the Kane and <lb/>EVO2.0 formulas significantly improved the <lb/>prediction of postoperative SE outcome for toric <lb/>IOL compared to the other formulas. <lb/>Keywords: Toric intraocular lens; Cataract; <lb/>Power calculation formulas; Sphere equivalent <lb/>Key Summary Points <lb/>Why carry out this study? <lb/>Previous studies focused on the <lb/>intraocular lens (IOL) power calculation <lb/>in predicting spherical equivalent (SE) for <lb/>non-toric IOLs. <lb/>This study aims to comprehensively assess <lb/>and compare the overall accuracy of new-<lb/>generation formulas against vergence-<lb/>based formulas for calculating SE after <lb/>toric IOL implantation. <lb/>What was learned from the study? <lb/>The Kane and Emmetropia verifying <lb/>optical 2.0 formulas demonstrated high <lb/>accuracy in predicting SE for toric IOLs. <lb/>Three improved IOL calculation formulas, <lb/>the Ladas Super, T2, and Hoffer <lb/>QST(Savini/Taroni) formula, performed <lb/>the superior outcome compared to <lb/>traditional third-generation formulas for <lb/>calculating SE after toric IOL <lb/>implantation. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Cataract surgery is regarded as a combined <lb/>rehabilitative and refractive procedure. As <lb/>modern surgical techniques advance, patients&apos; <lb/>expectations for optimal postoperative vision <lb/>continue to rise. The precision of the preoper-<lb/>ative intraocular lens (IOL) power formula <lb/>stands out as a key factor influencing postop-<lb/>erative refractive outcomes. <lb/>Various formulas for IOL power calculation <lb/>have evolved over time, aiming to enhance the <lb/>accuracy of predicting refractive results. The <lb/>third-and fourth-generation formulas, previ-<lb/>ously proposed, mostly employ vergence for-<lb/>mulas based on Gaussian optics, including the <lb/>Barrett Universal II (BU II) [1], Haigis [2], Hol-<lb/>laday 1 [3], Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretical <lb/>(SRK/T) [4], and Hoffer Q [5] formulas. In con-<lb/>trast, the latest generation of IOL formulas use <lb/>artificial intelligence (AI) and regression equa-<lb/>tions for predictions, demonstrating com-<lb/>mendable performance. Notably, studies <lb/>suggest that the Kane formula [6] seems to be <lb/>one of the most accurate formulas available <lb/>[7, 8]. The Emmetropia verifying optical <lb/>(EVO)2.0 formula C has also exhibited good <lb/>performance, ranking among the most accurate <lb/>formulas [8, 10]. Additionally, Sheard RM [11] <lb/>and Taroni L [12] have enhanced the SRK/T and <lb/>Hoffer Q formulas, resulting in the T2 [11] and <lb/>Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni) (HQST) [13] formu-<lb/>las, respectively, indicating improved accuracy <lb/>for traditional formulas. Ladas JG [14] intro-<lb/>duced a super surface, incorporating the opti-<lb/>mal aspects from four out of the five third-<lb/>generation formulas to generate a super formula <lb/>[15]. <lb/>Nonetheless, prior studies basically used <lb/>non-toric IOLs to assess prediction accuracy. In <lb/>fact, it is crucial to extend this evaluation to <lb/>toric IOLs, comparing the precision of various <lb/>formulas in predicting spherical equivalent (SE) <lb/>outcomes so as to further improve the refractive <lb/></body>

			<page>1322 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<body>results. Therefore, our study aims to compre-<lb/>hensively assess and compare the overall accu-<lb/>racy of new-generation formulas against <lb/>vergence-based formulas for calculating SE after <lb/>toric IOL implantation. Subgroup analyses will <lb/>also be conducted for each anterior chamber <lb/>depth (ACD), keratometry (K), and toricity <lb/>(T) group. We hope the illustration of these <lb/>formulas can guide the selection of IOL power <lb/>formulas for patients with cataracts, promoting <lb/>the attainment of improved postoperative <lb/>refractive outcomes. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Patients <lb/>This is a retrospective study, including consec-<lb/>utive patients who underwent clear cornea <lb/>temporal incision phacoemulsification and <lb/>intracapsular implantation of the AcrySof <lb/>SN6AT(2-9) IOL (Alcon Laboratories, Inc., Fort <lb/>Worth, TX, USA) during the period 2015-2022, <lb/>at the Eye Hospital of Wenzhou Medical <lb/>University in Hangzhou. All patients were <lb/>Table 1 Demographic and biometric data of patient <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Mean -SD/n (%) <lb/>Range <lb/>Male gender (%) <lb/>72 (34.7%) <lb/>Right eyes (%) <lb/>96 (46.4%) <lb/>IOL types (%) <lb/>T2-T3 <lb/>54 (26.1%) <lb/>T4-T5 <lb/>128 (61.8%) <lb/>T6-T9 <lb/>25 (12.1%) <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>72.32 ± 11.10 <lb/>24-89 <lb/>AL (mm) <lb/>23.54 ± 0.88 <lb/>22.06-25.94 <lb/>ACD (mm) <lb/>3.01 ± 0.43 <lb/>1.99-4.54 <lb/>ACD B 3 mm (n = 107) <lb/>2.68 ± 0.02 <lb/>1.99-3.00 <lb/>3 mm \ ACD \ 3.5 mm (n = 74) <lb/>3.22 ± 0.02 <lb/>3.01-3.49 <lb/>ACD C 3.5 mm (n = 26) <lb/>3.74 ± 0.05 <lb/>3.50-4.54 <lb/>K1 (D) <lb/>43.43 ± 1.32 <lb/>39.95-47.27 <lb/>K2 (D) <lb/>44.99 ± 1.37 <lb/>41.72-49.06 <lb/>K (D) <lb/>44.21 ± 1.31 <lb/>41.070-48.165 <lb/>K B 43D (n = 34) <lb/>42.25 ± 0.08 <lb/>41.070-42.900 <lb/>43D \ K \ 45D (n = 117) <lb/>43.98 ± 0.05 <lb/>43.015-44.945 <lb/>K C 45D (n = 56) <lb/>45.87 ± 0.09 <lb/>45.040-48.165 <lb/>Corneal astigmatism (D) <lb/>1.56 ± 0.60 <lb/>0.52-3.61 <lb/>IOL power (D) <lb/>21.27 ± 2.43 <lb/>13.5-27.5 <lb/>Continuous data are expressed as mean ± standard deviation <lb/>ACD anterior chamber depth, AL axial length, D diopters, IOL intraocular lens, K keratometry, K1 keratometry flat axis, K2 <lb/>keratometry steep axis, SD standard deviation <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<page>1323 <lb/></page>

			<body>successfully measured preoperatively with the <lb/>IOLMaster 500 or 700 (Carl Zeiss Meditec AG, <lb/>Jena, Germany). Subjective refraction was per-<lb/>formed 1 month post-operatively by three <lb/>experienced optometrists. According to the <lb/>recommendations of the editorials by Hoffer <lb/>et al., [16, 17] only one eye from each patient <lb/>was included at random, and only one single <lb/>toric IOL type was used. Exclusion criteria were: <lb/>(1) age below 18 or above 90; (2) axial length <lb/>(AL) less than 22 mm and more than 26 mm; (3) <lb/>preoperative corneal astigmatism greater than 4 <lb/>diopters (D); (4) other previous ophthalmic <lb/>diseases, previous ophthalmic trauma, previous <lb/>ophthalmic surgeries; (5) any intraoperative or <lb/>postoperative complication and (6) postopera-<lb/>tive Snellen best-corrected distance visual acuity <lb/>(BCVA) worse than 20/40. Subgroup analysis <lb/>was performed based on preoperative ACD, K <lb/>and T: shallow ACD group-ACD B 3.00 mm, <lb/>regular <lb/>ACD <lb/>group-<lb/>3.00 mm \ ACD \ 3.50 mm, <lb/>deep <lb/>ACD <lb/>group-ACD C 3.50 mm; flat K group-K B 43 <lb/>D, regular K group-43D \ K \ 45D, steep K <lb/>Table 2 Optimized IOL constants used for each formula <lb/>Formula <lb/>Measure <lb/>Optimized IOL constant <lb/>BU II <lb/>A-constant <lb/>119.39 <lb/>EVO2.0 <lb/>A-constant <lb/>119.31 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>a0 (a1, a2) <lb/>-0.290 (0.213, 0.208) <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>pACD <lb/>5.80 <lb/>HQST <lb/>pACD <lb/>5.78 <lb/>Holladay 1 Surgeon factor 1.99 <lb/>Kane <lb/>A-constant <lb/>119.29 <lb/>Ladas super A-constant <lb/>119.31 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>A-constant <lb/>119.24 <lb/>T2 <lb/>A-constant <lb/>119.27 <lb/>BU II Barrett Universal II, EVO Emmetropia Verifying <lb/>Optical, HQST Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), IOL <lb/>intraocular lens, pACD personalized anterior chamber <lb/>depth, SRK/T Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretical <lb/>Table 3 PE of ten IOL power calculation formulas in overall study cohort (N = 207) <lb/>Formula <lb/>ME <lb/>(D) <lb/>SD <lb/>(D) <lb/>Min <lb/>(D) <lb/>Max <lb/>(D) <lb/>MAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>MedAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>Percentage of eyes within different PE ranges <lb/>(%) <lb/>-0.25 D -0.50 D -0.75 D -1.00 D <lb/>BU II <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>-1.21 1.22 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>51.2 <lb/>83.6 <lb/>93.7 <lb/>98.1 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>-0.97 0.86 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>52.2 <lb/>87.0 <lb/>98.1 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>-1.18 0.88 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>45.9 <lb/>84.1 <lb/>94.7 <lb/>99.5 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>-1.22 1.03 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>46.4 <lb/>80.2 <lb/>94.7 <lb/>99.0 <lb/>HQST <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>-1.15 0.95 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>50.2 <lb/>85.0 <lb/>95.1 <lb/>99.0 <lb/>Holladay 1 0.00 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>-1.31 0.96 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>47.8 <lb/>84.0 <lb/>95.7 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>Kane <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>-1.12 0.93 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>52.7 <lb/>83.6 <lb/>95.2 <lb/>99.5 <lb/>Ladas super 0.00 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>-1.20 0.99 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>48.3 <lb/>82.6 <lb/>97.1 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>-1.37 1.08 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>46.4 <lb/>79.2 <lb/>91.8 <lb/>97.6 <lb/>T2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>-1.30 0.97 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>50.7 <lb/>84.5 <lb/>95.7 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>BU II Barrett Universal II, D diopters, EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), IOL <lb/>intraocular lens, K keratometry, MAE mean absolute error, Max maximum, MedAE median absolute error, ME mean error, <lb/>Min minimum, PE prediction error, SD standard deviation, SRK/T Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretical <lb/></body>

			<page>1324 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<body>group-K C 45D; low-toricity group-T2-T3, <lb/>medium-toricity group-T4-T5, high-toricity <lb/>group-T6-T9. This study was performed in <lb/>accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki of <lb/>1964 and its subsequent amendments. This <lb/>study was approved by the Ethics Committee of <lb/>Wenzhou Medical University (2021-036-K-29-<lb/>01). <lb/>Formula Calculation and Constant <lb/>Optimization <lb/>IOL constant optimization was carried out by <lb/>varying the constant used by trial and error <lb/>until the mean prediction error (ME) for each <lb/>formula was 0.00 D, following Wang et al.&apos;s <lb/>recommendations [18]. Published IOL power <lb/>formulas (e.g., the Haigis, Hoffer Q, Holladay 1, <lb/>SRK/T, and T2 formulas) were optimized using <lb/>Excel spreadsheets and validated against IOL-<lb/>Master 500 or 700. We can achieve the opti-<lb/>mized value of the predicted anterior chamber <lb/>depth (pACD; Hoffer Q), surgeon factor (Holla-<lb/>day 1), and A constant (SRK/T and T2), and so <lb/>forth. Outcomes for the single lens constant <lb/>(a0) optimization with the Haigis formula were <lb/>used to compare the formulas on a more equal <lb/>basis [19]. The a1 and a2 constants we used were <lb/>the already optimized values for the <lb/>SN6AT(2-9) IOLs as listed on the User Group for <lb/>Laser Interference Biometry (ULIB) website [20]. <lb/>Unpublished formulas (e.g., the BU II, EVO2.0, <lb/>Kane, Ladas Super and HQST formulas) were <lb/>optimized using specific computer program-<lb/>ming languages (e.g., Python Software Founda-<lb/>tion, Wilmington, DE, USA) through respective <lb/>online calculator. <lb/>Primary Outcomes <lb/>According to the previous protocol, the refrac-<lb/>tive prediction error (PE) for each eye was <lb/>defined as the difference between the SE of the <lb/>1-month postoperative subjective refraction <lb/>and the predicted postoperative refraction for <lb/>each IOL power formula. A negative PE indi-<lb/>cated a myopic result, while a positive PE rep-<lb/>resented a hyperopic outcome. The median <lb/>absolute error (MedAE) and mean absolute error <lb/>(MAE) were defined as the median absolute <lb/>value and mean absolute value of the refractive <lb/>PE, respectively. The percentage of eyes within <lb/>different <lb/>PE <lb/>ranges <lb/>(± 0.25 D, ± 0.50 D, <lb/>± 0.75 D and ± 1.00 D) were calculated. The <lb/>impact of ACD, K and T on ME, MAE, MedAE <lb/>and the percentage of eyes within different PE <lb/>ranges, were also investigated. <lb/>Fig. 1 Box plot graph of the absolute prediction errors <lb/>and stacked bars comparing the percentage of eyes within a <lb/>given diopter (D) range of predicted spherical equivalent <lb/>(SE) refraction outcome. BU II Barrett Universal II, <lb/>D diopters, EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST <lb/>Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), SRK/T Sanders-Ret-<lb/>zlaff-Kraff/theoretica <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<page>1325 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4 PE of ten IOL power calculation formulas in ACD subgroups <lb/>Formula <lb/>ME <lb/>(D) <lb/>SD <lb/>(D) <lb/>Min <lb/>(D) <lb/>Max <lb/>(D) <lb/>MAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>MedAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>Percentage of eyes within different PE ranges <lb/>(%) <lb/>-0.25 D -0.50 D -0.75 D -1.00 D <lb/>Shallow ACD group <lb/>BU II <lb/>0.01 0.38 -1.21 1.22 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>52.3 <lb/>86.9 <lb/>95.3 <lb/>97.2 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>-0.01 0.33 -0.97 0.71 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>50.5 <lb/>92.5 <lb/>97.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>-0.02 0.38 -1.18 0.83 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>44.9 <lb/>83.2 <lb/>95.3 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>-0.12 0.37 -1.22 0.78 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>42.1 <lb/>81.3 <lb/>94.4 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>HQST <lb/>-0.05 0.36 -1.15 0.85 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>47.7 <lb/>89.7 <lb/>95.3 <lb/>98.1 <lb/>Holladay 1 <lb/>-0.08 0.36 -1.31 0.81 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>45.8 <lb/>87.9 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>98.1 <lb/>Kane <lb/>-0.03 0.36 -1.12 0.85 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>51.4 <lb/>88.8 <lb/>95.3 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>Ladas super <lb/>-0.01 0.36 -1.20 0.99 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>46.7 <lb/>90.7 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>98.1 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>-0.06 0.40 -1.37 1.08 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>48.6 <lb/>81.3 <lb/>94.4 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>T2 <lb/>-0.07 0.37 -1.30 0.90 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>48.6 <lb/>87.9 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>98.1 <lb/>Regular ACD <lb/>group <lb/>BU II <lb/>0.04 0.39 -1.15 0.85 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>48.6 <lb/>82.4 <lb/>91.9 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>0.06 0.34 -0.75 0.86 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>52.7 <lb/>85.1 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>0.06 0.37 -0.86 0.88 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>48.6 <lb/>83.8 <lb/>93.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>0.14 0.37 -0.85 1.03 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>54.1 <lb/>77.0 <lb/>93.2 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>HQST <lb/>0.09 0.36 -0.98 0.95 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>51.4 <lb/>79.7 <lb/>94.6 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Holladay 1 <lb/>0.10 0.38 -1.07 0.96 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>50.0 <lb/>77.0 <lb/>95.9 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>Kane <lb/>0.10 0.37 -1.00 0.93 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>52.7 <lb/>78.4 <lb/>94.6 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Ladas super <lb/>0.07 0.37 -1.11 0.75 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>48.6 <lb/>74.3 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>0.09 0.43 -1.35 0.96 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>44.6 <lb/>77.0 <lb/>89.2 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>T2 <lb/>0.11 0.38 -1.07 0.97 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>51.4 <lb/>78.4 <lb/>94.6 <lb/>98.6 <lb/>Deep ACD <lb/>group <lb/>BU II <lb/>-0.13 0.36 -0.80 0.55 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>53.8 <lb/>73.1 <lb/>92.3 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>-0.14 0.33 -0.66 0.52 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>57.7 <lb/>69.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>-0.12 0.34 -0.87 0.39 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>42.3 <lb/>88.5 <lb/>96.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>0.10 0.31 -0.60 0.57 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>42.3 <lb/>84.6 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>HQST <lb/>-0.07 0.36 -0.82 0.52 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>57.7 <lb/>80.8 <lb/>96.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Holladay 1 <lb/>0.01 0.35 -0.88 0.64 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>50.0 <lb/>88.5 <lb/>92.3 <lb/>100.0 <lb/></body>

			<page>1326 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<body>Statistical Analysis <lb/>The data were presented using Microsoft Office <lb/>Excel (Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA), and <lb/>statistical analysis was performed using SPSS <lb/>(version 26.0, IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). The <lb/>Shapiro-Wilk test was used to verify the nor-<lb/>mality of data distribution. The non-parametric <lb/>Friedman M test (with Bonferroni correction for <lb/>multiple comparisons) was used to compare the <lb/>differences in absolute prediction error (AE) <lb/>between formulas. The Cochran&apos;s Q test was <lb/>utilized to compare percentage of eyes between <lb/>formulas within different PE groups. The one-<lb/>sample t test was conducted to evaluate whether <lb/>the ME of each formula in subgroups differed <lb/>significantly from zero. A P value less than 0.05 <lb/>Table 4 continued <lb/>Formula <lb/>ME <lb/>(D) <lb/>SD <lb/>(D) <lb/>Min <lb/>(D) <lb/>Max <lb/>(D) <lb/>MAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>MedAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>Percentage of eyes within different PE ranges <lb/>(%) <lb/>-0.25 D -0.50 D -0.75 D -1.00 D <lb/>Kane <lb/>-0.13 0.36 -0.80 0.51 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>57.7 <lb/>76.9 <lb/>96.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Ladas super <lb/>-0.15 0.35 -0.78 0.56 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>53.8 <lb/>73.1 <lb/>96.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>-0.03 0.43 -0.99 0.89 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>42.3 <lb/>76.9 <lb/>88.5 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>T2 <lb/>0.02 0.33 -0.76 0.67 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>57.7 <lb/>88.5 <lb/>96.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>ACD anterior chamber depth, BU II Barrett Universal II, ACD anterior chamber depth, D diopters, EVO Emmetropia <lb/>Verifying Optical, HQST Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), IOL intraocular lens, K keratometry, MAE mean absolute error, <lb/>Max maximum, MedAE median absolute error, ME mean error, Min minimum, PE prediction error, SD standard deviation, <lb/>SRK/T Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretical <lb/>Fig. 2 Mean prediction error (ME) of each formula, <lb/>distributed by anterior chamber depth (ACD) group. ACD <lb/>anterior chamber depth; BU II Barrett Universal II, <lb/>D diopters, EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST <lb/>Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), SRK/T Sanders-Ret-<lb/>zlaff-Kraff/theoretica <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<page>1327 <lb/></page>

			<body>was considered statistically significant. All <lb/>reported P values were two-sided. <lb/>The sample size was calculated using PASS <lb/>(version 15.0.5, NCSS LLC, Kaysville, UT, USA) <lb/>based on MedAE, which was the primary <lb/>parameter of interest in this study. We consid-<lb/>ered a two-sided 5% significance level and <lb/>power of 95%. The calculation indicated that <lb/>the total sample size should consist of 113 eyes. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Baseline <lb/>The study included 207 eyes of 207 patients. <lb/>Patients&apos; demographics and biometric data are <lb/>presented at Table 1. Optimized IOL constants <lb/>are shown in Table 2. <lb/>Fig. 3 Median absolute error (MedAE) plotted against <lb/>anterior chamber depth (ACD) groups for each formula. <lb/>ACD anterior chamber depth, BU II Barrett Universal II, <lb/>EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST Hoffer QST <lb/>(Savini/Taroni), MedAE median absolute error, SRK/T <lb/>Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretica <lb/></body>

			<page>1328 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 4 Stacked bars comparing the percentage of cases <lb/>within a given diopter (D) range of predicted spherical <lb/>equivalent (SE) refraction outcome of each subgroup of <lb/>anterior chamber depth (ACD). A Shallow ACD group, <lb/>B Regular ACD group, C Deep ACD group. BU II Barrett <lb/>Universal II, EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST <lb/>Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), SRK/T Sanders-Ret-<lb/>zlaff-Kraff/theoretica <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<page>1329 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 5 PE of ten IOL power calculation formulas in K subgroups <lb/>Formula <lb/>ME <lb/>(D) <lb/>SD <lb/>(D) <lb/>Min <lb/>(D) <lb/>Max <lb/>(D) <lb/>MAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>MedAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>Percentage of eyes within different PE ranges <lb/>(%) <lb/>-0.25 D -0.50 D -0.75 D -1.00 D <lb/>Flat K group <lb/>BU II <lb/>0.15 0.39 <lb/>-0.67 1.22 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>55.9 <lb/>76.5 <lb/>91.2 <lb/>97.1 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>0.06 0.29 <lb/>-0.67 0.71 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>61.8 <lb/>88.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>-0.07 0.38 <lb/>-0.86 0.74 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>50.0 <lb/>82.4 <lb/>94.1 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>0.00 0.38 <lb/>-0.80 0.68 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>47.1 <lb/>73.5 <lb/>97.1 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>HQST <lb/>0.09 0.37 <lb/>-0.74 0.85 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>52.9 <lb/>76.5 <lb/>94.1 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Holladay 1 <lb/>0.10 0.35 <lb/>-0.71 0.81 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>47.1 <lb/>79.4 <lb/>97.1 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Kane <lb/>0.11 0.37 <lb/>-0.73 0.85 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>52.9 <lb/>76.5 <lb/>94.1 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Ladas super <lb/>0.10 0.37 <lb/>-0.70 0.99 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>52.9 <lb/>76.5 <lb/>97.1 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>0.27 0.39 <lb/>-0.61 1.08 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>44.1 <lb/>73.5 <lb/>82.4 <lb/>97.1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>0.13 0.36 <lb/>-0.69 0.90 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>58.8 <lb/>79.4 <lb/>94.1 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Regular K group <lb/>BU II <lb/>0.03 0.34 <lb/>-1.21 0.85 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>53.0 <lb/>88.0 <lb/>96.6 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>0.03 0.32 <lb/>-0.97 0.86 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>52.1 <lb/>89.7 <lb/>98.3 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>-0.01 0.35 <lb/>-1.18 0.88 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>47.9 <lb/>89.7 <lb/>95.7 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>0.00 0.38 <lb/>-1.22 1.03 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>51.3 <lb/>82.1 <lb/>94.9 <lb/>98.3 <lb/>HQST <lb/>0.02 0.33 <lb/>-1.15 0.95 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>53.8 <lb/>89.7 <lb/>97.4 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>Holladay 1 <lb/>0.01 0.35 <lb/>-1.31 0.96 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>53.0 <lb/>87.2 <lb/>97.4 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>Kane <lb/>0.02 0.34 <lb/>-1.12 0.93 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>56.4 <lb/>88.0 <lb/>97.4 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>Ladas super <lb/>0.01 0.33 <lb/>-1.20 0.75 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>53.0 <lb/>88.0 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>0.04 0.35 <lb/>-1.37 0.96 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>56.4 <lb/>83.8 <lb/>97.4 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>0.02 0.35 <lb/>-1.30 0.97 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>53.0 <lb/>87.2 <lb/>97.4 <lb/>99.1 <lb/>Steep K group <lb/>BU II <lb/>-0.13 0.42 <lb/>-1.15 0.67 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>44.6 <lb/>78.6 <lb/>89.3 <lb/>96.4 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>-0.10 0.37 <lb/>-0.90 0.53 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>46.4 <lb/>80.4 <lb/>96.4 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>0.06 0.41 <lb/>-0.92 0.83 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>39.3 <lb/>73.2 <lb/>92.9 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>0.00 0.41 <lb/>-0.99 0.78 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>35.7 <lb/>80.4 <lb/>92.9 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>HQST <lb/>-0.09 0.41 <lb/>-1.01 0.69 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>41.1 <lb/>80.4 <lb/>91.1 <lb/>98.2 <lb/>Holladay 1 -0.09 0.42 <lb/>-1.07 0.70 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>37.5 <lb/>80.4 <lb/>91.1 <lb/>96.4 <lb/>Kane <lb/>-0.08 0.40 <lb/>-1.00 0.65 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>44.6 <lb/>78.6 <lb/>91.1 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Ladas super -0.01 0.42 <lb/>-1.11 0.74 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>35.7 <lb/>75.0 <lb/>92.9 <lb/>96.4 <lb/></body>

			<page>1330 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<body>PE of the Overall Study Cohort <lb/>Table 3 and Fig. 1 summarize the MEs, standard <lb/>deviation (SD)s, minimum (Min)s, maximum <lb/>(Max)s, MAEs and MedAEs for the ten IOL for-<lb/>mulas, as well as the percentage of eyes <lb/>within ± 0.25 D, ± 0.50 D, ± 0.75 D, <lb/>and ± 1.00 D of the target refraction for each <lb/>formula. <lb/>The Kane and the EVO2.0 formulas were the <lb/>most accurate formulas (P = 0.012, 0.016, <lb/>respectively). <lb/>The Kane formula had the highest percent-<lb/>age of eyes within ± 0.25 D of the target <lb/>refraction (52.7%), while the EVO2.0 formula <lb/>had <lb/>the <lb/>highest <lb/>percentage <lb/>of <lb/>eyes <lb/>within ± 0.50 D, ± 0.75 D and ± 1.00 D (87.0, <lb/>98.1, 100.0%, respectively) (P = 0.025, 0.000, <lb/>0.021, respectively). In addition, the Ladas <lb/>Table 5 continued <lb/>Formula <lb/>ME <lb/>(D) <lb/>SD <lb/>(D) <lb/>Min <lb/>(D) <lb/>Max <lb/>(D) <lb/>MAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>MedAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>Percentage of eyes within different PE ranges <lb/>(%) <lb/>-0.25 D -0.50 D -0.75 D -1.00 D <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>-0.24 0.44 <lb/>-1.35 0.58 <lb/>0.41 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>26.8 <lb/>73.2 <lb/>85.7 <lb/>94.6 <lb/>T2 <lb/>-0.11 0.41 <lb/>-1.07 0.68 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>41.1 <lb/>82.1 <lb/>92.9 <lb/>96.4 <lb/>BU II Barrett Universal II, D diopters, EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), IOL <lb/>intraocular lens, K keratometry, MAE mean absolute error, Max maximum, MedAE median absolute error, ME mean error, <lb/>Min minimum, PE prediction error, SD standard deviation, SRK/T Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretical <lb/>Fig. 5 Mean prediction error (ME) of each formula, <lb/>distributed by keratometry (K) group. BU II Barrett <lb/>Universal II, D diopters, EVO Emmetropia Verifying <lb/>Optical, HQST Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), SRK/T <lb/>Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretica <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<page>1331 <lb/></page>

			<body>super formula also had the second highest val-<lb/>ues (97.1%) for the ± 0.75 D endpoint <lb/>(P = 0.003). However, the BU II formula pre-<lb/>sented poor predictability (45.9%) in the per-<lb/>centage of eyes within ± 0.75 D, which was <lb/>significantly different from the EVO2.0 formula <lb/>(P = 0.048). <lb/>Subgroup Analysis with ACD <lb/>Table 4 and Figs. 2, 3, and 4 summarize the MEs, <lb/>SDs, Mins, Maxs, MAEs, and MedAEs for the ten <lb/>IOL formulas in ACD subgroups, as well as the <lb/>percentage <lb/>of <lb/>eyes <lb/>within ± 0.25 D, ± <lb/>0.50 D, ± 0.75 D, and ± 1.00 D for each <lb/>formula. <lb/>Fig. 6 Median absolute error (MedAE) plotted against <lb/>keratometry (K) groups for each formula. BU II Barrett <lb/>Universal II, EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST <lb/>Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), K keratometry, MedAE <lb/>median absolute error, SRK/T Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/ <lb/>theoretica <lb/></body>

			<page>1332 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 7 Stacked bars comparing the percentage of cases <lb/>within a given diopter (D) range of predicted spherical <lb/>equivalent (SE) refraction outcome of each subgroup of <lb/>keratometry (K). A Flat K group, B Regular K group, <lb/>C Steep K group. BU II Barrett Universal II, EVO <lb/>Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST Hoffer QST <lb/>(Savini/Taroni), <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/ <lb/>theoretica <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<page>1333 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 6 PE of ten IOL power calculation formulas in T subgroups <lb/>Formula <lb/>ME <lb/>(D) <lb/>SD <lb/>(D) <lb/>Min <lb/>(D) <lb/>Max <lb/>(D) <lb/>MAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>MedAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>Percentage of eyes within different PE ranges <lb/>(%) <lb/>-0.25 D -0.50 D -0.75 D -1.00 D <lb/>Low-toricity group <lb/>BU II <lb/>0.02 0.42 -1.15 0.85 0.33 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>48.1 <lb/>79.6 <lb/>90.7 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>0.01 0.35 -0.90 0.86 0.29 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>48.1 <lb/>85.2 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>0.03 0.43 -0.92 0.88 0.36 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>35.2 <lb/>75.9 <lb/>87.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>0.06 0.43 -0.99 1.03 0.35 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>44.4 <lb/>77.8 <lb/>88.9 <lb/>98.1 <lb/>HQST <lb/>0.04 0.40 -1.01 0.95 0.32 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>50.0 <lb/>83.3 <lb/>92.6 <lb/>98.1 <lb/>Holladay 1 <lb/>0.04 0.42 -1.07 0.96 0.33 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>48.1 <lb/>81.5 <lb/>92.6 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>Kane <lb/>0.06 0.40 -1.00 0.93 0.32 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>51.9 <lb/>77.8 <lb/>92.6 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Ladas super <lb/>0.01 0.41 -1.11 0.75 0.33 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>46.3 <lb/>77.8 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>0.04 0.44 -1.35 0.96 0.33 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>50.0 <lb/>79.6 <lb/>90.7 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>T2 <lb/>0.04 0.41 -1.07 0.97 0.32 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>50.0 <lb/>81.5 <lb/>92.6 <lb/>96.3 <lb/>Medium-toricity group <lb/>BU II <lb/>0.01 0.37 -1.21 1.22 0.29 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>52.3 <lb/>85.2 <lb/>94.5 <lb/>98.4 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>0.01 0.33 -0.97 0.71 0.26 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>55.5 <lb/>86.7 <lb/>99.2 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>0.00 0.35 -1.18 0.74 0.28 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>49.2 <lb/>88.3 <lb/>97.7 <lb/>99.2 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>0.00 0.36 -1.22 0.79 0.29 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>49.2 <lb/>79.7 <lb/>96.9 <lb/>99.2 <lb/>HQST <lb/>0.00 0.35 -1.15 0.85 0.27 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>51.6 <lb/>85.2 <lb/>96.1 <lb/>99.2 <lb/>Holladay 1 <lb/>0.00 0.36 -1.31 0.81 0.28 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>50.0 <lb/>85.2 <lb/>96.9 <lb/>99.2 <lb/>Kane <lb/>0.00 0.36 -1.12 0.85 0.27 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>53.1 <lb/>85.9 <lb/>96.1 <lb/>99.2 <lb/>Ladas super <lb/>0.01 0.35 -1.20 0.99 0.28 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>51.6 <lb/>85.9 <lb/>97.7 <lb/>99.2 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>0.01 0.41 -1.37 1.08 0.32 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>43.8 <lb/>78.9 <lb/>93.0 <lb/>98.4 <lb/>T2 <lb/>0.01 0.36 -1.30 0.90 0.28 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>52.3 <lb/>85.2 <lb/>96.9 <lb/>99.2 <lb/>High-toricity group <lb/>BU II <lb/>-0.08 0.34 -0.82 0.54 0.28 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>52.0 <lb/>84.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>EVO 2.0 <lb/>-0.08 0.34 -0.87 0.41 0.28 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>44.0 <lb/>92.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Haigis <lb/>-0.07 0.35 -0.78 0.57 0.30 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>52.0 <lb/>80.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Hoffer Q <lb/>-0.12 0.36 -0.82 0.56 0.33 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>36.0 <lb/>88.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>HQST <lb/>-0.10 0.35 -0.88 0.46 0.30 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>44.0 <lb/>88.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Holladay 1 <lb/>-0.10 0.34 -0.86 0.53 0.30 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>36.0 <lb/>84.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Kane <lb/>-0.11 0.34 -0.84 0.46 0.30 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>52.0 <lb/>84.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/></body>

			<page>1334 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 6 continued <lb/>Formula <lb/>ME <lb/>(D) <lb/>SD <lb/>(D) <lb/>Min <lb/>(D) <lb/>Max <lb/>(D) <lb/>MAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>MedAE <lb/>(D) <lb/>Percentage of eyes within different PE ranges <lb/>(%) <lb/>-0.25 D -0.50 D -0.75 D -1.00 D <lb/>Ladas super <lb/>-0.09 0.36 -0.83 0.57 0.31 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>36.0 <lb/>76.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>-0.13 0.40 -1.04 0.88 0.32 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>52.0 <lb/>80.0 <lb/>88.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>T2 <lb/>-0.11 0.36 -0.93 0.68 0.31 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>44.0 <lb/>88.0 <lb/>96.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>BU II Barrett Universal II, D diopters, EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), IOL <lb/>intraocular lens, K keratometry, MAE mean absolute error, Max maximum, MedAE median absolute error, ME mean error, <lb/>Min minimum, PE prediction error, SD standard deviation, SRK/T Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretical, T toricity <lb/>Fig. 8 Mean prediction error (ME) of each formula, <lb/>distributed by toricity (T) group. BU II Barrett Universal <lb/>II, D diopters, EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST <lb/>Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), SRK/T Sanders-Ret-<lb/>zlaff-Kraff/theoretica <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<page>1335 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the shallow ACD group, the formulas who <lb/>had a ME significantly different from zero were <lb/>the Hoffer Q and Holladay 1 formulas, with a <lb/>myopic shift (P = 0.001, 0.034, respectively). No <lb/>statistically significant difference existed in AE <lb/>among formulas. The EVO2.0 formula had the <lb/>highest percentage of eyes within ± 0.50 D <lb/>and ± 1.00 D of the target refraction (92.5% <lb/>and 100.0%, respectively) (P = 0.004 and 0.019, <lb/>respectively). <lb/>In the regular ACD group, the formulas who <lb/>had a ME significantly different from zero were <lb/>the Hoffer Q, HQST, Holladay 1, Kane and T2 <lb/>formulas, with a hyperopic shift (P = 0.003, <lb/>0.039, 0.026, 0.026, and 0.021, respectively). No <lb/>statistically significant difference existed in AE <lb/>among formulas. Both the EVO2.0 and Ladas <lb/>super formulas had the highest percentage of <lb/>eyes within ± 0.75 D of the target refraction <lb/>(98.6% and 98.6%, respectively) (P = 0.005 and <lb/>0.004, respectively). <lb/>Fig. 9 Median absolute error (MedAE) plotted against <lb/>toricity (T) groups for each formula. BU II Barrett <lb/>Universal II, EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST <lb/>Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni), MedAE median absolute <lb/>error, SRK/T Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/theoretica <lb/></body>

			<page>1336 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 10 Stacked bars comparing the percentage of cases <lb/>within a given diopter (D) range of predicted spherical <lb/>equivalent (SE) refraction outcome of each subgroup of <lb/>toricity (T). A Low-toricity group, B Medium-toricity <lb/>group, C High-toricity group. BU II Barrett Universal II, <lb/>EVO Emmetropia Verifying Optical, HQST Hoffer QST <lb/>(Savini/Taroni), <lb/>SRK/T <lb/>Sanders-Retzlaff-Kraff/ <lb/>theoretica <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<page>1337 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the deep ACD group, the formulas who <lb/>had a ME significantly different from zero were <lb/>the Ladas super formula, with a myopic shift <lb/>(P = 0.038). No statistically significant differ-<lb/>ence existed in AE as well as the percentage of <lb/>eyes <lb/>within ± 0.25 D, ± 0.50 D, ± 0.75 D, <lb/>and ± 1.00 D among formulas. <lb/>Subgroup Analysis with K <lb/>Table 5 and Figs. 5, 6 and 7 summarizes the <lb/>MEs, SDs, Mins, Maxs, MAEs and MedAEs for <lb/>the ten IOL formulas in K subgroups, as well as <lb/>the percentage of eyes within ± 0.25 D, ± 0.50 <lb/>D, ± 0.75 D, and ± 1.00 D for each formula. <lb/>In the flat K group, the formulas who had a <lb/>ME significantly different from zero were the BU <lb/>II and SRK/T formulas, with a hyperopic shift <lb/>(P = 0.037, 0.000, respectively). The EVO2.0 <lb/>formula was the most accurate (P = 0.024), <lb/>which also had the highest percentage of eyes <lb/>within ± 0.75 D of the target refraction <lb/>(100.0%) (P = 0.010). <lb/>In the regular K group, there was no signifi-<lb/>cant difference between ME and zero in any <lb/>formula. No statistically significant difference <lb/>existed in AE as well as the percentage of eyes <lb/>within ± 0.25 D, ± 0.50 D, ± 0.75 D, <lb/>and ± 1.00 D among formulas. <lb/>In the steep K group, the formulas who had a <lb/>ME significantly different from zero were the BU <lb/>II, EVO2.0, SRK/T and T2 formulas, with a <lb/>myopic shift (P = 0.023, 0.041, 0.000, 0.045, <lb/>respectively). No statistically significant differ-<lb/>ence existed in AE as well as the percentage of <lb/>eyes <lb/>within ± 0.25 D, ± 0.50 D, ± 0.75 D, <lb/>and ± 1.00 D among formulas. <lb/>Subgroup Analysis with T <lb/>Table 6 and Figs. 8, 9 and 10 summarizes the <lb/>MEs, SDs, Mins, Maxs, MAEs and MedAEs for <lb/>the ten IOL formulas in T subgroups, as well as <lb/>the percentage of eyes within ± 0.25 D, ± 0.50 <lb/>D, ± 0.75 D, and ± 1.00 D for each formula. <lb/>In the low-toricity group, there was no sig-<lb/>nificant difference between ME and zero in any <lb/>formula. The EVO2.0 and Ladas super formulas <lb/>both had the highest percentages of eyes <lb/>within ± 0.75 D of the target refraction (96.3% <lb/>and 96.3%, respectively) (P = 0.023, 0.023, <lb/>respectively). <lb/>In the medium-toricity group, there was no <lb/>significant difference between ME and zero in <lb/>any formula. The Kane and HQST formulas were <lb/>the most accurate formulas (P = 0.013 and <lb/>0.023, respectively). The EVO2.0 (99.2%) for-<lb/>mula performed the highest percentage of eyes <lb/>within ± 0.75 D (P = 0.006). <lb/>In the high-toricity group, there was no sig-<lb/>nificant difference between ME and zero in any <lb/>formula. No statistically significant difference <lb/>existed in AE as well as the percentage of eyes <lb/>within ± 0.25 D, ± 0.50 D, ± 0.75 D, <lb/>and ± 1.00 D among formulas. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>In this study, we assessed the precision of <lb/>diverse formulas in calculating the SE of toric <lb/>IOLs. Our findings indicated that the Kane and <lb/>EVO2.0 formulations exhibited superior out-<lb/>comes. Notably, the EVO2.0 formula performed <lb/>well across various ACD, K, and T subgroups. <lb/>The Ladas super formula provided additional <lb/>benefits within the normal ACD group. <lb/>Numerous scholars have emphasized the <lb/>superiority of new-generation formulas over <lb/>Gaussian optics-based standard formulas in <lb/>predicting SE for non-toric IOLs [8]. Pereira et al. <lb/>[21] asserted that the Kane, BU II, EVO, T2, and <lb/>Ladas Super formulas were the most accurate <lb/>preoperative refractive calculations for the <lb/>overall cohort. In two large studies, Darcy et al. <lb/>[7] and Melles et al. [8] concluded that the Kane <lb/>formula performed the highest accuracy overall. <lb/>Moreover, Cheng et al. [22] discovered that the <lb/>EVO2.0 formula significantly further enhanced <lb/>the accuracy compared to the previous version. <lb/>It is noteworthy that a formula exhibiting high <lb/>accuracy in predicting SE for non-toric IOLs <lb/>may not be equally effective for toric IOLs. <lb/>Given the distinct degrees on the two meridians <lb/>of toric IOLs, the effective lens position (ELP)-<lb/>related refractive effect for toric IOLs may differ <lb/>from that of non-toric IOLs. As a result, for-<lb/>mulas may inaccurately predict the ELP for toric <lb/>IOLs, consequently affecting the overall SE <lb/></body>

			<page>1338 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<body>outcome. Consequently, we selected a specific <lb/>cohort of eyes implanted with toric IOLs to <lb/>assess the predictive accuracy of both new-<lb/>generation formulas and the standard formulas <lb/>based on Gaussian optics, along with their <lb/>improved version, in estimating SE in this <lb/>investigation. <lb/>The Kane formula used multiple extensive <lb/>datasets compiled by skilled high-volume sur-<lb/>geons, employing a blend of theoretical optics, <lb/>regression analysis, and artificial intelligence <lb/>(AI) components to make its predictions. An <lb/>interesting facet of this calculation is the inte-<lb/>gration of patient sex as a variable into the <lb/>equation [23]. Kane et al. [24] contended that <lb/>the predictive efficacy of the Kane toric formula <lb/>for astigmatism surpassed that of the Abulafia-<lb/>Koch, Barrett, and EVO2.0 toric formulas. Our <lb/>current findings further affirmed the Kane for-<lb/>mula&apos;s precision in predicting SE of toric IOL. <lb/>Our study also found that the EVO2.0 formula <lb/>also displayed a promising algorithm. Remark-<lb/>ably, it even had a higher percentage of eyes <lb/>within ± 0.50 D, ± 0.75 D, and ± 1.00 D com-<lb/>pared to the Kane formula, a phenomenon <lb/>possibly linked to its emmetropization theory <lb/>[25]. As a novel thick-lens formula, it calculates <lb/>an &apos;&apos;emmetropia factor&apos;&apos; for each eye. Simulta-<lb/>neously, this formula considers both the optical <lb/>dimensions of the eye and diverse IOL geome-<lb/>tries [22]. <lb/>Furthermore, our study also included an <lb/>examination of three improved IOL calculation <lb/>formulas -the Ladas Super, T2, and HQST for-<lb/>mulas. The Ladas Super Formula integrates <lb/>optimal components from the Hoffer Q, Holla-<lb/>day 1, Holladay 1 with Koch adjustment, and <lb/>SRK/T formulas, employing a three-dimensional <lb/>model to select the most suitable formula [14]. <lb/>Additionally, this formula was revised in 2019 <lb/>based on the postoperative data from over 4000 <lb/>eyes and is now based on AI [26]. In our study, <lb/>the Ladas Super Formula exhibited a signifi-<lb/>cantly better performance than the SRK/T for-<lb/>mula in the percentage of eyes within ± 0.75 D. <lb/>The T2 formula, replacing the corneal height <lb/>estimation steps in the SRK/T formula with a <lb/>regression formula derived from extensive <lb/>patient data [11], performed better than the <lb/>SRK/T formula in our cohort. The HQST <lb/>formula, retaining the Gaussian optic architec-<lb/>ture while incorporating AI for enhanced ELP <lb/>prediction and adjustments for eyes with <lb/>AL [ 25 mm, [12] demonstrated improved out-<lb/>comes compared to the Hoffer Q formula. <lb/>Despite these advancements, these three for-<lb/>mulas still fell short of the predictive accuracy <lb/>achieved by the Kane and EVO2.0 formulas, <lb/>implying a potential need for enhancing. <lb/>In each of the ACD subgroups, the EVO2.0 <lb/>formula provided outstanding outcomes, and <lb/>the Ladas super formula also yielded good <lb/>results in the regular ACD group. Hipo ´lito-Fer-<lb/>nandes et al. [27] investigated the impact of <lb/>ACD in patients with normal ALs, concluding <lb/>that the PEARL-DGS, Kane, EVO2.0, and BU II <lb/>formulas were more accurate in the shallow <lb/>ACD group. Although no significant differences <lb/>were found with other formulas in our study, <lb/>the EVO2.0 formula consistently once again <lb/>showed a good predictive effect. In terms of ME, <lb/>both the Hoffer Q and Holladay 1 formulas <lb/>revealed myopic shifts in the shallow ACD <lb/>group because of the absence of ACD [3, 5], <lb/>which was similar to the other studies which <lb/>implanted non-toric IOLs [19, 28]. Moreover, <lb/>we discovered that the Ladas super formula <lb/>yielded myopic outcomes in the deep ACD <lb/>group, and the Hoffer Q, HQST, Holladay 1, <lb/>Kane, and T2 formulas resulted a hyperopic <lb/>outcome in the regular ACD group, suggesting <lb/>that there is room for improvement for these <lb/>formula. <lb/>In the analysis of K subgroups, the EVO2.0 <lb/>formula emerged as the most effective in the flat <lb/>K group. It is hard to discuss the specific factors <lb/>contributing to its outstanding performance, as <lb/>it has not been published; nevertheless, it still <lb/>merits further attention. Besides, the BU II for-<lb/>mula&apos;s poor result is challenging to interpret <lb/>due to its unknown principle, also possibly <lb/>influenced by the small sample size in this <lb/>subgroup, while the result of the SRK/T formula <lb/>is easy to explain because of &apos;&apos;cusp phe-<lb/>nomenon&apos;&apos; previously identified by scholars <lb/>[29]. Reitblat et al. [29] reported myopic MEs for <lb/>all formulas except the Haigis, Olsen, and Hof-<lb/>fer Q formulas. This aligned with our findings, <lb/>indicating suboptimal prediction accuracy for <lb/>each formula in the steep K group. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

			<page>1339 <lb/></page>

			<body>Additionally, we also investigated the SE <lb/>predictive accuracy of each formula for toric <lb/>IOL across various T subgroups. The EVO2.0 and <lb/>Ladas super formulas demonstrated high per-<lb/>formance in the low-toricity group, whereas the <lb/>Kane, HQST, and EVO2.0 formulas performed <lb/>well in the medium-toricity group. This <lb/>revealed the superior predictability of new-<lb/>generation and enhanced formulas in diverse T <lb/>subgroups compared to traditional third-gener-<lb/>ation formulas. <lb/>We acknowledge certain limitations in our <lb/>study. While our sample size calculation <lb/>deemed it sufficiently large to detect significant <lb/>differences in the overall MedAE, larger-scale <lb/>studies can offer more substantial insights in <lb/>subgroup analyses. In addition, the absence of <lb/>lens thickness, central corneal thickness, and <lb/>white-to-white measurements restricted our <lb/>ability to draw comprehensive conclusions <lb/>regarding the comparison between formulas <lb/>and the application of some specific formulas. It <lb/>is worth noting that these additional variables <lb/>are optional in the aforementioned formulas, <lb/>with none being mandatory. However, the <lb/>fundamental requirements for IOL power cal-<lb/>culation were fulfilled through the measure-<lb/>ment of AL, ACD, and K [7, 21]. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>In summary, our findings indicated that the <lb/>new-generation formulas, particularly the Kane <lb/>and EVO2.0 formulas, have better performances <lb/>in predicting SE for toric IOL in patients with <lb/>normal ALs, and the EVO2.0 formula provided <lb/>more accurate outcomes across various <lb/>subgroups. <lb/></body>
				
            <div type="annex">Medical Writing, Editorial, and Other <lb/>Assistance Hengli Lian, PhD, provided statisti-<lb/>cal assistance. Ruoqian Zhang, BD, provided <lb/>coding assistance. <lb/>Authorship All named authors meet the <lb/>International Committee of Medical Journal <lb/>Editors (ICMJE) criteria for authorship for this <lb/>article, take responsibility for the integrity of <lb/>the work as a whole, and have given their <lb/>approval for this version to be published. <lb/></div>
				
            <div type="contribution">Author Contributions. Jingyi Shi: concept <lb/>and design, data analysis, manuscript drafting, <lb/>and statistical analysis; Zehui Zhu: concept and <lb/>design, data analysis; Bin Hu: data acquisition; <lb/>Shuyi Qian: data acquisition; Yalan Wang: data <lb/>analysis; Pingjun Chang: concept and design, <lb/>clinical revision; Yun-e Zhao: clinical revision, <lb/>supervision, and final approval. All the authors <lb/>have read and approved the final version of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>
	  
	  <div type="funding">Funding. This study and the journal&apos;s <lb/>Rapid Service Fee was supported by the &apos;&apos;Pio-<lb/>neer&apos;&apos; and &apos;&apos;Leading Goose&apos;&apos; R&amp;D Program of <lb/>Zhejiang (Grant No. 2022C03070). <lb/></div>
		  
      <div type="availability">Data Availability. The datasets generated <lb/>and/or analyzed in the current study are avail-<lb/>able from the corresponding author upon rea-<lb/>sonable request. <lb/></div>
	  
	  <div type="annex">Declarations <lb/></div>
	  
	  <div type="conflict">Conflict of interest. Jingyi Shi, Zehui Zhu, <lb/>Bin Hu, Shuyi Qian, Yalan Wang, Pingjun <lb/>Chang, Yun-e Zhao declare no competing <lb/>interests. <lb/></div>
	  
	  <div type="annex">Ethical approval. This study was per-<lb/>formed in accordance with the Declaration of <lb/>Helsinki of 1964 and its subsequent amend-<lb/>ments. This study was approved by the Ethics <lb/>Committee of Wenzhou Medical University <lb/>(2021-036-K-29-01). <lb/></div>

      <front>Open Access. This article is licensed under <lb/>a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCom-<lb/>mercial 4.0 International License, which per-<lb/>mits any non-commercial use, sharing, <lb/>adaptation, distribution and reproduction in <lb/>any medium or format, as long as you give <lb/>appropriate credit to the original author(s) and <lb/>the source, provide a link to the Creative <lb/>Commons licence, and indicate if changes were <lb/>made. The images or other third party material <lb/>in this article are included in the article&apos;s <lb/>Creative Commons licence, unless indicated <lb/>otherwise in a credit line to the material. If <lb/>material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative <lb/>Commons licence and your intended use is not <lb/>permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the <lb/></front>

        <page>1340 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

        <front>permitted use, you will need to obtain permis-<lb/>sion directly from the copyright holder. To view <lb/>a copy of this licence, visit http:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/. <lb/></front>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Barrett GD. Barrett Universal II formula. Accessed <lb/>February 14, 2024. https://calc.apacrs.org/barrett_ <lb/>universal2105/Default.aspx. <lb/>2. Haigis W, Lege B, Miller N, Schneider B. Compar-<lb/>ison of immersion ultrasound biometry and partial <lb/>coherence interferometry for intraocular lens cal-<lb/>culation according to Haigis. Graefes Arch Clin Exp <lb/>Ophthalmol. 2000;238:765-73. <lb/>3. Holladay J, Prager T, Chandler T, Musgrove K, Lewis <lb/>J, Ruiz R. A three-part system for refining intraoc-<lb/>ular lens power calculations. J Cataract Refract Surg. <lb/>1988;14:17-24. <lb/>4. Retzlaff J, Sanders D, Kraff M. Development of the <lb/>SRK/T intraocular lens implant power calculation <lb/>formula. J Cataract Refract Surg. 1990;16:333-40. <lb/>5. Hoffer K. The Hoffer Q formula: a comparison of <lb/>theoretic and regression formulas. J Cataract Refract <lb/>Surg. 1993;19:700-12. <lb/>6. Kane JX. Kane formula. https://www.iolformula. <lb/>com. Accessed 14 Feb 2024. <lb/>7. Darcy K, Gunn D, Tavassoli S, Sparrow J, Kane J. <lb/>Assessment of the accuracy of new and updated <lb/>intraocular lens power calculation formulas in 10 <lb/>930 eyes from the UK National Health Service. <lb/>J Cataract Refract Surg. 2020;46:2-7. <lb/>8. Melles R, Kane J, Olsen T, Chang W. Update on <lb/>intraocular lens calculation formulas. Ophthal-<lb/>mology. 2019;126:1334-5. <lb/>9. Yeo TK. Emmetropia verifying optical (EVO) 2.0 <lb/>formula. http://www.evoiolcalculator.com. Acces-<lb/>sed 14 Feb 2024. <lb/>10. Hipo ´lito-Fernandes D, Elisa Luı ´s M, Gil P, et al. VRF-<lb/>G, a new intraocular lens power calculation for-<lb/>mula: a 13-formulas comparison study. Clin Oph-<lb/>thalmol (Auckland, NZ). 2020;14:4395-402. <lb/>11. Sheard R, Smith G, Cooke D. Improving the pre-<lb/>diction accuracy of the SRK/T formula: the T2 for-<lb/>mula. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2010;36:1829-34. <lb/>12. Taroni L, Hoffer K, Pellegrini M, Lupardi E, Savini <lb/>G. Comparison of the new Hoffer QST with 4 <lb/>modern accurate formulas. J Cataract Refract Surg. <lb/>2023;49:378-84. <lb/>13. Taroni L, Savini G. Hoffer QST (Savini/Taroni) <lb/>(HQST) formula. https://hofferqst.com/. Accessed <lb/>14 Feb 2024. <lb/>14. Ladas J, Siddiqui A, Devgan U, Jun A. A 3-D &apos;&apos;super <lb/>surface&apos;&apos; combining modern intraocular lens for-<lb/>mulas to generate a &apos;&apos;super formula&apos;&apos; and maximize <lb/>accuracy. JAMA Ophthalmol. 2015;133:1431-6. <lb/>15. Ladas JG. Ladas super formula. https://iolcalc.com/ <lb/>home. Accessed 14 Feb 2024. <lb/>16. Hoffer K, Savini G. Update on intraocular lens <lb/>power calculation study protocols: the better way to <lb/>design and report clinical trials. Ophthalmology. <lb/>2021;128:e115-20. <lb/>17. Hoffer K, Aramberri J, Haigis W, et al. Protocols for <lb/>studies of intraocular lens formula accuracy. Am J <lb/>Ophthalmol. 2015;160:403-405.e1. <lb/>18. Wang L, Koch D, Hill W, Abulafia A. Pursuing per-<lb/>fection in intraocular lens calculations: III. Criteria <lb/>for analyzing outcomes. J Cataract Refract Surg. <lb/>2017;43:999-1002. <lb/>19. Melles R, Holladay J, Chang W. Accuracy of <lb/>intraocular lens calculation formulas. Ophthal-<lb/>mology. 2018;125:169-78. <lb/>20. User Group for Laser Interference Biometry (ULIB). <lb/>http://ocusoft.de/ulib. Accessed 14 Feb 2024. <lb/>21. Pereira A, Popovic M, Ahmed Y, et al. A compara-<lb/>tive analysis of 12 intraocular lens power formulas. <lb/>Int Ophthalmol. 2021;41:4137-50. <lb/>22. Cheng H, Kane J, Liu L, Li J, Cheng B, Wu M. <lb/>Refractive predictability using the IOLMaster 700 <lb/>and artificial intelligence-based IOL power formulas <lb/>compared to standard formulas. J Refract Surg. <lb/>2020;36:466-72. <lb/>23. Connell B, Kane J. Comparison of the Kane formula <lb/>with existing formulas for intraocular lens power <lb/>selection. BMJ Open Ophthalmol. 2019;4: e000251. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjophth-2018-000251. <lb/>24. Pantanelli S, Sun A, Kansara N, Smits G. Compar-<lb/>ison of Barrett and emmetropia verifying optical <lb/>toric calculators. Clin Ophthalmol (Auckland, NZ). <lb/>2022;16:177-82. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 <lb/></note>

        <page>1341 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>25. Chen Y, Wei L, He W, Lu Y, Zhu X. Comparison of <lb/>Kane, Hill-RBF 2.0, Barrett Universal II, and <lb/>emmetropia verifying optical formulas in eyes with <lb/>extreme myopia. J Refract Surg. 2021;37:680-5. <lb/>26. Kothari S, Reddy J. Recent developments in the <lb/>intraocular lens formulae: an update. Semin Oph-<lb/>thalmol. 2023;38:143-50. <lb/>27. Hipo ´lito-Fernandes D, Luı ´s M, Serras-Pereira R, et al. <lb/>Anterior chamber depth, lens thickness and <lb/>intraocular lens calculation formula accuracy: nine <lb/>formulas comparison. Br J Ophthalmol. 2022;106: <lb/>349-55. <lb/>28. Eom Y, Kang S, Song J, Kim Y, Kim H. Comparison <lb/>of Hoffer Q and Haigis formulae for intraocular lens <lb/>power calculation according to the anterior cham-<lb/>ber depth in short eyes. Am J Ophthalmol. <lb/>2014;157:818-824.e2. <lb/>29. Reitblat O, Levy A, Kleinmann G, Lerman T, Assia E. <lb/>Intraocular lens power calculation for eyes with <lb/>high and low average keratometry readings: com-<lb/>parison between various formulas. J Cataract <lb/>Refract Surg. 2017;43:1149-56. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>1342 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Ophthalmol Ther (2024) 13:1321-1342 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>