<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Escherichia coli YmdB regulates biofilm formation <lb/>independently of its role as an RNase III <lb/>modulator <lb/>Taeyeon Kim 1 † , Juyeon Lee 1,2 † and Kwang-sun Kim 1,3* <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: Ribonuclease III (RNase III) activity modulates hundreds of genes in Escherichia coli (E. coli). YmdB, a <lb/>member of the macrodomain protein family, is one of known trans-acting regulators of RNase III activity; however, <lb/>the significance of its regulatory role in specific bacterial cellular processes and related genes has not been determined. <lb/>YmdB overexpression was used to model YmdB-induced RNase III inhibition in vivo, and microarray analysis identified <lb/>gene targets and cellular processes related to RNase III inhibition. <lb/>Results: The expression of &gt;2,000 E. coli genes was modulated by YmdB induction; 129 genes were strongly regulated, <lb/>of which 80 have not been reported as RNase III targets. Of these, ten are involved in biofilm formation. Significantly, <lb/>YmdB overexpression also inhibited biofilm formation via a process that is not uniquely dependent upon RNase III <lb/>inhibition. Moreover, biofilm formation is interdependently regulated by RpoS, a known stress response regulator and <lb/>biofilm inhibitor, and by YmdB. <lb/>Conclusions: This is the first global profile of target genes modulated by YmdB-induced RNase III inhibition in <lb/>E. coli, and the data reveal a novel, hitherto unrecognized regulatory role for YmdB in biofilm modulation. <lb/>Keywords: Ribonuclease III (RNase III), Microarray, Biofilm, Trans-acting regulator, Escherichia coli <lb/></front>

			<body>Background <lb/>RNase III family members cleave double-stranded RNAs <lb/>to yield 5′ phosphate and 3′ hydroxyl termini, and are <lb/>extensively conserved in prokaryotes and eukaryotes <lb/>[1-7]. During bacterial ribosome biogenesis, RNase III <lb/>processes the ribosomal RNA (rRNA) precursors [8], <lb/>and also mediates the maturation and/or degradation of <lb/>different types of transcripts [9], small RNAs [10,11], <lb/>and mRNAs containing rnc [12,13] or pnp genes [14]. <lb/>The structural and mechanistic features of RNase III <lb/>have been extensively studied [1-14]; however, questions <lb/>remain concerning the cellular control of RNase III <lb/>activity under different physiological conditions. <lb/>In E. coli, some proteins are known as regulators for <lb/>endo-RNase activity [15-18]. For example, RraA and <lb/>RraB negatively regulate RNase E activity [15,16]. In case <lb/>of RNase III, bacteriophage T7 protein kinase [17] and <lb/>YmdB [18] identified as an either activator or inhibitor of <lb/>RNase III function. The activation process by bacteriophage <lb/>T7 protein kinase is through binding to RNase III and <lb/>phosphorylates the enzyme on serine [17]. YmdB was <lb/>the first RNase III-binding inhibitor to be identified <lb/>in vivo using a novel genetic screening approach and, <lb/>in common with other RNase regulators, YmdB expression <lb/>is modulated by cold-or growth-stress [18]. YmdB, acting <lb/>in concert with other uncharacterized stress-mediated <lb/>trans-acting factors, facilitates the regulation of RNase III <lb/>activity under growth-[18] or osmotic stress conditions <lb/>[19]. Several protein identities are proposed for the <lb/>trans-acting inhibitor(s) and potential targets of their <lb/>inhibition has been suggested; for example, cellular <lb/>targets of RNase III activity, such as the RNase III <lb/>gene itself, rnc [12,13], pnp [14], and rRNA processing by <lb/>YmdB [18] and the level of bdm mRNA encoding a protein <lb/></body>

			<front>* Correspondence: sunny06@kribb.re.kr <lb/> † <lb/>Equal contributors <lb/>1 <lb/>Superbacteria Research Center, Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and <lb/>Biotechnology (KRIBB), 125 Gwahak-ro, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon 305-806, Korea <lb/>3 <lb/>Department of Biosystems and Bioengineering, University of Science and <lb/>Technology, 217 Gajung-ro, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon 305-350, Korea <lb/>Full list of author information is available at the end of the article <lb/>© 2013 Kim et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></front>

			<body>that promotes biofilm formation by unknown trans-acting <lb/>factor(s) [19]. The cellular processes required for RNase III <lb/>inhibition by trans-acting factor(s) during stress responses <lb/>are unclear; however, one post-transcriptional pathway <lb/>has been proposed [7], which involves the general <lb/>stress-responsive regulator, RpoS [20]. By cleaving the <lb/>rpoS mRNA 5′-leader [21], RNase III reduces RpoS <lb/>production; the presence of YmdB limits this reaction and <lb/>as a consequence, increases RpoS levels, which supports <lb/>entry into the stationary phase [7]. This hypothesis behind <lb/>this process came from a study that used an RNase III <lb/>mutant [21]; however, to clarify and identify new targets of <lb/>RNase III inhibition, it is essential to adopt a model that <lb/>mimics physiological RNase III inhibition via the induction <lb/>of trans-acting factor(s). <lb/>The present study investigated RNase III inhibition via <lb/>the ectopic expression of the regulatory protein, YmdB, <lb/>and identified novel targets of inhibition. We also explored <lb/>the mechanism(s) by which biofilm formation is regulated. <lb/>Gene expression profiling of the entire E. coli open reading <lb/>frame (ORF) following YmdB overexpression was performed <lb/>using DNA microarray analysis, and revealed that ~2,000 <lb/>transcripts were modulated. Of these, 129 genes spanning <lb/>ten cellular processes were strongly modulated by YmdB <lb/>expression. About 40 of these were similarly controlled by <lb/>RNase III, including five novel targets. Moreover, among the <lb/>YmdB-modulated genes, ten are reported to be related to <lb/>biofilm formation, the presence of which is a universal <lb/>feature of bacteria and a component of multicellular <lb/>communities [22]. Biochemical analyses indicate that <lb/>induction of YmdB strongly inhibits biofilm formation <lb/>in a manner similar to that of RpoS, which is a regulator of <lb/>general stress responses [20] and a biofilm inhibitor [23-25]. <lb/>Inhibition occurred via two mechanisms that were either <lb/>dependent or independent of RNase III activity. Genetic <lb/>studies revealed that the YmdB-and RpoS-induced decrease <lb/>in biofilm formation required RpoS and YmdB, respectively. <lb/>In conclusion, we have identified a novel role for YmdB as a <lb/>modulator of biofilm formation, and revealed how a <lb/>trans-acting factor can regulate RNase III activity, as well <lb/>as function independently to enable a rapid response to <lb/>changing cellular needs. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Bacterial strains, plasmids, primers, and growth <lb/>conditions <lb/>Details of the bacterial strains and plasmids used are <lb/>given in Additional file 1: Table S1. Primers used for <lb/>qPCR analysis and DNA sequencing were synthesized by <lb/>Bioneer (Korea) (Additional file 1: Table S2). All estab-<lb/>lished mutant strains or chromosomal lacZ fusions were <lb/>derived from E. coli BW25113. Analysis of rpoS pro-<lb/>moter activity was based on a plasmid, pKSK001, con-<lb/>taining promoter region −92 to +10 of the rpoS gene <lb/>from the E. coli K12 genome (GenBank U00096.2) sub-<lb/>cloned into the lacZ transcriptional fusion vector, <lb/>pSP417 [26], after linearization by EcoRI/BamHI. The <lb/>lacZ fusion in pKSK001 was recombined onto the <lb/>chromosome (KSK003) using the transducing λ phage <lb/>system, λRS45 [27], via a double recombination event <lb/>and was verified as previously described [18]. Strain <lb/>ΔymdB was constructed by eliminating the kana-<lb/>mycin cassette (ymdB::km R ) from Keio-ΔymdB as de-<lb/>scribed previously [28]. Verification of Keio-ΔymdB [28], <lb/>ΔymdB (KSK002), Keio-ΔrpoS [28], or rnc14•Keio-ΔrpoS <lb/>(KSK005) was carried out by colony PCR using primer <lb/>pairs ymdB-F/-R or rpoS-F/-R and Emerald PCR premix <lb/>(Takara) (Additional file 1: Figure S1), and the PCR <lb/>products were read by DNA sequencing analysis using <lb/>the same primers (data not shown). Verification of <lb/>RNase III mutation was confirmed by Western blot ana-<lb/>lysis using antibodies against RNase III (Additional file <lb/>1: Figure S1). Bacteria were grown in Luria-Bertani (LB) <lb/>broth or on LB plates at 37°C throughout this study. An-<lb/>tibiotics were used at the following concentrations: <lb/>kanamycin, 50 μg/mL; tetracycline, 10 μg/mL; and chlor-<lb/>amphenicol, 30 μg/mL. <lb/>Microarray analysis <lb/>Total RNA was extracted from IPTG (0.1 mM final con-<lb/>centration)-induced E. coli BW25113 cells (at an OD 600 <lb/>of 1.0) containing either pCA24N (−gfp) or ASKA-ymdB <lb/>(−) using an RNeasy® Kit (Qiagen) with two additional <lb/>DNase treatments. The integrity of the bacterial total RNA <lb/>was checked by an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer. The cDNA <lb/>probes were prepared by reverse transcription with random <lb/>priming of total RNA (25 μg) in the presence of aminoallyl-<lb/>dUTP for 3 h, followed by coupling of probes with Cy3 dye <lb/>(for the reference) or Cy5 dye (for the test sample) (AP Bio-<lb/>tech). The Cy3-or Cy5-labeled cDNA probes were purified, <lb/>dried, and resuspended in hybridization buffer containing <lb/>30% formamide, 5× SSC, 0.1% SDS, and 0.1 mg/mL salmon <lb/>sperm DNA. The cDNA probes were mixed together and <lb/>hybridized to customized microarray slides (E. coli K12 3 × <lb/>15 K microarray; www.Mycroarray.com). The image of the <lb/>slide was scanned with a GenePix 4000B (Axon Instru-<lb/>ments, USA) and analyzed by GenePix Pro 3.0 software <lb/>(Axon Instruments) to obtain the gene expression ratios <lb/>(reference vs. test sample). Microarray data analysis was <lb/>performed using Genowiz 4.0™ (Ocimum Biosolutions). <lb/>Global lowess (Locally weighted scatter plot smoothing) <lb/>method was used for data normalization. The cut-off values <lb/>for up-or down-regulated genes in duplicate hybridizations <lb/>were 1.5-or 0.6-fold, respectively. <lb/>RT-qPCR analysis <lb/>The E. coli strains listed in Additional file 1: Table S1 <lb/>were grown in LB medium to an OD 600 of 1.0, and the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>total RNA was extracted using an RNeasy Mini Kit <lb/>(Qiagen). Reverse transcription and qPCR (RT-qPCR) <lb/>analyses were performed using CFX96 (Bio-Rad) with <lb/>IQ™ SYBR® Green Supermix (Bio-Rad), as described <lb/>previously [29] and gene specific primers designed <lb/>by PrimerQuest (www.idtdna.com; Additional file 1: <lb/>Table S2). Primer-dimer and self-complementary forma-<lb/>tions were checked by melting curve analysis (CFX man-<lb/>ager v3.0; Bio-Rad). The 16S rRNA primers were used <lb/>for normalization [29]. <lb/>Crystal violet biofilm assay <lb/>The assay was adapted from Nakao et al. [30] with <lb/>the following modifications: E. coli were grown in LB broth <lb/>for 16 h at 37°C and diluted to 5 × 10 6 CFU/mL in fresh LB <lb/>broth with or without IPTG. Aliquots (800 μL) dis-<lb/>pensed into polystyrene tubes (Falcon 352058, BD <lb/>Biosciences) and incubated for 24 h at 37°C without <lb/>shaking. Each data point represents the mean ± standard <lb/>deviation of ten independent cultures. <lb/>β-galactosidase activity assays <lb/>The β-galactosidase activity from whole cells of <lb/>KSK003 (λrpoS&apos;-&apos;lacZ), KSK004 [SG30013 (λRpoS750:: <lb/>LacZ)] [31], RS8872 (λpnp&apos;-&apos;lacZ in rnc+) [32], or RS8942 <lb/>(λpnp&apos;-&apos;lacZ in rnc14) [32] overexpressing YmdB from <lb/>ASKA-ymdB (−) was determined as described by Miller <lb/>[33]. The results are expressed as the means of three inde-<lb/>pendent experiments. <lb/>Protein gel electrophoresis and Western blot analysis <lb/>Overexpression of the YmdB and RpoS proteins was <lb/>detected on Coomassie blue-stained 12% Mini-<lb/>PROTEAN TGX Precast gels (Bio-Rad). Western <lb/>blots for RNase III, YmdB, RpoS, or 6x Histidine-<lb/>tagged YmdB were prepared as described [18], probed <lb/>with antibodies (1:2,500 dilution) against YmdB, <lb/>RNase III [18], RpoS (1RS1: Santa Cruz Biotechnol-<lb/>ogy), or 6x Histidine-tagged YmdB (6xHis Epitope <lb/>Tag Antibody: Thermo Scientific) and developed with <lb/>Clarity™ western ECL substrate (Bio-Rad). To normalize the <lb/>signals, antibodies against S1 protein [34] was used as a <lb/>reference probe (1:100,000 dilution). Anti-rabbit IgG: <lb/>HRP or anti-mouse IgG:HRP conjugates (Promega; 1:5000 <lb/>dilution) were used for YmdB/RNase III/S1 proteins or <lb/>RpoS/6xHistidine tagged YmdB, respectively. Specific pro-<lb/>teins were imaged using MyECL and quantified with <lb/>myImage Analysis software (Thermo Scientific). <lb/>Results <lb/>Analysis of the E. coli transcriptome under conditions <lb/>mimicking those of an RNase III mutant <lb/>To identify which pathways and related genes are me-<lb/>diated by YmdB-modulated RNase III inhibition, a <lb/>genome-wide analysis of mRNA abundance at single <lb/>gene resolution was performed. In these experiments, <lb/>total steady-state RNA extracted from IPTG-induced <lb/>exponentially grown cells expressing either ASKA-<lb/>ymdB (a part of the ASKA (−) library: a complete set <lb/>of cloned individual E. coli genes encoding proteins <lb/>with 6x histidines at the N-terminal end and no GFP <lb/>fusion at the C-terminal end [35]); or pCA24N (a <lb/>control vector without GFP at the C-terminal end) <lb/>[29] were analyzed on customized ORF microarray <lb/>chips. Duplicate arrays were performed with biological rep-<lb/>licates to minimize experimental artifacts, and the gene ex-<lb/>pression profiles of 4,289 genes were averaged and <lb/>analyzed. YmdB overexpression modulated the relative <lb/>abundance of more than 2,000 transcripts (data not shown). <lb/>Of these, 129 genes were strongly regulated (changes in ex-<lb/>pression of either &gt;1.5 or &lt;0.6 fold) (Additional file 1: <lb/>Table S3). YmdB was previously identified as an RNase III <lb/>regulator [18]; thus, we examined the number of YmdB-<lb/>modulated genes that were related to the down-regulation <lb/>of RNase III activity to identify RNase III/YmdB-regulatory <lb/>genes. The microarray data related to YmdB overexpression <lb/>were compared with the tiling array data for an RNase III <lb/>mutant [36], in which 592 genes were affected by the <lb/>absence of RNase III. Of 127 coding genes from the <lb/>tiling array data, 47 are known RNase III targets and, <lb/>of these, 37 were similarly regulated by YmdB and the <lb/>RNase III mutant (Additional file 1: Table S3). This sug-<lb/>gests that YmdB modulates these genes by down-<lb/>regulating RNase III activity. However, 80 genes that <lb/>were not previously regarded as RNase III targets also <lb/>appeared to be modulated via an as yet uncharacterized <lb/>YmdB function(s). When the 80 genes were classified ac-<lb/>cording to the biological process in which they are in-<lb/>volved, we identified ten different cellular processes that <lb/>were modulated by YmdB induction (Table 1). Therefore, <lb/>the data indicate that YmdB, either as an RNase III regula-<lb/>tor or by itself, participates in the regulation of multiple <lb/>cellular processes within E. coli. <lb/>Identification of new RNase III targets regulated by YmdB <lb/>Using the results shown in Additional file 1: Table S3, <lb/>genes that showed the highest changes in expression <lb/>(&gt;2-fold change) were selected for quantification by real-<lb/>time quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR). These genes com-<lb/>prised confirmed (mltD, pnp, plsX, and ahpF) [14,36] <lb/>and unconfirmed (pspA, pspB, pspC, pspD, and ahpC) <lb/>RNase III targets. For all known RNase III-target genes, <lb/>increased expression was observed in the RNase III <lb/>mutant (rnc14), which correlated with the YmdB <lb/>overexpression data (Table 2). Moreover, gene expres-<lb/>sion decreased or remained at the same level in a ymdB <lb/>knockout strain in which RNase III activity was upregulated, <lb/>suggesting that YmdB-mediated inhibition of RNase III <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>activity is not involved in the regulation of genes of previ-<lb/>ously known to be RNase III targets. The abundance of <lb/>mRNAs for the unconfirmed RNase III target genes was <lb/>measured in the RNase III mutant and then <lb/>compared with the data regarding YmdB overexpres-<lb/>sion (Table 2). From five genes, the expression of the <lb/>pspB, pspC, and ahpC genes was slightly increased <lb/>upon both YmdB overexpression and RNase III <lb/>Table 1 Classification of up-or down-regulated 80 genes when YmdB was overexpressed <lb/>Functions <lb/>Gene <lb/>No. of gene <lb/>Go term ID <lb/>Transport <lb/>dppA, emrA, exbB, exuT, fdx, fecI, gutM, icd, mntH, nrfA 2 , proP, srlA 2 , srlB 2 , srlE 2 , <lb/>srlR, sucA 2 , sucC 2 , sucD 2 , tdcC, tolB, tolR, yhbE, ynfM <lb/>23 <lb/>GO:0006810 <lb/>GO:0006811 <lb/>GO:0006855 <lb/>GO:0006865 <lb/>GO:0006099 <lb/>GO:0009401 <lb/>GO:0015031 <lb/>GO:0015992 <lb/>GO:0017038 <lb/>GO:0022900 <lb/>GO:0043213 <lb/>GO:0055085 <lb/>Transcription/replication <lb/>cspB, cspG, fecI, gutM, lacI, mprA, mukF, mqsR 3 , pspB 1,2 , pspC 1,3 , relE 3 , rpoA, rpoB, <lb/>rpoC, rplD, rpoE 3 , rseB, srlR, yoeB, ygiT 3 <lb/>20 <lb/>GO:0006260 <lb/>GO:0006351 <lb/>GO:0006352 <lb/>GO:0006355 <lb/>GO:0045892 <lb/>GO:0055072 <lb/>Cellular responses <lb/>cspB, cspG, emrA, mprA, nusA, pspB 1,3 , pspC 1,3 , pspD 1,3 , <lb/>13 <lb/>GO:0006950 <lb/>GO:0009266 <lb/>GO:0009271 <lb/>relE 3 , rplD, rpoE 3 , rseA 3 , sseA <lb/>GO:0009408 <lb/>GO:0009409 <lb/>GO:0046677 <lb/>Modification <lb/>csdA, iscA, iscU, mqsR 3 , pheT, <lb/>11 <lb/>GO:0006432 <lb/>GO:0016226 <lb/>relE 3 , srlB 2 , srlE 2 <lb/>GO:0016310 <lb/>GO:0090305 <lb/>ydaL 3 , yfhJ, ygdK <lb/>Translation <lb/>mqsR 3 , pheT, rplC, rplD, rpsA, rpsJ, yhbC, relE 3 <lb/>8 <lb/>GO:0006412 <lb/>GO:0017148 <lb/>Metabolic process <lb/>fabD, lacI, srlA 2 , srlB 2 , srlD 2 , srlE 2 , sucA 2 , ycjM <lb/>8 <lb/>GO:0008152 <lb/>Oxidation-reduction <lb/>ahpC 3 , nrfA 2 , srlD 2 , sucA 2 , torZ, ygjR <lb/>6 <lb/>GO:0055114 <lb/>Biosynthesis <lb/>fabD <lb/>1 <lb/>GO:0006633 <lb/>GO:0006654 <lb/>GO:0008610 <lb/>Cell cycle <lb/>mukF <lb/>1 <lb/>GO:0007049 <lb/>GO:0051301 <lb/>Nucleotide binding <lb/>yeeZ 3 <lb/>1 <lb/>GO:0000166 <lb/>GO:0005524 <lb/>Genes 1 up-(&gt;3-fold) or 2 down-(&lt;0.5-fold) regulated by YmdB overexpression were indicated. Detailed quantitative data are shown in Additional file 1: Table S3. <lb/>3 <lb/>Gene is related to biofilm formation in literature, even though GO term analysis (www.ecocyc.org) did not classify it as such. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>knockout, further indicating that these genes might <lb/>be new RNase III targets regulated by YmdB. <lb/>Identification of YmdB as a protein that inhibits biofilm <lb/>formation <lb/>The results obtained thus far suggest a role for YmdB in <lb/>biofilm synthesis. Ten genes related to biofilm formation <lb/>[37-40] were modulated by YmdB overexpression <lb/>(Table 1); in particular, genes induced within the biofilm <lb/>were strongly upregulated, including rpoE [41] and <lb/>pspABCDE [41,42]. Additionally, rpoS and bdm, both <lb/>known targets of RNase III and related to either the <lb/>down-or up-regulation of biofilm formation [19,21,36], <lb/>were upregulated (by ~1.5-and 1.8-fold, respectively). <lb/>To investigate this further, biofilm formation by <lb/>BW25113 cells containing either pCA24N (−gfp) or <lb/>ASKA-ymdB (−) was measured after 24 h of growth <lb/>without agitation in LB containing different concentra-<lb/>tions of IPTG (0 to 0.1 mM). Compared with cells har-<lb/>boring the control vector, increased expression of YmdB <lb/>inhibited biofilm formation by up to 80% in the presence <lb/>or absence of IPTG (Figure 1A). The effect was linearly <lb/>correlated with IPTG concentration (10 -6 to 10 -1 mM), <lb/>with no further reduction observed above 1 mM IPTG <lb/>(data not shown). The physiological relevance of this in-<lb/>hibitory effect of YmdB is shown in Figure 1B. The total <lb/>relative level of YmdB protein was assessed by Western <lb/>Blotting [18] and was found to increase by 2.2-to 5.7-<lb/>fold in the presence of increasing concentrations of <lb/>IPTG (Figure 1B) (increased YmdB expression in the ab-<lb/>sence of IPTG results from the leaky lac promoter in <lb/>the ASKA plasmids) [35]. The changes in YmdB levels <lb/>are similar to those observed in vivo following growth-<lb/>or cold-stress (2-to 8-fold) [18] and are thus physiolo-<lb/>gically relevant. <lb/>RNase III does not affect biofilm inhibition by YmdB <lb/>The YmdB protein regulates RNase III activity through <lb/>the formation through the proposed formation of an <lb/>RNase III/YmdB heterocomplex [18]; hence, it was im-<lb/>portant to clarify whether the biofilm phenotype mediated by <lb/>ectopic expression of YmdB is similar to that mediated by <lb/>RNase III inhibition. Biofilm formation in the absence of <lb/>RNase III (rnc14) increased by ~52% (Figure 2A), implying <lb/>that inhibition of biofilm formation is independent of <lb/>RNase III/YmdB heterocomplex, and that an alternative, <lb/>hitherto uncharacterized, function of YmdB exists. To <lb/>verify this possibility, we measured the inhibition of <lb/>biofilm formation in the presence of YmdB overexpression <lb/>(confirmed in Figure 2B) against an rnc + and rnc14 <lb/>background. The results showed that inhibition was <lb/>almost the same between the wild-type strain (~70%) <lb/>and the strain lacking RNase III (~67%) (Figure 2A). <lb/>By contrast, processing of pnp&apos;-&apos;lacZ mRNA, a known target <lb/>for YmdB-mediated inhibition of RNase III activity [18], is <lb/>fully dependent on RNase III (Additional file 1: Figure S2). <lb/>Taken together, these results indicate that YmdB over-<lb/>expression inhibits biofilm formation via an RNase <lb/>III-independent pathway. <lb/>RpoS is required for the inhibition of biofilm formation <lb/>by YmdB <lb/>While it was clear that YmdB induction decreased <lb/>biofilm formation (Figure 1), biofilm formation also <lb/>decreased by ~35% in the absence of ymdB (ΔymdB) <lb/>gene in the chromosome (Figure 3A). This could indicate <lb/>that YmdB is involved in, but not essential for, the inhibition <lb/>of biofilm formation in E. coli, or that increased levels of <lb/>YmdB affect biofilm formation by modulating associated <lb/>cellular proteins and their pathways. To test this hypothesis, <lb/>we sought to identify candidate genes whose mRNA levels <lb/>Table 2 Relative abundance of RNase III-dependent or -independent transcripts by different level of YmdB or RNase III <lb/>RNase III-dependent genes <lb/>Microarray 1 <lb/>qPCR-ΔymdB 2 <lb/>qPCR-YmdB 3 <lb/>qPCR-rnc14 4 <lb/>mltD <lb/>3.66 <lb/>3.06 ± 0.04 <lb/>7.37 ± 0.03 <lb/>39.80 ± 0.01 <lb/>PnP <lb/>3.06 <lb/>0.84 ± 0.01 <lb/>3.27 ± 0.36 <lb/>8.02 ± 0.02 <lb/>plsX <lb/>3.01 <lb/>2.98 ± 0.01 <lb/>2.86 ± 0.31 <lb/>21.37 ± 0.01 <lb/>ahpF <lb/>2.48 <lb/>0.90 ± 0.02 <lb/>3.34 ± 0.33 <lb/>7.72 ± 0.01 <lb/>yhdE <lb/>2.26 <lb/>1.90 ± 0.01 <lb/>2.37 ± 0.20 <lb/>3.93 ± 0.01 <lb/>RNase III-independent genes <lb/>Microarray 1 <lb/>qPCR-ΔymdB 2 <lb/>qPCR-YmdB 3 <lb/>qPCR-rnc14 4 <lb/>pspB <lb/>5.18 <lb/>0.88 ± 0.13 <lb/>1.53 ± 0.01 <lb/>1.36 ± 0.01 <lb/>pspA <lb/>4.46 <lb/>0.78 ± 0.01 <lb/>1.50 ± 0.01 <lb/>1.15 ± 0.01 <lb/>pspD <lb/>4.30 <lb/>0.82 ± 0.01 <lb/>2.45 ± 0.06 <lb/>1.86 ± 0.02 <lb/>pspC <lb/>3.86 <lb/>1.01 ± 0.01 <lb/>1.59 ± 0.02 <lb/>1.38 ± 0.02 <lb/>ahpC <lb/>2.81 <lb/>0.67 ± 0.01 <lb/>3.73 ± 0.01 <lb/>3.30 ± 0.01 <lb/>1 <lb/>Fold-change of each transcript levels from microarray analysis (Additional file 1: Table S3): YmdB overexpression from ASKA-ymdB(−) vs pCA24N (−gfp) in <lb/>wild-type (BW25113) background. <lb/>Relative ratios of each transcript levels determined by qPCR with specific primers (Additional file 1: Table S2) are indicated: 2 ymdB knockout (ΔymdB: KSK002) vs <lb/>BW25113 (ymdB), 3 YmdB overexpression from ASKA-ymdB (−) vs pCA24N (−gfp) or 4 RNase III mutant (rnc14:KSK001) vs BW25113 (rnc+). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>A <lb/>Relative biofilm formation <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>10 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>-6 <lb/>10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 <lb/>-1 <lb/>pCA24N <lb/>ASKA -ymdB <lb/>: IPTG (mM) <lb/>S1 <lb/>YmdB <lb/>ASKA-ymdB <lb/>pCA24N <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>-6 10 <lb/>-1 : IPTG (mM) <lb/>1.0 1.0 1.7 2.2 5.7 : Fold <lb/>-<lb/>change <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 1 YmdB inhibits biofilm formation. (A) Inhibition of biofilm formation by YmdB overexpression. E. coli cells containing either pCA24N <lb/>(−gfp) or ASKA-ymdB (−) were grown at 37°C for 24 h in LB medium containing 0 to 10 -1 mM IPTG. Biofilm formation was analyzed, and mean <lb/>values calculated (n = 10, p = 0.05). (B) Western blot analysis of YmdB expression levels. Total cellular proteins from the cells described in (A) were <lb/>reacted with antibodies against YmdB or S1. Changes in YmdB protein levels from ASKA-ymdB induced by IPTG were determined relative to the <lb/>levels of chromosomally-encoded YmdB protein derived from pCA24N (-gfp) vector-containing cells (indicated below). <lb/>Relative biofilm formation <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>BW25113 KSK001 <lb/>(rnc14) <lb/>pCA24N ASKA-ymdB pCA24N ASKA-ymdB <lb/>BW25113 <lb/>KSK001 (rnc14 ) <lb/>A <lb/>S1 <lb/>His-YmdB <lb/>pCA24N <lb/>ASKA-ymdB <lb/>pCA24N <lb/>ASKA-ymdB <lb/>BW25113 <lb/>KSK001 <lb/>(rnc14) <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 2 YmdB inhibits biofilm formation in an RNase III-independent manner. (A) Effect of the presence or absence of RNase III on <lb/>YmdB-mediated inhibition of biofilm formation. Biofilm formation by BW25113 (rnc+) or KSK001 (rnc14) cells with or without plasmid [pCA24N (−gfp) <lb/>or ASKA-ymdB (−)] was measured using cells grown at 37°C for 24 h in LB medium containing IPTG (0.1 mM final) Mean values (n = 10, p = 0.05) are <lb/>shown. &quot;Relative biofilm formation&quot; for KSK001 and ASKA-ymdB (in BW25113 or KSK001) was determined relative to the biofilm formation by each <lb/>control set (BW25113 or pCA24N; set to 1.0). (B) Expression levels of YmdB. The expression of YmdB (His-YmdB) in total cell lysates (from A) was <lb/>detected by immunoblotting with 6xHis Epitope Tag antibody as described in Methods. S1 protein level was used as loading control. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>were increased by YmdB (Table 1) and which have a known <lb/>effect on the biofilm phenotype. One strong candidate is <lb/>RpoS, a stress-responsive sigma factor [21], which when <lb/>overexpressed led to a reduction in biofilm formation <lb/>(Figures 3B,C; [25]). To determine whether YmdB-mediated <lb/>inhibition of biofilm formation is dependent on the <lb/>presence or absence of rpoS, we measured biofilm <lb/>formation in an rpoS knockout strain (Keio-ΔrpoS). <lb/>Biofilm formation was activated in the rpoS knockout <lb/>(Figures 3A,C). Subsequent introduction of a plasmid <lb/>overexpressing YmdB only decreased biofilm inhibition by <lb/>12% in the rpoS knockout (Figure 3B) whereas it re-<lb/>sulted in 70% inhibition in wild-type cells (Figure 2A); <lb/>thus, the inhibition of biofilm formation by YmdB is <lb/>RpoS-dependent. <lb/>Both YmdB and RpoS interdependently regulate gene <lb/>expression and activity on biofilm formation <lb/>Since YmdB is transcriptionally activated by RpoS [18] and <lb/>the level of rpoS transcripts was increased by YmdB overex-<lb/>pression, it is possible that YmdB modulates RpoS expres-<lb/>sion. YmdB could affect this change in rpoS transcript levels <lb/>Relative biofilm formation <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>pCA24N ASKA-rpoS <lb/>BW25113 <lb/>pCA24N ASKA-rpoS <lb/>KSK002( <lb/>pCA24N ASKA-ymdB <lb/>Keio-<lb/>Plasmid : <lb/>Strain : <lb/>Relative biofilm formation <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>BW25113 KSK002 <lb/>( <lb/>Keio-<lb/>Strain : <lb/>His-YmdB <lb/>ASKA-rpoS <lb/>pCA24N <lb/>BW25113 <lb/>S1 <lb/>RpoS <lb/>ASKA-rpoS <lb/>pCA24N <lb/>KSK002 <lb/>( <lb/>ASKA-ymdB <lb/>pCA24N <lb/>Keio-rpoS <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>ymdB) <lb/>ymdB) <lb/>rpoS <lb/>ymdB) <lb/>rpoS <lb/>Figure 3 Interdependency on YmdB and RpoS for biofilm formation. (A) Effect of knocking out ymdB or rpoS on biofilm formation. Biofilm <lb/>formation was measured in wild-type (ymdB + or rpoS+), KSK002 (ΔymdB) and rpoS mutant (Keio-ΔrpoS) cells. (B) Dependency of RpoS and YmdB <lb/>phenotype on biofilm formation. The effect of ectopic expression of RpoS or YmdB in the absence of ymdB or rpoS, respectively, on biofilm <lb/>formation was determined. (C) Expression of RpoS and YmdB. Protein expression was detected by immunoblotting using antibodies against RpoS <lb/>and 6xHistidine tagged YmdB (His-YmdB) as described in Methods. S1 protein level was used as a loading control. All biofilm formation data were <lb/>obtained as described in Methods. Data represent the mean values from ten independent experiments. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>by either acting as an as yet unknown transcription factor <lb/>or by acting as an effector protein for the factor(s) involved <lb/>in rpoS transcription. We found that YmdB overexpression <lb/>had no effect on rpoS promoter activity (data not shown), <lb/>thereby excluding any role as a transcription factor. A linear <lb/>relationship between rpoS transcript levels and RpoS protein <lb/>levels was then investigated following YmdB induction, and <lb/>similar increases (~2.5-fold) in the induced β-galactosidase <lb/>activity of the rpoS&apos;-&apos;lacZ protein fusion and the RpoS <lb/>protein level were observed (Figures 4A,B). Moreover, the <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>IPTG <lb/>ND 1.0 2.5 <lb/>RpoS <lb/>S1 <lb/>Keio <lb/>-rpoS <lb/>BW25113 <lb/>pCA24N <lb/>ASKA-ymdB <lb/>A <lb/>Ratio of rpoS transcript levels <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>BW25113 <lb/>pCA24N <lb/>BW25113 <lb/>ASKA-ymdB <lb/>Plasmid : <lb/>KSK002 <lb/>( ymdB) <lb/>(rnc14) <lb/>KSK001 <lb/>Strain : <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>pCA 24N <lb/>BW25113 <lb/>ASKA-ymdB <lb/>BW25113 <lb/>no IPTG <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>(Miller units) <lb/>-galactosidase activity <lb/>Figure 4 Regulation of RpoS levels and activity by YmdB. (A) Effect of YmdB on in vivo expression levels of RpoS. KS004 [SG30013 (λRpoS750::LacZ] <lb/>[31] strains containing either pCA24N (−gfp) or ASKA-ymdB (−) were grown to OD 600 = 0.2, induced by IPTG (0.1 mM final), and further grown to <lb/>OD 600 = 1.0. Aliquots were then assayed for β-galactosidase activity. Data represent the mean values from n = 3 experiments (p = 0.05). (B) Expression <lb/>level of RpoS. Total lysates prepared from the cell described in (A) and from Keio-ΔrpoS cells were immunoblotted antibodies against RpoS and S1. The <lb/>Keio-ΔrpoS strain is included to show the specificity of the antibody. The relative levels of RpoS normalized against S1 protein are shown. ND, not <lb/>determined. (C) Determination of steady-state levels of rpoS transcript induced by YmdB. cDNA synthesized from total RNA obtained from BW25113, <lb/>KSK002 (ΔymdB), KSK001 (rnc14) or BW25113 cells containing either pCA24N (−gfp) or ASKA-ymdB (−) were qPCR amplified using the rpoS-or 16S <lb/>RNA-specific primer sets listed in Additional file 1: Table S2 and then compared. Data represent the mean values from triplicate experiments. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>steady-state level of rpoS transcript (Figure 4C) was <lb/>oppositely regulated in the absence of chromosomal <lb/>ymdB. Additionally, the level of rpoS transcript following <lb/>YmdB overexpression was lower than that in the RNase <lb/>III mutant strain. These data suggest that YmdB-mediated <lb/>regulation of RNase III activity alone cannot fully regulate <lb/>the processing of the 5′ UTR of rpoS mRNA. Because <lb/>RpoS can negatively regulate biofilm formation by itself <lb/>(Figure 3B) and is also required for complete YmdB func-<lb/>tion (Figure 3B), it is a matter of debate whether YmdB <lb/>can modulate RpoS activity. When the RpoS protein was <lb/>overexpressed in a wild-type and in an ymdB knockout <lb/>strain, RpoS-mediated inhibition of biofilm formation was <lb/>decreased from 70% to 43% (Figure 3B). This, when taken <lb/>together with the other data, suggests that the regulation <lb/>of RpoS function during biofilm formation is dependent <lb/>upon YmdB. Moreover, RpoS overexpression phenotype <lb/>on biofilm inhibition was not dependent upon the pres-<lb/>ence of RNase III activity (Additional file 1: Figure S3). <lb/>Thus, YmdB is a novel post-transcriptional regulator of <lb/>RpoS levels that acts independently of RNase III. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The results presented herein demonstrate that YmdB is <lb/>a major regulator of RNase III activity in E. coli, modulating <lb/>more than 30% of the genes targeted by RNase III. In <lb/>addition, the results of a microarray analysis following <lb/>YmdB overexpression (which identified changes in biofilm-<lb/>related genes and a decrease in biofilm formation) indicate <lb/>a novel role for YmdB as a modulator of biofilm formation. <lb/>Previous results indicated that overexpression of RpoS was <lb/>associated with decreased biofilm formation [25]. Our <lb/>microarray, qPCR, and Western blotting data showed that <lb/>overexpression of YmdB increased the levels of RpoS <lb/>(Additional file 1: Tables S3, Figures 2, 3 and 4). Moreover, <lb/>YmdB modulated RpoS levels and activity of biofilm <lb/>formation (Figures 3, 4). Thus, we propose a model to <lb/>illustrate the multiple roles played by YmdB during gene <lb/>expression and biofilm formation (Figure 5). <lb/>The 5′ UTR of rpoS mRNA is a known target of <lb/>RNase III and its levels increase when RNase III activity <lb/>is ablated [21]. Because biofilm formation is influenced <lb/>by RpoS levels, it may be proposed that the rpoS mRNA <lb/>is responsive to YmdB-directed RNase III inhibition. <lb/>However, this is not the case because the decrease in <lb/>biofilm formation following YmdB expression was not <lb/>reversed in the absence of RNase III (Figure 2), suggesting <lb/>that regulation of RNase III activity by YmdB is not essen-<lb/>tial for the inhibition of biofilm formation. Thus, the major <lb/>mechanism underlying biofilm regulation by YmdB appears <lb/>to be RNase III-independent (Figure 5). <lb/>A screen of potential regulatory gene(s) with a YmdB-<lb/>mediated phenotype demonstrated that RpoS is necessary <lb/>for inhibiting biofilm formation (Figure 3); RpoS activates <lb/>the transcription of ymdB [18]; thus, it is highly plausible <lb/>that the RpoS gene is an upstream regulator of YmdB <lb/>transcription and the resultant phenotypes. Conversely, <lb/>the possibility that YmdB is a transcription factor that <lb/>activates rpoS transcription was initially suggested by ob-<lb/>servations that RpoS levels were increased by YmdB over-<lb/>expression, and that YmdB and RpoS are both required <lb/>for the decrease in biofilm formation. However, this theory <lb/>was rejected because increases in YmdB expression had no <lb/>effect on promoter activity (data not shown). Hence, <lb/>YmdB-induced modulation of RpoS levels must occur via <lb/>post-transcriptional regulation (Figure 4). It is also possible <lb/>that YmdB modulates other rpoS transcription factor(s), <lb/>although we have not identified which other tran-<lb/>scription factors are required for this response. Over-<lb/>all, the data suggest that YmdB and RpoS are co-<lb/>regulators of biofilm formation (Figure 5). <lb/>The identification of a novel role for YmdB is not <lb/>altogether surprising, since eukaryotic macrodomain <lb/>proteins can have multiple roles [43,44], and YmdB <lb/>has additional functions in bacteria [45,46]. For instance, <lb/>in E. coli YmdB deacetylates the sirtuin product of <lb/>O-acetyl-ADP-ribose and reforms ADP ribose [45]. <lb/>The present study reveals that YmdB modulates the <lb/>expression of genes involved in physiologically important <lb/>pathways (Table 1); hence, YmdB could act as a general <lb/>regulator in a variety of cellular processes. Further examin-<lb/>ation of such a potential role for YmdB and its family <lb/>members in bacteria is necessary. YmdB is also required to <lb/>be coexpressed for the complementation of a function of <lb/>YmdB <lb/>YmdB <lb/>Biofilm <lb/>RNase III <lb/>RpoS <lb/>Unknown <lb/>factor(s) <lb/>RNase III <lb/>Figure 5 A model of biofilm formation and gene <lb/>expression involving YmdB, RpoS, and RNase III. Two different <lb/>pathways for biofilm formation are proposed: an RNase III-dependent <lb/>pathway in which other uncharacterized factor(s) inhibit RNase III activity, <lb/>thereby upregulating biofilm formation, and an RNase III-independent <lb/>pathway in which both YmdB and RpoS interdependently regulate the <lb/>inhibition of biofilm formation. In terms of gene expression, the level of <lb/>RpoS is post-transcriptionally regulated by YmdB either directly <lb/>or indirectly via the inhibition of RNase III activity [18,20], while the level <lb/>of YmdB is regulated transcriptionally by the RpoS protein [18]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>ClsC, a recently identified cardiolipin synthase in E. coli <lb/>[45]. ClsC utilizes phosphatidylethanolamines (PE) as the <lb/>phosphatidyl donor to phosphatidylglycine (PG) to form <lb/>cardiolipin (CL) [46]. While YmdB is apparently not a <lb/>direct modulator of that pathway (since changes in clsC <lb/>(ymdC) gene expression in the microarrays were negligible <lb/>(a 1.1-fold increase only); (data not shown), it may modu-<lb/>late it indirectly via the action of the fatty acid biosynthesis <lb/>gene, fabD (Table 1), on the CL synthesis-regulating gene; <lb/>however, such a role has not been confirmed. <lb/>The ectopic expression of YmdB almost completely <lb/>regulates RNase III activity with respect to several targets, <lb/>including pnp, rnc and ribosomal RNA processing <lb/>(Additional file 1: Figure S2) [6]; however, biofilm forma-<lb/>tion is not solely dependent upon YmdB-directed RNase <lb/>III regulation, suggesting that gene expression data will be <lb/>useful for identifying unknown RNase III-independently <lb/>regulated YmdB functions. <lb/>Several trans-acting factors that modulate the RNase <lb/>activity of both exo-and endo-RNases have been identified <lb/>in E. coli [15-18,47,48]. Among these four trans-acting <lb/>regulatory proteins for endo-RNase activity have been well <lb/>characterized in E. coli: RraA [15] and RraB [16] for RNase <lb/>E, and bacteriophage T7 protein kinase [17] and YmdB [18] <lb/>for RNase III. The presence of homologs in other species <lb/>suggests such regulation of endo-RNase activity is generally <lb/>required for bacterial physiology. Recently, gene expression <lb/>profiling revealed a role for RraA in regulating the SOS <lb/>response, a mechanism which responds to the stress caused <lb/>by DNA damage [15,49]. RNase III modulates approxi-<lb/>mately 12% (592 genes) of the E. coli genome [35]; using <lb/>YmdB-mediated down-regulation of RNase III rather than <lb/>an RNase III mutant retains the ability to measure the <lb/>effect of trans-acting factor(s) and hence the correct physio-<lb/>logical modulation of RNase III. Because YmdB regulates <lb/>the turnover of approximately 30% of the target genes <lb/>of RNase III (Additional file 1: Table S3) and the rpoS <lb/>level is not completely regulated by YmdB (Figure 4), <lb/>either other regulator(s) that result RNase III mutant-<lb/>like conditions must be present or YmdB partially <lb/>regulates the physiology of the RNase III-mutant to <lb/>induce the up-regulation of an RNase III activator <lb/>that has yet to be identified. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The data presented herein show that YmdB functions <lb/>both to regulate RNase III activity and to modulate <lb/>bacterial biofilm formation; therefore, YmdB seems to <lb/>be a multifunctional bacterial macrodomain protein, <lb/>similar to that in eukaryotic cells. Furthermore, this <lb/>protein will make it possible to design a more intelligent <lb/>synthetic scaffold for producing bacterial cells that <lb/>modulate difficult-to-treat pathogens that depend upon <lb/>biofilm production. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Availability of supporting data <lb/>The data sets supporting the results of this article are <lb/>included within the article and in Additional file 1. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Additional file <lb/>Additional file 1: Table S1. Strains and plasmids used in this study. <lb/>Table S2. List of primers used in this study. Table S3. Differential gene <lb/>expression profiles of E. coli 129 genes. Figure S1. Verification of rpoS, ymdB, <lb/>and rnc mutants. PCR validation of (A) Keio-ΔrpoS or (B) Keio-ΔymdB and <lb/>ΔymdB. (C) Schematic representations of PCR regions. (D) Western-blot <lb/>analysis verifying RNase III mutation. Figure S2. Dependency of <lb/>YmdB-mediated down-regulation of RNase III activity upon the presence of <lb/>RNase III. Figure S3. Interdependency of RpoS and RNase III for biofilm <lb/>formation. Figure S4. Dependency of YmdB-mediated phenotype upon the <lb/>absence of RpoS and RNase III. (A) Effect of biofilm formation by double <lb/>mutation of RpoS and RNase III. (B) Effect of YmdB-mediated inhibition of <lb/>biofilm formation in double mutation of RNase III and RpoS. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>TYK, JYL, and KSK conceived of and designed all the experiments in the <lb/>paper, executed experiments, collected, and interpreted the data, and <lb/>drafted the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Dr. Susan Gottesman for distributing RpoS fusion strain (SG30013). <lb/>This work is supported by the Basic Science Research program through the <lb/>NRF Korea (2010-0023011) to K.S.K. and the KRIBB initiative program. <lb/></div>

			<front>Author details <lb/>1 <lb/>Superbacteria Research Center, Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and <lb/>Biotechnology (KRIBB), 125 Gwahak-ro, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon 305-806, Korea. <lb/>2 <lb/>Department of Molecular Biology, Chonbuk National University, 567 <lb/>Baekje-daero, Deokjin-gu, Jeonju-si, Jeollabuk-do 561-756, Korea. <lb/>3 <lb/>Department of Biosystems and Bioengineering, University of Science and <lb/>Technology, 217 Gajung-ro, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon 305-350, Korea. <lb/>Received: 1 June 2013 Accepted: 21 November 2013 <lb/>Published: 24 November 2013 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Robertson HD, Webster RE, Zinder ND: Purification and properties of <lb/>ribonuclease III from Escherichia coli. J Biol Chem 1968, 243:82-91. <lb/>2. Court D: RNA processing and degradation by RNase III. In Control of <lb/>Messenger RNA Stability. 1st edition. Edited by Belasco JG, Brawerman G. <lb/>New York: Academic Press; 1993:71-116. <lb/>3. Nicholson AW: Structure, reactivity, and biology of double-stranded RNA. <lb/>Prog Nucleic Acid Res Mol Biol 1996, 52:1-65. <lb/>4. Nicholson AW: Function, mechanism and regulation of bacterial <lb/>ribonucleases. FEMS Microbiol Rev 1999, 23:371-390. <lb/>5. Drieder D, Condon C: The continuing story of endoribonuclease III. J Mol <lb/>Microbiol Biotechnol 2004, 8:195-200. <lb/>6. MacRae IJ, Doudna JA: Ribonuclease revisited: structural insights into <lb/>ribonuclease III family enzymes. Curr Opin Struct Biol 2007, 17:138-145. <lb/>7. Nicholson AW: Ribonuclease III and the role of double-stranded RNA pro-<lb/>cessing in bacterial systems. In Ribonucleases. Edited by Nicholson AW. <lb/>Berlin Heidelberg: Springer; 2011:269-297 [Bujnicki JM (Series Editor): Nucleic <lb/>Acids and Molecular Biology]. <lb/>8. Dunn JJ: Ribonuclease III. In The Enzymes. Edited by Boyer P. New York: <lb/>Academic Press; 1982:485-499. <lb/>9. Régnier P, Grunberg-Manago M: Cleavage by RNase III in the transcripts of <lb/>the metY-nusA-infB operon of Escherichia coli releases the tRNA and <lb/>initiates the decay of the downstream mRNA. J Mol Biol 1989, <lb/>210:293-302. <lb/>10. Murchison EP, Hannon GJ: miRNAs on the move: miRNA biogenesis and <lb/>the RNAi machinery. Curr Opin Cell Biol 2004, 16:223-229. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 10 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>11. Viegas SC, Silva IJ, Saramago M, Domingues S, Arraiano CM: Regulation of <lb/>the small regulatory RNA MicA by ribonuclease III: a target-dependent <lb/>pathway. Nucleic Acids Res 2011, 39:2918-2930. <lb/>12. Matsunaga J, Dyer M, Simons EL, Simons RW: Expression and regulation of <lb/>the rnc and pdxJ operons of E. coli. Mol Microbiol 1996, 22:977-989. <lb/>13. Matsunaga J, Simons EL, Simons RW: RNase III autoregulation: Structure <lb/>and function of rncO, the posttranscriptional &apos;operator. RNA 1996, <lb/>2:1228-1240. <lb/>14. Régnier P, Portier C: Initiation, attenuation and RNase III processing of <lb/>transcripts from the Escherichia coli operon encoding ribosomal protein <lb/>S15 and polynucleotide phosphorylase. J Mol Biol 1986, 187:23-32. <lb/>15. Lee K, et al: RraA, a protein inhibitor of RNase E activity that globally <lb/>modulates RNA abundance in E. coli. Cell 2003, 114:623-634. <lb/>16. Gao J, et al: Differential modulation of E. coli mRNA abundancy by <lb/>inhibitory proteins that alter the composition of the degradosome. <lb/>Mol Microbiol 2006, 61:394-406. <lb/>17. Mayer JE, Schweiger M: RNase III is positively regulated by T7 protein <lb/>kinase. J Biol Chem 1983, 258:5340-5343. <lb/>18. Kim KS, Manasherob R, Cohen SN: YmdB: a stress-responsive ribonuclease-<lb/>binding regulator of E. coli RNase III activity. Genes Dev 2008, <lb/>22:3497-3508. <lb/>19. Sim SH, et al: Escherichia coli ribonuclease III activity is downregulated by <lb/>osmotic stress: consequences for the degradation of bdm mRNA in <lb/>biofilm formation. Mol Microbiol 2010, 75:413-425. <lb/>20. Resch A, et al: Translational activation by the noncoding RNA DsrA <lb/>involves alternative RNase III processing in the rpoS 5′-leader. RNA 2008, <lb/>14:454-459. <lb/>21. Battesti A, Majdalani N, Gottesman S: The RpoS-mediated general stress <lb/>response in Escherichia coli. Annu Rev Microbiol 2011, 65:189-213. <lb/>22. López D, Vlamakis H, Kolter R: Biofilms. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol 2010, <lb/>2:a000398. <lb/>23. Corona-Izquierdo FP, Membrillo-Hernandez J: A mutation in rpoS enhances <lb/>biofilm formation in Escherichia coli during exponential phase of <lb/>growth. FEMS Microbiol Lett 2002, 211:105-110. <lb/>24. Sheldon JR, Yim MS, Saliba JH, Chung WH, Wong KY, Leung KT: Role of <lb/>rpoS in Escherichia coli O157:H7 strain H32 biofilm development and <lb/>survival. Appl Environ Microbiol 2012, 78:8331-8339. <lb/>25. Ferrières L, Thompson A, Clarke DJ: Elevated levels of σ S inhibit biofilm <lb/>formation in Escherichia coli: a role for the Rcs phosphorelay. <lb/>Microbiology 2009, 155:3544-3553. <lb/>26. Podkovyrov SM, Larson TJ: A new vector-host system for construction of <lb/>lacZ transcriptional fusions where only low-level gene expression is <lb/>desirable. Gene 1995, 156:151-152. <lb/>27. Simons RW, Houman F, Kleckner N: Improved single and multicopy <lb/>lac-based cloning vectors for protein and operon fusions. Gene 1987, <lb/>53:85-96. <lb/>28. Baba T, et al: Construction of Escherichia coli K-12 in-frame, single knock-<lb/>out mutants: the Keio collection. Mol Syst Biol 2006, 2:2006.0008. <lb/>29. Kim KS, et al: A novel fluorescent reporter system for monitoring and <lb/>identifying RNase III activity and its target RNAs. RNA Biol 2011, <lb/>9:1167-1176. <lb/>30. Nakao R, Senpuku H, Watanabe H: Porphyromonas gingivalis gale is <lb/>involved in lipopolysaccharide O-antigen synthesis and biofilm forma-<lb/>tion. Infect Immun 2006, 74:6145-6153. <lb/>31. Sledjeski DD, Gupta A, Gottesman S: The small RNA, DsrA, is essential for <lb/>the low temperature expression of RpoS during exponential growth in <lb/>Escherichia coli. EMBO J 1996, 15:3993-4000. <lb/>32. Beran RK, Simons RW: Cold-temperature induction of Escherichia coli <lb/>polynucleotide phosphorylase occurs by reversal of its autoregulation. <lb/>Mol Microbiol 2001, 39:112-125. <lb/>33. Miller JH: A short course in bacterial genetics: A laboratory manual and <lb/>handbook for Escherichia coli and related bacteria. New York: Cold Spring <lb/>Harbor Laboratory Press; 1992. <lb/>34. Feng Y, Huang H, Liao J, Cohen SN: Escherichia coli poly(A)-binding <lb/>proteins that interact with components of degradosomes or impede <lb/>RNA decay mediated by polynucleotide phosphorylase and RNase E. <lb/>J Biol Chem 2001, 276:31651-31656. <lb/>35. Kitagawa M, et al: Complete set of ORF clones of Escherichia coli ASKA <lb/>library (A Complete Set of E. coli K-12 ORF Archive): Unique Resources <lb/>for Biological Research. DNA Res 2006, 12:291-299. <lb/>36. Stead MB, et al: Analysis of Escherichia coli RNase E and RNase III activity <lb/>in vivo using tilling microarrays. Nucleic Acids Res 2011, 39:3188-3203. <lb/>37. Uhlich GA, Chen CY, Cottrell BJ, Irwin PL, Philips JG: Peroxide resistance in <lb/>Escherichia coli serotype O157: H7 biofilms is regulated by both RpoS-<lb/>dependent and -independent mechanisms. Microbiology 2009, <lb/>158:2225-2234. <lb/>38. Yamaguchi Y, Park JH, Inouye M: MqsR, a crucial regulator for quorum <lb/>sensing and biofilm formation, is a GCU-specific mRNA interferase in <lb/>Escherichia coli. J Biol Chem 2009, 284:28746-28753. <lb/>39. Yang X, Ma Q, Wood TK: The R1 conjugative plasmid increases <lb/>Escherichia coli biofilm formation through an envelope stress response. <lb/>Appl Environ Microbiol 2008, 74:2690-2699. <lb/>40. Thomason MK, Fontaine F, de Lay N, Storz G: A small RNA that regulates <lb/>motility and biofilm formation in response to changes in nutrient <lb/>availability in Escherichia coli. Mol Microbiol 2012, 84:17-35. <lb/>41. Beloin C, et al: Global impact of mature biofilm lifestyle on Escherichia <lb/>coli K-12 gene expression. Mol Microbiol 2004, 51:659-674. <lb/>42. Darwin AJ: The phage-shock-protein response. Mol Microbiol 2005, <lb/>57:621-628. <lb/>43. Kalisch T, Amé J, Dantzer F, Schreiber V: New readers and interpretations <lb/>of poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation. Trends Biochem Sci 2012, 37:381-390. <lb/>44. Saikatendu KS, et al: Structural basis of severe acute respiratory syndrome <lb/>coronavirus ADP-Ribose-1″-Phosphate dephosphorylation by a con-<lb/>served domain of nsP3. Structure 2005, 13:1665-1675. <lb/>45. Chen D, et al: Identification of macrodomain proteins as novel O-acetyl-<lb/>ADP-ribose deacetylases. J Biol Chem 2011, 286:13261-13271. <lb/>46. Tan BK, et al: Discovery of a cardiolipin synthase utilizing <lb/>phosphatidylethanolamine and phosphatidylglycerol as substrates. <lb/>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 2012, 109:16504-16509. <lb/>47. Cairrão F, Chora A, Zihão R, Carpousis AJ, Arraiano CM: RNase II levels <lb/>change according to the growth conditions: characterization of gmr, a <lb/>new Escherichia coli gene involved in the modulation of RNase II. <lb/>Mol Microbiol 2001, 39:1550-1561. <lb/>48. Liang W, Deutscher MP: Post-translational modification of RNase R is <lb/>regulated by stress-dependent reduction in the acetylating enzyme Pka <lb/>(YfiQ). RNA 2012, 18:37-41. <lb/>49. Manasherob R, Miller C, Kim KS, Cohen SN: Ribonuclease E modulation of <lb/>the bacterial SOS response. PLoS One 2012, 7:e38426. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>doi:10.1186/1471-2180-13-266 <lb/>Cite this article as: Kim et al.: Escherichia coli YmdB regulates biofilm <lb/>formation independently of its role as an RNase III modulator. BMC <lb/>Microbiology 2013 13:266. <lb/></front>

			Submit your next manuscript to BioMed Central <lb/>and take full advantage of: <lb/>• Convenient online submission <lb/>• Thorough peer review <lb/>• No space constraints or color figure charges <lb/>• Immediate publication on acceptance <lb/>• Inclusion in PubMed, CAS, Scopus and Google Scholar <lb/>• Research which is freely available for redistribution <lb/>Submit your manuscript at <lb/>www.biomedcentral.com/submit <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">Kim et al. BMC Microbiology 2013, 13:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 11 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2180/13/266 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
