<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/>Available online 21 March 2024 <lb/>2405-8440/© 2024 The Authors. <lb/>Published by Elsevier Ltd. <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/). <lb/>Research article <lb/>An assessment of the impact of traditional rice cooking practice <lb/>and eating habits on arsenic and iron transfer into the food chain <lb/>of smallholders of Indo-Gangetic plain of South-Asia: Using AMMI <lb/>and Monte-Carlo simulation model <lb/>Debojyoti Moulick a,b,1 , Dibakar Ghosh c, 1 , Yogita Gharde d , Arnab Majumdar e,1 , <lb/>Munish Kumar Upadhyay f , Deep Chakraborty g, 1 , Subrata Mahanta h , Anupam Das i , <lb/>Shuvasish Choudhury b , Marian Brestic j , Tahani Awad Alahmadi k , Mohammad <lb/>Javed Ansari l , Shubhas Chandra Santra a , Akbar Hossain m,* <lb/>a Department of Environmental Science, University of Kalyani, Kalyani, 741235, West Bengal, India <lb/>b Plant Stress Biology &amp; Metabolomics Laboratory, Department of Life Science and Bioinformatics, Assam University, Silchar, 788011, Assam, India <lb/>c ICAR-Indian Institute of Water Management, Bhubaneswar, 751023, Odisha, India <lb/>d ICAR-Directorate of Weed Research, Jabalpur, 482004, Madhya Pradesh, India <lb/>e School of Environmental Studies, Jadavpur University, Kolkata, 700032, West Bengal, India <lb/>f Centre for Environmental Science &amp; Engineering, Department of Civil Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology, Kanpur, 208016, India <lb/>g Department of Environmental Science, Amity School of Life Sciences (ASLS), Amity University, Madhya Pradesh (AUMP), Gwalior, 474005, <lb/>Madhya Pradesh, India <lb/>h Department of Chemistry, NIT Jamshedpur, Adityapur, Jamshedpur, 831014, Jharkhand, India <lb/>i Department of Soil Science and Agricultural Chemistry, Bihar Agricultural University, Sabour, Bhagalpur, 813210, India <lb/>j Institute of Plant and Environmental Sciences, Slovak University of Agriculture, Nitra, Tr. A. Hlinku 2, 949 01, Nitra, Slovak, Slovakia <lb/>k Department of Pediatrics, College of Medicine and King Khalid University Hospital, King Saud University, Medical City, P.O. Box 2925, Riyadh, <lb/>11461, Saudi Arabia <lb/>l Department of Botany, Hindu College Moradabad (Mahatma Jyotiba Phule Rohilkhand University, Bareilly), Moradabad, 244001, Uttar Pradesh, <lb/>India <lb/>m Division of Soil Science, Bangladesh Wheat and Maize Research Institute, Dinajpur, 5200, Bangladesh <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Arsenic <lb/>Soaked cooked rice <lb/>Iron <lb/>Risk assessment <lb/>Post-harvest phase <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>The current study was designed to investigate the consequences of rice cooking and soaking of <lb/>cooked rice (CR) with or without arsenic (As) contaminated water on As and Fe (iron) transfer to <lb/>the human body along with associated health risk assessment using additive main-effects and <lb/>multiplicative interaction (AMMI) and Monte Carlo Simulation model. In comparison to raw rice, <lb/>As content in cooked rice (CR) and soaked cooked rice (SCR) enhanced significantly (at p &lt; 0.05 <lb/>level), regardless of rice cultivars and locations (at p &lt; 0.05 level) due to the use of As-rich water <lb/>for cooking and soaking purposes. Whereas As content in CR and SCR was reduced significantly <lb/>* Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail addresses: drubha31@gmail.com (D. Moulick), dibakar.ghosh@icar.gov.in (D. Ghosh), yogitagharde@gmail.com (Y. Gharde), <lb/>arnabmajumdar891@gmail.com (A. Majumdar), munish007up@gmail.com (M.K. Upadhyay), deepckbty@gmail.com (D. Chakraborty), <lb/>smahanta.chem@nitjsr.ac.in (S. Mahanta), anusoil22@gmail.com (A. Das), shuvasish@gmail.com (S. Choudhury), marian.brestic@uniag.sk <lb/>(M. Brestic), talahmadi@ksu.edu.sa (T.A. Alahmadi), mjavedansari@gmail.com (M.J. Ansari), scsantra@yahoo.com (S. Chandra Santra), <lb/>akbarhossainwrc@gmail.com (A. Hossain). <lb/>1 Equal Credit with First Author. <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Heliyon <lb/>journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e28296 <lb/>Received 14 July 2023; Received in revised form 11 March 2024; Accepted 15 March 2024 <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>due to the use of As-free water for cooking and soaking purposes. The use of As-free water (AFW) <lb/>also enhanced the Fe content in CR. The overnight soaking of rice invariably enhanced the Fe <lb/>content despite the use of As-contaminated water in SCR however, comparatively in lesser <lb/>amount than As-free rice. In the studied area, due to consumption of As-rich CR and SCR children <lb/>are more vulnerable to health hazards than adults. Consumption of SCR (prepared with AFW) <lb/>could be an effective method to minimize As transmission and Fe enrichment among consumers. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Rice has been regarded as a staple food with the credit to feed approximately half of the world&apos;s population (30-70% of energy <lb/>source) [1-3]. Apart from being a whole sum serve, rice is also known to be a reliable source of various biogenic elements (zinc, iron, <lb/>copper, manganese etc.). At the same time, rice and rice-based products (mainly cooked rice) are a well-recognized source of arsenic <lb/>(As), classified as a Group 1 carcinogen by the International Agency for Research on Cancer, 2012. Intake of As by the population <lb/>across the world through various foods is considered a global health challenge. With the vivid expansion of the world food trade, the <lb/>consumption of As rich/contaminated rice/rice-based products also intensified [4-9]. Earlier findings suggest that for people residing <lb/>in As-affected areas or nearby, oral ingestion/consumption of rice seems to be the major pathway of As exposure into the human food <lb/>chain and associated complications, next to drinking As-contaminated water [10-15]. To minimize As exposure to the population to <lb/>prevent the entry of As into the food chain, various organizations have imposed guidelines regarding the As content in food stuffs, in <lb/>regular intervals. These guidelines regarding the permissible limits for inorganic-As (iAs) indicates various rice and rice based process <lb/>foods should have iAs content within the stipulated mark e.g. baby foods (0.1 mg kg -1 ), parboiled rice (0.25 mg kg -1 ) and 0.2 mg kg -1 <lb/>polished rice respectively FAO (Food and Agriculture Organization), and European Commission [16-18]. <lb/>For more than ten years, the micronutrient deficit or deficiency has been considered as a &quot;triple burden of malnutrition&quot; for low-and <lb/>middle-income countries (LMICs) fetched considerable global attention. Biofortification of crops including rice with micronutrients <lb/>become a major arena of research interest [19,20]. Malnutrition associated with inadequate availability of Fe is considered as one of <lb/>the utmost nutritional deficiencies [21-24]. A survey conducted by the World Health Organization (WHO) in 185 countries in the time <lb/>frame of 1990-2011, suggests that anaemia has the uppermost incidence among women who attain reproductive age and pre-school <lb/>children [25,26]. The prevalence of iron deficiency anaemia (IDA) among children (6-59 months) is alone responsible for 1.3% loss of <lb/>India&apos;s gross domestic product (GDP), estimated approximately 23.0 billion USD for the entire lifetime production losses if considered <lb/>[27]. In the year 2014, Rome&apos;s declaration on nutrition, reported that approximately two billion people are suffering from a deficiency <lb/>of iron per year, making it a prominent reason behind anaemia [28-30]. <lb/>Assessing the widespread anaemia (due to iron deficiency), WHO has come up with a plan for supplementation/enhancement of <lb/>iron in the diet or even through oral consumption. WHO recommended different doses of iron for different age groups i.e. children (&lt;5 <lb/>years), children (5-12 years) as well as for adolescent girls and women were advised to consume 2.0 mg kg -1 , 30.0 mg kg -1 and 60.0 <lb/>mg kg -1 of daily [25,31,32]. At present for therapeutic purposes, exsiccated ferrous sulphate, ferrous fumarate, and ferrous gluconate <lb/>are considered as the four major Fe-Supplementation preparations. However, the supplementation is often accompanied by side ef-<lb/>fects. Continuous attempts have been made to lessen the bearing deficiency of iron using various approaches like fortification and <lb/>biofortification programs, supplementation etc. [33-35]. Moreover, an investigation was carried out among the Indian population <lb/>residing state of Maharashtra (years 2018-2020), which suggested that injection of FCM (ferric carboxymaltose) a newer iron prep-<lb/>aration emerged to be effective in iron supplementation up to 1000.0 mg, when compared to the ferrous sulphate supplement [36]. <lb/>Apart from these, iron folic acid (administered every week), multiple micronutrient powder, trimaltol iron complex and lipophilic iron <lb/>chelator, and ferric carboxymaltose (intravenous injection) too names a few, which are under consideration for Fe-supplementation <lb/>purposes [37-41]. <lb/>Rice is one such field crop that can accumulate as much as ten times more As than other cereal crops [15,42-45], when cultivated in <lb/>As contaminated agroecosystem. A significant adverse impact of As on rice plant&apos;s life cycle with pronounced reactive oxygen species <lb/>(ROS) has been documented from time to time, applicable to other abiotic stressors [46-49]. At the same time, various mitigation <lb/>options are also tested to minimize As-induced phytotoxicity and subsequent accumulation in rice plants [50-59]. <lb/>Rice can be regarded as the staple food for the rural population residing in West Bengal, specifically cooked rice has been <lb/>considered the major route of As intake among the populations [60-64] with considerable contribution of drinking As contaminated <lb/>water also documented [65]. If one can carefully evaluate the trend of research focus, the majority of research however focused on <lb/>pre-harvest and yield attributes/stability in rice under As contaminated agroecosystem [49,66,67]. The impact of As on the <lb/>post-harvest phases of rice are also present in limited number [46,68-70]. <lb/>It has been quite a while, apart from assessing the As transfer into the food chain through the consumption of cooked rice, reports <lb/>are also describing the potential health hazard associated with drinking As-contaminated groundwater, in a major portion of the world <lb/>[71-73]. According to an observation made by Xu et al. [74] more than 40.0 million people residing in As-contaminated areas are in <lb/>great danger due to the consumption of As-contaminated water, throughout the world and increasing the number with every passing <lb/>day. Chronic As poisoning has been reported earlier mostly in West Bengal and adjoining Bangladesh [61,75,76]. In the Gangetic plain, <lb/>prolonged use of irrigation with groundwater leads to a stunning amount As (up to 83.0 mg kg -1 ) deposited in soil [77]. <lb/>The majority of research so far focused on the post-harvest phase, the consequences of different rice parboiling [73,78-80], various <lb/>cooking methods (in most cases deionized/ultrapure water considered as cooking medium) and the impact of cooking containers <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>(stainless steel container/pressure cooker/steamer etc.) on As content retention/modulation in cooked rice portion and associated risk <lb/>assessment [81-87]. <lb/>However, consequences of eating habits like soaking cooked rice (SCR) or sour rice, a popular delicacy among the rural population <lb/>from countless past, not been considered either for transmission of As (including health risk assessment) in to the food chain or even a <lb/>mean for micronutrient enrichment, till date. During the process of making soaking cooked rice (SCR), initially, rice is cooked in excess <lb/>amounts during the night and this excess/leftover cooked rice is soaked in water and kept the cooked rice in a closed container <lb/>overnight. The next morning these SCR is usually taken as breakfast as well as in lunch also, for at least 9-10 months/year, in rural, <lb/>semi-urban areas. These SCR is popularly known as panta/pakhal/poitha among rice consumers, throughout the world [88]. Sur-<lb/>prisingly, while evaluating As a transfer into the food chain through rice and rice consumption patterns as well as assessing it&apos;s impact <lb/>on human health not been well addressed to date. Besides these, the consequences of cooking rice with tap water (earlier studies mostly <lb/>done with deionized or ultra-pure water) are also very minimal. To get a realistic scenario of health hazards associated with traditional <lb/>eating habits and cooking practise among the people residing in As-contaminated and As-free areas, the study has been conceptualized. <lb/>In this investigation, four different rice varieties widely cultivated and consumed by the people residing in three As-Hotspot areas as <lb/>well as in As-free areas (designated as control sites) are considered. All the study sites are located within the Lower Indo-Gangetic <lb/>Plain. This particular experiment to investigate the impact of (i) consequences of cooking rice varieties with As-contaminated and <lb/>As-free ground water, (ii) outcomes of consumption of soaked cooked rice (SCR) prepared with As-contaminated and As-free ground <lb/>water on As and Fe transfer pattern and (iii) moreover, a probabilistic heath risk assessment carried out based on the total arsenic or tAs <lb/>content different rice preparation and in tap water (used for cooking, soaking and household work). The outcomes from the inves-<lb/>tigation can help enrich the knowledge of rice eating practices to minimize As content as well as fortify their diets with Fe along with a <lb/>comprehensive health risk assessment. <lb/>2. Materials and methods <lb/>2.1. Sample collection <lb/>In this study, three As-Hotspot areas located in Nadia district, West Bengal India, have been considered. These three administrative <lb/>units are Haringhata, Chandamari, and Tehatta respectively. These areas are regarded as highly contaminated areas located in the <lb/>Ganges-Brahmaputra-Meghna Basin (deltaic alluvium) [68,89]. Here, four high-yielding varieties that differ in their grain <lb/>morphology, origin and agronomic profile are considered. Lalat (Obs.677xIR-207xVikram, Medium and Slender, 4.0 t ha -1 ); Ranjit <lb/>(Pankaj x Mahsuri, Short Slender, 4.0 t ha -1 ), MTU-7029 (Vasista x Mahsuri, short and bold grain, 5.5 to 6.0 t ha -1 ) and <lb/>IET-4094/Khitis (BU-1 x CR-115, Medium and Slender, 4.0 t ha -1 ) respectively. <lb/>The household (farmers) are selected on the three main parameters (a) they used to consume brown rice regularly (b) used <lb/>cultivated in their own land holdings (minimum 2800.0 m 2 ) for a long time (over 15 years) and (c) dehusked the paddy using wooden <lb/>husking pedal operated manually (commonly known as dheki). Similarly, the same criteria were also applicable to the farmer&apos;s <lb/>households belonging to the control sites. Before collecting samples, they (families) were contacted and on the designated date, <lb/>drinking water (tube well), raw rice, cooked rice and soaked cooked rice (soaked for 12 h) were collected. The raw rice (RR), cooked <lb/>rice (CR) and soaked cooked rice (SCR) (including the soaking medium) were collected in a pre-marked plastic zipper pouch and <lb/>transported in an ice box. Ground water samples were collected in 500.0 ml plastic bottles. <lb/>2.2. Rice cooking in the laboratory and preparation of SCR <lb/>In the laboratory, rice samples were cooked in aluminium vessels (popularly called Handi) on an electric heater following the <lb/>traditional cooking method having rice to rice-to-water ratio of 1:3 and the gruel was discarded. Alike the farmer&apos;s family, to prepare <lb/>SCR, after cooling the CR samples were soaked in three times of ground/tap water (As free) and kept at room temperature. <lb/>2.3. Determination of pH of soaking medium used for soaking cooked rice <lb/>In the laboratory, rice samples were cooked in aluminium vessels (popularly called Handi) on an electric heater following the <lb/>traditional cooking method having the rice-to-water ratio of 1:3 and the gruel was discarded. Similar to the farmer&apos;s family, to prepare <lb/>SCR, after cooling the cooked rice, CR samples were soaked in three times of ground/tap water (As free) added into it and kept at room <lb/>temperature. While preparing SCR the pH of the soaking medium was noted at the beginning of the process and after 12 h of soaking. <lb/>First the soaking medium i.e. water of soaked cooked rice separated using a strainer followed by Whatman&apos;s No.41 filter-paper. Then <lb/>the pH of the filtrate of the SCR soaking medium was determined using Oakton® pH 150 Waterproof Portable pH/mV/Temperature <lb/>Meter in triplicates (Table S2). <lb/>2.4. Elemental quantification and quality control <lb/>Oven-dried raw, CR, SCR were grinded to fine powder and acid digested according to the protocol described earlier [46]. During <lb/>acid digestion, rice flour SRM (standard Reference Material, NIST-USA) 1568a was also digested in triplicate. Furthermore, during <lb/>elemental profiling of water samples, and water-SRM-1640a (also obtained from NIST-USA) were also quantified in triplicate. In the <lb/>process of elemental quantification (As and Fe) process, Agilent Model-FS240 -Atomic Absorption Spectrophotometer with hydride <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>generator (VGA) used (Table S1). <lb/>2.5. Health risk assumption <lb/>The Non-Carcinogenic Risk (NCR) and Carcinogenic Risk (CR) have been estimated via ingestion and dermal pathway by the <lb/>below-established equations (Eqs. (1)-(5)) as per Waste [90] and USEPA [91]: <lb/>CDI ing = <lb/>C m × IR × EF × ED <lb/>BW × AT <lb/>× 10 -3 <lb/>(1) <lb/>CDI derm = <lb/>C m × SL × SA × ABS × EF × ED <lb/>BW × AT <lb/>× 10 -6 <lb/>(2) <lb/>HQ = <lb/>CDI <lb/>RfD <lb/>(3) <lb/>HI = <lb/>∑ <lb/>HQ <lb/>(4) <lb/>ILTCR = CDI × SF <lb/>(5) <lb/>where, CDI (mg kg -1 day -1 ), CDI ing is Chronic Daily Intake via ingestion pathway, CDI derm is Chronic Daily Intake via the dermal <lb/>pathway, HQ is hazard quotient, HI is hazard index, ILTCR is Incremental Lifetime Cancer risk and the rest of the parameters have been <lb/>listed in Tables S7-10. According to USEPA [91], an adverse non-carcinogenic health risk is possible if the HQ value exceeds more than <lb/>1; on the other hand, ILTCR values &lt; 10 -6 indicates negligible cancer risk, the values are between 10 -6 &lt; to &lt; 10 -4 suggests potential <lb/>cancer risk, and if, the ILTCR values showed &gt;10 -4 is suggesting an indication of high-potential cancer risk. It is evident from previous <lb/>studies that the As has a high potential to develop cancer health risks among the exposed population during their lifetime [92-94]. <lb/>Fig. 1. (A) Effects of cooking practice on As content in rice when prepared with (1) As free and (2), contaminated water; (B) Interaction effect of <lb/>varieties and cooking practice on As content when prepared with As contaminated water, (C) Effects of water used (As free or contaminated) on pH <lb/>(D) Interaction effect of varieties and type of water used ((1) As free and (2) contaminated water) on pH. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.5.1. Monte-Carlo probabilistic simulation approach <lb/>Uncertainty of health risk was assessed by using the Monte-Carlo simulation model (Oracle Crystal Ball software, version 11.1.2.3) <lb/>[93]. <lb/>2.6. Statistical analysis <lb/>A three-factor asymmetrical design was adopted to analyze data on cooking type, varieties, and location effects on As, Fe content <lb/>and pH with As-contaminated and free water. These were subjected to ANOVA for comparing means using the Least Significant dif-<lb/>ference (LSD) value. Statistical analysis was done using SAS 9.3 (SAS Institute Inc., USA). The AMMI (Additive Main Effect and <lb/>Multiplicative Interaction) model [95] was used to determine the GE interaction effect. The AMMI model for Nutrient content of the <lb/>i-th variety in the j-th location is given in Eq. (6): <lb/>Y ij = μ + V i + L j + <lb/>∑ <lb/>n λ n δ in δ jn + ϵ ij <lb/>(6) <lb/>where Y ij is the nutrient content of genotype (variety) i in environment (location) j (i = 1, 2, .., 4; j = 1, 2, 3); μ is the grand mean; V i is <lb/>the genotype deviation from the grand mean; L j is the environment (location) deviation; λ n is the singular value for principal <lb/>component (PC) n and, thus, λ 2 <lb/>n is its eigenvalue; δ in is the eigenvector value for variety i and component n; δ jn is the eigenvector value <lb/>for environment j and component n, with both eigenvectors scaled as unit vectors; and ϵ ij is the residual. For AMMI analysis, GEA-R <lb/>(Genotype x Environment Analysis with R for Windows) 4.1 developed by ORACLE AMERICA, INC. and R was used. <lb/>3. Results and discussion <lb/>3.1. As content in RR, CR, cooking practices and varietal prospective <lb/>Variations in grain As (in RR) content can be seen among the four studied varieties cultivated in different As-contaminated lo-<lb/>cations. Among the variety (s) considered here the order of As content in RR was as follows IET-4094 (0.760 mg kg -1 ) &lt; Ranjit (0.791 <lb/>mg kg -1 ) &lt; Lalat (0.838 mg kg -1 ) &lt; MTU-7029 (0.920 mg kg -1 ) on dry weight basis. Upon cooking, a significant increase in As <lb/>content can be observed compared to RR, when the cooking medium was As-rich ground water (Fig. 1(A) &amp; (B); Table 1 and Table S1). <lb/>The household collection carried out from As-Hotspot areas, suggests that a noteworthy enhancement in As content of cooked rice took <lb/>place, irrespective of the variety (s) and location (s). On an average, the CR portion of the Ranjit variety exhibited a 42.61% <lb/>enhancement in As content, followed by Lalat (15.81%), MTU-7029 (15.43%) and IET-4094 (15.21%), when compared with the As <lb/>content in RR of the respective varieties. European Union (EU) has classified (No 1308/2013) rice into three distinct classes. Rice <lb/>varieties with round/short bold grain (MTU-7029), long and similar to medium slender (IET-4094, Lalat, Ranjit) have been considered <lb/>[96]. These four high-yielding varieties differ in their grain morphology, parental origin, yield attributes as well as in crop dura-<lb/>tion/period. Results showed a variety-wise, location-wise variation in As and Fe content in RR (Fig. 1(A) &amp; (B)). <lb/>Among the studied varieties considered here the highest grain As content found in MTU-7029 (SB grain; 0.857-1.019 mg kg -1 ) &gt; <lb/>Lalat (MS grain; 0.728-0.927 mg kg -1 ) &gt; IET-4094(MS grain; 0.676-0.887 mg kg -1 ) &gt; Ranjit (MS grain; 0.683-0.846 mg kg -1 ). The <lb/>trend of greater As accumulation by short and bold (SB) and round types grain earlier viewed was observed by Refs. [61,89,97]. <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Impact of cooking practices, cooking medium, variety and locations on As and Fe content in rice. <lb/>Treatments <lb/>As the content in rice <lb/>Fe content in rice <lb/>Prepared with As contaminated <lb/>water <lb/>Prepared with As free <lb/>water <lb/>Prepared with As contaminated <lb/>water <lb/>Prepared with As free <lb/>water <lb/>Cooking Practice <lb/>Cooked rice <lb/>0.991 b <lb/>0.666 b <lb/>6.583 b <lb/>9.079 b <lb/>Soaked-Cooked <lb/>Rice <lb/>1.073 a <lb/>0.908 a <lb/>6.909 a <lb/>10.52 a <lb/>LSD (p ≤ 0.05) <lb/>0.0276 <lb/>0.0239 <lb/>0.324 <lb/>0.358 <lb/>Variety <lb/>Lalat <lb/>0.980 c <lb/>0.802 b <lb/>6.985 b <lb/>10.795 b <lb/>Ranjit <lb/>1.193 a <lb/>0.769 b <lb/>6.085 c <lb/>8.318 c <lb/>MTU-7029 <lb/>1.054 b <lb/>0.852 a <lb/>5.701 c <lb/>8.551 c <lb/>IET-4094 <lb/>0.901 d <lb/>0.726 c <lb/>8.213 a <lb/>11.54 a <lb/>LSD (p ≤ 0.05) <lb/>0.039 <lb/>0.034 <lb/>0.458 <lb/>0.506 <lb/>Locations <lb/>Haringhata <lb/>1.046 b <lb/>0.803 b <lb/>6.051 b <lb/>6.854 c <lb/>Chandamari <lb/>0.910 c <lb/>0.697 c <lb/>8.098 a <lb/>8.893 b <lb/>Tehatta <lb/>1.140 a <lb/>0.861 a <lb/>6.089 b <lb/>6.532 c <lb/>Control site <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>16.92a <lb/>LSD (p ≤ 0.05) <lb/>0.0337 <lb/>0.029 <lb/>0.397 <lb/>0.506 <lb/># Values bearing identical letter cases are not significantly (at p &lt; 0.05 level) different. NA-Not applicable. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Enhancement of As content in CR portion observed in the samples collected from As-contaminated areas, where the people used <lb/>ACW to cook As-rich RR. A comparatively greater As content in cooked rice observed, when As-rich-RR cooked with ACW supports the <lb/>views laid by several groups [98-101]. The enhancement in As content of cooked rice may attributed to the elevated As load in the <lb/>cooking medium resulting from evaporation/chelation by RR occurring during cooking [102] (Fig. 1(B)). <lb/>On the other hand, when As-rich-RR is cooked with AFW there is a noteworthy reduction in As content of CR compared to the RR, <lb/>applicable to all the sampling sites and varieties. The decrease in As content in CR may be due to the absence of As in the cooking <lb/>medium and pour-out practice of gruel. Moreover, if look into the differences As content in CR-AFW and CR-AFW lies in the range of <lb/>23.47-45.05%, advocating in favour of cooking practice with AFW and the subsequent impact on human health (Table 1 and Table S1). <lb/>It was found that when rice is prepared with ACW, it builds up a significant amount of As even after cooking as compared to the rice <lb/>prepared with AFW. Interaction of variety with location and As contaminated water was significant at 5% level of significance. Overall, <lb/>Ranjit showed a higher amount of As, compared to others followed by MTU 7029. As far as location effect is concerned, Tehatta showed <lb/>a higher amount of As (Fig. 1(A) &amp; (B); Table 1 and Figs. 1-3). <lb/>Biplots of additive main effects and multiplicative interaction (AMMI) PCA1 score vs (A) As content in cooked rice, (B) As content in <lb/>soaked-cooked rice, (C) Fe content in cooked rice and (D) Fe content in soaked-cooked rice have been presented in Fig. 2 (A, B, C &amp; D). <lb/>The reduction in As content in CR lies in the range of 11.67-23.63% when compared to the As content of respective As load in RR. The <lb/>impact of the cooking medium can be assumed on the fact that when AFW was used for cooking it can reduce 23.47-45.05 % As in <lb/>cooked rice fraction, compared to the cooking practice using ACW as the cooking medium. The reduction in As content of CR compared <lb/>to the As content of RR when cooked with As-free water supports the observations of Moulick et al. [39,44]. <lb/>3.2. Fe content in RR, CR cooking practices and varietal prospective <lb/>When RR (As rich) cooked with ACW (household collection) located in As-Hotspot areas, an enhancement in Fe content of cooked <lb/>rice is visible. For Fe enhancement in cooked rice lies in the following order Lalat variety (8.61-15.70%) &gt; Ranjit (3.51-7.01%) &gt; <lb/>MTU-7029 (2.90-5.55%) &gt; IET-4094 (2.96-4.02%). In another scenario, when As-rich-RR are cooked in AFW, the order Fe <lb/>enhancement in CR is as follows Lalat (25.66%) &gt; MTU-7029 (11.80%) &gt; IET-4094 (9.40%) &gt; Ranjit (7.72 %). Here, the noteworthy <lb/>Fig. 2. Biplot of Additive main effects and multiplicative interaction (AMMI) PCA1 score vs (A) As content in cooked rice (B) As content in soaked-<lb/>cooked rice (C) Fe content in cooked rice (D) Fe content in soaked-cooked rice. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>impact of cooking medium (As-contaminated/As-free ground water) is evident (Fig. 1(B)). <lb/>3.3. As and Fe content of soaked cooked rice <lb/>The efforts given to minimize As content from sowing/transplanting to the harvest phase, there are several literatures available on <lb/>plants as well as in rice grain, at maturity. However, efforts of minimizing As load from grain/cooked rice in the post-harvest phase <lb/>have been restricted mostly to the effects of (i) grain polishing, (ii) cooking method variations and recently addressed the (iii) impact of <lb/>rice parboiling on grain/cooked rice As content are available [103-107]. <lb/>During the investigation apart from RR and CR, SCR samples from households as well as soaking medium used for preparing SCR <lb/>(cooked with ACW/AFW) were also analysed. Two distinctive scenarios emerge from the findings of the current study. First, the (i) <lb/>household samples (from As-Hot-Spot areas), where cooking and soaking of rice were both performed with ACW have exhibited an <lb/>enhancement in As content in SCR, compared to the As content of the CR fraction. The order of As content enhancement in SCR is 14.28 <lb/>% (Ranjit) &gt; 10.25 % (MTU -7029) &gt; 4.71% (Lalat) &gt; 4.16% (IET-4094) respectively, on an average. <lb/>On the other hand, (ii) upon comparison when CR (cooked with ACW) were soaked in AFW i.e., As-free ground water (in a lab-<lb/>oratory) had a reduction in As content of SCR. The order of reduction in As content of SCR lies Ranjit (-17.74%) &gt; MTU -7029 <lb/>(-14.30%) &gt; Lalat (-3.17%) &gt; IET-4094 (-0.862%) respectively, than As content in CR fraction. Findings clearly indicate that <lb/>soaking medium (As rich/As free ground water) dose have an influential role on As content in SCR fraction (Figs. 1(C), 2(A) and 3(A); <lb/>Table 1 and Table S3). <lb/>In terms of Fe content in SCR, collected from As -Hotspot areas and As -free sites (designated as control sites) noteworthy <lb/>variations can be seen. In the As -Hotspot areas, where CR soaked in ACW have displayed an increase in Fe content in SCR. A similar <lb/>trend of Fe enrichment is also applicable to SCR when soaked in AFW but with a significantly greater amount. Consequences of soaking <lb/>CR in ACW resulted in Fe enrichment in As-rich SCR in the following order 2.15 % (IET-4094) &lt; 5.12% (Ranjit) &lt; 5.75% (Lalat) &lt; <lb/>6.67% (MTU -7029) respectively. In another situation where, both As -rich as well as As -free RR (control) were soaked in As -free <lb/>ground water had a contrasting trend in Fe content, compared to the respective Fe content in RR. In the As -rich RR when soaked in As <lb/>-free ground water the resulted in SCR had 10.90% (IET-4094) &lt; 28.33% (MTU -7029) &lt; 38.84% (Ranjit) respectively. SCR obtained <lb/>from soaking (CR cooked with As -free water) of control sites had enhancement in Fe load by 66.04% (Ranjit) &gt; 47.77% (MTU -<lb/>7029) &gt; 39.41% (IET-4094) &gt; 30.63 (Lalat) respectively, compared to the Fe content of RR. The impact of the presence of As content in <lb/>Fig. 3. Additive main effects and multiplicative interaction biplot for principal components 1 and 2 (factor 1 and factor 2) for (A) As content in <lb/>cooked rice (B) As content in soaked-cooked rice (C) Fe content in cooked rice (D) Fe content in soaked-cooked rice. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>RR, As content in soaking medium can be visible apart from varietal differences are also evident (Figs. 2(C) &amp; 3(C)). <lb/>Apart from as usual or most popular mode of rice consumption (i.e., CR) among the people residing along the Indian subcontinent, <lb/>eating of sour-rice (popularly known as Panta/Pakhala/Poita/Pani-Bhat/Pazhedhu Saadham etc.) is a common practise, especially <lb/>among the rural population. SCR collected from the household of As-contaminated areas, where RR, cooked and SCR both were <lb/>prepared using ACW suggest that there is an increase in both As and Fe applicable to all the studied varieties and locations. However, <lb/>when compared the Fe content of RR collected from control sites (As-Free areas) which were cooked with AFW and then soaked <lb/>overnight in AFW had a significantly greater amount of Fe in the SCR portion than those SCR collected from households of As <lb/>contaminated areas. The enhancement in Fe content up to 60.042%, compared to the Fe content in RR among the rice varieties <lb/>collected from control sites. Whereas the enhancement of Fe content in SCR portion of As-rich RR were less. The enhancement of Fe <lb/>content in SCR supports the earlier reported findings of [108]. However, the authors didn&apos;t consider the impact of the presence of As <lb/>and G x E effects (interaction among genotype and environment) in their investigation. Findings from present investigation also are <lb/>well-aligned with the findings of [108] in the fact that in both cases after 12 h/overnight soaking of CR is associated with a sharp dip in <lb/>pH value (Figs. 1 (D), 2(B) &amp; 3(B); Tables S1-S3). A decrease in pH value of the soaking medium (water As free/As-rich) might have <lb/>facilitated the growth of lactic acid bacteria-mediated fermentation and modulation in phytate acid content which in turn may be <lb/>attributed to an increase in Fe content in SCR [109-111]. However, the differential behaviour exhibited by As-rich RR and As-free RR <lb/>might be attributed to the presence of As, due to contamination (Fig. 1(D)). <lb/>Consumption of at least two meals of SCR (alkies the local) might help to reduce As burden among the people. However, the soaking <lb/>medium should be As-free water. Cooking and soaking cooked rice in As-free cooking &amp;/or soaking medium could be an alternative, <lb/>easily executed method for As load minimizing and Fe fortification in the post-harvest phase. Speaking of Fe content, it was higher <lb/>when consumed as SCR as compared to cooked rice. Variety IET-4094 consumed as SCR contains the highest amount of Fe content <lb/>among all other varieties. pH of As-contaminated water was significantly different from what was found in As-free water. Varieties and <lb/>locations showed a significant difference among them with respect to pH. High pH values were found in rice of different varieties with <lb/>As-contaminated water when compared with As-free water. This gave a clear indication that As-contaminated water showed a high pH <lb/>as compared to As-free water (Fig. 1(D), 2(B) and 3(B)). <lb/>In the very recent past [112], have reported the consequences of soaking cooked rice for overnight on As and other toxicant and <lb/>nutrient content, using a market-based survey. In their experiment, they used Basmati (Indian long grain, aromatic variety), short grain <lb/>aromatic rice of Bangladesh (aromatic) and Australian-origin brown rice (medium slender morphology) to draw their conclusions. In <lb/>reality, (Lower Indo Gangetic Plain of Indian side) long and short grain, aromatic rice is used occasionally for preparing certain <lb/>delicacy (s) but short-bold and medium -slender grain non-aromatic rice varieties are used throughout the year for preparing and <lb/>consuming as SCR/Panta/Pakhal etc. The aromatic rice variety with a long/extra-long or even having short bold (SB)/round bold (RB) <lb/>grain morphology is generally considered premium-grade rice. In the present investigation, four high-yielding rice varieties with <lb/>different grain morphology, widely cultivated and consumed in rural areas have been studied. Moreover, authors have used tap water <lb/>(As-free) alike us. Their findings regarding the lessening of tAs content in CR as well as SCR, compared to the tAs load in RR support <lb/>previous findings (Fig. 2(D) &amp; 3(D); Table 1 and Table S1). Though this scenario is well aligned with those populations, those who <lb/>purchase (knowingly/unknowingly) As-rich-RR and cooked &amp;/soaked in As-free water (cooking medium). However, the population <lb/>residing in/adjacent to As-Hotspot areas used the As-rich water (collected from a deep tube well, occasionally attached with shallow <lb/>used for irrigation/bore well) there is an enhancement in tAs content observed in both CR as well as SCR too (Table 1 and Table S1), <lb/>reported for the first time from varietal, environment perspective. This situation of transmission of As in greater amounts in the human <lb/>body after consuming As-rich-SCR is really a matter of great concern (Table S1; Fig. 1(A) and (B), 4 &amp; 5) [113]. <lb/>To have a deep insight, one can further have considered the scenario using the same rice variety cultivated in an As-free envi-<lb/>ronment with no traces of As but having a considerable amount of Fe. Rahman et al. [112] have observed negligible/no change in Fe <lb/>content upon cooking and soaking CR in As-free tap water, which differs from current observations from the present investigation. The <lb/>enhancement in Fe content in As-rich RR was significantly less compared to the enhancement exhibited by As-free RR after cooking and <lb/>soaking. The difference in the degree of Fe enhancement among the As-rich RR and As-free RR may be attributed to the antagonistic <lb/>behaviour among As and Fe as well as the presence/absence of As in the cooking medium and variation in the dip of pH value (Fig. 1(C) <lb/>&amp; (D), 2(C) and 3(C); Table 1 and Tables S2-S4). Speaking of Fe content enrichment in SCR prepared after cooking As-free RR in AFW <lb/>and the habit of consuming bay rural as well as a larger portion of the urban population have emerged out to be an effective means of Fe <lb/>enrichment for the population belonging to LMICs (Fig. 2(D) and 3(D)). <lb/>Speaking of efforts made by policymakers to address the IDA, enriching rice with Fe requires approximately 350 million US$+ <lb/>spent per year and keeps increasing, indicating the widespread impact of IDA and the urge to address it. Continuing the effort, the <lb/>government of India has made a special provision of 130 + US$ in FY 2019-2020 to abolish IDA in India [19]. Whereas, a <lb/>meta-analysis-based Cochrane review believed that Fe enrichment in rice (pre-harvest phase) has negligible impact on the average <lb/>haemoglobin content of studied populations [114]. There is no doubt that a policy for minimizing IDA operating in a <lb/>local-regional-global framework level is urgently required [115]. <lb/>3.4. Genotype and environmental interactions <lb/>G × E interaction using the AMMI model in this experiment presented some interesting findings. This model combines the ANOVA <lb/>for the genotype and environmental main effects and PCA with multiplicative indices in a single analysis. Biplot analysis (Fig. 2 (A-D) <lb/>&amp; 3 (A-D)) shows the distribution pattern of As and Fe content present in the CR and SCR fraction, when prepared with As-<lb/>contaminated water, scattered among the study sites. It can be seen from the biplots that varieties and locations with long arrows <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>showed interactive behaviour with the others. Biplot analysis showed that the variety Ranjit in Haringhata showed a significant GE <lb/>interaction as compared to others; whereas the variety Lalat is less responsive to location and had general adaptation to the locations. <lb/>Varieties and locations appeared together and showed more interactive behavior (G x E). The same trend was found in the case of As <lb/>content in SCR prepared with As contaminated water (Fig. 2 (B)). In terms of Fe content, varieties Lalat and MTU-7029 show more <lb/>interactive behavior with Haringhata and Tehatta locations respectively (Fig. 2 (C)). Ranjit and IET-4094 varieties are not responsive <lb/>to different locations in both cases as CR rice, as well as SCR (Fig. 2(D)), are concerned. As far as the AMMI-biplot analysis with PC1 and <lb/>PC2 is concerned, the variety Lalat was affected least by the GE interaction followed by MTU-7029 in the case of As content in CR <lb/>cooked with ACW. However, when prepared as soaked-cooked rice MTU-7029 and IET-4094 varieties behaved similarly (Fig. 3). <lb/>3.5. Health risk assumption associated with As <lb/>Among men, women and children, CDI associated with RR, CR-ACW, CR-AFW, SCR-ACW, and SCR-AFW have shown values <lb/>ranging from 1.25 × 10 -03 to 1.94 × 10 -03 and 2.25 × 10 -03 to 3.56 × 10 -03 , respectively. This particular trend of CDI is irrespective <lb/>of sampling sites and the rice varieties. Surprisingly, it is also important to note the average CDI values were found high among men <lb/>population in the following combination of places and rice consumption habits/varietal preferences: Lalat rice -Tehatta; Ranjit -<lb/>Haringhata; MTU-7029 -Tehatta; and IET-4094 -Tehatta, respectively. Irrespective of sampling sites and consumption of rice vari-<lb/>eties. Findings also suggested that among three groups, the children population showed the highest average CDI values irrespective of <lb/>places, rice and type of rice consumption practice. It was also noted that, among places, people of Tehatta showed the highest CDI <lb/>values for men, women and children (Table S6). <lb/>Table S7 represents the HQ and HI associated with the RR, CR-ACW, CR-AFW, SCR-ACW, and SCR-AFW through oral ingestion <lb/>pathway among men, women and children. Among the male, women and children population, HQ linked with RR, CR-ACW, CR-AFW, <lb/>SCR-ACW, and SCR-AFW have shown values ranging from 4.16 to 6.57, and 7.51-11.86, respectively. Results also suggested that <lb/>among these three studied groups, the children showed the highest average HQ value (10) followed by men (5.56) and women (5.47) <lb/>regardless of places, rice varieties and types of rice consumption. It was also noted that, among locations, Tehatta has the highest HQ <lb/>values for men, women and children. Table S7 also revealed that the overall HI or Hazard Index was found highest among children. <lb/>Among men, the HI values ranged from 22.52 to 32.97, among women it ranged from 22.15 to 32.47 and among children it was found <lb/>from 4.67 to 59.53. It was interesting to note HI values of men, women and children showed the highest values for the population of <lb/>Tehatta location who habituated to consuming the rice variety MTU-7029 and the lowest was found in the population of the Har-<lb/>inghata who were used to consuming IET-4094 rice variety. <lb/>Incremental Lifetime Cancer Risk among men, women, and children ILTCR from allied with RR, CR-ACW, CR-AFW, SCR-ACW, and <lb/>SCR-AFW have shown values ranging from 7.69 × 10 -04 to 1.22 × 10 -03 , 7.57 × 10 -04 to 1.20 × 10 -03 , and 2.78 × 10 -04 to 4.39 × <lb/>10 -04 , respectively, regardless of sampling sites and consumption of rice varieties. It was also important to note the average ILTCR <lb/>values were found high among men population (Table S8). <lb/>On the contrary, the analysis also suggested that among the three groups, the men showed the highest average ILTCR value (1.03 × <lb/>10 -03 ) followed by women (1.01 × 10 -03 ) and Children (3.71 × 10 -04 ) notwithstanding places, rice varieties and types of rice <lb/>consumption pattern. It was also noted that, overall, among places Tehatta has the highest HQ values for men, women and children. <lb/>Among men, the average ILTCR values ranged from 8.33 × 10 -04 to 1.22 × 10 -03 . Among women, it ranged from 8.20 × 10 -04 to 1.20 <lb/>× 10 -03 and among children it was found from 3.01 × 10-04 to 4.40 × 10 -04 . It was interesting to note that ILTCR values of men, <lb/>women and children showed the highest values for the Tehatta population who habituated to consuming the MTU-7029 variety of rice <lb/>and the lowest found in the case of the Haringhata population who used to consume the IET-4094 rice variety (Table S8). <lb/>Moreover, rice varieties containing As and further cooked with As-CW showed a greater health risk among men, women and <lb/>children irrespective of multiple locations. A similar observation was also found that ILTCR values showed similar high end in the case <lb/>of cooked rice and soaked cooked rice when the population using As-contaminated water and low values when using AFW for cooking <lb/>and soaking. The risk from consumption of rice cooked with AFW is comparatively lesser than those cooked with ACW. This may be <lb/>due to the large amount of rice consumption by the local people which outweighs the reduction of As during the cooking process of <lb/>rice. Apart from cancer risk, other detrimental health effects have been associated with low levels of As exposure, including genotoxic <lb/>effects [60,116]. The recommended safe limit of ILTCR as per USEPA 2001 [91] should be 1 × 10 -06 . In the present study, the ILTCR <lb/>values were higher than the recommended values. Rehman et al. [117] reported the development of cancer risk in 2.3 (adult) and 13 <lb/>(children) extra individuals per 100,000 through ingestion of leafy vegetables collected from agricultural lands located in the Khyber <lb/>Pakhtunkhwa Province of Pakistan (Tables S8 and S9). <lb/>The HI values were 115 times and 113 times higher in the case of men and women population and almost 50 times higher in the case <lb/>of children, beyond the permissible value of 1. The average ILTCR values via ingestion pathway for drinking As -contaminated ground <lb/>water also exhibit higher than safe limit i.e., 1 × 10 -06 (Table S1). The CDI, HQ, HI and ILTCR values related to drinking ACW water via <lb/>ingestion pathway among men women and children residing at Haringhata, Chandamari and Tehatta which was categorised according <lb/>to consumption of rice types. It was revealed that among men, women, and children the CDI of arsenic ranges between 2.27-3.23 × <lb/>10 -03 ; and 2.24-3.18 × 10 -03 , 9.84 × 10 -04 to 1.40 × 10 -03 , respectively. <lb/>The highest average CDI was observed for men (2.88 × 10 -03 ) followed by women (2.84 × 10 -03 ) and children (1.25 × 10 -03 ) <lb/>irrespective of sampling sites and consumption of rice varieties. Table S1 also revealed that among men, women, and children the HQ <lb/>of arsenic ranges between 7.57 and 10.75, 7.46-10.59, and 3.28-4.66, respectively. According to HI, the highest hazard risk was found <lb/>among men (115.29) population followed by women (113.54) and children (49.96) via ingestion pathway. It was also noted that <lb/>among men, women and children the ILTCR value ranges between 1.40 × 10 -03 to 1.99 × 10 -03, 1.38 × 10 -03 to 1.96 × 10 -03 and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>(caption on next page) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>6.07 × 10 -04 to 8.62 × 10 -04 , respectively. The highest average ILTCR have observed for men (1.78 × 10 -03 ) followed by women <lb/>(1.75 × 10 -03 ) and children (7.70 × 10 -04 ) via ingestion pathway (Table S1). The CDI, HQ, HI and ILTCR associated with As exposure <lb/>via dermal pathway among men women and children residing at Haringhata, Chandamari and Tehatta were also considered here. The <lb/>average CDI have observed for men (3.88 × 10 -10 ) &lt; women (4.53 × 10 -10 ) &lt; children (2.33 × 10 -09 ). It was revealed that among <lb/>men, women and children the HQ of As ranges between 2.46-3.49 × 10 -06 ; 2.90-4.12 × 10 -06 and 1.49-2.12 × 10 -05 respectively. <lb/>According to HI, the highest hazard risk was found among the children (2.27 × 10 -04 ) population followed by women (4.42 × 10 -05 ) <lb/>and men (3.74 × 10 -05 ) via dermal pathway (Table S9). Results also revealed that among men, women and children the ILTCR of <lb/>arsenic ranges between 4.54 × 10 -10 to 6.45 × 10 -10 ; 5.37 × 10 -10 to 7.63 × 10 -10 ; and 5.53 × 10 -10 to 7.85 × 10 -10 , respectively. <lb/>The highest average ILTCR have observed for children (7.01 × 10 -10 ) followed by women (6.81 × 10 -10 ) and children (6.81 × 10 -10 ) <lb/>via dermal pathway (Table S9). <lb/>On the contrary, the estimated HI and ILTCR values via dermal pathway for drinking water arsenic showed under the safe limit. In <lb/>this regard, it must be noted that although the participants consumed vegetables irregularly in terms of amount and frequency, there <lb/>may still be an underestimation of inorganic arsenic exposure from diet, if only rice is used as a proxy for As exposure for staple foods. <lb/>As previously indicated, participant&apos;s residence histories were not known, but an effort to get around this limitation by selecting people <lb/>who had resided in their communities for a long period both before and after the transition from tube-wells to pipe-borne water <lb/>(Table S10). From the current study, the increasing order of types of rice eating habits is SCR-ACW &gt; CR-ACW &gt; SCR-AFW &gt; CR-AFW. <lb/>Fig. 4. Monte-Carlo probabilistic distribution of the NCR associated with As-rich rice intake via ingestion pathway for men (A), for women (B), for <lb/>children (C), and CR from rice arsenic intake via ingestion pathway for men (D), for women (E) and children (F). Distribution of the NCR associated <lb/>with drinking As-contaminated ground water intake via ingestion pathway for men (G), for women (H), for children (I), and CR from drinking water <lb/>arsenic intake via ingestion pathway for men (J), form women (K) and children (L). NCR linked with exposure to As -contaminated via dermal <lb/>pathway applicable to men (M), for women (N), for children (O), and CR from drinking via dermal pathway water arsenic for men (P), for women (Q) <lb/>and children (R). <lb/>Fig. 5. Cumulative comparative NCR (A) and CR (B) frequency distribution among men, women and children from rice intake via ingestion <lb/>pathway. Cumulative comparative NCR (C) and CR (D) frequency distribution among men, women and children from drinking water via ingestion <lb/>pathway. Cumulative comparative NCR (E) and CR (F) frequency distribution among men, women and children from drinking water via <lb/>dermal pathway. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Evaluation of As exposure biomarkers is crucial because it gives comprehensive information about the many sources of As exposure, <lb/>including drinking water, diet as well as soil, and air may be used to offset such arsenic exposure assessment bias [75,118]. <lb/>3.6. Monte Carlo probabilistic simulation model for uncertainty analysis <lb/>Measurement of uncertainty is extremely important for the estimation of health risks. Uncertainty is usually governed by various <lb/>factors such as the level of pollutants (As concentration here), variability of exposure, toxicity of pollutants, duration of exposure, etc. <lb/>Similarly, sensitivity analysis also depends on numerous exposure variables. <lb/>In the present analysis, overall uncertainty of non-carcinogenic risk (NCR) and carcinogenic risk (CR) both from rice intake in <lb/>various forms and drinking water intake were evaluated among men, women, and children. After running the simulation model <lb/>(100000 cycles), the median value of NCR for rice intake for men was found 5.38 (certainty range from 3.02 to 7.84), for women 5.29 <lb/>(certainty range from 2.96 to 7.74) and for children 9.76 (certainty range from 5.42 to 14.46) at a 95% level of confidence interval <lb/>respectively (Fig. 4 (A-C)). On the other hand, the carcinogenic risk for rice intake via ingestion pathway is depicted in Fig. 4 (D-F). The <lb/>median value of carcinogenic risk for rice intake for men was found 9.70 × 10 -4 (certainty range from 5.40 × 10 -4 -1.42 × 10 -3 ), for <lb/>women 9.60 × 10 -4 (certainty range from 5.30 × 10 -4 -1.40 × 10 -3 ) and finally for the children 3.52 × 10 -4 (certainty range from <lb/>1.95 × 10 -4 -5.22 × 10 -4 ) at a 95% level of confidence interval. <lb/>Human may be exposed to As in water via ingestion as well as by dermal exposure so uncertainty may also present during risk <lb/>estimation. Fig. 4 (G-L) represent the NCR and CR uncertainty via the ingestion pathway. From Fig. 4 (G-I), the median value of non-<lb/>carcinogenic risk for water intake for men was found 9.15 (certainty range from 6.88 to 11.59), for women 9.08 (certainty range from <lb/>6.81 to 11.52) and for the children 21.26 (certainty range from 16.04 to 26.73) at a 95% level of confidence interval, respectively. On <lb/>the other hand, the carcinogenic risk for water intake via ingestion pathway is depicted in (Fig. 4 (J-L)). The median value of CR for <lb/>water intake was 1.65 × 10 -3 , 1.64 × 10 -3 and 7.70 × 10 -4 associated with men, women, and children respectively, at a 95% level of <lb/>confidence interval. <lb/>Fig. 4(M-R) represents the scenario of uncertainty of NCR and CR from drinking water arsenic via dermal pathway among men, <lb/>women, and children. From Fig. 4 (M -O), the median value of non-carcinogenic risk for men was found 3.10 × 10 -6 3.69 × 10 -6 <lb/>(women) and 2.02 × 10 -5 (children) at a 95% level of confidence interval. On the other hand, at a 95% level of confidence interval, the <lb/>CR associated with As content of water and the population were exposed via the dermal pathway depicted in Fig. 4 (P-R). The median <lb/>value of CR was 5.59 × 10 -10 , 6.66 × 10 -10 and 7.30 × 10 -10 applicable to men, women, and children respectively. <lb/>Probabilistic study results also revealed that the children residing at the study sites were more susceptible to non-carcinogenic risk <lb/>from the presence of As in both rice and water trailed by men and women. The carcinogenic risks are associated with As for children, <lb/>men and women in the following order children &lt; men &lt; women. Fig. S1 (A-R) represent the sensitive factor analysis which may <lb/>influence the risk estimation steps. After running 1,00,000 trials the simulation results highlighted that the concentration of As present <lb/>in rice and water samples was the most influential factor regarding the health risk estimation for men, women and children. In that <lb/>case, exposure duration and ingestion rate were the two sensitive factors that have mostly contributed to estimating the toxicological <lb/>risk, except for the dermal pathway. Where, drinking water enriched with As, exposed to body surface i.e. skin area and skin adherence <lb/>factor of men, women and children were the three important parameters which may display influence during the health risk analysis. <lb/>The above findings were also visible from the comparative cumulative frequency distribution curve among men, women and children. <lb/>Fig. 5 (A-B) represents the comparative cumulative frequency distribution of NCR and CR among three groups from rice intake, while <lb/>Fig. 5 (C-F) represents the comparative NCR and CR distribution among three groups from drinking water arsenic via ingestion and <lb/>dermal pathway. <lb/>An initiative taken up by WHO and FAO called risk assessment, to protect human health from adverse environmental consequences. <lb/>During risk assessment, a scientific approach for appraising the latent effects of risk factors on human populations was evaluated. This <lb/>process embraces risk documentation, exposure calculation along with dose-response relationship valuation, and defining risk char-<lb/>acteristics [119]. Numerous factors govern the health risks assessment associated As via rice eating. These factors comprise factors like <lb/>frequency of rice consumption, consumption of rice per capita, type and probability of intrinsic risk caused by As and concentration, <lb/>body weight of subject, and duration of exposure to As. Moreover, eating habits like SCR were added to this list from this investigation. <lb/>Therefore, the typical levels of As in rice (forms of rice like CR and SCR) should be diverse among regions, and applying the standards <lb/>for As permitted in a particular country could not be the foundation for other countries. In order to make a comparative assessment <lb/>with the previously available standards, only gives a partial picture of the permitted level. Thus, in this study the CR and NCR <lb/>associated with As here have been incorporated (Tables S4-S10 and Fig. S1). <lb/>4. Conclusions <lb/>Varietal, environmental, and interactive aspects of As and other micronutrients in rice grain have been reported from time to time <lb/>from various As-contaminated regions. However, a comparative account addressing the role of cooking practice and eating habits of <lb/>the local population from As-free and As-rich areas using AMMI modelling has been reported for the first time. The findings of the study <lb/>give serious attention to the transmission of As into the food chain through rice-based popular delicacies (like SCR/Panta here) that <lb/>need to be taken into account. Earlier, health risks regarding As content in rice were restricted up to considering the As content in <lb/>cooked rice only. Here, the health risks based on tAs content in cooked rice, soaked cooked rice, drinking water as well as dermal <lb/>exposure have been computed. Thus, we aimed to provide a holistic scenario aligned with ground reality. Differential behaviour in <lb/>terms of tAs content in CR, and SCR when cooked and soaked in ACW and AFW demands further in-depth analysis to get a broader <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/>R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>picture. The choice of rice variety for cultivation and domestic consumption by small householders and people residing nearby in As-<lb/>contaminated areas needs to be considered while assessing the ILCR, and HQ for As. If the policymakers in different capacities could <lb/>implement a mean to provide As-free water (AFW) for household consumption and cooking to the residents of As-contaminated areas, <lb/>would help to minimize As load from transmission into the human body. Fe enrichment in SCR (mostly in As-free rice, cooked, soaked <lb/>in AFW) as an economically sound mean for Fe-biofortification in the post-harvest phase can be further assessed by analysing the bio-<lb/>accessibility of Fe from SCR using gastro epithelial cell line/selected volunteers (through clinical trials) conducted under the super-<lb/>vision of concerned regulatory bodies (e.g. Indian Council for Medical Research or ICMR in India). Thereafter, by implementing the <lb/>outcomes on a larger canvas by popularizing SCR-based preparations (like in the mid-day meal programme etc.) can solve the issue of <lb/>Fe-Malnutrition among the population, especially among the women (including pregnant and lactating) and children. Researchers <lb/>working constantly in developing suitable varieties for cultivation in As-contaminated paddy fields may also be considered for <lb/>incorporation of the traits related to the efficacy of Fe retention and/or enrichment at post-harvest phase in their venture. <lb/></body>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The study was funded by Department of Environmental Science, University of Kalyani, Nadia, West Bengal-741235, India. This <lb/>project was supported by Researchers Supporting Project Number (RSP2024R230), King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Ethics statement <lb/>We confirm that the study complies with all regulations and confirmation that informed consent was obtained from the participants <lb/>in collecting these samples. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>All the data are available in supplementary files. Data will be made available on request. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>Debojyoti Moulick: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Validation, Software, Resources, Methodology, Investigation, Formal <lb/>analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. Dibakar Ghosh: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Validation, Supervision, Meth-<lb/>odology, Investigation, Conceptualization. Yogita Gharde: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Validation, Software, Methodology, <lb/>Investigation, Conceptualization. Arnab Majumdar: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Validation, Resources, Methodology, <lb/>Investigation, Formal analysis, Conceptualization. Munish Kumar Upadhyay: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Resources, <lb/>Methodology, Investigation, Conceptualization. Deep Chakraborty: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Resources, Methodology, <lb/>Investigation, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. Subrata Mahanta: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Valida-<lb/>tion, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Conceptualization. Anupam Das: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Valida-<lb/>tion, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Conceptualization. Shuvasish Choudhury: Writing -original draft, Visualization, <lb/>Validation, Supervision, Methodology, Investigation, Conceptualization. Marian Brestic: Writing -review &amp; editing, Supervision, <lb/>Project administration, Funding acquisition, Formal analysis, Data curation. Tahani Awad Alahmadi: Writing -review &amp; editing, <lb/>Writing -original draft, Software, Project administration, Funding acquisition, Formal analysis, Data curation. Mohammad Javed <lb/>Ansari: Writing -review &amp; editing, Writing -original draft, Software, Formal analysis, Data curation. Shubhas Chandra Santra: <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing, Writing -original draft, Visualization, Validation, Supervision, Methodology, Investigation, Conceptu-<lb/>alization. Akbar Hossain: Writing -review &amp; editing, Writing -original draft, Supervision, Software, Resources, Funding acquisition, <lb/>Formal analysis, Data curation. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Declaration of generative AI and AI-assisted technologies in the writing process <lb/>We the authors at the stage of writing this article didn&apos;t use any AI and AI-assisted technologies. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to <lb/>influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

            <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors want to acknowledge the Department of Environmental Science, University of Kalyani, Nadia, West Bengal-741235, <lb/>India. This project was supported by Researchers Supporting Project Number (RSP2024R230), King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi <lb/>Arabia. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Supplementary data <lb/>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e28296. <lb/>References <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] P. Ranum, J.P. Peña-Rosas, M.N. Garcia-Casal, Global maize production, utilization, and consumption, Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 1312 (2014) 105-112. <lb/>[2] A. Majumdar, Arsenic Bio-Regulation Management and Altered Plant Physiology under Different Irrigation Regime, 2021. <lb/>[3] D. Mridha, J. Sarkar, A. Majumdar, K. Sarkar, A. Maiti, K. Acharya, M. Das, H. Chen, N.K. Niazi, T. Roychowdhury, Evaluation of iron-modified biochar on <lb/>arsenic accumulation by rice: a pathway to assess human health risk from cooked rice, Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. (2024) 1-19. <lb/>[4] D.T. Heitkemper, K.M. Kubachka, P.R. Halpin, M.N. Allen, N. V Shockey, Survey of total arsenic and arsenic speciation in US-produced rice as a reference point <lb/>for evaluating change and future trends, Food Addit. Contam. 2 (2009) 112-120. <lb/>[5] S. Islam, M.M. Rahman, M.R. Islam, R. Naidu, Effect of irrigation and genotypes towards reduction in arsenic load in rice, Sci. Total Environ. 609 (2017) <lb/>311-318, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.07.111. <lb/>[6] K.E. Nachman, T. Punshon, L. Rardin, A.J. Signes-Pastor, C.J. Murray, B.P. Jackson, M. Lou Guerinot, T.A. Burke, C.Y. Chen, H. Ahsan, Opportunities and <lb/>challenges for dietary arsenic intervention, Environ. Health Perspect. 126 (2018) 84503. <lb/>[7] A. Majumdar, P.K. Dubey, B. Giri, D. Moulick, A.K. Srivastava, T. Roychowdhury, S. Bose, M.K. Jaiswal, Combined effects of dry-wet irrigation, redox changes <lb/>and microbial diversity on soil nutrient bioavailability in the rice field, Soil Tillage Res. 232 (2023) 105752. <lb/>[8] A. Majumdar, M.K. Upadhyay, B. Giri, J. Karwadiya, S. Bose, M.K. Jaiswal, Iron oxide doped rice biochar reduces soil-plant arsenic stress, improves nutrient <lb/>values: an amendment towards sustainable development goals, Chemosphere 312 (2023) 137117. <lb/>[9] R. Mondal, A. Majumdar, S. Sarkar, C. Goswami, M. Joardar, A. Das, P.K. Mukhopadhyay, T. Roychowdhury, An extensive review of arsenic dynamics and its <lb/>distribution in soil-aqueous-rice plant systems in south and Southeast Asia with bibliographic and meta-data analysis, Chemosphere (2024) 141460. <lb/>[10] Y. Huang, M. Wang, X. Mao, Y. Qian, T. Chen, Y. Zhang, Concentrations of inorganic arsenic in milled rice from China and associated dietary exposure <lb/>assessment, J. Agric. Food Chem. 63 (2015) 10838-10845. <lb/>[11] J.C. Kwon, Z.D. Nejad, M.C. Jung, Arsenic and heavy metals in paddy soil and polished rice contaminated by mining activities in Korea, Catena 148 (2017) <lb/>92-100. <lb/>[12] A.A. Meharg, E. Lombi, P.N. Williams, K.G. Scheckel, J. Feldmann, A. Raab, Y. Zhu, R. Islam, Speciation and localization of arsenic in white and brown rice <lb/>grains, Environ. Sci. Technol. 42 (2008) 1051-1057, https://doi.org/10.1021/es702212p. <lb/>[13] A. Majumdar, F. Afsal, S. Pathak, M.K. Upadhayay, T. Roychowdhury, S. Srivastava, Molecular aspects of arsenic responsive microbes in soil-plant-aqueous <lb/>triphasic systems, in: Glob. Arsen. Hazard Ecotoxicol. Remediat, Springer, 2022, pp. 291-312. <lb/>[14] M.K. Upadhyay, A. Majumdar, Heavy metals&apos; stress responses in field crops, Response F. Crop. to Abiotic Stress Curr. Status Futur. Prospect (2022) 45. <lb/>[15] A. Majumdar, M.K. Upadhyay, B. Giri, P. Yadav, D. Moulick, S. Sarkar, B.K. Thakur, K. Sahu, A.K. Srivastava, M. Buck, Sustainable water management in rice <lb/>cultivation reduces arsenic contamination, increases productivity, microbial molecular response, and profitability, J. Hazard Mater. (2024) 133610. <lb/>[16] I. Var, S. Özçakmak, A. Tekin, S. Yılmaz, B. Heshmati, O. Uçkun, A. Çetinkaya, Evaluation of food safety of commercial baby foods according to legal <lb/>regulations, Eur. J. Agric. Food Sci. 3 (2021) 72-80. <lb/>[17] A. Shrivastava, Dietary arsenic exposure: sources and risks, Arsen. Toxic. Challenges Solut. (2021) 95-125. <lb/>[18] A. Majumdar, D. Moulick, S. Srivastava, &apos;Save Soil&apos;by managing soil nutrient losses, agronomic practices and crop-microbial interaction: world Soil Day 2022, <lb/>Front. Sustain. Food Syst. 8 (2024) 1360937. <lb/>[19] A. V Kurpad, S. Ghosh, T. Thomas, S. Bandyopadhyay, R. Goswami, A. Gupta, P. Gupta, A.T. John, U. Kapil, B. Kulkarni, Perspective: when the cure might <lb/>become the malady: the layering of multiple interventions with mandatory micronutrient fortification of foods in India, Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 114 (2021) <lb/>1261-1266. <lb/>[20] A. Majumdar, M.K. Upadhyay, M. Ojha, F. Afsal, B. Giri, S. Srivastava, S. Bose, Enhanced phytoremediation of Metal (loid) s via spiked ZVI nanoparticles: an <lb/>urban clean-up strategy with ornamental plants, Chemosphere 288 (2022) 132588. <lb/>[21] M.B. Zimmermann, R.F. Hurrell, Nutritional iron deficiency, Lancet 370 (2007) 511-520. <lb/>[22] Y. Fu, X. Yang, H. Shen, Root iron plaque alleviates cadmium toxicity to rice (Oryza sativa) seedlings, Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 161 (2018) 534-541. <lb/>[23] M.K. Upadhyay, A. Majumdar, A.K. Srivastava, S. Bose, P. Suprasanna, S. Srivastava, Antioxidant enzymes and transporter genes mediate arsenic stress <lb/>reduction in rice (Oryza sativa L.) upon thiourea supplementation, Chemosphere 292 (2022) 133482. <lb/>[24] N.R. Chowdhury, A. Das, M. Joardar, D. Mridha, A. De, S. Majumder, J. Mandal, A. Majumdar, T. Roychowdhury, Distribution of arsenic in rice grain from <lb/>West Bengal, India: its relevance to geographical origin, variety, cultivars and cultivation season, in: Glob. Arsen. Hazard Ecotoxicol. Remediat, Springer, 2022, <lb/>pp. 509-531. <lb/>[25] WHO, Arsenic in drinking-water, Background document for development of WHO guidelines for drinking-water quality, WHO/SDE/WSH/03.04/75/Rev/1 <lb/>Arsenic (2011), p. 11. Available link: https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/75375/WHO_SDE_WSH_03.04_75_eng.pdf. <lb/>[26] R.S. Bhatnagar, O.I. Padilla-Zakour, Plant-based dietary practices and socioeconomic factors that influence anemia in India, Nutrients 13 (2021) 3538. <lb/>[27] R. Plessow, N.K. Arora, B. Brunner, C. Tzogiou, K. Eichler, U. Brügger, S. Wieser, Social costs of iron deficiency anemia in 6-59-month-old children in India, <lb/>PLoS One 10 (2015) e0136581. <lb/>[28] H.X. Jia, J.H. Han, H.Z. Li, D. Liang, T.T. Deng, S.Y. Chang, Mineral intake in urban pregnant women from base diet, fortified foods, and food supplements: <lb/>focus on calcium, iron, and zinc, Biomed. Environ. Sci. 29 (2016) 898-901. <lb/>[29] G.J. Anderson, D.M. Frazer, Current understanding of iron homeostasis, Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 106 (2017) 1559S-1566S. <lb/>[30] A. Majumdar, M. kumar Upadhyay, A.K. Srivastava, S. Srivastava, S. Bose, Soil geochemical dynamics of arsenic and nutrients affects microbial diversity, <lb/>elemental release and plant-microbe interactions: a long-term study from field to genomics, in: 2022 Goldschmidt Conf., GOLDSCHMIDT, 2022. <lb/>[31] Fernández-Gaxiola AC, De-Regil LM. Intermittent iron supplementation for reducing anaemia and its associated impairments in menstruating women. <lb/>Cochrane Database Syst. Rev. 12 (2011) Art. No.: CD009218, pp. 72. DOI: 10.1002/14651858.CD009218.pub2. <lb/>[32] A. Majumdar, M.K. Upadhyay, P.K. Dubey, B. Giri, A.K. Srivastava, S. Srivastava, Effect of Combined Dry-Wet Irrigation and Microbial Dynamics on Soil <lb/>Nutrient Bioavailability, 2022. <lb/>[33] S. Swaminathan, S. Ghosh, J.S. Varghese, H.S. Sachdev, A. V Kurpad, T. Thomas, Dietary iron intake and anemia are weakly associated, limiting effective iron <lb/>fortification strategies in India, J. Nutr. 149 (2019) 831-839. <lb/>[34] A. Gupta, A. Majumdar, S. Srivastava, Approaches for assisted phytoremediation of arsenic contaminated sites, in: Assist. Phytoremediation, Elsevier, 2022, <lb/>pp. 221-242. <lb/>[35] N. Tyagi, M.K. Upadhyay, A. Majumdar, S.K. Pathak, B. Giri, M.K. Jaiswal, S. Srivastava, An assessment of various potentially toxic elements and associated <lb/>health risks in agricultural soil along the middle Gangetic basin, India, Chemosphere 300 (2022) 134433. <lb/>[36] S. Chawla, A. Singh, D. Jhamb, C.H. Anupama, A randomised controlled trial to compare injection ferric carboxymaltose and oral iron in treating iron <lb/>deficiency anemia during pregnancy, J. Obstet. Gynecol. India (2022) 1-5. <lb/>[37] R. Palika, T. Dasi, S. Ghosh, R. Peter, D.J. Parasannanavar, A.S. Pradhan, A. V Kurpad, H.S. Sachdev, B. Kulkarni, R. Pullakhandam, Efficacy of iron-folic acid <lb/>treatment for reducing anemia prevalence and improving iron status in women of reproductive age: a one-year longitudinal study, Clin. Nutr. ESPEN 49 (2022) <lb/>390-397. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[38] M.M. Black, S. Fernandez-Rao, K.M. Nair, N. Balakrishna, N. Tilton, K.V. Radhakrishna, P. Ravinder, K.B. Harding, G. Reinhart, D.P. Yimgang, A randomized <lb/>multiple micronutrient powder Point-of-Use fortification trial implemented in Indian Preschools increases expressive language and reduces anemia and iron <lb/>deficiency, J. Nutr. 151 (2021) 2029-2042. <lb/>[39] G.J. Kontoghiorghes, A. Kolnagou, T. Demetriou, M. Neocleous, C.N. Kontoghiorghe, New era in the treatment of iron deficiency anaemia using trimaltol iron <lb/>and other lipophilic iron chelator complexes: historical perspectives of discovery and future applications, Int. J. Mol. Sci. 22 (2021) 5546. <lb/>[40] F. Vanobberghen, O. Lweno, A. Kuemmerle, K.D. Mwebi, P. Asilia, A. Issa, B. Simon, S. Mswata, S. Schmidlin, T.R. Glass, Efficacy and safety of intravenous <lb/>ferric carboxymaltose compared with oral iron for the treatment of iron deficiency anaemia in women after childbirth in Tanzania: a parallel-group, open-<lb/>label, randomised controlled phase 3 trial, Lancet Glob. Heal. 9 (2021) e189-e198. <lb/>[41] M.K. Upadhyay, A. Majumdar, A. Barla, S. Bose, S. Srivastava, Thiourea supplementation mediated reduction of grain arsenic in rice (Oryza sativa L.) cultivars: <lb/>a two year field study, J. Hazard Mater. 407 (2021) 124368, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124368. <lb/>[42] P.N. Williams, A. Villada, C. Deacon, A. Raab, J. Figuerola, A.J. Green, J. Feldmann, A.A. Meharg, Greatly enhanced arsenic shoot assimilation in rice leads to <lb/>elevated grain levels compared to wheat and barley, Environ. Sci. Technol. 41 (2007) 6854-6859. <lb/>[43] A. Majumdar, M.K. Upadhyay, B. Giri, S. Srivastava, A.K. Srivastava, M.K. Jaiswal, S. Bose, Arsenic dynamics and flux assessment under drying-wetting <lb/>irrigation and enhanced microbial diversity in paddy soils: a four year study in Bengal delta plain, J. Hazard Mater. 409 (2021) 124443, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.jhazmat.2020.124443. <lb/>[44] A.K. Srivastava, M. Pandey, T. Ghate, V. Kumar, M.K. Upadhyay, A. Majumdar, A.K. Sanjukta, A.K. Agrawal, S. Bose, S. Srivastava, Chemical intervention for <lb/>enhancing growth and reducing grain arsenic accumulation in rice, Environ. Pollut. 276 (2021) 116719. <lb/>[45] D. Moulick, A. Mukherjee, A. Das, A. Roy, A. Majumdar, A. Dhar, B.K. Pattanaik, B. Chowardhara, D. Ghosh, M.K. Upadhyay, Selenium-An environmentally <lb/>friendly micronutrient in agroecosystem in the modern era: an overview of 50-year findings, Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 270 (2024) 115832. <lb/>[46] D. Moulick, D. Ghosh, S.C. Santra, Evaluation of effectiveness of seed priming with selenium in rice during germination under arsenic stress, Plant Physiol. <lb/>Biochem. 109 (2016) 571-578. <lb/>[47] D. Moulick, S.C. Santra, D. Ghosh, Seed priming with Se alleviate as induced phytotoxicity during germination and seedling growth by restricting as <lb/>translocation in rice (Oryza sativa L cv IET-4094), Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 145 (2017) 449-456. <lb/>[48] D. Moulick, B. Chowardhara, S.K. Panda, Agroecotoxicological aspect of arsenic (As) and cadmium (Cd) on Field crops and its mitigation: current status and <lb/>future prospect, Plant-Metal Interact (2019) 217-246. <lb/>[49] D. Moulick, S. Sarkar, J.P. Awasthi, D. Ghosh, S. Choudhury, S.K. Tata, K. Bramhachari, S.C. Santra, Rice grain quality traits: neglected or less addressed? Rice <lb/>Res. Qual. Improv. Genomics Genet. Eng. Vol. 1 Breed. Tech. Abiotic Stress Toler. (2020) 729-745. <lb/>[50] D. Moulick, S.C. Santra, D. Ghosh, Consequences of paddy cultivation in arsenic-contaminated paddy fields of lower Indo-Gangetic Plain on arsenic <lb/>accumulation pattern and selected grain quality traits: a preliminary assessment, Mech. Arsen. Toxic. Toler. Plants (2018) 49-78. <lb/>[51] D. Moulick, S.C. Santra, D. Ghosh, Rice seed priming with se: a novel approach to mitigate as induced adverse consequences on growth, yield and as load in <lb/>brown rice, J. Hazard Mater. 355 (2018) 187-196. <lb/>[52] D. Moulick, S.C. Santra, D. Ghosh, S.K. Panda, An assessment of efficiency of zinc priming in Rice (cv. MTU-7029) during germination and early seedling <lb/>growth, Priming Pretreat. Seeds Seedlings Implic. Plant Stress Toler. Enhancing Product, Crop Plants (2019) 495-507. <lb/>[53] A. Hossain, Z. Ahmad, D. Moulik, S. Maitra, P. Bhadra, A. Ahmad, S. Garai, M. Mondal, A. Roy, A.E.L. Sabagh, Jasmonates and salicylates: mechanisms, <lb/>transport and signalling during abiotic stress in plants, Jasmonates Salicylates Signal. Plants (2021) 1-29. <lb/>[54] A. Hossain, S. Maitra, B. Pramanick, K.L. Bhutia, Z. Ahmad, D. Moulik, M.A. Syed, T. Shankar, M. Adeel, M.M. Hassan, Wild relatives of plants as sources for <lb/>the development of abiotic stress tolerance in plants, in: Plant Perspect. To Glob. Clim. Chang, Elsevier, 2022, pp. 471-518. <lb/>[55] S. Choudhury, D. Moulick, M.K. Mazumder, Secondary metabolites protect against metal and metalloid stress in rice: an in silico investigation using <lb/>dehydroascorbate reductase, Acta Physiol. Plant. 43 (2021) 1-10. <lb/>[56] S. Choudhury, P. Sharma, D. Moulick, M.K. Mazumder, Unrevealing metabolomics for abiotic stress adaptation and tolerance in plants, J. Crop Sci. Biotechnol. <lb/>24 (2021) 479-493. <lb/>[57] S. Choudhury, D. Moulick, Response of Field Crops to Abiotic Stress: Current Status and Future Prospects, 2022. <lb/>[58] B. Saha, B. Chowardhara, S. Kar, S.S. Devi, J.P. Awasthi, D. Moulick, B. Tanti, S.K. Panda, Advances in heavy metal-induced stress alleviation with respect to <lb/>exogenous amendments in crop plants, Priming Pretreat. Seeds Seedlings Implic. Plant Stress Toler. Enhancing Product, Crop Plants (2019) 313-332. <lb/>[59] S. Sahoo, P. Borgohain, B. Saha, D. Moulick, B. Tanti, S.K. Panda, Seed priming and seedling pre-treatment induced tolerance to drought and salt stress: recent <lb/>advances, Priming Pretreat. Seeds Seedlings Implic. Plant Stress Toler. Enhancing Product, Crop Plants (2019) 253-263. <lb/>[60] A.J. Signes-Pastor, K. Mitra, S. Sarkhel, M. Hobbes, F. Burló, W.T. De Groot, A.A. Carbonell-Barrachina, Arsenic speciation in food and estimation of the dietary <lb/>intake of inorganic arsenic in a rural village of West Bengal, India, J. Agric. Food Chem. 56 (2008) 9469-9474. <lb/>[61] D. Halder, A. Biswas, Z. Šlejkovec, D. Chatterjee, J. Nriagu, G. Jacks, P. Bhattacharya, Arsenic species in raw and cooked rice: implications for human health in <lb/>rural Bengal, Sci. Total Environ. 497 (2014) 200-208. <lb/>[62] U. Mandal, P. Singh, A.K. Kundu, D. Chatterjee, J. Nriagu, S. Bhowmick, Arsenic retention in cooked rice: effects of rice type, cooking water, and indigenous <lb/>cooking methods in West Bengal, India, Sci. Total Environ. 648 (2019) 720-727. <lb/>[63] A.C. Samal, P. Bhattacharya, P. Biswas, J.P. Maity, J. Bundschuh, S.C. Santra, Variety-specific arsenic accumulation in 44 different rice cultivars (O. sativa L.) <lb/>and human health risks due to co-exposure of arsenic-contaminated rice and drinking water, J. Hazard Mater. 407 (2021) 124804, https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>jhazmat.2020.124804. <lb/>[64] F. Afsal, A. Majumdar, J.S. Kumar, S. Bose, Microbial inoculation to alleviate the metal toxicity in crop plants and subsequent growth promotion, Sustain. <lb/>Solut. Elem. Defic. Excess Crop Plants (2020) 451-479, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-15-8636-1_17. <lb/>[65] D. Moulick, S. Samanta, S. Sarkar, A. Mukherjee, B.K. Pattnaik, S. Saha, J.P. Awasthi, S. Bhowmick, D. Ghosh, A.C. Samal, Arsenic contamination, impact and <lb/>mitigation strategies in rice agro-environment: an inclusive insight, Sci. Total Environ. 800 (2021) 149477. <lb/>[66] D. Moulick, D. Ghosh, J. Mandal, S. Bhowmick, D. Mondal, S. Choudhury, S.C. Santra, M. Vithanage, J.K. Biswas, A cumulative assessment of plant growth <lb/>stages and selenium supplementation on arsenic and micronutrients accumulation in rice grains, J. Clean. Prod. (2023) 135764. <lb/>[67] A. Shrivastava, A. Barla, A. Majumdar, S. Singh, S. Bose, Arsenic mitigation in rice grain loading via alternative irrigation by proposed water management <lb/>practices, Chemosphere 238 (2020) 124988, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.124988. <lb/>[68] D. Moulick, K.L. Bhutia, S. Sarkar, A. Roy, U.N. Mishra, B. Pramanick, S. Maitra, T. Shankar, S. Hazra, M. Skalicky, The intertwining of Zn-finger motifs and <lb/>abiotic stress tolerance in plants: current status and future prospects, Front. Plant Sci. 13 (2022). <lb/>[69] D. Moulick, S.C. Santra, D. Ghosh, Seed priming with Se mitigates As-induced phytotoxicity in rice seedlings by enhancing essential micronutrient uptake and <lb/>translocation and reducing as translocation, Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 25 (2018) 26978-26991. <lb/>[70] M.K. Upadhyay, A. Majumdar, J. Suresh Kumar, S. Srivastava, Arsenic in rice agro-ecosystem: solutions for safe and sustainable rice production, Front. Sustain. <lb/>Food Syst. 4 (2020) 53. <lb/>[71] J.O. Nriagu, P. Bhattacharya, A.B. Mukherjee, J. Bundschuh, R. Zevenhoven, R.H. Loeppert, Arsenic in soil and groundwater: an overview, trace met. Other <lb/>contam, Environ. Times 9 (2007) 3-60. <lb/>[72] H. Brammer, P. Ravenscroft, Arsenic in groundwater: a threat to sustainable agriculture in South and South-east Asia, Environ. Int. 35 (2009) 647-654, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2008.10.004. <lb/>[73] A. Majumdar, J.S. Kumar, S. Bose, Agricultural water management practices and environmental influences on arsenic dynamics in rice field, in: Arsen. Drink. <lb/>Water Food, Springer, 2020, pp. 425-443. <lb/>[74] X.Y. Xu, S.P. McGrath, A.A. Meharg, F.J. Zhao, Growing rice aerobically markedly decreases arsenic accumulation, Environ. Sci. Technol. 42 (2008) <lb/>5574-5579. <lb/>[75] S. Bhowmick, S. Pramanik, P. Singh, P. Mondal, D. Chatterjee, J. Nriagu, Arsenic in groundwater of West Bengal, India: a review of human health risks and <lb/>assessment of possible intervention options, Sci. Total Environ. 612 (2018) 148-169. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[76] A. Majumdar, A. Shrivastava, S.R. Sarkar, S. Sathyavelu, A. Barla, S. Bose, Hydrology, sedimentation and mineralisation: a wetland ecology perspective, Clim. <lb/>Chang. Environ. Sustain. 8 (2020) 134-151. <lb/>[77] M.J. Abedin, J. Cotter-Howells, A.A. Meharg, Arsenic uptake and accumulation in rice (Oryza sativa L.) irrigated with contaminated water, Plant Soil 240 <lb/>(2002) 311-319, https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1015792723288. <lb/>[78] M.C. Fontanella, M. Martin, D. Tenni, G.M. Beone, M. Romani, Effect of milling and parboiling processes on arsenic species distribution in rice grains, Rice Sci. <lb/>28 (2021) 402-408. <lb/>[79] D. Mridha, P.C. Gorain, M. Joardar, A. Das, S. Majumder, A. De, N.R. Chowdhury, U. Lama, R. Pal, T. Roychowdhury, Rice grain arsenic and nutritional content <lb/>during post harvesting to cooking: a review on arsenic bioavailability and bioaccessibility in humans, Food Res. Int. 154 (2022) 111042, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111042. <lb/>[80] V. Taleon, M.Z. Hasan, R. Jongstra, R. Wegmüller, M.K. Bashar, Effect of parboiling conditions on zinc and iron retention in biofortified and non-biofortified <lb/>milled rice, J. Sci. Food Agric. 102 (2022) 514-522. <lb/>[81] M. Menon, W. Dong, X. Chen, J. Hufton, E.J. Rhodes, Improved rice cooking approach to maximise arsenic removal while preserving nutrient elements, Sci. <lb/>Total Environ. 755 (2021) 143341. <lb/>[82] B. Biswas, A. Chakraborty, D. Chatterjee, S. Pramanik, B. Ganguli, K.K. Majumdar, J. Nriagu, K.Y. Kulkarni, A. Bansiwal, P. Labhasetwar, Arsenic exposure <lb/>from drinking water and staple food (rice): a field scale study in rural Bengal for assessment of human health risk, Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 228 (2021) 113012. <lb/>[83] D. Mondal, T. Mwale, L. Xu, H. Matthews, A. Oyeka, G. Lace-Costigan, D.A. Polya, Risk perception of arsenic exposure from rice intake in a UK population, <lb/>Palgrave Commun 5 (2019) 1-7. <lb/>[84] D. Mondal, M. Banerjee, M. Kundu, N. Banerjee, U. Bhattacharya, A.K. Giri, B. Ganguli, S. Sen Roy, D.A. Polya, Comparison of drinking water, raw rice and <lb/>cooking of rice as arsenic exposure routes in three contrasting areas of West Bengal, India, Environ. Geochem. Health 32 (2010) 463-477. <lb/>[85] P. Kumarathilaka, S. Seneweera, Y.S. Ok, A. Meharg, J. Bundschuh, Arsenic in cooked rice foods: assessing health risks and mitigation options, Environ. Int. <lb/>127 (2019) 584-591. <lb/>[86] T. Mwale, M.M. Rahman, D. Mondal, Risk and benefit of different cooking methods on essential elements and arsenic in rice, Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. <lb/>15 (2018) 1056. <lb/>[87] M.K. Upadhyay, A. Majumdar, A. Barla, S. Bose, S. Srivastava, An assessment of arsenic hazard in groundwater-soil-rice system in two villages of Nadia <lb/>district, West Bengal, India, Environ. Geochem. Health 41 (2019) 2381-2395, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10653-019-00289-4. <lb/>[88] M. Ray, K. Ghosh, S. Singh, K.C. Mondal, Folk to functional: an explorative overview of rice-based fermented foods and beverages in India, J. Ethn. Foods. 3 <lb/>(2016) 5-18. <lb/>[89] A. Majumdar, M.K. Upadhyay, J.S. Kumar, A. Barla, S. Srivastava, M.K. Jaiswal, S. Bose, Ultra-structure alteration via enhanced silicon uptake in arsenic <lb/>stressed rice cultivars under intermittent irrigation practices in Bengal delta basin, Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf. 180 (2019) 770-779. <lb/>[90] S. Waste, Human Health Evaluation Manual, RISK, 1991. <lb/>[91] UEPA, Supplemental guidance for developing soil screening levels for superfund sites, Peer Rev. Draft. OSWER. 9355 (2001) 4-24. <lb/>[92] D. Chakraborty, N.K. Mondal, Assessment of health risk of children from traditional biomass burning in rural households, Expo. Heal. 10 (2018) 15-26. <lb/>[93] D. Chakraborty, N.K. Mondal, Hypertensive and toxicological health risk among women exposed to biomass smoke: a rural Indian scenario, Ecotoxicol. <lb/>Environ. Saf. 161 (2018) 706-714. <lb/>[94] D. Chakraborty, N.K. Mondal, Reduction in household air pollution and associated health risk: a pilot study with an improved cookstove in rural households, <lb/>Clean Technol. Environ. Policy 23 (2021) 1993-2009. <lb/>[95] H.G. Gauch Jr., Model selection and validation for yield trials with interaction, Biometrics (1988) 705-715. <lb/>[96] E. Parliament, Regulation (EU) No. 1308/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 17 December 2013 Establishing a Common Organisation of <lb/>the Markets in Agricultural Products and Repealing Council Regulations (EEC) No. 922/72,(EEC) No. 234/79,(EC) No. 1037/20, off J Euro Union, vol. 347, <lb/>2013, pp. 671-854. <lb/>[97] D. Moulick, S. Hazra, A. Mukherjee, S. Sinha, S. Mahanta, A. Das, B. Saha, N.K. Niazi, J.K. Biswas, Application of nanotechnology in mitigating arsenic stress <lb/>and accumulation in crops: where we are and where we are moving towards, in: Glob. Arsen. Hazard Ecotoxicol. Remediat, Springer, 2022, pp. 247-270. <lb/>[98] D. Mondal, M.M. Rahman, S. Suman, P. Sharma, A.B. Siddique, M.A. Rahman, A.S.M.F. Bari, R. Kumar, N. Bose, S.K. Singh, Arsenic exposure from food <lb/>exceeds that from drinking water in endemic area of Bihar, India, Sci. Total Environ. 754 (2021) 142082. <lb/>[99] N.R. Chowdhury, A. Das, M. Joardar, A. De, D. Mridha, R. Das, M.M. Rahman, T. Roychowdhury, Flow of arsenic between rice grain and water: its interaction, <lb/>accumulation and distribution in different fractions of cooked rice, Sci. Total Environ. 731 (2020), https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138937. <lb/>[100] D. Mondal, D.A. Polya, Rice is a major exposure route for arsenic in Chakdaha block, Nadia district, West Bengal, India: a probabilistic risk assessment, Appl. <lb/>Geochem. 23 (2008) 2987-2998, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apgeochem.2008.06.025. <lb/>[101] K. Ohno, Y. Matsuo, T. Kimura, T. Yanase, M.H. Rahman, Y. Magara, T. Matsushita, Y. Matsui, Effect of rice-cooking water to the daily arsenic intake in <lb/>Bangladesh: results of field surveys and rice-cooking experiments, Water Sci. Technol. 59 (2009) 195-201. <lb/>[102] M.M. Rahman, M. Asaduzzaman, R. Naidu, Arsenic exposure from rice and water sources in the noakhali district of Bangladesh, Water Qual. Expo. Heal. 3 <lb/>(2011) 1-10, https://doi.org/10.1007/s12403-010-0034-3. <lb/>[103] P. Kumarathilaka, S. Seneweera, A. Meharg, J. Bundschuh, Arsenic speciation dynamics in paddy rice soil-water environment: sources, physico-chemical, and <lb/>biological factors-a review, Water Res. 140 (2018) 403-414. <lb/>[104] T. Pedron, F.R. Segura, F.P. Paniz, F. de Moura Souza, M.C. dos Santos, A.M. de Magalhães Júnior, B.L. Batista, Mitigation of arsenic in rice grains by polishing <lb/>and washing: evidencing the benefit and the cost, J. Cereal. Sci. 87 (2019) 52-58. <lb/>[105] S. Naito, E. Matsumoto, K. Shindoh, T. Nishimura, Effects of polishing, cooking, and storing on total arsenic and arsenic species concentrations in rice <lb/>cultivated in Japan, Food Chem. 168 (2015) 294-301, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.07.060. <lb/>[106] A. Roel, F. Campos, M. Verger, R. Huertas, G. Carracelas, Regional variability of arsenic content in Uruguayan polished rice, Chemosphere 288 (2022) 132426. <lb/>[107] J.M. Oteiza, P.A. Barril, C.E. Quintero, M. Savio, R. Befani, A.F. Cirelli, N.S. Echegaray, C. Murad, A. Buedo, Arsenic in Argentinean polished rice: situation <lb/>overview and regulatory framework, Food Control 109 (2020) 106909. <lb/>[108] G. Goswami, H. Baruah, R.C. Boro, M. Barooah, Fermentation reduces anti-nutritional content and increases mineral availability in poita bhat, Asian J. Chem. <lb/>28 (2016). <lb/>[109] S. Hemalatha, K. Platel, K. Srinivasan, Influence of germination and fermentation on bioaccessibility of zinc and iron from food grains, Eur. J. Clin. Nutr. 61 <lb/>(2007) 342-348. <lb/>[110] X.Q. Liang, Y.X. Chen, Z.Y. Nie, Y.S. Ye, J. Liu, G.M. Tian, G.H. Wang, T.P. Tuong, Mitigation of nutrient losses via surface runoff from rice cropping systems <lb/>with alternate wetting and drying irrigation and site-specific nutrient management practices, Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 20 (2013) 6980-6991, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1007/s11356-012-1391-1. <lb/>[111] S. Nath, M. Roy, J. Sikidar, B. Deb, I. Sharma, A. Guha, Characterization and in-vitro screening of probiotic potential of novel Weissella confusa strain GCC_ <lb/>19R1 isolated from fermented sour rice, Curr. Res. Biotechnol. 3 (2021) 99-108. <lb/>[112] M.M. Rahman, J. Rinklebe, R. Naidu, Arsenic speciation as well as toxic and nutrient elements in pantavat (overnight steeped rice), Environ. Pollut. (2023) <lb/>121901. <lb/>[113] M. Joardar, A. Das, N.R. Chowdhury, D. Mridha, A. De, K.K. Majumdar, T. Roychowdhury, Health effect and risk assessment of the populations exposed to <lb/>different arsenic levels in drinking water and foodstuffs from four villages in arsenic endemic Gaighata block, West Bengal, India, Environ. Geochem. Health 43 <lb/>(2021) 3027-3053. <lb/>[114] J.P. Peña-Rosas, P. Mithra, B. Unnikrishnan, N. Kumar, L.M. De-Regil, N.S. Nair, M.N. Garcia-Casal, J.A. Solon, Fortification of rice with vitamins and minerals <lb/>for addressing micronutrient malnutrition, Cochrane Database Syst. Rev. 10 (2019) 132, https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD009902.pub2. <lb/>[115] R.K. Rai, S.S. Kumar, S. Sen Gupta, D.J. Parasannanavar, T.S.N. Anish, A. Barik, R.K. Varshney, H. Rajkumar, Shooting shadows: India&apos;s struggle to reduce the <lb/>burden of anaemia, Br. J. Nutr. 129 (2023) 416-427. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e28296 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[116] M. Banerjee, N. Banerjee, P. Bhattacharjee, D. Mondal, P.R. Lythgoe, M. Martínez, J. Pan, D.A. Polya, A.K. Giri, High arsenic in rice is associated with elevated <lb/>genotoxic effects in humans, Sci. Rep. 3 (2013) 2195, https://doi.org/10.1038/srep02195. <lb/>[117] Z.U. Rehman, S. Khan, K. Qin, M.L. Brusseau, M.T. Shah, I. Din, Quantification of inorganic arsenic exposure and cancer risk via consumption of vegetables in <lb/>southern selected districts of Pakistan, Sci. Total Environ. 550 (2016) 321-329. <lb/>[118] R. Sharifi, F. Moore, B. Keshavarzi, S. Badiei, Assessment of health risks of arsenic exposure via consumption of crops, Expo. Heal. 10 (2018) 129-143. <lb/>[119] M. Naseri, A. Vazirzadeh, R. Kazemi, F. Zaheri, Concentration of some heavy metals in rice types available in Shiraz market and human health risk assessment, <lb/>Food Chem. 175 (2015) 243-248. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">D. Moulick et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">R <lb/>E T R <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>T E D </note>


	</text>
</tei>
