<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Evolution of invasive pneumococcal disease by serotype 3 in <lb/>adults: a Spanish three-decade retrospective study <lb/>Sara Calvo-Silveria, a,b Aida González-Díaz, a,b, * * Inmaculada Grau, b,c José María Marimón, d Emilia Cercenado, b,e M Dolores Quesada, f <lb/>Antonio Casabella, g,h Nieves Larrosa, i,j José Yuste, b,k Dàmaris Berbel, a,b Marta Alonso, d Fe Tubau, a,b Sophie Belman, l Irene Cadenas-Jiménez, a,b <lb/>Antonio J. Martín-Galiano, m M Ángeles Domínguez, a,j,n Sara Martí, a,b,o Josefina Liñares, a Román Pallarés, b,c,p Jordi Càmara, a,b and <lb/>Carmen Ardanuy a,b,n, * <lb/>a <lb/>Microbiology Department, Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge -IDIBELL, L&apos;Hospitalet de Llobregat, Spain <lb/>b <lb/>Research Network for Respiratory Diseases (CIBERES), ISCIII, Madrid, Spain <lb/>c <lb/>Infectious Diseases Department, Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge -IDIBELL, L&apos;Hospitalet de Llobregat, Spain <lb/>d <lb/>Biogipuzkoa, Infectious Diseases Area, Respiratory Infection and Antimicrobial Resistance Group, Microbiology Department, Hospital <lb/>Donostia, Osakidetza Basque Health Service, Donostia -San Sebastian, Spain <lb/>e <lb/>Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Disease Department, Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón, Madrid, Spain <lb/>f <lb/>Microbiology Department, Clinical Laboratory North Metropolitan Area, Hospital Universitari Germans Trias i Pujol, UAB, Badalona, <lb/>Spain <lb/>g <lb/>Laboratory of Microbiology, Hospital Universitari Parc Taulí, Sabadell, Spain <lb/>h <lb/>Institut d&apos;Investigació i Innovació Parc Taulí (I3PT), Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Sabadell, Spain <lb/>i <lb/>Microbiology Department, Hospital Universitari Vall d&apos;Hebron, UAB, Barcelona, Spain <lb/>j <lb/>Research Network for Infectious Diseases (CIBERINFEC), ISCIII, Madrid, Spain <lb/>k <lb/>Spanish Pneumococcal Reference Laboratory, National Centre for Microbiology, Instituto de Salud Carlos III, Madrid, Spain <lb/>l <lb/>Earth Sciences Department, Barcelona Supercomputing Center -Centro Nacional de Supercomputación, Barcelona, Spain <lb/>m <lb/>Core Scientific and Technical Units, Instituto de Salud Carlos III, Madrid, Spain <lb/>n <lb/>Department of Pathology and Experimental Therapeutics, University of Barcelona, Spain <lb/>o <lb/>Department of Medicine, School of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Barcelona, Spain <lb/>p <lb/>Department of Clinical Sciences, University of Barcelona, Spain <lb/>Summary <lb/>Background Invasive pneumococcal disease due to serotype 3 (S3-IPD) is associated with high mortality rates and <lb/>long-term adverse effects. The introduction of the 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV13) into the <lb/>Spanish paediatric immunisation programme has not led to a decrease in the adult S3-IPD. We aimed to analyse <lb/>the incidence, clinical characteristics and genomics of S3-IPD in adults in Spain. <lb/>Methods Adult IPD episodes hospitalized in a Southern Barcelona hospital were prospectively collected (1994-2020). <lb/>For genomic comparison, S3-IPD isolates from six Spanish hospitals (2008-2020) and historical isolates (1989-1993) <lb/>were analysed by WGS (Illumina and/or MinION). <lb/>Findings From 1994 to 2020, 270 S3-IPD episodes were detected. When comparing pre-PCV (1994-2001) and late-<lb/>PCV13 (2016-2020) periods, only modest changes in S3-IPD were observed (from 1.58 to 1.28 episodes per <lb/>100,000 inhabitants year). In this period, the incidence of the two main lineages shifted from 0.38 to 0.67 (CC180-<lb/>GPSC12) and from 1.18 to 0.55 (CC260-GPSC83). The overall 30-day mortality remained high (24.1%), though a <lb/>decrease was observed between the pre-PCV (32.4%; 95.0% CI, 22.0-45.0) and the late-PCV13 period (16.7%; <lb/>95.0% CI, 7.5-32.0) (p = 0.06). At the same time, comorbidities increased from 77.3% (95.0% CI, 65.0-86.0) to <lb/>85.7% (95.0% CI, 71.0-94.0) (p = 0.69). There were no differences in clinical characteristics or 30-day mortality <lb/>between the two S3 lineages. Although both lineages were genetically homogeneous, the CC180-GPSC12 lineage <lb/>presented a higher SNP density, a more open pan-genome, and a major presence of prophages and mobile <lb/>genetic elements carrying resistance genes. <lb/>*Corresponding author. Microbiology Department, Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge, Feixa Llarga s/n, 08907, L&apos;Hospitalet de Llobregat, Barcelona, <lb/>Spain. <lb/>**Corresponding author. Microbiology Department, Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge, Feixa Llarga s/n, 08907, L&apos;Hospitalet de Llobregat, Barcelona, <lb/>Spain. <lb/>E-mail addresses: c.ardanuy@bellvitgehospital.cat (C. Ardanuy), agonzalezd@bellvitgehospital.cat (A. González-Díaz). <lb/>Translation: For the Spanish translation of the abstract see Supplementary Materials section. <lb/>The Lancet Regional <lb/>Health -Europe <lb/>2024;41: 100913 <lb/>Published Online xxx <lb/>https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.lanepe.2024. <lb/>100913 <lb/>www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/>1 <lb/>Articles <lb/>Interpretation Adult S3-IPD remained stable in our area over the study period despite PCV13 introduction in <lb/>children. However, a clonal shift was observed. The decrease in mortality rates and the increase in comorbidities <lb/>suggest a change in clinical management and overall population characteristics. The low genetic variability and <lb/>absence of clinical differences between lineages highlight the role of the S3 capsule in the disease severity. <lb/>Funding This study has been funded by Instituto de Salud Carlos III (ISCIII) &quot;PI18/00339&quot;, &quot;PI21/01000&quot;, &quot;INT22/ <lb/>00096&quot;, &quot;FI22/00279&quot;, CIBER &quot;CIBERES-CB06/06/0037&quot;, &quot;CIBERINFEC-CB21/13/00009&quot; and MSD grant &quot;IISP <lb/>60168&quot;. <lb/>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC <lb/>license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/). <lb/>Keywords: Streptococcus pneumoniae; Serotype 3; Genomics <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Pneumococcal infections, such as pneumonia, menin-<lb/>gitis and bacteraemia, are one of the main causes of <lb/>morbidity and mortality worldwide. 1 The introduction of <lb/>the pneumococcal conjugate vaccines (PCVs) has <lb/>reduced rates of disease and mortality in both children <lb/>and adults. 2 Nevertheless, the burden of disease and <lb/>associated mortality are still a global health problem, <lb/>mainly in adults. 2 Among them, invasive pneumococcal <lb/>disease (IPD) due to serotype 3 (S3-IPD), which is one of <lb/>the targets of the PCV13, remains predominant. More-<lb/>over, S3-IPD has been associated with high mortality <lb/>rates, particularly in the elderly, 3 as well as the severity <lb/>of pneumonia presentation 4 and long-term effects such <lb/>as major adverse cardiovascular events. 5 <lb/>The polysaccharide capsule is the main virulence <lb/>factor in pneumococci and forms the basis of vaccine <lb/>development. 6 To date, more than 100 serotypes have <lb/>been identified, with this diversity associated with dif-<lb/>ferences in invasiveness and mortality among the sero-<lb/>types. In Spain, the PCV7 was licensed in 2001, while <lb/>the PCV13, targeting serotype 3, was licensed in 2011. <lb/>Children were vaccinated on a voluntary basis until <lb/>2016, when the PCV13 was introduced into the official <lb/>immunisation programme for children, leading to an <lb/>uptake of 97.8% in 2020 (https://www.sanidad.gob.es/ <lb/>Research in context <lb/>Evidence before this study <lb/>Streptococcus pneumoniae has been extensively studied over <lb/>the decades, particularly after the introduction of vaccines. <lb/>However, despite the large number of articles on it, only a few <lb/>are specific to serotypes and provide a contextual analysis of <lb/>the clinical data and genomic features. To address this gap, <lb/>we conducted a literature search on PubMed for articles <lb/>published up to 1st September 2023, using the search terms <lb/>&quot;Streptococcus pneumoniae&quot;, &quot;Serotype 3 ′′ , &quot;IPD&quot; (invasive <lb/>pneumococcal disease), &quot;Dynamics&quot;, &quot;Genomics&quot;, and <lb/>&quot;Capsule&quot;. There is evidence respecting the stability of <lb/>the incidence of serotype 3 in some countries, despite the <lb/>introduction of the PCV13. Regarding genetic analysis, the <lb/>assessment of the globally disseminated lineage CC180 <lb/>revealed a differentiation into clades following the <lb/>introduction of the PCV13. Additionally, a genetic analysis <lb/>conducted in the UK linked the increase in serotype 3 cases to <lb/>a specific subclade within CC180. Notably, there were no <lb/>analyses available covering an extended time period in the <lb/>same geographical area, including on the strains collected <lb/>prior to the introduction of PCVs. <lb/>Added value of this study <lb/>This study offers a comprehensive perspective on serotype 3, <lb/>shedding light on its clinical significance and providing <lb/>valuable insights into its genomic evolution over more than <lb/>30 years, including isolates predating the introduction of <lb/>PCVs. By analysing a collection of 344 isolates, we have not <lb/>only contextualised serotype 3 within clinical data, but have <lb/>also detailed the evolutionary trajectories of various lineages <lb/>in the context of PCVs. Our disease analysis over an extended <lb/>period has revealed changes in the population affected by S3-<lb/>IPD and in the clinical presentation. Additionally, we have <lb/>examined the potential impact of serotype 3 lineages on IPD <lb/>outcomes. Furthermore, this extensive dataset has allowed us <lb/>to identify differences not only in clinical characteristics, but <lb/>also in genomic features among the major clonal complexes, <lb/>thereby enhancing our understanding of this important <lb/>pathogen. <lb/>Implications of all the available evidence <lb/>Despite high levels of childhood vaccination with the PCV13 in <lb/>Spain, no herd protection has been observed in adults for <lb/>serotype 3. Understanding its evolution could reveal new <lb/>strategies to prevent the prevalence of this serotype in a public <lb/>health context. Furthermore, the analysis of clinical <lb/>characteristics of patients over the study period could contribute <lb/>to our understanding of the epidemiology of this serotype. The <lb/>holistic and multidisciplinary approach of this work sheds new <lb/>light on the persistence of serotype 3 in the era of PCV13. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>areas/promocionPrevencion/vacunaciones/calendario-y-<lb/>coberturas/coberturas/home.htm). In contrast to the <lb/>incidence of IPD caused by other PCV13 serotypes <lb/>(such as 7F, 1 and 23F), which decreased after vaccine <lb/>introduction in all age groups, the prevalence of IPD <lb/>due to S3 has increased among adults over 60, sug-<lb/>gesting poor herd protection. 7,8 The PCV13 effectiveness <lb/>against serotype 3 has been reported to be as low as <lb/>25.9% (95.0% CI, -65.3 to 66.8) in children. 9 Thus, a <lb/>study suggested that antibody titres above 2.83 μg/mL <lb/>were needed to reach protection, which is higher than <lb/>those achieved for serotype 3 after PCV13 vaccination. 10 <lb/>In the present study, we analysed changes in clinical <lb/>characteristics among the adult S3-IPD cases and <lb/>compared genomes of the responsible pneumococcal <lb/>isolates before and after the introduction of the PCVs in <lb/>children. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Hospital setting and study design <lb/>We conducted two analyses of S3-IPD in adults using <lb/>three collections of isolates (Supplementary Figure S1). <lb/>The first analysis was a retrospective analysis of a pro-<lb/>spective laboratory-based study that included all adult <lb/>(≥18 years old) S3-IPD episodes (n = 270) from 1994 to <lb/>2020 detected in Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge <lb/>(HUB), a tertiary hospital located in the Southern Bar-<lb/>celona area. For this analysis, clinical data on patients, <lb/>including demographics, early (≤7 days) and 30-day <lb/>mortality, underlying diseases and previous antibiotic <lb/>therapy, were prospectively collected along with avail-<lb/>able isolates (n = 252, 1st collection). The second anal-<lb/>ysis included the whole genome sequencing (WGS) of <lb/>344 S3-IPD isolates: 252 genomes from the first analysis <lb/>(1st collection), 7 isolates (2nd collection) recovered <lb/>from the HUB historical collection (1989-1993), and 85 <lb/>isolates (3rd collection) from a multicentre study. 11 The <lb/>last collection includes strains from Catalonia (Hospital <lb/>Universitari Vall d&apos;Hebron [VH, n = 22], Hospital Uni-<lb/>versitari Germans Trias i Pujol [HUGTiP, n = 17] and <lb/>Hospital Universitari Parc Taulí [Taulí, n = 12], Madrid <lb/>(Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón <lb/>[HGUGM, n = 19]) and the Basque Country (Hospital <lb/>Universitario Donostia [HUD, n = 15]). <lb/>Identification, antibiotic susceptibility testing and <lb/>serotyping <lb/>Pneumococci were identified using standard microbio-<lb/>logical procedures, including optochin susceptibility <lb/>and/or bile solubility. Serotyping was performed at the <lb/>Spanish Pneumococcal Reference Laboratory for Pneu-<lb/>mococci by the quellung reaction, dot blot and/or <lb/>capsular sequence typing. The antimicrobial suscepti-<lb/>bility was assessed by microdilution, following the <lb/>guidelines of the European Committee on Antimicro-<lb/>bial Susceptibility Testing (EUCAST) (www.eucast.org/ <lb/>clinical_breakpoints/). The antibiotics tested were <lb/>penicillin, ampicillin, amoxicillin, tetracycline, chlor-<lb/>amphenicol, cefotaxime, clindamycin, erythromycin, <lb/>ciprofloxacin and trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>The incidence of S3-IPD was calculated as the number <lb/>of episodes per 100,000 inhabitants per year. The pop-<lb/>ulation was obtained from IDESCAT (http://www. <lb/>idescat.cat/). To analyse temporal trends, five different <lb/>periods were defined based on the introduction of the <lb/>PCVs in Spain: pre-PCV (1994-2001), early-PCV7 <lb/>(2002-2005), late-PCV7 (2006-2010), early-PCV13 <lb/>(2011-2015) and late-PCV13 (2016-2020). The Mantel-<lb/>Haenszel trend test for categorical and the Pearson <lb/>test for numerical variables were used to examine trends <lb/>across periods. A complete case analysis was performed <lb/>and the number of missingness are reported in Table 1. <lb/>Whole genome sequencing and bioinformatics <lb/>analysis <lb/>Genomic DNA was extracted (QIAamp-DNA-MiniKit, <lb/>Qiagen) and quantified (Qubit, Thermo Fisher). All <lb/>isolates were sequenced using Nextera XT followed by <lb/>paired-end sequencing (2 × 300 bp) on a MiSeq platform <lb/>(Illumina). Sequences were assembled using the <lb/>INNUca v4.2 pipeline (github.com/B-UMMI/INNUca), <lb/>with default parameters. The oldest genome of each <lb/>major lineage (HUB-01001 for CC180-GPSC12 and <lb/>HUB-01990 for CC260-GPSC83) and isolates presenting <lb/>resistance genes associated with mobile genetic ele-<lb/>ments (MGEs) were long-read sequenced (MinION, <lb/>ONT) and subjected to further hybrid assembly using <lb/>the Unicycler pipeline. 12 Reads were deposited in the <lb/>European Nucleotide Archive and the metadata from all <lb/>the genomes are summarised in Supplementary <lb/>Table S1. <lb/>Using the Global pneumococcal Sequencing project <lb/>(GPS) resources (pathogen.watch/), we grouped each ge-<lb/>notype into one global pneumococcal sequencing cluster <lb/>(GPSC). Furthermore, to contextualize our collection <lb/>(n = 344), the metadata of all adult S3-IPD cases from <lb/>1994 to 2020 (n = 383) available at www.pneumogen.net/ <lb/>gps/gps-database-overview/(accessed December 20th <lb/>2022) were downloaded and classified according to the <lb/>GPSC, ST, period and country (Supplementary Table S2). <lb/>Regarding the CC180-GSPC12 lineage, a correlation be-<lb/>tween our clades and those described worldwide 13,14 was <lb/>performed. A phylogenetic tree including 400 genomes <lb/>from Groves et al. 14 (clade Ia [n = 212], clade Ib [n = 3], <lb/>clade II [n = 102] and an external clade [n = 83] plus our <lb/>collection [n = 344]) was constructed, as described above <lb/>(Supplementary Table S3). <lb/>MLST was performed in silico using the MLST v4.2 <lb/>software (github.com/tseemann/mlst) with the PubMLST <lb/>database <lb/>(pubmlst.org/organisms/streptococcus-<lb/>pneumoniae/). Prokka v1.13.7 15 was used for the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>genome annotations and Roary 16 was applied for the <lb/>pan-genome analysis. A whole genome SNP-based <lb/>alignment was constructed by Snippy v4.4.0 (github. <lb/>com/tseemann/snippy) using the closed genomes of <lb/>HUB-01001 (CC180-GPSC12) and HUB-01990 (CC260-<lb/>GPSC83) as references. A phylogenetic tree was con-<lb/>structed by filtering recombination using Gubbins v3.0 17 <lb/>and the data were visualised with ggtree from ggplot2 <lb/>(ggplot2.tidyverse.org/) or iTol (itol.embl.de/). Genomes <lb/>were considered to belong to the same clade when the <lb/>number of SNPs was lower than 200. In order to assess <lb/>the temporal structure of CC180 and CC260, the Bact-<lb/>dating (github.com/xavierdidelot/BactDating) was used. <lb/>The capsular operon of S3 was analysed using <lb/>Geneious R9 (Biomatters) from wzg-wze and ugd-pgm in <lb/>order to exclude transposases since short-reads <lb/>sequencing is not appropriated to study these genes. <lb/>The 524/62 (CR931634) capsular operon was used as the <lb/>reference. <lb/>The chromosomal genes involved with antibiotic <lb/>resistance (parC, gyrA, folA, folP, pbp1a, pbp2x and <lb/>pbp2b) were studied using Geneious R9. The PBP alleles <lb/>(pbp1a, pbp2x and pbp2b) were analysed on the Patho-<lb/>genwatch website (pathogen.watch/). Acquired resis-<lb/>tance genes were screened using the ResFinder <lb/>database. 18 To characterise MGEs, a BLASTn search <lb/>between the MGE candidates containing resistance <lb/>genes and their flanking regions was performed to <lb/>compare them with previously described MGEs in <lb/>public databases. The genes involved in integration, <lb/>excision, mobilisation and replication were identified <lb/>using a BLASTx search to compare the predicted ORFs <lb/>with the NCBI NR database and to classify them <lb/>following the recommendations of Ambroset et al. 19 <lb/>pre-PCV n (%) <lb/>early-PCV7 n (%) <lb/>late-PCV7 n (%) <lb/>early-PCV13 n (%) <lb/>late-PCV13 n (%) <lb/>p-trend a <lb/>Available cases <lb/>76 <lb/>48 <lb/>54 <lb/>48 <lb/>44 <lb/>Clinical characteristics <lb/>Age (years), Mean (±SD) <lb/>67.6 (±17.5) <lb/>66.1 (±11.9) <lb/>66.8 (±15.6) <lb/>62.5 (±16.2) <lb/>70.8 (±12.9) <lb/>0.872 <lb/>Male <lb/>46 (60.5) <lb/>34 (70.8) <lb/>36 (66.7) <lb/>30 (62.5) <lb/>30 (68.2) <lb/>0.613 <lb/>Clinical presentation <lb/>0.642 <lb/>Pneumonia <lb/>73 (96.1) <lb/>43 (89.6) <lb/>38 (70.4) <lb/>42 (87.5) <lb/>35 (79.5) <lb/>Meningitis <lb/>2 (2.6) <lb/>2 (4.2) <lb/>10 (18.5) <lb/>2 (4.2) <lb/>6 (13.6) <lb/>Others <lb/>1 (1.3) <lb/>3 (6.3) <lb/>6 (11.1) <lb/>4 (8.3) <lb/>3 (6.8) <lb/>Bacteraemia <lb/>62 (81.6) <lb/>45 (93.8) <lb/>48 (88.9) <lb/>44 (91.7) <lb/>43 (97.7) <lb/>0.011 <lb/>Available cases <lb/>65 <lb/>46 <lb/>54 <lb/>48 <lb/>42 <lb/>Nosocomial acquisition b <lb/>4 (6.2) <lb/>2 (4.4) <lb/>3 (5.6) <lb/>2 (4.2) <lb/>1 (2.4) <lb/>0.414 <lb/>Risk factors <lb/>Smoking <lb/>21 (32.3) <lb/>15 (32.6) <lb/>17 (31.5) <lb/>18 (37.5) <lb/>13 (31.0) <lb/>0.841 <lb/>Alcohol abuse <lb/>12 (18.5) <lb/>8 (17.4) <lb/>6 (11.3) <lb/>8 (16.7) <lb/>10 (23.8) <lb/>0.756 <lb/>Prior antibiotic therapy <lb/>8 (12.3) <lb/>3 (6.5) <lb/>13 (24.1) <lb/>10 (20.8) <lb/>7 (16.7) <lb/>0.201 <lb/>Comorbidities <lb/>One or more <lb/>51 (77.3) <lb/>31 (67.4) <lb/>34 (63.0) <lb/>32 (66.7) <lb/>36 (85.7) <lb/>0.692 <lb/>Chronic pulmonary disease <lb/>14 (21.2) <lb/>13 (28.3) <lb/>14 (25.9) <lb/>16 (33.3) <lb/>6 (14.3) <lb/>0.864 <lb/>Chronic heart disease <lb/>20 (30.3) <lb/>12 (26.1) <lb/>9 (16.7) <lb/>8 (16.7) <lb/>15 (35.7) <lb/>0.800 <lb/>Diabetes mellitus <lb/>12 (18.2) <lb/>10 (21.7) <lb/>9 (16.7) <lb/>10 (20.8) <lb/>21 (50.0) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Malignancies <lb/>10 (15.2) <lb/>9 (19.6) <lb/>10 (18.5) <lb/>13 (27.1) <lb/>10 (23.8) <lb/>0.146 <lb/>Liver cirrhosis <lb/>5 (7.6) <lb/>2 (4.3) <lb/>3 (5.6) <lb/>1 (2.1) <lb/>4 (9.5) <lb/>0.955 <lb/>HIV infection <lb/>2 (3.0) <lb/>1 (2.2) <lb/>2 (3.7) <lb/>2 (4.2) <lb/>0 (0.0) <lb/>0.639 <lb/>Chronic renal failure <lb/>4 (6.1) <lb/>0 (0.0) <lb/>2 (3.7) <lb/>6 (12.5) <lb/>4 (9.5) <lb/>0.108 <lb/>Cerebrovascular disease/dementia <lb/>11 (16.7) <lb/>2 (4.3) <lb/>5 (9.3) <lb/>0 (0.0) <lb/>6 (14.3) <lb/>0.247 <lb/>Immunosuppressive therapy <lb/>5 (7.7) <lb/>5 (10.9) <lb/>3 (5.6) <lb/>7 (14.6) <lb/>6 (14.3) <lb/>0.217 <lb/>Septic shock <lb/>19 (29.2) <lb/>13 (28.3) <lb/>11 (20.8) <lb/>17 (35.4) <lb/>11 (26.2) <lb/>0.977 <lb/>Available cases <lb/>71 <lb/>46 <lb/>54 <lb/>48 <lb/>42 <lb/>7-day mortality <lb/>18 (25.4) <lb/>7 (15.2) <lb/>10 (18.5) <lb/>7 (14.6) <lb/>6 (14.3) <lb/>0.127 <lb/>30-day mortality <lb/>23 (32.4) <lb/>11 (23.9) <lb/>11 (20.4) <lb/>11 (22.9) <lb/>7 (16.7) <lb/>0.062 <lb/>Available cases <lb/>18 <lb/>29 <lb/>53 <lb/>48 <lb/>44 <lb/>PPV23 c <lb/>3 (16.7) <lb/>6 (20.7) <lb/>14 (26.4) <lb/>21 (43.8) <lb/>29 (65.9) <lb/>0.519 <lb/>Statistically significant results are highlighted in bold; SD (Standard deviation), n (number of cases), % (percentage). a p-value of first (pre-PCV) and last (late-PCV13) period <lb/>comparison. b Acquisition can be nosocomial or extrahospitalary. c Includes any vaccination with the pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine 23-valent (PPV23). <lb/>Table 1: Differences in clinical characteristics of patients with S3-IPD over the five study periods. <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>Finally, the Easyfig programme 20 was used to illustrate <lb/>the nucleotide sequence alignments. <lb/>Finally, the PHASTER website (phaster.ca/) was <lb/>used for the first screening for bacterial prophages. <lb/>Then, a classification was performed using Geneious R9 <lb/>and the bacterial prophages described in Brueggemann <lb/>et al. 21 and Martín-Galiano et al. 22 <lb/>Ethics statement <lb/>This work has been approved by The Clinical Research <lb/>Ethics Committee of Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge <lb/>(PR065/21). This study was in accordance with the <lb/>Declaration of Helsinki from the World Medical Asso-<lb/>ciation. Written informed consent was waived as this is <lb/>an observational study with isolates obtained as part of <lb/>the normal microbiological routine. According to na-<lb/>tional normative data, all the data were anonymized, and <lb/>patient confidentiality was always protected following <lb/>the current legal normative in Spain (LOPD 3/2018 and <lb/>RD 1720/2007). <lb/>Role of the funding source <lb/>The funders of the study had no role in the study design, <lb/>data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, or the <lb/>writing of the report. <lb/>Results <lb/>Trends and clinical characteristics of S3-IPD <lb/>Among the 2570 IPD episodes detected over the study <lb/>period (1994-2020), 270 (10.5%) were caused by serotype <lb/>3 isolates. As previously reported, we observed an <lb/>increase in the overall IPD incidence from 15.2/100,000 <lb/>inhabitants year in the pre-PCV period to 21.0/100,000 in <lb/>the late-PCV7 period (Fig. 1). After the introduction of the <lb/>PCV13, the IPD rate decreased to 12.9/100,000 (late-<lb/>PCV13). When focusing on S3-IPD, its incidence <lb/>remained stable after the introduction of the PCV7 (from <lb/>1.58/100,000 inhabitants year in the pre-PCV period to <lb/>1.61/100,000 in the late-PCV7 period) and showed a non-<lb/>significant decreased in the late-PCV13 period (1.28/ <lb/>100,000). <lb/>The analysis of the clinical characteristics of patients <lb/>with S3-IPD through the whole period showed differences <lb/>regarding to the clinical presentation and comorbidities, <lb/>between the first (pre-PCV) and last (late-PCV13) period. <lb/>However, due to the low number of cases only the in-<lb/>crease in the proportion of patients with diabetes mellitus <lb/>reach statistical significance (Table 1). In addition, the 30-<lb/>day mortality (32.4%-16.7%; p = 0.062) and 7-day mor-<lb/>tality (25.4%-14.3%; p = 0.127), usually related to the <lb/>severity of the disease at the onset of infection, showed a <lb/>decrease over the whole period. Over the study period, the <lb/>rate of S3-IPD patients vaccinated with the 23-valent <lb/>pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine (PPV23) increased <lb/>from 16.7% (pre-PCV) to 65.9% (late-PCV13) (p = 0.519). <lb/>However, in many cases, the vaccine was administered at <lb/>an interval greater than 5 years. Over the study period, 33 <lb/>vaccine failures were detected (Supplementary Table S4) <lb/>among 31 who had received the PPV23 alone, one who <lb/>had received a sequential schedule with the PCV7 and <lb/>PPSV23 and one who had received the PCV13 in the four <lb/>years before to the onset of infection. <lb/>Fig. 1: Evolution of serotype 3 lineages that cause IPD in adults. The black line (right axis) represents the overall incidence (episodes/ <lb/>100,000) of IPD in adults. The bars represent the incidence of S3-IPD by periods (left axis) caused by different STs. Other-CC180 includes <lb/>ST8561, ST9420 and ST18057. Other-CC260 includes ST1377, ST18059 and ST18060. Other Lineages represents isolates belonging to ST113 <lb/>(GPSC50), ST458 (GPSC458), ST717 (GPSC3), ST6193 (GPSC309) and ST18058. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Changes in the lineage composition of serotype 3 <lb/>pneumococci and clinical data <lb/>The analysis of 252 serotype 3 isolates obtained between <lb/>1994 and 2020 (Fig. 1) revealed the presence of two main <lb/>lineages, CC180-GPSC12 (n = 107) and CC260-GPSC83 <lb/>(n = 135), in addition to other minor ones grouped as <lb/>other lineages: ST113 (GPSC50), ST458 (GPSC51), <lb/>ST717 (GPSC3), ST6193 (GPSC309) and ST18058 (not <lb/>assigned). A lineage shift was observed during the study <lb/>period. The incidence of disease due to CC260-GPSC83 <lb/>decreased from 1.18/100,000 in the pre-PCV period to <lb/>0.55/100,000 in the late-PCV13 period (p &lt; 0.05), whereas <lb/>disease due to CC180-GPSC12 increased from 0.38/ <lb/>100,000 to 0.67/100,000 (p = 0.06). Within CC260-<lb/>GPSC83, disease caused by ST1220 progressively <lb/>increased, accounting for nearly half of the cases of this <lb/>lineage in the late-PCV13 period. Globally, the GPS <lb/>metadata (Supplementary Table S2) showed that 54.8% <lb/>of the available serotype 3 genomes belonged to CC180-<lb/>GPSC12, while 8.6% belonged to CC260-GPSC83. <lb/>GPSC12 was highly prevalent in North America (95.8%), <lb/>Oceania (85.7%), Europe (75.5%) and South America <lb/>(69.8%), whereas Asia and Africa presented more genetic <lb/>variability (GPSC12; 46.8% and 12.5%, respectively). <lb/>GPSC83 was present in most continents, but the fre-<lb/>quency was higher in Europe (17.0%) and Africa (13.5%). <lb/>There were no significant differences in the clinical <lb/>characteristics of the episodes between the CC180-<lb/>GPSC12 and CC260-GPSC83 lineages (Supplementary <lb/>Table S5). Nevertheless, pneumonia was more <lb/>frequent among the episodes caused by CC260-GPSC83 <lb/>(90.5% vs 82.3%; p = 0.062), while meningitis was more <lb/>common in those caused by CC180-GPSC12 (5.8% vs <lb/>10.6%; p = 0.241). Early mortality (19.7% vs 18.2%; <lb/>p = 0.869) and 30-day mortality (27.3% vs 22.7%; <lb/>p = 0.459) were also similar between the groups. Among <lb/>the vaccine failures, 54.5% were episodes caused by <lb/>CC260-GPSC83 (n = 18), and 36.4% were due to CC180-<lb/>GPSC12 (n = 12) (Supplementary Table S4). <lb/>Phenotypic and genetic features of the serotype 3 <lb/>lineages <lb/>The capsular operon of serotype 3 showed a low number <lb/>of polymorphic sites, a total of 28 in the wgz-wze region <lb/>and 45 in the ugd-pgm region. Most of them (n = 35) <lb/>were sporadic variations present in a few genomes, 13 <lb/>were polymorphisms present in all the genomes <lb/>compared to the references, and 21 differentiated the <lb/>capsular operon of the two major lineages. No differ-<lb/>ences were found between S3-ST260 and S3-ST1220 <lb/>(Supplementary Table S6A). The N57K and N375H <lb/>amino acid replacements in Ugd, A341T and H367N in <lb/>WchE and E58G in GalU were present in all the isolates, <lb/>whereas other minor substitutions were present in a <lb/>single isolate (Supplementary Table S6B). <lb/>All serotype 3 isolates were uniformly susceptible to <lb/>penicillin (MIC ≤0.03 mg/L), amoxicillin (MIC <lb/>≤0.03 mg/L) and cefotaxime (MIC ≤0.06 mg/L) <lb/>regardless of genotype or PBP pattern. The activity of <lb/>the remaining antibiotics tested was above 95%. The <lb/>exception was tetracycline which showed a 92.9% of <lb/>susceptibility rate among isolates of GPSC12 <lb/>(Supplementary Table S8). Among the isolates <lb/>harboring resistance determinants, 20 tetracycline-<lb/>resistant isolates carried the tet(M) gene, 9 presented <lb/>resistance to chloramphenicol through the expression of <lb/>cat and 8 exhibited resistance to macrolides via the <lb/>expression of erm(B). Three different transposon fam-<lb/>ilies and eight structures (Supplementary Figure S2) <lb/>were found: the Tn916 family (Acc. num. U09422.1) <lb/>(structures 1 and 2), the Tn1549 family (structure 3) and <lb/>the Tn5252 family (Acc. num. EU351020.1) (structures <lb/>4, 5, 6, 7 and 8). One isolate presented resistance to <lb/>trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole and another three were <lb/>not susceptible to quinolones (Supplementary Table S7). <lb/>An in-depth analysis of 170 CC180-GPSC12 ge-<lb/>nomes showed six major clades (named 180-1 to <lb/>180-6), with a maximum of 5468 SNPs when comparing <lb/>with the oldest genome of our series (HUB-01001) <lb/>(Fig. 2). Temporal structure analysis using Bactdating <lb/>did not find a good temporal signal. Nevertheless, clade <lb/>180-6 was dominant throughout the whole study period <lb/>(n = 140), followed by the clades 180-5 (n = 8), 180-3 <lb/>(n = 7), 180-1 (n = 6), 180-4 (n = 5) and 180-2 (n = 4). <lb/>The phylogenetic tree presented in Supplementary <lb/>Figure S3 reveals that the previously described 13,14 <lb/>clade Ia includes clade 180-6, clade Ib contains 180-1, <lb/>180-2 and 180-3, and clade II comprises 180-4 and <lb/>180-5. Ninety-four CC180-GPSC12 isolates carried <lb/>phages and their prevalence was clade-specific. A total of <lb/>83 genomes from clade 180-6 (59.2%) had the IPP57 <lb/>phage (Acc. num. KY065494) (Brueggemann et al.) 21 also <lb/>known as ΦOXC141, while one isolate had the IPP58 <lb/>phage (Acc. num. KY065495). Five genomes from clade <lb/>180 to 5 had the IPP19 prophage (Acc. num. KY065460), <lb/>2 genomes from clade 180 to 4 had the PPH020_2 <lb/>prophage (Acc. num. NZ_LR216031.1) and 3 genomes <lb/>from 180 to 2 had the PPH115_1 phage (Acc. num. <lb/>NZ_LR216034.1). 22 Finally, we did not find phages in the <lb/>isolates from clades 180-1 to 180-3. In all cases, phages <lb/>of the same type were inserted into the same location in <lb/>the genome. In general, the presence of MGEs in this <lb/>lineage was rare (n = 12). Six isolates from clade 180 to 5 <lb/>had the Tn916 transposon (structure 2), carrying the <lb/>tet(M) gene, while 2 had the integrative and conjugative <lb/>element belonging to the Tn5252 family (structure 7) <lb/>that carried both, tet(M) and erm(B). The remaining 4 <lb/>harbored Tn5252, with 2 isolates from 180 to 6 con-<lb/>taining structure 4, and 2 isolates from clade 180 to 4 <lb/>containing structure 8 (Supplementary Figure S2). <lb/>Isolates from the second lineage, CC260-GPSC83, <lb/>had a lower number of SNPs (2126 SNPs) than CC180-<lb/>GPSC12 ones (Fig. 3). As in CC180-GPSC12 a good <lb/>temporal signal was not obtained. However, seven <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>different clusters were detected among the 164 ge-<lb/>nomes, most being ST260 and sporadic ST isolates <lb/>(termed here clades 260-1 to 260-6) while the remain-<lb/>ing one was related to ST1220 isolates (260-7). No <lb/>phages were found in this lineage and the presence of <lb/>MGEs was also sporadic and associated with Tn5252. <lb/>Three genomes from the clades 260-5 (n = 1) to 260-6 <lb/>(n = 2) had structure 5, whereas one isolate from clade <lb/>260 to 3 had structure 3 (Supplementary Figure S2). <lb/>Regarding the minor lineages, four CC458-GPSC51 <lb/>genomes (n = 6) contained the PPH060 prophage (Acc. <lb/>num. NZ_LR216035.1) and one of them also had a <lb/>Tn1549 transposon (structure 3). CC717-GPSC3, which <lb/>is frequently associated with serotype 33F, consisted of a <lb/>single isolate harbouring Tn6002 [erm(B)] (Acc. num. <lb/>AY898750.1), with the IPP28 phage (Acc. num. <lb/>KY065469) located upstream of the transposon. <lb/>Genomes of the serotype 3 isolates from different <lb/>parts of the country were spread along the phylogenetic <lb/>trees of both lineages, without the presence of any <lb/>clusters that would suggest clonal differences between <lb/>the Spanish regions. <lb/>The pan-genome analysis highlighted the differences <lb/>between the two lineages (Fig. 4). Regarding the rela-<lb/>tionship between the total and conserved genes (Fig. 4a), <lb/>CC180-GPSC12 had a higher total gene count (2286 vs <lb/>2061 genes) and a more open genome compared to <lb/>CC260-GPSC83, resulting in fewer conserved genes <lb/>content (76.2% vs 88.5%). These differences also <lb/>correlated with those observed in Fig. 4c, where the line <lb/>Fig. 2: Genetic diversity of CC180-GPSC12. Heatmap displaying differences in the SNPs, using the oldest isolate HUB-01001 as a reference. The <lb/>phylogenetic tree groups genomes into different clades based on the SNPs, with their origins shown as black triangles in the tree. Circles at <lb/>the end of the branches represent hospitals. The other information displayed includes the ST (shown as squares) and the period, as well as the <lb/>presence of transposons and phages (shown as dots). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>representing the non-conserved genes was higher for <lb/>CC180-GPSC12. Furthermore, when this information <lb/>was stratified per lineage (Fig. 4b), CC180-GPSC12 had <lb/>more accessory genomes than CC260-GPSC83 (22.8% <lb/>vs 11.4%), representing almost a quarter of the total <lb/>compared to the 10.0% for CC260-GPSC83. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we analysed S3-IPD cases over a 30-year <lb/>period in which different PCVs were licensed for use <lb/>in Spain. Our results show that the incidence of S3-IPD <lb/>remained stable after PCV13 introduction, with no <lb/>observable herd protection. This has also been described <lb/>in other countries, suggesting that the vaccination of <lb/>children is not enough to achieve protection in adults. <lb/>This is probably due to the low impact of the PCV13 in <lb/>carriage that is the basis for herd protection. 14,23,24 The <lb/>pneumococcal diseases caused by S3 are associated with <lb/>a high risk of death, 2 severe disease, 4 and long-term <lb/>adverse effects. 5 In our study, a non-significant decline <lb/>in the 30-day mortality rates over the study period was <lb/>observed, probably reflecting the progressive improve-<lb/>ment in the management of pneumococcal diseases <lb/>such as meningitis and pneumonia. 25 In addition, we <lb/>observed similar mortality rates between the two major <lb/>lineages, CC180-GPSC12 and CC260-GPSC83, high-<lb/>lighting the fact that the type 3 capsular polysaccharide <lb/>is the main factor associated with disease fatality. A <lb/>change in the patient population over the study period <lb/>was observed, with progressive increases in the mean <lb/>age of patients and the presence of comorbidities <lb/>(especially diabetes), as observed previously, and a <lb/>decrease in the prevalence of pneumonia. 2 This could be <lb/>Fig. 3: Genetic diversity of CC260-GPSC83. Heatmap displaying differences in the SNPs, using the oldest isolate HUB-01990 (1991) as a <lb/>reference. The phylogenetic tree groups genomes into different clades based on the SNPs, with their origins shown as black triangles in the tree. <lb/>Circles at the end of the branches represent hospitals. The other information displayed includes the ST (shown as squares) and the period, as <lb/>well as the presence of transposons and phages (shown as dots). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>linked to an overall increase in life expectancy and un-<lb/>derscores the need to protect these populations that are <lb/>at risk of IPD. However, this comparison could yield <lb/>significant results with a larger population sample, <lb/>thereby increasing the statistical power, or applying a <lb/>better alternative that could be analysing within a mul-<lb/>tiple imputation framework. <lb/>Antibiotic resistance has been always low among S3 <lb/>isolates, despite the presence of MGEs. 13 We did not <lb/>find resistance to beta-lactam antibiotics, while resis-<lb/>tance to other antibiotics was low. Furthermore, ac-<lb/>quired resistance through MGEs was linked to the <lb/>Tn916 family of transposons that conferred resistance to <lb/>a single or multiple antibiotics. 13 Interestingly, despite <lb/>the high macrolide resistance rates in Spain and the <lb/>high antibiotic consumption rates (especially long-acting <lb/>ones), 26 these MGEs had not spread throughout these S3 <lb/>lineages, highlighting the stability of their genomes. <lb/>Most studies analysing the genomic composition of <lb/>invasive serotype 3 pneumococci have highlighted its <lb/>clonal homogeneity, with a worldwide dominance of <lb/>CC180-GPSC12. In our setting, the CC260-GPSC83 <lb/>lineage was gradually replaced by CC180-GPSC12, <lb/>especially in the early-PCV13 period. This replacement <lb/>has also been observed in Portugal, 27 a country where <lb/>CC260-GPSC83 was also an important lineage. Likewise <lb/>in Mexico, 28 after PCV13 introduction, CC180-GPSC12 <lb/>progressively replaced CC260-GPSC83. In addition to <lb/>the capsule, other factors could enhance the vaccine <lb/>resistance of CC180-GPSC12 pneumococci. Some <lb/>studies have highlighted the progressive increase in the <lb/>prevalence of clade II within CC180-GPSC12 lineage. <lb/>This clade is associated with higher antibiotic non-<lb/>susceptibility rates and a lower prophage content <lb/>compared to clade Ia. 13,14 In our study, clade Ia was <lb/>dominant in all the periods, while an increase in clade II <lb/>was not observed. Nevertheless, in agreement with <lb/>previous studies, 13,29 our clade Ia genomes (180-6) had <lb/>higher rates of integrated ΦOXC141 phages when <lb/>compared to clade II (clade 180-4 and clade 180-5), <lb/>which was more likely to have antibiotic resistance, and <lb/>clade Ib (180-1 to 180-3), which has few phages and <lb/>little resistance. The strict conservation of gene vicinity <lb/>indicates that the integration of this prophage occurred <lb/>just once in the history of the lineage. The presence of <lb/>the ΦOXC141 prophage in GPSC12-CC180 was associ-<lb/>ated with the inhibition of transformation, which could <lb/>explain the higher diversity of the CPSC12-CC180 ge-<lb/>nomes from clade 180-1 to 180-4 (without prophages) <lb/>that was observed in our study when compared to the <lb/>clades 180-5 and 180-6 (mainly with a prophage). 13 The <lb/>lower prevalence of this lineage before PCVs introduc-<lb/>tion in our setting and the existence of other dominant <lb/>lineages could explain these differences. On the other <lb/>hand, little is known about the genomics of the CC260-<lb/>GPSC83 lineage. This lineage showed greater genetic <lb/>homogeneity with few differences from the oldest <lb/>isolate, a reduced pan-genome and an absence of <lb/>Fig. 4: Analysis of the overall serotype 3 pangenome and major lineages. (a) The X-axis shows the number of genomes included in the <lb/>analysis, while the Y-axis presents the number of genes in the pan-genome analysis for each added genome. The squares display the conserved <lb/>genes of the genome, whereas the dots represent the accessory genes. (b) Representation of the pan-genome according to the core genome (in <lb/>dark green), the soft-core genome (in light green), the shell genome (in orange) and the cloud genome (in beige). The grey line represents the <lb/>core genome (core plus soft-core genome) and the dark purple line represents the accessory genome (shell plus cloud genome). (c) Differences <lb/>in the genes between the conserved genome and the accessory genome of GPSC12 (red line) and GPSC83 (blue line) are shown. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

            <body>phages. We hypothesise that this could be explained by <lb/>the narrower spread of this lineage compared to that of <lb/>CC180-GPSC12. <lb/>Our genomic analysis is a significant strength in the <lb/>study as it contributes to enhance our understanding of <lb/>the evolution and diversification of pneumococcal <lb/>serotype 3 lineages using a large collection of isolates <lb/>from across the country. Moreover, we have a large <lb/>collection of isolates from before the introduction of the <lb/>PCVs. The main limitation of our study is that the <lb/>overall analysis of both clinical and genetic data could <lb/>only be conducted at a single centre. Nevertheless, the <lb/>analysis of both the clinical and genetic characteristics of <lb/>this serotype over an extended period compensates for <lb/>this limitation, thereby adding strength to our study. <lb/>In conclusion, the number of adult S3-IPD cases <lb/>barely decreased in Spain, despite the introduction of <lb/>the PCV13 in children. The progressive decline in <lb/>mortality rates could be rather linked to an improve-<lb/>ment in clinical patient management. Despite the clonal <lb/>shift towards a higher prevalence of CC180-GPSC12, <lb/>the two main lineages presented high internal genetic <lb/>homology without any noticeable clinical difference. <lb/>Nevertheless, these results should be confirmed with <lb/>other studies. But, this observation, together with the <lb/>similarity of the capsular operon, highlights the role of <lb/>the serotype 3 capsule in IPD. Continuous surveillance <lb/>of this serotype will be needed to support this hypoth-<lb/>esis, along with the introduction of new PCVs that aim <lb/>to prevent pneumococcal pneumonia in adults. <lb/></body>

            <div type="annex">Contributors <lb/>SCS, AGD, IG, JMM, EC, MDQ, AC, NL, JY, DB, MA, FT, ICJ, AJMG, <lb/>MAD, SM, JL, RP, JC, CA. <lb/>CA, AGD conceptualised, designed, and supervised the study. IG, <lb/>JMM, EC, MDQ, AC, NL, JY, MA, FT, MAD, JL, RP contributed to <lb/>collect IPD cases and clinical characteristics. SCS, AGD, ICJ, SM, SB <lb/>designed and performed the whole genome sequencing approaches. <lb/>SCS, AGD, JC, DB, CA conducted the final analysis of data. SCS, AGD, <lb/>CA verified the data of the study and wrote the original draft of the <lb/>manuscript and had full access to all the data in the study. All authors <lb/>participated in manuscript review and editing, and had final re-<lb/>sponsibility for the decision to submit for publication. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data sharing statement <lb/>The data supporting the findings of this study are available within the <lb/>paper and its Supplementary materials. Genomes are available for <lb/>downloading through the accession number provided in the dataset <lb/>(see Supplementary materials). Additionally, the de-identified raw data <lb/>are available upon reasonable request from the corresponding author <lb/>c.ardanuy@bellvitgehospital.cat. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Declaration of interests <lb/>C.A. has been a scientific adviser for, and/or has received research <lb/>funding from, Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp and Pfizer. J.Y. has been a <lb/>scientific adviser for, and/or has received research funding from, Merck <lb/>Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp, Pfizer and GSK. All other authors declare that <lb/>they have no conflicts of interest regarding this research. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This study has been funded by Instituto de Salud Carlos III (ISCIII) <lb/>through the grant &quot;PI18/00339&quot; and &quot;PI21/01000&quot;, &quot;INT22/00096&quot; (co-<lb/>funded by European Social Fund), CIBER de Enfermedades Respiratorias <lb/>(CIBERES-CB06/06/0037) and CIBER de Enfermedades Infecciosas <lb/>(CIBERINFEC-CB21/13/00009). SCS was supported by a PFIS predoc-<lb/>toral grant number FI22/00279. The study is partially supported by an <lb/>Investigator Study Program of MSD grant (IISP 60168). The opinions <lb/>expressed in this manuscript are from the authors who did not represent <lb/>those of MSD. <lb/>We would like to thank to the Microbiology Departments of <lb/>Hospital Donostia, Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón, <lb/>Hospital Universitari Germans Trias i Pujol, Hospital Universitari Parc <lb/>Taulí and Hospital Universitari Vall d&apos;Hebrón, and the staff of the <lb/>Microbiology Laboratory of Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge who with <lb/>their daily work contributed to this project. We thank also the CERCA <lb/>Programme/Generalitat de Catalunya for institutional support. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Supplementary data <lb/>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.lanepe.2024.100913. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 Wang H, Naghavi M, Allen C, et al. Global, regional, and national <lb/>life expectancy, all-cause mortality, and cause-specific mortality for <lb/>249 causes of death, 1980-2015: a systematic analysis for the global <lb/>burden of disease study 2015. Lancet. 2016;388:1459-1544. <lb/>2 Grau I, Ardanuy C, Cubero M, et al. Declining mortality from adult <lb/>pneumococcal infections linked to children&apos;s vaccination. J Infect. <lb/>2016;72:439-449. <lb/>3 Luck JN, Tettelin H, Orihuela CJ. Sugar-coated killer: serotype 3 <lb/>pneumococcal disease. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2020;10:1-11. <lb/>4 Garcia-Vidal C, Ardanuy C, Tubau F, et al. Pneumococcal pneu-<lb/>monia presenting with septic shock: host-and pathogen-related <lb/>factors and outcomes. Thorax. 2010;65:77-81. <lb/>5 Africano H, Serrano-Mayorga C, Ramirez-Valbuena P, et al. Major <lb/>adverse cardiovascular events during invasive pneumococcal dis-<lb/>ease are serotype dependent. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;72:711-719. <lb/>6 Nelson AL, Roche AM, Gould JM, et al. Capsule enhances pneu-<lb/>mococcal colonization by limiting mucus-mediated clearance. Infect <lb/>Immun. 2007;75:83-90. <lb/>7 Sings HL, De Wals P, Gessner BD, et al. Effectiveness of 13-valent <lb/>pneumococcal conjugate vaccine against invasive disease caused by <lb/>serotype 3 in children: a systematic review and meta-analysis of <lb/>observational studies. Clin Infect Dis. 2019;68:2135-2143. <lb/>8 van der Linden M, Imöhl M, Perniciaro S. Limited indirect effects <lb/>of an infant pneumococcal vaccination program in an aging pop-<lb/>ulation. PLoS One. 2019;14:1-19. <lb/>9 Domínguez Á, Ciruela P, Hernández S, et al. Effectiveness of the <lb/>13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in preventing invasive <lb/>pneumococcal disease in children aged 7-59 months. A matched <lb/>case-control study. PLoS One. 2017;12:1-15. <lb/>10 Andrews N, Waight P, Burbidge P, et al. Serotype-specific effec-<lb/>tiveness and correlates of protection for the 13-valent pneumococcal <lb/>conjugate vaccine: a postlicensure indirect cohort study. Lancet <lb/>Infect Dis. 2014;14:839-846. <lb/>11 González-Díaz A, Càmara J, Ercibengoa M, et al. Emerging non-13-<lb/>valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV13) serotypes causing <lb/>adult invasive pneumococcal disease in the late-PCV13 period in <lb/>Spain. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2020;26:753-759. <lb/>12 Wick R, Judd L, Gorrie C, et al. Unicycler: resolving bacterial <lb/>genome assemblies from short and long sequencing reads. PLoS <lb/>Comput Biol. 2017;13:1-22. <lb/>13 Azarian T, Mitchell P, Georgieva M, et al. Global emergence and <lb/>population dynamics of divergent serotype 3 CC180 pneumococci. <lb/>PLoS Pathog. 2018;14:e1007438. <lb/>14 Groves N, Sheppard CL, Litt D, et al. Evolution of Streptococcus <lb/>pneumoniae serotype 3 in England and Wales: a major vaccine <lb/>evader. Genes. 2019;10:845-856. <lb/>15 Seemann T. Prokka: rapid prokaryotic genome annotation. Bioin-<lb/>formatics. 2014;30:2068-2069. <lb/>16 Page A, Cummins C, Hunt M, et al. Roary: rapid large-scale pro-<lb/>karyote pan genome analysis. Bioinformatics. 2015;31:3691-3693. <lb/>17 Croucher N, Page A, Connor T, et al. Rapid phylogenetic analysis of <lb/>large samples of recombinant bacterial whole genome sequences <lb/>using Gubbins. Nucleic Acids Res. 2015;43:e15. <lb/>18 Zankari E, Hasman H, Cosentino S, et al. Identification of acquired <lb/>antimicrobial resistance genes. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2012;67: <lb/>2640-2644. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>19 Ambroset C, Coluzzi C, Guédon G, et al. New insights into the <lb/>classification and integration specificity of Streptococcus integrative <lb/>conjugative elements through extensive genome exploration. Front <lb/>Microbiol. 2016;6:1-21. <lb/>20 Sullivan M, Petty N, Beatson S. Easyfig: a genome comparison <lb/>visualizer. Bioinformatics. 2011;27:1009-1010. <lb/>21 Brueggemann A, Harrold C, Rezaei R, et al. Pneumococcal pro-<lb/>phages are diverse, but not without structure or history. Sci Rep. <lb/>2017;7:1-13. <lb/>22 Martín-Galiano A, García E. Streptococcus pneumoniae: a plethora of <lb/>temperate bacteriophages with a role in host genome rearrange-<lb/>ment. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2021;11:1-21. <lb/>23 Horácio A, Silva-Costa C, Lopes J, et al. Serotype 3 remains the <lb/>leading cause of invasive pneumococcal disease in adults in <lb/>Portugal (2012-2014) despite continued reductions in other 13-<lb/>valent conjugate vaccine serotypes. Front Microbiol. 2016;7:1616. <lb/>24 Subramanian R, Liyanapathirana V, Barua N, et al. Persistence of <lb/>pneumococcal serotype 3 in adult pneumococcal disease in Hong <lb/>Kong. Vaccines (Basel). 2021;9:756-767. <lb/>25 Ruiz L, Zalacain R, Capelastegui A, et al. Bacteremic pneumococcal <lb/>pneumonia in elderly and very elderly patients. J Gerontol A Biol Sci <lb/>Med Sci. 2014;69:1018-1024. <lb/>26 Berbel D, González-Díaz A, López de Egea G, Camara J, <lb/>Ardanuy C. An overview of macrolide resistance in streptococci: <lb/>prevalence, mobile elements and dynamics. Microorganisms. <lb/>2022;10:2316. <lb/>27 Horácio A, Silva-Costa C, Diamantino-Miranda J, et al. Population <lb/>of Streptococcus pneumoniae causing invasive disease in <lb/>adults in Portugal before PCV13 availability for adults: 2008-2011. <lb/>PLoS One. 2016;11:2008-2011. <lb/>28 Echániz-aviles G, Guerreiro S, Silva-costa C, et al. Streptococcus <lb/>pneumoniae serotype 3 in Mexico (1994 to 2017): decrease of the <lb/>unusual clonal complex 4909 lineage following PCV13 introduc-<lb/>tion. Am Soc Microbiol. 2019;57:e01354-e01358. <lb/>29 Kwun M, Ion A, Cheng H, et al. Post-vaccine epidemiology of <lb/>serotype 3 pneumococci identifies transformation inhibition <lb/>through prophage-driven alteration of a non-coding RNA. Genome <lb/>Med. 2022;14:1-23. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 41 June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
