<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Unknown Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-28T10:54:12.523498Z">28.10.2025 10:54:12</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1093$1$pnasnexus_pgae470</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher/>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication"/>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1093/pnasnexus_pgae470</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>. (). Unknown Title. , (), . DOI: 10.1093/pnasnexus_pgae470</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T10:54:12.523498Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-28T10:54:12.523498Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Who to Boost When for COVID-19 • OFID • 1 <lb/>Open Forum Infectious Diseases <lb/>M A J O R A R T I C L E <lb/>Who to Boost When: The Effect of Age and Dosing Interval <lb/>on Delta and Omicron COVID-19 Incidence in the <lb/>Open-label Phase of the COVE Trial <lb/>Dean Follmann, 1, Xiaowei Wang, 2 Lindsey R. Baden, 3 Hana M. El Sahly, 4, Brandon Essink, 5 Peter Gilbert, 6 Holly E. Janes, 6 Colleen F. Kelley, 7, <lb/>Megan A. Berman, 8 Ian Frank, 9 Eric Chu, 1 Weiping Deng, 2 Frances Priddy, 2, Avika Dixit, 2 Joanne E. Tomassini, 2, Rituparna Das, 2 Jacqueline Miller, 2 <lb/>and Honghong Zhou 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, Biostatistics Research Branch, Bethesda, Maryland, USA, 2 Moderna, Inc., Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA, 3 Brigham and Women&apos;s Hospital, <lb/>Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA, 4 Departments of Molecular Virology and Microbiology and Medicine, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas, USA, 5 Meridian Clinical <lb/>Research, Savannah, Georgia, USA, 6 Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Vaccine and Infectious Diseases Division, Seattle, Washington, USA, 7 Division of Infectious Diseases, Emory University <lb/>School of Medicine Grady Health System, Atlanta, Georgia, USA, 8 Department of Internal Medicine, University of Texas Medical Branch, Galveston, Texas, USA, and 9 Deparment of Infectious <lb/>Diseases, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA <lb/>Background. To help inform COVID-19 vaccination recommendations, we evaluated the impact of age and dosing interval on <lb/>clinical benefit of a third dose of mRNA-1273. <lb/>Methods. Approximately 17 000 participants from the phase 3 Coronavirus Efficacy trial who previously received 2 doses of <lb/>100 µg mRNA-1273 were evaluated for COVID-19 between September 2021 and April 2022 during uptake of a third booster <lb/>dose of 50 µg of mRNA-1273. Cox models assessed booster relative efficacy of a third dose. <lb/>Results. Initial booster relative efficacy against Delta COVID-19 was 83% (95% confidence interval, 60-93) 14 days postdose <lb/>and 83% (67-91) 60 days later. Initial booster efficacy against Omicron COVID-19 was 56% (44-65) at 14 days postdose and 4% <lb/>(-27 to 28) 120 days later. For those aged ≥65 years, initial booster efficacy against Omicron COVID-19 was 86% (69-93) compared <lb/>with 50% (36-61) for those &lt;65 years. Placebo crossover to 2 doses of mRNA-1273 induced a median 5-month difference from the <lb/>second to third dose between the original randomized arms. Postboost, the mRNA-1273 arm had a 24% (16%, 32%) lower risk of <lb/>Omicron COVID-19 compared to the placebo-mRNA-1273 arm. Modeling predicted a 41% postboost reduction in Omicron <lb/>COVID-19 for a 15-versus 7-month interval between the second and third doses. <lb/>Conclusions. Boosting reduced Delta COVID-19 risk by 83% through 2 months and reduced Omicron COVID-19 risk by 56% but <lb/>declined by 4 months. A 15-versus 7-month dosing interval predicted a 41% postboost reduction in Omicron COVID-19 but increased <lb/>preboost risk. <lb/>Primary Funding Source. The National Institutes of Health/National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases. <lb/>Registration for the COVE Trial. ClinicalTrials.gov ID# NCT04470427 <lb/>Keywords. COVID-19 vaccine; booster dose; SARS-CoV2; mRNA-1273. <lb/>Received 20 June 2024; editorial decision 13 November 2024; accepted 22 November 2024; <lb/>published online 25 November 2024 <lb/>Correspondence: Dean Follmann, PhD, Biostatistics Research Branch, 5601 Fishers Lane, <lb/>Bethesda, MD 20892 (dfollmann@niaid.nih.gov). <lb/>Open Forum Infectious Diseases ® <lb/>Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Infectious Diseases Society of America 2024. <lb/>This work is written by (a) US Government employee(s) and is in the public domain in the US. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/ofid/ofae689 <lb/></front>

			<body>With the emergence of new variants, SARS-CoV-2, COVID-19 <lb/>remains a major threat to public health. Boosting the immune <lb/>response with additional vaccine doses increases antibody <lb/>levels [1-3] and reduces the risk of COVID-19 [4, 5]. As of <lb/>September 2024, the Centers for Disease Control and <lb/>Prevention (CDC) has tailored recommendations for vaccina-<lb/>tion depending on age, immunosuppression, and other factors. <lb/>For previously vaccinated adults, it is recommended to receive <lb/>a booster dose at least 6 months after their primary series or last <lb/>booster dose. The CDC notes that vaccination is especially <lb/>important for people at highest risk of severe COVID-19, in-<lb/>cluding people aged 65 years and older and other high-risk <lb/>groups [6]. As COVID-19 vaccine recommendations continue <lb/>to be updated, data to better understand additional dose dura-<lb/>bility, dosing intervals, and effectiveness in subgroups would be <lb/>helpful. <lb/>Studies showed that a fourth dose of mRNA-1273 adminis-<lb/>tered with a median dosing interval of around 180 days reduces <lb/>the risk of hospitalization and death by about 67% in those <lb/>aged &gt;50 years [7]. A study with a test-negative design evaluated <lb/>the effectiveness of a third dose on hospitalization from Delta and <lb/>Omicron SARS-CoV-2 variants and found that for those aged <lb/>18-64 years vaccine, effectiveness was 82% and dropped to <lb/>54% by 15 weeks overall, and for those ≥65 years of age, the <lb/>analogous estimates were 92% and 77% [8]. A study of the mono-<lb/>valent XBB.1.5 over the 2023-24 season estimated vaccine <lb/>effectiveness (VE) against COVID-19 was 51% (95% confidence <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/ofid/article/11/12/ofae689/7908454 by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>interval [CI], 47-54) during the first 7-59 days after an updated <lb/>dose and 39% (95% CI, 33-45) during the 60-119 days after an <lb/>updated dose. VE estimates against COVID-19-associated <lb/>hospitalization from 2 CDC VE networks were 52% (95% CI, <lb/>47-57) and 43% (95% CI, 27-56), with a median interval <lb/>from updated dose of 42 and 47 days, respectively [9]. <lb/>The interval between vaccine doses is a modifiable factor that <lb/>can impact VE and immunogenicity. For many vaccines, a longer <lb/>interval between the first and second doses results in better prim-<lb/>ing and higher antibody levels postdose 2 [10]. For example, an <lb/>interval of 6-14 weeks between the first and second dose was <lb/>shown to induce higher neutralizing antibody (nAb) levels com-<lb/>pared to a 3-4 week interval for the BNT162b2 COVID-19 vac-<lb/>cine [11]. Currently, the CDC recommends that a subsequent <lb/>dose be received at least 6 months after the last dose, whereas <lb/>the World Health Organization suggests a minimum interval of <lb/>6-12 months depending on age and risk [12]. In practice, uptake <lb/>of additional doses has been much less than for the primary se-<lb/>ries, the intervals between doses vary widely, and the impact of <lb/>interval times on vaccine effectiveness has not been well studied. <lb/>The Coronavirus Efficacy (COVE) phase 3 trial (ClinicalTrials. <lb/>gov ID# NCT04470427) randomized approximately 30 000 par-<lb/>ticipants to 2 doses of 100 µg mRNA-1273 (Spikevax) or placebo <lb/>and demonstrated high efficacy against COVID-19 in December <lb/>2020 [13]. Subsequently, participants randomized to placebo <lb/>were offered mRNA-1273 primary series in December 2020 <lb/>through April 2021. Following US government recommenda-<lb/>tions, a third dose of the original vaccine (booster) was offered <lb/>to trial participants starting 23 September 2021 [14]. This timing <lb/>created a difference in the interval between the second and third <lb/>dose of mRNA-1273 in the 2 groups (referred to here as the <lb/>mRNA-1273 arm and placebo/mRNA-1273 arm). The long-term <lb/>safety, immunogenicity, and efficacy of mRNA-1273 in the <lb/>COVE trial is reported in Baden et al [15]. In this study, we focus <lb/>on the efficacy and durability of a third dose of mRNA-1273 <lb/>against the incidence of COVID-19 caused by Delta and <lb/>Omicron variants over the period September 2021-April 2022. <lb/>We use the same surveillance and endpoint as in the primary <lb/>publications [13, 16]. The modulatory effects of the interval be-<lb/>tween the second and third doses and age (those aged ≥65 vs <lb/>&lt; 65 years) are investigated. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Study Design and Population <lb/>Details of the COVE trial are presented elsewhere [13, 16]. <lb/>Figure 1 provides a schematic of the analysis dataset used in <lb/>this study. COVE participants who received both doses of the pri-<lb/>mary immunization series of mRNA-1273 without major proto-<lb/>col violations and no evidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection as of <lb/>September 2021 comprise the analysis dataset. Participants who <lb/>acquired COVID-19 during the interval from the booster dose <lb/>up to 13 days later were censored. COVID-19 incidence was cal-<lb/>culated starting at 14 days postboost. Boosting was initiated on <lb/>September 2021 and participants who remained unboosted by <lb/>January 2022, were censored on that date. The incidence of Delta <lb/>and Omicron COVID-19 was assessed during the follow-up pe-<lb/>riod from 23 September 2021 to 5 April 2022 with COVID-19 de-<lb/>fined as a least 2 symptoms plus a positive real-time polymerase <lb/>chain reaction test using active surveillance where participants <lb/>were directed to be tested once they perceived symptoms (see <lb/>Supplementary Materials) [13, 15, 16]. Whole genomic sequenc-<lb/>ing was performed in SARS-CoV-2 polymerase chain reaction-<lb/>positive nasopharyngeal samples to identify infecting strain <lb/>[15]. A total of 8884 participants in the mRNA-1273 and <lb/>in the placebo/mRNA-1273 arms were evaluated in this open <lb/>label follow-up of the COVE trial. <lb/>In addition, a stratified random sample of the booster cohort <lb/>(n = 87 placebo/mRNA-1273 arm, n = 76 mRNA-1273 arm) <lb/>had nAb and binding antibody against ancestral and BA.1 <lb/>Figure 1. Schematic of the Coronavirus Efficacy trial from July 2020 through April 2022. PDV is the participant decision visit where participants were unblinded. <lb/>Blue syringes denote mRNA-1273. <lb/></body>

			<page>2</page>
    
    <note place="footnote">• OFID • Follmann et al <lb/>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/ofid/article/11/12/ofae689/7908454 by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Omicron strain measured on the day of the boost (BD1) and 28 <lb/>days later (BD29). We compared booster cohort for nAb and <lb/>binding antibody against ancestral and BA.1 Omicron strains. <lb/>See Supplementary Materials for details. <lb/>Statistical Methods. Cox proportional hazards regression models <lb/>with calendar time index were used to estimate booster relative ef-<lb/>ficacy and relative risk against incidence of Delta and BA.1 <lb/>Omicron COVID-19 [17, 18]. The modulatory effects of age, <lb/>arm, and interval between second dose and booster were assessed. <lb/>Models included terms for sex, stratification factors for severe <lb/>COVID-19 risk (aged ≥18 years and aged &lt;65 years with low <lb/>risk, aged ≥18 years and aged &lt;65 years with higher risk, and <lb/>aged ≥65 years), a standardized risk score [13, 19], and an indica-<lb/>tor for unblinding before the median unblinding date. Models fit <lb/>separately for aged &lt;65 years and aged ≥65 years removed the <lb/>stratification factors and adjusted for low/high risk in those aged <lb/>&lt;65 years old. COVID-19 cases with missing SARS-CoV-2 strain <lb/>information had strain (Delta or Omicron) imputed by a Bernoulli <lb/>draw (coin flip) with probability of Delta given by the GISAID es-<lb/>timated proportion of Delta cases matched on date and state of the <lb/>COVID-19 case with missing strain information. The percent <lb/>reduction in COVID-19 over a year under different boosting <lb/>strategies was based on parameter estimates from a Cox model <lb/>with bootstrap CIs. Geometric means and ratios for the binding <lb/>and neutralizing antibodies were calculated using weights to <lb/>reflect the stratified sampling. Details are provided in the <lb/>Supplementary Materials. <lb/>Analyses were conducted in SAS version 9.4 and R version <lb/>4.1.1. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Booster Efficacy and Durability <lb/>Booster uptake was rapid with 60% of participants vaccinated <lb/>by 31 October 2021, 88% by 30 November 2021, and 97% by <lb/>31 December 2021 (Supplementary Figure 1). Baseline charac-<lb/>teristics of the early boosted and late/never boosted groups <lb/>were generally balanced (Table 1). The mean age (range) of <lb/>the analysis set was 52 (18-95) years, 48% of participants <lb/>were female and 82% were White. Modest imbalances included <lb/>higher numbers of participants in the early boosted group than <lb/>in the late/never boosted group who were aged ≥65 years, <lb/>White, of non-Hispanic ethnicity, and randomized to the <lb/>mRNA-1273 arm and unblinded early (ie, before the median <lb/>unblinded date) tending to boost early. <lb/>Supplementary Figure 2 presents the occurrences of adjudicat-<lb/>ed COVID-19 cases in the COVE trial from September 2021 <lb/>through April 2022 annotated by booster status and strain. <lb/>Overall, there were 198 Delta COVID-19 cases and 1634 <lb/>Omicron COVID-19 cases. Through the Delta period, 23 <lb/>September 2021 through 15 December 2021, the total person <lb/>months of follow-up was 27 108 for the boosted and 26 405 un-<lb/>boosted groups. During the Omicron BA.1 period, 16 December <lb/>2021 through 5 April 2022, the analogous follow-up in person-<lb/>months was 59 486 for those boosted and 2283 unboosted, and <lb/>more than 95% of the Omicron cases were BA.1. <lb/>Table 1. Baseline Characteristics for the Early and Late/Never-boosted <lb/>Groups <lb/>Early Boosted <lb/>N = 8298 <lb/>Late Boosted <lb/>N = 8727 <lb/>Sex <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>Male <lb/>4331 (52.2) <lb/>4563 (52.3) <lb/>Female <lb/>3967 (47.8) <lb/>4164 (47.7) <lb/>Age at screening (y) <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>Mean (range) <lb/>54.5 (18-94) <lb/>51.8 (18-95) <lb/>Age (y) and health risk for severe COVID-19 <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>≥18 and &lt;65 and not at risk <lb/>4237 (51.1) <lb/>4987 (57.1) <lb/>≥18 and &lt;65 and at risk <lb/>1344 (16.2) <lb/>1543 (17.7) <lb/>≥65 <lb/>2717 (32.7) <lb/>2197 (25.2) <lb/>Ethnicity <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>Hispanic or Latino <lb/>1320 (15.9) <lb/>1973 (22.6) <lb/>Not Hispanic or Latino <lb/>6885 (83.0) <lb/>6681 (76.6) <lb/>Not reported or unknown <lb/>93 (1.1) <lb/>73 (0.8) <lb/>Race <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>White <lb/>6730 (81.1) <lb/>6734 (77.2) <lb/>Black or African American <lb/>761 (9.2) <lb/>989 (11.3) <lb/>Asian <lb/>324 (3.9) <lb/>407 (4.7) <lb/>American Indian or Alaska Native <lb/>65 (0.8) <lb/>67 (0.8) <lb/>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander <lb/>19 (0.2) <lb/>20 (0.2) <lb/>Multiracial <lb/>179 (2.2) <lb/>215 (2.5) <lb/>Other <lb/>148 (1.8) <lb/>193 (2.2) <lb/>Not reported or unknown <lb/>72 (0.9) <lb/>102 (1.2) <lb/>Risk factor for severe COVID-19 at <lb/>screening <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>At risk <lb/>1994 (24.0) <lb/>2106 (24.1) <lb/>Chronic lung disease <lb/>408 (4.9) <lb/>467 (5.4) <lb/>Significant cardiac disease <lb/>476 (5.7) <lb/>448 (5.1) <lb/>Severe obesity <lb/>570 (6.9) <lb/>653 (7.5) <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>837 (10.1) <lb/>926 (10.6) <lb/>Liver disease <lb/>55 (0.7) <lb/>70 (0.8) <lb/>HIV <lb/>59 (0.7) <lb/>52 (0.6) <lb/>Occupational risk <lb/>6651 (80.2) <lb/>6886 (78.9) <lb/>Healthcare workers <lb/>1894 (22.8) <lb/>1722 (19.7) <lb/>Body mass index (kg/m 2 ) <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>N <lb/>8232 <lb/>8671 <lb/>Mean (SD) <lb/>29.3 (6.7) <lb/>29.4 (6.8) <lb/>Standard risk score <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>N <lb/>8229 <lb/>8137 <lb/>Mean (SD) <lb/>-0.11 (1.01) <lb/>-0.03 (1.01) <lb/>Unblind <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>Early <lb/>4863 (58.6) <lb/>3930 (45.0) <lb/>Late <lb/>3435 (41.4) <lb/>4797 (55.0) <lb/>Randomization arm <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>mRNA-1273 <lb/>4563 (55.0) <lb/>4321 (49.5) <lb/>Placebo <lb/>3735 (45.0) <lb/>4406 (50.5) <lb/>Early boosted received the third dose before the median boost date of 25 October 2021. <lb/>Late boosted received their third dose after 25 October 2021, had an event before <lb/>boosting, or were unboosted on 31 January 2022, and censored. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="footnote">Who to Boost When for COVID-19 • OFID •</note>
    
    <page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/ofid/article/11/12/ofae689/7908454 by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>For Delta COVID-19, an initial booster efficacy (95% CI) of <lb/>83% (60-93) was maintained at 83% (67-91) through 60 days <lb/>(Figure 2). For Omicron COVID-19, the initial booster efficacy <lb/>was 56% (44-65) and decreased to 38% (28-47) by 60 days and <lb/>4% (-27% to 28%) by 120 days. Figure 3 presents booster effi-<lb/>cacy separately for those aged ≥65 and &lt;65 years for Omicron <lb/>COVID-19. The analogous estimates for those aged ≥65 years <lb/>were 86% (69-93) at 60 days and 28% (-47% to 65%) at 120 <lb/>days, whereas those &lt;65 years of age were 50% (36-61) and <lb/>6% (-29% to 31%), respectively. Preboost risk was similar for <lb/>the 2 age groups with the &lt;65 years of age: ≥65 years of age haz-<lb/>ard ratio 0.98 (0.61-1.57). <lb/>Effect of Interval Between Second and Third Dose <lb/>Our next set of analyses contrasted the original randomized arms. <lb/>Supplementary Table 1 provides baseline characteristics of the <lb/>mRNA-1273 and placebo/mRNA-1273 arms, which were mostly <lb/>similar except for earlier unblinding in the placebo arm. A discus-<lb/>sion of the comparability of these pseudo-randomized groups is <lb/>given in the Supplementary Materials. The median (interquartile <lb/>range) months from second dose to booster was 12.9 (12.3, 13.5) <lb/>for the original vaccine arm and 8.2 (7.8, 8.7) for the crossover <lb/>placebo arm (Supplementary Figure 3). <lb/>We estimated the hazard ratio for the mRNA-1273 arm rela-<lb/>tive to the placebo/mRNA-1273 arm for the prebooster and post-<lb/>booster periods, Supplementary Table 2. Prebooster, the hazard <lb/>ratios (95% CIs) were 1.24 (0.91-1.70) and 0.91 (0.69-1.22) for <lb/>Delta and Omicron infection, respectively. As both CIs included <lb/>1, the efficacy from the primary immunization had decreased to a <lb/>similar level for both variants. Postbooster, the hazard ratios were <lb/>0.86 (0.44, 1.67) for Delta and 0.76 (0.68, 0.84) for Omicron infec-<lb/>tions. For Omicron, this corresponded to a 24% (16%, 32%) re-<lb/>duction in risk for the mRNA-1273 arm. <lb/>We also analyzed the effect of different intervals between the <lb/>second and third dose. A boost interval of ≥1 year was estimat-<lb/>ed to have a 28% (20%, 35%) reduction in risk compared to an <lb/>interval of &lt;1 year. Treating month as a continuous variable, a <lb/>6% (4%, 8%) lower postbooster Omicron COVID-19 risk per <lb/>month increase in interval was estimated. Supplementary <lb/>Figure 4 shows the relative risk reduction, for intervals from <lb/>7 to 15 months compared to a 7-month interval. The postboos-<lb/>ter Omicron COVID-19 risk for a participant who remained <lb/>infection free and received the booster at 15 months was about <lb/>41% (30%, 50%) lower compared to a similar participant who <lb/>received the booster at the 7-month interval. In sensitivity anal-<lb/>yses, we adjusted for additional factors including health care <lb/>worker status, race, and ethnicity with minimal impact on the <lb/>model estimates. <lb/>Figure 2. Booster efficacy against Delta and Omicron COVID-19 over time. <lb/>Triangles represent the time of cases on the x-axis with random placement on <lb/>y-axis. Symbols at day 0 denote COVID-19 cases for participants who remained <lb/>unboosted throughout the trial. <lb/>Figure 3. Booster efficacy against Omicron COVID-19 over time by age group. <lb/>Triangles represent the time of cases on the x-axis with random placement on <lb/>y-axis. Symbols at day 0 denote COVID-19 cases for participants who remained <lb/>unboosted throughout the trial. <lb/>Table 2. Percent Reduction in COVID-19 Over 1 Year Following Boost on <lb/>1 October for Different age Groups, Constant or Winter Only Circulation of <lb/>SARS-CoV-2, and 8-or 14-month Intervals Between Booster Doses <lb/>Age Group SARS-CoV-2 Circulation 8-month Interval 14-month Interval <lb/>&lt;65 y <lb/>Entire year <lb/>12% <lb/>(4%, 28%) <lb/>17% <lb/>(11%,53%) <lb/>… <lb/>Only winter <lb/>11% <lb/>(1%, 25%) <lb/>36% <lb/>(51%, 79%) <lb/>≥65 y <lb/>Entire year <lb/>37% <lb/>(19%, 60%) <lb/>28% <lb/>(18%, 76%) <lb/>… <lb/>Only winter <lb/>37% <lb/>(14%,59%) <lb/>61% <lb/>(34%, 89%) <lb/></body>

			<page>4</page>
    
    <note place="footnote">• OFID • Follmann et al <lb/>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/ofid/article/11/12/ofae689/7908454 by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Evaluation of Boosting Interval Strategies <lb/>To quantify the effect of different boosting intervals on <lb/>COVID-19 risk throughout a year, we used the estimated mod-<lb/>els to evaluate an 8-versus 14-month interval between doses on <lb/>the risk of COVID-19 relative to no boosting (Table 2). Our year <lb/>started on 1 October when both interval groups were boosted, <lb/>and their previous boost was either 8 or 14 months prior. The <lb/>8-month interval group received an additional dose on 1 May, <lb/>whereas the 14-month interval group was not dosed again. <lb/>Attack rates were either constant over the entire year or entirely <lb/>restricted to winter. For those aged &lt;65 years, the benefit of <lb/>boosting was a 10%-20% reduction in COVID-19 risk relative <lb/>to no boosting, except for the 14-month interval group under <lb/>the Only Winter scenario for SARS-CoV-2 circulation. Under <lb/>this scenario, boosting was timed in October, a month before <lb/>the winter surge and was associated with a 36% reduction. For <lb/>those aged ≥65 years, the analogous estimates are 30%-40% re-<lb/>ductions with a 61% reduction for the 14-month interval timed <lb/>just before the winter surge. <lb/>Antibody Measurements pre-and Postbooster <lb/>The distribution of neutralizing antibodies and binding antibod-<lb/>ies against ancestral SARS-COV-2 (D614G) and BA.1 Omicron <lb/>strains at the day of boost (BD1) and 28 days (BD29) postboost <lb/>in the analysis set are shown in Supplementary Figures 5-S8. The <lb/>mRNA-1273 50-µg booster increased neutralizing antibody geo-<lb/>metric mean titers (GMTs) from baseline at BD1 with geometric <lb/>mean ratios (GMRs) (95% CIs) for placebo-mRNA-1237: <lb/>mRNA-1273 GMTs of 2.08 (1.45-2.97) and 1.12 (0.88-1.42) <lb/>for ancestral SARS-COV-2 (D614G) and Omicron BA.1 nAbs, <lb/>respectively (Supplementary Table 3). At BD29, the analogous <lb/>GMRs were 0.74 (0.55-1.00) and 0.70 (0.51-0.95). Findings for <lb/>binding antibodies were similar. Among participants aged &lt;65 <lb/>years, GMTs were higher than those aged &lt;65 years at BD1 <lb/>with GMRs of 1.86 (1.29-2.68) and 1.70 (1.39-2.09) for ancestral <lb/>SARS-COV-2 (D614G) D614G and Omicron BA.1 nAbs, re-<lb/>spectively (Supplementary Table 4). At BD29, the analogous <lb/>GMRs were 0.90 (0.65-1.25) and 0.86 (0.61-1.21). Results <lb/>were similar for binding antibodies. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Our study demonstrated that a third dose (50 µg) of the original <lb/>monovalent mRNA-1273 provided additional protection <lb/>against COVID-19 during the duration of the Delta wave in <lb/>the study, with an initial 83% reduction in Delta COVID-19, <lb/>which was maintained through 2 months of follow-up. It also <lb/>reduced the risk of Omicron, primarily BA.1, a more divergent <lb/>variant, providing an initial 56% reduction in Omicron <lb/>COVID-19, which dissipated by 4 months. <lb/>We separately studied those aged ≥65 years of age because of a <lb/>greater risk of death from COVID-19 in this population [20] and <lb/>found the effect of an additional dose was more pronounced <lb/>in those aged ≥65 years, with an initial efficacy in Omicron <lb/>COVID-19 of 86% compared to 50% for those aged &lt;65 years. <lb/>In the blinded phase of COVE, there was no appreciable difference <lb/>in primary series vaccine efficacy by age against COVID-19, but <lb/>some unblinded studies showed similar or somewhat larger ben-<lb/>efit of vaccination/boosting for those aged ≥65 years and other <lb/>studies did not [16]. For example, in the VISION network, a study <lb/>estimated the vaccine effectiveness of booster doses of mRNA vac-<lb/>cines during the Delta and Omicron waves [21]. For the Omicron <lb/>period, the study found vaccine efficacy against hospitalization fol-<lb/>lowing a third dose within 2 months was 77% for those aged ≥65 <lb/>years and 64% for those aged 18-44 years. Although we adjusted <lb/>for age, risk, and early unblinding, unmeasured confounding <lb/>may partly explain the greater benefit in those aged ≥65 years, <lb/>for example if those aged ≥65 years who boost early are also those <lb/>who especially avoid exposure. It is also possible that the vaccine <lb/>waned more in those aged ≥65 years, thus allowing a greater ben-<lb/>efit of the boost. The smaller benefit observed in younger persons <lb/>in our study provides a rationale for a risk-based approach for ad-<lb/>ditional doses, with emphasis on vaccinating those aged 65 and <lb/>older and other groups at higher risk of infection, such as immu-<lb/>nocompromised persons. A risk-based approach for the 2023-<lb/>2024 COVID-19 vaccination effort was adopted in the United <lb/>Kingdom and European Union, and current World Health <lb/>Organization recommendations for booster dose are do not in-<lb/>clude those aged younger than 50 years [12]. The cost effectiveness <lb/>of risk-based versus population-based approaches warrant addi-<lb/>tional careful evaluation [22-25]. <lb/>We also saw a moderate but highly statistically significant <lb/>24% reduction in Omicron COVID-19 for those randomized <lb/>to the original vaccine arm (median interval of 13 months <lb/>between second and third dose) [26] compared to the <lb/>placebo-crossover arm (median interval of 8 months between <lb/>second and third dose) and modeling predicted a 41% reduc-<lb/>tion in post-boost COVID-19 for a 15-month interval com-<lb/>pared to a 7-month interval. Other studies of interval in the <lb/>primary series have been reported. For the ChAdOx-1-S <lb/>COVID-19 vaccine, if the interval between the 1st and 2nd <lb/>dose was at least 12 weeks of protection against ancestral <lb/>COVID-19 was estimated at 81% compared to an estimated <lb/>55% when the interval was less than 6 weeks [27]. A longer <lb/>interval was also associated with higher binding and neutraliz-<lb/>ing antibody levels against the ancestral and Omicron BA.1 <lb/>strains. However, the interval between the second dose and <lb/>third doses had no appreciable impact on the incidence of <lb/>Delta COVID-19 [28]. This differential could be explained by <lb/>the higher infectivity of the Omicron strains, and its immuno-<lb/>logic distance from the ancestral strain. Studies showed that <lb/>after 3 doses of BNT162b2, the neutralizing antibody titers <lb/>were approximately 3-fold lower for the Delta strain versus <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="footnote">Who to Boost When for COVID-19 • OFID •</note>
    
    <page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/ofid/article/11/12/ofae689/7908454 by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>16-fold lower for the Omicron strain, in comparison to ances-<lb/>tral strain [29]. <lb/>To quantify the entire effect of a longer boosting interval <lb/>with higher preboost risk but lower postboost risk, we used <lb/>our estimated models to evaluate a strategy of 8-versus <lb/>14-month intervals. Other intervals would be of interest but in-<lb/>volve extrapolation beyond our data. We found modest benefits <lb/>of boosting in those aged &lt;65 years and greater benefits for <lb/>those aged ≥65 years, except when boosting was fortuitously <lb/>timed to occur just before a winter surge with 36% and 61% re-<lb/>ductions in the 2 age groups, respectively. These results indicate <lb/>that if one can roughly time the boost before the surge, a longer <lb/>interval would be preferred but otherwise either interval pro-<lb/>vides similar benefits. <lb/>We also examined the impact of dosing interval on antibody <lb/>response by comparing the randomized arms. Consistent with <lb/>a shorter interval from second to third dose, antibody levels at <lb/>BD1 were higher in the placebo-mRNA-1273 arm and lower in <lb/>the mRNA-1273 arm with GMRs of 2.08 and 1.12 for ancestral <lb/>SARS-COV-2 (D614G) and Omicron BA.1 nAbs, respectively. <lb/>At BD29, the analogous GMRs were 0.74 and 0.70, respectively. <lb/>Longer dosing intervals improve antibody response for differ-<lb/>ent vaccines, and our study adds to this literature [10]. <lb/>Our study has several limitations. We assessed boosting efficacy <lb/>of the original monovalent mRNA-1273 vaccine. The efficacy of <lb/>the current monovalent formula of mRNA-1273 vaccine remains <lb/>to be determined. In addition, the boosting efficacy was evaluated <lb/>against the Delta and BA.1 Omicron variants and not against var-<lb/>iants currently in circulation. The time of boosting was not ran-<lb/>domized and did not cover intervals shorter than 7 months. <lb/>Our analysis was performed in SARS-CoV-2-naïve individuals; <lb/>small numbers precluded an analysis of those with prior infection. <lb/>However, mRNA-1273 50 µg has been shown to be effective as a <lb/>booster regardless of prior infection status [15, 30]. And last, cases <lb/>were largely mild to moderate in severity, and an effect of the <lb/>interval on vaccine efficacy against severe disease cannot be <lb/>inferred from these data. A strength of the study was the <lb/>pseudo-randomized comparison of dosing interval by arm, <lb/>though dropout and infection may have resulted in group imbal-<lb/>ances in unmeasured confounders. Although we statistically ad-<lb/>justed for measured potential confounders and conducted <lb/>sensitivity analyses, residual unmeasured confounders are <lb/>possible. <lb/>In conclusion, these data demonstrate a clinical benefit of <lb/>additional mRNA-1273 vaccination for SARS-CoV-2-naïve <lb/>adults against mild to moderate Delta and BA.1 Omicron <lb/>COVID-19 with an increased benefit in those aged ≥65 years. <lb/>Additionally, although the research suggests there was a <lb/>benefit of a longer dosing interval between the primary <lb/>COVID-19 vaccination and booster dose, the clinical impact <lb/>of a longer interval is complex. A longer interval may have <lb/>led to a reduction in Omicron COVID-19, but this is <lb/>countered by an increased risk of COVID-19 while remaining <lb/>unboosted. Our modeling suggests similar benefits of 8-or <lb/>14-month interval unless one times a boost just before a surge, <lb/>in which case a longer interval has greater benefit. Although <lb/>updated research is needed on the impact of age and timing <lb/>of additional boosters on the efficacy of variant-targeting <lb/>vaccines, these data could be used to inform vaccination <lb/>policies [31]. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Data <lb/>Supplementary materials are available at Open Forum Infectious Diseases <lb/>online. Consisting of data provided by the authors to benefit the reader, the <lb/>posted materials are not copyedited and are the sole responsibility of the <lb/>authors, so questions or comments should be addressed to the correspond-<lb/>ing author. <lb/>Notes <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgments. This is an analysis of the open-label phase of the <lb/>COVE trial and provides a more focused evaluation of the effect of boosting <lb/>than is presented in Baden et al [15]. Statistical modeling is more thorough-<lb/>ly developed with sensitivity analyses, the effect of interval is modeled, risk <lb/>by age evaluated, new antibody data is presented and the entire effect of dif-<lb/>ferent boosting intervals modeled. <lb/></div>
      
      <div type="annex">Disclaimer. The findings and conclusions herein are those of the authors <lb/>and do not necessarily represent the views of the Department of Health and <lb/>Human Services or its components. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="availability">Data Sharing. Requests to use the data can be made to Moderna Inc., 200 <lb/>Technology Square, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA. A materials transfer and/ <lb/>or data access agreement with the sponsor will be required for accessing of <lb/>shared data. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="annex">IRB Approval. The COVE trial was conducted in accordance with <lb/>the Good Clinical Practice guidelines of the International Council <lb/>Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for Pharmaceuticals for Human <lb/>Use, and applicable government regulations. The central institutional review <lb/>board approved the protocol and the consent forms. All participants provided <lb/>written informed consent. <lb/></div>
      
      <div type="funding">Financial support. This work was supported in whole or in part with fede-<lb/>ral funds from the Department of Health and Human Services; <lb/>Administration for Strategic Preparedness and Response; Biomedical <lb/>Advanced Research and Development Authority, under Contract No. <lb/>75A50120C00034 (Moderna, Inc.). This study was supported by the <lb/>National Institutes of Health. The content is solely the responsibility of the <lb/>authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National <lb/>Institutes of Health. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="conflict">Potential conflicts of interest. All authors have completed the ICMJE <lb/>uniform disclosure form at www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Anderson E, Jackson L, Rouphael N, et al. Safety and immunogenicity of a third <lb/>dose of SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine-an interim analysis. Res Sq 2022: <lb/>rs.3.rs-1222037. <lb/>2. Pajon R, Paila YD, Girard B, et al. Initial analysis of viral dynamics and circulating <lb/>viral variants during the mRNA-1273 phase 3 COVE trial. Nat Med 2022; 28: <lb/>823-30. <lb/>3. Chu L, Vrbicky K, Montefiori D, et al. Immune response to SARS-CoV-2 after a <lb/>booster of mRNA-1273: an open-label phase 2 trial. Nat Med 2022; 28:1042-9. <lb/>4. Barda N, Dagan N, Cohen C, et al. Effectiveness of a third dose of the BNT162b2 <lb/>mRNA COVID-19 vaccine for preventing severe outcomes in Israel: an observa-<lb/>tional study. Lancet 2021; 398:2093-100. <lb/>5. Moreira ED, Jr., Kitchin N, Xu X, et al. Safety and efficacy of a third dose of <lb/>BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccine. N Engl J Med 2022; 386:1910-21. <lb/>6. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Interim Clinical Considerations for <lb/>Use of COVID-19 Vaccines in the United States. Available at: https://www.cdc. <lb/>gov/vaccines/covid-19/clinical-considerations/interim-considerations-us.html. <lb/>Accessed 27 September 2024 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6</page>
    
    <note place="footnote">• OFID • Follmann et al <lb/>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/ofid/article/11/12/ofae689/7908454 by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>7. Ku JH, Sy LS, Qian L, et al. Effectiveness of a fourth dose of mRNA-1273 against <lb/>COVID-19 among older adults in the United States: interim results from an ob-<lb/>servational cohort study. Vaccine 2023; 41:4212-9. <lb/>8. Stowe J, Andrews N, Kirsebom F, Ramsay M, Bernal JL. Effectiveness of <lb/>COVID-19 vaccines against Omicron and Delta hospitalisation, a test negative <lb/>case-control study. Nat Commun 2022; 13:5736. <lb/>9. DeCuir J, Payne AB, Self WH, et al. Interim effectiveness of updated 2023-2024 <lb/>(monovalent XBB.1.5) COVID-19 vaccines against COVID-19-associated emer-<lb/>gency department and urgent care encounters and hospitalization among immu-<lb/>nocompetent adults aged &gt;/=18 years -VISION and IVY networks, September <lb/>2023-January 2024. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2024; 73:180-8. <lb/>10. Rodrigues CMC, Plotkin SA. The influence of interval between doses on response <lb/>to vaccines. Vaccine 2021; 39:7123-7. <lb/>11. Payne RP, Longet S, Austin JA, et al. Immunogenicity of standard and extended <lb/>dosing intervals of BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine. Cell 2021; 184:5699-714.e11. <lb/>12. World Health Organization. COVID-19 advice for the public: Getting vaccinated. <lb/>Updated December 5, 2023. Available at: https://www.who.int/emergencies/ <lb/>diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/covid-19-vaccines/advice. Accessed 27 September <lb/>2024. <lb/>13. Baden LR, El Sahly HM, Essink B, et al. Efficacy and safety of the mRNA-1273 <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 vaccine. N Engl J Med 2021; 384:403-16. <lb/>14. U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration. Coronavirus (COVID-19) Update: FDA Takes <lb/>Additional Actions on the Use of a Booster Dose for COVID-19 Vaccines. <lb/>Available at: https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/coronavirus-<lb/>covid-19-update-fda-takes-additional-actions-use-booster-dose-covid-19-vaccines. <lb/>Accessed 9 February 2024. <lb/>15. Baden LR, Sahly HE, Essink B. Long-term safety and effectiveness of mRNA-1273 <lb/>vaccine in adults: COVE trial open-label and booster phases. Nat Commun 2024; <lb/>15:1-13. <lb/>16. El Sahly HM, Baden LR, Essink B, et al. Efficacy of the mRNA-1273 SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>vaccine at completion of blinded phase. N Engl J Med 2021; 385:1774-85. <lb/>17. Fintzi J, Follmann D. Assessing vaccine durability in randomized trials following <lb/>placebo crossover. Stat Med 2021; 40:5983-6007. <lb/>18. Follmann D, Fay M, Magaret C. Estimation of vaccine efficacy for variants that <lb/>emerge after the placebo group is vaccinated. Stat Med 2022; 41:3076-89. <lb/>19. Gilbert PB, Montefiori DC, McDermott AB, et al. Immune correlates analysis of <lb/>the mRNA-1273 COVID-19 vaccine efficacy clinical trial. Science 2022; 375: <lb/>43-50. <lb/>20. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. COVID-19 risks and vaccine infor-<lb/>mation for older adults: older unvaccinated adults are more likely to be hospital-<lb/>ized or die from COVID-19. Available at: https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/119720. <lb/>21. Ferdinands JM, Rao S, Dixon BE, et al. Waning of vaccine effectiveness against <lb/>moderate and severe COVID-19 among adults in the US from the VISION net-<lb/>work: test negative, case-control study. BMJ 2022; 379:e072141. <lb/>22. Kohli M, Maschio M, Becker D, Weinstein MC. The potential public health and <lb/>economic value of a hypothetical COVID-19 vaccine in the United States: use of <lb/>cost-effectiveness modeling to inform vaccination prioritization. Vaccine 2021; <lb/>39:1157-64. <lb/>23. Morales-Zamora G, Espinosa O, Puertas E, et al. Cost-effectiveness analysis of <lb/>strategies of COVID-19 vaccination in Colombia: comparison of high-risk prior-<lb/>itization and no prioritization strategies with the absence of a vaccination plan. <lb/>Value Health Reg Issues 2022; 31:101-10. <lb/>24. Chapman LAC, Shukla P, Rodríguez-Barraquer I, et al. Risk factor targeting for <lb/>vaccine prioritization during the COVID-19 pandemic. Sci Rep 2022; 12:3055. <lb/>25. Matrajt L, Eaton J, Leung T, Brown ER. Vaccine optimization for COVID-19: who <lb/>to vaccinate first? Sci Adv 2021; 7:eabf1374. <lb/>26. Kim SS, Flannery B, Foppa IM, et al. Effects of prior season vaccination on current <lb/>season vaccine effectiveness in the United States flu vaccine effectiveness network, <lb/>2012-2013 through 2017-2018. Clin Infect Dis 2021; 73:497-505. <lb/>27. Voysey M, Costa Clemens SA, Madhi SA, et al. Single-dose administration and <lb/>the influence of the timing of the booster dose on immunogenicity and efficacy <lb/>of ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 (AZD1222) vaccine: a pooled analysis of four randomised <lb/>trials. Lancet 2021; 397:881-91. <lb/>28. Niyomnaitham S, Jongkaewwattana A, Meesing A, et al. Immune responses of the <lb/>third dose of AZD1222 vaccine or BNT162b2 mRNA vaccine after two doses of <lb/>CoronaVac vaccines against Delta and Omicron variants. medRxiv 22280572 <lb/>[Preprint]. October 03, 2022. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.10.02. <lb/>22280572. <lb/>29. Planas D, Saunders N, Maes P, et al. Considerable escape of SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>Omicron to antibody neutralization. Nature 2022; 602:671-5. <lb/>30. Zhang B, Fong Y, Fintzi J, et al. Omicron COVID-19 immune correlates analysis <lb/>of a third dose of mRNA-1273 in the COVE trial. medRxiv 23295628 [Preprint]. <lb/>October 15, 2023. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.10.15.23295628. <lb/>31. Rogawski McQuade ET, Breskin A. Longer intervals and extra doses of ChAdOx1 <lb/>nCoV-19 vaccine. Lancet 2021; 398:933-5. doi:10.1016/s0140-6736(21)01817-1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Who to Boost When for COVID-19 • OFID • </note>
    
    <page>7 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/ofid/article/11/12/ofae689/7908454 by guest on 10 September 2025</note> 


	</text>

</TEI>