<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>LETTER • OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Evaluation of sea salt aerosols in climate systems: <lb/>global climate modeling and observation-based <lb/>analyses * <lb/>To cite this article: Yi-Chun Chen et al 2020 Environ. Res. Lett. 15 034047 <lb/>View the article online for updates and enhancements. <lb/>You may also like <lb/>A Prediction of Grain Yield Based on <lb/>Hybrid Intelligent Algorithm <lb/>Ibrahim Ahmed Saleh, Wasan Abdallah <lb/>Alawsi, Omar Ibrahim Alsaif et al. <lb/>-<lb/>Breaking waves and near-surface sea <lb/>spray aerosol dependence on changing <lb/>winds: Wave breaking efficiency and <lb/>bubble-related air-sea interaction <lb/>processes <lb/>P A Hwang, I B Savelyev and M D <lb/>Anguelova <lb/>-<lb/>Can baroreflex measurements with <lb/>spontaneous sequence analysis be <lb/>improved by also measuring breathing and <lb/>by standardization of filtering strategies? <lb/>M R Hollow, T H Clutton-Brock and M J <lb/>Parkes <lb/>-<lb/>This content was downloaded from IP address 5.102.4.39 on 02/08/2022 at 11:01 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>Environ. Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab751c <lb/>LETTER <lb/>Evaluation of sea salt aerosols in climate systems: global climate <lb/>modeling and observation-based analyses * <lb/>Yi-Chun Chen 1,5 , Jui-Lin F Li 2 , Wei-Liang Lee 1 , David J Diner 2 , Michael J Garay 2 , Jonathan H Jiang 2 , <lb/>Yi-Hui Wang 3 , Jia-Yuh Yu 4 and Olga V Kalashnikova 2 <lb/>1 Research Center for Environmental Changes, Academia Sinica, Taipei, Taiwan <lb/>2 Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA, United States of America <lb/>3 California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo, United States of America <lb/>4 Department of Atmospheric Sciences, National Central University, Taoyuan City, Taiwan <lb/>5 Author to whom any correspondence should be addressed. <lb/>E-mail: yichunchen@gate.sinica.edu.tw <lb/>Keywords: global climate modeling, aerosols, sea salt, falling ice radiative effects <lb/>Supplementary material for this article is available online <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Sea salt aerosols (SSA), one of the most abundant aerosol species over the global oceans, play important <lb/>roles for Earth&apos;s climate. State-of-the-art SSA parameterizations in global climate models (GCMs) are <lb/>typically modeled using near-surface wind speed, sea surface temperature (SST), and precipitation. <lb/>However, these have non-trivial biases in CMIP3 and CMIP5 GCMs over the tropical Pacific Ocean that <lb/>can contribute to biases in the simulated SSA. This study investigates the impacts of falling ice radiative <lb/>effects on the biases of the aforementioned modeled parameters and the resulting modeled SSA biases. We <lb/>compare the CMIP5 modeled SSA against satellite observations from MISR and MODIS using a pair of <lb/>sensitivity experiments with falling ice radiative effects on and off in the CESM1-CAM5 model. The results <lb/>show that when falling ice radiative effects are not taken into account, models have weaker surface wind <lb/>speeds, warmer SSTs, excessive precipitation, and diluted sea surface salinity (SSS) over the Pacific trade-<lb/>wind regions, leading to underestimated SSA. In the tropical Pacific Ocean, the inclusion of falling ice <lb/>radiative effects leads to improvements in the modeled near-surface wind speeds, SSTs, and precipitation <lb/>through cloud-precipitation-radiation-circulation coupling, which results in more representative patterns <lb/>of SSA and reduces the SSA biases by ∼10% to 15% relative to the satellite observations. Models including <lb/>falling ice radiative effects in CMIP5 produce smaller biases in SSA than those without falling ice radiative <lb/>effects. We suggest that one of the causes of these biases is likely the failure to account for falling ice radiative <lb/>effects, and these biases in turn affect the direct and indirect effects of SSA in the GCMs. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Despite decades of research, aerosols and clouds con-<lb/>tinue to contribute to large uncertainties in estimates of <lb/>the Earth&apos;s changing energy budget (Boucher et al 2013). <lb/>To reduce these uncertainties, it is essential for atmo-<lb/>spheric models to realistically represent the geographical <lb/>distributions of aerosols; this, in turn, is critical for <lb/>accurate simulation of Earth&apos;s surface energy and water <lb/>budgets. However, the present-day representation of <lb/>aerosols and clouds and, more specifically, their interac-<lb/>tions in general circulation models (GCMs), are major <lb/>contributors to the remaining uncertainties in climate <lb/>change predictions (Seinfeld et al 2016). <lb/>Sea spray aerosol including sea salt aerosols (SSA), <lb/>the largest natural aerosol source, is produced over <lb/>more than 70% of the Earth&apos;s surface and plays an <lb/>important role in the Earth&apos;s radiative budget (Seinfeld <lb/>and Pandis 2006). SSA perturb the radiation budget <lb/>through scattering and absorption of solar radiation <lb/>and emitting thermal infrared radiation (referred to as <lb/>aerosol direct effects). Observations in Nakajima et al <lb/>(2001) showed there is a positive correlation between <lb/></body>

			<front>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>RECEIVED <lb/>11 August 2019 <lb/>REVISED <lb/>30 January 2020 <lb/>ACCEPTED FOR PUBLICATION <lb/>11 February 2020 <lb/>PUBLISHED <lb/>5 March 2020 <lb/>Original content from this <lb/>work may be used under <lb/>the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution 4.0 <lb/>licence. <lb/>Any further distribution of <lb/>this work must maintain <lb/>attribution to the <lb/>author(s) and the title of <lb/>the work, journal citation <lb/>and DOI. <lb/>* The data that support the findings of this study are available from <lb/>the corresponding author upon reasonable request. <lb/>© 2020 The Author(s). Published by IOP Publishing Ltd <lb/></front>

			<body>cloud optical thickness and oceanic aerosol number <lb/>concentration, whereas the effective particle radius has <lb/>a negative correlation with aerosol number concentra-<lb/>tion. Many studies have suggested SSA are the main <lb/>sources of cloud condensation nuclei over the ocean <lb/>(e.g. Pierce and Adams 2006), affecting the micro-<lb/>physical properties of shallow planetary boundary <lb/>layer marine clouds and hence their radiative proper-<lb/>ties, amount, and lifetime (referred to as aerosol indir-<lb/>ect effects). Aerosols are coupled with clouds through <lb/>aerosol indirect effects and semi-direct effects (IPCC <lb/>AR5). Changes in aerosol abundance affect the <lb/>response of trade-wind shallow cumulus, including <lb/>cloud microphysical and macrophysical properties <lb/>(e.g. Xue et al 2008, Saleeby et al 2015), convection <lb/>(e.g. Jiang et al 2018), precipitation (e.g. Kogan et al <lb/>2012), and cloud lifetime (e.g. Jiang et al 2006). Sig-<lb/>nificant discrepancies in aerosol optical depth (AOD) <lb/>between GCMs and satellite observations contribute <lb/>to biases in estimating aerosol direct and indirect <lb/>radiative forcing, and therefore the climate feedback. <lb/>Over the ocean, the main emission of SSA is <lb/>through air bubbles bursting at the air-sea interface, <lb/>meaning the production of SSA is directly affected by <lb/>air-sea interactions such as near surface winds, sea sur-<lb/>face wind stress, sea surface temperature (SST), sea <lb/>surface salinity (SSS), and precipitation (Wood-<lb/>cock 1953, Seinfeld and Pandis 2006). Most para-<lb/>meterizations in GCMs assume that SSA emission has <lb/>a strong dependence on 10 m wind speed (Monahan <lb/>et al 1986). Some parameterizations also include <lb/>dependencies on different meteorological parameters, <lb/>such as SST (Martensson et al 2003, Jaegléet al 2011, <lb/>Witek et al 2016) and SSS (Ovadnevaite et al 2014). <lb/>In the Community Atmosphere Model version 5 <lb/>(CAM5) of the Community Earth System Model version <lb/>1 (CESM1), the parameterization of SSA sources is <lb/>derived from a method proposed by Martensson et al <lb/>(2003), which is based on lab experiment for particles <lb/>with dry diameters ( ) <lb/>D p from 20 to ∼2500 nm. The par-<lb/>ticle flux, F, as a function of whitecap area is expressed as: <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>() <lb/>= <lb/>´´+ <lb/>dF <lb/>d <lb/>D <lb/>W <lb/>A SST B <lb/>log <lb/>, <lb/>1 <lb/>p <lb/>where = <lb/>´-<lb/>W <lb/>U <lb/>3.84 10 <lb/>, <lb/>4 <lb/>10 <lb/>3.41 U 10 is the wind speed at <lb/>10 m above the sea surface; A and B are size dependent <lb/>polynomials, with coefficients listed in table 1 of <lb/>Martensson et al (2003). For dry diameters &gt;2-3 mm, <lb/>the parameterization is based on Monahan et al <lb/>(1986), derived as <lb/>= Ć U , <lb/>dF <lb/>d <lb/>D <lb/>log <lb/>10 <lb/>3.41 <lb/>p <lb/>where C is a <lb/>function of particle size. <lb/>Other than SSA produced by breaking waves, the <lb/>depletion of SSA includes wet deposition and dry <lb/>deposition (gravity and turbulence). As the para-<lb/>meterizations are dependent on 10 m wind speed, SST, <lb/>and precipitation, etc, model biases caused by these <lb/>parameters via other dynamical and physical errors <lb/>can lead to errors in the modeled SSA indirectly. One <lb/>cause of the aforementioned model biases could be <lb/>attributed to missing representation of the radiative <lb/>effects of falling ice (snow or precipitating ice) radia-<lb/>tive effects in the models (Li et al 2015; supplementary <lb/>information, available online at stacks.iop.org/ERL/ <lb/>15/034047/mmedia). Li et al (2015) pointed out that <lb/>all the GCMs in the Coupled Model Intercomparison <lb/>Project phase 3 (CMIP3) and most in the phase 5 <lb/>(CMIP5) do not consider precipitating ice radiative <lb/>effects, and these models tend to have too strong con-<lb/>vection, producing anomalous low-level outflow (see <lb/>SI, figure S2(b)) over the Intertropical Convergence <lb/>Zone (ITCZ), South Pacific Convergence Zone <lb/>(SPCZ), and Maritime Continent (See SI, figure S3). <lb/>This leads to weakening surface wind stress, weaker <lb/>low-level winds and upper ocean mixing, resulting in <lb/>warmer SSTs (See SI, figure S4), producing excessive <lb/>precipitation, and diluting SSS over trade-wind <lb/>regions (Li et al 2014, 2016, 2018). The following ques-<lb/>tion will be addressed in this study: to what extent do <lb/>the responses (i.e. weaker surface winds, warmer SSTs, <lb/>and excessive precipitation) from lacking falling ice <lb/>radiative effects contribute to the GCM biases in SSA <lb/>simulations?In other words, what are the impacts on <lb/>local SSA through the remote influence of changes in <lb/>circulation?The SSA biases would in turn affect the <lb/>shallow convection and aerosol direct effects, and thus <lb/>climate feedback. <lb/>In this study, we explore the impacts of missing <lb/>falling ice radiation interactions on aerosol loadings <lb/>parameterized in equation (1) for SSA by conducting a <lb/>pair of sensitivity tests by turning on or off falling ice <lb/>radiative effects in CESM1-CAM5, and comparing the <lb/>results to aerosol data from the Multi-angle Imaging <lb/>SpectroRadiometer (MISR) and MODerate-resolu-<lb/>tion Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) satellite <lb/>Table 1. List of coupled atmosphere-ocean climate models in CMIP5 archive historical run used in this study and corresponding institute. <lb/>Model <lb/>Institute <lb/>CESM1 <lb/>National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR, USA) <lb/>HadGEM2 <lb/>Met Office Hadley Center ESM (UK) <lb/>BNU-ESM <lb/>College of Global Change and Earth System Science, Beijing Normal University (China) <lb/>IPSL-CM5 <lb/>Institute Pierre-Simon Laplace (France) <lb/>MIROC-ESM <lb/>Japan Agency for Marine-Earth Science and Technology, Atmosphere and Ocean Research Institute (The University of <lb/>Tokyo), and National Institute for Environmental Studies (Japan) <lb/>MRI-CGCM3 <lb/>Meteorological Research Institute (Japan) <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Environ. Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 <lb/></note>

			<body>instruments. This paper is structured as follows: <lb/>section 2 includes a brief description of the model <lb/>simulations and key observations used. Section 3 <lb/>describes the biases in CMIP5 reports compared to <lb/>observations and results from sensitivity experiments. <lb/>Conclusions and a discussion of major findings are <lb/>provided in section 4. <lb/>2. Model and data description <lb/>2.1. Model and sensitivity experiment <lb/>The National Center for Atmospheric Research-<lb/>Department of Energy (NCAR-DOE) CESM1 is a <lb/>coupled climate model for simulating the Earth&apos;s <lb/>climate system (for details see section 2 in Li et al <lb/>(2015)). The descriptions and performance of the <lb/>cloud-related physical parameterizations in its atmos-<lb/>phere component, CAM5, can be found in Morrison <lb/>and Gettelman (2008), Gettelman et al (2010), and <lb/>Lindvall et al (2013). <lb/>In this study, numerical experiments were per-<lb/>formed with the diagnostic falling ice radiative effects <lb/>turned off (hereafter, NoS) and on (hereafter, S). The <lb/>changes of model fields due to the inclusion of falling <lb/>ice radiative effects are calculated as the difference <lb/>between the simulation without and with these effects, <lb/>which is referred to as &apos;NoS-S.&apos; Both simulations are <lb/>set up in the same manner as used in CMIP5. The spe-<lb/>cific scenario used in these sensitivity experiments is <lb/>the CMIP5 historical runs (1850-2005) with exactly <lb/>the same model components used in the CESM1 <lb/>contribution to CMIP5, where the same initial fields <lb/>from preindustrial and the observed 20th century <lb/>greenhouse gas, ozone, aerosol, and solar forcing are <lb/>used (Taylor et al 2012). The simulation time period <lb/>used in the analyses presented here is 1970-2005. <lb/>2.2. Satellite AOD data <lb/>In this study, AOD observations from MISR and MODIS <lb/>are utilized. MISR was launched in December 1999 <lb/>onboard Terra, NASA&apos;s flagship Earth Observing System <lb/>(EOS) spacecraft. MISR consists of nine cameras that <lb/>view the Earth simultaneously at different angles (nadir <lb/>and 26.1°, 45.6°, 60.0°, and 70.5°forward and backward <lb/>of nadir) and observes each scene over an interval of <lb/>7 min with a common swath of approximately 400 km <lb/>(Diner et al 1998). Global coverage is achieved every nine <lb/>days. MISR&apos;s standard, operational data products are <lb/>available and listed in the following link: http://eosweb. <lb/>larc.nasa.gov/project/misr/misr_table. <lb/>MODIS aboard NASA&apos;s Terra satellite, has 36 <lb/>spectral bands with wavelengths from 0.41 to 14 μm <lb/>and its 2330 km wide swath provides global coverage <lb/>every two days. Both MODIS and MISR have been <lb/>widely used for monitoring aerosol properties and <lb/>both provide long time series of global aerosol abun-<lb/>dances and properties. In this study, we utilize Level 3 <lb/>monthly gridded data from MISR Version 22 and <lb/>MODIS Collection 6.1 Dark Target (DT) to compare <lb/>with model results. <lb/>Figure 1 shows the annual mean AOD distribution <lb/>over the global ocean from these satellite observations <lb/>based on the time period from 2001 through 2005. <lb/>The spatial pattern and magnitudes are similar <lb/>between the MISR and MODIS annual AODs <lb/>(figures 1(a) and (b)), with a mean AOD difference of <lb/>about 0.01 over global ocean (figure 1(c)). Based on <lb/>Kahn et al (2009), the MISR-MODIS correlation coef-<lb/>ficient is about 0.9 over ocean. <lb/>For ocean, the MODIS Collection 6.1 DT AODs <lb/>agree well with the Aerosol Robotic Network (AERO-<lb/>NET) AODs (correlation coefficient = 0.880, and <lb/>root-mean-square error = 0.083) with 73.5% of the <lb/>data samples falling within the expected errors (as <lb/>shown in figure 3(a) in Wei et al 2019). The uncer-<lb/>tainty of MODIS AOD is ±(0.03+5% × AOD) over <lb/>ocean (Remer et al 2005, Wei et al 2019). As for MISR, <lb/>about 70%-75% of MISR-retrieved AOD values falls <lb/>within the greater of 0.05 or 20%×AOD of AERO-<lb/>NET (Kahn et al 2010). The correlation coefficients <lb/>between MISR AOD and AERONET are ∼0.9 for mar-<lb/>itime stations (Kahn et al 2010). In the version of the <lb/>product used here, the retrieval of MISR AOD over <lb/>water may be subject to several known issues, includ-<lb/>ing cloud contamination of retrieved AOD, camera <lb/>artifacts in high-contrast scenes, residual calibration <lb/>effects, etc (e.g. Witek et al 2018a, 2018b). Despite dif-<lb/>ferent sources of uncertainty from the two satellite <lb/>retrievals, these data sets are the best available in terms <lb/>of their long term records and global coverage, and <lb/>figure 1(c) provides confidence that their performance <lb/>is similar over global oceans. For model and observa-<lb/>tions comparisons, we use the long-term annual mean <lb/>AOD output from 10 CMIP5 CGCM historical runs <lb/>(1970-2005) with the mean annual AOD retrieved <lb/>from MISR and MODIS (2001-2005) (see figure 2). <lb/>3. Model results <lb/>3.1. CMIP5 model AOD bias <lb/>Figures 2(a)-(j) show the biases of long-term mean <lb/>(1970-2005) spatial distribution of AOD in the Pacific <lb/>from 10 CMIP5 CGCMs (see table 1) as compared with <lb/>satellite observations, shown in figure 2(k) for reference. <lb/>For six of the models, the simulated annual mean AOD <lb/>is underestimated relative to mean satellite AOD, while <lb/>four of the models (figures 2(a)-(d)) show relatively <lb/>good agreement. For the three models in which falling <lb/>ice radiative effects are considered (figures 2(a)-(c)), the <lb/>AOD bias is relatively small over the tropical Pacific <lb/>with a mean of −0.002 (figure 3(a)). In comparison, the <lb/>AOD over the tropical Pacific is significantly under-<lb/>estimated by those models that do not consider falling <lb/>ice radiative effects (figures 2(e)-(j)), which overall have <lb/>a mean bias of −0.047 (figure 3(b)). <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Environ. Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 <lb/></note>

			<body>It has already been demonstrated that non-trivial <lb/>biases exist in those CMIP3 and CMIP5 models that do <lb/>not have falling ice radiative effects, with the resulting <lb/>simulations exhibiting excessive precipitation, too-<lb/>weak low-level winds, and underestimated SSS over <lb/>Pacific trade-wind regions (Li et al 2014, 2016, 2018). <lb/>Here we investigate how these biases affect the <lb/>simulated AOD through sensitivity studies performed <lb/>using CESM1 as described in the following section. <lb/>3.2. Sensitivity results from falling ice radiative <lb/>effects using CESM1 <lb/>Using a pair of sensitivity tests turning on or off falling <lb/>ice radiative effects in CESM1-CAM5, we examine the <lb/>Figure 2. (a)-(j) Difference maps between the CMIP5 CGCM simulated and observed estimate of long term annual domain mean <lb/>AOD. (k) Annual domain mean AOD map from satellite MISR and MODIS ((MISR + MODIS)/2; 2001-2005 average). <lb/>Figure 1. Annual (ANN) domain mean AOD for oceanic regions between 45S and 45N from (a) MISR and (b) MODIS, based on the <lb/>means from 2001 to 2005. The AOD difference between satellite observations are shown in (c) MODIS AOD minus MISR AOD. The <lb/>data resolution is 1°× 1°. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Environ. Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 <lb/></note>

			<body>impacts of falling ice radiative effects on the SSA bias. <lb/>Based on the parameterization of SSA generation in <lb/>CESM1 represented in equation (1), the sensitivities of <lb/>wind speed, SST, and precipitation to the falling ice <lb/>radiative effects are examined over Pacific trade-wind <lb/>regions, in particular. <lb/>Figure 4 shows the 925 hPa wind differences for <lb/>1970-2005 for the NoS-S scenarios from our CESM1-<lb/>CAM5 simulations. The V-shaped marking in figure 4 <lb/>highlights a region where an anomalous southeast <lb/>low-level outflow is clearly found over the northern <lb/>warm pool and southern Pacific trade wind regions in <lb/>the annual mean state (figure 4(a)). The smallest wind <lb/>speed differences between the NoS and S scenarios are <lb/>observed in the boreal summer months (JJA, <lb/>figure 4(b)) while the largest wind speed differences <lb/>are observed in boreal winter (DJF, figure 4(c)). These <lb/>patterns are also common in the CMIP5 models that <lb/>lack falling ice-radiation effects (see SI). <lb/>The differences in annual means of AOD, 10 m <lb/>wind speed, precipitation, and SST between NoS and S <lb/>(NoS-S) for the Pacific basin are shown in figure 5. The <lb/>AOD difference between NoS and S simulations <lb/>(figure 5(a)) is more apparent from the Western Pacific <lb/>warm pool to the north of the SPCZ, with lower AOD in <lb/>NoS simulations (those not including falling ice-radia-<lb/>tion interactions). In the NoS case, relative to the S case, <lb/>there are weaker easterly trade winds (figure 5(b)) <lb/>caused by low-level outflow, resulting in weaker upper <lb/>ocean mixing along with excessive precipitation <lb/>(figure 5(c)), and warmer SST (Ts; shown in figure 5(d)) <lb/>over the tropical Pacific with underestimated AOD. <lb/>This demonstrates there are systematic biases in the <lb/>coupling of the precipitation-radiation-circulation <lb/>caused by the lack of falling ice radiative effects simu-<lb/>lated in CESM1. Through changes in wind, precipita-<lb/>tion, and SST, the abundance of SSA is altered via <lb/>dynamical air-sea coupling processes. <lb/>Figure 3. (a) Mean AOD bias from 3 GCMs with falling ice radiative effects (i.e. CESM1_S, HadGEM2-CC, and HadGEM2-ES) as <lb/>compared to satellite observations from MODIS and MISR. (b) same as (a), but from 7 GCMs without falling ice radiative effects (i.e. <lb/>models from figures 2(d)-(j)). (c) same as (a), but from all 10 GCMs. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 <lb/></note>

			<body>The correlation in the Pacific between the difference <lb/>in AOD and the change in each dependent parameter <lb/>was examined. The AOD difference between NoS and S <lb/>is highly correlated with the difference in wind speed <lb/>(figure 6(a)), with a domain-averaged spatial correlation <lb/>coefficient of 0.64. This is not surprising, as the source of <lb/>SSA depends on wind speed to the power of 3.41, as <lb/>shown in equation (1). On the other hand, excessive pre-<lb/>cipitation leads to a negative correlation between the <lb/>change in precipitation and the change in AOD from the <lb/>NoS and S simulations, with a domain-averaged correla-<lb/>tion coefficient of −0.40 (figure 6(b)). For AOD and SST, <lb/>the correlation coefficient is −0.32 (figure 6(c)), which <lb/>indicates a somewhat weaker relationship compared to <lb/>AOD-wind speed and AOD-precipitation. The relation-<lb/>ship between AOD and SST is dependent on the size of <lb/>the aerosol particles according to laboratory experiments <lb/>carried out by Martensson et al (2003). For aerosols with <lb/>dry diameters &lt;0.07 μm (&gt;0.35 μm), the number con-<lb/>centration decreases (increases) with increasing (decreas-<lb/>ing) water temperature. For the size range from 0.07 to <lb/>0.35 μm, there is no clear temperature dependence of the <lb/>aerosol concentrations. The correlations between AOD <lb/>difference and precipitation/SST difference (−0.4 and <lb/>−0.32) are not robust enough, which might be due to the <lb/>offset contributions from the 10m wind speed (positive <lb/>contribution) and precipitation/SSTs (negative contrib-<lb/>ution) to the net AOD changes. <lb/>Figure 7 shows the improvement from NoS to S <lb/>against the annual mean AOD from MISR and <lb/>MODIS observations. The satellite data are from 2001 <lb/>to 2005, corresponding to the period of overlap <lb/>between model simulations and observations. As <lb/>shown in figure 2(a), comparing the CESM1 simula-<lb/>tions with MISR and MODIS, the simulated AODs are <lb/>underestimated in the western central Pacific Ocean <lb/>near the equator and in the northwest Pacific Ocean. <lb/>In order to determine whether the inclusion of falling <lb/>ice radiation interactions can decrease the biases <lb/>between the model and the observations, the absolute <lb/>improvement from NoS to S run compared to obser-<lb/>vations is calculated as: <lb/>⎛ <lb/>⎝ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎞ <lb/>⎠ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>= <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Ábsolute <lb/>improvement <lb/>AOD <lb/>AOD <lb/>AOD <lb/>AOD <lb/>AOD <lb/>AOD <lb/>% <lb/>100%. <lb/>2 <lb/>NoS <lb/>satellite <lb/>satellite <lb/>S <lb/>satellite <lb/>satellite <lb/>Positive values indicate improvement from NoS to S. <lb/>In figure 7(a), regions with positive values (reddish <lb/>Figure 4. (a) Annual mean 925 hPa wind vector change (units: m s −1 ) from the simulation with the changes (falling ice radiative effect <lb/>off (NoS) minus falling ice radiative effect on (S)). Averages over 1970-2005 in CMIP5 historical protocol simulations using CESM1-<lb/>CAM5. By excluding the falling ice radiation effect, extra radiative cooling near cloud tops in convective regions destabilizes the <lb/>atmosphere and leads to local subsidence north of the SPCZ and south of the ITCZ. Consequent anomalous low-level eastward and/ <lb/>or southeastward advection from the warm pool, ITCZ, and SPCZ results in moisture convergence and excessive rain in the V-shaped <lb/>region bounded by the two black lines. The V-shaped region is defined by the region between north of the SPCZ and south of the <lb/>ITCZ. (b) Same as (a) but for June-July-August (JJA). (c) Same as (a) but for December-January-February (DJF). Units: m s −1 . <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Environ. Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 <lb/></note>

			<body>colors) indicate improvement when the falling ice <lb/>radiative effects are included in the CESM1 run, <lb/>whereas regions with negative values (darker colors) <lb/>indicate worse agreement. Improvements are found in <lb/>most areas of the Pacific Ocean, except for certain <lb/>regions in the eastern central Pacific and southwest <lb/>Pacific near Australia. The largest improvement occurs <lb/>in the central Pacific. With the falling ice radiative <lb/>effects included, simulated AOD in the central Pacific <lb/>Ocean improves by ∼10% to 15%. The patterns are <lb/>more or less matched with the difference between NoS <lb/>and S shown in figure 7(b). <lb/>Figure 5. The changes (falling ice radiative effect off (NoS) minus falling ice radiative effect on (S)) of annual mean maps of (a) AOD, <lb/>(b) 10 m wind speed (m s −1 ), (c) precipitation (mm d −1 ), and (d) sea surface temperature (K). <lb/>Figure 6. (a) Scatter plot of AOD difference between NoS and S run (ΔAOD) versus 10 m wind difference between NoS and S run <lb/>(ΔU 10 ) for the oceanic region from 60S to 60N and 120E to 60W (same domain as in figure 4); the correlation coefficient (corr) is <lb/>shown on the plot. (b) Same as (a), but for ΔAOD versus Δrain rate. (c) Same as (a), but for ΔAOD versus ΔTs. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 <lb/></note>

			<body>4. Conclusion and discussion <lb/>Oceanic aerosols are important for supplying cloud <lb/>condensation nuclei, and affect Earth&apos;s climate energy <lb/>and water budget through their coupling to clouds via <lb/>the indirect and semi-direct effects. In GCMs, the <lb/>representation of SSA is dependent upon modeled <lb/>near-surface wind speed, SST, and precipitation. <lb/>However, most GCMs do not consider falling ice <lb/>radiative effects, resulting in too-warm SSTs, weaker <lb/>surface winds and excessive precipitation over the <lb/>Pacific trade-wind regions. To explore whether these <lb/>effects might lead to underestimated SSA, we exam-<lb/>ined the impacts of falling ice radiative effects on <lb/>modeled SSA using CESM1-CAM5 by turning on and <lb/>off falling ice radiative effects (S and NoS). We found <lb/>that when neglecting the falling ice radiative effects in <lb/>CESM1, the model produces weaker low-level winds, <lb/>excessive precipitation, and warmer SST, leading to <lb/>underestimated SSA through precipitation-cloud-cir-<lb/>culation coupling. The above mentioned biases are <lb/>commonly found in most CMIP5 models. The geo-<lb/>graphic distribution and the values of the SSA bias are <lb/>found to be mainly controlled by the modeled biases in <lb/>precipitation and surface wind speeds. With the <lb/>inclusion of falling ice radiation effects in CESM1, the <lb/>SSA absolute biases decrease by ∼10% to 15% in the <lb/>central Pacific Ocean. <lb/>We conclude that the exclusion of falling ice radia-<lb/>tive effects in most GCMs partially contributes to the <lb/>modeled AOD biases. We found that in most CMIP5 <lb/>models the differences between the NoS and S scenar-<lb/>ios correspond to anomalously weaker outflow in the <lb/>western Pacific warm pool and southern Pacific trade <lb/>wind regions, which reduces upper ocean mixing and <lb/>ultimately increases SST and precipitation and decrea-<lb/>ses sea surface salinity. It is suggested that one cause of <lb/>bias between modeled SSA and satellite data is the <lb/>missing representation of the falling ice radiative <lb/>effects in the models. As indicated schematically in <lb/>figure 8, the local SSA can be affected by local and non-<lb/>local air-sea coupling. The SSA bias could be reduced <lb/>by improving the model-simulated near surface <lb/>winds, SST, and precipitation. For GCMs including <lb/>the falling ice radiative effects, the SSA biases have <lb/>decreased, as shown in CESM1-CAM5 and two Had-<lb/>GEM2 models in CMIP5. We found that the bias in <lb/>the simulating SSA radiative effects can therefore be <lb/>influenced by the biases either locally or remotely <lb/>determined by other parameters, in this case, pre-<lb/>cipitation, surface winds, and SSTs through air-sea <lb/>coupling. We suggest that when dealing with aerosol <lb/>biases in model, other than tuning the emissions, con-<lb/>sideration of the dynamical processes affecting aerosol <lb/>abundance is also essential. <lb/>Figure 7. (a) improvement from NoS to S run (%), as calculated in equation (2), (b) AOD difference between CESM1 NoS <lb/>and S run (i.e. NoS AOD AOD). <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Environ. Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>YCC acknowledge RCEC, Academia Sinica for sup-<lb/>porting this study. The authors acknowledge Marcin <lb/>Witek for his review and comments. The contribution <lb/>by JLL, DJD, MJG, JHJ, and OVK to this study was <lb/>carried out at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California <lb/>Institute of Technology, under contracts of ATMOS <lb/>COMP 2013 (NNH12ZDA001N-CCST) with the <lb/>National Aeronautics and Space Administration <lb/>(NASA). This work has been supported in part by the <lb/>NASA Making Earth System Data Records for Use in <lb/>Research Environments (MEaSUREs) programs. The <lb/>authors acknowledge PCMDI/DOE and the WCRP&apos;s <lb/>WGCM for their roles in making CMIP3/CMIP5 <lb/>available. MODIS aerosol data were downloaded using <lb/>the GES-DISC Interactive Online Visualization and <lb/>Analysis Infrastructure, a part of the NASA&apos;s Goddard <lb/>Earth Sciences Data and Information Services Center. <lb/>MISR aerosol data (MIL3MAE.004) were obtained <lb/>from the NASA Langley Research Center Atmospheric <lb/>Science Data center (ASDC). <lb/></div>

			<front>ORCID iDs <lb/>Yi-Chun Chen https:/ /orcid.org/0000-0001-<lb/>7997-8578 <lb/>Jui-Lin F Li https:/ /orcid.org/0000-0002-<lb/>1294-9526 <lb/>Wei-Liang Lee https:/ /orcid.org/0000-0003-<lb/>1419-315X <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Boucher OIPCC AR5 et al 2013 Clouds and aerosols Climate Change <lb/>2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working <lb/>Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental <lb/>Panel on Climate Change ed T F Stocker et al (Cambridge and <lb/>New York: Cambridge University Press) <lb/>Diner D J et al 1998 Multiangle Imaging SpectroRadiometer (MISR) <lb/>description and experiment overview IEEE Trans. Geosci. <lb/>Rem. Sens. 36 1072-87 <lb/>Gettelman A, Liu X, Ghan S J, Morrison H, Park S, Conley A J, <lb/>Klein S A, Boyle J, Mitchell D L and Li J-L F 2010 Global <lb/>simulations of ice nucleation and ice supersaturation with an <lb/>improved cloud scheme in the Community Atmosphere <lb/>Model J. Geophys. Res. 115 D18216 <lb/>JaegléL, Quinn P K, Bates T S, Alexander B and Lin J T 2011 Global <lb/>distribution of sea salt aerosols: new constraints from in situ <lb/>and remote sensing observations Atmos. Chem. Phys. 11 <lb/>3137-31573 <lb/>Jiang H, Xue H, Teller A, Feingold G and Levin Z 2006 Aerosol <lb/>effects on the lifetime of shallow cumulus Geophys. Res. Lett. <lb/>33 L14806 <lb/>Jiang J H, Su H, Huang L, Wang Y, Massie S, Zhao B, Omar A and <lb/>Wang Z 2018 Contrasting effects on deep convective clouds <lb/>by different types of aerosols Nat. Commun. 9 3874 <lb/>Kahn R A, Gaitley B J, Garay M J, Diner D J, Eck T F, Smirnov A and <lb/>Holben B N 2010 Multiangle imaging spectro radiometer <lb/>global aerosol product assessment by comparison with the <lb/>aerosol robotic network J. Geophys. Res. 115 D23209 <lb/>Kahn R A, Nelson D L, Garay M J, Levy R C, Bull M A, Diner D J, <lb/>Martonchik J V, Paradise S R, Hansen E G and Remer L A <lb/>2009 MISR aerosol product attributes and statistical <lb/>comparisons with MODIS IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sens. <lb/>47 4095-114 <lb/>Kogan Y L, Mechem D B and Choi K 2012 Effects of sea-salt aerosols <lb/>on precipitation in simulations of shallow cumulus J. Atmos. <lb/>Sci. 69 463-83 <lb/>Li J-L F, Lee W-L, Lee T, Fetzer E, Yu J-Y, Kubar T L and Boening C <lb/>2015 The impacts of cloud snow radiative effects on pacific <lb/>ocean surface heat fluxes, surface wind stress, and ocean <lb/>temperatures in coupled GCM simulations J. Geophys. Res. <lb/>Atmos. 120 2242-60 <lb/>Li J-L F, Lee W-L, Waliser D E, Neelin J D, Stachnik J P and Lee T <lb/>2014 Cloud-precipitation-radiation-dynamics interaction in <lb/>global climate models: a snow and radiation interaction <lb/>sensitivity experiment J. Geophys. Res. Atmos. 119 3809-24 <lb/>Li J-L F, Suhas E, Lee W-L, Richardson M, Wang Y-H, Yu J-Y, <lb/>Lee T, Fetzer E, Stephens G and Shen M-H 2018 The <lb/>impacts of bias in cloud-radiation-dynamics interactions <lb/>on central-Pacific El Niño simulations in contemporary <lb/>GCMs ESS 5 50-60 <lb/>Li J-L F, Wang Y-H, Lee T, Waliser D, Lee W-L, Yu J-Y, Chen Y-C, <lb/>Fetzer E and Hasson A 2016 The impacts of precipitating <lb/>cloud radiative effects on ocean surface evaporation, <lb/>precipitation, and ocean salinity in coupled GCM simulations <lb/>J. Geophys. Res. Atmos. 121 9474-91 <lb/>Lindvall J, Svensson G and Hannay C 2013 Evaluation of near-<lb/>surface parameters in the two versions of the atmospheric <lb/>model in CESM1 using flux station observations J. Clim. 26 <lb/>26-44 <lb/>Martensson E M, Nilsson E D, de Leeuw G, Cohen L H and <lb/>Hansson H C 2003 Laboratory simulations and <lb/>parameterization of the primary marine aerosol production <lb/>J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos. 108 4297 <lb/>Monahan E C, Spiel D E and Davidson K L 1986 A model of marine <lb/>aerosol generation via whitecaps and wave disruption Oceanic <lb/>Whitecaps and their Role in Air-Sea Exchange Processes ed <lb/>E C Monahan et al (Dordrecht: Springer) pp 167-74 The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>Morrison H and Gettelman A 2008 A new two-moment bulk <lb/>stratiform cloud microphysics scheme in the NCAR <lb/>Community Atmosphere Model (CAM3): I. Description and <lb/>numerical tests J. Clim. 21 3642-59 <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figure 8. A schematic depiction of the dynamical responses <lb/>resulting from missing falling ice radiative effects. Weaker <lb/>10 m wind speed, excessive rain, and too warm SST over <lb/>Pacific trade-wind regions due to missing falling ice radiative <lb/>effects would lead to underestimated sea salt aerosol, and this <lb/>in turn affects the shallow convection and aerosol direct <lb/>effects, and thus climate feedback. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Environ. Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Nakajima T, Higurahi A, Kawamoto K and Penner J E 2001 A <lb/>possible correlation between satellite-derived cloud and <lb/>aerosol microphysical parameters Geophys. Res. Lett. 28 <lb/>1171-4 <lb/>Ovadnevaite et al 2014 A sea spray aerosol flux parameterization <lb/>encapsulating wave state Atmos. Chem. Phys. 14 1837-52 <lb/>Pierce J R and Adams P J 2006 Global evaluation of CCN formation <lb/>by direct emission of sea salt and growth of ultrafine sea salt <lb/>J. Geophys. Res. 111 D06203 <lb/>Saleeby S M, Herbener S R, van den Heever S C and L&apos;Ecuyer T 2015 <lb/>Impacts of cloud droplet-nucleating aerosols on shallow <lb/>tropical convection J. Atmos. Sci. 72 1369-85 <lb/>Seinfeld J and Pandis S 2006 Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics: <lb/>from Air Pollution to Climate Change (New York: Wiley) <lb/>Seinfeld J H et al 2016 Improving our fundamental understanding of <lb/>the role of aerosol-cloud interactions in the climate system <lb/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 113 5781-90 <lb/>Taylor KE, Stouffer RJ and Meehl GA 2012 An overview of CMIP5 <lb/>and the experiment design Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc. 93 485-98 <lb/>Wei J, Li Z, Peng Y and Sun L 2019 MODIS collection 6.1 aerosol <lb/>optical depth products over land and ocean: validation and <lb/>comparison Atmos. Environ. 201 428-40 <lb/>Witek ML, Diner DJ and Garay MJ 2016 Satellite assessment of sea <lb/>spray aerosol productivity: southern ocean case study <lb/>J. Geophys. Res. Atmos. 121 872-94 <lb/>Witek ML, Diner DJ, Garay MJ, Xu F, Bull MA and Seidel FC 2018a <lb/>Improving MISR AOD retrievals with low-light-level <lb/>corrections for veiling light IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sens. <lb/>56 1251-68 <lb/>Witek ML, Garay MJ, Diner DJ, Bull MA and Seidel FC 2018b New <lb/>approach to the retrieval of AOD and its uncertainty from <lb/>MISR observations over dark water Atmos. Meas. Tech. 11 <lb/>429-39 <lb/>Woodcock AH 1953 Salt nuclei in marine air as a function of <lb/>altitude and wind force J. Meteorol. 10 362-71 <lb/>Xue H, Feingold G and Stevens B 2008 Aerosol effects on clouds, <lb/>precipitation, and the organization of shallow cumulus <lb/>convection J. Atmos. Sci. 65 392-406 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Res. Lett. 15 (2020) 034047 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
