<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Bilateral dens evaginatus and associated cystic pathology: An unusual case report</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Haeseong</forename>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Bach</forename>
            <surname>Le</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Parish</forename>
            <surname>Sedghizadeh</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-25T18:02:55.565848Z">25.10.2025 18:02:55</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1002$1$ccr3.8804</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Wiley</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1002/ccr3.8804</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Haeseong Lee, Bach Le, Parish Sedghizadeh. (2024). Bilateral dens evaginatus and associated cystic pathology: An unusual case report. Clinical Case Reports, 12(4), None. DOI: 10.1002/ccr3.8804</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-25T18:02:55.565848Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-25T18:02:55.565848Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>Granziera, Eleonora; Jalasjoki, Pirkka; Paloviita, Maritta <lb/>Working Paper <lb/>The bias of the ECB inflation projections: A State-<lb/>dependent analysis <lb/>Bank of Finland Research Discussion Papers, No. 4/2024 <lb/>Provided in Cooperation with: <lb/>Bank of Finland, Helsinki <lb/>Suggested Citation: Granziera, Eleonora; Jalasjoki, Pirkka; Paloviita, Maritta (2024) : The bias of the <lb/>ECB inflation projections: A State-dependent analysis, Bank of Finland Research Discussion Papers, <lb/>No. 4/2024, Bank of Finland, Helsinki, <lb/>https://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:fi-fe2024052234437 <lb/>This Version is available at: <lb/>https://hdl.handle.net/10419/295738 <lb/>Standard-Nutzungsbedingungen: <lb/>Die Dokumente auf EconStor dürfen zu eigenen wissenschaftlichen <lb/>Zwecken und zum Privatgebrauch gespeichert und kopiert werden. <lb/>Sie dürfen die Dokumente nicht für öffentliche oder kommerzielle <lb/>Zwecke vervielfältigen, öffentlich ausstellen, öffentlich zugänglich <lb/>machen, vertreiben oder anderweitig nutzen. <lb/>Sofern die Verfasser die Dokumente unter Open-Content-Lizenzen <lb/>(insbesondere CC-Lizenzen) zur Verfügung gestellt haben sollten, <lb/>gelten abweichend von diesen Nutzungsbedingungen die in der dort <lb/>genannten Lizenz gewährten Nutzungsrechte. <lb/>Terms of use: <lb/>Documents in EconStor may be saved and copied for your personal <lb/>and scholarly purposes. <lb/>You are not to copy documents for public or commercial purposes, to <lb/>exhibit the documents publicly, to make them publicly available on the <lb/>internet, or to distribute or otherwise use the documents in public. <lb/>If the documents have been made available under an Open Content <lb/>Licence (especially Creative Commons Licences), you may exercise <lb/>further usage rights as specified in the indicated licence. <lb/>Bank of Finland Research Discussion Papers <lb/>4 • 2024 <lb/>Eleonora Granziera -Pirkka Jalasjoki -<lb/>Maritta Paloviita <lb/>The bias of the ECB inflation projections: <lb/>a State-dependent analysis <lb/>Bank of Finland <lb/>Research <lb/>Bank of Finland Research Discussion Papers <lb/>Editor-in-Chief Esa Jokivuolle <lb/>Bank of Finland Research Discussion Papers 4/2024 <lb/>22 May 2024 <lb/>Eleonora Granziera -Pirkka Jalasjoki -Maritta Paloviita: <lb/>The bias of the ECB inflation projections: a State-dependent analysis <lb/>ISSN 1456-6184, online <lb/>Bank of Finland <lb/>Research Unit <lb/>PO Box 160 <lb/>FIN-00101 Helsinki <lb/>Phone: +358 9 1831 <lb/>Email: research@bof.fi <lb/>Website: www.suomenpankki.fi/en/research/research-unit/ <lb/>The opinions expressed in this paper are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views <lb/>of the Bank of Finland. <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>The Bias of the ECB Inflation Projections: <lb/>a State-Dependent Analysis * <lb/>Eleonora Granziera † <lb/>Pirkka Jalasjoki ‡ <lb/>Maritta Paloviita § <lb/>May 22,2024 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>We test for state-dependent bias in the European Central Bank&apos;s inflation projections. We <lb/>show that the ECB tends to underpredict when the observed inflation rate at the time of fore-<lb/>casting is higher than an estimated threshold of 1.8%. The bias is most pronounced at interme-<lb/>diate forecasting horizons. This suggests that inflation is projected to revert towards the target <lb/>too quickly. These results cannot be fully explained by the persistence embedded in the fore-<lb/>casting models nor by errors in the exogenous assumptions on interest rates, exchange rates <lb/>or oil prices. The state-dependent bias may be consistent with the aim of managing inflation <lb/>expectations, as published forecasts play a central role in the ECB&apos;s monetary policy commu-<lb/>nication strategy. <lb/>Keywords: Inflation Forecasts, Forecast Evaluation, ECB, Central Bank Communication <lb/>JEL classification: C12, C22, C53, E31, E52 <lb/>* The views expressed are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect those of Norges Bank, the Bank of <lb/>Finland or the Eurosystem. We thank Michael Ehrmann, Juha Kilponen, Jarmo Kontulainen, Barbara Rossi, Tate-<lb/>vik Sekhposyan, Annette Vissing-Jørgensen and seminar and conference participants at the 2022 EEA-ESEM, San <lb/>Francisco FED, De Nederlandsche Bank, Heidelberg Workshop on Survey Data and Probabilistic Expectations, 14th <lb/>International Conference on Computational and Financial Econometrics, 2nd Vienna Workshop on Economic Fore-<lb/>casting, 28th Annual Symposium of the Society for Nonlinear Dynamics and Econometrics, 3rd Forecasting at Central <lb/>Banks Conference, 17th Conference on Real-Time Data Analysis, Methods and Applications. We also thank an anony-<lb/>mous referee from the Norges Bank Working Paper series. We give special thanks to Florens Odendahl, Barbara Rossi <lb/>and Tatevik Sekhposyan for sharing their MATLAB codes. The earlier version of this paper was circulated as BOF <lb/>DP 7/2021 and NB WP 1/2021. <lb/> † Corresponding Author. Norges Bank; email: eleonora.granziera@norges-bank.no <lb/> ‡ Bank of Finland. Email: pirkka.jalasjoki@bof.fi <lb/> § Bank of Finland. Email: maritta.paloviita@bof.fi <lb/></front>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Forecasting is an essential part of monetary policy and published forecasts are at the core of <lb/>central bank communication. In fact, central bank inflation forecasts affect private sector expecta-<lb/>tions (see e.g. Coibion et al. (2022), Granziera et al. (2024), Lyziak and Paloviita (2018), Hubert <lb/>(2015a,b, 2017)) and therefore can serve as an additional policy tool. Published forecasts may be <lb/>used by central banks that implement make-up rules such as average inflation targeting in order <lb/>to create the expectation that inflation will over(under)shoot its target. In an environment of low <lb/>interest rates and low inflation, policies directly impacting agents&apos; inflation expectations can help <lb/>to stabilize economic conditions (Coibion et al., 2020). Managing inflation expectations is crucial <lb/>also in times of elevated inflation, when economic agents are more attentive to price developments <lb/>(Weber et al., 2023) and expectations may become unanchored. <lb/>However, published inflation projections have come under scrutiny. The accuracy of central <lb/>banks&apos; forecasts decreased during the Great Financial Crisis (Alessi et al. (2014)), and monetary <lb/>authorities overestimated the rate of inflation in the years that followed (Iversen et al. (2016), Kon-<lb/>togeorgos and Lambrias (2022)). Central banks made large forecasting errors during the COVID-<lb/>19 pandemic and the subsequent reopening (Goodhart and Pradhan (2023), Levy (2023)). Repeated <lb/>and systematic projection errors pose a challenge for central banks as they may increase the risk <lb/>of de-anchoring of inflation expectations and deteriorate the credibility of monetary authorities <lb/>(Mcmahon and Rholes, 2023). <lb/>Against this background, we analyze the bias in the Eurosystem/European Central Bank staff <lb/>(hereafter ECB) projections for HICP inflation. As a first novel contribution, we test for state <lb/>dependence in the bias. Specifically, we ask whether the ECB makes systematic forecast errors <lb/>depending on the level of inflation observed when making its projections. To answer this question, <lb/>we apply the newly developed state-dependent bias test by Odendahl et al. (2023). The test is <lb/>based on a regression model where the forecast errors are allowed to depend on both a linear (an <lb/>intercept, in our case) and a non-linear term. The latter is a function of some economic variables <lb/>and an unknown parameter. We consider the threshold regression model specification of the test, <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>where the bias depends on the level of inflation. Importantly, the test estimates the threshold level, <lb/>which is ex ante unknown. <lb/>On average, we find no sign of bias in the ECB&apos;s inflation projections, consistent with previous <lb/>studies. However, we document a significant difference in the properties of the forecasts condi-<lb/>tional on the level of inflation at the time of forecasting. In particular, we detect a systematic, <lb/>state-dependent bias, both statistically and economically significant for forecasts from one to four <lb/>quarters ahead: when inflation is higher than the estimated threshold, the ECB tends to underpre-<lb/>dict inflation. The estimated threshold value is 1.8% which is consistent with studies estimating <lb/>the de facto target of the ECB (Hartmann and Smets (2018), Rostagno et al. (2019), Paloviita et al. <lb/>(2021)). This suggests that there is a systematic bias towards the target, as the ECB projects infla-<lb/>tion to revert to the estimated threshold value too quickly. Importantly, these results are not driven <lb/>by large forecast errors observed in times of crisis, such as the Great Financial Crisis, the COVID <lb/>pandemic, or the post-pandemic recovery period, as we exclude large outliers from our analysis. <lb/>Thus, our finding implies that the bias is the result of systematic underprediction by the ECB even <lb/>in times when inflation does not substantially overshoot the target. <lb/>As a second contribution, we investigate possible determinants of the state-dependent bias we <lb/>documented. We consider two possible drivers: conditioning assumptions and forecasting mod-<lb/>els. The ECB projections are conditional forecasts, i.e., they are based on exogenous assumptions <lb/>regarding the path of future values of relevant macroeconomic and financial variables. One could <lb/>argue that systematic errors in inflation forecasts may reflect systematic errors in the exogenous <lb/>assumptions. Indeed, recent literature finds that the accuracy of the ECB projections is negatively <lb/>affected by the errors in the exogenous assumptions (Kontogeorgos and Lambrias, 2022). Using <lb/>the ECB&apos;s confidential data on the conditioning assumptions for the short term interest rate, the <lb/>Euro/US-Dollar exchange rate and oil prices, we test whether the errors in the exogenous assump-<lb/>tions can account for the state-dependent bias. We find that, while the inflation prediction errors <lb/>are correlated with errors in the exogenous assumptions, the inflation forecasts exhibit a significant <lb/>systematic bias even after controlling for errors in these assumptions. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Then, we turn to the forecasting models. We consider several reduced-form time series models <lb/>which are widely used to obtain forecasts for inflation, such as a random walk model, an AR <lb/>model, Autoregressive Distributed Lag (ADL) models and a small BVAR model (Stock and Watson <lb/>(2007), Granziera and Sekhposyan (2019)). We construct a real time dataset and produce inflation <lb/>forecasts for the same sample for which the ECB projections are available. We then apply the <lb/>Odendahl et al. (2023) bias test to these real time forecasts. For all the models we find evidence <lb/>of state-dependent bias, but of the opposite sign than the one observed for the ECB projections: <lb/>the forecasting models tend to overpredict when inflation is higher than the estimated threshold, <lb/>indicating that inflation is predicted to revert to its long term mean too slowly. This means that the <lb/>persistence embedded in the models is higher than the persistence in the ECB forecasts. Thus, the <lb/>forecasting models are not drivers of the state-dependent bias in the ECB projections. <lb/>Several papers rationalize the existence of bias in the published forecasts of central banks. <lb/>Capistran (2008) ascribes the bias to an asymmetric loss function, with overprediction occur-<lb/>ring when the monetary authority is more concerned about inflation above the target. However, <lb/>this explanation predicts a bias opposite in sign to what we find and does not generate a state-<lb/>dependent bias. Some recent studies have predictions in line with our findings. Herbert (2022) <lb/>shows that it is optimal for the monetary authority to systematically overpredict (underpredict) <lb/>aggregate conditions in recessions (expansions) in order to bias agents&apos; beliefs, if agents have het-<lb/>erogeneous priors about the state of the economy. Experimental evidence supports this prediction, <lb/>finding that test subject central bankers make announcements that deviate from the &quot;true&quot; forecasts <lb/>to manage agents&apos; inflation expectations (Duffy and Heinemann (2021), Ahrens et al. (2023)). <lb/>Gomez-Barrero and Parra-Polania (2014) prove the optimality of strategic forecasting in a theo-<lb/>retical model. Interestingly, they find that central banks have the strongest incentive to influence <lb/>inflation expectations at intermediate forecast horizons. While we do not identify the source of the <lb/>state-dependent bias, we note that it may be consistent with strategic behaviour of a central bank <lb/>aiming at steering expectations towards the target. <lb/>This paper contributes to the literature on forecast evaluation of policy institutions. A large <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>number of papers has analyzed the bias of the forecasts produced by the Federal Reserve: Clements <lb/>et al. (2007), Capistran (2008), Sinclair et al. (2010), Messina et al. (2015) and El-Shagi et al. <lb/>(2016) for Tealbook (earlier Greenbook) forecasts, and Romer and Romer (2008) and Arai (2016) <lb/>for the FOMC. Evidence regarding the bias of the Fed forecasts is mixed and depends on the sample <lb/>analyzed. Only a few papers investigate whether the properties of the forecasts are state-dependent, <lb/>and they define the states at the time when inflation is realized (Sinclair et al. (2010), Messina <lb/>et al. (2015)) rather than at the time of forecasting. Therefore, we relate the bias to the ECB&apos;s <lb/>mandate and its forecasting process. Moreover, this is the first paper that applies the methodology <lb/>by Odendahl et al. (2023) to testing for state-dependent bias with an unknown threshold value that <lb/>determines the switch between states. <lb/>We depart from these earlier studies also because we analyze the ECB projections, which <lb/>have received little attention so far. Several institutional differences distinguish the ECB from <lb/>the Federal Reserve. The ECB&apos;s mandate is defined in terms of price stability, while the Fed has a <lb/>dual mandate. The Fed has an explicit target of 2% for inflation, while, until July 2021, the ECB <lb/>aimed at keeping inflation below, but close to 2%. Finally, the Fed produces two sets of forecasts: <lb/>the Tealbook forecasts, which represent staff forecasts and are kept confidential for five years, and <lb/>the Summary of Economic Projections (SEP), which summarize the views of the FOMC members <lb/>and are published in real time. In contrast, the ECB projections are staff forecasts, similarly to the <lb/>Tealbook, but they are released to the public in the same quarter in which they are produced, like <lb/>the FOMC forecasts. These differences may affect the properties of the forecasts, and therefore <lb/>the findings documented for the Fed&apos;s forecasts may not hold in the ECB context. <lb/>A very recent set of papers analyzes the ECB inflation projections. Kontogeorgos and Lambrias <lb/>(2022), Goodhart and Pradhan (2023) and Argiri et al. (2024) attribute the bias in the ECB pro-<lb/>jections to periods of crises. We exclude the largest forecast errors in our sample, which coincide <lb/>with quarters during the Great Financial Crisis, the COVID pandemic, and the war in Ukraine, and <lb/>find that the underprediction during times of high inflation is statistically significant even outside <lb/>of these crisis periods. Glas and Heinisch (2023) and Kontogeorgos and Lambrias (2022) find a <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>strong association between inflation forecast errors and errors in the conditioning assumptions for <lb/>oil prices. We confirm the finding in those studies but show that the errors in external assumptions <lb/>cannot fully account for the state-dependent bias. <lb/>The rest of the paper is organized as follows: section 2 describes the testing framework, sec-<lb/>tion 3 presents the data and the implementation details, section 4 summarizes the baseline results <lb/>and the robustness checks, and section 5 explores the role of the external assumptions and the <lb/>forecasting models in explaining the bias. Section 6 concludes. <lb/>2 Testing for Bias <lb/>In this section, we describe our methodological approach. First, we outline how to test for <lb/>bias in a linear framework. Then, we present the novel forecast evaluation testing methodology <lb/>proposed by Odendahl et al. (2023) and we show how it can be applied to testing for bias in a <lb/>state-dependent setting. Finally, we describe the simplified approach to test for state-dependent <lb/>bias used in previous studies. <lb/>Linear Model. Denote as y t+h|t the prediction of the target variable y t+h made at time t for <lb/>the forecast horizon h and as L t+h|t the loss function. In our framework, the loss is simply the <lb/>difference between the realization of the target variable and its forecast, i.e., the forecast error: <lb/>L t+h|t = ε t+h|t = y t+h -y t+h|t . A positive (negative) forecast error indicates under(over)prediction. <lb/>In a linear framework, testing for bias is equivalent to testing whether the forecast errors have <lb/>zero mean (Holden and Peel (1990), Capistran (2008)) and to run the regression model: <lb/>ε t+h|t = µ h + u t+h|t <lb/>(1) <lb/>where µ h is the intercept and u t+h|t is an error term. The null of unbiasedness is µ h = 0. <lb/>Then, this test answers the question: are the ECB inflation forecasts for horizon h systemati-<lb/>cally biased? Or equivalently: on average, is the ECB systematically overpredicting (or underpre-<lb/>dicting) inflation? <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>State-Dependent Model with Unknown Threshold. We further investigate whether (and <lb/>how) the properties of the projection errors are related to economic conditions. Previous studies <lb/>have documented the presence of systematic bias related to the state of the economy both in the <lb/>projections of monetary authorities and in survey data (Goodhart and Pradhan (2023), Herbert <lb/>(2022), Messina et al. (2015), Sinclair et al. (2010)). If those systematic errors are opposite in sign <lb/>and offset each other, then we would fail to reject the null that the coefficient µ h in the regression <lb/>model (1) is statistically different from zero. Therefore, we would conclude that the forecast errors <lb/>are unbiased, because they are zero on average. <lb/>We test for state-dependent bias using the approach in Odendahl et al. (2023). They propose <lb/>a moment-based forecast evaluation test that has power against the alternative of state dependence <lb/>in the forecasting performance. The state dependence is modelled parametrically, as a threshold <lb/>model. Then, the forecast error loss is a non-linear function of an observable variable and an <lb/>unknown threshold value. In particular, it is assumed to evolve according to the following non-<lb/>linear model: <lb/>L t+h|t = X ′ <lb/>t µ h + X ′ <lb/>t θ h G (S t ; γ h ) + u t+h|t <lb/>(2) <lb/>where X t is a (k 1 × 1) vector of explanatory variables, S t is the observable variable that introduces <lb/>the state dependence, γ is an unknown parameter, G (•) is a nonlinear function and u t+h|t an error <lb/>term. Both the parameters µ h and θ h are of interest. Odendahl et al. (2023) propose several <lb/>functional forms for G (•). Given the research question of this paper, we assume G (S t ; γ h ) is a <lb/>threshold regression model: <lb/>G (S t ; γ h ) = 1 (S t ≥ γ h ) . <lb/>(3) <lb/>so that we allow the effect of X t on L t+h|t to differ according to whether S t is above or below <lb/>the unknown threshold γ h . It is straightforward to apply the model in equation (2), combined with <lb/>the functional form (3), to test for state-dependent bias. The unbiasedness test can be formulated <lb/>as follows: <lb/>ε t+h|t = µ h + θ h G (S t ; γ h ) + u t+h|t <lb/>(4) <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Given the functional form assumed for G (•), the state-dependent model can also be written as: <lb/>ε t+h|t = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>µ h + u t+h|t <lb/>if S t &lt; γ h <lb/>µ h + θ h + u t+h|t <lb/>if S t ≥ γ h <lb/>(5) <lb/>In our approach there are no additional explanatory variables X t , S t is the inflation rate observed <lb/>by the ECB when the projections are made, and γ h is the level of inflation that determines a switch <lb/>in the behavior of the forecast errors, which is allowed to differ across forecast horizons. Note that <lb/>we use S t rather than S t+h in equations (4). Therefore, we test whether the level of inflation known <lb/>when the forecasts were made, rather than realized, affects the characteristics of the forecasting <lb/>process. This approach distinguishes our analysis from most of previous studies. <lb/>Then, this test answers the question: are the ECB inflation forecasts for horizon h system-<lb/>atically biased conditional on inflation being above (below) the estimated threshold value? Or <lb/>equivalently: is the ECB systematically overpredicting or underpredicting inflation when inflation <lb/>is lower (higher) than the estimated threshold value? <lb/>State-Dependent Model with Known Threshold. The approach by Odendahl et al. (2023) <lb/>described above tests for potential state dependence without having to fix the threshold value that <lb/>determines the change in the state. In contrast, previous studies test for state-dependent bias by ex-<lb/>ogenously defining the state of the economy (Herbert (2022), Messina et al. (2015)). This amounts <lb/>to picking a value for the threshold parameter, say γ * , and constructing a dummy variable such <lb/>that: <lb/>d t = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>0 if S t &lt; γ * <lb/>1 <lb/>otherwise <lb/>Then, to test whether errors are systematic conditional on the state of the economy, it is sufficient <lb/>to include the dummy variable in equation (1): <lb/>ε t+h|t = µ h + θ h d t + u t+h|t . <lb/>(6) <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>The null of unbiasedness is µ h = θ h = 0. While using a known threshold value may be appropri-<lb/>ate in some applications, for example when testing for bias during recessions versus expansions, <lb/>allowing for an unknown threshold is paramount in our setting, where the value of inflation that <lb/>determines the change in the state cannot be set a priori. We will show the results from applying <lb/>the test with a known threshold in the robustness section. <lb/>3 Data <lb/>We analyze the ECB projections for the year-on-year rate of change of the euro area Harmo-<lb/>nized Index of Consumer Prices (HICP) at the quarterly frequency. We focus on this measure of <lb/>inflation because it is the one targeted by the ECB and used to define its price stability mandate. <lb/>Our data include real time estimates of current-quarter values (nowcasts) and real time projections <lb/>until eight quarters ahead. The sample runs from 1999Q1 to 2023Q4, resulting in 100 observations <lb/>for forecast evaluation of the nowcast and 92 of the eight step-ahead forecasts. 1 <lb/>The macroeconomic projections play a key role in monetary policy decision-making, as the <lb/>forecasts are presented to the ECB Governing Council ahead of its monetary policy deliberations. <lb/>They are produced by the ECB staff in March and September, and by both the ECB staff and experts <lb/>in national central banks in June and December. However, in each quarter, monthly inflation <lb/>projections are provided by national central bank experts for forecasting horizons up to 11 months, <lb/>through the Narrow Inflation Projection Exercise (NIPE). Finally, the projections are based on a <lb/>set of exogenous assumptions and are produced combining models as well as expert knowledge <lb/>and judgement. 2 <lb/>Panel A of Figure (1) shows the year-on-year euro area HICP inflation for the full sample. Our <lb/>sample period includes the relatively stable pre-crisis years, followed by the financial crisis, the <lb/>sovereign debt crisis and a period of persistently low inflation. The COVID-19 pandemic triggered <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 We evaluate the forecasts against the vintage published by Eurostat in January 2024. We do not experiment with <lb/>other vintages since both means and medians of data revisions of real-time observed inflation are close to zero. <lb/>2 Alessi et al. (2014) and Kontogeorgos and Lambrias (2022) provide further details on the ECB forecasting pro-<lb/>cess. <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>a further drop in inflation, while the recovery has been characterized by an unprecedented surge, <lb/>with inflation reaching a peak of almost 10%. The shaded areas in the figure mark the quarters in <lb/>which the inflation observed by the ECB, as defined below, lies above 1.8%, which turns out to be <lb/>the estimated value of the threshold parameter γ h for most forecasting horizons. This coincides with <lb/>the estimated value for the de facto ECB inflation target before the explicit target was announced <lb/>in the new ECB monetary policy strategy in July 2021 (Hartmann and Smets, 2018). With this <lb/>estimated threshold value, G (S t ; γ h ) takes the value of one in 58% of the observations. While the <lb/>latest portion of the sample sees the highest surge, inflation was above the estimated threshold also <lb/>shortly after the financial crisis and in the early 2000s. <lb/>Panel B of Figure (1) summarizes the projections for different forecast horizons over the whole <lb/>sample. For each forecast origin the figure shows selected quantiles of the projected path from <lb/>nowcasting up to two years ahead. We distinguish whether the inflation rate observed at the time <lb/>the forecasts are made is above or below 1.8%. The blue (red) line shows the median inflation <lb/>forecasts if the inflation observed by the ECB during the projection exercise is above (below) <lb/>1.8%. The red (blue) shaded areas denote the 10th and 25th (75th and 90th) percentiles of the <lb/>distribution conditional on inflation being below (above) 1.8%. <lb/>This figure highlights three properties of the forecasts. First, regardless of their initial level, <lb/>the forecasts revert towards 1.8% by the end of the projection horizon. Second, the convergence <lb/>happens rather quickly, within the first four quarters, and forecasts flatten out at longer horizons. <lb/>If the forecasts are reverting to the target quicker than actual inflation, i.e., the ECB is underesti-<lb/>mating the persistence of inflation, then we will observe positive (negative) forecast errors when <lb/>inflation during the projection exercise is high (low). Third, when inflation is high at the time of <lb/>forecasting, inflation projections fall below 1.8% from three quarters ahead onwards, suggestive of <lb/>undershooting. However, we do not see evidence of overshooting when inflation is low. If infla-<lb/>tion is eventually reverting to the target, then we will observe a larger bias, in absolute terms, for <lb/>projections made when inflation is high. <lb/>We investigate whether systematic errors are related to particular states, classified according to <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>the level of inflation observed by the ECB when the forecasts are made. In defining the observed <lb/>level of inflation at the time of forecasting, we carefully approximate the information set available <lb/>to the ECB during the projection exercise. Because of volatile economic conditions, such as sharp <lb/>changes in food and energy prices, it is reasonable to assume that the ECB observes price develop-<lb/>ments in recent months rather than only the latest available inflation figure. Therefore, consistent <lb/>with the cutoff dates of the forecasting process, we assume that the ECB takes into account both <lb/>the previous quarter year-on-year inflation rate π Q <lb/>t-1 and the year-on-year inflation of the first <lb/>month of the current quarter π M1 <lb/>t <lb/>. Then, the observed inflation measure S t is the simple average <lb/>of the two: S t = π Q <lb/>t-1 + π M1 <lb/>t <lb/>/2. <lb/>The ECB conditions its projections on a future path of a set of exogenous variables. We in-<lb/>clude in our analysis three exogenous variables which are considered the most important in driving <lb/>HICP inflation: the three-month EURIBOR rate, the Euro/US-Dollar exchange rate, and oil prices, <lb/>measured by the global price of Brent Crude in USD. 3 These assumptions are mainly based on <lb/>financial market expectations. With regard to the short-term interest rates, initially they were as-<lb/>sumed to stay constant at the level prevailing during the two weeks preceding the cut-off date. <lb/>Since June 2006, market expectations are derived from forward rates, reflecting the term struc-<lb/>ture of interest rates at the cut-off date. The technical assumptions for oil prices are based on the <lb/>path implied by futures markets, taking the average of the two-week period ending on the cut-off <lb/>date. For the bilateral exchange rate, the assumption is that it remains unchanged over the pro-<lb/>jection horizon at the average levels prevailing during the two-week period ending on the cut-off <lb/>date. While the technical assumptions for the exogenous variables are published together with the <lb/>macroeconomic projections for full calendar years, assumptions for fixed forecasting horizons of <lb/>each quarter remain confidential. <lb/>The latest four years in our sample have been ridden by extraordinary economic events. The <lb/>pandemic represented an unprecedented shock to the economy and generated an extremely high <lb/>level of uncertainty about future economic developments, such that the Fed did not publish the SEP <lb/></body>
	  
	        <note place="footnote">3 Technical assumptions regarding oil prices are available starting in 2001Q3. <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>projections in March 2020 while the ECB published two alternative scenarios, in addition to the <lb/>baseline scenario. The surge in commodity prices that followed the reopening of the economy and <lb/>the war in Ukraine brought inflation to levels unseen since the late 1980s. These shocks resulted <lb/>in particularly large forecast errors, which may drive results. For this reason, we exclude outliers <lb/>from our analysis. In particular, we disregard forecast errors larger than 1% for the one and two <lb/>quarters ahead horizons, 1.5% for the three to five and 1.75% for the six to eight. 4 <lb/>4 Results <lb/>First, we report the results for the linear model in (1). We then comment on the results for the <lb/>state-dependent model (4). Finally, we present some robustness checks. <lb/>4.1 Bias in the ECB Projections <lb/>We replicate the exercise done in previous studies by showing the results for the linear regres-<lb/>sion model in (1). Panel A of Table (1) shows the estimated coefficients for each forecast horizon <lb/>from nowcasting until five quarters ahead, h = 0, .., 5, and for the pooled horizons 0 through 5, and <lb/>0 through 8, as well as the heteroskedasticity and autocorrelation corrected standard errors. Except <lb/>for the nowcasting horizon, the constant is positive and largest for horizons 3 through 5. A positive <lb/>coefficient implies that on average the outcome is larger than the forecasts, i.e., there is a tendency <lb/>to underpredict. However, given that the coefficient associated with the constant is not statistically <lb/>significantly different from zero at any forecast horizon, we find no systematic bias in the ECB <lb/>inflation projections. Therefore, overall our regressions indicate that the ECB inflation projections <lb/>for all forecast horizons are unbiased on average. These findings for the single horizon forecasts <lb/>confirm the results in Kontogeorgos and Lambrias (2022) who conclude that ECB inflation projec-<lb/>tions are optimal and rational using a sample ending in 2018Q4 and analyzing one, four and eight <lb/>steps ahead projections. Note that, when pooling forecasting horizons, we find some statistically <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">4 Using this criterion, we also exclude from the analysis two vintages of forecasts made during the Great Financial <lb/>Crisis. <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>significant, positive bias, and therefore evidence of overall underprediction. Pooling allows us to <lb/>increase the number of observations and therefore improve on statistical significance. <lb/>Panel B of Table (1) shows the results for the state-dependent bias regression model in equation <lb/>(4). The coefficient associated with the intercept term is negative for all horizons but the nowcast, <lb/>albeit not statistically significant. The coefficient for the non-linear term instead is positive for all <lb/>horizons except for the nowcast and is significant for h = 1 up to h = 4 and for the pooled horizons <lb/>h = 0 -5 and h = 0 -8. When inflation is below the estimated threshold, the bias is given by the <lb/>intercept term and is therefore negative. Instead, when inflation is above the estimated threshold <lb/>level, the fitted values from the regression are positive, as the sum of µ h and θ h is positive. Given <lb/>that the forecast errors are defined as the difference between the realization and the forecast, a <lb/>positive (negative) bias indicates that the forecast is lower (higher) than the realized value. This <lb/>means that when inflation is above (below) the threshold, the ECB tends to underpredict (overpre-<lb/>dict) inflation. Interestingly, the size of this bias when inflation is high, measured as the sum of the <lb/>coefficients µ h and θ h , increases with the forecast horizon up to h = 4, and it declines until h = 8. <lb/>The bias is not only statistically but also economically significant: when inflation is above the <lb/>threshold, it ranges from 0.10p.p. for one quarter ahead to 0.37p.p. for four quarters ahead. Note <lb/>that the bias is asymmetric in its magnitude: it is larger in absolute value when inflation is above <lb/>the threshold than when below (e.g., fourfold for h = 3). Because we exclude from the sample <lb/>the large forecast errors made during the Great Financial Crisis and the post-COVID period, our <lb/>results speak of the properties of the projections during &quot;normal&quot; times, when inflation does not <lb/>deviate substantially from the target. In this respect, the magnitude of the bias is quite substantial. <lb/>Interestingly, we find no evidence of bias for the nowcasting horizon. This may be due to the fact <lb/>that current quarter inflation is easier to forecast. Also, at this horizon forecasting accuracy may <lb/>be more important than other objectives, like managing expectations, for the credibility and repu-<lb/>tation of the central bank, as the public may be more aware of errors made for the current level of <lb/>inflation than for longer horizons. <lb/>Note that the estimated threshold parameter is 1.8% for all the forecasting horizons except for <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>the nowcast. This number is consistent with the value of the de facto target estimated for the ECB. <lb/>Until the new monetary policy mandate was announced in July 2021, the ECB&apos;s price stability <lb/>definition was ambiguous with respect to the level of the target. In 2003 the ECB&apos;s Governing <lb/>Council stated that: &apos;in the pursuit of price stability it aims to maintain inflation rates below, but <lb/>close to, 2% over the medium term&apos;. Hartmann and Smets (2018) estimate the reaction functions <lb/>of the ECB&apos;s Governing Council and conclude that the ECB&apos;s inflation aim is 1.8%. This number <lb/>is in line with estimates by Paloviita et al. (2021) and Rostagno et al. (2019) which are based on <lb/>alternative approaches. As stressed in section (2), we do not impose the value of the indicator <lb/>variable that determines the switch in the state, so it is quite remarkable that the estimates for γ h <lb/>are equal to the de facto target. Also, note that we allow for γ h to change with the forecast horizon, <lb/>so it is interesting that the estimated threshold is virtually the same for all h. Overall, we document <lb/>that the forecasts are biased towards the target at short and intermediate forecast horizons, between <lb/>one and four quarters ahead, and for pooled forecast horizons h = 0-5 and h = 0-8. In section (5) <lb/>we will explore some possible explanations for the bias and we will discuss our results in relation <lb/>to the literature. <lb/>4.2 Robustness <lb/>We perform several exercises to check the robustness of our results. <lb/>First, we repeat our analysis using alternative assumptions regarding the information set avail-<lb/>able to the ECB at the time of forecasting. Table (4) reports the estimated coefficients from these <lb/>regressions. Results are qualitatively and quantitatively unchanged if we assume the inflation rate <lb/>observed by the ECB at the time of forecasting is either the nowcast published by the ECB, or <lb/>realized inflation for the target quarter, or the simple average of the year-on-year inflation on the <lb/>first month of the quarter when the forecasts are made and the previous two months. In all these <lb/>cases, and for all forecast horizons, the estimated threshold is around 1.8%, the estimated coef-<lb/>ficient for the intercept is negative while the estimated coefficient associated with the non-linear <lb/>term is positive, significant and similar in magnitude to our baseline estimation. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Second, we check the robustness of our results for different values of the threshold that deter-<lb/>mines the change between states. For this exercise, we fix the threshold level to either π * = 1.7, <lb/>π * = 1.75, π * = 1.85 or π * = 1.9 and define the dummy variable d t to equal one if observed infla-<lb/>tion is higher than the threshold. Then, we run the regression model (6). Results are unchanged if <lb/>we assume a lower target (π * = 1.7 or π * = 1.75 ), see Table (5). Interestingly, both coefficients <lb/>turn positive if we assume a higher target, (π * = 1.85 or π * = 1.9), although they lose their sig-<lb/>nificance, suggesting overall underprediction. This robustness exercise highlights that it is crucial <lb/>to estimate the threshold that determines the state-dependent bias, as a predetermined value can <lb/>greatly affect the results. <lb/>Finally, we replicate the approach in previous papers and condition the state on the value of <lb/>inflation observed when inflation is realized, i.e., we define the state based on S t+h rather than <lb/>on S t . Table (6) shows that, for this exercise, the bias is qualitatively the same as in our baseline <lb/>results, but quantitatively much stronger. In particular, when inflation is above the threshold, it <lb/>ranges from 0.14p.p. for one quarter ahead to 0.75p.p. for four quarters ahead. <lb/>5 Potential Drivers of Bias <lb/>In this section we analyze several potential drivers of state-dependent bias and discuss our <lb/>results with respect to the existing literature. The ECB projections are the result of the combina-<lb/>tion of three main ingredients: (i) the conditioning assumptions on the future path of exogenous <lb/>variables, (ii) a set of forecasting models, and (iii) expert judgement. We will analyze the role <lb/>of the first two ingredients in explaining the bias documented above and provide some alternative <lb/>explanations related to the loss function of the central bank and its strategic behavior. <lb/>5.1 The Role of External Assumptions <lb/>The ECB projections are conditional on a number of external assumptions, i.e., technical as-<lb/>sumptions regarding the future developments of the international economic environment. One <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>could argue that systematic errors found in the inflation projections may be driven by systematic <lb/>errors in external assumptions. In fact, Kontogeorgos and Lambrias (2022) find that errors in the <lb/>external assumptions decrease the accuracy of the ECB inflation projections. Glas and Heinisch <lb/>(2023) show that higher forecast errors in oil prices are associated with higher forecast errors for <lb/>inflation. Those studies are based on linear models. Still, the results may hold in our non-linear <lb/>framework and lead to a state-dependent bias. Given our access to the ECB assumptions for the <lb/>conditioning variables, we are in a unique position to test this conjecture. <lb/>We focus on three variables which are considered to be among the main drivers of inflation: the <lb/>short term interest rate (3M EURIBOR), Euro/US-Dollar exchange rate (EURUSD), 5 and Brent <lb/>Crude oil prices. The assumptions made by the ECB for the oil prices and interest rates are ob-<lb/>tained from futures prices while the exchange rate is assumed to be constant through the forecast <lb/>horizon, consistent with the prediction from a random walk model. Importantly, these conditioning <lb/>assumptions are completely exogenous, i.e., not affected by the ECB projections published in the <lb/>same quarter. <lb/>In order to assess the role of the conditioning assumptions in inflation projections, we include <lb/>the forecast errors in external assumptions as additional predictors in the bias regression models <lb/>(6), where we fix the threshold values to the ones estimated in model (4) and reported in Table (1). <lb/>Define the error in the external assumption i at time t for horizon h as: <lb/>ζ i <lb/>t+h|t = x i <lb/>t+h -x i <lb/>t+h|t <lb/>i = 1, .., 3; h = 0, ..8 <lb/>(7) <lb/>where x i <lb/>t+h is the realization and x i <lb/>t+h|t is the value assumed at t for date t + h. The variable <lb/>x i <lb/>t+h is the level of interest rate or exchange rate, or the growth rate of oil prices. <lb/>Then, we apply the bias test with a known threshold, 6 including the error ζ i <lb/>t,h as an additional <lb/>predictor: <lb/>ε t+h|t = β i <lb/>0,h + β i <lb/>1,h ζ i <lb/>t+h|t + β i <lb/>2,h d t + u i <lb/>t+h|t <lb/>i = 1, .., 3; h = 0, ..8 <lb/>(8) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">5 The exchange rate is defined as the amount dollars traded for one euro, so that when the exchange rate increases, <lb/>the euro appreciates. <lb/>6 We condition the threshold parameter γ h to the value estimated in Table (1). <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>where, ε t+h|t is the forecast error for predicting inflation at the forecast origin t for horizon h. <lb/>If the estimated parameters β i <lb/>0,h and β i <lb/>2,h were not significant in (8), while β i <lb/>1,h were significant, <lb/>the bias in the inflation forecasts could be attributed to the bias in the external assumptions. We <lb/>investigate the role of each technical assumption separately, as the relatively small number of <lb/>observations does not allow us to increase further the number of predictors. <lb/>Ideally, to carry out our investigation, we would first construct a counterfactual series of ad-<lb/>justed forecasts for inflation by using internal ECB models conditioned on the true realization of <lb/>the external variables, and then check whether the errors in the adjusted projections are biased. <lb/>However, we are unable to construct such counterfactual series based on the forecasting models <lb/>used in real time by the ECB and the national central banks or to include expert judgement. We <lb/>think that our simple approach is sensible because if systematic errors in the external assumptions <lb/>were driving the forecast errors, then the dummy should not have additional explanatory power. <lb/>Also, a similar specification has been used by Glas and Heinisch (2023), applied to forecast revi-<lb/>sions. <lb/>Results for regressions (8) are reported in Panel A through C of Table (2). Adding the forecast <lb/>errors to the bias regression does not alter the sign, the magnitude nor the significance of the <lb/>coefficients observed in Panel B of Table (1). The interest rate forecast errors are significant only <lb/>for the pooled horizon regressions and enter positively, so that a larger forecast error for interest <lb/>rates predicts a larger forecast error for inflation. In other words, underprediction of the short term <lb/>rate coincides with underprediction of inflation. Similarly, the forecast errors for the exchange <lb/>rate are not significant. The estimated coefficient is negative at short horizons and positive at <lb/>longer horizons. A negative coefficient means that if the euro appreciates more than expected, <lb/>inflation is lower than predicted. Finally, the oil price forecast errors are highly significant at <lb/>short term horizons and exhibit a positive coefficient, implying that a higher forecast error for oil <lb/>prices translates into a higher forecast error for inflation. As suggested by economic intuition, <lb/>underprediction of oil prices results in underprediction of inflation. This result is consistent with <lb/>previous findings in Kontogeorgos and Lambrias (2022) and Glas and Heinisch (2023). While <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>oil prices seem to be the most relevant exogenous assumption in explaining the inflation forecast <lb/>errors, as suggested by the higher adjusted R-squared for the regressions in Table (2), they do not <lb/>fully account for the state-dependent bias documented in Table (1). <lb/>In sum, we find evidence of systematic over(under)prediction for short and intermediate term <lb/>projections when inflation is lower (higher) than the estimated threshold even when controlling for <lb/>the errors in external assumptions. <lb/>5.2 The Role of Forecasting Models <lb/>Another potential source of bias is given by the forecasting models used to obtain the forecasts. <lb/>If there is little persistence embedded in the models, then inflation may be projected to return to <lb/>target too quickly and this could explain the underprediction we documented when inflation is high <lb/>and the overprediction when inflation is low. We test this hypothesis in this section. <lb/>The ECB staff and experts in national central banks make use of several forecasting models to <lb/>produce their forecasts. While we do not know all the details of the reduced form time series mod-<lb/>els in use, we know their general structure (Ciccarelli et al., 2024). We consider simple univariate <lb/>models, such as the random walk, an Autoregressive (AR) model, and the ADL as they have been <lb/>shown to be very accurate models for predicting inflation (Stock and Watson (2007), Granziera and <lb/>Sekhposyan (2019)). We include a small BVAR in our analysis because it is widely used in central <lb/>banks for forecasting macro variables, as it jointly models the evolution of the output, inflation <lb/>and interest rates. Finally, we want to study the property of the bias in the case where the central <lb/>bank predicts inflation will be at the target value for all forecasting horizons. The random walk <lb/>model assumes that inflation will remain at the realized value observed in the latest quarter. For <lb/>example, when producing the forecasts in 2023Q1 it projects inflation to stay at the value observed <lb/>in 2022Q4. In the baseline specification, the lag length of the AR model is fixed to one. The ADL <lb/>model includes one lag of inflation and two lags of each exogenous assumption. The BVAR model <lb/>includes the year-on-year growth rate of output, the EURIBOR rate and HICP inflation. We run <lb/>an out-of-sample exercise with real time data, making sure to use only information available at the <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>time when the ECB produced its forecasts. The models are estimated on data starting in 1970Q1 <lb/>and forecasts are obtained with the expanding window approach starting in 1999Q1. <lb/>After we obtain the forecasts, we test for state-dependent bias with a known threshold, using the <lb/>regression model (6), and conditioning the value of the threshold parameter γ h to the one estimated <lb/>for the ECB inflation projections shown in Table (1). 7 The results of this analysis are reported in <lb/>Table (3). For the random walk, the AR and the ADL model the coefficient associated with the <lb/>intercept term is positive but not statistically significant. The coefficient associated with the non-<lb/>linear term is instead highly significant and negative and the sum of µ h and θ h is negative. Although <lb/>there is evidence of bias, these results are opposite in sign to the ones obtained when analyzing <lb/>the forecast errors from the ECB projections, as they point to overprediction when inflation is <lb/>low and underprediction when inflation is low. This suggests that the persistence embedded in <lb/>the forecasting models is quite high and is not consistent with the forecasts reverting quickly to <lb/>1.8%. 8 For the BVAR model the estimated coefficients are generally positive, which indicates <lb/>overprediction, and the overprediction is stronger when inflation is above the threshold. Once <lb/>again, this bias is inconsistent with the one documented in Table (1). Instead, the forecasting <lb/>strategy of assuming a constant inflation rate equal to the de facto target generates a bias similar in <lb/>magnitude and sign to the one documented for the ECB projections. One difference is that in the <lb/>1.8% forecast model the bias is highest for nowcasting and decreases with the forecast horizon, <lb/>while in the ECB projections it is highest at four quarters ahead. <lb/>Our findings suggest that the forecasting models typically used to forecast inflation cannot <lb/>generate the bias found in the ECB projections. <lb/>5.3 Alternative Explanations <lb/>So far, we provided evidence of ECB underprediction when inflation is high and overpredic-<lb/>tion when inflation is low. In the previous two subsections we ruled out two possible explanations <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">7 In Table (7) we report results for state-dependent bias test with an unknown threshold, using the regression model <lb/>(4). The qualitative results for this alternative exercise are very similar to the baseline results. <lb/>8 Different lag lengths did not change the results in Table (3). <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>for this systematic bias: errors in the conditioning assumptions and the persistence embedded <lb/>in economic models. What else can generate bias in inflation forecasts of a central bank? The <lb/>literature has suggested several explanations. Capistran (2008) shows that if a central bank con-<lb/>siders inflation above the target more (less) costly than inflation below the target, then it should <lb/>systematically over(under)predict inflation. Intuitively, the central bank forecasts an inflation rate <lb/>higher than the forecast from a symmetric loss function in order to justify a tighter monetary policy <lb/>stance. This explanation is difficult to reconcile with our findings for two reasons: first, because <lb/>it predicts a bias opposite in sign to what we find, and second, it does not allow for the bias to <lb/>be state-dependent. Other papers attribute the bias in published forecasts to strategic forecasting. <lb/>Romer and Romer (2008) find that Greenbook forecasts are of higher quality than FOMC pro-<lb/>jections. The difference in accuracy can be explained by distinct objectives of these two sets of <lb/>forecasts or by different loss functions of the FOMC members and the Fed&apos;s staff (Ellison and <lb/>Sargent, 2012). The Greenbook forecasts are confidential staff forecasts which aim at being as <lb/>accurate as possible, while the FOMC forecasts, which are publicly available in real time, are used <lb/>for communication purposes. The ECB produces only one set of forecasts, which serve as inputs <lb/>for the Governing Council decisions and are released immediately. Therefore, if there is a strategic <lb/>component in published inflation projections, there may be tension between accuracy of forecasts <lb/>and management of expectations, resulting in a systematic bias. <lb/>Strategic communication motives are put forward as an explanation for bias also by Gomez-<lb/>Barrero and Parra-Polania (2014), which argue that a central bank may use its published inflation <lb/>projections to steer inflation expectations of private agents. In their stylized model the incentive <lb/>to manage expectations is higher at intermediate horizons, because in the medium term the central <lb/>bank has both relevant private information about future shocks hitting the economy and the possi-<lb/>bility to affect future inflation through its influence on private agents&apos; expectations. In a laboratory <lb/>experiment, Duffy and Heinemann (2021) find that their test subject central bankers act strategi-<lb/>cally and make announcements that deviate from the &quot;true&quot; forecasts in order to manage agents&apos; <lb/>inflation expectations. Similarly, in a laboratory experiment, Ahrens et al. (2023) document that <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>strategic inflation projections stabilize the economy by bringing inflation faster towards the infla-<lb/>tion target. Herbert (2022) shows that it is optimal for the monetary authority to systematically <lb/>overpredict (underpredict) aggregate conditions in recessions (expansions) in order to bias agents&apos; <lb/>beliefs, if agents have heterogeneous priors about the state of the economy. <lb/>While we do not identify the specific reasons for the systematic, state-dependent bias in the <lb/>ECB projections at intermediate horizons, we believe it may be consistent with the inflation expec-<lb/>tations management motives outlined in the studies mentioned above. <lb/>6 Conclusion <lb/>Using a novel testing approach, we document a systematic bias in the ECB inflation projections. <lb/>The ECB systematically underpredicts inflation when inflation is high, which results in projections <lb/>converging to the target too quickly. These findings are not driven by the large forecast errors <lb/>made during the Great Financial Crisis or the pandemic period. Our result suggests that looking at <lb/>state dependence is crucial, as previous studies which do not account for state dependence find no <lb/>evidence of bias. We further show that the bias cannot be explained by the errors in the conditioning <lb/>assumptions of short term interest rates, exchange rates or oil prices, contrary to the view that <lb/>forecast errors for inflation arise because of errors in these conditioning assumptions. Moreover, <lb/>forecasting models show a stronger inertia than what is implied in the ECB forecasts. Although <lb/>the reasons behind our findings are beyond the scope of this paper, we conjecture that the evidence <lb/>of state-dependent bias may be related to strategic motives in monetary policy communication. <lb/>Our investigation of the properties of the published projections is relevant also from a policy <lb/>perspective: the projections form the basis for the monetary policy decisions of the ECB Governing <lb/>Council and represent an important communication tool. Systematic bias in the projections may <lb/>undermine the credibility of the central bank. Because the credibility of a monetary authority may <lb/>be related to the forecast accuracy of its forecasts, further analysis about the determinants of the <lb/>bias is needed. <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1: HICP Inflation and Inflation Projections <lb/>2000 <lb/>2005 <lb/>2010 <lb/>2015 <lb/>2020 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>t <lb/>(a) Panel A: HICP Inflation and Distribution of States over Time <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>1 1 <lb/>forecasting horizon <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>forecasts <lb/>(b) Panel B: ECB Projections for HICP Inflation <lb/>Panel A. Year-on-year HICP inflation for the Euro Area (solid line) and periods in which inflation is above the <lb/>threshold, i.e. 1.8% (shaded areas). Panel B. The figure shows for each forecasting horizon the maximum and <lb/>minimum inflation projections, the 10 th and 25 th (75 th and 90 th ) percentiles and the medians conditional on <lb/>whether inflation was above or below the threshold (1.8%, green dashed line) during each projection exercise <lb/>from 1999Q1 till 2023Q4. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1: Bias in ECB Inflation Forecasts <lb/>Forecast Horizon <lb/>Single <lb/>Pooled <lb/>h = <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 -5 <lb/>0 -8 <lb/>Panel A: Linear Model <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.01 0.04 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.10** 0.10** <lb/>(0.01) (0.04) (0.07) (0.13) (0.14) (0.15) (0.05) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>Panel B: State-Dependent Model <lb/>µ h <lb/>0.00 -0.03 -0.07 -0.07 -0.09 -0.05 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>(0.04) (0.05) (0.09) (0.13) (0.17) (0.16) (0.05) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>θ h <lb/>-0.05 0.13* 0.28** 0.36* 0.46* 0.43 0.24*** 0.19*** <lb/>(0.04) (0.08) (0.14) (0.20) (0.26) (0.28) (0.08) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.27 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.81 <lb/>1.81 <lb/>1.81 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Note: Estimated coefficients from regressions (1) and (4) over the sample 1999Q1-2023Q4. <lb/>R 2 is the adjusted R 2 . Newey-West standard errors are in parenthesis. Stars denote the 10% <lb/>(*), 5% (**) and 1% (***) significance level. <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2: Bias in ECB Inflation Forecasts: Exogenous Assumptions <lb/>Forecast Horizon <lb/>Single <lb/>Pooled <lb/>h = <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 -5 <lb/>0 -8 <lb/>Panel A: Interest Rates <lb/>β i <lb/>0,h <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>-0.08 -0.04 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.14) (0.19) (0.20) (0.06) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>β i <lb/>1,h <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.15 0.17*** 0.18*** <lb/>(0.27) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.17) (0.15) (0.14) (0.08) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>β i <lb/>2,h <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.13* <lb/>0.28** 0.37* 0.48* <lb/>0.44 0.29*** 0.29*** <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.13) <lb/>(0.19) (0.25) (0.27) (0.09) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>Panel B: Exchange Rate <lb/>β i <lb/>0,h <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-0.08 -0.03 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.15) (0.19) (0.20) (0.06) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>β i <lb/>1,h <lb/>-0.74 <lb/>-0.78 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.58 <lb/>1.36 <lb/>0.69 <lb/>1.68*** <lb/>(1.29) <lb/>(0.72) <lb/>(0.83) <lb/>(1.03) (1.15) (1.16) (0.49) <lb/>(0.41) <lb/>β i <lb/>2,h <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.12* <lb/>0.25* <lb/>0.35* <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.31 0.24*** 0.17** <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.14) <lb/>(0.20) (0.26) (0.28) (0.08) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>Panel C: Oil Prices <lb/>β i <lb/>0,h <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>-0.20 -0.16 -0.09* <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>(0.02) <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>(0.14) (0.19) (0.20) (0.05) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>β i <lb/>1,h 0.01*** 0.01*** 0.01*** 0.01* <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 0.01*** 0.01*** <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>(0.01) (0.01) (0.01) (0.00) <lb/>(0.00) <lb/>β i <lb/>2,h <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.25** 0.37** 0.49** 0.49 0.28*** 0.28*** <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.12) <lb/>(0.19) (0.25) (0.27) (0.08) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>Note: Estimated coefficients from regression (4) over the sample 1999Q4-2023Q4. R 2 is the adjusted <lb/>R 2 . Newey-West standard errors are in parenthesis. Stars denote the 10% (*), 5% (**) and 1% (***) <lb/>significance level. For regressions involving the short term interest rates, note that before 2006 an <lb/>assumption of constant short term interest rates was used. External assumptions for oil prices are <lb/>available from 2001Q3. <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3: Bias in Forecasting Models <lb/>Forecast Horizon <lb/>Single <lb/>Pooled <lb/>h = <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 -5 <lb/>0 -8 <lb/>Panel A: Random Walk <lb/>µ h <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.17** <lb/>(0.15) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>(0.13) <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.20) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>θ h <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>-0.20 <lb/>-0.25 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>-0.55* <lb/>-0.18* -0.27*** <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.12) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>Panel B: AR <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.13* <lb/>(0.03) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>(0.13) <lb/>(0.20) <lb/>(0.20) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>-0.46* -0.45** -0.17* -0.30*** <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.14) <lb/>(0.17) <lb/>(0.27) <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>(0.24) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Panel B: AR with exogenous assumptions <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>(0.03) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>(0.13) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.17) <lb/>(0.17) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>-0.21 <lb/>-0.24 <lb/>-0.47** -0.42* -0.23*** -0.35*** <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.13) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.23) <lb/>(0.22) <lb/>(0.22) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>Panel C: Small BVAR <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.15* <lb/>(0.03) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.12) <lb/>(0.17) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.21) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.22** <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.26* <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.18** <lb/>0.02 <lb/>(0.04) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.15) <lb/>(0.22) <lb/>(0.23) <lb/>(0.26) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>Panel D: 1.8% Forecast <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.96*** -0.25*** -0.23** -0.31* <lb/>-0.18 <lb/>-0.07 -0.39*** -0.30*** <lb/>(0.36) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.13) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>θ h <lb/>2.15*** 0.56*** 0.53*** 0.60*** 0.39* <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.84*** 0.60*** <lb/>(0.48) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.14) <lb/>(0.20) <lb/>(0.23) <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>(0.17) <lb/>(0.14) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>Note: Estimated coefficients from regression (6) with value of the threshold as in Table (1). The forecasts <lb/>are obtained from the forecasting models described in section 5.2 over the sample 1999Q1-2023Q4. R 2 is <lb/>the adjusted R 2 . Newey-West standard errors are in parenthesis. Stars denote the 10% (*), 5% (**) and 1% <lb/>(***) significance level. <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4: Bias: Alternative Information Set <lb/>Forecast Horizon <lb/>Single <lb/>Pooled <lb/>h = <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 -5 <lb/>0 -8 <lb/>Panel A: Nowcast <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.01 -0.02 -0.07 <lb/>-0.09 -0.09 -0.11 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>(0.07) (0.05) (0.10) (0.14) (0.17) (0.17) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.10 0.28** 0.39** 0.46* 0.53** 0.28*** 0.24*** <lb/>(0.07) (0.07) (0.13) (0.18) (0.24) (0.28) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.50 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>Panel B: Realized Inflation <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.02 -0.03 -0.06 <lb/>-0.07 -0.07 -0.05 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>(0.06) (0.05) (0.09) (0.14) (0.17) (0.16) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.07 0.13* 0.29** 0.39** 0.46* 0.45* 0.27*** 0.20*** <lb/>(0.05) (0.08) (0.13) (0.18) (0.24) (0.25) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.33 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>1.92 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Panel C: Average of latest three months <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.01 -0.03 -0.07 <lb/>-0.07 -0.09 -0.05 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>(0.06) (0.05) (0.09) (0.13) (0.17) (0.17) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.03 0.13* 0.28** 0.36* 0.46* <lb/>0.43 0.26*** 0.21*** <lb/>(0.05) (0.07) (0.13) (0.19) (0.25) (0.29) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.30 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Coefficients&apos; estimates from regression model ((4)) when observed inflation π I is assumed to be: the nowcast <lb/>value (panel A), realized inflation (panel B) or the average of the current and last two months (panel C). <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 5: Bias: Alternative Values for Threshold <lb/>Forecast Horizon <lb/>Single <lb/>Pooled <lb/>h = <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 -5 <lb/>0 -8 <lb/>Panel A: π * = 1.7 <lb/>µ h <lb/>0.00 -0.03 -0.06 -0.06 -0.09 -0.09 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>(0.03) (0.05) (0.10) (0.14) (0.19) (0.22) (0.06) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>θ h <lb/>-0.00 0.13* 0.27** 0.34* 0.45* 0.48* 0.27*** 0.23*** <lb/>(0.04) (0.07) (0.13) (0.19) (0.25) (0.27) (0.08) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Panel C: π * = 1.75 <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.00 -0.03 -0.07 -0.07 -0.09 -0.07 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>(0.03) (0.05) (0.10) (0.14) (0.18) (0.20) (0.06) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.00 0.13* 0.28** 0.36* 0.46* 0.46* 0.27*** 0.22*** <lb/>(0.04) (0.07) (0.13) (0.19) (0.25) (0.27) (0.08) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Panel D: π * = 1.85 <lb/>µ h <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>(0.03) (0.05) (0.09) (0.14) (0.18) (0.19) (0.06) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>θ h <lb/>-0.01 0.07 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>(0.04) (0.07) (0.13) (0.20) (0.26) (0.28) (0.09) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>Panel B: π * = 1.9 <lb/>µ h <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>(0.03) (0.05) (0.09) (0.14) (0.18) (0.19) (0.06) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>θ h <lb/>-0.01 0.04 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>(0.04) (0.07) (0.14) (0.20) (0.26) (0.28) (0.09) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Coefficient estimates from regression (6) where the threshold used to define the dummy is <lb/>either 1.7 (panel A) or 1.9 (panel B). <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 6: Bias in ECB Inflation Forecasts <lb/>Forecast Horizon <lb/>Single <lb/>Pooled <lb/>h = <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 -5 <lb/>0 -8 <lb/>Panel B: State-Dependent Model <lb/>µ h <lb/>0.01 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.16 <lb/>-0.24 <lb/>-0.35 <lb/>-0.40 <lb/>-0.22*** -0.34*** <lb/>(0.04) (0.06) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>(0.26) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>θ h <lb/>-0.05 0.20*** 0.47*** 0.75*** 1.10*** 1.21*** 0.60*** 0.85*** <lb/>(0.04) (0.07) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.27 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>1.84 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>1.94 <lb/>1.94 <lb/>1.84 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>Note: Estimated coefficients from regressions (4) over the sample 1999Q1-2023Q4 where the state indi-<lb/>cator variable is S t+h instead of S t . R 2 is the adjusted R 2 . Newey-West standard errors are in parenthesis. <lb/>Stars denote the 10% (*), 5% (**) and 1% (***) significance level. <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 7: Bias in Forecasting Models <lb/>Forecast Horizon <lb/>Single <lb/>Pooled <lb/>h = <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 -5 <lb/>0 -8 <lb/>Panel A: Random Walk <lb/>µ h <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>(0.26) <lb/>(0.09) <lb/>(0.14) <lb/>(0.20) <lb/>(0.24) <lb/>(0.26) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>θ h <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>-0.15 <lb/>-0.35*** -0.63*** -0.56** -0.82** -0.41*** -0.45*** <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.13) <lb/>(0.21) <lb/>(0.24) <lb/>(0.23) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.29 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>2.29 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>Panel B: AR <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.36* <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.16*** <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.21) <lb/>(0.29) <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.02 <lb/>-0.20 <lb/>-0.18* <lb/>-0.50** -0.80*** -0.73*** -0.34*** -0.43*** <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.22) <lb/>(0.24) <lb/>(0.22) <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.39 <lb/>2.36 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>2.34 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>1.94 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>Panel B: AR with exogenous assumptions <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.12) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.20) <lb/>(0.20) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>θ h <lb/>-0.19 <lb/>-0.31* -0.50*** -0.69*** -0.66*** -0.70*** -0.34*** -0.40*** <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.12) <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.03 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>2.03 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>Panel C: Small BVAR <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.41* <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.25** <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>(0.12) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.23) <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.22* <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>-0.44* <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>-0.33*** <lb/>(0.05) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>(0.15) <lb/>(0.21) <lb/>(0.25) <lb/>(0.31) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.39 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>1.96 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>2.35 <lb/>1.97 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>2.39 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Panel D: 1.8% Forecast <lb/>µ h <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.00 <lb/>-0.11 <lb/>-0.21 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.13** -0.13** <lb/>(0.17) <lb/>(0.14) <lb/>(0.14) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.15) <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>(0.06) <lb/>θ h <lb/>0.55*** 0.42*** 0.43*** <lb/>0.49* <lb/>0.24*** <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.38*** 0.29*** <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>(0.12) <lb/>(0.18) <lb/>(0.19) <lb/>(0.21) <lb/>(0.07) <lb/>(0.08) <lb/>γ h <lb/>2.20 <lb/>2.26 <lb/>1.97 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>1.96 <lb/>1.84 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Note: Estimated coefficients from regression (4) applied to the forecasting models described in section (5.2) <lb/>over the sample 1999Q1-2023Q4. R 2 is the adjusted R 2 . Newey-West standard errors are in parenthesis. Stars <lb/>denote the 10% (*), 5% (**) and 1% (***) significance level. <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Ahrens, S., J. Lustenhouwer, and M. Tettamanzi (2023). The Stabilizing Effects of Publishing <lb/>Strategic Central Bank Projections. Macroeconomic Dynamics 27, 826-868. <lb/>Alessi, L., E. Ghysel, L. Onorante, R. Peach, and S. Potter (2014). Central Bank Macroeco-<lb/>nomic Forecasting During the Global Financial Crisis: The European Central Bank and Federal <lb/>Reserve Bank of New York Experiences. Journal of Business and Economic Statistics 32(4), <lb/>483-500. <lb/>Arai, N. (2016). Evaluating the Efficiency of the FOMC&apos;s New Economic Projections. Journal of <lb/>Money, Credit and Banking 48(5), 1019-1039. <lb/>Argiri, E., S. G. Hall, A. Momtsia, D. M. Papadopoulou, I. Skotida, G. S. Tavlas, and Y. Wang <lb/>(2024). An Evaluation of the Inflation Forecasting Performance of the European Central Bank, <lb/>the Federal Reserve, and the Bank of England. Journal of Forecasting, 1-16. <lb/>Capistran, C. (2008). Bias in Federal Reserve Inflation Forecasts: Is the Federal Reserve Irrational <lb/>of Just Cautious? Journal of Monetary Economics 55, 1415-1427. <lb/>Ciccarelli, M., M. D. Paries, and R. Priftis (2024). ECB Macroeconometric Models for Forecasting <lb/>and Policy Analysis. Occasional Paper Series 344, European Central Bank. <lb/>Clements, M. P., F. Joutz, and H. O. Stekler (2007). An Evaluation of the Forecasts of the Federal <lb/>Reserve: a Pooled Approach. Journal of Applied Econometrics 22, 121-136. <lb/>Coibion, O., Y. Gorodnichenko, S. Kumar, and M. Pedemonte (2020). Inflation Expectations as a <lb/>Policy Tool? Journal of International Economics 124, 2-26. <lb/>Coibion, O., Y. Gorodnichenko, and M. Weber (2022). Monetary Policy Communications and <lb/>Their Effects on Household Inflation Expectations. Journal of Political Economy 130(6), 1537-<lb/>1584. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Duffy, J. and F. Heinemann (2021). Central Bank Reputation, Cheap Talk and Transparency as <lb/>Substitutes for Commitment: Experimental Evidence. Journal of Monetary Economics 117, <lb/>887-903. <lb/>El-Shagi, M., S. Giesen, and A. Jung (2016). Revisiting the Relative Forecast Performances of Fed <lb/>Staff and Private Forecasters: A Dynamic Approach. International Journal of Forecasting 32, <lb/>313-323. <lb/>Ellison, M. and T. J. Sargent (2012). A Defence of the FOMC. International Economic Re-<lb/>view 53(34), 1047-1065. <lb/>Glas, A. and K. Heinisch (2023). Conditional Macroeconomic Survey Forecasts: Revisions and <lb/>Errors. Journal of International Money and Finance 138. <lb/>Gomez-Barrero, S. and J. A. Parra-Polania (2014). Central Bank Strategic Forecasting. Contem-<lb/>porary Economic Policy 32(4), 802-810. <lb/>Goodhart, C. and M. Pradhan (2023). A Snapshot of Central Bank (two year) Forecasting: a Mixed <lb/>Picture. Working Papers 18043, CEPR. <lb/>Granziera, E., V. Larsen, , L. Melosi, and G. Meggiorini (2024). Speaking of Inflation: The <lb/>Influence of FED Speeches on Expectations. mimeo, Norges Bank. <lb/>Granziera, E. and T. Sekhposyan (2019). Predicting Relative Forecasting Performance: an Empir-<lb/>ical Investigation. International Journal of Forecasting 35, 1636-1657. <lb/>Hartmann, P. and F. Smets (2018). The First Twenty Years of the European Central Bank: Mone-<lb/>tary Policy. Working Papers 2219, European Central Bank. <lb/>Herbert, S. (2022). State-Dependent Central Bank Communication with Heterogeneous Beliefs. <lb/>Working Papers 875, Banque de France. <lb/>Holden, K. and D. A. Peel (1990). On Testing for Unbiasedness and Efficiency of Forecasts. The <lb/>Manchester School 58(2), 120-127. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Hubert, P. (2015a). Do Central Bank Forecasts Influence Private Agents? Forecasting Performance <lb/>versus Signals. Journal of Money, Credit and Banking 47(4), 771-789. <lb/>Hubert, P. (2015b). ECB Projections as a Tool for Understanding Policy Decisions. Journal of <lb/>Forecasting 34, 574-587. <lb/>Hubert, P. (2017). Qualitative and Quantitative Central Bank Communication and Inflation Expec-<lb/>tations. B.E. Journal of Macroeconomics 17(1), 1-41. <lb/>Iversen, J., S. Laséen, S. L. H., and U. Söderström (2016). Real-Time Forecasting for Monetary <lb/>Policy Analysis: the Case of Sveriges Riksbank. Working Papers 318, Sveriges Riksbank. <lb/>Kontogeorgos, G. and K. Lambrias (2022). Evaluating the Eurosystem/ECB staff macroeconomic <lb/>projections: the first 20 years. Journal of Forecasting 1, 211-404. <lb/>Levy, M. D. (2023). The Fed: Bad Forecasts and Misguided Monetary Policy. Economics Working <lb/>Paper 23103, Hoover Institution. <lb/>Lyziak, T. and M. Paloviita (2018). On the Formation of Inflation Expectations in Turbulent Times: <lb/>The Case of the Euro Area. Economic Modelling 72, 132-139. <lb/>Mcmahon, M. and R. Rholes (2023). Building Central Bank Credibility: The Role of Forecast <lb/>Performance. Technical report, CEPR. <lb/>Messina, J., T. M. Sinclair, and H. Stekler (2015). What Can We Learn from Revisions to the <lb/>Greenbook Forecasts? Journal of Macroeconomics 45, 54-62. <lb/>Odendahl, F., B. Rossi, and T. Sekhposyan (2023). Evaluating Forecast Performance with State <lb/>Dependence. Journal of Econometrics 237(2). <lb/>Paloviita, M., M. Haavio, P. Jalasjoki, and J. Kilponen (2021). What Does &quot;Below, but Close to, <lb/>Two Per Cent&quot; Mean? Assessing the ECB&apos;s Reaction Function with Real Time Data. Interna-<lb/>tional Journal of Central Banking 17(2), 125-169. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Romer, C. D. and D. H. Romer (2008). The FOMC versus the Staff: Where Can Monetary Poli-<lb/>cymakers Add Value? American Economic Review 98(2), 230-235. <lb/>Rostagno, M., C. Altavilla, G. Carboni, W. Lemke, R. Motto, A. S. Guilhem, and J. Yiangou <lb/>(2019). A Tale of Two Decades: The ECB&apos;s Monetary Policy at 20. WP N. 2346, European <lb/>Central Bank. <lb/>Sinclair, T. M., F. Joutz, and H. Stekler (2010). Can the Fed Predict the State of the Economy? <lb/>Economic Letters 108, 28-32. <lb/>Stock, J. and M. Watson (2007). Why Has U.S. Inflation Become Harder to Forecast? Journal of <lb/>Money, Credit and Banking 39(1), 3-34. <lb/>Weber, M., S. Frache, D. Georgarakos, B. Candia, B. Meyer, O. Coibion, T. Ropele, S. Kumar, <lb/>G. Kenny, R. Lluberas, Y. Gorodnichenko, and J. Ponce (2023). Tell Me Something I Don&apos;t <lb/>Already Know: Learning in Low and High-Inflation Settings. Working paper 2023-102, Becker <lb/>Friedman Institute. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"></note>

			<div type="annex">Bank of Finland Research Discussion Papers 2024 <lb/>ISSN 1456-6184, online <lb/>1/2024 <lb/>Gene Ambrocio -Iftekhar Hasan -Xiang Li <lb/>Global political ties and the global financial cycle <lb/>2/2024 <lb/>Michaela Elfsbacka-Schmöller -Nigel McClung <lb/>Price stability and debt sustainability under endogenous trend growth <lb/>3/2024 <lb/>Diego Moreno -Tuomas Takalo <lb/>Stress test precision and bank competition <lb/>4/2024 <lb/>Eleonora Granziera -Pirkka Jalasjoki -Maritta Paloviita <lb/>The bias of the ECB inflation projections: a State-dependent analysis </div>


	</text>

</TEI>