<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Field-applicable simultaneous multiplex LAMP assay for screening HBV and HCV co-infection in a single tube</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Esra</forename>
            <surname>Agel</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Kevser Hanne</forename>
            <surname>Altın</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-31T11:49:25.786622Z">31.10.2025 11:49:25</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1186$1$s12879-024-09567-8</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12879-024-09567-8</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Esra Agel, Kevser Hanne Altın. (2024). Field-applicable simultaneous multiplex LAMP assay for screening HBV and HCV co-infection in a single tube. BMC Infectious Diseases, 24(1), None. DOI: 10.1186/s12879-024-09567-8</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-31T11:49:25.786622Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-31T11:49:25.786622Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Percutaneous Stylomastoid Foramen Pulsed <lb/>Radiofrequency Combined with Steroid Injection <lb/>for Treatment of Intractable Facial Paralysis After <lb/>Herpes Zoster <lb/>Ruyun Deng . Ruxiang Wang . Ming Yao . Ling Ma <lb/>Received: September 22, 2023 / Accepted: December 11, 2023 / Published online: January 4, 2024 <lb/>Ó The Author(s) 2024 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Introduction: We investigated the safety and <lb/>efficacy of percutaneous facial nerve pulsed <lb/>radiofrequency combined with drug injection <lb/>for treatment of intractable facial paralysis of <lb/>herpes zoster. The authors provide a detailed <lb/>description of percutaneous facial nerve pulsed <lb/>radiofrequency combined with steroid injection <lb/>for treatment of intractable facial paralysis after <lb/>herpes zoster, and they examine its clinical <lb/>efficacy. This is the first time in the literature to <lb/>our knowledge that this procedure has been <lb/>applied in facial paralysis after herpes zoster. <lb/>Methods: A total of 43 patients with a history of <lb/>facial paralysis after herpes zoster for [ 1 month <lb/>were enrolled in this retrospective study. The <lb/>patients were subjected to percutaneous stylo-<lb/>mastoid foramen pulsed radiofrequency of the <lb/>facial nerve under computed tomography (CT) <lb/>guidance combined with drug injection. The <lb/>House-Brackmann grades and NRS (Numerical <lb/>Rating Scale) data collection were performed at <lb/>different time points (preoperatively, 1 day post-<lb/>procedure, and 2, 4, and 12 weeks postoperatively). <lb/>The occurrence of complications was also assessed. <lb/>Results: The 43 participants successfully com-<lb/>pleted the CT-guided percutaneous stylomas-<lb/>toid foramen pulsed radiofrequency of the facial <lb/>nerve combined with drug injection. Both <lb/>approaches [posterior approach of the ear (7 <lb/>cases) and anterior approach of the ear (36 <lb/>cases)] were efficacious and safe. The House-<lb/>Brackmann grades (I, II, III, IV, V, VI) were 4 <lb/>(3-4), 2 (2-3), 1 (1-2), and 1 (0-2) at different <lb/>operation times (T0, T1, T2, T3, T4); patients <lb/>felt significant recovery at T1 after operation <lb/>and had gradually recovered at each time point <lb/>but had no significant recovery after T3. The <lb/>NRS scores at different operation times were <lb/>2.690 ± 2.213, 0.700 ± 0.939, 0.580 ± 1.006, <lb/>0.440 ± 0.908, and 0.260 ± 0.759, respectively. <lb/>Differences in NRS scores between T0 and T1/2/ <lb/>3/4 were significant while differences between <lb/>T1 and T2/3/4 were not significant. Six patients <lb/>developed mild numbness, nine patients <lb/>exhibited muscle tension, while one patient <lb/>exhibited facial stiffness. During surgery, there <lb/>was no intravascular injection of drugs, no <lb/>nerve injury was reported, and there was no <lb/>local anesthetic poisoning or spinal anesthesia. <lb/>Conclusions: Percutaneous stylomastoid fora-<lb/>men pulsed radiofrequency combined with <lb/>drug injection of the facial nerve for treatment <lb/>Ruyun Deng and Ruxiang Wang are co-first authors and <lb/>contributed equally to this work. <lb/>R. Wang Á M. Yao Á L. Ma (&amp;) <lb/>Department of Anesthesiology and Pain Medicine, <lb/>The Affiliated Hospital of Jiaxing University, Jiaxing, <lb/>China <lb/>e-mail: 1319108@qq.com <lb/>R. Deng <lb/>Department of Anesthesiology, Daqing Oilfeld <lb/>General Hospital, No. 9 Zhongkang Road, Sartu <lb/>District, Daqing 163001, China <lb/>Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s40122-023-00571-5 <lb/>of intractable facial paralysis after herpes zoster <lb/>is a minimally invasive technique with high <lb/>rates of success, safety, and effective outcomes. <lb/>It is a potential therapeutic option for cases of <lb/>facial paralysis of herpes zoster with a [ 1 <lb/>month history even for those with severe facial <lb/>paralysis and whose treatment has failed after <lb/>oral medication and physiotherapy. <lb/>Keywords: Facial paralysis; Herpes zoster; <lb/>Pulsed <lb/>radiofrequency; <lb/>Percutaneous <lb/>stylomastoid foramen <lb/>Key Summary Points <lb/>Facial paralysis is a facial function disorder <lb/>associated with significant psychosocial <lb/>impact, communication disorders, <lb/>aesthetic disfigurement, and poor <lb/>outcomes regarding quality of life. <lb/>Although we recognize that there can be <lb/>some self-recovery, still some patients <lb/>have residual facial paralysis, especially <lb/>after herpetic facial paralysis with pain, <lb/>which has a greater impact on patients <lb/>Percutaneous stylomastoid foramen <lb/>pulsed radiofrequency combined with <lb/>steroid injection for treatment of <lb/>intractable facial paralysis after herpes <lb/>zoster can not only relieve pain but also <lb/>improve facial paralysis. This retrospective <lb/>study evaluated the safety and efficacy of <lb/>this new technique and hopes to provide a <lb/>new treatment method for severe facial <lb/>paralysis or cases where drugs have failed <lb/>Percutaneous stylomastoid foramen <lb/>pulsed radiofrequency combined with <lb/>drug injection of the facial nerve for <lb/>treatment of intractable facial paralysis <lb/>after herpes zoster is a minimally invasive <lb/>technique with high rates of success, <lb/>safety, and effective outcomes <lb/>Percutaneous stylomastoid foramen <lb/>puncture with blunt radiofrequency <lb/>needle can decrease nerve injury and be <lb/>used adjacent to facial nerve therapy. It is <lb/>a potential therapeutic option specially <lb/>for cases of facial paralysis of herpes zoster <lb/>with long history even for those patients <lb/>who have severe facial paralysis and failed <lb/>recovery after oral medication and <lb/>physiotherapy <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Facial paralysis (FP) is a facial function disorder <lb/>associated with significant psychosocial impact, <lb/>communication disorders, aesthetic disfigure-<lb/>ment, and poor quality of life outcomes [1-3]. <lb/>Its etiology is attributed to trauma, infection, <lb/>neurologic, metabolic, genetic, vascular, and <lb/>neoplastic disorders as well as toxic, idiopathic, <lb/>and iatrogenic causes [4]. Most FP patients are <lb/>diagnosed with Hunt&apos;s syndrome and Bell&apos;s <lb/>palsy. Inflammation and edema resulting in FP <lb/>are the most common causes [5-7]. Orally <lb/>administered corticosteroids have been shown <lb/>to reduce inflammation and edema. <lb/>However, in some cases, especially in <lb/>patients with facial neuritis secondary to herpes <lb/>virus infection, accompanied by obvious pain, <lb/>early oral corticosteroid administration does <lb/>not relieve facial paralysis. Moreover, long-term <lb/>administration of oral corticosteroids is corre-<lb/>lated with some side effects; thus, these patients <lb/>face long-term consequences of facial paralysis. <lb/>Long-term loss of function of facial nerves has <lb/>implications beyond the associated functional <lb/>deficits, with significant psychosocial implica-<lb/>tions [8, 9]. A study involving 42,866 patients <lb/>with a formal diagnosis of Bell&apos;s palsy showed <lb/>that 1.4% received surgery, 0.9% received <lb/>botulinum toxin treatments, and 32.4% <lb/>received rehabilitation services [10]. Therefore, <lb/>oral medication alone does not alleviate facial <lb/>paralysis in all populations. Percutaneous facial <lb/>pulsed radiofrequency (PRF) is a minimally <lb/></body>

        <page>162 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <body>invasive approach that uses electrodes to stim-<lb/>ulate facial nerves [11]. <lb/>Through radiofrequency needle stimulation, <lb/>nerve conduction can be stimulated through <lb/>pulsed currents, and neurotrophic drugs as well <lb/>as hormones can be injected around the facial <lb/>nerve to directly produce the desired effects. We <lb/>retrospectively investigated the safety and <lb/>effectiveness of transcutaneous facial nerve <lb/>pulse combined with drugs for treatment of <lb/>stubborn facial paralysis after herpes zoster <lb/>(HZ). <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Ethical Approval <lb/>The Medical Ethics Committee of the Affiliated <lb/>Hospital of Jiaxing University approved this <lb/>study (LS2019-013). All participants agreed to <lb/>the study procedures and permitted the sharing <lb/>of their imaging data (including pre-and post-<lb/>treatment images) for future studies and publi-<lb/>cations. This study was conducted in accor-<lb/>dance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Signed <lb/>informed consent was obtained from all <lb/>patients. <lb/>Patients <lb/>A total of 43 patients with a history of facial <lb/>paralysis after HZ for [ 1 month and in whom <lb/>other treatments had failed were recruited from <lb/>the Pain Department of the First Hospital of <lb/>Jiaxing between May 2020 and May 2022. All <lb/>patients underwent computed tomography <lb/>(CT)-guided percutaneous stylomastoid fora-<lb/>men pulsed radiofrequency of the facial nerve. <lb/>All participants were required to sign informed <lb/>consents before inclusion in this study. <lb/>Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria <lb/>The inclusion criteria were: (1) patients with <lb/>clinically diagnosed facial paralysis after HZ; (2) <lb/>patients who failed to recover after 1 month <lb/>with other therapies; (3) patients aged [ <lb/>18 years; (4) those who agreed to undergo <lb/>pulsed radiofrequency modulation of the facial <lb/>nerve; (5) patients who agreed to a postopera-<lb/>tive telephone follow-up. The exclusion criteria <lb/>were: (1) patients with facial skin infections or <lb/>tumors; (2) those with severe disorders or major <lb/>systemic insufficiency; (3) patients with trauma-<lb/>induced nerve rupture; (4) patients with bad <lb/>coagulation functions; (5) patients that were <lb/>allergic to related drugs; (6) patients who <lb/>refused the operation itself and who were <lb/>unwilling to accept any complications or had <lb/>missing data. This study was performed in <lb/>accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. All <lb/>patients agreed to sign the informed consent <lb/>form prior to their inclusion in this study. <lb/>Surgical Procedures <lb/>Surgical procedures were performed under CT <lb/>guidance. The patients were laid in lateral <lb/>positions on the bed with the affected side up. <lb/>Oxygen intake and electrocardiogram (ECG) <lb/>monitoring were continuously performed. The <lb/>positioning grid was fixed on the affected facial <lb/>side by an adhesive tape (Fig. 1) and CT scan <lb/>imaging was carried out. The puncture path <lb/>targeting the stylomastoid foramen was via the <lb/>anterior (Fig 2-1) or posterior (Fig. 3-1) approa-<lb/>ches, according to CT scan imaging. Appropri-<lb/>ate local anesthesia and sedation were <lb/>performed before needle insertion. Soft inser-<lb/>tion of the needle was essential to avoid facial <lb/>nerve injury. We used specially designed blunt <lb/>needles (Fig. 4) in our research, which can avoid <lb/>nerve injury from the injection. When the sty-<lb/>lomastoid foramen was reached (Figs. 2-2, 3-2), <lb/>a PRF probe was induced. Parameters for the <lb/>sensory test (voltage \ 0.5 V and frequency <lb/>50 Hz) and exercise test (voltage \ 0.5 V and <lb/>frequency 2 Hz) were set, which could induce <lb/>soreness, swelling, numbness, or facial fibrilla-<lb/>tion as well as pulsation of trunk muscle fibers <lb/>in innervated areas considered positive. Tem-<lb/>perature, time, pulse width, and frequency were <lb/>set at 42 °C, 300 s, 20 ms, and 2 Hz, respectively <lb/>[12], while PRF voltage was not [ 50 V [13]. <lb/>Based on standard parameter pulses, we added <lb/>the maximum tolerable voltage exercise stimu-<lb/>lation, and patients experienced obvious muscle <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <page>163 <lb/></page>

        <body>contractions in innervated areas for 5 additional <lb/>min [11] . At the end of the above procedures, <lb/>the electrode core was pulled out, and 2 ml <lb/>treatment <lb/>solution <lb/>(0.25% <lb/>lidocaine <lb/>hydrochloride, 0.5 ml contrast agent, 1 mg <lb/>compound betamethasone, and 1 mg mecobal-<lb/>amin) was injected after withdrawing the <lb/>puncture needle with no blood, gas, or liquid <lb/>(Figs. 2-3, 3-3). Specially designed blunt <lb/>radiofrequency puncture needles made by <lb/>Fuerte Company of Zhejiang Province (Fig. 4) <lb/>were used; they do not have a sharp slope and <lb/>can avoid nerve damage during the puncture <lb/>process. <lb/>Observation Indices <lb/>The collected data included: <lb/>• General patient information (Table 1). <lb/>• The NRS scores at different times (T0: pre-<lb/>procedure, T1: 1 day post-procedure, T2: 2 <lb/>weeks, T3 and T4: 4 and 12 weeks post-proce-<lb/>dure) (Table 2, Fig. 5A). <lb/>• Facial paralysis grading according House-<lb/>Brackmann grades at T0, T1, T2, T3, and T4 <lb/>(Table 3). <lb/>• Presence/absence of post-procedural com-<lb/>plications (Table 4). <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>SPSS26.0 (IBM, Chicago, IL, USA) was used to <lb/>analyze the data. The Shapiro-Wilk test was <lb/>used to determine whether the measurement <lb/>data obeyed a normal distribution, and the <lb/>results were expressed as the mean ± standard <lb/>deviation (SD), while the non-normally dis-<lb/>tributed data were expressed as the median <lb/>(IQR). A paired sample t-test was used to com-<lb/>pare the differences among measurement data, <lb/>and the chi-square test was used to compare the <lb/>differences between counting data. We used the <lb/>Wilcoxon test to analyze the non-normally <lb/>distributed data. The Kruskal-Wallis test was <lb/>used to analyze the NRS score and facial paral-<lb/>ysis grading at each time interval after the <lb/>operation. Multiple comparisons were per-<lb/>formed by the Bonferroni test, and the signifi-<lb/>cance level was corrected. A violin plot was used <lb/>to describe the changing trends in NRS score <lb/>and facial paralysis grade. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Clinical Characteristics of Patients <lb/>A total of 43 patients [17 male and 26 female; <lb/>median IQR 59 (52-69) years, range 24--<lb/>76 years] were enrolled in this study. All <lb/>patients had facial paralysis disease after HZ for <lb/>[ 1 month and had had other prior treatments <lb/>that had produced no effect. All patients were <lb/>followed up by telephone. The general charac-<lb/>teristics of the patients are shown in Table 1. <lb/>Safety and Efficacy of the Puncture Path <lb/>A total of 43 cases successfully finished the CT-<lb/>guided percutaneous stylomastoid foramen <lb/>pulsed radiofrequency of the facial nerve. Spe-<lb/>cially designed blunt needles (Fig. 4) that <lb/>Fig. 1 Patient in the lateral position with the surgical site <lb/>exposed and computed tomography (CT) scan; the display <lb/>grid is positioned anterior and posterior to the patient&apos;s <lb/>ear. CT computed tomography <lb/></body>

        <page>164 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <body>minimize nerve injury during needle insertion <lb/>were used in our research. The puncture path <lb/>targeting the stylomastoid foramen was via the <lb/>anterior approach for 36 patients (Fig. 2-2) and <lb/>the posterior approach for 7 cases (Fig. 3-2). <lb/>Both approaches can obtain feeling by pulsed <lb/>radiofrequency; some can see tiny muscle tre-<lb/>mors. There were obvious muscle contractions <lb/>in the innervated areas during the additional 5 <lb/>min maximum tolerable voltage exercise <lb/>stimulation. <lb/>NRS Scores and House-Brackmann Grades <lb/>Before and After Treatment <lb/>The NRS score collection times were: T0: pre-<lb/>procedure, T1: 1 day post-procedure, T2: 2 <lb/>weeks, T3 and T4: 4 and 12 weeks post-proce-<lb/>dure. <lb/>The <lb/>scores <lb/>were <lb/>2.69 ± 2.213, <lb/>0.700 ± 0.939, 0.580 ± 1.006, 0.440 ± 0.908, <lb/>and 0.260 ± 0.759, respectively (Table 2). Dif-<lb/>ferences in NRS scores between T0 and T1-4 <lb/>were significant (Table 2), but those between T1 <lb/>and T2-4 were not significantly different. <lb/>The six House-Brackmann grades (I, II, III, <lb/>IV, V, VI) were determined at different times: <lb/>T0: pre-procedure, T1: 1 day post-procedure, T2: <lb/>2 weeks, T3 and T4: 4 and 12 weeks post-pro-<lb/>cedure. The patients felt better at T1 after <lb/>treatment and gradually improved at each time <lb/>point, but recovery slowed after T3 (Table 3, <lb/>Fig. 5B). <lb/>Fig. 2 2-1: Puncture path via the anterior approach <lb/>targeting the stylomastoid foramen. Black arrow shows <lb/>target point. 2-2: Intraoperative CT scan of the RF needle <lb/>reaching the stylomastoid foramen using the anterior <lb/>approach. Black arrows show RF needle imaging. 2-3: <lb/>Compound liquid was injected after RF procedure. Black <lb/>arrows show contrast agent diffusion. CT computed <lb/>tomography; RF radiofrequency <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <page>165 <lb/></page>

        <body>Intra-and Postoperative Complications <lb/>Follow-up assessment revealed that six patients <lb/>developed mild numbness, nine patients <lb/>showed muscle tension, and one patient had <lb/>facial stiffness. During surgery, there was no <lb/>intravascular drug injection; no nerve injuries <lb/>or local anesthetic poisoning were reported, and <lb/>spinal anesthesia was not performed (Table 4). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>FP affects facial appearance and seriously <lb/>impacts the patients&apos; quality of life. Bell&apos;s palsy <lb/>is the most common cause of acute facial palsy <lb/>and can affect all age groups. However, its <lb/>incidence rate is relatively low in children aged <lb/>B 10 years and in older adults [15]. Ramsay <lb/>Hunt syndrome is the second most common <lb/>cause of facial palsy [15, 16]. Our study assessed <lb/>the treatment of the facial paralysis after HZ. <lb/>The etiology of Bell&apos;s palsy is associated with <lb/>viral infections [17-19]. Varicella-zoster virus <lb/>(VZV) infections in patients&apos; face should be <lb/>Fig. 3 3-1: Puncture path via the posterior approach <lb/>targeting the stylomastoid foramen. Black arrow shows <lb/>target point. 3-2: Intraoperative CT scan of the RF needle <lb/>reaching the stylomastoid foramen using the posterior <lb/>approach. Black arrows show RF needle imaging. 3-3: <lb/>Compound liquids were injected after RF procedure. Black <lb/>arrows show contrast agent diffusion. CT computed <lb/>tomography; RF radiofrequency <lb/></body>

        <page>166 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <body>confirmed in patients with peripheral facial <lb/>paralysis and is believed to be a consequence of <lb/>herpes simplex virus (HSV) activation. In Ram-<lb/>say Hunt syndrome, facial paralysis is accom-<lb/>panied by herpes infections of the ear and face. <lb/>[20]. Therefore, antiviral medications are the <lb/>first choice therapeutic options for Bell&apos;s palsy <lb/>or Ramsay Hunt syndrome. Oral glucocorticoids <lb/>can decrease facial nerve inflammation or <lb/>edema, while surgery can alleviate facial nerve <lb/>Fig. 4 Specially designed blunt needles used in our research which minimize nerve injury when inserting the needle <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <page>167 <lb/></page>

        <body>compression [21]. In this study, percutaneous <lb/>stylomastoid foramen steroid injection com-<lb/>bined with pulsed radiofrequency of the facial <lb/>nerve relieved pain and decreased edema as well <lb/>as inflammation of HZ. <lb/>Percutaneous PRF is a minimally invasive <lb/>procedure that uses electrodes to stimulate <lb/>pathological nerves [11]. Mechanistically, PRF is <lb/>a temperature-independent neuromodulatory <lb/>process that alters synaptic transmission and <lb/>pain signaling via emission of electric fields, <lb/>with no to minimal resultant tissue destruction. <lb/>It has been reported that PRF can exert <lb/>destructive effects on the mitochondria, <lb/>microfilaments, and axonal microtubules, with <lb/>the greatest destruction in nociception mediat-<lb/>ing unmyelinated type C fibers, followed by <lb/>myelinated type A-beta and type A-delta fibers <lb/>[22]. In this study, facial paralysis after HZ <lb/>benefited from this mechanism, which also <lb/>resulted in pain relief. The specially designed <lb/>blunt puncture needle does not have a sharp <lb/>slope to avoid nerve damage during the punc-<lb/>ture process (Fig. 4). Furthermore, PRF also <lb/>relieved neuralgia via enhancement of <lb/>descending serotonergic and noradrenergic <lb/>inhibitory pathways [23]. We also used high-<lb/>voltage motors to stimulate the facial nerves by <lb/>pulsed radiofrequency. Facial muscle twitch <lb/>gradually increased as voltage increased, which <lb/>restored electric conduction of facial nerves and <lb/>helped with muscle contraction. More than <lb/>79% of study participants reported that their <lb/>muscle tightness was greatly relieved. This <lb/>electric motor stimulation of adjacent nerves <lb/>can exert similar effects in nerve or muscle <lb/>Table 1 Patient characteristics <lb/>Total number of patients <lb/>43 <lb/>Gender (men/women) <lb/>17/26 <lb/>Age, years, median (IQR) <lb/>59 (52-69) <lb/>Facial paralysis preoperative grading, <lb/>median (IQR) <lb/>4 (3-4) <lb/>Preoperative NRS score, mean ± SD <lb/>2.650 ± 2.213 <lb/>NRS numerical rating scale <lb/>Table 2 Comparison of pre-and postoperative facial paralysis NRS scores <lb/>T0 <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>T3 <lb/>T4 <lb/>N <lb/>43 <lb/>43 <lb/>43 <lb/>43 <lb/>43 <lb/>NRS <lb/>2.690 ± 2.213 <lb/>0.700 ± 0.939 <lb/>0.580 ± 1.006 <lb/>0.440 ± 0.908 <lb/>0.260 ± 0.759 <lb/>T0 <lb/>-<lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:*** <lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:*** <lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:*** <lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:**p <lb/>T1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>P = 1.000 <lb/>Sig:-<lb/>P = 0.904 <lb/>Sig:-<lb/>P = 0.189 <lb/>Sig:-<lb/>T2 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>P = 0.999 <lb/>Sig:-<lb/>P = 0.628 <lb/>Sig:-<lb/>T 3 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>P = 0.974 <lb/>Sig:-<lb/>T 4 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>** p \ 0.05, ***p \ 0.0001 <lb/>NRS numerical rating scale; T0 preoperation; T1 1 day postoperation; T2 2 weeks post-operation; T3 4 weeks postoper-<lb/>ation; T4 12 weeks postoperation <lb/></body>

        <page>168 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <body>massages. Considerations regarding this stimu-<lb/>lation are: (1) Exercise stimulation of facial <lb/>nerve regions may lead to recovery of <lb/>innervational muscle functions; (2) muscle <lb/>contraction and relaxation may lead to relysis of <lb/>surrounding tissues; (3) rhythmic muscle <lb/>Fig. 5 A Comparison of NRS scores before and after <lb/>treatment. B Comparison of facial paralysis grading before <lb/>and after treatment. Notes: **p \ 0.050, ***p \ 0.0001. <lb/>NRS, numerical rating scale; T0 preoperation; T1 1 day <lb/>after operation; T2 2 weeks after operation; T3 4 weeks <lb/>after operation; T4 12 weeks after operation <lb/>Table 3 Comparison of pre-and postoperative facial paralysis grades <lb/>T0 <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>T3 <lb/>T4 <lb/>N <lb/>43 <lb/>43 <lb/>43 <lb/>43 <lb/>43 <lb/>FPG <lb/>4(3-4) <lb/>2(2-3) <lb/>1(1-2) <lb/>1(0-2) <lb/>1(0-2) <lb/>T0 <lb/>-<lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:*** <lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:*** <lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:*** <lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:**p <lb/>T1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>P = 0.007 <lb/>Sig:** <lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:*** <lb/>p = 0.000 <lb/>Sig:*** <lb/>T2 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>P = 0.408 <lb/>Sig:-<lb/>P = 0.013 <lb/>Sig:** <lb/>T3 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>P = 0.873 <lb/>Sig:-<lb/>T 4 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>** p \ 0.05, ***p \ 0.0001 <lb/>FPG facial paralysis grading preoperation; T0 preoperation; T1 1 day postoperation; T2 2 weeks postoperation; T3 4 weeks <lb/>postoperation; T4 12 weeks postoperation <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <page>169 <lb/></page>

        <body>contractions and nerve discharge may lead to <lb/>acceleration of peripheral microcirculation and <lb/>decreased local edema as well as reduced <lb/>peripheral nerve compression [11]. These out-<lb/>comes have not been reported in previous per-<lb/>cutaneous stylomastoid foramen therapy. The <lb/>greater the stimulation of the nerve by needle <lb/>puncture is, the greater the decrease in edema of <lb/>the nerve capsule. <lb/>In clinical radiology, compared to fluo-<lb/>roscopy and ultrasound, CT-guided procedures <lb/>have been accepted because of their clinical <lb/>accuracy and safety [24-26]. In our study, CT-<lb/>guided percutaneous stylomastoid foramen <lb/>puncture increased accuracy and avoided nerve <lb/>damage because the needle could be con-<lb/>sciously and slowly inserted in the area around <lb/>the nerve. Furthermore, specially designed <lb/>blunt needles (Fig. 4) were used in our research, <lb/>which minimized nerve injury when the needle <lb/>was inserted. We selected the preauricular or <lb/>retroaurural approaches, both of which can <lb/>reach close to the stem facial nerve, increasing <lb/>the close contact between pulse radiofrequency <lb/>and the nerve, thereby producing therapeutic <lb/>effects. The retroaurural approach is usually <lb/>performed under x-ray or ultrasound. In our <lb/>clinical practice, the preauricular approach <lb/>under CT guidance reaches the target more <lb/>easily and accurately (Fig. 1). <lb/>Glucocorticoids for facial paralysis should be <lb/>administered orally and early; however, they are <lb/>metabolized throughout the body and can <lb/>affect many other organs, resulting in adverse <lb/>effects, including osteoporosis or necrosis of the <lb/>femoral head of elderly persons. Soluble gluco-<lb/>corticoids can be safely used locally [27] and <lb/>injected directly around the nerve to quickly <lb/>reduce inflammation and eliminate edema. <lb/>Thus, there is less systemic absorption. We used <lb/>a non-particulate glucocorticoid preparation in <lb/>this study. When the tip was near the nerve and <lb/>after electrical stimulation, corticosteroid com-<lb/>bined with a contrast agent and the nutritional <lb/>nerve drug, B 12 , were administered. Such local <lb/>administration increased the local target drug <lb/>concentration and reduced the side effects to <lb/>other organs. <lb/>In summary, CT-guided percutaneous stylo-<lb/>mastoid foramen PRF of the facial nerve is an <lb/>accurate, safe, and effective treatment option <lb/>for facial paralysis, even for stubborn cases after <lb/>HZ. This study provides a new treatment <lb/>approach to facial paralysis, especially for <lb/>refractory facial paralysis after HZ with pain and <lb/>poor oral drug effects. The study provided two <lb/>approaches, which are both safe and effective <lb/>[23]. <lb/>Limitations <lb/>Our study has some limitations that should be <lb/>addressed. First, patients enrolled were from <lb/>only one pain management center. Second, the <lb/>patients were only followed up for 3 months. <lb/>Future study should carry out research across <lb/>multiple centers with a longer follow-up. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>Percutaneous stylomastoid foramen PRF of the <lb/>facial nerve for difficult facial paralysis after HZ <lb/>is a minimally invasive technique with a high <lb/>success rate. It is a safe and effective approach <lb/>when combined with steroid injection. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>The authors thank the subjects of this study for <lb/>their participation. <lb/></div>

        <body>Table 4 Intraoperative and postoperative complications <lb/>Numbness <lb/>6 (13.9%) <lb/>Tightness <lb/>9 (20.9%) <lb/>Dizziness <lb/>1 (2.3%) <lb/>Steroid intravascular injection <lb/>0 <lb/>Nerve injury <lb/>0 <lb/>Local anesthetic poisoning <lb/>0 <lb/>Spinal anesthesia <lb/>0 <lb/></body>

        <page>170 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <div type="contribution">Author Contribution. All authors con-<lb/>tributed to the study conception and design. <lb/>Material preparation, data collection, and anal-<lb/>ysis were performed by Ling Ma, Ruxiang Wang, <lb/>and Ruyun Deng. The first draft of the manu-<lb/>script was written and Ethical Approval given by <lb/>Ling Ma and Ming Yao, and all authors com-<lb/>mented on previous versions of the manuscript. <lb/>All authors read and approved the final <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Funding. This work was supported by <lb/>funding from Jiaxing City Science and Tech-<lb/>nology Plan(2021AD30143), Key Discipline <lb/>Established by Zhejiang Province and Jiaxing <lb/>City Jointly -Pain Medicine (2019-ss-ttyx), Key <lb/>Discipline of Anesthesiology of Jiaxing City <lb/>(2019-zc-06) and Jiaxing Key Laboratory of <lb/>Neurology and Pain Medicine. The journal&apos;s <lb/>Rapid Service Fee was funded by the authors. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data Availability. The datasets generated <lb/>during and/or analyzed during the current <lb/>study are available from the corresponding <lb/>author on reasonable request. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Declarations <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Conflict of Interest. Ruyun Deng, Ruxiang <lb/>Wang, Ming Yao, and Ling Ma have no conflicts <lb/>of interest. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Ethical Approval. The Medical Ethics <lb/>Committee of the Affiliated Hospital of Jiaxing <lb/>University approved this study (LS2019-013). <lb/>All participants agreed to the study procedures <lb/>and permitted the sharing of their imaging data <lb/>(including pre-and post-treatment images) for <lb/>future studies and publications. This study was <lb/>conducted in accordance with the Declaration <lb/>of Helsinki. Signed informed consent was <lb/>obtained from all patients. <lb/></div>

        <front>Open Access. This article is licensed under <lb/>a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCom-<lb/>mercial 4.0 International License, which per-<lb/>mits any non-commercial use, sharing, <lb/>adaptation, distribution and reproduction in <lb/>any medium or format, as long as you give <lb/>appropriate credit to the original author(s) and <lb/>the source, provide a link to the Creative <lb/>Commons licence, and indicate if changes were <lb/>made. The images or other third party material <lb/>in this article are included in the article&apos;s <lb/>Creative Commons licence, unless indicated <lb/>otherwise in a credit line to the material. If <lb/>material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative <lb/>Commons licence and your intended use is not <lb/>permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the <lb/>permitted use, you will need to obtain permis-<lb/>sion directly from the copyright holder. To view <lb/>a copy of this licence, visit http:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/. <lb/></front>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Jowett N, Hadlock TA. An evidence-based approach <lb/>to facial reanimation. Facial Plast Surg Clin North <lb/>Am. 2015;23(3):313-24. <lb/>2. Jowett N, Hadlock TA. A contemporary approach to <lb/>facial reanimation. JAMA Facial Plast Surg. <lb/>2015;17(4):293-300. <lb/>3. Beurskens CH, Heymans PG. Positive effects of <lb/>mime therapy on sequelae of facial paralysis: stiff-<lb/>ness, lip mobility, and social and physical aspects of <lb/>facial disability. Otol Neurotol. 2003;24(4):677-81. <lb/>4. Sachs ME, Conley J. Dual simultaneous systems for <lb/>facial reanimation. Arch Otolaryngol. 1983;109(3): <lb/>137-49. <lb/>5. Baugh RF, et al. Clinical practice guideline: Bell&apos;s <lb/>palsy. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2013;149(3 <lb/>Suppl):11-27. <lb/>6. Sullivan FM, et al. Early treatment with pred-<lb/>nisolone or acyclovir in Bell&apos;s palsy. N Engl J Med. <lb/>2007;357(16):1598-607. <lb/>7. Engstro ¨m M, et al. Prednisolone and valaciclovir in <lb/>Bell&apos;s palsy: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-<lb/>controlled, multicentre trial. Lancet Neurol. <lb/>2008;7(11):993-1000. <lb/>8. Beurskens CH, Heymans PG. Physiotherapy in <lb/>patients with facial nerve paresis: description of <lb/>outcomes. Am J Otolaryngol. 2004;25(6):394-400. <lb/>9. Beurskens CH, Heymans PG. Mime therapy <lb/>improves facial symmetry in people with long-term <lb/>facial nerve paresis: a randomised controlled trial. <lb/>Aust J Physiother. 2006;52(3):177-83. <lb/>10. Shokri T, et al. Trends in the treatment of Bell&apos;s <lb/>palsy. Facial Plast Surg. 2020;36(5):628-34. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 <lb/></note>

        <page>171 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>11. Ma L, Yao M. Safety and efficacy of CT-guided <lb/>pulsed radiofrequency combined with steroid and <lb/>ozone injection-treated cervical 3-8 herpes zoster <lb/>neuralgia using a posterior and upper quarter of the <lb/>cervical foramina puncture approach. J Pain Res. <lb/>2022;15:23-32. <lb/>12. Zhu J, et al. Application and therapeutic effect of <lb/>puncturing of the costal transverse process for <lb/>pulsed radiofrequency treated T1-T3 herpes zoster <lb/>neuralgia. J Pain Res. 2020;13:2519-27. <lb/>13. Han Z, et al. CT-guided pulsed radiofrequency at <lb/>different voltages in the treatment of postherpetic <lb/>neuralgia. Front Neurosci. 2020;14:579-86. <lb/>14. May M, Klein SR. Differential diagnosis of facial <lb/>nerve palsy. Otolaryngol Clin North Am. <lb/>1991;24(3):613-45. <lb/>15. Kim SH, et al. Comparative prognosis in patients <lb/>with Ramsay-Hunt syndrome and Bell&apos;s palsy. Eur <lb/>Arch Otorhinolaryngol. 2019;276(4):1011-6. <lb/>16. Koshy E, et al. Epidemiology, treatment and pre-<lb/>vention of herpes zoster: a comprehensive review. <lb/>Indian J Dermatol Venereol Leprol. 2018;84(3): <lb/>251-62. <lb/>17. Dorafshar AH, et al. Surface anatomy of the middle <lb/>division of the facial nerve: Zuker&apos;s point. Plast <lb/>Reconstr Surg. 2013;131(2):253-7. <lb/>18. Poutoglidis A, et al. Extratemporal facial nerve <lb/>branching patterns: systematic review of 1497 <lb/>cases. J Laryngol Otol. 2022;136(12):1170-6. <lb/>19. Nakatani H, et al. Initial lesions in Bell&apos;s palsy and <lb/>Ramsay-Hunt syndrome. ORL J Otorhinolaryngol <lb/>Relat Spec. 2010;71(Suppl 1):105-11. <lb/>20. Steiner I, Mattan Y. Bell&apos;s palsy and herpes viruses: <lb/>to (acyclo)vir or not to (acyclo)vir? J Neurol Sci. <lb/>1999;170(1):19-23. <lb/>21. Grogan PM, Gronseth GS. Practice parameter: ster-<lb/>oids, acyclovir, and surgery for Bell&apos;s palsy (an evi-<lb/>dence-based review): report of the quality standards <lb/>subcommittee of the american academy of neurol-<lb/>ogy. Neurology. 2001;56(7):830-6. <lb/>22. Meyers JL, et al. Costs of herpes zoster complica-<lb/>tions in older adults: a cohort study of US claims <lb/>database. Vaccine. 2019;37(9):1235-44. <lb/>23. Huang B, et al. Awake CT-guided percutaneous <lb/>stylomastoid foramen puncture and radiofrequency <lb/>ablation of facial nerve for treatment of hemifacial <lb/>spasm. J Neurosurg. 2021;1:1-7. <lb/>24. Wolter T, et al. CT-guided cervical selective nerve <lb/>root block with a dorsal approach. AJNR Am J <lb/>Neuroradiol. 2010;31(10):1831-6. <lb/>25. Cyteval C, et al. Cervical radiculopathy: open study <lb/>on percutaneous periradicular foraminal steroid <lb/>infiltration performed under CT control in 30 <lb/>patients. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 2004;25(3):441-5. <lb/>26. Lasbleiz J, et al. Evaluation of CT guided cervical <lb/>epidural injections in patients with mechanical <lb/>cervicobrachial neuralgia. J Radiol. 2008;89(3 Pt 1): <lb/>317-23. <lb/>27. Bensler S, et al. Particulate versus non-particulate <lb/>corticosteroids for transforaminal nerve root blocks: <lb/>comparison of outcomes in 494 patients with <lb/>lumbar radiculopathy. Eur Radiol. 2018;28(3): <lb/>946-52. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>172 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Pain Ther (2024) 13:161-172 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>