<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">BrYOLO-Mamba: A Approach to Efficient Tracheal Lesion Detection in Bronchoscopy</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Yuejiao</forename>
            <surname>Cao</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Jianzhong</forename>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Ruibing</forename>
            <surname>Zhuo</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Jin</forename>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Yanting</forename>
            <surname>Dong</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Tanzhen</forename>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Hui</forename>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-28T14:19:56.623250Z">28.10.2025 14:19:56</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1109$1$access.2024.3503353</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1109/access.2024.3503353</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Yuejiao Cao, Jianzhong Zhang, Ruibing Zhuo, Jin Zhao, Yanting Dong, Tanzhen Liu, Hui Zhao. (2024). BrYOLO-Mamba: A Approach to Efficient Tracheal Lesion Detection in Bronchoscopy. IEEE Access, 12(None), 174630-174639. DOI: 10.1109/access.2024.3503353</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T14:19:56.623250Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-28T14:19:56.623250Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>IEEE PHOTONICS JOURNAL, VOL. 16, NO. 2, APRIL 2024 <lb/>6800610 <lb/>Combustion Field Prediction and Diagnosis via <lb/>Spatiotemporal Discrete U-ConvLSTM Model <lb/>Xiaodong Huang , Xiaojian Hao , Baowu Pan , Shaogang Chen , Shenxiang Feng , and Pan Pei <lb/>Abstract-Considering the importance of combustion diagno-<lb/>sis in industrial manufacturing and many fields, efficient, quick, <lb/>and real-time multidimensional reconstruction is necessary and <lb/>indispensable. Hence, focusing on the combustion field dynamic <lb/>and multi-dimensional reconstruction, a modified U-ConvLSTM <lb/>model was proposed to combine with the TDLAS method to resolve <lb/>the real-time reconstruction and short prediction. By dividing the <lb/>combustion field into space and time slices, we used discretized spa-<lb/>tiotemporal slices to complete the 2-D distribution reconstruction <lb/>and then expanded them into higher dimensions. The simulation <lb/>results demonstrate that our design can effectively reconstruct <lb/>different 2-D distributions, achieving a reconstruction error of less <lb/>than 5%. Three-step predictions also performed well, a PSNR no <lb/>less than 30 dB, and an SSIM no less than 0.75. In general, our <lb/>multidimensional combustion field reconstruction method, based <lb/>on the spatiotemporal discretization U-ConvLSTM model, can en-<lb/>hance the accuracy of combustion field reconstruction and provide <lb/>short-term predictions. This work will contribute to closed-loop <lb/>control in industrial fields. <lb/>Index Terms-Tunable diode laser absorption spectroscopy <lb/>(TDLAS), U-model convolutional long short-term memory (U-<lb/>ConvLSTM), combustion site, reconstruction, predicted. <lb/></front>
    
    <body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>A S THE environment changes everywhere, global warming <lb/>accelerates [1], [2], [3], [4], [5]. How to use limited energy <lb/>to meet production and living needs and control greenhouse gas <lb/>emissions is crucial. Combustion is one of the most important <lb/>processes in industrial production, covering energy consump-<lb/>tion and gas emissions. Combustion diagnostics are an effec-<lb/>tive method to detect combustion performance, efficiency and <lb/>emissions. <lb/>Because of the critical role of multi-parameter detection in <lb/>combustion, many re-searchers have focused on typical com-<lb/>bustion fields in industrial manufacturing and military defense. <lb/>These include detection and monitoring of high-temperature <lb/></body>
    
    <front>Manuscript received 12 December 2023; revised 25 January 2024; accepted <lb/>13 February 2024. Date of current version 1 March 2024. This work was <lb/>supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under <lb/>Grant 52075504, in part by the Fund for Shanxi 1331 Project Key Subject <lb/>Construction under Grant 1331PKSC, in part by the State Key Laboratory of <lb/>Quantum Optics and Quantum Optics Devices under Grant KF202301, and in <lb/>part by the Shanxi Key Laboratory of Advanced Semiconductor Optoelectronic <lb/>Devices and System Integration under Grant 2023SZKF11. (Corresponding <lb/>author: Xiaojian Hao.) <lb/>The authors are with the State Key Laboratory of Dynamic Measurement <lb/>Technology, North University of China, Taiyuan 030051, China, and also with <lb/>the Science and Technology on Electronic Test and Measurement Labora-<lb/>tory, North University of China, Taiyuan 030051, China (e-mail: haoxiaojian <lb/>@nuc.edu.cn). <lb/>Digital Object Identifier 10.1109/JPHOT.2024.3366425 <lb/></front>

			<body>boilers, combustion diagnosis of aerospace engine combustion <lb/>chambers [6], and assessment of damage efficiency of high-<lb/>temperature explosion fireballs. However, fire detection, moni-<lb/>toring, and prediction are also necessary to ensure life safety. <lb/>The distribution of the temperature field and gas concentration <lb/>field can directly and effectively reflect the combustion state, <lb/>providing an essential method for evaluating the combustion <lb/>field. Therefore, many researchers aim to redefine combustion <lb/>diagnostics as temperature and concentration field diagnostics <lb/>rather than focusing solely on flames or chemical reactions. <lb/>Common temperature measurement methods can be broadly <lb/>categorized into two types: contact and non-contact measure-<lb/>ments, each applicable in different scenarios. With the advance-<lb/>ment of new sensors and sensor techniques, particularly spec-<lb/>tral detection methods such as absorption spectroscopy, non-<lb/>contact measurement methods have gained popularity. These <lb/>techniques, known for their non-invasive nature, rapid response, <lb/>and high sensitivity [7], [8], are generally well-suited to meet <lb/>the demands of a wide variety of complex and harsh combustion <lb/>sites. To accurately represent the combustion field&apos;s distribution <lb/>and analyze combustion conditions, researchers are working <lb/>on reconstructing the 2-D or 3-D distributions of temperature, <lb/>concentration, or pressure. <lb/>On the one hand, due to the limitations of line of sight (LOS) <lb/>[9], the detected data represent the integral along the optical <lb/>path. Therefore, it&apos;s necessary to utilize computed tomography <lb/>(CT) techniques to reconstruct the distribution of parameters. <lb/>Traditional methods, such as filtered back projection (FBP) and <lb/>the algebraic reconstruction technique (ART) [10], [11], [12], <lb/>[13], are used to invert the actual distribution of temperature or <lb/>other parameters in the combustion field. Xu, Liu, et al. [14], <lb/>[15], [16], [17] used a pentagonal TDLAS detection system and <lb/>CT-TDLAS to accomplish the 2-D reconstruction of temper-<lb/>ature and H2O concentration in swirl combustion. Choi et al. <lb/>[18] deployed multi-angle temperature detection equipment that <lb/>divided the combustion field into a 22 × 22 square mesh grid. <lb/>Jeon et al. [19] constructed a CT-TDLAS system with 16-path <lb/>cells to measure the 2-dimensional temperature distribution <lb/>of a propane-air pre-mixed flame, which covered various fuel <lb/>mixing conditions. <lb/>On the other hand, given the complexity of the combustion <lb/>sitest, it is challenging to arrange a large number of lasers <lb/>and detectors for detection, leading to data scarcity and recon-<lb/>struction difficulties. Conversely, an excess of data can hinder <lb/>real-time reconstruction, failing to meet the demands of dynamic <lb/>combustion detection and reconstruction. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2024 The Authors. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. For more information, see <lb/>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">6800610 <lb/>IEEE PHOTONICS JOURNAL, VOL. 16, NO. 2, APRIL 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>Therefore, some researchers have tried soft measurements <lb/>to realize high-quality re-construction of the region of interest <lb/>(ROI). Cai et al. [20] used a deep learning method to improve <lb/>the reconstruction, such as the convolutional neural network <lb/>(CNN), and indicated that unsupervised or semi-supervised <lb/>deep learning models such as deep belief networks (DBN) and <lb/>generative adversarial networks (GAN), have a possible and <lb/>better application in the tunable diode laser absorption (TDLAS) <lb/>tomography reconstruction field. <lb/>The concept of spatiotemporal discretization was introduced <lb/>by Klapproth et al. [21] in 2015. Since then, the rise of deep learn-<lb/>ing has led some researchers to explore this concept further. They <lb/>aim to predict movement and forecast precipitation using images <lb/>like radar echo maps [22], [23]. Wang et al. [24] also improved <lb/>the PredRNN method to obtain good results for both action-free <lb/>and action-conditioned predictive performance. Through these <lb/>studies, we determined that the dynamic combustion process can <lb/>also be discretized with the spatiotemporal slice; using these <lb/>slices, we can realize the reconstruction under the time and <lb/>spatial dimensions, which will be beneficial for the detection, <lb/>diagnosis, and prediction. However, in the field of dynamic <lb/>combustion, there are few reports on predicting temperature <lb/>distribution. <lb/>In the article, we propose an improved U-ConvLSTM model <lb/>to reconstruct and predict the multi-parameter distribution <lb/>within the combustion field. Based on the TDLAS temperature <lb/>detection and reconstruction method, the feasibility of a multi-<lb/>parameter distribution reconstruction technology is demon-<lb/>strated, and the dynamic reconstruction of the temperature distri-<lb/>bution is achieved through spatio-temporal discretization. First, <lb/>we select appropriate laser spectrum line pairs, build a TDLAS <lb/>detection system to measure the combustion field, get projection <lb/>data and thereby establish an optical detection model. Then, the <lb/>U-ConvLSTM model is designed for subsequent reconstruction, <lb/>training, prediction and performance verification of combustion <lb/>field temperature distribution. Finally, we can demonstrate the <lb/>superior performance of our U-ConvLSTM reconstruction and <lb/>prediction method through comparison with different tempera-<lb/>ture reconstruction methods. <lb/>II. MATH <lb/>A. Tunable Diode Laser Absorption Spectroscopy and <lb/>Tomographic Methods <lb/>Tunable diode laser absorption spectroscopy (TDLAS) is a <lb/>popular absorption spectroscopy technique [8], [9], [10], fea-<lb/>turing a quick response and high selectivity. The mathematical <lb/>background of TDLAS is the Beer-Lambert law, which is shown <lb/>in Fig. 1, and the absorbance α(ν) dependent on the wavenumber <lb/>ν [cm -1 ] can be defined as: <lb/>α(ν) = <lb/>I t (ν) <lb/>I o (ν) <lb/>= exp{-k ν L} = exp{-S(T )P Xϕ(ν, T ) • L} <lb/>(1) <lb/>where I t (ν) and I i (ν) are the intensities of the transmitter laser <lb/>and the incident laser, P [atm] is the total pressure of the region <lb/>of interest, X is the concentration of the material under test, <lb/>Fig. 1. Schematic diagram of Beer-Lambert law. <lb/>Fig. 2. Schematic diagram of TDLAS: (a) the relationship of incident light and <lb/>the transmitted light with development of wavenumber; (b) the relationship of <lb/>the center wavenumber and ab-sorption coefficient under different temperature. <lb/>and S[T(x)] [cm -2 •atm -1 ] is the line strength of the molecular <lb/>transition of the absorbing species, which is dependent on the <lb/>temperature [22], [23], ϕ(ν, T) [cm] is the line-shape function. <lb/>The relationship between the incident light and the transmitted <lb/>light is shown in Fig. 2(a), and the relationship between the <lb/>absorption coefficient α(ν) and wavenumber at different tem-<lb/>peratures is shown in Fig. 2(b). <lb/>The path based integrated absorbance A i is: <lb/>A i = <lb/>b <lb/>a <lb/>a ν i (l)dl = <lb/>b <lb/>a <lb/>P • S ν i [T ] • X • ϕ(ν, T )dl <lb/>(2) <lb/>where line strength S[T] is a function of temperature, and the <lb/>relationship can be described as: <lb/>S(T ) = S(T 0 ) <lb/>Q(T 0 ) <lb/>Q(T ) <lb/>T 0 <lb/>T <lb/>• exp <lb/>⎧ <lb/>⎨ <lb/>⎩ <lb/>-<lb/>hcE i <lb/>k <lb/>1 <lb/>T <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>T 0 <lb/>1 -exp <lb/>-hcν 0,i <lb/>kT <lb/>1 -exp <lb/>-hcν 0,i <lb/>kT 0 <lb/>⎫ <lb/>⎬ <lb/>⎭ <lb/>(3) <lb/>Q(T 0 ) and Q(T) are partition functions of gas absorption <lb/>molecules at temperatures T 0 and T, which can be fitted by a <lb/>third-order polynomial of temperature and can be ex-pressed as: <lb/>Q(T ) = a + bT + cT 2 + dT 3 <lb/>(4) <lb/>In addition, the HITRAN spectral database [25] online web-<lb/>site (HITRAN on the Web) provides a large number of molecular <lb/>partition function curve with temperature change, which can be <lb/>queried, or directly called by Python through HAPI. <lb/>In this way, we can calculate the value of temperature T based <lb/>on the two selected spectral lines as follows, where h [J•S] and <lb/>c [m/s] are the Planck constant and speed of light, respectively, <lb/>h [J/K] is Boltzmann constant, T 0 is defined as 296 K, A 1 and <lb/>A 2 are the absorbances of different absorption lines. <lb/>T = <lb/>hc <lb/>k (E 1 -E 2 ) <lb/>ln A 1 <lb/>A 2 + ln S 2 (T 0 ) <lb/>S 1 (T 0 ) + hc <lb/>k <lb/>E 1 -E 2 <lb/>T 0 <lb/>(5) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HUANG et al.: COMBUSTION FIELD PREDICTION AND DIAGNOSIS VIA SPATIOTEMPORAL DISCRETE U-CONVLSTM MODEL <lb/>6800610 <lb/></note>

			<body>Meanwhile, the concentration X of the detected gas molecules <lb/>shall be: <lb/>X = <lb/>A <lb/>P S(T )ϕ(ν, T )L <lb/>(6) <lb/>In practical applications, we divide the ROI into grids to <lb/>simplify the calculation, and (2) can be discretized as: <lb/>A i (ν) = <lb/>M <lb/>m=1 <lb/>N <lb/>n=1 <lb/>α mn (T mn , X mn , ν) • l ν <lb/>mn <lb/>(7) <lb/>where m × n is the distribution of the grids, k is the number <lb/>of beams, and l ν <lb/>mn is the ab-sorption path length of the k th laser <lb/>beam through the pixel (m, n). It can be expressed in matrix form <lb/>in (8). <lb/>An absorption path isn&apos;t comprised solely of one parameter&apos;s <lb/>information about the combustion field. Consequently, when we <lb/>select different types of absorption lines, we can simultaneously <lb/>reconstruct multiple parameters. This technique is referred to <lb/>as Nonlinear Tomographic Absorption Spectroscopy (NTAS) <lb/>[21] in some studies, which uses known projection data to infer <lb/>the spatial distribution of the entire field, and can use regu-<lb/>larization techniques and optimization algorithms to improve <lb/>reconstruction the difference between the value and the actual <lb/>measured value. <lb/>A ν i = F • α ν i , <lb/>F = <lb/>⎡ <lb/>⎢ <lb/>⎢ <lb/>⎢ <lb/>⎢ <lb/>⎢ <lb/>⎣ <lb/>f 1,1 <lb/>f 1,2 <lb/>. . . <lb/>f 1,n-1 <lb/>f 1,n <lb/>f 2,1 <lb/>f 2,2 <lb/>• • • <lb/>f 2,n-1 <lb/>f 2,n <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>f m-1,1 f m-1,2 • • • f m-1,n-1 f m-1,n <lb/>f m,1 <lb/>f m,2 • • • <lb/>f m,n-1 <lb/>f m,n <lb/>⎤ <lb/>⎥ <lb/>⎥ <lb/>⎥ <lb/>⎥ <lb/>⎥ <lb/>⎦ <lb/>f mn = <lb/>0, (l ∩ mn = ∅) <lb/>l mn , (l ∩ mn = ∅) <lb/>, <lb/>⎡ <lb/>⎢ <lb/>⎣ <lb/>α 1,1 . . . α 1,n <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>α m,1 . . . α m,n <lb/>⎤ <lb/>⎥ <lb/>⎦ <lb/>ν 1 <lb/>, <lb/>⎡ <lb/>⎢ <lb/>⎣ <lb/>α 1,1 . . . α 1,n <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>α m,1 . . . α m,n <lb/>⎤ <lb/>⎥ <lb/>⎦ <lb/>ν 2 <lb/>. . . <lb/>⎡ <lb/>⎢ <lb/>⎣ <lb/>α 1,1 . . . α 1,n <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>α m,1 . . . α m,n <lb/>⎤ <lb/>⎥ <lb/>⎦ <lb/>ν i <lb/>(8) <lb/>Similarly, 2-D detection and reconstruction can be described <lb/>as shown in Fig. 3. X and Y make up the meshing grid of the <lb/>2-D distribution, and each grid is on behalf the absorbance of <lb/>this place, which is dependent on the wavenumber and is shown <lb/>with dimension Z. By computing the 3-D tensor, we realize the <lb/>multi-parameter distribution reconstruction. <lb/>B. Deep Convolutional Neural Networks <lb/>The 2-D reconstruction of the combustion field can be trans-<lb/>formed into an image generation problem for extracting, gen-<lb/>erating, and predicting image features. Therefore, the key can <lb/>be considered as how to extract and learn from image features, <lb/>including color, texture, shape, and local feature points. Among <lb/>these, local features exhibit good stability and are not easily <lb/>influenced by the external environment. <lb/>Fig. 3. Transforming 2-D parameter distribution into 3-D tensor based on the <lb/>TDLAS combustion diagnosis method. <lb/>Fig. 4. Schematic diagram of the typical structure of deep convolutional neural <lb/>network for prediction and generation. <lb/>Deep Convolutional Neural Networks (DCCNs) have proven <lb/>effective in addressing the problem of image feature extraction, <lb/>which benefits from their local receptive fields, shared weights, <lb/>and pooling. A typical DCCN includes multiple sets of convolu-<lb/>tional layers, pooling layers, and non-linear activation functions. <lb/>The convolutional layer is used to extract spatial information <lb/>represented in images, while the pooling layer is used to re-duce <lb/>the spatial size and prevent overfitting. This way, it can decrease <lb/>the amount of data processing while retaining useful informa-<lb/>tion, fulfilling the need for rapid computation. Through multiple <lb/>convolutional layers, discriminative local image features can <lb/>be de-scribed and extracted, which play a significant role in <lb/>subsequent generation. <lb/>The typical model of DCCN is shown in Fig. 4 and the whole <lb/>process can be de-scribed: <lb/>a) Design and select the convolutional and pooling layers, <lb/>including the kernel size, number, and connection, with the <lb/>aim of extracting the deep features of the input projection <lb/>data. <lb/>b) By driving the feature maps into a one-dimensional feature <lb/>vector with a full connection, we can then multiple the <lb/>coefficient matrix and add the biases on the vector to the <lb/>vector and generate the predicted distribution. <lb/>c) Calculate the loss function, set a reasonable learning rate, <lb/>decrease the loss, and optimize the model. <lb/>d) Deploy and invoke the optimal model. <lb/>In our design, the DCNN model was used to generate and <lb/>predict a distribution, so the loss function we used was the mean <lb/>squared error (MSE), defined as: <lb/>loss MSE = <lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 <lb/>(y * <lb/>i -y i ) 2 <lb/>(9) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">6800610 <lb/>IEEE PHOTONICS JOURNAL, VOL. 16, NO. 2, APRIL 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 5. Schematic diagram of ConvLSTM spatiotemporal discretization re-<lb/>constructive method based on the combustion field. <lb/>where n is the size of the output of the model, y * and y are the <lb/>true value and the generated value (predicted value) of the output. <lb/>By repeating training and optimizing the model, decreasing the <lb/>loss function value, the structure parameters are determined and <lb/>ready to be used for the generation and prediction. <lb/>C. Spatiotemporal Long Short-Term Memory <lb/>The combustion field is a dynamic and continuous process, <lb/>which is difficult to calculate, and must be discretized. Inside <lb/>every cell in the m × n discretized grid, several measurements are <lb/>determined by ν, varying over time. Therefore, the observation <lb/>at any time can be represented by a tensor like χ ∈ R v×m×n , <lb/>sharing the same structure as in Fig. 3, where R denotes the <lb/>domain of the observed features. By recording the observations <lb/>peri-odically, we obtained a sequence of tensors χ1 , χ2 , • • • , χt . <lb/>The spatiotemporal sequence forecasting problem is to predict <lb/>the most likely length-K sequence in the future, given previous <lb/>J observations that include the current one [18]. <lb/>χt+1 , χt+2 , • • • , χt+K <lb/>= <lb/>argmax <lb/>χt+1 , χt+2 ,••• , χt+K <lb/>× p (χ t+1, , • • • , χ t+K | χt-J+1 , χt-J+2 , • • • , χt ) (10) <lb/>To forecast the combustion field multi-parameter, the observa-<lb/>tion at each timestamp is the 2-D distribution feature map when <lb/>we are forced on just one parameter, such as the temperature <lb/>2-D distribution. <lb/>Long short-term memory (LSTM) is a type of RNN, which <lb/>has shown a good effect in the time prediction process, such <lb/>as aero-engine remaining useful life prediction [26], [27]. How-<lb/>ever, when it comes to image prediction, LTSM has a weak effect <lb/>on the spatial correlation. <lb/>The integration of Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) <lb/>and Conv-LSTM [22] is pivotal in extracting image features. <lb/>This is especially true for predicting and generating spatiotem-<lb/>poral discrete fields. For example, Fig. 5 shows the discretized <lb/>combustion temperature distribution divided into spatiotemporal <lb/>slices. These slices are dependent on dynamic time and display <lb/>spatial distribution information. Initially, distribution images are <lb/>Fig. 6. Typical Structure of LSTM. <lb/>fed into the CNN model. This model extracts feature informa-<lb/>tion, which includes both the statistical 2-D distribution and dy-<lb/>namic changing rules. The extracted feature maps, now in vector <lb/>form, are inputted into the LSTM. This process is designed to <lb/>capture temporal relations. In this two-step approach, the focus <lb/>of the first step is primarily on spatial information. The second <lb/>step, in contrast, concentrates on temporal information. <lb/>The principle of the LSTM is described in (10) and shown <lb/>in Fig. 6. The key process of the LSTM is how to handle the <lb/>new input, the status to be forgotten, and save the useful data, <lb/>covering the three different gates. <lb/>(χ t : input at time t; W : weight; • : Hadamard product). <lb/>a) Input process: If the input gate i t is activated, the informa-<lb/>tion will be accumulated in the cell. <lb/>b) Forget process: if the forget gate f t is on, the past cell status <lb/>c t-1 could be &quot;forgotten&quot;. <lb/>c) Save process: whether the latest cell output c t will be <lb/>propagated to the final state h t is further controlled by <lb/>the output gate o t . <lb/>i t = σ(W xi * χ t + W hi * H t-1 + W ci • c t-1 + b i ) <lb/>f t = σ(W xf * χ t + W hf * H t-1 + W cf • c t-1 + b f ) <lb/>c t = f t • c t-1 +i t • tanh (W xc * χ t +W hc * H t-1 +b f ) <lb/>o t = σ (W xo * χ t + W ho * H t-1 + W co • c t + b o ) <lb/>H t = o t • tanh(c t ) <lb/>(11) <lb/>More complex structures can be formed if more layers can <lb/>be stacked and temporally concatenated, meeting different en-<lb/>vironmental needs, and can be applied to solve many real-life <lb/>spatiotemporal prediction problems. <lb/>The above describes the working principles of TDLAS and <lb/>ConvLSTM. The function of TDLAS is to detect the optical <lb/>projection information of the temperature in the combustion <lb/>field, which is used as the input of the subsequent prediction <lb/>model. The role of ConvLSTM is to extract image features. As <lb/>the third step of the prediction model, it will solve the problem <lb/>of prediction and generation of spatiotemporal discrete fields. <lb/>III. IMPLEMENTATION OF THE RECONSTRUCTION METHOD <lb/>A. Simplified Mathematical Model <lb/>With the aim of making our designed combustion field multi-<lb/>dimensional reconstructive method based on spatiotemporal <lb/>discretization easier to understand, we have analyzed the math-<lb/>ematical model of the entire system. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HUANG et al.: COMBUSTION FIELD PREDICTION AND DIAGNOSIS VIA SPATIOTEMPORAL DISCRETE U-CONVLSTM MODEL <lb/>6800610 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 7. Schematic diagram of combustion field diagnosis based on TDLAS <lb/>photoelectric detection system. <lb/>Fig. 8. Schematic diagram of conversion between cartesian coordinates and <lb/>polar coordinates. <lb/>A schematic of the TDLAS combustion field detection system <lb/>is shown in Fig. 7. From left to right are the DFB laser controller, <lb/>the combustion field, often called the region-of-interest (ROI) <lb/>and the photoelectric detection device. With the aim of saving <lb/>the equipment input, we take advantage of a lens to change the <lb/>collimation laser to cone-beam and realize the 3-dimensional <lb/>field measurement detection, which will make a 2-dimensional <lb/>surface projection on the detector. We have made only one <lb/>angle projection process in Fig. 7, where (x k , y k , z k ) is the <lb/>3-dimensional combustion field coordinate and (x ω , y ω , z ω ) is <lb/>the photoelectric detection and projection coordinate. <lb/>Through the conversion between Cartesian and polar coor-<lb/>dinates, we can calculate the spatial coordinates of the points <lb/>on the cone beam in the ROI. The conversion process is shown <lb/>in Fig. 8. In this way, we can drive the body measurement into <lb/>surface measurement, which means we only care for one slice <lb/>of the body. <lb/>⎧ <lb/>⎨ <lb/>⎩ <lb/>x = l • sin ϕ • sin θ <lb/>y = l • cos ϕ <lb/>z = l • sin ϕ • cos θ <lb/>(12) <lb/>Hence, we only need to take the 2-D surface detection and <lb/>reconstruction, which is shown in Fig. 9, which is one of the <lb/>detection angles. In this design, we coupled the three types of <lb/>lasers and took advantage of the lens to drive it into a cone <lb/>beam (shown as a fan shape in 2-D). Through multi-angle <lb/>detection and nonlinear computing reconstruction, the parameter <lb/>distribution information is obtained. <lb/>Focusing on the slice measurement and the features of TD-<lb/>LAS, the nonlinear tomography reconstruction from 1-D LOS <lb/>Fig. 9. One measurement slice of ROI. <lb/>Fig. 10. Schematic diagram of nonlinear reconstruction from 1-D LOS to <lb/>multi-dimension measurement. <lb/>to multi-dimensional measurement can be described as shown <lb/>in Fig. 10. <lb/>B. Design of the U-ConvLSTM Model Based on <lb/>Spatiotemporal Discretization and Implementation of the <lb/>Reconstruction Method <lb/>The core of our method was the design and realization of the <lb/>U-ConvLSTM model, which was used to generate the multipa-<lb/>rameter distribution in the combustion field from two dimensions <lb/>to multiple dimensions. The design of the model can be divided <lb/>into two parts: 2-dimension distribution reconstruction and spa-<lb/>tiotemporal discretization sequence generation and prediction. <lb/>The first step in our research involves dataset preparation. Real <lb/>distribution data is hard to obtain and verify, posing challenges <lb/>for proving the training and testing efficiency of our method. <lb/>To tackle this, we used COMSOL, a commercial physical field <lb/>simulation software. With COMSOL, we generated simulated <lb/>combustion fields that featured different modal fields. These <lb/>included one to three burning centers and random mixed burning <lb/>peaks, as shown in Fig. 11. From these combustion simulations, <lb/>we collected transient temperature distribution data of specific <lb/>slices at 0.05-second intervals. To simplify computations, we <lb/>applied pooling operations on the original distributions. This <lb/>process resulted in 200000 distributions with a reduced reso-<lb/>lution of 64 × 64. These distributions maintained an inherent <lb/>spatiotemporal connection. We arranged them into sequences <lb/>of 20 and randomly shuffled these 10000 groups of discrete <lb/>temperature simulation sequences. We then divided these se-<lb/>quences into three subsets: 6000 for training, 2000 for validation, <lb/>and 2000 for testing. Our main objective was to learn how to <lb/>generate a 2-D distribution from projection data obtained at <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">6800610 <lb/>IEEE PHOTONICS JOURNAL, VOL. 16, NO. 2, APRIL 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 11. Different models of temperature distribution of the simulation com-<lb/>bustion field. (a) 1-peak temperature distribution; (b) 2-peak temperature distri-<lb/>bution; (c) 3-peak temperature distribution; (d) mixed-peak temperature distri-<lb/>bution. <lb/>various angles from the detector. In addressing the complexities <lb/>of traditional reconstruction methods in intricate combustion <lb/>sites, we considered several factors. These include the structure <lb/>of the distribution, feature extraction methods, and the size of <lb/>the data. <lb/>The features of the combustion field distribution are as fol-<lb/>lowed: <lb/>a) In contrast to automatic driving and other image recog-<lb/>nition fields, the distribution of the combustion field is <lb/>simpler and the structure is always fixed, meaning that the <lb/>image information is relatively small and all of the features <lb/>are all important. <lb/>b) Compared with some complex images, the distribution of <lb/>the combustion field had fewer parameters to describe. <lb/>improving the risk of overfitting if we use large models <lb/>such as DeepLabv3+ or SOTA. <lb/>c) In real industrial production, it was difficult to obtain a <lb/>large amount of distribution data, causing the model train-<lb/>ing to drop into small sample over-fitting or un-der-fitting <lb/>of the target task. <lb/>To overcome the several problems and meet the combustion <lb/>field reconstruction requirements, we chose the U-Net [24]. as <lb/>the base model of a deep convolutional neural network, with <lb/>these three advantages: <lb/>a) Taking the low-level and high-level distribution features <lb/>into consideration with the skip connection structure, <lb/>b) Maximum use limited supervisory information and a priori <lb/>knowledge to design and improve the model. <lb/>c) Take the splice of feature maps, making up for the loss <lb/>of edge information when we use the convolution, which <lb/>cannot be recovered by deconvolution. <lb/>d) Light-weight and easy to transplant to other projects and <lb/>different dynamic combustion modal needs. <lb/>In our design, we used the modified U-DCCN to realize a <lb/>2-D distribution reconstruction. The uniqueness of the U shape <lb/>greatly extracts the deep feature, capture contextual, and location <lb/>information, which benefits from the skip connection structure <lb/>or splicing of feature maps. The deeper the network layer, the <lb/>larger is the field of vision. The shallow convolution focuses <lb/>Fig. 12. Schematic diagram of the U-DCNN model structure for the 2-D <lb/>distribution generation. <lb/>on texture features, whereas the deep network focuses on the <lb/>essential features. <lb/>The input to the network consists of the detected projection <lb/>data. In the initial design and development phase, we used gener-<lb/>ated simulation temperature distributions to vali-date the model <lb/>and algorithm. The temperature distribution had dimensions of <lb/>(64, 64), and the virtual laser projection setup included three <lb/>center wavenumbers, 20 projection angles, and 64 detectors on <lb/>one side. The laser path followed a fan-like pattern, as shown in <lb/>Fig. 9. Therefore, the input size of the model was 3# (20, 64), <lb/>where 3# represents the three types of center wavenumbers. The <lb/>model architecture, as depicted in Fig. 12, can be divided into <lb/>two parts: the encoder and the decoder. The encoder comprises <lb/>two max-pooling layers with a kernel size of (2 × 2) and five <lb/>convolutional layers with a kernel size of (3 × 3). Its primary <lb/>function is to extract deep features from the input data. On the <lb/>other side of the model, we have the decoder, responsible for <lb/>upsampling and feature fusion. It consists of two upsampling <lb/>layers (deconvolution layers) with a kernel size of (2 × 2) and <lb/>two convolutional layers with a kernel size of (3 × 3). The <lb/>upsampling layers in-crease the size of the feature map, while the <lb/>key process involves copy and concatenation operations. Copy-<lb/>ing and concatenating allows us to preserve information lost <lb/>during the max-pooling process, such as edge features that can be <lb/>recovered through deconvolution. The skip connection structure <lb/>enables us to fuse features from different layers, leveraging the <lb/>strengths of shallow layers in capturing texture and morphology <lb/>features and deep layers in capturing essential characteristics, <lb/>such as the temperature distribution. This approach ensures <lb/>that both low-level and high-level features are retained and <lb/>well-suited for the reconstruction of the combustion field. <lb/>According to the dimensions of the projections and the shape <lb/>of the temperature (T) distribution, the design of the U-DCCN <lb/>architecture is shown in Fig. 12, where after the full connection <lb/>layer, the feature vector is put into the spatiotemporal discretiza-<lb/>tion ConvLSTM model. <lb/>The second part of our design addresses the issue of temporal <lb/>correlation. Unlike most 3D reconstruction methods for the com-<lb/>bustion field, which are time-consuming and computationally <lb/>intensive, we adopted a multiple slice reconstruction approach <lb/>for 3D combustion reconstruction, as illustrated in Figs. 7 and <lb/>9. By focusing on one slice of the field, we were able to rapidly <lb/>reconstruct the parameter distribution. Using multiple models to <lb/>process all the slices, we achieved parallel and efficient 3D field <lb/>reconstruction. Additionally, since combustion is a dynamic <lb/>process, it is crucial to consider the temporal relationship, which <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HUANG et al.: COMBUSTION FIELD PREDICTION AND DIAGNOSIS VIA SPATIOTEMPORAL DISCRETE U-CONVLSTM MODEL <lb/>6800610 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 13. Schematic diagram of the U-ConvLSTM model structure based on <lb/>spatiotemporal discretization distribution sequence. <lb/>reflects the laws of combustion and is often overlooked in <lb/>reconstruction methods. <lb/>To tackle this, we designed the U-ConvLSTM model to ad-<lb/>dress these challenges. In our design, the ConvLSTM serves as a <lb/>connection to learn the relationships among the spatiotemporal <lb/>discretization slices. The entire system can be visualized as <lb/>shown in Fig. 13. <lb/>From the global angle, the input of the model was continuous <lb/>projection sequences, and each sequence consisted of 20 pro-<lb/>jection distribution slice data. We divided the sequence into two <lb/>parts: the first 15 data [0:14] shall be put into the U-ConvLSTM <lb/>model to train, calculate the loss, and optimize the model and <lb/>generate the prediction value of the model, and the last five data <lb/>points [15:19] were considered as the target output of the model. <lb/>The objective function can be expressed as (12), and the aim is <lb/>to generate and predict the distribution of the combustion: <lb/>χt+1 , χt+2 , • • • , χt+5 <lb/>= <lb/>argmax <lb/>χt+1 , χt+2 ,••• , χt+5 <lb/>p (χ t+1, , • • • , χ t+5 | χt-14 , χt-13 , • • • , χt ) <lb/>= g f orecasting (f encoding ( χt-14 , χt-13 , • • • , χt )) <lb/>(13) <lb/>where f encoding was used to encode the former 15 data to search <lb/>the inner link of the distribution slices and g f orecasting was used <lb/>to generate the following distribution status. <lb/>The loss function we chose to identify and optimize the <lb/>prediction process was: <lb/>loss BCE (x i , y i ) = -w i [y i log x i + (1 -y i ) log(1 -x i )] <lb/>(14) <lb/>which was primarily used to create a standard for measuring the <lb/>binary cross entropy between the target and output. Thus, the <lb/>total loss can be described as: <lb/>loss = λloss MSE + (1 -λ)loss BCE <lb/>(15) <lb/>In general, the U-ConvLSTM reconstruction method de-<lb/>signed in this study has the following characteristics: <lb/>a) Modular design. We divided the different function parts <lb/>into different models and designed them as shown in <lb/>Fig. 14. Each part of the reconstruction method can be <lb/>implemented independently, which is easier to train and <lb/>transplant. <lb/>b) Lightweight small networks the total model of our design <lb/>was 51.36 MB, which could be used on the embedded <lb/>Fig. 14. Flow chart of the combustion field multi-dimensional reconstructive <lb/>method via spatiotemporal discretization U-ConvLSTM model. <lb/>terminal equipment, with the aim of realizing distributed <lb/>and real-time reconstruction. <lb/>C. The Quality Assessment Standard <lb/>To estimate the quality of the combustion field reconstruction, <lb/>we chose three main indexes to assess the temperature distri-<lb/>bution reconstruction image, including the root mean squared <lb/>error (RMSE), peak signal-to-noise ratio (PSNR), and structural <lb/>similarity (SSIM). <lb/>Combustion field reconstruction can be seen as a regression <lb/>process, which means training and generating a new distribution <lb/>to increasingly approach the original image, and the main eval-<lb/>uation criterion is the MSE or the RMSE. They can be defined <lb/>as: <lb/>MSE = <lb/>1 <lb/>mn <lb/>m-1 <lb/>i=0 <lb/>n-1 <lb/>j=0 <lb/>[I(i, j) -K(i, j)] 2 <lb/>(16) <lb/>RM SE = <lb/>√ <lb/>MSE <lb/>(17) <lb/>PSNR is one of the most widely used objective measurements <lb/>of image quality, which can be calculated using the MSE. <lb/>P SNR = 10 • log 10 <lb/>MAX 2 <lb/>I <lb/>MSE <lb/>= 20 • log 10 <lb/>MAX I <lb/>√ <lb/>MSE <lb/>(18) <lb/>where MAX = 2 n -1, n is the number of bits of one pixel. <lb/>The higher the PSNR value, the less distortion it represents. <lb/>SSIM is a measure of the similarity between two images, x <lb/>and y. It can be defined as: <lb/>SSIM (x, y) = <lb/>(2μ x μ y + c 1 ) • (2σ xy + c 2 ) <lb/>μ 2 <lb/>x + μ 2 <lb/>y + c 1 • σ 2 <lb/>x + μ 2 <lb/>y + c 2 <lb/>(19) <lb/>where μ x and μ y are the averages of the two images x and y, <lb/>σ 2 <lb/>x , σ 2 <lb/>y is the variance of x, y. Constant c 1 and c 2 are used to <lb/>maintain the stability of (11), and can be de-scribed as: <lb/>c i = (k i L) 2 (i = 1, 2) <lb/>(20) <lb/>where k 1 = 0.01, k 2 = 0.03 and L is the dynamic range of pixel <lb/>values, defined as L = 255 in our study. The closer the SSIM <lb/>value is to 1, the more similar are the two images. <lb/>IV. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>Our designed multi-dimensional reconstruction method <lb/>mainly consists of a 2-D slice and spatiotemporal discretization <lb/>multi-D combustion field reconstruction, and the accuracy and <lb/>result are largely dependent on the parameters of the two neural <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">6800610 <lb/>IEEE PHOTONICS JOURNAL, VOL. 16, NO. 2, APRIL 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 15. Evolution of the loss function for each of the 9-learning rate; (a) <lb/>excessive learning rate; (b) suitable learning rate; (c) low learning rate. <lb/>networks, such as the learning rate l r , the design of the convolu-<lb/>tion kernels N k that determine the features to be extracted, and <lb/>the number of the latent layer N l that determines the prediction <lb/>accuracy and the number of training samples N s . <lb/>Hence, in this section, we focus on these parameters to <lb/>determine how they affect our reconstruction results and how <lb/>they should be determined to optimize our network structure. <lb/>The designed method was then compared to the other two <lb/>reconstruction methods. <lb/>A. Determination of Learning Rate <lb/>The choice of learning rate plays a significant role in network <lb/>training. As shown in Fig. 15, a proper learning rate will show <lb/>a good performance on the results, while on the other hand, a <lb/>low learning rate will make it difficult to converge and cost a <lb/>large amount of computing source, and a large learning rate can <lb/>converge in a short but it is difficult to train and control. <lb/>B. Influences of the Number of Training Samples, Latent <lb/>Layers, and the Design of the Convolution Kernels <lb/>Deep learning models are data-driven, and a sufficient number <lb/>of samples should be used to extract the features during the <lb/>learning process [29]. <lb/>As shown in Fig. 16, by separately changing the three aspects, <lb/>comparing the training time and the optimal PSNR of the results, <lb/>we find that: <lb/>a) An adequate sample size is the foundation for high-quality <lb/>learning. When the number was less than 10000, the model <lb/>could not learn the inner relation. However, when the <lb/>Fig. 16. The relationship between calculation time consumption, opti-<lb/>mal PSNR and hyperparameters: (a) the number of the training samples; <lb/>(b) the design of the convolution kernels; (c) the number of the latent layers. <lb/>number was more than 10000, the accuracy did not show <lb/>obvious improvement, which meant that 10000 samples <lb/>could provide enough features for our mode, and more <lb/>samples had too much computing time. <lb/>b) The design of convolution kernels had a greater impact <lb/>on the results, determining the number of kernels or the <lb/>number of deep features. Our target was 64 × 64, and the <lb/>suit-able design was 32 + 64 + 128 + 64 + 32, with more <lb/>kernels causing high computing cost and low affect. <lb/>c) The number of latent layers did not have much influence <lb/>on the results of training time and optimal PSNR, and we <lb/>chose five layers in this design. <lb/>C. Comparison With the Different Reconstruction Methods <lb/>After determining the learning rate, number of convolution <lb/>kernels, latent layers, and number of training samples, the novel <lb/>U-ConvLSTM model for the reconstruction of the temperature <lb/>distribution was designed with l r = 1e-5, N k = 32 + 64 + <lb/>128 + 64 + 32, N l = 5, and N s = 10000. To demonstrate the <lb/>good performance of our proposed model, we compared it with <lb/>the classic SART algorithm optimized through NSGA-III and a <lb/>simple CNN model, and compare it with our method. <lb/>The results are shown in Fig. 17. It can be found that as <lb/>the number of peaks increases, the reconstruction error also <lb/>increases. The U-ConvLSTM model proposed in this article has <lb/>good reconstruction performance, with a maximum relative error <lb/>of only 4.2%, while the maximum reconstruction error of the <lb/>CNN model is 8.6%, the SART maximum reconstruction error <lb/>of the model is 7.4%. Simple CNN models perform poorly in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HUANG et al.: COMBUSTION FIELD PREDICTION AND DIAGNOSIS VIA SPATIOTEMPORAL DISCRETE U-CONVLSTM MODEL <lb/>6800610 <lb/></note>

            <body>Fig. 17. Comparison of the three reconstruction methods results based on the <lb/>two-dimensional temperature distribution, which was one slice of the spatiotem-<lb/>poral discretization combustion field. (a) Showcases the results obtained from <lb/>our proposed U-ConvLSTM reconstruction method. (b) Displays the results <lb/>obtained from a CNN-based computational re-construction method. (c) Exhibits <lb/>the results obtained from the NSGA-III optimized SART technique. The num-<lb/>bers (1)-(3) represent different distribution patterns, specifically single-peak, <lb/>double-peak, and triple-peak distributions, respectively. <lb/>TABLE I <lb/>THIS IS A SAMPLE OF A TABLE TITLE <lb/>multimodal reconstruction, and SART performs poorly due to <lb/>the influence of CT artifacts. <lb/>D. Results of the Different Preprocessing Steps and Prediction <lb/>Steps <lb/>To compare the results of different prediction steps, we <lb/>conducted tests using five sets of spatiotemporal discretization <lb/>temperature distribution sequence data. Each sequence data <lb/>comprised 10 to 30 distribution slices, with a time interval of <lb/>0.05s. In these tests, the previous slice data were utilized as <lb/>the prior step, while the remaining data were employed for the <lb/>prediction step. The complete results of these tests are presented <lb/>in Table I. <lb/>It can be concluded from Table I that the first, second and third <lb/>results can better predict the temperature distribution informa-<lb/>tion. Their PSNR is greater than 30 dB and SSIM is greater <lb/>than 0.75. However, as the number of predictions increases, <lb/>the accuracy of the predictions decreases. It also decreases, <lb/>their overall PSNR values are less than 13 dB, and their SSIM <lb/>values are less than 0.35. It is worth noting that more prior <lb/>steps will improve the prediction accuracy, but when the prior <lb/>steps reaches 25, the total performance is basically the same <lb/>as 20 prior steps, which means using too many distributions <lb/>as prior knowledge, the model will be overfitted and degraded. <lb/>Therefore, considering the computational and time costs, we <lb/>combine the 20 distributions into a sequence and predict the <lb/>short-term results for 3 time steps. <lb/>Predicting long-term outcomes still poses many challenges. It <lb/>is crucial to consider additional combustion evolution rules and <lb/>effectively incorporate them into the reconstruction or prediction <lb/>process. This requires further algorithm development and careful <lb/>handling of prior knowledge. By addressing these challenges, <lb/>we can enhance the accuracy and reliability of predictions in the <lb/>temporal dimension. <lb/>V. CONCLUSION <lb/>This paper proposes a multi-dimensional reconstruction <lb/>method of combustion fields based on spatio-temporal dis-<lb/>cretization, implemented through the improved U-ConvLSTM <lb/>model, aiming to solve the problem of rapid multi-dimensional <lb/>reconstruction and prediction of combustion fields. According to <lb/>the simulation experiment results of this study, we can find that <lb/>compared with the existing simple CNN model and the NSGA-<lb/>III algorithm optimized simultaneous algebraic reconstruction <lb/>technology (SART), the designed U-ConvLSTM model shows <lb/>better reconstruction performance and Lower time cost, and <lb/>considers the time dimension to learn the inter-temporal cor-<lb/>relation of combustion, expands the reconstruction dimension, <lb/>realizes slice distribution reconstruction and short-term pre-<lb/>diction, is more suitable for dynamic combustion processes, <lb/>and quickly reconstructs and predicts temperature field dis-<lb/>tribution has good application prospects. In future research, <lb/>we will try some semi-supervised or unsupervised learning <lb/>methods to modify our models and methods, such as gener-<lb/>ative adversarial networks (GAN) and graph neural networks <lb/>(GNN), to extract latent information from spatial and tempo-<lb/>ral data. The effectiveness of the features improves the accu-<lb/>racy of temperature distribution prediction in the combustion <lb/>field. <lb/></body>

      <div type="conflict">Disclosures: The authors declare no conflicts of interest. <lb/></div>

      <div type="availability">Data Availability: The data underlying the results presented <lb/>in this paper are not publicly available at this time but may be <lb/>obtained from the authors upon reasonable request. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENT <lb/>The authors would like to thank all reviewers, editors, and <lb/>contributors for their contributions and suggestions, as well as <lb/>all members of the OSEC Laboratory. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] O. Isinkaralar, &quot;Discovery of spatial climate parameters and bioclimatic <lb/>comfort change simulation in Türkiye under socioeconomic pathway <lb/>scenarios: A basin-scale case study for urban environments,&quot; Natural <lb/>Hazards, vol. 120, pp. 1809-1819, 2024. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">6800610 <lb/>IEEE PHOTONICS JOURNAL, VOL. 16, NO. 2, APRIL 2024 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[2] O. Isinkaralar, K. Isinkaralar, and D. Yilmaz, &quot;Climate-related spatial <lb/>reduction risk of agricultural lands on the Mediterranean coast in Türkiye <lb/>and scenario-based modelling of urban growth,&quot; Environ., Develop. Sus-<lb/>tainability, vol. 25, no. 11, pp. 13199-13217, 2023. <lb/>[3] O. Isinkaralar, &quot;Spatio-temporal patterns of climate parameter changes <lb/>in Western Mediterranean basin of Türkiye and implications for urban <lb/>planning,&quot; Air Qual., Atmos. Health, vol. 16, no. 11, pp. 2351-2363, 2023. <lb/>[4] O. Isinkaralar and K. Isinkaralar, &quot;Projection of bioclimatic patterns via <lb/>CMIP6 in the Southeast Region of Türkiye: A guidance for adaptation <lb/>strategies for climate policy,&quot; Environ. Monit. Assessment, vol. 195, no. 12, <lb/>2023, Art. no. 1448. <lb/>[5] O. Isinkaralar, &quot;A climate-sensitive approach for determining the urban <lb/>growth boundaries: Towards a spatial exploration for Bursa, Türkiye,&quot; J. <lb/>Urban Plan. Develop., vol. 149, no. 4, 2023, Art. no. 04023046. <lb/>[6] A. Sarmiento et al., &quot;Raman spectroscopy as a tool to diagnose the impacts <lb/>of combustion and greenhouse acid gases on properties of Built Heritage,&quot; <lb/>J. Raman Spectrosc., An International Journal for Original Work in all <lb/>Aspects of Raman Spectroscopy, Including Higher Order Processes, and <lb/>also Brillouin and Rayleigh Scattering, vol. 39, no. 8, pp. 1042-1049, <lb/>2008. <lb/>[7] H. N. Yang et al., &quot;Leakage detection of closed vials based on two-line <lb/>water-vapor TDLAS,&quot; Measurement, vol. 135, pp. 413-417, 2019. <lb/>[8] Z. Wang et al., &quot;Application of 2D temperature measurement to a coal-<lb/>fired furnace using CT-TDLAS,&quot; Meas. Sci. Technol., vol. 31, no. 3, 2019, <lb/>Art. no. 035203. <lb/>[9] G. R. Cho and D. W. Choi, &quot;Measurement enhancement of TDLAS based <lb/>on variable weighted cross-correlation tomography for the simultaneous <lb/>reconstruction of 2D temperature and concentration,&quot; J. Mech. Sci. Tech-<lb/>nol., vol. 35, pp. 525-534, 2021. <lb/>[10] F. Wang et al., &quot;Simultaneous measurement of 2-dimensional H 2 O con-<lb/>centration and temperature distribution in premixed methane/air flame <lb/>using TDLAS-based tomography technology,&quot; Opt. Commun., vol. 346, <lb/>pp. 53-63, 2015. <lb/>[11] Y. Kim et al., &quot;Deep learning-based denoising algorithm in comparison to <lb/>iterative reconstruction and filtered back projection: A 12-reader phantom <lb/>study,&quot; Eur. Radiol., vol. 31, no. 11, pp. 8755-8764, 2021. <lb/>[12] M. G. Jeon et al., &quot;Evaluation of 3D measurement using CT-TDLAS,&quot; <lb/>Modern Phys. Lett. B, vol. 33, no. 14n15, 2019, Art. no. 1940018. <lb/>[13] D. W. Choi et al., &quot;Performance improvements in temperature reconstruc-<lb/>tions of 2-D tunable diode laser absorption spectroscopy (TDLAS),&quot; J. <lb/>Thermal Sci., vol. 25, pp. 84-89, 2016. <lb/>[14] C. Liu, S.-A. Tsekenis, N. Polydorides, and H. McCann, &quot;Toward cus-<lb/>tomized spatial resolution in TDLAS tomography,&quot; IEEE Sensors J., <lb/>vol. 19, no. 5, pp. 1748-1755, Mar. 2019. <lb/>[15] C. Liu and L. Xu, &quot;Laser absorption spectroscopy for combustion diagnosis <lb/>in reactive flows: A review,&quot; Appl. Spectrosc. Rev., vol. 54, no. 1, pp. 1-44, <lb/>2019. <lb/>[16] C. Liu, Z. Cao, Y. Lin, L. Xu, and H. McCann, &quot;Online cross-sectional <lb/>monitoring of a swirling flame using TDLAS tomography,&quot; IEEE Trans. <lb/>Instrum. Meas., vol. 67, no. 6, pp. 1338-1348, Jun. 2018. <lb/>[17] A. Huang, Z. Cao, W. Zhao, H. Zhang, and L. Xu, &quot;Frequency-division <lb/>multiplexing and main peak scanning WMS method for TDLAS tomog-<lb/>raphy in flame monitoring,&quot; IEEE Trans. Instrum. Meas., vol. 69, no. 11, <lb/>pp. 9087-9096, Nov. 2020. <lb/>[18] D. W. Choi, D. H. Doh, and M. G. Jeon, &quot;The development of the <lb/>simultaneous reconstruction of 2D temperature and concentration using <lb/>a 6-peaks algorithm for CT-TDLAS,&quot; J. Mech. Sci. Technol., vol. 34, <lb/>pp. 2067-2074, 2020. <lb/>[19] M. G. Jeon et al., &quot;A study on two-dimensional temperature and concen-<lb/>tration distribution of Propane-Air premixed flame using CT-TDLAS,&quot; <lb/>Modern Phys. Lett. B, vol. 34, no. 07n09, 2020, Art. no. 2040020. <lb/>[20] J. Huang et al., &quot;Reconstruction for limited-data nonlinear tomographic <lb/>absorption spectroscopy via deep learning,&quot; J. Quantitative Spectrosc. <lb/>Radiative Transfer, vol. 218, pp. 187-193, 2018. <lb/>[21] C. Klapproth, &quot;The contact-stabilized Newmark method: Consistency er-<lb/>ror of a spatiotemporal discretization,&quot; Numerische Mathematik, vol. 131, <lb/>no. 1, pp. 59-82, 2015. <lb/>[22] X. Shi et al., &quot;Convolutional LSTM network: A machine learning approach <lb/>for precipitation nowcasting,&quot; in Proc.28th Int. Conf. Neural Inf. Process. <lb/>Syst., 2015, pp. 802-810. <lb/>[23] X. Zhou, J. Feng, and Y. Li, &quot;Non-intrusive load decomposition based <lb/>on CNN-LSTM hybrid deep learning model,&quot; Energy Rep., vol. 7, <lb/>pp. 5762-5771, 2021. <lb/>[24] Y. Wang et al., &quot;Predrnn: A recurrent neural network for spatiotemporal <lb/>predictive learning,&quot; IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell., vol. 45, no. 2, <lb/>pp. 2208-2225, Feb. 2023. <lb/>[25] I. E. Gordon et al., &quot;The HITRAN2020 molecular spectroscopic <lb/>database,&quot; J. Quantitative Spectrosc. Radiative Transfer, vol. 277, 2022, <lb/>Art. no. 107949. <lb/>[26] S. Xiang et al., &quot;Multicellular LSTM-based deep learning model for aero-<lb/>engine remaining useful life prediction,&quot; Rel. Eng. Syst. Saf., vol. 216, <lb/>2021, Art. no. 107927. <lb/>[27] Q. Wang, S. Bu, Z. He, and Z. Y. Dong, &quot;Toward the prediction level <lb/>of situation awareness for electric power systems using CNN-LSTM <lb/>network,&quot; IEEE Trans. Ind. Informat., vol. 17, no. 10, pp. 6951-6961, <lb/>Oct. 2021. <lb/>[28] X. Xu et al., &quot;CARes-UNet: Content-aware residual UNet for lesion <lb/>segmentation of COVID-19 from chest CT images,&quot; Med. Phys., vol. 48, <lb/>no. 11, pp. 7127-7140, 2021. <lb/>[29] T. O. Ayodele, &quot;Types of machine learning algorithms,&quot; in New Adv. Mach. <lb/>Learn., vol. 3, 2010, pp. 19-48. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>