<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			for publication elsewhere. The manuscript is submitted with the <lb/>knowledge and on behalf of the listed co-authors. <lb/>Data availability statement <lb/>All data are available (by contacting the Corresponding Author). <lb/>A. Giannattasio, 1,* <lb/>M. Rosa, 1 S. Esposito, 1 O. Di Mita, 1 <lb/>F. Angrisani, 1 S. Acierno, 1 C. D&apos;Anna, 1 F. Barbato, 2 <lb/>V. Tipo, 1 O. Ametrano 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Pediatric Emergency and Short Stay Unit, Santobono-Pausilipon <lb/>Children&apos;s Hospital, Naples, Italy, 2 Pediatric Dermatology Unit, <lb/>Santobono-Pausilipon Children&apos;s Hospital, Naples, Italy <lb/>*Correspondence: A. Giannattasio. E-mail: antonella.giannattasio@ <lb/>virgilio.it <lb/>References <lb/>1 Roberts LJ, Huffam SE, Walton SF, Currie BJ. Crusted scabies: clinical and <lb/>immunological findings in seventy-eight patients and a review of the litera-<lb/>ture. J Infect 2005; 50: 375-381. <lb/>2 Castagnoli R, Votto M, Licari A et al. Severe acute respiratory syndrome <lb/>coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection in children and adolescents: a sys-<lb/>tematic review. JAMA Pediatr 2020; 174: 882-889. <lb/>3 Giannattasio A, Maglione M, D&apos;Anna C et al. Silent RSV in infants with <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 infection: a case series. Pediatr Pulmonol 2021; 56: 3044-3046. <lb/>4 Giannattasio A, D&apos;Anna C, Muzzica S, Mauro A, Rosa M, Angrisani F <lb/>et al. Is COVID-19 a hyperferritinemic syndrome in children? Clin Chem <lb/>Lab Med 2021; 59: e409-e412. <lb/>5 Diao B, Wang C, Tan Y et al. Reduction and functional exhaustion of T <lb/>cells in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (Covid-19). Front Immunol <lb/>2020; 11: 827. <lb/>6 Zenzeri L, Giannattasio A, Zito Marinosci G et al. Immunodepres-<lb/>sion COVID-19-related as a promoting factor for severe Pseudomonas <lb/>sepsis in an infant with not respiratory symptoms. Emerg Care J 2021; 16: <lb/>155-157. <lb/>7 Haim A, Grunwald MH, Kapelushnik J, Moser AM, Beigelman A, Reuveni <lb/>H. Hypereosinophilia in red scaly infants with scabies. J Pediatr 2005; 146: <lb/>712. <lb/>8 Levy M, Martin L, Bursztejn AC et al. Ivermectin safety in infants and chil-<lb/>dren under 15 kg treated for scabies: a multicentric observational study. Br <lb/>J Dermatol 2020; 182: 1003-1006. <lb/>9 Popp M, Stegemann M, Metzendorf MI et al. Ivermectin for preventing <lb/>and treating COVID-19. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2021; 2021: <lb/>CD015017. <lb/>DOI: 10.1111/jdv.17850 <lb/>

			<front>Trend of sexually transmitted <lb/>infections during the Covid-19 <lb/>age. What was the impact of the <lb/>pandemic and the social <lb/>distancing measures? <lb/></front>

			Editor <lb/>

			<body>Covid-19 pandemic has led to social distancing guidelines and <lb/>resource allocation with subsequent impairment of sexual health <lb/>services. The impact of such measures and the recommendations <lb/>regarding changes of sexual behaviour is a matter of debate. 1-3 <lb/>Published reports have shown conflicting results. Balestri et al. 4 <lb/>suggested that the incidence of STI in 2020 was comparable to <lb/>2019. Bonato et al. 5 reported no differences in the syphilis cases <lb/>with previous years, while Cusini et al. 6 reported a reduction in <lb/>non-acute cases of STI and Latini et al. 7 showed a reduction in <lb/>STI diagnoses. <lb/>For this reason, we have analysed the trends of seven sexually <lb/>transmitted microorganisms in 5809 patients (4911 females and <lb/>898 males) from June 2014 to December 2020. Cervical swabs <lb/>(4495), vaginal swabs (270), seminal fluids (584), gland swabs <lb/>(39), urethral swabs (476), endometrial fluids (1565), oral swabs <lb/>(26) and anal swabs (79) were analysed. In case of multiple dif-<lb/>ferent samples collected from the same patient in the same date, <lb/>the results were pooled as a single one. In case of repetition of <lb/>the testing procedure in other dates, the results were removed by <lb/>a 2-year filter. <lb/>DNA was extracted by MagNa Pure Compact System (Roche <lb/>Diagnostics GmbH, Mannheim, Germany). DNA amplification <lb/>was performed by AnyplexTM II, STI-7 Detection Kit (Seegene, <lb/>Inc. Seoul, Korea). The study was approved by the Ethical Com-<lb/>mittee of Policlinico of Bari. <lb/>The analysis of the yearly positivity rates was performed by <lb/>either Poisson or Quasipoisson regression model. The P-values <lb/>of the models were corrected by Benjamini and Hochberg&apos;s pro-<lb/>cedure. Plots were created by the package ggplot2 implemented <lb/>in R and the calculations of all statistical tests were performed by <lb/>the open-source environment R 4.0.3. 8 P-values &lt; 0.05 were <lb/>considered statistically significant. <lb/>The number of patients remained stable until 2018 and then <lb/>decreased from 2019 (884) to 2020 (616). The percentage of <lb/>female (84.86% in 2020 vs. 83.77% in 2014-2019) and male <lb/>(16.23% in 2020 vs. 15.14% in 2014-2019) patients remained <lb/>stable in 2020 when compared to the previous years (Chi-<lb/>Squared P-value = 0.511). A slight increase of the median age of <lb/>the patients (36.00 [Interquartile Range, IQR: 31.00-42.00] in <lb/>2020 vs. 35.00 [IQR: 30.00-41.00] in 2014-2019) has been also <lb/>observed (Wilcoxon test P-value = 0.010). The prevalence rates <lb/>for each microorganism were not statistically different in the <lb/>year 2020 and the years 2014-2019 (Table 1). Some statistically <lb/>significant differences between females and males have been also <lb/>detected, but the effect size is likely negligible because of the <lb/>small values of the Cramer&apos;s V. UP accounted for the most pre-<lb/>valent microorganism both in females and males followed by <lb/>UU and MH. <lb/>The results of the models to evaluate the yearly trends for each <lb/>microorganism are reported in Fig. 1. After Benjamini and <lb/>Hochberg&apos;s correction, the only P-values of the UP model were <lb/>statistically significant. In particular, the UP positivity rates var-<lb/>ied in a quite complex way increasing from 2014 to a maximum <lb/>value in 2017 followed by a decreasing trend. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2021 European Academy of Dermatology and Venereology <lb/>JEADV 2022, 36, e158-e247 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">e190 <lb/>Letters to the Editor <lb/></note>

			<body>Overall, the results suggest that the lockdown measures hin-<lb/>dered access to the health care system, whereas they likely had <lb/>a limited impact on sexual behaviours. In fact, the prevalence <lb/>rates have remained stable in 2020, without any reduction in <lb/>sexually transmitted pathogens. Therefore, the risk of undiag-<lb/>nosed STIs has increased. Because of the decreased access to <lb/>Figure 1 Yearly positivity rates (continuos lines) and evaluation of the temporal trend (dashed lines) with 95% confidence bands (grey <lb/>shadows). P-values have been corrected by Benjamini and Hochberg&apos;s procedure and they were statistically significant in the UP model. <lb/>(a) CT, Chlamydia trachomatis; (b) NG, Neisseria gonorrhoeae; (c) UU, Ureaplasma urealyticum; (d) UP, Ureaplasma parvum; (e) MH, Myco-<lb/>plasma hominis; (f) MG, Mycoplasma genitalium; (g) TV, Trichomonas vaginalis. <lb/>Table 1 Evaluation of the prevalence for each microorganism by year (2014-2019 vs. 2020) and by sex <lb/>Micro-organism <lb/>Year <lb/>P-value <lb/>F vs. M <lb/>2014-2019 <lb/>2020 <lb/>Patients (%) <lb/>Patients (%) <lb/>F % <lb/>M % <lb/>P-value-Cramer&apos;s V <lb/>CT <lb/>122 (2.27%) <lb/>9 (1.46%) <lb/>0.243 <lb/>1.77 <lb/>4.49 <lb/>&lt;0.001-0.07 <lb/>NG <lb/>34 (0.63%) <lb/>2 (0.32%) <lb/>0.578 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>3.18 <lb/>&lt;0.001-0.14 <lb/>UU <lb/>277 (5.16%) <lb/>37 (6.03%) <lb/>0.413 <lb/>5.50 <lb/>3.83 <lb/>0.046-0.03 <lb/>UP <lb/>1383 (25.75%) <lb/>146 (23.78%) <lb/>0.312 <lb/>28.55 <lb/>8.87 <lb/>&lt;0.001-0.16 <lb/>MH <lb/>309 (5.75%) <lb/>30 (4.89%) <lb/>0.430 <lb/>6.33 <lb/>1.97 <lb/>&lt;0.001-0.07 <lb/>MG <lb/>50 (0.93%) <lb/>4 (0.65%) <lb/>0.653 <lb/>0.69 <lb/>2.08 <lb/>&lt;0.001-0.05 <lb/>TV <lb/>66 (1.23%) <lb/>4 (0.65%) <lb/>0.317 <lb/>1.20 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.738-0.01 <lb/>P-values have been calculated by Chi-Squared test or by Fisher&apos;s exact test as appropriate. Effect size was evaluated by Cramer&apos;s V. <lb/>CT, Chlamydia trachomatis; MG, Mycoplasma genitalium; MH, Mycoplasma hominis; NG, Neisseria gonorrhoeae; TV, Trichomonas vaginalis; UP, Urea-<lb/>plasma parvum; UU, Ureaplasma urealyticum. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">© 2021 European Academy of Dermatology and Venereology <lb/>JEADV 2022, 36, e158-e247 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Letters to the Editor <lb/>e191 <lb/></note>

			<body>the sexual health services, more intensive efforts will be needed <lb/>in the future to reorganize the territorial network of the sexual <lb/>health services to avoid the spread of STIs in the general popu-<lb/>lation. <lb/>Conflicts of interest <lb/>None to declare. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Funding sources <lb/>None. <lb/></div>

			<div type="data_availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study are available on <lb/>request from the corresponding author. The data are not pub-<lb/>licly available due to privacy or ethical restrictions. <lb/></div>

		  	<front>L. Ronga, 1 <lb/>S. Stolfa, 2 F. Romanelli, 2 D.F. Bavaro, 3 <lb/>A. Saracino, 3 A. Mosca, 1,2 E. Sparapano, 1 C. De Carlo, 1 <lb/>M.T. Montagna, 4 G. Diella, 4 L. Nisi, 2 R. Del Prete 1,2,* <lb/>1 <lb/>UOC Microbiologia e Virologia, Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria, Bari, <lb/>Italy, 2 Section of Microbiology, Interdisciplinary Department of Medicine, <lb/>School of Medicine, University of Bari &quot;Aldo Moro&quot;, Bari, Italy, 3 Clinic of <lb/>Infectious Diseases, Department of Biomedical Sciences and Human <lb/>Oncology, University of Bari &quot;Aldo Moro&quot;, Bari, Italy, 4 Hygiene Section, <lb/>Department of Biomedical Sciences and Human Oncology, University of <lb/>Bari &quot;Aldo Moro&quot;, Bari, Italy <lb/>*Correspondence: R. Del Prete. E-mail: raffaele.delprete@uniba.it <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 Berzkalns A, Thibault CS, Barbee LA, Golden MR, Khosropour C, Kerani <lb/>RP. Decreases in reported sexually transmitted infections during the time <lb/>of COVID-19 in king county, WA: Decreased transmission or screening?: <lb/>Decreased transmission or screening? Sex Transm Dis 2021; 48(8S): S44-<lb/>S49. <lb/>2 João AL, Lencastre A, Calvão J, Rodrigues A, Fernandes C. COVID-19, fear <lb/>and sexual behaviour: a survey in a tertiary STI clinic in Lisbon. Sex <lb/>Transm Infect 2021; 97: 549. <lb/>3 Crane MA, Popovic A, Stolbach AI, Ghanem KG. Reporting of sexually <lb/>transmitted infections during the COVID-19 pandemic. Sex Transm Infect <lb/>2021; 97: 101-102. <lb/>4 Balestri R, Magnano M, Rizzoli L, Infusino SD, Urbani F, Rech G. STIs <lb/>and the COVID-19 pandemic: the lockdown does not stop sexual infec-<lb/>tions. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol 2020; 34: e766-e768. <lb/>5 Bonato F, Ferreli C, Satta R, Rongioletti F, Atzori L. Syphilis and the <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic: did the lockdown stop risky sexual behavior? Clin <lb/>Dermatol 2021; 39: 710-713. <lb/>6 Cusini M, Benardon S, Vidoni G, Brignolo L, Veraldi S, Mandolini PL. <lb/>Trend of main STIs during COVID-19 pandemic in Milan, Italy. Sex <lb/>Transm Infect 2021; 97: 99. <lb/>7 Latini A, Magri F, Don a MG, Giuliani M, Cristaudo A, Zaccarelli M. Is <lb/>COVID-19 affecting the epidemiology of STIs? The experience of syphilis <lb/>in Rome. Sex Transm Infect 2021; 97: 78. <lb/>8 R Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. <lb/>R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria, 2020. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>DOI: 10.1111/jdv.17853 <lb/></front>

			EczemaPartner -adapting a <lb/>questionnaire to assess the <lb/>impact of atopic dermatitis on <lb/>partners of patients <lb/>Dear Editor, <lb/>Atopic dermatitis has an important impact on patients&apos; quality <lb/>of life, well-being and sleepiness. In addition, atopic dermatitis <lb/>in children affects parents and caregivers. 1 In adults, the impact <lb/>of the disease on the partner is poorly known. The FamilyPso <lb/>questionnaire was developed to measure the partner&apos;s burden of <lb/>psoriasis patients; however, it has not been adapted to other der-<lb/>matological conditions. 2 <lb/>The objective of this work was to adapt and validate the Fam-<lb/>ilyPso for partners of patients with atopic dermatitis. We, there-<lb/>fore, renamed it EczemaPartner. <lb/>In the first step, we adapted the FamilyPso questionnaire by <lb/>substituting the term &apos;Psoriasis&apos; with &apos;Eczema&apos;. <lb/>Adult patients with physician-confirmed atopic dermatitis <lb/>completed an online questionnaire containing demographic <lb/>information, the Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI), a <lb/>stress VAS, the Well-being 12 (WBQ12) and a self-assessment of <lb/>severity with the Patient-Oriented Eczema Measure (POEM). 3-5 <lb/>Severity scores were then divided in three severity categories: <lb/>mild, moderate and severe. The patient&apos;s partners fulfilled the <lb/>EczemaPartner&apos;s questionnaire, as well as a stress VAS and the <lb/>WBQ12. The online questionnaire was distributed by the French <lb/>Eczema Patients Association (Fig.1). <lb/>We used confirmatory factor analysis to check if the structure <lb/>that was originally found for psoriasis was valid for eczema using <lb/>three criteria: Comparative Fit Index (CFI) above 0.9, Tucker-<lb/>Lewis Index (TLI) above 0.9 and Root Mean Square Error of <lb/>Approximation (RMSEA) under 0.08. We then used Cronbach&apos;s <lb/>alpha to check for internal consistency aiming above 0.8. We <lb/>checked for external validity using Spearman&apos;s correlation with <lb/>each of the questionnaires&apos; answers. Finally, we checked the score <lb/>difference between different levels of severity. The EczemaPartner <lb/>score is expressed as a percentage of its maximum. The higher the <lb/>score, the higher the burden is on the partner. <lb/>We recruited 2411 patients, of which 1474 were in a relationship <lb/>including 1266 spouses who completed the EczemaPartner. Mean <lb/>patient age was 41.6 years (SD = 12.3) and 57.1% (n = 723) were <lb/>women, 44.2% (n = 560) of them were mild, 44.3% (n = 561) <lb/>were moderate and 11.5% (n = 145) were severe. <lb/>CFI score was 0.94, TLI score was 0.926 and RMSEA was <lb/>0.087 confirming a correct fit. Cronbach alpha was 0.96 IC 95% <lb/>(0.96, 0.96) confirming an excellent internal consistency. <lb/>LETTERS TO THE EDITOR <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">© 2021 European Academy of Dermatology and Venereology <lb/>JEADV 2022, 36, e158-e247 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">e192 <lb/>Letters to the Editor </note>


	</text>
</tei>
