<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Burden of digestive congenital anomalies among children aged 0–14 years in 204 countries and territories, 1990–2021: results from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Xi</forename>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Jie</forename>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Jinhua</forename>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Jun</forename>
            <surname>Du</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Deqin</forename>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Huajian</forename>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-28T15:51:19.857792Z">28.10.2025 15:51:19</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1136$1$bmjopen-2024-093902</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>BMJ</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjopen-2024-093902</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Xi Luo, Jie Luo, Jinhua Zhao, Jun Du, Deqin Lu, Huajian Gu. (2024). Burden of digestive congenital anomalies among children aged 0–14 years in 204 countries and territories, 1990–2021: results from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021. BMJ Open, 14(12), e093902. DOI: 10.1136/bmjopen-2024-093902</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T15:51:19.857792Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-28T15:51:19.857792Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>1 <lb/>Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/>Open access <lb/>Return of participant-level clinical trial <lb/>results to participants: pilot of a <lb/>simplified centralised approach <lb/>Eric Hoffman <lb/>, 1,2 Suzanne Gaglianone, 2 Rahel Ketema, 2 Wangshu Tu, 3 <lb/>Holly Peay, 4 Paula Clemens, 5 Utkarsh Dang, 3 Laurie Conklin 2 <lb/>To cite: Hoffman E, <lb/>Gaglianone S, Ketema R, <lb/>et al. Return of participant-<lb/>level clinical trial results to <lb/>participants: pilot of a simplified <lb/>centralised approach. BMJ Open <lb/>2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/>► Prepublication history <lb/>and additional supplemental <lb/>material for this paper are <lb/>available online. To view these <lb/>files, please visit the journal <lb/>online (https://doi.org/10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2023-080097). <lb/>Received 22 September 2023 <lb/>Accepted 12 March 2024 <lb/>1 <lb/>Pharmaceutical Sciences, <lb/>State University of New York at <lb/>Binghamton, Binghamton, New <lb/>York, USA <lb/>2 <lb/>ReveraGen BioPharma, <lb/>Rockville, Maryland, USA <lb/>3 <lb/>Carleton University, Ottawa, <lb/>Ontario, Canada <lb/>4 <lb/>RTI International, Research <lb/>Triangle Park, North Carolina, <lb/>USA <lb/>5 <lb/>University of Pittsburgh, <lb/>Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA <lb/>Correspondence to <lb/>Dr Eric Hoffman; <lb/>ehoffman@ binghamton. edu <lb/>Original research <lb/>© Author(s) (or their <lb/>employer(s)) 2024. Re-use <lb/>permitted under CC BY-NC. No <lb/>commercial re-use. See rights <lb/>and permissions. Published by <lb/>BMJ. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Objectives Public access databases such as clinicaltrials. <lb/>gov achieve dissemination of clinical trial design and <lb/>aggregated study results. However, return of participant-<lb/>level data is rarely done. A key barrier includes the <lb/>proprietary ownership of data by the sponsor. Additionally, <lb/>investigators may not have access to centralised data, and <lb/>per International Council for Harmonisation of Technical <lb/>Requirements for Pharmaceuticals for Human Use (ICH) <lb/>Good Clinical Practice, must maintain the confidentiality <lb/>of participants. This study piloted an approach to return <lb/>both individual and aggregate clinical trial data to parents <lb/>of children participating in a series of open-label clinical <lb/>trials. <lb/>Setting and design A small biotech company obtained <lb/>central ethics approval (centralised institutional review <lb/>board [IRB], non-exempt). The study was advertised via <lb/>parent advocacy groups. Parents of trial participants were <lb/>offered the option to contact an employee (coordinator) <lb/>within the company, requesting return of their child&apos;s <lb/>study results. Ethics approval covered participation in six <lb/>countries. The study focused on the sequential clinical <lb/>trials of vamorolone VBP15-002 (NCT02760264) and <lb/>VBP15-003 (NCT02760277) (post-results). <lb/>Interventions Contact initiated by the parent enabled <lb/>the coordinator to obtain informed consent (and separate <lb/>General Data Protection Regulations consent), with phone <lb/>translation when needed. Using date of birth and study <lb/>site location provided by the parent, the data manager <lb/>reported the participant number to the coordinator. The <lb/>coordinator retrieved and compiled data, along with an <lb/>aggregate summary, which was mailed via a password <lb/>protected and encrypted memory device to the parent. <lb/>Prereturn and postreturn surveys were sent to consented <lb/>parents (n=19; 40% of 48 total trial participants) and <lb/>investigators. <lb/>Results Prereturn surveys indicated a request for as <lb/>much data as offered, in all formats offered. Postreturn <lb/>survey showed high satisfaction with the process and <lb/>data returned. Survey of the physician site investigators <lb/>(n=10; 100% participation of investigators) voiced <lb/>general satisfaction with the process, with some <lb/>reservations. <lb/>Conclusions This pilot study demonstrates an innovative, <lb/>cost-effective, centralised and labour conservative <lb/>approach to return of participant-level and aggregate data <lb/>to participants in studies. <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Health authorities, academic societies and <lb/>patient advocacy groups are increasingly <lb/>focused on increasing transparency of clin-<lb/>ical trial design and conduct, as well as <lb/>data sharing and data stewardship. This is <lb/>reflected in the US 21st Century Cures legisla-<lb/>tion which supports the National Institutes of <lb/>Health data sharing mandates 1 2 and is further <lb/>exemplified by recent European Union <lb/>Clinical Trial Regulations, which note key <lb/>initiatives of improving information sharing <lb/>and increasing transparency of information <lb/>related to clinical trials (https://www.ema. <lb/>europa.eu/en/human-regulatory/research-<lb/>development/clinical-trials/clinical-trials-<lb/>regulation). Access to participant-level data <lb/>enable alternative approaches to data anal-<lb/>ysis, including meta-analyses and modelling <lb/>to facilitate drug development (eg, predictive <lb/>clinical disease progression models, clinical <lb/>trial simulation tools). 3 Data siloes, driven by <lb/>economic and academic incentives, have the <lb/>potential to undermine development of treat-<lb/>ments for rare diseases. 4 Studies demonstrate <lb/>that most clinical trial participants view data <lb/>sharing positively, despite some concerns <lb/>related to confidentiality and data security, <lb/></body>

        <front>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY <lb/>⇒ A strength is the novel approach of return of patient-<lb/>level clinical trial data to trial participants and their <lb/>families, directly by the trial sponsor. <lb/>⇒ A strength is the survey of the parents of the trial <lb/>participants regarding clinical trial data they wished <lb/>to have returned, the format of these data and their <lb/>satisfaction with the process. <lb/>⇒ A strength is the survey of physician attitudes re-<lb/>garding the direct communication of the sponsor <lb/>and trial participants. <lb/>⇒ A limitation is the small number of trial participants <lb/>(n=19) and physicians (n=10) that participated in <lb/>this pilot study. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></front>

        <page>2 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

        <body>awareness about access and control, and potential harms <lb/>resulting from these risks. 5 6 <lb/>Clinical trial data disclosure or sharing may take <lb/>several forms, including the posting of aggregate results <lb/>on a public or private website, sharing of deidentified <lb/>data with a third party (for research or other purposes), <lb/>or return of an individual&apos;s personal health data back <lb/>to them (figure 1A). Some data collected during a clin-<lb/>ical trial are monitored in order to assess a person&apos;s <lb/>well-being during the trial, or response to therapy (eg, <lb/>weight, height, clinical chemistries); some of these data <lb/>could duplicate data found in their medical record or be <lb/>used by their physician during their clinical care. Other <lb/>data collected during a trial may be less relevant to their <lb/>healthcare (eg, biomarkers and changes in outcome <lb/>measures that were selected to measure the effect of a <lb/>drug); often these data are not regularly assessed during <lb/>the care of a patient. Sometimes these data are not acces-<lb/>sible to their physician during the trial due to use of a <lb/>central laboratory or a non-CLIA-approved laboratory, <lb/>and even if they are, may not be easily interpreted by <lb/>the physician because they are exploratory, or intended <lb/>to assess the pharmacodynamics of a drug. Participants <lb/>(or parents) may misunderstand that biospecimens are <lb/>being collected for research purposes only, and not for <lb/>their direct care. <lb/>With the emergence of the General Data Protection <lb/>Regulations (GDPR) in Europe, there is an acknowl-<lb/>edgement that individuals have a fundamental right to <lb/>ownership of their own personal health data, including <lb/>data collected during a clinical trial (figure 1B). 7 Efforts <lb/>are underway to enable individual ownership of personal <lb/>health data through secure &apos;data lockers&apos;, and FAIR <lb/>consensus foundational principles have evolved to create <lb/>a construct for such data return, ownership and sharing <lb/>(Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability, Reusability). 8 <lb/>Patient advocacy groups have begun to focus on mech-<lb/>anisms to encourage and implement FAIR data lockers <lb/>for their stakeholders. 9 We hypothesised that the driving <lb/>principle for a clinical trial participant may be &apos;a right to <lb/>know and understand&apos; their personal clinical trial results, <lb/>and not as much a &apos;right to own&apos; their clinical trial data. <lb/>Additionally, while &apos;machine operability&apos; is imperative for <lb/>data sharing under GDPR, a recent study of clinical trial <lb/>participants demonstrated a preference for receiving data <lb/>by mail and not via a website. 10 <lb/>We sought to understand parent/caregiver and physi-<lb/>cian views on return of their child&apos;s individual personal <lb/>health data at the end of an open-label clinical trial. <lb/>We also sought to develop a cost-effective process for <lb/>returning clinical trial data directly to participant fami-<lb/>lies, while viewing it as an opportunity to be transparent <lb/>about how these data were similar or different from data <lb/>obtained by their physician during clinical care. The focus <lb/>of our study was clinical trials of young boys living with <lb/>Duchenne muscular dystrophy. This genetic disorder has <lb/>a worldwide incidence of 1:5,000 males worldwide, and <lb/>shows clinical onset around 5 years of age, and progressive <lb/>weakness and disability. The clinical trials were supported <lb/>by public funds (National Institutes of Health (USA), and <lb/>European Commission Horizons 2020 (EU)), and were <lb/>testing vamorolone, a disease-modifying therapy intended <lb/>to be a safer alternative to corticosteroid standard of care. <lb/>Vamorolone has received regulatory approval from FDA <lb/>(USA; 2023), EMA (EU; 2023) and MHRA (UK; 2024) <lb/>based in part on these clinical trials. <lb/>In 2019, the sponsor of the trials, ReveraGen BioPharma, <lb/>received an Administrative Supplement for Research on <lb/>Bioethical Issues award from the National Institutes of <lb/>Health (&apos;Establishing a Cost-effective Return of Results <lb/>to Parents of Boys in VISION-DMD Clinical Trials&apos;). The <lb/>goal of this study was to pilot a centralised approach for <lb/>return of participant-level data to families participating in <lb/>clinical trials of vamorolone. Here, we discuss this pilot <lb/>process using data from a series of small open-label trials <lb/>and present findings from parental and physician surveys, <lb/>intended to inform application of this process to other <lb/>studies. <lb/>Figure 1 Models or return of clinical trial results and return <lb/>of patient-level data. Panel A: models of return of clinical trial <lb/>results. Panel B: models for return of participant-level data. <lb/>Photographs licensed from iStock. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

        <page>3 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

        <body>METHODS <lb/>Patient population and trial design <lb/>This study was focused on participants in two vamorolone <lb/>trials, <lb/>VBP15-002 <lb/>(4-week <lb/>dose-ranging <lb/>study; <lb/>NCT02760264), 11 and VBP15-003 (24-week extension <lb/>study; NCT02760277). 12 These two trials were sequen-<lb/>tial open-label trials, with 48 participants with Duchenne <lb/>muscular dystrophy (DMD), age 4 to &lt;7 years at study <lb/>entry. VBP15-002 was a multiple-ascending dose study <lb/>over a 24-fold range of vamorolone doses (0.25 mg/kg/ <lb/>day to 6.0 mg/kg/day), recruited 12 participants in each <lb/>of 4 dose groups, and was a 4-week safety and pharma-<lb/>cokinetics study (2 weeks on drug, 2 weeks washout). <lb/>All participants were then enrolled into a 24-week <lb/>dose-finding study at the same doses (VBP15-003), with <lb/>motor outcomes at baseline, 12-week and 24-week treat-<lb/>ment, and laboratory outcomes (safety labs, exploratory <lb/>biomarkers). In this report, we focused on test results <lb/>reported back to patient families. These included the <lb/>motor outcomes Time to Stand from Supine velocity (in <lb/>event/s), 6-min walk test (in metres walked), time to run/ <lb/>walk 10 m (in m/s), time to climb 4 stairs (in event/s) <lb/>and NorthStar Ambulatory Assessment (total score). <lb/>Blood laboratory tests (safety biomarkers) assessed in a <lb/>central laboratory included creatine kinase, osteocalcin, <lb/>N-terminal propeptide of type 1 collagen (P1NP), C-ter-<lb/>minal telopeptide of type I collagen (CTX1), morning <lb/>cortisol, fasting insulin and glucose, and glutamate dehy-<lb/>drogenase. Exploratory blood pharmacodynamic protein <lb/>biomarkers, tested at Somalogic, were CD23, MDC/ <lb/>CCL22, IL22BP, lymphotoxin a1b2, IGFBP2 and MMP12. <lb/>Patient and public involvement statement <lb/>The concept of this study evolved from discussions with <lb/>parents of patients and advocates at disease-focused <lb/>conferences. Multiple patient advocacy group leaders, <lb/>physicians and parents of children with DMD were <lb/>consulted about the concept of this project, and were <lb/>asked to comment on and contribute to the design of the <lb/>data return and questionnaire content. <lb/>Consent of participants <lb/>Western IRB (recently renamed WCG; https://www. <lb/>wcgclinical.com/about/) is an accredited &apos;central&apos; ethics <lb/>review panel (not affiliated with a single institution). <lb/>Clinical trials funded by the US National Institutes of <lb/>Health now require such centralised ethics review. The <lb/>approval included advertisement of the study via patient <lb/>advocacy groups in countries in which enrolment had <lb/>taken place (USA, Canada, United Kingdom, Sweden, <lb/>Israel and Australia), and the ability to consent the partic-<lb/>ipant via telephone with use of a telephone interpreter if <lb/>requested by the parent (figure 2A). The advertisements <lb/>included the contact information of a single coordinator <lb/>employed by the sponsor; a strict firewall was established <lb/>where the coordinator shared no identifying information <lb/>with any other employee of the sponsor or others. <lb/>Once a trial participant family (parent) contacted the <lb/>coordinator and requested participation in the return of <lb/>results study, the coordinator then explained the study <lb/>and conducted the informed consent process by tele-<lb/>conference. The informed consent was sent via Adobe <lb/>Acrobat Sign for signature (online supplemental file 1). <lb/>For patients in European countries, a separate GDPR <lb/>consent was also completed, and signed via Adobe sign <lb/>(online supplemental file 2). Only those who signed <lb/>informed consent participated in the return of results <lb/>study (figure 2A). Following completion of informed <lb/>consent, the coordinator collected the following infor-<lb/>mation from the family and stored it in a password-<lb/>protected, cloud-based file: parent&apos;s name, home address, <lb/>parent&apos;s email address, child&apos;s study site and child&apos;s date <lb/>of birth. The child&apos;s study site and date of birth were <lb/>provided to the data manager, who identified the study <lb/>subject number. The data were extracted from the elec-<lb/>tronic data capture system using only the subject number, <lb/>Figure 2 Return of results design. Panel A: overall study <lb/>design of sponsor direct return of participant-level and <lb/>aggregate data to clinical trial participants. Panel B: example <lb/>of graphical return of participant-level data, showing the <lb/>participant&apos;s data relative to other participants in the same <lb/>treatment group. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

        <page>4 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

        <body>and then were presented in a standardised format and <lb/>converted to a pdf file. <lb/>Return of clinical trial results to families was done by <lb/>sending (by mail) an encrypted and password-protected <lb/>USB memory device. The memory device used SanDisk <lb/>Secure Access software (128-bit AES encryption to create <lb/>a password-protected folder-SanDiskSecureAccess <lb/>Vault-on the flash drive). Locked files were moved into <lb/>the SanDiskSecureAccess Vault and only accessed with a <lb/>password sent separately via email to the family. <lb/>Surveys <lb/>Three surveys, two for parents, and one for their physi-<lb/>cians, were developed, and feedback was sought on draft <lb/>content of surveys from parents, stakeholder foundations <lb/>and physicians prior to finalisation and dissemination. <lb/>The first parental survey was administered after signing <lb/>of consent to participate in the study, but before results <lb/>were returned (online supplemental file 3). This parental <lb/>survey was designed to instruct parents on the types of <lb/>data available from clinical trials (motor outcome, clin-<lb/>ical laboratory, exploratory biomarkers), and ask what <lb/>type of data they were interested in receiving (aggregate, <lb/>patient level), and in what data format for data return. <lb/>The second parental survey was administered after the <lb/>return of results, to gauge parental satisfaction with the <lb/>materials received (online supplemental file 4). <lb/>A third survey was developed to administer to the clin-<lb/>ical trial site physicians caring for the patient and patient <lb/>family that had consented to participate in the return <lb/>of results (online supplemental file 5). The purpose of <lb/>this survey was to assess the opinions of the physicians <lb/>regarding the return of patient-level clinical and labora-<lb/>tory data directly from the sponsor to the parents. The <lb/>physicians responsible for the participants during the <lb/>trial also followed the patient for the subsequent 2 years, <lb/>as all participants enrolled in a 2-year long-term exten-<lb/>sion study. Thus, the same physician cared for the partici-<lb/>pant during the trial, and afterwards during the return of <lb/>results and associated surveys. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Parental attitudes and desires regarding clinical trial return of <lb/>results <lb/>Of the 48 patient families participating in the VBP15-<lb/>002/003 clinical trial of vamorolone, 19 (40%) responded <lb/>to advertisements via stakeholder foundations (58% <lb/>North America (US, Canada), 42% Europe and Israel). <lb/>We also developed an informational sheet that could be <lb/>handed out at the clinical trial sites during patient family <lb/>follow-up visits, but clinical trial sites were uncomfortable <lb/>handing out this informational sheet without their own <lb/>institutional ethics approval. <lb/>The full results of the survey of 19 parents prior to return <lb/>of results are provided (online supplemental file 6). We <lb/>queried whether aggregate or individual participant-level <lb/>data were important to parents, and the majority (90%) <lb/>felt that access to both types of data was &apos;very important&apos;. <lb/>We then asked if data should be best presented in tabular, <lb/>or graphical form. Most parents (97%) indicated that <lb/>receipt of data in both formats was preferred. We then <lb/>queried what biomarkers were important to report <lb/>back to parents, giving examples of safety labs (cortisol, <lb/>insulin, glucose), bone turnover biomarkers (osteocalcin, <lb/>P1NP, CTX1) and exploratory efficacy biomarkers. The <lb/>majority of parents responded that they would like all <lb/>data reported to them. <lb/>For the questions, &quot;What do you expect you would do <lb/>with the information returned that summarizes results for <lb/>all boys in the trial?&apos; most responses acknowledged that <lb/>the return of data would be for informational purposes <lb/>only. For &apos;What do you expect you would do with informa-<lb/>tion return on your son&apos;s individual results?&apos; most again <lb/>responded that it would be for informational uses only, <lb/>although 4 (of 18) mentioned the possibility of discussing <lb/>the data with their physician. <lb/>Return of results <lb/>Both aggregate and individual (participant-level) were <lb/>returned to patient parents on a password-protected <lb/>USB memory device sent via the mail. An example report <lb/>is provided (online supplemental file 7). The report <lb/>included a 2-page educational introduction to aid inter-<lb/>pretation of the report. This included definitions of effi-<lb/>cacy and safety outcomes, the concept of aggregated data <lb/>for interpretation of drug efficacy and safety and distinc-<lb/>tions between data generated in a research study versus <lb/>clinical care. For educational purposes, the report also <lb/>elaborated on challenges facing sponsors in terms of <lb/>return of data, including confidentiality firewalls and risk <lb/>for parent/patient overinterpretation of research data <lb/>regarding clinical care. The following 15 pages provided <lb/>the trial participants individual clinical trial data (motor <lb/>outcomes, quantitative muscle testing, anthropomorphic <lb/>data and laboratory data), as well as his data superim-<lb/>posed on aggregated data, both as tabular and graphical <lb/>form for key clinic visits (baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks <lb/>treatment). The graphical form of data presentation <lb/>showed each individual in the specific vamorolone dose <lb/>group (n=12), with their child&apos;s data colour coded within <lb/>this group (figure 2B). <lb/>Parent follow-up survey <lb/>Of the 19 families to whom the prereturn survey was <lb/>completed and results were returned, 12 of these <lb/>completed the postreturn survey (63%). The complete <lb/>responses are provided (online supplemental file 8). The <lb/>majority of the families were &apos;very satisfied&apos; with both <lb/>the return of data approach (10/12; 83%), and method <lb/>of return of data on a password-protected USB memory <lb/>device (8/12; 67%) (figure 3). One family expressed <lb/>dissatisfaction with both of these queries (1/12; 8%), but <lb/>did not provide reasons for their dissatisfaction. Most <lb/>families (18/19) had no technical issues with receiving <lb/>the materials on a password-protected USB; one family <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

        <page>5 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

        <body>had technical problems and was mailed a hardcopy of the <lb/>materials. <lb/>When asked if they felt that the return of results was <lb/>important to them, all (12/12) replied that it was &apos;very <lb/>important&apos; (7/12; 58%) or &apos;important&apos; (5/12; 42%). <lb/>When given an open-field query for why they felt the data <lb/>return was important, 10 responded (see table 1). The <lb/>responses primarily oriented about the importance of <lb/>knowledge about the trial and being informed about the <lb/>child&apos;s health. <lb/>Most parents indicated that it was important to see their <lb/>child&apos;s data in comparison to others in the trial (11/12; <lb/>92%) and provided free text justifications that were <lb/>concordant with increased information exchange which <lb/>is preferred over more narrow information regarding <lb/>their child. Parents were queried regarding the amount of <lb/>data provided, and the majority (11/12; 92%) responded <lb/>that it was &apos;about the right amount of information&apos;, and 1 <lb/>parent reporting that it was too little information. <lb/>Parents were asked if they would have preferred their <lb/>child&apos;s data returned to them via their physician, rather <lb/>than the sponsor (ReveraGen). Most (8/12; 67%) <lb/>responded &quot;I&apos;m neutral; either way would be fine&quot;; some <lb/>responded that they would strongly prefer to receive their <lb/>child&apos;s data from the sponsor and not their physician <lb/>(3/12; 25%), and a single parent stated that they mostly <lb/>agree with their preference for receiving the data from <lb/>their physician, but not strongly (8%). When the respon-<lb/>dents were stratified by North America versus Europe, <lb/>there were no differences. <lb/>The parents were queried as to whether they had shared <lb/>the returned data with others. Half of respondents had <lb/>shared data with family members, 42% with healthcare <lb/>providers, 17% with friends and 8% with teachers; 42% <lb/>responded that they had not shared the data with anyone. <lb/>When asked if they would participate in such a return of <lb/>results study again, all responded affirmatively (12/12). <lb/>Asked if they had regret regarding participation in this <lb/>study, all responded that they did not have regret. <lb/>Survey of clinical trial site physicians <lb/>Of the 10 physicians that we asked to complete the <lb/>survey (eg, those physicians following the 19 patients), <lb/>all 10 responded. The trial had 12 sites in 6 countries, <lb/>so this represented 83% of physicians and sites. The <lb/>complete responses are provided (online supplemental <lb/>file 9). The physicians were unanimous in their opinion <lb/>that parents put a great deal of importance on receiving <lb/>both individual and aggregated trial data, and all physi-<lb/>cians affirmed that families should receive these data if <lb/>requested by the family (figure 4). We asked, &quot;Do you <lb/>agree with the concept of a Sponsor returning individual <lb/>clinical trial data directly to trial participants?&quot; most <lb/>(8/10) were supportive of this, but 5 of these 8 expressed <lb/>some reservations (&apos;Yes, but it depends on the circum-<lb/>stances&apos;); 1 was not sure, and 1 responded &apos;no&apos;. When <lb/>respondents were stratified by North America versus <lb/>Europe, North American physicians (n=6) voiced more <lb/>enthusiasm for this approach, whereas the European <lb/>physicians (n=3) were less enthusiastic (online supple-<lb/>mental file 10). When asked to elaborate on any concerns <lb/>of a sponsor returning participant-level data directly to <lb/>families, responses are shown (table 1). <lb/>Cost-effectiveness analysis <lb/>The clinical trials that were the focus of this study were <lb/>managed via a public-private partnership model, with <lb/>funding to the for-profit sponsor (ReveraGen) from the <lb/>National Institutes of Health and European Commission. <lb/>The sponsor contracted with each academic clinical trial <lb/>site directly (11 sites in 6 countries) and thus had access <lb/>to all costs associated with contracting of the academic <lb/>clinical trial sites, ethics review and participant visits to <lb/>the site. We estimated costs of the following four models <lb/>of returning participant-level clinical trial results to clin-<lb/>ical trial participants: <lb/>► Current model. Central ethics review held by the <lb/>sponsor, and direct communication with clinical trial <lb/>participant families. <lb/>► Model 2. A stand-alone study, with new contracts <lb/>for return of results between the sponsor and the <lb/>participating academic clinical trial centres, inclu-<lb/>sive of clinical trial site ethics review, and on-site visit <lb/>of the participating family for in-person return of <lb/>participant-level data. <lb/>► Model 3. Similar to model 2, but with remote (telecon-<lb/>ference) delivery of the participant-level clinical trial <lb/>data by the academic clinical trial site to the study <lb/>Figure 3 Post return of results parental satisfaction. Inner <lb/>pie: parental satisfaction with return of data approach used <lb/>by the sponsor. Outer donut: parental satisfaction with <lb/>delivery of the data by mailed, encrypted memory stick. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

        <page>6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

        <body>participant. This model does not include patient <lb/>travel-stay costs to go to the academic clinical trial site. <lb/>► Model 4. In this model, the return of results is included <lb/>in the clinical trial protocol from initiation of the <lb/>contracts with each academic clinical trial centre. In <lb/>this model, the initial costs of the ethics review are <lb/>covered by the costs for the clinical trial protocol. <lb/>However, the site would need to remain open (active <lb/>contract) for about 2 additional years beyond the <lb/>typical close-out (the clinical trial would need to <lb/>be completed, data unblinded and then the return <lb/>of results initiated). This model assumes in-person <lb/>delivery of the results to the study participant by the <lb/>academic clinical trial staff. <lb/>The results of this financial impact analysis are shown <lb/>(table 2). The realised costs associated with data manage-<lb/>ment and reporting (extraction of individual partici-<lb/>pant data, assembly into participant-specific reports, <lb/>reporting) were US$78 585, and this was assumed to be <lb/>a fixed cost across all models. In the current model, the <lb/>focus of this manuscript, there was only the additional <lb/>incremental cost of a centralised ethics approval held <lb/>by the sponsor, for a total cost of US$86 171. The alter-<lb/>native models where participant-level data was returned <lb/>to participants by the clinical trial sites following those <lb/>participants were considerably more expensive, with costs <lb/>driven by the ethics review that would be required at each <lb/>of the 11 participating sites, the time and effort of clinical <lb/>Table 1 Responses of parents of participating children in the clinical trial when asked why they thought that data return was <lb/>important to them, and their physicians regarding their degree of support of sponsor direct return of data to families <lb/>Parents of trial participants: why is trial data return important to them? <lb/>Personal knowledge <lb/>To be informed <lb/>It is a great benefit to be able to see how my son may have responded during the Clinical Trial in all of these areas recorded, In <lb/>Hopes to see some good benefit from the medication. <lb/>We took a big risk in being in the trial. Want to know if it works and how my son paired with the other boys <lb/>It&apos;s nice to see how things are going and not be in the dark <lb/>All data to do with how my son is managing the condition/meds is important <lb/>We would like further understanding about how the trial was going, and what difference it&apos;s made to our child as well as the rest <lb/>of the children <lb/>To understand the clinical help VBP15 provided <lb/>We would like further understanding about how the trial was going, and what difference it&apos;s made to our child as well as the rest <lb/>of the children <lb/>To see actual data of improvement and/ or progression is important. Data helps you to understand if treatment works or not. <lb/>Just to see how our son is doing. We are hopeful he is doing better because if the drug and seeing the results gives us more <lb/>hope. <lb/>Physician concerns of a sponsor returning participant-level data to directly to trial participants. <lb/>Supportive <lb/>after trial is finished, data should be shared <lb/>No comments <lb/>Supportive with reservations <lb/>about timing of delivery <lb/>I agree, but it needs to be done in a thoughtful manner, properly contextualized. At the end of <lb/>the trial, all data should be returned to families. However, on a week by week basis during the <lb/>trial, I don&apos;t favor providing results to individual families <lb/>Supportive, with reservations <lb/>about delivery outside of the <lb/>healthcare or investigative team <lb/>and interpretation of data <lb/>What&apos;s meant by &apos;clinical trial data&apos;? I don&apos;t think getting e.g., ECG, echo or MRI data is <lb/>very useful and even some of the functional or strength measurements don&apos;t mean much <lb/>to a family. It&apos;s a nice option for a family to see clinical trial data, but it would probably be <lb/>more meaningful to provide them through a healthcare professional, either a doctor or a <lb/>physiotherapist. <lb/>Has to go through PI, SI and/or site staff <lb/>Not to disagree with this objective, but to raise the concern that the PI/treating physician for <lb/>the participant could be blind-sided by the parent contacting the office and requesting an <lb/>urgent discussion with the physician over an abnormal lab result. How to educate parents on <lb/>labs/biomarkers/tests that are predicted to be abnormal (due to having DMD)? The poster <lb/>does not go into this in any detail. <lb/>Interpreting the data and put the individual data in the context of the study results and of a <lb/>progressive disease might not be easy for all families and can create some false judgement <lb/>and/or anxiety. It creates some &quot;inequality&quot; as proactive and well informed families are more <lb/>likely to ask for the data <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

        <page>7 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

        <body>site staff, institutional overhead costs associated with site <lb/>contracts, and (models 2 and 4) the cost of participant <lb/>travel to and stay near the clinical trial site for in-person <lb/>return of clinical trial data. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>We carried out a centralised return of both participant-<lb/>level and aggregated clinical trial data to parents of chil-<lb/>dren in an open-label dose-ranging study of vamorolone. <lb/>Key to our approach was the efficient navigation of <lb/>human subjects oversight, where we received a single-<lb/>centralised ethical approval for patients worldwide to <lb/>contact the sponsor to request the clinical trial data on <lb/>their child. Our method of alerting patient families of <lb/>this return of results project was through stakeholder <lb/>foundations in the six countries in which the clinical trial <lb/>was being conducted (US, UK, Canada, Israel, Australia <lb/>and Sweden). As the parents were contacting the sponsor <lb/>directly to request information on their own child, the <lb/>ethical committee felt that it was adequate to remotely <lb/>consent parents (with a translator if needed), and that the <lb/>study was &apos;expedited with no requirement for continuing <lb/>review,&quot; much as other survey-type research projects. <lb/>Figure 4 Physician attitudes towards returning clinical trial <lb/>data to participating families. Inner pie: physician agreement <lb/>with concept of sponsor returning individual data directly to <lb/>participants. Outer donut: physician perception of importance <lb/>families place on receiving individual trial results. <lb/>Table 2 Real or predicted costs associated with different return of participant-level data to clinical trial participants <lb/>Current model <lb/>Model 2 <lb/>Model 3 <lb/>Model 4 <lb/>Sponsor-managed, <lb/>centralised return <lb/>of participant-<lb/>level data to <lb/>participants <lb/>New IRB+ contract <lb/>at each trial site for <lb/>the return of data, <lb/>inclusive of on-<lb/>site visit of family <lb/>(standalone study) <lb/>New IRB+ <lb/>contract at <lb/>each site to <lb/>return data to <lb/>participants, <lb/>with remote <lb/>delivery of <lb/>information <lb/>(standalone <lb/>study) <lb/>Return of data <lb/>included in original <lb/>clinical trial <lb/>contract (part of <lb/>original IRB); extend <lb/>site contract by 2 <lb/>years for return of <lb/>data, on-site visit. <lb/>(included in initial <lb/>protocol) <lb/>Sponsor costs (US$) <lb/>Fixed costs of data management for <lb/>return of results <lb/>$78 585 <lb/>$78 585 <lb/>$78 585 <lb/>$78 585 <lb/>Central IRB/ethics (sponsor) <lb/>$7586 <lb/>Clinical site costs <lb/>Site IRB/ethics <lb/>0 <lb/>$36 900 <lb/>$36 900 <lb/>0 <lb/>Annual IRB renewal Models 2,3: 4 <lb/>years <lb/>Model 4: 2 years* <lb/>0 <lb/>$33 580 <lb/>$33 580 <lb/>$18 190 <lb/>Scheduling/coordinating date entry/ <lb/>query <lb/>0 <lb/>$2070 <lb/>0 <lb/>$2070 <lb/>Investigator time <lb/>0 <lb/>$4830 <lb/>$4830 <lb/>$4830 <lb/>Travel <lb/>0 <lb/>$11 323 <lb/>0 <lb/>$11 323 <lb/>Overhead <lb/>0 <lb/>$24 762 <lb/>$21 040 <lb/>$9825 <lb/>Total <lb/>$86 171.00 <lb/>$192 050.00 <lb/>$174 935.00 <lb/>$124 823.00 <lb/>*The reduced number of years (2 years) in model 4 is assuming that the IRB costs of the parent clinical trial would be borne by the parent <lb/>study (not the return of results portion of the study), but the parent study would need to be kept open an additional 2 years. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

        <page>8 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

        <body>The more typical alternative approach of returning clin-<lb/>ical trial data to participants is through collaborating clin-<lb/>ical trial sites via their healthcare providers. This would <lb/>require (in our case) local clinical site ethics approval <lb/>(12 sites in 6 countries), as well as contracts between the <lb/>sponsor and each site to carry out the return of results. <lb/>Our approach of implementing direct contact between <lb/>the parents contacting the sponsor greatly simplified the <lb/>otherwise complex challenge of returning patient-level <lb/>clinical trial data to clinical trial participants. Critical to <lb/>our approach is that the parents initiate contact with the <lb/>sponsor, not the sponsor with parents. Also central to <lb/>our approach is a &apos;data/information firewall&apos; within the <lb/>sponsor, where only a single employee had direct contact <lb/>with families, and no deidentifying information was <lb/>relayed to any other employee of the sponsor. Addition-<lb/>ally, an interpreter in the parents&apos; native language was <lb/>always made available, and consent forms were translated <lb/>to the parents&apos; native language. <lb/>We queried the attitudes of participating parents both <lb/>before the return of results, to learn what type of infor-<lb/>mation they felt was important, and how they would like <lb/>these data to be provided to them. In general, parents <lb/>expressed a strong desire for as much information <lb/>as possible, in all formats offered (individual, aggre-<lb/>gate; tabular, graphical). Thus, tailoring of information <lb/>provided to the families was not needed; all families <lb/>expressed a desire for all information offered. In returning <lb/>the data to participants&apos; parents, we instructed that this <lb/>was clinical research data and not generally relevant to <lb/>the clinical care of their child. Also, we provided tutorials <lb/>on motor outcome measures, and interpretation of clin-<lb/>ical laboratory and exploratory biomarker data. Partici-<lb/>pant families who participated in the return of results <lb/>directly by the sponsor expressed overall satisfaction with <lb/>all aspects, including the process, the amount of informa-<lb/>tion received, the graphical and tabular presentation, the <lb/>presentation of both individual and aggregate data, and <lb/>the manner in which it was received (password protected <lb/>and encrypted USB memory stick mailed directly to the <lb/>family). We note that our approach included two-factor <lb/>authentication (direct mail, separate password commu-<lb/>nication), which is important to maintain privacy and <lb/>confidentiality. <lb/>We found that, of the sample of parents who requested <lb/>their child&apos;s data, most would prefer to obtain the data <lb/>directly from the sponsor, or were indifferent to whether <lb/>they obtained data from the sponsor or their physician. <lb/>None of the parents indicated a strong preference for <lb/>obtaining the clinical trial data from their physician. This <lb/>finding supports our approach to providing individual-<lb/>level data directly from the sponsor. All participants felt <lb/>that return of data was quite important to them, and <lb/>parents showed a variable degree of sharing of informa-<lb/>tion with family, friends, teachers and their physicians. <lb/>Physician respondents unanimously acknowledged <lb/>the importance that families place on return of clinical <lb/>trial data. Some had reservations about return of results <lb/>without involving clinicians or the clinical site investiga-<lb/>tors. When physician responses were stratified by North <lb/>America versus Europe, North American physicians <lb/>were more accepting of the direct return of data partici-<lb/>pants by the sponsor (p=0.065; Wilcoxon rank-sum test), <lb/>although numbers were small and difference not signif-<lb/>icant (North American physicians n=6; European n=3). <lb/>These concerns, and potential cultural differences in <lb/>acceptance by physicians, will need to be further explored <lb/>and addressed in future return of results approaches. <lb/>For parents of children with DMD, participation in <lb/>clinical research is a balance of hope and expectations. <lb/>Parents of children with DMD report a feeling of invest-<lb/>ment in the trial. 13 In one study, at the termination of a <lb/>trial in DMD, parents wished for more communication <lb/>from the sponsor. Some parents felt that when the trial <lb/>ended, the partnership between the parent and sponsor <lb/>&apos;broke down&apos; and that the sponsor no longer valued <lb/>them. 14 Parents describe the significant burdens that <lb/>participation in clinical trials places on their families. 15 <lb/>In keeping with the ethical principles of beneficence <lb/>and autonomy, return of data demonstrates respect for <lb/>participants&apos; ownership of their health data, encour-<lb/>ages family engagement and fosters increased trust of <lb/>researchers by patients who are clinical trial participants <lb/>and their families. Operationally, there is a disconnect, as <lb/>the clinical trial site personnel and physician have direct <lb/>contact and responsibility for care for the patient, but <lb/>typically do not have access to all of the patient&apos;s data. <lb/>Direct industry-patient interaction for returning indi-<lb/>vidual results after trial completion, without the study <lb/>site/physician interface, has not been common histori-<lb/>cally due to potential for perceived loss of patient confi-<lb/>dentiality, concerns about results interpretation and the <lb/>potential for clinical follow-up for actionable findings <lb/>if clinicians are not involved, and possible conflict of <lb/>interest. However, our approach demonstrates that this <lb/>can be achieved by having an internal coordinator who <lb/>is not involved in the study conduct, keeps records confi-<lb/>dential and is under a &apos;firewall&apos; of confidentiality when it <lb/>comes to the study. Another approach could be to use a <lb/>third party vendor, though this would increase costs and <lb/>complexity. Sponsors may perceive the return of results to <lb/>trial participants as a risk to the participant and the trial, <lb/>or at least as a distraction to the sponsor, adding addi-<lb/>tional time and cost to the drug development process. We <lb/>have demonstrated that this can be a relatively straightfor-<lb/>ward process that is not costly and can be done after study <lb/>completion, and public disclosure of trial data. Alterna-<lb/>tive models of return of results require contracts between <lb/>the sponsor and the participating clinical trial sites, and <lb/>this adds considerably to the costs and administrative <lb/>complexity (table 2). <lb/>While the current proof-of-concept study is admittedly <lb/>quite small, we envision that such return of results could <lb/>be scaled up without additional barriers. Assuming a <lb/>large multinational phase 3 trial, either the sponsor or <lb/>a contract research organisation would receive central <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

        <page>9 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

        <body>ethics approval for return of results to trial partici-<lb/>pants requesting the data (as we have done here). This <lb/>participant-initiated request would permit deidentifica-<lb/>tion of the subject in the data, and direct return of the <lb/>data to the participant. The sponsor could either do this <lb/>internally with appropriate GDPR firewall (as we have <lb/>done), or could contract a third party to carry out the <lb/>process at arm&apos;s length. <lb/>Not all clinical trial data are relevant to a patient&apos;s <lb/>medical care, and indeed may not add value or be accept-<lb/>able to add to the participant&apos;s electronic medical health <lb/>record. While clinical trial data are personal health data, <lb/>it likely has different value to a clinical trial participant <lb/>compared with their own electronic medical health <lb/>record. The National Academies of Science (NAS), <lb/>Engineering, and Medicine convened a committee that <lb/>published &apos;Returning Individual Research Results to <lb/>Participants: Guidance for a New Research Paradigm&apos;, <lb/>a process-oriented approach to return of results that <lb/>considers value to the participants, feasibility of return and <lb/>quality of research results. 16 The NAS committee formu-<lb/>lated six principles to help guide deliberations and devel-<lb/>opment of recommendations presented in their report. <lb/>One principle was that the potential value of returning <lb/>individual research results must be carefully considered <lb/>along with the trade-offs for research participants, investi-<lb/>gators, research institutions and society. According to the <lb/>committee, &apos;value&apos; should consider the perspective of the <lb/>participant (or parent) and might entail clinical utility <lb/>or personal utility, as well as personal meaning. Thus, the <lb/>value of a result is not necessarily tied to its use, as viewed solely <lb/>through the eyes of the clinician or sponsor. DMD parents and <lb/>advocacy groups in the USA and European Union clearly <lb/>indicate that they value provision of individual and aggre-<lb/>gate clinical trial results to the study participant. <lb/>Recent reviews of efforts to return clinical trial data to <lb/>participants have found that these are relatively rare and <lb/>typically only include summarised or aggregate results <lb/>(not personal participant-level data). Bruhn et al 17 studied <lb/>clinical trials in a period from January 2008 to August <lb/>2019 and identified 33 studies involving 12 700 partici-<lb/>pants that explored returning results to trial participants, <lb/>and found that aggregate data were returned, without <lb/>evaluation of what information trial participants wished <lb/>to receive. 17 Of the 33 studies reviewed, only 2 returned <lb/>individual data to the participant, and for both of these <lb/>only &apos;unblinding&apos; was reported to the participant (not <lb/>participant-level clinical and laboratory data). A single <lb/>study provided both individual and aggregate results. <lb/>Also, the authors noted that there was a general lack of <lb/>&apos;actively including patients or the public as partners in <lb/>the development of the dissemination of results&apos;. The <lb/>authors noted that a weakness of their study was relying on <lb/>literature reports, and this likely underestimated dissem-<lb/>ination efforts. Shroter et al (2019) took an approach of <lb/>surveying authors of published clinical trials to ascertain <lb/>efforts to return clinical trial results to clinical trial partic-<lb/>ipants. 18 19 Questionnaires were emailed to 19 321 authors <lb/>and analysed 1818 responses of authors that had enrolled <lb/>individual patients. Of these, 498 (27%) had dissemi-<lb/>nated results to trial participants, but most were aggre-<lb/>gate data (academic reports, lay reports). Of the 164 <lb/>(33%) reporting that individualised data were returned, <lb/>the type of individualised data was not specified. Raza et <lb/>al (2019) queried the UK&apos;s research permissions system <lb/>for phase III trials for a 6-year period (2012-2017 inclu-<lb/>sive) and found that of the 1404 phase III trials studied, <lb/>88% reported the intention to disseminate results to <lb/>trial participants. 20 However, only 10 of the End of Study <lb/>reports cited dissemination activities, and 6 of these were <lb/>through a lay summary or letter. <lb/>The primary limitation of our study was the small number <lb/>of families (n=19) and their physicians (n=10) that partic-<lb/>ipated in this study. The clinical trial studied was an open-<lb/>label phase 2a dose-ranging and dose-finding study of 48 <lb/>participants (young children with a rare genetic muscle <lb/>disease; DMD), and future studies should extend our <lb/>approach to larger, double-blind placebo-controlled trials <lb/>in more common disorders (eg, phase 3). Future studies <lb/>will also need to address potential cultural differences in <lb/>attitudes of both families and their physicians based on <lb/>country of origin, or other factors. Another limitation of <lb/>our approach is the effectiveness of outreach (advertise-<lb/>ment) to the parents of participating children. We had a <lb/>40% participation rate (19/48). We do not know if the <lb/>60% that did not participate was because they did not <lb/>hear of the study (eg, ineffective outreach to them), or <lb/>if they did not wish to participate. Our ethics approval <lb/>included an &apos;informational flyer&apos; that was meant to be <lb/>distributed to clinical trial sites and provided to patient <lb/>families, but sites were uncomfortable with distributing <lb/>this flyer without their own institutional ethics approval. <lb/>If other sponsors wish to take our centralised approach, <lb/>we advise that the informational flyer for direct sponsor <lb/>return of data be provided to sites for distribution to trial <lb/>participants at initial contracting and ethics review and <lb/>be handed to patients at initial enrolment in the clinical <lb/>trial, and/or exit from the trial. <lb/>In conclusion, there is a strong desire for clinical trial <lb/>participants to receive patient-level and aggregate returns <lb/>of clinical trial data to them. Their treating physicians, <lb/>and stakeholder foundations all uniformly acknowledge <lb/>the importance of return of results to trial participants. <lb/>Despite this need, it is largely unmet due to fundamental <lb/>barriers (pragmatic, financial, organisational, confidenti-<lb/>ality and ethics). We have piloted a simplified return of <lb/>results process that removes most barriers, and we found <lb/>that trial participants (parents of children in a trial) were <lb/>highly satisfied with this novel process, and their treating <lb/>physicians were also generally satisfied while expressing <lb/>some reservations. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements The authors thank the foundations that provided input, <lb/>advertised this study, and enabled recruitment of participants (Muscular Dystrophy <lb/>Association, Parent Project Muscular Dystrophy, World Duchenne Organisation, <lb/>Foundation to Eradicate Duchenne, Little Steps Association). The authors would also <lb/>like to extend thanks to the following individuals who offered advice on approach <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

        <page>10 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Hoffman E, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e080097. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

        <div type="annex">and survey questions: Edward Smith, MD, John van den Anker MD PhD, Michela <lb/>Guglieri MD. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Contributors EH is the author responsible for the overall content as the guarantor, <lb/>and contributed substantially to concept and study design and drafted the manuscript. <lb/>SG contributed substantially to study design, data acquisition and interpretation, and <lb/>reviewed the manuscript critically. RK contributed substantially to data acquisition and <lb/>interpretation and reviewed the manuscript critically. WT contributed substantially to <lb/>data interpretation and presentation and reviewed the manuscript critically. HP and PC <lb/>contributed substantially to concept and study design and reviewed the manuscript <lb/>critically. UD contributed substantially to data interpretation and presentation and <lb/>reviewed the manuscript critically. LC contributed substantially to concept and study <lb/>design, data acquisition and interpretation and drafting of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Funding This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health (NIH) <lb/>(3R44NS095423-03S1). <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests UD received consultancy fees from ReveraGen Biopharma. <lb/>LC is currently an employee of Johnson &amp; Johnson, but the current work was <lb/>completed while she was an employee of ReveraGen BioPharma. HP was <lb/>contracted to provide expert insight into study design and interpretation of results. <lb/>EH, RK and SG are employees of ReveraGen BioPharma. EH, RK and LC are stock <lb/>holders in ReveraGen BioPharma. PC holds NIH, FDA and foundation grants on <lb/>vamorolone clinical trials with ReveraGen BioPharma. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Patient and public involvement Patients and/or the public were involved in the <lb/>design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. Refer to <lb/>the Methods section for further details. <lb/>Patient consent for publication Not applicable. <lb/>Ethics approval This study involves human participants and was approved by <lb/>Western IRB Sponsor: ReveraGen BioPharmaSponsor Pr #: VBP15-RORIRB, Pr #: <lb/>20192458IRB, Study #: 1266745. Participants gave informed consent to participate <lb/>in the study before taking part. <lb/>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability statement All data relevant to the study are included in the <lb/>article or uploaded as supplementary information. Not applicable. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has <lb/>not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been <lb/>peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those <lb/>of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and <lb/>responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content <lb/>includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability <lb/>of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, <lb/>terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error <lb/>and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise. <lb/></div>

        <front>Open access This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which <lb/>permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, <lb/>and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use <lb/>is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/. <lb/>ORCID iD <lb/>Eric Hoffman http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6470-5139 <lb/></front>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 Majumder MA, Guerrini CJ, Bollinger JM, et al. Sharing data under <lb/>the 21st century cures act. Genetics in Medicine 2017;19:1289-94. <lb/>2 Jorgenson LA, Wolinetz CD, Collins FS. Incentivizing a new culture of <lb/>data stewardship: the NIH policy for data management and sharing. <lb/>JAMA 2021;326:2259-60. <lb/>3 Karpen SR, White JK, Mullin AP, et al. Effective data sharing as a <lb/>conduit for advancing medical product development. Ther Innov <lb/>Regul Sci 2021;55:591-600. <lb/>4 Denton N, Molloy M, Charleston S, et al. Data silos are undermining <lb/>drug development and failing rare disease patients. Orphanet J Rare <lb/>Dis 2021;16:161. <lb/>5 Mello MM, Lieou V, Goodman SN. Clinical trial participants&apos; <lb/>views of the risks and benefits of data sharing. N Engl J Med <lb/>2018;378:2202-11. <lb/>6 Kalkman S, van Delden J, Banerjee A, et al. Patients&apos; and public <lb/>views and attitudes towards the sharing of health data for <lb/>research: a narrative review of the empirical evidence. J Med Ethics <lb/>2022;48:3-13. <lb/>7 Marelli L, Lievevrouw E, Van Hoyweghen I. Fit for purpose? The <lb/>GDPR and the governance of European Digital health. Policy Studies <lb/>2020;41:447-67. <lb/>8 Wilkinson MD, Dumontier M, Aalbersberg IJJ, et al. The FAIR guiding <lb/>principles for scientific data management and stewardship. Sci Data <lb/>2016;3:160018. <lb/>9 van Lin N, Paliouras G, Vroom E, et al. How patient organizations <lb/>can drive FAIR data efforts to facilitate research and health care: a <lb/>report of the virtual second International meeting on Duchenne data <lb/>sharing, March 3, 2021. J Neuromuscul Dis 2021;8:1097-108. <lb/>10 South A, Joharatnam-Hogan N, Purvis C, et al. Testing approaches <lb/>to sharing trial results with participants: the show RESPECT <lb/>cluster randomised, factorial, mixed methods trial. PLoS Med <lb/>2021;18:e1003798. <lb/>11 Conklin LS, Damsker JM, Hoffman EP, et al. Phase IIa trial in <lb/>Duchenne muscular dystrophy shows Vamorolone is a first-in-class <lb/>dissociative steroidal anti-inflammatory drug. Pharmacological <lb/>Research 2018;136:140-50. <lb/>12 Hoffman EP, Schwartz BD, Mengle-Gaw LJ, et al. Vamorolone trial in <lb/>Duchenne muscular dystrophy shows dose-related improvement of <lb/>muscle function. Neurology 2019;93:e1312-23. <lb/>13 Peay HL, Biesecker BB, Wilfond BS, et al. Barriers and facilitators <lb/>to clinical trial participation among parents of children with pediatric <lb/>neuromuscular disorders. Clinical Trials 2018;15:139-48. <lb/>14 Peay HL, Tibben A, Fisher T, et al. Expectations and experiences of <lb/>investigators and parents involved in a clinical trial for Duchenne/ <lb/>Becker muscular dystrophy. Clinical Trials 2014;11:77-85. <lb/>15 Franson T, Kinnett K, Cripe TP. Unique burdens of pediatric clinical <lb/>trials in Duchenne muscular dystrophy, April 20-21, 2017, Bethesda, <lb/>Maryland, USA. Ther Innov Regul Sci 2019;53:154-63. <lb/>16 National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine; Health <lb/>and Medicine Division; Board on Health Sciences Policy; Committee <lb/>on the Return of Individual-Specific Research Results Generated <lb/>in Research Laboratories. Returning individual research results to <lb/>participants: guidance for a new research paradigm. Washington <lb/>(DC): National Academies Press (US), 2018. <lb/>17 Bruhn H, Cowan E-J, Campbell MK, et al. Providing trial results to <lb/>participants in phase III pragmatic effectiveness RCTs: a scoping <lb/>review. Trials 2021;22:361. <lb/>18 Schroter S, Price A, Malički M, et al. Frequency and format of clinical <lb/>trial results dissemination to patients: a survey of authors of trials <lb/>indexed in PubMed. BMJ Open 2019;9:e032701. <lb/>19 Taylor J. Reporting research findings to participants is an ethical <lb/>imperative. BMJ 2019:l6324. <lb/>20 Raza MZ, Bruhn H, Gillies K. Dissemination of trial results to <lb/>participants in phase III pragmatic clinical trials: an audit of trial <lb/>investigators intentions. BMJ Open 2020;10:e035730. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>23 March 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-080097 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as </note>


	</text>

</TEI>