<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>R E S E A R C H <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Mesenchymal stem cell-derived <lb/>extracellular vesicles attenuate influenza <lb/>virus-induced acute lung injury in a pig <lb/>model <lb/>Mahesh Khatri 1* , Levi Arthur Richardson 1 and Tea Meulia 2 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: Mesenchymal stem (stromal) cells (MSCs) mediate their immunoregulatory and tissue repair functions <lb/>by secreting paracrine factors, including extracellular vesicles (EVs). In several animal models of human diseases, <lb/>MSC-EVs mimic the beneficial effects of MSCs. Influenza viruses cause annual outbreaks of acute respiratory illness <lb/>resulting in significant mortality and morbidity. Influenza viruses constantly evolve, thus generating drug-resistant <lb/>strains and rendering current vaccines less effective against the newly generated strains. Therefore, new therapies <lb/>that can control virus replication and the inflammatory response of the host are needed. The objective of this study <lb/>was to examine if MSC-EV treatment can attenuate influenza virus-induced acute lung injury in a preclinical model. <lb/>Methods: We isolated EVs from swine bone marrow-derived MSCs. Morphology of MSC-EVs was determined by <lb/>electron microscopy and expression of mesenchymal markers was examined by flow cytometry. Next, we examined <lb/>the anti-influenza activity of MSC-EVs in vitro in lung epithelial cells and anti-viral and immunomodulatory <lb/>properties in vivo in a pig model of influenza virus. <lb/>Results: MSC-EVs were isolated from MSC-conditioned medium by ultracentrifugation. MSC-EVs were round-shaped <lb/>and, similarly to MSCs, expressed mesenchymal markers and lacked the expression of swine leukocyte antigens I and II. <lb/>Incubation of PKH-26-labeled EVs with lung epithelial cells revealed that MSC-EVs incorporated into the epithelial cells. <lb/>Next, we examined the anti-influenza and anti-inflammatory properties of MSC-EVs. MSC-EVs inhibited the <lb/>hemagglutination activity of avian, swine, and human influenza viruses at concentrations of 1.25-5 μg/ml. <lb/>MSC-EVs inhibited influenza virus replication and virus-induced apoptosis in lung epithelial cells. The anti-<lb/>influenza activity of MSC-EVs was due to transfer of RNAs from EVs to epithelial cells since pre-incubation of <lb/>MSC-EVs with RNase enzyme abrogated the anti-influenza activity of MSC-EVs. In a pig model of influenza virus, <lb/>intratracheal administration of MSC-EVs 12 h after influenza virus infection significantly reduced virus shedding in the <lb/>nasal swabs, influenza virus replication in the lungs, and virus-induced production of proinflammatory cytokines in the <lb/>lungs of influenza-infected pigs. The histopathological findings revealed that MSC-EVs alleviated influenza virus-induced <lb/>lung lesions in pigs. <lb/>(Continued on next page) <lb/>* Correspondence: khatri.14@osu.edu <lb/>1 <lb/>Food Animal Health Research Program, Ohio Agricultural Research and <lb/>Development Center, The Ohio State University, 1680 Madison Avenue, <lb/>Wooster, OH 44691, USA <lb/>Full list of author information is available at the end of the article <lb/>© The Author(s). 2018 Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 <lb/>International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to <lb/>the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated. <lb/>Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/>DOI 10.1186/s13287-018-0774-8 <lb/>(Continued from previous page) <lb/>Conclusions: Our data demonstrated in a relevant preclinical large animal model of influenza virus that MSC-EVs <lb/>possessed anti-influenza and anti-inflammatory properties and that EVs may be used as cell-free therapy for influenza <lb/>in humans. <lb/>Keywords: Mesenchymal stem cells, Extracellular vesicles, Influenza, Acute lung injury, Stem cell therapy, Large animal <lb/>model <lb/></front>

			<body>Background <lb/>Influenza A viruses (IAV) cause an acute respiratory <lb/>disease in humans and animals. Annual outbreaks and <lb/>occasional pandemics of influenza result in millions of <lb/>deaths, suffering, and economic losses. In the US alone, <lb/>since 2010 influenza viruses have caused 140,000-710,000 <lb/>hospitalizations resulting in 12,000-56,000 deaths annu-<lb/>ally (https://www.cdc.gov/flu/about/disease/burden.htm). <lb/>The elderly, infants, and people with underlying condi-<lb/>tions are at high risk of influenza-associated mortality. In <lb/>addition to seasonal and pandemic viruses, highly patho-<lb/>genic avian influenza (HPAI) H5N1 virus has been repeat-<lb/>edly transmitted directly from avian species to humans. In <lb/>humans, H5N1 virus is associated with severe disease <lb/>resulting in multi-organ failure and high mortality rates <lb/>[1, 2]. As of 30 October 2017, HPAI H5N1 viruses have <lb/>caused 860 human infections resulting in 454 deaths since <lb/>2003 (http://www.who.int/influenza/human_animal_inter-<lb/>face/2017_10_30_tableH5N1.pdf?ua = 1) Severe cases of in-<lb/>fluenza cause significant mortality due to their ability to <lb/>induce cytokine-mediated immune lung pathology with fea-<lb/>tures of moderate to severe acute respiratory distress syn-<lb/>drome (ARDS) [3]. <lb/>Influenza virus infections are generally controlled by <lb/>annual vaccination. However, these vaccines provide <lb/>limited protection against new reassortants which are <lb/>genetically different from the vaccine virus. In the event <lb/>of a pandemic, generation of a new vaccine containing <lb/>circulating viruses takes approximately 6 months. More-<lb/>over, influenza viruses continually undergo mutations <lb/>resulting in the generation of new viral strains that can <lb/>become resistant to currently available antiviral drugs. <lb/>Thus, alternative therapies capable of inhibiting influ-<lb/>enza virus replication and attenuating the inflammatory <lb/>response of the host are needed. <lb/>Mesenchymal stem (stromal) cells (MSCs) are mul-<lb/>tipotent cells that were first identified in bone mar-<lb/>row (BM) as plastic adherent fibroblast-like cells. <lb/>MSCs possess multilineage differentiation, and immu-<lb/>nomodulatory and tissue repair properties [4]. Due to <lb/>these properties MSCs are attractive as cellular ther-<lb/>apy for inflammatory and autoimmune diseases, and <lb/>regenerative medicine. Several studies of ARDS in <lb/>animal models have shown beneficial effects of MSC <lb/>administration, and clinical trials have shown the <lb/>feasibility of MSC administration in patients with <lb/>ARDS [5-7]. Therapeutic studies are underway. Simi-<lb/>larly to ARDS, severe influenza virus infections in <lb/>humans and animal models show acute inflammatory <lb/>response and lung damage [8]. As MSCs suppress <lb/>inflammation and have tissue repair and regenerative <lb/>ability, ARDS and influenza are appropriate targets <lb/>for MSC therapy. However, MSC therapy in mice <lb/>models of influenza show inconsistent results [9-12]. <lb/>Also, we and others have shown that influenza virus <lb/>infects MSCs and that infection may alter the <lb/>immunoregulatory and differentiation properties of <lb/>MSCs [13-15]. <lb/>Several studies indicated that the beneficial actions <lb/>of MSCs are due to release of paracrine factors since <lb/>only a few transplanted MSCs engraft at the site of <lb/>injury [16]. Recently, extracellular vesicles (EVs) that <lb/>include exosomes (Exo) which are released from <lb/>multivesicular bodies and microvesicles (MVs) that <lb/>are shed from the cell surface, and apoptotic bodies <lb/>were identified in MSC secretions [17]. In this paper <lb/>EVs, Exo, and MVs will be collectively referred to as <lb/>EVs. MSC-derived EVs have similar expression of <lb/>surface molecules and contain MSC-specific proteins, <lb/>mRNAs, microRNAs (miRNAs), organelles, and lipids <lb/>[18-20]. In diseased tissue, MSC-EVs interact with <lb/>injured cells and transfer proteins, mRNA, and bio-<lb/>active lipids from MSCs to injured cells resulting in <lb/>tissue repair [21, 22]. In rodent models, these EVs <lb/>were as therapeutically efficacious as MSCs in E. coli <lb/>endotoxin-induced acute lung injury (ALI) and E. <lb/>coli-induced severe pneumonia in mice [20, 23]. <lb/>Due to their close similarity in anatomy, physiology, <lb/>and immunology to humans, pigs are used as a large <lb/>animal preclinical model for several human diseases, <lb/>including respiratory diseases and regenerative medi-<lb/>cine [24, 25]. In addition, pigs are naturally infected <lb/>with influenza virus as the respiratory epithelium of <lb/>pigs expresses receptors utilized by avian and mam-<lb/>malian influenza viruses [26]. Influenza virus patho-<lb/>genesis and clinical signs in pigs are also similar to <lb/>those observed in humans. Thus, pigs are a suitable <lb/>large animal model to study human influenza virus <lb/>pathogenesis and to test the efficacy of therapeutics <lb/>including MSCs or their derivatives for influenza. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Methods <lb/>Isolation of MSCs and MSC-derived EVs <lb/>MSCs from femur bones of 2-to 6-week-old commercial <lb/>pigs were isolated as described previously [27, 28]. <lb/>Briefly, the tip of each bone was removed and the <lb/>marrow was harvested by inserting a syringe needle into <lb/>one end of the bone and flushing with Dulbecco&apos;s <lb/>modified Eagle&apos;s medium (DMEM; Gibco). The BM cells <lb/>were filtered through a 70-μm nylon mesh filter (BD, <lb/>Falcon, USA) and mononuclear cells were obtained by <lb/>density gradient centrifugation over Ficoll-Hypaque. <lb/>Cells (1-5 × 10 5 /cm 2 ) were plated in 75-cm 2 cell culture <lb/>flasks in DMEM containing 10% fetal bovine serum <lb/>(FBS; Gibco) and 1% antibiotic solution (Gibco) (C-<lb/>DMEM). Cultures were incubated at 37 °C in a humidi-<lb/>fied atmosphere containing 95% air and 5% CO 2 . The <lb/>nonadherent cells were removed after 72 h of culture <lb/>and cells were passaged when they were 90% confluent <lb/>by treating them with 0.25% trypsin containing 0.02% <lb/>EDTA. MSCs passaged between three and five times <lb/>were used for the generation of MSC-EVs for in vitro <lb/>and in vivo experiments. For the isolation of MSC-EVs, <lb/>MSCs were cultured in C-DMEM in T225 flasks and <lb/>MSC-EVs were isolated as previously described [23, 29, <lb/>30]. Briefly, cells when 80% confluent were washed with <lb/>serum-free DMEM and cultured in DMEM containing <lb/>0.5% bovine serum albumin. After 48 h, conditioned <lb/>medium (CM) from MSC cultures was collected and <lb/>centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 20 min to remove the cellu-<lb/>lar debris. Next, CM was ultracentrifuged at 25,000 rpm <lb/>for 70 min at 4 °C. The EV pellet was washed with <lb/>DMEM by ultracentrifugation at 25,000 rpm for 70 min <lb/>at 4 °C. The EV pellet was then suspended in phosphate-<lb/>buffered saline (PBS; 10 μl PBS/million MSCs) and <lb/>further dilutions were made in serum-free DMEM. The <lb/>protein content of EVs was determined by micro-<lb/>bicinchoninic acid protein assay kit (Thermofisher Sci-<lb/>entific). MSC-EV RNA was isolated using the RNAeasy <lb/>kit (Qiagen) and RNA concentration was determined by <lb/>NanoDrop (Thermofisher Scientific). <lb/>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) <lb/>EVs (10 μl) were applied to a formvar/carbon-coated <lb/>grid for 5 min; after blotting, the grid was stained with <lb/>2% aqueous uranyl acetate for 1 min. After blotting, the <lb/>grids were air-dried and examined under TEM (HITA-<lb/>CHI, H-7500, Japan). <lb/>Flow cytometry <lb/>MSCs and EVs were examined for surface expression of <lb/>mesenchymal markers and swine leukocyte antigen <lb/>(SLA)-I and SLA-II, and EVs were also examined for EV <lb/>markers (CD9, CD63, and CD81) by flow cytometry as <lb/>described previously [31]. EVs (30 μg in 50 μl PBS) were <lb/>incubated with 10 μl of 4-μm diameter aldehyde/sulfate <lb/>latex beads for 15 min at room temperature followed by <lb/>the addition of 1 ml PBS and incubation was further <lb/>continued for 2 h with gentle shaking. The reaction was <lb/>stopped by incubation for 30 min in 100 mM glycine. <lb/>MSCs were detached by treatment with 0.25% trypsin-<lb/>EDTA and single cell suspensions of MSC and EV-<lb/>coated beads were stained with the following primary <lb/>antibodies: mouse anti-pig CD29, mouse anti-human <lb/>CD90 (BD Biosciences), mouse anti-pig CD44 and SLA-<lb/>I and SLA-II (VMRD). For the detection of EV markers, <lb/>EV-coated beads were stained with the following <lb/>primary antibodies cross-reactive with pig: mouse anti-<lb/>human CD9 (GeneTex), mouse anti-human CD63 (BD <lb/>Biosciences), and mouse anti-human CD81 (BD Biosci-<lb/>ences) for 20 min at 4 °C in dark. Cells and beads were <lb/>washed three times and incubated with secondary <lb/>antibodies conjugated with allophycocyanin or phyco-<lb/>erythrin for 30 min. Appropriate isotype and secondary <lb/>antibodies were used as controls for nonspecific binding. <lb/>Cells and beads were acquired by C6 flow cytometer <lb/>(BD Accuri Cytometers) and analyzed using CFlow® plus <lb/>Software (Accuri) as described previously [32]. <lb/>Incorporation of EVs in pig lung epithelial cells <lb/>We examined whether MSC-EVs had the ability to enter <lb/>cells using pig lung epithelial cells (MK1-OSU; LECs). <lb/>MK1-OSU is a spontaneously immortalized cell line <lb/>established in our laboratory. This cell line was derived <lb/>from the distal trachea and proximal lung tissue of a 5-<lb/>to 6-week-old pig. These cells express α2-3-and α2-6-<lb/>linked sialic acids (receptors for avian and mammalian <lb/>influenza viruses, respectively), and support the replica-<lb/>tion of swine, avian, and human-origin influenza viruses <lb/>(unpublished results). MSC-EVs were labeled using <lb/>PKH-26 Red Fluorescent Cell Linker Kit (Sigma-Aldrich) <lb/>as per the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. LECs cultured <lb/>overnight in a 24-well plate were incubated with labeled <lb/>MSC-EVs for 24 h at 37 °C. To confirm the internaliza-<lb/>tion of EVs inside the cells, the cell cytoplasm was <lb/>stained using polyclonal rabbit anti-human β-tubulin as <lb/>the primary antibody (Thermofisher Scientific) and <lb/>Alexa 488-conjugated goat anti-rabbit secondary anti-<lb/>body (Thermofisher Scientific). Cell nuclei were stained <lb/>with 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; Thermo-<lb/>fisher Scientific Life Sciences). The cells were examined <lb/>under a fluorescence microscope (Olympus, Japan). For <lb/>flow cytometry, a single cell suspension was obtained by <lb/>treating the cells with 0.25% trypsin-EDTA and washing <lb/>with PBS. Cells were acquired by C6 flow cytometer (BD <lb/>Accuri Cytometers) and incorporation of PKH-26 <lb/>labeled EVs in cells was analyzed by CFlow® plus Soft-<lb/>ware (Accuri). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Hemagglutination inhibition assay <lb/>The effect of MSC-EVs on the ability of influenza virus <lb/>to hemagglutinate red blood cells was examined by <lb/>hemagglutination inhibition assay. Two-fold dilutions of <lb/>MSC-EVs (starting from 10 μg/ml) in 25 μl volume were <lb/>mixed with 8 hemagglutination (HA) units of swine <lb/>(swine/TX/98; H3N2 and Swine/MN/08; H1N1), avian <lb/>(Gull/MD/1995; H9N5 and Chicken/NY/H7N2), and <lb/>human (Human/CA/09; H1N1) influenza viruses and <lb/>incubated for 20 min at 37 °C followed by the addition <lb/>of 50 μl 1% turkey red blood cell suspension. Plates were <lb/>incubated for 30 min at room temperature and the <lb/>concentration of MSC-EVs capable of inhibiting HA <lb/>activity of different influenza viruses was determined. <lb/>Effect of MSC-EVs on influenza virus replication and apop-<lb/>tosis in LECs <lb/>To examine the effect of MSC-EVs on influenza virus <lb/>replication, two sets of experiments were conducted. <lb/>In the first set, we incubated swine/MN/08; H1N1 <lb/>(SwIV) equivalent to MOI 1 with 10 μg/ml MSC-EVs <lb/>for 20 min at room temperature. LECs cultured over-<lb/>night were then infected with SwIV alone or virus-<lb/>MSC-EV mixture for 1 h at 37 °C. Cells were washed <lb/>with PBS and were incubated with or without MSC-<lb/>EVs. After 8 h, influenza virus nucleoprotein (NP) <lb/>was detected using anti-NP monoclonal antibody in <lb/>an immunofluorescence assay (IFA). Cells expressing <lb/>NP protein were counted in at least five microscopic <lb/>fields and virus titers in culture supernatants were de-<lb/>termined by titration in MDCK cells [8]. At 24 h <lb/>after infection, apoptotic cells were detected by <lb/>TUNEL assay using ApopTag Fluorescein Apoptosis <lb/>Detection Kit (EMD Millipore). Apoptotic cells were <lb/>counted in five microscopic fields and data are <lb/>expressed as mean ± SD number of apoptotic cells/ <lb/>microscopic field. <lb/>In the second set of experiment, LECs were infected <lb/>with SwIV at an MOI 1 for 1 h at 37 °C, followed by <lb/>washing with PBS, and LECs were incubated with or <lb/>without MSC-EVs for 8 h. Influenza-infected cells <lb/>were detected by the expression of NP by IFA. In <lb/>some experiments, MSC-EVs were treated with 1 U/ <lb/>ml RNase for 1 h at 37 °C, 1 U/ml RNase was then <lb/>added to stop the reaction and MSC-EVs were <lb/>washed by ultracentrifugation [29]. <lb/>Immunofluorescence assay <lb/>LECs were washed with PBS and fixed with 80% <lb/>acetone for 10 min at -20 °C. The expression of <lb/>influenza virus NP in infected cells was detected <lb/>using mouse anti-NP antibody as a primary antibody <lb/>and Alexa 488-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG as a <lb/>secondary antibody. Nuclei were stained with DAPI <lb/>(Thermofisher Scientific Life Sciences). <lb/>Animals <lb/>Five-week-old conventional large White-Duroc cross-<lb/>bred pigs were obtained from the OSU herd. Mainten-<lb/>ance of pigs and all experimental procedures were <lb/>conducted in accordance with the guidelines of the Insti-<lb/>tutional Laboratory Animal Care and Use Committee, <lb/>The Ohio State University (protocol #2014A00000040). <lb/>Experimental design and sample collection <lb/>At 8 weeks of age, nine pigs (mean weight 12.1 ± 1.3 kg) <lb/>were divided into three groups of three pigs each. Pigs in <lb/>group 1 were inoculated intranasally with DMEM and <lb/>these pigs served as controls. Pigs in groups 2 and 3 <lb/>were similarly inoculated with SwIV (5 × 10 6 TCID 50 per <lb/>pig). Pigs had a hemagglutination inhibition (HI) anti-<lb/>body titer of 1:12 ± 4 against SwIV before infection. In <lb/>our previous study, infection of 8-week-old commercial <lb/>pigs with SwIV (5 × 10 6 TCID 50 per pig) induced exten-<lb/>sive lung lesions [33]. Twelve hours after SwIV infection, <lb/>pigs in groups 2 and 3 were administered intratracheally <lb/>with DMEM and MSC-EVs (80 μg/kg body weight <lb/>(BW)), respectively. In human clinical trials for ARDS <lb/>[6], MSCs between 1 and 10 × 10 6 cells/kg BW were <lb/>used. In our study, EV dose per kg BW was calculated <lb/>by the protein content of EVs produced by 10 × 10 6 <lb/>MSCs cultured for 48 h. In a previous study [23] intra-<lb/>tracheally administered EVs were effective in treating E. <lb/>coli-induced severe pneumonia. Based on this observa-<lb/>tion, in this study EVs were administered by the intratra-<lb/>cheal route. Pigs were monitored daily for clinical signs <lb/>and nasal swabs were collected at 1 and 3 days post-<lb/>infection (DPI) for virus titration in MDCK cells. At DPI <lb/>3, pigs were euthanized and lungs were harvested. Lung <lb/>lysate was prepared from the left lung for virus quantifi-<lb/>cation and cytokine analysis, and the entire right lung <lb/>was fixed in 10% buffered formalin for microscopic <lb/>examination. The time-point DPI 3 was selected based <lb/>on our earlier publication showing higher virus replica-<lb/>tion and proinflammatory cytokine production at DPI 3 <lb/>compared with DPI 6 [8]. Paraffin-embedded sections of <lb/>lung tissues were stained with hematoxylin and eosin <lb/>and examined with the help of a trained pathologist who <lb/>was not aware of the experimental design. The slides <lb/>were examined for bronchiolar epithelial changes, peri-<lb/>bronchiolar inflammation, and interstitial pneumonia, <lb/>and lesions were scored from 0-3 as described previ-<lb/>ously [34, 35]. <lb/>Detection of SwIV in nasal swabs and lungs <lb/>A 10% (w/v) lung homogenate was prepared from left <lb/>apical lobe lung tissue and virus titer was determined by <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>titration in MDCK cells as described [33]. Virus titers <lb/>were calculated by the Reed and Muench method. <lb/>Detection of cytokines in lungs <lb/>Lung lysates from pigs were prepared and levels of <lb/>tumor necrosis factor (TNF)α, CXCL10, and interleu-<lb/>kin (IL)-10 in lung lysates were determined by <lb/>enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) as de-<lb/>scribed previously [8]. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>In vitro data on MSC-EV-mediated inhibition of SwIV <lb/>replication were analyzed by Student&apos;s t test. Micro-<lb/>scopic lung lesions, virus titers, and cytokine concentra-<lb/>tions between groups of pigs were compared using <lb/>Kruskal-Wallis test. P values &lt; 0.05 were considered <lb/>statistically significant. <lb/>Results <lb/>Characteristics of MSC-derived EVs <lb/>We isolated MSCs from the BM of 2-to 6-week-old pigs <lb/>that showed characteristic features of MSCs, such as <lb/>adherence to a plastic surface, fibroblast-like morph-<lb/>ology (Fig. 1), self-renewal potential, and high in vitro <lb/>proliferation capacity and differentiation potential (data <lb/>not shown). Colony-expanded MSCs showed the expres-<lb/>sion of the mesenchymal markers CD29, CD44, CD90, <lb/>and SLA-I, but SLA-II was not detected on these cells. <lb/>MSC-EVs were round-shaped and, similarly to MSCs, <lb/>EVs isolated from BM-MSCs also expressed mesenchy-<lb/>mal markers; however, unlike MSCs, they lacked the <lb/>expression of both SLA-I and II (Fig. 1). MSC-EVs also <lb/>expressed EV-specific markers such as CD9, CD63, and <lb/>CD81 (Fig. 2). We also determined the RNA and protein <lb/>concentration in MSC-EVs. MSC-EVs contained 113 ± <lb/>37 ng/100 μl EVs (n = 5) total RNA and 79 ± 1 μg/100 μl <lb/>EVs (n = 4) total protein. <lb/>Additionally, MSC-EVs showed the ability to incorpor-<lb/>ate into LECs. EVs stained red with PKH-26 dye were <lb/>found inside the cytoplasm of cells when examined <lb/>under a fluorescent microscope. Incorporation of MSC-<lb/>EVs in LECs was also confirmed by flow cytometry <lb/>(Fig. 3). <lb/>MSC-EVs inhibit the HA activity of influenza viruses <lb/>To determine if MSC-EVs possess anti-influenza activity, <lb/>we first examined if EVs inhibited the HA activity of in-<lb/>fluenza viruses. Eight HA units of swine/TX/98; H3N2, <lb/>swine/MN/08; H1N1, gull/MD/1995; H9N5, chicken/ <lb/>NY/H7N2, and human/CA/09; H1N1 influenza viruses <lb/>were incubated with different concentrations of MSC-<lb/>EVs and the HA activity of these viruses was examined. <lb/>MSC-EV concentrations between 1.25 and 5 μg/ml com-<lb/>pletely inhibited the HA activity of these viruses <lb/>(Table 1). <lb/>MSC-EVs inhibit SwIV replication and virus-induced apop-<lb/>tosis in LECs <lb/>We examined MSC-EVs derived from BM-MSCs for <lb/>anti-influenza activity. SwIV (Sw/MN/08; MOI of 1) was <lb/>incubated with MSC-EVs (10 μg/ml) for 20 min at room <lb/>temperature. LECs were infected with EV-SwIV mixture <lb/>or virus only. At 8 h after infection, IAV-NP was <lb/>detected by IFA (Fig. 4a and c). Significantly reduced (P <lb/>&lt; 0.05) influenza replication was detected when cells <lb/>were infected with SwIV pretreated with MSC-EVs. <lb/>Consistent with reduced influenza virus replication in <lb/>LECs treated with MSC-EVs, MSC-EVs also significantly <lb/>(P &lt; 0.05) inhibited the apoptosis of influenza-infected <lb/>LEC (Fig. 5a and b). <lb/>Fig. 1 Characteristics of MSC-derived EVs. Extracellular vesicles (EVs) were isolated from the conditioned medium of porcine bone marrow-derived <lb/>mesenchymal stem cells (BM-MSCs) by ultracentrifugation. Morphology and size of MSC-EVs was examined by TEM. EVs were round-shaped and <lb/>approximately 100 nm in size (×25 K). Expression of mesenchymal markers on MSCs and MSC-EVs was examined by flow cytometry. MSCs expressed <lb/>the mesenchymal markers CD29, CD44, and CD90, and swine leukocyte antigen (SLA)-I, but SLA-II was not expressed. Similarly to MSCs, EVs expressed <lb/>the mesenchymal markers but lacked the expression of SLA-I and SLA-II (black line: isotype staining; red line: specific staining) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>In another set of experiments, porcine lung epithelial <lb/>LECs were infected with SwIV for 1 h, washed, and incu-<lb/>bated with media without or with MSC-EVs (10 μg/ml). <lb/>At 8 h after infection, IAV-NP was detected by IFA. The <lb/>addition of MSC-EVs after virus entry significantly (P &lt; <lb/>0.05) reduced influenza replication in LECs (Fig. 6). <lb/>MSC-EVs attenuate SwIV-induced ALI in pigs <lb/>We examined the anti-influenza and immunomodula-<lb/>tory effect of MSC-EVs in influenza virus-induced ALI <lb/>in pigs. Eight-week-old pigs were infected intranasally <lb/>with 5 × 10 6 TCID 50 of SwIV. Twelve hours after SwIV <lb/>inoculation, DMEM or MSC-EVs (80 μg/kg) were <lb/>administered intratracheally in influenza-infected pigs. <lb/>At days 1 and 3 after EV administration, we collected <lb/>the nasal swabs, and at day 3 after EV administration the <lb/>pigs were euthanized and bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) <lb/>and lungs were collected. Lungs were homogenized to <lb/>make 10% lung lysate for determining virus titers, and <lb/>cytokines were examined in the lung lysate. <lb/>SwIV induced extensive lung lesions in infected pigs <lb/>as determined by infiltration of inflammatory cells, <lb/>thickened alveolar walls, and collapsed alveoli, whereas <lb/>lungs of pigs administered with MSC-EVs showed <lb/>minor infiltration of inflammatory cells. The mean <lb/>microscopic lung lesion score in SwIV + DMEM inocu-<lb/>lated pigs was 7.3 ± 1.5 compared with 2.6 ± 1.5 in the <lb/>SwIV + EV administered group (Fig. 7a-d). Consistent <lb/>Fig. 2 Mesenchymal stem cell extracellular vesicles (MSC-EVs) express EV markers. EV-coated latex beads were examined for the expression of EV <lb/>markers by flow cytometry. EVs expressed the specific EV markers CD9, CD63, and CD81 (broken line: isotype staining; solid line: specific staining) <lb/>Fig. 3 MSC-EVs incorporate into lung epithelial cells. PKH-26 labeled extracellular vesicles (EVs) were incubated with LECs for 24 h. Incorporation <lb/>of EVs in LECs was examined by fluorescent microscope and flow cytometry. The inset in the middle panel shows the internalization of EVs in the <lb/>cytoplasm of LECs. Cellular cytoplasm was stained using β-tubulin antibody (green); EVs (red) were found to be localized inside the LECs (×200) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>with the inflammatory lesions in lungs, the levels of <lb/>total protein in the BAL of SwIV + EV (174 ± 20 μg/ml) <lb/>administered pigs were also lower than the levels in <lb/>SwIV + DMEM (270 ± 34 μg/ml) inoculated pigs <lb/>(Fig. 7e). <lb/>We detected the influenza virus shedding in nasal <lb/>swabs at 1 and 3 days after EV administration. Virus <lb/>shedding was 100-fold lower in the EV-administered <lb/>group at 3 days post-EV administration as compared <lb/>with SwIV + DMEM inoculated pigs (Fig. 8). Similarly, <lb/>virus titers were also 100-fold lower in the lung lysate <lb/>of EV-administered pigs. These data suggest that <lb/>MSC-EVs inhibit influenza virus replication and shed-<lb/>ding in pigs. <lb/>MSC-EVs attenuate SwIV-induced inflammatory cytokines <lb/>Next, we examined if MSC-EVs also modulated the <lb/>inflammatory cytokine production in lungs. In the <lb/>MSC-EV administered group, the levels of TNFα were <lb/>251 ± 46 pg/g lung lysate compared with 386 ± 40 pg/g <lb/>in pigs inoculated with SwIV + DMEM. Similarly, levels <lb/>of CXCL10 in SwIV + EV administered pigs were 3259 <lb/>± 469 pg/g compared with 4456 ± 495 pg/g in lung <lb/>lysates of SwIV + DMEM inoculated pigs. The levels of <lb/>the anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 were slightly <lb/>higher in the SwIV + EV administered group compared <lb/>with the SwIV + DMEM inoculated pigs (Fig. 9). These <lb/>findings suggest that MSC-EVs possess anti-influenza <lb/>and anti-inflammatory properties and attenuated influ-<lb/>enza virus-induced ALI in a pig model. <lb/>Table 1 MSC-EVs inhibit hemagglutination (HA) activity of <lb/>influenza viruses <lb/>Influenza virus <lb/>Hemagglutination at EV concentrations <lb/>(μg/ml) <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>0.625 <lb/>Swine/TX/1998; H3N2 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Human/CA/09; H1N1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>Swine/MN/08; H1N1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Gull/MD/1995; H9N5 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Chicken/NY/1995; H7N2 -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>Eight HA units of swine, human, and avian origin influenza viruses were <lb/>incubated with different concentrations of mesenchymal stem cell <lb/>extracellular vesicles (MSC-EVs) or medium control at room temperature for <lb/>20 min; 50 μl 1% turkey red blood cells were then added to the wells and <lb/>MSC-EV-mediated inhibition of HA by influenza viruses was examined. Results <lb/>are representative of three different experiments using EVs derived from MSCs <lb/>isolated from three different pigs <lb/>Fig. 4 MSC-EVs inhibit influenza virus replication in lung epithelial cells. Swine/MN/08; H1N1 (SwIV; MOI = 1) was incubated with Dulbecco&apos;s modified <lb/>Eagle&apos;s medium (DMEM) or 10 μg/ml MSC extracellular vesicles (EVs) for 20 min at room temperature. After the incubation, LECs were inoculated with <lb/>virus-EV mixture or virus alone and incubated for 1 h at 37 °C. Influenza virus NP was detected at 8 h after infection (a) and SwIV-induced cytopathology <lb/>was observed at 48 h after infection (b). SwIV-infected cells expressing NP were counted at 8 h after infection. Each bar represents mean ± SD of virus-<lb/>infected cells in five microscopic fields (20×) (c). Virus titers in supernatants of SwIV-infected and MSC-EV-treated cells at 48 h after infection were <lb/>determined by titration in MDCK cells. Data are expressed as mean ± SD from three independent experiments using EVs derived from BM-MSCs from three <lb/>different pigs (d). *P &lt; 0.05 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we isolated porcine BM-MSC-derived EVs <lb/>and examined their anti-viral and immunomodulatory <lb/>properties in a pig model of influenza virus. MSC-EVs <lb/>were round-shaped and, similarly to BM-MSCs, <lb/>expressed mesenchymal markers but, unlike MSC, EVs <lb/>lacked the expression of both SLA-I and II whereas <lb/>MSCs expressed SLA-I. Importantly, MSC-EVs inhibited <lb/>the HA activity of influenza viruses, suppressed the <lb/>replication of influenza virus in lung epithelial cells, and <lb/>inhibited influenza virus replication and proinflamma-<lb/>tory cytokine production in the lungs of virus-<lb/>infected pigs. <lb/>We isolated and characterized EVs from porcine BM-<lb/>MSCs using protocols as described for human MSC-<lb/>derived EVs [23, 29, 30]. As for human MSC-EVs, we <lb/>also used TEM to determine the size and morphology of <lb/>MSC-EVs. Size distribution of human MSC-EVs was also <lb/>determined by nanotracking but this technique was not <lb/>used in this study. Human MSC-derived EVs expressed <lb/>mesenchymal markers and lacked the expression of <lb/>MHC molecules [36]. In our study, pig MSC-derived <lb/>EVs also expressed mesenchymal markers and the <lb/>expression of both SLA-I and II was not detected in <lb/>EVs, suggesting that pig MSC-EVs are similar to human <lb/>MSC-EVs and will be useful in understanding the mech-<lb/>anisms of MSC-EV-mediated therapeutic effects in a pig <lb/>model of human diseases. <lb/>A number of studies have demonstrated the beneficial <lb/>effects of MSC-EVs in vitro and in animal models of <lb/>lung, kidney, and liver diseases [37, 38]. Furthermore, <lb/>several studies have shown that EVs exert their thera-<lb/>peutic effects by transferring their mRNA to diseased <lb/>cells [20, 29, 39, 40]. In this study, the anti-influenza <lb/>virus activity of MSC-EVs in lung epithelial cells was <lb/>mediated by their mRNA content as pretreatment of <lb/>EVs with RNase enzyme abrogated the anti-influenza <lb/>virus activity of EVs. In a recent study, Qian and <lb/>colleagues [41] demonstrated that exosomes (Exo) <lb/>isolated from umbilical cord-derived MSCs inhibited <lb/>replication of hepatitis C virus (HCV) in human dermal <lb/>fibroblast 7 cells. These authors further identified four <lb/>MSC-Exo-specific miRNAs with anti-HCV activity. <lb/>MSC-EV-specific miRNAs have also been implicated in <lb/>the regulation of cell survival, differentiation, and immu-<lb/>nomodulation [42, 43]. Future studies will focus on <lb/>identifying MSC-EV-specific mRNA and miRNAs that <lb/>may play a role in regulating the anti-influenza activities <lb/>of MSC-EVs. <lb/>One of the mechanisms by which influenza viruses <lb/>cause extensive lung damage and mortality is due to the <lb/>induction of unregulated inflammatory response [44, <lb/>45]. Similarly to MSCs, MSC-derived EVs also possess <lb/>immunomodulatory activity [46-52]. In this study, <lb/>MSC-EV inoculated pigs showed significantly less lung <lb/>inflammation and decreased levels of proinflammatory <lb/>cytokine and chemokine production. Additionally, <lb/>increased levels of anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10 <lb/>were observed in MSC-EV administered pigs. These data <lb/>suggest that, in addition to anti-influenza activity, MSC-<lb/>EVs also exert their immunomodulatory activities and <lb/>suppress the inflammatory response in influenza. Similar <lb/>to our findings, MSC-EVs caused decreased production <lb/>of inflammatory cytokines and increased production of <lb/>IL-10 in a mouse model of ARDS [20]. Monsel and <lb/>colleagues [23] demonstrated that MSC-EVs express <lb/>cyclooxygenase (COX)-2 mRNA, the enzyme that in-<lb/>duces prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) synthesis. PGE2 secreted <lb/>by MSCs has been shown to reprogram proinflammatory <lb/>monocyte-macrophages (M1) to the anti-inflammatory <lb/>(M2) type that produces high levels of IL-10 [53]. Add-<lb/>itionally, MSC-EVs interact with immune cells and cause <lb/>the production of transforming growth factor (TGF)β <lb/>Fig. 5 MSC-EVs inhibit influenza virus-induced apoptosis. a Swine/ <lb/>MN/08; H1N1 (SwIV; MOI = 1) was incubated with Dulbecco&apos;s modi-<lb/>fied Eagle&apos;s medium (DMEM) or 10 μg/ml MSC extracellular vesicles <lb/>(EVs) for 20 min at room temperature. After the incubation, pig lung <lb/>epithelial cells were incubated for 1 h with SwIV or SwIV pre-<lb/>incubated with MSC-EVs. At 24 h after infection, apoptotic cells were <lb/>detected by TUNEL assay using the ApopTag Fluorescein Apoptosis <lb/>Detection Kit (EMD Millipore). b TUNEL-positive cells in SwIV-infected <lb/>and MSC-EV-treated LECs were counted at 24 h after infection. <lb/>Values are expressed as mean ± SD of apoptotic cells in five <lb/>microscopic fields (20×). *P &lt; 0.05 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 6 MSC-EVs inhibit influenza virus replication after virus entry in lung epithelial cells. a Pig lung epithelial cells were infected with swine/MN/ <lb/>08; H1N1 (SwIV; MOI = 1) for 1 h; after the adsorption, cells were washed and cultured in media only or media containing 10 μg/ml MSC <lb/>extracellular vesicles (EVs) or RNase-treated MSC-EVs. Influenza virus NP was detected 8 h after infection. b Each bar represents mean ± SD of <lb/>virus-infected cells in five microscopic fields (20×). Experiments were repeated three times using EVs derived from BM-MSCs from three different <lb/>pigs. *P &lt; 0.05. DMEM Dulbecco&apos;s modified Eagle&apos;s medium <lb/>Fig. 7 Effect of MSC-EV administration on microscopic lung lesions in pigs infected with SwIV. Eight-week-old pigs were mock infected or infected <lb/>with swine/MN/08; H1N1 (SwIV). After 12 h, pigs were administered with Dulbecco&apos;s modified Eagle&apos;s medium (DMEM) or MSC extracellular vesicles <lb/>(EVs). Three days after EV administration, pigs were euthanized and microscopic lung lesions and levels of total protein in bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) <lb/>were examined. a Control uninfected lung, showing normal alveolar walls, clear air space, and absence of exudation into the alveolar space. b SwIV <lb/>induced exudative interstitial pneumonia characterized by thickened alveolar walls, collapsed alveolar spaces, and infiltration of inflammatory cells, <lb/>whereas c lungs of pigs inoculated with MSC-EVs 12 h after SwIV infection show mild infiltration of inflammatory cells. Hematoxylin and eosin stain. <lb/>Magnification × 200. d,e Histopathological scores. Lung tissue slides were examined for bronchiolar epithelial changes, peribronchiolar inflammation, <lb/>and interstitial pneumonia, and lesions were scored from 0-3 (d). Values in each bar indicate mean microscopic lung lesions of three pigs ± SD. e <lb/>MSC-EV administration decreased the levels of total protein in the BAL of SwIV + EV administered pigs as compared with SwIV + DMEM inoculated pigs. <lb/>Data are expressed as mean levels of total protein in BAL of three pigs ± SD <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>and T-regulatory cells (Tregs) [48]. Tregs promote virus <lb/>clearance and recovery in influenza virus-infected <lb/>mice [54, 55]. In future studies, we will examine <lb/>whether MSC-EV treatment induces the generation of <lb/>M2-type macrophages and Tregs in a pig model of <lb/>influenza virus. <lb/>MSCs mediate their immunomodulatory and tissue <lb/>repair functions by the release of numerous therapeutic <lb/>soluble factors [43, 56]. Indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase <lb/>(IDO) is produced by MSCs and modulates the func-<lb/>tions of immune cells and inhibits influenza virus repli-<lb/>cation [57]. Similarly, LL37, an antimicrobial peptide, is <lb/>produced by MSCs and has been shown to inhibit the <lb/>growth of several species of bacteria and also inhibits <lb/>replication of influenza virus [58, 59]. Additionally, <lb/>LL37 was also shown to regulate the immunomodula-<lb/>tory activities of MSCs [60]. Currently, data on <lb/>whether LL37 and IDO are transferred from MSCs to <lb/>their secreted EVs are not available and were not <lb/>examined in this study. It may be possible that these <lb/>factors may be involved in mediating the anti-<lb/>influenza and anti-inflammatory activities of MSC-EVs <lb/>in our influenza model. <lb/>Recently, a few studies examined the therapeutic <lb/>potential of MSCs in influenza in mice with conflict-<lb/>ing results [9-12]. The Liles and Matthay groups <lb/>reported that mouse and human MSCs failed to pre-<lb/>vent influenza virus-induced mortality and ALI in <lb/>mice [10, 11]. More recently, two publications have <lb/>shown that MSCs reduced influenza virus-induced <lb/>ALI in mice infected with HPAI H5N1 and H9N2 <lb/>without affecting the virus replication [9, 12]. We and <lb/>others have shown previously that influenza virus <lb/>infected MSCs and that infected MSCs produced <lb/>inflammatory cytokines [13-15]. Of the in vivo <lb/>studies that examined the therapeutic efficacy of <lb/>MSCs in influenza virus-induced ALI, none examined <lb/>the infection of administered MSCs with influenza <lb/>virus. Replicating virus in influenza virus-infected <lb/>mice may infect the injected MSCs and virus-infected <lb/>MSCs may not be functionally effective in inhibiting <lb/>virus replication and inflammation. In in-vitro studies, <lb/>influenza virus infection caused the apoptosis and <lb/>lysis of infected MSCs [13]. Inactivated MSCs have <lb/>been shown to retain some of their immunomodula-<lb/>tory functions. Heat-inactivated MSCs modulated the <lb/>functions of monocytes/macrophages but had no <lb/>effect on T or B cells [61]. In studies which demon-<lb/>strated the protective effects of transplanted MSCs in <lb/>influenza virus-infected mice, anti-inflammatory <lb/>Fig. 8 Effect of MSC-EV administration on virus titers in nasal swabs <lb/>and lungs of pigs infected with SwIV. Eight-week-old pigs were mock <lb/>infected or infected with swine/MN/08; H1N1 (SwIV). After 12 h, pigs <lb/>were administered intratracheally with Dulbecco&apos;s modified Eagle&apos;s <lb/>medium (DMEM) or MSC extracellular vesicles (EVs). Nasal swabs were <lb/>collected from infected pigs at 1 and 3 days after EV administration <lb/>(1DPEV and 3DPEV). At 3 days after EV administration, pigs were <lb/>euthanized and lungs were harvested. Lung tissues were homogenized <lb/>to prepare 10% lung lysate. Influenza virus shedding in nasal swabs <lb/>and virus titers in lungs were determined by titration in MDCK cells. <lb/>Values in each bar indicate mean virus titers of three pigs ± SD <lb/>Fig. 9 Effect of MSC-EV administration on cytokine production in lungs of SwIV-infected pigs. Eight-week-old pigs were mock infected or infected <lb/>with swine/MN/08; H1N1 (SwIV). After 12 h, pigs were administered intratracheally with Dulbecco&apos;s modified Eagle&apos;s medium (DMEM) or MSC <lb/>extracellular vesicles (EVs). Three days after EV administration, pigs were euthanized and cytokine production in lung lysate was analyzed by ELISA. <lb/>Each bar represents mean concentrations of cytokines ± SD from three pigs. IL interleukin, TNF tumor necrosis factor <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 10 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>effects observed in these studies may likely be medi-<lb/>ated by influenza-infected dead or apoptotic MSCs. <lb/>Future experiments will be required to confirm the <lb/>infection of transplanted MSC by influenza virus and <lb/>to examine their interaction with immune cells in <lb/>animal models of influenza virus. <lb/>MSC-EVs were recently identified and were as <lb/>equally effective as MSCs in treating endotoxin and E <lb/>coli-induced ALI in rodent models [20, 23]. Here, we <lb/>demonstrated that MSC-EVs attenuated influenza <lb/>virus-induced ALI in a pig model. Importantly, <lb/>administration of MSC-EVs was safe since no gross <lb/>pathological lesions were observed in any of the <lb/>internal organs of the pigs. Additionally, MSC-EV <lb/>treatment was also found to be safe in human <lb/>patients treated for graft-versus-host disease (GvHD) <lb/>and chronic kidney disease [50, 62]. Thus, the find-<lb/>ings of this study may help in the planning of future <lb/>clinical trials in humans using MSC-EVs as a cell-free <lb/>therapy for ARDS. <lb/>MSC-EVs offer several advantages over MSCs as a <lb/>therapy for human diseases. Although MSCs have <lb/>been proven to be effective and safe in treating sev-<lb/>eral human conditions in animal models and clinical <lb/>trials, safety concerns such as pulmonary embolism, <lb/>uncontrolled differentiation, and tumor formation are <lb/>still associated with the use of MSCs as a therapy in <lb/>humans [63, 64]. On the other hand, use of EVs as a <lb/>therapy was found to be safer than MSCs [20, 50]. <lb/>EVs are stable in circulation due to their lipid mem-<lb/>brane, have no risk of aneuploidy, and are well toler-<lb/>ated in recipients due to their small size and lack of <lb/>expression of MHC molecules. Moreover, EVs can be <lb/>stored at -80 °C without losing their biochemical <lb/>activity [65, 66]. Thus, EVs have the potential to <lb/>become a safe and effective cell-free therapy for <lb/>human diseases. However, a number of challenges, <lb/>such as standard protocols for the production of clin-<lb/>ical grade EVs, their dosing, quality control, and stor-<lb/>age conditions, still need to be addressed before <lb/>MSC-EVs can be advanced to the clinic. <lb/>This study has certain limitations: 1) an additional <lb/>control group consisting of EVs derived from fibroblasts <lb/>is needed to confirm that the beneficial effects in influ-<lb/>enza are specifically mediated by MSC-EV; and 2) <lb/>administration of EVs by the intravenous route would be <lb/>more relevant in the clinical settings. However, in several <lb/>studies, EVs obtained from MSCs, but not from fibro-<lb/>blasts, showed beneficial effects in ARDS when inocu-<lb/>lated intravenously or intratracheally. In our preliminary <lb/>studies in a pig model of lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-in-<lb/>duced ARDS, only human MSC-derived EVs, and not <lb/>EVs from normal human lung fibroblasts, attenuated <lb/>lung inflammation. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In summary, EVs derived from porcine BM-MSCs <lb/>expressed mesenchymal markers, inhibited influenza <lb/>virus replication in vitro and in vivo, and attenuated <lb/>influenza virus-induced ALI in a relevant preclinical <lb/>large animal model. Our findings suggest that MSC-<lb/>EVs may be a potential cell-free therapy for acute <lb/>inflammatory diseases including influenza. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Abbreviations <lb/>ALI: Acute lung injury; ARDS: Acute respiratory distress syndrome; <lb/>BAL: Bronchoalveolar lavage; BM: Bone marrow; BW: Body weight; <lb/>CM: Conditioned medium; DAPI: 4′,6-Diamidino-2-phenylindole; <lb/>DMEM: Dulbecco&apos;s modified Eagle&apos;s medium; DPI: Days post-infection; <lb/>ELISA: Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; EV: Extracellular vesicle; <lb/>Exo: Exosomes; FBS: Fetal bovine serum; HA: Hemagglutination; <lb/>HCV: Hepatitis C virus; HPAI: Highly pathogenic avian influenza; IAV: Influenza <lb/>A viruses; IDO: Indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase; IFA: Immunofluorescence assay; <lb/>IL: Interleukin; LEC: Lung epithelial cell; miRNA: MicroRNA; MV: Microvesicle; <lb/>MSC: Mesenchymal stem (stromal) cell; NP: Nucleoprotein; PBS: Phosphate-<lb/>buffered saline; PGE2: Prostaglandin E2; SLA: Swine leukocyte antigen; <lb/>SwIV H1N1: Swine/MN/08; TEM: Transmission electron microscopy; <lb/>TNF: Tumor necrosis factor; Treg: T regulatory cell <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Dr. Juliette Hanson, Megan Strother, Ronna Woods, and Sara <lb/>Tallmadge for veterinary and animal care. We also thank Dr. Chun-Ming Lin <lb/>for his help with the histopathological examination of lung sections, Dr. <lb/>Kuldeep Chattha for his assistance with flow cytometry, and Santosh Dhakal <lb/>and Sydney Bartolet for their help with animal inoculations and necropsy. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This research was partly supported by the National Institute of Health (grant <lb/>#R21HL125191 to MK). <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Availability of data and materials <lb/>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available <lb/>from the corresponding author on reasonable request. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>MK: conceived of the study, performed experiments, and wrote manuscript. <lb/>LAR: carried out experiments. TM: carried out electron microscopy analysis of <lb/>MSC-EVs and helped to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved <lb/>the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Ethics approval and consent to participate <lb/>All experimental procedures involving pigs were conducted in accordance <lb/>with the guidelines of the Institutional Laboratory Animal Care and Use <lb/>Committee, The Ohio State University (protocol #2014A00000040). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Consent for publication <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s Note <lb/>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published <lb/>maps and institutional affiliations. <lb/></div>

			<front>Author details <lb/>1 <lb/>Food Animal Health Research Program, Ohio Agricultural Research and <lb/>Development Center, The Ohio State University, 1680 Madison Avenue, <lb/>Wooster, OH 44691, USA. 2 Molecular and Cellular Imaging Center, Ohio <lb/>Agricultural Research and Development Center, The Ohio State University, <lb/>Wooster, OH, USA. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 11 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<front>Received: 27 July 2017 Revised: 19 December 2017 <lb/>Accepted: 15 January 2018 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Beigel JH, Farrar J, Han AM, Hayden FG, Hyer R, de Jong MD, et al. Avian <lb/>influenza A (H5N1) infection in humans. N Engl J Med. 2005;353:1374-85. <lb/>2. de Jong MD, Bach VC, Phan TQ, Vo MH, Tran TT, Nguyen BH, et al. Fatal <lb/>avian influenza A (H5N1) in a child presenting with diarrhea followed by <lb/>coma. N Engl J Med. 2005;352:686-91. <lb/>3. de Jong MD, Simmons CP, Thanh TT, Hien VM, Smith GJ, Chau TN, et al. <lb/>Fatal outcome of human influenza A (H5N1) is associated with high viral <lb/>load and hypercytokinemia. Nat Med. 2006;12:1203-07. <lb/>4. Uccelli A, Moretta L, Pistoia V. Mesenchymal stem cells in health and <lb/>disease. Nat Rev Immunol. 2008;8:726-36. <lb/>5. Laffey JG, Matthay MA. Fifty years of research in ARDS. Cell-based therapy <lb/>for acute respiratory distress syndrome. biology and potential therapeutic <lb/>value. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2017;196:266-73. <lb/>6. Wilson JG, Liu KD, Zhuo H, Caballero L, McMillan M, Fang X, et al. <lb/>Mesenchymal stem (stromal) cells for treatment of ARDS: a phase 1 clinical <lb/>trial. Lancet Respir Med. 2015;3:24-32. <lb/>7. Zheng G, Huang L, Tong H, Shu Q, Hu Y, Ge M, et al. Treatment of <lb/>acute respiratory distress syndrome with allogeneic adipose-derived <lb/>mesenchymal stem cells: a randomized, placebo-controlled pilot study. <lb/>Respir Res. 2014;15:39. <lb/>8. Khatri M, Dwivedi V, Krakowka S, Manickam C, Ali A, Wang L, et al. Swine <lb/>influenza H1N1 virus induces acute inflammatory immune responses in pig <lb/>lungs: a potential animal model for human H1N1 influenza virus. J Virol. <lb/>2010;84:11210-218. <lb/>9. Chan MC, Kuok DI, Leung CY, Hui KP, Valkenburg SA, Lau EH, et al. Human <lb/>mesenchymal stromal cells reduce influenza A H5N1-associated acute lung <lb/>injury in vitro and in vivo. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2016;113:3621-26. <lb/>10. Darwish I, Banner D, Mubareka S, Kim H, Besla R, Kelvin DJ, et al. <lb/>Mesenchymal stromal (stem) cell therapy fails to improve outcomes in <lb/>experimental severe influenza. PLoS One. 2013;8:e71761. <lb/>11. Gotts JE, Abbott J, Matthay MA. Influenza causes prolonged disruption of <lb/>the alveolar-capillary barrier in mice unresponsive to mesenchymal stem <lb/>cell therapy. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol. 2014;307:L395-406. <lb/>12. Li Y, Xu J, Shi W, Chen C, Shao Y, Zhu L, et al. Mesenchymal stromal cell <lb/>treatment prevents H9N2 avian influenza virus-induced acute lung injury in <lb/>mice. Stem Cell Res Ther. 2016;7:159. <lb/>13. Khatri M, O&apos;Brien TD, Goyal SM, Sharma JM. Isolation and characterization of <lb/>chicken lung mesenchymal stromal cells and their susceptibility to avian <lb/>influenza virus. Dev Comp Immunol. 2010;34:474-79. <lb/>14. Khatri M, Saif YM. Influenza virus infects bone marrow mesenchymal stromal <lb/>cells in vitro: implications for bone marrow transplantation. Cell Transplant. <lb/>2013;22:461-68. <lb/>15. Thanunchai M, Kanrai P, Wiboon-Ut S, Puthavathana P, Hongeng S, <lb/>Thitithanyanont A. Tropism of avian influenza A (H5N1) virus to <lb/>mesenchymal stem cells and CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells. PLoS One. <lb/>2013;8:e81805. <lb/>16. Phinney DG, Prockop DJ. Concise review: mesenchymal stem/multipotent <lb/>stromal cells: the state of transdifferentiation and modes of tissue <lb/>repair-current views. Stem Cells. 2007;25:2896-902. <lb/>17. Yeo RW, Lai RC, Zhang B, Tan SS, Yin Y, Teh BJ, et al. Mesenchymal stem <lb/>cell: an efficient mass producer of exosomes for drug delivery. Adv Drug <lb/>Deliv Rev. 2013;65:336-41. <lb/>18. Kim HS, Choi DY, Yun SJ, Choi SM, Kang JW, Jung JW, et al. Proteomic <lb/>analysis of microvesicles derived from human mesenchymal stem cells. <lb/>J Proteome Res. 2012;11:839-49. <lb/>19. Phinney DG, Di Giuseppe M, Njah J, Sala E, Shiva S, St Croix CM, et al. <lb/>Mesenchymal stem cells use extracellular vesicles to outsource mitophagy <lb/>and shuttle microRNAs. Nat Commun. 2015;6:8472. <lb/>20. Zhu YG, Feng XM, Abbott J, Fang XH, Hao Q, Monsel A, et al. Human <lb/>mesenchymal stem cell microvesicles for treatment of Escherichia coli <lb/>endotoxin-induced acute lung injury in mice. Stem Cells. 2014;32:116-25. <lb/>21. Camussi G, Deregibus MC, Cantaluppi V. Role of stem cell-derived <lb/>microvesicles in the paracrine action of stem cells. Biochem Soc Trans. 2013; <lb/>41:283-87. <lb/>22. Quesenberry PJ, Aliotta JM. Cellular phenotype switching and microvesicles. <lb/>Adv Drug Deliv Rev. 2010;62:1141-48. <lb/>23. Monsel A, Zhu YG, Gennai S, Hao Q, Hu S, Rouby JJ, et al. Therapeutic <lb/>effects of human mesenchymal stem cell-derived microvesicles in severe <lb/>pneumonia in mice. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2015;192:324-36. <lb/>24. Rogers CS, Abraham WM, Brogden KA, Engelhardt JF, Fisher JT, McCray Jr <lb/>PB, et al. The porcine lung as a potential model for cystic fibrosis. Am J <lb/>Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol. 2008;295:L240-63. <lb/>25. Walters EM, Wells KD, Bryda EC, Schommer S, Prather RS. Swine models, <lb/>genomic tools and services to enhance our understanding of human health <lb/>and diseases. Lab Anim (NY). 2017;46:167-72. <lb/>26. Kuiken T, Taubenberger JK. Pathology of human influenza revisited. Vaccine. <lb/>2008;26 Suppl 4:D59-66. <lb/>27. Khatri M, O&apos;Brien TD, Sharma JM. Isolation and differentiation of chicken <lb/>mesenchymal stem cells from bone marrow. Stem Cells Dev. 2009;18: <lb/>1485-92. <lb/>28. Pittenger MF, Mackay AM, Beck SC, Jaiswal RK, Douglas R, Mosca JD, et al. <lb/>Multilineage potential of adult human mesenchymal stem cells. Science. <lb/>1999;284:143-47. <lb/>29. Bruno S, Grange C, Deregibus MC, Calogero RA, Saviozzi S, Collino F, et al. <lb/>Mesenchymal stem cell-derived microvesicles protect against acute tubular <lb/>injury. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2009;20:1053-67. <lb/>30. Cruz FF, Borg ZD, Goodwin M, Sokocevic D, Wagner DE, Coffey A, et al. <lb/>Systemic administration of human bone marrow-derived mesenchymal <lb/>stromal cell extracellular vesicles ameliorates aspergillus hyphal extract-<lb/>induced allergic airway inflammation in immunocompetent mice. Stem <lb/>Cells Transl Med. 2015;4:1302-16. <lb/>31. Thery C, Boussac M, Veron P, Ricciardi-Castagnoli P, Raposo G, Garin J, <lb/>Amigorena S. Proteomic analysis of dendritic cell-derived exosomes: a <lb/>secreted subcellular compartment distinct from apoptotic vesicles. <lb/>J Immunol. 2001;166:7309-18. <lb/>32. Khatri M, O&apos;Brien TD, Chattha KS, Saif LJ. Porcine lung mesenchymal stromal <lb/>cells possess differentiation and immunoregulatory properties. Stem Cell <lb/>Res Ther. 2015;6:222. <lb/>33. Thomas M, Wang Z, Sreenivasan CC, Hause BM, Gourapura JR, Li F, et al. <lb/>Poly I:C adjuvanted inactivated swine influenza vaccine induces <lb/>heterologous protective immunity in pigs. Vaccine. 2015;33:542-48. <lb/>34. Richt JA, Lager KM, Janke BH, Woods RD, Webster RG, Webby RJ. <lb/>Pathogenic and antigenic properties of phylogenetically distinct reassortant <lb/>H3N2 swine influenza viruses cocirculating in the United States. J Clin <lb/>Microbiol. 2003;41:3198-205. <lb/>35. Jung K, Renukaradhya GJ, Alekseev KP, Fang Y, Tang Y, Saif LJ. Porcine <lb/>reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus modifies innate immunity and <lb/>alters disease outcome in pigs subsequently infected with porcine <lb/>respiratory coronavirus: implications for respiratory viral co-infections. J Gen <lb/>Virol. 2009;90:2713-23. <lb/>36. De Luca L, Trino S, Laurenzana I, Simeon V, Calice G, Raimondo S, et al. <lb/>MiRNAs and piRNAs from bone marrow mesenchymal stem cell <lb/>extracellular vesicles induce cell survival and inhibit cell differentiation of <lb/>cord blood hematopoietic stem cells: a new insight in transplantation. <lb/>Oncotarget. 2016;7:6676-92. <lb/>37. Monsel A, Zhu YG, Gudapati V, Lim H, Lee JW. Mesenchymal stem cell <lb/>derived secretome and extracellular vesicles for acute lung injury and other <lb/>inflammatory lung diseases. Expert Opin Biol Ther. 2016;16:859-71. <lb/>38. Rani S, Ryan AE, Griffin MD, Ritter T. Mesenchymal stem cell-derived <lb/>extracellular vesicles: toward cell-free therapeutic applications. Mol Ther. <lb/>2015;23:812-23. <lb/>39. Ragni E, Banfi F, Barilani M, Cherubini A, Parazzi V, Larghi P, et al. <lb/>Extracellular vesicle-shuttled mRNA in mesenchymal stem cell <lb/>communication. Stem Cells. 2017;35:1093-105. <lb/>40. Tomasoni S, Longaretti L, Rota C, Morigi M, Conti S, Gotti E, et al. <lb/>Transfer of growth factor receptor mRNA via exosomes unravels the <lb/>regenerative effect of mesenchymal stem cells. Stem Cells Dev. 2013; <lb/>22:772-80. <lb/>41. Qian X, Xu C, Fang S, Zhao P, Wang Y, Liu H, et al. Exosomal microRNAs <lb/>derived from umbilical mesenchymal stem cells inhibit hepatitis C virus <lb/>infection. Stem Cells Transl Med. 2016;5:1190-203. <lb/>42. Baglio SR, Pegtel DM, Baldini N. Mesenchymal stem cell secreted <lb/>vesicles provide novel opportunities in (stem) cell-free therapy. Front <lb/>Physiol. 2012;3:359. <lb/>43. Bruno S, Deregibus MC, Camussi G. The secretome of mesenchymal stromal <lb/>cells: role of extracellular vesicles in immunomodulation. Immunol Lett. <lb/>2015;168:154-58. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 12 of 13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>44. Herold S, Becker C, Ridge KM, Budinger GR. Influenza virus-induced lung <lb/>injury: pathogenesis and implications for treatment. Eur Respir J. 2015;45: <lb/>1463-78. <lb/>45. Short KR, Kroeze EJ, Fouchier RA, Kuiken T. Pathogenesis of influenza-<lb/>induced acute respiratory distress syndrome. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014; <lb/>14:57-69. <lb/>46. Blazquez R, Sanchez-Margallo FM, de la Rosa O, Dalemans W, Alvarez V, <lb/>Tarazona R, et al. Immunomodulatory potential of human adipose <lb/>mesenchymal stem cells derived exosomes on in vitro stimulated T cells. <lb/>Front Immunol. 2014;5:556. <lb/>47. Budoni M, Fierabracci A, Luciano R, Petrini S, Di Ciommo V, Muraca M. The <lb/>immunosuppressive effect of mesenchymal stromal cells on B lymphocytes <lb/>is mediated by membrane vesicles. Cell Transplant. 2013;22:369-79. <lb/>48. Chen W, Huang Y, Han J, Yu L, Li Y, Lu Z, et al. Immunomodulatory <lb/>effects of mesenchymal stromal cells-derived exosome. Immunol Res. <lb/>2016;64:831-40. <lb/>49. Favaro E, Carpanetto A, Lamorte S, Fusco A, Caorsi C, Deregibus MC, et al. <lb/>Human mesenchymal stem cell-derived microvesicles modulate T cell <lb/>response to islet antigen glutamic acid decarboxylase in patients with type <lb/>1 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2014;57:1664-73. <lb/>50. Kordelas L, Rebmann V, Ludwig AK, Radtke S, Ruesing J, Doeppner TR, et al. <lb/>MSC-derived exosomes: a novel tool to treat therapy-refractory graft-versus-<lb/>host disease. Leukemia. 2014;28:970-73. <lb/>51. Mokarizadeh A, Delirezh N, Morshedi A, Mosayebi G, Farshid AA, Mardani K. <lb/>Microvesicles derived from mesenchymal stem cells: potent organelles for <lb/>induction of tolerogenic signaling. Immunol Lett. 2012;147:47-54. <lb/>52. Zhang B, Yin Y, Lai RC, Tan SS, Choo AB, Lim SK. Mesenchymal stem cells <lb/>secrete immunologically active exosomes. Stem Cells Dev. 2014;23:1233-44. <lb/>53. Nemeth K, Leelahavanichkul A, Yuen PS, Mayer B, Parmelee A, Doi K, et al. <lb/>Bone marrow stromal cells attenuate sepsis via prostaglandin E(2)-<lb/>dependent reprogramming of host macrophages to increase their <lb/>interleukin-10 production. Nat Med. 2009;15:42-9. <lb/>54. Moser EK, Hufford MM, Braciale TJ. Late engagement of CD86 after influenza <lb/>virus clearance promotes recovery in a FoxP3+ regulatory T cell dependent <lb/>manner. PLoS Pathog. 2014;10:e1004315. <lb/>55. Oliphant S, Lines JL, Hollifield ML, Garvy BA. Regulatory T cells are critical for <lb/>clearing influenza A virus in neonatal mice. Viral Immunol. 2015;28:580-89. <lb/>56. Gallina C, Turinetto V, Giachino C. A new paradigm in cardiac regeneration: <lb/>the mesenchymal stem cell secretome. Stem Cells Int. 2015;2015:765846. <lb/>57. Li F, Karlsson H. Antiviral effect of IDO in mouse fibroblast cells during <lb/>influenza virus infection. Viral Immunol. 2017;30:542-44. <lb/>58. Krasnodembskaya A, Song Y, Fang X, Gupta N, Serikov V, Lee JW, et al. <lb/>Antibacterial effect of human mesenchymal stem cells is mediated in <lb/>part from secretion of the antimicrobial peptide LL-37. Stem Cells. 2010; <lb/>28:2229-38. <lb/>59. Tripathi S, Tecle T, Verma A, Crouch E, White M, Hartshorn KL. The human <lb/>cathelicidin LL-37 inhibits influenza A viruses through a mechanism distinct <lb/>from that of surfactant protein D or defensins. J Gen Virol. 2013;94:40-9. <lb/>60. Oliveira-Bravo M, Sangiorgi BB, Schiavinato JL, Carvalho JL, Covas DT, <lb/>Panepucci RA, et al. LL-37 boosts immunosuppressive function of placenta-<lb/>derived mesenchymal stromal cells. Stem Cell Res Ther. 2016;7:189. <lb/>61. Luk F, de Witte SF, Korevaar SS, Roemeling-van Rhijn M, Franquesa M, Strini <lb/>T, et al. Inactivated mesenchymal stem cells maintain immunomodulatory <lb/>capacity. Stem Cells Dev. 2016;25:1342-54. <lb/>62. Nassar W, El-Ansary M, Sabry D, Mostafa MA, Fayad T, Kotb E, et al. <lb/>Umbilical cord mesenchymal stem cells derived extracellular vesicles <lb/>can safely ameliorate the progression of chronic kidney diseases. <lb/>Biomater Res. 2016;20:21. <lb/>63. Haarer J, Johnson CL, Soeder Y, Dahlke MH. Caveats of mesenchymal stem <lb/>cell therapy in solid organ transplantation. Transpl Int. 2015;28:1-9. <lb/>64. Heslop JA, Hammond TG, Santeramo I, Tort Piella A, Hopp I, Zhou J, et al. <lb/>Concise review: workshop review: understanding and assessing the risks of <lb/>stem cell-based therapies. Stem Cells Transl Med. 2015;4:389-400. <lb/>65. Kalimuthu S, Gangadaran P, Li XJ, Oh JM, Lee HW, Jeong SY, et al. <lb/>In vivo therapeutic potential of mesenchymal stem cell-derived <lb/>extracellular vesicles with optical imaging reporter in tumor mice <lb/>model. Sci Rep. 2016;6:30418. <lb/>66. Reis M, Ogonek J, Qesari M, Borges NM, Nicholson L, Preussner L, et al. <lb/>Recent developments in cellular immunotherapy for HSCT-associated <lb/>complications. Front Immunol. 2016;7:500. <lb/></listBibl>

			• We accept pre-submission inquiries <lb/>• Our selector tool helps you to find the most relevant journal <lb/>• We provide round the clock customer support <lb/>• Convenient online submission <lb/>• Thorough peer review <lb/>• Inclusion in PubMed and all major indexing services <lb/>• Maximum visibility for your research <lb/>Submit your manuscript at <lb/>www.biomedcentral.com/submit <lb/>Submit your next manuscript to BioMed Central <lb/>and we will help you at every step: <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">Khatri et al. Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy (2018) 9:17 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 13 of 13 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
