<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Perinatal factors and early neonatal outcomes of abnormal birthweight infants in Hangzhou, China, 2015–2021: a retrospective cohort study</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Yiming</forename>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Huimin</forename>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Yan</forename>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Wenwen</forename>
            <surname>Ning</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Lingling</forename>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Yanan</forename>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Xuelian</forename>
            <surname>Chu</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-29T11:16:37.448919Z">29.10.2025 11:16:37</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1136$1$bmjpo-2023-002347</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>BMJ</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjpo-2023-002347</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Yiming Chen, Huimin Zhang, Yan Jiang, Wenwen Ning, Lingling Huang, Yanan Wang, Xuelian Chu. (2024). Perinatal factors and early neonatal outcomes of abnormal birthweight infants in Hangzhou, China, 2015–2021: a retrospective cohort study. BMJ Paediatrics Open, 8(1), e002347. DOI: 10.1136/bmjpo-2023-002347</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T11:16:37.448919Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-29T11:16:37.448919Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>1 <lb/>Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/>Open access <lb/>Anti-TNF (adalimumab) injection for <lb/>the treatment of pain-predominant <lb/>early-stage frozen shoulder: the Anti-<lb/>Freaze-Feasibility randomised <lb/>controlled trial <lb/>Sally Hopewell <lb/>, 1 Cynthia Srikesavan, 2,3 Alison Evans, 4 Fema Er, 1 <lb/>Amar Rangan <lb/>, 5,6 Jane Preece, 7 Anne Francis, 1 M Sofia Massa <lb/>, 1 <lb/>Marc Feldmann, 4 Sarah Lamb, 3 Jagdeep Nanchahal 4 <lb/>To cite: Hopewell S, <lb/>Srikesavan C, Evans A, et al. <lb/>Anti-TNF (adalimumab) <lb/>injection for the treatment of <lb/>pain-predominant early-stage <lb/>frozen shoulder: the Anti-<lb/>Freaze-Feasibility randomised <lb/>controlled trial. BMJ Open <lb/>2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/>► Prepublication history <lb/>and additional supplemental <lb/>material for this paper are <lb/>available online. To view these <lb/>files, please visit the journal <lb/>online (https://doi.org/10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2023-078273). <lb/>Received 31 July 2023 <lb/>Accepted 01 March 2024 <lb/>For numbered affiliations see <lb/>end of article. <lb/>Correspondence to <lb/>Dr Sally Hopewell; <lb/>sally. hopewell@ csm. ox. ac. uk <lb/>Original research <lb/>© Author(s) (or their <lb/>employer(s)) 2024. Re-use <lb/>permitted under CC BY. <lb/>Published by BMJ. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Objective The Anti-Freaze-F (AFF) trial assessed the <lb/>feasibility of conducting a definitive trial to determine <lb/>whether intra-articular injection of adalimumab can <lb/>reduce pain and improve function in people with pain-<lb/>predominant early-stage frozen shoulder. <lb/>Design Multicentre, randomised feasibility trial, with <lb/>embedded qualitative study. <lb/>Setting Four UK National Health Service (NHS) <lb/>musculoskeletal and related physiotherapy services. <lb/>Participants Adults ≥18 years with new episode of <lb/>shoulder pain attributable to early-stage frozen shoulder. <lb/>Interventions Participants were randomised (centralised <lb/>computer generated 1:1 allocation) to either ultrasound-<lb/>guided intra-articular injection of: (1) adalimumab <lb/>(160 mg) or (2) placebo (saline (0.9% sodium chloride)). <lb/>Participants and outcome assessors were blinded to <lb/>treatment allocation. Second injection of allocated <lb/>treatment (adalimumab 80 mg) or equivalent placebo was <lb/>administered 2-3 weeks later. <lb/>Primary feasibility objectives (1) Ability to screen and <lb/>identify participants; (2) willingness of eligible participants <lb/>to consent and be randomised; (3) practicalities of <lb/>delivering the intervention; (4) SD of the Shoulder Pain <lb/>and Disability Index (SPADI) score and attrition rate at 3 <lb/>months. <lb/>Results Between 31 May 2022 and 7 February 2023, <lb/>156 patients were screened of whom 39 (25%) were <lb/>eligible. The main reasons for ineligibility were other <lb/>shoulder disorder (38.5%; n=45/117) or no longer in <lb/>pain-predominant frozen shoulder (33.3%; n=39/117). <lb/>Of the 39 eligible patients, nine (23.1%) consented to be <lb/>randomised (adalimumab n=4; placebo n=5). The main <lb/>reason patients declined was because they preferred <lb/>receiving steroid injection (n=13). All participants received <lb/>treatment as allocated. The mean time from randomisation <lb/>to first injection was 12.3 (adalimumab) and 7.2 days <lb/>(placebo). Completion rates for patient-reported and <lb/>clinician-assessed outcomes were 100%. <lb/>Conclusion This study demonstrated that current NHS <lb/>musculoskeletal physiotherapy settings yielded only small <lb/>numbers of participants, too few to make a trial viable. <lb/>This was because many patients had passed the early <lb/>stage of frozen shoulder or had already formulated a <lb/>preference for treatment. <lb/>Trial registration number ISRCTN 27075727, EudraCT <lb/>2021-03509-23, ClinicalTrials. gov NCT05299242 (REC 21/ <lb/>NE/0214). <lb/></front>
        
        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Frozen shoulder (adhesive capsulitis) is a <lb/>common and extremely painful and debili-<lb/>tating condition. Affected individuals struggle <lb/>with activities of daily living and significant <lb/>sleep disturbances as a result of severe pain. 1 <lb/></body>
        
        <front>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY <lb/>⇒ The Anti-Freaze-F study was a pilot randomised <lb/>controlled trial with an embedded qualitative study <lb/>to test the effectiveness of a new treatment for <lb/>people with early stage, pain-predominant frozen <lb/>shoulder. <lb/>⇒ Participants were randomised (centralised comput-<lb/>er generated 1:1 allocation) to either ultrasound-<lb/>guided intra-articular injection of adalimumab or <lb/>placebo injection. Participants and outcome asses-<lb/>sors were blinded to treatment allocation. <lb/>⇒ We assessed the feasibility of conducting a large <lb/>multicentre randomised trial in terms of the ability <lb/>to screen and identify participants, their willingness <lb/>to consent and be randomised, the practicalities of <lb/>delivering the intervention and attrition rates at 3 <lb/>months. <lb/>⇒ While all nine participants recruited into the trial re-<lb/>ceived both their first and second injections within <lb/>the specific timeframe, it is unclear whether this <lb/>would be same for larger definitive trial. <lb/>⇒ Similarly, while all participants completed both <lb/>patient-reported and clinician-assessed outcomes <lb/>at 3 months, it is unlikely this would be same for <lb/>larger trial with longer follow-up. <lb/></front>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>2 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <body>It affects about 9% of people in the United Kingdom (UK) <lb/>aged 25-64 years, 2 and 20% develop the same problem <lb/>in the other shoulder. 3 Frozen shoulder may develop as <lb/>a primary condition or secondarily following surgery or <lb/>trauma. <lb/>The classic description of the development of frozen <lb/>shoulder is of three overlapping phases. 4 5 The initial <lb/>pain-predominant inflammatory phase is character-<lb/>ised by constant pain and difficulty sleeping and lasts <lb/>between 3 and 9 months. This progresses to a stiffness-<lb/>predominant fibrotic phase, with progressive restriction <lb/>of motion, particularly external rotation and elevation <lb/>of the shoulder, and impairment of function and lasts <lb/>between 4 and 12 months. The pain changes from being <lb/>constant to being manifest at the end of range of motion <lb/>and of reduced intensity. Over the final phase, there is <lb/>a gradual improvement in range of motion and stiffness <lb/>over a 12 to 48-month period, although pain may persist <lb/>with end-range movements. The average duration of the <lb/>condition is 30 months (range 1-3.5 years) although full <lb/>resolution of symptoms does not always occur. 6 <lb/>The aetiology of frozen shoulder is poorly understood <lb/>and consequently there is no consensus on the optimal <lb/>treatment. The majority of patients with early-stage pain-<lb/>predominant frozen shoulder are managed in primary <lb/>care or at primary care interface musculoskeletal services <lb/>by physiotherapists and general practitioners. During <lb/>this stage, standard treatment consists of rest, advice, <lb/>analgesics, physiotherapy and corticosteroid injections <lb/>to address the symptoms. Current treatments available <lb/>to patients with frozen shoulder are of limited efficacy. <lb/>Two Cochrane reviews concluded that while oral steroid <lb/>or local steroid injections lead to short-term benefit <lb/>in pain and range of motion, the effects are not main-<lb/>tained beyond 6 weeks. 7 8 A more recent systematic review <lb/>(based on data from five randomised trials) also found <lb/>some benefit of corticosteroid injection compared with <lb/>placebo, but this pain relief was not sustained in the long <lb/>term. 9 Other Cochrane reviews concluded that there is <lb/>no evidence that physiotherapy or ultrasound therapy are <lb/>beneficial, 10 and that manual therapy with exercise is less <lb/>effective than corticosteroid injection in the short term. 11 <lb/>The UK FROST compared the effects of physiotherapy <lb/>plus corticosteroid injection, manipulation under anaes-<lb/>thesia with a steroid injection, and arthroscopic capsular <lb/>release supplemented with manipulation. 12 None of the <lb/>treatments was found to be clinically superior. <lb/>Our study (Anti-Freaze-F) was designed to specifically <lb/>target people with early-stage pain-predominant frozen <lb/>shoulder. We assessed the feasibility of conducting a large <lb/>multicentre randomised trial to test whether giving an <lb/>intra-articular injection of adalimumab (a drug targeting <lb/>the inflammatory mediator tumour necrosis factor <lb/>(TNF)) can reduce pain and prevent the condition from <lb/>getting worse, if given during the early pain-predominant <lb/>stage. <lb/>Approximately 50% of people with frozen shoulder also <lb/>develop Dupuytren&apos;s disease. 13 Dupuytren&apos;s disease has a <lb/>prominent genetic component, and in a study of twins, <lb/>the heritability was estimated at 80%. 14 We have recently <lb/>confirmed that there is a significant genetic correlation <lb/>between Dupuytren&apos;s disease and frozen shoulder. 15 <lb/>The pathology of the two conditions has several similar-<lb/>ities. 16 17 A systematic review of the pathophysiology of <lb/>frozen shoulder identified the presence of fibrosis and <lb/>the role of inflammation. 6 The affected tissues are infil-<lb/>trated by immune cells and there are elevated levels of <lb/>proinflammatory cytokines, including TNF, 18 19 with <lb/>myofibroblasts driving the development of fibrosis. 16 In <lb/>a dose-ranging proof of concept phase 2a followed by <lb/>a 2b clinical trial (RIDD trial), we found that injection <lb/>of anti-TNF (adalimumab) directly into Dupuytren&apos;s <lb/>nodules led to significant downregulation of the myofi-<lb/>broblast phenotype and reduction in nodule hardness <lb/>(primary endpoint) and nodule size on ultrasound scan <lb/>(secondary endpoint). 20 21 <lb/>Objectives <lb/>The aim of the Anti-Freaze-F (AFF) trial was to assess the <lb/>feasibility of conducting a large randomised controlled <lb/>trial to assess whether an intra-articular injection of <lb/>adalimumab (anti-TNF) can reduce pain and improve <lb/>function in people with early-stage frozen shoulder. The <lb/>primary objectives were to assess the: <lb/>► Ability to screen and identify potential participants <lb/>with pain-predominant early stage frozen shoulder. <lb/>► Willingness of eligible participants to consent and be <lb/>randomised to intervention. <lb/>► Practicalities of delivering the intervention, including <lb/>time to first injection and number of participants <lb/>receiving second injection. <lb/>► SD of the Shoulder Pain and Disability Index (SPADI) <lb/>score and attrition rate at 3 months (ie, 12 weeks) <lb/>postrandomisation in order to estimate the sample <lb/>size for a definitive trial. <lb/>Secondary objectives were to assess the follow-up rates <lb/>and viability of patient-reported outcome measures and <lb/>clinician-assessed shoulder range of motion at 3 months <lb/>(ie, 12 weeks). <lb/>The objectives of the embedded qualitative study were <lb/>to explore the participant experience of being recruited <lb/>to the AFF trial, the treatment received and follow-up <lb/>schedule, and to understand what helps participant <lb/>recruitment to the trial intervention. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Study design <lb/>A multi-centre, randomised, double-blind, parallel group, <lb/>feasibility trial with an embedded qualitative study. <lb/>Setting <lb/>Participants were recruited from four National Health <lb/>Service (NHS) musculoskeletal services and their related <lb/>physiotherapy services, with treatment delivered within <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>3 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <body>these services or local secondary care dependant on the <lb/>local service provision. <lb/>Study participants <lb/>Participants were eligible if they were aged 18 years and <lb/>above with a new episode of shoulder pain attributable <lb/>to pain-predominant stage of frozen shoulder (ie, within <lb/>approximately 3 to 9 months of onset of symptoms), <lb/>which was diagnosed clinically using the criteria set out <lb/>in the British Elbow and Shoulder Society (BESS) guide-<lb/>lines. 22 In line with the trial protocol, imaging, including <lb/>plain radiographs, may be used to help confirm a diag-<lb/>nosis of frozen shoulder by excluding other pathology <lb/>such as glenohumeral arthritis as per standard NHS <lb/>care. However, is not always necessary and hence routine <lb/>radiology was not as part of the trial procedures. 23 Patients <lb/>were excluded if they had frozen shoulder secondary to <lb/>significant shoulder trauma; other shoulder disorders <lb/>(eg, inflammatory arthritis, rotator cuff disorders, gleno-<lb/>humeral joint instability) or with red flags consistent <lb/>with the criteria set out in the BESS guidelines 22 ; bilat-<lb/>eral early stage frozen shoulder; had received corticoste-<lb/>roid injection for shoulder pain in the last 12 weeks; were <lb/>currently taking any anti-TNF drug, or being treated <lb/>with coumarin anticoagulants, such as warfarin; had <lb/>significant renal or hepatic impairment, or had contra-<lb/>indications to anti-TNF injection. Detailed inclusion and <lb/>exclusion criteria are described in the trial protocol. 23 <lb/>Patients who met the eligibility criteria and wanted <lb/>to participate were approached for written informed <lb/>consent by a research facilitator trained in Good Clinical <lb/>Practice at each participating site. All participants under-<lb/>went serological testing to check for latent tuberculosis <lb/>(TB) and hepatitis B surface antigen. The blood tests <lb/>were performed during the baseline assessment or at <lb/>the time the participant attended for their first injection <lb/>appointment (depending on the local site provision). <lb/>The risks of reactivation following a single injection are <lb/>low. If any participants had shown a positive serology test <lb/>result, they would have been referred to their local infec-<lb/>tious disease service and would not have received the <lb/>second injection. <lb/>Randomisation <lb/>Consented participants were randomly assigned to <lb/>receive either: (1) intra-articular injection of adalimumab <lb/>or (2) placebo injection (saline (0.9% sodium chloride), <lb/>both under ultrasound guidance. Randomisation (1:1) <lb/>was done by the research facilitator at each site using <lb/>the centralised randomisation service provided by the <lb/>Oxford Clinical Trials Research Unit once the patient was <lb/>enrolled and baseline assessment and questionnaire were <lb/>completed. Randomisation was computer generated and <lb/>stratified by study site using a variable block size (variable <lb/>block sizes of 2, 4 and 6 in a ratio of 1:2:1) to ensure the <lb/>participants from each study site had equal chance of <lb/>receiving either intervention. <lb/>Blinding <lb/>Study participants and site staff, except pharmacy staff, <lb/>were blinded to treatment allocation. The clinician deliv-<lb/>ering the treatment injection was not blinded but was not <lb/>involved in further trial-specific assessment of the partici-<lb/>pant. The trial statistician and data entry personnel were <lb/>not blinded to the treatment allocation. The remaining <lb/>members of the trial management team, including the <lb/>staff conducting the qualitative interviews, were blinded <lb/>to treatment allocation until after data analysis was <lb/>complete. <lb/>Adalimumab/placebo injection <lb/>As per their treatment allocation, participants received <lb/>either intra-articular injection of adalimumab (160 mg in <lb/>3.2 mL for the first injection, 80 mg in 1.6 mL for second <lb/>injection) or placebo (normal saline (0.9% sodium chlo-<lb/>ride) 3.2 mL for the first injection and 1.6 mL for the <lb/>second injection). Full details of the injection delivery <lb/>have been reported previously 23 and are described here <lb/>in brief. <lb/>Appointments were coordinated, so that participants <lb/>received their first injection within approximately 2 weeks <lb/>of randomisation, and second injection 2-3 weeks after <lb/>the first (unless the participant declined, tested positive <lb/>for TB or hepatitis B surface antigen or had a related <lb/>grade 3 or above adverse event). The injection was given <lb/>into the anterior shoulder joint space in the rotator cuff <lb/>interval where there is maximal inflammation of the <lb/>capsule and synovium, 24 under guided ultrasound by an <lb/>appropriately qualified practitioner. <lb/>The adalimumab/placebo injection was dispensed <lb/>by the local site pharmacy and sealed in identical sized <lb/>and sealed opaque packaging. Preparation of the adali-<lb/>mumab/placebo injection took place in a clinic room/ <lb/>area separate from the participant to ensure the partic-<lb/>ipant remained blinded to treatment allocation. Both <lb/>adalimumab and placebo have a similar appearance; <lb/>therefore, the two treatments are indistinguishable. <lb/>The skin at the site of injection of adalimumab/placebo <lb/>was infiltrated with local anaesthetic to reduce the pain <lb/>of the injection as per local practice. Injection details, <lb/>including success of the intra-articular injection (ie, <lb/>fully or partial), were recorded on a trial-specific injec-<lb/>tion treatment log. <lb/>All participants received a written physiotherapy advice <lb/>leaflet providing education and advice about frozen <lb/>shoulder and pain management. 4 The advice leaflet also <lb/>included simple self-guided exercises, which participants <lb/>could use to increase shoulder joint movements, once the <lb/>early pain-predominant stage reduced. Participants were <lb/>advised they may seek other forms of treatment during <lb/>the follow-up period of the trial but were informed that <lb/>they should use usual routes (eg, through GP referral) to <lb/>do so. Participants were also advised that they could seek <lb/>corticosteroid injection but were asked to wait until after <lb/>the 3-month follow-up period. <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>4 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <body>Outcome measures <lb/>Feasibility success criteria <lb/>To determine the feasibility of a definitive randomised <lb/>controlled trial, the prespecified success criteria were: <lb/>► Feasibility to recruit: ≥33% of potentially eligible <lb/>patients with frozen shoulder screened eligible for <lb/>recruitment. <lb/>► Success of consent process: ≥33% of eligible partici-<lb/>pants consented. <lb/>► Intervention delivery: ≥75% of participants receive first <lb/>injection as randomised within specified timeframe. <lb/>In addition, we collected outcomes at baseline and at <lb/>3 months to assess the feasibility of collecting these in a <lb/>future definitive trial and to obtain the variability esti-<lb/>mates required for estimation of the sample size of a <lb/>definitive trial. Patient-reported outcomes, collected via <lb/>online/paper questionnaire, included shoulder pain <lb/>and function measured using the SPADI scale (primary <lb/>outcome for definitive trial); 25 26 subdomains of pain <lb/>(SPADI 5-item pain subscale), function (SPADI 8-item <lb/>disability subscale) 25 26 ; shoulder range of motion (Partic-<lb/>ipant Shoulder Movement Questionnaire); psycholog-<lb/>ical factors (Fear-Avoidance Belief Questionnaire) 27 ; <lb/>pain self-efficacy questionnaire 28 ; sleep disturbance <lb/>(Insomnia Severity Index) 29 ; patient global impression <lb/>of change 30 ; return to desired activities; and additional <lb/>health resource use. At baseline and the 3-month face-to-<lb/>face follow-up appointment, a blinded assessor measured <lb/>the shoulder movements including active flexion, exten-<lb/>sion, abduction internal and external rotations, using a <lb/>manual goniometer. <lb/>Adverse events <lb/>The safety profile of adalimumab is well known, with <lb/>the most common adverse reactions being mild injec-<lb/>tion site reactions. The Common Terminology Criteria <lb/>for Adverse Events (CTCAE) V.5.0 was used to guide <lb/>recording of any adverse events including grading of <lb/>the event. Only clinician-assessed adverse events, graded <lb/>3 and above, occurring during the trial for each partic-<lb/>ipant, from their consent until the 3-month follow-up, <lb/>related to the trial medication (adalimumab/placebo) <lb/>were recorded. <lb/>Sample size <lb/>The main feasibility objective and, therefore, the basis <lb/>of the sample size estimate were participant recruitment <lb/>per centre. The target sample size was 84 participants, <lb/>equivalent of 1 to 2 participants per month per site over <lb/>12 months. Seventy is the recommended minimum target <lb/>sample size when including an estimate of the SD in an <lb/>external pilot trial. 31 The sample size was increased to 84 <lb/>to increase precision of the estimate of the SD of SPADI <lb/>at 3 months, the proposed primary outcome for the defin-<lb/>itive trial and to consider possible attrition based on an <lb/>attrition rate of 15%. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Feasibility outcomes were reported as numbers and <lb/>percentages. Baseline characteristics and outcome <lb/>measures were reported using descriptive statistics, sepa-<lb/>rately per group and overall, using either the mean and <lb/>SD for continuous variables and number and percentage <lb/>of participants in each group for categorical variables. <lb/>Embedded qualitative study <lb/>We planned to interview a purposive sample of up to 15 <lb/>participants (or until we reach data saturation) to provide <lb/>variability for age, gender, ethnicity and geographical <lb/>representation. A qualitative researcher (CS), blinded to <lb/>treatment allocation, conducted the telephone interviews <lb/>using a semistructured interview guide with open-ended <lb/>questions. Interviews were audio-taped and transcribed <lb/>verbatim. Data were analysed following Braun and <lb/>Clarke&apos;s thematic analysis method. 32 Interviews were <lb/>coded using NVivo qualitative software V.12 and catego-<lb/>rised into themes. Participant narrative quotes were used <lb/>to illustrate the themes. <lb/>Patient and public involvement <lb/>Patient representatives were involved in the design, <lb/>conduct and reporting of study, including reviewing of <lb/>patient-facing study materials (eg, patient information <lb/>sheet, physiotherapy advice booklet and patient follow-up <lb/>questionnaires) and through involvement of the trial <lb/>management and trial oversight committees. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Regulatory approvals were obtained on 22 December <lb/>2021. Patient screening and enrolment began 31 May <lb/>2022 and ended 7 February 2023; completion of the <lb/>3-month outcome assessment and follow-up ended 9 <lb/>May 2023. Delays in obtaining site approvals due to the <lb/>continuing impact of COVID-19 on staffing levels meant <lb/>that site opening and thus patient screening was delayed, <lb/>resulting in the recruitment period being just over <lb/>8 months as opposed to the planned 12 months. Delays <lb/>in local approvals at sites also meant we were only able <lb/>to open four of the planned five sites as stipulated in the <lb/>trial protocol. <lb/>Feasibility objectives <lb/>Feasibility to recruit <lb/>Of the 156 patients screened, 39 (25%) were eligible for <lb/>the trial. The main reasons screened patients were not <lb/>eligible were because they had other shoulder disorders <lb/>(eg, inflammatory arthritis, rotator cuff disorders, gleno-<lb/>humeral joint instability) (n=45/117; 38.5%); were no <lb/>longer in the pain-predominant stage of frozen shoulder <lb/>(n=39/117; 33.3%); had frozen shoulder due to signifi-<lb/>cant shoulder trauma or other causes (eg, recent breast <lb/>cancer surgery) (n=11/117; 9.4%); had bilateral early <lb/>stage frozen shoulder (n=7/117; 6.0%) or had received <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>5 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <body>corticosteroid injection for shoulder pain within the last <lb/>12 weeks to either shoulder (n=5/117; 4.3%) (figure 1). <lb/>Success of consent process <lb/>Of the 39 patients eligible for the trial, 29 (74.4%) <lb/>declined to participate, the main reasons being they <lb/>already had a treatment preference for receiving <lb/>steroid injection (n=13/29; 44.8%), did not wish to be <lb/>randomised (n=7/29; 24.1%) or already had a treat-<lb/>ment preference for not receiving an injection (n=4/29; <lb/>13.8%). In addition, one patient who was eligible was <lb/>not consented due to close of trial recruitment. This <lb/>resulted in nine (n=9/39; 23.1%) eligible patients being <lb/>consented into the trial (figure 1); four were randomised <lb/>to receive adalimumab injection and five to placebo injec-<lb/>tion. Baseline characteristics are summarised in table 1. <lb/>Participants had a mean age of 54.9 (SD 5.6) years and <lb/>three (33.3%) of the nine participants were women; all <lb/>were white British. The average (mean) duration of symp-<lb/>toms was 15.4 weeks (SD 9.0). The mean SPADI score at <lb/>baseline (primary outcome for definitive trial) was 70.8 <lb/>(SD 16.6) for the adalimumab group and 55.4 (SD 21.5) <lb/>for the placebo group. <lb/>Intervention delivery <lb/>All participants received their treatment as allocated <lb/>and in line with the trial protocol. The mean time from <lb/>randomisation to first injection was 12.3 days for the adali-<lb/>mumab group and 7.2 days for the placebo group. One <lb/>participant in the adalimumab group received their injec-<lb/>tion 18 days post-randomisation as they were not available <lb/>until then. The mean time from receiving first to second <lb/>injection was similar for adalimumab (18.5 days) and <lb/>placebo (20.8 days) (table 2). <lb/>Patient retention and outcome measure data collection <lb/>Data for patient-reported outcomes and clinician-<lb/>assessed range of shoulder motions are shown in online <lb/>supplemental tables S1-S3. The completion rates at <lb/>baseline and 3 months were 100% (n=9/9) for both <lb/>patient-reported outcomes, completed by questionnaire, <lb/>and clinician-assessed shoulder motion. Between-group <lb/>difference were not calculated as only nine participants <lb/>were recruited into the trial. Online supplemental figure <lb/>S1 shows the change from baseline and at 3 months for <lb/>shoulder pain and function (measured using the SPADI <lb/>scale) per participant for adalimumab and placebo <lb/>injection. <lb/>Adverse events <lb/>No graded 3 or above, adverse events occurred during <lb/>the trial related to the trial medication (adalimumab/ <lb/>placebo). <lb/>Embedded qualitative study <lb/>Eight participants took part in the telephone interviews <lb/>(four from each injection group), which included six <lb/>men and two women with an average age of 55.5 years <lb/>(range 46 to 62 years). The average duration of interviews <lb/>was 24 min (range 14 min-31 min). Five participants had <lb/>received both injections at the time of interviews. Four key <lb/>themes emerged: (1) experiences with pain-predominant <lb/>stage of frozen shoulder; (2) perceptions about partici-<lb/>pating in the AFF trial; (3) perceptions about the trial <lb/>processes and (4) perceptions about the effects of injec-<lb/>tions. Themes and illustrative quotes are presented in <lb/>table 3. <lb/>Experiences with pain-predominant phase of frozen shoulder <lb/>This theme describes the impact of the pain-predominant <lb/>phase of the frozen shoulder. Most participants reported <lb/>severe levels of pain, particularly with certain move-<lb/>ments or during sleep. The shoulder pain was described <lb/>as &apos;very acute&apos;, &apos;annoying&apos;, &apos;disruptive&apos;, &apos;excruciating&apos; <lb/>or &apos;completely unbearable&apos;. Participants also discussed <lb/>how their everyday function was limited (eg, difficulties <lb/>with getting dressed or driving). Sleep was substantially <lb/>affected by pain, with participants reporting shorter sleep <lb/>times and poorer sleep quality. They frequently woke up <lb/>in the night due to severe pain while changing position. <lb/>Perceptions about participating in the trial <lb/>This theme describes the participants&apos; views on partici-<lb/>pating in the AFF trial. Overall, participants were keen to <lb/>find a solution to their shoulder problem. Severe pain, <lb/>reduced function and sleep and previous treatments <lb/>such as steroid injections or physiotherapy that were not <lb/>helpful were other reasons that influenced their decision <lb/>to take part. Participants also reported altruistic reasons to <lb/>benefit others with similar problems. Their expectations <lb/>on taking part were to get adalimumab injection, pain <lb/>relief and improved function. Participants also expressed <lb/>a clear understanding and acceptance of the randomi-<lb/>sation process, mainly attributing to the trial-related <lb/>information provided to them. Having a 50% chance of <lb/>getting the placebo injection was a concern. However, <lb/>participants discussed various reasons, including long <lb/>waiting time for steroid injections, positive expectations <lb/>about adalimumab and flexibility to access standard care <lb/>(if AFF trial injections did not work) that helped them <lb/>take a &apos;balanced view&apos; in participating. <lb/>Perceptions about trial processes <lb/>This theme describes participant views about trial <lb/>processes, including provision of information, delivery of <lb/>injections, outcome assessments and their overall experi-<lb/>ence. Participants described that all trial-related informa-<lb/>tion such as randomisation and delivery of injections was <lb/>communicated effectively, with opportunities to clarify <lb/>their queries and make a decision. Injection appoint-<lb/>ments were scheduled quickly, and participants were <lb/>well-informed and supported during the sessions. Many <lb/>reported discomfort at the time of injections. Participants <lb/>perceived the outcome measurements (clinician-assessed <lb/>measurements and self-reports) as relevant to their condi-<lb/>tion and had no issues completing them. They also high-<lb/>lighted their positive experiences with the trial personnel <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>6 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <body>Figure 1 Participant flow diagram. BESS British Elbow and Shoulder Society; TNF, tumour necrosis factor. <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>7 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <body>at study sites and reported an overall positive experience <lb/>of participating in the AFF trial. <lb/>Perceived effects of adalimumab and placebo injections <lb/>Two participants who received adalimumab injections <lb/>reported improvements in pain and/or shoulder move-<lb/>ments. Another participant reported some pain relief <lb/>after the first injection. Pain remained unchanged and <lb/>movement decreased after the second injection. One <lb/>participant who had received first injection only reported <lb/>improvement in movement. Two participants who <lb/>received placebo injections reported increased pain after <lb/>their first injection that persisted after the second injec-<lb/>tion. Of the two participants who had only their first injec-<lb/>tion, one reported noticeable improvement in pain and <lb/>movement; the other reported increased pain. Two partic-<lb/>ipants (one from each group) were concerned about the <lb/>increased pain after the injections. Other concerns were <lb/>expectations about the long-term effects of adalimumab <lb/>and continued access to physiotherapy within the trial. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Our findings show that a definitive trial to assess whether <lb/>an intra-articular injection of adalimumab (anti-TNF) can <lb/>reduce pain and improve function in people with early-<lb/>stage frozen shoulder was not feasible within the NHS <lb/>musculoskeletal and related physiotherapy services that <lb/>participated in the AFF trial. Only a quarter of the people <lb/>screened were eligible to take part in this feasibility study; <lb/>of those eligible, only nine consented to be randomised. <lb/>Key themes from the semistructured interviews provided <lb/>a useful insight into the trial and focused on the partic-<lb/>ipant experiences during the pain-dominant stage of <lb/>frozen shoulder and their perceptions about trial partici-<lb/>pation, trial processes and outcomes following injection. <lb/>One of the main reasons people were ineligible to take <lb/>part in the AFF trial was because they were no longer in the <lb/>pain-predominant phase of frozen shoulder by the time they <lb/>were seen by the physiotherapist. People no longer being in <lb/>the pain-predominant phase of frozen shoulder is indicative <lb/>of long waiting lists and time taken to be seen across NHS <lb/>musculoskeletal and related physiotherapy services and was <lb/>a major barrier in terms of trial feasibility. Long waiting <lb/>times is a problem across the NHS, particularly during and <lb/>after the COVID-19 pandemic; 33 the period in which the <lb/>AFF trial was recruiting and not specific to people with <lb/>frozen shoulder. The four NHS sites that participated in the <lb/>AFF trial represented several different musculoskeletal and <lb/>physiotherapy service delivery approaches, with approaches <lb/>also changing during and post the COVID-19 pandemic. <lb/>Several of these sites also included a small number of First <lb/>Contact Practitioners (FCPs) embedded with primary care. <lb/>Table 1 Baseline characteristics by intervention group <lb/>Adalimumab <lb/>(n=4) <lb/>Placebo <lb/>(n=5) <lb/>Total <lb/>(n=9) <lb/>Age* <lb/>57.5 (5.9) <lb/>52.8 (5.0) <lb/>54.9 (5.6) <lb/>Sex † <lb/>Male <lb/>3 (75.0%) <lb/>3 (60.0%) <lb/>6 (66.7%) <lb/>Female <lb/>1 (25.0%) <lb/>2 (40.0%) <lb/>3 (33.3%) <lb/>Ethnicity † <lb/>White British <lb/>4 (100.0%) <lb/>5 (100.0%) 9 (100.0%) <lb/>Handedness † <lb/>Left <lb/>2 (50.0%) <lb/>1 (20.0%) <lb/>3 (33.3%) <lb/>Right <lb/>2 (50.0%) <lb/>4 (80.0%) <lb/>6 (66.7%) <lb/>Duration of <lb/>symptoms <lb/>(weeks)* <lb/>19.5 (13.1) <lb/>12.2 (2.3) <lb/>15.4 (9.0) <lb/>Affected shoulder † <lb/>Left <lb/>3 (75.0%) <lb/>2 (40.0%) <lb/>5 (55.6%) <lb/>Right <lb/>1 (25.0%) <lb/>3 (60.0%) <lb/>4 (44.4%) <lb/>BMI (kg/m 2 )* <lb/>29.5 (5.8) <lb/>30.3 (5.3) <lb/>30.0 (5.2) <lb/>Smoking status † <lb/>Never smoked 4 (100.0%) <lb/>3 (60.0%) <lb/>7 (77.8%) <lb/>Former smoker 0 <lb/>2 (40.0%) <lb/>2 (22.2%) <lb/>If ever smoked, <lb/>number of <lb/>cigarettes/day* <lb/>0 <lb/>12 (11.3) <lb/>12 (11.3) <lb/>Dupuytren&apos;s disease † <lb/>No <lb/>4 (100.0%) <lb/>4 (80.0%) <lb/>8 (88.9%) <lb/>Yes <lb/>0 <lb/>1 (20.0%) <lb/>1 (11.1%) <lb/>Diabetes † <lb/>Type 1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 (20.0%) <lb/>1 (11.1%) <lb/>Type 2 <lb/>1 (25.0%) <lb/>2 (40.0%) <lb/>3 (33.3%) <lb/>No <lb/>3 (75.0%) <lb/>2 (40.0%) <lb/>5 (55.6%) <lb/>* Summaries are mean (SD). <lb/> †Summaries are n (%). <lb/>Table 2 Injection delivery <lb/>Adalimumab <lb/>(n=4) <lb/>Placebo <lb/>(n=5) <lb/>Overall <lb/>(n=9) <lb/>First injection given* 4 (100%) <lb/>5 (100%) 9 (100%) <lb/>Time from <lb/>randomisation to first <lb/>injection (days) † <lb/>12.3 (4.8) <lb/>7.2 (4.1) <lb/>9.4 (4.9) <lb/>Injection administered?* <lb/>Yes-fully <lb/>4 (100%) <lb/>5 (100%) 9 (100%) <lb/>Second injection <lb/>given* <lb/>4 (100%) <lb/>5 (100%) 9 (100%) <lb/>Time from first to <lb/>second injection <lb/>(days) † <lb/>18.5 (3.3) <lb/>20.8 (5.9) 19.8 (4.8) <lb/>Injection administered?* <lb/>Yes-fully <lb/>4 (100%) <lb/>5 (100%) 9 (100%) <lb/>*Summaries are n (%). <lb/> †Summaries are mean (SD). <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>8 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <body>However, given the very small number of trial participants <lb/>and small number of FCPs, we are not able to determine <lb/>whether moving intervention delivery earlier in the patient <lb/>pathway would have improved recruitment. In addition, <lb/>our early feasibility work to identify potential trial sites <lb/>identified lack of local site pharmacy (ie, for storage and <lb/>dispensing of adalimumab) and delivery of injection under <lb/>ultrasound guidance was a major barrier to conducting the <lb/>AFF trial in primary care and should be considered for any <lb/>future trial. <lb/>We employed a number of different recruitment strat-<lb/>egies to try and maximise recruitment at sites. This <lb/>included sending targeted trial information packs to <lb/>GPs and healthcare professionals, such as FCPs, within a <lb/>15 mile radius of each recruiting site. We promoted the <lb/>trial at scientific conferences targeting clinicians in the <lb/>Table 3 Themes and participant quotes from qualitative interviews <lb/>Themes <lb/>Narrative quotes <lb/>Experiences with <lb/>pain-predominant <lb/>phase of frozen <lb/>shoulder <lb/>► &apos;I always put childbirth as a 10, so I always come back from that really, so I would say it was kind of like <lb/>an eight to nine (Adalimumab) <lb/>► &apos;It affects when I pretty much … every day, whatever I&apos;m doing&apos; (Placebo) <lb/>► &apos; it just doesn&apos;t help me sleeping. I&apos;m getting about three hours and max four hours at nights…&apos; <lb/>(Placebo) <lb/>Perceptions about <lb/>participation in the <lb/>trial <lb/>► &apos;…if it&apos;s gonna help me and help other people then, yeah, it&apos;s something I&apos;d do&apos; (Placebo) <lb/>► &apos;My first thought was yes, I was very happy to, primarily because the current treatment hadn&apos;t been <lb/>particularly successful and I was in still quite a bit of pain and struggling to sleep very well and I thought <lb/>the fact that another option was being made available, I was more than comfortable to participate&apos; <lb/>(Adalimumab) <lb/>► &apos;my expectation really was that if I did get the drug it was likely that I would see some kind of <lb/>improvement&apos; (Adalimumab) <lb/>► &apos;I hoped that I got the drug and not the placebo and it helped&apos; (Adalimumab) <lb/>► &apos;I accepted that that&apos;s now how drug trials work and, therefore, I knew there was a possibility that I may <lb/>not be receiving the drug&apos; (Adalimumab) <lb/>► &apos;I mean initially I was concerned because if I was the placebo I felt that potentially I was gonna be, well <lb/>maybe three months further down the line having had the placebo and no benefit. And then I&apos;d have <lb/>to go back to square one so I was slightly anxious about that. But I was reassured that it, you know, it <lb/>wasn&apos;t stopping me then getting further treatment if I hadn&apos;t had any response to the injections. And I <lb/>guess, this is a bit sceptical of me that waiting lists are what they are but I probably would have been <lb/>waiting three months for a steroid injection anyway. So, I didn&apos;t think it as a disadvantage to do the trial <lb/>really. If it worked, great, and if it didn&apos;t, then I&apos;d--like I say, I&apos;d go back to the GP&apos; (Placebo) <lb/>Perceptions about <lb/>trial processes <lb/>► &apos;I couldn&apos;t fault the information I was given to be honest, they were very good&apos; (Placebo) <lb/>► &apos;I just went in had the injection. It wasn&apos;t very pleasant. It was quite…quite painful. It did make me feel a <lb/>little bit queasy at the time&apos; (Adalimumab) <lb/>► &apos;I was happy to do that because I understand that they have to gauge any improvement in my shoulder <lb/>movements over time. So, yeah, I was happy to complete those movements&apos; (Placebo) <lb/>► &apos;I mean it all went well. I was seen on time, everything was ready. Everything went to plan&apos; <lb/>(Adalimumab) <lb/>► &apos;I&apos;m really delighted that I&apos;m part of the trial now because I&apos;m seeing the benefit of it already. So, I&apos;m <lb/>very … I&apos;m thrilled. I feel very lucky… I mean I do feel--I feel honoured and I feel like they&apos;ve treated me <lb/>so well&apos; (Placebo) <lb/>Perceptions <lb/>about effects of <lb/>adalimumab and <lb/>placebo injections <lb/>After first and second adalimumab injections <lb/>► &apos;I think there was a noticeable improvement from the first injection. Perhaps a slightly… bit of an extra <lb/>improvement after the second one. But I think it was quite noticeable following that first injection&apos; <lb/>(Adalimumab) <lb/>► Perhaps a slightly… bit of an extra improvement after the second one. But I think it was quite <lb/>noticeable following that first injection&apos;. I definitely have got significant reduction in the pain. I&apos;ve got <lb/>more what I would say is a tightness in the muscular areas now, so this almost feels as though where I <lb/>was on the old regime -pre-trial&apos; (Adalimumab) <lb/>After first and second placebo injections <lb/>► &apos;once I had the first injection, my arm … the actual … the pain actually increased quite significantly in <lb/>my shoulder for a good 7 to 10 days. And I was having to take strong painkillers to sort of manage that. <lb/>It&apos;s actually settled down a bit now&apos; (Placebo) <lb/>► &apos;…there wasn&apos;t any significant increase in pain after the second injection…I&apos;ve not noticed any real <lb/>improvement since I had the second injection…I still do get the discomfort that I&apos;ve got in my shoulder&apos; <lb/>(Placebo) <lb/></body>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>9 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <body>shoulder community and created a short trial promotional <lb/>video for the Chartered Society of Physiotherapists. We <lb/>also promoted the trial on social media with input from <lb/>our patient representative, and through patient organisa-<lb/>tions such as the Dupuytren&apos;s Society and Diabetes UK to <lb/>target groups in whom the incidence of frozen shoulder is <lb/>higher. 1 13 <lb/>Another main barrier to feasibility of the trial was <lb/>because some people, who were eligible and approached <lb/>to take part in the AFF trial, already had a treatment <lb/>preference for receiving a steroid injection and declined <lb/>to participate. We did consider the use of corticosteroid <lb/>injection as opposed to placebo when designing the trial; <lb/>however, given the available evidence showing that steroid <lb/>injection only leads to short-term benefit, 8 9 we decided to <lb/>use a placebo injection of saline (0.9% sodium chloride) <lb/>as the comparator. Unlike steroid (triamcinolone), which <lb/>is a white suspension, saline has the same appearance to <lb/>adalimumab meant we were able to blind participants as to <lb/>their treatment allocation. This was especially important <lb/>given the subjective nature of some of the outcomes we <lb/>planned to assess in the definitive trial, should this study <lb/>have shown to be feasible. Interestingly, one of the main <lb/>findings from our interviews was that participants under-<lb/>stood the concept of randomisation and accepted the <lb/>possibility of receiving placebo. <lb/>Despite not meeting the feasible objectives in terms <lb/>of recruitment and success of the consent process, it was <lb/>feasible to deliver the intervention in line with the trial <lb/>protocol and all participants completed patient-reported <lb/>and clinician assessed outcomes at 3 months. Data from <lb/>the semistructured interviews showed that participants <lb/>found the overall experience of the trial was positive. <lb/>They participated in the AFF trial considering it as an <lb/>opportunity to find a solution to their shoulder problem <lb/>and also to benefit others. <lb/>Strengths <lb/>To our knowledge, AFF is the first study to assess the feasi-<lb/>bility of conducting a large multicentre trial to test the <lb/>effectiveness of a new treatment for people with early stage, <lb/>pain-predominant frozen shoulder. This is important given <lb/>the evidence for the limited effectiveness for treatments <lb/>currently offered to people with frozen shoulder. 7 8 10 11 34 <lb/>The drug adalimumab has a very strong safety profile, having <lb/>been used in over 5 million people, more than 25 000 trial <lb/>participants and approved for nine different disorders. 35 <lb/>We used a targeted injection approach using ultrasound <lb/>guidance, which was standardised across sites and meant <lb/>we were able to maintain blinding of trial participants and <lb/>members of trial team at sites. Despite the small number of <lb/>participants recruited into the trial, our interviews provided <lb/>a useful insight into patient experiences with the early <lb/>painful phase of frozen shoulder and their perceptions <lb/>about being involved in the AFF trial. AFF is one of the very <lb/>few feasibility trials of upper limb conditions that include a <lb/>qualitative component. <lb/>Limitations <lb/>A limitation of this study is that all participants were <lb/>white British with an average age of 55 years. There-<lb/>fore, the population recruited were not truly repre-<lb/>sentative of the general population or those people <lb/>affected by frozen shoulder, 36 despite recruiting from <lb/>sites within inner cities with a more diverse population <lb/>demographic. In addition, while all nine participants <lb/>recruited into the trial received both their first and <lb/>second injection within the specific timeframe, it is <lb/>unclear whether this would be same for larger defin-<lb/>itive trial with more pressure on treatment appoint-<lb/>ment slots. Similarly, while all participants completed <lb/>both patient-reported and clinician-assessed outcomes <lb/>at 3 months, it is unlikely this would be same for larger <lb/>trial with longer follow-up. In a recent trial of corti-<lb/>costeroid injection and physiotherapy in people with <lb/>a rotator cuff disorder, carried out across 20 NHS <lb/>musculoskeletal services, the attrition rate at 6 and <lb/>12 months was 13%. 37 It is also uncertain whether data <lb/>saturation was reached from the eight semistructured <lb/>interviews and, therefore. These findings may not be <lb/>generalisable and should be interpreted only within <lb/>the context of the AFF trial. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>Our findings demonstrated that a definitive trial was not <lb/>feasible within the NHS musculoskeletal and related phys-<lb/>iotherapy services that participated in the AFF trial. This <lb/>was largely due to difficulties in identifying patients while <lb/>still in early-stage frozen shoulder and patient expecta-<lb/>tions regarding steroid injection. However, it was feasible <lb/>to deliver the injection in line with trial protocol and to <lb/>collect both patient and clinician assessed outcome data. <lb/>Our interview findings indicated positive experiences <lb/>from participants who took part in the trial. <lb/></body>
        
        <div type="annex">Author affiliations <lb/>1 <lb/>Oxford Clinical Trials Research Unit, Nuffield Department of Orthopaedics, <lb/>Rheumatology and Musculoskeletal Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK <lb/>2 <lb/>Centre for Rehabilitation Research in Oxford, Nuffield Department of Orthopaedics, <lb/>Rheumatology and Musculoskeletal Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK <lb/>3 <lb/>College of Medicine and Health, University of Exeter, Exeter, UK <lb/>4 <lb/>Kennedy Institute of Rheumatology, Nuffield Department of Orthopaedics, <lb/>Rheumatology and Musculoskeletal Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK <lb/>5 <lb/>South Tees Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, The James Cook University Hospital, <lb/>Middlesbrough, UK <lb/>6 <lb/>Department of Health Sciences, University of York, York, UK <lb/>7 <lb/>Patient and Public Involvement Representative, Kidderminster, UK <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements This study is coordinated by the UKCRC registered Oxford <lb/>Clinical Trials Research Unit (OCTRU) at the University of Oxford. It followed their <lb/>Standard Operating Procedures, ensuring compliance with the principles of Good <lb/>Clinical Practice and the Declaration of Helsinki and any applicable regulatory <lb/>requirements. Special thanks go Nicola Kenealy as trial manager and Sue Dutton <lb/>as co-applicant (now retired) and members of the Trial Oversight Committee: Ben <lb/>Fisher (chair; University of Birmingham), Jim Wiggle (Patient Representative), <lb/>Rebecca Evans (University of Bristol), Mike Thomas (Heatherwood and Wexham <lb/>Park NHS Hospitals Trust), Anju Jaggi (Royal National Orthopaedic Hospital NHS <lb/>Trust). <lb/></div>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>10 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <div type="annex">Collaborators The Anti-Freaze-F study collaborating principal investigators were <lb/>Vincent Gallagher (East Sussex Healthcare NHS Trust), Neil Smith (Sandwell and <lb/>West Birmingham Hospital NHS Trust), Alun Yewlett (United Lincolnshire Hospitals <lb/>NHS Trust), Paul Barker (University Hospitals Birmingham). <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="contribution">Contributors SH and JN are co-chief investigators and co-lead applicants. AR, <lb/>MF, JP and SL are co-applicants on the grant awarded by the National Institute <lb/>of Health Research-Research for Patient Benefit Programme (Project reference: <lb/>201031) and were involved in design and conduct of the study, and interpretation <lb/>of data. CS led the qualitative study, FE and SM conducted the statistical analysis <lb/>and AE and EAF provided trial management expertise. SH, JN and CS led on writing <lb/>the manuscript. All authors read, commented and approved the final version. SH is <lb/>responsible for the overall content as guarantor and accepts full responsibility for <lb/>the study, had access to the data and controlled the decision to publish. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="funding">Funding This report is independent research funded by the National Institute of <lb/>Health Research-Research for Patient Benefit Programme (NIHR: 201031). The <lb/>views expressed in this publication are those of the author(s) and not necessarily <lb/>those of the NIHR or the Department of Health and Social Care. 180 Life Sciences <lb/>provided funding for the purchase of adalimumab, the investigational medicinal <lb/>product used in this trial. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="annex">Disclaimer The views expressed are those of the author(s) and not necessarily <lb/>those of the NHS, the NIHR or the Department of Health. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="conflict">Competing interests MF and JN are co-founders and hold equity in 180 <lb/>Life Sciences, the company who funded the purchase of adalimumab, the <lb/>investigational medicinal product used in this trial. <lb/>Patient and public involvement Patients and/or the public were involved in the <lb/>design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. Refer to <lb/>the Methods section for further details. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="annex">Patient consent for publication Not applicable. <lb/>Ethics approval This study involves human participants and was approved by <lb/>Health Research Authority North East -Newcastle &amp; North Tyneside 1 (REC 21/ <lb/>NE/0214). Participants gave informed consent to participate in the study before <lb/>taking part. <lb/>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="availability">Data availability statement Data are available upon reasonable request. <lb/>Summary results data will be available on the trial registration databases within 12 <lb/>months of the end of the trial. Requests for data (anonymised trial participant level <lb/>data) will be provided at the end of the trial to external researchers who provide a <lb/>methodologically sound proposal to the trial team (and who will be required to sign <lb/>a data sharing access agreement with the Sponsor) and in accordance with the <lb/>NIHR guidance. Participant consent for this was included in the informed consent <lb/>form for the study. <lb/></div>
        
        <div type="annex">Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has <lb/>not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been <lb/>peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those <lb/>of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and <lb/>responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content <lb/>includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability <lb/>of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, <lb/>terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error <lb/>and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise. <lb/></div>
        
        <front>Open access This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported (CC BY 4.0) license, which permits <lb/>others to copy, redistribute, remix, transform and build upon this work for any <lb/>purpose, provided the original work is properly cited, a link to the licence is given, <lb/>and indication of whether changes were made. See: https://creativecommons.org/ <lb/>licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>ORCID iDs <lb/>Sally Hopewell http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6881-6984 <lb/>Amar Rangan http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5452-8578 <lb/>M Sofia Massa http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3205-6706 <lb/></front>
        
        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 Dawson J, Shepperd S, Carr A. An overview of factors relevant to <lb/>undertaking research and reviews on the effectiveness of treatment <lb/>for frozen shoulder. Shoulder &amp; Elbow 2010;2:232-7. <lb/>2 Walker-Bone K, Palmer KT, Reading I, et al. Prevalence and impact <lb/>of musculoskeletal disorders of the upper limb in the general <lb/>population. Arthritis Rheum 2004;51:642-51. <lb/>3 Hand C, Clipsham K, Rees JL, et al. Long-term outcome of frozen <lb/>shoulder. J Shoulder Elbow Surg 2008;17:231-6. <lb/>4 Rangan A, Hanchard N, McDaid C. What is the most effective <lb/>treatment for frozen shoulder BMJ 2016;354:i4162. <lb/>5 Hanchard NCA, Goodchild L, Thompson J, et al. Evidence-based <lb/>clinical guidelines for the diagnosis, assessment and physiotherapy <lb/>management of contracted (frozen) shoulder: quick reference <lb/>summary. Physiotherapy 2012;98:117-20. <lb/>6 Ryan V, Brown H, Minns Lowe CJ, et al. The pathophysiology <lb/>associated with primary (idiopathic) frozen shoulder: a systematic <lb/>review. BMC Musculoskelet Disord 2016;17:340. <lb/>7 Buchbinder R, Green S, Youd JM, et al. Oral steroids for adhesive <lb/>capsulitis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2006;2006:CD006189. <lb/>8 Buchbinder R, Green S, Youd JM. Corticosteroid injections for <lb/>shoulder pain. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2003;2003:CD004016. <lb/>9 Wang W, Shi M, Zhou C, et al. Effectiveness of corticosteroid <lb/>injections in adhesive capsulitis of shoulder: a meta-analysis. <lb/>Medicine (Baltimore) 2017;96:e7529. <lb/>10 Page MJ, Green S, Kramer S, et al. Electrotherapy modalities for <lb/>adhesive capsulitis (frozen shoulder). Cochrane Database Syst Rev <lb/>2014;2014:CD011324. <lb/>11 Page MJ, Green S, Kramer S, et al. Manual therapy and exercise for <lb/>adhesive capsulitis (frozen shoulder). Cochrane Database Syst Rev <lb/>2014;2014:CD011275. <lb/>12 Rangan A, Brealey SD, Keding A, et al. Management of adults <lb/>with primary frozen shoulder in secondary care (UK FROST): a <lb/>multicentre, pragmatic, three-arm, superiority randomised clinical <lb/>trial. Lancet 2020;396:977-89. <lb/>13 Smith SP, Devaraj VS, Bunker TD. The association between <lb/>frozen shoulder and dupuytren&apos;s disease. J Shoulder Elbow Surg <lb/>2001;10:149-51. <lb/>14 Larsen S, Krogsgaard DG, Larsen LA, et al. Genetic and <lb/>environmental influences in dupuytren&apos;s disease: a study of 30,330 <lb/>Danish twin pairs. J Hand Surg Eur Vol 2015;40:171-6. <lb/>15 Riesmeijer SA, Kamali Z, Ng M, et al. A genome-wide association <lb/>meta-analysis implicates hedgehog and notch signaling in <lb/>dupuytren&apos;s disease. Nat Commun 2024;15:199. <lb/>16 Bunker TD, Anthony PP. The pathology of frozen shoulder. a <lb/>dupuytren-like disease. J Bone Joint Surg Br 1995;77:677-83. <lb/>17 Hand GCR, Athanasou NA, Matthews T, et al. The pathology of <lb/>frozen shoulder. J Bone Joint Surg Br 2007;89:928-32. <lb/>18 Bunker TD, Reilly J, Baird KS, et al. Expression of growth factors, <lb/>cytokines and matrix metalloproteinases in frozen shoulder. J Bone <lb/>Joint Surg Br 2000;82:768-73. <lb/>19 Lho Y-M, Ha E, Cho C-H, et al. Inflammatory cytokines are <lb/>overexpressed in the subacromial bursa of frozen shoulder. J <lb/>Shoulder Elbow Surg 2013;22:666-72. <lb/>20 Nanchahal J, Ball C, Davidson D, et al. Anti-tumour necrosis factor <lb/>therapy for dupuytren&apos;s disease: a randomised dose response proof <lb/>of concept phase 2A clinical trial. EBioMedicine 2018;33:282-8. <lb/>21 Nanchahal J, Ball C, Rombach I, et al. Anti-tumour necrosis factor <lb/>therapy for early-stage dupuytren&apos;s disease (RIDD): a phase <lb/>2B, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet <lb/>Rheumatol 2022;4:E407-16. <lb/>22 Elbow. Royal College of Surgeons, Commissioning Guide: <lb/>Subacromial Shoulder Pain. 2014. <lb/>23 Hopewell S, Kenealy N, Knight R, et al. Anti-TNF (Adalimumab) <lb/>injection for the treatment of adults with frozen shoulder during the <lb/>pain predominant stage protocol for a multi-centre, randomised, <lb/>double blind, parallel group. NIHR Open Res 2022;2:28. <lb/>24 Sun Y, Liu S, Chen S, et al. The effect of corticosteroid injection into <lb/>rotator interval for early frozen shoulder: a randomized controlled <lb/>trial. Am J Sports Med 2018;46:663-70. <lb/>25 Roach KE, Budiman-Mak E, Songsiridej N, et al. Development of a <lb/>shoulder pain and disability index. Arthritis Care Res 1991;4:143-9. <lb/>26 Williams JW, Holleman DR, Simel DL. Measuring shoulder <lb/>function with the shoulder pain and disability index. J Rheumatol <lb/>1995;22:727-32. <lb/>27 Mintken PE, Cleland JA, Whitman JM, et al. Psychometric properties <lb/>of the fear-avoidance beliefs questionnaire and tampa scale of <lb/>kinesiophobia in patients with shoulder pain. Arch Phys Med Rehabil <lb/>2010;91:1128-36. <lb/>28 Nicholas MK, McGuire BE, Asghari A. A 2-item short form of the <lb/>pain self-efficacy questionnaire: development and psychometric <lb/>evaluation of PSEQ-2. J Pain 2015;16:153-63. <lb/>29 Bastien CH, Vallières A, Morin CM. Validation of the insomnia severity <lb/>index as an outcome measure for insomnia research. Sleep Med <lb/>2001;2:297-307. <lb/></listBibl>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>
        
        <page>11 <lb/></page>
        
        <note place="footnote">Hopewell S, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e078273. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 <lb/></note>
        
        <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
        
        <listBibl>30 Kamper SJ, Maher CG, Mackay G. Global rating of change scales: a <lb/>review of strengths and weaknesses and considerations for design. J <lb/>Man Manip Ther 2009;17:163-70. <lb/>31 Teare MD, Dimairo M, Shephard N, et al. Sample size requirements <lb/>to estimate key design parameters from external pilot randomised <lb/>controlled trials: a simulation study. Trials 2014;15:264. <lb/>32 Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qual Res in <lb/>Psychol 2006;3:77-101. <lb/>33 Limb M. Long NHS waits and rising living costs are harming people&apos;s <lb/>health, show ONS data. BMJ 2023;380:479. <lb/>34 Maund E, Craig D, Suekarran S, et al. Management of frozen <lb/>shoulder: a systematic review and cost-effectiveness analysis. Health <lb/>Technol Assess 2012;16:1-264. <lb/>35 US Food and Drug Adminstration. Available: www.accessdata.fda. <lb/>gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2018/125057s406lbl.pdf [Accessed 5 Jul <lb/>2023]. <lb/>36 Office of National Statistics. Ethnicity, Available: https://www.ons. <lb/>gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/culturalidentity/ethnicity <lb/>[Accessed 5 Jul 2023]. <lb/>37 Hopewell S, Keene DJ, Marian IR, et al. Progressive exercise <lb/>compared with best practice advice, with or without corticosteroid <lb/>injection, for the treatment of patients with rotator cuff disorders <lb/>(GRASP): a multicentre, pragmatic, 2×2 factorial, randomised <lb/>controlled trial. Lancet 2021;398:416-28. <lb/></listBibl>
        
        <note place="headnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>1 May 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-078273 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as </note>
        

	</text>

</TEI>